<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000207_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-18T06:14:01.308Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">A No.PA/FC/ THE CUSTOMHOUSE: BAHRAIN: 21st August, 194-3 *5 19th Shabban, 1362., H.E.ft^s Political Agent, Bahrain* MEMORANDUM Ref .your No:l879/36/l-D of 17th August, 194-3. I enclose herev/ith two applications from Abdul Koor Bastaki, togetherwith details of requirements from the United Kingdom and the United States, and would suggest that these may be recommended* Enel / ' v' / n / DIRECTOR OF CUSTOMS AND PORT OFFICER BAHRAIN.t Abdul Moor .VI. Bastaki General Merchant. BAHRAIN. P. GULF. Si’ 2#a/e*C ...August 1943^ The Director of Customs &amp; Port Officer, Bahrain# * Sir: Re: _ jjgpor t of Shi rts and undgrwears . We beg to state to your goodself that we have got an order with our Agent Messrs: Dayton Price a Co* New York for the above mentioned goods which we cannot receive from them due to export restriction imposed by their Government* In this connection we would like to inform you that we have got the above order with them since 17th November 1941 for which we have alrwady made payment to them in Dollars* and as it is a very long time that they are not able to send same, we shall be highly obliged if you will helfl us to get same * ° r We are giving the details as required by you as per x seperate sheet attached herewith* Thanking you in anticipation, we beg to remain, 4 V Yours faithfully. ABDULNOOR M. BASTAKI.Abdul Moor M. Bastaki General Merchant, BAHRAIN. P. GULF. 21^ M,^**** 1 A ^ust 1943 • £QjL_the goods req uired to be Imported from U«S»A,. !• Name of Importer# 2* Name of Exporter* 3* Description og Goods* 4* Weight of goods* 5* Exact Use of goods* 6 . a* Supply of good wanted. b* their import from this country* 7* Description oj the urgency with ttbich the goods are required* Abdul Noor M* Bastaki* Bahrain* Day tom Price &amp; Company* New York* Agents to Manufacture ers Cluett Peabody 8c Co* U.S*A* 64* Dozen Shirts (Arrow Brand) 20 * Dozen Shorts* n n 16* Dozen Under shirts* ” About £ Ton* Used by British &amp; Americans mostly* Selling here since 6 years. For Bahrain only to be sold in retail* Supplier since 6 years and this brand is prefered by all our clients* Also our order is lying with them since long fc* time for which we have already made payment to them* As soon as possible by freight shipment or parcel post* ABDUL NOOR M* BASTAKI.LJ Cl PHONE NO. 37.M Abdul Moor \1 Bastaki General Merchant. BAHRAIN. P. GULF. AUBUST 21 st 194 ^^ i 1 i ^ V Rie Director of Customs &amp; Port Officer^ Bahrain# Sir: Re; Import of Hbselry. We beg to state to your goodself that we have got an order with our supplier Messrs: Montgomery Ward and Co, Chicago for the above mentioned goods which we cannot receive from them due to export restrictions imposed by their Government, ^ In this connection we would like to inform you tk that we have got the above order with them since 27th November 1941 for which we have already made payment to them In Dollars, As it is now very long time that they are not able to send us the goods we shall be highly obliged If you will kindly help us to get the same# We are giving the details as required by you as per seperate sheet attached herewith# Thanking you in anticipation^ we beg to remain. Yours faithfully ABDUL NOOR M# BASTAKI# //s PHONE NO. 37 M Abdul Moor VI. Bastaki General Merchant. BAHRAIN. P. GULF. August 2lst 1945» detai ls of the goods require d to be Import ed^jCyoin Hk le Name of Importer* £• Name of Exporter* 3* Description of goods* 4* Weight of goods* 5« Exact use of the goods* 6 * a supply of goods wanted b their import from this country* 7* Description of the urgency with which the goods are required* ABDUINOOR M* BASTAKI* Montgomery Ward &amp; Co* Chicago* ( Jr' * f ' 63* Dozen Socks* as per our order of 27/11/41* 80* lbs* Gross• Daily use thing*worn by all* For Bahrain only* supplier since six years and also our order is lying with them since 27/11/41 for which wehave Already made payment* as soon as possible by freight shipment or parcel post* (Prefered by parcel post) ABDUL NOOR M* BASTAKI* YProm, Aboodi Yacoob Zeloof 8 c Sons, Bahrain,. Persain Gulf. E. B. M’s The Political Agent, Bahrrin. . $. 33 f* 9 ■ Bahrain, Through, The Director Of Custom and Port Officer of Bahrain. Bahrain. V3 6 th September 1943. Sir: J\*Lt l ' v ' e heg to inform you that we deal in English piece goods 32 years* i-t present cannot get any shipment from England unless you grant us permit. , v &gt; ie shall be highly obliged by your granting the necessity permission for importation the following goods in to Bahrain. Description of piece goods to be imported from England. 4 Bales 4 ' 2 5 3 1 2 2 I! 11 It II cases cases of black net 37 inches. 400 pieces, of black net 28 inches. 600'pieces. of white voile 52 inches of goods Quality. 200 pieces. of printed voile 36 inches. 200 pieces. of black crepe saten 36 inches. 100 pieces. of black striped doria 28 inches. 200 pieces. of red shawls 55 n x55 tf . 500 dozen. of red shawls 51 ,, x51 tf . 300 ” of white and cloured and striped poplin for shirts. 60 pieces, of wollen cloth 56 inches of different qualities. 20 pieces, of silk cloth for suits of different qualities. 40 pieces. (i) N- r me of would-be importer. (ii) Name and address of agent or manufacturer in the exporting countryfrom whom he wishes to arrange supply. (iii) Full description of goods required. (iv) Approximate weight in long tons of 2240 lbs. of the goods required. Aboodi Yacoob Zeloof, Bahrain. vj- O &lt;&gt; ■ &gt;&gt;.&lt; . 1. Akerib, ;sq., 21, Chorlton Street, Manchester, 1 . England. Mentioned in the above page. About 10 tons. Exact use or purpose contemplated for the goods to be imported. Special reason justifying- (a) sujjply of goods wanted, (b) their import from the country suggested rather than any’ other country. For sale in our market. None in the market. Not obt.inabi§ elsewhere. (vii) Description of the urgency with which the goods are required, and the latest date which will be suitable. As early as possible. ii* We remain, I suggest the/above is held si r over until thd^pplication for Your most ’ obediently, 400 tons space for Bahrain January!944 is known when it ✓ wfell be 'possible to allocate a portion of j-bs reauirements. 4— . ^ DIREGTCR OF CUSTOMS &amp; PORT 0FEICER, BAHRAIN._ J. E. KHEDOURI IMPORT EXPORT 8. COMMISSION AGENT. TELE ADDRESS KHEDOUR l-BAHR AIN TELEPHONE. 83-M CODES used:- BENTLEYS ACME a ORIENTAL bankers:- THE EASTERN BANK LTD.' i . 1 . 8 th Attgoat /pji ARABIA Name of would be Importers- J*E*Khedourl # Bahrain, Persian Gulf* Name and address of agent or manufacturer in the exporting country from whom he wishes to arrange supply:- The Central Agency Ltd* 50 Bothwall Street.Glasgow,England# Pull description of the goods required:- 4 Cases, each case cont#40 gross cotton sewing thread.(This order we placed with the said manufacturer on the 18th September 1943, and it is only under their airgraph letter of the 14th July 1940 they have asked us to secure the Import Assistance Recommendation)• Approximate weight in long tons of 2240 Lbs of the good s required:- About one ton. Exact use or purpose contemplated glM* &lt; for the goods to be imported:- For the purpose of local uses. Special reasons justifying:- O' e ^ i» (a) Stock is quite insufficient, v’ ^ r / * —(b) Consm^rs like better than the 4 thread manufactured in other countries# (c) Shipment as soon as possible. Please give us an Import Licence based on above named particulars and thanking you for the same. Yours faithfullyJ. E. KHEDOURI BENTLEYS ACME &amp; ORIENTAL bankers;- the eastern bank ltd. tele address khedouri-sahrain IMPORT &amp; EXPORT CODES USED;- (ARABIA) Political Agent Bahrain. Dear Sir: Please refer to your letter No.2110-36/43 dated 18th instant. Your above quoted letter is in connection with our orders we placed with our friends Messrs Reckitt &amp; Colman Ltd. for which we applied to you for permit on the 1942 and one in 194s and we think the orders are accepted by them and waiting for space. We have no definite information v from them. ^!.»»*•*- a ■ j — -t—»-&lt;• With the•latter firm we have placed several orders, and for some of them they have received the export permit and for some of them they are waiting for the export permit from your goodself. Aintrees Mensten Nr.Leeds, England. Messrs J.M.Shasha. Asia House 82 Princess Street Manchester. With the former firm we placed twoorders, one in Yours faithfully&lt; E. KHEDOURJ M 9 ■ IMPORT &amp; EXPORT khbdouri-bahrain ec.NTLEYS ACME &amp; ORIENTAL tblbphone. 83 -M CODES USED;- 19th Sept bankers;- the eastern bank ltd. Sts &amp;///*&amp;ft? (ARABIA) - Political Agent Bahrain# Dear Sir; 3 Bales Red Shell Shawls Quality No. 17938. 55'x55 ,, 100 Pieces 27' Mosquito Nets quality 18687/24 100 ' 36 n ' ' » » / 2 6 ‘ 500 n 27” ' « » 18698 In relation to our above mentioned outstanding o our friends Messrs J.M.Shasha. Asia House, 82 Princess Street, Manchester., advised us under their airgraph letter dated 1st September 1943, reading as follows ' We are giving you below an extract of a letter received this week from the India Office and we suggest in your own interests that you immediately approach the British Political Representative in regard to the following orders(Mentioned above) which we have on hand and which will be ready for shipment in the near future • n ” With reference to further consignments , I am to say that in accordance with the procedure which has now” been established for the allotment of shipping ' ^ space from the United Kingdom to the Arab States” ” t* 1 © Persian Gulf, you should advise your ” ” consignees to apply to the local British Political” f| Agent for an Import Assistance Recommendation.Any ” w such recommendations granted by the Political ” ^ authorities will be submitted to the Government ” ” of India and if endorsed by them to this office.” ^ We will then advise you if a letter of recommendatio for shipping space can be given to you.” requesting you to do the needful in the matter if possible by cable for which we shall be glad to meet with the cable charge. Thanking you in anticipation# Yours faithfullyJ. E. KHEDOUR I IMPORT EXPORT &amp; COMMISSION AGENT TELE ADDRESS KHE DOUR l-BAHR AIN TELEPHONE. 83-M CODES used:- BENTLEYS ACME a ORIENTAL BANKERS:- THE EASTERN BANK LTD. REF.NO .1 / .JP US? ft Septembe^^ s ARABIA Political Agent Bahrain, Dear Sir: MESSRS THE CENTRAL AGENCY LTD, GLASGOW 18th instant! 886 r6f6r t0 yOUr letter No * 8 H0-a6/4a dated r.f .oiv? e t.° r ? er ^ we P^ a0e&lt; 5 with the above named firm was thnfr - 1 i 8th ^ e P t f raber and was accepted by them under their airgraph letter dated 9th November 1942. Further It. % Yours faithTullyIJ. E. KHEDOURI IMPORT &amp; EXPORT j*y' ‘- i - y. TtLB AODRFSS khedouri-rahrain telephone. S 3 -M CODES USED;- BENTLEYS ACME &amp; ORIENTAL banrers;- thh eastern bank ltd. I V* '‘^0 \ ^7 11th October 5 Us/sram ^ARABIA) HEP. NO « 2 / 3 H.B.M’s Political Agent Bahrain, ^ /o (&lt;y Dear Sirs We have been advised by our Principals MESSRS J.M.SHASHA. ASIA HOUSAi, 82 PRINCESS STRiiJiT, MANCHESTER under their airgraph letter dated l£&gt;th August 194o to the effect that the BOARD OF TRADE, LONDON., would grant them export licence for woolen piecegoods such as Woven Tissues or Blanket of wool to Saudi Arabia. Upon the receipt of their said airgraph letter* we placed an order with our Principals by cable on the 6th September 1940 for the followings- 5 Bales Woolen Blankets ' Woolen suitings ' Blue Serge ” Pompbiege assorted ' Red Shawls 2 1 2 5 to be shipped to OJAIR, SAUDI ARABIA VIA BAHRAIN(FOR IBRAHIM ALJMAIH.HASSA) and also under the same cable we ordered the following for BAHRAIN. 5 Bales Woolen suitings!Assorted) 1 ' Blue Serge In the meantime we have received one cable dated oOth September 1940 from our said Principals reading as follows YOURS SIXTH APART FROM BLANKETS OTHER requirements could be supplied provided IMPORT LICENCES WITH PRIORITY RECOMMENDATIONS OBTAINED PLeASe TRY. We would x*oqu.est you to kindly do the needful by cable with the authority and v/e shall be glad to meet with the cable charge. Yours faithfully - r J• E. KHEDOURI import &amp; EXPORT tblr addrkss KHEDOURI-SAHRAIN TELEPHONE. g3~M CODES USED:- BENTLBVS ACME &amp; ORIENTAL Bankers;- thb eastern bank ltd. KbF.NO.S / 39 g&gt;/ Jjjia- J*UI y J 1 4 3 . y0ttrtr'atti Oo t . y /p/, ° (ARABIA) H«BoM 1 s Political Agent Bahrain. Dear Sir: %&gt; Bales Red Shawls 55Quality No.l79o8 100 Pieces 27' Mosquito nets Qual. 18687/24 100 ' ae' ' ' ' 18687/26 500 ' 27' it r» n 18698 With reference to our above mentioned order, we placed with our friends Messrs J.M.Shasha Asia House 82 Princess Street Manchester 1 we are inviting your attention to the remarks we received from our said Principals and embodied in our letter dated 19th ultimo and requesting you to kindly let us know the result if possible so that we can transmit the same to our friends named above* Yours faithfully .j © 2 ?) No * 23 H -36/43 Politics 1 Agency, Bahrain* Dated 23 'v{ October 1943 To J.S. Khcdouri, Bahrain* /'U /7 Dear Bir, Reference your letters Nos* 2 and 3 of the lltli October* 1943 asking for resistance for the export of goods from the United Kingdom. 2* y°u please submit these and all future applications thi*ough the Director of Customs. % for political Agent,Bahrain* yv'tyf J. E. KHEDOURI Import, Export &amp; Commission Agent Tele.-Address: Khedouri - Bahrain Codes used: Bentley’s Acme &amp; Oriental Bankers: The Eastern Bank Ltd. 'q^Tr BAHRAIN, 25th October 194b (Arabia) KEF.NO.4 Political Agent Bahrain. Through:- The Director of Customs and Port Officer Bahrain. Dear Sir; 3 Bells Red Shell Shawls (Quality No.17938. 55'X55') 100 Pieces 27 M Mosquito Nets Qual. _ ^100 w 36” w n n \bt 500 ,f 27 fl w w ' In relation to our above mentioned outstanding orders our friends Messrs J.M.Shasha.Asia House, 82 Princess Street, Manchester 1., advised us under their airgraph letter dated 1st September 1943, reading as follows M We are giving you below an extract of a letter' ' received this week fromthe India Office and we ' ! w suggest in your own interests that you immediately' ' approach the British Political Representative ' ' in regard to the following orders(Mentioned above)' ' which we have on hand and which will be ready for ' 'shipment in the near future'. ' With reference to the further consignments, I am to' say that in accordance with the procedure which has' ' now been established for the allotment of shipping' ' space from the United Kingdom to the Arab States' in the Persian Gulf, you should advise your ' ' consignees to apply to the local British Political' ' Agent for an Import Assistance Recommendation. Any' such recommendations granted by the Political ' ' Authorities will be submitted to the Government ' ' of India and If endorsed by them to this office.' ' We will then advise you if a letter of recommendation' ' for shipping space can be given to you', and requesting you to do the needful in the matter if possible by cable for which we shall be glad to meet with the cable charges. Thanking you in anticipation. No. 1868/24 '/26 18698 Yours faithfullyy i . Jc ■ J/E. K H E D O U R I n - U 7 Import, Export &amp; Commission Agent BAHRAIN, 25th October iq a.s (Arabia) Tele.-Address: Khedouri - Bahrain Codes used: Bentley’s Acme &amp; Oriental Bankers: The Eastern Bank Ltd. fiEF. NQ,5 Political Agent Bahrain. Through ^ The Director of Customs and Port Officer Bahrain. Dear Sir: T m qhccho T^l e been o a dv ised by our Principals Messrs Asia House, 82 Princess Street, Manchester 1. .under their airgraph letter dated 13th August 1943 to thp arrani- 4 -v-. the BOARD OP TRADE, LONDON., would ^ant ^em exp^t Ucence for woolen piecegoods such as Woven Tissues or Blanket of wool to Saudi Arabia. Upon the receipt of their letter na^ed above we placed an order with our Principals by cable on the 6th September 194o for the following:- 5 Bales Woolen Blankets 2 ,r Woolen suitings 1 ' Blue serge 'K- 2 M Pompbiege assorted 5 w Red shawls ALJMAIH h 4ASSAiBnrt 0J ? IR ' H 001 * R4BIA VIA B AHRAIN(FOR IBRAHIM 4 * SA) ^ 8130 under the same cable we ordered the following for BAHRAIN. ui-uexea cne 3 Bales Woolen Suitirgs(Assorted) 1 Bale Blue serge, , ' 'Vw 0 ^ 1136 an time we have received one cable dateri ^nows:- 6 194S fr ° m ° Ur Sald Prinol P 8l « reading a* • YOURS SIXTH APART FROM BLANKETS OTHER REQUIREMijNTS COULD BE SUPPLIED PROVIDED LICENCES WITH PRIORITY RECOMMENDATIONS OBTAINED PLEASE TRY. We would request you to kindly do the needful by cable with ” '' u 8l,a ^ Yours faithfully1 \ x Reference reverse. I recomuend that assistance may be given to import the following:- 3 bales woollen suitings (assorted). 1 ' ' Blue serge*. 3 ' ” Blardvdts. DIRECTOR OF CUSTOMS AND PORT OFFICER BA Ilf IN.J. E. KHEDOURI 9 ■ // • ‘r &gt; Import, Export &amp; Commission Agent BAHRAIN, &amp;rd November 19 4o (Arabia) Tele.-Address: Khedouri - Bahrain Codes used: Bentley’s Acme &amp; Oriental REF. NO.7 Bankers: The Eastern Bank Ltd. H.B.M's Political Agent Bahrain. T H R 0 U G H:- The Director of Customs and Port Officer Bahrain . Dear Sirj REF.MY LETTER NO.4 DATtiD 25TH OCTOBER 1940. We have received one cable dated 29th October,194o, from our Principals Messrs J.M.Shasha. Asia House, 82 Princess Street, Manchester 1., reading as follows ' THREE BALES SHAWLS READY APPLY BRITISH AGENT FOR IMPORT ASSISTANCE RECOMMENDATION SPACE WILL ONLY BE GRANTED WHEN GUARANTEE RECEIVED BY INDIA OFFICE AND LONDON INFORMED STOP MAY ALSO BE ABIE OBTAIN FURTHER QUANTITIES PROVIDED YOU OBTAINED INDIA GOVERNMENT SHIPPING PRIORITY CONTACT AUTHORITIES FOR RECOMMENDATION n In the said cable you would notice that three bales shawls are ready for shipment and further the price is very high and therefore requesting you to do the needful with the authority by cable. We shall be glad to meet with the cable charge• Yours faithfully , Passed on to the 1 DIRECTOR OF CUSTOMS AND PORT OFFICER BAHRAINV J/E. KHEDOURI 0 4 '. if u ~} Import, Export &amp; Commission Agent BAHRAIN, fr rd November 194 o (Arabia) Tele.-Address: Khedouri - Bahrain Codes used: Bentley’s Acme &amp; Oriental Bankers: The Eastern Bank Ltd. Rl^F* NO«b H.B.M’s Political Agent. Bahrain* THROUGH:- The Director of Customs and Port Officer. Bahrain* Messrs George Kaufmann(London)Ltd. Ibex House, Minories* London ii.C.b We are quoting hereunder a part of the cable we have received from our above named principals APPLY IMMEDIATELY BRITISH POLITICAL AGENT FOR IMPORT ASSISTANCE RECOMMENDATION TO BE SUBMITTED INDIA GOVERNMENT FOR SHIPPING SPACE. of those orders the under mentioned orders are outstanding with our friends: 100 Pieces Black mercerised voils(Cotton) [&lt;jb~ 250 Dozen Yashmagh 3 Cases cigarette paper in bobbins. I 2 Tons Salamoniac in blocks. 1 Ton Ultramarine blue paint. / ^12^ Tons Nepthaline(Balls, flasks and powder) and requesting you to do the needful with the authorities. Dear Sir: and in the meantime we would inform you that during the past one year to date we were placing orders with them and out 8 ' Kiwi Boot polish 3 ' Ink. Yours faithfully ,I \ I Refireverse• V O I recommeiid that assistance may be given to import the following 100 pcs Black mercerised veils (cotton); 100 doz. Yashmagh. 8 a ses Kiwi Boot polish. 3 cases Ink. 1 ton Salamon.iac in blocks. 1 ton Ultramarine blue paint. 1 ton Nepthaline (balls, flasks and powder). ~\ DIRECTOR OF CUSTOMS AND PORT OFFICER BAKRAIN^xJ. E. KHEDOURI © IMPORT &amp; EXPORT TBLB ADDRKSS khbdouri-bahrain TELEPHONE. g3~M CODES used:- 10tn Novemb^i^ o BENTLEYS ACME &amp; ORIENTAL bankers;- thb eastern bank ltd. H.B.M’s Political Agent Bahrain . T H R 0 U G H:- The Director of Customs and Port Officer. Bahrain. Messrs Arthur E.Evans &amp; Co. Ltd. Westminster Bank Chambers. Bishop’s Stortford.Herts(England) We have placed an order for 50 Pieces of Woolen nomAH firm And reauestin« you to Piecegoods, with the above named firm and requesting you do the needful with the authorities for the necessary export permit and shipping space. I recommend that assistance may be given to import Dear Sir: Yours faithfully Ref .above &lt;, 12 pieces of Woollen piecegoods. director of customs AND PORT OFFICER BAHAIN.. E. KHEDOURI IMPORT &amp; EXPORT TELE ADDRfSS KHED OURI-BAH RAIN TELEPHONE. g3-M CODES used:- BENTLEYS ACME &amp; ORIENTAL bankers:- THE EASTERN BANK LTD. I REF.NO.12 H.B.M's Political Agent. Bahrain. Dear Sir: 22rd No ^/^ (ARABIA) Ul9jL~ £(&lt; ■ rr 'll Please refer to your letter No.2568-s6/4o of the 16th instant. Hereunder we are embodying the required particulars of our orders 1. Name of would be importer: J.ii.KHEDOURI. BAHRAIN 2. Name and address of the agent or manufacturer in the exporting country from which he wishes to arrange supply Messrs J.M.Shasha. Full description of the goods required. ...•••••••••: *&gt; Ba'i.es Red Shawls (Quality No.l79o8. 55'x5f 100 Pieces 27' Mosquito Nets No.1868/24 100 Pieces as above o6 n No.1868/26 500 Pieces as above No.18698 4. Approximate weight in long tons of 2240 Lbs.... 3 Bales Red shawls gross weight 11 Cwts. Nett weight 10 Cwts. and Cubic feet 82. 700 Pieces Mosquito netting would be about 15 Cwtso 5. Exact use or purpose contemplated for the goods to be imported Shawls are for the use of males and called here YASHMAGH.Mosquito netting is being used by females as veils. 6. Special reason justifying:- (a) Supply of goods wanted: Not available here. (b) Their import from the country suggested rather than from any other country:-These particular, things are only being manu factured in England.J. E. KHEDOURI IMPORT &amp; EXPORT TILH ADDRFSS XHEP OURI-BAH RAIN TELEPHONE. 83~M CODES used:- RENTLEYS ACME &amp; ORIENTAL BANKERS:- THE EASTERN BANK LTD. JrAGii NO.2 22 ” a (ARABIA) b. REF.NO.12 H.B.NPs political Agent. Bahrain. 7. Description of the urgency with which the goods are required and latest date which will he suitable....; Stock exhausted, and shipment earliest possible. and for the above mentioned s Bales Red Shawls, the suppliers named above advised us under their Airgraph letter dated 27th October 194a stating that the goods are ready for shipment and they have received an export Licence No.9B/41459/4b. The value of the goods is about £1000/- and the gross weight 11 Cwts.,Nett weight 10 Cwts and Cubic feet 22. With our above mentioned suppliers we also placed an order for woolen plecegoods mentioned in ckur letter No.5 dated 25th October, for consumption in Saudi Arabia and if it is not possible to be recommended from here we would request you to treat this order as cancelled with the exception of 5 Bales Woolen Blankets. With reference to 5 Bales Woolen Blankets we would request you to treat the same for Bahrain and their particulars are given hereunder along with the other goods we ordered for consumption at Bahrain mentioned in our above quoted letter No.5. 1 . 2 . 5 . 4. 5. Name of would be importer; Name and address of the agent or manufacturer in the exporting country from whom he wishes to arrange supply ; Full description of the goods required Approximate weight in long tons of 2240 Lbs....; jixact use or purpose contemplated for the goods to be imported J.E.KHEDOURI. BAHRAIN. Messrs J.M.Shasha. Asia House. 82 Princess St./ Manchester, 1. v 5 Bales Woolen Blankets. 6 Bales Woolen Suitings. l^Bale Blue Serge. This information could be obtained from the suppliers. :For the use use of the Military people and civilian at Bahrain.J. E. KHEDOUKI TBLR ADDRFSS KHB DOUR I-BAHRAIN IMPORT &amp; EXPORT y&gt; TELEPHONE. 83~M CODES used:- BENTLEVS ACME &amp; ORIENTAL bankers;- 2ord No\ THE EASTERN BANK LTD. No. 5 RBF.N0.12 Political .Agent. Bahrain 6. Special reason justifying:- (aJSupjly of goods wanted.:- Not available at Bahrain. (b)Their import from the country suggested rather than from any other country.*. Now available only in England. 7. Description of the urgency with which the goods are required and latest date which will be suitable Urgently required. In the meantime we would request you to do the needful with the authorities. Shipment as soon as possible. Yours faithfully ,M M J. E. KHEDOUR1 ^ \ (u IMPORT &amp; EXPORT telr address KHS DQURI-BAH RAIN telephone. g3-M CODES USED:- BENTLEVS ACME &amp; ORIENTAL bankers;- the eastern bank ltd. KEF,MO.13 / ss/s/af/? 2«ird g (ARABIA) H.B.M’s Political Agent, Bahrain. s ear Sir; Please refer to your letter No.2568-06/W dated 16th instant in relation to our letter No.8 dated 3rd instant. Hereunder we give you the required particulars of our order 1. Name of would be importer; J.is.KHiiDOURI.BAHRAIN. 2. Name and address of the agent of manufacturer in the exporting country from whom he wishes to arrange supply Messrs George Kaufmann (London)Ltd. Ibex House. Minories. London xl.C.o 3. Full description of the goods required, 100 Pieces Black Mercerised voils (Cotton) 250 Dozen Yashmagh. 8 Cases Kiwi Boot Polish. 3 Cases Ink. 2 Tons Salamoniac in Blocks. 1 Ton Ultramarine blue paint 1 Ton Neptholine(balls flask and powder) 4. Approximate weight in long tons of 2240 Lbs Could be obtained from the suppliers. &amp; , 5. Exact use or purpose contem plated for the goods to be imported ;A11 these goods are necessary for the country. 6. Special reason justifying (a) Supply of goods wanted: Not available here. (b) Their import from the country suggested rather thanfrom any other country;-All these goods at present amiy are being avai lable only from England. 7. Description of the urgency with which the goods are. E. KHEDOURI IMPORT &amp; EXPORT TtLB ADDRFSS KHED OURI-EAH RAIN TBLEPHONE. g3~M CODES USED;- BENTLBYS ACME &amp; ORIENTAL bankers;- the eastern bank ltd. PAGE NO.2 hLF.N0.15 A ‘^rd Mov. a (ARABIA) H.B. M»s Political Agent. Bahrain. 7. Description of the urgency with which the goods are required and latest date which will be suitable :-Urgently required. Shipment as soon as possible. and requesting you to do the needful with the authorities. Yours faithfully ’Yours faithfully J. E. KHEDOURI import &amp; EXPORT TBLB ADDRKSS khb dquri-iah rain THLEPHONE. g3~M CODES used:- BENTL8YS ACME &amp; ORIENTAL bankers:- thb eastern bank ltd. 4/3/ 7// • 63 -&gt;*y' j^L/&gt; (ARABIA) 26th Nov* 3 &gt; 50 t3 CD •§ CD Cfi c+ H* 3 (fc o P r+ O a o c+ rr CD 3 CD CD Q* &gt;-*&gt; C * c+ ct CD ct ? ct CD a KbF* NO * 14 -* &gt; // / H*B*M*s Political Agent Bahrain* Dear Sir: Please refer to your letter No*2652-36/4o dated 24th instant in reply to my letter No*10 of the 10th instant* I am embodying hereunder the desired particulars of our order 1. 2. 4. 5* 6* 7 . Name of would be Importer:-J*E*Khedouri. Bahrain. Name and address of tfte agent or manufacturer in the exporting country from whom he wishes to arrange supply : Messrs Arthur E.Evans &amp; Co* Westminster Bank Chambers. Bishop^ Stortford. Herts (England). Full description of the goods required bO Pieces Woolen Piecegoods* Approximate weight in long tons of 2240 Lbs*..*: This information could be obtained from the suppliers. yf jsxact use or purpose contem- — —^ plated for the goods to be imported: :For the use of the public and military people at Bahrain* Special reasons justifying (a) Supply of goods wante d:-Nothing available at Bahrain. (b) Their import from the country suggested rather than from any other country :At present not available from any other country but England. Description of the urgency ) with which the goods are ) Urgently required, required and the latest date) Shipment as soon as which Will be suitable. possible./ © Political Agency, Bahrain. Dated J.&gt;t^C&gt;ocCMbor 1943. ■J'o Abdul Noor Sastakl, Bahrain.- ^ 'h /.-s Memorandum . Rcforoncc your let ers dated 21st August 1 43, to the address of the Director of Customs, Bahrain. 2. The Government of India have recommended assistance for export of the shirts, shorts and hosiery ordered by you from the United States of America. — for Political Agent, Bahrain.*/• ** lb 'a//r y atn (ARABIA) 20th Dec. 7^ J. E. KHEDOURI IMPORT &amp; EXPORT TBUt ADDRESS KHBD OURI-BAH RAIN TELEPHONE. g3“M codes osed:- 8CNTLEYS ACME &amp; ORIENTAL bankers THE EASTERN BANK LTD. RkF.NO.52 H.B.M *s Political Agent. Bahrain. THKOUGH:- The Director of Customs and Port Officer. 3 ? O*'/ Dear Sir J.E.Khedouri. Bahrain. Messrs J.M.Shasha. Asia House. 82 Princess Street Manchester, 1. 1. Name of would be importer: 2. Name and address of the ) agent or manufacturer .) in the exporting country ) from whom he wishes to ) arrange supply ) S.Full description of the)(a)i$00 Pieces^Turkey Red l goods required ). Yellow Prints. (d) 1000 Pieces Printed Mock Voils(two qualities) (c) 2000 Pieces Mishmar ' - (d) 1000 ” White sheeting. (e) 2000 ” White Mulls. )a. About 17 Cwts »t OP ft 4.Approximate weight in long tons of 2240 Lbs •} of Shiah females, males and females. f* 17 )b. M 25 c. ' 5 n d. w 25 M e. M 5 M 5.Exact use or purpose)a.For the use of females, contemplated for the)b.As above, goods to be Imported)c.For the use d.&amp; e.Both for 6.Special reason justifying:- (a) Supply of goods wanted:-(a)Since the last 20 years this is being used here.It is coming only from England. Prior to the war Japanease copied (b) The designs and colours are available only from England. (c) Available only from England. (d &amp; E)Available from India but quality not like England make. (b) Their import from the country suggested rather than from any other country:-As stated above.A,B and C are not available from any other countryV J. E. KHEDOURI IMPORT &amp; EXPORT TELE ADDRPSS khed ouri-bah rain telephone. 83~m codes used:- BCNTLEYS ACME &amp; ORIENTAL bankbrs;- thb eastern bank ltd. KEF.NO.52 (g) ^ ft PAGE NO.2 ir'ain 20 - h ° (ARABIA) H#b#Mf s Politic®! Agent.Bahrain.Through Director of Customs, and Fort Officer. the ur 6 e ncy ) A,B and C are urgently with whlcn the goods are ) required and not available required and the^latest date) at Bahrain. which will be suitable ) d &amp; E of London make are not available. Shipment as soon as possibly .vith reference to the goods under A. E and C mentioned above, we would inform you that during the last ?wo years arrived ing from England and if they do not arrive here for a long tirre Tnt-er/ result wou:, - d that the consumers would take nterest for goods of other country and after the end of the war for r these kin^ f® f ° r L 8110 ® 31111 - 6 goods at B«hrain(3pecially for these kind of goods), we have the samples in our hand* and if The suff^er Se u them T ^ ^ ^ t0 ^° duce them before you! . , ® su lPliers Pessrs J.M.Shasha named above, advised us that if they receive recomrr.endation for export and shipping space tn,! would be able to ship promptly. Trusting that £ou than *4 gJad thankingVu 063 tleS With ^ 'Cities for^hich we are® Yours faithfullyJ. E. KHEDOURI IMPORT &amp; EXPORT T*LK ADDRESS KHB DQURI-BAH RAIN telephone. 83-m codes used:- BENTLEYS ACME &amp; ORIENTAL bankers:- the eastern bank ltd. A / £ tr 2 / • i&amp;- hi iS) RjbiF. ^0 . ^&gt;6 ^v. The^Qlrector ol Eaiirklne Port Officer ^vvy^V) Dear Sir: Our Principals Messrs J,M*Shasha of Manchester., offered us under their cable dated 21st instant, ready stock of Netting 22425 Yards weighing about 18 Cwt., and I shall be much obliged if you kindly recommend for the necessary shipping space. 1. Name of would be importer:- J.E.Khedouri. Bahrain. 2. Name and address of agent ) Messrs J.M.Shasha. or manufacturer in the ) Asia House, exporting country from whom) 82 Princess Street he wishes to arrange supply) Manchester, 1« o • Full description of the goods required : 22425 Yards Cotton Netting, 4. Approiiihate weight in long tons of 2240 Lbs .:About 18 Cwts. 5. Exact use or purpose )Specially for the use of contemplated for the goods )Bahrain ladies, as veils to be imported :)and dress# 6. Special reason justifying:- . / * r . (a) Supply of goods wanted:- Require specially it Bahrain#.:r c , o 1 * rd# (b) Their import from the country)This g»f&gt;de are suggested rather than from Especially manufactured any other country 0 )only in Lancashire, Manchester,England. 7. Description of the urgency with) Urgently required as which the goods are required and) nothing available# the date which will be suitable ) Shipment as soon as 'S&gt; Thanking you in anticipation. possible# Yours faithfully ft '{'i n-aboody yacoob ZELOOF &amp; SONS. CLOTH MERCHANTS *fc COMMISSION AGENTS. Tele Add: ZELOOF. BAHRAIN &amp; BOMBAY. K- (iI I,F. INDIA. / 7 ^ ! I JJ ' ^.*Su j) j Or;j^ / 7 /• Bahrain, 4th J amary 1944. H. B. M f s Political Agent, Bahraiq. Sir: Reference to our order of 20th dune 1043, we beg £ou to inform us v/hether our order is recommended by you. enclosed, please find copy of our order which we sent to you for recommendation. Also, please find telegram which we just received from our supplier from Manchester that he requires Priority A to enable him to ship our goods. Also, please find enclosed two more telegrams, one for which he accepted our order and the second which_we have remitted 5:2000/ deposit for our goods which he has purchased for our account. noping you will grant me permit for the goods which are lying there in Manchester as most of our money now lying in Manchester. Please send back our telegrams and copy or our indent. Thanking you in anticipation of a formable reply, \, A A We remAin, Sir Your most obediently, V ^ £fon*. AO Political Agency, Ban rain. Dated a*//January Forwarded to the Director oi Customs, Bahrain ror comments and return. for Foiitica 1 agent,Bahrain.From* Aboodi Yacoob Zelfcof &amp; Sons. Bahrain. (Persain Gulf.) Bahrain, June 20th 1943* Ha B. M’s The Political Ae.ent, Bahrain, Description of niece floods to be exported from 4 Bales of Black and White Net 37 inches of 60 yards each piece. 400 pieces. 2 Bales of White Voile 52 inches of 40 yards each piece. 200 pieces. 2 Bales of Printed Voile 36 inches of 40 yards each piece. 200 Pieces, 2 Bales of Black Crepe Satan 36 inches of 50 yards each piece. 100 pieces. 2 Bales of Black Striped Doria 28 inches of 60 yards each piece. 200 pieces. 5 Bale* of Red Shawls 55 n x55 ,, 500 dozen. 5 Bales of Red Shawls 51flx51 ,, 300 dozen. 2 Bales of Wollen .Cloth 56 inches of 30 yards. 20 pieces. 1 Bale of Shirtinf^2 inches of 40 yards. 50 pieces. i) Name of would-be importer. ii) Name and address of agent or manufacture in the exporting country from whom he wishes to arrange supply. Aboodi Yacoob Zeloof &amp; Sons, Bahrair Messrs. J. Akerib. 21, Chorlton Street, Manchester,!. England. iii) Full description of the goods required. Mentioned in the above pagt iv) Approximate weight in long tons of 2240 lbs. of the goods required. About 10 Tons. (N.B-Weight is essential in order to arrange shipping programes). (v) Fxact use or purpose contemplated for For sale in our market, the goods to be imported. (vi) Special re son justifying- (a) supply of goods wanted, None in the market. (b) their import from the country suggested rather than any other country. Not obtainable elsewhere. (vii) Description of the urgency with which the goods are required, and As early as possible, the latest date which will be suitable. We r main, 3ir Your mosi obediently.~ t'A - * r- - BAHRAIN- © Bahrein 3rd January 44 List of the goods From, Llessrs, Earnest E, Tolson Bradford England I ton Woolen peice goodse.TRTKAMDAS &amp; CO. BAHRAIN. Bahrein 3rd January 44 List of the Coods From, Messrs, Bodge and Saymour New york I ton Hosiery and ^C.P.goods ekt-IB.TRIKAMDAS &amp;CO, ^IfAHRAJN Bahrein 3rd January 44 List of the goods From, Messrs, Standage &amp; Co Ltd Bradford (England) X Tone Woolen peice goods and Cotton peice gC.TRIXAMDAS &amp; CO, BAHRAIN- C; Bahrein 3rd January 44 List of the goods From, Messrs, Dayton Price and CO Nev/yourk U.S.^. I ton Iloseiry and C.P. Goods and Haberdashery$L CO. S'-? BAHHMN' Bahrein 3rd January 44 List of the goods From, Llessrs, Hawks &amp; Go Ltd London ©ne I ton ',/hite and Khaki Cork HairnetstS. TRI-KAMO AS &amp; C b! Bahrein January 3rd 44 List of the goods From, Messrs, Biddle Sawyer &amp; co Ltd England I ton Cottonpeice goods and Hoseiry and Haberdashery./ BAHRAIN. Bahrein 3rd Jauary 44 The Director of Customs and Port Officer. Bahrein. Dear Sir, v, r ith reference to the notification no 2963 36/39 of 29th December 43 from Political Agonoy we beg to enclose herewith indents of our requirements from U.K. and TJ.S.A and shall be much obliged if you will kindly grant us the neocessary permits for the same • Thanking you in anticipation C.0. To H.B.Ms Political Agent Bahrein.TRTfC AMDAS SCO BAHKMN. L. 4 Bahrein 3rd January 44 List of the goods From, Messrs, Tootal Broadhurst Lee and Co Ltd Manchester ton Cotton peioe goods/ c trikamdas &amp; c&lt; ^ BAHRAIN. The Director of Customs ? j ^7 and Port Officer I &gt;D Bahrefcn. •/: ££- 6.® 7 - / Vv Bahrain 3rd January 44 Dear Sir, With reference to the notification No 29 63 __ 36/39 of 29th december 43 from Political Agency we beg to enclose herewith indents of our requirements fromU.K, and U.S.A. and shall be much obliged if you will kindly grant us the neccessary permits for the same. Thanking you in anticipation C.C. to H«B«Ms Political Agent Bahrein. Yo s faithfully♦' . H P. i&gt; H * ^ ^ • 6$ Bahrein 3rd January 44 List of the goods Prom Messrs, May and Hamnel Ltd Bradford (England) I ton Woolen peioe goods and Silk lining and Canvis and Cotton lining -Ij L COPY AbbftBbhai Hatimbhai Bah I'fiin. To H-B.M’s Political Agent, Bahrain* Re spectea Sir, With reference to raeuioranciun No. BO of witii parti cniara form. We enclcvsea herewith particulars with full description of the goods wmch we requireci from United Kingdom imported for Persian Gulf. We hope your honour will kindly grant us a recommendation for shipping space and obliged. We remain Respected Sir, Sd. Yours Obedientlyin rn^nixi tc gooes e»sontinl3.y ro juirod from United Kingdom, United states oi‘ Ancrien or Canada by the Arab States in the Persian G,ulf* 1. Name would-be importer • . .Abbasbhai Hatimbhai,Bahrain. 2. Name and address of agent or. ••The Central Agency Ltd. f cilasgow. manufacturer in tne exporting country from whom he wishes to arrange suppl^ r . 3. Full description rf tne goods..Uotton throad Border ;i.:eins &amp; required. cotton tiircaci cord reels. Approximate weight in long tons..^ ton. of lbs. ^ b. K*xact use or purpose contem- • •.’inbroidand sewing purroae. platea for tno goods to oc import©a• 6. special reasons justifying* (a) guppiy of goods wanted.-No stock. (b) Thoir import from the ...Not obtainable elsewhere, country suggested rather tnan from aiiy other country* .. 7* lie script ion of the urgency ••••As soon as poesiLble. with which tiie goods are required and -hu .latent date which will bo suitable.No. HH-'S'OSf of 1363 Office of the Adviser to the Government, Bahrain Dated, Moharram 16, 1363 January 12, 1944. Reference your memorandum No.2970-36/43 dated 29th December 1943, enclosing letters from Mr. J.E. Khedouri, Bahrain (returned herewith). As all the goods for which a quota is requested are from the United Kingdom and the importer has in the past traded principally in British goods I suggest that in the interest of the future export trade from Great Britain he should be allowed to import as much of the goods as possible even if a* certain proportion may ultimately be sold to the mainland. As regards the essential necessity for the goods I enclose a copy of a memorandum from the Director of Customs and port Officer. I consider however that mosquitoe nettings, blankets and napthql^ne balls are required here also blue serge which is used for uniforms. Memorandum: - H. B. M’s Political Agent, Bahrain. S.Z. Adviser to the Government.Copy of memorandum No.GT/34 dated 5th January 1944 from the Director of Customs and Port Officer, Bahrain,’to the Adviser to the Government, Bahrain* -1% Reference attached application of J.E. Khedouri. not on the first Page of letter No. 12 are variable w 1 t0 Bahra i n l a nd have in the past when imported, in variably been re-exported to Saudi Arabia, Kuwait etc. With regards to Woolen Blankets, Suitings and Blue Serge n? trSm f^ h d0UbtfUl if the ez P° rt wi H be allowed from England, and they are not essential. Of the items mentioned in letter No.13, 4 cases Boot Polish may be recommended and 3 cases Ink. pieces 7/00len Piece Goods mentioned in letter No. 14 may also be recommended. our Pottor/pf^a Bettlir + No - 32 » in view o'f the smalliness of our Cotton Piece Goods quota from India, and provided the exnort i onn 1116 - 18 nob Pf oh i b i tod . a recommendation should be given for 1,000 pieces ,/hite Sheeting and 2,000 White Mulls.J. E. KHEDOURI IMPORT &amp; EXPORT TBLR ADDRPSS khedouri-bahrain •4 h 'b telephone. 83 -M codes used;- PENTLEV'S ACME &amp; ORIENTAL Bankers;- thb eastern bank ltd. REF.NO*44 j* Ul ui-,. 7J H.E.M’s Political Agent. BAHRAIN. Dear Sir: l^&gt;th January 4. Vs//r/7/t? ABIA) Please refer to your letter No.119-36/4o of the even date. As desired by you in your letter under reference, we are sending you herewith a telegram dated 21st December 194o, in origin, which would clarify you as to the acceptance of our order by our Principals Messrs J.M.Shasha., Manchester. Please return the cable when done with® Yours faithfully^ )ABOODY YACOOB ZELOOF &amp; SONS. CLOTH MERCHANTS * COMMISSION AGENTS. Tele Add: ZELOOF. BAHRAIN &amp; BOMBAY. F* GULF. INDIA. / 3/V t i / - O'/ V j' j&lt;_i Jj V H. B, M f s Political Agent, Bahrain. Bahraih, 17th January 1944. Sir: At oached please find an order of ten tons of the Controller of Bahrain fecomended to us. goods which ,, , . ^.Iso, please find telegram from our supplier in Iv-Ianchester onau he has accepted our order of ten tons of goods. Requesting you to grant space and thanks. us export Licence and shipping We remain. Sir Your most obediently, fZ/JtWk&amp;b St 'S; \£ /&gt; DotnilB in ro^arci to goods essentially required from the United Kingdom, United States of America or Canada by the Arab States in the Persian Gulf. 1. Name of would-be importer .... J.K.Khodouri, Bahrain. 2. Name and address of the agent • • • .Messrs J.y.shasha, Asia House, or manufacturer in the exporting 82 Princess Street, anchester, 1 country from whom he wishes to arrange supply. 3. Full description of the goods '•••22425 yards Cotton netting, required. fi. Approximate weight in long ....••About 18 Cwts. tons of 2240 lbs. 5. tixact use or purpose contem- Specially for the use of Bahrain plated for the goods to be ladies as veils and dress, imported. 6. Special reasons justifying:- (a) Supply of goods wanted . . ..Bahrain stocks of netting nearly exhausted. (b) Their import from the .......Not obtainable elsewhere. country suggested rather tlian from any other country. 7. Description of the urgency As soon as possible. with .vhich ttie goccis are required and tne latest date which will be suitable.£3 etftiln in 1 * 0 , find goodo oeaontially required from the Uni tod btntos ^moricn, united Kirv'dom or Conndn by the Arnb .»tat&lt; a in the Persian (Julf. 1* of would-bo inverter . . • Aboody Yficoob ^eloof &amp; u&gt;ns,Bnhiriin 2. flame nr address of tlie arjont tT.'kcrib T 'sq., 21 Chorlton street, or nanufacturc r in the expor- S!ancheater 1, Er^land. tinr country from whom ho wishes to arrange supply* 3. *ull des/criotion of be . • .as per attached list. Hoods required* 4. Approximate weight in long •••Approximate total lb tons* tons of 2240 lbs. 5. hxact uso or purT&gt;bae contcm- **Urr sale to the public, plated for the goods to be imported* 6* ispecinl r aeons justifying:- (a) iJupp^ of goods wanted • • Order placed over one year* ib) Their import from the ••••?Tot * country suggested isather tTian from any otlier country. • • • • Uot available elsewhere* 7* eseri'tion of the urgency •••as 8'on as with vihioli the goods are required and the latest date which will be suital 1c* possiblemmV Cajoles : Mostdfd, Bdhrdin CTel 68 U. Sole Distributors for : Wahl 'company Garvey &amp; Company A. G. Spalding &amp; Bros. ( British ) Ltd. Wanderer - Werke A. G. Albert Badberg Phoebus Werke Treibacher Chemische Werke Nationals Ltd. Famm Freres ( Lusina Watches ) West End Watch Co. (Arabian Peninsula Except Aden &amp; Bahrain ) Acme Export Corporation Cardinal Loboratories, Inc. Kia-Ora Ltd. Linc olns hire Products Ltd. Lioji'' Corporation Etc. Codes Used : Bentley's Oriental and Private H ( Prop. Mostafa bin Abdul Latiff ) IMPORTERS &amp; ! EXPORTERS H R A ( P. Gulf) N 24th January 1944 lief. No. s Political Agent. a ' Bankers : CThe Eastern Bank Ltd. Direct Importers k Dealers : Continental Typewriters (English, Arabic k Persian) Typewriter Ribbons Wanderer Cycles k M. Cycles Eversharp Pens &amp; Pencils Eveready Flashlights &amp; Cells Arrow Shirts k Shorts Krementz Products Sports Goods Palmolive Soap k Colgate Goods Hosiery &amp; Drapery Tootal Products Bourjois Perfumery Etc- Etc. Flameless Cig. Lighters Electric Toy Trains Etc. Keroga Stoves Johnson &amp; Johnson’s General Stores &amp; Provisions Bahrain. Dear Sir: We are sending you herewith a copy of an order No.16/42 dated 12th May 1942 for Tootal Neckties we placed with Messrs Tootal Broadhurst Lee &amp; Go.,Ltd. Manchester., and have to inform you that the order has been accepted and the ties are ready and even we have paid for them. We would request you to recommend to the higher authority to grant the export licence and shipping space to our Manchester Principals and thanking you for the same. In this connection we are sending you herewith the Suppliers Airgraph letter dated 30th December and their c%ble dated 9th November and our cable(Copy)dated 13th November 1943 which please return when done with. a f lv f s Yours faithfully ^LIFOPNIA HOUSE fit* Ab4ulluL%tj No. -36/43. Political Agency, Bahrain. Bated 4 January 1944. Forwarded to the director of Curtoms, Bahrain for his commenta and return. p. H'or Pol lt/fc al agen t«ORDER No. From: ■— IX'IMCIVT. California House Prof,. MUSTAFA BIN ABDULLATIFF. BAHRAIN. Persian Gulf, Date, $ &gt; j r* Shipment F^ayment Copy of an Order No. 16/42 dated 12th May 1942 1. Name of would be importer: California House. Bahrain. 2. Name and address of the agent) or manufacturers in the ) 1 essrs Tootal Broadhurst Lee exporting country from whom ) ^ -p he wishes to arrange supply ) Oxford Street anche s t er ^ 1. 3. Pull description of the goods) ^ 6 &lt; 70 Dozen Assorted required ) Tootal Neckties# 4. Approximate weight in long tons) ., &lt; About 100 Lbs of 2240 Lbs ) 5. Exact use or purpose contemplated)For consumption at Bahrain, for the goods to be imported.....) 6. Special reason justifying:- (a) Supply of goods wanted:- Order has already been accepted (Ref. their airgraph letter dated 30th December 1943 and the value also has been paid ref. their value 9th Nov. and . our cable dated 13th Nov.1943. (b) Their import from the country) - . suggested rather than from ) '°} aval lable this parti- any other country •••••••) brand of ties from any other country. 7. Description of the urgency with) TT which the goods are required and) Urgently required. To be the latest date which will be ) sent P er P ar cel post as suitable ) soon a s possible. Yours faithfully '-*l“ Or* awlja . , ‘titf)■ E. KHEDOURI IMPORT &amp; EXPORT TBLB ADDRESS KHED OURI-BAH RAIN telephone. g 3 -M CODES USED:- BENTLEYS ACME &amp; ORIENTAL bankers;- thb eastern bank ltd. r ' ssrt? (ARABIA) 25th Janua f94 44, Kef.wo,47 H.E.M's Political A^ent Bahrain,, Dear Sir: 7S SUB.200 DOZEN YAS/MAGH BAACK AND WHITE In reply to our letter No.lS dated 25rd November 1945, you advised us under your letter No.176-36/43 dated the 18th instant saying that recommendation assistance towards 250 Dozen Yashmagh Black and white cannot be granted and in this connection we beg to inform you that the goods were manufactured on our account and risk and we have already paid for the same. The goods are now ready and the suppliers have received an Export Licence No 0 9B/ll95(Ref. their cable dated 22nd January 1944 herewith),for 200 Dozen the weight ©f which would be about 7 Cwts. We would feel ourselves glad If you kindly recommend to the Higher authority to grant shipping space for the same. Thanking you in anticipation. Yours faithfully F.S: In this connection we are also sending you herewith suppliers Airgraph letter No.45 dated the 2nd October 1943 and the same is self-explanatory.V f . J- 5 J. E. KHEDOURI IMPORT &amp; EXPORT TBLE ADDRKSS KHEP QURI-BAH RAIN telephone. 83-m CODES USED:- BENTLEYS ACME &amp; ORIENTAL B ANKERS the eastern bank ltd. (ARABIA) Ref, No.52 H.E.M’s Political A^ent. Bahrain. / Dear Sir: RE.MY LETTER NO. 14 OP 23^11- I thank you for/your memorandum N®. Iv6-36/43 dated the 18th instant and in/reply t® the last item mentioned in regard to my letter N®.14 of the 23rd November 1943, I beg t® enclose herewith the telegram which I received from my Principals in England regarding, same and I trust this will fulfil your requirement. The weight ®f the goods would be about 10 Cwts. Yours faithfully rsDetails in regal’d to goods essentially required from the °nited Kingdom, United states o n America or Canada by the Arab iitatos in the Persian Gulf. 1 • Name of woul !-bc importer . . . .Messrs Haji Iteiis Hassan lais Sadi &amp; Co., IHibai. 2. Name and address of the agent ..Vessrs George Kaufrnann(London) or manufacturer in t!ie oxpor- Ltd., Ibex House, Kinories, ting country from whom he London, K.C.3 wishes to arrange supply. 3. Full description of the goods ..../5085 sqjiare yards black netting required. 4. Approximate weight in long ..••••350 lbs. nett. tons of 2240 lbs* 5. Exact use or purpsoocontem- For sale to the public* plated for the goods to bo imported. 6. Spec ini reasons jnotifying (a) Supply of goods wanted None available in Dubai market. (b) Their Import from the Not available elsewhere. country suggested rather tlian from any other country. ,.By May 1944 7. Description of the urgency with which the goods are reonired and the latest date which will be suitsfc le. • • •J. E. KHEDOUR1 IMPORT &amp; EXPORT TBLR ADDRESS KHED OURI-BAH RAIN telephone. 83~m codes used:- RENTLEYS ACME &amp; ORIENTAL Banrers;- thb eastern bank ltd. KEF,NO,55 H.b.M 1 s Political Agent* Bahrain, / 7/7 '7' ^ (ARABIA) ^*^1 jC*J\ 4th Februa % s \ Dear Sir: 1* Name of would be importer:- J,E,Khedouri, Bahrain, 2, Name and address of the agent) Messrs George Kaufmann or manufacturer in the expor-) (London )ltd, ting country from whom he ) Ibex House, Minories, wishes to arrange supply ) London E,C,3 3, Full description of the goods) 2500 Squareyards required ) Mosquito netting. y 4, Approximate weight in long tons of 2240 Lbs ) Net 185 Lbs, ) 5, Exact use or purpose contem-) For ladles dress and plated for the goods to be ) veils, imported ,,««««) 6, Special reason justifying:- (a) Supply of goods wanted:- Order has been accepted and received Export Licence No,9E/4049l/42• Waiting for sponsorship,(Suppliers telegram dated 28th Januai? 1944 is herewith) (b) Their import from the) Mosquito netting available cnl country suggested ) from England, rather than from any ) other country ) 7, Description of the urgency) Urgently required, Shiprmnt with which the goods are ) as soon as possible, required and the latest ) which will be suitable ) We would feel ourselves glad if you kindly recommend to the Higher authority to grant shipping space. C, J_ __ .. Director of Custom* and Port Officer, BAHRAIN- Yours faithfully ‘7J. E. KHEDOURI IMPORT &amp; EXPORT T8LE APDRKSS KHEDOURI-BAHRAIN telephone. 83~ m codes used:- PENTLEYS ACME &amp; ORIENTAL bankers;- thb eastern bank ltd. REF.NO *54 H.B.M’s Political Agent Bahrain. ?3 'a/srasn (ARABIA) 1000 1 5 700 4 3 1 Dear Sir: Please refer to your letter No.176-36/43 dated 18th January 1944. / With reference to the under mentipned items 2000 Pieces White Mulls - }* ^ l Pieces White shirtings Bale Blue serge ^ —-p—* n L ^ ^ Bales Woolen Blankets r’ . ■ Pieces Mosquito Nets *^—-—? 7 Cases Boot polish . Cases Ink , Ton Nepthaline balls , we are enclosing herewith a cable in origin dated 4th Instant we have received from our suppliers Messrs George Kaufmann(London)Ltd. Ibex House, Minories London E.C.3 In which you would notice that our order for the above named items, has been accepted and requesting you to kindly recommend to the Higher Authority to grant shipping space. In the meantime we also request you to consider the consignor named above Instead of MESSRS J^l.SHASHA and when recommending for shipping space please make the necessary alterations accordingly. Thanking you in anticipation. Yours faithfully0 © notoils in rogarri to goods essentially required from the United Kingdom, TTnitcd states of America or Canada by the Arab States in the Persian Gulf. 3. Name of would-be importer . • Khedouri, Bahrain. Name and address of the agent.Nessrs George Kaufmann,(London) or manufacturer in the expor- Ltd., Ibex House, wineries, ting country ’rom 4iom ho London , K.C. 3 wishes to arrange supply. Full description of the goods required. b ** 2 2000 pieces white mulls 1000 * M shirting 1 bale blue sei^ge 5 bales woollen bankets 700 pieces mosquito' jmub&amp;s nets 4 cases boot polish 3 cases ink 1 ton Napthalinc balls 3500 square yards mosquito netting 4. Approximate weight in long....5^ tons, tons of 2340 lbs* 5. fbcact use or purpose contemplated. .For sale to the public, for the goods to be imported. 6. Special reasons justifying*- (a) Supply of goods wanted ..Bahrain stocks limited. (b) Their import from the country suggested rather ••••Not available elsewhere. tlian from any other country. 7. Description of the urgency with..By *&gt;uno 1944. which the goed s arc required and the latest date which will be suitable•NO ENQUIRY RESPECTING THIS TELEGRAM CAN BE ATTENDED TO WITHOUT PRODUCTION OF THIS COPY. Printed in Ensland. JULY ItUO. (5.000 pad*.) CABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED. QV93/M BOMBAY 33 8 RB KR ANTEN = LC MAJOR T HICKINBOTHAM CIE OBE THE AGENCY BAHRAIN = • JOHN LEAN SONS LIMITED GLASGOW ONLY MANUFACTURERS ARAB SHAWLS EXPERIENCING CONSIDERABLE DIFFICULTIES to EXPORT REQUEST YOUR RECOMMENDATION FOR FIFTY BALES TO GOVERNMENT OF INDIA WHICH AFTER ENDORSEMENT WILL BE SENT INDIA OFFICE LONDON TO FACILITATE SHIPMENT STOP REQUEST TELEGRAPHIC RECOMMENDATION EXPENSE HORNSYROAft -NO ENQUIRY RESPECTING THIS TELEGRAM CAN BE ATTENDED TO WITHOUT PRODUCTION OF THIS COPY. Th« first line of this Telegram contains the following particulars in the order named Prefix Letcen and Number of Meuije. Office of Orifin, Number, of Words, Date, Time handed in and Offldj v «ructioni—if any. Printed in England. JULY 1D40. ( 5.000 pada.l » ax \*^V 5/-168 , CABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED. -1 'INCORPORATED IN ENOLAND.) \ 1 / DASV41/M BISHOPS STORTFORD 79 9 1810 = RP13.15 NLT BRITISH POLITICAL AGLNT BAHRAIN = UNDERSTAND JESEPH KHEDOURI EXPERIENCING DIFFICULTIES REGARDING SHIPPING PERMITS FIFTY PIECES WOOLLENS OFFERED BY US FOR SAUDI ARAB IA PURCHAS ED BY IBRAHIM — ALJMIAH HASSA FOR SHIPMENT VIA BAHRAIN TO OJAIR STOP WOOL CONTROL CALLS FOR UKCC RECOMMENDATION FOR SHIPPING SPACE BEFORE GRANTING EXPORTLICENCE RELEASE GOODS STOP WE UNDERSTAND BAHRAIN SHIPMENTS l MARK YOUR REPLY ‘ 4 2%a €?77i/ie^UaCNO ENQUIRY RESPECTING THIS TELEGRAM CAN BE ATTENDED TO WITHOUT PRODUCTION OF THIS COPY. The first line of this Telegram contains the followlr particulars in the order named :— Prefix Letter! and Number of Heuaje. v Office of Orlfin. Words, Date, Time handed in and Official Ructions—if a v 1940. (5.000 pads. 1 CABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED. 5/-168 Clerk’s Time Oircuit. Name. Received. DASV41/M SHT 2. NOT UNDER UKCC CONTROL PLEASE ASSIST BY RECOMMENDATION TO MESC OR APPROPRIATE AUTHORITY FOR TRANSMISSION LONDON STOP WOULD APPRECIATE ADVICE WHETHER YOU FIND THIS PRACTICABLE = = EVANS = MARK YOUR REPLY Sm/ieSiiaCTelegram From To Repealed to No. E.O. XXX. India Office, London. Political Resident, Bushire. Political Agent, Bahrain. 3357 Dated the 8th received the 10th February, 1944. —&amp; S j to £ A Khedouris order v/ith Messrs. Shasha for 1000 dozen /red shawls which were suported by yhu and Government of India. / 300 dozen already manufactured have been recommended for ship ment but Board of Trade are unwilling to release cotton for manufacture of rest # 3hasha states shawls are urge: tly required for religious purposes and that there is an acute shortage in Bahrain. PI ase confirm and add any comments regarding date by which delivery is required and consequences if not supplied to enable us to support to Board of Trade. - RET AX AND UM - V s-V HWD.Major?. Hickinbotham C. I.E.,O.B.E., The Agency, BAHREIN (Persian Gulf) Bear Sir, si f\J \ RE: ARAB SHAV/LS WARTIME TEL: ADDRESS: BELLRUSS. HORNBYRD. BOMBAY. We have the honour to address you at the request of our Principals Messrs. John Lean &amp; Sons,Ltd of Glasgow, who at present are the only manufacturers of Arab Shawls (Yashmags) in U.K. They have been regularly supplying for more than sixty years to your market, but due to abnormal circumstances, they are experiencing certain difficulties and hence after hearing from them we cabled you this day as follows:- JOHN LEAN SONS LIMITED GLASGOW ONLY MANUFACTURERS ARAB SHAWLS EXPERIENCING CONSIDERABLE DIFFICULTIES TO EXPORT REQUEST YOUR RECOMMENDATION FOR FIFTY BALES TO GOVERNMENT OF INDIA WHICH AFTER ENDORSEMENT WILL BE SENT INDIA OFFICE LONDON TO FACILITATE SHIPMENT STOP REQUEST TELEGRAPHIC RECOMMENDATION OUR EXPENSE BELLRUSS HORNBYROAD:- Before obtaining shipping priority it is necessary that the recommendation from your goodself is to be submitted to the Government of India for endorsement after which it will be forwarded ,o Inaia Office, London, who will act immediately arranging for priority or shipment. We shall be very grateful for your assistance to our Principals in this matter and we are confident you will send the recommendation by cable for which we shall be glad to reimburse your goodself for any expenses you may have been put to. For your information please note that we are members of the Bombay Chamber of Commerce and our Bankers are the Chartered Bank ox India, Australia &amp; China to whom we refer you if a reference is required. The matter is of great urgency as due to the stoppage of Japanese supplies and the closing down of the only other Glasgow manufacturer of these Shawls the Iranian Gulf markets are practically dependent on J our Principals for them. The fact that in recent years the demand has been well maintained appears to us to indicate that they are a very necessary article of apparel to the Arab and if supplies are now withdrawn he will have to find some substitute which may ultimately result in the U.K. losing the markets for these goods.M.T.H. 2 5/2/44 Theeraerohant who has placed orders with us for these Shawls for shipment to Gulf Ports assures us that they are very urgently required and is pressing for delivery* We fully appreciate that there must he large and urgent demands for freight space to Iranian Gulf at present ana that Military requirements must take precedence but we oo ^ee^ it is important that the needs of the Arab population should be considered whenever possible and that the British interest in this trade should not be lost. We have therhonour to be Sir, Your most obedient servants.fo}. rel* rrora To 1 -jo. 107 Dated 14th ^'ebiMary 1944. iiifT CLAIH Political Agent Dvans, Bishops , Bahrain. Stortford, England. ,7 »oolen shawls for Baudi-Arahia. Bahrain has yearly quota shipping space and I cannot give up any of this for goods to other countries. BAT' Political Agentfel. tin. clair i*‘rom Political Agent, Bahrain, To Cottage, Bomb ay Bo. 108 Dated 14th February 1944. f 6 , /.»» ’ ,#l Arab shawls. Consignee has not approached me for assistance. Flense Understand reexoort these goods from Bahrain will not be allowed. Poli :ical AgentI Cables : Moslafa, Bahrain CTal. 68 M. Sole Distributors for : Wahl Company Garvey &amp; Company A. G. Spalding &amp; Bros. ( British ) Ltd. Wanderer - Werke A. G. Albert Badberg Phoebus Werke Treibacher Chemische Werke Nationals Ltd. Famm Freres ( Lusina Watches ) West End Watch Co. (Arabian Peninsula Except Aden &amp; Bahrain ) Acme Export Corporation Cardinal Loboratories, Inc. Kia-Ora Ltd. Lincolnshire Products Ltd. Lionel Corporation Etc. Codes Used : Bentleg's Oriental and Private CALIFORNIA HOU Jit-f. iVu. ( Prop. Mostafa bin Abdul Latiff ) IMPORTERS EXPORTERS BAHRAIN ( P. Gulf) 13th February 194-4- Banlcers : CThe Eastern Bank Ltd. Direct Importers &amp; Dealers : Continental Typewriters (English, Arabic Persian) Typewriter Ribbons Wanderer Cycles &amp; M. Cycles Eversharp Pens &amp; Pencils Eveready Flashlights &lt; ells Arrow Shirts &amp; Shorts Krementz Products Sports Goods Palmolive Soap «Sc Colgate Goods Hosiery &amp; Drapery Tootal Products Bourjois Perfumery Etc- k tc ‘ Flameless Cig. Lighters Electric Toy Trains Etc. Keroga Stoves Johnson &amp; Johnsons General Stores &amp; Provisions i H.B.M’s Political Agent. Bahrain. Dear Sir: Please refer to your letter Ho.358-36/43 dated 3rd instant. We are sending you herewith in origin a cable dated 11th instant we have received from our Principals Messrs Tootal Broadhurst., in which you would 'otxce that they have received an Sxport Permit No.93/3158, 43 in connection with our order with them and requesting you to be kind enough to recommend to the Higher Authority to allow them shipping space. Please return the cable when done with. Yours faithfully ^ VL it Or- NiA H OUScm/tm Printed in fyiclanji. JULY 1»40. ( 5.000 padfl.i CABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED. DASV5/T BISHOPSTORTFORD 80 14 1?24 GIF CK== NLT RP10/5 BRITISH POLITICAL AGENT BAHREIN== APPARENTLY OUR TE^EffRAM N l/NTH ARRIVED MUTILATED h BECAUSE UNINTERESTED SHAWLS STOP ORDER ACCEPTED FOR ENGLISH WOOLLEN SUITINGS STOP POSITION IS THAT WOOL- CONTROL PREPARED RELEASE GOODS IF SHIPMENT PRACTICABLE STOP CONTROL HAS REQUESTED UKCC RECOMMENDATION BUT UNDERSTAND SAUDI ARAB IAN PERSIANGULF PORTS OUTSIDE THEIR SPHERE INTEREST STOP UNDERSTAND BAHREIN NORMAL MARK YOUR REPLY Jm/ie?uaC NO ENQUIRY RESPECTING THIS TELEGRAM CAN BE ATTENDED TO WITHOUT PRODUCTION OF THIS COPY.ftNO ENQUIRY RESPECTING THIS TELEGRAM CAN BE ATTENDED TO WITHOUT PRODUCTION OF THIS COPY. The first line of this Telegrer particulars in the order n ABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED. ^ ''-'fdB. Incorporated in England Clerk's Time Circuit. Name. Received. DASV5/T SHEET NO.2, PORT ENTRY FOR OJAIR WOULD MUCH APPRECIATE YOUR GRANTING INTERVIEW KHEDOURI ENABLING CLARIFICATION POSITION AND CABLING US WHETHER DELIVERY PRACTI CABLE VIA BAHRAIN OR SAY OTHER PORT THANKS == ==ARTHUR EVANS== MARK YOUR REPLY Dla Sm/ie?iia£^•mas Printed in England. Aug. 1941. (100) Counter No. i ?• 3 J i i j i •i ! v i CABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND.) PREPAID REPLY FORM. ~A9o^v$ /r lio' 57-233 No. of Telegram The charge for a reply to Telegram No. L3LX handed in at on the ^addressed to :— / m having been prepaid by the Sender, this Form will be accepted WITHIN THREE MONTHS of the date of its issue, at any of the Company's Branches in pay ment, part payment, as the case may be of an ordina/ till rate, or other class of telegram, where admissible, to the value of_ Xft* *|c. V) (Signature of Issuing Officer) The value of unused prepaid reply forms refunded to the Sender of the Original Telegrai the form be returned to the ISSUING OFFICE wi three months of the date of issue. If the charge for Reply Telegram is less than the amount deposited In payment of the reply, the difference will be refunded to the Sender of the original Telegram on application within three months, providing that the amount to be refunded is not less than one shilling and eightpence. Date. Words. Time. Excess Charges. Instructions. Sent at * No. and Circuit Sent by (Clerk’s Name and Date Stamp) _J To Receiver's Name Address i I request that the above Telegram may be forwarded subject to the Conditions printed on the back of this form 'l by which I agree to be bound. I Signature and Address of Sender Teuphom no.~ *f (NOT TO BE TELEGRAPHED.) z The Declaration on the back of the form must be signed for Deferred or Letter Telegrams. [P.T.O.♦ S c . ? CONDITIONS. 1. The Company or any Telegraph Company or Government Telegraph Administration, by whom this telegram is or would in the ordinary course of the. telegraphic service be forwarded, may decline to forward such telegram although^/ it has been received for that purpose ; but in such case the amount p&lt;^~^ f^r transmission will be refunded to the sender at his request. 2. Neither the Company nor any Telegraph Company, or Government Telegraph Administration, by whom this telegram is or would in the ordinary course of the telegraphic service be forwarded, nor any of their respective officers or servants shall be liable to make compensation for any loss, injury or damage arising or resulting from non-transmission or non-delivery of the telegram, or delay, or error, or omission in the transmission or delivery thereof, through whatever cause such non-transmission, non-delivery, delay, error, or omission shall have occurred even though occasioned by the neglect or default of such Company 01 Administiation 01 any officer or servant in their employ. 3. This telegram shall be forwarded in accordance with the provisions of the International Telegraph Regulations and the provisions of such Regulations shall be deemed to be binding between the sender and this or any Telegraph Company or Government Telegraph Administration by whom this telegram is or would in the ordinary course of the telegraphic service be forwarded. 4. The above mentioned conditions also apply to telegrams tendered to or delivered by the Company by telephone, over a private line, or by any other means whatsoever. / tuc FOLLOWING declaration must be signed for deferred or letter 1M TELEGRAMS I certify this telegram is written in the language, the text is entirely plain language and it does not bear any meaning other than that which appears on the face of it. Signature.. Address Date./ J. E. KHEDOURI khedouri-sahrain IMPORT &amp; EXPORT BENTLEYS ACME &amp; ORIENTAL BANKBRs;- thb eastern bank ltd. telephone. g 3 -M codes used:- (ARABIA) 26th Dec o REF.Nt • 35 H.B.M's Political Agent. Bahrain. THROUGH; The Director of Customs and Port Officer. Dear Sir: 1. Name of would be importer: J.h.Khedouri. Bahrain. 2. Name and address of agent) or manufacturer in the ) Messrs George Kaufmann exporting country from ) (London)Ltd. whom he wishes to arrange) Ibex House.Minor!es supply ) London K.C.b b. Full description of the 5 0 isxact use or purpose contem-) For consumption 6. Special reason justifying:- (a) Supply of goods wanted:- Not available at Bahrain. (b) Their import from the )Ready made goods country suggested rather )and available for than from any other country)immediate shipment. 7. Description of the urgency with) Urgently required, which the goods are required ) As soon as possible and the date which will be ) suitable ) Requesting you to do the needful with the authorities and thanking you for the same. goods required 25 Pieces Printed Woolen Cashmeres 4. Approximate weight in long tons of 2240 Lbs About S Cwts plated for the goods to j at Bahrain be imported ....:) Yours faithfully Director of Ct.u and fort Officeri lr , rT ^ 1 V THE following declaration must e BE # sig»ed for deferred or letter language, the text is entirely I ‘ hiS tdeg T“ meaning other than that which appears on the tace of it. plain language, ana u uuc ^ ^ ^ ..Address... Signaturem !»ctniln in regard to goods essentially required i*rom United Kingdom, United states of nneriea or Canada by the Arab states in the Persian Gulf* 1* Namr of viould-bc importer. 2m Nano and address of agent ..... or nnnufacturor in the exporting country from whom he wishes to arrange supply* 3 • Kull description of the goods required ✓ 4* Approximate weight in long to of ^240 lbs 5 6 : tona .. Abdulaflsiz Ali Baaaam*, Bahrain* r^essrs. John Lean aons i td* :1 - s ow* Arab Yashmags. (50 bales) 18 to 19n tons. Ji.xact use or purpose contemplated for the gocxls to be imported. Special reasons Justifying:- (a) supply of goods wanted (b) 'ilieir import froiJ the Country suggested mtlier thay from any other country. For salo to Public. ~IO btecks exhausted. Not available from elsewhere. 7 . description of the urgency with which the goods are required and the latest date which will be suitable**.**.**•*•*•• ns early as possible*ABOODY YACOOB ZELOOF &amp; SONS. CLOTH MERCHANTS &amp; COMMISSION AGENTS. Tele Add: ZELOOF. BAHRAIN &amp; BOMBAY. P- GULF. INDIA. ^ 'jJjv Bahrain, 12th March, 1944. H.B.M’s Political Agent, Bahrain. Dear Sir: In reply to your esteemed letter Do.622-36/43 dated the 8th instant, I beg to advise that the total length of all cloth (except red shawls) for which import license is requested is 106,000 Yards . Thanking you for your valued assistance. \ Yours faithfully, K ABOODY YACOUB ZELOOF &amp; SONS.File No. ■ • • 'T. DEPART BRANCH A . Class for telegrams To be issued qu 1st Reminder Pnd Reminder 3rd Reminder Heading : C’ase or Diary No. If post copy of telegram required Date of despatch of above List of enclosures Ordinary E&gt;;j&gt;icss&gt; J i gent '• Priority '' CJ ear Linef •Only for i No. Foreign i Telegrams. Datei ♦ Not for Foreign Telegrams. issued ou To (Code word fo telegrams.) Lcrial .\o. py i Letter OySLlt (Vlfino. nodun. Teiegtaru 19 i Ji«*rom To No.ail Dated 23rd March 1944. TKL&amp;GRAM - G.T.C. Political Agent, iiahrain. dritconsu1, Bushire• . 12 % Youi' telegram 631 TTarch IStli. 2. My recommendation may be considered as %£ cancelled as further enquiries have revealed that these shawls are similar to those mentioned in India office telegram No.3357 Pebrtiary 9th. 3A* - POIjIT ICAL -BENTLEYS ACME &amp; ORIENTAL bankers;- the eastern bank ltd. J. E. KHEDOURI IMPORT &amp; EXPORT TRLE ADDRPSS KHEDOUR I-BAHRAIN (ARABIA) REF. NO.58 J- Political Agent Bahrain* Dear sir We would request you to recommend to the Higher Authority to allow shipping spaee to the suppliers for the under mentioned order 1* Name of would be importer: J.E.Khedouri. Bahrain. 2. Name and address of the ) Messrs J.M.Shasha. agent or manufacturer ) Asia House, in the exporting country) 82 Princess Street from whom he wishes to ) Manchester 1. arrange supply. ) 5. Full description of the)500 Pieces Black netting with goods required. )big holes. 4. Approximate weight in) Approximately 1600 Lbs. long tons of 2240Lbs ) 5. Exact use or purpose contem-)For ladies dress and plated for the goods to be )veils. imported. ) 6. Special reason justifying;- (a)Supply of goods wanted:- Order has been accepted (b)Their import from the )Mosquito netting available country suggested )only from England, rather than from any ) other country. ) 7. Description of the urgency) Urgently required.Shipment with which the goods are ) as soon as possible, required and the latest ) Thanking you in anticipation. (Ref. Suppliers cables dated 20th and 21st March 1944 herewith) Yours faithfully ,J- E. KHEDOURI import &amp; EXPORT V-UDES USBD;- BENTL8VS ACME &amp; ORIENTAL THE EASTERN bank ltd. KHBDOURI-BAHRAIN ifjjiA* jAUI /n 23rcl March (ARABIA) REF«N0«57 The Director of Customs and Port Officer Bahrain* Dear Sir; MESSRS J.M.SHASHA. ASIA HOUSE 82 PRINCESS STREET MANCHESTER. We would request you to recommend to allow shipping for the same* The order has already been placed with our above named friends. with big holes weight approximately 1600 Lbs and thanking you S ?!u®v^° ? U 3; above named ^ends for 500 Pieces of Black Netting W1 til D l £T no 1 A O WO 1 rrVfc+ xv + r* r\r\ -r n ^ ^^ Yours faithfullyBAHRAIN 5th April 1944 ^Details in regard to goods essentially required from the United Kingdom, United States of America or Canada by the Arab States in the Persian Gulf. !• Name of would-be importer : hi/S Dhamanmal Issardas. 2. Name and address of the agent or manufacturer from whom he wishes to arrange supply: l/S Ralli Brothers Ltd. Manchester. 3. Full description of the goods required : White shirting 12 ' drills 10 Cheatz crepe 10 ' Printed 10 Crepe :Blaclc&amp; various colours 5 Voil printed &amp; plain 10 White ShawlB 5 Loongis 5 Woolen Cloth 5 tons•^ n tt t? tt tt 4. Approximate weight in long tons of 2240 lbs.: 72 4 bales per ton, i. e. each bale weighing approximately V560 lbs;. 5. Lxact use or purpose For local consumption, contemplated for the goods to be imported.: 6. Special reasons justifying:- (a) Supply of goods wanted: (b) their import from the country suggested rather than from any qther country . : 7. Description of the urgency with v/hich the goods are required and the latest date which will be suitable. : To relieve the local shortage, caused by the exhaustion of local stocks. 1. The above mentioned goods are unobtainable from any other country. 2. It will be cheaper if imported from the country of origin. The goods are required as early as possible, being totally out-of-stock, within 4 months at the latest;/?o Dotnils in ro^nrd to goods ossontially roq»tired from tlic United 1 in Mon, Tlhitod Jtntos of Anorion or Cnnncln by the A mb dtntoo in tho Pern inn 3ul£ • !• Nano of would-be importer. 2« None and address of the af'e*vt or manufacturer in tho expor ,inn country from vjhon ho wishes to arrange supply# J. Full description of tho goods required- 4# Approximate weight in long tons of 2240 lbs. 5# Exact use or purpose contonplntcd for the goods to bo imported. C • ipcc ia 1 re a sc n s j uo t if y 1 n g»- (s) Supply of goods wanted. (b) Thcii^ inrort from the country suggested rather than from any otlier country. 7. Ocscrintion of ho urgency with which the goods arc requirod and the latest date diich 4 ill be suitable. ■r. J.P. Khedouri, Bahrain. 'esars J.' r . &gt;ha &gt;ha, Asia Hotise, 82 3 rinoeaa street, ranc’iester 1. 500 nieces Black netting fith big holes. 14 cwt. £ 32 lbs. 'or sale to public. Stoc ks exhauated. Pot available from elsewhere. As early nn possible*—— No -36/43 POLITICAL AGENCY, _ mHTV v PT. The iouL. Aoril 1944. To The Director of Customs, Bahrain. Memorandum . deference Haji Ahdulnziz Ali Bassam’s appli cation for import of 60 bales Arab Yashmaks from the T nited Kingdom, which was recommended by you. 2. As the Yashmags are for re-export to the Saudi Arabia, 1 have not recommended his application for grant of shipping space. ^ ^ for Political Agent, Bahrain.© ,I ) 5j R i 1 S J in . ro » ,rcl to «oo&lt;la oaaontinlly i'oquii»od ;&gt;on U\n United -'in nlon, U'nitod .Jtntnn of '.noricn of Cenmiti by the mb g in the Persian Gulf. 1* Name of would-be inporter. i • Name and add re so of the a^orit or manufacturer in tlie exporting country from whom he wlohoo to arrange supply. 3* Full description of the goods •equired. ■ v '. Messrsi )hanannal IssardnB f Bahrain. Scssrs. Halli Brps., ] anchcster. Vhito shirting 'hito mulls Onintz crepe Chintz printed Crepe various colours Veil printed &amp; plain 'hito Gha vlo l oin clotJi oollen cloth 12 tons 10 Tt 10 , ^ ' 10 6 «• 10 »» 5 5 Tl c t.OTP. 4. Approximate weight in long urns of 2240 lbs., £• xact use or purpose oontenplntod for the goods to bo Imported. . ipecial reasons justifying:- (a) iupply of goods wanted V ) Their import from the coin try suggested rather than from any other country. 72 tons. V. For local consumption. Hahraih stocks being exhausted. Not available fron elsewhere. 7. )c script ion of tlic urgency with .n early as possible, which tiie goals arc required and the latest date which *ill bo suitable ✓ —-No*676-34/30 A A \ £ 3 ■ / • BaiTISH A03NCY, SHARJAH. DATiiD THE 20th aP^IL 1944 TO The Political A^ent, Bahrain* Subject : lraport« gsg Assistance * T/.jSLQBANDUl.i. A copy of an application for assistance in the import of Mosquito Netting from London to Dubai is forwarded with a completed copy of the usual application form* it is recommended that assistance be granted* political officer,Trueial coast)V7 COPY . HAJI RAI3 HASSAN HAIS SADI ci GO. , DURU. Dated the 18th April 1944* To The Political Officer, Trucial coast, 3K\RJAI1. i Respected sir, We most humbly ana respectfully bej to sub mit that we have recjived a letter from J.E.Kh^douri, Balmain informing us that Messrs George Kaufmann (London) Ltd., ibex House.hinries, Loi-don. e.C. 3 obtains ed an Export Licence No.92/40041/44 for shipment to Dubai to our name for sell upon arrival in account of Mr.J.E.Khoduroi, Bahrain, 174 pieces of Mosquito Netting which makes 4700 Yards weight 360 lbs. We therefore shall be much obliged if you will please recommend shipment in this respect. For this act of kindness we shall remain thankful to you. Yours obediently. Sealed. FOR HAJI RAID KASDAN RAIS SAADI &amp; CO. 3 d/- A. R.Saadi. jDetails in regard togood* essentially required from United Kingdom, United States of America or Oanda by the Arab States in the Persian Gulf. !• Name of would-be importer* D VtUJLA. y Cl ^ r J */» ' ' A-iA** Exact use or purpose contemplated l/u y for the goods to be imported. 0 . . . / _. Special reasons justifying:- 3. 4. 5. 6 . or manufacturer in the exporting country from whom he wishes to arrange supply. Approximate weight in long tons of 2340 lbs. (a) Supply of goods wanted. (b) Their import from the country suggested rather / than from e&lt;ttwp any other country* cUu* which the good- are re^uire^^ auitable 7. Description of the urgency with which the goods ari and the latest date 4 ' • * Jr ;r 5 *2. Bahrain 17-4-44, °! -p To The Political Agent, Bahrain, Dear Sir, We,herewith, send you the copy of the letter received from Messrs Ralli B rothers ntd., Bombay, for your information and necessary action. Thanking you, /p Yours faithfully, VYRALU BROTHERS LIMlTEO (XNOOBPOBATED IK BNGLAKD) Post Box No. 16fl. Tel. Add. ,&lt; KADI,I.* , Our Ref, PIKOK GOODS Y A 21, RAVELIN STREET, FORT, Bombay, 6th April 1944, Messrs Dhamanmal Isardaa, Sicka Nagar, Vithalbhai Patel Road, Bombay. Dear Sirs, Cotton Plepe Goods . Shipments from Mancheater . x We thank yon for your letter of 28th March and note that you are informed telegraphically by your Bahrein Office that they have obtained an import licence for 72 tons of Manchester Piece Goods, which is recoamonded by the Political Agent, Ah we have previoualy written to you, w© understand that the procedure for business for Bahrein, Dubai, Muscat and Koweit Ports for shipment from Manchester is that business can only be put through if it is recommended by the Political Agent and sponsored by the India Office, London. Under the circumstances you must now apply to the India Office for sponsorship for the 72 tons through the Political Agent in Bahrein. As soon as you receive this sponsorship please let us know its number, d&amp;te, and quantity mentioned therein. On receipt of this information we shall wire your requirements tq our Manchester Office. Yours faithfully, per pro BROTHERS LIMITED,Ho #23-36/43 pol me A] AO^rcy, IHA . oril 1944. To Tho Political Officor, Tracial Const, Sharjah. Memorandum . '^oforenco your memorandum No. 676-34/33, dented the 20tli April 1944. 2 . Aa no quota has been allotted to the Truein 1 Coast for ^oods from the United Kingdom, it is regrettdd that the application carjbt be recomraended for shipping space. 3. In the present case the applicant should obtain his requirements from India. He will save money as well shipping space. ~&amp;c r T r Political Agent, Pahrain.No 1244-36/43 POLITICAL V'CNCY, BAHRAIN. The# May 1944. To # Messrs. Rhamnrial Issardas Bahrain. renorand un. L Reference your letter dated the 17th April -he reconnendation nade in ny nenoi’andun No 1106-36/43, dated the 18th April 1944 is for shipping space from the United Kingdom for 72 tons of piece goods. Messrs. Halil Brothers should he asked to instruct their Manchester Branch to keep in touch with the India Office . 1944 Political Agent Bahrain./V — 5 I3UOX1J.X-U, rc \PolitaLcal, Bahrain. 4*1*' Reference your express letter No.485-79/175 dated 26th February. Goods essentially required for Bahrain from TJ.K. and U.3.A. 2. Import assistance recomm endation issued. /Khansaheb Abdulhusain fr Bros. IMPORTERS &amp; EXPORTERS. || Code Used:- A, Q. C. 5TH EDITION &amp; BENTLEY’S. To, / l^a .1 U f ■■ ' /- ^ O o /^lain-i 8 ^ 44. . J 49 irolitical Agent, Bahrain. (B. (xulf). Respected Sir, We beg to enclose herewith a form for Import Recommandation and a. copy of our Indent, recommanded by the Director of Customs &lt;± Rort Officer, for our repeat order of Sewing threads &amp; Broder Skeins, placed with n^s, Central Agency Ltd*, of Olasgow,.London, and suppliers Cable as the proof of our order.As the goods are ready for shippment, we shall be highly obliged if you will kindly pass the Assistance Recommandation by Cable to our suppliers at our expense as to enable them to execute the goods as per our order, Thanking you in anticipation, OA/- encl A Cable from u/s, Central Agency Ltd, A Copy of Invoice, A copy of aaplication form. We are, honour to be, Respected Sir, Yours most Obediently, ^ ;:jd Ihu&amp;ain &amp; £»'o ’Details in regard to goods essentially required from United Kingdom, United States of America or Canada by the Arab Stages in the Persian Gulf* i) . Name of would be importer: Khansaheb Abdulhusain &amp; Bros Bahrain. ii) .Name and address of agent The Central Agency Limited, in the exporting country obtain supply iii).Full description of the goods As per attached list, required * iv).Approximate weight in long About 1 Ton. tons of 2240 lbs of the goods required. • v). Exact use or purpose contem- To Supply in Govt Educational Dept, plated for the goods to be and to sell locally, imported .....* iv). Special reasons justifying as mentioned above. a) Supply of goods wanted. b) .their import from the To get the beu er quality. Bahrain Dqte 26.4.44. from whom he wished to Glasgow. vii)• Description of the urgency with As early as possible which the goods are required, and the latest date which will be suitable country suggested rether than from any other country. Per Pro. KhansatNo hff£36/43 POLITICAL AGT5T T CY BAHIA IN* i ho r V^^y 1944. To Messrs. J.E. Khodouri Bahrain. /W3 Memorandum The ^ovomnont of India have recommended tliat shipping space may be granted $o you for export of goods from the United Kingdom mentioned in my following memoranda addressed to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, copies of which were sent to you. ; 1. No.214-36/43, dated the 33rd January 1944. 2 . I'JOm 3R4—r?n + Oi^ +Vir&gt; V + H T?r» 1 '\r»Mr&gt;-mr T Q /L/l Bahrain.(i£j) ^©Vtils in vetterd x,o gootta ouncnti^lly required fvan the L’nitod in^dor, i tilted tnto of America or Cnnndn by the 'mb - tatca in the i crslan Cnilf • l#^ r nnc of ^ould-bc inportor# V han ahib Abdul J uenin l ^oa. Vihmin. ‘3* a me and address of the agent or Aho Central Agency, ltd., nsnufacturor in the exporting country ’'!aii;;ow f Krtgland, fron whom ho wiahen to arrange supply. 3. Full description of tlie goodo required. nor list attached. 4. Approximate weight in Ion; tons of &gt;»40 About ikon, lbs. ] .f • xact use or purpoHe con tome la to l for Aor ;ialo to the public, tlic goods to be imported. t. Special reasons Justifyingi- (a) Supply og goods wnnx.ed. (b) Their import from the country suggested rather than trow any otlier country. 7. ascription of tho urgency viith which tlic goals arc required and tho ^latest date which will be suitable. Hahi'nin ntrichs exliausted. Tot available from elsewhere. As early as possible.J. E. KHEDOURI IMPORT &amp; EXPORT t t*lh address KHE DQURi. 8AH ttA1N TELEPHONE. i CODES used:- RENTLBYS ac ME &amp; ORIENTAL bankbrs:- thb eastern bank ltd. • No,® 60® jj- t * nl H®B®M *3 Polit&gt;lcal Agent, Bahrain® 0- (ARABIA) _,»UI ,_L. 27th April 1 13 It- 5 / Dear Sir, Ae would request you to recommend to the Higher Authority to axlow shipping space to the Suppliers for the undermentioned^order 1® Name of would be importer. J.E.Khedouri, Bahrain® 2® Name or address of agent or «• manufacturer in the exporting country from wnom he wishes to arrange supply. Messrs® George Kaufmann(London) Ltd®, Ibex House, Minories, London, E®C. 3 . 1200 yards shirting poplin® 40 pieces Woollen suiting® Poplin •®o Woollen .® 230 lbs® 2010 lbs® 3. Pull description of the goods required® 4® Approxi iate weight in long tons of SS 2240 lbs. 5® Exact use of purpose contemplated for the goods to be imported. 6 . Special justifying- reason justi fying - (aj supply of goods wanted. Order has been accepted® Awaiting shipping space (Suppliers airgraphs of 7th and 8 th April attached). For shirting &amp; suiting purposes® (b) Their import from the Available only from England, country suggested rather than from any other country. 7. Description of the urgency with which the goods are required and As soon as possible. the latest date which will be suitable. We shall be grateful for your kind assistance in this matter Yours faithfully.J. E. KHEDOUHI import &amp; export TBLK ADDRPSS khed ourmah rain TKLCPHONE. g3~M CODES used:- BENTLEVS ACME &amp; ORIENTAL banrers:- thb eastern bank ltd. REF.NO.41 /w (ARABIA) The Director of Customs and Port Officer. Bahrain. Dear Sir; FROM LONDON 3 Tons Woollen Piecegoods (For gents suitings and ladies dresses) 5 Tons C otton^IleuegQ.ads( Nettings, Shawls and Printed voils) We would request you to give us quota for the above mentioned goods to he shipped by MESSRS GEORGE KAUFMANN(LONDON) LIMITED. IBEX HOUSE M1N0RIES, LONDON E.C.o., to arrive here during the last half year of 1944. Thanking you in anticipation. Yours faithfully (J /Ve A V,,.. - • 4. - • A# / r t \ ' V Director of Cuslor.is &lt; Port Ojj.c i , BAHRAIj L t/VJ. E. KHEDOURI import &amp; EXPORT TtLB ADDRRSS KHED OURMAH RAIN telephone. 83~m codes used:- BENTLEYS ACME &amp; ORIENTAL bankers;- thh eastern bank ltd. H.B«M's Political Agent, Bahrain 0 &amp; ft jMrsC Ora/n 7-tli Juna_^^4. (ARABIA) 9 l' Dear, Sir, As instructed, we give below, for your information, copies of our airgraph orders to Messrs* George Kaufmann (London) Ltd*, London, as under•- Reference our letter to t- Our airgraph No#48 of 28th Peb.to you No*60 of 27th April* Shipperso ~ WOOLLEN PIEGEGOODS FOR SUITINGS (REFERENCE YOUR AIRMAIL LETTER OF 17th DECEMBER 1945).- Kindly note that the quality of this woollen piecegoods are popular in this market for its prices and colours and therefore kindly cancel our previous order of woollen piecegoods sent to you under our airgraph letters Nos. 21 and 23 and please take the n^w order instead*- . x v Order No .6 -(Your letter and sample date 17*12.43) 2 pieces of sample No.35531 Price 7/9 3 ' 35543 ” 8 /- 5 ' 35444 9/6 3 ' 2/35589 12/6 3 ' 35719 10/3 3 ” 35720 10/3 3 ' 35721 10/3 2 ' 35328 12/9 2 ' 2/35740 11/3 2 ' 2/35736 11/9 —- ' 46639 14/9 Try to obtain the export licence for the above order and cable us so for us to obtain the shipping space recommeraj tion or if you have already received the shipping s^ace recommendation for woollen goods from India Off! ce, London, kindly use same for this order'. Yours faithfully. Order for 10 pieces Woolen Suitings per our airgraph ”TTo• SO' of 18th March to shippers. - 'Please ship one bale containing 5 pieces No.63704 54'/ ' 7/9d Dark Navy Blue, 5 pieces No. 377 56'/S' 10/9 Dai Navy blue. Please telegraph your acceptance and weight of the goods to enable us to secure shipping space rec-a: mendation for you'. Order for 1200 yards Poplin per our airgraph No.50 of 11 rj March.- We are in receipt of the sample of 1200 yards V? shrunk poplin shirtings and this lot we have accepted under our cable of the 8 th instant.J. E. KHEDOUHI IMPORT &amp; EXPORT telb address K H E D OURI-RAH R a IN tblkphone. 83~m codes used:- HENTLRVS ACME &amp; ORIENTAL bankers;- thb eastern bank ltd. / f 'tf/trcr/n (ARABIA) 1st May. 4* - — No.62. Political Agent, Bahrain. Dear Sir, y On the 4th January, the Director of Customs &amp; Port Officer, granted us the requisite import permit for 1 ton Woollen Piecegoods and 10 tons Cotton piecegoods for the last half year of 1944, to be shipped to us by Mr. J.M. Shasha, Asia House, 82 Princess St., Manchester 1. We communicated this information to Mr. J.M® Shasha and in reply, received from him the enclosed airgraph of the 10 th February stating amongst other things that they should have no diffi culty in supplying us with all our requirements, provided that the India Office arranged with the Board of Trade to allow Mr. Shasha the release of the raw material to produce the various qualities to complete our order. We shall be very grateful if you will kindly be good enough to assist us in this connection by making suitable recommendations to the quarter concerned as early as possible. In the meantime, we beg to enquire whether a part of this import permit can be utilised by any other firms in England, who may have some of the goods,required by us, available for shipment to Bahrain, and whose acceptance we shall obtain and produce to your goodself £e*-4he-ft©«e««ary- for making the necessary shipping space recommendation. Thanking you in advance. Yours faithfully, P•S. We also enclose the import permit of the Director of Customs &amp; Port Officer./ J - E. KHEDOURI IMPORT &amp; EXPORT t*lb address KHE DOURj. g AH g AIN trlephone. g3~M CODES USED;- RENTLEVS acme &amp; ORIENTAL bankers;- thk eastern bank ltd. RiiF.NO .39 js$V (ARABIA) The Director of Customs and Fort Officer Bahrain. Dear Sirs: FROM LONDON &amp; MANCHESIER 4 Tons Woollen Fiecegoods(For gents suitings and ladies dresses). Woollen Blankets, 15 ' Cotton Fiecegoods(Nettings, Shawls, and Printed veils) we would request you to give us quota for the above mentioned goods to be shipped by MESSRS J.M.SHASHA. ASIA HOUSE 82 PRINCESS STREET, MANCHESTER 1 ,. to arrive here during the last half year of 1944. Thanking you in anticipation. I Yours faithfully fort Ojjicer, BAH1U.1NNo. M5Z -36/43 political agr^cy GAHHAIN • The f~?(Z May 1944. To j .e. Khedouri Bahrain. Memorandum He for once your letter no. 62 of May 1st 1944. 3. I should like to know details of those orders already recommended by me, which Messrs, bhasha say they are unable to fulfil without further help in ^ettinn raw materials from the Board of Trade• 3. i should further like your explanation as to how it comes about that you have asked Messrs. .Ihasha and Co., to ship the netting order to Kuweit, after you had received assistance from me for shipping space to Bahrain. for Political Agent, BahrainBRITISH RESIDENCY AND CONSULATE GENERAL, buseire . K c X_P_R ta E_S ai S ja= _ c L_E = T T_E_R. ^ • — 7 i H. From s- To J- BRITCONSUL, BUSHIRE. FOREIGN. No. 1010-79/175, dated the 30th April, 1944. Reference memorandum No. 263-36/43 dated the 25th January 1944 from the Political Agent, Bahrain (copy sent to you). 2. I recommend import assistance for all the articles except red shawls. The total length of the cloth required is 106,000 yards. - BRITCONSUL - I The Sw j \ \V f S Secretary to the Political Resident &amp;n the Persian Gulf. Cony to the Political Agent, Bahrain.J. E. KHEDOURI IMPORT &amp; EXPORT TILE ADDRESS KHED OURI* BAH RAIN TELEPHONE. CODES used:- BENTLEY3 ACME &amp; ORIENTAL t bankers;— the eastern bank ltd. No® 66. \ % H.B.M's Political Agent, Bahrain® Dear Sir, We refer to your letter No.409-36/43 of the 10th February to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, recommending shipping space for the goods we have ordered from Messrs. George Kaufmann(London) Ltd®, Ibex House, Minories, London, E.C. 3® We have received a cable dated the 1st instant from Messrs. George Kaufmann that they have received the shipping space recommen dation, and enclose herewith their cable® We have also received a further telegram from them dated the 9th instant, which we attach herewith® We shall be extremely grateful if you can assist us in the matter. We are prepared to meet the cost of any cable you may be kind enough to send in this connection. The market is short of white shirtings and mulls® Thanking you for your assistance. Q * ^ ^9^ /rtf ^ J nJu. £ (ARABIA) 17th Mayj* E. KHEDOURI iMPoRT &amp; EXPORT t*lb addrkss KHEDOURI-RABRAIN trlrphqne. 83~m codes used;- PENTLEYS ACME &amp; ORIENTAL bankkrs:- thb eastern bank ltd. No.67o Political Agent, Bahrain. Dear Sir, 9 - P cXf . 'fjj (ARABIA) -— &lt;&amp;&gt; 21st May 4. / ,-&gt;l rS / /sTi With reference to paragraph 2 of your letter No.1453-36/43 of the 17th instant, we applied to you on the ^4th April 1945 for assistance for shipping space in respect of the following goods to Bahrain.-- V A. 200 pieces Fast Black Cotton Cashmere. 100 pieces Art Silk Black crepe. C. 200 pieces Printed Voile D. 100 ' Shirt Poplin. ,/E. 100 ,f Printed Art Silk - F. 50 pieces Wollen and Cotton mixed. This was granted in your letter No. 1943. 2391 of the 25th October, Subsequent to our receiving from Mr. Sha sha his airgraph of 10th February 1944 (which is now in your possession), we also received from him the following two cables dated the 5th April and the 4th instant.- Cable dated 5th April. - 'Have at last succeeded obtaining export licence woollens India Office recommendation already received expect space permit within twoweeks will be shipping 1600 yards tropical suitings 54 inches 50 percent wool 50 percent fibro 8 ounces yard excellent assortment invoice price 9/6d.per yard C.I.F war extra please remit telegraphically £850'. * Cable dated 4th May. 'Have today received India Office recommendation ”’22425 square yards netting expect space shortly am now agreeable putting further quantities into work provided India* Office recommendation ultimately obtained stop As 18565 unobtainable shall we substitute 18698 or 17872 and book 300 pieces 36 inch 200 pieces 27 inch all black also 200 pieces 18687/27 36 inch as per airgraph 3/4 if so indicate shades required stop Cotton Board promised export licence twelve thousand square yards cotton piecegoods India Office recommendation already received but as replacement facilities not available cannot execute original requirements 800 0 yards printed voiles and 4000 yards poplins. Have however permission buy available stocks unfortunately very scarce and prices high could buy 12000 yards 31 inch dyed limbric assorted ten shades 25d cif warextra if suitable confirm will thenJ. E. KHEDOURI IMPORT &amp; EXPORT TBLB ADDRPSS KHE DOURI. BAH RAIN telephone. 83~m codes usbd:- BENTLRYS ACME &amp; ORIENTAL bankers:- the eastern bank ltd. WA.«i Al I 2l3t Ma T-/^ (ARABIA) 4. No ft 67, Page 5 , To*- H*B*M*s Political Agent, Bnhrain. Mr* Shasha the contents of your letter No* 214-36/45 of the 23rd January granting shipping space recommendation; cleared the point of misunderstanding that had arisen in this connection, and requested him to ship the goods to us as soon as possible* Later, on 2nd February we cabled him that the shipping space had been recommended by you and had gone forward* On the 4th instant, he confirmed by telegram that he had received India Office recommendation for 22426 sq* yds* If you will grant us an interview when convenient, we shall produce to you all the correspondence that has passed between us and Mr. Shasha in this connection, and when the shipping documents arrive, we shall exhibit them to you for your perusal* Yours faithfully.No* 1646-36/43 POLITICAL ACENCY, BAHRAIN. The 5th June 1944 To Mr* J*E. Khedouri I^ahi^in. remorandun r Refcroneo your letters Nos. 66 and 67, dated the 17th and 21st Mny 1944* 2. As verbally explained to you this 4gency only helps importers in getting shipping space for the goods they intend to import from the Pnited Kingdom, and does not undertake to enter into correspondence on behalf of the exporters from the United Kingdom for release of raw materials from the Board of Trade for manufacture of goods. 3. The enclosures to your letter No. 66, dated the 17th May 1944 are returned herewith. for Political Agent, BahrainGOVERNMENT OF INDIA, oi 9 . S. fc. ‘ Department, EXPRESS LETTER \N % B % -—This is an OHIGIN AL MESSAGE, sent by .post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the save time and so despatched.] From same expedition as i) it load oeeu telegraphed. 1 o formalities iL -xs^worded atvd signed as if it had been BRIYCOFSUL, BU3FIHE. To ¥*ORFIGU f ‘ Vo - 1169-79/175. Datei 13th ay, 1344. m * 1 Reference rao) ;orand\i 2 a TTo* 11^0-36/43 of 18th Aprils 194^. from the Political Ag^nt^ Bahrair^ copy endorsed to yoti. Glcth from the United Kingdom, 2, 1 rceon^tad import aaeista/.ea for 23 tons cotton cloth and 5 tons woollen cloth. mT'COVSVL • « The issue of the above hns been ant'-orlsed. ^/c&lt; Copy to the Political Agent, Bahrain. For cotton piece-goods Bahrain is within the area supplied by India under a quarterly quota fixed by His Majesty’s Government. If a quantity as large as 72 tons is recommended there is every likelihood of the quota of piece-goods from India being reduced. Therefore only 20 tons of cotton cloth has been recommended.\ L M J. E. KHEDOURI IMPORT &amp; EXPORT TILE ADDRFSS K HBDOURI-1AHR AIN telephone. codes used:- BENTLRYS ACME &amp; ORIENTAL bankers;- the eastern bank ltd. No e 69* H7. ST. 4^ f 27th y7?^ * (ARABIA) r —v H.B.M 1 s Political Agent, Bahrain. Dear Sir, Messrs. Goode, Durrant &amp; Murray Ltd., Woodberry, Hindhead, Surrey, have offered us Cotton Netting. On the 5th instant we placed an order on them by cable for - 24,000 yds. of Quality No. 4001 6,000 yds. H 11 4014^ for shipment to Dubai, and have now received their attached telegraphic reply of the 12th instant. The total weight of the goods will be 1450 lbs. We shall be extremely grateful if you will kindly grant us the necessary shipping space recommendation for Dubai, if possible. Our agent at Dubai is - Messrs. Haji Rais Hasan Rais Saadi &amp; Co., Dubai. Thanking you for your assistance. Yours faithfully, %J- E. KHEDOURI import &amp; EXPORT TKLK AODRKfS KHE DQURi-gAH g AIN telephone. 83-m CODES USED&gt; BENTLRV 8 ACME &amp; ORIENTAL Bankers;- the eastern bank ltd. No* 69. Jj**-*- © / a //rtf tfi 27 th__M (ARABIA) H. B.M*s Political Agent, Bahrain. Dear Sir, w e shall be grateful if you will kindly srant 11 q necessary shipping space recommendation to the Higher Anthnr»i^ for the following goods to be shipped ?o Subai.l ^ Authority I. Name or would be importer. .. Messrs. Hajl Rais Hassan Rais Saadi &amp; Co*, Dubai (Our Agents). 2 ‘ ^V^V'T 638 ? f the a « ent -. Messrs. Goode Durrant &amp; Murrav Lt, or manufacturer in the exporting Woodberry, Hinnihead country from whom he wishes to Surrey! EnllSnd arrange supply. England. 3. Pull description of the goods • required. 4. Approximate weight in long tons of 2240 lbs* 5* Exact use or purpose contemplated for the goods to be imported. 6. Special reason justifying.- (a) Supply of goods wanted (b) Their import from the .. country suggested rather than from any other country. 7. Description of the urgency with which the goodt are required and the latest date which will be suitable. Thanking you for your assistance. 30,000 yds. Cotton Mosquito Netting. 1450 lbs. For dress and veils of ladies. Cable of 12th instant from manufacturers attached. Available only from England. As soon as possible, to Dubai Yours faithfullyPrinted in England. Sej&gt;t. 194Z (4,100. pad*J CABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED. I INCORPORATED IN ENOLANO.) in*; V-16 8 The first line of this Telegram contains the following particulars in the order named:— OfflSr«n n ^c?ion,-TS;. 0f Me * SaKe ’ 0ffiCe of 0ri « in - of Words, Date. Time handed In ajjd Circuit. Clerk’s Name. f » Time Received. M TJ/PLfc - 0715. 902 DASV164 HINDHKADSRY 25/24 12 = NLT J E KHEDOURI BAHMIN / /v YOURS FIFTH w'EIGHT 4001 HARD FINISH APPROXIMATELY 1200 LBS 4014-1/2 SOFT FINISH APPROXIMATELY 250 LBS NET WEIGHT GOODE DURRANT WARK YOUR REPLY JiruieJuaC ANY ENQUIRY RESPECTING THIS TELEGRAM SHOULD BE ACCOMPANIEd'bY THIS FORM AND MAY BE MADE AT ANY OF THE COMPANY’S OFFICES.11 j. E. KHEDOUHI IMPORT &amp; EXPORT tel* address KHB DOURr.g A H RAIN TELEPHONE. 23 -M CODES USED;- 8 CMTLEVS ACME &amp; ORIENTAL bankers:- the eastern bank ltd. No,70, ^ 5r&lt;M)u6&gt; Jt. £ J l v;!. •* V im Y/Aratn ^rd 4 (ARABIA) H.B.M’s Political Agent, Bahrain, Dear Sir, /&lt;3 Reference our letter No. 62 of the 1st May, 1944, re. 1 ton Woollen Piecegoods &amp; 10 tons Cotton Piecegoods from Mr. J.M. Shasha, Asia House, 82 Princes St., Manchester 1./^ f Vie have today placed our Order No.50 for the above goods on Mr. Shasha, as per copy of letter to him enclosed herewith. When his acceptance comes to hand, we shall apply to you for assistance for shipping space. Yours faithfully.J. E. KHEDOUR1 IMPORT &amp; EXPORT tile addrpss khkdouri-sahrain telephone! 83~m codes used:- 8 ENTLEVS ACME &amp; ORIENTAL bankers:- the eastern bank ltd. To.- J.to. Shasha, Esq., 82 Princess Street, Manchester 1, England. (!-&gt;i^ (ARABIA) ar Sir, 1 10 J.^.Khedouri, Bahrain, Persian Oulf. OUR ORDER 10.50 FOR TON WOOLLEN PIECEGOODS AND TONS COTTON PIECEOOODS Airgraph No.26. 3rd June,1944. FOR tv HIGH v»E HAVE ALRJ -ADY OBTAINED IIvIPORT PERluIT FROM THE CONI ROLLE R AT BAHR AIN FO R THE LAS T HALF YEAR, 1944. Please arrange to ship to our account to Bahrain our above Order No.50, consisting of the following goods.- 50 pieces Black woollen Ceshiaere, 6/7 ozs, Se/e*, 60/70$ wool, per your offer of 18th April 1944. 50 pieces Navy Blue Serge for suitings, or any other quality at your discretion, 2000 1500 500 500 200 500 Pi 500 500 200 200 200 1000 cea of 20 yds.each,Tnrkey,Red and Yellow Prints. “m zo/zi*. 12 yds. Prints. Printed Voiles. Black Cotton Satin Poplin Imitation Linen Black Leno X overs. Jean for suitings Cambric Urgandy or other fancy goods for ladles Printed or Plain Art Silk Spun Silk White shirting. On receipt of this airgraph, please cable us your acceptance as early as possible, quoting in the cable Order 50,as reference. Your acceptance cable, together with our 0r3er No.60, will then be produced to H.B.M’s Political Agent at Bahrain for obtaining the requisite shipping space recommendation. Please note that in all your mail or cable correspondence relating to these goods. Order No.50 should invariably be quoted as reference# Yours faithfully.To - THE BRITISH POLITICAL A£2»T, ■ IB PEBR1IAKY 1S44 BAHRAJfl, } AKAb X/v* , ^ PliifilAJf GULP ySV' 1 IRMitJj POHT VOL OJAIH WOULJ&gt; MUCH APPRECIATE lOUFi ZBXEKVZKV KHJDOUKI Li»A1jLIIJG OAItli'IC^TIOB POSITION aM; CABLING US NHA2HKR L^LIVSRT . FRilCTICABLE VIA BAHRAIN OR iJiY OTHER VOkf TKANA&amp; BVaHS ^.OM YOUR XKLLGMAU Of TUS 14TIi IT I.OULL aPPSAA HiAi 1 OLRS Qt ThL 9TH «AS MUTILAIHL. SINCE OUR CAI'U; RKFSPItKI; TO fim PIECLC Ot ittuLlSH LOOLLBW SUITINGS ARP NOT TO. SHAWLS. HOWEVER, THE PRDtCPLB WOUID AP/HAli TO BA THE SAMS AND HE ARS v^ITii sURL THAI' if MR KRELOURZ UAu STATES TLB CASE CLEARLY TO YOU, THERE WOULD HAVE BEfJM HO NEED FOR ILS TO TROUBLE YOU A SECOND TIME. THE POSITION IS THAT «E HAVE AN ORDER m FIITY PIECES WOOLLENS FOR im^IM ALJIIIAH HASSA, TO BE SHIPPED VIA OJAIR, ^HTCH TO UNDERSTAND INVOLVES TRANSHIPMENT AT BAHRAIN. BEFORE THE BOARD OF TRADE WILL GRANT AN EXPORT LICENCE THEY Ri^biRS A RECOMMBNDATIQN FltON THE U.K.C.C. OR SIMILAR BODY TO THE EFFECT THAT SHIPPING SPACE WILL BE ALLOCATBS) WHEN THE GOODS APB READY. WB UNDERSTAND FROM MR KHKl*OUPI THAT THE SHIPPING ALLOCATIONS VIA BAHRAIN ARE UNDER TOUT JURISDICTION AND NOT TaAT 01’ THE U.K.C.C., AND WHILST IT IS FAR F^CF BEING OUR WISH THAT 7Z?, BAHRAIN TONNAGE SHOULD BE U88D TOR THE PURPOSE OF TRANSITXFMNWT GOODS, YfE SHOUU&gt; BE VERY MUCH OBLIGKT- TO YOU INDEED IF YOU WOULD LET US OR MR KHBDOURI KNOW WHAT MACHINERY BUSTS FOR SUCH ALLOCATIONS. WE MUST APOLOGISE FOR TROUBLING YOU, BUT THE MATTER OF OF SOME CONSIDERABLE IMPORTANCE TO US SINCE THIS BUSINESS WILL FORM THE BASIS FOR FURTHER FUTURE BUSINESS IN THIS LINK AND SIIaLL BE VERY GRATEFUL INDSMD TO YOU FOR Otr ASSISTANCE YOU AES ABLE TO GIVE UE. TEAMING YOU IN ANTICIPATION, YOURS FAITHFUUY, ARTHUR E. EVANS ft CO. LTD.,ARTIiUK &amp;• &amp; CO. LID., WiiS»iIl©TSfla BANK OHAMBc&amp;S, BISHOP’S STORTFQRD. To - THB BKITZSH POLITICAL AG2KT, BAHRAIN. ARABIA* Pffi^IAJf GULF. 1C FEBRUARY 1944 DEAR SIR, WE EjG TO CORF IRK KXLHAKGR OF IKE FOLU)«I^b T^UiGRAMS DESP. B’PS CXOaTFOIw 9.£.44. 17.4S. EP 26 TORDS BRITISH POLITICAL AGENT BAHRAIN /- UKDERSTAKD JOSEPH KHSDOURI KXP^rSKCTU:- POTICULTXES REGARDING GRIPPING PERMITS FIFTY PIECES TOOT.MfS OFFERED BY US FOR SAUDIARABIA PURCHASED BY IBRAHIM ALJMIAH HASSA FOl&lt; fflUPUBMT VIA BAHRAIN TO OJAIR STOP vjOOLCOWTROL CAIXS FOR UKCC RECOMMENDATION FOR SHIPPING SPACE BEFORE GRANTING EXPORT LICENCE AND RSLBA8B GOODS STOP YE UNDERSTAND BAHRAIN SHIPMain'S NOT ^JNDHR UKCC CONTROL PLEAS3 ASSIST BY RECOMMENDATION TO &gt; T ^&gt;C OR APPROPRIATE AUTH^mr FOR TRANSMISSION LONDON STOP ^OUU /J'PKLCIATlS ADVICE WHSIHER YOU FIND TK3B PRACTICABLE DESP. BAHRAIN 14.2.44. 11.46 RECD. E’PS STORTFORD 14.2.44. 16.S6. EVANS BISHOPSCTOKTFGRD J WOOLEN SHAWLS TO? SAUDIARABIA STOP BAHRAIN HAS YEARLY QUOTA SHIPPING SPACE AND I CANNOT GIVE UP ANY OF THIS FOR GOODS TO OTHER COUNTRIES POLITICAL AGENT PKSP. 3»PS ST03P.TFQRL 14.2.44. 17.50. NLT hP 26 WORDS BRITISK POLITICAL AGENT BAHRAIN c APPARENTLY OUR TSLGGRAM NINTH ARRIVED MUTILATED BECAUSE UNINTERESTED SHAWLS STOP ORDER ACCEPTED FOR ENGLISH YOOLLKN SUITINGS STOP POSITION IS THAT WOOLCONTROL PREPARED RELEASE GOODS IF SHIPMENT PRACTICABLE STOP miOL HAS REQUESTED UKCC RECOMMENDATION BUT UNDERSTAND SAUDXARABIAN ISIANGULF PORTS OUTSIDE THEIR EVANSTel. Add ress:- FaW ru ddin Taliertkai- BAHRAIN. * FAKMRUDDIN n. TAI-IERBHAI. Generai HefcLanls- BAHRAIN. (Persian Gulf.) CoJas User):- ‘ ' Benlley s Oriental 111 ree teller &amp; Private. '7$P Dated lltb tTune 1944. — -&gt;) 75 To, H. B. M's Political Agent, Sir, We enclose here with recomadation letter and details regarding % ton cotton thi ead (sewin^ thi*ead) for import from United Kingdom, and shall be glad if you wilx arrange shipping space in united Kingdom in favour of The Central /gendy Ltd., 50 Bothwell street, Glasgow, (England)Tel. Address:- Faikruddin TolierLliai- BAHRAIN.. FAKHRUDDIN H. TAMERBMAI. General Merclianls. BAMRAIN. (Persian Gulf.) CoJ.s Us«J,. ^ Benlley s Oriental Tkree teller &amp; Private. Dated 4th «June,1944 # the United Kingdom. ^ regar&lt;i t0 goods essentially required from 1* Name of would be importer, 2 # Name and address of agent or manufacturer in the exporting country from whom he wishes to obtain supply. 3. Full description of the goods required. 4. Approximate weight in long tons of 2240 lbs of the goods required. 5. Exact use or purpose contemplated for the goods to be imported* 6. Special reasons justifyingj- a) Supply of goods wanted. b) Their import from the country suggested rather than from any other country. 7. Description of the urgency with which the goods are required and the latest date which will be suitable. Falchruddin M.Taherbhai, The Central Agency Ltd. 50, Bothwell Street, GLASGOW (England) 50 gross 3/200 yards cord Reels (Sewing thread) Letter Ticket. £ ton. for local consumption. Shortage of goods. October/November, 1944. Director of Of and Port Office; , r&gt; * I' 1 l I ,V11 ) List of goods ordered by Fakhruddin M. Taheibhai of Bahrain, From The Central igency Ltd., 50 Bothwell sx^ree^ , Glasgow, (England) through their Bombay office. 50 gloss 3/200 yards cord x^eels (Sewing thread) letter ticket. ■injrf v v&gt;; &gt; ■■ 1 /*7 d J. E. KHEDOURI y^) IMPORT &amp; EXPORT TBLE ADDRESS khedouri-iahrain TRLEPHONE. g 3 ~M CODES used;- BENTLEYS ACME &amp; ORIENTAL bankers;- the eastern bank ltd. No. 72. nfo. (ARABIA) 4. His Britannic Majesty ! s Political Agent, Bahrain. Dear Sir, -&gt;!77 1^ / We refer to our letter to you No.60 of the 27th April, enclosing an import licence granted by the Director of Customs and Port Officer for 5 tons of Cotton Piecegoods to be shipped to us by Messrs. George Kaufmann (London) Ltd., Ibex House, Minories, London, E.C. 3. We cabled Messrs. George Kaufmann on the 8th instant, as per copy of the telegram already furnished to you, and we have received their enclosed telegraphic reply of the 14th instant, stating - \ 'yours eighth accept - 250 piec es White Jeannes 1000 pieces Mulls /V r.'r. 100 ' Black Satins w Black Cashmeres 150 pieces Poplins aA 200 w Voiles' altogether weighing 6 tons, approximately. We shall be grateful if you will kindly recommend to Higher Authority necessary shipping space for these goods. A i, r Thanking you in advance. P.S. O ur import licence is for 5 tons only. If this cannot be increased to 6 tons, kindly advise us and we shall instruct the shi to reduce the quantity to 5 ton Yours faithfully. /U // 77 ' No. 1906-36/43 POLITICAL AGENCY BAHKAIN. The 4th July 1944 To The Hon*bio the Political Sosidont in the Persian Gulf, Bushiro Memorandum. /' jM ’ Mr. J.E. Khedouri, Bahiain, has applied to mo for assistance in exporting cotton piecegoods from the United Kingdom. 2. T recommend that assistance may bo granted cino. enclose the usuax details. The order has been placed and accepted. Copy forwarded to the Secretary to the Government of Inia in’ the External Affairs Department, Nov Delhi. Copy to Mr. J.B. Khedouri, Bahrain, with reference to his letter dated the 17th June 1944. itical Agent, Bahrain _((J5) Q ss g : vtiairy rcciuirGd from t.hG U.nit,Gd K i nydom. United States of America, or Canada by the Ar^b States in the Per sian Gulf lo Name of would-be importer . 2. Name and address of the agent or manufacturer in the export -ing country from vhom t h e importer wishes to arrange •• supply. .. ^ 3. Full description o:: 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 the goods required 4. Approximate weight in long tons of 2240 lbs. 5. Exact use or purpo ,e.nonn&amp;n— plated for the goods to be imported 6. Special reasons justifying;-- (a) Supply of go ds wanted. .b) Their imports from the country suggested rather than from any other... 7. Description of-the urgency with which the goods are re quired and the latest date which.will be suitable. Mr* Khodourl, itohrolru Moasra* ooorr^c Kaufmnnn Ltd*, Ibox Koufio, Minorie^, London, E*C* 3* woollon Piocogood^* X ton. For anlo to tho public* rianmin stooka oxrmuatoci* Not avnilablo from claonhorot Aa c?rly ??«E. KHEDOURI import &amp; EXPORT TBLR ADDRPSS KHEDOURI-SAHRAIN ,n jMJI y tn I'KLEPHONE. g3~M CODES USED.-- BENTLE\S acme &amp; oriental bankers;— THB eastern bank ltd. No© 75© Political Agent, Bnhrain© Dear Sir, We shall be grateful if you will kindly recommend to Higher Authority shipping space assistance for the folifcwii^g.- 1© Name of would be importer. •• 2. Name and address of the agent .. or manufacturer in the exporting country from whom he wishes to arrange supply© &gt; %»' *** 5© Pull description of the goods •• required. 4© Approximate weight in long tons of2240® lbs© 5© Exact use or purpose contemplated for the goods to be imported. .. 6. Special reason justifying©- (a) Supply of goods wanted. ©&lt; (b) Their import from the .. country suggested rather than from any other country. © Description of the urgency with . which the goods are required and the latest date wnich will be suitable• J.E© Khedouri, Bahrain. The Central Agency, 50, Bothwell St., Glasgow. Cotton Thread, Stranded Cotton Thread and Pearl Cotton Thread. 560 lbs. For sewing and embroidery purposes© Stock not available. Our order for goods accepted by manufacturers per their cable of 9th inst©attached. Available from England. As soon as possible. We enclose herewith the import Recommendation from the Director of Customs and Fort Officer in this connection. Thanking you for your assistance. Yours faithfully,J- E. KHEDOURI import &amp; EXPORT TKLB ADDRFSS KHEDOURI-1AHRAIN trlbphone. #3-m CODES USED:- PENTLEVS ACME &amp; ORIENTAL eankers:- 7 hb eastern bank ltd. 12 % ji 'aAr'a/n (ARABIA) 4. J-he Director of Customs &amp; Port Officer, Bahrain. Dear Sir, We shall be extremely grateful if you will kindly crant us the necessary permit for the import of the following.- Y 8 1 - Narrwa n-P T ^ j j _ 1* Name of would be importer 2. Name and address of the agent or m* nufacturer in the exporting country from whom he wishes to arrange supply. 5. Pull description of the goods required. J*E• Khedouri, Bahrain. The Central Agency Ltd., 50, Bothwell Street, Glasgow. Cotton Thread, Stranded Cotton Thread and Pearl Cotton Thread. 4. Approximate^ weight in long tons 5 cwt. 5. Exact use or purpose contemplated B&gt;or aewlno «. for the goods to be imported. e ng &amp; embroidery purposes, 6. Ixeefc-Hee-ep-purpese- Special reason justifying.- (a) Supply of goods wanted. On receipt of your import permit order will be placed for the goodi and manufacturer»s acceptance and weight of goods obtained, after aJ?* 1 space recommendatit will be applied for from Politica' Agent (b) Their import from the country Avail«b1^ -p-nn-m a suggested rather than from any 7 allable from England, other country. • Description of the urgency with which the goods are re- As soon as possible. quired and tne latest date which will be suitable. 4 tHr tf**-*-—*Pu.. k. 4.- 4- Director t and H Officer, L&gt; vl LI 101 /*/• Yours faithfully.J. E. KHEDOURI IMPORT &amp; EXPORT Jj* 3 -** ^ k-i- y m KHEDOURI-BAHRAIN telephone. g 3 ~M CODES tlSED;- 19th June BENTLEYS ACME &amp; ORIENTAL Stsa/ir'afn (ARABIA) bankers;- thb eastern bank ltd, Our Order reference our letter No»75« Copy of our telegram of 8.6*4 4 to Central Agency, Glasgow. quantities yours thirtieth to maximum 56&lt;:lbs. wire definite acceptance and approximate weight for obtaining shipping space. Copy of a telegram dated 9.6.44 from Central Agency, Glasgow to Khedouri, Bahrain. Can accept order 345 gross A4636 800 boxes A 4591 170 g ross A4374 netweight 560 lbs c.i.f. value £700 approxi mately. Obtained import, permit for 5 cwt. therefore increase • • • •E. KHEDOURI v N ^ . (ARABIA) # • His Britannic Majesty's iolitical Agent, ^ vtV No. 75, IMPORT &amp; EXPORT tble ADDRKS? KHB DQURi.g AH gArN telephone. g3 ~M codes used:- BENTLEYS acme &amp; ORIENTAL Bankers;- the eastern bank ltd. (I&amp;9 h&lt;A Baiirsin, n Dear Sir, /V 'V Autiioritv the '^ r ' : I' 6 '3 OXi will kindly recommend to Hleher Autnority the necessary shipping space for the following.- -^gne. -V- !• Name of would be importer 2. Name and address of the agent or manufacturer in the exporting country from whom he wishes to arrange supply. f’ull description of the goods required. 4. Approximate weight in long tons of 2240 lbs. 5. Exact use or purpose contemplated • for the goods to be imported. 6. Special reason justifying.- (a) Supply of goods wanted .. (b) Their import from the country suggested rather than from any other country. 7# D ,tH?ri p £i!i on of J the urgency with which the goods are required and o,,? 4 - 1 Sn est date which will be suitable. Joseph E© Khedouri, Bahrain. Messrs. Simon May &amp; Go. Ltd.. Weekday Cross, 9 Nottingham, England. 20,000 yards Black Mosquito Netting Quality No.28018. 8,000 yards Black Sandfly Netting Quality No.28022. • 6 19 cwt. Jor bedding, ladies dress and veils. Cabled offer of 27th June from the manufacturer, which we have accepted, is attached. Available from England. As soon as possible. Thanking you in advance / r Director of Cusiv,^ and Port Ofluier, Pd H HA l^1 Haj V abul Kassem Shirazi. Telegraphic Address:— ‘ire axi. BAHREIN. (P. GULF ) fZi d/- * * ** ** L? ** I » * d'-d \ 1st July 1944 H.B.M’s Political Agent. Baiarain. Dear Sir: . We would request you to recommend to the Higher authority to allow shipping space to our suppliers named in the order we have emoodied hereunder and thanking you for the same. 1. Name of would be importer:- Haji Abul Kaseem Shirazi. 0 AT ^ Bahrain, Persian Gulf. 4 . Name and address of agent or ) manufacturer inthe exporting ) ]l ^ essrs Hercules Export &amp; Import country from whom he wishes to), ^ „ Soy Inc. arrange supply ) 42 Broadway. New York. N.Y. 3# Pull description of the goods)/5~Mil ? l-±on-cigarrettes.About 5 fa requirea ) 5 Tons Cotton Piecegoods. (Prints, veils and shirting) 1 Ton Woollen piecegoods (For gents and ladies) X1 fon Hosieries. ^4000 Pairs shoes(For gents and 1 , * . . .... ladies).About i tons. A S P 5^i ma J e wei S^ m long tons) 1 Ton Safety match. Total 14 Tons. of 2240 Lbs of the goods ) required ) 3. Exact use or purpose contemplated) For consumption at Bahrain for the goods to be imported ) * 6 . Special reason justifying:- a. Supply of goods wanted :-Not available at Bahrain, o. Their import from the country suggested)Not available from rather than from any other country )other country. Description of the urgency with which) TT the goods are required and the’latest) re 3 hired. date v/hich will be suitable ) U ' ^ possible. Thanking you in anticipation. Yours faithfully t '7 of Cugt&amp;ti&amp;f and Port Officerj BAMBjiUt.ACCREDITED DEALERS FOR ^HIS MASTER'S VOICE'/ RADIO ' RADIOGRAMOPHONES • RECORDS l- H tV M ^ STE . R iYQ^ E - Branches—BASRAH | MARCH f KOWEIT JASHANNAL BAHREIN (Persian Gulf) Telephone No. 9.M. Telegrams: 'Utjashco, Bahrein' Details of goods easontialV requirea from U.S.A. Same of Importer.^ Jashanmal, Bahrein^ Name of Exporter*- Dayton Price &amp; Co. One Park Avenue New York* Description of goods required Item 3095.00 250 3096.05 422 3099.95 30 50 3099.15 12 . Tons 3-g- Tons. H Cotton underwear Knitted Ties Sweaters* Purpose of the goods For local consumption specially by the imported* employees in the oil companies. Description oi t**e urgency,- tmoria^e 01 &amp; oous* uoous requires as early as possible* ) Bahrein.J. E. KHEDOUHI IMPORT &amp; EXPORT tblb addrfss KHED QURI-BAH RAIN telephone. g3~M codes used:- RP N'T LEVS ACME &amp; ORIENTAL banrers;- thk eastern bank ltd. V3 I '///'&amp;//? (ARABIA) 15th July ^ 4 No.77. H.B.M's political A^ent, y/a '1 Banrain. / l'' ^ I Off Dear Sir, We shall he extremely grateful if you will kindly recommend necessary shipping space for us for the following,- lo Name of would he importer J.E* Khedouri, Bahrain* 2* Name and address of the agent William Laycock &amp; Son(Bradford)Ltd, or manufacturer in the exporting 4-6 Burnett Street, country from whom he wishes to arrange supply* 5* Full description of tne goods required* Bradford. 20 pieces Black Cashmere and Twill for ahba 20 pieces Union Tropical &amp; Union Mixture for suitings* 15 c.w*t« For use as abba and suitings* 4. Approximate weight in long tons of 2240 lbs, 5. Lxact use or purpose contem plated for the goods to be imported. 6. Special reason justifying*- ^ . 0 , ... (a) Supply of goods wanted. Black Cashmere for abba for sheikh ladies and the public. Urgently needed as Bahrain is out of stock of this at present, and its previous stock having entirely run out. (b) Their import from the country^ Before the war, supply was had suggested ratner than from any from Czech o 3 lavakia. Now avail- other country. able only from United Kingdom. 7. Description of the urgency with which the goods are required and the latest date which will be suitable) -i’, Thanking you in anticipation^ at As soon as possible (In our opi nion, once the goods become po pular here as to quality and durability,when compared to to those previously obtained from elsewhere, Bahrain will only prefer British goods after the war Yours, faithfully.far E- KHEDOUHI IMPORT &amp; EXPORT tblb address kiiedouri-Bahrain TELKPHOnIT ’g3-M COOKS USED;- PENTLEYS ACME &amp; ORIENTAL Bankers;— the eastern bank ltd. J (ARABIA) heierence our letter Bo.77 of 15th July to Political Agent, Bahrain. ?R Py ^ f ewf^ rgraph S f lst Apr11 to Messrs. Vlllllam Laycock &amp; Son (Bradford) Ltd., 4-6 Burnett Street, Bradford, England. . .. VVe ^f ve deceived a copy of your letter of the 19th January »n^ herwi u h 3amp;Le3 enclosed. The original letter together with its enclosures has not come to hand y&lt;=t. as follows re0e:i ' pt 0:f your lett er we cabled you on the 26th March 'Ship ten pieces each 2755. black 2754 black 2749_ dark grey ^744_^colour your choice. If cannot shipping all please try for twenty pieces 2753 wire acceptance and weight for obtaining shipping space recommendation aend letters samples registered'. Original airgraph dated 18th April from Messrs. William Lay cock &amp; Son, together with their price list dated 18th January is enclosed herewith, which please return to us when done with.Cables: “Mostafa Codes: A B C 5th-Edition. Bantley’s Oriental &amp; Private' CALIFORNIA HOUSE ! Agents: NEW ZEALAND INSURANCE CO. LTD FIRE. MARINE. ACCIDENT. Sole Distributors For: Wahl Company Everlast Pen &amp; Pencil Corp Garvey &amp; Company Metalfix Company Geo. J. Kelly, Inc. W anderer-W erke. A.G* Albert Padberg Phoebus Werke Treibacher Chemische Werke Nationals Ltd. West End Watch Co. (Arabian Peninsula except Aden &amp; Bahrain) Proprietors: [ MOSTAFA ABDULLATIFF &amp; CO ] IMPORT &amp; EXPOR BAHRAIN Persian Gulf Dealers in: Continental Typewriters Wanderer Cycles &amp; M. Cycles Eversharp Pens &amp; Pencils Eveready Flashlights &amp; Cells Arrow Shirts &amp; Shorts Palmolive Soap &amp; Colgate,s Goods Krementz Products Daimon Lights &amp; Cells Hosiery Bourjois Perfumes Johnson &amp; Johnson’s Tootal Products General Stores &amp; Provisions ^ef. No. 18th July 1944 Etc, Etc. H.B.Mts Political Agent. Bahrain . Dear Sir: With reference to our application for shipping space recoimnendation(Copy attached herewith), we beg to invite your attention to our letter dated the 13th February 1944 in reply to your letter No.358-36/43 dated the 3rd of the same month, we regret to have to inform that the suppliers have not yet received the recommendation from the India Office(Ref. their airgraph letter of the 30th June 1944). we would again request you to kindly do the needful and thanking you for the same. A Yours faithfullys ® l ?7 )j Copy of an order No.16/42 dated 12th May 1942 1. Name of would be importer: California House, Bahrain. 2 - ting country from whom he ’ * ’ * wishes to arrange supply 50 Oxford Street Manchester 1. 3* Pull description of the goods) 70 Bozen assorted footal required ) Neckties. 4. Approximate v/eight in long ) About 100 Lbs ton of 2240 Lbs ) 5. Exact use or purpose contem-) -jj. ^ plated for the goods to be ) - or at Bahrain. imported ) 6. Special reason justifying:- a. Supply of goods wanted:- Order has already been accepted (Ref.their airgraph letter dated 30th December 1943 and the value also has been paid (Ref. their value 9th Noc. and our cable dated 13th Nov. 1943) b. Their import from the ) TT ~+ „ -n ^ n country sup-eested ra- ) Not a vallab:Le thls particular +iicv. {brand of ties from any other ther than from any country . other country ) J w!t£ r which\he Sods r Ire Cy ) Urgently required. To be sent reauired and thf latest per P arcel P° st or shipment dXwhicfwi^ bel^tabll) as - on possible. /3 &lt; f E. KHEDOURI IMPORT &amp; EXPORT tblb address J khedourmahrain / t , ) TBLBPHONE. g3-M CODES USED;* BENTLEYS ACME &amp; ORIENTAL BANKERS.- the eastern bank ltd. REF.NO.1 H.B.M's Political Agent. Bahrain. 'a/tr'atn (ARABIA) 19th July &gt;2 0 21 Dear Sir: I shall glad if you will kindly recommend to the Higher Authority to grant the shipping space assistance for the following lo Name of would he importer: K.E.Khedouri. Bahrain. 2. Name and address of the agent) Mr.Jack Dellal. or manufacturer in the expor-) 86 George Street ting country from whom he ) Manchester 1. England, wishes to arrange supply ) 3. Full description of the goods)26 Pieces Black Crepe. ' required ) 4. Approximate weight in long )About 200 Lbs. ton of 2240 Lbs ) 5. Exact use or purpose contemplated) For ABBA for the for the goods to be imported ) natives. 6. Special reason justifying:- a. Supply of goods wanted:- Stock exhausted. Our order has been accepted, as per cable attached. b. Their import from the country) Available only from suggested rather than from ) England. any other country ) Description of the urgency with) which the goods are required ) and the latest date which will ) be suitable ) Urgently required. Shipment as soon as possible. Thanking you in anticipation. Yours faithfullyDetails in regard to goods essentially required from the United Kingdom, United itatos of ^erica or Canada by the Arab States in the Persian Qulf* of 2240 Ibc. £^dbdkSLxstX8xrt^tisiix^xtyax^Kiast?i 5* Exact use or purpose contcm- For snlo to the public, plated for the goods to bo imported. 6. Special reasons justifying*- (a) Supply of goods wanted. Bahrain stocks exliaustc (b) Their import from the ^ country suggested rather 7. Description of the urgency ^fith As early as possible, which the goods are required and the latest date which will be suitable. 1. Name of would-bo importer. Mr. K.E. Khodouri, Bahrain. Mr. Jack Della1, 86 George Street, Manchester 1. England 2. Name and address of the agent or irianufacturer in the export ing country from whom ho wishes to arrange supply. 3* Full description of the goods required. 26 pieces black crepe. 4. Approximate weight in long tons 1 cwt. and 88 lbs.^ XoL sg JjiA&gt; y ^75? 2fH&gt; J. E. KHEDOURI import &amp; export *y' . tele address V kh EDOURI-FIAHRAIN Vj /TELEPHONE. 1 83 -M Q / CODES USED;- &lt; ^EN t TLEYS ACME &amp; ORIENTAL BaNkers;- the eastern bank ltd. Two. 78a H.BaM’s Political Agent, Bahrain, ^Dear Sir, We shall be grateful if you will kindly recommend to Higher Authority necessary shipping space assistance for the following.- !• Name would be importer .. J.E. Khedouri, Bahrain. 2. Name &amp; address of the agent.. J.M. Shasha, i or manufacturer in the export ing country from Wxaom he wishes to arrange supply. 5. Pull description of the goods required. 4. Approximate weight in long tons of 2240 lbs. fix Exact use or purpose contemplated for the goods to be imported. 6. Special reasons justifying (a) Supply of goods wanted. (b) Their import from the country suggested rather* than from any other country. 7. Description of the urgency with which the goods are required. 82 Princess Street, Manchester 1. 500 pieees,black mosquito Weight. net,large mesh,20000 yds. 8 c.w.t 200 pieces coloured mosquito net,,large mesh,8000 yds. 9 cwt. 30 pieces,white &amp; black mosquito net,1170 yds, 1 cwt. large mesh. TB~~cwt 0 ~ •. 18 c.w.t© For ladies dress &amp; veils. Orders accepted per J.M.Shasha’s letters of 10th &amp; 18th May attache do Mosquito netting available only from England. As soon as possible Thanking you in anticipation.w J. E. KHEDOURI IMPORT &amp; EXPORT tblr address KHE DOURI. gAH BAiy telephone. 83~m codes used;- BENTLEY8 ACME &amp; ORIENTAL bankers:- the eastern bane ltd. (g Jl' (ARABIA) No. 71. The Director of Customs &amp; Port Officer, Bahrain. Dear Sir, We refer to your recommendation for us to import from Mr. J.M.Shasha, Manchester, for the second half year of 1944, 1 ton woollen piecegoods and 10 tons Cotton piecegoods. We have today placed our Order No.50 on Mr. Shasha for these goods, as per copy of our letter to him enclosed herewith^ for your information. Yours faithfully^ ' Ends.- 1J. E. KHEDOURI IMPORT &amp; EXPORT TKLR A DDR PS? KHB DQURI. gAH R&amp;IN tblephone. 83-M codes used:- 8ENTLEV3 ACME &amp; ORIENTAL bankers;- thb eastern bank ltd. (ARABIA) To.- J.M. Shasha, Esq., 82 Princess Street, Manchester 1, England. J.E.Khedouri, Bahrain, Persian Gulf. A irgraph No.26. ZT&amp;. June, 1944, Dear Sir, OUROKDEft MO,§Q 1 TOM TOOIXEST PIECEGOODS AMD 10 TOMS COTTON PIECEG00D3 POft ^HICH ri£ HA^B XLREkm OBTAINED IMFOKT PEKMIT THB COMThOLLBB AT BAHH A IM FOR THE LAST H ALF YEAR. 1944. Please arrange to ship to our account to Bahrain our above Order Mo.50, consisting of the following goods.- 50 pieces Black woollen Cashmere, 6/7 oes, Se/S'. 60/70^ wool. p«r your offer of 13th April 1944. ' * ’ fO pieces Navy Blue Serge for suitings, or any other Quality •t your discretion. 3 2000 pieces of 20 yds.each, Turkey,Red and Yellow Prints. 12 yds. * 30/31*, Black Leno X overs. ^ Prints. Printed Voiles. Black Cotton Satin Poplin Imitation Linen Jean for suitings Cambric Urgandy or other fancy goods for ladies Printed or Plain Art Silk Spun Silk ^ White shirting. On receipt of this airgraph, please cable us your acceptance as early as possible, quoting in the cable Order 50^ss reference. Your acceptance cable, together with our Orcfer No.50. will be produced to H.h.M^s Political Agent at Bahrain xor obtaining the requisite shipping space recommendation. Please note that in all your mall or cable cori'eapondence relating to these goods. Order Ho.50 should invariably be quoted as reference. Yours faithfully, 1600 500 500 200 500 200 500 600 200 200 200 1000TV _ iv.E. KHEOOURI, Bahrain. Bahrain, 24th July 1944. H.B.^'s Political A^ent, Bahrain. De- r ^ir, I shall he extremely grateful if you will kindly recommend to Higher Authority necessary shipping space assistance for the followl-ng for my account. 1. Name of would be importer. 2. Name and address of the agent., or manufacturer in the export ing country from whom he wishes to arrange supply. 5. Full description of the goods., required. 4. Approximate weight in long •• tons of 2240 lbs. 5. Exact use or purpose con templated for the goods to be imported. 6. Special reason justifying.- (a) Supply of goods wanted (b) Their import from the country suggested rather than from any other country. 7. Description of the urgency with which the goods are required and the latest date which will be suitable. K.E. Khedouri, Bahrain. Messrs. George Kaufmann(London)Ltd, Ibex House, Minories, London, E.C.3. Coloured cotton netting, with small spots. 580 lbs. For ladies’ dress and veils. Not available at Bahrain. My order has been accepted per cable 20th July attached. As soon as possible.' Thanking you in anticipation. Yours faithfully. j/rt ^ C j 0 A(- )iC v Bc O ' ' 1 fort Offirer, 90K.ii. KHiiDOUKI BAHRAIN* ^ 4 7 7 • ^ July 27, 1944 5o ) H.B.M’s Political A&amp;ent Bahrain. Dear Sir I enclose herewith my letter No. 8 of the 25th instant to you*in which the Director of Customs and Port Officer has endorsed in regard to my order for 1450 lbs Cotton Mosquito Netting, Black, from Messrs. Goode Durrant &amp; Murray Ltd., Woodberry, Hindhead, Surrey. instant with regard to my order for 5 tons of goods from Mr. Jack Dellal, Manchester, against which the Director of Customs has recommended shipping space for only - I have been informed by the Director of Customs that he has included his recommendation for shipping space for 1450 lbs. Cotton Mosquito Netting, Black, from Messrs.Goods Durrant &amp; Murray Ltd., in the 5 tons C.P. Goods from Mr. Jack Dellal. In other words, he has made me underst nd that ^he- out of the 3 tons shipping space for 3=t©Hg C.F.Goods, 1450 lbs would be deducted and allotted to to me for the Mosquito Netting from Good Durrant &amp; Murray. 'For shipping space see recommendation as per your letter No.2 of 25.7.44' I also enclose herewith my letter No. 2 of the 25th 3 tons C.P. Goods ton Woollen Goods I shall be therefore very grateful if you will kindly do the aed4== needful in the matter. Thanking you in anticipati n. Yours faithfully. EndsK.E. roiEDuURI. BAHRAIN. REF. NO.12 TO BE ATI ACHED 7th August 1944 TO MY LETTER NO.9'OF THE 27.7.1944 H.B.7’s Political Agent. Bahrain. Dear Sir: I shall be glad if you will kindly recommend for me shipping space assistance for the following:- 1. Name and address of would) be importer ) K. ; ..Khedouri. Bahrain. 2. Name and address of the agent) or manufacturer in the expor-) ting country from whom he ) wishes to arrange supply ) Mr.Jack Dellal. 86,George Street Manchester. England. 3. Bull description of the goods) required ^ £ •) 4. Approximate weight in long ) ton of 2240 Lbs ) 1 Ton Dyed Poplin. 1 T$n Hair cord cotton Cashmere. t Ton Dyed Limbric. Ton Woo li en 3 Tons. 3 Tons. 5. Exact use or purpose contem-) For consumption at Bahrain plated for the goods to be ) imported ) 6. Special reason justifying:- (a) Supply of goods wanted:- To meet local demands. (b) Their import from the country) Available from England, suggested rather than from ) Order has been accepted any other country ) as per cable of the 2nd August 1944 attached herewith. 7. Description of the urgency with) As soon as possible, which the goods are required ) and the latest date which will ) be suitable ) Thanking you in anticipation. Yours faithfullyK.k. KHEjXURI, BAHRAIN. 1944. July 2$, Ref. No. 2, * * 3 * 5 The Director of Customs &amp; Port Officer Bahrain. ’ Dear Sir, Goods to be imported from Manchester and London. 3 tons Cotton Piecegoods. J ton Woollen Piecegoods. ton Artificial Silk. 1 ton Sundry * goods. 5 tons• • • • • I would request you to be good enough to grant me a quota for the abovementioned goods to be imported from kr * Jack Dell al, 86, George Street, Manchester.K.E. KHEDOURI, BAHRAIN. No.8. July 25, 1944 l in] H. B.M's Political Agent, Manama, Bahrain. Dear Sir, I shall be grateful if you will kindly grant me the necessary shipping space recommendation to the Higher Authority for the import of the following goods to Bahrain.- I. Name of would be importer .. K.E. Khedouri, Bahrain. 2. Name and address of the agent.. Messrs. Goode Durrant &amp; Murray Ltd or manufacturer in the ex porting country from whom he wishes to arrange supply. 3. Pull description of the goods . required. 4. Approximate weight in long tons of 2240 lbs. 5. Exact use or purpose contem plated for the goods to be imported. 6. Special reason justifying.- (a) Supply of goods wanted (b) Their import from the country suggested rather than from any other country. 7 7. Description of the urgency with which the goods are required and the latest date which will be suitable. Woodberry, Hindhead, Surrey, England. 30,000 yards Cotton Mosquito Netting. 1450 15s« For dress and veils of local women. Demand in Bahrain. Available only from England. Cabled acceptance of my order attached hereto. As soon as possible Thanking you for your assistance in anticipation. Yours faithfully. J A / 7i . rj. , , w f I ant &lt; ft A 1 -t t a 1 - ** */ ,//7 isT&amp;CtQf Of Of -&gt; •• and Port Officer, U' 'l«?y K.ii. KtiJiiDullhl, BAHhAlN. / V No, 10, Bahrain, 31st July, 1944. 4h.b.m«s toil \ t l Manama, V 1 / t litical Agent, Bahrain. Dear Sir, I shall be very grateful if you will kindly recommend for me shipping space assistance for the following goods.- 1. 2 . 3. Name of would be importer. Name and address of the agent or manufacturer in the exporting country from whom he wishes to arrange supply. Full description of the goods required. 4. Approximate weight in long tons ., 5. Exact use or purpose contemplated for tne goods to be imported. 6. Special reason justifying (a) Supply of goods wanted. (b) Their import from the country suggested rather than from any other country. 7. Description of the urgency with which the goods are required and the latest date which will be suitable. Thanking you in anticipation. K.E. Khedouri, Bahrain. William Laycock 8c Son( Bradford) Limited, 4-6 Burnett Street, Bradford. 20 pieces Black cashmere,woollen 7 pieces Union Mixture,cotton 8c woollen. 870 lbs. , Black cashmere for ladies' abba and Union Mixture for gents suitings. To meet local demands. ,. Available from England. Gabled acceptance of my order attached. As soon as possible. Yours faithfully. q . l( • i I - v 1 ' '' I'» &gt; S 0^4 K.E. KHEDOUKI, BAdKAIN.. July 24th July, 1944. No. 7. The Director of Customs &amp; port Officer, Bahrain. Dear Sir, Goods to be imported from Messrs. William Laycock &amp; 3on(Bradford) Ltd., Bradfo rd. 10 c.w.t. Woollen Piecegoods. I would request you to be good enough to grant me a quota for the import of the abovementioned goods. Thanking you in anticipation. ^ /-tHy m**r of and P*ri (J+cer, 7tv* . ACCREDITED DEALERS FOR 2JT} N'HIS MASTER'S VOICE'/ RADIO • RADIOCRAMOPHO N ES • RECORDS [ Branches—BASRAH | MARGIL ) KOWEIT JASHANNAL BAHREIN (Persian Gulf) Telephone No. 9.M. Telegrams: 'Utjashco, Bahrein' f I Detail* of Goods ossenti&amp;lly roquirod from Unitod Kingdom Name of Importer«- Name of Exporter.- Description of goods required. Weight in Tons, Jashanmal, Bahrein, Osmond Boyes 9 King William St .House Ludon £. a. 4 1 case Tootal Ties 1 ” Tootal cotton handkerchiefs, i Ten. Purpose of goods required. For Local consumption specially by the employees in the oil companies. Description of the urgency. Shortage of goods, goods required as early as possible. and Fwrt MJ M MJIM si*-! ^ 7(Iju) ft ACCREDITED DEALERS FOR RADIO • RADIOGRAMOPHONES • RECORDS y | HIS MASTERS VOICETj Branches—BASRAH | MARCH I KOWEIT y A V) &gt; JASHANMAL BAHREIN (Persian Gulf) Telephone No. 9.M. Telegram?: 'Utjashco, Bahrein' Details of goods essentially required from United Kingdom, Name of Importer.- Name of Exporter.- Description of goods required. Total Weight in Tons. Jashanmal Bahrein. Osmond Boyes, King William St.House,London EC4. 70 pcs. cotton dress material Tootals. i Ton Purpose of goods required. Eor local consumption specially by the empires in the oil companies. Description of the urgency. Shortage of goods. Goods required as early as possible. (JasHanmal) Bahrein. E&amp;rvc&amp;or of CehAsm* and Pari (J/prcr,V K' • jass _ 3 (\ . ^ IvX GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. Department. EXPRESS LETTER JV. B.—Tkis is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities 'it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched. jiOt 18GC-79/175. Dated ' • , .-the 7th August, 1944 / h FOTT'TLtxr pre;’ i}tarav^ri4in Bo. ei9! -36/43 la tie 5 4 t'a 2) 6 y.v, No. 2#9S-3c/43 d tv' 22/e/l$M. I loliU' S). ^..id Agent, IBafcr&amp;to, copies sent to you direct* Goods essentially leal required from tlie United, Kin.gf3.oss. 1 recent ani import asststancjo^ Use issue of the abewe tee lUeeu authorised# V to! ^or Bucsr- tar; r to the Polities Bog icier: t in the Persian Jul Copy to the Political Agent, Baltrain. S. 6. MFP—275 S&lt;tP—676S—(M-676)—27-7-43—1,000,000.Bahrein, 14th August, 1944. H. B. M's. Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir, I beg to enclose herewith the Director of Customs' recommendation together with the suppliers’ telegram dated 29th.. July and my order, and request you to kindly grant Assistance Recommendation; Details of the goods are as under 1. - Name of Importer:- Ali R. Reza, Bahrein. 2. - Shippers:- Messrs. Carters (Merchants) Ltd., Y/inchester House, 3. - HAND KNITTINwG WOOL 4. - Approximate weight in long tons of 2240 lbs.:- 3 cwts. 5. - For sale to the public. 6. - (a) No stocks available in the market, (b) Not available elsewhere. 7. - As soon as possible. Thanking you, I beg to remain, Old Broad Street, London,E.C.2 Yours faithfully,Bahrein, The Director of Customs &amp; Port Officer, Bahrein. Dirurior of 3rd. August, 1944. / \w Dear Sir, I beg to attach hereto Telegram dated 29th July, 1944, from Messrs. Carters (Merchants J Ltd., Juondon, offering 250 lbs. Hand Knitting Wool, and shall feel grateful if assistance Recommendation may kindly be granted Shippers:- Messrs. Carters (Merchants) Ltd., Old Broad Street, London, B*C#2 * 250 lbs. Hand Knitting Wool .... Approx Gross Weight:- 320 lbs I beg to remain, ARIi :MA Enclosure:- 1.in Bahrein, 14th August, 1944. H. B. M f s Political Agent Bahrein. Dear Sir, 1 beg to enclose herewith the Director of customs 1 Kecommendation together with Airgraph dated 13th ^uly from Messrs. The Central Agency Ltd., Glasgow, and shall be grateful if Assistance Recommendat on may kindly be granted. goods are as under:- !•- Name of Importer:- Ali R. Reza, Bahrein. 2. - Suppliers:- Messrs. The Central Agency Ltd.,( 50 Bothv/ell street T, H tt Dept. i Glasgow. 3. - Sewing Cotton Thread, etc. 4. - Approximate wight in long tons of 2240 lbs.:- 1 ton 5. - For sale to the public. 6 . - (a) No stocks available in the market, (b) Not available elsewhere. 7. - As soon as possible. Thanking you, I beg to remain, ARR:MA Enclosures:- 5r Bahrein, 3rd August, 1944. 2 - 2 /S The Director of Customs &amp; Port Officer, Bahrein. Dear Sir, I beg to enclose herewith airgraph dated 13th July, 1944, advising the acceptance of my order placed with them for the follow ing, and shall ieel obliged ii assistance recommendation may kindlv be granted J ^uppliers.— ihe Central Aoency Ltd., 01as 0 ow. Sewin^ Cotton Thread Appr. Cross Weight i— 1 ton Thanking you, I beg to * AKH:MA Enclosure : 1 . remain, Yours faithful ALI K. RBZAJ. E. K HE DOUR I IMPORT &amp; EXPORT addrpss K^DOURI-BAHRAIN telephone. 83-m codes used:- /fiNTLEYS ACME &amp; ORIENTAL lst 3ept -y^ bankers;- (ARABIA) the eastern bank ltd. hefce.No* 84. 1 3 ) Bahrain Receipt Ko H.B.M * s Political Agent, Bahrain® Dear Sir, 2 000 pie ces Turk ey Red and Yellow Prin t a. We enclose herewith, in original, an airgraph dated the 10th August from Mr. J.M* Shasha, Manchester, our principal, in connection with our order for the above goods, which is self- explanatory. We beg to inform you that - (1) we have been importing this commodity into Bahrain for the last 15 years; (2) these goods are not manufactured in India, and (3) the ladies of local Sheikhs and families of local notables only prefer these goods for their use. We send herewith a sample of the goods for your inspection. We shall be extremely grateful if you will kindly be good enough to make suitable representations, if possible, to Commercial Relations and Treaties Department of the Board of Trade for the release of the necessary raw material to the extent of 4,000 lbs cotton for the manufacture of the above goods for import into Bahrain, referred to in Mr. Shasha^ airgraph. Thanking you for your assistance in anticipation. Yours faithfully., ^ _ Me &lt;&amp;ZQtint ^.uuth. Cuiuffj&gt; (incorporated in England) ALL LETTERS TO BE ADDRESSED TO the eastern bank limited __ T^legraptvc Address: 'er^reRTiDE:' 5th Septp* y// 44 . Politic*! Agent* Bahrain. Dear Sir, Bahrain Receipt Textlloe ft Yam. We encleaft a copy #r a latter recelaod by enr Head OCflce from the Manchester Chamber »f Commerce, ahloh may be ef interest to y»u. Xoura faithfully. Sncls1. ManagerJ • Codes used : Bentley, s, Oriental-Letter and paramont NV c/* Our Ref Your Ref,. ■^CaBle^^ress: Trikamdts, Bahrain C. TRIKAMDAS &amp; CO. Specialists in Fancy Silks, Cotton, Woollen piece Goods Curios and General Merchants o PjfirvTj BELGRA.VK ROAD . J. ^ UCLCipi BAHREIN Telephone No. ?3-m xv / *&gt;h- 0 , PERSIAN GULF No Allx% Bahrain^epteffiber lOtbp- % *1 The Director of Customs URGrSlTT Port Officer Bahrein* Dear 3ir, He* Import of Todstal Tie^ from IT,K In the above connection , we have received a telegram from our \ suppliers which originally we enclose her^vith for your kind A - perusal and shall be very glad if you kindly grant us the necessar import licence on enclosed Indent in order to cable them* Thanking you, Your* faithfully C.Trikamdas &amp; Co* Enc indent. /Detnila in regard to goodn osacnt^all/ required from the Utiitcd Kingdomi United ^Statoa of America or Jana da by the Arab States in the Persian Gulf* l*VaM of sould-bc iraportor. —— y r ^ jj # E # Khodouri, Bahrain* 2 *Kamo and addrnos of the agent or manufacturer in the exporting country from whom he nishes to arrange supply* 3 *Full description of the goods required. 4•Approximate weight in long tons of 2240 lbs* 5 *Exact use or purpose contemplated for the goods to be imported. 6*3pocial reasons justifying!- (a) Supply of goods viantod* (b) Their lnpoi*t from the country suggested rather than from any other country. 7* Description Of the urgency tfith which the goods are required and the latest date which will be suitable* Messrs# J.M* Shasha 9 32 rrincosa Street, !^anchestcr,l Mosquito Netting* 18 cwt* For sale to the public* Bahrain stocks exhausted* Wot available from olaowhoro. As onrly ns possible.11 \ TTr,&lt;+„ 5 0 ^ i1 ^ 1,1 t0 Goods oaaontinlly roquirod from the ^titoa S» 6 ^ nitod States of America or Canada by the Arab btatea in tho Persian Oulf* ‘237 1# Kamo of would-bo impor'tQr# 2. Name and address of the agent or manufacturer in tho export ing country from whom ho wishes to arrange supply. 3* Full description of the goods required. 4. Approximate weight in long tons of 2240 lbs. 5. xact use or purpose contemplated for the goods to bo imported. ?!r. K.K. Khodouri f Bahrain. Messrs. George Kaufmannltd., Ibex House, Minorios, )bndon.K.C.3. Coloured Cotton Netting with small spots. $ ton. ;? or sale tc tho public. 6 . Ipocial reasons Juatifying:- (a) Supply of goods wanted. (b) Their ini&gt;ort from the country suggested rather than farm any other countary. 7. Doseriptier of the urgency with which the goods aaro roquiarod and tho latest date which will be suit able. Bahrain stocks exhausted. -ot available from elsewhere. As'ealy as poesj^e. LDetails in regard to goods osoontially raquirtKi from the United kingdom, United States of America or Canada by f lu \ the Arab States in the Persian Gulf*. l.Kame of would-be inpor&gt;er« K«K# Kl\edouri f Bahx^ain* 2•Name and address of the agent or manufacturer in the exporting country from shorn he sishee to arrange supply* Mr* Jack nellal, 86, George Street,Manchester, England. a. Full description of the goods required* Cotton piecegood8*2 % ;tons&lt;?7£vYt wollan ]&gt;ieccgoods. 10^cwts. 4. Approximats weight in long tons of 2240 lbs* b.Sxact use or purpose contemp la ted for the goods to be imported* 6.Special reasons justifying *- (a) Supply of goods wanted* (b) Their Import from the country suggested rather than trow any other country* ^ ttens ’ *&lt; nc 1 17 c &gt; ts. For sale to th« public. W.brain stocks exhausted* Wot available frore elsewhere# As ealy as possi^&gt;le 7. Description of the urgency w ith v»hich tlie goods are required and the latest date^ which will be suitable#w Details in rog^ni to Roods essentially required from the united &amp;ingdom t United of Araoricn or Cnnadn by the Arab States in the Persian &gt; tU If. !• Name cf weu3d 'K5 i^orter*. 2* Maine and address of the iqjont or suitfiuiaoturer in Uio oxpoi*t- infj country from ^hon he ^iiahoe to ar7*an4»o supply* 3« Full description of the &gt;;oods required * 4» Approxi'-ate wei;l\t in long tone of 2240 lbs* b# fitwet use or con ten pin to 1 for the goods to bo imported• Mr# Jadtamalf Bahrain* Mocsro# Osmond uoyoo, King William at • Hou • e f Lord or. f £ *C *4 » Cotton efros^ -r tcvisl. 1/2 ton* For o&amp;le to tlx public* (nj Bahrein stocks exhausted* 6* Specin1 reasons justifying: (a; Supply of goods aantod (h) Tiicir ii:i;&gt;ort from the country su;posted natlier tivnn from (b) Hot available from anywhere else* any other country* 7* Do script! on of tiio urgency witii which the goods ero roquirod a rail *U\f» iUuMt latest date which will be suitable* As seen an posniblo*' - . • • • , * ' '■ , Details in to |{oodo essentially required fr'ori tJie United Kingdom, United states of Anorica or Canada by tiie Arab States in the Persian Gulf* Ur. Ali H. Bossa Messrs. Carters (Mcrcliants) •'inchooter House, Old Broad Streo Pond on, K.C.B. Hand knitting wool. !• Name of would-ho importer 2. Name and address of the agent or manufacturer in the export ing country frcri whom he whiohos to arrange supply. 3* Full description of the goods required. 4* Approximate weight in long tons of 8240 lb?. 5. exact use or purpose contem plated for the goods to be imported• 6. Special reasons juotifying:- (a) Sup of goods wanted (b) Their import from the country eu rgestod rather tlian from any other country. 3 cwta. 'or sale to tiic public. (a) Bahrain stocks exhausted. (b) not available from anywhere olao. 7. Description of tlie urgency with which t!\o goods are required and As soon as possible. the latest late which will bo suitable.'lift Ootflils in rcnsml to fjoode coaontially roquirocl fror the United Kin^jclom, United 3tatoa of America or Canaria by the Arab States in the Persian Gulf. 1* Name of *ould-bo importer. Mr.' Ali R* Reza» Bahrain* 2. Name and address of the a rent ^or manufacturer in the exporting country from when he wishes to ai'raiu'e supply. 3. Full description of the gooda ^acquired. 4* Approximate ^oi^it in lon 4 ; x-ona of 2240 lbs. 5. Exact use or purpose contemplated for the goods to be imported 6* Special reasona justifyings- (a) Supnly of goods wanted Cb) Their import from the country sag :c a tod rather tlian from any other country. 7* Description of the urgency with which the goods arc required and the latest date wnich will bo ^Nuitable* The Central Agency I/td*, 50 9 nothwell Street, Glasgow* Sewing Cotton fShrcnd etc. 1 ton. For sale to tlio public* (a) Bahrain stocks exhausted* (b) Not available from anywhere else* As soon as possible*Khansaheb Abdulhusain &amp; Bros. IMPORTERS &amp; EXPORTERS. Cartr Ps(*&lt;/:- A, B. C. 3TH EDITION &amp; BENTLEY’S («!&gt; '&amp;&gt;■ ”h. M*s, Political To , u rj Bahrein. (P.Gulf.) Kespected Sir, /BaAtam - ^ 7 ^~». 3ep.t^. - --1 ^• ( T. GULF. ) flaVatn Receipt We enclose herewith a form for Import Becommendation and a copy of our indent, reccommended by the Director of Custom &amp; rort Officer, for our order of Sewing thread and Sroder S'Xein placed with Messrs^ The Central Agency,Ltd. of Glasgow (Scotland) with their letter of 1th Sept .1944 aa a rjrocf of the acceptance of our Indent . As the goods are awaiting shipping space, we shall be highly obliged if you will pass the Assisstance Hecommendation to our supplier, to enable them tO e xe cure the order. \ • Than King ycu in anticipation, We are, Kespected Sir, Yours Obediently. o er Pro. Khansc^-^ idu,! ’ usain 4 end: Appl .form, indent copy, Supplier’s letter.( 1 ) ( 2 ) (3) (4) (5) ( 6 ) (7) Details in regard to goods esseantially required from United Kingdom, United States of America or Canada by the Arab States in the Persian Gulf.. .Name of Would be Importer. Khansaheb Abdulhusein Bros. ^ Bahrein. (P .Gulf.) Hame and address of agent in the exporting country from he wished to obtain supply. Pull Description of the goods Reqiiiired. Approximate weight in long tons of 2240 Lbs .of the goods required. Exact use or purpose contemp lating for the goods to be imported . Special reasons justifying i^/s: The Central Agency .Ltd. 50th,Bothwell Street. Gclasgow . (U.K.) &gt; . As per attached list. li ton approximately. To sell locally. 1 v ' 1 a.Supply oi goods wanted. As mentioned above. b.Their import from the To get better quality, country suggested rather than fro many other country . Description of the urgency with As early as possible, which the goods are required, and the latest date which will be suitable. / ss ft. tfr /l *7 IItP *ho- H. B. M's. Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir, 1^4 Bahrein, 26th September, 1944. f T ' * . _ --'rt Jo.-uu 1 beg to enclose herewith the Director of Customs’ recommendation together with Airgraph dated 30th August, 1944, from Messrs. Tootal Broadhurst Lee Co., Ltd., Manchester, and request you to kindly grant Assistance Recommendation:- Details of the Goods 1•- Name of Importer:- Ali R. Reza, Bahrein. 2. - Manufacturers &amp; Shippers:- Messrs. Tootal Broadhurst Lee Co., Ltd., 56 Oxford Street, Manchester 1 . 3. - Pull description of the goods:- 19,000 yards Manchester Piecegoods. 4. - Approximate weight in long tons of 2240 lbs.:- 2 tons. 5. - Por sale to the public in Bahrein. 6 . -(a) English piecegoods are not available in the m rket at present (b) These cloths can only be had from Great Britain. 7. As soon as possible. Thanking you, I beg to remain. ARE:MA Enclosures:- 3. -4. cv /Bahrain, 23rd September, 1944. 4 A The Director of Customs &amp; Port Officer, Bahrain. Dear Sir, r l beg to enclose herewith Airgraph dated 30th August, 1944, from Messrs. Tootal Broadhurst Lee Co # , Ltd., Manchester, and request you to kindly grant recommendation. Shippers:- Messrs. Tootal Broadhurst Lee Co. Ltd., Manchester. Detail of Goods:- 19000 yards Manchester Piecegoods .... 2 tons In view of the fact that good quality British piecegoods are not available in the market at present I trust you will extend your assistance in order that these goods may be imported as quickly as possible. Thanking you, I remain,1 H. B. M's. Political Agent, Bahrain. Bahrain, 1st October, 1944. 1&lt;P. $1(0 XT'. Dear Sir, Xo57^.. I beg to enclose herewith the Director of Customs' Recommendation together with telegram and Airgraph from Messrs. W.F. Gouda &amp; Co. Ltd., London, advising the acceptance of my order as nnder, and request you to kindly grant Import Assistance Recommendation:- Details of the goods :- 1. Name of Importer:- Ali R. Reza, Bahrain. 2. Suppliers:- Messrs. Y». F. Gouda &amp; Co. Ltd., 88 Penchurch St., London, E.C.3. 3. Full description of the goods:- 18,000 yards Cotton Mosquitto Nettings, Colours &amp; Black only. . ^ 4. Approximate weight in long tons ^ wiic puuxie. of 2240 lbs.:- 6 . |f;| No stocks available in the ( ) Not available elsewhere. market. 7. As soon as possible. Thanking you I beg to remain ARR:MA Yours faithfully.The Director of Customs &amp; Port Officer Bahrain. Bahrein, 25th September, 1944 Dear Sir I beg to enclose herewith telegram and Airgraph from Messrs. Yt/• 1. Gouda &amp; Co., Ltd., London, advising the acceptanceof my order as under, and shall be grateful if Assis tance Recommendation may kindly be granted Suppliers:- kessrs. W. P. Gouda &amp; Co., Ltd., London. Detail of goods:- 18,000 yards Cotton Losquitto Lettings, £ ton ARR:MA Ends. Yours faithfullydetails in regard to goods essentially required from the Ohlted Jaa^doa, united St ldS of America or Canada by the iurab States in the Persian Gulf* » 1 * Name of would be importer* 2* l«Bie end address of the or aajriufacturer in the exporting country froza v'xtm he wishes to arrange supply* 3* Pull description of the goods required. dr* all H* Reza, Bahrain* Messrs* Tootal Bro&amp;dhurst Lee Co* f Ltd* 9 o* : ? Oxford Streetf Manchester 1* 19 9 000 yards Manchester piece-goods* 4* Approximate weight lo long tons of 2240 lbs* 2 tons* 6* JSx&amp;et use or purpose oontaz lated for the goods to be Imported* For sale to the pubxic* 6 * Special reafsons Jastifying* (a) Supply of r&gt;ds wanted. (a) Bahrain stocks exhausted* (b) Their import from the country suggested rather than from any other country* (b) 5ot available x'rom elsewhere* 7* Description of the urgency with which the goods are required and the latest date whlOh will be suitable* As soon as possible*to * 00 &amp;* esseiiti^ily r^quir^vi from the Ualt«d King* v' 1 o r :-; ;f /ip»aric4i ox» CtiUtck by bhi* /uwt States in the Persian Gulf* « X. Hame of would bo inportor. Khwioahob Abdulhuoaln A Bros., Bahrain. 2. Naso and address if th-3 e^ent Stes&amp;j's. Kii' Central Agoney. ltd., or aenufacturar In tho orportir-x 60th Bcthwall Street, Glasgow, country front whom fc*? wiar?i«3 to arrange supply* 3« Pull desCliptlon of the goods r required* tewing t’lread *tfid broder skeins* 4* Approximate weijbt In lozu tons of 2840 lbs* One ton* 6* Sxaet use or purpose cor.templatad for the goods to be Imported. For sale to tho puhllo. 6* Special reasons justifying* (a) Supply of goods wanted. (a) Bahrain stocks exhausted. (b) Their Insert from the coujztiy suggested rather than from any other country. (b) Hot ewsilabie from elsewhere. \i 7* Description of the urgency with which the goods are required end the la tost datv ?rhioh irill be suitable* As soon as possible*J. E. KHEDOURI U ' v A IMPORT '&amp; EXPORT TBLB AODRKSS KHEDOUR I-BAHRAIN tblephone. 83~m cooes used:- RENTLEYS ACME &amp; ORIENTAL bankers;- the eastern bank ltd. Reference No„ 860 H.B.lvi's I-oliticel Bahrain, Jm 75) 7 ^ hs/ratn -1st. Octre^^^ (ARABIA) Bahrain Receipt 4 . Dear Sir, V. ^e snail be very grateful if you will kindly recommend for us shipping space assistance for the following goods,- 1, Name &amp; address of would be importer. 2, Nsme &amp; address of the agent from whom he wishes to arrange supply. 5. Pull description of the goods required. 4. Approximate weight in long tons. • o J.E* Khedouri, Bahrain. o. Messrs, ^avid like &amp; Go. Ltd., Kbor Mills, Bingley, Yorks, England. .. woollen suitings for Ladies. about 4 c .w, t. 1 5. Exact use or purpose con templated for the goods to • be imported. 6 . Special reason justifying (a) Supply of goods wanted. (b) Their import from the country suggested rather than from any other country. 7 0 Desspiption of the urgency with which -the ^oods are to be sent. ) To meet local demands. ) ) Telegram of offer dated 21st and our acceptance of 30th attached. As soon as possible. 'lhanking you in anticipation. ■» 4 * a *•'“'N B^fcrafa Receipt Na ^C.^ ta ul:M^L- 11th October 1944 .P.'J's Political Agent, Bahrain, Dear Sir: ./e would request you'to recommend to the Higher Authority to grant shipping space and release of the goods mentioned hereunder hnd' thanking you for the same. 'lame of would be importer: Tame and address of the agent) or manufacturer in the expor-) ting country from whom he ) wishes to arrange supply ) Pull description of the goods required. California louse. Bahrain J'essrs Tootal Broadhurst lee &amp; Co., Ltd, ■ anche ster. Robia veils &amp; Novelties 2000 Yds. Torantulla popular ) white,dyed &amp; printed ) 2000 ' Torantulla Std.white 1000 ' Tootal Longcloth 3000 ' Tobral co,white Dyd.Prin.5000 ' Lovassia 36' white ) dyed Printed ) 5000 Honeysuckle Gingham 5000 ' Violet lable Poplin 2000 ' Red lable Poplin 2000 ' Approximate weight tons of 2240 Lbs. in long ) 5. Exact use or purpose contem for the goods to be imported About 2i Tons. (Director of Customs*and Port Officer, Bahrain, recommended j or 2-g- Tons as per our appli cation dated 8 th Yarch 1944 attached herewith) plated) Por the use of gents and ladies at Bahrain. 6 . Special reason justifying:- (a) Supply of goods wanted:- Not available at Bahrain and great in demand. (b) Their import from the country) This particular goods suggested rather than from ) available only from any other country are ) J ingland and manufacturers can supply the goods and waiting for shipping space recommendation and certi ficate for the release of poods(Ref. their airgraph let er of the 25 th September a94 / - attached herewith) 7» description of the urgency with) which the goods are required ) Urgently required. Shipment which will which the goods are and the latest date be suitable soon as possible. _ o fhanking you in anticipation. 1 . 3 ! rlease return the attached &gt;' •Yours f-i letters when done with. ' ' ^Cable^: “Mostafa Codet t A \l&gt; C 5th Edition. Bentley’s Oriental &amp; Private CALIFORNIA HOUSE % -fa Agents: ^ NEW ZEALAND INSURANCE CO. LTD FIRE, MARINE. ACCIDENT. Sde Distributors For: Wahl Company Everlast Pen &amp; Pencil Corp. Garvey &amp; Company Metalfix Company Geo. J. Kelly, Inc. W anderer-W erke. A.G* Albert Padberg Phoebus Werke Treibacher Chemische Werke Nationals Ltd. West End Watch Co. (Arabian Peninsula except Aden &amp; Bahrain) Proprietors: t MOSTAFA ABDULLATIFF IMPORT &amp; EXPORT BAHRAIN Persian Gulf ^ Lj Dealers in: Continental Typewriters Wanderer Cycles &amp; M. Cycles Eversharp Pens &amp; Pencils Eveready Flashlights &amp; Cells Arrow Shirts &amp; Shorts Palmolive Soap &amp; Colgate,s Goods Krementz Products Daimon Lights &amp; Cells Hosiery Bourjois Perfumes # Johnson &amp; Johnson’s Tootal Products General Stores &amp; Provisions No. 8 th March 1944- Etc, Etc. The Director of Customs and Port Officer, Bahrain. Dear Sir: We would request you to recommend for the import of the goods mentioned hereunder:- 1. Name of would be importer:- California House. Bahrain, 2. Name and address of the agent)Messrs Tootal Broadhurst or manufacturers in the expor) Lee Company, ting country from whom he )P.O.Box No.245. wishes to arrange supply ) 56 Oxford Street.Manchester 3. Pull description of the goods) Assorted cotton piecegoods . required ) suitable for gents shirting pents etc, and ladies dress 4 . Approximate weight in long ) About 5 Tons, tons of 2240 Lbs ) 5 . Exact use or purposes contem)p or g en ^ Q an( j ladies, plated for the goods to be ) imported ) 6 , Special reason justifying:- (a) Supply of goods wanted:-Not available at Bahrain. (b) Their import from the ) The particular qualities country suggested rather ) of goods are not than from any other country) available from any other country. 7. Description of the urgency) with which the goods are ) required and the latest ) date which will be suutable Urgently required. Shipment as soon as possible. ) Thanking you in anticipation. Yours f ai thf f 'h A :oi £ ^'V J. E. KHEDOUHI IMPORT &amp; EXPORT tblk addrpss khbd ouri-Bah rain tblkphone!. 83-m CODES USED;- RENTLEYS ACME &amp; ORIENTAL bankers;- thk eastern bank ltd. Ref, NOo87 . H.B.M's Political Agent, Bahrain, Dear Sir, 1 ^ tf 1 ~Q$&amp; • fir't/tn (ARABIA) Z24 4 - ?xece : # . (d^ - So PaVa® ' v; 1 %..&gt;-• fte shall he very ^rateful if you will kindly recommend for us shipping space assistance for tne following goods.- 1. Name and address of would he J.E. Khedouri, Bahrain, importer. 2 . Name and address of the agent General Trade &amp; Chemical exports from whom he wishes to arrange Company Ltd., supply. HO Cannon Street, London,E.C.4* 3. Full description of the goods required. 4. Approximate weight in long tons. 5. Exact use or purpose con templated for the goods to he imported. 6 . Special reason justifying j (a) Supply of goods wanted. (h) Their import from the country suggested ratner than from any other country. 7. description of the urgency with which the goods are to he sent. Thanking you in anticipation. 20 pieces Tropical Suiting (Quality 5053). 10 c.w.t* To meet local demands. Telegram of offer of 9th and our acceptance cable of 10th inst. enclosed herewith. As soon as possible. i /Ft lot 'iAROOPY YACOOB ZELOOF &amp; SONS. CLOTH MERCHANTS &amp; COMMISSION AGENTS. Tele Add:ZELOOF. BAHR 4 IN &amp; BOMBAY. P- GULF. INDIA. —S j)! ji_j &gt; Y ; : Li 1 H, B* M’s Political Agent, Bahrain. ^j) j Bahrain, 1?th October 1944. Bahrain Receipt Respected Sir; ttanram , No. Kindly read below translation of an excerpt of a letter rom our agent in Manchester dated 15th March 1944, P which is written in Hebrew and which is attached, wr irren ' In reply to your letter dated 20th ultimo, we have sent you samples of our stocks with full details,' etc, * At present we have in our stoclc:- Ho, 127, 36inches 156 pieces of 40/45 yds. Spun silk woven fesh.4/10 per yd. cif Bahrain. No. 128, 36 inches 101 pieces 40/45 yds. bpun silk printed ^sh.4/9 per yd. cif Bahrain. No. 129, 54 inches 400 pieces &amp;0/&amp;9 yds. Black satan ^ ^sh.2/10 per yd. cif Bahrain. No. 130, 36 inches 400 pieces 50/52 yds. Iimbric|i @sh. 1/7 per yd. cif Bahrain. No. 131, 36 inches 300 pieces 40/45 yds. Art silk crepe @sh.4/3 per yd. cif Bahrain. ' Those goods will be shipped to you immediately upon Bahrain &amp; P ermit shipping space from your Authority in The above, Sir, is self-explanatory, unnecessary to add anything which would make it and we find it clearer. The balance of the attached letter deals with various business relations between the writer and ourselves, and we would be glad to translate it to you in full, in case, you want us ?o do oO • Thanking you in anticipation of a favourable reply. We beg to remain, Sir, Your most obediently.ABOODV VAC'OOB ZELOOF &amp; SONS. ^LOFH MERCHANTS A COMMISSION AGENTS. TeJe Add: Z ELOOf. BAHRAIN ^ BOMBAY. P * GlILF * INDIA. Political A.^ent, Bahcain, ■ - . Hj 21 1) jAjO,J3 1 ^Jb J ulj^. l?th Octooer 1944. Through The Director of Customs &amp; Port Officer, Bahrain. Dear Sir, We shall be grateful if you will kindly recommend shipping ~Pace assistance for us for the following goods.- Aboody Yacoob Zeloof &amp; Sons f Bahrain. • Mr. J. Akerib, 21 Chorlton Street, Manchester 1 , England. 800 pieces. 1. Name of would be importer. 2. Name and address of agent or ra nufacturer in the exporting country from whom he wishes to arrange supply. 5. Pull description of the goods., required. 4. Approximate weight in long tons of 224 o lbs. 5. Exact use or purpose contemplated.. To meet the for the goods to be imported. market. 6 . Special reason justifying.- (a) Supply of goods wanted. .. Not available from elsewhere. (b) Their import from the country.. Available from U.K. Mr.Akerib f s suggested rather than any acceptance of our order, dated o h-r country. 15 -^ March 1944 is enclosed. Art Silk,coloured (32,000 yds.). .. 4 tons approx. (Pour tons) demands of the 7. Description of the urgency with which the goods c re required and the latest date which will be suitable. As soon as possible. Thanking you in anticipation, Yours faithfully, -it' , y .igtails ^ in regard to goods erssontially roquircd from the United King- om, United States of America or Canada by the Arab State* in the - Persian Gulf • 1. Name of would be importer. 2. Name and addresa of the agent or manufacturer in the export ing country from whom ho wishes to arrange supply. 3. Full description of the goods required. 4. Approximate weight in long tons of 2240 lbs. 5. Exact use or purpose contemplated for the goods to be imported# 6 . Special reasons justifying: (a) Supply of goods wanted. (b) Their import from the country suggested rather than from any other country. . 7. Description of the urgency with which the goods are roejuired* and the latest date which will • be suitable* Mr# J.S. Khedourl* Bahrain# Messrs# David Pike Co« y Iitd# § Sbor Mills 9 Bingley f Yor«St jingla Woollen suitings for ladies# 4 cv.ts* For sale to the public# Bahrain stocks exhausted# Not available from elsewhere# As soon as possible#1. 2, 3. Namo of would bo importer. Name and address of the agent or manufacturer in the export ing country from whom ho wishes to arrange supply. The itan&amp;ger/ California House 9 Bahrain* Messrs* Toot&amp;l Broadhurst Lee &amp; Co* f Ltd* Manchester* , Full description of the goods required. Cotton piece-goods (as oor list attached) 4. Approximate weight in long tons of 2240 lbs. 2ft tons* 5. 6 • 7. Exact use or purpose contemplated for the goods to be imported. Special reasons justifying: (a) Supply of goods wanted. * (a) (b) Their import from the couhtry suggested rather than from 00 any other country. Description of the urgency with which the goods are required and the latest date which will ■ be suitable. For sale to the public* Bahrain stocks exhausted* Not available from elsewhere* As soon as possible*Ko.5^^-3^/43. Pol.lticiiX Agency f Bahrain * The October | 194*:* To The Hon f fcle the Politict.l Resident in tbe Peralar. Guir* Bu«hlre» Hr* J.E. Khadoiiri, BaiUa5n y has applied to me for assistance in exporting cotton piece-goods froix the lTntte»i Kingdom* 2* I reconeoenl t’\at a£si3te;ice&gt; m^y granted out of the allotment for JaCLuaiy/Jtzne 1945 under hfia'iiiAg cotton piece-goods «nl enclose the usual details* Toe order has placed and accepted. Copy forwarded to the Secretary to the Goveraflient of India in the Sxteraal Affairs Donartnent, Deilii, Copy forwarded to Mr, J.E, Khedouri^ Bahrain with reference to his letter dated 10th October, 1944.I Qtails m regard to goods ^essentially required from the United King- om, -Jnited Stages of America or Canada by the Arab States in the Persian Gulf. 1. Name of would be importer. 2# Name and address of the agent or manufacturer in the export ing country from whom ho wishes to arrange supply. 3. Full description of the goods required. 4. Approximate weight in long tons of 2240 lbs. 5. Exact use or purpose contemplated for the goods to' bo imported. 6 . Special reasons justifying; (a) Supply of goods wanted. (b) Their import from the country suggested rather than from any other country. . 7. Description of the urgency with which the goods are reauired and the latest date which will be suitable. Mr* J.E. Khedouri, Bahrain. General Trade &amp; Chemical Exports Co.* Ltd.| 110 Cannon Street* London, E.C.4. 20 pieces tropical suiting (Quality 5063). 10 Cwts. For sale to the public* (a) Bahrain stocks exhausted* (b) Not available from elsewhere. As soon as possible.* * No. Jo$^~36/43* Political Agency, Bahrain, The October, 1944* To The Ho.n ‘ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Boshire. j |eaivra/,\dj:LU. Messrs. Aboody Yacoob Zeloof A Sons, Bahrain havs aopllod to me tor assistance in exporting silk from the United Kingdacu X reoc^Ttend that assistance my be granted out of ih.j allotaent ror J^niiary/June, 1945 W&amp;9T beading cotton pioco-goods Eind enclose tlie us ^i details. The order has beon placed and accepted. 0}C' Political Agent, Bahrain. sA** Copy forwarded to the Secretary to the Government of India in the External AXfuirs Bef&gt;artment, New Delhi. Copy to Mossrs. Aboody Yacoob Zeloof &amp; Sons, Bahrain with reference to their letter dated 17th October, 3.944.J K I r p y . IQtails in rega rd to goods ossontially required from the United King- Lom, United Sta ^es of America or Canada by the Arab States in the Persian Gulf* 1* Name of would be importer. 2# Name and address of the agent or manufacturer in the export ing country from whom he wishes to arrange supply. 3. Full description of the goods required. 4. Approximate weight in long tons of 2240 lbs. 5. Exact use or purpose contemplated for the goods to bo imported. 6 . Special reasons justifying: (a) Supply of goods wanted. (b) Their import from the country suggested ra oher than from any other country. . 7. Description of the urgency with which the goods are required • and the latest date which will be suitable. Mej rsra* AfeotxSj Xaeoob Zeloof &amp; Sons t Bahrain. mx* J* Akerib f £1 Cher1ton Street, Kanshtfeisr i, Inglaml* Art tank* coloured pieces &lt;32.000 ytfs*) A tonr« Fo: r^ila to the public* (a) li&amp;hratn stocks exhaustei* (b) Not available from else fhore* AM as possible#mamI Tel. AdJ pess:- Faltirud(Jin TaliertJial- BAHRAIN. FAKNRUDDIN 11. TANERBNAI General Merclienls. BANRAIN. (Persian Gulf.) Codes Used:- Benlley s Orienlal III ree Leller &amp; Private. Daoed 3i. d August 1^44, Details in regard to goods essentially reouiied from the United Kingdom. 1 1. Name of would be importer. 2 . Name end address of Agent or Manufacturer in the exporting country from whom he wishes to obtain supply. 3. Full description of the goods iequired. 4. Approximate weight in long tons of 2240 lbs of the goods required 5. Exact use or purpose contemplated for the goods to be imported 6 . Special reason Justifying*- a) supply if of the goods wanted b) Their import from the country suggested rather than from any other country. 7. Description of the urgency with which the goods are required and the latest date which will be suitable. X 7 Me ssrs: Fakhruddin M. Tanerbhai, The Central Agency Ltd., 50, Bothwell Street, GLASGOW (England) 234 Gaoss Anchor brand coton a Broder Art.No.4375, £ Ton. For local consumption Shortage of goods. Octobe/November 1944. Dirt&amp;tor of Cu *» and Port Officer, 9 4 Si KJ.h JfTHE CENTRAL AGENCY, LTD. (INCORPORATED IN SCOTLAND.) 81, PALTAN ROAD, P.O.BOX 280. Telegraphic Address: “SIXCORD BOMBAY” Telephone No. 23414. BOMBAY, 13th October 1944. Khenbehsdur Fekrudin M. Taherbhoy, No.75, Mohsmedally Road, BOMBAY. , Dear 51r, We have been advised by our Head Office g that your Indents Nos. 2, 3, 4 and 5 for 234. Gross Anchor Coton-'a-Broder have been booked for execution. Please, therefore, advise your Baharein Office to arrange for the import permit from the Political Agent. Yours faithfully For THE De poju-liati a ge r. W' DHaUANUAL IbaAuDAS Bahrain 25-10-44. To The Political Agent, Bahrain. Bear Sir, No.. v - v Bahrain Aeceipt S^ate u 6o- i With reference to your Memorandum No. 1244-36/43, dated the let May, 1944, we, herewith enclose a copy of a letter we have received from Messrs Ralli Brothers Limited, Bombay, and request that the necessary recommendation may be given to us in order to enable us to import the said goods. Awaiting your reply, and thanking you in anticipation. Yours faithfully, p.p. Lhamanmal IssardasSd/- C.J.D. Sd/- A.G* Sotiriadi PIECE GOODS YTT. Messrs* Dharaanlal Issardas, BOMBAY* Dear Sirs, Bombay, 22nd September 1944 23rd Lancashire Plecegoods for shipment to Persian Gulf Ports » With reference to your enquiry for certain Imported Cotton &amp; Woollen Plecegoods for shipment to Bahrein we give you below copy of a letter we have received from our Manchester Office In this connection, which speaks for Itself:- ?, 0n the 18th July we received a letter from the India Office informing us that the Government of India was supporting the recommendation of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf for the above order* Upon receipt of your telegram giving us the details of this order we again communicated with the India Office but they informed us that their support was limited to assistance in faci litating the shipment of the goods when they had been obtained and did not include sponsorship of the order by the Government of India # Without sponsorship it Is impossible for our manufacturers to obtain supplies for replacement allocation from the Cotton and Wool Controls and we are therefore unable to proceed further with this order* n As you will see sponsorship from the Government of India is required and please let us know what you can do in this connection* Yours faithfully, per pro Rail! Brothers Limited,I Details i n regard to goods, eaa^ntially required from the United King dom, United States of America or Canada by the Arab State* in the Persian GulT. /*\ 1. 2 . 3. Name of would be importer. Name and address of the agent or manufacturer in the export ing country from whom ho wishes to arrange supply. Full description of the goods required. Mr. Fakhruddin M. Taherbhai,’ &lt; Bahrain. The Central Agency Ltd., 50 Bothwell f, itreet, Glasgow, England. a 234 •Gross i'mehor brand cotton a Brwler Art. No.4375. 4. Approximate weight in long tons of 2240 lbs. ' 1/2 ton. 5. 6. Exact use or purpose contemplated for the goods to be impor-^ed/. Special reasons justifying! (a) Supply of goods wanted. (b) Their import from the country v Suggested rather* than from. any other country. . For sale to the public. Bahrain stocks exhausted. Not available from elsewhere. 7. Description of the urgency with which the goods arc required jiS soon as possible, and the latest date which will • be suitable*No. 5/026/43. Political Agency, Bahrain The 3/^0 ctober, 1944. Messrs. Dhanarnal Issardas, Bahrain. Momorcunlnm Heferenco youi* letter dated the 25th Octobor. 194-1. 2 . I aiii afraid it is outside the sphere of this Agency r.o arrange to get supplies froni the cotton and wool controls. Tt is for your agent in th*-* Uni tea ICingdoiii co get export pern it etc. The L-diu Office is only responsible for giving shipping space for goods for Bahrain. Political Agent, Bahrainr jr. ..t. &amp; A &lt; ?‘V ' yf ^ &gt; J. E. KHEDOUKI IMPORT &amp; EXPORT TELE ADDRESS KHKDOUfU-BAHRAl '4 TBLRPHONE. 83 »M CODES USEDj- BKMLEYS ACME &amp; ORIENTAL BANKERS: THE BASTE RN BANK LTD* Ref, ino. 91» H.B.M’s Political Agent, Bahrain. &lt;£. /' / ( Persian - Gulf ) Pahra:‘n Receipt 6 j} ate / . /^ r Dear Sir, We shall be very grateful if you will kindly recommend for us shipping space assistance for the following goods.- 1. Name of the importer. •• J.D. Ahedouri, Bahrain. 2. Name and address of the agent or.. Iklessrs. Arthur Lvans &amp; Co. Lto manufacturer from whom he v/ishes Westminster Bank Chambers, to arrange supply. Bishop’s Stortford, Herts, Bngland. 3. pull description of the goods •• 24 pieces Woollen Suitings, required. 4. Approxim te weight of goods .. 10 c.w.t. in long tons. 5 . Bxact use or purpose contemplated , for the goods to be imported. ) To meet local demanas. 6 . Special reason justifying.- ) (aj Supply of goods wanted. ) (b) Their import from the country suggested rather than from any other country. Available from Lngland. Cable and airgraph of acceptance attached. 7. Description of the urgency with .. As soon as possible, which the goods are required and the latest date which will be suitable. shanking you in advance for your assistance, Yours faithfully,■No. 3^^5-36/43 Po3.itical Agency, Bahrain, The November, 1944» To The Director of Customs, Bahrain. Reference Mr. J.B. Khedouri ! s application dated 30th October, 1944 to import 24 pieces woollen suitings from Messrs. Arthur Bvans &amp; Co., Ltd., England. 2 . It is requested that 10 cwts. allocated by you to Mr. J.E. Khedouri *under woollen goods' may be cancelled as the order has not yet been accepted by the exporters. for Political Agent, Bahrain.4. * \ ! .J, r7«/ dia ^flWpttNMENT OF INDIA. s' Departn ^ 1 1 EXPRESS LETTER JV.' B.—This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by postNo save 'telegrapliic expense and undue use of the ivires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and shmed as if it had been so despatched. ° k 0, 2420-79/175-V. Dated Bushire, ^ ie 28th Octo^ber,19^ To FOBEIGN, NElfi? DELHI Reference marginally noted correspondence £rom 1. Memorandum No. 2836-36/43 dated 10-10-^44. j Political 2. ^eEPrandum No. 2859-56/43 dated 10-10-'44.0 Agent, Bahrain. Goods required from the United Kingdom. Ii 2. I recommend import assistance.u h (Jahrate .aovjp tNMENX OF INDIA. kM^AlOS * •' V. / EXPRESS LETTER N. B This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched. No. 2419-7S/175-V. Dated Xushire To the o &amp; 6 fcLL 0 ctio'bbr &gt; 194 4 $ i'&amp;terirtxcQ iLaflorandLim Ho. &amp;B37-56/4S, dated the lC«h Octobor ? 1944 f copy seiiu te you direct, ^ewing triroaa aud i.BOXUiifc. skeins (for ee&amp;uroldery) for Bahrain. 2 . I recoiameni isporh assistance. -B R I f CONSUL- r iUe issue of Uie above has Been authorised. to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, * s. 6 . ■' 0 O py to the Politioal Agent. _ MPP—275 S&amp;P—6768—(M-676)—27-7-43—1,000,000.J. E. KHEDOUKI IMPORT &amp; EXPORT TILE ADDRESS KHEDOURJ-BAHRAl m TBLRPHONE. 83 -M CODES USEDJ- BEMLEYS ACME &amp; ORIENTAL / BANKERS: THE EASTLRN BANK LTD* Reference No. 98. H.B.M*s Political Agent, ( Persian - Gulf ) , s2 „ Bahrain. Dear Sir, We beg to invite a reference to your letter No.2266-36/43 of the 9th August 1944 to The non'ble The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, recommending shipping space assistance on our behalf for exporting Cotton Piecegoods and Woollen Piecegoods from the United Kingdom. Mr. J.M. Shasha, Manchester, with whom the order for these goods was placed by us, has advised us by telegram that the recommenda tion has not yet reached the India Office in London. We shall be extremely grateful therefore if you can assist us in any way possible with a view to enable the recommendation to reach the India uffice as early as possible. Your assistance will be greatly appreciated, as the goods in question, mostly requisitioned for the winter season, have been paid for, packed ready, and awaiting shipment for a considerable period for lack of the shipping space recommendation. Thanking you in anticipation, Yours faithfully,H. B. k’s. Political Agents Bahrain, Dear Sir, I shall feel obliged if you will kindly grant Iiuport Assistance recorricendation for the following goods ordered by us. The Director of Customs Recommendation together with the suppliers' letter ad copy of my order is enclosed, I) IMPORTER : liahmo^d Abbas Akbar EPBORPERS: Sassoon I. Setty, Sons &amp; Co., Ltd., London 111) DESCR1P T 1UK OP GOODS : IOC Doz. Neckties. 1V ) APPROXIMATE WEIGHT: 62 lbs. gross V) - - VI) - - VII) The goods are required to be imported as soon as possible. Yours faithfully, LAHkCCD ABBAS AKBAR36/43. Political Agency, Bahrain, The November» 1944* To M Tan Uon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf f Bushire. Memorandusa o Hr. kahmood Abbas Akbar* Bahrain» has applied to me for assistance in exporting 100 dozen neckties from the United Kingdom. 2. I recommend that assistance may be granted out of the allotment for January/Juue 1945 under heading sundries and enclose the usual details. The order has been placed and accepted. Bahrain, for information with reference to his letter dated 1st November, 1944. % for Political Agent, Bahrain. 3A30 Copy forwarded to Mr. Mahmood Abbas Akbar,§ §tails in rcgand to goods ossontially required from the United King- om, United States of America or Canada by the Arab States in tho Persian Gulf* 1. Name of would be importer. 2# Name and address of the agent or manufacturer in the export ing country from whom ho wishes to arrange supply. 3. Full description of the goods required. 4. Approximate weight in long tons of 2240 lbs* Ur* ^ahaoed Abb&amp;s BiJirain* Messrs* Sassoon X* Setty* Bon &lt;5: Co M 83, Mark Lux o, bondon, c«*C*3* 100 dosen necktios* 62 lbs* 5. 6 . Exact use or purpose contemplated for tho goods to bo Imported. For aale t0 tho pubUo. Special reasons justifying; (a) Supply of goods wanted. (b) Their import from the country suggested rather than from ■ b* any other country. . Description of the urgency with which the goods are required and tho latest date which will be suitable. Bahrain stocks exhausted* Not available fron elsewhere. As sson as possible*4 J. E. K H E D O ' U R I Import, Export &amp; Commission Agent Tele.-Address: Khedouri - Bahrain Codes used: Bentley’s Acme &amp; Oriental Bankers: The Eastern Bank Ltd. B A H R A I N. 9Ul ° Ve;riber 1944 Bahrain*ftece^t f AH LICATiuN dUR oHIH ING Gi AGji Ref. \iO,9b H.B.h’a Political ..gent. Bakrain. Dear Sir: We would request you to recommend to the higher authority to allow shipping space for the under mentioned ordered goods. 1. Name of would be importer:- J*5.Khedouri. , ahrain. b. Name and address of the agent)Ressrs J.l .Shasha. or manufacturer in the expor-)82 Princess Street ting country from whom he )Manchester.England, wishes to arrange supply ) 5. Pull description of the goods) 7 Tons Cotton liecegoods. required ) 2 Ton s woollen liecegoods. 9 Tons 4. Approximate weight in long ton) 9 Tons, of 2240 Lbs ) 5. Exact use or purpose contemplated) For consumption at Bahrain, for the goods to be imported ) b. Special reason justifying:- (a) Supply of goods wanted:- To meet local demands. (b) Their import from the country )Aavailable from England, suggested rather than from any)order has been accepted as otner country )per the suppliers cable of the bth Nov.1944 attached herewith. /. uescriition of the urgency with which) -or shipment during the goods are required and the latest) &lt; anuary/June 1945. date which will be suitable )j. e: k h e d o u r i Iniport, Export &amp; Commission Agent j9 Tele.-Address: Khedouri - Bahrain Codes used: Bentley’s Acme &amp; Oriental _ Banhers: The Eastern Bank Ltd. hefere nee N o • XJfc .99. H.b.iv^s toll tic al Agent, Bahrain. Dear Sir, © We shall he grateful if you will kindly recommend fdr us shipping space assistance for the following goods from the United Kingdom.- 1. Name of would be importer. J.E. Khedouri, Bahrain. B. Name and address of tne agent .. Messrs. General trade and Chemical or manufacturer in the exporting country from whom he wisnes to arrange supply. 3. Pull description of tne goods required. 4. Approximate weight of the goods.. in long tons. 5. Bxact use or purpose contemplated for the t^oods to be imported. b. Special reason justifying.- (a) Supply of goods wanted.- (b) Their B port from the country suggested ratner than from any other country. 7. Description of the urgency with . which the goods are require* and the latest date suitable. «e shall be greatly obliged if you can arrange to forward your recommendation to India Office in London by the quickest meanS/possible by cable or otherwise to enable the goods to arrive in time lor the winter season. We are prepared to meet the cost of all tel&lt; giams in this connection. Thanking you in anticipation. Yours faithfully, ^ / ^ ? p ioS 'Pr'-tor of (hi* Exports Company Limited, 110 CannonStreet, London, E.O. 4. Woollen and Fibro Sutings, Mixed. 92 pieces. 92 pieces weighing 3 tons cwts. ) ) To meet local demands. ) )) Available from England. Two cables dated 8th November from the firm accepting our ordei are enclosed. As expeditiously as possible. rJ..E. KHEDOURI Import, Export &amp; Commission Agent Tele.-Address: Khedouri - Bahrain Codes used: Bentley's Acme &amp; Oriental Bankers: The Eastern Bank Ltd. H.b.M’s 1-olitical Agent, Bahr ain. Dear sir. BAHRAIN, (Arabia) reference Wo. 101. 0 /7 Vie snail Be very grateful if you will kindly recormnpnd for us snipping space assistance for the following goods from the United Kingdom.- 1. Name of would be importer. .. J.Ei. Khed.uri, Bahrain. 2. Name and address of the agent.. Messrs. Arthur E. Evans &amp; Go. Ltd., or manufacturer in the exporting vvestminster Bank Ghamoers, country from whom he wishes to Bishop's Stortfora, arrange supply. Herts, England. 3. Full description of tne goods required. 12 pieces Woollen Suitings. 4• Approximate weight in long „„ 7 c.w.t. tons of 2240 lbs. 5. Exact use or purpose contemplated ) for the goods to be ii ported. 6. Special reason justifying.- (a) Supply of goods wanted. ) ) ) To meet local demands. available from England. Our order has been accepted by the firm whose cable sand airgraph are enclosed. As expeditiously ps possible. (b) Their import from the country suggested rather than from any other country. 7. Description of the urgency with which tne goods are required and the’ latest date which w ill be suitable. We shall be greatly obliged if you will kindly forward your recommendation to the India Oflice in London, il possible by cable, to enable the goods to arrive in Bahrain before the summer season.^ We are prepared to meet the cost of all your cables in tnis connection. Thanking you for tne assistance in anticipation. Yours faithfully.3** as**- Ko. 3^,7 ?€/43. To Political Agency t Bahrain, The JZc&gt;k November, 1944* The Hon , ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, BushIre* A t p D Meaor-.ndmi. Mr# J#S. Khedouri, Bahrain has applied to me Toi assistance in exporting woollen and fibro suitings from the United Kingdom# 2* I recommend that assistance ;ay be granted out of the allotment for January/June 1945 under headirig woollen goods and enclose the usual details. The order has been placed and accepted# Copy forwarded to the Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Department, flew Delhi# No. 3&lt;,6f Copy forwarded to Mr. J.E. Khedouri, Bahrain for information with reference to his letter H dated 10th November, 194- -•I Qgtails ^ in regal’d to goods crasontially required from the United King dom, United States of America or Canada by the Arab Statoa- in tha- Persian Gulf. — ■■ m* mm !• Name of v;ould be importer. Mr# J#.-. Khed^uri. ahrain. 2. Name and address of the agent or manufacturer in*the export ing country from whom ho wishes to arrange supply. 3. Full description of the goods required. 4. Approximate weight in long tons of 2240 lbs. 5. Exact use or purpose contemplated for the goods to be imported. 6 . Special reasons justifying: (a) Supply of goods wanted. (b) Their import from the country suggested rather than from any other ccuntry. . 7. Description of the urgency with which the goods are required and the latest date which will be suitable. Messrs* General Tr«.de Sr. Chemical wx; orts Co*&gt; Ltd.? 110 Cannon Streot» London) L.C. 4« . Woollen 4 flbro suiting* 92 piece*• 3 tons 11 Cw t&gt; ;i * For sale to the public# a# Bahrain stock* exhausted# b# Not available from elsewhere# As soon as possible#) A Ho* - 36/43. Political Agency, Bahrain, The ZQjfc Hovember, 1944* To The Hon’ble the oolitical Resident in the Persian Gulf, Sushire. / ^ Ur. J.S. Khedouri, Bahrain has applied to me for assistance in exoortiiig cotton and woollen piece-goods from the Uhited Kingdom. 2 . I recomaend that assistance may be granted out of the allotment for January/Juno 1945 under heading cotton piece-goods and enclose the usual details. The order has been placed and accepted. Ir tor Political Agent, Bahrain. No. 3&lt;f7f ^ ^ Copy forwarded to the Secretary to the Government of India in th4 .External Affairs Depart ment, New Delhi. No. 3^71 . Copy forwarded to Mr. J.iS. Khedouri, Bahrain with reference to his letter dated 9th November, 1944.+ t0 g 0o &lt;ls essentially required from the United King, dom, United States of America or Canada by the Arab States in the Persian Gulf. !• Name of would bo importer. 2. Name and address of the agent or manufacturer in the export ing country from whom ho wishes to arrange supply. 3. Full description of the goods required. 4. Approximate weight in long tons of 2240 lbs. 5. Exact use or purpose contemplated for the goods to bo imported. 6. Special reasons justifying: (a) Supply of goods wanted. (b) Their import from the country suggested rather than from any other country. 7. Description of the urgency with which the goods are required and the latest date which will be suitable• Mr* Khedourif Bahrain* ioissrs* Shasha y 32 Princess Street* launches ter* England* 7 Tons cotton piece-goods* 2 Tons woollen piece-goods* 9 Tons* For sale to the ^blic* s* Bahrain stocks exhausted* b* Not available froia elsewhere* As soon as possible*Political Agency, Bahrain, The November, 1944* No. 3- 36 / 43 . To The Hon’ble the Political Besident In the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Meaoraiidua . / '!&gt;'*'. itr. J Khedouri, Bahrain, has applied to me for assistance in exporting 12 pieces woollen suitings from the United Kingdom* 2 * I recommend that assistance riay be granted out of the allotment for January/June 1945 under heading woollen goods and enclose the usual detailisc The order has been placed and accepted* CP - No. ' v &lt;r for Political Agent, Bahrain* Copy forwarded to the Secretary to the Government of India in the bixternai Affairs Depart ment, New Delhi* ^ No. itf-lS'- 1 Copy forwarded to Mr* Khedouri, j Bahrain for information with reference to his letter dated 13th November, 1944*! n^tails in regard to goods'credentially roquircd from the United King dom, Jnitcd Stac.es of America or Canada by the Arab State#- in the- Persian Gulf. I 1. Name of would be importer. 2. Name and address of the agent or manufacturer in the export ing country from whom he wishes to arrange supply. 3. Full description of the goods required. 4. Approximate weight in long tons of 2240 lbs. 5. Exact use or purpose contemplated for the goods to be imported. 6 . Special reasons Justifying; (a) Supply of goods wanted. (b) Their import from the country suggested racher than from any other country. . 7. Description of the urgency with Which the goods are required and the latest date which will - be suitable. Khedouri, Bahrain. Messrs. Arthur £. Evans &amp; Co. Ltd., Westminster Bank Chambers, Bishop’s Stortford, Herts, England. 12 pieces woollen suitings. 7 Cwts. For sale to the public. a. Bahrain stocks exhausted. b. Not available from elsewhere. As soon as possible.i Printed ia England. Sept. 1941 (4,100. pads. I CABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED. (incorporated in enolano.) 5/-16I y The first line of this Telegram contains the following particulars in the order named Prefix Letters and Number of Message, Office of Origin, Number of Words, Date, Time handed in and Official instructions—if any. Clerk’s Time Circuit. &gt; Name. Received. /~N MHjlj. 0130 107 1 ,4 'i i ,7.4S ASV4/C GLASGOW AT21 = Ho. NLT MAJOR T HICKINBOTHAM THE AGENCY BAHREIN = WE HAVE FOUR BALES ARAB YASHMAGHS FOR ABDUL AZIZ ALI BASSAM READY FOR SHIPMENT STOP INDIA OFFICE AWAITING YOUR RECOMMENDATION STOP WILL SUPPLY ALI BASSAM WITH REGULAR SHIPMENTS OF TWO BALES EACH MONTH IF RECOMMENDATIONS GRANTED = JOHN LEAN AND SON LTD GLASGOW MARK YOUR REPLY Sm/ie^uaC ANY ENQUIRY RESPECTING THIS TELEGRAM SHOULD BE ACCOMPANIED BY THIS FORM AND MAY BE MADE AT ANY OF THE COMPANY’S OFFICES.* • A- Telegram G.T.tfT From Political, Bahrain. M _ 4.0 Brit consul, Busliire Repeated Foreign, Naw Delhi. No. I&lt;f0 Dated 28th November 1944. jJy telegram 211 March 23rd. ; ,, / 2 ‘ John Lean and Sons Glas/gow have Informed me that they have four bales ready for shipment and that India office are awaiting export recommendation. They state further that they can supply regular shipments of two bales a month. would seem that Board of Trade have overcome their reluctance to make cotton / available (India Office telegram 3357 Fabruar; 1 3th)refers) and as these articles are now badly needed here I request that India Office^tsked telegraphically to permit export.( { n^ J. E. KHEDOURI Import, Export &amp; Commission Agent Tele.-Address: Khedouri - Bahrain 3o r BAHRAIN, 19th Novr &gt;1944 . (Arabia) Codes used: Bentley’s Acme &amp; Oriental Reference No»102« Ba nkers: The Eastern Bank Ltd. H.B.M’s Political Agent, Bahrain. Dear Sir, Bahrain Lecepi . // l /fa* •OO We shall he grateful if you will kindly recommend shipping space assistance for us in respect ol the following goods from the United Kingdom.- 1. Name of would he importer .. J.B. Khedouri, Bahrain. 2. Name and address of the agent or manufacturer in the exporting country from whom he wisxhes to arrange supply. Manufacturers.- Messrs.J.Clay of Bradford, c/o Messrs.General Trade 8c Chemical Exports Co.Ltd., 110 Cannon St., London, E.C.4. 5.Pull description of th* goods.. Worsted Woollen Yarn. required* 4* Approximate weight in long tons of 2240 Ihs* 5. Exact use or purpose con templated for the goods to he imported.- 6. Special reason justifying (a) Supply of goods wanted. . . 550 Its. ^ Co.*-; 2. *'•** • ) ) ) To meet local demands. ) ) (h) Their import from the country suggested rather than from any other country. 7. Description of the urgency with vnich the ^oods are re- .. quired and the latest date which will he suitable. Thanking you. / A. i'~t' &lt;• ' t A*, f f \ t •r' ( ' f • H ^ , II. Available from England* Suppliers cable of acceptance dated 14th inst. attached. as soon as possible* Yours faithfully, * / &lt;*■ &gt; / v- S'! i* A*-;. Binct+r of (* v*. &amp; and Puri Off’ PA P KJ fLs^- \nJ. E. - K H E D O U R Import, Export &amp; Commission Agent Tele.-Address: Khedouri - Bahrain \ {\ A Vl Codes used: Bentley’s Acme &amp; Oriental ' yf ’ Bankers: The Eastern Bank Ltd. H.B.M’s lolitical -tigent, Bahrain. Dear Sir, BAHRAIN, (Arabia) 21st November 1944. Reference No._104• s RaliFain ReceiDf * oJ -Z ■&gt;**. We shall be grateful if you will kindly recommend for us shipping space assistance in respect of the following goods from the United Kingdom.- 1. Name of would be importer. 2. Name and address of the agent or manufacturer in the exporting country from whom he wishes to arrange supply. 5. Full description of the goods required. J.E• Khedouri, Bahrain. Messrs. David Pike, c/o Ebor-dale Fabrics(iixi ort)Ltd. Ebor Mills, Bingley, Yorks, England, woollen Suitings for Ladies. 4. Approximate weight in long tons.. 5. Exact use or purpose contemplated for tne O oods to be imported. 6. Special reason justifying (a) Supply of goods wanted. (b) The r ii port from the country suggested rather tnan from any other country. 7. Description oi the urgency with wnich the goods are required and .. the latest date which will be suitable• 3 c. w. i - 1 . ) ) ) To meet local demands. ) ) Available from England. Telegraphic offer of 17th &amp; our acceptance of 20th inst. enclosed. As soon as possible. Thanking you for your kind assistance, in anticipation.@ Telegram From To No, Dated Bahrain Receipt G.T.C. Foreign, Nev/ Delhi. Political, Bahrain. 1931 ME. ' . 30th November and received 1st December, 1944. U- ’9t) No Your telegram 790 November 23th. \ Reference not traceable. * Please receat. r3n Telegram From To No. la ted G.T.C. « Political Agent, Bahrain Foreign, New Delhi. S 02 3rd December'1944. 3| 1 \ Your telegram 1931 l\ffi November 30tli. 2. My tdegra March 23rd was not repeated to you. It cancelled the reccommendation made in my memorandum 637 of 8 th March which I now desire to renew. -POLITICAL- mo .vb Political Agency| Bahrain, The 3rd December, 1944* &amp; The Hon f ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire* Meaorandum* Mr. J.iS. Khedouri, Bahrain, has applied to me for assistance in exporting worsted woollen yam from the United Kingdom. 2m I recommend that assistance may be granted out of the allotment for January/June 1945 under heading cotton piece-goods and enclose the usual details. The order has been placed and accepted. No.3593-36/43. To 0 for Political Agent, Bahrain. Copy forwarded to the Secretary to the Governujent of India in the External AffAirs Department, New Delhi. N ’ / . Copy forwarded to Mr. J.iS. Khedouri, Bahrain, for information with reference to his letter No. 102 dated 19th November, 1944. 1I orrf Tin i t orl r =:+ n o to „S0°d3 osaontiaiXy required from the United King- lom, Jmted Sta.es of America or Canada by the Arab States in the Persian GuXf. 1® Name of would be importer* 2. Name and address of the agent or manufacturer in the export ing country from whom he wishes to arrange supply. 3. Full description of the goods required. 4. Approximate weight in long tons of 2240 lbs. . * 5. Exact use or purooso contemplated for the goods to^bo imported. 6 . Special reasons /justifying; (a) Supply_of goods wanted. (b) Their import from the country suggested rather than from any other country. . 7. Description of the urgency with which the goods arc required and the latest date which will • be suitable. Mr* Khedouri, Bahrain. Hessr»* General Trade A Chemical Exports Co* f Ltd*, 110 Cannon street London, i£*C* 4* Worsted woollen yarn. 4 Cwts. and 2 lbs* For sale to the public* a* Bahrain stocks exhausted, b. Not available from elsewhere* As soon as possible*No.3694-36/43 Politic&amp;l Agency, Bahrain, 3rd December, 1944. To The Hon^la the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire* Memorandum. Mr. J.iS. Khedouri, Bahrain, has applied to me for assistance in exporting woollen suitings for ladies from the United Kingdom. 2 . I recommend that assistance may be granted out of the allotment for January/June 1946 under heading cotton piece-goods and enclose the usual details. The order has been placed and accepted. Copy forwarded to the Secretary to the Govern .ent of India in the External Affairs Department, New Delhi. ^ Copy forwarded to Mr. J.E. Khedouri, Bahrain for information with reference to his letter No.104 dated 21st November, 1944. for Political Agent, Bahrain. 0 *^QQtails in regal’d to goods essentially required from the United King dom, United States of America or Canada by the Arab States in the ^ Persian Gulf. !• Name of would be importer. 2. Name and address of the agent or manufacturer in the export ing country from whom ho wishes to arrange supply. 3. Full description of the goods required. 4. Approximate weight in long tons of 2240 lbs. i Ur* J#i£. Khedouri, Bahrain. Messrs. David Pike, C/o JSbordale Fabrics Clxport) Ltd., Bbor Mills, Blagley, Yorks, England.. Woolen suitings for ladies. 3 cwts. 5. Exact use or purpose contemplated for the goods to bo imported. 6 . Special reasons justifying: (a) Supply of goods wanted. (b) Their import from the country - x suggested rather than from any other country. 7. Description of the urgency with which the goods are required and the latest date which will be suitable. For sale to ths public. a. Bahrain stocks exhausted. b. Not available from elsewhere. # As soon as possible.i in England. Sept. 1942. (4,100. pads, f CABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED (INCORPORATED IN ENOLANO.) V-.&lt;M The first line of this Telegram contains the following particulars in the order n Prefix Letter* and Number of Message. Office otOcilin^ MflaibcUbi&gt;lN»fde&gt;fcate. Time ha Official instructions-if any. n^Uraiir I\cCCipiT Clerk’s Time Circuit. Name. Received. MHjwl 02-10 r * 081) Datfi . 13 OUR PRINCIPALS JOHN LEAN OF GLASGOW ONLY MANUFACTURERS OF ARAB SHAWLS YASMAG HA 1 QV188/C DF BOMBAY 51/50 2 QD KR ANTEN = LC POLITICAL AGENT BAHREIN= _ ' tr fourV^ BALES READY FOR SHIP FURTHER SIX BALES READYAj^ o' 1 ' WITHIN FEW WEEKS BOTH AGAINST ORDERS OF 3 K* ABDULAZIZ ALI BASSAM STOP REQUEST EXPEDITE RECOMMENDATION To INDIA OFFICE AS EXPORT LICENCE EXPIRING ELEVENTH JANUARY = MARK YOUR REPLY - L L L rtU . S ANY ENQUIRY RESPECTING THIS TELEGRAM SHOULO BE ACCOMPANIED BY THIS FORM AND MAY BE MADE AT ANY OF THE COMPANY’S OFFICES.'■ J. E. KHEDOURI Import, Export &amp; Commission Agent Tele.-Address: Khedouri - Bahrain Codes used: Bentley’s Acme &amp; Oriental 3/7 (hoN BAHRAIN, 23rd iNovemoer 1^ 44 (Arabia) Bankers: The Eastern Bank Ltd. Ref.No,107 H.i3.M*s Political Agent. Bahrain. p-Wain *&lt;.!&gt;' ku Lear Sir: 1 shall be glad if you kinaly recommend for me shipping space assistance for the following:- Name ana address of would be exporter: J.L.Khedouri. .Bahrain. Name and address of the agent or ) Messrs General Trade &amp; 1 . 2 . 4. 6 . 7. manufacturer in the exporting ) country from whom he wishes to \ arrange supply ) Chemical Lxports 110 Cannon Street London L.C.4 CO. f ±jtr&amp;i 3. Full description of the goods ) 200 Gross Anchor Stranded required ) cotton thread. 500 Gross anchor cotton Embroidery white olack ana colours threaa. Approximate weight in long ton) Approximate gross weight of 2240 Lbs ) 2700 Los. 5. Exact use or purpose contemplated) To meet local demana. for the goods to be imported ) Special reason justifying:- (a) Special reason justifying:- For embroidering works etc. (b) Their demand from the country) This particular brand of suggested rather than from ) threaa is availaole only any other country ) from England. (Oraer has been accepted as ... ^ Der +1 supP liers cable of 2uth Nov.herewith Inscription of the urgency tfitffP'*' As soon as possiole . ' which the goods are required ) and the latest date which will ) be suitable )322 _ YUSUF HASAN L H A S A N Senera! merchant Bahrain, December 3, 194-4. ,19 His Britannic Majesty’s Political A 0 ent, /_ Bahrain. ' \XAr- Uir, Export of Cotton Bretonne i«et (sample attached ) from England . enclose herewith an order ^recommended by the Director of Customs and Port Officer, -Bahrain), placed by me to Messrs. Biddle, Sawyer 3c Co., Ltd., London, and a letter from them, which proves that my order is accepted in the United Kingdom and that the goods can be exported. You are request-ed, therefore, to kindly grant me your valuable recommendation, in order that the abovementioned firm can export the goods. y ^ -r ^ &lt;f OL Ct^u ^ s While the shipping space/a&amp;3^W=m&lt;**e, 1 with to have 4,000yards, approximate weight of which is 200 lbs. In the meantime, I enclose herewith particulars required by your honour in this regard. Yours respectfully, for YUSUP HASiiN ALHaSaIm Enel 1. Order dated 2.12.44. 2 . fetter dated 25 . 10.44 3. Sample of the cloth. 4. Particulars.S&gt; 3'? U«&gt;L- TELE. A DD; *' yastzfalhasan' U~* YUSUF HASAN ALHASAN General Merchant BAHRAIN Vonr re/. Our re/. P. Gulf Code need.-. BENTLEY'S &amp; PRIVATE Bankert: THE EASTERN BANK LTD., BAHRAIN \ December 2, 1944. Messrs. Biddle, Sawyer cc Go., Ltd., Empire House, St. Martin f s le Grand, London, E.c.l. Dear Sirs, w’ith reference to your letter dated 29th October 1944, we have pleasure in placing an orier for: 2,000 yards Cotton Bretonne Net, Quality 195T, y&amp; inches width, Different Colours, White and Black required more. Thanking you in anticipation, Yours faithfully, ^or YU So i? hIKaS^NNo. $1UU '36/43. To Political Agency, Bahrain, The )! Becfe/uber, 1944. Tie Hon v ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Hr. J.v-. IC^louri, Bahrain, has ao-died to n.e for in exporting cotton thread from t h- United K.inudon. 2, X recommend tin t esijl stance tuy be granted out oi the fellotfient for J-fiiiary/vmc 19--5 under headij:g cotton piece-good &amp; and enc lose the usual details* ~ Tne order tus been placed and acconted. sM*^. Copy f&gt;rwari*d to the Secretary to th* Cavern .ont^ of India in the External /JTairs Bepartaient, Now Delhi. \ Copy forwarded to Mr. J.^* Khedburi, Bahrain for information with reference to his letter dated 23rd November, 1944. _I I I . ft § 0 tails in rega \1 to goods essentially required from the United King- om, vnited Sta &gt;os of America or Canada by the Arab States in the Persian Gulf. 1. Name o'.’ would be importer. Mr. J.K. Khadouri,-Bahrain. 2. Name a. id address of the agent or manufacturer :_n the export ing country from whom he wishes to arrange supply. 3. Full description of.the goods requir od. Messrs. General Trade &amp; Chemical Exports Co., Ltd., 110 Cannon Street, London E.C.4. 200 gross anchor stranded cotton thread. 500 M anchor cotton embroidery thread. 4. Approx mate weight in long tons of 22 / '^) lbs. 5. Exact use or pur, oso contemplated for the goods to* be imported. 6 . Spociui reasons justifying: (a) Supply of goods wanted. (b) Their import from the country suggested rr. eher than from any ether country. 7. Description of the urgency with which the goods are required and the latest date which wil n be suitable. 1 ton. For sale to the public. a. Bahrain stocks exhausted. b. Not available from elsewhere. As soon as possible.2 , 20 - No. S'Y /fS- 36/43 Political Agency, Bahrain, The 11th December, 1944* To © The Hobble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire* damoranduia. Mr* Yusuf Hasan Alhasan, Bahrain, has applied to me for assistance in exporting 2000 yards of cotton bretonne net from the United Kingdom* 2* I reconLiend that assistance may be grantee out of the allotment for January/June 1945 under heading cotton piece-goods and enclose the usual details* The order has been placed and accepted. Copy forwarded to the Secretary to the Government of India in the Axtemal Affairs Department, New Delhi* n o |v Alhasan, Bahrain for information with reference to his letter dated 2nd December, 1944. for Political Agent, Bahrain* Copy forwarded to Mr. Yusuf Hasans » («v 2 3 » I in r cge : u to goods cssontially required from tho United King dom, United Stfi c.es of America or Canada by the Arab States in tho Persian Gulf. 1. 2 . 3. 4. 5. 6. Name or* would bo importer. MrPJuauf Hasan Alhasan f Bahrain. Name and address of tho agent Messrs. Biddle, f 1 or manufacturer n the export- empire House, ot. Martin s , 7. ing. country from whom he wishes to arrange supply. Full description of the goods required - Approximate weight in long tons of 2240 lbs. Exact use or purpose contemplated for tho goods to oe imported. Special r easons ; ustiffing: (a) Supply of goods wanted. (b) Their import from the country suggested r? thor than from any other country. Description of tho urgency with which the goods are required and the latest date which will bo suitable. London, j£.C.1. 2000 yards cotton bretonne not. 2 Cwts. For sale to the public. a. Bahrain stocks exhausted. b. Not available from elsewhere. As soon as possible.* i A d 3^ a *' I ‘ C ‘ S9 ^?-.tL..v M ■^ritconsul, Bushire. Political, Bahrein. A/1967. (I * L'*\ Telegram From To No. Dated 12th received 34 oh December, 1944 L3o“| Your telegram 790 November 28th Are these red Shawls for re-export to Saudi Arabia or Shawls of different si colours for Bahrein populace. - ^ritconsul- 0^ CAVw NmJ 3* Telegram From To ro. Dated Political Agent, Bahrain. Britconsul, Bushire. 841 17th December 1944. ^2 l ! Your telegram A/ldjfe? 12th December. 2. These are red shawls but will be worn t by Bahrain populace in default of anything else -POLITICAL- alo.Tele^ram From To No. Dated (g, -.t'.g. x»~M0. 8 /ULJbiM#* Britconsul, ^uohire. Political Agent, Bahrain. a/1980 15th received 16th December 1944. 'bh &lt;^c Your memorandum 3470-3^/43 dated rovember 20tl 2. I am recommending 7 tons cotton piece-goods under heading cotton piecegoods. 3 . I am not recommending 2 tons woollen piece- goods which cannot be classified under heading cotton piecegoods and as your woollen quota is already completed.Te legram From Ho. Dated Bahrai Xo^Sli) am Receipt •Date Dritconsul, Bushire. Political Agent, Bahrain. A/1981 and received l6th December 1944. 3.6 C / Your memorandum Ho. 3473-36/43 dated Hovembcr 20tli. 2. I am not recommending as your woollen * , goods quota is already used up. -3RITC 0H.3UL- AT TO •No.cSSAo- 36/43. Political Agency, Bahrain, The 17th December, 1944. To The Director of Customs, Bahrain. Memorandiiiu I shall be grateful if you will send me a statement of allocation of shipping space made from the United Kingdom under the head M Woollen goods” for the f*rst half of 1945.J. E. KHEDOURI Import, Export &amp; Commission Agent BAHRAIN, 1 ' : - t - (Arabia) December 194b. Tele.-Address: Khedouri - Bahrain Codes used: Bentley’s Acme &amp; Oriental Bankers: The Eastern Bank Ltd. Keference No fi. b. 1 3 1 o 111 1 c 8 1 Baurain. Dear Sir, . 112 . /v \ke shall be grateful if you will kindly recommend shipping space assistance for us in respect of the folloving goods from the United Kin 6 om.- 1 . Name of would be importer .. J.li.. Khedouri, banrain. 2. Name of s^ent or manufacturer .. The Central Agency Ltd., from whom he wishes to arrange supply. b. Full description of tie ^oods •• required. 4. Approximate weight of the goods in long tons. 5 . jixact use or purpose contemplated for trie &amp; oods to be imported. ) o. Special reason justiTying.- (a) Supply of goods wanted. ) 50, bothwell Street, Glasgow, Scotland. 4 cases Cotton Thread.(IbO gross.) 1,170 lbs.gross weight (net weight 3bb lbs.) To meet local demands. fb) . Their* import from tne country The firm’s cabled acceptance suggested rather tnan from any dated 7th instant attached, other country. 7. Description of the urgency with .. As soon as possible, which the goods are required and tne latest date which v ill be suitable. Thanking you in anticipation for your assistance.Tue iion'fcltf fcU&amp; Political resident In the Persian Gulf, Bush!re* Mr. J.&amp;* Kbed^urit ;r4»iu&gt; i^as applied • to for assistance In exporting cotton thread from the Uni tea Kingdoa* 2* I reo^c%^eno that aa^lstaiK;© -ia/ be granted out of the mXlfitssMkt for JenuarT/Vun^ 1946 under cotton pio* '■“■' &gt;ode aiiti enclose the uruu! detaila* X&gt;ic ortlci* has teen placed .&lt;na acce )ted« Copy for^a^aed to tue ^creUary to the iiovtfjm&amp;ant of India in the external Affairs oepartnenti New p«lhi* Copy to: The Direct iSj Bahrain. Mr. J.ni. Khedouri, Bahrain. for Political Agent, Bahrain*No. Political Agency, Bahrain, The 27th December, 1944• To The Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushlre. Memorandum* Reference your telegrams Nos. V1973 and A/1981 dated 16th December, 1944. 2. Bahrain has been allotted 5 tons under woollen goods for the first half of 1945 from the United Kingdom, vide Residency endorsement No.637-S dated 27th Jun§| 1944. 3« ‘ Recommendations already made for imports under this head from the United Kingdom are, according to our records:- Date* 25th Sept. 1944 28 th Oct. 1944 20th Nov. 1944 do. Reference. Memo No.2717-36/43 ' 3052-36/43 ' 3467-36/43 ' 3473-36/43 Total. lej&amp;hJte Tons. Cwts. 3 4 3 11 7 Tons 4 - 5 cwts. 4. Kindly confirm, if you are in agreement, that 15 cwts. of Bahrain’s quota of woollen goods has not yet been recommended. P 'll U* for Political Agent, Bahrain.Telegram G.T.C. From Britconsul, Bushire To Political, Bahrain. No.- A/ 2049. • ^ated 26th received 27th December v 1944. Your memoranda Do.^593-36/43 *nd No. 3694-36/43 dated December 3rd, , I cannot recoiTHiendr woolen goods under cotton piece goods. Your woolen piece goods quota has already been completed. - -oritconsulTelegram From To Political Agent, Bahrain. Britconsul, Bushire. 28th December 1944. 1 Your telegrams a/1979 December 16th &amp; A/&gt;d043 December 26th. 2 . My woollen quota was five tons for firs_t hall 1945. My recommendations up to ^November 20th amounted ^ to 4 tons 5 cwt. see my memos. 2717,3052, 3467, and 3473 thus my balance should be 15 cwt. therefore request my recommendations 3593 and 3594 be made under woollen • goods and not cotton piecegoods as originally requestea. 3 . Request following amendment be made in quota to meet further demands under woollen goods under 'necessary £or 'cotton piecegoods 50 tons' read 'cotton piecegoods 45 tons' and add new head 'Woollen goods 5 tons'. Your telegram No.1500 dated June 26th refers. No. SU Dated -POLITICAL- A-V- A. -4GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. Department; EXPRESS LETTER JV. B. Tins is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save tclegrapln'c expense and undue use of tlie wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if if had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched. ° 79/m. Dated Bushire, t!ic 15th Bocsater, 19 ** (io^j Refarenca maaorandum No. 3429-36/43, dated the 19th Noveiaber, 1944, £rom Political Agent, Bahrain, copy sent to you direct. Neckties froe the United Kingdom. I reeanmend Import a88i.ataace under the heading 'Sundries*' • ^ -Bi-OTCORSUL- The issue of the above has been authorised. Bahrain Receipt Seoretary Resident in Copy to the Political Agent f Bahrain* NS. MFP 2/5 S&lt;fcF— $768—(M-676)—27-7-43—1,000,000. S. 6.* ' COVEBNMENT OF INDIA. Department. EXPRESS LETTER A. J?.—This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue u;.e of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched. No. 2866-79/175. Dated FOhKIGlf, Nil,.. UBhire, ° 27th Decanter' ' r 4' Bahrain Receipt No • Patfi. A . -*• • 114 ., n Biaaqrinflna Ho. 3744^6/4^ flatod the 1944, Nrom Political Agent, -^hrain, lingdom 11 ^ ^ ^ CU ( ^^ rec ^* Cotton thread from the United “Habertish^r 1 “ POrt ansi8tanCtt ,xndar beading -EKiTCONaOL- ’he issuo ol* the ^bove has loan autiiarlsod. □ S. 6. Copy to the Political NS. MFP—275 S&amp;P—6768—(M-676)—27-7-43—1,000,000.-me No, 79/175 Telegram G.T.C From To Mo. Britconsul, Bushire. Foreign, Mew Delhi. A/ 2047 . Bahrain Receipt Dated 2oth December 1944. So Your telegram No, 1960ME December 5th. 2. I recommend India office be asked tele graphically to grant export permit under Bahrain cotton piece goods quota. Political Agent reports these red shawls will be worn in Bahrain default of other types. / VSRK. -BRITCONSUI/- \ _ Post copy to Political Agent, Bahrain for information, with reference to his telegram Mp. 790 dated the 30th November 1944 2 . Please state the weight of the consignment.i. &gt; £ ■ SUV s-r-l'* G.T.C, ' ’ Foreign, ITo-.-j Delhi. Political, Bahrain. 1075 HE. Dated 30th and received Slat December, 1944* Addressed London repeated Bushirc and Bahrain• John Lean &amp; Spns, Glasgow have ready for shipment to Bahrain 0004 bales red cotton shawals which are reported to be badly heeded. BritivSh Consul General, Bushire recommended ‘export assistance and we support.3b The 6 th January, 1945. To Haji Abdulaziz All al Bassan, Bahrain. Dear Sir, The Government of India have asked India Gaixue telegraphically to grant an exuort permit john Lean &amp; Sons, Glasgow, for shipnent to Bahrain of 4 bales red shawls. 2 . I shall be glad to know the gross weight of the consignment In long tons. 3. lour exporters signify their ability to ship t*o bales per month. Would you like me to rccoramem i .poi „ assistance for 10 bales more which can be suippea against 1st half of 1946? If so please intimate the weight and submit your application tnrough the Director of Customs.DETAIL'S 01' GOODS 333ENTIALiy REQUIRED FROM THE UNITED KINGDOM UNITED STATES OF AMERICA OR CANADA IT THE ARAB STATES IN THE FEESIAN GULF. m )) (( ^[•NAme of ^would-b® importor* ^.Namc and address of the manufacturer or agent from whom he wishes to arrange supply. 3*^011 description the goods required* 4*Approximate weight in long tons of 2240 lbs of the goods to be ordered. 5.Exact use or purpose contemplated for the goods to be ordered. 6.Special reasons justifying:- a) Suppit of goods wanted. b) Their import from the country suggested rather any other country. —7 .Description of the urgency with whioh the goods required and the latest date which® will be suitable. Afirniwala - Bahrain. The Central Agency Ltd, Glasgow - Scotland.. gxx Broder ^enibroldery thread. Vfe tons, ^ono cx. a halfl ton-) 18o gross ticKets/Dundles, For sale in the local market scarcity oi goods. Country of origin. &gt;arliest possibleTel. AJJ ress:- FaUruJJln TakerLUl. BAHRAIN.' FAKHRUDDIN II. TAMERBMAI. General Nerclianls. BANPAIN. (Persian Gulf.) CoJes Used;- Benlley s Orienlal Jliree Lelter &amp; Private. Dated 29th December 1944. To, H. B. M f s Political Agent, Bahrain. Babr-' 67o6 ::’pt Sir t We enclose here with recomadation letter and other details regarding 100 gross cotton sewing thread and 469 gross and 4 dozen cotton a broder for import from United Kingdom and shall be highly obliged if you will arrange shipping space in United Kingdom in favour of Messrs: The Central Agency Ltd., 50,Bothwell street, Glasgow. You^s re £tfull;Tel. Address:- Fakhruddin Tak erUtai BAHRAIN*/' FAKWRUDDIN n. TANERBNAI. General Nerclianls. BAHRAIN. (Persian Gulf.) Codes Used:- ' Bentleys Oriental Iliree teller &amp; Private. Dated 19th December 1944. Details in regard to goods essentially reouired from the United Kingdom. 1 . 2 . 3. Name of would be imported Name and address of Agent or manufacturer in the exporting country from whom he wishes to obtain supply. Pull Description of the goods required. Messrs: Pakhruddin M. Taherbhai, The Central Agency Ltd., 50, Bothwwll street, GLASGOW (England) 100 Gross Cotton Sewing thread 469 gross and 4 dozen cotton a Broder. 4 Approximate weight in long tons of 2240 lbs. of the goods required. 5. Exact use or purposes contemplated for the goods to be imported. 2 Tons. Por local consumption. 6 . Specially reason Justifying a. Supply of the goods wanted b. Their import from the country suggested rather than from any other country. * 7. Description of the urgency with which the goods are required and latest date which will be suitable. vf / * 7 -ft*- t.- f Cm** *( * 1&gt;0J Shortage of goods. M*rch 194 . 5 .2.M EXPRES TTER, F i o .11 io Repeated No 36/43. Dated £&amp;§ 13tii JciaufiLr/ f 194o. POUTICAL AGENT BAHRAIN POLITICAL RESIDENT BUSHIRE GOVERNMENT OP INDIA NEW DELHI. f Subject!— IMPORT ASS ISTA NCE RECOMM END ATION. Reference Government of India letter No. D, 3154-N/42 dated 218th May, 1 942 forwarded under fushire Priuf.ed Letter No, 655-S dated 25th June, 1942, 2 . The particulars required by para 3 of the letter under reference are given below (i) Name of would-be importer j- kUruddll MMiMMLy iJ^Ti-vi .• (ii) Name &amp; address of agent or manufacturer in the exporting ccuutry from whom he wishes to arrange supply (iii) Full description of the goods required Tb« Central Agency Ltd* t 60* Bothardll Gtracty ul&amp;sgo*» 100 gross 00 1 ton sawing thro tad* 469 gross and 4 dox« cotton a brold«r 4 (iv) Approximate weight in long ton^ of 2240 lbs. cf the goods required t- (v) Exact use or purpose contemplated for the goods to be imported (vij Special reasons justifying (a) Supply of goods required - 2 tons* /or sals to the public* Bahrain stocks (b) Their import from the country suggested rather than from any other country :~ Hot swAllabis frou alsewhd»ro&lt; (vii) Descrirtien of the urgency with which the goods are r o quired, and th^ latest date which will be suitable Heading!- CottOT plSC«fgOO(U* For Jammiy/ «»X94&amp;. 3* Ibe order has been placed and accepted and I rcconmend that aesistarce be granted, Copy to: 1* The Director of Customs, Bahrain* 2* Mr* Fakrudctiu M* Taherbhai, Bahrain* :u^r for T^TTtir'al Agent, Bahrain- vAvA'J. E. KHEDOURI Import, Export &amp; Commission Agent (Arabia) Tele.-Address: Khedouri - Bahrain Reference No* 1I&lt;±„ Codes used: Bentley’s Acme &amp; Oriental H.B.k's i-olitical A^ent, Bankers: The Eastern Bank Ltd. Boiirain. Dear Sir, We snail be grateful if you will kindly shipping space assistance for us in respect of tne following goods from the United Kingdom*- (b) Their import from the country .. Airgraph acceptance from the suggested rather than from any firm dated 22*11.44 attache .other country, 7. Description of tne urgency with wnich.. As soon as possible, tne goods are required and the latest date which will be suitable. Thanking you in advance for your kind assistance. 1* Name of would be i .porter. J.; . Khedouri, Banrain. 2. Name of agent or m; nufacturer from whom he wishes to arrange supply. J*M. ohasha, 82, Trincess Street, Manchester, England* 3. Bull description of the goods ,. Netting, (1,700 pieces) required* 4* Approximate weight of the goods ., 1 ton 8 c *w*ts, in long tons. 5. Bxact use or purpose contemplated for tne ^oods to be imported. 6. Special reason justifying.- To meet local demands. (a) Supply of gDods wanted. Yours faithfully. Jhr&amp;rtor of amAEXPRESS LETTER. P ro:n t o Repeated POLITICAL AGENT BAHRAIN POLITICAL RESIDENT BUSHIRB GOVERNMENT OP INDIA NEW DELHI. Ko /£8~ 34/43* Dated The llth JimjAlJf Subject:— IMPORT ASS KSTA NCE RECOM M ENDATION. Keference Government of India letter No, D* 3154-N/42 dated aiSth May, 1942 forwarded under tushire Printed Letter No, 655-S dated 251b June, I 94 2 * Tbe particulars required by para 3 of the letter under reference are given below (i) Name of would-be importer (ii) Name &amp; address of agent or manufacturer in tbe exporting ccuutry from whom he wishes to arrange supply (hi; Full description of the goods required V. Mr# J*I5* 82y Princes# (J.^700 nl9c#m)* (iv) Approximate weight in long tons of 2240 lbs. cf the goods required 1- (v) fcxact use or purpose contemplated for the goods to be imported (vij Special reasons justifying (a) Supply of goods required (b) Their import from the country suggested rather than from any other country 1 tea 8 cwts# ‘ For 1 a to the public# Bahrain stocks exhausted# Hot available from eleowhor^# (vii) Descrirtien of »he ur k ercy with which tbe goods are required, and th^ latest date which will be suitable Heading:- QotUXi pidCe*gOOds# For Jen^ry/June I'^Mo# 3* Copy The order has been assistance be grnirted. placed and accepted aed I rccemmend that 1 ( 6 ? (iox PoliTral Agent, Bahrain- tot 1# The Director of Customs, Bahrain* 2. Mr* J*E. Khedouri, Bahrain* vK. E. KHEDOUKI TILE ADORES K. KHBDOURI. - BAHRAIN BANKERS Messrs, Glyn, Mills &lt;x Co, London Ref (Persian - Gulf ) No . 20 . .’s Political Agent, Bahrain. Pah-^l J‘ . 1 - ;ir, //' /&gt; ~ I be glaa i you will kindly recommend for me snipping space assistance for the following 1* Name qnd address of £h« ai$axLfc&gt;0 K.b.KJiedouri, Bahrain, would-be importer 2 . Name and address of the agent ) Mr.Jack Dellal, or manufacturer in tne export- ) 86 , George Street, rom whom he wishes) Manchester, Engladn. to arrange supply. 5. Full description of the goods required. k 4 -Tons Cotton Jiece fe oods { 2 Tons v oollen Fice^oods 1 Ion hua-quito Nettings 4. Approximate weight in long ton of 224o lbs. B. Bxact use or purpose contem plated for the goods to be imported. b. Special reason justifying (a) Supply of goods wnted:- (b) Their import from the country sugg ested rather 7 Tons. ) For consumption at ( Bahrain. To meet local demands. ) Available from Bn^land. , -- ) Or^er has been accepted ° :ian -' om any other country:; as per Cable of the 2 nd January, 1945, attached 7. Description of tne urgency with which the goods are re quired and tine latest date wnich will be suitable. herevith. as soon as possible. y 1 hanking you in anticipation. y a. i A ffi« *- Yours faithfully.EXPRESS LETTER. F rom 1 o Repeated POLITICAL AGENT BAHRAIN POLITICAL RESIDENT BUSH 1 RE GOVERNMENT OP INDIA NEW DELHI. 11a !, °* m - 36/43 * The 14th January, 194#» Subject:— IMPORT ASS ISTA NCE RECOM MEND ATION. Reference Government of India latter No. D, 3154-N/42 dated ai8tb May, 1 94 2 forwarded under tushire Printed Letter No. 655-S dated 25th June, 1942, 2 . The particulars required by para 3 of the letter under reference are given below (1) Name of would-be importer (ii) Name &amp; address of agent or manufacturer in the exporting ccuutry from whom he wishes to arrange supply (iii; Full description of the goods required Mr* K*£« IChedourl, Bahrain* Mr# Jack 86 aoori;^ - troci, Manchfcstor, Cotton plecogoods - 4 tons* rf^ollon -tlo# - 2^ * Mosquito netting - 1' (iv) Approximate weight in long tone of 2240 lbs. cf the goods required 1- ^^torts# (v) Exact use or purpose contemplated for the goods to he ub ported for sale to th*t public# (vi) Special leasone justifying (a) Supply of goods required - Bahrain stocks exhausted* (b) Their import from the country suggested rather than from any other country Mot available froa slsawhare# (vii) Oescriptien of fhe urgency with which the goods are required, and th? latest date which will be suitable Heading •.« Cotton pieca*goods* for Jonuary/Juna l£Ko* 3 , The order has been placed and accepted and I reccmmend that aesistance be granted. Sa . M • P- rT&gt;3v_4 FbC . ^ ' , ^ Political Agent, Bahrain- Copy to: 1. The Director of Customs, Bahrain# 2# Mr, K.E. Khedourl, Bahrain#J. E. KHEDOURI Import, Export &amp; Commission Agent Tele.-Address: Khedouri - Bahrain Codes used: Bentley’s Acme &amp; Oriental Bankers: The Eastern Bank Ltd. hr- fe re nee No. H.b.L f s Political B«nrain. K»V a ; n Re ' e i p \ • oj&amp; AkS-o**™-- Dear Sir, n Vye snail be most grateful if you will kindly recommend shipping space assistance for us for tne following &amp;oods from the United Kingdom.- 1. Name and address of the would be i porter. 2. Name and address of the agent or manufacturer from whom'he wishes to arrange supply. 5. Full description of the goods required. 4. ij proximate weight of the goods in lon t tons. 5. Exact use or purpose contera- ) plated for the goods to be ) • . imported. ) 6. Special reason justifying.- ) (a) Supply of goods wanted. ) .. (b) Iheir import from the country suggested rather than from any other country. 7. Description of the urgency with which tne goods are required and tne latest date wnich will be suitable. Thanking you in anticipation for J.E. Khedouri, Bahrain. Messrs. Selim Homsy &amp; Co., 32, St. Mary Axe, London, g.C. 3. Cotton Tussore Suitings. Two tons. For sale to the Public. To meet local demands, as badrain stocks exhausted. Available from England. Cable dated 19th instant from the above firm accepting our order attached. As soon as possible. vour kind assistance. Yours faithfully, » jfcrtc&amp;or of Ch s arid Port , r.;1 * *.4 / ¥ qI&gt; MSt EXPRESS LETTER. F !0:n 1 o Repealed POLITICAL AGENT BAHRAIN POLITICAL RESIDENT BUSH 1 RB GOVERNMENT OP INDIA NEW DELHI. J0-3S/43* The 23rd Jimmzy f 104L« Subjecti— IMPORT ASS IST ANCE RECOM MENDATION. Refcrente Government of India letter No. D % 3154-N/42 dated ai8th May, 1942 forwarded under Printed Letter No. 655-8 dated 25th June, 1942. 2 . The particulars required by para 3 of the letter under reference are given below to arrange suppjy (iii) Full description of the goods required;' Cottcrt (iv) Approximate weight in long tons 01 2240 lbs. of the goods required J- 2 tOfiS. ^v) Exact use or purpose contemplated lor the goods to be imported (vi) Special reasons justifying (a) Supply of goods required - suitable ^ The order has been placed and accepted and I rcccmmend tb»t (i) Name of would-be importer i- J. (ii) Name &amp; address of agent or manufacturer in the exporting ccuutry from whom he wishes i&amp;jsrs# Sollft hcusy a Co* 9 32 f Uury Axo f i«oiuioji 9 E«C«3« Bahrain 3 tocks exh^ustod* (b) Their import from the country suggested rather than from any other country lot bvaliUi)** fra* vjlsewhera* (vii) Oescriptien of the ur k ency with which the goods are required, and th^ latest date which will be Heading Cotton ^piece-goods* for 1^4 6* assistance be granted. 0 )* (of Political Agent, Bahrain Copy to* 1 . The Directox of Customs* Bahrain. 2. Mr. J.E. Khedouri* Bahrain.GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. Department. EXPRESS LETTER jV. B. —Tl)is is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched. No. 228-79/175. Dated * lushire, tlie 23rd January, 1G t ■ To % : V Foreign, Hgw DgjM* ^ ^ Bahrain ^emaranduin No. 3967-36/43 dated 27th December, 1944, copy sent to you direct. Goods from the United Kingdom. 2 . I recommend import assistance under 'Haberdashery' =EHITCONSUL= The issue of the above lias been authorised. Bahrain Receipt No 2 P.i Date No. 229-79/175. Bushire, the 23rd January, 1945. Sd./- R.G. MUEENY, Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. ^Forwarded with compliments to the Political Agent, Bahrain. S. 6. Secretary to the Political NS* 1VIiP — 275 - &amp;p — 6768 —( M 6 7 6i- 7 27-7-43— 1 , 000 , 000 . Resident in the Persian Gulf.- BRITISH RESUffiNCY AND CONSULATE GENERAL, BUSHIRE. d y\\ (3to; 5S V E_XJP_R_E_S_S LJS_T_TE_R. No. 232-79/175. Dated the 23rd January, 1945. To Loal&gt; PaVain Fteceipt ^ Bahrai^ 6 .Date. Political, Your meraorandum No. 3968-36/43 dated 27th December, 1944, and your telegram No. 877 dated 28th December, 1944. 2. I agree that 15 cwts. or Bahrain’s guota of woollen goods for 1945 has not yet been recommended. As you will see from my Egress letter No. 235*79/175 dated the 23rd January, 1945, I am now recommending your full requirements as detailed in your Memoranda Nos. 3467-36/43, 3473-36/43 dated 20th November, 1944, 3594-36/43 dated 3rd December, 1944 and No. 3593-36/43 dated 3rd December, 1944. &lt; M l 'V 3. The confusion arose through ray office including your recommendation for 1 ton woollen goods referred to in your Memorandum No. ^2266-36/43 dated 9th August, 1944, in your 1945 quota. You will notice that you did not state that this order was for the year 1944. Further your quota for 1944 had already been exceeded. I am, however, now assuming that the 1 ton woollen goods referred to in your Memorandum No. y 2266-36/43 dated 9th August, 1944, has been accepted by the Government of India as part of your 1944 quota. iV 4. The position now is that we have recommended the following under woollen goods to the Government of India:- (a) Bahrain Memorandum No. 2717-36/43 dated 25th September, 1944, in my Express letter No. 2264-79/175 dated 11th October, 1944. 3 cwt. (b) Bahrain Memorandum No. 3052-36/43 dated 28th October, 1944, in my Express letter No. 2501-79/175 dated 5th November, 1944. 3 4 cwt. (c) Bahrain Meraorandum No. 3467-36/43 dated 20th November, 1944, in my Express letter No. 2847-79/175 dated 24th December, 1944, and my Express letter No. 235-79/175 dated 23rd January, 1945. 3 tons 11 cwt. (d) Bahrain Meraorandum No. 3473-36/43 dated 20th November. 1944, in my Express letter No. 237-79/175 dated 23rd January, 1945. 7 cwt. (e) Bahrain Memorandum No. 3593-36/43 dated 3rd December, 1944, in ray Express letter No. 242-79/175 dated 24th January, 1945 4 cwt. 2 lbs /(f)t— 'J - 2 - 3!^ (f) Bahrain Memorandura No. 3594-36/43 dated 3rd December, 1944, in my Express letter No. 244-79/175 dated 24tfi January, 1945. Total 3 cwt. 4 tons 12 cwt. 2 IDs. 7 cwt llC) S lhs presen ^ l 0 av 9 S a 'balance not yet used ot A ? tion if ‘being taken to transfer 5 tons of your a? J ) ^f ce S^o ( is quota to your woollen goods quota hut nn+i? h0Uld recommendations for tMs 5 tons i- you are informed that the transfer has 'been sanctioned. -BRITCONSUL- The issue of the above has been authorised. Secretary to the Political Besidenbjin the Persian Gulf. NS.'J 3 Si GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. Department. EXPRESS LETTER \v Is.B. Ihjs is an 0H1GDAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended tp be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if n ha&lt; been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched. ^ io 255-79/175. Dated lushiro, the Foreign, Urn Dellii 23rtL January, 1 ^ 4 5* ^ V ^ ^ V' v ^ Vo Rererence my .Express letter No. 2847-79/175 dated the 24th December, 1944. 2 . I now reconnend import assistance for the ”balance of 18 cwt. woollen goods requested in the application* sent with Bahrain Memorandum No. 3467- 36/43 dated the 20th November, 1944. \ 3,0 &gt; *BRITCONSUI^ The issue of the a'bove has teen authorised. Bahrain Receipt sa./- R.g. daiibeny, ^^ ***••• *^* •••^* Secretary to the Political Residen t in the Persian Gulf. No. 236-79/175.• Bushire, the 23rd January, 1945. Forwarded with compliments to the Political Agent, Bahrain. NS. Mi7,p 275 s&amp;p 6768 (M-676) 27-7-43—i,ooo,ooo. Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.GOVERNMENT OK INDIA. Department. EXPRESS LETTER JV. B .—This is an ORICtINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched. No. 244-79/176. Dattd Buahlre, the 24th January 194 5- Foreign, iiasUMLi. Bahrain aemomndum No* 3594-56/43 dated 3rd Decem'ber # 1944 y copy aant to you direct. roods required from the United Kingdom. • I recommend import assistance. . *ERITCQNSUIis The issue cf the ahove i?as Teen authorised. Bahrain Receipt 1;'..%,^' Sd.A R.G. mUBENY, Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. No, 245^79/175. Bushire, the 24th January, 1945. / Porwarded compliments to the Political Agent, Bahrain S. 6. NS .MFP—275 SAP—6768—(M 676)—27-7-43— SecreWjr to the Political 1 , 000 , 000 . Resident in the Persian Gul:36/43. Political Agency, Bahrain, The 4th February, 1945. To The Director of Customs, Bahrain. Memorandum . Reference your memorandum No.PVR /9 dated the 19th December, 1944. 2. The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, has confirmed that we have a balance of 7 cwts. and 110 lbs. under woollen piece-goods from the United Kingdom. 3. He has also requested the Government of India to transfer 5 tons from cotton piece-goods to wollen goods. I shall inform you as soon as the change is sanctioned. for Political Agent, Bahrain. V3S* GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. Department. EXPRESS LETTER ■N- B -—J his i* an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and sDned as if it had been so despatched. / ° No&lt; 237-79/175. I)at( -' 1 lusiilre, t%3rd January, R'S • 'to .Foreign, New Jelhl . GeTerence kamoranitiin Ho* 3475-36/43 dated 20th Nove^iher, 1944, i^rom Political Agent, Bahrain, copy sent to you direct*. Goods required froro the United Kingdom* 2* I recommend import assistance* »JBRITCONbU]&gt; The issue of the above has been authorised* Bahrain Receipt ^ Sd./- r.g. muBENY, Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf* No. 238-79/175. Bushire, the 23rd January,.1945. ^Forwarded with compliments to the Political Agent,Bahrain Secretary to Political Resideht in the Persian Gulf S. 6. # MFP—275^S&amp;P—6768—(M 676)—27-7-43—1,000, 000.■s* * ^ GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. Department. EXPRESS LETTER j\ . B. i his is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the \\ ires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if n had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched. • g u No, To 242-79/175. ^ed Bushlref January&gt; 19% foreign, liew • 5 V* 0 / *‘ emarantlu ? 110 • 3593-36/43 dated 3rd sr&amp;ujitti sss 1 ^ you iireot - 2. I reooiamand import assistance. =Ep.irecw3U]&gt; • ••• • mmwmrnm* 'Cha issue of the ahore has been authorised. . Bahrain Receipt No-./^£..Date Z.:.Z-~4£.S No. 243-79/175. sd./- e.g. mumsNy, Secretary to the Political Besident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, the 24th January, 1945. V ' ;Forwarded with compliments to the Political Agent, Bahrain. . T s _ 6 - Secretary to the Political No .mfp ^275 s&amp;p 6768—(M- 876 )—^7-7-43—1,000,000. Eesident in the Persian Gulf.GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. V ITT Department. JlQ EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). [N.B. This is an ORIGINAL tnessjge sent by AIR MAIL ie\ioh provides a means of communication more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department.] No. 466-79/175. Dated §W®blre 31st January, 19 45 To foreign New Delhi. Ir Bahrain express letter No, 134-36/43dated 10th January, l c, 45. Copy sent to you direct# Embroidery thread required from United Kingdom. 2 . dashery 1 . I recommend import assistance under 'Haber- -BIITCONSUL- The issue of the above has been author1sed. Wm Sd/- B.G.Daubeny Secfetary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Bahrain Reteifl ' 0.467-79/175. Bushire, the 31st January,1945 °py forwarded to the Political Age- t, Bahrain. (Signature) s. 44. AGL. MGIPC— SI—238o(S&amp;P)MFP—(M-1744)—3-12-40—20,000. 9 ^ bar\ (Designation) \ tcfthe Political Resident in the Persian U ulf/ Q . — EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). [N.B. This ia an ORIGINAL message sent by AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more expeditious than the ordinary ituiil and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted m the form of a telegiam. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department. No. 463-79/175-A. Dated To 4th February, ^ 45.- FOfFiar, ICMXJUJdL t. Reference*^ f^ahrain Fxpreas letter Ho. 132-26/43, dated the h January, 19 ■*, copy sent to you direct. Goods required 10 th ■■■PI frorr the United Kingdom. 2 . I recommend import aasistance under 'Haberdashery *. ■ BRITCOH8UL* ^hc issue of the xbove has been authorised. Bahrain Receipt ^ ^ -. 0 . dav ^’^^ecretary to the Folitical Resident an the Persian Gulf. vcs. Ho. 459-7C/175-A. ' Bushire, dated the 11 h February, 1915, Copy forwarded rith cor^lirents to 'olitical Ay^nt, Bahrain, v.ho i ay nlease note that the proper heading is ’Ha^erd-ishery^ and not *Coi ton ''i^e-ypbds 1 as shorn by him m3m s. 44. SecretafW'to the '’o,. itica , l Resident l 'c 'ersi^.r BiPf. MGIPO—S2—2278 (Genl) MFP—(6806/M-2013)—13-3-43—■2ft,000. VC 5. /No. ( 36/43. Political Agency, Bahrain ^^ KZAIK+J y AJCLIll cl The 8th February, 1945 (0/to To The Director of Customs Bahrain. Memorandum Reference my Express Letters Nos.132-36/43 and 134-36/43 dated the 10th January, 1945 to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, copy sent to you. 2. The applications referred to above have been recommended by the Hon'ble the Political Resident under haberdashery and not cotton piece-goods. % for Political Agent, Bahrain© GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. DEPARTMENT. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). n [N.B. This is an ORIGINAL message sent by AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt with, the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it d ™J ted ln th e form of a telegiam. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of No. To y Jmshlre, 478-79/175 -A Dated -jglL, the -•oraign, Jeltii i No.. 31st January, aiiraia &lt;k\l 19. 45 .Date. 2 US&gt; R^fftrenoA your Bahrain express letter No. 195^36/43 dated 14th January , 1945, copy sent to you direct. Bed shawls £rom John -jean and bons, .Glasgow. ky telegram No. A/2047 dated 25th Decemher, 1944, recommended import assistance for 4 hales weighing 16 cwt. 3. I recommend import assistance for further 2 tons under 'pieoegoods', during first half of 1945. • -BBITCONbUL- v The issue of the above has “oean authorised. / Sd.A B.G. milEENY, i-ecretar^' tc* the Political Besident in tlie Persian Gulf. v/no. 479-79/175-A. Bushire, the olst January, 1945. forwarded with compliments to the Political Agent, Bahrain. s. 44 . Secretary t^the Polit'jXci]- Resident MGIPC—S2—2278 (Genl) MFP—(6^O0/M-2O13)—13-3-43—25,000.in l^je Persia^ Gulf . NS.GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). DEPARTMENT. Foreign, New Delhi. Inference ■srs' 25i^l January, 1945, copy sent to you direct. Gtoods £rom the United Kiagdom. Sd./- B.a. BAUEIiNY, Secretary to the Political Besilent in the Persian Gulf. No. 483-79/175-A. Bushire, the 31st January, 1945. ‘'Copy forwarded with compliments to the Political Agent, Bahrain. s. 44 . Nfc. Secretary W the Political P MGIPC—S-—2278 (Genl) MFP—(6806/M-2013)— 13 - 3-43 —Persian Gulf.GOVERNMENT OF INDIA Department. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). ^ (u [N.B .—TMi ia an ORIGINAL mwszge tent by AIR MAIL which provide a meant of communication mart expeditious Ilian the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It it intended to be treated, on receipt, with the tame expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To tave time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department.] No. 464-79/175 Dated ire 31st, January, 19 45 To Foreign New Delhi. my £*UjOr&gt;Ol{A I, V Bahrain express letter No. 148-36/48 dated 11 th January, 1945. Copy sent to you direct. Netting required from United Kingdom. 2 . I recommend -BRITCONSUL- ^he issue of the above has been authorised. Sd/- R.0.Daub eny Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Rakain Receipt X .Date *** Bushire, the 31st January,1945 Copy forwarded to the Pblitical A^ent, Bahrain.TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS. “STAGLEAN. GLASGOW.' TELEPHONE N? 2572 BRIDGETON J DANIEL LEAN. ROBERT LEAN. ^eNrA-LO^ Mrrf*HAfL. . MALCOLM McPHA | L I D. GORDON LEAN. \.D. MACLELLAN LEAN Major T. Hiokinbotham. Political Agent, Phe agency, Bahrein. Dear Sir. 0 We beg to advise you that we have to-day received from the India Office, their Jhipoing Priority Letter for 4 Bales Red Shawls (Shumcghs) to be shipped to Haji Abdulaziz Ali Al Bassam, Bahrein. ^7e &lt;h^ve had the Export Licence and the 4 Bales ready for shipment since January, 1944 and as soon as we have the Export Licence Period extended, it having expired this month, we shall register the goods for shipment. 7/e confirm that we have contracted to ship £ Bales per month to Mr. Bassam if the India Office will issue the necessary O.P.L. for shipment. Phis permission has not been given in the Priority setter received to-day. We are permitted by the Board of Trade to ship 5^u of our Shawl production to Persian Gulf Markets and as Mr. Bassam is our most valued customer, we trust that we shall be permitted to supply him. We thank you for your consideration in connection with the present four bales and shall much appreciate any assistance you can give to enable us to supply the Bahrein Market with their share of Red Shawls. We are the largest Manufacturer United Kingdom,&amp;supply Iraq, Syria, Lebanon and Persian Gulf Markets. of Shawls in the Transjordan (Arab Legion) Yours faithfully. For and on behalf of / JOHN LEAN A SONS, LTD, 7 p ^DHAMANMAL ISSARDAS The Political Agent, Bahrain. 27th February, 194p. P Bear Sir, fr om Unitea Kingaom . Reference your letter No. 1106-36/43 dated the 18th April,1944 ana the minutes of the Merchant's Advisory Committee Meeting held at the Agency on 12th June, 1944. We had applied to you for assistance in exporting 72 tons of piece-goods from the United Kingdom, which was accepted and duly recommended by you as per your letter under reference. * But this recommendation of 72 tons was reduced to 20 tons by th ®-^ on,bl e the Political Resident vide the 3 rd paragraoh of the mi ^es of the Merchants' meeting under reference. In this respect, we have received telegraphic aavice from our Bombay Office to request you to kindly issue us 'A' class Imoort Licence and also to request you to kindly despatch the following telegraphic information to the U.K.C.C. London: 1. Port Licence Holder: M/s Dhamanmal Issaruas, Bahrain. 2 . Exporters : M/s Ralli Brothers Limited, Manchester. 7e attach hereto the full description of the goods intended for import by us. We request you to help us in this matter injoraer to facilitate the shipment of these goods. ^ Thanking you in anticipation,DHAMANMAL ISSAHDAS The following is the list by us : Printed Crepe Crepe, black &amp; other colours Voil printed Woolen cloth Bahrain 27-2-45. of the goods to be imported tons it n n 5 5 5 5 • • • •No. SflS- 36/43. Political Agency, Bahrain, The 1st March, 1945. To Mr. Abdulaziz Ali Bassam, Bahrain. Memorandum , j / I enclose a copy of letter jdated the 15th January 1945 from your exporters Messrs. John Lean &lt;Sc Sons, Ltd. 2. Will you please inform them of ray recommen dation and the support of the Hobble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, which I conveyed to you in ray endorsements Nos.195-36/43 dated the 14th January, 1945 and 62^-36/43 dated the 17th February, 1945. ' ^ ■ b 3±-' 1 ^ I / for Political Agent, Bahrain.No. 36/43. Political Agency, Bahrain, The 6 th March, 1945. To Mr. Abdulaziz Ali al Bassara, Bahrain. Reference my endorsement No.652-36/43 dated the 17th February, 1945. ^ ^' / &lt;- 2 . The Government of India have supported the recommendation of the Hon»ble the Political Resident for red shawls weighing two tons from John Lean &amp; Sons, Glasgow. - ■ 0 for Political Agent, Bahrain cAcA _LHAMANMAL issardas Bahrain 5-3-45. The Political Agent, Bahrain . . # I'ahrAia Recent ^ ar Sir - x a ..mj.D^. Piece-goo ds from United Kinprinm . With reference to our conversation of yesterday regarding our application of 27th ultimo, for the good under reference, the following is the copy of the telegram sent by us to our Bombay Office as xwas decided:- Of -io. tv,' Manchester's all details forwarded India Office through normal channels. Obtained shipping let UKCC C Raili° °^ her T licence required. If necesfary ■Lez ukuu halli refer India Office ' J Yours faithfully, Bhamanmal Issardas</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000207_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1784</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000207</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1784</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 36/43 Applications for Assistance to Export Piece Goods from U.K. &amp; U.S.A.'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1943/1945</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-04-22T12:24:10</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (381 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 381; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 2-380; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains short letters and telegrams from a number of merchants active in Bahrain requesting permission and assistance from the Political Agency to import goods from the United Kingdom and the United States.The goods mentioned are predominantly clothing, underwear and woollens. A large proportion of the correspondence in the file is from the merchant firm, J E Khedouri Import and Export.Also enclosed in the file are letters from the Political Agency to the Political Residency forwarding on the merchants' requests for approval.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>J E Khedouri &amp; Sons</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Imports</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000207#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>