<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000517.0x0001d6_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-11T14:32:33.309Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">I17th i^ebrunry, 19 ^ 7 * H 0.61 (K 1 ^109'11233/93) ^ tiir R^iTKICTED With reference to Your ^xcexlenc INDEXED No. 426 of 6th November last concerning— project or an Iraqi shipping line, I approve the attitude which the iunbaasy ia adopting on the subject. The project should not be given any express encouragement, but if the inter*ated parties are determined to pursue it, it is hoped that they will wish to place in this country eny contracts for the building of ships and they should be given the necessary assistance to get into touch with British shipbuilding firms through the intermediary of th* Boara of Trade. 1 am, with greet truth and respect sir, Your Kxcellency*s obedient servant (For the Secretary of State) t icr Bird, K. . .G. , o. r . . , 5 T. C • ,FOREIGN OFFICE, 3.W.1 (E.11233/H233/93) ^7th November, 1946 Dear Swann dlscuseing tentative Iraqi projects for running merchant ships under the Iraq flag, »Te agree with the attitude adopted by the Embassy, but before replying, we should be grateful for your views on the whole matter. I am oending copies ox* this letter to General Money, Ministry of Transport, and Donaldson at the Indi* Office, for their comments also. F. A. Swann, Esq., Export promotions Department Board of Trade.It will be noted th«t the intention i* to porch*•• abin© and e^utipmnt from vn^l^^nd end the ooplopMnt of J^ritieh Bsaatere and p^rhaja nom Britlnh Of He era ie eiiTimaged# Hiohael Hanna iheikh hat asked Hie tf&amp;jeety 1 * ^n»ul-Cen&lt;5r«3»l whether th*? Hritiah Uov^rnnjent would have an/ objection to the eetftbll ahiJient of vn Irfitji shippiiAg line and has stated th^t he «•/ later «e&amp; fbr a letter of introduction to United Kinii^oo authorities in order that h? be aeeieted in th&lt;‘ acquisition of ships# 6# Kr# relhftto has replied to Mr# Davies that, of course| there osn be no qu^ation of objection to each a project b/ Hie fca^eety** Oovurrunofvt but that in view of the doubtful econom o value of such a line of ships run by Iraqi© in competition with inf ini tel/ caore experienced ship owners lwhich wight well raise Questions of protection sdbeidi#s» or oth^r 04scrimination against foreign shipping) the re should be no expression of snsoorsgetusnl t &gt; if Uishssl Hanna theikh applied for a letter of introduction# his Msj««t/*s ocnsul^^nsrsl Scold provide him with a brief letter of i icntlt/ to th. ..xport .r roKsoilon &gt;#p»rU4ent of th^ isoard of Trade anl at the snuss %%m dlrcctljr Inform tlmt ; epart sent mors fall/ of the applicant's standing and desires# 7# It is probable th*t we tadwll he**r mere of the project before it reaches an/ oensrete stage# In the stent jins 1 sm ooiii ient that /ou will approve the attitude which this .•iidntaay is adopting# 8# I enclose an extra oop/ of this despatch for the information of U\c Export Promotion ^artmsnt of the Board of Trade# X hnvs the honour to be, with Uifi highest respect, 54r, four most obedient, humble Servant— i'here Is an interesting news about a&lt;' peoyoe form an Iraqi shipping ooiapany* Mr. a! r has been eonsulted by the Ministerial Gonvnittee as an es^ert on the subject and has put before them a plan for the formation of a company, of which the laain points ore as follows:-* fhe shares of the company should be limited to ID 2.000,000 • The company would buy six ships at first,' the freight of each not to be less than 6,000 tons. ab a financial guarantee, some of th&amp;se ships would be mortgaged with 1*caJun companies, through the Baltic Axchtmge, a method practised by the moat famous and rich world shipping companies* Shares to be offered on the (narked, 31 per cent to Iraqis only ;nd the remaining 49 per cent to Iraqis and foreigners together. No sale or transfer of shares to others would be performed without the consent of the maittiging coomittt e. If subscriptions within one year from the date of issue of shares did not reach ID 2,000,000 the reraainder of shares would be mwrtgaged by the Privy xurse, at an interest not exceeding 2 1-2 per cent per annum. The Privy iurae would have the right to sell the mortgaged shares, keeping in mind that not mors than 49 per cent of the issue total is to be sold to foreigners. British shipping companies in Iraq who have sea lines, like ^tricks, Grey Maciicnxie and African and eastern should be urged to buy shares, in order to prevent competition and to pave the way for the inclusion of tile Iraqi shipping coo^pan^ in the pool now organised by the leading foreign shipping companies* A managing comiittce of five persons, would be selected from sharc-holders, unler the supervision of the Cofununicatlona Ministry, the number of Iraqis so selected not to be leas than three out of five* Go-operation of the Managing Committee with British shipping companies in Iraq* Members of the Iraqi Managing Gomaitt e would have the right to amend, postpone or reject decisions taken by a foreign firm navigating an Iraqi ship. If the managing comriittee authorised a foreign firm to navigate Iraqi ships, thie firm Mftst submit to the former a detailed account of each voyage of an Iraqi ship showing income and expenses, confirmed by receipts* The company’s agents abroad rauat be of idle ojterience and specialised in shipping work* They should preferably be ship-owners who have connections with xraq and have agents in Iraq, in order to prevent competition. The head office of the cou^any should be In Xondon to fix dates of shipping and consigning, receive payiants, repair and clean ships, appoint or dismiss masters and crew, buy or sell or replace ships as necessary and perform everything connected with the management of ships, as known and practised by all shipping companies which have sea connections with Iraq.So 1587 (17/1/1 ) British Oonaulote-viencral, Basra* 24th October, 1546* eo^c Dear Pelham, X have bee^ approaAfed by kiohael Hanna ohelkh of Basra who wante^F^ow WetRer the British Oovernnient would have any objection to the eetabliahraent of an Xraqi shipping line by himself and certain asaociat s« 2* Michael Hanna uheikh is a partner in the Hanna Dheikh Kiver Transport Company which is owned by three brothers, Michael, who lives at Basra, and Gabriel and Jabourl Hanna oheilch who live at Amara# Its Head Office is in Bssrs juad branch offices in Bagdad and Amarflu It is well known fins and has a good record for friendliness and co-operation with the British authorities* 3* kiohael tells me an approach has been made to the Iraqi Government through the kutaaarrifiya here with a view to ascertaining their views but he does not anticipate any difficulty from that quarter: on the contrary, ho rather expects support and encouragement* 4* He also tells me the Intention is to buy or build . one or more ships in the United Kingdom and run tucm with British roasters and perhaps British officers. All necessary equipment would also be purchased in the United i^ingdom* He says they already hnve a representative who has gone to Bngland on a business visit and is making tentative enquiries and so far the prospects are favourable thou^i of course nothing is definite yet* 5 . officially and le .ally X presume we couli not and would not object to the establishment of an Iraqi merchant marine since Iraq is an independent State with a coast line and seaports and a considerable import and export trade and therefore has every Justification for possessing a merchant navy of her own* whether our shipping firms would take a good or a poor view of it is another question* 6* Michael Hanna uhei^h says that when the prospects are more definite he may ask us for a letter of intro duction to the United UAgdom authox'ities for the facilitation of the business of acquisition of ships and the like* At the moment however he does not want any action by us as the project is still in Its early stages* 7* He also requested that the affair should be treated ffgi i r )t lf 0 - 1 ; confidential for the time being since he must consult partners nna associates b of ere taking any positive action* However, I thought you raight like to know about it (if you are not already au fai t j so am passing it on to you, also inconfldeuce* fours ever, (signed; A. &lt;• )«vis G.O.lelhsm r.sq*, Coiftnerclal Counsellor, British dnibassy, Bagdad*</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000517.0x0001d6_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/1186</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000517.0x0001d6</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/1186</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Ext 8046/46 'Proposed Iraqi merchant shipping line'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1946/1947</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-11-14T18:00:52</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (11 folios)</extent><extent>The file's contents are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 13; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains correspondence regarding a proposal made by the Hanna Sheikh River Transport Company to open an Iraqi shipping line. The message is relayed by Sir George Clinton Pelham (British Embassy in Iraq, Baghdad) to Archibald William David (British Consul, Basra). Subsequent correspondents include Hugh Stonehewer Bird (HM Ambassador to Iraq), and Peter Isham Garran (Foreign Office), Eion Pelly Donaldson (India Office) and Charles William Baxter (Foreign Office).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Hanna Sheikh River Transport Company</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>British Embassy in Iraq, Baghdad</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Shipping</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000517.0x0001d6#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>