<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000135_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T18:14:55.600Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">0 Confidential» No*0/256-24/2 * , f M British Agency, Sharjah, 2nd April 1938* To, The Political Agent, Bahrain* / / Memorandum^ / ^ ' j f 1 f Reference your express letter No*0/203-10/12 dated the 27th March 1938* dated the 27th Muharram 1357(i*e* 30th March 1938) from the Shaikh of Sharjah in reply to your letter No.0/202-10/12 dated the 27th March 1938,which is in terms of (Draft , A f ) received with your above mentioned letter® I beg to enclose a cover containg a letter Residency Agent,Sharjah®Translation of letter dated the 27th Muharram 1357 Rui 1938} frQm shaikh Sultan bln Saqr, D!^^'f^J 0f -, Shar * ,all, 10 H *Nightman Esquire, I.C.S., Political Agent,Bahrain. ’ * After Compliments, , , In reply to your letter No.C/202-10/12 dated the 24th Muharram 1367 equivalent to the 27th March 1938, I beg to inform you that should I wish to * rall 't' permission to a Bank to open a Branch or Agency in Sharjah, I will obtain His Majesty's Government's approval before entering into any negotiations with the R^nv. Usual Ending*GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. Department. EXPRESS LET T ER (AIR MAIL). Confidential.'' [N.B • Thit is an ORIGINAL message sent by AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, tvilh the same expedition as if it had been teleraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities tt is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department.] No C/251-10/12-b. Bahrain, Dated 13th /'prll ^ 38 . To Political Resident, Camp Bahrain, Repeated to:- His Majesty’s Secretai*y of State for India, \ India Office, London, The Secretary to the Government of India Reference your * n External Affairs Department, New Delhi, Subject :- Sharjah Political Agreement, Reference correspondence ending with your Express letter No, C/164 of the 27th March 1938, i 2, The exchange of letters 1 to 4 is now complete, and in accordance with the instructions contained in India Office Hxpress letter No, P,Z, 7603/37 dated the 20th November 1937- I an sending copies of these letters to the India Office and the Government of India. Copies are also enclosed for your record. / Political Agent, Bahrain, (Signature) (Designation) S. 44. MFP—825S&amp;P—(M-1070)—14-0 34 —10,000.(Original in file 10/12) Copy of demi-official letter No, D0/PCL/SAA19/963 dated the 21st April 1938 from E,V,Packer, Esquire, Manager, Petroleum Concessions Limited, Bahrain, to the Political Agent, Bahrain. I have had a letter from Lermitte which may be summarised as under: BAS EL KHAILiAK . No developments except that the Shaikh according to Lermitte’s infomation is putting round rumours that Lermitte has applied to him for permission to start trading on his own account in Ras el Khaimah. ABU EKABI . Ahmed bin Khalaf has been to Dubai and wants Ler mitte to return to Abu Dhabi. Lermitte proposes to cable London and ask whether he should return. Vehicles for Shaikh of Shar.iah . These are expected in Dubai on 21st and will be handed over when assembled.( 3 ) H 1 938 Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office.K INDIA OFFICE 5 P.Z.3176/38. 17th May, 1938. Sir I am directed by the Secretary of State to refer to Bahrein Express Letter No.C/251-10/12-b of the 13th April 1938, enclosing copies of the Notes exchanged v/ith the Sheikh of Sharjah in regard to the oil concession granted by him to Petroleum Concessions Limited on the 17th September 1937 and to forward for your information will now instruct the Political Agent, Bahrein, to communicate with the Sheikh of Sharjah on the lines of i / ^ ( Draft No.5 which formed an enclosure to India Office xpress Letter No.P.Z.7053/37 of the 20th November 1937. A copy of the Political Agent's communication should be sent to this Office for record. . 3 sent to the Government of India, External Affairs Department, and to the Political Agent, Bahrein. To Company dated 3rd May, 1938. f Lv .) From Company Gate' To Company dated • 9 ) copies of the complementary 3rd May, 1938^, ) ' correspondence exchanged with the Company. 2 I am to request that, if you see no objection, you 3 Copies of this letter (and enclosures) are being I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant The Hon'ble Lieut.Colonel Sir T.C.E.Fowle H.3.M.'s Consulate General, BU SHIRE.1 I I I 6) P.Z. 2797/38. / I1TDIA OFFICE, ^iTHITKiALIi, LOFFOF, S.W.l. 3rd Kay, 1938. Sir , si X/V / 0 ,4 Tn e I am directed by the Secretary of State for India S' to enclose herewith, for the informatior&gt; of Petroleum Concessions Limited, a copy of a letter Ho.C/929-10/12, dated 23rd December, 1937, from the Political Agent, Bahrein, to the Sheikh of Sharjah, together with a translation of the latter’s reply dated 26th/larch, 1938, in regard to certain points which arise in connection with the oil concession granted (subject to the approval of His Majesty’s Government) to your Company by the Sheikh of Sharjah on the 17th September, 1937, and in connection with the political agreement of the 12th November, 1937, between your Company and His Majesty’s Government regarding the said concession. 2. I am to request that, in accordance with the unofficial understanding already reached, your Company will now be good enough formally to confirm their acceptance of the arrangements embodied in the Political Agent's letter of the 23rd December, 1937, as binding on them. 3. On receipt of a letter from .the Company accepting the arrangements mentioned above the Marquess of Zetland will convey to the Company His Majesty’s Government's formal approval of the oil concession granted to the Can pany by the Sheikh of Sharjah. I am , etc. , (Sgd.) J.P.GIBSCN. General Manager, Petroleum Concessions Ltd., City-Gate House, Finsbury Square, E.C.2.P.Z.3176/38. PC 31. PETHCLETF CC1TCE8SI0HS LIMITED, CITY-GATE HOUSE, FIFSBURY SQUARE, E.C . 2. 4th May, 1938. Sir, LV I have the honoi^r to acknowledge receipt of your letter Yo.P.Z.2797/38 dated May 3rd, relating to a Concession obtained during 1937 by this Company from the Shaikh of Sharjah. A'//, , t ^ I beg hereby formally to confim the Company’s acceptance of the arrangements embodied in letter Do. C/S29/lc/l2 -dated December 23rd, 1937, from the Political Agent, Bahrain, to the Ruler of Sharjah, and confirmed in the reply of the latter dated 23rd Muharran 1357 (26th March, 1938). k^ The Company will be glad to receive notice of His Majesty’s Government’s formal approval of the Concession concerned. I have, etc., (Sd.) J.Skliros, Managing Director. The Under Secreta^ of State for India, India Office, Whitehall, S.W.l.INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL, S.W.l. P.Z.3175/38. 17th May 1938. Sir, I am directed 'by the Secretary of State for India to acknowledge the receipt of your letter of the 4th May''(Ho.P.C .31) on the subject of the Sharjah Oil Concession and to express on behalf of His Majesty’s Government their formal approval of the concession granted to the Company by the Sheikh of Sharjah on the 17th September 1937. 2. Copies of this correspondence are being sent to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf with a view to action being taken as indicated in paragraph 4 of Mr.Weightman’s letter dated 23rd December 1937 to the I am, Sir Your obedient Servant, (Sgd.) R. PEEL. The Managing Director, Petroleum Concessions Limited, City-Gate House, Finsbury Square , S.C. 2Confidential. No. C/340-10/12-b. The Political Ageut, Bahrain, PreEents his compliments to : 1* His Majesty^ Secretary of State for India, India Office, London* 2. The Secretary to the Government of India, External Affairs Department, Simla, 3* The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. and has the honour to §end him a copy of the undermentioned document O) The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf. D&amp;ted 24:th May 1938, Reference to previous corre* pond cnee: India Office Printed letter Ho. P. r /.3176/38 dated the 17th May 1938. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Letter Ho. C/339-10/12.b. dated the 23rd May 1938 from the Political Agent, Bahrain, to Shaikh Sultan bin Saqr, Ruler of Sharjah* Subject. Sharjah Concession,TELEGRAMS : PETRUCIAL, BAHREIN CODES : BENTLEY’S SECOND PHRASE PETROLEUM DEVELOPMENT (TRUCIAL COAST) LIMITED DIRECTORS : Sir John Cadman, G.C.M.G. (Chairman) A-Aon«w.rtt^(J. ^ R. Cayrol, D.S.O., D.S.C. (French) W. Fraser, C.B.E. C. S. Gulbenkian (formerly Armenian) I. B. A. Kessler (Dutch) Sir Iflhn R Uayd x ./if../ J. A. Meny (French) 7 ' H. G. Seidel (U.S.A.) R. W. Sellers J. Skliros PTC/CATS/ f ICO CONFIDENTIAL BAHREIN PERSIAN GULF 9th July, 1938. H.B.M. *s Political Agent, Bahrain. Dear Sir, A J VEHICLES FOH H.S. THE SHAIKH OF SHARJAH The vehicles, one Saloon &amp; one lorry, for presentation by this Company to the Ruler of Sharjah are being assembled at Dubai and it is proposed that Mr.Packer should proceed to Sharjah on the 12th and make the presentation. We presume that there is nothing in the present situation which makes this presentation inappropriate. »- Yours faithfully, For &amp; on behalf of PETROLEUM DEVELOPMENT (TRUCIAL COAST) LTD.Confidential K No. C/451-1C/12.&gt;). Political Agency, Bahrain, the 10th July 1338. To The Manager, Petroleum Concessions Limited, BAHRAIN. Deer 8ir, Reference your letter No. PTC/CAT5/110C dated the 9th July 1938. 2. There is no objection to your making the presentation to the Shaikh of Sharjah. Yours faithfully, Political Agent, Bahrain.'N. C. 12.37. TELEGRAMS: PETCONCESS, BAHREIN (9 DIRECTORS: Lord Cadman, G.C.M.G. 1 n PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS CODES: BENTLEY'S SECOND PHRASE LIMITED / man, G.C.M.G. (Chairman) Cayrol . Fraser,C.B.E. S. Gulbenkian (formerly Armenian) B. A. Kessler (Dutch) L. M. Lefroy J. A. Meny (French) H. G. Seidel (U.S.A.) R. W. Sellers J. Skliros OA'fl PCL/SAA.15/1096. To H.B.M. T s Political Agent, Bahrain, BAHREIN PERSIAN GULF 7th July, 1938. 'Aj&gt; '1 Dear Sir, CONCBSSION PAYMENT, SHARJAH . We bring it to notice that the annual concession payment of Rs.30,000 is due to the Ruler of Sharjah on the 17th September, 1938. We attach a copy of our letter PCL/SAA.15 1095 dated 7th July, 1938 to the Ruler in this connection. Tours faithfully, For &amp; on behalf of PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LIMITED, / ? &lt; // hi (/v Ja^vliAGER. Enclos.. By Air Mail. P.Z. 537 y 19 3f /7 /—\ INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, 'kz AIGK58 Forwarded with the compliments of* the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. '7/f A copy has been sent to hy ^ Mail.India Office Confidential JT- Memo. B 467 SHARJAH OIL CONCESSION AND CONNECTED DOCUMENTSIndia Office Memo. B 467 Confidential SHARJAH OIL CONCESSION and CONNECTED DOCUMENTS No. 1. Commercial Agreement of 17th September 1937. No. 2. Political Agreement of 12th November 1937. No. 3. Letter dated 23rd December 1937 from Political Agent, Bahrein, to Sheikh of Sharjah. No. 4. Letter dated 26th March 1938 from Sheikh of Sharjah to Political Agent, Bahrein. No. 5. Letter dated 27th March 1938 fx-om Political Agent, Bahrein, to Sheikh of Sharjah. No. 6. Letter dated 30th March 1938 from Sheikh of Sharjah to Political Agent, Bahrein. No 7. Letter dated 3rd May 1938 from India Office to Peti*oleum Concessions, Limited. No. 8. Letter dated 4th May 1938 from Petroleum Concessions, Limited, to India Office. No. 9. Letter dated 17th May 1938 from India Office to Petroleum Concessions, Limited. No. 10. Letter dated 23rd May 1938 from Political Agent, Bahrein, to Sheikh of Shax-jah. 7347 A3 No. 1 PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LIMITED. Agreement made with the Shaikh of Sharjah on the 17th September 1937, with Annexure. In the Name of God the Merciful. This is an Agreement made at Sharjah, Arabia, on the Seventeenth day of September 1937, corresponding to the Eleventh day of Rajab 1356 between His Excellency Shaikh Sultan Bin Sagar in the exercise of his powers as Ruler of Sharjah, Arabia, on his own behalf and on behalf of and in the name of his heirs and successors in whom is or shall be vested for the time being the responsibility for the control and government of the State of Sharjah (hereinafter called “ the Shaikh ”) of the one part and Petroleum Concessions, Limited, a Company registered in Great Britain under the Companies Act, 1929, its successors and assigns (hereinafter called “ the Company ”) of the second part. ^ Article 1.— (a) The area to which this Agreement applies is the State of Sharjah including all islands and territorial waters appertaining thereto (hereinafter referred to as “ the State ”) being all that territory included in the Shaikhdom of Sharjah. The Shaikh agrees that when the territorial limits of the State of Sharjah have been determined the area covered by the Concession will be coterminous with the limits so determined. (b) The area within the State of Sharjah at present being used by Imperial Airways, Limited, and the Royal Air Force as an aerodrome, the buildings thereon, and all concerned with that area is entirely excluded from and for the purposes of this Agreement. Article 2. The period of this Agreement shall be 75 calendar years from the date of signature. The expression year, month and day used in this Agreement shall mean what is consistent with the English solar calendar and not any other. Further, the weights mentioned in this Agreement shall be reckoned on the English ton of 2,240 lbs. Article 3. The Shaikh hereby grants to the Company the exclusive right to explore search for drill for produce and win natural gas asphalt ozokerite crude petroleum and their products and cognate substances (hereinafter referred to as “ the substances ”) within the State, the exclusive ownership of all the substances so produced and won, the right to refine transport sell for use within and without the State or for export and to export or otherwise deal with or dispose of the substances, and the right to import export pump ship or otherwise transport the substances across or to any country or place at the Company’s discretion and the right to do all things necessary for the purpose of these operations. Article 4. If hereafter any neutral zone is created adjacent to the territory of the State, wherein the Shaikh shall have a co-equal and joint interest, the Shaikh hereby agrees to grant to the Company an oil concession over such neutral zone on terms to be agreed between the Shaikh, the Company and the joint ruler of such neutral zone. Article 5. In consideration of the rights granted by the Shaikh by this Agreement the Company shall pay to the Shaikh— (a) on signature of the agreement Rupees 60,000 (Sixty thousand). (b) Rupees 200,000 (Two hundred thousand) within a period of Sixty (60) days from the date upon which the Company declares in writing to the Shaikh that substances have been discovered in commercial quantities. If the Company should fail to declare so sooner, then the date of discovery of substances in commercial quantities shall be that date upon which the Company has completed and tested a well or wells capable of producing in accordance with first-class oil practice not less than Two thousand (2,000; English tons of clean substances per day for a period of Thirty (30) consecutive days.(c) Rupees 30,000 (Thirty thousand) at the end of each year from the date of signature hereof until the Company declares in writing to the bhaikh that substances have been discovered in commercial quantities in accordance wit i the sub-clause (b) of this Article 5, or until the Company commences production from quantities less than commercial quantities. In the event of sue i production by the Company from quantities less than commercial quantities either Rupees 50,000 (Fifty thousand) per year or Rupees 3 P e ^ English ton of 2,240 lbs. in respect of the substances so won and saved shall be payable, whichever is the greater. (d) At the end of every year from the date upon which the Company makes in writing to the Shaikh the declaration that the substances have been discovered in commercial quantities Rupees 90,000 (Ninety thousand) oi Rupees 3 (Three) per English ton of 2,240 lbs. in respect of the substances other than natural gas, won and saved during the preceding calendar year, whichever is the greater. (e) Annas 2 (Two) per 1,000 cubic feet of natural gas produced and sold. In calculating royalty for the purpose of this article account shall not be taken of any of the substances used by the Company in its operations or used by the Company’s employees within the State, necessary for their use, nor of any water or foreign matter which may be produced with the substances. Article 6 . The Company shall not carry on any operations within areas occupied by or devoted to the purposes of mosques, sacred buildings or graveyards. Article 7. The Company shall conduct its operations in a workmanlike manner and by appropriate scientific methods and shall take all reasonable measures to prevent the ingress of water to any petroleum-bearing strata and shall duly close any unproductive holes drilled by it and subsequently abandoned. The Company shall keep the Shaikh informed generally as to the progress and result of its drilling operations but such information shall be treated as confidential. Article 8 . Within three months after the expiry of each calendar year, the Company shall deliver to the Shaikh a statement of the amount of the substances won and saved and in the case of natural gas produced and sold during the said calendar year, and of the royalty which is or might have been payable under Article 5, together with a report of its operations during the said year. The Shaikh or his representative shall have the right to check such returns and statements, and all such returns and statements and the reports of the Company’s operations shall be treated as confidential by the Shaikh. Article 9.— {a) The Company shall have the right to import water, the substances, fuel, machinery, motor-cars and lorries, aircraft, equipment, plant, timber, utensils, iron work, building materials, food supplies, medicines, medical supplies, office equipment and household furniture, and other materials, equipment and goods of whatsoever nature required by the Company and its employees for the purpose of its operations hereunder and to export the substances and articles previously imported by the Company free of customs or export duty and taxes or other charges, but it shall pay on all personal goods, clothing and general merchandise imported by the Company for the personal use of its employees or for resale to them the ordinary duty in force for the time being in the State. Saving as in Article 5 and in this Article provided, the Company, its personnel, its operations, income, profits and property including the substances shall be exempt and free during the period of this Agreement from all present or future harbour duties, import duties, export duties, taxes, imposts and charges of any kind whether State or local, tolls and land surface rent of whatever nature. In consideration of the right herein granted the Company shall pay—in addition to the royalty per ton of Rupees Three (3) as provided in Article 5—to the Shaikh within Three (3) months after the close of each calendar year the sum of Four (4) annas per English ton of 2,240 lbs. in respect of the substances won and saved during the said calendar year. (b) The importation by the Company of firearms and other weapons is prohibited, except with the written permission of the Shaikh. (c) The Company may import such alcoholic drinks and liquors as the Company may require for the use of their foreign employees but only with the written permission of the Shaikh, and the Political Agent, Bahrain, or any authority deputed5 by them, but the Company shall not sell or give alcoholic drinks or liquors to the subjects of the Shaikh or to the subjects of adjoining Rulers who may be employed within the State. Article 10. The employees of the Company shall be allowed to enter into and to leave the State at all times without let or hindrance and free of all charge, and the Shaikh shall grant to the Company’s employees every facility required for the purpose of the Company’s operations hereunder. Bui the Company’s employees shall not interfere or by their actions cause any disturbance or cause opposition to the Shaikh’s authority within the State of Sharjah and the employees shall not go beyond the limit of their duties when employed within or when leaving the confines of the State of Sharjah for the purpose of this Agreement. Further in the event of any of the Company’s employees—whether he be a senior or a junior employee—committing an offence which may cause disorder or interfere with the moral or religious laws or interfere with the politics or subjects of the State of Sharjah or excite them to sedition, then the Shaikh may apply to the Political Agent, Bahrain, to send the person concerned—if a foreigner—out of the State of Sharjah, but if a subject of the Shaikh then the Shaikh may arrest the culprit and deal with him according to the laws of the State of Sharjah. Article 11.—(a) For the purpose of its operations hereunder the Company shall have the right without hindrance to construct, maintain and operate power stations, refineries, pipelines and storage tanks, facilities for water supply including boring for water, telegraph and telephone lines and installations and wireless installations, roads, railways, tramways, buildings, ports, harbours, harbour works, aircraft, buildings and landing places for aircraft, wharves and jetties, oil and coaling stations, with such lighting as may be requisite and any other facilities or works which the Company may consider necessary and for such purposes to use free of all payments any stone, sand, gravel, gypsum, lime, clay or similar materials or water which may be available provided always that the inhabitants of the State are not prevented from taking their usual requirements of these materials and that the water supply of the local inhabitants and nomad population who may be dependent on the same is not endangered. The Company at its discretion may select the position of any such works. The Company may likewise instal and operate without hindrance all such means of transportation by land, air and water as may be necessary for the effective conduct of its operations hereunder provided it is for the purposes of this Agreement. (b) The Company shall under normal conditions accept and transmit free of charge on its wireless and telegraph installations such of the Shaikh’s messages as will not interfere with the Company’s business, and in times of national emergency the Shaikh shall have the necessary use free of charge of the Company’s wireless and telegraph installations and railways for governmental purposes. (c) The Shaikh’s ships shall have the right to use harbours utilised or constructed by the Company provided that such use in no way hampers the Company or interferes in any way with the safety of its operations of which the Company shall be the sole judge. Any wharves or appurtenances constructed by the Company shall be for its exclusive use. The Company may use for the purpose of its operations the harbours along the coast of the State, but the Company shall not impede or interfere with the subjects of the Shaikh or their right to continue the use of existing harbours, anchorages, wharves and docks along the coast of the State at present utilised by them for their sailing craft and fishing boats. Article 12. The Company shall have the right and be given the necessary facilities— (а) for the import of the substances into the State from any adjoining territory by pipe-lines or otherwise for the purpose of operating any refinery which the Company may decide to erect within the State; and (б) for the transport of the substances by pipe-lines or otherwise over and across the State from and to any adjoining territory to any point suitable for the refining or shipping of the substances. And no duties, taxes, charges or dues of an} 7 nature whatsoever shall be levied in respect of such import or transport. 7347 4 ◄ B6 Article 13.—(a) The Company shall have free of cost the unrestricted use and occupation of and surface rights over all uncultivated lands of the State which the Company may need for the purpose of its operations and in particular the Company shall have the right to select an area or areas of land chosen by the Company with exclusive surface rights upon which to erect drilling rigs, pump stations, oil refineries, storage, terminal shipping and aircraft facilities and any other works required for the Company’s operations; and the Company may lease for such purposes any lands, houses or buildings with the consent of and on conditions to be arranged with the proprietors thereof, but the terms of such lease shall not be in excess of those ordinarily current in their respective localities. (6) The Company shall acquire only such lands, houses and buildings as are necessary for its operations under this Agreement. The Company shall inform the Shaikh from time to time of the land, houses and buildings which it requires to occupy for its operations; and land, houses and buildings previously acquired by the Company from the Shaikh but found no longer necessary for its operations shall be returned by the Company to the Shaikh free of cost. Article 14.—(a) The Company shall have the right to purchase at current market rates fuel, water, food, building and constructional materials and other supplies of every kind in connection with its operations hereunder; further the Shaikh grants to the Company the right to construct new roads for motor and general traffic, and to make use of all existing roads or tracks free of charge or taxes of any kind whatever. (6) The Company shall employ subjects of the Shaikh as far as possible for all work for which they are suited under the supervision of the Company’s skilled employees, but if the local supply of labour should in the judgment of the Company be inadequate or unsuitable the Company shall have the right to import labour, preference being given to labourers from neighbouring Arab countries who will obey the local laws. The Company shall also have the right to import skilled and technical employees. The Company shall pay to the workmen it employs a fair wage, such wage to be decided and stated by the Company at the time the workmen are engaged. Further, the fact of the Company employing subjects of the Shaikh shall not in any way whatever alter the status of such employees in respect of their rights, privileges and duties as subjects of the Shaikh, and such employees will remain in all ways subject to the jurisdiction of the laws and under the legal authority of the Shaikh in his capacity as the Ruler of the State of Sharjah. Article 15. The Shaikh shall give to the Company and its employees and property all protection in his power from theft, highway robbery, assault, wilful damage and destruction, and the Company may appoint in consultation with the Shaikh and itself pay trustworthy guards who shall at all times be subjects of the Shaikh unless the Shaikh permits otherwise to assist in protecting the property of the Company and its employees. The Company shall erect at its own expense suitable buildings for the accommodation of such guards at such places as the Company shall decide. Article 16. In measuring the substances for purposes of royalty the factor for conversion of the volume of oil into weight shall be such figure as may be determined and agreed upon between the Shaikh and the Company after the discovery of oil and the ascertainment of its specific gravity. The Company shall measure the substances by a method customarily used in good technical practice and the Shaikh by his representative duly authorised by him shall have the right to observe such measuring and to examine and test what ever appliances may be used for such measuring. Such representative shall comply with all necessary and usual safeguards for the prevention of fire and other accident; and shall make all examinations and tests at such times and in such manner as will cause the minimum of interference with the Company’s operations. If upon such examination or testing any such appliance shall be found to be out of order the Company will cause the same to be put in order at its own expense within a reasonable time, and if upon any such examination aforesaid any error shall be discovered in any such appliance, such error shall—if the Shaikh so decides after hearing the Company’s explanation—be considered to have existed for three (3) calendar months previous to the discovery thereof or from the last occasion of examining the same in case such occasion shall be within such period of threecalendar months and the royalty shall be adjusted accordingly. If the Company should find it necessary to alter, repair or replace any measuring appliances it shall give reasonable notice to the Shaikh or his representative to enable a representative of the Shaikh to be present during such alteration, repair or replacement. I he Company shall keep full and correct records of all measurements as aforesaid and the said representative of the Shaikh shall have access at all reasonable times to such records and shall be at liberty to make extracts from them. Suck recoids shall be treated as confidential by the Shaikh and his representative. Article 17.—(a) The Company shall have the right at any time after the expiry of three years from the date of signature of this Agreement to give the Shaikh six months’ notice in writing of its intention to terminate this Agreement and this Agreement shall absolutely determine on the date fixed for such termination in such notice. (6) If such notice be given not later than 30 years after the date of such signature the Company shall be entitled on such determination to remove free of all taxes and duties all plant buildings stores material and property of every sort provided that for a period of three months from the receipt of such notice the Shaikh may purchase—should he so desire—the same at a price equal to the replacement value at that date less depreciation which price shall be agreed or failing agreement settled under Article 24 hereof. (c) If such notice be given later than 30 years after the date of such signature all the property aforesaid shall become the property of the Shaikh free of all cost. Article 18. On the expiry of this Agreement at the end of the period of 75 years provided in Article 2 or any extension or renewal of that period all the movable and immovable property of the Company in the State shall be handed over to the Shaikh free of cost. Producing wells or borings at the time of such expiry shall be handed over in reasonably good order and repair. Article 19. Subject to the provisions of Article 22 hereof the Shaikh shall have the right to terminate this Agreement and to take without payment all the property of the Company in the State if— (a) the Company shall fail to make any of the payments prescribed in this Agreement within six months of the date on which they fall due ; or (b) the Company shall be in default in respect of an arbitration award under Article 24 hereof. Article 20. Nothing in this Agreement shall be read as restricting in any way the right of the Shaikh to grant to other parties concessions or permits for materials other than the substances as defined in Article 3 provided that the operations and rights of the Company hereunder are not thereby injuriously affected. If the bhaikh should at any date subsequent to the date of signature of this Agreement grant to any other parties concessions or permits as aforesaid the Shaikh undertakes that such concessions shall contain provisions requiring the holders thereof to abstain from damaging, impeding or interfering with the property, operations and interests of the Company. Deposits of minerals such as gold, silver, copper, lead, potash, sulphur and salt or the like which may be discovered by the Company shall be reported to the Shaikh and shall not be worked by the Company except under special concession or permit from the Shaikh. Further, the Company shall instruct Geologists to mark carefully and report to the Company any area and its location which appears to them to give promise of yielding minerals or fresh water from a bore-hole and the Company undertakes to keep the Shaikh informed of all such minerals and water reports and the sites of the area or areas. Article 21. The Shaikh hereby agrees that the Company may transfer the obligations and benefits of this Agreement to a British Company to be called “Petroleum Development (Trucial Coast) Limited” or to any other Company registered within the British Empire. Article 22. Failure on the part of the Company to fulfil any of the conditions of this Agreement shall not give the Shaikh any claim against the Company or be deemed a breach of this Agreement in so far as such failure arises from force majeure, and if through force majeure the fulfilment b} r the Companv of any of the conditions of this Agreement be delayed, the period of such delay shall be added to the periods fixed by this Agreement.Force majeure as used in this Agreement includes the Act of God, war, insurrection, riot, civil commotion, tide, storm, tidal wave, flood, lightning, explosion, fire, earthquakes and any other happening which the Company could not reasonably prevent or control. Article 23. The Shaikh shall not by general or special legislation or by administrative measures or by any other act whatever annul this Agreement except as provided in Article 19. 0 .. No alteration shall be made in the terms of this Agreement by either the Shaikh or the Company except in the event of the Shaikh and the Company jointly agreeing that it is desirable in the interests of both parties to make certain alterations, deletions or additions to this Agreement. Article 24.—(a) If at any time during the currency of this Agreement any difference or dispute shall arise between the parties hereto concerning the inter pretation or execution hereof, or anything herein contained, or in connection herewith, or the rights or liabilities of either party hereunder, the same shall, failing any agreement to settle it in any other way, be referred to two arbitrators, one of whom shall be chosen by each party, and a referee, who shall be chosen by the arbitrators before proceeding to arbitration. (6) Each party shall nominate its own arbitrator within 60 days after delivery of a request so to do by the other party, failing which its arbitrator may at the request of the other party be designated by the British Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. In the event of the arbitrators failing to agree within 60 days after being chosen or designated the British Political Resident in the Persian Gulf may appoint a referee at the request of the arbitrators or of either of them. (c) The decision of the arbitrators, or in a case of a difference of opinion between them, the decision of the referee, shall be final and binding upon both parties. (d) In giving a decision the arbitrators or the referee shall specify an adequate period of delay, during which the party against whom the decision is given shall conform to the decision, and that party shall be in default only if that party has failed to conform to the decision prior to the expiry of that period and not otherwise. (e) The place of arbitration shall be such as may be agreed by the parties and in default of agreement shall be London. Article 25. The Company shall make all payments that become due to the Shaikh under this Agreement into the Shaikh’s account at the Eastern Bank, Ltd., Bahrain, and the Bank’s receipt shall be a full discharge for the Company in respect to the payment of the sum stated in the Bank’s receipt. Should the Shaikh decide to grant permission for a Bank to open a branch or Agency in Sharjah the Shaikh shall consult with the Company as to which Bank shall be given the permission. The Shaikh may from time to time designate in writing another Bank or Banks for the purpose of this Article. Article 26. The Shaikh may select a local man to act as a confidential person as between the Shaikh and the Company’s Representative and to assist in procuring the labour that the Company may require. The salary of the Shaikh’s confidential person so appointed shall be paid by the Company through the Shaikh in Sharjah and shall be at the rate of Rupees Four hundred (400) per month. Article 27. This Agreement is written in English and translated into Arabic. In Witness whereof the parties to this Agreement have set their hands the day and year first above written. And God is Gracious. The Company, The Shaikh, ERNEST 0. PARKES. SULTAN BIN SAGAR. (Signed in Arabic.) In the presence of T. HICKINBOTHAM, Political Agent, Bahrain. 17th September 1937.Annexuke. To His Excellency, Shaikh Sultan Bin Sagar, Ruler of Sharjah. Your Excellency, Sharjah, 17th September 1937. Greetings: la confirmation of the arrangement made between Your Excellency and myself—acting for and on behalf of Petroleum Concessions, Limited—it is agreed that the Company shall pay to Your Excellency—for your personal account with the Eastern Bank Limited, Bahrain—the sum of Rupees Eight hundred and thirty-three, Annas five and Pies four only (Rs. 833. 5. 4) per mensem. Such monthly payments shall begin to accrue from the date of signature of the Sharjah Oil Concession Agreement and shall continue until that date upon which the yearly payment of Rs. 50,000 becomes operative as provided for in Article No. 5 (c) of the above-mentioned Concession Agreement. 2.. When the said yearly payment of Rs. 50,000 becomes operative then the monthly payments of Rs. 833. 5. 4 shall cease and Your Excellency shall have no further claim upon the Company in respect of this latter provided that the Company has paid all the monthly payments that may have become due prior to the date upon which the annual payment of Rs. 50,000 became effective. 3. But should it become obligatory upon the Company—during the period that ihe annual rental of Rs. 30,000 is operative—to increase the yearly rental payment to Rs. 90,000 to comply with the conditions laid down in Article No. 5 (d), then the monthly payments of Rs. 833. 5. 4 shall cease upon that date upon which the yearly rental of Rs. 90,000 becomes operative, and this latter date shall replace that specified in paragraphs 1 and 2 hereof in connection with the annual payment of Rs. 50,000 becoming operative. I have the honour, Sir, to remain, Your Excellency’s obedient Servant, ERNEST O. PARKES, For and on behalf of Petroleum Concessions, Limited. Schedule No. 1. The provisions of this SCHEDULE No. 1—and now attached to the Oil Concession Agreement (of the same date) for the State of Sharjah—forms an integral part of the above-mentioned Concession Agreement and has equal validity thereto. Reference to Article No. 14 (a) The Company may construct roads within the town areas of the State of Sharjah, but must first obtain the consent and written permission of the Shaikh to do so. 14 (6) The Company shall train such subjects of the Shaikh that may be employed by the Company for office and technical work ; for the purposes of such training the Company shall afford such native employees all reasonable facilities so that they may improve their professional efficiency and the Company shall make necessary arrange ments for them. 2b. The Shaikh shall select a person as his Representative in whom he shall have confidence and it is not necessary that such person be conversant with the English language. Should any dispute occur in respect of this Agreement then both the English and Arabic text shall have equal status. 27.m 10 A. Any amount paid by the Company to the Shaikh in respect of this Agreement shall not be returnable in any circumstances. B. The period allowed within which drilling shall begin is that of nine calendar years from the date of signature of the Concession Agreement. If the period of nine years stipulated above is expired and the Company did not do geological examination and field work, &amp;c. constantly with every diligence and activity then the Agreement shall be annulled. C. Until the Shaikh permits the Company in writing the Company may not enter for the present nor undertake any work in the two areas named Al-Fayah and Wadi Al-Hulu. D. The Company shall use the Shaikh’s flag within the State of Sharjah. The Company ERNEST 0. PARKES. In the presence of The Shaikh, SULTAN BIN SAGAR. (Signed in Arabic.) T. HICKINBOTHAM, Political Agent, Bahrain. 17th September 1937.No. 2 Dated 12th Is ovember 1937 HIS MAJESTY’S GOVERNMENT IN THE UNITED KINGDOM AND PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LIMITED Agreement relating to the Sharjah Oil Concession Stamp THIS AGREEMENT dated the Twelfth day of November One Thousand nine hundred and thirty-seven is made BETWEEN His Majesty’s Government in the United Kingdom (hereinafter called “His Majesty’s Government ”) of the one part and Petroleum Concessions Limited (hereinafter called “ the Company ” which expression shall where the context so admits be deemed to include its successors and/or assignees and shall also be deemed to include any subsidiary Company) of the other part. WHEREAS Petroleum Development (Trucial Coast) Ltd. is a subsidiary Company of Petroleum Concessions Limited. AND WHEREAS in the event of the Company obtaining a concession from the Sheikh of Sharjah (hereinafter called “ the Sheikh ”) certain responsibilities will devolve on His Majesty’s Government, the Company has agreed with His Majesty’s Government as follows : — L Petroleum Concessions Limited and any subsidiary company shall be and remain a British company registered in Great Britain and having its principal place of business in Great Britain, and its Chairman shall at all times be a British subject. 2. The Agreement between the Company and the Sheikh shall not be transferred to any other company without the prior consent in writing of His Majesty’s Govern ment and any other company to which that Agreement may be transferred shall be and remain a British company registered in Great Britain and having its principal place of business in Great Britain, and its Chairman shall at all times be a British subject. 3. The employees of the Company in Sharjah shall at all times be British subjects or subjects of the Sheikh, provided that, with the consent of His Majesty’s Government, such persons of other nationality as are required for the efficient carrying on of the undertaking may be employed. Notwithstanding anything contained in the Agreement between the Company and the Sheikh, the importation of foreign native labour shall be subject to the approval of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. 4. The Company in all except unimportant or routine matters shall deal with the Sharjah authorities through a Chief Local Representative in the Persian Gulf, ^ who shall be a British subject. The approval of His Majesty's Government shall be required for the person so designated. He will be ordinarily resident in Sharjah or Bahrein and will be responsible for the Company’s local relations with the Sharjah authorities, which shall, except in routine or unimportant matters, be conducted through the political representative of His Majesty’s Government in Bahrein or through any other person whom the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf may from time to time designate. 5. Subject to the terms of the Agreement between the Company and the Sheikh the Company undertakes at all times to pay due deference to the wishes of the Sheikh and to the advice of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf and of the Political Officers subordinate to him. 6. Any right given to the Company under its Agreement with the Sheikh to utilise means of transportation by air shall be subject to any general regulations for civil aircraft made by the Sheikh on the advice of His Majesty’s Government, and to any instructions which may be issued by the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.12 7. Notwithstanding anything contained in the Agreement between the Company and the Sheikh the Company shall not have the right to use or occupy, and shall not include in the areas to be acquired or utilised for the purposes of its operations, anv sites which may have been selected by or on behalf of the Sheikh or 1 is Majesty’s Government for defence purposes, for aerodromes, aeroplane or seaplane bases or for wireless and telegraph installations or in connection with the develop ment of harbours, provided that with the consent of His Majesty s Government which shall not be unreasonably withheld the Company shall have the right to use for the purposes of its operations such harbours as may be developed by the bheiKh or His Majesty’s Government if there is not reasonable harbour accommodation available elsewhere. Subject to the terms of the Agreement between the Company and the Sheikh harbours developed by the Company shall be under its complete and exclusive control. 8 Telegraph, wireless and telephone installations, if any, maintained by the Company shall be for use only in its business and as provided in the concession, and shall be so constructed and operated that their operations shall not interfere with the operations of such wireless, telegraph or telephone installations as may be established by the Sheikh or His Majesty’s Government, or their agent. 9. In the event of a state of national emergency or war (of the existence of either of which His Majesty’s Government shall be the sole judge) His Majesty s Government shall have the right of pre-emption of all the oil produced in Sharjah in accordance with the terms of the Schedule hereto. 10. The Company shall obtain the prior permission of the Sheikh before working in any particular area, in order that the Sheikh may be in a position to fulfil his responsibilities for the protection of the Company. The Sheikh shall not unreasonably withhold such permission, and in any case in which the Company feels that the free movement of its personnel within the concession area is being unnecessarily restricted the matter shall be referred for decision to the Political Resident. H j n phe event of notice of termination of the Agreement between the Company and the Sheikh being given on the ground that the Company has failed to observe any of the terms of the present Agreement between the Company and His Majesty’s Government, the arbitration provisions of the said Agreement between the Company and the Sheikh shall apply if the Company considers that notice of termination on such grounds is not justified, and in that event the Sheikh shall not cancel the said Agreement until arbitration takes place in accordance with the said provisions and unless the Company fails to comply with the award of the arbitrators within the reasonable time which shall be fixed by the arbitrators for so doing. IN WITNESS whereof John Charles Walton, C.B., on behalf of His Majesty’s Government has hereunto set his hand and seal and the Company has hereunto caused its Common Seal to be affixed the day and year first above written. THE SCHEDULE above referred to. Pre-emption Clause. In the event of a state of national emergency or war (of the existence of which His Majesty’s Government shall be the sole judge)— (1) His Majesty’s Government shall have the right of pre-emption of all crude oil gotten under the concession granted by the Sheikh to the Company and of all the products thereof and shall have the right to require the Company to the extent of any refining capacity it may have in Sharjah to produce oil fuel that shall comply with the Admiralty specifications at the time provided that Sharjah oil be of a suitable kind and quality for this purpose. (2) The Company shall use its utmost endeavours to increase so far as reasonably possible with existing facilities the supply of oil and/or products thereof for the Government to the extent required by the Government. (o) The Company shall with every reasonable expedition and so as to avoid demurrage on the vessel or vessels engaged to convey the same, do its utmost to deliver all oil or products of oil purchased by the Government under theirsaid right of pre-emption in the quantities at the time and in the manner required by the Government at a convenient place of shipment or at a place of storage in Sharjah to be determined by His Majesty’s Government. In the event of a vessel employed to carry any such oil or products thereof on behalf of his Majesty being detained on demurrage at the port of loading the Company shall pay the amount due for demurrage according to the terms of the charter party and/or the rates of loading previously agreed with the Company unless the delay is due to causes beyond the control of the Company. Any dispute which may arise as to whether the delay is due to causes beyond the control of the Company shall be settled by agreement between His Majesty’s Government and the Company, and, in default of such agreement, the question shall be referred to two arbitrators, one to be chosen by His Majesty’s Government (or the Political Resident) and the other by the Company, with power to appoint an umpire in case of disagreement, such arbitration to be held in England and to be deemed a reference to arbitration under the provisions of the Arbitration Acts 1889 to 1934 (52 and 53 Viet. c. 49 ; 24 and 25 Geo. V. c. 14) of the Imperial Parliament, or any statutory modification or re-enactment thereof for the time being in force. (4) r l he price to be paid for all oil or products of the refining or treatment of oil taken in pre-emption by His Majesty’s Government shall be either (a) as specified in a separate agreement or (b) if no such agreement shall have been entered into, a fair price for the time being at the point of delivery as the same shall be settled by agreement between His Majesty’s Government and the Company, or in default of such agreement by arbitration in the manner provided by the last preceding sub-clause. To assist in arriving at a fair price at the point of delivery the Company so required, particulars of the quantities, descriptions and prices of Sharjah oil or products sold to other customers and of charters or contracts entered into for carriage and shall exhibit to His Majesty’s Government original or authenticated copies of contracts or charter parties entered into for the sale and/or carriage of such oil or products. (5) His Majesty’s Government shall be at liberty to take control of the works, plant and premises of the Company in Sharjah, and in such event the Company shall conform to and obey all directions issued by or on behalf of His Majesty’s Government. Compensation shall be paid to the Company for any loss or damage that may be proved to have been sustained by the Company by reason sub-clause. Any such compensation shall be settled by agreement between His Majesty’s Government and the Company or, in default of agreement, by arbitration in the manner provided by sub-clause (3). Signed Sealed and Delivered by the shall furnish for the confidential information of His Majesty’s Government, if of the exercise by His Majesty’s Government of the powers conferred by this said John Charles Walton, C.B., on behalf of His Majesty’s Govern ment in the presence of— J. C. WALTON (l.s.) A. C. B. SYMON, India Office. (seal) f W. FRASER, Director. E. J. BROWN, Secretary.14 No. 3 C!opy of letter from H. Weightman, Esq., Political Agent, Bahrain, dated the 2'dr'd December 1937, No. 0/929-10/12, to Shaikh Sultan bin Saqr, Ruler of Sharjah. After compliments, His Majesty’s Government have been furnished with a copy of the Agreement signed by you on the 17th September 1937 [No. 1] corresponding to the 11th day of Rajab 1356 granting to Petroleum Concessions, Limited, an oil concession in respect of your territory on the understanding that the Agreement is subject to the approval of His Majesty’s Government. 2. Under instructions from His Majesty’s Government I now enclose a cop} r of an Agreement which has been concluded between His Majesty’s Government and Petroleum Concessions, Limited, in London on 12th November 1937 [No. 2]. 3. I am to inform you that the understanding described below has been reached with the Company :— (a) Should any of the terms of the Agreement between you and the Company be inconsistent or in conflict with the terms of the Agreement between the Company and His Majesty’s Government signed in London on 12th November the Agreement between you and the Company will to the extent of any such inconsistency or conflict be subordinate to and be controlled by the terms of the Agreement between the Company and His Majesty’s Government. (b) If the Company should fail to observe any of the terms of the Agreement between the Company and His Majesty’s Government signed in London on 12th November 1937, or if the alleged failure having been disputed by the Company the matter has been referred to arbitration under Article 24 of the Company’s Agreement with you (which is made applicable to the case by Article 11 of the Agreement between the Company and His Majesty’s Government) and the Company should not remedy such failure within the reasonable time which should be fixed by the arbitrators for so doing then in these cases, as in the cases mentioned in Article 19 of the Company’s Agreement with you, but in no other, the Company agrees that you will be entitled to terminate the Agreement between the Company and yourself, and that all properties of the Company within your territory shall become your property, and that they will hand over to you free of cost land granted to the Company by you and any lands or buildings which the Company may have bought and any houses or buildings constructed by the Company and all other irremovable property of the Company within your territory, including the producing wells and borings which shall be handed over in reasonably good order and repair. 4. Please let me have a reply to this letter to the effect that you understand the nature of the arrangements set out above and that you are prepared to agree to them. On receipt of your reply His Majesty’s Government will obtain from the Company formal confirmation of their acceptance of the arrangements and will communicate such confirmation to you. Usual ending, 0k. (Sd.) H. WEIGHTMAN, Political Agent, Bahrain. No. 4 Translation of letter No. 2, dated the 23rd Muharram 1357 (2Qth March 1938), from Shaikh Sultan bin Saqr, Ruler of Sharjah, to H. Weightman, Esq., I.C.S., Political Agent, Bahrain. After compliments, In reply to your letter dated the 20th Shauwal 1356 [No. 3], equivalent to the 23rd December 1937, I beg to inform you that I have taken notice of the conditions set out in your letter and that I agree to them. I undertake, moreover, that I will be guided by the advice of His Majesty’s Government in regard to my termination of the concession which is referred to in paragraph 3 (b) of your letter. Usual ending.No. 5 °f letter from H. Weightmun, Esq., Political Agent, Bahrain, dated the -tth March 1938. Eo. C'/202-l()/J 2, to Shaikh Sultan bin Saqr, Ruler of Sharjah. After compliments, ^ ^ re ference to the Agreement signed by you on the 17th September 1937 o. 1J, corresponding to the 11th day of Rajab 1356, granting to Petroleum Concessions, Limited, an oil concession in respect of your territory, 1 have been directed by His Majesty’s Government to inform you that, subject to the formal confirmation by the Company of the arrangements described in my letter of the uzr ^ ecem ^ er 1^37 [No. 3], to which you have agreed in your letter of the loth March 1938 [No. 4], corresponding to the 23rd Muharram 1357, they are prepared to accord their approval to the concession provided you accept the following condition, namely, that should jmu wish to grant permission to a Bank to open a branch or agency in Sharjah, as mentioned in Article 25 of the Concession, y ou will obtain His Majesty s Government’s approval before entering into any negotiations with the Bank. Please let me know whether this condition is accepted by you. Usual ending, (Sd.) H. WEIGHTMAN, Political Agent, Bahrain No. 6 Translation of letter dated the 21th Muharram 1357 (i.e. 2&gt;0th March 1938) from Shaikh Sultan bin Saqr, Ruler of Sharjah, to H. Weightrnan, Esq., I.C.S., Political Agent, Bahrain. After compliments, In reply to your letter No. C/202-10/12, dated the 24th Muharram 1357, equivalent to the 27th March 1938 [No. 5], 1 beg to inform you that should 1 wish to grant permission to a Bank to open a branch or agency in Sharjah, I will obtain His Majesty’s Government’s approval before entering into any negotiations with the Bank. Usual ending. No. 7 Copy of letter from India Office to Petroleum Concessions, Limited, dated 3rd May 1938, No. P.Z. 2797/38. Sir, I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to enclose herewith for the information of Petroleum Concessions, Limited, a copy of a letter, No. C/929-10/J2, dated 23rd December 1937, from the Political Agent, Bahrein, to the Sheikh of Sharjah [No. 3], together with a translation of the latter’s reply dated 26th March 1938 [No. 4], in regard to certain points which arise in connection with the oil concession granted (subject to the approval of His Majesty’s Government) to your Company by the Sheikh of Sharjah on the 17th September 1937 [No. 1], and in connection with the Political Agreement of the 12th November 1937 [No. 2], between your Company and His Majesty’s Government, regarding the said concession. 2. I am to request that in accordance with the unofficial understanding already reached, your Company will now be good enough formally to confirm their acceptance of the arrangements embodied in the Political Agent’s letter of the 23rd December 1937, as binding on them. 3. On receipt of a letter from the Company accepting the arrangements mentioned above, the Marquess of Zetland will convey to the Company His Majesty’s Government’s formal approval of the oil concession granted to the Company bv the Sheikh of Sharjah. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, (Sd.) J. P. GIBSON.16 No. 8 Copy of letter from Petroleum Concessions, Limited, to Indio, Office, dated, 4:th May 1938, No. P.C. 31. Sir I have the honour to acknowledge receipt of your letter No. P.Z. 2797/38,. dated 3rd May [No. 7], relating to a concession obtained during 1937 by this Company from the Shaikh of Sharjah. I beg hereby formally to confirm the Company’s acceptance of the arrangements embodied in letter No. C/929/10/12, dated 23rd December 1937, from the Political Agent, Bahrain, to the Ruler of Sharjah [No 3j. and confirmed in the reply of the latter dated 23rd Muharram 1357 (26th March 1938) [No. 4]. The Company will be glad to receive notice of His Majesty’s Government’s formal approval of the concession concerned. We have the honour to be, Sir, Your obedient Servant, for Petroleum Concessions, Limited, (Sd.) Managing Director. No. 9 Copy of letter from India Office to Petroleum Concessions, Limited, dated 17ih May 1938, No. P.Z. 3176/38. Sir, I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to acknowledge the receipt of your letter dated the 4th May (No. P.C. 31) [No. 8], on the subject of the Sharjah Oil Concession, and to express on behalf of His Majesty’s Government their formal approval of the concession granted to the Company by the Sheikh of Sharjah on the 17th September 1937. 2. Copies of this correspondence are being sent to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf with a view to action being taken as indicated in paragraph 4 of Mr. Weightman’s letter dated the 23rd December 1937 to the Sheikh of Sharjah [No. 3]. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, (Sd.) R. PEEL. No. 10 Copt) of letter from H. Weightman, Esq., Political Agent, Bahrain, dated 23rd May 1938, No. C/339-10/126, to Shaikh Sultan bin Sagr, Rider of Sharjah. After compliments, With reference to paragraph 4 of my letter No. C/929-10/12 dated the 23rd December 1937 [No. 3], I have been instructed by His Majesty’s Government to inform you that the arrangements set forth in that letter and your acceptance of them conveyed in your letter No. 2 dated the 23rd Muharram 1357 (corresponding to the 26th March 1938) [No. 4], have been communicated to Petroleum Concessions, Limited, and that the Company formally confirm their acceptance of these arrangements. 2. I am now to express to you on behalf of His Majesty’s Government their approval of the Agreement concluded by you on the 17th September 1937 with Petroleum Concessions Limited [No. 1]. Usual ending, (Sd.) H. WEIGHTMAN, Political Agent, Bahrain.. 7347 Wt 17961/P 177 150 7.38TELEGRAMS : PETCONCESS, BAHREIN CODES : BENTLEY’S SECOND PHRASE PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LIMITED instructed by our London principals to notify E. H. the Sultan of Muscat and the Shaikhs of Sharjah, Dubai and Kalba that, owing to war conditions, there is nothing to report on the Company f s operations in their territories for the year ending December 1940. We enclose copies of the letters dispatched. DIRECTORS : Sie J.Kri Cadroan, G.C.M.G. (Chairman) BAHREIN r\. L-'. W. Fraser, C.B.E. PERSIAN GULF C. S. Gulbenkian (formerly Armenian) J. B A. Kessler (Dutch) L. M. Lefroy n. u. aeiaei i R. W. Sellers J. Skliros PCL/OAC.3/2374 CQ DENTIAL 6th April, 1941 To H.B.M.’s Political Agent Bahrain. Sir annual reports We have the honour to inform you that we have been We have the honour to be Your most obedient servants For 8c on behalf of PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LIMITED .4 Enel ACMConfidential No. C/318 - 10/12 The Political Agent, Bahrain, Presents his compliments to:— The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document ( s ) The agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf. Dated 8th April 1941 Reference to previous correspondence: Description df Enclosure. Name and Date. /N Letter No. PCL/CAC.3/2374 dated 6th April 1941 from the Manager, Petroleum Concessions Limited, Bahrain, with enclosures. Subject. Annual Reports on the working of the concessions on the Trucial Coast Sheikhdoms by P.C.L.PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LTD. BAHRAIN PERSIAN GULF. My dear Bird, DO/SA. 15/4075 llth December, 1945. Confidential. BAHRAIN RECEIPT. , ii.l&amp;L if part We are to arrange for cancellation of part of the Sharjah OillConcession and in view of its importance would very much like your official translator to confirm that the Arabic translation conveys the correct meaning. As you may be aware Public F.elations absorbed our usual translators and the one we are using now is new to this class of work. If you will permit your man to glance through it we shall be most grateful and be pleased to pay any fee to him you may think appropriate. I enclose three drafts - a letter to the shaikh and two alternative forms of the amendment marked 'A' and n B'. We are of course addressing the Political Agent formally on this subject with copies of th e documents concerned. Yours sincerely, Ends. 3 Capt. R.E.R.Bird, Asst. Political Agent, Bahrain. £ tO - i/Lujl cl d^JL ItZa CsC- ■D.O. No. C/1125. The 13th of December, 1945. My dear Packer, Please refer to your letter No. DO/SA. 15/4075, dated the 11th December, 1945. 2. I return herewith your two drafts of the Amendment to the Sharjah Oil Concession and your draft covering letter to the Shaikh of Sharjah. 3. Our Head Munshi is away at the moment but Mr. Ali Tajir of the Public Relations Office has looked through these drafts and made certain corrections. If you wish to, please pay him whatever fee you have paid for similar work in the past. Yours.sincerely.C.12.37. CODES: BENTLEY'S SECOND PHRASE PETROLEUM DEVELOPMENT LIMITED &amp;• o-h - tra /*es Directors i BAHREIN CONFIDENTIAL PERSIAN GULF T/SA. 15/4074 8th December, 1945. To H.B.M 1 s Political Agent Bahrain. Confidential. rrTT atm t?^OEIPT, Sir, CANCE LIATION OF PARAORAPH B OF SCHEDULE NQ.l TO THE SHARJAH OIL AGKEK^NT OF 19 57' We have the honour to refer to paragraph B of Schedule No.l to the Sharjah Oil Agreement of 1937 extracted as under for ready reference n The period allowed within which^drilling shall begin is thatAof -9 calendar years from the date of signature oi\the Cpncession Agreement. If the period of 9\ye^rs stipulated above is^ expired and the Company did not do^geological examination and field work etc. constantly with every diligence and activity then the Agreement shall be annulled.” As you are doubtless aware geological exploration on the Trucial Coast was suspended during the war and^ without this essential prelude the commencement of drilling cannot be justified. As you know the Company has already approached the Ruler of Sharjah with a view to resumption of geological work in the Jabal Faiyah area to commence in January 1946, but 6 years have been lost and\the period allowed expires in September 1946. vide the abovementioned paragraph B. • • •T/SA, 15/4074 (concld.) It is proposed that Mr. Lermitte should^proceed shortly to Sharjah to arrange this cancellation. Copies of the letter to the Shaikh and the form of agreement he is to take with him are enclosed. *ou will note that provision has been made for a payment to the Ruler in return for the cancellation if this proves necessary. We shall he grateful if you will inform us if this suggested procedure is in order and for your comments before Mr. Lermitte leaves for Sharjah. We have the honour to he Sir, Your most obedient servants, For &amp; on behalf of PETROLEUM DEVELOPMENT (TRUCIAL COAST) LIMITED Ends .32. lN '-U / ' \ ' / i*v / • 4 /' T/SA.15/4073 8th December, 1945 V w \ Your Excellency, We have the honour to refer to To H.E.Sultan bin Sagr al Qassim Ruler of Sharjah, Sharjah* paragraph B of Schedule No#l to the Si Oil Concession concluded with Your 4&gt;V«a 1 &lt;7 4- Vi Q ATk'V am H a t* Excellency on the 17th September 1937. Your Excellency will understand that the date of ccanmencement of drilling is dependent upon the results of geological examination of the territory concerned and this examination is an essential prelude in the abovementioned paragraph B of Schedule No.l you agreed to a period of nine years for geological exploration of which two years only were available before thw war broke out in 1939 and the Company was forn by conditions created by this war to discontinue geological work on the Trucial Coast. The six war years have been lost and the Company have not sufficient data on which to select a drilling site. As Your Excellency is aware the Company have taken the first opportunity of recommencing its to the drilling. Your Excellency will note that • * • *• • • &gt; LJ -j jjr ij' .n ait - { •*' ^ Ji L*1 v v.r- i ‘_^il - V^v-U &gt;f&gt; , I u&gt;. ^ * ; K J*++~ '■ •« 1JI ^ i- * Jf* jJUj ■ jmkx, • • j* • L. ‘ «. ^IhJ ’ »j^ ( ^. •J«* ’V mgmt^ i J j3i,4*, - ? * JA ^»&gt;»r&gt;*'■*■ .'.•»’ ' '' f~-. -it Al wtjP*r J» J ■ wlL«gr/ ^ ? t *4 U.J J«Jt* r ^u. &amp;J t *&gt; LJ) &gt; i it Ijjj * tr. ji - 2 - T/SA. 15/4073 (contd.) geological work in your territory end have already approached you to arrange for our geologists to enter the Jabal Faiyah area next month but much time mist lapse before a drilling point can be located and the period of nine years originally agreed on expires in reptember 1946. In these circumstances we are sure Tour Excellency will agree that it is reasonable for the Company to request that paragraph B of Schedule Ho.l, which fixed a period within which drilling must begin but which did not foresee or take into account the enforced interruption caused by this war, be cancelled and we have been directed by our Managing Director to approach four Excellency with reference to this cancellation. Mr. Lermitte will be visiting Your Excellency and will put before you a form of agreement covering this cancellation for Your Excellency’s consideration. H.B.M’a Politics! Agent,Bahrain, has been informed and has a copy of the proposed form of agreement. We have the honour to be Your Excellency’s most obedient servants, For &amp; on behalf of PETFOLKtJM DEVKLOP^SNT(TRUCIAL COAST) LIMITED. MANAGER ACMTelegram SCPad)* From Political Agent, Bahraih. To Political Resident, Bushire. No. 622. Dated 23rd December, 1D45. Correspondence ending with oilr Printed Letter No.C.313 of the 3th April, 1941. 2. P.C.Lt have informed me that the geological survey party will proceed to Sharjah within the next ten days and that the Company think it advisable for Lermitte to negotiate cancellation of paragraph B of Schedule One to the Concession of September 17th 1937 as early as possible. This is necessary since because of the war six years have been lost and it is not now possible to select sites and commence drilling within the period of nine years expiring September 1946. 3. The Company 1 s proposal is to 'arrange the cancellation' by means of a letter and amended form of agreement and also 'provision has been made for a payment to the Ruler in return for cancellation if that proves necessary.' 4. My comments are (paragraph two) that an extended period is necessary in the circumstances and that the method proposed is suitable. (Paragraph three) The Shaikh is almost certain to consider the question of compensation and I think we can refrain from advising him unless he refers to us. I am informed that the Company are prepared to pay up to half one lakh of rupees. 5. No date is mentioned by which drilling must commence. This in view of the fact that the Company are proceeding as fast as possible (I learn they are sending party of twentyfour geo physicistsphysicists, etc,, to work from October 1046) is not objectionable. If the Shaikh raises the point I suggest that a limit might be set to cover the lost six years, 6, I think we can convey to the Company our no objection to the suggested procedure but am sending copies of correspondence by Seabelle. LEI POLITICAL(§) 3.y CONFIDENTIAL. Political Agency, Bahrain, No. c/ 1136. The 24th December, 1945. The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to The Ron’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Bushire, and has the honour to send him a copy of the under mentioned document. The letter was not actually received by me until the 18th December. REFERENCE TO PREVIOUS CORRESPONDENCE: Bahrain telegram No. 622 dated 23rd Dec., 1945. Description of Enclosure: NAME &amp; DATE D SUBJECT P.C.L. letter No. T/SA.15/. ^Cancellation of Para.B 4074, dated the 8th December,0 of Schedule No.l to theTelegram S.6. From Political Resident, Bushire. India Office, London. Political Agent, Bahrain. To Repeated Copy by post to Government of India, New Delhi. No. 23 Dated and received 3rd January 1946 IMPORTANT. Bahrain Manager of Petroleum Development Trucial Coast has informed Political Agent, Bahrain, that he has been instructed to negotiate with Shaikh of Sharjah for cancellation of paragraph B of Schedule 1 to Sharjah Oil Concession. Provision has been made for payment to Ruler in return should this prove necessary. an extension up to six years (to cover period of war on account of nine year period specified in paragraph in question) but consider in Shaikh's interests they should not be permitted to negotiate cancellation of paragraph and thus escape obligation to drill within limited period. 3. If you concur please ask Company's Head Office to modify accordingly their instructions to Bahrain Manager. 4. Political Agent, Bahrain, should inform Bahrain Manager that negotiations should not repeat not be opened with Shaikh pending decision of His Majesty.'s Government. 2 . I see no objection to Company negotiating PRIOR I.R.4.Telegram G.T.C. From Political Agent, Bahrain To Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Sharjah. No. 4 Dated IMPORTANT '3rd January 1946 Has geological survey party and or Lermitte arrived &lt;ln Trucial Coast? Please report by telegram. PoliticalCONFIDENTIAL Dated the 4th January, 1946 No. C/23 To E.V.Packer, Esquire, M.B.E., Petroleum Concessions Limited Bahrain. V ■ Memorandum. ^ ^ , „ Heference^^our letter No. T/SA. 15/4074 dated the 3th December 1945.' The matter has been referred to the India Office and I have been instructed to inform you that negotiations should not be opened with the Shaikh pending the decision of His Majesty’s Government. Political Agent, Bahrain JANGTelegram From To No. G.T.C. Political, Sharjah. Political, Bahrain. Nil. Dated and received the 4th January, 1946. Reference to your telegram No.4 dated January 3rd, Lermite arrived January 3rd, Geological party expected to arrive about 8th. Political© PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LTD. BAHRAIN PERSIAN GULF. 7th February, 1946. My dear Colonel, DRILLING OBLIGATION - SHARJAH Reference your No.C^BS dated the 4th January 1946, we enclose a copy of telegram No.4 dated the 6th February from our London principals. E. You will note that the action to be taken appears to have been decided in agreement between the India Office and the company in London. In these circumstances, it would seem that it will be in order for Lermitte now in Dubai to carry out the necessary negotiations with the bhaikh of Sharjah. If you agree, we propose to send Lermitte the necessary authority and to ask him to keep the Assistant Political Agent, Sharjah, informed. K Yours sincerely, Enel. Lt.-Col. A.C.Galloway, O.B.E., s Political Agent, Bahrain. Confidential. BAHRAIN RECEIPT. Date.,.9* * ICopy of Telegram 355 FKOM LONDON TO PACKER PETROLEUM CONCES SI ONS BAHRAIN DATED 6.2.46 REC’D _ 7.2.46 DECODED MESSAGE: 4 REFERRING TO YOUR TELEGRAM 161 .AND RELATED CORRESPONDENCE 7 7 , 7 7 7 ( / WE HAVE AGREED WITH AUTHORITIES HERE TO DROP IDEA OF / / f f ^ DELETION'OF DRILLING OBLIGATION AND TO GO FOR EXTENSION OF r ( \ 7 / 7 f / y PERIOD WITHIN WHICH DRILLING SHOULD COMMENCE FROM NINE TO FIFTEEN YEARS ON GROUNDS OF INABILITY CARRY OUT NECESSARY GEOLOGICAL AND GEOPHYSICAL SURVEYS OWING TO WARTIME RESTRICTIONS FULLSTOP YOU SHOULD PROCEED ON THESE LINES IN CONSULTATION WITH POLITICAL AUTHORITY P.C.L., Bahrain. 7.2.46 op d/ACMTelegram From S(Pad) Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Resident, Bushire To No.58. Dated the 9th February, 1946. Paragraph 3 of your telegram No.23 of January 3rd. 2. P.C.L. have received following telegram begins:- 'We have agreed with authorities here to drop idea of deletion of drilling obligation and to go for extension of period within which drilling should commence from nine to- fifteen years.' Ends. 3. Grateful for telegraphic confirmation that P.C.L. may proceed with negotiations POLITICALTelegram From To Repeated 33/4. S (Pad). India Office, London. Political Resident, Bushire. Political Agent, Bahrain and Government of India, New Delhi. No.2908. Dated 9th Received 10th February, 1946. Your telegram No.23 of January 3rd. 2. Petroleum develppment (Trucial Coast) are prepared to accept six years extension of period within which drilling must commence at Sharjah and have instructed Bahrain manager accordingly. = R3TAXANDUM = LSI. ' I • R.No.49.Telegram S(Pad) From political Resident, Bushire. To Political Agent, Bahrain. No.246. Dated 11th Received 12th of February, 1946, Your telegram No.58 of February 9th. 2. Confirmed that P.C.L. may proceed with negotiations. =PRIOR=POLITICAL AGENCY BAHRAIN D.O. No.C/173, The 13th February, 1946. My dear Packer, Please refer to your letter No. 4127 dated the 7th February, 1946. DO/SA,15/ 2. There is no objection to your opening negotiations with the Shaikh of Sharjah on the lines proposed. Yours sincerely, V. . * E.V. Packer, Esq., M.B.E., Messrs. Petroleum Concessions Limited, B a h r a i n.i^xt. 989/ 1946. | Ling House, Dominion Street London bth February 1946. Dear Mr. Donaldson son, Referring to your letter ^Lxt. fb7/46J undated regarding the drilling obligation in the Sharjah Concession, we are prepared to accept an extension of six years to the period within which drilling must commence, if such is obtainable from the Shaikh, and we have instructed our Bahrain Manager accordingly. Political Resident as to the possibility of obtaining the deletion of the drilling obligation, we offered the postpone ment as an alternative. obligation was that no similar obligation is contained in the otrier Concessions held by us on the Trucial Coast and we preferred, for economic reasons, to be free to locate our first test wells on structures, wherever situated, which geological and geophysical survey indicated to be the most f avo urable. dollar exchange from His Majesty's Treasury to enable us to employ American geophysists equipped with the most modern instruments and methods. Naturally we wish to obtain the fullest possible value from the expenditure of Dollar Exchange and therefore wished to have a free hand as to where tne first wells would be located. &lt;Ve also had in mind the uncertainty as regards the inter-State boundaries on the Trucial Coast and the areas (such as diraimij in which the coastal Shaikhs have control or influence. anple latitude, as We hope to be in a position both as regards the siting of the first test wells and the supply of driliing equipment (some of which is now on orderJ to spud in our first well in 2/3 years from now, providing that no unforeseen! difficulties arise preventing the free movement of our survey parties in the Trucial Coast area generally. A small party of geologists is now at work on the Trucial Coast preparing the way for the larger Geophysical Parties next year and, we hope, making contacts which will enable such parties to obtain the maximum possible information during next working season. When we instructed him originally to consult the Our reason for preferring the deletion of the For this purpose, we have obtained sufficient However, an extension of six years will give us Yours &amp; c., Sd. I.W.L.Wheat ley. CO NE 1DEHT 1-aL h o rc/ 4 » Political Resident, Persian Gulf L.T . i, Hearchus' , at sea, the 3rd March 1946. Office of the Copy forwarded, with compliments, to The Political Agent, BAHRAIN. LL .. with/reference to India Office telegram Ho. 290 8 dated the 9th February 1946. RHL. Confidential. BAHRAIN RECEIPT.x to ■'x x. &gt;v „ ■ &gt; x xgf - ^ ■ -v'i, l Confidential! ^o.c352.o2c^ \ \ ConfidaatiaL BAHRAIN RECEIPT. No.. H?/ Date.. /:. British ij^ency, Bharj&amp;h. jj&amp;ted 2Bth j^srch 1946. 2 will you kindly refer to para 28 uii) of my Be^s report no.4 or 1^46. k. i enclose a copy^ith translation of the agreement concluded between the shaikh of bhar^ah and bhaikh jkuhanjmad bin ali bin Buwaidin ana Ali bin Abdullah bin Huwaiain, chiefs of the Beni i^itab, re^aioing the income derived from the oil concession. 3. The bhaikh of b^rjah has paid kuhammad bin Ali and other members of his family their share for b months of the annual payment received from the B.C*L. it remains, however, to be seen il he will continue to fulfil his undertaking if and when oil is extracted in commercial quantities. 4. This agreement, which is the first ol its kino on the irucial coast, will probably have repercussions on other tribes resulting in demands for similar agreements from their respective shaikhs, bhaikh Ali bin itashid as- beman, chief of a sub-section of the reni tgitab named al-jtasa• id, has already made such a oeniand which has, of course, been rejected by the bhaikh of bharjah. Lieutenant-colonel a. c. callowey, U-B.g., Political Agent, Bahrain.in the naite ol CjOo. the compeesionate ena the i^ereii'ul. hie it known to whoever may see this document^ that, having a aesire to help my friends, the teni ^iteb, i have (.aa 1 ' 060 - v ith; shaikh buhaoma.o bin aii that when, ii boo is willing, oil etc. come out to our mutual ecventege 1 shall not ‘deprive him of any income and to give him one third of the yield after expenses, this is in return for their compliance with my special oraers and their protection ot the company 1 s interests. They should be obedient to me whenever any necessity arises as has been the case since the time of our ancestors, cod is the best witness. od» &amp; beeleo Thumb impression of sultan bin s£qr. Muhammad bin nli bin Huweidin. seel of isiuhd bin seer. Thumb impression of ihLi x . bin Abuulleh bin nuwaioin. seal of s£qr a. 1 — (^asim Witnessed by;- said Dir. ^baulleh, ‘Amir bin salih, iv a' dhaa bin Ali bin Abdullah, said bin buwaidin 6c buhamrr.ad baai nwaahi.0 &lt; GOVERNMENT OF INDIA Department. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). [N.B. — This is an ORIGINAL message sent by AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more SI Sis] A 4 a S\*M 4 S~S AA S L A S* ss .* AA AAAAA . T — AA I - — - 1 - J 7 A 7 A 7 T A * * I 7 T A f A t 7 expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, uith the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signatwe of a responsible officer of the Department.] No. 321-s the 27th *arcH B l*4Cu** xi? Persian Gulf ita*i.clency f 5u*hir* To Offlc#, London* xtfm&amp;flhi 1 Political Agent, Bahrein* x Reference^ tologrta Mo. 2908 d&amp;tad 9th February 1946. ^eutoabar 1337 /' i' - 2. Copy 1* enclosed of letter Mo. TSA. 15/4156 dated 6th Kerch 1&amp;46 from the .iarajjer, Petroleum Uerelopaient (Truelal Coast) Limited. Bahrain, eithout its enclosure. 3. As no sp^re copies of the enclosure have been received, 1 shall be grateful if, while obtaining a copy for your records from the Company's Head Office ia London, three spare copies could be obtained and forwarded to the Government of India, the Political Agent, 'ahrain and this Residency. Sd. GAOmtAf PRIOR Political Resident, Persian Gulf for Secretary to Political Resident, Persian Gulf. {Signature) S. 44. MFP—1015 S&amp; P—(M-1870}—9-2-39—20,000. {DesignationTSA.15/4155 CONFIDENTIAL 6th March, 1*45 To Th« Hon’bla the Political resident in the Persian Gulf, Through H.B.M’e Political Agent, Bahrain, Sir EHARJAH OIL AGHIEVJiWT 1937 AMKN1 ^ ^,1 (Drilling We have the honour to forward herewith a signed copy of the Amendment dated the £6th February 1946 to oharjah Oil Agreement dated the 17th September 1937, which extends the period within which drilling should commence from nine to fifteen years, £• Ve shall be pleased if you will acknowledge receipt in due course, 3, The Ruler of Sharjah has a signed copy and we have also sent a similar signed copy to our Managing Director, London. 4. As far as we are concerned, this brings the matter to a satisfactory conclusion. w# have the honour to be Sir, Your most obedient servants, For &amp; on behalf of PETROLEUM DEVELOPMENT (TRUCIAL COAST) LIMITED MANAGER ?ncl 1No. 320-3 Persian Gulf Residency Bushire. 27th March li46. Sir f. I am directed to acknowledge receipt of your letter No. TSA 15/4155, dated the 6th Kfarch 1546, and to request that all communications relating to the Company's Oil Concessions on the Trucial Coast including Qatar be addressed to the Political Agent, Bahrain, and not to the Hon'ble the Political Resident, Persian Gulf. I have the honour to be Sir, Your most obedient servant Sd. J. CRONING. for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf The Manager Petroleum Development (Trucial Coast) Limited, BAHRAIN. No. 330-S Persian Gulf Residency, Bushire. 28th March 1546. Forwarded with compliments to: The Political Agent, BahrainD.O. NO. C/388. The 14th April 1946. My dear Packer, Will you please refer to your letter No. T3A.15/4155 dated the 6th March, 1946, to the Hon’ble the political Resident? 2. I have only just seen a copy of the above quoted letter which has been sent to me from Bushire. 3. The method of address you have adopted is not in conformity with practice and moreover I don f t know how the letter was sent to Bushire. I hope it did not go in the open post for I certainly was not asked to send it by bag. Yours sincerely, % ^ V. Packer, IiiSq., , Messrs. Petroleum Concessions, Limited, Bahrain.CONFIDENTIAL y|Lf vV| M ' Coji 4 JeatiaI. 'D \ TTT\ 1 T-K-r PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LTD. BAHRAIN DO/SA.15/4193 IPtli April, 1946. PERSIAN GULF. My dear Colonel, Will you please refer to your D.O.No.c/388 dated the 14th April 1946. For some time we have been sending in to your office correspondence on Trucial Coast Concession matters addressed to 'The Hobble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, through H.B.M f s Political Agent, Bahrain.” I think this practice arose from the time we were in communication with the Hon’ble the Political Resident on the subject of Muscat and Dhofar Concession (taking up of the concession after the expiry of the option period). If I remember rightly, I asked the Political Agent at the time if the correspondence should go through Muscat and was informed that the channel should be through Bahrain. We continued this practice, however, in the case of Umm-al-Quwain, Ajman and Ras-al- Khaimah without arousing comment. We now take it that in future all correspondence on our concessions should be addressed to the Political Agent, Bahrain, and it is not necessary for us to indicate in the body of the letter that the contents are for the information of the Hon T ble the Political Resident^ Perhaps you will confirm the procedure in respect of Muscat and Dhofar. Our letter under reference was sent to the Agency addressed on the cover, as inside, to ”The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Through H.B.M’s Political Agent, Bahrain,” and the number C/4155 was also shown on the cover. This is our recognised practice. We hold your clerk’s signature on our peon book dated the 7th March 1946. The addressee in the peon book was the Hon’ble the Political Resident. My Office Superintendent took the peon book this morning to your office and the initials of the receiver were acknowledged. It would seem that our letter must have been sent in your bag or taken by hand. If in the bag our number,4 2 - DO/SA. 15/4193 (eontd.) C/4155, should normally be on the mail list. I believe your Office Superintendent thinks the Political Resident’s staff was in Bahrain at the time and probably took over the cover. In conclusion I would mention that we have always recognised the principle that our communications with the Hon’ble the Political Resident, Bushire, should pass through the hands of the Political Agent, Bahrain, and in using the address ’’through H.B.M’s Political Agent, Bahrain, w we felt that we were complying with this principle. Yours sincerely, Lt.-Col. A.C.Galloway, O.B.E., H.B.M’s Political Agent, Bahrain.■ A D.O. No. C/453. The 29th April, 1946. -O Please refer to your letter No. DO/SA.15/4193 dated the 16th April, 1946. 2. I am now given to understand that your letter No. TSA. 15/4155 of the 6th March 1946 to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf was taken over by a member of his staff in Bahrain. 3. I confirm that all correspondence on the Qatar and Trucial Coast Oil Concessions should be addressed to me. It will not be necessary to state that a letter is for the information of the Political Resident. In fact the use of through, when probably ’care of* was meant may have led to the confusion. 4. I will confirm the correct procedure to be adopted for correspondence relating to the Muscat and Dhofar Concession later. R.V. Packer, Esq., M.B.E., Messrs. Petroleum Concessions, Limited., BAHRAIN.No. C/454. To Political Agency, Bahrain, The 30th of April, 1946. The Hon*ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire . MEMORANDUM . f’ 3 ° Reference your endorsement No.330-S dated the 28th March, 1946. 2. Mr. Packer has now asked me to confirm the procedure to be adopted in regard to corres pondence relating to the Muscat and Dhofar con cession. In the past such correspondence has been addressed to me with copies to the Political Agent, Muscat, and I should be grateful for con firmation that I may inform Mr. Packer that this is still the correct procedure. Sd./- A.C. GALLOWAY ATTESTED. Political Agent, Bahrain. for Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain.No.SSO-o S°t. Persian Gulf Residency, Bushi re. 7th Hay li46. To: ^The Political Agent, Bahrain . Cooy to: The Political Agent, i uscat . f ^ ■ ixemoranduiu. Reference your nemorandur No. G/454 dated the 30th April 1146, regarding the procedure to oe adopted in respect of correspondence relating to the 1 uscat and Dhofar Concessions. 3. Please inf on. nr. Packer that such correspondence should in future be addressed to the Political Agent, I uscat and that, to avoid delay, copies should be sent to the Political Resident, c/o The Political Agent, Bahrain. 3. He should also be asked to ensure that questions relating to the various concessions should be dealt with in seoarate cornunications. Sd.G3.0FFRRY PRIOR. Political Resident,Persian Gulf. a rn i n p rn rn-pv fi i. _L u Jl .i-j L/ • for secretary to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf. HDN Confidential. ^SCEIPT- No. BAHRAIN «&lt;- n- iD.O. No.C/488 The 14th of May, 1946 My dear packer Please refer to my letter No.C/453 dated the 29th April, 1946. pondence regarding the Muscat and Dhofar Con cession should in future be addressed to the Political Agent, Muscat, and, to avoid delay, copies should be sent to the Hon'ble the poli tical Resident, c/o The Political Agent, Bahrain. 3. I have to ask you to ensure that corres pondence regarding the various concessions are dealt with in separate communications. 2 I have been asked to say that corres- Yours sincerely E.V* Packer, Esq Packer, Esq., M.B.E., Messrs. Petroleum Concessions, Limited Bahrain.Translation of letter, ta. 123 dated 24th Habi Awal 1363 (26*2*V&gt;) from Shaikh of Sharjah to Mr. S.V.Packer, Manager, Petroleum Development (Trucial Coast), Bahrain — / After compliments Reference your letter No. T&amp;A /41J ^l c j dated 12th l ebruary 1946* I have duly signed the Amerkfcaent to tlio Agreement referred to by you as you requested with our friend, .Ir. B.Ii.Lemxtte. If, Cod willing, you will find me always doing all I can to afford valuable help to the Company and I l»x&gt;e she will do tiie same to me. I wish Cod to crown all our efforts v/ith success. Usual eliding. ±P&amp;7, Signature and Seal of Shaikh Sultan bin Saqr.AKBUKSHT DATW 26th FmtVARY 1946 to 3iWiJMl OIL i\CRKSM3Jir miTKD THE 17th SEHPSLIB^S, 1937. 1* This AGs^ShiiHI'fP made tiie Tv/enty-sixth day of February One Thousand Nine hundred and Forty Six between His Excellency Sliailch Sultan bin Soqr al 'ossiin. Holer of Sharjah and its territories (hereinafter called 'The Ruler”) of the first part and Ur. Basil Henry Lemitte. attorney of Fetroleua Development (Trucial Coast) Limited (hereinafter called 'The Compaiiy”) of the other ,»art is hereafter referred to as ”A;aendm(mt dated Twenty-sixth February 1946 ( LcrMMHfeAne f ® to Sharjah Oil Agreement of 1937'* 2. In this agreement t’ae Ruler and the a^ree to amend Paragraph B of Schedule Ho. I, page 2 which formed an integral part of the Oil Conoession Agreement w’oich was signed on the 17th September, 1937 oorr -sending to the Hth Hajab 1336. The amended Article which will take effect from the date of the signature to this Agreement is as follows: 'The period allowed within which drilling shall begin is that of 13 calendar years from the date of signature of the conoession Agreement. If the period of 13 years stipulated above expires and the Company has not done geological examination and field work, etc., constantly with every diligence and activity then the Agroeme t shall be annulled.' 3« The Holer agrees that all obligations of the Company under the original Paragraph ”B n of Schedule Ho.1, Page No. 2, shall now be cancelled with effect from the date of this Ameokienfc dated Twenty-sixth February, 1946 to the /SharjahSharjah Oil A^roonent of 1937. In witness whereof the parties to this A^roeoont ha/e set their bands tiie Day and Tear first above writteni- The Coramiv (3d) B.H.I«5,IIOTiS * In the presence of (3d)TSA.15/U32 12th February, 19'4. The H.E, Sultan bin Saqr al Qaasim, Ruler of Sharjah, Sharjah. Tour jccollenqy. 1* W© have the lionour to refer to paragraph B of Schedule No# 1 to the Oil Concession concluded with Tour Excellency on the 17th September, 1937* 2# Your Excellency will understand that the date of coranenooneiit of drilling is dependent upon the results of geological examination of the territory concerned and this exa dnation is an essential prelud^ to^tbo drilling# 3. Tour Excellency will note that in the above-mentioned paragraph B of Schedule No# 1 you agreed to a period of nine years for geological exploration of which two years only were available before the war broloe out in 1939 and the Company was forced by conditions created by this war to discontinue geological work on the Tracial Coast# The six war years have been lost and the Company have not sufficient data on which to select a drilling site# 4# As Tour Excellency is aware the Company hove taken the first opportunity of reoouinencing its goologioul work in your territory although equipaent is very difficult to obtain, and a party Is already funcrfcioning in the Jabal Faiyuh area# Much time, however, must elapse before a drilling point can be located and the period of nine years originally agreed on expires in 1946# 5# In these circumstances we are sure Tour ExceHeracy will agree that it is reasonable for the Company to request /thatthat paragraph B of Schedule Ifo.l, fldh^ the period of nine years witiiin which drilling must begin but which did not foresee or talao into account the enforced interruption caused by the war, be changed and the period be extended by six years to make fifteen years ending in September, 1952« Mr* Lermitte will be rislting Tour ISxeellency and will put before you a iom of agreeiaeiit cx&gt;verir^ tills cnange for Tour lixcellenqy* s consideration* 7* H*B*M* f s Political Agent, Bahrain, has been infbmed and has a copy of the proposed fora of agreement* We hare the honour to be, etc.. For and on behalf of (THBDIAL 00AST) 13!%, ♦ (Sd) «)*V. Packer, Manager*•n (g) hi Telegrams : PETCONCESS, BAHREIN Codes: BENTLEY’S SECOND PHRASE PETROLEUM DEVELOPMENT (Trucial Coast) LIMITED W* ''A Confidential BAHREIN. PERSIAN GULF. 7'% TSA. 15/10536 Political Agent, Bahrain. 10th December, 1950. ' N 1 Dear Sir, Under the Exchange of Letters dated 17th September, 1937, appended to the Sharjah Concession, drilling mast commence with in nine calendar years from that date under pain qf cancellation, that is, by 17th September, 1946. ^ ' In February. 1946 the nine years was altered to fifteen by Exchange of Letters with the Shaikh. The date for commencing drilling now stands, therefore, at 17th September, 1952 or sooner. At the moment we are unable to recommend a drilling site until the territory of the State of Sharjah is clearly defined on the ground or on the map. ■iVe would be grateful if you would inform us when a definition of the boundaries of Sharjah will be available. Similarly, in order to evaluate the potentiax of the other Sheikhdoms a clear definition of their boundaries will also be required. yours faithfully, PETROIEI^LDEVELOPMENT (TRUCIAL COAST) LTD. MANAGER 4 ssjsl *!* 1 ttp ; r m .n *-/ ** 11 im’-v • ,,-tx SV. . ACMConfidential, No.C/R-643. Political Agency, Bahrain, 14th December, 1950. D^er Sir Rupert, I enclose a copy of a letter No.TSA.15/ 10536 of the 10th December from Petroleum Deve lopment (Trucial Coast) Ltd., which is self- explanatory. 2. I think that we should now try and fix provisional boundaries, at any rate, for all the Sheikhdoms, and if you agree, I will instruct Michell to commence the work forthwith. In view of the Dubal-Abu Dhabi precedent, I would not suggest that we try to obtain the agreement of the Shaikhs to the boundaries; we would merely announce them and state that what for our own purposes we considered their boundaries to be. Me could inform I.P.C. of these at the same time emphasising that the boundaries were provisional. I assume of course that the Saudi attitude makes it Impossible for us to finalise them. 3. It is, as we all know, a great pity that the limitation of the boundaries - even provisionally » was not done long before this. Yours sincerely, His Excellency Sir Rupert Hay, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Political Resident, Persian Gulf, Bahrain.3%f4. / O- ' / 4 - 4-4 ^ ^-^ 7 ’ y - P^^-, P- c. L. • V The letter under reference was signed for in J3.0. and passed to Mr. Croning, who opened all mail during the absence of P.R. and the tour party on the last tour. • I now recollect him asking me if we had received a copy of P.C.L's letter, when I replied that we had not received a copy. Muscat and Dhofar Concession but from pages 46 and 83 of F.38/15 jit will be seen that corres. regarding the Agreement was sent to us for the P.R's information but th&amp;t P.R.-was not addressed. For the Ajman Agreement P.R. was addressed by P.C.L. but both the ' original letter and a copy were sent to us under covering letter, vide'is.113 of F.38/8. For Umm al C^aiwain Agreement P.R. was addressed and copy of this letter sent us - not under covering letter. For Ras al Khaimah Agreement and amendment to Sharjah Agreement P.R. was addressed (in covers marked to him through P.A.B.?) and no cojbies of these letters sent us. P.R. has now asked that all corres. regarding the T.C. and Qatar Concessions should be addressed to us, vide p.53 of file. It is in fact ridiculous that we should conduct corres. in all the intermediary stages and be bypassed at the draft concession stage. May confirm that all corres. regarding concessions mentioned above should be addressed to us, and that is not necessary to specify that a letter is for the information of the P.R. the Muscat Concession was a measure of convenience (copies were also sent to P.A.M.) andihai that P.C.L. should:continue sending copies of corres. both to us and to P.A.M. We may however confirm from P.R. before replying to this part of the letter. There is no record of the arrangement at time of the It would seem that the sending to us of corres. regarding D.F.A.s I and II.INDIA OmCE RECORDS A / / MICROFILM INDIA OFFICE LIBRARY and RECORDS Photocopying record Ref. No. ICL: ICR Date Name Process No. of exposures 1 8. B.Bo trv5\ju\&gt; Oy. 1% 2 3 4 5 6 REFER TO THE SPECIALIST CONCERNED</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000135_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/866</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000135</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/866</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 38/4 Petroleum Concessions Limited Sharjah Concession'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1938/1950</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-04-24T11:06:49</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (79 folios)</extent><extent>The file is arranged chronologically.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover, and terminates at the inside back cover; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 2-75; these numbers are also written in pencil, and can be found in the same position as the main sequence, but they are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains correspondence relating to the oil concession in the Sharjah territories. The correspondence is between: the Political Agent at Bahrain; representatives of Petroleum Concessions Limited and Petroleum Development (Trucial Coast) Limited, in London, Bahrain, and the Trucial Coast [United Arab Emirates]; the Residency Agent at Sharjah; the Political Residency at Bushire (later Bahrain) [Persian Gulf Political Residency]; the India Office; Sultan bin Saqr [Sulṭān bin Saqr Āl Qāsimī], the Ruler of Sharjah; and the Government of India.The majority of the file covers an amendment to the 1937 concession agreement between the oil company, Petroleum Concessions Ltd, and Shaikh Sultan that was made in February 1946. This amendment was made in order to extend the permitted drilling period following the Second World War, during which no drilling was carried out. Permission to open negotiations over the matter was sought from the British Government by the company. There is a copy of the agreed amendment on folio 72.Other matters covered by the file include:the desire of Shaikh Sultan to open a bank branch in Sharjah in order to receive royalty payments;confirmation of the initial 1937 concession agreement;the presentation by Petroleum Concessions Limited of a gift of motor vehicles to Shaikh Sultan;payment of the annual concession payment by the company to Shaikh Sultan;the arrival of a geological party in the Trucial Coast in early 1946;the correct channels of communication with the British Government to be used by the company.Folios 19-28 is Memo B 467 of the India Office and includes a copy of the commercial agreement between the company and Shaikh Sultan, a copy of the 'political agreement' between the company and the British Government, and copies of correspondence relating to both.Folios 76-80 are internal office notes.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Native Agent, Trucial Coast, Sharjah</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of India</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Emir of Sharjah, Āl Qāsimī dynasty</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Persian Gulf Political Residency</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Abu Dhabi Company for Onshore Oil Operations</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Sharjah</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Concessions, Oil, Sharjah</topic></subject><subject><topic>Second World War (1939-1945)</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000135#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>