<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0000da_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T05:20:57.718Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">DRAFT 1J1TT2R Lieutenant•Colonel R.R, Burnett, 0.B.E., External Affairs Department, Government of India. 'T.A. wo. IGr. Harri^n I have at last been able to confirm from the Foreign Office that expenditure on the Commercial Secretariat is borne wholly by the D.O.T. CIO. 7/ /// 10 / 10 MOV 1944 i,( Dear Burnett, sVill you please refer to your letter D. 0. No. F.160-N/2+4 of 3rd June regarding 7 'I certain expenditure at the Jainv.^rr inbassy. • The salary of the iinbassy Surgeon is included in the statements showing expenditure incurred by H. M. G-. in Persia which are received annually in this Office from the Bahrlin Office, and is divisible equally between Tndij^and Imperial revenues. ^Expenditure in connection .with the Commercial Secretariat is borne solely by H. G. and falls as a charge on the vote of the Department of Overseas Trade. / rVith regard to^expenditure oj^ the Office of ./orks, the position ^J-s set out in •paragraph 3 of your letter under reference is correct. (Sgd.) R., „ v . eU , .a.. it# ®. Account ant-G-eneral Please see Government of India Express Letter below about the incidence of expenditure on the ^Commercial Secretariat, the Embassy Surgeon and the Office of Works at H.M. Embassy, Tehran# There do not seem to be any papers in this Department which throw light on the problem; Collection 29/80 below appears to deal with civil works carried out by the Public Works Department and Collection 29/86 (attached) to deal with the general question and not with specific instances. Do you receive copies of the divisibility statements mentioned in paragraph A of the Government of India letter, and have you any information regarding the details of the expenditure on the Tehran Embassy? S SEP 1944 E.K-I COPY HR KAIL . / External Affairs Department Hew Delhi, •’'Phe'~ June ly44. !L£^Io JLfL6Q&gt;N/44 , F L^i'xdS ■ i &gt; * i ]J c* u €1 'i'e have been trying to ascertain definitely the incidence of tne expenditQron -the Commercial Secretariat, the Hhibassy Surgeon and the Office of worts at the iehran iilnbassy, but the necessary details are not available here. 2. bo iar as the Commercial Secretariat and the Embassy Surgeon are concerned, we presume that, since the whole cost^of the Embassy is shared equally by the Imperial and Indian Grovemnents, and as the commercial Secretary and the Surgeon are included in the^personnel of the iibassy shown in tne Eoreigyi Office List, half of their cost is in fact paid oy tne Government of India. 3. As regards the Office of 7/orks. the position, so far as is known here, is as follows: 1 (a) All expenditure in regard to the maintenance of diplomatic and consular buildings mjran, irrespective of the amount, is shared in moieties by the two Governments. (b) The expenditure on new minor works costing less than Z.20G or Ks.2500, as the case may oe, is charged to the maintenance account and shared m moieties. (c) All new works costing £.200 or Ib.2500, as the case may be, or more, are rhnrgnil tn thw igllTi Vil account and borne by the 'Gov9rnmet^i^|^^6•l^l•iilJW ^ ^ , ' for the maintenance of the post. • • » • I4, As the Accountant Oen^ral does not get conies of the divisibility statements prepared in x England, we shall be gratQful__if yeu will let us know the actual position regarding'tne incidence of the expenditure which 1 have mentioned. o■ ;07Y. fa (K 7962/2042/234) No. 3694. H.M. Ofrice of \torK:s, storey 1 s (late, iestminster» S.Vi.l. 29 June, 1938&lt; Sir, With reference to your uieiaorandU'* of the 7th instant, reference K 6316/2042/234, enclosing a copy of a letter from the India Office of the 20th ultimo, together with an extract from a letter from the Government of India dated the 7th May, 1937, I am directed to state that ari'angements have been made for the expenditure on minor works costing between £200 and £500 to be shown separately in the annual return furnished by this Department. 2. The Board assume that the limit of Es. 2,500 refers only to disbursements made by the Government of India and does not in any way 'effect the accounts of this Department. I am, etc. , (Signed) A.G. Barnett. The Under Secretary of State, Foreign Office, S.1.1No.D.910-A/ 38 * Prom M To The Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Department, His Majesty’s Under Secretary of State for India, Political Department, India Office, London. Dated Simla, the 7th May 1938. J. Diplomatic and Consular expenditure in Iran. Sir, With reference to your letter No.P.Z.7307/37, dated the 18th November 1937 and subsequent reminder dated the 5th April 1938, in regard to the method of classifying construction expenditure in Iran and the Persian Gulf, I am directed to state that the Government of India accept the suggestion of the Foreign Office that all new minor works costing less than £200 in each case should he charged to the maintenance account and shared in moieties as usual hy the Government of India and His Majesty's Government, subject to the condition that so far as the expenditure incurred in posts under the control of the Government of India is concerned, the limit should be Rs.2,500 roundly in each case instead of Rs. 2, 666. 10. 8, the exact equivalent of £200 converted at the official rate of exchange. I am to suggest that this arrangement should be given effect to commencing from the accounts for 1937-38. 2. The position under this arrangement will be as follows (a) All expenditure in regard to maintenance of buildings irrespective of amount, will as at present be shared in moieties by the two Governments. ( v,} ^he expenditure on new minor works costing less than £200 or Rs.2,500 as the case may be, should also be charged to the maintenance account and shared in moieties. (c) All new works costing £200 or Rs.2,500 as the case may be, or more, will be charged to the capital account and borne by the Government responsible for the maintenance of the post. (d)(d) The above arrangement will not be applicable to Kuweit where all expenditure is shared in moieties by the two Governments irrespective of whether it is chargeable to the capital account or not, nor will it apply to Bahrein, Muscat and Zahidan Trade Agency so long as the expenditure at these posts is borne entirely by the Government of India. 3, The Government of India would in this connection invite a reference to the proposals forwarded in this Department letter NO.F.457-N/37, dated the 12th November 1937, in regard to the transfer of the Bushire Residency to Bahrein, where it has been suggested that the liability of the Government of India in regard to their share of expenditure in Kuweit, Iran and the Gulf and their share of th3 expenditure in Bahrein, Muscat and the Zahidan Trade Agency should be limited to Rupees 9 lakhs per annum. I am to add that the above arrangements in regard to division of works expenditure should not affect the maximum liability referred to above when this arrangement is accepted. I have, etc., (Sd.) For Secretary to the Government of India.IT ,'JJ A iJ iTom ( y { Uo. D.235-A/37. I D 5 U I 9 S 7 xS(3 The foreign becretary to the Government of India. To / ^ / (T) Cxxtyt ho p ftrG. ^/vA^U • j The Under Secretary of State for India, Political Department, India Office, London* ^7 Dated New Delhi, the l* 1 ' February 1937* Percentage charges on public works in the Persian Gulf. Sir, Yfith reference to the correspondence ending with i^v’v 7 &gt; the letter from the India Office Ho. P*2 j* 7835/36, dated the 7th January 1937, i am directed to say that for the reasons stated therein, the Government of India concur in the proposal that the designation of the head '‘Percentage Charges»• in relation to expenditure on public works in the Persian Gulf sub-division should be altered to “Public Works Department Establishment etc., costs*. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant.V’ 5400 that in any further communi- bject the under-mentioned letter nay be quoted, and the reply Secretary of State for India, 'olitical Department, India Office, London, S. W. 1. 7836 / 36 . . V INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL, LONDON, S.W. 1. Li K ' ¥} i &amp;nd January, 1936. blr, I ani direoted by the secretary of btate for India to refer to your letter of the 19th deceiuber 1935, Ho*JL.1299l/ ±32/Z34, on the subject of percentage charges on civil v/orks undertaken by the Public Works department of the Government of India at diplomatic and consular posts in Iran and the Persian Gulf, the cost of which is divisible between Imperial and Indian hevenues. 1. It has now been ascertained that the cost in any one year of the Persian Gulf sub-division of the Public works department excluding the pay !,nd allowances of the Assistant Sngineer in charge is divided in the proportion of the outlay on divisible and non-divisible works undertaken in Iran and the mersian Gulf during that year. The latter proportion is charged wholly to Indian hevenues while the former, together with l‘/&gt; of the expenditure on repairs to cover accounting and audit costs, is charged in the Indian statements of d. and C. expenditure under the heading of 'percentage charges' (partly under 'hushire' and partly under ’kov.eit'), with a view to recovery of a moiety from your department. 3. These 'peroenteg* charges' represent therefore establishment charges which in the case of the Office of horks would be included in the prime cost of works, on which a percentage charge is levied. They bear no relation to the administration charge of 11 / applied by that department in connection with similar undertakings, which it is understood covers only a proportion of the cost of their engineer/ The Under Secretary of State, Foreign Office, •u. . 1 .iingineer in Iran and o£ headquartera* expenses. 4. a moiety of the pay and alio vancos of the iublio ♦forks department Assietant Engineer in charge of the iersian Gull eub-division, who not only supervises the execution of all public works in the Persian Gulf but also acts as Adviser to the Political Resident on public works matters, it charged separately to Imperial Revenues as in the case of other headquarters appointments in the Gulf • 5* The secretary oi wtate for India concurs in the opinion of the Government of India that thie division of tiie cost of adiainistratj.on and labour connected with divisible works is fair and that the substitution for it of the Office of -orks method of adding a percentage charge for administration would not be correct, he proposes, however, to suggest to the Government of India that the heading 'percentage chargee' used in the B. and C. Accounts is aoisleading and might with advantage bo changed. 6, ihe Secretary of btate for Foreign Affaire will appreciate that since the whole cost of the iersian Gulf sub-division of the iublio »,orks department related to non-divieiole works and a moiety of the cost related to divisible works it charged to Indian Revenues, the Government of India are concerned to maintain as economical an establishment as possible. The Government of India explain, however, that owing to the conditions of service the staff employed in the Gulf receive higher rate© of pay and allowances than Public works department staff elsewhere that travelling by steamer is expensive, and that the area covered by the sub-division necessitates a large outdoor establishment. 1 am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, (Sgd.) ML J. CLAUSONDraft Paper, political Department. DRAFT The U.S. of S. , Foreign Office. Its, A V-'' rn T d I'fo 4 tayvCtlVa (iOvKy CA^-^-O Omus^ S^i 4,03 Vo r ' ^ £XA-VJ O Fv 7s\J^s, 1. ctv&lt;4b* '^/.u LETTER. r2jfc« ( ,5? Sir, I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to refer to your letter of the 19th December 1935, o.K. 12991/132/ 234, on the subject of percentage charges on civil works undertaken by the Public Works Department of the Government of India at diplomatic and consular posts in Iran and the Persian Gulf, the cost of which is divisible between Imperial and Indian Revenues. 2. It has now been ascertained that the cost in any one year of the Persian Gulf sub-division of the Public Works Department excluding the pay and allowances of the Assistant Engineer in charge is divided in the proportion of the outlay on divisible and non-divisible Imccw- works undertaken in Peroia and the Persian Gulf during that year. The latter proportion is charged wholly to Indian Revenue: charged in the -9-. —— 5t-ftooounts under s while a moie-ty- ■&amp;■£ the former/is uT iar\ ^«Jkm«vvb 4 ^ ^ ^ • ■G r-ftOO* 5000 7 36 the heading of 'percentage charges'^partly under 'Bushire' and partly under 'Koweit'^), cv VuLvV to &lt;4 c*. HnvOOiAi It-is underotood—fchat to this moiety is • added——e-f the pxpen iitnre on-repairs to 1 eover no counting and— audit nncjt, 3. These 'percentage charges' cWau'oCfc represent therefore the appropriate ! pgopogti o&gt;i u r t~trt!—^upei 1 vision and labour 50 i6 n T n / w ^ UJ U TJ ,, iv\ Hu, tA,&gt;i cr{» * # « | ' o a ' urW&lt;&gt;U OWfc ^ HUl C&gt;(^\u. O^- Wovks Htmvk) U. u-.c-UaJ^O Ii/V rw^tgta wnnrn—ftS il fat IT. Gt——C©-f?t Kax jVf-C^U, C-Art-V LXn&gt;vic&lt;; , sW tv-tvvci-v oc ^J.ACOvV(U^ ckx&lt;T^f L^v\£^&lt; , l Uxv^ n-f —»»4 'b ear no relation to the adrr.inistration charge of 11% applied by lyc^vvkvu^r%f n.Mi Office of Tories in connection with similar undertakings^which it is understood dvvU* ^ covers^ a proportion of the cost Ox tneir Engineer in -Pa p oia and of headquarters expenses f i?er A moiety of the pay and allowances of the P.W.D.Assistant Engineer in charge of the Persian Gulf sub-division^ Who not only supervises the execution of all public works in the Persian Gulf but also acts as Adviser to the Political Resident on public works matters, is charged separately to Imperial Revenues as in the case of other headquarters appointments in the Gulf. 5. The Secretary of State for India concurs in the opinion of the Government of India that this division of the cost of administration and labour connected with divisible works is fair and that the substitution for it of the Office of Works method of adding a percentage charge for administration would not be -prncticab 1-e. he proposes, however, to suggest to the Government of India that the heading ’•percentage charges” used in the D. &amp; C. Accounts is misleading and might with advantage be changed. 6. The Secretary of State for foreign Affairs will appreciate that sine the whole cost of the Persian^sub -division) 4 ^ '^■D. related to non-divisible works and a moiety of the cost related to divisiole works /Draft Paper. Department. 50 16 5000 7 36 works is charged to Indian Revenues, the Government of India are concerned to maintain as economical an establishment as possible. The Government of India explain, however, that owing to the conditions of service the staff emplo; in the Gulf receive higher rates of pay and allowances than P.W.D.staff elsewhere, that travelling by steamer is expensive^ and that the area covered by the sub division necessitates a large outdoor establishment. syed pay W j CLAUSONDraft Paper. political Department. DRAF']’ LETT SR. The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, F. 8c P. Department. 50 16 5000 7 36 :-7 JAN 1937 Sir , I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to refer to your letter of the 15th October, No.F.47- A/ 36, on the subject of percentage charges on public works in the Persian Gulf, and to enclose copy of a letter to the Foreign Office. 2. In view of the fact that the expenditure charged under the head of 'percentage charges' in the D. &amp; C. Accounts represents the appropriate proportion of the cost of the Persian Gulf sub-division of the P.W.D., together with an addition of \% on the cost of repairs to cover accounting and audit expenses (as stated in the letter from the Accountant-General, Central Revenues, of the 22nd December 1932, No.T.A.27-3-1128), the Secretary of State for India suggests that,subject to the concurrence of the Government of India,the heading might with advantage be altered to 'P.W.D.HsloM etc.costs' or some similar title which will describe more accurately the true nature of the charges. The present heading evidently invites comparison with the fixed percentage charged by the Imperial Government for administration expenses in connection with the similar works undertaken by them. (Sgd.) M. J. CLAUSONTZ- ■ ■ i s5&gt; ‘ 5 7 ilr ' Reference Paper. political Department. Letter No. Rec. 193 . 'eferred to Accountant-General, .&gt; Financial Secretary, 4thday of Dec emb er 193 6. On looking at this question again it seems to me that the proper reply to the Foreign Office is that the ’’percentage charges” in the D. &amp; C.accounts hear no relation whatever to the W% administration charge of the Office of Works. The former really represent the costs of supervision (apart from the pay and allowances of the Assistant Engineer in Charge) and the labour of the works undertaken together with \% addition to the cost of repairs for accounting and audit (see A.6.366 of 1933, copy now attached) while the 11^? represents a part of the cost of the Office of Works’ Engineer plus something for headquarters expenses. The Office of Works include both material and labour in the cost of the works. On this.reading the amounts of the 'percentage charges' are not by any means excessive, since expenditure on ^ost maintenance and repair works is chiefly in respect of labour and not of material. An explanation on these lines will admit of a reference in the reply to the Foreign Office to the fact that a moiety of the pay and allowances of the P.W.D. Assistant Engineer is charged to them separately, which seems advisable in the light of the Financial Secretary’s comment. It will, moreover, avoid any mention of the comparative figures given in the Government of India’s letter which the Accountant-General considers to be unreli able. . The heading 'percentage charges' is obviously misleading, and it is proposed to suggest to the ;»2v» 5000 11.34 Government/Government of India that some such title as 'P. W.D.etc.costs” should he substituted in future. Drafts are attached on which I should he glad of your observations. ‘-/-•x h ' 3U. The system of the Office of Works was explained in a notification transmitted by the Foreign Office in 1930, vide P.890/30, an extract from which has now also been placed below, and it is evident that charges for labour, i.e. as distinct from the controlling or headquarters staff, are included in the prime \ cost of works as suggested. It is also evident from the various communications from India on the subject, that the Indian practice differs widely therefrom in that the works charges are exclusive of establishment costs, which appear under percentage charges, the only doubt being as to the degree to which the difference exists. Details of the actual establishment in the Persian Gulf have now been noticed in one of the enclosures to P,2i.6818^/36 on the file regarding the transfer of the Residency to Bahrein. An extract has been added below for convenience of reference. It will be observed that as far as ordinary works, i.e. other than in connection with the Electric and Water plants ; are concerned, the personnel do not seem to be inclusive of such as would actually do the work, e.g. bricklayers and carpenters. It is questionable, however, whether this vitiates the main argument but it is suggested that the third paragraph of the letter to the Foreign Office might be redrafted as follows: “These “percentage charges’ 1 , therefore, represent establishment charges that in the case of the Office of Works would be taken into account in the assessment of prime costs, the basis on which the levy is made of the administration charge of 11%, which it is understood is in respect of headquarters services/Reference Paper. POLITICAL Department. Letter No. Rec. 193 . ^^ferred to day of 193 . service8 ( including in the present instance those of an engineer in Iran. It will thus he seen that there is a marked difference between the two systems that renders 3279 5000 11.34 any comparison of percentage charges of little value'*. Some verbal changes in paragraph 2 have been suggested in view of the fact that the halving process is not effected until this Office merges the Indian and Foreign Office accounts in the yearly claim. Jy\ #4 , H-. XaC~ &amp; ft- ^ ^vvx^Zv ' h * t ' ^ ^ ^ * &lt;C. / arttf-fi £v**-wl^^-C^ ^'o C-Ov-V ■f^ • // V'l'i'lzl,wrnm (e) Public Works Department Officer. Assistant Engineer. Staff . Divisional Accountant Supervisor Draftsman Clerks Inferior Establishment . Peon ... ... * Khallasis Chowkidar Donkey Post Runner 1 1 1 2 1 6 1 1 Workcharged Establishment engaged for the Electric and Water Supply Plants. E.&amp; M.Assistant Tally Clerk Wireman Fireman Oil Engine drivers Greasers Attendants Fitter Chowkidar Sweepers 1 1 1 1 3 3 3 1 1 2repayment services. • h / - (22) KSTAELISHtirarr ANT) store charges- The report of the Comnittee on Departmental Expenses charged hy Government Departments for services rendered to other Departments and outside bodies has been under discussion with the Treasury, and the following arrangements have now been approved. With certain exceptions, referred to below, the full administrative cost to the Department calculated as percentage of the value of all work carried out, will be added to the prime cost of services rendered on repayment terms. This establishment charge is at present 11£ and this rate is to be taken as the standard charge, subject to review at intervals of 3 years. 1. Repayment Services carried out on behalf of Exchequer Departments . x x x * x x (d) Works Services . The standard rate of Ilf, will be charged (as from 1st April, 1930), in place of 7^ as hitherto, on the prime cost (which includes charges for Clerks of Works, Foremen, etc. whether of New Works or Maintenance Services. Full Stores handling charges will be included in cases of issues from Stores of goods or materials to be used in connection with Works services. xxx H.M. Office of Works, x December, 1929.—— OFFICE OF THE ACCOUNTANT GENERAL, CENTRAL REVENUES, Imperial Secretariat Buildings, New Delhi, the 22nd December 1932. * No.TA.27-3-1128. From The Accountant General, Central Revenues, TA. Section. To The Under Secretary of State for India, Accountant Generals Department, India Office, London, S.W.l Subject:- Expenditure in respect of Diplomatic and Consular Services in Persia for 1929-30. Sir, With reference to the India Office letter No.A.G.1101^32 M.I., dated 3rd November 1932 on the subject mentioned above, I have the honour to observe as follows:- The assumption made by the India Office that the departmental charges in the Persian Gulf Division were levied on a fixed scale is not correct. These charges are calculated on the actual cost of maintenance and repairs to buildings connected with the Diplomatic and Consular Services in Persia by adopting the rates which the total cost of establishment of the Division (excluding the pay and allowances of the Executive or Assistant Engineer) bears to the total expenditure on worfts and repairs incurred by the Division, together with an addition of 1 per cent, of cost of repairs to cover charges for accounts and audit establishment. These charges therefore vary every year according as the three factors - viz., (1) the cost of repairs to buildings connected with the Diplomatic and Consular Services in Persia, (2) total expenditure on works and repairs executed by/by the Division and (3) the cost of total establishment vary from year to year. It has, however, been ascertained that no part of the percentage charges in the statements for 1929-30 and 1930-31 relates to capital works. 2 . In this connection 1 would point out that in reply to an enquiry made by the India Office in paragraph 4 of their letter No.A.G* 2485, dated 26th March 1929, it was only stated in the final paragraph of this oiiice letter No.TA.Divl. 1(1) of 29-30-498, dated 11th July 1932, that the expenditure under Civil Y/orks in the Inciian statements included departmental percentage charges. It was not intended to suggest in that letter that the method of compilation of percentage charges in the Indian statements was analogous to that adopted by His Majesty 1 s Office of Works. 1 have, etc., (Sd.) Assistant Accounts Officer.■ \-o* — I _ ..Reference Paper. p. z. 7835 / 36 . POLITICAL Department. —2 Letter No. Uec. 193 £ Referred to rv Accountant-General, day of November, 193 6. Financial Secretary, V4 V /I ;» 2 v« 5000 11.34 I shall be glad of your observations on the Government of Indian letter of 15 th October below, regarding departmental charges. Apparently a moiety of the Assistant Engineer 1 s pay is regularly charged to H.M. G. although, so far as this Department is aware, Treasury concurrence has never been obtained. However, as the Foreign Office do not raise the point in their letter of the 19th December last it is, perhaps, unnecessary to make any reference to it in our reply. We might pass on to the Foreign Office the explanations given in paragraph 5 : they are very much as expected. I suppose the fact is that the total P.W.D., annual cost of the Persian Gulf sub-division^ remains more or less constant, while the expenditure on the work they carry out varies -considerably from year to year. Hence the proportion of one to the other may be high in one year but possibly for a series of years not more excessive than the conditions warrant# , 3 ^ TThere seems to be no possibility of adopting the Office of Works’ method of a standard percentage charge. ^ &lt;TVv 'A*, tru^c A.No.47-A/36 ! &gt; 7 ‘7 4^ : 7835 i from [ o 3 3 I The Jt)reign Beoretaiy to tke s &amp;e¥era»e»fc- To The linier Secretary of State for India, India Office, London# Bated Simla, the ^ ’ Catcher 1936# Subject:- Percent ago charges on Public Works in the Persian Gulf. Sir, I am directed to refer to India Offieel letter No.P#2«268/36, dated the 30th January 1936 on the above -/JttZ* ■ } a , V-, subject and to stalfe as follows j- go It the outset* the Government of India consider it desirable to explain the method of apportionment of the es tab! is hment charg es oft he P e rs ian Gul f Sub-L iv is io n between thexaselves and His Majesty*3 Govsmiflent&lt;. out of the total expenditure on public works in connection with the Diplomatic and Consular Services in Iran, only that relating to Kowait and the maintenance expenditure in other posts are at present divisible between the Government of India and His Majesty’s Government# The charges of the Sub-Division excluding the pay and allowances of the Assistant Sngineer in charge are first divided in proportion to the non-divisible and divisible works outlay for the year and only the portion relating to the divisible works outlay is included in the statement of divisible expenditure and shown partly under Bushire and partly under Kowait, the other portion being debitedentirely to Ifte Grovenraent ot India, xhere can l&gt;e no Q.uestion that this is not a fair distribution. 3* As regards the Assistant Engineer, his pay ami allowances, which are excluded from the above Calculation are wholly included separately in the statement or divisible expenditure, and a moiety of these charges is allocated in the proportion of the divisible woifcs outlay in various places, and added to His Hajesty # s Governments share of that outlay. The net result in any case is that His Majesty 9 s Government pay a moiety of the pay and allowances of of this to the works-outlay does not increase the debit. Resident in all Public Works matters and the Government of India consider that as in the case of other o&amp;volntmQnts in the Gulf, a moiety of the whole of his emoluments should, be borne by His Majesty # s Government. 5. AS regards the suggestion that a fixed not be correct*. On the whole the present method of allocation appears to be fair to both parties* AS charges to the works-outlay it may be mentioned that the cost of establishment entertained for the the Assistant Engineer and the subsequent allocation 4* The Assistant Engineer, not only supervises the execution of all public works in the Persian Gulf but also aots as the Adviser to the Political general rate on the analogy of the practice obtaining in the Office of Works might be adopted, the Government of India consider that such a method will regards the high percentage of the estaolishment execution/execution of subllc works In different localities is 'bouni to wary according to local circumstances, xhe staff employed In the Gulf receive more pay ^ addition specla'l allowances necessitated oy the corniltlons of service there. Trave-j-‘-eg Jjf ^ In the Gulf Is more costly and the area comprised in the Sub-Division helng large a^ the means of communication difficult, the outdoor establishment for worte has to he entertained on a larger scale than Is the case in rc*. These factors account for the high rate of establishment charges in the Gulf In relation to works expenditure. Bvan in IikLia the rate differs widely in differed localities, e.g., Central Works executed by the Worth West Wrontier Province are charged at the rate of i to Bihar and Orissa the rate is 27 * and in Burma 57-'#. I am to request that an explanation on the above lines, may If the Secretary of State, agrees, be furnish. e&amp; to to© Foreign Of floe* X ha Vfl the honour to b8 f 3 ir Your Most oho^ient serv^nt^ for JOreign Secretary to the Government of India.In any further communication on this subject, please quote no. K. and address— not to any person by name, but to— “The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. 1. (J2) THE Under - Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his npliments to ob-'l and begs to enquire, by direction of the Secretary of State, whether an answer may shortly be expected to the Foreign Office letter No. Y\ , l^L l j ^ /&lt;f/t j)^. respecting &amp; U_A (/\— Foreign Office, ^floV-X i 1^3V ' H fit&amp;i B. 0. &lt;/a,fZyr-7 ^ I / 516 «; NO. 47-A./36. ' / f / ]g3S J From 57 The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, To The Under Secretary of State for India, Political Department, India Office, London, S.W.l. Dated Simla, the September 1936. Percentage charges in respect of Civil ^orks in Persia and Koveit. • • • • • Sir, j / With reference to your letter Ho. P.Z.268/36, dated the 30th January 1936 and the reminder thereon dated the 13th August 1936, on the above subject, I am directed to state that it has been necessary to obtain certain particulars from the Accountant General, Central Revenues, in regard to the points raised. The matter is being expedited and it is hoped that a reply to the reference will be sent shortly. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, for Foreign Secretary to the Government of Indiar-\ n xy ic /a Y Accountant-Generars Department. *4 A.G. No. 13r*!*) /s Rec. 193 Referred to the Secretary, ii ^ 193i Political Dept. Please see the Foreign Office letter of 19th December 1935 below. That Department is aware of the system of charging in the D. and 0. Accounts a share of the expenditure of the Persian Gulf Independent Sub division, P.W.D., (vide paragraph 2 of the letter and the India Office letter there referred to - flag A) and it must be assumed that the Foreign Office realise that the objections raised are to figures obtained by the division of actual expenditure on establishments in ratios determined by the relationship between other - * items of actual expenditure. The letter must be read, therefore, as an appeal that India should abandon the existing system of charging the real cost of the services rendered by the Public Works Department, or an t - j approach thereto, and substitute charges at some arbitrary rate which will not cover the whole of the P.W.D. expenditure. Such a concession, the Foreign Office contend, is called for because the Office of Works charge only ll^o. The point at issue is thus one which cannot be dealt with as an accounting matter, and this letter is therefore referred for action by the Secretary, Political Department. Some observations which may assist consideration of the question follow. The 11/6 rate is explained at flag B and it will be noticed that it is a rate for general application, not one specially calculated for Persia where the prevailing conditions must add to expense. On this ground, therefore, the Foreign Office appear to have a case, not/net of course for the adoption of the llyo rate by India (it is unlikely that India and -the Office of Works observe the same methods of compiling 1 prime cost* and departmental expenses 1 ) but for the adoption of an Indian general rate in place of the high fluctuating rate resulting from the separate calculation of costs of the Persian Gulf establishment. The iromlnat Indian rate is in the neighbourhood of 24;o. Figures which show the effect of the percentage charges in recent years are as follows. Indian Accounts . F.Q. Accounts . Cost of Percentage Pay etc .of Prime cost of Works. Charges. Asst.Eng. workplis receipts. 11% 1933/34 Rs. (Bushire 11,477 (Koweit 1,09,872 Rs. 2,123 20,327 Rs. 1,085 10,392 £ £ 1,21,349 22,450 11,477 Not yet available. 193S/33 (Bushire 5,057 (Koweit 61,153 1,430 17,287 780 9,426 66,210 18,717 10,206 5,726 630 1931/33 Bushire 7,508 10,722 9,595 4,196 462 The amounts shown above under ’Indian Accounts' include all P.W.D. charges which are identifiable. The figures may not be complete but it is unlikely that any large items have been omitted. ■ The pay and allowances of the Assistant Engineer, P.W.D. , are shown above as, although the Foreign Off ice have made no reference to these charges which appear in D. and C. Accounts, the true amounts of the additions for establishment charges in the Indian accounts are the amounts of the percentage charged plus the charges for pay and allowances of this officer.Reference Paper. Accountant-General’s Department. A.G. No. liec. 193 Referred to 193 3 So far as this Department is aware the Office of Works official vis-a-vis the Assistant Engineer, P.W.D., is not charged for outside the llyb addition. Incidentally it would seem from a comparison with the entries in the Finance and 'Revenue Accounts that the practice is to charge up the whole of the emoluments of the Assistant Engineer in either the Persia or Koweit statements regardless of the fact that some portion of his duties may he connected with (a) works in Persia of a capital nature and (b) works of any description at posts such as Muscat, in neither case involving adjustment of their cost with H.M. Government. If this surmise is correct the Foreign Office, who would not be in a position to detect this apparent anomaly, seem to be overcharged, and relief under the pay head might ease the way for acceptance of the continuance of the existing scheme ofP.Z.268/36 Draft Paper political Department DRAFT LETTER. The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India F.&amp; P.Department. 3 y JAN 1936 Sir I am directed by the s/s for 1. to forward a copy of a letter noted in the F.O.letter of 19th Dec NO.. K 12991/132/234. margin on the subject of Diplomatic and Consular expenditure in Persia, and in particular the percentage charges in respect of Civil Works. U U.LJ. J. J. U LJ vy_l_ WJ.XW Kjjr kj u em^ but he would araw the attention of the G.of I. to the following considerations. The rate charged by the Office of Works is a rate for general application and not one specially calculated for Persia, where prevailing conditions must add to eta expense. On tlbs analogy ; there would appear to be a case for the adoption by the G.of 1. of a fixed general rate in place of the now fluctuating rate resulting from a separate calculation of cost of the Persian Gulf establishment. His Lordship also observes that the pay and allowances of the Assistant Engineer •ef tta Public Works Department, appear in the Indian accounts as a separate item over and above the percentage charges, whereas the Office of Works* official / corresponding to the Assistant Engineer^is not charged for outside the 11 per cent. rate. It appaars,^ moreover, from irrinl MM^iinfOr that the whole of the emoluments of the Assistant Engineer are charged in either the Persia or the Koweit statements, regardless of the lact that some portion of his duties may be connected with works or in Persia of a capital nature snsd works of description &lt;&gt;f posts such as Muscat which in neither case involve an adjustment of cost with His Majesty’s Government. If this is the case His Loraship considers that the F.O. might rightly complain that they are overcharged. 1 am to request, therefore, that the G.of 1. will examine the whole question, and in particular the considerations set r out above, and will communicate to the S/S as soon as possible their recommendations for a reply to the points raised by the F.O. in paragraph 3 of their letter fid horowith. (Sgd.) H, ’ °n r' n and nt butz - ' No. K 12991/132/234 In any further communication on this subject, please quote and address— not to any person by name but to— “ The Under-Secretary of State,” /V\ \ Foreign Office. S.W.l. 19th December, 1935 Foreign Office, London, S.W.l. Sir, r With further reference to India Office letter A»G. H70/35 M.l of the 12th March last preferring a claim for the payment of an amount in respect of the adjustment of diplomatic and consular expenditure in Persia and elsewhere for the year 1932/33 I am directed hy the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs to state that his attention has heen drawn to the proportionally high charges made by the Government of India in respect of Civil Works. In the- case of repairs at the Residency at Bushire at a cost of 5,057 Rupees, this charge was 1,430 Rupees, and in the case of expenditure amounting to 61,153 Rupees on the construct! of the new Agency buildings at Koweit, the charge was 17,287 Rupees. In both cases, therefore, the charge was over 28/ which compares unfavourably with the 11/ administration charge applied by His Majesty's Office of Works in connexion with similar undertakings^ 2. The method employed in calculating these charges was explained in the enclosure in India Office letter A.G*366/33 M.l of 19th January, 1933, but the employment of that method results in charges for administration which appear to be disproportionately high. 3. I am therefore to enquire whether a reduction of/ The Under-Secretary of State, India Office</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0000da_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/3656</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0000da</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/3656</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 29/80 'Diplomatic and consular expenditure: percentage charges on Civil works'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1935/1944</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-09-25T10:50:39</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (42 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 44; these numbers are written in pencil and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file concerns expenditure for Diplomatic and Consular services in Persia.The file covers percentage charges on Public Works in the Persian Gulf and percentage charges for special and ordinary repairs to consular buildings.The file is composed of correspondence between the Political Residency in the Persian Gulf, the Foreign Office, the India Office, the Government of India, and the Office of Works.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of India</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Persian Gulf Political Residency</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Office of Works, London</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Expenditure</topic></subject><subject><topic>Building maintenance</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0000da#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>