<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x00006d_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T11:51:15.384Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Notes on Tours in Persia in 1881 . The natural Obstruction to the Navigation to the Karoon River at Ahwaz, as seen 1st December 1881. 1. It will be seen by sketch forwarded with this, that as the Karoon approaches Ahwaz its course is divided into two parts by an island, marked I. 1 on plan Ao. 4. The branch to the west carries about one third of the stream, whilst that to the east has the other two thirds; the latter is deep and navigable for boats or flats of from 4 feet to 4 feet 6 inches draught, and this is the case with the river up stream as far as Bend-i-kir. 2. At Bend-i-kir is the junction of three streams, viz., the Dizful River on the west, the Karoon from Shuster alias Shtait in the centre, and Gerber or the stream diverted from the Karoon above Shuster (and regulated Tdv the Kaiser Bend) on the east; these three combined are 200 yards wide at their confluence. 3. The Dizful River, as seen 10 miles below the town of Dizful, is a rapid stream with a variable course over stony pebble bed, and quite unnavigable. At Bend-i-kir it is about 70 yards wide. 4. The Karoon just below Shuster is not navigable, and this is said to be the case with it the whole way upw r ards from Bend-i-kir, where it is 80 yards wide. 5. The “ Kaiser Bend ” or Gerger Stream is 50 yards w r ide at Bend-i-kir, where it joins the Karoon, and is over six feet, and probably 10 feet in depth. It is said to be navigable for large boats close up to Shuster. It has a slow placid stream, which is the case of the combined river below Bend-i-kir, though its banks showed in December marks of floods six feet above the then level of the river. 6. The combined river at Weis, half way between Bend-i-kir and Ahwaz, measured 283 yards in width. The banks of alluvial silt are throughout 20 feet above the water, and admirably adapted for towing gangs who would tow craft by means of ropes attached* to their masts, as is done in Bengal when the rivers are low. 7. To return to Ahwaz. Below the island mentioned in para. 1 the river only unites in a stream to be immediately confronted by the obstruction, which 1 will now describe in detail. 8. A ridge of sandstone which emerges from the Ram Hormuz Plain, som£ 20 miles west by south of Ahwaz, here approaches the river, and apparently it is greatly due to this ridge of rock that the river presents the navigable aspect it does for so many miles above Ahwaz. The rocks form a complete weir across the stream, which, flowing as best it can over the numerous outcrops, falls at least six feet in three fourths of a mile of its course. Were it not for this weir it is doubtful if the nature of the river would not be entirely different. 9. The sandstone so plainly visible in the river bed never rises above the level of the country to^iie east by north. 10. The weir or series of weirs at Ahwaz comprise five principal outcrops of sandstone, with a dip to the north of 15°, the outcrop being south, and the strike, as already stated, from west by south to east by north. 11. No. 1 group is perhaps the most formidable; appearing 25 yards below the island, it narrows the river to 300 yards in width, presenting a double ridge of rock, over which the water roars in times of flood. There are, how- 7652. I. 2720.2 ever, two openings, each of 50 yards in width, in the low wall of rock, and through these the water pours at ordinary times, having a tall of, say, - feet 6 inches in a length of 30 yards. 12. No. 2 group crosses the river 1,100 yards below No. 1, the river having turned 15° to the east to avoijl the numerous rocks which crop out from the left hank, hut do not extend right across its bed. Considerable accumulations of silt have collected on tlie rocks on the left, but they do not ioin the bank. Water channels have been cut in rock between them and the bank for the purpose of turning mills {vide plan), and then direction marks the course of a considerable flow of water in flood time. It was along the rid-eof group 2 that the ancient band was built by the Sasamans (?). Remains of this massive structure are still visible, but only high and dry, far out of the present course of the water, which is m a rapid stream between depressions in the rock, and impassable for boats. The ancient band was adapted to the configuration of the rock to the left hank, where the sandstone is high above the river. A loop in the band took in these high rocks, which are pierced by tunnels and sluice channels tor diverting, probably, the water into canals for irrigating t.m country. 13. Between group 1 and group 2 a small ferry boat now plies, but has difficulty in avoiding the shallows and rocks. 14. No. 3 group is 200 yards below group 2. It is of low flattish rock, and causes rapids. By below is meant down stream. 15. No 4 group is 200 yards below group 3. It is of the same character as No 3 Below this group an island has been formed of silt (marked I, 2 on plan), and it divides the river. This island extends down stream over and beyond group 5. 16. No. 5 group causes rapids in the two branches, formed by the island above mentioned, throughout their whole width. 17 Below group 5 the river is narrowed by rocks to a width of 165 yards. Here it becomes deep, and from this point to its mouth is easdy navigable by large boats. 18 It would, no doubt, not be difficult to blow out passages in the above- named ridges of sandstone, and leave an uninterrupted way for the river, hut it is impossible to predict what effect thus letting loose the pent up water of the Upper Karoon would have on the whole bed of the river. 10 I calculate roughly that, from the narrows down stream to the island ah™, group No 1, the' river falls from 8 to 10 feet. It may be conceived what a torrent would flow from No. 1, were a free channel out for the water from it to the narrows. 20 The whole of the rocks, &amp;c., within the present limits of the river hanks are liable to he swept by floods. Therefore, supposmga canal were cut in the rock in the direction shown in dotted lines, thus — — fui which would be the least expensive way as regards excavation, yet the difficulty of protecting the lock gates from damage at the up stream end, and the difficulty and cost of protecting the canal with masonry from |»mg s t up bv the spill of the river in flood tune, would, I think, make this plan inadmissible, besides more than two locks would he required. 21. The best plan, in my opinion, would teto dig a canal from the narrows at (A) to the pool above Ah war at (B), following the red line on plan. Two locks would be required, viz., one at A and one at B, and no doubt sandstone would be met with for the greater part of the length (2,3o0 yards), vet, once the work executed, these same sandstone walls to the canal would be of the greatest benefit, and would never he a cause of expense, i the hanks of most navigable water ways. Again, the sandstone would form excellent walls to the locks, and greatly lessen the cost of their construction, as the locks could he placed wherever the rock was best, and need no necessarily be at A or B.22. Between A and 1&gt;, along the red line shown on the plan, there would probably never he more than 35 feet of excavation required, even if the canal were to he 8 feet deep. 23. As a temporary measure, a wharf might he constructed on piles in the pool at A, and in the still water below the narrows at B, where native boats are now in the habit of lying, and these two points be connected by means of a tramway, which could be laid with very little labour, the ground being nearly level, and goods transhipped thus from the lower to the upper river, or vice versd. With this tramway irrigation, canals would not be interfered with, if led from either side of the river above No. 1 group; but even with the locks at work there would be a very small waste of water, unless the traffic became very great. However, there is enough good ground about Shuster to be developed without irrigating that below the band for many a year.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x00006d_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/18/C34</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x00006d</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/18/C34</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Notes on Tours in Persia in 1881: the natural obstruction to the Navigation to the Karoon River at Ahwaz as seen 1st December 1881'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1881/1881</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-06-06T00:34:24</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>2 folios</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence commences at f 133, and terminates at f 134, as it is part of a larger physical volume; these numbers are written in pencil, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. Pagination: the item also contains an original pagination sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The memorandum consists of notes and observations on the navigability of the Karoon [Kārūn] river supplied by Captain H Wells, Royal Engineers, with a particular focus on Ahwaz [Ahvāz]. It also supplies a few suggestions for possible improvements.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><geographic>Karoon River</geographic></subject><subject><topic>River navigation</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x00006d#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>