<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0003c2_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-12T01:53:18.897Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Telegram (en clair) From Special, Basrah. To Political, Kuwait No. Nil. Dated 1st January 1928. Sulailat Arali mentioned in Special Nasirlyah's telegram of yesterday arrived here to-day and gives similar hearsay information as already mentioned by Special, Nasiriyah, Also that Ibn Sa'ud summoned heads of villages of Najd for assistance against Dawish*Telegram (C)* Proa Political, Kuwait. To Resident,Bushire; repd. Baghdad,Basrah &amp; Nasiriyah. No. 4. Dated 2nd January 1928. My telegram No. 3* The messengers (Shaikh of Kuwait's own men and also men sent by I bn Sa'ud) with despatches for the Shaikh as well as for the High Commissioner for 'Iraq, left Riyadh on the 23rd December and arrived here on 1st January. Ibn Sa'ud was in Riyadh when they left and had no inten tion of leaving it in the immediate future. It is only the Mutair who are out of control at present and other tribes are quiet. Ibn Humaid is at Ghatghat, his ordinary headquarters. Another force under Fahd bin ’Abdullah bln Jiluwl has been ordered up from Hasa and instructed to punish Ibn Shuqair for the raid near Jahrah on 4th December. Ibn Shuqair is near,but not actually at, Safah. Present whereabouts of Dawish not known. Telegram (P). Prom Political, Kuwait. To Resident, Bushire, repeated to Baghdad. No. 5. Dated 2nd January 1928. My immediately preceding telegram. Shaikh Ahmad thinks fchfcm that the prospects of Ibn Sa'ud speedily regaining control over the Mutaib are good. He is still of opinion however that he will employ peaceful methods in achieving this end and that he would be ill advised to attempt to punish Dawish^Telegram (en clair) From Special, Nasiriyah To Political, Kuwait. No. 1/859. Dated 2nd January 1928. Traveller reports shepherds near Bamiyah (33 miles south-west Shu'aibah) heard rumours of impending raid by Ibn Shuqair and retreated northwards• Telegram (en olair)» From Special, Nasiriyah, To Political, Kuwait* No. 1/872. Dated 3rd January 1928. Special, Samawah, reports. Begins* 'All Salih (Zaiyad) states Dhafiri arrived al-Ans says was cap cured by Ikhwan near Qubbah south ’Athamln nine days ago. Dhafiri reports lithwan here intended send away loot and continue raids* Hamud Salman traveller Zubalr to Baghdad allege reports from Kuwait Ibn Hithlain now allied Ibn Shuqair and intends raids Kuwait area&lt; Messenger reached Khashl Chalawl (Asaidah) near ’Ain Sa'id stated Hashl Khashaim (Dharawishah) intends join Zaiyadl al- Ans district owing to rumours that Muhsin al«Flrm intends raiding. Can you confirm re Ibn Shuqair and Ibn Hithlain or Al-Flrm? Telegram (en clair). From Political, Kuwait. To Special, Nasiriyah. No. 14. Dated 3rd January 1928. Your l/8?2. No confirmation and part about Ibn Hithlain not believed.• 9 Telegram (C)« From Political, Kuwait To Resident, Bushire; repeated to Baghdad, Basrah and Nasiriyah* No Dated 4th January 1928 . There was an unimportant raid by Ibn 'Ashwan and about Twenty Buraih Mutair on Kuwait Arabs near Llyah (Yah on maps) 19 miles north of Jahrah on 2nd January. The raiders were driven off. Dated 3rd January 1928. Taxi driver arrived Zubair to«day stated he was turned back Jal al-Liyah yesterday by Arab who stated Ikhwan raided ^raibdar yesterday. Please telegraph if true. Telegram (en clair). From Political, Kuwait. To Special, Busrah. No. 16 . Dated 4th January 1928. Your 222. Raid quite unimportant. Details sent to Admintor. Telegram (en clair). From Special, Busrah To Political, Kuwait&lt; 3 j Tele^raoi (en clalr). From Special, Basrah. To Political, Kuwait No 223 Datdd 3rd January 1928- Special, Nasiriyah, received information that Ion Hithlain of the ^Jman allied to Ibn Shuqalr intend to raid Kuwait. Also that Muhsin al-Firm of the Harb intends raiding. Have you any confirmation ? Telegram (en clair). From Political. Kuwait. To Special, Basrah. No Dated 4th January 1928 Your 223. No.Dated 4th January 1928. Police Busaiyah report the arrival of a Dhafiri from Najd who states Dawish at Sha ! ib al-Massarl, north west of *AwaJ, with approximately 1000 men. Also that the Dhafir believe Ibn Sa^d at Artawlyah and has asked the following leaders to assist him against Dawish: Ibn Nuhalyir, Al-Firm, Ibn Ruba^an ('Utaibah). Also that Ibn Humaid refused to meet Ibn Sa'ud. Letter No. 18 dated 4th January 1928 from P # A., Kuwait to H*E. Shaikh Ahmad al-Jabir as-Subah, G 0 I*E,, Ruler of Kuwait. After compliments. I have the honour to inform your Excellency that I have received a telegram from Nasiriyah to the effect that a Dhafiri from Na$d who has arrived at Baswah Police Post states that Faisal ad-Dawish is at present at Sha'lb al- Massarl, north west of ’AwaJ, with approximately 1000 men. I cannot find either name on my map. This Is for your information. Usual ending.tfQUBSi) that they were to withdraw to aJIBia (135 alios S.I¥«of AL U4JBJAU ) 9 A however, are said to have disregarded these instruetions and to have joined the DW 1 SE after the raid pro seeding with him to AJfcAl* One of Ah Jt'Xlili v s personal following named AL yOxtli met the sen of HUSoaUI IM MliiWAtf (aiWALD - HHaPIK) and told him 'tell IM ^UWaXT from AX* ilili that the IUWIis goiqg te raid him and let him move westwards at ones and mix with &amp;AMMAn“» MUIM 1 BN SUWMT still declined to move on receipt of this warning and said he would await word from AJAliil* After the raid the camped in aHAlB A&amp;J MAM AM (25 miles of al ) for some days# His intention to return te AftfAPflYAd haa beeome known when suddenly he ehanged hie plans and proceeded towards AdaAil. He was in constant touch, by messenger, udth Axi^AWl YM • stated that before his arrival at IBB TUVIaLa»s camp messaigezm had reached there from IM MBsaaB calling on all tribes to send contingents te join IM oaUD's force against the WWIaB* IM MUdaih premised a dhelul and a rifl# to such of those joining qp who had none. HUEAtUR had set out in person with 200/300 men and other shaikhs were sending detachments. He gatnered that public opinion in HAiJ, and throughout JAiAX* oUMUj* was unanimously against the BOWIsl,On his viay baok to tho oaiop ho met a who alaLnod to hare just oome from IB* BAUD and who told him that the latter’s force had reached IMBAlUJOi some 40/bo miles east of AxtfA'.VXXAfc• He would not -vouch for the solufcbl's information as correot but said it was quite probably true* He also reported a rumour that Idi HUMaID had refused to visit the sultan Then ordered te do so* t intelligent Bedouin opinion consulted by the writer, considers that if the report is true that 1M saUD is marching on aaSaWIYAK, the DHTliM may be endeavouring to escape to Syria* On the other hand it may be that he proposes to carry out a further raid possibly on the DAhaHSJUih or on the shepherds who were camped south of SUIidAK, but were this his intention, they consider he would have attacked some five days ago* Should he subsequently return te and receive any less punishment than death*, from IBIf BAUD, nothing will convince local Bedouin opinion that the sultan is not the instigator of the apparent upheaval in Ba4 d* DopieS;- Flying of£io«r air Headquarters, S.S«0., Nasiriyak A«I»,#asiriyah I»G*P * ,Na»i riyah A»l#, Diwaniyah S • B *0 • , Di wani yah 3*3*0* ,Basrah political JLimrait pile • /• /Telegram (P). From Hlghcoma, Baghdad. To Colonies; repeated to Busnl^e 4-S (9 to Colonies). ffg( N n No I. Iraq ministers. Air Officer Commanding and I have dis cussed the question of attacking tribal headquarters, and have decided unanimously that it is impracticable to do so too far off. Other places are only small oases or wells ana If tents were pitched and occupied they would doubtless scatter when they received warning and no subsequent opera tions of any value would be possible. The maps we have are far from accurate and thete is no British Officer in 'Iraq who has a sufficient knowledge of the country to insure the oDjectives being reached by the machines. Any operations undertaken must fulfil two purposes both of which are equally important (A) to stop the raiding forth with and (3) to inflict as severe a punishment as possible on the Mutair. The Air Officer Commanding and I think that these objectives can be obtained by exercising air control over the largest possible area of Najd territory. Two air bases will therefore be established forthwith under the protection of armoured cars. To start with these bases will ' oe well within the territory of 'Iraq, but will be gradually pushed forward as far to the south as tne question of supplies permits, and it is hoped will eventually be loca ed one at eacn end of the 1 ms neutral zone. Warnings will be dropped to camps and grazing parties where the Mutair usually graze telling them to march south to the frontier withing four days. Failure to do so will mean that they will be attacked. Parties oh the move without flocks and herds will be presumed tu be raiders and will be attacked without warning whenever met. There is n. fear that the forces of Ion Sa'ud will be in the area controlled. I believe that this method affords the best hope of (A) putting a stop to raiding, (B)punishing L the Mutair, (C) showing the Ikhwan that we are as able to be buildings are known to exist except at Artawiyah which leprevent them from fcrazint, peacefully in tineir normal pastures as they are to prevent 'Iraq tribes from grazing peacefully in , Iraq, and (D) forcing the Mutair to suomit to Ibn Sa*ud. These measures will make It impose!ole to comply with the Shaikh of the 'Anizah's request for aeroplanes and armoured cars to protect his tribe, but they should reassure the 'Anizah. Small posts equiped with wireless and Lewis guns will also be established forthwith, probably as a permanent measure, at Shabichah and Salman. Desert opinion is strongly in favour of the blockade of Hasa ports as being the most effective weapon against the Ikhwan. It would not, however, have as rapid an effect as attacks on the Mutair, and it kx«L has the further oejection that it would Iook as if it were directed against Ibn Sa*ud himself, and not against, his rebellious tribes. I still think, how ever, that this measure should be adopted if those proposed in this telegram prove ineffective. Latest Najd news is very conflicting but indicates that the measures taken by Ibn Sa*ud hg&amp;inst Dawish have been checked by the 'Utaibah tribes* threatening attotude. Expert opinio 1 holds that if they combine with the Mutair Ibn Sa'ud will be^- powerless to reduce them by force. If these measures be adopted the message to Ibn Sa*ud will have to be amended and I presume that you will instruct the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf accordingly. Telegram (P). From Political, Kuwait. To Resident, Bushire; repeated to Baghdad. No. 22. Dated 6 th January 1928. Reference telegram No.4~S from the High Commissioner for ‘Iraq. I venture to remind you that one of the chief causes of the quarrel between ibn Sa’ud and Shaikh Salim of Kuwait was the building of a village at Jaryah by Ibn Shuqair in 1920.Telegr im (en clair) C&lt;Q Prom Special, Nasirlyah Political, Kuwait. 1/891 To No Dated 5th January 1920. Ruwaiyan bin Nawasir (Araif Dhfir) who left Linah on 20th December states that Dawish was camped at Naja east of Linah and believed, though not definitelt imown, that his intention is to raid the Dahamishah when his horses ape recovered. He stated that Dawish promised immunity to I bn Shuraim and Ibn Habbas (Shammar) and Qumaiz al-Aslib (Dhafir) and ordered them to camp near him. When laf orman left they were camped a little nortK of Linah. Informant also stated that Dawish’s force numbers 2000 and that Firm agreed to Join Dawish until he heard that the latter was acting contrary to Ibn Sard's orders. The degree of informant's acuuracy is not yet known.Letter No .21 dated 6 th January 1928 from P.A H.E, Shalich Ahmad al-Jablr as-Subah, ,, Kuwait, to Rller of Kuwait. After compliments. I have the honour to inform Your Excellency that I have received a telegram from Nasiriyah to the effect that according to the statement of a Dhafiri who left Linah on the 4th Rajab, Dawish was then camped at a place called Naq'ah or Naqah, to the east of Linah, and it was thought, although not definifeelj* known, that his intention was to raid the Dahamishah when his horses were rested. Dawish had promised immunity to I bn Shuraim and Ibn Habbas and also to Qumaiz al-Aslib and had ordered them to camp near him, and when he left they were camped a little to the north of Linah. He had heard that Firm had agreed to Join Dawish until he heard that he was acting contrary to Ibn Sa'ud^ orders. Usual ending.Dated 6 th January 1928. Special Samawah's l/41 of 5th January begins:- tribesman of Jawasim Dhafir reports the following. Jabbar Dhafiri messenger yesterday reached Muhammad Shi brum (Jawsim Dhafir) near Humaid from Jada'an Suwait at Abu AJJaJ near Abu Ghar. Jabbar reports messenger arrived Jada'an from ’UJaimi Suwait at Taiyarat Llnah reporting that ten days ago Ibn Masa'ad, Jazza 1 Mijlad with Ibn Ruraall (Shammar Singarah) also possibly Muhsin Firm and Ruwailah sections, raided 'Uzaiyiz ad-Dawish at Najah and inflicted defeat,capturing ’Uzaiyiz. Sa’ud bin ’Abdul 'Aziz reported entered Artawiyah and Ibn Sa’ud himself advancing. Faisal ad-Dawish reported with Ibn Humaid. Reliability of this report quite indefinite here yet, but supported by many other rumours from from the tribes. Ends*Telegram (P). From Aviation, Baghdad. To Political, Kuwait. No. 3/956. Dated 5 th January 1928. lould Jaryat al-'Ulya, Jaryat as-Sifla and Najirah, or any of theaij, make suitable targets for aeroplanes? The last two are believed to be the headquarters of Haif al-Fuqm and ? Ali bin 'Ashwan. Jaryat al-’lllya is belived to be the headquarters of Ibn Lami, who has been reported to be used by Ibn Sa f ud against Dawish. Would it be undesirable to take action against this village? Where is Turahib bin Shuqair’s headquarters, and is he for or against Dawish? Please wire your comments. Telegram( jp/ (P). From Political, Kuwait. To Aviation, Baghdad; repeated to Bushire. No. 25. Dated ?th January 1928. Jaryat al-’Ulya is Ibn Shuqair’s headquarters, and it was he who was responsible for the raid on 4th December near Jahrah. Jaryat as-Sifla is Fuqm's headquarters, and Ibn ’Ashwan's headquarters is Najirah. There are not more than one or two houses each, if as many, at the last two places; but the first named is a regular village and in my opinion would make a fairly good target but for tne reasons given in my immediately following telegram.Telegram (0) Prom Political, Kuwait. To Resident, Bushire; repeated to Highcoma and Avatlon, Baghdad, Basrah and Nasiriyah. No. 26. Dated ?th January 1928. Traveller frora the south arrived here 6 th January, reports that Jaryah has been evacuated and entirely abandoned, in habitants with all animals, etc, having moved to Safah for fear of Pahd bln Jiluwi. Ibn Shuqair has sent message to Ion Sa^d asking for pardon and begging him to punish him himself if he likes, but not to leave him to the mercy of Ibn Jiluwi. Ibn Sa'ud is still at Riyadh. Reliability of man not known but story considered possible.^o2/ 2Z Telegram (en clair). From Special, Nasiriyah. To Political, Kuwait. No. 1/915. Dated 11th January 1928 . Reliable agent from Jilabi reports Dawlsh with force 1500 to A 2000 and 50 tents passed Thamami (90 miles S.S*W, of Uqubbah, about seven days ago, believed proceeding to Ibn Humaid. No truth in the report that Ibn Musa 1 ad attacked Dawish. Habbas bin Habbas (Shammar ’Abdah) and Musir bin Dirrah (Aralf Dhaflr) camped Jilbabi* Telegram (C). From Admintor, Basrah. To Political, Kuwait. No. 49. Dated 11th January 1928. Ibn Musa’ad said to have captured Dawish near Linah. Can you confirm? Telegram (C). From Political, Kuwait. To Admintor, Basrah. No. 37. Dated 12th January 1928. Your telegran No. 49. No confirmation here( 0 ) To Froa No PoliLiujil, Kuwait. Resident, Bushire; repeated to Baghdad, Basrah and Naslriyah. 39a Dated 12th January 19^8a f^utairi froiB Safah arrived here lion January says that news had reached there before he left that Ion Sa^ud, accompanied all the principal UJlama of the Ikhwan, leaves Riyadh on the 13th January for Hafar al*- , Akk (pronounced wt Ach am s[mlo *Ats* on some paps), 95 miles north of Riyadh, where Ion Humald has arranged that Dawish shall come in to him. Ion Laml only Mutalri shaikh now at Safah. Ion Shuqair and Fuqn* gone further north. Present whereabouts of Dawish not known Reliability of the ^n not known.Telegram (C) From Highcoma, 3aghd To S. of S, for Colonies;repd. Bushire &amp; Kuwait 22 (25 to Colonies). No Dared 14th January 1928. Reference Ikhwan raid near Jaukhah on 1?th or 22nd Decem ber. Reports of survivors estimate the number of killed at seventy five belonging to the ’Iraq tribes of Zaiyad and Ban! Huchaia. Details of animals looted are expected shortly.To Telegram (C). From Hi&amp;hcama, Ba&amp;hdad To Political, Kuwait No Dated 20th January 1928. Baghdad Arab newspaper reports that large Wahhabi caravans are collecting supplies of grain, sugar, tea, and cloth from Kuwait and 'Uqair. Can you confirm? Telegram (C)* From Political, Kuwait. To Highcoma, Baghdad. No. 45. Dated 21st January 1928. Your telegram No.34. No. The report is quite untrue so far as Kuwait is concerned. I have no Information as to 'Uqair, but it is of course normal port at which such goods are imported from India, via Bahrain, into Najd. Telegram (C). From Political, Kuwait. To Highcoma, Baghdad. No. 46. Dated 21st January 1028. My immediately preceding telegram. I hear that Shaikh of Kuwait is presenting 500 ba&amp;d of rice to Fahd bin Jiluwi (please see my telegram No. 4 of 2nd January),which may be the origin of the rumour about Kuwait.Telegram (en clair). Recent reports of ij/l and later state Dawlsh’s force at Safah, himself at Artawiyan. Have you confirmation. Letter No. 4? dated 21st January 1928 from P.A., Kuwait, to H.E. Shaikh Ahmad al-Jabir as-Subah, G.I.E., Ruler of Kuwait. A.C. I have the honour to inform Your Excellency that ,1 have received a telegram from the Intelligence Officer of the Ur Force at Nasiriyah, in which he says that for the last seven /been days he has/hearlng rumours which Indicate that Faisal ad- Lawlsh himself has gone to Artawiyah, and that his force is now at Safah, and asks if I have any confirmation. Refore replying to him I should be glad to know if Your Excellency heard any news which might confirm or refute the above. u.Ey Telegram (en clair). From Political, Kuwait. To Special, Nasiriyah. No. 48. Dated 21 st January 1928 Your 1/16. No.Telegram (C). Prom Political, Kuwait. To Highcoma, Baghdad, with a request that he will give a copy to the Resident in the Persian Gulf; repd. to Basrah and Nasiriyah, last named informing Special with reference to my telegram No.48. No. 49 . Dated 22nd January 1928 . The Shaikh of Kuwait Informs me that he has Just heard that Dawlsh has arrived at Artawiyah. Telegram (C) Prom Political, Kuwait. To Highcoma, Baghdad, with the request that he will give copy to Resident; repeated to Basrah and Nasiriyah. No. 50 . Dayed 23rd January 1928. My telegrams No. 49 and No. 39- Information has been received from a source believed to be reliable that Dawish went to Artawiyah, and from there was going to Hafar al-'Ach to meet Ibn Sa'ud. He was taking a large body of Mutair with him for safty’s sake. The meeting was to take place on Thursday, but whether 19th or 26th January is not clear: probably the former date. /ri To Telegram fd). From Political, Kuwait. Highcoma, Baghdad (with the request that he will give a copy to Resident in the Persian Gulf);repd. to Basrah and Nasiriyah. 52. 25 th January 1928. My telegram N 0 . 5 O confirmed by Dhafiri Just arrived here who states that Dawish with all his force camped with I bn Suwait for four days about a fortnight ago. He tried to persuade him to Join him in a raiding expedition, but without success. While there messengers arrived from Ibn Humaid inviting Dawish to meet Ibn Sa'ud at Hafafc al-'Ach. Dawish decided to do so and left for the south, ne heard that Ibn Sa'ud was due to arrive at the rendezvous on or about the 24th January and that he would be aocompaniec by all the ’Ulama of the Ikhwan and of Najd.Basrah* { , The aarai, 16th January* 1*28. To, The adviser* Ministry of Interior* Baghdad. • inspector General of Police* Baghdad. • Administrative Inspector* Bi wanly ah. ” O.C. B.A.f. Based Stores, Ka'gil • Inspecting Oflicer of Police, Basrah. itemcraudum . By the Courtesy of the Special Service Officer, Basrah, I have been shown today the message given below. and am forwarding you a copy in case it may you previously. Similarly a copy has been-^e tical Agent* Kuwait. have reached to the Poli- Administrative Inspector, Basrah. TO Prom Akforce repeated Special Buscol. Baghdad Special Nasiriyah B/2&gt; of 12/1. Have found Hammad ibn Ghunaim of &amp;1 Suwait Sec* tion Ehafir camped near Jau Khirs&amp;n IB miles aouth of Buaaiyah. He gave inibraation in my fc/1 of 11/1. Gives following addi tional information. He was camped Ajalml suwaiVs camp at Na fud south Bir urn® Budhumsah within sight of Duvish's camp. Buwish and son with raiding party left hurriedly on evening of 2/1 on arrival two messengers from ^rtawlyah informing him ibn sa'ud was preparing march on Artawiy&amp;h. Similar news brought in ty Busalyah policeman who met caravan of Gumaiz al Aslib who had left al Gus&amp;ir ( 20 miles north of Abu Char ) to return to Jumaimah ( 80 miles N. W. of Ansab )• Hamnad ibn Ghunaim sta ted AJaiml Kuwait informed him that on day he left ?oya4h Sul tan ibn Humald was due in Blyadh as he had been alienated from Duwlsl^s support and won over by Ibn 3a*ud **ho had seat Mm presents and religious Akhwan shaikhs to denounce TUwish’s sec tions and hostility. Ibn Ss’ud ordered AJaimi return to his section which had been raided by TXiwish on 9/12 promising to avenge his royal honour as Suvait section ^ere under his pro tection. believed that Dovish and son going Artawiyah remove their families and have sent raiders to Safa join Thrahib ibn Jhugair threatened by force sent against him by Ibn Jilluwi from Hass&amp;. Before leaving Buwish presented Pirwi Ibn Suwait with camel horse and 20 sheep informing him would have liked continue raiding but his followers expended ammunition. Buwish and party reported as seen by Fabbas ibn Habbas spies crossing ai Batin at Thamami S.w. end of Batin foregoing believed fairly reliable so far unconfirmed. K. /Telegram (P) From Resident, Baghdad To Foreign, Delhi; repeated to Kuwait No T. 6 \ Dated 26th January 1928. Your telegram No. 145 S, There is no objection if there be any danger of Kuwait being attacked,. Anything that . marks the fact that Kuwait is under our protection is welcome to me, but X should be loath to increase the hostility between Ibn Sa'ud and Kuwait if it could be avoided. For this reason I would suggest that action be subject to the concurrence of both the Political Agent and the Shaikh. This refers to hhe removal of the prohibition against bombing over the territory of Kuwait.Telegram (C) PDom To Political, Kuwait, Resident, Muhamraarah; repeated to Basrah, Baghdad, and Nasiriyah. No. 55. Dated 2?th January 1928. Information has been received this evening, Friday, that the Ikhwan under 'All bin ’Ashwan of the Buralh Mutair raided Kuwait arabs at Urn® Ruwaisat, No details at present Telegram (C). From Political, Kuwait. To Resident, Muhammarah; repd. to Baghdad, Basran and Nasiriyah. No. 56. Dated 28th January 1928. My telegram No.55. Scene of the raid 58 miles north-west of Jahrah, Raiders estimated at 550 men plus 50 horsemen but said to be very badly armed. This information received from Shaikh’s representative at Jahrah yesterday evening, Friday, who asked for all available cars to be sent, out as soon as possible, and said that if the raiders were encumbered by sheep he had hopes of catching them. On receipt of the report the Shaikh commandeered practically all cars and sent them ax out to Jahrah last night. No further information has been received.Telegram (C) From More, Kuwait To Lincoln, Muhammarah No Dated 2?th January 1928, Following for the Resident in the Persian Gulf on arrival. Begins. Have you any objection to my going to Bushlre in Emerald and returning by first mail steamer? H.M.S, Emerald arrives there 2 p.m. ?donday so I should be able to A catch the Barjora due to sail the same evening. Telegram (C). From Resident, Muhammarah. To Political f Kuwait. No. Nil. Dated 28 th January 1928. I was Just about to ask you to come to Bushire by next mail. If you come by H.M.S. Smerald, perhaps Mrs. More would follow by mail. Bring your Ibn Sa'ud file. Telegram (C). From Mor e, Kuwait. To Resident, Bushire. No. 60. Dated 29th January 1928. Your telegram of 28th January. Thank you for invitation, out in view of the disturbed state of the country I am very unwilling to leave Kuwait at* all Just at present, as you wish to see me, however, I think I had better come in H.M.S, Emerald but will return by ss. Barjora if I can possibly do so. In view of the recent weather she will probably be slightly lateTelegram (C) e From Admtntor, Basrah# Political, Kuwait# No. a/M5- Dated 28th January 1928. j-Qur telegram dated 27th January No«55» Repeat word after 'raided”. Map reference of Ruwaisat requested. Telegram (C). From Political, Kuwait. To Admintor, Basrah. No. 57o Dated 28th January 1928# Your telegram dated 28th January No. C/115. Repetition begins. Kuwait Arabs. Ends* See my telegram No. 56. It is the same place as Shiqqat ar-Ruwaisat.Tele&amp;ram (C). From Political, Kuwait. To Resident, Bashir©; repd. to Baghdad,Basrah &amp; Nasiriyai No. 59 ,, Dated 29 th January 1928 . My telegram No* 56 . Kuwait force in twenty five cars (of which eighteen arrived there) proceeded direct to Riga'i, 90 miles west, south-west of Jahrah, in the hope of cutting off the raiders retirement« This they did and an engagement took place yesterday, Saturday. No details at present except that there were casualties on both sides. Raiders said to have retired, further details expected shortly. Telegram (C). Prom Political, Kuwait. To Resident,Bushire;repd. to Baghdad,Basrah ft Nasiriyah. No. 61 * Dated 29 th January 1928. My telegram No. 59® Fighting lasted from 1430 to 1630 hours. Most of plunder recovered. Pour of the Kuwait force wounded, including Shaikh 'All al-Khallfah and Shaikh Abdullah al-Jabir Considerable losses inflicted on raiders* Our aeroilanes seen. In the fighting at Umm Ruwaisat on 2?th January three Kuwait Arabs were killed.Telegram (C). From Political, Kuwait. Ho Reflident, Bushire; repd. to Baghdad,Basrah &amp;. Nasiriyah 59. Dated 29 th January 1928 . Uy telegram No. 56 . Kuwo.it force in twenty five cars (of which eighteen arrived there) proceeded direct to Riga’i, 90 miles ^eet, south-west of Jahr&amp;h, in the hope of cutting off the raiders retirement. This they did and an engagement took place yesterday, Saturday. No details at present except that there were casualties on both sides. Raiders said to have retired, further details expected shortly. Telegram (G). From Political, Kuwait* Daoed 29 th January 1928. My telegram No. 39. Fighting lasted from H 30 to 1630 hours, host of plunder recovered. Four of the Kuwait force wounded, including Shaikh *Ali nl-Khallfah and Shaikh 'Abdullah al-Jabir. Considerable losses inflicted on raiders. Our aeroplanes seen. In the fighting at Umm Ruwaisat on 27th January three Kuwait \rabs were killed. Telegram, Cole. From Political, Kuwait. Resident,Bushire; repd to Baghdad, Basrah k Nasiriya reported but not very serious except that Sheikh 'Ali bin Salim is missing and believed killed. To Resident,Bushire;repd. to Baghdad,Basrah &amp; Nasiriyah 61 . No. ^ated 30th January 1228. My telegram No.61. There were a few more &lt;xst oasualities amongst Kuwait force than those originallyTelegram (C) From More B Bushire To Political, Kuwait Words. 8 Dated 31st January 191i8 Please wire if* any news of* Shaikh Ali hin Salim and his party. Telegram (C), Ali hin Salim and his party of 10 are all killed except driver. Total numhoi.* of killed 13 amongst Kuwait force. Following telegram received from Special Nasiriyah dated the 31st January begins H 30th Januaey Machines attacked raiders north east alt Kafar 29th January inflicting casualities believed ten probably underestimated. Low clouds interered From To Political, Kuwait. Resident, Bushire No 4 33 Dated 31st January 1928 Following for Political Agent.Kuwait, Your telegram of 31st January. Skaikh with pursuit yesterday' Message ends Shaikh informed. All is qiiietTelegram (C) From To Special, Nasiriyah Political, Kuwait. No. ‘3/ 41 * ^ated 31st January 1928. 30/1 Machines attacked raiders north-east Al-IIafar 29th January inflicting casualities believed ten probably underestimated. Low clouds interfered with pursuit yesterday. * I Translation of a letter No.4 32 1 slit dated the 31st January 1928 from H.C., Political Agency, Kuwait, to H.F. Shaikh Ahmad al-Jabir as-Subah, Ruler of Kuwait. After compliments, I have the honour to inform Your Excellency that I have received a telegram from Nasiriyah to the effect that our machines attacked the raiders north-east of al-dlafar on the 29th January inflicting casualities believed ten persons but this is probably underestimated and low clouds ixfcaxfaxtt interfered with pursuit yesterday. Usual endingTelegram (C ). From Special, Nasiriyah To Political, Kuwait. No. 1/4 3. ■^atel 1st February 1928. Further my 1/41 of 31st January Aircraft attacked raiders twice on afternoon 30th January south of Batin eight miles from Kafar. casualities estimated 12 men, 36 camels and 2 horses. T&gt;etails follow hy post. To H.F. Shaikh Ahmad etc No.4330/ 1st Fehy.l92j After compliments. In continuation of my letter No.432, dated the 31st January 1928, I have the honour to inform Your Excellency that I have x*«xxa;&lt;t received a further telegram from Nasiriyah stating that the aircrafts attacked the raiaers twice on the afternoon of 30th January south of Batin eight miles from Hafar and casualities estimated 12 men, 36 camels and 2 horses. U.EI have the honour to acknowledge the receipt of Your Excellency's letter dated the 10th Sha'ban (i.e. 2-2-28) regarding 400 sheep which were carried off by the 'Iraq Muntafik. I have communicated this to the authorities concerned.% TELEG-jiaIi. (C) From Political, Kuwait Resirient,Bushire; repeated to Baghdad, Basrah and Nasiriyah. 4 35 3rd February 1928 To No. dated His Focellency the Shaikh informs me that a portion of plundered sheep amounting to 400 belonging to Kuwait and abandoned by the raiders were collected by local Bedouins with a * view to returning them to Kuwait, but they were met with a party of ’Iraq tribes of Muntafiq whose chief is Naif bin ’Agil and carried off the sheep. The local Bedouins think that this party will remain fo^ sometime au Akhdhar al-Mah. miles south-west Khabari al-Lajah near al-Batln has Kuwait J Telegram (en dale). From Special, Basrah, Kuwait. To. Special, Nasiriyah. No. 1/300. Dated 3rd February 1928. Am informed Sharshab ibn Shaham of Budur at Khadhr al-Mai,ten sheep or knows their whereabouts.Telegram (C). From Migh Commissioner for ’Iraq* Baghdad. Addressed Secretary of States for colonies, Resident in the Persian Gulf, Kuwait, Jerusalem and Jeddah. Words 108. hated 31st January 1928. Circular Telegram . On the 27th January Akhwan raiding party estimated at 400 men of Braih Mutair under Itm Ashwan raided Kuwait trihe at Chiqqat alvRuwaisat 35 miles north west of Tahrah and looted about 180 camels and 300 sheep, casualties on both sides. Shaikh of Kuwait cammandeered all available motor cars and despatched them to intercept the raiders. About tt 15 cars led by *Ali ibn Khalifa encountered at tom al-Riqai (at eastern extremity of neutral zone) on the night of 28th January and recaptured the looted animals. *Ali ibn Khalifah and ’Abdullah jabar, brother St Shaikh of Kuwait reported wounded and two irregulars killed* On the 29th January Air reconnaissance located th rt raiders in Nejd territory 15 miles north of Hafar, latter opened fire on aircrafts which replied with bombs and machine gun fire indicting casualities estimated at 10 men and 20 camels. Aircrafts were hit by rifle lire. On the 30th January raiders were again attacked about 8 miles south of Hafar by Aircrafts, ca sualities estimated at 4 men, 26 camels and 2 horses, Ibn t Ashwan is Chief who raided Ohafir in •Iraq territory in July 1925 and looted 3000 camels_^ He has always been friendly with nawish.p r-v A Telegram From To Aviation Baghdad Political Kuwait No. Pc6 Peted and received Sard. February 1928 Please discuss with de Gaury mutual measures which might be made for better co-operation in the case of future opportunities arising. Effective co-operation could have been arranged on the 28th. if only AK force or Shaibah had known in time that cars were proceeding to Riqai. In my opinion the most effective and rapid method obtaining and of/transmitting such news to Basrah by car or telegram would mean communicating with field Verey Lights etc. Please let me know whether the Kuwait forces wear any distinctive head dress or other mark of identity whereby they may be recognised. A V/ AT/ \ Telegram (C). From Political, Kuwait, Bushire. To Aviation, Baghdad. No. T-l. Dated 3rd February 1928. Immediate. Your telegram No.236. Am now in Bushire. Probably returning 5th. Will Inform you on arrival. Telegram (C). From Political, Kuwait. To Aviation, Baghdad; repeated to Special, Basrah. No. 63. Dated 5th February 1928. My telegram of 3rd February No. T-l. I have arrived here today Sunday./ ^ S Telegram (C). From Political, Kuwait. Resident, Bushire; repeated to Baghdad, Basrah and Nasiriyah. xVo. 64. Dated 6th February 1928. Uy telegram No. 52. According to information available here, the meeting between Ibn Sa'ud and Dawish did not take place. Ibn Sa ud is still at Riyadh and Dawish has moved out from Artawiyah to Sufaiyah, 42 miles to the North, north-east. Telegram (0). From Political, Kuwait. To Resident, Bushire; repeated to Aviation, Baghdad. No. 65o Dated 6th February 1928. Shaikh of Kuwait is very grateful for the action of the Royal Air Force after the recent raid. He says that he would appreciate it very much if aeroplahea could occasionally reconnoitre Kuwait territory. \Telegram (3) From Political, Kuwait, To Resident, Bushire: repeated to Badgdad, Basrah No and Naairiyah. 66 Dated ?th February 1928, Reference to my telegram No. 64, A member of the Rashaidah tribe, who was with Dawish on his earlier raid ing expeditions but who like most non- Mutair has now left him on realizing that he is definitely against Ibn Sa’ud, has arrived here* According to him Dawish himself is at Arfcawiyah and tJzaiyiz at Sufaiyah. Ibn Sa ! ud recently sent Dawish an ultimatum through Ibn Humaid, ordering him to come into him at once and definitely declaring war on him if he did not. Dawish did not go in and is consequently now avowdly in open rebellion * Everyone not of the Mutair has left Dawishe Ibn Ba’ud has ordered a blockade against the Mutair. Fahd bln Jiluwi’s force at 'Uwainah (about 175 miles south of Kuwait) is now said to number 5000 men, of whom a thousand are settled Arabs from Hasa and the xaKmxJi&amp; remainder tribesmen of the ’Awazim, Bani Khalid, Bani Hajir and other eastern tribes except the ’AJman, who are not trusted. Ibn Hithlain himself is with Ibn Jiluwi in Hasa, so cannot do much harm even if he wants to. The attitude of Ibn Humaid and the , Utalbah is doubtful. Ibn Humaid is at his headquarters, Ghatghat.a iu -ir^ relieve': tu hnve Allied t«eiye ai*n and a numi^r of and horses. On th^ whole the raiders appear to have suffered very heavily, and will prooebly not loo a upon Kuwait tribes as such an ^aay prey in future as they hive dcn» In tne peat. The extensive vise of o^rs by the Kuwait ft^roes in this •n£,ageaeat is interesting, and it ^ives thea an advantage over the Ixh.wttn ''/hioh L i itter oan never counter. Major, Political A&amp;ent, Kuwait. Jopy, vith compliments, to 'he Political .Secretary to H.T5. the U^i joaniasloner for 1 Iraq,Baghdad* The Administrative Inspector,Basrah ° ” ” ' The Administrative Inspector, hasiriyah.Tele^raa (Oode). From Admlator, anslrlyan. To Folitioftl, Kuwait. Ho. i07. Oateu 7th Fworuary 19^8. Your telegram dated &gt;ra Feoruary. Onrael dorps from nusaiyah fouiid VO Kuwait sheep with ’Iraq ««Asnal m tribe. Propose to oraer them to oe handed over to Mutl tq aou uihuhalll. *«o. 69 - 0 . Political A c ency, Kuwait. oth February 19*3. To The Secretary to the Hon'ole the Political Hesident in the Perelan Gulf, B U S H I R E. A copy of the above telegram is forwarded herewith for information with reference to my telegram ho.4J5 of Jrd last. Major, Political As«A«, Kuwait. Letter No.68 dated 8th Feoruary 19^3 from tne P.A.,Kuwait,to h.S. Snaiicn Ahmad al-Jablr a«-Subah, G.I.E., Ruler of Kuwait, A.C. ± have the honour to inform Your Excellency that I have receiv-d a telegram from the Administrative Inspector,Nasir-l- yah,on the subject of the sheep referred to in your letter dated the 10th Sha'bun 1346, in which he says that men of the camel corps from Busaiyah founfl 270 Kuwait sheep with the Iraq Mishalah tribe, and that it is proposed to order them to be handed over to wutlaq Abu Dh hair. U.E. * 5 iTelegram Proa To 1*06 Dated (C). Resident, Bushire. Political 9 Kuwait* 1 19. 7th February I 92 w». rour telegram No. 65 . Thanks from the Shai*h of Kuwait an* rnnuests from him should be through me only unless the latter are urgent.D/0 xlo 0 .S .4 as Sief, S' i^asran. Otn February 192Q. xnaniL ^ou for tne wire letting me A.now that .you are bacji from ijuanire. mere are one or two tnings tnat I would li^e to aak ^our opinion about and also I am in searon of inform- -ation for Air Headquarters tnat can now be nardly obtained except in nuwait so if it is convenient I propose coming down for tne day only on mursday. ^s this letter will not get to you much before tnen 1 will send you a wire as well. me suc^ect of tne information required b^ Bagndad for tne columns is snovn in tne extract of s/l Buss’s letter to me wnicn i enclose. Zooair and aistrict nave been searcned yesterday and toaay witnout producing anyone wno really mows tne place. «ould it be possiile for you to nave someone looxed out in ^uwait so tnat wnen 1 turn up we coula nave avaij.aLle. 1 am afraid you may be quite busy enougn witnout tms to arrange and nope you don’t mind doing so. 7^■le are very short of information oil the p;eograol 9 * 0 ff &amp; of tha rectangle between 26 and 28 North and 45 and 46 East. Odn you get anything which would be useful if aircraft have to operate down there? is the edge of the Dahana well-defined? *re there easily-recognised tracks crossing it in the stripy area N.E. of irtawiya? ind if so what tracks? where do they start on the N.E. edge and where do they go to? Can you get a reliable description of ^ttawiya itself to check a rough plan that we hav- already got? Philby’s book is uite a lot? of help but there is much that we want which he does not tell us,and there is absolutely nothing in the Gazetteer of Arabia.(15962) Wt. 14094/11030 20,000 pds. 11/24 Harrow (E.1215). R.A.F. Form 818. MESSAGE FORM. •3fThe Signal Department Is nspoosible that these details are transposed to the appropriate portion of the message form and that all possibility of comprorrisln ^sUngnishinf signals, etc., by omitting to remove their signUicatiou from the address, etc., is avoided. Before delivery of the message these details are to l ■ insetted in P L. Charge. Call.: IN OUT Series No. Service Instructions. Indication of Priority. Words. Time handed in Special Instructions. TO* FROM* No. of Qroups In text. Serial No. of Telegram For Postage Stamps To be affixed by the Sender, and Date Stamp. In Out System Reader Sender Receipt Despatch Time of (Write horizontally.) juj. il3UG.2lL ajSEH &amp; ■Ili-Hii- ....k?A^..UiLLA.XEii. - 0 M. Uxtd Hi 2? auito lj7o £i?3J 4 M3J 2.0 2 I!.AJ!U.Ec5,ja AiJa jUSLIEj? i 1 *i oHHii Afi'Aitii 2ir iir2i .02 AaA CREW uS' i A ItJAxkF'H uUl ituk uroiii? in .....BY aa KHviiiG nua - 3 x.k- 1’ u 2tu.n'2 .i kILLlM. ULHI5S.I H H jS UK i!C Bit »3ttT Xll2(i us.-3 31/1 ifUv.W.L. it! CTrJT o.iLi^rf jl/ 1 XJlifO PKC^^OH Y.3 JS.3ftQ.fc M. itW 213 aa-i iiUo^L u Uv. KEJJ {0 illiliA ’aw .i.( E .s).W. U 4J! k.iEUxt A/IA o Up a. !l xam, T k . ,1 • \ Degree of Priority* This message must be sent {or S iN^OYPHERt} ant * mayj be sent by W/T. t If the message is not to be transmitted by W/T over any portion of its route either in P/L or cypher the originator will insert ' NOT ” in the blank space. t Strike out words inapplicable. Originator’s Special Instructions and Signature.* TIME OF ORIGIN. T.O.R.Telegram (C). 6S Prom To No. Dated Political, Kuwait. Resident, Bushire; repeated Nasiriyah. . 73. 9 th February to Baghdad, Basrah and My telegram No. 66 . Mutari seoGled in Kuwait who lias just re^uraet froia /isit to the tribe reports that practically all tribal leaders are with Dawlsh as dufalyah and Artawiyali. The tribe is very short of ammunition eTelegram (P). Proa Political, Kuwait, To Aviation, Baghdad; repeated to Bushlre, No. 75. Dated ICth February 1928* Your telegram No, 236, De Gaury and I have discussed the question of co-operation, and agree that Verey lights would be of use for communicating between aircraft and Kuwait forces. The latter have no distinctive dress, but the Shaikh is prepared to adopt a distinguishing badge which we will recommend. Telegram (P). Prom Political, Kuwait, To Resident, Bushire, No. 76. Dated 10th February 1928. My telegram No.75. As the suggestion for their use emanated from them,would it be possible to ask the R.A.P. for three or four Verey light pistols and the necessary ammunition for the use of Kuwait.Telegram (C) Prom Polltiwal, Kuwait, To Resident, Bushire. No, 79 Dated 10th February 1928 - * - Shaikh of Kuwait asks me if it would be possible for him to purchase from Government two machine guns and three Lewis guns for use against Ikhwan raiders. He proposes to mount them in armoured cars ( i.e. cars which he is going to have roughly armoured), and xasl also to use them for the defence of Kuwait itself if it should be attacked. He particually fancies Lewis guns because of their simplicity and portability. I hope it will be possible to assist him in the matter. Blegram (C). From Political, Kuwait. To Resident, Bushire. No. 80 Dated 10th February 1928. My immediately preceding tsi telegram. The shaikh has also asked my advice about what sort of cars to get to make into armoured cars. I told him about our recent conversation sm on the subject, but, while aggreelng about getting cars armoured locally, he thinks he would prefer something better than Dodge cars. I think he is certainly right if he doesn't mind spending the money, and what he really wants are light lorries with either caterpillars ar six wheels, and in any case not pnewmatic rubber tyres. It requires considerable tecnical knowledge to advise him as to the relative merits of different makes of vehicles, and this I naturally do not possess. As there was time to do so, I have written by this air mail to the Royal Automobile Club, to which I Delong, describing the country and asking what kind of vehicle they recommend for rough cross-country work in it. I suggest that you might be able to obtain the expert advice of the War Office, who have carried out most exhaustive tests(e* No. 74-3. 9th February 1928 . Dear Sir, Hie Excellency the Shaikh of Kuwait is mich troubled by raiders froa outside his territory carrying, off his sheep and caaels, and, as he has recently employed cars x ostiy Fords) for sending out pursuit parties with very aaraed success, he has conceived the idea of ealntaining two.or three arwoured cars specially for the purpose, his idea is to iaport the cars - or acre correctly lorries - and have then roughly armoured hiaself, as being more eco- uoaical than having regular araoured oars built. He has asked ey advice as to the type of car or lorry uesfc suited to his purpose, and, as this reoulres ajore technical knowledge than I possess, I ae writing to ask if you will be so good as to assist ise in the aatter. The oars are required for extremely rough use in a country where there are no roads. Although the desert is comparatively flat and normally has a hard and quite surface, they must be able to negotiate occasional sandy watercourses, some of which are beyond the capacity of an ordinary car. Again, there are tracts of country in which there is a profusion of camel-thorn bushes, which aaxe I motoring somewhat difficult, as the sand has a tendency to orift round their roots and form hummocks, and for this reason a high clearance is absolutely essential , uia ideK^ is to have &amp; machine gun and four or five men in each car, so, even with a comparatively small amount of armour, the load will be heavy, and something with a fairly high horse power would seem to be indicated. Perhaps it might be as 11 well for it to have either six wheels or a light cater pillar, and in any case, I think, not pneumatic tires. Great speed is not essential, and ability to ’get there* is much more im ortant. He does not want to pay an outside Yours faithfully. Major, Political Agent, Kuwait.Tele&amp;ra.n (P) &amp; From Resident, Bushire. To Political, Kuwait. No 131 Dated 9th February 1928 The following i 3 a paraphrase of Colonial Office telegram No, 6?o Begins, In order to make possible future air action as effective as possible the Air Ministry desire permission to bomb Ikhwan raiders in Kuwait territory should the necessity arise. Please therefore approach the Shaikh of Kuwait with a request for his general concurrence in such a course, but add that his specific concurrence will be sought on each occasion before action is taken if time allows, though it is improbable that there will be time for this if immediate action is necessary* Xnctaii Ends* Please take action accordingly and wire me result* Letter No*82 dated the 11th February 1928 from P.A., Kuwait, to H,E, Shaikh Ahmad al-Jabir as-Subah, 0*1,E*, Rulor of Kuwait. After compliments* I have the honour to inform Your Excellency that in order to make possible future air action against Ikhwan raiders as effective as possible,the British Air Ministry desire permission to bomb such raiders in Kuwait territory should the necessity arise. I have accordingly been instructed to approach Your Eacel- /your lenoy with the request for/general concurrence In this course* I am to add that if time allows your specific concurrence will be sought on each occasion before action is taken, though there may not always be time for this if immediate action is necessary Usual ending*Telegram (0) 1%- From Political, Kuwait. To Resident, 3A3hi re;repeated to No. 83. Dated 11th February 1928. Naslrlyaho Naflsi’c messenger left Riyadh ^Ist January and arrived here on the 10th February; also Shal&amp;h of Kuwait’s messengers from there, travelling via 'Uwainah (7th Fejnary), arrived here to-day Saturday the 11th February. They report Ibn Sa’ud still at Riyadh and Dawiah at \rtawiyah with his animals at Sufaiyah No meeting has taken place and no reconciliation heon mado. On the contrary Ibn Sa’ud is very angry with DawisVu ^ahd bln Jiluwi is still at ’Uwainah with a large force. Ibn Musa 5 ad also with a considerable force Is on the borders of Qaslnie Both leaders are in constant communication with each other and with Ibn Sa’ud. -jTelegram (P). From Aviation, Baghdad. To Political, Kuwait. No. Z 54. Dated 11th February 1928. Following from Dent. Personal. How would you view the idea of a Special Service Officer being temporarily stationed in Kuwait? I presume you have plenty of other work besides Intelligence, but do not fcnow whether this would help or hinder you. Even if you approve, I presume we should have to ask the Resident and London first. Please let me have your advice by wire. We much appreciate your valuable telegrams and co-operation. Telegram (P). From More, Kuwait. To Aviation, Baghdad. No. 84. Dated 12th February 1928. Following for Colonel Dent. Personal. Your telegram No. Z 54. I certainly have no objection if the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf has none, I assume of course that you will send a tactful man who will not dabble in politica and will be guided by my advice vis-a-vis the Local Government, and am perfectly confident that you will. I think I get hold of most information of any value that comes into Kuwait in the ordinary course of events - though I dare say an all-time man might occasionally do so quicker. Stilly I employ no secret service agents and in my Job I think it would be undesirable that I should, and for this reason alone it ml^ht be well worth while havin R a Special Service Officer in Kuwait. I suggest that, if one does come, he normally wear mufti.Telegram (P) 8 From Political, Kuwait cS To Resident, Bushire No 11 85 Dated 12th February 1928. Your telegram No. 121. I have approached the Shaikh of Kuwait in accordance with your instructions, and he replies that he has no objection whatever to any Ikhwan raiders who enter the frontiers of Kuwait being attacked by aircraft.Telegram Prom To («). Political, Kuwait. Resident, Buahire; repd, No, cz3&gt; Baghdad,Basrah and Nasitiyah. Dated 13th February 1928, My telegram No.83. Information believed to be reliable Just received that Dawish has again moved to Safah. It is said he intends sending the Shaikh of Kuwait a demand to replenish supplies here and also that he is planning another raid to the north.Telegram (C). From Resident, Bushlre* To Political, Kuwait. No. 142, Dated 13th February 1928, Your letter dated 8th February No,69-S. Have you taken the necessary action on Administrative Inspector’s No.107? Telegram (C). From Political, Kuwait. To Resident P Budhire. ^o. 87. Dated 14th February 1928, Your telegram No.142. I have taken all necessary action. Telegram (C). From Political, Kuwait. To Resident, Bushire. No. EB 88 Dated 14th February 1928. Your telegram No.119. I have received no reply as yet to the Shaikh’r&gt; request for occasional air reconnaissances conveyed in my telegram No. 65 of 6th February.Telegram (en clair)» From Aviation, Baghdad, To Political, Kuwait. No, A/336. Dated Hth February 1928. Following addressed Akforce, repeated for information. Begins. Reference your AK/0/20 of 12th February. Before returns Hinaldi he is to go with special to visit More, Kuwait, and definitely fix simple code for co-operation with aircraft. He should also give some instruction in armed car tactics. Peck can stay Kuwait one week if necessary but Special not more than two days. Plain clothes to be worn. Ends.Telegram (C) * . •?&gt;) Prom / Political, Kuwait. T ^&gt; Resident, Bushire; repeated to Baghdad, Basrah and Nasiriyah. No. 89 Dated 14th February 1928 My telegram No. 86. Confirmation received that Dawish is either at or on his way to Safah. Telegram (P) Prom Political, Kuwait. 5o Resident, Bushire; repeated to Baghdad. No 90 Dated 14th February 1928. My immediately preceeding telegram,. The Shaikh of 8 Kuwait tells me that Dawish has sent him a verbal message to the effect?that he has no ill-will against Kuwait and does not want to quarrel with it, but demanding ppr*mi s «io^ to buy supoiies nere. The messanger was a Kuwait born Mutairi, and the Shaikh took advantage of this fact to gain time, and sent back word that he could not treat verablly with him through a subject of his own, but that if Dawish were to send a responsible pleni potentiary or write to him, he would consider the question. The Shaikh is very nervous that a raid against Kuwait may be the kauDkatsxssxMlkxatxkhlui immediate result of this. Telegram (P) % Prom Political, Kuwait. To Resident, Bushire. No. 91 Dated 14th February 1928. My telegrams No.90 and No.88® Shaixh Ahmad has repeated his request that aeroplanes may reconnoitre over his territory.TELEGRAM (C), From Special, Basrah# To Political, Kuwait, No* 256. Dated 15th February 1928* Pecic and I arrive about midday 16th February. Very grateful if you would arrange accommodation for us where available* Telegram (G). From Political, Kuwait. To Speclax, Basrah. No. 92 . Dated 15th February 19*b. Your telegram No. xfc 256 . I will make the best arrangement 1 can but please bring your own bedding as I have other guest.ITelegram (C)« From Special,Basrah. £? To No. Dated Political, Kuwait; repeated to Shu*aibah. ffx/ fiZCEj Kii. 253 /n ' - ' 15th fsic) February 1923. Air Headquarters asked me to inform you that in case of urgent message they should be addressed Akforce. Reiegram (C). From Highcoma, Baghdad. To Resident, Bushire; repeated to Kuwait. No. ?4. Dated 15th February 1928 . ...AJl tf-A^LSr Messages containing Frontier news may in future be telegraphed by Political Agent, Kuwait, to Special, Nasiriyah, who is being instructed to distribute them to all concerned. Urgent messages should be sent to all stations as hitherto.Telefcram (P) From Resident, Bushire No To Politioai, Kuwait, 159. Dated Your telegrams Noo, 9^ &amp; 91* Ploase telegraph after consulting ShaiJth Ahmad the numbers that may be expected if the raiders do attack, and whether he is afraid they will attack Kuwait itself. Will aeroplanes be sufficient assistance in your opinion or would you like H.M.S. Emerald to be called to Kuwait as a precautionary measureTelegram (c) From Political, Kuwait c To Resident, Bushlre; repeated to BaghdiA, Basrah and No Nasiriyah 94 Dated 15th February 1920* She Shailch of Kuwait now informs me that he has received reliable information that Fahd bin-Jiluwi 9 s force has been disbanded by order of Ibn Sa^ud, particularly in view of Danish's recent action. Telegram (P) From Political, Kuwait. To Resident, Bushire. No. 95 Dated 15th February 1928 . Your telegram No. 159 . Please see my immediately pre ceding telegram. Shailch Ahmad had heard this a few days ago, but had not told me. Now he is satisfied that it is true and this is what makes him so nervous, as also does the fact that he has heard nothing further about restitution of plunder from Ibn Sa'ud, as he had expected to do. Up to now he has always been most emphatic in maintaining that Dawish was acting against Xbn Sa’ud^ wishes. Now he does not know what to think. He points out, however, that, if they have come to an understanding, it is stnange that Dawish should have sent him the message he did. He certainly appears to expect an attack, probably on the coastal villages or on Jahrah, but possibly on Kuwait itself. The situation is so obscure that it Is Impossible to es timate the number of possible raiders. In view of Shaikh Ahmad's fears and the possibility that the Mutair may not be the only people Involved, I certainly should feel happier with a ship here.Telegram (^). Prom Admintor, Naslrlyah. To Political, Kuwait. No. 154. Qated 16 th February 1928 Thirty four more Kuwait sheep at Buaaiyah ready to be handed over. Letter No. 9 ? of 16 th February 1928 from P.A., Kuwait, to H„E, Shaikh Ahmad al-Jabir as-Subah, C.I fl E., Ruler of Kuwait. After compliments. I have the honour to inform Your Excellency that I have received a telegram from the Administrative Inspector, Naslriyah, to say that thirty four more Kuwait sheep are at Baswah ready to be handed over. If therefore Your Excellency will detail someone to take them over, and will let me know his name, I will inform the Administrative Inspector accord ingly. Usual ending. .Telegram (P) Prom Resident, Bushire Political, Kuwait,&lt;&amp; Highcoma, Baghdad, To No 170 Dated 16th February 1928, H e M,S. Emerald has left Hinjam at economic speed of thirteen knots for Kuwait, I will telegraph for her to increase speed should the situation necessitate it. Telegram (G), Prom Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, Hinjam Radio, To Political, Kuwait. Dated 16th February 1928, Expeot to arrive at Kuwait at 1^00 hours local time to-morrow Friday. Iit 0£ J p r /Telegram (G). From Political, Kuwait. To Special, Naslriyah. No* 98 * Dated l?th February Have you any information confirming the reports that Dawlsh ia at Safah? Telegram (C). From Political, Kuwait* To Resident, Bushire; repeated Special, Nasiriyah* No. 99* Dated 17th February 1928* No further developements and no further news. Telegram (en clair). From Special, Nasiriyafc. OCI l J T •i Ho. sir To Political, Kuwait* No. 1/65. Dated 17th February 1928. Your 93 17/2 None* Expect news shortly* Police, Busaiyah, report Mashari, Musaiyis raiding on 13/2. Direction unknown* Telegram (0). From Political, Kuwait. To Resident, Bushire* No. ICO* Dated 17th February 1928. My 99* Following from Special, Nasiriyah, Begins. a olice,Busaiya report Maahari Muaaiyia raiding 13th February. Direction un known. Letter No.lCI of 17-2-26 to H„E. Shalih Ah»ad, etc, A “°’ I hare the honour to Inform Y.E. that I hare received a telegram from the S.S,0,.Nasirtyah, to the effect that henae received no confirmation of the report that Dawlsh is at Safah r but he hopes to be able to send me news shortly. , He has received a report from Baswah post that Mashari alvMusalyis went raiding on the 21st inst., but he does not know in what direction® U.E*Telegram (P) Prom Hlghcoma, Bagdad. To Resident, Bushlre; repeated to Kuwait. No. 31 S Dated 17th February 1928. Do you see any objection to Special Service Officer being posted to Kuwait as a temporary measure? He would be al ways guided by the Political Agent’s advice and would normally wear mufti. The Political Agenti wires have been extremely helpful, but this might womewhat increase the amount of in formation from Riyadh and Artawiyah and speed up its receipt. Telegram (P) From Political, Kuwait. To Bushire. No. 103 Dated 18th February 1928. I would welcome the proposal conrained in High Commissioner Baghdad's telegram No. 31 S.PSHSOrtAL &amp; JOWFIDli-JTXAL. D.O. Ho. 103-3. 13th February 1923. X tot Hlthooma's vfire 2^o.3l-S about an S.S.O. for here addressed to Uie Resident and repeated to me last an^ I have wired to the Resident this Jiorn- ing, that so far as I aai concehnei I would welcome the proposal. I hope therefore that xt will throufh all riftht. ^ I hope you will not think that I aa interfer ing unduly if I say that I hope the man you select will not be Kenny Levee*. I have really nothin^ whatever a^alnet the chap, and 1 dare say he is very efficient - he certainly talks Arabic well, but I someway feel that he and I would pull pull together so well as miftht be desired. The situation is aaraiin&amp;ly obscure these days. Isn’t it? I simply cannot understand Ibn Sa'ud’s action over Fahd bln Jiluwi’s orowd. The Shaikh has oeen very Jumpy since fawlsh's demand for muscCpalah . and seems to quite expect an attack. Anyway they are not likely to bother the town itself now, as the 'Emerald' is here. As a matter of fact, 1 never thought there w is any feir of that myself, but the Shaikh thought it not impossible. Colonel W. Dent, C.B.S., D.3.G., Air Headquarters, Baghdad.PROPOSED TELEGRAM PROM S.N.O. Persian Gulf. TO Commander-in-Chief, East Indies. ! Sheikh of Kuwait had become seriously alarmed at the possibility og an attack on the town by raiding tribesmen. Political Resident asked Political Agent here whether the presence of a man-of-war was desired. This was at first considered unnecessary'- but subsequently a ship was asked for. Situation on arrival was normal and Political Agent assures me that my presence here has greatly restored the Sheikhas confidence. Political Agent also states that he considers any attack unlikely while a man-of-war is here. Preparations have been made to land guards and to assist in the defence of the town but Political Agent considers that no action is r required now.Telegram (P) From Aviation, Baghdad. To folitloal, Kuwait. No. 2 66 Dated 17th February IS28 ' &gt; j&amp;±ilSr % i-' Following is for Peck. mf r reference to the Shaikh* request for the maintenance of reconnalear.ee. Piea 8e texegraph your views regarding the minimum air reconnaissance. that are required and what route they should follow. Doe. the 3iiaii h find car or came! patrols and if so where are they posted atta 0Uld thelr lnf0rMt l° n regarding a raid be transmitted to Shaibah rapidly. Ends. Telegram vP) From Political, Kuwait To Aviation, Baghdad.* repeated to Resident, Bushire. No. 109 Dated I6th February 1928. Your telegram No. 2 66. Following from Peck. Begins: Reconnaissances are required as a protection against surprize attack and for moral support. I suggest that one flight and one section of cars should operate from Kuwait, making daily afternoon reconnaissances of a seventy mile radiud. The Political Agent &amp;ggx*£* agrees. A force basea on Kuwait coula be supplied by sea or by good road. If this be not approved I suggest two reconnaissances to Safan weekly using Kuwait as an advanced landing ground if need be. Two camel and horse patrols operating, one fifteen miles north west of Jahrah and tr e other forty miles south west of Kuwait, also friendly tribes at Burqan and to the east of it. Information would take abut eight hours to reach Shaibah by land line, but H.M.S.Emerald is temporarily at Kuwait and ship 1 ® wireless is available during her stay.Telegram (C) From Political, Kuwait To Resident, Bushire' repeated Baghdad and Special Naslrlyah. No. 107 -- Dated 18th February Immediate. The Shaikh of Kuwait has received reliable information that Dawish arrived at Ma T raJ as-Sauban, 26 miles east of Safah. He thinks Lhat this Indicates that he intends raiding Kuwait. r Telegram (P). From Political, Kuwait. To Resident, Bushire* No. in. Dated '16th February 1928. My telegram No. 90. Shaikh of Kuwait asks whether there would be any objection to his replying to Dawish if he make any subsequent demand for permission to trade with Kuwait t^at ne has no wish to quarreu with Dawish at ally but that it Is impossible for him to agree to his request because we would not let him. I told him I was sure there could not be any objeotiorI /*s % Telegram (C). From Political, Kuwait* To Resident, Bushire P No. 112. Dated 18 th February 1928. My telegram No. 80. Squadron Leader Peck af the Armoured Gars, who has come to arrange a code of signals between the Kuwait forces and Aircraft, is of opinion that locally armoured lorries or cars would be quite useless. Any steel plates available in this part of the world would need to be at least half a n inch thick, and even enough to protect personnel without the engine would be so heavy as to mrlc? t*« the car quit# immobile. He has seen it tried on a powerful Grossley tender and it was a dismal failure. He says it the Shaikh wants armoured cars at all he should get proper ones, or better still whippet tanks which would be ideal. Would the Shaikh be allowed to buy latter? If so would it be possible to find out the price? He does not seem to mind paying a big price 0 I should be glad fcfiapouB to know ilxy for his information if you can help him in the matter, and also regarding the machine guns and Lewis guns.Telegram From To No. Dated Political, Kuwait. Resident, Bushirej repeated to Special, Nasiriyah. 113 I8fch February IJyfiS. My telegram No. 107* No further information this evening Saturday. Ihe Shaikh of Kuwait says Dawlsh's camp should be conspicuous object for aeroplanes as he uses white tents. Telegram (C) From Resident, Bushlre. To Political, Kuwait. ' No. 185 Dated 18th February 1928 Immediate. Your No. 107. Do you mean Kuwait or Kuwait territory? Please keep me exactly informed of your anticipa tion of events so that I can ask Colonial Office to what extent they are prepared that we should assist if necessary that we should do so. Telegram (C) FromP iolitical, jvuwait. To Resident, Bushire. No. 114 Dated 10th February 1928 Yaxje Immediate. Your No. 185* ^lease see my No.95» Attack anticipated would probably be on Kuwait territory, but possibly on Kuwait town itself. Any assistance required will probably be required very soon.Telegram (c) . From To No. Dated Sail! Resident, Bushireo PoliLicai, Kuwait. 166 18th February 1&gt;28 If possibility of requiring assistance from”Eineiald'let me know what you would propose. Telegam (C) From Political, Kuwait. To Resident, Bush!re. ITo. Ub Dated 1?th February Your No. 186 . If I consider the lives and property of British subjects endangered by an attack on Kuwait town I shal- as-t Senior Naval Officer in the ^ersuan Gulf to ta*e sucii steps as may be necessary for their protection.Tele&amp;raru (P) From Aviation, Baghdad. To Political, Kuwait# No. 2 73 Da tec tSLh February lil&amp;tt 1928 ^|||5£n^3^ One Flight of No.84 Squadrad and one Section of Armoured Cars will be sent to Kuwait as soon as possible# They will be commanded by Squadron Leader Pecic and will act under the general Hupervision of Akforce# They will attack raiders if found# Shaibah will make immediate bfcpply arrangements# If necessary victorias will be supplied by Akforoe to assist# Air Headquarters will issue orders regarding further supply arrangements. No. II 6 -S. Political Agency, Kuwait. 19 th February 1928. To Squadron Leader A. H, Peck, D.S.O., M#C, A copy of the above telegram is sent herewith for information# Major, Political Agant, Kuwait# Telegram (P) From Political, Kuwait To Resident, Bushire. No. 118 Dated I9th February 1928 My No. 1Q9» Telegram No.Z 73 of 18th February from Aviation Baghdad. Begins. x x x x Ends. This Is the very thing the Shaikh has been longing for, and should ptt an end to the danger of the town being attacked* ’-t to\ /&amp;!&gt; H.M.S.'Smerald° » at Kuwait. 19th February 1928. Dear More* For your consideration arising out of Political Resident’s message today - The clear cut issue to me is the protection of British liyes and property. This can he effected in one of three ways (A) By preventing raiders entering the town at all. (B) By holding the Residency as a fortress - all British subjects to be concentrated there• (C) By evacuation. (A) is by far the most effective* but entails the use of ship’s guns. (B) entirely ignores the presence of other white people* i.e.* the Americans, and is by no means certain. '— - » (C) Extremely bad moral effect and ignores the property. (A) must therefore be adopted# Consular and American Mission guard being also provided to guard ^ against sympathetic revolt inside the walls. What is not clear cut is the possibility of the Sheikh claiming British protection. If he does that are we to give him full support# in other words# are v/e to fight his war for him ? As far as I understand from the papers I have got he jjj entitled to ask for protection* but I should prefer that to be settled definitely, which should be done by the Political Resident or higher authority y ^^^* Jtr^ &amp;U Yours sincerely, His Britabnic Majesty’s Political Agent# KuwaitKUWAIT In the event of a dangerous situation arising from the probability of a serious attack by Akhwan tribesmen on the town of Kuwait* the following steps will be taken (A) to ensure the protection of British and American subjects* i»e«* Internal Security* and (B) to assist in driving off the attacks of the tribesmen* i*e«* Defence of the 7/alls. The question of evacuation v/ill be dealt with separately• (A) IKTERIIAI SECURITY. At the British Residency. A guard of two sections R.l£* Seargeant in charge. At the Mission Hospital. A guard of two sections of Seamen. Lieutenant in command. (B) DEEEIICE OE THE 7/ALLS . The shir will be anchored and will enfilade the Eastern arm of the Wall. Lewis Gun Sections will be stationed on the three gate towers. Captain R.M. in command. Cutter with machine gun to be anchored to enfilade the short North-Western arm of the Wall. Warrant Officer st Chief Petty Officer in charge. Remainder of the Seamen and Marine platoons (rifle sections]* Jkm* 4 six-inch guns* crews* will be landed and remain in a central position in rear of the Lewis Gun Sections - ready to reinforce by manning the Wall and supporting with rifle fire. The Commander will be in command of all men landed. COMMUNICATIONS. Two Signal ratings at the Residency. Short distance W/F Set in the close vicinity of the Central Gate. Intercommunication between units 'by Signal rating. MEDICAL ARRANGEMENTS. Surgeon Lieutenant and one Sick Berth rating at the Residency. Stretcher bearers and first aid party with the platoons. SUPPLY. Paymaster Lieutenant and three Supply ratings to establish a ration supply station at the Residency. All units to have water bottles filled and to draw water and rations from the supply station as required.Personal anfl Jonfldentlal«_ D.O. No. H9-S. (o^ jtsL. &amp; \*jth February 1928. In reply to your deal-official letter of to-day’» date, I enclose herewith a copy of five tele- »,rasia which have pr.Bsed between the Resident and my self on the subject of the possibility of my aakine you for assistance aftalnst raiders attacking Kuwait (viz. my numbers 1^7, H4 and 1 *5» his and From my telegram No.ilb you will see what the conditions are under which I would ask you for assistance I entirely a^ree with you that the most effect ive method of protecting British lives and property is to prevent the raiders fron entering the town at all, and this seems to me to £ive the ShaiKh any protection he can require in the event of such an attack. From the Resident’s telegram* fto.165 I assume that he has asked the Colonial Office to what extent we are to help the Shaikh, but until I hear I shall confine myself to the above. Captain H. G. C. Franklin, R.N# Senior Naval Officer,Persian Gulf, H.M.3. !Caerald,at Kuwait. \Telegram (P) FVom Resident, Bushire. To Colonial Office; repeated to Delhi, Kuwait. lot* Baghdad and No. 191 (28 to CoO.) Dated 19th February 1928. I have agreed as a temporary measure that aeroplanes and armoured cars from lin* ‘Iraq form a base at Kuwait* in view of the reported danger Ihala thefce. I Mjucx am of opinion^ however,that the pfcinclpie should be laid down that this Is a special case, that political necessities exist, and that the main issue is to compel Ibn Sa’ud to contrl his own frontier which he has shown he can take measures to do. We have only to look at history to see that, if he does not do this we shall have a frontier which is permanently unsettled, or we shall be forced to aquire it ourselves. If we want him to assume this responsibility, the less we do the better once we have established the safety of Kuwait.Telegram (0) Prom Resident, Bushire* To Political, Kuwait. No. I9i Dated 19th February 1928 Your No. 118. I pres-ime Shaikh upon to pay expence. Teieiti’am (0) Prom Political, Kuwait. To Resident, Bushire. No. 121 Dated 19t»h February 1928 Your No. 118. No such suggestion has been made. Telesram (C) From Resident, Bushire. To Political, Kuwait. No. 193 Dated 19th February • Imadiate. Your No. 115« Yes. Now that aviation forces are arriving no other action is necessary.Telegram (en clear) Prom Akforce, Ur Junction To Political, Kuwait. No. A/226 19/2 Dated 1&gt;th February 1928. lot 5 To Mutair raiders 1000 strong reported by aircraft ten miles from Jarishan at 10.20 $.m.t. today. Air attack in progress. Suggest Kuwait car force endeavour cooperate with aircraft by interception of raiders on return journey. }CC raiders and 20 white tents located 0820 G.m 0 t 0 ten miles north point marked al-Riqai. This probably base from tfhich r»ld started. Kuwait forces should display white *trlp to airceaft and cars. Telegram ifii (en clear) Prom Political, Kuwait. To ixlcfcrce, Ur Junction No. 120 Dated 19th February 1928 Your A/226. Shaikh regrets he is unable to send any cars. Telegram (C) From Political, Kuwait. To Resident, Bushire. No. 122 Dated 19th Feoruary 1*28 YMMtt Telegram No.A 226 of 19 th February from Akforce, Ur Junction. Begins, x x x x x Ends. I replied in my telegram No.120. Begins x x Ends. Jarishan is on the ^raq side of the Batin 58 miles south west of Basrah and on some maps Is spelt Djarisha.Telegram (P) Prom Resident, Bushire. To Aviation, Baghdad; repeat© No. 190 Dated • 19th February 19^8 Your 2 72. I presume you have instructed your Officer Commanding not to take action without the Political Agent's consent, and to act in conformity with his views. » -• * • «^ &gt; Telegram (P) Prom To No. Dat*3d (tr/S. ( N /Cx RECEIPT v/ /..c^ '■&gt; \ Resident, Bushire. Political, Kuwait. 188 19th February 1928 Demi-Official. Please make it clear to the R.A.P. Commander at Kuwait that I do not wmt machines to cross the frontier unless in actual fight without orders from Colonial Office? and the approval of the Government of India, and that no action should be taken without political consent. I expect you to see that our political control of the situation Is maintained and keep me fully informed. Please do not forget that what Shaikh Ahmad may be longing for may not suit our books or the longer view of politics for either him or us. Telegram (P) Frwtt Political, Kuwait, To Resident, Bushire. No. 120 Dated 19th February 1928 Demi- Official. Your No. 188. I have every intention of maintaining our political control and you can rest assured that I am not out for unneeessary bombing® In my opimion our first object should be to safeguard British lives and property,and our second to assist Shaikh Ahmad againstan unprovoked attack. I further presume that, when not contrary to the interests of Kuwait, it is desireable to further our general British policy regarding the Mutair. The first two objects can best be served by obtaining the earliest possible Information of any attack which may be contemplated. With this object in view I most strongly recommend that you endeavour to obtain immediate sanction for aeroplanes to cross the frontier, which at its nearest point is only 42 miles distant. Otherwise they will be of • * an comparatively little value against such/exceptionally mobile foe. furthermore, I would point out that aeroplanes from Iraq and the ftUQtk Neutral Zone habitually do cross the frontier, and that consequently it is in the best interests of the Shaikh of Kuwait that they should do so from here too, so that it will appear that they are not specially helping him out our part of of our xxitBxxftk general plan. I presume that in any case there is no objection to their reconnoltering over the territory, common to Kuwait and Najd. I will keep you fully informed of everything./ Personal and Confidential. /oV Qio) H.M.S.'Emerald' 9 at Kuwait. 19th February 1928. Dear 2Iore&gt; Thank you for your letter. I shall be much obliged if you will hasten the Political Resident on the question of the protection of the Sheikh^ property. My proposed line of action is - as you say - tantamount to protection of the Sheikh, and we shall feel far clearer if that is an approved measure. If you do not wish to do so I will tackle the Political Resident rpyself. Sorry to bother you with this at the end of a busy day. Yours sincerely. KuwaitPersonal St Confldenolul. D.O. No. 123-S. I9t.h February 1926. I am sorry you have had the bother of sending, off again. I received the following telegram from the Resident (No.193 of to-day^ date) late this evening, wnich I thin* settles the question. 'Your telegram No.U3. Yes. Now that Aviation forces are arriving no other action la necessary”• Captain H. 0. C. Franklin, R.N., S.N.O., P.G., H.M.S. Emerald. \(?) Froa Political, Kuwait, To Resident, Buahlre, No, 125 Dated 20th February 1928, My telegram No, 120, I have Just had time to reaa tne which arrived the day before yesterday, and seen your telagram No, t7 of Hth Pebr uary to the Colonial Office (which was notm repeated to me at the time), X venture to repeat that I wa* ooneiderlns the safety of Kuwait (which I presume it is our duty to help seelns that it is under our protection) and still more the safety of -v British subjects in Kuwait. The best method of securins this is to obtain the earliest possible warning of an intended attack, and in view of the extreme mobility of the Ilchwan this cannot be done effectively if reconnaissances be limited to Kuwait territory. It seems to me that the objective of yesterday's raid must have been Zubalr, and this can only mean that the Ilchwan are desperate for supplies,. and, • as it has failed it seems likely that they will try this side next unless they have been too heavily punished in the present Instance, \ mmm Telegram (?) From Resident, Bushire. To Kuwait, and repeated to Baghdad for Aviation. No. 195 Dated 19th February 1928. X did not receive telegram No. Z 66 referred to by you. I would suggest that a daily reconnaissance of a 60 mila radius would meet the ease and would keep practically with in the frontiers of Kuwait. Otherwise I agree. fYREG . \ r ( o f No //O-r~\ vy Letter No.126 of 20 - 2-28 from the P.A., Kuwait, to H.E. Shallth Ahmad al-Jablr as-Subah, C.I.E.,Ruler of Kuwait A.C. I have the honour to Inform Y.E. that I have heard that the raiders this morning were Just t o the south east of Riqa'l and were making off to the south east. This for Your Excellency's Information. U.E.* ^ r Letter No.12? of 20-2-28 from the P.A., Kuwait, to H.E. Shaikh Ahmad al-Jabir aa-Subah, C.I.E., Ruler of Kwt. A.O. I have the honour to forward herewith a schedule of signals which the Gonnandant of Armoured Gars thinks a can usefully be employed between Your Excellency's forces and the aeroplanes. U.EGROUND SIGNALS PROM KUWAIT FORCES TO AEROPLANES We are Kuwaitis. The tents or animals in the direction of the arrow are hostile. The tents or axxeiii animals in the direction of the arrow are friendly. Enemy located in the direction of the arrow. We have been attacked. We want ammunition. We want water. We are proceeding in the direction of the arrow. We are returning to the base. We cannot proceed further owing to ground. We are camping here. We want petrol. SlgMAL FROM AEROPLANES TO KUWAIT FORCES. The aeroplane will signal the position of the enemy to Kuwait troops as follows. It will fly past them and fire off a light as it does so. It will then ialiiJJLL and pass over their heads at a low altitude IN THE DIRECTION IN WHICH THE ENEMY IS. This will Indicate that the enemy is not more than to miles distant In that direction. If the enemy be more than 10 miles and less than 2C miles distant, the ene^y^wLl 1 pksa over their heads twice in his direction; and an additional time for each additional 10 miles• ■ m f Dated 19th February 1928 Telegram to) From Resident, Bushire. To Political, Kuwait. No. 189 Your telegram No.111. Reply which the Shaikh wishes to give is one that has very far reaching effects and would give the idea to Arabs or interior and to Najd which Government of India Is most anxious to avoid that, we are forcing the Shaikh to all actions they commit. My whole instructions at Bahrain are to avoid giving this idea. To let them have the idea that owing to their commitments with us the Shaikh is unable to agree has a very different psychological value and this should be the Shaikh's line of reply. In the present circumstances the request would be rather ridiculous since we have massed an army to attack the man to whom the Shaikh is nervous about refusing food supply. Telegram (C) From Political, Kuwait. To Resident, Bushire. No. 129 Dated 20th February 1928 Your telegram Naxxlft No.l89* I will convey to the Shaikh what you think, but the situation is not likely to arise now.T»l«sram (?) Tpoaa Political, Kuwait, To Resident, Bushire No* 130 Dated 20th February 1928 Your telegram No* 195. As I have already pointed out in my telegram No* 120, the frontier at the nearest place is only 42 miles AtmAaamm distant.0 Telegram (P) Prom Aviation, Baghdad. To Political, Kuwait. No. Z ?8 Dated 20th February 1928 following for SquadronfLeader Peek. The force will not now oroceed to Kuwait until the present raid is over. You should return to Shaibah on 2let February. Ends. Ne. 131-S Political Agency, Kuwait. 20th February 1928. Squadron Leader A.H.Pecic, D.S.O., M.G. A copy of the above telegram is sent herewith for information. Major, Political Agent, Kuwait . %Telegram (?) No To From Resident, Bushire. Political, Kuwait. 198 Dated 20th February 1928 Your telegram No. 120 of loth February« The liohammarah Treaty map shows the average frontier to be 60* Un4»r these circumstances an actual attack by raiders as Eeported in your telegram No. 122 of yesterday the question of frontier naturally disappears. My object is only to give Ibn Sa*ud no grounds for argument, but in/case of his tribes actually attacking he can have none, and the more they are punished the better. Telegram (?) Your telegrata No. 198. Am I right In assuming that you sanction rsconaissances of 60 Biles radius? the From Political, Kuwait To Resident, Bushire. 133 Dated 20th February t$ 1928■■■■■ (*L) aanssIoT •©alriaufi a©^ twu i jlaolJiio^ oT Sp T . cl: r i^Qr fWOS ' &amp;• JaG ^.nsrlolS! y/^ rlSot Go r ii:j .oil ajj-i-^Iwj *1 ;oY aaa;l^ rffio ;J ,•)'&gt; -i-j oj -i tjYt.'ccn! 'sj-rx-yva .} iJ r ■ 4 0.i m . ^ s.u Yv.r -o r .': nG a a anaalA^ I.iydo.a il; a^ jaA,tatTijjo r ilo G© noivtaai/p ©itf *^© SSf .oM aa^^Iad itjo i 'rvly QJ x^ n&lt;) «-* • .a^aqqaai:^ *• i^A-ujAn •►rid vII;j.jjoA aotfl id aii Go -MAoV't! dud ^dnofau^'X© toG *;i&gt;:tu &gt;tl 0 on fr^r'ainuq •j'xn add bn/*. &lt;onon ovgj’ nao arf jnixo^rji.- .Taddad add (®[) fffiiaaleT .diAKu^l , J ac id i:i c. c i rrio'i^. * ai i n aua f ‘n *; biaa£ Uf 8i:ef x^©wncf9 4 l rldOfi bed.sC uoy, darfd gfilinuGBM r.i d , r{ 3 i'i X 01 A. .S^f • oK (BAn 3 aIad ‘'ffoY ?ai;Ifc£n aaliii Oc Go aocr:A? i aianooa'i noidonABTelegram iii (C) From Political, Kuwait. To Resident, Bushire; repeated to Special, Nasiriyah No. ±2* 124 Dated 20th February 1928. Nothing to report in Kuwait area this morning Monday Telegram (C) From Political, Kuwait. To Resident, Bushire; repeated to Special, Nasiriyah. No. 134 Dated 20th February 1928, My No. I24 e Patrols from Jahrah report very heavy bombing all morning in the direction of Riqa 1 ! and to the south eastTelegram (P) Fram Political, Kuwait, To Resident, Buahire, No. t28 Dated 20th February 1928 iZ5 Your telegram No. 193. In the event of my having to take action in accordance with ay telegram No. 1the Senior Naval Officer intends to prevent the raiders from affecting an entry into the tewn by every possible means in his pewer* as being the best methed of protecting British lives and property - if not the only effective one* He points eut f however, that this also affords protection to the Shaikh ef Kuwait, and asks whether there is any politioal oDjection o this* Subject to your confirmation I have replied to him that there is nene* Please confirm* s — — - — -- — Telegram (P) From Resident, Bushire. To Political, Kuwait* No. 207 Dated 20tn February 1928 Your telegram No. 128. I am asking Secretary of State for the Colonies for his approval, but pending the arriwal of aero planes and armoured cars you and the Senior Naval Officer have authority to use any means which you may Jointly consider necessary for the defence of Kuwait.Tele&amp; ram (P) Prom Political, Kuwait. To Resident, Bushire. No. 136 Dated / 21st February 1928 Your telegram No. 20?. The despatch to Kuwait of aero planes and armoured cars has been postponed until the present operations against raiders in the nei&amp;hhourhood of Riqa 1 ! are completed. Even after they have come, however, if I consider that the safety of the town jos demands it X intend to asK the Senior Naval Officer to cooperate in the defence, unless definitely forbidden toTelegram (en clmfcr) From Special, Naairlyah. To Political, Kuwait. No. 1/77 Dated 20th February 1928 . Raiders attacked at Jawarin south of Jarlshan approximately 50 C strong on the morning of 19 th February. Raiders attacked by aircraft five times on 19 th February and seven times on 20 th February. Also cars from Rukhaimlyah via al Hafar cutting off retreat and cars from Shalbah pur suing. No reports yet of car actions or casualties in- flicted. Telegram (C) From Political, Kuwait. To Resident, Bushire. No. 136 Dated 2tat February 1928 Following from Special, Nasiriyah, No.1/77 of 20th February begins. x x x x Ends. This morning, Tuesday, we can hear heavy bombing in Kuwait from the west south west. Letter No. 137 dated 21st February 1928 from P*A.,Kuwait,to HoE 0 Shaikh Ahmad al~Jabir as-SubahyCoIeEo,Ruler of Kuwait. A O C « I hake the honoufc to inform Y,E. that 1 have received a telegram, dated yesterday evening, from the S.S.O.Naslrlyah, saying that ’’Raiders x x x x inflicted”. I have also heard from the S.S.O*,Basrah,at Jarishan, that a party of men of the ’Ahharimah ’Awazim and of Kuwait people were unharmed by the raiders and are now on their way to Hulaibaho UoEoH.M.S• n EIv^BRALD ,, at Kuwait 22nd February 1928 The Stoker Petty Officer who brings thie is in charge of six stokers who are called in our organisation - Personal Guard for Political Agent. They do know how to fire their weapons though they are stokers ! 2. I wonder if you will have an opportunity to tackle Mylrae today. X gave hin a chance of coining to me or expressing his views by letter the other day but have heard aothing. It is this 'laisse* faire' attitude which usually leads to tjoijble. The questions we want answered are (i) Does he propose to claim protection for the (ii) If so, when and in what form ? 3. Personally I think his redundant women should go if trouble threatens and this is so easily done if a reliable dhow is eannarKed which can sail them off to the ship where they can be looked after temporarily. 4. Th© evacuation of the hospital with its sick in all states of illness is a very different matter and I should think that it would be far better for the American men to stand by the sick and trust to the Arabs respecting a hospital. T a is is a point of view on which you know all S^Arab* 10 * no ^^ n ^* Bofis the Red Cross mean anything to 5. I feel that this matter should be stabilized and once we can get it done it should be able stand for all Americans here ? time.CONPIlENTIAL. D.O. No.145-3. &lt;3 i2nd February 1928. In reply to your letter of to-aay's aate, I aa afraid It Is absolutely impossible for me to do any thing re*sardin&amp; the Americans. Sq far j.a { , am concerned I could not even accede to any request for protection tferi~~€K ey to maXe rt, without reference to ni^her authority. Of course, if they or anyone else were to ask you to take them as refugees, that is a matter for you to decide, but I cannot surest it. have much more claim on me than Americans have • The Persian Government has asked that I should &amp;lve my 'good offices' (a much less thing than 'protection',of course) to Persian subjects in Kuwait, and the American Government has not. According to the 'Kuwait Order in Council i' 1925 ' which governs such questions 'Foreigners .with re spect to whom the Shaikh of Kuwait and any State, King, | Chief or Government whose subjects or under whose pro tection they are have agreed with His Majesty for, or j consented to, the exercise of Jurisdiction Dy His kajesty' can have practically the same privileges here | as British subjects. The Shaikh h^s agreed that we should protect the subjects of ill non-Muslim states who \ ask us to do so, but .America has never asked us. About eighteen months ago the American consul in Baghdad asked me for a copy of the 'Kuwait Order-in-Council, I923 n , presumably In connection with this question. No such request has ever been made, however, and until it is, I 1 can obviously do nothing - whatever my personal wishes might be. I do not think there vould be any danger to the hospital, even in case of attack - unless of course the raiders were to get in. I enclose a telegram from the Resident about defending the town. I have asked about after the cars So far as I am concerned officially, PersiansTelegram (P) From Resident, Bushire. To Political, Kuwait. No. 210. Dated 21st February 1928 Your telegram No. 135* My telegrams Noo. I8ij, 186, 193 and 198 had already conveyed the sanction to which you refer. Telegram (P). From Resident, Bushire. To Political, Kuwait. No. 211. Dated 21st February 1928. Your telegrams Noo. 130 and 138. Please be more careful in wording your telegrams. I am still awaiting a reply from the Colonial Office. Obviously if the town be in actual danger and you have no time to refer for orders you must take what action is necessary - this is the only reason for which I obtained the presence of H.M.S. Emerald. My telegrams Noo. 185, 186, 195 and 198 show my objects sufficiently clearly, but I will repeat them to you. They are:- any action which is necessary for the safety of Kuwait, and if it can be avoided no action likely to make my task with Ibn Sa'ud more difficult. I want no more telegrams in the tone of your No. 138 please. You should have said that even with the help of the care you might still require the Emerald's assistance. Phis question will obviously have to be reconsidered on the arrival of the forces in question. Telegram (P). From Political, Kuwait. To Resident, Bushire. No. 147. Dated 22nd February 1928. Your Noo.210 4 211. I regret that you objected to the wording of my wire. I only wanted to remove a few doubts as to what exactly I had authority to doo in case of meed.Now I think I know,but if time permit I W 1H always refer important thingsWireless (en clair) V J ^ Proa Akforoe, Ur Junction* Buscol &amp; Shaibah; repeated Carone, Carfour,Aviation To No* Dated and Emerald for Political Agent, Kuwait* A/255. 22nd February I 92 Q. [O Mo. \ \ Da ta jj Appears likely that raiders will concentrate at Safah area to distribute loot. Raids will be carried out on this area 24th February by Shaibah and Buscol from Ruk and Kuwait. Shaibah formation to consist of six Ninaks, Buscol same plus three Viotorlas. Each NAnak formation to include two ballast.Shaibah aircraft may proceed Kuwait 23rd February if desired. Both raids will leave bases dawn 24th February or as soon as weathei s permits. Every endeavour must be made to maintain W/T communi cation between formations. Aircraft are to bomb 4000 feet and not go down to gun. Signals to and from raid aircraft are to be given priority over all W/T traflic in Ucforce, including Shaibah. Shaibah is to send convoy to Kuwait forthwith with necessary supplies. King's Victoria not available Raid.Victoria proceed Ruk 23rd February. Orders for car section will be issued later. They will not be used in the raid, but aircraft should reconnoitre position of car route for possible future use. Provided to-day's reconnaissances indicate areas clear no reconnaissance will be made on 23rd February. Wkomless (en clair). From Aviation, Baghdad. To Akforce; rd. Buscol, Shaibah, Carone, Carfour, H.M.S. Emerald for P.A., Kuwait. v : No. Dated A/379. 22nd February 1928, ■In, Your k/255 of 22/2. Kuwait must mot be used for base for Safah xatd operations owing to political objections. Shaibah craft can use Rukhalmlyah or place in Batin such as Hubara as refuelling base as you consider best.No To To Political, Kuwait. No. 1/71. Dated 23rd February 1928 Telegram (en clair). From Akforce, Ur Junction Your 143 of to-day. No further developments. Details posted you to-day* Telegram (C). Dated . 23rd February 1928. Your telegram No e 1/71. Your letter will probably not reach Rumour has reached here from Basrah that raiders shot down one aeroplane, captured another aeroplane and an armoured car and killed 300 'Iraq tribesmen, themselves only losing 70 men* I should be glad to know how mueh of this is true and how much I can deny* Telegram (C) From Special, Nasiriyah. To Political, Kuwait. Dated 23rd February 1928. Your telegram No. 148. One aeroplane shot dawn and pilot killed but no further casualties of British forces. Casualties amongst raided tribes or raiders not yet kmaanx known here. From Political, Kuwait To No Special, Nasiriyah* 148. No I 76Telegram (C) ! Prom Highcoma, Baghdad, Secretary ofo State for the Colonies; repeated to Resident, Bushire, Kuwait, Bahrain, Jerusalem, Jiddah and India. To No. nil Dated 23rd February 1928. ATWA'm# The following is an account of the last Ikhwan raid, com piled from the latest telegraphic reports which are in complete and fragmentary. On the 19th February sections of the 1 1raq Juwarin tribe, yC the Kuwait '’Atharimah tribe, and of nomad Sulubba tribes men were attacked near Jarishan by an Ikhwan force, es timated at 1000 camels carrying two men each and a large number of horse, probably 2300 men in all. Losses not yet known in detail but reported to have been heavy. The raid is said to have been tasA led by Faisal ad-Dawish in person, chief of the Mutair tribe. On the 19th February aerial reconnaissances located two parties of raiders, one near Riqa’i and a larger party ten miles south of Jarishan. Later reconnaissances on the same day observed parties in the Jarishan district, spreading over a considerable area and driving Off loot. All parties seen were attacked. Aircraft were heavily fired on and one machine came down in flames, the pilot being killed. On the 20th February the raiders were again attacked from the air, teeing then spread over a large area east of Abrak al-Habara (AbradJ el Hibari) and Qulban. Casualties inflicted can be only aproximately estimated owing to the scattering of the raiders, but are probably 50 men, and certainly a number of camels and sheep were killed.Letter No.151 dated 24th February 1928 from P.A.,Kuwait, to H.E. Shaikh Ahmad al-Jabir aa-Subah,C.I.E.,Ruler of Kuwait. After complimentfl. I have the honour to &amp;lve Your Excellency the following account of the recent raid, compiled from various telegrams, but it is not a very complete account as yet. On Sunday,the 2?th Sha’ban, sections of the Juwarin tribe of 'Iraq, of the and of the Sulubba were attacked near Jarishan by a force of Ikhwan estimated at 1,000 camels carrying two men each and a large number of horsemen, probably 2,J00 men in all, and believed to have been commanded by Faisal ad-Dawish in person. The losses are not yet known In detail, but are reported to have been heavy. On the same day, Sunday, aerial reconnaissances located two parties of raiders, one near Riqa’i and a larger one ten miles south of Jarishan. Later reconnaissances on the same day observed parties in the Jarishan district spread over a considerable area driving off loot. All parties seen were attacked and the aeroplanes were heavily fired on in return. One aeroplane fell in flames and the pilot was killed but there were no further British casualties. On Monday the raiders were again attacked from the air being then spread over a large area east of Abrak al-Hubara and Qulban, and they were again attacked on Tuesday, as we were able to hear here in Kuwait. The casualties inflicted on the raiders cannot be accurately estimated owing to their being so scattered. The last I heard of them was that it was thought that they would concentrate at Safah, but I have not heard yet whether they actually did, or where tney now are. Usual ending.CONFIDENTIAL. D.O. No* 77-3. Bushire, 18th February 1928 Your telegram ^lo. 103 of today* You are aware that my view of policy regarding Kuwait differs somewhat from that of ’Iraq. 1 separate Kuwait as a permanent factor in our international policy from ’Iraq, which has one interest as a mandate but quite another if that mandate weakens or ceases. The posting of an ’Iraq intelligence officer at Kuwait has a tendency, of which i doubt the wisdom, of bringing an ’Iraq official as an immediate liaison between Kuwait and ’Iraq resulting in opinions of which the Kesident may have no knowledge and thus which he may be unable to contradict. It would bring an ’Iraq officer into immed- \ -iate touch with the Shaikh of Kuwait and must weaken the ' position of the JPolitical Agent and produce friction since the tendency of the Shaikh will be to turn to ’Iraq for assistance. This would gradually link Kuwait with *iraq a nd might result in a very close alliance, even a tendency to absorption in subordinate alliance as opposed to ibn saud. As protecting power we should have to combat any such tendency as opposed to our interests. i can see no compensatory advantage to be gained. would you let me know what the Intelligence Officer can do that you cannot, and your studied opinion in view of what 1 have said. i am quite ready, if you can put up a case, to suggest an intelligence officer from India. Major J.C.More, D.S.O., Political Agent, Kuwait.Telegram (P) From Political, Kuwait, To Resident, Bushire. No. 149 Dated 23rd February 1928. Demi-Official. Your D.O. letter No.77 S of 18th February. I quite understand why you think it undesireable to have an Intellegence Officer from 'Iraq posted to Kuwait, and but for the fact that it was only proposed as a temporary measure, I would be as much opposed to it as you are. No doubt one reason why the proposal seemed to me so attract ive was that when it was made I was snowed under with more work than I could satisfactorily cope with, and I know that he would relieve me of some of it. There is not the slightest need more an Intellegence Officer here in normal times, and I think that even now the only things which he could do which I do not are:- (a) as it would be he all-time work he could go round himself more, and so get the information quicker. (b) He could employ secret service agents. I thiik,however, that at a time like the present he would be worth having for (b) alone. I have no funds for secret service work and I do not think that it would be desirable for me personally to employ spies in any case, yet it is an undeniable fact that they are useful and Kuwait would be the best recruiting ground for them for the type of tribal work which is required. I do not advocate your applying for a man from India as it would take too long, and besides he would be absolutely use less unless he knew Arabic really well. If you think that the advantages are outweighed by the dis advantages I venture to suggest the possibility of a com promise by your borrowing the services of an Arabic speaking British Officer from Air Headquarters, ’Iraq, to act Tempor arily as my assistant, on the understanding that I would only employ him on Intellegence work, for which they would provide the funds, and he would make his reports to me and not correspond directly at all. They might agree to this as thehead of the Intellegenoe ln Baghdad and I worked together at Intellegence all through the War, The next day or two will show whether XKsrsi there is any need £or anything of the sort or not.Telesram (C) /fo \ % Froa Political,•Kuwait. To Resident, Bushire; repeated to Hifthcoma, Baghdad and Special, Nasiriyah. No. /5‘ci Dated 24th February 1928. Shaikh* of Kuwait*® messengers to Ibn Sa*ud left Riyadh on their return on 17th February and arrived here this afternoon, Friday© Ibn Sa*ud expresses regret to the Shaikh that he cannot do more about restoration of plunder as Dawlsh is quite out of control at present© The messengers report that all the Ikhwan are now definitely Joining with Dawlsh in a regular Jihad against all non- Ikhwaji, and they heard (though they cannot vouch for the truth of this) that Ibn Sa*ud had been bullied into promising to supply them with arms and amunition, and associate himself with the Jihad. It is perfectly certain that he can do nothing to restrain them. Ibn Hithlain was actually with Ibn Sa'ud in Riyadh when they left, but was known to be leaving shortly and was believed to have sent orders for the whole of the *AJman tribe to meet him at some unknown rendezvous. Ibn Humaid was said to be still at Ghatghat but was also about to take the field©Telegram (?) From Resident, Buahire. No To Dated Secretary of State for the Coloniesjrepeated to Baghdad, and Kuwait. 220 (No.# 35 to Colonies) 24th February 1928. Aviation telesram No. X 379 of 22nd February in which it was for the Safah operatloas for political reasons. It would be useful in future discussions to be able to make the statements that aircraft from Kuwait had never been used in the interests of ’Iraq,*lt is obvious that if in the present circumstances this unduly handicaps the operations, it become a question of relatives values and in case of urgency the restriction cannot be maintained. said that aeroplanes should not be used from a base at KuwaitTelegram (C) Prom Political, Kuwait. To Resident, Bushire. No. 153 Dated 25th February 1928. My telegram No. 147. Wireless message intercepted by Emerald. Begins. Vincent and two Whistlers 0945 from bomb raid proceeded via * * * Hafar to point 20 miles north north west of Safah where a large camp was located. Camp was similar to the camp located at Umm al-’Amarah on 19th February and was surrounded by camels, horses and flooks of sheep. One salvo from Aerofive and two of Supcol aircraft were dropped amongst the tents. Then proceeded to Safah. Aerofour and one aircraft of Supcol remained over the camp and dropped all bombs with excellent results. Safah consisted of three wells, a mud fort and about ten mud houses in two gpoups also one large white tent. Tribes men, camels and horses were all about the camp. All bombs of Aerofive and two aircraft of Supcol were dropped. Two direct hits xsxcxax by 20-lb bombs were observed on the buildings and the remainder of the bombing was all amongst the men, camels and horses. (Technical details ommited). Casualties con siderable but impossible to estimate.I Telegram (G) Foom Political, Kuwait. To Special, Nasiriyah; • o 154 Dated 25th February 1928. / repeated to Bushlre. # 64 donkeys and about 200 sheep and goats plundered from 'Iraq tribes and abandoned by raiders have been brought into Jahrah* The Shaikh of Kuwait is having them looked after until sent for.Wireless (en clalr). Prom Details, Shaibah. To H.M.S.Emerald for Political Agent, Kuwait. No. A/l02. Dated 24th February 1928. ^7 A.O.C. and Colonel Dent leaving Shaibah by air 0800 local time 25th February for Kuwait. Returning to Busaiyah about noon. Telegram (G). Prom Political, Kuwait. To Resident, Bushire. No. 136. Dated 25th February 1928 . I heard late last night that the A.O.C. and Colonel Dent (Head of the Intelligence) arrive here by air this morning, Saturday, and return noon today.Telegram (P) 0 Prom Political, Kuwait* To Resident, Bushire© No. 155. Dated 25th February 1928* My telegram No*149* In my opinion the information contain ed in my telegram No*152 throws an entirely new light on the situation* If this report be true, as I think it must be, Ibn Sa’ud may be said to have ceased to exist as a political factor - at all events for the time being* Most regrettable as this fact is, I fear we must face it*Instead of there being a fair chance of the troubles being over soon, as I had thought, we now seem to be in fop a pro tracted campaign* Diplomacy must give place to armed force too in dealing with religious fanatics* I think therefore that it is now desirable that there should be an Intelli gence Officer here as the requirements of the fighting forces become paramount* If you think as I do about the above, I fancy you will no longer object to an Intelligence Officer from 'Iraq, but if you stile do, and think my other suggestion unworkable, I would suggest that you do ask India for a British Officer who knows Arabic*J'jl Letter No«157 dated 25th February 1928 from P.A*, Kuwait, to H.E. ShaiKh Ahmad al-J&amp;bir as-Subah, C.I.E., Ruler of Kuwait, I have the honour to Inform Your Excellency that yester day morning a number ad aeroplanes proceeded from the Neutral Zone by way of Hafar al-Batin towards Safah. Twenty miles to the north, north-west of Safah a large camp of white tents was located surrounded by camels, horses and flocks of sheep, Some of the aeroplanes dropped all their bombs there, and the ethers after dropping one each were ordered to proceed to Safah. The results of this bombing is thought to have been good, Safah was found to consist of three wells, a fort of mud bricks, and about ten mud houses in two groups; and there was also one large white tent there. All the remaining bombs were dropped here. Two direct hits by large bombs were observed on the buildings, and the remainder of the bombs fell all amongst the men camels and horses. The casualties inflicted were certainly heavy but it was impossible to estimate the numbers, U.E. / «Telegram (P) From Political, Kuwait. To Resident, Bushire. No. 157 Dated 25th February 1928. My telegram No, 156o The A.O.C. accompanied by Colonel Dent has been and gone. He is going to send armoured cars and aeroplanes to form a base in Kuwait on the 27th February. In this connection he tells me that he now understands there are to be no res trictions at all regarding their use. In view of your telegram No. 193 I shall be grateful if ypu will let me know if this is the case. He also intended to send a Special Service Officer here, but at once cancelled the order on my telling him that you were not in favour of the proposal. At the same time he asks me to point out to you that a Special Service Officer is really necessary to accompany car reconnaissances etc.. I sounded him on the subject and he says that he would every bit as soon have him come here as my assistant if you consider that preferable. In any case he would have the atxfcatsx* strictest orders to keep me fully informed and take my advice in everything.Telegram (G) From Highcoma, Baghdad. &lt;^9 To No. Secretary of State for the Colonies; repeated to Resident, Bushire, Kuwait and Delhi. 84 (No.110 to Colonies) Dated 25th February 1928. 4 Provisional miaiMM minimum estimate of casualties and losses inflicted on ’Iraq shepherd tribes by Ikhwan during raid near Jaukhah on 19th £skxiuu££ December are killed 50 men; lost 10,000 sheep and 1,100 donkeys. The figures given are the result of prolonged inquiries and are not yet completely verified, many reports putting losses to the Shammar ,Dhaflr and Dahamishah tribes which have not yet been verified. The Dahamishah alone claim to have lost 12 men,2,000 sheep and jrf 250 camels.Telegram (en clear) Prom A&amp;force. To Political, Kuwait. No. I 81 Dated 25thHebruary 1928. Special, Nasiriyah, has information from two independent sources that, the majority of the ’Ajman were with I bn J1luwl* s force. If correct this supplies possible explanation for ]i disbandment. Telegram (en clear) Proa Political, Kuwait. To Akforce, Ur Junction. No. 161 Dated 26th February 1928. Your I 81* According to my information *AJman were not with him.Telegram (C) Prom Political, Kuwait. f., /S'- 2 . Resident, 3ushire;repeated to Highcoma Bagtidad and Special, Nasiriyah. No. • 164 Dated 26th February 1923e My telegram No. 152. Only now have I had an opportunity of examining the messenger myself. X think from what he says that there is no doubt that Ibn Sa’ud has actually given his permission to all the Ikhwan to go raiding, though whether from fear or for what reason is not clear. Apparently he was influenced by a letter which he received from the north. There were rumours fcfcafcfc* that he had actually sent arms and ammunition to Ibn Humaid, but he does not know whether this was true. Such wild rumours were current that it was difficult to arrive at the truth. He travelled with Ibn Rubi*ah who went on to Basrah and has been seen by Special.r n Telegram (P) Resident, Bushire. To Political, Kuwait; repeated to Colonial Office No Dated Baghdad and India 234 (No. 40 to Colonial Offi 25th February 19 2 8. /(/ Your teiegram No.157. Under the circumstances I natually realize that an Intellegence Officer is necessary at Kuwait and that military measures are required without political restriction^ Please consult the Air Officer Commanding and the Senior Naval Officer and telegraph their opinion regarding the troops necessaryn to hold Kuwait if attached, by the Ikhwan in the number which may be possible to arrive, repeatfedg your telegram td Baghdad, and India. Draw up a plan of defence for the town. The defence of Jahrah and the outer territory of Kuwait would, I presume* # be difficult if not impossible.^^ Telegram (P) From Political, Kuwait. To Resident, Bushire; repeated to Colonial Office, here now. He only visited Kuwait for a short time yester day. I have consulted the S.N.O. and it is his opinion that, with the Air reconnaissances now available, he has at his disposal sufficient force to defend the town of Kuwait against any force which it appears probable that the lichwan can bring against it, and, now that he is moving H.M.SS. Lupin and Crocus up in this direction, he thinks there ought not to be the slightest doubt, even if the India, High Commissioner, Baghdad, and Aviation, Baghdad. No. H 165 Dated 26th February 1928. Your telegram No. 234. The Air Officer Commanding is not numbers far exce ed those feared by the Shaikh. I agree/4^ Ms-'Z-Z'*' ) entirely. Plan for the defence of the town had been drawn up already. In the event of a very large force approaching, of which the Shaikh anticipates receiving sufficient warning, Jahrah and the other villages would be evacuated to Kuwait. Against anything less Jahrah would be defended by its existing garrison. Telegram (P) Fromm Political, Kuwait. To Resident, Bushire. No. 168 Dated 2?th February 1928. Your telegram No. 242 (in which he gave repetitions to certain groups in his No. 234 asked for in my No*, 162) As I received no reply to my telegram No. 162 by the evening of the 26th February, I thought it better not to delay answering it longer. So I sent my No. 165&gt; repeated Jtn it amongst other places to the Colonial Office, assuming that you had told me to do so In the undecypherable 15th double group of your No.234 and which you now tell me to delete. Telegram (P). From Pa* Resident, Bushire. To Political, Kuwait. No. Nil. Dated 28th February 1928. Yovr telegram No.168. The group In question did say 'and Colonial Office'. I sent the Instructions to delete In error which I regret./-N Telegram (P) Prom Political, Kuwait To Resident, Bushire 16JU No Dated 25th February 1928. The American Missionaries here tell me that they are anxious to regularize their position here under the Kuwait Order in Council so as to be entitled to our protection if the worsfc came to the worsfc* They are asking the American Consul in Baghdad to fc take the necessary official action. To ease their minds meanwhile I have agreed to ask for authority to promise them our protection in the pres ent crisis in anticip tion of the request of the United States Government. Telegram (P) Prom Resident, Bushire. Your telegram No. 160. If the occasion should arise you will protect Americans and any other Europeans in the same way as if they were British Subjects.Telegram (C) From Akforce, Ur Junction. To Political, Kuwait. No. 1/85 Dated 2?th February 1928. Following from Dent. What would the utility and prac ticability of sending a Special Service Officer to Bahrain. Who is Political Agent there? Telegram (C) From Political, Kuwait. To Akforce, Ur Junction. No. 167 Dated 27th February 1928. Your telegram No. I/85- Personal for Colonel Dent. Major Barrett, whom you will remember at Ba'qubah, is Political Agent at Bahrain. I am not sure but he could tell you better than I.Telegram (G). i(*o From Political, Kuwait To Resident, Bushire. No* 166 Dated 27th February 1928 # / J # My 164. Following from Special,Basrah,to Aviation etc.* Intercepted by Emerald, T/2?6. Beginso Zaldar-Rubi 1 ah, a relative of Ibn Sa'ud, appears reliable, returned from Riyadh to-day having left that place 16th February where he stayed as guest of Sultan. He says he was in Riyadh 50 days. Gives following unconfirmed information* On first of Sha'ban Ibn Sa*ud was not in agreement with the Mutair but in the middle of the month changed his policy apparently as the result of the letter from the north, origin unicnown. He then sent for all chiefs of the Ikhw^n. All came except Ibn Humaid, the latter was sent 800 rifles and eight camel loads of ammunition together with &amp;X1K0 8,000 dollars and leave to attack the frontier. Ibn Humaid asked for a son of Ibn Sa^d, preferably Sa’ud, to accompany him. This was refused. Ibn Humaid reported to be leaving Ghat-Ghat on 24th February approximate available following 10,000 plus section of the Qahtan. Objective said to be the frontier post then north eastwards. Ibn Hithlain and ^ Fuqm were still in Riyadh when he left and receiving tents and presents. Forces of Ibn Jiluwi and Ibn Musa'ad both disbanded as consequence of changed policy. If the abow is true the attack would take place about the end of February or beginning of March. The story of the murder of Ibn Humaid was due to an abortive attack by the sons of an executed wife accused of reverting from Wahkibiism. Ends. I consider the estimate of followimg excessive.Telegram (C) From Political, Kuwait. To Resident, Bushire. No. 172 Dated 28th February. 1928 ”Kowcol w , as the force is called, consisting of four aero planes, and three armoured cars and four armed Fords, under Squadron Leader Peck arrived here this evening Monday. Telegram (G). From Political, Kuwait. To Resident, Bushire. No. 2 173. Dated 28th February 1928. H.M.S. Lupin arrived here this morning, Tuesday,28th February. Telegram (C). From Political, Kuwait. To Resident, Bushire. No. 180. Dated 1st March 1928. H.MS. Crocus arrived here late last night, Wednesday.Telegram (C). From Political, Kuwait 't- / 6 d To No Fesidont, Bushire; repeated to Special, Nasiriyah 174. Dated 28th February 1928. A traveller from Mecca via Qasim and Habah (28 miles S.S.E, of Safah) arrived here today, Tuesday. He heard at BftJftif Habah on 22nd February that Dawish was then encamped at Hairah, twenty miles N.W, of Safah - evidently the first zamiDUl camp bombed on 24th February. He did not hear the bombing on 24th February and has no fresh newsKuwait, 27 February 19-P- 170-S, of even date, and on behalf of ail the African citizens in Kuwait I extend to you our thank a for the information that, ehould the neoeeaity ari»e durin 0 the present crisis American citi-ens are to be protected in exactly the Sisme manner as British subjects, and for your efforts in securing that arrangement and assurance for us.Telegram From To No. Dated ( 0 ) Political, Kuwait. Resident, Bushire. 176. 28th February 1928. Owing to the uncertainty of the weather at this time of the year and the difficulty in landing parties sxjisjifcgtttiastiy expeditiously in bad weather, the S®N # 0. thinks it advisable to maintain the shore jdju&amp;£ parties on shore* I have arranged for tents for them with the Shaikh of Kuwait, but they would be obviously better under a roof* Shaikh Khas’al* palace (men's part) is conveniently situated and would suit admirably. Would bt be possible to obtain permission from him for it to be used?Telegram (P). Prom Political, Kuwait To Rpsid^nt, Bushire No 179 Dated 29 th February 1928. My No.1?2. I am informed by the S.N.Q, that he has only received Admiralty sanction to co-operate in the defence of the town of Kuwait until the arrival ofl the armoured cars and aeroplanes. As it is obvious that he will still have to do so if the place is attacked in force, he is applying for the necessary sanction. He has asked whether he may say fciiaJ that I consider it necessary, and, to save the time which a previous reference to you would have involved, I have agreed.Telegram (P) -A From To No* Dated Resident, Bushire* Colonial Office; repeated to Baghdad, India and Kuwait• 24? (45 to Colonial Office) 2?th February 1928* Immediate* Telegram No* 165 from Political, Kuwait* If the x * condition of things even remotly resembling those designated by Baghdad In hie telegram No. 110 should arise, defence measures will certainly be necessary* If the statement of Political, Kuwait, In hie telegram No. 155 that Xbn Sa’ud Is now negllgeable as a political factor joxuuu prove to be even half true and there Is truth in the statement that a Jihad has been declared then a grave condition must arise* I presume i that in that case ’Iraq would require all her armoured cars and could only assist with aeroplane reconnaissances, since possibly Kuwait might not be attacked but the religious fanatic would concentrate against Karbala and Najaf* It is possible that His Majesty’s ships with the Kuwait forces might be sufficient to prevent the town from being attacked, but this is a question which cannot be left in any doubt* We cannot afford to have our men overwhelmed if the defence of the Arabs break. We should only have a few days notice if a critical \jj0To. /o condition-^sr arise* It takes some time for troops to get preliminaries ready, hence the suggestion to India in my telegram No. 235 that they should be told to stand by in case they are required as a precautionary measure, as in that case the whole essence of the matter would be true* No harm is done if they are not required* Consequently although it is my hope that these conditions will not arise, it is very possible on the evidence now before us that they may, aid I think that we should be prepared for them. vO y ' “' i[2[ 'o yS /Telegram (p). Prom Political, Kuwait To Resident, Buehire No 184 Dated 2nd March 1928. Your No. 234. Captain de Galiry, S.S.O., Basrah, who x appears to be the right type of man, arrived here to-day for Intelligence work. He is giving me copies off all telegrams and other reports which he sends, and if you agree I will post a copy of each to you, only wiping such things as are interesting but not mere routine reports. Telegrai (P). ^rom Resident, Bushire. To Political, Kuwait. No. ?8 q: Dat^d Jrd March 1928. I agree to the proposal in your No.184. What is the position at x^resent. You might please let me have a daily telegram&amp; /// COPY OF MESSAGE . From* •••••Resident, Bushire, To#.••••••The C*in C # , E.I.jfNo. 272) Repeated to Secretary of State for Colonies. India, ( (56) S.N.O*, P.G* who will kindly deliver to Political Agent, Koweit. Date. ..•• .1st March. 1928. System W/T. S.H.O.Js telegraom 1510/29. I am anxious to maintain personal control of political situation in Persian Gulf as local officers cannot always have knowledge of general policy and thus would ask that all matters other than those of immediate urgency be referred to me. S.N.O^s request in this case will pribably already have been sanctioned by Admiralty since he drew up plan of defence of town with concurrence of political Agent and stated that with ships at his disposal he could hold the place# This was at my request telegraphed by the Political Agent, Koweit, in his 165 direct to the Secretary of State for the Chlonies and India. I I have made certain other precautionary suggestions which do not for the present affect the proposals of the S.B.O. and Political Agent. Latter already has full authority in case of emergency.Tele&amp;raai (3). Frona Hi^hooaa, Baghdad. Political, Kuwait. Nil. 2nd March 1928. To No. Dated liroular Te legr am. My circular telegram of 23rd February. Losses to the tribes attacked by the Ikhwan near Jarishan on 19th February are reported to have been 26 men killed arid 18 wounded. Lost - 178 O sheep and 130 camels/ Tele^ra® (?)• Prod Winery, London, To ReRident, Busbire. No. 101 . Dated 2nd March 1928* Your telegram No,53 of 29th February. Of course Kowcol should remain under the operational control of the Mr Officer Commanding, 'Iraq, in order to ensure co-ordination in the defence measures. ■ijv nc/. 3 •IAN S'Telegram (Code) r W from Political, Kuwait* • To Resident, Bushire; repeawed to Hifchcoimt, Baghdad, and Spe ilal, Kaairlyah* No. 105. Dated ^rd March 192ft* The Kuwait Mutalrl by whom Dawlsh sent In the deaund to be allowed to trade with Kuwait on the 14th February, and by whom the Shaikh sent back his refusal, has returned to Kuwait where his family le. According to hie statement: (l) Dawish in person wao in the camp to the north, north west or Safah when it iris bombed on 24th February# The Ikhw&amp;n heard the aeroplanes in time to scatter and there were no casualties amongst the men# At &gt; S&amp;fah itself the mosque waj destroyed and ®ne wom^n wounded in the leg# A* both places some animals were killed. There were two or three raen killed on the previous days# &lt; 4 ) Dawiah himself has now gone to Artawlyah, having, sent worn to five o'-lraas (standards) of Ikhwan from the other side of Najd, who were on their way to Join him, to wait until he could communicate with Ibn 3a*ud again. He wants to try and persuade Ion 3a 1 ud to definitely declare war on the British and to send one of his sons with the Ikhw&amp;n force, both of which Ibn Sa’ud has so far refused to do, although he has given permission to raid and has supplied them with arms ^nd e&amp;munltlon and also money# (&gt;) Bawl ah*s son t U*aiyli has gone with Ibn Shunair and I on Laml to Jaryah for a few days snd will then rejoin his force which he has left a little way south of Safah. In view of (l) above, which I presume must be untrue, the 7 t s tn cannot be considered reliable# No#~l86-iT Political Agency, Kuwait, Jrd ^.rch %9u6 A cony of the above telegram is sent, with compliments, to Senior i'iaval Officer in the Persian Gulf, ri. ,.3#herald. Officer Commanding, 'Kowcoi’’, Royal Air Force, Kuwait. Bpeolal Bervice Officer, Basrah, Kuwait# Lieut. Ool., Political .Agent, Kuwait#Secret Kuwait, AUus? 6 No 1/929 4 th ^Etaasry To:-Air Staff Intelligence, Air Headquarters Baghdad, An agent of thi r office,a Hashaidi,who war with the Futair and accompanied them on the Jarirhari raid returned on 3/^ 28. Fe ir believed to be quite reliable and makes the following statement, Origionally tie intention of the t'Tutair was an attack on Ibn Jaluwi of Kara but this plan was vetoed by Ibn Huraaid who sent aletter forbidding it if they valued his friend: hip. They then set out with the intention'of raiding ever the Irac frontier outwards from al Fiqai. The fcllowing well- - known leaders were wit) them,Ft it al ad Dari rh,hi: son Azayiz,Jesr Ibn I«jni ,Tur&amp;l ib Ibn fl igi air tud h li Ibn A r hwan. Tl.ey werf in three divisions vritlf three flags. (Azayiz and Ibn Ashwan being rit v the Dc.vith end living no separate flag) On approaching the frontier tone rcoutt on tl^e right ring reported the easy prey in the Juwarin shepherds near Jarirhan end they were being dealt with on the morning of the 19tk when the Thai bed; 'recco 'fortunately came upon them. This altered their planr and by tl e evening ohe whole raid was in retreat. Informant says on the outward journey they watered at as rafa and at Fhigayih(a few miles noruh of al Riqai)and that after the raid they sent parties to al Fiqai to v/ater and meet them. Ke says that on^the evening of the 19th tie raiders loss^that he himtelf^or 5 lad good kiiovdedge of was 8 men killed,abou-u the tame rnjiE.bei wounded,5camels killed ‘ 2 horses killed and many sheep killed,wounded or abandoned. 5 of the men killed were shot he says by t.ie Atarnah section of the Awazim during the ^id. .Informant was himself at Fm-al /anarai:,where was ad Dawish*&gt; when it was bombed. They heard the planes coning from some distance and struck their tents and scattered, the Fhaikhe made o f at top speed on horses but the following casualties occurred. Ibn luwailah of the Buraih killed.2 men wounded, a horse and a mare of 2Taif Ibn Kaziad(llaj id)killed,b Braih cartels killed and about 80 sheep killed or wounded. Three tents were completely destroyed. In addition a man of the Rashaidi who was not far from the camp and was riding his camel and driving shoep(about CO)was struck by a bomb and mu t have received it*r full exiloi ion as he card hir c mel and three quarflerr of the sheep were blown to bits . On the 24th informant was at Khalaiiah with the tents of the Dawish. That morning Bawlsh set out with an escort of 70 camelraen for Artiviyah. Hot long after his departure planes . arrived with little warning owing to the high wind and also because no look qut was being kept, however there war just time to strike the tentr end scatter**. The large black guest-tent of the Dawish war completely destroyed togeather with all it’s contents( cook-pots snd coffee uteri; ilr ). Informant says that 40 men of t e Ataibah tribe were with the raider^ and that this party lost 3 camels. Two men of the hut air were wounded and one men hiding in a ditch from the planef was bitten byfa snake and subsequently died. The majority of the raided sheep had reached the camp and of these about 20 were killed. Informant war not himself at as fafa that day but spoke with several who were there who gave him the following account. The nor que wa: almost entirely destroyed. The house of r harayan Ibn Isuni wa: destroyed and all it f t contents. One woman was wounded in the mosque and one woman wa- v/ounded in ti e chest and expected to die. A man who was leaving* as fafa on his camel and iiad got : ome way was kil ed although his mount was unhurt.Telegram (F) From Resident, Bushlre. To Political, Kuwait, No, 299 Dated 4th* March 1928. Demi-Official. Your telegram No. 184, As always my object is to maintain political control. You will no doubt have gathered from the correspondence that the Hifeh Commissioner for Iraq and I do not insariably see eye to eye, and I want nothing to be done without my Knowledge which might react on our political situation in Kuwait or any where in the Persian Gulf, or prejudice our British Indian interests. You will be guided by this in deciding what to send on, as I of course do not want pure routine matters. Telegram (P) From Resident, Bushire. To Political, Kuwait. No. 300 Dated 4th March 1928. Your telegram No. 176. The Dlwaniya h part of the palace outside the town may be used, as also a twelve roomed house in the town itself. The Hara m has people in it and cannot used. Mulla Salih will make the necessary arrangements.Telegram (P) Prom Political, Kuwait To Resident, Bushire 187 (S&gt; No Dated 4th March 1928, My telegram No. 18S&gt;« Secret Service Agent whomthe Special oervice -(filicer, Basrah, had sent to Dawish’s camp, and whom the latter had detained until the raid was over and compelled to tajte part in it, has arrived here. He confirms what we had heard before that the bombing casualties were negligable and also that Faisal ad-Dawish has gone to Artawiyah, and 1 Uzaiyiz and the other shaikhs mentioned to Jaryah. It was expedted that Ibn Humaid would raid immediately.3 ONg I DENT IAL. i.o. J 8 C-S. Folitloal March 1923. in the Persian Gulf, Intelligence. MEMORANDUM. Reference niy tele^raa No. 137 of yesterday's date* I enclose herewith a copy of Captain de Gaury’s examina tion of the a&amp;ent, No.I /929 dated the 4th March I923 # .ind also a note by him, Mo. I /928 dated the 3rd March &lt;943, on the topography of the northern portion of the Batin. Captain de Gaury appears to be a very well qualified officer, and has evldentiy had very strict instructions net U&gt; have anything, to do with political matters. I shall be guided by what you say in your telegram No. 239 of yesterday’s date, and be careful not to omit sendln, you anything of any importance. Lieut.-Col., Political A^ent, Kuwait. To The Hon'ble the Political Resident B U 3 H I R S. OJ* Agency, Kuwait.S £ C f? £T. AKFORCE HEADQUARTERS. Royal Air Force. UR JUNCTION. Reference:- 1/66 /zr To:- Major J.C. More Political Agent KOWAIT. 21st. February Subject:- MUTAIR RAID ULimaTM ARflt. - 1 9/2/2,S. ^ ^r^ATjnin.i. The following brief details of air and armoured car action, subsequent to the Mutair raid in the vicinity of. 1 . Feb. 1 6th. Orders issued from Akforce H.Q,. for armoured car section to move from BUSAIYAH to RUKHAIMIYAH and re-establish the advanced base for air operations in the Neutral Zone and south of the frontier. Feb. 17th. Rumours of Mutair raid in unknown direction received from Police Post at BUSAIYAH from Harb via. Dhafir sections encamped in Neutral Zone, No protective reooo. south of the frontier on this date owing to unfavourable weather conditions. , eb. 18 th. Aircraft move to advanced base at RUKHAIMIYAH. Information received from Political KOWAIT via. A.I. NASIRIYAH that reliable news had arrived to effect that ad Dawish had reached a position 26 miles east of AS SAFA and that a raid on KOWAIT was considered probable. Protective air reoco. carried out over tribes in Neutral Zone. Further reoco. ordered for 1^/2. over area HAFAR - MASHID IBN RASHID - ABU AL HIRAM - AL RIQAI; Shaibah aircraft also ordered to carry out patrol over area KOWAIT - AL RIQAI a nd return Shaibah along AL BATIN. These patrols cover probable line of advance of raiding party on KOWAIT territory. No news of raiding party received from any source. 4. Feb. 19th. Air recco. located $00 raiders and 2C white tents 10 miles NE. of AL RIQAI# Leader of formation shot through petrol tank and compelled to retire and land to repair damage. Second reoco. also located $00 camel and horsemen, with captured flocks and camels, proceeding south and located £ miles S. of JARISHAN. Both parties of raiders repeatedly attacked by aircraft and armoured oars ordered to proceed in direction of attack and endeavour to co-operate with aircraft. Information from Special Service Officer BASRAH indicates that the raiding party had attacked and looted flocks of Juwarin, Solubba and Kowait Arabs in vicinity of JARISHAN prior to their interception by patrolling aircraft. Later report from A.I. BASRAH states convoy of Mishail ibn Tawala of the Shammar ’Aslam attacked and looted by raiders. Raid appears to have been a large one and may have totalled 1.000 raiders, possibly operating from a previously established base at AL RIQAI# The following of ibn Shuqair, ibn Ashwan and ibn Lami JARISHAN, are forwarded herewith for information. Events are chronicled in date sequence.believed implicated in raid* Line of raiders 1 retreat at present south-west down JLL BATIN. Casualities inflicted by air action very few, owing to rapid dispersal of raiders on approach of aircraft. -5-._-Eeb. Huth. Raiders again located by aircraft and still retreating down BATIN, but tending to move south towards AL MUSANiiA ridge. Air action continued throughout the day against scattered sections of raiders by all available aircraft. Movement of raiders very slow, owing to apparent reluctance to abandon loot. Majority of air action has taken place in vicinity of ABRAJ AL HI BARI (L.G. 'X'). No report of oars being in touch with raiders, but one Mutairi reported to have been captured. One aircraft brought down and destroyed by fire; pilot dead, but body recovered (stripped of uniform). Total oasualities among raiders approx. 36 (probably conservative estimate), also considerable damage inflicted on camels and stock. 6# Feb, a1st. Air action against raiders still in progress. General movement still southward, but raiders dispersing into still smaller sections and consequently difficult to locate by aircraft. Minor casualities inflicted upon personnel (only 3 given in final estimate) but fairly heavy losses among stock in possession of raiders. No aircraft oasualities. No reports yet received relative to action by armoured cars* Comment:- The above gives a very brief outline of the sequence of evaliAs up to date. Captured Mutairi is stated to be badly wounded, but has made . statement to the effect that ad Dawish himself was in camp at AL RI^AI. Flight Lieut. Intelligence, Akforce Headquarters. Royal Air Force. UR. 21/2/28^ / Letter No.191 dated 6th March 1928 from P.A., Kuwait, to H.E. Shaiith Ahmad al-Jabir as-Subah, ,Ruler of Kuwait As I told Your Excellency verbally yesterday afternoon the Senior Naval Officer wishes to have the &amp;un which is mounted on the wall between the Naif Gate and Tower No.12 fired for a short time to-day to tesu the emplacement. The gun will fire in the direction which Y.E. approved yesterday, and it is necessary that a plot of ground half a mile / or roughly 175G dhira 1 s broad be kept absolutely three and a half miles in that direction, and I shall be grateful if Y«E. will give very strict orders for this to be done in ample time. The actual firing will take place at a quarter past eight, but I shall be there at eight o’clock, and will be glad if you will detail a responsible person jtftxxMfcxu (whose name I *should like to know beforehand) to meet me there at that hour and report to me that the ground is clear, as I have asked the S.N.O, not to order the firing to begin until I can assure him on Your Excellency’s behalf that it can be done without any danger to people or animals« U,E„ A. G. clear of people and animals for a distance ofTelegram (P). Prom Political, Auwait. To Resident, Bushire 0 No. 192. Dated 6th March 1928. Do you get the British Unofficial Wireless Press from Rugby and see the exaggerations which appear daily. In case you do not, the actual words of a proclamation said to have been issued by Ibn Sa'ud are given in to-day’s, in which he describes the peoples of Trans-Jordania, 'Iraq and Kuwait as ''Exiles of Islam”, and ends up with the words ’’March to Victory! Allah will help you!' They presumably get this from some correspondent'in 'Iraq and unless it can be stopped tXxmt this sort of thing will make your task much more difficult if a meeting ever does take place.Telegram (C) Fromm Resident, Bushire. To Political, Kuwfcit* No. 317 Dated 6th March 1928. I am rather In the dark at present. The last news X have is that the Wahhabis are In force on the Kuwait front.wr. Is this true? Telegram (0) From Political, Kuwait. To Resident, Bushire. No. 193 Dated 6th March 1928. Your telegram No. 317. See my 185 and 187. Latest informa' tion is that the Kutair have temporarily broken up and there is no news of a concentration of other tribes on this frontier as yet, but very little news coming in.Telegram (C) SECRET From Political, Kuwait. To Resident, Bushire; repeated to Highcoma, Baghdad. No. 194 Dated 7th March 1928, I hear that 1 All Abu Shuwairibat of the Birzan subsection of the Buraih Mutair, one of the seceders from the Ikhwan who caused so much trouble by raiding into Majd until moved from the frontier by the ’Iraq Government in 1925* ^ as arrived here* Telegram (P) From Political, Kuwait* To Resident, Bushire; repeated to Highcoma, Bagndad* No. 197* Dated ?th March 1928. My telegram No. 194. The Shaikh Of Kuwait tells me that a minor shaikh of the ’AJman in his service has been approached by ’Ali Abu Shuwairibat, who, representing himself as speaking on King Faisal’s behalf, urged him to be ready to raid into Najd, as before long the King himself would be leading a force there. The Shaikh says that he is taking the necessary steps to pre vent his intrigues from causing trouble. No. 198-5. Political Agency, Kuwait. ?th March 192^. A copy of the above telegrams is forwarded herewith, with compliments, to:- The Senior Naval Officer in the Persian Gulf, H.M.S. Emerald. Captain de Gaury, Kuwait,Telegram (C) From Political, Kuwait, lo Resident, Bushire; repeated to Highcoma and Nasiriyah. No. 196 . Dated 7th March 1928. Arrivals from Riyadh say Ibn Hithlain was there when they left and Ibn Humaid was at Ghafcghat. Ibn Sa’ud had sent the latter ammunition but not rifles and had refused to send his son. I am arranging to examine them myself.Tele&amp;ram Prom To ( 0 ). Political, Kuwait* Resident, Bahrain; repeated to Highcoma, Baghdad &amp; Special, N&amp;uiriyah* No* 2CC. Dated (\,h March ;928. My telegram No*1^6. I have examined the most intelligent who is a retainer of the Shaixh of Kuwait and considered * reliable. Ke has teen on leave in (lasina whence he returned via Riyadh. Left Riyadh 23rd February. Ibn Hithlain was going to spend all Ramadhan in Riyadh* Half al-Fuqm of the Sahabah sept of the Muwahah subsection of the 'Ilwah Mutair was also there but no other Ikhwan shaikhs * / Ibn Humaid had not visited Ibn Sa’ud but had been corres ponding with hlifi. He had demanded that Ibn Saud should send a son or other close relative and his standard with the Ikhwan force, but this Ibn Sa’ud absolutely refused to do, saving that it would mean aaa regular war with British, and that we would institute a* blockade of all his ports and starve them out. He also refused a request for rifles but sent hin 3 j boxes of ammunition, 10,000 dollars, 200 camel loads of dates and rice, and other presents, and said he wished him well. Ibn Hums.id was s?.id to be leaving Ghatghat for Shaqra, yO miles south of Artawiyah, on the 25th February, and was inviting all to meet there for a huge raid* The 7th &amp;as the date fixed for the concentration but they might not actually move before the 23rd y#be»**»ry. He thinks the ’AJman and Karb are. quiet at present and that the only tribes involved so far are the 'Utaibah and of course the Mutair. He avoided the latter on his way but herd thej were some where south of Safah and that Dawish had gone to visit Ibn Humaid to try and get Ibn Sa'ud to send son and standard. He heard that they lost 75 men killed and died of wour p in the fight with the Kuwait forces on 29 th JanuaryTelegram (G). From Admintor, Basrah. To Political, Kuwait. No. 0/253. Dated ?th March 1923. Have you any confinflation of the report current here that Ibn Sa'ud has proclamed a jihad against Kuwait, Iraq and Trans-Jordania? Telegram (C). From Political, Kuwait. To Admintor, Basrah. No. 203. Dated 8th March 1928. Your telegraju No. C/253. All recent reports indicate that Ibn Sa’ud has definitely refused to send his son and his standard with the Ikhwan forces, as demanded by Ibn Humaid, but that he has been persuaded to authorize raiding and even to issue ammunition. According to the latest reports only the 'Utaibah and the Mutair are involved so far, all other tribes being quiet, which is more reassuring.Letter No.204 dated 3th March 1928 from P.A. H.E. Shaikh Ahmad al-Jabir aa-Subah,G.I.E,, J , Kuwait, to 1 Ruler of Kuwait. A.O. The Senior Naval Officer wishes to test the new gun emplacement between Towers 25 and 26 by firing the gun from it to-morrow, Friday, at half past four ^rabic. The ^un will be fired in the direction indicated to Khan Banaaur * a Salih the day before yesterday, i.e. towards the new buildings to the MMEtxMt east of Dimnah, and as it is a larger gun than the other a larger piece of ground must be Kept clear. For this one a plot of ground 2000 dhlra' a broad should be Kept absolutely clear of oen and animals for a distance of five miles. 1 shall be grateful if Y.E. will give orders for this to be done, and will instruct some person who can be trusted to see that it has been done to meet me there shortly before the appointed time to report to me that the ground is clear, so that I can tell the officer in charge that he can fire without danger. I shall be grateful if you will let me Know the name of the person whom you appoint for this duty before hand. U.E. /Telegram (0). From Political, Kuwait. To Resident, Bahrain. No. 211. Dated 10th February 1^23. My telegram No. 1?2. Kowcol has been increased by anotner section of Armoured Oars (i.e. three armoured cars and four armed Fords) which arrived here yesterday evening, Friday, 9th March. Telegram (CJ). From Political, Kuwait. To Resident, Bushire. No. 215. Dated 10th March 1928. My telegram No. 211. Under instructions from Akforce the armoured cars and four armed Fords have left here temporarily for a reconnaissance on the other side of the Batin. Iney wil be away about four days.Traaslation of letter of icth Marcn ^^8 froa P.A.,Kuwait To H.S.ohaiKl'i. Aiiiiad al-j£blr ae-3ub Ih,0.I.E. ,fluler of Kuwait. After compliments. The b°arero of this letter, Saiwan bln Majid and Khazzar bin ’Anqud, have identified 47 donkeys and 12 sheep belonging to the ’Asmi Juwarin and 3 donkeys and ?S sheep belonging to the Tuyus Juwarin respectively, from amongst thoee abandoned by the raiders and now being kept oy Your Excellency at Jahrah, for which the owners are very grateful to Your Excellency. I shall be grateful if Your Excellency will issue instructions for the animals In question to be handed over to them. Telegram (dode). Prom Political, Kuwait. To Admintor, Basrah. No. 2\Z. Dated toth March 1923. Saiwan bln Majid and Khazzar bln 'Anqu$, who are both known to de Gaury’s nan, have identified 4y donkeys and 12 sheep belonglrg to the ’Asmi Juwarfn and 3 donK&lt;*ys and 15 sheep belonging to the Tuyiis Juwarfn respectively from amonget the animals abandoned b&gt; raiders and brought Into Jahrah. I have asxed the Shaikh to have the animals in question handed over to them. The men have been instructed to proceed direct to the camp of Shaikh Nasir al-^abit at Birjislyah. No. 214-3. Political Agency, Kuwait. 10th March 1923. A oopy ol the above correspondence is forwarded to Japtain G. S. H. R. V. de Gaury, S.S.O., Ko.7col, with reference to his memorandum No. I/p3? of to-day’s date. lit. —s^O&gt;v. , Political Agent, Kuwrxt.By 7/ir e ler. ^irn^l frora R .A. No 1/93^ 10/3. To:-Aviation Baghdad repeated Ak: Buf col. (Copy to the politics. the Senior Naval Officer in the Persian Gulf and operator to show O.O.Nowcol inmedia-tely s.fter sending) vr ora:-Be Gaury Kuwait. Man appears reliable who arrived here 9/3 frora Riyadh states orders Ataibah raiders frora Ibn TT umaid to be in area Marrat(20 miles South East of c haqra in Washra)to al Ithla(in as Sirr south of Buraidah exact location unknown but headquarters Shaikh Ibn Sharrar outlying section of Bani Abdullah,Buraih,Mutair,query al Athla S5 miles West of Shaqra) be tween JOth and T5th Raraa.than( 2nd to 7th T r arch approxiraa.te). Dated 10th March 1^2S, Special Service Officer's teleferaai No.# I 932 of 1 Oth March The man apparently left in the same party as the man referred to in my telegram No.200 byt was delayed on the Telegram (G). Prom Political, Kuwait To Resident, Bahrain No 216 to Aviation Baghdad. Begins, x x x x X X X X X X X X X X . Ends wayTelegram (G) To From Resident, Bahrain# Secretary of State for the Colon es; repeated to Delhi, B*6h&lt;iad # Jerusalem, Political, Kuwait* No 3.T Dated 8th March (received 9th March) My telegram dated 28th February. Shaikh ’Abdullah's mfissenter has returned* He says that Xbn Humaid, chief 0! the ’Utalbah, has called out his men to a destination un known ana that they have marched out with banners* This news, which he obtained from members from the ‘Utaibah, If true is serious, uj the ‘Utaibah are the most numerous tribe of Ikhwan* Their haoitat is G-hatghat, one march from Riyadh, and westward towards Mecca* I bn Hums, id visited Ion Sa‘ud last year with an unnecessary large retinue* This year he has not visited him at all* The messenger heard no mention of a 11had or any other news* No* 2i6-S, Pclitijal Agency, Kuwait* with compliments to:- The Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, H.M*S* Emerald* Captain G*S.H*R*V* de Gaury, 3*5.0«, Ko^col* 10th March 1928* A copy of the above telegram is forwarded herewith Political Agent, KuweitTo Telegram (P). Prom Hi^hcoma, Baghdad* Resident, Bushlre; repeated No. 4y-f3. Dated ^th Mat»oh 19 ^ 6 . (Received Reference Kuwait telegram No.1^7. His Majesty ia much upcet that ’All Abu 3huwairlbit has oeen spreading rumours and making representations of the kind reported as ne had no authority to do so. He was merely sent to see Hilal al- J.’utairi, and &amp;et the latest news from him. His Majesty would like him cent back at once. Telegram (P). Prom Political, Kuwait. To Resident, iifikkix*; repeated to Hi&amp;hdoma, Baghdad. No. 2 \t. Dated 10th March 1^28. Ixjua Baghdad telegram No. 49 - 3 . I have conveyed King Faisal!!i wishes to the Bhaikh who has told him to tS°* No. 216-3. Political Agency, Kuweit. herewith, with compliments, to:- The Senior Naval Officer in the Persian Gulf, H.M,3.Emerald. Captain G. S. H. R. V. de G&amp;ury, S.5.G., Kowcol. ICth March 1928. A copy of the above correspondence i*i forwarded Lt.—Col , Political A&amp;ent, KuwaitTelegram (P). Prom Colonial Office, London. To Political, Kuwait. No. Nil. Dated 9th March 19^3. Reference telegram No.l-T from Resident, Bahrain. Please repeat the S.N.O.'s reference which I have not got to me and to Baghdad. Telegram (P). From Political, Kuwait. To Chapelries, London; repeated to Baghdad. No. 219. Dated 10th March 1928. Your telegram of 9th March. S.N.O.'s telegram No.lOJO of 6th March to the Resident in the Persian Gulf Begins. A report which I made to the Commander-in-Chief at his direction contained the following. The forces now available entrenched behind the strong wall which entirely surrounds une uown ana supported by t in my °P lnion to defend the town against an attack by Arabi only armed with rifles. I desire, however, to point out that if it be considered tl the situation demands that Kuwait be garrisoned durin* a Period of unrest which may last for some time, an infantry -attalion supportea by artillery or ships* guns could best perform this duty. Ends.Telegram (P). From Resident, Bahrain* To S. of S. for Colonies; repeated to Delhi, Baghdad* Jerusalem, Cairo, Jiddah and Kuwait. No. 7-T. Dated icth March 1928. Baghdad telegram No. 139 . According to a Dawasir shailch who has Just arrived here Ibn Humaid is going to meet Faisal ad- D&amp;wXsh at Artawlyah immediately. He still hopes to obtain Ibn 8a’ud's permission to raid, but says that some other way must be found if it cannot be obtained. No. 220-5. Political igency, Kuwait. A copy of the above telegram is forwarded Herewith, with compliments, to:- The Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, H.M.S, Emerald. Captain G. 5. H. R. V. de Gaury, S.S.O., Kowcol. 10 th March 1928 . Lt. —C o 1« $ Political \gwnt, Kuwait.Tela&amp;ram (p) # From To No. Dated Resident, Bahrain. Secretary of State for the Colonies; repeated to Delhi for favour of communication to C.-in-C.,East Indies. Baghdad « « .. „ „ j, ruaaleffl&gt; aBd Kuwait « « \ -T.' 9th March 19^3* ** S . N . 0 . Telegram 1030 from the Senior Naval Officer to the Comaundei in-Chief, East Indies, reached me badly mutilated. I depend on ships to keep me informed of what is happening on the Truoial Coast, and at the present crlsia it is most important that we should be informed of this, and the squadron being rendered immobile by the defence of Kuwait makes the work difficult. There does not appear to be much chance of the crisis terminating in the immediate future, and I therefore venture to suggest that a battalion of infantry with a strong compliment of machine guns and the necessary artillery be sent to Kuwait. I am requesting the Senior Naval Officer to telegraph the length of the perimeter of defence to the Naval Commander-in-Chief and the Chief of the General Staff, Simla, direct. If it be preferred to postpone taking this action until more definite news is received, I suggest that a Royal Indian Marine ship be ordered to the Persian Gulf and placed at my disposal. If there be any choice I would prefer R.I.M.S, Clive as she has suitable accommodation. No. 224-S. Political Agency, Kuwait. 11th March 1928. A copy of the above telegram is forwarded herewith, with compliments, to the Senior Naval Officer,Persian Gulf, H.M.S. Emerald, Kuwait. Political Agent, Kuwait.Telegram (en clair). Prom Special, Buscol. To Akforce; rd. Nufcol, Kowcol, S No. J/Bus/6. Dated Hth March 1928. « Tribesman said Dhaflr Just arrived from Umm Rudhumma area cons firms reports that Harb in flight south-westwards. ^Iso con firms reports Jaden Mishari (Kathlr) and a small following Dhaffrin in flight northwards from Khurmah Amnah. Majority Dhafir proceeding to Join Ajami. Scouts of unknown force k*jd reported to have fired upon Jadaan Mishari &amp; Dhafir near kXax Khuroah Amnah. General tribal opinion large combined raid Dawish and Ibn Humaid approaching border. Probable route of raiders rumoured via Rukhaimiyah towards Busalyah &lt;k JoKha simultaneously. Propose to proceed with cars tomorrow to Aqubba in order to gain further tribal reports if possible &amp; await at Rukhaimiyah for aircraft to convey me Hafar. Instructions awaited. Telegram (C). Prom Political, Kuwait. To Resident, Bahrain. No. 22b. Dated 12th March 1928. Special,Buacol, telegram Wo.J/Bu»/6 of nth March. Begina. Tribeamen x x x x x simultaneously. Enda. la view of previous Information It looks to me like a preaa- ture panic on the part of the tribes./ I w Telegram (en clair). Proa Special, Nasiriyah. I To Kowcol for Political, Kuwait# No. I/A/2. No Dated 12th March 1928. A^ent reporta Ibn Huaaid and Dawiah camped at Qaraa \o milea south of Safah and Habafc 25 miles south-east of Safah seven days ago. Gan you confirm. Telegram {G ). From Political, Kuwait. To Resident, Bahrain. No. 226. Dated 12th March 1928. .Telegram No. I/A/2 of 12th March from Special, Nasirlyah, Begins. x x . x x x x x .Ends. I have received no information here to confirm this.£/2&gt; Letter No.22? of 12th Larch 1928 from the P.A., Kuwait,' Vo H.E* Shaikh Ahmad al-Jabir as-Subah, C.I.E., Ruler of Kuwait A.C, I have the honour to inform Y,E* that I have received a telegram from the Intelligence Officer at Buaaiyah that according to a Dhafirl Just arrived from Umm Radhamah the Harb are in flight south-westwards. Jad'an Miahari and a small following are in flight northwards from Khurmah al-Amnah. Scouts of an unknown force are reported to have fired upon Jadaan, Mlsharl and the Dhaflr near Khurmah al~ Amnah. It is the general opinion amongst the tribes that a large combined raiding party of Dawlah and Ibn Humaid is approaching the border, and that the probable route which the raiders will take is via Rukhaimiyah towards Baswah and Jaukhah simultaneously. I have aiso Just received another telegram from the Intelligence Officer at Naslriyah that he has received a report that Ibn Humaid and Dawish were camped at Qara*, 15 miles south of Safah, and at Habah seven days ago, I presume that Y.E. has heard nothing to confirm either S0 of these reports, which appear to me to be probably onle a premature panic on the part of the tribes, but which I am sending to Y 0 E 0 for what they are worth.Tele&amp;ram (P). Prom D Resident, Bahrain. To Political, Kuwait. No. 18 -T. Dated 11th March 1928. Telegram No. 517-S from the Government of India. Begins. The General Staff want to bring their Intelligence informa tion about Kuwait up to date, and will be grateful for a detailed report by mail on the landing facilities for troops, heavy vehicles and animals, the best tactical line of defence to cover the town, condition of water and fuel supplies,and camping sites. Ends. Please comply, adding details regarding any measures which may already have been taken. D.O. No. 228-S. 12th March 1928. I enclose herewith a copy of the Resident’s telogrun No. 18 -T of yesterday's date, about which I spoke to you this morning. As you wilx see the General Staff, Army Head quarters, India, want a detailed report on Kuwait,deal ing with various points, some of which you can help me with enormously, if you will be so Kind. I shall as* you about it verbally when next we meet. Captain H. G. C. Franklin, R.N. # S.N»0.,P.G. # H.: .S. Emerald.71 Tour telegram of to-day No .229 The misunder 3 landing was mine Telegram (P) From Resident, Bahrain. To Political, Kuwait. No. 20-T. Dated 12th March 1928. Your telegram No.213&lt;&gt; It seems to me tnat the action was a transgression of the undertakings which I have given to Ibn Sa’ud on behalf of His Majesty's Government, as the Batin is the frontier line. Telegram (P) e From Politicals Kuwait. To Resident, Bahrain. No. 229- Dated 13th March 19^8. Your telegram No. 20-T. I do dot see in what way it was, unless you have given one after that contained in your telegram No.22b, which I have not seen, as surely our under taking was conditional on his giving an assurance which so far as I know he has not yet given. As a matter of fact it would have been difficult for me to do anything even if I had thought it was, as the Batin is the frontier between ’Iraq and Kuwait - not between Najd &amp; either, and any violation of the frontier was not from Kuwait at all but from ’Iraq. Besides, would not telegram No.J01 from the Secretary of State for the Colonies have made it difficult for me to interfere. If you do not agree with me please let me have instructions. Telegram (P). From Resident, kaaAiKsx Bahrain. To Political, Kuwait. No 26-T. Dated 13th March 1928.\ \ Telegram (P). From Political, Kuwait, To Resident, Bahrain. No. 230. Dated 13th March 1928. Your telegram No. 1$-F. I am doing so. Do you wish me to post the report to the Chief of the General Staff direot so as to avoid delay? Telegram (P). From Resident, Bahrain. To Political, Kuwait. No. 2?-T. Dated 13th March 1928 . Your No. 230. Yes, please do so.Wirelesa (en cla.ir) nn Froai Garfive Recco To Akforee; repeatc?d to Buseol &amp; Kowool Hour 1615 Dated 12th March 1928 Arrived Hafar 1330 G.M.T, Founf party of men and camels at wells. Approached them with armoured cars. The party ran down Batin. One man opened fire so cars opened fire. One man xbmxA' wounded and could not be found. One man taken prisoner and six camels destroyed. Am ascertaining who these men are.Please send S.SoOo as early as possible, prisoner has information of the raiders. Remainder of party got away owing to ground. Suggest sending flight at dawn tomorrow to reconnoitre if the prisoner gives information. Telegram (C). From Political, Kuwait. To Resident, Bahrain. No. 232. Dated 13th March 1928. Armoured cars fired on by a party at Hafar al-Batln yesterday afternoon, Monday. They, opened fire in return, wounded one man who could not be found, and captured one prisoner. The rest escaped. The prisoner has information of raiders but had not been examined properly when message despatched. No information received regarding movement towards the Kuwait area.Telegram (C) Froai * Political, Kuwait. r i2P To Resident, Bahrain. No. 233. Dated 14th March 1928. My No. 232. Wireless messa&amp;e from Buscol sent yesterday afternoon, Tuesday, begins Captured tribesman Alihaiyah subsection of the Jiblan Mutair reports the following. Begins: Twenty tents of his sub section are camped approximately 20 miles south west of Hafar. After the Safah air raid Dawish went to 'Ausajiyah near Dahal Abu Naichlah north of Sufaiyah and thence via Artawiyah to visit Ibn Humaid. Dawish proposed a combined raid after Ramadnan, but Ibn Humaid insisted on immediate action. The raid fe rumoured to be very large, including li&amp;g flags of the shaikhs of the Mutair, 'Utaibah, Harb and Shammar Aslaa 0 The main raid is generally understood to be making for Basrah via Hafar al~3atin and now reported one ana a half days journey from Hafar al-Batin. The following snnkhs are m « n t,ioned as raid leaders: Sultan bin Humaid of the 'Utaibah, Jasir bin Lami and Faisal ad-Dawish of the Mutair, Mish’al Tawalah of the Shammar Aslam and Muhsin al- Firm of the Harb. The proposed attack on Basrah is in direct opposition to wishes of Ibn Sa'ud. Xx** End of prisoner's statement. The prisoner is youn ft and uninteliegent but appears to have reported tribal information as locally understood. Telegram (C) From PD&amp;ifatical, Kuwait. To Resident, Bahrain* No. 234 Dated 14th March 1928. Telegram No. I 130 of 13th March from Akforce. Begins: Following is a complete precis of information received from Special, Buscol, to-day. Jad'an Mishari (Kathir Dhafir) j^st arrived at Huk states that he was raided five days aRO when&amp; camped at Khurmah Amnah with 40 tents. Raid took place at sunset and information as to number of raiders , raid lossa number of killed etc. is at present lacking. Raid is stated to have been of Harb origin though this information was received by Jad'an via Ghadan bin Nuqaiyiran of the Ikhwan Dhafir, who though camped near Jad’an was himself untouched. It seems possible that Jad'an might wish to implicate the Harb, but if true tends to conffcm the Jihad rumours. One Hamad Hiss (Ikhwan Dhafir) visited Jad'an about three days prior to .he raid and advised immediate flight. He stated that all Najd was combined in Jihad against 'Iraq with Basrah as primary objective. This is said fco be in opposition of wishes of Ibn Sa'ud. Ends. Then follows information given in ;iy telegram No.Telegram (C)- From To No. Dated Political, Kuwait, Resident, Bahrain; repeated to Special, Nasiriyah 235. 14th March, 1928, I have Just seen a man of the Rashaidah tribe who is con- sidered reliable. He was at Jaryah on 3rd March and says that Ibn Shuqair was there then and there was no talk of his fcoing raiding again in the immediate future. He has no other information. No. 239-S Political Agency, Kuwait. 14th March 1928, A copy of the above telegram is forwarded herewith, with compliments, to S,S.O,, Kowcol, Kuwait. Lt.-Col,, Political Agent, KuwaitTelegram (C). From Political, Kuwait. Resident, Bahrain. No. 240. Dated 15 th March 1928 . Intercepted message No. G 6145 Officer, Salman. Begins. of 15th March from Intelligence Travellers from Aiwlj state Ibn Tawalah, 'AJmi Suwalt and other Dhaflr and Shammar camped round Aiwlj. They are afraid of Dawlsh and Ibn Humald. They heard Ibn Humald raiding but Ibn Sa'ud sent after him in endeavour to dissuade him. They left AlwlJ 9 th March and had then no definite Information of the approach of raiders. i2iM Telegram (P). From Secretary of State for the Colonies. To Political, Kuwait; rd. Baghdad,Jerusalem and P.R., Bahrain. No. 1^9 (No.44 to Jerusalem). Dated 14th March 1928. Please report any further Information which reaches you about the threatened raid by the 'Utaibah and Mutalr to me at once, repeating to Resident and to Baghdad and JerusalemTelegram (G). Prom To Political, Kuwait. S. of S* for Colonies; repeated to Resident,3ahrain ; Baghdad and Jerusalem. No. 243. Dated 15 th March 1928. Man from the village of Raudhah in the district of Sudalr, 94 miles north-west of Riyadh, who left there (Raudhah) on 7th March arrived here yesterday evening, Wednesday. He says that Ion Humaid started from Ghatghat according to programme, but only got as far as Shams (70 miles west by north of Riyadh) when he was overtaken by Khalid bin al-Wai (the member of the Sharffian family who joined the Ikhwan and is now one of the leauin^ Ikhwan in the Hijaz), who had arrived in Riyadh a few days earlier, and who now went to Ibn Humaid to try to dissuade him from acting contrary to the wishes of Ibn Sa f ud. He evidently suceeded in his mission, whether by pursuasion or threats, as on 3th March Ibn Humaid went back to Ghatghat. His standard was still at Shams but the general opinion was that the raid would no£ take place. He heard that Dawish was at Artawiyah and his standard about 25 miles south of Safah. No meeting between him and Ibn Humaid had taken place. The Shaikh of Kuwait says iihe man is known here and things he is reliable. His story, if true, explains why our air reconnaissances have seen no movements such as one would have expected from the statement of the prisoner recently captured, who evident^ ly had not heard of the change of plans. No. 244-S. Political Agency, Kuwait. 15th March 1928. A copy of the above telegram is forwarded herewith with compliments, to: The Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, H B M.S. Emerald. The Special Service Officer, Kowcol, Kuwait. l*t .-Colonel, Political Agent, Kuwait*Telegram (©n clair) 2^ From De Gaury, Kuwait. To Aviation, Baghdad No. 1/307 Dated 15th March 1928. Have confiUmed from entirely different eouroe to tnat mention ed in my 1/306 and 303 of to-day (l.o. from agent from Haea arrived by to-day*a mail boat) that Abulwal did in fact arrive in Riyadh on \ 4th February having travelled swiftly from Mecoi escorted by 130 camel riders and hoping to improve position ot Ibn Sa'ud. Agent received information from a wealthy merchant of Zilfi who had brought new cars to Ibn Sa'ud and passed JUdm! Abulwal on the road* Merchant had no news of subsequent developments but confirmed all that has been reported about intention of Ibn Humaid to raid and gifts of food, money and ammunition by Ibn Sa*ud, and refusal of arms and son as leader He believed Humaid intended to raid during or after Ramadhan but thought good ohance Ibn Sa'ud recover situation in time*Teiebraip (P) CONFIDENTIAL^-’ ^ Prom To Resident, Babrain* S« of S. for the Colonies; repeat Jerusalem, India, Cairo, Jiddah and No. 26 T •f'-'s-nr ’Isa Joint paramount shaikh of the Dawasir who left Riyadh about ten days a^o states that Ibn Sa’ud gave permission to the Mutair and ’Utaibah to raid but not to the south of Zubair. Other tribes asked to be allowed to Join them with a view to amassing plunder, but he told them they were not to .raid to tne north against ’Iraq. Ibn Hithlain said that he was in treaty with the Mutair and ’Utaibah, but was still refused permission to raid ’Iraq. He says that Ibn Sa’ud paid 8020 dollars on 9th March to Ibn Humaid. The Collector of Customs, Jubail, says that fts.1000 from Jubail Customs and an unknown quantity of rupees from Qatif Customs is still being distributed monthly to the Ikhwan tribesmen. ri No. 245-S. Political Agency, Kuwait. 15th March 1928. A copy of the above telegram is forwarded herewith, with compliments, to: The Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, H.M.S. Bmerald. The Special Service Officer, Kowcol, Kuwait. Lt: Colonel, Political Agent, Kuwait.Telegram (P). From S. of S* for Colonies, London To Resident, Bahrain; repeated to Ki No Nil Dated 15th March 1928 Your telegram of 13th February No.18. His Majesty's Govern ment see no objection to the machine guns and Lewis guns referred to in telegram No.439-S of 28th February from the Government of India being supplied to the Shaikh. If it Is desired to taice advantage of India's offer, please communi cate direct with them. -Tith regard to tanks: please let me have your views on the question of whether it could be ensured that they would be used for purposes of defence alone, and not for counter raiding. In the meanwhile I am enquiring into the price, delivery, etc. of armoured cars. I am told by the War Office that Whippet tanks are obsolete and that no other type of tank would be suitable. Telegram (P) From Political, Kuwait. To Resiaent, Bahrain. No. 246. Dated 16th March 1928. Colonial Office telegram of yesterday^ date. I presume that it would not be counted as ’’counter raiding” to pursue or cut off raiders into Kuwait territory and force them to disgorge plunder which they have captured from Kuwait subjects. If so, there would, in my opinion, be no fear of the armoured cars being put to an improper use, as the Shaikh could not possibly use them for purposes of aggr icti ithout the knowledge of the Political Agent. Shall I now speak to H. E. anent machine and Lwwis guns?T? Repe at el ^eIhi ghlad # Je rusale m, C airo,Jiiinh anl Kuwait, No, 'Oatei 38-T • 15th (receive! iJwL', ^rch 1^3, iiatedt news a relation of Governor of Hail who is here, is that Ihn Ga’ul ia afrai-l of British hlockate of Ports, He has fort)mien export of tales from Hasa ani is collecting all Rialh and Buraidah, News of this emhargo is c onfirmei. They state Ihn Sa’ud is not afraid of tribes but of British, Ibn oa’ui’s Agent sent him 30,000/- dollars from Bahrain \ few days ago* 'Ajman are still all round Jubail and not moving, Ibn Hitniain is still at Uadh, Ibn Ja’ul’s Agent here states motor cars which proceed® 1 Hath were new motor cars from Englani anl that Ibn 3a*ud J'ill not proceed to Mecca till after Idl that is till after a week. No. £49-S. • Political Agency, Kuwait, 16 th March 19^8, A copy of the above telegram 1 b forwarded herewith, with compliments, to:- The Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, Emerald, The Special Service Officer, Kuwait, ^--Lt, -Gol,, Political Agent, Kuwait, rTelegram (P) 2 .%° From Hi&amp;hcoma, Bagdad* To 3#of S* for Colonies; repeat To No. 66 (No. 162 to London) Dated 15th March 1923* Cairo, Jerusalem and Kuwait. ident» The following is a summary of the measures taken to meet the Ikhwan menace. (N.B. For R.A.F. and *Iraq Army dispositions see appendix to A*H.Q. R&amp;sum^ of Operations of 3rd March sent to Air Ministry)• (&amp;£ Aerodromes based on Kuwait, Shaibah, Salman, Busaiyah Ur with the co-operation of armoured cars are constantly patrolling the whole Najd frontier from the Persian Gulf to the Wadi al-Kharr to a depth of about fifty miles within Najd territory. There is an armoured train for the defence of the line from Basrah to Samawah* (b) The *Iraq Army, besides furnisning garrisons for the air bases in ^raq, is sending two companies to Shabichah. A half company of ’Iraq Infantry Is at Rutbah and another platoon is going tnere. A mobile column is being main tained in Baghdad ready for action at twelve hours notice. This consists of a cakalry regiment, a section of eight- teen pounders, a pack battery of light Howitzers and a battalion of ’Iraq infantry. (c) Captain Glubb has been appointed by the Ministry of the Interior to co-ordinate and supervise the movements of ’Iraq tribes in the whole frontier area. By his agency the shepherd tribes of ’Iraq have been withdrawn behind the line Busaiyah - Salman - Shabichah, and every effort is being made to withdraw the ’Iraq Bedouin sections which still remain outside tnls line in the same way. (d) The Ministry of the Interior has Increased the sub sidy of Shaikh Mahrut of tne ’Amarat section of the ’Anizah tribe from Rs. 3QCC to R8.15G0G a month to enable him to rally the ’Amarat for defence against a possibleattack and also to retain the allegiance of as many of the Dahamishah sub-section as possible. The Ministry of Defence is also considering a proposal for the forma tion of two companies of armed Fords (forty to fifty cars all told) for the defence of the 'Amarat. (e) The Ministry of Defence is preparing a scheme for the formation of a camel corps about strong to be composed of •Iraq regular troope and tribesmen combined under the control of the Air Officer Commandfeng. (f) The Ministry of Interior have purchased Chevrolet cars for use in conjuxiction with the Diwaniyah Camel Corps Police for scouting purposes. By day they will reconnoitre in front of the line of posts, and will withdraw behind the line by wifcfc night• mu it’ umuiuiu• uuiuuuuiuui 1 ’luiiiuaiuu No. 248-S. Political Agency, Kuwait. 16 th March 1920. A copy of the above telegram is forwarded here with, with compliments, to:» The Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, H.M.S. Emerald. The Special Service Officer, Kuwait. Political Agent, Kuwait.Telegram (C). Prom Adnlntor, Basrah. To No. Political, Kuwait. 1/284. Dated 12th Larch 1028. Zubairi states that Sultan bin Ibrahim al-Kulaib Is a friend of the Shaikh of Kuwait and that he brought informa* tion recently to Zubair that Ibn Sa'ud had practically proclaimed a jihad . Can you please check the Zubair state ment. Telegram (C). Prom Political, Kuwait. To Admintor, Basrah. No. 238. Dated 14th March 1928. Your telegram dated 12th March No. C/284. I have made inquiries and do not think Sultan, whom I Know well, had l anything to do with it. Are you quite sure of the name? If not please verify it, as there is another person with a rather similar name regarding whom I am now making inquirier 'J7 W -- - _ - ^ '7~e/e&lt;fTj.rH(C ). / 3J' orTl A d Vi ttssraA C/ja/Telegram From To (P). Resident, Political Bahrain. Kuwait. No. Dated 14th March 1923 (repetition asKed for reed.17th) Your telegram No. 229 , last paragraph. Jolonial Office telegram No.lCI would not prevent your telegraphing any political objection which the action might have to me or protesting if the matter be urgent.No. ,03-3. Political Agency , Kuwait. 13th ICarch /^N ■ ■ A copy of t 0 lafc,raia No. 47—T dated, the t / th March ly'jid from the Hon ble the Political Resident in the Peroi-^n Gulf is forwarded herewith, witli cottpllaente, to The Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, iflerald. The Special Service Officer, Kuwait.Telei^rim (C) From Resident, Bahrain* To S. of S* for Colonies; repeated to Delhi,BattaUw* Jerusalem, Cairo, Jiddah and Kuwait* No. 47-T. J’al'zcl Letter from Xbn Sa'ud received in which he expresses re^et at what has happened, recapitulating events and stating that while the Mutair were acting in a way of which he could not approve, at no time were they beyond power in hii own country, that he had Dawish ringed and boycotted with his food supplies stopped so that he had to try and get food at Kuwait, but that the conduct of the 'Iraci people in invading his country and bombing innocent and guilty alike had forced his hand, had made it impossible for him to finish punishment he was ready to inflict. He regretted that the impatient ones had got, out of his control and were proceeding somewhere out of his ken. /B5S That he had now ^^.sirsd Information as to what was happen- Included In the bombing. That the only way that he oould see out of the difficulty was (t) the maintenance of the 'Uqair Protocol and the destruction of Bueaiyah; (2) the mutual refusal to shelter criminals; (3) the prevention of officials from mixing-with the tribes and causing sedition; and (4) the British Government to hold responsible those who had caused the happenings on the 'Iraq frontier and punish them. That he agrees that a settlement could better be reached bj conversation with the Resident than by correspondence, and that if the Resident saw no objection to the meeting even at a time that he was unable to arrest the reoels,who •re headstrong, he was ready to fix a time and place for a meeting to resolve the present difficulties. Ends. Letter is long. Full text follows.CONFIDENTIAL. c23*-^ No. 257-S. Political Agency, Kuwait. I^th Maroh 1928 The Hon* ble the Political Resident in the Perelan Qulf, BAHRAIN. Intelligence. MEMORANDUM. In continuation of my ’neiaoranduai No. 168 -S dated the 5th March 1928, I enclose herewith a copy of the under mentioned Intelligence reports by Captain G.S.H.R.V. de Gaury, M.C., Special Service Officer, Kuwait, which are the only ones which can be of any Interest to you. Lt.-Col., Political Agent, Kuwait. No. 1/289 dated 6-3-23 No. 1/29» it 7-3-28 No. 1/305 M ip-3-23 No. 1/306 « 15-3-23 No. 1/307 « 15-3-28 No. 1/931 it 9-3-23 No. 1/299 w 12 - 3-28■f I 'EMERALD at Kuwait, 18th March 1928. I am forwarding copies of two cypher messages I have receded as they mjQr be of interest to you.From The C.in C«, East indies. To........The Air Officer Commanding, Bagdad. Bate......17th March 1928. No.... With regard to the detention of H.M.Ships ' 'EMERALD', 'LUPIN' and 'CROCUS' at Kuwait and immobility of these ships consequent on landing of officers and men in defence of that place against expected raids request I may be informed whether estimated date can be given —v when force landed will be relieved in order that ships may once more become mobile and available for duty elsewhere should occasion arise. 1312/17.————Cojiv of Message . Prora Admiralty. To •C*in C., East Indies, repeated to S.N.O.,T? # G, Date. 17th March 1928. Bray letter has been received from Colonial Office pointing out tfcsfc political inadvisability of despatch of troops assuraraed Kuwait and requesting in view of the possibility that the present crias will shortly be relieved approval may be given for tetention on shore of 'EMERALD'S' landing parties. This is approved. 1504./17.Telegram (F)* From Political, —BM Kuwait. To Resident, Bahrain* No. 238. Dated 19th Maroh 1928. My telegram No.245. I venture to suggest the desirability of taking up the question of Lewis guns and machine guns as soon as possible. We will never again have as good an opportunity of getting the men trained in their use as now that His Majesty's ships and the R.A.F. are here. Now that the situ ation seems to be Improving theywlll probably not be here much longer, and in the interests of political control we do not want to have to keep them longer than necessary. Kuwait can be trusted to defend itself sooner with these weapons than without uhem. Telegram (P). From Political, Kuwait. To Reaidaut, Bahrain. No. 259* Dated l9th March 1928. I learn from the S.N.O. that the Naval G.-ln-O. has wired to the A.OoG., Baghdad, asking if he can estimate how long ships are likely to be kept immobile in the defence of Kuwait. The A.Q.C. sent a non-committal reply.Tel#&amp;raa (P). Proa R&amp;i»ld9nt, BahraiTi* To Politioal, Kuwait. No. i?-T. Dated tyth Karon 1928. Your telo^raa No. it is sure to taUt# soao time to get the Lewis guns ^nd machine guns fro® India, and the Shipe and Air Poroe will presuoiaoly hare leTt by then. I suggest that if the Senior Naval Officer will a&amp;ree, a pnrty be trained now with the Ships* guns, as otherwise they will have to go to Indi«i or Iraq to be trained. OOOOOOOOOOOOOOOOOOOUOOOOOOOOOOOQOOOOOOOOQOOOOOOCOOOOOOOOOOOC Telegram (P)« B'rom Political, Kuwait* To Resident, Bahrain* No 31 264 , Dated 21st March 1928 . - Your ^7-T. Proposal has been agreed to oy and a party starts training on Mondayc The prospect of having the Lewis guns and machine guns comes as a great relief to the Shaikh, as he holds the opinion that Ibrx Sa’ud will never again establish effective control over the Ikhwan tribes.No Prom Resident, Bahrain. '±° Political, Kuwait „ ^ 63 T Dated Zf 21et March 1928. Your No. 239« I Know. A.0.0s e wire was repeated to me. OOOOOOOwC w wwC C C OC, C v v. ^CPOOOOOOOOOOOOOOOOOOOOOOOOOOOOOOOOO Telegram (P) n Prom Political, Kuwait. Dated 22nd March 1928. On 22nd March an air reconnaieance is being carried out from here to Jaryah. The A.O.Oe tel±s me he has prohibited all bombing except against obvious raiders or if fired on, and to minimize the chance of the latter he has ordered machines to keep very high. To Resident, Bahrain 26 ?. Noy'\ Prom. ..••• Air Officer Conmiandins, Bagdad. To ..C.in C., East Indies, repeated Resident Bahrein. Date 20th March 1928. Estimate of duration of present emergency is not possible. Present information indicates Jehad unlikely and if it does not materialise, Kuweit, with such assistance as can be given by the aircraft and armoured cars should be able to look after itself and would not require the permanent presence of the disembarked crews of H.M.Ships. Periodical visits of H.M.Ships to Kuweit would produce good moral effect on inhabitants and I therefore suggest that one or more ships should carry out such visits and should always be available to proceed to Kuwait to meet and emergency. Prom.•....S.N.O., i*G, To C.in C.E.I., repeated Political Resident. Date......21st March 1928. No... 0840/21. 1 entire]y concur with the opinion contained in the Air Officer Commanding^ message of 20th March, which expresses my own view on the matter at this juncture. Prom S.N.O.P.G. To Political Resident, Bahrein. Date. 21st March 1928. No 2000/21. I am sorry to ask again but I cannot hold on more than two days longer about 'CROCUS', fl} am quite prepared to send her to Basra now if you would agree to that measure. Prom P°litical Resident, Bahrein, To.•....••S.N.O.P.G. Date..... ,22nd March 1928. Your telegraja 2000, 'CROCUS'. Very good. I agree,iLuwait, 22 nd karcn 1928 A p eLt-fr*- Ccf If tne Snai^n is inclined to tcute tne maciaine and lewis gun instruction really seriously and maintain always some men trained in tne weapons tne following might interest you. hx-lattalion i^acnine and Lewis gun Instructor of 1st B’n tne Iraq uevies. i.amar ibn Biamar.now agriculturist near ^ualet Salad, under Snaixn natim as Sainoud,man of excellent cnaracter and appearance,good instructor,father was Shai^n of the hait barri Bani kalicn.(Banx was corporal; Snli^ar ibn bnarraisn t now agriculturist also near ^alat Saian,well-trained gunner and decent man.(ranx was Ser t -eant) ^a'afar ^ijuas is a good man who would do you well and collect and bring if required a couple of otners sucn as those mentio ned . iou xnow the ^rab ^evy B’n nad ratner different traditions to tne Iraq ^rmy and was trained umer nritisn officers for aboa seven ^ears. xhe men mentioned were all i believe tnoroughly respectable nangers-on of tne Amarah snai^ns before tne Var. 1 suppose tney would want ratner good pay to come so far out if tney were wanted would come 1 am sure in answer to a letter from me witn conditions stated. oa’afar ibn aibas,Bani nam tribe,now small trader at ri.marah,first class instructor,very decent man. nx Macnine and newis gun instructors.Telegram (C) From Political, Kuwait To Resident, Bahrain No. 268. Dated 23rd March 1928. My telegram No. 2\5, Gars returned p„m«, 22nd March less two « expected this morning, Friday. HoMcSo Grocus left to coal this morning 23rd March. fififihhnnfthhhhfiflhnfinf.nnfilnflf.5!nnnnnnnnhd/if ilftflflflhFiftf Telegram (G). Hrom Politicals Kuwait. To Resident, Bahrain. No. 269 - Dated £3rd March 1928. My No»268. All cars now in. Kowool is now being reduced to original strength and the additional section of Armoured Gars referred to in my NOe211 leaves for Basrah this afternoon, Friday, 22nd March. hflhfihhhhFinhnnhhfLnfmh^hhnhhhfifihhnfifinhhnhhhhmiiihhhrimifhiflhhhhhhi Telegram (P). From Political, Kuwait. To Resident, Bahrain. No. 270. Dated 23rd March 1928 . My telegram No 0 264„ Captain de Gaury, the S.S.O., who used to be in the 'Iraq Levies has given me the names of a few Machine 3a Lewis Gun Instructors of the First Battalion (now disbanded) whom he knows personally and can recommend, and who, he thinks, would willingly enter the Shaikh's service. As this seems to be a good solution of the training problem, I purpose suggesting it to the Shaikh- (C) /^cuo/uhjz A4_y Mo 2&amp;Sr. /S.A1.S' 7'e^cno^^ &amp;UasZ4~ )Telegram (G) Proa Political, Kuwait# To S. of S# for Colonies; repeated to Resident, Bahrain, Baghdad and Jeruselam# No. 271• Dated 24th March 1928. Man of the ’Utaibah tribe domiciled in Kuwait, who went to see relatives at Jaryah, were he spent 16 th March, arrived here yesterday evening, Friday. Ibn Shuqair and Fuqm were at Jaryah when he was there. He heard that Dawish was at Artawiyah, but does not Know about the other Mutair shaiKhs. He heard that Ibn Hithlain was at Slu'ar# He heard that some*- time before he arrived there messengers had come from Ibn Humaid inviting Ibn Shuqair to Join him in a raid, but the latter had refused • He talks of Ibn Humaid as raiding now, but his information appears to be old. Man seems truthful but not well informed. hhnfthhfthfthhhhnhhfihhhfihhhfihhhhfthnhhhhhhhhhfihhhnhhfihrifihnhnfihhhf No. 272-S. Political Agency, Kuwait 24th March 1928 A copy of the above telegram is forwarded herewith, with compliments, to:- The Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, H»M»S. Emerald. The Special Service Officer, Kuwait, Lt # —Col# , Political Agent, Kuwait.m Telegram (C). Prom Political, Kuwait To 3• of S. for the ( 3. of S* for the Colonies; repeated to Resident, Bahrain, and to Baghdad and Jerusalem. 274. . No Dated *4th March I 92 B* Msaaen^er of Ibn Sa’dd's a^ent, who took the Hi&amp;h Jornmis- sloner for Iraq's letter No. 3.0# J79 dated Jrd February, arrived at Riyadh on 7th March, and left there with reply v which I am posting to the High Joaiiissioner for 'Iraq) on 17th March, and arrived hex»e this evening, Saturday. Ibn Huaaid was at Majma'ah In the Sudair. He had started out to raid, but Ibn al-Wai and Sa’iid al-'Arafah had per suaded him not to. ^Then the messenger left it was not quite certiin vhether the raid would take place or not, but the probability tfae that it would not. On ois way to Riyadh he met Ibn Hithlcain returning to Sarar, where he is at present. Da»fsh io t,*nerftlly supposed to be at Art i»Xyah, but some say he is in the Sununan. He passed throueh Jp.ryah on the aist March, and Ibn Shunair was there then. On the 22nd March he saw the six aeroplanes proceeding t Jaryah. He talks freely * but it must be remembered whose servant he is. with, with oonrlicents, to:- The Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, H.M.3. Emerald. The Special Service Officer, Kuwait. Political Agency, Kuwait 2pth March 19*0 \ copy of the above telegram ic forwarded here- Political vgent, Kuwait.W-T 5 1final To:-\vlatlon Baghdad, repeated Akforoe and Special From:- De Qaury, Kuwait. Naslrlyah No 1/407 24/3 Man who arrived today from Riyadh having left there on 1?th March makes following statements which however should be accepted with reservation aaa Ibn Shighair was in Jarya Ilya when he passed through aaa Ibn Ashwan he heard was at Abraq al Jarrah 30 miles north-west of Artawiyah and Thaidan Ibn Hathlaim in Sarrar no news Lami aaa He says Ibn Hathlaln was given permission to raid and received present of few arms and many camels aaa Ibn Hathlain left for Sarrar but subsequently Ibn Saud sent after him to cancel permission and Informant^ heard of messenger with order repeated leaving Riyadh on loth March aaa On 15th March Saud al Arafa brother-in-law of Ibn Saud left Riyadh to try to persuade Ibn Humaid to abandon raid to the north aaa Informant believed Ibn Humaid to be at Majmaa then and to have arranged to meet Dawish at Niqqa al Jarrab 40 miles north-west of Artawiyah where Ibn Hathlaln would also meet them aaa Informants information on last points should be considered as doubtful. W-T Signal To:-Aviation Baghdad, repeated Akforce and Special Nasiriyah From:- De Gaury, Kuwait. No 1/408 25/3 Man referred to in my 1/407 gives following additional information aaa Muhsln al Firm was in Riyadh on March 17th and had earlier received permission to raid which was cancelled aa Al Firm had escort of 40 men and Ibn Mathayan with him only aa Informant saw Abulwai in Riyadh and although he had heard report of his intention to intervene on behalf of Ibn Saud could not confirm that he had done so successfully aaa Prices of foodstuffs in Riyadh are normal aaa Cartridges in Mutair country are three for one rupee four annas aaa Tribal units passed on return Journey as follows aaa 100 temts of S&amp;balh at Awsat in Dahana due south of Safa (place is unmarked) under Abu Ithnain follower of Ibn Saud aaa 80 tents AJman at Taraibi 50 miles south-east Safa under Naif ibn Chilab aaa 30 tents AJman at Saflr 60 miles south-east Safa under Falah al Asql aa 40 tents Awazia at Jofain 20 miles north-east Jarya Ilya aaa Informant saw aeroplanes on the direct route for Ilya and feels certain they cannot have missed It if they continued in the same direction aaa He was then at Umm an NiqqaShould the proposals put forward in the Air Officer Coru landinc* s message of 20th Uarch 1928 be adopted I should propose the following disposition for the Persian Gulf Division. One sloop to renain at Kuwait, One sloop to proceed to Shatt A1 Arab or to Bushire. Qhe cruiser to cruise as required but not beyond lienjan.qoHyiiaareiAjL (P). From Politic;^!, KuTnii. To ^9ld«nt, B^ahraia* Ko. ;.?3. Dat#d jth March 19^* lV.f*reiv;# teleeraa Ko. ; vCo/..‘4 fror- the iiwiior Huval Offioar. I think thi£ propor.»X fcight bt fc.dcptsti aithout unuu« It it practically cortain ths-t would £et aufflclaAt earning of &amp;a i^endin^ attack on Kuwait to enable the other sloop and the cruiser to return before it could materialize. The danger of attack is unnueetionshly much leas than it was. Political ^fcency, Kuwait, *jta Marofc A copy of the above telegram is forwarded herewith, with compliments, to The Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, H.M.S. Emerald. i.t . **101 .0 Political Agent, Kuwait.Telegram From To No* Dated (?) Resident, as. B&amp;roda, Basrah Radio. Political, Kuwait^ repeated to 76 T. 26th March 1928* Your telegram No. 278« I agree that one ship is sufficient at Kuwait now. If an entorgengy should arise, you should comumnicate with the S.N.O* direct and repeat to me No. 283-S. Political Agcfrcy, Kuwait. 26th March 1928. A copy of the above telegram is forwarded herewith, with compliments, to:- The Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, H.M.S. Emerald. Lt.-Oolonel, Political Agent, Kuwait.iie£ Ho I/I4 a uwait 27tn Marcn 1928 ioi-iiae Poiitictii Agent ^UWiiit 1 nave received a cypner wire as follows (paraphrased from ^ir Headquarters. 'Sai^id Hashim ar Bifai atu Danan left Baghdad for Banrain on karch 22nd. Siyid Hasnim nas been writing for tne newspapers and is a Sharifian Agent, banrain has not been informed.' ^s far as Kuwait is concerned I will tell my man to keep an eye on tne Down Mail in case hec.should nave decided to breau. nis journey nere and would let you ^now if he landed. I will also fins, out from basran if ne das started yet. ^3 regards informing will* please let me i^now if if „ ou will send a Signal or if % vou would liiie me to send tne same message on to tnem. (I am not if tne^ nave tne a.I k cypner)jonriPsariAL. N'o. ;&gt;a 5-3 I’olitloal Agenoy, Kuwait. JYth Uaroh I93S. The Special Service Officer, KUWAIT gjiljlg.H? tei|l9i ar-Hafa’U jggjiOHAHt.iA'. Refer ftace yeur neaoraadua No * 1/1 4 of to-day’s data* X am pa£ainf, on the information which you h&amp;ya received to i;he Poxitioal A^ent, Bahrain* 1 hive never heard the name 'Abu Daaah' before, but I expect tne man referred to is Saiyid nishia bin as-Saiyid xihaad ar-Rafa 1 !, who doee, I Know, write to newspaper*. ii© was foraeriy - if he is not still - in Ibn Sa’ud’s employ, and tv&amp;a used by aim on more than cue occasion to ’'bear-lead' 1 foreigners, auoh as Am^n Rfh£nl, ^ajor holies,etc He came to Kuwait as fSeoretary to the Kajd Leleiiation at the Kuwait Conference in December 19UJ, and, beln^ himself a native of Kuwait, he delayed returning to tfajd after the Con ference w%a over and stopped on in Kuwait until the beginning of May 1 ^ 4 . He then left rather hurredly, somewhat under a aloud, having been badly beaten - both by private individual# and afterwards, I believe, by the Shaikh's 'Chief of Police' - for being drunk and disorderly in a house of ill fame* Since then I h^ve lost trace of him* Political Agent, KuwaitTelegram (P) From Political, Kuwait. To Political, Bahrain Ko. 288. Dated 27th March 1928. The SeSoQ, here has given me the following from Air Head quarters, Baghdad. Begins. Saiyid Hashim ar-Rafai Abu Danah left Baghdad for Bahrain on the 22nd March. Saiyid Hashim has been writing for the newspapers and is a Sharifian agent.Ends. The name M Abu Danah” is new to me, but I presume he is the Saiyid Hashim who was - or is - in Ibn Sard’s service. He used to be employed to Jbear lead” foreigners such as Major Holmes. He came here as secretaty to the Najd Delegation at the Kuwait Conference of 1923 - 24, and, as Kuwait is his home stopped on here after it was over, until he was beaten both by private indivuals and also by the Shaikhs police for being drunk and disorderly in A brothel.Telegram (C) Prom Political, Kuwait. To S. of S# Colonies; Jerusalem* No. 287, Dated 27th March 1928. ^5^ My telegram No« 2?4* The Special Service Officer has learnt that a man arrived here yesterday, Monday, who says he accompanied Ibn Humaid to Majma*ah« Prom there he went to Sarar« Ibn Hithlain was there then, but was said to be only awaiting the arrival of caravan from Juball to start for Jarab, about 37 miles north-west of Artawiyah,to meet Ibn Humaid, Dawish and others for a raid on a larger scale* No responsible person has examined the man as yet, but the Shaikh is having a search made for him and will send him to me if found# I know nothing of his reliability and am inclined to disbelieve the story# Political Agency, Kiiwait# 2?th March 1928# A wopy of the above telegram is sent herewith,with compliments, to:- Senior Naval Officer,Persian Gulf, H#M#S*Emerald (by signal) Special Service Officer, Kuwait# Lt#-Col#, Political Agent, Kuwait#Tolegraa (C)» Prow Political, Kuwait* To of S» for Oolonles; repeated to Buehire,Baghdad and Jerusalem* Dated 27th March 1928* My telegram No« 287» The man has been brought in from one of the villages on the ooast and sent to me for examination* He belongs to the 'Awazim of Kuwait and is known here, and the Shaikh says he has no reason to doubt his good faith* ie says he had gone to Shaqra to get some women relations,and left there on or about the 7th March* Ibn Humald moved from there the same day with tern standards and a force which he estimates at 3000 strong* He actually accompanied them to Zulalqlf which he describes as roughly half way between haa and Majaa'ah, and slightly to the west of the latter. that Ibn Hlthlain Intended to leave for Jarab after the festival (23rd March). Hh heard that Dawish was in the Dahanah. 289. Proa there he went by easy stages to Sarar, thsre on 19th March and leaving again on 21st Ma lo sarar, arriving thar. on 21 st March*He heard I shall exaalne hla again to-aorrow, Wednesday , morning* Political Agency, Kuwait, 28th March t 928 . , with 3*N*0*, H*M#S* S«S*0*, Kuwait* *?*!?'’ Em *rald (by signal)The attached remarks on Kuwait are forwarded as requested in your letter of 12th Marc h. i wconfidential KUWAIT - INTELLIGENCE INFORMATION. LMma.FASILiSiSS Troops If local craft and labour are employed, tropps can be landed in the boat harbours very quickly although the landing will be better if carried out at high water. If transport or man of war^ boats are used, landing except in a strong kaus or S.E. wind would be better on the beach to the south of Ras A1 Ajusa where boats can get close to the shore at all states of the tide. AplmcAfl :- Most easily landed in local dhows. -Heavx Cruld be landed in local craft, at the Customs landing at High Water but it would probably be a better plan for these to be landed at Basrah (Margin) and driven down. The whole question of landing depends on (a) Whether is is to be assumed that local! facilities are available or not. (b) Whether the landing is to be carried out as an emergency or not. smmLSim. - A good camping site is inside the wall which surrounds the town. Plenty of room is available for any number of tents and the ground is reasonably hard. m m . At present all water has to be imported by boat and so it is scarce. Artesian wells are being drilled but are not yet in working order. Local water is too brackish for horses but suitable for local camels. sm. None available. All has to be imported. DBFBNCB OP THE TOW N* The town is surrounded on the land side by a mud wdl 3! miles long with 31 towers at intervals along it and 3 gates The wall between the towers is 14|* high and is loopholed in most places. The towers are of one storey with a living room on the ground level. Tb© wall towers and gates make most excellent machine and Lewis gun posts and t&gt;e use of sand bags can transform them into almost perfect emplacements. All towers project forward from the wall and give enfilading arcs along the wall. Tb e ground outside the walls is entirely open and passable to troops, horses and vehicles in all directions and there is very good field of fire for 2,000 yards from the wall. There are certain areas of broken and dead ground beyond this but they are not extensive and would afford little cover for advancing troops. An outpost could be established at Sitra Pdrt 5| mi*!es from the Main Gate. This is a disused mud fort standiw on a slight hill and commanding the whole of the surrounding country.KU.7AIT - IK2ELLIGE]:CE IKP0BIH2I0M. l^:dikg mzhmm '2roo. a If local craft and labour aro enployedj trop ;.)0 can be landed in the boat harbours very quickly although the landing will be better if carried out at high ’7ater. If transport or nan of vrar’s b ats are used, landing except in a strong kaus or S.E* wind would be better on the beach to the south of Eao A1 Ajusa /here boats can get close to the shore at all states of the tide. Aninala :- Host easily landed in local dhows. Hea?:; Vehicles :- C uld be landed in local craft.at the Customs landing at High jfater but it would probably be a better plan for these to be landed at Basrah (llargill) and driven down. Ths whole question of landing depends on (a) Whether is is to be assumed that loca2 facilities are available or not. (b) Whether the landing is to be carried out as an emergency or not. A good camping site is inside the wall which surrounds the to n. Plenty of room is available for any number of tents and the ground is reasonably hard. . mm* At present all water has to be imported by boat and so it is scarce. Artesian wells are being drilled but are ::c&lt; yet in working order. Loc;l water is too brackish for horses but suitable for local camels. sm. None available. All has to be imported. MPmca gg ma mm . She town is surrounded on the land side by a mud vd 3*1 miles long with 31 towers at intervals along it and 3 gatee The wall between the towers is 141* high and is loop holed in most places. The towers are of one storey with a living room on the ground level. The wall toweirs and gates make most excellent machine and Lewis ;un posts and the use of sand bags can transform then into almost erfect emplacements. All towers project forward from the wall and give e: filading arcs along the wall. Th e ground outside the walls is entirely o an and passable to troops, horses and vehicles in all directions and there is very good field of fire for 2,000 y^rds from the wall. There are certain areas of broken and dead round beyond this but they are not extensive and would afford little cover for advancing troops. An outpost could be established at Sifra Port, miles from the main Gate, This is a disused mud fort standi it on a slight hill and commanding the whale of t he ^surrounding country.iio i/ d Kuwait, I 9 wh ^arcn 1928 . iO:-ihe Poi.it ioao. .^gent, ^uwait. 1 fonvarci herewii;n - samples of tae water from tne desert wells of csirra and jPanatis to the ooutn of Kuwait as requested. rhe following information ma^ also be of use. cirra x wo wells in use,deptn to water surface is 4 o feet,aepth of water 1 foot on 19/3/28. One well nas been allowed to...fall in. xhe atove are |&gt;U 0 yards east of qasr as Sirra. ihree old wells wnion nave fallen in are traceatle 200 yards nortn of the ^asr. (Qasr is I^o feet by I 40 ,wall ±2 feet high, corner towers 18 feet high,accomadation for 30 men under cover,soutn-west tower is falling into disrepair, nill on wnich ^asr is built is about 4 ^ feet above surrounding plain, material boulders and local cement,average tniciLness of waxl halfway up 2 ft binches. oo-natis ^30 yards from the sea by single tamarisk tree. i^our wells,depth to surface of vater 32 feet, depth of water 8 feet,water appears very good for desert well. 100 yards from the sea are remains of other wells which are reported to have given plenty of good water in the past. One of these is not entirely fallen in and has some water of indifferent quality. The road from kuwait is 100 yards from the sea. CV ptain.CONFIDENTIAL. No. 284-8. Polltloal Agency, Kuwait 26 th M iroh 1928 From Lieut.-Colonel J. C. More, D.3.O., Polltloal Agent, Kuwait. To . The Chief of the General Staff, Array Headquarter*, India, DELHI. Sir, Under instruction* from the Hon’ble the Political ^aidant in the Persian Gulf I have the honour to forward herewith a Note on Intelligence Information regarding Kuwait, which I have prepared with the assistance of Captain H, G. C. Franklin, R.I., Senior Naval Officer in the Persian Gulf. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant. Lt.—Col., Political Agent, Kuwait. 3opy to the Hon'ble the ?oUtloal Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire.mmas moz IMM uKjligu HmAiwz i:9 Ku.,Ait. MiJCiaQ FAJILITI^a. Zt’? Tr^ opat- If loonl cr^ft and labour *«re employ#d, troop* oould 09 lauded very quickly in tho nig . or tidal bar- . bours, rhigfc li« nearly all the way alonfc the front of the town, but the landing could be more conveniently carried oui at high water. If the transport' s boate or muzi of ear's boats were utied, the landing,, except in a strong, south-east wind,would be better on the beaoh to the south of ft&amp;a c.l-*AJua.ah t when oo&amp;ts can get close to ti e shore at all states of the tide. inlaalj; 7 nlaiale could be most easily landed in local craft. He iyy Vehlclea. Heavy Vehicles could be landed in local craft at the Customs House at nigh water, or, if l-rge quantities were involved, it might be more convenient for then to be landed at Basrah, and driven down by road. CA &amp;PiftS SlTBa, , A good oafuiing site is available inside the wall which surrounds the town, with aapie room for at least a division, on reasonably n&amp;rd O rotmd. Shere la ^Uso ualiaitec e^soe outside the wall. mm* The wfcter supply of Kuwait is very limited, ^nd the majority of the inhabitants, Had practically all who live near the sea, drink river water Imported from the Shatt al- * Vrab in special boats. The price of this viu*iea from time to time, but three plea n gallon at the boat aide, or six piea delivered in the town, is about the average. The Sfcaaiyah wells, less than a iaiXe outside the Centre Cate of the town, also supply a liuUted quantity of good water, 'ad sons people who live far from the sea find it cheaper to have it brought from the®.CONFIDENTIAL. No. 290-3. Politloal Afceaoy,Kuwait. 26th March &lt;928. To The Hor.'ble the Political Resident in the Pereian Gulf, B U 8 H I R E. Intelll^^enofe. MEMORANDUM. In continuation of, my memorandum No.2^7-3 dated the 19th March 1928. I enclose herewith copies of the Special Service Officer's telegrams Noo. 1/40? and l/4©8 dated the 24th an&lt; $ 29th March 1928 respectively, which are the only ones of any Interest which he has sent. Lt.—Col .p Political Agent, Kuwait.To... • •.. #Cor]nander in Chief f Sarrfc Indies. Hepeatod to Adnira3.ty, Air Officer Connandingi Ira^. 'KJTBRP XSB' Political Resident, BusJiire. Date 27th March 1928. Political Resident has concurred in : y proposal to reduce the ships at Kuwait.now. Landinn parties are beinc r©-onbar!:ed* BUM#S # 'CROCUS” will proceed to BUshire shorf;ly at the request of the Political Re sident and H.n.S. ft LUPIR n will ronain at Kuwait for the present. X propose to renain Kuwait until arrival of 'ENTERPRISE' as it will be nost satisfactory to the P°!itical Agont and Kuwait, and nyself to turn over here. 2005/27. Copy to The P°litical Agent, Kuwait. For information.To From Telegram (P). Secretary of State for the Colox ’ealdent. Bush Ire; rapo-jted to Baghdafi and Kuwait *54 JoayiD SMT iii.. Dated 27th Starch Your toieeram No, 77 T, I have not received teiesrem No.2?e fron Kuwait to which you refer In your telegram No, 76 T f axKi consequently l am not aware of the considerations which prompt you to suggest that the landing parties should he re- esH*»riced # u n the information tefore me, however, I adhere to the instructions conveyed in my telegram of 24th i;arch. Until s run time as th* vlanger of a raid has definitely passed, I ooad.uer it undesireable that the precautions should be relaxed ?a ® r ' ot thRt Samadhan has only just ended may explain why the threatened raid has not yet -aaterialized, I consider it rash to asouae that tne raid has been definitely abandoned until the next two weeks Or so hsve passed. A oopy of the above telegram is forwarded herewith, with oomnliaents, to The Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, H.M.3. Emerald. Political Agency, Kuwait 2 dth March 1^23, ht,-Col*, Political Agent, Kuwait*To... Datel ..The S.N.O.P.G. ..The political Resident, ..28th March 1928. *52. ,2 7(5 Bushire. Reference telegraja frora the Secretary of State for the Colonies No. 154 repeated to me by the Political Agent, I am holding matters here in abeyance pending your further wishes. 1035/28. The political Agent, Kuwait. Copy for information.CONFIDENTIAL Telegram (P) From Resident, Bushire. To S, of 3* for Colonies; repeated to Baghdad and To Kuwait. No. 594 (63 to Colonies) Dated 28th Karuh 1928. The views expressed in your telegram No. 1p4 are the same as mine and I was only trying to follow the views of the Naval and Military authorities with regard to the defence, and having regard to your telegram No. 1^1. I aia now xsjpiextedxlax^&amp;ii repeating to you Kuwait telegram No. 278 to my address also the Senior Naval Officer*8 tele&amp;raa No. 2000 to the Naval Commander-In-Chief; please also see Air Officer Commandinfc,*s telegram No. Z 190 to the Air Ministry which refers to his No. Z 193 quoted by the Senior Naval Officer. However, I considered that as lon&amp; as one ship was at Kuwait and the others.within Immediate recall the danger could be met as we would have sufficient notice. Moreover, the landing partfees if re-embarked oould be landed quickly aa they would know their places in the line of defence - other wise I should have expressed the views which I personally held. I have presumed that you received copies of all the Air Officer Commanding*s telegrams to the Air Ministry on matters relating to Ibn Sa*ud. No. 2 92-S. Political Agency, Ku .ait, 28th March 1923 A copy of the above telegram is forwarded herewith with compliments, to Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, H.M.S. Emerald. Lt.—Col., Political Ap&gt;ent, Kuwait.^Telegram (0) Prom Political, Kuwait. S. of So for Colonies; and Jerusalem. repeated to Bushire,Baghdad No. 298 . Dated JOth March 1928. My No. 289. Second hand information received from a man who left Sarar on 22nd March that messengers from Ibn Sa*ud arrived there on 21st March forbidding the raid and that in consequence Ibn Hithl&amp;in gave out that he would not raid. I am having the man sent for. llegram (C) From Political Kuwait. To Resident, Bushire. No. 299«&gt; Dated 30th March 1928* Following from Akforce to Aviation etc.. No. 1/164 of 30th March, Begins. Special, Buscol, reports the following from agent who left ’AiwlJ four days ago. Six days ago Ibn Habbaa returned to th&lt; vlcfenlty of Lin&amp;h from Riyadh and sent messengers to Ibn Shuraim at Linah alleging a large raid led by Dawish and Ibn Humaid about to take place contrary to the orders of Ibn Sa f ud with the probable objective 'Iraq Government posts.All Shauunar moved by night into the Dahanah south of Linah. Telegram (C). Prom Political, Kuwait. To Resident, Bushire. No. 300. Dated 30th March 1928. My No.299• Armoured cars from here plus another section from Basrah have been ordered to proceed to Hafar on 31st March.m r V-T signal TO:-Aviation Baghdad repeated Aiiforee and Special IJasariyah. iJ'rom:-Be Gaury,^uwait J Ho 1/^13 3o/3 kan who left Sarrar on Marcn 2iafi and is iaiown here and believed fairly relable arrived Kuwait area on 29 th and states messengers from Ibn Baud arrived Sarrar about karch 2lst forbidding Ibn Hathiain to raid and that Ibn Hathlain gave out in consequence that ne would not raid aaa Kef my 1/504 of 28/3 and your queries of today's date man stated that ne saw Ibn Humaid about karch 4tn sligntly south of Snaqra but not subsequently consequently he inferred that ne was still witn force on about karch bth when he nimself left it aithougn he may hitw actually have turned back by then. CaptainJO/jgIDJ&amp;TlAL. Telegram To No« Dated (?)* Resident, Buehire, 3. of S. for Ooloniee; repeated to Delhi, Bagdad, J e r u s fi 1 e u., J p 1 ro, d 1 d«lali a/id ^uwa it* H j (ho.6d to Jolonlee). Jt. th March Telegram of 2 dth March from Political, Bahrain, Begina. MabKhut bia Muqrad vif the ’AJman, who has just arrived from a visit to Ib.i Da'ud at Riyadh, caye that there is not the least doubt that Ihn dithlain left Xbn S&amp;’ud &lt;fith the intention of Ju^uing ix raid a^^inst I r dq, the exception of oultar bln Ifai&amp;h b followers, the *AJjian t^ere to accompany him* Ibn Sa’ud gave him food and he gave Ibn dumaid 10,000 dollars and aoae ammunition. He had heard nothing about a messenger from Ibn 3a ud having diasuaded Ibn Humaid from the projected raid. I am trying to find oufc on what date Mabkhut left Riyadh. The Shaikh says it was during Hamadhan and that he celebrated the 4 ‘id at Qatif. The people of Najd are confident that there will be a raid in the near future. 2 nds. Telegram (P) # Fro® Resident, Bushire. s * f ( &gt;t* Colonies; repe^teu to i&gt;?lhl, Jerusalem, Cairo, Jiddah and Kuwait, f(No. 69 to Colonies). Dated &gt;~th March 1928 . Baghdad, Telegram No .109 of 2 th March from Political, Bahrain. Begins. There is an unconfirmed rumour here that Ibn Sa’ud is raising^ a force of 3°, 0^0 men in IJajd and Has a, and that it is being concentrated at Riyadh. Ibn 3a ud has again Informed Holmes by letter that h» is too busy to meet him. Ends. No. ;w2-3. Political Agency, Kuwait. Jlet March ly^d. with, wlth A oo2p{lMnS? tW ° teUfera “ 8 18 foraaM9d The Senior Naval Officer, Persian Qulf, The Special Service Officer, Kuwait, H.H.3. Saerald. Lt. Politica l Agen^ f?' “Telegram (0) From To * Political, Kuwait* S. of So for the Colonies; No* 301. Dated 31st March 1928* ^ £ 7 / C£f9 repeated to Buehire, Baghdad and Kerusalesa* My telegram No 0 298 e The Shwikh of Kuwait doee not ooneider the man at all reliable*ertmce Nasirivah, N« .1 .N./2 3/3 Dat«d ^arck 17tk, 1928 Officer Ce«s*anll!?ir # ▲kferee. Ur. Tke fellowiiis repert ea tke oress-exaMinatioa of a Mutair trikesaam capture! ky ameurel cars on 12tk Marek is ferwariei for your inferaatioa. Priaeaer, Skakik ikn Gkadaiyan, states ke is of tke Baskdak suk-section -Jiklan section Mutair, some 20- 30 tents of wkick \?ere cameei soutk of Craisum ( 15 miles S. 1 *. ef kL HAT AH) . Tkey kal keen situatel in tkis locality sinee tke kegiming of winter (^eceWot»ri an! from tkeir camp tkey ka! kear! aircraft in tke distance 'but ha! not actually seen them. On the 12th March the prisoner pro ceeded with a party of 4 others to get water from AL 5A3£fc$ HATAB wells, whence they had 'been in the hahit of watering since camping at their present location. The prisoner and Zaid al Hinaidi were in advance of the others and had • hardly reaclwthe wells when armoured cars •ppeared* at the sight af which the party fled. Three or their number but nat Zaid al Hinaidi himself, hia rifles and being frightemed fired some snots at the cars who returned the fire. Prisoner was woun*~* in the left leg and captured. Questioned witn regard to rumours of impending xailm raids, prisoner stated that the ^awish*s aeal in this respect had considerably abated. The kiiitair horses were exhausted by the recent raids and were resting at Umm.al Janajim. Also a considerable proportion of the kutair, including prominent members of all sections, i.e. HAIT AL TUG13M (AL#A) UASIA3I I3N BUSAIYI3 (BBAIH) AL ANNA1 (JIBLAH) and others, were loyal to Ibn La*ud. With regard to the activities of Ibn Humaid prisoner stated they had heard rumours that he had reached 3HAQL1A x with/ e large force variously reported to consist of 15 - 30 bairaqs. He was however imclined to desbelieve these rumours as it had also been resorted that Ibn Kumaid and Ibn Sa’ud had become reconciled and the former was now obeying the Sultan’s order to refrain from raiding. Previous to ti.e reconciliation I on Kumaid had ex pressed his intention of attacking THua aGH SHlnA'O (Shaibah) but his requests to Ihn for ammunition and food had been refused by the Gultan. With reference to the bombardment of A3 3ATA, prisoner was unable to give an estimate of the casualties caused, hich, however, he thought were few. The guest tent of the nawish, a black tent pitched in the middle , of a number ©f white tents was destroyed, as also were the tents of two prominent members of the family, SIUBAIYAN IBN FAIGai, an.l another. BHUBAIYAN’S tent was a three poled black tent # the okLow was a large white tent and both were pitched close to the fort. Some houses, the mosque, nrH ~ large number of camels were also destroyed. The prisoner states that the ^awish set off a day or two after the bombardment with an escort of 40 mom to visit Ibm fiumaid, via Artawiyah. His son AzaiyizTelegram (0) Prom Political, Kuwait* To S* of S&gt; for Colonies; repeated to Resident Bushire, Baghdad, and Jerusalem* 304* Dated 31st March 1928* Ibn Sa'ud’s agent has received Inforation ( of which how ever I doubt reliability) that towards the end of Raaadhan Ibn Humaid left his force near Majma’ah and him self visited Dawish at Artawiyah. While there Sa'ud al~ Arafafc arrived from Ibn Sa , ud and succeeded in persuading Ibn Humaid to send word to his force that raid was cancelled Political Agent, Kuwait, 31st March 1928 Copy to b»N*0,, P e G*, Emerald (by signal)® S*S*0*, Kuwait* Lt,-Col,j Political Agent, Kuwait*</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0003c2_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/5/39</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0003c2</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/5/39</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>File [10/12] Tribal and desert information: Ikhwan raids on Kuwait and defensive measures</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1928/1928</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-07-07T23:18:12</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (286 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.An index of topics discussed is contained at the rear of the file (on folios 285-286); the folios used in this index relate to an earlier incomplete foliation system that is in uncircled pencil in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence for this description commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 288; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. Two additional foliation sequences are present in parallel between ff 2-286 and ff 3-286; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains correspondence related to the British Government's relationship with Ibn Sa'ud [‘Abd al-‘Azīz bin ‘Abd al-Raḥmān bin Fayṣal Āl Sa‘ūd].Specifically, the correspondence in the file relates to raids made by Ikhwan forces in and around Kuwaiti territory, military action taken against these raids by British and Kuwaiti military forces, discussions regarding the possibility of supplying armoured cars and machine guns to Kuwait and logistical arrangements for the defence of Kuwait from attack. It also contains broader discussions concerning developments between Ibn Sa'ud and leaders of the Ikhwan, notably Faisal al-Duwaish [Faysal al-Duwaysh].British military action against the Ikhwan involved the use of aeroplanes and as such, the file contains details of ground signals that Kuwaiti forces were to use to signal to British aircraft in English (folio 117) and Arabic (folio 124)On folio 210, the file contains a list of British subjects and British protected persons that were to be evacuated from Kuwait in the event of an attack.The majority of the correspondence in the file is internal correspondence between British officials but letters exchanged between the Political Agent in Kuwait, Major James Carmichael More, and the Ruler of Kuwait, Shaikh Ahmad al-Jaber al-Sabah (in Arabic with English translations), also appear throughout the file.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><name type="personal"><namePart>Fayṣal bin Sulṭān al-Dawīsh</namePart></name></subject><subject><topic>Ikhwan revolt (1927-1930)</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0003c2#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>