<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000419.0x0001cb_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-06-04T10:31:06.909Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">NOT FOR DIRECT PHOTOCOPYING COPIES MAY BE ORDERED FROM , 4 O *WE? 1 ®?From Viceroy, 18th November 1915. Foreign Secret. Your telegram dated 9th November. Amara merchants. We are of opinion that treatment of cargoes of Amara merchants should be same as that accorded to Basra merchants. Nixon agrees. j O \ 18 N 0 V 1315y In any further commtinication on the subject, please quote no. 159604/15. and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. t i ' 8 Hi Foreign Office 337^/is' U^J V Novernb.er 3rd, 1915. With reference to your letter, P. 4662, of the 2nd of December last, relative to the treatment to be accorded to the property of merchants of Basra men on the high seas, I am directed by Secretary Sir Baward Grey to state that an enquiry has been addressed to him as to whether similar privileged treatment should be extended to goods belonging to merchants of Amara. Sir Edward Grey would be glad to receive an expression of the views of the Secretary of State for India as to what principle should be adopted towards such cargoes. I am, Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant, The Under Secretary of State, India Office,Under Secretary.. Secretary of State. Committee Under Secretary .. Secretary of State. Coum //«2^ * i/iv,. Previous Papers 11858. I. 1992 IOCThe Under Secretary of State, Foreign Office. Copy (9404). Y-MOUDA, HESKKL AND CO&amp;'FA'Y, 6, DICKINSON STREET, kAN CHESTER, January 23rd 1915. bir:- Keferring to our letter of the 12th instant, and your acknowledgement of the 14th instant, ve snail be glad if you can give us any information, how best to act in relation to these goods. Naturally we are very desirous of saving them, if it is humanely possible, and any instruction you could give at the earliest possible moment would be highly appreciated. Yours faithfully, (Signed) Y. Heskel and Commny.The Under Secretary of State, Foreign Office. YSHOUDA HESK^L AND COMPANY, Copy MANCHESTER. (4623). January 12th 191b. Sir:- i er the S.S. 'i anica' from Manchester, 27th April 1914, ne sent to the Custom House at Bagdad, the fol lowing goods:- 22 bales marked E.R.N. '38/59' Oobton Goods, of the value £2,139 Bagdad idara 102 ' M M '5811/5912* * * * * ' £12,333 Y H &amp; Co. Bagdad Idara 124 £14,472. The bills of lading for same are in our hanas, and as we are unable to communicate in any way with our agent at Bagdad, we are at a loss to know hov/ to act. Could you advise the nest means to have these goods cleared, and as we fear if left until the arrival of the British forces, they may receive similar treatment to those at the Busra Custom House, when we were mulcted in damage to the extent of £14,294, and naturally we are very desirous of escaping similar losses. Being British merchants, we appeal for guidance, andand any information you could offer, or any services render on our behalf, would be gratefully appreciated, as under prevailing circumstances it has been impossible to effect Insurance against these risks. Yours faithfully, (Signed) Y. Heskel and Company.(9404). FOREIGN O^’ICE, January 17th 1915. Gentlemen:- uith reference to your letter of the l^th instant regarding two consignments of cotton goods sent by you to the Custom House, Bagdad, I arn directed by Secretary Sir E. Grey to inform you that your claim will be noted, for such action as may be possible at the end of the war. I am &amp;\c., (Signed) Messrs. Yehouda Heskel and Company, 6, Dickinson Street, Manchester.— c ft o FOREIGN OFFICE. Dear Hlrtzel:- Thanks for your letter of the 27th ultimo respecting Uehonda Heskel's goods at Bagdad. We are sorry we did not explain matters more clearly to the firm, hut we took It for granted that It would he as ohvlous to them as It was to us that neither the British Government nor a British firm can rescue goods in the hands of the enemy except hy re suming possession of them hy act of war or hy claiming them or their value when peace is concluded. Do Messrs. T 'ehonda Heskel think German firms are clearing their goodsgoods in England? All over lurkey British goods have been ruthlessly seized and requisitioned - at Constan tinople alone the claims will run into thousands of pounds - and even if the American Consular staff were very much strengthened they could do nothing, any more than they can do here for the Germans. Messrs. IJehonda Heskel's claim has been duly noted here and they must in the meanwhile I fear bear the loss like hundreds of other firmsE. S. DAVID’S SONS &amp; CO. Telegraphic Address: DAYLIGHT, MANCHESTER. Tel. No. 3309 Central. Lloyd’s House, Manchester, ^ y: w i 9 i ! ir, The Under-cecretarj r of State for Poreign Affaire informs us that he 'ms referred to your department our communication respecting sene goods of ours being looted &amp; destroyed at Buereh at the time of the British occupation of that town. we shall be obliged if you vi]i Kindly let us Know vhat steps if any are new necessary to ta^e in our interests. Should you require any further particulars on the subject we shall be glad to furnish you with any information we V ,ve. we are fir.\ At r In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote 7 9 ^ b~ No, and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. T/ie Under-Secret city of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Under-Secretary of State for d — ' and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith — e&amp;p of— the under-mentioned paper. / Foreign Office, W ? 6 ~ IQI$ RECEIVED 25 JAN1915 Xt c ^l£ y, IWD1A OFFICE Reference to previous letter: 'F ui/fiRo. S'? //$' Description of Inclosure. /y? /i/i' Name and Date. Subject. L £»- ' . i o / cirf- . L 25 JftN 19 15 s) (Similar letter sent to% s. f\viD’S SONS &amp; CO. Telegraphic Address: DAYLIGHT, MANCHESTER. Tel. No. 3309 Central. r&lt; ; v • - f V Lloyd’s House, Manchester, ' 'L J igi Ml ion to the Persian Gulf ir hrii.^ to your notice tne following; facte- ^d.ti.erea from received at Lloyd's. :~ ..n the. arrival of the British Expedition at Busren it v-as found that the d.stem House ana the stores of the laara Nahrieh (River steamship Co) had. teen Icoted and fired, and practically every thing therein had either he h 1 ox ted or destroyed oy fire.^ We further understand that the cargoes of the r/s Avristan and S/S Amatonga inter dec for IrtiSshipr.ent to 'Bagdad were stored at the time, the former H t the stores of the laara Nahrieh, and the latter at the Custom House. Our interest in the ah eve t^c cargoes v ; j ich in^' have suffered consists c f ti e fOa.lo _g packager ot cctton gcoc . x . ••r 12 J Out 1-W v wun In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote NO. JiTjC. and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. 'Mou- his compliments to the Under-Secretary of State for Q/-i^ _ and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith — &amp;f~ the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, r , &lt;? 3 , 1916 . RECEIVED 25 JAN1915 V. v. Xi CKX. iic*istry, INDIA OrFiCE. Reference to previous letter: Description of Inclosure. Name and Date. Subject.BOOTE, EDGAR, GRACE &amp; RYLANDS, In tortileranoe of our letter to you dated the 12th Instant on behalf of our Ollente The Continental Trading Company of £9, ilinsnull Street, Manchester they Inform us that they have now received inform&amp;tion that three packages In addition to the packages mentioned in such letter have been looted or destroyed at Basran. The particulars of the packages are as follows Bossorah Value £83 1Mb OH w * tlZl g • • £l£l and they have been lost whilst awaiting transhipment. Our Clients desire us to communicate with you thereon and to respectfully request you to have enquiries made and to give instruct ions to have - the goods restored or their value checked and paid. Will you kindly let the matter have your attention. We are. Sir, Your obedient Servants, The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, Foreign Office, Whitehall, JEOHSOI.- — - f\ r - t n ay£ s lS As s ^ 8c C° ° 0 0. C a l -' r eleg f&lt;APH Address: 'saleh: MAUCHeSTER. ABC Code. AhoAi Codf used. A To © V &gt; February 15 . A? The Under-Seoretary of State for India India Offioe, tondon. S.W. r 4 8 0 Sir, -i N ° ao ’ :ot you are ;v ‘ are on the arrival of the British War vessels at Bussorah in November last it was found that the Custom House and the office and store of the Idara Nahrieh had been looted and fired and practically everything therein had been removed or destroyed. We understand that the British Government have recovered a quantif ofjthelooted goods. Ve are interested in 13 Bales Cotton goods marked ^VlJSJT No 878/390 . and should be obliged if you can obtain for us any I inf °^ ati0n ^Speoti^ same or are we to cormmicate direct with Sir Percy Cox at Bugsorafli, We are. ! I[ 12 ) I* m HS' '* * 3^J In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote No, jmd address— The Under-Secretary of - ’ * / V Foreign Office, London. The Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents / / ‘ his compliments to the Undersecretary of State for v and } by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith &amp;&amp;p of the under-mentioned paper % Foreign Office, v7^&gt;~. 2., igi$~ Letter to {pern Reference to previous correspondence: Foreign 0jjice : Astf ^^ Description of Inclosure. Name and Date. Subject. L ■^I(rz/-Ao AUr-iSfLW (Similar letter sent to*J3*a3H ACI.U0H3Y ejj^aoA DtnqAfl03jjT .5?3T23HOMAM .'jaM/SBH* :.V ^ \\ \ - ^ &gt;&lt; jd'&gt;ioW HibiV/ xt M 4 % s 1 i £ 6 1 % &gt;?.; ■ * / 6&gt; 2 j£ , $ tf ' I &amp; _ /? V? sty s' &gt; In any further communication on the subject, please quote n„. 6262/15. and address— ^ The Under-Secretary of State, V» Foreign Office, London. Sir:- With reference to Mr. Shuckburgh*8 lett er t o Mr. Oliphant of the 16th instant, enclosing a letter] from Messrs. Yehouda, Heskel and Company of Manchester, respecting certain of their goods now lying at Bagdad, I am directed by Secretary Sir E. Grey to inform you that a similar letter from the Firm has already been received in this Office. In reply, they have been informed that His Majesty's Government have noted the facts submitted, and will give them such assistance as they can, at the end of the war. &amp; ( ■t * S' S’ /r SSL i iT £ 4 Jrv BOOTE, EDGAR, GRACE &amp; RYLANDS, SOL.IC ITORS. R. A. EDGAR. R.W. RYLAN DS. R.G. E DG A R 'I.A.OXON. J.GRACE. 'M'K 20, Booth Street, BbH* Manchester, telegrams:“Boote. Edgar’.’ 0^ TELEPHONE NQS 6293 &amp; 6294 CENTRAL. Sir, 19 t*i Jannar y J9J b In furtharanca of our latter to you dated the 12th Instant on behalf of our Clients The Continental Trading Company of 29, Mine hull Street, Manchester they inform us that they have now received information that three packages in addition to the paolcages mentioned in suoh letter have been looted or destroyed at Busrah* The particulars of the packages are as followss- J.H.H. Buseorah value £83 1 14 &amp; Oh w ' / 0121 1 2 » ■ £121 and they have been lost whilst awaiting transhipment. Our Clients desire us to oonmunicate with you thereon and to respectfully request you to have enquiries made and to give instructions to have the goods restored or their value checked and paid. Will you kindly let the matter have your attention. We cure. Sir, Your obedient Servants, The Bight Hon. The Secretary of State for India, Whitehall, LOB DOW.Aiiy further communication should be addressed to — the assistant secretary, at the address giveu opposite. The following letter and number should be quoted :— (V 20401. Telegraphic Address: COLASTA, LONDON. Telephone No.: 3840 Victoria. R- BOARD OF TRADE, (COMMERCIAL DEPARTMENT). . GWYDYR HOUSE, WHITEHALL, 69 LONDON, S.W. l4th January, 1915. Sir, With reference to the letter of the 10th December from this Department enclosing copy of a letter from Vt, Messrs Stanley and Company relative to the shipment of certain goods to Busreh on the Persian Gulf, I am direct ed by the Board of Trade to state that they would be glad to be informed as soon as possible whether the Secretary of State considers it advisable to allow the shipment in question to be made. 3 The Under Secretary of State, India Office, I have the honour to be, Sir, Your obedient Servant, S. W.k 4^ BOOTE, EDGAR, GRACE &amp; RYLANDS, SOUIC ! TO R S. R. A. EDGAR. R.W. RYLA N D8. R.G.EDGAR.j.a.okon. J.GRACE. 20, Booth Street, Manchester, H. tei_egrams:“Boote. Edgar? TELEPHONE NOS 6293 &amp; 6294- CENTRAL. ■’ 55 Sir, Put January 15th ;&lt;]/ 5, 'Moll- T v w*. v wun Our Client b UesBrs. li. Jl» Shashoua &amp; Co. who are shipper8 to Bagdad have been Informed by cablegram that their shipment of 65 packages per SS 'Amatonga' which are valued at £4 9 850 have been lost whilst awaiting shipment at Busrah. Our Clients desired us to write to you to have enquiries t •• made and to give instructions to have the goods restored or their 'value checked and paid* We shall be glad if you will let the matter have your attention* We are Sir, Your obedient Servants, A/** The Bight Honourable The Secretary of State for India Whitehall, — LOU BOH• f ' ; D r T» | v r- I i 16JAN1S15 '^TofT'iK.3 Our Clients oannot yet say whether these particulars include all the goods in respect of which they desire your assistance. They are making the best enquiries they can and as soon as possible we will extend the particulars if necessary. Ve enclose complete details and particulars of the contents of the bales* Ve propose to send a similar letter to Lieut. Col. Sir Peroy Cox at Busrah and will do so in the course of the next few days unless you instruct us to the contrary. May we ask the farour of your consideration towards our Clients in obtaining the recovery of the damages which they have sustained which will be required by them to discharge their obligations to We an The fit. Hohble. The Secretary of State for India. Whitehall* London*A ,\\ . . VANNNV^ • a L\ \ti SL 6 fToiiqi^wa I P^ 3 ^ ooi.N b ^ovv &gt; a ^‘\ , \.\-.x^'.. -V ^ •■ ^ x Vi v. \\&lt;^ ‘&gt;» \ '“A V. ■V.-X?. jj &gt; ‘t lb .8 | ^ tet)ii ( I 8^0314 .o?l X s. VW* Widtli Length °o^a 7 tv y^o w/ /y&lt; ^ ^.SOVV t. &gt; » vx.. ^ ^Vi x aNN x i » ^ ^ 0 ‘° A...V \&gt; ^ VKVV.N^ I ^ * ovv: o v i' : x\ ^ Xx-- - •• S \v v - \ osX XQ Caj \ x ' ^ oS\ t,0% ^ ^'A ^ V ■ V.^. V\\ ;\ v\'• N a.j iV. 's an \\i X \ 'A v \. AK ^ oai\ --v^\' A ^ A X K.vJi &lt;X a av X ? n , OCX ^&gt;sx i V\ A... &gt;\»x&amp; x. A A •* ^ N oxA v,..\ AA. .vV^ o o JA— \ OJ.\s‘ x^W x\ O C&gt; O &gt; A o ^ vX • oo^» X i o ox \ iv o \ '' ■». r\ v X -A^v . &gt;X - a a V X A&lt;\ .^.-AV^ vv v/ i ^ 5- ^vVtV ;\ v\ iSX ^'V.. \ '^\\ \ \ o \\ l* *#\ \ I .£ ^ &gt; 5.V-&lt; Si A' -As V A- .^ \&lt;&gt; v * ^ v 'i b Ob o ^ b.„ \' v ^ ^ \ \\ &amp; , V, A x e - —r \ A ^ A &lt;y &lt;*\ CjO'C* ^ V ob X .V . \' V V ‘SbiSZ* v 0\ vK ; \i °M \ \\\ NSS FV' ’ b St aohH aeoojM oK ■',‘Auil ifi^nod ([ibiV/ - j Ji'iii] j V Cj iv ^0 v ^ -&gt;-VftVl\&gt;rV ; \ bjXXV-^ V ' \ VV XV ^ ^ ' ^ O 5. ^ ' \ '^ 4t » .t\» 00 \ \\ o\ \ \ \\ o\ tA c)^ &amp; ^ \ V v\^ )-.. v.v&gt;SN. tHi •c'v ^S^ c *- f ^ - &gt; ^ ^ ^ ^ o-^\ \ y jxjwA&lt;,&gt;vW AaV'y \v \ v ** x \ &lt;. &lt; s ^ a\ ^ J^sa \ i jw^X ^ \&lt;* \&gt;s * \ A j ^ \ Vty\ \ v V X D S, 0 i i : i 1 KX—- h ifljainoJ. •ifibtW i QJ^O \ &gt; ^ i^y\ &gt; &gt;- ^ &gt;ex ^5^- BOOTE, EDGAR, GRACE &amp; RYLANDS, ‘ Souic ITORS. sac R. A. EDGAR. R.W. RYLA N DS. R. G. E D G A R , •.a.oxon. J.G RACE. B. TELEGRAMS:' BOOTE. Edgar’.’ TELEPHONE N&lt;35 6293 &amp; 6294 CENTRAL. 20 , Booth Street, Manchester, 14th Jmmmrr jgj 5. i l 1 ^ ^ ftl ] Sir V« are desired by our Olients Messrs. Isaacs Bros. Sons So Oo. of 43 Dlokinson Street Manchester to giro you particulars of goods shipped by them to Busrah and which hare been destroyed or looted there. The particulars are as follows;- Shipped by the 'Amatonga* to Busrah and from there to Bagdad: Mark. Bos. Bales. Invoice price. Insured for; IBS &amp; Oo. 1/66 66 £S945. 18. 9. £3.674 Our Olients cannot yet say whether these particulars include all the goods in respect of which they desire your assistance. They are making the best enquiries they can and as soon as possible we will extend the particulars if necessary Ve enclose complete details and particulars of the contents of the bales. We propose to send a similar letter to Lieut. Col. Sir Percy Oox at Busrah and will do so in the course of the next few days unless you instruct us to the contrary. May wrgSF [JheL favour of your consideration 15j3tol915towards our Clients in obtaining the rocowery of the damages which they hare sustained whioh will be required by them to discharge their obligations to Manufacturers in Lancashire. We are, The Bt. Honble. The Secretary of State for India. Whitehall. London.&lt;6 44, Whitworth Street, MANCHESTER. ftl&amp;grammes “SHASHA, Manchester.” Telephone No. 5536 Central. A.B.C. Code:- 5th Edition. * •xQ the secretary, Political Department* India Ofiico* hy Dear Sir, w« are In raoeipt of your favour of yeaterday'a data contents of which we have noted and for which we thank you. we are elaining according to your instructions and are address Ing our olein, Colonel Sir Percy Cox K. 0. I. B. at Bussorah. Ycj/urs faithfully* 20JAN1915 Nnr - mm it) BOOTE. EDGAR, GRACE &amp; RYLANDS, S O l_ I C ITO RS. R. A. EDGAR. R. W. RV LANDS. R.G. E DG A R , t.A.oxoN. J.GRACE. B. TELEGRAMS :''B OOTE EDGAR? *r •4-Vl TELEPHONE NQ»1 6293 &amp; 6294 CENTRAL. 20, Booth Street, Manchester l£th Iwauary Sir 75 \ r OH It Oar Clients Messrs. The Continental Trading Co. of 29 Mlnshull Street Manchester who are Shippers to Bagdad have bean Informed that their shipment of packages marked as follows:- K.S.A.21/3; 0.T.67: C.T.68: C.T.69: A.H.3.54 and C.T.65/6 which are rained at 2856 hare been lost whilst waiting transhipment at Basrah. Oar Clients desired as to write to you to hare enquiries made and to giro instructions to hare the goods restored or their ralue checked and paid. We shall he glad if you will kindly let the matter hare your attention. We are t Sir, Your obedient servants The Bt. Eonble. The Secretary of State for India. Whitehall. 13 JAN1S15 1 B / i-&gt; l AIn any further communication on the subject, please quote Xo. 1562/15. and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. Sir: * With reference to the letter from this Office of the 6th instant, I am directed hy Secretary Sir E. Grey to transmit herewith copy of a letter from Messrs. Boote, Edgar, Grace and Rylands, regarding property, belonging to their clients, Messrs. Shashoua and Company, said to have been lost while awaiting transhipment at Basra. Subject to the concurrence of the Secretary of State for India Sir E. Grey proposes to inform the firm that the matter has been noted for such action as may be possible at the end of the war. I am, R b C fc i V \ 13 JAN 1915 I . ► a I.. t .. y, IRDiA Or b iC r. Sir, C&gt;nv to W Xv 15 JAN 1915 Your most obedient humble Servant The Under Secretary of State, India Office. 13 JAN1S15 -yA 4th January 1915, Sir, Our Clients, Messrs. M.A.Shashoua &amp; Co., who are onippers to Bagdad have been informed by cablegram that tneir shipment of 65 Packages per s.s. 'Amatonga' which are valued at £4,850 have been lost whilst awaiting transhipment at Bassorah. ,Jur Clients desired us to write to you to have en- quiries made and to give instructions to have the goods restored or their value chequed and paid. We sna11 be £ lab you will kindly let the matter have your attention. We are &amp;c., (Signed) Boots, Edgar &amp; Co., The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, Foreign Office, Whitehall, London.J 2 . carried on to Busrah but they ara without any dotalla with regard thereto# Our Cli« t . cannot yot say whether these particulars include all the goods In respect of which they desire your assistance. They are making the best enquiries they can and « soon as w ; rtU ^ the particulars if necessary. We enclose /details and particulars of the contents of the bales. A'e propose to send a similar letter to Ueut. Col. Sir Percy Cox at Busrah and will do bo » ao so in the course of the next few day. unless you instruct us to the contrary. London#W# propose to send a similar letter to Lieut* Col* Sir Percy Cox at Busrah and will do so in the course of the next few days unless you instruct us to the contrary* May we ask the favour of your consideration towards our Clients in obtaining the raoovery of the damages which they have sustained which will be required by them to discharge their obligations to the Banks previously mentioned and to Whitehall. London*\J^ V V In any further communication on the subject, please quote 88553/14. ^ ?/ No and address— The Under-Secrctary of State, Foreign Office, . London. , * ’ V' ^ anuary pu \ *• * ■ Sir:- 9 1 Q1 S /,/ i$is&gt; V2 I am directed by Secretary 1 Sir'i-.-Sroy to treas- in it to you hzv&amp;J^jh copies of two letters from Messrs. s ? Boote, Edgar, Grace and Rylands respectinf the claim of Messrs. Isaacs Brothers and Company in respect of goods said to have been requisitioned by the Turkish Government /hi1st awaiting transhipment at Amarah and -rfi . , Bagdad. (f ^ Cfff 3 ^ j/iA- / Subject to the concurrence of the marquess of ' / Crewe, Sir E. Grey vould propose to inform the firm that these claiins have heen noted for such action as may he possible at the end of tee war. 4 I an 9 \ 31 r &gt; Your iuosn obedient, humble Servint, it. otiilii/ ' R B C * V E D S JAN 1915 Ollct/vS The Under Seer ti u of 8m s , Indie Office. j@ fR&amp;3 112 Copy BOOTE, EDGAR, GRACE AND SO, BOOTH 3TREET, MANCHESTER. (88553) 28th Du c eml). j r, 1914 Our CllentB iviessrs. Isaacs Brothers and Coiupany have soon us irlth ./• f ,r.r*cu to two Bhlpments - one of 194 packages per s/3 'Avrlstan' valued at £20,406 and also 181 packages par 3/3 'Auatonga' valued at £18,359 which goods they are inforued by cablagram have bean looted r M1st awaiting transhipment to Auarah and bag dad Oiir Clients desire us to vrite you to have enquir ies made and to givj instructions to have the goods re stored or th^lr value chocked and t'? id. We shall he glad if you 'ill kindly let J e matter have your at’ ent. ion. (3ignod) Boots, Edgtr, a d Coiupany. The Secretary of State for Foreign AffairsCopy. (88*ra). BOOTE, EDGAR, GRACE A &gt;T D RYLAMD3, 20, BOOTH STREET, MANCHESTER. 28th Decauhjr, 1914. Sir:- Our Clients uieoars. Isaacs Brothers Sons and Com pany who are shippers to Bussorah have been inforiaud by cablegram thrr their shipiuent of 66 packages per s/s 'Aiaatonga 1 ’ which are valued at £3,674 have been looted whilst awaiting transhipment to Bagdad. Our Clients desire us to write you o h?ve enquir ies made and to give Instructions to have the goods re stored or their value checked and paid. We shall be glad if you will kindly let the matter have your attention. v are, &lt;5c., (Signed) Boote, Edgar and Company, The Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.» W« propose to Bon4 a Biallar letter to lleut. Col* Sir Peroy Cox at Bxierah and will Ao so in the ooorse of the aext few days uless you instruot us to the oontrary. May wo ash the farour of your oonsideratlon towards our Clients in obtaining the reoorery of the daaages which they hare sustained which will be required by them to discharge their obligations to the Banks preriously mentioned and to Whitehall* B* London*A M' ” ' n a, /n N In any further communication on tho subject, please quote No. 80396/14. and address— Tho Under-Secretary of State, ^3 Foreign Office Foreign Office, London. 1 p 1 December 30 1914. Sir: - t 1 ^ ^ i 1914 j With reference to your letter of the 7th instant P.4703 respecting the status of natives of Basra I am directed by Secretary Sir E. Grey to reply that Basra bein^, a portion ot Ottoman territory occupied by an invading torce, the nationality of its inhabitants is not thereby affected, and that, from a legal point of view, until some formal change in their status is made by annexation or otherwise, they must continue to be regarded as Ottoman subjects. Sir E. Grey does not therefore consider it advis able to apply to such persons the rule laid down in the Circular telegram of November 9th from this Office to His Majesty's Representatives abroad with regard to Egyptians. mis telegram had in view the approaching declara- . .'u -77 ~ Uon of a f ° rma l protectorate in Egypt and above all th&lt; SI DEC 1914 i ir anomalous position of Egyptians at a time whei 1 i\iL4A Orr j Secretary of State, ^IDECISH. India Office, when a state of •Jr&amp; (80396/14). of war was existing between His Majesty’s Government end the Sultan as Suzerain of Egypt. V/hile deprecating a declaration that natives of hasra should he considered as British protected persons Sir E. Grey wishes to observe that this attitude would not of course preclude the issue of instructions to treat them with special consideration and to give them all possible unofficial assistance. Your most obedient I am Sir humble Servant17976. I. 1694. 10,000.- 11/1914. [L 311.] COPY OF TELEGRAM. Sir P. Cox 25th December 1914 r p ] Received at London Office i No. HOB. Telegram of inquiry regarding Heskel's goods received at Gurna without name or address of sender. Following is reply. Ellerman had no private godown. It is feared that goods in question were among those looted from customs warehouse by mob before our arrival but it is impossible go trace them without details as to name of im ± or ting ship) and marks on bales. Addressed Foreign repeated India Office,In any further communication on the subject, please quote 83574/14 Foreign Office and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. lecem'ber 2-1 1914 Sir:- With reference to your letter P.4863 of the 10th instant I am directed hy Secretary Sir E. Grey to state that, as Basra is in the occupation of His Majesty’s Indian forces, it should not for the present he regard ed as an enemy port for the purposes of trade. Licenses should however in Sir E. Grey's opinion be issued for the exportation to that port of all goods on the prohibited list. I am Sir 9k a ((jl tf Your most obedient humb 1e Servant r c - - 3 , MVbiA Cr i : 22 DEC 1914 1 * The Under Secretary of State India Office.In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote No. :r-Secretary of Stale, and address— The Under-Secretary Foreign Office, London. *3* 1 4 961 The Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents dimeats to the Undersecretary of State for and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop of the under-mentioned papery . Foreign Office, 1914 . Reference to previous correspondence: to Letter , Foreiqn O ffice from J Description of Inclosure. Name and Date. (&lt;) Clssy'te-vvsys //. ^ 0 fIo . ^ Subject. RECEIVED 18 DEC 1914 i K L l A V- r r (Similar lettgr-sFnt toCUSTOM HOUSE, LCFDCF , E.C., December 11th, 1914 fls^ Sir I sin directed by the Board of Customs and Excise to state that they have received an enquiry from Messrs. Lynch Brothers of Salters' Hall Court, E.C., as to whether it is now permissible to send goods to Bussorah. The Board would be glad to be advised as to what reply should be given to the applicants. I am oc., (Signed) E. C. Cirningham. ier Secretary of State, '• &gt; , &amp;c., Foreigi Office.The Under Secrc\r In any further communication on the subject, please quote no. 80689/14. and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. Sir:- / P 4904 Foreign Opfice Uecember /(„ 1914. r 0^ ! \Ck\A l am directed by Secretary Sir E. Grey to transmit to you herewith a copy of a letter from Messrs. E. and J. S. Sykes respecting their claim in regard to goods damaged at Basra. Sir E. (Grey would be glad if, in this and similar cases of damage to goods belonging to British subjects in regions now, or in the future, occupied by His °i /is) a pensaticn cannot be obtained locally, I am to request that this Department may be notified in oraer that the claims may be noted for eventual presentation to the k 01 ' Majesty's Indian forces, reports could be obtained as K 1/ to the extent of the damage done. If redress and com- rtft'F'J 4* *' 1 1 Turkish Government. I'V r ?'&gt; « rv I am, Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant, The Under Secretary of State, India Office.^S5*P . &lt; (80689). Copy E. u J.S.SYKU AND CC DPJ \ , 52, PRINCESS STREET, MANCHESTER. December 8th 1914. Sir ' e ^ ci ra your attention to the information which we have, that the Turks in Bussorah have looted and des troyed goods in the Custom-house and elsewhere there, belonging to British firms. i*e have a considerable quantity of goods at Bussorah but as yet have no information whether the same have been destroyed, damaged, or stolen. *a shall be obliged if you will take notice of our Cxairn of wnich 7;e will give you fuller details as soon as the same are received and if you will extend to us your assistance in obtaining recompense for such loss or damage as we may have sustained. e are cxC ., (Signed) E.aJ.S. Sykes. Th© Right Honourable His uiajesty’s Secretary for Foreigi Affairs.-- J Any further communication ahould be addressed to— the; assistant secretary, at the address given opposite. The following letter and number should be quoted: Put away with, P 4 863 Lq(yo Telegraphic Address: COLASTA, LONDON. Telephone No.3840 Victoria. BOARD OF TRADE, (COMMERCIAL DEPARTMENT), GWYDYR/HOUSE, WHITEHALL, LONDON, S.W. Com/ to fndia U AN • 1914.5 10th December, iyi4 Sir, I am directed by the Board of Trade to transmit copy oi a letter which has been received from Messrs Staveley and Company with reference to the shipment of certain £;oods to Busreh, Persian Gulf,and to state that they would be N glad to be informed whether the Marquess of Crewe considers that it is advisable for the present to allow the shipment to be made. - I have the honour to be, f R F C F ‘ V £ D ) 11 Dtc 1914 i O -fcvxjr 1 I { NDIA CrhiCE.I The Under Secretary of State, India Office, S. W.(Copy) The Board of Trade, Whitehall, S. W. 14, Golden Lane, London, E.C., 26th November, 1S14. Gentlemen, re Trading with the Enemy. Before war broke out with Turkey, in fact before War oroKe out m Europe at all, we executed an order for account of our client Mr. Fathalla Tomas Wahayed, Busreh, Persian Gulf. We dul y arranged shipment per the s.s. 'Kansas' from Liverpool to Busreh, via Bombay and documents have not been completed, and we want to know how we now stand in this matter. We have no means of knowing the nationality of Lr. Wahayed, and as you know Busreh is in Turkey, but we understand it has now been taken by Indian Forces and is present in British occupation. Will you please be kind enough to advise us whether we shall be quite in order in drawing on this client for the amount of the shipment, or whether it will be necessary for us to make arrangements for delivery to be taken at Bombay and the goods held there until such time as the war is over. ■se await the pleasure of your advice in the matter, and beg to remain, Yours faithfully, per pro Staveley and Co. (Sgd) A. Thompson.C12 ] In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote ‘xrt'LC'L and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, • London. 1u 1 k A\ r r K 1914 , Tlle Undersecretary of State/for Foreign Affairs presetds his compliments to the Undersecretary of State for ^-v^cLoc^ and, by direction of the Secretary * of State, transmits herewith cop\M of the under-mentioned papers • Foreigti Office, / (4 , 1914 . '*'&lt; ti 1 Reference to previous correspondence: to Letter Foreign Office: Description of Inc to sure.lopy. 80202 ). IX)NDON AND SOUTH WESTERN BANK ; LDvIITED, FOREIGN BRANCH, 168, FENCHURCH STREET, LONDON, E.C. December 7th, 1914. Dear Sir: We beg to inf oitti you that we have received an enquiry from a firm in Marseilles as to whether liquorice ('Bois-Rsglisse en Bailee pressees') pui'- * % cliased in Bassorah (Turkish territory in British occu pation), may he exported f rom that place to London in view of present circumstances or whether such export would he prohibited. We shall esteem it a favour if you will kindly advise us on this point at your early con venience . Thanking you in anticipation. v Secretary,o In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote no. 82i3i/m - and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. his coit of St a papers.In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote no. 8213//n+ . and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. 5208 I9!4 The Under-Secretary of State for Foreign A fairs presents his compliments to the Undersecretary of State for and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith copies of the under-mentioned papers, ,8 ^ &lt;1^ Foreign Office, 12 . 19^ • Reference to previous correspondence to Letter from Foreic J n °fi ce: Description of I)iclosure. Name and Date. Subject. &lt;T-fr\ y 14 nr:r&gt; 101 *- L .. r : . 1 (Similar letter sent to 1 12 ] 4rB n: ^ \ . % Communications on this subject should be addressed to— The Under secretary of State, Colonial Office, London, S.W., and the following number quoted :— ^ _ / ml™ Put ewsy W 2 in._-f. ^ 3 ^ 1 Reference to 'previous correspondence : sdJA ¥1 Letter ^/ n ^ T the C-kknmd Office of the 2-^ of 5^ Downing Street, M 19^ Sir, l am directed by the Secretary of Stale for the Colonies to transmit to you Sir, Your most obedient servant, / JOHN ANDERSON.Copy. fe 48429/14, The Secretary of State for the Colonies to the Goremora of Ceylon, kauritiua. ,, : ]ta, Gibraltar and the British Resident, Zanzibar, ( ^ent 6 ,Id p,m. 9th Jecember, 1914.) Prize Court. Please instruct Proper Officer that, if the case arises, oaiyo now on the hi*rh seas hi loiving to Basra merchants is not to be treated as enemy cargo and should be released. ‘HAJCOUHT. r&lt;In any further communication on the Bubject, please quote no. 78267/14. and address— , / 1 The Under secretary of State, Foreign Office, i London. • i 4 1 6 0 Sir:- i 914. Foreign Office December 5th, 1914. In reply to your letter of the 2nd instant P. 4662 t f regarding the treatment to be accorded to consignments of goods belonging to merchants at Basra, which are now on the high aeas, I am directed by Secretary Sir Edward Grey to state that he concurs in the proposal of the Marquess of Crewe that the Political Officer with the Expeditionary^ Force should be authorized to reassure enquirers on the point. I am to enclose a copy of a telegram to His Majesty’s Charge d’Affaires at Cairo on the subject and to suggest that a telegram in similar terms should be addressed to such Prize Courts under His Lordship’s jurisdiction as are likely to be affected in the matter. i y w A similar suggestion has been made to the Colonial Office, and a copy of the correspondence has been sent to His The Under Secretary of State, India Office.112 ] (fro) In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote No - 1S11 % and address— j l The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London, P 4 705 1914 7 /ic Uiidcr-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Under-Secretary of State for J and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith coP'XsS of the under-mentioned paper. 'J'C-Z co 1/7. tft'i / ffa-* tc t£# JSea Foreign Office, jj 3 0 , 1914 . Inference to previous correspondence : /&gt;* up tff r Description of Inclosure. Name and Date. Subject. 'y&amp;Mj . (/Sov.'iff &lt;^xy-ty~t&gt;(yy A ffi o^yft\Copy. r (^71C) YEHOtTO. HESKEL AMD COHPAIIY, 6, DICKTNnON STHEET, ’■AMCHKHTER. Movdriber 25th # 1914• Gen'le^n; - At the moment War hroko out with Turkey we had lying at The Elleman and Bucknall Steanohip Cornpany f B warehouse for storage at Bussorah,Tirrkoy , the following - 10P. Bales N (Y.H.6. Co.) Bagdad Idara Nos.5811/5912 Cotton Goods N E.H.N. Bagdad Idara 38/59 ' 116 « (Y.H.&amp; Co.) Bagdad Lynch 6104/6219 17 II E.R.N. 89/105 Bagdad Lynch and we notice this port has now been occupied hy our troops. lv&lt; i'‘l' Ac British oublectc and nerchants we should he ^ ^ t 0 ' grateful to know if you would give us any information in regard to these goods and if sane are still in existence mid intact. r ntelligence Foreign Department Office. Yours faithfully, (Si Tied) Y.Heskel and Company. \ •hrom Secretary of Slate to Viceroy, Foreign Department, 10th November 1914 . His Majesty’s represen- Foreign Secret. Following telegram sent to tatives abroad, dated 9th November : — ' His Majesty’s Government having annexed Cyprus, all natives of that island, unless domiciled m the Ottoman dominions elsewhere than in Km-pt are to be considered British subjects, and may he given passports as 'such provided that they produce satisfactory evidence such as a passport issued m the island or proof of birth therein. “In view of the military occupation of Fgypt Egyptians are henceforth to be considered as British-protected persons, and mav be given passports describing them as natives of Egypt. They should, however, be required to establish fact that they were born in Egypt and that they are not domiciled m any part of Ottoman dominions other than Egypt or in service of Ottoman Government or have taken special steps to retain Ottoman nationality.”From My telegrj expedite reply Foreign S( Following is s - of General Off good friend 1 into this war, to assure Tui Turkey paid ] Britain. Bril Basra and nei and administ Government I and were pre] flag t hey woul secular affairs, business with( to treat popuk was expected . This is sea • I21 5o&lt;5 From Secretary of State to Sir P. Cox, 30th November 1914. Mj telegram dated 24tli November. Basra proclamation. Please expedite reply. From Viceroy, 30th November 1914. Foreign Secret. Proclamation, Basra. Cox telegraphs 27th November. summary of proclamation issued over my signature on behalf of General Officer Commanding :— Reminds^ public that Great Britain greatest Mohamadan powers always good mend 1 urkey, and repeatedly urged Turkey against being inveigled into this war, and^ in the event of her abstaining undertook with her allies to assure Turkey’s integrity and independence, but mislead by Germany Turkey paid no heed and by her hostile behaviour forced war upon Great Britain. British expedition consequently despatched and had occupied Basra and neighbourhood and British flag had now replaced Turkish flag and administration in this region. But though at war with Turks [?] Government British had no enmity or design against the local inhabitants and were prepared to be their friends and protectors. Under th e British flag th ey would en joy prote cticm and freedom both in their religious and secular affairs. They were at liberty to pursue their normal avocations and business without apprehension, and troops had received strictest instructions to treat population with utmost courtesy and consideration and same attitude was expected from them.” This is sent with reference to your telegram of 24th November.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000419.0x0001cb_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/10/564</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000419.0x0001cb</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/10/564</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>File 3104/1915 Pt 1 ‘German War: conquered territory: status: question of trading; looting, etc. of goods by Turks.’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1914/1915</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-02-22T22:30:23</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (198 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the volume.The subject 3104 (German War: conquered territory, Mesopotamia: trade) consists of 9 volumes, IOR/L/PS/10/564-572. The volumes are divided into ten parts, with parts 1 to 8 comprising one volume each, and parts 9 and 10 comprising the last volume.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the first folio with 1 and terminates at the last folio with 200; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. The foliation sequence does not include the front and back covers, nor does it include the leading and ending flyleaves.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Correspondence and other papers relating to the status of cargo consignments held at Basra, Mesopotamia, for export to Britain, during the British invasion of Turkish Mesopotamia [Iraq] in November 1914. The file includes: discussion as to whether consignments of cargo that are on their way from Basra to Britain should be considered enemy cargo; reports of the looting and destruction of British goods held at the customs house in Basra by the Turks; enquiries made to the Foreign Office by several companies based in Manchester, England (and their legal representatives), concerning claims for losses incurred in the wake of their cargo at Basra having been destroyed or looted; lists of cargo stored at Basra by various British companies, with descriptions of the good, quantities, and prices.The file’s principal correspondents are: the Foreign Office; the Under Secretary of State for India; and Manchester solicitors Boote, Edgar, Grace &amp; Rylands.The file includes a divider which gives the subject number, the year the subject file was opened, the subject heading, and a list of correspondence references by year. This is placed at the back of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Permanent Under-Secretary of State for India</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Boote, Edgar &amp; Rylands, solicitors and notaries</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Basra</geographic></subject><subject><topic>First World War (1914-1918)</topic></subject><subject><topic>Mesopotamian Campaign (1914-1918)</topic></subject><subject><topic>International trade</topic></subject><subject><topic>Looting</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000419.0x0001cb#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>