<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000254_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T11:59:44.780Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">CONFIDENTIAL. iier-General A. \\ , Money, General Hea&lt;lqnart&lt;M*s, Indian Expeditionary Force D,' to India OHice. No. Ig. 1983. Basrah, ^ ir ' 22nd January 191(5. In continuation of my letter No. Ig. 105(5, dated 19th November 191^, 1 furnish a further re])ort on the tribal situation ;— (JeueraL I. 1 he check received by our lorce at Ctesiphou on 22nd November temporarily changed what had up to that time been our uninterrupted policy ol steady advance into Mesopotamia into an SO mile withdrawal on our main line of operations. 1 his might reasonably have been expected to have produced a marked elFect throughout the whole theatre of operations. Such has not, however, proved to be the case. With one notable exception (that of Khayun-el- ' H)ei(l at Shattra, to whom reference will be made later) the tribes have retained their former attitude which may be roughly summarised as upstream ol us, hostile ; downstream, friendly. • Euphrates Line. 2. 1 ribes in neighbourhood ol Nasiriyah are friendly. Ajaimi of the Muntafik is in neighbourhood of Samawa, with but a small following; he is the first actively hostile element upstream of us on the Euphrates. Desert tribes between Zobiur and Nasiriyah are not of much account. \\ e have strong allies at each end—Sheikh Ibrahim of Zobeir and Sheikh Hamad at Khamsieh. Shatt-al-Hn i. Stirred up by the exertions of a Turkish oflieer (Mizher Bey) at Shattra, the AI Abudah Chief Khayun-el-Obeid (of Shattra) together with a portion of the Kaffajah tribe immediately south of that place) have abandoned the attitude oi allegiance to the British, which had been won for us by our victory at Kut-al-Amarah in September last, and showed their active hostility by an attack ou a reconnaissance which went out from the British camp at Butaniyah ^between Nasiriyah and Shattra) on Uth January. 4. this Khayun-el-Obeid is an ill-conditioned chieftain who constantly proved a thorn in the Hesh to the Turks and on more than one occasion defeated Turkish expeditions despatched against him. Upstream of him again, along the Shatt-al-Hai, the Qaraqul, Beni Uichab, and Shawelat are now doubtless influenced by his new example though we have no positive proof thereof. fj. Finally, at the head of the waterway, are the actively hostile Beni Rubiah who extend up river as far as Baghialah, actively friendly to us alter September, but now entirely turned round since our retirement and tlie Turkish advance from Ctesiphon.9 (') To sunniiarise, the Shutt-ui-llai cjills loi conlrc)! by military iorce. \iid a column should operate down Irom Kut to Nasiriyah as scon as may be convenient, after the relief of Kut. Tigris Line. 7. Working upstream from Quruah, the important clans of tlie A1 bu Muhammad marsh Arabs between Qnrnah and Amarah have shown no si^ns ol unrest whatever during the last six months. 1 revenue business has been ])roceeding in a normal way. 8. From Amarah up to the present scene of hostilities the situation is equally satisfactory. Our former enemy (ihadhban of the Hani Lam has twice recently provided us with camels, and his attitude lias continued satisfactory. To avoid inter-tribal disturbance he has lately been ordered to proceed East of the Dawairij River, ami he has lately written a con gratulatory letter dated 11th on hearing of the British success at Sheikh Saad. 1'pstream of Kut are the two big tribes of Zubaid and Shammar Toqah Arabs. Our opportunities between the battles of Kut and Ctesiphon ♦ A proportion of both dwell above any Were UX) lew t0 a ^ (nv 1,s l() Properly point we have reached and were at the ingratiate Ourselves with the lower mercy of the Turks. . - .•. ± , . sections•' ot these tribes (though a good beginning was made) and it is therefore too much to expect them to have remained aloof from Turkish influence during recent events. Kamn. Ml. 1 he Chaab, Hawi, and other tribes subject to our staunch ally, the Sheikh ol Muhammareh, are all quiet, and affairs arc satisfactory in that direction. II. As regards the oil lields, pro-lJerman influencest are undoubtedly + u i , . . ,, constantIv active among the Hakhtiaris T oaseii on Ispahan and Ham Hormuz, but have been unsuccessful sod'ar, and ihere appears to be no present reason to fear any change in this situation. 1 he demeanour oi their Khans in Feheran has lately been very satisfactory &lt;mt ' ' 11 absence ol any specilic set-back to the Allies no difficulty is contemplated by ilis Majesty's Minister in getting them to countersign any agieement arrived at between the British and . the Bakhti aris ia the Oil 1 ields Aiea. I his is now under negotiation, though an interruption has jnst o( ( niled thtough the rumoured departure of the Khans to Behbelian until March. Hie Chiel Political Officer, however, is disinclined to impute a sinist. i motive to this movement, pending further knowledge of their reasons lor it, information regarding which is expected from Dr. Vonng shortly. 11'. Die \\ r ali of Pusht-i-Kuh has been another object of pro -Germqii lll,Me ' 111 ' '' e a vacillating and unsatisfactory character, but, though suspected of having coquetted with German emissaries, the influence of ^on and ol Ins subjects have so lar prevented his siding with the lurks. '' ll ^ ^' ( ' ' 'I't'eal Officer is endeavouring to maintain touch with hiiu through the Political Officer Ainarah.I.!. Jtussiau action towards Kirmanshah an,I Ispahan is expected to have a very , ons,derable effect in discouraging pro-Gern.an propaganda both among the Hakhtiaris and in Pnsht-i-Knh. Persia. 14. A defensive Rritlsh-l'ersian allianc.. is now the subject of negotiation between His Britannic Majesty's Minister and the Persian Prime Minister at I'eheran. The main advantage of this would be the failure of German hopes of an Islamic Union. 1.). I he recent success of the Gendarmes and the Nationalist party at Shiraz resulting in the departure of the Governor-General of Fars is expected by the Political Department to he likely to lead to a Gendarme- Xationalist movement either against the pro-British confederacy of Khans at Shahankareh and Hayat Haoud, or against Bushire or both. Latest reports show the Saulat (rnler of the Qashqais) as being likely to allow his subjects to support such anti-British action. Total numbers wiio might thus become involved are very considerable. The Gendarmes have Mountain Artillery (but the Russian menace against Ispahan may curtail the number likely to be brought towards Bushire). I he approach to Bushire is, however, such as to render it highly improbable that any movement sufficiently formidable to render the reinforcement of Bushire imperative could take place with our getting due warning. A rabia. 10. The Chief Political Oihcer during the last days of 1915 concluded a treaty with Ibn Saoud. The attitude of the latter was all that could be desired throughout the negotiations and his allegiance may be reckoned on throughout the war. The lately installed Shaikh of Koweit is equally well disposed to us, as was his late father Ibn Mubarak. AlVairs in those directions are therefore entirely satisfactory. And the recent rumours of a combined hostile movement against us by Ibn Rashid and the Sherif of .Mecca have lately been entirely discredited. 1 have 1 , etc., A. W. Monky , Brigadier-General, for General Officer Commanding Indian Expeditionary Force 'D.' The Secretary to the Government of India, Foreign and Political Department. Memorandum. Copy of the above forwarded for information. \V. H. Beach , Lieutenant-Colonel, w for General Officer Commanding Indian Expeditionary Force ' D.' The Political Secretary, India Office. The Chief of the General Stall', India.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000254_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/18/B226</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000254</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/18/B226</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Letter from Brigadier-General Arthur Wigram Money, General Headquarters, India Expeditionary Force "D", Basrah [Basra] to the Secretary to the Government of India, Foreign and Political Department, India Office</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1916/1916</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-10-22T14:34:22</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (2 folios)</extent><extent>Foliation: The foliation for this description commences at folio 28 and terminates at folio 29, as it is part of a larger physical volume; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is also present in the volume; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled, and can be found in the same position as the main sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The confidential letter reports on the tribal situation in Mesopotamia [Iraq], describing the various tribes located in the different listed geographic areas and noting whether they were friendly or hostile to British forces. The sections in the letter include:General - reporting on the check received by the British force at Ctesiphon, 22 November 1915, which had temporarily changed the progress of their advance, but that it had not appeared to have changed the tribes attitudes towards them;Euphrates Line, reporting on the tribes of the Nasirayah [al-Nāsirīyah] neighbourhood and of Ajaimi [al-‘Ajamī] of the Muntafik [al-Muntafiq] who was in the Samawa [al-Samāwah] neighbourhood;Shatt-al-Hai [Shaṭṭ al-Gharrāf], reporting that Khayun-el-Obeid, the Chief of Al Abudah had been stirred up by Turkish officers and had now abandoned his allegiance to Britain, detailing which other chiefs in the area were likely to follow him, and reporting on the Bani Rubiah who were now actively hostile towards them;Tigris Line, reporting that good relations had continued with some of the tribes along river, with the exception of the Zubaid [al-Zubayd] and Shammar Toqah Arabs as there had not been sufficient time to develop British relations with them;Karun [Kārūn], reporting that there were tribes in the area loyal to the Shaikh of Muhammareh (Shaikh Khaz‘al bin Jābir al-Ka‘bī) [Muhammarah, now Khorramshahr] , an ally of the British, and that Germany had attempted to gain influence around the oil-fields in the area, but had not succeeded;Persia, discussing the British-Persian alliance which was under negotiation, and the fact that the British would have sufficient warning should any force move towards Bushire;Arabia, reporting on the conclusion of a treaty with Ibn Saʻūd and relations with the new Shaikh of Kuwait (Jābir bin Mubārak Āl Sabāh).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="personal"><namePart>Sir Arthur Wigram Money Knight</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Mesopotamia</geographic></subject><subject><topic>First World War (1914-1918)</topic></subject><subject><topic>Mesopotamian Campaign (1914-1918)</topic></subject><subject><topic>Tribes</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000254#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>