<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0003ad_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T10:56:52.588Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">microfilmed document DO NOT PHOTOCOPY USE IOR NEG———».,*i a vcuoe j» i,o iiiipor. largo quaixPilic 3 of axiux im,o either Persi m or furbish territory &amp; it appears to me that the authorities of aitaer count aright tr P effect/ Ms arrest on this account alone ^ we should have nothing to 3 :£ in Ms defence • Indeed » one miaour of his capture hy the -Turkish authorities at '$&amp; i^asra ha/s already reacned me 9 though I am inclined to i.reat it &lt;V3 a wild flight of the imagination * 10 9 * Oomparei with tnis escapable , the interference in the affairs of General Arabia -would appeal* mere lid’s pias • 10 # With much hesitation in deal inn with matters of such grave import » I venture to suggest that onlf tiro courses are or on to ns :- (a) to administer a shatfp mionstrance 'bo Sheikh llobamk » supportim it with '3uch a show of force &gt; as will make it evident to him tiiat vn. ai‘e his masters &gt; as well as protectors &amp; ucan to bo so S? insist on the scrupulous fulfiliaent &gt; soxar as is now possible 9 o-, all the various promises txait ha has made &amp; broken « An important point would be tiia cioport-ation of throe n or four of the principal Importers of anas * It does nol seem to me that there would be an5 serious local opposition 9 even if the inhabitants vmre capable Oi.The Major is p^r his way ho Shiraz.: I am :forwarding: your NO: 5315 Whim by the earliest, possible means. IJ * ' Pv / 1'Ieaxiv.h.ile, I venhure a comment on para 3 of your letter ' y m? It is true that Sheihh hhazaal is no longer Governor of Arabistan ant his precise position at present as a Persian Official is not quite clear,but there is no doubt that he is a Persian Gificial,with the Persian title of Sardar Arfa,and is moreover so far on the best terms with Sardar Mukarram,the Governor of Arabistan, so that Sheihh Kubarak’s proceedings seem to me more defensible internationally than you consider them,he could always say that the Persian Authorities had asked him to assist in quelling a rebellion in their territory and in doing so he was shewing his friendliness to the Persian Government and their local representatives. Of course if they cross the Turkish frontier after the Beni Truf it will be a different matter,but even so Sheikh.Shell* ZhaEzal is in charge,and the respon- sit 11 ity will he his.Similarly if Government send SHeiMi ISiazzal orders to desist Kutarak ought to come away,tut so far there i- no reason to suppose that they will do so. So I donL think that Sheikh Kutarak has committed any offence against- international law comparable e.g.to Admiral favies’ proceedings at Jamaica. These constant reports of Sheildi ilha^zal' s oeatn are curious. As far as HcTouall’s information goes (I enclose copies of the pertinent references in his last 3 diaries) he is merely carrying on his recurrent punitive proceedings against the border Arabs,on a rather larger scale than usual.12th, 14th, 16th. 17th. 13th. 20th. 21 St . 25 th. hxt^racts from Mohammerah diary. 9th to ,15th June 1907. The forces of Sardar Arfa have left the Karim to operate against iiawijeh, he hopes by show of strength to induce tne -deni Truf and Beni Sala to submit reinforcements to follow. S. S. 'Nusret' arrived from Bender Nasseri with cargo and passengers including the headmen of huhaysin and Cha’a-b, who have been in attendance on Sardar Arfa, to raise their contingents. •dheil-h ITubarek arrived in his yacht from Koweit. The forces which have started under lianzal Khan nephew of tardor Arfa are 1200 horse of Bawi tribe. The Shurfa of Kawijeh have joined the Beni Truf. The three revolted tribes are variously estimated from five to' ten thousand fighting men. -ran left for Bender Musafferi with first contin gent of Mahaysin provisions, rifles, and cartridges, sheikh Mubarak’s yacht returned, from I'ao. 2. S. 'Nusret' left for Bender Muzafferi with provisions tor the army. Also launch 'Nassery' towing lighter with levies. Contingents from Sh^-el-Arab river are still coming in. 500 men remain atjrahlia (Bandar Arfa’s palace as garrison/ 23rd to 29th June. B. Y. 'Iran' left for Bend.er Muzafferi with the eight gunners and some of Muhaysin levies. S. Y. 'Karoon' and S. S. 'Nusreh' arrived from Bender Muzafferi and after coaling left for that place. They pick up lighters with levies who have preceded them. The Beni Truf and Beni Saleh are making offers of submi ssion, which are not accepted. The Sardar Arfa intends to prevent their yearly rebellion. 26 thmemmnm 26t;h. Tlie Oha*ab have crossed ho hhe right, bank of' bhe Karun at, Nasseri and the Muhaysin at Um-el-Temer. The former are to operate against the Beni Truf and the latter against Kawijeh. About 5000 Bawi are in advance and total forces amount to about 25000-men. 29t£i. Sheikh Hub are k of Koweit is still at Bender i/IuzaTferi with the Sardar Arfa. He has lent him some Bedliin to guard Ousba during absence of tribesmen.26t-Iu The Cha’ab have crossed to the right bank o:f the Tarur at Nasser! and the Muhaysin at Um-el-Temer. The former are to operate against the Beni Truf and tne latter against Hawijeh* About 5000 Bawi are in advance and total forces amount to about 25000 men. 29t|i. Sheibh Hub are k of Koweit is still at Bender Lluzafferi with the Sardar Arfa. He has lent him some Bed*in to guard Gusba during absence of tribesmen.Mo: /£/a of 1907. British Residency and Consulate-General, Bushire, as' 'July 1907. A copy of the undermentioned letter is forwarded with compliments to the Political Agent, ho we it, for information, with reference to his letter No: 313 dated 22nd June 1907.tfe. no* /(&gt; fI /£ Of IPQ7. Frora 0 0 British Basidanoy and Consulate-Saner.al, Sj\iraz. July 1^07. Qu&amp;biirie StS Major P* 21 . Co 3 C t C. I* M. t Political E^fsidant# in tlie Persian 'Kill* To Sir Lo ills Dane* K. 0* • C. H. I. , Heoretax^y to tne ‘lovainuiant of in the Foroign Da^aruaent* S I M L A. Sir t I have u/ie honour to for.fard for Cihe ln- fo mat ion of the Jovernuent of India a copy of a Koweit Ho. 313 dated 33nd June l o 07. I oorm unioation^ which I have received fror. the Poiitioal Agent at Koneit on tne subject of Siiaikh Ktubarak * e recent visits to ; lahorii.erslx, 2. On receipt, before I left Bushire. of tne derd-official oor^unication mentioned in ^arapra^h 3 thereof, I let Major tr nox iciow informally that 1 did not ^repose to take any action until I had received further and. parallel illumination on the suojiect from Mis Majesty’s Ooneul at ]labor:or.lere^u Up to the tine I left for 8hiras on 26th June Mr. ) !o T &gt;oual.l # e reports did not give me the impression that any deterrent action on my yart was either neces— is&amp;xy or useful, nor indeed was any possible, as X was not in %nv case in a position to com municate ouicx.ly or satis factor! ly vita Shaikh Jfubarak in tiiae for 2 ~r advice to be of use. Major Knox * s letter No. 313 no’ r enclosed arrived after I had left Bushire and followed me to Shiraz, where, on arrival. 1 ascertained by telegraph from Bushire taat tue shaikh of ;iaiaoi an 1 s w■'lahoniaarfth’s operations had -oarminatedi xhit Uv&gt;X a^; \ }iad 9ffeot.iV9l7 toroii it hue .•■ani Truf to aaelj and/^) ’tiiat# j'!ubaraK Aa&lt;i ravam^d *to Koweit#* Under uiroiuusbanoes ws can afford t#o oxa- rd.ne 'Ude several of ‘one incident with deliber ation. $• Stated briefly the position was as follows: ShaiJLii Xa al in hi i official oa^aoity of lovem- or on behalf of the D arsi .n .lovemment of wie )4anora- nerah dietriot and appanages, having for a long tir-.e ^aeu had difficulties witi the Beni Truf* owint to non-^ayiaont of revenue b:r Uxm.,. ultliaatelj fomid niu- self obliged to take the field against Shaiki'i Xubarah learnings tiat his fast friend was having an anxi'vus ttae • and a,l so proi^ted no doubt by trie oon- si deration that were %aikh Kasai defeated, his ovn security for larf a sms of money lent to aim would be greatly yrajunioed, proceeded to Ma}eommax*ah in his steen yaxro to su^nort his ally witi his yrasenea and &lt;3 ° r '- 1 Xe took wit/i nim at the sane tine (and sent hi ^ vassal back for a second consignment) a laiT-e quantity of email arms a-al ar^ .unitionj watersixins♦ and other articles likely to ^rove useful to his ally* * T e also arranged at SnaixA Kasai’s request to y laoe of his own man ten.^orarily 'to garrison the Xaiioi.- uerah outpost of Xasben opposite Jlajiorm.erajm in order to free itj ^.resent Arab garrison for service vita 'diaikh Xasa.l * 3 fi eld-force. • Looking at tae picture from taa most favour- ac 1 a poinu of view we see knaika fubarak rendering? prompt and yeoman lervice to his friend the Persian jovemor of i-heioszei.eraa* with a result greatly to the benefit of the 'Persian A&lt;1rhnistration and of law and P^rder in Arabistan* .as well as to tne enh.ancei.ent of the ^restire of their representative. If trie Persian fovernr .ant t&lt;ai;e exception to Xtaiph T 'asal receiving help from Shaikh X,xbaiw^., it 1-3 ^resu];ably bj Mi to them to display ouch signs of their displeasure towm ^ n !■ Ocpy of a telegram No: 104 dated 50th June 1907, from H.B.M's Minister Teheran, to Resident Bushire. he are accused by the Russians of organising an alliance between the Sheibhs of Mohammerah. and Rowe it with a view to the &lt; independence of the former. ^ Wicked man! Please let me have your observations by telegraph. Copy of a telegram Nor 109/424 dated. 3rd July 1907, from the First Assistant Resident (In charge current duties) to H.B.M’s Minister Teheran. i? y Please refer to your telegram No: 104. The Resident who is on his way to Shiraz is out of telegraphic touch. Sheikh Mubarek fre quently visits Mohammerah without informing the Political Agent before-hand and did so on this occasion. There is nothing 'unusual in the punitive expedition of the Sheikh ff Mohammerah against the Beni Truf, as it is a frequent occurrence for this tribe to be in revolt. The accusation made by the Russians is of course entirely, without foundation. (Bill).No. 150J or 1907. GOVERNMENT OP INDIA. FOREIGN DEPARTMENT. SECRET. External. To The Right Hon’ble JOHN MORLEY, O.M., IBs Majesty's Secretary of State for India, Simla, the 5th September 1907, Sir, We have the honour to forward herewith copies of correspondence* regard ing the conduct of the Sheikh of Koweit * Letter from the Political Resident in the Persian i n taking part in an expedition Organized ?907 with 1 enclosures,^ 00tiadated the 28fch Jaly ^7 the Sheikh of Mohammerah against his rehellious tribesmen. 2. It appears that Sheikh Khazal of Mohammerah found himself obliged to take strong measures in his capacity as Persian Governor of the Mohammerah District, in order to compel the tribesmen of the Beni Truf to pay their revenue. Sheikh Mubarak, about the middle of June, proceeded to Moham- merah in his steam-yacht for the purpose of supporting his friend. He took with him a large quantity of small arms and ammunition, waterskins and other articles which he handed over to Sheikh Khazal, and he subsequently sent his vessel back for a second consignment. He also arranged, at Sheikh Khazal’s request, to garrison the Mohammerah outpost of Kasheh temporarily with some of his own men, so as to free the Arab garrison for service with the field force. The operations resulted in the surrender of the Beni Truf. Although the operations in which Sheikh Khazal was engaged are described merely as the reduction to order of a rebellious tribe the Beni Truf, we have reason to believe from a note by Colonel Burton, when acting as Consul at Mohammerah in 1904, that the Sheikh has contemplated the reduction of this tribe for some time, with the object of extending his unquestioned territorial authority to Hawizeh on the Turkish frontier; so that the proceedings have probably more than a temporary and local significance and may form part of a scheme for consolidating the Arab power in these regions under a central head. 3, We consider that by conveying arms and ammunition up^ the Shatt-el-Arab in his private yacht without the ^ authority or permission of the Persian Government, the Sheikh ran the risk of involving himself m serious difficulties with that Government or with the Turkish authorities, m either of which cases diplomatic complications affecting His Majesty s Gov ernment might have arisen. The Persian Government might reasonably imagine that the prompt assistance rendered by Mubarak to Sheikh Khazal would encourage the latter to assert his independence, should he find a conve nient opportunity for doing so, while the Porte might regard the incident as an indication of Mubarak’s growing disregard of Turkish suzerainty and he mig t r!even have been alliance between f Vide enclosure. tVide correspondence forwarded with roreign Secretary’s letters No. 41 M., dated the 11th October 1906, and No. 45 M., dated the 8th November 1906. , 1 « -mVafA for Diving: in Turkish waters with an arrested as a p arme( j vessel. We understand* that the ^ 9 to letter from the Poll- Minister at Tehran has received intimation that the Russians suspect the British fidential), dated the 28th July 1907. authorities of haying organised an ^hpikhs of Mohammerah and Koweit with a view ^ to the ttle Sh independence of the former, and it is also 1 reportedf from Mohammerah that ^ the Persian i.'£SX,p .kieh *&gt;« preceding remarks were written. „ , ,, 4 The possibility of a coalition between these Sheikhs who occupy the territory dominating the head of the Gulf had not escaped our attention, Ind n connection with this incident we venture to invite a reference to ana m cuo ^ apprehensions which we expressed in our telegram J No. S.—100, dated the 8th October 1906, to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, as to the possible formation of a confederacy of Arab Sheikhs led by Sheikh Mubarak and the Sheikh of Mohamraerah in order to secure their independence of foreign dominion. The attitude assumed by Sheikh Mubarak appears to favour the supposition that he is at all events desirous of drawing closer the bonds between himself and Sheikh Khazal, even to the extent of furnishing armed assistance to the ^ latter in Persian territory, so that the matter will have to be closely watched in future. 5. As you are aware, the Agreement§ concluded 'with the Sheikh of Koweit § Vide our Secret despatch No. 35 (External), OU the 23rd January 1899 Contain^ UO dated tbe 23rd February 1899. stipulation aS to the conduct of the Sheikh’s external relations by the British Government, but merely provides that the Sheikh shall not, without the previous sanction of the British Govern ment, receive the representative of any Poreign Power at Koweit, or give for occupation or any other purpose any portion of his territory to the Government or subjects of any other Power. Por so long as these stipulations are observed, the good offices of the British Government were promised under the Agree ment to the Sheikh. This formal Agreement has, however, since been modified by the messages conveyed to the Sheikh in compliance with Lord George Hamilton’s telegram of the 27th September 1901, in connection with the differences between the Sheikh of Koweit and the Amir of Nejd, and the Hon’ble St. John Brodrick’s telegram of the 3rd February 1904, when a conflict was feared between the Sheikh, in combination with Sadun Pasha, and certain Arab tribes under Turkish protection. On both these occasions the Sheikh of Koweit was informed that His Majesty’s Government would use their good offices on his behalf only if he refrained from aggression and was guided by da!e&lt;Tthe i^h ^ 1907 eDdins with your tolegram &gt; their advice ; and His Majesty’s Govern- ... '• ment recently contemplated ij conveying a smu ar message to tbe Sheikh, in order to prevent him from making reprisals rT 6, ma y&gt; consequence, be held to be the settled policy iL-.n r V lsh -D G&lt; ? Verrimeut . that the external relations of Koweit should be in Pnwm*c an Ss 1,1 We cons ^ er that our position in Koweit vis-a-vis other now V&gt;p PwlL/r i 6 * great j y streri gthened if this principle of policy could he taken of a g r eement; and advantage might perhaps of the neontiatirm ^ aza ^ s re cent warlike expedition in Mohammerah and to add the rennidf 120 ^ in h r0 &amp; ress ^ or purchase of the Koweit foreshore, Sheikh Mubarak ^ » n ClaUSe ., t0 the . Agreement to be executed in which exclusion of all forpio* PP aren ^ y anxious to repeat his pledges as to the — Tn 0 dtTn 1 er !i tS “ Koweit than the British? It might be way of asubsidv the cure ? ll eS!)e i kh’s consent to this addition, to increase, by y or a subsidy, the annual payment of Rs. 60,000 for which the Sheikh has _ T r ' dt Wes*™, dated the asth Anga»t 1907 . as ked^f as rent for the foreshore ; but we consent without the nmmieo „ s t° uld &gt; °t course, attempt to obtain his may also be able to utilise this L l ln ® reas ® d P a y ment ; Our Political Agent recent adventure of Sheikh Mubarak as a leverto induce him to give us the reservations required on reasonable terms. We now have the honour to request your sanction to the foregoing proposal; and, if xu \_AJ 1 L 1 1A10L11AC3 auocxj. u\j .U.AO A»xa/jooi/jr o VJ U v ciumcilli, W t3 WUU1U cISIS. bllctli yOUF Views may be communicated to us by telegraph, since the Sheikh has stated that his offer regarding the foreshore will only remain open for two months with effect, as we understand, from the 14th August; and it would he convenient that the negotiations regarding the proposed addition to the Agreement should be con ducted simultaneously with those regarding the foreshore. 6. If His Majesty’s Government do not approve of this proposal, we con sider that the Sheikh should be informed that the Government of India take strong exception to the share taken by him in the recent expedition in Arabistan and that, unless he seeks and is guided by our advice in such matters, we shall not be able to exercise our good offices on his behalf. We have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient, humble servants,Confidential 'o: 5l« 0 f 1^07 .CTo f; ' , &amp;*) 5 ^ rom Lajor S.—. ^nox, I.i # Political i.gent , -^oweit # lo Lajor P*z.Cox, I.A., i •esiMent ^ s Gonsul—f^enelfal in t.te * Persian, (hilt , Lushire. ^/- -loweit 23/9/7, Sir, T have the honour to invite a reference to correspondence on the subject of the possibility of a coalition between the Arab Sheihho at the head of the Pulf * last alluded to in paragraph 4 of Secret exter nal patch no: I50&gt; dated the 6th of September 1907 from the C-overnment of India to the Secretary of State for India , ac • An incident I do not wish to exaggerate its importance- has recently come to notice which is perhaps suggestive in this connection • Sheikh , Isa T ud ul i.&gt;ugam with his son Oadah visited me thid morning both dressed in robes of honour . 1‘he^ are usually in rags , Isaud , before his departure , had to beg me ior an abba xor his son to enable him to make a proper appearance on Sheikh Lobarak * s w acht. 7 • It appears that the,/ accompanied Sheikh Mobarak on his last visit to lluhamnierah and received valuable presents when there from Sheikh Ahazal .1 should sa^ that the clothes the^ were wearing would be worth at least one hundred dollars „about ZIZ, % I learnt that they received cash presents besides ,i‘hey were deeply impressed with a senseof Sheikh .Oiazal^ magnificence. I have the honour to be , Sir, Political Agent , ^oweit.Z ~?~ ?0. . Telegrsau FROM 9 Foreign 9 Simla • 1/ Ho* S 474 9 dated 12-10-07 V (P)* Following dated October the 8th hae been 1 received from the Secretary of State and Is repeated for Information* * Please see paragraphs 8 &amp; 8 of your letter Ho* 150$ dated the 5th ultimo# Kowelt and Mahomerah# Ho action should be taken at present in the direction of either proposal • It will be a matter for consideration whether on conclusion of the foreshore negotiations* the warning given to the Sheikh of Koweit in 1901 and 1904 should not be repeated • 11 '1 M ' y; &gt; : » (Foreign)» ) v ; -- Hv [Confidential j No. 2196, dated Bushire, the 12th (received 22nd) October 1907. From—J. H. Bill, Esq., I.C.S., First Assistant Resident, In charge current duties, To—S ir Louis Dane, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department, Simla. With reference to this office letter No. 2477, dated 21st October 1906, on Kow.it, No, 529 , dated a8th September ,9.7. ‘ h ® object of a possible Arab confederacy, I nave the honour to forward, for the in formation of the Government of India, a copy of the communication marginally noted received from the Political Agent, Koweit, in this connection. No. 529, dated Koweit, the 28th September 1907. From—M ajor S. G. Knox, I.A., Political Agent, Koweit, To—MAJOR P. Z. COX, LA., C.I.E., Resident and His Britannic Majesty's Consul- General in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. I have the honour to invite a reference to correspondence on the subject of the possibility of a coalition between the Arab Sheikhs at the head of the Gulf, last alluded to in paragraph 4 of Secret—External Despatch No. 150J, dated the 5th of September 1907, from the Government of India to the Secretary of State for India. 2. An incident—I do not wish to exaggerate its importance—has recently come to my notice which is perhaps suggestive in this connection. Sheikh Isaud ul Fugam with his son Badah visited me this morning both dressed in robes of honour. They are usually in rags. Isaud, before his departure, had to beg me for an abba for his son to enable him to make a proper appearance on Sheikh Mubarak’s yacht. 3. It appears that they accompanied Sheikh Mobarak on his last visit to Muhammerah and received valuable presents when there from Sheikh Khazal. I should say that the clothes they were wearing would be worth at least one hundred dollars, about ^12, and I learnt that they received cash presents besides. They were deeply impressed with a sense of Sheikh Khazal’s magnificence. G,C B. P* Simla.—No. C-Si6 F. D.— 30 . 20 -e 7 .~ 14 .—J-D.-neqo' 1 ai ions » he »irould. prove as in tract able and ungrat*e*fal f even indolent ,as Hheikh Jlobarak , on occasions , shows himself to be^ 4 * The latter 9 indeed » ^rtated aha' , if Bheikh^*- Khaz 1 al * s request was not acceded to , \,he two would combine to thwart British interests in the Gulf . lifnile I am. not blind to the fact that much of this must be regarded as the arguments that the Sheikh *• bought most likely to appeal to me , &amp; therefore not seriously , the possibility of such arguments being used is not without its significance* 5 . The interview , coupled with Shaikh** Mobarak 1 s recent requests for the protection of his Fao estate 6 compels me to the belief that the Sheikhs arP aiming %% a complete independence of both Persian and Turk- ish control over i he mouth of the Shatt el Arab f while Sheikh Ilobarak at least appears fondly to ima^^ ine that the British Government is likely to prove a subservient instrument to his ambitious views • 6 • The conversation » apart from what I have already noted above was confined to vague generalities , if I except the question of customs » Sheikh Mobarak declared tlat he had warned Sheikh khaz’al that he was committing a grievous error in permitting the Persian claim to the revenues of the port ox he had conceded the point at the urgent instance of His Excellency the British Minister at Teheran , who had promised him that , if the Persians broke faith in any 7 of the conditions on which they had Muhamuerah , while Sheikh Khaz'al informed me that support , leading no control • Sheikh Kh * many such grievances j «3 auiA uotniiv; had. roaultKd .r 7 # la re pi, %o all this 9 I stated that Shei&amp;h lihaz’al had hoacmred me with his confidence % at the same time embarrassed me considerably by inviting my opinion on cuestions that were completely beyond m v purview , that he had already infomed me,in the course of conversation #t3nat his wishes » ambitions and grievances were before the Political Resident in the Persian Crulf and His hxcellenc^ the British Uin*t ister at i'eheran and how could he expect me to give an^ opinion , while such high authorities were t almo^^ Certainly , considering hie position * £oth Sheikh Mobarak and Sheikh ^ihaz*al then combined to assure me that the^ were one and the same and that it was impossible for me to be an. efficient Political Agent at ;ioweit , while affecting to ignore the problems of Muhammerah . It seemed unnecessary to repl, to this view of my position and I assured them that the communication with which the* had honoured me would be faithfully transmitted to higher authority I have the honour to be Sir * Tour most obedient servant * ? Major Political Agent , £oweit.Kcweit, 1 tth. Oct© 1909. T© f in charge ^^eaidency, ZIt, * Lave tb.c Lencnr t« rejcrt tLo sub- -atabce f a ccnvaraaticn wbicb JLeikL Mnbara a few days ago -k Laid witL me ©n tLe affairs ©f tbe JLoikL of MrLammerab in case it may prove of interos/' to u rvornmont # 2 . Itappears that shortly after Wajor Cox 1 a las^t visit to hammerxh Jheikh KLazal called together the Loa,d men of his tribes and d is classed with them the advantages of definitely binding himself to the British by a document , which evidently from Jheikh Mubarak 1 s description was intended to be a rognalr treaty on more or less equal terms* The headmen of the tribes were very averse to any such proposal pointing cut that though they might make a treajry and so avoid Persian and Turkish interference in their affairs the// i would bo subjected to endless interference from the ^ritish who would little by little reduce them and their Cheikh^kcazal^t'' the condition of Bahrein , whore nww nothing was possible without the ’order 1 tf the Political Agent l thay comld aee no c&lt; mpensating ad~ -vantage in such an arrangement ii especially as at present they found fy&amp;fa ^ combination of all the near Arab tribes could make things so unpleasant for either Persians *r Turks that Mohammerah generally secured its own43, o v A DRAFT—(For Approval). Agency, Political R^^&gt;kncy, Persian Gule. K' -weit Demi-Of f No. S 638 — Dated 2Q1L Ootube r 190 9 To, F#a*R# in charge ^esidoncy, BU3HIRB, My det.r Trevor, You will notice the di&lt;*ry tLis we 3keikh KLti.z^l f 3 visit to Kuwait **nd the refer &amp; report thiit ho advises JhoikL Mubarak to go of his own* 2. Jheikh Khazal f s visit was quite unexpected by Mubarak and 1 dontt know whether ho sized up moaning of it or rather what I take to have b real cause of it* as you know up the 3hatt-el- Arab Pirmly convinced that Cheikh Mubj^rak was^dead the real eon the up there * ^yit t,» be and there were various rumours connected wi*h JLoikh Khazal obviously heard this and boliov true rushed down by the first ship he cou on with a lot of luggage and a hundred armed hardly the usual accompaniment of a friendly -quire after Mubarak*s health , which is what fcrt.TiisM l_is doctor , Fri-ncss, down for. Moreover tkoao ^oikha are not in the habit of dropping in o|n e-ch other casually wit id lay aands followers' visit to en- he ostonsibl j without .notice. #^0UZICL 3 During ^haiHh \iisd* v^e seomod (very reticent about Jhoikh Khazal 'a visit though - referred to it more than once . He may *ell rao more later . but- I was rather surprised his reticence as generally he is rather rank about Mohammerah and usually complains a little abou/^ jheikh Khazal owing him a pile of money and tjrying to get F 2,000-7'08out of paying up tlb.Q cash when duo , substi^u+iig dat ®or coin 9 otc« oa 4. It is curious how ho sooms to trust Jhoikh Khazal far more than any ono olso , and this is tho roUson am rather exorcised (h/ ho rumour about, Jhoi’ch Khazal Ihoikh for Limsolf this is c an 1 1 My was This ill- supplying him with a doctor • It appears that Mubarak novor calls in our Asst-Jurgoon oithor T- ^kiUo or his family , but when that/quacK Dr Ibrahim was horo ho used t(» have him in and from all ac &gt;unt s troat — -od him very woll whon ho first arrived • I also hear that Mubarak never takes any medocino himself ; probably a wise precaution against poison , but go on for ever as he is over 73 now &lt;*nd apparen really ill at the boginning of xvamzan* ii.444/ -noa 3 miibo m-lro itim rut.hor inolinod to feivoor odoikt Khuz&amp;l's 3 x.ggo3ti.m if it ro-liy w.s mudo , tiu.jagh wty to should not trust our man I cannot imagine , uni thinks wo might- have some motive for helping hir off the hooks • Ho is such a dark suspicious old man that he is quite capable of thinking this . x am writing this D* 0 as there is not hing luffioently definite to make an official letter of and 1 want to catch '- 11 '1^2 iw i &amp;£&amp; may bo got told of later Ibut, meanwhile y-a - ^ itio spare copy of ttls letter on to Mobammorab. for -any information wbieb can be gleaned tboro as to tbl reasons of ohtikh Kbazal's sudden descent. yours sincerelyDRAFT—(For Approval). vN v ' r Political Persian Gulf No Koweit Dcmi-Oi icial t Dated Inih Jany 191 Q /g Q To, H« B t M 1 Consul , MOHAMMERAH AM t bi? ba '• &gt;ik at to: fe Z tl) com- 38— My dear Wiluon, \ Yonr-j of tJfec 29th ~oc re Mxibarak^ and Khaz f ai financial relations, I 'h^vc not been able to ^o^nd Mubarak himslef but here is the result of what a co-pic 0 men who know most of the sheikh’s affairs ,ay:» Wi lent Kha’aal T£ 20 000 oomc two year .. a?c to be repaid with -in 4 years , no instalments bein? fixed. Sc far has been repaying by the sa- of hit, dates in Kowcit cred- -itin^ the proceeds tc Mubarak . Thi , last eea^ejn’s date I hear Khaz’al a ked Mubarak to -o-- for him; the demurred but ovontnally agreed. Natural res*^-1, at acccnnt -ct ling time at the end of iatt,month -plained that hi. date, had been ,o,.d below market-price,t best price obtainable and recalled that lie* had 1 arti a.ked Bhazal to sol them himself or by his own a not through Mubarak. X am informed that it wa ; c ctiled by Khazal giving in and accepting the prices at which htlic dates werosold&lt; On thi^ same oc asion however he induced Mubarak to pro- -long the time for repayment of the loan from 4 to so that 4 more years hser now available in which he -pay. Nobfdy can say definitely how much is sti^-x w Mubarak but all agree tkat not more than T£’*00Q ha repaid annually that at the best estimate shx leave T£ 12 000 still due from Khazal. The idea that Mu bank could be in debt u Khaz|aa i- fc»cof u-arly gents and on totally 6 year can re ing to been W 0 Xi . Cft. i -fed at hero and I think in the comfortable state I 2,000-7-08 of Mubar-So. V V vV 7 3 \ .vV / r - #/ 5 Maii.OTTiineraii 21,5,10, My dear Snalcespear, Pleas 0 refer to your diary no. 14, enory under April 3rd, I have found this para, most useful, as 1 had r eceived orders from Bushire to enquire what had teen done hy the Shaildi of Mha. in the matter, &amp; got my first intimation from your diary, as the old bird is very secretive. He now tells me that he has had to release two of the three aforesaid scoundrels, as Mubarak has written to him that he has certain proofs that they are innocent &lt;&amp; that it is only the third who is guilty of the piracy. As Shaikh Mubarak handed the three of them over willingly a7/ Shaikh Khas’al’s request, the latter did not feel able to enquire to closeljs into the nature of the proofs which Mubarak had discovered, &amp; handed them over without demur. I;f yOU can geb ^ confirmation of this it might be of interest. /^yours sincerely... 6 /. DRAF r—(For Approval). ,-'''’1, A 'v ^ _ Agency, Political Residency, Persian Gulf. Ko T .veIt No Derni-Olf icial Dated 25 th May TO, H. M. S* Oonstil &amp; at Mohaminaorah. My dear Wilson, Your D/o of the 21st May re the Kas Da Sheikhs* The information in my diary was not obtained froi a Mubarak and now I don f t remember whence exactly it came* But here is what my Mai ah tells me now* They were taken up by Mob -barak etc, as reported in my diary. After a bi t when they were confronted by the owner of the bol“ am which was pirate «ed , the O'vner said they were not the culprits ; on this they wore released and the two , Jabir and M-ehsi n, return -ed to Koweit* Farther enquiries up-river disci Dsed that the piracy was committed either by one of Hajr 3 11 tan 1 s slaves or one of his cultivators ,and presumably this new culprit was the proof on which the two Kasba she released* Ikhs were My Mullah says the two sheikhs in the old day &gt; and thier sons etc, ased to do a good deal of piracy and w 2 re a thorn in Khazal’s side : that after Mubrak and Khazal 00 came such thick pals things fot too hot for them and an ar .angement was made by which their estates etc, go on as be usual but they personally are exiled to Koweit* fore as The above is all I can discover for you an^i i b is the \ ^common report' here* For that reason probably very garbled Vat it may help yoa to lever something t of yc.ir Sheikh* . yours sincerely. rue 0 ut She Ikh*Political Agenoj, Koweit * IStSi June 1910 My dear Wilson, ’^any thankii. &gt;for yours of the 4th w ano « r^mbaratk void r* a prioally the sauje as you give in your latter « Of oo'oxb^ the old gentleman has to bo osref-al not to fall f^~l of the ^ali as so vary n :oi - i depends upon kis not doing so % but - still think i;s docs it booanso no has to* •‘oweveir, A 9 ro is aamotjiing of the s? 4 Ra sort for 701 *, Mubarak says that ha gave no mi of # ood advioa to dhaaal and that it was ha who indnosd Khasal to surrender those four malifacters to the Turks; that as it was oert&amp;in Bas- -ra nsewio-wssls did take rafnge at ^ouaran©rah nhazal ought not to pro toot them* -n gjy diary this we .k you will sc© a r©foronoo to shaikh Ohasib * I hear hara that he is anpposod to be a Turkish subject , r.aving as far as ^ oan gather takon out one # of those dratted Turkish Nationality certifioatea aoma tw or three years ago for buying property on the Turkish aide of the river# X ion * t what truth thore is in it but I am told hare that it is an oil known fact. If so it would appear tc have some effect on the ancoeaaion to the Shaikhship of Mohammerah# x hai is about all X have for yon* I *lso hear that SfeeikH eont«mpl»ta 3 a visit tale wa.y aoon j 1 b tnia really likely ? yonra ainoorely#Mahimineraii 24/6/10. My dear Shake spear, I .forward a copy of the foregoing d/o to Col. Cox, which is practically a reply to your s of the 15th June, I will “ask about the propsed visit to Kowait, I have not heard of it. yours sincerely6^4 DRAFT—(For Approval). Political Pf^Sian Gulf/ TO, [ 90 ^» H.B. Consul, MOHATVTWERAH . My dear Wilson, Re yo ir R/° of the R4th J mo to the dolrmol abont that rimo ir abont dhauib beinej registered as a Turkish subject* I was trying to Ret information at Basra from old Lyle abo'it M-ibarak f s affairs and c .rionsly cno ^h he entirely on his tjwn corroborated my previons K jweit rum* r‘:mo -r» He was more explicit as a fact and said that it is common talk in Basra that Khazal after sn'!iffino; otit his brother and becoming Sheikh had all Mizal’s property registered in Chasib’s name as f, son of Mizal tr fearing at the time rrobably to have the traefers made to !biis own name or to claim Ohasib as his orm son in case the Turks make the should refuse to^transfers . Later s~ch property as Khaza red in SYired me himself bonerht in TTirkish soil he also re°:istc dhasib f s name b t as ,f son of Khazal tT • Lyle ass that everybody ////// in Basra Jr/titdi/ was certainly mder the impression that dhasib has taken oTit a Turkish nation- -ajity certificate* I did not imntin it to drow but it ourhi to be easy for his dragoman on some pretext to get a look at the Tapn Office bo ks to settle the j^oint, if you think it worth doing. It is carious T should^et S'ch distient corr^b-ration from two entirely different s r '*irces« To save time a copy of this goes direct to Ru^hire#CONFIDENTIAL 1 V 0 . Cite 25 .SEP. 1 i &amp; I AM Ga No. 2642, dated Bushire, the 31st August (received 8th September) 1913. From Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Percy Cox, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Political Resi dent in the Persian Gulf, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department, Simla- I have the honour to forward, for the information of the Government of India, copies of correspondence which has passed between His Majesty’s Consul at Mohammerah and His Majesty’s Legation and this Residency, regarding certain incidents which have recently occurred at Mohammerah and the general question of the relations existing between the Belgian Customs and the Shaikh of Mohammerah. I have only just returned from tour and cannot offer any useful comment at the moment. LIST OF ENCLOSURES. 1. Telegram No. 350-1432, dated 18th August, from First Assistant Resident to His Majesty's Minister, Tehran. 2. Telegram No. 355-1464, dated 24th August, from First Assistant Resident to His Majesty’s Minister, Tehran. 3. Telegram No. Nil, dated 24th August, from First Assistant Resident to His Majesty’s Minister, Tehran. 4 . Telegram No. 282, dated 24th August 1913, from His Majesty’s Minister, Tehran, to First Assistant Resident. 5. Telegram No. 358-1469, dated 24th August, from First Assistant Resident, to His Majesty’s Minister, Tehran. 6. Telegram No. 9, dated 25th August 1913, from His Majesty’s Consul, Moham merah, to His Majesty’s Minister, Tehran. 7. Telegram No. 290, dated 30th August 1913, from His Majesty’s Minister, Tehran^ to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. 8. Letter No. 120-C., dated 23rd August 1913, from His Majesty’s Consul, Moham merah, to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. 9. Letter No. 790, dated 23rd August 1913, from His Majesty’s Consul, Moham merah, to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. 10 . Letter No. 791, dated 23rd August 1913, from His Majesty’s Consul, Moham merah, to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Telegram En. Cl., No. 350-1432, dated 18th August 1913. From—The First Assistant Resident, Bushire, To—His Majesty’s Minister, Tehran. Following for information. Consul, Mohammerah, reports that on evening of August 15 th, Monsieur Fourman, Customs Director, and Depifcre, Captain of the “ Muzzafari,” while coming home from a walk, were attacked by two Arabs Depibre being hit on the head and Fourman having his arm damaged. ^ Attack is supposed to have been made by date pickers for robbery. Incident is being investigated. Telegram En. Cl., No. 355-1464, dated 24th August 1913. From—The First Assistant Resident, Bushire, To—His Majesty’s Minister, Tehran. In case M. Mornard mentions subject I report following for information. On August 21st Director of Customs told me he had received a telegram from Fourman, the Director at Mohammerah to the effect that a sailor of themmmssmm S launch “ Mazandaran” had been killed and that agressors had been caught, but that whole personnel of Customs and Marine were menaced by Arabs, a fate identical with their own, t.e., presumably the Belgians. I at once* wired to Haworth for details and have received the following dated 24th. Quarrel occurred between some of quarantine staff and sailors of ship “ Mazandaran ” on account of latter bathing naked at place where former’s women get water; in course of quarrel one of the men of “ Mazandran ” fell and appears to have burst something internal with result he subsequently died ; man was examined by Dr. Marzin and Mr. Lincoln- He had no bruise or any mark of violence on him and death was purely accidental; no cause for Customs agitation. Frids. Telegram R., dated 24th August 1913. From—First Assistant Resident, Bushire, To—His Majesty’s Minister, Tehran. Private.—My telegram 355-1464. Reason I am keeping Your Excellency tu'ly informed of incidents at Mohammerah is that Haworth writing privately last week mentioned that Shaikh and Fourman had been quarrelling about matters connected with the Customs and that latter were anxious to try to get the Shaikh to give up his rights under Firman. It appears to me therefore tnat fourman by grossly misrepresenting situation may be trying to build uo a case against the Shaikh m order to further his own intrigues. I repeat abo^e Kl ifdue f W ° r t th T r, yet Submitted his views in officiaHorm andas ourman is due for transfer shortly, question may drop. icitgicuii jc.n. ^ 1 ., i\o, 232 , dated From—His Majesty's Minister, Tehran, To—The First Assistant Resident, Bushire. killed ^Tugu^TsTh' btrmb'Tin^ 3 Seaman of the ‘‘Mazandaran- was He connects this murder with attack b^Amh^ 6 S ^ vice w ^° ^ ave ^ een arrested, in your telegram 550 and Lnrests° n ? 0Urman and De P i3!re re ™'-ted Mohammerah must be privy^o this^Arab'wavi S:,aikh of subjects are too well in hand fo dare to attack ff ° aggression, because his of their Chief’s support. k Euro P ean s Without feeling assured I should be glad of any information Haworth may b 2 able to furnish. Telegram En. Cl., No. 358-: 4 6 9 , dated 24th Aujust 15,3. rom The First Assistant Resident, Bushire, To—His Majesty's Minister, Tehran. /our telegram 282 just received Y^nr n &amp; ' , “ h ' Telegram P., No. 9 , dated 25th (received 26th) nl , ?r„;; &gt;■* J,.i. ’■ Sfu *n«M Commandant Do, W'&gt;“ « ™ A® mSn*” ‘&amp;1; ■a”S,o h „12 Sk,The Shaikh states that no such incident has taken place in his territory before and that two Arabs only armed with sticks would never dare to make an attack on the same number of Europeans. Before my seeing the Shaikh I had formed the same opinion myself that it was almost certain that the offenders were date pickers who come from all over the place and among whom there are many bad characters, like the Kentish hop-pickers I have been asked by the Shaikh to warn Europeans that they should not go out on the desert unaccompanied nor should they be there after sunset, as there are date camps all over the country. For the date season he has put police everywhere. The Belgians seem to think that the responsilility for the attack lies with some of the Shaikh’s Arabs owing to the friction which has been taking place with the Customs. There is, however, nothing to support this view of which personal suspicion is the cause. An event which occurred on August 19th has unfortun ately enhanced this. An objection was raised by some employes of the Quarantine to men from the Customs ship bathing naked in the vicinity of the place from which their women fetch water. A quarrel arose when, in spite of remonstrance, the sailors returned to that place. Tw t o quarantine guards ran to help one of their men whom the sailors were attempting to seize and one of the sailors fell down with a quarantine guard on the top of him in the course of the struggle. The sailor must have burst something internal for that night he died. The French Customs doctor from Bushire and the Quarantine Surgeon examined him, but they could discover no trace of any blow or violence and the death was caused quite accident ally. It seems that the Belgians think the affair connected with the attack on themselves though it is difficult to follow on what grounds they do so. Telegram P., No. 290, dated (and received) 30th August £913* From—His Majesty’s Minister, Tehran, To—The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. (Repeated Mohammerah, No. 6.) With reference to your telegram No. 35 °'* 43 3 ‘ A telegram has been received from Depikre that ha is convinced that the attack on Fourman and himself is traceable to the hnaikh. It is also said tnat the Arabs, by whom the sailors of the “ Mazandaran ” were attacked, threatened to treat ihem in the same way as the Director of Customs had been dealt with. On the strength of this some connection between the two attacks is alleged. No doubt the Belgians are nervous to an undue extent but I consider that severe punishment should be meted out to the arrested Arabs ana threats based on the former incident were clearly used by them. No. 120-C, dated Mohammerah, the 23rd August 19 1 3 - From— Major L. Haworth, His Britannic Majesty's Consul for Arabistan, To—The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. I have the honour to state that in recent reports and diaries I have referred to the fact that friction was occurring between the Customs and the Shaikh of Mohammerah. This friction has lately come to a head owing to the high-handed action of Monsieur Fourman in dismissing two of the Shaikh’s Agents who are attached to the Custons Department. These two men are not Customs officials, as such, but are the Shaikh s per sonal guards, and are appointed by him alone: if then Monsieur Fourman had any complaint to’prefer he should have made it to the Shaikh and asked him to appoint other men in their place. Instead of doing this he attempted to override the authority of the Shaikh and to take the law into his own hands, with the result that the men refused to accept their dismissal until it was communicated to them by the proper authority. Apart from the question of his own nominees you are aware that under the Shaikh’s firmans he has considerable rights with reference to the appointment ofthe actual employes in the Customs. These rights it is necessary to maintain in order to enable him to carry on with success the difficult task of his rule in a country like Arabistan, a country the people of which is composed of a series of clans which he has to keep under efficient control. It is written with great distinctness in the Custom’s firmans that all servants and employes of the Department shall be appointed with the approval and the sanction of the Shaikh of Mohammerah. This reservation is a very necessary one. The Shaikh though an autocratic ruler rules on patriarchal lines and his power lies in the support and approval of his people. By his skilful management he has steadily strengthened and consolidated his power and I doubt if any other Arab Chief in Iraq has the same amount of control over his people. Nevertheless, the Arabs of this part of the world are far from being civilised and it is unfortunate that none of the Belgian officials who have come here appear to have the least understanding of the conditions of the country. They appear to consider the circumstances are the same as Belg-'um and apparently misled by the habitual security of Mohammerah and the country sur» rounding it, think that the whole district is the same. Indeed their ignorance is not perhaps surprising when it is considered that no official who has come here can speak 5 words of Persian or Arabic and that all are consequently absolutelv m the hands of their subordinates for all information of any kind. It is true that fear of the Shaikh’s authority has a great effect in maintain ing order but, as an example of how much of this is due to his personal influence may instance the fact that, when he was away at Ahwaz for some months in the spring, I was unable to obtain boatmen who would face the journey to Basrah by night for fear of robbers. When the Shaikh is at Mohammerah boats pass up and down nightly without the slightest fear. This power which the Shaikh possesses is due to the fact that he has the complete confidence and support of his chiefs of clans, or perhaps it would h^ more correct to say the balk of them, for disaffected men naturally exist ^t all prevalence of smuggling ThatsmXw/-, Belg,an a ?}' ,0n has teen th&lt; largely encoura g ed g \v?heexorL«antfus fmT , rmes n ° This T ^ ” of two kinds i firstly the systematic smumdi™ nf t hl' u smu &amp;? lln g consists especially in tea and tobacco for ni.rroc/® * ° °! t le nlerc l i ants and traders more tribes for their own personal use. hvfth thelffor^ofThTc^ I he Sm n ug S lin 2 of the Stop the first I have every sympathy with ’ ^11 ki Cu 1 stoms Department to latter 1 have none, nor woufd ™ny man'of sensehttemtit tQ 6 *^ the present circumstances and conditions of the country P To ItP 'f W “ h “ m the to smugglmg force is required and when it comes tl tho • mP ! ° end obtainable except that which the Shaikh possesses H ‘ SSUe n0 force IS quite uncivilised that unpopXity^PanThegrea'teP’o ^ ' n t- C0Untry which is preventive service. to nsk their ,lv es fighting the Customs ... 3 T. 1 rc d ' 3 'l lh £, —-r«» — ame the Shaikh for not using his power and i j ri -^f s ' ® ut t ^ le Customs toce Now I have explained Wh P s power ijc d W ‘ S u t0 de P end u P on his VVere he then to use his paid levies in this work ’l P ° n su PP ort of his tribes. S rounrf n k- WOU d Very shortI y have a hornets’ nest o7t “ ^ , fightin g his own all round h,s country. U i s a paradox b s nest of trouble about his ears and the greater his dependence on his neonle a t ie g reat er the autocrat ■sthen impossible for the Shaikh to approve |n ;L eSpecial, y tru e in the East. approve, in the present state of civilisationof the country, of the bureaucratic efforts of the Customs Department to interfere with the petty smuggling which goes on among the tribes though he is ready to give his support in all other cases. I recently in my No. 84-C., dated 7th June, reported how the Belgians very nearly had Shuster and Dizful in an uproar over revenue matters; and were they to pursue the policy they desire in the Customs they would speedily have the whole of lower Arabistan in a similar condition. 1 am given to understand that this policy is to a large extent forced on local officers by the central administra tion at Tehran. Now the Customs officials not only wish to use the ShaikhV power when it suits them but they wish to neglect it and even run counter to it when it appears, to their short-sighted eyes, to be in their way. At no time in this more apparent than in their neglect of the right of the Shaikh to approve of appointments to the Department. The result is that a low class of Armenians and Jews succeed in obtaining the ear of the Director and the consequence is a state of friction with the local Arabs which can only result in trouble, while as a matter of fact the merchants bribe the Customs almost openly. Thus the most important part of the smuggling is done freely without hindrance. A local British merchant smuggled a lot of goods through the Customs in this way and hid ^ the proofs before M. Delcroix, the late Director, to show him the condition of his office. The Shaikh has stated to Monsieur Fourman that one Shimal, a Jew, is an undesirable and the cause of most of the friction which is occurring. He points out that the man is improperly appointed and has never received his approval or sanction and consequently asks for his dismissal. Notwithstanding the details of the firman Monsieur bourman refuses to dismiss this man, a refusal which he cannot, of course, uphold. In appointing this employe irregularly he has obviously gone beyond his powers ; and in actual fact the man cannot legally be considered an employe of the Customs at ail, since he has been refused the sanc tion which his provisional appointment necessitated. I have now discovered that Monsieur Fourman wishes to bribe the Shaikh by offering him a percentage on the Customs takings, and thus to induce him to give up some of his rights. This, tempting as it may sound, the Shaikh wou d not dream of accepting at the price. His position amongst his clans depends upon his prestige, while of money he has sufficient for normal purposes. The fact that he had sold'his birthright for a mess of pottage would lose him among his people far more than the few thousands a year tie would gain, and it would be the first step of the Belgians towards that which I have so frequently pointed out as their policy viz., the curbing of the power of the Shaikn and the encroachment on his rights and privileges. I can fully understand their policy on their part but as it does not suit us or the Shaikh it will be necessary for us to supportthe latter from the first should the question arise at Tehran. I attach herewith a copy of a letter which the Shaikh has addressed to the Director of Customs on this subject. No. 790 dated Mohammerah, the 23rd August From— Major L. HawoRIH, His Britannic Majesty’s Consul for Arabistan, To—The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. I have the honour to inform you that while Monsieur Fourman, the Director of Customs, and Monsieur Depiere, Commandant of the “ Persepohs, were walking in the desert behind Mohammerah on the evening of the 15th instant they were attacked by two Arabs. The canal which runs from the Katun to the Shatt-el-Arab crosses the desert. The earth which has been dug out of the canal has been thr0 *' u P ° n either side to form an embankment and anyone walking on the banks of the canal is completely hidden from view.mmmmrnmmm I—BW— / 6 Messrs. Fourman and Deplore state that while they were walking along the bank of the canal Monsieur Depi^re suddenly received a blow on the head which knocked him on to his knees. Immediately both turned to defend themselves and they found they were confronted by two Arabs with clubs in their hands. Monsieur Fourman received a blow on his arm and Monsieur Depi&amp;re another blow on the head. Monsieur Fourman then placed his hand on his breast as though to produce a revolver and the Arabs fled. Many theories have been brought forward for this attack which has astounded every one. The Shaikh refuses to consider for an instant that the men thought they were attacking Europeans. He states—a point which I also remarked directly I heard of the event—that two Arabs armed with clubs would never dare to attack an equal number of Europeans, and says that they must have thought they were attacking Armenian clerks. This is very possible. The Belgians wear clothes very like Armenians and l have myself mistaken them on the desert for such. The country is now overrun with date pickers and I incline to the belief, as the only reasonable one, that it was a couple of bad characters among them who made the attack. There has been a good deal of friction between the Shaikh and Customs Department on which 1 have reported separately. The Belgians appear to think that the attack was part of a deep laid plot against them and their subordinates are spreading this in the bazaars. The idea is however chimerical having nothing to support it beyond the imagination of the Customs Department and I think it may safely be put on one side. The suggestion would apparently be that Haji Ambar of the Customs guard is responsible but there is absolutely nothing to sustain such a thought nor can I imagine only two men being sent to do such a deed even if one accept ed the possibility of its being done. ^ r — s a,o tnc uaie picKers remain. The event has been unfortunate but I think there recurrence in any form. is little chance of its ixcsiuenc j: •ncs.uciu in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. ' lound one attempting7 to seize the guard. On this two more men of the quarantine guard came to his assistance. In the course of the struggle which ensued one of the sailors tell with one of the quarantine guard on top of him. In falling he appears to have burst something internal. He died the following morning. His corpse was examined by Dr. Marzin and Mr. Lincoln and no bruise on it or any sign of violence could be found. s The enquiry, at which I had a representative, was held today and full details are to be sent to me to morrow, but the evidence is quite clear that the whole matter was a pure accident and it would appear that the sailors are mainly, if not entirely to blame for the affair. Dr. Marzin's report states that ' no signs of violence could be found ” with the words underlined; it then adds “ one is permitted to suppose that the death was caused by an internal haemorrhage (perhaps a rupture of the liver or spleen?) occasioned by the blows he had received.” It seems pretty evident, from Dr. Marzin’s own evidence and that of the sailors that there were no blows, but only a struggle, in the case of the deceased man. Monsieur Fourman and Monsieur Depibre appear to wish to suggest that this incident has some bearing on the attack on them. The facts are however simple enough and have no connection with the other matter whatsoever, the quarrel being an ordinary one which might occur any day. On receiving the Governor’s statement I will send a complete report. C6i FD — 44 —12-9-! 3—GCBP SimlaNosoC Cjh of IfOS . ji'rom Hajor SS.O.Knox » I.A. Political Agent » Koweit To Major P.Z.OOX , He aidant &amp; H.B.Mja Oonaul-Gene I’aJ in tixe Persian (Julf Bushira . iated to wait 9/&lt;J/08. , I liave the honour to aciawwledga the receipt of lo98 tour letter Ho: S33X dated Sdth lias 190?'; , inviting * / ay attention to P*l). telegraja Ho: 8.533 dated 21st of Novaiaber 1907 and requesting the expadition of the report called for therein regarding V/arba island , 2 . I would first express ay extrema regret a- the -telayr that has taxon place in submitting the report on this important question . It was seldom during the cold weather that Sheikh Hobarais tad myself were together in Koweit ,ahd sinoe I returned from tour x in the beginning of J.Iaroh ,Sheikh Hobaraii has been so occupied in m trrSAtje festivities tliat it has been difficult to persuade him to attend to business. 3 . I was , at first . inclined tt&gt; throw xam on Sheikh Mobarak the onus of producing proof of Ms ovaiership of the island and he undertook verb -lly to do so . but copies of recent correspondence between us , forwarddd herewith , vd.ll show how completely he fails to understand the nature of the proof that x is required to establish his o'v/nex-ship successfully » 4.1 was therefore compelled no request the Sheikh as irill be seen from the oorrespondence » xo send me Aw&amp;zim witnesses aEid hold an informal enquiry myself Tire re-^ult of this enquiry - the depositions in English, and vemacula-r are forttarded herewith - has be n to furnish clear evidence as to tne ownership of Bu^iyan, island curd there i &lt; therefore room for f' \congratulation in that , so far , the encuir^ has not been barren of results « X nia^ be permitted, to record here the ver 0 favorable impression I formed of the Awazim witnesses . Their evidence was clear and to the point and obviously untutored • I think a mere perusal of their statements will convince a disinterested observer of this fact , No one with anj regard to truth will be able to den^ that an ancient grant of fishing rights was accordd^. to the Awazim fishermen b^ Sheikh Mob a rak* s great-grandfath er and that his order has been universally respected to the present day • I hope shortly to obtain written evidence that these rights are capable of inheritance and transfer and that the forum which habitually deals with such cases ± is the old Shar’a Court of lioweit , in which the hereditary Aazi is of the Atsani family and which depends for the execution of its decrees on the executive action of the Sheikhs of ho we it . This will go far to establish the anElx ancient ownership of the Sheikhs of ho we it in iubiy an island and the unwarranted encroachment of the Turkish authorities in establishing , in spite of remonstrances , a post there &gt; flanked on all sea sides , by the Awazim properties • 5 . The proof of ownership of ' area island will have to de? pend on other considerations and we are here on weaker grou*/ The Awasim evidence is clear and ’jncornprising that the island has never been of anj use to an„bod„ and no rights 2 of ownership would appear to have ever been exercised there . It would seem therefore to depend mainly on geographical considerations and the cuestion ma*, oe posed thus : ' Is T 'arba an offshoot of Lubi^an and does therefore the ownership of ’ arba island follow that of xubi,,an T or ' Is T 'arba an offshoot of the mainland and does the owner ship pertain to whoever can establish his claim to the mainland ? Sheikh Mobarak maintains that the mainland swamp between T'ao and the Khor bubair is his property , but in his capacity of Turkish subject , pacing revenues to the Turkish Government . The Sheikh states thatthere isincom rovertlble proof of this fact, in wh dead of ^et-ble** menb between himself and the s*om of his mrderad brethren, in which the boundaries are ciearl^ laid do\m to be , to the south and west P the aea , the Khor Abdulla » and the creek . This creek ae contend.^ to be the Khor Subair , explored in 1907 a wxrv&amp;y party from Investiga^ tor „ The Sheikh declares that there is no other creek between Poo and Kho» Subair and , however this ma^ be ,'^m ml I am inclined to doubt it , the mention of Khor Abdulla would^go far to support his contention that the creek in question lies far to the westward . Bubiy an island on the other hand would appear to be as clearly the property' of the Sheikhs of Koweit under s tod , as one of the Amsim \hLtnesses quaintly rut it . There remains the coaet line from Utam Oamr to Rabija . Sheilsh Hobarah lays claim to Urn Oasar on the Rround that ,! the old fort ,marh®d on the chart* , waa erectert b- one Ahnw ed bin Hizn In nha nime of hia graiidfather * Jaoir as S U bah and that the original name of the place ia .oaitaith &gt; that the name of the rlaoe mm changed by the bedouin to Uam Oasar by the fact of the erection of the fori. - tne tem forfc is nerhapa rather a misnomer , as amy is bem- ed Oasar by the Bedouin -in the time of his ancestor by toe 3 =uae Ahmed bin Biz* vrtio waa undoubtedly a Ko eit 3 xib.ject , ^ — -si t 11 live in his house here iu and vfhose descendants ^xxx xivo Kowelt . It ms this same Ahmed bin Biz* v ' mo dw 1Ao ^ ^ ,r wells . Another proof to which Bheihh Hobara* attache import.anoe is the presence of :tn island , called Jazirat as Suf or Wool island , immediately opposite UmmOasar , » where the Koweit wodouinc used to wash their wool for market . The Turkish erection of a fort at Utot crasar was an encroachment that has never , so far as I m aware , been K acquiesced in by the brinish Government and is still a grievance withBhaikh Hobarass. . .^rom IfiumUasar down the coast I can myself testify without hesitation to tire fact that the land is regarded as-toe gracing ground of the ho wait •t**- /iArabs is law , i 3 . * ■ • ' ° * ' Q 3m U P » I venture to rocort the opinion that » Sheil.li Job a ran* a claiia to the ownership of Warb .. island ia ordad above are worths of credit and could be established a with lintla trouble . I regard the private own.ereh.Ap of Warba island as undoubtedly vested in Sheihh itobaraa as , on the north private proprietor of the coast line , proved so by deeds recorded in a Turkish court of law . The proofs tothe oimership of Item Oaaar would have to be exaiained and the considerations , utvanced by Sheikh Hobai’su; will undoui £— ^tedly have great weight , as will Uso hie do facto occupa tion of th western bank; of the Khor R ably a , as evidenced by the old settlments of Araifljiya » Hogai.la and Rabiya » the nuaerous wells dug by Kb welt Araibdar nd the actual status quo , as evidenced by the grazing rights of Koweit Araibdar and the Sheikh’s authority throughout this tract . a very strong one , and that the general' considerations rac I have the honou? -no be , Sir , Your 130 nt obedient servant » Political Agent , Koweit .please God we shall send for’Ubaid al Gharaib S 5 (Hheilh of *bh© Aghruba section of the Awa&amp;im) that he should bring tx&gt; us what documents he can prooure.iiikewiae we will send to the Bheilh of the VAclsahi and ask hii*; about what la in his oharge with regard to agreemta i-uid wills. Usual ending*Translation of lett-er No.79, dated 33rd June 1908 froa Major Knox.Politioal Agent,Kowait,to Sheikh Mobarais. us Subah, ruler of Koweit, A.w. ’?orraerly we asked your honour that you should send to us two or three papers of the proofs that were with the Awasiia who have fishr--. rights in Hubiyanf like^rlse,the statement of evidence of the Adsani and you promised me in your letter dated 14th Jaaadi til Avrvral= 14th June 1908 that you would send them to us and up till now vre see nothing.Please &lt;*od tnat yon will send them to us, for I have sent no the Government tne info mat ion which I have obtain ed in that affair and have promised them that I would complete it with the evidence of the Adsahi aforesaid. Usual ending. a TTSpIST Translation of a letter from Sheikh Mobara* us Subah, ruler of Koweit, dated the 36th Jamadi ul Avnml, to Major Knox, Political Agent, Ko we in. A.O. a V \ I received your letter daued the 34th JiMavii ul Awwal 133 d.H. end what you have men tioned was made known.he have asked ‘Obaid al Gharaba. . There are no papers with them according uo statement of 'Ubaid al Ghtaraba but their enjoy- ment of hmdreds of years suffices and the Kasi.at the time of necessity,will sive a • v &gt;,« certifies about their papers raper in which he oext -e u nw t do not see the wferenoe to dubiy an.i'towOOMF 75. 'V - Ho. &lt;^7 of 1908. A Office of the Political Agent,Koweit. Koweit# 39th June 1908. Prom To Haj or B. O. Knox, I. A *, Political Agent,Koweit* ( Major P.Z.Gox,O.I.K., Political Resident in th© Persian Gulf# Bushire. Sir, 11 In c.on-tinuation of mi confidential letter No.395, dated the 9th Jims 1908 on the subject of the ownership of Warba island, I have the honour to forward / here.ath^ copies with translations of the correspondence that has lately passed between mi*self and Sheikh Mobarak on this subject,in which Sheikh Kobarau shows that he no longer attaches ^P^giSes^ the question, while we neglect, as he^teaKH*»his inherestiS ah Pao. p,. '^rom later enquiries as to Ahaed bin Rizq who is alleged to have dug the wells and built a fort at Uxora tlasar,! find that such evidence as I have been able to obtain will make it extremely difficult to pro’ e the man in question to be anything but a Turkish sub ject.He appears to have been a native of i'ie.jd and to have led a wandering life, eventually retiring from business as a pearl merchant, t,o Oridilan. close to Basra.Another Ahmed bin kisq deceased has a grandson,living also named Aimed a fellah of Sheikh Mobarak’s at ^who served in njae Turkish arms *11 is no*t aui easy mat/ber *bo get# certain evidence on these points but should further definite information be obtained bs .me,it will at once be forwarded and no effort*will be spared to procure it. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant? Political Agent,Koweitm 7:r- i‘0.2o2-l of 1908 British Residency and Consulate-deneraX. Bushire, $0 June 1908, id st- Copy of the undermentioned letter is forwarded, with compliments, to the Political Agent, Kowelt, for information, with reference to his letter No.295, dated the 9th June 1908, with a request that he will be good enough to take such action as he finds possible, in the direction indicated. First Assistant Resident. (In charge current duties). No. 2o%0 dated the 3o June 1908, from the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf to Foreign Department, Simla. irvO!■■■■ i ■mi 76 . ®J 1 Cop^ of* a letter No, 202,0 dotted Shiraz, the 3o June 1908, from the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, to the Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department. msmmmm I have the honour to refer to Captain Trevor*s letter No.1906, of 17th instant, forwarding to Govern ment copies of the marginally cited report and enclosures from the Political 5 Koweit No.295,dated 9th June 1908.} Agent, howeit, on '\ . 5 the subject of the rights of the Sheikhs of Koweit over Warba, Eubiyan and the neighbourhood. 2. I have no special comment to offer at the pre sent stage. The information now obtained seems satis factory so far as it goes, but I am asking Liajor Knox with the present data to go upon, to repeat his endea vours, by personal explanation, to arouse Sheikh Muba rak to specific effort in the direction of bringing to light ancient documents tending to support his claims. Even if he has no old records in his own possession one would suppose that old deeds of gift or lease of land and rights, must be in existence among his rela tions or subjects, which would directly or indirectly prove the exercise of sovereign or proprietary rights by the Sheikhs of Koweit over the localities under re ference •■ IM J Sru Oonfidantial* British Residency and Consulate-General. Bushire, /S*' October 1908. / He sent on to the Government of India the corres- \ pondence received from you, ending with your Bo.347, da ted the 29th June, regarding V/arba and Bubeyan Islands and they have sent us this mail, demi-officially, a copy of a despatch they have addressed to the Secretary of State on/the subject. I enclose the copy for your in- formatioh. Please return it as soon as possible as Major !ox lias hot ooon it yat . f a V -i Major S. G. rnox, ^ Political Agent, iv o w e i t- •British Residency and Consulate-General, Bushire, ^ March 1909. The Political Agent, C' '‘ T rn t rn ± ± U M ih ± i • Sir, I have the honour to forward a copy of Foreign Department letter No. 3493-E.A. dated 27th November 1908 on the subject of the rights of the Sheikh of koweit to Bubiyan and Warba. We spoke of the matter during our last meeting at the end of December and you doubted then whether there was anything further in the way of information or record to be procured. It would be as well, however, if before you proceed on leave you were to take an opportunity to ask oheikh Mubar ek, ix re lias any further evidence to put us in possession of, and then submit a final report.No. 3493-E.A. From The Deputy Secretary to the Govt, of India In the Foreign Department. To Major P.Z. Cox, C.I.E., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Dated Fort William, the 27th November 1908. ■A I am directed to refer to the correspondence ending with Captain Trevor’s letter No. 2119, dated the 7th Jul£ 1908, regarding the rights of the Sheikh of noweit to the islands of Bubiyan and Warba. 2. I am to inform you that it is not considered advisable by His Majesty's Government to raise the question in existing circumstances. There is, however, no objection to the continu ance of the further enquiries, which are being made under your direction by Major unox, as to the Sheikh’s rights in these localities, and I am to request that the result may be commu nicated when the enquiries are completed.S^jl|ll s c!Iott2iilate (General, iSusKite. 7th March 1909. With referenoe to my official letter Mo. 6/Jf of today’s date, i send you in original for reference and return x by first post, Reynold’s D/0 letter of 25th September 190b and enclosure on the subject of t% Bubiyan Warba question. If I remember right, I brought with me and showed it to you, but am not sure. i'\ ^ Do not refer to the enclosure in any official letter, out write separately to me demi-officially if you have any special comment to maise.-^1 xJ Copy oi a letter No. 884 -e.A., dated the 29th April 1910. ^ from the Deputy Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department, Simla, to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. C 3 I am directed to refer to the correspondence ending with your letter No* 77b, dated the 28th March 1909, regarding the rights of the Sheikh of Koweit over the Islands of Bubiyan and Warba. 2 * I am to inform you that it is not considered advisable by His Majesty U Government that any stops should be taken to raise the question in present circumstances. No. of 1910. British Residency and Consulate-General, rr Bushire, Ji /May 1910 . A copy of the foregoing letter is forwarded with compliments to the Political Agent, Aoweit, for information. c v / O'Memorandum No. OFFICE OF THE DY. CIVIL COMMISSIONER, BASRAH WILAYET. 27th March 8 • Basrah, dated /9/ j 0 The Political Agent K 0 W E I T, Have you an 3 r information whether the Island of WARBA in the Khor Abdullah north of BUBIYAN is claimed by the Shaikh of Koweit. We are at present defining our district boundaries and there seems to be nothing on record about WARBA - ' Lieu1&gt;-Col, e Deputy Civil ComTiiissionerCQHFIDBMTIAX.. Ho.? o/a o H.B.M'a Political Agency KUWAIT. April 9th,1918. To Tho Deputy Civil feismt saionor Basrah MEMORANDUM. Tour memo.No.449? of March S7th f 1018. The island of W&amp;rhah has been claimed by Kuwait for mere than 200 years and the claim was recognised by us in 1907 when the Government of India proposed to the Secretary of State for India that we should secure from Shaikh Mubarak the right of pre-emption over Warbah I si add and the anchorages north and south of it. This was further recognised both by our own and the Turkish Government in the Anglo-Turkish agreement of 1913 , in which it is stated in Article 5 of the section relating to Kuwait t- i 'L'autonoal. du Chslkh do Kouelt .at excrete par lul dan a lea terrl toiroa --— . . Lea ilea de Duprba.Soubiane, ---—---• a^ec les llota et les eaux adjaeents 9 sont oomprls dans cette zone.” I have not asked Shaikh Salim his views but hs would no doubt claim the island and I trust that no question regarding the boundary of Kuwait territory will be raised at present if it can be avoided. Captain. Political Agent,Kuwait. fm&amp;BF '——m / 0 Vi #H. I ♦ SliakoGpQ&amp;r» PO 1-L ^ i &gt; K o -V ft i ^ * 7th March 1912. / f/f « please sco letters of which I enclose copies one from Crow to me and the other from me to the C1ork-in-Char£3, lelographs, Fi Ho can probably gQt information better than you can, but please also take such steps as you can to obtain information and report result.Copy of a letter (domi-offioial) ^o.ld, dated 29th February 1912, from f.2.Crow, require, ii.h*s Consul, iiuaroh, to Lieut-Colonal Lir Percy Cqk, iv.C.I.h:., C.S.I., Political deaident in the Persian Gulf. The Ambassador has aafed mo to report by telegraph any indication of intention on the part of the Turks to increase the garrison on Lubian Island. I am ivceping a look out here but, as it would be easy for them to reinforce the garrison at Nubian ircm the dotacliment at the Um x^assr without my knowledge, I suggest that the Political Agent at noweit should be as^od to report also as he may have better opportunities of observation. as the Ambassador has no means of communication with dhakospear would you /ary kindly ask him to keep a looa out and let me know if he notices anything of tne i^ort i’rou hi3 and*Very Confidential 7til March 1912. I want you, if you Kindly will and can do so without attracting attention, (i) to find out through your confidential local servant whether the snail Turkish military post on Bubian Island is still fro be. manned and fed from the Pao V garrison and how many men there are there'at present, and (ii) to Keep yourself informed, so as to be able to give me timely intimation of any steps being taken to increase the strength of the post. The Clerk-in-Charge, Indo-Buropean Telegraphs,DRAFT—(For Approval). Agency, Political Rj^volncy, Ph^sian/Gul^/ No. o /a Kuwait CONFIDENTIAL Dated 190 TO. Political Resident, BU^HIRE* Dear ^ir Percy, With reference to ymir D/o of the 7th War- 19 i? abe-Jit Bnbian and the losijFble increase of the Turkish had been ary rmmoTir Post there* I cmildn’t rentier it before as the Sheikh away ^intil he care back for his inves it^.re* I asked hir the other day if he had heard on the subject at Basra or Failiyah • He said he had not but xroroised to warn his people at Fao to keej a careful look-out for any r ve o of one and to let roe know as sern as he heard an Yours sincerely. r rurooir Tthin g. W* H« I. Shakespe s.r*9 % CONFIDENTIAL. No. 2581 , dated Bushire, the 13 th (received 21 st) October 1912 . From— Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Percy Cox, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department. With reference to the correspondence ending with Foreign Department endorsement No. 9I4-E.A., dated May 23rd 1912, I have the honour to forward, „ , for the information of the Government of Busreh to Resident. India, copies of the marginally cited corre- Telegram dated 8 th October 1912 , Resident spondenCC which has passed between this TcLgram dated 8 th October 1912 , Consul,Busreh, office and His Majesty s Consul, Busreh, to Resident. with regard to the rumoured movements of Turkish troops in the Persian Gulf region. 2. I am expecting news trom Fao regarding the Bubian garrison by next post, but so far no increase has taken place, and as the post is manned from the Fao garrison, it may be presumed, pending further report, that it will be included in any relief or change affecting Fao. Extract from cl letter No. 27, dated 2nd October 1912, from F. E. Crow ) £sq. t His Majesty's Consul, Busreh, to Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Percy Cox, K.C./.E., C.SJ., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. **•**♦♦ We have no Vali at Busreh at present and one has not yet been appointed. The arrangement to send Reshid Pasha or Reshid Bey, who was formerly at Mosul and exiled under the Hamidian regime has not been confirmed. Orders have been 'received to collect the units of the 1st Battalion of the • 1 2 th Regiment now distributed at Umm-Kasr, Zobeir, Sefwan and Fao and despatch them at an early opportunity to Ojair. The garrison in Busreh town has been reduced to about 80 soldiers and 159 marines including the military and naval bands. Telegram (P-)/ dated the 8 th October 1912 . F rom The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, To—His Majesty’s Consul, Busreh. Please see last paragraph of your demi-official No. 27. Is it possible for you to form any idea as to the reasons which give rise to the collection of units and their despatch to Ojair ? Telegram (P.), dated the 8 th (received 9 th) October 1912 . From—His Majesty’s Consul, Busreh, To—The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Your telegram of 8th. I think that time has come to relieve men in normal course but 1 will report after enquiry. According to present information inspection not mobilization of four army corps is ordered. G. C. B. P„ Simla.—No, C .64 F. D.— 25 -I 0 -i 3 .- 44 .-N. C./(TO, but here so lanuh depeiihs on strings \,na'u are puiied in London, GQnsvuitinupIe,or 4 Berlin tnax, 1 be „ thi&amp; &gt;\ 'A Freely forgiven for leaving care no iiameasurabi^ v O n v/iser heads than mine 21 . I h we ventured to use the question of Sheikh Mobarak* s salute as a text on which to hang 1 fear a lengthy dessert ation on problems that have long been troubling me * After derailing the consider ations that have guided me to a decision , I have the honour to recommend the saline of eleven guns to Sheikh Hobarak as a personal salute • - I venture to consider the person J proviso indispensable and thin) i hat it should be carefully explained to Bheik- Mobarak that we do not consider the ordinal^ dignity of i he Rheilh of ho we it cm it lea nxm io mo five -a salute of five gms ' Lne heir apparent , Sheikh Jabir when he repr s«nts m.-. father* and a salute of three guns : hen he visiis on his ov/n account I have the honour to be Sir , Your most obedient servant , Major , Political Accent , KoweitKo. ^5 a of T909 # Residency 'ind Oonaulatie-General, Busaire , it October 19C9, file Political Ay exit, K OWE I T. 0/ Sir, I have the aonour to refer to the correspondence ending / \ tfitn your latter ho. 294,dated Stli July 1908, regarding the proposed increase in the salute of rheildi Mubarek. His Majesty’s Government at the recommendation of the Indian Government have been pleased to prescribe a personal salute of 12 guns to Sheikh Mubarek at the termination of an official visit to a British man-of-war. They nave further directed that a salute of o guns shall be accorded to tne Sheikh’s eldest son when making an official visit dn his be half. Government reserve the right to continue or no^ uhe salute to the fheikh’s successors. I now enclose a letter to the Bheikh informing him of these feicts and request you will be good enough to deliver it to him.No. 2877, dated Busbire, the 7th November 1909. From— Major A. P. Trevor, First Assistant to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, in charge of Residency, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department. Witli reference to correspondence ending with [Foreign Department letter No. I509-E. A„ dated the 22nd September 1909, regarding the in creased salutes to be accorded to the * (1) From Sheikli Mobarak, Koweifc, dated the lltb October 1909. (2) From Political Agent, Bahrein, No. 679, dated the 22nd October 1909, and enclosure. (3) From His Majesty’s Acting Consul, Moham- merah, No. 433, dated the 31st October 1909. Sheikhs of Mohammerah, Koweit, and Bahrein, I have the honour to state, for the information of the Government of India, that I issued the necessary in structions to the officers concerned with view to their acquainting Sheikhs Khazal, Mobarak, and Isa with the decision of Government and also wrote myself to the two last named. I beg to enclose the replies * I have received in the matter. tX r&gt; Dated the 11th October 1909. From— Sheikh Mobarak-el-Sabah, Chief of Koweit, To Majob A. P. Trevor, First Assistant to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, in charge of Residency. I have duly received your letter dated the 19th Bamazan 1327= 5th October 1909, giving me the good news of the favour shown by the High British Government to me, their grateful friend, by issuing orders to, the Commanders of the men-of-war to fire a salute of 12 guns in my honour when I have the honour to call on them, and to fire a salute of five guns in honour or my son when he calls on the men*of-war. I and my sons thank the Government for their favour and graces towards us, and shall not forget their previous generosity. We are obliged and S ateful for this good news, and beg of you to convey our thanks to the High ritish Government. We are always thankful to them for their good graces and to you for the enhancement of your friendship. No. 679, dated the 22nd October 1909. j? rom —C aptain C. F. Mackenzie, Political Agent, Bahrein, To— Major A. P. Trevor, First Assistant to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, in charge of Residency. With reference to your letter No. 2530, dated the 5th October 1909,1 have the honour to enclose herewith a letter from Sheikh Esa to your address, together with its translation in duplicate. 2. Sheikh Esa was extremely pleased with the honour that has thus been conferred on him and on his son, Sheikh Hamad. Translation of a letter dated the Chief of Bahrein, to 30th Ramazan 1327 from g HEIKH EsA-BIN-Au-Al-KhALIFA 15th October 1909 Major A. P. Trevor, First Assistant to the Political Resi dent in the Persian Gulf (in charge of Residency), Bushire. After compliments,—I have the honour to acknowledge the receipt of Ifi 7 .fated the 19th Ra y ^ r Hg-, on the subject of the establish- your letter IN o. do/, aatea x-ne 5th October 1909 ment of your friend’s (i.e., my) rule iu Bahrein, its stability and (the hope) of its continuation for a long period. , ,, , v Verilv I receive with the greatest thanks and gratitude the honour 5 °J. n W the Hieh Government in approving the view of the Governmen of India to^ncreasety honouTby dring V greater) salute at the termination of my official visits to a man-of-war.I also congratulate you on your promotion by the High Government to 4116 God hashelpetl me as well as you with a great help and has raised my ,. n v and vou« n the world. May you ever enjoy health and prosperity. No. 483 , dated the 31 st October 1909 . T. Wilson, His Majesty's From— Lieutenant A. Mohammerah, To—The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Acting Consul, iU—iUO 1 have the honour to state that on the 16 th instant, I communioated to the Sheikh of Mohammerah the decision of the Government ot India regarding Lk personal salute and that of his son referred to in your letter No. 2164 of 3rd October 1909. • „ ^ .. . 2 The date selected was the Id-ul-Qurban, after the eu d of the month of Ramazan, when the Sheikh holds a durbar and receives officials, merchants, and subjects in State in his palace at Failiyah. # 3 I proceeded thither in the Steam Launch Mohammerah in full uniform, and was received with proper ceremony, the band playing the National Anthem as I entered the hall. 4 , The Sheikh expressed his pleasure and gratitude at the honour which had been accorded to him by the Government of India. 5 . At a su bsequent interview with Haji Rais, who was not present at the durbar, I explained the decision again, so as to leave no room for misapprehension.TABLE OF SALUTES ©hiefs anil |tobk3 of f tibia AND TO CERTAIN CHIEFS NEAR ADEN AND IN THE PERSIAN GULP, 1909. SALUTES OF 21 GUNS. Baroda. The Maharaja (Gaekwar) ef— Hyderabad. The Nizam of— Mysore. The Maharaja of— SALUTES OF 19 GUNS. Bhopal, f The Begam (or Nawab) of— Gwalior, f The Maharaja (Sindhia) of— Indore, f The Maharaja (Holkar) of— Jammu and Kashmir, f The Maharaja of Kalat. The Khan (Wali) of—» Kolhapur. * The Maharaja of— Me war (Udaipur). * The Maharana of Travancore. * The Maharaja of— SALUTES OF 17 GUNS. Bahawalpur. The Nawab of— Bharatpur. The Maharaja of— Bikaner. The Maharaja of— Bundi. The Maharao Raja of— Cochin. The Raja of— Cutch. The Rao of— Jaipur. * The Maharaja of— Karauli. The Maharaja of— Kota. The Maharao of— Mar war (Jodhpur). The Maharaja of- Patiala. The Maharaja of— Rewa. The Maharaja of— Tonk. The Nawab of— 2293 F. D.2 SALUTES OF 15 GUNS. Alwar. The Maharaja of— Banswara. The Maharawal of Datia. The Maharaja of— Dew as (Senior Branch). The Baja of— Dew as (Junior Branch). The Baja of Dear. The Baja of— Dholptjr. The Maharaj Bana of • Dxjngarptir. The Maharawal of— Idar.* The Maharaja of— Jaisalmer. The Maharawal of Khairpttr. The Mir of— Kishangarh. The Maharaja of— OrchhaA The Maharaja of— Partabgarh. The Maharawat of— Sikkim. The Maharaja of— Sirohi. The Maharao of— SALUTES OF 13 GUNS. Benares.} The Baja of— Cooch Behar. The Maharaja of— Jaora. The Nawab of— Bampijr. The Nawab of— Tippera. The Baja of— SALUTES OF 11 GUNS. Ajaigarh. The Maharaja of— Baoni. The Nawab of— Bhaunagar.} The Thakur Sahib of— Bijawar. The Maharaja of— Cambay. The Nawab of— Chamba. The Baja of— Charkhari. The Maharaja of— Chhatarpur.} The Baja of— Dhrangadra. The Baj Sahib of— Paridkot. The Baja of— Gondal. The Thakur Sahib of — Janjira. The Nawab of — Jhabua. The Baja of— Jhalawar. The Baj Bana of— Jind. The Baja of — Jtjnagarh.* The Nawab of — Kahlur (Bilaspur). The Baja of Kapurthala. The Baja of— Manei. The Baja of— Manipur. The Baja of— Moryi. The Thakur Sahib of— Nabha.* The Baja of— •See table of personal salutes. tlle • &gt;rCSmtCli * Bhaanagar and Chkatarpur anjoy tha title Si!^ 6 PiXJ'i- POJBA* 1 Bads^ 5 Bajgas Buhpi BaILD glKTHi Stilt. Ieeei Alba Baus Baxsi Bm' Bael Baeh Ceho Dhai Dhei Hsu Kae Kb Kei Kisi Lae La Ln 1i • , • SALUTES OP 11 GUNS —contd. Narsinghgarh. The Raja of— Nawanagar. The Jam of— Palanptjr. The Diwan of— Panna. The Maharaja of— Porbandar. The Rana of— Ptjdttkota. The Raja of— Radhanptjr. The Nawab of— Rajgarh. The Raja of— Rajpipla. The Raja of— Ratlam. The Raja of— Sailana. The Raja of— Samthar.J The Raja of— Sirmtjr (Karan). The Raja of— Sit am atj. The Raja of— Sheet. The Raja of— Terri (Garhwal). The Raja of— SALUTES OF 9 GUNS. Alirajphr. The Rana of — Balasinor. The Nawab (Babi) of— Bansda. The Raja of— Baratjnda. The Ptaja of— Baria. The Raja of— B arwani. The Rana of— Chhota Udaipur. The Raja of— Dharampur. The Raja of—• Dhrol. The Thakur Sahib of—• Padthli Sultan. The— Hsi Paw. The Sawbwa of— Karond (Kalahandi). The Raja of— Keng Tung. The Sawbwa of— Khilchipur. The Rao of— Kjshn and Socotra. The Sultan of — Lahej. The Sultan of — Limri. The Thakur Sahib of — Luna war a. The Raja of — Maihar. The Raja of — Maler Kotla.* The Nawab of — Mong Nai. The Sawbwa of — Nagod. The Raja of — Palitana. The Thakur Sahib of — Rajkot. The Thakur Sahib of — Sachin. The Nawab of — Sawantwari. The Sar JDesai of — Shehr and Mokalla.* The Sultan of — Sunth. The Raja of — Wadhwan. The Thakur Sahib of — Wankaner. The Raj Sahib of — Yawnghwe. The Sawbwa of—* * See table of personal salutes. X The present Chief enjoys the title of Maharaja as a personal distinction.‘Stable of personal iSalutes. SALUTES OF 21 GUNS. Jaipur. His Highness Sir Madho Singh Bahadur, G.C.S.I., G.C.I.E., G.C.V.O. ? Maharaja of— Kolhapur. His Highness Sir Shahu Chhatrapati Maharaj G.C .S. I. , G.O.Y.O., Maharaja of— Mewar (Udaipur). His Highness Sir Eateh Singh Bahadur, G.C.S.I., Maharana of— Travancore. His Highness Sir Bala Bama Varma, G.C.S.I., G.C.I.E., Maharaja of— SALUTE OF 19 GUNS. Mysore. Her Highness Maharani Kempa Nanjammanni Avaru Yaniviias, C.I., of f— SALUTES OF 17 GUNS. Idar. Major-General His Highness Maharajadhiraja Sir Partab Singh Bahadur, G.C.S.I., K.C.B., A.H.C., Maharaja of—- Orchha. His Highness Sir Pratap Singh Bahadur, G.C.S.I., G.C.I.E., Maha raja of— SALUTES OF 15 GUNS. JunaGARH. His Highness Sir Rasulkhanji Mohabat Khanji, G.C.S.I., NTawab of— Nabha. His Highness Sir Hira Singh Bahadur, G.C.S.I., G.C.I.E., Baja of— SALUTE OF 12 GUNS. Shehr and Mokalla. His Highness Awadth-bin-Omar Alkayati, Sultan of— SALUTE OF 11 GUNS. Maler Kotla. His Highness Ahmad Ali Khan Bahadur, Nawab of SALUTES OF 9 GUNS. Bhor. Shankar Bao Chimnaji, Pant Sachiv of— Las Bela. Mir Kamal Khan, Jam of— Loharu. Nawab Sir Amir-ud-din Ahmad Khan Bahadur, K.C.I.E., ot— Mudhol. Meherban Malojirav Vyankatrav Raje Ghorpade alias hana Saheb. of— in tte first in.tnnc during tfie minority of hor .on, the Maharaja of My.ore, and in her rapacity of Regent, and subsequently continued for her life time.lablt of f oral ^aitttco. SALUTES OF 21 GUNS. Bhopal. The Bcgam (or Nawah) of Gwalior. The Maharaja (Smdhia) ot- Indore, The Maharaja (Holkar) ot -r-r- r^r ! Within the limits of their own territories, permanently. SALUTES The Sheikh of Koweit*— The Sheikh of Bahrein*— The Sheikh of Abu Thabi— OF 5 GUNS. ■) Fired by British Ships of War in the ( Persian Gulf at the termination of ) an official visit by these Chiefs. SALUTES OF 3 GUNS. The Sheikh of Debay— The Sheikh of Shargah— The Sheikh of Ajman— The Sheikh of Um-el-Kawain—■ The Sheikh of K»as-al-Kheima— | Fired by British Ships of War in the Persian Gulf at the termination of | an official visit by these Chiefs. J * See table of local personal salutes. 'Habit of fCocal fkroonal .Salntta. SALUTES OF 12 GUNS. The Sheikh of Mohammerah— ) Fired by British Ships of M ar in the S Persian Gulf on the termination ot The Sheikh of Koweit— ) an official visit by these Chiefs. SALUTE OF 11 GUNS. The Sheikh of Bahrein ... ... Fired by British Ships of War in the , Persian Gulf on the termination of an official visit by this Chief. SALUTES OF 5 GUNS. Eldest son of the Sheikh of MohamO Fired on occasions when they visit merah— l one of His Majesty’s Ships as their Eldest son of the Sheikh of Koweit— ) fathers’ representatives. SALUTE OF 3 GUNS. Eldest son of the Sheikh of Bahrein ... Fired on occasions when he visits one of His Majesty’s Ships as his father’s representative.. //£• No. 3S ~®of 1916. Poli-uioal Agenoy, Kuwait The 28th August 1916. From Major il. TH. A. Hamilton, I.A. , Political Agent, Kuwait. To The Hon'ble Xjt—Colonel Sir P.S.Cox, K.G.S.X. , K.G»I»Tj. , Political Resident in the Persian Gulf and Chief Politisal Officer, Basrah. Sir, With reference to your First Assistant's endorsement jjo.265 dated 28th January 1910 I have the honour to report that on Sunday Augu.it «27th H.U.S. ’Lawrenoe* arrived in Kuwait Harbour with Gonmodore D. St.A vfake, C.B., on board. Previous notice had not been given: otherwise it is probable that the Shahdi who ±s now in the Shatt-al-Arab would have returned to reoeive the Com- -aodore. 2. The Politioal Agent called on the Commodore Oxxicialxy at 5-30 P.M. the same day. 3. Next day at 9-30 A.M. Shaikh Sal in, Governor of Kuwait in the absence of hie brother (Shaikh Jabir), aooonpanied by the Political Agent visited the Gomnodore on board H.U.S. 'Lawrence- and was given a salute of 5 guns on the ternination of his visit. 4 . Shis salute has been granted to tne eldest son of the Thaiidi on occasions when he visits one of His Majesty's ships a. hi. father's representative and was not strictly due to Shaikh Salm who is only the brother. However as the representative of the — ooou»i.. th. P.1.0, .nl mtm p “'' *“ the■WWW—ww— jlfllk. ///, the latter is away from Kuwait. The salute waa thus perhaps in aooordanoe with the spirit of the regulation, which was made dur- -ing the life time of the late Shaikh, when it was oustomary for his eldest son, the present Shaikh, to represent his father on such occasions. 5, The case of a brother or other member of the ruling family representing the Shaikh, when out of his dominions, has not pre- -viously occurred and owing to the unexpected nature of this visit, it was not possible for me to refer to you for orders on the point. When consulted by the Commodore, I suggested that Shaikh Salim should be given a salute of 5 guns at the termination of his visit as on occasions when the Shaikh's representative was his eldest son. In so doing I trust I have not created an unde- -sirable precedent, but in any event I venture to recommend tnat tne case, which is likely to recur at intervals during Shaikh Jabir's reign may be considered with a view to extending tne sa- -lute of 5 guns, now receivable by the eldest son, to any member of the ruling family who has been appointed regent of Kuwaio dur- —ing the absence of the Shaikh. 6. A oopy of this letter iu being sent to the Deputy Political Resident in the Persian Oulf, Bushire.Poet script. I make thic recoEnaendation arter a full coruider- -ation of it j effect upon the question of succession. That is a question to he avoided just now and there is no reason why it should arUe in an aoute fona for .joae oiae to oone. Meanv;hile t.ie itui of influenoe and authority in Kuwai o, next uo 3haiKh jabiro i - f'haiiih Salim who besides having a oonuiderable personal following, is oouiiander of the looal foroee. 5he arrangement is ae.de by Shaiith ^abir himself and 1 do not believe he would think of making any onmer, unless possibly, he 'were pressed or en- o our aged by u j to put forward his eldest son. The latter is a man about 33 years of age. He is said to be devoted to the 3ri- -tioh and to be in other ways a promising young man. Meanwhile he remains in the baokground and it would be leaving well alone that we should not. go out o± to allow that to oo.ae about -tate, at cone future tine. 23 - 8 - 16 . our way to bring him out but rather in due cource or au&gt; policy may dio-N°. 11,1+1+ Of 1917. British Residency and C5onsulate- u eneral, Bus-iire, l3nd June 1917. v To The Political Agent, Koweit. MEMORANDUI:. 1 / Your Diary entry No.11 shows Shaikh Salim was given a salute of 12 guns from H.P.5.’’Bramble” on 7th February and again on 8th February. Do you recommend that he should continue to receive a personal salute of 12 guns.Bated'16€h received 17th* Maroon 192'6. Political Agent, Kuwait's iiary No.2 paragraph 11 shows that, salute of 12 was given to present Shaikh of Kuwait had he ever received 12 before ? In reply to telegra i fror Officer Cor anding His Majesty’s Ship I telegraphed on the morning, of 14th February to the effect that five should be given unless you could show that present Shaixh of Kuwait had received 12 before, please report fully by letter specifying occasion on which he did. . political.r £he Hesiden&lt;^' # Bi33hir$&gt; lift June 1020 Dear Wilson, I enclose herewith a copy of a deni-official letter I have sent to Loch about personal salutes for Tio^eit and Hoham- merah.* 1 think it would he a good thing to get rid of the 12 gun sal\:te if possible and I hope you agree* If not there will 'be plenty of tine to send a wire, hut thought it advisable to send off say v/0 at once in case government are on the point of settling Shaikh Salim * s salute. Yours sincerely, Sd/~ A.P.Trevor. To Cony to P # A.Bahrain. * w P»A*Koweit. w w Consul, Hoharanerah* Biout-Col. Sir A.T.Wilson, K.O.I.S. etc. etc. Acting Civil Cormissioncr in Mesopotamia, BAGHDAD. \jg.' ^ 4 , 4 - . Vtfr-nij. 7 (fc. *- - -• -X-- — — with reference to this office endorsement no.920 dated w/b/SO.ISO* Of X9B0, British HeBidenoy and Conpulato-Uajieral, Buahlra, Hay 19fc0. From To Liout-Colonal A*P*Trevor, J #f o.I*K.» (&amp;/ Deputy Politloal Hoaidant, Persian ^ilf. The Hon’ble ^r,H.M.G.LrObba # 0.a*I,,C w I.K. # Forei^i oecretary to the Govemiaent of India, Foreign, and Political Deparinant, SIMLA# Sir, I have the honour to address you in continuation of my lettei Ko*74£, dated 4th May 1920 on the subject of salutea to Chiefs in the Persian Uulf* At present shaikh ^ir nhazal Khan,(1*0.1.of Slohanmarah, Shaikh Sallxa bin Hubarak, of Kowelt, and ^&gt;haikh Sir Ib&amp; bln All get p or norm 1 salutes the first two of twelve guns each and the 3rd of 11 guns. Shaikh Sal in rather drooped into hie personal salute without earning it, as he succeeded at the height of the war; as a natter of fact he hae adopted rather an obstructive policy, and if he had not enjoyed &amp; personal salute of 18 guns since hie acoeueion I should have hesitated to recom mend him for it now. However, that is beside the point of this letter which is that actual valuta that each of these Shaikhs would get as Chiefs of their respective districts would be only 6 guns. As I have recently recommended and Government have sanctioned a local salute of 7 guna to the oh&amp;ikh of Qatar, I think the local salute (sx-officio and apart from personal honours) of the Shaikhs of Mohannerah, Koweit and Bahrain should be raised to 7 guns also. This should be the salute to which the more important Shaikhs would bo entitled on acoeasion, and they should not expect to obtain the personal salute mi Joyed by their predeeossore until they have shown by their actions and behaviours that they deserveFurther X would suggest that on the danise or abdication of tho preo^it inounbanta of ' ohanrand Koweit the salute of 13 i$una should bo abolished and 11 guns (or IS) be granted as a personal distinction when necessary, Salutes are nearly always in odd numbers of guns and the personal salute of 13 guns was only introduced In the dulf because when the question of a personal salute to Shaikh Mubarak was raised Colonel Knox then Political Agent thought that the Shaikh should get a Hlgger salute than the Political Agent; Colonel Prideaux then at Bahrain thought that the Shaikh there should n ot get more than the Political Agent, hence the difference between the salutes of the Shaikhs of Koweit and Bahrain* When the personal salute for the shaikh of liohanmerah was mooted it was thought that he could not have leas than the Shaikh of Koweit. I liave the honour to be, sir, lour 'ioet obedient servant. Sd/~ A* P, Trevor, Lieut-Colonel. Deputy Political Meaident, Persian Lulf#Telegram Code From Political„ Kuwait* To Citfcom Baghdad* No. /3 2_ . Bated 27th Beptei::her 1920* Shaikh of Kuwait asks what salute Sir Percy Cox should have as High Commissioner.DRAFT—(For Approval). Political Residency, Persian Gulf, No. Dated 190Your No. 920 of 3°th May. Now that Shaikh Salim is dead question of salute for Ruler of Kuwait requires consideration,' I presume that % v pending further instructions from Government of India Shaikh Ahmad . ?all he entitled to five guns only? Telegram (P). ■ d Prom Fraser &gt; Bushire. N To Political, Kuwait, * Ho. 461. Bated 14th (Reed. t5th) March 19^1. Your telegram No, ^6-C of 24th February. I am instructed by the Resident, who wishes to raise the salute to seven guns, to ask the Foreign and Political Department of the Government of India. It is probable that no definite answer will be forthcoming in the immediate future. Meanwhile if yd can please try and avoid giving ; .t salute. Telegram (Code). From Resident, Bushira. To Political, Kuwait. Ho. 758. Dated the 14th May ? 92 l. , My telegram of 14th March No.361 (? 461). Government of India have / ' \ sanctioned the raising of local and personal salute to Shaikh of Kuwait from five to seven guns as provisional measure. ys: 7^7Extract from a latter No. 893 dated 26th May 1922 fror? the Hon’ble Lieut-Golonel A.P.Travor, O.S.I. ,0,1.E., Political deaident in the Persian Gulf, to Denys de S.Bray, Psquire, O.S.X.,0.I.E. f G.B.E., Foreign Secretary to the Government of India in the For^gn and Pdlitical Department, Simla. Salutes for Chiefs in the Persian Gulf. Sir, In continuation of my letter No.919, dated 30th May 1920, I have the honour to address you again on the subject of the revision of salutes for Chiefs in the Persian Gulf. This question was deferred vide your telegram No.513-3, dated 11th April 1921, hut I consider it is now time that these salutes i should he put on to a permanent basis, and I herewith put up my proposals which I venture to hipe will he favourably considered by the Government of India. x x x x -xx x KUWAIT . Under your telegram No.513-3, dated 11th Aoril 1921 the salute of the Shaikh of Kuwait was raised to ? guns provisionally apart from personal honours and I would recommend that this be made permanent. In addition I would request sanction for a salute of 5 guns for the eldest son or deputy of the Shaikh as recommended in my letter No.2124, dated 18th December 1916, para. 4. x x x xxx Thus briefly the changes shown in the annexed 4 schedule would be necessary in the table of salutes provided my suggestions are approved. In most of the oases, however, I would note that provisional sanction has already been given. X x X X XX KUWaIT . Permanent salute for ohaikh. ...M gons Salute for eldest son or deputy of Shaikh 5 guns when **4 visiting one of H.M»s ships as the Shaikh’s representative.■HR Qonfidential jgemo randum. Hq . 6* 1. It is said here that Idialid, who is a son of Muhammad and a nephew of Sheikh Mubarek, has been made a Pasha, that he is on very good terms with Sheikh Kubarek, from whom he has received £T.8,000 and 200 camels. It is also said that the Sultan has sent presents to Mubarek and settled him on an allowance of £T.150/- a month. Mubarek is said to have sent 15 horses to the Sultan, but my informant could not tell me who had bought the presents nor by what road the horses had been sent.Tioies on the events of the Subah family , On the 1st Jul a 1905,Sheihh Mo- Death of the SheifiAs mother. barak’s mother^Lulwa, died. It was said that / at the time of her death she was 112 ..ears old,This lad^ lived separate from her sons in the house now occupied by the Agency tc clerks and dispensary .Sheikh. Mobaraic used to visit her on ever., Friday morning. Death of Fahad. Fahad the 5th lame son of Sheikh Mobarak / / died on the morning of the 18th Ma^ 1905.The bo^ had been slowly d., ing for the past 2 aars It was said that the Sheikh was ashamed of this bOj ’ s existence as he was never well. One of his legs was amputated in bomb ay g&gt; Death of Sheikh Subah. * Death of the Sheikh’s smster. On the 20th June 1906 Sheikh Subah, the r ?rd son of Sheikh Mobarak,died of consumption. Assistant Surgeon Daudur Rahman was called in bj Sheikh Mobarak on the 1st June when h®s condition was dangerous to give his opinion on the state of the patient but did not place him in his hands for medical treatment,Sheikh Subah was treated b„ a native pi\, sician.His condition was pronounced to be ver u critical and he died within^ 20 da 0 s.He exsercised^ while in good health magisterial powers&gt; tried cases of less gravity• 0h the 24th Fovember 1907 evening y the elder sister of Sheikh Mobarak,Hebaba,died. She had married two husbands.The first Khalifa^ of the Subah family had b, her a so^Sa’ud^ now about 54 ears old who is a Koweit mer chant. The second, Fazil, was the son of Sheikh Diaij,brother of Subah and Sheikh Mobarak’s uncle.Fazil had a son,Jabir,who lives at——— — i^i- Jimljas and is now over 50 ears old#His pe digree connects in ‘tlie following wa 0 :- Hababa, during her life time,used to tr^ cases- pett„ complaints and ouarrels- both of men and women and Sheikh Mobarak alwa^ s respected her dicision the cases decided b., her. Sheikh Mobarak has proposed his ^oungest exchange his own(Sheikh Mobarak’s) daughter to Sa f ud bin Muhammad, the 2nd son of the same father.The marriage ceremone^ was to take place in one of these da^ s and all preparations for the occasions were read,, • But there are strong protests against these proposals from all the sons of Sheikh Mo barak heading from Sheikh Jabir who is , it is said, mostly concerned.'Jhe whole thing is now hanging fire and it is said that Sheikh Mobarak is determined to carr^ out his intentions notwithstanding the strong objections.If however^the marriages do take place it is feared that there is sure to be bloodshed in the near future or as soon as the old Sheikh closes his e.,es and it is on this account the strong objections are put forward.Sheikh Sub ail 1 Mobarak/present Sheikh) Jabir. Fazil 1 Jabirbin Fazil (mentioned above) of his late ' ' brother Muhammad,-mad*daughter in Marriage and give inm. Hobarak's daughter was to marr^ at Zain, (V^) near basra where it is said the Sheikh has r • / given some date plantations to his ne phew^ Saud bin Muhammad, the prospective groom.it x&amp; Here the girl’s grandmother also lives.The Sheikh, it is said,has written for Egyptian dancing girls for these occasions and the Sheikh of Muhamme- rah is expected.Further it is said that the places where the marriages were to take place were furnished with fumitube etc.. SIMkxJcx LOCAL OFFICIALS . 103. Sheikh Mubarak is suffering from acute'bronchitis with K&amp;Kt&amp;i cardiac and renal complications. He is being treated by Dr. Harrison of the American Mission and Assis- -tant Surgeon C.C. &amp;elly who consider his condition as serious. Sheikh Jabir who is about a day’s distance in the interior has been s it is stated, sent for to 1 . 00 k at- -ter the Sheikh's affairs. X X X X X XDRAFT—(For Approval). Political KEfsitfEi/ofy Persian GclK/ Kuwait No.__aA&gt; Dated A.rll rrjia . T% e^ratefTil if ^e?3dt: - C^irarder A.E. H.M.s. ^AlerV* Dear Wnod, If y-n wonldnH irind I tihall be cnuld make the following wireless for ire to To Resdt , BUSHIl^E. f, Got back today and saw Mu &gt;arak who seems fa:Lrly con -valescent though good deal shaken stop No Politics discus ed Shakespear” I hope its not too long to be a nuisanc^. y'urs sincerely. /C3- W.H. . shakespearDRAFT—(For Approval). Agency, Political /Residency/ Persian Gule. Kuwait No. D/0 Dated. 28rd Arril ^3 To, rres age by Resident, BO^HIRE. J ear ^ir Percy, In continuation of py hurried wireless 'Alert” , re the Sheikh ! s nines' , 'T’he doctors, Harrison A Kelly , had not seen blip since See 18th but saw hi tp again to-day- 22nd- and found hi| - er • Attached T give Kelly f s report of to-day, -couraging as tar as it g^es. I shall go and see to-day; this ii a urried line t' go by 'Bandura' you au conrant, as py pails won f t reach y^u ^nti Monday, My capels only cape in to-day afternoo I have been pestered to death with visitors all yours sincerely. W,H. T . ^hakespeai* p Puch befc- whlch is en- hi p again to keep 1 n, and I day. 9,000-3-10Note by Its si deucy Surgeon X gather from above acoouait of the Sheikl^s condition, that ho i** oiif fori fig from disease especially affecting the hoart and blood vessels, by which they, especially the blood vessels, boGoiao very hard and rigid, having lost their former elasticity, so that the heart ie put to great strain in pumping blood through them and too often on© or other yields or breaks, resulting in heart failure or a cerebral haemorrhage or something of that sort* It is all important to keep the Sheikh ce quiet as poss ible, in a recumbent or -recumbent pc nation, and every thing should be done for tiixa to avoid his making any sudden bodily effort* Mental anxiety or vorry is equally bad# X agree with what Assistant Surgeon Kelly cays about hie diet. Food and driiJk should be limited to a minimum chiefly milky food, su$h as 3engor's Food, Horlxck’s malted milk or Mollin f G Food or Allanbury*e Diets, and milky puddings etc* Eggs, meat, soups, meat essences, tea, tobacco, all act as poieone in the Sheikh*s present condition and must not be allowed* 'Phe less food and drink he takes the better and should be taken in small quantities, several times during the day, tx rather than in 2 big meala which are apt to lie in the stomach and embarrass the already overworked heart* r rh© very slow pul as indicates at what a disadvantage the heart is working* Relief should be ontained by judicious purging, leeches a pulled to heart region - bleeding woui'» no doubt do much good if permi tted - rest, mental and bodily - diet, and Uotaesirtm Iodide given as medicine snd small ioees of Liquor Trinitrini or Tabellaa nitroglycerine for any exacerbation of distress orvdioconfort* S« Huntmrnmsmmmmim ^^JB^cHoBstdate^neral, Bnahite. j.u'y d ©til'' '39'P‘3 tiX* y A merjry Xrraa and a happy now Year fcoj^ou. 1 was so sorry that you did not manage to get here fior /nas, as I was id oh m ^ f or w r ■ to a ou^h wit you« In the meantime I write a hasty note at dead of night to tell you the following bit of news, * bomb wua thrown at Lord ^ardinge whilst riding in the stats entry at Delhi on the 23rd . The Vic roy received a slight wound in the shoulder, -ady Hardinge escaped unhurt.x One Jamadar was killed and another wound d in 3 places. Bomb apparently thrown frorr a roof of a house in Chandni Cahuk. Several ai t boon mada. S.r G.FLebtwcod is acting in the place of Lor . a. later Viceroy made a speech with referance to the tastily outrage, vociferously applauded. PWoession went original ftoute, no change being made. Latest news from P.S.V.Delhi is dated today 4 n.,n, to the effect that wounds were serious but it is hoped nfc danger ousy': Viceroy had spe^t a restless night and that he was slightly easier today. perhaps Mubarak will wire condolences and express satisfactio, at providential escape of Lord . thinks it would be a good thing is he dad Resident, With all seasonable wishes yours sincerely1 left Kow®it for a tour along the pearl tanka to Bahrein on the 24th Auguet* The Koweit pearl boats were nov® -ing northwards # dally expecting the signal closing the 1010 pearling season. A largej* nuaber of the bigger boats, sons 20© or more, were congregated eff Jazlrat Abu All, the reaaln* -der being strung out between Ras tana jib and Has as-Zor. 2« Here I was asked whether I had any news of the natter between Sheikh Mubarak and the towaahes, but on enquiry as to what the natter between then referred to I could get no res- •ponse. A diver on ny launch,however, said there was sons wild talk of the diving community deserting Koweit in a body if the Sheikh refused to agree to their requests to ease the burden of useless expenditure imposed upon then in consequence of his operations against Sheikh Sadun of the Muntlfieh. on arrival at Bahrein on the 28th August Captain Mackenzie gave ae the opportunity of seeing soae Influential Bahrein aen, who inforaed ae that all the wealthy Kowet. t - washes had agreed ft not to return to Koweit at the end of tip 40 : the present diving season unless Mubarak accepted thalr teras vizi- that they should be relieved of the Indefinitely oontln- -ued expense of keeping up a foroe for reprisals on Sheikh Sadun, as the drain of capital was seriously crippling their industry. I woe Informed also that the boats I saw at Jaxlrat Abu All were waiting there for orders fron the Towaahes, as/ 77, moot of them were their property* and that their orewe would follow the owners* who were said to be negotiating for a settlement at Dammam* a few miles south of Katif. Hearing that some of the Koweit men were in Bahrein I endeavoured to discover the real facts from certain pnkhudas and Bishr bin Humi, who controls the fleets operations* but without succeed for they would only admit that they had heard much the same * and did not know how far it was true. 4. Subsequently I had a long Interview with tiio Towashes the richest and perhaps most Important in ^oweit* who said they spoke for themselves and two other Towashes* also amongsf t the most important* the nakhudaa and crews of their own boats! and of those dependent on them for financial support. They, however* excluded one rich Towash and Bishr bin Rumi • After reldSing their grievances in having to find a large number (more than their fair proportion) of flghuiag men* camels* tents, rifles* ammunition, and foot for the Sheikh's raid in March last they said that what bore most hardly on them was the wontinued expense of maintaining these ior months on end (more than six months already) with no visible prospect of an early cessation* They said they were at tL &lt; end of their tether and unless some alleviation wae forth- -coming bankruptcy was their oertain end. Accordingly they had removed their valuables quietly from Koweit and had al~ -lowed it become known there that they would not return them-themselves for the above reasons and that also probably some POO boats with their orewe would be misoing fro» the returning fleet. They had not actually written to the Sheikh because 1- was inadvisable to expose particular persons to the Sheikh*e ? vengeance. They had received a written invitation from Sheikl Jasia bin Than! to settle in Xatar but they would prefer Bah- -rein, where they felt themselves more eeoAre from molestation But there was the objection to Bahrein that Sheikh Isa al Kha.f- -ifa would certainly order them to leave should Mubarak a&amp;dreSS him on the subject, even if he did not do so of his own raotioi to avoid friction between himself and Mubarak. They were thitk -ing of settling at Dammam as its proximity to Katif would ensure them grom reprisals 9 or at Qasr-as-babaih with the Al bu Ainain, but the latter place was objectionable, bei^ regarded as within Mubarak *8 jurisdiction. The news of their determination having got abroad it was impossible for them to return to K 0 weit without some solid guarantee that their persons and property would be respected. If the boats and their crews returned this year their flnanctkl obligations to the Towashes would require their coming back t&lt; them the following season, after which it was extr^-aU -bable they would return to Koweit# The Towashes went on to / say that they were all KoweitArabs by birth and family tradit^ and did not want to leave, but oould re.ain no longer If the present exactions continued, their only hope lay in the chancyof the Reslent or the Political Agent intereetlng thennelre.' In their diffloultloa, and. If the Political Agent could guarantee or obtain a guarantee fro® the 3 h©tkh again® reprisala and further exaotiona, they were quite willing to return ac all they wanted was bare justice. £ told tnem that as they had been frank with me I would see what oould be done; I would first consult the Resident and then go on to ^oweit. I saw no chance of the British Government openly supporting the® against *Ubarnk, their own Sheikh, but it was possible that Mubarak, if quiet -ly shown the probable damage he was doing to Koweit and to himself and the evil effects on his prestige of tho proposed emigration, would himself move in tho natter. I told then that their names and our conversation would not be divulged and that if any solution of the difficutly waa arrived at I must not appear in itj it would come fro® Mubarak and must b^ accepted as of his own initiative* They begged me to write to them in Bahrein, but I explain -ed that was undesirable and I would prefer to let the Pol Agent Bahrein know how matters went and he would inform the® verbally. 6 . The incident is serious, and is of course the resul/i* of the Towashes having seen how successfully the A1 bu Ainain carried out their move last year fro® Katar. In the case of Koweit it will be far more serious as tho whole of the avail-available wealth and capital in Koweit ie derived fro* the no P ’arl industry. Ihe four Towashee oonoerned represent so*e % 1 25 to 50 lakhs of rupees In capital and probably hare some financial hold difceot or indirect over aorae 25d to 500 boats and perhaps 6000 to 8000 men* It can bo imagined shat effect the displacement of this large amount of capital and population (for the men would follow their leading Towashes very shortly) would have on the ooKimerolal prosperity of the port of Koweit* ~ly plainly the undesirability of forcing such an emigration pointing out the certain lose to Koweit, to himself personallj and the damage to hie good name and to euggeet that it would be politi* on his part to take the intiative by lightening the oppresive burden his (hltherto^iselese) military prep&amp;ra- -tiona against Sadun have laid on his peopbe# I should urge the above as a private friend pointing out carefully that I m not conunisoionsd to interfere between him and his people and all I am suggesting is solely for hia own benefit and that of his town for of course Government would not like to see the place or Mubarak’s prestige weakened, a result the proposed exodus would certainly bring about* Any concession mede by himself would knit hla people *ore closely to please Government by showing how wisely ha had dlalt with the 7* I think I know the Sheikh well enough to explain fairconsiderably If I could proco^d absolutely informally on the above lines adding that I had consulted the u enident and he V \ was strongly of the opinion that Mubarak should make the con- -cession himself rather than drive away the most Important portion of hie population and that if the diving community de -ired to settle at Bahrein it would be Impossible to forbid their doing so. Mubarak is thoroughly alive to hie own inters but his pride might make the concession difficult unless it was hinted that Government would see no reason to ask Sheikh Isa to turn the ^oweitis out of Bahrein should they elect to go there, whilst a settlement Dammass would be viewed with strong disfavour. Bushire 2- 9- 10 \4 Extracts from Kuwait news for wss&amp; ending 31st /x 1910 x X X X 83. The pearling fleet returned during trie ween from their annual visit to the pearl ban&amp;s. News has reached Kuwait that the richest and tne leading Toimshia of Kuwait - Hellal CJmtair, S'hamlan tin Saif and Ebrahim bin Matnaf - have approached the British authorities in Bahrain with a view to obtaining British protection for them selves and for their nakhodas and sailors and thus avoid Shaikh Bub a rax 1 s continued (zulum) tyranny demands for money. It is said that the Towaahis have expressed their intention not to return again to Kuwait but to settle permanently in Bahrain or at any other place the British Government may be pleased to allot to them in the Bahrain terri tory. The Towashis, it is said, had prearranged among themselves to tame this step and had quieolj tauten away vvith them all their valuables leaving behind only their families, fhey actornad also bidden good-bye to their faithful trieude in Kuwait telling them that they would not return to Kuwait. A large number of nakhodas and sailors are suill away and it is feared that they too will follow the example of their To wash! s and remain with them. The news has been re reived with great .joy and ^a- tisfaction in all quarters in Kuwait and opinions hazarded that, if the attempt made by their leader* turns a success, they too will follow the example. 84. With Hellal Umtairi, it is said, there is a goodly number of pearlers whose debts he has promised to forego and destroy his account books in t^ir presence provided they remain with him. He has// also proiuised uo build new houses for t/hem ab his 0\r/n cost before he bmlds one for hiiiiself. 85. Shaikh Mubarak is said Po be heartily sorry over Phis. Shaikh Jabir is aBBtmax oursing and swearing aP Phe aoPion and oonduou of the Powashis and Nasir Pasha, Phe blind son of Shaikh Mubarak, is said no have much regraPued his faPher's acuion and Pyracmioal PreaPaenP of nhe people and has ex pressed hope Po coax him no Pry ana co send some one uO Bahrain Po brim^ back Phe Powaahis and others promising them good PreaPmenP in uhe future. 86. Incidentally Phe Polix-ical Agent's visit Po Bahrain came off .just in the nick of time when Phe Kuwait Powashis uhough of seeking redress under the Brinish GovernmenP• Phe people have mis- consnrjied^ Phe object of the FoliPical Agent*8 visit and say' that Phe question of Uie Kuwait Towashis must have been under discussion for a long time between wsstsx Phe 2 Political Agents of Bahrain and Kuwait and that nhe present visit of the latter officer to Bahrain is no finally smooth over matters. 87. Peoole are heartily glad and say that the nime has at last come for the Shaikh to learn a lesson and to put a stop no further injustice an', tyranny* The final result is anxiously awaited and frequent enquiries are being made as to when the Pol ini cal Agent will be back to Kuwait. 88. Arrivals from the pearl banks on nno ^ ua report that, besides the 3 le ading fowashis tioned above, the following big nakhodas and pearlers have also remained behind. Phey are.- Bashir bin Roomi, Ahraed bin Dab bus, Mannai - 3 brothers, Rashid bu Rusli, Khoma, Jasim bin Asfoor and his brother, msa, Kasir Nejdi, Sa*ad &gt;&gt;*!« /m 1 ^alli and many others./u B9 # Zaid ul r^iialid wlio r a'turned on tine evening of the 39th from the pearl banks went uo see uhe Shaikh and gave him details of what had happened. He no Id the Shaikh that all those than had not as yet returned to Kuwait would not do so. Where upon the Sheikh is said no have got much enraged; wrote out several letters and da stanched them to Bahrain by nhe hands of Husain Din Saif, brother of Shfuulan bin Saif (who has, it is sand, non followed his brother but may do so now) and Paris ul Whogaian, the Shaikh’s Bedouin zikat collector. They left for Bahrain on nhe night of 39th. 90. On the morning of the 30nh Shaikh Mubarak despatched his Customs boat to ,.ias Abu Ali where he has heard a good many of Kuwait nakhodas and pearlers are anchored discussing as uo the spot the^ should settle on. The boat is in charge of Hasir el Bedar, an influential Kuwaiti. He is to try and in due o them no come back 'uo Kuwait. The Shaikh has given Nasir el Seder a number of rifles in case there should be any disturbance and necessity for recourse to # firearms. 91. One immediate good result of nhe snap naken by nhe To wash! s and nearlers is that Shaikh Mubarak has quietly given orders on the 30th for nhe dismissal of the raiding force at Jahara. He has ordered, in is said, that nhe raiders should take their omi camels etc with them. He has also told them that he would buy all the good camels for himself. The Shaikh, however, does not wish that the news of nhe disbandment of nhe rai ling force should get abroad* 93. The talk of nhe week is nothing but the '.o- washis and nakhodas and nheir sailors* x Xi^iaiwwaywwfflijaffligB^M Ext.raG*b3 from Kuwait news for weak ending 7tli September 1910. /f7. x X X 99* Shaikh Mubarak; is said to have sent for and taken charge of Hillal (Jmtairi’s horses which were out in the desert with the Uiiitair Shaikhs. 100. Shaikh Mubarak’s raiders returned from Jahara on the night of uhe 1st September. All c:Uitels and firearms etc were returned to their owners* It is said&gt; the Shaikh at iirst allowed the bigger merchants only to tame their camels and rifles and retained others. This caused much talk and heartburning among tne smaller mercnanus. They discussed why only the bigger merchants should get their property bacx and not the others, thereupon, it is said, one Jasim Budai, who enjoys Shaikh Mubarak * s good graces, went up to the Shaikh and expl lined to him what people were saying and that it would be advisable to return everybody's camels etc. It is said, the Shaikh readily consented and gave orders to that effect. The Shaikh is said to have oecome veiy tame and courteous after the trouble of the To was his and pearlers and is now ever ready' to listen to reason and to help. 101. A good iuany of doe nkhodas uid otUera, tfhose return to Kuwait was at first doubted, have arrived during the week. It is said tnao they we re doubtful whether or not the British uovt would extend to their leaders(Towashis) uheir paternal protection and so they thought it better to return to Kuwait for Uie Assaz.m. month and then, xf tneir leaders succeed in their efforts in obtaining tneir object, to remain away when ohey again visit* ^ • W. the pearl banks aft^er the itaiuzm Eed. They also thought that by coming to Kuwait they would get the ohanoe of uaKing away their valuable them* x X X 105. Maser el Beder and Husain bin Baif,brother of Shamlan, roturned on the 4th froiit Bahrain un- auoooaaful. Husain, it is said, tried his best to induce his brother but ‘.vitnout success. Shamlan it is said, bold Husein that he -.’ouli not 001119 to Kuwait unless Shaikh Mubarak aepuued hio oQ^t Shaikh Saliiu, and alien too he would require guarantee that nothing would be done to him or his prouerts' it he returned to Kuwait. X04. Shaikh Mubarak has written to Shaikh Salim vmo is at Juntas, to come and go to Jazirat-al- Amas'ir where Shamlaii is said no be. Shaikh Salim is said to be afraid to go on this mission as he mistrusts his father and fears that he may be blamed if he did not succeed in inducing Shuulan and others. ***105. Shaikh Salim returned from Juntas on the night of the dth and after consulting Shaikh Sstla Mubarak left for Jazirat-al-Amayir on -one mom- ing of the 7th in his father’s steam launch vide paragraph 98 above. It is said Sh.mlan has written to his friends, Hillal and Sbrahim Manhaf, ho come and see Shaikh Salim. 106. In connection with me troubles of the rearl- -ers, it is feared, than 8 of ihe Kuwait men will eventually come in trouble with bhe Shaikh. ; mey are (1) Abdulla al Hajri and (2) Yusuf bin Miumis. These men, it is said, are bhe chief cause of all this nrouble as bhey have acned beyond bhe . „ m qbused r ^“i i opT&gt;resaed Phe Bhaijh* s orders and Have aousea ^ people without li.* it.Extract/ from Bahrein Diar^ for week ending the //^ 2nd September 1910. -ing season. Out of these 10 belong to Ibrahim bin Ma - -dhaf and 7 to Hilal al Matairi. The latter sent a jolly boat to other Koweit Tawwashes. (pearl buyers) and ffakhudas requesting them also to come to Bahrein. It would however appear that they do not intend to do so, although some are said to be waiting at the; Jazi- -rat-al-Amair ( ) awaiting results. It is said that there would have been a large immigration only seeing the Koweit Steam Launch on the banks, they believed that the Political Agent had been requested by Sheikh Mubarak to assist him in obtaining the re- -turn of any' immigrants and they thus feared to im- -p1icate themselves. Ibrahim bin Madhaf and Hilal al Matairi had made overtures from Darin through Mansur bin Juma&gt; to the Kaimmakan of Qatif to pemit them to settle at Dammam ( ) &lt;* This was only a precaufi ojia.it measure in case they r could obtain no assurance of safety from Sheikh Mubarak or Sheikh Esa. offer was not accepted. On arrival in Bahrein these men natuaally went to Abdullah bin Hass an, Dosiri, Chief of the Dowasir, and leader inrgeneral of the tribes inhabit -ing Bahx’ein. x x X X X Condition of Country . 307 Owing to Sheikh Mubarak* s extortions 17 Koweit boats came to Bahrein at the end of the Pearl- Sheikh Jasim bin Thani also requested them Het?3. He brought these two among others to visit the Political Agent, Koweit, who discussed the quest- -ion with them. After Captain Shake spear* s departure, they visited Sheikh Esa and asked him what policy he would adopt. He replied he would like to see them settle amicably with Sheikh Mubarak, but would not hand them over to the latter, and would permit them to live in Bahrein if they desired. They are now saying that they would not return to Koweit even if they receive assurance from Sheikh Mubarak. Later news states that Husain bin Rumi has been reconciled, to Sheikh Mubarak. The 1 attei then sent Husain and one of his own mfLn to tiy to peioiiade Hilal and others to return to Koweit. There are some divers and tawwashes (pearl buyers) at the island Jinn ah of the Jazirat-ai-Amair ) awaiting final results. Husain^Rumi told them to go to Koweit but they refused to do so. He then asked them to go over to Darin and await results there, as- -suring them that very soon Sheikh Mubarak will send his representative^ to come to terms with them* Husain then sent a letter with Sheikh* s man to Hilal in Bahrein asking him to return with his companions to Jinnah whence to proceed to Koweit. Hilal replied that he would never return to Koweit, said that his divers could do what they liked. Sheikh’s man took Hilal *s reply and return- -ed to Juma. x x X X X X X X X XI m /f /9i 'Extract from Banrein Diary for week ending the 9th September 1910. x x X X X CONDITION of COUNTRY . 31-5. With reference to paragraph 307, Husain bin All bin Rumi arrived here on the 8th September with his brother and a,shed Hilal al Matairi and Ibrahim cin Madhaf to forgive Sheikh Mubarak who is now ready to do whatever they would desire for their future comiort and that Sheikh’s steamer with Sheikh's son Salim on board was waiting for them at. Has Tannura. Hilal ana Ibrahim replied that they could not accept any agree- -ment of Sheikh Mubarak and in no case could they be reconciled to him except under the gurantee of the Political Agent. Then Husain returned to Ras Tannuara to con- -sult Sheikh Salim bin Sheikh Mubarak. On 4th September 1910, Sheikh Esa received a letter from Sheikh Mubarak asking him not to entertain Mubarak's refugees in Bahrein. Sheikh Esa replied to Sheikh Mubarak that he would not prevent them settling in Bahrein, and ha,d is own subjects absconded to Koweit he would not have addressed Mubarak about tham. He continued that these men had had some conversation with the Political Agent, Koweit, purport of which Sheikh Mubarak was probably aware. He however desired from the bottom of his heart that an amicable settle -ment be arrived at between him (Mubarak) and his subjects. The fact is that Hilal and Ibrahim are a- -fraid of being murdered by Sheikh Mubarak inciting some Bedouin to kill them in the desert or even m Kowe.it itself. It has been reported that t-hes saidHHBBHWBWW——B m the^ would not- go back even with British Government guarantee as this would not protect them from their death being instigated Mubarak who could aftei’warda deno all knowledge. It is freely said that a man who would kill his brother would not hesitate to do any- -thing. 8£8c8£8?8c828e8?8c&amp;fc8?8&amp;8c8c&amp;u?8c&amp;Q2&amp;&amp;3e£e&amp;(}:£cie8ed:mmtBmsmmmm £r&amp; % KJ7 Extracts from Bahrain News for week ending 16th Sep tember 1910. x xxx Condition of counts; . 319. Vith reference to paragraph 315, Shaikh Salim bin Mubarak arrived from Ras Tannum in his father's launch 'Mashrif Surah' accompanied by Husain bin gai.Rumi'. Hilal al Matairi, Ibrahim bin Madhaf, Shamlan and Husain bin Saif bin Rumi discussed the subject with Shaikh Salim, in the presence of Shaikh E#sa bin Ali. Hilal said that as Shaikh Salim had come to them from Kuwait they were ready to be reconciled with their Shaikh, provided, that Shaikh Salim gave an undertaking on behalf of his i at he r that hru-*„ would be treated in Kuwait with consideration, their life and property would be protected and no harm would be done to them. On these conditions onl u , they said, they could return to Kuwait with Shaikh Salim. Shaikh Salim replied he would take Hilal and others to his father in Kuwait with whom they could settle as they desired. Ibrahim bin. Mad ha:: and his companions agreed to return to Kuwait with Shaikh Salim but Hilal would not agree. Shaikh Esa remarked to Shaikh Salim that Hilal wanted assurance for the safety oi his lixe and, he could not give this, Hilal feared the more for his life. Shaikh Salim replied to Shaikh Esa r,hat he was not authorized by his father to make any promises and supposing his father killed any body, it did not follow, that he should kill his father for their sakes. Hilal, hearing the reply of Shaikh Salim, absolutely refused to accompany Shaikh Salim while Ibrahim and his companions left in the launch for KuwaitShaikh. Esa has written to Shaikh Mubarak that all the Kuwaitis were reconciled, except Hilal al Matairi who demanded guarantee for the safety of his ±xx life in Kuwait, but was not given Shaikh Salim x x x/ J €&gt;&lt;} of 3 tat*e i o- till la* Th&lt;sr^' le nothin^ aoeclal to record r^arclin th.lo_ except perhaps that the Interview .as a vaT tJ plea ant T e left Lonlon on 'Joverahsr 3rd and arrived in 'rla 40 rn I rig. Here .70 stayed at the Central Station Hotel. Oh. $th we had dunthco a at the Cl t v o one. y aex t Sfo^emb©’^ , .. Cha-ibe^s with the Lord Provost, alviermon and friondn. After - luncheon we Inspected the Chambers and then mmt'to see the Jniverslty and Art •* * v .'/e Hext olt, Oallerles. Hridge ^ — ' ' - ^ ^ A V - J A. W # motored to Queensferry via Edinburgh,saw the 7orth were taken through a sutriarine. The next day was to be and our last In Britain:we vlslVd some shlppln to the aerodrome at Hetifrew. ^ different ty. eg,then exhibitions of flying and finall thre $ follow® s and myself went up in separate planes. - — — -A V- ^ ^ ^ M , * S. / - t S ^ A. ■* * W y -A. A V 4 -W » ■» A o ^ very hard go get the Shaikh hi is&gt;. If to fly* He got so far gat dressed and into one but-then his courage forsook him made excuses and tha v Pyramids. November 4th,the Mission was — w .,5. received by Lord we visited the,Citadel and wer shown throu^ Hohanmel ’All and afterwards we attended an At nua«. j^y^u ^ -r M^ e Mission* Hoveabsr f6th,Shaikh Ahmuc .an l myself was r*.- g interview. In the rASinli th* party n«t day (D*c»rab.r IStn) th.n *. &lt; ,t&gt;L wtn the r r rgdL thft dh th :v:,;L/“o for me ve re o O town was dressed beyond the Shaikh for Shaikh as I stepped ,t 8 ^ yards' and than went ere we saw scores f aeroplanes of the Shaikhib We tried as to au^ sk^vvr- iAAiu arul he saying it was not bia enough for him, that he ms afraid he might touch what he wa# told he should k-ep claar of,etc and finally got out* It was a gre • t pity w® could not gr ! t him to up. Hsxt da£, Noveaber dih we sails! from Olacgow. The Shaikh .is a very poor sailor and .as -&gt;v had exception ally bad wesrthsf* almost the whole of .the way it cannot bt S said that he enjoyed his time on board. We passed a floating mine in the teditorrane&amp;n*. This added to his iiscofifItur:i. He »as very nervous after that until we arrived In Alexandria. '-?&lt;# - got there on the morning of November fist. We were iaet by H .jor gayer Andercon,H• A.M. C.,aii officer attached by the Residency, lairo to the ission during its stay ^ in dgy &gt;t. ' T e saw as much of Alexandria s possible that day. W® stayed* aV tne Savoy Hotel that night and next morning set out for Cairo t ;Ich ve reached gabout noon. Here mo stayed at Shephoard s Hotel. In the afternoon of the first day we attended a race meetig ing. Next day (November f'rd) we visited the Zoological darclyns Allenby who presented the Shaikh wi th -two autographed p.iotogrApii-s - )ne r for %imse 1 f and the other' for Shaikh Sallsu In the afternoui h the No s rue o f ^ _ p Home, given b.v the Arab Hurea i i?i honour o accompanied by the Residency 'Mrst Assistant ceived by the' Sultan. It was julie a frlmndl afternoon Shaikh Ahmad and his suit® ware taken to trie as ar. ^^ University by a 4,ohaaaedan gentleman arranged for^by- r. , And rson a t we could not accompany thea there. November j&gt;ta, * ff . ' ,„ a t to the Tuseua in the forenoon and around the baaaarn la - ths’’ afternoon. Noveab.r 97th,w left Cairo for 3u-&gt;z g/gfg, 0 ?', Ohio. A3 ho-»ever th'« ship lid not arrive in tlau. h« i to In hotel s that nl jht. Next 'morning *« •mbarked. . ' • Ul th&lt; «J up the Persian Gulf the weather ^as &lt;; , jin very bad. We reached ?ao bar at noon on Decoaoer - th. &amp; y- up to ni£jht ad watted there severai-noura lor yv _ hh.reh’s 'acht which we saw on our ray up. It arrived ah-&gt;u. • - r Sli 5 0 ;„Sj*tS Sh.iK. «»■-;&gt;. ay' 1 .'' :: to Aiwah where the 'Lewis Pell} *«• raitln ; Vv 4 -/q i t • ^ iittl® b®for® sunset thut v®riin w ju^ait a li ^Lent)i r • - our ships w«r® ala ^ T&gt;fiHf fnf - a hu,e crowd,esuvtated at ov-r - ,:^; palace. The Shaikh's, battery boora^gout Uv« iUu&amp; Ahaad as his ship He '(Shaikh Baltia);«i\t te ashore to pay hia an arrival visit. ...u&gt; n ^ 1 Vhi AA - . ' 1 ^ shaikh Salim was,! 1 ide : t HoiL o' Shaikh' Ahaad. This -will fom the bu‘ ojeot of 033aiml0aU ° n *&amp;» 1 kh AhLd is very popugr in go. : u in . wwi ,, « irr^^’-.ion I mm very gl^d ^nu.irmi ^lim -uib no g - J0 ' B 1 ’ tv* 'trio has done him a ver y deal of g.iod ‘ uf^icUnt attention in tHe future 1 hav, no -^e nil have- a rSm^ly good i riena j g. hli o f his •1 ve n a n o pi ion* and i f h.im doubt when his, time com® 3SSffi!iEHS!Si!5!!SS!!®55®SI!fflfflfflBBS!!iB!lEffi^iWP!HI^RBi r /6 za Kir-JAIT MISSION. The Khw&gt;it&lt; fission wxll p^y their xio.a^ge to -one Kiug .-t 12 noon on Thur.cUy 30th October. They will consist of - (1) . Ahnwei ion J^oir ion Saoah. (2) • Aiina-n ion Abel a 1 Jalil. (3) • Jasi-*i &gt;1 y^diio • with suite of one. On being inorociuoecl to His Majesty's presente the three ^ent ioned i.bove will be presented by onptnln D.V. iviaoCollun, politioal Agent, Kuwait. The T &gt;ring will then weloone the^o to Hngl’ond -nu as.c .iiter she health of His HAoellenoy KhairCh Kalin ion Subah,Ruler of Kuw-iit. Kh.aij.th Ah a ad ion Jj.bir will then express the appreciation of the Mission of the gre it honour conferred on then oy their reception, will offer one cordi al oongr rtulrtions ox nis nncle Shai*-sh Sal in, the Ruler of Kuwait, ana of all his subjects on the victorious teruinxtion of the great war, will then ash for a oonti.iucnoe of His Md.jeit.y'a ..inaness a.-ia p.-oneotion, .M will G aea present the gold sword mu digger. Tae time of t..e sword ueloaged to a forcer Saltan of Persia, aoth weapons belonged to the great Shaikh jlubara... He will explain that ais personal gift of an \ra’o stallion to His -fejesty is now on its wry to England. It is suggested that in reply the King should the Mission to u onvey to Hhai.th Sail a his than.« for the presents, then tharv nhai.di Aha.4 for the .Arab horse and st .be His sincere pleasure in we-souing this distinguished MiBsion. His Majesty will say He is well &gt;«are of the long friendship between His government and Kuwait ana trusts this will s-'ow ever stronger and more intim.te. It lithe King's re .ret that the late ‘‘jhai.th Sir Mubarax al Sabah aid not survive to see the final tridsPh of his polity. Tde King might then tnarmc them for tne mind expression of tne sentiments of the present Huler and assure tnethat in any uifiisulties that any arise in the future they will always be able to rely on the he -rty cooperation and .ssm, tance of His Majesty ts OovemmentiFIDENTIAL, rolitliial Agency, Kuwait Dated 16th January, 1920- The Civil Co oiaie lioner, Baghdad. xiencran duiii . Dr. Mylrei has ve^y kindly let ce have &amp; copy of e an a^t^oie, enticlea “Shaiich Ah^d goes to England', written oy him for public -tion in “Neglected Arabia' and probably “The Tines'. As I consider it a very interesting account, I an, with hie permission, sending yon a copy out it is not, of course, to be used for publioau. on. r Captain, political Agent, Kuwait. opy with copy of Article to the Depucy x 3 olitica 1 r^ec^dent x d ushire.miuiiiu— uuiuiiiun ShaiiSh Aiiaect goer to i,oacton by Dr. c.Stanley O.Mylrea. Kuwait .Persian dulf Soae time ago an article appeared in ' Hegleoted Arabia ^ entitled ** The HajJ '. a?lie central figure in that article wae the heir to the Kuweit tnrone, SheiAh Ahmed bin Jabr t who in the summer of 1918 showed his devotion as one of the leading men of this side of Arab la, by visiting the Holy City of Mecca, in Mecca t nowever,he not only o&amp;n© into contact with the past, but also with the very recent precent, in the person of Hussein, King of Hejaa, the most powerful man in Arabia to-day, and whose son, the ]5mir Feisul, was a signatory to the Treaty of Versailles, besides being a fairly familiar figure in London. Hussein's ,cnowledge of the world mist have made no little impression on our simple-ainded ,ibar-&amp;t~ho.ae Arab. In any case it was Ahmed's preparation for a second journey, which was to oe political and not a religious pil grimage, for in the early summer of 1919 he received an invitation to visit King George V ana to enjoy for a few wee^s the ho vitality of the British Isles. October 1919 found ^ Aimed residing in London. It is m bad time of the year for an Oriental to see London for the first time. The days are short,it rains three days out of four, and those thicA,pea-soup fogs for which London is famous in the winter, are apt to descend with unwelcome frequency. The sun is scarcely ever seen and it is probable that SheiAh Ahmed and his suite were never able to see the horizon at sunset, in order to set their watches. As everyone the Arab's day begin - at sunset,when it is t^el^e o'oIooa. .Ahmed thought the English houses were lovely insiue, but outside ** they are so blaOA and gloomy • Anyone picturing a large London house on a wet,foggy day, will agree with him. He was lauoh impressed with tlx© fact that no mattei how much it rained, the streets were never really dirty. H Their roads are iron * he declares. He never went out stereo at - He probably ap.-reolete* now wb*t the white people(zz&amp;f people wenti tarougH during tne xir.,t year or so that they settled rn Kulw eit. Wien asiced wliy ne did not a'fi.eot TSuropean dress and thus avoid the c onspicuoucnesa of his Arab oor-tume.he replied, H If I had worn ]5nglish clotiies,people would have caiten it for granted that I spo.te Siglisii, and I should have h^d the huailia.ting experience of explaining every little while that I was an Arab, and did not Know English *. Selfridge * a,that huge Anglo-Ameriran department store in Oxford Street, was popular haunt of Ahmed*s, and he was mujh amused by the eales-girls to whom he refers as ^ Maaa is * all being demurely dressed in blaoic. ** You cant just go in ana ouy a thing H he eiiplains ^ for they firat write uown your pur oh ae on a slip of paper and then you nave to wait while the paper and your aoney, together wi&amp;h you purchase, are sent away some where or other. Presently, when you have teoome int^resteu in something else* b»o&amp; oomes your purchase neatly wrapped up. &amp; n d at the same time the receipted bill and your change a?e handed to you. fhen there was the gunsmith’s. He wa4 shown a weapon he particularly admired, and promptly wished to ouy « 1 of the ame pattern, but was told that owing to the late i— was still a great shortage of these things and ti.ey could *, let him have the one. Biis astonished him. Altogether the young 'heiKh spent some seven hundred pounds aliopplng in Lonaon, in addition to another five hundred which he alterwa.ds syent in the same way in Cairo. The unaerground railways were a source of real wonder, especially the sueriuoued tunnels under the Ihamea. * One tunnel on toy of another - he tells his admiring audience. r*rt of toe time toat he w&gt;a in London,lived at - ;2t.e Carlton * and toat splendid hotel was a revelation to him. • He uic. not din, in public, however, out in his own apart meat a.. As I id Oefore, he does not liAe to be stared at. From ,toe ^7to o. Ootooer on, Pheiich Ahmed and his suite were under toe per oare ai and guidance of Captain D.v. iiocollum, our ^re ei Kuweit political Agent, and it was a happy coincidence Cap-ain MOCoilum should have been on leave during Ahmed in England. They were old ;rlends and Capo? in o ;olluW. ■ ! hia laaguage and tala aeide all the differenje. 3heiith Atitaed wiB of oourae UiKen to sea tae prinoipal sights of London, including areenwioh Otserv-tory.We^ tains ter Abb ay and She Houses of Parliament, which latter were fortunately in session, ana the visitor was able to observe how the Mother of all parliaments does its worm, including the taming of a vote on soae measure before the house. He was also driven out to Haaptoc Court, that ancient palaoe built by Cardinal v:olsey and pre entec by him to Henry VIII. Of oourse he went to ti.e Coologioal (Jirdens, fend it must have tiomled his Arab heart to see darnels on view as curiosities. Ordinary theatres he did not o re for, but a i erformanoe at Uaamelyne &amp; cooic's Theatre of Mysteries, where they olal/a to be sole to eiiue.1 if not surpass, all tue traditional marvels of Indian magic, left him profoundly and perhaps somewhat unpleasantly stirred. He admits that he has not tee faintest idea now the tricics and illusions ware done, but after all, who has ? Ahmed tooic a decided fancy to ' movies - and patronised one of the pioture-palaoes almost every night. The great and central oooasion of the visit o*me on October 30th when escorted by Captain iJOuOllu»,SheliSh Ahmed and his suite were presented to the King at Buoitingham palace. The audienoe lasted 17 minutes and Ahmed oongr .tulated tee King on the -iuooessful termination of tlie most dev .stasing war in hif cory, at the s.&gt;me tiue tea ruing him for his Iwsp^u lity and pre.:anting him with a gold mounted Arab dagger ana also s very fine old gold-mounted sword, which had once belonged mo a Shah of Persia. There was also a gift of an Arab stallion, but toil for obvious reasons was not personally tendered in the audieno* ohamber. The King, who was in undress naval uniform, welcomed Ahmed very Kindly, especially as he was a grandson of tee gre: t gubareic, assured aim that he «M ready to go thoroughly into any question that Ahmed might oare to raise with reference to Kuweit and ended up by giving him a photograph of himself duly autographed and grimed in solid silver. On tee border of tee frame were the royal monogram and orown in enamel. Captain MoJollua aoted throughout, as interpreter. gefore they left London, Ahmed was able to meet tee teal r r ^ ,-5-1 ^ ..4 1.— - -2 ^ &lt; drive to the railway station, M tii® roads lined with the finest troops in the world, and the polioeaen in perfect control of the orowds H . reception at the railway station, where in honour of tne Sh&amp;h, the floor was carpeted and. the walls were hung with flags, while paisas and floral decorations transformed the ugly tarnisned into a veritable garden, n&amp;de a soenfc no detail of which was lost on the yong mn froa Ar bia. He tells che story with extraordinay accuracy, considering that he was seeing every tiling througn the eyes of the unknowing foreigner. On ifoveaber 3rd the party went to Glasgow # where on the 6tlithey were entertained to luncheon by the Lord Provost, Alderaen and friends. Later they inspected the University and tiie Art galleries. The following diy they saw the Forth Bridge, that marvellous cantilever structure, with its total length of 5330 and its two main spans of 1710 feet each. One of the party took notes of the particulars of the bxidge. The ne-^t wonder was a submarine* It was a long motor drive from the Forth Bridge to the submarine base and wxien they arrived,it was past sunset, our Arub friends,with one exception, had only one idea in their heads at that time, and th t was, tne sunset prayer. So no sooner had they boarded the submarine than the oommnnding officer was begged to find them a corner in the cramped accom modation of the submarine, where they light turn their faces Heconwards and testify that there is no god but Allah and Mohammed is His Prophet. The one exception,However, and he w ? the same gentle aen wno bed been so busy at the Forth Bridge, was too Aeen on trie u&amp;fcter in hem, to let the demands of religion interfere, j^ote—boo^c in hand he went tne rounds, demanding Information down to the ainutesfc detail, and insuAbriously writing everything down. The w-xr xs o* s*e wo^ld have left the submrine with blame pages as far as that vessel’s particulars were concerned. Sheiuh Ahmed had his own troubles examining the submarine - he is a Dig can, and well ! submarines are not oailt for big men. He n^d to w&amp;lk. sideways joat of use tf.e. and so-« O-C tne mnaoles &amp;ui toed co be left unpenetrated.MWU—MMli ^Jll 5 •Jhe da^y before they sailed, the partly were shown so ae of the dlaftgow shipbuilding yards and also visited the aerodrome at Renfrew, where they saw aeroplanes oy the soore. All of the jparty except the Kheiich himself, made a flight, but for some reason or other, Ahmed got ' cold feet ' and consented himself with merely puttifig on flying *cit, entering one of tiie planes, ,nd being photographed in situ. On November dth the party smiled from (Hasgow for home. ’Bie weather was rougli and as Aimed is a ^oor sailor, he got little fun out of this part of the show. In fact ax ere warn hardly a oalm day between llaegow and Kuweit, On Novemoer 31st Alex vndria was reaoned and toe mission was duly met oy represen tatives of the Government who showed the visitors what there is to see in that city. ' Cairo was next visited and there they were reoeived by Lord Allenby, who, liKe the King,presented SheiKii Ahmed with a signed photograph, fhe party lodged at the famous Shepheard’s Hotel. Ixoursions in Cairo included the puramids and the Sphinx, which curiously enough,did not impress the visi tors, but the museum with its collection of mammies of age-long departed Eg/^ti ;&lt;ns could not but make the Ar*b ^ top and think. t d.nd in the world. Tlie aosque of Mohoaaed All and the Cit cel were visited and of oourse El Athar University. There was a special audience with the Sultan of Egypt besides a reception given in Ahmed’s Honour by the Arao Bureau. On November 27th everyone left for Sue* where the mission was to rejoin its ship. £»% *$• •hip was late and our Arab December 15th when the little launch.which had aet Sheikh Ahmed at the Jv ra bar, entered Kuweit harbour, to the salute of five gins from Sheikh Salim’s battery, The town was aecorated &amp;S was also the launch, and the be^ch wa * crowded. There is no doubt of Ahmed’s popul rity, his weloome after an absence of some conthe wss a sure test. Without quection his tr vels have taught him much, and it is to be hoped thaw what he had lammed may make him one more influe ace foi good in this part of the world. He now knows a little English for an Arab grave is one of the least permanent things of its rriendt; had one aore nitfss in an hotel. It w e n .t untiland it r&lt;|a ^iiie to be seen whether he i sufrioiently energetic to learn so ae acre, and ufficimtly progressive insist that his yohg sons shall learn English too, perhaps the photograph of deorge V as it hangs in his house, its silver i'rsuae steadily tarnishing, and with the du t settling on it .ior evernore, will be to him whit Kipling’s ^ oe, i&amp;&gt; to us H Lest we forget *.2 2 3 Telegram - Code Prom Civil Commissioner, Baghdad To India Office, London No. 15717 Dated 30th December 1919 Shaikh Ahmad of Koweit asks me to express his gratitude to the officers of the India office in general and to Sir James Dunlop Smith in particular for the arrangements made for his comfort whilst in London. He has expressed himself most gratified with this treatment, and I consider that his tour is likely to have good political effect. Civil Commissioner, Baghdad, Office of the Civil Commissioner, Baghdad, the 31st December 1919. *'P. A. KOffBIT. D.P.R. BUSHIRE # IX jI Ccfpy forwarded for information. \V ,•(*&gt; ■' '{X Lieut-Col., I.A., Acting Civil Commissioner in Mesopotamia,BBBHBBOBBBSHMBHHHHHHBKBBHHinBHIBHHSfflISIflIISfflIlfiBRBnBSSSBSfflKJSBffl INDIA OFFICE LIBRARY MICROFiLM 'j</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0003ad_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/5/18</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0003ad</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/5/18</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File VIII/3. Pedigree, Private affairs, notes, etc on the As-Subah family.'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1904/1922</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-07-21T22:02:24</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">fre</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (228 folios)</extent><extent>The papers appear to be arranged randomly within the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1 and terminates at the inside back cover with 230; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located at the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 4-227; these numbers are also written in pencil but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains correspondence in the form of letters, notes, pedigrees, news extracts and telegrams. The correspondence is mainly related to the ruling family in Kuwait. Reports were sent between the Political Agency, Kuwait and the Political Residency, Bushire regarding the following: political and social news in Kuwait; events concerning the al-Subah family (death, marriage or illness); news of Shaikh Mubarak’s coalition with Shaikh Khaz‘al against a number of tribes in the region; and reports on incidents taking place at Mohammerah, as well as news of the status of a number of Islands, such as Warba, which were claimed by the Shaikh of Kuwait.The file contains extracts from the Bahrain and Kuwait News, Residency reports about Shaikh Mubarak’s dispute with his pearl towashes (pearlers or pearl merchants), and an article (folios 219-224) on Shaikh Ahmad’s visit to London in 1919. It also contains a number of pedigrees of the al-Subah family.The file also includes correspondence related to the number of gun salutes due to chiefs in the Persian Gulf.The main correspondence is between the Political Agency, Kuwait, the Political Residency in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, the Secretary to the Government of India, Foreign Department, and the British Consul at Mohammerah.Due to the random arrangement of the papers in the file, the earliest paper (dated Nov 1904) is found at f 144, and the latest (dated Oct 1922) is found at f 135.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><name type="personal"><namePart>Ibrahim bin Madhaf</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="personal"><namePart>Hilal al-Matairi</namePart></name></subject><subject><geographic>Jazīrat Warbah</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Shat-el-Arab</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Political coalitions</topic></subject><subject><name type="personal"><namePart>Shaikh Hakim of Kuwait Mubārak bin Ṣabāḥ Āl Ṣabāḥ</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="personal"><namePart>Shaikh Emir of Mohammerah Khaz'al bin Jābir bin Mirdāw al-Ka'bī</namePart></name></subject><name type="personal"><namePart>Shaikh Hakim of Kuwait Aḥmad al-Jābir Āl Ṣabāḥ</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Bubiyan Island</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Mohammerah</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Pearl industry and trade</topic></subject><subject><topic>Visits</topic></subject><subject><topic>News flow</topic></subject><subject><topic>Sailors</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0003ad#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>