<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x00003c_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-18T00:48:33.649Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">No.1272-7/12 ■■ ——w Jolitical Agency, Bahrain. 4th July | 1940. The Director of Customs and Port Officer, ?ct!raln. Hemorandum * Reference your wemoranciuri tto.! , x./ FC/4224 dated the 30th June 1940, regarding'Ha ft 1 and Vereeds 1 • 2. This office has no information on the subjects for Political Agent, Bahrain.No PA/FC/^.).'H^&gt;^. . . To:- H.B.M's Political Agent, BAHRAIN: MEMORANDUM:- THE CUSTOMHOUSE: BAHRAIN: 28th October, 1940., 26th Ramadhan, 1359., /a I enclose herewith for favour of your perusal and return a petition in original, submitted to-day by a number of leading local merhhalits. If it is thought desirable, perhaps this may please be submitted to The Hon'ble the Resident, as a matter of information. Enc los ^ f DIRECTOR OF CUSTOMS, and PORT OFFICER. BAHRAIN:No.2063-7/12 The Political Agent, Bahrain, Presents his compliments to:— The Director of Customs &amp; Port Officer, Bahrain. return in original and has the honour to the undermentioned document ( / ) I hr agency, BAHRAIN, P ersian G ulf. Dated 30th October^ lfl40. J^HO - Reference to previous correspondence: His Memorandum No.PA/FC/4/439 dated 28th October, 1940• Description dj Enclosure. Name and Date. ! Subject. Petition dated 28th October,I Extension of Transhipment Period 1940, from certain Bahrain merchants to the Director of Customs &amp; Port Officer, Bahrain.Political ^gent, Kuwait. Political Agent, Bahrain, Dated and received the loth November, 1344. II^DIATS. Please see in censorship telegrams from Kuwait of today's date from .(a.) j'ahad Sulaiman Tukheim to Abdul Aziz S al Bassam (b) //haya 1 to Sulaiman Hamad al Bassam (c) Mohamed as - Sayar to as - Sayar care of Hanidan - I/dfia' all addressees in Bahrain. • ■ • , . Grateful to know (a) if Bahrain Gusto is are permitted to e idorse manifests 'Kuwait in transit' without disclosing ultimate destination of carjoes; and (b) whether export of piecegoods from Bahrain for sale is permitted. H.I.I. - POLITICAL - /J. ' It oPrinted in England. Sept. 1942. (4*100. pads. J CABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED. (INCORPORATED IN ENOLANO.) OF '^5 The first line of this Telegram contains the following particulars in the order named;— Prefix Letters and Number of Message- Office of Origin, Number of Words, Date, Time handed in and Official instructions—if any. Clerk's Time Circuit. Name. Received. r-, J 0 C *A u /*r &amp;d r \ O \S-y I MARK YOUR REPLY s P2a Jm/ ie uat. ANY ENQUIRY RESPECTING THIS TELEGRAM SHOULD BE ACCOMPANIED BY THIS FORM AND MAY BE MADE AT ANY OF THE COMPANY'S OFFICES.Printed in England. Sept. 194Z (4,100. pads. I CABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED. (incorporated in enolano.) The first line of this Telegram contains the following particulars in the order named:— v^ rerix Letters and Number of Message^ Office of Origin, Number of Words, Date, Time handed in and official instructions—if any. Clerk's Time Circuit. Name. Received. 1 / ' . cv&lt;, 7* l _c, /k! s r j/ u M ixz~ ^ r n ik \ —' /V ^ &lt;xj6L . I0~o i/i MARK YOUR fl r *Via JmAetuaC i ANY ENQUIRY RESPECTING THIS TELEGRAM SHOULD BE ACCOMPANIED BY THIS FORM AND MAY BE MADE AT ANY OF THE COMPANY'S OFFICES.'X Telegram No. 826 dated 16.11.44 from the Political Agent, Kuwait. 6 ' P.A. Copies of telegrams mentioned at (a) and (b) are submitted with English translation. Res telegram at (c)* From Cable and Wireless 1 record, it appears that no such telegram was received here from Kuwait,on 16,11,44. There were, however, two telegrams from two different persons; one from Fahad al Rijaib and another from A1 Sahali, 196.1,441 \ No. 214-22. &gt;i (17/6/5) Dear Agency, RITISH C011SULATS-GI2I X T3RAL BASRA. 3th December 19U4« Bahrain Receipt ^ (j At O . Date. We enclose Bahrein Customs Clearance No,79/63 of October 10th, 19^4, relative to a cargo of Kerosene carried by the T.V. 'San Vito' from Bahrein, together with a complimentary slip from the British Consulate, Suez, for favour of transmission to the Director of Customs and Port Officer, Bahrein. 2. Although this clearance was not endorsed according to requirements, it appears that the I'erosene load in question was discharged at Suez. 3, 7e are sending a copy,of the present to His Britannic Majesty's Consulate, Suez, for information. Yours ever, Consulate-General. The Political Agency, Bahrein. AG/GNo. 58^ _7/l2. Political Agency, Bahrain, Tae 18th December, 1944. The undementioned papers are forv/arded to the Director o.f Customs, Bahrain. for Political Agent, Bahrain. cA^ Enclosure. 1. Bahrain Customs clearance No.79/63 dated 10th October, 1944. 2. Complimentary slip from the British Consulate, Suez..■'W. No.1998-7/12. To Political Agency, Bahrain, The 24th June, 1946. Messrs* Haridas Janimal &amp; Sons, Bahrain. ated t the 17th Memorandum . Reference your letter d June, 1946. 2. Please inform me of the cost per ton of this sugar c.i.f., Bahrain. 4. for Political Agent, Bahrain.\ No.2162-7/12. To Political Agency, Bahrain, The 7th July, 1946. Messrs. Haridas Janimal &lt;5k Sons, Bahrain. Heqorandi^. T s1- Reference yov^ letteis dated the 17th June, 1946 and 26th June, 1946. 2. I regret that I am unable to agree to your proposal. C. i^. for Political Agent, Bahrain.$'3 No.PA/c/.^f THE CUSTOMHOUSE BAHRAIN. 1st October, 1946. K. B. M's Political Agent, Bahrain. / Memorandum ;^ Reference attached, it-has been brought to my notice that large scale transactions have been taking place between Ships crew and labourers working vessels at Sitra- an example quoted being one watch supplied by labourer, for 6 cartoons of chewing gum, from ship crew. At present labourers and stores proceed to and from ships by lorries and avoi^d Customs inspections, and a considerable number of articles from the bazar, eggs, etc, have been exported to vessels by Mohamed Tahdr al Shariff, without permission from this department. b I ho DIRECTOR OP CUSTOMS AND PORT OFFICER, BAHRAIN. I c.c. The Adviser, The Government of Bahrain.Ko.Cue A-lsc/ . THE CUETCB(iH0U5S BAHRAIN 1st October f 19^6. Messrs ioh &amp;med T»h ®r si liu -rllT, Labour Contractors Bahrain* Paar lirs, Will you please note 9 that with immediate effect, all labour working Ships at Sitra anchorage 9 whether at Saa f or alongside, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Ltd 9 wharf, must proceed to and from the vessels 9 by Lsunch from Maharraq* Time of departure and returns must be given to this office 9 so that the usual Customs inspection may be carried out* Similarly all food for labourers must be sent by Launch 9 also any stores which have been requested by a particular vessel, and sanctioned by the Food Controller* Any contravention of this will render the offender liable to prosecution* /L - DIRECTOR QT CU&amp;T0K6 AKP PORT OFFICER 9 BAHRAIN. c«o* Messrs Gray ^ackenxie &amp; Co, Ltd* c*o* Messrs Jasim k Ali Kanoo. c.c. H* B* E's Political Agent, The Adviser the Govt, of Bahrain, The C*L*R* Bapco. in reference to the writers conversation with Mr* F* W* Bird, security warden*fv Dgted. ?4ih Octofer 1946. To The H.b.M'S.Political A^ent, Bahreio , Dear Sir, I hereunder be^ to iDforir your Iclrd honour that there is a n»i sipanagement ^olnK on frorr- a lon^ tiire in The Bahrein Government Custoirs Departirent and irerchants are ^ettin^ always disappointed time to tiire. As regards ftefunds and Certificates are concerned I have to state that irercants applying for the Clainrs, are siirply passing through The Director of Custoirs on otder to prepare cl aiirs for paywents: but very sorry to tell you that Years &amp; Years passing away, there is no reply given to their nor the claitts ironey is refunded tc the applicant, Flease the present ii'anageirent does not care to solve any exairple of a roerchant grievance, which is their first duty,bring a public office. In the last 1 request your kind honour to iralce privat -e inquiry in the said matter and try your best to do the needful in the same. I am grately thankful, for your &lt;lnd favour. YOUrtS FAITHFULLY| A Public Wan of Bahrein. Bahrain Receipt hBabrairi i.L Dated. November, 22nd 194 6, -V 4 A 'ro The H. B.M'S. Political Agent, Bahrein, Dear Sir, We are grately surprised tosee the affairs moving in the Bahrein Government Customs Department, '.Veil we wish to inform you ' after our long long sleep' by the message that there is no attention paid to Merc han t Work by the management in this office, which should be their chief object. As regards R efunds are concerned we have to request you that we are not able to get our refunds from a long time, when Mr. Purshotum was an appraiser and hence our claims become very old nor any re-oly has been given to us,Now we see &amp; hear some fresh ones issued very soon ,therefore it is clearly seen that our correspondan -ce have no value and are put in the Waste Pa^er Basket.So it isall in vain to make any more correspondance with them though our true right. . Further we have to request that the Management m the Customs Department is so poor that one cannot clear his goods very easily. But with a longer delay of about 5-6 days, to wait &amp;spoil the whole day in the Customs Office, wea are hardly able to get the delivery of the goods and go home safely. About the present position of the Import Yard Shed in the bazaar,we have to say that many a times going for work, we meet no Clerk but Peons and have to wait and wait for him. In the last we put this with a hope that our humble two lines will draw your kind attention to solve our defficulties and do your best to help us. For this act of kindness, we remain always grateful to you. YOURS FAITHFULLY. Leading Merchants of Bahrein. Confidential. ®4 h o iarn receipt. ,&gt; No . -a/17 The Political Agent and His Majesty's Consul, Muscat, presents his compliments to The Political Ag«nt, BAHRAIN . S and has the honour to transmit to him the u ider nentioned document(s), for favour of nacessary acx.ion« Ka. *; i Receipt J/- 3 v y &gt; I i \|« .0 u/t \ , 'A .A' Political Agency and British Consulate, Muscat. Dated 4:th March Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. juettar Wo.CC^SGM.6ai/^ dated tm 31s't January 1^7 from Go-LLector of Customs,iLarachi^ 1947 Landing Certificata® t s ^■No. 1334 - 7/12. POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. The 17th April 1947. To The Collector of Customs, Karachi. Sir, With reference to your letter No. CC. EGl^/46, dated the 31st January 1947 to the address of the Political Agent, Muscat, I have the honour to inform you that the certificate in question was issued by Muhammad bin Ahmad bin Sulaiman, Shaikh of Bakha, who is the proper authority to issue such a certificate in respect of his territory. The \ certificate is returned herewith. I have the honour to be Sir, Your most obedient servant, r rtTt for POLITICAL AGKNT. BAH:AIN, b S KMSiL NO.4.50-9/17. From Major A.C. Stewart, O.B.E., Political Agent and H.B.M's Consul, Muscat. yv To The Collector of Customs, » Custom House, Karachi. Sir, I have the honour to refer to your letter No.C.C.EGM. 631/4.6, dated the 27th March, 1947, and to inform you that your letter No.C.C.£011.631/46, dated the 3l8t January, 1947 with its enclosure was forwarded to the Political Agent, Bahrain under my Printed Letter No.189-9dated the 4th March, 1947 as Bukha is in his jurisdiction. It is therefore suggested that you take up this case with the Political Agent, Bahrain. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant. * Pol Consul, ituscat. Copy to the Political Agent, Bahrain.H11 ROYAL AIR JDRCE STATION, BAHR3IN. 17 November 1948. Ref BAH/ 268/ORG. The Political Agent, — Bahrein. Dear Sir, It has 'been reported to Air Headquarters, Royal Air Force, Iraq, that certain crews and passengers, in transit through Bahrein, have been purchasing cigarettes locally and transporting same off the Island without Custom's clearance. I can deal adequately with the relatively small number of Service crews and passengers passing through this Station, but would appreciate any help you can offer with regard to civilians. Perhaps the Chief Customs Officer could be approached and his assistance solicited in this matter. Yours faithfully, (L.V. WALLACS)F/LT. OFFICER COMMANDING. R.A.F. UNIT dAHH^IN. c.c. Iraq - their 54/2/AT dated 25/10/48 refers, c.c. R.A.F. Shaibah.No.PA/C/.. L datk H.B.M 1 s Political Agent, Bahrain. Memorandum:- THE CUSTOMHOUSES BAHRAINJ '2nd November, 1948., I should be very grateful if it could be arranged through your good offices, to obtain for this Department, a complete and up-to-date Schedule of Import duties into the U.K. together with a list of scales of purchase tax. I am being continually asked these questions by residents here and would like to be in a position to reply favourably. Thanking you. DIRECTOR OFCUSTOMS AND PORT OFFICER, BAHRAIN.'''N . . .. By Registered Air Mail. V POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN. No.5381-7/12. The 8th December 1948. Dear Department, We shall be grateful if you could kindly arrange to supply to this Agency two copies of up-to-date schedule of imoort duties into the United Kingdom together with a list of scales of purchase tax by Air Mail. We are being continually asked questions on these matters, and have very little knowledge on the subject. Yours ever. Agency. The Export Promotion Department, Board of Trade, Thanes House North, Millbank, London, S .W.I.( M &amp; No.198-7/12 POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN, The 22nd January, 1949 To The Director of Customs, B A H R A I N MEMORANDUM V Reference your memorandum No.PA/C/3, dated the 22nd November, 1948, 2. I forward herewith one copy each of the following for your official use:- 1) Customs and Excise Tariff of the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland in operation on the 1st Aug.1948. 2) Notice No.78 of September 1948, by the Commissioners of Customs and Excise. NNR /■ ' tyr/'tj FOR POLITICAL AGENT, BAHRAIN\ - I I i |]\l D.0• Ho./^o &amp; ■ .f / Adviser ate, vV^ . April 35, 1949,. ^ Dear Lermi^ The Bahrain Grovernraent is tigjitening up the control on traffic between Bahrain and v ^atar. His Highness has issued a proclamation, of which a copy has been sent to you, which forbids Bahrain subjects to go to C^atar without the previous permission of the Government. In addition to this it is proposed to set up a customs post at your pier at Sitra. At present the Government has no control over traffic to and from this pier between Bahrain and Qatar. Goods which are shipped from here to Qatar are now being inspected at the Manama Customs House before they are conveyed to Sitra but this arrangement is not a satisfactory one. The Government will erect a small house outside the gate of your enclosure which will serve as a customs office and a customs officer will be on duty there during the day. He will undertake the customs forma lities which are now dealt with in Manama, examining persons and goods which enter and leave Bahrain. We have recently established a police post on the old Sitra pier, the detachment has a launch for sea patrolling. The customs post and the police post will work together as a combined unit. I hope that the new arrangement will be more satisfactory from both our point af view and yours than the present method of dealing with customs inspections. Yours sincerely. Cc K&amp;Mi , ): A[ L 2146/21/407 ] Foreign Office, 9th June, 1949. Revised Customs Memorandum for Consular Officers Sir, With reference to Foreign Office circular No. 34 of 29th April, 1949, I transmit to you herewith a copy of the revised Customs Memorandum No. 4/1 (May 1949), which summarises the British Customs rules and concessions relating to passengers' baggage and effects imported into the United Kingdom in force in May 1949. Additional copies of this memorandum cannot be supplied but, if necessary, you may reproduce a limited number for official use only, providing the text is strictly adhered to. I am. Sir, Your obedient Servant, ERNEST BEVIN. His Majesty's Superintending Consular Officers. ^^vtica jS\/ 69 4./ Memo* 4/1 PAS SMGIRS 1 BAG GAGE /JJD EPFSCTS (iiiy 1949) TF^- POLLOVOTG- SUi'£jiRY OB' BRITISH GUSTO].3 RULES AND CONCESSIONS RELATING TO PASSENGERS' BAGGAGE MD Ii 1 F3CTS Il/iPORTKD INTO THE UNITED KINGDOL. REPRESLiNTS THE POSITION AT THE DATE OP ISSUE OP THIS liHviCRANDmi. 1, Custo ms examination . The personal baggage and other belongings of all persons arriving in the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland, whether in transit or otherwise, are subject to Customs examination. The responsibility for opening, unpacking and repacking the packages rests with the passenger or his agent. Decl ara tion requi red. All articles obtained (l) outside the United Kingdom or (2) dviring the voyage, whether by purchase or otherwise, must be declared to the Customs Officer, whether they have been worn or used or not, aid however small the quantity, Failure to make a proper declaration may involve heavy penalties, including forfeiture of the goods. 3« Liability to dut y and Purcha se Tax . Practically all articles are liable to duty and may be liable to purchase Tax. In practice, passengers carrying only a small quantity of dutiable goods (including tobacco, spirits and perfumery) for their personal use ari allowed to retain it free of duty and tax. The limits on the qurntities of consumable goods passed free under this concession are as follows : - Por visitors pe rmanontly r esident outside Europe . Tobacco (including cigars and cigarettes) spirits (including liqueurs and cordials) Perfumed spirits and toilet waters containing spirit Wine in bottle up to 1 lb, up to 1 bottle (i, e, one-sixth of a gallon) up to ■§■ pint. up to 1 bottle (i, e, one-sixth of a gallon) For vi sitors from Eprftope and returning British residents . Tobacco (including cigars and cigarettes) Spirits (including liqueurs and cordials) Perfumed spirits and toilet waters containing spirit Wine in bottle up to ^ lb, up to 4- bottle (i, e, one-twelfth of a gallon) up to ^ pint. up to 1 bottle (i, e, one-sixth of a gallon) In the case of visitors from Europe and returning British residents, duty is charged on the whole quantity where it exceeds twice the specified limit. These concessions do not extend to dutiable articles in unaccompanied baggage or in registered baggage not examined simultaneously with the unregistered baggage. Us ed articles of personal effects which have been in the possession and use of the passenger for an appreciable period and are not intended for other persons or for sale, may also be admitted free of duty and Purchase Tax, ' ^Person a l effec ts' moans any portable articles imported in the baggage or on the person of a passenger which he might reasonably be expected to carry with him for his own regular and private use, (See also paragraph 6), All concessions are subject to the articles being duly declared and produced to the Customs Officer and to his being satisfied as to the facts,10. / 4-, prohibitod and rest rioted goods * The importation of certain goods, e.g. dangerous drugs, is prohibitod and no such prohibited article, howcvur anall the quantity, will be permitted to bo imported. Ivierchandiso, or any goods other than bona fide private effects, must not bo imported as passengers' baggage. Import licences are not required for passengers 1 effects provided that they are not being imported for sale and that the quantities arc reasonable, nor are they required for household affects imported on a bona fide change of residence. In the case of foodstuffs the concession is limited as followc :- (a) a person arriving from Eire* 7 lbs. in all# No one foodstuff to oxceed 2 lbs. (b) a person arriving from other countries; 50 lbs. in all. No one foodstuff to exceed 10 lbs# 5. Temporary importations . In the case of persons making only a temporary stay (i.e. up to six months) in the United Kingdom, personal effects which are not achniasible under paragraph 3 will bo achnittod free of duty and tax, subject to the Customs Officers being satisfied, that the articles will be re-exported. In some cases this will be secured by (i) scaling the goods and sending them forward under a carrior's bond to the port of exportation or (ii) the payment of a roturnable deposit to cover the duty and tax. 6. To ols of trade and professionol offecto . Portable tools of trade, occupation or omployment and articles of professional use which are in actual ownership and possession of the passenger at the time of importation and intended to bo used by him in the course of his occupation, employment or profession in future ore treated as 'personal of foots' (paragraph o) and will be acknitted free of duty and purchase Tax provided they are shown to have been in the possession and use of the passenger for on appreciable time. 7. Household effects . Furniture and other articlos of ordinary and domestic use (but not including such articles as wines, spirits and tobacco, or cinematograph film of the standard width of ly') which are iiaported on a bona fido transfer of residence to this country by the owner will be admitted free of duty and purchase Tax provided that the articles are shown to the satisfaction of tho Customs Officers to have been in the importer's possession and use abroad for a considerable period and are not intended to bo disposed of in this country. It is not possible for the Commissioners of Customs and Excise to say whether particular articles will qualify for free admission under this concession, unless information as to the date on which the articles were obtained and the period of possession and use by the importer abroad are available. 8. Motor vehicles . Except in the case of a motor vehicle imported tanporarily under the touring regulations, motor vehicles may ordinarily be Imported only on production of an import licence and payment of duty and Tax. yhere certain conditions are fulfilled and subject to the satisfaction of the Customs Examining Officer as to the facts, a motor vehicle owned by a person removing his residence to this country from abroad is admitted without licence and free of duty and Tax. The conditions are (i) there must be a bona fide transfer of residence; (ii) the vehicle must have been in the importer's private use and possession abroad for at least two years before importation; and (iii) the vehicle must be imported for continued private use by the importer and not for sale. This also applies to a pedal cycle, 9. British returned goods . Articles which on importation are proved to have been previously exported from this country after any proper duty has been paid and not refunded and which have undergone no process, alteration, addition or repair while abroad are admissible duty free, purchase Tax may sometimes be payable, however, e.g., in tho caso of goods which had been purchased tax free for export.v &gt; 10* Bv.pire f ^oods &gt; Articles which can be shown to hr'.vo been consigned froin, and grown, produced .or. riiwi^^pturq^/ih:'.-lthc British Bnpire arc- admissible free of Oust cms. -duty, .pr .a V -reducrdd- 'fates' of 'duty.The liability to Purchase Tcoc, 'however, is not affected, '• ' 11, An tique articles , Custotiis duty is not charged on goods (other than spirits or wines) which are proved to have been manufactured or produced more than one hundred years before the date of Importation, Articles which qualify for admission free of Customs duty under this provision qualify also for admission frue of Purchase Tax, 12, Q-iftsj including w--'ddinp; presents# There is no specific exemption from^ duty and Purchase Tax in respect of intended presents or of articles acquired by way of wedding presents or other'gifts, or in respect of articles fori) ing part of a trousseau. Duty and Tax (if any) are chargeable unless the articles are admissible free under one of the forogjing paragraphs,' 13, Li vestock , The importation of ga'rto.ts is prohibited. Dogs and cats brought from any country other than Sire'or-the Channel Islands, must not be landed except under a^l'icencc issued by the-Ministry of Agriculture and Fisheries C-nd in accordance with .the terms of tho licence. The importation of certain other animals is also subject to restrictions^ 14, Warning , If any articles admitted free of duty ano/or Purchase Tax under par..graphs 3, 5, 6, 7 or G above are sold or otherwise disposed of in this country, they will be liable to forfeiture-under Section 12 of the Finance Act, 1948, Secretaries' Office, • • '■ Custcms and Excise, • ■ : City Gate. House, i' Pinsbury Square, ' SiC, 2, May, 1949. ■ sec, 50813/47&lt;V) V Rifei^ce CPE (IB) 10987/49. Oversur.s Trade Kemoranduni I mportation of luotoi cars into the United Kinprd om ^ A number of enquiries have been received ab6ut the liability to Customs duty and purchase Tax and the import licensing requirements in respect of cars iiriported into the ^nited Kingdom, A memorandum by Qua tarns &amp; li .xcise is attached shov/ing the present position refarding; the importation of motor cars. Particular caution should be observed in answering any enquiries ana it should be emphasised that as tht regulations are liable to change at any time, no responsibility can be accepted for the information furnished. Further memoranda will be issued showing any changes 'which may occur. 20th June, 1949 Commercial Relations &amp; Exports Department, (industries Branch), Thames House (North), Killbank, London, S.Y. r . 1, Circulation; T,C»s,,1,T,C.s, C.D.O.s. Superintending Consular PI MPOP.TATION OP IvIOTQR G;.RG INTO THE UNITED KUTO M ^ • G-faneral U Motor—cars v/hether nev/ - or secondhand imported into the United Kingdom are normally subject to the production, at importation, cf 'a Board of Trade Inrport Licence (granted by the Import Licensing Department, 1 . , Regent Street, W # 1») and to payment of the appropriate Customs duty and purchase Tax, but there are the following exceptions to these requirements:- (a) Under the Road Vehicles (Temporary Importation) Regulations, 1938 (S.'v.- &amp; 0,193&lt;No, 826) a motor vehicle may be imported temporarily into the United Kinglom free of duty and Purchase Tax by a person ^ usually resideni: abroad who intends to make only a temporary stay in this country, i # e, a stay not exceeding twelve months* A person desiring so to import a motor vehicle temporarily may either - arrange with an accredited motoring association for the issue to him of an international touring document, i^e, camet or triptyque; or On arrival in the United Kingdom, submit to the Customs a declaration and claim for exemption in the approved form(Customs form C. 111) together with a deposit to cover the duty and tax v/hich would otherwise be payable; if this course is followed, the deposit is returned on re-exportation of the vehicle subject to fulfilment of the conditions printed on the form C.111. A motor vehicle admitted into the United Kingdom under the above Regulations is subject to the conditions that it shall not be exchanged nor lent, hired, sold or given away to any person in the United Kingdom and that it shall be exported by the importer when his temporary stay comes to an end. Any breach of these conditions would render the vehicle forfeit to the Crown, under Section 12 of the Finance Act, 194 -8. Full infonnation regarding the issue of international touring documents may be obtained from the Royal Automobile Club, Pall Mall, S.W.I#, or the Automobile Association, Fanum House, New Coventry Street, 1• (b) On a bona fide change of residence of the owner to the United Kingdom, moreover, a car which has been in the i iporter's private possession and use abroad for at least 2 years prior to importation may, as a concession, be admitted without payment of Customs duty and Purchase Tax. For this purpose the importer will be required to furnish a declaration as to the facts and also to give an undertaking to pay the appropriate Customs duty and Purchase Tax if the car is sold or otherwise disposed of within 2 years of the date of importation. Any breach of this undertaking would render the car liable to seizure under Section 12 of the Finance Act, 1948, The form of declaration and undertaking is provided at the time of importation by the Customs Officer, who will require to be satisfied as to the facts. It will also be necessary to advise the Officer of the British car registration number before the car is released, 2, Customs Duty (a) Cars of foreign or Empire origin . Cars are normally liable to duty at the rate of 335' P c - r cont t ad Valorem. If, however, a car is shown to the satisfaction of the Commissioners of Customs and Excise to have been consigned from and manufactured in the British Empire, it /wouldwould be admissible under fepcrial Preference at the reduced rate of 22 2/9 per cent, ad valorem. To substantiate a claim to Imperial Preference, a certificate of origin on Form E No, l20(Sale) furnished by the actual manufacturers overseas, should be produced. Cars of British origin , A car, whether Ajised or not, which is proved to the satisfaction of the Customs Examining Officers to have been previously exported from the United Kingdom in a fully assembled condition after any proper duty had been paid and not refunded and which has undergone no alteration, addition or repair (other than running repairs) whilst abroad would be re-admitted without payment of duty, purchase Tax , Motor cars, whether new or second-hand are liable on^ importation to Purchase Tax at the basic rate of 33350 of the duty- inclusive wholesale value or, alternatively, at the rate of 66 2/3^b of the duty-inelusive wholesale value, if the retail value in this country, including Import Duty and Purchase Tax at the basic rate, exceeds £1,260 at the time of importation. Admission free of tax is, however, normally allowed in the cases of a car which is proved to the satisfaction of the Customs Officer at the time of importation to have been, at some time, in private possession and use in this com try, provided that:- (1), it had not been obtained tax-free for temporary use in this country and subsequent exportation; (2) such use was other than when imported temporarily under touring documents; (3) at the time of importation it is in substantially the same state as it was in when exported, .) Also a car may normally be re-imported tax-free if it was exported, fully assembled, from the United Kingdom before 21st October, 1940, provided it is still in substantially the same state as at export* Value , The value on which import duty is chargeable is, briefly the price which the car would fetch on a sale in the open market at the time and place of importation, while the value on which Purchase Tax is chargeable is the price, inclusive of import duty, but exclusive of Purchase Tax, the car would fetch on a sale made by a person selling by wholesale in the open market, in the United Kingdom, to a retail trader* Accordingly, in determining acceptable values for duty and purchase tax purposes regard has to be paid to the general level of prices prevaj l^iig in the open market in the United Kingdom at the time of importation and it is not possible to state precisely what values would be regarded as acceptable for any particular car ih advance of its importation and examination by an Officer of this Department, Impo rt Licen ces , As already stated a licence is not required for cars imported under the arrangements set out in sub-paras 1 (a) and (b) above, A licence may be issued for the import of a car of British manufacture, provided that it is the personal property of the applicant and Mas originally purchased by him for use abroad. No definite period of ownership is prescribed, each case being considered on its merits; but. /unlessunless the circumstances are exceptional, the Board of Trade win requzrc to be satisfied that the car has'been used by the 'erIL concerned for at least six months SoendiWe If 0f for&lt;:i S n manufacture, particularly when the expenditure of hard currency may be involved, licences will not in ir ' vh? t XSSUed ' unless the car has been owned for at least 12 months Sri v-arr 3 ^ given that the car will not be resold' befor the ! nf ^ a Car ^ been P^^sed immediately haf bin La r ! r&lt; ; t0 this countr y or ^en the purchase has been made at a port of call en route to the United Kingdom. • f0 ^ : mport licences Should be made on Form ICM/CAR(which -y c obtajji^d from the Board of Trade) to the Board of Trade Import Licensing Departeent, (Machinery Licences Division), ' 1o9, Regent Street, London, W,1. J ' 27th May, 1949, /[ L 5968/21/407 ] CIRCULAR No. 76 @ Foreign Office, 25th November, 1949. Revised Customs Memorandum for Consular Officers Sir, . U (■ With reference to Foreign Office circular No. 44 of 9th June, 1949, I transmit to you herewith a copy of the revised Customs Memorandum No. 4/1 (October 1949), which summarises the British Customs rules and concessions relating to passengers' baggage and effects imported into the United Kingdom in force in October 1949. Additional copies of this memorandum cannot be supplied but, if necessary, you may reproduce a limited number for official use only, providing the text is strictly adhered to. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, ERNEST BEVIN. His Majesty's Superintending Consular Officers. 15789 37774—194./ Mcroot 4/l» PASSEMGERS* P AC^/.GE /J'Tp F^^TS (Oirboba' # lilST THE FOLLOWING SUMM/JIY OP BRITISH CUSTOMS RTJI^S AND OONCKSSOTS RELATING TO PASSENGERS' BAGGAGE iJ\D EFFECTS D /IPGld'ED INl'C THE UlIiriD KIlC-LOM R3£{REtiEi ;TS the position at the d ^ e op issue of this 1# Custo ms ex amination* The personal baggage and other belongings of all persons arrivirg in t-ie United Kingdom of Great Bribain and NcrVuern Ireland, vvhothor in w.-mffit or or/nenvise, are subject tc Customs exsmination. The rG3tjcvir;loiii'b:/ for opening, unpacking and repacking the packages resbs with the passc'iigor or his agent # 2. Dec larat i on required * All articles obtained (l) outride the United Kingdom or (2) during the voyage, whether by purchase or otherwise, must be declaimed to the Custcras Officer, whether they have ooen v/orn or used or not, and however small the quantity* Failure to make a pc-oper declaration may involve heavy penalties, including forfeiture of bho goods» 3« Liability to duty and Fur chas e Tar* Practically all articles are liable to duty and may 'be liable to i*u&gt;'o:i?,.se Tax* In practifjo, pansongers carrying on'jy a small quantity cf dutiable goods (including bobacco, spirits and perfumery) for their personal use are allowed to retain it free of duty and tax* The limits on the quantities of consumable goods passed free under this concession are as follows 1- For visitors permanently rcsidont outside Europe* Tobacco (including cigars and cigarettes) ^P to 1 lb* Spirits (including liqueurs and cordials) up to 1 bottle (i«e* one-sixth of a gallon) • Perfumed spirits and toilet waters containing spirit up to 2 pint- Wine in bottle up to 1 bottle (i*e« one-sixth of a gallon) • For visitors from Europe and returning Brit i sh residents* Tobacco (including cigars and cigarettes) up to -J- lb* Spirits (including liqueurs and cordials) up to ^ bottle (i *e» o no-twelfth of a ^ gallon) * Perfumed spirits and toilet waters containing spirit 13?to J pint* Wine in bottle up to 1 bottle (i*e» one-sixth of a gallon) • In the case of visitors from Europe and return;}ng British residents, duty is charged on the whole quantity where it exeecr.s twi-jc the specified limit* These concessions do not extend to du^i^b] e arb'«c'l ^ in unpcr-ompanled baggage or in registered ba^ago nc-t ej:aiirlncd n? iturb rj '.cou J/ with thn i-rrc j:!. i!:crod l^rgage* They do not ccvor pev.'jor-.s moilr.'g ir-c ^'laoes ?u ; :sid^ the United Kingdom and are modified in thoir application bo the liibh Land BounJax:/* •, Us^cd articles cf pav^onal effects whi^h have been in the possession and use of the ppssengcr for an appreciable period and ale r&gt;ot intended for other persons or for sale, may also bo adx 1 ttecl free of dr.ty rjr»d Purchase Tax* ''Persona l e ffec ts' means any portable article:', imported in t);..e b^ggo^c or on tno person of a passenger which he mr'.ght reasonably be cx-pected to carry with him for Ids own regular and private use* (See also paragraph 6) * All concessions are subject to the articles being duly declared and produced to the Customs Officer and to his being satisfied as to the facts*10*/ P roliilpited and restricted ^ood3» The importation of certain goods, e*g. dangerous drugs, is proliibited and no such prohibited article, however small tiie quantity, will be permitted to be imported* Merchandise, or any goods other than bona fide private effects, must not be imported as passengers' baggage. Import licences are not required for passengers' effects provided that they are not being imported for sale and that the quantities are reasonable, nor are they required for household effects imported on a bona fide change of residence* In the case of foodstuffs the concession is limited as follows i— (a) a person arriving from Eire: 7 lbs. in all. No one foodstuff to exceed 2 lbs. (b) a person arriving from other countries; 150 lbs. in all. No one foodstuff to exceed 10 lbs. ^ orrpo rrry inroor ta t ion s. In the case of persons making only a temporary stay (i.e. up to six months) in the United Kingdom, personal effects which are not admissible under paragraph 3 will be admitted free of duty and tax, subject to the Customs Officers being satisfied, that the articles will be re-exported. In some cases this will be secured by (i) sealing the goods and sending them forward under a carrier's bond to the port of exportation or \ii) payment of a returnable deposit to cover the duty and tax# ^ t Tools of trade ajid profess ional ef fects. Portable tools of trade, occupation or employment and articles of pro!e r :sional use which are in actual ovn^rship and possession of the passenger at the time of importation and intended to do used by him in the course of his occupation, employment or profession in future are treated as 'personal effects' (paragraph 3} and will be admitted free of duty and Purchase Tax provided they are shown to have been in the possession and use oi the passenger for an appreciable time. Hou sehoId e ff-cts. Furniture and oth(jr articles of ordinary and domestic use (but not including such articles as wines, si'irits and tobacco,, or cinemabograph film of the standard width of 1^') which are imported on a bona iicio transtor of residence to this country by the owner will be admitted free of duty and Purchase Tax provided tliat the articles are shown to the satisfaction o - l the Customs Officers to have been in the importer's possession and use abroad ior^a consiaerable period and are not intended to be disposed of in tliis country. It is not possible lor tne Commissi.oners of Customs and Excise to say whether particular articles will qualify for free admission under this concession, unless iijiorm at ion as to the date on which the articles were obtained and the period ox possession and use by the importer abroad are available. j-ip/' or vehinlus. Except where imported temporarily under the touring regulations, motor ears may ordinarily be imported only on production of an import l±ce/ice and payment of duty and Tax. Where certain conditions are fulfilled and sulgcct to the satisfaction of the Customs Examining Officer as to the facts, a moter car owned by a person removing his residence to this country from abroad is admitted witliout licence and free of duty and Tax. The conditions are (i.) there must be a bona fide transfer of residence; (ii) the car must have been in the importer's private use and possession abroad for at least two years before importation; and (iii) the ear must be imported for continued private use by the importer and not for sale* The same rales apply to motor cycles except that where saca vehicles do not qualify for admission free of duty and tax under conditions ( - L /&gt; s : ^nd (iii) above they are nevertheless admitted without licence if imported irotn^ aertam countries* Particulars of the countries concerned may be obtained on enquiry at the address given below* ^rit'ish returned goods * Articles which on importation are proved to have been previously exported from this country after any proper duty has been paid and nct^rc-unded and which have undergone no process, alteration, addition or repair while aero ad arc admissible duty free. Purchase Tax may sometimes be payable, however, e«g., in the case of goods which had been purchased tax free for export*10* Empire /^oods* Articles which can 'be shovm to Viave 'been consigned from, and grown, produced or manufactured in the British Empire are admissible free of Customs duty or at reduced rates of duty# The liability to Purchase Tax, howover, is not affected. 11 • Antique articles* Customs duty is not charged on goods (other than spirits or wines) which are proved to have 'been manufactured or produced more than one hundred years before the date of importation* Articles which qualify for admission free of Customs duty under this provision qualify also for admission free of Purchase Tax# 12. Gifts, including: woddinr: 'presents* There is no specific exemption from duty and Purchase Tax in respect of intended presents or of articles acquired by way of wedding presents or other gifts, or in respect of articles forming part of a trousseau* Duty and Tax (if any) are chargeable unless the articles are admissible free under one of the foregoing paragraphs* 13* Livestocks The importation of parrots is prohibited* Dogs and cats brought from any country other than Eire or the Channel Islands, must not be landed except under a licence issued by the Ministry of Agriculture and Fisheries# and in accordance with the terms of the licence* The importation of certain other animals is also subject to restrictions* 14* Warnin/ 1 :* If any articles admitted free of duty and/o^ Purchase Tax under paragraphs 3, 5, 6, 7 or 8 above are sold or otherwise disposed of in this country, they will be liable to forfeiture under Section 12 of the Finance Act# 1948. It is to be noted that there is no legal entitlement to the concessions referred to in paragraphs 3-8 above, and they may at any time be withdrawn as the interests of the Revenue require. Secretaries , Office, Customs and Excise, City Gate House, Cec. 60929/49. Finsbur/ Square, E. C. 2 October, 1949r* 4 ' , i * i Q ' ' CIRCULAR No. 44 y#*- s /v LP 16/20 ] Foreign Office, 16/// June, 1950. Revised Customs Memorandum for Consular Officers _ 7 Pl^' Sir, With reference to Foreign Office circular No. 76 of 25th Novem- ^^ ber, 1949, 1 transmit to you herewith a copy of the revised Customs Memorandum No. 4/1 (May 1950), which summarises the British Customs rules and concessions relating to passengers' baggage and effects imported into the United Kingdom in force in May 1950. Additional copies of this memorandum cannot be supplied but, if necessary, you may reproduce a limited number for official use only, providing the text is strictly adhered to. I am. Sir, Your obedient Servant, K. G. YOUNGER. ^7 His Majesty's Superintending Consular Officers. ?/■ 16201 38801—15■jC K, A Mono. Yl V-Ti/&gt;~ 1^50) PAnCI'T THERS' BAGT mCE AFP EF CTTS THE POLLOY/E'G oinUJriY OF BRITISH CU^'OlvIG RULES JuTD OONCESSIOHS KWJUtJG TO P/JSSmGEliS 1 BAGGAGE AHD EFFECTS E v ^OHTKD B1T0 THE UlIITED KIITGDOll RE^TiEGEMTS THE POSITION AT THE EAi'E OF ISSUE OF THIS miOR/. NDCM 1. C us torn s oxani nat ion» Tho personal ba^a^o and otbor 'bolon^ings of all porsons arriving in the United Kingdom of Great Eritain and Northern Ireland, whether in transit or otherwise, are subject to Customs examination# Tho responsibility for opening, unpacking and repacking the paclcagos rests with tho jassonger or his age 2. Declara tion required. All articles obtained (l) outside the United Kingdom or ('2) during the voyage, whether hy purchase or otherv/ise, must be declared to the Customs Officer f whether they have been worn or used or not, and however small tho quantity* Failure to make a proper djcl a-ation mny involve heavy penalties, including forfeiture of the goods. 3. Liab i li ty to d uty nnd Purchase Tax. Practically all articles are liable to duty and may be liable to Purchase Trx. In practice, passen gers carrying only a small quantity of dutiable goods (inciting tobacco, spirits and perfumery) for their personal use are allowed to retain it free of duty and tax* The limits on the quantities of consumable goods passed free under this concession are as follows •- For visi tors ' permanently resi dent outsi de Eur ope. Tobacco (including cigars and cigarettes) up io 1 lb* Spirits (including liqueui's and cordials) up to 1 bottle (i.e. one-sixth of a gallon) • Wine in bottle up to 1 bottle (i.e. one-sixth of a gallon) • As an alternative to one bottle each of wine and spirits, a visitor may import two of either if opened and in use* ■s Perfumed spirits and toilet waters up to 2 pint- VISITORS IN TRANSIT through this country will be allowed to take with them, in addition to the above, up to 600 cigarettes (or equivalent and -J litre (-J pint) of perfumed spirits and toilet waters. For viaitors f rom Europe and retu rni ng Fr it:ish resident s,. Tobacco (including cigars and cigarettes) . up to J lb. Spirits (including liqueurs and cordials) up to -J- bottle (i.e. one- twelfth of a gallon) . Wine in bottle .. up to 1 bottle (i.e. one-sixth of a gallon) • Perfumed spirits and toilet waters up to 2 pint of which not more than half to be perfumed spirits- VISITORSVISITOKS IN TR/'iNGIT thruu^h this country will 'bo allowud to take with th'jm&gt; in addition to tha above, u-. to ^ pint of perfumed spirits and toilet waters, fli unbroken packings, of whioh not triore than 1 oz. to 'be perfumed % spirits. In the case of visitors from iJuropc and roturnin/r 1 litish rosiueni-s,^ duty is charged on the whole qaantity where it oxcefids twice tae apeciiied limit. Those concessions do not extend to dutiable articles in unaccompanied ba^gaf'C or in resi''stored ba.',nrr.^o not examined simultaneously v/icn the unregistered ba&amp;^aflc* T h oy do not cover persons making day-trips to places outside the Jnitod ivin^uom and are modified in their application to the Irish Land Boundary, Used articles of personal effects which have been in the possession and use the passenger fot a considerable period and arc not intended for other persons cr for sale, may also be admitted free of duty and Purchase Tax. '?.c^onal jJiJ5.ct^_ means any portable articles imported in the ba^are or on the person of a pass oncer which ho might reasonably be expected to carry with him for his own regular ana private use. (See also pararraph 6). All concessions are subject to the articles being duly declared and produced to the Customs Officer and to Ms being satisfied as to the facts. 4. Prohibited and restricted g oods,*. The importation of certain goods, e.g* dangerous dru^s, is'frexhibited and no such prohibited .article, however small the quantity, will be permitted to be imported# # &gt; Merchandise, or any goods other than bona fide private eixects, i.iust not be imported as passengers' baggage. Import licences are not required for p assengers^ effects provided that they are not beinn: imported for sale and that the quantities rire rcasonaDl^o, nor ore they required for household effects imported on a bona iiae ctian ; e &lt; i lesit.ence# In the case of foodstuffs the concession is limited as follows :~ (a) a person arriving from Eire! 7 lbs. in all. -^o one locdstufi to exceed 2 lbs® (b) a person arriving from other countries; 50 lbs. in all. one foodstuff to exceed 10 lbs. Uncooked meat may not be imported from the Continent. 5. Tempt rary importa tions ». In the case of persons who at the time of their arrival intend making only a temporary stay (i.e. up to six months) in the Unitec. Kingdom, personal and professional effects which are not admissible^unuer par^.gra} 5 will be admitted free of duty and tax, subject to the Customs Officers being satisfied, that the articles will be re-exported. In some cases this^will be secured b/ (i) sealing the goods and sending them forward unler a^ carrier s b-ixl to the port of exportation or (ii) the payment of a returnaolo deposit to e^ver e duty and tax. 6. Tool s of trade and profes sio nal effects.- Portable tools of trade, occupation or employment and articles of professional use waie.i are in acoual ^ ownership and possession of the passenger at the time of importation an.^ia -nc.e to be used by him in the course of his occupation, employment or profession in future are treated as 'personal effects' (paragraph 5) and will be^ admitteci of duty and Purchase Tax provided they are shown to have been in the possession and use of the passenger for an appreciable time. 7. Household effects. Furniture and other articles of ordinary and donestic use (but not including such articles as wines, spirits and tobacco, or cinematograpn film of the standard width of if') which are imported on a bona fide trans!or oi ■ residence to this country by the owner will be admitted free of duty an. j-urciiase Tax provided that the articles are shown to the satisfaction of the -us-c i is C - x icors to have been in the importer's possession and use abroad for^a co;.siaoiau ^ p^' 100 - and are not intended to be disposed of in this country. It ns nob possxoi- the Commissioners of Customs and Excise to say whether particular^ artic-.os ..ix _ qualify for free admission under this concession, unless information as to ^ao aat^ on which the articles were obtained and the period of possossi n ao-.^u^f ^ v importer abroad axe available. The concession envisages that tae eixects sn.-.il e imported at or about the same time as the owner .arrives in this cjuns. j*&amp;. Motor vehicles* Except where imported temporarily under the touring 'e^ultions &gt; motor cars may ordinarily oe imported only on production of an import licence and payment of duty and Tax. Where certain conditions are fulfilled and subject to the satisfaction of the Customs Examining Oificer as to the facts* a motor car owned 'by a person removing his residence to this country from abroad ia admitted without lie''..'0 and free of duty and Tax* ihe conditions are (i; there must be a bon&lt;a fide .rc'or of residence; (ii) the car must have been in the importer's private use ci-i. ^sses^icn abroad lor at least t.vo yearo before importation; and (iii) the car must oa imported for continued private use bv the importer and not for sale. The p. ;nc rules apply to motor cyci-es except that where such vehicles do not qualify for admission free of duty and tax -under conditions (i), (ii) and (iii) above they are nevertheless admitted without licence if imported from certain countries* Particulars of the countries concerned may oe obtained on enquiry at the address given below# 9# British ret urned '•oods. Articles 'which on i'iportation are proved^ oo have been previously exported from this country after any proper duty^has oeen paid^and not refunded and which have undergone no process, alteration, addition or repair while abroad are admissible duty free. Purchase Tax may sometimes be payable, however, e*3*&gt; in the case of goods which had been purchased tax free for export# i_0» Empire floods* Articles which can be shown to have been consigned from, and rrown, produced or manufactured in the British Empire are admissible free of Customs duty or at reduced rates of duty. The liability to Purchase Tax, however, is not affected. 11. Antiq ue articles. Customs duty is not charged on /pods (other than spirits or wines) which are proved to have been manufactured or produced more than one hundred years before the date of importation. Articles v/hich qualify^ for admission free of Customs duty under this provision qualify also for admission free of Purchase Tax* 12. Gifts, including wedd ing prese nts*. There is no specific exemption from dutv and Purchase Tax 'in 'respect of intended presents or of articles acquired cy wa: of wedding presents or other gifts, or in respect of articles forming part oi a trousseau. Duty and Tax (if any) are chargeable unless the articles are admissible free under one of the foregoing paragraphs* 13. Livestock. Tho importation of p.-xrrots is prohibited. Docs and oats ^ brought from any oovmtry other than Eire or tho Channel Islands, must not he landed except under a licence issued by the Ivtinistry oi .agriculture anc i^noncs, an accordance with the terns of the licence. The taportation of certain other animal. is also subject to restrictions* 14. Warning* If any articles admitted free of duty and/or Purchase Tax under paragraphs 3, 5, 6, V or 8 above are sold or otherwise disposer of in t i country, they will bo liable to forfeiture under Section 12 of the iinance jict, 1948. It is to bo noted that there is no legal entitloment to the concessions rofcrrc to in paragraph 3-8 above, and they may at any time be withdrawn as tho interest of the Revenue require* Secretaries' Office, Customs and Hxoiso, 50813/47 City Gate House, Pinsbury Square; E. C* 2 May; 1950*No PA/GA H.B.] T s Political Agent, BAHRAIn: ];3CiiORaNDUM; - THS bUSTOMHOUSE: BAHRAIN; Pth January, $35. Vt^.Shawal, 1303., 7y 'J I should be 'very much obliged if you could kindly obtain for me a copy of the forms in use in the Iraq Customs Department, and also in the Indian Customs for: Port Clearance Certificate for steamships, and Port Clearance Certificate for Native Craft. It is possible that such forms may be of essistance to me tonwards imporving the form at present in use in this port, please. - — DIftEELOK OF CUSTOMS, and PORT OFFICER. LAHRAIN:The Political Agent, Bahrain. ^Cbllector of Customsi Customs House, Karachi* - . Political Ag ncy f Bahrain, the 10th February 1935i # I have the honour to inform you that the Bahrain Government are desirous of improving their form of certifi cate for Port Clearance for both steamships and for native craft and I have to request that you will be so good as to send me a sample of (1) Certificate for Port Clearance for Steamships and (2) Certificate for Port Clearance for Native Craft as used in your Department. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant. /u- C-' I.C.S., for Political Agont, Bahrain,No# J ^7 •'7/12# Political Agency, Bahrain, the /^^ebruary 1936. Sir, I have the honour to irffonn you tliat th6 Bahrain Government are desirous of improving their form of certificate for Port Clearance for both steamships and for native craft and I have to request that you will be so good as to send me a sample of (1) certificate for port Clearance for Steamships and (2) certificate for Port Clearance for N^ive Craft as used by v/he •Iraqi Customs Department at Basrah. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant. tfc for Political Agent, Bahrain# I.C.S His Britannic Majesty's Consul, Basrah.* ' - —— —- aNo PA/G/.5.W/* H.B.M's Political Agent, BAHRAIN: MEMORANDUM: - THE CUSTOMHOUSE; BAtiBhTl.: 11th February, 1935., 8th Dhul Qaada, 1353., s.s,'Bamora*v.233 discharged at this port on 27th January 1935 a quantity of parcels, which included one for Mrs R. Carter. Reference to the Waybill No.3., Sheet No.l., will disclose that this parcel was of declared value of £ll-8-3d. Reference to the enclosed British Customs Declaration will disclose that the parcel was declared at lls.Bd., and it weighed 311)s; consequently the record in the waybill is incorrectly stated. I should be very much obliged if the attention of the proper authority in Karachi may nlease be drawn to this discrepancy, in the hope that future similar errors may be avoided. vi 1^ Enclos:- \ ^ DIRECTOR Oi' CUSTOMS, and PORT OFFICER. BAHRAIN:M Not *.—In replying please c ote the nnmber and date of vhia letter and address the Officer from whom it is received by designation and not by name. Telegraphic Address : ' Customs, Kabaohi.' Telephone Nos. 1117 &amp; 1118. Post Box No. 105. FflOM &lt;r To Collector op Customs, Custom House, Karachi, The Political isent, Bahrein. Sir No. L.Dis . Dated tie 20th Fehy. 1935. Reference: Your letter lo. 246-7 /12 of 10-2-1935. ^ith reference to your letter quoted ahove, I have the honour to enclose^ as desireci^a sample form of Port Clearance certificate issued hy this Custom House. The same form is used for steamships as well as native craft. 1 Have the honour to 'be, Sir r Y 0 ur most obedient servant, for Collector Gf Customs.■3 POET CLEARANCE. This is to certify that the S.S. Commander, Burthen, * under colours is now cleared outwards from this Port for with cargo as per manifest and passengers as per annexed list. The Commander of the eaid vessel has rendered, or has through the ship's agent undertaken to render, an account of the import and export cargo, and has otherwise complied with all the regulations of this port. Custom House, 19 . Assistant Collector of Customs. C. B. R. Customs—15* MFP—513Customs—(M-621)—6-8-34—25,000. (See reverse.)Noi 3 .^?.. 6 BRITISH CONSULATE, BASRA, IRAQ. 4th March,1955 Sir, t ^ In accordance with the request conveyed in your letter No.267 -7/12 of the 17th February last, I have the honour to enclose a specimen of the clearance form used for steamships and also for country craft by the Iraq Customs Department here. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient Servant, His Majesty's Consul. Political Agent, Bahrain.No. ^'1,7/ Political Agency f Bahrain, the 14th March 1936• TO aiiv I have the honour to refer to your letter No# dated the 4th March 1935 and to state that the specimen of the clearance jform used for steamships and also for country craft by the 4 Iraq Customs Department at Basrah was omitted from your letter- I should be grateful tf you would kindly Bend it to me# X have the honour to be, bir p Your most obedient servant. Lieut*Colonel| Political Agent, Bahrain# # His Majesty's Consul, Basrah#I 1 — i 7/12. Political Agency f Bahraini the 14th March 1936• to The Director of Cuetoras aiid Port Officer, Bahrain , jdemuraiidanu &gt; J Reference your memoranaum ^0,^^3/34/433 dated the 11th February 1935. 2. Kindly send me, for ray inspection and return, the V/ay Bill No*3, shoot No.l, referrea t.o in paragraph 1 of your memorandum quoted above # Lieut.Colonel| Political Agent, Bahrain*f Ho: PA/Gr/ THE CUSTOMHOUSE: BAHRAIN: 18th March, 1935., 13th Dhul Haj, 1353., H.B.m's Political Agent, BAHRAIN: MEMORAUDUIu : - In reply to your No:4^0/7/lE., I submit herewith, for inspection and return. Sheet No.l., of Way Bill No.3., please. Enclos: -\ DIRECTOR OF CUSTOMS, and PORT OFFICER. BAHRAIN:1 Ho PA/G /.A'&lt; + .|hS'| H.B.M's Political Agent, BAHrain: TKE CUSTOMHOUSE: BAHRAIN: 31st March, 1935., 26th Dhul Ha.), 135S. ^Morandum : - s. s. ^ankura 1 arrived at this port on £4th March 1936. and discharged its mail, which included parcels from Karachi, listed in the Karachi Post Office Parcel Bill No.11. Sheet No.II of this parcel 'bill shews item No:E3, Sh. Zohur Ahmed Sahih Storekeeper Medicines Declared Value at Rs:83/- Customs Duty was duly collected from the Consignee^ upon this valuation. A claim has now 'been submitted 'by this consignee for a ref-Mid. of duty on the ground® th^t We yal^e of the goo?r Is Rs :8.annas 3. only, not Rs :83/-. The claim is supported hy satisfactory evidence, and appears to 'be in order. This consignee would not have 'been put to the trouble of making a claim if the declared value had been properly stated in the Parcel Bill. I drew your attention to this in the hope that the matter will be submitted to the proper authority in Sind, so that the individual responsible for this error may be duly rebuked, and such carelessness may be prevented in future, please DIRECTOR OF CUSTOMS, and PORT OFFICER. BAHRAIN: ■ Wfu Ur/A- ^ ^ W 3H No. 507. HIS Majesty's Consul ' at Basra presents his oompliraents to the Political Agent, Bahrain, aud has the honour to transmit to him titfL under-mentioned documents. Bri tish...C.QIi S.U.l &amp;. t. 3as.r.a., Iiraq.f .22nd..March., 193.5.' Reference to previous correspondence Basra Consulate Letter No. 587 darted 4th March 1955* Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. A specimen of the clearance form used for steamships and also for country craft by the Iraq Customs Department. / RH. 3479 5898 (*) I*i. C\.&gt;« 'IRAQ GOVERNMENT. 1 P- i ^ BASRAH PORT CLEARANCE. This is to Certify that the s. s. Comma nder_ Burthen. Under colours^ _ J! Form No C-7. »oAa&gt; fjr^J r'' ^ Jl .t«U» jl t^U. is now cleared Outwards from this Port for_ Laden or in ballast and carrying Passengers as Per annexed list. The Commander of the said vessel has complied with all the Customs Regulations of this Port. •L ; LI Iaa ^ iJjl^JI (j c ij 5&gt;»Lrt J (jl I 4ii»JlU icliil {jJikj sal IBASR^H CUSTOM HOUSE. iJjT Dated. Colleclor of Customs &amp; Excise. ^^Cib i)^.11 jS* \ .I 0 No. . 7/12. Political Agency| Bahrain, the 6th April 1935, -vS pv I «■ ni Tr From Captain Q. A. Cole, I.A., Officiating Political A^ent, Bahrain , The Director of Posts and Telegraphs, Sind and Baluchistan Circle, (Foreign Parcels Department) Karachi # Siri I have the honour to inform /ou ohat my attention has been drawn to a wrong declaration being entered In Parcels Wfty Bill No,3, dated bhe 19th January 1935, Liheet I f item 3, prepared in the foreign Parc9ls Department, Karachi, and •iespatchen by s,s, Bamora, voyage 5&gt;33, In the column ♦♦Declared value M you will notice that ohr mm of t: 11,8.3 has been entered instead of lls,8d, vrhich is tha value an declared by uae sender on the parcel. In this oonneotion I enclose the reportion of the original wrapping off the parcel addressad to lira. R# Carter, 'i'he lialirein Petroleum Con^pany liimitiedi i'or your iaapeotion and return# 1 ^ave the honour to request that you will take such action as you think necessary, I have the honour to be, bir, Your most obedient servant. Captain Offg, Political Agent, Bahrain. -No. .7/12, Memorandum# 4 Political Agency f Bahrain, the 17th April 1935. The Director of Customs and Port Officer, a irain * / Reference correspondence ending with your memorandum No#PA/G/S9/384 dated the 12th January 19a5» 2, I enclose, as desired, a specimen of Port Clearance Certificate as issued by the 6 j stems Oepartnent at Basrah and Karachi. The e ms form is used for steamships as well as for country craft# ^ Captain, Offg. Political Agent, BeUirain#Corr.-40. Indian Posts and Telegraphs Department. Peom No, 'FT-24/4. The Director of posts and Telegraphs 3inci and Ba is tar dircije. ^aptain.a.A.^ole I .A. officiating ,Political Agent Bahrain Number of enclosures !ir, Tated Karachi | ;,^9th May m 5. H i/^'A ' n ' h In oontinuanoe of this of floe letter No .^P-24/2, latel the 17th April 19 35,1 have the honour to say that the necessary correction has he en made in the records of the Karachi General i'ost office and the Suh-Postmaster, 'Bahrain has also 'been directed to rectify the mistake Ihe official responsible for the irregularity has 'been suitably dealt with.The inconvenience caused to you is much regretted. The enclosure is returned herewith. I^/AO. 1 have the honour to 'be 3i r, Your most obedient servant. | for director.r^ mmm^\ Post Office of GREAT BRITAIN.' — CUSTOMS DECLARATION (C) (DECLARATION noUAM: . * t ' .name andNo PA/G/iKj/ 5 .^ THE CUSTOMHOUSE: BAHRAIN; 4th February, 192^., 11th Dhal Qaada, 1354., H.B.M's Political Agent, BAHRAin:- MEMOrandum: - I observe that Customs Landing Certificates at the port of Qatar are now being signed by one Abdulla bin Durwish Fakroo. Could you please inform me if this person is now the local Mudir of the Customs, and the term of his appointment. )IRECT0R OF CUSTOMS, and PORT OFFICER. BAHRAIN; ANo. 48; &gt;(1^7) political Agency, Bah^111, the 16th Febma-^y 1^36. To The Di-'-ecto'- of Customs and FoH Office^, Bah-^ain. I.eno^muum * ^efen^nce you^ memo^iTiaum No.PA/G/l&lt;i/313 dated the 4th i?ebma''y 1936. 2. I have no oflicial information of the appointment of Abdullah bin Danish i'akhm as Di-'-ecto^ of Customs at ^ata^, but I undent and that he has been acting in that capacity fo- the past fou^ 0^ five months* Any endocements and/o^ landing certificates signed by this individual may, I think, be accepted as genuine. (^ / Tc ^ Xl , captain, fo'' Political Agent, Bah^inS P E C I 'AM- I T 1 E S OF GEORG DRALLE v\ PERFUMERIES AND TOILET SOAPS ASHROF BROTHERS BAHREIN ' ' ' ; v E February 191 The Director of Customs f 'y- B A H R A I Dear Sir , A copy of the British Journal Photographic Almanac consigned to us by Messrs. Kodak Ltd., London through the Eastern Bank Ltd, Bahrain, arrived here on or about the 7th instant. When it came to the Customs for clearance our Mr. Arif Lukraani called the Custom House and inspected the Journal. It was hov/ever not delivered to him at that time. To-day Mir. Arif Lukmani again called at the Custom Plouse to take the Journal ovei? v/hen he found some pa^-ges missing. The missing pages wore rerjroductions of pictures of ladies. Since these Journals are printed in London and the pictures are reproduced for lovers of the art of photography a^ll the world over, would you please let us know for what reason these particular pictures were torn out of the Jo^»^ before information being given to us ? We would als^^Buest you to quote under what regulation you have ta^fc)i|pb:ch a high handed action. ; /Ould you please note that we are not prepared to take delivery of the Journal in its damaged state and are advising Messrs. Kodak Ltd., London accordingly* Yours faithfully, cz*) ftsf/j?ftp a/eos ' Copy to The Advisor to the Government of Bahrain. w H. B. Majesty 1 s Political Agent, Bahrain. ' w The Eastern Bank Ltd., Bahrain. C jL'^' If / F,:V Wi ;?• / &lt; K- . PA/G/^Vf; THE CUST0L2H0USE; BAHRAIN; 27th October, 1937., 21st Shaman, 1356., H.B.M's Political Agent, BAHRAIN; MEMORANDUM: - As a matter of information, I write to inform you that I have to-day impounded two prints brought here by an Indian barber named Malang, which are deemed to be indecent, having regard to local Muslim sentiment. These are confiscated, and will be destroyed in due course, please. DIRECTOR OF CUSTOMS, and PORT OFFICER. BAHRAIN: tIF ^ Wext al 4ffiluWr t ^aljrain P^er^ian ®nl£. 30th October, 1937., I received a telephone enquiry this afternoon from Mr H. Newell Phillips, the Chief Accountant of the Bapco, asking me to inform him the retail prices at which petrol and kerosene oil are supplied to the Saudian-Arabian Government ex steamer from Bahrain, and I understand that it is the purpose of the Bapco to market their products retail locally and on the mainland of Arabia in competition with the products of the Anglo-Iranian Oil Coy Ltd.,whose tanker the s.s.Khuzistan calls here regularly and delivers motor spirit and kerosene oil, and also does a considerable business by oversides delivery within the port for the mainland ports of Arabia, which are of course the Saudian-Arabian ports. It is of course quite possible for me to collate this information and supply it; but I would prefer to do so through official channels, and not over the telephone, especially as, according to the official Annual Trade Report, you are the authority to whom trade enquiries should be directed, when no doubt, you would kindly decide as to the expediency of such information being granted. It has long been the rule that all trade information in the possession of the Customs is confidential. I therefore suggested to Mr Phillips that he had better enquire first from Yourself, when no doubt you would give me suitable instructions. I fancy that he was a little sorry I said this as he wanted to reply to a cabled enquiry urgently. Believe me. Yours sincerely, Ce, To:- H. Weightman Esquire, I.C.S,, H.B.M's Political Agent, BAHRAIN.jfl XT' government of bahrain. CUSTOMS DEPARTMENT. &gt;1 M A A K iij 24 th May, 1938 •, 24th H/Awal,1357., notice. IT Xb HOliiriiUi tnats nH f i i On and after the let Haoia al Thany, 1357, (corresponding *lth Slet May, 1938.,) the Import Yard Charges oi' KhAJsUHlA and of JL^JftALI upon liquid oile and fats in bulk will be collected at the r&amp;te of three pies ( RsfC # C.3.) on each (.British) Ifflperial gallon of content, LET THIS BS HCTSs JSxamples of the aoovt com ouities are: Aviation spirits aero-shell; a, i 0 C, oil; coco-nut oil; engine oil; luel oil; lisn oil; ^hee; ground nuts oil; ^rease; inula oil; kerosene oil; linseed oil; lubricating oil; motor oil; petrol; sesamum oil; vegetable lats; white tne liice* :h cf customs Ml i OKI I Oyif ICE1I, B/hRAHi • Cop&gt; tot- Political Agent, Bahrain. The Adriser, the (roremment of i^anrain, Bahrain* it i] —NATIOII.'il AIR CO!.a i TW L zC BAHRAIN ISLANDS PERSIAN GULF ( Telepk one : 43M Telegrams : Airways, Balirain BAH/1/3000/C. ^oveigber, 1939. The Political Agent, Bahrein, Dear Mr, Weightman, I wonder if you would take up with the Adviser the question of the Customs shutting for such a long period for MOhamnedan holidays. One or two days is reasonable 'but for Id they have been shut since Sunday and do not open again till Saturday, i In the old days when there was only access to the outside world 'by ship this was all right out nowadays with quick air transport the idea is antedeluvian. People pay high rates to send, things by air so that they can go quickly but the whole tning looses its point if goods are held up on arrival here for five or six days as a result of the Customs being closed. During this period it is im possible to export or import anyoning out of Bahrein, I am sure you will agree with me that at no place which is more advanced than a century ago should this state of affairs exist. In case you are not aware tot* it, I would mention that in Iraq the Customs do not close at all for Id, Yours sincerely. CD.D.O.Mo. 2066-7/12 The 27 th November 1939 I forwarsi herewith a copy of a letter No. BAH/1/ 3000/C.5 dated the 17th November 1939 from Stuart- flfcrtley on which I should like to teive your comraenta. 2# I am inclined to think that the time has come when lengthy interruptions of public service organisationi should be eliminatede Yours sincerely, L C. Dalrymple Belgrave f Ksquire, C.B.K., Adviser to the Bahrain Government, Bahrain. ^ v'VD.O. No, 1944/3. r- J ain, November 29, 1939. Dear Weightman, With reference to your D.O. 2066/7-12 dated 27th November enclosing a letter from National Air Communication Service Station Superintendent. I agree that lengthy interruptions of public service organisations are undesirable but Stuart-Wortley 1 s statement that goods were held up for five or six days owing to the Customs being closed is not correct. 2o The Eid day, 13th November, and the three following days were holidays, the 17th was a Friday. During this time four parcels arrived by air, one arrived on 14th and was passed on 15th, one arrived on 15th and was passed on 16th and the other two parcels would have been delivered if the consignees had claimed them. It was not 'impossible to import or export anything out of Bahrain' during the days when the customs was officially closed. 3o During the days in question which were part of the official Moslem holiday the Director of Customs had a skeleton staff on hand dealing with any urgent work. On all similar occasions in the past the Station Superintendent has communicated with the Director of Customs regarding urgent matters such as parcel delivery which has been dealt with atonce. Yours sincerely. H. Weightman. Esquire, I.G.S., H.i3„M T s Political Agent, Bahrain. t ■^ 0 D.C .No. 2113-7/12. The 2nd December 1939. ] £ Please refer to your demi-official letter No. BAH/ 1/3000/C.S dated the 17th November 1939. 2. I an informed that a skeleton staff is on duty during 'Id holidays, which deals at once with any 5 deliveries of air freight parcels^ and- should be glad to have details of any case of delayed delivery. Yours sincerely, (i J.M. Stuart-flortley, Require, National Air Comnunicatlons Service, Bahrain. AI L M I n-y k* From To f 'j - No. Bahrain, Dated, 7th December 1939 C. Dalrymple Belgrave, Esquire, Adviser to the Government of Bahrain, Bahrain, Persian Gulf. His Britannic Majesty's Political Agent, Bahrain, Persian Gulf. i Sir, I have the honour to acquaint you with certain facts regarding the behaviour of a number of U.S.A. lady passengers who arrived in Bahrain by fast mail 'Varsova n on 29th November, from Bombay on route for al Khobar. Special arrangements were made for these nine ladies to go direct from the ship to Al Khobar and customs officials were detailed to inspect their i baggage on board the steamer in order to avoid any delay or inconvenience to the passengers. The passengers m question made it impossible for the customs officials to carry out their duty by making obviously untrue declarations and by affording no opportunities for examining baggage. Eventually owing to the confusion on board the ship's officers requested that the luggage should be taken on shore for inspection and about one hundred pieces of luggage and cases were taken to the Customs pier. The following is a comparison of declarations and assessments:- (1) l.irs nubert Fritzie: declaration reasonable,no objections. (2) ,T C.M. Potter: declaration 0 .10.00; assessed at Rs.SOO/- (3) —-2- at tt (3) i:rs E.Jensen (Nurse) : declaration none .Assessed at Rs.200/- 200/- 100/- 500/- 200/- 1,000/- (4) ' Velrna E.Eastland: (5) ' A.B.Williams: (6) ' I.^.'/eigand: (7) ' L.I.I.Eollingworth: {8) ' M. /.Harkness: (9) ' H.B.Becklay: nil. ' ' 7 packages. ' n used personal effects none ' ,T ^. 75. ' ' amended later by- husband to H3.35/- ,T 500/- The amount of unnecessary examination and delay was considerable and I think it is desirable that the Manager of the Company should impress on his staff the need of compliance with normal customs procedure. Because Bahrain is a small place there is no reason for Europeans and Americans dis regarding local rules and regulations which they would hesitate to ignore in other parts of the world. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Adviser to the Government.D.O. No. ill I -7/13 Dated the 13th December ls33J Will you please refer to your letter No. 1991 cUted the 7th December 1^5^ regarding the behaviour of certain it.dy passengers disembarking from the ^Varsova* en route to Al Khobar ? . 2. I suggest thi t th^ line to take be thi t in of the behaviour of these ladies it will not be possible to make special arrangements for Customs inspection on board the mail steamers and that all passengers and baggage for Saudi Arabia will in future have to land from the mail steamers at Bahrain for the usual Customs inspection. It might also be added that failure to make proper declarations of the value of bc-^gt ^ will rtnaer such persons 1 aole to vy .'im s. Before however I write to the Company on these lines I should be glad to know if there is any free allowance, covering especially used personal effects, such as is normally granted in other countries. C. Dalrymple Belgrave, Isquire, C.B .E., Auviser to the Bahrain Government, Bahrain. Yours sincerely. ijj&gt; -fc- il- I ?. 3 fNo. 2^ ahrain. 17th December 1939 nl^ Dear height man, Reference your D.O. No.2191-7/12 dated 13th December 1939. I enclose a copy of the declaration form which shows what goods are free from duty. In practice we do not ipake a detailed exami nation of ladies 1 effects but pass things which may not actually be 'used'. I believe in the case in question the passen gers brought a quantity of carved boxes and curious etc. Yours sincerely, H. Weight man, Ssquire, J H. B, M*s Political Agent, Bahrain.GOVERNMENT OF BAHRAIN. CUSTOMS DEPARTMENT PASSENGERS' BAGGAGE DECLARATION. per s. s. V. No. from The bona fide baggage of passengers including used wearing apparel, personal erfects ami instruments of trade, not including the following articles, is exempt from import duty. PROHIBITED ARTICLES: 1. Cultured and imitation pearls. •2. Arms &amp; Ammunition. •i. Liquor (wines &amp; spirits) and intoxicating drugs, and methylated spirits. 1. Dogs. o. Obscene &amp; seditious pictures, literature etc. Classification. Quantity and Value. Description. Duty. Remarks. 1. Perfumes •2. Tobacco (manufactured or raw)... EXEMPTIONS: Cigarettes not exceeding one hundred Cigars not exceeding 50 ... Tobacco „ „ 1 lb. ... 3. Motor Vehicles, musical instru ments &amp; accessories, radio sets 4. Household goods, furniture &amp; unused personal effects 5. Articles intended for the use of other parties or for sale Total ... \ DECLARATION : I certify that the above particulars are true. Number of packages Occupation Date Customs Officer's Countersignature i HNALT\ FOR UNTRUE DECLARATION: Confiscation; and/or fine not exceeding Rs. 1,000/-, and/or imprisonment.A 2236-7/12. PolitiCAl Agency, E^hrfiln, the 19th December 1939 To C.A. Hodstrom, Esquire, California Arabian Standard Oil Company, Bahrain. Dear Sir, My attention has been dra^n by the Bahrain Government to the behaviour of certain lady passengers v»ho arrived in Bahrain by the fast mail steamer 'Varsova' on the 29th November 1939 from Bombay en route for A1 Khobar. 2. It appears that in order to enable these passenders tx) proceed direct to A1 I hobftr without landing in Bahrain, Bahrain Customs Officials were detailed to examine their baggage on the ship. The Bahrain Government were under no obligation to do this and it was done to ensure the least possible inconvenience to those concerned. By making obviously untrue declarations, and by affording no opportunities for examining their baggage, these passengers made it quite impossible for the k,u8t,o-^s Officials to carry out their duties and ev-ntually, o^ing to the confusion which occurred, the ship's officers requested that the luggage should be taken ashore for inspection. Such behaviour in the presence of subordinate Customs Officials is deplorable. In future, to avoid its repetition, no special arrangements for customs inspection on board mail steamers will be made, and all passengers and baggage for Saudi Arabia will have to be landed at Bahrain to comply with the usu^l customs formalities. It has/2 It has alttnyt been the deaire of the Bahrain Government to make the inspection of the baggage of paaaengera for A1 Khobar a a simple as possible- and thoy have taken a lenient view of this case in the hope that adequate steps will be taken to ensure thnt similar cases do not occur in future- The failure to make proper declaration of the value of baggage| it should be remembered, renders a person liable to a heavy fine. Yours faithfully N 4 Political Agent, Bahrain. Copy to j The Adviser to the Bahrain Government, Bahrain.California Arabian ~ Dhahran, Saudi Arabia December 23&gt; 1939 Hugh Welghtman, Esquire # / 0 *^ ' Political Agent, |-v 9$ DEC. W&amp; ) jj Bahrein. \v /* Dear Sir: A copy of your letter No. 2236-7/12 of December 19&gt; 1939&gt; 'to Mr. C. A. Rodstrom has Just been forwarded to me. during customs examination on the steamer 'Varsova' on November 29&gt; 1939* While we assume responsibility for our employees to a certain degree, we are unable to for- see such happenings as you report. In the future we shall make no request of the Bahrain Customs Office to grant any special arrangement. G-W :R cc - Mr. C. A. Rodstrom Copy fowarded to Adviser under P.L.No. 12 of 3-1-1940. I regret very much the behavior of our employees Sincerely,No PA/FC/ THE CU ST OHHOU SE: BAHRAIN: 30th June, 1940., 25th Jemad I, 1359., BP H.B.M ? s Political Agent, BAHRAIN: l^MORANDUM;- I am informed that in Saudia-Arabia, a 'ban has been put upon the export from Qatif to Bahrain of ^afs' and ^ereeds* (i.e. date-sticks ) which are much in demand locally at this season for construction of huts. Would you please confirm the accuracy, or otherwise, of this report. w (j- DIRECTOR OF CUSTOKS, and PORT OFFICER. BAHRAIN: /</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x00003c_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1325</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x00003c</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1325</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 7/12 Miscellaneous Correspondence re Customs Matters'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1935/1950</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-07-17T00:09:00</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (101 folios)</extent><extent>This file is arranged approximately in chronological order.</extent><extent>Foliation: The file has one primary foliation sequence that runs from the first folio following the front cover to the back cover. It appears in pencil, occasionally underlined, in the top right of the recto of the folio. Another crossed-out foliation sequence appears from ff. 80-93 in pencil, circled, in the top right hand of the recto of the folio. This was a foliation mistake when the Office Notes of this file were misplaced at the beginning of IOR/R/15/2/1324. Another crossed-out foliation sequence runs from ff. 81-84 and appears in pencil in the top right hand corner of the recto of the folio. Foliation anomalies: 5A, 9A, 11A, 18A, 22A and 35A.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file includes correspondence between the Political Agents at Bahrain, Kuwait and Muscat; the Political Officer and Residency Agent on the Trucial Coast at Sharjah; the Foreign Office, London; Charles Dalrymple Belgrave, Adviser to the Bahrain Government; Claude C L de Grenier, Director of Customs and Ports Officer; the British Consul at Basrah; Director of Posts and Telegraphs, Sind and Baluchistan Circle; Collector of Customs, Karachi; J M Stuart-Wortley, National Air Communications Service, Bahrain; C A Rodstrom, California Arabian Oil Company; Haridas Janimal; 'A Public Man of Bahrain' and 'Leading Merchants of Bahrain'; L V Wallace, Officer Commanding, Royal Air Force, Bahrain; The Export Promotion Department, Board of Trade.The file includes various miscellaneous customs matters, including: a request for specimen customs certificates from Basrah and Karachi (ff. 1-3, 5-6, 11-11A and 15); Qatar customs and Bahrain customs regulations relating to Qatar (ff. 18A-19 and 67); import of photographs (including the
                           British Journal Photographic Almanac) considered to be indecent (ff. 21 and 23); closure of Bahrain customs during Muslim holidays (ff. 26-27 and 29-30); a request to expedite customs procedures at Bahrain for the sons of the Shaikh of Ras al-Khaymah proceeding on hajj pilgrimage with their families (f. 28); the behaviour of certain lady passengers from the USA and inconvenience caused to customs (ff. 31-37); import of sugar from United States by Haridas Janimal in 1946 (ff. 49-52); complaints of mismanagement of Bahrain Customs (ff. 55-56); issuing of customs certificates by Muḥammad bin Aḥmad bin Sulaymān, Shaikh of Bukhā (ff. 57-61); revised Customs Memorandum No. 4/1 (May 1949, October 1949 and May 1950) regarding British customs rules and concessions relating to passengers' baggage and effects imported into the United Kingdom (ff. 68-70 and 74-79); and Overseas Trade Memorandum regarding importation of motor cars into the United Kingdom dated 27 May 1949 (ff. 71-73).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x00003c#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>