<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00025e_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-12T01:13:38.792Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">■an - ij s From To Dated No. COMMONV^ALTH RriLiiTICNS OFFICE, External Department. Secretary of State for Commonwealth Relations The Political Resident, Persian Gulf. 13th February, 1948. Ext.370/48. Sanction is accorded to payment of provisional foreign allowance (untaxable) of £500 a year to P.D. Stobart and R. Mc.C.Andrew with effect from day after their arrival in Persian Gulf. The issue of the above has been duly authorised (SGD) F.A.K. HARRISON. '&gt; No.571-65/46. PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY, Bahrain, Dated 26th February, 1948 Co^y forwarded, with compliments, to The Political Agent, Bahrain, for record. Mr. Stobart's salary is £468/- (£675/- frora 1st January, 1948^ ^ r* V i • .. 1 ——No. 7 POLITICAL AGENCY BAHRAIN 7^ March, 1948. To The Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resideno in the Persiai Gulf, Bahrain. MEMORANDUM - Reference your endorseuient No.571-65/46 dated the 26th February 194.8 regarding Mr. P.D.Stobart's pay and foreign allowance. 2. I have not so far received his last pay certificate or any other document to show up to what date Mr.Stobart has been paid or if any deduction has to be nade from his salary and allowances drawn here. Neither have I received any communication to show to what head his pay and allowances should be debited. However, I am drawing Mr. Stobart f s pay and foreign allowance from 1st January 1948 debiting same under the head fl C-l. Pay of Officers'. As no provision exists in our budget for his pay and allowances I am including same in my final review under the above head. I may also be informed what post he should be shown as holding. for Political Agent, Bahrain. -— yNo. 804-65/46 PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN. Dated 20th March, 1948. To The political Agent, Bahrain. Memorandum. Reference your Memorandum No. 762 dated the 7th March, 1948. 2• Copies of Commonwealth Relations Office telegram No. 80 dated the 8th March, 1948, and this Residency Express Letter No. 718-65/46 dated the 13th March, 1948, are enclosed in continuation of this Residency endorsement No. 671-65/46 dated the 26th February, 1948. 3. Pending receipt of reply to this Residency Express Letter referred to above the salary and allowance of Mr. P.D. Stobart may be drawn from 5th December and 29th December, 1948, respectively and debited under the head H C-I. Pay of Officers'. 4. He should be shown as holding the post of ditional Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain. Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.Copy of Commonwealth Relations Office, London telegram No. 80 dated the 8th March, 1948, to the Political Resident, Bahrain. Your Express Letter No. 329-65/46 February 6th. Andrew and Stobart. 2. Officers are entitled to salary with effect from December 6th and allowance from December 26th.. Advances may be given on the lines i already approved as from these dates. i Copy of Residency Express Letter No. 718-65/46 dated 13th March, 1948 to Commonwealth Relations Office, London. Reference your telegram No. 80 dated the 8th March, 1948. 2. Andrew and Stobart arrived here on 28th December, 1947, and sanction was accorded to thejr drawing foreign allowance with effect from the day after their arrival here i.e. December 29th vide your Express Letter No. Ext. 370/48, dated the 13th February, 1948.- In your telegram under reference, however, they have been authorised to draw their foreign allowance from December 26th. Grateful if you will inform me of the correct date from which they are entitled to this allowance and whether their salary should be drawn here from December 4th (the date of their departure from the United Kingdom)or from December 5th.Gs No. &lt;^^9 -1/5'^ POLITICAL AGENCY BAHRAIN 24th Ii4arch, 194S To The Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain. Mj -iMOr ANDUM Mr, P.D. otobart who accompanied the Ho^bJe the Political Resident on his recent tour to Kuwait, left Bahrain by air on the 12th March *48 in the forenoon and stayed at Kuwait up to the 16th March. He made his return journey by sea. It is requested that the necessary sa^tion order of the Hon'ble the Political Resident sanctioning his journey by air and authorising him to draw daily allowance at full rates for the period of his halt at Kuwait may kindly be issued and for warded to me in duplicate v^ry early. for Pol:tical Agent, Bahrain.- Persian Grulf Residency, .~r Bahrain, N9.\ ^ Try.7. 24th March, 1948. T© The Station Superintendent, B.O.A.C., Bahrain, Dear Sir, I enclose herewith a cheque for D s. 133/5/- in part payment of your invoice No/'/l305 dated the 14th March, 194o, b^in,^ the c«st of air passage •f Sir Rupert Hay. The cost of passage of I T r. Stebart will be paid to you by. the Political talent, Bahrain. Please acknowledge receipt. Yours faithfully. Treasury^Off icer, Persian Gulf*Residency, Bahrain * N ^opy forwarded to the Foliticil ^gent, Bahrain. The T. 5. of ,r r. Stobart pay please ' h e drawn before the Zlzt larch, 1948, and his cost of air passage ^ror Bahrain to Tuwait bein,^ p ; .153/5/- be raid to B.0.A..G., Bahrain, under intir.ation to'this office.No. ltd'-1/54. POLITICAL AGENCY BAHRAIN 6th April, 1948. To The Station Superintendent, British Overseas Airways Corporation Bahrain. Dear Sir, Please refer to Residency letter No.lVe-Try.'? dated the 24th March 1948. 2. I enclose herewith a cheque for Rs, 133/6/- being the cost of Mr. P.D.Stobart 1 s air pa.sage from Bahrain to Kuwait included in your invoice No.M/1306 dated 14th March 1948 addressed to tb? Residency. Kindly acknowledge receipt. Yours faithfully, K il Agent, for Political Agent, Bahrain. k (y-No. 970-65/46. K y The Secretary to the Hon'hle the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to 1. The Political Agant, B^.hradn . 2. The Political «.g«nt, muscat . and is directed to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents. i ~7 ^ \ K«tTi«b--Re8ifleftey- aiid- Genstilat'e-GeiierftlT PERSIAN GULF aSSIDi^GY, , .5.th.. .dipr.i J..,... 1.948.. Reference to previous correspondence : (For Bahrain only. Residency endorsement Ko. 571-65/46 dated 26th February, 1948) Description of Enclosure Name and Date. Subject. Express letter No. 778/48 dated 22nd March, 1948 from the Secretary of State for Commonwealth Relations. Pay and allowances of Andrew and Stobaaft. ,4Sv ■ f| Qi( HR^ yGOmOKMtdXE EELAl 1 IONS OFFICE xxxxxxxxxxxxxxx external Department. IO KXtRESS LETTER (AIR IIAIL) /-n a ' rem To Dated Secretary of State for Coinaonvealth Relations Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. 22nd March, 1946* No. art.77^¥j Reference your express letter No.713-68/^6 of 13'bh iiarch. Pay and allowances of Mdrew and Stobart. Salary should be drawn in Bahrein from 5th December and allowance froLi 29th December (ray telegram No, 80 Of 3th i aroh mentioned 29th December not 26th December and mistake must have occurred in transmission. The issue of the above has been authorised. ft, A. K- 11M61WW/* X w Certificate of Last ravrent . o- Certified that 'Y. 'o Mc. Indrev, Under Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gl-ulf, Bahrain, has been paid un to and for the 29th February, 1948, § 6% of his salary and Foreign Service Allowance ^er annurr 'V .. at rates p -iven below. 6/o of salary § £ 36/6 or '\484/- p.m. 6% of F.S. allowance § £ 30 or r - # 400/- p. r, 7thApril,1943. Treasury ufficer, Persian G^ulf Residency, Bahrain, • Persian lulf Residency, p.g jnra in No.Try.12. 7th April,'i94B. F9rwaFded to the Pol itical i^ent, Bahrain, witl- two &lt; copies of the pay bills for necessarv action. It is requested that a sir.il ar certificate in respect of ' r r. r .D. Stobart ^ay please be issued as ear' Trcatury Officer, Persian Gulf Residcnry,PAY BILL (FOR PAYMENT AT TREASURIES). f it r .,R. is. [Treasury Rule 249 (1).] (Obverse.) Note .—Government accepts no responsibility for any fraud or misappropriation in respect of money, cheques or drafts made over to a messenger. Name of Gazetted Government Servant Hf m J / q ^ Andrew. District. Bahrain Audit No. Head of Account.* 35-Eiternal Affairs. Charges on accaunt of DiDlamatic and Consular Services in Iran. C.l. P^y of Officers. C.3. Allowances, Honoraria etc. Voucher No. - of J list of payments for March, 10 48. Monthly Amount. Keceived for the months&gt;f January &amp; Februat'^, 1948, as Und er Secretary t» the Political TTe^Tdent, Persian Gulf, y advmce of Forei.'^i Service Mlo.-.ancu. Gross claim Less Fund Deductions as follows (Separate Schedules attached) I. C. S. Provident Fund .... Post Office Insurance Fund .... Uncovenanted Service Family Pension Fund . Bengal and Madras Service Family Pension Fund General Family Pension Fund Hindu Family Annuity Fund .... Bengal Christian Family Pension Fund . General Provident Fund .... ICS 1 ' M ' g '- Family Pension Regulations Superior Services (India) Family Pension Fund Indian Military Widows' and Orphans' Fund Other Funds (with details) Net claim Deduct Income-tax Super-Tax - &gt; ^ Less abatement on Rs. ........ J Deductions on account of Advances and Recoveries as detailed below :— Advance of pay ....... ^ • House rent ........ V overdrawn ...... J Net amount payable Net amount to be written in words)Riipee8 Qna thouaund aev^n hundred and sixty eidht only. Please pay/to : ')atr March, 19 48. SignatuflP^ cr r ^gj id * ni * To be entered by drawing officer and checked in the Aooountant General's Office.r* PAY BILL (FOR PAYMENT AT TREASURIES). f 12- T.JR. 16. [Treasury Rule 249 (1).] (Obverse.) Note .—Government accepts no responsibility for any fraud or misappropriation in respect of money, cheques or drafts made over to a messenger. Name of Gazetted Government Servant Andrew, District. Bahrain Audit No. Head of Account.* 35-Eiternal Affairs. Charges on accaunt of Dir)] •psatic and Censular Services in Iran. C.l. Pay of Officers. O • o. Allowances 9 Hscoraria etc. Voucher No. ) of 1 list of payments for March, 19 48. i h Received for the month ^fJan^jiary &amp; Februai'^, 1948. fedte^*^ BaIar y as Cod6r f ^ TTs^ident, Fsrsian uulf, Ftreign Snrvice .Mlosanca. Less Fund Deductions as follows {Separate Schedules attached) I. C. S. Provident Fund .... Post Office Insurance Fund .... Uncovenanted Service Family Pension Fund . Bengal and Madras Service Family Pension Fund General Family Pension Fund Hindu Family Annuity Fund . Bengal Christian Family Pension Fund General Provident Fund ICS ' Family Pension Regulations Gross claim I. M. 8. Superior Services (India) Family Pension Fund Indian Military Widows* and Orphans' Fund Other Funds (with details) . . . . Net claim Deduct Income-tax Super-Tax - V s Less abatement on Rs. . . . . . . . .J Deductions on account of Advances and Recoveries as detailed below :— Advance of pay ....... ■ House rent ........ &gt; overdrawn ...... Net amount payable Monthly rate. Rs. 484-0 400-0 Amount. Rs. 968-0 300-0 17 1768-0 1768-0 (Net amount to be written in words)Rupees. One thousand aev^n hundred and sixty eirht enly. Please nav/to : ^ Please pa Date tuc March, — 19 48. » To be entered by drawing officer and checked in the Accountant General's Office.(Reverse.) m DIRECTIONS FOR NOTE. 1. A pay bill may be presented at a district treasury two days before the last working day of the month by the labour of which the pay is earned ; but see rule 217. 2. A pay bill may, if desired, be enfaced for payment to a Banker or Agent and submitted for collection through such Banker or Agent; this will obviate the necessity of the Government servant's attendance in person or by messenger, as payment may then be made direct to the Banker or Agent. 3. The period for which a subscription to a Fund is due should be specified when it differs from the period for which pay is drawn. 4. In the case of Government servants entitled to Sterling Overseas Pay, fund deductions are based on the Rupee Pay plus the rupee equivalent of the Sterling Overseas Pay. Note 1.—Treasury Officers should see that all compulsory deductions including those for Indian Civil Service Provident Fund are duly made and that the schedules showing particulars of Fund deductions, are attached to the pay bills. _ Note 2.—Subscribers to the Sterling Branch of a Provident Fund should note on the bill and in th« Fund Schedule attached to the bill that the recoverieil relate to the Sterling Branch. ■ MGIPC—SI—23(Aadit)MFP—(186l6/M.2l28)—10-4-43—2,00,000.If f-1- « PAY BILL (FOE PAYMENT AT TREASURIES). C Treasury Rule 249 (1).] (Obverse.) Note .—Government accepts no responsibility for any fraud or misappropriation in respect of money, cheques or drafts made over to a messenger. Xarne of Gazetted Government Servant Mr. R• ? r C. Andrew, District. Bahrain Audit No. 35-External Head of Account.* Affairs.. Charges «n account cf DixxLoiiatic and Consular Services in Iran, C.l. P^y of Officers. C.?, Allowances, Honoraria etc. Voucher No. ' of I list of period frorc 4th to Slst Dacewber, 1947. Received for the 19 ^ adrance of salary as Under Secretary to tha Political 1 yXKijEiKXXEXXXr Resident in the Persian 0\;lf froig 4 to— —| 51-12-47. Hj advance tf Toreiggi Service Allowance fror ^9tii to 31st De cewbar. 194 7. • ■ Gross claim Less Fund Deductions as follows (Separate Scheduies attached) I. C. S. Provident Fund .... Post Office Insurance Fund .... Uncovenanted Service Family Pension Fund . Bengal and Madras Service Family Pension Fund General Family Pension Fund Hindu Family Annuity Fund . Bengal Christian Family Pension Fund General Provident Fund ^ Family Pension Regulations Superior Services (India) Family Pension Fund Indian Military Widows* and Orphans' Fund Other Funds (with details) .... Net claim Dedmt Income-tax | Super-Tax V Less abatement on Rs. . . . . . . . .J Deductions on account of Advances and Recoveries as^detailed below :— Advance of pay ........ '1 House rent ........ V overdrawn ...... - J Net amount payable Monthly rate. Rs. 403-4 335-li Amount. Rs. 364 32 rv (Net amount to be written in words) Rupees -Thr ftfi -fa.undrcd. AjJld ililift t&gt;y annas ^4—Ki. Please pay t&lt;/- , SWW • Date ({ JLl * «l5- l^aroh f — Signatureesi§en^fri 6 fee^PersIan Gui^ ♦ To be entered by drawing officer and checked in the Accountant General's Office'r* v it T. R. 16 PAY BILL (FOR PAYMENT AT TREASURIES). C [Treasury Rule 249 (I).] • , - (Obverse.) Note . Government accepts no responsibility for any fraud or misappropriation in respect of money, cheques or drafts made over to a messenger. Name of Gazetted Government Servant Mr. R, ITc. Andrew, District. Head of Account.* Bahrain 35-Extornal Affairs.. Charges cn account cf Diplerratic and Consular Services in Iran. C.l. Pay of Officers, ^tuiieivo. C.?. Allowances, H®n®raria etc. period from 4th to Slst December, 1947. Received for 19 \r of salary as Under Secretary to tho Political -Rt^identr in the -Pornian 31-12-47. My advance of Forei^ Service Allowance fr^jr ^9thi t® 31 at De cem ber f 1947. / v_ Vouaher No. ' of I list of Amount. Gross claim Less Fund Deductions as follows (Separate Schedules attached) I. C. S. Provident Fund .... Post Office Insurance Fund .... Uncovenanted Service Family Pension Fund . Bengal and Madras Service Family Pension Fund General Family Pension Fund Hindu Family Annuity Fund . Bengal Christian Family Pension Fund General Provident Fund ICS 1 ' M ' g ■ Family Pension Regulations Superior Services (India) Family Pension Fund Indian Military Widows* and Orphans' Fund . Other Funds (with details) .... Net claim Deduct Income-tax Super-Tax Less abatement on Rs. . . . . . Deductions on account of Advances and Recoveries as^detailed below Advance of pay . . . ... House rent ........ overdrawn ...... Net amount payable 396-8 rv (Net amount to be written in words)Rupees Thrfte hnndr^H gnH n-in^.-hy gipfrt 0nly . Please pay t/. , Date March,— -^4Bv ♦ To be entered by drawing officer and cheeked in the Acoonntant General's Offic«'(Reverse.) DIRECTIONS FOR NOTE. 1. A pay bill may be presented at a district treasury two days before the last working day of the month by the labour of which the pay is earned ; but see rule 217. * ** 2. A pay bill may, if desired, be enfaced for payment to a Banker or Agent and submitted for collection through such Banker or Agent; this will obviate the necessity of the Government servant's attendance in person or by messenger, as payment may then be made direct to the Banker or Agent. 3. The period for which a subscription to a Fund is due should be specified when it differs from the period for which pay is drawn. 4. In the case of Government servants entitled to Sterling Overseas Pay, fund deductions are based on the Rupee Pay plus the rupee equivalent of the Sterling Overseas Pay. Xote 1.—Treasury Officers should see that all compulsory deductions including those, for Indian Civil Service Provident Fund are duly made and that the schedules showing particulars of Fund deductions, are attached to the pay bills. Xote 2.—Subscribers to the Sterling Branch of a Provident Fund should note on the bill and in the Fund Schedule attached to the bill that the recoreries relate to the Sterling Branch. MGIPC—=-81—23(Audit)MFP—(18616/M-2128)—10-4-43—2,00,000.IG Ho. 994-65/3. To PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY, B AriHA . 7th April, 1948. The Political Agent, Bahrain. kiMOIUKDUM. Reference correspondence resting with Re^i^ency 'iviemoranduiii No. 176-Try/7 dated 2nd , :'larch,r 1948. 2. A sum of Rs. 121/8/- on account of cost of-Ist 4 class passage with food from Kuwait to Bahrain for Mr. P.D. Stobart may please be paid to Messrs Gray Mackenzie &amp; Go. Ltd Bahrain, quo.ting item No. ,2 of their debit note No'.'BI/48/80 dated 'Srd March, 1948 uhder intimation to this office. Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Copy to*MeSsrs Gray Mackenzie &amp; Co. Ltd., Bahrain for information. fh-UrUU- -^iiLT 0 'N 0'//T7 -V64. i 10 To POLITICAL AGENCY BAHRAIN 13th Arpil, 1948, Messrs. Gray Mackenzie &amp; Co., Ltd., Bahrain Dear Sirs, Reference copy of Residency memorandum No.994-66/3 dated 7th April 1948, endorsed to you/ regarding payment of your bill No.BI/48/80 dated 3rd March 1948. 2. Mr. P.D. Stobart is now in Muscat and you may kindly obtain settlement of your bill through your Muscat office. Yours faithfully. for Political Agent, Bahrain. Copy to the Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident, Persian Gulf, Bahrain, reference his memo randum No.994-66/3 dated 7th April 1948.■ is: CERTIFICATE OF LilST PAYMENT Certified that Mr. P.D. Stobart, Additional Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain, ha-s been paid upto and for the 29th February 1948 @ 6% of his salary and Foreign Service Allowance per annum at rates given below. €&gt;% of salary @ £ 34/10 or Rs. 460/- p.m. 6% of F.S. Allnce @ £ 30 or Es4C0/- p.m. / / .1 10th April, 1948. for Political Agent, Bahrain :/ \ eic No./^OV- -1/64. POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN ELth April, 1948. Forwarded to the Political Agent, Muscat, with a xaciacyjc copy of Life Certificate form for the quarter ended 31st March 1948, giving details of eiaoluments drawn by Mr. P.D. Stobart, while at this Agency. nth April, 1948. for Political Agent, Bahrain &gt; Oj'n v Telegran From C«de (n: vK ' - Secretary of St«ite for Foreign iiffairs, London. T© - Political Resident, Bahrain. No. 11 Dated the 7th and received on the 8th April, 1943. as a result of Inspectors visit, following allowances approved for Foreign Service Officers in lieu of those previously authorised for 3tewart £1750, Jackson £876 plus £90 (tax^blj) language alio ance, Stobart £660, Andrews £660. Authority being sought for Johnson's allowance which will be notified soon. Hudson's allowance increased to £1100 total inplace of present allowances of £750 plus £90. All above increases effective froi day following arrival of individual oost except in case of J«cksan for whom effective date is April 1st, 1948, ? in view of cut. Despatch follov/s. = SliCHiSTAKY OF ST^TUI «. —- —&gt;2i C i^TIFICATE OF Li\ST PAYMiOT Certified that Mr. P.D. utob^rt, Additional Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain, has been paid upto and for the 29th February 1948 @ 6^ of his salary and Foreign Service Allowance per annun at rates given below. 6^ of salary @ £ 34/10 or Rs. 460/- p.m. 6^ of F.S.Allnce @ £ 30 or R5.400/- p.m. (Sd.) J.B.H. HUDSON 10th April 1948. for Political Agent, Bahrain. No. 1204-1/64. POLITICAL AGIiNCY BAHRAIN 11th April, 1948 Forwarded to the Political Agent, Muscat, with a copy of Life Certificate form for the quarter ended 31st March 1948, giving details of emoluments drawn by Mr. P.D. Stobart, while at this Agency. (Sd.) J.E.H. HUDSON 11th April 1948. ^'^for Political Agent, Bahrain. [Wj Copy forwarded for Information to the Secre tary to The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Banrain, with reference to his memorandum No. 239-Try.l3 dated 24th/27th April, 1948. M 28th April, 1948. for iKlcal Agent, Bahrain.■ H i r,. TIKICATK (ff L..6i:&gt;Am.HT Certified that Mr. R. ilcAndrew, Additional ^ Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain, has been paid - upto and for 31st March 1948, 6# for January and February and 6^ for llarch, against his salary and Foreign Service Allowance at following annual ratesi- Salary £ 606/- or 2s. 8066-11-0 p. a Foreign Sex^rice All.£660/- or Ks.8666-11-0 p»a 28th April, 1948. for Political Agent, Bahrain. ' ^ No./3^ -1/64. POLITICAL aUKNCY BAHRAIK April, 1948. Forwardod to the Political Agent, Ku ait. Mr. McAndrew , s Life Certificate for the quarter ended 31st March 1948 has already b en forwarded to Finance Department, Foreign Office, London. 2. Copy to the Secretary to kk* His Excellency the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain, for infomatlon. 28th April 1948. for Political Agent, Behraln.Fxtraxt of paragraphs 1 to 6 of letter No.l (XSO3/34(12/48) dated the 19th April, 1948, from the Forlegn o iice j Lor .ion 5 to the Persian Gulf Residencyj Bahrain, • «i . J I . ftsv f 1° to ^oriegn office telegram No.11 of 7th April, and state that revised Forlegn allowance in lieu of those previously notified are approved for the Foriegn Service Officers Mr serving the Persian Gulf as follows . lj r r. Stewart £ 1750 Mr. Jackson £ 876 plus £ 90( taxable) language allowance. Mr. Stobart £ 650 Mr. Andrew £ 650 2 Mr. Jackson s new allowance will be effective froni the 1st ^ pr i ?-, 19 f 8 ' those of yessrs. Stewart, wStobart and Andrew from the -'-y ~o_.LOw.inj their arrival at their posts. The allowances are subject o variation int the li^ht o' change? in tne rate of exchan-e and the cost of living index. 3 * 11he amount of Mr f Johnson^ forign allowance will be notified shortly. 1 . T ^ e a ^^owance8 of officers on temporary contract with the For^gn Ofiice will remain unchanged except in ^he case of Mr. Hudson whose present allowances of £ 750 plus r 90 (language allowance )are increased to £ 1100 (inclusivej. 6. All Fort^gn Service Officers, and Officers on Sterling contr- -acts with the Foriegn Office will be paid the balance of their^ BmoiHaiSi emclUErent? in this country on receipt of qw rterly Life Certificates Buont^ly advances may be drawn locally but should be restricted in total to (a; l/12th of Foriegn allowance plus 6% of gros? annual salary for each of r .he first two montas of each quarter and (b) 1/I2th of Foriepn allowance plus 5^ of gross annual salary for the third month. It is important that Life certificated ( a supply of which is enclosed), fully completed, should be submitted at the end of each quarter. 6 ' . ^ While acting Political Agent at Muscat, Mr Stobart should receive the higher foriegn alio-ance of the post, in accord'nee with 2 r i: S iS c ervice re S^tions Chapter II No.3 (6) (1) (b), at the rate of £875 per annum instead of £ 650 per annum. He should also receive subsistence allowance, reduced by one third if accomodation i^ provided. No. 1263-65/46. Copy forwarded to the PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY BAHRAIN, Dated the 10th Mav, 1948. Politiaal Agent, Bahrain, Political Agent, Kuweit, Political Agent, Muscat, above With li^e c rtificates as mentioned in para 5/» V 2fc No. 1619-1/54 To POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN 9 The 23 rd Mtiy 1948 The Political Agent, U u s cat * ^wlQP.AriDUiA &lt; J Reference your memorandum No«363-S/61 dated 11th Jay 1948. 2. iiessrs. Gray Mackenzie &amp; Company's bill for Bs.121/3/0, being cost of Mr. P.D. Stobart's passage from Kuwait to Bahrain, has not been paid by this office. Mi'. Stobart drew his travelling allowance for this journey on the 31st ularch 1948 under the Government of India rules. A sum of Rs.133/5/0 was paid to British Overseas Airways Corporation, for the air journey to Kuwait and the balance of his travelling allowance bill was paid to him by cheque along with his salary bill. No d«duc- tion was made for the steamer fare as no bill had been received from Messrs. Gray Mackenzie &amp; Company at the time. cA,c For Political Agent, Bahrain. NNR ^</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00025e_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1047</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00025e</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1047</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 1/54 Additional Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1948/1948</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-04-02T00:06:30</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (29 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in chronological order from the front to the rear of the file. Circled serial numbers (red for received correspondence; blue/black for issued correspondence) refer to entries in the notes at the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation system in use commences at 1 on the front cover, and continues through to 30 on the back cover. The sequence is written in pencil, and appears in the top right hand corner of the recto page of each folio. The following number does not appear in the sequence: 28. The following two folios need to be folded out slightly to be read: ff. 12, 14.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file relates to the service of holders of the post of Additional Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain. The papers, which consist of correspondence, telegrams, memoranda, certificates of last payment, and pay bills, cover the following topics: pay and allowances; and travel expenses.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Additional Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain</namePart></name></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00025e#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>