<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x00019a_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-05-24T08:11:37.402Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">E&amp;O. 6100/Vf. Iy&amp;a kccC (&gt; if* I ’ 4 r fl' October, 19A4 O.o. i)rAV /l^uwt^ Jtfi, Xd ho ' A3 You will remember that at the meeting at the India Office on ' 4th August the question was raised of the position of the protected Arab sheikdoms in the Persian Gulf in respect of cabotage (vide paragraph 3(9) of the minutes of the meeting)* This matter was, as promised, taken up with the Foreign Office and the Air Ministry and as a result the following phrase has been proposed for inclus ion in the definition in any international convention of the territories to which cabotage should apply: 'territories under the protection, jurisdiction or authority of the contracting parties' • 2* It has been carefully considered from the legal point of view whether, in order to safeguard the United Kingdoms cabotage rights in the Arab sheikdoms it would be better to rely on the term 'protectorate' as used in the existing Paris Air Convention or whether it would be safer to employ some new phrase* The distinction between a protectorate and a protected state is largely one which we ourselves have made for our own constitutional purposes, a protectorate being a territory which has not got a local sovoredgnbut which is at the same time not administered by us as an ordinary colony; whereas a protected state has its own native sovereign* In international law, however, there does not appear to be ary distinction between a protectorate and a protected state; indeed, the term 'protectorate' is mainly used with reference to what we should call a protected state* There is no doubt that the French teim 'protectorat' ’would cover a protected state* Therefore, unless it appeared on investigation that in practice protected states such as the Arab sheikdoms had not been regarded as coining within the term 'protectorate' for the purposes of the Paris Convention, it would bo sufficient to rely on this term as covering them and therefore, in any new convention, simply to repeat Sir Gurunnth Bewoor, C.I.E.,, I.C.S., /the Secretary to the Government of India, Department of Posts and Air*— A -A the phrasoology of the old ono» To adopt this course might enable the Arab sheikdoms to bo covered v/ithourt? the issue bo^^, actually raised. ' ... w 3* Nevertheless, our inclination, subject to the vie'ws of the Government of India, is that it is better to come into the open, as it is probable that the issue will bo raised in any event. It is conceivable that the Americans may object to a French _ reservation of cabotage rights in respect of Morocco, Tunis and some of the French territories in the Far East. It is by no means impossible that they may adopt a similar attitude in regard to British protected states under the aegis of the Colonial Office, such as Zanzibar and the Malay States, to say nothing of Dutch territories in a similar position in the Far East. Therefore, if the issue is likely to emerge in a wider field at tne forthcoming international conference, there 7/111 bo no particular. point in adhering to the term '’protectorate' if a better phraseology can be found. The fact that the term 'protectorate' does cover a protected State, as a matter of international law, does not, of course, mean that for the purposes of Treaty definition there may not be seme phrase which would be preferable. The term in common use in treaties to which His Majesty's Government is a party is 'territories under the protection (of the contracting parties)'. The Americans like to use the term 'jurisdiction' to refer to territories of theirs in a somewhat similar position to our protected states and the Dutch similarly tend to apply the term 'authority 4 '. It is with these considerations in mind that we put forward the phrase suggested in paragraph 1 above. 4* I am sending a ccpy of this letter to the Indian Agency- General, Washington. \!f ■'•ms SSMCEtWM V U 4 - ^ A p, 6 . JM 0.61£XV%4* ;ilr (Xmmath Ijewoor, C.I.3., X*0. ## j^orwtary to ttm '^rwamaent of Ixtiia, DopartsMBt Of Mis Mdl Air. 7*v You «ULX re&amp;MKabor that at the ting at the India offio* on 4th iu^uet the lueation aaa raiaod of the position of the protected rab aneikdone in the eraian Oislf in respect of cabotage (vide paragraph 3 (9) of the ?ainut©s of the ^eetiaj). thia Matter aa» 9 ae pra&amp;ised # taken up with the Boruign Offiee and the dr UinAstry and as a re volt the fdio log phrase has been proposed for iAoIneion in the definition territories to wiii.ch cabotage aiunUd apply? ^terrilories under the protection* Jurisdiction or authority of the ccmtrftcting partiee'** 2. Zt has been carefully ooneldored frcei the legal point of view whetlMr* in order to mfk&amp;mTi the united KlagiQ**a cabotage rights in the irab sbeikdoKe it would be better to in any Intemati^nal cxxw^nti m &lt;f ther»ly on tb» terra ’'pro+mtarptm* ns In the oadsting aria Air ftxmntion or •ibethw' it would be safer to m&amp;jloy som am &amp;msm. IHe distlnotiao between s protecrtorate eed a J(Pi%Nrted stats la largely one eiiish as ouraelyes ■ T... ^r etip own constituti nal pur^«me«^ a iiroteotaratc beio^ a territory haa not | got &amp; local soyersiga but ahich is at the ssaas tins not cdbdsiiatersd by us as an ordinary colony ^ whereas u protected state has its O'&amp;i imtire vuraiipt. in international however, thero loe^ not appear to be bdj distinction between a |srotectomte and a prot«ct«l state; \ laised, the teMn *pret«otQrat« ' r la mainly used eitb referesice to idiat jae should call a - px-otooted state, lliere is t*r doubt tluit the ^noh tirra proteotorat** cover a protected state, therefore, unless it bipeared on investigation that in practice protected states sash as the Arab sheUodm had not been regarded as couinr, -dthin the tern/fter *at« *i1i«r#rore f If the issue la likely to emerge in e wider field at the farther wing international ooni oreuoe, there will be no parUeular point In adhering to the team proteotorate* if a better phrf*aeolo©r oan b© found* Ihe fact that the term 'protectorate’* doee cover a proteoted state, as a matter of inteomatianal law, does not, of oonroe, mean that for the purposes of Treaty definition there any not be aoae phrase which would be preferable, '{bet ter ; in aceeien use in treatise to which Hi* Itejesty's Ooverenatst la a party is ’territories under the preteotlon (of the ocntzwMiting parties)'. *£110 fseriosm like to use the term juxifwiicrtxuii to refer to territories of theirs In a soaewhat aimllar pOBitioo to our proi&amp;oted states and' the Dutch stailarly tend to apply the term ^authority'. Zt Is with these oanaideratioas in mind that we put forward the phrase suggested in paragraph 42 Extract from The Constitution Administrat ion and La\,s of the ' ‘ The Protected States. Essentially distinct from Protectorates of the oolonial type are a number of protected States, chiefly in lioru o, and the lualay Peninsula. The essential characteristic of the Protectorate is that the Crown assumes and exereisoc tail sovereign authority, tiiough without annexing the territory. In the case of the protected States the sovereign outliority clongs to the sovereign of the State, and not ir&gt; a y sense to the British Crown, and the role of the latter is dc ivod from treaty arrangements with the States wracii do not confer ary sovereignty over them, but give powers and duties in respect either of both internal and external affairs, or th, latter aloost exclusively. Historical accident largely rx. lains the distinction between the two oases; in these eastern turritorios tliere was a longer tradition of governmental forms Tv doh presenter the possibility of preserving the existing State for , while the British Government was most anxious not to extend its responsibilities. In Africa, where such a policy \v Id have been willingly followed, it proved infractic&amp;ble of , inintenance in the long run owing to the inferiority of politiccl ^ v or^^anisation and capacity of those concerned*fr 4. Km (b) the PoliticeX gent la in the r same letter# statin, thnt he hfi» an aeeurame from the Ueneral Meneger of the California *mtoien standard II Co^uuny tiuit fooiistuffa ao Imported will be used only by the Company 1 a staff pereoimel in ' x rob la and that the company w!3H oom^ly with the re •uiremente of the Union Government. Gooaa imported by the Bahrein Petroleum Company on behalf of the C^GLifornla Arabian standard Oil compa?iy will be ao declared before export from the Union# and treatment r aa for .mpire %oo&amp;&amp; is not claimed for them. 5 . ?ho r;ecrotary of ;tute would be glad if# provided the High Commissioner ecee no objection# the Union Govesmnment could be informed at «H warty date that this letter from the Political gent at Bahrein to the Chief hcoal Kopx’eoentative of the Bahrein Petroleum Oomptmy will be produced In duo course to the Union authorities by Assays. Caltex ( Africa) Limited and that this letter# in go far as it deals with supplies imported into Bahrein by the Bahrein Petroleum Company for their own use# vma written after oonaultetion with the competent departments of His &amp;oJc ty** OoTerfr^nt in the United Kingdom and la accordingly endorsed by them. X am # sir# Tour most obedient Semrunt# P. A. CLUTTERBUCK.South Africa House, Trafalgar Square, London, W.G.2. SECRET. ^ir, 24th February, 1942. With reference to your letter WT.146/14 of the 20th February about enquiries recently made to the Union Authorities concerning the importation of supplies from South Africa by the Bahrein Petroleum Company for their own use and for transhipment to Saudi Arabia, for the use of the California /Arabian Standard Oil Company, I am directed by the High Commissioner to state for the information of &lt; M ‘ Mr, Secretary Attlee, that the Union .Government have been advised as requested in the last paragraph of the abovementioned letter, I am, etc., (Sgd.) F.J. du Toit. Secretary. Under-Secretary of State, Dominions Office, Downing Street, S.W.l.^T. 6^5/42. The U• 6 .o., Dominions office. From Political Resident in Persian Gulf Do. 439 of December 19th 1941. To ' »&gt; ho.17215 dated January 1 st 1942 . From ” ' lios. 183 and 184 dated February 3rd 1942. 0. £cr*\(Mj\. (g) DRAFT LETTiiR. 9 FEB 1942 S ir, I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to forward herewith a copy of the telegraphic correspondence noted in the margin, with the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf^ regarding the importation of supplies from the Union of South Africa by the Bahrain Petroleum Company, both for their own use on trie island of Bahrein and for transhipment to Saudi Arabia for the use of the California^ Arabian Standard Oil Company. 2. It will be seen that the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf has authorised the Political Agent at Bahrein to make a statement in writing to the Chief Local Representative of’ the Bahrain Petroleum Company in the terms/terms of his telegram fto. 184 and paragraph 3 of his telegram No, 183; and that it has been suggested that this statement should be confirmed to the Union Government through the Dominions Office, I am accordingly to request that, if Viscount Cranborne sees no oojection^ the necessary steps may be taken to advise the Union Government at an early date &lt; that a letter in these terms from the Political Agent at Bahrein to the Chief Local Representative of the Bahrein Petroleum Company will be produced in due course to the Union Authorities by Messrs. Caltex (Africa) Ltd; and to inform them that tha£letter, in so far as it deals with supplies imported into Bahrein by the Bahrein Petroleum Company for their own - -L U X use, was written after consultation with the competent Departments of H.m.G, and is accordingly endorsed by them. 3. a copy of this letter is being sent to the P.u. r&gt; The previous pep ers are at mXT 8295/41 between Flags A and B. Do you concur in the Draft? - b.i(.V All otted to External Pe ptc, 8^'' v gGYPHER Off TSL5GRA U , Fi'Cin Political Resident in the Persian G-ulf to Secretary of State for India* Dated Bushire* 15.00 licursp 3*2.42* Reed. 11.00 hours, 4th February # 1942. Bahrain is a British Protected State which is regarded for war purposes as part of British Empire;) and it may he taken that goods exported from Union of South Africa to Bahrain Petroleum Company will he used in furtherance of Empire's war* effox v A I am prepared to accept your assurance given in your letter that such supplies imported by you will he for.your own use at Bahrain and will not in any circumstances he re-exported from Bahrain without authority from Political Agent* KSCd. POL. r ’ Pt. 184. Addressed to- India Office copy by p Govt.of India# Political Agent* Bahrain* The Union authorities may he informed that INDIA OFHCEhe dLi* t - tL fv j 0 ~. ht ^ HjU ^ Please see LIr. Rumbold's note below. The letter which you had from the Petroleum Department yesterday suggests that it is true to say that the supplies would be used in furtherance of the Umpire * s war effort. I am not so sure that they would be used wholly in Bahrein and not re-exported; are not some of the goods landed in Bahrein transferred to the mainland for C.A.S.O.C.? But, having pointed out this difficulty to the Political Resident, we can perhaps leave him and the Political Agent to frame the best statement they con. May the revised draft issue, please? ' 3(- frii.DRAFT TELEGRAM. Secretary of State. Political pLesidcnt in the Persian Gulf, repeated to Government of India and Bahrein. Gopy Addressed to Political Resident in r Persian Gulf repeated to Government of India and Political Agent, Bahrein. Your telegram !7o. 439 December 19 th. I see no objection to Political Agent at^ Bahrain making statement in writing that Bahrein is a'^British protected^ state .umbo Id, which is / regarded for war purposes a,s part / ''fS / of the British Impire. But fact that f\ / s' s' Indian export licensing system does not ^ ^ s / . automatically treat Bahrein as British ^ ^ // ^ ^ territoiY r would ; Eeem to make it incorrect e/ l to add for the purpose of export pemits / s @ s s ^ in particular. I suggest that we should say instead that goods exported from the Union to Bahrein Petroleum Company would be used in furtherance of the Empire’s /war- 2 - / . ^ S Lx eu/X war effort. j'-. vfo-H.ld ; uu** 1 .,’^ 1 !! / / ' that such goods would not be re-exported, provided that in fact no / j S / S ' part of them is intended for transfer to mainland or elsewhere. ' / / / 2. if you agree that statement / on lines suggested above would serve the / r / / purpose, please instruct political Agent &lt;?/■ dSLUdsA according-^ and inform'me/so that I may * confirm statement to Union Government through ^Dominions Office.$ ^&gt;FILE COPY 6* : r b A i 8295 1941 Allotted to Bxfrernal I)epto_ Ku .21913» SECRET fo -Q R 0 Y P H B R Og T E L B G R .A .M Prom Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, to 3. of S„ for Indies Dated 'Bushira 13sl0 hrs» 19th Decsl941» Received 0.0%00 lirsj. 20td Dec# 1941* 439. Addressed to S. of S. for India repeate To^Oovto of India copy by post Political Agen„ Badrain. XXX Bahrain Petroleum Co* regularly import supplies from South Africa and Union Oovt* have asked Caltex ( Africa) Ltd Cape Town to produce a a letter from Political Agent Bahrain s tQt-i-nfe whether Bahrain does or does nct^fall within - British Commonwealth* Caltex ( Axnca) report that if negative reply (? is) given considerably delay will be experienced in obtaining export permits* 2, Whatever may be the exact status of Bahrain it for all practical purposes connecoed ^th the war regarded as part of the British Empire ^ c.f. para No. 3 Beckett's minute referred to in HM* to India Office lett er No* nf M nv 12th 1938^ Ma.v I authorise political Aieno §at^afn to statej.n writing &lt;? that) Bahrain is regarded for the purpose of war m seneral an export permits in particular as pait 01 the Brit , Commonwealth? It would I think Be as well ii H-w- Govt, could confirm this in direct communication with the Union Govt*Chas. Page &amp; C? U-? TELEPHONES Sloane 8151 (10 lines). TELEGRAM S: Inland: Paganini.Sowest,London’.' Foreign iPaganini.Lpndon' codes*. Marconi,Bentleys,Bentley's 2?? A.B.C.(5T*?&amp;6T?) Western-Union and all Standard Codes. The UND&amp;R SECRETARY ^ India Office, ^ ^Whitehall, LONDON . .T S. Diotcrows r- C.M.PACC . F. AITK F.L.F.LCNN ARO. W.L.A.LENN ARO. C VV UOVKCROVE . r m. &amp; -A- * A FERTS II pT jkl' t e7frw 1940^^4 PLEASE fatty fn TCm^P^T (Opposite CROSVENOR HOTEL) 24th Sept ember 1S4P Address ! “ LATCHETTS,' CHURCH ROAD, BURGESS HILL. SUSSEX, OF STATE FOR INDLIu BURGESS HILL hone: 2025 (4 Un«s) To! rams t ■ PAGANINI, EURGESS HILL* W.I. Sir, 3o^ Your Ref: P.Z. SlOS/dOp In reply to your letter of 17 th Instant, we beg to inform you that Duty on the parcel which arrived in May, as well as Duty on two previous shipments, was refunded to us by the Customs at about the end of July last. It would therefore appear that the Customs have admitted our contentions regarding the status of the territory of Dibai (Debai), and we thank you for the help you have given us in the matter. Yours faithfully, CHAS. PAGE &amp; CO.LT]indexed Dated the 7th August 1940 IuMjluU bvpM^t* You may remember that I sent you some correspondence which I had received from an Aden merchant of the name of Bazara regarding the import into England of Guan~o—from—tnu' Trucial Coast. I remember that you told^that Bazara’s Agents in England were being informed that for import purposes the Guano wouxd be considered a£ an Empire product and be duty free. I have received a letter from Bazara written from Aden on 4th July to the effect that duty has been charged and that apparently the product is to be considered as of Foreign origin. The Sultan got back from Bombay ten days or a fortnight before I arrived here. Ke is well and cheerful. I have not forgotten the photograph and as he has recently had some tahen in Bombay I will, a suitable opportunity occurring, ask him for one for the India Office. Muscat is much as usual but warmer and much more peaceful than your part of the world. Elease forgive me for worrying you aboit my Aden friend. If I have any more correspondence from him I will tell him to write officially to Prior. J.P. Gibson, Esquire India Office, London.CHAS. PAGE &amp; CO. LTD. telephone: BURGESS HILL 2025. telegrams: PAGANINI BURGESS HILL. “LATCHETTS”, CHURCH ROAD, BURGES SUSSEX MGr/jDL We thank you for your letter of the 28th instant, reference P.Z. 2892 /40^ appreciate your advice regarding Dihai in connection with Imperial Preferehce. Yours faChas. Page: &amp; C? L 1 '. 1 ? TELEPHONE : Sloane 8151 (10 lines). TELEGRAMS : Inland: Paganini.Sowest.London.' Foreign '. Paganini,London'.’ codes -. Marconi,Bentley’s,Bentleys A.B. C.(5T?&amp;6T?] Wester n-Un ion The Secretary for Thdia Office, lOTDOT.^.l. Dear Sir, We refer again to our letter of the 21st instant on the subject of merchandise originating at Dibai in the Persian Gulf being liable or not to Imperial Preference when imported into this country. Cur supplier, namely T.'essrs. Tohamed Bazara, Aden, has telegraphed on the subject to Captain T. T ^ickinbotham, who, until recently was the Civil Secretary at Aden and actually is HBM Consul at 1'uscat. It happens that this gentleman is on leave in England. Messrs. Bazara have asked him by cable to intervene in the matter. His London address is the Bast India Club, 16, St. lames Square. London. We understand that he is already in communication with you and the object of the present is to ask that you give consideration to his communication and further, that you should recognise his intervention in the matter.TELEGRAMS ACCEPTED FOR ALL PARTS OF THE WORLD. (except for the following European Countries: Belgium, Luxemburg, Danzig, Denmark, Esthonla, Finland. Germany, Holland, Latvia, Lithuania, Norway, Poland and Sweden) AND FOR SHIPS AT SEA, AT THE COMPANY’S BRANCHES:— L ON DON. — pj? O VINCES. CENTRAL TELEGRAPH STATION : (Always Open). TOWER CHAMBERS, MOORGATE, E.C.2. Telegraphic Address : “ Signally, Phone, LONDON.” Telephone Numbers : METropolitan{ &lt;{£ ^eS'ch of tele- grams only). Telex Number : METropoliUn 0133 (4 lines). BRANCH OFFICES :— Telephone Numbers. The Baltic Exchange, Bury Street, E.C.3 18, Old Broad Street, E.C.2 | 22, Leadenhall Street, E.C.3 I Cereal House, 58, Mark Lane, E.C.3 - METropolitan 6666 24, Royal Exchange, E.C.3 ... ... ... ... j The Fruit Exchange, Spitalflelds Market, E.l I Candlewick House, 116/126, Cannon Street, E.C.4/ Shorters Court, Throgmorton Street, E.C.2 ... LONdon Wall 4811 3-5, Charterhouse Street, E.C.l 3, Borough High Street, S.E.l Plectra House, Victoria Embankment, W.C.2 41 &amp; 42, Parliament Street, S.W.l Thos. Cook &amp; Son, Ltd., Main Office, 43, Berkeley Street, W.l Cumberland Hotel, Marble Arch, W.l ... 73, Regent Street, W.l 35, Southampton Street, Strand, W.C.2 Golden Cross House, Charing Cross, Strand, W.CJ ! Thames House, Millbanlt. .S.W.l The Adelphl, John Street, Strand, W.C.2 .., And the District Messenger Company's Offices. HOLborn HOP TEMple Bar WHItehall MAYfalr AMBassador REGent TEMple Bar WHItehall TEMpfeTiar 4755 0818 1353 2441 4587 1234 6244 1353 3696 7871 1353 Birmingham 3 : Lombard House, 142, Great Charles Street Bradford : 6 10, Broadway Dundee : 46 and 50, Bell Street Edinburgh : 42, George Street (rear block) Glasgow C.l : 40, Royal Exchange Square Hull: 76, Lowgate ... Leeds 1 : King Street Chambers, 52, Wellington Street Leith : 64, Constitution Street Liverpool 2 : India Buildings, Brunswick Street) ,. The Cotton Exchange ,, The Fruit Exchange , Manchester 2 : &lt; 55, Spring Gardens Newcastle: 31, Mosley Street „ Princes Buildings, 1, Queen Street [ Porthcurno (Cornwall) Sheffield 3 : 50, The Wicker Southampton: South Western Chambers, 1, Canute Road Southampton 66144 And at the Company’s Wireless Stations at Bodmin, Brentwood, Bridgwater, Dorchester, Ongar, Skegness, Somerton and Tetney. NORTHERN IRELAND— Imperial House, 9, Donegall Square East, Belfast ... Belfast 27438 ''I Telephone Numbers. Central 8321 Bradford 6007 Dundee 2108 Edinburgh 25068 City 7761 Central 35811 Leeds 21518 Leith 35787 Bank 5020 Central 3223 Newcastle 22321 St. Buryan 206 Sheffield 20283 BIRMINGHAM : Central Telex 7370. LEITH : Telex 36054. TELEX NUMBERS IN PROVINCES: LIVERPOOL: Bank Telex 4012. MANCHESTER: Central Telex 5800. NEWCASTLE : Telex 23033. SHEFFIELD : Telex 23040. It is recommended that telegrams be handed direct to the Company's Branches as above. Receipts are given gratis for the amount charged. Telegrams for this Company's system are also received at all Postal Telegraph Offices, but should be marked “ VIA IMPERIAL CABLE ” if intended for transmission by cable, or “VIA IMPERIAL WIRELESS ” if intended for transmission by wireless. This indication is not Charged for. TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESSES REGISTERED FREE OF COST. Books of Telegram Forms, Tariffs, Rules, etc., can be obtained at the Head Offices of the Company, or at any of the above-named Branches EIRE. (IRELAND). DUBLIN : 67, Middle Abbey Street (Enquiry Office only) Telephone No. : Dublin 44995. HEAD OFFICE OF THE COMPANY :-ELECTRA HOUSE, VICTORIA EMRAHKMENT, LONDON, W.C.2. Telegraphic Address: EMP1REGRAM ESTRAND. Telephone: TEMple Bar 1222.Chas. Page &amp; C? U. 1 ? TEUEPHONE : Si.OANE 815! (10 lines). • ^ ^ TELEGRAMS: Inland: Paganini.Sowest.London'.’ “ Foreign: Paganini,London' CODES: Marconi,Eentley’s.Bentlevs 2^*? A.B. C.(5T?&amp;6T?) Western-Un 10 N and allStandard Codes. FILE COPY -k* - a ammrm. ^ Ol«tCTO»3 C.M.PAOE . F. A IT K BN. F.L.F.LCNNARO. W L.A.LCNN ARC. C.W LO'/CORO VC . (Opposite GROSVENOR HOTEL) 21st ray, 194Q^ The Secretary of State for India, India Office. LOifl) 0IT.W.1 ♦ PLEASE MOTE — Reply to be sent to Temporary Address : “ LATCHETTS,” CHURCH ROAD, BURGESS HILL SUSSEX. Telephone: BURGESS HILL 2025 (4 Lines) Telegrams: M PAGANINI, BURGESS HILL' Dear Sir, We recentlyreceived in London a shipment of merchandise originating at Dibai in the Persian Gulf. The goods were accompanied by an Imperial Preference Certificate, but despite same, the customs authorities here are refusing to admit same to preferential duty contending that Dibai does not come within territo^ ex which imports are entitled to Imperial Preference. % Our shipper adamantly contends that Dibai comes under British Rule, being situated in TRTJCIAL ryAN and by treaty a British Protectorate under the Government of India. Pay we ask you th: e favour, without responsibility, to confirm or contradict our shipper f s atatement. With thanks in advance for your attention. 30 IJJ 0 VldNI OK Z j •J43&lt;1 'KM '“OBil 22MAY13Wo FILE COPY 7roi in the External .Iffairs Department To The Under Secretary of State for India, India Office, London* r^ Dated New Delhi, the o February 1940* Sir, I am directed to refer to the papers on the above subject forwarded to the India Office under cover of Secretary* s weekly letter No* 19-M., dated the 17th February 193S, and to enclose, for information, a copy 2* Memo* from do—No* 1579-10/13, dated 4* 12.1939, } marginally correspondence. 2 * It will be seen that the Political Agent, Kuwait, does not anticipate sny difficulty in countersigning certificates of origin issued by the Kuwait authorities; but as none of the articles exported from there (namely, pearls, skins, wool and fish oil) are subject to preferential duty, the extension of the preferential tariff to Kuwait is of no practical value. Of the only dates are subject to preferential duty. As, SUBJECT:- Inclusion of the Shaikhdoms of the Persian Gulf in the new Trade Agreement between the United Kingdom and India. 1 . Memo, to the Hon’ble the Political 'Resident in the Persian Gulf, No. F.258-N/39 dated 9*8*1939. J of the 5 3. Endorsement from the Central Board of Revenue, New Delhi, No*872-Cus*I/39, dated 16.1.1940* 5 { noted articles exported from 'Bahrain and the Trucial Coast REC». POL. DEPt. 15 FEB '940 INDIA OFFICE however • • • • •however, it is not possible to segregate locally grown dates from those imported from Saudi Arabia, and as exports to India are small, it has been decided that dates from the Arab littoral of the Persian Gulf should not be admitted to the preferential rate of duty* I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, for Secretary to the Government of India*^roni-- The Under oecretsry to the Urovernment of India in the external Affairs Department, To.-- The non’ble the Po Memorandum imo. F. 258-im/3^. L Dated oirnla, the 9th August 1939 inclusion of the ohaikhdoms of the Persian G-ulf in the nev/ Trade Agreement between the Uni tea kingdom and India. Heference Czovernment of India, external Affairs Department, Express letter Do. F. 775-N/36, dated the 10th June 1937. 2. *our copies of each of the documenits noted on the ) margin are 1. Notification by The Department oi Commerce No. 20.T(21)/39, dated the 17th June 1939. ) o j , ,, , ) forwarded for 2. indorsement by the Central board of Revenue, ) (J.ho. 872-Cus -1/39, dated the 28th June 1939. ) information. The bhaikhdoms of the P era fan ^SuIjjFhave 'been included in the new Trade Agreement between the United Kingdom ana India. Before, however, it can be agreed to admit the produce of the Shaikhdoms to preference, it is necessary that some satisfactory arrangements should be made for certify ing their origin. 3. it is requested therefore that this matter, which has already been discussed in paragraph 4 of the express letter under reference relating to the question of the s countersigning of certificate^ of origin may now kindly be examingd. in this connection the Government of India would be glad to know how the trade between the Shaikhdoms. and British India conducted and whether in that trade there is any segregation of the produce of the Shaikhdoms from that of the neighbouring territories. Sd/- C.A.G-.Savidge. Under Secretary to the Government of India.Copy of a memorandum ^o. 1579-10/13, dated the 4th December 1939, from the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian G-ul£, shpp i) to Ihe secretary to the liovernment Ox India, External A 9b/ ffairs Department, Kew Delhi inclusioi of Persian bulf hai a hdoms of the w Trade Agreement __ AFr between tKe^3JniTl3’ kingdom and India. Reference memorandum ^o. F-258-h/39, dated the 9th August 1939, from the Government of ^ndia in the External Affairs Department. 2. The only Shaikhdoms in the Persian Gulf area with which i am concerned are Bahrain, Kuwait and the Trucial Coast. 3. The Chief items of export are pearls and dates from the Trucial Coast, oil, pearls and dates from Bah rain and pearls, skins, wool and fish oil from Kuwait, ^either oil nor pearls are affected by the agreement. 4. The Political Agent, Kuwait, anticipates no difficulty in countersigning the certificates of origin issued by the Kuwait authorities. The Political Agent, Bahrain, points out that^it will be quite impossible for any authority counter signing the certificates of origin to segregate locally grown dates from those impor ted from Gaudi Arabia. However, dates from Bahrain and the Trucial Coast are exported to India in such small quantities that it is unnecessary to consider them. 5. Trade between the Bhaikhdoms of Bahrain, the Trucial Coast and Kuwait and British Pndia is conducted by means of sailing vessels and steamships. Copy, to;- i. The Political ^gent, Bahrain, with reference to his memorandum Do.C/73C-i.a/i dated the 15th November 1939. The Political Agent, Kuwait, with reference to his memorandum No. 664-27/38, dated the 18th November 1939. , 2.4448/39 UV E. &amp; 0. 4118/39 Secretary, Political (External) Department? You will see from the ^irst Schedule to these Rules that Bahrein, Koweit and the Trucial Coast Sheikhdoms are, for the purpose of goods imported into India, treated as part of the British Empire. (Sd) A.C.B.Symon, 18/7. Seen thanks. Quite right tool (Sd) J.P.G-ibson, 20/7.NOTIFICATION. © Tariffs. In exercise of the powers conferred hy suh-section (2) of section 3 of the Indian Tariff Act, 1934, (XXXII of 1934) and in supersession of the notification of the G-overnment of India in the Department of Gommerce, No. 780-T(ll), dated the 24th December, 1932, the Central Government is pleased to make the following Rules:- RULES !• These Rules may he called the United Kingdom - India Trade Agreement Rules, 1939. 2. These Rules apply to goods consigned from the following countries, namely:- (a) The United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland, and (b) The Colonies, British Protectorates, and territories under the British Mandate specified in the First Schedule. In these Rules - (a) 'Act' means the Indian Tariff Act, 1934 (XXXII of 1934); (b) ’’British Colony” means any country specified in the First Schedule; (c) ’’expenditure on material” means the cost to the manufacturer of the mateial at the factory or works, including containers but excluding royalties; (d) ’’factory or v/orks cost” means the cost of production to the manufacturer at the factory or works and shall include the value of containers and other forms of interior packing ordinarily sold with the article when it is sold retail, but shall not include the manufacturer *3/♦manufacturer^ or exporter 1 s profit or the cost of exterior packing, carriage to port and other charges incidental to the export of the article subsequent to its manufacture; and (e) ’’United Kindgom” means the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland.22/ FIRST SCHEDULE. (See rules 2 ( 11 ) and 3(‘b). ) LIST OF BRITISH COLONIES. East Africa* 1. Kenya, Uganda Protectorate, and the Mandated Territory of Tanganyika. 2. Northern Rhodesia. 3* Nyasaland Protectorate. U* Somaliland Protectorate. 3* Zanzibar Protectorate. South Africa , (including St. Helena). 6 . Basutoland. 7. Bechuanaland Protectorate. 8 . Swaziland. 9* St. Helena. V/est Africa. 10. Gambia. 11. Gold Coast. 12. Togoland under British Mandate. 13« Nigeria. 1U- The Cameroons under British Mandate. 13. Sierra Leone. Eastern and Far Eastern . 16. Arab Littoral of the Persian Gulf (i.e. Bahrein, Kuwait and the Trucial Shaikhdoms). 1?. Ceylon. 18. Hong Kong. 19* Malaya (i.e., the Straits Settlements, the Federated Malay States and the Unfederated Malay States of Johore, Kedah, Kalantan, Perils and Trengganu). 20 . Mauritius. 21. North Borneo.a 2 22. Sarawak. 23. Seychelles. Mediterrane an. 24* Cyprus. 25 . Gibraltar. 26. Malta. Pacific. 27 British Solomon Islands Protectorate. 28. Fiji. 29 . Gilbert and Ellice Islands. 30. Tonga. 31* New Hebrides (Condominium). West Indian (including the Falkland Islands. 32. Bahamas. 33« Barbados. 34. Bermuda. 35* British Guiana. 36. British Honduras. 37* Jamaica. 38. Cayman Islands. 39* Turks and Caicos Islands. 40. Leeward Islands, i.e. Antigua, Dominica, Montserrat, St.Christopher-Nevis, and the Virgin Islands. 41. Trinidad and Tobago. 42. Windward Islands, i.e., Grenada, St. Lucia and St. Vincent. 43 Falkland IslandsV Any reply to this Letter *' QhnnlH Qrlrlrooco/^ • and not to any particular individual. The following number should be quoted: No. ...246*16/0!* FcaL^i to comply with these diru ns may involve delay. 938 -ettSTOM-nousE, LOWER THAMES STREET, LONDON. E C.3. 20th December, 1938 I am directed by the Board ol' Customs and hxcise to refer to your letter of the 31st October, 1938, reference rZ 7280/38 regarding an importation of a silver condiment set despatched from Bahrein by . C. Kennard-Poulkes and to inform you that it has been ascertained from the officer who opened the package that no specific claim to Preference was made as required by the regulations governing the grant of Imperial Preference. In this instance the responsible Officer knowing that similar ware is made in Iraq assumed that the goods in question were of Iraqian origin and accordingly duty was charged. however, in view of the facts now revealed in the correspondence with hr. C. Kinnard-Poulkes, the Commissioners^ !lf ' 1 * Gonmiis si oners have directed that the duty charged shall be repaid. I am, Sir, lour obedient Servant, The Under Secretary of state for India, Political Department, India Office, 5 . . 1 •I Awali, BAHREIN. P.G. October 17, 1938. Dear Sir: ' Herewith I enclose a letter received from the Commissioners of Customs &amp; Excise which was in reply to my letter enquiring why the duty charged on a silver condiment set was so high. It is apparent from their reply that goods made in Bahrein - as these most certainly were - are erroneously designated to be products of Iraq. As you are fully aware,this Island is an independent sheikhdom in its own exclusive right, and a British Political Agent is resident here. taken place with the Iranians, I feel confident you will agree that such a mistatement as is contained in the attached letter might have a serious political significance here! any preferential consideration in the matter of Customs &amp; Excise, I think you will agree that Bahrein should be quoted independently and not associated with Iraq in any way. In view of the repeated controversies that have Even if this British Protectorate is not given I await your observations with keen interest! Yours faithfully,Any reply to this Letter should be addressed : “ Tiie Secretary, Custom House, London, E.C.3.” and not to any particular individual. The following number should be quoted: No. ...246416/38 Failure to comply with these dirpifd^ns may involve delay. (55: JH CUSTOM HOUSE, LOWER THAMES STREET. LONDON. E.C.T Sir, I 11 reply to your letter of tne 15tii ultimo regarding a parcel sent to this country, I am directed by tne Commissioners of Customs and Hxcise to inform you tdat the Customs charge of ^s. on the parcel in question represented uuty at the rate of 30*’ of the declared value ox the gilvers xiths 1 .v^res (products ox' Iraq) contained therein vis. 3os. Od. The additional 6 d was a lost Office fee for Customs Clearance and it appears that the charges were correctly raised. I am to add that comprehensive particulars of import duties (full and preferential) together with lists of goods exempted therefrom are contained in the Customs and Excise Tariff, a copy of which mey be obtainedB With the compliments of the Under- . Secretary of State for the Colonies. ;tG0. POL. Dt?T. Colonial Office, ^ SEP 1938 Downing Street. ^ , ND | A OFFICE FT • 1• 4 . 15806/SMR/W f / ■ ' 4 \ / vy ^ 2611|£ 5 ^p«JLbep,19S8, Dear Belth, I enclore for Foreign Office concurrence the draft of a telegran which we auggeet night be sent to the Anbaesador and the Trade Delegation at Washington regarding Schedule V to the United Kingdom-United States Trade Agreenent 9 with special reference to the i Falkland Islands and Tonga. If you agree I think that a telegrari on the linee of thf* draft should go to 1! ashington in eptte of the fact that they have already taken action as reported in thsir telegran No.554. In the revised version of Article 1 which we now propose, after consulting Bushe, we have, as you will see, somewhat altered the wording originally suggested by Beckett. The lominlone Office agree with the wording as now set out. I have also spoken to ^non of the Political Department of the India Office, and he says that—X. that he is catteried that the definition can be held SS2t eorep the places c f tt»e Irrelan oulf, which la what we went. I hare read cot the draft to Howell of the lioarG :f T Tnfi* who agroo«i t so far os they ar© ooncorno&lt;l t with the wording. I m mnSlng ooplss of this letter and its enclopurs to oyd- ih»Tinon f mow 11 ond r^non. Tours sincerely. (Signed) T. f. DAVIES,* W j/ * ff ; I ,0.. IC^O l di aft thlhokak BRITISH AMBABtiADOR VASHITWPW. Follovfin|{ for . Jibaaoador and t verton Be^inu* Your telcgran m&gt;.3B4« A furihar ntudy of vnrioua aapaotn of the Matter hae tiaUa it appoar that our projxjaala ragardir^ Schedule V in telegras 631 muat be revioed* For instance it la clear that if the British £X&gt;lonon XaXando and iioaaliland are onltted from uehedule V the ocncesalone offered in respect of then will also have to be omitted from schedule lll f and we px^aune tliat the Anericans might object to such emissions* uimilsrlyt ao long ae it is stated in the ^xahaiitie of IK t^e 5 that there in no present intention of introducing preferenueo in Aden and oibraltar* we ircjuld not wish those two Colonies to be deleted from Schedule V* Apart from the bolomon Island&amp; 9 i^mallland* ;ulen and aibrtiltar 9 all other parts of the Colonial }feplr* 9 with the exception of the Gilbert and glllee Xalands and at.Helena 9 (and BasutoliUKl 9 BecIwaniiliUKl i^rotcctorate and awaxilanu wiJLch have been excluded from the negotiations all along) have it direct Interest in being included within the scope of the Agx*eenont« It fellows that 9 if we retained Uohedule V in its present fom 9 and wars obliged to omit the Falkland Itilanda and Tonga, the only other plades which we could omit would be the Gilbert and Kllicf Xslonda and Bt*Helena* $o aixyone therefore who examined the agreement from the point of view of lu w it applied toto ihm Golonlea it would inroUiwtoly h i&gt;ear Unit thaao four tarritorioa hail alonw bean omitted and there night be PerilAmentary queBtione enU other erltioieais hardly leme embarreaeltig tium thoao envlaeged ee lively if e footnote were inserted; and, ee in the oaee of the footnote, the real reeaon for the onlaalon of theart terrltoriea w^uld probably leek out* In theee oirounetenoee we Udnk it deeiroDle* if the ^nerloane otill reiuae to include 9i&gt;ngn anil the Falkland I»lan a in uchedule V, to revert to the idee embodied in the earlier draft (Omj.7j of defining the Colonial impire rather than 11«ting each territory ^ncerned by nane in a echedule, %• te should be glad therefore if the following alternative vereion of Article X could be auggeated U the United htatee - ,&gt; ¥he terrltorlee to which this Agj^eement eitell apply are on the part of Hie Nfa^eety the King of Great Britain, Ireland and the Britlah Boailnlona beyond the beau, idtperor of India (hereinafter referred to aa Hit* Majeuty the Kintf}» Great Britain and ^forthcra Ireland, Hewfoundland, hritlah non aelf governing Colon!mi, Pmteotoratea and Protected btatea (except B»autoland, Bechuanaland Prt tectorate and ;&gt;waailai»4) and the Herniated Terri tori ea named in iChedule V annexed to this Agreement'• ached ale V would then e imply con el at of the Intst five territorlee lifted in it (namely the Oameroone, Paleatine, Tanganyika, Togolnnda '' J - Ariiia—J'ordan)• Certain consequential afiienuiaonta will be required in later articles f namely where, in Articleo XII,XV, and XVII, the words occur w the United Kingdom cf Great Britain ; nd Northern Irelaiid, Newfoundland or any of the territories named in schedule V*' the phrase should be substituted M the territories to which this Agreement applies on the part of His Majesty the King”. 3* Among other advantages which this proposal will have are the following — (a) it reverts in substance to the earlier draft t which oi*iginated from the Americans and therefore it ought to be acceptable to them* (b^ it makes a distinction in the clearest possible way between viandated territories and the other territories administered by the Colonial Office* (c) it renders it unnecessary to define the exact political status of the Falkland Islands and Tonga. In the unlikely event of the united Jtntes ever attempting to discriminate against these two places the matter would of course have to be taken up through diplomatic chajuiels, out in view of the remote trade connexions between them and the United Utatea it is unlikely that the United atates would have the means to dl &gt;criminate even if they wished to do so • 4. If the United atates still r efuae to include the Falkland Islands and Tonga in achedule V as at present constituted we trust that you will be able to induce them to agree to tiiia alternative proposal. (In any case the proposals made in telegram No.631 would require substantial modifications as indicated in paragraph 1 above).P.Z.2444/38 INDIA OFFICE WHITEHALL, S.W.l 12th April, 1938 Dear Sir Malcolm, I am sorry that it has taken so long to furnish a reply to your letter of the 28th October to Tomkins regarding the submission of estimates for Bahrein under the Drug Limitation Convention of 1931. We agree that, since exports to Bahrein are being reported to the Central Opium Board, the inclusion of estimates for Bahrein in the Annual Statement issued by the Supervisory Body cannot be avoided. As Turner said in his letter of 25th May, 1936, Bahrein cannot be treated as part of India for this purpose, nor do we think it can be included in any other country’s estimates. A separate entry is therefore necessary, and on the whole we think that Bahrein might be shov/n in the list among British Dependencies, Protectorates, Colonies, etc. The Foreign Office concur. As regards your further point, it is true that the action of the Central Opium Board in sending forms to the Political Agent was not consistent with the procedure indicated in Turner’s letter, but since it was the British representative and not the Ruler or the local Government that was addressed we think that the position is sufficiently safeguarded and that we need raise no objection to the procedure adopted on that occasion by the Central Board. As a result, however, of the inclusion of Bahrein in the list of British Dependencies etc. it would no Sir Malcolm Delevingne, KCB., KCVO., 20, FitzGeorge Avenue, West Kensington, W.14.longer be appropriate for the Board to apply direct to any authority in Bahrein for a statement of estimated drug requirements. They ought instead to apply to the Home Office who would furnish the estimate to the Board after obtaining the necessary particulars through the India Office. Yours sincerely, (Sd. ) W.D. CROFT.' * P.Z.2444/38. COPY TT\1 INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL, S.W.l. 12th April, 1938. Dear Coles, Please refer to Tomkins* letter No. E.&amp; 0. 3611/36 of the 4th June, 1936. The question of drug estimates for Bahrein has come up again, and I enclose for your / / information a copy of a letter from Sir Malcolm Delevingne / and of our reply, which is the result of consultation with the Foreign Office. You will see from the last sentence of our reply that the Central Opium Board should in future apply to the Home Office for estimates for Bahrein, with which the Political (External) Department of this Office will furnish you. Yours sincerely, (Sd.) W.D. CROFT. Major W.H. Coles, D.S.O., Home Office, S.W.l.Minute Paper. p.s. 2444/38. Department. r\ Sir T&gt; Fowle , We are still awaiting an ansv/er from you to our letter of 29th January, below. Would you like to answer it now? (Sd.) J.P. GIBSON. 2. 4. Mr. Gibson . I think I answered your letter just before leaving Bushire. Anyhow I agree with the reply proposed in para. 2 of your letter. (Sd.) T. FOWLE. 5.4. Secretary. E.&amp; 0. Department . We are at last able to advise the nature of the reply to be sent to Sir Malcolm Delevingne^ letter of 28th October, viz. in the terms of the draft at f C f • (Sd.) J.P. GIBSON. 8.4.P.2.2444/38 D.O. No. 492/19/244. BRITISH RESIDENCY AND CONSULATE GENERAL, BUSHIRE. Dated the 16th March, 1938. My dear Walton, Would you please refer to your demi-official letter No. P.Z.312/38, dated the 29th January, 1938, regarding the submission of estimates for Bahrain under the Drug Limitation Convention of 1931? 2. For the present purpose, I see no objection to Bahrain being shown in the Annual statement among British Dependencies, Protectorates, Colonies, etc., and, therefore, concur in the terms of your enclosed draft. 3. I am sending a copy of this letter, and of your letter under reference, to Weightman with the request that he should in future act as now arranged. Yours sincerely, (Sd. ) T.C. FOWLE. J.C. Walton, Esquire, CB. , MC. , The India Office, London.In any further communication on this subject, wlease quote * Nc. £Tl 0 (, 0 / and address —not to any person by name, bqt to— “The U^^p^cretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. 1. CT* THE Under-Secretary of State for J^reigir'ltffidl'S ‘ presents his rs compliments to ^ transmits herewith cop Foreign Office, , 193 /. and, by direction of the Sec of the under-mentioned paper. Sety 4 t Xtc*. f A ^ . Secretary of State, |a A Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. cX-2~ . l a $ mar 1938 E.:CLGbU,.E AIR MAIL letter ffo. /3 d. ' v; POLITICAL AND FRSN Similar letter sent to 14—6130 10950 ( 2 ) G*»S 1060/13/91 FOH&amp;IQH OFFIGI, 22nd ilarch, 1938• Sir, I ara directed by Viscount Halifax to refer to your Confidential letter Ho. Pe.60 of the 23rd February in regard to the status of the Bahrein islands and to inform you in reply that the interpretation of the manufacturing agreements referred to in your letter is not a matter on which His Lordship can advise you. 2. I am to add that the statue of the islands is correctly described in paragraph 6 of your letter, that is to say, the islands are a British Protected btate enjoying Imperial Preference for the purpose of Section 21 of the Import Duties Act of 1932. The Sheikh of Bahrein is an independent Ruler in Treaty relations with His Majesty’s Government who conduct his foreign relations and exercise jurisdiction over foreigners in his territory. Your obedient Servant. I am Sir, The General Secret....,, Federation of British Industrie® (Sd ) K J. EOWKER 21, Tothill streetCOPY P (E 1060/13/91) J VEmftA'rioH op British H'IDUstriss. ■ i. _ / *; •) f ^ 2 / r £§ 1 , :tothill strset, Reference No: Pe.60. COiriDjaiTIAL. ^LONDON, S.'H. 1. 23rd February, 1938. Dear Sir We snould be grateful if you could give us some guidance regarding an enquiry which we nave received from one of our member firms, Turner Brothers’ Asbestos-Cement Company, Trafford Park, Manchester. processes is one for the production of Asbestos-Cement Pressure Pipes, which is licensed to them by the Italian originators for the British Smpire. Other parts of the world are, we understand, allotted to another manufacturer in 'Ireland, Gibraltar, Malta, Aden, Bahrein Island, Northern 'Borneo, Sarawak and Brunei, India, Burma, Ceylon, Cyprus, 'Hong Kong, Malay States, Straits Settlements, Wei-Hai-Wei, '^.nglo-Egyptian Sudan, Ascension, Basutoland, Union of South 'Africa, Gambia, Gold Coast, Kenya Colony and Protectorate, 'Mauritius, Nigeria, Nyasaland, Rhodesia, St. Helena, 'Seychelles, Sierra Leone, British Somaliland, Swaziland, 'Uganda, Sudan, Zanzibar Protectorate, The Bermudas, British 'Guiana, British Honduras, British West India Islands, 'Falkland Islands, Newfoundland and Labrador, New Zealand, 'Fiji Islands, British Solomon Islands, New Hebrides, Gilbert, 'Nawin and Tongan Islands and all other places forming part of 'British and Crown Colonies qnd Dominions other than Canada 'and Australia'. Canada and Australia were presumably excluded by consent for some special reason. They inform us that amongst their manufacturing Belgium. When the Manufacturing Agreements were drawn up, the L hLr** » term 'British Empire' was defined by the following list of ^ •% territories:- 'Great Britain, Northern Ireland, Free State of This firm has recently tendered for a contract for the supply/ His Majesty’s Under Secretary of State Foreign Office, London, S.W. 1./ /wmA &lt;V9&lt;U0 /ti* Cut* fc* rtwO ♦wv/t ^ 44 f* U&gt;. ^ supply of such pipes to an oil-producing Company estadlisHed in the Bahrein Islands, and were greatly surprised to find that both Italian and Belgian licensees under the original Patent were quoting. They naturally objected, and asked for withdrawal of their tenders under the terms of the Agreement. We understand that the other firms concerned, on the position being pointed out to them, agreed to withdraw, but that one of them said that they had no idea that the Bahrein Islands were British. The matter has been adjusted so far as this particular enquiry is concerned, and in any case, if difficulty should arise lai^er, Turner Brothers 1 Asbestos-Cement Company inform us that they would prefer to settle it amicably by reasonable discussion and would not contemplate resorting to law, but as they think one of the other firms concerned might in the future raise the question of whether the Bahrein Islands ought to be included in their territory, they desire to know whether they are in fact part of the Empire. As far as we can discover, these Islands could not, technically speaking, be described as Britisn territory, but the position is rauher obscure, because we understand that they are a British Protected State, and enjoy Imperial Preference, also that the ruling Sheikh is in Treaty relations with His Majesty 1 s Government, and with the Government of India, and that although he is an independent sovereign within his own domains, the Islands* external affairs are conducted through His Majesty’s Government. Furthermore, the Bahrein Islands are, in a standard work of reference, the Statesman’s Year Book, included under * Che British Empire Section. The point on which Turner Brothers’ Asbestos-Cement Company ask our opinion is whether the Bahrein Islands are in the Empire, or sufficiently near to that status as reasonably/reasonably to justify inclusion in the list of territories quoted at the beginning of this letter. They wish for advice on this point so that if the question is raised at later date they might, according to the advice given, argue that they should remain part of their territory, or agree to their removal from the list. The writer recently called at the Foreign Office, and was given some helpful information regarding the status of the Islands by Mr. Etherington-Smith of the Eastern Department wno suggested that if a more definite opinion were required, it would be better to lay the matter before you in writing; we should be very much obliged if you feel aoie to give us any advice which would be helpful to the above-mentioned firm. They ask that the particulars given in this letter should be regarded as confidential, as the details of their working arrangements under this particular Patent are not public property. Yours faithfully, (Sgd.) A. W. COWS. SUKOPKAN AND ESAE 3AST DEPARTMENT.D.O. I!o.2502/10/13. I 1 y dear Hay, ft' Please refer to Government of India Express UMioo/y Letter No.P. 775-N/36, dated the lOtii June, 1937. the Persian Gulf have been included in the new Trade iigreement between the United Kingdom and India, v/hich was to have been concluded last July, in the form suggested in paragraph 3 of your letter under reference. Sir Trenchard willt ake up the question of the countersign ing of Certificates of Origin with the Political .Agents with particular reference to the possibility of the import of commodities into States enjoying preference for re-export. 2 . Sir Trenchard presumes that the Shaikhdoms of 3. If you will confim that the entry has been made Yours sincerely, Sd/- T. Hickinbotham Major Y/.R. Hay^, C.I. h, Deputy Secretary to the Government of India, External Affairs Department, 0 ^ £. V'O. enclosure in HCIA FOREiGN SECRETARY’S letter No. 1 9 Dated i 7 FEl Received 7 Mm.External Affairs Department D.0.No,D.97-N/36. New Delhi, The ^ February 1938. question of the inclusion of the cihaiKhdomB of the Persian Gulf in the new Trade A^ree.ient between the United Kingdom and India. X* With reference to your demi-official letter No.2502/10/13, dated the 22nd December 1937, I am desired to say tiiat the Indo-Bfitiah Trade Negotiations which commenced in June 19^7 were suspended in October and have now been resumed in London. There is every prospect of their early termination, but the position of the Colonies witn regard to the new Agreement lias still not been finally settled. 2. In the circumstances, the matter discussed in paragraph 4 of our express letter No.F.775-N/36, dated the 10th June 1937, need not be examined further until the position becomes clearer. Yours sincerely 3d/- W.R. Hay. Captain T. Hickinbothara, Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in tiie 'i * p )REiGN secretary's -}ici. r jsurE Dated i7 FEl | Received 7V Telephone: Victoria iWW. 8155. Telegrams : Minindust, Sowkst, London. Reference No.:-P.D. 21/X4 W reply to this letter should be sed to the Director. Petroleum Dept. January, 1938 Dear i, ✓ I enclose copy of a letter which we have received from the High Commissioner for New Zealand on the subject of marketing Bahrein oil in the Dominion, together with a draft of the reply it is proposed to send. Have you any observations on the latter? Yours sincerely, Whitehall M. J. Clauson, India Office, S.W. 1 3 U JAN 1938 INDIA OFFICE BSCOPY. DOMINION OF NEW ZEALAND. New Zealand Government Offices, 415, Strand, London, W.C. 2. /S M/W 1451/Enq. 12th j anuary&gt; 1938 . For the attention of Mr. F. C. Starling . Sir, I am directed by the High Commissioner to inform you that the Department of Industries and Commerce in Wellington, New Zealand, have received advice from the Associated Motorists ^etrol Co. Ltd., of that city that future supplies of motor spirit to be marketed by the concern will be of British origin, in that they will come from the Island of Bahrein in the Persian Gulf. From enquiries made at this end it would appear that the products of the Bahrein Petrol Co. will be marketed through the organisation of the Texas Oil Corporation, and for this purpose a new Company called the Californian Texas Oil Co. has been formed. It is also understood that the Bahrein Oil Co. is owned entirely by the Standard Oil Co., of California and Texas Oil Corporation and that the shareholders of these concerns are all American. Hence it would appear to this Department that whatever the product may be, the interest is entirely American. In order that he may advise his Government of the true position, the High Commissioner will be glad to have any information you may be able to furnish him on any of the points named, and in particular whether Bahrein Island is British-owned, controlled, protected, or if not, what is its status internationally. With thanks in advance for any assistance you may be able to render. f I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, F. T. SANDFORD. Official Secretary.I P.D. 21/14 DRAFT. CONFIDENTIAL. Sir I am directed by the Secretary for Mines to refer to your letter of 12th January (ref: I/S M/W 1451/Enq.) regarding the marketing of Bahrein oil products by the Associated Motorists Petrol Company, Ltd., in New Zealand and to say that, from the information available in the Department, the position with regard to the Bahrein Petroleum Company would appear to be as follows: D&gt;, The Company was incorporated in Canada in 1929, the whole of the share capital being subscribed by the Standard Oil Company of California. In 1936 an agreement was reached between the Standard Oil Company and the Texas Corporation whereby the latter Company obtained a half interest in the Bahrein Petroleum Company* At the same time arrangements were made for the Texas Corporation to market the output of the Standard Oil Company production east of Suez and also the output from the refinery at Bahrein. For this purpose a marketing The marketing company of the Bahrein Petroleum Company is therefore registered in a British Colony, but the share capital is held jointly by the Standard Oil Company and the Texas Corporation, both of which are American concerns. The Official Secretary, Dominion of New Zealand, New Zealand Government Offices, 415, Strand, W.C. 2. organisation called The Californian Texas Oil Company Limited was organised in the Bahamas. Texas Oilr f - 2 - h.ytyy 3 The Bahrein Islands form an independent sheikdom and are not a British Possession or Protectorate. There are, however, special Treaty arrangements with Bahrein and certain other sheikdoms in the Persian Gulf as a result of which they are regarded as territories under His Majesty f s protection” and for the purposes of Section 21 of the Imports Duties Act, 1932, Bahrein products imported into the United Kingdom are regarded as eligible to receive the benefit of the preferential tariff duties applied to Empire goods. As you are aware, there is no Empire preference in the United Kingdom for petroleum products. It might be mentioned for the confidential information of the High Commissioner that in 1937 the Bahrein Petroleum Company enquired semi-officially whether H.M. Government would have any objection to their marketing organisation applying to the Australian and New Zealand Government for a preference for Bahrein oils. The quantity of oil produced in the Empire is small and the seeking or granting of a preference on oil products generally has not been the policy of H.M. Government. The grant of a preference would adversely affect established British oil companies marketing non-Empire oil, and the Company were informed in confidence that the disadvantages which-3- might arise from any change of policy with regard to the granting of preference on oil products were likely to he greater than the advantages and that for these reasons H.M. Government, so far as they were concerned, would prefer that the question should not he pursued hy the Company. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant,r P» Z• 31S/38. S.W. 1. 29th January, 1938. / / / AIR MAIL . My dear Fowle, By the sea mail of 6 th January we sent you a copy of correspondence with the Foreign Office arising out of a letter from Sir Malcolm Delevingne regarding the submission of estimates for Bahrein under the Drug Limitation Convention of 1931. I now enclose a copy of the reply received from the Foreign Office to our letter of 31st December. An example of the Annual Statement of Estimates issued by the Supervisory Body is also enclosed for your information. In view of the latest letter from the Foreign Office we might perhaps, if you see no objection, agree that for the present purpose Bahrein might be shown in the Annual Statement among British Dependencies, Protectorates, Colonies, etc., and subject to your views we would propose to reply to Sir Malcolm’s letter of 28th October in the terms of the enclosed (revised) draft. If you concur, it will follow that the Political Agent should be told to submit any future estimates through us, and not direct to the Central Opium Board, since I understand that in the case of all British Dependencies, Colonies, Protectorates etc. the Board apply for estimates to the Home Office and do not correspond direct with the territory concerned. (Sd.) J. C. WALTON. The Hon’ble Lt. Col. Sir T.C.W. Fowle, K.C.I.E. , c.b.e. , His Britannic Majesty’s Consulate-General, Bushire.Dear Gibson, Seen, thank you. If Bahrain is to be shown among Br. dependencies, Protectorates etc. in future, there ought to be no longer any question of Geneva applying direct to Bahrain for estimates or of the Political Agent sending them direct to Geneva. The P.C.O. B. ought to apply to the H.O. for the estimates (really it should be the P.0., but by arrangement the H.O. do the work) and the H.O. would ask us (I presume it is we and not the P. 0 .) to get them. The Political Agent ought to send them to us (or ? the P.0.) and we send them to H.O. In writing to Powle it might be as well to suggest that if he concurs in the course proposed in your draft letter he should instruct the Political Agent to send estimates regularly in future direct to this office; you would then send them to the H.O. (Ind.) W.D.T. 19.1.(§&gt; Dear Tomkins, You might be interested - and depressed - to see the + slow course that this correspondence is pursuing# Walton now wishes to consult the Political Resident before comraitting himself# Can your Registry supply a copy of the Supervisory Body’s annual statement? It will help the Resident to understand what the fuss is about# Yours (Ind.) J.P.G. 18.1. The urgent label will seem ludicrous - its object is to help to get this letter out by this week’s sea mailP.Z. 313/1938 (P 90/90/87) Dear Gibson, Many thanks for your letter P.Z* 8283/37 of 31st December relating to the submission of drug estimates for Bahrein. 2. We quite agree that in the past certain considerations have led His Majesty f s Government to abstain from publicly giving undue emphasis to their views on the political status of Bahrein. V/e do not however feel that these considerations still apply in the same way as formerly. In particular, as regards the possibility of embarrassing criticism from Persia our views are as set out in Renders letter S 2463/2463/91 of 22nd May, 1936, to V/alton in connexion with the question of the status of the Trucial Sheikhdoms, and of Bahrein and Koweit, for the purposes of Section 21 of the Import Duties Act, 1932. In brief, we are prepared to face a possible Persian protest in this connexion with equanimity. 3. With regard to the attitude of such other countries as are ready at the present time to seize any stick with which to beat His Majesty*s Government, we admit that they may try to misrepresent the position, but we feel we must be prepared to face their possible criticism on this issue. Bahrein is a British Protected State for which it has been decided His Majesty’s Government must admit ultimate international responsibility. We therefore feel that the territory should appropriately appear in the annual Statement issued J.P. Gibson, Esq,2. by the Permanent Central Opium Board among the Dependencies, Protectorates, Colonies etc., of Great Britain. 4. V/e trust the foregoing will enable you to reply to Sir Malcolm Delevingne’s letter, of which you sent me a copy in your letter of 25th November. In the meantime we will go into the point raised in paragraph 4 of your letter under reference and give you.our further views later on. Yours sincerely, (Sd.) T.V. BRHNAN.P.Z.8283/37. * W4 s INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL, S.W.l. 31st December, 1937. Dear Brenan, V/ould you please refer to your letter of the 21st December (F.10103/10103/87) relating to the submission of drug estimates for Bahrain. It is true that for the purposes of the Import Duties Act Bahrain is treated as part of the British Empire, but this is merely for the purposes of that Act and results from the fact that in Section 21 of the Act the British Qnpire is defined as including territories under His Majesty’s protection. There are, however, considerations in favour of refraining wherever possible from any action that would describe publicly to the outside world the position of Bahrain as being part of the British Empire. If Bahrain is included among the ’’Dependencies, Protectorates, Colonies, etc.” of Great Britain in the annual Statement issued by the Supervisory Body is there not a risk that this might attract rather embarrassing criticism from Persia, or possibly other countries? You will remember in this connection the Political Resident’s telegram of 20th December (our No. P.Z. 8245/37) about the Bari broadcast of 14th December. The Italians no doubt would be only too pleased to misconstrue for their own purposes the inclusion of Bahrain in the ’’Dependencies, Protectorates, Colonies, etc.” of Great Britain. Perhaps you would let me rvnow whether, notwithstanding these considerations, you still think that Bahrain should be included in the present connection among the Dependencies, etc. of Great Britain. T.V. Brenan, Esq., O.B.E. , Foreign Office, S.W.l.There is a separate further point arising out of paragraph 4 of your letter on which there may perhaps be some misunderstanding. It seems to suggest that in the view of the Foreign Office international undertakings assumed by His Majesty’s Government, as in the various Geneva Conventions, must be held to apply to the Arab Sheikhdoms of the Persian Gulf unless they have been contracted out under a reservation clause, and that Bahrain is consequently bound by the Convention of 1931. We certainly could not agree to this, and as it is not a question which is raised by the present correspondence, it seems possible that there may be some misunderstanding. The action of the Permanent Central Opium Board in calling for estimates of drug requirements for Bahrain did not of course indicate that in the Board’s view Bahrain was a party to the Drug Limitation Convention of 1931. Article 2(3) of the Convention provides for such action in the case of ’’countries or territories to which this Convention does not apply”, and the action taken was in consequence of the export of drugs to Bahrain having been reported by the United Kingdom. Yours sincerely, (Sd.) J.P. GIBSON.P.Z. 8283/1937 * (P 10103/10103/87) Porei.^n Office, S.W.l. 21st December, 1937. Dear Gibson, We have been considering your letter P.Z.7216/37 of the 25th November, about the submission of drug estimates for Bahrain. 2. The point with which we are specifically concerned, is where precisely Bahrain should be included in the Supervisory Body’s tables. 3. At the 42nd Meeting of the Middle East (Official) Sub-Committee of the Committee of Imperial Defence on the 24th September, 1935, one of the recommendations of the Sub-Committee was 'that His Majesty’s Government must admit ultimate international responsibility for the affairs of the Trucial Coast, including Qatar'. It will also be remembered that as regards the application of customs duties in this country it was recently decided that Bahrain, Koweit, Sharjah and the other Sheikhdoms on the Trucial Coast of the Persian Gulf, shall be regarded as British Protected States within the meaning of the definition of the 'British Empire' for purposes of Imperial preference. In this connexion please see Colonial Office circular despatch No. 15281/36 of the 22nd October, 1936. 4. Our view therefore is that as Bahrain is a State under British protection and counted as part of the British Empire for purposes of Imperial preference, it should also be counted as a Protectorate for the purposes of Article 26 of the Narcotic Drugs Convention of 1931. It follows therefore that as Bahrain was never excluded from that Convention under that article, it should in our opinion figure in the tables among the British Dependencies, Protectorates, Colonies etc. J.P. Gibson, Esq.5. We trust you will agree. 6 . We have no observations to offer on the remainder of your draft letter to Sir Malcolm Delevingne. Yours sincerely, (Sd. ) T.V. BRjSNAN.INDIA OPFIC: \ P.2i. 5608/37 N V Uuc VHITEHALL, 37th August, 1937. Dear Sir, ^ill you fcindly refer to your letter ot the 7th August, A. 7/B, on the subject of British refined Products. Your liueuticne are net raainly for this Department to answer, but largely concern the Coioniai fllee and Board of Trade. After consultation, howerer, with these De .ertnenta, it is possible to answer the^ aa fol7.owa. Petroleum producta froa a refinery at Haifa (where in fact there ia no refinery at present) would not be eligible for Imperial Preference. adan is not in British territory but in Iran and products of a refinery there would of course not be eligible for Inperial Preference. ctaxi xaitiiu a anr bheikhdoms \there are at preeent no refineries in he letter ,heikhdomj) are regarder, as 'territories he shipping Manager* under, Vacuum Oil Company, Ltd., Caxton House, S. V. 1.under Hie Majesty’s protection* for preference mrposes* It ie regretted that there has been some delay in replying to your letter* Yours faithfully. (Sd.) M. J. OLAUSON.15281/37. Do-/;\..\c Street, S. ///, J' ^August, 1937. \w ^ pf I ani sorry lor the delay in replying to your letter P.Z.5170/37 of the 10th of August enclosing a questionnaire from the Vacuum Oil Company about Imperial preference for petroleum products. Coleman has answered all your queries in his letter to you of the 17th of August, and there is little for me to add. As he says, there is no refinery at Haifa at present, and even if there were one petroleum refined there would not he eligible for Imperial preference, which does not apply to Palestine products. The answers to the questions of the Vacuum Oil Company are therefore as follows Paragraph 1. fa) No. (b) No. (c) Yes. Paragraph 2. Yes. ^ M.J.CLACSON,ESQ. I. ' I confirm the assumption that oil produced within the ’’Empire 1 ' hut refined outside it could in no circumstances he eligible for preference.x BY APPOINTMENT JrttcTC.o. s TELEPHONE WHITEHALL 1010 (14 Lines) VACUUM Ott COMPANY LIMITED W‘ / ^ TELEGRAMS VACUUM • PHONE • LONDON CAXTON HOUSE - WESTMINSTER ■ LO N D O N - REFERENCE S ' W • I sf/aiih. India Office, WhitehaL 1, London, S.V7 # 1. Dear Sirs, 23rd August, BRITISH REFINED PRODUCTS. Attention of Mr. Clans on. / //^ ^ On the 7th instant, we wrote to you/in connection with the above, and shall be glad to know yo\Jy position to let us have the information as same is urgently required. ** UNLESS STATED OTHERWISE ALL OILS ARE QUOTED AND INVOICED PER UNIT GALLON OF 9 LBS. AND ALL QUOTATIONS ARE WITHOUT ENGAGEMENTreply to this letter should be addressed to the Director, Petroleum Dept. I ' Telephone: Victoria 9310. Telegrams: Mintndust, Sowest, London. f * PETROLEUM Dl K**f&gt; ■ ; ‘ARTMENT UC(&lt; Reference No.:-P.D. n -Department), / Dean Stanley Street, ' /f /f 5434'j r. 1 Millbank, London, S.W.l. /; August, 1937. Dear Clauson, pT 2^°]^ With reference to your official note of the 12th August (P.Z.5170/37) and enclosures on the subject of the Vacuum Oil Company’s enquiry about Imperial preference for oil products, I agree that the reply should he confined to a simple statement of the position as regards each country on the lines suggested in your letter of the 10th August to Eastwood. There is no refinery at Haifa at present. The first question is therefore a hypothetical one. The Vacuum Oil Company are an American Company and are manufacturers of lubricating oils in this country, and also market lubricating oils produced by the Socony-Vacuum Company in the U.S.A. This latter Company also market all refined products in various parts of the world. They will be aware generally of the conditions under which preferences are granted in certain of the Dominions and Colonies on lubricating oils of Empire origin. In Starling’s letter of the 12th June he set M. J. Clauson, Esq. , The India Office, Whitehall, S.W. 1.out our views on the question of preferences for petroleum products with particular reference to Bahrein oil (your reference P. 2992/37). Generally the criterion for deciding the origin of a refined oil product is the extent of the manufacturing processes to which it has been subjected in the country which exports it. The position is perhaps best illustrated by taking the case of this country and Australia. I enclose a copy of the Australian Preference Regulations from which you will see that to qualify for the preference refined oil products have to satisfy certain percentages of ’’British content”. Somewhat similar conditions apply in other Dominions and Colonies. In no case would Empire Preference apply to refined products produced from Empire crude refined in non-Empire countries, therefore, correct. S&gt; o — Yours sincerely,AUSTRALIAN PKEFEiiSEICE KEGULATIONS» (a) Goods wholly produced or manufactured in the U.K. from (1) materials wholly produced or manufactured in U.K. or Australia; ( 2 ) unmanufactured raw materials; or (3) manufactured raw materials, as determined by the Minister. NOTE ;- Manufactured raw materials could be used for the purpose of satisfying this condition only if in their treatment no process has been performed abroad which is a process commercially performed in the U.K. (b) Goods which are not in accordance with the preceding paragraph, wholly produced or manufactured in the U.K. in the manufacture or production of which not less than 75 per cent, of their factory or works cost consists of U.K. and/or Australian labour and material. (c) Goods of a class or kind not commercially produced or manufactured in Australia, provided that not less than 25 per cent, of their factory or works cost is represented by labour or material (l) of the U.K. or (2) of the U.K. or Australia. (d) Goods described at (c) with the substitution of 50 per cent. for 25 per cent, where the Minister of Customs is satisfied that such substitutes are desirable. The classes of goods not commercially manufactured in Australia are determined by the Minister and listed. NOTE ;- Pending a final decision on certain questions affecting the import duties on lubricating oils imported from the U.K. to Australia, the Australian Customs Department are prepared to accept lubricating oils made in the U.K. from 'topped* crude at preferential rates of duty, under paragraph (a) of the Australian Preference Regulations. /EAL 17.8.37P.Z.5170/37. India Office, t, fr(U' 'Z Whit ehall, S•W.1. h 10th August, 1937. My dear Christopher, With reference to your letter of the 5th August, No.15281/37, and previous correspondence, I enclose a copy of a letter dated 7th August from the London Office of the Vacuum Oil Company Limited about Imperial preference for petroleum products. The reason why we have received this letter is that the Department of Overseas Trade t elephoned the other day that they had been asked by the Vacuum Oil Company for a definition cf the phrase T, Trucial States' 1 , and I suggested that they should send us a letter on the subject. (There are oil negotiations in progress on the Trucial Coast at the present time, and we treat any oil enquiries about that area, particularly from companies which may be American, with suspicion at the moment). In the event the Company have sent us a questionnaire, which partly concerns your Office. I propose to reply that:- (a) The enquiry about Haifa has been passed on to your Office; (b) that Abadan is not in British territory, but is in Persia; (c) that the Bahrein Islands are not a British possession or protectorate, but are regarded as being covered by the words 'territories under His Majesty’s protection' for preference purposes, and (d) The Sheikhdoms on the Trucial Coast of the Persian Gulf are similarly regarded. Cristopher Eastwood, Esq., Colonial Office, S.W.l. i/2 . I suppose it is unnecessary to explain to the Company how far petroleum products are entitled to a preference in the Empire generally, as I imagine they know this already. As I understand the position, there is no preference for any petroleum products in this country, hut certain of the Colonies (such as Sierra Leone) give some sort of preference to British Empire petroleum products, which presumably apply in present circumstances automatically to Bahrein and Trucial Coast products. I also assume that the criterion for deciding whether a refined product comes from any particular area, is whether or not it has been refined in that area; that is to say, I assume that oil from Qatar or the Trucial Coast refined at Abadan in Persian territory, would not in any case be eligible for any Imperial preference. Can you confirm my assumptions on these points? In any case, do you concur in my proposed reply to the Vacuum Oil Company? I am sending a copy of this letter and enclosure to Coleman at the Petroleum Department. Yours ever, (Sgd.) Miles Clauson.UNLESS STATED OTHERWISE ALL OILS ARE QUOTED AND INVOICED PER UNIT GALLON OF 9 LBS. AND ALL QUOTATIONS ARE WITHOUT ENGAGEMENT V {BY APPOINTMENT r &gt; VACULTWOTL COMPANY LIMITED TBLBPHONB WHIV^ALL 1010 (14 LINES) TELEGRAMS VACUUM • PHONE • LONDON CAXTON HOUSE - WESTMINSTER REFERENCE A7/B. • LO N D O N S W • I 7th August, 1937* India Office, Whitehall, London S«W.l. BRITISH REFIN 5 D PRODUCTS* Attn. :.Ir» Clanson♦ Dear Sirs, We recently received from the Stationery Office Notice No.27. in connection with Imperial Preference but as same does not contain the information we require, are writing to enquire if petroleum products obtained from a Refinery situated at - a) Haifa in Palestine. b) Abadan in Persian Gulf. c) Bahrein Island 5.n Persian Gulf. would be admitted to Imperial Preference. \I C Further, would products obtained from a' Sheikdom on the Trucial Coast of the Persian Gulf be admitted to Preference ? We would mention that we have been referred to your office by the Overseas Trade Department.; C /C v5 August, 1937. \ With reference to our letter No.15281/36 28. 6 . 57. of the 22nd of October last, about the admission to preference of goods from Bahrein,Kuwait,3hargah and the other Sheikhdoms on the Trucial Coast of the Persian Gulf, I enclose a copy of a despatch * from Sierra Leone enquiring whether preference may be accorded to petroleum products refined at Abadan. I imagine that the answer is quite clearly no but before replying accordingly we should be grateful for your confirmation. RECd. POL. DE‘?r. SAUG1937, INDIA OFFICE •M.J. CLAUSON.ESQ. /w.a.A. ?.o., s*.?.. ^ITRRA L'tilT? 1S37 | GO VEBHMERT HOU 3E » -J. d- SirR Vi I5?0NE. Sir, 1 fciaTc tat honour to info rut you ttiht ^«#sir8. Th« United Africa Coapony, Limitta, enquired on b«hftlf of thtir principals* The Vacuum Oil company, limited, whether petroleum products refined at Abadan can be admitted into Sierra Leone at Preferential aateo of duty. 2. In your Circular deepatca of the loth October, 1936, it is stated that the territories of Bahrein, Kuwait, Shargah *and the other ^heikhdomc on the Trueial Coast of the Persian Gulf*' may be regarded as British protected States for preference purposes, but it is not clear whether Abadan nay be similarly so regarded or whether it forme part of tne Trucial Coast referred to. 1 shall he obliged for your instructions in this connection. I nave the honour to oe» 3ir» Your most obedient* iumble servant. ( sgd. ) TOTS' MDOST?, ACTHfO OOTT-WOR. TH* 1 SIG r T RCWOURABTFDear Mr. Clauson, Thank you for your letter P.Z.3963/37 of the 10th July, the contents of which are noted. M.J. Clauson Esq.., India Office, Whitehall, S.W.l./ My dear Kisch, Many thanks for your letter of 5th July about the Bahrein Petroleum Company^ proposal to seek preference on Bahrein oil in the British Empire. We entirely agree with the lines of your proposed reply. Yours sincerely Sir Cecil Kisch, K.C.I.E., C.BM. 02999/37. nr p. 4422 195 7 J CONFIDENTIAL• Military Bran* Admiralty, S.W.l. 5th July, 1937. iv A My dear Clauson, The Admiralty have read the correspondence about the grant of preferential rates for Bahrein oils with interest. Whilst we should not wish to press that the Bahrein Petroleum Company should he placed in a better case than the purely British oil concern^ we desire to draw attention to the great strategical importance of this source of supply. Bahrein is an island and the protection of its output in wartime would be much easier than would be protection of Anglo- Persian oil. In fact, it would seem that in war Bahrein oil would be one of our most valuable sources of supply. At the present moment we understand that the Bahrein Petroleum Company is doing very well and no question should arise of its going out of business. The strategic importance of the oil is such, however, that if production ever threatened to be uneconomic we should prefer that the Company should have preferences over purely British concerns rather than cease operations, I am sending copies of this letter to Starling, Brenan and Bankes Amery. Yours sincerely. M.J, Clauson, Esq., India Office, S. W. 1. 1as 2 - mesun ^ articles exported, for instance from the Trucial 3 h a Adorns via Bahrain, will not be entitled to any p^ference. If necessary therefore it is proposed that the jntry in any list of countries entitled to preierence should be in the following fom : 'Arab Littoral of the Persian Gulf', (i.e* Bahrain, Kuwait, and the Trucial Shaikhdoms). 4. The only article of any .importance exported to India from the places concerned, which would be entitled to preference under the Ottawa Agreement, is dates, which are imported annually to India from the Bahrain Island to the value of over Rs» lakhs# These would be grunted a 10 per cent preference, provided they were the actual produce of such places ( vide rule 4(T)(a) of the Ottawa Trade Agreement Rules)* It would probably there!ore oe necessary to make some arrangement whereby dates which were entitled to preference under this rule would be accompanied by a certificate oi origin* It is suggested that this should be granted by the local authorities and countersigned by the Political Agent concerned. It will however be a matter for serious consideration how far the Political Agents will feel themselves in a position to countersign such certificates of origin, having regard to the possibility that dates produced in other territories may be brought to Bahrain, etc., for shipment* This difficulty has been felt in respect of certain commodities imported from other Colonies. For example, it was found necessary entirely to reiuse the beneiit* ol u.^3 preferential rate of duty in the case of the copra imported from Penang owing to the difficulty ol ensuring thac he copra was really the product of Malaga* again, it ,a3 not found possible to apply the preferential tariff to coconut shipped from Penang or betel-nuts shipped from Kalantan until an assurance had been obtained irom the local authorities concerned th^t there was not in fact any import trade in these commodities into these seuti.omenta from territories outside Malaya* The issue of the above has been autnorised* i2JJUN!9t tf (v&gt; From Foreign, Simla* To The Political Resident in the Persian G-ulf. ‘O (Repeated) Secretaiy of State for India, London. vX political Agent, Muscat. “ * , Bahrain. ' ' * , Kuwait. NO.F.77&amp;-N/36. Dated Simla, the /o-' 4 ' June 1937. Reference paragraph 4 of Secretary ol State*s express letter No.P.Z.277/37, dated the 13th February 1937. Tariff preferences for the Shaikhdoms of the Persian G-ulf. 2. As negotiations for a new trade agreement with the United Kingdom are about to conmence and are expected to be concluded by the end of July 1937, the Government of India do not now consider it worth while to extend the existing scheme of preferences to Bahrain, Kuwait, and the Trucial Shaikhdoms. It is possible, however, that the question of such preferences may have to be considered in connection with the new agreement, and the Government of India would therefore be glad of your views on the following points. 3. Under rule 4 (1) of the Ottawa Trade Agreement Rules, (copy enclosed) an article in order to obtain preference must be consigned direct to India from the producing country named in the list. If therefore Bahrain, Kuwait, and the Trucial Shaikhdoms are each mentioned in the list; separately, it will mean5973 5000 3.37 P. Z. 3963/37. Draft Paper. r political Department. H. R. Ballantyne, Esq&gt; , 11, Birchin Lane, E.C.3. Dear Mr. Ballantyne,' Would you kindly refer to your letter of the 30th April and our conversation about that time in which you asked for the view 5 of His Majesty f s Government on the suggestion that the Australian Government might be asked to grant an Imperial preference on Bahrein oil products. This question has necessitated various consultations and I am sorry not to have been able to give you an earlier reply. 2, The reply is that the quantity of oil produced in the Empire is small and that the seeking or granting of preference on oil products generally has not been the policy of His Majesty’s Government. The disadvantages which might arise from any change of policy are likely to be greater than the advantages these reasons His Majesty’s Government, so far as they are concerned, would prefer that the question should not be pursued by the Company. 3. The above is, of course, for your confidential information. Yours sincerely, C«U) M. J. CLAUSORMinute Paper. political Department. The Bahrein Petroleum Company is of course a subsidiary of the Standard Oil Company of California (though it is registered in Canada, has one Canadian Director approved by H.M.G., and has an office in London in charge of a British subject - Mr. Ballantyne - approved by H.M.G.). Recently a marketing arrangement for Bahrein oil was made between the California Company and the Texas Corporation, involving the formation of a marketing Company known as the Cal-Tex, and the division of interest in Bahrein oil between the two Companies. The Texas people (who are the marketing experts) have lately put up a proposition in the Cal-Tex Company for an attempt to be made to secure Imperial Preference for Bahrein Oil. The California people are a little suspicious of the Texas people, who have not had their experience of working with H.M.G. and the Sheikh of Bahrein, and do not realise the importance of keeping on good terms with the British authorities in all matters affecting the Persian Gulf. They fear that the Texas people's proposition (the latter are apparently confident that they can fix things with the Australian Government and perhaps the New Zealand Government and obtain preferences in these Dominions) might cut across H.M.G.'s interests and policy. They therefore authorised Mr. Ballantyne to ask the India Office what H.M.G.'s views are on the subject. The points at issue are explained in my letter to the Petroleum Department dated 18th May at P.Z.2992/37 (flagged below). The reply of the Colonial Office (which does not carry one much further) is at P.Z. 3651/37. The/ 6063 Wt 9696/P 28 5000 4.37 IOPThe letter from the Petroleum Department dated 12 th June, which is now submitted, does, however, deal with the problem as a whole and seems to show conclusively that we ought to discourage the Company from pursuing its project. The Foreign Office and Admiralty are understood not to . have any special views on the subject, and it is accordingly proposed to write to Mr. Ballantyne on the lines suggested by the Petroleum Department. Copies of the papers will be sent to the Government of India, but it is unnecessary to consult them since in this matter we are acting for H.M.G. and speaking merely of their general policy. (Of course if the Government of India wish to grant a preference to Bahrein oil - which is hardly likely - they can raise the question themselves). The K.&amp; 0.Department have no observations to make. r-=\4 Any reply to this letter should he Addressed to the Director, Petroleum Dept. Telephone: Victoria 9310. Telegrams : Mintndttst, Sowkst, London. Reference No.:- P.D. 21/4. PETROLEUM DEPARTMENT (Mines Department), %„ r -— 3 b \ * • Dean Stanley Street, Millbank, O vJ O j » ^ London, S.W.l. . June, 1937. My dear Clauson, - With reference to your letter of 18th May on the subject of the preferential rates of duty in Australia and New Zealand for Bahrein oils, while I think it is unlikely that either of these two countries would accede to the request of the Bahrein Petroleum Company, I do not think we should allow the matter to he put to the test. As you know, there is no preference in the United Kingdom for Empire oils. Trinidad have applied for a preference on motor spirit on a number of occasions in recent years, but have been turned down. Empire production (apart from Bahrein) is very small and is confined to Trinidad, Sarawak and Brunei, Burmah and India. Burmah production is absorbed in India. Trinidad oil enjoys a preference in some of the West Indian Islands, but that is largely a local arrangement. It also enjoys a preference in Sierra Leone, but the quantity of oil involved is almost negligible. M. J. Clauson, Esq., India Office, Whitehall, S.W. 1. ensure m wEekly lettcr tio. 29 1937 raw SECRETARY, K-..- -L AMD SECRET DEPT. INDIA OFFICE__ —2— i ine only cases in which v/e have endeavoured to obtain preference have been in respect of lubricating oils manufactured in this country. This is a rather specialised trade faced with -tiix American competition, the American sources of supply being very much nearer to both the West Indies and the Australasian markets. Over a period of years v/e have managed to secure a f^T improvements in the qualifying conditions in both places. An^ general extension of preference to motor spirit, fuel oil, etc., would not in practice benefit Empire producers. On the other hand, the grant of a preference to Bahrein oil would, in certain countries, notably Australia, enable the Bahrein Company . r to compete on favourable terms with existing British interests marketing oil not of Empire origin. This question arose in July last, when the marketing arrangements with the Texas Company were under discussion. On that occasion X mentioned that there were certain advantages from the point of view of our big oil groups in a Company like the Texas handling the oil, since it will then flow into the channels where they normally trade, and thus there would be a minimum of disturbance of markets, which is all to the good from the point of view of British oil interests. (See my letter of 3rd July, 1936, 1 . 0 . ref. P.Z.4298/36.) But if the Bahrein—Texas Company is going to get a preference in certain markets, it cannot but prejudice the interests of the Anglo- Iranian and Shell Companies. To take the case of Australia,*2.'- — r w. -3- I enclose a statement showing the imports of petroleum products in the year 1934/5, from which you will see that the hulk of the imports are obtained from Dutch East Indies and Persia, the Shell Group and the Anglo-Iranian being the principal companies concerned. The latter Company operate through the Commonwealth Oil Refineries, Limited, one half of whose capital is held by the Commonwealth Government. I suggest, therefore, that it should be pointed out to Ballantyne in general terms that the quantity of oil produced in the Empire is small, and that the seeking or granting of preferences on oil products generally has not been the policy of H.M. Government. The disadvantages which might arise from any change of policy are likely to be greater than the advantages. For these reasons, therefore, H.M. Government would prefer that the matter were not pursued. On the question of assurances to be given in regard to the control of the Bahrein Petroleum Company (your letter P.Z.2544/37 of 28th April), I am inclined to think that the proposal to exchange letters would be the best way of dealing with the matter, providing, as Seal suggests in his letter of 25th May, that it is made clear that any proposal regarding the transfer of control to other interests will be notified well in advance to H.M. Government.I am sending copies of this letter to Brenan, Bankes-Amery, Clauson and Seal. Yours sincerely,s AUSTRALIA* IMPORTS 1954-35. Statute Tons. Country of Origin. Crude Oil. Motor Spirit. Residual Fuel Oil. Solar Oil. Kerosene (Power). Kerosene and other refined petroleum burning oils, n.e.i. Lubri cating Oil. Total Liquid Products. British Empire. Great Britain British Borneo 5 1 5,403 152 87 179 3 505 510 671 6,174 Other British Countries | 34 OJ . 34 Foreign Countries Dutch E. Indies Persia Roumania U.S.A. Mexico Belgium Denmark Germany Russia 108,784 112,465 459,767 20,785 29,947 191,828 308,041 25,405 25,004 8 2,638 1,063 40,825 1,418 1,405 18,632 30,181 3,148 2 23,281 515 49,982 131 42 19 1,686 178 Usj 950,751 164*284 31,354 308,727 139 42 19 1,686 178 Other Foreign Countries. 1 X 19 20 TOTAL 221,254 707,732 358,610 3,788 62,459 57,120 53,116 1,464,079 * Less than 1 ton'■ COOb Wt 8322—r 8 1000 + 3000 4.37 It is requested that in any further communi cation on this subject the under-mentioned letter and number may be quoted, and the reply addressed to — The Under Secretary of State for India, Political Department, India Office, 3. 3734/37. London, S.W. 1. fjfC 7FICE, n , S.W. If. * INDIA 01 WHITEHALL, LONDON 12th June, 1937. Sir, I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to refer to your letter of the 7th June, No. X.2/7002/ 562, regarding the etatua of the Bahrein Inlands. These Islands are not a British Pocsession or Protectorate but the Sheikh of Bahrein 1 b &amp;xi independent ruler in special treaty relations with His Majesty’s Government, under which His Majesty’s Government conduct his foreign relations and guarantee him protection* It would accordingly seem to be appropriate to regard the Islands as included within the definition of Section 42(1) of the Widows’, Orphans’ and Old Age Contributory Pensions Act, 1936. It may be relevant in this connection to state that Bahrein is regarded by the competent authorities as being covered by the words ’’Territories under His Majesty’s Protection” for the purpose of Section 21 of the Import Duties Act of 1932. I am. Sir, Your obedient Servant, M. J. The Controller, Ministry of Health, Insurance Department, Whitehall, S. W. 1.* *^5^ 0. 5. r Telegrams— “Localise, Parl, London.” Telephone— Whitehall, 4300. Please address any further communication on this subject to :— THE CONTROLLER. &gt;/. / ‘ . Ministry of Health, 3734 Insurance Departj i© r^r j J ^'Whitehall, S.W.l Please quote the following reference— X2/7002/562. June, 1937. Sir, 4 j^^S4A(?&gt; s 8 JUN.0.7 dows 1 . Orphans 1 and Old Age Pensions Act, 1936. f A° , s. I have to 'state that, under Section 22 of the above-named Act, persons who satisfy certain qualifying conditions may become insured as voluntary contributors while in any part of His Majesty 1 s dominions outside Great Britain and that it is provided, by Section 42(l) of the Act, that the term 'His Majesty’s dominions' shall include British Protectorates and Protected States and any territory in respect of which a mandate is being exercised by the Government of any part of His Majesty’s dominions. It is desired to know whether Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, may be regarded as included in His Majesty’s dominions for this purpose, and the Department would, therefore, appreciate any information you can afford as to the present status of this territory. I am. Sir, Your obedient Servant, India Office, Whitehall, S.W.l. *f D.O.No. 0 go Will you please refer to your demi-official letter No. P.Z.1507/37, dated the 18th March 1937, on the subject of commercial preference for the Sheikhdoms of the Persian Gulf. putting the Gulf States into Appendix I of the Customs Public Leaflet to which you refer. As however the Customs Officers have already received the necessary instructions (vide last paragraph of your letter) is there any necessity for the Gulf States to appear in any list ? 3. I do not think that the actual volume of trade from the States concerned should affect our action, which is a point you touched on. Even though the present volume of trade is small it may increase in the future and in any case as a matter of principle the States concerned should get the benefit of the preference to whatever extent it may point could you please let me know) I suggest that the Political - v • * Agents concerned should inform the Shaikhs of their areas that Imperial Preference is being extended to them. We may at I am sending copies of this letter to Hay # Hickinbotham and de Gaury. 2. I agree with you that there is no real objection to apply. 4. Unless the India Office see any objection (on which least get the credit of a gesture. M.J. Claus on Esquire, The India office, London. REGd. sept. 31MAV193715024/B/37. r~^~ 3651 ^ r w 1 9 3 / Dcwn'jng Street, S.V7.1, 4 JIIN m/ /\~7 L^L^&lt;/ / With reference to your letter P.Z. 2992/37 to Starling of the 18th of May (a copy of which you sent to Eastwood), about preference for Bahrein oil, I write to say that the following Colonies give a preference on British motor spirit, which of course includes the Bahrein product:- All the West Indian Colonies (including British Guiana and British Honduras), St. Helena, Cyprus, the Gambia and Sierra Leone^ but the preference is likely to disappear shortly in Jamaica^) In the unlikely event of Australia granting preference to Bahrein oil we should no doubt ask for a similar concession for oil from Sarawak and Trinidad. At a guess the Australians are very unlikely to grant preference on oil; they will, I think, say with truth that there is no preference in the United Kingdom and that the Netherlands East Indies from which they get theirtheir oil now are much too valuable customers to alienate. I* am sending copies of this letter to Starling, Brenan, Bankes-Amery and Seal.t \ j \. (a, ^-i)(».tvu (lift- H‘^^%4^A '' ^ lrol * omcs ' Mac /‘c TOIT3H S.w.x. / Xjh May 1937 • M 5 My dear Starling, Ballantyne of the Bahrein Petroleum Company ^[ enquired the other dpy whether His Majesty’s Qovernnent would have any objection to their Taarlceting people, the California Texas Company, applying to the Australian i* ^nd New Zealand Governments for preference^b&lt; Bahrein oil. He asked at the same time whether there would be any objection to preference being asked in other British possessions, ^including India) The reason for the enquiry wop that the marketing people said they thought they could secure preference from the Australian Government but the Bahrein Petroleum Company (or rather the parent Company - Standard Oil of California) are anxious not to do anything which might in any way embarrass His Majesty’s Government, and are therefore not disposed to accept the suggestion of their marketing people unless they are assured that His Majesty’s Aw* /^v!4 Govemrent^jtiiJuXd not hnve any object ion.^ ENCLOSURE IN WE P.C.Starling, Jsq. , Petroleum Depaxftme Mines Be Dean .Y/ IE fTEI NO. 20 /&lt;? *QMAY 1937 W5CM aa&amp;RETARV, -''wAL AND T DEPT. INDIA OFFICE The/ Stanley street .©OPY SENT BY AIR MAIL s.w.i. pt/ 4 'S-h £ 12 The first question soems to be - do His Majesty’s Government object in principle to the Bahrein Petroleum asking for preferences in the British Empire which, if obtained, would put them in a better position for can we tell Ballantyne this ? Alternatively, should we say to him that His Majesty’s Government are opposed in principle to oil preferences, that there is no Imperial preference for oil in this country or in the British Empire generally, and that in these circumstances His Majesty's Government would deprecate the Bahrein Company raising the matter with a Dominion Government.? If His Majesty’s Government have no objection in principle, there seem to be two alternative answers that we might make to Ballantyne:- (l) tell him to let his people go ahead and that competing wit] le Anglo-Iranian Oil Company^ If so we should be interested to know whether they are successful. (2) to say that we have no objection to application being made to the Australian Government but that if so. His Majesty's Government would do their best to ensure that any preference granted to Bahrein3. is granted also to all Colonial oil products. I should be glad if you would kindly let me know as soon as possible what your views are as to the answer to be given. I understand from conversation with Coleman that in point of fact there is not at present sny Imperial preference in respect of oil granted by the Australian Government (with one small exception) and if we can say this of the British Empire as a whole we should, of course, have good ground for deprecating the action proposed by the Bahrain Company if in fact His Majesty’s Government do not like the idea of possible reactions on the ‘inglo-Iranian Cil Company. I am sending copies of this^retter to Brenan at the foreign Office, Bankes-Am^y at the Dominions Office, Eastwood at the ColonialX^*ice and Seal at the Admiralty.The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited 11, Birchin Lan e Lon don . e. c. 3. ICth Ijstf, 1937. Dear Mr. Glauson, the 7 th llay. I note that it will he sorue little time before you can give me an answer to the question I have put to you. I know that you will take no longer than needful because the question is one of marketing and my people would like to know so soon as possible what they ought to do. Yours sipc M.J.Clauson Esq., India Office, Y/hi tehall, S.W. 1.M Draft Paper. P.Z.2£|92/37 Department. F.J. Coleman, Esq., M.B.E., Petroleum Department, Mines Department, Dean Stanley St., S. W. 1. Copy to India Bushire Bahrein F.O. Admiralty D.O. C.O. 5973 5000 3.37 -t /IT: a 1 Dear Coleman, I spoke to you the other day about an enquiry from Mr. Ballantyne, / the London representative of the Bahrein 7 Petroleum Company, regarding the possibility of securing in British possessions, with particular reference to Australia, Imperial preference for Bahrein product^. As I told you, he explained that the California Texas people in New York, who, under present arrangements, look after the marketing of the Banrein Petroleum Company’s product^, say that they think they can obtain/Imperial preference from the Commonwealth Government. The Bahrein Pet/ole urn Company, however, (that is to sa# the parent Company, Standard Oil California) are anxious not to do anything which might in any way embarrass H.M.G., and they are not disposed to accept the suggestion of their marketing people unlessthey are assured that H.M.G. would not have any objection. 2. The position is that for the purposes of s.21 of the Import Duties Act, 1932, the Persian Gulf States are regarded as 'protected States', and Bahrein products are accordingly entitled to/to claim preference in the United KingdOEi. This, however, does not affect the position in Australia or any other part of the British Empire, where I imagine the Government concerned can decide for themselves how far they are prepared to It extend Imperial preferences. 4- think jy Q^otir thfrt we should not wish in * any way to encourage an application for preference from the Bahrein Petroleum Company, in view of the fact that such a preference^'might facilitate the i ii It i idu nt i nn of tlio ritnnrinrrl Oil Cn * * n -product s, m-ifrwh upset the balance of the Indian market^ On the other hand, i^ would be up to the Government of India when the time came to consider the question whether they should, or should not, give a preference to Bahrein oil, and this question need not perhaps necessarily affect the reply that should be given to the Company in respect of Australia or New Zealand. If Australia and New Zealand do not in fact give preference to products of e.g. Trinidad, then presumably we can say to the Bahrein Petroleum Company straight away that in view cf this fact we do not think they should apply for a preference for Bahrein since it would be wrong for a i&amp;J* '(hx. tarri tnry nln Nnfr¥»fnn tonM - ^ y cU ^ — V ^ - M , U^,t oj to get better treatment than a Colony receives.Draft Paper. 5973 5000 3.37 Department 3. You said that you would look into the matter point of view of Australia i *aland, and would le t me know wh* )ur views as to a am writing :er to record the matter. I ig copies to Brenan at the Foreign Office and to Seal at the Admiralty, since they are interested from the point of view of the Persian Gulf, -and am also sending copies to the 9'ominions Office and Colonial Office in c/ase they are interested from the point of view of Imperial preference. reply to M: lantyne. Meanwhile , IIHDIA OFFICE, WHIT;.HALL, ?tii May, 1937. Daar Kr. Ballantyiia, Would you kindly refer to your letter of 30tk April reg«u*dixig your enquiry about preferential treatment for jiahrein prolueta in British poaeeasion^ overseas? I write to let you know tftat this question appears to raise rather oomplioated issue© which are under canal deration* I am afraid, however, that it may be some little time before I can rive you an anuvver. Tours sincerely. (Si.) M. J. CuAUSO-N. H.H. Jiallantyue, , fhe Bahrein letroleum Co., 11, Birchin Lone, R’ r 'Ji- Ltd.# ,t f The Bahrein O Q • » I % V . i Petroleum Company Limited i 11, Birchin Lan e, Lon don . e. c. 3. 30th April, 1937. Dear Mr. Clauson, Concerning my encjuiiy of you the other day about preferential treatment for Bahrein products in Australia and Lev; Zealand, my enquiry, I see, ex tends to British Possessions. Y/e must assume that by 'British Possessions' India is intended to be in cluded. The question at present affects parti cularly New Zealand and Australia but in any reply you may make, would you be good enough to bear in mird that India and other Countries may also be regarded as in cluded in any general reply? • • H.J.Clauson Esq., India Office, ’Whitehall, S.W.l.P.z.1507/37. INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL, LONDON, S.V7.1. 18th March, 1937. My dear Fowle, Will you please refer to the correspondence ending with our official express letter of the 13th February, 1937, No. P.2.277/37 regarding commercial preference for the Sheikdoms of the Persiaa Gulf. The Customs authorities have now asked whether we consider that Bahrein, Koweit, 'atar and the Trucial Sheikdoms should be included in the list of British Empire territories shown in Appendix I of their public leaflet about preference. Since these States are now accorded Imperial Preference, it seems strictly illogical that they should not be listed v/ith the other territories in Appendix I; but against that is the obvious objection to entering them unuer the heading ’’British -Empire', even though they are so, at any rate, for this particular purpose. On the other hand, the Aden Protectorate, Zanzibar, etc*, are already in the list and their status is similar to that of the Gulf States. On the whole, therefore, whi1e it might have been better from our point of viev; if there hau been a separate list with a heading such / Lt.Co1.T.C.W.Fowle,CBE.,IA., Consulate General, Bushire.such as States enjoying His Majesty’s protection' there may not be any real objection to putting the Cfulf States into the existing list. But before we reach a decision in the matter we should be glad of your views. There is of course no reason why we should take any action at all, if you do not feel that the volume of trade justifies it. The Customs Officers here have already received the necessary instructions and the leaflet is of course intended merely for the information of the public. I am sending a copy of this letter to India and to Loch and de Gaury. Yours sincerely. M. J CLAUSONMinute Paper. reforms Department. Mr. Johnston . I think this letter from the Customs is for you to deal with now. The writer I believe to be A.W. Mackenzie, but you will probably be able to make sure of this from the previous correspondence. I suppose the reason why the Customs refer to the Adaptation of Acts of Parliament Order as the reason for a change in the Imperial Preference Lis t is (l) that the Order repeals the definition of India in the Interpretation Act, and (2) the reference to Burma in the adaptation of the Import Duties Act of 1932. I seem to remember that they were a good deal consoled at being referred to the definition of India at an earlier stage, and it might be convenient when you reply to them to tell them that the statutory definition still exists and is still of general application, but is now to be found in s.31l(l) of the Government of India Act, where there is also a statutory definition of Burma. The actual changes required in their list will be presumably to aud Burma at the end of the first part of List 1 (Dominions, etc.) after Southern Rhodesia; secondly, in List 2 , subject to what the Colonial Office may say; to substitute for the word 'Protectorate' after Aden the words 'Settlement and Protectorate'; and thirdly, to make some entry in respect of 'Bahrein etc.' . whatever that may mean. This last may be something of a conundrum, and no doubt the Political Department will have something to say about it. The trouble seems to be that the whole of the list refers to 'countries of the British Empire', apart from this the second part of the list is probably wide enough to cover the inclusion /inclusion in it of any territory which can establish a claim to Inroerial preference. Will you take the letter over? (Sd.) A. Dibdin. 11.2.37. Political Secretar.Y t I regret that this paper has been mislaid for a time. I should be glad to have your views as to the entry which should be made in respect of Bahrein etc. (Sd.) W. Johnston 4.3.37 Secretary. E and 0 Department . The question of putting something in the leaflet about Bahrein, Kuwait, Qatar and the Trucial Sheikhdoms of the Persian Gulf raises certain difficulties, ahd I think it will be desirable to consult the Political Resident on the subject. On the one hand it has seemed to us to be illogical that these states, which we now accorded Imperial Preference, should not be listed in the Appendix, on the other hand there are certain (perhaps sentinmental) objections to describing them as part of '’the British Empire” - admittedly they are so for this particular purpose at least, but it might perhaps have been preferable to have them described as 'States enjoying His Majesty’s Protection” or something of the kind, less definitive than 'British Empire”. If you do not mind, we will deal with the relevant paragraph of Mr. McKenzie’s letter separately on our file and let you know the outcome in due course. We have kept a copy of the paragraph and of your note and mine. (Sd.) M.J.ClausonSECRETARIES’ OFFICE, CUSTOM HOUSE, E.C.3 37804/36 10th February, 1937. Dear Dibdin, I do not know whether the subject of this letter is still your concern but if it is not perhaps you will kindly pass it on. the list of British Empire territories included in our preference leaflet. I enclose a copy of&gt; f the current edition of the leaflet and should be very grateful if you would indicate any amendments which are considered necessary to meet the position which will Parliament) Ord^r of 1937 comes into operation. It seems to me y that Burma,,will have to be mentioned somewhere but I am not sure where, ^and I am also not sure whether any amendment or addition to bHe existing reference to Aden Protectorate will be necessary. There is one further point. Symon of your Office recently raised with me the question of including Bahrein etc. in the list to give effect to our correspondence last year on this subject under your reference PZ 3539/36. We told our Officers that goods from Bahrein etc. are entitled to preference, but if you consider that something should be included in the public leaflet I shall be glad to know what you suggest. I am sending a copy of this letter to Eastwood of the Colonial Office. arise when the Government of India (Adaptation of Acts of v y Yours sincerely, (3d*) A.W. McKenzie. A. Dibdin, EsqIt is requested that in any further communi cation on this subject the under-mentioned letter and number may be quoted, and the reply addressed to — The Under Secretary of State for India, Political Department, India Office, INDIA OFFICE. WHITEHALL, LONDON, Z. 960/37. London, S.TF. 1. 15th February, 1937 Gentlemen I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to refer to your letter of 9th February, (HJW/'SiS), resardin* the atatua of the Bahrein Islands. 2. These Islands are not a British possession or Protectorate, but the Sheikh of Bahrein is an independent Kuler in special treaty relations with His Majesty's Government under which His Majesty's Government conduct his foreign relations and ^urrantee him protection; and it may be relevant to inform you that the State is regarded as being covered by the words ♦'territories under His Majesty's protection' for the purpose of s.51 of the Import Duties Act of 1932. I am, Gentlemen Your obedient Servant (Sgd.) M. J. CLAUSOK Messrs.Shaen, Roscoe, Massey &amp; Co. , 8, Bedford Row, W.C.l.INDIA OFFICE, P.Z. 6755/36. WHITEHALL, 3.W. 1. 24th September 1936. Sir, I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to refer to your letter of the 17th September regarding the status of the Bahrein Islands. 2* These Islands are not a British possession -aye- they a- British Protectorate^ UKe Sheikh of Bahrein is an independent Euler in special treaty relations with His Majesty’s Government under which His Majesty’s Government conduct his foreign relations and guarantee him protection; and it may be relevant to inform you that the State is regarded as being covered by the words ’’territories under His Majesty’s protection” for the purpose of s.21 of the Import Duties Act of 1932. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, (Sgd.) OLAUSOM The Secretary, Intelligence Department, Imperial Chemical Industries, Ltd., Millbank, S.V/.l.§ m Draft Paper. DRAFT FXPRFSS LETTER (AIR HAIL ). P , ^ Department. 3 3 FEB 1537 From Secretary of State for India To The Polltrlcal Resident in the Persian Gulf, repealed to the Government of Inpda, Foreign and Political DepaiOment, Political Agent M^&amp;dat, Political Agent, / Bahrain, Political Agent, Kuweit. Your Express Letter jno. 2529 dated 19th Decemher 1936, Commercial preference for the Sheikdoms of the Persian Gulf. 2. So far as this oorrnwy is concerned Bahrein, Kttweit and the Trucial Sheikdoms (hut not of course Muscat) are regarded hy the competent authorities as being covered hy the words ”territories under His Majesty’s protection' for the purpose of Section 21 of the Import Duties | Act of 1932# 3« Full information in regard to the preferential rates of duty charged on Empire products imported into the United Kingdom is contained in the enclosed volume entitled 'Customs and Excise Tariff of the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland in operation on the 1st January 1937'. :Your attention is also invited to the enclosed pamphlet dated December 1936 issued hy the Commissioners of Customs and Excise entitled 'Imperial preference notes to Importers in the United Kingdom Pto.Department. 2 . and to Exporters in the British Empire”. I understand that, when this pamphlet if -«Keurlif is next revised .Bahrein, WGtetot and the Trucial Sheikdoms wr±l ho-4 m eluded, in the list of territories shown in Appendix I. 4* I assume that the Government of India will inform you direct of the regulations relating to preferences in India. 5- One copy each of the Import Duties Act of 1932 and of the amending Acts is being sent to the Political Agents at Muscat, Bahrein and Kuweit together with one copy each of the publications referred to in paragraph 3 above. s- d.) Nl. Jv CLAUSONDraft Paper. /-&gt; f-2. Department. DRAl^T KXPRHS3 LBTT2SR (AIR MAIL) . 3/ / 3 FEB 1957 From Secretary of State for India r To Cl) The Political Agent, Muscat 2 ) ' ' B^^in 3 ) ” ” ' KijsFelt repeated in each c^ise to tae Government of Injarfa, Foreign and Political Department and^to the Political Resident, Bushire. Please refer to Bushire Express Letter ho. 2529 dated 19th December 1936 and my reply ho. P.Z. 277/37 dated regarding commercial preference for the Sheikdoms of the Persian Gulf. One copy each of the following documents is enclosed herewith:- (1) The Import Duties Act of 1932 and amending Acts; (2) Customs and Excise Tariff of the United Kingdom of Great Britain and horthern Ireland in operation on the 1st January 1937; (3) Pamphlet dated December 1936 issued hy the Commissioners of Customs and Excise entitled ’’Imperial preference hotes to Importers in the United Kingdom and to Exporters in the British Empire.” 5.319c 5000 10.3(&gt;EXPRESS LETTER From: - Brit consul, Bushire To:- The India Office, The Foreign, The Political Agent, The Political Agent, The Political Agent, Ho •■2 Dated the December, 1936 Hew Delhi. V. mscat { witn copies of 0 ^ Bahrain j correspondence j ' Kuwait. j mentioned below. Subject Commercial preference for the Sheikhdoms of Persian &amp;ilf. . &gt; With reference to your P.Z. 7619/36 forwarding Colonial • ,1 &gt;r~ Office letter of 15th October, 1936, with enclosure of End June, 1933, I should be grateful if I could have particulars of the preferential treatment. Is this treatment covered by Section 21 of the Import Duties Act of 1932, vide your letter Ho. P.Z. 1037/35, dated 14th Februaiy, 1935 ? If so, please send copies to the Political Agents, Kuwait, Bahrain and Muscat. Sgd. T. C. Fowle. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Attested. His Majesty f s Vice-Consul.CIRCULAR. n Downing Street, \5th October, 1936. Sir, In his circular despatch of the 2nd June, 1933, Sir Philip Cunlijfe-Lister {now Viscount Swinton) addressed you regarding the definition of “ the British Empire ” for use in tariff legislation of Colonies and Protectorates which grant Imperial preference. 2. Attention has recently been called to the position of Bahrein, Kuwait, Shargah and the other Sheikhdoms on the Trucial Coast of the Persian Gulf. The practice in this country hitherto has been not to admit goods from these territories to preference, but the position has recently been reviewed and as a result goods from these territories will now be accorded preferential treatment in the United Kingdom, subject to their complying with the usual conditions. 3. / shall be glad if a similar practice may be followed in the territory under your administration. No amendment to local legislation will be necessary if the definition of “ British Empire ” for preference purposes communicated in the circular despatch referred to has been adopted, as I am advised that the territories in question can be regarded as British protected States within the meaning of those words occurring in that definition. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your 7nost obedient, humble servant, W. ORMSBY GORE. The Officer Administering the Government ofDowning Street, 2nd June, 1933. Sir, I have the honour to inform you that I have recently had under consideration the question of the exact definition of “ the British Empire ” to be used in the tariff legislation of the ( olonies and Protectorates which grant Imperial Preference, in order to make it clear that the British preferential rates of duty are applicable to goods imported from all parts of the Empire and British Mandated Territories, excepting only Palestine (including Trans-Jordan). 2. An examination of the existing legislation has revecded that in a number of cases the term “British Empire is used simpliciter without any definition of this expression being included in the Interpretation or other local laws, while the laws in which “ the British Empire ” is defined disclose a number of ividely divergent formulae all of which are imperfect in varying degrees. 3. 1 ou will appreciate the desirability of uniformity in this matter, and I shall be glad if you will arrange for the early amendment of the local law by the adoption of the following formula which I am advised is satisfactory for the purpose in view :— “The British Empire” means the United Kingdom of Great Britain and A orthern Ireland, the Dominions, India, the territories administered by His Majesty's Governments in the Dominions under Mandate or otherwise, the British Colonies, the British Protectorates and protected States, and the Mandated Territories of Tanganyika, the Cameroons under British Mandate and Togoland under British Mandate. 4. Care should be taken that the ivord “ Dominions ” is spelt with a large D. 1 have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient, humble servant, P. CUNLIFFE-L1STER. The Officer Administering the Government of11, Birchin Lan e, Lon don, e. c. 3. 6th October, 1936. Dear Mr. Claus on, Thank you for your confidential letter P^Z^7000/56 of the 3rd instant. I am forwarding to the Company your kindly suggest ions in the hope that they will be sufficient for the Company’s needs. M.J.Clauson Esq., India Office, Whitehall, S.W.l.Colonel Fowle Please see the attached note about a conversation with Mr. Ballantyne. Can you confirm that the Political Agent would he a suitable authority for issuing certificates of idofotity? If so, I will communicate with Mr. Ballantyne accordingly.i &lt;r i : , i •' •' I ft' L ^ ! jtff'f+.n'* ' * v ia COKPIDEHTIAL. . /b iy _ - fiut6*u ( /l M j M~fhc*a*&gt; r p.z. 7000/36 ^ OdF^fU (g) BAHREIN OIL. Mr, Ballantyne called on SeptemLer 24 th and raised two points in connection with the marketing of Bahrein oil. He said that the Company were hoping to market some of their oil in the Phillipine Islands and another part in Indo-China. These were, so far as he knew? the only territories in which difficulties might arise in regard to preferential duties. He understood from his principals in San Francisco that for oil products going into French or Phillipine territory it would make a difference whether the shipment was from British territory or not since there was in Loth cases a preferential tariff for British goods. I informed Mr. Ballantyne that for the purpose of section 21 of the Import Duties Act 1932 the Bahrein islands are regarded as ’'territory under His Majesty's protection” and therefore that Bahrein products imported into this country receive the Benefit of the preferential tariff duties applied to Empire goods. Presumahly this fact would he accepted hy the Phillipine aiid Indo-Chinese customs authorities as entitling Bahrein Oil to British preferential tariff. Mr. Ballantyne agreed that this was probably so and that he might tackle the matter on those lines. He went on to refer in the same connection to the question how certificates of origin should be obtained for shipments of Bahrein oil which might be imported iiito foreign territories. His principals in San Francisco had suggested that an arrangement might be made whereby employees of the Bahrein Petroleum Company would be made Honorary Vice-Consuls for e.g. France etc., and that in that capacity2 they should issue certificates of origin for use in the countries to which the oil was being shipped. I informed Mr. Ballantyne that this was quite out of the question as the Sheikh of Bahrein was by treaty debarred from receiving representatives of any Governments other than His Majesty’s Government. His Majesty’s Government would certainly not allow any infringement of their treaty rights in this connection. SaJJL I that so far as I knew there would be no difficulty in such certificates being issued by the Political Agent and my impression was that this procedure was already normal in Bahrein. I promised to consult Colonel Fowl® and/or Mr. Balgrave, and let Mr. Ballantyne know whether my presumption was correct. Mr. Ballantyne agreed that prima facie such an arrangement would be quite suitable. All that was wanted was definite proof of origin for the purposes of the customs authorities the importing country. M.J. CLAUSON. India Office, 28th September, 1936.lNt&gt; In any further communication on this s ibject, please qiote No. .nd address —«£&gt;/ to any person by nam The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. i. THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to jJL~JUy &amp;T J ' ^ j qA ) and, by direction of the Secretary ^&gt;f State, transmits herewith cop &lt; of the under-mentioned paper. 5 Foreign Office, Odr 2 , 193 &lt;£. Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. UcjdLj u)olL 'MA JbjJo. oUfe Ocfc. 14-6130 13667(2) Subject. ^ TTYyv dib-UL OL. closure in weekly letter ^ - 8OCT 1936 io ^ •t C-ORETaoV, FOLluCAL AND EFT INDIA OFFICE Similar letter sent toCopy (E 6046/2463/91) Keynsham, Nr. Bristol. Sept. 24, 1936. Dear Sir, V/e have been grinders of Red Oxide of Iron from the Persian Gulf for many years. This colour has mainly come from the Persian island of Ormuz, close to Bandar Abbas, but a certain amount has also been obtained from Abu Musa, some 90 miles from the Arabian coast and north of the Oman peninsula. Persian or British and as we cannot get this information in Bristol we are writing you as being the most authoritative source and should be very much obliged if you could tell us what we need, or alternatively put us in touch with right quarter. We are trying to find out whether this Abu Musa is Thanking you in anticipation Yours faithfully, V.W.M.C.C (Sgd. ) E.D. Evens H.M. Minister for Foreign Affairs Foreign Office LONDON.E 6046/2463/91 I 'v s.w.T' 1st October, 1936, Sir, I am directed by Mr. Secretary Eden to acknowledge the receipt of your letter of the 24th September regarding the status of the island of Abu Musa in the Persian Gulf. 2. In reply I am to inform you that this island is not Persian, but belongs to the Sheikh of Sharjah, who is under British protection. Sharjah is a principality on the Arabian coast of the Gulf. I am, etc., (Sgd.) Lacy Baggallay. E.D. Evens, Esq.., The Valley Water Mills Color Company, Near Bristol, Keynsham,A. . FORM M.O./l. IMPKEMI VIC Corresonnc esponc this u to i- in . :• . . '•*! ■' * \ ’ &gt;• , 1 YOUR REFINDIA OFFICE, f Y/HITEHALL, 3.W. 1 . 24th September 1936. P.Z. 6755/36. Sir I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to refer to your letter of the 17th September regarding the status of the Bahrein Islands. are they a British Protectorate. The Sheikh of Bahrein is an independent Ruler in special treaty relations with His Majesty’s Government under which His Majesty's Government conduct his foreign relations and guarantee him protection; and it may be relevant to inform you that the State is regarded as being covered by the words ’’territories under His Majesty’s protection” for the purpose of s.21 of the Import Duties Act of 1932* 2* These Islands are not a British possession nor I am, Sir Your obedient Servant (Sgd.) M. J. CLAUSON The Secretary, Intelligence Department, Imperial Chemical Industries, Ltd., Millbank, S.W.l.4m It is requested that 'in any further communi cation on this subject the under-mentioned letter and number may be quoted, and the reply addressed to— The Under Secretary of State for India, Political Department, India Office, London, S.IF. 1. P. Z.6755/36 vV • V. INDIA OFFICE, w WHITEHALL, LONDON, S.W.l. 24th September, Sir, I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to refer to your letter of the 17th September regarding the status of the Bahrein Islands. 2. These Islands are not a British possession nor are they a British Protectorate. The Sheikh of Bahrein is an independent Ruler in special treaty relations with His Majesty’s Government under which His Majesty’s Government conduct his foreign relations; and it may be A relevant to inform you that the State is regarded as being covered by the words ’’territories under His Majesty protection” for the purpose of s.21 of the Import Duties Act of 1932. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, EWCU)eU!» IN WEEKLY LETnV NO. 40 -1 OCT 3086 FROM SECRETARY, POLITICAL AND r d:p t. II’DIA c.'fic; . 3.. ,7_ ' ' ■ • '• C\ QOPV SENT TO. The Secretary, Intelligence Department, Imperial Chemical Industries, Ltd., Millbank, S.W.l.Dj® SECRETARIES’ OFFICE, CUSTOM HOUSE, E.C.3. ! ’ i roi Q 10th August, 1936. 1 'JO ! O Dear Glauson, Your letter of the 6 th to Rhydderch enclosing a copy of one transmitted by the Colonial Office enquiring as to the position of Bahrein. We agree to your proposed reply. We are issuing instructions to our officers that Bahrein and Shargah are in future to be regarded as within the definition of the British iiimpire for preference purposes and that goods from either of these places may accordingly be admitted to preference subject to the usual evidence of origin and consignment. Yours sincerely. M. J. Clausen, Esq., India Office. . POL \ AUG1936 ' U'DiA OF~'IHBIA. C^^ICt, I , . 6th August 1936. r i From Mr.J.C.Grant dated ^nd July. / Will you ple*ee refer to the correepondenee ending with your letter of the Stth July to alton, Wo. 3817C/36, about the position of Bahrein, Sharjah ^nd other Shellrhdeme in the Persian Gulf in regard to Section fcl of the Import Cutie* Act, 1^52. I eneloae in thie connection a copy of the letter noted in the ip*r«;in which has been transferred to us for diepoeal. The simplest reply to send to Mr.Grant would be to tell hire how produete originating from Bahrein are treated in thie country. 1 em not quite cle* r from your letter of 50th *1 uly whether we can definitely tell him that Bahrein ie regarded ae coTared by the werde •territoriee under Kis Majesty’ e protection'* for the purposes of the Import duties Act. If it is not yet open to ue to do eo po«*eibly the simplest pl^n would be for your Office to reply f.a.H.Rhyddereh, £e%. fecretarlee’ Office, H.M.Custcme and iSwciee, to/ Oust ere Rouae, London, S.C.Sto Mr.Grunt in due course wh#r your flnnl decision has formally boon taken. Ynurs alncoroly. (Sgd.) M. J. CLAUSON(K 4624/2463/91) FORFIIU:: OPFIC , . .1. 30th July,1936. i Dear Simpson, \ -i a You will remember that we^fcfedentl/Jdiscussed over the telephone the question of customs duties to be levied in the United Kingdom on goods coming from Sharja] sncl from Bahrain on which the Board of Customs were anxious to learn the views of the Foreign Office* This is to confirm that the India Office semi official letter Ko*P*Z*3539/36 of the 24th June to which you referred, was concurred in by the Foreign office before its despatch to you. Yours sincerely. W. Simpson, Ksq^38170/1936 30th July, 1936. Dear Walton, Your letter of the 24th June, P.Z .3559/5 6. to Walicer about the position of Bahrein, STargah and other Sheikhdoms in the Persian Gulf in regard to Section 21 of the Import Duties Act, 1932. The information contained in your letter seems to leave us with no option hut to reverse our previous decision and to regard these Sheikhdoms as within the definition of the British Empire for preference purposes. I gather that the Foreign Office*' are in agreement with this view, and the Board of Trade, whom we have consulted, offer no objection from the Treaty point of view. We shall probably not be in a position to resist claims for repayment of duty, if these are made, in respect of past importations. I am sending copies of this letter to Hendel and Fennelly. Yours sincerely, J. 0. Walton Esq., C.B.,\ Refer enck. 5 ° * The Under Secretary of State for the Colonies presents his compliments to the the Linder Secretary of State, India Office, and begs to transmit, for disposal, the accompanying communication which has been received at the Colonial Office.1010 St. Catherine St. West MONTREAL, CANADA PHONE: PLATEAU 1505 July ?nd, 1936. Dear Sir: RE: Bahrein Island - Gulf of Persia Will you please inform the ?/riter the actual status - either as a British Colony or pro tectorate - of the above. The object of this inquiry is to ascertain whether products originating therefrom are entitled to entry into Canada under our British Preferential Tariff. jcg/ycAny reply to this letter should be addressed:— “ The Solicitor, SOLICITOR’S OFFICE, H.M. CUSTOMS and EXCISE, LONDON, E.C.3. 29th June, 1936. Custom House, London E.C.3,” and the following Numbers quoted:— Secty’s. No Your Bef.P.Z.3639/36. Dear Walton, Thank you for your letter of the 24th instant which was apparently delayed in the post. I am bringing the matter to the notice of the Board. Yours sincerely J. C. Walton Esq., C.B., M.C., • » India Office, 'Whitehall, S.W.l.FM Cory P.Z.3539/36. Draft Paper. political Department. DRAFT LE TT HR. 24 JUN 1936 C.V.Walker, Esq. , Customs House, E.C.3. Confi dential. Dear Walker, Would you kindly refer to Laithwaite ! s letter of the 14th February 1935 and connected correspondence about the position of Bahrein, Shargah, and other Sheikhdoms in the Persian Gulf in respect of Section 21 of the Import Duties Act, 1932. j: We have now had occasion to look into this question again, and have come to the conclusion that the political difficulties to which Laithwaite referred as likely to be caused by regarding Bahrein (or the other Sheikhdoms) as covered by the words ’’territories under H.M.’s protection' in the Act do not any longer exist. We do Customs should act on the view that the Sheikhdoms are not covered by the Section. 3 The Board may accordingly wish to reconsider its own attitude in regard to 1861 states:- 'The British Resident i engages / desire to suggest that the Board of for the purposes of the Import Duties Act**. In case this is so, we think it may be not, therefore, in existing circumstances, the construction of the words in question ENCLOSURE IN riEKLY LETTER NO. 97 -2JUL1936 useful to give you the thg-parts of the relevant treaties with the Sheikhdoms. f Bahrein . Art.3 of the treaty of* engages that he will forthwith take the necessary steps for obtaining reparation for every injury by sea upon Bahrein.. .. or its dependencies”. Bahrein being a collection of islands, this clearly constitutes protection. r Sharga h and the oth e r Trucia l Sheikhdoms. Art.10 of the Treaty of 1820 with these Sheikhs states:- 'If any shall attack them ^i.e. the ships of the Sheikh the British Government shall take notice it.' This in effect means protection by sea (though not by land). C Koweit. In 1914 a letter was sent to the Sheikh in which he was given an assurance that 'Koweit shall be recognised as an independent principality under British protection'. Thus, as regards Koweit, the position is quite clear. ( We also have Agreements, dated 1892, with Bahrein and the Trucial Sheikhdoms whereby they agreed (1) not to enter into any agreement or correspondence with any other Power than the British Government: ( 2 ) not to receive the agents of any other Government: and (3) not to cede, sell, mortgage or -.otherwise give for occupation any part of their territories save to the British Government. Thus H.M.G. have exclusive control of the foreign relations of all these . 1 Sheikhdoms/Draft Paper Department. Sheikhdoms, and consequently international responsibility for their affairs. ( It may be felt that the provisions of the treaties, combined with the de facto position in which H.M.Gr.find themselves in the Gulf (which would necessitate intervention in any major crisis affecting the safety and peace of the Sheikhdoms) point towards the inclusion of the Sheikhdoms under the phrase 'territories under H.M.’s protection' in the Act. I[m Oi/U Yours sincerelYt •JlDraft Paper. G.' r . Rendel, Esn., C.M.G., ^. 0 . t My dear Rendel, -8JUN 1956 Please refer to yoar letter of the / 22nd Pay on the question of customs duty on red oxide imported from iibu Musa. I agree with you that if we can obtain imperial preference for Commander Bayldon’s imports it will be all to the good; and that it is unnecessary on account of any political consideration to give the Board of Customs a lead in the direction of not regarding the Persian Gulf Sheikhdoms as under H.L.’s protection. It is for the Board to decide whether they are so or not^ for the purposes of the Imports D. ty, Act. To assist them we should give them the facts regarding the status of these Sheikhdoms resulting from practice and their treaties # with 1 1 • I..• G• I accordingly propose, i f you concur, to write to Walker on the lines of the enclosed draft, giving him the facts and leaving the Board to consider what conclusion they must reach in the li&amp;ht of &lt; v s— ahem. I would send *a copy of it to J ’ennelly. j Consideration of our general policy in the Gulf appears to be largely irrelevant ^0 uhe present issue, which only concerns as you point out, the interpretation of Section 21 of the Import Duties Act. As Regards your reference to conclusion (1) if the 42nd eeting of the f .E.(0) Sab- Committee/Committee aboat Tracial Coast Policy, we of coarse quite agree with this, so far as it goes (in fact it has never struck us as '71 pSxjfwX /H. anything but the statement of an axiom), ^tnis f^ni- among others is stated m the draft letter to '/alker a u t U ^ e. ^ (gaj J. C, WALXOiu(E 24b3/84b3/91) * L ^ f i o cr o ^ ^ ?? j o D o :) j |C 3f) FOREIGN OFFICE, S.W.l. 22nd May, 1936. My dear Walton, We have 'been considering Clauson’s letter P.Z. 2574/36 of 28th April to Brenan on the subject of the status of Sharjah, and the connected question of customs duty on red oxide imported from Abu Musa. 2, We are, of course, concerned here only with the question of the status of the Trucial Sheikhs ( and of course of Bahrain and Koweit as well) for the nurposes of Section 21 of the Import Duties Act 1932. 3. When tnis question was considered last year the political situation in the Gulf was somewhat different from what it is today, and when Johnstone 1 s letter E 647/4/91 of 12th February to Laithwaite was written we seem to have been actuated by anxiety to avoid any action which might provoke further trouble with Persia in connexion with our position in the Gulf and possibly /lead J. C. Walton, Esq., C. B. , M.C.lead to our premature ejection from Henjam and Basidu. We therefore put up the best case we could for ’’straining the law to meet political exigencies without ’’absolutely misrepresenting it”. 4. Since then the position has undergone a material change. We have evacuated Henjam and Basidu, so that we have less to fear from Persia, and we are no longer much concerned over the increasingly remote possibility of Persia pursuing claims on the Arab side of the Persian Gulf. Meanwhile the development of the air route on that side of the Gulf and the progress made in the negotiation of oil concessions have produced a tendency to bring the Arab Sheikhdoms more closely under our control, and it has been definitely agreed by the Middle East (Official) Sub-Committee of the Committee of Imperial Defence (at its 42nd meeting of 24th September last), that His Majesty’s Government must admit ultimate international responsibility for the affairs of these territories. 5. It is, therefore, not only difficult for us to contend that Sharjah and indeed the other Sheikhdoms of the Trucial Coast, including Bahrain and Koweit but /excludingexcluding of course Muscat, are not 'territories under 'His Majesty’s protection', but it in fact no longer accords -with our general policy in the Gulf to support that contention. In other words our policy points in the opposite direction and there is in our view no need to 'strain the law' any more. b. We think, therefore, that the India Office would be perfectly justified in informing the Board of Customs and Excise that, since Laithwaite’s letter P.Z. 1057/55 of 14th February, 1955, was written, political changes in the Persian Gulf have caused His Majesty’s Government to reconsider their attitude towards the question raised in Walker’s letter of 24th January, and that the position today warrants their advising the Board that Koweit, Bahrain and the Trucial Sheikhdoms of the Gulf are 'territories subject to the 'protection of His Majesty’s Government' within the meaning of the Act. 7. The acceptance of such a ruling by the Board of Customs and Excise would presumably enable the board to afford a satisfactory solution of Commander Bayldon’s difficulties regarding the importation of red oxidefrom At&gt;u Musa, and this would, of course, he all to the good. Yours sincerely,Any reply to this letter should be addressed to :— “ The Solicitor, Custom House, London E.C.3,” and the following Numbers quoted :— No. Solr’s. No. SOLICITOR’S OFFICE, at H.M. CUSTOMS and EXCISE LONDON My , E.C.3. fyjr 2nd key, 1936 fW* . Dear Clauson, Thank you for your letter enclosing copy correspondence in regard to the importation of red oxide from Abu kusa. Yours sincerely. R. J. Clauson, Es^., India Office, Whitehall, S.W.l.3436b 5000 1/35 Minute * ?z ♦(- Paper. P.Z. 2574/36 Department, 'is T * %i- 0 ' Mr, Clauson . Please see Mr. Fennelly* s letter belov/. This question has already been thrashed out in the correspondence under cover. Commander Bayldon can, I think, justifiably complain as being the unfortunate victim of our rather anomalous position in the Persian Gulf, but there seems to be nothing to do about it / aj wc must maintain our former attitude of refusing to recognise any of the Arab Sheikhdoms as part of the British Empire. 'TV red oxide deposits in Abu Musa are of considerable value^one would like, if possible, to make some except ion}/J* so. far as I can see 7 there is no means of doing SO^ t 4 A r'*i -ffc jh h J , Y Zj tfax ifoif- ** (toykt — Awt ° fwvJr Miu C^&lt;u^- 70 *ou* 'htMspi / iJk fcrf&lt;**uAS' ^ •% yA ** A *'(kUy ^ - ‘fyr ± ?ADraft Paper P. Z. 2574/36 Department '- !r \ A v T.V. Brenan, Esq., O.B.E., Foreign Office, S. W. Lrt btfAfr aduaty ImjU* flM'* (tJc, pziuu -t 7&lt;^t'K ^ 'UV ftdwJj , 2 8 APR 1936 Will you please refer to Ward's letter of B3rd July, 1935, No. E.4337/4/91 and connected correspondence about the status of Sharjah? I enclose a copy of a letter which I have received from Fennelly of the Board of Trade from which you will see that Commander Bayldon has once more raised the question whether the red oxide imported from Abu Musa must pay customs duty. jrt) —tn -his letter, there is a good deal to be /said in support of Commander Bayldon Vs view that he has been harshly treated, and there is the further point that we would like if possible to encourage the development of the Abu/Musa deposits, which are more or less under our control. We feel, however, /that it is impossible to differentiate^between the Arab Sheikhdoms, and it seems clear unfortun ately that /If we bring Sharjah within the Import Duties Act we shall inevitably in the course of time have to extenci similar treatment to the other Stages. The political objectionsto this in the particular^ case of Bahrein 1 HUPP' -j *£here seems no other course open to us than to reply/ 4599 5000 2.36.if mm* 1 • - r* 16 APR 1936 _lr m /-. •&lt; * ! 2574 ! looa i J £ C-A.-i SO/ J—. IT C:£O^C£ SV^££T, 15th April, 1936. Dear Glauson, k, IN I had a visit to-day from Commander Bayldon who is connected with the Golden Valley Ochre Company, one of the important companies in this country making pigments for paints. I think you know all about his project to develop a reu oxide of iron deposit in the Island of /xbu Musa in the Persian Gulf which is to take tne place of material now imported from Hormuz. Briefly the position is that red oxide of iron is not iron ore and is, therefore, subject to a general ad valorem duty of 10 per cent, unless it comes from the Empire, and Commander Bay1ton argues that Abu Musa, though it apparently belongs to the Sheik of Sharjah, is sufficiently under our protection to be entitled to preference. The duty amounts to about 9/- a ton, and as the material from Abu Musa is not uniformally so good as that from Hormuz at least that margin is necessary to meet the cost of extra treatment, etc., in M.J. Clauson, Esq. - :will not admit this material duty-free unless they have a huling from you either that the Island is 'territory which is under His Majesty's protection' within the meaning of Section 5(1) of the Import Duties Act, 1932, or that it falls under 'India' in Section 4 of the same Act. Possibly Commander Baylton has been told the answer to all this already, but we would be glad to know what the position is. Yours sincerely,2/F./35. Gillotts House Henley-on-Thames Dear Ir Clauson, L.an^ thanks for .cur letter cf the 1st inst, and tor all the trouble }ou have taken in the i atter. 1 take it that the explanation is that the Act of parliament under v.hich duties are levied is so v.orded , as not to le wide enough to cover free imports from a country standing in the particular relationship to our selves,which S&amp;arjah does ,an om/ission possiblj quite accidental but unsurmountable. I will pass the infer' ation to the Golden Valley Com} anj with regret,as the. are binding so r an\ dif'bicult^ 3n the opening u^. ot this trade,that 1 leai tl^ev v&gt;ill find this rather unexpected one,rather a Llow. Yours sincerely Clauson i^sq The Political Department The India Office S.Vt.l.IMiixA Oi'i'iOii, &amp;iil. ( l‘3£t}.Ajluli t Li * 1st Aujust, ±voo Dear OoifMander Bayl&amp;on, ,.ould you kindly refer to your corroB^/ondonce last month with Laithwaite about the Abji Muoa Oxide. Laithvfaite has now left the Le par talent temporarily, and I am doing his work. He made enquiries as he px’omisad to, to see if anything oould be done to assist you, but from information which we have now reooived from the duotoms it is, I am afraid, pretty clear that the legal considerations involved make it impossible for your company to receive exemption. I have no doubt that you will have heard or be hearin^ officially from the Customs. Yours sincerely. Commander . J. ^ayldon, L. h. ( etd), Gillotts House, Henley on Thauass.near Clauson, Your letter of the 24th to Walker about ochre from Abu Musa in the territory of the Sheikh of Shargah. I note that you say that politically the position in regard to Shargah is the same as that in regard to Bahrein* We acted on the view that Bahrein was not covered by Section 21 of the Import Duties Act, 1932, and we had better take a similar line in the present case. We are issuing instructions accordingly. Yours sincerely, M* J. Clauson, Esq*, India Office, Whitehall, S.W*1* PE''' -H. 3 0JUL1935INDIA OPPICA, mnrnALL, 3.w. i. 24th July 1935. Dear Walker, C,V. Lalthwaite Is temporarily leaving this Department ana I am taKing on his work. You will remember the corresponience with him unaer our reiex*ence P. Z.4492/35 on the question oi the auty to be paia on rea oxiue importea by the Golaen Yttlley company iroiii Abu ^Usa in the territory of the 3heikh of shargah. Zm we have gone into the question with the Foreign Office, but I am not sure that there is very much wnich we can ao to help, politically the position in regara to sh&amp;rgah is the same as that in regard to Bahrein, as explaineu in i/*ithwaite*s letter to you of 14th February last, p. 1037/35, and it must be for the Customs to aeciae, in the light of this, what attitude to adopt on the question of the payment of auty. 3. I should, however, be grateful if you could let me know, if possible in the next two or three days, what/ Walker, &amp;sq., solicitor’s Oifice, Board of customs and excise Custom House, £.C« 3* »•tost ueciBion you reach in the oatter, as we are anxious to reply to the private letter froiii Bayrlaon of which copies sent to you under our reference P.'',.4482/35 of the 11th July. Yours sincerely. CLAU30N.(E 4337/4/91). immediate. FOREIGN OFFICE, S.W.l. 23rd July, 1935. Dear Clauson, I am writing to you in reply to Laithwaite^ letter to me P.Z. 4492/35 ol‘ 13th July, about the status of Sharjah, as I understand that he has now more or less handed over to you the ordinary Persian Gulf work. We agree with Laithwaite that there is a good deal in what Coimnander Bayldon says in his letter, and it seems hard that the 'special interest' of His Majesty’s Government in Sharjah should necessitate his company giving certain guarantees as a condition of obtaining their concession, while at the same time they are prevented from enjoying the customs advantages which 'Protectorates' may enjoy. Nevertheless, as matters stand, and so long as the status of the Gulf Sheikhdoms remains in its present anomalous condition, we cannot see that there is any course open to us other than that suggested in paragraph 4 of Laithwaite’s letter, and we accordingly concur in the action proposed therein. M. J. Clauson, msq. m As a matter of fact the Board of Customs have already/■already 'been informed, in paragraph 4 of Laithwaite’s confidential letter No. P.Z. 1037/35 or 14th February to Walker (which way based on a minute by Beckett), that the position in regard to the Trucial Sheikhdoms is the same as that in regard to Bahrein. OG uy&gt;*jaK~Any reply to this letter should be addressed to :— “ The Solicitor, Custom House, London E.C.3,” and the following Numbers quoted:— Secty’s. No SOLICITOR’S OFFICE, (5 H.M. CUSTOMS and EXCISE, LONDON, E.C.3. 12th July, 1935. Sir, I beg to acknowledge the receipt of your letter of yesterday's date for which I am obliged I am, Sir, Your most obedient Servant, The Under Secretary of State, Political Dept., India Office, London, S. W. 1.i « ,.449ii/3b. LONDON, 1. 13th July 1 j35. ly uear Ward, l^foula you refer to Ken Jalln;ito^ie , s letter to ii^e of aOtft February last, £ 647/4/^1* embodyiag the sub stance of a iiiinute by Beckett draft reply v^iich we naa proposed to send to m enquiry by tiie Boaru of Customs and incise about the status of Bahrein? Copies of the reply sent In the If ht of Beckett’s minute to the Customs were sent you unaer my letter to Johnstone of 14th February, F.'* 1037/35. 2. An almost precisely similar question has now arisen in the case of 3hargah« The correspondence with COiiatiander Bsylaon, copies of which I enclose, shows the position. The solicitor’s Department at trie customs have been in touch with me on tne question by telephone ana t re anxious lor aavice as to the line to be taken. Fending a further communication from us they propose, I understand, to mark timw#- Tiie legal question is, of course, one for the customs to settle, and tue only matter for uecleion by us is whether we ought to ,ive them any lead in one direction or the other. Partly because of the special difficulties connected with the status of Bahrein, we gave them no lead in trie earlier correspondence. (Those difficulties ao not exist in same oegree in the case of ohurgah, but the fact that there Is a Persian claim to Abu iusa is perhaps a relevant factor). I tun rather disposed to think that in the circumstances there is nothing for it but (a) to inform the customs that the position in regard to jh&amp;rgah is the same as that in regard to Juhrein, as explained in uy letter to Walker of the Customs, P.2.1037 of 14th February last, (b) on receiving an indication from the Customs of the line they propose to take in the light of an intimation to this effect, to reply to Counmnder Bayluon saying that we have explained the position fully to tne Board of customs, but that we have reason/reason to I oar that the technical legal difficulties connected with the definition of 'protectorate* are such that ee gather that it is unlikely that taa custoins (with whom, of course, the uecision rests) will be able to cake any concession to him. b, will you let me know as soon an possible whether toe Foreign Office agree? Biere is a good aeai of force in oohiaander Bayluon’s remarks and one would be glad, if it were possible, to take some concession to him. Yours sincerely, J.G. LAI1HWAITE.11 JUL1935 r 29/6/35. Gillotts House Henley-on-Thames Dear Lr Laithivaite, kanj thanks ter i cur letter ct' the 2 6th June vhich 1 sent on to the 6.V Comianj who have taken the Unfortunately Sharjah,as ma; well Le iiragined, does not come on thuir printed list of 'Protectorates' \ hole situation I am writing' to ask you if 1 ray enlist the good offices of The India Office in the matter,in the first instance, and lefore the UV Company takes the matter up further. Without official explanation it seems to me iroballe that a wrong perspective may well be arrived at,unless,in the first instance,the board of Trade are advised as tc v.hat is the real situation,for whilst it is jrob&amp;bl} correct to say that Sharjah nay not L^e a protectorate in one sense,yet in effect,it is ncre of a protectorate than c.re many ethers,so officially In no ordinary Lritish Protectorate .is it naeeog necessary for undertakings to be oi veD leases of matter up with the Cisterns Authorities at Lristol. so the matter will have to Le taken up with the board of Trade in London. In view of the peculiar circumstances of the styled.—I V such 'L thine red oxide shall not ;ass into the hands of anyone,not British subjects,and so ; -cn,and vhilst fully apereciating the necessity for such restrictions, — 1 feel that it would seem ver^ inconsistent,if WniTe submitting to restrictions more severe than usual,one is debarred from the compensating advantage of freedom from Customs duties,usual in cases of protectorates, owing to a technical wording of the position which inadequately describes the actual effects of the position and 1 think that it is one of those cases where inter departmental communication night well clear the situation in a way q uite impossible te outside persons^ such os the G.V.Company. If )ou consider my view to be a not unreasonable one,I should be most grateful if you would te kind enough to put the matter \i\ to The board qf Trade,before we do anything further in the matter. lours sincerely J.G.Laithwaite Esq The India Office S.w.lk, Draft Paper. t&gt; &lt;{/&gt; Ar ' l/l-L f political Department. DRAFT LETTER % b JUN 1935 ■ ^omnanaer R.C. Baylaon, &gt; R«N.(Retd.), Gillotts House, Henl ey - on- Tdanie s. Mr. Walton, Please see Commander Bay1don f s letter below and also the correspondence with the solicitor to the Board of Customs last February about the position of Bahrein, consequent on which, the Customs informs me, they ruled that Bahrein was not_entitled to a preference. I think (after informal discussion with the Customs) that we might reply on the lines of the present draft, -t^atgte^he . decision ipho □ ■■ uii njuUikoefc I imagine, probably be similar to that taken in the case of Bahrein, although the Customs do not wish at this stage definitely to commit themselves regarding it. 4' / 7 U) 'M. I OOPY SENT DY AIR MAIL ©f y (3+1 ■ l a/ Dear Commander Baylaon, J^any thanks for your letter of the 18th June about the Abu Musa oxihe. 2. The Sheikh of Shargah is an independent ruler in special treaty relations with H.M.G. Under the terms of his treaties he is precluded from entering into any agreement or correspondence witn any power other than the Britisn Govt., from consenting without tne consent of H.M.G. to the residence within his territory of the agent of any other Government, and ,^ from ceding, selling, mortgaging, or otherwise giving lor occupation any \ part of his territory, save to H.M.G.^ He has also undertaken a variety of obligations in relation to the prohibition of the slave trade, the arms traffic, and tne maintenance of the Maritime Truce in the Persian Gul^ H.M.G. on their part nave undertaken certain specific obligations in regard to the defence of tne sheikh’s vessels against attack while the effect of the undertakings entered into above is to vest in them responsibility for nis foreign relations. From-thia you will oec unui*i while shargah is not in tho striaan,-;* * ariti-'n ,wy-, tr ^ the/18/6/35. 43gb G 'i Gillotts House ’Henley-on-Thames —- ; ^•4' f . L Dear Lr LaithYiaite Uur iirst consignmtnt of L usa oxide v.ill le arriving in this country an^ dav nov» and the Customs Officials at Avonmouth are raising questions as to its 'nationality”. Would iou therefore le kind enough to give me some letter which the Golden Valle} Co can shew to It ¥.111 le interesting to see of what value the oxide turns cut to be from a commercial point of view. them to vouch for the fact that ti-tt the Sheik of Sharjah i v s a person under British protection or ^ritish influence and that Alu Lusa is one cf his possessions,so that no dut} need be paid it. lours sincerely J.G*Laithvvaite Ksq The India Office S.W.I.P~L. .oVV VC Mr. Waicely, With reference to our recent conversation, I think you may he interested in the correspondence heiow with the Foreign Office on the question of the position of Bahrein etc. in international law. I think that the Foreign Office are now fully alive to the difficulty of pressing the strict legal view and to the danger of giving any publicity to it. 21 .ii.JS-' 7h^ ^ k OLSI^. tvA VL k . ^7trn INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL, 3.W. 1. p,2.1031/35. Oonf iaential . m V') 14tA February 1955. Dear walker, I am sorry to have been so long in replying to your letter o£ the 54th January on the question whether the Bahrein Islands are within the British Empire for the purposes of the Import Duties Act, 1935, but we thought it well to go into tne question, which, as you will see from what follows is one of some little delicacy and difficulty, fully with the Foreign Office. 2. The definition of 'The British Empire' in Section 21 of the Import Duties Act, 1932, is, of course, a definition of the British Empire for the purposes of this Act and not for general purposes and the question at issue is merely whether Bahrein is or is not covered by any of the woras of tnis definition section. The only words by which it could be covered, if it were covered at all, are the words 'territories under His Majesty*' C.V. walker, Esq. Solicitor* s Gusto 3 /3. The position is tnat under treaties concluded with the Rulers of Bahrein the sheikh of Bahrein has no relations with any power other than His IViajesty’s Government and His Majesty’s Government deal with foreign powers over any questions which arise in relation to Bahrein and have also undertaken certain obligations to protect the territories of the sheikh from foreign aggression. As regards the internal government of his territory the sheikh is left full independence, except that jurisdiction over British subjects and foreigners is exercised by His Majesty, who is represented in Bahrein by a Political Agent. Though it must be recognised that the expression territories under His Majesty's protection'is held to cover territories such as the Malay States, Sarawak, Brunei and Zanzibar, where there is a native ruler who enjoys independence in the matter of internal government of his territories in which His Majesty does not directly exercise jurisdiction except over foreigners and where from the formal point of view the position is rather similar to that of Bahrein, nevertheless there are grounds for distinguishing Bahrein from those territories. In the first place, the measure of control exercised in fact by His Majesty's Government in the other/- 3 - other territories mentioned, above is ^^Qater than in Bahrein, and in the second place, there are political difficulties which would he caused by regarding Bahrein as covered by these words in this Act,which do not apply in the case of the other territories mentioned. For political reasons it has been deemed expedient in communications to foreign governments to stress the independence of Bahrein. Apart from this, the Ruler of Bahrein would probably take exception to the inclusion of his territories as part of the British Empire, even under a purely statutory definition of the British Empire for a particular purpose, the niceties of which he would never understand. In these circumstances, although from the point of view of strict international law it would be correct to regard Bahrein as a territory under His Majesty’s protection, it does not necessarily follow that Bahrein should be regarded as coming under these words in this particular Act of Parliament, and the view might be taken that the connection with Bahrein is in practice so loose that it should not be regarding as coming within the intention of Parliament in enacting this section and we would therefore suggest that the Board of Customs should/4 should act on the view that Banrein is not covered hy the section. If the ruling of the customs in this sense were challenged the question might, of course, come before a court, which would then have to decide the natter on the basis of such information as was officially communicated to the court on behalf of the Crown. 4. The position in regard to Koweit and the Sheikhdoms of the Trucial Coast is the same as that in regard to Bahrein, as described above. The sultanate of Muscat and Oman is, however, In a wholly different position ana though His Ivajesty's Government exercise a particular influence there and protect nationals of the sultanate in foreign countries, the sultan is still free to enter into airect relations with other powers and therefore even from the point of view of strict international law his territories would not be covered by the expression 'territories under His Majesty's protection' and a fortiori not covered by this expression in an Act of Parliament of the United Kingdom. Yours sincerely, 'J.G# LAITHWAITE.INDIA OPPICS, ■ r~y K.d. WHITOiALL, 3.’V. 1. P.”.1037/55. 14th pebruary I'j35. hy hear Ken, kany thanks lor your letter of the 12tu February, S 647/4/91, and for the itost valuable surest ions contained in It as to the reply to be sent to the Customs, m agree entirely and I enclose a copy of the reply, based on your letter, viilch has no.? been sent to Ta lker• Yours ever, GILBERT LAITHWAITS. Johnstone, K 0 Q., Foreign Office.* NOTE. The effect of excluding Bahrein from tne British Empire for the purposes of the Import Duties Act, 1932, will he to leave goods imported from Bahrein liable to the special 10% ad valorem duty and to any additional duty which might he imposed on luxury goods, or goods of a kind which are being produced or are likely within a reasonable time to be produced in the United Kingdom in quantities which are substantial in relation to United Kingdom consumption. The Act provides a special preference for (a) the Dominions, India and Southern Rhodesia; and (b) for goods ’•which are shown to the satisfaction of the Commissioners to have been consigned from any part of the British Empire and grown, produced, or manufactured in;(a) any part of His Iviajesty’s dominions, outside a country to which the last preceding section of this Act applies (i.e. a Dominion or India) is or (b) any territory which/under His Majesty’s protection...” 2/r 22P) of the expression 'British quoted in Mr. Walker*s letter of 24th January on P.Z.583/35 helow. fcu. - 2 2. The definition ^ Empire' is in the termsImport Duties Act, 1932. [22 Geo. 5. Ch. 8.] ARRANGEMENT OF SECTIONS. Part I. General ad valorem Duty and Additional Duties. Section. 1. Charge of general ad valorem customs duty of ten per cent. 2 . Constitution of Advisory Committee. 3. Additional duty of customs on special classes or descriptions of goods. 4. Preference for Dominions, India and Southern Rhodesia. 5. Colonial preference. 6 . Application of s. 8 of 9 &amp; 10 Geo. 5. c. 32 for purpose of Imperial preference under Part I. 7. Preference in case of certain foreign goods. 8 . Charge of duty in case of composite goods. 9. Power of Board of Trade to require information. 10. Prevention of disclosure of information. 11. Provision as to shipbuilding yards. Part II. Duties in respect of Foreign Discrimination. 12. Power of Board of Trade to impose supplementary duties in case of foreign discrimination. Part III. General. 13. Exception for goods imported with a view to re exportation. 14. Provision as to re-importation of goods of a class or description liable to duty under Act. [Prize 6d. Net.] A iw. | A.D. 1932. Section. — 15. Value of goods for purpose of Act. 16. Determination of disputes as to value of goods. 17. Conversion of ad valorem duty into duty charge able by weight or other measure of quantity. 18. Computation of equivalent of ad valorem rate. 19. Provisions as to orders. 20. Declaration as to operation of s. 8 of 16 &amp;T1 / Geo. 5. c. 22. 21. Interpretation. 22. Exercise of powers of Board of Trade under Act. 23. Short title. Schedules : First Schedule.—Goods exempted from the general ad valorem duty. Second Schedule.—Becommendation and allow ance of drawback. Third Schedule.—Supplementary provisions as to Imperial preference:— Part I.—Provisions of section 8 of the Finance Act, 1919, as modified and applied for the purpose of sections 4 and 5 of this Act. Part II.—Proof of origin of goods.A 2 1 [22 Geo. 5.] Import Duties Act, 1932. [Ch. 8.] A'Yl'S CHAPTER 8. An Act to provide for the imposition of a general a.d. 1932 . ad valorem duty of customs and of additional duties on any goods chargeable with the duty aforesaid, for the imposition of duties on goods produced or manufactured in a foreign country which discriminates in the matter of importation as against goods produced or manufactured in the United Kingdom, in certain other parts of His Majesty’s dominions, in protectorates or in mandated territories, and for purposes connected with the matters aforesaid. [29th February 1932.] Most Gracious Sovereign, W E, Your Majesty’s most dutiful and loyal subjects, the Commons of the United Kingdom in Parliament assembled, with a view to the restricting in the national interest of the importation of goods into the United Kingdom, to the providing of a remedy in cases where a foreign country discriminates in the matter of importation as against goods produced or manufactured in the United Kingdom, in certain other parts of Your Majesty’s dominions or in territories under Your Majesty’s protection or in respect of which a mandate is being exercised by Your Majesty’s Government of the United Kingdom, and to the making of an addition to the public revenue, have freely and voluntarily resolved to give and grant unto Your Majesty the duties for which[Ch. 8.] Import Duties Act, 1932. [22 Geo. 5.] A.D 1932. Charge of general ad valorem customs duty of ten per cent. provision is hereinafter contained; and do therefore most humbly beseech Your Majesty that it may be enacted, and be it enacted, by the King’s most Excellent Majesty, by and with the advice and consent of the Lords Spiritual and Temporal, and Commons, in this present Parliament assembled, and by the authority of the same, as follows :— A Part I. General ad valorem Duty and Additional Duties. 1.—(1) As from the first day of March, nineteen hundred and thirty-two, there shall, subject to the provi sions of this Act, be charged on all goods imported into the United Kingdom, other than goods exempted as hereinafter provided from the provisions of this section, a duty of customs equal to ten per cent, of the value of the goods. (2) The following goods shall be exempted from the provisions of this section— (а) goods for the time being chargeable with a duty of customs by or under any enactment other than this Act, but not including (subject to the provisions of this Act) any composite goods in the case of which duty is chargeable under any such enactment as aforesaid because some (but not all) of their components are articles so chargeable; (б) goods of any class or description specified in the First Schedule to this Act or added to that Schedule by an order made under the next following subsection. (3) The Treasury, after receiving a recommendation from the Committee to be constituted under the follow ing provisions of this Act that goods of any class or description ought to be exempted from the provisions of this section, and after consultation with the appro priate department, may by order direct that goods of all or any of the classes or descriptions specified in the recom mendation shall be added to the First Schedule to this Act: Provided that, except in such cases as seem to them of special urgency, the said Committee shall not take 23 ct, 1932. [22 Geo. 5.] [22 Geo. 5.] Import Duties Act, 1932. [Ch. 8.] ned; and do therefore [ajesty that it may be le King’s most Excellent and consent of the Lords ommons, in this present le authority of the same, rY and Additional day of March, nineteen lall, subject to the provi- all goods imported into lan goods exempted as 'ovisions of this section, l per cent, of the value ,11 be exempted from the 1 chargeable with a duty * ir any enactment other including (subject to the any composite goods in is chargeable under any esaid because some (but ponents are articles so ascription specified in the s Act or added to that r made under the next civing a recommendation tituted under the foilow- ,t goods of any class or &gt;ted from the provisions altation with the appro- ’ direct that goods of all or ns specified in the recom- First Schedule to this Act: such cases as seem to Committee shall not take into consideration the question whether any recommen- A.D. 1932. dation ought to be made under this subsection until the p A ~ ^ expiration of six months from the passing of this Act. ^on t . (4) The duty imposed by this section is in this Act referred to as “ the general ad valorem duty.” (5) The provisions of the Second Schedule to this Act shall have effect with respect to the recommendation and allowance of drawback in respect of the general ad valorem duty. 2.—(1) For the purpose of giving advice and assist- Constitu- ance in connection with the discharge by the Treasury tion of of their functions under this Act, there shall be consti- p tuted a committee, to be called “ the Import Duties Advisory Committee,” consisting of a chairman and not less than two or more than five other members to be appointed by the Treasury. (2) The members of the Committee shall hold office for a period of three years and shall be eligible for re-appointment from time to time on the expiration of their term of office. If a member becomes, in the opinion of the Treasury, unfit to continue in office or incapable of performing his duties under this Act, the Treasury shall forthwith declare his office to be vacant and shall notify the fact in such manner as they think fit, and thereupon the office shall become vacant. (3) The Committee shall, as soon as may be after the commencement of this Act, take into consideration the provisions of this Act, and shall, from tune to time, take into consideration any representations which may be made to them with respect to matters on which, under the provisions of this Act, action may be taken on a recommendation by the Committee, and may make recommendations to the Treasury with respect to the matters aforesaid. (4) The Treasury shall publish in such manner as they think fit any recommendation made to them by the Committee as soon as may be after they have made an order in pursuance of the recommendation or have deter mined to make no order on the recommendation. (5) The expenses of the Committee to such an amount as may be approved by the Treasury (including[Ch. 8.] Import Duties Act, 1932. [22 Geo. 5.] A.D. 1932. Part I. — cont. Additional duty of customs on special classes or descriptions of goods. the expenses of their staff and such salaries or other remuneration paid to all or any of the members as the Treasury may determine) shall be paid out of moneys provided by Parliament. (6) The Committee may make rules— (а) for regulating the proceedings, includin^®lQe quorum, of the Committee; and (б) for authorising the delegation of any of the functions of the Committee to a sub-commit tee consisting of members of the Committee. (7) The Committee, so far as they consider it necessary or desirable so to do for the purpose of the proper discharge of their functions, may by notice in writing require any person to furnish them with returns or other information, or, subject to the payment or tender of the reasonable expenses of his attendance, to attend as a witness before them or before any person authorised by them and to give evidence or to produce documents, and if any person fails without reasonable excuse to comply with the provisions of any such notice, he shall be liable on summary conviction to a fine not exceeding fifty pounds, and in the case of a second or subsequent conviction to a fine not exceeding two hundred pounds : Provided that the power of the Committee under this subsection to require a person to attend as a witness before a person authorised by them shall not be exercised unless the Committee are satisfied that, having regard to the nature of the proposed inquiry, it can be conducted more conveniently or more efficiently by a person so authorised than by the Committee, and that the person proposed to be authorised possesses the necessary qualifications for the purpose. (8) The Committee or any person authorised by them shall have power to take evidence on oath, and for that purpose to administer oaths. (^) Where it appears to the Committee that an additional duty of customs ought to be charged in respect of goods of any class or description which are chargeable with the general ad valorem duty and which, in their opinion, are either articles of luxury or articles of a kind which are being produced or are likely within a reasonable time to be produced in the United Kingdom 4ct, 1932. [Ch. 8.] [22 Geo. 5.] [22 Geo. 5.] Import Duties Act, 1932. ' such salaries or other y of the members as the be paid out of moneys ke rules— oceedings, includin^lQe aittee; and elegation of any of the mittee to a sub-commit- ibers of the Committee. r as they consider it for the purpose of the ions, may by notice in mish them with returns jet to the payment or es of his attendance, to m or before any person evidence or to produce ails without reasonable ions of any such notice, conviction to a fine not he case of a second or ie not exceeding two F the Committee under erson to attend as a d by them shall not be re satisfied that, having )sed inquiry, it can be r more efficiently by a s Committee, and that ithorised possesses the impose. person authorised by idence on oath, and for ■■ the Committee that an ^ht to be charged in description which are dorem duty and which, 3s of luxury or articles ced or are likely within in the United Kingdom in quantities which are substantial in relation to United A.D. 1932. Kingdom consumption, the Committee may recommend p ART j to the Treasury that an additional duty ought to be conf ’ charged on goods of that class or description at such rate as is specified in the recommendation. ^ (2) In deciding what recommendation, if any, to make for the purposes of this section, the Committee shall have regard to the advisability in the national interest of restricting imports into the United Kingdom and the interests generally of trade and industry in the United Kingdom, including those of trades and industries which are consumers of goods as well as those of trades and industries which are producers of goods. (3) The Treasury, after receiving a recommendation from the Committee that an additional duty of customs ought to be charged on goods of any class or description, , may, if they think fit so to do, and after consultation with the appropriate Department, by order direct that such additional duty of customs as is specified in the order (being a duty at a rate not exceeding the rate specified in the recommendation) shall be charged on the importation into the United Kingdom of goods of all or any of the classes or description specified in the recommendation, and an additional duty so directed to be charged shall for all purposes be deemed to be chargeable under this section. (4) An order under this section directing an additional duty to be charged may direct that it shall be charged— (a) by reference to value or to weight or any other measure of quantity; (b) for any period or periods, whether continuous or not, or without any limit of period; (c) at different rates for different periods or parts of periods. (5) Where it is apprehended that goods of any class or description which, by reason of their being charge able with a duty of customs by or under any enactment other than this Act, are not chargeable with the general ad valorem duty, will shortly become chargeable with the general ad valorem duty by reason of the duty by[Ch. 8.] •Import Duties Act, 1932. [22 Geo. 5.] A.D. 1932. or under that other enactment ceasing to be chargeable, p Committee may make a recommendation under this -^ont sec tion with respect to goods of that class or description, and the Treasury may make an order accordingly, so, however, that the order shall not have effect until the date on which the general ad valorem duty becomes chargeable. ® (6) The provisions of the Second Schedule to this Act shall have effect with respect to the recommenda tion and allowance of drawback in respect of additional duties. (7) The Committee may at any time make to the Treasury a recommendation that any additional duties which are chargeable, or any drawbacks which are to be allowed, under this Act ought to be varied or discontinued. (8) A duty imposed by this section is in this Act referred to as an “ additional duty.” Preference for Dominions, India and Southern Rhodesia. 22 Geo. 5 c. 4. 4* (1) This section shall apply to the following countries, that is to say, the Dominions within the meaning of the Statute of Westminster, 1931, India and Southern Rhodesia, and any territories in respect of which a mandate of the League of Nations is being exercised by, or which are administered under the authority of, the Government of any such Dominion as aforesaid. (2) In the case of goods which are shown to the satisfaction of the Commissioners to have been consigned ^ rom an y P ar t °f ^e British Empire and grown, pro duced or manufactured in any country to which this section applies, neither the general ad valorem duty nor any additional duty shall be chargeable until the ntteenth day of November, nineteen hundred and thirty- two, or if a later date is fixed for the purposes of this section by resolution of the Commons House of Parlia ment either generally or as respects any particular country then, in cases to which the resolution applies, Until that lofor. , [OJ . tne first day of November mneteen hundred and thirty-two, the Treasury ma y ; on the recommendation of the Secretary of State! by Older direct as respects goods of any class 01 desciiption specified m the order, being goods which are shown to the satisfaction of the Commissioners to 6cty 1932. [22 Geo. 5.] Import Duties Act, 1932. [Ch. 8.] [22 Geo. 5.] easing to be chargeable, ^mmendation under this hat class or description, i order accordingly, so, )t have effect until the valorem duty becomes lecond Schedule to this set to the recommenda- n respect of additional any time make to the » any additional duties vbacks which are to be s varied or discontinued. section is in this Act _ »&gt; pply to the following Dominions within the ainster, 1931, India and *ries in respect of which ions is being exercised 3r the authority of, the n as aforesaid. lich are shown to the io have been consigned npire and grown, pro- sountry to which this eral ad valorem duty &gt; chargeable until the m hundred and thirty- the purposes of this nons House of Parlia- ipects any particular the resolution applies, st day of November, ', the Treasury may, Secretary of State, ods of any class or f, being goods which he Commissioners to have been consigned from any part of the British A.D. 1932. Empire and grown, produced or manufactured in any country specified in the order, being a country to which this section applies, that as from such date as may be specified in the order, not being earlier than the said fijt^nth day of November or, if any later day is fixed as aforesaid, not being earlier than that date, the general ad valorem duty or any additional duty or both such duties shall not be chargeable or shall be chargeable only at some specified rate less than the full rate, and where any such order is made, the provisions of this Act shall have effect accordingly. (4) Where by virtue of subsection (2) of this section any duty under this Part of this Act becomes charge able on goods grown, produced or manufactured in any country to which this section applies, goods consigned from that country shall, unless they are goods of a class or description specified in an order made with respect to that country under the last foregoing subsection, or are goods of a class or description which are not grown, produced, or manufactured in that country, be treated for the purposes of this section and of any order made thereunder with respect to any other country and for the purposes of the next following section of this Act as not having been consigned from a part of the British Empire. 5 # — (i) Neither the general ad valorem duty nor Colonial any additional duty shall be chargeable in respect of goods preference, which are shown to the satisfaction of the Commissioners to have been consigned from any part of the British Empire and grown, produced or manufactured in— (а) any part of His Majesty’s dominions outside the United Kingdom, other than a country to which the last preceding section of this Act applies; or (б) any territory which is under His Majesty’s protection. (2) His Majesty may by Order in Council declare that this section shall apply to any territory in respect of which a mandate of the League of Nations is being exercised by the Government of the United Kingdom as if that territory were a territory under His Majesty’s protection. 7[Ch. 8.] Import Duties Act, 1932. [22 Geo. 5.] 8 A.D. 1932. Part I. — cont. Application of s. 8 of 9 &amp; 10 Geo. 5. o. 32 for purpose of Imperial preference under Part I. 6. Such of the provisions contained in section eight of the Finance Act, 1919, as are set out with modifica tions in Part I of the Third Schedule to this Act shall a Pply for the purposes of the last two preceding sections of this Act, and the provisions of Part II of that Schedule shall have effect with respect to the evidence requir^i^to show that goods are by reason of the provisions ot che sections aforesaid free, whether in whole or in part, from any duty chargeable under this Part of this Act: Provided that, if any duty becomes so chargeable in respect of goods consigned from or grown, produced or manufactured in any country to which section four of this Act applies, the Board of Trade may by regulations modify the provisions of the said Schedule so far as may appear to them to be necessary to meet the circumstances of the case. Preference in case of certain foreign goods. '7.—(1) The Treasury may, on the recommendation of the Board of Trade, by order direct, as respects goods of any class or description specified in the order, being goods which are shown to the satisfaction of the Com missioners to have been consigned from, and grown, produced or manufactured in any foreign country specified in the order, that, as from such date as may be specified in the order, the general ad valorem duty, or any additional duty, or both such duties, shall not be chargeable or shall be chargeable only at some specified rate less than the full rate, and, where any such order is made, the provisions of this Act shall have effect accordingly. (2) The Board of Trade may make regulations pre scribing, either generally or in relation to goods of any particular class or description, the conditions which must be fulfilled in order to establish that goods have been grown, produced or manufactured in a foreign country specified in an order made under this section, and the Commissioners may in any case require an importer to furnish, in such form as they may prescribe, proof that *?Au 01 Z diti0 i n * 80 P rescribed b y the Board have been luinlled, and if such proof is not furnished to the Com missioners satisfaction, the goods shall not be deemed to be goods grown, produced or manufactured in that country.[22 Geo. 5.] Import Duties Act, 1932. [Ch. 8.] 8. Where by virtue of section one of this Act any A.D. 1932. composite goods would, if no other provision were made Pakt l in relation thereto by this Act, be chargeable both with the general ad valorem duty and with a duty of customs Charge of chargeable by or under some enactment other than this i n the general ad valorem duty shall be chargeable case of com- oiny up to the amount, if any, by which it exceeds the posite duty of customs chargeable by or under that other g 00 8 * enactment: Provided that nothing in this section shall be taken to affect the power of the Committee to make recom mendations with respect to any class or description of such goods, or the power of the Treasury to make an order in pursuance of any recommendation, as if they were goods chargeable with the general ad valorem duty, and if the Committee recommend that an additional duty shall be charged in respect of any class or description of such goods, the Committee may also recommend that any duty of customs chargeable m respect of goods of that class or description by or under any such other enactment as aforesaid shall either cease to be chargeable so long as the additional duty continues to be chargeable or shall continue to be chargeable, and an order made by the Treasury in pursuance of the recommendation may provide accordingly. 9.— (1) With a view to obtaining information as to Power of the condition and progress of trades and industries ^, ra( j e t0 engaged in the manufacture in the United Kingdom of squire in. goods of a class or description which, if they were formation, imported into the United Kingdom, would be chargeable with a duty of customs under this Part of this Act, the Board of Trade may, before the commencement of the year nineteen hundred and thirty-three and any su |^‘ sequent year, publish in the Gazette notice that they will require returns in relation to that year in accordance with the provisions of this section. (2) After any such notice has been published as respects any year, the Board of Trade may issue to any person who appears to the Board to ha\ e been during any part of that year the occupier or manager of any factory or workshop, being a factory or workshop in which it appears to the Board that the manufacture of any such goods as aforesaid is being carried on or has[Ch. 8.] Import Duties Act, 1932. [22 Geo. 5.] A.D. 1932. Part I. — cont. been carried on during that year or any part thereof, such form of return, and such instructions for filling up the form and delivering it to the Board, as they consider necessary for the purpose of obtaining, with respect to that factory or workshop and in relation to that year or any part thereof, information as to all or any of^fce following matters, namely :— (a) The quantity and value of output; (b) The quantity and cost of materials used; (c) The quantity and cost of fuel and electricity consumed; (d) The number of persons employed. (3) Every person to whom a form of return and instructions are issued under this section shall, in accordance with the instructions, fill up the form and deliver it to the Board of Trade, and if he fails to do so he shall for each offence be liable on summary conviction to a fine not exceeding ten pounds, and in the case of a continuing offence to a further fine not exceeding five pounds for each day during which the offence continues. (4) If any person to whom a form of return has been issued under this section makes a false return, he shall for each offence be liable on summary conviction to a fine not exceeding fifty pounds and, in the case of a second or subsequent conviction to a fine not exceeding two hundred pounds or to imprisonment for a term not exceeding twelve months or to both such fine and imprisonment. (5) For the purpose of this section— (а) the expressions “ factory ” and “workshop” have the same meanings as in the Factory and Workshop Acts, 1901 to 1929; (б) references to the manufacture of goods of a class or description which if they were imported into the United Kingdom would be chargeable with a duty of customs under this Part of this Act shall be deemed to include references to the subjection of goods of that class or description to any process and to the subjection of goods to any process 10» , 1932. [Ch. 8J [22 Geo. 5.] r or any part thereof, jtructions for filling up Board, as they consider ining, with respect to . relation to that year as to all or any ofjflfce f output; materials used; &gt;f fuel and electricity iployed. a form of return and his section shall, in fill up the form and [e, and if he fails to be liable on summary ig ten pounds, and in to a further fine not lay during which the a form of return has ikes a false return, he n summary conviction mds and, in the case iction to a fine not to imprisonment for a 3 or to both such fine ition— y ” and “ workshop ” igs as in the Factory 01 to 1929; acture of goods of a which if they were ed Kingdom would be by of customs under shall be deemed to le subjection of goods ption to any process : goods to any process @) [22 Geo. 5.] Import Duties Act, 1932. which renders them goods of that class or a.D. 1932. description; p — L (c) the expression “ the Gazette ” means the —amt ' London, Edinburgh and Belfast Gazettes. (6) The Board of Trade shall present to Parliament a. ^immary of the information obtained by them under tK., section in respect of any year. (7) The expenses incurred by the Board of Trade in carrying this section into effect shall, up to an amount approved by the Treasury, be defrayed out of moneys provided by Parliament. 10.—(1) No information relating to any individual Prevention business, being information which has been obtained by °1 disclosure the Committee or the Board of Trade by virtue of the orma provisions of this Act, shall, without the previous consent in writing of the owner for the time being of that business, be published or disclosed except to mem bers of the Committee or to a Government Department requiring that information for the purposes of this Act, or to a person authorised by the Committee or by a Government Department and requiring that information for those purposes, or except for the purposes of a prosecution under this Act. (2) If any person publishes or discloses any infor mation contrary to the provisions of this section, he shall be liable on summary conviction to a fine not exceeding fifty pounds and, on conviction on indictment, to imprisonment for a term not exceeding two years or to a fine not exceeding two hundred pounds, or to both such imprisonment and fine. H # (1) Where goods imported into the United Provision as Kingdom are consigned direct to a registered shipbuilding yard within the meaning of this section, the Commissioners may, subject to such conditions as they may impose ^ for securing that the goods are used for the building, repairing or refitting of ships in that yard, allow the goods to be imported free of any duty chargeable under this Part of this Act. (2) Where goods are brought into any such regis tered shipbuilding yard from any other part of the United Kingdom, the Commissioners may, subject to such12 [Ch. 8 .] Import Duties Act, 1932. [22 Geo. 5 .] A.D. 1932. conditions as aforesaid, treat the goods for the purpose Part I t ^ ie P rov i s i° ns of this Act relating to drawback as if _^ nl ' they had been exported from the United Kingdom. (3) The Commissioners, if it is shown to their satis faction that any premises in the United Kingdom are occupied and used for the purpose of the building, repairing or refitting of ships shall, on an applicajfc made to them in that behalf and on payment by me applicant of a fee of one pound, register those premises for the purposes of this section as a shipbuilding yard, and the expression “ registered shipbuilding yard ” in this section means premises so registered. Part II. Duties m respect of Foreign Discrimination. 12.—(1) If it appears to the Board of Trade that the difference between the treatment accorded in any foreign country (whether by way of the imposition of duties or the prohibition or restriction of importation or otherwise) to any goods produced or manufactured in a country to which this section applies and that so accorded to like goods produced or manufactured in crimination. an y ? ou ^ tT J other than a country to which this section applies is such as to amount to discrimination as against a country to which this section applies, the Board of Trade may, with the concurrence of the Treasury (given after consultation with any other Government department which appears to the Treasury to be interested) and subject to the provisions of this Act, bv order made for the purposes of this Part of this Act direct that there shall be charged on the importation into the United Kingdom of goods of any class or description produced or manufactured in that foreign country such duties of customs as may be specified m the order, and any duty so directed to be charged shall for all purposes be deemed to be chargeable under this Part of this Act. (2) Ihe countries to which this section applies are the United Kingdom (including the Isle of Man), the Channel Islands, the colonies and territories which ai i?- Majesty s protection or in respect of which a mandate is being exercised by the Government of the United Kingdom. Power of Board of Trade to impose supple mentary duties in case of[Ch. 8.] 5, 1932. [22 Geo. 5.] [22 Geo. 5.] Import Duties Act, 1932. goods for the purpose iting to drawback as if United Kingdom. is shown to their satis- : United Kingdom are pose of the building, tall, on an applicaj^a id on payment by tne register those premises is a shipbuilding yard, shipbuilding yard ” in istered. n Discrimination. b Board of Trade that nent accorded in any of the imposition of 3tion of importation or i or manufactured in applies and that so 1 or manufactured in to which this section crimination as against applies, the Board of ice of the Treasury y other Government the Treasury to be visions of this Act, by ;his Part of this Act 1 on the importation ods of any class or )ured in that foreign s may be specified in d to be charged shall chargeable under this is section applies are he Isle of Man), the id territories which on or in respect of l by the Government (3) The duties to be charged as aforesaid— A.D. 1932. (a) may be charged by reference to value or to p ART n. weight or any other measure of quantity, as — cont. may be provided in the order; and (b) shall not exceed one hundred per cent, of the value of the goods. (4) Any duty chargeable under this Part of this Act on any goods shall be charged in addition to any other duty of customs chargeable on those goods. (5) It shall be lawful for the Commissioners, on the importation into the United Kingdom of any goods which, if produced or manufactured in any particular foreign country, would be liable to duty under this Part of this Act and which are consigned either from that foreign country or from such other countries as the Board of Trade may direct, to require the importer to furnish to the Commissioners, in such form as they may prescribe, proof with respect to the country in which the goods were produced or manufactured, and unless proof is furnished to the satisfaction of the Commissioners that the goods were produced or manufactured elsewhere than in the first-mentioned country, the goods shall be deemed to be goods produced or manufactured in the first-mentioned country. Part III. General. 13. Where it is shown to the satisfaction of the Exception Commissioners that any goods are being imported solely for goods with a view to the re-exportation thereof— Saview (a) after undergoing a process in the United Kingdom to re-expor- which will not change the form or character of tation. the goods; or (6) after transit through the United Kingdom, or by way of transhipment, the Commissioners may, subject to such conditions as they think fit to impose for securing the re-exportation of the goods, allow the goods to be imported free of any duty chargeable under this Act. 13[Ch. 8.] Import Duties Act, 1932. [22 Geo. 5.] A.D. 1932 Part III. — cont. Provision as to re importation of goods of a class or description liable to duty under Act. 42 &amp; 43 Viet, c 21. Value of goods for purpose of Act. 14.^ Section six of the Customs and Inland Revenue Act, 1879, shall not apply to goods chargeable with a duty of customs under this Act, but where any goods (whether British or foreign) of a class or description so chargeable are re-imported into the United Kingdom after exportation therefrom and it is shown to the satisfaction of the Commissioners ^fcat any duty so chargeable in respect of the goods was uuly paid and either that no drawback of any such duty was allowed on exportation, or that any drawback so allowed has been repaid to the Exchequer, then {a) if it is further shown as aforesaid that the goods have not been subjected to any process abroad, the goods shall be exempt from anv such duty; and J (6) if it is further shown as aforesaid that the goods have been subjected to a process abroad but that their form or character has not been changed, the goods shall be chargeable with duty under this Act as if the amount of the increase in the value of the goods attri butable to the process were the whole value thereof, and, where any sum has been con tracted to be paid for the execution of the process, that sum shall be prima facie evidence oi that amount, but without prejudice to the powers of the Commissioners under this Act as to the ascertainment of the value of goods for the purposes of this Act. 15.— (!) The value of any imported goods for the purposes of this Act shall be taken to be the price which th/nrfl T 0 ? , gl u ve for the g° ods on a purchase in e open market if the goods were delivered to him at and *n Jif im P°f tatl fb height, insurance, commission thp nnr^ ther a nd expenses incidental to f3 r ±f, and deh / eiy at that P° rt (except any duties of customs) having been paid, and duty shall be paid on that value as fixed by the Commissioners. ? nosei of I thG Value 0f ^ g° ods to the pur- onlv to Commissioners may have regard not but^to all tpI Ue&lt; f k e .&amp; 00( f s as declared by an importer, but to all relevant considerations and in particular— {a) ^ * he Price which at the time of importation of the goods of which the value is to be ascertained 14[22 Geo. 5.] Import Duties Act, 1932. [Ch. 8.] Part III. — cont. (in this subsection referred to as “ the said A.D. 1932 goods ”) is being paid by other importers for goods of the like class or description and quality; or lb) if the price aforesaid cannot be determined to m the satisfaction of the Commissioners, then to the price at which the said goods or imported goods of the like class or description and quality, are being freely offered for sale in the United Kingdom to purchasers in the ordmary course oi trade, less an allowance in respect of duties ot customs and reasonable merchanting expenses and profits incidental to the marketing oi the goods after importation; or (c) if the last-mentioned price cannot be determined as aforesaid, then to the price at which goods oi the like class or description and quality wholly or partly manufactured or produced m the United Kingdom are being freely offered for sale m the United Kingdom to purchasers in the ordinary course of trade, less an allowance m respect oi duties of customs which that price would in clude if the goods had been imported and in respect of reasonable merchanting expenses and profits incidental to the marketing of the goods. (S’) The Commissioners may make regulations for Ibe nurnose of giving effect to the provisions of this section, 'and in particular for requiring any person con cerned with the importation of goods into the United Kingdom to furnish to the Commissioners, in such form as they may require, such information as is in their opinion necessary for a proper valuation of the goods, and to produce any books of account or other documents of whatever nature relating to the purchase, importation, or sale of the goods by that person. (4) If any person contravenes or fails to comply with any regulations made under this section, he shaU in respect of each offence be liable to a customs penalty of fifty pounds. 16. If, in ascertaining the amount of any duty Det~ chargeable on any goods under ’ T. ,11 pules as to arises as to the value of the goods, the question shall be referred to the arbitration of a referee appomted by goods B I 5[Ch. 8.] Import Duties Act, 1932. [22 Geo. 5 ] Conversion of ad valorem duty into duty chargeable by Weight or other measure of quantity. A.D^1932. the Lord Chancellor, who shall not be an official of anv Part III. Go y emment department, and the decision of the referee —cont. W1 j res pect to the matter in dispute shall be final and conclusive, and sections thirty and thirtv nrm 39&amp;40Vict. of the Customs Consolidation Act, 1876, shall appfyas if he dispute were such a dispute as is referred to in tho said section thirty, with the substitution of the applicarTi lor a reference to a referee under this section for the commencement of the action or suit mentioned in those sections. 17. (1) Where at any time it appears to the treasury, after consultation with the appropriate De partment, that any duty chargeable under this Act on goods of any class or description by reference to the value thereof could be levied with greater advantage and convenience if that duty were chargeable by reference to weight or other measure of quantity, the Treasury may by regulations direct that the duty shall be charged by reference to weight or other measure of quantity, as may be specified in the regulations. J (2) The duty to be charged as aforesaid shall be charged at such rate as may be specified in the Regulations, being the rate which appears to the treasury to be equivalent to the rate chargeable by reference to value, and in the case of goods the value ii 1 l SUb3eC ^ t ? seasonal variations, a separate late shall be specified for each part of the year in respect of which it appears to the Treasury to be necessary, having regard to those variations, to make separate provision. (3) The Treasury may from time to time make regulations varying the rate specified in any previous regulations so far as is necessary for securing that t i _ r '| e ,° duty shall continue to be equivalent to the rate chargeable by reference to value : 1&gt;rovided that no regulations varying a rate of duty shall come into operation before the expiration of s x months from the date when the regulations specifying that rate of duty came into operation. nf for the P ur P os es of any of the provisions ot this Act, it is necessary to ascertain what rate of duty chargeable on goods of any class or description by reference to weight or other measure of quantity is Computa tion of equivalent of ad valorem rate.C 17 [22 Geo. 5.J Import Duties Act, 1932. [Ch. 8.] equivalent to a rate of duty chargeable by reference A.D. 1932. to the value thereof, regard shall be had either— Part~III (a) to the average import value as determined by —cont. the appropriate Department of goods of that class or description imported in the last half calendar year (or, if the appropriate Department so decides, any longer period not exceeding three years) for which records are available at the time when the rate to be chargeable by reference to weight or other measure of quantity is to be ascertained; or (b) in the case of a duty to be chargeable at different rates for different periods or parts of periods, to the average import value as deter mined by the appropriate Department of goods of that class or description imported in the corresponding periods, or parts of periods, of the last three preceding calendar years for which records are available as aforesaid. 19 (l) Any order made by the Treasury or the Provisions Board of Trade under this Act shall be laid before ^ to or( era the Commons House of Parliament as soon as may be after it is made. (2) Any such order as aforesaid imposing a duty of customs shall cease to have effect on the expiration of a period of twenty-eight days from the date on which it is made, unless at some time before the expiration of that period it has been approved by resolution passed by that House, but without prejudice to anything previously done thereunder or to the making of a new order. (3) Any such order as aforesaid, other than an order imposing a duty of customs, shall cease to have effect if the Commons House of Parliament within a period of twenty-eight days from the date on which the order is laid before the House, resolves that the order shall be annulled, but without prejudice to anything previously done thereunder or to the making of a new order. (4) In reckoning any such period of twenty-eight days as aforesaid no account shall be taken of any time during which Parliament is dissolved or prorogued,18 f ■ r ~— [Ch. 8 .] Import Duties Act, 1932. [22 Geo. 5 .] Part III. — cont. A.D. 1932. or during which the Commons House is adjourned for more than four days. (5) Any such order as aforesaid may be varied or revoked by a subsequent order made in the like manner and subject to the like provisions : Provided that— ^ (a) this subsection shall not apply to an order made under section one of this Act ; and (b) an order made on the recommendation of the Committee may, notwithstanding any further recommendation and without any further recommendation, be revoked or varied by the Treasury as they think fit, after consulta tion with the appropriate Department, except that the rate of an additional duty shall not be increased above the rate specified in the original recommendation without a further recommendation. 20. For the removal of doubts, it is hereby declared that section eight of the Finance Act, 1926 (which exempts from duties of customs, with certain exceptions, goods proved to the satisfaction of the Commissioners to have been manufactured or produced more than one hundred years before the date of im portation) applies in relation to duties of customs chargeable under this Act. 21. (1) In this Act, unless the context otherwise requires:— The expression Vappropriate Department” means— (a) in relation to agricultural or horticultural produce of a class or description produced in the United Kingdom or used for the purpose of agriculture or horticulture in the United Kingdom, and in relation to the produce of any fishing industry, the Board of Trade, the Minister of Agriculture and Fisheries, and the Secretaries of State concerned with agriculture and the fishing industry in Scotland and Northern Ireland respectively, acting jointly; (b) in relation to any other goods, the Board of Trade, acting alone : Declaration as to opera- tion of s. 8 of 16 &amp; 17 ' Geo. 5. c. 22 Interpreta tion.19 [Ch. 8.] 932. [22 Geo. 5.] House is adjourned d may be varied or Le in the like manner 3 apply to an order )f this Act; and ommendation of the standing any further ithout any further oked or varied by ik fit, after consulta- Department, except tional duty shall not rate specified in the without a further ubts, it is hereby Finance Act, 1926 stoms, with certain satisfaction of the i,ctured or produced &gt;re the date of im- duties of customs e context otherwise partment” means— ’al or horticultural ;ription produced in ised for the purpose Iture in the United to the produce of Board of Trade, the id Fisheries, and the ned with agriculture y in Scotland and vely, acting jointly; goods, the Board of [22 Geo. 5.] Import Duties Act, 1932. The expression “ the Commissioners ” means the A.D. 1932. Commissioners of Customs and Excise: ' TTT Fart 111. The expression “the Committee” means the —com. Import Duties Advisory Committee: The expression “the United Kingdom” does not ^ include the Isle of Man: The expression “the British Empire” means His Majesty’s dominions outside the United Kingdom (including all parts of India), territories under His Majesty's protection, territories in respect of which a mandate of the League of Nations is being exercised by the Government of any dominion within the mean ing of the Statute of Westminster, 1931, and any territory in respect of which a mandate of the League of Nations is being exercised by the Government of the United Kingdom and to which section five of this Act has been declared by Order in Council to apply as if it were a territory under His Majesty’s protection. (2) If any question arises as to who was, or is, the appropriate Department in relation to any provision of this Act, the question shall be referred to the Treasury, whose decision shall for all purposes be final. (3) For the purposes of this Act references to goods produced in the United Kingdom or to goods produced in anv other country shall be deemed to include fish of British taking, or fish of that other country’s taking, as the case may be. 22. Any order or regulations authorised under this Exercise of Act to be made by the Board of Trade may be made by the President of the Board or in his absence by a r^ ra( j e Secretary of State, and any other thing required or authorised under this Act to be done by, to, or before the Board of Trade may be done by, to, or before the President of the Board or any person authorised by him in that behalf. 23. This Act may be cited as the Import Duties Short title. Act, 1932.c:—* 20 [Ch. 8.] Import Duties Act, 1932. [22 Geo. 5 .] A.D. 1932* Section 1. SCHEDULES. FIRST SCHEDULE. Goods exempted from the General ad valorem Duty. Gold and silver bullion and coin; platinum in grain, ingot, bar, or powder. Wheat in grain. Maize in grain. Meat, that is to say, beef, veal, mutton, lamb, pork, bacon, ham and edible offals, but not including extracts and essences of meat or meat preserved in any airtight container. Live quadruped animals. Fish of British taking, including shell-fish. Whale oil and whale products shown to the satisfaction of the Commissioners to have been produced or manufactured in floating factories which are British concerns. Tea. Cotton (raw) (including unmanufactured cotton waste and unbleached cotton linters). Flax and true hemp (cannabis sativa), not further dressed after scutching or decorticating; tow of flax and true hemp (cannabis sativa). Cotton seed, rape seed and linseed. Wool and animal hair (raw), whether cleaned, scoured or carbonised or not; rags of wool not pulled; wool noils; and wool waste not pulled or garnetted. Hides and skins (including fur skins, but not including goat skins), raw, dried, salted or pickled, but not further treated. Newspapers, periodicals, printed books and printed music. Newsprint, that is to say, paper in rolls containing not less than 70 per cent of mechanical wood pulp and of a weight of not less than 20 lbs. or more than 25 lbs. to the ream of 480 sheets of double crown, measuring 30 inches by 20 inches. Wood pulp and esparto. Rubber (raw) including crepe; rubber latex; gutta-percha (raw). Metallic ores, concentrates and residues; scrap metals and wastes fit only for the recovery of metal.[22 Geo. 5.] Import Duties Act, 1932. [Ch. 8.] 21 Iron pyrites, including cupreous pyrites. Copper unwrought, whether refined or not, in ingots, bars, blocks, slabs, cakes, and rods. Wooden pit-props. Sulphur. Mineral phosphates of lime. ^^Potassium carbonate, chloride and sulphate; kainite and other mineral potassium fertiliser salts. Cinchona bark. Coal, coke, and manufactured fuel of which coal or coke is the chief constituent. Unset precious and semi-precious stones and pearls. Radium compounds and ores. Scientific films, that is to say, cinematograph films exempted under the provisions of section eight of the Finance Act, 1928, from the customs duty imposed by section three of the Finance Act, 1925. Flint, unground. Soya beans. Cork, raw and granulated, cork shavings and waste. Ramie, not dressed. SECOND SCHEDULE. Recommendation and Allowance of Drawback. 1. The Treasury, on receiving a recommendation from the Committee to the effect that a drawback of any duties which are chargeable under Part I. of this Act or which the Committee recommend should be so chargeable, ought to be allowed in respect of any class or description of goods, may, after con sultation with the appropriate Department and subject to the provisions of this Schedule, by order give such directions as they think proper for the allowance of the drawback hereinafter provided in respect of goods of that class or description. 2. In deciding what recommendation, if any, to make for the purposes of this Schedule in relation to goods of any class or description, the Committee shall have regard to the general interests of the industries concerned, including the export trade, and to the facilities available for warehousing in bond and otherwise for enabling goods intended for re-exportation to be dealt with without payment of duty. 3. The drawback aforesaid may be allowed in the following case, that is to say, on the exportation, or shipment as stores, of goods which are exported or so shipped, either by the importer A.D. 1932. 1st Sch. — cont. Sections 1 and 3.[22 Geo. 5.] Import Duties Act y 1932. [Ch. 8J 3. Where gooda are manufactured in a bonded factory in the United Kingdom from dutiable material shown to the satisfaction of the Commissioners to have been consigned from and grown or produced in a part of the British Empire, the goods shall, to the extent to which they are shown to have been manufactured out of such material, bo free from the general a^oi-cm duty and any additional duty. Part II. Proof of Origin of Goods. It shall bo lawful for the Commissioners on the importation of any goods consigned from any part of the British Empire to require the importer to furnish to the Commissioners, in such form as they may prescribe, proof that the goods were grown, produced or manufactured in a part of the British Empire, and if such proof is not furnished to their satisfaction (having regard, in the case of manufactured goods, to the foregoing provisions of this Schedule) the goods shall not be deemed to be goods so grown, produced or manufactured. Printed by Eyre and Spottiswoode Limited, for William Richard Codling, Esq., C.B., C.V.O., C.B.E., the King’s Printer of Acts of Parliament. To be purchased directly from H.M. STATIONERY OFFICE at the foUowing addresses: Adastral House, Kinesway, London, W.C.2; 120, George Street, Edinburgh, York Street, Manciiester; 1, St. Andrew’s Crescent, Cardiff; 15, Donegall Square West, Belfast; or through any Bookseller. A.D. 1932. 3rd Sch. — cont.f '/ . IGI'J OFFICE, S.V.'.l. ! 1077 12th February, 1935. A (E 647/4/91) With reference to your letter No. P.Z. 583/35 of the 26th January to Hendel, you will remember that I showed you yesterday a minute by Beckett on your draft reply to the letter from the Board of Customs and Excise about the status of Bahrain. Since, however, Beckett sees grave objections to the draft which you sent us, I send you this record of his views in writing. 2. In general f Beckett’s position is that, although he fully appreciates the strength of the political arguments against stating, at any rate publicly, that Bahrain or any of the other Arab Sheikhdoms of the Persian Gulf are part of the British Empire for any purpose, he considers that according to international law, since His Majesty f s Government control the foreign relations of tnese Sheikhs (except of course the Sultan of Muscat) these are British protected states over/ J.G. Laithwaite, Esq., C.I.Eover which from the point of view of international law His Majesty possesses sovereignty and therefore we shall have to walk very warily in any official description of the status of the Sheikhdom of Bahrain. The position in international law is however not conclusive for the purposes of the interpretation of an Act of Parliament of the United Kingdom and the following represents the best that he can do in the way of straining the law to meet political exigencies without absolutely misrepresenting it. 3, He suggests that your reply to the Solicitor of the Customs should begin by referring to Section 21 of the Import lArties Act (1932) and pointing out that this is a definition of the British Empire for the purposes^ of this Act and not for general purposes, and that the question at issue is merely whether Bahrain is or is not covered by any of the words of this definition Section. The only words by which it could be covered, if it were covered at all, are M territories 'under His Majesty's protection'. The letter should then go on to say that the position is that, under treaties/treaties concluded with the rulers of Bahrain, the Sheikh of Bahrain has no relations with any Power other than His Majesty’s Government, and His Majesty's Government deal with foreign Powers over any questions which arise in relation to Bahrain and have also undertaken certain obligations to protect the territories of the Sheikh from foreign aggression; that, as regards , the internal government of his territory, the Sheikh is left full independence except that jurisdiction over British subjects and foreigners is exercised by His Majesty, who is represented in Bahrain by a political agent. Though it must be recognised that the expression ’’territories under His Majesty's protection” is neld to cover territories such as the Malay States, Sarawak, Brunei and Zanzibar, where there is a native ruler who enjoys independence in the matter of the internal government of his territories in which His Majesty does not directly exercise jurisdiction except over foreigners and where from the formal point of view the position is rather similar to that.of Bahrain, nevertheless there are grounds for distinguishing Bahrain from these territories Jterritories. In the first place, the measure of control exercised in fact by His Majesty's Government in the other territories mentioned above is greater than in Bahrain, and in the second place there are political difficulties which would be caused by regarding Bahrain as covered by these words in this Act which do not apply in the case of the other territories mentioned. Bor political reasons it has been deemed expedient in communications to foreign Governments to stress the independence of Bahrain and further the ruler of Bahrain would probably take objection to the inclusion of his territories as part of the British Empire, even under a purely statutory definition of the British Empire for a particular purpose, the niceties of which he would never understand. Therefore, although from the point of view of strict international law it would be correct to regard Bahrain as a territory under His Majesty’s protection, it does not necessarily follow that Bahrain should be regarded as coming under i/nese words in this particular Act of Parliament. The view might be taken that/that the connexion vfith Bahrain is in practice so loose that it should not be regarded as coming within the intention of Parliament in enacting this Section, and we should therefore suggest that the Customs should act on the view that Bahrain is not covered by the Section, If the ruling of the Customs in this sense were challenged, the question might come before a court, which would then have to decide the matter on the basis of such information as was officially communicated to the court on behalf of the Crown, 4. The letter might then go on to say that the position is the same in regard to Koweit and the Sheikhdoms of the Trucial Coast, but that the Sultanate of Muscat and Oman is in any case in a wholly different position, and, though His Majesty's Government exercise a particular influence there and protect nationals of the Sultanate in foreign countries, the Suluan is still free to enter into direct relations with other Powers, and therefore, even from the point of view of strict international law, his/his territories would not be covered by the expression ’’territories under His majesty’s protection” and fort lari not covered by this expression in an Act of Parliament of the United Kingdom. s ttfCv^ p.z.583/35. 6th February 1935. Dear Walker, I send this interim reply to your letter oi the 24th January to say that I nave thaue,at it well to consult the Foreign Oiiice before ^jiswering your question about the status of Bahrein, etc., ana that there may therefore be some little delay; but I nope to let you have a reply in the course of the next few hays. Yours sincerely, J.G. LAITHWAITE. C.V. V#alker, Esq Solicitor’s Custom House, E.C. 3« »INDIA OPPICa, jtw— P.3.583/35. h pc^y' TO IT1SHALL, S.W. 1. 26th January 1935. t&gt;y aear George, I enclose copy ol a letter froic the Boara ol Gustoxus ana gxcise on tne question of tlie status of Banrein and of the araft reply wiich, subject to 2 / your concurrence, I propose to send. I ao not think / there can be any doubt as to the answer. Yours ever, GlnBEiiT LAIIHWAITE. G.a : . Handel, Esc., C.M.G., Foreign office.Draft Paper Department. DRAR' j Dear Walker, G.V. Whlker, Esq., Mmy thanks for your letter of the 24th January. Solicitor’s Office, H.L. customs &amp; Excise *,2. I write in reply to say that Custom House, E• C. 5• the Bahrein Islands cannot he * regarded as falling within the British Empire for the purposes of the Import Duties Act, 1932. H.M.G# have consistently conducted their relations with the Sheikh on the basis that he is an independent ruler and they have affirmed this view in recent correspondence with the ‘ I Persian Government copies of which have been sent to the League of Nations. While it is true that they have undertaken certain obligations oi protection towards hirii in return for certain undertaking on his part in regard to slavery, piiacy, etc., tnoso obligations are not such as to justify the view that the sheikh's dominions form part o tne uominions of His Majesty. 3. The position is the same in regara to Koweit and the Sheikhdoms of trie Trucial Coast. Tne sultanate of ivAiscat is a ; wholly independent state which has treaties of its own in that capacity with countries such as Prance ana the/ ?800 5000 5.34Draft Paper Department. a. the United States of America, as well as a Commercial Convention with Holland. There is no question of its forming a part of the British Empire. 5. The Foreign Office, whom I have consulted, concur in the views expressed above. Yours sincerely,A question has arisen whether the Bahrein Islands are within the British Empire for the purposes of the Import Duties Act, 1932. Section 21 defines the expression 'British Empire' as meaning 'His Majesty's dominions outside the United Kingdom (including all parts of India), territories under his Majesty’s protection, territories in respect of which a mandate of the League of Nations is being exercised by the Government of any dominion within the meaning of the Statute of Westminster, 1931, and any territory in respect of which a mandate of the League of Nations is being exercised by the Government of the United Kingdom and to which section five of this Act has been declared by Order in Council to apply as if it were a territory under His Majesty’s protection.” I understand that certain protection is afforded to the Islands under a Treaty with the Government of India, which is represented by a political agent, and the question whether this amounts to his Majesty’s protection within the meaning of the above quoted definition appears to depend upon what, in fact, is the nature of the protection enjoyed. I believe that you were good enough to say that you would let me have your opinion on the matter, and I should be veiy grateful if you would do so. If it is not too much trouble, it would be very useful to have your views on the other places mentioned. J. G. Laithwaite Esq., India Office, Whitehall, namely, Kaweit, Muscat, &amp;c. London, S. W. 1. Yours sincerely,IXm i x. •.Tilton . It seems unnecessary to take any action on the lines suggested in the Board of Trade letter of 13th April below about the Persian Gulf section of Arabia. The Trucial Chiefs, Bahrein, Muscat and Koweit are hardly the type of country to which reference was contemplated in the Board of Trade letter of 16th November, of which a copy is below. The Colonial Office will presumably take the same view about the Aden Sheikhdoms. Perhaps x^r. Mumbold might confirm this 9 It seems doubtful whether any action is requisite as regards Nepal. fw«v wv 7 to 3 cowvw'*wxcoa:C»\ K&gt;« oAi-fiSStA S-yT* RrabCov ,'■“'N Forwarded with the Compliments of the Assistant Secretary for the Mercantile Marine Department of the Board of Trade. As requested in your contnunication of the 18th inst. Ref•P.2905, Board of Trade, 23/ 4/ X92 9 . Political Dept., India Office, S.W.l. .y G 2178 » 1C00 J HCOPY M.13843/28. /\ Mercantile Marine Department, Board of Trade, 3, Sanctuary Buildings, Great Smith Street, London, S,ff.l # 16th Jlovember, 1928. With referenoe to your letters of the 19th Ootober {W.9984/411/50) ana 26th October (*.10174/411/50) respecting the International Code of Signals, I am directed by the Board of Trade to state for the information of Lord Cashenden that the Editing Committee of the International Code of Signals hare requested that the Tarioas countries of the world should be ashed to revise that‘part of the Geographical Section of the International Code of Signals which applies to their country and should forward the results of their revision as soon as possible* In making the revision the oountries should be asked to Insert the names of places of special interest to aircraft, and they should also forward with their revision of the Geographical Section a chart on whloh the places are clearly marked. This latter is desirable in order to avoid any misunderstanding as to the exact location of the place to be indicated by the Geographical signal. The Editing Committee also ask that the countries should be advised that the total number/ Under secretary of State, Foreign Office, 3« W« 1 • » * j&lt; « musber of places In the Section relating to any country should not exceed the present number of entries by more than 90 %at the utmost. It might be added that the « signal letters appropriate to the various piaoes will be re-allooate&lt;l so that no attempt need he made to give signal letters new entries* So ooramanication need he sent to the Japanese Government who have already revised their part of the Geographical Section* A copy of this letter is being sent to the Dominions Office, the Colonial Office and the India Office* I have the honour to be 9 Sir* Yoar obedient Servant* (Signed) G«E* BAKER.Forwarded with tk •j \ e Compliments of the Assistant Secretary for the Mercantile Marine Department of the Board of Trade. Copy fa India 2 5 AP1 1929 ^ Board of Trade, /jy/fr 192^ .TelegramsSHIPMINDER, PARL, LONDON.” TelephoVie—VICTORIA 8740 Ext. Any further communication on this subject should be addressed to:— The Assistant Secretary, Mercantile Marine Department (address as opposite) Mercantile Marine Department, Board of Trade, and the following number quoted :— M. 3454/29 r 20, Great Smith Street, Westminster, S.W.l. 29 0b 13th April, 1929 Sir Pstts/oy O 5 a r With reference to your letter of** the 4th April 9 ^ (W.2812/103/50) on the subject of the revision of the Geographical Section of the International Jode of Signals, I am directed by the B ard of Trade to state, for the information of Secretary Sir Austen Chamberlain, that they would be glad if the Governments of a 11 the countries comprised in the list forwarded with your letter, with the exception of Abyssinia, Afghanistan, Arabia, Liechenstein, Luxemburg and Nepal, could be approached as suggested in the Board’s letter of the 16th November last. their names are at present included in the Code and it is not thought that any further names are really required. If, however, it is considered desirable on general grounds that a communication should be sent to these countries and if it As regards the six countries specified above, only The Under Secretary of State Foreign Office, S.W.l. /isIn any further communication on this subject, pleasp quote No. WJif/ZL//03/SC- and address —not to any person by name, but to— “The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S. i. - m, THE Under-Secretary of Sta\;e for Foreign Affairs ion of the Secretary of State, compliments to and, by direction % transmits herewith cop of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, S , m n&gt;- Reference to previous correspondence : ty-y ( v // / / wJ Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Uopy to India r, 11 API 1329 Similar letter sent to 14— 18814 B 2/29 (2)German. Russia (Including all territory administered or controlled by the U«S«S»R*). See Union of Socialist Soviet Republics. Greek.. -.1929 Guatemalan. Haitian. Honduran©an. Hungarian. Iraqi Italian. Japanese. Latvian. Lebanon©se. Liberian. Liechtenstein. Lithuanian. Luxemburg. Mexican. Monegasque. Moroccan. Hepalese. Metherlands. Micaraguan. Morwegian. Palestinian. Panamanian. Paraguayan. Persian. Peruvian. Polish. Portuguese. Roumanian.Salvador. San Marino. Siam. Spain. Sweden. Switzerland. Syria. Transjordan. Turkey• Union of Soviet Socialist Republics. United States of America. Uruguay. Venezuela. Yugo-slavia. Salvadorean. San Marino. Siamese• Spanish. Swedish. Swiss. Syrian. Transjordanian. Turkish. Soviet. United States. Uruguayan. Venezuelan. Yugo-slav.Register No. 3 p. Political Department. Letter „ rr A m~i irom r- 0 Teiegrgmi Dated -y - Rec . 192 /‘ Formally acknowledged Date. Initials. SUBJECT. To • / Chairman Under Secretary Secretary of Stafte... Committee Under Secretary Secretary of State... Council lu » * t Request from Board of Trade for complete list of the countries of the world. Enquiry from Foreign Office as to Arabia and the rt independent States of India'. / Copy to C*5 t f, &gt;/r €*: 6*. p-d. FOR USE BY DEPARTMENTS ONLY- Draft letter to Foreign Office. -to 5 ,; 2 £MiniEnquiry has been made of the Board of Trade as to the nature of the international code of signals. They state that hitherto there has been no international code, and that foreign countries have used for shipping purposes a British code, which they have translated into their own languages with varying degrees of success. With a view to removing the inconvenience to which misinterpretation of this code has given rise, it is now proposed to draw up, if possible, an international code in seven standard languages. The countries of importance from the point of view of this code are countries with a maritime trade or a sea coast, and countries with air potentialities, across which air routes may pass. It has been arranged with the Colonial Office that South-western Arabia (which is dealt with in some detail in a geographical list furnished by the | Board of Tradewith the letter forwarded by the Foreign Office) shall be dealt with by them in their reply to the similar letter which the Foreign Office have addressed to them, and that this Department shall reply 7 in so far as Arabia is concerned only as regards the the Persian Gulf. In the Persian Gulf/list forwarded by the Board of Trade omits the Trucial Sheikhdoms and refers to Muscat as , '0man M . The Trucial Sheikhdoms are, it is thought, worth mentioning, especially in connection with a code of signals, having regard to the existence of a special Trucial flag. It seems desirable, too, to prevent any misapprehension, that Muscat should be referred to under that name as well as under Oman. 2871 5000 0.28 Having/Having regard to the purpose with which this ! enquiry is made, there seems no reason to mention the names of any of the ordinary Indian States or of Bhutan, the position of which is not quite on a par with that of the ordinary Indian State under the suzerainty of His Majesty. c As regards independent States bordering on India, it is perhaps worth mentioning Nepal. The position of Tibet is less simple; we may perhaps leave it to the Foreign Office to deal with. The objection to mentioning it is the possibility of causing difficulty with China, while, from a practical point of view, its importance for the present purpose seems very small. A draft to the Foreign Office is submitted. This has been somewhat delayed (there is no urgency about it) because, in the absence of the previous correspondence between the B. of T. and the F.O., it was not certain with what precise object the list is being drawn up, and consequently what ought to be included in it. For example, if it were a question of states flying separate flags, there might conceivably have been some question as to the position of the maritime (States in India which, by Admiralty warrant, are authorised to use the Red Ensign defaced by the badge of each State. I understand from Mr. Baker, however, that it is not so much a question of flags as a purely geographical exercise, and that all that the B. of T. want (but feel incompetent to draw up for themselves) is a list of the independent countries of the world as they stand as the „ -11 .p x - x ii-i , J U VCA-r** ^ ^ result of the post-war settlements.^^^^p-^^j / ^„ r ^ Syw* A* * &gt;v **~'* ? ^ ***Minute Paper. political Department. \7e might, however, suggest for consideration the inclusion of the Trucial Sheikhdoms (presumably they will be included, if at all, as one unit). It seems best to say nothing about Bhutan. Its position is at present indeterminate, but it may at some time fall into the category of Indian States, and in cany case it is hardly independent. the list of the British Empire / or any of its constituent parts, but presumably the B. of T. will not forget it. It is curious that there is no mention in Jll' J, 32J2a 5000 11/28DraftDraft Paper. POLITICAL Department. The ohder Secretary of State, FOREIGN OFFICE, S.W. 1. Sir, “9 AP11929 ) Qc 25^ ^9% Vw 'tyrt-J ^ U/laS’ L* k U % /C C&lt;m+y L*c 3222b 5000 11.28 2 5 MAR 1929 In reply to Foreign Office letter of 11th February, No. W 103/103/50, I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to inform you that from demi-official discussion with the Colonial Office he understands that that Department are dealing with the est: [_*r c /l^.e»v&gt;.s 6 South-western Arabia. jat^^eetiron -crf-the Sheilchdoms of~ So far as the Persian Gulf is concerned, Viscount Peel would suggest that for ’Oman' there should be substituted 'Muscat and Oman' (adjectives - Muscati; 0mani)^-^^3 swab that the addition of the Trucial Sheikhdoms (Shargah; Has al Khaima; Ajman; Abu Dhabi; Dabai; Ummal Qaiwain; El Katr) would be desirable, in view of the fact that the ships of those States fly, under their treaty engagements with His Majesty’s Government, the flag known as the Trucial flag , A?- regard g-^the-lndi an -Sub- Con-tinent, |he Secretary of State &lt;vC&gt;c would suggest the insertion of tte- — independent Kingdom of Nepal (adjective - Nepalese). -He does not consider it necessary to include the names of any of the IndianStates under the suzerainty of His Majesty. Copy of this letter is being sent to the Colonial Office. (ScU J. C. WAhTOtL* In any further communication on this subject, please quote '“V.W 103/103/50. and address— not to any person by name, but — “ The Under-Secretary of State.’’ ? Foreign Office, London, S.W. 1. P 12 45 929 J Foreign Office, S.W.l. 11th February, 1929 Sir, I am directed by Secretary Sir Austen Chamberlain to transmit herewith a copy of a letter from the Board of Trade containing a request for a complete list of all the countries of the world. 2. A copy of a list prepared by this department in accordance with the Board’s wishes is enclosed. Before communicating it to the Board of Trade Sir Austen Chamberlain will be glad if the Secretary of State for India will, if necessary, complete it by supplying the names of the independent states of India and of any of the Arabian Sheikdoms which may have been omitted. The Colonial Office are being consulted with regard to the names of territories under British mandate. 41 25 A 1929 I am. Sir, Your obedient Servant, The Under-Secretary of State, India Office..'I.' 'U..'-' » 103/103/50) M. 13843/28. ” P i 2 4 5 i k 19 2 9 Mercantile Marine Department, Board of Trade, 20, (treat Smith Street, Westminster, S»W*1* 2nd January, 1929. Sir, r I am directed by the Board of Trade to refer to their letter of the 16th Hovember regarding the International Code of Signals, and to state for the information of Secretary Sir Austen Chamberlain that on reconsideration they are of opinion that it would be , preferable if, before a decision is taken as to the countries which should be requested to revise the appropriate parts of the Geographical Section of the 1 Code, the Board could be furnished with a complete list of all the countries of the world. The Board would then examine this list carefully in conjunction with the existing Geographical Tables with a view to recommending a satisfactory method of dealing with the question. I am to add that it would be convenient for the purposes of the vocabulary section of the Code if the proper adjective for each nationality could be indicated in the list and I am to enquire whether it would be possible for this to be done. I have, etc., (Signed) 0. E. Baker. The Under-Secretary of State Foreign Office, S.W.lHonduras Honduranean Hungary. Hungarian. Iraq. Iraqi. Italy. Italian. Japan. Japanese. Latvia. Latvian. Lebanon. Lebanon. Liberia. Liberian. Liechtenstein. Lie chtens te in • Lithuania. Lithuanian. Luxemburg. Luxemburg. Mexico. Mexican. Monaco. Monegasque. Morocco. Moroccan. Netherlands. Netherlands. Nicaragua. Nicaraguan. Norway. Norwegian. Palestine. Palestinian. Panama. Panamanian. Paraguay. Paraguayan. Persia. Persian. Peru. Peruvian. Poland, Polish. Portugal. Portuguese. Roumania. Russia (including all territory administered or controlled by the U.S.S.R.)* See Union of Socialist Soviet Republics. Roumanian. Salvador. Salvadorean, San Marino. San Marino. Siam. Siamese. Spain. Spanish. Sweden. Swedish. Switzerland.Switzerland Swiss Syria. Transjordan. Turkey. Union of Soviet Socialist Republics. United States of America. Uruguay. Venezuela. Syrian. Transjordanian. Turkish. Soviet. United States. Uruguayan. Venezuelan. Yugo-slav. Yugo-slavia.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x00019a_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/3842</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x00019a</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/3842</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 30/113 'Position of the Trucial Sheikhdoms in international law: Definition of Bahrain and Shargah in connection with the Import Duties Act 1932.'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1929/1944</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-08-10T22:29:35</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (264 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the inside front cover with 1, and terminates at the last folio with 265; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file concerns the question of whether Bahrain (also referred to as Bahrein), the Trucial Coast, and Kuwait should be considered part of the British Empire for the purposes of import duties and international agreements. The issue is mainly discussed in terms of the Import Duties Act, 1932 (copy of the Act, folios 221-233), which granted exemption of general ad valorem duty and any additional duty on goods consigned from any part of the British Empire, and produced in:any part of His Majesty's dominions outside the United Kingdomany territory under His Majesty's protectionThe papers include: discussion of the status of Bahrain under the terms of the Import Duties Act, 1932; India Office and Foreign Office agreement, 1935, that Bahrain (and the Trucial Coast and Kuwait) should not be classed as part of the British Empire for the purposes of the Act; representations from a company importing red oxide from Abu Musa about the payment of such duty, 1935; the decision of the Foreign Office to reverse their earlier decision and to include Bahrain, the Trucial Coast, and Kuwait in the British Empire for the purposes of the Act, 1936; enquiries from various companies over the status of Bahrain and other British-protected states in the Persian Gulf for import purposes; a request, which the British Government declined, from the Bahrain Petroleum Company (BAPCO) for imperial preference to be given to Bahrain oil for export to Australia and New Zealand, 1937; the view of the Foreign Office, 1937, that Bahrain should be counted as a British protectorate for the purposes the Narcotics Drugs Convention of 1931; and related correspondence concerning the duty on imports from the region.The file includes a divider, which gives a list of correspondence references contained in the file by year. This is placed at the back of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Import Duties Act 1932 c8</topic></subject><subject><geographic>Bahrain</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Trucial Coast</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Kuwait</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Imports</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x00019a#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>