<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000555.0x000296_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-20T07:18:07.844Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">CONFIPKNTIAi D. 0 . No. 42' S.' ’isr^a' l ~‘ ^ r . | r per'JTak 5?lp residency, BAHRAIN. the 4th January, 1947. *9*7 ^ ( Jbu -ow NtAA^Jc^^vv ^^ (’•a I forward herewith a copy of Stewart’s isy, demi official letter No. C.338-8/62, dated the 19th December, 1946, and its enclosures which you may find of interest. Thoms, as you probably know, is the American doctor in charge of the Dutch Reformed Church Mission Hospital at Muscat. E. P. Donaldson, Esquire, C.M.G., India Office, London. G.A.M.No. C.838-2/62. 5! X\ POLITICAL AGENCY, MUSCAT. Dated the 19th December, 1946. Dear Colonel Hay, I enclose for your information a copy of a letter addressed by the American Consul at Dhahran to the Sultan, together with a copy of its enclosure. 2. Tfye Sultan seemed upset to discover that Thoms had allowed himself to act as a medium for correspon dence between one of the Sheikhs of the interior and a foreign Consul, but contented himself by saying he proposed to warn Thoms not to repeat such an indiscretion. Yours sincerely, Sd. a. C. Stewart. The Hon'ble Lieutenant Colonel W. R. Hay, C.S.I., C.I.E., Political Resident, Persian Gulf, BAHRAIN. Copied. G.A.M. '■'—— - -70C/Y/EB/ ah The Foreign Service T £ | of the I .&gt;• ; j United States of America. Ufcpartment of jS^.te. AMERICAN CONSULATE, Dhahran, Saudi Arabia, November 15 1946. His Highness Said bin Taimur, Sultan of Muscat and Oman, Muscat. Your Highness, 1 have the honour to transmit herewith Consul Parker T. Hart's letter of November 13 to Sheikh Sulaiman bin Humayer A1 Nabhani, which your Highness is requested to pass on to him. An Arabic translation of this letter is also enclosed. Accept, Your Highness, the assurances of my highest consideration. Sd. Waldo E. Bailey. American Consul. CopiedHI- N 700/PTH/db. 2 ^ ' r^he Foreign Service Department of St 0 of the United States of America. AMERICAN CONSULATE, aHraTT, 1?audi Arabia, November 13, 1946, From To Parker T. Hart, American Consul. Sheikh Sulaiman bin Humayer A1 Nabhani, Tenoof, Jebel Akhdhar, Oman. Greetings and best wishes. I was most happy to receive your friendly letter of July 24, 1946, transmitted by the hand of our good friend Dr. W. Welles Thoms, and I reciprocate heartily your cordial greetings and those of your sons Sultan and Humayer. As I am now departing from Dhahran for the Ui ited States I am delivering my reply to my successor Consul ualdo E. Bailey, who will forward it to you through His Highness Said bin Taimur, Sultan of Muscat and Oman. It is a pleasure and an honour to have news of you through Dr. Thoms and to learn that you have extended to him such gracious hospitality and assistance. For this, Consul Bailey joins me in expressing deepest thanks. May ■’’he friendly relations betv/een Arabs and Americans continue to be a factor for stability and peace. God keep you and your family well and happy, and give you long life. 3d. Parker T. Hart. Copied. t G.A.M.as Chief Court (? v?ith) exception that death sentences require confirmation by Government of India and that Agency Courts work under Indian code They have also been informed that no ^ Americans have been in Agency Courts since refinC y expansion began- Second request was from American Consul at Basra. In order to enable me to comply with it, grateful if you would supply me with 6 copies of Bahrain Order in Council and all Regulations issued under it as I have no spare copies in ny office.. ‘lejtlB :W OtJT;.:^ THLEG-R/Al (if in any case the communication of the contents of this document to any person outside British or American G-overnment Service is authorised, it imist be paraphrased*) Your telegram No. 970 dated 22nd April, and Government of India’s telegram No. 2^865 of 26th April. Question has been further discussed with Wallace Kurray on basis of your teleyram* He was ylad to learn that four A. eric an special constables had already been appointed, and that no cases had so far come before the Courts. He accepted objections to appointment of American Joint Judye and appeared satisfied with explanation that existing law already provided as in India for American assessors and American jurors. It was clear from previous discussion that he had not fully appreciated that Sheikh had ceded jurisdiction over foreigners and explanation of position now given has I think considerably reassured Mm. He enquired whether the Consul at Dhahran would be given facilities to visit American ' prisoners under trial and assist them with advice, and was told that there would be no objection to this. He will consider matter further on return to Washington and will reply after discussing our proposals with State Department Legal Adviser. External Denartment SACHET Erom Secretary of State to Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, repeated to Government of India, External Affairs Department, and Political Agent Bahrein, dated 29th April, 194 A, despatched 19 «A 5 hours. UPORTiHT 9394.COPY (D * IHWARD TKLKORiUi Al lotted to External Department Co pies Circulated ilYP HUB 'I'KHmAli (O.g.P . ) From Government of India,? External Affairs Department ? To Secretary of Gtate for India. Repeated to Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Dated New Delhi* Id.55 hours, 26th April, 1944. Received SO*30 hours, 26th Apri3., 1944. IMMEDIATE, 4865. Addressed Secretary of State for India repeated to Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Your telegram 9211 dated April Plot Political Resident 7 s telegram 970 dated April 22nd and Political Agent Bahrain*s telegram*382 dated April 22nd* 2 0 As we see it question is whether position of Bahrain as de facto or not and there is little room for concession. This position most (sic .7 must) he gravely compromised by grant of judicial powers to Americ si Consul and since fair trial is^ already ensured to American nationals under existing provisions of Code of Criminal Procedure we. see no reason why eoncegaijjn^ should he given. While we consider that argument from vrusloAB only was still probably over-statement we should apprehend that surrender of principle in favour of America would sooner or lator involve us in difficulties in other quarters. We agree also with Political Agent that the presence of refinery construction-men is (7 special) pleading given facts that construction is likely to he finished by the end of the year and no American has been tried in Agency courts since it begun. 3. As regards police arrangements Political Agent s proposals in paragraph No. 3 of his telegram 378 when react with his paragraph No.2 (V are not) altogether clear. Apparently his intention is that required number of picxed (7 American) Military Police would be (7 train)ed in Provost duties by P.A« 1*0. but it is not. clear( 7 if it is)(? intended) that they should then work under station commander like British Military Police or as special constables (latter would be preferable as they would then sure(7 ly b®) appointed by Political Agent and not by Americans us appears to be contemplated in paragraph No.3 of your telegram). Nor do wo understand why American snould oe expected to agree to their Military Police being trained oy safeguarded by the provisions of the Code of Criminal Procedure which must allow for American majority on jury \V ana) enable appointment of (7 Americans) assessor (who could either be Consul himself or his nominee). As regards legal practitioners Judicial position of Americans la adequately American#—^ Am^rioans already enjoy the (7 .same) facili ties as svibjeooa of other nations and assurance a contiiiaod in paragraph ill of Political Hesident* s telegram ho.970 should dispel any Soviet Government apprehensions* 5 ,' Question of office (V accommodation and) clerical assistance for Consul is hardly (Tone) for BritiBh initiative in view of presence of (V American) (? acting) (7 Manager) Bahrein Oil Company ^ Bui up./ it) (V Island) Viceroy has seen this telegram.Ui, £6 April, 1944. ' 4 &gt;*ar Haikay, You ^ 1 now have seen telegrams /&amp;&gt;»• )1‘ anti 38^ ftpoia th* ^olitlc^al esidmt a,id the olitical . gent Bahrein, reepeotiveiy, regarding i&gt;olioe an^ judicial arrangeiaenta at Bahrein. In the MgHr. of tliese telegrams, subject to any com^nt j by the ^overnawnt of India which have not yet been .^ece.'vea, -e suggest that, if the Porei^i Office agree, the matter mght now be put to aliace :iirray &lt;» the following lines: ( 1 ) e are i»w informed by the olitical /ig®nt, darrein, tiiat lie has already ap ointed foux' ^iaericarx and four British subjects as special constables under his existing powe*-^. e feel that if a^y further police re rerjuired these 1 ^agnt suitably be provided by P. A.I.O. and could like wise be appointed as speolai castables. If, hoover, the United Btates GonrrvHnt wished furtlier American subjects to be appointed as special constables under the authority of the Political gent, Bahrein, we shoul 1 of course be prepared to take up the matter -sath the political authorities* (o) In the light of the olitical Resident’s views,, which «e .We now reoelwd, «• regret thet .ee do not t’eei ^ to the suiigestion that the American Consul at i&amp;ahran should be appointed to act jointly with the Political Agent, lA hearing Aaerioaa cases. riot only would there be gf®%t lega^^ difficulty in putting this suggestion into ei feet, but it be liable to be aisunderstood by the rabs in and would 2 «&gt;gt seriously undemine the position of the olifcioal Agent. The Hon. -U14 A.Hsnk»y, Foreign Office, S. (3)/(3) In tii© oircuastanoeB, w© thii^c that African reqair«na©nit» on the Judicial aide could Most suitabi^ be iaet by the api&gt;ointia®nt of Aaerican aaaessora to ait with the iolitioal gent in cases in sfhich Ohiteti Ttatea citiaens are involved. This is an arrangeiaent which ia already admissible under tlie law as it staztds* e are reini'orced in the belief that this should sufficiently provide for American interests by the fact that no United States citizen has appeared in the Agency Jourta at Bahrein since the Re finely construction ci^jenced. e need hardly add that if the A/jeriean Consul from hahran desires to attend Judicial prooeediiiga in Court as an observer, there is no objection at all to tills* It Haight be added, if you think it necessary, that we are inf &gt;rrued that, so far as legal advice for United States subjects is concerned, there are no legal practitioners at present in Bahrain, but that ary legal loforaiatioci which the British cliticai Agent or his Assistants could give in ary instance would always be most raadily forthscoioing. t Tours sinceraiy, v^ 0 U.i » A« ^ ^ i V(5^^ y. iTo\ !0 .IWARD TELEGRAM SECRET 14234 (If in ar^' case the communication of the contents /- N of this document to any person outside British or U e So Government Service is authorised, it must he paraphrased) 0 Allotted to External Department, Copies Circulated Fr ora To Repeate'd to Dated Received 0 Y P H E .R T E . L_E;, G JR A M Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Secretary of State for India- Gbverisnent of India and Bahrain* Bus hire, 18.45' hours, 22nd'April, 1944, 21.30 hours, 22nd April, X944o T 970. Addressed to Secretary of State for India, repeated t;o Government of India, Balirain Saving. Reference your telegram 9211 April 21st. Following is repetition of Political Agent Bahrain 1 s telegram No. 378. Be gins -: India Office telegram 9211 April 21st, &lt;•8 Police arrangements, 8 Special Constables were appointed by me under Regulation 2 of 1939 on (? February 8 th) (see my printed letter C/32 February 9th) of whom 4 are British subjects and 4 Americans. These appointments were made after consultation with Chief Local Representative of Bahrain Petroleum Company and the Station Commander specifically for control of Bahrain Petroleum Company and B'eM.P, employe. Station Commander has 4 British military policemen whose services are always available in case of trouble with Oil Company employd. 3. Native police must not be relied upon and. I do not now welcome the idea of American military police unless they are picked men. Colonel V/arburton Provost Marshal P.A.I.G. was recently here and after discussing position with him I-gather P.A. I.C. could augment their Provost personnel and this would in my opinion be the best course. Provost personnel could if necessary be appointed- special constables under Regulation 2 of 1939. 4. Judicial. Murray 9 s suggestion that American Consul should be appointed to act jointly with the Political Agent in hearing American cases is objectionable from both political and legal • point of view. Political Agent 4 * * 7 * s loss of prestige would be very considerable and in no time he would be sharing the Bench with a Persian colleague, American Consul can attend Judicial proceedings here as be can anywhere else in the Empire and also act as jury man or assessor. ■» Arrangements can be made for all cases in which Americans are /accusedaccused to be investigated by a European Magistrate as long as there is an assistant Political Agent. Section P'75 of Code of Criminal Procedure already allows for an American majority on a jury and Section 284- A of American assessor and Political Agent could be instructed not tp invoke his Section 30 Powers in American cases. So There are no legal practitioners in Bahrain but such .advice as I and vny subordinates are able to give has never been and* will nev er be withheld from British or American subjects. 7. In my opinion Murray* s concern over presence of the refinery construction'men is only an excuse. They will probably have completed their work by the-end of the year* 8 , I anticipate that Bahrain Petroleum Company can provide accommodation'and clerical staff for Consul but X cannot verify this without mentioning the subject to the chief local representative which I have so far refrained from doing. Ends . £* My records (including Regulation 2) are still in Koweit but from papers- here and recent discussions at Bahrain I agree, generally with Political Agent 9 s views. Whole value of locating American Consul in Dhahran will be lost if he is given judicial powers in Bahrain and Political Agent's position would be completely undermined. On the other hand there is no objection to allowing Americans as assessors but I can see no justification whatever for giving American Consul better position than he enjoys in British India or for that Shatter in Saudi Ar ah i a wher e t’hey have no (? &lt; Jud i cl al 0 ommi as ionsr). 3. So far as I remember Legal Practitioners Act has not been extended to Bahrain and practice has always been to . restrict entry (sic ? field) but question has been considered 1 before and if any particular case was such that legal defence was essential position could be waived. Best course will however be to assure them that Political Agent or his assistant will be glad to supply any legal information they require. 4 4. I have asked Political Agent to telegraph you figures of Americans who have been brought- into court since expansion began, I understood him to say that the number had been very small and my impression is that Americans are trying to extort concessions of permanent value under -cover of forwarding the war effort.OUTWARD TSLEG-RAIvl (if in any case the communication of tlie contents of this document to any person outside British or American Government Seirvice is authorised, it must be paraphrased*) SECRET CYPHER TELHIGRAM From Secretary of State to Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, repeated to Government of India and Political Agent, Bahrein, dated 21st April, despatched 01.15 hours. E,MEDIATE 92TTr ~ Your tele^am No. 796 dated 28th March. American Consul for Bahrein. Question ha.s been discussed with Wallace Murray during his visit here and he -was persuaded, vitla some difficulty, to be content with visits from Consul at Dhahran* Vfe assume there would be no difficulty about arranging for an office to be placed at his disposal by the Bahrain Oil Company on their premises and any necessary clerical assistance. It rill no doubt be necessary to arrange for him to have radio-telephone facilities. 2. Immediate cause for Sta.te Department's pressure in this matter lies in presence in Bahrein of large number of American workers engaged in refinery construction and .'allace Murray is concerned that there should bo:- (a) satisfactory Police arrangements, and (b) some arrangement for American participation on judicial side. 3. As to (a) it seems doubtful whether control by American Military Police i/ill bo acceptable to U.S, Vfar Department and Murray suggested that Oil Company might be able/matter/ able to furnish small number of civilian police. If not the State Department v/ould v/ish to introduce some from elsewhere. IThile ao-reein.p; that assistance of /jnerican personnel would be desirable, (l presume they would be appointed Special Police Officers under Regulation No, 2 of 1936 ) I do not think that we should accept position under which Political .went would depend entirely on American personnel as Ms executive agents. It would presumably be equally unwise to depend on existin'? native Police Force for control of .'merican personnel and it ’would therefore appear .'i“ v desirable to brinq in some British Police personnel, say n a Superintendent and about half a doxen others in order to maintain our position, I should be prepared to ask Par Office to move P.A. I.C. to rele.ase personnel for this purpose in civilian capacity if no other source of supply, e.cr, India, is available. As to (b),, Murray 1 s suyyestion was that as a temporary expedient American Consul should be appointed to act jointly with Political ..gent in his Court for hearing of .merican cases. This could not be done under existing Bahrein Order in Council and further would imply U,S. consular jurisdiction unless the U, S. Consul sat on bench as a judge appointed by and not as Consul. Presumably if .'merican Consul chose to attend Court purely as observer and without any judicial functions, there would be no objection to this, though it probably would not fully meet '.allane Murray’s needs. Alternatively would it be practicable under the Criminal Procedure Code as at present applied for Political Agent to try such cases as Sessions Judge with the aid of .'merican assessors' who might include the U.S. Consul if desired or suitable members of the Oil Company, I should also like to be assured that Americans charged with offences will have legal advice readily accessible to then. 5 . I should be glad to have your view’s and those of Government of India, on these suggestions or any alternative suggestions for meeting American desiderata. You will appreciate that as we have gained our point over Consul it is important that we should go as far as possible to meet wishes of Americans on these other points. Please treatable to furnish snail nuriber of civilian police. If not the State Department v/ould v/ish to introduce some from elsewhere, hhile acrreeinp; that assistance of American personnel would be desirable, (l presume they ’would be appointed Special Police Officers under Population No. 2 of 1936 ) I do not think that we should accept position under which Political hpent would depend entirely on American personnel as liis executive apents. It ’would presumably be equally unwise to depend on existing native Police Force for control of American personnel and it would therefore appear desirable to bring in some British Police personnel, say rr a Superintendent and about half a doxen others in order to maintain our position, I should be prepared to ask Par Office to move P.A.I.C. to release personnel for this purpose in civilian capacity if no other source of supply, e.g, India, is available. matter/FILE WDexeo T ?! V • = - t —-' J L (a 2032/138/25) Immediate. 1 A 7 o i S- f c ; FORKIGK OFFICE, S.W.l. 4th April, 1944. Dear ieel, In his telegram ITe. 796 of the S/th March f the Political Resident says that it would he preferable that the United States Consul at dhahran should not he given formal Jurisdiction in Bahrein, hut that we should allow him to enter Bahrein on toe same footing as his colleagues from Iraq. If this is not enough, Prior thinks that The King’s'Exequatur would he all that is required and that no authority from the Sheikh is necessary. We will certainly try to get the Americans to agree to the first proposal. Only if the Americans make a very strong case for going further than this and press strongly for the formal recognition of the United States Consul as functioning also in Bahrein, will we agree to the Consul having a separate exequatur granted hy The King. This would involve the Americans issuing him with a separate commission for the purpose. We would not, as at present advised, in any case make any arrangement involving the issue °£ a dorat hy the Sheikh. I presume however that the Consul could get along without that. As Y/allace Murray will arrive very shortly, we should he grateful if you would confirm that you agree as soon as you can. I may add as regards^th^elast sentenceparagraph 5 of rrior’s telegram that we should not regard the grant by The King of an exequatur to a foreign consul as being contrary to the provision in the agreement of 1892 by which the bheikh reaffirmed his undertaking to abstain from relations with foreign governments. (R.M.A. Hankey)4, Viceroy has e-een this telegram* • '' ‘ '— fo ^ n~H- x mAKV TELEGR 4 M 4 llotte&gt;A to jgUctrernel Departme nts 0 opi e a ^Circufa t §d~ fc i a r y ■&gt;' 8 * AscSst Ilf 06 1944 ^ \_/ Pr 4 om TO Repeated to .Dated Recalled 0 Y ?' H E R T E L E G S A M (Q, T,P, } rA**i+&lt;*~&gt;* •'■ii -.*.**s.-j«n-’+ At»A. V.a - nr/mipr**. *u r *- wry%&gt;+ : n»L«» Government of Ir-dia, External Affaire Departments Secretary of State for India* Political Resident in the Persian Gnlf* New Del hi ? 03,35 hours, 4th April, 1944.: 07.00 hours» 4th April, 1944» 3843, Addressed to Secretary of State for Resident in the Persian Gulf^ india repeated* to Political '39^' /' 7£_ No, Your- telegram. No-6648 dat-od March 18th and Euehire telegram 7 96 dated M;-iroh 28 th We are not fully apprised of the procedure by which the jurisdiction of Consul appointed in one country can be extended to cover territory of a second country but the proposed grant t-o Dhahran American Consul of exequatur for Bahrain appears to indicate that he wound enjoy ail rights and privileges and be entitled to exorcise all consular functions in Bahrain sole difference being that ha would not ordinarily be resident there. If this is so proposal made in your tslegr&amp;m No*6648 appears to us to Imperil whole position which we ha^e sought to protect (see In particular iav_ relevant that Bahrain «». ■ * ’’ • —.r - - ~V-» ' ~ i ^ ’V a3?c /.^ t olenram No, 3556 dated Hav 5 th I 945 U It is 1 ris tv/o hours journey ::rom.\DhahPan and that w we should expect Araerioan Consul to have little difficulty in securing office and residential accommodation with the aid of the Bahrain Pour oleum Company so that in effect there 'would be no residential disability. 3ofu (rW 3„ In view of above our attitude remains unchanged and (?w© must) strongly urge American pressure for extension of Dhahran Consul's jurisdiction be resisted. Foreign Office letter No,5093 dated : ^rd to U,S«- Embassy i n London referred to possibility of provld facilities to enable a U« S, Consular off!car to visit. Bahrain J'uni ■. ng regularly and we suggest Kis Majesty 9 s Coverment should stand fv principle) of freedom of visit v/ithout formal extensioi. of jurisdiction or issue or exs^Mfer’v In ax\y event we agree w- th Political Resident in regarding it as neither necessary nor adv to arrange for issue of authority cm Sheikh on the lines of t Znnzih ar pre cedent „ on i sab! i he• ■' 1 J J ' 1 '™'‘ » M 1 ' V 3 (V'T l!r. JPeel, - • ~c^—— jute*- J ^ •Cot- ^ t* jpflitr-o M&lt;k^ fc*' ^&gt;'&lt; *&gt; C&lt; e- cCl£ UtiL- /I-9 fc ^ ^“ fc The provisions of the 1892 Agreement which were &gt;f/&gt; binding on the Sheikh, his heirs and successors are ' as follows:- (1) That ^ will on no account enter into any agreement or correspondence with any power other than the British Govenxnent; (2) That without the assent of the British Government ^e will not consent to the residence within my territory of the agent^ of any other Government^; (3) That ^e will on no account cede, sell, mortgage or otherwise give for occupation any part of my territory save to the British Government. The present position of Bahrein is that the Sheikhdom continues theoretically to be regarded as independent from the international standpoint and makes no claim to sovereignty. I imagine, however, that the issue by H.M. of an Exequatur in respect of Bahrein would probably be regarded under International Law as implying a claim to sovereignty. Unless we are prepared to declare Bahrein a protectorate it would probably be desirable to avoid raising the question of an Exequatur at all, if this is possible. So far as Persia is concerned, it seems doubtful whether she would, in fact, desire the formal recognition of a Consul at Bahrein since this presumably would amount to a renunciation of her claims to the Islands. J/Mt- iifi ■mm L*. * x Al.iT 1 U?l 1 3 9 5 © Vi »&amp; IinVARD T^Ul-GRAM / 944 , SEdHKT 10646 l/t) it. v ttecl t o External Department s fL-jH' ■ JU GYPliliR , XEEEg:(O.'J.'.^ . )^wf ct$li s ' Prom To Repeated to Delhi and Bahrein* Dated Bushire* 16*00 hours, 26th March, 1944. Received 22.00 hours, 28th March, 1944. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf $^ w Gecretary of State for India* IMPORTANT. ?96o t/'- ) (jjt ^ C(*&gt;dr tiUj 1 o i &amp; ^-^&lt;Z —A I*C^, ^&lt;/dU^Uru If r&lt; V ^ *[} tiysL Addressed Secretary of State for India repeated to Delhi and Bahrain (3aVing)c Your telegram 6648 Maix^h 18th«, 2* As the American Consult Exequatur to the Saudi Government will according to international practice specify his district, i»e. Bhahran I am not clear her far we can formally 1 *W^^ I,eco £ niss ^jurisdiction in Bahrain, a State foreign to Saudi Arabia* without the c oncurren ce of Saudi Government to whose territory he is specifically appointed* Diplomatic Mieeions often cover more j 5 *^* /than one territory hut I do not recall similar instances of consular . •fV' jurisdiction. r ■ 3 . In trur discussions with Persia we have rigidly refrained from public examination and discussion of our position in the islands. If proposed appointment is formally recognised w® may sooner or later have to fao© such examination and discussion if requests for similar facilities for their Consuls at Jedda or elsewhere are made by Iraq or Persia op any other power. An added complication in such an event would he that we would either have to admit that exclusive agreement of 1892 is a dead letter or take a stand on this agreement and declare Bahrain a protectorate. 4. Taking all this into consideration I suggest our host course would he to endeavour to avoid formally recognising jurisdiction of U.S. Consul at Dhahran and allow him to enter Bahrain on the same footing as his colleagues at Bagdad or Basra. This should satisfy Americans who have been Informed of our difficulties hut in ■last^r esort the King s* Exequatur should suffice . The Sheikh is a smaller man than Sultan of Zanzibar and taer© 'are gravest objections to giving him any international position* 5'.* Incidentally, Political Agent reports that Sheikhas attitude toward Americans has recently undergone a change owing largely to behaviour of Bahrain Petroleum Company employees and ho would now be disturbed and not repeat not flattered by presence of American Consulate* V ' ftlgs,Ext. DPL^PT TlIuXZUJA x'XX - Prom: Secretaiy of State for India, n ¥ 4 TO! Reptd: 1 ' m Copy to : C.W. Baxter, Esq.^ P.0, ^ r^. &amp; Government of India, External Affairs Department, / ufe T ^ ;c» Jr** pA, VP 1 '*' *: &lt; r A '. rJ - Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Addressed Government of India, repeated I *&gt;, r or ,bT« f''' RCH Bushire . 1 Ity telegram ( 9^1 ^ / . u.S. Consulate at Dhahran. This question nay be ]t raised/during 'conversations with Stettinius Mission? next month. I presume you ~ Tr ii 11 ^ t c£^ii u&gt;*J c/Jr &gt; no—oh i^n'hi r&gt;r&gt; -f- ir? a ^p^r, Bahrein skottid hr*- aAwwd in ; area of Consul* s Jurisdiction if'nothing less Wu/content the^ Anericai^? 2 . / If^we-agx\;t; i^-i^ri 5 , question of Exequatur will arise. Please see in this-^c5nciection ^accia^s-dt^Hter of 5th April 1943, copy sent I am 'inclined to- think that ; since/Consul /will be resident at fchahran,' King*s Exequatur in respect of Bahrein may be/ sufficient but should be glad to have as soon as possible/your views -and those of the Political Resident as to whether Some authority fron/ x'INDEXED 2-1 FOREIGN OFFICE, S.W.l r ],6th March, 1944 (E 1637/128/25) o Dear Peel In my letter E suggested that a Uni 15jfh February I Dhahran who would have Bahrein in his consular district, would solve the difficulties created by the United States desire for a consular representative in Bahrein. A similar suggestion was put forward by Prior in his ^^g^Aa telegram No. 956 of the 25th April last. /t f You will now have seen from Jedua telegram No. 85- /pl that Ibn Saud has agreed to the appointment of a United States Consul at Dhahran. This question may be raised during the conversations with Mr. Wallace Murray next month and we presume you would have no objection to our agreeing that Bahrein should be included in the jurisdiction of the consul at Hiahran, if nothing less will content the Americans. If this occurs, r the consul will require an exequatur from The King and it might, we think, also be advisable for him to have some authority from the Sheikh (see Caccia's letter to Rumbold E 1580/296/91 of the and Prior on these points and if so, as there is not very much time to spare, we should be grateful if you would ask them to let you have their views as soon as possible. 5th April). I ¥ to 1' (C.w. Baxter) R.T. Peel, Esq. , C.B.E. , M.C. , India Office.Fob Repeated to Govt.of India, External Affairs Dept. ? end Secretary of State for India* Dated Busb.ix*e # 15.10 hours* 3rd March* 1944. Heceived Up 00 hours* 4th March* 1944. 524 * Addressed to Tehran repeated Government of India , External Affairs Department New Delhi. Your telegram 75-3 4994 February 29th. I agree that in circumstances best cotxrse is to agree to U. 3. Ao Consulate at Dhahran. It is of ccmrse assumed that position vis-a-vis Bahrain remains unaffected.[CYPHER] Secret Mr. No. 1944. Qtj^February, 194^. R; 3^15 p.m. 9th February, 1944. fa. S t i £ i°o&lt;-/W.U^h iL ^ /? 7 , ^ijutuh&gt; £ tf//, ft/k §@@ M J @@© §@@ /Yy u+S+jJ'i r^lfijximr , My desp atch No._ 98 of December 16th //United States Legation have again raised the question # of United States Consular representation-at Dahran. My United States colleague informed Amir Faisal that'as Ihn Saud objected to the creation of a consular post. United^States Government ' proposed a member of the Staff of Legation at Jedda should visit Dahran at intervals. He^-added that United States citizens at Dahran suffered considerable inconvenience owing- to the absence of a~ consular representative and had had trouble over passport and other consulate facilities. „ ‘2. Ibn Saud wishes you to be informed and seeks your advice since he knows His Majesty’s Government have, up to the present, objected to foreign consular posts in the Persian Gull. He begs- that youi'reply will be constructive and-thert you will not pass the ball‘back'absolutely. , 3^Ee -wonders if it would not be possible for His Majesty’s Government to ‘Come to some modus vivendi' with United States over this question without of course letting them know that he has • referred the question to us; Confidential. '4^ In view of considerable development of United States interests in’Sandi oil/fielHs and the number of United States citizens likely to bre. employed in that area, I suggest that United^ States consular representation at Dahran cannpt be long delayed and that we-should acquiesce'to the-creation ol a United States consular post. ^ It*would perhaps be unfortunate if some official in the pay of the oil company - there are spme were to inform the company who in turn would inform Legation that His Majesty’s Government were obstructive over this matter.OUTWARD TELEGRAM IMDEX £0 Under Sec for For E.928A28/25_ [Cypher] I Qyt/ f FROM FOREIGN OFFICE TO RIY;j)H Nq&lt;, 1 D. 6.45 p.ra. 24th February, 1944. 24th February, 1944. Repeated to Government of India Political Resident in the Persian Gulf M.E.Min No. 29 Saving. Your telegram Nn.Afl [Question of appointment of an American Consul at Dhahranj. I agree with you that in view of United States interests in Hasa the .American request for consular representation there seems justified and I think we should, advise Ibn Saud to accede to it. You should therefore, if you see no objection, reply to Ibn Saud on the following lines. 2. His Majesty's Government are aware that hitherto Ibn Saud has not been prepared to agree to consular representation at any place in his territories except Jedda, and that until recently there have been no foreign interests in other parts of Saudi .Arabia which would justify the establishment of consular posts. But now an immense industry is growing up at Dhahran which will employ increasing numbers of United States citizens, and it is reasonable that the United States Government should wish to provide consular facilities for them. His Majesty s Government feel that in the circumstances continued refusal of the Merican request would only be a source of natural irritation to the United States Government and they would therefore suggest that Ibn Saud would be well advised to agree to it. They consider Ibn Saud need have no fear that the appointment of an Merican consul to Dhahran v/ould be likely to be taken as a precedent and lead to corresponding requests for consular representation at Dhahran by other Powers, since no other country has commercial interests comparable with those of the United States of America in Eastern Saudi Arabia. 3. As regards His Majesty’s Government’s attitude towards the establishment of consular posts in the Arab States of the Persian Gulf to which Ibn Saud refers, you should explain that conditions there do not correspond with those in Saudi Arabia, since by agreement with the^rulers His Majesty's Government are responsible for their foreign relations and in many cases exercise jurisdiction over all foreign nationals. OTP. i tv^ iso) y 7lSa&lt; ^ f^nf us. *■* —&gt;4~ U I' Ll .S. CtW*v{c*L \i^nX^tS^L i'K &amp;L £,/*AA4v Under Secretaiy of State , l ^ ^ . I i^j^rU tfTr-ft t ^ 2 w IfcjT'X'^u* (\\***J ^ y ^L«a «c «^‘ &gt;i* L ' Please see the Foreign Office letter of li?th February below. Previous approaches by U.S. to Ibn Saud on this question are referred to at dxt. 5793/43 and juxt. 197 /^ 4 , flagged. The question of U.S. representation at Dhahran is, of course, closely connected with earlier requests to be allowed to establish a Consulate at Bahrein. Please see in this connection the submission at Ext.2390/43, flagged in the attached files, the Political Hesident*s telegram 936 of 27th April, 1943, and Government of India's 3356 of 3th „Iay, 1943. It will be seen that the Political Resident there suggested that the U.S. requirements could be met by a Consul at Dhahran who would visit Bahrein, smd that the Government of India said that while they-were not anxious to see the establishment of a U.S.Consul^at Dfhahran, H.J-.G. might consider the possibility of attempting to divert U.S. attention from Bahrein to Dhahran. It seems impossible indefinitely to resist the American desire for Consular representation near their oil interests on the HaSa Coast, and it is submitted that we should concur in the line which the Foreign Office propose talcing, namely to advise Ibn Saud to accede to the Americans' request. A draft letter to the Foreign Office is submitted accordingly, together with a draft telegram to the Political Resident repeated to the Government of India, informing them of what is being done and our views on the subject./V-. 3&gt; EERAPT LETTER C.W.Baxter, Bsq., GMG-. ,2*3., Foreign Office, S.W.l. Dear Baxter, (, 94 ; Thank you for your letter. No.E.&gt;'28/123/25 of 15th February, about Ibn Saud* s request for our advice at Dhahran. We concur in your draft telegram, which we should be grateful if you would repeat to the Political Resident and the Government of India. lie are sending a covering telegram to both which we will despatch as soon as we hear from you that your telegram has gone off. In view of the interest of the Political Resident and the Government of India in this subject, H.M.Minister might perhaps with advantage have repeated his telegram No.4-3 to both. I wonder whether you would consider drawing his attention to the desirability of repeating telegrams of this sort to them, since otherwise we have only to repeat them from here, and this involves unnecessary labour apart from the delay thereby caused. Another example of this sort recently was his telegrams about the American on the subject of American Consular representation project/_s indexed Secret C &gt; ^ . (ii 928/128/25) H , l &gt; ^ FOREIGN OFFICE, S.VV.l. A — February, 1944, ea i ? 53 Dear Peel, I enclose a cOTfcr„g£!..,_k -'^4e^raJ i from Jed&amp;a in which Jordan reports Ibn Sand’s desire for our advice on the American request for the creation of a consular post at Dhahran. V/e have long thought that an American consul at Dhahran, who would have Bahrein in his consular district, would be a good solution to the problem of providing consular facilities for the expanding American interests in that part of the world, without prejudicing our inability to agree to foreign consuls resident in Bahrein. We observe that the Political Resident also thought that this would be a suitable arrangement (see paragraph 2 of his telepram TIo. 956 the 27th April, 1945 ). Hitherto, Ibn Saud has refused to agree to the appointment of a consul at Dhahran, but now that he has asked for our advice ' on this point we think we should advise him to agree. I enclose a draft telegram to Jedda in this sense and should be grateful for your comments on it. 1 1n I INDIA OFFICE ! f—^l. ^ (C.W. Baxter) R.T. Peel, o^sq. , C.B.E., M.C., India Office.FOREIGN OFFICE, S.W.l. February, 1944. Your telegram No. 43 ^ Question of appointment of an American Consul at Jhahran J. I agree with you that in view of United justified and I think we should advise Ibn Saud to accede to it. You should therefore, if you see no objection, reply to Ibn baud on the following lines* 2. His Majesty’s Government are aware that hitherto Ibn Saud has not been prepared to agree to consular representation at any place in his territories except Jedda, and that until recently there have been no foreign interests in other parts of t audi rabia which would justify the establishment of consular posts. But now an immense industry is growing up at Dhahran which will emoloy increasing numbers of United States citizens, and it is reasonable that the United States Government should wish to provide consular facilities for them. His Majesty’s Government feel that in the circumstances continued refusal of the American request would only be a source of natural irritation to the United States Government and they would therefore suggest that Ibn Saud would be well advised to agree to it* They consider Ibn Saud need have no fear that the appointment of an American consul to Dhahran would be likely to be taken as a precedent and lead to H*M. Linister Jedda. States interests in Hasa the American request for consular representation there seems Telegram No. • • Cypher Departmental No.l. corresponding/corresponding requests for consular representation at Dhahran by other Powers, since no other country has commercial interests comparable with those of the United States of America in Eastern Saudi Arabia. 3. As regards His Majesty’s Government’s attitude towards the establishment of consular posts in the Arab States of the Persian Gulf to which Ibn Baud refers, you should explain that conditions there do not correspond with those rulers His Majesty’s Government are responsible i for their foreign relations and in many cases | exercise jurisdiction over all foreign nationals in baud! Arabia, since by agreement with therss riafi 403/3/44 COl-f. T cy; r ’ ' ^ ^ 420 ! 27 jan m 3 /z^J i '?■/*} SECRET ^ M ' i _ •; January 12 th # 1944* SECRET Dear DopartJTient, or tbs UnNan SaM^tny m S*f.«r- for For«ig* AMkt-, ’ e enclose a copy of a minute by erlin about an alleged secret report by someone In the American War Department dealing with . Saudi Arabia, Though there are undoubtedly people in the American Administration who have ideas of this kind, perhaps more particularly in the rar Department and O.S.S., this document should not be regarded as expressing the views of the Dnited States Government as a whole. We do not, for instance, believe that the State Department has worked things out quite as far as this. Bat there is no question that the Near Eastern Division are taking a considerable Interest In Saudi Arabia and that they are not being entirely frank with us on the subject of their intentions in that area. Several members of the Division are also prone to absurd suspicions of Russia, which would be in line with some of the views indicated by the supposed ? ar Department memorandum. Yours ever. ?.G, ayter“1 K M I N tpT'E. SECRET ?5r. Fay ter Mr, Wright During my recerit visit to .Hew; York I was shown what purported to be an extract from a secret report written by a highly-placed member of the U.S. Far Department and accepted by the War Department as in line with its policy. It dealt with American plans in Saudi Arabia, and stated that there were three principal reasons for American Interest in that country 1. Its untapped and allegedly vast oil resources; 420 4. o/ A 2. Its strategic Importance In the* event of a future war with the U.S.S.R. It was the only part of the world susceptible of American penetration which possessed facilities for a large number of military airfields as well as having advantages of a natural supply of fuel, storage, and the possibility of aircraft construction from light metals and plastics i which might be manufactured in Last Africa. The Persian Gulf would provide convenient places for the American Pacific fleet, whose duty it would be to implement American demands, vis-a-vis the U.S.S.R., and more remotely the British Empire, should that ever be required. It followed from this that no effort should be spared to develop close relations with King Ibij Baud, and in the event of disagreement on his part with anyone else, the U.S.G. should unhesitatingly align itself on his side. The document I saw was bluntly expressed and did not mince matters in the slightest. My informant is an earnest anti-imperialist, concerned with the economic aspect of American relations In the Middle East, and appears genuinely shocked by the contents of the memorandum, which, however, he maintained represented the settled policy of not only the Far Department but the Hear Eastern Division of the State Department, which look on the Arabs as its only genuinely reliable allies against the U.S.S.R. pa*f‘ ^yJUP'^. Cf” r . 3. This might perhaps Interest the Foreign Office, if only as an indication of a trend. (SGD•) I. 3. January 5, 1943.' file cqfpvixi'l .o n'4 * v /■ s c o L (g44 fef (If in any case the commuriication of the contents of t^ls document to any person outside Oovernment 3erwi j is authorised# it must be pareptiresed^« Allotted t o external-D«?agt!ifeati CYPHER 'i’KLaOgAM Prom Political Healdent in the Persian Oulf. To Secretary of State for India* Dated Bushire# 15*30 hours, tfSth January 1^44 Received 10.45 hours, 26th January 1944* 3* H ®&gt; *un Your Ex t 5793 forv/arding copy of Jedda telegram 419 October 8th. Grateful if such correspondence is in future repeated to me by cable; also for indication whether in (sic) copy has been sent to India.{/T'‘Z-z/z ? A r) INDEXED S a t. M ( 2403/1617/41) .A \v\ A tile 0 «mfg^mMU of the •. Under Seero’taf'y of tKnte for Foreign Affaire r\ fi S' - Hr-' . 18 JAN 1944 / / 1 8 JAN ml ^ British Legation, tXedda* 4^' / , k, . 16th December, 1943^ IS JAN 1944 'tmi/ ir air. if 6&lt;&gt;2.g//S~S AfJ ‘tf' ference to my telegram flo. 41 S6. Hr / 7 7^ ^ L l*fl r ' StC\4_ '~cUu. k: bo C. &lt;&gt;M~t ' Uth reference to tty telegram !to« 419 of the ath Cctcbor la at concerning the desire of the United states Oovernaaent to appoint a oonaalar official at Dahran the ^ principal seat of operations of the California Arabian Jtandard Cil Company, I have the honour to inform you that the nlted states minister Resident again pressed the United states Government*a claim to consular representation in that area during the visit of the United states military mission. % h- 4 a. Ibn Saud later caused the United btates liniater to be informed that he had no objection to the United dtatea Government appointing a commercial agent, a firm or person comparable to the local British firm of Gellatly, Hankey and Company but that he was not prepared to agree to consular representation at any place in his territories other than Jedda. 3. Kia Majesty also stipulated that a commercial agent if appointed by the United States Government would have no authority to intervene in the relations between the iaudl Government and the California Arabian standard Oil Company. 4. A copy of this deapatoh has been sent to the minister of dtate resident in Cairo. I have the honour to be, with the highest respect, dir, iour most obedient, humble servant, 3. R. JORDAN The Right Honourable Anthony Aden, H.C., M.P., Ac . 4:0 * dC . , foreign Office.■■■■PS h—HBH im ■ Ibn Saad states that United States Minister now in Riyadh is pressing for authority to establish Consular post at Danran. Ibn Saud has refused but said that United States Government could appoint a Commercial Agent at that place if they desired. 2. He has instructed Feisal in the United States to inform the United States Government of his objection which he claims is supported by his people.- ^ SP INWARD TELEGRAM l n A n SECRET — •. -J' _££698 (if in any case the communication of the contents of _ jfrh- r document to any person outside Government SeJ .ce is authorised* it must be paraphrased). Allotted to External Department* Oopie a Circulated, CYPHER T E L £ G R A M From 'Prior'. To Tehran* Repeated to External Affairs Department New Delhi, Dated Shiraz* 16,30 hours, PQth August* 1943* Recei ved 17.30 hours, 29th August, 1943.- IMPORTANT. T/ 576, Addressed to Tehran repeated to External Affairs Department New Delhi** Following Is repetition of Koweit telegram 122 August 26th. Beglrn ; Colonel Hoskins President Roosevelt’s personal envoy to Ibn Saud arrived Am August 26th from Saudi Arabia and left for Basra after calling on Sheikh. 2 t In course of conversation he said his visit to Saudi Arabia had been agreed to by His La.jesty ’ s Government and that he had discussed Arab federation and/and Jews with Ibn Saud and would report to Roosevelt immediately on arrival in thS^Ao His report would later be shown to His Maoesty’s Government* • He confirmed that Amir Raisal w r ould (? shortly) pay an official visit to thSoA. probably immediately after Ramzan, Invitation was I understand extended to Ibn Saud but he deputed Faisal to act (? for him) instead of Saud because latter is said to have eye trouble (Saud is in charge of tribal affairs and (2 corrupt groups) be spared). 4, Hoskins talk(?ed to) me of Zion:i(?s)t movement in lhS*A«. and indiscretions in American press. It might well be his visit was t.o reassure Ibn Saud and counteract Jewish propaganda* g.nds»With the Compliments of THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs. Foreign Office. // , WSd. iECoTPOLOtPt. 12 FEB1938 15844 -A (4'Copy. (E 701/701/25) Ns^ 50/4 64/1. Confidential . n 1 'iu' BRITISH LEGATION, JEDDA, SAUDI ARABIA. 9th January, 1938. My dear Rendel, It seems that the representative of the California Arabian Standard Oil Company in Jedda reports direct to the State Department in Washington on matters of political interest. There is no reason why he should not, but it is worth mentioning. As you know, there is no official United States representative here, and is is unlikely that an appointment will result from the enquiry, reported in the Jedda Report fo r February, 1937 , para 83, which was made on the spot by the United States Consul- General in Alexandria, Mr. Morris, nearly a year ago. During the summer the Assistant Manager of C.A.S.O.C. ■^pj[ 0 ( 3 _ 'to pump our late accountant, Porter, about the alleged smuggling of arms into Saudi Arabia through the Gulf of Akaba, having he said been asked by his Company to find out all he could about the matter. More recently we came across another instance of the interest of C.A.S.O.C. in the arms question. Judd had to go to Egypt to see a dentist and on the way he talked much to a Canadian of Hungarian extraction named VACZEK who had been staying with Lenahan, the Manager of C.A.S.O.C. in Jedda - without, by the way, ever coming near the British Legation* Vaczek represents/ G.W.Rendel Esq., C.M.G., Foreign Office.-represents an American firm, Chesborough and Weekes, in Cairo, which serves apparently as a kind of American commercial intelligence bureau for the Near East. He asked Judd from whom Ibn Saud received the supply of arms which arrived recently, i.e. those sold to him by His Majesty's Government, as Lenahan was interested and wanted to report it. Judd found it easy to evade the inquiry on the ground that he was away on leave when the arms arrived. Judd concluded at the time that the information was wanted by Lenahan's commercial principals in America, but during a call which he made on Vaczek on a personal matter, at the office of Chesborough and Weekes, where he met the principals of this business, he learned quite definitely that Lenahan sends reports to the State Department. I am sending a copy of this letter to Cairo (No. 51/464/1). Yours ever (Signed) R.w.Bullard. £4 dtp m \ ' vr&gt; EXFi&gt;. In any further communication on this subject, please quote * No. t-YA-^S- Wv-kvUS . and address—no^ to any person by name, but to— ‘The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. 1. f P. Z71 I ' r ;' o I 1 1954 ... ,J l^c THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to kXj^cSslA &lt;x &lt; 0 ^ and, by direction of the Secretary of State, ■transmits herewith cop'-*-** of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, &lt;^o—. , 193V . Reference to previous correspondence : ¥ % 'll X Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. W.CCv . Subject. ENCLOSURE IN WEEKLY U-TTER NO. 4 25 JAN. 1934 FROM SECRETARY, POLITIC SECRET DEPT. INDIA OFFICE{E 7491/7491/36) No 360 . (?3&lt;19/2723/3). Britisii Legation, Sir I have the honour to transmit to you herewith W/ the translation of a brief announoement which appeared in the ’’Umm-al-'ura^ of the loth November, according to which diplomatic notes, relating to commerce, shipping. etc., were signed on the 7th November last in London by the united States Ambassador and the Sa*ddi Arab Minister, on behalf of their respective Governments. % 2. This perhaps follows as a natural consequence upon the grant of the Easa Oil Concession to an .jaerican Company. It would be of interest to know more exactly the provisions of the notes which have new been signed and I should be grateful if copies could be sent to me, should they be procurable. 3. I am Bending copies of this despatch and its enclosure to The principal secretary of state for Foreign Affairs, Department of overseas Trade and to The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. I have, etc. (Signed) a. 3. Calvert. The Right Honourable, Sir Jo tin S imo n, vr.C.S.X., L.C./.G*,Enclosure to Jedda despatch No*330 to foreign Office -12/11/38 Ti&amp;NSLATIOtf. EXTHACT from the Mecca ^Umm-al^ura* 1 No&gt;465 of Ip/ll/gS . BETWEEN the Government of His Majesty the King and the United states of America. The Sa’&amp;di Minister at London and the Ambassador 0 f the united States of America have signed diplomatic notes which take the place of a treaty concerning trade and navigation affairs, etc. on the 7th November 1923.THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY’S GOVERNMENT EASTERN (Arabia). Decembrnnrrwsi. CONFIDENTIAL. SE&lt;?Tiort 3. E 7725/7491/25] No. 1. (No. 332.) Sir, Sir John Simon to Sir A. Ryan (Jedda). Foreign Office, December 14, 1933. WITH reference to Mr. Calvert’s despatch No. 330 of the 12th November, I transmit to you the accompanying copy of a provisional agreement relating to commerce, shipping, &amp;c., which was signed on the 7th November last in London by the United States Ambassador and the Saudi Arabian Minister on behalf of their respective Governments. 2. This copy has been obtained from the Saudi Arabian Minister in London, who stated that the agreement was not confidential and would eventually be published both in Saudi Arabia and in the United States. 3. A copy of this despatch is being sent to His Majesty’s Ambassador at Washington. of Saudi Arabia in regard to Diplomatic and Consular Representation, Juridical Protection, Commerce and Navigation. THE undersigned, the Hon. Robert Worth Bingham, Ambassador Extra ordinary and Plenipotentiary of the United States of America at London, and Sheikh Hafiz Wahba, Minister of the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia at London, desiring to confirm and make a record of the understanding which they have reached in the course of recent conversations in the names of their respective Governments in regard to diplomatic and consular representation, juridical protection, commerce and navigation, have signed this provisional agreement:— The diplomatic representatives of each country shall enjoy in the territories of the other the privileges and immunities derived from generally recognised international law. The consular representatives of each country, duly provided with exequatur, will be permitted to reside in the territories of the other in the places wherein consular representatives are by local laws permitted to reside; they shall enjoy the honorary privileges and the immunities accorded to such officers by general international usage; and they shall not be treated in a manner less favourable than similar officers of any other foreign country. Subjects of His Majesty the King of the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia in the United States of America, its territories and possessions, and nationals of the United States of America, its territories and possessions, in the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia, shall be received and treated in accordance with the requirements and practices of generally recognised international law. In respect of their persons, possessions and rights, they shall enjoy the fullest protection of the laws and authorities of the country, and they shall not be treated in regard to their persons in any manner less favourable than the nationals of any other foreign country. I am, &amp;c. JOHN SIMON. Enclosure in No. 1. Provisional Agreement between the United States of America and the Kingdom Article 1. Article 2.2 Article 3. In respect of import, export and other duties and charges affecting commerce and navigation, as well as in respect of transit, warehousing, and other facilities, the United States of America, its territories and possessions, will accord to the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia, and the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia will accord to the United States of America, its territories and possessions, unconditional most favoured-nation treatment. Every concession with respect to any duty, charge or 4 * regulation affecting commerce or navigation now accorded or that may hereafter be accorded by the United States of America, its territories and possessions, or by the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia to any foreign country will become immediately applicable without request and without compensation to the commerce and navigation of the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia and of the United States of America, its territories and possessions, respectively. Article 4. The stipulations of this agreement shall not extend to the treatment which is accorded by the United States of America to the commerce of Cuba under the provisions of the Commercial Convention concluded between the United States and Cuba on the 11th December, 1902, or the provisions of any other commercial convention which hereafter may be concluded between the United States of America and Cuba. Such stipulations, moreover, shall not extend to the treat ment which is accorded to the commerce between the United States of America and the Panama Canal Zone or any of the dependencies of the United States of America or to the commerce of the dependencies of the United States of America with one another under existing or future laws. Nothing in this agreement shall be construed as a limitation of the right of either Government to impose, on such terms as it may see fit, prohibitions or restrictions of a sanitary character designed to protect human, animal or plant life, or regulations for the enforcement of police or revenue laws, Nothing in this agreement shall he construed to affect existing statutes of l either country in relation to the immigration of aliens or the right of either Government to enact such statutes. Article 5. The present stipulations shall become operative on the day of signature hereof and shall remain respectively in effect until the entry in force of a definitive treaty of commerce and navigation, or until thirty days after notice of their termination shall have been given by the Government of either country, but, should the Government of the United States of America be prevented by future action of its Legislature from carrying out the terms of these stipulations, the obligations thereof shall thereupon lapse. Article 6. The English and Arabic texts of the present agreement shall be of equal validity. Signed at London, this 7th day of November, 1933. (Seal) (Seal)In any further communifftion on this subject/ please quote r~ 77, l(^ ^ no. \ Hzt/H/o/ If s —not to any person by navtei but to— and address —not to any person ty natnel bi “ The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. i. i --r -v £)\J /Z» I 1931 _ conn THE Under-Secretaiy of State for Foreign Affairs presents his ipliments to JlU ^IuajU\ w jjatf fjt* and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop Ifi of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, I'm,i93t. Reference to previous correspondence Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. x/MK . f (MJwvKpf l7i\ ' ^ j-LtUA, tf&amp;lKaAj Subject. 7 JlTodu IINDIA OFFICE RECORDS ..rJAQ.U MICROFILM * y ■ I</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000555.0x000296_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/2124</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000555.0x000296</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/2124</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 6/57 'U.S.A.: Saudi Relations with U.S.A.'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1931/1947</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-05-05T11:26:06</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (64 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 66; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 1-64; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file concerns relations between Saudi Arabia and the United States, and features the following principal correspondents: His Majesty's Chargé d’Affaires to Jedda (Albert Spencer Calvert); His Majesty's Chargé d'Affaires to Washington (Ronald Ian Campbell); His Majesty's Minister at Jedda (Sir Reader William Bullard, and later, Stanley R Jordan); the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf; the Secretary of State for India; the United States Consul, Dhahran; Isaiah Berlin (writing from the British Embassy, Washington); officials of the Foreign Office and the Government of India's External Affairs Department.The correspondence includes discussion of the following:The United States Government's recognition of King Ibn Saud [‘Abd al-‘Azīz bin ‘Abd al-Raḥmān bin Fayṣal Āl Sa‘ūd] in 1931.The conclusion of a provisional agreement between the United States and the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia, regarding diplomatic and consular representation, juridical protection, commerce and navigation, dated 7 November 1933.Details of the visit of Colonel Harold Hoskins, President Roosevelt's personal envoy, to Saudi Arabia in August 1943.Details of the visit of Emir Feisal [Fayṣal bin ‘Abd al-‘Azīz Āl Sa‘ūd], Saudi Minister for Foreign Affairs, and his brother Khalid [Khalid ibn 'Abdul 'Aziz Āl Sa‘ūd], to the United States in September-October 1943.The United States Government's request to establish consular representation in Saudi Arabia, which the British Government advises Ibn Saud to accept.The reflections of Foreign Office officials on the United States' possible economic and strategic interests in Saudi Arabia.Ibn Saud's acceptance of the appointment of a United States Consul at Dhahran in 1944.In addition to correspondence, the file includes a copy of the aforementioned Saudi-United States provisional agreement, plus a number of extracts from various United States newspapers and news agencies.The file includes a divider which gives a list of correspondence references contained in the file by year. This is placed at the back of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Minister for Foreign Affairs</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Chargé d’Affaires</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>British Embassy</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Ambassador to Saudi Arabia</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Chargé d'Affaires to Jeddah</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Secretary of State for India and Burma, United Kingdom</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Indian Political Service, External Affairs Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>United States Consul General, Dhahran</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>United States Federal Government</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>King of Saudi Arabia</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Arabian American Oil Company</namePart></name></subject><subject><geographic>Dhahran</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Bilateral relations</topic></subject><subject><topic>Consular services</topic></subject><subject><topic>Diplomacy</topic></subject><subject><topic>Royal visits</topic></subject><subject><topic>Visits</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000555.0x000296#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>