<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000881.0x000004_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-09-12T11:49:29.715Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">mmNo.C.-Za .8/50 POLITICAL AGSWCY, MUSCAT • From To Tht Superintendent| Central Btentai hospital, Yeravtia. The Political Agent, rjuacat Sir, I have the honour to refer to your letter No.S/6690 dated the 20tli November, 194^, on the subject of the replacement of Almas Juma the private servant of patient Saiyid All bin Faisal and to state that the Muscat State authorities have no objection to the return to ita^cat of Almas Juma provided a replacement can be found locally who will accept the same pay. They will be grateful for your assistance in making tills arrangement. 1 have the honour to ba, Sir, Your most obedient servant VC for Political Agent, Muscat.n^yv* ✓ v Y.P.P.—S 940—8,000 (80 Bks.) + loose 20,800z—9-41—82*—st. e; (ju Spl—M. H. 17 s. C.M. No. Datecl r ,U H 19^4 194 1* 7 k. r ! O -4- [Interest at 7 pep cent pep annum ehapg-ed on accounts remaininsf unpaid : ^ one month after delivery. If the bill is not paid within a period of six months after its delivery interest at 8 per cent will be charged.] ' A *■. fp - , /P Jsj'mj ^ ^ { ^ Name of patient OJL^&lt;K Particulars of charges. No. of days. Amount. Remarks. Maintenance charges in advance from / to at 2&gt; per diem... Arrears as per bill No. /?z£. dated g/Vk, /9&lt;ft, Wages of a special attendant .. 3/ fZ-o-a //$~o Washing charges Miscellaneous private charges ... Total UK - o -ts 3 ^ —o Total Rupees {in words) l/mchda** 0 / Cb No:? p-To- pe^ (eec.&lt;kO 1^7 (QM* M L i l Notks.— 1. All remittances should be made payable to the Superintendent of v,nu&gt;p. 2. While remitting the charges a reference should be made invariably to the bill No. in the coupon of the money order form. ^ 3. Changes of addresses should be communicated regularly.-V NO. ZQ/&lt;? Office of the Treasury Offic ^ (Government of Hnsoat ^ Omar , KuHCcit, the 15th January 1945, To, Hi a Britannic fajesity'a Consul, Muscat, qi o-a- , T have the honour to form arc! herewith / the sum of 113/4/- ( Bupees one hundred eighteen and annas four only ) being Hospital expenses of C. Ali bin Faisel and his servant*s pay for the month of January 1945 Kindly acknowledge receipt, I have the honour to be, Sir , Your most obedient servant* HtC Treasury Officer, Muscat Btat e.a Ho.C./#’ .8/60. To POLITICAL AGLNCtt, .^USCaT. Th* ^January, 1945. The Cuparintendent, Central Mental Hospital, Yaravda. I enclose herewith a bank draft for fis.118/- representing the following 1. Maintenance charges of Saiyid All bin Faisal for the month of •January, 19^5. .. ..It. 93- 0- 0 3. rfages of his special attendant•• Hs. 25- 0- 0 Total 8s.118- 0- 0 Please acknowledge receipt. V for Political Agent, Muscat.■mi No. 33/Sii Office of the Treasury Officer (iovernraent of ?£uscat &amp; Oman, Muscat, the l^th February 1945* To His Britannic “ajesty's Consul, Muscat. Sir, I have the honour to forward herewith the sum of Ps. 109/4/- ( Bupees one hundred nine and annas four only ) being Hospital expenses of Sayed £li bin *aisel and his servant*3 pay for the month of February 1945. The receipt may please bo acknowledged. . , ^ * -u 1 have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant, n Treasury Officer, Muscat Stafc e. 7^'Y.P.P.—S 940—8,000 (80 Bks.)+loose 20,300z—9-41—32*—st. Reg. No. Bill No. ' C.M. No. Dated I94 1 Spl. —M. H. ITeT i 194 To A i ~ 1— \K.S p » N y [Interest at 7 per cent per annum charged on accounts remaining unpaid one month after delivery. If the hill is not paid within a period of six months after its delivery interest at 8 per cent will be charged.] ' &gt; • Name of patient _ Maintenance charges in advance from / to 3S- 3/ at 3~0—0 per diem... D-R.^d; J/. f-TO- *P€{ Arrears as per bill No. dated ... Wages of a special attendant .. Washing charges Miscellaneous private charges ... Total Total Eupees (in ivords) &amp;1. spjtal. JSTotf.s. —1. All remittances should be made payable to the Superintendent of 2. While remitting the charges a reference should be made invariably to the bill No. in the coupon of the money order form. 3. Changes of addresses should be communicated regularly.} 1 Y.P.P.—S 94C&gt;—8,000 (80 Bks.) 4 -loose 20,800z—9-41—32*—st- Reg. No. Bill No. * \^VTV) ' , , hTits: C.M. No. Dated 1 0TB1945 '• M ;- , i,._i: v ' ' ^ ^ — X-i i Clnterest at 7 pec cent pec annum charged on accounts remaining unpaid 0 ne month after delivery. If the bill is not paid within a period of six months after its delivery interest at 8 per cent will be charged.] Name of patient ...» Particulars of charges. No. of day; Maintenance charges in advance from. y to .2 8 -?- 4-i- a* 3 —O per diem... *-8 $&lt;/-* Arrears as per bill No. 44 dated / C j CH%^aa &lt;£ *y- - r c r l AS *... Wages of a special attendant . ^Washing charges PAY MENTIS REQUESTED Miscellaneous private charges ... / / 8 - 0 ~ &lt; L JL O-R-No.-^^ P 'iTO-pf) vi''' Total Total Rupees {in words) 9 * Notes.— 1. All remittances should be made payable to the Superint™^7t, of‘AjQntfjjj^iJfJ^A^KI'^idvance. 2- While remitting the charges a reference should be made invariably to the bill No. in the coupon of the money order form. 8. Changes of addresses should be communicated regularly.V a X O From v ' / * No. S//^ '3 2 ..of 194 Central mental hospital: Yeravda, 30th January 1945 . THE SUPERINTENDENT, TO Sir. Subject: -Private attendant Almas Juma, or patient Saiyid Alii Bin -Faisal - Heturn of - Wrtfi reference to your letter dated 8 th January 1945 , _ h'o. 0 * 22 - 8 / 50 , I have the honour to state that I am trying to - get a suitable substitute for Almas Juma^knowing Arabic in — ^ Bombay, and as soon as one is available he will be relieved of his duties..In the meantime will you arrange for his passage the probable time of his sailing to Muscat may please be intima -ted to this Office. He will also have to be provided with monej for his return journey* He will be paid his wages upto date of his relief. Please treat this matter as most urgent . TheNo.C.231-8/50 POLITICAL AGENCY, MUSCAT From Lieut. Colonel A. C. Galloway Political Agent, Muscat. To Messrs. Mackinnon Mackenzie &amp; Company Limited, Bombay. Dated Muscat, tne 28th February, 1945 Deal- Sirs I shall be glad if you will kindly arrange to reserve a deck passage from Bombay to Muscat for one Almas Juma, and inform the Superintendent, Central Mental Hospital, Yaravda, the approximate date on which Almas Juma should reach Bombay. Yours faithfully, Political Agent, Muscat No.C.282-8/50 POLITICAL AGENCY, MUSCAT The 28th February, 1945. Copy forwarded to the Superintendent, Central Mental Hospital, Yaravda, with reference to his letter No.S/1432 of 1945 dated the 30th January, 1945, with the request that the sum of rupees sixty (Rs.60/-) only may please be advanced to Almas Jume^to cover his travelling expenses from Yaravda to Bombay by rail and thence by steamer to Muscat. The amount will be reimbursed on receipt of your bill. Political Agent, Muscat.NO. 38/54 Office of the Treasury Officer, v Governmen tof Muscat &amp; onai , Muscat, the 11th ^arch 1945. To, f Hi 8 Hritannic Majesty's consul, ' Muscat. 1 S ir * 1 have the honour to send herewith the sum of te. 118/4/- ( Bupees one hundred eighteen and annas four only ) on account of Hospital expenses of S. Ali Din Fttisel and his servants pay for the month of March 1945. The receipt may olease he acknowledged. I h&amp;ve the honour to he, Sir. Tour most obedient servant. y . Treasury Officer, Muscat Stafc e.a i M No.C.440-8/60. Al) To POLITICAL ASENCY, MUSCAT The 18th March, 1946. The Superintendent, Central liental Hospital, Yaravda. MEMORANDUM I enclose herewith a bank draft for ffc.118/- presenting the following 1. Maintenance charges of Saiyid Ali bin Faisal for the month of March, 1946. 2. Wages of his special attendant Total.. Please acknowledge receipt. fts. 93— 0—0 fc. 26- 0-0 Rs • 118— 0—0 Political Agent, Muscat,¥ No • C • 441-8/50 » HIS BRITANIvIC MAJESTY'S CONSULATE, Bftiscat, the 13th ?larch, 1945. To The Treasury Officer, \5iscat State, Muscat. The sum of ?!s. 118/4/- sent with your letter No.38/54 dated the 11th March, 1945, has been received. fe His Britannic Majesty's Consul, Muscat.MR All Communications to be Addressed to:— MACKINNON MACKENZIE &amp; CO., Agents, B. I. S. N. Co., Ltd., KARACHI. raphic Address:—MACKINNONS. No. 2. BRITISH INDIA STEAM NAVIGATION COMPANY, LIMITED. IN REPLY PLEASE QUOTE No- £&gt;/PSA/349. Teleohona : —KARACHI 2836. tJfyatac/i, 'U (Incorporated in England) Post Box No. 40. 9th March, 5 • Messrs:Macklnnon Mackenzie &amp; Go., Agents, B.I.S.N.Co.Ltd., Bo^ay. Bear Sirs, We enclose a letter In original.. No:C.281-8/50 dated 28th February 1^45, received hy us from the Political agent, Muscat . which is addre 8 sed to you. Yours faithfully, Pro: Mack inn on Mackenzie Sc Go. sd/-W.alien. A3°nts. Bhcl:-1. Copy to*Lt.Col.A.C.Galloway,Political agent, MC Muscat, for information. ©No. 3 / /£ ?&gt;/ of 194 5 . Central m Yeravda, 13 th Central mental hospital : Yeravda, 13th tjl A S C H 1945 • Grant of dearness allowance to private servant hin 5aisal. Grant of dearness allowan Subject :— MEMORANDUM Reference jour letter No.C/267» dated 27 th March 19^3« fhe Government of Bombay have sanctioned a dearness of Ks.14 per mensem from 1st April I 944 . At present the attendant of Baid Alii bin Raisal is paid Fa. 25 /- per mensem as agreed to. Th-e -- Government attendants are getting i^s.33/- from 1st April 1944-* 1 am sure that you will agree with me that the private attendants are also entitled to this increase; and it has become very dif- -ficult to get private attendants on the old scale of pay. it is therefore decided that they may be paid the minimum salary of - S 3 ; 30/- p.m. v/ith effect from 1st January 19^5* if not from the retrospective effect from 1st April 194-4-• Please let me know as soon as possible what you would like me to do. It may not be possible to keep private attendants for le-ss than Es. 30 /- hereafter. H.G.K 13/3.Y.P.P.—S 1140—8,000 (80 Bks.) + loose 20,3O0z—9-41—32*—st- Reg. No. Bill No. V r * v C.M. No. Dated UMAR 1945 Spl.—M. H. 17 e, 194 To vJTNf , -r * -^'4' ] ' r ' I J r - '^ e —n C _iq. -4— pO ! ‘ X ( - A -- -S'',* li'zr r i t&gt;4 ^ -^2.1—J- tlnterest at 7 per cent per annum charged on accounts remaining unpaid one month after delivery. If the bill is not paid within a period of six months after its delivery interest at 8 per cent will be charged.] Name of patient A a*, '-f ® £ | £&gt;; Particulars of charges. No. of days. Amount. Remarks. Maintenance charges in advance from / at a to 3/- 3 '^A per diem... Arrears as per bill No. 2 fr* dated /a &amp; /Ce£. 4 ± ... Wages of a special attendant .. 3 / 9 3-o QMo-.g R. Z/ i /e iJ / ^ , Yashing charges EASILY PAYMENT IS REQUESTED Miscellaneous private charges t.Eavel 11# Ain: m -ses to attendant Almas Juma, Total ^y'c^ Z 6 '-o - o g expen 60-0-0, I7S~ o - £ Total Rupees (m ivords) One Hundred and Seventy di^ht only. al Ho spital. Notes.—1. All remittances should her made payable to the Superintendent of * 2. While remitting the charges a reference should be madajnvariably to the bill No. in the coupon of the money order form. 3. Changes of addresses should be communicated regularly.548-8/50 .y His Britannic Majesty’s Consulate, Muscat* 'he 4th. April, 1^45. Lyid Shihab bin Faisal, Minister for External Affairs, Muscat* compliments, With reference to your letter No.7/2 dated hh* January, 1945, 1 have the honour to inform you the Bombay Government have sanctioned a dearness mce of Hs• 14/- per mensem to their menial staff with jpective effect from the 1st* April, 1944, and the .ntendent of the Central Mental Hospital, Yaravda, its that the special attendant with oaiyid Ali bin L be paid at least Hs.30/- with effect from 1st* January Please confirm that you have no objection to •oposed increase and that the new local attendant may jaged at Rs.30/- per month. Usual Ending. His Britannic Majesty's Consul, Muscat*No.c.548-8/50 * ,'N l y r-s w vJ^S His Britannic Majesty*&amp; Consulate, Muscat* m he 4th. April, 1^45. Saiyid Shihab bin Faisal, Muscat* After compliments, , ^ With reference to your letter No.7/2 dated the 6+h. January, 1945, 1 have the honour t° inform you that the Bombay Government have sanctioned a dearness allowance of Hs.14/- per mensem to their menial staff with retrospective effect from the 1st* April,1944, and the Superintendent of the Central Mental Hospital, Xaravda, requests that the special attendant with oaiyid Ali bin Faisal be paid at least Rs.30/- with effect from 1st* January 2* Flease confirm that you have no objection to the proposed increase and that the new local attendant may be engaged at Hs*30/- per month. Usual iiiiding. His Britannic Majesty's Consul, Muscat*wmm mmmmm No. &gt;V?7 Offio® of the Treasury officer, G®vorniient of rsuscat and OJaan, Muscat, th« 18th April 1945. To, His Britannic Majesty’s Consul, Muscat. Sir, I haye the honour t© send herei;ith the sua of Ys„ 115/4/- ( Rupees one hundred fifteen and annas four only ) “being Hospital expenses of S. Ali “bin Kaisel and his servants pay for the nonth of April 1945. Kindly acknoWidege receipt. I hare the honour to he, Sir, Your nost ohedienr ser’vant, Treasury Officer, Muscat State.Ho.£47/8/50 The 22nd. April, 1945. To, Saiyid Shihab bln Faisal, Minister for External ilffairs, Muscat* After compliments, I have the honour to refer you to my letter No.C*548-8/50, dated the 4th. April, 1945# and to request the favour of an early roply. t \ Usual ending. His Britannic Majesty's Consul, Muscat.No.C.763-3/50. To HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY’S CONSULATE, Muscat, the 17th May, 1945- The Treasury Officer, Muscat State, Muscat. MEMORANDUM The sum of fc.llS/V- sent with your letter No.3&amp;/93 dated the 17th Uay 9 1945, has been received. 7 His Britannic Majesty’s Consul, C • Muscat. \ '(a (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND) THI REPLY TO BE ADDRESSED Mackinnon. Mackenzie AGENTS. BOMBAY. 8c Co Telegraphic Address: 'MACKINNONS' Telephone: 25021. IN REPLY PLEASE QUOTE 4 th ApriX Lieut. Coi.A.C.Galloway, O.B.K., PosT Box No ' 122 Political Agent, Muscat. }Cj Dear Sir, Fe are in receipt of your letter No.( .281-3/50 dated the 28th February 1345, and as desired we have commui icated with the Superintendent, central Mental Hospital, Yaravda, in regard to a passage for one Almas Juma from Bombay to Muscat. He wi^ l be provided with a -Passage in due course, but in the meantime we sh; 11 be glad if you will confirm that he is in possession of a valid pass] ort; also please advise us to whom the bill for cost of his passage shou. d be submitted. Yours faitJhfuliy, Pro:xii.iiCh, « CONo.C.808-8/50 £ ^ y f POLITICAL AGENCY, MUSCAT• The 23rd May, 1946• To MOssrs. Mackinnon Mackenzie &amp; Company Limited Bombay. Dear Sirs, With reference to your letter No.P/B.l dated the 4th April, 1946, I have to inform you that the cost of the passage will be paid in cash by Almas Jume. 2, The Superintendent, Central Mental Hospital, Yaravda, to whom you have already referred the matter (Your letter No.P/B.l dated the 6th April, 1946, refers) will confirm the validity of the passport of Almas Jume. Yours faithfully, V K Political Agent, Muscat. Copy forwarded for information to the Superintendent, Central Mental Hospital, Yaravda.Y.P.P.—S 940 -8,000 (80 Bks.) + loose 20,300z—9-41—S2*—st KS*/ Spl.—M. H. 17 e. Reg. No. To Bill No. W C.M. No. (TN L* '{t;,, 0 TR' Dated_ 2i^' P Rl945l_ 194 \ fj q * r^KjM Zl v 'A _ / O eJl o (Intepest at 7 pep cent pep annum charged on accounts remaining unpaid ' one month after delivery. If the bill is not paid within a period of six months after its delivery interest at 8 per cent will be charged.] Name of patient ^ ^ ^ JJ Particulars of charges. No. of dai s. ! Amount. Maintenance charges in advan to at per diem.. Arrears as per bill No. /? : V •. dated / Remarks. Wages of a special attendant... vVashing charges UMLY ■PAYM.^Y4^££ t Ui Miscellaneous private charges ... &lt;5- ^ £-4^ Total /KO -a o 0 - R'^o: in) /v ' Total Rupees (in words) SfliiiiiiiiitfndHit, aiuditl ttiapital. Notes. — 1. All remittances should be made payable to the Superinteudent of AOGOUNTA^dvanc. 2. While remitting the charges a reference should be made invariably to the bill No. in the coupon of the money order form. ^ 3. Changes of addresses should be communicated regularly.Fo. sa/Z/y Office of the Treasury Officer, Government of Muscat A Oman , Muscat, the 16th June 1945, To, His Britannic Maj Cs 1 u It Sir, I have the honour to send herewith the sum of Rso 115/4/- ( Rupees one hundred fifteen and annas four only ) hein^ Hospital expenses of S. Ali 'bin Faisel anf his servant's pay for the month of June 1945. The receipt may please he aolga owl edged. I have the honour to he, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Treasury officer, Muscat State.'^ppi.jjV UPPP? Spl.—M. H. 11 Bill No. C.M. No. Dated l &amp;yAlUSi.i 193 To ~ ,r Y- P -T v-O n •' &lt;-( ' . w ' r-o*. • 1 ! ‘ l n [Interest at 7 per cent per annum charged on accounts remaining unpaid one month after delivery. If the bill is not paid within a period of six months afte r its delivery interest at 8 per cent will be charged.] Name of patient Particulars of charges. Maintenance charges in advance from / to 3/ - 5~~ at Ah g/- per diem... Arrears as per bill No. dated ; ■ f • • • Wages of a special attendant ... V ,shing charges ... EARLr AAYMENT IS REQUESTED Miscellaneous private charges ... Total ... Total Rupees (in words) ■ ■Supcrmfrcgdcnt,- Ment;-)!. Hospital. 2 g OTE8- i. a. 11 remittances should be made payable to the SuperintendeutALtGCi^N^AN^ly in advance. 2. While remitting the charges a reference should be made invariably to the bill No. in the coupon of the money order form. 3. Changes of addresses should be communicated regularly.Reg. No. To Bill No. Dated C.M. No. 1 3 JUNIUS 193 [Interest at 7 per cent per annum charged on accounts remaining unpaid one month after delivery. If the bill is not paid within a period of six months afte r its delivery interest at 8 per cent will be charged.] ame of patient v ^ Particulars of charges. No. of days. Amount. Remarks. Maintenance charges in advance from to ^ o c \ l\ ' ) Q at per diem... Arrears as per bill No. ^ * dated / ... Wages of a special attendant ... V’^shing charges EARLY PAY Mi Miscellaneous private charges ... ENT IS REQUEi . Total ... f ! Y&amp;~£ 40 Total Rupees (in words) Mental Hospital. Notes.— 1. All remittances should be made payable to the Superintendent aclvance ' 2. While remitting the charges a reference should be made invariably to the billNa inttie coupon of the money order form. 3. Changes of addresses should be communicated regularly.\V £ Ho.C.968-8/50. U' To / / V/v POLITICAL AGENCY 9 MUSCAT The 15th July, 1945. The Superintendent, Bentral Mental Hospital, Yaravda, MEMORANDUM I enclose herewith a bank draft for \ Rs. 118/- representing the following t- 1. Maintenance charges of Saiyid All bin Faisal for the month of July, 1945 * 2. Wages of his special attendant «• Total Rs. 93- 0-0 Rs. 25- 0-0 Rs.118- 0-0 Please acknowledge receipt. Political Agent, Muscat,Ho.0.969-8/50 HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY’S CONSULATE, Muscat, the 15th July, 1945. Ttoa Treasury Officer, Muscat State, Muscat. ^QRANDUM The sun of Rs .118/4/- sent with your letter Ne.38/128 dated the 15th July, 1945, has been receiyed. 4 c His Britannic Majesty's Consul, MuscatITO. 16/_? OiTice cf the Treasury Officer, Governnent of ] r uscat &amp; Oman, Muscat, the 3th August 1945 c To, /- V His Britannic majesty # s Consul, Mu s ca t* Sir, I have the honour to forward herewith tie sura cf Rs. 118/4/- ( Rupees one nundred and eighteen and annas four only ) on account of Hospital expenses of s. Ali hin Faisel and his servant's pay for the month of August 1945* The receipt may please he acknowledged. I have the honour to he, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Treasury Officer , Muscat State.No.C.1100-8/50. POLITICAL AGENCY, MUSCAT, Dated 12th. August, 1945. J To The Superintendent, Central Mental hospital; laravda. Memorandum . ,1 enclose herewith a tank draft for Re-118/- representing the following: 1- Maintenance charges of Saiyid All bin Faisal for the month of August, 1945 Rs. 93-0-0 2. Wages of his special attendant Rs. 25-0-0 Total Rs.118-0-0 2. Please acknowledge receipt. Political Agent, Muscat.Memorandum. The sum of Rs.118/4/“ sent with your letter Mo. 16/3, dated the 8th. August. 1945&gt; has been received.^ ^ • ur Office of the Treasury Officer, Government of Muscat &amp; Oman, Muscat, the ISth September, 1945* NO. 16/V m To Hia Britannic Majesty # s Gonsul Muscat Sir I have the honour to send herewith the sum of Ps* 115/4/- ( 'Rupees one hundred anf fifteen and annas four only ) 'being Hospital expenses of S. Ali bin Faisel and his servant's pay for the month of September 1945* The receipt mayp please be acknov/1 edged. 1 have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Treasury Officer Muscat State.( )x\) Ho.C. 1230 - 8 / 50 . POLITICAL AGENCY, MUSCAT, Dated 15th. September, 1945. The Superintb*.^«^w, Central Mental Hospital TARAVDA. Memorandum. I enclose herewith a bank draft for Rs.115/- representing the following: 1. Maintenance charges of Saiyld All bin Faisal for the month of September, 1945. 2. Wages of his special attendant Total * 2. Please acknowledge receipt. f\ ? 5\- Political Agent, Muscat. f/^ 1 —— :No.0.1^31-8/50. HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY'S CONSULATE, MUSCAT, Dated 15th September, 1945. To T* 1 MUSCAT. Memorandum. The sum of Rs.115/4/* sent with your letter No. 16/7, doted the 13th. September, 1945, has been received. O'' His Britannic Majesty's Consul, Muscat.r e Bill No. $ To W C.M. No. Dated ?Oth . July . 1 Q45 ft \ V Spl.—M. H. 17 e. 193 [Interest at 7 per cent per annum charged on accounts remaining unpaid . month after delivery. If the bill is not paid within a period of six months afte r its delivery interest at 8 per cent will be charged.] one iName of patient Particulars of charges. No. of days. Amount. Remarks. Maintenance charges in advance from to ! at per diem... Arrears as per bill No. wa ^ es dated • are 1 . as no servant m pi Attendant 7.45 ace of Wages of a special attendant ...- ... w-tm*- 0 r Almas Jumraa, is kept Wasjjj^g charges Miscellaneous private charges ... Total 62/8/- lAs on the - reverse ,plea 155/8 7otal Rupees {in words) eigtit only* OneTiTn^red and TlTty-flve and annas itant, ^ Hospital. iTES. 1- All remittances should be made payable ina^fhe Superintendent of the hospitaladvance. 2. While remitting the charges a reference should be made invariably to the bill No. in the coupon of the money order form. 3. Changes of addresses should be communicated regularly.S s 'V / Y.P.P.—S 940—8,000 (80 Bks.)+loose 20,300z—9-11—S2*—st- Reg. No. Bill No. C.M. No. Dated ^ AUG l$£ Spl.—M. H. 17 a. 194 • r - -U !. J r 'L T y S n ^-H ■ V — —— ^ y [Interest at 7 per cent per annum charged on accounts remaining unpaid one month after delivery. If the bill is not paid within a period of six months after its delivery interest at 8 per cent will be charged.] Aeoocntant, Hospital. Notes— 1. All remittances should be made payable&gt;rtEe Superintendent of the hospital^j^lycte^dvance. 2. While remitting the charges a reference should be made invariably to the bill No. in the coupon of the money order form. 3. Changes of addresses should be communicated regularly.! &gt; \ Ho.C.1344-8/50. To POLITICAL AGENCY, MUSCAT Dated lC)th. October, 1945. The Superintendent, Central Mental Hoepital, YARAVM. Memorandum. I enclose herewith a bank draft for Rs.118/- wlth the request that the amount may be adjusted as followsi 1. Maintenance charges of Salyld All bln Faisal for the month of October, 1945. Rs. 93-0-0 2. Charges Incurred in connection with the repatriation of the attendant Almas Uma to Muscat Rs. 62-8-0 Total Rs. 155-8-0 Less wages of attendant al ready remitted for the months of July, August &amp; September '45.RS. 75-0-0 Net amount due Rs. 80-8-0 2. The balance of Rs .37-8-0 will be adjusted in the next month's bill. A / ^ Political Agent, Muscat. ■— Copy to the Treasury Officer, Muscat State for information No wages for attendant are claimed from 1-7-45 as no ser vant in place of Almas Juma is kept. *mmm ■■■ ■■■HH No.C.1345-8/50. HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY’S CONSULATE, MUSCAT, Dated 10th. October, 1945. To Memorandum. The Treasury Officer, Muscat State, Muscat. x? The sum of Rs.118/4/- sent with your letter No. 17/16^ dated the 8th. October, 1945, has been received. His Britannic Majesty’s Consul, MUSCAT. \ 4No. 0.1521-8/50. POLITICAL AOFNCY, MUSCAT, Dated 22nd. November, 1945. To The Snocrlntendent. Central Wental Hospital, TARAWA. Memorandum. Reference this office Monorendum No.C.1344-^/50, dated the 10th October, 1945. • * • » 2. A bank draft for Re.52-8-0 is enclosed herewith for the maintenance chargee of Saiyid All bin Faisal for the month of November, 1945. 3. Please acknowledge receipt. Political Arent, Muscat. office copyI'turn ■■■■■■■ ■■■ The Treasury Officer, Muscat State, Muscat. Memorandum. The suit of P.s.52/12 sent v/itb your letter No 24/16, dated the 3th. November, 1945. has t©en received. Eis Brittnnic Majesty’s Consul, fAiscat.fnl I -yr Y.P.P.—S 946 -8,000 (80 Bka.) + loose 20,300z -9-41—Sj* 4 —tst.' ' Bill No. C.M. No. Dated ti-' ur Spl.—M. H. 17 e. 194 [Interest at 7 per cent per annum charged on accounts remaining unpaid one — month after delivery. If the bill is not paid within a period of six months after its delivery interest at 8 per cent will be charged.] Name of patient ' • 1 . Hospital. Honsa, 1. All remittances should be made payable to tbe Superintendent of the hospital jteidSfy'^&amp;adYance. 2. While remitting the charges a reference should be made invariably to the bill No. in the coupon of the money order form. 3. Changes of addresses should be communicated regularly.i—i i ■ '•» ^- NO. 16/3$i ST\TB T^^ASTOTj WHOM The liitb December 1945. To, His Britannic Hajesty*s Consul, ttu scat. Sir 1 have the honour to forward herewith the sum of I*. 93/4/- ( Rupees ninety three and annas four only ) on account or Hospital expenses of Sayecl Ali Din Faisel for the month of December 1945. The receipt may please be acknowledged. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servacrt, Treasury Officer, I/uscat State.HHBSPnM @ POLITICAL AGENCY, MUSCAT, Dated 15tb. December, 1945. To The Superintendent, Central Mental Hospital, Yaravda. Memorandum. A bank draft for Rs-93/- is enclosed herewith for the maintenance charges of Saiyid All bin Faisal for the month of December, 1945. 2 . Please acknowledge receipt. “ ■ m Political Agent, Muscat. OFFICE COPYmmm Dated 15th. December, 1945. To The Treasury Officer, Insect State, Muecat. Memorandum. The sub of Rs.93/4 sent with your letter No.16/32, dated the 12th. December, 1945, has been received. His Britannic Majesty's Consul, Muscat. ^. ? 7ICE COPYReceived iYom a cheque of account of. in the pu^onent ’Tac , f y (tioCcd~. Central Mental Hospital, (* el ' vcia ^ -t^c ‘r ireu -. CJ e' * Account-int, C.M.Hospital , lergvda or/bili wo. im Reg. WO. /f/. The Original receipt will 'oa sent with the bill for the next month.ORIGINAL COPY (See I?in. R. No. 1) NOT TRANSFERABLE f fl^No. 95 Gen. / (Pin. R. Form No. j RECEIPT FOR PAYMENT TO GOVERNMENT Place - Date Received from. , Rq (Rupees ) on account of^ (Signature) Cashier or Accountant. (Designation)Y --P-P-—S 946—8,000 (80 Bks.) +loose 20,800z—9-41—S-i*—st Reg. No. Bill No. C.M. No. Dated Spl—M. H. 17 a. 194 ^ [Interest at 7 per cent per annum charged on accounts remaining unpaid one month after delivery. If the bill is not paid within a period of six months after its delivery interest at 8 per cent will be charged.] Name of patient Maintenance charges in advance from cn/ Particulars of charges. No. of days. Amount. Arrears as per bill No. dated ... Wages of a special attendant ./ Washing charges Miscellaneous private charges ... Total •i'O 9o i Remarks. Total Kupees (in words) Hospital. Norms. —1. All remittances should be made payable fo the Superintendent of the hospital httf dranco- 2. While remitting the charges a reference should be made invariably to the bill No in the counon oi the money order form. ‘ F 3. Changes of addresses should be communicated regularly.£1 f:o. S/ //S~*2L OF 194 2 -f - ^ 1 /tf) CENTRAL MENTAL ?iOSPlTAJL Subjects Increase in tke rat^S of maintenance ciiarges ( P00WA 0 )»(§) in respect of Class patients* Rated The //&gt;- // _ 194 ^ Name of patient 1 - Sa*y/&lt;*'(/(cy . ) . :,e r ^ripjEASK N0T5 that Government in their G.R.G.d.No. 9545 dated 6 * 11 . 19 , i '5 kave sanctioned i.n increase of 33 V3 per cent in the rates of maintenance charges chargeable in respect of First and Second class European, Par si and Indian patients with effect from the 16th«of November 19 ^ 5 * As hills for November are already sent out, the claim at increased rate for the remaining period of November I 945 will he included in the hill for December 1945 to be preferred in the first week of December 1943 , lours faithfully, J Lt.OoXrTwVs. ^ 1! Superintem z* /ya&lt;orr*/-_ Central Mental Hospital, leravda* /^/c ^ f# ! e&amp;.n ■ U)' To r\ Y.P.P.—S 946-8,000 (80 Bks.) +loose 20,300z—^41^52*—st. 8pl.—M. H. 17 e. Keg. No. Bill No. C.M. No. Dated 194 [Interest at 7 per cent per annum charged on accounts remaining unpaid 0 ne month after delivery. If the bill is not paid within a period of six months after its delivery interest at 8 per cent will be charged.] Name of patient_ Particulars of charges. No. of days. ! 'Amount. Remarks. Maintenance charges in advance from to at - 4 per diem... Arrears as per bill No. dated __... Wages of a special attendant .. Washing charges Miscellaneous private charges ... Total Total Rupees (in words) il Hospital. Notes. —1. All remittances should bo made payahfe to the Superintendent of the hospitaHtoricayiigadvance. 2. While remitting, the charges a reference should be made invariably to the bill No. in the coupon of the money order form. 8 . Changes of addresses should be communicated regularly.® (g) No.C.1-8/50. My dear friend, The Government of India liave sanctioned an increase of 33 1/3S&amp; in the rates of maintenance chargee chargeable in respect of first and second class patients in the Central Mental Hospital, Yaravda with effect from the 16th November, 1945. 2. I shall be glad if Your Highness will there fore kindly arrange for the sum of Rs. 46 /- (plus commission charges) to be sent to this Consulate for the months of November and December and autho rise fut«re remittances to be made at the rate of Rs. 4 /- per day instead of Rs.3/- per day as pre viously . Your Highness' sincere friend / Eis Highness Saiyid Said bin Taimur, &lt;-f Sultan of Muscat and Oman, iA - Muscat. HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY*S CONSULATE, MUSCAT, Dated 2nd January, 1946.■pum wmmm m No.C.26-8/50. To POLITICAL AGENCY, MUSCAT, Dated 8th January, 1946. The Superintendent, Central Mental Hospital, Yaravda. .-Vy Memorandum. Reference your letter No.S/ll52, dated the 10th November, 1945. 2. A bank draft for Rs. 46 /- for the diffe rence in maintenance charges from 16-11-1945 to 31-12-1945 of Saiyid Ali bin Faisal is en closed. 3. Please acknowledge receipt. Political Agent, Muscat. sSiCE COP^'TOTf/l.gTTnV, MJJSCA.T HO. 16/3 The 8 th January 1946„ To, His Britannic majesty's Oonaul, Muscat. Sir * I have the honour to forward herewith the sum of Fs.lii4/4/- ( Rupees one hundred twenty four and annus four only) on account of Hospital expenses of 3. All hin iraisel for the month of January 1946. The receipts may please he acknowledged. I have the honour to he, dir, Your most obedient servant. fi* Treasury officer Muscat State. * k°No.C.40-8/56 POLITICAL AGENCY, MUSCAT, Dated 11th January, 1946. The Superintendent, Central Mental Hospital, Yaravda. Memorandum. A bank draft for Rs.124/- is enclosed herewith for the maintenance charges of Saiyid Ali bin Faisal for the month of January, 1946. 2. Please acknowledge receipt. Political Agent, Muscat.■■■ No.C. 41-8/50. HIS BRITANNIC fUJESTY’S CONSULATE, MUSCAT, Dated 11th January, 1946. The Treasury Officer, Muscat State, Muscat. Memorandum. The sum of Rs.124/4 sent with your letter No.16/3, dated the 8th January, 1946 has been received. His Britannic Majesty's Consul, Muscat. 6)eNo.C.139-8/50 POLITICAL AGFNCY, MUSCAT, Dated 11th February, 1946. To The Superintendent, Central Mental Hospital, Yaravda (Poona) Memorandum. A bank draft for Rs.124/- is enclosed for the maintenance chargee of Salyld All bln Faisal. 2, A eum of Ha. 112/- may please be adjunted towards the bill for February and the balance of Ra.12/- in next month's bill. 3. Please acknowledge receipt. Sd/- R.I. Hallows, Political Agent, Muscat o No.C.145-8/50 Copy to the Treasury Officer, Muscat State, for information with reference to his letter No. 16/8, dated the 7th February, 1946. His Britannic Majesty's Consul Muscat. OFFICE COPY &gt; $xnNo.C LU-S/50. HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY’S CONSULATE, MUSCAT, Dated 11th February, 1946. To The Treasury Officer, Muscat State, Muscat. L * Memorandum. The sum of Rs.124/4/- sent with your letter No.16/8, dated the 7th February, 1946, has been re ceived . His Britannic Majesty's Consul, Muscat. OFFICE COPYThe Superintendent, Central Mental Hospital, YARaVPa. Memorandum. Reference this office Memorandum No.C.139-&amp;/50, dated the 11th February, 1946. 2. A bank draft for Ra.112/- is enclosed for the maintenance charges of Saiyid Ali bin Faisal for the month of March, 1946. 3- Please acknowledge receipt. Political Agent, Muscat. 21 ^ ^ PY -iPlWHHHHi 4 'V No.C. S^fT-8/50. To HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY’S CONSULATE, MUSCAT, Dated /&amp;/j,March, 1946. The Treasury Officer, Muscat State, Muscat. Memorandum. A 0 The stun of Rs ,112/4 sent with your letter Nc.l6/l6, dated the 9tb March 1946. has been re ceived . His Britannic Majesty’s Consul, ^ Muscat.warn m 3 While remituns amnurJ S Y-P-t'.—S 940—8,000 (80 Bks.)+loode 20 , 300 z— 9 - 41 —S2*—st. pleftSC QUO .■ Spl—M. H. 1 &gt; e. ^ Reg. No. Bill No. C.M. No. 5 JAN Dated 194 To [Interest at 7 per cent per annum charged on accounts remaining unpaid one month after delivery. If the bill is not paid within a period of six months after its delivery interest at 8 per cent will be charged.] Name of patient_ Particulars of charges. No. of days, j Amount. Remarks. Maintenance charges in advance from i - 1 - -d o to : ■ I--'' at Kg: J-}- j per diem... Arrears as per bill No, ^ 2 v ? dated H - Os - ••• Wages of a special attendant .. . _ Washing charges EARLY PAYMENT IS REQUES1 Miscellaneous private charges ... , . Total m r / Total Rupees (in words) t • / f '' ,r *' L / Aceoautant, Hospital. Notes.— 1. All remittances should be made payable to the Superintendent of the hospital YtfiEayCtoadvance. 2. While remitting the charges a reference should bo made invariably to the bill No. in the coupon of the money order form. 3 . Changes of addresses should be communicated regularly.While n n{Ming: amount 4 ' 3 . Y.P.P.—S 946-8,000 (80 Bk s .)+loose 20 , 3003 - 9 - 41 —S 2 *—st. P^ftSC quote Bill No, Spl.—M. H. 17 e. Reg. No. 194 * To [Interest at 7 per cent per annum charged on accounts remaining unpaid one month after delivery. If the bill is not paid within a period of six months after its delivery interest at 8 per cent will be charged.] Name of patient Particulars of charges. No. of days. Amount. Remarks. Maintenance charges in advance from / to a,r/*./y 3 J T, 4/ per diem... Arrears as per bill No. dated ~Wages of a special attendant... '“'Vasking charges Miscellaneous private charges ... Total ... It'/-' U Z /d. Total Rupees (in words) T Notes.—1. 2 . •Accountant, ifendaiiity^Maat^l Hospital. All remittances should be made payaWe’to the Superintendent of the hospital^jtgj^irjjfl^idvance. 'While remitting the charges a reference should be made invariably to the bill No. in the coupon of the money order form. Changes of addresses should be communicated regularly.n ^ JTCVO '■ ‘ ’ ; Wtitle rerr.'.ttinc. amount ^ T - . . 5 f please quote Bill Not Y.P.P.—S 946-8,000 (80 Bkg.) +loose 20,30^:—9-41—S2*—at- Spl.—M. H. 17 e. Reg. No. Bill No. C.M. No. Notmb. 1. All remittances should be made payable to the Superintendent of the hospital’y^jotiy ^advance. 2. While remitting the charges a reference should be made invariably to the btirNo. in the coupon of the money order form. 8. Changes of addresses should be communicated regularly.%HMHHHHHi No.C.333 -8/50. POLITICAL AGENCY, MUSCAT, Dated S3^April, 1946. To The Superintendent, Central Mental Hospital, laravda. Mfemoianaum. A bank draft for Rs.120/- is enclosed herewith for the maintenance charges of Saiyid Ali bin Eaisal for the month of April, 1946. 2. Please acknowledge receipt. Political Agent, Muscat.■'N U6o No.C.3^^ -8/50. POLITI CAL AGENCY, MOSCAT, Dated l&amp;t\May, 1946. To The Superintendent, Central Mental Hospital, Yaravda. Memorandum. A bank draft for Re.124/* is enclosed herewith for the maintenance charges of Saiyid All bin Faisal for the month of lay, 1946. 2. Please acknowledge receipt. for Political Agent, Muscat. %wmwmmrm Ho.C. 397-8/50. HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY’S CONSULATE, MUSCAT, Dated /ffn May, 1946. The Treasury Officer, Muscat State, Muscat . Meiaoraaduai. The sum of Rs. 124/4 sent to this Consulate for remittance to the Central Mental Hospital, Tara via, has been received. for His Britannic Majesty’s Consul, Muscat.[Interest at 7 per cent per annum charged on accounts remaining unpaid one month after delivery. If the bill is not paid within a period of six months atte r its delivery interest at 8 per cent will be charged.} ame of patient T rPAK* —— —— Particulars of charges. No. of days, j Amount. Remarks. Maintenance charges in advance from to 3«&gt; at per diem... Arrears as per bill No. 4 dated Wages of a special attendant ... Waging charges Miscellaneous private charges ... Total / OmJ Total Rupees (m words) ( i^en^aftlospital. Notes:. —1. All remittances should bo made payable to the Superintendent of the hospital strictly in advance. 2. While remitting the charges a feference should be made invariably to the bill No. in the coupon of the money order form. 3. Changes of addresses should be communicated regularly.'y'u ^ i Reg. No. C&gt;, r-r XJ I Bill No. 1 , ,-&gt;r. «fi [Interest at 7 per cent per annum charged &lt;in accounts remaining unpaid one month after delivery. If the bill is not paid within a period of six months afte r its V Dated C.M. No. g/2. Spl.—M. H. 17 e. w alik. K fid. wira — -J 70' M h W D —tX. -f KK delivery interest at 8 per cent will be charged.] , \ * j. r : ■ a , ».,'/* \ ti / iv/yv iName of patient v v- _ Particulars of charges. No^of days. Amount. Remarks. Maintenance charges in advance from to ' t V . ~'l X &gt;!' P&gt;fl- lm 1 at per diem... • Arrears as per bill No. /'c/h dated 'Wages of a special attendant ... Waging charges Miscellaneous private charges .. « Total ... ^ M A } ff v . Total Rupees {in words) • * O ndentj^RmTldospital. Notes;.— 1. All remittances should be made payable to the Superintendent of the hospital strictly in advance i2. While remitting the charges a reference should be made invariably to the bill No. in the coupon of the money order form. 3. Changes of addresses should be communicated regularly.His Britannic Majesty's Consulate, I. us cat , Dated the 29 th June, 1946. r&gt; To The Treasury Of-’icer, J^uscat State, Sfuscat . Memorandum. The sum of Rs.l2C-4-0 sent tq this Consulate for remittance to the Central Mental Hospital, Yaravada, has beer received. n x or I!is Britannic Majesty’s Consul Muscat.Ro.C 5C7-8/50 Political Agency, Muscat &gt; Dated the 23 rd July, 1946 . The Superintendent, Central Mental Hospital, Yaravda« i : 3D t or induin* \ baitk. draft for Hs.124/- only is herewith enclosed for the maintenance charges of Saiyid All bin Faisal for the month of July, ly46. 2, Please acknowledge receipt.Ho.C 5&lt;X-8/50 His Britannic iisjesty's Consulate, Muscat. Dated the 23rd July, 194-6 Ihe Treasury Officer, Muscat St at huscat . M€&gt;-Ticrgr:jU(h . The sum of Hs. 124/- sent to .h:s Consulate for remittance :c the Cen-Lral Mental Hospital, Yeravda, has been received. I j o for His Britafnic iSajesty's Consul, Muscat .Chalan No # \\ Chalan of cash paid into the l^easnxy at Muscat. ^ ^ , Amount Head of By whom Name ( dr jb&amp;£ full Account, tendered. designation particulars of the person of the on whose hehalf remittance money is paid. &amp; of authority ( if any ) Sfc^^niry Oi^.cer, Fuse at State. S. All Faisel. Hospital expenses, for August, 1946. ia4/4/- y*^ Total. PS. U4/4/- ( In words) Rupees.One hundred twenty four^s* four A / (% —^ rour Mil Hecej^red payment ( In words) R^pe ^gj ^ ! Accountant. D/- n Treasury Officer, y Muscat.No.c 535 - 6/50 Political Agency, Muscat * Dated the 12th August, 194-6, To ihe Superintendent, Central Mental Hospital, Yaravda* yeaoranduir.. A bank draft for Rs.124/- is enclosed herewith for the maintenance charges of Saiyid Ali bin Faisal fcr the month of August, 1946. for Political Agent, MuscatNo.C 536-8/50 His Britannic majesty's Consulate, Muscat . Dated the 12ih August, 1946. ' o xhe Treasury Officer, Muscat State, Muscat. ^ ttemorandum . The sum of Rs.120/4/0 sent to this Consulate for remittance to the Central Mental Hospital, Yarvada, has been received. for His Britannic Majesty’s Consul, Muscat.—-w—- wm - 1 - 1 !H.i . WJiWBl r\ \ U \ 1 ?• S'/lr Reg. No. U 1 Bill No. 7 ? C.M. No. (oio ^ , V;. Spl.—M. H. 17 e. Dated 193 -•&gt; '’•&gt; •'Of i ■a'! bnC 0 ^ t p^ - $i R —« ) KZT —° J/ ^terest at 7 pep cent per annum ehararei on aeeounts pemainin^ unpaid one month after delivery. If the bill is not paid within a period of six months afte r its delivery interest at 8 per cent will be charged.] ? Name of patient C ^ ^ | ^ ^ i v Jl Particulars of charges. No. of days. | Amount. Remarks. Maintenance charges in advance from 1 at E*M to 3 o ~~ C~ k per diem.. Arrears as per bill No. /dated ••• Wages of a special attendant ... Washing charges Miscellaneous private .charges ... Total Total Rupees (in ivords) if^ncient, ital. NoriS'..—1. All remittances should be made payable to the Superintendent of the hospital strictly in advance. 2. While remitting the charges a reference should be made invariably to the bill No. in the coupon of the money order form. 3. Changes of addresses should be communicated regularly.Chalan No* *Chalan of cash paid into the treasury at Muscat. designation tendered* person on ^hose hehalf money is paid* Full particulars of the remittance and of authority ( if any ) Amount* Es* Head, of account. Treasury s. Ali “bin Officer, Faisel* Hospital expenses XiiO/V- Muscat State. for September, 1946* Total* Rs* 120/4/- ( In Tjror&amp;s) Rupees one hundred twenty and annas four only, Received paynent ( in T&lt;;ords ) Rupees, D/- Treasury Officer, Muscat ,(r No.C 583-S/50 To u Political Agency, Muscat. Dated the 17th September,1946 M\ \ W Memorandum A bank draft for Rs. 120/- is enclosed herewith for the maintenance charges of Saiyid All bin Faisal for the month of September, 1946 v: '■K Political Agent, Muscat .Ho.C 584*8/50 His Britannic Uajasty's Conciliate, Mtiacat* Dated tbe 17th September, 1946. The Treasury Officer, Muscat State, Muscat &gt; (jenorapdua, The sin of Rs. 120/4/0 sent to this Consulate for reaittance to the Central Mental Hospital, Yeravda, has been recelTed # His Britannic Majesty's Consul, Muscat .- I -!• Reg. No. To Bill No. Spl.—M. H. 17 e C.M. No. V Dated ^ 193 Kj ! I S' •XI [Interest at 7 pep cent pep annum charged on accounts remaining unpaid • one month after delivery. If the bill is not paid within a period of six months afte r its delivery interest at 8 per cent will be charged.] Oi Name of patient , Particulars of charges. No. of days. ! Amount. Remarks. Maintenance charoes in advance from to at \ • per diem Arrears as per bill No. dated Wages of a special attendant Wiling charges Miscellaneous private charges Total i o Total Rupees (in words) fin* ^ ^ J? tSrtl^Hos pital. jsf^xE?:. 1. All remittances should be made pay able t o the Superintendent of the hospital s trict ly in ad_vance. 2. While remitting the charges a reference should be made~Tnvariably to the bill No. in the coupon of the money order form. ' T- 3 . Changes of addresses should be communicated regularly.f While remitting nialntennnce chargCfc please quoie mil no and date. Reg. No. ' ' Bill No. A-q:ears as per bill No. Wages of a special attendant .. Washing charges liscellaueous private charges ... Total Rupees {in words) Notes.— 1. All remittances should be made payable to the Sup erintende nt of the hospital itmjTy in advance. 2. While remitting the charges a re ferenc e should be made i nvariab ly to the bin,No ; in the coupon of the money order form. , 3. Changes of addresses should be communicated regularly.CThalan ito into the at_Mijs cat. By vhom teudred. I^ame or Bull particulars person on whose 0 ; moae y 13 arl of ^ 1CL,&gt; authority ( if any) Amount. Ps. Head of account. Treasury Officer, S. Ali Hospital lii4/4/ Muscjat State. Bin Faisel expenses for oct: 1946. Total. Rs. ( In words) Bupees one hundred twenty ived payment ( in words ) Bupees. 1^4/4 A four and annas four only. Accountant. B/ Treasury Officer, Muscat. BMfl——MMMBMNo.c.&lt;o76 - 8 / 50 . POLITICAL AGENCY, MUSCAT, Dated October, 1946. To The Superintendent, Central Mental Hospital, Yaravda. ✓ Memorandum. A bank draft for Rs.124/“ is enclosed for the maintenance charges of Saiyid All bin Faisal for the month of October, 1946. 2. Please acknowledge receipt. Political Agent, Muscat.Pin^spniiMiR ohm No.C. til “8/50. HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY’S CONSULATE MUSCAT, Dated 5/6/^October, 1946. To The Treasury Officer Muscat State, Muscat. Memorandum. The sum of Rs.124/4 sent to this Consulate for remittance to the Central Mental Hospital, Yaravda, has been received. His Britannic Majesty's Consul, Muscat.’ rtf ' iV 8 ^- No - To 1C Bill ^o. WViUe remitting maintenance charges /i^l^ please quote mil no. and date. ^ s P fiS. {i° i 7 ^.\ C.M. No. i I; f # | Dated Sti1i4§ 193 4lt [L jrest at 7 per cent per annum charged on accounts remaining unpaid one month after delivery. If the bill is not paid within a period of six njonths afte r its delivery interest at 8 per cent will be charged.] ame of patient Particulars of charges. No. of days. ' Amount. Remarks. Maintenance charges in advance from : &gt;. . r&gt; [. to at Ar^ars as per bill No. dated per diem... Wages of a special attendant ... Washing charges M^cellaneous private charges ... Total Total Rupees (i?i words) /&amp;c/- ^en^ent; 3j^8Jfltf!lt^:Iospital. Notes. —^ 1 . All^remittances should be made payable to the Superintendent of the hospital strictly in advance. 2. 'While remitting the charges a reference should be made invariably to the bill No. in the coupon of the money order form. ’ - 3. Changes of addresses should be communicated regularly. yfp,,.Reg. No. To While remitting maintenance charges please quote mU no. and date. ^ _ m ^ ^ ^ Bill No. C.M. No. gXftnUb , Dated 0CUS46-193 A——: ^ f “ [lu.erest at 7 per cent per annum charged on accounts remaining unpaid one month after delivery. If the bill is not paid within a period of six months afte r its delivery interest at 8 per cent will be charged.] Name of patient Particulars of charges. No. of days. Amount. Remarks. Maintenance charges in advance from to at Ar^ars as per bill No. dated per diem... Wages of a special attendant ... Washing charges Miscellaneous private charges ... Total Total Rupees (in words) Manta' HosP ltal ’ Sjjll^ttenaent, M#fi$$%ospital. ' remittances should be made payable to the Superintendent of the hospital strictly in advance. bile remitting the charges a reference should be made invariably to the bill No. in the coupon of e money order form. es of addresses should be communicated regularly.No.C. 737-8/50. POLITICAL AGENCY, MUSCAT, Dated24tf ovember, 1946. To The Suport nt ?ndertt Contra! Mental Hospital, Yars.vda. Memorandum. A bank draft for Hs.120/- is enclosed for tne maintenance charges of Saiyid All bin Faisal for the month of November, 1946. 2. Please acknowledge receipt. 5T for Political Agent, Muscat.lio.C* 73 9 -8/50 His Britannic Majesty’s Consulate TJhiscat, Dated &lt;34/^Novenber, 1946. To The Treasury Officer, Muscat State, Muscat. ivleaoz'c nduni. Ti e smi of Rs .120/4 sent tc this Consulate for remittance to the Central Mental Hospital, Yaravda, has been received. for His Britannic i^njesty’s Consul, MuscatNo.C.^^7 - 8 / 50 . POLITICAL AGENCY, MUSCAT, Dated/£/ a, ■December, 1946. To The Superintendent, Central Mental Hospital, Yaravda. Memorandum. A bank draft for Rs.120/- and Postage Stamps for Rs4/“ are enclosed for the maintenance charges of Saiyid All bin Faisal for the month of December, 1946. 2. Please acknowledge receipt. Political Agent, ****** '• Muscat. W'' *A ANo.C. &lt;2 8 -8/50. POLITICAL AGENCY, MUSCAT, DatedJanuary, 1947. To The Superintendent, Central Mental Hospital, Yaravda. Memorandum. A bank draft for Rs. 124A is enclosed for the maintenance charges of Saiyid Ali bin ^aisal for the month of January, 1947. 2. Please acknowledge receipt. Political Agent, Muscat.No.C. &lt;5/9- -8/50 HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY'S CONSULATE, MUSCAT, Dated/A .January. 1947. To The Treasury Officer, Muscat State, Muscat. Memorandum. The sum of Rs.l2$/4 sent to this Consulate for remittance to the Central Mental Hospital, Yaravda, has been received.r^. Reg. No, To While feinlttijRg maintenance charge# / please quote Dili no. and date, iscu? [Spi,— m,h Bill No. C.M. No. J1B1— ZSU'Uj. )CT Jfiifi—m Dated NOV Interest at 1 per cent, per annum charged on accounts remaining unpaid one month after delivery. If the bill Is not paid within a period of six months after its delivery interest at 8 per cent, will be charged.]. Name of patien t Particulars of charges No, of days Maintenance charges in advance from to. ' , ' Al —^___per diem Arrears as per bill No.. dated Wages of a special attendant Washing charges Miscellaneous private charges Amount Remarks Total ... Total Rupees (in words) Awsounuuu. )ital. Not^s. 1 . All remittances should be k made payable to the Superintendent of the hc^ruSlstnctly i n advance. 2 ' Wh the money order^orm. “ referenCe sbould be made invariably to' the bill No.' in the coupon of 3. Changes of addresses should be communicated regularly.mmmm ‘Op Reg. No. To t' / While remitting maintenance charge* v_ please quote uili no and date. [Spl.-~M.H. 17 e Bill No. C.M. No. x Dated Dt C°Q^ 194 tlnterest at 7 per cent, per annum charged on accounts remaining unpaid month after delivery. If the bill is not paid within a period of six months after its delivery interest at 8 per cent, will be charged.] Name of patient one Particulars of charges Maintenance charges in advance from —-— 1 to_ No. of days at .per diem Amount Remarks Arrears as per bill No., dated Wages of a special attendant Washing charges Miscellaneous private charges Total Total Rupees (in words) AWUa u»pW*l. XT , ^J^r^i^ooent, ^hf&amp;tftHSospital. . otek. . All remittances should be_ made payable to the 'Superintendent of the hospital strictly in advance. Wh tht money o?der e form rge ' ' referenCe shoUld be made invariably to the bill No. in the coupon ol 3. Changes of addresses should be communicated regularly.(Signature) Cashier nr Accountant. (Desimagjjg)ORIGIN A (See PGi -1 HI No. 3 R8/4 0±, ■ on accc''ii mwpj. mm mm A ro Reg. No. To Bill No. maintenance cUcrg*» Wbi ,e ^ t ( please - 5^774?. [Spl.—M.H. 17 e C.M. No. w Dated_/: ^1 'Si' C - 94p 194 [Interest at 7 per cent, per annum charged on accounts remaining unpaid one month after delivery. If the bill is not |.ald within a period of six months after its delivery interest at 8 per cent, will be charged.] Name of patient 2 , Particulars of charges No. of days ; Amount Remarks Maintenance charges in advance from to at Arrears as per bill No. dated^ per diem Wages of a special attendant Washing charges Miscellaneous private charges Total ... Total Rupees (in words) i-fcflteSltllSclefflt, MefltXtolospital. Notes — 1 . All remittances should be made payable to the Superintendent of the hospital strictly in advance. 2 . While remitting the charges a reference should be made invariably to th&lt;? bill No. in the coupon of the monfey order form. 3. Changes of addresses should be communicated regularly.No.C./^O -8/50. POLITICAL AGENCY, MUSCAT, Dated ^'v r Februar 2 ^, 1947. To The Superintendent, Central Mental Hospital, Yaravda. Memoranduni. A bank draft for Rs.112/- is enclosed for the maintenance charges of Saiyid All bln Faisal for the month of February 1947. 2. Please acknowledge receipt. Politic*! Agent, Muscat.3. Changes of addresses should be communicated regularly. A, 4 ~neg, No, To n [Interest at 7 per cent, per annum charged on accounts remaining unpaid one month after delivery. If the bill is not paid within a period of six months after its delivery interest at 8 per cent, will be charged.] t * ''7 t • ' ... f ^ Name of patient .. 5 , Particulars of charges No. of days Amount Remarks Maintenance charges in advance from to at per diem Arrears as per bill No. dated Wages of a special attendant Washing charges Miscellaneous private charges Total Total Rupees (in words) tKl^l^kSS^n^^^^^irtuHospi tal. Notes 1. All remittances should be made payable to the Superintendent of the hospital strictly in advance. 2. While remitting the charges a reference should be made invariably to the bill No. in tbe coupon of the money order form.ini ■■■■■ ■■■■■■■■■ •m -m wm No.C. /9% -8/50. POLITICAL AGENCY, MUSCAT, Dated ///vMarch, 1947. To The Superintendent, Central Mental Hospital, Yaravda. Memorandum. A bank draft for Rs.124/* is enclosed for the maintenance charges of Saiyid Ali bin Faisal for the month of March, 1947. 2. Please acknowledge receipt. Political Agent, Muscat.No.C. 199- -8/50. HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY«S CONSULATE, MUSCAT, Dated ///L- March, 1947. To The Treasury Officer, Muscat State, Muscat. Memorandum. Mhe sum of Rs.124/4 sent to this Consulate for remittance to the Central Mental Hospital, Yaravda, has been received. His Britannic Majesty’s Consul, Muscat.lA\A) Reg, No, c*- ^rw mi ' ^ please Bill No. C.M. No. Dated — fWhite remitting maintenance chargd^j ^ 0 ^Bpl.-ivi.«.'rr 0 »u ^ quote Dili no. aad date, jBpl—M.H^T'o Tt [Interest at 7 per cent, per annum charged on accounts remaining unph ttL ^ one month after delivery. If the bill is not t aid within a period of six months after its delivery interest at 8 per cent, will be charged.] - • Name of patient ^\ 0 — jJ- Particulars of charges No. of days Amount Remarks Maintenance charges in advance from to ^ - - In' 1 \ • at 1 -- ' ' per diem ArrooTs n,s dpiT bill No. dated Wages of a special attendant .••• Washing charges EARLY _ Miscellaneous private charges • 1 DEQUES'. r£D Total ... Total Rupees {in words) AoeoOBtAnt, ent, Mental Hospital. Notes 1. All remittances should be made payable to the Superintendent of the hospital strictly in advance. 2. While remitting the charges a reference should he made invariably to the bill No. in the coupon of the money order form. 3. Changes of addresses should be communicated regularly.No.C. ^43 -8/50. POLITICAL AGENCY, MUSCAT, Dated ^9/^ April, 1947. To The Superintendent, Central Mental Hospital, Yaravda. Memorandum. A bank draft for Rs.120/- is enclosed for the maintenance charges of Saiyid Ali bin Faisal for the month of April, 1947. 2. Please acknowledge receipt. Political Agent, Muscatmrnmmmmrnmm »&lt; No.C. ^44 -8/50. HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY»S CONSULATE, MUSCAT, Dated 19 k April, 1947. To The Treasury Officer, Muscat State, Muscat, Memorandum. The sum of Rs.120/4 sent to this Consulate for remittance to the Central Mental Hospital, Yaravda, has been received. His Britannic Majesty*s Consul, Muscat. ■ ■While remitt V ii 0&gt; Reg, No, To please quote i. and L'S'tc ). B1U No. C.M. No. i Dated 17 e 194 Interest at 7 per cent, per annum charged on accounts remaining unpaid month after delivery. If the bill is not paid within a period of six months after its delivery interest at 8 per cent, will be charged ] Name of patient___ one Particulars of charges Maintenance charges in advance from ~_L to at No. of days per diem Amount Remarks Wages of a special attendant Washing charges Miscellaneous private charges Total Superintendent, M’.e.nt^l Hospital. Notes. —1. All remittances should be made payable to the Superintendent of the hospital strictly in advance. 2. While remitting the cha rges a reference should be made invariably to the bill No. in the coupon of the money order form.Ho.C. 3 )7 -S/50. POLITICAL AGENCY, MUSCAT, Dated 2 .i 4 rtMay, 1947. To The Superintendent, Central Mental Hospital, Yaravda. Memorandum. A bank draft for Rs.124/- is enclosed for the maintenance charges of Saiyid Ali bin Faisal for the month of May, 1947* 2. Please acknowledge receipt. Political Agent, Muscat.No.C. 318-8/50. BRITISH CONSULATE, MUSCAT, Dated 2 .^^May, 1947. To The Treasury Officer, Muscat State, Muscat. Memorandum. The sum of Rs.124/4 sent to this Consulate for remittance to the Central Mental Hospital, Yaravda, has been received. His Britannic Majesty’s Consul, Muscat.4K a ■ Reg. No. To 4'^ Whnp remitting mointr»nnce chargea £7^ r please quote 01U ao. aau date. 2_?^L C) ^ [Spl.—M,H. 17 e - Bill No. C.M. No. [Interest at 7 per cent, per annum charged on accounts remaining unpaid one month after delivery. If the bill is not paid within a period of six months after its delivery interest at 8 per cent, will be charged.] Name of patient- Particulars of charges No. of days Amount Remarks Maintenance charges in advance from &lt; •——to ! at i__ per d iem ... ! Arrears as per bill No dated • . Wages of a special attendant Washing charges KA&amp;LY ^ ... QUESTED- Miscellaneous private charges Total ...| m/- r „ - a A/ » Total Rupees (in words) k\ Mocph ah moent, IRentab Hospital. Notes — 1 . All remittances should be made payable to the Superintendent of the hospital strictly in advance. 2. While remitting the charges^ reference should be made invariably to the bill No. in the coupon of the money order form. 3. Changes of addresses should be communicated regularly.Ho.C.370-8/50 BRITISH CONSULATE. MUSCAT, Dated 25th June, 1947 To The Secretary to His Highness the Sultan of Muscat and Oman Muscat Memorandum. The Superintendent, Central Mental Hospital, Taravda, informs this Consulate in his letter of 10th May, 1947, that Saiyid Ali bin F&amp;isal is suffering from chronic bronchitis and that he has had fever since 9th May, 1947. Acting British Consul, Muscat \IRVRinHHHH ■—■'— To The Superintendent, Central Mental Hospital Taravda. Memorandum. A bank draft for Re.120/- is enclosed for the maintenance charges of Saiyid Ali bin Faisal for the month of June, 1947. 2. Please acknowledge receipt. Offg. Political Agent, Muscat.,— m No.C. 39/ -8/50. BRITISH CONSULATE, MUSCAT, Dated 3&lt;5^ June, 1947. To The Treasury Officer, Muscat State, Muscat. Memorandum. The sum of Rs .120/4 sent to this Consulate for remittance to the Central Mental Hospital, laravda has been recelyed. Acting British Consul, Muscat.i ~ih \ — ^ c k- No*.Q^ T 8 /?p. POLITICAL A®1NCT, WJSCAT, Dated 15th July, 1947. To The Superintendent, Central Mental Hospital, Yaravda. Memorandum. ▲ bank draft for Rs. 124/-* is enclosed for the naintenance charges of Sniyid Ali bin Faisal for the month of July, 1947. 2. Please acknowledge receipt. Offg. Political Agent, Muscat.Ho. C.£07-8/50. POLITICAL AGENCY, MUSCAT Dat«d 15th July, 1947. To The Treasury Officer, Muscat State, Muscat. Menoranduia. The sum of Rs. 124/' sent to this Consulate for remittance to the Central Mental Hospital, Yaravda, has been received. Acting British Consul, Muscat.Reg. No, To Interest at 7 per cent, per annum charged on accounts remaining unpaid 0 ne month after delivery. If the bill is not paid within a period of six months after its delivery interest at 8 per cent, will be charged.] Name of patient. Particulars of charges No. of days j Amount Maintenance charges in advance from . to at .per diem Arrears as per bill No., dated Wages of a special attendant Washing charges Miscellaneous private charges Total t Total Rupees (in words) S^psfiniendent, 'Menf^Hospital. Notes. 1 . All remittances should be&gt;ade payable to the Superintendent of the hospital strictly in advance. ' W ^the moneyorde^form. FgeS ' refcrence s ^ ou ^d be made invariably to the bill No. in the coupon of 3. Changes of addresses should be communicated regularly.fieceived a cheque for on account of *- - *1 in payment of bill No. Heg. No. Jy” Official receipt will be sent with the bill for the next month* Central Mental Hospital, TeraTia, 3/^ 1947 / Accountant, C*ll.Hospital, Yeravda*fieceived from/^ a cheque for on account of Sc in payment of bi: fieg. fto.SV Official receipt with the bill fojNo.C.Z.38-8/50 His Majesty'sConsulate, MUSCAT. 13th August, 1947. Memorandum The sum of Rs« 124/- sent to this Consulate for remittance to the Central Mental Hospital, Taravda, had been received. OFFICE COP YM* C *439-8/50 POLITICAL AGENCY, MUSCAT, the 13th August,1947. To The Superintendent, Central Mental Hospital, Yaravda. Memorandum &gt; A bank draft for Rs. 124/- is enclosed for the maintenance charges of Saiyid Ali bin Faisal for the month of August, 1947 . 2* Please acknowledge receipt* of .-ice cor 7Washin ( Miscellai SAMLf^ Total Eupees (in ivords) ’ ’ , ^xioA ViOSP^^' ^|^rtk#‘'tTOent, ^^a^'Hospital. Notes 1. All remittances should be made payable to the Superintendent of the hospital strictly in advance. 2. While remitting the charges a reference should be made invariably to the bill No. in the coupon of the money order form. 3. Changes of addresses should be communicated regularly.w Reg. N( \[Ir * ^ a ’ ” * X- ■ 13 one iths after its Partioulars of charges No. of days Amount Remarks Maintenance charges in advance from to per diem Arrears as per bill No. 1 Wages of a special attendant Washing charges ...| s Miscellaneous private charges gJUULf Total Rupees {in words) ^j§|BlkS^alnt, Hospital. Notes 1. All remittances should be made payable to the Superintendent of the hospital strictly in advance. 2. While remitting the charges a reference should be made invariably to the bill No. in the coupon of the money order form. 3. Changes of addresses should be communicated regularly.—- X Reg. No. a / ✓ / Bill No. Whne * 2 r ••, 0 please quote biUnO «»^ 0 ^ Dated C.M. No. / 17 194 -4.% [Interest at 7 per cent, per annum charged on accounts remaining unpaid one month after delivery. If the bill is not paid within a period of six months after its delivery interest at 8 per cent, will be charged.] Name of patients 1 ’ Particulars of charges No. of days j Amount Remarks Maintenance charges in advance from to at.. Arrears as per bill No. dated per diem J 2 Ji Wages of a special attendant Washing charges Miscellaneous private charges t f. w . i-r ■ *(** Total W- Total Rupees (in words) r v , /UWAltV Notes —1. All remittances should be made payable to the Superintendent of the Hospital. [Tsfrictly in advance. 2. While remitting the charges a reference should be made invariably to the bill No. in tbe coupon of the money order form. 3. Changes of addresses should be communicated regularly.British Consulate, Muscat. 7th September, 1947. Mo, C» 487-8/50 To:- The Treasury Officer, Muscat State, Muscat. Memorandum The sum of Rs. 120/- sent to this Consulate for remittance to the Central Mental Hospital, Taravda, has been received. IV- OFFICE COPYNo, C. 488-8/50 Political Agency, Muscat. 7th September,1947 Memorandum A bank draft for Rs. 120/- is enclosed for the maintenance charges of Saiyid All bin Faisal for the month of September, 1947. 2. Please acknowledge receipt. IK/- OFFICE COPY, • J&gt;k Reg. No. ' To BUI No. While remitting mmnUnence charge* v \^§ pl case quote oUi no. an, OaW. C.M. No. ^ ^ Dated [interest at 7 per cent, per annum charged on accounts remaining unpaid one month after delivery. If the bill is.not paid within a period of six months after its delivery interest at 8 per cent, will be charged.! Name of patient — V. \Ur qe ° H rBin ** 's-ttasO ^ tBbvBieY I f ^nBiavoooA .sbvaieY, 'aJlq E e H .M.3 Particulars of charges ^-^Vages of a special attendant Washing charges Miscellaneous private charges y&gt;4 •• .A #' 5 Total Rupees (in words) charges in advance from 1 ■ :i §£ ^ _ per diem rf^Jtw ^nea ed fr lw 1)111 Nq rldiiom ^csn V ^ floepltw* ^^Wixendent, ^featti^Hospital. Notes— 1. All remittances should be made pajable to the Superintendent of the hospital strictly in advance. 2. While remitting the charges a reference should be made invariably to the bill No. in the coupon of the money order form. S. Changes of addresses should be communicated regularly.Ko.C. 527-8/50 British Consulate 9 Muscat• 7th October 1947. Tot- The Treasury Officer, Muscat State, Muscat. I Memorandum The sum of Rs. 124/- sent to this Cohsulate for remittance to the Central Mental Hospital, Yaravda, has been received. (✓A v His Majesty^ Consul, Muscat^ IM/- Oprr*? — OP YNo. C. 528-8/50 Political Agency Muscat• 7th October 1947 Toi- The Superintendent, Central Mental Hospital, Taravda• Memorandum A bank draft for Rs, 124/- is enclosed for the maintenance charges of Saiyid Ali bin Faisal for the month of October, ? 1947• 1U/- Political Agent, Muscat. OFFICE COPYsri N2x £*m - 8/50 Toi- The Treasury Officer, Muscat State, Muscat* British Coasulfcte, Muscat* 13th November 1947* Memorandum The sum of Rs* 120/- sent to this Consulate for remittance to the Central Mental Hospital, Yaravda, has been received**No. C. 572 - 8/50 Political Agency, Muscat. 13th November 1947 To:- The Superintendent, Central Mental Hospital, Xaravda. Memorandum A bank dr&amp;rt for Rs. 120/- is enclosed for the maintenance charges of Saiyid Ali bin Faisal for the month of November 1947. IM/- Political Agent, Muscat. OF A w ^ 0OPYReg. No. To Bill No. While remitting maintenance chargt| xx SM^ please quote bill no and date. [gpl _ M C.M. No. fr\l) Dated- $z) * [Interest at 7 per cent, per annum charged on accounts remaining unpaid one month after delivery. If the bill is not t aid within a period of six months after its delivery interest at 8 per cent, will be charged.] Name of patient — 1 — -~~ Particulars of charges No. of days Amount Maintenance charges in advance from to at Arrears as per bill No. per diem dated. Wages of a special attendant Washing charges ^Miscellaneous private charges . Total Rupees (m words) Remarks Total Notes.— 1. All remittances should be made payable to the Superintendent of the hApu^ singly in advance. 2. While remitting the charges a reference should be made invariably to the bill No. in the coupon of the money order form. f 3 . Changes of addresses should be communicated regularly.■J*'. l-. 1 l{eg. No, To BiU No, While eemittirg maintenance charge* please quote 01 U ao. and date, CM, No. Pated (Spl,—M,H. J7 e ^ ■ 2A' Interest at 7 per cent, per annum charged on accounts remaining unpaid one month after delivery. If the bill is not paid within a period of six months after its delivery interest at 8 per cent, will be charged.] Name of patient Particulars of charges No. of days j Amount Maintenance charges in advance from ; to at ■ - -—— :: per diem Arrears as per biJl No., dated. Wages of a special attendant Washing charges Miscellaneous private charges Total Rupees (in words) Total ... Remarks Ifl^f^Hospital.. Notes. 1 , All remittances should be k made payable to the Superintendent of the hospital strictly in advance. 2 ' W1 the moneyorder^orm ^ 8 reference should be made invariably to the ‘bill No. in the coupon of 8 . Changes of addresses should be communicated regularly.Mo. C. 646 - 8/50 Political Agency, Muscat. 24th December 1947 T 01 - The Superintendent, Central Mental Hospital, Yaravda. Memorandum A bank draft for Rs. 124/- is enclosed forthe maintenance charges of Saiyid Ali bin Faisal for the month of December 1947. IM/- Political ’Muscat•Muscat* 24th December 1947. T 01 - The Treasury Officer, Muscat State, Muscat. Memorandum l The sum of Rs. 124/* sent to this Consulate for remittance to the Central Mental Hospital, Yaravda, has beenc \ _No&gt; C» jl-S/SO Brit 1 eh Consulate, Muscat. 12th January 1948* Toi- The Treasury Officer, Muscat State, Muscat• Memorandum The sum of Rs. 124/- sent to this Consulate for remittance to the Central Mental Hospital, Yaravda, has been —No* C. 83 - 8/50 British Consulate, Muscat* 5th February 1948* Tei- The Treasury Officer, Muscat State, Muscat* Memorandum The sum ef Rs* 116/- sent to this Consulate for remittance to the Central Mental Hospital, Taravda, has been received* w- fer His Majesty's Consul esty Muse cat*/j f » Reg. No, To BUI No. While reirittinp; maint^^ence charge*, please que,e 'nil no ami date [Spl.—M.H,4? e C,M. No, J -&gt;3) CInt ”''* at I, per °f, nt ' per annum charged on accounts remaining unpaid 0 ne month after delivery. If the bill is not paid within a period of six months after its delivery interest at 8 per cent, will be charged.] , Name of patient Particulars of charges Maintenance charges in advance from to per diem Arrears as per bill No.__ dated No. of days Amount Wages of a special attendant Washing charges Miscellaneous private charges Total ...! Total Rupees {in words) Remarks Votes —1 All remittan k mu - Hospital. o' “ . . ! Sh . 0U,d IW - B “ d * ^ to the Superintendent o, the hospit.t etr.etlv advance. 2 ' 'S miney ofdS'tem. 5b ° U ' d ^ “&gt; de 3. Chapges of addresses should be commuaicated regularly. to the bill No. in the coupon of1 , Reg. No. To Bill No. While remitting maintenance charge®* please quote mil no and dote. [gp| _ M H „ „ C.M. No. iicTx) Dated 194 Interest at 7 per cent, per annum charged on accounts remaining unpaid one month after delivery. If the bill is not paid within a period of six months after its \ delivery interest at 8 per cent, will be charged.] Name of patient_ Particulars cf charges Maintenance charges in advance from 1 to_ No. of days Amount Remarks ati ' per diem &lt;... Arrears as per bill No._ dated Wages of a special attendant W ashing'charges Miscellaneous private charges Total ...v | Total Rupees (in words) Notes 1. 2 . 3. l^ipfi^lfeh^eh^^Jen^lJBospital. All remittances should be made payable to the Superintendent of the hospital strictly in advance. W ^he moneyofdeMorm ^ 8 referenCe Sh ° Uld b6 made iDVari&amp;bly to the bil1 Na in the cou P on of Changes of addresses should be communicated regularly.v ORIGINAL COPY NOT TRANSFE RABLE (See Fin. R. No. 1 )' (F RECMPi FOR PAYMENT TO GOVE Original copy not transfer able (See Fin. R. No. X) Wi Gen. 113 e. (Fin. R, Form No. 1 ) RECEIPT FOR PAYMENT TO GOVERNMENT Nc&gt;‘- V 'n'i ' No. 98 Kec.lived from y - ■. • ^ i_j 1 Place Date 19 Received from _'(Rnpoes -T &gt; Rs. (Rupee?: 4 . on account of T S' on account of (Signature) { I (Signature) Cashier or Accountant. jDcsignjtjjgi, , C &lt;'h ; er rt A ■'’•■nntan*. (Designation) #+'■ Received from a cheque for on account of S^ /Cz in payment of bill no. 33 Re^. no. sy Official recei r t will be sent with the bill for the next month. Central Mental Hospital, Yeravda, 9y^y 1j48. Accountant, C .^.Hospital,Yeravda•Reg. No. To \\ 3 \ Bill No. Wbile remitting maintenance charge® quote oill no and date. S v ; i ^[Spl.—M.H- 17 r m [Interest at 7 per cent, per annum charged on accounts remaining unpaid one month after delivery. If the bil{ is not paid within a period of six months after its delivery interest at 8 per cent, will be charged.] Name of patient Maintenance charges in advance from to . * per diem Arrears as per bill No. dated &lt; , Wages of a special attendant Washing'charges Miscellaneous private charges Total ... Total Rupees (in words) Notes./$/ No. C. 8/50 British Consulate, Muscat* 14th March 1948* Tot- The Treasury Officer, Hub cat State, Muscat* Memorandum The sura of Rs. 124/- sent to this Consulate for remittance to the Central Mental Hospital, Yaravda, has been received. in/- Pis Male Muscat* OF^iCB COi ^ » — -Ho. C. 15t - ?/50. Political Agency, Muscat* 14th March 1948. Tot- The Superintendent, Central Mental Hospital, Yaravda. Meroorandua A bank draft for Rs. 124/- ia enclosed for the Maintenance charges of Saiyid Ali bin Paisal for the month of niarch 1948. Please acknowled^ receipt. IM/- OFFICE COPYReg. No. ' Bill No. C.M. i.w No, tSpl.—M,547 e To Dated 194 Interest at 7 per cent, per annum charged on accounts remaining unpaid one month after delivery. If the bill is not paid within a period of six months after its delivery interest at 8 per cent, will be charged.]. Name of patient _ Particulars of charges Maintenance charges in advance from — - i to ‘ at. .per diem Arrears as per bill No., dated Wages of a special attendant W ashing'charges Miscellaneous private charges Total Total Rupees (in words) Jp^6rmlendent,)Sftif(lR Hospital. Notes. 1. All remittances should be made payable to the Superintendent of the hospital strictly in advance. W *the mooey order^orm. r ^ eS 8 ,e ^ erence s ^ ou ^ be made invariably to the bill No. in the coupot, of 3. Changes of addresses should be communicated regularly./ ' '' ' ‘ ir ^ mcint^anct charges j.mae qucr? oil! no date. Reg. No. To Rill No. C.M. No. Datad. [Spl.—M.H. 17 e Ato)^ 194 P / . [Interest at 7 per cent, per annum charged on accounts remaining unpaid om month after delivery. If the bill is not paid within a period of six months after its delivery interest at 8 per cent, will be charged.] / Name of patient ' Particulars cf charges Maintenance charges in advance from to^ No. of days | Amount Remarks at_ _per diem Arrears as per bill No._. dated Wages of a special attendant Washing charges Miscellaneous private charges Total Total Rupees (in words) 7 Superintendp^fjVIeSlai Hospital. ' Notes. 1. All remittances should be made payable to the Superintend^$ the hospitaUtri&amp;Tv i n advance. 2 . While remitting the charges a reference should be madelnyariably to the the money order form. ^ ' 7 3. Changes of addresses should be commuaicated regularly. the coupon ofpw.-. Aim While r jnaiice chfif|^PC Reg. No, To tspl.^-M.H- 17 e Bill No. 47 / lsa3e ^ Dated /■^ Interest at 7 per cent, per annum charged on accounts remaining unpaid ^ one month after delivery. If the bill is not paid within a period of six months after its delivery interest at 8 per cent, will be charged ] Name of patient, v ; , ( - -V Particulars of charges Maintenance charges in advance from «-*/&lt;* to 3f- r - No. of days Remarks at. ——____per diem Arrears as per biJl No.. dated Wages of a special attendant Washing'charges Miscellaneous private charges Total Rupees (in words) Superintendent, Mental Hospital. Notes. 1. All remittances should be made payable to the Superintendent of the hospital strictly in advance. 2. While remitting the cha rges a reference should be made invariably to the biJflTN^ i * 1 the coupon of the njoney order form. S 3. Changes of addresses should be communicated regularly, • y 7C* 1 • * I ——_____ \ _ l t &lt;</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000881.0x000004_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/6/229</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000881.0x000004</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/6/229</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 8/50 MUSCAT STATE AFFAIRS: SAIYID ALI BIN FAISAL.'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1945/1948</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-04-19T22:03:46</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (219 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in chronological order from the front to the rear of the file. Circled serial numbers (red for received correspondence; blue for issued correspondence) refer to entries in the notes at the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 221; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Continuing on from the previous file in the sequence [IOR/R/15/6/228], this file concerns Saiyid Ali bin Faisal [Sayyid ‘Alī bin Fayṣal Āl Bū Sa‘īd], uncle of the Sultan of Muscat and Oman [Sa‘īd bin Taymūr Āl Bū Sa‘īd], who was admitted to a Government of India mental hospital at Yeravda (also spelled Yaravda) in Poona [Pune], India, in March 1942. Most of the correspondence relates to the payment of monthly maintenance charges for Ali bin Faisal's treatment, including the salary of his personal attendant. Also discussed is the replacement of Ali bin Faisal's personal attendant in 1945.Notable correspondents include the following: the Political Agent and Consul, Muscat; the Superintendent of the Central Mental Hospital, Yeravda; the Sultan of Muscat and Oman; the Minister for External Affairs, Muscat; the Treasury Officer, Muscat State.The Arabic language material consists of correspondence between the Political Agent and the Minister for External Affairs, Muscat (English translations are included).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><name type="personal"><namePart>‘Alī bin Fayṣal Āl Bū Sa‘īd</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Minister for Foreign Affairs</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of Muscat and Oman, Treasury Officer</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Sultan of Muscat and Oman, Āl Bū Sa'īd Dynasty</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Psychiatric hospitals</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000881.0x000004#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>