<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000157_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-18T03:50:36.186Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">No. t c : ^ Political Af-ency, Bahrain, Uated the November 1920. To The Branch Uanager, General Electric Conpany, Ltd., Hornb ,r Hoad, Bombay. Dear Lir, Please sunplv nn urgently with the 1'ollowin?' articlee and send ne your bill for parent. one endless canvas^ belt 24 feet long and 4 inches wide (connlete) one dozen spare bolts for reuniting the ends of sane. ®ours faithfully.T No. /d ^3- /storeSy//^\3 ^ ^ Political Agency, Bahrain, Dated the November 1926. To Messrs Grossley Brothers, Commerce House, Currimbhoy Road, BOM B A Y. Dear Birs, Please supply me urgently with the following spare parts for P.lll type Croesley oil engine No. 82081 and send me your bill for payment. borial No. Name Quantity. 107. 3 24 26 . Piston Top Governor Dye ancVexhaus t va Iv e collar. Governor bpring one. six. Governor lever soring two Yours faithfully,CONTINUATION SHEET NO. J DATE wear, we would then recommend a new piston with gudgeon pin complete but if the replacement is on account of wear then a new liner also should be supplied. Would you kindly let us have your instructiions when we shall be pleased to cable our works for the parts required. Aft n or X c4~ % -e^c^ocJ' v&gt;- ot^ «^CU-e^eT&gt;-ci&gt;vX^ ^ Jt-c_ ch^tcwc^x: {v^Sk^v^n ♦■£&lt;-*- ^C5&gt;r- J^tolo-^* t W C5^T&gt;V^., UJk tL^ t, Li L'1—zr ^Uv't^'W^ Leo t.l L-X^LA ^ i jiXAA^iJ.. kA^x 1a -zh,—— No, ^ /zt OVQ&amp; Political Agency, Bahrain Da to cl th ej 2 ^ Dec enb or 1926 To .3 TI 10 Branch liana go r&gt; bonoral Rloctric Coy, Ltd,, Nornhy ,oad, Bombay Dear Sir, PleaBe supply me with throe dozen 2^0 volte 60 watte Phillips AkGA Watt type electric frosted bulbs and send no your bill for payment. Yours faithfulIv, cl. Political Agent, jahrain.1924. JTE CARGO CLAUSES, (W.A.) .. &lt;*rranted free of cap^re, seizure, arrest, restraint, or detainment, and the conse quence thereof or of any attempt thereat (piracy excepted), and also from all consequences of hostilities or warlike operations, whether before or after declara tion of war. t -rranted free of loss or damage caused by strikers, locked-out workmen, or persons taking part in labour disturbances, or riots or civil commotions. 2 ' Should Clause !fo. X be deleted, Clause ICo, 3 is to operate as part of this Policy, granted free of any claim based upon loss of, or frustration of, the insured voyage, or adventure, caused by arrests, restraints or detainments of kings, princes or peoples. ° r General Average and salvage Charges payable according to Foreign Statement or pe York-Antwerp Rules if in accordance with the contract of affreightment. Held covered at a premium to be arranged in case of deviation or change of voyage, ( other variation of the risk by reason of the exercise of any liberty granted to th ship-owner or charterer under the contract of affreightment, or of any omission ' error in the description of the interest vessel or voyage. The risks covered by this policy attach from the time the goods leave the shipper’s &lt; manufacturer s warehouse at the port of shipment, unless otherwise stated, an continue during the ordinary course of transit, including customary traushipmei until the goods are safely deposited in the consignee’s or other warehous at the destination narned in the policy or until the expiry of fifteen days from mid night of the day on which the discharge of the goods hereby insured from the ovei seas vessel is completed whichever may first occur. When the destination t which the goods are insured is without the limits of the port of discharge of th overseas vessel the risk covered by this policy continue until the goods are safe! deposited in the consignee’s or other warehouse at the destination named in th ^a^° r Ti 1 , th0 ex P lr .V °f 30 days from midnight of the day on which the dis charge of the goods hereby insured from the overseas vessel is completed w uchever may first occur. Transhipment if any, otherwise than as above, nnd/o delay arising from circumstances beyond the control of the assured, held covers at a premium to be arranged. eluding transit by craft, raft and/or lighter to and from the vessel. Each craff raft, and/or lighter to be deemed a separate insurance. The assured are not to h prejudiced by any agreement exempting lightermen from liability. The Assured are not to be prejudiced by the presence of the negligence claus and/or latent defect clause in the Bills of Lading and/or Charter Party The sea worthiness of the vessel as between the Assured and the Assurers is hereb admitted and the wrongful act or misconduct of the shipowner or his servant^ causing a loss is not to defeat the recovery by an innocent Assured if the loss ir the absence of such wrongful act or misconduct would have been a loss recover able on the pohcy. With leave to sail with or without pilots, and to tow an assist vessels or craft in all situations, and to be towed. Warranted free from average under the percentage specified iu the Policy, unless general, or the vessel or craft, be stranded, sunk or burnt, but notwittatending this warranty the Assurers are to pay the insured value of any package whicl may be totally lost in loading, transhipment or discharge, also for any loss of oi damage to the ja^rest insured which may reasonably be attributed to fire, colli sion, or contact of the vessel and/or craft and/or conveyance with any externa' distress?® 106 inc U&lt; * 0I * ) 0l '^ 8r tl x aa water, or to discharge of cargo it port 0I F. C. &amp; 8. clause* Strikes, riot and civil commotions clause. G/A. clause. Deviation clause. Warehouse to warehouse clause. Craft, &amp;c. clause. Bill of Lading. &amp;c., clause. Average clause01^ LONDON OFFICE I 28, Budge Row, Cannon Street e.c. 4. Afriran duaranttr attb Jnimnttjj (Enmjiatm, ICtmitPii (INCORPORATED IN THE TRANSVAAL) HEAD OFFICE-J OHANNESBURG. NEW YORK office: 44, Beaver Street. 58338. No. Sr it known that as well in his or their own Name, alftOiOJi jP t n e s Qli» 4 nfi Pe r gjnii or Persons to . t ^- e ^ Same doth ' may ’ or sha11 appertain, in part or in all. do m^e ^ssurai^J^lPyME AFRICAN -.0ARANTEE ANI) INDEMNITY COMPANY, DTD., and hereby cause himself or themselves and them and every of them, to be insured, lost or not lost, at and from -Bombay to Bahrein. M &lt;~\YABLE IN j Bombay. ■ ) Customer's Quantity, j C ok £ ^5. louA nS 1 * ^ 16aa&gt; Ha. 1-0-0. .jL Policies issued sbrosd and ' } fl p£»ya4D^k3»iOThle-(X^iited # ired by Law to t stamp affixed ter receipt in the k upon Freight or any kind of Goods and Merchandises; or upon the Body, Tackle, Apparel. Ordnance. Munition. Artillery, Boat, and other Furniture, of and in the good Ship or Vessel called the MerchanHii !* 6 'P?» &gt;•)«or Goods and Merchandises from the loading of the Goods and nr ^ ? S ab ™f’ and sha11 continue until the same be discharged and safely landed, anrl mrtor,aH r he - 7 S | 1 L P ° r V essel at aad from * a s above, and shall continue until she hath arrived at, as above. tourh^and 6 ^!^ anchor 24 hours in good safety ; and it shall be lawful for the said Ship to proceed and sail to and purposes'withom pnsjtKlice 3 to'this^sm-ancfe! 6 ' 6 ' m ‘ he “““ 0 ' the VOylge inSUred 35 a, ° reSaid f ° r a “ n ' CeSSar &gt;' be vaS by an a d 8 1edJed a ‘^lTo b vis eCt „pon t,er ° f ‘ hiS P ° IiCy “ h 61 '' 66 ' 1 ‘ he ASSUred a ' d ,he Com P an &gt;' sha11 na.joo/. (Hupees. one nunared only J. - 1 ' 6 : Case Canvas Cotton H pr- -ss otherwftP'stated in writing th .natter of this insurance is warranted Particular Average unless the vessel or craft b« stranded, sunk or burnt, but notwithstanding this is agreed t excluded by * it ‘ : V- a:},- ■ ■■ ^i ibu b£ warranty the Assurers are to pay the insured value of any package or packages which may be totally r l?st in loading, transhipment or discharge, also any ^ loss of or damage to the interest insured which may -• mmm reasonably be attributed to collision or contact of the ' WK ves9€l and/or craft and/or conveyance with any external If * substance (ice included* other than water, or to -• 4 discharge of cargo at a port of distress, and also to pay- landing, warehousing and forwarding charges for which ■ . w Y t l ,ey W0l ^ &lt; * ot l |erw ' se I&gt; e liable. Grounding or stranding in Canals, Harbours or Tidal Rivers not to be deemed a strand, but the Company shall pay for any damage or loss to the interest insured which may reasonably be attributed thereto. ii.s Policy covers risks • ^.4. o. Claus® -&amp;o. 3. . - - • • . .. Warranted free of capture, siezure, arrest, restraint or detainment, and the consequences thereof or of any attempt thereat, piracy excepted, and also from all consequences of hostilities or warlike operations, whether before or after declaration of war. Warranted free of loss or damage caused by- strikers, locked out workmen or persons taking part in labour disturbances or riots or civil commotions. Warranted free of any claim based upon loss o4 or frustration of the insured voyage or adventure caused by arrests, restraints, or detainments of itflgs. Princes or Peoples. ^ General Average and Salvage Charges payaV “Oruing to Foreign Statement or per York-Antwer Rules if in accordance with the contract of affreEhL ment. Held covered, at a premiui^TK) be 3kr\nged. case of deviation or change of voyaHAor othldvariation of the risk by- reason of the exercWiVof 1/y liberty granted to the shipowner or charterer contract ot affreightment, or of any omission A/Crror in the description of the interest, vessel or voy-age. Including risk of craft, raft and/or lighter to and from tne vessel. Each craft, raft and/or lighter to be (teemed a separate insurance. The Assured are not to be prejudiced by any agreement exempting lightermen from liability, nor by- the presence of the negligence clause and/or latent defect clause in the Bills of Lading and/or Charter Party. The seaworthiness of the vessel as between the Assured and the Assurers is hereby admitted. No claim will be paid under this Policy unless notice in writing has been given to the Company or its Agents, if any, at the port of arrival previous to survey. The adjustment of all losses and other matters relating to this insurance shall be made agreeably to the tenor of this Policy and the established practice. No claim for loss or damage under this Policy will be recognised .unless provisional notification of Touching the Adventures and Penlswijjch the sautyCompany is contented to bear and does Ufekai upoa itseLL in this vnyage, they are, of the Seas, Menj^TWar, Fire, Enemies, Pirates, Rovers, AssatiKmj Th ie vesj Jet tisem ^ ^lart and Counter-Mart, Surpnsalin'aktngs at Sea, Arrests, Restraints, and *U Kings Princes and TwSi S A h %t- I ? at ‘ 0r1, Condlt J° n A«LQ^ty soever, Barratry of the Master and Mariners, and of fll’other Perth Losses, and Misfortunesihat haveVQjSftll come to the Hurt, Detriment or Damage of the said Goods and’ - erchandises and Ship, or any part thereof; and in case of any Loss or Misfortune, it shall be lawful for the Assured, them Factors sj%ts, and Assigns, to sue, labour, and travel for. in and about he Def^i Safeguard and recovery of the sa.d FreVk or Goods and Merchandises or Ship, &amp;c„ or anv part thereof, withoutnrciudSTo It Nl nb n ran ^ t 0 i the i Char | e ^^ ie i re °L f thG Said Com P any wil1 contribute in proportion to the Sum herein assured Prnn f PrebS 1f e tut and j hat no acts of the Insurer or Assured in recovering, saving or preserving the Property assu^A^halK^ie considered a waiver or acceptance of abandonment. ' P g Freig^ chartere^^artered. is warranted free from any claim consequent upon detention or loss of time whether arising from a r ®re warranted free from any claim for leakage or breakage unless caused by fire. ^ k .;toU| t los^r , the S less S el BOtt ° lnry 0r ^spondentia Bonds are warranted free from average except total loss occasioned by the This J^ ran f e docs not cover any loss or damage to property, which at the time of the happening of such lays PoOctes^ 6 tS inSUred by ' orwould &gt; but f or the existence of this Policy, be insured by any Fire Policy or ‘^’^gr? 0 , rn ’ Salt, Saltpetre, Fruit. Flour, Seeds, and all Liquids and Metals are warranted free fmm i Ship be stranded; Sugar, Tobacco, Rice. Hemp, Flax. Hides, and Skins are warranted free froin Average under^ivTpmfn^” 6 ™ ’ the . and all other Goods, also the Ship and Freight, are warranted free from Average under Three Pm,“ 5. hlve founds per centum. Ship or Craft be stranded, sunk or burnt, or the damage be caused by Fire or by- Collision with any- olher Ship or'vessel 6 ^ General - or the Now If?is llaltrg J 0 itiu- 0 HrtIr. that the said Company takes upon itself the burden of this Insurance to th„ amount ot nic and promises and binds itself to the Assured, their Executors, Administrators and Assigns fnr th~ * performance of the contract contained in this Policy in consideration of ^ f th trUe effecting this pSWjpfff&amp;t^ng t(HdAhi«Mlddft«4iyOjQ^yiiim at and after the rate of ‘ 1 rson or P ersons per cent. Jht HttltPHS whereof, the African Guarantee and Indemnity Company. Ltd., has cau*Uth«&gt;s ^-asonts be signed by its Managing Director and its Secretary, at Johannesburg this ^ f 26. Agents at Bonioay Countersigned at. KXXXjPjr*' has been given to the Office'of‘Vhe CoInpanv in joiiannesburg within Thirty davs of vessel’s arrival at destination. In the event of a Genera! Average Contribution arising under this Policy, the Assured is requested not to sign any General Average Bond without first consulting the Agents of this Company. JCoaiaa^.Lloyas Agents, at Bahrein. -or Survey &amp; Adjustment, Per Pro iiormusjVe Ardesni ifTtl ' * Co. /■ Managing Director. toeft d i‘ 1T ri ^ Pierage n„ d/or . th9ft aa ,Up attach'd. X ;jj WUllK»tJniMiMin TtBr CUUSE, Shippa lff0 • pep./'f auy Woods go lost nof L Under '' ri ‘-«‘i’s- “ Shi PPin^ Valn J 6 i ‘’ hicheTer the Z^ 0 *™** ^ cfTee te d^ p hi a 6 1 ^ *' 1 r p whom b oro n n whnse ,,ORt of the char We 8 of insuramjer 611868 ° f an,, i^Wental tS ih^ping'a^the Carriers 6 ^ 1 of) S to ^ 0n t*tlod to any amonnfflDemoranbum CROSSLEY BROS. LTD. ENGINEERS Commerce House, Currimbiioy Rd., Bauuard Estate. BOMBAY. ( grams:—GASENGINE. Tele ■ ' phone No. 22985. POST BOX No. 157. /? -i BocLa*' lith.*... .Deer; 192 6 Ta. v; ' r The Poljtical Agent, Bahrain, ^ (Persian Gulf.) ■A 5-7 . : Dear Sir, We have to thank you for your esteemed favour of the 29th ultimo ordering various spare parts for your P. HI type engine No. 82081. We regret that most of these parts are net ao present in stock hut they have all been ordered from our Works and will he despatched to you as quickly as possible. Yours faithfully, CRCSSLEY BROTHERS LTD. , iult- Datod th «/5 _ January 1027 To .'iosers Croccl^y Brothors Post Box Ho. 157, Bombay Boar Sirs, I have to acknowledge, with thanks, the receipt of your letter of the*29th ultimo and to state in reply that ny order for a cist on and for cylinder liner with packings nay for the present, be deferred. }iy present cylinder has a e^all crack but 1 an. advised that it will probably give another five years service in its present condition. Lhould necessity arise I will communicate with you again. Yours faithfully Political A ent, Bahrain(&amp;. .^-O ’'■* ■&lt;. A -t-T b6L» pa-Az enrckA^jutk 'l •, v ' • • -f* - * K r * bfeTY &gt;tje ^ 0 * J ' c ^ ut ££[■ ^ Vrt^UU ' '**&gt; L^» cJjtuto 1u ^ t 1 ^ bi U_&lt;s^Wt^ . W. ^ ^ &lt;^\' ' 1 . , ftz t^Ui. ^ t ^-~ A tr^ ^ ^ . M /r. (ft t^vi, «^h«V A-A ^ ^ v^l* Co^-dj^A- &lt;Y^ cSy^Uj' SUH^f- ■t+JUvS jtfV'Calcutta Office.- 3 A, Vans it tart R ow Madras OFFiCE;- f4-. Broadway LONDON Office-139 I4-I Queen Victoria St.e c Code used A B C 6 T .. M E — - ' ■ A:, /&lt;5 3 CROSSLEY BROTHERS MAJ&lt;EKS OK GAS &amp; OIL ENGINES, AND SUCTION GAS PI,ANTS. FOR ACL FUELS 8&gt; ALL PURPOSES. Opens haw Manchester. =r Teuephone N? 22985 Bombay Telegrams G asengi n e ’ Bomb av. in YO PLEASE =L Commirce House, i= ice B u i u p i h o c UR REPLY i refer to CURRIMBHOV Road, .^0 B allard Estate. post Box No. 157. BOMBAY: 19th. January 1927 The Political Agent, Bahrein, (Persian Gulf.) Pear Sir, Pe are in receipt of your telegram of the 18th. instant reading as follows:- M YOURS ELEVENTH DECE?£BER. ONE ' M BOTTOM GOVERNOR BYE URGENTLY H H REQUIRED DESPATCH IMMEDIATELY ' In order to meet your requirement we have taken the governor die from a P.lll type engine which we have in stock and we have today nested this to you per parcel post and trufct that it will arrive quickly. Ve enclose herewith our Bill No. 24M amounting to Rs.. 6 -4 -0 only which we trust you will find in order. r r &gt; Yours faithfully, d t*, . - A ■&gt; OC4»L 'mVr'y' - -Ji. 14, OLD COURT HOUSE STREET, CALCUTTA. The General Electric De France, Ltd. The General Electric Co. of China, Ltd. The British General Electric Co., Ltd., Australia The British General Electric Co., Ltd., S. Africa. The Anglo-Argentine General Electric Co., Ltd TRADE mark Our Re f- C . L« 35/D, lOO, ARMENIAN STREET, MADRAS. 86, THE MALL LAHORE. SOHRAB HOUSE” HORNBY ROAD, FORT, (Post Box No. 861.) BOMBAY. 31st January* 1927c WORKS &amp; ASSOCIATED MANUFACTURING COMPANIES: HEAV^ENGINEERING, GENERATORS, MOTORS. SWITCHGEAR, FANS, PRIMARY BATTERIES, CARBONS, MOULDED INSULATION, Witton, near Birminhg am. TURBINES, BLOWERS, COMPRESSORS, CONVEYING &amp; MINING PLANT, Fraser &amp; Chalmers Engineering Works, Erith, Kent. ' OSRAM ” LAMPS, OSRAM” WIRELESS VALVES, Hammersmith, London, ELECTRIC LIFTS, Express Lift Co., Ltd., London, WIRES St CABLES, Pirelli-General Cable Works, Ltd., Southampton. GLASS WORKS, Lemington-on-Tyne &amp; Wembley. HEATING &amp; COOKING. Birmingham. INSTRUMENTS &amp; METERS, Salforc electrical Instruments, Ltd., Manchester. Chamberlain St Hookham, Ltd., Birmingham. TELEPHONES, Peel-Conner Telephone Works, Coventry St Manchester. ART METAL FITTINGS. Edgbaston, Birmingham. SIEMENS St GENERAL ELECTRIC RAILWAY SIGNAL CO„ LTD. STEEL CONDUIT CO., LTD. RESEARCH LABORATORIES, Wembley, Middlesex. Dear Sirs* We have much pleasure in handing you herewith a copy of our new Indian Catalogue of Fixtures and Glassware, which we think you will find an interesting and useful publication, Y/e should like to draw special attention to the following features in this catalogue Pages 11-13 show a range of enclosed diffusing units, particularly suitable for use in India, as they prevent the entry of dust and insects c Pages 18-20 show a selection of adjustable dressing table pendantsc Pages 21-25 show a large and varied range of ornamental brackets t Pages 30-34 contain a wide range of table and floor standards„ Pages 40-41 deal with ^, GI!Co?JlY ^, Deflectors, which are the most efficient equipment for Show window lightingo Page 43 shows a range of fittings for Ship Lightingc Page 46 deals with the .C * “Wembley ,f Lantern, which embodies the latest and most efficient practice for Street and Yard Lighting, Pages 48-52 show a large and varied selection of glassware for electric lighting. Inside the front cover of the catalogue will be found a complete list of prices in Indian currency. Should you desire to have a supply of these catalogues fox distribution to your own customers, we shall be pleased to supply same at gw0/l^/0 per copy, which represents the bare cost of publication.: Yours faithfully ; TKD GYIYIP-X 2L2CTRIG CO. (India) LTD. Sncl.i. 'KH* TheS.G.Q -your guarantee. VLONDON OFFICE : / 28, Budge Row, Cannon Street E.C. 4. NEW YORK OFFICE: 44, Beaver Street. 58367. No. Afrirai ( I it fctumm t as v^ell in his or their r whom the same dott GUARANTEE ANE and every of them, PAYABLE IN Bombay. upon Freight or any Artillery, Boat, and o £ Rs. 100 /- beginning the adven Merchandises aboard as above ; or upon tfc and moored at ancho touch and stay at an\ purposes without pre made payable in the United It is hereby agreed be valued and dec Rs. 100 /- (] within ten days after receipt in the United Kingdom. 1 (One) Ci 1 Unless otherwise stated in writing the subject matter of this insurance is warranted free from Particular Average unless the vessel or craft be stranded, sunk or burnt, but notwithstanding this warranty the Assurers are to pay the insured value of any package or packages which may be totally lost in loading, transhipment or discharge, also any loss of or damage to the interest insured which may reasonably be attributed to collision or contact of the vessel and/or craft and/or conveyance with any external substance (ice included) other than water, or to discharge of cargo at a port of distress, and also to pay landing, warehousing and for warding charges fur whiolt- they would otherwise be liable. Grounding or stranding in Canals, Harbours or Tidal Rivers not to be deemed a strand, but the Company shall pay for any damage or loss to the interest insured which may reasonably be attributed thereto. Warranted free of capture, siezure, arrest, restraint or detainment, and the consequences thereof or of any attempt thereat, piracy excepted, and also from all consequences of hostilities or warlike operations, whether before or after declaration of war. Warranted free of loss or damage caused by strikers, locked out workmen or persons taking part in labour disturbances or riots or civil commotions. ^A/arranted free of any claim based upon loss o, or stration of the insured voyage or adventure ca d by arrests, restraints, or detainments of £&lt;f^gs Princes or Peoples. General Average and Salvage Charges payJ, according to Foreign Statement or per York-Antwe:„ Rules if in accordance with the contract of affreight ment. Held covered, at a premiunt'fc be lhti\nged. in case of deviation or change of voya^Acr othidvariation of the risk by reason of the exercWiXof Hy liberty granted to the shipowner or charterer utac^jj^ne contract of affreightment, or of any omission ar^rror in the description of the interest, vessel or voyage. Including risk of craft, raft and/or lighter to and from the vessel. Each craft, raft and/or lighter to be deemed a separate insurance. The Assured are not to be prejudiced by any agreement exempting lightermen from liability, nor by the presence of the negligence clause and/or latent defect clause in the Bills of Lading and/or Charter Party. The seaworthiness of the vessel as between the Assured and the Assurers is hereby admitted. No claim will be paid under this Policy unless notice in writing has been given to the Company or its Agents, if any, at the port of arrival previous to survey. The adjustment of all losses and other matters relating to this insurance shall be made agreeably to the tenor of this Policy and the established practice. No claim for loss or damage under this Policy will be recognised .unless provisional notification of same has been given to the Office of the Company in Johannesburg within Thirty days of vessel’s arrival XtKJ&amp;SuXtion. In the event of a General Average Contribution arising under this Policy, the Assured is requested not to sign any General Average Bond without first consulting the Agents of this Company. Marked Touching the Advet voyage, they are, oi Mart and Counter-! Peoples of what Na Merchandises and S Assured, their Factt and recovery of the this Insurance ; to t It is expressljg^ecla Property assu^pys' olute total loss This Ilyntrance do or damage is t Policies. IN.B.—Com, Fish, Salt Ship be stranded : and all other Goodi Ship or Craft be sti Nmu thin $IoItrtf • amount of and promises and performance and effecting this Po&amp; 3n 3®ttne0s t be signed by its Countersigned at. T&gt;LONDON OFFICE : 28, Budge Row, Cannon Street e.c. 4. African (fiuarantrr ani Snbrmntig ©nntpang, ffimitri (INCORPORATED IN THE TRANSVAAL) HEAD OFFICE-J OHANNESBURG NEW YORK OFFICE! 44, Beaver Street. 58367. No. it kwmm that &gt;wn m N^mes and every ojher Person or Persons to &gt;. may, or shalf appertain; m paiT^&amp;r^nPaTl. I^iftrakcOiap enyEl^iiict^n. as w'dl in his or their own whom the same doth, GUARANTEE AND INDEMNITY COMPANY, LTD., and hereby cause himseif 'orThemfelves^TtheV and every of them, to be insured, lost or not lost, at and from Payable in -Bombay. ., Bombay to Bahrein. upon b reight or any kind of Goods and Merchandises; or upon the Body, Tackle, Apparel, Ordnance, Munition, Artillery, Boat, and other Furniture, of and in the good Ship or Vessel called the £ Rs. l00/~ rema&lt;uiKH-@ &gt; SB&amp;S'b % ^peg d o, made payable in the United have a ^Governtn*efif ^falrfp^fiffiUetF • within ten days after receipt in the United Kingdom. Unless otherwise stated in writing the subject matter of this insurance is warranted free from Particular Average unless the vessel or craft be stranded, sunk or burnt, but notwithstanding this warranty the Assurers are to pay the insured value of any package or packages which may be totally lost in loading, transhipment or discharge, also any loss of or damage to the interest insured which may reasonably be attributed to collision or contact of the vessel and/or craft and/or conveyance with any external substance (ice included) other than water, or to discharge of cargo at a port of distress, and also to pay landing, warehousing and forwarding charges for which they would otherwise be liable. Grounding or stranding in Canals, Harbours or Tidal Rivers not to be deemed a strand, but the Company shall pay for any damage or loss to the interest insured which may reasonably be attributed thereto. Warranted free of capture, siezure, arrest, restraint or detainment, and the consequences thereof or of any attempt thereat, piracy excepted, and also from all consequences of hostilities or warlike operations, whether before or after declaration of war. Warranted free of loss or damage caused by strikers, locked out workmen or persons taking part in labour disturbances or riots or civil commotions. ’Warranted free of any claim based upon loss o, or Jstration of the insured voyage or adventure ca A by arrests, restraints, or detainments of £&lt;f^gs. Princes or Peoples. General Average and Salvage Charges pay^ according to Foreign Statement or per York Antwe . Rules if in accordance with the con tract of affreight ment. Held covered, at a premiun^fc be Iknbiged, in case of deviation or change of voyaWNor othlnvariation of the risk by reason of the exermisXof jWy liberty granted to the shipowner or charterer ImcSyipne contract of affreightment, or of any omission c*/§rror in the description of the interest, vessel or voyage. Including risk of craft, raft and/or lighter to and from the vessel. Each craft, raft and/or lighter to be deemed a separate insurance. The Assured are not to be prejudiced by any agreement exempting lightermen from liability, nor by the presence of the negligence clause and/or latent defect clause in the Bills of Lading and/or Charter Party, The seaworthiness of the vessel as between the Assured and the Assurers is hereby admitted. No claim will he paid under this Policy unless notice in writing has been given to the Company or its Agents, if any, at the port of arrival previous to survey. The adjustment of all losses and other matters relating to this insurance shall he made agreeably to the tenor of this Policy and the established practice. No claim for loss or damage under this Policy will he recognised .unless provisional notification of same has been given to the Ofifice of the Company in ^^ haimes burg within Thirty days of vessel’s arrival In the event of a General Average Contribution arising under this Policy, the Assured is requested not to sign any General Average Bond without first consulting the Agents of this Company. beginning the adventure upon the said Freight or Goods and Merchandises from the loading of the Goods and Merchandises aboard the said Shig ^(tifapil continue until the same be discharged and safely landed, as above ; or upon the Ship or Vessel at and from, as above, and shalUcontinue until she hath arrived at, as above, and moored at anchor 24 hours in good safety ; and it shall be lawful for the said Ship to proceed and sail to and touch and stay at any Ports or Places whatsoever in the course of the voyage insured as aforesaid for all necessary purposes without prejudice to this Insurance. It is hereby agreed that the subject matter of this Policy as between the Assured and the Company shall be valued and declared as follows upon BjeaBsajL* Lloyds A^f \ts at Rs. Ino/- (Rupees. One hundred only.) 1 (One) Case Electric Lamps. Marked as per Bln of Ladin is contentecf^to biaPihd ^7^ Touching the Adventures and Perils wjrich the said\Company is contentecfTo b^ar^nd ’ry?tF l jp 0n itse i f in thjs voyage, they are, of the Seas, MenjOFWar, Fire, Knemies, Pirates, Rovers, Assailing Thieves, Jettisons, Letters of Mart and Counter-Mart, Surprisali\Takings at Sea, Arrests, Restraints, and Detainments of all Kings, Princes, and Peoples of what Nation, Condition,\dcQuaBty soever, Barratry of the Master and Mariners, and of all other Perils Losses, and Misfortunesthat haveN^^SHl come to the Hurt. Detriment or Damage of the said Goods and Merchandises and Ship, or any part thereof ; and in case of any Loss or Misfortune, it shall be IcAvful for the Assured, their Factors, Sef^nts, and Assigns, to sue, labour, and travel for, in and about the Defence, Safeguard and recovery of the said Freftfu or Goods and Merchandises or Ship, &amp;c„ or any part thereof, without prejudice to this Insurance , to the chargesjy^nereof the said Company will contribute in proportion to the Sum herein assured. It is expresslj^eclared and agreed that no acts of the Insurer or Assured in recovering, saving or preserving the Property assur^vshallrBe considered a waiver or acceptance of abandonment. Frciglu, ehartered (Sn^rchRi-tered. is warranted free from any claim consequent upon detention or loss of time whether arisim 1 from a the Sea ftrotherwise. ** ^uSmdWre warranted free from any claim for leakage or breakage unless caused by fire JE L S^lme'tmaUos^Lf The S lessel BOtl ° mry or Respondentia Bonds ar e warranted free from average except total loss occasioned by the This Iterance does not cover any loss or damage to property, which at the time of the happening of such loss or damage is insured by, or would, but for the existence of this Policy, be insured by any Fire Policv or Policies. xx y N-B^Corn. Fish, Salt, Saltpetre, Fruit Flour Seeds, and all Liquids and Metals are arranted free from Average unless General or the Ship be stranded; Sugar, Tobacco, Rice. Hemp, Flax, Hides, and Skins are warranted free from Average under Five Pounds per centum and all other Goods, also the Ship and Freight, are warranted free from Average undid: Three Pounds per centum, unless General or the' Ship or Craft he stranded, sunk or burnt, or the damage be caused by Fire or by Collision with any other Ship or Vessel Nmu tltta llaltra SJUnpaaetlj,, that the said Company takes upon itself the burden of this Insurance to the amount of and promises and binds itself to the Assured, their Executors, Administrators, and Assigns, for the true performance and fulfilment of the contract contained in this Policy, ii consideration of the person or persons efleeting this I 'o.ra 3 jip*$ 0 igi{)g at and after the rate of , per cent. Jtt UlttttMH whereof, the African Guarantee and Indemnity Company, Ltd., has caused these presents to be signed by its Managing Director and its Secretary, at Johannesburg this ^3 f*, .19.. February 27. Agents at Bombay Countersigned at Bombay. Per Pro Hormusjee Ardeshir &amp; Co. ' * *** Managing Director. 1 Agents, Including risk of pilferage ‘irf^eft aa \ ip ?■ an^/(5i .’ON-DEtlYERY 'UUSE. ,&lt;... u.jtis policy,covers dfie risk of Theft (8pecti'.t‘' ; of percentage bjft Underwriters' u m respect tf any froiU 8 so lost not to exceed their ship- ...f, or insured vahNs whichever is the smaller No liability for loss to attach hereM unless notice of surrey h is been given to Underwriters’ Agents withir 1 ' 10 days of tho expiry of risk under the Policy. (B) It is hereby agreed that this Policv covers v v, e risk of Non- Delivery for which thr liability of the Shipowner or other Carrier is limited, redr,fed or negatived by the Contract of Carriage by reason of the value of the goods but Underwriters liability in respect of any goods so lost not to exceed their shipping or insured value whichever is the smaller. “ Shipping Yalne ’’ as used above moans the prime cost of the goods to the Assured hy whom or on whose behalf the insurance is effected plus tho expenses of and incidental to shipping and tho Charges of insurance. Underwriters to ho entitled to any amount recovered from tho Carriers or others in respect of such losses (less cost of recovery if any) up to the amount paid by them in respect of the loss . B. U. A. 192). Secretary.flDemoranbum. Dear Sir, w e have to thank you for your favcir of the 15th- ultimo No. 42/l7 / / 7 and note that you do not now wish us to supply a piston and liner at present ^cr your type engine./?/? /\&amp;f Qy^/U /tAre*^ ^ /y_ A AZ(. ^Jf .-'S/^g/SU. \ ^ -LW^ /\//// I'/' fx Sid ty /V \l~ £/V ^ A^yS^ ^ $AvV^ j/CkyxC^ dxAA^C /v\&amp; / A£^Z vi/\ / ^ u ^ ( / V?vr A '77 ^ /f^^ A^*&lt;AyjO /l/jz /q if /^/ /u * /x^Ay^dt^flDemovanimm. ^ 3 BQmlE)ay....l7tJbi.,.Pehiy .; 1 92 7 ENGINEERS * - t*' f * ( COMMSRCT? House, CURRIMBHOY yc r»'» Bauuard Hstate. BOMBAY. 1 grams:—GASENGINE. Vele , ' phone No. 22985. POST BOX No. 157. -* r - ■- r The Poll tj.cal Agent, ^3 Bahrein (Persian Giilf.) ^ / oc Dear Sir, With further reference to our letter of the 11th. December last, we now have pleasure in advising despatch of all the spare parts ordered 'by you, per uarcel post. We have sent only two 'bottom governor dies instead of three, one being supplied to you as per our letter of the 19th. of January. Enclosed herewith ulease find our Bill No. 2476 amounting to Rs,. 86 -0 -0 only. fe. °k Yotirs faithfvaiy, CRCSSLEY ] (OIHERS LTD. r for India. N.TELEPHONE No. 24225 TELEGRAMS: 'KILOWATT' Codes Used : COLE &amp; PRIVATE AFFILIATED WITH THE GENERAL ELECTRIC Co., LTD. “MAGNET HOUSE/’ KINGSWAY, LONDON, W.C. 2. AND The General Electric De France, Ltd. The General Electric Co. of China, Ltd. The British General Electric Co., Ltd., Australia. The British General Electric Co.. Ltd., S. Africa. The Anglo-Argentine General Electric Co., Ltd. WORKS &amp; ASSOCIATED MANUFACTURING COMPANIES HEAVV-SNGINEERING, GENERATORS, MOTORS, SWITCHGEAR, FANS, PRIMARY BATTERIES, CARBONS, MOULDED INSULATION, Witton, near Birminhgam. TURBINES, BLOWERS, COMPRESSORS, CONVEYING &amp; MINING PLANT, Fraser &amp; Chalmers Engineering Works, Erith, Kent. “ OSRAM ” LAMPS, “ OSRAM ” WIRELESS VALVES, Hammersmith, London, ELECTRIC LIFTS, Express Lift Co., Ltd., London, WIRES &amp; CABLES, Pirelli-General Cable Works, Ltd., Southampton. GLASS WORKS, Lemington-on-Tyne &amp; Wembley. HEATING &amp; COOKING. Birmingham. INSTR” iNTS &amp; METERS, Salford Electrical Instruments, Ltd., Manchester. Chamberlain &amp; Hookham, Ltd., Birmingham. TELEPHONES, Peel-Conner Telephone Works, Coventry &amp; Manchester. ART METAL FITTINGS, Edgbaston, Birmingham. SIEMENS &amp; GENERAL ELECTRIC RAILWAY SIGNAL CO., LTD. STEEL CONDUIT CO., LTD. RESEARCH LABORATORIES, Wembley, Middlesex. Dear Sirs, Breakers Te nave pleacu-e in brin^in* to your notice tnis new lignt pattern of Circuit Breaker, wuica aas been designed by our Switcdgear 'Yorks for various capacities up to 100 uteres, and for circuits waere tae pressure doefc not exceed 350 volts. We enclose a copy of Leaflet X.3942 illustrating and fully describing tnese Breakers, vmicn can be supplied witn all tae usual combinations of overload and no-volt releases, and in beta open and ironclad patterns, tae latter being particularly suitable for use in Mils, Factories or Workshops. Tae G.F.c. reputation for reliability and nigh quality is tally upaeld by tnese circuit breakers, waich also comply witn tae requirements of tne B.E.S.A. Specification Bo.110 of 1920 . We trust tnat tne enclosed leaflet, with it’s accompanying price list in Indian Currency, will be of interest to you. Yours faitnfully, THK GEITEYAL TLKCTRIC CO. (India) LTD- Snclos.1. cyA v » ThcS.G.Q -your guaranteeLeaflet X .V.)f¥7l (February, 1926) A CIRCUIT BREAKERS. Patent No. 184,935 1 FOR ORDINARY DUTY UP TO 100 AMPS &amp; 660 VOLTS. OPEN TYPE. (With Back Connections) Single, Double &amp; Triple Pole. Single, Double &amp; Triple Pole. X 9505. SINGLE POLE. X 9511. DOUBLE POLE. FACTORY TYPE. (With Front Connections) X 9603. Cover on. X 9603. Cover Removed. Mounted on Enamelled Slate Base. Mounted on Enamelled Slate Base in Cast Iron Case. K£? T RAX t RfcA*. THE GENERAL ELECTRIC COMPANY, LIMITED Telephone : Regent 7050 (50 lines). Telegrams : “ Electricity, Westcent, London.” Head Office-. Magnet House, Kingsway, London, W.C.2. Branches throughout the United Kingdom and in all the principal markets of the World. sec; rairt haba D/11867.43 TELEPHONE No. 24225 TELEGRAMS: 'KILOWATT' Codes Used ; COLE 8t PRIVATE AFFILIATED WITH THE GENERAL ELECTRIC Co., LTD. “MAGNET HOUSE.' KINGSWAY, LONDON, W.C. 2. The General Electric De France, Ltd. The General Electric Co. of China, Ltd. The British General Electric Co., Ltd., Australia. The British General Electric Co., Ltd., S. Africa. The Anglo-Argentine General Electric Co., Ltd. HEAD OFFICE 14, OLD COURT HOUSE STREET, CALCUTTA. Rel*. CoL&lt; 3 Q/R. MALL V f ^ . • • S. i ORE. ‘SOHRAB HOUSE” HORNBY ROAD, FORT, (Post Box No. 861.) BOMBAY. 25th torch, 1927c WORKS &amp; ASSOCIATED MANUFACTURING COMPANIES : heaV^^ngineering, GEN ERRORS, MOTORS. SWITCHGEAR, FANS, PRIMARY BATTERIES, CARBONS, MOULDED INSULATION, Witton, near Birminhgam. TURBINES, BLOWERS, COMPRESSORS, CONVEYING &amp; MINING PLANT, Fraser &amp; Chalmers Engineering Works, Erith, Kent. “ OSRAM ” LAMPS. •• OSRAM” WIRELESS VALVES, Hammersmith, London, ELECTRIC LIFTS, Express Lift Co., Ltd., London, WIRES &amp; CABLES, Pirelli-General Cable Works, Ltd., Southampton. GLASS WORKS, Lemington-on-Tyne &amp; Wembley. HEATING &amp; COOKING. Birmingham. INSTR^^TS &amp; METERS, Salford Electrical Instruments, Ltd., Manchester. Chamberlain &amp; Hookham, Ltd., Birmingham. TELEPHONES, Peel-Conner Telephone Works, Coventry &amp; Manchester. ART METAL FITTINGS, Edgbaston, Birmingham. SIEMENS &amp; GENERAL ELECTRIC RAILWAY SIGNAL CO., LTD. STEEL CONDUIT CO., LTD. RESEARCH LABORATORIES, Wembley, Middlesex. RF.Tfl. JC TI QU Iff PRICE OF G«E«C c LIGHTING ACCESrOHISS &lt; Bear Sirfc, i \ 7 e have pleksure in announcing the following reductione in the prices of our Electric Lighting Accessories s- S.226 10 amp. Channel type Fuses and Basesc S t 385 5. amp. PeBeSlicK Cwitche*. 'S* 388 IQ amp. u : “ ' S.391 * 5 amp. Combined' SV/itehee . and pluge. So412 5 amp.Double Pole Sv/itehee S.416 10 amp. :i S.432 20 amp. ' ” Sc 650 Bakelite 2-pin Plugs and Sockets. Sc 7406 Ceiling Roses. : ’S.SOSS 5 amp. Round Cutouts. S.846 10 amp. .Oblong Cutoute. Sc 1028 Cordgrip Switch Holders. ’Sc 1037 1/2” Switch Holders. ’S. 1068 PoB.fatten Holders S.ii03 ” Co'rdgrip Holders S•1105 ' 1/2” Holders 6.1107 ' 5/8 u •. n Old price 13/8 10/14 24/- 39/- 27/12 52/8 135/- 20/4 6/6 6 /- 12/12 30/- 27/- 8/1 7/2 6/12 6/12 Hew price . ll/4 per doz. 10/2 “ “ 21 /- 36/- '27/- 48/- 126/- 19/8 6/3 5/10 9/12 24/- 23/4 7/2 6/12 6/9 6/9 ... These are subjec-t to 33 1/3SJ trade discount, packing and delivery on rail extra at cost; except on orders to a nett value of ^ 3 . 200 /- or over, which will he delivered P.0,2.Bombay. - Special.rates for large quantities will be t quoted on applicationc Yours faithfully? THE GENERAL ELECTRIC CO.(India) LTD, it ti ii u it it u it u ii n u it n TheS.G.e -your guarantee.No • ^ D Of 1927. Political Agency, Balirain, Datod theJuly, 1927. Mossrc Urossley Brothers, Exchange Buildings, Bonbay. Dear birs. Please supply rae urgently with the following snare parts for P. Ill type Crossley oil Engine No. 82081 and send me your bill for payment. Yours faithfully, Captain, Bahrain. Serial No. 76 77 88 96. Name Quantity. Admission valve spring g for sleeve Admission valve srring 5. Lamp for starting. 1. Exhaust valve xxrtx?: plug. 1. /Calcutta Off-ice - 3 A. Vansittart R ow. Madras Office:- 14. Broadway LON.OON Office 139 1-41 Queen Vi ctoria St.e c Code A B C eT.' CROSSLEY BROTHERS MAKERS OF GAS 8c OIL ENGINES, A N O SUCTION GAS PLANTS. FOR ACL FUELS Sc ALL PURPOSES. Opens haw, Manchester. Tclephonc 22985 Bombay Telegrams Gasengine” Bombay. ct 4 La 1 M YOUR REPLY PLEASE REFE R TO * l, rl Post Box No.157. Commerce House, CuRRIMBHOY ROAD, Ballard Estate Bombay, ioth. August 1927 . The Political Agent, BAHREIN. TPersian Gulf.) Bear Sir, We thank you for your favour No.610/17/7 of 1927 of the 23rd. ultimo and in reply we have pleasure in advising despatch of one Blow Lamp complete for your P.lll type engine No.82081. As regards the remaining parts, we regret we have not these in stock but we have at once sent your order to our Works and as soon as we receive them, we will forward to you without any delay. Enclosed herewith please our bill No. 2730 amounting to Es.54/8/- only, which we trust you will find in order and favour us with your cheque at your convenience. Yours faithfully.No. of 1927. Political Agency, 3a 1 ] rain, Datod tha 22 nd October 27. iiOGGre CraGGloy rotliors, * Excanpe DuildingG, Bombay. Dear BirG, With referonco to the corroGpondenco rorting with yourG of tho 10th Auguet, will you pleaGo let me know v/Iion the spare parte may now be expected. The following additional part-G may also be Gupplied TheG 9 are urgently required. Yours faitlifully, \ix^ Captain, Political Agent, Bahrain. erial No. Name Quantity 114 Small end adjusting Gotecrew &amp; locknut 119 Stud &lt;5c nut for locking plate 2 \ 120 Locking plate 2flDemoranbum I / reply we are glad to infoanyou that the spare parts which were on order for yo- are at present under clearance in the doc&amp;'and we expect them in a day or two when we will send them to you. As regards the parts which you now require . V/e very much regret that these parts are not in stock, hut we have at once passed your order to our works and have asked them to send the parts with all possible haste. Tours faithfully, /4e m uclAaaaMMj 'j \ u &lt; 2 //- &lt;s&amp;*fUf%T 4 f, 14 -u • IK • M CHOSSLSYteROTHIiKS LTD. A '~%y/ri]vy Managei- for India. WflDemotanbum 4f' CROSSLEY BROS. LTD. ENGINEERS Commerce House, Currimbhoy Rd., Ballard Estate- BOMBAY. { grams :-GASENGINE. phone No. 22985. POST BOX No. 157. Bora‘ba.y.....l 5 -th»-Novbr:^ To , The Political Bahrei n (Per Dear Sir, With further reference to our letter of the 10th. of August, we now have pleasure in advising despatch of the spare parts by Parcel post to you and we enclose herewith our Bill No, 29llj. amounting to Rs. 30/9/- only. Kind ]7 aclenowlndge receipt. *JA Yours faithfully, CROSSLEY BROTHERS LTD. 3- ManagerVor India. V., /£L: Meesre Crossl«y Brothers Commerce House, Currimbhoy Road, Ballard Estate, Bombay. Dear birs. Tiie spare parts referred to in your letter dated the 15th November have been received. A money order for the amount of the bill is being sent separately. fours faithfully,Calcutta Office- 3 A, Vans it tart R Ow. London Office-139 I4-! Queen Victoria St,e.c. Madras Office:- 14, Broadway CROSSLEY I MAKERS OF GAS Sc OIL ENGINES. Opens haw, Manchester. AND SUCTION GAS PLANTS. FJD R AUL FUELS 8* ALL PURPOSES. Telephone N“ 22985 Bombay. u &gt;&gt; Telegrams Gasengine Bombav. IK YOUR REPLY PLEASE REFER TO Commerce House, CuRRIMBHOY ROAD, Ballard Estate Post Box No.157. B O MB AY. 214 -th. January 1928 The Political Agent, Bahrein. (Persian Gulf.) ■near Sir, / We thank you for your favour No.18 of the 10th.instant ordering therein some spare parts for your P.111 type engine and in reply we very much regret to say that we have no stock of these parts here, as the engine is of a very old type. vr e have, however, at once passed your order on to our T!7 orks in England and have requested them to send the parts as soon as ever possible and on receipt of same, we will forward them on to you. 'N Assuring you of our best attention at all times. Yours faithfully. CROSSLEY BROTHERS LTDflDemoranbum z&gt; &gt; Jr &amp; CROSSLEY BROS. LTD. Bomb ay.... 1 .7 th ... J.a nua rif 2 ... B »• - ENGINEERS To , Commkrce House, Currimbhoy Rd., 'political Agent Bahrein. (_ phone No. 22985 . POST BOX No. 157. f grams:—GASENGINE. Tele. ■ { Baelard Estate* BOMBAY. (Persian Guli) Dear Sir, With further reference to our letter of the 7th.November 192? we now have pleasure in advising despatch of the spare parts by Parcel Post as ordered in your letter No. 88.0/17/7 of 22-10-27 and we enclose herewith our Bill No. JO^J amounting to fh. 19-7-0 only, which we trust you* will find in order .* Kindly acknowledge receipt q i Yours faithfully.Ho. ' of 1928. Political Agency, Bahrain, Oatod the //^ FeVru&amp;ry 1028. To UeecrG Crossloy Brother^, Liraitod, Cor 3 norco House, Currinbhoy Road, Bombay. H Dear Sirs, With reference to your letter Ro. 17th January T928, I have to advise having by money order the sum of R“ l^/?/- in settlement of your bill, the receipt of wliicli please acknowledge. Yours faithfully.* flDemotan&amp;um. Tele, CROSSLEY BROS. LTD. ENGINEERS Commerce House, Currimbhoy Rd., Baeeard Estate* BOMBAY. f grams:—GASENGINE. \ phone No. 22985 . POST BOX No. 157. Bomb.ay....5.tiu.Mar.ch. f ^8. Cs To, Political AgeniGAl Bahrein. j/T ^ (Persia pi*/foif.) /7/ or it' ^ate. 1^1 S- 2 .fr /(&lt;/ Dear Sir, We are in receipt of your Money Order for Rs. 13-7-0 in full payment of our Bill No. 5033 -tor which we thank you and are enclosing herewith our Receipt No.1222 for the same, which please receive. ACKINOVV LEDGAIENT. Postal Service.) ^ „ Nam *^„ &gt; eS8r s •0 ro ssley Bros .Ltd., {C^/. A mount of order (in figures) 3s.CROSSLEY BROS. LTD ilftenioranbum Bombay....2nd..Ap.r.il., If2 8 ,... ^ (S ENGINEERS To, Commerce House, Currimbhoy Rd., Ballard Estate* BOMBAY. The Political Agent (Persian Gulf.) { gramsGASENGINE. phone No. 22985. POST BOX No. 157. { gramsGASENGINE. phone No. 22985. Dear Sir, ''ith further reference to our letter of the 2 kth.January, we now have pleasure in advising despatch of the spare parts ordered by you as per your letter No .18 of 1 Oth.January, by parcel post and we enclose herewith our Bill No. 3153 amounting to Rs. 51 - 1-0 only, which we trust you will fipd in order. Kindly acknowledge receipt Yours faithfully, c: ajd/fNo. Commerce House, Currimbhoy Road, Ballard Estate, BOMBAY. 2nd ..April, I.. 9 . 28 -. The. Political Agent , Bahrain ..(..Persian....Gulf t &amp; CR05SLEY BROTHERS, Ltd. Your Order No. 6 Interest at g per cent, per annum will be charged on all accounts not settled within 30 days. P.111 No, 82081. To. ip bottom governor dies 1 ; top governor blades ip bottom ” ” 12 governor springs • • 9 • • Rs. 20 10 8 12 ; ' , 4 Rs. 50 - - Postage &amp; Packing 11 - Rs. 51 1 (Rupees fifty-one and anna one, only.) £• &amp; 0. E.William Jacks &amp; Co Head Office: LONDON. Telephone.- 461. BRANCHES: Telegrams: “astorr.-- Codes : acme. ca lc utta. BOMBAY. RANGOON. MADRAS. SINGAPORE. KUALA LUMPUR. SHANGHAI. McLeod Road, BENTLEY-S. GENERAL. PRIVATE. KARACIII.Ip Lh. rarciL, 192....6 (P.O. BOX 179) The Political Agent, Political Agency, Bahrain. Bear Sir, 7,6 thank you for your letter No. 154 dated 5th instant, but very much regret that v/e are unable to supply Cling^ Surface Composition. We can offer you,however^'Gripoly” Belt Preservative @ r; 3 . 3/4/. per 2 lb tins and 10/4 per 7 lb tins F.O.R. or i’.C.B. Karachi, and enclose a pamphlet for your perusal. We might mention that we are the Agents &amp; Stockists 'Gripoly” Patent Solid Woven Belting and we shall appreciate an opportunity of quoting against your requirements in future.i r /'N u B sm ill d K ,v ' ' '' r ,M slllrs while runnins. Th- I n ' M «W'« , !lvJ , „( Ik lcmu. ■■•'•I » ■' , .•,.„„ m . n.|v -I— 1 ' ul • ..Kifoi.v f c„|., Manufacturers of Prepared only by t PIPOLY BELTING. Patent solid Woven GRIPOL Gripoly Belt Preservative J 1 A Dressing that Preserves and Prevents SLIP KF.CJ USE Supplied^,I, contains no resin or other injurious compound. vT‘ ’ Its waterproof nature helps the belt to resist dampness. It preserves the belt and lengthens its life. It produces an adhesive condition, by which a larger amount of power can he transmitted. It does not become hard, cake, nor crystallize, con sequently remaining in the belt permanently. screw tops. Tins free but weighed in as Preservative.NOTES on the CARE of PATENT u CjRIPQL\ 11 Belting more* iLii ^,11 , 0 !^ tl!’n'Hu- 'iT It'' ' ^“ pr0per am0,lnt of rare : ‘'»t looking after tXep te“L are ; - ‘' V,&gt; maX,ms whid &gt; the ^ «-r will ,i„ well (1) “ Keep Belts Clean.” (2) 44 Prevent Slipping.” Belts should be looked over occasionally when they are stopped and carefullv cleaned, and any matter adhering to them removed. The pulley flees should at the and^L* tTve^a'V* 'n f T o prevent slipping, Betts should frequently ami regularly have a small Quantity of “ GRIPOLY ” Belt Preservative anolied BettL r ''an'd S it t k hd' T^'t is f '’ n ' ,&lt;l for a ' olas^es of tenVporariiy! ' ,ten&lt;led to P revent sll PPi&gt;&gt;« altogether, not merely to stop it To get the maximum length of life and the highest efficiency out of a Belt it to be Tcd't *' ; B *?■ Start sIi PP in «’ if it does start, some reuedy will h’ave used to stop the slipping at once, and all such remedies are bad for the belt. RFTTTvr^f! r.T most certainly able to claim for our Patent “GRIPOLY” BLLIINCv that it has undoubtedly the highest possible pulley-grippimr capacity Lai' oTwfere h ' P d” 'T^i j' cas « ' h «e the pulleys’ire ^bno^malfv M.td Or v. /11 d,a 'T ter . the re 'S great disparity between the sizes of the Driving wile 10 s bfo brf hC ° f the . Dri Y in g -Kl Driven pulleys should therefore! Is possible ’ 1 1 R rat, ° ° f three to one t and as large in diamete; The result of a Belt slipping is to set up heat through friction, which may in tune render the fibres from which the Belting is manufactured tender and brittle and consequently cause considerable damage to the Belt. The slipping of a Belt can’very 1 h^ fI by a / lose examination of the Driving face of the Belt and the pullev . lould the Driving face of the Belt show any signs of becoming hard and shiny or takfog place! WaM11 immedlately thc Belt is dipped, this is a sure sign that “ slip ” is tins !o^ Y ” Be ! t i • iS PUt UP in special nozzled screw-top Use\erv httle ofTbf? 7 bc P ° ured 1 f. a th u in stre am upon the Belt while running. Use very little of the Preservative at a time, but use it regularly and frequently until the Belt is in mellow and supple condition, with a perfect driving face. Then continue the treatment regularly but less frequently, so that the Belt is kept in this conditionr Wo. A/ ^ of 1928. 1 'ho Political Agency# Bahrein. Dated the April 1920. To Xha heeara William Jacks &amp; Co.# AfcLeod Road, Karachi . Dear Sirs# With reference to your letter dated the 15th March 192 q # will you please let ne Irriovr if 'Gripoly' will give the belt a better grip so as to keep it from slipping. Yours faithfully. Political Agent# Bahrein.© &lt;1 1^0 • ot 19 JiQ • The Political Agency, Bahrein. Dated the /jfckpril 19&amp;8 To keaare Orosaley Brothers, Limited, Commerce House, Currimbhoy Road, Bombay. Dear Sira, with releronce to your letter dated the gad April 19L0# I have to advise having remitted by money order iflb^sum of Ra.51-1-0 in settlement of your bill, the receipt of which please acknowledge. Yours faithfully. Political Agent, Bahrein. »William Jacks &amp; Co. Head Office.- LONDON. Branches.- c a lc utta. BOM BAY. RANGOON. MADRAS. SINGAPORE. KUALA LUMPUR. SHANGHAI. /^\ Telephone: 461. Telegrams: “astorr.-- CODES: ACME. BENTLEYS. GENERAL. PRIVATE. The Political Agent, Political Agency, Bahrein. Bear Sir, McLeod Road, K. ARACIII,. 1.0th April, 193 8 (P.O. Box 179) In reply to your letter No, 190 dated 2nd instant, 'Gripoly' Belt Preservative will keep beltsin a supple condition with perfect driving faces and thus will prevent slipping altogether and not merely stop it temporarily. rcvb. jyjfours faithfully, V ^\lmffr liajn Jacics &amp; c o., ft r*- Ok 0 2~ £(&gt; f 3fIff ~ &gt;vt o^-eLe^t^l {kf 'V- (P, ^ 1 rri T-^LfThe Poll t.i ciil Aganey, Balirein Dateci th© ^/^Tpril 1935. To Messrs WilliaK Jacks &amp; Co., MeLeod Hoad, Karachi• Dear Sirs, With reference to your letter dated the 10th April 1938 ^ please supply jae by V.P.P. with one 2lb/rf. tin of ,, G^ipoly ,, costing Ra.3/4/~. Political Agent, Bahreinflftemoranbum. CROSSLEY BROS. LTD. ENGINEERS Commerce House, Currimbhoy Rd., Ballard Estate. BOMBAY. { grams:—GASENGINE. phone No. 22985. POST BOX No. 157. A t§) Tele. 192 .8. To Political Agent, BAHREIN. Z7* ■ I $ t */n Itjl \ '7?\ RMf A ■ Dear Sir, ,;e are receipt of your money order amounting to L, 51.1.0. for v/hich we thank you and are enclosing herewith, our receipt for the same wnich please receive. Yours faithfully, CRO SSLSY JBRO THERS IT I).William Jacks &amp; Co Telephone: 461. TELEGRAMS: “ASTORR.' Codes : acme. BENTLEYS. GENERAL PRIVATE. McLeod Road. Karachi, 4th May r 192 a (P.O. Box 179) The Political Agent, Political Agency, Bahrein. Bear Sir, Y/ith reference to your letters No. 134 &amp; 190 dated March 5th and April 2nd respectively we shall be glad to know if H Gripoly M Belt Preservative will suit your purpose. urs faithfully, 'tfjiliiam Jacks &amp; Co., RCM/B Pi'William Jacks &amp; Co Head Office: LONDON. BRANCHES: CALC UTTA. BOM BAY. RANGOON. MADRAS. SINGAPORE. KUALA LUMPUR. SHANGHAI. The Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir, TELEPHONE: 461. Telegrams: “astorr.” CODES: ACME. BENTLEYS. GENERAL. PRIVATE. McLeod Road, Karachi, 7 th Kas. 192.1 (P.O. BOX 179) We thank you for your letter No. 252 dated 27th April and as requested are despatching per V.P.P. one 2 lb tin of Gripoly belt preservative. With pleasure at your service. RCM/D.TELEPHONE No. 24225 &lt;t telegrams : 'KILOWATT” Codes Used : COLE &amp; PRIVATE AFFILIATED WITH THE GENERAL ELECTRIC Co., LTD. “MAGNET HOUSE.” KINGSWAY, LONDON, W.C. 2. AND The General Electric De France, Ltd. The General Electric Co. of China, Ltd. The British General Electric Co., Ltd., Australia. The British General Electric Co., Ltd., S. Africa. Ref « G • it • 53/D* The Anglo-Argentine General Electric Co., Ltd. 7 (n HEAD OFFICE 14, OLD COURT HOUSE STREET. CALCUTTA. BRANCHES lOO, ARMENIAN STREET, MADRAS. s § TRADE mark 86, THE MALL LAHORE. SOHRAB HOUSE” HORNBY ROAD, FORT, (Post Box No. 86 1.) BOMBAY. 23rd li/j&amp;y, 1928. WORKS &amp; ASSOCIATED MANUFACTURING COMPANIES i HEAVY ENGINEERING, GENB ORS, MOTORS, SWITCHGEAR, FANS. PRIMARY BATTERIES, CARBONS, MOULDED INSULATION, Witton, near Birminhgam. TURBINES, BLOWERS, COMPRESSORS, CONVEYING &amp; MINING PLANT, Fraser &amp; Chalmers Engineering Works, Erith, Kent. “ OSRAM ” LAMPS, “ OSRAM ” WIRELESS VALVES, Hammersmith, London, ELECTRIC LIFTS, Express Lift Co., Ltd., London, WIRES &amp; CABLES, Pirelli-General Cable Works, Ltd., Southampton. GLASS WORKS, Lemington-on-Tyne &amp; Wembley. HEATING &amp; COOKING. Birmingham. INSTRUMENTS &amp; METERS, Salford E ical Instruments, Ltd., Manchester. Cham in &amp; Hookham, Ltd., Birmingham. TELEPHONES, Peel-Conner Telephone Works, Coventry &amp; Manchester. ART METAL FITTINGS, Edgbaston, Birmingham. SIEMENS &amp; GENERAL ELECTRIC RAILWAY SIGNAL CO., LTD. STEEL CONDUIT CO., LTD. RESEARCH LABORATORIES, Wembley, Middlesex. OSR/q: Deer Sirs, The production of the P3ARX, OSRAIt ro^rks a^her step forward in the steady improvement o( electric lamps, which has been made since the introduction of the original metal filament lamp, mth the invention of the gasfilled lamp the intrinsic brilliancy of the filament became a P tive menace to eyesi fe nt, and although several methods have been tried for overcoming this darling glare, each had its own particular disadvantage, e ; g. *** ^ absorb a large proportion of the light, the aheppption Retimes oeing a s high u s 20^, white sprayed lamps absorbed abop* 7^ light and also collected dirt, externally frosted lamps also had the disadvantage of collecting dirt on the outer surface. How the PEARL OSR/J! has none of these drawbacks and yet provides perfect diffusion, the bulb is frosted on the inside, leaving the outside perfectly smooth and easy to keep clean, the absorption of light is only 1^ to an amount so small that it can only be measured by very sensitive apparatus, ana yet the diffusion is sufficient to eliminate the dangerous and unpleasant dazzle, inseparabl froui the clear ei^sfilled lamp. In spite of these improvements, you can buy PEARi, oSRAmS for the same price as clear lamps. Give FEiJU, 03R.J1S a trial, you will never go back to the glaring jclear lamp. Yours faithfully, T-fa* .G^OT^IC GO* (India) LTD, Dnclos. 1 leaflet 0., 3 . 4366 . The S.G.C- your guaranteemm D. GASFILLED LAMPS Why “ PEARL OSRAM ” ? The PEARL OSRAM marks a goal towards which the science of electric lighting has been striving for many years. It represents the solution of a problem which seemed for a while so baffling as to be on the verge of the impossible. With each step upwards in the development of the electric lamp, the light became more brilliant. In the gasfilled lamp it is intensely brilliant—so intense is it, indeed, that it cannot be looked at with comfort. When a bare gasfilled lamp is hung anywhere near the line of sight, it causes “ glare,' which has been aptly defined by Webster as “ disagree able brightness.' So we reach the paradox that a brilliant light may be, in certain conditions, not so good to see by as a less brilliant light. The human eye is accustomed to diffused light, like that of the sun filtered through clouds. Light from a powerful concentrated source has a dazzling effect. First Step to Diffusion. So the gasfilled OSRAM, which made electric light about six times cheaper than it had been with carbon lamps, gave birth to a variety of methods of diffusing their light. Moving Towards Perfection. The original plan of frosting the bulb on the outside was not satisfactory for two reasons. The frosting absorbed considerable light, and the frosted surface harboured dust and dirt, which nothing would remove. Anything from a fifth to nearly one quarter of the light of a lamp can be wasted by dirt on the bulb. The Perfection of the “ PEARL.” In the PEARL OSRAM the diffusing surface is inside the bulb. The outside remains perfectly smooth, so that it does not readily catch any dust or dirt, and can be wiped or washed clean in a moment. The Chameleon. Simple as the solution appears, it was not reached without an immense amount of research and experiment. The “ inside frost ' is produced by treating the inside surface of the bulb in a particular manner which results in more efficient diffusion than the outside frost. In cidentally, it gives the lamp, when it is alight, a charming pearl grey tint, from which its name PEARL OSRAM is derived. Further, the PEARL OSRAM is like a chameleon ; it takes on the tints of its surroundings. By virtue of this quality, it harmonises perfectly with any colour scheme. Perfect Light. The light from a PEARL OSRAM is free from all harshness, and cannot injure or strain the most sensitive eye. For economy and comfort, use PEARL OSRAMS. New—Better—Cost the Same.TELEPHONE No. 24225 telegrams: • KILOWATT* Codes Used : COLE &amp; PRIVATE AFFILIATED WITH THE GENERAL ELECTRIC Co., LTD. “MAGNET HOUSE,' KINGSWAY, LONDON, W.C. 2. AND The General Electric De France, Ltd. The General Electric Co. of China, Ltd. The British General Electric Co., Ltd., Australia. The British General Electric Co., Ltd., S. Africa. The Anglo-Argentine General Electric Co., Ltd. WORKS &amp; ASSOCIATED MANUFACTURING COMPANIES 7 Y REGISTERED flef,C,I).57/D„ HEAD OFFICE 14, OLD COURT HOUSE STREET. CALCUTTA. BRANCHES lOO, ARMENIAN STREET, MADRAS. 86, THE MALL LAHORE. SOHRAB HOUSE” HORNBY ROAD, FORT, (Post Box No. 861.) BOMBAY. Z l ^...... y J-Oth July, 1928 HEAVY'' , .wiNEERING, GENERATORS, MOTORS. V SWITCHGEAR, FANS, PRIMARY BATTERIES, CARBONS, v MOULDED INSULATION, Witton, near Birminhgam. TURBINES, BLOWERS, COMPRESSORS, CONVEYING &amp; MINING PLANT, Fraser &amp; Chalmers Engineering Works, Erith, Kent. “ OSRAM ” LAMPS. “ OS RAM” WIRELESS VALVES, Hammersmith, London, ELECTRIC LIFTS, v Express Lift Co., Ltd., London, WIRES &amp; CABLES, Pirelli-General Cable Works, Ltd., Southampton. GLASS WORKS, Lemington-on-Tyne &amp; Wembley. HEATING &amp; COOKING. Birmingham. NSTRUMENTS &amp; METERS, Salford Eleo^*J'St'struments, Ltd., r J c** Manchester. hamberlain &amp; Hookham, Ltd., Birmingham. TELEPHONES, Peel-Conner Telephone Works, Coventry &amp; Manchester. T METAL FITTINGS. dgbaston, Birmingham. SIEMENS &amp; GENERAL ELECTRIC RAILWAY SIGNAL CO., LTD. STEEL CONDUIT CO., LTD. RESEARCH LABORATORIES, V Wembley, Middlesex. PSARL OSRAU LAMPS Bear Sir, in thoi* Peopie are rather conservative t01,ardB anything new which is put on ^ ut once they have been persuaded to try a by W it^s meritl! d they Cftn 158 favourably impressed v,o«&lt;+ * T® b ® lieT8 that there are a number of people who as ?^ARL nlpivt neW i^ernally frosted lamps, known as Marl OSRAltS, because they think that there must be a serious diminution of illuminating power; actually there is no ground for this fear, as the absorption of light is so small as to be imperceptible to the human eye. As a proof of this statement,, a number of our PEARL OSRAH bulbs were tested, against an equal number of opal glass bulbs of another make, by Paraday House, London, which, 1 f an ab s° lllt ely independent authority; the result gf this test showed that the average light 7 absorption of t^e PEARL OSRAM bulbs was only 2 &lt;, as A g oirt?ffL aVeraee ^ a ?f 0rptiOn 0f 15 - the °P al hulbs. A certified copy of the report on this test can be inspected at our Offices by any of our clients. in of this low absorption factor, e light from PEARL OSRAM Lamps is perfectly diffused and is absolutely free from the blinding dazzle, which is inseparable from the clear gasfilled (or so-called * watt) lamp, and which is so harmful to the eyesight. In spite ©f their manifest advantages, thp prices of PEARL ©SRAMS are the same as the prices of clear OSRAM Lamps. content! y ° U tPy them ’ and P rove the truth of our that vou .fn h y ^'satisfaction? We are confident xnat you will be pleased with the results. Yours faithfully, THi] GENERAL ELECTRIC CO.,(India), LTD. 77ie S.G.C-your guarcniee.9HBB I' *c TELEPHONE No. Z4ZZ5 TELEGRAMS: “ KILOWATT Codes Used : COLE &amp; PRIVATE AFFILIATED WITH THE GENERAL ELECTRIC Co., LTD “MAGNET HOUSE,” KINGSWAY, LONDON, W. C. 2. The General Electric De France, Ltd. The General Electric Co. of China, Ltd. The British General Electric Co., Ltd., Australia. The British General Electric Co., Ltd., S. Africa. The Anglo-Argentine General Electric Co., Ltd. REGISTERED V trade mark Kef ♦C.L. 60/D. HEAD OFFICE *—^ * ,, 14, OLD COURT HOUSE STREET. CALCUTTA. BRANCHES 100, ARMENIAN STREET, MADRAS. 30, THE MALL, LAHORE. THE MALL, CAWNPORE. “ SOHRAB HOUSE,” HORNBY ROAD, FORT, ( Post Box No. 861 ) BOMBAY. 25th Septr.1928. WORKS &amp; ASSOCIATED MANUFACTURING COMPANIES: HEAVY ENGINEERING, GENERATORS, MOTORS, ^“*\TCHGEAR, FANS, i BATTERIES, CA^iiONS, MOULDED INSULATION, Witton, near Birmingham. TURBINES, BLOWERS. COMPRESSORS, CONVEYING &amp; MINING PLANT, Fraser &amp; Chalmers Engineering Works, Erith, Kent. OSRAM ” LAMPS, ROBERTSON ” LAMPS, OSRAM ” WIRELESS VALVES, Hammersmith, London. ELECTRIC LIFTS, Express Lift Co., Ltd., London. WIRES &amp; CABLES, Pirelli-General Cable Works, Ltd. Southampton. GLASS WORKS. Lemington-on-Tyne &amp; Wembley. HEATING &amp; COOKING, Birmingham. INSTRUMENTS &amp; METERS, Salford Electrical Instruments, Ltd. Manchester. Chamberlain &amp; Hookham, Ltd., Birmingham. TELEPHONE &amp; WIRELESS APPARATUS, ''^''''Coventry &amp; Manchester. ART METAL FITTINGS, Birmingham. CONDUIT &amp; ACCESSORIES, Birmingham &amp; West Bromwich. SIEMENS &amp; GENERAL ELECTRIC RAILWAY SIGNAL CO., LTD. 'M^GiraT” BAKSLITS lAkIPHOLDJ1RS . Dear 3ir(s)» We have pleasure in enclosing a leaflet, nhich clearly sets forth the many advantages of our ’’WAGiiST Baicelite Pendant Lampholders, which we feel sure will he of interest to you. We should also like to draw your attention to the fact that the range of our Bakelite Lampholders has now been extended to include both Bracket and Batten types, of which we have pleasure in quoting you prices: 3.1133 ,, MA.Gi32JT n Bakelite Pendant Lampholders with cordgrips and shade rings. Rs.10.12 dozen S.1135 'MAGlviST’* Bakelite Bracket Lampholders 1 / 2 ” with shade rings. w !!• 4 M S.1268 M j»iL.GL T jjT M Bakelite Batten Lampholders with shade lings. . u 14. 7 ^ The above list prices are subject to your usual terms. For quantities of not Jess than, one gross, or three gross, of one pattern of lamphoJ der, we are prepared to quote special reduced nett rates, which can be had on application. The advantages of Bakelite Lampholders, men tioned in. the enclosed leaflet? apply with equal force to the Bracket and Batten types* all these lampholders are BRITISH made throughout in our own Works, and we can confidently recommend them as thoroughly reliable articles. WATSON &amp; SONS ( Electro-Medical) LTD. G. E. C. RESEARCH LABORATORIES, Wembley, Middlesex. dJiTCLOS.l. 77ie £.G.G—your guarantee.Leaflet S 4417. {May, 1027.) BAKELITE LAMPHOLDER. (Prov. Patents : Nos. 22950/26 and 28413 26.) The “MAGNET” Bakelite Cordgrip Lampholder represents a definite advance in lampholder design and is a further example of the adaptability of bakelite. The salient features of this lampholder are brought out in the illustrations below. AulomaHc Cordgrip which will accommodate varying types of flexible. There are no loose woods Heavy milled shade carrier ring wifh projecfions ro facilifafe removal of bell moufhed shade Bakelite liner fo accommodate standard shade wifh 1/^ hole. S Guards fo prevent flexible touching terminal of opposite polarity Heavy easily wired terminal with smooth hole fo prevent wires being guillotined All external parts are of bake life. The lampholder is therefore entirely insulated. 1133 This Lampholder can be wired in half the time required for an ordinary lampholder 1 here are no cordgrip woods to be cut or small holes in which conductors have to be inserted. 1 he Lampholder consists of three loose parts only. All parts are made to fine limits and are strictly interchangeable. 1 he natural brown finish of the “ MAGNET ” Bakelite Lampholder is highlv attractive, and tones with most decorative schemes. Bakelite has distinct advantages, as it is untarnishable and non-corrodible ; the shade carrier rintr cannot bind under any atmospheric conditions. It is speciallv suitable for Bathrooms Sculleries Cellars Lavatories, and similar olaces. ’ ’ Cat. No. Description. Per Standard Package. Approx. Dimensions. Quantity Approx. Weight. Price per dozen. S 113 3 “ Magnet ” Bakelite lampholder inches. lbs. kilos. £ s - d. with cordgrip and shade carrier rmg 9 x 5 x 4i 3 doz. 3 1 36 15 O S 1 1 5 O Ditto, ditto, with Home Office Type Shock-proof Shield 8 x 6 &gt; x 3f 1 doz. u •68 12 6 ■ EC&gt; fR»0l NAPk The General Electric Company, Limited Head Office: Magnet House, Kingsway, London, W.C. 2. telephone: Regent 7050 (61 lines). Telegrams: 'Electricity, Westcent, London.’’ Branches throughout Great Britain and in all principal markets of the World. •tc* UAMPUIfc R/16137.sgj .gatgJjsflSg BAKELITE B.C. ADAPTORS. (Prov. Patent : No. 22950 26.) The Bakelite Adaptor is the result of efforts to supply a really high-grade article at a reasonable price. It is fitted with substantial elliptical contacts and heavy terminals, with holes designed to prevent the flexible being guillotined. An effective cordgrip is obtained by means of a high dividing bridge, and guards are provided to prevent the flexible short circuiting on the opposite pole. The small projecting lugs on each side of the body facilitate removal from the lampholder. The adaptor is smaller than the ordinary hardwood pattern and is very robust. Cat. No. Description. Per Standard Package of Three Dozen. Dimensions. Approx, weight. Price per dozen. S 7 53 S 754 “ Magnet ” Brown Bakelite B.C. Adaptor with |-in. hole in cap Ditto with ffc-in. diam. hole inches. lbs. I kilos. 7 x 5 x 5£ 3 l-36 7 x 5 x 5f 3 l -36 s7 d. 9 O 9 O “MAGNET” BAKELITE TWO-CIRCUIT ADAPTOR. Patent No. 27503. This very useful Adaptor, which permits light and a lead for domestic appliances to be taken nickel plat P° lnt ’ I&lt;? SUpphed Wlth a brown Bakelite body. The metal parts are finished heavy Cat. No. Description. Per Standard Package of One Dozen. Dimensions. I Approx, weight. Price each. S 3 / 9 Two circuit adaptor with switch to control the light. Brown Bakelite body with nickelled metal parts inches. lbs. ' kilos. 6£ X 6 x 6J j 31 1-63 s. d. 5 9 BAKELITE TWO-PIN TO B.C. ADAPTOR. Patent No. 251068. The majority of domestic appliances are fitted with ordinary bayonet cap adaptors. There as been a growing demand for an adaptor which would permit these appliances to be connected -onTh 3 a° Ck +v, S ° n e a X 1 S V n , g , installatlons - The device here shown consists of a B.C. Lampholder combined with an adjustable two-pin plug. The plug pins, which are replaceable are made in six ^Mmc^T^gauge^oTs^mp.^E^^gauge^ 1118 ’ ^ t0 ** ^ 2 -amp. Cat. No S 730a Description. Combined two-pin adiustable plug and B.C. Lampholder, complete with a pair of pins of one of the following gauges : 2-amp. Midget, 5-amp. B.E.S.A., 5-amp or 10-amp. T., 10-amp. Union, or 15-amp B.E.S.A. Per Standard Package of One Dozen. Price per dozen. i Dimensions. Approx. Weight. inches. lbs. kilos. £ s. d. 44 X4£ x4 U •68 17 6 Gauge Pi.ates (Cat. No. S 728) for use with S 730a . . 1 3s. 6 d. per dozenTh© Political Agency* Bahrein 9 Dated the ^/4 tfeptenber 1928• To The Branch Manager* General Electric Company, Ltd., Hornby Road, Fort, Bombay. Dear Sir, Please supply me with three dozen 830 volto 60 watts white Oar,am G.E.C. Gasfilled electric bulbs and send me your bill t'or payment. Yours faithfully, Indian Assistant, in the absence of the Political Agent, Bahrein. (yv-V-ReGISTERED A V) Telephone N? 24225 Telegrams: KILOWATT!’ Codes Us ed: COLE and PRIVATE N •LJ trade mark Head Office : I4-. OLD COURT HOUSE S^RtET C A L_C U T T A . Affiliated with: THE GENERAL ELECTRIC CP LIP, MAGNET HOUSE!’ KINGS WAY, LO NOON, W.C.2. AND THE GENERAL ELECTRIC DE FRANCE,LTP THE GENERAL ELECTRIC CO.(OF CHINA),LTP THE BRITISH GENERAL ELECTRIC CO., LTP, AUSTRALIA. ^ THE BRITISH GENERAL ELECTRIC CO. LTP, S. AFRICA. • TH E ANGLO-ARGENTINE GENERAL ELECTRIC CO , LTSI^ ' J ^ Branches: IOO,ARMENIAN STREET, MADRAS. 30, TH E MALL, LAN ORE. VO UR REF. OUR R E f r csd/v WORKS: ENGINEERING. SWITCHGEAR. MOULDED INSULATION. BATTERY. CARBONS. STEEL CONDUIT. ELECTRIC FANS. WITTON, near BIRMINGHAM. S () h r ab 11 o 11 s e, 5^ 235, Hornby Road, Fort, ^ (p.o Box N° 8 6 1 ) 17. Bombay. 28th Septr.aib Tiie Political Agent, Political Agency, BAHRSIN, Persian Gulf. ART METAL. •O' EDGBASTON, BIRMINGHAM. ACCESSORIES. WEMBLEY, MIDDLESEX. \ OSRAM’ LAMPS &amp; VALVES. ROBERTSON” LAMPS. HAMMERSMITH, LONDON. INSTRUMENTS. SALFORD ELECTRICAL INSTRUMENTS LT?, SALFORD. WIRELESS APPARATUS. TELEPHONES, E TP PEEL-CONNER TELEPHONE WORKS, COVENTRY, STEAM TURBINES. DIESEL ENGINES. BLOWERS, COMPRESSORS. CONVEYING &amp; MINING PLANT/ FRASER &amp; CHALMERS ENGINEERING WORKS, ERITH, KENT. ACCESSORIES 8. RAILWAY SIGNALLING APPARATUS. SIEMENS 8. GENERAL ELECTRIC RY SIGNAL CP LTp G LASS. LEMINGTON-ON-TYNE. &amp; WE M B LEY. HEATING &amp; COOKING TOWER WORKS, BIRMINGHAM. WIRES &amp; CABLES. PIRELLI-GENERAL CABLE WORKS LTP, SOUTHAM PTON. METERS. CHAMBERLAIN &amp; HOOKHAM.LT?. BIRMINGHAM. ELECTRIC LIFTS. EXPRESS LIFT C9 LONDON. A y ^LECTRO-MEDICAL 8. X-RAY. TSON &amp; SONS (ELECTRO-MEDICAL) LT D Dei Sir, We beg to acknowledge, with thanks, receipt of your esteemed order tto*573 of tne 8th inst*, for 36 230 volt 60W.vhi 0 SRAMs • We have to advise ycu, however, that the white sprayec OSRAM lamp has now been superseded by the “PEARL' (internally frosted; OSRAM which has great advantages over White 0SR/M i^ that / whilst effectively diffusing the light, the absorption is only about 2% f as against 10^ in the White OSRAMf, and moreover tne outside surface is perfectly smooth, and does not collect dirt which was a serious draw-back to the \7nite OSRAM. We nave, therefore taken the liberty of despatching “PEARL' 0SRAMs against your order, and we trust that our action will have your approval. We enclose a copy of Pamphlet CS.4366 whill will rive you full particulars regarding the “PEARL' OSRAM lamps. Yours faithfully, EJtfCLOS.lTELEPHONE No. 24225 TELEGRAMS: “KILOWATT /V Codes Used: COLE &amp; PRIVATE registered sl trade mark HEAD OFFICE 0 14. OLD COURT HOUSE STREET. CALCUTTA. BRANCHES 100. ARMENIAN STREET, MADRAS. AFFILIATED WITH THE GENERAL ELECTRIC Co.. LTD “MAGNET HOUSE.” KINGSWAV, LONDON, W. C. 2. The General Electric De France, Ltd. The General Electric Co. of China, Ltd. The British General Electric Co., Ltd., Australia. The British General Electric Co., Ltd., S. Africa. The Anglo-Argentine General Electric Co., Ltd. 30, THE MALL. LAHORE. THE MALL, CAWNPORE. Hef .C.L.66,0 C t *! 1' ^ Q c l SOHRAB HOUSE, HORNBY ROAD, FORT, (Post Box No. 861 BOMBAY. 5th November,1928* 0-N WORKS &amp; ASSOCIATED MA»*HFACTURING COMPANIES: 1 .VY ENGINEERING, GENERATORS, MOTORS, SWITCHGEAR, FANS, PRIMARY BATTERIES, CARBONS, MOULDED INSULATION. Witton, near Birmingham. TURBINES, BLOWERS. COMPRESSORS, CONVEYING &amp; MINING PLANT, Fraser &amp; Chalmers Engineering Work's, Erith, Kent. “ OSRAM ” LAMPS, “ ROBERTSON ” LAMPS, “OSRAM” WIRELESS VALVES, Hammersmith, London. ’-U P ^ VS.. • R' 1 ELECTRIC LIFTS, Express Lift Co., Ltd., London. WIRES &amp; CABLES, Pirelli-General Cable Works, Ltd.. •Southampton. GLASS WORKS, Lemington-on-Tyne &amp; Wembley. HEATING &amp; COOKING, Birmingham. INSTRUMENTS &amp; METERS, Salford Electrical’ Instruments, Ltd. Manchester. Chamberlain &amp; Hookham, Ltd., Birmingham. •'N EPHONE &amp; WIRELESS APPARATUS, Coventry &amp; Manchester. ART METAL FITTINGS, Birmingham. CONDUIT &amp; ACCESSORIES, Birmingham &amp; West Bromwich. SIEMENS &amp; GENERAL ELECTRIC RAILWAY SIGNAL CO., LTD. WATSON &amp; SONS ( Electro-Medical ^ LTD. . G. E. C. RESEARCH LABORATORIES, Wembley, Middlesex. FOUR REASONS WHY YOU SHOULD USE PEA RL OSRAM LAMPS 1. A PEARL OSRAM can replace a clear lamp, because the light absorption is negligible* 2. A PEARL OSRAM can replace any of the following types of diffused lamps, Opal, White Sprayed, Externally Frosted, because the light from it is perfectly diffused. 3. A PEARL OSRAM can replace a clear OSRAM, because it is a better lamp at the same price. 4* A PEARL OSRAM lamp will serve every normal lighting requirement, they are available in 15 and 25 watts Vacuum type, and 40, 60, 75 and 100 watts Gasfilled type. Specify PEARL 0SRAMS for ybur future lighting require ments, and refuse to be satisfied with substitutes. NEW BETTER COST NO MORE ALL PEARL FINISH ALL ONE SHAPE for ALL GENERAL LIGHTING PURPOSES* The General Electric Co.(India), Ltd. The S.G.G — your guarantee.m Telephone N? 24225 Telegrams: KILOWATT” Codes Used. COLE and PRIVATE Affiliated with: THE GENERAL ELECTRIC C9 LIP, 'magnet house!’ kingswav, LONDON, W.C.2. . AND THE GENERAL ELECTRIC DE FRANCE,LT? THE GENERAL ELECTRIC CO. (O F C H I N A), LT 9 THE BRITISH GENERAL ELECTRIC CO., LTP, AUSTRALIA THE BRITISH GENERAL ELECTRIC CO. LT9, S.AFRICA. THE ANGLO-ARGENTINE GENERAL ELECTRIC CO.,LTP V O U R REF. OUR REF adn/r WORKS: ENGINEERING. SWITCHGEAR. MOULDED INSULATION. BATTE RY. CARBONS. STEEL CONDUIT. ELECTRIC FANS. WITTON, near BIRMINGHAM. Head O f f i c e - ■ I4-, OLD COURT HOUSE STREET, CA LCU T TA . Branches: IOO.ARMENIAN STREET, MADRAS. 30,TH E MALL, LAHORE.. S o h r ab H o u s e, , Hornby Road,Fort, ( P.O. Box N° 86 1) ART METAL. EDGBASTON, BIRMINGHAM. ACCESSORIES. WEMBLEY, MIDDLESEX. GSRAM LAM PS &amp; VALVES. “ROBERTSON” LAMPS. HAMMERSMITH, LONDON. INSTRUMENTS. SALFORD ELECTRICAL INSTRUMENTS LT°, SALFORD. WIRELESS APPARATUS. TELEPHON ES, ET? PEEL-CONNER TELEPHONE WORKS, COVENTRY, STEAM TURBINES. DIESEL ENGINES. BLOWERS, COMPRESSORS. CONVEYING &amp; MINING PLANT. FRASER » CHALMERS ENGINEERING WORKS, ERITH, KENT. ACCESSORIES &amp; RAILWAY SIGNALLING APPARATUS. SIEMENS 8. GENERAL ELECTRIC RY SIGNAL C&lt;? L T P G LASS. LEMINGTON-ON-TYNE. 8, WE M B LE Y. B om b a’ 29th OetoiSlisr 1928 Political' Agent,' BAHRAIN ''T' Dear Sir, We thank you for your esteemed order lTo,656 of the 16th instant, and in reply would inform you that we are arranging to ship all the items called for* As regards V/ires, we would inform you that these are made up in 100 yards coils, and where you call for 1000 ft, we . are supplying four 100 yard! coils. As regards Flexible, this is made up in 50 yards coils • and we are accordingly despatching 2 coils against item 16. ’• Once again thanking you for your order. Your s faithfully, HEATING &amp; COOKING. TOWER WORKS, BIRMINGHAM. WIRES &amp; CABLES. PIRELLI-GENERAL CABLE WORKS LT?. SOUTHAMPTON. METERS. CHAMBERLAIN &amp; HOOKHAM.LT?. BIRMINGHAM. ELECTRIC LIFTS. S' ''express LI FT CP LON DO N. electro-medicals, x-ray. WATSON &amp; SONS (ELECTRO-MEDICAL) LT? X m4 The 5.C. Gryour guarantee. r\ ; -i x y/)t* Bill No. /.,.j— &gt;:..arei.L... xi..:, /.air.,... Da/e, i,;..* L......~ . TRIPLICATE TRADEMARK Telephone 24225, Telegrams- “ kilowatt. 1 REGISTERED Jo TRADE MARK_9 REGISTERED Telephone N? 24225 z — Telegrams: KILOWATT!’ Codes Used. COLE and PRIVATE. Affiliated with: THE GENERAL ELECTRIC C9 LT9, MAGNET HOUSE!’ KINGS WAV, LO NOON, W.C.2. AND THE GENERAL ELECTRIC DE FRANCE,LT? THE GENERAL ELECTRIC CO.(OF CHINA),LTP THE BRITISH GENERAL ELECTRIC CO., LT?, AUSTRALIA. '’'H E BRITISH GENERAL ELECTRIC CO. LT?, S. AFRICA. THE ANGLO-ARGENTINE GENERAL ELECTRIC CO., LT? I 4 TRADE MARK Head 0 ff i c e : 14-, OLD COURT HOUSE STREET, CA LC U TTA . Branches: IOO,ARMENIAN STREET, MADRAS. 30,THE MALL, LAHORE. VO U R s REF. r Sohra b Hons e, 235, Hornby Road, Fort, OUR. ___ , ^ refADN/H (p.o. Box N° 8 6 1) WORKS' ENGINEERING. SWITCHGEAR. MOULDED INSULATION. BATTERY. CARBONS. STEEL CONDUIT. ELECTRIC FANS. TTQN, near BIRMINGHAM. ART METAL. EDG BA STON, BIRMINGHAM. ACCESSORIES. WEMBLEY, MIDDLESEX. ’ O S R AM' LAM P S &amp; VALVES. ROBERTSON” LAMPS. HAMMERSMITH, LONDON. INSTRUMENTS. SALFORD ELECTRICAL INSTRUMENTS LT?, SALFORD. W I Rt LESS APPARATUS. TELEPHONES, ET? PEEL-CONNER TELEPHONE WORKS, COVENTRY. STEAM TURBINES DIESEL ENGINES. BLOWERS, COMPRESSORS. CONVEYING &amp; MINING PLANT. | FRASER &amp; CHALMERS ENGINEERING WORKS, ERITH, KENT. | ACCESSORIES &amp; RAILWAY j SIGNALLING APPARATUS. SIEMENS &amp; GENERAL ELECTRIC RY SIGNAL C&lt;? L T ? GLASS. LEMINGTON-ON-TYNE. &amp; WEMBLEY. HEATING &amp; COOKING. ^WER WORKS, BIRMINGHAM. WIRES &amp; CABLES PIRELLI-GENERAL CABLE WORKS LT? SOUTHAM PTON METERS CHAMBERLAIN &amp; H O OK H A M , LT?, Bl RM INGHAM ELECTRIC LIFTS. PRESS LIFT C? LONDON. ELECTRO-MEDICAL &amp; X-RAY. WATSON &amp; SONS (ELECTRO-MEDICAL) LT? x ^/ Bombay. 11th December 1328. The Political Agent, BAHRAIN. ft Dear Sir, In reply to your letter No.814 of tae 28th ultimo, we “ have pleasure in submitting our quotation as follows:- 2 - K 7850 Table Pattern Battery Call Telephone with K 7728 Induction Coil, han^ irv combination K7709, buzzer ?;ound to 25 ohms, ringing key with flexible cord and rosette Es 63. 0 each {*3 _ nett. Delivery from stock. \ * ly c»Ae paye 1585 of K Section Catalogue herewith. 3 - L 4801 'Witton” Leclanche Cells Porous Pot Pattern 3 pint 150 Yds. No. 14 S.W.Gr. Copper Wire hard drav/n for overhead line, approximate fis 3. 9 each 3 nett. To • weight 8 lbs. Alternatively, we offer 2 - K 8058 Table Pattern Magneto Call Telephone See page 1591 of K Section Catalogue .Bs 106. 0 each ?nett Delivery from stock F.OeB. Bombay SU T2, For Wiring diagram please refer to page 1520 oft^4 lata log ue We enclose herewith Section K of our Catalogue dealin-THE GENERAL ELECTRIC CO : , (INDIA) LTD. CONTINUATION SHEET NC. 1 y\ •—\ with, telephones m^ide at the G.S.C. Telephone 7/orks, StoKe, Coventry, England. We have quoted you for the essential telephone equipment* You will probably require some poles for tne telephone wire, but no doubt you will be able to procure these locally. Trusting to be favoured with your valued order which will have our best attention. Yours faithfully, ENCLOS: K Section. 4# k ■no. 220/22^ of 1347 Office oft the Adviser to the Government, Bahrain. Bated, 9th Shahban, 1347 H. B. M’s Political Agent, Bahrain * Memorandum Ref. your note re. fixing of telephones between your office and mine. H. E. Shaikh Hamad agreesand we shall be&gt; I'T To • 7Z Political Arency, Bahrain, Bated the Januazy 1929. The General Electric Coy., Ltd., 3orab T, ou3e, Hornby Hoad, Post Pox No. 861, J or-bay. Pear Jirs, vith reference to your letter dated the 11th Ultiro, I should be obliged if you will arrange to send tre the following, being ry requirerents for fitting up a telephone service and a few sundries, es early as you can together with a bill for ^ayrrent. If po-isible, I ray be allowed the relate of Indiau Cu.itors duty on these goods# Instructions for fitting up the telephones ray also be supplied. Yours faithfully, ^/Polit ical Agent, Bahrain. . &gt;- 1. K#8Q58 Table Pattern telephones vagneto Call. 2. L.4801 Witton Leo lanehe Cells porpus pattern - 3 pints 3. Copper Vire. ho. 14.j.y.G. for overhead line. 4. Bell wire. (sarple sent) 5. Calling bells (non-corrosive r^etal) 6. Lcclanche cell of the type supplied by you on 29-10-28 (ho. 2523/24) Two. i?our. 450 yds. 200 yds. Xwo. two.The s.c.e r your guarantee. ...The Political Agent, BAHREIN (Persian 3 ulf) V Bill No. 35 Date, 5-2-1929. ,Jb . TELEPHONE No. 24225 REGISTERED TELEGRAMS: •‘KILOWATT ” CODES USED : COLE &amp; PRIVATE trade mark 30. THE MALL. LAHORE AFFILIATED WITH THE GENERAL ELECTRIC Co.. LTD- “MAGNET HOUSE.” KINGSWAY, LONDON. W. C. 2 AND v The General Electric De France, Ltd. f *-J*' The General Electric Co. of China, Ltd. The British General Electric Co., Ltd., Aidtr^lia. ^Jfhe British General Electric Co., Ltd., ||. Africa, he e Anglo-Argentine General.Electric C^L.^td. ♦•tc IQ r / ^ Ref. C.J.. 70/D. ' _ ‘ 11 . THE MALL. CAWNPOBE “ SOHRAB HOUSE, HORNBY ROAD, FORT, ( Post Box No. 861) BOMBAY 3rd December,1928. 'xtmmsgrz- Dor.eL ti c ances. Dear Sir(s), Ve beg to enclose a revised Price List of ’’MAGIIST” Electric Heating and Cooping ij.ppLic.nces, a.nd siiall be obliged if you will kindly file sane for future reference. A number of reductions in prices are included in this new list which is subject to your usual terms, and ive trust that we shall receive increased orders for 'LAGHE?” Appliances from you in the future. Yo urs faithfully ; ZU GXIEHAL E. IHGTHIG 00. (India) LTD. EECLOS - 1 j,No. of 1929. The Political Agency, Bahrein. Dated [ft June 1929. To The Adviser, Bahrein Government, Bahrein. Memorandum . I shall he glad if you will please remit me a, sum of Rs.171-15-0 ( Rupees one hundred seventy one and anna* fifteen only) being half cost of telephones etc., as per details below:- Half cost of telephones, and accessories paid to General Electric Company, Bombay —Dp— Wages of a carpenter —Do— Wages of a mason Rs.161-3-0 9-4-0 1 - 6-0 Rs.171-15-0 Political Agent, Bahrein.No. Political Agency, Bahrain, Bated the HI June 1929. 'x Messrs Crossley Brothers, . ' Exchange Buildings, Bombay. Bear Sirs, Please supply me urgently with the following spare parts for 111 type Crossley Engine No. 82081 and send me your bill for payment. Yours faithfully, v Serial No. Name quantity \ 12. 24. / Governor S, ring 27. Grinding handle for exhaust valve 1. 119. Stud and nut for locking plate. 6. - Si rUi, K/-No. of 1929. ^7? The Political Agency, Bahrein. Bated June 1929. To The Adviser, Bahrein Government, Bahrein. % Memorandum . ; . Reference your Memorandum No.99/22, dated the 19th Maharaja 1348. I acknowledge, with thanks, the receipt of a cheque for Rs.171-15-0 ( rupees one hundred seventy one and annas fifteen only) forwarded therewith. Political Agent, Bahrein./ &gt;&lt;; ¥e thank you for your favour No. 684 of the 27th. ultimo ordering therein, some spare parts for your engine and in reply we regret to say that we have n^stock of these here as the engine being of old type we do not st#ck such parts. We have however, passed your order to our Works and on receipt of the parts we will forward them to you. / Yours faijchfully, CROSSLE'!) 1 Pele^ran- Jnclair. Ltol - Political, Id rein, io - Gas engine, dcidoay do.1183. Dated tlie 1st October 1031 lours 8th July spare parts urgently required, lease expedite. &amp; Political. Pcle^raa- Jnclair• Proa- Political, Ddirein. do - lase: pine, Bosibay. do• 1269• Dated the 15th October 1929. ly telegram 1183 first October wire if spare parts despatched, urgent. Political.&amp; nii§) cal Agency, Bahrain, the Septr. 1929. The Commandant of Police, Bahrain. I^MOMNDUM . I era sending herewith the canvas belt of the Agency electric plant. I should be obliged if you would please have it repaired as required by the bearer. for Political Agent, Bahrain.Memo No. 6 ^ 3 &gt; of 1348 Office of/the Adviser to the Government. Bahrain. Bated, 10th J/lwal, 1348 Till you kindly send me for perusal and return the corres pondence and catalogues in connection with a pair of telephones purchased recently oy you and installed between our offices? 1 like to have another set of machines and before ordering I should like to see the catalogues. adviser to the Government, Bahrain.all No. /17/7 of 1923. The Political Ageaicy, Bahrein^ Dated the j ^ iZ October 1929. To The Adviser, Bahrein State, Bahrein. Reference /our memorandum No.656/23 dated the 10th J/Avral, 1348. I forward,herewith,the correspondence and catalogues in connection with the p&lt;vir of teleiDhones purchased as requested. Kindly return when done with. ■ Indian Assistant, In the absence of Political Agent, ! Bahrein. G.II.The Political Agency, Bahrain. &gt; w Dated the^g ^November 1929. To _r The Adviser, Balirain (xovernment, Bahrain* UmznMm* Please refer to my memorandum No.1272/7/7 dated the 16th October 1929. The papers regarding telephone may please be returned, if no longer required. of Indian Assistant f Political Agent, Bahrain* I i■I mBm mm., No. I7^S Political jency, Bahrain, lated the -lechr. 1929. Messrs Crossley Brothers, 138, Medows Street, Bombay 1 Tear firs, Please sup. ly me urgently with the following sp; re parts for 111 type Crossley engine No. 3_C81 ana send, me your bill for payment. ioui’s i? i ti.iully, Political Agent, Bahrain. :erisl No. 24 4. 11 . N?me Governor Spring Bottom Governor die. Quantit/' 12 . 4. Stud for bottom Governor 4. O aiernmmmmm fIDemoranbum, IS* M CROSSLEY BROS. LTD. ENGINEERS 138, Medows Street, Fort, BOMBAY. C grams:—GASENGINE. Tele. C. phone No 24987. POST BOX No. 157. 5 tn Oct p b er , ig 2 9 To The Political Agent, BAHhAlil. (P. Gulf) Dear Sir, &amp; .&gt;3.U f 6 &amp;ns. %a v/e are in receipt of your telegtarn reading as follows ;- 'YOURS EIGHTH JULY SPaRE PARTS 'URGENTLY REQUIRED PLEASE E/HPEL1TE. ' V/e now have pleasure in advising despatch ofthe Spare Parts oy Registered Parcel Post and we enclose herewith our bill Ho.4326No. of 1929• The Political kgmcy 9 Bahrain# Dated the November 192 November 1929# To Messrs Crossley Brothers Ltd#, Engineers, 138 Medows Street, Port Bombay# Dear sirs. Reference your letter No# nil dated the !3th October 1929# A sum of Rs#19-10-0 has this day been remitted by postal money order to your address in settlement of your account• Please acknowledge receipt# Yours faithfully, ,0fIDemoranfcum, CROSSLEY BROS. LTD. ENGINEERS , j 138, Medows Street, Fort, BOMBAY. grams: —GASENGINH. Tele. phone No 24987. POST BOX No. 157. To ig)\v\V s s ^ The Political Agent,' BAHREIN Dear Sir, \7e 'beg to remind you of our 'bill No. 4326 for 19. jO. l . and x’equest the favour of your cheque at an early dateflDemoraitfcum, CROSSLEY BROS. LTD. ENGINEERS 2.5.th. No..v.em.her.., 7 £2 ...9.... 0 The Political Agent, BAHRAIN. 138, Medows Street, Fort, BOMBAY. C grams:—GASENGINK Tele. ^ ( phone No 24987. POST BOX No. 157. if*/ — '^-\Z 'QT^ajP?^ Dear Sir, &gt;■ /7S5 ' f V c l &gt; 1?, We beg to acknowledge with thanks, receipt of your money order for R s 19.10.0. in full payment of our bill No.4326. Our official receipt is sent herewith. Yours faithfully, CROSSLEt/ElROTHSRS LTD. MB. ;anTEUEPHONE NO. 24225 REGISTERED TELEG RAMS: ‘ * K I LOWATT * * e \ '^ HEAD OFFICE 14. OLD COURT HOUSE STREET. CALCUTTA. BRANCHES trademark 100, ARMENIAN STREET, MADRAS. CODES USED ; COLE &amp; PRIVATE AFFILIATED WITH THE GENERAL ELECTRIC Co., LTD. “MAGNET HOUSE.” KINGSWAY. LONDON, W. C. 2. The General Eleetric De Franee, Ltd. The General Eleetrie Co. of China, Ltd; The British General Eleetric Co., Ltd., Australia. The British General Eleetrie Co., Ltd., S. Africa. The Anglo-Argentine General Electric Co., Ltd. CL112/R, WORKS &amp; ASSOCIATED MANUFACTURING COMPANIES: 30. THE MALL. LAHORE- THE MALL. CAWNPORE. “SOHRAB HOUSE,” HORNBY ROAD, FORT, (Post Box No. 86 i) BOMBAY. 24th January, 193' HEAVY ENGINEERING, GENi~ ATORS, MOTORS, SWITCHGEAR, FANS, PRIMARY BATTERIES, carbons, MOULDED INSULATION, Witton, near Birmingham. Dear Sirs* G.E.C.British made, D«C. fans Velocity Pattern,, vie attach leaflet Vo4S26 illustrating and TURBINES, BLOWERS, COMPRESSORS, CONVEYING &amp; MINING PLANT, Fraser &amp; chaimers Engineering works, jgiving a brief specification of our V. 30 5 5P fan 'which Erith, Kent. “ OSRAM ” LAMPS, “ROBERTSON ” LAMPS, “OSRAM” WIRELESS VALVES, Hammersmith, London. ELECTRIC LIFTS. Express Lift Co., Ltd., London. WIRES &amp; CABLES, Pirelli-General Cable Works, Ltd., Southampton. GLASS WORKS, Lemington-on-Tyne &amp; Wembley. HEATING &amp; COOKING Birmingham. INSTRUMENTS &amp; METERS, Salford Electrical Instruments, Ltd. Manchester. Chamberlain &amp; Hookham, Ltd., . Birmingham. TELEPHONE &amp; WIRELESS APPARATUS, Coventry &amp; Manchester. ART METAL FITTINGS, Birmingham. CONDUIT &amp; ACCESSORIES. Birmingham &amp; West Bromwich. SIEMENS &amp; GENERAL ELECTRIC RAILWAY SIGNAL CO., LTD. marks the very latest practice in fan design,. This fan has heen developed to give the maximum physiological cooling 'affect by providing a concentrated breeze over a relatively restricted area. Particular attention has been paid to both the electrical and mechanical design, and a total displacement of over 15,000 cu.ft 0 per minute is obtained with a very low power consumption,. Automatic oil lubrication is provided on similar lines to that incorporated in our well-known Swan Patent fan, and all windings are specially impregnated to withstand climatic conditions. We are offering this fan at the very attractive price of Rs.90/- complete with down-rod and 'AKVOR' regulator and trust that when you are in the market for fans, this offer will receive your consideration. Yours faithfully, THE GENERAL ELECTRIC CO.(INDIA) LTD„ WATSON &amp; SONS ( Electro-Medical ) LTD. # a e. c. RESEARCH LABORATORIES, Wembley, Middlesex. EnclOo Leaflet V.4926 TA'See: your guarantee.. • .V. .v,lfe4yiiiv4)sH8ssli Iili 'jj;- flDemoranbum, CROSSLEY BROS. LTD. ENGINEERS To 138, Medows Street, C grams:—GASENGINE. Tele. 5 (. phone No 24987. POST BOX No. 157. Zth.» January,. . . ; The Political Agency, -r r &gt;B)aiRAXN Fort, BOMBAY. ,' 0-0 (P/ Gulf) . r*/t«c. /' ] V^P 15,4 *' Dear Sirs, P.lll No. 82081. We thank you for your favour No, 1765 of the 25th, ultimo ordering therein some Spare Parts for the above Engine. We regret we have none of the parts ordered, in stock hut we have at once passed your order to our Works asking them to send the parts as early as possible and on receipt of same we will forward them to you.flDemoranbum, With further reference to our letter of the 7th January» we have pleasure in advising despatch of the Jpare Parts for the above engine by parcel post and enclose herewith our hill No.480^ amounting to lis. 36/10/- only. Yours faithful GR03 3According to your oruer I went to the dace referred to in the attached letter. X The telephone line runs as shown in the attached sketch. The property of Ahmad al Muaiyad lies between ”A M &amp; 'B' ana tne tele phone line passes over the roof of the build- in^from 'A” ( a pole fixed to the ground about 15 feet XExi away from the kestern wall of Ahmad’s property) to B ( a wooden block about three feet high^ which is fixed to the top eage of the buildingj. ihe line then crosses over the road to G and Q and finally passes on to the Telegraph office. Ahmad wants the Mce between A and B removed together with the block at B to en able him to erect new building on the top of the present one* 18.3.30 k / d/j n ^ ‘ -V . ■ /V LI * M / a ,- i- . -**% i it-m No. / 7 f 2 - Political Ajency, Balirain. Dated the 30th December, 1930. ! Phe Resident Engineer, ressrs. Callenders Cable &amp; Construction Co*,Ltd*, Bahrain. Dear Sir, I forward herewith a Supply Bill for Rs.4430-15-0 in settlement of the undernoted bills:- i Bill Dated 3-10-30 for Rs. 4300-0-0 ditto — for Rs . 130-15-Q Total Rs.% *. 4430—15—0 Will you please send me separate receipts, in duplicate, for both the bills. The bills referred to are hereto attached. Yours faithfully t $ Political Agent, Bahrain.CALLENDER’S CABLE &amp; CONSTRUCTION COMPANY, LIMITED. Head office For India Forbes building. Home Street, Fort, BOMBAY. Engineers, Cable Manufacturers 8c Contractors, RESIDENT ENGINEER’S OFFICE. Bahrain BW/872 DEC* 51th 1950 E.B.M. POLITICAL AGMT BAHRAIN Bear Sir, I have to acknowledge receipt of your Supply Bill for Rs 44^0/0/0 in payment of our Invoices Nos m/m ?, BN/l8l a dated ?rd October 1950, for which I thank you. The invoices in question are herewith returned duly receipted.No. 10 of 19301. Political Agency, Bahrain, the 6 th January 1931. The Bahrain Government Electric Supply Department, eight annas and the amount of current should be deducted from and n 6 t added to the main total, as it has already run through that meter. Also neither heater shows more than 8 units.in all. Please also see the office bill to which these remarks apply equally. BAHRAIN. Memorandum . Please refer to the attached bill. It is not understood what the third column refers to. If it is a heater it is not debitable at Political Agent, BahrainBAH MU! * V /3C/ C&gt; THH BAHMTH GOTEOTHHT HL^CTETC SUPPLY BEPAHTMEITT Dec. 7th 1930 H.B.M. Political Agent 0 Bahrain ^ ' 4ith reference to your letter Ho 10 dated 6th January 1930, I herewith return your meter cards, on which you will note I have explained the purpose of each meter. The readings, I think, you will iind correct. I shall he pleased to give you any further information.Political Agency, Bahrain, the 12th January 1931. The Resident Engineer, Bahrain Government Electric Supply Corporation, Me morandum . Please refer to your letter N 0 .B 6/6 dated the 7th December 1930 (presumably the 7th January 1931). I would be glad if a separate card could be prepared in future for the Head Clerk. BAH RAIN. Political Agent, Bahrain.No. (sty /17/7. Political /igency, Bahrain. Dated the 18th January, 1930. The Resident Engineer, Messrs. Callender’s Cable c Construction Co.,Ltd., Bahrain. Bear Sir, I have to refer to your letter No.BW/832 of the 31st ultimo and to enclose, herewith, a receipt in duplicate which I should be glad if you would sign and return to me, in support of the charge in my accounts. The receipted bill, in tins connection, which accom panied your letter under reference, is herewith returned. Yours faithfully, a Political Agent, Bahrain.tn% H&gt;AD OFFIC* FOR INDIA Forbes building. Home Street. Fort. BOMBAY. Callender’s cable a construction company, limited. Engineers. Cable Manufacturers &amp; Contractors. RESIDENT ENGINEER’S OFFICE. BAHRAIN BG/5-2 Bear Sir, I have pleasure in enclosing herewith a stamped receipt a or Bg. 4430/15/0 (Sapees four thousand, four hundred, and thirty, annas fifteen only), this amount being in payment of our invoice No. BM/181.ies- defrosting has been done in dach 24 hours as the current is £/ switched off at night* The booklet was found long ago behind refigeration and carefully followed* Id. E.G* 30/8.TELEPHONE No. 24225 ft TELEGRAMS: ••KILOWATT” Codes Used : COLE &amp; PRIVATE AFFILIATED WITH THE GENERAL ELECTRIC CO.. LTD. “MAGNET HOUSE.” KINGSWAY. LONDON. W. C. 2. AND The General Electric De France, Ltd. The General Electric Co. of China, Ltd. The British General Electric Co., Ltd., Australia. The British General Electric Co., Ltd., S. Africa. The Anglo-Argentine General Electric Co., Ltd. KAISER-I-HIND BUILDING, BALLARD ESTATE, (Post Box No. 861) BOMBAY. 14. OLD COURT HOUSE STREET CALCUTTA. BRANCHES MOUNT ROAD. MADRAS. 30. THE MALL. LAHORE. THE MALL. CAWNPORE. 5. SOUTH PARADE. BANGALORE. McLEOD ROAD, KARACHI. MAIN ROAD. TRIVANDRUM. 5,25. AVANASHI ROAD. COIMBATORE. RANGOON OFFICE;- STEWART RAEBURN &amp; COMPANY 57. LEWIS STREET. WORKS &amp; ASSOCIATED. MANUFACTURING COMPANIES: .VY ENGINEERING. GENERATORS. MOTORS, SWITCHGEAR, FANS, PRIMARY BATTERIES, CARBONS. MOULDED INSULATION, Witton, near Birmingham. TURBINES, BLOWERS. COMPRESSORS. CONVEYING &amp; MINING PLANT Fraser &amp; Chalmers Engineering Works Kef. CL/OS/SG/? Erith, Kent, I '©SRAM' LAMPS, “ROBERTSON’’ LAMPS. “OSRAM” WIRELESS VALVES Hammersmith, London. ELECTRIC LIFTS, Express Lift Co., Ltd. London. WIRES &amp; CABLES Pirelli-General Cable Works, Ltd. Southampton. Lear Sir f T2IXIC3D PRICES OF , OSRAM , G.3.C, BRITISH H4LE HM?$ - STANDARD IISHTISTG TYB3S . Ve have great pleasure In enclosing herewith a copy of our revised pricelist of ‘Ceram 1 Vacuum and Gasfilled Lamps which comes into force on the 15th inst. GLASS WORKS, Lamington-on-Tyne &amp; Wembley. HEATING &amp; COOKING. Birmingham. INSTRUMENTS &amp; METERS, ^^Nrd Electrical Instruments, Ltd., Manchester. Chamberlain &amp; Hookham Ltd., Birmingham. TELEPHONE &amp; WIRELESS APPARATUS, Coventry &amp; Manchester. ART METAL FITTINGS, Birmingham. CONDUIT &amp; ACCESSORIES. Birmingham &amp; West Bromwich. SIEMENS &amp; GENERAL ELECTRIC RAILWAY SIGNAL CO.. LTD. WATSON &amp; SONS (Electro-Medical) LTD. G. E. C. RESEARCH LABORATORIES. Wembley.Middlesex. You will see that the prices of the Standard lighting types have been considerably reduced and we trust that this reduction will result in us being favoured with your valued orders for Gsram Lamps - which, you are no doubt aware, are manufactured at the well-equipped Osram Lamp Works in accordance with the strict regulations of the British Sngineering Standards Association Specification iJo.161 - 1932* The Pearl Osrams with their many advantages can be had at the same prices as the corresponding clear types* MCI. Yours faithfully, Por and on behalf of TH3 GBinRAL 3L3CTRIC CO. (INDIA) LD. Branch Manage USE 'OSRAM’ LAMPS TOR T'OU’OT LI GMT AT MINIMUM COST. TheS.c.e ~ your guarantee.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000157_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1608</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000157</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1608</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 17/7 Electric Installation – E. Engine spare parts &amp; Use of current in the Agency Buildings – Telephones.'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1926/1933</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-01-07T18:04:45</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (182 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 184; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 4-170; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file concerns the supply of electrical goods, engine parts, and other mechanical devices to the Political Agency, Bahrain. It includes correspondence with electrical and engineering companies, as well as memoranda, invoices, receipts, product brochures, and price lists.Correspondents include: the Political Agent, Bahrain; Crossley Brothers Ltd; the General Electric Company (not to be confused with the United States company, General Electric); William Jacks and Co; Charles Dalrymple Belgrave, Adviser to the Government of Bahrain.The file also contains a letter addressed to the Political Agent, Bahrain, from a Bahraini resident who requests that the telephone wires connecting the Political Agency to the wireless station, which run across the roof of his property, be removed.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>William Jacks and Co</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>General Electric Company</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Crossley Brothers Ltd</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Engines</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Adviser to the Government of Bahrain</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Electrical equipment</topic></subject><subject><topic>Telephone</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000157#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>