<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100024051548.0x000005_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T01:11:13.190Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100024051548.0x000005_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/132, ff 8-11</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100024051548.0x000005</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/132, ff 8-11</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Letter No. 7 of 1852 from Captain Arnold Burrowes Kemball, Resident in the Persian Gulf, at Bushire to Arthur Malet, Chief Secretary to the Government, Secret Department, Bombay</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1852/1852</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-10-15T00:32:27</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>4 folios</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The letter is reporting that the Resident has discovered a discrepancy in the expiry date in the Treaty for Maritime Truce 1843; the 'English date' indicates June 1853, while the 'Mahomedan [Mohammedan] date' indicates February 1853. It explains that as all the parties — with the exception of Abdulla ben Rashid, Chief of Amulgavine [Umm al-Qaywayn] — have indicated they desire for its provisions to be continued, the Resident has addressed letters to each signatory requesting they recognise the 'English' date. It is noted that the Resident fears that if the treaty is allowed to lapse, some parties may use the opportunity afforded to attack another; he therefore believes that the re-establishment of the truce is a matter of urgency.Enclosed is a copy of a communication from the Resident to Shaikh Sultan ben Suggur [Sulṭān bin Saqr], Chief of Rusul Khymah [Ra's al-Khaymah], dated 16 September 1852.The enclosure concerns the discrepancy found in the expiry date for the Treaty of Maritime Truce 1843. It urges him to adopt the interpretation of June 1853 to avoid confusion, and to record his formal acquiescence to the continued operation of the agreement. It further solicits his opinion on whether he favours the renewal of the existing treaty, or its replacement with another in lieu.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100024051548.0x000005#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>