<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000555.0x0002e5_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-20T08:21:11.210Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">■■■■ICS . ''fr . &lt;1 file copr Ho. F. 156-F/38. From The Secretary to the Government of India in the External /vffairs Departnent, To The Under Secretary of State for India, Political Department, India Office. c Dated Hew Delhi, the // February 1939. Liability of the Government of India in respect of the sale of 1914 pattern rifles to the Afghan Government. Sir, 7ith reference to the correspondence ending with the letter from the India Office No. P.2.-8170/38, dated the 12th January 1939, I am directed to state that in the circumstances explained the Government of India agree to the Army Council being informed as proposed in para graph 2 of your letter under reply. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant.The Secretary to the Groveminent of India, External Affairs Dept., New Delhi. Subject : Liability of the Government of India in respect of the sale of 1914 pattern rifles to the Afghan Government. Sir, With reference to your letter No. F.1 56 -F /38 of 3rd December, 1938, on the above subject, I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to explain that the agreement between c Messrs. Soley and the War Office was »*«*■» • 2 ” i / b ''*w paragraph (2) ^ / V . r n # of^Memorandum B^enclosed in Hr Walton*s demi-official letter No. tL P.Z.8784/35 of 16th January, 1936X-^ \*+*Sl***. i/ bt. £ tX A? whioh yoforonoo io -ffiado in yonr' mb’ ^ £ f • 0 . i, A* j ) lott-e-r^&lt;. 'fcak error wao ho^yevc-^ % t i, y—^ S+Cj corrected in the last paragraph of the Treasury letter of 29th February, 1936 , a copy of which was forwarded with Mr. Walton*s demi-official letter of 2nd March, 1938, No. P.Z.773/36. From this it will be seen that the arrangement with Messrs. Soley was to the effect that the latter would be willing to share equally with His Majesty 1 s Government in any payments made by the Afghan Government as and when received up to the total due to the firm of 10/ / - in respect of each rifle (i.e. instead of/ (8610) Wt.25956/286 10,000 0/88 A.&amp;E.W.Ltd. Gp.685of insisting on full payment being made to them by the War Office as soon as the rifles were despatched to the Afghan Government). Reference is also invited to paragraph 4 of India Office letter No. P.Z. 3558/37 of 10th June, 1537 to the War Office, a copy of which was forwarded with this department's weekly letter No. 24 dated 17 th June, 1937* The arrangement with Messrs. Soley was applied in the first instance to the 10,000 rifles which it was originally proposed to sell to the Afghan Government but was later extended to cover the whole of the 25&gt;000 rifles eventually supplied. 2. If the Government of India see no objection, the Secretary of State accordingly proposes to inform the Army Council in reply to the War Office letter of 9th August, 1938, a- oopy of wfci-Qh wag forwardod with this department's, air mail letter Net-33 dated- 16 th-Auguot ■laQ'fr that he confirms that the position regarding the Government of India's liability in the event of an Afghan default is as stated in the War Office letter.FILE COPY £ 170 ; From rfl&amp;u j 41 ' X 0 .? .±X&gt;-V/Q ,1953 j To The Secretary to the Grovemment of India in the External Affairs Departfaont, His Majesty’s Under Secretary of State for India, Political Department, India Office, London. Dated New Delhi, the ?&gt; ^December 1938. Sir, I am directed to refer to the War Office letter No. P.Z.o60o/36, dated the 9th August 1938 on the subject of the liability of the Grovemment of India in respect of the 1914 pattern rifles which have been sold to the Government of Afghanistan. 2. It is stated at the end of paragraph 2 of the letter under reference thst the amount of the contin ent liability in question at present stands at 18/- shillings a rifle, on four-sixths of 25,000 rifles, namely Z 15,000. The Government of India are unable to accept this figure without further question in view of what is st; ted in paragraph (2) of Memorandum B forwarded with i r. Dalton’s demi-official letter No. P.2. 8784/35, dated the 16th January 1936 (Of. the concluding sentence of the letter from the Government of India in the External Affairs Department, No.F.320-F/34, dated the 20th I ay 1937). This statement is to the effect that 'it is understood that L essrs. • • •- 2 - I essra. Soley have now agreed to accept 50 percent of the amount due to them out of any payments made by the Afghans as and when received 1 *. It would appear from this that if the Afghans default in any payment the out-of- pocket expenditure incurred by the V»ar Office under their agreement with Messrs. Soley will be only 5 s. per rifle and not 10 s. This makes their total out-of-pocket expendi ture in respect of each rifle, in the event of such default, 13 s. instead of 18 s. The Government of India consider their liability should not exceed this figure in which case their contingent liability at present on four-sixths of 25,000 rifles would amount to only £ 10,833 instead of £ 15,000. I am to request that the Government of India may kindly be informed vhether this figure is accepted. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant, 3d/- H.A.F.Metcalfe, Secretary to the Government of India.vt* &amp; s i Tel. No.— Whitehall 9400. Any further communication on this subject should be addressed to :— l he Under-Secretary of State. The War Office, London, S.W.l and the following number quoted. FILE GORY v ‘ « Q) 04/6260 (M.G.O.P.a.) 6) Sir, THE WAR OFFICE, LONDON, S.W.l. Cj JkJL . August, 1938, I am .commanded 'by the Army Council to refer to f your letter Lo. T.z.3558/37 d ated 10th June, 1937, on the * subject of the liability of the Government of. India in respect of the 1914 pattern rifles which have been sold to the Government of Afghanistan. (o 2. The Council note that the Government of India accept the position that they are bound by the agreement recorded in paragraph 6 of India Office letter ho. P.Z.1674/36 to the War Office of 11th April, 1936, and the iYar Oi'fice reply No. 0 1 64/ 6260(F. 1.) dated 25th Aprils under which in the case of an Afghan default the Government of India’s Afghan Reserve Fund would be liable for the out-of-pocket expenditure of the War Office in respect of that proportion of the rifles for which the purchase price had not already been received from the Afghan Government at the time of default. In this connection I am to observe that since the Afghan Government have now paid for two-sixths of the total quantity of 25,000 rifles and since the out-of-pocket expenses were reduced by the omission of the firing test, the amount of the contingent liability in question at present stands at 18/- a rifle, on four-sixths of 25,000 rifles, namely £15,000. 3 3. With reference to paragraph 3 of your letter, the Council note that the Government of India are not prepared, except on terms which the Council are unable to accept, to undertake the liability to refund to the War Office their out-of-pocket expenses in any given financial year, in so far as these out-of- pocket expenses The Under Secretary of State cannot/ — .... for India, LObUfi: IN AIR MAIL LETTER -4j ;&lt;E8». WL. KPT. 10 AUG 1938 'olitical Department, ^ JA India Office, V S • W • 1. INDIA OFFICE ^'To z. r 2 Itz cannot be met from payments from circumstances the Council do not matter further. They understand cable ho. 1179* dated 3rd June of to the War Office with Mr. dated 5th June, 1936, that 'A Afghanistan. In the proi'tose- to press this from Government of India’s which a copy was forv/arded WaLton’s semi-official letter the Government of India will 2 pay to the War Office within any financial year in which the Afghanistan Government is in default on an instalment for that year a sum of £3,750,representing one-sixth of the total out-of-pocket expenses at the rate of 18/- per. rifle. - . 4 5 They unders tanding. would be glad to have confirmation of this f / 5 trcro / + &lt;1 4. In reply to paragraph 4 of your letter, I am to state that the agreement described in that paragraph was applied to the full number of 25,000 rifles. Payment of the full amount of £12,500 due under the agreement was completed on receipt from Afghanistan of the second instalment of the purchase, price of the rifles. Accordingly the agreement cannot oper ite to reduce the amount of out- of-pocket expenses for which the Afghan Reserve Fund is contingently liable. 5. In conclusion, I am to express regret that the foregoing reply has been delayed. A copy of it has been sent to the Foreign Office and the Treasury. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, for Permanent Under-Secretary of State*if 6008 Wt 8322—P 8 1000 + 3000 4.37 It is requested that in any further communi cation on this subject the under-mentioned letter and number may be quoted, and the reply 1 addressed to — The Under Secretary of State for India, Political Department, f\ . India Office, - ! 3558/37. s '' r ' '' LONDON, S.W. 1. p&gt; 0 . **■ 6th January, 1938. 'A' Jir, With reference to India Office letter, No. x J . 3558/37, of 10th June, 1937, regarding tie liability of the Government of India in respect of the sale of 1914 pattern rifles to the Afghan Government, i am directed by the Secretary of 3tate for India to enquire whether a reply may now be expected at an early date. , Copies of this letter are being sent to the Treasury and to the Foreign Office, I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, (Sgd.) G.E. CR0LIBIE. The Under uecretary of Jtate. WAR OFFICE, G.W. 1. f enclosure in ^ MA)L l . t , - ! No - : i “S' I. ^ ■ POLITICAL and 1 »EPI. ,,D jADraft Paper 5 r _ I 0 political Department. ^HAFT LETTER. U.S. of S., War Office. 2 4 1 ^ ,JUN ,937 saWETARY, Ai-,0 SSOilEr DEPT. INDIA 0 F J ICE ^ b€xQ. dao'- ^^U.VA^ i-jOsa\^ 'kckWi ~1 5973 5000 3.37 itrfL ivi Sir , I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to refer to the correspondence resting with India Office letter No.P.Z. 7217/36 of 26th October 1936^ regarding the liability of the Government of India in respect of the 1914 pattern rifles which have been sold to the Afghan Government. As a result of correspondence on this question between the Government of India and the India Office^the Government of India have reached the following conclusions^which have the concurrence of the Secretary of State for India. 2. The Government of India accept the position that they are bound by the agreement recorded in para.6 of India Office letter No.P.Z.1674/36 to the War Office of 11th April 1936, and the War Office reply No.0164/6260(F.1) of 25th lAe Uu'ij ^hI: April , under i n-io 7t^.o Flut£ In d iate t-iffbilityjin the case of an — Afghan default would be—l-imitcc to the War Office’s out of pocket expenditure in respect of that proportion of the rifles for v/hich the purcha.se price had not already been received from the Afghan Government at the time of such default. 3. The Government of India are not prepared to accept^**^ addition to the liability/liability defined in para.2 above the further liability which it is understood CouxCcV. the f f fiod^ wish them to assumej They- spy that the excess of the War Office’s out of pocket expenses in a given financial year over any payment received from the Afghan Government in that year should be covered by an advance from the Government of India’s Afghan Peserve Fund subject to recovery by that Fund as further Afghan instalments are received in excess of the War Office’s out of pocket expenditure. / G oycrryr.&amp;nt—e-f -In dim a r a , h ow o v a prepared * to make adVrance payments in the manner I Co 'A.vv. suggested the Way Gfoon their part are willing to modify the agreement referred to in para.2 of this letter^ in a way which would limit the Government of India’s liability in the event of an Afghan default to such proportion^if any^ of the out of pocket expenses in respect of the whole number of rifles as was not covered by payments received from the Afghan Government at the time of their default. I am to enquire whether the Army Council are willing to accept this suggestion. 4. As regards the amount of the War Office’s out of pocket expenditure^ it is understood that an agreement was reached between the War Office and Messrs.Soley in respect of the 10,000 1914 pattern rifles which it was originally/ y r — '’ir&amp;.e. CCocT'' &lt;L© m.S\t o*- vv c r OSw* b-Q. ^ -^&gt;vSv«x us*. o a\'o_ [Z C v'o as L ^ sv a \ ^ V‘ S UV'Q. T«.c.e\:vQ.i. vw e^rz-ess yoxvceV' ^ ' -^voo-x' 6-e J mSSSKammDraft Paper. Department. r [yiU SCr&lt;l n-f.uiiiWoA originally proposed to sell to the Afghan Government whereby the Company expressed their willingness to accept 5C per cent (up to £5,C00) of any payment made by the Afghan Government as and when received by the War Officer I am to enquire whether this agreement is -mLITT operative in respect of the 25,COO rifles which were eventually sold to the Afghan Government. A cS s P'^€\BY AIR MAIL . C0NFID3NTIAL . r vv U \J U No*F.320-F/34* From .. /. v &lt;? ^ c A^ r To The Secretary to the G-overnment of India in the External Affairs Department, His Majesty^ Under Secretary of State for India, Political Department, India Office, London# * Dated Simla, the 3o May 1937. Liability of the Government of India in respect of the sale of 1914 pattern rifles to the Afghan Government. •«• •. Sir, With reference to your letter No.P.Z.9150/; dated the 1st February 1937, I am directed to state that 9 the Government of India welcome the proposal in paragraph 3 thereof as affording a chance of modifying an agreement which they consider to be manifestly inequitable, and which they would not have accepted had its full implications been appreciated earlier. Although the Government of India reluctantly accept the position that they are committed to this agreement (whereby their liability in the event of an Af S lian default extends to the out of pocket expenditure in respect of rifles not paid for at the time of default) and cannot alter it in the direction indicated in their ^' v !&gt; letter NO.F.320-F/34, dated the 5th December 1936, without the concurrence of the War Office, they would favour any action which secures that concurrence* - f2 The suggestion by the War Office that the excess of their out-of-pocket expenses in a given financial year over any payment received from the Afghans in that year should be covered by an advance from the Afghan Reserve Fund would have amounted in 1936-37 to a further mortgaging of that Fund to an amount of about a lakh of rupees for what appears to be a mere technical convenience of His Majesty’s Government* Hie Groverament of India do not consider that this is a proper use for their fund, but would be prepared to accept the suggestion provided that the War Office agree that the ultimate liability on the Afghan Reserve Fund will be limited to so much of the out-of-pocket expenses in respect of the whole number of rifles as has not been covered by payments received from the Afghans. I am to add that although from paragraph (2) of Memorandum B forwarded with Mr. ihlton's demi-official letter No.8784/35, dated the 16th January 1936, it seems probable that the out of pocket expenses to the War Office amount only to 15s. 6d. per rifle, yet the charge to the Fund in respect of such out of pocket expenses has been fixed at £ 1. 0. 6 per rifle and that this already allows a sufficient margin of profit to the War Office. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant Secretary to the Government of India.V &amp; Ms H BY AIR MIT. . Ceml official No. 824. f' I QO-J II w/ O 1 ® , ^ _ Britjish Legation, Kabul i. ! y / j ■V...,.,— —-Qth March, 1957, (Ij Jttu * * / 7 &lt;y0 I regret the delay in answering your letter P.Z.9150/36 dated 1st February, 1937 which was received here when I was in India, 2. I have already dealt with the question of publicity, when discussing the proposal for credits, vide my telegram No. 14 ela ted 9th February 1937. The position is I think much the same in the case of arms, now under reference. It is as well to avoid publicity if possible in connection with our transactions with Afghanistan, but if it is unavoidable I do not think much damage will be done The fact that the Afghan Government is buying arms from His Maiesty»s Government is public property and has been so for some time, and the publication of the details of the transaction are not likely to cause much embarrassment in Kabul. j X. CL' &gt; J.C.’A'alton, Esq., CB.,MC., India Office, London. EN(V r • V Aim MAIL LETTER \ 3 lc,b'wlAR1957 ■ •!. A* 1 v.Register No. P. Z. 915C/3( SECRET. v\v POLITICAL DEPARTMENT. ^- r _ from . * 3 grani Dated liec. Formally acknowledged 19 Date. Initials. SUBJECT. Chairman Under Secretary.. Secretary of State Committee Under Sectary Secretarf of State. Mov'^cw *bg\pV:. . 1 4 ^ ip:* AFGHANISTAN. Sale of 25,000 1914 pattern rifles to the Afghan Government from War Office stocks. Question of the Government of India’s financial liability in respect of this transaction. Copy of to FOR USE BY DEPARTMENTS ONLY. Previous Papers :— 1742b 500 3.33Minute Paper. political Department. In connection with the sale of 25,000 1914 pattern rifles from the War Office’s surplus stocks, the India Office agreed with the Treasury and the War Office that the Government of India should undertake a liability in the event of an Afghan default for the out of pocket expenditure (commission to Messrs.Soley, cost of inspection packing^and freight) in respect of rifles not wholly paid f or at the time of the default . This meant that any of the six annual instalments due from the Afghans received before a default occurred would be regarded as having paid entirely for a proportion of the rifles at £3:5:6 Uaa. fruA-okas-i. fyuxx. /w* y- ^ per rifle^ having paid off i-^-whole or pg.rt the -*Vw* out-of-pocket expenditure on^all^the rifles at £1:0:6 per rifle. In accepting this arrangement, which was part of our general agreement with the Treasury regarding specil\ expenditure on Afghanistan, we believed that we had the concurrence of the Government of India. When, however, we consulted the Government of India on a further request made by the War Office that they should receive their out- of-pocket expenses in the same financial year as that in which.they are incurred, the Government of India, while ready to meet this new request, have objected to the old one. It is clear from their letter of 5th December that they do not realise that a definite agreement was reached on the point. 2. A draft letter to the Government of India explaining the situation and suggesting the reply which, if they agree, we might give to the War Office, is attached. 3. If the War Office’s new request is not met the transaction with the Afghans will necessarily come before the Public Accounts Committee, and hence it may receive publicity. There seems no objection to thiso^'5^Minute Paper. Department. r-' 4795 The misunderstanding which has arisen with the G. of I. relates to a point which will not arise at all unless and until there is an Afghan default on one of the six instalments of the purchase price of the rifles. But since it exists, we had better clear it up. The War Office are making a profit from their sale to the Afghans, and have always stipulated that, if a default should occur; they should be allowed to keep that part of the profit which they had already made. On the other hand, they conceded that, in the event of such default, they would not claim from the G. of I.'s fund (which has been set up for the purpose of financing this and similar transactions) the whole of the purchase price, including profit, due to them m respect of that proportion of the rifles which had not already been covered by Afghan payments; in respect of such outstanding payments they agreed to claim only their out-of-pocket expenses from the G. of I.’s fund. We agreed to this arrangement, which at any rate definitely limits the G. of I.'s liability to small amounts, which will diminish as Afghan instalments come in. On the other hand, we are not m any way committed to the new request which has been made by the | W.O. that the G. of I. should, so far as necessary, finance their out-of-pocket expenses in the financial year m which they are incurred. This is a new idea which has occurred to the W.O. recently as a means of avoiding any charge on the W.O. vote. The G. of I. could meet this request quite cheaply, and, if the W.O. attach sufficient importance to it, they might possibly be willing to revise the existing agreement in a manner which would meet the 5000 5/56 G. of I.'s views in regard to it.- - —Draft Paper. P.Z.9150/36. Department. SECRET AIR L1AIL . Sir, -1 FEB 1957 The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, Foreign and Political Department, NEW DELHI. v-0 - \ $ &amp; P.Z.3399/36. ^ ■ 0 - Is. S' Cs 5000 lo.ae I am directed by the Secretary of State to refer to your letter, NO.F.320-F/34 of 5th December, regarding the Government of India’s liability in respect of the sale of 1914 pattern rifles to the Afghan Government. The Secretary of State’s agreement with the Treasury and the War Office for the sale of these rifles provided, as was stated in India Office telegram No.1552 of 19th May, 1936, for the limitation of the Government of India’s liability in the event of an Afghan default to the out-of-pocket expenditure incurred in respect of rifles not paid for at the time of the default. The Secretary of State notes, however, from paragraph 1 of your letter that the Government of India have hitherto not appreciated that this arrangement constituted a definite agreement under which the liability of the Government of India's Afghan Reserve Fund in the case of a default would be limited to the War Office’s out-of-pocket expenses, but in res_ect only of that proportion of the rifles for which the purchase price had not already been received from the Afghan Government at the time of such default. e./ 5319c2* It is regretted that this misunderstanding should have arisen. The War Office have throughout these negotiations stipulated that they should receive their purchase price in full for the rifles so long as, and to the extent to which, instalments of payment are forthcoming from the Afghan Government; but, in order to limit the Government of India*s liability for further payments if and when a default should occur, they were ready to agree that this liability for payments outstanding at the time of the default should be limited to that part of such outstanding payments which represents the out-of-pocket expenses of the War Office, and should not extend to the whole of the purchase price. The agreement in this sense which was reached with the Treasury is contained in paragraphs 2 and 4 of the memorandum B which was communicated to the Treasury, read with the last paragraph of Mr, Barlow*s letter of 29th February, 1936 (copies of which were enclosed with my demi-official letters to Sir A. Metcalfe of 16th January, P.3.8784/35, and 2nd March, P.Z.773/36, respectively). In the former of these documents it was stated that “It is hoped that it willDepartment be agreed that in the event of a default the amount of the indemnity (and of the consequent charge to the fund) should be limited to the out-of-pocket expenditure in respect of rifles not paid for at the time of the default, or even to the amount of the expenditure which had not been covered by the payments already received from the Afghans, as otherwise His Majesty's Government would in effect be making a profit at the expense of the Government of India's fund 1 ’. Mr. Barlow's reply agreed only to the adoption of the first of these alternatives. It is regretted that the point was not explicitly stated in the telegram No. 1056 which was sent on 25th March with reference to these papers. The agreement reached on the point was again expressed in the India Office letter to the War Office of 11th April and the War Office reply of 25th April, copies of which were sent to the Government of India by mail of 7th May under India Office Nos. P.Z.1674 and 2877/36. 3. There can of course be no question of withdrawing, without the concurrence of the War Office, from this agreement. It will be observed, however (vide my letter of 16th July, Do./No.P.Z.4876/36), that the War Office, being anxious to recover their out-of- pocket expenses in the same financial year as that in which they are incurred, have put forward an additional request (outside the agreement arrived at which deals only with the hypothetical case of an Afghan default). The new suggestion made by the War Office is that the excess of their out-of-pocket expenses in a given financial year over any payment received from the Afghans in that year should be covered by an advance from the Government of India’s fund. The Secretary of State would be willing, if the Government of India agree, and subject to any observations which His Majesty’s Minister at Kabul might have to offer, to inform the War Office that the Government of India can either undertake the liability already agreed upon in the event of an Afghan default, or can undertake to make advance payments in the manner suggested (subject to refund as further Afghan instalments are received), on the understanding that their ultimate liability will be limited to such proportion, if any, of the out-of- pocket expenses in respect of the whole number of rifles as was not covered by payments received from the/Paper. Department. fS the Afghans. I am to enquire whether the Government of India agree to this proposal. (Sd.) J. C. WALTO»-Draft Paper. Department 5319c 5000 10.;.6 decline/ Lt.Ool. W* K. Fraser-Tytler* CMG., MC. , Minister* British Legation* KABUL. V7ill you please refer to the 1.0. letter to the Q. of I* of 29th October* 1936* P.Z. 7217/36* and previous correspondence regarding the question of 1 the liability of the G. of I. in respect of the \7. 0. rifles* which are being sold to the Afghan Govt. * if the latter should default? I enclose copy of a letter dated 3th December received from the G. of I. You will see that one of the points in this complicated case is that the W.0. desire to recover their out-of- pocket expenses each year in the same financial year as that in which they falling on the W.O. vote. They therefore ask that* in addition to the G. of I’s liability in the event of an Afghan to make from the Afglian reserve fund any advance payment necessary to cover the difference betv/een the V,’. 0. * s out- of-pocket expenses in a given year and the amount which they receive from the Afghans in that year* A point on which we w mid like to consult you is this. The G* of I. might ^ ^t-0- Jt ^ and of the letter which we have sent to them in reply. are incurred* in order to avoid a charge default* the G* of !• should undertakedecline to accede to the additional request made 'by the W. 0. » unless the latter v/ere willing to revise the existing agreement, which the G* of I. do not like, in regard to liability in the event of a default* If as a result some charge for the out-of-pocket expenses had to be included in the ¥. 0. vote, and if publicity was thus given to the fact that the Afghan Govt, are buying rifles from H.M.G. on credit terms, do you agree that no political embarrassment at Kabul is likely to result from this? I am sending copy of this letter to Metcalfe. Your* sinoeroW- .^l.c.****negot iations/ 5319c P.z. 9150/36. Draft Paper. Department. SECRET aIR I'AIl. ^oreigi Secy, to the G. of I.. &amp; P. PeDt., NEW DELHI. Sir, I am directed by the S. of ,S. to refer to your letter, No. F.320-F/34 of 5th December, regarding the G. of I.'s liability in respect of the sale of 1914 pattern rifles to the Afghan Govt. The S. of S.'s agreement with the Treasury and the W.O. for the sale of these rifles provided, as was stated in 1.0. telegram No. 1552 of 19th May, 1936, for the limitation of the G. of I.’s liability in the event of an Afghan default to the out-of-pocket expenditure incurred m respect of rifles not paid for at the time of the default. The S. of S. notes, however, from para. 1 of your letter that the G. of I. have hitherto not appreciated that thts^ arrangement^ constituted a definite i agreement under which the liability of the G. of I.'s Afghan Reserve Fund m the case of a default would be limited to the r.O.'s out-of-pocket expenses, but in respect only of that proportion of the rifles for which the purchase price had not already been received ffom 'the Afghan Govt, at the time of such default. 2. It is regretted that this misunderstanding should have arisen. The V/.O. have throughout thesenegotiations stipulated that they should receive their purchase price in full for the rifles so long as, and to the extent to which, instalments of payment are forthcoming from the Afghan Govt.; but, in order to limit the G. of I.’s liability * • for further payments if and when a default should occur, they were ready to agree that this liability for payments outstanding at the time of the default should be limited to that part of such outstanding payments which represents the out-of-pocket expenses of the W.O., and should not extend to the whole of the purchase price. The agreement in this sense which was reached with the Treasury is contained in paras. 2 and 4 of the memo. B which was communicated to the Treasury, read with the last paragraph of I'r . Barlow’s letter of 29th February, 1936 (copies of which were enclosed with my d.jo. letters to Sir A. Metcalfe of 16th January, P.Z. 8784/35, and 2nd larch, P.Z. 773/36, respectively)'. In the former of these documents it was stated that M It is hoped that it will be agreed that in the event of a default the amount of the indemnity (and of the consequent charge to the fund) should be limited to the out-of-pocket expenditure in respect of rifles not naid for at the time o^ the default, or even/Draft Paper. Department. even to the amount of the expenditure which had not been covered by the payments already received from the Afghans, as otherwise H.M.G. would in effect be making a profit at the expense of the G. of 1.'s fund”. Mr. Barlow’s reply agreed only to the adoption of the first of these alternatives. It is regretted that the point was not explicitly stated m the telegram No. 1056 which was sent on 25th March with reference to these papers. The agreement reached on the point was again expressed in the 1.0. letter to the W.O. of 11th April and the W.O. reply of 25th April, copies of which were sent to the G. of 1. by mail of 7th May under 1.0. Nos. P.Z. 1674 and 2877/36. 3. There can of course be no question of withdrawing, without the concurrence of the W.O., from this agreement. It will be observed, however ( -VJ.de my letter of 16th July, No. r'.Z. 48 , / 6/36), that the V/.O., being anxious to recover their out-of-pocket expenses in the same financial year as thaM., in which they are incurred, have put forward an additional request^outside the agreement arrived aty which deals only with the hypothetical case of an Afghan default^ The new suggestion made by the ...0. is that the excess of their out-of- pocket/I pocket expenses m a given financial year over any payment received from the Afghans in that year should be covered by an advance from the G. of I.’s fund. The S. of S. would be willing, if the G. of I. agree, to f &gt;)/■ t inform the W.O. that Indian- revenues can either aftoumc the liability already agreed upon in the event of an Afghan default, or can undertake to make advance payments in * the manner suggested (subject to refund as further Afghan instalments are received), on the understanding that their ultimate liability will be limited to such pronortion, if any, of the out-of-pocket expenses in respect of the whole number o rifles as was not covered by payments received from the Afghans. I am to enquire whether the G. of I. agree to this proposal. r /t'Or’Draft Paper. Department. Lt.-Col. W.K. Fraser-Tytler,C.M.G. M.C., H.M. Minister, British Legation, KABUL. 5319c 5000 10.36 Will you please refer to the 1.0. , letter to the G. of I. of 29th October, 1936, P.Z. 7217/36, and previous correspondence regarding the question of the liability of the G. of I. in respect of the W.0. rifles^which are being sold to the Afghan Govt, if the latter should 9 . default? I enclose copy of a letter dated 5th December received from the G. of I. and of the letter which we have sent 4 them h in reply. Lou will see that one of the points in this complicated case is that the W.0. desire to recover their out-of- pocket expenses each year m the same financial year as that m which they are incurred, in order to avoid a charge falling on the W.0. vote. They therefore ask that, in addition to the G. of I.'s liability in the event of an Afghan default, the G. of I. should undertake to make from the Afghan reserve fund any advance payment necessary to cover the difference between the W.G.’s out-of-pocket expenses in a given year and the amount which they receive from the Afghans in that year. A point on which** would like to consult you is this. The G. of I. might decline to accede to the additional request made by the W.O., unless the latterlatter were willing to revise the existing agreement, which the G. of I. do not like, in regard to liability in the event of a default. If as a result some charge for the out-of-pocket expenses had to be included m the W.O. vote, and if publicity was thus given to the fact that the Afghan Govt, are buying rifles from H.M.G. on credit terms, woal4- any political embarrassment at Kabul be likely to result from this? / i * /j-*. a//, / * bo. t « ^ * h. u.u / ^ (■ IM oW? ,l/, APPROVED POLITICAL COMMITTEF 19 JAN 193, Set&gt;q-(yO. A. /} ■ h+ScUf* ftour Oi, nw 7/ /'CONFIDENT IAT.. f P. z' NO.F.320-F./34. i 9150 From To QKR . v..' kJ \J The Foreign Secretary to the Government of -India, The Under Secretary of State for India, India Office, London. Sir, Dated New Delhi, the 5' December 1936. With reference to your letter No.P.2.7217/ 36, dated the 29th October 1936, I am directed to state that the Government of India regret that they cannot see their way to reconsider the attitude taken up in their letter No.F.320-F/34, dated the 31st August 1936. The proposal of the War Office is, as the Government of India understand it, that, if the Afghan Government default on the second instalment of the money due from them for the rifles supplied by His Majesty's Government,the firso instalment paid by them will be taken as pay ment at the £3-5-6 rate for one-sixth of the rifles and that the Government of India will be expected to pay the balance,which on this basis will be still due on account of out-of-pocket expenses for the remaining five-sixths. This sum, viz . £ 9 , 375 /- actually represents the profit that will be made ^^hy His Majesty’s Government on the one-sixth of the rifles which are to be treated as having been paid for at the full purchase rate. The Government of India do not consider that this is a fair against Indian revenues. The sale of the 25,000 is one transaction and it seems only reason- i ble i- 0 treat any payment received from the Afghan ^ ToDEC»i government as being part payment in respect of the rFlCE K £ ^ * / V v/ J 't wholer \ - 2 - whole transaction and not as full payment for a part of the goods delivered. 2. Moreover acceptance of the War Office proposal would seem to impose a continuing liability upon the Government of India until the final instal ment has been paid by the Afghans. Thus if the Afghan Government default on the fourth instalment His Majesty's Government will have already received £13,645-16-8 x 3* £40,937-10-0 in payment for i the rifles at the full rate but the Government of India will still be liable for the out-of-pocket expenses on the remaining half of the rifles at £1-0-6 per rifle l.e. £12,812-10-0. since they would have already been repaid in 1937-8 the £11,979-3-4 contributed by them in 1936-7'*the whole of this sum would presumably fall to be paid to His Majesty's Government in 3 instalments. The liability would be reduced annually but would in 0 ^.a 1941/42 still amount to £25,625 -f 6 = £4270 until the last instalment was paid. Such an arrangement would I am to suggest be clearly inequitable. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant. Foreign Secretary to the Government of India /rv ‘ ( (-'X-th XicUl&lt;o' Draft Paper P.Z.7217/36 Department. Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, F. &amp; P. Department, New Delhi. Copy to F.O. Kabul with enclosures [/ The point at A in the War Office letter is a new one and I think it materially affects the issue. I think these drafts follow the lines you indicated in discussion, l-CoOl' oJ^xS'^. £■ \JS 29 0GT 1936 Sir, I am directed by the Secretary of State to refer to your letter No.F.320-F/34 of 31st August and connected correspondence regarding the liability of the Government of India in respect of the 25,000 1914 pattern rifles to be sold to the Afghan Government and to enclose a copy of further correspondence with the War Office on the subject. The Secretary of State would be glad to learn the result of such further consideration of the question as the Government of India may feel able to give to it in the light of this correspondence. Ob co^vrs*. C. ^Oro- c-C W-yUs ^ ^ udA.' q Va.O'TvmqV '^S€.-vO«-€_ S&gt;V otvcs , (Sd.) H, A. F. RUM BOLD v£a.q. c*- cxVjo aJL' urCl'q 00-0 (^r 'Li+z. 5036 5000 7.36 ^ ^Draft Paper. P.Z.72X7/36 Department. Under Secretary of State, War Office, S. W. 1 . od ^ Sir, ^ \ (1/ \&amp;Jl%L 'rC\ &gt; \tS So Q.S to ^\rces\&gt;etX‘\ve S^av^P^W^ W %u. ^^ o^-^Y«wat i^e.A%es t^s. I^iac «-S otu. ''4 ^CAored, I am directed by the Secretary of . t State for India to refer to your letter No.0.164/6260 (F.l) of 6 th October regarding the liability of the Government of India in respect of the 25,000 1914 pattern rifles to be sold to the Afghan Government, and to forward a copy of a letter which has been sent to the Government of India. joOlHfc Out 2. In this connection I am to eyaphaoioo that the India Office letter of 16th July not to the Government of India embodied ir&amp; it- an agreement between the War Office and V&gt;*At the India Officea suggestion made by the War Office, whiehTthe Secretary of State for India e^road to forward to the Government of India for their consideration^ ^ £he Government of India G.?svtc ce.ce^\S&lt;k-v£x.e uo.o W-aOt L€».e^. ate SVi\\ hf*vu re^Iiod t mm u +**^7 unable to J accept this suggestion without amendment^, av, iA te.en 5$j7 the Army Council would prefer to leave standing the original agreement reached with the acquiescence of the Government of India, whereby the liability _ ^ a.cCses of the Government of India arosre only in the event of an Afghan default and extended to the out-of-pocket expenses in respect of rifles not paid for at the time of the default, the Secretary of State would of/of course agree 3. A copy of this letter with a copy of the War Office letter of 6th October hao boon sent to the Foreign Office. (Sd.) H. A. F. RUM BOLDand the following number quoted. subject should be addressed to:— Tel. No.—Whitehall 9400. Any further communication on this The Under-Secretary of State. The War Office, London, S.W.l, THE WAR OFFICE, LONDON, S.W.l. 0164/6260 (F.l.) r / b October, 1936 / /. Sir I Q ^ p, In reply to your LettNoP.Z. 6585/36, of 28th September, regarding the liability of the Government of India in respect of the 25,000 1914 pattern rifles which have been offered to the Afghan Government, I am commanded by the Army Council to inform you that tney regret that they see no reason to depart from the terms of that liability as agreed between the India Office and the War r , Office and embodied in the letter of 16th July last from your Department to the Government of India. The reference, in the Government of India’s letter No. P 320 P/34 of 31st August, a copy of which was sent to this Office, that this undertaking would involve the payment of profits to His Majesty’s Government at the expense of Indian revenues is not understood: I am to point out in this connection that •the price (£2. 5. 0.) to be paid for each rifle is a very low one for arms which will probably shortly cease to be surplus and will be taken into normal reserve stocks; further, the Council, as Lord Zetland is aware, agreed to forgo the value of any rifles not paid for at the time of possible Afghan default, the liability of the Government of India being limited in respect of those rifles to the out- of-pocket expenses incurred from Army funds. They trust therefore, in the light of the fore going considerations, that Lord Zetland will find himself able to urge upon the Government of India acceptance of the continent liability for these rifles, in the event of Afghan default with the payments, as defined in the India Office letter of 16th July referred to above. I am, Sir The Under Secretary of State The India Office, S. W. 1.//. . ^v k. ^ Cw4^V Mr. Clatfson: 4c^ ^v».o * ^&gt;^6 Zr^Cl^ G-it -\ kJL- fc ^ v &lt; irC/~ A *— K - ^ r ^ fr^^Lc ^ l. ^ t«-rvl U.S.S:' ‘Tv ' &lt;) * (r-vit^ju / &lt;- f~vL °^U In Mr. Barlow's letter of 29th February (P.Z.773/36) agreeing demi-officially to the establishment of the Afghan Reserve Fund^he said that the Treasury view is that in the event of an Afghan default on the unpaid purchase money for the 1914 pattern rifles the Fund should be liable for out-of-pocket expenses in respect of rifles not paid for at the time of the default . This meant that any instalments received from the Afghans before a default occurred would be regarded as having paid entirely for a proportion of the rifles at £3.5.6 per rifle and not as having paid off in whole or part the out-of-pocket expenses on all the rifles at £1.0.6 per rifle. The Government of India in reply noted with t satisfaction that the potential debit to the Fund on xO -u\*S\ account of an Afghan default^ould be limited to the fV\ f \ j ? • out-of-pocket expenses (P.Z. 2376/36). We thereupon &amp;L 6\^ w* asked the War Office officially to agree to the ■x- Treasury view’(P.Z.1674/36) which they did (P.Z.2877/36) CTr\ W** ^There then followed the correspondence with the Government of India at P.Z.3399/36 and the Government of Indian telegram of 3rd June, P.Z.3829/36. We consulted the War Office on the latter and they put forward an entirely new claim, namely that the Government of India should undertake to refund them their out-of-pocket expenses at the rate of £l.-.6 per rifle insofar as these are not covered by Afghan payments in the financial year in which the expenditure is incurred. This involves payments by the Government of India irrespective of any Afghan default and its meaning is explained in our letter of 16th July to the Government of India (P.Z.4876/36). I think that the Government of India*s reply of 31st August may be read as an acceptance of this principle but they refuse to accept as well the obligation in respect of an Afghan default which had previously been agreed to. I think that their attitude is reasonable bthfe it is suggested that we might write to the War Office as in the attached draft• * 1 o-vx'bb r D~ it dr.cu^i ^ J) In IaMM* A thK J-P.Z. 6585/36. Draft Paper. Ml u POLITICAL Department. DRAFT LETTER. The U.S. of S., War Office, S.W.l. 'iU £ 1 M WEEKLY LET'i 40 -l OCT 193-6 utary, political 8SC - T PcPT. INDIA OFFICc r Ci nr&gt;(% ^ U^biU I C '01Q^ I am directed by the Secretary &lt; of State for India to refer to India '&gt; Office letter of 16th July to the Government of India, regarding the liability of the Government of India in respect of 25,000 1914 pattern rifles which have been offered to the Afghan Government, and to the Government of India’s reply of 31st August on this subject. Copies of these papers were forwarded to the War Office with India Office printed letters Nos.P.Z. 4876/36 of 15th July and P.Z.6585/36 of 16th September. 2. The Marquess of Zetland understands the Government of India’s letter of 31st August to be an acceptance of the proposal described in paras.2-4 of the India Office letter of 16th July. His Lordship hopes that in these circumstances the Army Council will agree that the Government of India should not now be asked to accept in addition the obligation in the event of an Afghan default agreed upon in para.6 of India Office letter No.P.Z.1674/36 of 11th April and the War Office reply No.0164/6260(F.1.) of 25th April as modified in para.5 of India Office letter of 16th July to the Government of India. 3. A copy of this letter he* b^en 4599 5000 2.36 sent/f'. K'\- ~Pt. 12 SEP 1936 rlQE COMFIDKInTIAL r\ s rx r 1 dd8o No. 'F.320-F/34. BY AIR MAIL From The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India. To ' •&gt; The Secretary, Political Department, Inaia Office, L o n d o n. Q^r Dated SIMLA, the 3/ c August 1936. Supply of 25,000 1914 pattern rifles to the Afghan ''Government. sir ’ /^- 7/ith reference to Mr. Walton's letter No. P.Zw 4876/36, dated 16th July 1936, I am directed to state that the Government of India regret that they are unable to accept the proposal put forward in para. 5 of the letter. All that the Government of India have undertaken is to reimburse, in case of Afghan default, the War Office for their out-of-pocket expenses, viz: £ 25,625/-, on account of the sale of 25,000 1914 pattern rifles and they are not prepared to undertake the further liability proposed, which would appear to involve the payment of profits to His Majesty's Government at the expense of Indian revenues. They agree to pay the whole of this sum in the first year, if all the rifles are delivered that year and the Afghan Government default on the first instalment. If, as is likely, the Afghan Government pay the first instalment, the Government of India will then pay to the War Office the balance, viz: £ 11,979-3-4, in the current year and will not be liable to pay anything more if the Afghans default thereafter.2 . If, however, the Afghan Government pay the second instalment nezt year or later, the Government of India would be entitled to recover £ 11,979-3-4 out of that amount and remit the surplus to His Majesty*s Government. Any instalments that the Afghan Government may pay after the second instalment will of course be remitted to His Majesty*s Government. A copy of*this letter is being sent to His Majesty*s Minister, Kabul. Sir, Your most obedient servant, I have the honour to be, Foreign Secretary to the Government of India* M✓7 / P.Z. 40-»5/36&gt; POLITIG/\L T['6 J«l^ &amp; DRAFT LETT The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India* Foreign A Political Department* Simla* Sir, I am directed by the Secretary of State to reier to the Government of India’s telegram Ro.1302 of 3rd June* regarding the Government of India*a liability in respect of the out-of- pocket expenses of the War Office arisiiy letter s with the War Of rice on this subject* copies of which were sent to thi Government of India by the mail of 18th June under India Office Hos.P*2.3829/36 and P.2.4046/36* 2* The question has been further discussed with the War Office* who have explained that they propose to finance Government by means of a suspense account and that* unless they recover their out- of-pocket expenses in the same financial year as that in which the expenulture is Off loo J theref ore suggest that the Government of India should undertake to Copy to* ftom the proposed sale of 26*000 1914 pattern rifles to the Afghan Government* ana to the exchange of demi-official co^v SENT TO- the transaction with the Afghan CS ouAr ^ /te incurred* a charge would fall upon the CXv*. &lt;*A%. P&lt;&gt;$ p\-CV^\^ \vls. vAv\VQ. refund/refunu them their out-of-pocket expenses at the rate of £1«0*6« per rifle in so far as these are not cove^ by Afghan payments in the financial year in which the expenditure is incurred. seems likely that some payment by the Government of India to the Var ff Ice would be necessary uncled this proposal in the ye r in which delivery begins in the event of more than three instalments being agreed upon with the Afghan Government, even the first instalment is paid on delivery If however the Afghan Government agreed to three annual instalments and to payment of the first instalment on uel- ivery, this would cover the whole of the out-of-pocket expenses in respect of the total of 25, 00 rifles. 3. To illustrate how this proposal would work out, the event maybe considered of all 25,0 0 rifles being delivered before the end of the current financial year, which in fact seems unlikely to be possible, and six annual instalments being agreed u )on with the Afghan Government. The iar Office suggest that the Government of India financial should then pay them in the^year 1936/7 the sura of £11,7¥6»-1Q»0«, being their out-of-pocket expenses on 25,0 0 rifles, , S-ifc-8 namely, £25,625, less £13,64/• , being/being the first instalment paid by the Afghan Go/ernment on delivery of the rifles* In the probable event of less than 26*000 rifles being delivered beitw the eno of the current financial year* or in the event of less than six instalments being agreed upon* the payment made from the Government of India's fund would be correa;&gt;ondingly reduced* On the other hand there is the eventuality referred to in para.3 of Mr.Newling’s letter of 10th June* 4* If the Government of India are willing to accept this proposal, the War Office would of course agree that after their out-of-pocket expenses^?mive been met in full any further payments from the Afghan Government would go to the Government of India until the latter have recovered the sums paid by them to the var Of lice* Thus in the case taken in para.3 as an illustration the Government of India would receive in 1937/8* out of the second annual instalment pain by the Afghan Government &lt;vn-vw the sum at* £11*776* IuhI). f and the War i\biofe-Ab-W Office would receive £3r*07*)* 5* Under this proposal* in the event of an Afghan default* the liability of the Government of India in respect of the out-of-socket expenses ojj rifles not paid for by the Afghan Government/Government would be reuuced by the amount or the sums already paid by the Government or India to thJwar OfH ce. Thus in the illustrative case taken in para*.% in the event of a total Afghan default on the second instalment# 1/6th of the rifles would be regarded as paid for^and the total liability of the Government of India to the Tar Office would be £ —- b - m.yyoAorci. . £9,DVf\ 10 1 4 ., the payment of which would be spread over five equal instalments* 6* The Secretary of State would be glad to know whether the Government of India are willing to agree to the Tar Office proposal* 7* A copy of this letter is being sent to H.M. Minister, Kabul.f I e Dear Rumbold, ^ -Jvay, 1936. I have one or two minor amendments to suggest to the draft letter which you propose to send to the Government of India with regard to the liability of their Afghan Reserve Fund in respect of the 1914 pattern rifles* In paragraph 2, in lieu of the words ’’involving publicity Public Accounts Committee,” we should prefer to see a separate sentence as follows : ’’Such a charge would not be an appropriate-one oU for Army funds to bear, and would in addition invite publicity to the transaction.” Paragraph 4 (line 4): after ’’their out-of- pocket expenses” add ”in the financial year;^ and in para graph 5 (line 13) add the words ”in full” after”paid for.” Incidentally, we make out the figures of the actual example you give in paragraphs 3-5 to be £11, 979* 3* 4 . y £13&gt;64 5* 16* 8 (paragraph 3); £11, 979. 3* 4 . and £1,666,13, 4 (paragraph 4); and £11. 979* 3* 4 . and £9,375 in paragraph 5: you will no doubt check the variations I have underlined. As you know, the War Office concern is with the acceptance by India of an undertaking in general to reimburse to Army funds, in the event of default by the Afghans at any stage of the transaction, the out-of-pocket expenditure necessarily incurred on rifles not paid for in full at the time of default; and, in addition, for accounting reasons to cover Army funds, in the twelve months period over which the rifles will be despatched, against the risk of showing a deficit on the transaction, which is to pay for itself. In asking India to undertake this liability, as we understand your letter to do, you have thought it well to indicate to India what it might amount to in certain eventualities. It is hardly practicable to cover all possible combinations of Afghan default and/or expenditure incurred at the time of default; but if the Government of India accept the general liability stated above there should be little difficulty in agreeing upon its translation into terms of cash in the H.A.F. Rumbold, Esq India Office, S. W. 1. Jr REOo. FSL DEPr. | 9JUU936 unfortunate IX ■c* (N 3204/593/97) kW'0 a . o.'^.4•&gt;.e.^' CkA vxvv\o'C^OcaC«w^»• ^-O. ^Jb*^vH TJVvU \^SK* v^b FOREIGN OFFICE, S. W. 1. 22nd June, 1936. Dear Walton, We concur in the draft telegram to Kabul about rifles enclosed in your letter to me of June 19th, except that we think the last sentence would be clearer if the word ”similar” was inserted before the second ’'payment”. The sentence would then run: ”If Afghan Government agree to payment of first ’’instalment on delivery, similar payment on delivery of ’’each batch would appear to be natural arrangement”. In general we feel in agreement with the sense of Newling*s letter to you of June 13th, that, once we have decided to trust the Afghans at all, we should not be too niggardly in the terms we make, or the good effect of our action will be spoilt. J.C. Walton, Esq., C.B. ,M.C,/ P.Z. 4045/3 6. Su ^ ■ Draft Paper. politi cal Department. .Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, F. &amp; P. Dept. DRAFT LETTER. Sir, Copy to Kabul, War Office, Foreign Office, Treasury. I am directed by the Secretary of State to refer to the Government of India’s telegram No.1302 of 3rd June, regarding the Government of India’s liability f-dJF the out-of-pocket expenses of the War Office arising from the proposed sale of 25,000 1914 pattern rifles to the Afghan Government , and to the exchange of demi -official letters with the War Office on this subject, copies of which were sent to the Government of India by the mail of 18th June under India Office Nos.P.Z.3829/36 and P.Z.4045/36. 2. The question has been further discussed with the War Office, who have explained that they propose to finance the transaction with the Afghan Government by means of a suspense account and that,unless they recover their out-of-pocket expenses In the same financial year as that in which the expenditure is incurred, a charge would fall upon the War Office Vote, involving publicity for the transaction with the Afghan Government and possibly a query by the Public Accounts Committee. The War Office therefore ae-k that the Government of India should undertake to refund them their out-of-pocket expenses ft the rate of £1:0:6 per rifle in so far $.s these are not covered by Afghan payments 4599 5000 2.36 in/in the financial year in which the expenditure is incurred. It seems likely that some payment by the Government of India to the War Office w4^rl be necessary 1%. VAA.*^ecof under this proposal^in the event of more than three instalments being agreed upon i€c«. Picsv with the Afghan Government, eve^i if ?te- w^sva^e^v cs \~ir#h/U^ ^t. A f ghan -d e f aul t—»o ouro &gt; ' u ^ 3. To illustrate how this proposal would work out, the event may be considereci of all 25,000 rifles being delivered before the end of the current financial year,which in fact seems unlikely to be possible, and six annual instalments being y 1 ^ CVW. k ^ 4£ vy-f CL /i &amp; f- . ^7 *tX 1-/ agreed upon with the Afghan Government. ^WeijDhc v&amp;av Tk« Government of India mould then pay thevlv ^y^^ffioo in the financial year 193 6/7 the sum of £11,77 6:10:-, being thevc'WW Q^-^i-ee out-of-pocket expenses on 25,000 rifles, namely, £25,625^ 1653 £13,648:10:-, being the first instalment paid by the Afghan Government on delivery of the rifles In the^ event of less than 25,000 rifles being delivered before the end of the current financial year, or in the event of less than six instalments being agreed upon, the^Government of India’s liab-i-14-ty would be correspondingly reduced. On the other hand there is the eventuality referred to in para.3 of Mr.Newling’s letter of 10th June. 4. If the Government of India are willing to accept this proposal, the War sf- £*\v^v&lt; Office would^agree that after their out-of- pocket expenses have been met in full any further payments from the Afghan Govt.pocket expenses would then be covered. If the Afghans Minute Paper. poli ti c al Department. r' Mr.Wal l/ It is not clear whether Colonel Fraser-Tytler has definitely been authorised by the Government of India to resume his negotiations for the sale of rifles and ammunition. Possibly he will read the first sentence of para.4 of the Government of India’s telegram, No.1302, as authority to resume them, but I suggest a telegram to clear up the point. 2. The total cost to the Afghans of 25,000 rifles will be £81,875. Ov\ The out of pocket expenses 25,000 rifles will be £25,625. If payment in six annual instalments is arranged each instalment will be £13,648^-, 3. I have never understood that there was any question of the Government of India having to pay forthwith £25,525 if the Afghans should default on the first instalment. I read the Government of India’s present proposal to be that in the event of an Afghan default on the first instalment they should pay from the Afghan Reserve Fund s £4,27o|- per annum for six years or until the Afghans resume payments (the actual annual debit from the Reserve Fund would depend on the number of instalments agreed on with the Afghans). I suggest that we might try this out on the War Office and a draft to Sir R.Paterson is suggested. 4. I think, however, that the War Office may make the counter suggestion that in the event of an Afghan default on the first instalment the Government of India would pay the first instalment in full and most of the second instalment when due. The War Office’s out oflater resame payments ; t^±-9 would go to the War Office until they had received their full £81,875, subsequent payments being credited to the Afghan Reserve. Similarly, if the Afghans defaulted on the second 2 instalment, 4,165^- rifles would have been paid for in full by the first instalment, leaving 20,833^ rifles to be paid for. The out of pocket expenses owing to the War Office would then be £21,354^-, and the Government of India would have to pay in full the second instalment; of £13,648^ and £7,706|- on the third instalment. u . \fC'mm —i 0164/6260 (P.l.) The War Office, Whitehall, S.W.2. 10 'June, 1936. Dear Walton, Thanks for your letter P.Z. 3829/36 of 5th June enclosing telegrams exchanged with the Indian Government about the liability of their Afghan Reserve Fund in respect of the 25,000 1914 Pattern rifles. We agree generally with the interpretation placed, in paragraph 2 of your letter, on the agreement as regards India*s payment for the rifles not paid for at the time of Afghan default, i.e., by instalments corresponding to the period (six years or less, as may be arranged) covered by the plan of payment by the Afghans. But we must make the reservation that, irrespective of the amount actually due to be refunded under the instalment plan you describe, India reimburses to us in any year at least the actual amount of the cash expenditure on inspection, packing, etc. on the rifles: otherwise we shall get into difficulties with this transaction on the Army Account. With regard to paragraph 3, while delivery may probably have to be spread over such period of time as may allow of the suspension of the later consignments in the event of default on the earlier, you will realise that we may have incurred considerable expense on inspection, etc. of the later instalments of rifles even if they had not left this country. We should, of course, expect the Indian fund to reimburse this to us, as is implicit in India*s acceptance of liability for out-of-pocket expenditure incurred from Army funds on these rifles. I am sending a copy of this note to Bridges and Collier. J.C. Walton, Esq., C.B. THE INDIA OFFICE, S. W. 1. No. n! y, Yours sincerely, MEBCWSUrtll WNlte^LY LETT 35'DIAl SCyiUN.1926 K/u '&lt;.L AHi) Oc.r’T. INDIA OrFICcDraft Paper. A.J. Newlirv, Esn., I .V.O., WAR OFFICE, S./. 1. ^rom G. of I. /T/-16.5.36. ' ' n V- 19.5.36. ' H/ d/- 3.6.36. Copv' to E.E. Bridges, F.Cd, Treasury, with copy of Forminka 36 of 5th May G. of I. Aelm. 1179 of 16th Lay 1.0. te/m. 1552 of 19th May G. of/I. teim. 1302 of 3rd Jane. Copy to Mr. L. C/llier, C.M.G., F.O. ' ENCLOSURE I - ' ' ,rrv X'f LETTER NO. 25 18JUN 1936 FROM CUR : .. - L AMD SECRET DEPT. INDIA O.VTCt P.Z. 3829/36 Department. v „ .. '-5 JUN 1936 _ I enclose copy of telegrams which we have exchanged with the G. of I. regarding the G. of I.'s liability in the event of an Afghan default on the 25,000 1914 pattern rifles which we are offering to the Afghan Govt. 2. We should be grateful if you could let us know whether you agree with the G. of I.’s interpretation of our agreement stated in their telegram of 3rd June. This interpretation (which seems - to us natural) means for example that, in the event of an Afghan default on the first of six instalments, the W.O. would be paid from the Afghan Reserve Fund one-sixth of their out-of- pocket expenses (of £1.0s r 6d. per rifle) every year for six years or until the Afghans resumed payment. Similarly, if tne Afghans paid the first instalment, f but defaulted on the second and subsequent instalments, the W.O. would be paid their out-of-pocket expenses on 5/6ths of the rifles, this payment being spread over five annual instalments; and so on. In the event of less than six instalments being agreed with the Afghans, a corresponding alteration would of course be made in the G. of I.'s contingent liability to the W.O. 3. It will be remembered that it is proposed that the rifles should bedelivered in batches, tne total del-ivery may be, spread over aconsiderable period. If an Afglian default ^should occur before the total of 25,000 rifles has been delivered, further deliveries would of course be suspended and the G. of I.’s liability for out-of-pocket expenses proportionately reduced. 4. I am sending a copy of this letter to Bridges, with copies of the telegrams, and to Collier. J. 0. WALTON.FILE COPY jkl/aw. r~T' '7 r r vJ L L- 9 j i 1936 ) (151 groups) DECYPHBR OF TELEGRAM . SECRET 2709. Prom Gorernment of India, Foreign and Political Department, to (COPIES Secretary of State for India. CIRCULATED) Dated Simla, 3rd June, 1936. Received 3rd June, 1936, 7.50 p.m. 1302. S 3+1 XXX Addressed to Secretary of State 1302, repeated to Kabul, 121. Your telegram of the 19th ultimo, 1552. Rifles. 2 V We presume that this does not*mean that if Afghans default on one (say the first) instalment we shall he expected to pay forthwith’whole amount, at out-of-pocket rates, of sum remaining due on 25,000 riflea, wMch in this case would total some Re.a-J- lakhs. Such an arrangement would not only place undue strain on the fund, in riew of other probable calls thereon, but would lead to difficult accounting questions if Afghans subsequently resumed payment at supply rates of £3.5.0 per rifle. 3. Our interpretation is that we pay instalments at £1 out-of-pocket rate per rifle if and when' each Afghan' default | takes place. 4, Matter ia hypothetical at present and we do not propose to hold up offer to Afghans on this account. But we must press for acceptance of our interpretation as the only reasonable arrangement which will enable us to take other demands, e.g,, for ammunition, on the fund. RE 6 d. P 0 L. DEPt. - 4 JUN 1936 INDi\ OFFICEP.2. 3399/36 /V, SECRET. CYPHER TELEGRAM PROM SECRETARY OP STATE FOR INDIA TO GOVERNMENT OP INDIA, FOREIGN &amp; POLITICAL DEPARTMENT, REPEATED TO HIS MAJESTY’S REPRESENTATIVE, KABUL, DATED 19th MAY 1936. XXX (No.of words: 35) 1552. Addressed 'by Secretary of State for India to Government of India, repeated Kabul, No.39. Your telegram No.1179 of 16th May. Rifles. Government of India’s liability in event of Afghan default is limited to out of pocket expenditure incurred in respect of rifles not paid for at time of default.2. 2891/36. Cypher Telegram from Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs to H.M. Minister, Kabul. Repeated to Government of India, Foreign and Political Department. Dated 5th May, 1936. (No. of Words - 133). XXX SECK3T 38. Katodon 20 of 25th February, Rifles. Please inform Afghan Government that His Majesty’s Government are willing to sell 15,000 1914 pattern rifles in addition to 10,000 already offered and at the same price. As testing and packing of both lots will take several months it would be convenient for delivery to be in batches over a period. Possible arrangement might be that first 10,000 should be delivered as soon as practicable in one or more batches and additional 15,000 in further batches when Afghan Government have received first lot and reported them satisfactory. 2. You may agree to payment for 10,000 as well as 15,000 being spread over six annual instalments if as a result of your further discussions you judge this essential for acceptance of offer and provided Government of India concur. But His Majesty’s Government hope you will be able in each case to obtain payment of first instalment on delivery. 3. Ammunition should be offered on terms suggested in paragraph 2 of Government of India’s telegram No.1017 of 27th Apr il.(P.Z. 2877/36) 0164/6260 (F.l.) Sir, THE WAR OFFICE, LONDON, S.7. 1. 25th April, 1936. I am conxnanded by the Army Council to refer to &gt;oar letter P.Z. 1674/36 of 11th April forwarding copies of telegrams, etc., relating to the supply of rifles to the Afghan Government. The Council observe, from the Government of India’s telegram Mo. 875 of 6th April, that substantial agreement has been reached semi-officially with the Treasury with regard to the fund which the Indian Government propose to create for the purpose of financing political expenditure m connection with Afghanistan; and they note from your letter under reply that the liability in respect of the 10,000 rifles, 1914 pattern, already offered to the Afghans, and of the 15,000 additional rifles now under consideration, in the event of Afghan default on the agreed purchase price, has been accepted against this fund by the Government of India. I am to say, for Secretary ^ord Zetland’s information, that the Council are prepared to make available for offer to the Afghan Government the further 15,000 rifles, 1914 pattern, now requested. In view of the undertaking by the Government of India referred to m the previous paragraph they agree that their claim against the Afghan expenditure fund of that Government, m the event of default on the part of the Afghans, shall be limited to the out-of-pocket expenditure incurred from Army Funds in respect of such of these additional rifles as had not been paid for at the time of the default, as in the case of the 10,000 rifles already offered to the Afghan Government. The Council observe, from the third paragraph of your telegram No. 1238 to the Government of India, that it is proposed/ The Under Secretary of State, India Office , S.W. 1.proposed to authorise His Lajesty's Minister at Kabul to agree to payment m six annual instalments for both the 10,000 and the 15,000 rifles in lieu of the three instalments recommended by the inter-departmental Conference held at the War Office on 14th November and mentioned in telegram No. 113 of 19th November from the Foreign Office to His Majesty's I inister at Kabul. If this course is regarded as essential to the acceptance of the offer of these rifles by the Afghan Government, the Council are prepared to defer to Lord Zetland’s views in the matter. They trust, however, that, as mentioned in the closing paragraph of Foreign Office telegram to Kabul, No. 1G of 14th February, some substantial token of the intention of the Afghan Government to honour its financial commitments m respect of the arms supplied will be forthcoming before the necessary negotiations are concluded. Copies of this letter are being sent to the Treasury and to the Foreign Office. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, (Sgd.) A.E. 7/iddows.It is requested that in any further communi cation on this subject the under-mentioned letter / and number may be quoted, and the reply INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL, u addressed to — The Under Secretary of State for India, Political Department, India Office, London, S.TF. 1. LONDON, S.W. l. 5U674/36 11th April, 19 Sir, I am directed by the secretary of stale lor India to refer to the uelogram addressed to His Majesty's Minis ter 4 at xabul on 14th February, no. 16, anc his reply of 25th February, No.20 (cojieo enclosed for ease of reference), and connected correspondence re^ardins the supply of rifles to the Afghan Government• 2. It will be oboorved that the Afghan Government ore anxious that the question of supplying the further 15,COO rifles which they require snould be settled at the same time as that of the 10,COO 1914 pattern rifles which have already been offered to them on the terms authorised in the telegram sent to His ..lajeaty's Minister at Kauul on 19th November last, No. 113. 3. The general question of the xneiuonce as between the Government of ^ndia and His Majesty's Government of ex;anditure and liabilities incurred in the interests of An Cj lo-Afghan relations has recently boon under discussion with the Treasury ana the Go Vermont of .ndia. u am to enclose copy of the Telegram to Government of ^ndia, dated ) 25th March. ) will observe that the general Telegram from Govornmunt of india, dated ) 6th April. ) question of incidence has now ) been settled by the decision to establish the special Afghan fund described m paragraph 7 of the enclosed memorandum in view of the assurance received from the Treasury which is referred to in paragraph 2 of the telegram sent to the Govcrment of india on 25th March. The Under-Secretary of State, India Oxf^co memorandum on expenditure on Afghanistan# ) papers noted in the margin on ) this subject. The Army council War Gif s 4./(g&gt; 2 . 4# as regarae the oli&amp;ical expediency of meet^n^ the Afghan request for a further supply of 15,000 rifles, reference ie invited to the telegram from His Majesty^ Mixiintor, Kabul, of 2bth October last. No. 127, and paragraph 4 of his telegram of 8th September, No*92. Copy ie enclosed of a telegram which has been despatched to the aovornmont of ^ndla. Subject to their concurrence, the Marquess of Zetland has little doubt that it will be generally agreed that it will be desirable, if possible, to supply the further req ireraents. The Afghan War Minister has stated that the full supply of 30,000 rifles is required to complete ihe armament of the Afghan Any, and it is perhaps not unnatural tint the Afghan dorernment should hesitate about accepting the offer of It,000 1£14 pattern rifles until they know whether the balance of their requirementa can be supplied with rifles of the same pattern. 5. Lord Zetland would therefore be grateful ii the Army Council could state whether they would find it jracticable to supply 15,ttO 1514 pattern rifles for the same price as that ior which 10,000 of these rifles have already been offered to the Afghan Government, if the aoveriaaent of India agree that it would be politically desirable to offer the additioiial supply. 6. The Army council will note that as a result of the arrangements for the establishment of a special Afghan ;und. Ills Majesty^ Government will no longer have to bear the liability which they provisionally accepted for the contin, exit loss in the event of an Afghan default on the payment for tl»o 10,000 rifles already offered, nor would they incur axiy liability in respect of the additional 15,000 rifles. Lord ^etlanb hopes that, as His Majesty 1 ® Govorximent are now beixig relieved of ail liability, the Amy council will agree that the amount of the potential debit to the Government of Ixidia^ iund ^xi the event of a default by the Afghan Goverximent should be/3 . b© limltdo. to the out oi pocket ©aspenoes inourrtd including the payment to Mesaio. Soley Limited in reapeot oi such rii'lee aa had not been paid ior at the time ox the do ault^both aa regard® the 10,000 ril'iee and the further supply of 15,000 rifles• 7. Lord zetlana would be grateful for an early reply to the enquiry made xn paragraph 5 of this letter, 8, A copy of this letter is being sent to the Foreign Office, who have concurred in its terms, and to the Treasury, I am, Sir, Your obecUent servant, CSd.) H. A. P, RUMSOLDExpenditure on Afghanistan* aoverna^nt of Inuia f e proposed special fund* 1* The atability and frienaship of the Afghan Government is Important to British interests for two reasons - (i) an unstable Afghan Government would be unable, and an unfriendly one might be unwilling, to eo-cperate with us in the maintenance of order among the Pathan tribes on either aide of the Durand lines this may be regarded ns a specifically Indian problem; (ii) a disunited or unfriendly Afghanistan, or a weak Afghan Government, would no longer serve as an efficient buffer against military aggression or (whit is even more likely) revolutionary intrigue directed towards India by the soviet Government} in such conditions it would be easy for that Government, by bringing Afghanistan, piecemeal or as a whole, under economic domination and political influence, to e&amp;p the approaches to India and gain a base moat conveniently situated either for the preparation of future military aggression or for the promotion of that Internal revolution in India which is the acknowledged aim of the Communist International* 'fith reference particularly to the danger of military aggression the Cabinet on 14th March, 1954, reaffirmed the previous policy of regarding the independence and integrity of Afghanistan as essential to the defence of Inula and the Empire* 3* It is clear that the second interest referred to above is not only, nor even mainly, a distinctively Indian Interest, but is a British interest in the widest sense* But it is also true that in the concrete the two intereste are so interlinked that, in considering the particular questions which arise, it is for the most part impossible to estimate otherwise than 4 uite arbitrarily in what proportions the distinctively Indian or the wider Imperial aspect of the matter/■ auitter predoainatea* 3* In the caae of a hypothatleal war, in, or «lth 9 &amp;fghanii»tan» a distinction is drawn between the two aspects of our Interest in that country. A war with jfghaniatan alone or with Afghanistan and the tribes of tht North eat frontier (l.e. s war arising out of the necessity for maintaining peace and order on the frontier) would be regarded as a natter of distinctively Indian interest* would be a task for the Army In India alone* and would be financed iron Indian revenues# But on the other h*na* it is recognised that a war iadefenoe of Afghanistan against Toiseia* or a war in defence of India against Hussla and Afghanistan in alliance* would not be a natter of purely Indian concern nor a possible task for the Army in India abne, but that it would be necessary to employ forces raised in this country and other parts of the Empire* md for the Home Government to assume direction of the operations and financial rea ’♦onaibility# 4# Before the Anglo-Afgfcaa war of 1919 Afghanistan's foreign relations were* at any rate in theory* and as a result of certain treaty provisions* controlled by the British Government* and this control* so far as it existed in practice* was exercised through the Government of India as agent of His ^nlesty's Government# The Auir also received a large annual subsidy from Indian revenues# in Afghanistan* •*# elsewhere in Asia* the Great War resulted in a stimulation of national aeir~con$clousness# The Afghan Government resented their position of theoretical subordination to the Government of India* and as a result of the recognition of Afghan Independence in the Anglo-Afghan Treaty of 1921 they gained the right to direct diplomatic relatione with His Majesty's Government and the governments of ether foreign powers# Uince th*t date Aagio-Afghan relations have been conducted in the normal way through diplomatic represen tat Ives in Kabul and London I the annual siAaidy h '.a ceased*/3 . ami all control of the Ai ghan Goyernraent by or through the Goyernment of In*;ia ha* com© to sm end. Heverthe- l#aa the Governaent of India have continued to be financially rea^onaible for all piece-time expenalture 9 i.e. (a) the regular expenditure on the British legation and Consulateat and (b) any additional expenditure incurred in the interests of Afghan stability and friendly relations with this country. o. The regular annual expenditure under head (a) amounts approximately to Rs.4.4b laichs a year. That unoer head (b) naturally yaries fro* year to year. Although in the altered conditions resulting fro* Afghan independence an annual subsidy is no longer paid 9 nevertheless 9 in view of the British and Indian Interests referred to above 9 and in accordance with recommendations nude by the Defcnoe of India dub-Comaittee of the C.I.D. in 1927 9 a policy ox' oceaelonal subsidy to promote projects of mutual benefit has been followed. This is sometimes referred to as the policy of 'subsidy in kina*. ince the establishment of direct relations in 1932, additional payments under head (b) above (all from Indian revenues) have averaged a little over Re.4 lakhs a year. By far the greater proportion of this expend!ture 9 however 9 was incurred in a single year - 1931-2 - *hen 9 as a result of the emergency created by the Afghan revolution and the desirability of helping to stabilise the new r©gime 9 10 9 tX&gt;0 rifles and also about £l7b»0Q0 in cash were surolled to Nadir Shah. 6. The Government of India are prepared 9 though with some reluctanee 9 to continue to finance this additional expenditure on a scale comparable to that already Incurred. But they feel that it is only equitable (especially hiving regard to the dual object - Imperial as well as distinctively Indian - which this expenditure serves) that some limitation should be placed on their futore/fvittre LiaMlitieo ui-uitr this htu • They co;^i ©r V.r% it ie sieceeBary tliat they should b© fible to oaloulat© rit; eat*© degree of certainty tins rmxlnrjin auount of expen iituxv? ot till, nature to vhieli they will be eo?uraitt©d In any give i year# a© it la itaporiaat in present circunuitanoeo that they should n&gt;t b© faced with heavy unexpeete expenditure under this hem 1 in any particular year which t ould 1 ipoae a severe strain on t ie Indian xonequer* burdened as it is already with the heavy costs of Defence. 7# The uovt'vn* -at of inais therefore propos^te feet ? .e a fixed \ aa ,ual au « for the purpose of ‘’subsi^iy in kind' to Afg smlatan fro i In .iau funds in addition to beering the annual e v &gt; i ture un er head a) above* They propose to fix t is annual appropriation at Ks* 5 lakhs a year (i#c* aore tlian t: • •wt.rage of the past 13 years)* The balance of this annual appropriation over the actual expenditure In any one year would be takeu t &gt; reservep where it would eceuisnlat© up to a riaxiimi t of Hxu 25 1^ list tills high isaxinum of the proposed re&amp;erve being allows for the pir^&gt;ose of providing against emergencies such as that a 1931- • As a corollary of the establishment of this fecial fuui t'ho * ovtrnient of nils would naturally oxpeot that in future# if ex;&gt; .n i tore which could not be zuet fro &gt; the fund were required on mmm object of IHAicy in elation to Afghanistan which both His Majesty’s Govt, athe (iovcrnrasuit of In ia agreed was desirable* its incidence would fern the subject of discussion between thi two Oovonameats* •^ilch would proceed on the presumption that India he l air ady* by th s voluntary establish tent of the &gt; eial funi* fulfilled her own obligations ia reopeet of additional expenditure of an or Inary kind; and the Qewwrnraeot of Inila would therefore trust that* in the event of further expenditure (beycm i th capacity of their fund) being refpUrea* the caf e for it» being borne orft. *h*r»d by Hi* ^oyernment would b* fawourably oon«id^r«d t ftspeeinlly if it* object ww* primarily to eountor *ow* specific longer of Fustian penetration in Afghanittan.P.Z. 1674/36. CYPHER TELEGRAM PROM SECRETARY OP STATE TO GOVERNMENT OP INDIA, FOREIGN &amp; POLITICAL DEPARTMENT, DATED 9th APRIL 1936. XXX (No.of words: 128) 1238. Addressed 'by Secretary of State for India to Government of India, Foreign and Political Department. Repeated to His Majesty’s Minister, Kabul No.33. Your telegram 7th March, No.624, paragraph 3, and your telegram 6th April, No.875. It seems desirable that in further discussion of sale of 10,000 rifles Fraser-Tytler should be able to state that His Majesty’s Government will be preyjared to make further supply of 15,000 rifles of the same pattern. In this connection please see paragraph 4 of Kabul telegram of 8th September last, No.92, which may partly explain Afghan hesitation in accepting offer of 10,000 rifles* 2. Please telegraph whether you concur. I am asking War Office whether, if you concur, they would be able to supply 15,000 additional rifles. 3. With reference to paragraph 2 of Forminka No.113 of 19th November last, in view of importance of supplying rifles from British sources it would be undesirable to risk failure of negotiations by insistence over question of instalments. It is therefore proposed, if you concur, to authorise Minister to agree if necessary, to deferred payments in six annual instalments both in respect of 10,000 and additional 15,000 rifles.RC/FCiVMo HM v o c 3 i o SECRET (13B groupso) v_ 19 3 G i 1941 D F 0 Y P H E R OF TELEGRAM. (COPIES CIRCULATED) From Government of India. Foreign and Political Department, to Secretary of State for India. Dated New Delhi, 6th April, 1936. Received 8.20 p.m., 6th April, 1926. XXX First of Se?eral PartSc (? 875, omitted) Addressed Secretary of State and repeated to Minister at Kabul, 4b. Your telegram of the 25th ultimo, 10cC. Afghan Fund. We accept Barlow’s letter of February 29th as giving in effect assurance we asked in paragraph No*5 of our telegram £475 P September 14th, as further explained in our telegram 2049, November 8th, and we agree that matter should be placed on official basis by exchange of letters with Treasury in the sense of paragraph 7, India Office memorandum A, and of Barlow’s reply. In token of this acceptance we have already, without prejudice, transferred a sum of 5 lakhs of rupees in accounts of 1925-36 to establish this fund. We propose to amalgamate this fund with deposits already made for road development policy into one fund to be known as 'frontier deposit fund” but separate parts of it will be accounted for separately. 2e We are prepared to give assurance that endeavours will be made to draw gradually on fund during first few years and give time for reserve to accumulate.jgs/ m (COPIES CIRCULATED) SECRET { 1X6 groupso ) iV40&lt; DECT PEER OF TELSGRA _Mc__ Prom GoTermneat of India, Foreign and. Political Department, to Secretary of State for India,, Dated New Delhi, 6th April, 1936„ Received 8ol5 pom 0 , 6th April, 1936, 8?5 0 SECOND PART XXX We have in fact already given effect to this intention ty deciding not to charge a possible default by the Afghan Government on 5,000 rifle mils to the fund. We also agree to furnish annual statements for submission to the Treasury, showing expenditure incurred, and general position of the fund together with probable future commitments, 3 0 4.3 regards subsidising of industry in Afghanistan, we adhere to position taken in our telegram 925, April 8th, 1935c We are not prepared to spend Indian revenues on subsidising industry in A.fghanistan 0 This prohibition would not necessarily apply to provision of experts at cost of fund if good case could be made out on special grounds^ As regards Afghan suggestion for credite in London for purchasing British machinery, we would not be willing to accept any liability against Indian revenues eithei' (?iB8ide) of (sic,?or} outeide the scope of the fund.SECRET { 1E5 group8o ) DECTPHEH OF TELECtRAM,. Prom GoTernmenw of India, Poreigr and (COPIES Political Department, to Secretary CIRCULATED) of State for India,, Dated flew Delhi, 6th April, 1936 0 Received 7 0 45 p 0 mo, 6th April, 1936 0 S75o THIRD AND LAST PART, 4 0 We note with satisfaction that potential debit to fund on account of default on unpaid purchase money for 10*000 and further 15,000 rifles would be limited to out of pocket expenses 0 So Pro forma book balance on account of former Afghan reserve will be regarded as absorbed in fund from the date of its establishment, see Metcalfe^s letter to Walton, P c (?393) 0 p 0 35, February 29tho 6 0 We are repeating your telegram and this reply to Fraser Tytier and suggest early despatch of telegram from Foreign Office to Kabul notifying establish ment of fund, and authorise Fraser Tytier to proceed with further discussions before the return of the Afghan Foreign Minister from European tour e ' We shall be glad to know the attitude of His Majesty’s Government on the proposals put forward in our express letter F c 321„Fo35, December 9th, 1935, as regards the question of establishing civil air 1939c XXX servicef SECRET ma/wB ( 32* 1016 DECT P H &amp; H OF T E L E 0 H A Bated New Delhi, 16th February, 1936 0 Beceired ll o 30 a 0 mc^ 16th February,1936 0 Addressed to Secretary of State, 450, repeated to Kabul* 14 0 Forminlca 16, February 14th, paragraph No 0 5o We are informed that the Afghan Government have paid the first instalment due on 6,000 rifle units, into the Peshawar branch of the Imperial Bank a From Government of India, Foreign (COPIES CIRCULATED) and Political Department, to Secretary of State for India XXX 450*t. -w u.s.s With reference to my letters to Sir R. Paterson and Mr. Bridges of 14th December, please see their replies of 16th December. I have agreed with them on the telephone that the addition proposed by Sir R. Paterson may take the more precise form of that added in the margin of the draft telegram. I am asking for Mr. Collier's concurrence in this draft telegram and in the attached draft to Kabul instructing^Fraser-Tytler to proceed. fa- ■*.. WW*' 1 '^pKi f 4 S' INDIA OFFICE, ffHITSHALL. S.W. 1. 17th Decenber, 1935. ith reference to the tele^r?iPi sent to Kabul on 19th November, Tio. 113, about the supply of 10,000 / rifles from Var Office stocks and some anar.unition fro?' / India to the Afglian Coyemment, you tiill see from the To Cfovera:ient of India^ ^8th oveicber* ) corre- r x&gt;ndence rith the l ..India. loth Decem ber.) ihovemment of India of ^rhich i enclose a copy that there has been delay in reaching agreement with them on the question of the proportional distribution of payments in the event of a default. The Government of India agreed to the understanding as stated in our telegram of 19th November, but not to the different form of it stated in our telegram of 2 th November, which was sent on receipt of / Paterson’s letter of 27th November (copy enclosed)• In view of the Government of India*s tele ram , of/ L. Collier, sn., C.I.G., FOREIGN OFFICE, S.W. 1.of ICth December Paterson and bridges agree that, in order t-o settle the natter and avoid holding up Kraeer-'fytler's negotiations any longer, we nay send the telegrara^of which a draft is enclosed to the Government of India which leaves it to then to opt ;or either of the formulas proposed, so that, whatever happens, Kraser-:ytler c-in nroceed at once with the negotiations. Gould you kindly let me know by telephone whether you concur in this draft telegram, and m the second draft which is also enclosed to kraser-Tytler!’ (Sgd.) J.C. 'felton.■■■■ Telephone No.: Whitehall 1234. / In reply please quote Regd. No. TREASURY CHAMBERS, WHITEHALL, S.W.l 16 December 1935. Dear Walton, Many thanks for your letter of the 14th enclosing a copy of a telegram from the Government of India with enclosed draft reply. I have had a word with Paterson on the telephone about this matter. tie agree the draft reply subject to the addition which I understand that Paterson is putting to you in regard to paragraph 2. Yours sincerely, IfLQuM' J.C Walton, Ssq., C.B^ y India Office. M.C.,0164/6215 16th December, 1935 Dear walton Your letter T.Z. 8893/35 of 14th December I agree with you that the important thing is to let Prazer-Tytler get on with the negotiations for the sale of the rifles without delay, and the final paragraph of your draft telegram to India should have this effect. India that the war office offer to forgo the value of any of the 1914 pattern rifles not paid for at the time of a possible default is bound up with the proposal that all receipts, both before and after default, are pooled for division pro rata between the two parties. With your forecast of its financial effect before them, India may be induced to accept the arrangement proposed in your telegram No.3806, and I hope this may be the case. But in order to make the position clear as to our offer to forgo the value of the rifles in return for a complete pooling of receipts, I think the following should be added at the end of paragraph 2 of the draft telegram to India: 'In that event the value of the 1914 pattern 'rifles not paid for at time of default will be included 'in claim of H.M.G. in addition to out-of-pocket 'expenditure mentioned above.' I have spoken to Bridges, and he is telling you that he agrees with this. I think, however, that it should be made clear to Yours sincerely J.C. Walton, Esq., C*B. ,M.C. &gt; India Office, s.w.i.Draft Paper. R. Paterson, K.B.E., C.B., W.O. P.Z. Department. ^4 DEGV 5 Will you please see the enclosed copy of a telegram from the G. of I. of 10th December in reply to oars of 28th November (copy of which is also enclosed for ease of reference). Unfortunately the hitch over this secondary point is holding up Praser- Tytler's negotiations for the sale of the rifles and ammunition, and we are all agreed, I think, as to the desirability of his proceeding with them at once. The 1.0. has therefore been anxious to get the point about the proportionate distribution of payments settled one way or another as soon as possible. The first instalment on the 5,000 rifles, with ammunition, supplied by the G. of I. is due on 1st February, and if an Afghan default should occur after that date and before any instalment is received on the W.O. rifles, the G. of I. would have to pay over something received on account of their own rifles. It may be this possibility which makes them reluctant to accept the arrangement. On the other hand, sc far as we can calculate, under the pooling arrangement proposed it would be Indian revenues that are likely to benefit in any other than this rather improbable contingency, because in respect of W.O. rifles not paid for at the time of the default H.M.G.woald rank as creditor for the amount of their out-of-pocket expenditure only. The G. of I. have not been told what that out-of-pocket expenditure amounts to. We would like to tell them that it would fee- Limitcd-to £10,250 (which we gather would be the amount if the default did not occur till after Soley had received the whole of their £5,000) and to point out how this affects the calculation. ^ f'UVw A&lt; Of course, our calculation may be wrong, but in any case it does not seem likely that the amount of the adjustment either way would be large enough to make it worth while to hold up the negotiations further on this point. So far as the 1.0. is concerned, therefore, we are perfectly willing to accept either of the formulas proposed, and I daresay that you and Bridges have no great preference between them, so long as the G. of I* are satisfied and we are able to get on with the business. We would accordingly propose, if you and Bridges concur, to send the G. of I. the telegram of which a draft is enclosed. I am sending a copy of this letter to Bridges.f.2. m yl v Department. ^ . 14DEG1935 I enclose copy of a telegram from the G. of I. and of a letter, with enclosed draft telegram, which 1 am sending to Paterson. Could you kindly let me know whether you agree to the proposal embodied m the draft telegram? Yours sincfcJf'KilY ^J.C.VTAL-o:.Uf jo/* DRAFT TELEGRAM. SECRETARY OF STATE TO GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, FOREIGN AND POLITICAL DEPARTMENT. (Retamilla) srfvV PORMINKA PESHAWAR AVX Addressed by S. of for I. to G. of I.; repeated to H.M# Minister, Kabul. Your telegram 10th December, No. 3295. Pooling arrangement described in my telegram 2Bth November, 3806, seems/ favourably to India rather than otherwise. Adjustment would be in favour of H.M.G. if Afghan default occurred m interval between 1st February next and time of receipt of first instalment due to H.M.G. But tha 1 im^robab k OvV/ 9entingcnoy&gt; and when once H.M.G. have begun to receive instalments, poolings ^arrangement, so far as I can calculate, would^result in adjustment m favour of G. of I. j ThdG results frem the provision stated m last sentence of my telegram No. 3806, because out-of- pocket expenditure there referred to will not exceed £10,250. 2 , In any case point has little importance compared with desirability i of early resumption of negotiations with Afghans for sale of the rifles and ammunition. If therefore notwithstanding the above explanation you still prefer the arrangement stated m last sentence ( f /Vw'/ of para. 3 of my telegram 3720, H.M.G. will substitute this for the revised understanding. 3- H.M. Minister, Kabul, can therefore in any case proceed at once v/ith his pending negotiations.INDEXED FCIf/vffi (COPIES CIRCULATED) 32S5„ Addressed to Secretary of State for India, 3295, repeated to Kabul, 407o Your telegram of the 29th ultimo, 3806 0 We see no reason why payments already credited to either GoYernment prior to any default should come into calculation 0 We are, therefore, unable to agree to understanding as now proposed 0 Subsequent resumed payments would be shared between the two parties on principles agreed in our telegram (corrupt group) 0 For this purpose, pari passu and pro rata may be understood to mean the allocation of each resumed payment in proportion to the amount of default to date in respect of each partyoDRAFT TELEGRAM. 7- &amp;ti 4 . 1 v&lt; SECRETARY OF STATE TO GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, FOREIGN AND POLITICAL DEPARTMENT. for i• to (i* or i* ; ✓ (Retamilla) PKSHAWAR Cypher xTT7 '7 ^ / ' .iddresaed by u* of £ repeated to h*L» l.iniBter* Kabul. I L!y telegram Ivth November, 3720. 'S’ y Rifles for Afghan Govt. ^ ^ / y 2* Understanding stated in last sentence of para. 3 of my telegram (regardin{: proportionate allocation of r ; V y m y recoveries in event of default; should be revised as follows. . In the event of Afghan default any payments A received from Aptian (iovt^m respect of (a) 5,000 rifles supplied by ✓ z' lx*y -. of I. in .a, ust/ and armumtion now to ^ / V ; ^ ^ ^ be supplied, and (b) 10,000 rifles y / » y ^ ** supplied by li.l'.O.^should (subject to the general settlement) be shared by Indian and Imperial revenues in proportion to the value of the stores and cost of the services respectively supplied# For this purpose debt to ii.L.G. would be calculated as consisting only 0 ' our- r- pocket emen it are incurred in connection with the preparation and despatch of the *0. rifles and the payment to t essrn. holey ^ Ltd. ^gjiue eKpmi ilmu ’irrounts to § HbO r 1 i (. 1 ! ^ p// 3- $&lt;r}? 7 xxx &gt;^|m ^ 100164/6213 &lt;T 27th November, 1935. Dear Walton, I agree that it would be well to let India have a further telegram about the agreed basis for sharing any Afghan payments in the event of default. I suggest one or two amendments of the draft in order to bring it more into line with the terms of conclusion (3) of our meeting on 14th November. These are; (^) line 10 ; after 'Afghan default' add 'any payments already received from Afghan Government before default and (if payment is subsequently resumed) after default in respect of ...' (2) line 21-2 : after 'calculated as consisting' insert 'in respect of w.O. rifles not paid for at time of default'. (3) omit the last sentence: 'This expenditure ... £10,250'. The reason for the third amendment is that, following our meeting on 14th November, the Director of Army Contract^x saw S. A./Soley, who are now willing to accept fifty p^r* 9 cent*/ of any payment made by the Afghans, as and when received by us: this is an advance on their previous attitude that they should receive the whole £5,000 (10/- each on 10,000 rifles) as soon as we despatched the rifles to the Afghans. we need not explain all this to India in the telegram, but I would omit the £10,250 figure, which may tempt India to 'do sums' without knowing all the contingencies, and arrive at the wrong answer. Yours sincerely, J.C* Walton, Ssq., G•B.&gt; M»G*&gt; India Office, s.w.i.26th hov ember. 19?b With reference to your letter of terd November 0164/o213 # and oox* tubrserac rvt telephone conversation» i write to say that after iiecassion with akely it is a forthfr tele^ar? to the Gofemwnt of India restating the underat&lt;iiv in {5 about the proportionate distribution of naynents received in th# ev&lt;mt of an default* business, and. in order to facilitate the Govemnent of In ia f p aoeoptance of the stipulation, we think it dooirablo to inform them definitely that for the purpose of any adjustment of actual receipts, the purchase rice to the Afghans of the 1914 pattern rifles would not be included, but only the out-of-pocket expenditure incurred m connection with the preparation and despatch of the thought that it would be advisable, if you agree, to send e&gt; are anxious, however, to Rinittiso 'any delay which this m\y cause in the settlement of the rifles/ Sir R. Paterson, K*h. C*B., ^AH QmCh, S*f* 1.rifle?* and the payment to B*3 .a. 1 accordingly enclose tlie draft of a telegram which « if joa concur, we would propose to the Goferament of India* (Sgd*) J.C* Walton.INDIA OFFICK, WHITEHALL, S.K. 26th November, 193b. I enclose copy of a letter to Paterson (with enclosed draft telegram), which arises oat of the fact that the statement regarding the proportionate distribution of payments received for the rifles, etc., supplied to the ..fghan Government at the end of paragraph 3 of our telegram to the Government of India No. 3720, of 19th November, does not cover the ground of conclusion (3) in the record of the meeting on 14th Rovember- (Sgd.) J.C. Walton. E.K. Bridges, Esq*, M.C., TREASURY, 3.W. 1.Minute Paper. Department. U.S.S. . Please see Sir R. Paterson’s letter of 23rd November. When I saw him on 15th November to get his concurrence in the draft telegrams, I pointed specially to the last part of para. 3 of the telegram to the G. of I., and after he had shown me the draft record of the meeting I pointed out again that what was stated in the draft telegram did not cover the ground of the conclusion in the draft record. Nevertheless, he stated that he concurred in the draft telegram. I have now discussed the question again with him on the telephone* He agrees that he concurred in the draft telegram, and his own view is that it is not necessary to send a further telegram to the G. of I. In view of his letter, however, you may think it desirable to send a adjustment would work unfavourably to the G. of I.), the adjustment. If, however, we send a further telegram, I think we should explain that the debt due to H.M.G* would be reckoned for purposes of adjustment as their out of pocket expenses only; this is what Sir R. Paterson says he has m mind (though the record, by the employment of the word ’’necessarily', is so expressed as to leave the point oper '7 ' w « f -“V^'the event of a default occurring, and in the very improbable event of its occurring almost at once /•* \ . JLJ . i the only case, so far as I can see, in which the ^ in further telegram, if Sir R. Paterson agrees, ■ H 4U ^w,) further telegram, if Sir R. Paterson agrees, since, in G. of I. might possibly complain that we had not secured their concurrence in advance to the proposed method of improbable event of its occurring almost at once (which is the only case, so far as I can see, in which the proposed 2956 6000 7 34 decision when the time comes).m ■ Thank you for your letter P.Z* 8333/35 of 20th November, enclosing copies of telegrams sent to the Government of India and to Kabul about the rifles for Afghanistan. I notice that the second sentence of paragraph 3 of your telegram 3720 does not appear faithfully to reproduce the agreement in conclusion (3) of our meeting on 14th November. That conclusion stated that, in the event of Afghan default, any payments received from the Afghans in respect of the 5,0(50 rifles supplied by India, of the 10,000 1914 rifles, and of the six million rounds of ammunition, should be shared by imperial and Indian funds proportionately to the value of the stores and services each Government was supplying. You will remember that when you brought over the draft telegrams on 15th November we discussed this point, and I hoped l had made my view clear that in the event of default all receipts would be pooled. The telegram, as now despatched, appears to regard any payments which might have been made at the time of default as outside the pooling arrangement, which will apply only to such payments as the Afghans may make if and after they resume the interrupted payments. The record of the meeting does not appear to bear out this interpretation, and it was not I think v/hat we had in our minds. The effect of this variation of conclusion (3) may not in practice prove considerable*, that will depend on the terms of repayment by the Afghans which may be agreed, and on the circumstances in which any default takes place. But as they stand in the telegram to India, the proposals do not appear to achieve the proportionate sharing of risk at which we aimed when agreeing to forgo an indemnity from the Government of India in respect of the 10,000 1914 pattern rifles. J.C* Walton, Esq[. , C»B* » M*C» &gt; India Office, s.w.i. yours sincerely,'VW mmm v.v.flgl.asiaft..iai» line 1, after ^eoeept 1 * insert ^prorleionelly'*. line 6 f after 'without prejudice to' insert 'end aubjeot to the ultimate decision on '* J^ftClualon Uli' insert 'subject to the general settlement it should be arranged that' oefore the first line of this conclusion as at present drafted*Oi^ THE WAR OFFICE, O &gt; • 'i \3&gt; a With the compliments of the Deputy Under Secretary of State for War. 15.11.35.8246 1935 J A Gon'Tcrenoo r;ac hold at the Jar Office on Tliai’ccic-S? 5 14th riorc; ibor f to consiclor further the question of the eaoplj of rifles to Af£&gt;hanintan* The follor/inc v7oro present J- l/ar Office. Sir Reginald. Paternon-, ih B. .A ? G.B. ; (far Office) (Chairman)* hr. 3i.h. Bridcos, LOG.) m peaQ113?Vi Mr. Ct. h. A. Gre t y, A. 0 o ,) A ' oa ° lXL - 8 hr. 3. i.i* Draper j G.B. ? ) Brigadier 3. Ir\ Andorsonj, G. it. G*. ^ .o. ci. C..'* j :.Ir« II.‘A LIoccrid^Gp O.LJ.G., Major J.V*. Meredith t LG0. 9 Mr, L. Collier 5 Foreirp Office. Aleut.-General Oir John GcloridyOj) xA G. 3* j G.. . (1. j J/. O', p ) Ur. J.0. V/alton? G.B. ? AGO. p ) Hr. H. A. ?o Runhold. ) India Office. Mr. A. J. Healing.o M.V.O. ? (Mar Offica) (Secretary). Tlie Qhainiian oxelainod tliat the mooting had Been nimonod to consider the position as regards the supply of these rifle a in the light of recent telegrams from the Government of India. Mr* Vial t on eaid that the telegrams indicated that the Afghans wanted iG,JCO’ of the 1914 pattern rifioc 9 after inspection and toot; that they could not pay cash for thorn ? hut would prohahly pay in six yearly instalments. The Government of India now declined to assume financial liability for theoo rifles, unless and until a decision was reached on the general question of the incidence of expenditure on metjonn affecting Afghanistan. Mr. falton added that India wore still bearing the ria’: of any Afghan dofaul - supplied by India last August. on the 5 0 GGG rif3.es The Chairman pointed out that the purpose of the meeting was to arrive - 'at oono arrangement which would enable the 1C,CLC- rifles, as a natter of urgency, to bo sent to Afghanistan. The natter v;ao complicated by the existence of the agreement under which the B.LGA. Ar/io Gompany had the sole rights of the 1914 pattern rifles, r right which they were vailling to waive in this case if they received a payment of 10s. a rifle. There was thus the danger that, in the case of l..-\ f/h. n lofault, Amy funds would be involved in out-of-poehet expenditure of 10s. to B.G.A., 5 g. for transport, and 5s.6d. for inspection, apart frau the value of the rifles thouselves, v.Iiiel. was at present asseesod nominally at £8.5.0. a rifle, but in view of the /vope.r-c.' t iiTpoonibility of selling then in any larg;e quantities this might perhaps be more properly accessed at a scrap value which was perhaps 5 s. Ho sag, os ted the possibility of issuing the rifles as a gift to Afghanistan. He ashed Mr. Mow;wridr:e to aooertain whether pay .ent wcilcl have to be made to B» if rifles wore dieoosed of as a gift to the Afghans. Ur. Bridges thought there r/ould be difficulties attendant on issuing the r if loo ao a gift, and General G ole.ridge thought that it would establish a very inconvenient precedent to make a present of the rifles to the Afghans, apart from its effect on the earlier supply of some 5,900 rifles by India. Mr. Bridges/r Ur© Bpidr:oG aclrod vliothc^ it ucio fcaoiblo to postpone tho sale until tho expiry of tho arproauent r;ith 3* G. A. in nine raonthB* tirie ? \yat tho India Cffico and Porei^pa Of:?ico roprooentatir ob atressed the need of early action© There uns diGCUBBion of tho general question incidento ootneon tho Imperial and Indian GoromnentB of expenditure in connection with Afghanistan* and hr© ;/alton ropronontod that it war. an Inporlal interest to prevent the absorption of that country into the Russian sphere© The Chairman reminded the meeting of the position taken up in the natter by the war Office before the qr.r rm Tribunal* and accepted by that Tribunal* by which Soviet intrigue in Afglianietan ? as distinct fron overt military action* was a factor for the Government of India to take into account© In answer to a question by M.r© Bridges as to whether India r;as prepared to accept part of the liability in the event of Afghan default, L;r© .b.lton mentioned that India were providing amur.ition at the rate of one million rounds a year, and they stood to lose up to £7,CpO on this account, via., the value of one year’s supply© Brigadier Anders 02 : stated that it was still the view of the General Jtaff that it was important to ensure the maintenance of friendly relations with Afghanistan. Hr. Co ll ier suggested that the liability as regards the 10,000 rifles should bo borne half-aM-lialf by the Indian and Lnporial GoveririontG, but Hr. Bridges thought thivc arrangement would tend to obscure the principles in question in tho general incideneo of /Afghanistan expenditure© After further diSQuesion, and reference to the difficulties attaching tc showing the expenditure, which might be Anouorod by an Afghan default, on India Office or Foreign Of lice votes, the Ohoir 1:121 said that since it was agreed to be a matter of urgency that tho rifles should be despatched at an early date, he would agree that the far Office should accept the financial liability in respect of tho 10,000 193.4 pattern rifles on Array votes. It was agreed that s (l) the India Office, the Govermont of India and the British Minister in :abul should be left to aahe the boot arrangements possible with the Afghan Government as regards Instalments of payment for the 10,000 1914 pattern rifles, such arranger.onts providing if practieable for repayment within three years, since on instalincnt of that nngnitudo would cover the cash expenditure of about £1 per rifle on packing and n V*® A .; ( 2 ) carriage, inspeo-ion and paynont to D Vtrv^w^v. the Trciasury aocep*^ tho liability of Imperial funds in the event of dorn’alt on the part of the Afghan Government in rospoct of those rifles, the cash expenditure in that event being borne, as a matter of convenience, on Amy votes % this acceptance of I lab; Xity boln'; without nroindiao tq^tho general question 01 xncidonoc of Afghanistan expenditure which the India Office will tai;e up with the Treasury $ /© &gt; 1 (5) /in tho event of default on the part of A^jhar-lstan, f,OT pavnents reooived from Afghaniut.an ±n roopw^t of the 5 ? 0CG rifloo supplied hy India in Aucaot, ana of tho 10 p 000 1914- pattern rifles and tno six mx.. r,iou roundo of anmunition nor; to oo supplied^irora hoai^ ^na India, ohould ho oiiarod oy Indian and Imperial fanlB in proportion to the value of tho Guorec and the -ost of the' norvicoo reopoctiyely supplied; for ^his f nurpoec the War Office would not necosoarily include the value of any 1914 pattern rif loir not paid for at tho time of default, out only the oub-of-pockct exoondituro incurred in connection uae preparation and despatch of those rifles and the payment to B* S. A* (Soley)&lt;&gt; (a) the India Office should prepare a draft tele cram to the Government of India enhodyinc oho results of the discussion and should circulate it in dra^t for ohe concurroneo of the other interested Departments* VIf \o Minute Paper. v 7.7' •W ♦ / A Department. * \J Sj \m) 1935 J ! o ^ ' &amp;(\ A[ (?c^ ^\ P.l.Uef, 5 A^i-4 At 0-*^ f£; ^- (iL ^Hr-e-Alj U, wu, 'W-'Ujvt , ^ ^ fe,™ w /• 7^,^, -c^t-, ^ ^ ^ A ^'* 'v ^ f'*- 1} 2-t'« ^ t. ^ *£ &lt;L^JH, ^ t '~(rv J *** i' *~v^ww.;L\L . •y ^C -4c^ a^I,* - v(_^ twW«WVv ^u- - * '&lt;* u * {y A. I Yj * a, ~ ^ ^ *^n. ^“v-s. ^&gt;L ^v . 2956 6000 7 34 S&lt;&gt;t L. W&lt;*Jtd*f ^r. sw/ At the meeting tfeds morning it was agreed by the W.O. a,nd Treasury representatives, after some discussion, that H.M.G. should waive their previous request for an indemnity from the G. of I. in respect of any default on payment of the price of the 10,000 rifles. In urging that H.M.G, should be prepared to undertake this liability themselves, we used only arguments based on the equity of the case as one which involves important Imperial interests (on account of the Russian menace,in its various forms) viz .. the maintenance of the stability of the Afghan Govt., the preservation in power of the present friendly Afghan Govt., and the desirability of the Afghan forces being armed with a British weapon in the event of a war in which Afghanistan was our ally . The W.O. and Treasury were influenced by the fact that the real extent of the contingent liability is considerably less than that of the purchase price of the rifles. Sir R. Patterson did not put the real value of the latter at higher than scrap value. The question whether the rifles could be supplied as a gift was discussed, but this was not pursued (and there would, indeed, be objections to it from the point of view of our Afghan policy). The rifles will therefore be sold at the price already offered (£3.5s.6d. per unit), though the real cost to the W.O. is only £1.0s.6d. per unit (£10,250 for the s 10,000, made up as follows:- 5/- freight, 5/6d. individual inspection and firing test, and 10/- which has to be paid under agreement to Messrs. Soley). At one point it was suggested that the liability should be split between the G. of I. and H.M.G. We/ rMinute Paper. Department. 2956 6000 7 34 We pointed out that the G. of I. (apart from the fact that they have already supplied 5,000 modem rifles) are prepared to incur a liability of Rs.93,000 in respect of ammunition, and that it would be equitable that the latter liability should also be divided between the two Govts, if it were proposed that the liability in respect of the 10,000 rifles should be divided. This would mean that H.M.G.'s share would be £8,500, which is not very much less than the total liability for the rifles alone. The W.0. and Treasury agreed that it was not worth while, for the sake of this difference, to delay a decision on the question pending the further correspondence with the G. of I. which a proposal to split the liability would involve. I agreed that H.M.G.’s liability could be expressed as being undertaken pending a settlement of the general question (of expenditure on Afghanistan) and without prejudice thereto. There seems no reason to suppose that the G. of I. can object to this. Sir R. Patterson also stipulated that, in the event of a general default by the Afghan Govt., any debts still outstanding to H.M.G. in respect of these rifles should rank pari passu and pro rat ft with debts due to the G. of I. This stipulation I understand to mean that if a complete cessation of payments by the Afghan Govt, should occur owing to revolution or otherwise, and that Govt, or its successor subsequently agreed to liquidate or compound for its debts, any money received in partial liquidation would be applied as it was received, pari passu and pro rata , to debts still outstanding to H.M.G. and the G. of I. The stipulation has been expressed in this way in the draft telegram. I showed/Minute Paper. Department. A 7~hsjL *£k? Jtuj &amp; 'H &lt;vv3 ^ U. 7; Y\ C'^-i-c ‘U^- C t£\-r lv''*d ^ UiaJ&lt; &gt;r^J ^ i* W(^ ~Tk^ t\h) 7vm'v+-*i * To ^ iVVwi^ ^ t ^7&gt;r jtu~) { ''i^sXi^y C++L4++/ U-j u w~, KctUsuj t^L. IW&gt;L] t &lt;UM PL »^L ^ ^ /-^cU showed this to Sir R. Paterson, drawing special attention to this part of the draft, he quite concurs in the draft as it stands, as he considers it gives sufficient expression to the principle he has in mind, although, m reply to my questions, he stated that he also meant that (a) in the event of default the payments already received would be brought into a common account and adjusted between H.M.G* and the G. of I. in the proportion of the totals of the original expenditure, and (b) that in the event (which seems very improbabr/) of the Afghans defaulting on their debt to H.M.G. but not on that to the G. of !• (or vice versa). the amounts of further payments on the debt which continued to be met would be brought into the pool (which in the improbable event envisaged would seem to be only equitable) Incidentally, it seems to me that the adjustment _ * / , ,, / inci /VX cV%y J* r * p'j * * &gt;v/u ; contemplated in (a) would be more likely to work out ^1, favourably to the G. of I. than otherwise, because Sir R. Paterson contemplates that the amount for which H.M.G. would rank as creditor would not necessarily be the purchase price of the rifles - about £30,000 - but would probably be their actual out'of pocket expenditure - about £10,000; there is also the possibility that the Afghan Govt -flr+JrJL lr+ — ^ J ~ u cv_ f^r-A. ^ b*-r{r r&gt; L* Ivccjl. ^ ^ ^ A*-*-***!^ iL-y 0 *i. ^CjV. ' it 2956 6000 7 34 may pay the purchase price of the W.0. rifles over a /£&lt;w A Ax L /&lt;tY. shorter period of instalments; if they should agree, for example, to payment in three instalments, H.M.G. would have f recovered their actual expenditure by payment of one instalment; even if the Afghan Govt, do not agree to less than six instalments, two of these would cover the &lt;V.0. expenses. ^ ' z *y^ tf. * ^ ^ ^ It was arranged at the meeting that I should prepare draft telegrams for the concurrence of the *V.G., F.0. and Treasury. Drafts are submitted, which at the same time are being simultaneously sent to the F.0. and Treasury for concurrence or observations. I have shown them to Sir/ J fMinute Paper. Department. © 3436b 5000 1/35 Sir R. Paterson, and the W.O. concur in them. A second draft telegram to the G. of !• is also attached, referring to the question of the additional supply of 15,000 rifles, which will require further consideration from the political as well as the financial point of view. IS. A 7T Please see Mr. Bridges’s letter of 16th November now attached. The Treasury suggest a few modifications in the draft telegrams which do not seem to present any difficulty. The effect of their principal modification is to express the acceptance of the liability as provisional, and subject to review in the light of the general settlement, besides being (as we have expressed it) ’’pending a decision on the general question and without prejudice thereto”. I should not think that the G* of I. could have any objection to the additional formula. It is part of their proposals for a general settlement that they should give the guarantee required at the expense of their fund. In the draft telegram to Kabul the Treasury desire a somewhat more definite instruction to Col. Fraser- Tytler to press for payment of the first instalment on receipt of the rifles. We need not, 1 think, object to this. It is not intended that the sale should be made dependent on the Afghan Govt, accepting the arrangements regarding instalments for which the Minister is instructed to press. The conclusion of the meeting on 14th November was that the 1.0. and the Minister should be left to make the best arrangements possible with the Afghan Govt, regarding instalments. We mi^it instruct Col. Fraser-1 ytler to report the replies of the Afghan Govt, on the points raised. rL i ^ ^ rr 3 . I 'VWIA OFFICE, WlflTKHA .L S.W.l. P.2.8333/36. 20th November, 1936. / With reference to the supply of 10,000 rifles to the Afghan Govern ent, the Indie Office eees no objection to the modificetiomi pro oeed in Bridges's letter of 16th received Collier's concurrence in the telegrams which have been despatched with a few further modifications made in the India Office* I enclose copies of he telegrams* Vie do not suppose that the Government of India will have anything further to say to the proposals, but think it desirable, if only as a matter of form, to get their express concurrence* We h ve therefore added at the end o^ the longer telegran to them an instruction to telegra h to Fraeer-Tytler if they agree that action may now be taken as pro x&gt;sed; and we have commenced the telegram to Fraser- Tytler with the words 'Subject to the concurrence of the Govern sent of India, please take the fol owing action'• At the end of the telegram to Fraser-Tytler we h? ve also November, of which he sent you a copy. Ve hr ve also Sir R. Paterson, K*B*E., C*B., War Office, S.W.l. instructed/Instructed him to negotiate the sale of anmmltion which the Government of Indir are willing to supply on the conditions stated hy them* As regards the instructions to Fraser-Tytier to press for three, or at most four, annual instalments and for payment of the first instalment to he made on receipt of the rifles, re are instructing him to report the replies of the Afghan Oovemment on these points. 7 e understand that it was not the intention of the meeting on 14th November to make the sale of the rifles absolutely dependent on the /fghen Government accepting the arrangements proposed regarding instalments, but t at, as stated in the first conclusion of the record, s ould be left to make the best arrangements ossible. Yours sincerely. (&amp;i.) J. C. WALTOKDepartment. ? 9 NOV Ccr'C-C^Lx/v- With reference to Bridges’s letter to me of 16th November, of which he sent you a copy, I enclose copy of ariet ter 'wrth revised cnpiea-ef the two draft telegrams regarding the supply of rifles to the Afghan Govt ^ ■ , uz) 7 u ^ ^ ^ ^ Void* sincerely. (Sd.) J. C. V IDRAFT TELEGRAM. SECRETARY OF STATE &gt; TO GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, FOREIGN AND POLITICAL DEPARTMENT. (Retamilla) FORMINKA PESHAWAR Cypher XXX 4 *•** J BENffeR’S INI I Copy to/W^O. .&lt;aVF.O- % v&lt; ^. N ' / Treaaary ^lily. W' .u° U v 1935 j 3720- Addressed by S repeated to h.M. Minister, [Kabul .tfo. 112, of S. for I. to G. of I; AO \ rfh/ s' ^ Your telegram 30th October, Ho. 2972/ Offer of rifles to Afghan Govt r 2. H.M.G. note that you are unable to give the indemnity suggested in para, 4 af my telegram of 27th July, No. 2364, until general principle of incidence of expenditure on Afghanistan is settled and money becomes available through establishment of your proposed fund for discharge of such indemnity in the event of a default of payment^by Afghan Uovt.^ If, however, H.M.G. could supply the 10,000 rifles without such indemnity from you, you would be pre pared to supply acmunition in annual instalments of 1,000,000 rounds (I presume up to the 6,000,000 rounds in all mentioned in para. 2(b) of Kabul - —* + telegram of 12th September, No. 96) on the system of deferred payment described in para. 3 of your telegram, under which the credit allowed to Afghan Govt, in respect of such ammunition would be limited to'^ Rsl93,000 f 1550 500 1.33 rrrr T ' / 3. In these circumstances, H.M.G., having regard to the importance of^ meeting the Afghan 7 request for 10,000 rifles without further delay, are prepared/(1,ablest) ON HIS MAJESTY’S SEKVICE. FASTEN Envelope by gumming this Label across Flap. OPEN by cutting Label instead of tearing Envelope. __HIS MAJES TY'S SEUYICE K ' r ‘' ope r thi a ncross j — ^cutting Label instead of fearing Envelope.3938 Draft Paper. Department. ii^i i prepared, pending a decision on the general question and without prejudice thereto, to accept provisionally (and subject to review in the light of the / / / / general settlement) the liability involved in the supply of 10,000 rifles'to / / / / the Afghan Oovt. against'payment by / instalments, without insisting on their z / ! / — / previous request for an mdemnityi The y ( ^3 V\a r LJ hTi (1 ”1 r% r* ^ / . / decision reached by h.M.Cje is also 'subject to the following understanding, viz ., if as a/result of revolution or otherwise there is a cessation of payment s due from I Afghan Uovt. to G. of I. and H.M.G., then 1 in the event of'partial liquidation of x these debts being subsequently resumed, any debt outstanding in respect of 10,000 rifles would rank pari passu and pro rata with debts due to U. of I. in respect of 5,000 rifles'already supplied and / anmunition supply‘of which is now contemplated. 4.^ Please see 1 Porminka 1 No. 1 113 dated l and telegraph to Fraser- ~ r i 1 i V \ Tytler ('repeating to' me) if you agree that action may now be ^taken as proposed/DRAFT TELEGRAM. SECRETARY OF STATE TO GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, FOREIGN AND POLITICAL DEPARTMENT. (Retamilla) ^ORMINKA PESHAWAR. &gt;1' ■ / r° \ p ' p. z. 8 555 nil- Addressed by S« 1955 J ^ ^ / of S. for I. to G. of I . ^ y / repeated to H.M. Minister, Kabul bio.f/j. telegram datedv^37^^ #0 /^^^^Rifles^for^Afghanistan. H.M.G.^have not 'dealt with question of supply of additional 15,000 'rifles as this requires further consideration^from the point of view of 'policy'^apart from the ^ ^ S' question of incidence). H.M.G. will ^ / S in due course consult you and H.M. Minister^further'in regard to political ''aspect of this question^ with reference to Kabul telegram of 28th October,^No. 127,'ejid^ ^ ^ s S S expression of G. of I.'s view in first sentence of para. 5“of your telegram of 29th June^No. 1586.^ 1 fyvtsSs Tdephone No.: Whitehall 1234. In reply please quote Regd. No. ( jy 7~ ) I 8333 i ] 9?5 5 Jr.KEA^UR¥^CHAMBERS, WHITEHALL, S.W.l. 16 November 19^5. Near dalton. Many thanks for your letter of the 15th, t enclosing copies of the draft telegrams to H.M. Minister at Kabul and to the Government of India. I suggest the following redraft of the first sentence of the concluding paragraph of the telegram to the Government of India :- 'In these circumstances, H.M.G., having regard to the importance of meeting the Afghan request for 10,000 rifles without further delay, are prepared, pending a decision on the general question and without prejudice thereto, to accept provisionally r (and subject to review in the light of the general settlement) the liability involved in the supply of 10,000 rifles to the Afghan Government against payment by instalments, without insisting on their previous request for an indemnity.' de have a few very trivial amendments to suggest J.G. dalton, 3sq., C.3., M.C., India Office. /on&gt; / on the draft telegram to H.M. Minister at Kabul. The last sentence of the first long paragraph might, we think, read as follows n tfe should also press for payment of the first instalment to be made on receipt of the rifles.” The last two lines of the telegram might read as follows ”To recover this expenditure from the first, or at most, the first two instalments of the purchase price.” I am sending copies of this letter to Paterson at the &lt;/ar Office and to Collier at the Foreign Office. Yours sincerely,* INDIA OFFICE. IHITEHALL, S..7. 1. loth November # 193b. Vy deir Collier, As arrm^ed at the r.eetin^:: at the ar office yesterday, 1 enclose tvc draft telegrane to the Govermrient of Indi i and Kabul about the 10,000 rifles for the ifghan Government. Paterson has seen and concurs in them. Could you kindly let rr.e know whether you concur or have my observations'.' I nn writing also to bridges. 1 also enclose the draft of a shorter telegram to the f ovemnent of India promising further con -ultation vith them in regard to the nuestion of lb t C00 additional rifles. The Government of India in their telegram of 29th June said that they considered that the initial offer should be definitely limited to Ib.OOO (out of the 30,000 asked for). Since then we have not had anything useful from the Government of India on the question whether it is politic to supply more than lL&gt; t OOO already arranged for. Eraser-Jytler in his telegram of 28th October has iven some reasons for doing so, but it will be desirable Ii. Collier, Lao., to, mmm office. S.7. i.t to consult the Govemnsent of India also again on the subject. There is, however» no immediate hurry about this. (Sgd.) J.C. Walton./ ' / ' / / INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL, S.W. 1 15th November, 1935. Uy dear Bridges, as arranged at the reetin at the War Office yesterday, I enclose two draft teiegrans to the ovemi ent of India an i Kabul about the 10,000 rifles for the Afghan Government. Paterson has seen and concurs in them. &lt; ould you kindly let me kno^ whether you concur or have any observations? (Sgd.) J.C.Walton. E.E. Bridges, Esq., L.C., H.L. Treasury, S.W. 1.DRAFT TELEGRAM. SECRETARY OF STATE TO GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, FOREIGN AND POLITICAL DEPARTMENT. FOHMINKA (Retamilla) PESHAWAR Ujpi— h * , V'. 1550 500 1.33 Addressed by S. of S. for I. to G« of I.; repeated to H.LL Minister, Kabul. Your telegram 30th October, Mo. 2972. Offer of rifles to Afghan Govt. ^ H.M.G. note that you are unable to give the indemnity suggested in para. 4 of my telegram of Z^th July, No. 2364, until general principle of incidence of expenditure on Afghanistan is settled and money becomes available through establishment of your proposed fund for discharge of such indemnity in the event of a default of payment by Afghan Govt. If, however, H.M.G. could supply the 10,000 rifles without such indemnity from you, you would be prepared to supply acmunition in annual instalments of 1 , 000,000 rounds (I presume up to the 6 , 000,000 rounds in all mentioned in para. 2 (b) of Kabul telegram of 12th September, No. 96) on the system of deferred payment described in para. 3 of your telegram, under which the credit allowed to Afghan Govt, in respect of such ammunition would be limited to Rs.93,000. 3 In these circumstances H.M.G., having regard to the political importance of meeting the Afghan request for 10,000 rifles without further/Department. further delay, are prepared, pending a decision on the general question and without prejudice thereto, to undertake the liability involved by the supply of these rifles on credit to the Afghan Govt, without insisting on their previous request for an indemnity. The decision reached by H.M.G. is also subject to the following understanding, viz .. if as a result of revolution or otherwise there is a cessation of payments due from Afghan Govt, to G. of I. and H.M.G., then in the event of partial liquidation of these debts being subsequently resumed, any debt outstanding in respect of 10,000 rifles would rank pari passu and pro rata with debts due to G. of I. in respect of 5,000 rifles already supplied and anxnunition supply of which is now contemplated. USrJDraft Paper. Department. MEL TELEGRAM : JfORMINKA PESHAWAR fr-y t ta/ 1 3938 5090 7.35 From S. of S. for F.A. to H.M. Minister, Kabul. Please see telegram from S. of S. for !• to G. of I. Wo. dated regarding supply of 10,000 rifles. ^ ^ You should now resume your negotiations for sale of these rifles at a price of £3 per rifle complete with bayonet, scabbard, oil bottle and pull- through, delivered at Karachi, plus 5/6d. per rifle for an individual inspection and fir invest. H.M.G. note that Afghan Govt, state that they could only buy on deferred payments, and that they suggest six equal annual instalments. You should press strongly for a reduction of the number of instalments to three, or at most four, in view of the fact that a much smaller sum is involved in the purchase of these rifles than in that of the 5,000 rifles from G. of I., price of which annual is to be paid in six^instalments. You should also press for payment,of instalments in advance, i.e., first instalment to be paid on receipt of the rifles. ^ For your own information, H.M.G. attach/Department. fU attach importance to shortening^period of payment because, though these rifles do not constitute a very important item in their reserve, their supply involves imnediate expenditure of upwards of £10,000 in respect of freight, inspection and test, and payment under agreement to Messrs. Soley, Ltd., and they hope that it will be possible to cover this expenditure in one or two instalments of the purchase price. .A'p/vA yfciJ W /&gt; '&gt; 4 i *}. ^ ^ ^ 37 a .&lt; 30 ; 14 of A Gonforenoo r:ac hold at the Jar Office on Thuz’ctlay p 4th h r ovc;foor f to consider further the question of the su;,)pl t y f rifles to Afghanistan. The follor/ing vroro present •Sir Reginald Paterson? ih B. h ? 0.3. ^ (' v ar 0 ffice) (Cha 1 man) l.Po Bria^oa, i ‘*0. ) rp. 0 Mr. Of. JS. A. Grey, M. 0. 1 ' oasa3? - ° ) ) ) V/ar Office, Mr. B. li. Draper, G.B. P Brigadier j 0 1 \ Andorson„ 0.11. G« , D. ci. 0. p Hr. II. VA IJoggridgo, G. M. G. , r.Ia;] or cT. Y. Meredith ? I.. G» ? Mr. Lc Collier r . Poroicn Office. Mior^t.-General Sir Jolm Goloridge,) /&gt;-. G. , 0. .C‘» * «/. o. 0. p Mr. J. Go V/alton? 0. B. ? M. G. p Mr. M. A. ?o Rusholdp India Office. Mr, Menlinn;? M. Y.O. , {'far Office) (Secretary) The OhaImnn osnlaincd tlxat the iriooting had been nimonod to consider the position as regards the supply of these rifles in the light of recent telegrams from the Government of India. Mr. 1/aIton said that the telegrams indicated that the Afghans wanted To, 000 of the 1914 pattern rifles, after inspection and tost? that they could not pay cash for them? but would probably pay in nix yearly instalments. The Government of India now declined to assume financial liability for these rifles, unless and until a decision was reached on the general question of the incidence of expenditure on matters affecting Afghanistan. Mr. Mai ton added that India wore still bearing the Pi s’: of any Afghan default on the 5,000 rifles supplied by India last August. The Chairman pointed out that the purpose of the meeting was to arrive at ceno arrangement which would enable the 1C,OX rifles, as a natter of urgency, to bo sent to Afghanistan. The matter was complicated by the existence of the agreement under which the B. S. A. Arris Company had the sole rights of the 1914 pattern rifles, r right which they wore willing to waive in this case if they received a payment of 10s. a rifle. There was thus the danger that, in the case of i i j -i., - . n le fault, Amy funds would bo involved in out-of-poeI:et expenditure of 10s. to B.B.A. , 5s. for transport, and 5s.6d. for inspootion, apart from the value of the rifles themselves, v/hlcl: wao at present acnossod noriinally at £2.5.0. a rifle, but in view of the np • rc' t hinosoibility of selling then in any large quantities this might perhaps bo more properly aooossed at a scrap value which was perhaps 5s. He sag ’ested the possibi.lr.ty of issuing the rifles as a gift to Afghanistan. He ashed Mr. Moggridgo to ascertain whether pay icnt wcild Jmvq to be made to B. e.A. if rifles wore diswosed of as a gift to the Afghans. Mr. Bridges thought them would be GifxMcultios attendant on issuing the rifles as a gift, and General Goleridge thought that it would establish a very inconvenient precedent ^ to toaho a present of tho rifles to the Afgiians, apart from its effect on the earlier supply of sane 5,900 rifles by India. Mr. Bridges/( 3 )/ Ur© Brlcl; :og aclzod uliGulior it uao fcaoi'blo to postpone the sale until the ezplv-j of tho aercanent uith 3. G. A. in nine months ? tine 9 hut the India Office and Porei^n Office popncoentatir’OB stroGacd the need of early action* There r;ne diGcuooion of the {jencral questioners the incidence he117con tho Imperial and Indian Govorments of expenditure # in connection with Afahonistan* and hr* ;/alton roprcDcntod that it tear, an Inporial interest to prevent the ahsorption of that country into the RugG ian sphere* The Chairaian raninclod the meeting of the position taken up in the natter hy the war Office before the~ Garrcn Trihunalj and accepted by that Tribunal^ hy which Soviet intr:i{pie in Afr;haniGtan ? an distinct fron overt military action^ was a factor for the Government of India to take into account* In answer to a question hy I4r* 3ridr:es as to whether India was prepared to accept part of the liability in the event of Afchar, default, Hr. halt on mentioned that India wore providing ammunition at tho rate of one million rounds a year, and they stood to lose up to £7,000 cn this account, via*, the value of one year 1 g supply* Briradior Aadoraoi: stated that it was still the view of the General dtaff that it wac important to ensnare the main.tonance of froicndly relations with Afchxuoistan* n?:-o Q oil lor sucroeted that the liability as regards ICpCVj rifles should ho home hfUf-ancl-half hy the Indian Bridm^: ohcuc?A this ho 1C, and Imperial Govornments, :;uii uz arranG^mont would tc^d to obscure tho principles in question in the cenoval incidence of Afghanistan expenditure© After further discucsion, and reference to the. difficultios cattaching to showing the expenditure, which might be ^inourrod by an Afghan default, on India Office or Foreign Of fice votes, tho Qhaiman said that since it was agreed to be a natter of urgency that the rifles should be despatched at an early date, he would agree that the war Office should accept the financial liability in respect of tho 10,000 1914 pattern rifles on Amy votes* (I) (2) It was agreed »&gt;x-&lt; the India Office, the Gororznont British minister in fabul ohcula of he best arrangements possible with tho ro; India)and the left to mabo the Afghan Government r) n.tte.r:a ::ardr, inetnlnenta of payment for the 10,000 1914 rifles, such arran^;cmontG providing if practicable for repayment within throe years, since an instatoont of that magnitude would cover the cash expenditure of about £1 per rifle cn packing and cnrriage, inspect % and payment to B. 9. A* ; the Sraasnry accept tho liability of Imperial funds in tho event of default on tho cart of the Afghan Covorrcpont in respect of those* rifles, the cash expenditure in that event being borne, as a matter of convenience, on Army vetoes thin acceptance of liability being without prejudice to the general question of incidence of Afghanistan expenditure which the India Office will tape up with the Treasury;in tho event of default on the port of Afghanistan,, raiy parents received from Afghaniotan in rospoet of the 5,000 rifles supplied hy India in August, and of the 10,000 1914 pattern rifles and tho six million rounds of ammunition now to oe supplied from homo and India, should he shared 'by Indian and Imperial funds in proportion to tho value of tho stores and the cost of the services respectively supplied; for this purpose the War Office would not necessarily include the value of any 1914 pattern rifles not paid for at the time of default, hut only the out-of-poefcet expenditure incurred in connection with the preparation and despatch of those rifles and the payment to B. 8.A. (Soley). (4) the India Office should prepare a draft telegram to the Goverrr.tent of India embodying the results of tlie discussion and should circulate it in draft for the concurrence of the other interested Departments®4F &amp; .UC/DIA. P.Z.' ) 81 SO {82 g l oupt;955 J h^) SECRET yc. i /^ 1 {&gt; (COPIES CIRCULATED) nECYPHE R OP TE 1. .E Q_iLA-% • - ^ ‘fi’roiii GoveiTiment u ' 1 jnciia. P'ore'xgn i u/ Political. Department ? to Secretary oi '^ lv ' State for India. - Dated New Delhi, 13th November, 1935, Received 13th November, 1935, 6^15 pcm,. XXX 3Q8JL Addressed to Secretary of State, v ^ I 3082, repeated to Kabul, 382^ Katodon 127« Supply of rifles to Afghanistan, if 7 A .j .^3 2 C AS already explained in our telegram 2972* we are unable to go any further than we have agreed therein until the question of principle between His Majesty s Government and ourselves has been decided in a manner ^hich will enable us to set up the proposed fund of five lakhs of rup see annually« 3 V We do not „ tiierfcfcra* wish to olfer any comments on the merits of the proposals made by Minister with regard to rifles and ammunition until our main contention has been conceded by His Majesty^ Government* 4 0 Regarding Katodom 128, Aeroplane Sc We are add reeling you separatelyMinute Paper. Department. 2956 6000 7 34 Supply of rifles to Afghan Govt. U.S.S ., F. 9L^J: The Afghan request is for 30,000 rifles altogether. It is generally agreed that 15,000 would be not too many to let them have. Five thousand modern rifles were supplied by the G. of I. urgently last August. Since then we have had under discussion the supply of 10,000 1914 pattern rifles from War Office stocks. Col. Fraser-Tytler has made a tentative offer of these to the Afghan Govt, at a price of £3 per unit, excluding ammunition, and though their first reactions were not favourable, they have now asked for them at this price, subject to individual inspection and test at an additional cost of 5/6d. per unit. They say, however, that they can only make deferred payments, and suggest six equal annual instalments. A decision is held up by the question of incidence, because the W.0. stipulated that (pending a decision on the general question of expenditure on Afghanistan) the G. of I. should agree to indemnify H.M.G, in respect of any loss by default of payment, and the G. of I. (telegram of 30th October) decline to give this indemnity until the general principle which they have separately proposed in regard to Afghan expenditure is accepted and money becomes available through the establishment of their proposed fund. We have been discussing with the G. of I. the method of approaching the Treasury on the general question (see papers on separate file). If we are now in a position to approach the Treasury, and if they agree to the proposed principle, it is probable that money//l . /a Yr 2956 6000 7 34 Minute Paper. Department. money 'jvould be available from the fund to make good defaults on instalments of the price of 10,000 rifles at £3.5s.6d. per unit (but even this is not quite certain, as we do not know what other calls there may be on the fund, and there might be a big call on it for subsidising an Indo-Afghan civil air service, and another possibly for X ^ — — _ . • _ — T_ _ T _! U. _ — _ \ l. ‘ t ^I* /r ^_ * matter of some importance and urgency to supply the number of rifles in question (in accordance with the spirit of a Cabinet decision of 193^), it is a question whether we might not urge the W.0« and Treasury to waive their request for an indemnity. Any loss on the rifles would be largely a paper loss, as they form part of an existing reserve which is never likely to be called on. When the matter was discussed at a meeting at the W.O. on 19th July, it was agreed that the G. of I. should first be asked to shoulder the contingent liability, but I indicated that if they declined to do so, we might then raise the matter again with the W.O. and Treasury. I think that there is a feeling in some branches of the W.O. itself that it would be a pity, merely on account of reasons which are largely technical, to forgo the political advantage to be gained by supplying these rifles to the Afghan Govt. The W.O. have now calleda further meeting on the question for 14th November, at which we can ascertain whether they will be willing to meet us further. their request for an indemnity, they on their side would make themselves responsible for the supply of ammunition (the Afghan Govt, do not want the W.O. ammunition). The G. of I. say that if h.M.G. would waivePHBBI near draper, ? any thanks for your letter of 9th ftovember. I «hall be very glad to come to the meeting at the i¥ar Office at 11 o’clock on 14th November. B. ! . Draper, Esc., C.B., WAR OFFICE, S.W. 1.The War Office, Whitehall, S.W.l. 9th November, 1935. Dear Walton, You will recollect attending a conference held under Paterson's Chairmanship on the 18th July last, about a proposed sale of rifles and ammunition to Afghanistan. No sale has yet taken place, but further developments have occurred in correspondence with India which render the reassembly of the conference necessary. Paterson will again preside, and would like to hold the conference on Thursday next, the 14th November at 11 o'clock in Room 254 at this Office. Can you make it convenient to attend? Yours sincerely. J.C.Walton, Esq., India Office, King Charles Street, S.W.l.F!LE COPY / T) r f O r ) &lt;’ \ SECRET FJE/UM, (81 groups «&gt;) /822 1955 J 5814. OJLUPJLO. . OF T E L E 8 R k M,_ From Gorernment of India. Forsign and Political Department, to Secretary of State for India. Dated New Delhi, 30th October. .1S35. XXX Received 11.0 a„m,, 30th October, 1935. IMPORTANT. Ji22£i Private an d Personal. Metcalfe to Walton. Our official telegram . ''9/2, October 30th, was drafted and agreed to by the other departments before receipt of Katodon 127 and 128, on which our comments will be telegraphed as soon as possible. Attempt to revise the draft in the light of the minister's comments would have caused delay, and also jeopardised the concession regarding ammunition, which was only- agreed to with great difficulty. I anticipate no charge in our attitude as the result of Fraser Tytler’s remarks, and am convinced that we shall agree to nothing more until the question of principle is decided.5 copy or 7 9 00 SECRET FCN/DIA, (69 groups) 5879 c DEG _P J E R OF T E L £ G R.AJt - From His Majesty’s Minister at Kabul to Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, India Office., Dated Kabul, 2nd November, 1935c Received 2nd November, 1935, 5 p*nu SQLQ* Private and personal* Frase 3 &gt;Tytler for Walt one Foreign’s express letter F,387(ll)F/35, dated the 25th October, 1935^ Actions of the Afghan Government during the recent hostilities* Government as seen from here in my Despatch NodlG, dated 23rd October^ which will reach you on 18th November* Should be grateful if you would delay consideration of the views setforth in Foreign's express letter till receipt of my Despatcbu XXX 2 0 I ha/e summarised the actions of the Afghan Praser»Tytler 1 30. November 2ndmmm FfLE COPY 7^V HTP/AW. (12 groups) • 5833 DBCYPHBR OF TBLBGRAM , From Government of India, Foreign and Political Department, to COPIES Seoretaiy of State for India* CIRCULATED) Dated New Delhi, 30th October, 1935* Received 30th October, 1935, 4 0 45 p 0 m a _____ X Addressed to Secretary of State and repeated to Kabul* My telegram No*105 to Kabul should be renumered 370«JRL/iffiL FfL r* (132 groups,) ~p: 7823 1955 J T SECRET / cM 5812 DEC Y P H E R OF T E L E G R A M. v (COPIES CIRCULATED) From Government of India, Foreign and Political Department, to Secretary of State for India&lt; Dated New Delhi, 30th October, 1925. Received 10.45 a.m., 20th October, 1925. — XXX 2972, First of Several Parts* • 3Jt&gt; Addressed to Secretary of State and repeated to Kabul, Your telegram of the 19th instant, 3369* Forminka 104 an d express letter P*Zo6798/35, 18th October* Proposals for assistance to Afghanistan, 2, We are glad to feel that we have your sympathy and support for principle which we are seeking to establish, and appreciate your anxiety to translate our proposals into form more likely to be acceptable to His Majesty^s Government, There is ? however, material difference between vague assurance suggested at conclusion of paragraph No,2 of your express letter and liability sought to be imposed by paragraph No.5 of our telegram 2475 ^, Our suggestions for bridging this gulf will follow by air mail letter very shortly, and we now only wish to make it clear that your alternative suggestions are not acceptable, and that proposals for immediate action which follow should not be taken to imply abandonment of position taken up in our telegram 2475,SECRET jrl/fhb/mm 5810 (COPIES CIRCULATED) DECYPHER OF TELEGRAM* From Gorernment of India. Foreign and Political Department, to Received 10*15 aari Dated Secretary of State for India* New Delhi, 30th October, 1935* 10*15 aom*, 30th October, 1935 XXX 2972 Part Two S'** S’. 3« We were strorgly disposed at first to decline to consider any further concession to Afghanistan until the general principle was decided, and this view was reinforced by recent events on Mohmand frontier which suggest that both value of Afghan Government’s friendship and its instability have perhaps been over-estimated. Moreover, we feel that argument used in paragraph No*^ of your telegram 3364 would mat at is mutandis be equally applicable against the acceptance of any other liability by His Majesty’s Government* We cannot therefore agree either to give any such indemnity as is proposed in respect of 10,000 (? Lee-Metford) rifles, to be supplied by His Majesty’s Government nor to supply aeroplanes on deferred payments unless and until general principle is decided and money becomes available through establishment of proposed fund*SECRET ee/aw. iq* (153 groups) jD E C Y P H E R OF T E L E G R A M. 5813. Rrom Government of India, Foreign and Political Department, to Secretary of State for India. (COPIES CIRCULATED) Dated Uew Delhi, 30th October, 1935, Received 30th October, 1935, 10.45 a.m, 2972 . Third Part. 9£LL?J-lj:&gt; we cannot agree to give any indemnity at present for additional 15,000 rifles. Since, however, we recognise that discussion may take some time and meantime Afghan Government ought to (? receive) some further reply on the subject of these 10,000 rifles, we are prepared to give immediate assistance over ammunition, if His Majesty's Government on their part agree to supply rifles without any indemnity from us. Our assistance would take following form. We will give, simultaneously with arrival of the rifles in India, one million rounds, charger packed, on deferred payment of Rs. 93,000, after one year. similarly, as soon as first instalment is paid, we would give another million rounds on sam., terms. This scheme follows closely that suggested in paragraph Ho.4 of Formlnka 104, and is in our opinion preferable on all grounds to the simultaneous supply of (? six) million rounds, it will however involve us in advanced payment „o Indian Military authorities, who must undertake immediate replacement of stock and cannot afford to wait for payment of Afghan instalment, even if that is punctually paid. XXXSECRET K£/FJt;/DIA. f p. z7'~l 7823 ( f t ' fi-Sj£JLLJL£JB_£LZ 5811c Prom Government of India, Foreign and Political Department, to Secretary (COPIES of State for India* CIRCULATED) Dated New Delhi, 30th October, 1935. Received 30th October, 1935, 10^*20 adiu XXX momma* Mis* 4* This disposes of questions raised in your telegram, 3369, except that asked in paragraph No«6 about types of aeroplanes, which is perhaps academic, unless His Majesty’s Government are prepared to supply on deferred payment* If, however, you still wish for our views we will telegraph separately* With regard to Forminka JL04 , we agree that the question of 10,000 rifles should be dealt with separately and immediately and hope that the Minister will be able to postpone or protract discussion of other requests until principles of division of the charges are decided*INDEXED s- A FJE/AW. (136 groups) DECTPHBR OP TELBGRA SECRET ip (\*i\ XL iv V © v«' From His Majesty’s Minister at Kabul to Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs. India Office, (COPIES CIRCULATED) Dated Kabul, 28th October, 1935* Received 28th October, 1935, 4 p.m* First of Six Parts. XXX t Addressed to Secretary of State, and repeated to Foreign.Formi nka 104 o Supply of further 15,000 rifles. 2. Supply of total quantity of munitions asked for in January (Katodon 10 paragraph Ho.2) is, I understand, considered not unreasonable from military point of view. Question to what extent request should be met depends therefore on the following considerations^ (a) Whether portions of the sum involved could not be better utilised on other forms of assistance; (b) Whether the risks involved in complying with the Afghan Government’s request are greater than those involved in refusing them. 3, As regards (?(a)^ If request for a full supply of munitions (? were) refused Afghan Ministers would enquire reason. if i were in a position to reply that the balance of credit offered, say total of £500,000, was available for other forms of assistance of greater mutual benefit, Afghans might accept the position and turn elsewhere for balance of munitions. End of first part f second jp&amp; rt follows . Fraser Tytler 127, October 28th. . . -- - i ^ ' 1 — —SECRET EE/HJM, (103 groupso) 5776 „ S D E C Y P HER 0 P T E L E G-.B A 11 . (COPIES CIRCULATED) From His Majesty’s Minister at Kabul to Secretary of State for foreign Affairs, India Office- Dated Kabul, 28th October, 1935. Received 4 p.m., 28th October, 1935. XXX Second Part* As, however, His Majesty r s Government have decided that the grant of assistance of this kind must be preceded by enquiry(ies) by sxpero&amp;, acceptance of which by the Afghan Government seems for political reasons to be impossible, I should not be in a position to make any (? concrete) offer* It is also possible that even if 1 could do so, Minister might reply that no assistance could be of greater mutual benefit than increase of stability of Afghan Government, which would result from strengthening of the Armyo UPhile, therefore, possibility cannot be ruled out that Afghan Government may require other forms of assistance in the next few years, which it may be difficult for His Majesty's Government to refuse, only possible course in the present circumstances seems to be to consider the question of supplying munitions as separate issueo Erago r Tytler 127. October 28th.SECRET © UC/MM. (113 groups.) 5773. (COPIES CIRCULATED) BJLC_Y.,.P HER OF T e From Hie Majesty’s Minister at Kabul to Secretpy of State for Foreign Affairs, India Office. Dated Received Kabul, 28th October, 1935. 3.30 p.m., 28th October, 1935. XXX Third Part. 4, As regards (b). Risks of imolTed are as follows i. In complying with request, His Majesty's Gorernment and the Gofernment of India might lose their money. Risk is apparent and requires no emphasis. Against it must be planed the fact that the Afghan Government is showing increased stability and has every intention of paying. I believe that if the present Government remains in power and does not go bankrupt obligations will be met in full. 11 ° In refusing the request, there is the risk that the Afghan Government may fail through lack of munitions. This risk is at present slight and, in any case, if we refuse to supply, munitions will probably be purchased elsewhere. More important 18 the rask that ref u3al to supply may be looked upon as unfriendly act. Prase rTytler 127. October 28th.SECRET A se/wb (COPIES CIRCULATED) 5 0 This risk is serious 0 In the spring Afghan Gorernment asked for our assistance with credits and munitions,, We made enquiry by an expert condition precedent to consideration of former 0 However reasonable request may have been, it now appears to be politically unacceptable to the Afghan Government, who turned to Germany for their requirements 0 They are now negotiating with Soviet for extension of commercial agreement,, If this is concluded, comraerci.al penetration by Soviet will increase, and with it, difficulty of resisting political penetration« 6 0 If, at this point, we refuse request for reasonable supply of munitions on the ground that we fear to risk the loss of sum which will probably not exceed £200,000 ? Prime Minister may find great difficulty in persuading the Afghan Government, who have had recent cause to question sincerity of our professed desire for stability, that it is worth while to continue to look to us as a genuine friend and supporter,, Fraser T.vtler 127. October 28fcho ( 1£7 groupso) 5777o D E C Y P H B R OF T E L F G R A -M, From His Majesty f s Minister at Kabul to Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, India Office&lt;, Dated Kabul, 28th October, 1935„ Received 4 p o 0 io 3 28th October, 1935„ FOURTH PARTo XXXSECRET KJtf/AWo (127 groups) 5787 fc D E C Y P H E R 0 E T E L E G R A M o From His Majesty’s Minister at Kabul to Secretary of State for Foreign (COPIES Affairs, India Office c CIRCULATED) Dated Kabul, through Peshawar, 28th October, 1935« Received 28th October, 1935, 8 C 30 p®m« XXX Fifth Part , 7 e It ia for His Majesty’s Government to say which of these risks (? it is better to) face, but it -jeems preferable to endeavour to minimise them as far as possible* With this end in view* I make the following suggestions, * Rifles* inform the Afghan Government that: . (a) Their request for 10,000 will be complied with and delivery will be completed by the end of March next* (b) 15 3 000 rifles of 3.914 pattern will be supplied as soon as they have been tested and delivery will be completed by the end of 3936* bayonets and Rifles include/all accessories* Payment to be made in 6 yearly Instalment e. Ammunition* it is noted that Afghan request for 30,000 rifles includes ammunition^ On the basis of 600 rounds $er rifle, 15,000,000 rounds remain to be supplied « E nd of Fij't h part, sixth part follows ^ Eraser Tytl er 127^ Octo b er SB*C5 SECRET JGS/A¥ 0 (93 groups) 5738 0 I; S C_ Y P H B R OP TEL J G_ R_A M, From His Majesty’s Minister at Kabul to Secretary of State for (COPIES Foreign Affairs,, India Office. CIRCULATED) Dated Kabul through Peshawar, 28th October* 1935,,• Received 28th October. 1935, 8*45 p«m c XXX S^xth^and_L ast JPart * Inform the Afghan Government that, in view of difficulty of supply and liability to deterioration. His Majesty's Government propose to supply at the rate of 2,500,000 per annum, but will undertake to supply further reasonable quantities at any time in the event of crisis arising in Afghanistan. Payment for each instalment to be made (? annually) 6 8. I do not, of course, know if the Afghan Government will accept these proposals but I suggest them as basis of negotiation* It will be noticed that the greatest liability incurred by the Afghan Government (?? will be) at the end of 1936 and wi3.1 amount to between £150,000 and £200,000. 9. I am commenting on the question of aircraft in my immediately succeeding telegram* Fras er^Tytier 127., O ctober 28th ;,P. Z. 7175 / 35 . DPAPT TELEGRAM. in Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs. To K. M. Minister, Kabul. Repeated to Government of India. FORMINKA PESHAWAR X X X. ^ l« / India Office telegram to the — ^ * Government of India No. jjCCf and Katodon 96 , para.U. Munitions. H. M. G. ^ S' would prefer, subject to the views of the Government of India, to dispose of the question of 10,000 rifles as a s separate issue. 2. I Jilioifld he glad of your views on / * ~ S' policy of supplying a further 15,000 rifles. Does desirability of supiDly ✓ from'point of view of good relations * s with'Afghanistan outweigh disadvantage of possible friction caused by Afghan + * S S' ^ Government owing us too much money? *' / / * You v/’ill appreciate that the greater the ^ * s * * quantity of munitions supplied on credit the more difficult does it become to S’ s' S S S S finance other forms of assistance to the Afghan Government which might ' ^ ✓ s ' possiblY be of greater mutual benefit. S’ ** s 3* If it is decided to make the ^ ' s ^ ^ further supply of rifles one course might perhaps be to agree to do so ^ s * s „ after a period of say 18 months for ' / s — instalments payable over a term of say s three years? y S * •* 4* Please also telegraph your views regarding the request for 6 million rounds ammunition. In view of S , s' liability of ammunition to deteriorate, s s s S would it be feasible to negotiate an2 agreement whereby we undertake to supply so much ammunition per year? This expedient might reduce our ✓ ✓ financial liability./ s / *; V % 3. 3 * Taelovi. ^ r 5. Please see Fominka Ho. /Ot+ s '' on which I should like your views. J ^ V s' As regards request in Katodon 92 War * S' ^ s Office could supply 15,000 s s * ' additional 1914 pattern rifles if S’ * s' Government of India would give in s s' S' respect of them indemnity suggested ^ s * * in' paragraph 4 of my telegram Ho. 2364. 6. As regards Katodon 93 I would like your views regarding type / / ^ of aircraft to he supplied, training - ✓ ^ ^ of pilots in India and suggestion , , / S ' that R.A.F. officer should visit Kab ul^ There is a good deal to be n a said for selling the Afghans as far as possible the type of aircraft S s / S' * S they ask for and not seeking unduly to ✓ ' ' s influence them in their choice. ' ^ ^ Air Ministry regret that it is y s y s s / unlikely that either Harts or Foxes s S’ s S' would be available in numbers v s s s y * s - * until 1937. but state that Dragons 9 • * / ^ s would be available at once. s s s ' ss 7. If you accept proposal in S S paragraph 3 please telegr^h your ^ y y &gt; recommendations regarding offer which s / * ' has now to be made to the Afghan y^ * Government. I am inclined to suggest s S that it might be on the lines that wef / I 1 x below (a) 10,000 rifles at once to be paid y for' in' six equal' annual'instalments (b) two aeroplapes to be delivered as soon as ✓ possible ^id'paid or in six''equal anjqual ' ✓ instalments. There may ✓ be sane delay in^ effecting delivery^owing to'British' aircraft &lt;7ork|f being ^ occupied with H.A.F. y expans ion''programme; ' s / (c) additional aeroplanes at any time^for' cash;^ S S’ * j (d) As regards 15,000 further rifles'and 6 million rounds ammunition 'see' Forminka* No.« ^ 8. If you feel it impossiole to ' ' * undertake contingent liability in respect of 5 (d), v r e might try to * s ^ postpone definite reply to Afghan Government on this point until general question is settled.'' It seems however S s S S essential to dispose at once of ^ * s * ✓ question of 10,000 rifles and open S s' ^ negotiations regarding aeroplanes. If ' S s you find it convenient you will no S' * S * doubt telegraph separately in advance - ' ' s . s regarding 5 (a) and reserve other 's' s' heads for further examination. fi Si The War Office, (^) Whitehall S.W.l. 0164/6213 18th October, 1935. SECRET. Dear Walton, ^ In reply to your letter to me T.Z.7175/35 of the 17th October, enclosing fresh drafts of telegrams about the sale of munitions to the Afghan Government, we agree, so far as the War Office is concerned, with the new drafts. Paragraph 3 of your draft telegram to the Government of India entirely meets the point which we endeavoured to make by the amendment suggested in Ismay’s letter of the 15th October. Yours sincerely. J.C. Walton, Esq., C.B. M.O., India Office, S.W.l.3436b 5000 135 of/ Minute Paper. M i?t poli ti cal Departm en t. / h/,._ Mr. W a^t on, iif-' We have now had the views of other Departrrents on our draft telegram to the Government of India regarding the sale of munitions to the Afghan Government. The Foreign Office concur without amendments; the Air Ministry suggest a minor amendment set out in the minute below; the War Office suggest an insertion in paragraph 3 of the draft of a reference to India Office telegram No.2364 to the Government of India, paragraph 4. This passage asked the Government of India to give an undertaking (pending a decision on the general question and without prejudice to that decision) to agree to indemnify H.M.G. in respect of any loss incurred through delivery of 10,000 rifles from War Office stocks in advance of payment and eventual default of payment at due date. I think this suggestion is rather off the rails. The undertaking asked for is relevant only in the case where munitions are supplied from War Office stocks, whereas the argument in para.3 of our draft relates to the supply of munitions from whatever source. 2. I have discussed this point with Mr.Lambert of the War Office. Apparently they misunderstood our draft and have not consulted the Treasury^which they now wish to do. A redraft of paragraph 3 of the draft telegram designed to make this point clear is suggested and also a draft covering letter which I might send to Mr.Lambert. 3. As regards the last paragraph of Colonel Ismay's letter, I have suggested some alterations in the draft telegram to the Government of India which are consequential on a draft telegram of enquiry to Kabul which is also put up. 1 The effect of these changes is to put greater stress on the i 'immediate disposal of the question of the 10,000 rifles and to leave that of the further 15,000 and the 6,000,000 rounds&lt; over imat of InOlm fro t their cnm stocks or paid f or by the.i. I enclose copy of a revised ireft in which paragraph 3 ha© been redrafted to raert the Uar Office point* You will see that we woul i be proposiiur to the ovenvaent of India* (a) that in respect of the 10,000 1914 pattern rifles they should give the in e;vvify suggested in our tslegra j 256ii of 27th July* an^i (b) thi^t the ulti mte liability for further anj unit ion and ai3pci*af t (for both of which the owemraent of India ^ould actually pay In 'lie iiret place) .houl be reserved for decision* 'there a re also certain other al*orations in the re rsf of the teleiiparnt, one in the paragrerjh now audbereu-f; # which hae been suggested by the Air iniatryt min others (e*g* in v he paragraphs n ?w nttibere l 7 anti 8) which have been :aclc in view of t c last para raph of Isnay’s letter of 15th October* and whic#i are resigned to ?uv gi*e v er r-tress on the ©Birability of 'die In ediat V'the division of responsibility as between M.ll. G. and the G. of I. for e xtraordinary expg ririif.nre Afghans^an, bjil^that the ultimate liability for IT aeroplaiigs and further ammunition •.^coaQ\r {/n hi j, jLji &lt; &lt; 1 / /*^ ^ i supp^iredr-by th6 G. o'f I. or paid^TSi—bry supp iXed—by~ t i nf 3ra r 1 y b^—4^iii»d&gt; enclose a revised copy of the d] 1 notic\ that the draft doesy^ot imnose any liaYilitv on H.M.G.Xin what is in U&gt;- our view vae inconceivable event of an Afghan default before the settlement of the general ^lestion, other of course than willingness to discuss its incidence as paixc of the Viscussion of the general question’ There are also a ^ '■£ ■p*' number., of other alterations/, one in ^ /suggested by the Air Ministry (o cL /&gt;yw f ‘r-f ) and others ^in^paras.5 nnd-6 which have para. j been made in view of the last para, of ££lT Ismay’s letter of 15th October snd which are designed to put greater stress on the desirability of the immediate disposal of thequestion of the 10,000 rifles and to leave the question of selling the further 15,000 rifles and 6 million rounds of ammunition more open. A draft telegram which we would like sent to Kabul at the same/i Department same time is also enclosed. 5 . we are extremely anxious to get these telegrams out within + he next few days. Our Minister at Kabul reports axe that the Afghan Government irs becoming restive at the delays which there have been over thfs^ quest ion/^-swa^ ^h-© danger that they may turn elsewhere for their rifles and other weapons is A a real one. I,ioxeo-ver the Hohmand operations have put a ^ertaxn strain on good relations and fa^ ^e /t^T mame an early move regarding munitions fey be i.ii aconotruod by th^ Afghan b d* ^ * A/ T om a ^-i nrr a pnnv othis letter to Collier at the foreign Office and Darvall at the Air Ministry. (jJcL) j • . : V• 'JLo 'Draft Paper. P.Z. 7175/35. political Department DRAFT LETTER. 17 OCT 1935 Many thanks for your letter No.N.5044/121/97 of 5th October about the sale of munitions to the Afghan Government. I enclose a copy of a letter which I received from Ismay of the War which I am sending to-day to Lambert at Office appear to have misread xne scope iragraph 3 thereof with 1914 pattern We should be grateful if you could let us know whether the Foreign Office ! concur in the terms of the revised draft to the Government of India and also in the new draft to the Minister at Kabul. / Office on this subject, and of a letter the War Off ice 4 luiiululy have acted on the (Scu J. o. wAJuaxutfz- 7/7Vyr political Department, |€0 DRAFT LETTER. . ,DSO. 17 )CT1935 Thank you very much for your letter of 15th October No. 0164/6213(M.1.2) regarding the sale of munitions to the Afghan Government. X spoke to Lambert on the telephone about it and I enclose a copy of a letter which I am sending to him. (Sd.) J. (J. WALTOF*.P.Z. 7175/35 .f * DRAFT TELEGRAM. From Secretary of State for Foreign /JTfairs. To H.M. Minister, Kabul. Repeated to Government of India. FOmilNKA PESHAWAR X X X. (Mily. (F. 0 . Copy to (d.M.I. (A. M* India Office telegrai.i to the Government of India No* and Katodon 96 , para.4* Munitions. H. M. G. would prefer, subject to the views of the Government of India, to dispose of the question of 10,000 rifles as a separate issue. 2 . I should be glad of your views on policy of supplying a further 15&gt;000 rifles. Does desirability of supply from point of view of good relations with Afghanistan outweigh disadvantage of possible friction caused by Afghan Government owing us too much money? You will appreciate that the greater the quantity of munitions supplied on credit the more difficult does it become to finance other forms of assistance to the Afghan Government y/hich might possiblY be of greater mutual benefit. 3- If it is decided to make the further supply of rifles one course might perhaps be to agree to do so after a period of say 18 months for instalments payable over a term of say three years? 4- Please also telegraph your views regarding the request for 6 million rounds ammunition. In view of liability of ammunition to deteriorate, would it be feasible to negotiate anagreement whereby we undertake to supply so much ammunition per year? This expedient might reduce our financial liability.■jy. ■ C^in&lt;Lr © Draft Paper. Department. DRA?T TiCLiiJGrHAlil. Prom Secretary of State for foreign Affairs To H.M.Minister, Kabul. Repeated to Government of India FORHIUKA PESHAWAR XXX \UP Copy to I F.O* I D.M.I. A.M. it fi^\ W-S h ~ ^ ^ 4s t L ' x India Office telegram to the Government of India No. and Katodon y6, para.4. Munitions. H.m.G. would prefer, subject to the views Oi the Govern.lent of India, to dispose o ■' the question of 10,000 rifles as a separate i s su e. shall. 2. I shuulTTbe glad of your views on policy of sup lying a further 15,000 rifles. Does or desirability ^ from point of view of good relations with Afghanistan outweigh disadvantage of possible friction caused by Afghan Government owing us too much money?/\On^~ c , u ^ -j :: nt. ^nP t.n..^.(-rp-e to^ supply/^ a#trer t G A* ^ a period of^ say 18 months for instalments payable over a term of say three years/ Please also telegraph your views regarding the request for 6 million rounds ammunition^ in view of liability of ammunition to deteriorate, would it be feasible to negotiate an agreement whereby we undertake to supply so much ammunition per year? This expedient might reduce our financial liability.P.Z.6608/35* Draft Paper. \W' Department. DRAFT TELEGRAM. Prom: Secretary of State for India, To: Government of India, Foreign and Political Dept., Repeated to H. M. Minister, Kat&gt;ul. XXX. FORMINKA PESHAWAR Copy to '(Do F.O. D.M. I. Air Ministry, Addressed 'by Secretary of State for India to Government of India, repeated to KaLul. Katodon Nos.92, 93 and 96 . 2. Proposals in your telegram No.2475 of 14th September are under examination but it is inevitable that their discussion must take a considerable time. Meanwhile it appears essential to give very early reply to Afghan requests for munitions. It is especially necessary at a time when reactions of Mohmand campaign may place a strain on Afghan co-operation with us on frontier matters that we should not now after long discussions appear reluctant to provide Afghan Government with munitions. There is also the danger that they may turn elsewhere. They have expressed wish to accept our offer of 10,000 rifles and only question of method of payment remains for settlement. They have already waited without a reply regarding aeroplanes for over seven months. It is desirable also to give a reply soon to their request for additional rifles ^ 6 , 000,000 rounds of ammunition. 3* I observe however that proposals in paragraph 6 of your telegram No.2475 are/ 3761 6000 5.051 r Draft Paper, Department. are conditional on His Majesty 1 s G-overnment undertaking liability defined in paragraph 5* I am afraid that this would make it impossible to give any replies to the Afghan requests for some time. I hope however that in circumstances set out in paragraph 2 you will agree to give in respect 1(300 0 of^rifles indemnity suggested in paragraph 4 of my telegram 2364 without prior settlement of large issues raised in your telegram 2475« I suggest that question of ultimate liability for Afghan default in respect of any aeroplanes and additional ammunition provided by Government of India should similarly dec-Cs»-0'&gt;A be dee-ided^as part of settlement of general question of division of responsibility as between His Majesty’s Government and Government of India for extraordinary expenditure in Afghanistan. S’. At? rcgardrr-Tequcata in Katodon Q . X T-O* 92 please see Forminka No. As on which I should like your views. ^War jj Office could supply 15&gt;000 additional 1914 pattern rifles if Government of India would give in respect of them indemnity suggested in paragraph 4 of my3. Department. ^at, ppioo- weuld you As regards Katodon 93 I would like your views regarding type of aircraft to 'be supplied, training of pilots in India and suggestion that R.A.P* officer should visit Kabul. There is a good deal to he said for selling the Afghans as far as possible the type of aircraft they ask for and not seeking unduly to influence them in their choice. Air Ministry regret that it is unlikely that either Harts or Poxes would be available in numbers until 1937 &gt; but state that Dragons would be available at once. ^ If you accept proposal in ^ Vico paragraph 3 please telegram your recommendations regarding offer which has now to be made to the Afghan Government. I am inclined to suggest that; j it might be on the lines that we are willing to supply (a) 10,000 rifles at once to be paid for in six equal annual instalments; (b) two aeroplanes to be delivered as soon as possible and paid for in six equal annual instalments. There may be some delay in effecting delivery owing to British aircraft works being occupied with R.A.P. expansion programme; (c) additional aeroplanes at any time for cash. (d) As regards 15,000 further rifles and 6 million rounds ammunition f —-Department. If you feel it impossible to undertake contingent liatiility in respect of 5(d), v/e might try to postpone definite reply to Afghan Government on this point until general question is settled. It seems however essential to dispose at once of question of 10,000 rifles and open negotiations regarding aeroplanes. If you find it convenient you will no doubt telegraph separately in advance regarding 5(a) and reserve other heads for further examination.0164/6213 (M.I.2. ) October, 1935. &lt;7 My dear N C4^— ^ I am now able to reply to your P.Z.6608/35 of the 30th September, enclosing inter alia a draft of the reply which you proposed to send to Government of India telegram No. 2475 of the 14th September. suggest is the insertion of the following sentence in para.3 between the words ”on the basis*’ and the words ’’that the question” ’’proposed in para.4 of my cable 2364 Porminka 63 of 27th July”. 3. As to the general lines of the draft, we feel that it might be preferable to deal with the original proposition of the supply of 10,000 rifles as a self-contained issue, in order that this transaction might be put through without the risk of further delay which may be caused by a reference in the same telegram to those other matters which call for further discussion (see para.5 of your draft). 2 . The only detailed amendment which we desire to Yours H.A.P. Rumbold, Esq., India Office.Ou\ © I discussed with Squadron-Leader Larval1 his letter of the 4th October, suggesting some changes in the draft telegram about rifles* We agreed on the following redraft: - 'I would like your views regarding type of aircraft to be supplied, training of pilots in India and the suggestion that a Royal Air Force officer should visit Kabul. There is a good deal to be said for selling the Afghans as far as possible the type of aircraft they ask for, and not seeking unduly to influence them in their choice. Air Ministry regret that it is unlikely that either Harts or Foxes would be available in numbers until 1937&gt; but state that Dragons would be available at once.' I read this over the telephone to Colonel Ismay, who concurs. to o-f 5 vnsj T&gt; r l AIR MINISTRY, ADASTRAU HOUSE. 7175 I955 J KINGSWAY. W.C.2. 4th October, 1935. We have carefully considered your letter No.P.Z.6608/35 dated the 30th September, 1935, particularly in regard to the sale of aircraft to the Afghan Government. In general we have no comments to offer on the draft telegram, which you kindly enclosed, although we would like to suggest an amendment to the last sentence of paragraph 4. The amendment reads as follows 'I would like your views regarding the type of aircraft to be supplied, the training of pilots in India and the suggestion that a Royal Air Force officer should visit Kabul. The Air Ministry favour the view that the Afghans should be sold, as far as possible, the type of aircraft that they ask for, and that we should not seek unduly to influence them in their choice. They regret that it is unlikely that either Harts or Foxes would be available until 1937, but state that Dragons would be available at once.” I am writing similarly to Collier at the Foreign Office and Colonel Ismay at the War Office.(N 5044/121/97) /•&gt; -i Dear Rumbold, Thank you for your letter No.P # Z.6608/35 of 30th September, forwarding for our concurrence the draft of a telegram to the Government of India about the sale of munitions to the Afghan Government. As Labouchere has told you, we concur in the draft. Prom the Foreign Office point of view, of course, the only two essential points in any reply to the Government of India are (l) that the political importance of meeting the Afghan request as far as possible and as soon as possible should be emphasised, and (2) that His Majesty^ Government in the United Kingdom should not be committed to any promise of the nature suggested in paragraph 5 of the Government of India’s telegram before the whole question of the general principles on which assistance to Afghanistan should be allocated between them and the Government of India has been re-examined, which clearly /cannot I • 1*4* • 7 OCT 1935. H.A.P.Rumbold, Esq.cannot be done now; and both these requirements met in the draft telegram.The War Office, Whitehall, S.W.l. 0164/6213. SECRET. 23rd September, 1935. 'iW Y° s ^ v'iXa. C 5 e.x\Acu.^ V'o Hv' V&lt;x^\jtiVr V'&amp;Ve^&gt;Vo^c. Ibl lV . Dear Walton, With reference tc yoiir letter of 27th August to Sir Reginald Paterson about the proposed sale of rifles etc. to Afghanistan, I am v/riting in his absence to ask whether you have had any indication from the Government of India of their attitude to our enquiry whether, pending a decision on the general question of Afghan relations, the Government of India »fruia agree to indemnify His Ma^esty T s G-ovemment in respect of any loss incurred through delivery of rifles in advance of payment and eventual default of payment at due date - see paragraph 4 of 1.0. cypher telegram 2364 of 27th July last. The chances are that we shall very shortly be telling you that we can offer another 15,000 units (25,000 in all) at the same price, but even with this further quantity to bargain with, it is clear that Afghanistan will want to spread the payment over some years (up to 6), and none of the telegrams you have sent us since 27th July contains an answer to the above enquiry. If India hesitate to give the assurance asked for, it will still further delay the negotiations. Yours sincerely, J.C. Walton, Esq., C.B., M.C., INDIA 0HFICE.Extract from Kabul Military Attached Diary No. 38 for week ending 20th September, 1935. Army . Armament . 22 22. The Russian Military Attache stated recently that the announcement in the Islah of 31st July (cl. Diary No.31 paragraph 22) that the Alghan Government had bought mountain guns from the Soviet Government was untrue. The Afghans had inquired about guns but no agreement had been reached regarding prices.Minute Paper. © POLITICAL • Department. 1. H. M. Minister Katrnl reported in Katodon No«77 of 31st July, P.Z. 5243/35 &gt; that the Afghan Government were not attracted hy our offer to sell them 1914 pattern .303 rifles. It appears, however, from Katodon No.92 of 8th September and Katodon 96 of 12th September that the statement of the merits of this weapon contained in Forminka 75 of 23rd August (P. Z. 5478/35) has led the Afghan War Minister to take a different view of the matter. The Afghan Government accept our offer to sell 10,000 rifle units, complete with bayonet, scabbard, oil • bottle and pull-through, delivered at Karachi, at a price of £3 per rifle, and our recommendation that each rifle should be given an individual inspection and firing test, at an additional cost of 5/6d per rifle. This will be in addition to the 5&gt;000 new .303 rifles which have already been supplied from India. 2. We cannot carry the matter further until the Government of India reply to India Office telegram No .2364 of 27 th July, No.P.Z.5005/35 in which we suggested that, pending a decision on this general question,and without prejudice to this decision, liability for the 10,000 1914 pattern rifles should be settled on the basis that . in the event of deferred payments being proposed and wJUyc*, ^ agreed to, the Government of India would agree to indemnify H.M.G. in respect of any losses incurred through delivery of the rifles in advance of payment and eventual default of payment at due date. The Government of India were asked to reply to this suggestion when Lt.Col. Fraser-Tytler has ascertained from the Afghan Government whether they are attracted by our offer; whether and to what extent they could pay cash; and what is the best basis of deferred payment that they could accept. 3 ./ W: 4, ^ ^ (V ^ ^ VU bifguS* v'a \ 3436b ^5000 1332 3. H.M. Minister asked in Katodon 92 of 8th September for early instructions regarding the wish of the Afghan Government for 30,000 rifles in all; that is to say 15&gt;000 rifles in addition to the 5&gt;000 new rifles already supplied, and the 10,000 1914 pattern rifles which we have already offered the Afghans. The figure of 15,000 was fixed as a total to be supplied in the first instance because Sir R. Maconachie thought that the figure of 30,000 original demanded by the Afghans was a maximum which they did not expect to receive, and because it was the limit of the possibility of supply from the Government of Indian own stocks (Government of India’s telegram 1586 of 29 th June, P.Z.4538/35)* As the 1914 pattern.303 rifles would be supplied from surplus War Office stocks, and as the iy Afghans now appear genuinely to want 30,000, or at least 25 rifles, these considerations do not apply. Such arguments as there are against meeting their request are: / x * (1) the danger of the rifles getting into the hands of the tribes. It is suggested that we ought not to give weight to this, as if we do not supply rifles the Afghan Government will get them from other sources. The Japanese are believed to have offered the Afghans new .303 rifles cheaply (P. Z. 5180/35) and the y &gt;000 y$ooo c\*q to X ov' oSUlcW v'^icce . ( 2 ) I t , v ior° Czechoslovak factory of Brno has a stock of slightly used .303 rifles. Financial difficulties. The sale of 25,000 rifled would involve a greater contingent financial liability than the sale of 10,000 rifles. The Afghans already owe the Government of India S-o'i Rs.6fi“5 lakhs for the 5&gt;000 new rifles already supplied. 10,000 1914 pattern rifles would cost about Rs.4i lakhs, and 25,000 would t cost about Rs.ll lakhs. It is also possible that the/ I (j ; 000 ( ooo \roo^s urt&gt;u\£ CcsV: (Is S UkUs Scr^« v ' cs uxMinute Paper Department the proposals which we understand we may expect soon from the Government of India on the general question of the division of responsibility between H.M.G. and the Government of India for extraordinary expenditure on Afghanistan, may be of a nature which, if adopted, would affect the question of the number of rifles supplied 0 hoped that this will not be the case, as it is clearly on Katodon No.92 and Katodon No. 96 , it is, however, impossible to give Lt.Col.Fraser Tytler instructions on Government of India asking them whether, in replying to paragraph 4 of India Office telegram No.2364* they would give the indemnity they are asked for in respect of Afghan War Ministerhas asked for two samples of the 1914 pattern rifle to be sent by Air Mail. In Forminka 75 Lt. Col.Fraser Tytler was told that samples could be that he has made Shah Mahmud aware of this condition, and that both he and Shah Mahmud appreciate that the cost of carriage by Air Mail would be considerable. In view of the information in Katodon 96 , however, it seems i unnecessary to send samples at all, and rather stupid to send them by Air Mail. A telegram has therefore been sent to the Minister asking whether he stills desires samples. I&amp;aX uo , hC- h* me &lt;0 'a*-'*' AtL /A IMu. within the next few years. It is, however, much to be undesirable to keep the Afghan Government waiting long u&gt;s\- for an answer regarding these additional 15&gt;000 rifles/ t&amp;.e av'cjua'A.e^v C.\&gt;©iaC^JJI VVxo-v vJXlV \yQ. G &lt;V\e . 4* Pending the comments of the Government of India \oSV\V the point. It is suggested that we might telegraph to the o&lt;\\ uj© ixjM.yjvr toe 10,000 rifles, in respect of an additional 15&gt;000 rifles *£ as well. Vtr- Ko wo ^ M uns^l^s. 5. In Katodon No.92 H.M. Minister reported that the so despatched on payment by the Afghans and we must assume4. 6. The question of the sale of aircraft and the training of Afghan pilots in India, referred to in Katodon 93 of 8th September, was discussed with Sir R. Maconachie by the Afghan Ministers on 21st February. Besides the sale of 24 aircraft, the Afghans wanted their 28 pilots to be trained in India. Sir R. Maconachie suggested that after tt[e main features of the programme had been considered by H.M.G. and the Government of India, an R.A.F. officer might visit Kabul to give advice on the execution of whatever was decided. In paragraph 8 of the Government of India’s telegram. No. 1586 of 3^th June, P.2.4538/35, they said that they were addressing the Secretary of State separately by air mail regarding aircraft and the training of pilots. Nothing has, however, arrived, and in Katodon 71 of 7th July (P.Z.4644/35) Lieut.Colonel Fraser-Tytler reported tha on the Afghan Ministers’ raising the question of aircraft X he told them that it was still under consideration.' 7- The present situation, in which it is impossible to give any answer to the Afghan requests because of delays caused by the Government of India’s claim that H.M.G. should, share responsibility for extraordinary expenditure in Afghanistan, is intolerable and it is suggested that we should try to reach some decision regarding aircraft withou prejudice to the solution eventually reached on the question of financial liability, the question of liability being treated in a e-imii-ar way to that in which we have suggested that liability in respect of rifles shopld be treated. I understand from the Air Ministry liaison officer that the Government of India obtain their own aircraft through the India Store Department from the Air Ministry; that this procedure enables the Government of India to get machines more cheaply than by going to the manufacturing firms direct, and that they would no doubt follow the same procedure in obtaining machines for the Afghan Government. In this connection there is the possibility that/ A* ^ n O \«n‘s\-*v' j, wrv^cos ovv vCvS. OAvca'c^v l-c'L« are. vA Uc«, 14 v -' , | Pi. CdSoS/IjS VU V C Co v-v o*. t &amp; 5 v£*.e ^ 'XA } V&gt;u\~ V* ^ &lt;i*.'cVa.V:ei. a.\\'~osV e«Ar\Ven^ V&gt;*^ ^vCc^aivV. C£&gt;'*-Vv&lt;^evc.VCO'.^ VSVjXV. WvA \^cv'Ue »S u£\' VevCvi-^ V'iVro c.tco ova.V'. Q ^ ^ccV' lAe. avrcoc^ \ VVK Q.c g°V sVoo j c*. ^GjiO r^c l-o a lc&gt;c&lt;^ k vs/vv.Minute Paper. 1^, 5. Department. % 2* tldhlfdA * 6*11*” If p. H-'P'ti'** ”V Vo vV' ^eA^ c^pc V‘o C: q} , A' ^v&lt;vrc.ie^ v-o Om . fVtWvo^ • ^cc^v W-^ee-v ^CvV'-^'^vaa&gt;v\ . So-®. H-SVn-^ 'o^- vW s?-. (■8|« that unless they place an order for aircraft for the Afghan Government comparatively soon there may he some delay in the completion of the order owing to the pressure on aircraft manufacturing works in Great Britain caused hy the R. A.F. expansion programme. There is also the possibility mentioned hy H.M. Minister that our continued procrastination may irritate the Afghan Government into turning elsewhere for their requirements. It is suggested that as a first step we might ask the Government of India whether they can give us their views on the aircraft question on the basis that the problem of financial liability should be reserved. Points on which their comment might be particularly useful are whether x the types of aircraft asked for by the Afghans (Hawker-Harts, Fairy Foxes and D.H. Dragons) should be supplied, although they are unsuitable for Afghan requirements; whether the Government can train the Afghan pilots and where, and their suggestions regarding the tactics to be used in disposing of this question vis-a-vis the Afghan Government. t A telegram is suggested. It seems unnecessary to consult the Foreign Office or the Air Ministry before it issues. O d Q. V C. vm^ „o.q O VO** }(• ^ 6 y ^ c V OS' &lt; - VOq_^uh. \ w ■ : Vbbif UldWe have now received the Government of India’s telegram jno.2475, copy of which is on the file. The proposals contained in it for the settlement of the question of responsibility as between H.M.G. and the Government of India for extraordinary expenditure on Afghanistan are under examination and the papers will be submitted as soon as possible. Meanwhile we must consider how in the light of the Government of India’s attitude we can best proceed with the question of the sale of munitions to the Afghan Government. The Government of India’s proposals are not very clear, but their essence appears to be:- (a) The Government of India will, as at present, meet expenditure on/Legation^ and Consulates in Afghanistan. (b) A fund would be set up by the Government of India into which they would pay Rs.5 lakhs per annum to meet extraordinary expenditure c.\Locoe.A&gt;&lt;:o ext*. m\u.V«v\~q. in Afghanistan. The fund would be Mmitod to a maximum of Rs.25 lakhs. lc) Any extraordinary demand beyond the resources of the fund, especially if it relates primarily to countering of a Russian menace to the security of India as part of the Empire, would in the absence of any special circumstances be met by H.M.G. / lUs. ^&lt;2- Government of India would be ready to bear themselves the contingent liability of an Afghan default on instalments payable over the next six years for the five thousand new rifles which have already been supplied. They would also accept as a contingent liability on the fund the possibility of default on the instalments due in respect of 10,000 1914 pattern riflesAw^ fchey would ■ o supplyMinute Paper. 'l Department. \ uW&lt;-V covurcu.^. fr' ^ 00 ° bpOOfiOO ^ CcV'-T&lt;W.'&lt;A.'CC'Ov\ V ^ «■- ^VS V '® «.vVcc*tSV'. (AH iLh'V^ “■ uc J-JO &amp; fifl'-** ^ W'-W'. /W'^ h.miUiM &lt; * 1 . *'_ &lt; % from the fund two aeroplpnea per annum. The telegram appears to have been drafted before the T Government of India received Katodon 92, 93 and 96, and does not take these telegrams into account. The whole scheme is conditional on H.M.G. assuming the liability suggested in (c) above. Under this scheme the fund would probably be almost exhausted if there were imposed upon it (a) an annual recurring cost of between Rs.3 and 4 lakhs for air service between India and Kabul. On this matter we have for some time been awaiting the views of the Government of India. We cannot, of course, be certain that it will be necessary to institute this service. (b) the cost of supplying two aeroplanes per annum ■ on credit. Thus its effect would probably be to throw on H.M.G. a liability for an Afghan default on instalments due in irespect of 1914 pattern rifles or the additional six million 3436b 5000 1.35 rounds of ammunition for which the Afghans have asked g.v.V sconce. \'*'sV-0v'uA'eA3 . It seems likely that before we can approach the Treasury we shall have to discuss the scheme further with the Government of India, but even when we are in a position to approach the Treasury negotiations with them are likely to be prolonged. In the meanwhile we must deal with the Afghan requests, as if we keep the Afghans waiting until after we have resolved the question of responsibility they would have a good excuse for going elsewhere for their arms. Moreover, a further delay (the Afghans made their original requests in January) would give the impression that our willingness to sell munitions is reluctant, and we/we might thus fail to reap any recompense in gratitude. country are putting a certain strain on Afghan loyalty to our friendship. It would be well to do what we can to counterbalance the harm which this factor may do to our relations. It therefore seems essential to proceed in regard to the Question of munitions on the basis that a liability for an Afghan default on instalments would be decided as part of the settlement of the general question of responsioility as between H.M.G. and the Government of mdia for extraordinary expenditure on Afghanistan. But the Government of India are in effect using the urgency of giving definite replies to the Afghans as a pistol to hold at the head of H.M.G.^in the same way as they used the minute attempt to secure an undertaking that H.M.G. would give a definite guarantee that in an emergency they would #/ M despatch at their own charge to India weapons to replace any deficiency caused in the Government of India’s witnout prejudice to the question of payment which they stated must remain prim? faci e an Indian liability pending a decision on the Government of India’s general request for assistance in their Afghan relations. It seems necessary to dispose of these tactics in the present case submitted,seeking their agreement to the reservation of the question of liability for munitions. It is drafted in more polite language than the situation would justify, as this is perhaps advisable in the first round of what promises to be an acrimonious controversy. I have tentatively inserted in the draft a lead to tne Government of India regarding the instructions to be given to Lieut.uolonel Fraser Tytler. It may serve to Also at the present moment our operations in the Mohmand urgency of sending 5,000 rifles for the Jashan Is a last mobilization reserves. A telegram to the Government of India is thereforeMinute Paper Department. crystallize the issues for the Government of India, and | so hasten consideration of the question. On the other hand it may be thought premature to go into detail on this point until we have got the Government of India's agreement settlement of the question of liability. This draft would require the concurrence of the c»V&gt;L^ ^ Foreign Office, War Office, Air Ministry and^Treasury, and Wvc^ these Departments wou-l-d—probab 1 y wish to have a meeting to discuss it. l4.tte.Ci vrcra^e fO t co-o O ^ ^Co^r C.CQ. . to proceeding with the sale of munitions in advance of a ^ tuuMu • ' u -UaNi t - **^ • At M / \ % &amp; /M. 5-) KH* j ttu V4 ^ U—***&gt; us*. TtriA* ^ a, C- « * “‘M rMinute Paper. POLITICAL Department. 4./ 1. As the minutes on tjiis case have hecome rather long, the position is summarized in this note. 2. In March 1934 the Cabinet decided that a . favourable reply should be returned to Afghan requests which were expected for the sale of arms* It was however not until January 1935 that the Afghan Government made specific requests for 30,000 *303 rifles and 24 aircraft. There was considerable difficulty in obtaining recommendations from the Government of India, who have in fact not yet put forward any views regarding aircraft* Eventually it appeared that some rifles were required by the Afghans in order to impress the tribesmen gathered at Kabul for the Independence Celebrations in the middle of August and 5,000 rifles, complete with bayonet and scabbard and 3 million rounds of ammunition^ obtained from India’s mobilization reserve^ere hastily sent to Kabul. The Afghan Government undertook to pay Rs.8 lakhs (£60,000) in six annual instalments* 3. The Afghan Government have also accepted our offer to sell 10,000 * 303 1914 Pattern rifles valued at Rs.4.36 lakhs (£32,750) and have asked to be allowed to pay for these in instalments. They have further asked for another 15,000 1914 Pattern rifles, valued at »®s^»^6v^khs (£49,125), and 6,000,000 rounds of ammunition, valued at about Rs.5 lakhs (£3^,500). There is also their request for 24 aircraft tobe dealt with. For all these the Afghans offer payment in instalments. There seems no objection on grounds other than financial to the supply of | this material, but it would on the whole be well to avoid placing ourselves in the position of being owed too large a sum by the Afghan Government. ■ .Minute Paper Department _ 2 i 4. W© have for some months known that the Government of India considered that His Majesty’s Government should asstime a certain liability for expenditure on Afghanistan. In April, in connection with the question of the provision of economic assistance to Afghanistan, the Government of India took the view that the entire financial responsibility for such measures should be borne by His Majesty’s Government* It has not been necessary to approach the Treasury on this subject as the offer which it was decided to make to the Afghans to despatch an expert to undertake an examination of the financial and economic position of Afghanistan would not involve any substantial expenditure. No reply to this offer has yet been received from the Afghan Government. The Government of India have now made proposals in their telegram No.2475 of 14th September, whereby:- (a) The Government of India would as at present meet expenditure on the Legation and Consulates in Afghanistan; (b) A fund would be set up by the Government of India into which they would pay Rs.5 lakhs (£37,500) per annum to meet extraordinary expenditure in (c) (a) Afghanistan- The fund would accumulate to a maximum of Rs.25 lakhs* Extraordinary expenditure beyond the resources of the fund, especially if it relates primarily to countering of a Russian menace to the security of India as part of the Empire, would in the absence of any special circumstances be met by His Majesty’s Government; The Government of India would bear themselves the contingent liability for the 5,000 rifles and the 3436b 5000 1/35 ammunition/Minute Paper. Department 3, r-'N ^ UMAli / M* tkl tlOiMi* ita‘ *■“ k\ ?~u\ t, ^ -,u ^ ^ ^ l ~ J ~ &lt;t- : ammunition already supplied to the Afghan Government and the fund would hear the liability (immediate or contingent) for further munitions to be supplied on credit, provided that His Majesty’s Government accept the proposition under (c) above* These proposals are under examination and some time must elapse before a settlement of the question can be reached with the Treasury. Meanwhile it is urgent to reply to the Afghan requests because these were made in January, because other Powers particularly the Japanese would probably be ready to supply munitions on favourable terms, and because delay may be understood by the Afghans as reluctance to supply, thus depriving us of the political value of our action. 5. The Government of India are in effect using the urgency of the munitions question &lt;W\)**tyV***as a lever to persuade His Majesty’s Government to accept their proposals for the division of liability as between His Majesty’s Government and the Government of India for extraordinary expenditure on Afghanistan. It is proposed that we should try to obtain the agreement of the Government of India to disposal of the munitions question on the basis that the incidence of the contingent liability for an Afghan default should be reserved for decision as part of the settlement of the general question. As a similar undertaking by His Majesty’s Government would be involved, it is necessary to obtain the concurrence of other Departments to our telegram* It • \K . 3436b 5000 1/35Secretary of State, * © There is, inevitably, a good deal of relatively unimportant detail in the minuting on this file. The short note immediately below brings out the main points. The whole difficulty at the moment is financial. The Government of India begun in April to put forward suggestions that the Home Treasury should bear some part of the cost of measures designed to assist Afghanistan. In July, when 5,000 rifles were supplied to the Afghans from stocks in India, they asked, in pursuance the same line of thought, that His Jfcttjesty's Government would guarantee, if an emergency arose, to despatch to India at tneir own charge rifles to make good the deficiency, but were persuaded to agree to send off the rifles and let the question of payment stand over for the present. The Goverrment of India*s telegram now received puts forward comprehensive proposals for the division between the Home and Indian Governments of expenditure in connexion with Afghanistan. Whatever possibility there/there may he of securing some such division as the Government of India desire, it is obvious that the question involves considerable difficulties, and it is quite unreasonable to expect His Majesty’s Government to accept on the spur of the moment - or at the point of the Government of India’s pistol - the liability that the Government of India suggest. At the same time we obviously cannot, after long discussions with the Afghans, ending in their acceptance (subject to terms of payment)of an offer to sell them 10,000 rifles, tell them that we cannot proceed ary further until we have settled who is to bear the loss if they default on the instalments of the purchase price; and it is rather late in the day, or would at any rate from some points of view be undesirable, to tell them that any further sales can only be on a cash basis. below for concurrence to the Foreign Office, War Office and Air Ministry. They may, I should think, ask for a discussion including a Treasury representative. It is proposed to send the draft telegramIn paragraph k of their telegram the Government of India appear to attach prime importance to keeping secret the proposed arrangement for setting up a kind of Afghanistan Contract Budget grant. It seems very- unlikely that the proposal could he camouflaged successfully against the searching investigations of audit and Finance Committee of the Legislature. However this may be, there is a good deal to be said against having pockets in the Budget which are to be filled as a matter of course and without regard to other competitive claimants. In the case of the Army a special reason was that the Contract Budget would promote economy. This, however, does not apply in the present instance. From the point of view of the Treasury, the proposal does not seem to offer any bait towards getting them to share expenditure which has hitherto been regarded as an Indian liability. The annual allotment of Rs.5 lakhs is based upon actual average expenditure since 1921 so that the proposal does not apparently /2 apparently involve India in any greater degree of expenditure than she has hitherto shouldered. If, in order to get the Treamury to pay something, India had said we will be prepared to pay up to say twice our recent actuals in the event of need, the idea of the Treasury coming in to share in Afghanistan outlay would have had more attraction. 25th September 1935f / Draft Paper. political Department. DRAFT From Secretary of State for India To Government of India, Foreign &amp; Political Department, Repeated to H.M.Minister, Kab ul. XXX FORMINKA PESHAWAR. Copy to F.0. D.M.I. Air Ministry Trearsury. ^#0 TELEGRAI^ Addressed by Secretary of State for India to Government of India, repeated to Kabul. /v.?. Katodon Nos92,93 /a Proposals in your telegram and 9 6 No.2475 of 14th September are under tU+jfUu examination but it is that their discussion wi-H take a considerable time. CMeanv/hile l it essential to give very early reply to Afghan requests for munitions. It is t'QactAo^s J ' cUoPrablc^at a time when^Mohmand campaign sterns likely to /place a strain on Afghan co-operation with us on frontier m-tters v/e should not/’appear reluctant cxu^ ^iLIrlTTPTre^rs- to provide Afghan Government with munitions. There is also the danger that they may turn elsewhere. They have?accept&amp;d our offer of 10,000 rifles and only question of method of payment remains for settlement. They have already waited without a reply regarding aeroplanes for over seven months. It is desirable also to give a reply soon to their request for 15,000 additional rifles and 6,000,000 rounds of ammunition. 3. I observe however that proposals in para.6 of your telegram No. 2475 are conditional on H.M.G. undertaking liability defined in para.5. I am afraid that we could not give anyPaper Department replies to the Afghan requests for some time,unless we proceed on the 'basis that the question whether a contingent liability for an Afghan default should fall on H.M.G. or the Government of India is reserved for decision as part of | settlement of general question of division of responsibility as between H.M.G. and Government of India for extraordinary expenditure in Afghanistan. I hope you will agree that in circumstances set out in paragraph 2 we should proceed on this basis. 4. As regards requests in Katodon No.92 and Katodon No.93 War Office could supply 15,000 additional 1914 pattern rifles if Government of India would give |in respect of them indemnity suggested in paragraph 4 of my telegram No.2364, Which I note you would^/give in respect of 10,000 rifles. Could you supply the additional ammunition desired if H.M.G. gave guarantee similar to that given in paragraph 5 of my telegram 2190 of 13th o July: What price would you ask V I would also like your views regarding (a) type of aircraft to be supplied (b) training of pilots in India (c) suggestion that R.A.F.officer should visit Kabul. 5. If you accept proposal in paragraph 3 please telegraph yourDraft Paper Department. recommendations regarding offer which has now to be made to the Afghan Government. I am inclined to suggest that it might be on the lines that we are willing to supply (a) 10,000 rifles at once to be paid for in six equal annual instalment s (b) up to 15,000 further rifles and 6,000,000 rounds ammunition to be supplied at any time for Say cash or after a period of abo'ut 18 months for instalments payable over term of say three years (fbiA* J a (c) two aeroplanes to be delivered as soon ss possible and paid for in six equal annual instalments. There may be some delay in effecting delivery ov/ing to British aircraft works being occupied with R.A.F. expansion programme e^dCvccmaV. (d) further aeroplanes at any time for cash. y“ vt vvC^)o5&gt;s»b\e. w^.'^A.vr ^ Vo ^90 cCVq. Vo L \^ Vc,v CCcvT* O- vCmTs \^oiv\\r % O^^'TlOw ^v V^ooeotc eVieA-vaV Vo ^cs\jose C.V O-'CC. Vtvov Vjo^ooO &lt;Sy&gt;qvi. ^e^(£V CcA'um^,SECRET XT/A^c {X63 groups) 4912, V s DBCYPH3H OF T S L F ORA ,M C From {COPIES ClRCTTLATEP) Bated Government of India* Foreign and Poiitlea! Department s to Secretary of State for India* Simla, 14th September, 1935* Received )4th September, X935, 9 0 30 p*m c XXX 247^6* First of aeyera) parts 6 Addressed to Secretaj'y of State and repeated to Kabul, 295 G Your telegram of July 13th, 2190^ and our telegram of July 16th, 1726* We hare carefully reviewed our position in the matter of peace-time expenditure in Afghanistan in the light of our existing and prospect ire financial position and of our responsibility to coming Federal Government* This expenditure falls under two heads’- ordinary, namely^ costs of maintenance of Legation and Consulates (approximately 4»45 lakha per annum) and (b), extraordinary, being cost of material assistance rendered from time to time in order to maintain friendship and Btahii ii^ . of Afghanistan* The former head is not in questicn c as regards latter, our present attitude is defined by Government of India’s telegram, 1323-S of October 22nd, 1925, as being to grant to Amir material assistance in kind, provided that he asks for it,, has earned it, and it is to mutual advantage of India and Afghanistan* Since establishment of Legation in 1922, our average annual expenditure under this head has come to little over 4 lakhs* By far greater portion of this expenditure was,, however, incurred in a single year, 1931, as a result of emergency created by Afghan revolution and necessity of stabilising the new regime*SECRET UC/AW (183 groups) 4914 D E C Y P HBK OF TELEGRAM. (COPIES CIRCULATED) Prom Government of India* Foreign and Political Department* to Secretary of State for India 0 Dated Simla* 14th September, 1935. Received 14th September* 1935* 10.30 p.mc XXX Part Two 2 0 We feel that our future policy in thie matter must be determined mainly by what we feel to be the basic necessity of maintaining and affirming decision and control in the policy towards Afghanistan secured to the Government of India in conjunction with the Secretary of State by the agreement arrived at in 1921 between the Secretary of State and His Wajeaty^s Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs « see correspondence at serial numbers 36 and 62 of Afghan eeries 6 part 7* The necessity for this single control of policy on both aides of the Afghan frontier has* in our view* been clearly established by the experience of the 13 years which have elapsed since the establishment of the Legation in Kabul 0 Division of control would involve dangerous possibilities of friction and delay in handling of the frequent problems which arise* in which both the Afghan Government and our frontier administrations are vitally concerned* such* for instance, as the events following on the Ellis outrage in (? 1923)* Khost rebellion of 1924* incursion of Wazir tribesmen into Afghanistan tn \933 s and the present trouble with the Torobo Chiiiz&amp;ia* who are residents of Afghanistan but winter on the Indian aide of and close to the Durand Line,, we recognise that a necessary corollary to this power of control is the acceptance by us of the primary responsibility for peace-time expenditure in Afghanistan under both of the heads mentioned r\ above(w) SECRET W/AV* (£06 groups) 4911. PSCYPHBR OF TBLBGKAM , Prom Government of imUa* Foreign and Political Department, to (COPIES Secretary of State for India, CIRCULATED) Dated Simla, J4th September, 1935. Received 14th September, 1935, 9*30 p.m* XXX ^25* Part Three * 3* We feel, however, that it is necessary, in justice both to present Government of India and to Federal Government which will shortly succeed it, to re-state at this juncture the limitation which in our opinion, must be placed on this liability* we are strongly impressed with the necessity for the future Federal Government of India to have a clear knowledge of the maximum to which it is committed in any given year in respect of its extraordinary expenditure in Afghanistan and that it shall not find itself faced 7/ith demands, each of which may be described as necessary or even imperative^ the cumulative effect of which may be to impose, without any certainty or even prospect of relief in succeeding years, an intolerable burden on the Indian Exchequer already strained by heavy costs of defence*SECRET LJC/AW* {X39 groupt&gt;) 49X5* D 2 C Y PH E H .OF T 3 L, Prom (COPIES CIRCULATED) Dated Gc veminent of India^ Poreign tiiul political Department„ to Secretary of State tor India© S-mla* itth September^ 1935© Received 15th Septemberp 1935j ^©0 ae^c. XXX 2 475 o Eo.. *lHL c Por instaace, we are at present confronted with demand, including a sam which we estimate at between •&gt; an 4 )akhs annually un account of subsidisation of an Indian air line to Kabul and a possible further 8 lafrhe in course of the next six years in the not unlikely event of an Afghan default over the (? 5,000) rifles recently sold on credit to the Afghan Government* This would be increased by still further rials if the proposals for the sale of another 10,000 rifles and of a large number of aircraft fructify* ^e have a'so been called on to consider a iui indefinite demand for credits to subsidise Afghan economic development* 7?e have, therefore, been contxatned to re-examine the proposal of Sir P*Humphrys in 1923 ~ see paragraph of hi s Despatch Ho,. 56 of 1923 that a iixed annual sum should be assigned for the purpose of subsidy in kind 0 After weighing carefully the disadvantages oi c-his course we have come to the conclusion -hat on balance they are outweighed by the uncertainty involved in the present practice©it/aw. 4920 (J.fc4 groups) DBCYPHER 0 y TELEGRAM . From Government of India s Foreign &amp;nd Political Department P to Secretary (COPIES of State for India, CIRCULATED) Dated SimJa* 15th September s 1935^ Received 15th September* 1935 £ 1*25 XXX 2475, Fifth Part * 4* We are considering formation of equalisation reserve for extraordinary expenditure in connection with maintenance of peace on frontier on analogy of provincial famine relief funds: detailed proposals will be submitted in due course* In calculating annual appropriation to this reserve* we propose,,with your approval* to allot 5 lakhs for expenditure of nature referred to above* This figure corresponds closely enough to actual average cost of extraordinary expenditure on Afghanistan since 1921* Balance of annual appropriation over actual expenditure will be taken to reserve* In fixing maximum of reserve* we shall allow 25 lakhs for the purposes discussed in this telegram to provide for emergencies such as that of 3 931* Pro foma accounts of euoh Afghan expenditure will be maintained in addition to accounts of whole equalisation reserve 0 Careful scrutiny will be applied to ail proposals to be charged to this portion of reserve* it is essential of course that Afghan Government should receive no information of existence of such arrangement for their benefit^ this is one reason why we prefer a reserve on a broader basis than purely Afghan expenditure*SECRET ^XiT/DIA, (151 groups) JL&amp;JLXJLtL IL E—O-P T E L fi G R a i . 4921, From (COPIES ClflCULATED) Government of India, Foreign and Political Department, to secretary of State for India, Dated Simla, 15th September, 1935, Received 15th September, 1935, 2-lb p„m„ XXX 2415. §ixtb_Part» Any extraordinary demaixi beyond the resources of uuis -Tund especially if it relates primarily to countering of a I^uesian menace to security of India as a part of the British Bmpire, sfiould. in the absence of very special circumstances, l&gt;e met by His Majesty's Governments b e on condition that His Iflajesty’s Government will undertake the liability defined in paragraph No*5 of this telegram,, we propose dealing with specific proposals of His Majesty*s Minister as follows^ 5*000 rifles* tie agree to take risk of default on this account 'without charging defaults against fund* (b) 10»000 rifles, uJ If Afghans accept offer of His Majesty 6 s Government to sell 1914 rifles, we will give guarantee required at expense of our fund* (vi) If they refuse this offer and if Army here can at foiti to draw still further on their mobilisation reserve we will supply, subject to a similar guarantee from 'ter Office to that given in case of the 5*000* Any repayments will go !o Army to replace rifles; any default on repayments will fall on fund*SECRET PJM/CWP/DXAo (130 groups) 4922^ D.ii;_C_Y-P.H_E H O F T E L iii G R A Mo Prom Goyermntnt of India;, Foreign &amp; Political Departments to (COPIES Secretary of State for India, CIRCULATED) Dated Simla s 15th September* 1935. Jteeeived 15th September* 1935 6 3-15 p e m c XXX M2§. c Eajt,, (iii) If army cannot affoitl fuit/her to deplete their reserves we can only supply subject to the resources of the fund and in competition with other demandso (c) Sale of aircraft* This presents more difficulty as aircraft would not be available from stock like rifles but would have to be paid for at oncec We would be prepared to supply at once as many as the Afghan Government can pay for in cash. On credit we could not supply more than two in any one year without depleting fund 0 Initial cost would be (? debited) and any repayments credited to the fund, (d) Economic and mining experts. We would agree to charge cost of this to pro f orma Afghan reserve account without indenting on the new fund. We will address you separately on the subject of taking up option for air service between India and Kabul*etp/ljg/wb ILE OOPY P. z 6468 1935 j J SECRET (COPIES CIRCULATED) ( 117 groupso ) DECYPHER OF telegram^ From 4864o His Majesty^s Minister at Kabul to Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, India Office,, Dated Kabul, 12th September, 1935o Received 6,30 p.au, 12th September, 1935 (&gt; XXX 1&lt; t Goo V cc ^ ^pooo • FIRST OF TWO PARTS 0 In continuation of Katodon 92 0 2 0 Foreign Minister informed me, September 10th, that, after discussion in the Cabinet, Afghan Government would like to buy (a) 10,000, 1914 pattern rifles at the price (?omission)ed in paragraph HOo2 of Forminka 63, after full test, as described in paragraph Ho 0 3 of Forminka 75, for which they would of course pay rates quoted 0 t* (b) Six million rounds new small arms y ammunitioirtrom India as supplied in consignment just received; same rate 0 3o In response to discreet enquiries regarding payment, Foreign Minister said cash payment whole consignment was out of the question and War Minister V&gt;*3 would not consider purchasing (4o4harwar&amp;«) (c 0 fo Forminka 63, paragraph No 0 5) as arms were urgently needed 0 Fnd of first oart, second part follows^ Fraser-Tytler 96 T September lEtho. \ECo. PX. §EPt. 13 SEP 1935 N C. r-\ OFFICE&gt; SECRET etp/ljc/ecf/wb ( 88 groupso ) 0 P T E L E G B A Mo. 4865 o BECYPHER (COPIES CIRCULATED) Prom His Majesty*s Minister at Kabul to Secretary of State f° r Foreign Affairs, India Office 0 Dated Kabul s 12th September, 19350 Received 6,30 p.m,, 12th September, 1935 XXX SE COND AMD LAST PART ■&gt;_ Afghan GoTernment could only buy on deferred payments and suggest six equal annual instalments 0 4 0 I do not know whether His Majesty 7 s Government are prepared to consider payment oy instalments* but I am doubtful whether Afghan Government would make better c-ifer© If j however, I were authorised tp. discuss question of supplying remaining 15,000, vid e Katodon 92, paragraph Ho4, ^ might do so in the first place on basis of shorter term payments for full supply of 25,000 units 0 5 0 Prime Minister recently informed me that £100,000 had been earmarked in military budget for * next six years to pay for these arms and aeroplanes 0 SooD Praser-Tvtler 967 September l^tho sF';l E CORY c&gt; r SECRET jgs/frb/cw/fcr/'to (COPIES CIRCRLATED) I C I ( 187 groups, ) DECTPHBR OF TELEGRAM. From Y 4779, His Majesty 3 s Minister at Kabul to Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs* India Officeo Kabul, through Peshawar, 8th September, 1935 0 Dated Received 4 pom 0 , 8th September, 1935 0 XXX v ^ IMPORTANT o Forminka 75o 2 0 At interview today. Military Attache and I discussed the 1914 rifle further with War Minister on the lines of paragraphs (?2) to 4 of your teiegranu He seemed attracted by offer as now put to him, but deferred decision till after discussion with Cabineto 3 0 He asked for samples 0 I suggest 2 rifles might be sent by air 0 4 0 He raised question of supplying 30,000 units asked for 0 I said I only had authority to discuss supplying of 15,000, of which 5,000 had been receivedo War Minister said that full (?30,000) were urgently required to complete armaments of Afghan Army, and that question of whether he would ask for 1914 rifle or newest model depended to a considerable extent on whether His Majesty*s Government would supply Afghan Government with 15,000 or 30,000 units* In. any case payment could only be made by instalments 0 5* This question will come up again next week when 1/Var Minister wishes to discuss matter further* I should be glad of early instructions as to line I am to take* War Minister stated that for army of 50,000 they now had 250,000 (sic) ^$000Extract from Kabul Diary No&gt;29 dated 18th July 1935 12* Mr. Cermakian (Diary No.25, paragraph 31) said recently that he had failed to do a deal in machine guns with the Afghan War Office. The Minister of Defence had told him that he wanted the guns within six or eight months. This, Mr. Cermakian said, his firm, which had many orders in Europe to fulfill, could not do. The Minister then said he would have to deal elsewhere. Mr. Cermakian is hopeful however of selling .303 rifles and ammunition to the Afghan Government. His firm (Brno) has a stock of slightly used .303 rifles, and Mr. ftermakian, at the Minister of Defence^ request, has asked his firm to send out two as samples by air mail. 13. The Minister of Defence recently stated that he wished to buy 200 light and 400 heavy machine guns.— Draft Paper. (&gt; z 'L Department. Sir R. Paterson, K.B.E., C.B., WAR OFFICE, S.W. 1. y 2 7 AUG 1955 Many thanks for year letter of 23rd August. We have made a note of the reduction in the price of the cartridges S.A.Ball .303, in case further developments arise. (Sd.) J. 0. WALTQ*.With reference to my letter of 22nd July, on the subject of the sale of rifles and small arm ammunition to Afghanistan, it has now been decided to reduce the price of the Cartridges, S.A. Ball ,303, taken from war stock, from £1.4.-. to £1.1.-. per 600 rounds delivered at Karachi. I realise that the telegram from Praser Tytler of 31st July shows that a sale is highly improbable as we are unable to guarantee the ammunition, but you should be aware of the reduction in price in case further developments arise. J.C. Walton, Esq., C.B., M.C., India Office.C ' ! S&gt; Register Nn. 'Tz SECRET. POLITICAL DEPARTMENT Tele gran) from Dated Rec. Formally acknowledged 19 Date. To Chairman Under Secretary Secretary of ^tate... Committee Under Secretary Secretajp^ of State N/b'f 7 ». . ^ ' Y^ t 'p.C.i' Initials. SUBJECT. Ai 1 GHAlNilSTAN . Supply ox rifles to Afghan Government. Copy of to FOR USE BY DEPARTMENTS ONLY. Draft telegram to H.M. Minister, Kabul. to 2 3 Ab Ql 935 Previous Papers :—Minute Paper. ^2 Department The history of the Afghan^quest for a supply of munitions will be found in the Minute at P.Z. 4758/35. 5,000 rifles have already arrived at Kabul and the Government of India were preparing to send a further in depleting Indian stocks to this extent/, and it was, therefore, proposed that the Afghan requirements for the supply of these 10,000 rifles should be made from War Office stocks of unused 1914 pattern rifles in this country as an alternative to their supply from India. The minutes of the Conference which discussed this proposal were submitted (flagged G) and the telegrams P.Z. 5005 were sent to Kabul and the Government of India. The Government of India's,reply will be found at P.Z. 5186 in which they draw attention to the fact that these rifles exhibited certain magazine defects. They felt that as the Afghanis are connoisseurs of small arms it would be undesirable to sell them rifles under false pretences. T£e^reactions of the Afghan Ministers to th&amp;e proposal are reported in Col. Fraser-Tytler’s it does not seem likely that they will accept the offer. After consultation with the War Office it is, however, proposed to send the draft telegram now submitted. 10,000 within six months. ls. There is, however, a danger r'wc*&gt;/ telegram'P.Z. 5243. They were not enthusiastic, and«*• ^ Pz. -aft Paper. From Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs To ii*M.*Minister, Kabul. Repeated to Gover. ment of India, F. da P. Department. Forminlda Peshawar 0 &lt;S&gt;. Cypher iXX S' 3S Department. 37G1 5000 5.35 Katodon, Ro.77 of 31ct July. / x ✓ ✓ 2. Statement in Small Arms Book ^ 4 referred to in Government of Indian telegram of ^9th July Do.1896 is , ^ f + misleading. 1914 pattern rifle was ^ + originally designed to take a cartridge / * * y y with a bullet of *276 calibre/ When f + +■ / however it was decided to substitute s* t the *303 cartridge it become necessary to put a lining into the magazine in * * t * + order that it mi lit take the smaller cartridges.' The only result of the alteration is that if the bolt is used m a slovenly manner a round occasional! sticks. 3. -.lease inform the -Afghan Govern..ient f p s in this sense. You may also soy as regards guarantee of reliability that /'V ^ f * &amp; + s ‘«'ar Office regard these rifles as so ✓ * ^ satisfactory that they were considering . . . . f ^ * + a short time ago substituting them for the Bhort l»ee Enfield Rifles now used ir 0 * s uhe Regular - rmy. Proposal was however turned down for other reasons. ^ ✓ it may therefore be said that H.M.G. f * t # consider rifles to be reliable.' As an additional safeguard the »var Office + f + + &gt;&gt; recommends that each rifle should be x / / given an individual inspection and al^o ^ _. . # ^ s y a firing test for accuracy of sighting* The additional cost of these test^would be Ssr/ea. for each fifle^ bayonet' and ^f J l Ef.aft Paper. Department. H ls'6d. would be due' for Bcabbord of whio the firfrig^teot. ^ln this connection statement of Afgiian'^Prime Minister in ^ XI- ^ S s' S Katodon No.77 para* 3 about similar pattern rifles 'fresumably refers to ocdle X' / / / S of some -thousands of ^1914 pattern rifles^througlf^lemin^ via Paris In / 19^8. These were taken from the semeX stock^as now offered but they were noty' specially selected nor individually inspected before sale. 4. Xwar OfficeXire not prepared to give any^particular or written X S s / y s guar ant ee^vvith this type of rifle^beyond emphasising itsXaerits and ssdggesting additional^safeguard of inspection^T If by written guarantee^VarXTinister means^ that if' any of the rifles'be found ^by the £f. :hans amc unsatisfactory by the Afghans amount zy ^ ^ ^ ^ paid for than would be refunded to Afghan Government^ !!• *G. could not give such a^guarantee even in respect of nev^ rifles in view of impossibility-^f their being''sure that after delivery to the are Afghans'they would be looked'after as carefullX a s by British' units. 5.' llease telegraph your'views on ^ Goverimient of India*s'suggestion that S' ^ some sample rifles might be sent for^ S trial by the Afghans. 07or Office do y / ^ ^ not think it necessary to send sample / / - o 1 rifles especially in view of the explanation/^Department explanation and inspection offered in paragraphs 2 and 3.^ On the other hand S' &lt;'■' —■ they con despatch samples on payment by the Afghans if it is thought that such s ^ S ^ ^ s'* a course would avoid any possibility of^roisunderstanding ^r recrimination, ^ 6. it is cletr that Afghans will x ^ ^ r- not take old onLiunition and for new ^ stock the best source of supply would be India*Department Draft Paper. From Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs To H.M. Minister, Kabul Repeated to Government of India, F. &amp; p. Department. a c jf' L r.o Katodon, No. 77 of 31st July. 2. Statement in Small Arms Book referred to in Government of India’s telegram of 29th July No. 1896 is misleading. 1914 pattern rifle was originally designed to take a cartridge with a bullet of -276 calibre. When however it was decided to substitute the *303 cartridge it became necessary to put a lining into the magazine in order that it might take the smaller cartridges. The only result of the alteration is that if the bolt is used in a slovenly manner a round occasionally sticks. 3. Please inform the Afghan Government in this sense. You may also say as regards guarantee of reliability that War Office regard these rifles as so satisfactory that they were considering a short time ago substituting them for the Short Lee Enfield Rifles now used in the Regular Army. Proposal was however turned down for other reasons. It may therefore be said that H.M.G. consider rifles to be reliable. as an additional safeguard the War Office recommends that each rifle should be given an individual inspection and also a firing test for accuracy of sighting. The additional cost of these tests would be 5^6 for each rifle, bayonet and scabbard of which 2^6 would be due for the firing test. 3761 5000 5.35Department. In this connection statement of Afghan Prime Minister in Katodon No. 77 para.3 about similar pattern rifles presumably refers to sale of some thousands of 1914 pattern rifles through Fleming via Paris in 1928. These were taken from the same stock as now offered but they were not specially selected nor individually inspected before sale. 4. War Office are not prepared to give any particular or written guarantee with this type of rifle beyond emphasising its merits and suggesting additional safeguard of inspection. J %£ Wsr $f-fioc mean* that if any of the rifles be found unsatisfactory by the Afghans amount paid for them would be refunded to Afghan Government, H.M.G. could not give such a guarantee even in respect of new rifles in view of impossibility of their being sure that after delivery to the Afghans they would be looked after as carefully as by British units. 5. Please telegraph your views on Government of India’s suggestion that some sample rifles might be sent for trial by the Afghans. War Office do not think it necessary to send sample rifles especially in view of the explanation and inspection offered in paragraphs 2 and 3. On the can despatch samples on Afghans if it is thought that such a course would avoid any possibility of misunderstanding other hand (iei payment by t] or/Department ft tacrimination. 6. It is clear that Afghans wi]J_ not ■la kuJ Jr^ck take old ammunition and n’oiure Lhink the best source of supply wou4.d be India.SECRET 0164/6213 (M.I.2.) . 5H' ij August, 1935. Thank you very much for your letter of 3rd August with its enclosures. To take each of the points in your second paragraph in turn:- (1) . I have made some suggestions in my comments on para.3. of your draft telegram. (2) . There is no .objection. (3) • I am certain that you can rest assured that British reputation will not suffer from the sale of these rifles, if the tests suggested below (para.3. draft telegram) are exercised. As regards the draft telegram forwarded by you:- (a) . (b) . Para,2, States the facts exactly, and I think it should stand as drafted. Para.3, I suggest it might be redrafted on the following lines H.A.F.Kumbold, Esq,, Political Department, India Office, S.W.l. Please /f* * Please inform the Afghan Government in this sense. You may also say as regards guarantee of reliability that War Office regard these rifles as so satisfactory that they were considering a short time ago substituting them for the Short Lee Enfield rifles now used in the Regular Army. Proposal was however, turned down for other reasons. It may therefore be said that H.M.G. consider rifles to be reliable. As an additional safe guard the War Office recommends that each rifle should be given an individual inspection, and also a firing test for accuracy of sighting. The additional cost of these tests would be 5s, 6d, for each rifle, bayonet and scabbard, of which 2s.6d. would be due for the firing test. In this connection statement of Afghan Prime Minister in Katadon No.77, para.3, about similar pattern rifles presumably refers to sale of some thousands of 1914 pattern rifles through Fleming via Paris in 1928. These were taken from the same /same stock as now offered, but they were not s pecially selected, nor individually inspected before sale* Para # 4. I suggest the following additional wording before the commencement of your draft:- not Phe War Office are/prepared to give any particular or written guarantee with this type of rifle beyond emphasising its merits and suggesting additional safeguard of inspection. Para,5. F do not think it necessary to send sample rifles especially in view of the explanation and inspection offered in paras.2 and 3. On the other hand we could despatch samples fr % l « if it is thought that such a course would avoid any possibility of misunderstanding or recrimin ation. Fraser-f'ytler might be asked his views on this point. If the Afghans want sample rifles, they will have to pay for them.* (e) Para,6. As regards ammunition# It is clear the Afghans will not take old ammunition and I suggest they should be advised to buy new stock if they want any. In this case I think the best source of supply would be India. '^he War Office price could not be less than cost of replacement plus cost of carriage, and in any event this transaction might be difficult to effect. In this connection. If this suggestion is accepted, the War Office would not be concerned in the reply to Fraser-Tytler*s query in para.2. of telegram No.500 dated 22nd July.Extract from Diary No.29 for the week ending 18th July, 1935. Kabul. 12. Mr. Cermakian (Diary No.25, paragraph 31) said recently that he had failed to do a deal in machine guns with the Afghan War Office. The Minister of Defence had told him that he wanted the guns within six or eight months. This, Mr. Cermakian said, his firm, which had many orders in Europe to fulfill, could not do. The Minister then said he would have to deal elsewhere. Mr. Cermakian is hopeful however: of selling .303 rifles and ammunition to the Afghan Government. His firm (Brno) has a stock of slightly used .303 rifles, and Mr.Cermakian, at the Minister of Defence's request, has asked his firm to send out two as samples by air mail. 13. The Minister of Defence recently stated that he wished to buy 200 light and 400 heavy machine guns./ ggn ret 1hmn± you T«ry much for your letter of 31 #t July to Dalton who la or a few days laavw, about sal a of rifles and awrur?!tion to the Afghan OoTam ont. 1 soul J ba inclinod to rersly to tha ^Iniotor, If you concur. X aJioul 1 be grateful for your Yiewa on thia ihare are tho following points in it on hi eh wa should be particularly grateful for your gul anee. \1) o«ui we * jr that is huIww taittuts^way ii*«wrte4 in paragraph 3 of the draft about Inspect ion? if not, coul i you suggest an alternative? 12) Do you see any objection to passing on to the Afghan Uavern ent the statement that the war Office conoid ere' some titae age substituting the lb!4 pattern rifle for the short Lee- nfield? If we can say this we go a long towards giving the Afghans the guarantee of reliability for which they a sic. / / / enclose a copy of a furth-r telsgraa which v.# have / / received from Fraser 'iytler, !*o*?7 # of 31st J^ly, &gt;n6 also a very tentative draft along the lines of which we draft hr i gad i er i&gt;. ?. An er son, C. v • (i* 0 I). S» 0» t uar office, d. V. 1. (3)/2. (3) in eon&amp;iduring ho't fur mm can go in giving a ^uar-anto® of rcliadilitj, great weight has of course to b‘- giv n to the &gt;oir t *ade by Freser-iytier about our present high reputation .sith the Afghan Govern ert for the quality of our usnutions being at stake* Wt.)&amp; the political point of view also it ie necessary to be careful on t is point* We -flight perhaps consult ^reaer-Tytler as suggested in the draft on ths question of sending on so -'.e ssoujIss? 1 an sending a copy of this letter to Dodds et the foreign office* (Sd.) H. A. F. RUMBOLODraft Paper, Department. Brigadier D.F. Anderson, C.M.G., D.S.O., War Office. S-aCBET &amp; PERSOHAL. / /J ^ ^' Copy to Mr. Scrt^i 5 ’ 1 '• r °' ^ uvVV ^ ^ fWk SAio* s Of 4./*^ *■» C+~*- ****** ^ ^ a ^ Ay/ ^ ^ /4 ^/ ^ a. a / / Woo » ,•3 / 4^v*^ A ^A^- A ^ / t ^J ^ ^ ^ ^ / 4 ^ 3 AUG 1935 Thank you very much for your 4 OiU ^ yLv 3*^ 4^ letter of 31st July/about sale of rifles and ammunition to the Afghan Government. I enclose a copy of a further telegram which we have received from Lfr-Qod?. Fraser Tytler, No. 77, of 3lst July* a copy of-which io going te— the- V/ar Qffio« offirlally and also a very tentative draft along the lines of which we sh^.ul-d- like to reply to the Minister. I should be grateful for your views on this draft. There are twcr points in it on which we should be particularly grateful for your guidance. Jji-the-firot-^plat^eT— £? do you see any objection to passing on to the Afghan Government the statement that the War Office considered some time ago substituting the 1914 pattern rifle for the short Lee-Enfield. 27 if we can say this we go a long way towards giving the Afghans the guarantee of reliability for which they ask. The Rftrtnnri pn i rvh to whi particularly wish to draw^artTffention is whether we coi^Ld^say that H.M.G. consider therifles to be reliable. •Ncrt only_JLs^our present high reputation with the Afghan Government for the quality of our munitions^at stake, bnt' ak«€&gt; mir general good faifch-»afld x Trom the political point of view^ it wtruld 3761 5000 5.35Draft Paper Department. From Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs To H.M. Minister, Kabul, repeated Government of India, Foreign &amp; Political Department, Forminka, Peshawar. Cypher XXX Copy to F.O. W. 0 .(Secv'ei-j A x5 3761 5000 5.35 Katodon, No. 77 of 31st July. 2. Statement in Small Arms Book referred to in Government of India’s telegram of 29th July No. 1896 is misleading. 1914 pattern rifle was originally designed to take a cartridge with a bullet of •276 calibre. When however it was decided to substitute the *303 cartridge it became necessary to put a lining into the magazine in order that it might take the smaller cartridges. The only result of the alteration is that if the bolt is used in a slovenly manner a round occasionally sticks. 'h. Please inform AfghanGovernme /-WV ^that rifles are-reg-nlar.ly inspected by / War Office and they will be given special inspection before their despatch from £i-v» SA+f United Kingdom. As regards guarantee of reliability War Office regard these rifles as so satisfactory that they were considering a 'short time ago substituting them for the Short Lee Enfield rifles q-* used Id the Regular Army. Proposal was/however turned down for other reasons. It may therefore be said that H.M.G. consider rifles to be reliable. W. Yotr-iafty ral p,n make snob use as you / /Jr wi-slvof argument that if by written ids**. Kv . -3 guarantee Is-jBeant that if rifles were-- it- ffc r?&gt; ^found unsatisfactoryv amount paid for them would be refunded to Afghan Government/Goverrmentjj/il.M.G. could not give such a guarantee even in respect of new rifles u^yposs ibtUV ^ in view of imper-tance of their being sure that after delivery to the Afghans, they would be looked after as carefully as by British units. 6\ Please telegraph whether -you— — ^ wish sample rifles—fco—be—oent to you. 6 . H.M.G. ceuinot give guarantee regarding ammunition but rifles couldPC H/CWP/LJ C/D IA FILE COfPYj.&gt; 2 .. ^o ^ &lt; SECRET | 0 ■ v' 4 / (121 groUpal . 406^. y- ' / JxtJLasi C X-E-L,.S.P..B..A. ) C, ’ Prom Hie Majesty’s Minister at Kabul to Secretary of State for Foreign (COPIES Affairs&gt; India office. CHCULATED) Dated Kabul,,31st July, 1935. Received 31st July, 1935, 5*45 p,m, x. — ft* , XXX P-1 rst-gf.. ^ .Ear ts . ^ °' Formlnka 63, J uly 27th. Arms for the Afghan Government, 2. I was Just leaving for interviews when I received Foreign telegram to the Secretary of State for \ t India, No*1896p It was not possible to £ut off meetings and I therefore discussed His Majesty*a Government’s off er with the Afghan Ministers In general teims with a view to finding out whether they were interested in it. 3« As regards rifles, War Minister said they had bought similar pattern rifles through French firm some years ago and had found them fairly satis^actorye Before considering the offer further he asked for inspection of rifles by British experts and a written guarantee of their reliability, I said that at the price he could not expect guarantee In terms similar to that given for the latest pattern, but that I would enquire further om this point. Enfl-pf. Flrgt, Part, Secpnfl, Pa&amp;XQ,U?ws. Fraser Tytler 77 ,si** REVISED COPY* FRB/CHfP/DIAAil. (139 groups) SECRET 4062. D E G Y P H E P Off TELEGRAM. (COPIES CIRCULATED) From Hia Majesty’s Minister at Kabul to Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, India Officeo Dated Kabul* 31st Julyj 1935. Received 31st July, 1955, 7'~3C p-nu xxx Second anti Last Par to 4* As regards ammunition War Minister &amp;aid that if His Majesty’s Government could not give guarantee he could not consider offere Ammunition was required to replenish stocks and might not be used for some considerable time. His own experience was that no ammunition was really reliable after ten years c 5c Generally speaking Afghan Ministers were not attracted by the offer,, I emphasised the low price and fact that rifle was being used with muon success at Bisley* eto* But as Government of India note, Afghans are connoisseurs in small arms and Ear Minister insisted they must have reliability and were prepared to pay for it, in instalments,. Unless therefore guarantee of high degree of reliability in face of Ministers' (?* demands) can he given in respect of the rifles, I do not advise that the proposals now under consideration should be pursued. It would be a pity to impair His Majesty's Government's high reputation here for quality of their goods,, Fraser Tytler 77. July Sl at, NOTE , This telegram has been revised in accordance with corrections received from the Telegraph Company, 2nd August, 1935.As Ismay is a?my on leave until the 20th August, your letter to him of the 30th inst. has been opened by me. J.G From enquiries I have made the statement in the Small Arms Book referred to by India appears to be misleading. The 1914 pattern rifle was orginally designed to take a cartridge with a bullet of .276 calibre, when, however, it was decided to substitute the .303 cartridge it became necessary to put a lining into the magazine, in order that it might take the smaller cartridges. The only result of the alteration is that, if the bolt is used in a slovenly manner a round occasionally sticks. in view of the above do you consider the question of samples arises? In fact, so satisfactory are these rifles considered that the War Office was considering a short time ago substituting them for the Short Lee-Enfield rifles at present bem^ used in the Regular Army, the proposal being turned down for other reasons. With reference to the last para, of your letter I quite agree with your proposed draft to Acheson. There seems to be no good reason for giving any additional publicity to the transaction. Walton Esq., G.B., M.C., India Office, S.W.l. irv SUITSHALL, S.3. 1. 30th July. 1935. 1 enclose a s-pas*® co^ of a t si8(^*3 fwvsa t.he iioi emnent of copy of which iu.s {Wta officially to the «ar Office ooder oar printed letter, P.2.0186/55, about the 1914 pattent rifle*. if the rifles ire liak-H- to i;!dividual defecte of the kind referred to oy the OoverriBent of India, it ni, jit be wiee to ou'oiw the ..f^ian ;soifenr.unt cf the fact. Bat of course it would be preferable, if poMiblt, to select rifle* eithout thece defects to \-e able to givs the guar&lt;uitee feuggesrtod by the OoTemruerit oi India. Is this practicable? The hovemraent of India’s suggestion jthat aaeiple rifles wi^it be sent r«jy in any case be a good one. These are all points, of course, for the iar Off ret, Ougiit we to send an o i ficial letter iskin^; for advice/ Colonel H.L. Immy, C.B., ii.u.U., WAH uFFlCii, 3 . 1 . 1 .advice as to the reply to be returned to the Goverffisent of India* s telegram, or cun these points be disposed of demi-officially for the sake of exoedition? I m sending this deiri-official letter to you in the first instance as you have been good enough to show so much interest in the case* 1 also enclose an advance copy of a demi- official telegram from Fraser-Tytler about the 5*000 rifles. I can*t think tdiy he suggests a conrunication to the Idress in India, and perhaps kcheapn will turn the idea down of his own accord. There would seem to be no advantage in giving additional publicity to tne aeal in India, and frora our point of view at this end also i imagine that it is to be deprecated, since the afghan announcement naturally refers to purchases from the British Government (though they are actually from India’s stocks). If Collier agrees, I would orooose to sem a demi-official telegram to Vcheson deprecating any announcement in . (Sgd.) J.C. Walton.INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL* S.W. 1. 30th July, 1935 I enclose copy of a letter sent to Isniay regarding the Goveminevit of India's telegram of 29th July, No* 1896. Sith reference to Fraser-Tytler’s demi-official telegram of 30th July, copy of which is also enclosed, 1 would propose, if ^ou concur, to send a reply in the «ense of t ^e attached draft* (Sgd.) J.C. Walton. L. Collier, Em*, FOREIGN OFFICE, S.W. 1*FILE GOrt SECRET pch/u c/aw, PBCYPH3R 0? TBLaiGRAM (130 group a) 4034 V ^ yJUj OS From Government of India s Foreign (COPIES CIRCULATED) Dated and Political Department, to Secretary of State for India. Dated Simla, 29th July, 1935. Received 29th July, 1935, 8 p.m, IMPORT A. T. ^ 5 '°' XXX 1QU 6. Addressed to Secretary of State, 1896, repeated to Kabul, 20? Form ink a 64 From the text book. Small Arms, 1929, pages 7 and 8, it appears that the 1914 pattern rifles are not entirely suitable for general ue© in the field and that the magazines are also not wholly satisfactory. It seems most desirable that the Afghans, who are connoisseurs in email arms, should be frankly informed of these defects, especially ae British munitions hitherto supplied to them have always been satisfactory. It is suggested that some sample rifles might be sent .preferably by air, for trial by Afghans before they decide to purchase. Samples should,, of course,, include some in rixles exhibiting the magazine defects mentioned/the text books, unless it can be guaranteed that no rifles with these defects would be supplied. Understood that Brno firm (Czeoho Slovakia) ar sending two os. vheir old rifles to Afghanistan by air.SECRET P.Z. 5X80/36. GOVERNMENT OP INDIA FOREIGN A POLITICAL DEPARTMENT EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). D.O. No.F. 320-F/34. Dated t the 22nd July 1935. TO: Secretary of State for India, London. Demi-official. Walton from Acheson Your telegram 13th July No.2192. Your difficulty in obtaining decision on our telegram of 29th June within short time limit imposed by imminence of Jashan is fully understood here, and we appreciate action of His Majesty’s Government in giving the arms guarantee. Seasons given in our telegram of 29th June for insistence on both arms and financial guarantee were real. On consideration of their position in light of new financial burden imposed on them by Quetta, Government of India felt very strongly on point of incidence of cost and on their side agreement to defer decision on this point was due to desire to contribute to solution of immediate problem confronting both Governments. We are consulting Fraser-Tytler regarding 1914 rifles suggestion but I doubt if Afghans would regard it with favour if as is believed here they are being offered new ones cheap by Japanese. The issue of the above has been authorised. (Sgd.) 0.K. CAROE, Deputy Secretary to the Government of India.© Minute Paper. Department. The W.O. agree to the draft telegrams with minor amendment, and have supplied a description of the rifles and ammunition and their capabilities for insertion in the telegram addressed to Kabul. They agree to the amendment of para. 4 of the telegram addressed to the G. of I. suggested by Sir . Stewart in the margin of the original draft. Mr. Collier of the F.Q. has telephoned concurring in the drafts, which might accordingly issue. Perhaps the S. of S. would be willing also to send a private telegram to acknowledge the Viceroy’s private telegram of 17th July (flagged A), and v/ith a view to facilitating sympathetic consideration of the suggestion in the official draft that the G* of I. should accept a certain contingent liability pending a decision on the general principle of the incidence of charges for measures calculated to promote the stability of the Afghan ' Govt. The contingent liability involved in the present case would be less than that involved by the supply of more costly rifles from India, especially as payment would probably be less long deferred, and there is, as a matter of fact, a good prospect of the Afghan Govt, lasting until it is completed. A draft telegram is suggested. Kabul telegram of 21st July (at P.Z. 5005/35 ) is also submitted; We have asked for repetition of the figure quoted in para. 2, but if it is 8 lakhs, it means that the Afghan Govt, have agreed to pay approximately the cost of these rifles to the G. of I. This is satisfactory, especially as it indicates that the Afghan Govt, are not inclined to haggle over prices.PZ. Scot; Department. From S. of S. for F.A. to H.M. Minister, Kabul. [&gt;?&gt; ^ „ - Please see para. 4 of telegram from S. of S. for I. to G. of I., No. 2190, dated 13th July. Supply of rifles to Afghan Govt. In this connection please see also para. 2 of Forminka b7 of 5th July, 1934, para. 2 of Forminka 70 of 4th September and para. 3 of Katodon 101 of 26th September, 193^. ^ 2. W.O. have large stocks of unused 1914 pattern rifles which they could supply at price of £5 per rifle complete with bayonet, scabbard, oil bottle and pull-through, delivered at Karachi. W.O. also have stocks of .303 ammunition made during the War which they could supply at a price of £1.4.0 per 600 rounds^delivered at Karachi. 3. Further particulars of the rifles and ammunition are as follows: Hifies. . Bazins ■•■3Q3'- The rifles can be reckoned as unused weapons, having been made for the British Army during tlie war and only issued in small numbers to Home Defence Units. L-Ost of the rifles have only fired the number of rounds necessary for inspection while the remainder can be taken/Draft Paper. v^) Department. French rifles / / / / / / If they cannot pay cash for 10,000 at once ^bhey might wish to 'purchase what they can 'afford-liow 'and the ''remainder^at subsequent' dates./ I may add''for your information that^we understand that Afghan Govt. ^^Iready'ih negotiation through a^ intermediary^for purchase^of such ^ fron/Messrs. Soiey'f and it seems ^ highly probablejthat purchasing through/ such a channel they would have to^pay a^ considerably^higher cash priced If they / can afford this they are perhaps the more likely to b/attracted by our' own''offer / also.' Sy , 5. toa shoaldrit once,^in'whatever ;deem best, make offer to Afghan manner you Govt . / to sell' 10, ly smaller .0,000’ or an] number of these rifles on terms'mentioned and ascertain whether t he,&lt;r e luract.d'' / / / / / / by the proposal, and are y able to pay cash on delivery for 10 .000 at ^ce'ir for sma Her numbers gradually delivered over a'^period of time.'^ . /g / y 6.' If however Afghan Govt./while / / / ^ willing to take 7 these rifles, profess to x X X / j be unable to make any purchase except on deferred payment,^it is desirable^o obtain information of their proposals. In this event, therefore,^you should' discreetly ascertain what is the best y ^ ^ / basis of payment by instalments that theyDraft Paper. Department. X •'L / ^ of our telegrarng) This contingent 's’ * liability must be much smaller than that S s S s' which would be involved by supply of—' 10,000'rifles 'from India,’^both on account / / , ^ s' s. . of the lov/er price and because it seems probable that payment (if deferred at s f ^ s' all) 'would be spread over a shorter / / ^ s period^) ^Risk of default would be ^ correspondingly less since position of Afghan Gpvt., according to Fraser- .y , ~ s . y Tytler’s reports, seems to be growing stronger rather than otherwise, and there seems to be a reasonable pros:Tect of the regime lasting for at any rate some years.Immam INDIA OFFICE. WHITEHALL. S.W* 1. 23rd Jaly. 1935. / / i enclose copy of a letter from Katerson, / / and its enclosore. regarding the draft telegrams to / / ^raser-Tytler and the Government of India about the ^ 1914 rifles. could you let me know whether the 'oreign Office concur in the despatch of the telegrams #ith Paterson’s amendments (to which we see no objection)^ (Sgd.) J.C. Walton. L. Collier, Eso«. C, .G., FOREIGN OFFICE, S.W. 1.I return the draft telegram amended3in accordance with our views* I have included the substance of the addition you told me of on Saturday but I may not have got your exact words - please amend if you wish. I see no object in telling Fraser Tytler the details of how the £3# will be apportioned when we get it*^ J • G• Walton* Esq.. * C.B. * M• G. * India Office*TELEGRAM TO HIS MAJESTY’S MINISTER, KABUL* Para.2. India Office can condense this as they think desirable. 4 Second sentence - omit. (Prom 'This price is ••••••••••• to 4th September * 1934 . t para.3. - substitute;- Rifles, Ma g azine .303'. P/1914. B.R.A.Mk,!* The rifles can be reckoned as unused weapons, having been made for the British Army during the war and only issued in small numbers to Home Defence Units. Most of the rifles have only fired the number of rounds necessary for inspection while the remainder can be taken as not having fired more than two or three hundred rounds. Rifles of this pattern were this year allowed to be used in the National Rifle Association competitions at Bisley and achieved much success. The 1914 Pattern rifle is also, with the addition of the necessary fittings to take a telescopic sight, the sniper rifle of the British Army. Ammunition. Cartridges, Small Arm, Ball .303', Mk.VII. While, in view of the age of this ammunition, no guarantee can be given, recent reports show that the ammunition continues to behave in a reasonably regular manner.TELEG R AM TO GOVE R NMENT OP INDIA Para#4« line 20* For Spending a decision on this general question” read 'pending a decision on this general question and without prejudice to the decision, to agree to indemnify His Majesty’s Governmentdkaft telegr/^ oy. h . .xxx FROM SKOH TARY OF 3TATK FOH FOREIGN AFFAIRS TO HIS MAJESTY’S MINI3TK* f KABUL* Please see paragraph 4 of telegram fro* Secretary of State for Inula to Got eminent of naia. No. 2190, dated l&lt;5th July* Supply of rifles to Afghan Government. 2* War office have large stocks of unused 1914 pattern rifles which they could supply at price of £3 per rifle complete with bayonet, scabbard, oil bottle ana pull-through, delivered at Karachi* This price is maue up as followsi £3.&amp;*0. cost to far office, bs* carriage, *nd 10a. compensation to Messrs* Holey who possess the selling rights (see Formiaka 70 of 4th bepteaber 1934)* War Office also have stocks of •303 ammunition made during the War which they coula supply at a price of £1*4.0. per duo ro nas delivered at Karachi* 3* (Lescriotion of rifles and ammunition).2SW 2# 4. Ftcjbi the Afghan ;x&gt;int of view# eu rply of XOfOOO of these units (rifled plus 600 rounds of amranltion) at a price of £4* 4.o. per unit plus cost of transport from Karachi to Afghanistan would appear to be a much more attractive proposition than urchase of current pattern rifles from Xnai&amp;n stocks at a nrice approximating to cost ^ucted in paragraph 6(b) of Government of India’s telegram of 29th ^une» No. 1686# which mox’lcs out at nearly £11 per unit, price quoted above is for cash on delivery# but# even so# offer might be attractive to Afghan Government. If they cannot pay cash for l0#O 0 at once they might wish to purchase what they can afford now and the remainder at subsequent dates. I may add for your information that we understand that Afghan Government is already in negotiation through a French intermediary for purchase of such rifles from Messrs* Soley# and it seems highly probable that purchasing through such a channel they would have to pay a considerably higher cash price. If they can afford this thej are perhaps the more likely to be attracted/attracted bjr uur own offer also* &amp;• You should at once* in whatever manner you deem best* make offer to Afghan Governwent to sell 10*000 or any smaller number of these rifles on terms mentioned and ascertain whether they are attracted by the pro 'Osal* and are able to pay cash on delivery for 10*000 at once or for smaller numbers gradually delivered over a period of time* 6* If however Afghan Ooveromtn t* while willing to take these rifles* profess to be unable to make any purchase except on deferred payment* it is desirable to obtain information of their proposals* In tnis event* therefor you should discreetly ascertain what is th best basis of payment by instalments that they can offer* but you should not at this stage commit Ris Majesty's Government to accepting payment by instalments as this question is still under consideration (see telegram No* dated to Government of ncia)*1 .L/XmlI 1 ’!' j.’ itJ. i-iwi 4 s.it Cyi^ier jUJL /iddroBeed by bee rot ary of State to ttovermaant of India and repeated to H.&lt;u. Minister, Kabul. FormirUta . Supply of riflet? to AtijaL&amp;n Government. If offer which U.tA. U ini a ter has been instructed to make ie tnoepted by Afghan Goyermaent, this will afford by fur tho least ooatlj afeana of sutisfying our political desideratum, meet their reidflot for aaslstance in the interests of their internal aecurity. From Indian point of Yiew, tills alternative neoiae also to have the advantage of avoiding &lt; riek of a further depletion of Indiras wjjt reoervea. 5. If ^fghan Government ; h ? vii.g regard to low price offered, are able to pry cash for consignments aa delivered, no difficulty will nrine. 4. If, howover, the^ prate for p&lt; yment by instilments, it eeeme probable that, having regard to the disparity in price, they may bo able to offer a much more fjvourrble basie of deferred payment a -,han the six-year bi^nie offered to the Govoriiment of India, j.ny bfujio of deferred ra^rsaent, ho ever, ^ould involve a liability on His Majeety'e Governmont which (in view ea peel ally of the fset th« t an/rr c~ , ^ '■ V: 1 ^ 0 lj4. 1 trK, IT— I, ^ ^ 4» (fk- '^'Ml ft, cyn unpaid claim on the j.jTghtm Government would h&amp;ve to appear in the appropriation account^ they arc reluctant to undertiJce pending a decision on general ue.tion of incidence of charges for anj&amp;fcuroB ot&lt;lcul^ ted to aaaiat Afghan Government, ne trust therefore tnat^in event ol deferred payments being proj^oned raid agreed to, Govemment of India would bo willing. &lt;h e ' fid* H}~p. peiuiiag a decision on this general ft- ♦ ju*&lt;f Vi s'-j (~ ^ -—^ uoatior^ to a^ree to reimburse Uio Majeaty 1 © Government in respect of any loss incurred through delivory of rifxea in advenoe of payment and eventual default of payment at due date. lou v.^11 oooervo that this contingent liability vould be v^zry much smtHler than that incurred by sale of 10,000 of the more expensive rifles from your war reserves on deferred payments spread over six years, b. I t*ould be glad if you could let me have a reply on point raised in paragraph 4 above when once Fraser-Tytler has uaoertaired from Afghan Government whether they euro attracted by our offer, whether or to what extent they can pay cosh, and what is the beet bta,is of deferred payment that they could accept. When tills information is available it will be possible to calculate more accurately the extent of the cuntingent liability (if &amp;nyy involved.3164/6S«i3 ' ^ &lt;,'.K l?L * C A OiL^ISV.^ Note on Conference et the war of floe held on 18th July f 1958. air R. pateraon, (iar office) - in the ohair. Mr. B*K. Bridges ) Mr. G.E.A. Grey ) ^aeury. Mr. L. Collier, Foreign office. Mr. J.C. Walton, India office. Colonel H.1-. laiiay, M.l.M. Mr. fi.t. Noggridge, O.B.A.C. Major JV . Merrifian,M.a.0.5, Mr. Q.f. Lanbert, M.G.O.F. | War office. ) 1« The chairman outlined the history of the proposal to supply 15,000 rifles to the Afghan GoYernnen,. He had Marned that the Indian Government had now agreed to supply 5,000 rifles from Indian stocks at once, H.&lt;v. Government having undertaken to aa*ce t;ood, in on emergency, any deficiency up to this nu&amp;toer slthout prejudice to the question of payment, which would follow any decision reached as to India 9 a general request for aauist&amp;nce in their Afghan relations. The Conference now nad to consider ne proposal to supply the remaining 10,000 rifles by selling them to Afghanistan from far Office stocks of 19i4 pattern. He explained that the B.^.A. Guns, ntd. and the ^oiey Armament co. had oOi.e selling rights of these rifles, subject to their paying whe War Office £M.5.0. per rifle sold, and reserving go of their net profits for application to maintaining and improving machinery for making rifles in this country. Consequently if we sold rifles otherwise than through ioley, we should have to compensate them, and he understood that the contractors would accept 10/- per rifle in such circumstances. o* this basis, a price of &amp;&amp; per rifle would allow - (a) lU.^.G. to the war office. (b) 10/- to doley. (c) b/- for carriage to India. If the rifles were sold to any extent on credit, he thought that an arrangement should be madt; whereby dole/ should only be paid their 10/- on rifles in respect of which we actually received £8. iftbe Afghan Ooveraaent, defaulted in ret*peat of anjr of the rifles, we should, to that extent, lose - (1) rifles not paid for. (il) the 10/- to dole/ (unless t*n arrange*, nt on the above lines was made) (iii) the cost of carriage (5/- per rifle). Any such loss would have to be publlahed as a loss in the Appropriation Account. Alternative!/ we could sell 10,000 rifles to Afghanistan with an indemnity from the Indian Government against an/ loss. 8* iir. collier (Foreign Office) thought publication of the loss would not ettreat much attention, instancing the case of a default by Ibn daub of which not much notice has ben taken. &amp;• #r. jalton (India office) thought the alternative of insisting on a complete indemnity from the Indian Government would almost certainly lead to a breakdown of the arrangement. He thought that there was some tendency to over-sstimate the risk of a default. He thought the present Government of Afghanistan would only default if it disappeared as s Government, and their political prospects appeared to have been improving in the last five years; and thsre was s reasonable prospect of the Government lasting ano her two or three years. He thought the Afghan Government might be willing to pay cash down for the rifles or possibly in two instalments. This would reduce the risk to ^ulte small proportions Hi*. Bridges (Treasu y) pointed out that the argument on smallness of risk applied equally to both the Indian and Imperial Governments, and Mr. collier (Foreign Office) pointed out that the supply of 10,000 rifles from British stocks would relieve Indie of the considerable risk that would arise from depletion of her stocks, if she found the 10,000 rifles. Colonel Isnay (War office) asked whether there was any prospect of obtaining s decision on the question of principle as to r\ how/{^l6o how far the laperial OoTerruicjnt wer^e responsible for the cost of epeoial Aeasoree to aaintein good reletioos with Afghanistan* but melton (India office) thought it would be better not to raise hia major question at present* as an answer could not be given for aome time. 6- &amp;*V AQggricUe (iar Office) did not think that tha arrange*^a with and i&gt;oley could be fairly modified on renewal in such a way ae to exclude the 10*000 rifles for Afghanistan as* up to date* the contraetors had loet through abortive traneeetlone, and were* in fact. In negotiation with Afghanistan through a foreign fim* Mor was it liksly that an arrangement could ba made for aelllng the riflea at tha proposed price through the contractors* as the latter were possibly tied to intemedlariss who would Bake t&gt;uch a course unprofitable* ’• After discussion it was decided that the beat course would be for the India Of flea to send two telegrans - (1) to the British representative at Kabul quoting a price of £4*4*0* per unit of rifle* beyonet and scabbard with 600 rounds of aamvmitlon and asking him to find out frotf tha Afghan Ooverojaent whether they would buy 10*000 rifles et this price (delivered at Karachi) - (a) on the basis of payment in full for all 10*000 or (b) for (say) 6*000 to be delivered and paid for now* and (say) 5*000 to be delivered and paid for in a year 9 a time; or (c) 10*000 to be delivered now, payment to be so much on delivery* and the balance in instalments. (&amp;) .o the Government of India in the same sense* and saying that If Afghanistan chooses the third alternatlva* tha Indian Governmsnt would ba expected to indemnify H*ll* Government against loss on the same condition as that applied to tha first 6*000 rifles* i.e* the liability would follow tha lines of any general settlement reached between the two Governments in the matter of Afghan relations* It was furthar decided that tha negotiation with ^oley of an arrangement whereby the 10/- per rifle (see p&amp;ra.l above) would only be paid to then on rifles for which payment was actually received by the war Office should be left over ui til answers to the above telegrams had been received, on D.P.A.C's as ur&amp;nce that* if found to be necessary* such negotiations would not take more than a weak* WAd omCM. *»*♦* ■ ■ —- -Draft Paper. Department. Forrainka From S. of S. for F.A. to H.M. Minister, Kabul. Peshawar. Please see paragraph 4 of telegram from S. of S. for I.„ no. 21 dated 13th July. Supply of rifles to Afghan Government. 2. War Office have large stocks of unused 1914 pattern rifles which they could supply at price of £3 per rifle complete with bayonet, scabbard, at Karachi, This price is made up as follows: £2.5.0 cost to War Office, 4th September 1934). War Office also have stocks of .303 ammunition made during the War which they could supply at a price of £1.4.0 per 600 rounds delivered at Karachi. oil bottle and pull-through, delivered 5s. carriage, and 10s. compensation to Messrs. Soley who possess the selling rights (see Forminka 70 of 3. (Description of rifles and ammunition).p* 4. From the Afghan point of view, supply of 10,000 of these units (rifle plus 600 rounds of ammunition) at a pried of £4.4.0 per unit plus cost of transport from Karachi to Afghanistan would apoear to be a much more attractive proposition than purchase of current pattern rifles from Indian stocks at a price approximating to cost quoted in paragraph 6(b) of O. of I.'s _ telegram of 29th June, ho* 1586, which works out at nearly £ll psr unit. * Fppm— nri point ■&gt;£—y-tew udiTu1 7 :u.11vt suggested seems to haye^the' advantage of avoiding anyjp^Tof a further depletion of reserves. Price quoted above is for cash on delivery, but } * • even so offer might be attractive to ) » Afghan Government. If they cannot pay cash for 10,000 f wish to purchase, now and * I add for your ^ information/ \ \ . «Draft Paper. - 3 - Department. info mat ion that we understand that Afghan Government is already in negotiation through a French intemediary for purchase of such rifles from Messrs. Soley, and it seens highly probable that purchasing through such a channel they would have to pay a considerably higher,price. ^ 5. You should at once, in whatever manner you deem best, make offer to Afghan Government to bay 10,000 or any smaller number of these rifles on terns mentioned and ascertain whether they are attracted by the proposal^ ^ 7 ,- 6 . lLJi ^ Tice, ^/lU L /Vt yv»^t ^A^ue Ca t oArfc**» of the,y ai imnabl-e ‘to pay cash/for 10,000 at once or for smaller numbers gradually delivered over a period of time^y^te should discreetly ascertain what is the best basis of payment by instalments that they can offer, b ut you should not at this stage commit H.M.G. to accepting payment by instalments as this question is still under consideration (see telegram Klr» r\ q+.oH +.n ft. r*fDepartment. telegral: . Epom S. of S. to G. of Ir •teener* rifles to Afghan Government, instracted to make is accepted by Afghan Government, this will afford by far the least costly means of satisfying our political desideratum, viz. to meet their request for assistance in the interests of their internal security^ From Indian point of view, this alternative seems also to have the advantage of avoiding any risk of a further depletion of India’s war reserves. If Afghan Government, having regard to low price offered, are able t. pay for ooraignmnU a 8 delivered, no difficulty will arise. ^If, however, they press for payment by instalments, it seems probable that, having regard to the disparity in price, they may be able to offer a much more favourable basis of deferred Forminka . Supply of ^ offer which H.M. Minister has been payments than the six-year basis offered/\ offered to the G. of I. Any basis of deferred payment, however, would involve a liability on H.M*G» which^the_v are reluctant to undertake pending a decision on general question of incidence of charges for measures calculated to assist Afghan Government. We trust therefore that in event of deferred payments being proposed and agreed to, G. of I. would be willing, pending a decision on Hi* general question to reimburse H.M.G^any*loss incurred through delivery of rifles in advance of payment and eventual default of payment at due date. You will observe that this contingent liability would be very much smaller than that incurred by sale of 10,000 of the'more expensive rifles from your war reserves on deferred payments spread over six years. ir. / ^ ^ /Go. 'LWtV Jw ^ jpLr ; cn / i-t-r \ O^V V C^tZZt ^ ^Draft Paper. G.W. Lambert, Esq. , War Office, S.W.l. 3761 5000 5.35 F&gt; 2^ LfJ£Z(* / Department. 1 7 JUL1936 Copy is enclosed of the telegram about the rifles for Afghanistan which was sent on 13th July (in the form finally agreed between Wakely and Paterson) and of the Government of India’s reply of 15th July, which is satisfactory so far as it goes and settles the question of the first instalment of 5,000. 2. We understand here that the purpose of the meeting neactJIhursdr&amp;y will be to consider further the idea ^tentatively incorporated in paragraph- 4^ 5 and 6 of ouiL_Qriginal draft telegram that the Afghan requirements to the extent of the second and third instalments of 10,000 rifles in all might be supplied from 1914 stocks in this country. This was suggested as an alternative to the G. of I.’s own proposal to supply this number of latest pattern rifles from their own war reserves at a much greater cost (and consequently at a higher price to the Afghans) but subject to the condition of a contingent. guarantee of replacement by H.M.G. at the latter T s charge in a hypothetical emergency if such replacement were then considered necessary by the Comrrander-in-Chief in India, - a condition which the G. of I. have now partially waived so far as the first instalment of 5,000 is concerned. If it is found possible to proceed with this alternative suggestion in one form or another, the first step would in any case be to sound the Afghan Government upon it. The original draft kept open for further consideration the question of the conditions of sale, i.e. whether * it would be for cash or on the basis of payment by instalments. If after Thursday’s meeting we can put a firm proposition, or alternative propositions, to the Afghan Government as regards conditions of sale, as well as price, it will, of course, be so much the better. It is conceivable that if the price is 9 low enough the Afghans might be able to pay cash; or they might be able to pay in two or three instalments rather than by deferred nayments spread over six years which they have proposed to the G. of I. and which the latter are prepared to accept. Thus if this alternative were adopted the financial liability incurred by H.M.G in respect of the risk of an eventual default/Department. default would be comparatively small, or conceivably there might be no liability. 3. This question of the 10,000 rifles therefore seems to rest on a much narrower basis than the large question which has recently been raised by the G. of I. of the financial liability for measures intended to assist Anglo-Afghan relations. It may perhaps be useful to explain how the latter question has recently cropped up. The G. of I. already pay the whole of the charges for diplomatic and consular representation in Afghanistan and are willing to continue to do so, but they have recently shown a disposition to suggest that the cost of other measures intended to promote the stability of the Afghan Government should be borne, or at any rate shared, by Imperial revenues. They originally, however, made an exception in their telegram of in regard to the supply of a certain number of Indian rifles which they said they were prepared to supply either free of cost or on long term deferred/deferred payments. The demand for a guarantee involving H.M.G. in a t contingent liability, which was stated in the G. of I.’s telegram of 29th June, therefore came as a surprise. 4. The point on which the G* of !• have shown special insistence is that H.M.G. should undertake the entire financial responsibility for any * *■ measures that might be decided on for maintaining the economic stability of Afghanistan. As a matter of fact it is premature to take this particular question up,because, for political reasons^into which I need not enter at the moment^ it is doubtful whether any such measures involving serious financial commitments will be decided upon. Before that question is considered further, it is proposed, if the Afghan Government agree, to send out an expert to examine their financial and economic situation. The Afghan Government may decline this step or they may ask for a League of nations expert. If. however, they should ask H.M.G. to supply an expert, the question may arise of the incidence of the small charge for the expenses of his deputation. 5. There is also the question of an Indo-Afghan civil air service; we have/- 5 - Department. have an option from the Afghan Government to establish such a service if they should enter into a for the establishment of a Russo- Afghan service in northern Afghanistan. In a despatch of 5th June 1933 the contingency arose, there were strong political and strategic reasons for 'the motive for undertaking the operation of such a service is even of greater concern to Imperial than to Indian interests, and we therefore wish to reserve our right to ask for assistance from H.M.G. in financing the service, should this appear to us necessary, if and when the occasion arises'. The occasion is likely to arise in the near future, as the Afghan Government are considering a convention with Russia and have asked us for our views and enquired whether - * we would take up the option of a service in southern and eastern s Afghanistan. We are now awaiting the G. of I.*8 present views on the question of the air service. convention with the Soviet Government G. of I. agreed that, if this exercising our option but they added 6./&gt; 6. It will thus be necessary sooner or later to consider the broad question whether H.M.G. would be willing to make contributions towards expenditure incurred for the sake of Imperial and Indian interests in Afghanistan. Consideration might either be given to this as a general question or to particular aspects of it - such as (a) measures (if any) to maintain the economic stability of Afghanistan and (b) the air service - as these particular items come up. This broad question^or particulax^more important aspects of it ^will probably require a good deal of consideration, and if our Secretary of State decided to take such matters up with the Imperial Departments concerned he might consider that the most convenient procedure would be to set out the Government of India 1 s case, and the various facts and considerations which affect it, in writing in the first instance. The broad question, therefore, is hardly one that could be considered an fond at next-^hursdaj^e meeting* - | 7. I am sending copy of this letter to Ismay, Collier and • J. 0. WALTOK.A Meeting will be held at the War Office, Room 254, on Thursday, the 18th July, at 11.30 a.m. to discuss the question of the supply of Rifles to Afghanistan. 15th July, 1935.P.2. 4758/35. SECRET CYPHER TELEGRaM ADDRESSED BY THE SECRETARY OF STaTE FOR INDIA TO GOVERNMENT OF INDIA REPEATED TO H.M. MINISTER, KABUL, NO. 61. dated isth july 1935 . NO. OF WORDS 159. XXX 2190. Your telegrams 29 June, No.1586 and 11th July, No.1679, and Kabul telegram 7 July, No.71. Supply of Rifles to Afghan Government. 2. H.M.G. consider it politically most desirable to meet Afghan request so far as possible. 3. H.M.G. consider that in accordance with Afghan Government's original request and more especially in view of Kabul telegram No.71, it is most important that 5,000 complete units should be delivered in time for Jashan. In view of time margin this supply at any rate must come from India's stocks and we trust that arrangements to ensure timely delivery will be put in hand at once as suggested in paragraph 5 of Kabul telegram No.71. Price for these 5,000 should then be negotiated (as proposed in paragraph 6(b) of your telegram) between Fraser-Tytler and Afghan Ministers. 4. a further cable will be sent as regards a further 10 , 000 . 5. In the event of an emergency arising in India, H.M.G. undertake to make good a deficiency of 5,000 units but without prejudice to question of payment which must remain prima facie an Indian liability pending a decision on Government of India's general request for assistance in their Afghan relations. jaa frfpiATE r-</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000555.0x0002e5_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/2203</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000555.0x0002e5</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/2203</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 7/36 'Afghanistan: sale of 1914 pattern rifles to the Afghan government; incidence of liability between Indian and Imperial revenues'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1935/1939</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-09-27T22:52:17</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (270 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in rough chronological order from the rear to the front of the file</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence commences at the inside front cover with 1, and terminates at the last folio with 270; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file is a continuation of Collection 7/23, reference IOR/L/PS/12/2191. It contains correspondence between the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, the Secretary of State for India, HM Minister at Kabul, the War Office, the Government of India Foreign and Political Department, and the India Office Political Department, regarding requests for rifles and ammunition received from the Afghan Government.The opening correspondence concerns an Afghan Government request for 10,000 rifles and 6 million rounds of ammunition, and covers the following topics: the possibility of supplying 1914 pattern rifles from War Office surplus stocks, plus .303 Mk VII ammunition; Afghan concerns over the quality of the older rifles; payment options; Afghan overtures to arms manufacturers in Czechoslovakia; the possible provision of aircraft and training; and the need to compensate Messrs Soley Armament Company for any 1914 pattern rifles sold.The bulk of the correspondence concerns arrangements over the division of liability between the British Government and the Government of India for extraordinary expenditure on Afghanistan, and the Afghan Reserve Fund. A memorandum providing details of the Fund can be found at folios 67-71.At the end of the file it is agreed to supply a further 25,000 1914 pattern-rifles, plus ammunition, over six scheduled payments. The Government of India agree to assume liability for out of pocket expenditure (commission to the Soley Armament Company, plus inspection, packing and freight charges) in respect of rifles not wholly paid for at the time of any default on payment.The file includes a divider which gives a list of correspondence references contained in the file by year. This is placed at the end of the correspondence (folio 2).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Ambassador to Afghanistan</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>War Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Secretary of State for India and Burma, United Kingdom</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of India, Foreign and Political Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Afghanistan</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Colonial administration</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000555.0x0002e5#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>