<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100026906787.0x000001_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T21:32:09.940Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100026906787.0x000001_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>Add MS 23494</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100026906787.0x000001</url><physicalLocation>British Library: Oriental Manuscripts</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>Add MS 23494</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>al-Durr al-naqī fī fann al-mūsīqī الدرّ النقيّ في الفنّ الموسيقي  Mawṣilī, Aḥmad ibn ʿAbd al-Raḥman موصلي، أحمد بن عبد الرحمن</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1800/1899</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-11-30T11:15:09</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>Codex; ff. v+1+iii+9+xiii</extent><extent>Material: Western laid paper with watermark bearing initials 'G F B' visible in gutter on most foliosDimensions: 205 x 140 mm leaf [150 x 80 mm written]Foliation: British Museum foliation in pencilRuling:
                           Misṭarah; 21 lines per page; vertical spacing 14 lines per 10 cmScript:
                           NaskhInk: Black ink, with rubricated headings and overlinings in redBinding: Red leather case binding with blind tooled medallion and pendants on both boardsCondition: Minor tears and damage to some outer margins repairedSeals: f. 2r</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Treatise on music theory relating the musical modes, or
                           maqams(مقامات), to the Prophets, signs of the zodiac, hours of the day, etc. by Abū Ṣāliḥ al-Sayyid Aḥmad al-Rifā‘ī ibn ‘Abd al-Raḥmān, given the
                           laqabal-Musallam al-Mawṣlī (أبو صالح السيّد الرفاعي الملقّب بالمسلم الموصلي ابن عبد الرحمن, d. 1737; see f. 3r, lines 6-7). The text is a commentary on a Persian treatise on music theory by ‘Abd al-Mu’min al-Balkhī (عبد المؤمن البلخي; see f. 3r, line 9).Contents:Introduction (المقدمة; ff. 2v-3v);Chapter 1 (الباب الأوّل; f. 4r-4v);Chapter 2 (الباب الثاني; ff. 4v-5v);Chapter 3 (الباب الثالث; ff. 5v- 7v);Conclusion (الخاتمة; ff. 7v-9v).The treatise contains two fold-out diagrams on ff. 6r and 8r.The treatise is followed by an anonymous poem (f. 10r-10v) relating the modes, or
                           maqams(مقامات), to the hours, planets, days of the week, spheres, signs of the zodiac and the temperaments.Begins (f. 2v, lines 3-5):الحمد لله الذي منّ علينا بدين الإسلام وهدانا بنبيه محمد سيّدالأنام وشرّفنا على كثير ممّن خلق بمريد الكرم والأنعام وكلّفنابالعبادة وأقام كلّ فرد منّا بمقام فسبحان من اسمعنا خطابEnds (f. 9v, lines 15-19):... ثمّ ليختم بما ابتدأ ولايتنقل إلى غيرها من المقامات فإنّه الزواحلا من الانتقال منمقام إلى مقام واقهما على هذا الأستاذ الكبير يوسف جاميوإبراهيم نهاوندي وعلي الزوياني ومولانا جسين چاکیريوغيرهم</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="personal"><namePart>Aḥmad ibn ʿAbd al-Raḥman Mawṣilī</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Music theory--Early works to 1800</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100026906787.0x000001#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>