<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0001b9_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-06-01T19:39:36.435Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">6716 A India Office Memo. B 458 Confidential DUBAI OIL CONCESSION and CONNECTED DOCUMENTS No. 1. No. 2. No. 3. No. 4. No. 5. No. 6. No. 7. No. 8. No. 9. No. 10. No. 11. No. 12. Political Agreement of 5th February 1937, between His Majesty’s Government in the United Kingdom and Petroleum Concessions, Ltd. Commercial Agreement (and annexure) of 22nd May 1937, between the Shaikh of Dubai and Petroleum Concessions, Ltd. Letter from Political Agent, Bahrain, to the Shaikh of Dubai, dated 22nd May 1937, No. T. 1. Shaikh’s reply, dated 22nd May 1937. Letter from Political Agent, Bahrain, to the Shaikh of Dubai, dated 22nd May 1937, No. T. 2. Shaikh’s reply, dated 22nd May 1937. Letter from Political Agent, Bahrain, to the Shaikh of Dubai, dated 24th May 1937, No. T. 3. Letter from the Shaikh of Dubai to Political Agent, Bahrain, dated 12th June 1937. Letter from India Office to Petroleum Concessions, Ltd., dated 14th August 1937. Letter from Petroleum Concessions, Ltd., to India Office, dated 17th August 1937. Letter from India Office to Petroleum Concessions, Ltd., dated 26th August 1937. Letter from Political Agent, Bahrain, to the Shaikh of Dubai, dated 6th October 1937.No. 1 Dated 5th February 1937 HIS MAJESTY’S GOVERNMENT IN THE UNITED KINGDOM AND PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LIMITED Agreement relating to the Debai Oil Concession THIS AGREEMENT dated the Fifth day of February One Thousand nine hundred and thirty-seven is made BETWEEN His Majesty’s Government in the United Kingdom (hereinafter called “His Majesty’s Government”) of the one part and Petroleum Concessions Limited (hereinafter called “ the Company ” which expression shall where the context so admits be deemed to include its successors and/or assignees and shall also be deemed to include any subsidiary Company) of the other part. \\ HERE AS Petroleum Development (Trucial Coast) Ltd. is a subsidiary Company of Petroleum Concessions Limited. AND WHEREAS in the event of the Company obtaining a concession from the Sheikh of Debai (hereinafter called “ the Sheikh ”) certain responsibilities will devolve on His Majesty’s Government, the Company has agreed with His Majesty’s Government as follows : — L Petroleum Concessions Limited and any subsidiary company shall be and remain a British company registered in Great Britain and having its principal place of business in Great Britain, and its Chairman shall at all times be a British subject. 2. The Agreement between the Company and the Sheikh shall not be transferred to any other company without the prior consent in writing of His Majesty’s Govern ment and any other company to which that Agreement may be transferred shall be and remain a British company registered in Great Britain and having its principal place of business in Great Britain, and its Chairman shall at all times be a British subject. 3. The employees of the Company in Debai shall at all times be British subjects or subjects of the Sheikh, provided that, with the consent of His Majesty’s Govern ment, such persons of other nationality as are required for the efficient carrying on of the undertaking may be employed. Notwithstanding anything contained in the Agreement between the Company and the Sheikh, the importation of foreign native labour shall be subject to the approval of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. 4. The Company in all except unimportant or routine matters shall deal with the Debai authorities through a Chief Local Representative in the Persian Gulf, who shall be a British subject. The approval of His Majesty’s Government shall be required for the person so designated. He will be ordinarily resident in Debai or Bahrein and will be responsible for the Company’s local relations with the Debai authorities, which shall, except in routine or unimportant matters, be conducted through the political representative of His Majesty’s Government in Bahrein or through any other person whom the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf may from time to time designate. 5. Subject to the terms of the Agreement between the Company and the Sheikh the Company undertakes at ail times to pay due deference to the wishes of the Sheikh and to the advice of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf and of the Political Officers subordinate to him. 6. Any right given to the Company under its Agreement with the Sheikh to utilise means of transportation by air shall be subject to any general regulations for civil aircraft made by the Sheikh on the advice of His Majesty’s Government, and to any instructions which may be issued by the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.■■ 4 7. Notwithstanding anything contained in the Agreement between the Company and the Sheikh the Company shall not have the right to use or occupy, and shall not include in the areas to be acquired or utilised for the purposes of its operations, any sites which may have been selected by or on behalf of the Sheikh or His Majesty’s Government for defence purposes, for aerodromes, aeroplane or seaplane bases or for wireless and telegraph installations or in connection with the develop- f ment of harbours, provided that with the consent of His Majesty’s Government which shall not be unreasonably withheld the Company shall have the right to use for the purposes of its operations such harbours as may be developed by the Sheikh or His Majesty’s Government if there is not reasonable harbour accommodation available elsewhere. Subject to the terms of the Agreement between the Company and the Sheikh harbours developed by the Company shall be under its complete and exclusive control. 8. Telegraph, wireless and telephone installations, if any, maintained by the Company shall be for use only in its business and as provided in the concession, and shall be so constructed and operated that their operations shall not interfere with the operations of such wireless, telegraph or telephone installations as may be established by the Sheikh or His Majesty’s Government, or their agent. 9. In the event of a state of national emergency or war (of the existence of either of which His Majesty’s Government shall be the sole judge) His Majesty’s Government shall have the right of pre-emption of all the oil produced in Debai in accordance with the terms of the Schedule hereto. 10. The Company shall obtain the prior permission of the Sheikh before working in any particular area, in order that the Sheikh may be in a position to fulfil his responsibilities for the protection of the Company. The Sheikh shall not unreasonably withhold such permission, and in any case in which the Company feels that, the free movement of its personnel within the concession area is being unnecessarily restricted the matter shall be referred for decision to the Political Resident. 11. In the event of notice of termination of the Agreement between the Company and the Sheikh being given on the ground that the Company has failed to observe any of the terms of the present Agreement between the Company and His Majesty’s Government, the arbitration provisions of the said Agreement between the Company and the Sheikh shall apply if the Company considers that notice of termination on such grounds is not justified, and in that event the Sheikh shall not cancel the said Agreement until arbitration takes place in accordance with the said provisions and unless the Company fails to comply with the award of the arbitrators within the reasonable time which shall be fixed by the arbitrators for so doing. IN WITNESS whereof John Charles Walton, C.B., on behalf of His Majesty’s Government has hereunto set his hand and seal and the Company has hereunto caused its Common Seal to be affixed the day and year first above written. THE SCHEDULE above referred to. Pre-emption Clause. In the event of a state of national emergency or war (of the existence of which His Majesty’s Government shall be the sole judge)— (1) His Majesty’s Government shall have the right of pre-emption of all crude oil gotten under the concession granted by the Sheikh to the Company and of all the products thereof and shall have the right to require the Company to the extent of any refining capacity it may have in Debai to produce oil fuel that shall comply with the Admiralty specifications at the time provided that Debai oil be of a suitable kind and quality for this purpose. (2) The Company shall use its utmost endeavours to increase so far as reasonably possible with existing facilities the supply of oil and/or products thereof for the Government to the extent required by the Government. (3) The Company shall with every reasonable expedition and so as to avoid demurrage on the vessel or vessels engaged to convey the same, do its utmost to deliver all oil or products of oil purchased by the Government under their5 &lt;2) (?) 6716 A 2 said right of pre-emption in the quantities at the time and in the manner required by the Government at a convenient place of shipment or at a place of storage in Debai to be determined by His Majesty’s Government. In the event of a vessel employed to carry any such oil or products thereof on behalf of His Majesty being detained on demurrage at the port of loading the Company shall pay the amount due for demurrage according to the terms of the charter party and/or the rates of loading previously agreed with the Company unless the delay is due to causes beyond the control of the Company. Any dispute which may arise as to whether the delay is due to causes beyond the control of the Company shall be settled by agreement between His Majesty’s Government and the Company, and, in default of such agreement, the question shall be referred to two arbitrators, one to be chosen by His Majesty’s Government (or the Political Resident) and the other by the Company, with power to appoint an umpire in case of disagreement, such arbitration to be held in England and to be deemed a reference to arbitration under the provisions of the Arbitration Acts 1889 to 1934 (52 and 53 Viet. c. 49 ; 24 and 25 Geo. V. c. 14) of the Imperial Parliament, or any statutory modification or re-enactment thereof for the time being in force. (4) The price to be paid for all oil or products of the refining or treatment of oil taken in pre-emption by His Majesty’s Government shall be either (a) as specified in a separate agreement or (6) if no such agreement shall have been entered into, a fair price for the time being at the point of delivery as the same shall be settled by agreement between His Majesty’s Government and the Company, or in default of such agreement by arbitration in the manner provided by the last preceding sub-clause. To assist in arriving at a fair price at the point of delivery the Company shall furnish for the confidential information of His Majesty’s Government, if so required, particulars of the quantities, descriptions and prices of Debai oil or products sold to other customers and of charters or contracts entered into for carriage and shall exhibit to His Majesty’s Government original or authenticated copies of contracts or charter parties entered into for the sale and/or carriage of such oil or products. (5) His Majesty’s Government shall be at liberty to take control of the works, plant and premises of the Company in Debai, and in such event the Company shall conform to and obey all directions issued by or on behalf of His Majesty’s Government. Compensation shall be paid to the Company for any loss or damage that may be proved to have been sustained by the Company by reason of the exercise by His Majesty’s Government of the powers conferred by this sub-clause. Any such compensation shall be settled by agreement between His Majesty’s Government and the Company or, in default of agreement, by arbitration in the manner provided by sub-clause (3). Signed Sealed and Delivered by the said John Charles Walton on behalf of His Majesty’s Government in the presence of— H. S. PAINTER, India Office. (seal) JOHN CADMAN, Director. E. J. BROWN, Secretary.t \ 6 No. 2 PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LIMITED. Agreement made with the Shaikh of Dubai, on the 22nd May 1937, with Annexure. In the Name of God the Merciful. This is an Agreement made at Dubai, Arabia, on the Twenty-second day of May 1937, corresponding to the Eleventh day of Rabi-Awwal 1356 between His Excellency Shaikh Said Bin Maktum Al-Hasher in the exercise of his powers as Ruler of Dubai, Arabia, on his own behalf and on behalf of and in the name of his heirs and successors in whom is or shall be vested for the time being the responsibility for the control and government of the State of Dubai (hereinafter called “ the Shaikh ”) of the one part and Petroleum Concessions Limited, a Company registered in Great Britain under the Companies Act, 1929, its successors and assigns (hereinafter called “ the Company ”) of the second part. Article 1.—(a) The area to which this Agreement applies is the State of Dubai including all islands and territorial waters appertaining thereto (hereinafter referred to as “the State”) being all that territory included in the Shaikhdom of Dubai. The Shaikh agrees that when the territorial limits of the State of Dubai have been determined the area covered by the Concession will be coterminous with the limits so determined. (b) But the Company shall refrain from working or entering for the present into the area upon which the town named Hatta Al Jabaliyah is located until the Shaikh grants the Company permission to do so. (c) The area in the Dubai Khor surveyed by Imperial Airways Limited and all concerned with that area is entirely excluded for the purposes of this Agreement. Article 2. The period of this Agreement shall be 75 calendar years from the date of signature. The expression year, month and day used in this Agreement shall mean what is consistent with the English solar calendar and not an} 7 other. Further, the weights mentioned in this Agreement shall be reckoned on the English ton of 2,240 lbs. Article 3. The Shaikh hereby grants to the Company the exclusive right to explore search for drill for produce and win natural gas asphalt ozokerite crude petroleum and their products and cognate substances (hereinafter referred to as “ the substances”) within the State, the exclusive ownership of all the substances so produced and won, the right to refine transport sell for use within and without the State or for export and to export or otherwise deal with or dispose of the substances, and the right to import export pump ship or otherwise transport the substances across or to any country or place at the Company’s discretion and the right to do all things necessary for the purpose of these operations. Article 4. If hereafter any neutral zone is created adjacent to the territory of the State, wherein the Shaikh shall have a co-equal and joint interest, the Shaikh hereby agrees to grant to the Company an oil concession over such neutral zone on terms to be agreed between the Shaikh, the Company and the joint ruler of such neutral zone. Article 5. In consideration of the rights granted by the Shaikh by this Agreement the Company shall pay to the Shaikh— (a) on signature of the agreement Rupees 60,000 (Sixty thousand). (b) Rupees 200,000 (Two hundred thousand) within a period of sixty (60) days from the date upon which the Company declares in writing to the Shaikh that substances have been discovered in commercial quantities. If the Company should fail to declare so sooner, then the date of discovery of substances in commercial quantities shall be that date upon which the Company has completed and tested a well or wells capable of producing in accordance with first-class oil practice not less than Two thousand (2,000) English tons of clean substances per day for a period of Thirty (30) consecutive days.7 (c) Rupees 30,000 (Thirty thousand) at the end of each year from the date of signature hereof until the Company declares in writing to the Shaikh that substances have been discovered in commercial quantities in accordance with the sub-clause (b) of this Article 5, or until the Company commences production from quantities less than commercial quantities. In the event of such production by the Company from quantities less than commercial quantities either Rupees 50,000 (Fifty thousand) per year or Rupees 3 (Three) per English ton of 2,240 lbs. in respect of the substances so won and saved shall be payable, whichever is the greater. (d) At the end of every year from the date upon which the Company makes in writing to the Shaikh the declaration that the substances have been discovered in commercial quantities Rupees 90,000 (Ninety thousand) or Rupees 3 (Three) per English ton of 2,240 lbs. in respect of the substances other than natural gas, won and saved during the preceding calendar year, whichever is the greater. (e) Annas 2 (Two) per 1,000 cubic feet of natural gas produced and sold. In calculating royalty for the purpose of this article account shall not be taken of any of the substances used by the Company in its operations or used by the Company’s employees within the State, necessary for their use, nor of any water or foreign matter which may be produced with the substances. Article 6. The Company shall not carry on any operations within areas occupied by or devoted to the purposes of mosques, sacred buildings or graveyards. Article 7. The Company shall conduct its operations in a workmanlike manner and by appropriate scientific methods and shall take all reasonable measures to prevent the ingress of water to any petroleum-bearing strata and shall duly close any unproductive holes drilled by it and subsequently abandoned. The Company shall keep the Shaikh informed generally as to the progress and result of its drilling operations but such information shall be treated as confidential. Article 8. Within three months after the expiry of each calendar year, the Company shall deliver to the Shaikh a statement of the amount of the substances won and saved and in the case of natural gas produced and sold during the said calendar year, and of the royalty which is or might have been payable under Article 5, together with a report of its operations during the said year. The Shaikh or his representative shall have the right to check such returns and statements, and all such returns and statements and the reports of the Company’s operations shall be treated as confidential by the Shaikh. Article 9.— (a) The Company shall have the right to import water, the substances, fuel, machinery, motor-cars and lorries, aircraft, equipment, plant, timber, utensils, iron work, building materials, food supplies, medicines, medical supplies, office equipment and household furniture, and other materials, equipment and goods of whatsoever nature required by the Company and its employees for the purpose of its operations hereunder and to export the substauces and articles previously imported by the Company free of customs or export duty and taxes or other charges, but it shall pay on all personal goods, clothing and general merchandise imported by the Company for the personal use of its employees or for resale to them the ordinary duty in force for the time being in the State. Saving as in Article 5 and in this Article provided, the Company, its personnel, its operations, income, profits and property including the substances shall be exempt and free during the period of this Agreement from all present or future harbour duties, import duties, export duties, taxes, imposts and charges of any kind whether State or local, tolls and land surface rent of whatever nature. In consideration of the right herein granted the Company shall pay—in addition to the royalty per ton of Rupees Three (3) as provided in Article 5—to the Shaikh within Three (3) months after the close of each calendar year the sum of Four (4) annas per English ton of 2,240 lbs. in respect of the substances won and saved during the said calendar year. (6) The importation by the Company of firearms and other weapons is prohibited, except with the written permission of the Shaikh. (c) The Company may import such alcoholic drinks and liquors as the Company may require for the use of their foreign employees but only with the written permission of the Shaikh, and the Political Agent, Bahrain, or any authority deputedby them, but the Company shall not sell or give alcoholic drinks or liquors to the subjects of the Shaikh or to the subjects of adjoining Rulers who may be employed within the State. Article 10. The employees of the Company shall be allowed to enter into and to leave the State at all times without let or hindrance and free of all charge, and the Shaikh shall grant to the Company’s employees every facility required for the purpose of the Company’s operations hereunder. But the Company’s employees shall not interfere or by their actions cause any disturbance or cause opposition to the Shaikh’s authority within the State of Dubai and the employees shall not go beyond the limit of their duties when employed within or when leaving the confines of the State of Dubai for the purpose of this Agreement. Further in the event of any of the Company’s employees—whether he be a senior or a junior employee—committing an offence which may cause disorder or interfere with the moral or religious laws or interfere with the politics or subjects of the State of Dubai or excite them to sedition, then the Shaikh may apply to the Political Agent, Bahrain, to send the person concerned—if a foreigner—out of the State of Dubai, but if a subject of the Shaikh then the Shaikh may arrest the culprit and deal with him according to the laws of the State of Dubai. Article 11.—(a) For the purpose of its operations hereunder the Company shall have the right without hindrance to construct, maintain and operate power stations, refineries, pipelines and storage tanks, facilities for water supply including boring for water, telegraph and telephone lines and installations and wireless installations, roads, railways, tramways, buildings, ports, harbours, harbour works, aircraft, buildings and landing places for aircraft, wharves and jetties, oil and coaling stations, with such lighting as may be requisite and any other facilities or works which the Company may consider necessary and for such purposes to use free of all payments any stone, sand, gravel, gypsum, lime, clay or similar materials or water which may be available provided always that the inhabitants of the State are not prevented from taking their usual requirements of these materials and that the water supply of the local inhabitants and nomad population who may be dependent on the same is not endangered. The Company at its discretion may select the position of any such works. The Company may likewise instal and operate without hindrance all such means of transportation by land, air and water as may be necessary for the effective conduct of its operations hereunder provided it is for the purposes of this Agreement. (6) The Company shall under normal conditions accept and transmit free of charge on its wireless and telegraph installations such of the Shaikh’s messages as will not interfere with the Company’s business, and in times of national emergency the Shaikh shall have the necessary use free of charge of the Company’s wireless and telegraph installations and railways for governmental purposes. (c) The Shaikh’s ships shall have the right to use harbours utilised or constructed by the Company provided that such use in no way hampers the Company or interferes in any way with the safety of its operations of which the Company shall be the sole judge. Any wharves or appurtenances constructed by the Company shall be for its exclusive use. The Company may use for the purpose of its operations the harbours along the coast of the State, but the Company shall not impede or interfere with the subjects of the Shaikh or their right to continue the use of existing harbours, anchorages, wharves and docks along the coast of the State at present utilised by them for their sailing craft and fishing- boats. Article 12. The Company shall have the right and be given the necessarv facilities— (u) for the. import of the substances into the State from any adjoining territoiy bj pipedmes or otherwise for the purpose of operating anv refinery which the Company may decide to erect within the State ; and (6) lor the transport of the substances by pipe-lines or otherwise over and across the State from and to any adjoining territory to any point suitable for the refining or shipping of the substances. And no duties, taxes, charges or dues of any nature whatsoever shall be levied in respect of such import or transportArticle 13,—(a) 1 he Company shall have free of cost the unrestricted use and occupation of and surface rights over all uncultivated lands of the State which the Company may need for the purpose of its operations and in particular t e Company shall have the right to select an area or areas of land chosen by the Company with exclusive surface rights upon which to erect drilling rigs, pump- stations, 01 refinei ics, storage, terminal shipping and aircraft facilities and any other works required for the Company s operations; and the Company may lease for such pui poses any lands, houses or buildings with the consent of and on conditions to be arranged with the proprietors thereof, but the terms of such lease shall not be in excess of those ordinarily current in their respective localities. (6) The Company shall acquire only such lands, houses and buildings as are necessaiy for its operations under this Agreement. The Company shall inform the Shaikh from time to time of the land, houses and buildings which it requires to occupy for its operations, and land, houses and buildings previously acquired by the Company from tfie Shaikh but found no longer necessary for its operations shall be returned by the Company to the Shaikh free of cost. Article 14. (a) Ihe Company shall have the right to purchase at current market rates fuel, water, food, building and constructional materials and other supplies of every kind in connection with its operations hereunder; further the Shaikh grants to the Company the right to construct new roads for motor and general traffic, and to make use of all existing roads or tracks free of charge or taxes of any kind whatever. (6) The Company shall employ subjects of the Shaikh as far as possible for all work for which they are suited under the supervision of the Company’s skilled employees, but if the local supply of labour should in the judgment of the Company be inadequate or unsuitable the Company shall have the right to import labour, preference being given to labourers from neighbouring Arab countries who will obey the local laws. The Company shall also have the right to import skilled and technical employees. The Company shall pay to the workmen it employs a fail- wage, such wage to be decided and stated by the Company at the time the workmen are engaged. Further, the fact of the Company employing subjects of the Shaikh shall not in any way whatever alter the status of such employees in respect of their rights, privileges and duties as subjects of the Shaikh, and such employees will remain in all ways subject to the jurisdiction of the laws and under the legal authority of the Shaikh in his capacity as the Ruler of the State of Dubai. Article 15. The Shaikh shall give to the Company and its employees and property all protection in his power from theft, highway robbery, assault, wilful damage and destruction, and the Company may appoint in consultation with the Shaikh and itself pay trustworthy guards who shall at all times be subjects of the Shaikh unless the Shaikh permits otherwise to assist in protecting the property of the Company and its employees. The Company shall erect at its own expense suitable buildings for ihe accommodation of such guards at such places as the Company shall decide. Article 16. In measuring the substances for the purposes of royalty the factor for conversion of the volume of oil into weight shall be such figure as may lie determined and agreed upon between the Shaikh and the Company after the discovery of oil and the ascertainment of its specific gravity. The Company shall measure the substances by a method customarily used in good technical practice and the Shaikh by his representative duly authorised by him shall have the right to observe such measuring and to examine and test what ever appliances may be used for such measuring. Such representative shall complv with all necessary and usual safeguards for the prevention of fire and other accident; and shall make all examinations and tests at such times and in such manner as will cause the minimum of interference with the Company’s operations. If upon such examination or testing any such appliance shall be found to be out of order the Company will cause the same to be put in order at its own expense within a reasonable time, and if upon any such examination aforesaid any error shall be discovered in any such appliance, such error shall if the Shaikh so decides after hearing the Company’s explanation be considered to have existed for three (3) calendar months previous to the discovery thereof or from the last occasion of examining the same in case such occasion shall be within such period of three10 * calendar months and the royalty shall be adjusted accordingly. If the Company should find it necessary to alter, repair or replace any measuring appliances it shall give reasonable notice to the Shaikh or his representative to enable a representative of the Shaikh to be present during such alteration, repair or replacement. The Company shall keep full and correct records of all measurements as aforesaid and the said representative of the Shaikh shall have access at all reasonable W times to such records and shall be at liberty to make extracts from them. Such records shall be treated as confidential by the Shaikh and his representative. Article 17 —(a) The Company shall have the right at any time after the expiry of three years from the date of signature of this Agreement to give the Shaikh six months’ notice in writing of its intention to terminate this Agreement and this Agreement shall absolutely determine on the date fixed for such termination in such notice. (6) If such notice be given not later than 30 years after the date of such signature the Company shall be entitled on such determination to remove free of all taxes and duties all plant buildings stores material and property of every sort provided that for a period of three months from the receipt of such notice the Shaikh may purchase—should he so desire—the same at a price equal to the replacement value at that date less depreciation which price shall be agreed or failing agreement settled under Article 24 hereof. (c) If such notice be given later than 30 years after the date of such signature all the property aforesaid shall become the property of the Shaikh free of all cost. Article 18. On the expiry of tins Agreement at the end of the period of 75 years provided in Article 2 or any extension or renewal of that period all the movable and immovable property of the Company in the State shall be handed over to the Shaikh free of cost. Producing wells or borings at the time of such expiry shall be handed over in reasonably good order and repair. Article 19. Subject to the provisions of Article 22 hereof the Shaikh shall have the right to terminate this Agreement and to take without payment all the property of the Company in the State if— (а) the Company shall fail to make any of the payments prescribed in this Agreement within six months of the date on which they fall due ; or (б) the Company shall be in default in respect of an arbitration award under Article 24 hereof. Article 20. Nothing in this Agreement shall be read as restricting in any way the right of the Shaikh to grant to other parties concessions or permits for materials other than the substances as defined in Article 3 provided that the operations and rights of the Company hereunder are not thereby injuriously affected. If the Shaikh should at any date subsequent to the date of signature of this Agreement grant to any other parties concessions or permits as aforesaid the Shaikh undertakes that such concessions shall contain provisions requiring the holders thereof to abstain from damaging, impeding or interfering with the property, operations and interests of the Company. Deposits of minerals such as gold, silver, copper, lead, potash, sulphur and salt or the like which may be discovered by the Company shall be reported to the Shaikh and shall not be worked by the Company except under special concession or permit from the Shaikh. Further, the Company shall instruct Geologists to mark carefully and report to the Company any area and its location which appears to them to give promise of yielding minerals or fresh water from a bore-hole and the Company undertakes to keep the Shaikh informed of all such minerals and water reports and the sites of the area or areas. Article 21. The Shaikh hereby agrees that the Company may transfer the obligations and benefits of this Agreement to a British Company to be called “ Petroleum Development (Trucial Coast) Limited ” or to any other Company registered within the British Empire. Article 22. kailure on the part of the Company to fulfil any of the conditions of this Agreement shall not give the Shaikh any claim against the Company or be deemed a breach of this Agreement in so far as such failure arises from force majeure, and if through force majeure the fulfilment by the Companv of any of the conditions of this Agreement be delayed, the period of such delay shall be added to the periods fixed by this Agreement. &lt;4 V V *h orce majeure as used in this Agreement includes the Act of God, war, insurrection, riot, civil commotion, tide, storm, tidal wave, Hood, lightning, explosion, fire, earthquakes and any other happening which the Company could not reasonably prevent or control. Article l'\. 1 he Shaikh shall not by general or special legislation or by administrative measures or by any other act whatever annul this Agreement except as provided in Article 19. No alteration shall be made in the terms of this Agreement by either the Shaikh or the Company except in the event of the Shaikh and the Company jointly agreeing that it is desirable in the interests of both parties to make certain alterations, deletions or additions to this Agreement. Article 24.—(a) If at any time during the currency of this Agreement any difference or dispute shall arise between the parties hereto concerning the inter pretation or execution hereof, or anything herein contained, or in connection herewith, or the rights or liabilities of either party hereunder, the same shall, failing any agreement to settle it in any other way, be referred to two arbitrators, one of whom shall be chosen by each party, and a referee, who shall be chosen by the arbitrators before proceeding to arbitration. ib) Each party shall nominate its own arbitrator within 60 days after delivery of a request so to do by the other party, failing which its arbitrator may at the request of the other party be designated by the British Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. In the event of the arbitrators failing to agree within 60 days after being chosen or designated the British Political Resident in the Persian Gulf may appoint a referee at the request of the arbitrators or of either of them. (c) The decision of the arbitrators, or in a case of a difference of opinion between them, the decision of the referee, shall be final and binding upon both parties. (d) In giving a decision the arbitrators or the referee shall specify an adequate period of delay, during which the party against whom the decision is given shall conform to the decision, and that party shall be in default only if that party has failed to conform to the decision prior to the expiry of that period and not otherwise. (e) The place of arbitration shall be such as may be agreed by the parties and in default of agreement shall be London. Article 25. The Company shall make all payments that become due to the Shaikh under this Agreement into the Shaikh’s account at the Eastern Bank, Ltd., Bahrain, and the Bank’s receipt shall be a full discharge for the Company in respect to the payment of the sum stated in the Bank’s receipt. Should the Shaikh decide to grant permission for a Bank to open a branch or Agency in Dubai the Shaikh shall consult with the Company as to which Bank shall be given the permission. The Shaikh may from time to time designate in writing another Bank or Banks for the purpose of this Article. Article 26. The Shaikh may select in consultation with the Local Representa tive of the Company, a local man—conversant with the English language—to act as a confidential person as between the Shaikh and the Company’s Representative and to assist in procuring the labour that the Company may require. The salary of the Shaikh’s confidential person so appointed shall be paid by the Company through the Shaikh in Dubai and shall be at the rate of Rupees Four hundred (400) per month. Article 27. This Agreement is written in English and translated into Arabic. If there should at any time be disagreement as to the meaning or interpretation of any clause in this Agreement the English text shall prevail. In Witness whereof the parties to this Agreement have set their hands the day and year first above written. And God is Gracious. The Company, The Shaikh, FRANK HOLMES. SAID BIN MAKTUM AL-HASHER. (Signed in Arabic.) In the presence of T. HICKINBOTHAM, Political Agent, Bahrain. 22nd May 1937.Annexure. To His Excellency, Shaikh Said Bin Maktum Al-Hashar, Ruler of Dubai. Your Excellency, Dubai, 22nd May 1937. Greetings : I am authorised by my Company to inform Your Excellency that should Your Excellency see fit to appoint a London Representative after discovery of oil in commercial quantities such Representative will have access to the management of the Company at any reasonable time for the purposes of making representations which Your Excellency may wish him to make regarding the working of the Concession Agreement that Your Excellency graciously granted to this Company on 22nd May 1937 corresponding to 11th Rabi-Awwal 1356. The Company s officials will be pleased to supply all information to such Representative pertaining to oil production and the Company s operations generally in Dubai at any reasonable time. With expressions of deep respect and regard for the person of \our Excellency. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your Excellency’s obedient Servant, FRANK HOLMES, For and on behalf of Petroleum Concessions, Limited. No. 3 C!opy of letter from Captain Hickinbotham, Political Agent, Bahrain, dated the 22nd May 1937, No. T/l of 1937, to Shaikh Sa’id Bin Maktum, O.B.E., Ruler of Dubai. After compliments, His Majesty’s Government have been furnished with a copy of the Agreement [No. 2] signed by you on the 22nd May 1937 granting to Petroleum Development (Trucial Coast), Limited, which is a subsidiary Company of Petroleum Concessions Limited, an oil concession in respect of your territory on the understanding that the Agreement is subject to the approval of His Majesty’s Government. 2. Under instructions from His Majesty’s Government I now enclose a copy of an Agreement (No. 1) which has been concluded between His Majesty’s Government and Petroleum Concessions, Limited, in London on 5th February 1937. 3. It is desirable that there should be a clear understanding as to the position which would arise in certain eventualities in connection with these two Agreements, and I am to inform you that in these circumstances the understanding described below has been reached with the Company:— (a) Should any of the terms of the Agreement between you and the Company be inconsistent or in conflict with the terms of the Agreement between the Company and His Majesty’s Government signed in London on 5th February 1937 the Agreement between you and the Company will to the extent of any such inconsistency or conflict be subordinate to and be controlled by the terms of the Agreement between the Company and His Majesty’s Government. (b) If the Company should fail to observe any of the terms of the Agreement between the Company and His Majesty’s Government signed in London on 5th February 1937, or if the alleged failure having been disputed by the Company the matter has been referred to arbitration under Article 24 of the Company’s Agreement with you (which is made applicable to the case by Article 11 of the Agreement between the Company and His Majesty’s Government) and the Company should not remedy such failure within the reasonable time which should be fixed by the arbitrators for so doing then in these cases, as in the cases mentioned in Article 19 of the Company’s Agreement with you, but in no other, the Company agrees that you will be entitled to terminate the Agreement between the Company and yourself, andthat all properties of the Company within your territory shall become your property, and that they will hand over to you free of cost land granted to the ompany by you and any lands or buildings which the Company may have bought and any houses or buddings constructed by the Company and all other 11 removable property of the Company within your territory, including the pi oducing wells and borings which shall be handed over in reasonably good order and repair. &amp; . Please let me have a reply to this letter to the effect that you understand the nature or the arrangements as set out above and that you are prepared to agree to t lem. On receipt at your reply His Majesty’s Government will obtain from the Company formal confirmation of their acceptance of the arrangements in question and will communicate such confirmation to you. Usual ending, (Sd.) T. HICKINBOTHAM, Captain, Political Agent, Bahrain. No. 4 Translation of letter dated the 22nd May 1937, equivalent to the ll£/&lt; l{ahi al Auwal 1356, from Shaikh Said bin Maktum, O.B.E., Ruler of Dubai, to Captain T. Hickinbotham, Political Agent, Bahrain. After compliments, In reply to youi letter No. 1/1, dated the 22nd May 193 f [No. 3], equivalent to the Llth Rabi al Auwal 1356, I beg to inform you that I have taken notice of the conditions set out in your above-mentioned letter and that I agree to them. / Usual ending. No. 5 Copy of letter from Captain T. Hickinbotham, Political Agent, Bahrain, dated the 22nd May 1937, No. 1/2 of 19of, to shaikh Said bin Maktum, O.B.E., Ruler of Dubai. After compliments, With reference to the Agreement signed by you on the 22nd May 1937 [No. 2] granting the Petroleum Development (Trucial Coast), Limited, an oil concession in respect of your territory, I have been directed by His Majesty’s Government to inform you that they are prepared to accord their approval to the concession provided you accept the following condition, namely, that should you wish to grant permission to a Bank to open a branch or agency in Dubai, as mentioned in Article 25 of the Concession, you will obtain His Majesty’s Govern ment’s approval before entering into any negotiations with the Bank. *' On receipt of your reply accepting the above condition, the formal approval of His Majesty’s Government to the Concession will be communicated to you and to the Company. Usual ending, (Sd.) T. HICKINBOTHAM, Captain, Political Agent, Bahrain No. 6 Translation of letter dated the 22nd May 1937, equivalent to the Wth Rabi' al Auwal 1356, from Shaikh Sa'id bin Maktum, O.B.E., Ruler of Dubai, to Capt. T. Hickinbotham, Political Agent, Bahrain. After compliments, In reply to your letter No. T/2, dated the 22nd May 1937 [No. 5], equivalent to the llth Rabi’ al Auwal 1356, I beg to inform you that should 1 wish to grant permission to a Bank to open a branch or agency in Dubai, I will obtain His Majesty’s Government’s approval before entering into any negotiations with the Bank. Usual ending.14 * No. 7 Copy of letter from Copt. T. HickiribothcLm, Political Agent, Bahrain, dated 21th May 1937, Mo. T/3 of 1937, to Shaikh Said bin Muktam, O.B.E., Ruler of Dubai. After compliments, With reference to your letter dated the 22nd May 1937 [No. 4], equivalent to- the 11th Rabi’ al Auwal 1356, accepting the conditions set forth in my letter No. T/l, dated the 22nd May 1937 [No. 3], equivalent to the 11th Rabi’ al Auwal 1356, 1 am directed by His Majesty’s Government to convey to you their approval of the Agreement concluded by you on the 22nd May 1937 [No. 2] with Petroleum Development (Trucial Coast), Limited. Usual ending, (Sd.) T. HICKIN BOTHAM, Captain, Political Agent, Bahrain. No. 8 Translation of a letter, dated the 12th June 1937, equivalent to the 2nd Rabi ath Thani 1356, from Shaikh Said bin Muktam, O.B.E., Ruler of Dubai, to Capt. T. Hickinbotham, Political Agent, Bahrein. After compliments, 1 write to inform you that I undertake that I will be guided by the advice of His Majesty’s Government in regard to my exercising the right of termination of the concession which is referred to in paragraph 3 (6) of your letter No. T/l, dated the 22nd May 1937 [No. 3], equivalent to the 11th Rabi’ al Auwal 1356. Usual ending. No. 9 Copy of letter from India Office to Petroleum Concessions, Limited, dated lAth August 1937, No. P.Z. 4377/37. Sir, 1 am directed by the Secretary of State for India to enclose herewith for the information of Petroleum Concessions, limited, a copy of a letter, No. T/l, dated the 22nd May 1937, from the Political Agent, Bahrein, to the Sheikh of Debai [No. 3], together with a translation of the latter’s reply dated 22nd May 1937 [No. 4], in regard to certain points which arise in connection with the oil concession granted (subject to the approval of His Majesty’s Government) to your Company by the Sheikh of Debai on 22nd May 1937 [So. 2], and in connection with the Political Agreement of the 5th February 1937 [No. 1], between your Company and His Majesty’s Government, regarding the said concession. 2. I am to request that in accordance with the unofficial understanding already reached with the Company, Petroleum Concessions, Limited, will now be good enough formally to confirm their acceptance of the arrangements embodied in the PoJitieal Agent’s letter No. T/l, dated the 22nd May 1937 [No. 3], as binding on the Company. I am to add that on receipt of a letter from the Company accepting the arrangements mentioned above, the Marquess of Zetland will cause a further letter to be addressed to the Company expressing His Majesty’s Government’s formal approval of the oil concession granted to the Company by the Sheikh of Debai. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, (Sd.) M. J. CLAUSON.6716 Wt 29299/P 210 120 11.37 Copy of letter from Petroleum Concessions, Limited, to India OJfice, dated. 17th August 1937, No. 433. Sir, We have the honour to acknowledge receipt of your letter of the 14th August 1937, under No. P.Z. 4377/37 [No. 9j, relative to a concession recently obtained by this Company for the territory of Dubai. 2. We beg formally to confirm our acceptance, as binding on the Company, of the arrangements embodied in the letter of 22nd May 1937, under No. T/l, from the Political Agent, Bahrain, to the Ruler of Dubai [No. 3]. 3. We shall be glad to receive notice of His Majesty’s Government s formal approval of the concession granted to us by the Shaikh of Dubai on 22nd May 1937 [No. 2]. We have the honour to be, Sir, Your obedient Servants, for Petroleum Concessions, Limited, (Sd.) J. SKLIROS, Managing Director. No. 11 Copy of letter from India Office to Petroleum Concessions, Limited, dated 26th August 1937, No. P.Z. 5431/37. Sir, I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to acknowledge receipt of your letter dated the 17th August 1937, No. 433 [No. 10], on the subject of the Debai Oil Concession, and to express on behalf of His Majesty’s Government their formal approval of the concession granted to the Company by the Sheikh of Debai on the 22nd May 1937. 2. Copies of this correspondence are being sent to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf with a view to action being taken as indicated in paragraph 4 of Captain Hickinbotham’s letter dated the 22nd May to the Sheikh of Debai. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, (Sd.) J. C. WALTON. No. 12 Copy of letter from Captain T. llickinbotham, Political Agent, Bahrain, dated the 6th October 1937, No. C/743-10/12, to Shaikh Said bin Maktum, O.B.E., Ruler of Dubai. After compliments, With reference to paragraph 4 of my letter No. T/l of 1937 dated the 22nd May 1937 [No. 3], I have been instructed by His Majesty’s Government to inform you that the arrangements set forth in that letter and your acceptance of them conveyed in your letter dated the 22nd May 1937 [No. 4], have been communicated to Petroleum Concessions, Limited, and that the Company formally confirm their acceptance of these arrangements. Usual ending, (Sd.) T. HICKINBOTHAM, Captain, Political Agent, Bahrain.CONFIDENTIAL. No. 699-ii of 1937. 1 6970 i - y l ; ^ J The Hon*ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to His Majesty*s Secretary of State for India, London* / The Secretary to the Government of India, External Affairs Department, Simla* and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document* (*). *1° 6\C( c VT British Consulate-Gtneral, BUSHIKE. Dated.,. ; !-.3th..0ctober 1937 Reference to previous correspondence: India Office letter No,P*2.5431/S7, dated 2 nd September 1957* Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Letter No.C/743-10/12 dated the 6 th October 1937 to Shaikh Said bin Maktum al Trucial Coast Oil. Hashar, O.B*E., Ruler of Dubai Concession* Dubai, from Political Agent, Bahrain, MM**' n i , iWb J No. C/743-10/12 6970 0 &lt;? The 6 th October 7 .J To / Shaikh Said bin Maktum al Hashar, O.B.E., Huler of Dubai. After Compliments. With reference to paragraph 4 of my letter No. T/l of 1937 dated the 22nd May 1937, I have been instructed by His Majestyts Government to inform you that the arrangements set forth in that letter and your acceptance of them conveyed in your letter dated the 22nd May 1937 have been communicated to Petroleum Concessions Limited and that the Company formally confirm their acceptance of these arrangements. Usual Ending. Sd/- T. Hickinbothan, Captain. Political Agent, Bahrain. .'TV.5973 5000 3.37 . 05 ) Draft Paper. P. Z. 5431/37. poli ti cal Department. DRAFT j LETTER. 1 SfiD tfV) ' s “*\ \ , /' lir 0. K. Caroe , Esq . , C . I.E. , H.B.M.Consulate General, Bushire. Sir , I am directed by the Secretary of State to refer to Bushire telegram No.473 of the 25th May, 1937, and to Bushire Printed Letter of the 5th June Copy to F.O. Admiralty Petroleum Dept. 2 7 MG 1357 To Company dated 14.8.37 From To 17.8.37 / / / / ENCLOSURE IN v»rr^i V I ETTCR ’ | No. 3 5 2-SEP 1937 FiitM ScCRET,... . »»J SECRET DEPT. INDIA OFMCE CO.-Y SENT TO. i tU f-A ,J i*****^'' In 'ft ' '\icd\l &gt; No.438-S of 1937, enclosing copies of Notes exchanged with the Sheikh of D^hnl in regard to the Oil Concession granted by him to Petroleum Concessions Limited on the 22nd May 1937, and to forward for your information copies of the complementary correspondence exchanged with the Company. 2. I am to request that you will instruct the Political Agent, Bahrein, to communicate to the Sheikh of Dubai the formal confirmation by the Company of their acceptance of the arrangements set out in Captain Hickinbothan’s letter of 22nd May to the Sheikh^ 3. Copies of this letter and enclosures are being sent to the Government of India, External Affairs Department, and to the Political Agent, Bahrein. 11. J e CLAUiStv.f Draft Paper. P.Z.5431/37. Department. The Managing Director, Petroleum Concessions Ltd., City-Gate House, Finsbury Square, Sir, I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to acknowledge receipt of your letter dated the 17th August 1937,Ho.433, on the subject of the D£bai Oil Concession,and to express on behalf of His Majesty’s Government their formal a proval of the Concession granted to the Company by the Sheikh of Dgbai on the 22nd May,1937. 2. Copies of this correspondence are being sent to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf with a view to action being taken as indicated in paragraph 4 of Captain Hickinbotham’s letter dated the 22nd May to the Sheikh of D^bai.TELEPHONE : NATIONAL 3582 JV c TELEGRAMS : INLAND : PETCONCESS, FINSQUARE, LONDON FOREIGN : PETCONCESS, LONDON CODES : BENTLEY’S SECOND PHRASE BENTLEY’S COMPLETE PHRASE WITH OIL SUPPLEMENT LOMBARD PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LIMITED DIRECTORS : CITY-GATE HOUSE FINSBURY SQUARE Sir John Cadman, G.C.M.G. (Chairman) A. Agnew, C —1— \ R. Cayrol, D. D.S.C. (French) W. Fraser, C.b... C. S. Gulbenkian (formerly Armenian) J. B. A. Kessler (Dutch) L. M. Lefroy J. A. Meny (French) H. G. Seidel (U.S.A.) R. W. Sellers J. Skliros LONDON • E.C.2 No.4^5 of State for India, Under Secretary India Office, Whitehall, S.W.l. 17th August 1957 Sir, We have the honour to acknowledge receipt of your letter of the 14th August 1957, under No.PZ.4577/57, relative to a concession recently obtained by this Company for the territory of Dubai. (2). We beg formally to confirm our acceptance, as binding on the Company, of the arrangements embodied in the letter of 22nd May 1957, under No.T/1, from the Political Agent, Bahrain, to the Ruler of Dubai. (5). We shall be glad to receive notice of His Majesty ! s Governments formal approval of the concession granted to us by the Shaikh of Dubai on May 22nd 1957* We have the honour to be. Sir, Your obedient servants. For PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LIMITED, Managing Director.TELEPHONE : NATIONAL 3582 TELEGRAMS : INLAND : PETCONCESS, FINSQUARE, LONDON FOREIGN : PETCONCESS, LONDON CODES : BENTLEY’S SECOND PHRASE BENTLEY’S COMPLETE PHRASE WITH OIL SUPPLEMENT LOMBARD PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LIMITED DIRECTORS : Sir John Cadman, G.C.M.G. (Chairman) A. Agnew, C.B.E. R. Cayrol, [ ^0., D.S.C. (french) W. Fraser, C C. S. Gulbenk. formerly Armenian) J. B. A. Kessler (Dutch) SemdmimJImUatid L. M. Lefroy J. A. Meny (French) H. G. Seidel (U.S.A.) R. W. Sellers J. Skliros No.439 CITY-GATE HOUSE FINSBURY SQUARE LONDON * E.C.2 17th August 1937* My dear Clauson, Your letter P.Z.4^77/37 of August 16th. Mr. Skliros has to-day replied to your official letter of August 14th regarding the Dubai exchange of letters, by a letter to the Under Secretary of State following closely the lines of Mr. Fraser’s letter of June 24th 1935- We therefore await formal notification that the Secretary of State has formally approved our Dubai Concession. Yours sincerely. M.J. ClausonEsq., Indie Office, Whitehall, S.W.l.9 6008 Wfc 8322—P 8 1000 + 3000 1..37 It is requested that in any further communi cation on this subject the under-mentioned letter and number may be quoted, and the reply addressed to — ! U INDIA OF NIGH, The Under Secretary of State for India, WHITEHALL, LONDON, 8.W.I. Z.4377/37 Political Department, India Office, '/37. London, S. W. 1. August,1937. Sir, I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to enclose herewith for the information of petroleum Concessions Limited, a copy of a letter Uo.T/l dated the 22nd May,1937, from the Political Agent, Bahrein to the Sheikh of Debai, together with a translation of the latter^ reply dated 22nd May, 1937, in regard to certain points which arise in connection with the oil concession granted (subject to the approval of His Majesty's Government) to your Company by the Sheikh of Debai on 22nd May, 1937, and in connection with the Political Agreement of the 5th February, 1937, between your Company and His Majesty's Government, regarding the said concession* 2 . I am to request that in accordance with the unofficial understanding already reached with the Company, Petroleum Concessions Limited will now be good enough formally to confirm their acceptance of the arrangements embodied in the Political Agent's letter,Ho.T/l dated the 22nd May,1937, as binding on the Company* I am to add that on receipt of a letter from the Company accenting the arrangements mentioned above, the Marquess of Zetland will cause a further letter to be addressed to the Company expressing His Majesty's Government'! formal approval of the oil concession granted to the Company by the Sheikh of Debai* I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant 9 P id.) M. J. GUMISON 1 ‘ The Managing Director Petroleum Concessions Ltd*, City Gate House, 9 E.C.2.Vx f oU 5 f ^ P.Z. 4377/37. My dear Longri^g, \ - India Of lee, Whitehall, S.l&amp;.l, lith Aujuat, 1937. F / / / Would you icindly refer to your letter of the 27th October, 1936, P.Ch 29/190, and connected correspondence about the Debai Political Agreement and Exchange of Kotes. We received some tine ago from the Political Resident, copies of the Hotes which were exchanged with the Sheihh of Debal. I enclose a copy for your infor at ion. ,/e shall in due course he printing then up. It had, of course, been the intention to exchange Notes with the Company concurrently with those exchanged with the Sheikhs, but I regret to say that this was overlooked at the time. The ntter should now be regularised, and I am accordingly sending * you herewith a letter signed by Mr. Walton which, as you will see, follows the lines of the letter sent to the Anglo-Persian Oil Co pany on the 21st June, 1935, in respect of the atar concession. The reply from the Anglo-Persian Oil Company was sent on the 24th June, 1935, i;. i • Longr igg, Es , Petroleum Concessions limited. City Cate House, Finsbury Square, E. C. 2.and we should be obliged if you would kindly arrange for a formal reply to be sent by the Go pany on these lines* We will then issue to you the final letter giving the forral approval of His Majesty’s (lorernnent to tiie concession* Yours sincerely, (Sgd.) M. J. CLAUSON °r\w4. r | &lt;3&gt;|- \ .. ^ - ^ ^ ^ A.tJ-W . X't I 1U. 'CONFIDENTIAL. 1. H.M’s Secretary of State for India, London. 2 . The Secretary to the Government of India, External Affairs Department, Simla. and has the honour documents (s). to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned \ \ / A IV ' 'V British Consulate-General, BU^HIRE. Dated. Reference to previous correspondence: Political Resident* s telegram No. 475, dated 25th May 1937, copy to Government of India under Residency Printed Letter No. 388-S, dated 25th May 1937. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. 1. Copy of letter No. T/l dated 22.5.37 from Political Agent, Bahrain, to Shaikh of Dubai. 2. Copy of letter No. T/2 dated 22.5.37 from Political Agent, Bahrain, to Shaikh of Dubai. 3. Copy of translation of letter dated 11th Rabi* al Auwal 135l6 from Shaikh of Dubai to Pol itical Agent, Bahrain. 4. Copy of translation of letter dated 11th Rabi* al Auwal 1356 from the Shaikh of Dubai to Political Agent, Bahrain. 5. Copy of letter No. T/3 dated 24.5.37 from Political Agent, Bahrain, to Shaikh of Dubai. .-5 JUL 133 ? IWDIA v i, &gt;jf DUBAI OIL CONCESSION.&gt; t X 4 To .i.' • ^ » 4377 1957 No. T/l Of 1957. { Office of the Political Agent, 1 Bahrain, Camp Sharjah. Dated the 22nd May 1957. J Shaikh Sa*id bin Maktum, O.B.E., Kuler of Dubai. ' Cl rl l * |Yo ^ ^jo&gt;Aa 4 L. ^ tU\ ** ^ T.p.fr.t)/.. \ After Compliments, His Majesty 1 s Government have been furnished with a copy of the Agreement signed by you on the 22nd May 1957 granting to Petroleum Development (Trucial Coast ) Limited, which is a subsidiary Company of Petroleum Concessions Lim ited, an oil concession in respect of your territory on the understanding that the Agreement is subject to the approval of His Majesty’s Government. 2. Under instructions from His Majesty’s Government I now enclose a copy of an Agreement which has been between His Majesty's Government and Petroleum Concessioaa n ^ Limited in London on 5th February 1957. 5 . It is desirable that there should be a clear under standing as to the position which would arise in certain eventualities in connection with these two Agreements and I am to inform you that in these circumstances the under standing described below has been reached with the Company:- (aj Should any of the terms of the Agreement between you and the Company be inconsistent or in conflict with the terms of the Agreement between the Company and His Majesty’s Government signed in London on 5th February 1937 the Agree ment between you and the Company will to the extent of any such inconsistency or conflict be subordinate to and be controlled by the terms of the Agreement between the Company and His Majesty's Government. W/ n concluded , ''l /(Wfall '**' J * ^ •A f\' ftt Vtn a ' /* ,' v ^ V*&gt;U^ &gt; » ^ • '■’ ^ IK ' ■• &gt; *Vf . (b) If the Company should fail to observe an&gt; oi the terms of the Agreement between the Company and His Majesty*» Government signed in Lonaon on/bth February 19S7 or if the alleged failure having been disputed by the Company the matter has been referred to arbitration unaer Article 24 oi the lAr (y* ^4 a&gt;» s l elt 9K s ifeae]applicable to the 1»— case by Article 11 of the Agreement between the Company ana His Majesty* s Government} and the Coppany shoula not remedy such failure within the xeusonable time *,&lt;iiich shoul be fixea by the arbitrators for so doing then in these cases, as in the cas^s mentionea in Article 19 of the Company’s Agreement with you, but in no other, the Company agrees that you will be entitled to terminate the Agreement between the Company ana yourself, ana that ail properties of the Company within your territory shall become your property, and that they wixi hana over to you free of cost land granted to the Company by y -u ana any lanas or buildings which the Company may have bought ana any houses or buildings constructed, by the Com any and all other irremovable property of the Company 7 witnin your territory including the producing wells anc borings which shall bfc hanaea over in reasonably good oraex anc repair. 4. Please let me have a reply to this letter to the effect that you understand the nature of tne arrangements as set out above and that you are prepared to agree to them. On receipt of your reply his Majesty’s Government will obtain from the Company formal confirmation of their acceptance of the arrange ments in question and will communicate such confirmation to you. Usual Lnaing. Sd. T.Hickinbotham, Captain. Company* s Agreement with you (whicn^I TO Political Agi nt, Banrain.No. T/2 of 1957. Office of the Political Agent, Bahrain, Camp BharJan. fatea the S^na May 1957. Shaikh Sa T id bin MaKtum, O.B.h., Hiller of Lubki. After Compliments, ( 21 ivith reference to the Agreement signed by you on the %2na May 1957 granting the Petroleum Development (Trucial Coast) Limitec an oil concession in respect oi your territory, I have teen directed by iiis Majesty 1 s Government to inform you tnat they are prepared to accora their approval to tne con cession provided you accept the following condition, namely that should you wish to giant permission toa Bana to open a Brancn or Agency inj^Libai,, as mentioned in Article 25 of the Concession, you will obtain His Majesty's Government's approval before entering into any negotations with the Bana. On receipt of your reply accepting tne above condition tne •formal approval oi His Majesty's Government to the Concession will bfe communicated to you and to the Company. Usual knalng. Sd. T.Hickinbotham, Captain. Political Agnt, Bahrain.No. T/S of 1937 Office of the Political Agent, Bahrain, Camp Sharjah. Dated the 24th May 1937. To Shaikh Sa^d bin Maktum, O.B.E., huler of Dubai. After Compliments, With reference to your letter dated the 22nd May 1937 equivalent to the 11th habi* al Auwal 1356 accepting the conditions set forth in my letter No. T/l dated 22nd May 1937 equivalent to the 11th Habi 1 al Auwal 1356, I am directed by His Majesty* s Government to convey to you their approval of the Agreement concluded by you on the /22nd May 1937 with Petroleum Develppment (Trucial Coast; Limited Usual Ending. Sd. T.Hickinbotham, Captain. Political Agent, Bahrain.r 1&gt;. /.. ! 5067 I . f Coni identxal. G0VERNME ^ ei j YN'i)tA; ' (Z I i ?k ^ i/^ fa (fatuX* [?2 S?7i/ } J C7kKx k tw, EXPRESS LETTER ^ Department* [N, C ,—This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To sace time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] FftOM - political Res ident, Buanire. To Rep eat ed To Secretary oi State tor 1 nd.iaj GrQVeminent ox India, iSxternad Poiitical Agent, Baiirain. London. V All airs Lepartiaent, Simia* xVcx ‘3l9-o. Ikued 7tn July Sutnect: Dioai Oil Concession. 1 nave received copy or concession, as nas tne political Agent, Bahrain, trom tne Coinpftny. I suggest you snould obtain copies rrom Company^ neadquarters in London ana send a copy to tne government of India. sd. f. C.Povvle. Political Resident in tne Persian dull'. Attest ed. L for Secretary to tne Political Resident in tne Persian Gulf*CONFIDENTIAL. No. 484-S of 1957 The Hon’ble the Political compliments to I&gt; Z. ) 4375 :| S 1937 J ItesidCTit nir tire'” Persian Gulf presents his y 1* H.M's Secretary of State for India, London. 2 . The Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Department, Simla. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents (s). British Consulate-General, BUSHIKE. Dated.. .22nd. .J.une. .1937., Reference to previous correspondence: Residency Printed Letter No. 438-S, dated 5th June 1937. Description of Enclosure, Name and Date. Copy of letter dated 12th June 1937 from Ruler of Dubai to the Political Agent, Bahrai Subject. Dubai Oil Concession. n. REG&amp;. P3L. D£PT, INC,... OFFlOlljVi Translation of letter dated the 12 th June 1937 equivalent to the 2 nd Rabi* ath-Thani 1356 from Shaikh SaUd bin Maktum, 0*B#S., Ruler of Dubai to Captain T.HiQkiabotham, Political Agent, Bahrain* (,s4 After Compliments, I write to inform you that I undertake that I will be S^ided by the advice of His Majesty* s Government in regard to my exercising the rigto of termination of the Concession which is referred to in paragraph 3(b) of your letter No. T/l dated the 22nd May 1937 equivalent to the 11th Rabi* al Auwal 1356. Usual Ending 0P^e, . p l+a . m THIS AGREEMENT dated the fifth day of February One thousand Stamp 10s/-. 1. 2 . 3. 4. 5. nine hundred and thirty seven is made BETWEEN HIS MAJESTY'S GOVERNMENT IN THE UNITED KINGDOM (hereinafter called 'His Majesty's Government') of the one part and PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LIMITED (herein after called 'the Company' which expression shall v/here the context so admits be deemed to include its successors and/or assignees and shall also be deemed to include any subsidiary Company) of the other part. WHEREAS Petroleum Development (Trucial Coast) Ltd. is a Subsidiary Company of Petroleum Concessions Limited. AND WHEREAS in the event of the Company obtaining a concession from the Sheikh of Debai (hereinafter called 'the Sheikh') certain responsibilities will devolve on His Majesty's Government, the Company has agreed with His Majesty’s Government as follows Petroleum Concessions Limited and any subsidiary company shall be and remain a British company registered in Great Britain and having its principal place of business in Great Britain, and its Chairman shall at all times be a British subject. THE Agreement between the Company and the Sheikh shall not be transferred to any other companv without the prior consent in writing of His Majesty's Government, and any other company to which that agreement may be transferred shall be and remain a British company registered in Great Britain and having its principal place of business in Great Britain, and its Chairman shall at all times be a British subject. THE employees of the Company in Debai shall at all times be British subjects or subjects of the Sheikh, provided that, with the consent of His Majesty's Government, such persons of other nationality as are renuired for the efficient carrying on of the undertaking may be employed. NOTWITHSTANDING anything contained in the Agreement between the Company and the Sheikh, the importation of foreign native labour shall be subject to the approval of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. THE Company in all except unimportant or routine matters shall deal with the Debai Authorities through a Chief Local Representative in the Persian Gulf, who shall be a British subject. The approval of His Majesty’s Government shall be recuired for the person so designated. He will be ordinarily resident in Debai or Bahrein and will be responsible for the Company's local relations with the Debai authorities, which shall, except in routine or unimportant matters, be conducted through the political representative of His Majesty's Government in Bahrein or through any other person whom the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf may from time to time designate. SUBJECT to the terms of the Agreement between the Company and the Sheikh the Company undertakes at all times to pay due deference to the wishes of the Sheikh and to the advice of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf and of the Political Officers subordinate to him. ANY right given to the Companv under its agreement with the Sheikh to utilise means of transportation by air shall be subject to any general regulations for civil aircraft made by the Sheikh on the advice of His Majesty's Government, and to any instructions which may be issued by the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. NOTWITHSTANDING anything contained in the Agreement between the Company and the Sheikh the Company shall not have the right to use or occupy, and shall not include in the areas to be acouired or utilised for the purposes of its operations, any sites which may have been selected by or on behalf of the Sheikh or His Majesty’s Government for defence purposes, for aerodromes, aeroplane or seaplane bases or for wireless and Stamp 10s/-. 1. 2 . 3. 4. 5. P.Z.351/37(2) Xb; al iioJ sd* b : * telegraph installations or in connection with the development of harbours, provided that with the consent of His Majesty’s Government which shall not be unreasonably withheld the Company shall have the right to use for the purposes of its operations such harbours as may be developed by the Sheikh or His Majesty’s Government if there is not reasonable harbour accommodation available elsewhere. Subject to the terms of the agreement between the Company and the Sheikh harbo^^ developed by the Company shall be under its complete and exclusj^w control. 8. TELEGRAPH, wireless and telephone installations, if any, maintained by the Company shall be for use only in its business and as provided in the concession, and shall be so constructed and operated that their operations shall not interfere with the operations of such wireless, telegraph or telephone installations as may be established by the Sheikh or His Majesty’s Government, or their agent. 9. IN the event of a state of national emergency or war (of the existence of either of which His Majesty’s Government shall be the sole judge) His Majesty’s Government shall have the right of pre-emption of all the oil produced in Debai in accordance with the terms of the Schedule hereto. 10. THE Company shall obtain the prior permission of the Sheikh before working in any particular area, in order that the Sheikh may be in a position to fulfil his responsibilities for the protection of the Company. The Sheikh shall not unreasonably withhold such permission, and in any case in which the Company feels that the free movement of its personnel within the concession area is being unnecessarily restricted the matter shall be referred for decision to the Political Resident. 11. IN the event of notice of termination of the Agreement between the Company and the Sheikh being given on the ground that the Company has failed to observe any of the terms of the present Agreement between the Company and His Majesty’s Government, the arbitration provisions of the said Agreement between the Company and the Sheikh shall apply if the Company considers that notice of termination on such grounds is not justified, and in that event the Sheikh shall not cancel the said Agreement until arbitration takes place in accordance with the said provisions and unless the Company fails to comply with the award of the arbitrators within the reasonable time which shall be fixed by the arbitrators for so doing. IN WITNESS whereof John Charles Walton C.B. on behalf of His Majesty’s Government has hereunto set his hand and seal and the Company has hereunto caused its Common Seal to be affixed the day and year first above written THE SCHEDULE ab ove referred to Pre-emption Clause. In the event of a state of national emergency or war (of the existence of which His Majesty’s Government shall be the sole judge) - (1) His Majesty’s Government shall have the right of pre-emption of all crude oil gotten under the Concession granted by the Sheikh to the Company and of all the products thereof and shall have the right to require the Company to the extent of any refining capacity it may have in Debai to produce oil fuel that shall comply with the Admiralty specifications at the time provided that Debai oil be of a suitable kind and quality for this purpose. (2) The Company shall use its utmost endeavours to increase so far as reasonably possible with existing facilities the supply of oil and/or products thereof for the Government to the extent required by the Government.(3) The Company shall 'irith every reasonable expedition and so as to avoid demurrage on the vessel or vessels engaged to convey the same, do its utmost to deliver all oil or products of oil purchased by the Government under their said right of pre-emption in the quantities at the time and in the manner required by the Government at a convenient place of shipment or at a place of storage in Debai to be determined by His Majesty’s Government. In the event of a vessel employed to carry any such oil or products thereof on behalf of His Majesty being detained on demurrage at the port of loading the Company shall pay the amount due for demurrage according to the terms of the charter party and/or the rates of loading previously agreed with the Company unless the delay is due to causes beyond the control of the Company. Any dispute which may arise as to whether the delay is due to causes beyond the control of the Company shall be settled by agreement between His Majesty’s Government and the Company, and, in default of such agreement, the question shall be referred to two arbitrators, one to be chosen by His Majesty’s Government (or the Political Resident) and the other by the Company, with power to appoint an umpire in case of disagreement, such arbitration to be held in England and to be deemed a reference to Arbitration under the provisions of the Arbitra tion Acts 1389 to 1934 (52 and 53 Viet, c.49; 24 and 25 Geo.V. c.14) of the Imperial Parliament, or any statutory modification or re-enactment thereof for the time being in force. (4) The price to be paid for all oil or products of the refining or treatment of oil taken in pre-emption by His Majesty’s Government shall be either (a) as specified in a separate agreement or (b) if no such agreement shall have been entered into, a fair price for the time being at the point of delivery as the same shall be settled by agreement between His Majesty’s Government and the Company, or in default of such agreement by arbitration in the manner provided by the last preceding sub-clause. To assist in arriving at a fair price at the point of delivery the Company shall furnish for the confidential information of Kis Majesty's Government, if so required, particulars of the quantities, descriptions and prices of Debai oil or products sold to other customers and of charters or contracts entered into for carriage and shall exhibit to His Majesty's Government original or authenticated copies of contracts or charter parties entered into for the sale and/or carriage of such oil or products. (5) His Majesty’s Government shall be at liberty to take control of the works, plant and premises of the Company in Debai, and in such event the Company shall conform to and obey all directions issued by or on behalf of His Majesty’s Government. Compensation shall be paid to the Company for any loss or damage that may be proved to have been sustained by the Company by reason of the exercise by His Majesty’s Government of the powers conferred by this sub-clause. Any such compensation shall be settled by agreement between His Majesty’s Government and the Company or, in default of agreement, by arbitration in the manner provided by sub-clause (3). SIGHED SEALED AND DELIVERED by) the said John Charles ) Walton on behalf of His ) J. C. ./ALTON (L.S.) Majesty's Government in the ) presence of:- ) H. S. PAINTER India Office. THE COMMON SEAL of Petroleum ) Concessions Limited was here- ) unto affixed in the presence ) of:- ) JOHN CADMAN Director E. J. BROWN Secretary (SEAL)DATED 5 th February 1957. HIS MAJESTY T S GOVERNMENT IN THE UNITED KINGDOM S** - and - PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LIMITED AGREEMENT relating to the Debai Oil Concession.* 6 — 2 — ARTICLE 3. The Shaikh hereby grants to the Company the exclusive right to explore search for drill for produce and win natural gas asphalt ozokerite crude petroleum and their products and cognate substances (hereinafter referred to as “^be /obstances”) within the State, the exclusive ownership of all the Substances so produced and won, the right to refine transport sell for use within and without the State or for export and to export or otherwise deal with or dispose of the/Substances, and the right to import export pump ship or otherwise transport the Substances across or to any country or place at the Company’s dis cretion and the right to do all things necessary for the purpose of these oper ations. A RTICL E 4. If hereafter any neutral Zone is created adjacent to the territory of the State, wherein the Shaikh shall have a co-equal and joint interest, the Shaikh hereby agrees to grant to the Company an oil concession over such neutral zone on terms to be agreed between the Shaikh, the Company and the joint ruler of such Nautral £one. ARTICLE 5. In consideration of the rights granted by the Shaikh by this Agreement the Company shall pay to the Shaikh*—-* (a) on signature of the agreement Rupees 60,000 ( Sixty thousand ). / ( b) Rupees 200,000 (Two hundred ^housand)within a period of sixty (60) days from the date upon which the Company declares in writing to the Shaikh that substances have been discovered in com mercial quantities. If the Company should fail to declare so sooner, then the date of discovery of substances in commercial quantities shall be that date upon which the Company has completed and tested a well or wells capable of producing in accordance with first class oil practice not less than /wo thousand (^OOO) English Tons of clean substances per day for a period of ^lurty (30) consecutive days. A ( c ) Rupees 30,000 ( Thirty ousand ) at the end of each year from the date of signature hereof until the ‘ Fa y ,mk\ I ..a l_A&gt;- { ^y* — -t*’ W* jLlH ) ^ y y j • * * a ^ * \ I • jJlj* j '/JLalfi y y t y^ y^ Lyu j' yi jUy y ^ i/'t ^ ij jsULiii lii-L.ijioai ^y**' ^ o/. si-&gt;- • ju 4-&gt;U»Vl *ja jyfi 4jk«dl j ill4 a^L1I •Jbli-I *Jufc ljU.1 Jp iljLlll ^,.1)1 (j\i L LjJU- jh • »jjk J ^ • j * &lt;&gt;-oil I . ^Ul ^U\ &lt;jU*V! Q--*h T • j • • • Jp yA\ jup ( I) • Oy~ &lt;yjj r • • j • • • ( v ) ^JLaj j ilic ^I ^iyi jt* AA/Ol *y. ^jLr £jt^\ s2 &gt;1 jlj (^ill ^ jUl w—^ iiyi — ^bi yXx jii ji ji&gt;~ “&amp; yj' \2&gt;j£\ — (JjVi &lt;&gt;■ jjJi o jUl* ^y&lt; v&gt;* &lt;s^ ^ (r--*) • Lj» (r •) &lt;jOb* •-x! &lt;jlJ1 v-ill ( 5 ^) •-u jp ^ c- j6=» y.i j *' ^&gt;1 jLr j» &lt;&gt; -■■ —— 3 — — r — Company declares in writing to the Shaikh that ^bstances have been discovered in j commercial quantities in accordance with the Xub (Clause ^b) of this Article 5 . or until the Company commences Production from quantities less than commercial quantities In the event of such / Production by the Company , from quantities less than commer cial quantities either Rupees 50p00 ( Fifty ^/housand ) per year or Rupees 3 (|Rree) per English Ton of 2,240 lbs. in respect of the Substances so won and saved shall be payable, whichever is the greater. (d) At the end of every year from the date upon which the Company makes in writing to the Shaikh the declaration that the^Substances have been discovered in commercial quantities Rupees ^90,000^ (Ninety thousand) or Rupees 3 (Three) per English ton of 2,240 lbs. in respect of the /Substances other than natural gas, won and saved during the preceding Calendar year, whichever is the greater. ( e ) Annas 2 (JTwoi per 1,000 cubic feet of natural gas produced and sold. In calculating royalty for the purpose of this article account shall not be taken of any of the substances used by the Com pany in its operations or used by the Com pany’s employees within the State, necessary for their use, nor of any water or foreign matter which may be produced with the Substances. ARTiQLE 6 . The Company shall not carry on any operations within areas occu pied by or devoted to the purposes of mosques, sacred buildings or graveyards. ARTICLE 7. The Company shall conduct its operations in a workmanlike manner and by appropriate scientific me thods and shall take all reasonable measures to prevent the ingress of water to any petroleum - bearing strata and shall duly close any unproductive holes drilled by it and subsequently abandoned. The Company shall keep the Shaikh informed generally as to the progress and result of its drilling operations but such information shall be treated as confidential. 3^1*^ —&gt;• \ ^ ytl V ) • yull L*JI ja L JL o. •. • u vji* \ r b ^ ^ j' ^ M ) j ( 3 ) i y yi 4j 'i jU'l l-U. \a - y[\ TYt • j_/ ^ &lt;1—'I (_j j j . ;Ui jir u ;iui JA ^ ^ £/* M * (*) jljJI #^111 j -Xi JUP^j * i • i * • • • • • • J I Ul^ I O \ lyi+A-*-) ^ ^ &lt;&gt; jj•jUVI otyi ^o ^iii .yij *lii 4*1 l »yb Vl» &lt;5^JLM JytZ — i—iLJl oll| 4-ii Vlj j\ 4l^i-lll ^yidl . Jjljdlj 4—oil • 4^yJLUj^AL _ 4 aj l— jjl j 4 .«*Il» 4JJ^5 ji+t j 4^1^ OliLL ^ 4juL 4j * All V'^ ^ ^ o 'j J' f &gt;Ul ijf&gt; j dJjS -A* ^r — 4 — — i — A RTIC LE 8 . Within three months after the expiry of each calendar year, the Company shall deliver to the Shaikh a statement of the amount of the Substances won and saved and in the case of natural gas produced and sold during the said calen dar year,and of the royalty which is or might have been payable under Article 5, together with a report of its operations during the said year. The Shaikh or his representative shall have the right to check such returns and statements, and all such returns and statements and the reports of the Company’s operations shall be treated as confidential by the Shaikh ARTICLE 9.—-(a) The Company shall have the right to import water, the Sub stances, fuel, machinery, motor-cars and lorries,aircraft, equipment, plant, timber, utensils, iron work, building materials, food supplies, medicines, medical supplies, office equipment and household furniture, and other materials, equipment and goods of whatsoever nature required by the Company and its employees for the purpose of its operations hereunder and to export the^Substances and articles previously imported by the Company free of customs or export duty and taxes or other charges, but it shall pay on all personal goods, clothing and general mer chandise imported by the Company for the personal use of its employees or for resale to them the ordinary duty in force for the time being in the State. Saving as in Article 5 and in this Article provided, the Company, its personnel, its operations, income, profits and property including the ygubstances shall be exempt and free during the period of this Agreement from all present or future harbour duties, import duties, export duties, taxes, imposts and charges of any kind whether State or local, tolls and land surface rent of whatever nature. In consideration of the right herein granted the Company shall pay-in addition to the Royalty per ton of Rupees/( 3 ) iiL) tcJLU A—AL-. ^ J ijj A&gt;dl jl' J 3 Oj ^ j li 1 L. 1 . Aj aS^JL!'J l/’l A^liLI j j\A~y j jf ^‘4 (1) _ ;.-ui 0U1 ill yi O' Ja jOlj -j ON^' li' j»UJI^'^»jAi Jb JL^IOW^LoI'^aJ v A^IiJl 1 &gt; j Ay^O'l O' 9 jt J\ yyj yjL-i'j aju*vi .i&gt; &gt; v U's's A--a&gt;«.JL ^ pJt; pi £ j'015^ \ ^3 ' a^» i-aJij oi— pJ' - y l ^ 3J&gt;% ~~ S Aj o&gt;j)' j • 3'^’ a^Uj oLII J f 3 U I JlC- L Aj ' J UU! y \yjb y y A^y»— ^ jU S^Ll' bJJt^yyLalA a^ 4 *&gt;» ^'y' j' ■ f^^yj y Jb ' y* y ^y&lt;aJ'j0'jil-A)'^0'^j'y' \JTy &lt;.• A-J Oj ^ UHI a y» J\ y j y^+ ^ &lt;a\c. ■ O' p9x LfU'Ni •if- yp ^ 3 ' j is aS^o'i 3y^ —*&gt;■ J«' J* ^ ( r ) V 1 -**-— 5 — — • — 9 as provided in Article 5 - to the Shaikh within (3) three months after the close of each calendar year the sum of (4) four annas per English ton of 2,240 lbs. in respect of the Substances won and saved during the said calendar year. (b) The importation by the Company of firearms and other weapons is prohibited, except with the written permission of the Shaikh. ( c ) The Company may import su^h alcoholic drinks and liquors as the Company may require for the use of their foreign employees but only with the written permission of the Shaikh, and the Political Agent, Bahrain, or any authority deputed by them, but the Company shall not sell or give alcoholic drinks or liquors to the Subjects of the Shaikh or to the Subjects of adjoining Rulers who may be employed within the State. ARTICLE 10. The employees of th; Company shall be allowed to enter into an i to leave the State at all times without let or hindrance and free of all charge, and the Shaikh shall grant to the Company's employees every facility required for the purpose of the Company’s operations hereunder. But the Company’s employees shall not interfere or by their actions cause any disturbance or cause opposition to the Shaikh’s authority within the State of Dubai and the employees shall not go beyond the limit of their duties when employed within or when leaving the confines of the State of Dubai for the purpose of this Agreement. Further in the event of any of the Company’s employees - whether he be a senior or a junior employee-committing an offence which may cause disorder or interfere with the moral or religious laws or interfere with the politics or Subjects of the State of Dubai or excite them to sedition, then the Shaikh may apply to the Political Agent, Bahrain, to send the person concern- ed-if a foreigner-out of the State of Dubai but if a Subject of the Shaikh then the Shaikh may arrest the culprit and deal with him according to the laws of the State of Dubai • ‘-a-sil -X*, ly\\ ^ TYt* j&gt; • Cr” o- ^ Vi u.Mi 0 , JUl-V UlaL- j^ J . VJ V cUjS jCjj V Cf j* 51 j rc^L!l ja j Jy^y j* 'yi _ Ai X^a iLi— &lt;)i ^ y l»lc JoJuLI Tt*—) _ O a y *0 ^ ‘ _^ A ij^.iAA y Ic- y\ p La\J J&lt;&gt;x.Z+~A . oU'yi •i* j* j\ &lt;5^iR v 4la 1—1 jl wl jl *3* •jt*1 \ c ^- &lt;-5UiVI »jjb Jf w-'/L. *jLVI •jiU&lt; -X^l IjI L« a!W Lo _ ^ '^-5^ 4-o'il ^&gt;- I-Xij j\ ^U*ylL ,^1 jy\ ijL.1 i-L-J jl jl aJ ^_lll j! JrytJ' J *jUI ^jU - Lo-I jiS^o! _ j jjl 1! Jl k lc_j ^ !j| •Ji i^LI ^,‘ly (ji-ill6 — / » . ARTICLE H.—{a) For the purpose of its operations hereunder the Company shall have the right without hindrance to construct, maintain and operate power stations, refineries, pipelines and storage tanks, facilities for water supply including boring for water, telegraph and telephone lines and installations and wireless install ations, roads, railways, tramways, buildings, ports, harbours, harbour works, aircraft, buildings and landing places for aircraft, wharves and jetties, oil and coaling stations, with such lighting as may be requisite and any other facilities or works which the Company may consider necessary and for such purposes to use free of all payments any stone, sand, gravel, gypsum, lime, clay or similar materials or water which may be available provided always that the in habitants of the State are not prevented from taking their usual requirements of these materials and that the water supply of the local inhabitants and nomad population who may be dependent on the same is not endangered. The Company at its discretion may select the position of any such works. The Company may likewise install and operate without hindrance all such means of transportation by land, air and water as may be necessary for the effective conduct of its operations hereunder provided it is for the purposes of this Agreement. ^ (b] The Company shall under normal conditions accept and transmit free of charge on its wireless and telegraph in stallations such of the Shaikh’s messages as will not interfere with the Company's business, and in times of national emergency the Shaikh shall have the necessary use free of charge of the Company’s wireless and telegraph installations and railways for governmental purposes. Jl/l r UUl (I) _ \&gt;\L\ oil! lK*) J j! J jl )y • 11 * * J! Sjf- j'j #'1! jll U *11! j&gt;l!j ^ J Oil A&gt; Jb Jll.! O' j! j ^ j o'jLL)' j ij* A j *jl&gt;V ij* 015^ &lt;i jZ&gt; ^jZ. I l* ^]! Jl/’N' J 0^011 • Olil*)' j j y 0$**' o'j^V! ii-' ^ ^ j' lu'^ 5^y* (j'j •Jk—• 4»iU)l y»i\) jxJ'j yJU jlou *111 ^ L-O •'yl» jlli^ jjl ^J ! j: JiJI ^ J m x y jl UU-1» jLi)l yjUl vOS^ ^ jZi ou^ jj^ji yo j oil . oUNI ji iiU j '&lt;^1 j, ( v ) I l,. LLi. j j ^3?* j, ;f&gt; Jo j^ j-i'i j‘Uj ^*l*'ll^ j’ tO—U *a^l O'ijl . oyA ^yiyN ijiji-i(c^ The Shaikh s ships shall have the right to use harbours utilised or constructed by the Company provided that such use in no way hampers the Company or interferes in any way with the safety of its operations of which the Company shall be the sole judge. Any wharves or appurtenances con structed by the Company shall be for its exclusive use. The Company may use for the purpose of its operations the harbours along the coast of the State, but the Company shall not impede or interfere with the subjects of the Shaikh or their right to continue the use of existing harbours, anchorages, wharves and docks along the coast of the State at present utilised by them for their sailing craft and fishing boats. AR TICLE 12. The Company shall have the right and be given the necessary facilities**.^ (a) for the import of the Substances into the State from any adjoining territory by pipe lines or otherwise for the purpose of operating any refinery which the Com pany may decide to erect within the State, and (b) for the transport of the Substances by pipe lines or otherwise over and across the State from and to any adjoining terri tory to any point suitable for the refining or shipping of the Substances. And no duties, taxes, charges or dues of any nature whatsoever shall be levied in respect of such import or transport. ARTICLE 13.—(a) The Company shall have free of cost the unrestricted use and occupation of and surface rights over all uncultivated lands of the State which the Company may need for the purpose of its operations and in particular the Company shall have the right to select an area or areas of land chosen by the Company with exclusive surface rights upon which to erect drilling rigs, pump-stations, oil - refineries, storage, terminal, shipping and aircraft facilities and any other works required for the Company’s operations; and the Company may. HIHB* lease for such purposes O' Q;-' 1 £) *j yC’4; ^ &gt; o y y ^ j. -L»-j IfLlxT Aj'yi .jV 1 UUM j j' ^4 O' pt'**' J J ^ j U !\ j J..LJ a$^J 4 j_ a j^Lc. o till o'JLl . Aj yy ill y &gt;ty Vo- ji &gt;\^\ (i) J ; aJLi) db^y^'i^l ly\z* . »jL»N! ^ ••'—'! aT j —^ j j* -li jt /^ c y ]c&gt;yW£ i!y^! ( v t j ) aoU ^o'y v J'j j* j' . j' V'! ^ jCj y jJJ'j y '^d'l (') - ^ ^•i'l IA\ -X. *.*? y y J^»-! J Jl(A— W! u?' J Aij^l! yl-! &lt;6-rCs j^C Wi; syi i*5'j!yi.!d»M I \pJku 0 y^. ylkil yi»! IJL J&gt;/J&gt;c!'\y d-l y j&gt;_j^ &lt;-&gt; ix£y ! y j 1 j 1 !y J j! ^y Ji/ yiL:: j' j v J*\ | //— 8 — A — V any lands, houses or buildings with the consent of and on conditions to be arranged with the proprietors thereof, but the terms of suc]|/^BiBHHM Mease shall not be in excess of those ordinarily current in their respective localities. (y The Company shall acquire only such lands, houses and buildings as are necessary for its operations under this Agreement. The Company shall inform the Shaikh from time to time of the land, houses and buildings which it requires to occupy for its operations; and land, houses and buildings previously acquired by the Company from the Shaikh but found no longer necessary for its operations shall be returned by the Company to the Shaikh free of cost. ARTICLE 14.— (a) The Company shall have tKe right to purchase at current market rates fuel, water, food, building and constructional materials and other supplies of every kind in connection with its oper ations hereunder; further the Shaikh grants to the Company the right to construct new roads for motor and general traffic, and to make use of all existing roads or tracks free of charge, or taxes of any kind whatever. (J&gt;J The Company shall employ Subjects of the Shaikh as far as possible for all work for which they are suited under the supervision of the Com pany's skilled employees, but if the local supply of labour should in the judgment of the Company be inadequate or unsuitable the Company shall have the right to import labour, preference being given to labourers from neighbouring Arab countries who will obey the local laws. The Company shall also have the right to import skilled and technical employees. The Company shall pay to the workmen it employs a fair wage, such wage to be decided and stated by the Company at the time the workmen are engaged. Further, the fact of the Company employing Subjects of the Shaikh shall not in any way whatever alter the Status of such employees in respect of their rights, privil eges and duties as Subjects of the Shaikh, and such employees will remain in all » a » j v.'**** 1 * y i WKtk S* ^ X .‘J o' 3*0^ . If.JJUOjLU jUN 1 | S\ ^ /J 1 viiuX, (v) IjyZ 1 il.r ^ #j&gt; J-V jii ^/.u j/T (i) _ iji oiH jLill J rclC jli villi JC. J ^“““''^7 Jr- y jj 1 '' J^' S^y o* At*y&gt; . [uM k *. J* 'j' ^ s--' ^ ^ uiA Ik* ikiWi -i, M. jisC-yi Js l&gt; J U/n^4v9 ^ ^ o^'^j o**** J**® y v-&gt;ir 3 J- Jy'w-l^O' V.j*' o'-^?' j* pr. &lt;Jx. . aii yi\ o^L) j* o' y Oj^j *9^i ^ ^«-9j ^’2 '*3 ^ a ^ . . J*A&gt; J a)' i w ») . ) U ^y^ u&gt;0'-^ ib iwj i •V&gt; O' JI^VI Or- J - wit V L^lc j' rr U- ij oW 0:*i*yways - subject to the jurisdiction of the laws and under the legal authority of the Shaikh in his capacity as the Ruler of the State of Dubai. ARTICLE 15. The Shaikh shall give to the Company and its employees and property all protection in his power from theft, highway robbery, assault, wilful damage and destruction,and the Company may appoint in consultation with the Shaikh and itself pay trustworthy guards who shall at all times be subjects of the Shaikh unless the Shaikh permits otherwise to assist in protecting the property of the Company and its employees. The Company shall erect at its own expense suitable buildings for the accommodation of such guards at such places as the Company shall decide. ^ U cLL- ijLV olil ' A**.) v —*J-4 » £ j 1 iff #1^3- ^ V-X&gt;* j rc^JLlI lil Ml ^ : J| tWj Ub \y f&gt; ARTICLE 16. In measuring the Sub stances for purposes of royalty the factor for conversion of the volume of oil into weight shall be such figure as may be determined and agreed upon between the Shaikh and the Company after the discovery of oil and the ascertainment of its specific gravity. The Company shall measure the Subs tances by a method customarily used in good technical practice and the Shaikh by his representative duly authorised by him shall have the right to observe such measuring and to examine and test whatever applian ces may be used for such measuring. Such representative shall comply with all neces sary and usual safeguards for the prevention of fire and other accident; and shall make all examinations and tests at such times and in such manner as will cause the minimum of interference with the company’s operations. If upon such examination or testing any such appliance shall be found to be out of order the Company will cause the same to be put in order at its own expense within a reasonable time, and if upon any such examination aforesaid any error sliall be . iS''/Jl j!l J''LV! j .1 jL\ My. j &lt;;l -jL* CoLJI i^UI j j -1 *-' j j ^)\ j3^' ^ J 1 \ JU3 ^ &lt;.U- jL_i (jA-l oH j&gt;-\ &lt;j_I j U_» ^ ^ tj-*««-'»-&gt; ijU^I J J* ^■ , r - ; ' c fj.Lj &lt;oU- jl jbli J J wMLi-l jjj wlijVI lj OL‘UcL.^1 J . JL/-1 J j- cfi L* J»' ^11 vII'La j' i cJj* ^ * j \ ^ ^ ^— 40 — • ■■ ♦ r t discovered in any such appliance, such error shall - if the Shaikh so decides after hearing the Company's explanation • be considered to have existed for 7 kree( 3 )Calan- dar Months previous to the discovery there of or from the last occasion of examining the same in case such occasion shall be within such period of Three calendar Months and the Royalty shall be adjusted accordingly. If the Company should find it necessary to alter, repair or replace any measuring appliances it shall give reasonable notice to the Shaikh or his representative to en able a representative of the Shaikh to be present during such alteration, repair or replacement. V The Company shall keep full and correct records of all measurements as aforesaid and the said representative of the Shaikh shall have access at all reasonable times to such records and shall be at liberty to make extracts from them. Such records shall be treated as confidential by the Shaikh and his representative. ARTICLE 47.—j[a) The Company shall have the right at any time after the expiry of three years from the date of signature of this Agreement to give the Shaikh six months' notice in writing of its intention to terminate this Agreement and this Agreement shall absolutely determine on the date fixed for such termination in •uch notice. (b) If such notice be given not later than 30 years after the date of such signa ture the Company shall be entitled on such determination to remove free of all taxes and duties all plant buildings stores mate rial and property of every sort provided that for a period of three months from the receipt of such notice the Shaikh may purchase - should he so desire - the same at a price equal to the replacement value at that date less depreciation which price shall be agreed or failing agreement settled under Article 24 hereof. bl A* 4i\j J •U b! JU^I 4)7 ^1)1 JJ (r) jL. • J villi IS! '-U 4) ^Jl J-ur^ j^\ 7 ^ jl'j- ^1 ;ju O* ^ r- 1 ' 'S' . vilJS a) ' *' J-Ll—) j' ^ liyb' i|. li ^LjJl I ^ j-^j 1 QplU -Utf- 1 w j ! iO-' &gt; -O r-juj aIxA' v— j lil' } a* L* oliL a) jOt ,j' A^Li'oijV A» 7 j vl&gt; Ulallx JL&gt;-' J . A&gt; j-Lu» j rt-lJI ^-ll ( I) y Ul Jatil o'y-* sl»^» Jjj* Jm) ^ O' b' V' *J&gt; &lt;-.&gt; 1 * j 4^i4»'yi#jjk jiL' juu '-U l^liL j iUl' LU j^UN' '7^ u' v -^** (&lt;-&gt;) yli\ ^ '-•b (J/Vl *JL« ^ j* v^y** jjli'J &lt;ji» ^1'J sZjS V' ^1^ j' ^ A ' J#yl) y (jlT j J &lt;j&gt;* ij* IX» *i» A“i j* - *1')^ J—^ J 'S'-^JL' Ac. lial—' l vllb^A 'ju j v_^—&gt; y* vllfi-j U vlllS jj* ,jU»N' ^ 'Sli aJa ju, o'/5 —11 — — N\ (c) If such notice be given later than 30 years after the date of such signature all the property aforesaid shall become th e property of the Shaikh free of all cost. ARTICLE 18. On the expiry of this Agreement at the end of the period of Seventy-five Years provided in Article 2 or any extension or renewal of that period all the movable and immovable property of the Company in the State shall be handed over to the Shaikh free of cost. Producing wells or borings at the time of such expiry shall be handed over in reasonably good order and repair. ARTICLE 19. Subject to the provisions of Article 22 hereof the Shaikh shall have the right to terminate this Agreement and to take without payment all the property of the Company in the State if—— (a) The Company shall fail to make any of the payments prescribed in this Agree ment within 6 months of the date on which they fall due, or (b) The Company shall be in default respect of an arbitration award under Article 24 hereof. L in r ArU ARTICLE 20. Nothing in this Agree ment ~sEail be read as restricting in any way the right of the Shaikh to grant to other parties concessions or permits for materials other than the Substances as defined in Ar ticle 3 provided that the operations and rights of the Company hereunder are not thereby injuriously affected. If the Shaikh should at any date sub sequent to the date of signature of this Agreement grant to any other parties con cessions or permits as aforesaid the Shaikh undertakes that such concessions shall con tain provisions requiring the holders thereof to abstain from damaging, impeding or interfering with the property, operations and interests of the Company. Deposits of minerals such as gold, silver, copper, lead, potash, sulphur and salt or the like which may be discovered by the Company shall be reported to the Shaikh and shall not be worked by the Company except under special concession or permit from the Shaikh. I • Op U&gt; L* •ji* 1 Xt a) ^ olll *jjl y -a ju ju&gt; y Ajti'i oUi j a] pm j aJ^lii aS^jji o^ U» Op ^^41 #_i&gt; 1 Xc- Jaal'■ ! • ^ *.*11 aL ^ j A»^LL« sX&gt;- a)U A^Sub'N^ A*-Ul ^ ja ol_II 0 -1—^l» 0*J aJ'a O' ( I ) SI ijLNI ^ j\l\} A*53 .SI aT t*-' y» ai^ aJ'a'^ii yn a ^^jh i si (^) y o'^-iii »Ji&gt; • 5 i_.ll ^yx&gt;». y s px . A^U’SI *J&gt; A*) 1^1 I , v Jx—) ^ _ .Jl oil! eT ^—: &gt;^&gt; -Ojj— Aj I* Xa» L* O' ^ AxIa»'^I' ^yX« vJ^|jLl«i j»-\ jA nsx, o* (j ^mi aa y» A^uiiioiiijiij^.i yy' .i.-Nt qjjLaj ji A^yUl J^l j o' ^j-*. TzIa S^J I I/j l' aS S’ NI • *a_. A-ji* si#xk (( j^ ^jIjXw ^i^i ^--.mi • ^ 3*Xl jl m&gt;l jlx.1 j 'il IL y OljLl*^l o'* ^-&gt;-0! Jipi) jl ijf ^ I pile O' • . 'a^jji u^a y ji^i y isu j A^ai'l y pJ^lAOJuISIyi jl Jl uj iU iTjl l,iilSL.- a» • err-' 1 j- J 1 O'*''’ r.— 12 — — NT — t . / Further the Company shall instruct Geologists to mark carefully and report to the Company any area and its location which appears to them to give promise of yielding minerals or fresh water from a bore hole and the Company undertakes to keep the Shaikh informed of all such minerals and water reports and the sites of the area or areas. ARTICLE 21. The Shaikh hereby agrees that the Company may transfer the obligations and benefits of this Agreement to a British Company to be called “Petroleum Development ( Trucial Coast) Limited” or to any other Company registered within the British Empire. ARTICLE 22. Failure on the part of the Company to fulfil any of the conditions of this Agreement shall not give the Shaikh any claim against the Company or be deemed a breach of this Agreement in so far as such failure arises from force majeure, and if through force majeure the fulfilment by the Company of any of the conditions of this Agreement be delayed the period of such delay shall be added to the periods fixed by this Agreement. Force majeure as used in this Ag reement includes the Act of God, war, insurrection, riot, civil commotion, tide, storm, tidal wave, flood, lightning, explosion, fire, earthquakes and any other happening which the Company could not reasonably prevent or control. ARTICLE 23. The Shaikh shall not by general or special legislation or by administrative measures or by any other act whatever annul this Agreement except as provided in Article 19. No alteration shall be made in the terms of this Agreement by either the Shaikh or the Company except in the event of the Shaikh and the Company jointly agreeing that it is desirable in the interests of both parties to make certain alterations deletions or additions to this Agreement. 'J ^ ^ J j*y O* j &lt;&gt;-Xc#L« j! AJA** J3 l^l pj, J* Aj f j[jb Aj 1 . j* ^ J jJi Aj &gt;1X1 olil j 1 aS^IH jl Jc IjLik A^J lltt) J ^jjJ aJU*MI a. JbUI . jiajj t^® j** . aJ Uoj jA\ A^y.- jjl _ a*J 1^11 ^ui]l *-X^- j' • ^1) £ aJ JaC Tt-JLO b'j l1^1 aJU'MI 0 y~A\ 0JL&gt; fT A* j\*- vl' 1 ^ Jl* iLi A^.9 Ia*N^ j jA aS^ . A^iUNI 0^ Alkali ijd' J 1 • J. _A j ^ 0 ^aIa)I 0 ^ J-aA J a*, j.xl'j o-iJ ojy ] j Aj_!j j . j' ^ jP~\ ^ ' oIII j&gt;- } ' *-*&gt; A»l ic-*- Vi aJU'Vi 0 -i —a ^*1 ji i^y [xa • j y^' ^y S' Aa^bl 03 I—J A^ifr j a^Ui ^ ^ 0-x&gt; ^ I All &gt; W Ml ”4^1)1 -X Jl ^ j 1 jjyb ^1 Aa%l-a-&gt; A^j v^y.^11 . aJIaMI Jl AiUMI J* viiJJ j!o — 13 — — \r — ♦ i &gt; t ARTICLE 24.*“ (a) If at any time during the currency of this Agreement any dif ference or dispute shall arise between the parties hereto concerning the interpretation or execution hereof, or anything herein contained, or in connection herewith, or the rights or liabilities of either party hereunder, the same shall, failing any agreement to settle it in any other way, be referred to two arbitrators, one of whom shall be chosen by each party, and a referee, who shall be chosen by the arbit rators before proceeding to arbitration. Each party shall nominate its own arbitrator within Sixty days after delivery of a request so to do by the other party failing which its arbitrator may at the request of the other party be designated by the British Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. In the event of the arbitrators failing to agree within Sixty days after being chosen or designated the British Political Resident in the Persian Gulf may appoint a referee at the request of the arbitrators or of either of them. (c) The decision of the arbitrators, or in a case of a difference of opinion between them the decision of the referee, shall be final and binding upon both parties. (d) In giving a decision the arbitrators or the referee shall specify an adequate period of delay during which the party against whom the decision is given shall conform to the decision and that party shall be in default only if that party has failed to conform to the decision priorto the expiry of that period and not otherwise. (e) The place of arbitration shall be such as may be agreed by the parties and in default of agreement shall be London. JU’ Jsf' j *! ( 1 ) _ jj•ill! L ^’ l,l&gt; a-Ujl ^ lei o?. y * * * I • • . ? • a) y ^ y j Jli 'il villi u{ lb .j a ‘ ] J* j.j* ^ ^ . j ji r* ot;*— j 3i y cX 02 *!. (v) iy ^ ^11 yi'l y* &lt;i.liy ^-Air -u» '-A* J 6, •Ui &amp;&gt;■ jli viJ-X» ij* j*** ^-LJIjlL ^01 y ^iLl j Jl juyi r iU jli c-- - * * * \- ^ j -^- e ’ ^ju- 3 j' yy o| ((r) j yCu ^ y &gt; y^&gt; xp (^) 3 »-u j! ' s** y y 1 * ni i x*** 3 * y^&gt; vLn.* ^i ^’ 1 y 3 ® J*y j' (^ L,, . Ml r J ;all &lt;-.U 3 4 -' j {* ) . yd 3 3 ^^' l«r — 14 — — M — ARTICLE 25. The Company shall make all payments that become due to the Shaikh under this Agreement into the Shaikhs ac count at the £ast£RN. and the Bank’s receipt shall be a full discharge for the Company in respect to the payment of the sum stated in the Bank’s receipt. Should the Shaikh decide to grant permission for a Bank to open a branch or Agency in Dubai the Shaikh shall consult with the Company as to which Bank shall be given the permission. The Shaikh may from time to time designate in writing another Bank or Banks for the purpose of this Article. ARICLE 26. The Shaikh may select in consuiratjon with the Local Represent ative of the Company a local man - con versant with the English Language - to act as a confidential person as between the Shaikh and the Company’s Representative and to assist in procuring the labour that the Company may require. The salary of the Shaikh’s confidential person so appointed shall be paid by the Company, through the Shaikh in Dubai and shall be at the rate of Rupees Four hundred (400) per month. ARTICLE 27. This Agreement is writ ten in English and translated into Arabic. If there should at any time be disagreement as to the meaning or interpretation of any clause in this Agreement the English iext shall prevail. ^ In witness whereof the parties to this Agreement have set their hands the Ffay and Year first above written AnS (Soft ia (Srariaua THE COMPANY vr A ^ - J) j-* ) *■ .ii oi:i £ 0&gt;ui - -S' ^ • j j^:i uii* jio j - V- j ^ 1 j jJ ^11-^ j' ll j *rtlib .dill ji&gt;N' n.:c j '^^ • ^y*' ^ wI-j (J/'-* 1 _ jjS^LII a*u' ^J*' J‘ juL-&gt; j .O y^.'l n: ’' AS Jyi J&gt;-a 1' j jyvj - ^ ^ ^»sa’ C jt- v. ^V. y (t • •) J® # JL» - j) 1“' J lli 'Sli . y*' 1 J' #A&gt; ^1 J* ol* jl (J*- Tj! ^1 v oU'Sl J*- j'-tsl*:!' J f 1 . Oull Al—'j sJ U*NI Aai U (S) IN THE PRESENCE OF Oil ^ ;C», r^cu^ i) kJ u.0fu*v^ ^ £iu iLu^ Uaaaj ^ ' V *7lwT t -^ IN THE PRESENCE OF siijjumm &gt; ! UC/MM. DECYPHER OF T J, A, J.G R,.A,¥.« (oOPIES CIRCULATED) From Political Resident in the Persian Gulf to Secretary of State for India* / Dated Bahrain, 12th April, 1937c Received 2,45 p.m., 12th April, 1937. XXX T/34, Addressed to Secretary of State for India, copy by post to the Government of Inaia, copy given to Bahrain. Your telegram No. 1140 , April 6th, Previous to receipt of your telegram I had wired for Holmes and the Sheikh of Dibai to meet me here, and Loch and I interviewed them yesterday. 2, With the Company’s concurrence in Sheikh having a London representative, Sheikh stated that he was willing to sign and we endeavoured to get him to sign forthwith. Sheikh replied that he attached importance to doing this at Dibai in the presence of his notables. In spite of much argument he held to this position. I secured from him, however, a promise that he would sign the concession within a fortnight of his return to Dibai whither Sheikh returns in a few days.Draft Paper. ^) &gt; o r z. z. v ^ ) &lt; tjst c. » / ,r^ i c? O / Department. DRAFT TELKGRZ.: /-From S. of S. for I. To Political xigent, Koweit Repeated P.A., Bahrein. IfM^NT. / Addressed Koweit for Resident, repeated Bahrein.' Debai Concession.' Petroleom * &lt; f ' •* Concessions Ltd. state that final S' ^ 'r ' ' agreement with Sheikh now tarns only on question whether Company will recognise ^ ^ ^ ' ** * a London representative of Sheikh.' They ^ ^ S' S' are prepared to write to Sheikh saying S’ ' r '—^ * — that if he sees fit to appoint London S ^ ^ s * y Representative after discovery of oil m commercial quantities such representative will have access to Company for making of —• s' representations on behalf of Sheikh regarding working of concession And for receiving information on all matters ^ S' ^ ' pertaining to oil production and ^ ^ S' / ^ operations generally in Debai/ Holmes ^ S ' s has been instructed accordingly but told to obtain your prior concurrence. ' 2. If Sheikh attaches importance S' ** s' &lt;- to appointment of London representative ^ ^ ^ s and Company are willing to agree, S' ^ s' * ' presumably we need not interfere.' There S' s ^ ^ does not appear to be any objection m principle particularly in view of Koweit S' precedent. ✓ ^ S s' „ 3/ It is increasingly desirable to S’ s S' s s ^ get Debai concession disposed of, and if S S' S’ s s* ^ you agree that we may acquiesce m Company'g/sir OUTWARD COPY AND TRANSLATION OF TELEGRAM from PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LTD. to MAJOR HOLMES - SHARJAH I&gt; matched 5TH APRIL YOUR TELEGRAM MO.I 9 . DRAFT TO RULER SHOULD RUN AS FOLLOWS BRGIMS I AM AUTHORISED TO INFORM YOUR HIGHNESS THAT SHOULD YOUR HIGHNESS SEE FIT TO APPOINT A LONDON REPRESENTATI?E AFTER DISCOVERY OF OIL IN COMMERCIAL QUANTITIES SUCH REPRESENTATIVE WILL HAVE ACCESS TO THE MANAGEMENT OF THE COMPANY AT ANY REASONABLE TIME FOR THE PURPOSE OF MAKING REPRESENTATIONS WHICH YOUR HIGHNESS MAY WISH HIM TO MAKE REGARDING THE WORKING OF THE CONCESSION AND FOR RECEIVING INFORMATION ON ALL MATTERS PERTAINING TO OIL PRODUCTION AND THE COMPANY'S OPERATIONS GENERALLY IN DUBAI. M.DAWTLIO fHQ moi^ sTI jJx. fl .ts.O J P.2. 8832/36. 0 P (g) ^ ^ //, CYPHER TELEGRAM PROM SECRETARY OP STATE FOR INDIA TO POLITICAL RESIDENT, BU3HIRE; REPEATED TO GOVERNMENT OP INDIA, FOREIGN etc POLITICAL DEPARTMENT; POLITICAL AGENT, BAHREIN, DATED 14th DECEMBER 1936. (No.of words: 145,145 &amp; 146) X 3568. Addressed Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, repeated to Government of India and Bahrein. Debai Oil Concession. Draft Political Agreement and Draft Exchange of Notes may now be shown and explained to Sheikh. Please telegraph his acceptance of principles involved. Political Agreement will then be completed here and date telegraphed to you. You can then proceed to exchange of notese provided Commercial Concession is concluded substantially in form of present draft. 2. Sheikh should be told, when signing concession, to state upon it or in separate document that signature is subject to His Majesty’s Government’s approval. This is merely matter of form. 3. Foreign office have suggested with reference to paragraph 3(b) of first draft letter to Sheikh that it may be desirable to secure from him a formal undertaking that hv will be guided by the advice of His Majesty's Government in regard to the exercise of his right of termination. If you think this feasible please endeavour to arrange it with Sheikh. 4. Please note that final drafts of documents are those enclosed with India Office letter dated 2nd December to Foreign Office, etc., copy by air mail of 5th December. They differ verbally from previous versions. Debai should of course be substituted for Qatar in Article 9 of Political Agreement.Gifri P.Z.7856/36. IJ: MEDIATE. INDIA OFFICE, VHITEHALL, 8.’,7. 1. —December 1936. 2^ Sir, I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to refer to the conclusions of the meeting held at the India Office on February 21st 1936 and to subsequent correspondence regarding the negotiations of Petroleum Concessions Limited for oil concessions in the Persian Gulf. 2. As a result of discussions with the Company and consultations with the departments of His Majesty 1 s Government immediately concerned, agreement has been reached on the terms of the undertakings which the Company are prepared tc give to His Majesty’s Government in the event of their securing a concession from the Sheikh of Debai, with whom they are at present negotiating. These terms are embodied in the draft political Agreement ot which a copy is enclosed. Similar Agreements wixl be made in respect of any further concessions which the Company may obtain in the Persian Gulf area. Agreement has also been reached on the terms of an undertaking which the Company are prepared at the same time to give to His Majesty’s Government in respect of the erection of a Refinery in the Persian Gulf: this undertaking is embodied in the draft Refinery Agreement, of which a copy is enclosed. It covers the whole Persian Gulf area and will automatically apply in respect of any &gt; concession in that area which the Company or its subsidiaries may obtain. The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, S. v/. 1. 3./ms-z, a wAsmm 2. 3, The terms of the proposed Commercial Concession hetween the Company (who, it is understood, will deal through a subsidiary Company named Petroleum Development (Trucial Coast) Limited in regard to concessions on the Trucial Coast) and the Sheikh of Debai have been scrutinised in consultation with the departments concerned, and agreement has been reached with the Company on the form in which this Concession can be approved by His Majesty’s Governiment» If the Concession is obtained substantially in this form, it is proposed that notes should be exchanged between the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf and the Sheikh on the lines of the enclosed drafts, which have been drawn up on the basis of the notes exchanged with the Anglc- Iranian Oil Company in respect of the Qatar Oil Concession, and in consultation with the interested departments. At the appropriate stage complementary notes would be exchanged with the Company whereby the latter would accept the arrangements detailed in the first draft note to the Sheikh. 4. I am to enquire whether the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs concurs in the action proposed in paragraph 3 above, and in the signature of the Debai Political Agreement and of the Refinery Agreement by one of the Urd er-Secretaries of State at the India Office, on behalf of His Majesty’s Government, in accordance with the procedure previously adopted in similar cases. 5. A similar letter is being sent to the Admiralty m i»ves JOactM eiN/r and Briard and a copy to the Air Ministry* I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant,between HU MAKTUM AL-H powers as RU behalf and o of his heirs shall be ve responsiblity of the State “ The Shaikh ” Concessions Lit Great Britain its successc called “The ( ARTIC1 Agreement a “Ihe State” ) all Islands a ing thereto, included in (b) from workii into the are Hatta A1 J Shaikh gran do so. ( c ) surveyed by granted by Airways for and all cone excluded for ARTIC Agreement Calendar ye The ej used in this is consiste Calendar an weights me be reckonedThis is an Agreement made at on the day of 1936, corresponding to the day of 1355 between HIS EXCELLENCY SHAIKH SAID BIN MAKTUM AL-HASHER in the exercise of his powers as RULER OF DUBAI, ARABIA, on his own behalf and on behalf of and in the name of his hairs and successors in whom is or shall be vested for the time being the responsiblity for the control and Government of the State of Dubai ( hereinafter called “The Shaikh”) of the one part and Petroleum Concessions Limited, a Company registered in Great Britain under tha Companies Act, 1929, its successors and assigns ( hereinafter called “The Company” ) of the second part. ARTICLE 1. (a) The area to which this Agreement applies (hereinafter referred to as “Ihe Mate”) is the State of Dubai, including all Islands and Territorial Waters appertain ing thereto, and being all that Territory included in the Shaikhdom of Dubai. ( b) But the Company shall refrain from working or entering for the present into the area upon which the town named Hatta A1 Jabaliyah is located until the Shaikh grants the Company permission to do so. J OJUp 1 •ifj J .. \ VT^ « -&gt;/&gt; Vf 'J/// !) VJ t* Mm w/&gt; (TY/y '4LJI jL&gt;- J I ^ ;L.H ) ^J iafll’i o' OS^-lH jy\S ^9 l|JI ) [fA^A pfl) JA : 3'.} f j' (' ) — JL*&gt; ^5 ^*^0 j ) O*- \a&gt; III! •LHj £2*73 ejU' i 1 j' J'*' O*’ ^ ■) ( V ) aA*?' AjLuII O^' (J — rtOH txI C (j! . dUi&gt; ijiNi (c) The Area in the Dubai Khor surveyed by Imperial Airways Limited and granted by the Shaikh to the Imperial Airways for their commercial Air Liners and all concerned with that area is entirely excluded for the purposes of this Agreement. ARTICLE 2. The period of this Agreement shall be seventyfive (75) Solar Calendar years from the date of signature. The expression year, month and day used in this Agreement shall mean what is consistent with the English Solar Calendar and not any other. Further, the weights mentioned in this Agreement shall be reckoned on the English Ten of 2,240 lbs. J\j j oKJI iikil o' ( (7 ) \^A J O jr\*N'o''f^**'**'* ^Dl ^JDI ^Lk^.) Aalaill Oll:&gt; 3 Aj _ aJ lill olll . If JO ^ jl&gt; Al*» ( J &lt; ^ {j j o'j J. L a*sUiL' 0^ (jc- ^^9j . ^.**-.'1 &gt;- j\2*i A-jLi'ii' ^ • J cO . rtt • 0 yito the Com search for gas asphal their pro (hereinafte within the of all the the right within ant and to ex dispose of import es transport country c cretion ai necessary at ions. ART] Zone is ci the State, co-equal hereby ag oil conces terms to the Comp! Neutral Z&lt; ART rights gr Agreemen Shaikh (a) Rupees 6( (b) thousand days fron pany decl substance mercial q fail to de discovery quantities Company or wells t with first two thous substance (30) const— 2 ARTICLE 3. The Shaikh hereby grants to the Company the exclusive right to explore search for drill for produce and win natural gas asphalt ozokerite crude petroleum and their products and cognate substances (hereinafter referred to as “The Subitances”) within the State, the exclusive ownership of all the Substances so produced and won, the right to refine transport sell for use within and without the State or for export and to export or otherwise deal with or dispose of the Substances, and the right to import export pump ship or otherwise transport the Substances across or to any country or place at the Company’s dis cretion and the right to do all things necessary for the purpose of these oper ations. ARTICLE 4. If hereafter any neutral Zone is created adjacent to the territory of the State, wherein the Shaikh shall have a co-equal and joint interest, the Shaikh hereby agrees to grant to the Company an oil concession over such neutral zone on terms to be agreed between the Shaikh, the Company, and the joint ruler of such Neutral Zone. ARTICLE 5. In consideration of the rights granted by the Shaikh by this Agreement the Company shall pay to the Shaikh (a) on signature of the Agreement Rupees 60,000 ( Sixty Thousand ) (b) Rupees 200,000 ( Two hundred thousand ) within a period of sixty ( 60) days from the date upon which the Com pany declares in writing to the Shaikh that substances have been discovered in com mercial quantities. If the Company should fail to declare so sooner, then the date of discovery of substances in commercial quantities shall be that date upon which the Company has completed and tested a well or wells capable of producing in accordance with first class oil practice not less than two thousand ( 2000 ) English Tons of clean substances per day for a period of thirty (30) consecutive days. .1 J \ A \ j~.3.&gt;*.-.» Li&gt;- li ( Ig.* IjJ! jlJLil ) j if&gt;- 3 ^ yyi • - ^ I I ^ j' OLiUlj ^^1 4$'y‘4 J* &lt;S ^ . r-A) jj LJ JjUI J ^Li3l lil - mJl oil! J^-11) jj,/T aA a^?^L 3^ A_31a'^! A_5^J\j JJaIi Aflk:U »JA *JkA&gt; lb U • Aikll j * A&gt;-A-*^«li“l o^lll . '^iJ\ aJUVI ijj j • • aJUVI Jp ^&gt;3' (I) • A-j jj ill C—*j j j »—os*. ( ^ oj ^ * * / * * *) (v) aJ JLj j- Lj» (jp* joli; ^1^11 o' Aj^y' f~ jl&gt;' 0^® AJb^^ 0^' &lt;-jj+a3 l-ilj ^ib ^jb\ ^ Aiji^ ^ 31 ! jll jl jO Aj A-? *—'j^' Aj»-jaSl r-bVI U-&gt;- ^ o- ^ ^ ( r * -) • aJ\ 1^1* Lj» ('f' *) A*aJ13 — C&lt;M* tifo CiiJ j)M+ / ^L^Jxlx^ uttu* (pM ^rj /»u £*^&lt; ^ ijuJt J} fa tMlto** , k iskd** ( c) Rupees 25,000 (Twenty five thousand ) at the end of each year from the date of signature hereof until the Company declares in writing to the Shaikh that Substances have been discovered in commercial quantities in accordance with the Sub-Clause (b) of this Article 5** (d) At the end of ppefy aubseqtfent year from the date that the Company makes in writing to the Shaikh the declaration that the Substances have been discovered in commercial quantities Rupees Eighty Thousand ( 80,000 ) or Rupees Three ( 3 ) per English Ton of 2,240 lbs, in respect of the Subslanc'es^ won^ ana ^saved during the preceding Calendar year, whichever is greater^ fx* 4 , 66 * cuUt. fuJr Q In calculating royalty for the purpose of this article account shall not be taken of any of the substances used by the Com pany in its operations or used by the Com pany’s employees within the State, necessary for their use, nor of any water or foreign matter which may be produced with the Substances. ARTICLE 6. The Company shall not carry on any operations within areas occu pied by or devoted to the purposes of mosques, sacred buildings or graveyards. ARTICLE 7. The Company shall conduct its operations in a workmanlike manner and by appropriate scientific me thods and shall take all reasonable measures to prevent the ingress of water to any petroleum - bearing strata and shall duly close any unproductive holes drilled by it and subsequently abandoned. The Company shall keep the Shaikh informed generally as to the progress and result of its drilling operations but such information shall be treated as confidential. ^1 * * ( £) •-U Jf j*-' J ( V. (jl &lt;1 \~jX 4^ ytJI jOliH ^ til -oUl a. (v ) Syil 1 cJ ( ^ ) ^ J* ** ) p\*ai jolac Jp (r ) Cj' jl v_&lt;)l &lt;jyU j\ j* l/J tti* j&gt; ij* a« l—JI J j . ji.ii ^J-\J oil O Jjb J -il) -Xiij Uli'l ^ Ll ^ jj ojLVI j\ • ^1^11 ^ jl Jjjsldl . jsIjIIj L-Juil ^ — Lu 1— O'juL 4a*L&gt; L1 alii j A9 ~ C-** o'J -^ A *' ci' L&gt;*J'&gt; j jaL\ \a\c &lt;*•+&gt;' ^r^ 1 ' 4 jmMj \» j! ol* jlai' j ARTICLE 8. Within three months after the expiry of each calendar year, the Company shall deliver to the Shaikh a statement of the amount of the Substances won and saved during the said calendar year, and of the royalty which is or might ju J}U j Li _ obi olil l&gt; L»&gt; ^ •I.aAj I 4a-**AJI C-.)l I ^jC-)have been with a re] said year, shall have and stater statement! operations by the Sh ART have the stances, and lorrie utensils, i supplies, i equipment materials, nature re employees hereunder articles p free of ci or other personal ] chandise i personal 1 to them t time bei in Article the Comp income, f Substance the peric present c duties, e charges c tolls and nature. In c granted to the R three as Shaikh w close of i (4) four £ in respec during tlhave been payable under Article 5, together with a report of its operations during the said year. The Shaikh or his representative shall have the right to check such returns and statements, and all such returns and statements and the reports of the Company’s operations shall be treated as confidential by the Shaikh ARTICLE 9. (a) The Company shall have the right to import water, the Sub stances, fuel, machinery, motor-cars and lorries,aircraft, equipment, plant, timber, utensils, iron work, building materials, food supplies, medicines, medical supplies, office equipment and household furniture, and other materials, equipment and goods of whatsoever nature required by the Company and its employees for the purpose of its operations hereunder and to export the Substances and articles previously imported by the Company free of customs or export duty and taxes or other charges, but it shall pay on all personal goods, clothing and general mer chandise imported by the Company for the personal use of its employees or for resale to them the ordinary duty in force for the time being in the State. Saving as in Article 5 and in this Article provided, the Company, its personnel, its operations, income, profits and property including the Substances shall be exempt and free during the period of this Agreement from all present or future harbour duties, import duties, export duties, taxes, imposts and charges of any kind whether State or local, tolls and land surface rent of whatever nature. In consideration of the right herein granted the Company shall pay in addition to the Royalty per ton of Rupees ( 3 ) three as provided in Article 5 - to the Shaikh within ( 3) three months after ths close of each calender year the sum of (4) four annas per English ton of 2,240 lbs. in respect of the Substances won and saved during the said calendar year. 11UI Jf yC* OU j Oij j jOli .4) jf oU! k_-»L!L&gt;- s y^ j j j ONill Jl ^^11 j'JL-al) y oUrNI ^11 11'il j y} j U^l jwl J^^l! Ol ^\c.^! I y*iJI y*yy^ ^ l-a? y^y** cHJ-5 y 4» j ijUN! j JH 40 UI 4.»-y) \a y ^ l„.ll lllj^l y [f+ApyAy ^j»L\) jU *3 [.J* I * JlA y&amp;*A 4*.Aaa J yC^ ^a J y^y^* JU I^*'1 y y 4 A *y\.&gt;. 4 a) ^ I dJ»L~Ujl 4 ^) ill jllj % % I * ' * — ^^jNl Jy*-^ pi jy^ -k^yC-^ 4^W • d u* fiiJC lib'll ©ij- ^.il jll J» \aa dl jjf 1^*5 JL) ^)| u*l ^*)l O^b J Q.^.15 ^jyW^A -&gt;■ jjl® 1 ' ^ yj 4) (r) • l^aA)l Jl*) jf-ll 4j^l) ^_5 — 4-u.lil ©5 II ©j^^-lj 4&gt;«.IlLI il^11 TTt • OJf . lyfjtt 4i-.)l J^l&gt;- (J— • — (b) The importation by the Company of firearms and other weapons is prohibited, except with the written permission of the Shaikh. ( c ) The Company may import such alcoholic drink and liquors as the Company may require for the use of their foreign ployees but only with the written peTmission but the Company shall not sell or give alcoholic drinks or liquors to the Subjects of the Shaikh or to the Subjects of adjoining Rulers who may be employed within the State. ARTICLE 10. The employees of the Company shall be allowed to enter into and to leave the State at all times without let or hindrance and free of all charge, and the Shaikh shall grant to the Company's employees every facility required for the purpose of the Company’s operations hereunder. But the Company’s employees shall not interfere or by their actions cause any disturbance or cause opposition to the Shaikh’s authority within the State of Dubai and the employees shall not go beyond the limit of their duties when employed within or when leaving the confines of the State of Dubai for the purpose of this Agreement. Further in the event of any of the Company’s employees - whether he be a senior or a junior employee-committing an offence which may cause disorder, or interfere with the religious or moral laws or interfere with the politics or Subjects of the State of Dubai or excite them to sedition, then the Shaikh may ^request the Local ncprc&amp;CTitative th»—Gompan^ to send the person concerned-if a foreigner- out of the State of Dubai, but if a Subject of the Shaikh then the Shaikh may arrest the culprit and deal with him according to the laws of the State of Dubai. jHBirtr trj! agreed by the Shaikh and tha Company that before ordering .deportation of any foreign eniph&gt;yei3 that the charge is fully wdoped -by-the Straikh'€e»44he ■Goffipanyjj I \p\ W-NI 3 !joJ ( v ) . ^yJL)| 1:$^ ( VI \b ft* j yjtVi ^i ^ ) Jl.**!**V ^ai'l s_A j j jil VI jjC v dte jCJj 11 xf./iU ji Ml _ ^ ^ 1 j 1 j ji j' ..^i ^ji ^11 iWj ji i&gt;j • 0 jVVl ^ yA 4Tyjjl wl _ 0 oil_ll ^\a jji ojUVi y ^yi iy&gt;--L ji » . * jl j J ijA ^.Aaa J 1^ jl . U \h VI -Lr Jl\ jl V 4.1*1—I 4^ijU4 jl 45^111 J jLcJj 0 jLI j»ji^ 0 .^ 4 ! \p~&gt;- 4-3LnVI 0 JA Ji* ^V ojLVI J.»-l l^l I- 4 j Us _ 1 ji i jjf' y y ~ *s^\ 4 ^.)jii ji 0^1 yi ijtl Icj .}! ®4-»l—5 y&gt;-_jl 4« ^Vl j\ ^jl (3^; jl z 4 ! ^-iii—^oi y^i 'jt^ ijUl — ^Vl (J tlr’V* jjA-ill ^ I 4_S'^w\3 4 Jp ^ 3 *-^! (3'* 4-^—V y* l ^P‘\ \~i)e&gt;y ^1 ^l^&gt;l J /VI iUil J-i Cl4 4^J\ 3 45^U\j j^-'t6 ARTICLE 11. (a) For the purpose ■* of its operations hereunder the Company shall have the right without hindrance to construct, maintain and operate power stations, refineries, pipelines and storage tanks, facilities for water supply including •- boring for water, telegraph and telephone lines and installations and wireless instal lations, roads, railways, tramways, buildings, ports, harbours, harbour works, aircraft, , buildings and landing places for aircraft, ■ wharves and jetties, oil and coaling stations, with such lighting as may be requisite and : any other facilities or works which the Company may consider necessary and for such purposes to use free of all payments any stone, sand, gravel, gypsum, lime, clay or similar, materials or water which may be available provided always that the in habitants of the State are not prevented from taking their usual requirements of these materials and that the water supply of the local inhabitants and nomad population who may be dependent on the same is not endangered. The Company at its discretion may select the position of any such works. The Company may likewise install and operate without hindrance all such means of transportation by land, air and water as may be necessary for the effective conduct of its operations hereunder provided it is for the purposes of this j Agreement. (b) The Company shall under normal conditions accept and transmit free of charge on its wireless and telegraph in- l stallations such of the Shaikh’s messages as will not interfere with the Company’s business, and in times of national emergency the Shaikh shall have the necessary use free of charge of the Company’s wireless and telegraph installations and railways for governmental purposes. I (I ) _ eft^ll^ Jklij .iiiUj tjLi: j! ^ op ^ V.) ^La&gt;- jy J a jl) y J' 6^ o'J jl&gt; I ji*- Oil At Jb ^ jb-&gt;- j O- ^ j jtlj j ol jLL)I ijjy A) jj UjCaT Jl^l ^ 0^0)1 Ull *.aa o* V* ^ &amp; o* A)liUjl J jO) j p.|«l&gt;-l&gt;* »A&gt;-I ^ j' Lcl^ 5j*y* (O*^a Aj ^U!l j)\ *lU J'^VI .-u Jd jC- ^ , ft Iy. Ja:)I ^ j'Xj jl IU&gt;'l&gt; JLaII ^LaII dU^ ^ dli^ j^yjl ^ ) AA?ik) i AixJii jl i jUI ji^ni j (v) ol ykll j AiJLjU I lli&gt;* Jc- Ji :.’j JJt “A$^d)i,Ji;/i j)i £~p\ Jdj y&gt;U,lla£ j 1 Olsj! ol^khllj^OlA-jl'l AS^dl'O Ul* . A+a yK&gt;- (^^1 AjJL&gt;JLi“l dJ^**JI^ ( c )' right to u by the Cc no way hi in any wi of which { judge. An structed 1 exclusive 5 the purpc along th Company with the right to c( anchorag( coast of 1 them for boats. AM the rigb facilities. w into the ! by pipe li of operat pany ma; and by pipe 1: the State tory to a or shippi And of any r in respec AM have fret occupatio uncultiva the Comj its opera shall hav areas of exclusive drilling i storage, facilities the Comi may bu(c) The Shaikh’s ships shall have the right to use harbours utilised or constructed by the Company provided that such use in no way hampers the Company or interferes in any way with the safety of its operations of which the Company shall be the sole judge. Any wharves or appurtenances con structed by the Company shall be for its exclusive use. The Company may use for the purpose of its operations the harbours along the coast of the State, but the Company shall not impede or interfere with the subjects of the Shaikh or their right to continue the use of existing harbours, anchorages, wharves and docks along the coast of the State at present utilised by them for their sailing craft and fishing boats. ARTICLE 12. The Company shall have the right and be given the necessary facilities. (a) for the import of the Substances into the State from any adjoining territory by pipe lines or otherwise for the purpose of operating any refinery which the Com pany may decide to erect within the State, and (b) for the transport of the Substances by pipe lines or otherwise over and across the State from and to any adjoining terri tory to any point suitable for the refining or shipping of the Substances. And no duties, taxes, charges or dues of any nature whatsoever shall be levied in respect of such import or transport. ARTICLE 13. (a) The Company shall have free of cost the unrestricted use and occupation of and surface rights over all uncultivated lands of the State which the Company may need for the purpose of its operations and in particular the Company shall have the right to select an area or areas of land chosen by the Company with exclusive surface rights upon which to erect drilling rigs, pump-stations, oil - refineries, storage, terminal, shipping and aircraft facilities and any other works required for the Company’s operations; and the Company may buy or lease for such purposes ,jl -L» ^ I^IaAIaa.) ^11 aa ,1 4) \i ^ I u I^aa.?- ULp! A^AaJ UUM ^ % A AAA*) i jl J* j' dyr j Zc\^ I jJA y^U-l ^11 j . JL-a)! &lt;—&gt; y* ^^.1 o 1*11 ol_JJ • ^ JJO^L^aaIH ijy'^ j j0\) v iyy\ ji j^ii (i) . *jL»ni ^**0 ~zyj\ j jA&gt; ^ j&gt; yy jl ^X) liNI JiJ (&lt;--&gt;) 4)ji^ ^i ji jj ^ y u j\cj ojUMi jy . y ^iyi aLaiJj ©jU^) j'-X) ly:-J^a^-Nj » » OlJyAlIljOSj’yi jp £__y ^ jJJ U U (I) ^ ^ ^ IDI “.Mil ^a^- rclaA* Jc. -Xa 1 ' JlAi^lj JI^Ia. 1 J^li)! W! jH • J Ujii^ w ^y^ y* ^i^-'i 4aJ 1 JI I I lf&gt;JaA* J^ jikil J^l 1^ 'j&gt;xy}\2 jio y j jK.l) J^Iaaj OLiL)) OlL^ j (JU-Ma, I j j 1 I j 1 ) j Ja.D O^L^a~5 j &lt;Sf'~ S j' Z y^)l J'&lt;^! if-ikl' y 1 ^ V j’ry' j'(b) ' such land necessary Agreemen the Shaik] houses an occupy foi and buildi Company longer nei returned free of cc ART have the market r&lt; construct! of every ations hei ' (b Subjects possible f suited un pany’s si supply of the Compi Company labour, pi from neic obey the also have technical pay to th such wag Company engaged. Furl employim in any wa employee eges and and sucl: ways - sul laws and Shaikh in State ofany lands, houses or buildings with the consent of and on conditions to be arranged with the proprietors thereof, but the terms of such purchase or lease shall not be in excess of those ordinarily current in their respective localities. (b) The Company shall acquire only such lands, houses and buildings as are necessary for its operations under this Agreement. The Company shall inform the Shaikh from time to time of the land, houses and buildings which it requires to occupy for its operations; and land, houses and buildings previously acquired by the Company from the Shaikh but found no longer necessary for its operations shall be returned by the Company to the Shaikh free of cost. ARTICLE 14. (a) The Company shall have the right to purchase at current market rates fuel, water, food, building and constructional materials and other supplies of every kind in connection with its oper ations hereunder. ( b ) The Company shall employ Subjects of the Shaikh as far as possible for all work for which they are suited under the supervision of the Com pany’s skilled employees, but if the local supply of labour should in the judgment of the Company be inadequate or unsuitable the Company shall have the right to import labour, preference being given to labourers from neighbouring Arab countries who will obey the local laws. The Company shall also have the right to import skilled and technical employees. The Company shall pay to the workmen it employs a fair wage, such wage to be decided and stated by the Company at the time the workmen are engaged. Further, the fact of the Company employing Subjects of the Shaikh shall not in any way whatever-alter the Status of such employees in respect of their rights, privil eges and duties as Subjects of the Shaikh, and such employees will remain - in all ways - subject to the jurisdiction of the laws and under the legal authority of the Shaikh in his capacity as the Ruler of the State of Dubai. — A — » » » t, ; u -1* J ^£0 ,1 Ol) I CAc^Jl .i* Ji. 9 j' ^ 0 *.^ (v) A) j:)! a*xj N ^ j j c J' j.J\ {Jl\^ t^ikr a -A&gt;- j ^ ^ ^ aS**^*-*!! UA^r^«-.)l Aj jj jJJ aS^.115 of (0 - ^ 1 J' r uyij m * * .aJIa^J! AS^C-Ajl^^y ja ji a^ yj\ Jp (^) JU^Nl ^ir jl^»Nl j-X9 ^Jp ^Ul iWj j^lil ^ i—^PAff^jJI j’ jll j Jl&lt;,»llw*l^jl ^jS'j o^*11 jljUl jr* p-r. &lt;J$l . AaI^. 1 ^1 yjJI j^n^L) j-* j^ cl ^*^1 Ojfj • U -XIp 1^1*^j U y r jl ^JLH lieJ A_^»tH jJ-tscl—1 jli *VjA A.i^ Jjl \^a AlW A^l (_j — 1 —^ ^ lie f j ^*1IjLi^'j &lt;jK lc|* jf- —j^-V1 £*: J - W AZ'r^aj O^iUS\ y*- V ‘jj&gt; SjLVproperty theft, hie damage ar appoint i and itself ] all times the Shaik protecting and its en at its o\* the accon places as ART stances f&lt; for conv weight s determim Shaikh an of oil ant gravity. The ( ces by a technical represent have the and to e: ces may represent sary and of fire ai all exam: in such m interfere If upon such app order thi be put ii a reason examinat9 - ARTICLE 15. The Shaikh shall give to the Company and its employees and property all protection in his power from theft, highway robbery, assault, wilful damage and destruction,and the Company may appoint in consultation with the Shaikh and itself pay trustworthy guards who shall at all times be subjects of the Shaikh unless the Shaikh permits otherwise to assist in protecting the property of the Company and its employees. The Company shall erect at its own expense suitable buildings for the accommodation of such guards at such places as the Company shall decide. ARTICLE 16. In measuring the Sub stances for purposes of royalty the factor for conversion of the volume of oil into weight shall be such figure as may be determined and agreed upon between the Shaikh and the Company after the discovery of oil and the ascertainment of its specific gravity. The Company shall measure the Substan ces by a method customarily used in good technical practice and the Shaikh by his representative duly authorised by him shall have the right to observe such measuring and to examine and test whatever applian ces may be used for such measuring. Such representative shall comply with all neces sary and usual safeguards for the prevention of fire and other accident; and shall make all examinations and tests at such times and in such manner as will cause the minimum of interference with the company’s operations. If upon such examination or testing any such appliance shall be found to be out of order the Company will cause the same to be put in order at its own expense within a reasonable time, and if upon any such examination aforesaid any error shall be A* !! J JVl)lOli ! if'/Jl Jill • • I . j'Jo j)*-\ If—ik ^ j CX ^-4 UU ^ y . 4^ .■XX ^!l ^(j »1 y* Jjk ^ J 1 t—I Jl*) )lj £•-*—]I fjy A-lc- ^1^11 j* j lolc ll Ai^kJL Lc*j Aj J-U-4 OM &lt;j 1 j l-kb l-X (b J lj—&amp;• ci (J-**—J •A;iL-.*l\ Aj13jSI ”' C j*wJL j j&gt;-\ &lt;TiU- &lt;cl -j\ jUi ^U. Aj j j j-kMj oVLM Jj OlajVI J v^l'UcL.VI j . jui j ,&gt; jJi ^ ^ u jii j!\ -til’ll*, o' ij jif ■ A '' p • ifc ^discovered error shal hearing 1 considered dar Month of or from same in c such peric the Royalt If the Con alter, re] appliances to the Shi able a re] present di replaceme The correct r aforesaid Shaikh sh times to liberty to records s the Shaik! ART have the of three of this A months' to termi Agreemei the date such noti (b) than 30 ^ ture the determine and dutie rial and that for i receipt oj purchase a price e that date be agree under Ar— 10 — —V discovered in any such appliance, such error shall - if .the Shaikh so decides after hearing the Company’s explanation - be considered to have existed for Three(3)Caldn- dar Months previous to the discovery there of or from the last occasion of examining the same in case such occasion shall be within such period of Three calendar Months and the Royalty shall be adjusted accordingly. If the Company should find it necessary to alter, repair or replace any measuring appliances it shall give reasonable notice to the Shaikh or his representative to en able a representative of the Shaikh to be present during such alteration, repair or replacement. The Company shall keep full and correct records of all measurements as aforesaid and the said representative of the Shaikh shall have access at all reasonable times to such records and shall be at liberty to make extracts from them. Such records shall be treated as confidential by the Shaikh and his representative. ARTICLE 17. (a) The Company shall have the right at any time after the expiry of three years from the date of signature of this Agreement to give the Shaikh six months’ notice in writing of its intention to terminate this Agreement and this Agreement shall absolutely determine on the date fixed for such termination in such notice. (b) If such notice be given not later than 30 years after the date of such signa ture the Company shall be entitled on such determination to remove free of all taxes and duties all plant buildings stores mate, rial and property of every sort provided that for a period of three months from the receipt of such notice the Shaikh may purchase - should he so desire - the same at a price equal to the replacement value at that date less deprciation which price shall be agreed or failing agreement settled under Article 24 hereof. 1^1 -Up Ij &gt;• aJ'^I Ul jjUM IJub Jl* a! I ,j jp-j &lt;LjA&gt;- A)'^' \ Jjk) J* I A) (r) -L. j li-Ui a) 1^9 j&gt;-\ Txj jlrA*—X* Aj a! ! a»J JjlL-j *aj aJ n-ir 1;%! li ^*04)1 v— jN I ^** 1 !! Jilp 1 of&gt; o' O' w ^ J \ ' Ajui' OUUi' ^a-2^- ^jC- A*l» Oli L) 0 ^' -ti' »^Ap' A) a! LJI • j&gt; o' A^lil'olsjN' Aj OC j O-i&gt;-' ^ . A) j ( I ) ^ Ul lalll yZ\\ O'* O' jjj* -L»» JL-ij aj o*^** o' a*&gt;iaN! A*iljli N ■ j Aa® Iji *JLA J via)' ^P -X*) O^p 4 ^' '-t» lii- jjil! »i' ^ UU O^p^' 'o&gt; J*&gt;* O' '^' (‘-r*) OW 0 ^ ^ Jj'?*' 1 J 3^' o' iSy* ^oip ji' 03'i'j ^ rl &gt; A l i»l|P y 0^ j 0 ^ c ^' A)^t aO* tfilk ^/.O jl _ vOb jv-^ J '3'^.qO)1 Ac- Ik:-' a*0^jO'* 'j&gt;j w*;—&gt; 0 ^ u A '•* O'* o^^ ^ s ^'j o' 0 ^^ O'* 0-0'“*''^ ^' J' . aOU'N’ »Ji&gt;(c) I 30 years i all the pn property o art: Agreemen Seventy-fi any exten the moval Company over to tl wells or expiry sh good orde ART of Article the right to take w the Compi (a) 1 any of the ment witl they fall (b) ' in respect Article 2^ ART ment she way the r parties co other thai tide 3 pro of the Co: injurioush If tl sequent Agreemer cessions ( undertake tain provi to abstai interferim interests Depi silver, c salt or tl by the C Shaikh e Company or permi11 — \s — (c) If such notice be given later than 30 years after the date of such signature all the property aforesaid shall become the property of the Shaikh free of all cost. ARTICLE 18. On the expiry of this Agreement at the end of the period of Seventy-five Years provided in Article 2 or any extension or renewal of that period all the movable and immovable property of the Company in the State shall be handed over to the Shaikh free of cost. Producing wells or borings at the time of such expiry shall be handed over in reasonably good order and repair. ARTICLE 19. Subject to the provisions of Article 22 hereof the Shaikh shall have the right to terminate this Agreement and to take without payment all the property of the Company in the State if (a) The Company shall fail to make any of the payments prescribed in this Agree ment within 6 months of the date on which they fall due, or (b) The Company shall be in default in respect of an arbitration award under Article 24 hereof. ARTICLE 20. Nothing in this Agree ment shall be read as restricting in any way the right of the Shaikh to grant to other parties concessions or permits for materials other than the Substances as defined in Ar ticle 3 provided that the operations and rights of the Company hereunder are not thereby injuriously affected. If the Shaikh should at any date sub sequent to the date of signature of this Agreement grant to any other parties con cessions or permits as aforesaid the Shaikh undertakes that such concessions shall con tain provisions requiring the holders thereof to abstain from damaging, impeding or interfering with the property, operations and interests of the Company. Deposits of minerals such as gold, silver, copper, lead, potash, sulphur and salt or the like which may be discovered by the Company shall be reported to the Shaikh and shall not be worked by the Company except under special concession or permit from the Shaikh. (jA&gt;% JJ ^ ^ -.jfM olSOr.!! . U* C*J I JUc 4-' ^ 8.2li! - ► v 41^. j i-L* j»-l ci * » m * » -1 -Is -1*5 ^ 4-i Ijl •2l_H 4)^fllll j\* I j 4]^4ll! OtSCLll/ (jli ejCI j'Lai-^ j jli L*l la« &gt;1 *1^' 21*-* -Uc- 1^* *—5.) • ^**11 4i-l*^j 4—«LL* »JL&gt;- 4)1^ 1—1.9 4-9lai‘^ll » ' . ,&gt;• 4j I — 4*-» ll)l e2li' 4»9Ut’ S ill aJ.A &lt;J 1-1! «2l_il - » _ _ n . . * ^*92 1 jj2-\_&gt;-l&gt; 4-9lai' ^ ( I ) I 2 ) j X^ .J. jllll 4*92 J\ ftbl jz 4^1)10^9 jl&gt;* ^jA 4I-# 4-9iaN^ ©Jjfc ^)l j^L)\ 1 12^ ( l —») j' Ol*9jJ^ oAA Jjla**!-.! . 4-9Ui ^i oA* 4*5 I jl ^a JA*-.) * j ' 4i l&gt; A-a) U j' t&gt;l» o' j*-\ j' (J y 9 - 4!)Ut!82li'^S2Jb^' 2 '^1' fj&gt; ftL—^L ^ jl^ai jl 45^1'! 3} Ap ~J J ^ (j' -kj***! Tt.:* ' 2 ' j \j*'*a 1 yM 1' 4-9 U; Mi *Aa ^ o^Ia—.1! 4-9U&gt; ^'a /ft-9^1 ' A*) *J5 2^Aai j' O'jl-*-*' j*-\ y[j* ^ O'jloM' aAA jli Af*l&gt; ji ~^9 jZ-y\ i^*—S (j' ^ . O^JJI j' J'^i ji t)%\ j 4 -aia!l j A Ali^ jMi^js^^Al!^-' A*!^'^!! jl ^J«.*)Mjrt--—^ii Uj*' *1-1 4^^—)t 1|4—A9 e:~ 6 y l^' s 3 I 0 I 1 M'l S m • »^ ^ Furtl Geologists the Comp which app yielding m bore-hole , keep the minerals &lt; of the are ** ART] agrees tha obligations to a Britisl Developim other Con Empire. ART the Comp: of this ^ Shaikh ar deemed a far as s majeure, ; fulfilment conditions the period the period Fore reement insurrectn storm, tid fire, eartt which the prevent o * ART by genera administr: act whate as providi No a terms of Shaikh o of the ! agreeing of both p; deletions— 12 — — NY — Further the Company shall instruct Geologists to mark carefully and report to the Company any area and its location which appears to them to give promise of yielding minerals or fresh water from a bore-hole and the Company undertakes to keep the Shaikh informed of all such minerals and water reports and the sites of the area or areas. ARTICLE 21. The Shaikh hereby agrees that the Company may transfer the obligations and benefits of this Agreement to a British Company to be called “Petroleum Development ( Dubai) Limited ” or to any other Company registered within the British Empire. ARTICLE 22. Failure on the part of the Company to fulfil any of the conditions of this Agreement shall not give the Shaikh any claim against the Company or be deemed a breach of this Agreement in so far as such failure arises from force majeure, and if through force majeure the fulfilment by the Company of any of the conditions of this Agreement be delayed the period of such delay shall be added to the periods fixed by this Agreement. Force majeure as used in this Ag reement includes the Act of God, war, insurrection, riot, civil commotion, tide, storm, tidal wave, flood, lightning, explosion, fire, earthquakes and any other happening which the Company could not reasonably prevent or control. ARTICLE 23. The Shaikh shall not by general or special legislation or by administrative measures or by any other act whatever annul this Agreement except as provided in Article 19. No alteration shall be made in the terms of this Agreement by either the Shaikh or the Company except in the event of the Shaikh and the Company jointly agreeing that it is desirable in the interests of both parties to make certain alterations deletions or additions to this Agreement. 4) I ^' yT; &gt;X9 jc. j* /.II J/j 'J* 9 - . ^UJI ^ 4*iJ! y — ^ 4) ^ii-1 a^ill 4-j ILai y 4 : jUNI . &amp; aijJl^.' 4-3y 4 ^. &lt;/ \V . 4 J Ik) yvH 4^y*l'l yv-ajJi* (jl _ 4*5 lill olll jkl aJlA kj^L a)I j\~*&gt; y * ^ /k'l 4 J ikj; a ly9 -JA j\*a.Al}} 4*f lib * . j9- 1) (j' • ^k)l a^4l! a-N^ {j A ^4^.9a-X® kj-X&gt;-1 4^ . iksUrNl a-X^« 41**11 ;^=-X -X^4) j ^9^14.'!^ 41:4)1 j ■k9U) , ^l JxU ^ 9*} -Xl^ ^ d J y&gt;- 4)J j jkJlj ^.*18 olll j&gt;-\ 44; ,L 4)1 ^ y k*-&gt;&gt;- 4*9U)'il^ a-X* ^J*!) k'' ^ y* X jy^r 4»*»L.'I a^l—ll ^ 4^1^. y ^-*^1)1^**^ 4*9 li) ^ a-XA kj {j* 4&gt;IJc Im lil VI '&lt;&amp;jZW ^-X^l lyi y y)l 4?eLal 4-9 . 4*jU)'VI a_Ajt ^1 49UVI jl O-ikl j\ft {Ucd* (M XA /| ^ JfL /Vw ^ 1 lAu/fo* A huptcUli frfc- ^ tiuA htf A ^ {aJjU /I ^&lt;uf U(Ot*£^ Suk /L+ “O JytUrtUl?' K C&lt;M*Jl&lt;l*' A/ ) “* \ Hajd' f*U\ }«*h'&lt;A &lt; Jjt^ ARTICLE 24. (a) If at any time during the currency of this Agreement any dif ference or dispute shall arise between the parties hereto concerning the interpretation or execution hereof, or anything herein contained, or in connection herewith, or the rights or liabilities of either party hereunder, the same shall, failing any agreement to settle it in any other way, be referred to two arbitrators, one of whom shall be chosen by each party, and a referee, who shall be chosen by the arbit rators before proceeding to arbitration. (b) Each party shall nominate its own arbitrator within Sixty days after delivery of a request so to do by the other party failing which its arbitrator may at the request of the other party be designated by the British Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. In the event of the arbitrators failing to agree within Sixty days after being chosen or designated the British Political Resident in the Persian Gulf may appoint a referee at the request of the arbitrators or of either of them. (c) The decision of the arbitrators, or in a case of a difference of opinion between them the decision of the referee, shall be final and binding upon both parties. (d) In giving a decision the arbitrators or the referee shall specify an adequate period of delay during which the party against whom the decision is given shall conform to the decision and that party shall be in default only if that party has failed to conform to the decision prior to the expiry of that period and not otherwise. (e) The place of arbitration shall be such as may be agreed by the parties and in default of agreement shall be London. ARTICLE 2s(. The Company shall make all payments that become due to the Shaikh under this Agreement into the Shaikh ac count at the and the Bank’s receipt shall be a full discharge for the Company in respect to the payment of the sum stated in the Bank’s receipt. Should the Shaikh decide to grant permission for a Bank to open a branch or Agency in Dubai the Shaikh shall consult with the Company as to which Bank shall be given the permission. The Shaikh may from time to time designate in writing another Bank or Banks for the purpose of this Article. * * • * Li) 1^1 4-jUrV! « ‘LI v— ^iaj ta! (Jaa- ^ • \ 1 ^ j_5 (v) VI JS\ ^ -X_A) j&gt;- VI Jl&gt; jflll t—bb A^&gt;- cUjJu |»LaJ\ l^lj ^jUl 0-&gt;i^-l ti ^ail ^4 Lj&gt; (jA-.— jUrVI (J ^Ul ^lia.j^41 ^.all jjlj I^A-U-Jt) jl l^jLlp-l jl j^-Svli-l w-Us Alt- V^a-3 Ul • l-o^,^-* Aa*lj &lt;j 1 J jl ^-1 jiy oi ( ^_ ) * . • * , Jc L‘l r 'Jl jJ-a-oll j\ ^^*3 jl^3 jlA-al A'^ AjI ( i ) * * ■ ^ yll llll 4 ^—Ia oAa ^jl Vj (jl jlj^ll JA-s&gt; ^iSl jlj^U jjili j)l (jf- bl VI \j-aA* J&lt;yb I^A . VI 'aAli cLlb' j^Lab oU;yl\ A^ic- JLiu&gt; ^X^lb (. A ) • o-i-J J J^*VI ^ J- lilj ^—^7 A-S^i—b (AJly****l^_J A^—«li-l o^lll A-3UVI «AA y. —&gt; J\ vj»lj»3Al| \ &lt;5^111 A^il Q jy dlub y« ^&gt;-lll Jl^VI Cjj^j .. dUl JUJ J (j^JI ,ji iJji-b viXJ jj^vi (ji jj31^1 jwIa jl J jl Ic j . (iJOJu jiVI j! ^ ^aII dkb jlL Ai^jJl jl j^l (Ji u?- jr* ^-t~II J J**U jl j’-l cry* . oLH aAA4) ARIC] in consult; ative of th as a confi Shaikh anc and to ass tha Gompa the Shaikh shall be p? Shaikh in of Rupees ARTI ten in En If there si as to the clause in t shall prev; In v this Agrei Day and ^ARICLE 2o. The Shaikh may select in consultation with the Local Represent ative of the Company a local man to act as a confidential person as between the Shaikh and the Company's Representative and to assist in procuring the labour that the Company may require. The salary of | the Shaikh’s confidential person so appointed shall be paid by the Company, through the i Shaikh in Dubai and shall be at the rate of Rupees Four hundred (400) per month. ARTICLE 2^ This Agreement is writ ten in English and translated into Arabic. If there should at any time be disagreement as to the meaning or interpretation of any clause in this Agreement the English text shall prevail. In witness whereof the parties to this Agreement have set their hands the Day and Year first above written 4.*oLJI j ^^ jla: Oy ^ ^ a 'A&gt;. &gt;' o- ^ aj jJL\\ ai Jyi y ^jJl)\ l f »9-ir IjlCa ^ m m * * \\)) ^l»! j' ( ^ * * ) A^5 iji)' N ^ d-X* (j j jJL»} \ y^A&gt; Ul a^ll! ^ ^ iJL) . A-j j*}\ j 1 j A)^.^)^!* • 1 | . •* # d-XA y* ^ja9^\a a' y\ l—J Tjl j\ A;*' y . J*»i Aj lj AJUi^i a^. 9U.jjU) yi!i u *• . Alull Ah!&amp; (Skiis ta drarwuw JKJVlJljej THE COMPANY THE SHAIKH &lt;&lt;r^\ c-~' IN THE PRESENCE OF IN THE PRESENCE OF ml) IN THE PRESENCE OFJGS/MM, f !\~7~] i 7860 (4 j_, 4952, i 9 3 6 j ITTc'^D K 0 F T, AJ^L From Political Resident in the Persian Gulf to Secretary of State for Indian Dated Higher, 3rd November, 1936, Received 12*30 pom*, 3rd November, 1936, 778, Fowl© to Clauson, My note of 12th September on Article XIV (b) of Petroleum Concession Limited draft Trucial Coast Commercial .Agreements, I do not recollect this point being raised again in our subsequent discussions, I trust it is being included in Commercial or Political Agreements,My dear Clauson, Your letter P.Z.726b of 20th October on the subject of Petroleum Concessions Limited and their draft Dibai concession* We concur in the draft exchange of notes and in the modifications proposed by the India Office. Yours sincerely, AmAIR MINISTRY. ADASTRAL HOUSE. KINGSWAY. W.C.2. S .35804/5 JET Dear 30th October, 1936. With reference to your letter PZ.7265/36 of the 20th October, 1936, we have examined the copies of a draft exchange of letters between the Sheikh of Dibai and his Majesty^ Government enclosed therewith. We concur in the draft exchange of notes as suggested by you in the last paragraph of page 2 of your letter. M. J. Clauson, Esq., India Office, Whitehall, S .W .1.X ' TELEPHONE : NATIONAL 35*2 TELEGRAMS : NLAND : PETCONCESlSSfINSQUARE, LONDON FOREIGN : PETCONCESS. LONDON PETROLEUM /(«Aa , fwMwy l^oy «r2 m-m CODES : BENTLEY’S SECOND PHRASE tf^ENTLEY’S COMPLETE PHRASE WITH OIL SUPPLEMENT LOMBARD DEVELOPMENT UAL COAST) LIMITED DIRECTORS : Sir John Cadman, G.C.M.G. (Chairman) A. Ajn®'*^C.9.E. R. Cayr '-O., D.S.C. (French) W. Fraser, ~.8.E. C. S. Gulbenkian (formerly Armenian) i. B. A. Kessler (Dutch) Sir John B. Lloyd J. A. Meny (French) H. G. Seidel (U.S.A) R. W. Sellers J. Skliros CITY-GATE HOUSE FINSBURY SQUARE PC. 29/189. LONDON • E.C.2 / 27 th October, 1936 . * . . t My dear Clauson, • “ With reference to your letter P.Z. 7265/36 dated October 23rd, we have no objection to the addition of the words which you propose to the amended Article 9(c). As regards Article 25 (now to be added). Holmes feels that the Shaikh may find difficulty in accepting this Article, owing to unwillingness to let the Political Resident make decisions regarding the boundaries of his territory. In fact, of course, the Political Resident would, in case of a frontier dispute between tw T o of the Shaikhs, be the umpire and have the last word, but Holmes feels that to say so quite so definitely as is done in Article 25 may cause the Shaikh of Dubai to hesitate. Although, therefore, we will now include this Article in the Draft Concession, we cannot ignore the possibility that Holmes may have to omit it if its presence is a stumbling-block to signature. As the Article is not one for which you have ever pressed, (though you have accepted it), I imagine that its omission would not worry you. We appreciate that all the Drafts which you mention in your letter under reply must be finally approved by the Secrfit qT&gt; y °f £tate. , It peems that all is now ready ENCLOSURE IN AIR MAIL LETTER No.&lt;r -4 NOV 1936 FKOM I -ORETARY, POLITICAL AND SRC INDIA OFFltE C#PY SENT BY AIR MAE. 07 '9 f otJz* HOV1366 Rq r ( -.-'C KQ ■■ -1 . / 1 ' •2 - for this in so far as concerns the Concession itself, and the Draft Exchange of Notes with the Shaikh. You have not yet shown us the Draft Political Agreement, since I made comments in my PC.28/149 of October 1st on your No. 6412 of September 29 th. As regards the Refinery Agreement, we await with great interest the revised proposal which you have, I believe, nearly ready for us. Yours sincerely. M.J. Clauson Esq., India Office, Whitehall, S.W. 1 £.W. 1« ■ ' TELEPHONE : NATIONAL J5«J TELEGRAMS : INLAND : PETCONCESS, FINSQUARE. LONDON FOREIGN : PETCONCESS, LONDON u lOid C?J 7\ CODES : BENTLEY’S SECOND PHRASE BENTLEY'S COMPLETE PHRASE WITH OIL SUPPLEMENT LOMBARD PETROLEUM L&gt;. CTORS: Sir John Cabman, G.C.M.G. (Chairman) A. Agn«»*«« ^*^,.E. R. Cayro .0., D.S.C. (French) W. Frase_.B.E. C. S. Gulbenkian (formerly Armenian) i. B. A. Kessler (Dutch) Sir John B. Lloyd J. A. Meny (French) H. G. Seidel (U.S.A.) R. W. Sellers J. Skliros n -t: DEVELOPMENT (TRUCIAL COAST) LIMITED pc. 29 / 190 ■ 7 O CONFIDENTIAL / ' J i k u~-~ CITY-GATE HOUSE FINSBURY SQUARE LONDON • E.C.2 27th October, 1936* My dear Clauson, With reference to your Confidential letter P.Z. 7265/36 dated October 25rd. Many thanks for the Draft Exchange of Notes. These appear entirely satisfactory* My only comment is that the Concession will, in fact, be granted by the Shaikh to Petroleum Development (Trucial Coast) Ltd., a subsidiary of Petroleum Concessions Ltd. which we have formed especially for the six Trucial Coast Sheikhdoms. You may wish to mention this Company instead of P.C.L. itself in the Political Residents letters to the Shaikh. In passing, I am worried by the absence of any suitable Arabic equivalent for the ex pression ’’Trucial Coast,” and shall be interested to see what the Political Resident decides to use. Many thanks for the three copies of your Print of the Qatar Docume nts. enclosure ho. 4. ST - 4 m W FROM SECRETARY, POLITICAL AR!&gt; SECRET DEPT. INDIA OPEHE M.J. Clauson Esq., India Office, Whit ehall, S.W. 1 . Yours sincerely. gf)OCT)936 COPY SENT BY AIR \ivlr. V/alt&lt;3n&gt; u In your note of the 10th October, just below, you raised two points. As regards (2);-the suggestion at the end of paragraph 3(‘b) of the note at P. Z. 1254/36 has already been included in the draft Political agreement. As regards (3)&gt;I attach a draft demi-official u il’* , letter to the Foreign Office and Air Ministry (copies to Admiralty and Petroleum Department) forwarding the draft exchange of notes for concurrence. The next step will be to secure the Company 1 s concurrence. We now have the draft commercial concession, draft political agreement (with the exception of the Refinery clause) and draft exchange of notes in a more or less final form, and we should, I suppose, submit them all for formal sanction shortly. It may, however, be worth while waiting until we ge&gt;t agreement with the Admiralty and Petroleum Department about the Refinery clause (which it is now proposed to put in a separate agreement between H.M.G. and the Company/Draft Paper. 3 S p. z. 7265/36. Department. ..o \ T.V. Brenan, Esq., 0. B.E., Foreign Office, S. W. 1. DRAFT Qia /Hwv“^ ™* , 0 /l, 20 0011956 P^Us If. /r With reference to our correspondenc about Petroleum Concessions Limited and their draft Dibai concession, I enclose a copy of a draft exchange of letters between the Shaikh of Dibai and H. M. G., which has been prepared by the acting Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. We discussed the drafts with Colonel Fowle v/hile he was on deputation here. The drafts, as you will see, follow the lines of the Qatar notes, except that there are rrr?Q additional items not included in the Qatar notes, namely 'g/paragraph 3(c) of the first draft letter to the Sheikh about the deportation of foreign employees of the /4&gt; l hiM i —U* Company, and r * llVl 'nvn third pnragPflph to the Sheikh about the protection of the Company's employees and property. In present A. circumstances we do not consider that oithor of these additions is necessary. The first point, about deportation of foreign employees, has already been covered by an amendment of the Conunercial concession (see my letter of the 18th September, No.P.Z.6412/36,and my letter to Longrigg dated 24 th September under the same number).i \ inclined to think that Article 15 of the draft commercial concession covers the position adequately in regard to protection. In that Article the Sheikh undertakes to ’'give to the Company and its employees and property all protection in his power from theft* highway robbery, assault, wilful damage and destruction”. \ Any failure of the Sheikh to implement that undertaking would, presumably, tend to invalidate the concession as a whole, including the royalty clause, and it therefore seems to us to be unnecessary to make any further provision in the exchange of notes. Provision was, of course, necessary in respect of the ^ options , because there was nothing in the option agreements between-the various Sheikhs aid the Company to cover the question of protection. May we assume that you concur in the draft exchange of notes, with the omission, of the two passages to which I refer above. I am sending a similar letter to Pirie^and copies to Starling and Seal.PETROLEUM DEPARTMENT (Mines Department), Reference No.:- .p.D. 859/7 Dean Stanley Street. Mills a nk, London, S.W.l October, 1936* My dear Clauson In reply to your letter of 5th October, numbered P.Z. 7006/36, regarding the Bebai Commercial Agreement, the amendments to the Royalty clause proposed in Longrigg^ letter of 28th September have been examined and the clause, as amended, now substantially covers the points raised in my letter of 4th September. The Company, however, will still not have to pay royalty on any natural gas sold before the discovery of oil in commercial quantities is declared, but the probability of any such sales at that stage is, I think, remote, and we might, therefore, leave the clause as it now stands. I am sending a copy of this letter to Brenan and Seal. Yours sincerely. M. J. Clauson, Esq India Office, Great Charles Street, S.W. 1. RECo. P'U. DEPT. 9 OCT 1936 l;*^^rflCE' TELEPHONE : NATIONAL 3SM TELEGRAMS : INLAtA'^FtTCONCESS, FINSQUARE, LONDON V-i nfe frEIGN : PETCONCESS, LONDON f.e. 3 0 jaw- ' ; 'u^ BENTLEY S SECOND PHRASE BENTLEY’S COMPLETE PHRASE WITH OIL SUPPLEMENT LOMBARD PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LIMITED DIRECTORS : Sir John Cadman, G.C.M.G. (Chairman) A. Agnew, C.B.E. R. Cayrol, D.S.O., D.S.C. (French) W. Fraser, C. S. Gulb*. ormerly Armenian) J. B. A. Kessler (Dutch) Sir John B. Lloyd J. A. Meny (French) H. G. Seidel (L/.SA) R. W. Sellers J. Skliros PC.29/14J. My dear Clauson, fT 7 f / &gt; /Cl / u r&gt;, n c V. U CITY-GATE HOUSE FINSBURY SQUARE LONDON E.C.2 28th September 1936. A I acknowledge, with many thanks, your letter PZ.6412/36 dated September 24th, ana appreciate your willingness not to insist upon the two suggested amend ments to the Dubai text, mentioned on pages 4 ana 5 of your letter. These referred respectively to an obliga tion to make available for the Shaikh accurate geological maps and records, ana to a proposed alteration of wording ('cognate substances') in Article 3- Regarding the amendments which you ask us to make, I give below the precise alteration to the text which I conceive these amendments would involve, ana should be very glad to have your specific agreement to this. Article 5( c ) - AS REVISED: i —~ 'Rupees 25,000 (Tv/enty-five thousand) at the end of each year from the date of signature hereof until the Company declares in writing to the Shaikh that Substances have been discovered in commercial quantities in accordance with sub clause (b) of this Article 5 or until the Company commences Production from quantities less than commercial quantities. In the event ol such Production by the Company from quantities less than commercial quantities either Rupees 25*000 (Twenty-five thousand) per year or Rupees 3 (three) per English ton of 2,240 lbs. in respect of the substances so w r on and saved shal l be payabl e., wD. $£PT. | 2 9 SEP 1936 D i A OrPiQEi! whichever is the greater”. a S &gt; E?K)56_ '-'di p2 Article 5(^0 - AS AMliJDlD : ”At the end of every year from the date upon which the Company makes in writing to the Shaikh the declaration that the Substances have been dis covered in commercial quantities Rupees 80,000 (Eighty thousana) or Rupees 3 (three)per English ton of 2,240 lbs. in respect of the Substances (other than natural gas) won and saved during the preceding calendar year, whichever is the greater”. Article 5(d) - ADDED: 'Annas 2 (two) per 1,000 cubic feet of natural gas produced and sold'. (Last sentence of existing Article 5 remains). Article 9(c) - AS AMENDED : 'The Company may import such alcoholic drinks ana liquor as the Company may require for the use of their foreign employees but only with the written permission of the Political Agent, Bahrain, but H the Company shall not sell (remainder of sub-Article unaltered) J QR ALTERNATIVELY : 'but only with the written permission of the Shaikh and the Political Agent, Bahrain, but the Company ti Article 10 (third paragraph) - AS AMENDED : 'Further in the event of any of the Company*s. employees — whether he be a senior or a junior employee — committing an offence which may cause disorder or interfere with the politics or subjects of the State of Dubai or excite them to sedition, then the Shaikh may apply to the Political Agent, Bahrain, to send the person concerned — if a foreigner — out of the State of Dubai, but if a subject of the Shaikh, then the Shaikh may arrest(33 &amp; “ 5 ' the culprit and aeal with him according to the Laws of the State of Dubai”. (LAST SENTENCE OF EXISTING ARTICLE 10 TO BE Omitted). Article 25 - TO BE ADDED : 'The Shaikh agrees that, in the event of a difference of opinion between him and any other ruler or authority as to whether a given place or district is properly to be considered as with in his territory or in that of the other ruler or authority he will accept without reservation the decision of the Political Resident on this matter and will in so far as lies in his power, prevent the existence of the dispute from affecting adversely the operations of the Company in any manner. The Company agrees similarly without reservation to accept such decision'. Existing Article 25 becomes Article 26. 26 ' ' 27- 27 ' ' 28 .LJC/DIA (78 groups) n -rt fiurh , 4231. ^J r DEGYPHER OF TELEflRAM. From Dated Received Political Resident in the Persian Gulf to Secretary of State for Indiao Risher, 23rd September^ 1936» 23rd September, 1936, 2-30 p*m&lt;&gt; X H bl+ 0 v /v&gt; &lt;/ 671 o Addressed to Secretary of State for India, repeated to Political Agent, Bahrain, for his private informationo Following for Fowleo Begins 0 There is a lot of intrigue on the Trucial Coast over the oil concessions and in particular at the moment about accepting unlimited responsibility for protection® Attempts are being made(so far I think without success) to persuade the Sheikh (of) Daban to go back on his promises to Holmes and undertake the protectionc 2 ® I cannot help feeling that it was a mistake from the Company’s point of view for Holmes to leave before the final settlement was reached with Daban and that it would be best for them to complete the agreement before the intrigue becomes strong enough to upset Sheikh (of) Daban.0 $ / * ir . Z. 6740/v36 DHAI'x LIITTZiH To i Shaikh Said oin I .aktum al Hashar, , Ruler cl JDioai. Altei Compliments, His Hajesty's Government have been furnished v/ith a copy of the Agreement signed by you on .. [ TwJ. ' « ‘'bit'***] C0O4^ sy&gt; granting to Petroleum Concessions A Limited an oil concession in respect of your territory on the understanding that the Agreement is subject to the approval of His Majesty's Government. 2. Under instructions from His Majesty's Government I now enclose a copy of an Agreement which has been concluded between His Majesty's Government and Petroleum Concessions Limited in London on 3. It is desirable that there should be a clear understanding as to the position which would arise in certain eventualities in connection with these two Agreements, and I am to inform you that in these circum stances the understanding described below has been reached wi tn the Company,- (a) Should any of the terms of the Agreement between you and the Company/O Uj • Company be inconsistent or in conflict v/ith the terms of the Agreement bef./e-en the Company and His Ha jesty ’ s Government signed in London on the Agneoment between you and the Company will to the extent of any such inconsistency or conflict be subordinate to and be controlled by the terms of the A&amp;reemen'c between the Company and His Majesty 1 s Covernment. (b) If the Company should fail to observe any of the terms of the Agreement between the Company and His Majesty’s Government signed in London on..... or if the alleged failure having been disputed by the Company the matter has been referred to arbitration under Article 24 of the Company’s Agreement with you (which is made applicable to the case by Article of the Agreement between the Company and His Majesty’s Cover nment) and the Company should not remedy such failure within the reasonable time which shall be fixed by the arbitrators for so doing then in those cases, as inJ&gt; tnc cases oiied in Article 19 of the Company’s Agreement with you, hut in no other, the Company agrees that * you will he entitled to terminate the Agreement between the Company and yourself, and that all properties of the Company within your territory shall hecome your property, and that they will hand over to you free of cost land granted to the Company hy you and any lands or buildings which the Company may have bought and any houses or buildings constructed by the Company and all other irremovable property of the Company within your territory, including the producing wells and borings which shall be handed over in reasonably good order and repair, s or as in Qatar Agreement 4. Please let me have a reply to this according to whether Matter has been discussed letter to the effect that you understand or not. the nature of the arrangements as set out above and that you are prepared to agree to them. On receipt of your reply His Majesty’s Government will obtain from the Company formal confirmation of their acceptance of the arrangements in question and will communicate such confirmation to you. Usual Ending. Lieut.-Colonel. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.V io£) (ffi DRAFT LETTER. To Shaikh. Said 'bin Maktum al Hashar, . ‘ . iu* j Ruler Qf Dihai. After C ompliraent8, With reference to the Agreement oigned Ly you on the . . (\wm*L i su. , \I / a granting to Petroleum Cmic-n^s-iono- Limited an oil concession in respect of your territory* I have been directed by His Majesty's Government to inform you that they are prepared to accord their approval to the concession provided you accept the following condition* namely that should you v/ish to grant permission to a Bank to open a Branch or Agency in Dibai, as mentioned in Article 25 of theCbncession, you will obtain His Majesty’s Government’s approval before entering into any • negotiations v.dth the Bank. On receipt of your reply accepting the above condition the formal approval of His Majesty’s Government to the Concession will be communicated to you and to the Company. Usual Ending. Lieut.-Colonel. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.To t Shaikli Said b in Makturn a 1 Hashar, O.B.h. 'Ruler ol Dibai After C omp1iment s, With reference to your letter dated the accept - ing the conditions set forth in my letter No dated the I am directed by His Majesty's Government to convey to you their approval of the Agreement concluded by you on the v/ith Petroleum Limited. Usual Anding. Lieutenant-Colonel Political Resident in the lersian Gulf.CONFIDENTIAL. Noc/175 of 1956. The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to 1. His Majesty’s Secretary of ^tate for India, London. 2. The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, Simla. 3. The Political Agent ,• Bahrain , at Karachi. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document (s). ! V i Office of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Gamp, SHIRAZ# Dated.. IQth .Sep tember. ,193 6 . Reference to previous correspondence: Political Resident’s telegram No.T/160 of 10th Septanber 193 6 . « ’’Printed letter No. c/162 of 4th September /1936. M H telegram No.T/129 of 4th September 1936. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. To(2)&amp; 1. Political Resident’s telegram No. (3) only. T/160 of 10th September 193 6 . 2. Draft letters to the Shaikh of Dibfi i. ## 18 *# r 18 SEP 1936 J r r'. r: y: r Subject. Petroleum Concessions Ltd. Dibai•DRAj?T LETTER To Shaikh Said bin Maktum al Hashar» 0»B#!3»» Ruler of Dibai* After Compliments, His Majesty’s Government have been furnished with a copy of the Agreement signed hy y° u (uvl y(\/c/sji\MUA4' granting to ,,,,1 i 1 o» Ctodr) f nfivl it &lt;k futuJk*** &amp;*/&gt;***)—&amp; fMm Binna-JdA^red]an oil concession in respect of your territory on the understanding that the Agreement is subject to the approval of His Majesty• s Coverrinent. 2. Under instructions from His Majesty’s Government I now enclose a copy of an Agreement which has been concluded between His Majesty’s Government and Petroleum Concessions Limited in London on 3. It is desirable that there should be a clear understanding as to the position which would arise in certain eventualities in connection with these two Agreements, and I am to inform you that in these circum stances the understanding described below has been reached with the Company (a) Should any of the terms of the Agreement /- 2 - wo) Agreement between you and tlie Company be inconsistent or in conflict with the terns of the Agreement between the Comjs. ny and His iShjesty’s Government signed in ^ondon on . the Agreement between you and the Company will to the extent of any such inconsistency or conflict be subordinate to and be controlled by the terms of the Agreement between the Company and His Majesty’s Government. (b} If the Company should fail to observe ary of the terms of the Agreement between the CompL ny and His Majesty’s Government signed in London on.••••««...»...... of if the alleged failure having been disputed by the Company the matter has been referred to arbitration under Article 24 of the Company’s Agreement with you (which is made applicable to the case by Article of the Agreement between the Company and His Majesty’s Government) and the Company should not remedy such failure within the reasonable time which shall be fixed by the arbitrators for so doing then in these cases, as in the /-5 the cases mentioned in Article 19 of the Company’s Agreement with you, but in no other, the Com^ny agrees that you will be entitled to terminate the Agree ment between the Company and yourself» and that all properties of the Company within your terri tory shall become your property, and that they will hand over to you free of cost land granted to the Company by you and any 3a nds or buildings which the Company may have bought and any houses or buildings constructed by the Company and all other irremovable property of the Company within your territory, including the producing wells and borings which shall be handed over in sn foreign employee c£ should /* or as in ^atar Agreement accord ing to whether matter has been discussed or not. 0 O'? shoulcCS&amp;e sent^but of your terri tory, the^^tter should be referred to tlpe^Britislt^olitical Resident the Persian Gul^Ssi'or his final vision* 4. Please let me have a reply to this letter to the effect that you understand the nature of the arrangements as set out above and that you are prepared to agree to them. On receipt of your reply His Majesty’s Government will obtain from the Company formal confirmation of their acceptance of the arrangements in question and will communicate such confirmation to y ou. Usual Ending. Lieut.-Colonel. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.DKAffT L5TTER To Shaikh Said bin mktum al Haahar. O.B.B*, Ruler of Dibai. After Compliments, With reference to paragraph 4 of my letter No* •••••••• dated •••• I have been instructed by His Majesty’s Government to inform you that the arrangements set forth in that letter and your acceptance of them conveyed in your letter dated have been communicated to Petroleum Concessions Limited and that the Compi ny have formally confirmed their acceptance of these arrange ments • Usual Ending. Lieut.-Colonel. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.draft letter fC\ AA /kAvwfritM, To Shaikh Said bin Maktum al Hashar, O.B.S., Ruler of Dibai. After Compliments, With reference to the Agreement signed by you on the granting to/^Petroleum Concessions Limitedjan oil concession in respect of your territory, I have been directed by His Majesty’s Government to inform you that they are prepared to accord their approval to the concession provided you accept the following condition * that you agr^' that you wi^l &lt;^&gt;6 responsible for the p^otec- ti\a of y^ne employees And prop^ri^ or rne company in yo&gt;Tr territory aiid that in the £vent of aim incident occurring you will tak^^ll possible action aga/ tit ti^e culprits anc pay any hompensatio\ which Hie Maj ei^y * s Gove] poTytiidor nocea3cii’y f j 'that should you wish to grant permission to a Bank to open a Branch or Agency in Dibai, as mentioned in Article 25 ofthe Concesaion, you will obtain Hie Majesty’s Government’s approval before entering into any negotiations with the Bank. On receipt of your reply accept ing the above condition^^the formal approval of His Majesty’s Government to the Concession will be communicated to you and to the Company. Usual Ending. Lieut.-Colonel. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. 4DRAFT LETTER Shaikh Said bin Maktum al Hashar, Ruler of Dibai* After compliments. With reference to your letter dated the accepting the conditions set forth in my letter No*..... dated the I am directed by His Majesty^ Government to convey to you their approval of the Agreement concluded by you on the with Usual Ending. Li eut.-Colonel. Politic &amp;1 Resident in the Persian Gulf.~$c P.&gt;s6412/36 IMMEDIATE INDIA CPPICS, %-t 0 Ll L. WHITEHALL, S.W. 1. H~ ir 24th September, 1936, &lt;© My dear Longrigg, With reference to the Meeting at the India Office yesterday between yourself, Mr. Packer and Major Holmes on the one side, and Colonel Fowle and myself on the other, I write to confirm that we desire to suggest the following amendments in the text of the Dibai Commercial Concession as finally initialled by the Sheikh and Major Holmes. Article 5(c) . We pointed out that there appears to be a drafting error in this Article as revised. The original draft Concession provided at all stages for an annual payment ^or royalty at Rs.3 per ton, v/hich ever is the greater. The new Article does not provide for any royalty payments at all until the Company declares the discovery of oil in commercial quantities, or is deemed to have done so on obtaining the substantial production of 2,000 tons per day. It was agreed that the Company would S.H. Longrigg, Esq., Petroleum Concessions, Ltd., City Gate House, Finsbury Square, E. C. 2. reconsider/ ENCLOSURE IN A* MAH LETTER no. ?/0 2 SEP 1955 FROM SECRETARY, POLITICAL AND SECuEl DEPT. INDIA OFFItEreconsider Article 5(c) with a view to meeting this point. A further point which we raised in regard to Article 5 is that it seems desirable, as in the Qatar Agreeme nt, to maintain the principle of having a separate provision for the payment of royalty on natural gas produced and sold, and, for this purpose, a royalty of Annas 2 per thousand cubic feet appears suitable. This would entail making a consequential amendment to Article 5(d) so as to exclude natural gas from the ,T sub stance s ,T won and saved in respect ol which the uraj-t provides for royalty at the rate of Rs.3 per ton. It was agreed that although the point is largely academic, the Company should revise the Article accordingly. Article 9(c ) . This should be altered and the position made more or less the same as in Bahrein, where alcohol can only be imported by permission of the political Agent. 'Permission of the Political Agent' should therefore be substituted for 'permission of the Sheikh'. Alternatively, if this is not acceptable to the bheikh, the words 'and the Political Agent or any Authority deputed by him' should be inserted alter 'permission of the Sneikh .3. It was agreed that there ought to he no difficulty in making one or other of these amendments. Article 10, paragraph 5 . We pointed out that while the Company have, of course, every right to dismiss any of their employees, they cannot he given judicial powers of deportation. It would not, therefore, he possible to agree to the sentence I,r Fhe Sheikh may request the Local Representative of the Company to send the person concerned, if a foreigner, out of the State of Dioai T '. In this sentence we suggested that the words 'Political Agent, Bahrein' could he substituted for 'Local Representative of the Company'. As a consequential amendment the last sentence of the paragraph should he omitted. It was agreed that the Company would consider these suggestions which, prima facie , appear^to he acceptable. Article 25 . We mentioned that it was desirable that the bank in question should he a British one, provided that a British hank was prepared to open a branch. It is proposed to insert a suitable provision in the Exchange of Notes between His Majesty’s Government and the Sheikh. Article 25 need not he altered. We referred to your letter to Mr. Walton dated 14th September/——4. September in which you suggested a draft Article designed to cover the position which would arise in the case of a dispute in regard to the boundaries of the various Sheikhdoms, and explained that this draft additional Article had apparently been overlooked. It was agreed that this Article should be added to the draft Concession. Two further points were mentioned which were left for further consideration by the India Office. One was a suggestion put forward by us that there should be a provision on somewhat the same lines as in paragraph o of the third Article of the Qatar Concession, to the effect that accurate geolog] ' aps and records of the wells drilled should be e£&gt; pied*, which should be open to inspection by the Sheikh or his authorised representative. We understood from you that you felt serious objection to this suggestion not because you wished in any way to conceal from the Sheikh any information which he, or his representative, might legitimately require in respect of the Company's operations, but because you feared that if confidential maps and records were communicated there would be a grave danger of their falling into other hands than those for which they 'were intended. ' 'e have considered5. this matter again (which is, after all, a comparatively small one) and we do not wish to press it on the Company, in spite of the fact that the provision already exists in the Qatar Agreement. We feel that the Sheikh may safely rely on the Company treating him fairly in this respect; and if he or His Majesty’s Government 'were at any time to feel that due diligence was not being shown by the Company in working the Concession, the matter could quite well be taken up, even without a specific provision of this kind in the Concession. The second point was raised by you. You asked whether we v/ished to insist on the change of the phrase 'cognate substances' in Article 3. After further consideration of this matter with our technical advisers, we feel that it is unnecessary to make this alteration. This point is also a very small one. You will no doubt let us know as soon as possible whether you are prepared to make the alterations in the Commercial Concession which were suggested at the feting and detailed above. Yours sincerely, (Sgd.)Any reply to this letter should be addressed to the Director, Petroleum Dept. PETROLEUM DEPARTMENT (Mines Department), Dean Stanley Street. Millbank, London, S.W.l. Telephone: Victoria 9310. Telegrams: Minindttst, Sowest, London. Reference No.:-P.D. *2 September, 1936 My dear Clauson, Many thanks for your letter of 18th September and enclosure regarding the Debai concession, together with a draft letter to Longrigg. We have no further comments to make except to point out that three alterations to the draft Debai Commercial Concession were referred to in my letter of 4th September and not two, as indicated in the note accompanying your letter. Yours sincerely M. J. Clauson, Esq., India Office, Whitehall, S.W. 1. HPWGr/BSDraft Paper. p.z. ltd r\ T.V. Brenan, Esq., O.B.E., FOREIGN OFFICE, S.W. 1. /&gt;. f(k&lt;L ff 1 ' I'W/ (A^ ; cj- Department. 50 56 5000 7 3G 18 SEP 1936 My dear Brenan, Woaldyoa kindly refer to year letter of 1st September, No. E 5461/260/91, and connected correspondence on the subject oi the Debai concession? As regards the draft corrmercial concession, I enclose a note regarding amendments which m Fowle's opinion ought to be made before the concession is finally concluded. We are, I think, in agreement with v owle, and we shall be seeing Longrigg and Holmes next Wednesday, when we will put these points to them. I should be grateful if you v/ould let me know m the meantime whether you have any comments to make. I shall assume otherwise, especially in the, lugkt-of your 1-etter -of- -Sftptember^ that you have not. As regards the political a greement , I enclose a copy of a draft letter which we are proposing to send to Longrigg. It follows ise^y-tr~e'~agi ueM'iwitr whicHi^e kavp hirparly —jg^r^-fl interdepartmentally, except that we have not hitherto got to the stage of drafting the actual text of a ( /(Me/ uri oa^- ill pec .that clause about protection e -now-dom, so.—-he—p •f ou- \^± J iu C.A/ -podritnroai friArh. . agree^rent ■ wirl~ntr tkrubt be diocanoeu a-x-BO v^ltbi hnngngg cxi ./ednoodayr- -shatir aaaume--yetuHiarve'niD~TJlJSefvatrioTTB^^ unless ymi le-t us know. As/ !Note . The draft Uebai commercial concession has been scrutinised with the assistance of Col. Fowle, particularly in regard to the new articles added at the suggestion of the Sheikh at the last moment. The following amendments a-opear to be necessary:- Article 5(c) .- The two alterations suggested by Mr. Starling in his letter of 4th September, P.Jl). 859/7, should be made. article 9(c) .- This should be altered and the position made more or less the same as in bahrein, where alcohol can only be imported by permission of the Political Agent. 'Permission of the Political Agent 1 ' should therefore be substituted for 'permission of the Sheikh'. Alternatively, if this is not acceptable, the words 'and the Political Agent or any authority authorised by him' should be inserted after 'permission of the Sheikh'. Article 10. nara. 3. - Colonel Fowle notes as follows: 'While the company have of course every right to dismiss any of their employees they cannot be given judicial powers of deportation, which is what the relevant sentence in this paragraph comes to:- 'The Sheikh may request the local representative of the Company to send the person concerned - if a foreigner - out of the state of Debai’. These powers should be reserved as they are in Bahrein under the Order m Council to the Political Agent, Bahrein (he is the nearest political authority), in the relevant sentence the words 'Political Agent, Bahrein’ instead of ’local representative of the company/V (g&gt; company‘ mi^ht be sabstitated. ‘ihis point, however, brings up the whole question of our legal powers on the Trucial coast which are of course nil, since v/e have no Order in council there, we may have to have an Order in Council for Debai (as well as for the other States of the i'rucial coast where oil is found) as we have had to have one for Qatar, but I think the change in the wording of this article which I suggest would be a useful step in getting the Sheikh to recognise one at least of the powers which we shall have to get by Order in Council. I suppose, however, that from the legal point of view even though the Sheikh agrees no one can legally be deported until an Order in Council containing that proviso has actually been published.* 1 In addition to the amendments suggested by Colonel Fowle, it is agreed that the last sentence of the article should be omittea. Article 25 .- Some provision should be made that the bank must be a british one, provided that a British bank is nared to onen a branch. This might well be inserted r^renared to onen a branch. make any alteration of the commercial agreement. A fresh article should be inserted on the lines suggested in Mr. Longrigg’s letter to Mr. Walton dated 14th May. A copy of this was enclosed m the express letter to the Government of India dated 2Uth May, P.Z. 3363/36. The article reserves the decision in regard to frontier disputes between Trucial Sheikhdoms to the Resident. It -mrill -bo seen -that the-soggestcd amendmenl7s-t7e-Mr.Clauson. Generally in regard to the commercial and political agreements for the Trucial Coast concessions, ^particularly DebaiJ, though the latter overrides the former we want I think as little overriding as possible otherwise we may unnecessarily disgruntle the Sheikh* It is^ perhaps not much good our passing in the canmercial agreement anything of importance which we know we will have to annul in the political agreement. 2. Taking the comm ercial agreement with Debai first. Once this is suitable fiom our point of view it can form, mutatis mutandis , a^pattern for the other Trucial Coast Sheikhdoms where similar conditions prevail. The following comments occur to me:- Article 1 (c). This is important. There f-u-u bkc\. may be totok air facilities required in the future, but I suppose it will be difficult to provide for these in the commercial agreement though scmething might be put into the political agreement to the effect that 'The Company will give due consideration to any air facilities required byH.M.G. w Article 4. This seems a wise provision in view of the contiguity of Debai with its next door neighbours, Abu Dhabi and Shargah. Article^S jc). I agree with Starling in his suggestion, vide letter of 4th September, P.Z.6412, that this article should be rectified. I also agree ft, CIamU if • th* Hfcbtoj) fa in his further remarks re payments of royalty on 'natural gas produced and sold', but there is nothing apparent^as to this in the agreement unless I have overlooked it. Article/sentence the words 'Political Agent, Bahrein' instead 2 . Article 9 (a). You will remember that on behalf of the Bahrein Government we had some difficulty with the B.P.C. re the interpretation of their customs exemption clause. Here, however, it is laid down that the Company should pay on all ’’personal clothing” etc., so I think the point is covered. Article 9 (c). This should be altered and the position made more or less the same as in Bahrein where alcohol can only be imported by permission of the Political Agent. The liquor control question is of some importance on the Arab coast and I don’t think that at Debai it should be left to the sole control of the Sheikh. If he is slack in his control and either his subjects (in spite of the efforts of the Company) take to alcohol, or the Company’s employees imbibe too muchj the consequent odium will fall in one way or another on us, and the local political authorities will have to deal with tne results. I think, therefore, that after the word ’’Sheikh' should come the words ” and the Political Agent, Bahrein, or any authority authorised by him”. Article 10 Third paragraph. While the Company have of course every right to dismiss any of their employees they cannot be given judicial powers of deportation, which is what the relevant sentence in this paragraph comes to:- 'The Sheikh may request the local representative of the Company to send the person concerned - if a foreigner - out of the state of Debai'. These powers should be reserved as they are in Bahrein under the Order in Council to the P.A., Bahrein, (he 19 the nearest political authority). In the relevant\ Article/ Sr 'i Ys efr. X V C/ 4 3. of 'local representative of the Company' might be substituted. This point, however, brings up the whole question of our legal powers on the Trucial Coast which are of course nil, since we have no Order in Council there. We may have to have an Order in Council for Debai (as well as for the other States of the Trucial Coast where oil is found)as we have had to have one for Qatar, but I think the change in the wording of this article which I suggest would be a useful step in getting the Sheikh to recognise one at least of the powers which we shall have to get by Order in Council. I suppose, however, that from the legal point of view even though the Sheikh agrees no one can legally be deported until an Order in Council containing that proviso has actually been published. Article 11 (a). The last part of this is important. Civil aircraft are not allowed to fly over Koweit, Bahrein and Muscat under proclamations issued by these Rulers, but we have not asked the Trucial Coast Sheikhs to follow suit. However, only aeroplanes used by the Company will be employed and I do not think that we need make any objection. Article 14(b). After local inhabitants of Debai and labourers from neighbouring Arab countries, we should, I think, ensure that British or British- Indian labour is employed in preference to foreign, e.g. Iraq or Persian. I suggest, therefore, after the words 'obey the law' might be inserted 'and then British subjects'; after the word 'employees' might be inserted 'who shall, unless sufficient cause to the contrary is shown to H.M.G. by the Company,be British subjects' or something to that effect.a - - / Article 21. This is covered by my paragraph below. 3 %l) I think that a proviso the bank must be a British ish bank is prepared to open 3. With regard to the politic al agreement which is dealt with in your draft letter to Mr.Longrigg (a) Paras. 1 and 2. Your substitutes tighten up Article^l to the Ccmmercial Agreement and there are no comments. (b) Paras. 4 to 8. No comments. (c) The new paragraph after para.9. See below^fo Article 25. Ban should be inserted that one,provided that a Bri up there. L • / (d) Your note . Para.1. I should like to discuss the new clause about the protection of the Company's employees. Para.2. See my paragraph 2 above. © Para.3. Prima facie, since the Sheikhs of Abu Dhabi and Debai have given the required undertaking, vide my letter of 9th July, P.Z.5642, there would seem no reason why Shargah and Ras-al-Khaimah should not also agree. At the same time their request that they should know what is the extent of their financial commitments in the way of compensation, vide P.C.L. letter of 2nd September, P.Z.6366, is not unreasonable, and if we can hit on any method of assessing a possible maximum I would be inclined to let them have one. For the moment I do not see how this maximum can be arrived at, and I think that Colonel Loch might be instructed to approach the Sheikhs of Shargah and Ras-al-Khaimah, pointing out that/M.J. Clauson Esq., India Office, Whitehall, S.W.l. \C&gt;%) PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LIMITED DIRECTORS : Sir John Cadman, G.C.M.G. {Chairman) A. Agnew, C.B.E. R. Cayrol, D.S.O., D.S.C. (French) W. Fraser.&gt;C_E.E. C. S. Gulr 'n (formerly Armenian) J. B. A. K (Dutch) Sir John k.. /d J. A. Meny (French) H. G. Seidel (U.S.A.) R. W. Sellers J. Skliros PC.29/97- CITY-GATE HOUSE FINSBURY SQUARE LONDON E.C.2 ♦ w. “~ pr-rr 9th September 1936. My dear Clauson, Your letter P.Z^6220/36 dated September 2nd, second to sixth lines on page 2. I had, when I received your letter, already telegraphed to Major Holmes in the agreed sense, but the telegram was returned to me two days later undelivered, owing to his having left Sharjah. I will mention the matter to him on his arrival here, which we expect within the next day or two. n We are all perfectly clear as to the necessity of keeping JFvty ' the Political Resident and the Political Agent closely in : tj-^ ' touch with all our proceedings in the Gulf, and I think you can count absolutely on this being done. Yours sincerely. CODES f l ; BENTLEY’S SECOND PHRASE Fk/tr /-/- 1 MDI ETC DUD ACC WITH OIL SUPPLEMENT E : NATIONAL 35«2 TELEGRAMS : PETCONCESS, FINSQUARE, LONDON .EIGN : PETCONCESS, LONDON*5&gt; FfLh^OP'V \r / 4 J - R R X ; V. J U ^ L w ^—/ v-&lt; , FHB/UM, MX (COPIES CIRCULATED) J (155 groups») D E C T P H E R Q....F_,:r ..£_kJLg.£^JL From Lieutenant Colonel GoLooh, C.l.Io, to Secretary of State for India.. Dated Shiraz, 10th September, 1936» , Received ?«30 p»m«, 10th September, 1936.M X T/I 6 Q 0 Addressed to Secretary of State for India, copy by post to Government of India and Bahrain- My telegram No«129~T ? September 4th- I assume that modifications given in enclosure to your printed letter PZo61 5 5 , August 26th, are identical with those in Holme's final draft, which X have not yet received* If so, subject to comments below, I agree with suggestions in paragraph Nod (Article 10 and not 14 is, I think, referred to) and paragraph NOc2 your telegram No„2556 (sic, ? 2456), August 27tho 2c Article 99« 1 do not think company should give alcohol to jiny Mohamedan, even if a foreign employ©o I think that the word *adjoinirg' should be held to cover all Arab States of the Arab littoral of the Gulfo 3c I would also suggest that the Company should be required to get Political Agent's, Bahrain, concurrence with all orders for alcoholic liquors for Dhubis before they are placed* This would give us check on account (sic ? amount) of drinkir^ (? omission) oil fieldsr. At first sight, this may not seem our business. but T if there is disturbance, it is on Political Agent that trouble will fall* 4° I am not quite clear about proposed addition to article 11 5./ —— — *--•*&gt; —r-W.— * ' - . — —L 5 0 New article 2(3 C I think that the Sheikh and the i Company should both be obliged to consult His Majesty a Government about the banko 1 am inserting paragraph in draft letter to the Sheikh and suggest clause be inserted in political agreement, 6 0 Draft letters will be posted by air mail leaving Buahire 15th September,Colonel Fowle. Would you now kindly give your observations on various points which are outstanding on this file regarding P.C.L.*8 negotiations for Trucial Coast concessions; and in particular Debai# (1) The time has come to agree with the Company on the text of the political agreement, I attach a draft letter to Mr. Longrigg on this subject. Perhaps you would look at it, particularly at the suggested new clause about the protection of the Company^ employees, and let me know whether you agree. It is, of course, based on the alterations suggested in India Office Express l, Letter of 3rd April in which you concurred in your FJt * Express Letter of 29th May (Flag a), k** t; k ti* (2) Please see the new additions to the Debai Concession which have resulted from Major Holmes^ conversations with the Sheikh. As I explained to you % Luavsifc, these are sidelined in red in the printed copy with a * white cover given us by the Company. You will remember that in our discussion with Mr. Longrigg the other day he said that the Company were anxious not to have toalter the text of the actual concession if they can avoid it and it may be possible, if we do not like the additions quite as they stand, to deal with the points in the accompanying Political Agreement and/or the Exchange of Notes with the sheikh. On the other hand, as it appears that the Sheikh and Holmes have only initialled the Articles and not formally signed the Concession, there may not be any overwhelming difficulty about altering the Concession text. However, all this depends on the extent ft JU U\M tu pUAftc ryar of the alterations which we require. t** CUu^J (3) please see Mr. Longrigg f s letter of 2nd September about the refusal of the Sheikhs of Shargah and Ras-al- Khaimah to give the necessary guarantee regarding protection of the Company^ employees. The suggestion is that a maximum might be set on the compensation to be paid. What are your views on this? (4) Our telegram of 27th August to ^fetfe Acting Resident and Bahrein telegram of the 29th August leave the present position in regard to tjie^t)ebai Concession rather in the air. Perhaps ijt^fould be worth sending a short telegram in the t^nfs of the draft attached. u, fo*tU /UVh, P° h* ^ M T- 1 ':-9 SEP 1936 { Arty* rfeply to this letter should be ad&amp;resfced to the Director, Petroleum Dept. Telephone : Victoria 9310. Telegrams: Mintndust, Sowest, London. Reference No.:-P.D. 859/ 7 • PETROLEUM DEPARTMEN (Mines Department), Dean Stanley Street. Millbank, Dear Clauson, f ; • A Li* ■ i VI ■ / 1 London, S.W.l. 4th September, 1936 (7 K3 aJ In reply to your letter^-io-'-Snarling of 28th August, No.P.Z.6135/36, we have now had an opportunity of examining the draft Gommeroial Agreement for Dibai in the form finally agreed between Holmes and the Sheikh and have one or two comments to offer before the Agreement is finally concluded. The financial terms are presumably largely a matter for arrangement between the Company and the Sheikh and I am not sure in the case of the Trucial Sheikhdoms how far we are justified in raising questions with the Oompany on these terms. Subject, however, to the important point mentioned below, they appear on the whole to be fair and reasonable. The important point which results from the modification made in the original draft of the Royalty Clause is that until the Company declares the discovery of oil in commercial quantities, or is deemed to have done so on obtaining the LI. J. Clauson, Esq*, India Office, Whitehall, S.W. 1.I—- — o _ substantial production of S,000 tons per day, they would not, as I understand the position, have to pay any royalty at all on their production• They would merely pay the anriual sum of Rs.25,000 v/hich would be a somewhat poor return for a production of say 1,000 tons per day. I imagine that this is simply a drafting error in the revised Article 5(c), as the original draft Concession provided at all stages for annual payments or royalty at Rs. 3 per ton, v/hichever is the greater and I suggest that the point should be mentioned to the Company on that assumption. A further point is that, as in the Qatar Agreement, it seems desirable to maintain the principle of having a separate provision for the payment of royalty on natural gas produced and sold and for this purpose a royalty of Annas 2 per 1,000 cubic feet appears suitable and might be suggested to the Company. This would entail making a consequential amendment to Article 5(d) so as to exclude natural gas from the 'substances” won and saved in respect of which the draft provides for royalty at the rate of Rs. 3 per ton . Of course, it is not likely that any natural gas will be sold in these territories for a considerable time, if ever, but in concluding an Agreement which may run for 75 years the point is one which I suggest might be put to the Company.Military Branch. 4th September 1936, My dear Clauson, In reply to your letter of the 28th August, No.P.Z.6135/36, about the Trucial Coast Oil Negotiations, I write to confirm that we have no comments to make on the final text of the draft Commercial Concession for Dibai. Yours sincerely, OAH/ M.J. Clauson, Esq., India Office, S. W. 1. — m —«* - —UC/AW. Ftf C' t 64 \ \ 1_9 o S j (99 groups) 3962. DECT PHER OE TELEGRAM* //w ^ From Acting Political Resident in the Persian Gulf to Secretary of State (COPIES for India. CIRCULATED) . Dated Shiraz, 4th September, 1936. Received 4th September, 1936, 3.45 p.m* T/129. X Addressed to Secretary of State for India, repeated to Political Agent, Bahrein, copy sent by sea mail to the Government of India. Your telegram dated 27th August, 2456. I am awaiting modifications mentioned in paragraph lfa. 1 , which are being sent from Bahrein. 2 . Sheikh has asked if he may sign concession, informing Holmes at the same time in writing that it can only be considered binding if His Majesty’s Government approve and if the political agreement is made. I agreed to his doing so as I was anxious lest delay might make the Sheikh or hie relations alter their mind. 3. I hear informally that Holmes’s final draft of concession has been lost in the Soipio, but (though i have not yet seen the modifications)I think that it would be a pity V} require Holmes to reopen negotiations in order to make changes s if it can be avoided. 4. Draft letters will be prepared as soon as I get the modifications. Looh./ TELEPHONE : NATIONAL 3582 TELEGRAMS : INLAND : PETCONCESS, FINSQUARE, LONDON FOREIGN : PETCONCESS, LONDON '•4 SEP 1956 v^_ CODES : BENTLEY’S SECOND PHRASE BENTLEY’S COMPLETE PHRASE WITH OIL SUPPLEMENT LOMBARD PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LIMITED DIRECTORS : Sir John Cadman, G.C.M.G. (Chairman) A. Agnew, C.B.E. R. Cayrol, D.S.O., D.S.C. (French) W. Fraser C. S. Gulbei (formerly Armenian) J. B. A. Kessi. {Dutch) Sir John B. Lloyd J. A. Meny (French) H. G. Seidel (U.S.A.) R. W. Sellers J. Skliros PC.29/81 CITY-GATE HOUSE FINSBURY SQUARE LONDON 2nd September, • E.C.2 1936. 1 cd ui LU &gt; -J u_ ( o m~X 5 r CO KO or? a. a -ZL m Ql» CO CL. u J 1 UJ i F ' CO K 5 My dear Clauson. In order to keep you fully posted as to the state of our negotiations with the Shaikh of Dubai, I will give you the text of recent telegrams passing between us and Major Holmes, sub sequent to my letter to you dated August 24th:- (1) P.C.L. telegram to Major Holmes dated August 24th, 1956 : M Your telegram of August 23rd Approval of H-3.M.G# without which Concession cannot be in force must wait for firstly India Office approval of text secondly Political Agreement between Company and India Office. Regarding text approval is being sought urgently and will be probably forthcoming. Regarding Political Agreement this cannot be concluded with in the next few days. On the whole I see little objection to payment of money by you on receiving Shaikh’s signature. His proviso in separate letter that validity depends upon consent of H-B.M.C* is necessary and not dangerous. Can his letter also state that money returnable in the event of H.B.M.C. consent being withheld? Hope that India Office will wire Bushire agreement to text with a day or two”. (2) P«C,I. telegram to Major Holmes dated August 25th, 1936: 'India Office have studied revised text and are likely to approve it provided Political Resident has no objection to last paragraph of Article 10. It is however always under stood that filial approval of K.B.M.G. is conditional on acceptance by Shaikh and by us of various conditions which will be embodied in subsequent letters and agreements. To this extent letter of proviso suggested by Shaikh appears inevitable and need not delay payment”.2 \ (3) P»C»L. telegram to Itejor Holmes dated august 27th, 1936: ’’India Of fie© postpone definite agreement to revised text until they can consult Fowle which they expect to do on September 1st. India Office meanwhile is telegraphing Bushire interim and conditional agreement. India Office do not like thirtieth and thirtyfirst words of Article 3 and would like to substitute ’’everything which is extracted therefrom”. Can you without difficulty make this change?” (4) Major Holmes* telegram to P»C.L. dated .august 31st, 1956: ”1 have to-day 12th Jam&amp;d Thani received letter from Ruler Dubai dated 10th Jamad Thani. First paragraph of letter states ’’Holmes had told Ruler 10 days ago that there was only the letter of approval of H.B.M.G. which concerned Ruler to make concession effective” Second paragraph states ”0n the 8th Jamad Thani Holmes informed Ruler of receipt of telegram from S^H. Longrigg informing Holmes to take careful note that letter dealing with oil concession agreement would also have to be agreed to and signed by Ruler Company and H.B.M.G.” Third paragraph 'As you cannot inform me of contents of this second letter we after careful consideration have decided postpone signing concession until arrival of letter of approval from H.B.M.G. and of the above mentioned second paragraph of letter to be signed by Ruler Company and H.B.M.G.' Fourth paragraph ’’However in the meantime Ruler is prepared to initial separately each of the 27 articles final draft Agreement as agreed between Ruler and Holmes but Ruler will not initial Agreement as a whole but if Holmes agrees Ruler will initial the Articles forthwith”. Holmes sees nothing narmful except period delay and recommends that Holmes initials the Articles with Ruler. Holmes feels strongly that the time has come for him to con sult with London as Dubai area cannot be isolated because Dubai and Abu Dhabi are complementary to each other so any delay regarding completing Dubai will be compensated by avoiding same difficulties with Abu Dhabi. Holmes foresees considerable delay but the Ruler who is driven by his family is our staunch friend and therefore delay though disappointing is not iiarmful especially as it provides an interim during which Holmes can consult with London regarding whole position here which is not simple. I have opportunity going by boat to Kuwait 4th September as Airways is much disorganised Intend taking above opportunity. The intense heat is becoming too much for me after 90 days of it and lately it has been excessive to almost an unbearable degree”.(5) P»C»L. telegram to Major Holmes dated September 1st, 1936: '’Your telegram dated 31st August final ratification of Con cession by H.B.M.G. must depend upon conclusion of separate subsequent Agreement between H.B.1T-Cr. and Ruler as well as between H*B.T.T*G. and Company. You should secure Ruler's signature to Concession and make payment if possible and accept any letter of proviso which he may address to you. If Ruler refuses signature you can adopt procedure described your telegram of 31st ultimo.. rully appreciate your desire to leave Dubai and look forward to your arrival here'. (6) l^ajor Holmes' telegram to P»C»L. dated September lst» 1936: 'Ruler Dubai has initialled 27 articles separately of Con cession ^igreement. holmes also initialled it. I am leaving direct for Kuwait by aeroplane 3rd September'. The last of these telegrams was received since I had the pleasure of seeing you and Colonel Kowle at your office this morning. It appears to me that we shall now have a breathing-space in which to proceed with the Political agreement, and your ratification of the text of the Concession. This should, I hope, mean that your definite approval and the Shaikh's definite signature may be forthcoming with in a few weeks. Yours sincerely, L'.J. Clauson Esq., India Office, Whitehall, S.W.l.f - Z -. bZl _ c &gt;) y £ w p i u e c.o imiK ©F^ICJI, WUITi^HAlL* S.W.l. 2nd September 1936. Vy dear Longrigg, In my letter of the 27th August, P.Z.6135/36, I «aid thnt we were telegraphing to the Political Resident on the subject of the Dubai Conceseion. In our telegram we atated that we understand from the Company that agreement had been reached with the 'Iheikh on the basis of the original draft oonceseion with certain modifications which presumably would h ve been co munic^ted to the Political Resident and the Political Agent, Bahrain. We h^re since had a telegram from the Political Agent saying that he has not received a copy of the proposed Agreement. It would appear, therefore, on the face of it that Major Holmes was failing to keep the Political Resident, and through him the Political Agent, informed of the progress of his negotiation*? with the Trucial fJheikhe. It is, of course, vitally important that he should do so/ S.H.Longrigg, 4sq. Petroleum Concessions Ltd., City Cate House, Finsbury Square, iS.C. 2./ A technical point which has occurred to us in going through the draft Concession is that it seems desirable that there should be a provision on somewhat the same lines as in paragraph 3 of the Third Article of the Qatar Agreement to the effect that ’’accurate geological maps, and records of the wells drilled, should be kept, v/hich should be open to inspection by the Sheikh or his authorised representative”. I am sending a copy of this letter to Brenan and Seal. *ours sincerely, HBWS/JS.2. bo, and this was in fact apecifically , rjertioned in paragraph 3 (2) of 'alton’s letter to Skliro# dated 2nd April, N o. P. Z. 2078/36. Perhaps you would consider sending a telegram to Major Holmes asicing him whether he has in fact kept the Political Agent informed and if not asking him to do so. I understand from our conversation this morning thst Major Holmes is coming home very shortly and that in the meantime he is concentrating on trying to get a signature or initial from the Sheikh subject to the final approval of His Majesty’s aovernment. Yours sincerely, (Sgd.) M. J. CLAUSOIMCONFIDENTIAL. No. 650-S of 1936. « The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to 1 , H 1 b Pajen+y’B Gecretar^r of /Hate for India, London, 2. The ^oreiftn Secretary 1 o the Governnert of India, Simla. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment Osjf. British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. 8 th August 1936. Dated Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. ^ele^ram Ho.933 of r Hh Aiifniat 1936 from the Political '’’rucial Coast - Oil. A^rent, Bahrain.3872 FILE COPY r DECYPHER Off TEIBGRAMo Prom Political Agent, Bahrein, to Political Resident in the Persian Gulf and repeated 'by the former to Secretary of State for India 0 Dated Sharjah, 29th August, 1936 0 Received 9*15 p o m 0 , 29th August, 1936 0 lp ? Addressed to Pol-tical Resident in the Persian Gulf, repeated to Secretary of State for India 0 Secretary of State for India*s telegram 2456, paragraph No 0 lo I hare not received a copy of proposed agreementoDraft Paper. ? 7 political Department. DRAFT From Secretary of State To Political Resident in Persian Gulf, repeated to Political Agent,Bahrein X T3LSGRAM. I 0^ Copy to I^ia (A.M.non secret) ■Admiralty Petr .Dept / j a*u&lt; JkitA [ka*\ br 0^' AXtj, + y •iAwli^yCXi Q 'It n CLOSURE, in Am WAIL LEI NO. 3 6 29AUGW56 PROM SECr.tlAIvV, P0L1 1 1 j J SECRET DEPT. INDIA d '' ■7/y r. J-7/W 5-as*V x Vs + A i Addressed Political Resident in ✓ the Persian Gulf repeated Bahrein, copy hy air mail to Government of India. , 'S’ ' Bushire express letter to Bahrein no. st, / ✓ ^ 289-S dated 14th April and connected ✓ S * * correspondence regarding Trucial Oil ✓ ^ ' Negotiations^ Company state that agreement has Been reached with Sheikh ✓ s ^ •&gt; of Dihai on basis of original draft S' s s' concession with certain modifications f which particulars are being sent by ai\ mail. Only alterations which appeVr to concern us are (a) new provision whereby Sheikh may request company to deport from State any foreign employee 'committing an offence which may cause disorder or interfere with the religious or nrpral laws or interfere with the politics orWbjects of the State or excite them to sedition.' Deportation \ is not to be ordered before 'the charge is fully considered the Sheikh and the Company'. (b) new provision\for appointment of a local man to be paidkby Company to 'act as a confidential person as between the Sheikh and the Company* s\Representative and to assist in procuring th^labour that the Company may require.' Presumably there is no obj 5000 5.36 479-ifb4&gt;—Jt may be desirable s ' s y e.g. in case Sheikh and Company disagree y S * y to reserve final decision regarding expulsion of foreign employees to Political Resident. But this might be covered in f * * * Political Agreement with Company and / s'. S ' Jixchange of Notes with Sheikh which will ' y S'* ^ be necessary before Concession is finally S' ' y approve^ I should be glad of your views y y on this point. 9 2-T Company are -particularly anxious that Sheikh ^should be informedf as soon as possible''that' H.M.g/ see no objection to^ r / , p« ifa* draft Concession in final form£&gt; Sttbject flirt. f^yur^L 'u* ' t-e ( -any oboervation-s- yon may ho ve-t-o-make / „ , , / I-would suggest that Sheikh should now be / informed that there is no objection t his signing concession' witbf text as how agreed^provide'd he makeS^his signature subject to subsequent approval of ft ^ ^ fhis approval will not finally be given till Political Agreement has been signed betweeh^H.M.G. and 6 ompany and until Sheikh lias exchanged lettei^s with H.M.G. (pJ on lines of^those^ relating to Qatar r ^ t*r Concession'but ^rith addition of formal ^ / &lt;/ r f undertaking regarding protection (see ray y y J/ f r rr Expres/letter of 3rd April, P/Z. &amp;678/36). 3 Substance of^Political Agreement has been agreed with Company^except for Refinery^lau^e which i'S' still under consideration*''-'Meanwhile please let me have draft of aoQompanying letter to fa uf&lt; ^ ^ Sheikh. 1INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL, S.W.l. P.Z^ 6 1 35/5 6 &gt; 27th August 1935. I-nmecUate. &gt; My dear Longrigg, I write in reply to your letter of the 24th August, P.C.29/64, about the Dubai Concession. We have looked at the modifications which have been introduced into the text of the Draft Concession as a result of the negotiations between Major Holmes and the Sheilch. There is at least one substantial change, namely the addition to Article 10, which requires consideration. Prima facie it appears to us to be satisfactory, but the local political authorities may have views to express on it. For instance, it may be desirable for provision to be made for the Political Resident to be the final authority as regards the disposal of European employees of the Company who are alleged to have ccmmitted some offence; but this is a matter which may well be dealt with in the Political Agreement and in the Exchange of Notes between His S.H.Lcngrigg, Esq., Majesty's/ Petroleum Concessions Ltd., City Gate House, Finsbury Square, E.C.2.2 . Majesty's Government and the Sheildi. On the whole, therefore, and subject to any observations by the local authorities, we are disposed to the view that the text of the Concession as finally agreed contains nothing which will cause His Majesty's Government eventually to withhold their consent to it. Before, however, we do anything we are anxious to discuss the matter with Colonel Fowl© who will be arriving in London on deputation early next week. We are accordingly telegraphing to the Political Resident suggesting that, subject to any observations he may have to offer, and if Colonel Fowle agrees, the Sheikh should now be informed that there is no objection to his signing the Concession with the text as now agreed, provided that he makes his signature subject to the subsequent approval of His Majesty's Government. It will be explained to him that this approval will not finally be given until a Political Agreement of a satisfactory kind has been signed by His Majesty's Government and the Company and until the Sheikh has exchanged letters with His Majesty's Government on the lines of those relating to the Q,atar Concession, with the addition of a formal undertaking/;/ 4 . 3. undertaking regarding the protection of the Company’s employees. The substance of the Political Agreement, except for the Refinery Clause (as to which we await a letter from you) has been agreed, I think, with the Company. We will send you very shortly a draft text for your approval. The Exchange of Rotes between His Majesty’s Government and the Sheikh will include the recognition by him of the Political Agreement and must therefore be subsequent to the conclusion of that Agreement. At the moment, therefore, the only thing that seems to be holding us up is the Refinery Clause. Yours sincerely, ad.) M. J. CLAUSON P.S. There is one small point which we ought to have raised before but omitted to do so. In connection with the draft Bahrein Lease Mr.Walton (in his letter to Mr.Skliros dated 19th March, p.Z. 1834/36), suggested that/that ’’Cognate substances” in Article 3 was a vague term and that something like ’’everything which is extracted therefrom” would be better. Mr.Skliros in his reply of 2Cth March said he had no objection to the change. We had intended, of course, to suggest the change in all the drafts. There 1 would perhaps be no difficulty, if you agree, in incorporating this change in the Dubai Concession fcfoife. signature ?TELEPHONE : NATIONAL 3582 TELEGRAMS : INLAND : PETCONCESS, FINSQUARE, LONDON FOREIGN : PETCONCESS, LONDON IA V ' V CODES BENTLEY’S SECOND PHRASE BENTLEY’S COMPLETE PHRASE WITH OIL SUPPLEMENT LOMBARD DIRECTORS : Sir John O^man, G.C.M.G. (Chairman) A. Agn*«0- R. Cayrv , D.S.C. (French) W. Fraser, C.b. v C. S. Gulbenkian (formerly Armenian) J. B. A. Kessler (Dutch) Sir John B. Lloyd J. A. Meny (French) H. G. Seidel (U.S.A.) R. W. Sellers J. Skliros PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LIMITED CITY-GATE HOUSE fch frfo' FINSBURY SQUARE PC.29/64SV r LONDON E.C.2 D *7. R 24th August, 1936. My dear Clauson, With reference to our telephone conversation of this morning, I enclose the text of the Dubai Concession, as already seen and approved by you, and the final text, as now awaiting signature at Dubai, The former is dated 19.1.36, on the cover, which is pale green; the second is undated and has a white cover. I have marked in the latter copy, with red pencil, the points which are added to, or altered from, the earlier draft. It would be very greatly appreciated if you could look at these and confirm (in writing or by telephone) that the final draft contains nothing which will cause H.B.M.G. to withhold their consent thereto. The position at the moment is that the Shaikh of Dubai will sign the revised text if instructed by the Political Resident (through the Political Agent, Bahrain, who is reported to be now at Sharjah). Would it therefore be possible for you to cable to Bushire (or Bahrain, or Sharjah) giving your blessing to the revised text? I appreciate, of course, that none of this has anything to do with the Political Agreement which you and we shall subsequently enter into. It would be greatly appreciated if you could treat this matter as of some urgency. COPY SENT EY AIR MAIL ^ 28 AUG 1936 -to Yours sincerely. M.J. Clauson Esq., India Office, Whitehall, S.W. 1. EflCLOSURE IN All WAIL LETTER—j NO. 3 5 1 26 AUG 1956 | FROM SECRETARY, POLITICAL AMD SECRET DEPT. INDIA OFFICE* / V DUBAI CONCSSSIOK- Modifications made in original draft. Article 1. Omit 'as shown generally on the map annexed heret o'. Renumber Article 1 as Article 1 (a) and add.- (b) But the Company shall refrain frcm working or entering for the present into the area upon which the town named Katta A1 Jabaliyah is located until the Shaikh grants the Company permission to do so. (c) The Area in the Dubai Khor surveyed by Imperial Airways Limited and granted by the Shaikh to the Imperial Airways for their commercial Air Liners and all concerned with that area is entirely excluded for the purposes of this Agreement. Article 2. Add:- 'The expression year, month and day used in this Agreement shall mean what is consistent with the English Solar Calendar and not any other. Further, the weights mentioned in this Agreement shall be reckoned on the English Ton of 2,240 lbs. Article 5 (a) Add:- 'Rupees 60,000 (Sixty Thousand)' (b) Delete, and substitute:- 'Rupees 200,000 (Two hundred thousand) within a period of sixty (60) days from the date upon which the Company declares in writing to the Shaikh that substances have been discovered in commercial quantities. If the Company should fail to declare so sooner, then the date of discovery of substances in commercial quantities shall be that date upon which the Company has completed and tested a well or wells capable of producing in accordance/accordance with first class oil practice not less than two thousand (2000) English Tons of clean substances per day for a period of thirty (30) consecutive days.” (c) Delete and substitute:- ’’Rupees 25,000 (Twenty five thousand) at the end of each year from the date of signature hereof until the Company declares in writing to the Shaikh that Substances have been discovered in commercial quantities in accordance with the Sub-Clause (o) of this Article 5.'' Add (d) ”At the end of every subsequent year fron the date that the Company makes in writing to the Shaikh the declaration that the Substances have been discovered in commercial quantities Rupees Eighty Thousand (80,000) or Rupees Three (3) per English Ton of 2,240 lbs. in respect of the Substances won and saved during the preceding Calendar year, whichever is greater.' Retain last paragraph. Article 9. Add (c) 'The Company may import such alcoholic drink and liquors as the Company may require for the use of their foreign employees but only with the written permission of the Shaikh, but the Company shall not sell or give alcoholic drinks or liquors to the Subjects of the Shaikh or to the Subjects of adjoining Rulers who may be employed within the State. Article 10. Add two paragraphs as follows:- 'But the Company’s employees shall not interfere or by their actions cause any disturbance or cause opposition to the Shaikh’s authority within the State3. of Dubai and the employees shall not go beyond the limit of their duties when employed within or when leaving the confines of the State of Dubai for the purpose of this Agreement. Further in the event of any of the Company’s employees - whether he be a senior or a junior employee- committing an offence which may cause disorder, or interfere with the religious or moral laws or interfere with the politics or Subjects of the State of Dubai or excite them to sedition, then the Shaikh may request the Local Representative of the Company to send the person concerned - if a foreigner - out of the State of Dubai, but if a Subject of the Shaikh then the Shaikh may arrest the culprit and deal with him according to the laws of the State of Dubai. But it is agreed by the Shaikh and the Company that before ordering deportation of any foreign employee that the charge is fully considered by the Shaikh and the Company.' Article 11. Add at end 'provided it is for the purposes of this Agreement 1‘ Article 14. Add new paragraph:- 'Further, the fact of the Company employing Subjects of the Shaikh shall not in any way whatever alter the Status of such employees in respect of their rights, privileges and duties as Subjects of the Shaikh, and such employees will remain-in all ways - subject to the jurisdiction of the laws and under the legal authority of the Shaikh in his capacity as the Ruler of the State of Dubai.' Article/4. * \ Article 21. Substitute 'Development' for 'Concessions'. ^ Article 25. Add new paragraph between existing paragraphs as follows:- 'Should the Shaikh decide to grant permission for a Bank to open a branch or Agency in Dubai the Shaikh shall consult with the Company as to which Bank shall be given the permission.' Article 25. Renumber Article 27 and insert new Article 26 as follows:- 'The Shaikh may select in consultation with the Local Representative of the Company a local man to act as a confidential person as between the Shaikh and the Company’s Representative and to assist in procuring the labour that the Company may require. The salary of the Shaikh’s confidential person so appointed shall be paid by the Company, through the Shaikh in Dubai and shall be at the rate of Rupees Four hundred (400) per month.'This is an Agreement made at on the day of 1936, corresponding to the day of 1354 between HIS EXCELLENCY SHAIKH SAID BIN MAKTUM AL-HASHER in the exercise of his powers as RULER OF DUBAI, ARABIA, on his own behalf and on behalf of and in the name of his heirs and successors in whom is or shall be vested for the time being the responsiblity for the control and Government of the State of Dubai ( hereinafter called “ The Shaikh ”) of the one part and Petroleum Concessions Limited, a Company recistered in Great Britain under the Companies Act, 1929, its successors and assigns (hereinafter called “The Company” ) of the second part. ARTICLE 1. The area to which this Agreement applies (hereinafter referred to as “ The State”) is the State of Dubai, including all Islands and Territorial Waters apperain- ing thereto, as shewn generally on the map annexed hereto. (3 Cj-vic. i—#U.i j ^ 1 \ So'—j L» ^ NT® t O J* iUU! i.UL_j ^jc- ^ Jjl b 3’- ) 3 ^JailH £j\ jL&gt;.l NAtA , -&gt;-L \^,J, 3’ \f* ^_ji) * j * jl l|.» lil&gt;-J • jb* 3ij* ( ^ l* • a* ^jl — 3 jVI Sibil i SjLl ( • ^b»Vl Juo !&lt;&gt;» 3 ) *;*1aiVI 3 ^rfba. l—X i«Ul •LUj ARTICLE 2. The period of this Agreement shall be T5 years from the date of signature. ARTICLE 3. The Shaikh hereby grants to the Company the exclusive right to explore search for drill for produce and win natural gas asphalt ozokerite crude petroleum and their products and cognate Substances (hereinafter referred to as “ The Substances ”) within the State, the exclusive ownership of all the Substances so produced and won, the right to refine transport sell for use within and without the State or for export and to export or otherwise deal with or dispose of the Substances, and the right to import export pump ship or otherwise transport the Substances across or to any country or place at the Company’s disc retion and the right to do all things necessary for the purpose of these oper ations. _ &lt;11 bill i^bll , fl-iCL-U b t .i li»- j| l 5 *~1 3 II 3^ JV-i-l jl rb-*V ij *jVl j\ b t rb»^?*iA-^j bib - 1 Jaiillj *1*, JTj3jVIj wU—VI i*.isr_» A.) \c» '. t JI ;LiLil ) b^ip- 3 II aI^II jl iiyJL \ bi»J ijlAVI ( € ^1^4 5 j b*&gt;- 3H a! y! 3 jl #jLVI ^ jU- _jl aI^II Ji.j * • * (J, J&gt;~\ i» | *1 j&gt;\ * I • J&gt;_ A^i • y A^dU A«tj ^JAJ J } a! jC-'b j) 3 t^V jl A^\jl JC’ b|Ii»» jl If.lsfcij oLJiall aI^II 3 *'*} 3 ^'^^ -r^b! c^l Ijm -?I . Jl/Vl •A* i&gt; *LiVl— 2 — Y ARTICLE 4. If hereafter any neutral Mk zone is created adjacent to the territory cf the State, wherein the Shaikh shall have a co-equal and joint interest, the Shaikh hereby agrees to grant to the Company an oil concession over *uch neutral zone on terms to be agreed between the Shaikh, the Company, and the joint ruler of such Neutral Zone. ARTICLE 5. In consideratiou of the rights granted by the Shaikh by this Agreement the Company shall pay to the Shaikh (a) on signature of the Agreement Rupees (b) at the end of each year of the first five years from the date of signature rupees or rupees three (3) per English ton of 2,240 lbs. in respect of the substances won and saved during the preceding calender year, whichever is greater. (c) at the end of the sixth and every subsequent year from the date of signature rupees or rupees three 3 per English ton of 2.240 lbs. in respect of the substances won and saved during the preceding calendar year, whichever is greater. In calculating royalty for the purpose of this article account shall not be taken of any of the Substances used by the Com pany in its operations or used by the Com pany’s employees within the State, nor of any water or foreign matter which may be produced with the Substances. ARTICLE 6. The Company shall not carry on any operations within areas occu pied by or devoted to the purposes of mosques, sacred buildings or graveyards. m Ai • -X» 1^1 •-X* ^31 • • 1 iilalll *JkJk jJj li-* I i.iI aT VI ^ ^.5 yJI Jut ( I ) jjVi 0 . J (v) oLjj ir^r (r) ^^i •**? ^1 jly .1 * ^*1 &lt;A&gt; Im.1I . J^TVI ^i A,*-**' A» Ij- ^ ^-jL.11 ^ ^ ) ^&gt;jlr iJ l*' jjs 4‘A?\ ilA uP u 6, ( r ) ^ ^ ^11 ^l^ll A^a&gt;- Y Y t * ^lll aA&gt;LJ! a-—^J l CJI . sf • A A A* I y J.iT JUC_J Kj I laAl I yp- I ^C- A&gt;-1 a Jkc I y -. » • ijLVI y*-* 0 « 4*-*—{JI t^l^l ^11 A-i jill jl^tlj •Lll lw») I J-i I *Jl tJ 3 A) V&gt; VI| Aj ^&gt;■“11 -^** 1 A-^ Ul •jlll ^»I^&gt;*U Awt^i^-I JI Al^Lill ^LUI y+i* Jl— . ^I-Xllj A^Aii! aJuVIjcond man thodi to p petn close and shall as t&lt; oper; traat A tha Com] state won year have with said shall and state open by tl have stanc and 1 utem supp] equif mate natui empl herei articl free or ol perse chan perse to th time in A] the ( incor Subs3 — r ARTICLE 7. The Company shall conduct its operations in a workmanlike manner and by appropriate scientific me thods and shall take all reasonable measures to prevent the ingress of water to any petroleum - bearing strata and shall duly close any unproductive holes drilled by it and subsequently abandoned. The Company shall keep the Shaikh informed generally as to the progress and result of its drilling operations but such information shall be treated as confidential. Ul/l ^jl Ul oW CjIa.L iiuL a &gt; I aUlI i!^i«ll ^11 jiX-\ ^ JwT jlj ^1 L.lc ii^j ARTICLE 8. Within three months after the expiry of each calendar year, the Company shall deliver to the Shaikh a statement of the amount of the Substances won and saved during the said calendar year and of the royalty which is or might have been payable under Article 5, together with a report of its operations during the said year. The Shaikh or his representative shall have the right to check such returns and statements, and all such returns and statements and the reports of the Comany’s operations shall be treated as confidential by the Shaikh. ARTICLE 9. (a) The Company shall have the right to import water, the Sub stances, fuel, machinery, motor - cars and lorries,aircraft, equipment, plant, timber, utensils, iron work, building materials, food supplies, medicines, medical supplies, office equipment and household furniture, and other materials, equipment and goods of whatsoever nature required by the Company and its employees for the purpose of its operations hereunder and to export the Substances and articles previously imported by the Company free of customs or export duty and taxes or other charges, but it shall pay on all personal goods, clothing and gsneral mer chandise imported by the Company for the personal use of its employees or for resale to them the ordinary duty in force for the time being in the State. Saving as in Article 5 and in this Article provided, the Company, its personnel, its operations, income, profits and properly including the Substances shall be exempt and free during the period of this Agreement from all present or future harbour duties, import duties, export duties, taxes, imposts and charges of any kind whether State or local, tolls and land surface rent of whatever nature. ^ I — oUJI *,*..*« liL&gt; 1 I J j** &lt;*«..• lit-! &lt;o 11 . il^Jl ^ • • • I * oliljl • j.»&gt; 4»&gt;-l J* &lt;3^ £r.«£.l!j oli LI! «.xjk j Is •^Ss._]lj • a&gt; aJT^oII J'^li ^ 3 ^ ( 1 «^lll yVIJ oL.’i L-llj ^l^llj *1—11 J O^A-ll_j OljLkllj olj^J^lllj oV^TUl^.Ubl^j Ole O- VI, otl,^l'j 1^-11 O^A«, o^a. 1!, &lt;,,^V1 _j j* ^‘L«Jlj 0^11, olj^Vl JA OUi &gt;cj ioull lil^V j &lt;&gt;^li^ b? y olj^Vlj ^1^11 oUVl i.J’jUl All ,*11 ^ ^ 3 1 y\ U^l I • • . ^a ,1 ^i_Jual)l j*,-, ,|o^i-| A .war&gt;cOll ^ l^a»! Jli 1^»_\—1 , ^| a?)’[* ijy.~S ^11 ^M«a.llj ot-^ill, At 3 —(^*^11 o &gt;31 *3 1 ^ 3 —^)i l«J .«1&gt;1 •jl_ll 3 ^ l AC L &lt;»1, lil/l, \ t .i]e&gt;fAj jli i^lll *A_* 3 ^^— 4 — In consideration of the right herein granted the Company shall pay-in addition to the Royalty per ton of Rupees ( 3 ) three as provided in Article 5 - to the Shaikh within (3) three months after the close of each calender year the sum of (4) four annas per English ton of 2,240 lbs. in respect of the Substances won and saved during the said calendar year. (B) The importation by the Company of firearms and other weapons is prohibited, except with the written permission of the Shaikh ARTICLE 10. The employees of the Company shall be allowed to enter into and to leave the State at all times without let or hindrance and free of all charge, and the Shaikh shall grant to the Company’s employees every facility required for the purpose of the Company’s operations hereunder. ARTICLE 11. (a) For the purpose of its operations hereunder the Company shall have the right without hindrance to construct, maintain and operate power stations, refineries, pipelines and storage tanks, facilities for water supply including boring for water, telegraph and telephone lines and installations and wireless instal lations, roads, railways, tramways, buildings, ports, harbours, harbour works, aircraft, buildings and landing places for aircraft, wharves and jetties, oil and coaling stations, with such lighting as may be requisite and any other facilities or works which the Company may consider necessary and for such purposes to use free of all payments any stone, sand, gravel, gypsum, lime, clay or similar materials or water which may be available provided always that the inhabitants of the State are not prevented from taking their usual require ments of these materials and that the water supply of the local inhabitants and nomad population who may be dependent on the same is not endangered. The Company at L*^II J (jp oIai VI • ^ 2 ^I iJ \^^\3 • * • * m * &lt;il -Vj‘I^c .1 i ; L^ |*l £&gt;.xi' i_.5li»VI ^ ,3^ 3; ^ ^ ^11 jo I^*1! 3oL ij T ^ 1—&gt;■ • L&lt;aii| JU&gt; 'jf~\ ••i^l I £jjl jf • j'J TYt* jjr . kSi 'All 3 &lt;, jU\ &lt;&gt;tl-.VI ^1 jC-l jjzi\ Jf- {^&gt;) . ^.^1^ jSl VI ~UVI jjl (3*— • ^.iUI i^lll jl ^iil« oj!«V! • J + l^&gt;- jl til I 3^111 £lc jlj 3* 3‘lt . &lt;JU;VI »-v&gt; ^ *■-' 3^1 &lt;;l (I) i.^li-1 ;^UI j^l ’SyJi jf» m ji UUrVI .A* j o : U Jf- • c5 i*rji jru ^1 ^KiliVl j&gt; ^11 J«U.J -xJy J' I* *bilj *111 jU ^ dl!3 J lc .Ul ^Ul 3^lallj &lt;i&gt; liillj jjAi'Jlj v3l yid\ i.A&gt;Vlj A^L&gt;-j ^oL*j jljAal) &lt;A VIj *ol^llj vljUa^J ^je&gt;l^ll_J Ai_w?jVlj oljl-Ll 1 djjr ^ • j A JjliVI dll A j* A._ Lj ^,&gt;eillj iA^dJI U jC*r ^.1 JI^Vl jl oy^Ail ^a ^1 3Aj - • Ja jJIj .jUti-' ijA &lt;_JI I 4 * ^5* c5l ja dUj L _j| jUIA3 j^-!j J^LII ji 3jn—t c^All •lll_* I ol J&gt;VI— 5 — — • — its discretion may select the position of any such works. The Company may likewise install and operate without hindrance all such means of transportation by land, air and water as may be necessary for the effective conduct of its operations hereunder. (b) The Company shall under normal conditions accept and transmit free of charge on its wireless and telegraph in stallations such of the Shaikh’s messages as will not interfere with the Company’s business, and in times of national emergency the Shaikh shall have the necessary use free of charge of the Company’s wireless and telegraph installations and railways for governmental purposes. ( c ) The Shaikh’s ships shall have the right to use harbours utilised or constructed by the Company provided that such use in no way hampers the Company or interferes in any way with the safety of its operations of which the Company shall be the sole judge. Any wharves or appurtenances con structed by the Company shall be for its exclusive use. The Company may use for the purpose of its operations the harbours along the coast of the State, but the Company shall not impede or interfere with the subjects of the Shaikh or their right to continue tne use of existing harbours, anchorages, wharves and docks along the coast of the State at present utilised by them for their sailing craft and fishing boats. ARTICLE 12. The Company shall have the right and be given the necessary facilities. (a) for the import of the aubstances into the State from any adjoining territory by pipe lines or otherwise for the purpose of operating any refinery which the Com pany may decide to erect within the State, and (b) for the transport of the Substances by pipe lines or otherwise over and across the State from and to any adjoining terri tory to any point suitable for the refining or shipping of the Substances. And no duties, taxes, charges or dues of any nature whatsoever shall be levied in respect of such import or transport. jk_» I ^ V 1 / 1 ^ J y V jlj * J * jjJI j w *111 L-L. •! jjl r H] 3 *. OllT, Jl/Vl JU jfj* &lt;i! * * 1^&gt; Jill! JM-j j* JLaJI ^Li)l dUi ^ ^ . UWVI •A* jarjl ^ (*-&gt;) jrUj &lt;j \j t if Jicrj d»Ujl ^ JUdl» U l If jl ^ jl yd) S'j*l\\ _j| 1 ^. 1 *. *i» &lt;1 1 * _jl ^ydJl jl»*^-&lt;Vl 1 ^—^ j J 11 Ik [S' I 4.4 jl 4a_^ j\ 4 )_ I J • dilS 1 Jai» iklyL-V j/lr ijT^jJI 4j^l J^u Uipl Jux- j» 4.r,^ kTydU V J ijUVI . ^ • * • 1 * - . jl ^.dLlI jjy-d vi j| J» ^.l^lljl o Jlyl-I ^ j \I ^ jll ^I^JI^I^lj . JX.«&lt;all J Jjk 1 £jUh j ^-1 _ i j.^Lc- k. llii o^Ul • 4) Ji ' J*\j\ LJ 0 4 ij\^\ Jl J^ll ( I ) J**«t£l J idU dlli yfr jl w »{liVI • I 4*ldl I 4i^JI «X$ J dUi yC- j\ Ji»l (v_&gt;) , _j| jl J 4^«LL» &lt;laAJ _J o • • • . I .X* • * CjI ^&gt;t^.lljd»l ^^1 J'l •k» &lt; jC ^ *t (^1 j-» J jl6 — — ■v ARTICLE 13. (a) Tha Company shall have free of cost the unrestricted use and occupation of and surface rights over all uncultivated lands of the State which the Company may need for the purpose of its operations and in particular the Company shall have the right to select an area or areas of land chosen by the Company with exclusive surface rights upon which to erect drilling rigs, pump-stations, .oil-refineries, storage,terminal,shipping and aircraft facilities and any other works required for the Com pany’s operations ; and the Company may buy or lease for such purposes any lands, houses or buildings with the consent of and on conditions to be arranged with the pro prietors thereof, but the terms of such purchase or lease shall not be in excess of those ordinarily current in their respective localities. (b) The Company shall acquire only such lands, houses and buildings as are necessary for its operations under this Agreement. The Company shall inform the Shaikh from time to time of the land, houses and buildings which it requires to occupy for its operations; and land, houses and buildings previously acquired by the Company from the Shaikh but found no longer necessary for its operations shall be returned by the Company to the Shaikh free of cost. ARTICLE 14. (a) The Company shall have the right to purchase at current market rates fuel, water, food, building and constructional materials and other supplns of every kind in connection with its oper ations hereunder. ( b ) The Company shall employ Arabs belonging to the State as far as possible for all work for which they are suited under the supervision of the Com pany’s skilled employees, but if the local supply of labour should in the judgment of the Company be inadequate or unsuitable the Company shall have the right to import labour, preference being given to labourers from neighbouring Arab countries who will obey the local laws. The Company shall also have the right to import skilled and technical employees. The Company shall pay to the workmen it employs a fair wage, such wage to be decided and stated by the Company at the time the workmen are engaged. ^ (1) _ ^ dl iM l t J! \cli» I ^ ,3^ ^ O 'J I \ ^ J- ^ ji jl JU'! IfJ.U:? • * • Ij-lc ft* - * 3***-^ &gt;Zj lc 3 “* J 1 J . ^j)l I 3 4* l/ jl Vl^n diu:.- (v) j** 9 j9»\ ji cJjj* ^)i ji o j^ Ul/V Jl * 3 ^^ J*- jl ^ 3 ^ 3)1 iijVlj Ua ;W - Ul/V i.; * ^ l^lc -X&gt; J ^ 3’ Ia* j_?^ (l) _ mJl ii'±\ *liij 3 ^)' J ^jl J o!^l».«llj tCJI fLLallj i» ^Lzlll Ukl/l ^1 1_^ (.5 1 . iJ Ur VI 3*&gt; I jl j Jl JUiVI jl^VI Jjj J 41 • j\.i-l ^^.31 31 j~t. I li Jl jK^lil sJS.4- jl 3^.i ^ jl *^t &lt;-Liz»VI 3 ^jli-&lt; ^ JLJ1 ^»j''l jl-x^H 3 - . Uil ^1 ^11 d* *r*^jl 3 3^' UU ^)l a • •A—^j a!I j^&gt;-l ^«as»:3 3’ • jl**H LaIcJIiu * l*^i) jl— V — ARTICLE 15. The Shaikh shall give to the Company and its employees and property all protection in his power frcm theft, highway robbery, assault, wilful damage and destruction, and the Company may appoint in consultation with the Shaikh and itself pay trustworthy guards who shail at all times be subjects of the Shaikh unless the Shaikh permits otherwise to assist in protecting the property of the Company and its employees. The Company shall erect at its own expense suitable buildings for the accommodation of such guards at such places as the Company shall decide. ARTICLE 16. In measu irg the Sub stances for purposes of royalty the factor for conversion of the volume of oil into weight shall be such figure as may be determined and agreed upon between the Shaikh and the Company after the discovery of oil and the ascertainment of its specif:c gravity. The Company shall measure the Substan ces by a method customarily used in gocd technical practice and the Shaikh by his representative duly authorised by him shall have the right to observe such measuring and to examine and test whatever applian ces may be used for such meisurirg. Such representative shall comply with all neces sary and usual safeguards for the prevention of fire and other accident; and shall make all examinations and tests at such times and in such manner as will cause the minimum of interference with the company’s operatiors. If upon such examination or testing any such appliance shall be found to be out of order the Company will cause the same to be put in order at its own expense within a reasonable time, and if upon any such examination aforesaid any error shall be discovered in any such appliance, such error shall - if the Shaikh so decides after hearing the Company’s explanation - be considered to have existed for Three(3)calen- dar Months previous to the discovery there of or from the last occasion of examining the same in case such occasion shall be within such period of Three calendar Months and the Royalty shall be adjusted accordingly. If the Company should find it necessary to alter, repair or replace any measuring appliances it shall give reasonable notice to the Shaikh or his representative to en able a representative of the Shaikh to be present during such alteration, repair or replacement. A_ii _ y — ll ^ yh If-* 4 (J\»» j * * * . jl J ff! jr y .1 If-il. &lt;3* jt^ lil VI ^_.^JI llcj i j* Lc 1^ * 5^.111 IjacL-x! di'i . ^JJI ^1 LVI ^ .1 &gt;11 .V&gt; Jl jl***. &lt;^JII J&gt;-UI j&gt;. -^1^1 j (^-dl .i-x»)l jjjl! bL.1* til .**^ ji\ I .^Jl ijt't ^—.ix* ^l&gt; &gt;1 lytyij &lt;;jj j* i^All la .4 lolc Aii ^ia.) l» # C&gt;UI^»I &lt;• I * jrl-ill 1-^* Ai^UI J•l J &gt;VI IJ&gt; -Xlc- &gt; J t5j&gt;-l *.il jl ^Ul ^*1 A| / &lt;a)lj oVli-l ol»jVI J si)l»Usi*VI • I^&gt;-I_‘^j-*&gt;«AJl .*^&gt;11 JUI J &gt;xJI jCr L C 15 I ^Jl • • • jl jl (j**** »jj* ^ur jl ^ a! I iij j -vie ^aS VI 1^1 UJ-I IJi* jl* jli •-^^5 ^” a! I j «^&gt;-j lil jy* a 5 ^&gt;) ^La&gt; I ^--^11 •l-i' IJ &gt; &gt;^&gt;1 a:-^* (r) v ij&lt;* *L*I j duj lil 1 ^* aI VI IfJ i . * •. I J jh-^l ^ j***I Aj jl yixJI jj* AjT^i.11 lil . viUi jC w * # • oV I a! I Aj I _j| y _j| _/ji, • + * jl ^.^ 4 ! A.A V 1 * I*.z'*; ^1 i.m.II • * _j| ^* 4 jJI jl J'-iJI l-A* jl* *1^1 -Alt I iiA^ w * J I A 5 ^&gt;JI ^ ^ JIjuL-VIThe Company shall keep full and correct records of all measurements as aforesaid and the said representative of the Shaikh shall have access at all reasonable times to such records and shall be at liberty to make extracts from them. Such records shall be treated as confidential by the Shaikh and his representative. ARTICLE il (a) The Company shall have the right at any time after the expiry of three years from the date of signature of this Agreement to give the Shaikh six months’ notice in writing of its intention to terminate this Agreement and this Agreement shall absolutely determine on the date fixed for such termination in such notice. (b) If such notice be given not later than 30 years after the date of such signa ture the Company shall be entitled on such determination to remove free of all taxes and duties all plant buildings stores mate rial and property of every sort provided that for a period of three months from the receipt of such notice the Shaikh may purchase the same at a price equal to the replacement value at that date less depre ciation which price shall be agreed or failing agreement settled under Article 24 hereof. (c) If such notice be given later than 30 years after the date of such signature all the property aforesaid shall become the property of the Shaikh free of all cost. ARTICLE 18. On the expiry of this Agreement at the end of the period of Seventy-five Years provided in Article 2 or any extension or renewal of that period all the movable and immovable property of the Company in the State shall be handed over to the Shaikh free of cost. Producing wells or borings at the time of such expiry shall be handed over in reasonably good order and repair. .^1 Oull oL-jUU i.*lr ol U .&gt;&gt;»! oliUI jl oli •A* y*™ • V* j llTyjb (1) - ^*11 jlT ^ I y*** si,* j * ^3 • j • -X* (ji—ia) i ^ j ^Lull j Ll_£ (v) 1 Lit ^ JiilT jt cilJi LAle ^~\ j I J» jJL\ l -^y jlf L f 4 olOulIj J \1-m t j. jf~\ ft (S jl ^ A.clia»4.| 3 • ^1*11 If-sl*.*.! *4.-5 (S3 L-* jU'Vi jC-c liis Vi j *.u ji jVi ^ ^*1 I jll •&gt;lll m J A \ . &lt; ; 5U*VI ofy* 33 y j^VI \1-* ^Lcl U! ( C&gt;Kl-ll*.Ll jli I ^Jylll . &lt;^1 til L^-L L&gt; L» • Jd.1 4-X.lk *l^aAi I A-C I — y—.e *l*. m jy\j»-4*.!ly I o A —* ^^1 &lt;-»L. V I - • . • * . A.A^^I Aj AC A«j _jl ^-1 Ul oAul ^ ykillj AjyilH y-ill jlj *A _ll *AJb yl VI LI . J • yLVI ^^**11 j&gt;- I • l^-l I jL-« A-C JsA-II lj.*4 ^A) ^qI I y» l.-fl^ IJ . ju4*U «ll« *A-&gt;- aSU i—xi &lt;.iU’V' *a*— 9 — ARTICLE 19. Subject to the provisions of Article 22 hereof the Shaikh shall have the right to terminate this Agreement and to take without payment all the property of the Company in the State if (a) The Company shall fail to make any of the payments prescribed in this Agree ment within 6 months of the date on which they fall due, or (b) The Company shall be in default in respect of an arbitration award under Article 24 hereof. ARTICLE 20. (a) Nothing in this Agree ment shall be read as restricting in any way the right of the Shaikh to grant to other parties concessions or permits for materials other than the Substances as defined in Ar ticle 3 provided that the operations and rights of the Company hereunder are not thereby injuriously affected. If the Shaikh should at any date sub sequent to the date of signature of this Agreement grant to any other parties con cessions or permits as aforesaid the Shaikh undertakes that such concessions shall con tain provisions requiring the holders thereof to abstain from damaging, impeding or interfering with the property, operations and interests of the Company. Deposits of minerals such as gold, silver, copper, lead, potash, sulphur and salt or the like which may be discovered by the Company shall be reported to the Shaikh and shall not be worked by the Company except under special concession or permit from the Shaikh. Further the Company shall instruct its Geologists to mark carefully and report to the Company any area and its location which appears to them to give promise of yielding fresh water from a bore-hole and the Com pany undertakes to keep the Shaikh informed of all such water reports and the sites of the area or areas. ARTICLE 21. The Shaikh hereby agrees that the Company may transfer the obligations and benefits of this Agreement to a British Company to be called 'Petroleum Concessions ( Dubai) Limited” or to any ll (_jI _ •^li! j! ^»b)l # * jtj iJWVl .O* (l) iji jjUVi 4 c.iCu •.x * ^ oL»a]I (_$! •ta! ^ • ^&lt; 1 I c) £j.xi ^ oL»jI1 y . UUV! *-x* y* y» «J ^ j l — jj Ll» jc.a. L jl UUV1 jjUl- o'jLl»l j»~\ y jl tj • i 1^1' •l.iVl jl Jl/’l dUS yy. ^ *-^^**1 \1 jmIi' A jlit'Vl • ^ ^l)l •**! C • I ol j’&gt;- 1 y j* A^jIaTVI •jl I* ^ _ j L ^.oll • ' jf ' J -V4.) r 6J ur jl 1-^JL.U- oljl-l*Vl jl iJ^I J j c jl j c . •} juj ij-v«'J j» 1 jl a» ^11 a.^ | l. j^Cll jjrl'1JI VI a 5^-J1 iy^.»jCi . £jl!I y jl oVLJl J—r jl» xllli jt j ^ ^ ^ jx*jUl f i-i* yi j fr y.A A &gt; A t O 'J jiil\ y ;j- V.AC. ♦ L Ai y I ^ »Ut A ^ 1»- jlkT Aj I . ^-liJl •! &lt;«iJI ^tT ^11 ^Olyij y m — jjy^J'j A.oli-1 •^lll ^jUlljol A^*lll JJLi jl a 5^**-1I jl Ia* y*J aj'L^&gt; UUrVI .a_» Ly*:!!— 40 — — \ • — other Company registered within the British Empire. ARTICLE 22. Failure on the part of the Company to fulfil any of the conditions of this Agreement shall not give the Shaikh any claim against the Company or be deemed a breach of this Agreement in so far as such failure arises from force majeure, and if through force majeure the fulfilment by the Company of any of the conditions of this Agreement be delayed the period of such delay shall be added to the periods fixed by this Agreement. Force majeure as used in this Ag reement includes the Act of God, war, insurrection, riot, civil commotion, tide, storm, tidal wave, flood, lightning, explosion, fire, earthquakes and any other happening which the Company could not reasonably prevent or control. ARTICLE 23. The Shaikh shall not by general or special legislation or by administrative measures or by any other act whatever annul this Agreement except as provided in Article 19. No alteration shall be made in the terms of this Agreement by either the Shaikh or the Company except in the event of the Shaikh and the Company jointly agreeing that it is desirable in the interests of both parties to make certain alterations, deletions or additions to this Agreement. ARTICLE 24. (a) If at any time during the currency of this Agreement any dif ference or dispute shall arise between the parties hereto concerning the interpretation or execution hereof, or anything herein contained, or in connection herewith, or the rights or liabilities of either party hereunder, the same shall, failing any agreement to settle it in any other way, be jwair iJU'VI -kjy-i (£' X9 '\ O 6, iJiUi ij*\&gt; • *l&gt;* ISl iJlirV! *j! • #^iJI !s!j . iJlirV! •Jy &lt;1^*1! jjd! J! ^ -UaL J J j\\j ^L)l sl&gt;^! y&gt;- i&gt;_l j j ^! j * • • • [a.* LU jl L^!j\ &gt;»!^:» 'V! oUj V! 0^ jjJz IS! V! Vj ^-^-l! j* ^ &lt;JUrVi .S* J&gt;Si-l jl J*.-^'! t/**! . &lt;J'irV! *Sj» J! jl cJj &lt;^l j ^ Lii Is! cks'* ' ^'!*j^! tj-* £\y jl oL»!j!!j ■?*ni — 11 — w— raferred to two arbitrators, one of whom shall be chosen by each party, and a referee, who shall be chosen by the arbit rators before proceeding to arbitration. (b) Each party shall nominate its own arbitrator within Sixty days after delivery of a request so to do by the other party failing which its arbitrator may at the request of the other party be designated by the British Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. In the event of the arbitra tors failing to agree within Sixty days after being chosen or designated, the British Political Resident in the Persian Gulf may appoint a referee at the request of the arbitrators or of either of them. (c) The decision of the arbitrators, or in case of a difference of opinion between them the decision of the referee, shall be final and binding upon both parties. (d) In giving a decision the arbitrators or the referee shall specify an adequate period of delay during which the party against whom the decision is given shall conform to the decision and that party shall be in default only if that party has failed to conform to the decision prior to the expiry of that period and not otherwise. (e) The place of arbitration shall be such as may be agreed by the parties and in default of agreement shall be London. ARTICLE 25. The Company shall make all payments that become due to the Shaikh under this Agreement into the Shaikh’s ac count at the and the Bank’s receipt shall be a full discharge for the Company in respect to the payment of the sum stated in the Bank’s receipt. The Shaikh may from time to time designate in writing another Bank or Banks for the purpose of this Article. ^4 —&gt;-1^ (‘r 5 ) ^ ^ O* **-'^*^ , ^ .xi» *Li jjli dy-».i O'-**. J jlX^' o' * jU _) 1 -XjJ jCc- (j\«J ^^Ull J ^.LJI JlUjJI j aIU- ^ jwCJ-i j\ j jl (^r) j| Jusl Jilc- 4» 1 (^) « ■ jk\\ ix* 1 jf Vj J&gt;Hc jl jl jl^iU jl jc- ^:&gt;.l 'Si VI I^aa* j^y'l 1 . VI J : » J^i-oll jUt jiii &lt;Ac. j^ j^C (^) j^J j jyC jUVl ^ ^ iSb iS^lll - jjy^llj &lt;—-1^1 oUl t jl oIaj'^ 1 »A* yt. ^!l OL#&gt;lJ| - iS^jJl *-»Sl \r jriA dljjl Sj&gt;-Ul JLajVl j^^J . dXJI JLail ^ j^J.1 ^Lil b' 1 **’. ^ jl J* 1 J' J* ^liC jl j*- 1 (&gt;*» . *jLl o AA&gt;12 — \ Y — ARTICLE 26. This Agreement is writ ten in English and translated into Arabic. If there should at any time be disagreement as to the meaning or interpretation of any clause in this Agreement the English text shall prevail. In witness whereof the parties to this Agreement have set their hands the Day and Year first above written AmS (foil w (fcaOTKB \y^i ij* ;aL j^aj ^jiir U l Ij . ^ 3 olArVl •a-* jljJiLJ,! * (3**3^ j •^Vc’l jtClIl Jjl THE COMPANY THE SHAIKH IN THE PRESENCE OF IN THE PRESENCE OF cU)X&gt; -V— ^</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0001b9_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/3873</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0001b9</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/3873</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 30/139 'Oil: Debai Commercial Concession and Exchange of Notes.'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1936/1937</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-01-10T22:41:05</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (181 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the inside front cover with 1, and terminates at the last folio with 182; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. A previous foliation sequence, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file concerns the drafting of the Dubai Oil Concession commercial agreement between the Ruler of Dubai (Shaikh Said bin Maktum Al-Hasher [Saʻīd bin Maktūm bin Hasher Āl Maktūm]) and Petroleum Development (Trucial Coast) Limited, a subsidiary of Petroleum Concessions Limited. The agreement was signed on 22 May 1937 (folios 38-55). The Ruler of Dubai also agreed to the following conditions set by the British Government:The commercial agreement was to be subordinate to the political agreement between HM Government and Petroleum Concessions Limited, signed on 5 February 1937If the Company failed to observe any of the terms of the political agreement, the Ruler had the right to terminate the commercial agreement, and take over all the company's properties within his territory.The papers include draft and signed copies of the agreement; correspondence between the India Office and representatives of the Company over the wording of the agreement; comments from other British Government departments (e.g. the Foreign Office and the Air Ministry); and India Office confidential print entitled 'Dubai Oil Concession and Connected Documents' (Memo. B 458).The Arabic language content of the file consists of draft and signed copies of the agreement in both English and Arabic.The file includes a divider, which gives a list of correspondence references contained in the file by year. This is placed at the back of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Petroleum Concessions Limited</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Abu Dhabi Company for Onshore Oil Operations</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Emir of Dubai, Āl Maktūm dynasty</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Concessions, Oil, Dubai</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0001b9#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>