<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000186_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-18T04:19:40.423Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Bahrain Receipt ' ~~ ■ ». LaJa; ^ relegrtim' ^’rom To No. Dated u) u.T.C. Political Resident, Bushire. Political Agent, Bahraih. 264 5tli received 6tli February 1945. Circular from Political Resident Persian Gulf telegram No.254 dated February 5th. Leaving for Arab Coast and India February 10th repeat February 10th. Please continue to address all the telegrams and mail to Bush ire until further notice. -PRIOR-Political ^ency, Bahrain, The Station Manager, British Overseas Airways Corporation, Bahrain. Memorandum. Reference my telephone conversation this morning. confirmation from Baghdad that a passage ha s been received for the Hon'ble air Geoffrey Prior, K.C.I.K., leaving Bahrain on the 18th February for Delhi. 2 Yill you kindly obtain telegraphic 0 V Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain.rs TELEGRAMS: •FLYING’ BAHRAIN. CODES : BENTLEY’S 8t A. I. T. A. TELEPHONE; 43M. TBT.328.5505 BRITISH OVERSEAS AIRWAYS CORPORATION Bahrain Recent 2 ^ _/nrao..Date BAHREIN ISLANDS. PERSIAN GULF. 14th February 1945. H.B.M’a Political Agent. Bahrein. Sir, S ir Geoffrey Prior, K.C.I.E. w cno . 1 _ Th l'2 J _ s ^S i: ^ on ^ as honour to refer to your letter No.608 of the 13th February 1945 . r r It is confirmed that a signal was sent to Baghdad yesterday asking confirmation of the priority reservation for Sir Geoffrey Prior from Bahrein to Delhi on 18th February 1945. Immediately a reply is received you will be advised. I have the honour to be, SirNo * bbZ - 19/2* Political Agency, Bahrain, The 18th February, 1945* Certificate. Certified that the Hobble Sir Geoffrey Prior, K.C.I.B., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, is a Government servant. lA' for Political Agent, Bahrain.Pahrab Receipt .. X) its.. # Telegram G.T.C. From To No • Dated Engineer due to arrive Bahrain by Nearchus forenoon Thursday February 22nd. Please make usual disembarkation arrangements. -BRITCONSUL- Britconsul, Bushire. Political Agent, Bahrain. 364 (0 20th received 21st February 1945. Tour party including ExecutiveTe leg ram From To Dated Following for B.0.A.G. Grateful if you can arrange to accommodate rolitiea^ Resident and myself on nights sixth and seventh March* g.t.o. Political Agent, ;3ahrain. Residency Agent, Sharjah. 128 1st March, 1945. © =PCLITICA]^i'ele^ram From G.T.C. To Tolitical Agent, Mhrain. iiesideney Agent, Sharjah. No. Dated 130 - 1st March 1945 Resident has approved gathering and will arrive March 6th and re tom i larch 8th.. Sheikh should meet him on arrival at Sharjah. I am arranging for Resident and self to live in the Fort- Captain Tandy will not be back from India until 5th. AMO ^POLITICALf&gt;|rtf Telegram From To No. B&amp;fcrara Receipt G.T.C. Britagent, Sharjah. Political, Bahrain, 252. Dated and received the 1st March, 1945. p-f Your telegram 128, March 1st. 2. B.O.A.C. arranged accommodation for Political Resident and yourself on nights of 6th and 7th March. _A_. BritagentX6l S SHARJAH 5 7 1120 BG POLITICAL BAHREIN - SEAPLANE TOMORROW - = POLITICAL ) A A-^A MARK YOUR REPLY JmAeSuaL \ ANY ENQUIRY RESPECTING THIS TELEGRAM SHOULD BE ACCOMPANIED BY THIS FORM AND MAY BE MADE AT ANY OF THE COMPANY’S OFFICES.p-V- 17 Telegram From To No. Dated Political Political resident, Bushire. political Agent, Bahrain. 742 l7th received 18th April, 1945. Please enquire for mail from. Resident. -PRIOR* AMOTelegram G.T.C. From Prior, Bushire. To Political Agent. Bahrain. No. 759 Dated 19th and received 20th April, 1945. Meaning of my telegram 742 is that you should ask Political Resident on arrival if he has any mails for you. ^Prior- NMJ /^*7 /L M'| ^ ^ j)l‘Pahvain Receipt I .Dabe. Telegram From Secretary to the Political tiesident, Bushiro. To Repeated No. Bated Higheocaa^ *Tcrus$lera^c tL . Political Agent, Muscat. Political Agent, P-Utrain. 792 I 23rd received 24th April, 1945. Addressed Jerusalem repeated Muscat for Political Resident, and Bahrain. Grateful if a room at King Davids Hotel Jerusalem for May 2nd repeat May 2nd could be booked for Sir Geoffrey Prior Political Resident Persian Gulf. Please confirm repeating Political Agent Bahrain. -BRITAIN 3No. 1825-19/2. Political Agency, Bahrain, The 1st May, 1945. CERTIFICATE. This is to certify that Sir Geoffrey Prior, K.C.I.E., the Hon*ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, is an official of the Government of India.Telegram Prom To No. Dated 14th rece GTC Ga1loway, Bushire• Political, Bahrain. 1085. ived 15th June, 1945. r Circular. Leaving for Khorramshahr June 17th to meet Political Agent, Kuwait returning June 22nd . 3. Telegrams and mails should continue to be addressed to Bushirc. Galloway. Bahrain Receipt No ... Date.33/61 Telegram G.T.C, 6 &lt;' 0 ^ 2 - From Political Resident at Ghiraz. To India Office, London No. T/346. Govenur.cnt of India, New Delhi No. T/347. fl.M.Ambassador, Tehran No. T/348. Political Agent, Hur,cat No. T/349. L.m. Consta, fiiorrawshalir Nc. t/360. H*M. ConsiU, Kansan No. T/3^1. H.M. Consul, Bushire No. T/35?‘. Copy to Political Agent, Bahrain, at Shiraz. Political Agent, Kuwait, at Shiraz. Dated 80th August 1946. Circular. Leaving Shiraz Friday August 24tb for Tehran returning August Blst. Please continue to address telegrams as usual. GALLOWAY RHL. w/a. • * ' .e) Telegram GTC From Galloway, Bushire. Political, Bahrain 1546. To No Dated 11th received 12th October, 1945 CIRCULAR. From Political Resident Persian Gulf Telegram No.1546 dated October 11th. Leaving for Bahrain October 20th . From October 17th until further notice please address all telegrams and mail^. requiring my personal attention to Bahrain. 2. Telegrams and correspondence on main office subjects should continue to be addressed to Bushire. Pass to Senior Naval Officer. Copy forwarded to the Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, Bahrain. No.4304-19/2 =GALL0WAY= Political Agency, Bahrain The 13th October, 1945. for Political Agent, Bahrain/ ■ . 2X Bahrain Receipt Telegram GTC From Galloway, Bushire. To Political, Bahrain. No. . 1547. (ft) Dated 11th and received 12th October, 1945. My Circular telegram No.1546 October 11th. 2. Staff will arrive by NEARCHUS October 19th . Please make usual arrangements. 3. I shall arrive in SEABELLE October 21st AM and glad if you could put me up. 4. Arrival private. =GALLOWAY=Teldgreim From To Ho. Dated Resident. G.T.C. Political, Bahrain. Britain, Bushire. 738 13th October, 1945. g) p - a * Your telegrara 1547 of 11th October. Political Agent mill be glad to accommodate ^POLITICAL-/ /* UvlPORTANT. For Political Agent, Bahrain* (1) Resident’s staff arrive Bahrain by Nearchus on 19th October and Resident arrives Seabelle 21st October AM and says he will be glad if you could put him up. Arrival private. • •• j (2) Have replied Political Agent will be glad to accommodate Resident. -POLITICAL* AMOTelegram G.T.C. From Political Resident, at Bahrain. To All addresses. Copy to ^ H.B.M's. Political Agent, Bahrain.^ The Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, Bahrain. No. T/668 Dated the 29th October, 1945. IIVIMEDI ATE Circular from Political Resident Persian Gulf. r .| My circular telegram No. 1546 October 11th. Leaving for Bushire November 1st. From October 30th please address all telegrams and mail to Bushire.The first lTr&gt;e ofthi* Telegram contain* the following particulars in the order named :— Prefi* Letttrj and Number of Mettaft, Office of Orifin. Number of Worda, Date. Time handed in and Official instructions if any. YIP 153 /RR 143 ss NEARCHUS BAHRAINRADIO 14/13 16 0715Z S BG IMPORTANT POLITICAL BAHRAIN ARRIVING BAHREIN SEVENTEENTH EIGHT HOURS ' LOCAL = PRIOR = • * e • - # • e e t , #f , '—' MARK YOUR REPLY Sm/ieSuad NO ENQUIRY RESPECTING THIS TELEGRAM CAN BE ATTENDED TO WITHOUT PRODUCTION Of THIS COPY.The first line of this Telegram contains the following particulars in the order namedi ^ J Telegram- G.T.C. ^ From- Prior, Nearchus, Bahrain Kadio, • f ' ' * F- ■ ^* To- Political, Bahrain. _ u-A) . No. T/721. Dated 12th and received 13th December, 1945. expect to arrive at Bahrain A.M. and leave P.M. December 17th repeat December 17th. Will notify time later. 2 . Hadow and wife will be on board. 3. Please inform Shaikh visit is private and that owing to lack of time no call will be exchanged. addition to Diana for me please arrange quarantine or other launch to be at disposal of party during stay. - Prior Nu4JTelegram From To Ar® IMPORTANT I'l/v' 0 Political, Bahrain. Britagent, Sharjah. 6 // /(f ^ . For Political Agent. Resident expects to arrive Bahrain A.M. December 17th and leave P.M. same day. =POLITICAL= NS.Telegram G.T.C. Fro/a Galloway, Sharjah, To Political, Bahrain. No. 1268. i)atod and received 16th December, 1946. Important . ..9 ^ ' • Your telegram 611 of 10th. Please inform Resident that I am proceeding to Abu Dhabi returning 17th and as ho has not asked me to come X am not interrupting ray tour. Galloway.Telegran From Political Resident, Bushire Political, Bahrain. 207 No To Dated 7th and received 8th February, 1946. CIRCU1..R 1 I am leaving Bushire 13th February repeat 13 th February for Delhi via Bahrain, returning Bahrain 27th February. Further movements will be telegraphed later. Please continue addressing telegrams and mails to Bushire. — PRIOR -- SDh-ay - •• y -'Ty' B»hraii» Receipt Telegram G.T.C. From Political Resident, Bushire, To Political Agent, Bahrain. No. 264. Dated and received 13th February, 1946. Important. Arriving without office p.m. February 14th. Arrival private. = Prior = m.Telegram From To No. Dated 21st and received 22nd February, 1946. Circular. From February 23rd repeat February 23rd please address to Bahrain all telegrams requiring personal attention of Political Resident, Persian Gulf. Pass to Commander in Chief, East Indies. Britain. tfG-../.2&gt;7Ll)afce 2?: -2-^ G.T.C. Britain, Bushire Political, Bahrain. 319. C.( ^)2 &amp; Copy of telegram No,319 dated the 21st February, 1946 from the Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire to the Political Agent, Bahrain. Circular. From February 23rd repeat February 23rd please address to Bahrain all telegrams requiring personal attention of Political Resident, Persian Gulf. Pass to Commander in Chief, iiast Indies* Copy forwarded to the Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, Bahrain, with the request that he will please pass on this message to the Commander in Chief, Hast Indies. —-x Political Agency, Bahrain The 23rd February, 1946. for Political Agent, BahrainTelegram GTC From Secretary to the Political Resident, Bushire. To Political Agent, Bahrain. No. 346 Dated and 2&amp;±ii received February 24th, 1946. IMPORTANT . Under Secretary and staff four leaving by Nearchus • Please warn caretaker. AMO. =BRITAIN= Bahrain R No 5 ■ Data. 2 A^ow&gt;&lt;.Telegram En Clair* From Political Resident, 'Nearchus”. To Political Agent, Bahrain* No* NR44. Dated 2nd &lt;&amp; Beceived 3rd February Regret still not possible give you firm dates. Weather makes movements uncertain. * PRIOR = . KMS Bahrain Receipt HiTelegram From To No. Dated GTC Political, Bahrain. Britain, Bushire. 177 17th March, 1946. • • • • From Political Resident. Please send Mandonca out to supervise discharge of three refrigerators. =POLITICAL= r AMO45 GTC \ l i Political Resident, Bushire. Political Agent, Bahrain, 496 1st and received the 2nd April, 1946. • ••••• Leaving Bushire April 6th repeat April 6th for Bahrain, 2. Please continue to address all telegrams and mails to Bushire. =PRIOR= AMO Bahrain Receipt Ure^QTelegram GTC From Political Resident, Bushire. To Political Agent, Bahrain. No. 549 Dated 6th and received the Jth April, 1946 IMMEDIATE. Arriving on the Nearchus forenoon April 7th repeat April 7th with one clerk and much heavy baggage. Please make usual landing arrangements. =FRIOR= AMO. tsl .Data.Confidential Mo.395.-S» Persian Gulf Residency, Bushire, 5th April, 19 46. To Mr. A • J. Smales Memorandum Your first task on the forthcoming tour will be to see to the proper unloading and storage of the Political Resident’s luggage, and office and other boxes sent with you. 2. If there is an up mail by which you can return to Bushire by 20th April, you and farrash . Reza should return by it; if not, you are, if required by the Polit ical Agent, Bahrain, to work in the Confi dential Office of the Bahrain Agency until arrival of the Residency tour party in May. 3u. J. Croning Under Secretary to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf. Itfo .396-3 Copy forwarded, with compliments, to rn 1 he Political Agent, BahrainURGENT No.1119-19/2. Political Agency, Bahrain, Dear Sirs, Please reserve the following passages from Bahrain to Bushire by S.S. Barjora:- i. Second class with food for Mr. A.J. Smales. ii. Deck without food for farrash Reza. The 9th April, 1946 To Messrs. Gray Mackenzie &amp; Co., Ltd., Bahrain. Yours faithfully, for Political Agent, Bahrain CTelegram GTC From Political Resident, Bushire. To Political i.gent, Bahrain. No. 690 Dated 3rd and received 4th May, 1946. • • • • CIRCULAR. From Political Resident Persian Gulf. Leaving Bushire May 9th repeat May 9th for Bahrain. 2. From May 8th repeat May 8th please addre telegrams requiring ny personal attention to Bahrain. =PRIOR=^ rom Political Resident, Bushire. Political Agent, Bahrain. No. 707 Bated 3rd and received the 4th May, 1946. • • • • * - My telegram Circular No.^90 May 3rd. 'Pelegrams correspondence on main office subjects should continue to be addressed to Bushire. r~ f Re l. AMO. =PRI0R= Bate.Telegram GTC From Political, Bahrain. To Political, Sharjah. No. 278 Dated 4th May, 1946. For Galloway from Ranee. Resident leaving Bushire for Bahrain. May 9th repeat May 9th. =POLITICAL=4 So. 1473 - 19/2. To POLITICAL AGKNCY f BAHHaIK• The 11th May 1946. The Secretary to the Hon^le the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, BIJSHIKK. I enclose herewith debit note No.BI/56, dated the 7th May 1946 from Messrs. Gray, Mackenzie and Company, Limited, Bahrain, and request that payment may kindly be made to their agent at Bashire. Copy toi ler Messrs. Grey, for information. KiiS POLITICAL A GLUT, BAIL A IN. Mackenzie and Company, Limited, Bahrain, 9 $ 5mtm The firet line of thi* TePegrem contain* the following • particular* in the order named ;— Prefix Letters and Number of Message. Office of Origin, Number of Words. Date. Time handed in and Official instructions if any. RR64 nri ss nearchus/yiaj bahrainradio 9 3 0800 PTY ✓ 5 ==^ BG . IMPORTANT POLITICAL BAHRAIN ' ARRIVING TENTH EIGHT HOURS LOCAL PRIOR - WRC PORT DIRECTORATE BASRAH ,( ahr s ; a R ece {p{ ■ ”f ^^Data !??..;^ . ' MARK YOUR**RE?Ly 'ffia €?7n/ietia£ ^ , — WafaT l/V? NO ENQUIRY RESPECTING THIS TELEGRAM CAN RE ATTENDED TO WITHOUT PRODUCTION Of THIS COPY.Telegram From To No. Dated on morning En Clair. Political Agent, Bahrain. P. O.T.C. , Sharjah. 382 8th July, 1946. You should meet Political Resident July 11th passenger C Class Eastbound. =POLITICAL=Telegram From To No.1393. India Office, London. Government of India, New Political Agent, Kuwait. Political Agent, Bahrain Political Agent, Muscat. Delhi. (By hand) Dated the 2nd December 1946. IMMEDIATE /\ Circular. Leaving for Muscat and Gwadur December 3rd repeat December 3rd. 2. Please address telegrams requiring my personal attention to n Hay, Steamship King Faisal, Bahrain Radio'. * 3. All other telegrams should continue to be addressed to Bahrain. - REPGU - *To Agencies only.Telegram From To &gt; No. En Clair. Political, Resident, King Faisal Political, Bahrain. T/623 Dated l6th and received 17th December, 194-6. CIRCULAR My telegram No.1393 Circular December 2nd. Returning to Bahrain December 17th repeat December 17thG.T.C Telegram From Political Resident, King Faisal, Bahrain Radio. To Political Agent, Bahrain. No. T/608. Dated &amp; reed. 15th December 1946. IMPORTANT Please convey my warmest thanks to Sultan for arrangements for my Batinah tour which proved most enjoyable and interesting and wish him a happy journey and a pleasant stay in Dhofar. i = HAY = SEND TO MUSCAT. /. N 0 . KMS 6 ^ rJ,o Intlci. A.C.G. 15.12.46. I f/l &gt;Telegram En Clair From Political Resident, 'Nearchus”. To Political, Bahrain. No. T/28 Dated and received 27th January, 194-7. IMMEDIATE Addressed Repgu and Political Bahrain. Arrival postponed owing bad weather. Please send cars Sitra ten a.m. repeat ten a.m. 28th. i — HAY — I.R. N0_»18 SDNHO. y.r-2 -19/2. To POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAII , February, 1947. The Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain. I^MORAIIDIU:- The following expenditure has been incurred by the Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Sharjah, in connection with the Hobble the Political Resident's tour to the Trucial Coast:- Hire of launch to and from L.V. Wearchus at Sharjah, 5 return trips and detention. Rs. 120-0-0 Hire of 3 ferries at Sharjah. Rs. 10-0-0 Hire of a taxi for delivering a message to the Ruler of Dubai. Rs. 30-0-0 Gratuity to Shaikh of Ras-al- Khaimah's men. Rs. 20-0-0 Gratuity to Shaikh of Abu- Dhabi's men. Rs. 25-0-0 Total Rs. 205-0-0 2. It is requested that the amount of rs.205/- may please be sent to me for reimbursing it to the Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Sharjah. iiA * for Political Agent, Bahrain. \ ^so. Lf/o -19/2. POLITICAL AOENCT, The Secretary to the Hon^le the Political Resident in the Persian Uulf, BAHRA I R. Jlil.lORANDUiil: - cost of 25 tins of petrol and one gallon oil was spent by the Political Officer, Trucial Coast, on trips to Abu Dhabi, Dubai, Ajman, Uuua al ^aiwain, Ras al Khaimah, (including Ras and Khatt) in coj nection with the recent tour of the Hon’ble the Political Resident on the Trucial Coast. 2. It is requested that the above amount may please be sent to me ^or reimbursement to the Political Officer, Trucial Coast. BAHRAIN, /y ^February, 1947. To A sura of Ps. 10^/9/- on account of for Political Agent Bahrain.W' ^ S' O' NO. J&gt;'/ -19/2 POLITICAL AGENCY, JBAHRAIN /J J'feroh, 1947. TO Ihe Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Gharjah. D MEMORANDUM:, C 2- Reference your raemoranda No.89.0110 dated the 27th January and No.120.0130 dated the 3rd February 1947. 2* I enclose herewith a Bank Draft for Rs. 311/9/- being the refund of the expenditure incurred by you in connection with the tour of the Hon’ble the Political Resident on the Trucial Coast. 3. Please acknowledge receipt. °[U for Political Agent, Bahrain, ^ :S ’ tT—Telegram G.T.C. \ From Political Resident, Warship Wildgoose. To Political, Bahrain, No. T/141 Dated 11th and received 12th April, 19^7. II j PORTA NT Returning to Bahrain April 13th repeat April 13th, From April 12th repeat A.pril 12th please address all telegrams to Bahrain, — hay — I,R.No.Ill SDN7'^P W.F. &amp; M.O k/f U Telegram G.T.C. From Political Agent, Muscat, at Salalah. Repgu Bahrain. No. C.168. Circular. My telegram C.123 March 10th. 2. Leaving for Muscat April 6th repeat April 6th. Please address all telegrams to Muscat with immediate effect. - STEWART - No.568 -S . Persian Gulf Residency, Bahrain, the 6th April 1947. Copy forwarded, with compliments, to The Political Agent, BAHRAIN , Confidential. BAHRAIN RECEIPT.© 33/51 M.O. &amp; P*A, Telegram G.T.C From Political Resident on Warship ,, Wildgoose H Dated To No RFPGQ, Bahrain. T/135. 9th received 10th April, 194 Wildgoose now expected to arrive Sitra repeat Sitra 1800 hours 13th repeat 13th. S#N*0. is arranging for dhow Jufair to meet ship on arrival and take whole of my party to Jufair where we should arrive 1900 hours. No necessity to send car to meet me Sitra but if for any reason it is considered preferable that I should land there ple.se telegraph me accordingly. - HAY - 2LL.mmmm 35/51, M»0* &amp; p#A» Telegram O.T.C, From Repgu Bahrain. To Political He aid en t, on H.M.S. '•WILD GC0SB w . Ko. 425. Dated 10 th April 1947 . Your telegram Ho. T/135 April loth. It would be more convenient if you yourself landed at bitra while staff and baggage came in dhow to Jufair. Am arranging accordingly. - RiSPCSU - No.584 -S. Persian Gulf Residency, Bahrain, the 10th April 1947 . Copy, with copy of telegram under reference, forwarded, with compliments, to !• The Political Agent, Bahrain, in continuation of Residency endorsement No.581-3 dated the 9th April 1947. 2* The Staff officer (Intelligence), Persian Gulf, Jufair. RHL. 0 -&gt;S'k7 I ! .iT l C/) 'x V O' vm Governinent of India, New Delhi. Government of Pakistan, Karachi. Coomonwealth Relations Office, London ^Political Agent, Bahrain, (by hand). Political Agent, Muscat. Political Agent, Kuwait. H.M*s Vice Consul, Bushire. H.i^s Consul, Khorramshahr. No. A/795. Dated the 7th October, 1947. b &lt;6 Resumed charge afternoon sixth.33/51 0 ^ %lr k Telegram From To No. G.T.C. Political Resident, Bahrain. Political Agent, Muscat, Political Agent, Bahrain, (by Hand) 726 Dated the 19th August, 1948. Leaving for Kuwait August 22nd expect return Bahrain August 26th. Only telegrams requiring my immediate personal attention should be addressed to Kuwait. = GALLOWAY = *CLS *Telegram En Clair From Galloway, Kuweit, To Prodrome, London, Political, Muscat, Political, Bahrain, No. T/64. Dated The 6th Sept, and receieved the 7th Sept, 1948. Leaving for Bahrain PU September 7th. IK Galloway =i ) Te le gram From TO Dated 30th prodrome Bahrain. Forei^i Office London lilo. 222. Political Agent Bahrain. Sa/ing No. 6.' Political Agent Kuwait No. 18. Political Agent Muscat No. 21. October 1948. Ad leaving for Cairo November let returning to habbaniya November 9th Kuwait November 10th ijahrain November nth. address at Cairo MBMIN • Hay. ABri-tis*] Residency, Bahrain, Persian Gulf*TE1E EN CLAIR FROM P.R. BAHREIN TO F.O. TEL NO 184 DATED 23/4/49 Leave for Kuwait 26th returning Bahrein 28th. Please continue to address all telegrams to Bahrein except those requiring ny immediate personal attention Hay. ^ 'jj s. m c -o.TELE FROM TO BPTI n Kin, AIX P.A. ilAH.t! IN Tl'.L NO 13. TEL NO 20 Saving. DATED 8/5/49 Important. I leave for Muscat with Burrows 8th returning Bahrein 11th. Hay IProcedure on the arrival of Visits of the Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Oificial Arrival. Details. Authority. P^ljj^nary. On receipt of intimation that the arrival will be oificial P.A. informs:- S — V Arri^i of PTKI calls. ana (aj The Adviser to the Banrain Government, S.No;2 File 19/2 . ^ ^ ana Vo1 Ir (b; H.E. the Shaikh. (Letters are written), p.125-File 19/2 Vol.I. ms ^ e s arrangements by letter with the S.No:3 File 19/2 Adviser for Guam of Honour to wait upon Vol.II. P*h., usually at the Customs pier, ana for a salute to be firea. P*R. should be asked by telegram at what time he wishes the P.A to come aboard and (if necessary) whether hot or cola weather uniform should be worn. It is well to ask the Adviser to warn H.E. the Snaikh to wear his decorations. On arrival of the Political Resident f s ship, p. 73-File. 19/2 P.A. (accompaniea by the A.P.A.) goes on Vol.I. board to pay his call on the P.E., and remains on boara the ship for H.E. the Shaikh T s visit. After an interval of 20 minutes from the time the Political Agent has left the pier, II.E. the Shaikh is accompanied by members ofhis family ana usually by the Adviser. When P.A. comes on board the C.O. meets nim on the top of the gangway ana conaucts him to where the P.E. is receiving guests. 'ben H.n. the shaikh comes on board he is met by the C.O. at the top of the gangway and P * 73-I i le. 19/2 Vol.I. -do-' ~~~ &gt; O fficial Arrival (continuea) Le tails. Autiiority. and a Guard of Honour is arawn up on the quarter aeck a bugler sounds the salute if availaole. The 0.0. conducts H.E. the Shaikh to the place where the P.R. is receiving guests, ana the ?•A* ana A*P*A* meet H*E* the Shaikn outside the cabin. A r hen the P.E. returns the visit the Shaikh receiving him at the top of the Majlis stops outside the room. Usually the G.O. ol tne ship accompanies the P.R. on the call, coming on shore _ kf* separately^motor launch. He usually stays on board about ualf an hour, when he leaves under a salute of 11 guns. P.R. leaves tne ship under a salute of p.73-Pile.19/2 Vol.I. 13 guns (if in a saluting ship; goes ashore with the P.a. and- A.P.A. in the Agency launch. _ Q0 _ P.R. lands at the Customs pier. A salute of 13 guns is fired. He inspects the Guard of Honour ana proceeds on foot between lines of naturs to the Customs Majlis where he returns the Shaikh’s call. -do- i hhile the P.n. is with H.E. the Shaikh in the Mtts-hms Majlis the Guard of Honour marches from the pier he*d to a opposite the Majlis, where they again present arms on the ^.R’s coming out to get into the Agency car to go to the Agency&gt;3 File 19/k: P.R’s visit (ofiicial) (continuea) Full uniform with meaals ana aecorations. P.R. snoula be askeu whether he wishes to nave hot or cold weather uniform. On board it is usual to serve coflee,sharbat ana essences and/or sweets. It is necessary to warn the Commanaing Officer that a plate of ^aite plain biscuits- ana soaa insteaa of sweet sharbat- should be offerea to il.E. the Shaikh, wno is on a aiet. At the Majlis coffee, tea ana itr ana aua is given. Details Authority* « P.K s Visit (private; Details. Authority Preliminary . 1. V 1 On receipt of information P.^. informs (1) The Adviser to the Bahrain Government. (2; H.nu the Bhaikh. 2. P.^. accompaniea by A.?.^ meets P.E. on board the ship or at the aeroarome ana brings P.R. to tne agency in the Agency launch. Notes 3. H.E. the Shaikh calls on P#h. informally at some convenient time, aua P .R. returns H.£i. the Shaikh f s call accompaniea by P.A. and A.P.^. Usual courtesies are exchangea. 4. P.A. ana A.P.A. see off P.R. on boara the ship or at the aeroarome. 5. Dress- Mufti, lounge suit. On the occasion of P.R’s visits (official ana/or private; office arranges for hire of the Balaaiyah lorry ana necessary taxis, for P.R T s kit ana staff; also accommoaation for P.R f s staff, if and when necessary.Visit of the Hon f ble the Political Resident to Bahrain on March 5th, 1942« 1. Tho time of the Hon^le the Political negident f s arrival in 3.3. 'Nearchus** is uncertain. The Political .^gant and the Assistant Political Agent should he prepared to go out to the 'Nearchus* hn the evening of March 4th if she is sighted, and, in any case to leave et 7.45 a.m. on March 5th. 2. The Assistant Political Agent will please arrange for earliest possible information of 3.3. '•Nearchus H being sighted. Presumably the Naval Base can help in this. 3. The Agency launch 'Disna'’ should be moored off the Customs pier from the afternoon of March 4th. 4. If His Highness the Shaikh is good enough to provide 3 cer for the Hon* ble the Politic*! FesidenVs use it may please be available at the Customs pier from 8.45 a.m. on March 5th. 5. Agency office should arrange for two lorries to be at the Customs pier at 8.45 a.m. on March 5 for the Hon*ble the Political Residents luggage. 6. Agency office will for two launches for the Kon'ble the Political Resident's luggage to leave the Customs pier at 7.00 a.m. on March 5th for the 'Kearchus' i 7* The Hon'ble the Political Resident and his family will land at the Customs pier at about 9 a.m. and drive to the Agency. The arrival will be private. 8. After the Hon'ble tho Political Resident has arrived the Political ^gent will inform the Adviser and tell him ct wh*t time the Hon*hie the Politieel Resident will be prepared to receive His Highness* visit. Tha tim^ will probably be 10 a.m. or 10.30 a.m. 9. At the time fixed for the visit His Highness will arrive (probably accompanied by Shaikh Mohammad bin *Isa, Shaikh Abdullah bin ’Tsa and the Adviser) and will be met when he descends from his car by the Assistant Political Agent. 10. Subject to consultation with the Adviser a guard of honour will be provided at the Agency for the arrival of His Highness the Shaikh. 11. The Assistant Political Agent will escort His Highness and party to the top of the Agency staircase where they will be met by the Political Agent. The Political Agent will escort His Highness and party to the entrance of the aajlis whore they will be received by the Hon*Die the Political Resident. 12. Coffee will be served, and. rose water and incense will be brought in after 15 minutes. IS /-13• The Hoii'ole tha Poliuicttl Resident will bid farewell to Kis Highness Pt the entrance to the majlis, the Political Agent will escort His Highness to the top of the Agency steps snd the Assistant Political Agent from there to His Highness* motor car* 14* The Hon*ble the Politic?! Hesilent, sccompanied by the Political Agent and the Assistant Political Agent, will return His Highness* visit s.fter a suitable interval. ^ 15. It will be decided later by the Hon*ble the Political Resident whether levj^ 16. dress or un dress uniform will be worn. The Hon T bl« the Political Resident has intimated that he will v/e©r uniform during the exchange of visit. The Politicel Agani and the Assistant Political Agent will also wear uniform. Ho salutes will be fired. oOo* File 19/3 His iSxeellency the Naval Comrnande-^in-Ghief T s \ (including Tmcial Ooast and 4 ata^)# % Details. Authority. Pn^limina^v . The Political Agent receives a p.83/File 19/3 copy of the proposed pn&gt;gr*anime of His Excellency the Naval Commande^in-Chief f s visit to the Persian Gulf. Action. (a) The political Agent info&gt;tns:~ (1) The Advisee, Bahrain Gove&gt;nnient, (2) The Residency Agent, Sharjah, (3) The niler of ^atar. (b) The Tmcial Chiefs a-»-e invited to meet His Excellency the Naval Commanderin-Chief at Dubai (in future this is mo^ likely to be at Sharjah). (c) The Political Agent sends a d*^aft p-^og^amme of ^'vents* and ’Exchange of Calls’ (demi-ofiicially) to His Excellency the Naval Commande^in-Chief, with a copy each to the Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf Division and the Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. This should be done in sufficient time to get by air mail any comments o^ alterations which His Excellency She Naval Commande^in-Chief may wish to make. (d) Invitation cards for ’Parties’ an* ordered from Messrs. Cartie^ London. Specimen p cards ar© on the file. p.84 p.86 p.85 f .!2/notes. • # A’s note d/-29-12-34 s.110(a) &amp; is.90,91, 1 and 93. .88 P.T.O.- 2 - (v) Hie 19/3 His Excellency the Naval Comaande^in-Chief^s visit (including Tmcial Coast and ^ata^). Details. Authority. From p^e-page,- (e) The political Agent invites p.90-9l His Excellency the Naval Commandsin-Chief and the Senior Naval Ofi’ioer, Persian Gulf Division, to stay at the Bahrain Agency. Arrangements a^e made lor the Flag Lieutenant to stay nea*r at hand. (The Advise- may kindly put him up). Note; It would probably be better in future ii the j lag Lieutenant we—e to be at the Agency and the Senio— Naval Office— stays with the •Adviser or at Jufai-. Matter should be discussed with the Senior Naval Office- at the time. Calls.- (i) The Political Agent accompanied by the p.110(d) Assistant Political Agent calls on His Excellency 1 ^ 16 the Naval Commands—in-Chief on boa-d the Flagship. (if) His Excellency the Shaikh of Bah-ain 'with his Family and usually the Advise- and the Di-ecto- of Customs follows after about 15 or 20 minutes. (iii) His Excellency the Shaikh of Bah-ain leaves the Flagship under a salute of 11 guns. (iv) The Political Agent accompanied by the Assistant political Agent leaves the Flagship unde- a salute of 11 guns.- 3 - iile 19/3 His excellency the Naval Oomraande^ia-Ohief's visit (including I'mcial Coast and ^atar). Details. Authority. (v) His Ercellenoj the Naval Commande^in- Ohiei lands at the Customs pie*^ under a salute °i‘ guns (co^ect number should be asceHained irom the Senior Naval Officer) and inspects the Guard 01 Honour* phe Di^ctor of Customs meets »k His skcellency the Naval Commando—in-Chief at the foot of the steps of the Customs pier, and the Political Agent, the Assistant Political Agent, end the Advise^ to the Bahrain Government meet him at the top of the steps. He is usually accompanied round the Guard by the Advise~ and the Political Agent and one Naval Officer (Flag Lieutenant). ( Note; I have always given the Adviser* the place of walking with His i&amp;ceiiency as it is the Bahrain Guani ). His lixcellency the Naval Commande^-in-Chief walks to the Customs Majlis between lines * of natu^. (vl) His Excellency the Naval Commanded in- «A.k Chief returns the Call of the Shaikh of Bahr-ain at the Customs Majlis. His Excellency the Shaikh meets His Excellency the Naval Commander in- Chief at the top of the Majlis room. D^ess . ~ ~ Full dress, hot o^ cold weather as onie~ed. P.f.O.File 19/3 - 4 - His Excellency the Naval Commande&gt;^iii-Chief f s visit Notes; (1) The Political Agent whites to the Advise^ to the Bahrain Grove^nnient for &amp;ua&gt;^l of Honour to wait upon His Excellency the Commande^-in-Chief at the Customs pie-r and info'ias him of the number of guns in the salute# This should be ascertained from the Senior Naval Office^ Persian Gulf Division, previously# His Excellency Shaikh Sir Hamad is not allowed anything sweet as he is on diet# (3) Calls between the Shaikhah and Mfe of His Excellency the Naval Commander.in-Chief an? made by special ar&gt;ungement • The Shaikhah p.125,p.146 calls first at the Agency. If the Political Agent f s 7-ife does not talk Arabic, it would be best to ask the adviser*s Wife to accompany them. Naturally the events vary somewhat on each occasion# programmes should be typed on coloured crested demi-official paper. Communion Service# - The political Agent arranges for a p.138. Communion Service to be held at the Agency p.150# (including Tmcial Coast and ^tar). Details. Authority. (2) The Political Agent explains to the Flag Lieutenant (demi-officially) that idle 19/3 p.113 Social Events .- A specimen programme is shown on the file. by the Flagship*s Chaplain, who is invited to/-- 5 - Hie 19/3 His iixcellency the Naval Commande-^in-Chief T s visit (includiug Pmcial Coast aad ^tar) # Details* Authority* , ^om p^e-pa^ce* - to stay ashore fo^ the ni^ht* This should iMk JL 4«aL W W in future be a^-^anged ahead by letter. j- % G-enc ^al * *4»t (a) 1 Felix JonesTennis Cou^t and Squash racquet couH a-e offered by the p.139, 140, 141* political Agent to the p'^esident, i'/ard loom Mess, for use by the Navy. (b) The Political Agent makes arrangements for taxis as required, but pages.175,176,177. the Navy reimburses the Agency lor any amounts spent on their behalf* It would be well to find out ahead what taxis will be wanted, as they are not easy to get at such times. (c) Ihen the invitation to His Excellency the Naval Commander-in r Chief to stay at the Agency is made, it would be well to find out separately from the ^lag Lieutenant by demi-official letter whether any other officers’ wives will be in the flagship and if they would like the Political Agent to ivy to ar-r'ange accommodation on shore.File 21/1-Vol.II) ?ile 19/5. ) Air Officer Commanding 1 s official visit . Details. Authority. 1. On receipt of information that the Air Officer Commanding’s visit is official, the Political Agent informs the Adviser to the Bahrain Government accordingly and makes arrangements for the Shaikh’s call on the Air Officer Commanding. Procedure. File 21/1. Vol-II p.58 It has been arranged that, until the C.O.File l-a/£ Royal Air Force have suitable buildings of their F.21/1—Vol.II X) 60 own, the Shaikh’s call on the Air Officer Commanding P * shell take place at the Agency. On one occasion ^in Captain Gastrell’s time) a Guard of Honour was provided and it may be that the Shaikh will bring his Guard of Honour for his own call at the Agency. If so, it is possible that the Shaikh may out of courtesy to the Air Officer Commanding (who like the Senior tfaval Officer is not entitled to a Guard of Honour) leave his Guard at the Agency to pay a compliment to the Air Officer Commanding on his leaving the Agency for the return Call. Otherwise the Guard usually on duty at the Qasr (for example, at the ’Ids) would, if it is on duty, turn out in the ordinary way. The return call would be paid at the Qasr. The Political Agent (and the Assistant Political Agent) will meet the Air Officer Commanding at the Landing ground or Flying Boat harbour. This will constitute* his call and the Air Officer Commanding’s coming to the Agency will constitute his return call. The Political Agent does not go out to the Flying Boat. | Dregsi Full unilorm with medals and decorations.Pile 19/5 Air Cfficer .Private visit, L i Details. Authority Arrival » The Air Cfficer Commanding will be met by the Assistant Political Agent at Muharraq aerodrome or the sea—plane anchorage, and conducted to the Agency. Interchange of Calls with the Shaikh will be dependent on the length of his stay (which is seldom more than one night)• Departure . The Air Cfficer Commanding upon his /' / departure from Bahrain will be accompanied by the Assistant Political Agent to Muharraq aerodrome or the seaplane anchorage. So t e Warning of the Air Officer Commanding*s arrival and departure is generally received three days beforehand. The Assistant Political Agent should then issue the necessary preliminary orders for Taxis, and Diana. In the case of his arrival at Muharraq the Assistant Political Agent should ascertain if a good taxi is available and if not write a letter n for Political Agent' asking Shaikh Abdullah to be kind enough to lend his car to meet the Air Officer Commanding on the aerodromeFile 3/16 © Senior Naval Officer’s call on His Excellency the Shaikh of Bahrain* Details* Authority&lt; 'A' Prior to establishment of Na val Base at Jufair . 1* The Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, telegraphs the Political Agent asking him to S.No.l File 3/16. arrange callp between him (the Senior Naval Officer) and the Shaikh* 2* The Political Agent arranges the calls S*No.20 &amp; p*21 with the Shaikh through the Adviser by letters* Procedure; The Political Agent (accompanied by the Assistant Political Agent) calls on the Senior p.9/noteB Naval Officer, first on board the Ship, which lies at the Ship anchorage off the Customs Pier* The Shaikh (accompanied by his relatives and usually by the Adviser) follows the Political Agent after 30 minutes* The Shaikh remains on board for about haxf an hour and the usual courtesies are -do- exchanged. On termination of visit, the Shaikh leaves the ship under a salute of 11 guns. On his arrival at the Customs Pier, the Bahrain guns fire a further salute of 11 guns. After the Shaikh’s guns have finished firing, the Political Agent leaves the Ship under a salute of 11 guns and awaits the Senior Naval Officer, who follows in his barge accompanied by one or more naval officers at the head of the Customs Pier. On landing at the Customs Pier, the Senior Naval Officerv&gt; H ^ ll( File 3/16 Senior Naval Officer’s call on His Excellency the Shaikh of Bahrain. Details. Authority. is met at the ftfot of the steps by the Director of Customs and at the top of the steps by the Adviser to the Bahrain Government* The Senior Naval Officer returns the Shaikh’s call at the Customs * Majlis and then goes with the Political Agent to the Agency f usually for lunch* and this consti tutes his return call. goMir. On one occasion (a visit b? Captain Creagh) the Shaikh’s Guard of Honour was left at the pierhead as a matter of courtesy* but the Senior Naval Officer is not entitled to it. p.ll/notes F.3/1* On that occasion the Guard also presented arm© as the Political Agent,landed. The Senior Naval Officer inspected the Guard of Honour and walked to the Customs rajlis between lines of nature. ,er Vpc e s.Q£..^e, Naya^L..Sa§SL.%i. .?Mair. There has only been one such call. The Political Agent was away and Lieutenant H.D. Metcalfe as officiating was Assistant Political Agent. The Senior Naval Officer apparently arranged his own Call without reference to the Agency. , The following procedure was, it is understood* followedi- 'His Excellency called upon the Senior Naval Officer in H.M.S. Shoreham off Jufair. He went out in his own launch from the Jufair pier. There was no guard of honour and the only salutes \- r-N U Senior Naval Officer’s call on His Excellency the Shaikh of Bahrain- (!5 Details. Authority. salutes fired were by the ship for His Excellency when he left. His Excellency wore his usual dress and carried his sword. The Senior Naval Officer returned the visit at the Palace immediately after His Excellency returned there. The Senior Naval Officer wore white uniform. The visits took place in the afternoon. 2 * On the next occasion of an exchange of calls between the Shaikh and a new Senior Naval Officer, arrangements shall be made in the usual way through the Political Agent (or m his absence the Assistant Political Agent). ~ e — Exchange of calls on His Excellency the Shaikh should be avoided, if possible, during the month of Hamadhan. Caas of Naval Officer are regulated b\ the orders contained in memorandum No. 23/464 p.30 File 3/16 S.No.31 -do- dated the 28th Hay 1931 f ronl the s enior ij- aval Officer, Persian Gulf, to the Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. C.O.File 1 -a. 3.File 16/5 &amp; ) 3/20., ) Vis its ench Admira » A » Authority. ’ Visit 1 of French Admiral Seville in lasn . 1. French Admiral Deville arrived at Bahrain Diary from on the 30th December 1930 and left on the December^ 2 nd January 1930, 2 . The Political Agent Captain (now Major) Prior called on the French Admiral on his arrival, but no salute was fired as the *Diana f had apparently exhausted the year f s supply of ammunition of this fleet in connection with the coronation festivities in Abyssinia. 3. The Admiral called on Shaikh (now Sir) Hamad who was then acting on behalf of his father the late Shaikh •Isa bin r Ali at the Palace. 4. The Admiral returned the Political Agent's call on the 31st December 1930 and Shaikh Hamad returned the Admiral's call at the Agency. 5. Dress: Full uniform. 1930. File 16/5. -do- -do- -do- •B 1 Xlsit of trench A dmiral Rivet in 19.^/s . 1. The French Sloop 'Bougainville”, flying the Flag of Centre Amiral Rivet, Officer Commanding, Levant Station, arrived on a visit to Bahrain on the 14th February 1935 . The Political Agent (Colonel Loch) was away Kv tour in H.M.S. Fowey and Mr. Worth, Assistant Political Agent, was in Bahrain. P«24,30 File 3/20.s.tp Bahrain Details* Authority* p.24 File 3/20. 2* No direct informationof the arrival of 'Bougainville” had been received till 9*0 a*m. - February 14 - an hour after the ship had arrived. It was impossible for the launch to go out as the tide was exceptionally low. At 1 p*m* the Assistant Political Agent sent a letter to the Admiral to say that he proposed visiting him privately at 3*15 to discuss the programme of calls* The Admiral replied that he would come ashore at 3 p.m. The Assistant Political Agent accordingly met the Admiral, who was accompanied by several officers, at the Customs pier. He brought them to the Agency 5 gave them tea and drew up a programme of calls. The following programme was followed:- Le^uary l$th* Hours * 09.30 The Assistant Political Agent called on Hear Admiral Bivet on board Bougainville. 09.45 The Assistant Political Agent left Bougainville (Mo salute was fired as Mr.Worth was not entitled to it)• 10.25 Hear Admiral Rivet arrived at the Customs Pier and was met by the Financial Adviser to the Government of Bahrain and the Assistant Political Agent. He inspected the Guard of Honour. A * salute of 13 guns was fired. 10.40 Rear Admiral Rivet returned the call of the Assistant Political Agent at the Agency. 11.00 *Hear Admiral Rivet accompanied by the Assistant Political Agent called on His Excellency Shaikh Sir Hamad bin »Isa A1 Khalifah, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., at the Palace. 9 P.T.O.— Details Authority * Calls were arranged beforehand• 11.30 His Excellency bhaikh Sir Hamad returned the call of Rear Admiral Rivet at the Agency. Rote . The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf had suggested to the Assistant Political Agent that p.27 it would be proper during the present File 3/20 visit of 'Bougainville' if the Shaikh returned the call of Rear Admiral Rivet on board. It was found, however, impracticable to do this as the Shaikh wished to attend Juma prayers at midday and Rear Admiral Rivet would have been unable to lunch at the Agency. Reair Admiral Rivet said to the Assistant Political Agent that he preferred to have the return call paid at the Agency. Dress: Full uniforms were worn. Social » The Assistant Political Agent entertained the Admiral and four officers of the French Warship at luncheon at the Agency and afterwards took them to the Oil Field where they were shown drilling operations. On their return they met the Political Agent (Colonel Loch) who had come back from tour P*30 that afternoon. The Political Agent saw the Admiral in the evening at the Agency. He offered to call upon the Admiral who said that the official calls had been done and that the Political Agent should lunch ^ with him (Admiral) on board the next day (16th February). The Admiral held a luncheon party on board the 'Bougainville' on the 16th and sailed for Bushire on the same afternoon. H.M.S. Fowey,when coming into Bahrain harbour saluted the Admiral 1 s Flag when passing the 'Bougainville' and the latter replied. The usual Hval naval calls were exchanged.VISIT OF MR. KNATCHBULL-HUGESSEN See C.O. File 12/9, pages 27 to 31. Details. Authority. Mr. Knatchbull-Hugessen, His Majesty’s Minister at Tehran, accompanied by Mrs.Knatchbull- Hugessen, arrived at Bahrain in H.M.S. Shoreham on the afternoon of 27th February and departed for Bushire on the 28th February. The visit was unofficial and informal and no calls were inter changed with Shaikh. The Political Agent asked him and his wife to stay the night Pages 30 &amp; 31, of 27th February, which was accepted.VISIT OF MINISTER AT JEDDA. Details Authority. Sir Andrew Ryan, X.fl.h., British i'in it ter at Jedda * - - An invitation for hit. stay ^and alto Captain de Gaury, who was interpreting for him) was given privately by Political Agent in England* At the Political Resident was expected at the sa:ae time the Adviser was aa^ced to accommodate Captain de Gaury* m M&amp;u . The Political Agent met the Minister at the aerodrome. Mufti was worn* (Assistant Political Agent was ill or would have accompanied him)* (Adviser, Shaikh Caiman and Minister’s staff were present in this case). Minister met the Shaikh at the top of the stairs* The call was returned informally at the asr. The ^litical Agent took the Minister in the Agency car and the Adviser took Captain de Gaury a few minutes before them. Bahrain from 17th November 1936 to C.G. file 12 / 9 . 20 th November 1936 on hie way to Riyadh and•Jedda. Shaikh called informally on Page 14 - the day after the ini©ter’e arrival. C.o* file 12/9 / Social.Details Authority mm*. The Political Agent arranged an f At Home’ for British and American residents of Manaaah to meet the inis ter and a dinner party. Ihe Shaikh *afc asked to take tea with the Minister on some convenient afternoon. The Political Agent (Assistant Political Agent was ill) accompanied the Minister Note*- It was decided that Political Resident should take precedence at table over the Minister, as the latter was outside his own area. £. Minister should not be addressed, or written of, as His Excellency, though the style is accorded to him in ^ Jedda by a special order of the Sa'udi Arabian Government. Page £9 and 70 Etequette file. page ?l9.t. Foreign M^ta^er (See C.O. File la/20 (a) ). Details* Authority* 1* If Minister is not staying in Agency and does not call on the Political p.64 &amp; 59 Agent in the course of the first day cr so f p.66 the Political Agent should call on him informally* 2. The Political Agent takes Minister p*38,78 A 80 to call on Shaikh informally* 3* The Minister receives Shaikh*s return call at the Agency*'‘k-Y^ris) Fil« 6/58 Accession celebrations. Details* Authority. p.103, p•106• p*48 p.47 1. Invitation Cards for British and Americans are obtained from Messrs. Cartier Iiimited f London and for local people from the p.91 Times Press l imited, Basrah three months in p*106 advance. Action should be started three months before the date of the Celebrations. 2. If suitable, the Political Agent invites the Honourable the Political Hesident, Senior Naval Officer and Air Officer Commanding on the occasion of the Accession Anniversary. They usually send messages of congratulation if possible and/take part in the celebrations in Bahrain. Invitations should issue a month before the Celebrations. 3. The Political Agent closes his office on the Sports day except for urgent work. 4. The Political Agent gives an *At Home* p.93 at the Police Sports ground to the Shaikhs, British and Americans and the leading merchants. From the Political Agent’s office the Indian Assistant and Head Munshi are invited. The Sports are usually on the last day. 6 . The Political Agent offers two special p.110 prizes of Rs.15/- and Hs.10/- each to the best and second best competitor in the Police Sports. Money is sent to the Adviser beforehand for the purpose. Note? The question of presentation of a File 6/69 shield is under consideration. 6 . \ The Political Agent and the Assistant Political Agent call on the Shaikh on the Accession/^File 6/58 Accession celebrations * Details. Authority. Shailch on the Accession Day at the Palace and see the displays. 7. The Political Agent and Assistant Political Agent go to the Baladiyah to a receiption held in honour of the Shaikh. Io£&amp;: The Indian Assistant and the Political Agent's clerical staff receive independent invitations from the Baladiyah on this occasion. 8 . The Political Agent and the Assistant Political Agent go to see the Arab dances at His Excellency the Shaikh's Palace and on one night to the Suq which is decorated for three nights. 9. Flagstaff and launches are dressed for three days. go taf Detailed notes on the proceedings are2 rt me 20/1. r ing*B Birthday celebrations. Tetcile. Authority. i u The Honourable tlie Political Hesldent p*109.P.20/1, infoma the Political Aifcnt (by telcijfrea) date of r ln^ , e Birthday celebratione. AsAlma. !• The PoliticGl Agent obtains Invitation cards for British and Aaericane from Messrs Cartier p.104 •ad limited t londcn, and from the Times Press, Basrah, p.XCd i or local people 3 months In advenes. a sample os it! p.l5/h. ie on the file. 3. Hje Political Agent infonaa Hi# Excellency the Shaikh who with his relatives calls on the Political Agent (the Assistant Political Agent is p*166 present) on the King's Birthday at the Agency. Political Agent writes to the Adviser for Guard of Honour to be drawn up at p*116 the Agency Oats to *mit upon His Excellency the Shaikh. ^• Office is closed for one day. Fijla 16/43. ijrooechire. ; 1» j Flagataff ia dresaad. 1 ' 2. The Agency ataff call# on the Political Agent (the Assistant Political Agent ia present) at the Agency at &amp; o'clock. 3. ; His Excellency the Shaikh!# visit. See 2 above. The Indian Assistant leads His Excellency Dhnikh to the Political Agent and the Assistant Political Agent, who receive His Excellency thek a^t the top cf Agency star is. Bimil*rly/ p.13/notea, A i\V @ File 20/1 • 2 Details* Authority* :iiail&amp;rly after meeting the Indian Aseistnnt leads back His Excellency the Shaikh to Hie Excellency the Shaikh*e car outside the Agency gate* The Adviser to the Bahrain Govern ant usually accompanies the shaikh* 4* Arabs, Fere lane, Indians and other costramities call on the Political Agent (the Assietent Political Agent is present) afV r the termination of the t5haikh , s visit* 1* Vhe Court ^looa is decorated and fumiehed with carpet# and chaire borrov/ed from Baladiyah sad dais and seating arrangement are made under the Indian Assistant*# supervise 2* Tht Indian Assistant reports to the Political Agent that th* guests &gt;mve arrived# The Political Agent accompanied by th© Assistant Political Agent end Indian Assist nt enters the Hall and the gucots rise up* The Political .Agent, Assistant Folitical Ager.t and the Indian Assistant go to the dais and the PolitiCnl Agent shakes hands with those on the dais* Then all t&amp;ke their seats* The Political Agent sits in the middle with the Assistant Political Agent on the right end Indian Asaist&amp;nt on the left* 3* The leading members of the various communities make speeches and sweats ar^rl coffee are served to the gueota in the following suann^rt- « . 1* CoffeeAuthority# 3 . 3m**tjm*Xa* 4* Coffoe* 5# Tih* Tihon r#fr&lt;iiihment« ure ov#r f tha Political a#s i»t#*nt Political Ag^nt and the Indian Aeaiatant ehcke hands with the guests priority be inf givtn to those on dels# Sole i 1* Heed Ifunshi cotlecte and subnits to tli« Political Agent draft speeches from the representatives of the v^rlou^ coia unities beforehand and checks the contents to make suire that the apeeches ar*: suitable. 2# Venaacular Office check the liste of guests| see that no uninvited guests enter and report on the absentees* The Political Agent holds reception of tlie British and American coqpmmitie# in the afternoon* fiBUi* Pul drsea with decorations for morning Calls* Itufti Ictmge suit for afternoon reception*• 2 - 5 &amp; File 20/1 Christmas and New Year’s Day. Details. Authority. See notes* 5# The Indian Assistant leads His Excellency the Shaikh to the Political Agent and Assistant Political Agent, who receive^Hls Excellency the Shaikh at the top of Agency stairs. Similarly after meeting, the Indian Assistant leads back His Excellency the Shaikh to Hie Excellency the Shaikh’s car outside the Agency gate. The Adviser to the Bahrain Government usually accompanies His Excellency the Shaikh. 6. The Political Agent and Assistant Political Agent receive visits from Arabs, Persians, British Indians and others at 10.30 a.m. in the Court Room. 7. The Court Room is decorated and furnished with carpets and chairs borrowed from the Baladiyah and dais and seating arrangements are made under the Indian Assistant’s supervision. The following procedure is observedi- 1* The Indian Assistant reports to the Political Agent that the guests have arrived. The Political Agent accompanied by the Assistant Political Agent and the Indian Assistant enters the Hall and the guests rise up. The Political Agent, Assistant Political Agent and Indian Assistant go to the dais and the Political Agent shakes hands with those on the dais. Then all take their seats. The Political Agent sits in the middle with the Assistant Political Agent an the ri^it and the Indian Assistant on the left. pages,14,15 &amp; 16, F.20/1-Vol. III. See notes* pages 14.15 &amp; 16. —do-— ——doFile 20/1 Christmas and New Year’s Day Details Authority 2 The leading members of the various communities make speeches and sweets and coffee ©re served to the guests in the following manner i- 1# Coffee. 2# Speeches. 3. Sweetmeats. 4. Coffee. 5. Tib. Political Agent, Assistant Political Agent and Indian Assistant shake hands with the guests priority being given to those on the dais. the Political Agent draft speeches from the representatives of the various communities before-hand and checks the contents to make of guests; see that no uninvited guests enter -and report on the absentees. Calls from British and Ame r ican Communities. The Political Agent receives calls from British and American communities at 12.00 hours. They are notified by means of a circular. Dress: The Political Agent and Assistant in uniform for the British and American calls. p.9 File //hen refreshments are over, the Note: 1. Head Munshi collects and submits to sure that the speeches are suitable. 2. Vernacular Office check the listsFile 16/9 Dotails. v Authority. Action^ 1 . i?iie 16/43. Phe roiicical Agent issues notice that his office will be closed fo~ fcwo day. 2. Flagstaff is dossed on the ii~st day of ’Id. 3. Phe political iigont issues fetuses of coiigmtulations to the lie si deucy iigont, p.230-243 oharjah, Pmcial dhiefs, shaikh of ^ta-r, iuni*^ of Kasa and luler of Kuwait* 4. Phe political Agent sometimes distributes 1 lb suga*^ ana 4 lbs ri ce each to the menial staff on ’Id-ui-Fitr (not the ’Id-ul-hhuha) but in 1935 this was not done p.4/notes as the ’Id was so near Christmas that all the staff got cash presents. Palis. - 5. Phe political Agent, the Assistant Political Agent and the Indian Assistant p.225 call on His Excellency the Shaikh* pine is fixed befo-ohand. 6* Phe lolitical Agent and the Assistant Political Agent and the Indian Assistant call on the leading me^ohunts and ihalkhs at Manamah and Kuha^ra^ on the 1st and End day of ’Id as arranged. Mrs. Locn calls on He~ Excellency the Shaikhah. Peo Etiquette file in 0*0* Note. - Phe political Agent and the Assistant Political Agent go in the Agency car the Indian Assistant in a taxi* phe Heau Fe-ash p.id43Filefe 12/5 ARRIVAL OP HE? POLITICAL AOEHT. 1/1 Voluiaefe I A II. ■S \ 3. Shaikh Selaiwn, feon of !U*i jaKae-llertey Shaikh Sir Hamad, and alfco Shaikh Uashld bin Muhammad, met Colonel Loch at the aerodrome on hie arrival ae Political Agent on the 27th November 1^32. Shaikh Muhammad bin ’lea went to the aerodrome to welcome the new Political Agent but aa he waa suffering from cold and the aeroplane waa late he aaked the Political Agent Captain (now Ma^or) C.O.Prior to express his regret© to Colonel Loch and went home. It la probable that this was done as they had known Colonel Loch before. As far as can be traced it was not done when Captain Prior arrived and it la certain that it was not done when Colonel Barrett arrived. His fcjrojfeteney the Shaikh accompanied by his sons and brothers calls on the new Political Agent at the Agency on do—- /the second2 0 Ufctallp # the second day. The outgoing Political Agent (and the AeBietant Political Agent) are present. The cuetomary Arab refreehRicntB, coffee, ecent and incense are eerved. Full dre«fc Uniform ie worn. i^^ojPity,_ V '’ages 1, 2, Z&gt; $ 4 file 12/5. ‘'age 172/corr. file 1/1 Volume I 4. The yieit of His utodillewoy ie returned by the new Political /'.gent (with the outgoing Political Agent and Assistant Political Agent). Full dreee Uniform ie worn. 5. Notables call on the Political Agent to pay their respects. PlZXSl A h, 1. Specimen signature© are sent toj- (l) The Sub-Postmester, Bahrain. do do p. 120 file l/l *(2) The hastem Banlc imlted, Bahrain, p. 119 (3) The Reserve Sank of India,Karachi, o.118 - (4) The Reserve Bank of India,Bombay, p.117 2. Form of official seal and specimen of signaturee of new- political Agent are sent, in quadruplicate, to Bushire, also charge certificate, in quadruplicate. 5. Charge certificate is sent to the Acco\mtant-Oeneral, Central Revenues, New Delhi. 4. The following are notified:- ;&gt; . 121, 122 - file 3/1. page 116 - file l/l. 1. Air Officer Commanding, Royal Air Force, Baghdad. / 2. p.113 file l/l By ta’lefrPQTin L.File l/24. 9 1 Mi political \ Authority* Ts Details* ictioiu * * 4 »% 1* i?he iroliwical u-uafc io^wa^ds to if' i / « ■ f the new ju^istant Political Agent a conciee p*76^' note containing gone^l information about T Bahrain f # p.i!2(a) file l/24~I 2# fhe Assistant political Agent (accoic^janied by the Indian Assistant if ^juui^d) meets the new Assistant political p*b/notes -do- 4gent on boanl the siiip o- at the ae'~od~ome as the case may be. 3. ’Felix Jones’ is sank out to b-iny the Assistant iolitioal Agent to the Agency. Heoiry kit should be brought in an hired launch* 4* Oha%c OeHiiicate is sent to the Secr-etar/ to the Honou^ble the political p*ld6-139 Hie 1/24-1 ^Jesid^t in the Persian Gulf, bnshi^ and the j'-ccountant-Gcneral Central BeTenues, New ifeliii. 5. ?ho Political Agent takes the Assistant political Af-ent to cull on His Excellency the Shaikh in the Agency fhe Shaikh ^tu^ns call at the p *6/notee. /lie 1/24-1 • igency. full d^ss. Mik His dKcellcncy the uhaiAh meets the/-The Agency *At Homes* ^ Details. Authority i It is understood that an Agency *At Home* on Friday afternoon for Europeans was started in Major Daly*s time. Then it was the only social event of the week and everyone was expected to attend• 2. Captain Prior carried on the *At Home*, but on my arrival told me that it was getting bigger than was easy to manager with the limited accommodation of the Agency. In the meantime Mr Belgrave and the Mission had started a tennis afternoon also. 3. After some hesitation I decided to carry on with the party as it had considerable value socially and politically. In 1933 it was just manageable, but afterwards became rather crowded, especially when tennis was played. With the just increase in the British and American Community, it has become impossible to have an *At Home* to which all have an open invitation, otherwise on some Fridays few may come, while on some a great crowd may evidently appear. In the circumstances of Bahrain, it is impossible to cater for such fluctuations. Some difficulty, in spreading out the tennis, is also caused by the fact that there are now other *afternoons *, for example, at the Adviser’s, Bank, Mespers, Mission and so on. Two alternatives were considered (a) to. ask residents, Manamah with an invitation for_ all Fridays and residents at the New Camp a ■ '7 few/-</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000186_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1655</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000186</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1655</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 19/2 V Tours of the Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1945/1950</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-11-26T18:00:39</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (132 folios)</extent><extent>The papers in the file are arranged chronologically. There are notes within the file, on folios 84-91. The notes are arranged chronologically and refer to documents within the file; they give brief description of the correspondence with a number in blue and red crayon, which refers back to that correspondence in the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 134; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 1-83 and between ff 93-133; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled, and are located in the same position as the main sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains telegrams and correspondence regarding arrangements for official visits of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf to Bahrain and other Persian Gulf countries between 1945 and 1950.The principal correspondents are: British Overseas Airways Corporation (BOAC); the Political Officer in the Trucial Coast; the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf; the Political Agent at Muscat; the Political Agent at Kuwait; and the Political Agent at Bahrain.The final part of the file contains procedure for visits of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf and other officials, the protocol for the accession celebration of the Ruler of Bahrain, for the King's birthday, and for public holidays.The file contains a letter in English and Arabic, to the Political Officer in the Trucial Coast.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Agent, Trucial Coast</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Agent, Kuwait</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Agent and Consul, Muscat</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>British Overseas Airways Corporation</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent; subject</roleTerm></role></name><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000186#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>