<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000419.0x0001a3_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-19T21:53:24.680Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">NOT FOR DIRECT COPIES MAY BE PHOTOCOPYING ORDERED FROMMinutes. t 0 Lyi ) b) OvJld U-B^l '£tZ^ 0 V////6 ,2—q.') Wt. 40797—11. 5000 2—„) „ 30564—113. 3000 Mr Oliphant, The pencil minute at the end of the draft 'Repeat to Indl perhaps a' is the hand writing of someone in the India Office? I rather fancy it must be. The man who cyphered the telegram in question has no re collection whether the pencil minute was there or not when he did it,but the inference is that it was,as it app'/aars on the manifolded copies. I regret therefore that we must accept responsibility for the lache,the only consolation being that they do not occur oftener. M.W.L. 24.1,16. &amp;f l/v&amp;i* '~&gt; n * x y c ^° * B&amp;B.In reply please quote P 131. My dear Oliphant, Please see enclosed copy of a letter from the Foreign Secretary to the Government of India. The words 'repeat to India” appear in the copy of Foreign Office telegram to Cairo No.874 dated 11th November as furnished to us. Possibly by some mischance they were not cyphered'? Yours sincerely. L. Oliphant, Esq.Confidentia l. Foreign and Political Department, Delhi. 16th December 1915. My dear Hirtzel, Will you kindly refer to the telegram from the London Foreign Office to the High Commissioner, Egypt, Ho.674, dated the 11th November 1915, a copy of which was sent to the Government of India with your weekly letter, No.46 dated the 12th November 1915. The message in question deals with the Arab negotiations. From the copy received here it appears that the High Commissioner was instructed to ' repeat to India '. Sir H.McMahon in reply to. an enquiry states that he received no injunction to repeat the message to us. i The telegram was of great importance and to prevent further misunderstandings we should be grateful if the matter could be cleared up. Yours sincerely, (Sd.) A.H.Grant. Sir Arthur Hirtzel. K.C.B.. Secretary, Political Department, India Office, London.C 0 n f i c • 'f : t i 1. f 13 1 ^pfj . .f 4 ; \ ol j Delhi. »|A ; i The Decemljer 1915. I ^ My 5 esr Hlrtzel, Sill you kindly refer to the telegram from the London For elm Office to the High Commissioner, Egypt, No. tllf) 874, dated the 11th November 1915, a copy of which was sent to the Government of India with your weekly letter, No. 46 dated the lath November 1915. The message in question deals with the Arab negotiations. From the copy received here It appears that the Hign Commissioner was instructed to M re,oe• ti m to, I rrmji” • 3ir H. McMahon in reply to tm enquiry states that he receiver no injunction to repeat the message to us. The telegram was of great importance arc to prevent further misunderstandings v: e should he grateful it the matter could he cleared up. Yours sineerely, ^ Jf To Sir r/rthur hlrtzel, K.C.3., Secretary, political Department, India office, London. tyv 'S* ft 13 JANISC^ ~o \'.In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote No. 19826 ^i 9 i5 and address— The Under-Secretary of State Foreign Office, London. SECRET r ( v 'ro The Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the UNDER SECRETARY OP STATE FOR INDIA anc ^ b direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop)/ of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, December 29th , Sip. Reference to previous correspondence Letter H } Foreign Office : from * ^ Description of Inclosure. Name and Date. Subject, Sir H. McMahon, Cairo. No. 172, Secret. Dec. 14th Arab Question. (Similar letter sent to Director of Military Operationsi/J / / #/ 1' Secret. Sir (Vri*) (W^j Cr&amp;l*-) if‘pinJ I have the honour to forward a copy of ay letter of today to the ^herif of lecca. Time does not allow before the mail leaves of more than a few brief remarks. It will be observed that I have adhered closely to the wording of the draft submitted in my telegram ??o.?36 of Hov.SQth as amended by your tel egram of Dec.loth. I have done so especially in re gard to the portion relating to Bagdad and Basra, tout had to omit the word Mesopotamia, as there is no Arab equivalent for this English term which would assist the intended meaning of tbs formula as ex plained in the Viceroy»£ telegram of !!ov,22nd # with out exciting suspicions. I have also omitted any reference in the letter to the possibility of a future settlement of tJi Mesopotamian question on a financial basis, but I have verbally hinted something to this effect to the Sherif’s messenger. I hlive availed myself of the sanction conveyed in your telegram of December 10th, to send a sum of £20,000 to the Sherif, It was at first intended to send only £ 10,000 on this occasion, but the urgency of the case renders in Eight Honourable Dir Grey Bart. {.G. M.’’ etc. etc., etc. ,T C'—', To /Sherif -Hussein : After customary greetings and acknowledgment of previous letter I am gratified to observe that you agree to the exclusion of the vilayets of T/ersina and Adana from the boundaries of the Arab territories. I also note with great pleasure and satis- faction your assurances that the Arabs are deter mined to act in conformity with the precepts laid down by Omar Ibn Khattab and the early Khalils, which secure the rights and privileges of all religions alike. In stating that the Arabs are ready to re cognize and respect all our treaties with Arab Chiefs , it is of course understood that this will apply to all territories included in the Arab Kingdom, as the Government of Great Britain cannot repudiate engagements which already exist . W'ith regard to the vilayets of Aleppo and Beyrout, the Government of Great hritain have taxon careful note of your observations, but, as the inter ests of our Ally France are involved, the question will require careful consideration and a luriher communication on the subject will be addressed to you c in due course . The Government of Great Britain as I have already infomed you , are ready t &gt; rive all guarantees of assistance and support within their power to the Arab Kingdom, hut their interests demand , as you yourself have recognized, a friendly and stable admin istration in the vilayet of iagMad, and the adequateThe Residency, Cairo. Ba f 'egua.r&lt;Ung of these interests calls for a much fuller and more detailed consideration than the present situation and the urgency of these negotiat ions permits . vie fully appreciate your desire for caution, and we have no wish to urge you to hasty nctJ m, which miffst ieopardize the eventual success of your projects, out in: the reantirne, it if r most ( vonn tri a L th r: t you should so a. re no effort to 2 touch all the Are a peoples to our united cause and u rrp ther e i-o afford. no assist ande to our enemies. It is on the success of the-e the more active measures which the Ar oake in support of our cause, ^hen th comes, that the nemance and strength efforts and on nos any hereafter e tine for action yf our e “rcenne&amp;t mu 8 o depend. Under these clrcans .ances I aia further directed py the Government of Great Britain to inform you that : ou may rest assured that Great Britain has no intent ion of concluding any peace, in terns of which the freedom of the Aral) peoples from German and Turkish domination does not form an essential cono.1 tion . As an earnest of our intentions ana in order to aid you in your efforts in our joint cause I am sending by your trustworthy messenger a sun of* twenty thousand pounds• ( Customary ending ) ( signed ) H . McMahdn.s' x 7 r» /U &amp; \J Telegram P., dated (and received) the 22nd October 1915. From—The High Commissioner of Egypt, To— His Excellency the Viceroy (Foreign and Political Department), Simla. I have sent the following telegram No. 623 to London Foreign Office on 18th October. Please see my despatch No. 121. I submit herewith following summary of a letter from Sheriff of Mecca dated September 9th, wdiich I received in reply to a letter sent to him by myself on August 30th—in this connection please see my despatch No, 94. Though Sheriff finds its tone lukewarm and ambiguous on central point of future of Arab boundaries he has received my letter with greatest pleasure. Sheriff expresses his preference for end confidence in British Empire in all circumstances as dictated by his followers* real interests. Nevertheless he is disturbed by our statement that it is useless to discuss territorial limits of Arab power, while countries involved are still in hands of enemy. Though it may be a matter of necessity to settle Arab boundaries with more than one power and that only after the present war has come to end, matter is never theless one of life and death for Arab people. As Arab people are united on this point, they, therefore, must discuss question with Great Britain, as she is the one power in which Arabs repose confidence. To inspire their people with con fidence and avoid possibility of finding themselves in opposition to England or any of her Allies, a settlement of boundaries of their country is necessary, In territories which they demand, they have not included places inhabited by foreign race and in this connection their attitude is but a bare expression of necessaries of their economic life, and not vain show of words. Sheriff dismisses idea that His Majesty’s Government hesitate to admit demands of Arabs because some of their people are still^ defending Turkish interests and reiterates his expression of loyalty to us. We may rest assured that all Arabs are only waiting result of present negotiations even including those who are obeying Turco-German orders. This result will depend on refusal or acceptance by His Majesty’s Government of territorial proposals put forward by rhem and on a declaration by His Majesty s Government safeguarding their rights and religion. Sheriff asks for directions as to course wffiich he is to pursue and for a com munication as to nature of our policy. Telegram ?., dated the 22nd (received 23rd) October 1915. From-—His Majesty’s Secretary of State for India, London, To—His Excellency the Viceroy (Foreign and Political Department), Simla. Arabia Reference is invited to telegram* from High Commissioner in •Serial NO. (i). Egypt ^ October 18th and telegramf from tSeriai No. (3). Foreign Office to High Commissioner, Egypt, of October 20th, both of which were repeated to Government of India. It was wfith great reluctance that I expressed concurrence in instructions made with out consulting Your Excellency, but both Kitchener and Grey attached utmost importance to returning immediate and favourable reply to Arab overtures, and matter was represented to me as of an extremely urgent nature. Two telegrams which I saw' for first time on 20th instant from General Officer Commanding Egypt to War Office reported young Arab party, which was represented V&gt;y Sheriff of Mecca, included influential and large section actually m Turkish army, who are sworn to cause of Arab party. It was stated by Maxwe t la Germans and Turks were already spending money to win support ot party and negotiating with them, but that Arabs had a strong leaning towards England and were anxious that we should declare what policy of His Majesty s Govern- meat w r as to he. If them overtures were rejected or our reply delayed, they J C. t w &gt; 0 n;:vA foreign secretary’s ko. 33 me 2 would throw in their lot with enemy, and would thus increase our difficulties materially both in Arabia and Mesopotamia as well as with Senoussi, and would facilitate invasion of Egypt greatly. He considered we should run the^ risk of genuine jehad and united Islam against us unless definite and agreeable proposal was made to Sheriff. Eord Hitchener and Sir Edward Grey have accepted this view of situation. Your Excellency will receive copy of Maxwell’s telegrams by mail which leaves here on 22nd October. Telegram P., dated (and received) the 22nd October 1915. Prom—The High Commissioner, Egypt, To—Ihe Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment. On the 20th instant the Foreign Office, London, telegraphed as follows:— #Sft-- al Xni Yo. 796, Please refer to your per sonal telegram* of 18th instant. Cordial assurances on the lines proposed by you and with reserve about our Allies may he given. Unless it is necessary to secure Arab consent, the stipulation that Arabs will recognise as paramount British interests, and will work under British guidance, etc., should not be included, as this might give rise in France to an impression that we were not only endeavouring to secure Arab interest but at the expense of the French were endeavouring to establish our own interests in Syria. There is in speaking without reserve about Arab peninsula and holy places no difficulty. The general reserve you propose is however necessary more especially for boundaries on north-western quarter. The proposed sphere of British control as regards Mesopotamia, namely Basrah Vilayat in view of special^interests in Baghdad Province and area actually in our occupation will need extension. Of course, our existing treaties with Arab Chiefs will stand. &amp; f the most important thing is to give an assurance that will prevent the Arabs from being alienated, and as the matter is urgent and there is no time to discuss exact terms, I must leave things to your discretion in the matter. Simplest plan would be^to give an assurance of Arab independence sayim* if they will send representatives we will proceed at once to discuss boundaries, but you can give it if something more precise than this is required, Wingate should be kept informed by you. Telegram P., dated the 22nd (received 23rd) October 1915, From—The High Commissioner, Egypt, His Excellency the Viceroy. To On the 20th instant the following telegram sent to Foreign Office. London as No, 626. 5 Please refer to my telegram No. 623.f The messenger of the Sheriff f Seriar No. 1. of Medina, who brought his letter to Eoypt , , q-i ... TT , has arrived at Cairo, and is now awaiting our reply to Sheriff. He reports as follows:— ° The fact that the English have not prevented the despatch of the sacred carpet or pilgrimage has much impressed Sheriff, and for all privations endured by Hedjaz the Turks are now held responsible. On the 2nd SentemW 1 ,- son Sheriff Abdullah left with 16,000 men for Nejed, ostensibly to support I n Bashid, who had received from the Turks as nrice of bi« iloiofo 1 • “A projected attack on Basrah ten thousand rifles and ten thousand pounds Urt to dissuade Bin Bashid from this enterprise in reality. P C Si to ■The Sheriff was much incensed by news of hanging in Homs Hama by the Turks of fifteen leading Arabs as also by * * * * of well-known Wahhabi Sheikh to proclaiming him an infidel. The Turks have summoned his third son Faisal to assist them in Syria and was to leave with twenty thousand men on the express condition of free access to all Arab Chiefs in Syria by Medina where arms were awaiting him. The messenger was instructed by Faisal to assure High Commissioner that of fighting for the Turks they had no intention. The Turks might even send him to canal in which case their attack would be mere pretence, the one object of Arabs being to conclude with England an agreement: the Arabs in Syria were under a signed compact to follow him. It is stated by the messenger, who is of some consequence in Hedjaz, that the result of the negotiations with England is anxiously awaited by the Arabs. Sheikh of Eategh, in particular, was most friendly and with many other Chiefs is only waiting for some such guarantees to fall on Turks. Correspondence is passing between Imamin Yehhia and the Sheriff, as the Sheriff wishes to dis suade him from aiding the Turk. When asked by messenger why he would not show his hand he himself replied that so long as he had no definite treaty with England he had to reckon with possibility of the Allies making peace with the Turks, and he would then find himself at latter’s mercy. The merchants of Jeddah instigated by Turks have, my Agent, who accompanied carpet, reports, sent to the Porte a petition against Sheriff that all troops clothing had been transferred to Mecca Taif and that Sheriff was in considerable danger (from Turkish Government?). 5 2089 No. g090-W., dated Simla, the 27th October 1915. 2091 Endorsed by Foreign and Political Department. the Arm y Departmen t A copy of the undermentioned telegrams is forwarded to the Home Department the General Officer ~ I ZT ? f° r information. Commanding, Force “ D ” From the High Commissioner of Egypt, dated the 22nd October 19 L5. From His Majesty^s Secretary of State for India, dated the 22nd October 19lo. From the High Commissioner of Egypt, dated the 22nd October 1915. From the High Commissioner of Egypt, dated the 22nd October 1915. 6 Telegram P., dated the 26th (received 27th) October 1915. From—The High Commissioner, Egypt, Cairo, To—His Excellency the Viceroy (Foreign and Political Department), Simla. The following telegram 644, dated 26th October, was sent to the Foreign Office:— Begins.—Szoxst . Reference your telegram No. 796.* Having regard to * Serial No 3 ur g eiic y matter I took suitable advantage of opportunity which presented itself to-day to send reply to the Sheriff of Mecca. Letter, full text of which leaves by bag to-day, is to following effect. After referring to last letter received from Sheriff, I stated that districts of Alexandretta and Mersina and portions of Syria to the west of districts of Hama, Damascus, Aleppo and Homs should be excluded from area which is proposed by him as they cannot be regarded as purely Arab. I also stated that we accept those boundaries (without prejudice to existing engagements with Arab Chiefs and with above modification) and as regardsjm — r ~*— territories therein, in which His Majesty’s Government are free to act without detriment to interest of French Government, I gave assurances as detai ed His Maiesty’s Government will (1) recognise and support independence of Arabs within above limits, (2) she will guarantee Holy Places against a qg r s ' sions, (3) will give advice to, and assist Arabs m establishment of most G form of Government when the proper time is at hand, it being understood that desire of Arabs is that officials and advisers required should be Bntis^ . On their part Arabs will recognise that interest and position of His Majesty’s Government call for special measures m Yilayats of Baghdad and Basrah of advanced administrative control. I then expressed hope that this declaration will remove all possible doubt that may exist as to sympathy of His Majesty’s Government towards Arab aspirations and lead to firm and abiding alliance, immediate result of which will be to expel Turks from Arab countries. It is now my intention to communicate above terms to Foroki Aziz El Nasri in definite shape and facilitate their commencement of piopaganda. Later on I will report how Arabs propose to act. Since recent reports show that Sheriff’s life is in some danger, the greatest possible secrecy is being observed regarding our direct correspondence with him. This does not of course affect communication to other Arab leaders of terms which we are offering. This telegram is addressed to Foreign Office and sent to Government of India, to whom I am sending Arabic and English version of Mecca letter by next bag. Telegram P., dated (and received) the 28th October 1915. Prom—Lieutenant-Colonel Sir H. McMaiion, G.C.Y.O., K.C.I.E., C.S.I., High Commissioner of Egypt, Cairo, To--His Excellency the Viceroy (Foreign and Political Department), Simla. Please see my telegram* of 26th instant. Mail bag leaves to-day by P. and O. mail steamer in Captain’s charge. 8 Telegram P., No. S.-1013, dated the 30th October 1915. From—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, Simla, To—The Secretary to the Government of Bombay, Political Department, Bombay. Sir H.'McMahon is despatching mail bag to Government of India per P« and O, steamer which left Suez on the 28th October in charge of the Commander. On arrival will you kindly take delivery of bag and forward it to this Department at Delhi. 9 Telegram No. 7662-W., dated the 1st November 1915. From—The Secretary to the Government of Bombay, Political Department, Bombay, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Department, Delhi. Foreign and Political Sealed bag from Egypt addressed Secretary, Foreign Department, Simla, and signed on label by Sir Henry McMahon, arrived on mail steamer yesterday. Post Office refused accept delivery but are now holding at request of Bombay Government. Please wire instructions. a «Telegram P., No. 10-D. S v dated tlie dtp November 1915. From—His Excellency tbe Viceroy (Foreign and Political Department), Delhi, To—His Majesty’s Secretary of State for India, London. Arabia. Kindly refer to your telegram* dated the 22nd October and tbe * Serial No. 2 . * telegramf to the Foreign Office, from High t Serial No. 6. Commissioner, Egypt, No, 644, dated the 26th October. The Government of India fully realise and with regret that as reported by you, you were prevented by circumstances from consulting us in connection with the overtures to the Arabs particularly in mew of the discretion allowed to High Commissioner of Egypt with regard to our special interests in the area actually in our occupation and the Baghdad province. This discretion we consider has been exercised without due regard to the interests of India, by the inclusion of the provinces of Basrah and Baghdad in the proposed independent Arab State, “ only special measures of advanced administrative control ” in these two Vilayats being reserved to the Government of India or His Majesty’s Government, We should not, we think, have been committed to a policy of tbis nature and before a pledge of such vital importance to the future of India was given we should have been consulted. The creation of a strong Arab State lying astride our interests in the Gulf and in the East has always been regarded by us with much diffidence as a not unlikely source of trouble ultimately and we entertain doubts in regard to any political or military advantages likely to accrue in this manner. If His Ma jesty’s Government are satisfied that the termination of the war is likely to be hastened by an Arab alliance, we do not on general grounds wish to oppose it, although we object to the conditions on which it is proposed that it should be based in respect of Mesopotamia. Some form of native administration in Baghdad Vilayat under our close political control and the eventual annexation of Basrah Vilayat have always been contemplated by us as a minimum. Annexation is apparently put out of the question by Sir H. McMahon’s guarantee. By the surrender to an Arab Govern ment of any kind of the Basrah Vilayat not only shall we be preparing trouble for ourselves at the head and along the southern littoral of the Gulf, but we shall be giving up the main fruits of our hard-won vic tories in Mesopotamia. Such a course will not only mean abandonment of .enormous potential sources of revenue, but will also be resented by the European Commercial Community and the Indian people who look to Mesopotamia as a field for emigration and commercial expansion in return for the blood of their countrymen shed there. We sincerely trust that formula may be so amended as to admit of His Majesty’s Govern ment having free hand eventually in the disposal of Baghdad and Basrali Vilayats which have been won at such cost. We hesitate to recommend the publication if any proclamation on the lines suggested by Sir McMahon in his private telegram to the Foreign Office of 1st instant pending orders. Bepeated High Commissioner, Egypt, and addressed Secretary of State lor India. 11 No. H.-8910, dated Delhi, the 3rd November 1915. Endorsed by Army Department. A copy of the undermentioned paper is forwurded to the Foreign and Political Department. Telegram No. 209!-E., dated the 31st October 1915, from the General Officer Command ing, Egypt, to the Commander-in-Chief in India.Enclosure to Serial No, 11, Telegram P.^ No. 209'1 , -E. J dated the 31st October 191o. Prom—The General Officer Commanding, Egypt, Cairo, To—The Commander-in-Chief in India, Delhi. A copy of telegram No. 827* (dated October 27th ?) from Foreign Office, , AT to the Viceroy, repeated to High Commis- sioner, Egypt, has been seen by me. In my opinion we should seize this excellent opportunity of issuing a pro clamation giving verbatim text of our proposals to the Sheriff of Mecca and Arab party; so far as Iraq and Mesopotamia are affected thereby. The High Com missioner, Egypt, has already sent the gist of these proposals to the Viceroy, This is an opportunity of honestly and properly letting our intentions be known, and it would convince the Sheriff that we are sincere, and would also do an infinite amount of good. Suspicion would be aroused if we did anything short of this, and Arabs are peculiarly suspicious, I am told by leaders of Arab party here that a certain Lieutenant Mowlood Mukhlis is a man of influence among the Arab party and would be useful for spreading our policy among Arabs, He is a Cavalry Officer from Musal and with 3 others, is reported to have deserted from the Turks 3 or 1 months a^o. 12 Telegram ?., dated (and received) the 4th November 1915 From—His Majesty's British High Commissioner of Egypt, Cairo, To—His Excellency the Viceroy (Foreign and Political Department), Delhi. Please see last paragraph of my telegramf to Foreign Office No. B44-Secret. t Serial No. 6. To-iay we are sending you Arabic text of letter to Sheriff of Mecca by bag. 13 Telegram P., dated the 5th (received 6th) November 1915, From The High Commissioner of Egypt, To—His Excellency the Viceroy (Foreign and Political Department). Secret. I have sent following as No. 674, dated 5th November, to Foreign t Semi xo. 10 . Office:— Begins, Please see Viceroy of “sheriff- tirfcd S mf h “ reStrfcted lati ^ewhreFn a :tu a ;^rXtua? regard^ to'^Vilayats^of^Baghdad^and* 1 !!^ 68 ?^ 111 ^ t 38 . follows established position and interests of G^eaT^ t 6 - ArabS V* recognise that sures of administrative control L„ ? . ® lltam “ e &lt;=essitate special mea- ‘ administrative ’ in Imha’s^telefframVif r' ^ before word those territories from foreign aesressio-n • to ull( ers * oo l J 111 order to secure populations and to safeguard' our^mutuaUconoSntere^-- Welfare ° f ^ definitelMonX.'adn ,!^ ° f ^ and as well as development and commercial nmi’' 1 ''* r' • I ? ternal administration as regards military measures maustnal enterprise and also in those' “n ^onruVtiou^ith and control representatives here interpreted it in that sense. P dlnS clause an(1 Arab7 ii i ^ i . . , ° . 7 lcuuih «,» lu clVUill ail danger ot alarming Arab suspicions by divergent statements. To-day I received copy of a later letter just received from Sheriff by El Murgham of Soudan in which former urges supreme importance of immediate assurances by us of intentions specially in regard to frontiers as previously denned by him, to which be says Arabs are attaching very great weight. Of critical situation of Arabia and of great nanger of Arabs being committed by lurkish pressure and German promises to a real jehad against us he warns Ibis indicates urgency of situation under which I issued my recent statement. Ends. Telegram P., dated London, the 8th (received 9th) November 1915. From—His Majesty's Secretary of State for India, r i'° hh® Excellency the Viceroy (Foreign and Political Department). I agree with views expressed in your telegram of November 4th^ on November 5th. Assurances, if given, will be conditional on Arabs performing their part of bargain, This constitutes additional reason against proclaiming them as McMahon proposed to do. It would perhaps be better in these circumstances if Nixon issued no proclamation at all on occupation of Baghdad. If, however, one is thought necessary for local or Indian purposes, please, as soon as possible, let me have draft. It should not refer to the wider political issues which McMahon has raised. With reference to my telegram f No. 644-Secret, of October 26th, + Serial Nn 6 addressed to the Foreign Office and repeated to Your Excellency, I have the honour to forward herewith copy of a despatch which I addressed to Sir Edward Grey (No, 131-Secret) on the 26th instant, enclosing copy of my reply to the Sheriff of Mecca’s letter to me, dated September 9th. I need hardly point out the necessity for keeping all our negotiations with the Sheriff most secret. . ’ ^^ vymcc. x icasc ict me know at once if you have anything to say on McMahon’s telegramf of * Serial No. 10. f Serial No. 13. subject of Arabia and am pressing your views on Foreign Office. Please let 15 Secret. Sie, Cairo; October 28th, 1915. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your Excellency’s most obedient humble servant, His Excellency, The Bight Honourable Lord Hardinge of Penshurst, P.C., G.C.B,, G.C.S.I., etc., etc., A. HENBY McMAHON. Viceroy and Governor General of India,Enclosure 1 to Serial No. 15. The Residency, Cairo, ,J ' October 26th, 1915. No. 131 Secret, Sir, With reference to my secret telegram No. 614 of to-day’s date, I have the honour to enclose herewith the English text of the reply which X have despatched in Arabic to the Sheriff of Mecca. The matter appeared to me to admit of no delay, and I have therefore lost no time in answering the Sheriff’s letter, and have availed myself of the authority to act without further reference, accorded to me in your telegram* No, 796 of the 20th instant. *Seml No. 3. The composition of a reply which would he acceptable to the Arab party and which would at the same time leave as free a hand as possible to His Majesty’s Government in the future has been a difficult task, I have been definite in stating that Great Britain will recognize the principle of Arab independence in purely Arab territory, this being the main point on w hich agreement depends, but have been equally definite in exclud ing Mersina, Alexandretta and those districts on the northern coast cf Syria, winch cannot be said to be Arab, and where, I understand, that French interests have been recognized, I am not awnre of the extent of French claims in Syria, nor of how far His Majesty’s Government have agreed to recognize them. Hence, wRile recognizing the towms of Damascus, Hama, Homs and Aleppo as being within the circle of Arab countries, I have endeavoured to provide for possible French pretensions to those places by a general modification to the effect that His Majesty’s Govern ment can only give assurances in regard to those territories “in w T hieh she can act without detriment to the interests of her Ally, France.” It will be observed that I have definitely specified France as the only Ally concerned. The use of the term “ Allies ” would. I understand, inevit ably have aroused the suspicion of the Arabs, who wmild have conjured up visions of all our Allies putting forward claims in various parts of the Arab territories, I believe I am right in the supposition that no territorial interests have ever been even tentatively claimed, either by Russia in Northern Mesopotamia or by Italy on the Arabian coasts of the Red Sea, and that it is therefore unnecessary, and indeed inadvisable, to provide for any such interests. I venture to emphasize the fact that the eventual arrangement would be very greatly facilitated if France would consent to forego any territorial claims she may have to purely Arab territories, such as Damascus, Hama, Homs and Aleppo. The inclusion of such districts in Arabia will be insisted on by the Arabs, and although they might possibly agree in regard to them to accept from France a similar arrangement to that which w T e are proposing elsewhere, it is obvious that this will give rise to trouble, and that much more satisfac tory and lasting results will be possible in the future if the Arab question can be dealt with as a whole by Great Britain. In face of the vital importance to the allied cause of the present issues involved, France could hardly be unreasonable on this point and the question of compensation elsewEere if necessary is well worthy of serious consideration. It is, I consider, not going too far to say that the only hope of preventing this question becoming eventually one of trouble and anxiety to all concerned is to leave it in the direction of one power alone. X would also once more lay stress on the religious importance attached to Damascus by Arabs, not only as one of the three points of departure of the Sacred Carpet, but as, in their eyes, one of the principal Holy Places.In conclusion, I am of opinion that while the terms I have proposed are the minimum that could he offered with any promise of success, there is reasonable hope of their being accepted by the Sheriff individually and the leaders of the Arab party. The letter was despatched yesterday in the hands of the Sheriff’s messenger, Mahmoud Arif Arayfar, who is in the complete confidence of the Sheriff and appears to be a man of considerable intelligence and of some influence. The opportunity was taken of verbally explaining the terms of the letter to facilitate its comprehension by the Sheriff, further verbal assurances of sympathv and support were also given and, in particular, care was taken to allay any apprehension which the Sheriff might entertain regarding the possibly sinister motives towards himself of our assistance to the Idrisi of Asir, in whom he is said not to place complete confidence. A copy of this despatch is being sent by this mail to India. I have the honour to be, with the highest respect, Sir, Your most obedient, humble servant, Eight Honourable Sir E, Grey, Bart,, K.G., M.P., etc,, etc,, etc, (Sd,) A. H, McMAHON. Enclosure 2 to Serial No. 15. To the Sheriff of Mecca. (with titles) I have received your letter of 19th Shaw r al with much pleasure and your expressions of friendliness and sincerity have given me the greatest satisfaction. I regret that you should have received from my last letter the impression that I regarded the question of the limits and boundaries with coldness and hesitation ; such was not the case, but it appeared to ine that the moment had not yet arrived when they could be most profitably discussed. I have realized, however, from your last letter that you regard this question as one of vital and urgent importance. I have, therefore, lost no time in informing the Government of Great Britain of the contents of your letter and it is with^great pleasure that I communicate to you on their behalf the following statement, which I am confident you will receive with satisfaction. The districts of Mersina and Alexandretta and portions of Syria lying to the west of the districts of Damascus, Hama, Homs and Aleppo cannot be said to be purely Arab, and should be excluded from the proposed limits and boundaries. With the above modification, and without prejudice to our existing trea ties with Arab Chiefs, we accept those limits and boundaries and, in regard to those portions of the territories therein in which Great Britain is free to act without detriment to the interests of her Ally, France, I am empowered m the name of the Government of Great Britain to give the following assurances and make the following reply to our letter: Subject to the above modifications, Great Britain is prepared to recognize and support the independence of the Arabs within the territories included m the limits and boundaries proposed by the Sheriff of Mecca. Great Britain will guarantee the Holy Places against all external aggres sion and will recognize their inviolability. When the situation admits, Great Britain will give to the Arabs her advice and will assist them to establish what may appear to be the most suitable forms of Government in those various territories.i ■ 10 On the other hand, it is understood that the Arabs have decided to seek the advice and guidance of Great Britain only, and that such European advisers and officials as may be required for the formation of a sound form of administration will be British. With regard to the Vilayats of Baghdad and Basrah, the Arabs will recognize that the established position and interests of Great Britain necessitate special measures of administrative control in or er to secure these territories from foreign aggression, to promote the welfare of the local populations and to safeguard our mutual economic interests. I am convinced that this declaration will assure you beyond all possible doubt of the sympathy of Great Britain towards the aspirations of her traditional friends the Arabs and will result in a firm and lasting alliance, the immediate results of which will be the expulsion of the Turks from the Arab countries and the freeing of the Arab peoples from the Turkish yoke which for so many years has pressed heavily upon them. I have confined myself in this letter to the more vital and important questions, and if there are any other matters dealt with in your letters which I have omitted to mention, we may discuss them at some convenient date in the future. . Ifc was wit h very great relief and satisfaction that I heard of the safe arrival of the Holy Carpet and the accompanying offerings which, thanks to the clearness ^ of your directions and the excellence of your arrangements, were landed without trouble or mishap in spite of the dangers and difficulties occasioned by the present sad war-May God soon bring a lasting peace and freedom to all peoples, lam sending this letter by the hand of your trusted and excellent messenger, Sheikn Mohammed Ibn Arif Arayfan, and he will inform vou of various matters of interest but of less vital importance, which I have not mentioned in this letter, • (Here follow the usual compliments.) 16 Telegram F., No. 32-D S., dated the 10th November 1915. From—His Excellency the Viceroy (Foreign and Political Department), Delhi To—His Majesty’s Secretary of State for India, London. Your telegram* of 8th November regarding Arabia. In McMahon’s tele- * Serial No. 14, gramf of 5th November we find nothino' t Serial No. 13 palliate in any way position he has although, without imperilling the ,T' faCt ‘; emains that other interests in Mersina, Alexandretta and Syria he yefTound Yt SaieSUard to guarantee to Arabs the rendition of tend fori in vr 1 ^ * Pessary Moslem leaders creation of an Arab State and administration the financing of lar^f ° £ f he lapse into a worse condition than even under TuitthTulfan^be g 6 n ke1y SX tt St StS Ve f H for the security of British interests in the^oii-fields re|“!s £r~ seet pean Qi of will itate 1 ories i to sible lier tlie irab .for ill I the !afe the ere ;ies d 3Et of lot 11 are siill ^in ^clafk frn in rC5 ^ Llrn for these s leeping assurances we a e. ail m claiK, but tiust it may be of sufficiently definite character to enable us to repudiate these assurances if Arabs fail to perform their part—at any rate as far as Mesopotamia is concerned. 1 i tt rG ? aS re S ards prcciamation that, in anew of chaotic position created by McMahon s assurances, it will be best if General Nixon issued no procla mation at all on occupation of Baghdad, except perhaps a formal notice calling ?if 0n P°P U atl0n to acquiesce quietly in our occupation and assuring them that their persons, property and religion will be scrupulously respected should they do so. In India, as soon as Baghdad is actually occupied, we propose to suppress the news ^ for day or two and to publish following procla mation His Majesty’s Government have authorised General JNixon to advance on Baghdad, his forces having once more defeated Turkish opposition on the Tigris in vicinity of Suliman Pak. Not only for military reasons is this advance necessary, but in order to relieve British ladies and British Indian subjects who, contrary to usage of civilised war, have been detained at Baghdad; and in order to break up a focus of Geiman intrigue in Middle Bast. His Majesty’s Government, however, desire that it should be clearly understood that stringent orders have been issued that every precaution should be taken to prevent sacred shrine of Shaikh Abdul Qadir, Gilani, and other tombs and shrines in vicinity from being in any way even accidentallv damaged in course of the operations, in accordance with their unswerving policy of respecting the sacred places of Islam and the susceptibilities of the Moslem community; and they wish it to be clearly understood that in regard to all other holy places in Mesopotamia, this policy has been and will be scru pulously followed, and that no obstacle whatever will he placed in way of Imams, Ulemas, Mujtahids and other religions persons following freely and as usual their ordinary religious practices, after occupation of Baghdad. Ends, 17 Telegram P., No. 33-D. S., dated the 10th November 1915. From—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, Delhi, To—The General Officer Commanding, Force &lt;f D,” Basrah. Beference correspondence forwarded with my endorsement 2091-WA of * Semi No 5 27 th October on subject of negotiations between High Commissioner, Egypt, and Sheriff of Mecca, Subsequent correspondence shows that High Commis sioner, Egypt, acting on discretion given him by London Eoreign Office, has included Basrah and Baghdad Vilayats in territories where His Majesty’s Government are prepared to recognise and support the independence of the Arabs. High Commissioner has modified this by following stipulation:— Begins. Arabs will recognise that established position and interest of Great Britain with regard to Vilayats of Baghdad and Basrah necessitate special measures of administrative control in order to safeguard our mutual economic interests to secure these territories from foreign aggression and to promote welfare of local populations. Ends, Against this surrender of Indian interests in Mesopotamia we have pro tested in strongest terms. Secretary of State agrees and is pressing our views on Eoreign Office, London. We have to-day again telegraphed further protest ; copies of correspondence have been sent by post to you. Secretary of State thinks, and we agree, that in view of chaotic position created by .McMahon’s assurances, it would he better for you to issue no proclamation at all on occupation of Baghdad, except perhaps formal notice calling upon civil population to acquiesce quietly in our occupation and assuring them that their persons, property and religion, should they do so, will be scrupulously respected ; but further instructions on this point will shortly be conveyed to you.12 18 No. 218 ^-w^ dated Delhi, the 13th November 1915. 2183-W. Endorsed by the foreign and Political Department. Army Department A copy of the undermentioned papers is forwarded to the ^ for information, (1) in continuation of the endorsement by the ing, Force “ D Foreign and Political Department, No. dated the 27th October 1915. *(2) in continuation of the telegram from the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, No. •To General Officer Commanding, Force “ D ” only g ^ dated the November 1915 . 2. It is requested that the papers forwarded he kindly treated as &lt;c Extremely Secret.” Telegram from the High Commissioner, Egypt, dated the 26th October 1915. Telegram from the High Commissioner, Egypt, dated the 28th October 1916. Telegram to His Majesty’s Secretary November 1915. fOmit to Army Department. ( ) To General Officer Commanding, Force ' D,” only. of State for India, No. 10-D. S., dated the 4th tEndorsement by the (Government of India in the) Army Department, No. H.-8910, dated the 3rd November 1915 (with enclosure). Telegram from the High Commissioner, Egypt, dated the 4th November 1915. Telegram from the High Commissioner, Egypt, dated the 5th November 1915. Telegram from His Majesty’s Secretary of State for India, dated the^th November 1915. Despatch from the High Commissioner, Egypt, dated the 28th October 191 o. Telegram to His Majesty’s Secretary of State for India, No. 32-D. S., dated the 10th November 1915. JTelegram to General Officer Commanding, J Omit to General Officer Commanding, Force “D.” IOrce &lt;f D, J ’ No. 33-D. S., dated the 10th Novem ber 1915. 19 Telegram P., No, 358, dated (and received) the 14th November 1915. From—Sir John Nixon, General Officer Commanding, Force “ D,” Basrah, Aziziyah, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Delhi. (Addressed Secretary of State for India, sent to India.) It appears from a communication§ received from the Government of § Serial No 17 . Iridia y esterd ay that, in the course of negotiations with Mecca the details (of) which I have not yet learnt, the High Commissioner, Egypt, has with certain modifications included Basrah and Baghdad Yilayats in territories wherein His Majesty’s Government are prepared to recognise the independence of Arabs and give it support. Apart from the fact that such a commitment appears to be nremature and will prejudice future of this great country and existing British interests at Basrah and Baghdad, it seems to me to involve complete misconception oc attitude of inhabitants of Yilayats affected. It moreover overlooks the important and fundamental fact that four-fifths of the population of Basrah and two-thirds of Baghdad Yilayats are Shiahs (?). I earnestly trust that before any final step is taken further consideration may be devoted to this subject and hope that reference may be made to me on issues affecting Mesopotanra, Cox agrees with these views here expressed.20 13 {Received with Office Memorandum No. 1993, dated Delhi, the 16th November 1915, from II. A. F. Metcalfe, Fsq., Assistant Frivate Secretary to the Viceroy.) {Secret.) The High Commissioner for Egypt presents his compliments to the Viceroy •and Goyernor General of India, and has the honour to transmit herewith the Arabic text* of the letter addressed by Sir Henry McMahon to the Sheriff of Mecca, the English copy of which was enclosed in his despatchf to the Foreign Office, No. 131-Secret, of 26th October 1915, copy ot which was forwarded by bag to His Excellency by last mail to India, IThe Residency, Cairo, 3rd Noyember 1915. * Xot printed. f Enclosure to Serial No. 15. 21 Telegram P., dated the 18th (received 19th) November 1915. Prom—His Majesty’s Secretary of State for India, London, To—His Excellency the Viceroy^(Foreign and Political Department), Delhi. Arab negotiations. Please see your telegram t of J Serial No. 16. § Vide Enclosure to Serial No. 15. 10th instant. Fol lowing from Cairo :— Begins. “ Messen ger has arrived with letter§ from Sheriff. Letter is long and requires careful trans lation to ascertain full meaning but fol lowing are main points. (A) He agrees to exclusion of Mersina and Minisandria •Spartan (?) Alexandretta. &lt;B) He maintains that Vilayats Alleppo and Beyrout are Arab and should be under Arab Mohamedan Government. (C) He maintains that Mesopotamia is Arab also, but as Great Britain has special interests there it may for the present be left out of discussion. Meanwhile he requests subsidy for what he terms “the Arab Kingdom.” (D) Fourthly, he expresses fear lest European peace should leave Arabs at mercy of Turks and wishes Great Britain to bind herself not to abandon Arabs. They will come in at once on these four conditions. Messenger states feeling amongst Arabs is very favourable tons. Sheriff impresses upon him readiness and intention of Arabs to begin work without delay. Abdulla, son of Sheriff, has returned from Nejd bringing several Chiefs whom he detached from Bin Rashid’s cause. Oppenheim having been expelled from Medina is said to have returned to Syria. Faisal, son of Sheriff, has left Mecca and is negotiating on behalf of his father with Arab Chiefs.” Fnds. Please repeat to Nixon paragraph regarding Mesopotamia, adding that we have communicated to McMahon sub- 11 Senai No. 19. stance of his telegram of 14th November, 358.H 21-A. MEMORANDUM. The papers specified in the margin were ’The Shebiee oe Mecca. Proposed issue of a proclamaiion giving the text •of proposals to the Sheriff of Mecca and the Arab party, so far as Iraq and Mesopotamia are affected thereby. Endorsement by the Government of India in the Army Department, No. H.-8UlO,T[ dated the 3rd November 1915 (with enclosure). V Serial No. 11. Telegram to the General Officer Commanding, Force “D,” No. 33-D, S ** dated the 10th November .1915. transmitted to the Secretary, Political Department, India Office, London, for the information of His Majesty’s Secretary of State for India, under* cover of the Foreign Secretary’s letter No. 59-M., ** Serial No. 17. dated the 19th November 191514 21-B. N°. . dated Delhi, the 19th November 1915. (Confidential) Endorsed by Foreign and Political Department. A copy of the undermentioned papers is forwarded confidentially to the Army l ■ apartment Home department, for information, in continuation of the endorsement by the 2181 Foreign and Political Department, No. 2182 -W., dated the 13th November # # 1915. Telegram from the General Officer Commanding, Force “ D/ J No. 358, dated the 14th November 1915. ***** 22 Telegram P., No. 68-D. S., dated the 20th November 1915. From—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, Delhi, To—The General Officer Commanding, Force “ D/’ Basrah. I have repeated to Sir Henry McMahon the substance of your telegram No, 358* of the 14th instant. The substance of a letterf now received from Sheriff of Mecca in Cairo has been telegraphed to us by Secretary of State. In it the former maintains that Mesopotamia is Arab, but as Great Britain has special interests there it may for the present be left out of the discus sion. * Serial No. 19. t Vide Serial No. 21. 23 Telegram P., dated the 19th (received 20th) November 1915. From—His Majesty's Secretary of State for India, To—His Excellency the Viceroy (Foreign and Political Department). Following telegram addressed to Aden is repeated to you :—Any positive evidence that you have to show that the Turks are being supported by the Grand Sheriff of Mecca should be telegraphed as soon as possible. 24 Telegram P., dated the 19th (received 20th) November 1915. From—His Majesty’s Secretary of State for India, To—His Excellency the Viceroy (Foreign and Political Department). Arabia. Please see my telegram $ of 18th November. Cairo telegraphs as X Serial No. 2 i. follows : Begins. Translation has now been done carefully and the general sense of tliG second licili of tJie letter^ wliicli is rntlier ynguely expressed, is ffiven more fully in the following :— Begins. Interest in Adana Mersina is renounced by Sheriff but retention of Beyrout, Aleppo Vilayats as purely Arab are insisted on by him. Iraq cannot be abandoned by him for trading economic reasons but he is prepared to “leave under British administration for a short time those districts now occupied by British troops against a suitable sum paid as compensation to Arab Kingdom for period of occupation ” without prejudice to rights of either party in order to facilitate agreement and in consideration of guarantee offered by His Majesty’s Government. Actual agreement with15 adverse*oninfon^^Mnfl'pm^ 8 f° i ® m .®® iate acti ®. Sheriff hesitates for fear of left to T^e ^to^ Government ^ ^ ^ MajeSty ’ S . , His Majesty’s Government having disclaimed all intention of internal o^hcia^s^^tSheriff 6 ^ 8 1 ?| e ^^ on ^® question of British administrative SWiflM i S ,n must behove alluding to Arabia only unless purposely vague.) Sheriff is forced by Arabs to his (? present) course of action, though he would prefer seclusion from all politics for himself. End of telegram. 25 Telegram P., No. 71-D. S., dated the 21st November 1915. From—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, Delhi, To—The General Officer Commanding, Force “ D/’ Basrah. Reference my telegram of the 20th instant, No. 68-D. S. Secretary of State telegraphs on 19th instant, that McMahon reports translation done carefully giving general sense of portion of letter from Sheriff or Mecca, which, though rather vaguely expressed, is as follows :— Beqins. Interest m * * * u ^ * * politics for himself. JEnds. 26 Telegram P., No. 145-A. P., dated the 20th (received 21st) November 1915, From The Resident and General Officer Commanding at Aden, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Delhi. Documentary evidence* exists shewing that Sheriff of Mecca has assisted * vide Serial No. 23 . Turks in the form of a letter from Ahmad Tewfik (Commander of 7th Yemen Army Corps at Sanaa)^ to Hassan Izzat Bey Bimbashi, Commanding 1st Battalion, 115th Regiment, at Loheiya, found on latter when captured en route to Jeddah by sea. The letter tells Hassan Izzat distinctly that the Sheriff had received and held in charge money intended for Ahmad Tewfik’s command and also that Sheriff would arrange for safe transmission to destina tions in Asir and Yemen of money and that Hassan Izzat was to act as the Sheriff directed. General Officer Commanding, Egypt, has the originals of the correspond ence. Repeated to Foreign Department of the Government of India, addressed to Secretary of State.u-o6$~ : S ) (e£lj ( e—* ^ 1 In Any further communica- tion on this subject, please quote No. ffdOYlf /191 i? and address— The Under-Secretary of State y Foreis^n Office, g/yf s* ^ 1 London. ^ 'Jr • The Under-Sec ret ary oj State for Foreign A fairs presents his compliments to the Under-Secretary of State for and., by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop ^^7 of the under-mentioned, papers. Foreign Office, 191 &amp;. r V yNO 161 sir With reference to your despatch Ho 231 of the 2nd ultimo, in which are set forth the Agha Khan's apprehensions at the creation of fin Arab Khalifate , I have the honour to observe that the policy of His Majesty's Government , to the effect that the Khal- ifate is a question which concerns exclusively the Islamic world, and is not a matter in which we have any intention of interfering, has been consistently followed by this Residency; nor do I think it prob* able or even possible that Arabs In the tiudan or Kgypt ( who take much less interest in the matter than is generally supposed ) con have received encouragement from local officials in connection with an Arab Khal- ifate . A copy of your despatch was fovwarded to Sir Reginald 'iingate , and his remarks upon it are as follows J« * The opinions expressed to the Secretary of dtate for Foreign Affairs by the Agha Khan seem to me to be much as were to be expected from the Head of the Ismailia beet, who would be opposed, oh principle, to the establishment of a Hunnite Arabian Khalifate an well as the inclusion of the districts contain ing the Shiite Shrines within its territories. In what degree Arab racial ambitions and affinities can be expected to over-ride Sectarian differences The Right “onourable .A V Grey K.n., .4 .,differences and to overcome predilections of the tihlitee Inhabitants of these districts to Persian m opposed to Sunnite Arab control , I am unable to st'. te ; but such information on the subject as l possess inclines me totthe belief that the ideas of a horaoeretteoua Arab State and the realisation of Pan-Arab aspirations , would receive considerable support in those regions . y personal acquaintance with the Agha Khan is slight , but it is a subject to me for speculation how tar a Westernised I'oslera of his type or even an advanced thinker such as ;?yed Ameer AH a &gt;e .able trujy to reflect the attitude of the btlk of their nominal co-religionists in Matters of religious sentiment . In any case I venture to hasard the opinion that neither of these individuals la in a posttita to rep resent the views of the .'Sunnite population of India on the question of the Khalifate . I may add that in all conversations with audan Notables whose sympathies are practically entire ly pro-Arab , I have been careful to explain that any support by His Majesty's Government to the cause of Arabian Independence was directed to assist the Arabs to secure their national aspirations and bore no ref erence to the Khalifate, or other religious question, with which , as a purely Islamic affair His Majesty's Government have no concern I am in complete accord with the above ,views arid would only add that, with regard to the opinion of the Agtaa Khan that the Arabs have no claim to Bagdad and that that region and the Shrine of Kerbela ought more properly to be given to Persia , 1 believe thatthat the Shiite Shrine and district in Mesopotamia is likely always to prove an incongruous element in any administration. The inhabitants are Arab Shiites ; - as Arabs they dislike the Persians no less than the Turks; as Shiites they would dis like a Bunnite Government; and, as Muslims of a fanatical type they would not welcome a supreme Christian control. They are moreover themselves divided into violent factions, so that effective foreign protection and control such as Persia can never provide would appear to be essential to order in their region . At the same time they need not be taken too seriously, as may be seen from the passive manner in which they accepted and apparently have forgotten the looting ofnthelr Shrine by Turkish troops last winter. In saying that the Arabs have no claim to Bagdad, the Agha Khan would appear to vitiate his title to speak with authority on this subject; as &amp; the statement indicates astonishing ignorance of the history past and present of both the Arabs and Bagdad . X have the honour to be with the highest respect Your most obedient humble servantSir, In continuation of ray despatch No.161 of the 5th instant, relative to the interview between Sir Maurice de Bunsen and the Agha Khan, I have the honour to transmit herewith copy of a despatch which I have received from Sir R Wingate enclosing the telegram, text of which forms a part of my above-mentioned despatch. I have the honour to be, with the highest respect. Sir, your most obedient, humble servant. (Signed) A. H. M® MAH' The Right Honourable Sir E Grey Bart. K.G. M.P. etc., etc., etc.Enclosure In Sir H McMion’s despatch No.165 of Dee.Yth, 1915. Copy of Sir R Wingate’s despatch of December 1st. Sir, I have the honour to acknowledge receipt of a copy of the Foreign Of Ice letter of Nov.2nd, recording an interview between Sir &lt;1 de Bunsen and the Agha Khan. In my telegram of Nov.23rd, of v/hich i enclose copy, I have already given a personal opinion as to the significance of the views expressed by the Agha Khan. I am aware of the close connection in Arabia and other Moslem minds between the cause of /-.rabian independence and the institution of an Arab Khalifa; but I feel strongly that to withhold British support of the former in deference to the susceptibilities of certain sections of Moslem opinion with regard to the latter, would be detrimental not only to our immed late interests but to our prestige and, reputation amongst Moslems generally. At the same time I am in complete agree ment regarding the necessity to show that in support ing the Arabs we are moved solely by the desire to assist them to secure their national aspirations, without r n ference or prejudice to their religious pretensions ih the matter of the Khalifate. I have etc. (signedJ Reginald WingateIn any further communica tion on this subject, please quote No, ICfi223 /I9I5 and address— The Under-Secretary of State Foreign Office, London. \ v A' ry 16 The Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the b+J 1 * ^ iJKdCA and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, Jtr $1'° &gt; I 9 I 5 Reference to previous correspondence: Letter Foreign Office : from * Description of Inclosure. Name and Date. Subject. j1uUrvUhF+^ fkc.Si'f i Similar letter sent to1 * n i 9 lb At the meeting held at the Foreign Office on the 21st December with M. Picot of the French Embassy, the following points regarding the future French sphere in the proposed Arab State were discussed, and are to be submitted to the French Government by M. Picot:- FRENCH TERRITORY, OR DIRECT ADMINISTRATION. 1.- Southern limit, approximately TARTOUS-KILLIS-BIREDJIK-JEZIREH. Eastward of this to be arranged with RUSSIA. t 2w- Arab State, to include all lands to the South of this line with the following provisions (a) Arab State to be divided between England and France in£o spheres of commercial and administrative in terest, the actual line of demarcation to be reserved, but it was agreed that it should pivot on DEIR EL ZOR Eastward and Westward. (b) That the LEBANON should in so far as is practi cable retain its present constitution, but that it should comprise BEYRUT and the ANT I-LEBANON, and that the Go vernor should be nominated by the French Government. (c) (c) That the coast as far South as BEYRUT should be policed and protected by France. (d) JERUSALEM to form anjzf enclave, its boundaries yet to be defined. The following points were reserved (1) The allocation of the MOSUL Vilayet. (2) The position of HAIFA and ACRE as Cutlets for Great Britain on Mediterranean from Mesopotamia. December 21st, 1915. V:; (, ' . Miai rAHom-.i ■ ©Ojllio £ ■ ■ ' : ' ; ' ; '' : ' r ' ' ):iJ ' '■ 9 icf t a.Bcfr,.1' xlon©t f i lo. cfcoi^ I ; vX' ,; r i'90 r m90S('. jai:.. n;i aioagg xiona'i'i eiuXul sri-X gniiyxsigs' .s^.iioc a^i^ollcl ^ N . 9C( C j 910 Jii- { bOQBUOBLb 019W 9^8 CfBlA &amp;930Q01C Silt ~: foot^l .H v;cf J’nsr^ievoD rlonsTi oxIj c-t De J'Jixncfua :TAf r T8I-!i::riA TOaril HO t Yff.OOI'HraT ’ID 1 ' 1F V: Esef.BrriixoiqqB t cfimil niorf^foa -.1 ' . HS HISML -&gt;I 1 LQor IH - iIJ J10 - Cl JOT' : lA : am xlJ-^w £)9 ^xibiib 3cx ccr aiiU lo .biawjaea rl^uoa eriJ* cj aMAI IIb cdr 1 9 -:aaoi: 9 ivoiq grstmlL&amp;t Qd$ nJ*iw ©nil aixlJ’ lo ; ') ' .J,vi:I) ad oi alBCTB d'BiA (a) -nl Qvidve/rlBinifJae br.-. * laloieorixpo lo a9 19443 ooni ooriBil 9cf cl noilaoTBiaa;) lo snil I.bi loa 3.J ,139131 no loviq blnoua li lanl no 31,^5 anw o'i lucf , Dovisaai .bnawlaoC; nan biBwlaoS HOS 43 HISQ -i U ■ .. 5134 941 ladT (cf) Muoila 11 1 b 41 Ind .nollnlilanoo inoaoiq all nlalai alcfno ~o . 1 . t -I ■ &gt;na PUHYaa eaite-oo • IfieffifTiavot) 4Dn3i r x nil ; v :f. Is Inn imon 34 blnorla imisv 94 Mnona TUFYSR an rflirc0 ml an lanoo 941 1 b4T ( 0 ) ( 0 ) « soibiO 41 Dsloslciq bnn bsolloq aslmixmol all , aval on 9 \h.b mol cl mnJ^cURML (b) *4snll9Jb 94 cl 191 -: nsvieaai bio • alriloq :,;:iwolIol 04 :: •lovoliv JU80M 341 lo nollBOolIe 94T (I) 10 I alslliro an 3H0A onn A3IA.I lo nolllaoq s4T (8) .almBloqoasM nioii nasBans 11 ibsM no nlalliS lasiO 1 .From Viceroy, 22nd December 1915. Foreign Secret. Bin Sand. Political Agent, Bahrein, reports certain information given him by Bin Sand's doctor, Abdul Ahmai, whom he con siders to be genuine and who professes to be very stongly anti-Turk, lie is an Arab of Mosul, was educated at Constantinople and Beyrout and has visited Paris. According to doctor’s account, in an abortive night attack on Bin Rashid, in the course of which, Bin Sand's brother was killed, Bin Sand himself w r as severely wounded, and again in the next light he was slightly wounded. All Nejd firmly agrees that strongest efforts to create a diversion in Arabia are being made by Turks, and there is much coming and going between Sheriff of Mecca and Bin Rashid. Attack on Egypt is expected to take place shortly. Doctor farther states negotiations between Bin Kashid and other chiefs and Sheriff of Mecca are being presided over by Turks, that 40,000 camels are being purchased by Turks for an attack on Egypt, and that Ma’an railway has been completed.'B3^ c; iat / * C: L(&lt; ( KJffiOO ,0*j9V (3) lilO? i eaeg#**'** 91 From General, Force “ D,” Basra, 20th December 1915. (Addressed to General OfflaerCommanding, Egypt, repeated to Chief General Staff and Secretary of State India.) No I G 1802 19th December, 6 a.m. In continuation of my LG. 1759, following extract from memorandum 66 0., dated 4th December 1915, from Political Argent, Bahrein, to Political Resident, Basra, is repeated for information. “ Binsaud’s doctor, whose information has been telegraphed to von informs me Binsaud was somewhat severely wounded in abortive night attack in which his brother was killed, and again slightly wounded in next light He tells me it is firmly believed all through Najd that lurks are inakino- strenuous efforts to create a diversion in Arabia and that there is much coming and going between Binrashid and Shariff of Mecca. Also, it &gt;s expected that attack on Egypt will soon take place, the doctor, Abdullahsai, an Arab of Mosul, who was educated at Beyront and Constantinople, and has visited Paris, professes to be very strongly anti-Turk. 1 think he is genuine.n P 4259 From Secretary of State to Viceroy, Foreign Department, 22nd November 1915. Foreign Secret. Your telegram dated 16tli November. Sykes’ telegram of d3rd October goes by next mail. Substance is that scheme A of inter departmental committee alone guarantees security in Gulf and Mesopotamia, that an autonomous state in Irak is impracticable, and that as regards .Arabian peninsula our policy should be to protect it as a whole from without, leaving internal affairs alone.17 MEMORANDUM. The undermentioned papers were transmitted to the Secretary, Political Department, India Office, London, for the information of His Majesty’s Secretary of State for India, under cover of the Eoreign Secretary’s letter No. 53-M, dated the 29th October 1915. Telegram from the General Officer Commanding, Indian Expeditionary Force “D, No. 1894-1. G., dated the 14th October 1915. Telegram to the General Officer Commanding, Indian Expeditionary Force “D,” No. S.-1076, dated the 24th October 1915. 18 Telegram P., dated the 27th (received 28th) October 19 J 5. p rorn —His Majesty’s Secretary of State for India, London, To Hi s Excellency the Viceroy (Foreign and Political Department), Simla. It is desired by His Majesty’s Government that General Nixon should, on the occupation of Baghdad, issue a proclamation on similar lines to the communique which Cox suggests in his * Serial No. 3. telegram* to the Government of India, 2073-B., of 19th ultimo. The goodwill of Great Britain towards the Arabs and sympathy for their aspirations to form autonomous state independent of Turkey should be put foremost in the proclamation. I am inclined to omit any reference to the future status of Baghdad Vilayat, but to give assurances of scrupulous respect for Holy Places of Shiahs and Sunnis, and Moslem religion. Please kindly wire the draft of the proclamation you propose to Issue and repeat it to Sir H. McMahon with the least possible delay. 19 No. H.-8809, dated Simla, the 2Sth October 1915. Endorsed by the Army Department. A copy of the undermentioned papers is forwarded, in contmuation of Army Department memorandum No. H.-8795, dated the 27th October 1915, to the Foreign and Political Department. Telegram No. 129-222-1, dated the 25th October 1915, from the General Officer Commanding, Force “D,” to the Chief of the General Staff. ^ . c , ,, r , Telegram No. S-25374, dated the 26th October^ 1915, from the Chief of the General Staff, to the General Officer Commanding, Force “D.' ; : ? 2 ived on SO Ofcv i 5 j INDIA FOREIGN SECRETARY’S ? 01Enclosure 1 to Serial No, 19, Telegram P., No. 129-222—1., dated the 25th October 1915. From—The General Officer Commanding, Force “D,' Knt, To—The Chief of the General Staff. Eollowing addressed to Chief General Staff and repeated Secretary of State, 12th Division, and Inspector General of Communications, No change in situation. Enclosure 2 to Serial No. 19. Telegram No. S.-25374, dated the 26th October 1915. From—The Chief of the General Staff, To—The General Officer Commanding, Force “ D,” Kut-al-Amarah. With regard to procedure of addressing political telegrams, Government of India have ruled that all political telegrams, other than those of merely routine nature, which bear on matters coming within area of military operations should he addressed to you, and this will be done in future. In cases where India Office repeat to Cox their telegrams addressed to Government of India, he has been instructed to arrange for their immediate communication to you. You will of course hear in mind the great importance of ensuring that copies of all political telegrams received by you are sent to Cox direct without delay, and of receiving his advice before any action is taken. 20 Telegram P., No. 5-D. S., dated the 3rd November 1915. From—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, Delhi, To—The General Officer Commanding, Force “ D/ } Basrah. Please refer to my telegram No. 107C-S., dated the 2Ith October. On the 27th October Secretary of State for India telegraphed as follows :—“ It is desired by His Majesty’s ****** ****** and Moslem religion. ” The draft of the proclamation it is proposed to issue is as follows :—“ The Turkish ai^lSes have been driven from the field and the British flag flies over Baghdad. This occupation has resulted from the intrigues of Germany by whom Turkey was induced without just cause to draw the sword against Great Britain. Great Britain has retaliated by invading the soil of Turkey in order to break up a centre of German intrigue and to hasten the day of peace. “ The present campaign in Mesopotamia is however directed solely against the Turkish Government and the Turkish army. Towards the Arab population the British nourish feelings of warm friendship and goodwill, and they enter tain a deep sympathy with the aspirations of the Arabs to detach themselves from Turkish dominion, to found an Arab State under independent Arab rule under which the Arab race will renew its past glories and will rise again as a great and prosperous nation, controlling Arabia. The Arabs may confidently rely on the benevolent assistance of Great Britain in order that this object may be achieved. With the help of Great Britain the foundations of this great Arab State shall be laid down and the natural aspirations of the Arab race will thus at length be realised. “ Muhammadans 1 Our name as a sure friend of your religion is too firmly established for lying tongues to injure it. The sympathy which Great Britain extends to Muhammadans is known to all the world. Thus though at war with Turkey, Great Britain has allowed thousands of Mu hammadan pilgrims from India and from British possessions in the Ear East to visit Mecca for the pilgrimage, and though the port of Jeddah was under the Turkish flag she has despatched ships full of grain and supplies in order that the innocent residents of the Holy Placesshould not suffer distress and want and this notwithstanding the fact that this privilege was abused by the Turkish military authorities in the hopes of gaining some slight military advantage. “ Similarly, here in Iraq Great Britain will in no way interfere with the religious life of the people and of their leaders nor with the Holy Places, but will in virtue of her power on sea and land enable pilgrims from distant parts to make the pilgrimage to the shrines of Kerbela, Najaf and Baghdad. “ So long therefore as the inhabitants of the occupied territories conduct themselves in a friendly manner towards us they will have nothing to fear at our hands, but on the contrary will receive friendly and considerate treatment such as the people of Basrah are now experiencing. “ Refuse therefore steadfastly to be misled by lies prompted by Turkish and German agents .realise that the hour of destiny for the A-rab race has now come and that the hopes of the Arabs depend upon the co-operation and support of the British Government. Avail yourselves therefore of this unique opportunity. r&lt;( Let all the Muhammadans of Iraq abide firmly in an attitude of neutrality from which no harms can come to them and which will prove the foundation of peace and prosperity,” Please let me know if you have any modifications to suggest and whether you agree to its issue. 21 No, 2158-W., dated Delhi, the 8th November 1915. Endorsed Joy the Foreign and Political Department. A copy of the undermentioned papers is forwarded to the Army Depart ment for information with reference to the endorsement by the Foreign and Political Department, No. 2094-W., dated the 2Sth October 1915. Telegram from His Majesty^s Secretary of State for India, dated the 27th October 1915. Telegram to the General Officer Commanding, Force “ D, ” Basrah, No. 5-D. S., dated the 3rd November 1915. 22 Telegram P., No. I. Gc—1603, dated (and received) the 9th November 1915. From—The General Officer Commanding, Force “ D,” Basrah, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Delhi. Dth, No. 586. In his No. 16* of October 23rd to Director of Military Operations, War Office, my views and * Not received. Cox’s were communicated by Sir Mark Sykes, to be placed before Prime Minister, Sub-Committee. I request reference to be made thereto. As stated therein the formation of an autonomous state in Iraq appears to he unnecessary arid impossible. There is no sign here, in Iraq, of the slightest umbitlon of the kind among the people who expect our administration and seem to he quite ready to accept it. As they have in India, other ideas may grow in the eourse of years, but we are of opinion that from the point of view of Iraq it is highly unnecessary and inexpedient to put into the heads of the backward people of the country what seems to us the visionary and premature notions of the creation of an Arabic state; notions which will only tend to make endless difficulties here for Great Britain and serve no present purpose but to stimulate a small section of ambitious men to turn their activities to a direction from which, for many years to come, it is highly desirable to keep them. Moreover there is no personality who could be called on to assume the high position of ruler of an independent Arabic state, as far as we know. 713 F. D,10 My views being as above and Cox concurring in them, [ recommend the omission of the following passages in the proposed proclamation if any is to bo issued. Firstly, from words “ the campaign in ” to words “ at length be real ised ” and, secondly, from the words “ realise that ” to the words “ unique opportunity, ” and, thirdly, the last paragraph from “ let all Muhammadans to sc peace and prosperity ”, as we might be able, in the case of some of these Muhammadans, to obtain active co-operation. More follows. 23 Telegram P., No. I. Gr.— 1603, dated (and received) the 9th November 1915. From—The General Officer Commanding, Force D, ” To—The Secretary to the Government of Inula in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Delhi. Continuation of my I.Gr.—1603.* Finally I urge for consideration that our „ . communications to the public at Bagh- dad should be within my competence and restricted to subjects of local import and that, unless such issue be forced on us or until the end of the war, neither this nor any other proclamation involv ing such wide questions as are raised in Secietary of State’s draft be issued in Mesopotamia at all as whatever is said will be construed to our disadvantage and it is better to let our deeds speak for the good of our rule and intentions. The issue of a press communique in India is different. Should the Government of India, in order to reassure Indian Muhammadans, desire to make such an issue I suggest it be the proclamation proposed in Secretary of State’s telegram of October 27th subject to amendments suggested. 24 Telegram P., dated the Kth (received 14-th) November 1915. From—His Majesty’s Secretary of State for India, London, To—His Excellency the Viceroy (Foreign and Political Department), Delhi. Arabia. Your telegramf of November 10th. With the addition of . TV „ CQO _ , rr sentence expressing our determination f Diary No. 633o-W. , , -fi i i 3 i -i • . to respect all holy places, shrines, etc., as in your suggested notification in India I agree as to proclamation by Nixon. I do not, as regards latter notification, understand your reasons for sup pressing news of occupation. This will certainly come out from other sources. 1 propose therefore as soon as I have certain news of it to publish it here. See my telegram^ of October 12th. Proposed reference to British ladies X Diary No 5650 -W appears no longer suitable as Turkish Government have agreed to their exchange. 25 Telegram P., No. 48-D. S., dated the 16th November 1915. From—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, Delhi, To—The General Officer Commanding, Force “ D, ” Basrah. Please see our telegram§ of 10th instant, No.-33 D. S. Secretary of State § Diary No. 6335-w. agrees that proclamation to be issued on occupation of Baghdad should be confined to a formal notice calling upon civil population to acquiesce quietly in our occupation and assuring them that their persons and property wall be scrupulously respected if they do so. You should add that, in accordance with His Majesty’s Government’s unswerving policy of respecting the sacred places of Islam and susceptibilities o^ the Moslem community, you have issued stringent orders securing the shrines11 and torobs from damage in the course of military operations and occupation, and directing that no obstacles whatever be placed in the way of Imams, Mujtahi r !s, Ulemas, and other religious persons following freely and as usual the ordinary practices of their religion. 27 Telegram P., No. 50-D. S., dated tie 16th November 1915. Prom—His Excellency the Viceroy (Foreign and Political Department), Delhi, To—His Majesty's Secretary of State for India, London. In a telegram § from General Nixon regarding future of Mesopotamia he refers us to Sir Mark Sykes’ No. 16, of § scnai No. 22 . ^ 3 ^ October, to Director, Military Opera tions, War Office, in which Cox’s and his own views were communicated. No copy of Sykes’ communication referred to above has been received by us, and we should he obliged if you could obtain and communicate to us gist of its contents. Otherwise confusion is likely to result from this procedure. 28 Telegram P., No. 149, dated the 18th (received 19th) November 1915. From—His Britannic Majesty's Minister, Tehran, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, Delhi. In case Germans should cut Indo-European Telegraph Department wires from Tehran will you instruct Consuls in Persia to whom you can still send messages to issue proclamation which has been prepared for publication on fall of Baghdad. All wires from Tehran are interrupted at Kum already. S. G. P. I., Delhi.—No. 713 F. D.—25-11-15—6.C.QttEIDEiiTlAL. v ' Delhi j Q ‘■I* ^ '' fc theNovember 1915 3 1 9 i b' j My dear Hirtzel, r ^ • '-2 £ 4 * '/tAi4. » o , I enclose herewith a copy of correspondence Letter from Sir Mark Sykes, dated ) with Sir Mark Sykes, 21st August 1915. Letter to Sir Mark Sykes, dated the 28th October 1915. Letter from Sir Mark Sykes, dated 7th November 1915. m. Itulirin MaTterre-- together with a copy of the Memorandum on Indian \ Moslems which may be useful should he approach the ,p/’‘ India or Foreign Office on the subject. I may add that the Memorandum was necessarily hurriedly 1 ' r y-t prepared and owing to the illness of the o± ficer who deals specially with the Pan-Islamic movement, thi sI —— ■«*«--- r&gt; - (COl'Y). x'-v / •M-/ Viceregal Lodge, Sirala, 21st August 191b. Dear Grant, i shall be in India till at least 29tn and A.G. will nave ray address. Do you think it would be possible to prepare a memorandum on Indian .aoslem feeling on the following lines : 3ec. i- General distribution of moselems Analysis of above on racial lines. Ditto on religious divergencies ' on Intellectuals arid Old School. Give comon factors. Sectional tendencies. Sec.vii. Ati/itude of various sections towards A. Ottoman Caliphate. B. Sherif of Mecca. C. 1 an-islaioiam. D. Lan-Arabism. g. Indian Composite nationalism t Including idea of Moslem and hindu co-operation. Sec.viii. Deal with External and internal Influences. EXTERNAL. lurkieh Empire. Pilgrimage. European Education. INTERNAL• Various propaganda^ Moslem Unity. inter-religious Nationalism Local Education. Bee. i. Sec. ii. Bee • ill. See. iv. 3ec. v. Sec. vi. Sec. vii.l Foreign and Political Department, Simla. JL n (3- 1 Teel if such a msnaoraiidum were available if would help a great deal towards getting a co- j retina ted policy on tills subject xn relation to the 1*Q*«* F*0• and hgypt» if it were ready by Beptember 20th it would be in plenty of time as that is the very earliest I can be back. . ky idea is that such a memorandum would serve as a very useful instruction to those who study Islam from another angle than the Indian one and would nelp to complete the general report 1 must make at the end of my journey. 1 lease let me thank you for your patience in my daily intrusions. Yours very sincerely. SdA Mark Bykes. 1 have the Viceroy's sanction to write you this letter - of course I don't suggest you should prepare the memorandum but set some one else on To to it. Bd/- M.3. Ihe Hon'ble Mr. A.H. Grant, C.3.1., Secretary to the Government of India in tne(COPY) ISy dear SykeB, &lt; Foreign a iolitical department, Simla, the 28th October 1915, 1 enclose herewith ten copies of a memorandum on mdian Moslems for which you ashed in your letter of the 21st August. Owing to the illness of our expert on the fan-Islam question, the memorandum could not be completed altogether but 1 trust you will find it useful P I am also Bending 'Cor.rdBBion deila Reforme de I'Universite d'el-Aztiar* which you lent Sharp. He was under the impreeBion you would return to him!a before his departure. I now return une booh with many thanks. x hope you iiave had an interesting and profitable time in Mesopotamia. Yours sincerely, 3d/- A. H. Grant. Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Marls Sykes, Bt. J-i •. R.R.c.o., M.l C/o General Officer Commanding, Karachi(com. -'Ti,-' &lt;:t? British India Steam navigation Coy., Ld. * (Incorporated In England) T. 3. “Llnga** 7th November 1915. 2vly dear Grant, Very ruany thaiiKB for your letter and memorandum which 1 b to rqy mind of immense value and most suggestive. Section IV shows that fundamentally the * intellectual* is in fact the young lurk of the Committee of Union and and fanaticism along with it but to smash the power of the Moll ah, Ulraa, Moulvi, Cadhi or Mufti and put the revolutionary lawyer, pleader or editor in his place. In section XV you see the same move and 1 nave little doubt as to whence the inspiration comes. vVith all differences of climate, history and Is the attempt of a “modern* literate class to get a mass of ignorant fanatics under its control, and to in Turkey with our applause and assistance the C.U.P. pulled off the coup and now we see the result, the Progress - Their policy is to fceep the name of Islam tradition accounted for, we have the same huawour, that which at present stands in its way. fthe ignorant lurk and Arab fights for Islam, and the ulema and the 3haykh ul Islam anci the Sultan himself are powerless in the face of a collection of cosmopolitan rascals in the pay of Germany. 1 am sure it is up to us to realise this lesson and to back honest moderate conservatism as typified in the Azhar heform rnoveraant a block revolutionary intellectualism for all we are worth. One word of criticism on the memorandum on ran- islarniern - ihe writer says the idea of I anislamism in India is different to that in Turkey in as much as the Turks wish to Turkify - this really is not the case - The Committee of Union and progress as a revolutionary society wishes to control, and will use any Instrument that comes along,It appears anti-national because it cannot convert the Arab educated or not^ to its particular way of thinking and squashes the Arab, but it A is pro-zionist, and as long as the Armenians were anti- Kussian anci pro-nihilists it bacKed the Armenian Tasnnakist society - it has backed i ersian nationalism, and will back any thing that is likely to work in with anarchy, atheism and disintegration - it falls out with the Arabs because the Arab sense of breed, morale,and cleanliness is so strong tdiat Goaraittee ideas IMA* cannot flourish in an Arab “mily&amp;r'. 1 will send you a full rnemroandum:please accept my beet thanks and also my highest compliments to the author of the memorandum. Yours very sincerely, 30/• Mark Oykes. To The Hoi/ble Mr. A.H. Grant, C.B.l. .C.I.E.. Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Folitieal Department, Simla(Confidential.) MEMORANDUM ON INDIAN MOSLEMS. SECTION I. rphg total number of Indian Moslems is G6‘6 millions or more than one-fifth of the total butiorf of Mos' P°P u l a tion of India. Their distribution is far from uniform. In the North-West Frontier lems. Province 98 per cent., in Baluchistan 91 per cent, in the Punjab 55 and in Bengal 53 per cent. of the inhabitants profess this religion. The proportion falls to 28 per cent, in Assam, 20 per cent, in Bombay and 14&lt; per cent, in the United Provinces. Bihar and Orissa is the only other major pro\inee where it exceeds 10 per cent., while in the Madras Presidency it is 6L in the Central Provinces and Berar it is only 4, and in Burma 3‘5 per cent. In the Native States taken as a whole, the proportion of Muhammadans is much smaller than in British territory, but they are very numerous in the Baluchistan States and Kashmir and fairly so in the States of the Punjab, Bengal and United Provinces. (u) The Muhammadans of India belong to seven distinctive groups— SECTION II. Analysis of above on racial lines. V {a) (*) SECTION III. Analysis on religious diverg encies. \ Turko-Iranian in Baluchistan and the North-West Frontier Province (2,723,145). Indo-Aryan in Ajmer-Merwara, Rajputana, the Punjab and Kashmir (15,334,727). Dravidian in Madras, Mj^sore, Hyderabad, Travancore, Cochin, Ckota Nagpur, Central Provinces and* Berar (4,986,473). (d) Aryo-Dravidian in the United Provinces and Bihar (10,294,446). (e) Mongolo-Dravidian in Bengal and Orissa (21,419,408). (f) Mongoloid in Assam, Sikkim, Cooch Behar and Hill Tippera (1,794,897)? (g) Scytho-Dravidian in Bombay, Baroda and Coorg (4,770,544). (Hi) The main sects of Islam are the Sunnis and the Shiahs, the latter number about 15 millions. The schism arose within the first century after the death of the Prophet, the Sunnis, or Traditionalists, accepting the Sunnat, or collected body of usage, as possessing authority concurrent with or supplementary to the Koran, a view which the Shiahs reject. Shiahs maintain that the Imamate, or temporal and spiritual headship of the faithful, was by divine right vested in Ali and his descendants through Hasan and Husain, the illfated grandsons of the Prophet. They necessarily reject as usurpers the first 3 Imams, Abu Bakr, Umar and Usman—whom the Sunnis respect. The former observe the annual feast of the Muharram in memory of the martyrdom of Ali and his two sons, while the Sunnis celebrate only the The Wahabis. V The Shiah movement, in fact, is strongest where there is least Arab intermixture in the population. Hence some have defined it as an Aryan protest against Semite domination. Minor sects of In Islam the sectarian movement usually follows one of two lines : it is either puritanical Islam. or pietistie. A type of the first class of sect is that of the Wahabis, founded in Nejd in Arabia, early in the eighteenth century. It was an attempt to restore the primitive practices of Islam, which, in the°view of the founder, had become corrupted during its world wide career of conquest. The new doctrine was introduced into India by Saiyid Ahmad Shah, who pro claimed a holy war against the Sikhs in 1826, and founded the colony of fanatics on the North-West Frontier. Wahabis accept the six books of traditions collected by the Sunnis but reject the glosses of the Church theologians and claim liberty of conscience and the right of private interpretation. They insist on the unity of God which, they say, has been endangered by the reverence paid to the person of the Prophet, to the Imams and Saints. Hence they condemn pilgrimages to shrines. They discountenance the use of rosaries, and regard tobacco as unlawful? From a political point of view the most dangerous doctrine of the sect was to assert that India is “ the land of warfare”, against the rulers of which to wage war is a religious duty. Much controversy has arisen regarding this doctrine which is undoubtedly accepted by some members of the sect. It would seem, however, that the fanatical element in the movement has for the present died out in many parts. The second sectarian movement in Islam tends in the direction of Sufiism a strange combination of the pantheism of the Aryan race, and of the severe monotheism of their Semitic conquerors. Sufiism aims at leading men to the contemplation of spiritual things by appealing to their emotions. The keynote of the system is that the human soul is an emanation from God, and that it is always seeking and yearning to rejoin the source from which it sprung. Ecstasy is the means by which a nearer intercourse is obtained and absorption in the divinity is the ultimate object to be attained. Thise doctrines, with more or less variance of practice, are accepted by the leading Sunni orders, such as the Chistiyas and Kadiriyas. Outside these are the Be-shara, or non-orthodox orders, who, while calling themselves Musalmans, do not accommodate their lives to the principles of any definite creed. These furnish the most desperate Musalman fanatics. Suflism.2 * The Ahmadiyas. Moplahs, Bohras, Khojas. SECTION IV. Intellectuals and old school. SECTION V. Common Factors. SECTION VI. Sectional tendencies. / SECTION VII. (a) Attitude of Moslems to wards the Cali phate, The wildest development of recent sectarianism in Islam is furnished by the Ah madia sect, which has its headquarters in the Punjab. Its leader, Mulla Ghulam Ahmad, in a recent manifesto claims to be the counterpart of the Saviour of Christianity, and to be the Mahdi or Messiah expected by Musalmans and Christians alike. The Koran is to him the repository of all knowledge. The resurrection is at hand, While discouraging religious war, he is said to preach strongly against Christianity, Hinduism, the Shiah doctrines, and the movement in favour of English education. Three notable phases of Muhammadan religious life are illustrated by the Moplahs, the Bohras and the Khojas. The first are found to the number of a million in Malabar. This tribe is remarkable for the savage fanaticism displayed in successive revolts against Hindus. The Bohras, or “traders” of western India, fall into two groups, the mercantile branch, originally Shiahs, and the land holding section, who are generally Sunnis, Both are mainly converts from Hinduism. The Khojas are active traders on the west coast of the Peninsula and in East Africa. The well-known Agha Khan of Bombay is their head. The precise meaning of “ Intellectuals and old school ” is not clear but the following facts may be of interest : — In the last 10 years or so there has in certain parts of India been a great change in the attitude of Muhammadans towards the old Moslem educational system on the one hand and the modern educational system on the other. The figures given under the head “ Education ” sufficiently prove this. It is particularly interesting to note that the number of pupils in private institutions (which are institutions largely concerned with the teaching of Arabic, Persian and the Koran) is, within a few hundreds, the same in 1914 that it was in 1902 ; whereas the number of pupils in public institutions (which follow the ordinary courses, though their numbers include a certain number of Male fab a, &amp;c.) has in the same period almost doubled. The Muhammadans of Eastern Bengal have quarrelled with the courses prescribed in the Madrassas with the result that the Local Government have published a highly modernised course for the majority of these institutions (the famous Calcutta Madrassa being excepted) which insists upon English in most of the courses. The discussions leading up to this change show that the feeling against the retention of Persian and the old traditional subjects (save in a minor degree or for special courses) is quite surprising. This reform of the Madras'ws contrasts most strongly with the reforms contemplated in the Al-Azhar University at Cairo. The one is a radical change, the other a conservative compromise. It will yet remain to be seen how these courses in Bengal can be introduced and what will be their effect. This does not mean that there is total neglect of the traditional subjects. Hadis and Tafsir, &amp;c., will be still taught, but less time will be devoted to them. The traditional curriculum still flourishes unchanged in many up-country Madrassas such as the institution at Deobund. The only common factors running through all shades of Moslem feeling and Moslem thought in India would appear to be the vague idea of Islam which acts as a political catchword and as a fanatical war-cry : a conscientious though often artificiaL. and* jj^perficial contempt for and dislike of all non-Moslems or infidels : and a desire to see the Moslem races raised once more to a dominant position. In fact the common aim would appear to be secular self-interest rather than religious propagandism. Caste is a creation of Hinduism but the Muhammadan community is largely influenced by caste practices derived from its long contact with the Hindu system. Even among Muham madans the evolution of the caste system has moreover proceeded on characteristically Hindu lines. In both communities foreign descent forms the highest claim to social distinction, in both promotion cometh from the west. As the twice-born Aryan is to the mass of Hindus, so is the Muhammadan of Arab, Persian, Afghan or Mughal origin to the rank and file of his co-religionists. The highest class of men of alleged foreign origin will marry daughters of men who rank below them in social estimation but the converse process is vigorously condemned. Thus a Saiyid will marry a Sheikh's daughter but will not give his daughter in return and inter marriage between the upper circle of soidisant foreigners and the main body of Indian Muham madans is generally reprobated, except in parts of the country where the aristocratic element is small and must arrange its marriages as best it can. Speaking generally, it may be said that the social cadre of the higher ranks of Muhammadans is based on hypergamy with a tendency in the direction of endogamy, while the lower functional groups are strictly endogamous, and are organized on the model of regular castes, with councils and officers which enforce the observance of caste rules by the time honoured sanction of boycotting. For further information please see also Section III. The question of the Caliphate concerns only the Orthodox Moslems (Sunnis) who are in the great majority. The other sects have conflicting views on the subject. The Sunnis hold that the guardianship of the holy places must be in the hands of a Moslem Sovereign who derives his title to the Caliphate by nomination from his predecessor. This precedent of nomination has been followed since the Itith Century. For this reason the Orthodox Moslems regard the Sultan of Turkey as the rightful Caliph of Islam and owe him spiritual allegiance. The Wahabis and Shiahs, however, hold that the Turkish Sultans are usurpers as also do the Moslems of Morocco, while those of Arabia and Mecca in particular are3 (b) Attitude of various sec tions towards ■ k the Shari£^ % Mecca. ▼ r^fo) Pan- Isiamism. said to be awaiting a favourable opportunity to drive the Turks out of tbeir country and choose a Caliph from amongst the Sharif families of Mecca. As regards the attitude of Indian Muhammadans towards the Sharif of Mecca there is no direct evidence. As far as can be ascertained they regard the Sharif as merely a civil goveinor appointed by the Sultan of Turkey and not possessed of any religious authority. In the case of a complex phenomenon such as Pan-Islaraism, to the formation of which a number of subtle tendencies have contributed, it is necessary to disentangle one or two ideas to show how their operation appear to have produced the result. The movement is religious as well as political. The former is practically universal; the latter, though widespread, has features peculiar to India and Turkey, but with different objectives. The bonds of sympathy between Moslems in India and elsewhere is very strong and real and their susceptibilities were wounded by the recent misfortunes befalling their co-religionists in Tripoli and Persia. Muhammadans imagined a Christian coalition to encompass the 'ruin of Islam which could only be averted by a Moslem federation justified on religious or humanitarian grounds. Such appears to have been the origin of the Pan-Islamic religious movement. ^ The Pan-Islamic political movement generally is based on the principle of nationality. The various Musalman peoples see in Pan-Islamism a means of safeguarding their rights and averting absorption and Turkish domination politically. Indian Muhammadans, apprehensive of absorption by Hinduism, see in the political Pan-Islamic movement a means for the continuance of Islamism as a national entity in India. The idea of Pan-Islamism among the young Turk party is widely different. The Turks wish to make Pan-Islamism an instrument for the effective domination of all other Musalman peoples. The absolute predominance of the Turkish element is with them an inviolab le principle. \ c \ (d) Indian composite nationalism including the idea of Moslem and Hindu co-operation. In 1907 was founded the All-India Moslem League. One of its chief objects is to culti vate harmonious relations with other Indian communities, especially with the great sister community of the Hindus. Since the foundation of the league there has been a growing tendency on the part of the elite Hindus and Muhammadans to strengthen the solidarity of political unity. But the absence of the essential factors which make for nationality, such as the possession of a common language and literature, common historic traditions, community of religion and of social customs, tends towards separation rather than consolidation. The object of the league will therefore take a long time to effect and great changes of religious feeling and social customs must take place before the masses of either community will follow their leaders. So long as Muhammadans kill for food or sacrifice the animal (cow) deemed sacred by the .Hindus and so long as^the Hindus of some parts of India suggest by the cult of Sivaji the revolt of Hinduism againsf Islam, occasions for deadly strife are bound to arise when the passion of religious animosity will overpower the sentiment of common nationality. SECTION VIII. Turkish Empire. Most Moslems fear that the destruction of the Turkish Government will involve also the destruction of Muhammadan principles. It is principally the religious bond which makes them so attached to Turkey. The greatest desire of the Moslem races is to see a strong, prosperous and educated Ottoman Empire. Its traditions appeal to their imagination and stir their sympathies. But it is an accepted doctrine that the recognition of the Sultan as Caliph does not involve any political allegiance to him. Eor this reason the Moslems of India and Egypt have not wavered in their secular allegiance. External grimage. k External. European education. pil- The duty of pilgrimage is enforced by the law of Islam on every Moslem who is not exempted under the law. The interest of the Muhammadan public in questions relating to the pilgrimage is evidenced by the formation of Haj Committees in several of the large towns of India and by the establishment, in 1913, of the Anjuman-i-Khuddam-i-Kaaba, or Society of Servants^ of the Kaaba. The object of the former institutions is to disseminate useful information regarding various questions connected with the Haj. The ostensible object of the latter society is to safeguard the sanctity of the Kaaba and other sacred places of Islam from violation, to maintain an independent and effective Moslem sovereignty over those lands and to remove existing difficulties of pilgrimage to the Hedjaz. To this end the Society of Servants of the Kaaba has decided to publish a newspaper in Arabic in order to enlighten the Bedouins who harass Musalman pilgrims and thus put difficulties in the performance of pilgrimage.^ The object of the society is also to impress on Musalmans everywhere their duty to their religion. There is abundant evidence that the leaders of the Muhammadan community are strenuously endeavouring to take advantage of the State system of education. The prejudice of Muhammadans against the learning of English is a thing of the past. Muhammadans do not go to Europe or America to the same extent as do the Hindus. Figures are not available as the majority if Indians who go abroad for education go with private scholarships or private means.4 Moslem unity. Inter-religious nationalism. Internal Local education. The question of tlie Imamate or the spiritual headship of the Moslem Commonwealth is the chief battle ground of the two main sects of Muhammadans—Sunnis and Shiahs. In other matters there is a bond of sympathy which is much in evidence whenever indications appear of any concerted movement destructive of Islamism. Thus it is that the independence of Islamic States, such as Turkey and Persia, is dear to Indian Muhammadans. They consider that the existence of independent Moslem States will not only prevent their absorption by Hinduism, a fear ever present to the Moslem mind, but also that independent Islamic States go far to guarantee, by their moral, as well as their political, support, the continuance of Muhammadans as a separate national entity in India. The “ Moslem League ” which includes both Sunnis and Shiahs is an organisation to strengthen the solidarity of political unity. According to the census statistics of 1911 of the total population of India, only 59 persons per mille are literate in the sense of being able to write a letter to a friend and to read his reply. There are many Muhammadans, especially in Northern India, who can read the Koran, though they cannot write a word. No statistics of this form of literacy are available. Of the different religious communities, the Muhammadans stand almost at the bottom of the list as regards literates. They have 69 males and 4 females per mille. The low position of the Muhammadans is due largely to the fact that they are found chiefly in the North-West of India where all classes are backward in respect of education, and in Eastern Bengal where they consist mainly of local converts from a depressed class. Tn Sind the Muhammadan population is exceptionally illiterate; in the rest of the Presidency proper the most educated classes are Bohras, Khojas, Memons and Telis. The Statistical table below gives the Muhammadan literates per mille throughout India : NUMBER PER MILLE WHO ARE LITERATE. Province, State or Agency. Musalman. Males. Females. India 69 4 Provinces ... ... • •• 69 4 A jmer-Merwara • t • 95 6 Andamans and Nicobars t • • 195 34 Assam ... ... 57 2 Baluchistan ... • • • 16 1 Bengal ... ... • • t 79 2 Bihar and Orissa 79 5 Bombay • * « 85 7 Burma ... • • • 284 77 Centra] Provinces and Berar • • « —167 10 Coorg • •• 183 16 Madras ... 166 11 N.-W. E. Province ... 25 1 Punjab ... • a • 27 2 United Provinces • ♦ • 58 6 States and Agencies 70 8 Baroda State —— 232 17 Central India Agency 107 12 Cochin State ... 138 7 Hyderabad State ... • • • 103 13 Kashmir State ... • • • 15 Mysore State 200 41 Bajputana Agency ... • • • 44 3 Sikkim State 632 Travancore State , v ... 171 13 Note .—The figures for Provinces are inclusive of the States attached to them, except in the case of Madras, where they exclude Cochin and Travancore. The last 12 years have witnessed a remarkable awakening on the part of this community to the advantages of English education. Within this period the number of Muhammadan pupils in institutions of all kinds has increased by approximately 721,000 or by 73%, The number at school accordingly represents over 17% of those of school-going age. The number in the old-fashioned private schools remains stationary. The increase is almost wholly due to numbers in the public schools, which has increased by 98%. Still more remarkable has been the increase of Muhammadan pupils in higher institutions. The number of Muham madans in Arts Colleges was 1,259 in 1902 and 3,792 in 1914; that in professional colleges h^s approximately doubled within the period, while that in English secondary schools has5 advanced from about 55,000 to 161,000. In primary institutions (in which the vernacular is taught) the proportion of Muhammadan pupils is considerable, being 1 11*1% of those of school-going age as against 14 j’ 4% in the case of pupils of all creeds in primary schools. The Muhammadans now avail themselves largely of the ordinary institutions which are common to all communities, but special facilities are also afforded them in the shape of special institu tions such as Madrassas and also Muhammadan hostels and scholarships and a few special Inspectors. In some parts of India, notably in Sind and in Bengal, efforts have been made by Government to impart a considerable element of secular education into the Mullah schools, the Koran schools and MaMabs, while Koran teaching and instruction in Urdu (even where it is not the ordinary vernacular) are still retained. These efforts have been successful. In April 1913, the Government of India issued an important circular to Local Governments regarding the encouragement of Muhammadan education. This circular gave high satisfaction to the community. While the Muhammadans have shown great keenness on the subject of secular education they are nevertheless eager to retain or introduce religious instruction in special Muhammadan institutions. The scheme for a Muhammadan University, initiated at the beginning of 1911 and not yet matured, partly reflects this feeling but was prompted mainly by other motives. It is proposed to locate this University at Aligarh, where the famous M. A. O. College already exists. This institution which was previously the nearest approach, in India to an English public school has now increased its number, admitting pupils from ranks of society who previously did not aspire to such education, and under extra-educational influence has suffered deterioration. («) Total population of school-going age (S) Muhammadan population of school-going age (c) Total Muhammadans at school {d) Muhammadans in primary (i.e., primary public institutions) institutions (e) All creeds in primary institutions ( f) Percentage of total Muhammadans at school (c) to Muhammadan population of school-going age (6) (g) Percentage of total Muhammadans at school (c) to total population of school-going age (a) {h) Percentage of Muhammadans in primary institutions (d) to total population of school-going ages (a) {i) Percentage of Muhammadans in primary institutions {d) to Muhammadan population of school-going age (6) ... ••• ••• ••• (_/) Percentage of all creeds in primary institutions (e) to total population of school-going age («).,, 38,273,073 9,997,095 1,699,449 1,108,218 5,518,671 17 4-4 2-9 11*1 14*4 \ F, &amp; P. Dept. Press—No, 1762-1M0.15-50,Decypher Sir H. Llachahcn (Cairo) December 10th 1915. 13 c 5 aM 0 December 11th r. 10 0 35 a fc rn, December 11th. No.761 Arab question. Selection of Picot as their representative on recent ccrnmittee on this question is discouraging indication of French attitude. Picot is a notorious fanatic on Syrian question and quite incapable of assisting'^-any mutual settlement on reasonable common sense grounds which present situation requires. It is unfortunate that adviser of French Government here, de France is man of similar type, Notwithstanding recent assurances to me I am informed that he sent a few -days ago for a leading Arab notary of Damascus now in Egypt and told him as follows, M You can tell all your friends here from me and I tell you this in my capacity as representative of French Government that Syria shall never be part of Arab empire,' Siria will be under protection of France and we shall shortly send an army to oenupy it but we shall govern it in the way which most suits its people ci all races and religions. w This is not helpful but while present attitude of French Government continues it appears useless for me to remonstrate with him. In the Meantime both desirability and difficulty of detabhing arabs from our enemy are daily increasing. Conditions of Arabia never justified expectation of ac tive or organised assistance such as seme people think is object of our porerposed mutual understanding, dhat we want is material advantage of even passive Arab sympathy and assistance on our side instead of their active co-operation with enemy. This advantage will become of still more vital importance to us if as now seems probable time does not longer permit of action elsewhere and we have to await enemy's advance on Egypt, Addressed to Foreign Office, sent to India.In Any further communica tion or. this subject, please quote No. ISlSJif /I9I5 and address— The Under-Secretary of State Foreitfn Office, London. The Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the $ nAt-Ct CtliSCf ft C/t / and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith copy of the under-mentioned^ paper. Foreign Office, /he. « ( 9 , tQa Reference to previous correspondence : Letter to from Foreign Office: Description of Inc to sure. Name and Date. Subject. CaO,. &lt;f\ft . (it, . ■ 4 (y* eiry A . CIS IjECISU.^ (Similar letter sent to // ST -v^lS I 14 ]! \ i» r EGWT, l (181634/15)„ Cypiioi' lo 1 g grsni uO t&gt;ii* ii*t-iQ.CwJfi.!ioxi (C^ilioj 0 Foreign Office. Decem’oor 10 th 19X5, 6.40 p.m No, 961, Urgent, Your tolegrara No,756„ Importance of display of British or Allied force round which Arabs can rally is fully recognised here, but you will realise that present situation at Gallipoli and Balonica makes it out of the question for the moment to embark on any other expedition* Attitude of French Government in regard to Syria is also very difficult and we have little hope oi obtaining from them any assurance that will really satisly Arabs* Gn the other hand, we must try to keep the negotiations with the Sherif in being, and you are authorised oo reply uo him as followsw- Points ] and 2, as you propose* . , as regards' point 3/you should say that as /ie interests Of others a-e involved, the point requires careful consiaeia- tion by His‘Majesty^ Government and a further communication in regard to'it will be sent later® . , r . Point 4* V/e should prefer to say tnat his mages uy Government are. as the Sheri.l knows, Sisposed oo^gi/e ^ antee to assist and protect the proposed Arab kingdom as fai as may be within their power, but their interests demand, as the Sherif has recognised, a friendly administration m the Vilayet of Bagdad and the safeguarding of those interests call for much fuller and more, detailed consideration oi the future of Mesopotamia than the present situation and the urgency of the negotiations permit* (This need not, however preclude eventual consideration of a perpetual lease or any other reasonable financial proposal that may be made to jus, though it will of course depend on extent and success of Arab co-operation)* Point 5« The first and narrower assurance you propose* Points 6 and 7* As you suggest, t+ onn-iiri «i p;n hft mRd &amp; olear to Sherif that when we ty : s Government have no wish or intention to interfeie in the internal affairs of Arabia_» _ 4 In Any further communica tion on this subject, please quote No. 18502ii9i5 and address— The Under-Secretary of State Foreign Office, London. SECRET, f ■&lt;,. ■■ ! O 4 %„J&gt; The Under-Secretarv of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the UNDER SECRETARY OF STATE FOR INDIA and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop y of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, December 12th , /o&gt;/j. Reference to previous correspondence L, K r&lt; to Letter \ Foreign Office : from * ^ Description of Inclosure. Name and Date. ect. Sir H. McMahon, Cairo. Tel No. 749, December 5th, 1915. Arab Question,J' X ,| | EGV.2 Decypher of telegran from sir HeMacMahon (Cairo) B (dr 12p 55 Pciric r, 2,0 p,m P No,749, Decemher Oth 1910, December Oth), My telegram No,736 r Sirdar telegraphs as follows H I share your opinion tha,t assurances quoted in your draft letter to Sharif are minimum that can be expected to secure his approval and that of Arabs, German success in the Balkans, our check before Bagdad and uncertainties of general military position have seriously reinforced German designs and situa tion of Arab question appears to me most critical, I have no doubt unless we can bring effective influen ces to bear at once solution of this question will be found by enemy and very seriously to our disadvantage by grant of autonomy to Arab countries by Sultan at instigation of German Emperor, I presume His Majesty’s Government will be aware of grave and possibly disastrous effects on public opinion in Moslem countries if Arab peoples should openly subscribe to Ottoman Jehad r and I would most strongly urge - 1 , that (? reply to) Sherif be at once (? group omitted) containing assurances of a character to ob tain acceptance by Arab leaders and promises of moral (? and) material support when required, and 2, that we should prepare to support Sherif and Arab cause by all means in our power that may be con venient and required by leader of movement,”' Addressed to Foreign Office No,749, \ -a 3 'Cal2663 B. Three Ajrabs of Shaimiar with 200 camels arrived at Zobeyr from Hail about 11th November to buy pro visions, Following is substance of speech which they gave in reply to my question. While BinSaud was in Hassa Bin Rashid had skirmish with people of Qasim Aneiza Boreida but Bin Rashid suffered no reverse at hands of Bin Baud. No recent agreement made be tween Bin Rashid and Bin Baud, but latter broke agreement made two years ago. Turkish Officer came to Bin Rashid 10 months ago, but returned immediately. No Turkish Officer now with Bin Rashid. 4 - 4 Sherriff Mecca came to Athala in Sadair to claim against tax from Ataiba. He fought { Bareih clan Almatair who sur- r . /fv „ rendered to him. Son of Sheriff last heard of-him-Shagra in Badair and then reported to be returning to Mecca. Sherriff of Mecca said to be friendly relations with Bin Baud and impression given me was that no communication held between son of Sherriff and Bin Rashid. Addressed to C.G-.S.^Simla, repeated to S. of S. for I.&gt; . &gt; !' i—^ In Any further communica tion on this subject, please quote n°. and address— The Under-Secretary of State Foreign Office, London. Pat L'l r.vvr.r Tke Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Undersecretary of State for ^ and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop ULc of the under-mentioned paper. j [ 12 ]&gt;!C'. mo*:.- Copy. No. 573. (179206) BERNE, November 23rd, 1915. Sir:- ' —,—^ I have the honour to enclose copy of a despatch addressed to me hy Lieutenant Colonel Picot giving an account of an interview he has had with Moukhtar Bley Soulh, formerly Aide-de-Camp to the Crown Prince of Turkey and at present Inspector of the Baghdad rail way. Moukhtar declares that he has been deputed to make it known to His Majesty’s Government that Syria and Arabia are ready to revolt against Turkish rule. I have, etc., (Signed) Acton. (For the Minister) l The Right Honourable Sir Edward Grey, Bart., K.G., M.P. c*iC . , SiO * ,Copy. NO, 404. 3 E R N E, November 23rd, 1915 1 Sir I have the honour to report that I received a visit on November 22nd, 1915, from a certain Moukhtar Bey Soulh, formerly Aide-de-Camp of the Crown Prince of Turkey and at present Inspector of the Baghdad Railway, Moukhtar Bey Soulh has just arrived from Aleppo and Constantinople accompanied by his sister who is seeking medical advice abroad. He states that he was deputed by Committees in Syria and Constantinople to represent to the first British authority with whom he could establish contact that Syria and Arabia are ripe for revolt and have been so any time during the last four months. Committees of notables have been secretly established in every town in Syria, as also in Constantinople, j who would give every support to and rally round any j Expeditionary Force landed in Syria for the purpose of raising the country in open rebellion. Certain declarations would be required by which the country might be assured of its complete independence of Constantinople in both a political and religious sense. The Mahomedans of Syria would not continue to recognize the Sultan as Khalif and wished to nominate a Khalif of their own choice. Further, the people would require arms, ammunitions, supplies. If Evelyn Grant Duff, Esq., C.M.G., &amp;c., &amp;c., &amp;c. Berne,If the foregoing guarantees were given and equipment supplied we could count on the Arabs and Syrians from Baghdad to the Mediterranean and a barrier would be raised against movements of Turkish troops from the direction of the Taurus. Committee Agents are with the Anase Tribe who give tribal allegiance to Sheikh Hadjim Bin Mihied. one of these agents, Sami Bey Soulh, Conseiller Legist© of the Baghdad Hallway Company, is own brother to Moukhtar Bey Soulh. Moukhtar Bey suggests that his brother should be sent for as soon as Baghdad is occupied by British troops. He describes him as an energetic well educated man who influences the Sheikh and who would prove useful.* Regarding the Baghdad railway Moukhtar Bey states that it is open from Islahieh south of the Amanus to Aleppo, and thence by Muslimii, Djerabus, Tel-al- Abiad to Rass-el-Ein. The long tunnel through the Araanus; as also the work in the Taurus which com prises 24 tunnels of some 23 kilometers in length, is, according to this informant, far from completion. He gave two years as an estimate for the linking up of the line between Anatolia and Aleppo, I have, etc., (Signed) H. Picot, Lieutenant Colonel. Military Attach^.In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote No. / /1915 and address— The Under-Secretary of State Foreign Office, London. s/tcrtJ The Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the (-TutAh Tccn l ci^ ^v $nnllM. and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop y of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, , '9*5 Iveference to previous correspondence to Letter , Foreign Office: from y ^ Description of Inclosure. Name and Date. ^ k». iT- /Uv ’ Subject. 1 f H I 14 ]Coryv to India, 3 DEC 1915 1 JCT2T. Decypher, Sir H. Mch^hon (feieh) November 30th. D. 8.5 p 0 m. Mover R. 10.40 pan., No. 736. Your telegram No- 867, You will have now received full text of Shereef’s letter. It is satisfactory as snowing a desire for mutual understanding on reasonable lines. It also affords an opportunity of meeting the wishes of Government of India with regard to Mesopotamia by some change of formula, but I cannot personally think of any formula on that subject wore favourable to Indian interests than the one employed in my former letter, without raising Arab suspicions. I think criticism of Government of India and Secretary of State ignores the very great importance which the Arabs attach to Baghdad and Irak, by their historical religious and economic reasons. It- is quite impossible to come to any general understand ing with Arabs without some acknowledgment that Irak is in theory part of Arabia proper. With regard to nonentity of Shereef or his pro-Turkish proclivity I can find no corroboration of this here or in the Sudan, or amongst other Arabs with whom we are in touch nor in the attitude of Ottomon Government towards him. Everything would tend to prove that he is of sufficient (&amp;roup■■tmdcuypncrabItrHmg importance, by position descent and personality,, to be the only possible central rally in ■•point for mrab cause, and sufficiently anti-Turkish to be in great personal danger at Turkish hands. Again the present Arab movement it must be remembered is based on national rather than religious grounds and differs widely from pan I slam ism with which Arab party disdain sympathy.* Thereare _ There are manv Shiah Arabs in Irak but there/also many Christian 'fi Arabs in the west, but neither fact appears to me to preclude general agreement on lines suggested. Every portion of Arab empire will require some different form of admnistration to suit its local conditions, and this alone will I think sufficiently postpone or prevent creation of united independent Arab State wnich India seems to apprehend. Even such an Arab State established and controlled under entente auspices will present far less danger than survival of : hostile Ottoman empire wherein Arabs would be under Turks, Turks under Committee of Union and progress and the latter under Germany a contingency which cannot be regarded as impossible if con clusion of (group undecypherable ?war) finds Turkey with an unbeaten army in Syria and North Mesopotamia. Jith regard to objections to Arab movement raised in other quarters I tuink io right to warn His Alajesty’s Government Gnat Germans ano. Young Turks are doubtless endeavouring to employ certain indirect in fluences. French financial interests and Indian Mohammedanism were both brought into play on the recapture of Adrianople, and one must anticipate this influence again in tnis connection. The Shereef’s letter demands a reply, and I regret the delay which my absence has caused in submitting proposals. In doing so now I am faced with the great difficulty wnich besets our treatment of the Arab question if tne policy of awaiting in Egypt the threatened Turco-German advance is adhered to. This policy will jeopardise any attempt to secure Arab co operation and it would appsar unwise urging Arabs into prema ture activity which through want of our support and xear of Tur kish retaliation might hasten their abandonment of our cause.(In this connection see also the Sirdar’s views as staoed in my telegram of November 16th). TheThe serious situation however now facing us in Egypt and Mesopotamia renders alienation of Arab assistance from Turks a matter of great importance, and we must make every effort to enlist the sympathy and assistance * even though passive, of Arab people. With the above object I suggest reply to thereof on the following lines 1. Acknowledge his exclusion oi Adana and Mersina from Arab sphere. 2. Note with pleasure his assurance (quoting his own words) that Arabs are determined to act in accordance with the precedents of Omar and the early Khalifs which secure the righus and privileges of M&amp;slems and Christians alike. (?3).Agree that with the exception of tract around Marasn and Aintab, vilayets of Beirut Aleppo are inhabited by Arabs,but in these vilayets as elsewhere in Syria our ally France has ccm- siderable interests.to safeguard which some special arrangements will be necessary and as this is a matter for the French Govern ment we cannot say more now than assure the Shereef of our earnes wish that satisfactory settlement may be arrived at. ( Some more brief and definite statement is desirable now it French Government. an be got to agree). 4. With regard to the vilayets of Basra and bag;hdad some !uch arrangement as he suggests would provide suitable solution, . e . that these vilayets which have been taken by us from the hirKs by force of arms should remain under British administra tion until such time as a satisfactory mutual arrangement can ie made. (Indian Government may be able to suggest some setter formula. I should note that as far as I can ascertain vie.vs of the Shereef and Arab party, they recognise their inability to administer these vilayets and are content to leave rhem in^ C*'our hands but require formula that satisfies Arab sentiment). What they obviously most d.sire is some assurance of our considering the question of a quit-rent or subsidy. o. Assurance of the Shcreef that Great Britain has no intention to conclude peace in terms of which freedom of Arabs irom Turkish domination does not form essential condition. (On some assurance of tills nature solo hops od* successful under standing depends. I would even suggestfthat| stronger assurance to tne effect teat il Arabs play proper part in the war we bind ourselves not to desert them nor to conclude any ce etc * as above). 6. Appreciation of Shcreef 5 s desire for caution and dis claim wish to urge him to hasty action jeopardizing Arab pro jects but in tne meantime he must spare no effort to attach Arab ■peoples to our cause and prevent them assisting the enemy, as it Yv is the success of these efforts and on active measures which tne Araos may hereafter take in our cause when the time comes that permanency of present arrangement must depend. 7. Inform him that, to- facilitate his efforts in our joint cause, we are sending him some funds. (Since stoppage of Ottoman Government doraihens to the Shereef he is in pressing need of funds for the maintenance of Liecca and Medina and for the maintenance of his forces. It is most desirable to assist him generously and I would recommend grant of £50,000 to be given in instalments as matters progress. To be effective sum must be large and greater part of any money we give him will find its way to our own trade ports). It is desirable to reply without undue delay as messenger is still waiting here. Addressed to Foreign Office, sent to India No. 736. 5In Any further communica tion on this subject, please quote No. /8//8o /1915 and address— The Under-Secretary of State Foreign Office, London. /fen/, The Under-Secretary of State for Foreign A fairs presents his compliments to the ^rStf /ten i and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith copy of the under-mentioncd paper. Foreign Office, /he. nO *v « , I 9 I 5- r npy to India 10 DEC 1915 Reference to previous correspondence to Letter J Foreign Office : from M Description of Inc Insure. isame and Date. A, M 0 . tAw. Subject. rirrA Qo-tvfunA, 'Similar letter sent to I 14 ]Copy . Note on the Arab Move ment. (1) On the 23rd of November a meeting was held of the committee appointed to discuss with a French represen tative the question of Syria and the Arabs. The object of the committee was to persuade the French representative of the necessity of offering to the Arabs and Syrians, in the Syrian area to be allotted to the French, some measure of independence, conditional on their assisting the Allies, thus putting a check to Turkish and German aims in consolidating Mohammedan religious feeling with them. (2) The attitude of the French representative was absolutely uncompromising. He held out no hopes whatever of the French making any offer of independence to the Sy rians. He endeavoured to throw doubt on the Turks and Ger mans being able to stir up any religious Mohammedan move ment. And he asked for proofs as to the strength of the Arab and Syrian racial movement, which he suggested was much exaggerated by the Cairo authorities. (3) It may be well in this connection to allude to the expression of views, reported elsewhere, by the French Military Attache, namely that, should an expedition to Alexandretta be undertaken, the French must insist on their supplying at least two thirds of the force. (4) The attitude of the French can only be explained in one way - However much they may protest to the contrary, they are fully aware of the fact that the Syrians and Arabs would very much prefer to be under British than French tu telage - And they foresee the great embarrassment end dif ficulty which might result to themselves from this fact. Ifr If Syria from the first is treated as a purely French possession and if ? in the event of an expedition to Syria, the great preponderance of troops were French, making it obvious that no other Power had any interests, they rea lize that the difficulty is never likely to arise. (5) To compel the French to fall in with our views it is only possible to reiterate arguments already put forward, and to emphasize them in such a way that it is obviously to their own disadvantage, as well as unfriendly to us, not to do so. The arguments are briefly as follows:- From information, the sources of which (Cairo and Constantinople) are not available to the French, it is known that the Arab and Syrian racial movement has great force, given the opportunity. There is a chance, though it is every moment becoming fainter, of using it as a powerful weapon against the Turks. There is the certainty that, if proofs are not given of the sympathy of the Frenchsf and British with the move ment, it will range itself on the Turkish side and that, provided the Turks play their cards cleverly, it will become solid against the Allies. Consequent upon the above there is the most imminent danger that the Germans and Young Turks will succeed in what it has been their constant endeavour to achieve from long past, namely the military co-operation of the whole Mohammedan world in a religious war against the Allies. From the above considerations it should be pointed out to the French that their refusal to act as we wish may endangerlions'll ^Xa'mq s gb ba./Baivt ax adJ moil bxt^C II 'SliyB of noiflbeqxo rw lo fnovo axil ai ,11 baB aoisaosaoq 11 ,xion9i^ erew a&lt;:oo*il lo aoaB'iatooqaic iBaia oxil -boi ^axil ,slsaialni \- ;bb bsil lav/oq isillo on IbuI aucivic 4 ♦ oaiiB ol ^lodxl iavsn ai ^lljjoilli.b axil IbII asll 11 awaiv ijjo xiliw ni ilal ol xionsi^ adl Jsqmoo ol (6) f biBv/iol Ixrq ^dbdiIb alnenu^Te siBiailai ol slcfiaaoq Y-tao ai ol Ylsuoivlo ai li IjgxII ysw b xiox/a ni maxil a si aBriqma ol bna cl Ion , au ol Ylbnaiilnn as Haw ao t a^BlnBvbBai b rtwo ilaxil .03 ob -:awolIol 3B ^Ilaiil bib alnamnaiB axiT bnB oilaO) xloixiw lo aaouca aril ,noil.3miolni :.ioi rf i .won?! ai li t dor/9i'l 9dl ol olefBliBVB Ion 9 ib (olqoniinBlanoO ,90101 lB9ia 3£xi In sms vo;n IbIobi hbIiyS bnB cfsiA sxil IB/il .YliriLrliocrqo sxil navis snimooeci In9mom viovo ai li xtsnoxll t aonBilo b ai sioilT .adm^Biil loniasp nor g:v^ luliawoq a sa li snieu lo , is mi si :s ion sub alooiq li t lBrll Yinialiso axil ai sibxIT -avom axil xiliw xfalliiH baa ^xlonsi'i axil lo ^rUsqm^a axil lo ,Isxll bos abia /i3i:iiirT b cif no llaaii esnai Iliw li ,lft9fn srnooecf Iliw li ,^Ii9V9Xo obiao ii9;fl qalv adinT axil bsbivoiq «aaiXIA aril laniasa biloa Inanirini laom 9itl ai sisrfl svccfa aril ncqu InsnpaanoO ni bosooua Iliw adix/l snuoY bnc ansmisO oxll IbxII 193 nsb moil avoirlos ol iuo vaebn 9 laalsneo lisxll nsscf asd li Isxlw ©Xoiiw enl lo iioiisiDco-oo YisliXim oxll Yl^xnen , Isbc sac I .aeilXA oxll laxiisss isw anoisilai s ni bliow nsbsmmsdoM bslnioq 3d bJnoils li anoiIsis.bianco svoIb axil moi'I ^em xlaiw aw as los ol Isanlei liaxli imiS xlonsi^ exll ol Ino 193 ns moendanger all British possessions in the East, and may thus necessitate the removal of a very large part of the British Army from Prance, thus weakening the Allies in the French theatre dangerously; also that the French themselves may he faced with serious embarrassment and danger in North Africa. The French must allow that we have studied the matter carefully and honestly. They must allow that no opportunity of damaging the enemy, however slight it may seem, should he heglected. Even supposing, as suggested hy the French representa tive, that out premises are incorrect, the French are lia ble to no drawbacks, except possibly sentimental ones, in making the offers suggested, stoce these offers are only conditional on the action of the Arabs against the Turks. (6) Further, if other means fail, it may be desirable to point out to the Frenhfc that, since their refusal to consider sympathetically our suggestions will, in our opinion, consolidate the Arabs and Syrians against the Al lies, the result of which will chiefly be felt in Egypt by us, we must therefore reserve to ourselves the right to en tirely reconsider the whole Syrian question. (Sd). Chas.E.Callwell. D.M.O. (Sd). A.C.Parker, A/&amp;o. Z(jj ^ ( t? Lt-CoionelX l f -$5'7 Decypher,- D# ,7♦Qep # n # . Sir IL licl'iahon (liUdroc) Uovenher 16th, 1915. K • 9 * 3.0, p • Ujinurnhered, . November 16th, .1915, Vi i ‘V i V My previous telegram. Following telegram from Cairo begins; Careful translation has now been done and follow ing gives more fully general sense of second half of letter which is rather vaguely expressed. Begins: Shereef renounces interest in Adana Mersina but insists on retention of Beyrout, Aleppo Vilayets as purely Arab, For trading economic reasons he cannot abandon Irak but is prepared in order to facilitate agreement and in consideration of guarantees offered by nis Majes ty’s Government to u leave under British Administration for a short time those districts now occupied by- British troops against a suitable sum paid as com pensation to Arab Kingdom for period of occupation without prejudice to rights of either party. . Actual agreements with Sheikhs to be respected. As to immediate action Shereef hesitates for fear of adverse opinion of Moslems of opposite camp and still more lest in the event ol peace uniavcurable to Entente Arabs may be loft to facc^Turco-German combina tion. Once they are sure that His Majesty s jGovernmen ^ will effectively support them they are ready tor action. As to British Administrative ofncials there is no heed to mention this question His Majesty’s Government having disclaimed all intention of internal inten^er- enceo (N.B, unless purposely vague Ghercei must oe^ here alluding to Arabia, only) Shereef would jr etor lor himself seclusion from all politics but is forced by- Arabs to his (?present) course of action. salutation. I propose to defer my views on this question until my return to Cairo,r In Any further communica tion or. this subject, please quote No. f8023 S' / I91S and address The Under-Secretary of State Foreign Office, London. T/ie Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the ffnJux y y , and, by direction of the Secretary °f State, transmits herewith copff of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, fflrnJl So ^ &gt; I 9 I 5- Reference to previous correspondence to Letter , Foreign Office: from J ^ Description of Inclosure. Name and Date. VtC. Av. ~j 4^- Subject. (Similar letter sent to iffifet •Lp tfYl S-jff A 14 JEGYPT . Decypher. Sir H,McMahon. November 28th. (Cairo) D, 9.25.p,m. November 28th. Mo. 733. Secret. Since my return to Egypt the more I learn the feeling of the country and the anxiety now (?grow)ing in all classes of Egyptians, the : more convinced I am of the danger we will incur in restricting measures for meet ing Turco-German menace to defence of Egypt itself. If we allow enemy to advance beyond Cilicia we must be prepared for following results. I. Alienation of Arabs to German side. In place of their assistance whether active or passive we will meet active hostility. Turks will at once replace present Sheriff o&gt;f Mecca by man hostile to us and whole position in Arabia will turn to our disadvantage for indefinite period, II. Syria must endeavour to propitiate the enemy,and this will alienate large element in Egypt. III. , New life will bt given to Ottoman Government and Empire which must hence forward be largely German. IV. Baghdad railway will remain in German hands. * V. Serious loss of prestige throughout the East. Egypt is subject and will create situation here which may of above results will prejudice our position throughout the east in very dangerous an-i even vital manner. ■j Effect of number I.coupled with Senoussi's hostility puts against us all important religious influences to which endanger success of defensive operations. Combined effect \U'TVVery similar remarks apply to French possessions and interests i i the East* Incidentally I may point out relative advantages of giving or denying to enemy (1) trade and supplies of so large an area, and (2) a long coast line suitable for submarine bases on our flank.. In view of vital issues at stake I feel it my duty to urge most strongly that alternative policy of meeting Turco-German advance in Cilicia may be re-considered. Success will depend on rapidity of decision and action as time left is very short. In this respect also I fear time available will render preparation of strong de fences which new conditions now demand for defence of Canal and i^ypt ar$ extremely difficult matter. Repeated privately to Lord Kitciiener.Military Secret, 134 i From Viceroy, 30th November 1915. Reference your telegram of 25th instant, No. 3160. Independent examination prior to receipt of Nixon’s 1008/64/0, 26th November, leads us i? a f r 7 ee 1 generally with estimate of Turkish strength at Ctesiphon and In Ann U ^ *, ts rate ^ rowt ^’ exc ept that we prefer to work on the figures 60 000 by end of January, as estimated-by combined War Office and Admiralty staffs in their Memorandum of 19th October Nixon is correct c i ru ^ng factor in rapidity of our concentration is the supply o additional river tiansport, in wlncli respect yon liave received repeated requests from us to hasten rate of supplies, and we are searching India for suitable vessels. In the meantime Nixon must do the best he can with what he has got, winch on a rise of the river and by marching troops from Amara should enable him to get the Lahore and Meerut Divi sions to Kut-el-Amara early in February. As regards his force, Nixon is in eiror in counting upon 34th and 35th Brigades which, aide our telegram of 25th instant, H. 9386, are to be withdrawn when replaced by Lahore and Meerut Divisions as their presence in India is necessary. It follows that Nixon’s force may have to be increased from elsewhere, and in our opinion a safe estimate for the capture and retention of Baghdad under altered conditions involves addition of at least one more division which with the Lahore and Meerut divisions and drafts will make Nixon’s force to five divisions in all. This estimate of five divisions which we consider a safe one is, however, based on the following facts (1) That since 19th October, when the joint Admiralty and War Office Staff drew up their memorandum nothing has occurred or is likely to occur in the near East to prevent Turks sending the full amount of reinforcement then considered possible ; (2) That Russia remains inactive in the Caucasus and north-west Persia. If on the other hand it should be thought that any important modifica tions in above factors have taken place or are likely to do so we consider Nixon will be able to capture and hold Baghdad with four divisions and that it will not be necessary to draw an additional division from the main theatre unless it were freely available owing to the general strategic plan of operations. To regard capture of Baghdad as impossible would be to give up our best means of countering the German intrigues in Persia and Von Der Goltz’s plans for organising Persia and Afghanistan against India and should therefore be dismissed from our calculations. Our success hitherto in Mesopotamia has been main factor which has kept Persia, Afghanistan, and India itself quiet, and to give up the idea of Baghdad would be to relinquish initiative and would result in a further transference eastward of the theatre of war. For these reasons we approve Nixon’s attitude in not discussing the alternative of adopting a defensive attitude as a permanency though he must necessarily remain chiefly on the defensive until his reinforcements can reach the front.'&lt;40 * In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote No. W 2 /1915 and address— The Under-Secretary of State Foreiam Office, —. London. 5 &lt;f6 ccol. I - . !• w \ Q . u ' . — 1 \.J- The Under-Secretary of State for Foreign A fairs presents his compliments to the ej ffarC and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith copy of the nnder-mentiomd paper. Foreign Office, Arv ' .. 9.5 Reference to previous correspondence : Letter to i oreign Office: Description of Inclosure. Name and Date. Subject. j'Ci -M. , i/fynA) *40. u+S. lAwsj. (J (Similar letter sent to ■—— 14 ]rnmim c.*1^:, i a '■'0.148. Secret. 0. &gt;r Mov. - •'*&gt; Sir. j 179240 1th reference to my despatch Ho*141 Secret of the S ultimo* 1 have honour JifiV 26 : 9^5 trariBmit herewith a literal, translation of a fur* ther latter which 1 have received from the Cherlf of Mecca* dated the 5th instant, in reply to mine of the 24th. ultimo. As this translation was only completed and corrected after the official bag had been closed and despatched to you, I have considered it advisable to despatch this document by special messenger to fort laid* I have the honour to be with the highest respect, your *u*st obediunt, uroble aervont &lt;ight honourable Air . trey iart. K.4* tl.i etc*, etc., etc.A^V I ) /i, CfY'/tryw^f\ 'p t i4/r-4 ij hr^Hl-'h * If* , '^# v ^jc‘&gt; • ^-- A £ —v i -U S '-..y ■ •'&amp; f • K? 1 Literal translation In the name of God the Merciful the Compassionate. To His Excellency the most exalted and eminent Minist^ who ie endowed with the highest authority and sound- ness of opinion. May God guide him to do His Mill l I received with great pleisure your honoured letter dated 15th Zul hiji (October Mth 1915) to which I beg to answer as follows ;- (1) In order to facilitate an agreement and to render a service to Islam # and at the same time to avoid all that may cause Islam troubles and hardships - seeing moreover that we have great consideration for the distinguished qualities and dispositions of the Gov ernment of Great Britain - we renounce our insistence on the inclusion of the vilayets of Meksina and Adana In the Arab Kingdom. But the Provinces of Aleppo and Beyrdyand their sea-coasts are purely Arab Provinces add there is no difference between a Moslem and a Christian Arab: they are both descendants of one forefather . We Moslems will follow the footsteps of the Commander of the Faithful-Omar ibn Khattab- and other Khalifas succeeding him, who ordained in the Laws of the Moslem Faith that Moslems should treat the Christians as they treat themselvea. lm 3 Umar ,declared with reference to Christians * they will have the same privileges and submit t# the same duties as ourselves *. They will thus enjoy their civic rights in as much as it accords with the general interest of the whole nation. (2) Ae the Provinces of Irak are parts of the pure Arab Kingdom and were in fact the neat of its Govera- ments^ in the time of All Ibn Abu Talib, an.h in the time of all Khalifs who succeeded him; and as in them began : ,he civilisation -n We know that our lot in this War will he either a success which will guarantee to the Arabs a life be- cowing their cast history t or destruction 5 a Jte atter#t to attain their objects, had it not been for the detent inati m which I see in the Arabs for the attainment of their objects 1 would have preferred to seclude myself 6 : one of the heights of a mountain:- out they # the Arabs , have insisted that I should guide the movement to this end. Kay tod Keep jh. safe and victorious , as we devoutly hope and desire. ( unsigned ) Dated 21 el Hijj 1333 (November 5 1915) H!A In Any further communica tion on this subject, please quote No. iws and address— The Under-Secretary of State Foreign Office, London. y.vt. W~' The Under-Secret ary of State for Foreign Affairs presents, his compliments to the Under-Secretary of State for and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop 4 ^ of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, n , I 9 I 5- Reference to previous correspondence to Letter , Foreign Office: from v “ Description of Inclosure. Name and Date. Subject. f hvo . Af 3, 29 NOVI SI 5 (Similar letter sent to . [ 12 ]—-—- -*•.»» I., 1 No.143 Nov.9,1915 4 1 I hav® the honour to trnmmit herewith copies of a report on the second mission to the Sharif of ecca of the messenger, who is employed in the transmission of confidential communicaticme between the Sirdar end the Bherif. I have the honour to be, with the highest respect, sir, your most obedient, humble servant. for the high CO Right Honourable ir Grey art. .4 etc., etc., etcf — i $ 3 \ ! RMmm of ®mQm uimim qw zLmmmam to tm mmuw mmmm nm mj. of ^g&amp;a . left ouakin on 3n«i Oetober X915 and proceeded in a private dhow to the asichorago referred to in the previous report (iil*a,16) where he found mi agent of the dherif and »ix follower a awaiting Mm. M« waa asked if he had drought anything with him (cash for the guardians of the Hoiy ilaoea and pious offerings) and on his replying in thenegatiwe hut stating that he had an urgent Message to the fiherif he was conducted to Jeddah whence an. urgent telephonic co iraunication (in code) was made to the ilherif oy the latter* s local representative. *0® was then instructed to proceed at once and arrived at fAlF two days later. here he was conducted without delay to the Ohorif to whom he delivered the following v or del message (in Arabic) * In reference to recent com unications and having regard ®to the well-known disposition of Your Highness it is 'reported for Your Highness*s secret information that the 'JSg^ptlM MAH^aAL will leave Hues by sdiip for Jeddah about 'October ?th (h? Mlgada ).as no military escort will 'aecompaiiy the MAhMAJL this year it will be for Your Highness 'to make the requisite arrangements for the landing of tiie •MAIMAl at Jeddah and its subsequent transport to necon**. *0® also handed the Sharif a letter from 111 Bayed Mi 11 * orghani 9 C.h.0. * containing friendly greetings* acknow ledging the safe receipt of the Sheriffs previous letter* and stating that tile earlier oomcaun 1 sstion therein mentioned had apparently miscarried. the Sherif, on receipt of the above message, sent urgent Instructions to his representative at Jeddah in regardto me reception of tiie kAHMAL, Mid directed n to proceed thither and to verify (for the information of those by who* he waa sent) the satisfactory arr&lt;uig«a«ita made and the fact that the Turkish author!tiss were not pemittsd to Intarfovs in me matter. *0** reached Jeddah in time to see the arrival of the &amp;MMM* and its handing over to the custody of me Arab authorities mere. uti return to *iftXW me CHierif handed him a letter (translation attnohad) with instructions that he ahould deliver it to hayed All Kl orgiiaiti, and instructed hi* to deliver the following verbal aossage to the British author- i ties from whom he came $ «» A British War-ship arrived at fiPTAL, an anchorage «{m®rsa) between Jeddah and KAbSGH and eight or nine hours **distant from the former port, and anchored mere* The **sheikh oi mis p&amp;aoe went out to meet me Com^andiixit end *»asked him what he required. The latter said he intended to ^occupy cmd fortify the plaoe* Tnm sheikh asked him on whose •authority he was acting, and was informed that an arrange- •jaent to this effect had been made with a certain I bn •Kreifan. The sheikh reported to the Bherif mis occurrence, * which also came to me ears of the Turkish Governor with •the result mat me latter*s suspicions have bsen roused •and m closer watch set on me coast ^lich formerly had been •left principally to the control of mo Sheriff followers. •The occurrence i® regarded by m© Bh©rif as most inopportune •and liable to eiidaugor his purpose, he begs that sum m •indiscretion may not bo repeated.* *G* men obtained me Sheriff permission to return in order to attend the iairam festivities at Mecca w^iere he remained several days before leaving for the coast* He states mat me relations between the Bherif and other Arabian Chieftains are cordial,and that arj agreement between him md1 .44 )i A A In the hm# ®t c^d, trie Urmlpetent aoa Coiapaeeiafiate. ****■ euppert Vmm who truly h^Uere iu thte world and ‘’the world to eome» (text) the general *t*i# of affaire t more empeoially at the prso^mt time, has made almost all the inhabitant® of the G«*ir&amp; reoognloi? the necessity of thinking about their future prospecto; firstly in regard to the protoetion of the integrity of their religion, and eeoondly that of their tribal honour and life, mis eompels th«* to hold out certain demands among which any be aentionod their definition of many districts which ore inhabitsted by the Arab race, in order to maintain their religious existence, mis is the solo great fundesental reason* men comes the moral reason which is connected with, the holiness of the source of the Faith and the situation of their country* as the principle of existing Governments, whether small or great* is mutual assistance and support, and as the balance of opinion in the country inclines toward© the Government which controls .Egypt for reasons too obvious to need enumeration, therefore we have mixed ourselves with her in this matter, men. the country attain® by the help of God what she desires, this noble Government to which we have alluded will have the right of precedence and the first consideration in regard to everything which me country may require from outside* 1 have already explained the boundary which would enable us to preserve our dominions or existence. To mis the answer was that the discussion of the boundary was or mature. As me matter however is not so, ana as it is most important and necessary to decide this now for fear that when we comeIs futti?# to immimt os hound^rim w# o&amp;osld tmU in Obtaining our dooiros asd the reoult wo«ld thm he quite the r«r«r»o, as the a»tt«r is of euoh Yitmt import Affeetij^ our Tory life «nd oxiotonoo, mor^ore we tseiotod m S®^tisg forthor is regard to theiMi boundariea 00 that we migjat 1‘irot ho ar^i?! to know what the wiewe of that Oorerrsaent w^re and -thus fee guided is our ohoioe of the looser of -the two #rUs and th« easier eours# fey wfeioh to uphold the integrity of the faith and aatiea&amp;Uty as ms more feefitting. Here is a ol«ar proof of th© neoessity for desperate measures in seeking the happiness of attaining the holy efejeot* X refer to the proofamstion issued fey the Ottuemns and whidh was based on the fetwe of their shaikh of Islea, authorising their troops to eat during fee month of Bamadan last in the town of your aneestor (the rrophet) and in Ms holy preeenee. this was based merely on the supposition feat they were prepared for the Jehad, while in fact they wore idying (quietly} • Such an crept act, though but m snail thing makes further explanation in regard to the nobility of fee cause decided upon unnecessary, they haws at least transgressed against God and against your ancestor and his family. We May fee among those feeliswers of whm he said*-* fher# are men who acted in accordance wife their «holy promise to God - some of thm have and some are still * waiting and are making changes* this is what we have united to do. key God help ue end you to hold to our word, lists is the purport of what you wanted to know and 1 have only reproduced it in conformity with-your previous request. We ask fee co-operation of your great seal in the cause of protecting fee honour of fee faith no matter whet fee result of fee present war may fee, because you also have great moral and material interests to safeguard# Our inclinations, which you wife to understand, are confinedwithin thi&amp; ©ircXt and 1 “Mr© no doyht # honourable brother, that you ®r© w©U aware of this and that t hme no ©uT*biti«me whatever for great name® or title©* ?ou asked me, ny dear friend, mey God he with you f to ©arplain to yets what we retire* Owr firot rm*ixmmt9 are that Qod My protect yon frc« every mil end give yonalway© otrongth and good health* I alto with to be guided by your ideat with regard to our aformentioned friend© who have full , oontrol of tliw country and no to whether they think of any j necessity to aafcs siodifieatlona in owr dewaads to the boundarieo that have h«en doeorited. If so this will he j annoying, psrUculF.rly to the Avnfce and very likely it will | affect all the l ahanmedane and ohlige th« to meet events, no Matter whence they ewe, with bravery and determination at the outstart. ; ^h«y will then bwoo^o positive that the mu**- for making such difficulties is th# intention to mtexm&amp;mmt* Urn .Arab© and destroy their faith and unity* l do not think in this cast that there i© any mm who dost not know that a General Gall { to the J'ehad ) in the ears of the Moham^adan world will differ from the call of fh© ottomans, tlhe Osvsrnasnt to which X am referring could avoid the outcome of the effect produced by ouch a ©tat© of affairs, especially owing to the presence of a tmn like yourself who allows no reason for blame in the cause of God* l have very strong end decided hopes that I am only stating in this sentence whet is absolutely true with the greatest sincerity. the second question is that we shell stand in need of funds partly to be used for the preliminary expenses and the greater portion to be retained until the time when with God 1 © help the whole eoheme is taken effectively in hand. A* regard© the arms, we have no need of the-, as this mightn % n&amp;ii&amp;e 9m&gt;G wm®®mmry disturbance and divulge tbe ecJi^e before it has matured# If this however wore possible there ia no objection end we must b® prepared for it. We raise redoubled prayers to 0od from the death of our hm*%* and with sincerity to defend the law of your ancestor and maintain his inspiration and his holy tomb, fher# is no doubt that Ood would be our (great defender and supporter. lliis is the gist of what 1 wish to inform you and 1 Insist on hoping that you will beep it very secret end act with the utmost wisdom and Quietness. 1 $m depending on your servant other (messenger) and mm taking no/steps in my dealing*: with our friends err opt through you. 1 am confining all esmmuni* cations and dealings to you. X have full trust in God and in the truth of your faith. May God keep you in his good keeping and protect both ourselves and you and give m good fortune. Pe&amp;ee be upon you and the ^erey of God and Bis Blot sing. ( unsigned * ho date. Envelope sealed with a private seal of the chsrif Hussein of ocas )*n mmm'kA'sim m A mm on mmmmrm . { mclomul with l etter ) • k«r*iaa (ami) &amp;&amp;m&amp; (districts) to the parallel, on which, lies Killis, Mrojik, Urfa, kardin, ^idiat, 0#sirst iil mnxim, to th« frontier of Persia. on the iSast th« torsi an frontier to th© Oulf of Basra (and) thsnoo to the Indian hceaa * exclusive of Men. On the South the Mod Sea • on the West the iediterranean• Tim greatest proof that the inhabitants of this (?) place are united is (afforded By) the revolt of the MABHHAh (Keroela) natives of Irak which (revolt) was however premature*CONFIDENTIAL. u I EGYPT Sir E. McMahon to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received June 30, 5'30 p.m.) Ramleh, June 30, 1915. (No. 306.) R. (June 39, 2*20 p.m.) YOUR telegram No. 380 of 26th June. Nothing in the shape of formal proclamation has been issued. Purport of jour telegram No. 173 of 14th April was communicated privately in certain quarters of Egypt and the Soudan, but no public announcement, as authorised in your telegram No. 262 of 20th May, has yet been made in either country. An unsigned printed leaflet in Arabic has been distributed, as authorised in your telegram No. 274 of 21st May, on coast of Hedjaz by such aeroplanes and trading vessels as have been able to go there. It has not been distributed in the Soudan, but a copy was sent to Senoussi. It was in the following terms :— “ To the people of Arabia : “ It is already known to you that we, the English, went to war with Germany because she attacked, without any provocation, small States upon her borders whose independence she had solemnly sworn to guarantee. “ You also know that Germany, being hard pressed, cunningly induced the Turkish Government to assist her. This she effected by lavish expenditure of gold and by lying promises. Her real object was to obtain a proclamation by the Sultan of Turkey of a Jehad against ourselves and our Allies; for under the protection of our Empire are many millions of Mahommedans, of whom thousands are now actually fighting in our armies, and Germany hoped that they would be induced to attack us and so afford her help. Surely every true Mahommedan must regard with loathing this cynical employment of his religion as an instrument to be used by a foreign Power for the furtherance of its own selfish ambitions. “ Mahommedan subjects of British Empire and of France, Russia, and her Allies have shown their view of the matter by supplying thousands upon thousands of troops to help us in fighting against the Turks and their deceivers, and even the more honourable of the Turks must realise the baseness of what has been done. “ Perhaps, however, there are those amongst you who ask what may be our intentions after the war -is over. “ Lest there be any misunderstanding, let the following be known :—- “ The Government of His Majesty the King of England and Emperor of India has declared when this war ends it shall be laid down in the terms of peace, as a necessary condition, that Arabian peninsula and its Mahommedan holy places shall remain independent. We shall not annex one foot of land in it, nor suffer any other Power to do so. Your independence of all foreign control is thus assured, and with such guarantees the lands of Arabia will, please God, return along the paths of freedom to their ancient prosperity. Surely this is sufficient. Certain Arab chiefs have already assured us of their desire to be rid of Turks, and some are assisting our troops with their swords. “ To those of you who wish us well, but are perhaps afraid to show their feelings, we say: ‘ Have no' distrust of us; wait for a favourable opportunity, and, when it comes, shake off the oppressor s yoke, and we will support you to the full extent of our ability, and will, with God’s help, make you a truly independent people/ “ But it must be with respect to your religion that you chiefly wish to know our attitude. [780-11]“ The religion of Islam, as history proves, will always be scrupulously respected by the British Government, and it is for this very reason that in the past we have befriended and assisted the Sultan of Turkey. Now that his venal Ministers have induced him to forget all gratitude and attack us that were his filends, he must accept ^ the consequences but our policy of respect and^ friendliness towards Islam remains' unchanged. The latest proot ot this is that we wished to assist the inhabitants of the Holy Cities and pilgrims with gifts of corn ; but German and Turkish officers seized the corn on its arrival at Jeddah, and thus forced us to cease sending corn for our enemies to [? group omitted] while the poor go hungry. u In spite of this, His Majesty’s Government, having heard that pilgrims and innocent inhabitants are suffering grievously from want of food, and moved by compas sion and their continual friendship towards the Arabs, have now decided once more to allow food to be brought in by sea to Jeddah, and it will be for the Arabs themselves to ensure that this food is used for sustenance of themselves, and theirs to prevent its being seized by those who act contrary to the usages of [? war] and seek to take bread out of the mouths of the hungry.”In Any further communica tion or. this subject, please quote 'Vv.N'fr i No. /I9I5 and address— The Under-Secretary of State Foreign Office, London. t pCf-h c ^-f The Under-Secretary of State for Foreign A fairs presents his compliments to the A JrJhit and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop ^ of the under-mentioned paper J Foreign Office, fUry. Za 1/1 I 9 I 5' Reference to previous correspondence: Letter to from Foreign Office: Description of Inclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Dv /V. JiLfdt&amp;'Lvv*. 7 ^ 4 . -j&gt;-] ^ py 'Similar letter sent to/o. FILi;S ONLY . Decyplier bir ii. i.acLialion (Cairo) Nov. 20th. D. 1. 0 am November 21st. h. 12.35 pm November 21st. Me. 707. Pollovanp: from Sir Li. Sykes for D.M.O. No. 19. !, Your private letter of November 5th just received. Previous to getting it I saw Faruki and anticipating French difficulty discussed the situation v/ith him with that in view. Following is best I could got but seems to me to meet the situation both with regard to France and Great Britain. Arabs would agree to accept as approximate northern frontier Alexandretta Aintab Birijik Urfa Midiat Zakhc Kowanduz. Arabs would agree to convention with France granting her monopoly of all concessionary enter prise in Syria and Palestine, Syria being defined as' bounded by hupimates as far south as Deir Zor and from there to Deraa and along Hedjaz hailway to Iv.-aan. Hedjaz Bailway as far South as Amman could be sold to French concessionaire. Arabs would further agree to employment of noiie but Frenchmen as advisers and European employes in tins area. Note® Arabs will not (? undertake to) employ Europeans if they can do without them but Faruki points out this stipulation is to avoid any shadow of control. Arabs would agree to ail French Educational establishments having special recognition in this area. Arabs would agree to identical convention with Great Britain with regard to remainder of greater Arabia viz ir-sk and Jazirah and Northern Mesopotamia. Further Arabs would mmmwould agree to any territority North of greater Arabian Frontier being French possessions under Frencn flag, Arabs would agree to Basrah town andail cultivated lands to- the south being British territory, Arabs would be prepared to make a treaty with Entente lowers, 1„ Undertaking on their part to have no dealings with Turkey Germany or Austria for period of 15 years. 2. On the part of Entente powers to guarantee to protest independence of the Arabs, Further a treaty of alliance wltu Entente Powers giving them freedom of movement in greater Arabia and use of hallways in Arabian area for duration a- of the war. Entente troops in Arab territories to be on same footing as British troops in Flanders. Entente troops to evacuate territories on cessation of hostilities. Faruki insisted that this was dependent on Entente landing troops at a point between Lerslna and Alexandria and making good Arnanus Pass or Cilician gates, he nil u.mi stipulated that Sherif should not take action until this 3 T r&gt; f h nt, 971 V Ot&gt; YlC V COUrS0 IS Ollt Of hj tj been clone. I ^reo ona^ the question and that to call on Sherif or Arabs to take action until we had made above mentioned passes secure would be impossible. Faruki also urged necessity for inrnediate adequate action in the Gulf of nlexandretta adding that if Entente did not take this opportunity Germans would forestall tnen and once Turks or Germans got into Syria Arabs would in their own interests be obliged to reconsider . + t oirrp t/hat there can be . . , . rp^.-y-t vrnr r.\. : r \ 1)9,1' t JL bui- d u ui situation,, lei w ° no doubt of Arabs merely troubling Eurks in advances onthe canal. If we allow lurks into Syria Arabs will side with them in order to obtain special consideration, Germans have already suggested Idea of Turko - Arabia on the same lines as Austria Hungary, I will give observations on less important aspects in further telegram, heanwhile I am convinced of necessity for efficient action at earliest possible moment to enable Arabs to move.f.ik:b QNiy . Decypner t Sir H. McMahon (Cairo) Novemher 21st. D. 7„15 p c m e Ho 11,&gt; 15 p*rtu , November 21st 1915. No. 70S Following lor D M.O* from Sir Mo Sykes No. 20:- Pending a continuation of my telegram No. 19 on hy po thesis that parukis interview is basis of our arrange ments with Arabs, I submit:- (i)vWith regard to France and Arabs our task' is to get Arabs to concede as much as possible to French and to get our Ha if fa Outlet and Palestine included in our spnere of enterprise in the form of French concession to us„ Thus we smooth the way for prance with Syrians and In the matter where Prance has s( tradin^) m ^terest, deal directly with her. Note. Arabs will always welcome any extension of our sphere of enterprise, (2) hath regard to Arabia proper I do not consider proposed Arab movement affects our position with regard to) various Gulf and Fed Sea interests. Gulf and Aden treaties wM hold good and I am confident that suzer ainty of She reef in Arabia proper will be in practice purely Honorary, (3) .with regard to our position in Irak, our estab lishment of civilian G overnraent must hold for duration of the war and we should stipulate for this.Bagdad and Basrah provinces are divided from Arabia, by schism. and are too disorderly and mwourcus for newborn state to govern. When the time for evacuation comes the Shereef { s Government will have to face the Shiah and Kerbela question and I anticipate will be glad enough to^toget us to run the administration for them for some time to come in order to get revenue, Arab nationalism has little inf&amp;uenoo and the Mhalifate none south of Bag dad in the cultivated ar€a 0 (4) c I submit for the strategical and political consideration of India th&amp;t the suggested Arab state cannot become a formidable power in itse-lf so long as it is protacted from Gorman and Turkish influence by Prance and ourselves, I anticipate that in the event of our giving the Arabs their csportunity that matters will shape them selves as follows;- influx of trade and money owing to opening of Syrian ports will keep things quiet in Syria and Palestine, and Government will be carried on on 'Turkish formulas with local personnel. Bagdad and Basrah provinces will continue to accept our provisional rule without demur. Governments of Mosul and urfa will be dis orderly and Arab Stats will probably have to ask for our assistance. Arabs of northern Arabia proper will fight indecisively among thanselves. (o)&lt;&gt; In the event of our letting this opportunity go Arabs in syriaiand northern Mesopotamia will, i be lieve, fall in with the Turks in order to get the beet terms for nationalist aspirations from those whom they would then regard as certain winners.From Secretary of State to Viceroy, Foreign Department, 1 November 1915. Foreign Secret. My telegram dated 18th November. Arabia. Following from Cairo :— ^ “ Careful translation has now been done, and following gives more fully general sense of second half of letter which is rather vaguely expressed. Shereel renounces interest in Adana Mersina, hut insists on retention of Beyrout, Aleppo Vilayets as purely Arab. For trading economic reasons he cannot abandon Irak, but is prepared in order to facilitate agreement, and in consideration of guarantees offered by His Majesty’s Government to ‘leave under British Administration for a short time those districts now occupied by British troops against a suitable sum paid as compensation to Arab Kingdom for period of occupation ’ without prejudice to rights of either party. Actual agreements with Sheikhs to be respected. ' 1 ^s to immediate action Shereef hesitates for fear of adverse opinion of Moslems of opposite camp, and still more lest in the event of peace un favourable to Entente, Arabs may be leit to face I urco-German combination. Once they are sure that His Majesty’s Government will effectively support them they are ready for action. “ ‘As to British Administrative officials there is no need to mention this question^ His Majesty’s Government having disclaimed all intention of internal interference. (N.B. Unless purposely vague Shereef must be heie alluding to Arabia only.) ShereeJ would prefer for himsell seclusion from all politics, but is forced bv Arabs to ids (? present) course of action.’ ”I FOREIGN SECRET TELEGRAMS, Secret Department, From Secretary of State to Viceroy, Foreign Department, \ Sth November 1915. Foreign Secret. Your telegram dated Ilth instant. Arab negotiations, hollowing from Cairo : — “ Messenger with letter from Sherif lias arrived. Letter is long, and requires careful translation to ascertain full meaning, but main points are as follows :— “ First, he agrees to exclusion of Mersina and Minisandria (sic ? Alexan- dretta). “ Secondly, he maintains that vilayets of Beirut and Aleppo are Arab and should be under Arab Mohammedan (lovernment. Thirdly, he maintains that Mesopotamia is also Arab, but, as Great Britain has special interests there, it may be left out of discussion for the present. Mean while he asks for subsidy for what he terms ‘ the Arab Kingdom.’ “ Fourthly, he expresses fear lest a European peace should leave Arabs at the mercy of Turks, and wishes Great Britain to bind herself not to abandon Arabs. “On these four conditions they will come in at once. “ Messenger states feeling amongst Arabs is very favourable to us. “ Sherif impressed on him readiness and intention of Arabs to begin work at once. Sherif’s son, Abdulla, has returned from Nejd bringing several chiefs whom he detached from Ben Rashids. Oppenheim is said to have returned to Syria having been expelled from Medina. Faisal, son of Sherif, has left Mecca and is negotiating with Arab chiefs on behalf of his father.” I lease repeat to Nixon paragraph regarding Mesopotamia, adding that substance of his telegram of 14th November, No. 358, has been communi cated to McMahon.EGYPTr Cypher Telegram to Sir Hr McMahon (Cairo) Foreign Office, November 17thc 1915c lOrOcp.mc NOc 887. Your telegram of 16thc Novemberc I will await your views on the last proposals of the'Shereefr You will of course bear carefully in mind the necessity of avoiding all possibility of being involved in any in questions concerning the Khalifate.n.evfo q ) ^xLl. 1^3 Oi^LY . er telo^am uo Sir II. r cl ahon (Cairo) Foreign Office November 20th. 11.20 ,o o 901 : 5ecrot „ Ch Please see G.O. C’s telegram to Lord Kitchener No t 2122 L of November 4th. Lotfullah Bey has submitted scheme wnicii amounts to British Protectorate of Byria, Cilicia and Palestine with a Christian Prince, and an Arab Monarchy with British Advisers at Baghdad under Lx-Khedive who would nomin roe Khal if a. Scheme is clearly irresponsible and conflicts with out present line of negotiations with Arabs, but, ifand when latter come to anything Lotfullah may be useful with his fellow*-Christians in Syria, He has therefore been told verbally that we much appreciate the importance of his proposals which will need careful consideration and that he should, meanwhile proceed to Egypt which must in any case be the centre for any movement such as he proposes. He is returning to Egypt via Switzerland, where he will ho doubt see ex-Khedive, and an unobtrusive watch should be kept over him when ho returns to Egypt. &lt;K). a- ft t\ u ] In Any further communica tion on this subject, please quote No. nuC3s /1915 and address— The Under-Secretary of State Foreign Office, London. . L 4 9 q q 4 i L.., il v..&gt; The Under Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the f A d riAScQ. and } by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop f of the under-menfioned paper. Foreign Office, ffWutAAAjfti d{ 1 ' , I 9 I S- deference to previous correspondence V n Office Letter , Fo from Description of Inclosure. Name and Date. Subject. /f tl^C , Vet. m. lot. xLff - / / '422 NOVI935 IT' 'h. Similar letter sent toEGYPT . _ ,i r- L5 J Decypher, sir H. McMahon (Cairo) Noveraher 19th, D . 8.55 November 19th 1915. h. 10 p.m., No. 706. Following for D.M.O. from Sir M. , Sykes No, 18. 'I am waiting here for an opportunity of seeing General Officer Commanding and the High Commissioner in accordance with your instructions. By the favour of Sof M- . ffi 1 . Cneetharn I have seen correspondence relating to Arab movement and Sheriff. Two difficulties strike me. (a) Arab want of confidence in our might;(b) dif ficulty of making arrangements with Arabs, inoffen sive to French susceptibiliity based on financial interests and historical sentiment. I suggest as a means of coping with the diffi culty (a);- that we blockade Ciliefan Gates, or deny Turkey access to Syria vid Adana plain as the first step, as the second step the occupation of the line Aintab, Birljik, Suverek^Diarbekir, and establish touch with Russians while Turkish and German, masses are immobilized by Anatolian and Armenian winter snow. leaving Arabs to do as they please south of this line. Details of this scheme and quantity of troops required should reach you by November 24th. Difficulty (b) could be coped with as follows; Entente to agree with Arabs to recognise, respect and protect Arab provisional Government, or Governments in the vilayets of Beyrout, Aleppo, Damascus, Jerusalem and Hedjaz and the sandjak of Dersor Urfa during the warwar. Guaiantee oi abovo ocreas as 'bliG irinjjirjjTi ol* i - dGpendGnt Arab territory after the war, Arabs to ea- gaye not to grant concessions directly or iirarcctly to financial groups of Central powers for the period of 25 years, nor to establish diplomatic relations with them for a period of ten years. Great Britain, Kussia, and Italy go engage not to obtain concessions in vilayets of Aleppo, Beyrout, Damascus, and the Bandjak of Urfa without cpproval of the French Government and to i ecognise the spirit of previous agreements between French Government and the Ottoman Government with regard to educational establishments in the same area in sug gested Arab independent state or states. I further suggest that vilayets of Bagdad and Basrah are in capable of self-government and a new and weak state coulc not administer them owing to Shiah and Sunni dissensions We might agree with Arabs to administer these provinces on their behalf allocating certain revenues to their exchequer or exchequer(?s) (this corresponding to their demand for subsidy)and further agreeing that in the event of populations of vilayets of Bagdad and Basrah not producing a sufficient number for administrative personal under British supervision„ deficit will be •u ' made good from Arab State o% states, I make these suggestions because I believe the situation is critical. I feel that Arab nationalism as suen presents no danger to India now or in future un less we confine ourselves to the canal defensive andlet Turk and German masses assemble in Syria and northern Mesopotamia and re-establish their prestige and so work a real Jehad with Arab support. This would entail strong repercussion in north Africa, both French and Italian, as well as in Persia the Caucasus, and Afghanistan, eventually engrossing a larger force of entente troops under less favourable circumstances than at present. I submit that Russia, Italy, and France are all directly affected by this situation. At present Arabs are anti-Turk, and Taurus and Armenian snow hampers our enony’s movements. I therefore be lieve now is our chance of foiling German plan involving all entente powers in defensive operations against Islam.I p Telegram frorn'R^sldent at Aden Dated 20th* November 1915* 145 A.P. There is documentary evidence to show that the Sheriff of Mecca has assisted Turks in a letter from Ahmad gsraot ftnraxx Tewfik (Commander of 7th Yemen Arm# Corps at Sanaa) to Hassan Izzat Bey Bimbashi, Commanding 1st Battalion 115th Regiment at Loheiyah, found on latter which (? when) captured en route by sea to Jeddah. The letter distinctly tells Hassan Izzat that the Sheriff had received and held in charge money intended for Ahmad TewfiMT’s^also that Sheriff would arrange for safe transmission of money to destinations in Asir and Yemen and that Hassgn Izzat was to act in accordance as the Sheriff directed. Originals of the correspondence are with G.O.C*,Egypt. Addressed to the S.of S. and repeated to Foreign Dept., G-ovt. of India. comnanaT v'irl 1 O (Copy) J 8 r a r. - P vA ^ &amp; r« &amp;1) i 4 Ct iiu.-Juk 0 —I LD r— CD 00 &gt;i CCS &lt;J {-■ cc o . w CO i__ o o . ° D3 O u* Tror — Thi.e General. Officer Corouaidin^ Ttirce W D' 3 BasraH, Zo TBe Secretary to the G-overmient of India ^ in the Foreign and Political Department, Sir-la. (repeated to Chief of the General Staff). No. 1394 I .Gf. Bated ti e 14th (and reed. the 15th) October 191 dL Please refer to your tel^yr&amp;i, 1034 S.. to Sir Percy Cox. The Government of India must judge for theriselves as to the extent to which the feelings of Indian Folaiaedan are likely to be adversely affected by the idea of the capture of Baghdad and of the need for reassuring it, but there are several reason. th« issue of a procl.amation on the lines suggested would be inconvenient for the Military point of view on the following grounds (l) /fter a successful action at Ctesirhon it is not unlikely possible that I migot have to fight again between there and F, J4ad or even at BaJ dad itself, so that until Taj dad is. occurded for certain I would prefer that no proclamation should be issued. In fact until Government of India have been informed of what has actually taken place and so are in a position to issue notification to prepare public opinio} I should prefer their awaiting fnit acoopp! i and the suppression of the news of our reach!ng Bap^idad• (2) It is probable tl'at any puclic annou■ u;e- went made by us m advance ti. at our ojoo^. s wouxu unaer no circumstances boirbard specific shrines, woula oe taeen advanuage of hr r the eneiy to occupy sucli places with troops or to place batteries under cover of the shrines of even to fire info ''rem themselves, and accuse our troops of doing so. ( 3 ) if a reference is made to British ladies in any proclamation oq j Yfhich might be issued here this right eP-ve - u rrs a, hii!-, m) ^ o ^ n n 4 fc—.1 remove tljem. On the whole I would recommend flat copy of the circular letter which I communicated to Chief of the General Staff in mw telegram No. 1341 of October 11th. and vi.icl ^ iet/ueci to the tribal Sheikhs should now be given ly the e&lt;n.un of( i2fyj India to the Press with a view to rrejare the rublio Kind and ttat the issue of tie r reposed proclacation should await the s ecre t advance and definite news that the occupation ’as heen o-ctuai ij aCj.ieved when a notification refer in, to shrines etc. A ^ could 'be issued with greater confidence. Fvery precaution will of course he taken should an odvan on Baghdad he undertaken to avoid injuring the tor,Is and shrines mentioned in your 1034 of 10th October, /my other action which might have a tendency to unnecessarily offend the feelings either of the inhabitants or of our own Mohaumadan troops would also be carefully avoided. Mr f r fr-M[P 4151] 7 FOREIGN SECRET TELEGRAMS, Secret Department, From Viceroy, 11th November 1915. Foreign Secret. Arabia. Your telegram 8th November. We find nothing in McMahon’s telegram of 5th November to palliate in any way position he has brought about, and fact remains that althugh he could apparently, without imperilling the negotiations, safeguard other interests at Alexandretta, Mersina and Syria, he yet found it necessary to guarantee to Arabs the rendition of territories in Mesopotamia won by our arms in face not only of Turkish but also of Arab opposition, without which Turks alone would have been of small account. Moreover, from information received from Sir Reginald Wingate, it appears that leaders in Egypt were quite ready to recognise as a necessity the incorporation of certain portions ofMesopotamia in the British Empire and would not oppose it. Further, it need hardly be pointed out that financing of large irrigation schemes by which the prosperity of Mesopotamia is enhanced a hundredfold is not likely to be encouraged by fact of the creation of an Arab State and administration, and the whole country would be likely to lapse into a worse condition than under Turkish rule and be a source of danger to British political and commercial interests. The possession of Basra is in our opinion essential for the protection of Abadan and the security of our interests in oil-fields. We are still in dark as to actual quid pro quo to be given by Arabs in return for those sweeping assurances, but trust it may be of sufficiently 7 definite character to enable us, if Arabs fail to perform their part, to repudiate those assurances—at any rate as far as Mesopotamia is concerned. As regards proclamation we agree that in view of chaotic position created by McMahon’s assurances it will be best if General Nixon on occupation of Bagdad issued no proclamation at all except perhaps a formal notice calling upon civil population to acquiesce quietly in our occupation, and assuring them, should they do so, their persons, property, and religion will be scrupulously respected. In India we propose, as soon as Bagdad is actually occupied, to suppress news for day or two, and to publish following proclamation :—“ [R.] His Majesty’s Government have authorised General Nixon to advance on Bagdad, his forces having once more defeated Turkish opposition on Tigris in vicinity of Suliman Pak. Not only for military reasons is this advance necessary, but in order to relieve British ladies and British Indian subjects who, contrary to usage of civilised war, have been detained at Bagdad ; and in order to break up a focus of German intrigue in middle East. His Majesty’s Government, however, desire that it should be clearly understood that stringent orders have been issued that every precaution should be taken to prevent sacred shrine of Sheikh Abdul Qadir, Gilani, and the other tombs and shrines in the vicinity 7 , from being in any way even accidentally damaged in course of the operations, in accordance with their unswerving policy of respecting the sacred places of Islam and the susceptibilities of the Moslem community ; and they wish it clearly to be understood that in regard to all other Holy Places in Mesopotamia, this policy^ has been and will be scrupulously^ followed, and that no obstacle whatever will be placed in way of Imams, Ulemas, Mujtahids and other religious persons following freely and as usual their ordinary religious practices, after occupation of Bagdad.”F.O.Pb, B20/3/483 director of Military Operations presents , &gt; nis compliments to the Under Secretary of State, and hegs to state with reference to India Office letter P.4223 of November 17th, that there is no objection on the part of the Army Council to the India Office repeating to the Government of India, Foreign Department, Sir M. Sykes 1 s telegram No.16 of 23rd October regarding lue future of Mesopotamia, copy of which is herewith enclosed. sir M. Sykes is on his way home and considerable delay might be involved in asking him to repeat the telegram as suggested. The Under Secretary of State India Office.(B348) 25 10/15 H&amp;S 1097-4 wo SECRET. From Sir Mark Sykes, M.P., to War Office. (No- 16.) OO J ^ X , tt p 23rd October, 1915, 7.45 p.m. . Have conferred with Sir P. Cox and Army Commander, Force D, on the report of the Committee on Asiatic Turkey. Following is their opinion P the Anatolfo ^ the retenti ° n ° f the Turkish Em P ire Asia beyond the Anatolia Peninsula would be m opposition to our highest interest and leave us in a wh'fhT fr'r.r the ^ ^ be contrary to' _hich ve entered the war, see Prime Minister’s speech at Guildhall and the first desideratum in the report. It is essential that German trade establishments industrial south P of e the n ]h C T merC1 / al VentUreS sh ? ul . d ^ be Permanently excluded from the area south of the line Acre—(one group undecipherable) Wanduz. As the only guarantee of the security m the Persian Gulf and Mesopotamia Course A, Map 11 I/the only satisfactory solution offered m the report. A natural corollary to this scheme is that Arabia as a whole should be recognized as within our sphere of influence ^ il’ t WOUl i . f ntra JP t0 British interests that the present tract of the Baghdad Tt ° U hrl i e -R C ° r f ° rn ; P ar&gt;t tbe M eso P°tamia railway system, or that the ferred d \o R the W Eh^ P p y T*™ 116 ’ 6Ven thoU S h the contro l should be trans- terred to the Entente Powers, as for many years to come through communication afdTr^tegt retonr 136 8h ° Uld ^ aS Hmited aS l J ° Ssible ’ both for P 01 ^- 1 3. Railway communication under British control between Irak and the Mediter ranean is important and desirable, but it is not essential to defence of Irak which if held alone, can be supported by the Red Sea and the Persian Gulf. If, therefore the coiisti iiction of a R'dish comrollcd line between Baghdad and a Mediterranean’port tkm’of b r e a £ bStrUCted b y future political circumstances, this would not forbid our reten- t lu® vf enC ! and ad 'poyi'ation of Irak should be an Imperial responsibility. miite ship t, Vlla p tS f Ba s hdad and Basrah one® they are formally under our control are quite able to make a large proportionate contribution to their own defence, both in men to thTMosul pro “nee 6 'P 6 ™' 06 ’ 1 ^ 8a ^ that this et l uall y -PP 1 - 6. The formation of an autonomous state in Irak seems to be impossible owing to the want of any local ruling family or cohesion of political party with sufficient prestige or capacity to assume the government. ^ ^ 7. The riparian population and semi-nomads in the area at present under our control show an increased inclination to settle down gradually to agriculture and ; *f* 10n ’ and the T ? nl 7 aw ft settled government to do so on a larger scale. Once tt ed government is introduced there is every reason to believe that the existing population will increase rapidly. ^ 8. The collection of revenue and taxes in all the areas which we effectively dominate is essential as it confirms and continues the tradition of settled government and prevents disorder which would degenerate into anarchy. r i 9 ' 11 - S ad 7 isadle that , a11 matters primarily connected with the Shiah shrines of ra (u their belongings either financial or administrative, should be left entirely in the hands of the religious hierarchy. J 10. With regard to Arabia and the Persian Gulf, from the point of view of our present position m Irak it is desirable that our policy should be to protect rabia as a whole from without, leaving each situation to develop on its own lines from rT^ 1 ^ n® pref T able t0 regard the Sherif of Mecca &gt; if he shobdd assume the Ahahphate, as an ally, rather than as a protege like the Sheikh of Koweit. about it the^etter^ Callphate seems to ar0llse little interest in ^ak and the less said ] to India 26 NOV 1915^r-., r r 7 r* V. / £ v’V ^ v tr ; ^ ^ 1 «/ W [This Do cu ment is the Property of His Britaimic Majesty’s Government , and should be returned to the Foreign Office when done with unless required for official useJ (171785) / ^ . % l „ ■ ti&gt; ') i uj^.a ' - v *-- 3 i / .. i rujiSIA. ( VV PO LITICiVL . Cypher telegram to Mr. Marling (Teheran) Foreign Office Movember 17th. 11. No.. 396 (K) . r t (jL 4, A • • -• '• *• • -• proclamation v?hich v?ill ho issued in India on fall of Baghdad v/ill contain folloidng assurances (H) ! 'Hi s Majesty’s Government desire that i u should do clearly understood that sti'ingent orders have 'been that every precaution should he taken to prevent sacreo. shrine of Shehkh Ahdul Nadir, Gilani, ana ohe ounei tombs and slirines in tne vicinity froti oeing in any v.oy even accidentally damaged m course oi one ope-ratiO:.i&amp;, in accordance vith their unswerving policy of respecting the sacred places of Islam and the sosiceptibill oles Oi the Moslem community; and they uish it clearly to be understood that in 1 ’egard to ill other Holy places in Mesopotamia this policy has been and will oe scrupulously followed and that no obstacle v;hatever will be placed in way of Imams, Ulemas, Mujtahids and other religious persons following freely and as usual their ordinary religious practices after occupation of Baghdad .(end of I K.. You should issue analogous communiQue on being officially informed of fall of Baghdad.14 /+22 D In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote *o.hZ4i(, No. and address— /I9I5 f «•■ * ■- i' *' ■- 1 ' ' , The Under-Secretary of State Foreign Office, London. n r\ ' V . - ./'■ Tke Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the ca/ tls *9 rUtcjx. and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop u^o of the nnder-mentioncd paperS. Foreign Office, &lt;A&lt;rfu~iA&gt;z&lt; /8^ - ^ts- Reference to previous correspondence Letter J rQm Foreign Office Description of Inclosure. Am. Name and Date. a. j Subject. /i A c ruiC^i. d/jsryi pj At . I (Similar letter sent toEGYPT r Cypher Telegram to Sir Hr McMahon (Cairo) Foreign Office, November 17thc 1915 P lOrOrp.r:^ NOc 887• Your telegram of 16thc Novemhere I will await your views on the last proposals o the Shereefr You will of course oear carefully in mind the necessity of avoiding all possibility of being involved in any lipl questions concerning the Khalifate.14 (Zl In any farther communica tion on this subject, please quote and address— The Under-Secretary of State Foreign Office, London. The Under-Secretary of State for Foreign A {fairs presents his compliments to the pe and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop f of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, JUm. tj iY ^ , I 9 I 5- Reference to previous correspondence: Letter ^ rom Foreign Office: ( ~J2. 0 22 f Description of Inclosure. Name and Date. V&amp;e.rLo. ylw - 16 Subject. a l r (Similar letter sent to\ i (W / r~ 1 V s ^ a ** Sir T T &gt;- ir- Decypher. D. 7-,0.p-,rr, ^ i * , A McMahon (Mudrbs) ' Hovomher 16th. 1915 H* 9*20‘tPt»r.i. Unnurnhored. November 16th. 1915 Cfl ^ 6 My previous telegram,*. Following telegram from. Cairo begins: jlfareful translation has now been done and follow ing gives more fully general sense of second half of letter which is rather vaguely expressed. Begins; Shereef renounces interest in Adana Mersina but insists on retention of Beyrout, Aleppo Vilayets as purely Arab. For trading economic reasons he cannot abandon Irak but is prepared in order to facilitate agreement and in consideration of guarantees offered by His Majes ty’s Government to 11 leave under British Administration for a short time those districts now occupied by British troops against a suitable sum paid as com pensation to Arab Kingdom for period of occupation' without prejudice to rights of either party. Actual agreements with Sheikhs to be respected n As to immediate action Shereef hesitates for fear of adverse opinion of Moslems of opposite camp and still more lest in the event of peace unfavourable to Entente Arabs may bo left to face Turco-German combina tion. once they arc sure that His Majesty’s Government will effectively support them they are ready tor action. As to British Administrative officials there is no heed to mention this question His Majesty’s Government having disclaimed all intention of internal interfer ence. (N.B. unless purposely vague shoreof must be here alluding to Arabia only) Shereef would^prefer for himself seclusion from anil politics but is forced by Arabs to his (?present) course of action.] Salutation. I propose to defer my views on this question until my return to Cairo.4^ Telegram from the Viceroy, Dated the 16th November 1915* ? 4 tiwcy wit&amp;l Si 0 Foreign, secret* We have received from G-eneral Nixon a telegram regarding the future of Mesopotamia, in which he refers us to Sir Mark Sykes 1 No.16 of October 23rd to D.M.O*, War Office, in which his own and Cox* views were coinmunicated. We have received no copy of Sykes* No.16 of October 23rd and should be obliged if you could obtain and communicate the gist of its contents to us. Otherwise this procedure is likely to lead to confusion.(172022/15) Secret and Iny ne diat e. S i r: - I &gt; Foreign Office, r it,, * % i .v November 16th, 1915 C-O - tr 2*3 NOV 1915 .iiJi reference to your letter P. 4024 of the 6th in stant, relative to the assurances given by His Majesty’s High Commissioner for Egypt to the Grand Sherif of Mecca, t regarding the future policy of His Majesty's Government towards the Arab question, I am directed by Secretary Sir Eo-'iiai a urey to transmit to you herewith a copy of a tele gram which he has despatched to Sir H. McMahon, embodvin* jii© obsei vaoions of fno General Officer Co'm T 'landing the iiesopouaiiiian Expeditionary Force, as to the inclusion in these assurances of the Vilayets of Bagdad and Basrah. Sir E. Grey would suggest that Sir John Nixon might he informed of the action taken by this Department on his above-mentioned telegram, and be told that the Sherif maintains that ITesopotamia is Arab, but as Great Britain has special interests there, it may be left out of dis- The Under Secretary of State for India. cussion . ring ^ le above-mentioned statement on the part of the Sherif is aiso enclosed herein for convenience of re ference* I am, Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant, 4/2o ' rrT i r-M / «&lt;*• o ''• / I r&gt; V' •• { t Lz-. »'«* ’'*'■' L rnsz- Cypher telegram to Sir H. McMahon (Cairo). Foreign Office, November 16th 1915, 1 p.m. No, 884. Following is view of General Nixon and should he borne in mind in future communications \/ith Arabs as far as possible, 'Such a commitment appears to me to involve comp; misconception of attitude of inhabitants of vilayets. It moreover, overlooks the important and fundamental fact that four-fifths of the population of Basra and two-thirds of Baghdad vilayets are Shiahs. I earnestly trust that further consideration may be devoted to this subject before any final step is t; and hope that on issues affecting Mesopotamia, referee may be made to me. Cox agrees with these views,' /A. a i ice \ Chun* l^iX’CVlfeSS..' i rt- W* £ li So) o 4 «■* n ' i 4*' *- 8 «*»■ * *»&gt;**( )ecypher Sir H. kcMahon (Mudros) I). 5. 4b pm November 14th. N. 10 . lb am i ovember Ibtn. 2i Following telegram received from Cairo. 'Messenger with letter from Sherif has arrived. Letter is long and requires careful translation to .ascertain full meaning butmain points are as follows:- First he agrees to exclusion of hersina and minisan dite (sic ? A 1 e xandr e 11 a). Secondly lie maintains that vilayets of Beirut and Aleppo are Arab and should be under Arab Mohammedan Governrne nt. Thirdly he maintains that Mesopotamia is also Arab but as Great Britain has special interests there it may be left out of discussion for the present. Mean while he asks for subsidy for what he terms 'the Arab Kingdom'. Four tally he expresses fear lost a Luropeaxi peace should leave Arabs at the mercy of Turks and wishes Great Britain to bind herself not to abandon Arabs. On these four conditions tney will conic in at once. Messenger states feeling amongst Arabs is very favourable to us. Sherif impressed on him readiness and intention of Arabs to begin work at once. Sherif 1 s son Abdulla has returned from Hejd bringing several chic.fst whom he detached from Ben Lashids. Oppenheim is said to have returned to Syria having been expelled from Medina. Faisal son of u her if his left Mecca and is negotiating with Arab chiefs on behalf of his father'p I will communicate my views later*. ~ Sir a. McMahon. .. 1 l l^WOVlsrsp&gt; ^ Secret. 72 From General Nixon, Aziziyah, I Uh November 1015. (Sent to India.) 3o8. From a communication received from Government of India yester day, it appears that High Commissioner of Egypr in the course of negotiations with f • Mecca, the details of which I have not yet learnt, has uuh certain modifications, included Basra and Baghdad vilayets in territories, wherein His Majesty’s Government are prepared to recognise and support independeiiUArabs. Apart from fact thafj such a commitment (appears to be premature and will prejudice existing British interests at Basra and Baghdad and future of this great country, it| seems to me to invole complete misconception of attitude of inhabitants of vilayets. It, moreover, overlooks the important and fundamental fact that four-fifths of the population of Basra and two- thirds of Baghdad vilayets are Shiahs. I earnestly trust that further consideration may be devoted to this subject before any final step is taken, and hope that on issues affecting Mesoootamia reference may be made to me. Cox agrees with these views.X I Telegram from G-eneral Nixon Dated A ziziyah, 14th Nov, 1915 358, From a communication received frdln Govt, of I ndia yesterday it appears that High Commissioner of Egypt, in the course of negotiations with ? Mecca, the details of which I have not yet leamjs, has with certain modifications included Basra and B'aghdad Vilayets in territory , , , recognize les wherein H,M,Government are prepared to XKKrisiit and support independent Arabs. Apart from fact that such a commitment appears to be premature and will prejudice existing British interests at Basra and Baghdad and future of this great country, it seems to me to involve complete misconception of attitude of inhabitants of Vilayets* It moreover overlooks the important and fundamental fact that four fifths of the population of Basra and two thirds of Baghdad Vilayets are Shiahs* I earnestly trust that further consideration may be devoted to this subject before any final step is taken and hope that on issues affecting Mesopotamia reference may be made to me * Cox agrees with these views • Addressed to Secretary of State for India, sent to iHdt: India * I : v/\st Memorandum on Sir E.Grey's conversation with the French Ambassador. I am afraid that this conversation leaves some ambiguity in our position. I have already said that I regret the offer made by Sir H.kcmahon, but this offer was not merely conditional on'a sep aration between the Arabs and the Turks but on the i rrmediat* of the Arabs with us against the Turks. I venture to urge that it is of the first importance that this should be made clear to the French as well as to the ^irabs, end that Monsieur Gambon should be told that it is only on tnis condition that McMahon’s offer is binding on us or tnat we seek the assent of the French Government to the propos al regarding Syria. (Initialled) A.C 12/11 lt/l([P 4063] From Secretary of State to Viceroy, Foreign Department, Sth November 1915. Foreign Secret. Your telegram dated 4tli November, Arabia. I agree and am pressing your view on Foreign Office. If you have anything to say on McMahon’s telegram of 5th November please let me know at once. Assurances, if given, will be conditional on Arabs performing their part of bargain, which is additional reason against proclaiming them as McMahon proposed. In these circumstances it would perhaps be better if Nixon issued no proclamation at all on occupation of Baghdad, but if one is thought necessary for local or Indian purposes please let me have draft as soon as possible. It should not refer to the wider political issues raised by McMahon.IS In Any further communica tion or. this subject, please quote no. /I9I5 and address- The Under-Secretary of State Foreign Office, London. The Undersecretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the UaaS£&lt; dccoA Ay L\ fix &amp; and, by direction of the Secretary of State, ti ansmits herewith cop y of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, /lAAJXU^uftr tl/^ &gt; ms- Reference to previous correspondence : Letter ^ ()m Foreign Office: f ^A dl/iAf, 6 Description of Inclosure. (Similar letter sent toIn any further communica tion or. this subject, please quote Xo . tUSoj i (o / 191 S and address- The Under-Secretary of State Foreign Office, London. fv fu- 0 '/ ,r The Under-Secretarv of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the UaaSu A ^ ffy iff If and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith copy of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, CUv. tz. ' v . Reference to previous correspondence: Lette?' Foreign Office: Description of /nc to sure. Name and Date. Subject. h % ey T w, d ^ 1 U ia'i\iOV19l5 Similar letter sent tois (166807/15). EGYPT Cypher telegram to Sir H. MaMahorr (Cairo) Foreign Office, November 11th, 1915. 2.p.m Question). Following is the view of the Secretary of State for India:- 'I have read with concern terms of Sir H. McMahon’s letter to the Shereof. His assurances with regard to future of Basrah and Bagdad, even as explained in his telegram No. 674, go much further than I contemplated and will cause great disappointment in India, where Arabs are not popular.and Mesopotamia has been ragarded as India’s reward for her exertions - see Viceroy’s telegram of November 4th with which I concur But we must of course abide by McMahon’s promises if Arabs do their part. I cannot decide here what weight attaches to information as to Arab feeling collected in Egypt, but my inforration is that Shereef is a nonentity without power $o carry out his proposals, that Arabs are without unity or possibility of uniting and I disbelieve in reality and efficacy of sug gested Arab revolt in army and elsewhere.. Please observe that our friends Idrisi and Bin Baud are believed to be hostile to bhereef and his friends Imam and Bin Rashid are pro-Turk whilst one of the Shereef's sons is actually on his way to support Bin Reshid presumably against Bin Baud. Until therefore it is proved that Bhereef and Farugi both can and will carry out their promises, I agree with the Government of India in deprecating issue of any procla- No, 874, Secret. Your telegram No. 674 (of November 5tlt &gt;proclamation be to make cl at Bagdad or in Egypt. Tne next step should ear to them that promises made by McMahon are dependent on immediate action by them in sense of their offers and will not be binding on us unless they do their part at once. i concur with Sir E. Grey that the clause placing the whole of Greater Arabia under British protection would saddle us with embarrassing and useless liability and destroy possibility of such agreement with Branco as he wishes to make; out our special position and interests in Mesopotamia must be safeguarded as far as is still possible after McMahon’s pledges”. I agree with Secretary of State for India that no proclamation should be issued at Bagdad. We must now await result of your letter to the Shereef. If Arabs do their part we will fulfill promises made through you, but in next communication made to them we should state that they should act at once. In my opinion an effective Arab movement against Turks would be worth the future inconvenience as regards Bagdad, but I share doubts as to chances of securing this movement. Repeat to India,ho.lol secret rcilereiice to uy secret telegram &amp;o•6%‘* oi toaay f a elate, 1 have tae honour to enclose herewith hit English text of the reply which x have dehpatche-d. in Arabic to the hherif of Mecca* iiie mtter appeared to ae to admit of no delay, -.iid I h..vf' therefor© la eh no time in answering tnt/ aherif ? f letter, ani have availed r/iyself of the authority to act /lUiout 'further reference, accorded to tie m your tel eg mm iio.Tto of the 3utri inrhant* ihc coiapoeitiou of a reply which would be accept'ible to tuc Arab party and which would at the oc*; it tiire x0*.aV 6 as free.;’ as pofci-ible to his x-ajesty ’ a Government iji the future iwi.e* bceiA a difficult t l*■ i\ » x hu,vc bent a ex xi a ti xn stutini) tijnt treat hritaxn wixl rtcognize trie -rx.fic.ipl6 of Arab in/iep- eitiiiice xii purely Arab territory, tlctB being the liiain point on milch agrceiuent depends, but hove be n equally definite in cxcluaini *-&lt;rsina, Irxandretta and those Ustricts on the northern coast of Syria, which cannot be said to be 4rob, md where 1 understand that French interests have been recognised * I am not aware of the extent of french claims in Syria, nor of how far his majesty ‘ s government have agreed 'to recognise Vnm. Hence, while recognising the towns of Damascus, lama, Homs .uml Aleppo as being within the circle of Arab countries Mignt Honourable Dir y■ Grey wart* ;• *G, ^-*i , etc#, etc*, etc. SXlf,5 y countries, X have endeavoured to provide for possible French pretensions to those places by a gen eral modification to the effect the His majesty's Government can only give assurances in regard to those territories *in vhich she can act without detriment to the interests of her ally France, 4 * It will be observed that 1 have definitely specified. France as the only Ally concerned. The use of the tera *Allies' would, I understand, inevitably have aroused the suspicion of the Arabs, who would have conjured up visions of all our Allies putting forward claims in various parts of the Arab territories* I believe I am right in the supposition that no territorial interests have ever been even tentatively claimed, either by Aussie in Northern Mesopotamia or by Italy on the Arabian coasts of the Heel Sea, and that it is therefore unnecessary, and indeed inadvisable, to provide for any such interests. I venture to emphasize the fact that the eventual arrangement would m very greatly facilitated if France would consent lo forego any territorial claims she may have to purely Arab territories, such as Damascus-, uaraa, horns and Aleppo. The inclusion of such districts in Arabia will be insisted on by the Arabs, find although tiiay might possibly agree in regard to them to accept from ranee a similar arrange ment to that which we are proposing elsewhere, it is obvious that this will give rise to trouble, arid that much more satisfactory and lasting results will be possible in the future if the Arab question can be dealt with as a whole by Great Britain. InIn face of %m vital importance to the Allied caurc of the present issues involved, France could hardly foe unreasonable on this point and the question of compensation elsewhere if necessary is well worthy of serious consideration* It is, X consider, not going too far to say that the only hope of preventing this question becoming eventually one of trouble and anxiety to all concerned is to leave it in the direction of one power alone, I would also once more lay stress on the religious importance attached to Damascus by Arabs, not only as one of the three points of departure of the Leered Carpet, but as, in their eyes, one of the principal Holy Places* in conclusion, 1 am of opinion that while the terms X r*ave proposed are the minimum that couxd toe offered with any •oromise of success, there is reasonable hope of their being accepted by the Lherif individually and the leaders of the Arab party. The letter ms despatched yesterday in the hands of the Lherif’s messenger, mahmoud Arif Arayfar, who Is in t .e complete confidence of the Sherif and appears to toe a man of considerable intelligence and of some influence* The opportunity was taken of verbally explaining, the terms of the letter to facilitate its comprehension by the Sherif. Further verbal assurances of sympathy mid support were also given and , in particular, care was taken to allay any apprehension whichwhich the sherif alight entertain w^ardini tliR o pOf.Bibiy sinister motives towards himself of our assistance to the idrlei of Asir, la whoia he is raid aot to place complete confidence. 1 ccpy f this despatch is oeing sent by this mail to ^ndia. 1 Imvc the honour to h% $ wit/ the highest respect, «r f yoar morn oh$€.lmt § iiuiiihie mr¥mt % Signed) A. H. JVJc MAHON—U/l 1 To The smmix of .iBCCA* (with titles) X have received your letter of 19th/miawal with much pleasure and your expressions of fri on (illness and sincerity have given me the greatest satisfaction* X regret that you should have received from my last letter the impression that X regarded the question of the limits and boundaries with coldness and hesitation} such was not the case, but it appeared to mo that the moment had not yet arrived when they could be most profitably discussed* X have realised,however* from your last letter that you regard this question as one of vital and urgent importance* I have, therefore, lost no time in informing the Government of Great Britain of the contents of your letter and it is with great pleasure that I communicate to you on their behalf the following statement, which X am confident you will receive with satisfaction. The districts of kiffiSXKA anti mid portions x of 3YBIA lying to the &gt;«st of the districts of PAiiASCW, MAMA, HOME and AUSPK) cannot be said to be purely Arab, and | should be excluded from the proposed limits end boundaries* | With the above modification, and without prejudice to our existing treaties with Arab chiefs, we accept those limits and boundaries and, in regard to those portions of the territories therein in which Great Britain is free to act without detriment to the interests of her Ally, WHMW&amp;, X am empowered in the name of the Government of Great Britain to give the following assurances and make the following reply to your letter : • Subject to the above modifications. Great Britain is prepared to recognise and support the Independence of the Arabs within the territories included in the limits and boundaries proposed by the Slier if of Mecca. »;ape *t ^itain will guarantee the Holy Places against All external aggression and will reoognlsa their inviolabi lity. * __ When the situation admits # Great Britain will give to the Arabs her advice and will assist them to establish mat ujay appear to be the most suitable forms of Government in those various territories. 0?* the other hand, it is understood that the Arabs have decided to -seek the advice and guidance of Croat Britain only* and that such European Advisers and officials as may be required for the formation of a sound form of administra tion will be British* With regard to the Vilayets of BA0HPAP and BAS1U* the Arabs will recognise that the established position and interests oi Great Britain necessitate special measures of administrative control in order to secure these territories from foreign aggression, to promote the welfare of the local populations and to safeguard our mutual enonomic interests* I m convinced that tills declaration will assure you beyond all possible doubt of the sympathy of Great Britain towards the aspirations of her traditional friends the Arabs and will result in a firm and lasting alliance, the imm«diat« results of which will be the expulsion of the Turks from the Arab countries and the freeing of the Arab peoples from the Turkish yoke which for so many years has pressed heavily upon them. I have confined myself In this? letter to the more vit^l and important questions and if there are any other matters dealt with in your letters which X have omitted to mention, we may discuss them at some convenient date in the future. It was with very great relief and satisfaction that 1 heard of the safe arrival of the Holy Carpet and the accompanying offerings which, thanks to the clearness of your directions and the excellence of your arrangements, were■ 4 js^ ] 7C landed witiiout trouble or aiaiiap in spito of the dangers arid difficulties occasioned Oy the present sad w«’ir • kay bod soon bring a lasting peace and freedom to all peoples# i am sending this letter by the hand of your trusted and excellent messenger. Sheikh Mohammed Ibn Arif Arayfsn, and he will inform you of various matters of interest but of less vital importance, which I have not mentioned in this letter. ( Here follow the usual compliments ) J * (jut'' ' ~$/S; r , fyFrom Viceroy, 11th November 1915. Foreign becret. Arabia. Your telegram 8th November. We find nothing in McMahon’s telegram of 5th November to palliate in any way position he has brought about, and fact remains that althugh lie could apparently, without imperilling the negotiations, safeguard other interests at Alexandrette&lt; Mersina and Syria, he yet found it necessary to guarantee to Arabs the rendition of territories in Mesopotamia won by our arms in face not only of Turkish but also of Arab opposition, without which Turks alone would have been of small account. Moreover, from information recei ved from Sir Reginald Wingate, it appears that leaders in Egypt were quite ready to recognise as a necessity the incorporation of certain portions ofMesopotamia in the British Empire and would not oppose it. Further, it need hardly be pointed out that financing of huge irrigation schemes by which the prosperity of Mesopotamia is enhanced a hundredfold is not likely to be encouraged by fact of the creation of an Arab State and administration, and the whole country would be likely to lapse into a worse condition than under Turkish rule and be a source of danger to British political and commercial interests. The possession of Basra is in our opinion essential for the protection of Abadan and the security of our interests in oil-fields. We are still in dark as to actual quid pro quo to be given by Arabs in return for those sweeping assurances, but trust it may be of sufficiently definite character to enable us, if Arabs fail to perform their part, to repudiate those assurances—at any rate as far as Mesopotamia is concerned. //y As regards proclamation we agree that in view of chaotic position created by McMahon’s assurances it will be best if General Nixon on occupation of Bagdad issued no proclamation at all except perhaps a formal notice calling upon civil population to acquiesce quietly in our occupation, and assuring them, should they do so, their persons, property, and religion will be scrupulously respected^/ln India we propose, as soon as Bagdad is actually occupied, to suppress^ news for day or two, and to publish following proclamation:—“ [R.] ilis Majesty’s Government have authorised General Nixon to advance on Bagdad, his forces having once more defeated Turkish opposition on Tigris in vicinity of Suliman Rak. Not only for military reasons is this advance necessary, but m order to relieve British ladies and British Indian subjects who, contrary to usage of civilised war, have been detained at Bagdad; and in order to break up a focus of German intrigue in middle East, His Majesty’s Government, however, desire that it should be clearly understood that stringent orders have been issued that every precaution should be taken to prevent sacred shrine of Sheikh Abdul Qadir, Gilani, and the other tombs and shrines in the vicinity, from being in any way even accidentally damaged in course of the operations, in accordance with their unswerving policy of respecting the sacred places of Islam and the susceptibilities of the Moslem community ; and they wish it clearly to be understood that in regard to all other Holy Places in Mesopotamia, this policy has been and will be scrupulously followed, and that no obstacle whatever will be placed in way of Imams, Ulemas, Mujtahids and other religious persons following freely and as usual their ordinary religious practices, alter occupation of Bagdad. )( A 1 P 4151 Secretary of State to Viceroy, Foreign Department, 13th November 1915. . t Vou r '- e .y et &gt;, ! J -NovemW, A rabia. 1 agree as to the procla mation by Nixon, with adi ition of sentence expressing our determination to India 3 h ° y P aCeS ' 8hr,ne8 &gt; 4c - as in y°' r suggested notification in As regards latter notification, 1 do not understand your reasons for suppressing news of occupation which will certainly come out from other sou ices. I propose, therefore, to publish it here as soon as I hare certain news of it. 1 roposed reference to British ladies appears no longer suitable, as Turkish Government have agreed to their exchange, see mv tplAo-va™ 1 9 +r owm i I tilPz+I 51 - From Viceroy, Wth November 1915. Foreign Secret. Arabia. Your telegram 8th November. We find nothing in McMahon’s telegram of 5th November to palliate in any way position he has brought about, and fact remains that althugh he could apparently, without imperilling the negotiations, safeguard other interests at Alexandrett^ Mersina and Syria, he yet found it necessary to guarantee to Arabs the rendition of territories in Mesopotamia won by our arms in face not only of Turkish but also of Arab opposition, without which Turks alone would have been of small account. Moreover, from information received from Sir Reginald Wingate, it appears that leaders in Egypt were quite ready to recognise as a necessity the incorporation of certain portions ofMesopotamia in the British Empire and would not oppose it. Further, it need hardly be pointed out that financing of large irrigation schemes by which the prosperity of Mesopotamia is enhanced a hundredfold is not likely to be encouraged by fact of the creation of an Arab State and administration, and the whole country would be likely to lapse into a worse condition than under Turkish rule and be a source of danger to British political and commercial interests. The possession of Basra is in our opinion essential for the protection of Abadan and the security of our interests in oil-fields. We are still in dark as to actual (fuid pro &lt;iuo to be given by Arabs in return for those sweeping assurances, but trust it may be of sufficiently definite character to enable us, if Arabs fail to perform their part, to repudiate those assurances—at any rate as tar as Mesopotamia is concerned. /regards proclamation we agree that m view ol chaotic position created oy McMahon’s assurances it will be best if General Nixon on occupation of Bagdad issued no proclamation at all except perhaps a formal notice calling upon civil population to acquiesce quietly in our occupation, and assuiing them, should they do so, their persons, property, and^ religion will be scrupulously respected/£/Ln India we propose, as soon as Bagdad is actually occupied, to suppress 7 news for day or two, and to publish following proclamation :—“ [R. I lis Majesty’s Government have authorised Genera! Nixon to advance on Bagdad, his forces having once more defeated Turkish opposition on Tigris in vicinity of Subman Rak. Not only for military reasons is this advance necessary, but in order to relieve British ladies and British Indian subjects who, contrary to usage ol civilised war, have been detained at Bagdad; and m order t(&gt; break up a focus of German intrigue in middle East, His Majesty s Government, however, desire that it should be clearly understood that stringent orders have been issued that every precaution should be taken to prevent sacied shrine of Sheikh Abdul Qadir, Gilani, and the other tombs and shrines m the vicinity, from being in anyway even accidentally damaged m couisi of the operations, in accordance with their unswerving pohcv of inspecting the sacred places of Islam and the susceptibilities of the Mosleni commumtv and they wish it clearly to be understood that in regard to all othei Ho v Places in Mesopotamia, this policy has been and will be sciupulousl} followed, and that no obstacle whatever will be placed in wav of I,i ai11 ^ Ulemas, Mujtahids and other religious persons following freely and as usua their ordinary religious practices, alter occupation ol Bagda&lt; .on j.O ;■ ii'i i with IIDIA FOREIGN SECRETARY'S ’(Copy) CO LO CD f- t-w c ;) o S ^0 Eh ^ rx 'O N Telegram P* 1 r oui- Tlie Sec re t»ciry 't o - • - X« a. ‘f .... I'rnmentOf' India N (77 in tha Foreign and Political Bspartment, Simla, To - The Hon’’ole Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Percy Cox K.C.r.E., d.S.I,, Political Sesident in the Persian Gulf, Basrah. No. S-1034. Dated the 9th October 1915, S’ y ! c;.i c P-ealizijig the great political importance of taking j&gt;agndad, ais Majesty's Government are now making every ex fort to supply the reinforcements necessary. It is considered all-important that every precaution should he taken in course of operations to prevent the accidental ueserration by shell-fire or otherwise of any shrines or socreu places at Baghdad or in its vicinity find at same time that the Moslem community here should he duly informed in auvance ol our intentions. With regard to mosque of Shaikh Abdul Qadir, G-ilani; tombs of Shaikh 'Umr and Lady Zubaidah, and any other shrines in that vicinity special precautions should be taken. As soon as Nur-ud-din's force has been defeated at Suliman Pak, we propose to issue a proclamation here to following effect. Begins. His Majesty's Government nave authorized General Mixon to advance on Baghdad, Ms i orces, having once more defeated M r ,-, , „ il xar ^l3h Oppositi on ontxi3 Tigris in vicinity of Sulimn Pak, Not only for miliu^ry reasons is this advance necessary hut in order to relieve the British ladies and British Indian subjects who contrary to the usage of civilised war have been detained at Ba^adad and in order to break up a i focus of German intrigue in Middle East, His Majesty’s Government,however, desire that it should be clearly understood that stringent orders have been issued that every precaution should be taken to prevent sacred shrine of Shaikh Abdul Qadir, Gilani, and the other tombs and shrines in the vicinit y j yJ 9 from being in any way even accidentally damaged in the course of the operations in accordance with their unswerving policy of respecting the sacred places of Islam and the susceptibilities of the Moslem Community; and they wish it to be clearly understood that in regard to all other Holy Places in Mesopotamia, this policy has been and will be scrupulously followed and that no obstacle whatever will be placed in the way of the Imams, Ulemas Mujtahids and other religious persons following freely and as usual their ordinary religious practices after occupation of Baghdad.Ends, After consulting General Officer Commanding, please i telegraph your opinion on proposed proclamation and please let us know whether similar proclamation might not suitably be issued simultaneously in Mesopotamia itself and in- Foreign Office, llo vember 9th, 1915, (167429/15) O Secret and Immediate. Sir With reference to previous correspondence regarding the attitude to be adopted by His Majesty’s Government to wards the Arabs, I am directed by Secretary Sir Edward Grey to state, for the information of Mr. Secretary Chamber- lain, that arrangements have been made with the French Go vernment for a conference to be held in London to discuss the question of French co-operation in this matter. The conference will be mainly occupied in considering the peculiar interests of France in the four towns of Damas cus, Homs, Hama and Aleppo. The French Government will be represented by M. Picot, and Sir E. Grey desires that His Majesty’s Government should be represented by delegatee from the India Office, the War Office and from this Department. I am accordingly to request that, if Mr. Chamberlain concurs, Sir E. Grey may be informed in due course of the names of the officials delegated to attend the conference. The Under Secretary of State for India.On receipt of this information, a further communica tion will be made with regard to the date, hour find place of meeting of the conference. A similar letter has been addressed to the War Office. I am, Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant,^XJOTlATIOiiiii vsITH GHiL.iJ mjmw* i, emoranuum by secretary of btate for India. 1 have read with concern terms of dir ii, i cmahon’s letter to the Grand Ghareef. His assurances in regard to future of uaerah and - agdad, even as explained in his telegra/n, 140.^74 of hovonber 5th, go much further than 1 contemplated and will cause great disappointment in India where iirabs are not popular and Mesopotamia has been regarded as India* s reward for her exertions. On this point please see Viceroy’s telegram with which 1 concur, but we must of course abide by bcuanon’s promises if the Arabs do their part. i cannot decide here what weight attaches to information as to Arab feeling collected in bgypt but my Information is tnat Grand bhareef is a nonentity without power to carry out his proposals, that Arabs are without unity and with no possibility of uniting and 1 believe in reality and efficacy of suggested Arab revolt in Army and elsewhere. I lease observe that our friends Idrisi and i in band are believed to be hostile to Grand Shareef and his friends Imam and Bin Aashid are pro-Turk whilst one of bhareef* s sons is actually on his way to support Bin Rashid (i presumably against Bin oa»a. Until therefore it is proved tnat Grand ohareef and .ar^i both can and will carry out tneir promises, 1 agree with tne Government of India in deprecating issue of any proclamation at uagdad or in %ypt # The next step should be to make clear to them that promises made by McMahon are dependent on immediate action by them in sense oi their oilers and^ and Villi not be binding on ur&gt; unless they do their part at once. I concur with bir 4 Grey that the clause placing whole of Greater Arabia under British protection would saddle us with embarrassing and useless liability and destroy possibility of aucn agreement with France as he wishes to make; but our special position and interests in tesopotamia must be safeguarded as far as is still possible after 1 cMahon’s piedges.In Any further communica tion or. this subject, please quote /I9I5 and address— ' The Under-Secretary of State Foreign Office, London. ..A -v \ , 1 - c 1 &lt;li enJ, r &gt; : 4082 | &gt;&lt;-, _ I The Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Afiatfc pfesmtf his compliments to the CfiAJTrSh C^a/f-eu^ and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop y of the under-mentioned paper. Fo reig n Off ce, . ,„S. Reference to previous correspondence: to Letter , Foreign Office: from J ^ Description of Inclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Jlf // ^ Set. n*. hi duU tUnr. J • (\ st .' (Similar letter sent toDecy?l'ier. Sir H. McMahon (Cairo) Novemher 7tn. D ; 9.a p.m. H. 11c 20 pnn .lovernloer 7 th 191! ...&gt; No. 677 4082 1 ‘ o : l- . Your telegram No, 860. great Arabs attach very/importance to inclusion of Damascus Hama, Korns and Aleppo in Arab boundaries and have, in fact, repeatedly expressed the determination to fight for those territories if necessary. provision that Arabs are to seek advice and guidance: of Great Britain only, and that all European advisers and ■«■ • at officials are to be British was iaserted/exoress (?request of) Arabs who ws .e anxious that the sane provision should, apoiy to all Arabia especially in territories above men tioned where they do not welcome the idea oi iiencr. in fluence. It was, however, expiAhed to the. than owing to our obligations to our ally France , we hadnot a free hand as regards all Arabia and therefore the above mentioned pro vision applies, as is clearly s taoeo in tne pi eamble ol oai assurances, to, those portions pnlj' o- Aiat) teii to°tfip’in- felhtl oi her algfPrance, This the Arab representatives Agtg fullv undersfood and aumifUGG. &gt; , , , I reward the provision as very important- to safe- pnard not onlv our own present interests especiohij' in Me sopo taniaf but to prevent Arabia ^^gng a future source of trouble and danger. I therefore trust taut A : - maintained unweakened with regard to all Arabs ue.iitor„ in our sphere. in my assurances to prevent some similar understanding between,France ano t.ie A ® f . gardinw the hinterland 01 wyna, i.e. aleu u, euc_., cns the future peace of Arabia if it is ^dre^trictht such hinterland altogether it would te wise w reouricu it to the smallest limits possible. It was mag^tecuy tne France, ant I considered Vaat ey y ,sw^^io.rs nerdA non bo far witbout reference to you i 01 wnicn jime aia allow.... js-r In Any further communica tion on this subject, please quote No. and address— The Under-Secretary of State Foreign Office, London. % ! i u \ 7'fie Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Jl fairs-f resjgits his compliments to the Under-Secret ary of State for Sn^jdUjOis and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop y of the wider-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, MMsrrJrfJ^ g? , IQ’S- Reference to previous correspondence: Letter Foreiqn Office from * ^ CcLAJuQfM IlO .106, Sir, T'ithrafar onca to ,;iy tala^Taai ?fo, 60S of me X^tSx instant*, oont ining a nvmmxy of a latter filch I have Just raoeivad ' : hom the Sharir of 'tecca, I have the non our to transmit hei-a^ith a translation of the letter itself* tfhich is da tod Ifecoa, September 9, r ,e original Arabic is- px obably p-.arposaly and as is the cistta of the Sherif* - couoad in vague terms, The construction .acreover in soma cases is faulty; so that a translation of* the document has presented diffi culties, it has therefore been thought better tot ron ’e the Arabic text as nearly as possible, the eneral seme being, as a rule, tolerably clear. fije major part of the letter, a Ire a ’y simsarized in my above-mentioned telegram, may be summed up as a plain intimation that the Sharif of Mecca and the Arab communities /hose policy and idea® he represents, are ready to side tith us in the present far on the condi tion that we can accept their min demands and espe cially the territorial boundaries defined in the Sha rif’s previous communication forwarded to you in my decpevtcli Ho. 94 of August AC. The remainder of the letter refers to arrangemjfcts to b, made for sending grain and money to Mecca. The grain has as a matter of fewbt alrea : y left and the mon ey is folio.ring. -tter paragra-/, &gt;t dealt with in my telegraphic report as not directly bearing The Honble, on SirJ. drey Bart, .3., etc, etc. etc/»■ ^ p /0S*- f J ' v &gt; r c , , i /'l le -S27l i p A I ^ i ^ j fit**/ fK htm-Ai ^KMaZ / A/nI/ /O' r- / ;--To His Excellency the Most Exalted, the Most Eminent - The British High Commissioner in Egypt; may God grant him Success* With great cheerfulness and delight I received your letter dated 19th Shawal 1333X(30th August,1915) and have given it great consideration and regard, in spite of the impression I received from it of ambiguity and its tone of coldness and hesitation with regard to our essential point. It is necessary to make clear to Your Excellency our sincerity towards the Illustrious British Bnpire and our confession of preference for it in all cases and matters and under all forms and circumstances. The real interests of the followers of our religion necessitate this. nevertheless. Your Excellency will pardon me and permit me to say clearly that the coldness and hesitation which you have displayed in the question of the limits and boundaries by saying that the discussion of these at present is of no use and is a loss of time and that they are still in the hands of the Government which is ruling them, etc., might be taken to infer an estrangement or something of the sort. As these limits and boundaries demanded are not those of one person whom we should satisfy and with whom we should discuss them after the war is over but our peoples have seen that the life of their new proposal is bound at least by these limits and their word is united on this.Therefore they have found it necessary to first discuss this point with the Power in whom they now have their confidence and trust as a final appeal viz: the Illustrious British Empire, (Literal translation of the above passage) * And therefore they saw the discussion in it first the place of their confidence and trust the axis of final ' appeal now and that is the illustrious British Empire* Their reason for this union and confidence!-is mutual interest, the necessity of regulating territorial divisions the feelings of their inhabitants, so that they may know how to base their future and life , so not to meet her (England?) or any of her allies in opposition to their resolution which would produce a contrary issue, which God forbid (Literal translation of above passage as follows) * the feelings of its inhabitants to know how to base * their future and life for not to meet her or one of its For the object is * , honourable Minister, the truth &lt; which is established on a basis which guarantees the essential sources of life in future. Yet within these limits they have not included places 77 inhabited by a foreign race. It is * vain show of words and titles. May God have mercy on the Caliphate and comfort Moslems who| in short, believe that they are necessary for economic and H allies in front of their resolution when the thing comes to a contrary result, which G$d forbid*. M in it I am confident that Your Excellency will not doubt that cl &lt;£ 4 n#t I personally who am demanding of these limits which include only our race but that they are all proposals of the people lifeIs this not right . Your Excellency the Minister ? In a word « Your High Excellency we are firm, in our sincerity and declaring our preference for loyalty towards you, whether you are satisfied with us as has been said or angry. With reference to your remark in your letter above- mentioned that some of our people are still doing their utmost in promoting the interests of Turkey - Your Goodness (lit, M Perfectness”) would not permit you to make this an excuse for the tone of coldness and hesitation with regard to our demands, demands which I cannot admit that you, as a man of sound opinion, will deny to be necessary for our existence; nay, they are the essential essence of our life material and moral. Up to the present moment I am myself with all my might carrying out in my country all things in conformity with tne Islamic Law all things which tend to benefit the rest of the kingdom, and I shall continue to do so until it pleases God to order otherwise. In order to reassure Your Excellency, I can declare that the w&amp;o&amp;e country, together with those who you say are submitting themselves to Turco-German orders, are all waiting the result of these negotiations, which are dependent only on your refusal or acceptance the question of the limits and in your declaration of safeguarding their religion first and then the rest of rights from any harm or danger. Whatever the illustrious Government of Great Britain finds conformable to its policy in this subject communicate it to us and specify to us the course we should follow. In all cases it is only God’s will which shall be executed and it is God who is the real factor in everything.— With regard to our demand for grain for the natives ana tne monies (surras) known to the Wakfs Ministry and all other articles sent here with pilgrims caravan, 0. High Excellency, my intention in this matter is to confinn your proclamations to the whole world and especially to the Moslem world that your antagonism is confined only to the party which has usurped the rights of Caliphate in which are included the rights of all Moslems. Moreover, the said grain is from the special Wakfs and has nothing to do with politics. If you think it should be, let the grain of the two years be transported in a special steamer to Jeddah in an official manner, in the name of all the natives as usual, and the captain of the steamer or the special ^Mamur/ detailed as usual every year to hand it over on his arrival at the port, will send to the Governor of Jeddah asking for the Mamur of the grain at Jeddah or a responsible official to take over the grain and give the necessary receipt signed by the said Mamur, that is the Mamur of the grain himself. He should make it a condition that he would accept any receipt but that signed by this Mamur. Let the captain of the steamer or the w Mamur H (detailed with the grain) should be instructed that if he finds anything contrary to this arrangement he should warn them that he will return home with the cargo. Thereupon the Mamur and the special committee detailed with him which is known as the committee of the grain for the natives, will take over the grain in the proper form. Please accept my best regards and salutations. If you choose to send a reply to this please send it with bearer. 29th Shawal 1333 9th September ,1915.*[T his Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government, and should be returned to the Foreig n Office when done with unless required for official use.] r i M]ANGF POLITICAL. D8cypher c Lord Bertie (Paris) November 4th r 1915 r Dr SrlO^Prin. ii r 8 r 20 r p r&gt; Tl r November 4th r 1915 N0o 841 r Qr\ -Your telegram. IlOo 2464 r Negotiations with the Arabs r French Government realize the danger of touching on question of Kha(?l)ifate and no negotiations are being conducted by their representative at Cairo al though he naturally has to receive many Arabs* They ha.ve full confidence in his discretion,,s, r' P 406 EGYPT , j | g: Be cypher. Sir H. MclJahon (Cairo ) c November 5 th, D. 8.40 p.m., November 5th 1915- R. 11.45 a.m. , November 6th 1915 No. 674. Secret, please see telegram (7sent me) Secret of November 4th from Viceroy of India. In framing reply to the Sherif I kept special in terests of India fully in mind and within restricted lati tude which the nature and urgency of the situation allowed me I endeavoured to safeguard those interests as far as was possible in the circumstances. The full wording of clause relating to Mesopotamia is as follows;-* ''•/Jith regard to the Vilayets of Bagdad and Basra the Arabs will recognize that the established posi tion and interests of Great Britain necessitate special measures of administrative control (the word 'advanced” snown before the word 'administrative' in Viceroy of In dia’s telegram is not understood) in order to secure those territories from foreign aggression; to promote the wel fare of the local populations and to safeguard our mutual economic interests'. This formula was intended to give us everything short of definite and open annexation i.e. a free hand regard ing military measures, internal administration as well as development and commercial and industrial enterprize. Read in conjunction with preceding clause it prac tically amounts to our monopoly of all administration and control in those Vilayets and was interpreted in that sense by Arab representatives here. I fully share the views of Indian G overnment regardingregarding potential inconvenience of a strong Arad state Put even the elements of such a state can hardly as yet he said to exist and I have endeavoured in my statement of mutual guarantees to make any such future Arab state (with in British sphere) subject to our creation, direction and control. I regret that Indian Government should have read into my statement a disregard of Indian interests but if this explanation does not reassure them, terns of Bagdad pro clamation might be restricted to such general terms as to avoid all danger of alarming Arab suspicions by divergent statements. As regards the urgency of the situation under which my recent statement was issued I have received to-day a copy of a later letter just received by El Murghani of the Sudan from the Sherif in which the latter urges the supreme inportance of immediate assurances by us of inten tions especially in regard to frontiers as previously de fined by him, and t;p which he says the Arabs are attaching very great weights He warns Murghani of critical situation of Arabia and of great danger of Arabs being committed by Turkish pressure and German promises to a real Jehad against us. ...Addressed to Foreign Office, sent to India,2. x think it desirable to put this on record and to transnit it to you; and a copy should be sent to Sir Ha-cine id Wingate. It is evidently a matter on which there is, amongst Indian Moslems, some suspicion, which we must be careful not to increase. The Aga Khan seemed of opinion that the Arabs had no claim to Beydod. end that that reyion and the Shrine of Kerbsla ought more properly to be given to Persia. But I did not enter upon a. discussion of this subject.- t 3 (Eelegraai from Viceroy. X Dated 4th November 1915. Received 9.30 p.ra. McMahon’s telegram to Foreig:i Office XS 644 of 26th October. Arabia. We fully realise and with regret that circumstances prevented your consulting us in connection with Arab over left to High Commissioner of Egypt in ooniunetion with our special interests in^aghdad Province and area actually in our occupation,which we consider has been exercised without due regard to Indian interests,by the inclusion of provinces of Baghdad and Bussorah in the proposed independent Arab sttte, only ’’special measure of advanced administrative control” in these two vilayatis being reserved to H.M.G-ovt, or the Govt, of India. Wethink we should not have been committed to such a policy and that we should have been consulted before a / pledge of such vital importance to future^India was given. of strong Arab state lying o-utedde our interests in the East we doubt either military or political advantage likely to accrue from it . If H.M.Govt* are satisfied tnat an Aia.o alliance is likely to hasten termination of war we do not wish to oppose it on general grounds, although we object to conditions affecting Mesopotamia on which it is proposed that it should be based. Yfe have always contemplated as a minimum eventual annexation of Bussorah vilayat and (?some isxmxxxH form) of native administration in Baghdad vilayat under our close political control. McMahon^guarantees apparently put- annexation out of the question. By surrendering Bussorah vilayat to Arab) Govt, of any kind, we shall not only be pre- paring trouble for ourselvesjana along southern littoral of the Gulf, 'out shall be giving up tures as reported by you.particularly in view of discretion / ~ We have always regarded xi&amp;hx with much ere si ion1 L V. * ( 2 ) not only be abandoning enormous potential sources of revenue, but will also be resented by Indian people, end the European commercial community who look to Mesopotamia as a field for ^commercial expansion aiid emigration in return for the blood of their countrymen there shed. We sincerely trust that formula may be amended so as to admit of H.M.G-ovt. having n § /W. hand in eventual disposal of Bussorah and Baghdad vilayats, which have been won at such a cost. Pending orders ,we hesitate to recommend publication of any proclamation on lines si suggested by McMahon in his private telegram to Foreign Office of 1st November. Addressed to 8. of S. and repeated to Cairo as No. 10 D 3.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000419.0x0001a3_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/10/524</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000419.0x0001a3</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/10/524</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 53/1915 Pt 2 German War: Turkey; the Caliphate and Pan-Arab movement'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1915/1916</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-01-18T11:17:58</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (218 folios)</extent><extent>The subject 55 (German War) consists of 5 volumes, IOR/L/PS/10/524-527. The volumes are divided into 5 parts with parts 1 and 2 comprising one volume each, parts 3 and 4 comprising the third volume and parts 5 and 6 comprising one volume each.The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence for this description commences at the inside front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 220; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. A previous foliation sequence, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The volume comprises telegrams, despatches, correspondence, memoranda, and notes, relating to the war with Germany and Turkey and implications for the Caliphate and the pan-Arab movement. The discussion in the volume relates specifically to the view of the Government of India on Sir Henry Arthur McMahon's correspondence and negotiations with Ḥusayn bin ‘Alī al-Hāshimī, Grand Sharif of Mecca. Also included are the views of Colonel Sir Tatton Benvenuto Mark Sykes.The volume includes the text of the Grand Sharif's letter and the text of Sir Henry McMahon's reply. Further discussion surrounds the advance on Baghdad, the protection of Muslim shrines and the deferment of any public pronouncement until the city had been captured by British forces.The principal correspondents in the volume include: the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs (Sir Edward Grey); the Secretary of State for India; the Grand Sharif of Mecca (Ḥusayn bin ‘Alī al-Hāshimī) and the Viceroy (Charles Hardinge).The volume includes a divider which gives the subject and part numbers, the year the subject file was opened, subject headings, and a list of correspondence references contained in that part by year. This is placed at the back of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>First World War campaigns</topic></subject><subject><topic>Insurrections</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Viceroy and Governor-General of India in Council</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Commander of the Mesopotamia Expeditionary Force</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Grand Sharif of Mecca</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>High Commissioner, Egypt</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Permanent Under-Secretary of State for India</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Arabian Peninsula</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Baghdad</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Iraq</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Middle East</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Muslims</topic></subject><subject><topic>Rebellions</topic></subject><subject><topic>Boundaries</topic></subject><subject><topic>First World War (1914-1918)</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000419.0x0001a3#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>