<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100024051548.0x000018_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T01:11:13.190Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100024051548.0x000018_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/132, ff 60-62</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100024051548.0x000018</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/132, ff 60-62</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Letter No. 178 of 1853 Captain Arnold Burrowes Kemball, Resident in the Persian Gulf, at Bushire to William Taylor Thomas, HM Chargé d'affaires at the Court of Persia, at Tehran</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1853/1853</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-10-15T00:33:18</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>3 folios</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The letter is enclosing a report on the state of Persian fortifications at Karrack [Khārk, Jazīreh-ye]; the investigation was undertaken as a result of a suggestion from James Howard Harris, Lord Malmesbury and the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.Note that Karrack is also spelt Kharg in this item.The item has two enclosures:1. Letter from Commodore George Robinson, Commander of the Indian Naval Squadron in the Persian Gulf to the Resident in the Persian Gulf, dated 10 June 1853.The enclosure is forwarding enclosure No. 2.2. Letter from Lieutenant Chas Golding Constable, Commander of the HC Brig Euphrates to Commodore George Robinson, dated 2 June 1853.The enclosure is reporting that the Lieutenant's vessel arrived at Karrack on 15 May 1853; it notes that the Lieutenant did not observe any signs of new fortification work, or of any efforts to repair existing structures.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100024051548.0x000018#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>