<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100024165374.0x000008_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T00:29:37.623Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100024165374.0x000008_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/55, ff 3-16</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100024165374.0x000008</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/55, ff 3-16</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Letter to Major David Wilson, Resident of the Persian Gulf, from John Pollard Willoughby, Acting Secretary to Government, Bombay</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1830/1830</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-09-12T00:25:51</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>14 folios</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The letter introduces three attached appendices, which are themselves copies of three letters regarding the need for British naval presence in the Persian Gulf. The first appendix is a summary of a consultation with William Bruce, the former Resident of Bushire and it draws heavily on information from appendices two and three. It is recommended that the naval force required in the Persian Gulf can be reduced, with a firm assertion attributed to Bruce, that pirates are unlikely to attack ships carrying the British flag. Two tables displaying trade between India (specifically the cities of Bengal, Madras and Bombay) and the Persian Gulf from 1821 to 1828 are included.The second appendix is a copy of a letter to William Bruce, late Resident at Bushire, from R. A. Bannerman, initially sent on 17 August 1829. The third appendix is a copy of Bruce’s reply to Bannerman, originally sent on 24 August 1829.Notations are made in the margin on several of the folios; they are made in pencil and appear to have been added by a researcher.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100024165374.0x000008#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>