<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0000f7_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-07-09T11:27:06.897Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">r £ .. 55f\9 . F^ t'dan ../aiicipal Co'-iit toe, wMch lias not been in existence for the past rs# .-pie Municii ,1 projects mentioned in the last two ly diaries do not ao^ear to have * o.de ''c T i nrepress durinr the past few we bis, and it is feared that unless work co v i ences shortly these -nrojects .'dll once again be shelved until a 'more suitable occasion'. 2 # txl' r in ,T * ; chan e s made in the Directorate o .* Education. ghai S Director of Education, was transferred to Tehran and has been replaced by ;hai . D «hc from GORG D*hai d'D DDihx ..SHfl il formerly of the Roads Department Tehran has taken over the Roads Department at in from Engineer D HTODSH, slio ferred to a similar post in F o.S. Towards the end of May -ghai D r ‘ DEH an Inspector of the Finis try of Justice arrived in Ramadan to inspect the Directorate* POLIDiaX. With the elections at an end little or no interest has I’een oaKen in politics duri ig the past month. Of the two deputies BSB2HI loi'pfor _ Tehran where he h&amp;s been ippointed head of one of the courts, and ESKAnDAKX continues to interest himself in other places .than his own constituency, •e he lias not yet been seen. It is understood that Bar sin has requested the Shah to visit Hamadan and that he has also asked for the railway oo '.&gt;e extended to Ramadan* &gt; j n viev/ of the recent election troubles at ASADABAD the British Vice-Consul availed himself - now that the elections are over - of repeated invitations by AI.XR DAKESRVAR, Baklishdar of Asadabad, to pa; hun a visit. The situation appears to be satis! actor; , unougn xoilier joaloxai-s ^ rivalries have’been strained in coD^eouence of this disturbance, anaitrzrj &gt;e a little .vdiile before relationships tliroughout the dis-nco oecome normal Relations bet e,n the mhhshaar and ABUL BASUH WEUf™ g* less easy than they were before the disturbance. TJnfertunately ttie B^shdar has'not a strong personality and his chief of gendarmerie Lieut. PEA-, .*o „ ras to have been removed after the election disturbance, is treiue - y drunk on duty. In the words of the Governor they make 'a -cod couple - b-t that does not f -ive the district the steadying influence -Bhioh it needs a-nter tie recent -olitical vriheavel. With politics lading in o '' 1 ® pj s , nd interest grovdng in sumuer crops, the situation is lively to right itself. SdCH-IT' . c The-ce has been a slight increase in the nuriber of stabbing and 3 no tin” cases. According to the Director of lealth admissions to nospi.al stabbing are now numbering JO-AO a month. The police however, have wv efficient director in Oolonel KH. UL FOE, and it is not thought that ^e.e is any cause for alarm in this increase of lawlessness , aa - ^ seasonal* T1.TDEH iGTIVI‘-T-!S. .'/hilst it is known tiia£ TUDEH activities are continuing . * -,1 ‘Uere is no reason to s'.Tn^ose that they are at present m ill a s...-- .... , .- — local Tudeh leaders have little influence and, any wa^ dangerous, sin -.-rmart from Tehran. Disturbing rumours, : .' U RD. le capital is. on the tne re-public^ oion in—i - -a- ^ n A spread propaganda AEDABILI to stir u? the workers m ne canye y ' y in■■■ in some of the villages. Ardahili v/as imprisoned for a few.d£tys, vas released on 12th May. The local Tudeh leader attempted to hold demons ac tions on May Dajr, hut /as prevented from doinj so by the police. MILITARY. '* 7. The rSamadan rarrison, mirberine approximately 1200, nas recently been moved to MAHABAD in Kurdestan. It is understood that a small garrison of some 200-300 troops dll he sent from Kurdestan to Ramadan. ..ocoruxn^ ou local officials the present situation does not warrant the retention Ox sucn a big garrison at Ramadan. RUSSLUI ETT'IR ;ST£. C' SevorcJL visits liave been paid to Hama dan by tne Russian Consul of Kermanshah and members of his staff, .f thou.h tee reason ior their visits is not known, it is knov/n by the police that they nave been visiting certain prominent .rmienians in the town; and it is thou.;;no the primary object of their visits may be the transfer of rmenians to jrmenia. Several Armenian and Jewish families have left Kamadan during the month for Tehran, and possibly some of the Armenians ma, ave gone on o irmenia. One visit of special interest was made by the Russian Consul to the British Readin- Room when the attendant was asked whether certain improvements, /hich had been proposed by the British Vice-Consul a few months a mo, were to be carried out. These suggestions were made to the proprietor of the Iran hotel, from whom the room is rented, and .mo is- on very in.ii-iite terms dth the Russian C 0 ns;a and his staff. During the month a visit ,:as mid to Hamadan 'hy the Russian Consul from AHT.VAZ. He sta.yed here for a e da' r s. and it is understood that 'lis visit was made for health reasons. ^ Several Russian programmes have been shown in the local cinema during one monta. Rcai-ajc. x &lt;j m There lias been a sharp rise in the price of ce tain co: modi oies, and sever-1. eonrolaints have been made to the Governor concerning. tne uigh prices and the shortage of bread. It is believed that the rise in the price of rice may have been caused by the export of rice to Russia and that the rise in the price of other commodities is due to the instable political situation - possibly the holding of Persian gold in Russia. 1 T&amp;AYER. 10. Dr. ALI SAJYDI has replaced Aghai ARRIS TAAV'A’A.T as. Governor of Malayer. The latter has been appointed a .Iinistr; r Inspec tor m Te .. RPI^I SH UHllRRSTS. 11 9 5th May - Mr. Chase, the American Vice-Consul of BASRAH and Mr. tf/orant Macdonald, a former .L.0. of ^.ghdad, passed tlurough T called at the ’British Vice-Consulate. 28th May - The British Vice-Consul visited AB-3 “-D anc returned to Hamadan the same day. 'Vice-C 0 nsul, . 5 th June 19V7- )istribution: sr k ' - ■ —■ .S E C R K T. ro.'2/1 - 4 E‘4298 HAilADivN J.10IITHLY DI-RY -Lit •‘/‘V .pril 1947. -f LOC.iL GOV-MIL^ 1 . LV EX: 150 . still remains at feftlATi, the Governor, Ramadan although, novr that the elections are finished, he L-s requested leave to Tehran with a vie./ to obtaining a better appointment. It is possible that he may remain here till late simmer ana. it is hoped that he will, since he is a man dio commands respect and has the confidence of u.ie people# ^ol# KHALIL FUR, ./ho was temporarily removed from his post as Chief of Police during the elections, has resumed his duties; and Col. DAD GOSTAR, who v/as acting for him, left for Tehran on 1st Yaj. Aghai MOGJTADSR, Director of Supplies, his been transferred to Isfahan and replaced by Aghai liARZ ;faADT, who' held a similar post, at Malayer. Aghai Moghtader has a good reputation, laid Isfahan should benefit from the change. Dr. AHMAD MHADGRAN, Head of the Health Depca-tment, returned to Ramadan a few days ago after an absence of several weeks, during .vhich he lias been trying to make better arrangements for his department, and particularly for the Government hospital. Kis efforts have met with some success, and he has brought back with him a quantity of vp to date surgical equipment and other material for the hospital. 2. The plans for the Ramadan Mater Scheme are now being studied by the engineer-in-charge prior to their being sent to Tehran for approval. Preliminary work on the scheme for the supply of drinking water is now completed f and the Mayor has wired to Tehran giving specifications of # v. pipes and fittings required for this project. The Municipal ’''udget has been sanctioned, and the two schemes for asphalting the MC XI avenue and opening up of a nev/ avenue which wer&lt; 4 -‘eluded the budget, are no under consideration in dr.try of Interior. Aghai 'RARTIH, the newly elected deputy, who proceeded to Tehran on 1st May,’ stated that he intended to press for the sanction of these schemes aad for the improvement of sanitation in the town. XECTIQMS. 3 . On 1 f;th .'pril the result of the elections was published, ESKaTDARI ./us first dth , r 3 votes and 'Rarzi nd only 14 votes behind. S.-RDAR -Juuil ^nxu-G02IAJ was tail'd with so :e 1o0C-1700 votes beiiind the leaders. Tills result was not entirely acceptable to the population and posters purporting to be signed by the youth of Ramadan were placarded in the town to this effect. The Governor however issued an official notice that Bar sin and Eskandari had been elected deputies for Ramadan. Sirdar Akram, who also felt that the elections had not been conducted fairly, i mediately proceeded to Tehran where he registered his complaint. This resulted in the despatch from Tehran to Ramadan of MOHAMMAD MCMTXAM, Assistant of the Minister of Interior, to investigate. It is said that inmad Montezam was instructed 'to investigate but to make no alteration'. Whatever his instructions may have been, he saw no reason to make any change; and on 29th April it was made known, that after investigations it hid been decided tint Bar sin and Es'-a?.ndari ’ ire the properly elected deputies for Ramadan. ]j_. phe Ramadan elections have creited a considerable amount of local •rest. It ir bo th t the interest is only local; but, since they have hi'AJ on over a period of several weeks and since it is said that the Manadan elections liave been the only really free elections in the country, a resune of the course of the elections nwy be of some interest. . f-ilst it must be admitted that the course of the elections has to a very large ertent been guided, or oven forced, by the Prime Pinaster, the fail ure of S rdar kram to be elected deputy nay attributed partly to his unpopularity several years a ;o, wiien he was Governor at Ramadan, and partly to the poor way in which he played his cards during the period of his candi dature. In or. er to see the picture in its right perspective it is necessary / to look,- 2 - A 150 to look 'back to last year, when a case against Sar&amp;ar Akram fc^r? Interfering in matters relating to the Department of Justice during his tqnn of Gov ernor f* ship was being reviev/ed in the Linistry of Justice. Barsin, as head of the tribunal enquiring into the case, decided that Sardar Akram should not be punished and that the case should be dropped. Sardar Akram appreciated this favour and offered to ^ive his si^port to Barsin in the elections. He even v/ent so fcir as to tell Barsin that there was no need for him to come to Hamadan, since his seat was secure. 1C 6 . Sliortly after tliis Pur sin became a member of the Iran Democratic Party of Tehran, of which the Prime minister was the head; and Aghai M0USA7I 'JiDEH, Minister of Justice and Assistant Leader of the Iran Democratic Party, advised him to start worlm.ng up his candidature Tor Hamadan. Bar sin, therefore, resigned from the Ministry of Justice and procee ed to Hamadan, v/here on a - 'rival he fouid that he must cooperate with either Sardar .‘Jaram or askandari. 7* According to '^arzin hi.iself he was anxio^is then to cooperate .’dth Sardar kram to v/hich end he worked the people 15 ) against Iskandari and joined Bill;I S DR in urging the people to telegraph to the Prime Minister protesting against the conduct of the flections and the candidature of Mskandari, - vide January Monthly Diary, 'ut at that time ani Sadr was indirectly oi'-posing him ov/ing to some land oispute dth his uncle M.IS-UL- miSLAll; and this lost liim many supporters. .Men S'-rdar -dcr^ra heard of this dispute, he decided to cooperate .’dth Bani S -ilr, /ho had the s'pport of hLi-UL-MCLK. In view of the Sardar’s decision and of the Prime hinister’s reply to the effect ti^at the elections ./ere free Barsin, according to Ills 0 ‘. 7 n statement, had no alternative than to line up .dth Askanrari, M 10 .ras supported by BAfta-UL-rlOLK• The latter, 'vvlio o.ms a number of villages in the Hamadan district and is respected by the people, together .dth arzin, .Mo is generally liked in the town of Hamadan, for ed a strong combin-dign in spite of opposition to Mskandari. C. K*n .'.die Sardar 4kr , had disoardod bo«n Barsin and Esk idari - he had been -urged by the Prir.ie Minister to help the latter - proceeded to flirt with TAGHaVI and ASHTIAMI. At about this time t ie inspectors, ./ho v/ere to v/atch the elections, arrived from Tehran. According a one account Jcl. SHAHS, one of the inspectors and a supporter of the Prime * iiiister, advised Sardar AJaram to sun-ender come votes in his brother's village of KABI'TMVHAITG to Sskandari promising at the same time that he ./orld be recompensed by a similar nunber of votes at AS.’UMMD - hich is not a gTMHrCCLH stro .ghold. This, it is alleged. Colonel S3 l the Said ir Id - Prlae Minister* Sardar Akraa f so th story goes, fell for »stion and gave some 4000 votes to .skanhari, b-it he :ns double-crossed by 'ol. Shams, v/ho had in the meantime arranged .1th M T X '. .S .-I t’aat no votes should be given to S -rdar Jn*an in the s idabad boxesy see • 'rch Diary. . sr account refutes this alleged interferenoe by Col. . ■ md relates that Sardar Akram being confident of success anl wishing to pie .se the Prime Ilinister gave the AD 0 votes to iSkanMari of his orn '.coord, n th; t his name was kept out of one of the sadabad boxes by *bul hashar on account o -.ome previous family quarrel. hiciiever i true aco ' , ’ ppears that S rdar Akram and his supporters realising th t he ras losing rounc 1 madh arrangements for the /3T MJI!I box - see arch ont'vly Diary - to v e taken to the house of 'T 1 , a prominent 1 •, were to be changed. P is ruse was reported to the Governor, who or the confiscation of the ' ; , ccording to re oth official other .vise, the taiapering of this box was discovered ov/ing to one nail -cing Lng. .. uiriec by iiOH.'!’!!!) be burnt, and this lost •dar aot only 2000 votes but Iso is election as deputy for Hamad&amp;n. fhilst t is is believed to be the true story of the Ramadan elections, it is by no means cert in that 3 r r .Act o 1 t successful even if he had i- . osrds well. Prom the start di© $ were loaded against him, and it ./o.Ad have taken u cleverer /.inn than he to overcome the opposition. Rumour now has it that o nis close relationshin by iiiurriage to the Prise Minister he .ill be awarded a consolation prize of a Governorship or ncod of a diploma tic mission in one 01 the less i..portu,.t foreign countries.- 3 - Q. The result of the 'free elections ' ut K 2 jna&amp;::.n is not The people .jpe pleased that Barzin has been elected but are. evei coiiiplaining thut dskandari has no interest in Hama dan and has ncjt_ visited the tov/n since his election* The progress of the Hamadan d.actions has been reported at lengthy since it pives sooe idea of no. - 'freest J elections' in the country have been conducted and to vliut extent the people choose their deputies! TKa HOitiA. kal’CK fn.CTCEH* 10. After beinp closed for a few weeks the KOLA match factory reopened following an announcement made by tne -linister of finance to the effect that the import of foreign matches -vas forbidden. TUDliH ^CTIYITXdS. 11 . Following a lapse of some months there has been a recurrence of Tuleh activities. Jt appears that sometime during April a certain AEDABILI, an employee in the Department of Piiblic ’forks and Prop&amp;yanda, visited the carnet factory and demanded to be allowed to tain cne /or.'ers. The liana~er refused pen.iission and cor.plained to AKBAR OARAlOLLh, Head of the Department of Public ..'dries and Propaganda. At about the sane time -Irdabili 1 s brother *11X1, who was head of one of the branches in the Municipal offices, commenced propaganda amongst the municipal employees and was discharged by •ompl’ined of his dismissal to Tskanoari, the newly elected deputy, who -.'/rote to the Mayor that Tali’- was not to dismissed. Doth _jrdabili and Talik have unsavour: r reputations,. 12 . 1 few days ago a pamphlet - copy of which has been forwarded to H.$.!■!. Embassy, TEHR 1 - '• l lished in Hamdan by '.ghai . IT , Omari leader of the Tudeh p.arty in HamadAn end T I I and closely connected .ith the suspended newspaper 'Rj-HlillIA' • Azarmehr, wiio ret aTied to Hanadan last month, has taken a house in the to./n o.nd proposes to re-open t ie worker^ club. The gist of the pamphlet, which is entitled ' _n iiinex to Rahnema paper' .and which -was -vritten expressly for May Day, is as follows. (i) Owing to the injustice of the Government hundreds of our laborers ^nd 1 lardv/orking peasants liave been coiipelled to spend unis day in prison. (ii) The enemies of the Labour Glass are so strong that they have n ible to 3 r 'ison Ag RilZA ROUSTA, the Head of ; - Union of Iran. The false Labour Syndicate, which is a tool of the lovemment, is celebrating this dr.y, whilst the prisons are full of labourers. Ai^y privileges .nd benefits received in ATAD-JJ Irom tne and tliroughout the country up to IIAZAIDARAI! h ve ; &gt; een obtained as a result of efforts made by the Tudeh and other Labour organi sations. The sole aim of the reactioneries and capitalists is to destroy morale n nd organisations .and to create idleness resulting in oiie of labourers • t the ‘ , o'. r est .Tapes* The pamphl’et concl ndes with an appeal to all labourers to join the l; hour Union. 13. , Q 1 ieously with this rec^irrence of T^deh activities at Uamdan a dude' nrpporter by mine f '.T rrrr has recoranenced propaganda ■ rby has r • ; ' een releas€ 5 d from prison, 'where he wfts unitte^l 1 ■ ry “or n illeged attempt to ww^ev 'rernor of yer, .'Tien he w ospital at an. In security continu;o e fairly satisfactory. o further atserr^ts /havehuve been r.mde to enter the bank ca.c ound, -aid polioa p&amp;trols -re blowing their v/histies in the vicinity every niyht. —■ orliZDrl-: r.JLkK Sulk -) Sone sriall excitement v/as created in Harx.dan in tne middle of April by the arrest for debt of Shasdeh Malek IJansur, one of tiie yr ndsons of Shah Itozaftar-nl-Din. At the tine he md his Belgian afe h d come from Serishabad to Te’nran to make arrangements for her departure to Belyiinu It m:.y be that his creditors feared that he too miyht disappear . For about two reeks he was kept under house arrest, whilst the lawyers of all parties, endeo.voi.red to make b i ' co reraise, he left Tehr •••e, it is understood, he has met SH . S, his ditor, and thot an arranyenent has been made bet vesn them -.k.ere p half tne debt is liquidated now .and the balance, amounting .to 50,000 tomans has to be paid within ci.yht years* bio arife is now unable to proceed to 3el and has returned to S'I Jo '’b D. Shazdeh Kalek ansur, who has always &gt;e n most friendly to any T ritish liviip; at kamadan, is an intellectual man vdt i an attractive personalityj but l^einy impractical ie has ■ ilea in *he n tny business transactions, which he has underb-iken, nd it is feared that he has endeavoured to recover his losses by y-mbliof. RUSSLdT UrT.'k SOS. -]£• During .i.pril Russian Consul has paid one visit to i 1 . / ' • Since MOIL--VI the ex-bovemor, left knmadan his cliief contact here has been SGHRXI, a landa-mer and for er Tudeh supporter. Several Russian proyran.ies i-ve been shown at the local Cinema. As these v/erevaccompanied by Oriental music, they attracted a canparatively large audience. ECCbCiJC. 1G. For several months past rich merchants have been leaving bamadan for Tehran. This has had an adverse effect on business in Ham dan. fhe prices of staple foods, wood and coal, rex.in unclianged since last morffu According to a carpet dealer the prices of all carpets have fallen from 1 (&gt;: to jjO/- during the last few monthe owing to a. ioak American ■arke't* If this market continues v/eak, prices are likely to drop furtlier. Tne price of local ci rettes has risen Rials 5 per 100. BRITISH IbTbR S^. 19 . Cr- the 1?th of ipril br. G.T. STnFKa.'S, Imperial Bank of * Iran, arrived at Hanadan to take tr his duties ns ccountant in the Ramadan • branch. On 23rd pril Yx. STOKES M.P. and 1ft*. SH LI were compelled to make a farced landing at Ramadan on their my to ■ n n* .3 they ere unable to p?roceed by air and no cr.r vas available --t faraadan, they were sent the same evening to Tehran in the Vice-Consul* s car. The par by arrived at Telirnn at ■&gt; a.m. the ollov/in morning. Cn 2^th pril .k. Vice- onsul attended a small reception given to the '•ovemor at the Pottery factor} at k U3 . be rty vere conducted roimd the 1 ctory by the Manager. . Bistribution: Foreign Office. R.M. Embassy, Tehran* H.M. Consulate-General, .. lz. . . late-Gei , H.K. Consulate, Kermansh • . . , 5th 1 y 194-7• A.C.C. Ira .... rile.,rr -. H lli y.'- CTC. • . 1C. On 23 th xrcMhe HflMA ttc! Factor; hich eranlo^ r s several hundred men and &gt;va*en, ■£ closed 'by the ovaier, Aghai Md, who had received no retire -.s from the Government to his complaint that imported matches - chiefly Huftslan - v/ere beiu ( ; sold at a cheaper rate than he could afford to produce. Ihe closing of the factoi vris followed by a .vire to Tehran fresr. the ..orhers conplaining th:.t they were out of work. The Governor intervened and put the case to Tehran^ thot\;h he insisted that thi f actory should be re-opened or the ./orlonen paid pending a reply. So is known no reply has yet been received# 11 , The improvement in security continues # hough in th- v/orfts ol tlie Hayor it still leaves much, to bn desired. There were two attempts durin.^ the month to buryle the Bank To ne, which is sitmted outside the teen and adjacent to the Vice-Consul ttc. Representations for better protection in this are the Vice-J , u d. to the Ohio! o 1 lice # /ho arranged for patrols at night and promised .&lt; iditionul police protection after the elections, «he 1 sneci:il duties connected .dt’ t o elections. T.DTH ACTIVITI ES. 12 . . During the raont -- ' of not much iiapart&amp;nce and formerly a schoolmaster of MALATMT, and one of. the three L . I brothers from KERMAN, who have recently been in prir son. arrived in 11 mad&amp;n with several of their supporters. Tie object their visit is not known hut Innkaxani 1 is intervie id by the chi- o: police and or'ered to le ve 'una an oistric^. IT, In the mi 'die o p the month some '’arty peo; le, mostly omen, arrived in Kamadan from the AIT TA district. It is sdd that this is part of a Government scheme for removing a rrTiber o ’ people from the northern boundary and that more have been sent to other places, .'•/hether they are politically undesiraable or not is unnno.m, out the I,A; or at firwt objected to giving them employment on .unicr 1 or&gt;: for fear that they might contaminate his own enples ees. of the Governor, however, he put soue-on .enial work ■ id sent ol '.eta? the local factories. Those, who were sent to factories, w re returned as being useless. ’Whilst it is not thought that these people are in 5 , ' contamination 6f their employees. RUSSIAN II TIAT^STS. the month, and the Reading Room remains unopened. u. &gt;w&gt;. ^ . J a 1 G. Prices remain . “ 0 '^1 'V,',! a further small dro in the price of charcoal - and fowls has also fallen slightly. A temporary rise in .vier during the Tow ?.uz holidays • ■pr. T’’T 3 T- r lK r TT?’'’S r '’S. , larch and returned to Hamadan tl *oll Hr. Heritage, Ministry of ^orks repree mtatia , at T enadan on 22 ft: 1 Harch an' proceeded to ermans'' a the e = Mr* H.B. Sinclair, Rmperial Bank of Iran, Tehran, 'f&gt;. wife and two children, arrived at Hamadan on 25 th /Kerroanshah IS £ C R I T^ !io* - 2 iinj-AD-u' j DL^HY. . E.2846 i Lk m , IftCAL GOVEEIftSg: T. \ T’here has been no clianse of officials during ^ r 'c past •,onth, thorc-h tfaree Of th « 9 the chief of Police, the ’ayor uad the Director of Finance, h v 13 \ callea to Tehran* On 5th Pebtrusu^_ k colonel DrI 1 . . . , Police, received a telegram instructing him to report to Tsr '' n * ^ t ’•eroval, nhich is said to be only tcqpcrary, ras in o, •• mde of his interference in the elections. ::e has no ' retimied and he mar not be permitted to resume office until fter - - elections are finished. Col. VXD GOST/iR oootir-ies _to r-.-t or his absence. The Director of Finance, vrho has held this P^t for abou ^ three vears. onl v left during the past week. It i' mi • rs o is likelv to be made but whether he is leaving as a result of adv 'se Sforll lr not is uncertain. Ruaour has it that he has profitted to the extent , ring hi* term of &lt;rf i««* . ; ; that the . ayor’s visit to Tehran was also in connection with ment, 2 Preliminary ^ork has at last been started on - . years; , txe&amp;r m o-^r. » . • j h- done until the hill# are dear of ana*. About 2 million n-ls i is scheme. Of this 1,200,000 have dre dy fr^o the Government and a father'600,000 have been promised ^ Stedw If work is carried on satisfactorily, the scheme should collet two'years, though some effects should be evident before the .vinter. ELSCIIQKS (HAHADAlQ . w Barlv in Febrikary the Governor appointed a ne\ su^^visoi-/ comrittee. According to the ^-ovemor and to others this 2 S idh W,, definitely favoured SfHMH «MU ^^°S^^ otea 3 T.ti-in a chort ^it to Tehran during tne month, seem. Hth r tS ttS^.rf th“Gove nor and the vork of the sw ,ervieory ooomattee the res^t th!t so-.e friction has arisen bet,veer, the Governor and Svrder AkAm. the Governor on the other hard oosplains that not^^ly « i^xd-r r.iram no politician but that he is also inconsistent. Whether tne Governor is right or not the Sardf.r was very undecided as to a ' sriLs b^ BAH/ -UL-^IULK, v»ho has given A p nS 0 i nx.v o , 1 Tr .r^ I.T . ' ni , + _ , * k a&lt;ro JT left for Tehran end has not ^et returned r ' J e 1 c; Inyo vp m states that he may be returning any da: to Hamden, ' ‘etean in order to he told that he others are saying tn-t. ne. as J --- LO , T is not to stand as a candidate ''or , If it is true that ASHTI \ T I is being removed and that * 4 . - r i-’ick'f’ t*o at * is losing groi- *' 1 &gt; BARZIH is making headway, then it may &gt;e ‘oovex'nor. This does and this would accost for nis &lt; - - be elected deputy, since he not, however, necessarily . ean that he . ;^ and is held in has a big following in his own an^his bro^r sji lag ^ ^ ^ some esteem in tne district, . e — &gt; - _ . f Ha.madan. His p-rtner Ol-wni and he has little or no su;,?or^^in^ of votes in consequence ■ I Vbich hi. Ofiloisl' I'Osition erwbdes hi- to . rte. vjhilst BARZIK is known and generally liked. r The present situation .vould, therefore appear to he very* much as follows - Fifty percent of the -votes will SC o ' '- 2 - family, but of these a percentage will pass to Baha-ul-Mulk, '/ho owns villages on the BIJAR road. These votes will be given either to BARZIK or ABBAS SSKANDAKI. Of the remainin': fifty percent two of the largest landowners, and SARAPI, support SaPdar Akram, whilst the rea tinder and the town of Hamadan support Bar sin and Abbas uskandari. The Sardar, ho ever, has the influential mulla BAITI S BP. behind aiir. 6 . Although it is said that all preliminiary arrangements have been made and everything is ready for the people to cast their votes, there appears to be an unaccountable lullj °n' this, it has oeen suggested, is because the Hamadan elections are not to be free, and f’irther instructions are awaited from Tehran. The G-cvemor, on the other hand, believes tnat ^ the Centre’1 Government 1 oes not now t! sh to interfere in ' e a m dan ^elections which he t'rinks would be finished by now, had they intended to do so. ELECTIONS BIJAR). y. The BIJ R elections h ve not been running as smoot’ily as was anticipated. It appears tha.t G80LAM HUSSEIN BCRBOR, Manager of the A.I.O.C. Hamadan, heard directly or indirectly that the poopany viewed his candidature with displeasure. He, therefore, withdrew and made an amo -nce- nent to this effect in the local press. A certain 08RANG, from the Ministry of Justice at Tehran was sent to Bijvr as Govaasnr ent oandidate. On February, the eve of the elections, - deputation from Piyir vc ^ reached Gholam Hussein Borbor with . reguest t} -t ]ie wo Id alter his decision. They stated that no one in Bijar wanted Ourang, and further that a telegram had'already been sent to Tehran to the effect that the people of Bijar refused to accept Ourang at any cost. RUSSIAK EsUBRESTS. 8 . The Russian Consul and his deputy continue to interest themselves in Hamadan, and the Governor has received three visits from the Russian Consul. On one occasion he asked for permission to open R ading Roan and stated that 1500 tomans good will money had already been paid. The (Governor refused penaission on the grounds that he 'iad received no instructions from the Ministry o r ‘ Foreign Af ‘airs, t the sane time advised him. to take the matter up himself with the Minister. The Russian Consul showed extreme displeasure with thi y and asked why, if the British had a heading P.oon, nermission could not be given for to 'ave one too. To this the Governor retorted that the British Reading Room was in existence, when he came, and that he had no authority to make any change, 1 either the Russian Consul nor his deputy have ■ aid co'trtesy calls on he Vice-Consul. . , t is understood that ar: an to be sent. One of i c lied 'Oscow Parade'. ECCRO 1'S. 1C. There has been a further slight !rop - • , adities effected being , ~hee, tos t charcoal and eggs. The fall in the price of eggs is of course seasonal. - .1 ’ I S. R R 'h_. 11 . . . .I.O.C. was admitted to hospil on 19th Febr '*red on 26 th* On 28th he ' - H'c ucl' n. Distribution: ’-er Jan1 • ' . AHR S HSSKviATI replaced ' iO^/LAVI Z/D3H as Governor of Hamadan on 26th January'' /+7* Lt. Col. KHALIL PUR replaced Lt. Col. FATEMI as Chief of Police on 22 nd Decernber l+Jo, LOCAL GOVERNMENT. 3 . There are now only five likely candidates for the election o &lt;&lt;ne tvro Hamadan deputies* These e-re: I AFSUR ALI KH-Lf QARAGOZLU (S RDAR AKR. L1;, v/hose election appears to be a certainty. ABBAS ESKALBARI, forner Governor-General of Tehran, who is supported by BAHA-UL-MOLK and who, from all accounts, appears to be persona grata with the Prime Minister. _ . TaGKE BARZIN, of Hamadan, a judge, xrho being originally the official democrat candidate expected Government support. His Candida t ire, hovrever, was not publicly announced; and this lias to some extent damped his ardour, although it is said that he would not carry much weight at the best of times. ASHTIAKI, a member of the Ministry of Finance, who has considerable energy and sane support but, not being a Hamadani, meets with considerable opposition. He has, however, the simport of the intriguing and influential mul3ji v- - SaDr^. SEYTED ABDULLAH TAGHAVI, a mulla of little consequence, tnough lie, 000 has the support of BAKI SADR. Dr. AbllED BAHADORAH replaced Dr. FARIDI as Head of Health Department on 3rd January 47* * KAFRDAN MONTHLY DIARY , January 1947» Durinn the first half of the month it was generally expect d a t SARDAR AKRAM and A^RAS ESKAKDARI would be elected. There was consider ] e o t -nosition to the latter, but it was believed that any opposition uld te of no avail , since he ted been sent down from Teton and^ RDAE iSRAK, had the si^port of the s cons±n, P-' - * .. 07 .TK , however, who wab nettled over hat he considered a sli/ht to his / /candidature 2. The three changes mentioned above of local officials should be to the advantage of RAMADAN• The former Governor was not big enough for the position and had not the confidence of the people. His successor is a very .different type of man, and it is hoped that he will steer safely through the present rather difficult period of the elections. Unfortunately he is not too pleased with the appointment and does not intend to stay any longer than he can help. The reputation of the former chief of police was sordid; and his successor, who is a Hamadani and has had considerable police experience in Kurdistan, has already taken steps to improve the police force and reduce crime. Rumour has it that he, like the former Governor, has shown himself to be biassed in the elections; but it is hoped that with a change of Governor he will confine himself to his police duties. The head of the Health Department is an active man, who has already made one or two improvements in the hospital* It remains to be seen, whether the new officials will continue their interest or whether these are further examples of a 'new broom sweeping clean”. The Mayor, ALI MANSUR JALILI, who has only held the z'ost for three months, though pleasant ^nd apparently, interested, has the reputation of not being strong enough for the position. The heads of all denartments speak of insufficient money allowed in their budgets. ELECTIONS. (Hamadan). S CCRET, No. 2/1-1Candidatni«/4nd vrho disliked ABBAS ESKAl'JDARI intensely, joined forces ■with ASHTIANT and together they approached BANI S DR, T’he latter took the cudgels, and on 16th January a nimber of landovmers and others met in his house, when they protested against the Governors interference in the election and the supervisory committee, as set up by him. The result of this meeting was a telegram from Bani Sadr to the Prime Minister demanding the removal of the Governor and the cancellation of his arrange- 4) ments for the elections. In reply a telegram was sent from Tehran to the Governor instructing him not to interfere in the elections, and a few days later he //as removed from office, 5, By this time public attention was focussed more on the removal of Abbas Eskandari from standing as candidate and on the formation of a new supervisory committee than ori who was actually to be the second deputy. Meanwhile Sardar Akram arrived at Ramadan v/ith a request, if not an actual instruction, from the Prime Minister to lend his support to Abbas Eskandari, This, however, was not to the Sardar's liking, since he realised that his own position in Ramadan would be effected, if he were to join forces v/ith a man so generally disliked by the local people. The arrival of the new Governor was, therefore awaited by all with considerable interest, 6 . On 26th January ABBAS HESHMATI, the newly appointed governor, arrived at Ramadan, He is an ex-Army officer, who has the reputation of being a strong man and he certainly appears to be far better fitted for the post than his predecessor. But his first step to effect a remedy for the pre sent dead-lock seems to give the lie to Ms reputation for strength of character since instead of reforndng the supervisory committee and filling it with men holding different political views he has merely appealed to the Oentral Government for advice, Bp to date no reply has been received, and the position of stalemate continues, 7 * Prom conversations with local people the general opinion would appear to be that the delay in Ramadan - and also in other districts - is being caused more by the central government than by the local officials. It is known that the Prime T Minister was warned not to send Abbas Eskandari to Ramadan, since he would not receive the support of the people. And yet not only was he sent, but private instructions have been given by the Prime Minister to at least one person to render him every support. It is not unlikely that the recently dismissed Governor received similar instructions and was eventually removed for 'carrying them out. Possibly the new Governor finds himself in a similar quand£y, and by his telegram asking for advice ^e intends to force the Prime Minister to declare his hand. It is doubtful, if he will receive any more definite or detailed instructions than were sent to his predecessor to the effect that he must ensure that the elections are free, 8 . It has been suggested b 3 &gt;- some that the delay over the elections in the provinces is intentional with a view to postponing the ox^ening of the 15th Majlis until the world situation, particularly in so far as it concerns Russia, has become more crystallised. By then the Government may be in a position to decide whether or not to grant the oil concession to Russia, The suggestion has even been made that the Majlis, for wMch the present candidates are standing, may never meet. At any rate whatever the policy of the Central Government regarding the provinces, the position of Ramadan remains obscure and at a standstill. Elections. (Malayer). 9, The elections at MALAYER have followed a somewhat similar course to those at Ramadan, although they are now finished and the two deputies MALSK MADANI and ZAPARI have been elected. The trouble arose, when certain landov/ners objected to the candidature of Malek ;.’:adani, the most prominent landowner in the district who has represented Malayer in the Majlis for many years, on the grounds that he only worked in Ms own interests. The complainants, afraid to take action in Malayeb, came to Ramadan, from where they sent a telegram to the Prime Minister requesting the cancellation of Malek Madani's name from the list of candidates and /the 24- 3 - and the reroval of the Governor. A reply was received not from the Prime Minister hut 'Tom the ’ inister of v ar, who is a frier;’ of Mfleh a'ani, to the effect that the elections -/ere free ancl advising the landowners to return to their hones* The Gove nor of i alayer, AB n .3 T hvTAPf J MOGH^HDAI’, is at present in the -jnerican Hospital at Hamadan suffering from para-typhoid. elections (Bij ar] * 10. The elections it h-ve not yet coinmenced. The most prominent candidate is GKOL^Jd HUSSEIG ^ChPOR, lianager of . »I.0.C., Ramadan, who seems confident that he will he elected* SECURITY - . 11 . General security in Ramadan has irrproved. This is attributed partly to the activity of the new police chief and partly to the recent settlement of a misunderstanding between the police force and Gendarmerie, • both of whom maintained that the responsibility/ for certain outskirts of Ramadan belonged to the other. The result of this misunderstanding ms that for several nohths criminals had a happy hunting ground, where they could operate unmolested. RUSSIAN INTERESTS. 12. Three visits have been paid during the month by either the Russian Consul of Kerraanshah or his deputy. The main object of these visits seems to be the establishment of a heading Room - A room has already been taken, but it is n© ! , furnished yet, though it is understood that furniture has been ordered. The scheme to move certain Armenians to Armenia and A.ssprians to some part o^ Soviet Russia has not, as was thought, been shelved; but it is understood that it is chiefly farm labourers, who 'will be required, and there are not many of these available. ECONOMICS. 13 * r, here has been a small drop in the prices of a few commodities since last month. The commodities effected are rice, ghee, tea, straw, charcoal and eggs. BRITISH IN TRUSTS. 1A. Mr* D.R. Smith, Consul-General, Meshed, visited Ramadan on 29th January on his way to the U.K. on leave. • Mr* P. SANUERMAN arrived at Ramadan 2nd January to take over the post of Manager of the Ramadan branch of the Imperial Bank of Iran from C .D. LTJH1.. Mr. C*D. Lunn left Ramadan on 6 th January for leave in U.K. prior to taking up his appointment as Manager of tne Kenoanshah oranch of the Imperial Bank of Iran. Distribution: Foreign Office. S H.M. Embassy, Tehran. H.M. Cons ulate-General, Ahwaz. H.M. Consulate-General, Tabriz. H.H. Consulate, Kermanshah. H.M. Consulate, Resht. Vice-Consul, Ramadan. Ath February 1947* A.O.C.; Iraq. C.I.C.I. Baghdad. File.f 1 . AHMAD SALAHI, Governor of Ramadan, left for Tehran on July 3rd, He went with the intention of securing his appointment as Ustandar , (Governor- General), of the 5th Ustan. (Kermanshah). The first news of his promotion came from a radio announcement, and he is expected to return to Ramadan in a few days to take up his new appointment. It is rumoured that he vrill make Ramadan, not Kermansnah, the seat of the Governor—General* On the other hand the Mayor, AHMAD JAHANSHAHI, has hi$,hopes of being made Deputy-Governor of Hamadan in return for being held d*ir^fct!J.y responsible to Salahi in Kermanshah* It is significant of the influence wielded by Salahi in Tehran that, while h e was Governor of Hamadan, he obtained.special dispensation from Qavam—es-oaltanen to work independently of the Governor-General, in Kermanshah* He dealt directly with the Ministry of the Interior in Tehran, (c*f* para, 3 April Diary.) But now that he himself has become Governor-General, he has lost no time in having the Govemorate of Ramadan again made subordinate to Kermansnali, 2. MOHAMMAD OR IZI, Public Prosecutor, also v/ent to Tehran to angle for another post. He, however, was unsuccessful, and returned empty- handed. 3 . Taking into account the latest developments, the following tips are offered for the ejection stakes in Hamadan:- i) HiiSSAN All FARMAHD ^ARAGOZLU (ZIA-UL-MOLK): now a hot favourite. He has got himself appointed head of a commission in Tehran to arbitrate between landowners and peasants* This is thought to bring him nearer to .javam, and thus improve his chances. ii) ABBAS ISKANDARI : Governor of Tehran. At the moment the safest bet for second place. Uncle of Iraj Iskandari, the Tudeh leader, but as tar as is known is not badly contaminated himself* It is reported that, since he has the support of Qavam, the Tudeh wish to adopt him as their candidate for Ramadan* They are not strong enough now, after their internal dissensions (see below), to elect a deputy by their own efforts. iii) ABDULLAH KHAN QARAGOZLU (MOEZZ-UL-iuOLK): and iv) GflOLAM H0S3EIH KHAR QARAGOZLU (HHTESHAM-UD -DOWLEH): Outsiders; not expected to males a spectacular finish, v) MOHANDES KELVAN: also ran. Owing to a recent break with the Tudeh, Keivan has now definitely dropped out of the race. He has renounced the Tudeh - or has been rejected by them as being too conservative - and now solaces himself by bitter tirades against them. A delegate of the newly-constituted 'Democratic party of Iran' is said to be coming to Hamadan shortly to inaugurate a branch here. In that case they \ 7 ill presumably put forward their own candidate. Tudeh activity in the villages is now widespread, and tridays and other holidays are regularly made occasions for meetings. Recently the Tudeh published a virulent attack on AMIR NEZAM, for attempting to suppress thei - ^ activities in his village of Kabutrahang* Later they appeared in Qassemabad, a village belonging to GHOLAM HOSSEIN KHALI uMIRI, the nephew of Amir ITezam. Their representatives, sent to Assadabad to make speeches and generally whip up local enthusiasm, were forcibly expelled on the orders of /SEAHZDEH\ - 2 - SHAHZDiiH AB0LBA3HAR Without the restraining influence of more moderate elements like Keivan, the Tudeh are now showing their hand more openly, and are resorting more and more to mere hysterical shouting and abuse. On July 26th they held a meeting in the main square in protest against the continuance of the Franco regime. But soon forgetting this ludicrously irrelevent theme, they degenerated to a much more congenial topic - offensive attacks against LIr. Churchill and British Imperialism generally. Compared with previous assemblies, this one was a paltry affair. They could only muster some 400 members. They had at first arranged to bring peasants into town for the demonstration, but were advised against it owing to the possibility of “hostile elements” mingling with the crowd and by violence injuring the Tudeh's reputation, (sic). 5. The stock of the Qara^ozlus, the principal family in Haraadan, has slink very low. Amir Kezam has a personal feud with Qavam-es-Saltaneh, as his previous wife, whom he divorced, was Qavam's niece. 1AKDAR AKRAM, Amir Nezam's brother and former Governor of Hamadan, has a similar relationship with Qavam; his wife, with whom he quarrelled violently over a lawsuit regarding property and who has now instigated divorce proceedings against him, is also Qavam's niece, being the daughter of Vosuq-ud-Dowleh. The Qaragozlus have thus fallen foul of Qavam on two counts, and their fortunes are at a low ebb. Sardar Akram recently paid a visit to Amir Nezam at Kabutrahang, but could not get much consolation from him. 6 . Mohandes Keivan (see para. 3&amp; 4 above) opened a new club at the beginning of the month, with amenities such as ping-pong, roller skating etc. There is a gambling saloon for those who prefer more weighty pastimes. The original plan was to open the club on a plot of ground adjoining Avicenna's tomb, but this was vetoed “by reactionary intriguers.' In any case the Tudeh have now forbidden their members to frequent the club, and Keivan lias borne most of the expenditure himself. Economic. 7 . Prices of staple foods remained high; bread went 15 ) from 10 to 11 - 2 * Riads per 3 kilos, rice from 48 to 50 Rials and roghan from 200 to 320 Rials. Large quantities of the last conmodity were sent to Tehran, which partly accounts for the sudden jump in price. Fruit was plentiful and cheap, as there has been a heavy crop of apricots from the Hamadan orchards this season. Byt Morello cherries only faired moderately, and white cherries were poor owing 'to damage caused by hail early in the yeax. A bumper crop of grapes of all varieties is expected. British Interests . 8 . Mr. H.N. Pullar, Acting Consul, Kermanshah, visited Hamadan on July 1st, and returned to Kermanshah on the 2nd. 9 . The Acting Vice-Consul took local leave from July 5th - oFuly 18th. 10. Mr. J.P.G. Finch, H.M. Consul, Mosul, returned to Iraq on July 20th after his period of leave in Hamadan. 11 . Mr. H.N. Pullar, Acting Consul, Ke^manshah, arrived at Hamadan from Tehran on July 22nd, and left for Kermanshah the following day. La A.cting Vice-Consul, Hamadan. 1st August 1946. Distribution: As for June Diary.CONFIDE. TLiL. 2/1 - 9 . Han adan i \cr. dij. / f iary , June 194o* I F 8167 ! ! 20 AUG (340 Political. 1 . HOSSEIN GHOLI KH/Jf QAR.IGOZLTT (AMIR NEZAM), 'the wealthiest man in Ramadan,' ret^jmed to his village of Kabutrahang at the beginning of June, after a prolonged tour of Palestine and Syria and a visit to Karbala. His return was opportune, as he was in time to prevent serious unrest among his villagers. His presence restored their confidence and curtailed Tudeh activities. Amir Nezam spent the whole month in Kabutrahang straightening out his affairs, which were in considerable confusion after his long absence, and he did not visit Hamadan until June 30th. He then came to collect medecines and a doctor to combat the attacks of recurring fever, which had ai'fected six hundred out of the five thousand population of his village. He finally succeeded in persuading a doctor to go out to Kabutrahang for three weeks; most of them were unwilling to work in the Villages even for good pay. Amir Nezam still has stocks of wheat due to the Supplies Department, which he has been unable to collect since the Democrats sealed the stores and threatened the villagers with reprisals if the stocks were tampered with. Although since the pseudo-agreement with Azerbaijan conditions are supposed to be normal in the districts of Khamseh and Mehraban, the Supplies Depart ment is still q.uite powerless to enforce its authority. 2 . The Armenians have formed a committee ostensibly to facilitate the passage of Armenians to Russia, and collect funds for this purpose. It is therefore interesting to note that one of the principal members of this committee, SAMVEL KHAR, is building himself a new house, and another is indulging in business speculations in Tehran. 3 . Brigadier MDGHTADER, brother of ABDUL HOSSEIN MOGHTADER, Chief of the Supplies D e partment, arrived in Haraadan on June 4th and stayed here ten days. 4 . ABOLGHASSEM SADIGHI has replaced EHTESHAMI as Director of the Finance D uartment of Lalayer. Shteshami had had a long and corrupt career in that post. 5 . ALIGHOLI DOULATSH HI, principal interrogator of the Hamadan Justice Department, resigned rather than accept a transfer to Kermanshah, The Governor, AHMAD SALAHI, has now achieved his end of bringing the Justice Department completely under his thumb. YAMINI has taken Doulatshahi s plape. The new head of the Department, IiJR AHMAD I, arrived in Hamadan on June 13th. 6 . On Sunday June 16th, the local Tudeh party held a 'rally' in the main square. Previously leaflets announcing the meeting had been dropped by a Government aircraft from the Hamadan airfield. It is not clear on whose authority a military aircraft was used to drop leaflets for a political party. Captain QAL* BBGI arrived in Hamadan to take up his post as Chief of Gendarmerie. Qal* Begi had formerly held posts in Posht-i-Kuh and Borujird. He is a Caucasian, and speaks Russian and Turki. 6 . ABDULLAH KHAN QARAGOZLU (MCEZZ-UL-MGLK) arrived in Hamadan on June 20th, and stayed a few days at his village of Faqireh in order to collect some money which was owing to him before returning to Tehran. He also took the opportunity to test the ground with regard to the elections, -oi whicn .it is a probable candidate.9 . GHOLAM HOSSEIN BORBOR, manager of the Ramadan branch of the A.I.O.C., visited B$jar between June 26th - 29th. He regards his election prospects there as very favourable, and is confident of getting 85^0 oi fee ^ votes. The Governor of Bijar is well-disposed. In Bijar a 'Union ot outh party has been formed, but under the leadership of a Tudeh party member. The candidates in the field for Hamadan itself are: 1) MOHAKD'dS K3IVM: a left-wing man of Socialist tendencies. Hopes to come third at the polls, so that if the number of .lajles deputies returned by Hamadan is increased, he will get in. (At present Hamadan returns two deputies). Keivan was relying on the support of the Tudeh and allied organisation, it nov 7 seems less likely that this ’will be forthcoming.- 2) HAS SAN ALI FARMaND QARAGOZLU: (ZIA-UL-MOLK): Deputy for Hamadan in the 14th Majles. May stand for either Hamadan or Tehran, ’.There ne counts on 'is friendship with Dr. MOSSADEQ -UL—SALTAN Hr! to gain him support. 3) ABBAS ISKAlvQDARI: Governor of Tehran. Candidature supported by ALI RAZA QARAGOZLU (BAHA-UL-MOLK). Apparently a man well in with Qavam-es-Saltaneh. 4 ) ABDULLAH KHAII QARAGOZLU: (MOEZZ-UL-MOLK): A rather half-hearted candid ate vriio has entered the lists on being promised the support oj. Baha—uln.IolK• 5) GHOLAM HOSSEIN KiAI QARAGOZLU: (EHTESHAM-UD-DOWLEH): A thoroughly undesirable character. Was interned by the Allied authorities during tne . war for his pro-German sympathies. Economic. &lt;10. During the month the Mayor made several vain attempts to reduce the price of meat. The only tangible results were that the butchers went on strike and no meat was available in the bazaar lor over a week. A butcher was publicly flogged, but the strike continued. The blame did not lie entirely with the butchers, because the cattle and sheep breeders refused to slaughter stock at the reduced prices. Miscellaneous. 11 . On June 20th the new Head of the Health Department, Dr. FAR3DI, invited Government officials to inspect the Government Hospital and laboratory. 7/ith the meagre apparatus at his disposal. Dr. Faridi has achieved quite reasonable results, but fewer beds were occupied than in the time ot Dr. SH£SD00SH, the former Health Department Chief and one of the most energetic and conscientious officials in Hamadan. 12 . An epidemic of recurring fever broke out during the month, and the infection was spread rapidly by the insanitary conditions prevaling in the town. Security. 13 . General security in the town is poor. Robberies occur daily, and even the Mayor's house was burgled. British Interests. 12 f# The Acting Vice-Consul visited Serishabad from June 6 th - 10th. 19 . The Acting Vice-Consul held a reception on June 13th on the occasion of the birthday of H.M. the King.- 3 - ^ Mr' l.c. Cartwright, the manager of the Kermanshah branch of the Imperial Bank of Iran, accompanied by Mr. and Mrs. Sinclair oi the A.I.O.C., visited Ramadan on June 12th, returning to Kermanshah on June 1Ath. 17 . Mr. A.W. Davis, H.M. Consul, Kennanshah, and Mrs. Davis arrived in Ramadan on June 15 th, and left tor Tehran on June 17 th. Mr. J.P.G-. Pinch, H.M. Consul, Mosul, arrived in Ramadan on leave on June 24th, and returned to Iraq on 20th July. Acting Vice-Consul, Ramadan. 25th July 1946. Distribution: Foreign Office. y H.M. Embassy, Tehran. H.M. Consulate-General, Ahwaz. H.M. Consulate-General, Tabriz. H.M. Consulate, Kermanshah. A.O.C., Iraq. C.I.C.I., Baghdad. Pile.CONFIDENTIAL. 27l - o. Haaadan Ivlonthly Diary. Z s iiofl mb Political. ^• The l.iay Day celebrations passed off quietly in riainadan. A large crowd assembled in the main square, ana traffic was unable to pass through the dense masses of people who had come to hear their leaders* speeches relayed over a network of loudspeakers from the balcony of the local cinema. The Tudeh had appointed their own unofficial police to control the crowd and to act as 'cheer-leaders', since in spite of the imposing array of amplifiers the speeches were quite inaudible across the square. Strong forces of police and mounted troops from the camp, with fixed bayonets, patrolled the centre of the town, and their presence undoubtedly acted as a . deterrent upon would-be rioters. The proceedings ended with the singing of Tudeh party songs, and the meeting dispersed in an orderly manner. 2» The month has been chiefly notable for a marked drop in morale and a lack of enthusiasm on the part of those who up to now had managed to retain some hopes for the future and a modicum of energy with which to stirve for those ideals. The uncertainties of the political and economic situation resulted in a cynical and frustrated outlook among the more liberal and progressive elements. In the Government Departments a wave of corruption set in which was unprecedented even in their corrupt annals, and the 'devil takes the hindermost'* principle found favour with the majority in their feverish desire to amass money and to hold on to what they had already extorted, embezzled or acquired by any of the other methods dear to the hearts of Persian administrators. The rot spread to all strata of society, and expediency shamelessly overcame the last moral scruples of men who had previously put up some sort of fight against it. The Government's 'hands- off policy with regard to the Tudeh party vastly encouraged them and proportionately dismayed their opponents. The stage was further cleared for xudeh activities by the spineless attitude of most of the landowners, .tAO deserted the town and their villages and fled to Tehran. The Governor, AHMAD SALAHI, persued a policy of direct encouragement to the Tudeh, and continued to try and. bring under his control any heads of departments who still showed spirit enough to act independently. ABDUL HOSSEIN MOC-HTADER, Head of the Supplies Department, has so far resisted all attempts to remove him, because he has powerful support in Tehran. ALIGHOLI DOULA.TSR~.HI, the principle interrogator of the JusticeDepartment, has also been threatened with dismissal for his si^port of YUSSEP RAHMANZADEH. -(para. 4 April Diary.) He contemplates resignation if the Governor keeps up his pressure and continues to demand lenient treatment for members of left-wing parties on trial, for two months there has been nobody in charge of the Justice Department. Perhaps Salahr could not find anyone servile enough. On the other hand, an official with whom he must be well-pleased is AZIZOLLAH HEKM: 1 T, Head of the Finance department, with whom he has concluded some crooned and highly-remunerative deals concerning government monopoly goods. In spite of the Government's announcement that no action will be taken regarding the elections until the Azerbaijan problem is solved, tne ardour ior pre-election intrigue does not seem to have been one v/hit dampened. Candidates appear with mushroom-like rapidity, and drop out of the picture with equal suddenness. The powerful Qaragozlu family appears to be putting four candidates into the field - ABDULLAH KHAN (MGELZ-UL-MGLK), HASSA 1 ; All FiHJLiND (ZIa-UL-MOUK) , MANSOOR ALI KHAN (SARD.. AKPA x ) and CHOLALl HOSSEIN KHAN (EHTESHAM-UD-DOWLEH). MOHANDES KEIVAN will stand for the 'freedom-lovers', (para. 2 April Diary.) But the Tudeh party is at present split by internal factions, and Dr. MIR SEPASI AND NASQOTI are persuing their claims in rivelry to those of AZARMEHR, the party leader. Unless Keivan can prevail on these warring elements to unite in his si^port- 2 - at the elections, his chances of success are poor. MQHA]©£S i : ^BDUL j'J-DiD I.L-lKSRiT arrived in Hama dan on 14th May to replace MQNTAZAlril as Director of the Roads Department. 5» Dr. P.JIIDT arrived in Hamadan on 2Cth May to take over control of the Health Department from Dr. GHOLIiiALHH, .vho had been 'acting' since the departure of the former Chief, Dr. SHaDOOSH, on December 11th, 1945. Captain MOHAiffl.IAD TAG HI PATHPOQR, O.C. Gendarmerie, left his post during the month and returned to Tehran. Lalayer. 7 • The Governor, MOBASS .R R0.7SI AI\ T , v/ho went to Tehran in Llarch, (para. 10 Llarch Diary.} is not expected to return. Various conjectures have been made as to his successor, and names mentioned include GKOLAM HOSSiLiH KHAN QARAGOZLU (RKTESKAiu-UD-DO.'/TiEH), but reports on this subject are very vague. Ileanvdiile, in the absence of a Governor, the Tudeh party is flourishing in llalayer. MOVVLAVIZADEil and LOTPALIAN (para. 11 Larch Diary) are actively intriguing in the hopes of securing the return at the polls of a Tudeh member - M0SADEGH1, who was defeated at the last elections. But the position of MALIK KADAHI, who has been for twenty years Llajles deputy for Malayer, has not been seriously threatened, and the numerous influential people working on his behalf include his brother, AKIN MADANT. Nehavand. 8 . The chief troubles here are economic rather than political, as the Tudeh are comparatively weak. The abundant produce of this extremely fertile area is in the hands of a few unscrupulous men, who by their extortions from the peasants and the maintenance of high prices provide a permanent breeding-ground for agitators and malcontents. MOHASSEl.lT, whose position in charge of the Finance, Supplies and 7/heat Departments is virtually unassailable, and AHMAD ISFANDIARI, a member of the Municipal Council, have a tight grip on the Municipality, which is unable to lower the price of meat and other essential foodstuffs. Mohassemi has been in Nehavand for five years, steadily consolidating his position, and defying all attempts to uproot him. The succession of inspectors sent from Tehran to investigate the situation have all returned satisfied with their bribes and consequently satisfied, for the purposes of their reports, that no action is required. This year there will be good crops of opium, tobacco, and most varieties of fruit and grain. Almonds and walnuts will, hov/ever, be below nomal. Opium growers are worried about the Government* s policy to stamp out opium smoking, because if it is strictly enforced they will have to hand over a larger proportion of their crops to the government. This will entail a cut in their black-market profits. 9. The headquarters of the Gendarmerie for the 'Selas' - Kalayer, Nehavand and Tuiserkan - has been transferred from Malayer to Nehavand, and Captain MEHJilR, formerly O.C. Gendarmerie in Hamacan, is now in charge there. Tuiserkan. 10. ZAF.LR-ES-SOLTAN, the Majles deputy for the 'Selas' elected from Nehavand, is unlikely to stand again for the 15th Majles. Since there is no other suitable candidate in Nehavand, a 'Tuiserkan Commission' has been formed in Tehran to agitate for the nomination of a candidate for the Tuiserkan itself. But it is fairly certain that whoever finally stands must co-operate with Malek adani if he wishes to be successful.- 3- 11 . There is no sign of Tudeh activities in Tuis-erkan. JAkALI, the Governor, is an able and sensible man, and the-local—lUndowiers are much more lenient towards their peasants than those oi Nehavand* Certain amenities have been provided for them in the form of j ublic baths etc*, and consequently they are less prone to h .ed Tudeh prc psganda*£^ Q ^ ^ Llilitary and Security* ?8 — i 12. This month also saw the petering out olNthe- laat-aiXorta—✓ at resistance to the Democrat forces north of Hamadan* HEDid r ATOLLi\H KHAN YAl.IXNI has disbanded his men, and the other three landowners are following suit* ZOLFAQARI, who had remained inactive for a long period in the Pirtaj area, is now convinced of the futility of playing a lone game and lias come to liamadan, thus leaving the way open to Bijar* It is impossible for them to keep in existence indefinitely large bodies of armed men who eke out their livelihood by preying on the villagers* The Democrat forces have made no move recently* Presumably they are v/sjbing to see what Qavam-es-Saltaneh proposes to do about Azerbaijan* They are occupying their time in dividing up all forms of movable property and either carrying it off themselves or distributing it among the peasants. From time to time they raid neighbouring villages in search of wheat, and then withdraw again to their centre at Zarrinabad. MORTEZA AFSHATOOS, a free-lance iadventurer who had been trying all along to instil unity of command and action into the uncertain alliance of landowners, conceived a desperate and impracticable scheme for enlisting the aid of the Shahsavan tribe* Afshatoos has now returned to Tehran with his brother, Colonel MAHkOOD AFSHATOOS, commander of the garrison at Razan* 13* Early in the month Colonel ASLAKT arrived to take charge of the Hamadan garrison* Colonel EMAMVJBDI, (para* 4 March Diary) now commands the brigade stationed here, which is part of the Division stationed at Qazvin, as distinct from Aslani’s men, who are intended solely for the defence of Hamadan. But all these troops are so riddled with Tudeh propaganda, and justifiably discontented with their lot and with the oppression of their officers, that it is extremely problematical whether they would in fact offer the slightest opposition to an attacking force* 14* Brigadier RAZI.1ARRA arrived in Hamadan on 25th Hay, accompanied by the Azerbaijan deputation to Kordestan, and left for Sain Qal'eh and Saqqiz on 26th Hay* The Azerbaijan representatives were YAHYA, Democrat Minister of Jar, and another Democrat officer; Aghai JUDAT, editor of the 'Judat' newspaper published in Ardebil; and AZARPADEGAN, an assistant of Pishevari. 15* Colonel MAHMOOD AFSHATOOS, in command of the garrison at Razan, has been replaced by .Colonel GHOLAI HOSSEIN LASRGARC. This is the more significant after Afshatoos 1 action in preventing grain stocks there being removed by the Russians* The Russian Consul in Qazvin had despatched several Iran-Sov-Trans lorries to Razan with a letter of authority signed by the Governor of Qazvin to fetch wheat from Supply Department stocks held there* Colonel Afshatoos categorically refused to authorise such a transaction, and was not intimidated when the Consul himself came post-haste from Qazvin with dire threats of the consequences which a continued refusal would entail. Afshatoos remained adamant, and reminded him that since he took his orders from the Ministry of War and not to form the Ministry of the Interior, the Governor* s letter cut no ice with him* 16* There are also large stocks of grain at Salamatabad on the Bijar road* In this case, however, the Democrats are apparently at liberty to walk off with them, as Colonel BnlaKDOR, O.C. Troops at Bijar says he is not prepared to exceed his orders, ■•which are to protect himself if attacked* The fact that if the Democrats took Salamatabad they would cut his only line of communication v/ith Hamadan and encircle Bijar itself, roes not appear to worry him.Economic mm 17* The municipality succeeded in reducing the price of bread from 11J to 10 Rials per three kilos, but this is still high compared vtith rates in other towns in the area. Vith meat, however, they have met with no success at all. Butchers merely withheld supplies until the Llayor gave up his attempt or else was 'persuaded” to drop the idea. British Interests. 18 . Mr# G.C. Boyle, Acting Vice-Consul at Kennanshah, arrived in Ramadan on May 4th and left for Kennanshah on Iday 5th. 19#. Mr. A. V. Davis, H.M. Consul, Kennanshah, and Mrs. Davis, arrived in Ramadan on 17th May, leaving for Tehran on the 18 th. On their return journey they arrived in Ramadan on 24th May and left for Kermanshah on the 25 th. 20. The .acting Vice-Consul toured the Malayer-ITehavand-Tuiserkan area on 22nd-23rd May. Russian Interests. 21. Li. Mirochine and M. Kochelev, Russian Consul and Vice- Consul in Kermanshah, visited Ramadan on 22nd-23rd Inlay to interview Armenians who had registered themselves as wishing to go to Soviet Armenia. Acting Vice-Consul, Ramadan. 7th June 194&amp;. Distribution:- Foreign Office. ✓ H.M. Embassy, Tehran. H.M. Consulate-General, Tabriz, H.M. Consulate-General, Ahwaz. H.M. Consulate, Kermanshah. File.FILE GORY U COPY (E 4892/2133/34) CONFIDENTIAL. 27w: Hamadan Monthly -^jary. April 1946. 4F Political. 1. Throughout the month the Tudeh party steadily continued to build-up and consolidate their position# indeed, there was no opposition, far less any concerted movement or action taken against them. Absolutely no landowners of note remained in the city - the majority having fled to Tehran or having been seized with an apparently irresistable desire to visit Karbala and other places of pilgrimage# Until the arrival on 18th April ALI REZA QARAGOZLU, (BAHA-OL-MOLK) the only representative of the wealthy Qaragozlu family was a junior member, GHOLAM HOSSEIN KHAN AMIRI. Several important people are, however, expected to return to Hamadan shortly. One is the Majles deputy HASSAN ALI FARMAND QARAGOZLU, (ZIA-OL-MOLK) and another is SEYYED NASROLLAH BANISADR. Banisadr has great influence in the town, especially among the mollahs, and since he seems to have made an amicable agreement with HOSSEIN GHOLI KHAN QARAGOZLU, (AMIR NEZAM) his weight may well turn the scales in favour of the 'reactionary' elements in the General Election. The Qaragozlus may put forward two candidates, and in any case the other deputy, HASSAN MOKHBAR FARAHMAND, does not appear to have much chance of re-election. 2. RAHIM NAMVAR, editor of the newspaper 'Shahbaz', spent a week in Hamadan, (see para. 11 March Diary) in an effort to form a coalition of the left-wing parties so that they should have a greater chance of returning a deputy to the Majles. It now seems certain that MOHANDES KEIVAN (para. 3 March Diary) will stand as their principal candidate. The Tudeh have organised classes to inculate in their followers the principals for which they are to vote. 3. AHMAD SALAHI, Governor of Hamadan, returned from Tehran on 8 th April. On his way he called at Razan, 53ni* north of Hamadan, and dismissed the Governor there for inefficiency. Arriving in Hamadan, he announced that he was no longer obliged to refer matters to the Ustandar in Kermanshah, but was entitled to deal directly with the Ministry'of the interior. He had obtained this concession because he disliked the thought of working under EETEBAR-UD-DOWLEH, who had been appointed Ustandar but who showed no signs of being anxious to take up his post. Salahi was soon engulfed in a pent-up flood of petitions — and complaints of maladministration, and bent again to the exacting task of pleasing all and offending none — the policy on which he depends to maintain control. He scoffed at the suggestion made by Col. EMAMVERDI, O.C. Hamadan garrison, that the town should be put under military law and that a curfew should be brought into operation. He does not consider that the situation either within or beyond the city boundaries gives any cause fbr uneasiness. 4. • One result of Salah^s visit to Tehran was the dismissal of YUSSEF RAHMANZADEH, Chief of the Justice department. This is a blow which weakens the local administration immensely, because Rahmanzadeh was a man of considerable integrity and probity, and worked conscientiously and relatively honestly. His removal seems to have been a spiteful act on the part of Salahi. The latter had demanded to see a certain secret dossier, and Rahmanzadeh - fully within his rights - had refused. Up to the present no successor has been appointed, though the name of /BIRASHK,BIRASHK, a notoriously corrupt official during his previous stay in Hamadan, has been mentioned. Consequently the various branches of the Justice Department, left without a controlling hand, are merrily pursuing their own devices. Salahi evidently wants to reduce all the Heads of Departments to a state of subservience, b}i£-J££hmanzadeh would not submit. 5. v Aghai SADIGHIAN, Manager of the Bank-i-Rehni, has been replaced by IDMAIL SHAYEGAN, who has had two periods of service with the imperial Bank of Iran, and is reputed to be a reliable man. ^ -the Tudeh will no doubt mourn the loss of Sadighian, who is soon going to Tehran, especially as Shayegan is a man of more liberal ideas. Sadighian was reported to have contacts with the Democrat forces at present 50m. from Hamadan, and was in every way a zealous party member. 6 . M. Pankratov and Ml Kochelev, Soviet Vice-Consuls at Kermanshah, arrived on 9th April, visited Malayer on 10th, and returned to Kermanshah the following day. They held a reception in a local hotel, and later interviewed Armenians who had previously registered as willing to migrate to Soviet Armenia. (see para. 9 Jan. Diary). Miscellaneous. 7 . Forty members of the Government Hospital went on strike recently for arrears of pay. Their case was taken up in. an impudent, fashion by AZARMEHR, nominal Tudeh leader, but he was rebuffed by the Governor, who himself took the necessary steps to settle their grievance. 8 . GHOLAM HOSSEIN BORBOR, who achieved such notable success during the time when he was in charge of the administration of the local orphanage, thereby aroused the anger of the people who formerly had taken their rake-off^represented by the economy effected by Borbor. (see para. 12 Feb. Diary). Rather than let him continue, the Mayor closed down the institution, and its inmates are now swelling the numbers ' of beggars and street-idlers. British interests. 9 . The Acting Vice-Consul visited Kermanshah on ?th April, returning on the 9 th. •jq # Two newspaper correspondents, Mr. Stephen Barber of the News Chronicle’' and Major Wyndham of the 'News of the World’', visited Hamadan on 14th April en route for Kermanshah. The former returned with Captain Roosevelt, American Military Attach, Tehran, on 22nd April, en route for Tehran. 11# Mr. Nevill Barbour, Assistant Director of the B.B.C’s Eastern Services, spent two days here ( 1 5th-1 6 th April) on his way to Baghdad. 12. Col. A.R. Watson, of A.D. Hirings and Disposals, Tehran, arrived on 16th April from Ahwaz. He cleared up all remaining questions concerning Hirings, and left for Kermanshah on the 17th. 13 . Mr. G.C. Boyle, Acting Vice-Consul, Kermanshah, arrived on 22nd April, and left for Tehran the following day. (Signed) R.M. Savory. Acting Vice-Consul, Hamadan. 3rd May 1946. Distribution:- Foreign Office H.M. Embassy, Tehran. H.M. Consulate-General, Tabriz. H.M. H.M. Consulate-General, Ahwaz. Consulate-General, Kermanshah. i mi ~r ~ ^CONFIDENTIAL. Kamadan Monthly Diar y, March 1946. ,cal. r I fOtPlIM ^1. . . Colonel HABIB-ul-.MOJAHDD.tn FATEMI.^Ke ' 0 X-ehiel of nj^jolice, (see ^ara. 4 Feb. Diary) le Hamadan for Teriran on 2nd /arch. He was sanguine enough to ex, ct to be posted to Arak* but the general opinion is that he will extremely fortunate to be reinstated before a decent interval oi time has elapsed. LOTI*I, one of the principal inspectors oi the Ministry of the Interior, returned to Tehran on March 28th after a lengthy stay in Hamadan. He was primarily concerned with the Police Department, but he also delved into the Justice and Finance Departments. As a result of his activities, Captain MESHKINGHALAM, a senior police officer, was arrested, along with numerous smaller fry. Thus the reign of Fatemi, who could keep order with a strong hand whatever else his faults - and they were many - is at an end. Previous complaints against his corrupt and vicious practices had always been pigeon-holed, because he had the pov/erful support of SEYYSD NAbhJLLAH BANISaDR, the v. scheming mollah, and the tacit approval of the Majles deputies for Hamadan, HA3GAN aLI FARMAND ^iAAGOBLU (ZIA-UL-MOLK) and KABbah MOiuiBE FAhAHMANB . ' • • • 2 . Various other changes have been made among the personnel of the police force. Captain RA’ODFI, formerly head of the C.I.D. in Abadan^ has replaced Captain HESMATI as Officer i/c Prison. Captain SA:*A'I has again been put in charge of the C.I.D. branch. (see para. 2 Nov. Diary.) Captain DGbLATBHAHI has be‘en promoted Major, and is now responsible for the central police post. f 3. During this month Tudeh activities have been very marked, I and their influence has undoubtedly increased greatly. The prestige of the ’Bdalat' party has waned proportionately. The scale of Tudeh propaganda has been stepped up, and whereas their number was less than a thousand at the beginning of the year, (see para, lb Jan. Diary.) the most conservative estimate now places it at 5,000. MOHANDES KdIVAB and NAbOOTI (para. 8 Feb. Diary.) have installed several loudspeakers in the '•Fcbatan' theatfre, and soapbox orators draw large audiences every night. Pugnacious action by Keivan caused aLIGHOLI DOULaTSHAKI to drop his id^a of forming a party from the more intellectual elements, while it v/as still no more than in an embr#yonic state. (see para. 1 Feb. Diary.) The Tudeh can boast of members from every Government Department, end thus they have a well-organised system for spying on all written and telegra phic communications with Tehran. The motives which prompt people to flock to the Tudeh banners are often obscure. Basically there would seem to be a desire to back the right horse. There would appear no other reason why such men as Dr. MIR bBPAOl, ol the Agriculture Department, and EGHBALI, former manager of the Agricul tural Bank, should be Tudeh supporters: not to mention a man lixe SA^A 1 !, the Head of the C.I.D. Others again are prompted by a desire for reform, and see the Tudeh party as a means to this end, apparently being blind to its origins and nature. An instance is Vi-uvLuI, Manager of the Bank-i-Melli. Even Keivan himsell poses as a patriotic Socialist. Although working with the Tudeh, whose support he reckons on to further his ambitions, he is not strictly a Tudeh member, and dislikes being associated with the party. The Tudeh themselves have no outstanding leaders; AsARMEHR, theii nominal head, is not a Hamadani and is not liked oy the populace. Therefore it is convenient for them to put forward Keivan as a candidate, because he is a man of greater capabilities and aaas intellectual 'tone 1 to their party. The Governor, aB^AU is treading on thin ice in his policy of appeasing tne iudeh. (para. 6 Feb. Diary.) The time will come when he must either toxe4- - 2 - , a firm line, or else capitulate. , There is no doubt that, as the weather becomes more clement, the Tudeh will extend their movemen to 13ae villages, although their efforts in this direction last year were on the whole ineffectual. It may well be that t e testing time for Salahi will be then. So far, however, he nas kept the peace, and has resolutely refused to allow preparations for the provincial counci]/elections to go forward, ^til ne feels he is on firmer ground. He left for Tehran on March 2£th. ^4. In spite of persistent reports that the 3rd. (Azerbaijan) Division is to be reformed in Hanadan, no such move is, in fact, contemplated. A few officers of this Division, who filtered through to Hamadan as they succeeded in evading the 'Democrats' 1 , have now joined their comrades in Tehran. The command of the troops at present in Hamsdan, who number some 500 trained men ana 700 recruits, was changed about the middle of the month. Col. Hi&amp;4ATTG.LLAH PAHLEVAb ftEJAD left for Tehran prior to taking up another post, and was replaced by Colonel CIJU.VCHDI. Col. Emamverdi has served for several years in Pars, in the Shiraz-ilazerun area, and is reported to have a good record. Now that the weather is improving, it is easier to supply the camp with foodstulxs stc., in spite of the fact that only four trucks are available for „his purpose. During the cold spell, however, lack of provisions wa s only one of a whole series of misfortunes of which Col. I 3 mamverdi complained. m he water pipes burst, and how there is insufficient piping for their needs: fuel oil could not.be transported to the camp, so charcoal and wood had to be burnt instead.. The electric light plant has been repaired and is working after a fashion, out the general standard of comfort cannot be rated as high as beloie, because the greater part of the movable equipment, including beds, blankets etc., has been used to provide ready cash. An effort has been made to find accommodation for the troops in oi* nnaiei tne town, but has failed. 5 . Dr. MOHAMMAD SHESDOOSH, Chief of the Health.Department, has not yet returned from Tehran, end Dr. GJbDLIis at present locum tenens at the Government Hospital. Conditions there, is usual in Dr. Sheedoush’s absence, have deteriorated considerably. 6 . Captain F^TiiPOOE, Chief of Gendarmerie, .has gone on leave to Tehran and Captain liAKJUK is acting for him. Eighty Gendarmes have been sent to Tehran, in spite of protests that they would be more useful here. SKAHZDEH 7 # IblviAlL MawSOOB left for Tehran on March 9th, returning on the 21st with his Belgian wife. The latter went out to their village at Serishebad on the 29th. They are contemplating returning to Belgium after Shahzdeh has cleared up his ousiness affairs. 8 . H0SS3IN GHOLI KHAlb v ^GO^LU (AMIR KiZahi), after changing his plans for a trip to Palestine, (para. 5 Nov. Diary.) l^ft io^ Karbala on March 23rd with his 16 yesr-old wife. 9 . SSYYED JAVAD Ti^JATABAI O-^ilS-Ul-IbLA.*), Head of the . Municipality, went to Qom for Nowruz, taking his numerous relatives with him. Malayer and District . 10 P The new Governor of Malayer, MOBa^B-uu xD^bhAi\, nas rone to Tehran to fetch his family. Ared 65, I obasser Hov.shsn canes ircm the Ministry of foreign Affairs. He has served as Iranian ConsUl at various places in Russia. The chief preoccupation of the Mayor and Assistant Governor of Malayer - - is once again ^ ® '■. u * &gt;r# Formerly the Governor of Nehavand, Azoodi is cooperating v.itn tneo 1 - 3 - Chief of Police, NSGAHBAN, in order to cope with the situation. The ^udeh have the active support of If0 VLAVIzjADEH, former Governor of Eorujird end a notoriously cori'upt administrator and virulent intriguer; T'ovlavizadeh, at present without a job, has taken up residence in Talayer end is encouraging the Tudeh to stage open demonstrations more frequently. The party received a further stimulus recently from the visit of RAHL.I NAIvIVaR, editor of the m ehran newspaper “Shahhaz'. Namvar came to Hamadan on March 29th. LJf’TudilAh, a prominent landowner and enemy of IfALEK IIajuANI, Majles f deputy for lalayer, is also one of the leading lights in the Tudeh t arty there. The ^Ilihan’* party is making a show of opposition, and both sides hold meetings around the main square. 12. Ja^ILI, former Governor of Assadabad, now holds a similar r ost in I.eh&amp;vand. ISMAIL zAI’FAhl (LnllAri-db-SOLT^u^j , the other I'ajles deputy for Malayer, is at present in hehsvand, where he holds large properties. 13. In Lalayer too the bazaar is very slack. Little business is being done in Malayer 1 s chief exports - almonds, raisins, walnuts and opium. There are, however, expectations of good crops of the latter, especially round Nehevand. Economic. 14. Between March 5th-7th the Acting Vice-Consul distributed 2,300 yds. of A.I.R.F. cloth among poor schoolchildren in the Government and National schools. 350 boys and 250 girls received lengths of khaki or poplin material respectively. 15. The present state of the bazaar is, in the opinion of many people, the worst since the entry of Allied troops into Persia in 1941. Prices generally remain at a phenomally high level, although the drop in the price of ’roghan’ from 400 Rials per kilos to 250 Rials is a welcome relief. Merchants are going bankrupt almost daily, and the withdrawal of the bulk of their credit by the Imperial Bank and the Bank-i-MeHi at the end of the current financial year has further aggravated an already unstable situation. Recently several trucks loaded with sugar left Tehran bound for Ramadan, but later turned up in Meshed or Tabriz. This serious loss has been hushed by the merchants involved. 16. The Governor, Salahi, the Mayor, An. JAILuNbrihlil, and the Chief of Police, A~Aik.AL, recently launched a drive to prohibit the sale of liquor on unlicensed premises.. They now claim that the * practice of shopkeepers and tea-house proprietors of selling by pegs any bottles of liquor they happen to have in stock has been stamped out. T-ritish Interests* 17. Mr. A.W. Davis, H.M. Consul, Kermanshah, visited Ramadan on March 26th, returning to Kermanshah the following day. American Interests . 12. Captain Roosevelt, American Military Attache, Tehran, visited Hamadan on March 30th. / Acting Vice-Consul, Hamadan. 2nd April 1946. Distribution :- Foreign Office.*/ H.M. anbassy, Tehran. H.M. Consulate-General, Tabriz. H.M. Consulate-General, Ahwaz. H.M. Consulate, Kermanshah. File. .v CONFIDENTIAL • Hamadan M&lt; ’ebrunry l£^o. Political, 9 Q 7 Q C jOJ i ap 194t ‘l # A new party, calling itself the 'Sazeman-i-Javanan', or 'Youth Society', has been formed in Hamadan. Composed nominally of the v/ealthier and more intellectual strata of society, its object is to counteract Tudeh activities relative to the provincial elections. It includes among its number two leading members of the Justice Department - MOHAMMaD OhSIZI, the Public Prosecutor, and ALIGHOLI DOULATSHAHI, one of the Interrogating Magistrates. The rank and file are recruited from the higher wage groups in the Government offices. 2 . The Tudeh, on the other hand, have been far from idle. Apart from a much-publicised meeting in the 'Mayak' Cinema on February 4th, they have held gathering on several occasions. The speeches, as usual, were merely ill-informed and fantastic distortions of the truth. 3. The Edalat party, whose total strength in Hamadan is about 230, met in opposition on February 15th in the Alvand Hotel. MA&amp;££, the party manager, was there, but none of the big influences behind the party were represented. The landed class was present in the person of YAMIN-UL-HOMAYUN, a member of the wealthy landowning family of Yamini, who own large properties in the Kazan district. 'T’he speakers were MALSK, who outlined the growth of the party since its inauguration in 1941; FARIDI, a well-known contractor, whose hesitant speech appeared to be in praise of the party ideals; and ARDABILI, the local agent for the 'Ettela’at' newspaper, who entered the more ambitious field of party politics generally. It can confidently be asserted that none of the parties in Hamadan inspire the slightest grounds for enthusiasm either for their members or their actions. 4 . Col. HABIB-UL-MOJAHEDIN FaTEMI had a new lease of life as Chief of Police, because his successor was unable to reach Hamadan owing to the conditions of the roads. The latter, at first reported to be the ex-Chief of Police from Tabriz - ZiA’I - finally turned out to be AZADKAD, who arrived on February 18th after a ten days 1 sojourn in Malayer waiting for the road to be opened. has also served in the North - in Tabriz, Goigan etc, and appears to have a loftier conception of the object of his position than his pre decessor. But perhaps it is too early to judge. FATSuil was still in Hamadan at the end of the month, ostensibly waiting until his daughter arrived from Kordestan, but actually until the legal proceedings instigated against him should be terminated. 5 # FATKPOOR, the new Chief of Gendarmerie, arrived in Hamadan at the beginning of February, but bad weather prevented him from seeing much of his area. 1T e too has v/orked for some ti.ae in the Caspian area, especially in Kasht. Apparently he did not get on well there with the Russians, who accused him of being a supporter of Seyd Zia. This story may, of course, be intended for consumption in other quarters. AHUAD SaLAKI, the Governor of Hamadan, is obviously an old hand at the political game. He has ingratiated himself with the Tudeh by subtle intimations that he sympathises ^ ltii d aspirations. On the fall of the Hekimi Gove innent, he stressed the hope of being promoted to Governor-General of thebthtstan. In this connection, he would prefer to see namaQo i “‘ c “ of the Governor-General.i - 2 - For all his diplomacy, Salahi has neverthe^less made enemies. One such alleged that he accepts money freely, and that as the Governor is merely a figurehead, his activity is only pretentious, whereas SAItDAK AKhAi. was quite justified in not taking his job seriouslyl It is undoubtly true, however, that had not Sardar Akram been at It is undoubfly true, however, that had not Sardar Akram been at loggerheads with his wife, he would now have had a good chance of staging a come-back, as his wife is the niece of Qavam-es-Saltaneh. i-iANSOOK returned from Qorveh on February l&lt;*th. On account of the snow he had never reached his village of Serishabad (see para. 7 Jan. Diary) and it took him fifteen days to do the '±0 miles from Qorveh to Hamadan, which he accomplished partly on foot and partly on horseback. He now owns quite a fleet of trucks, but again owing to the weather his wheat-transporting contract has expired with only one-fifth of his allocation completed. Shahzdeh, freed from the restraining influence of Major Simmons, Regional Grain Adviser to the Kharbar, is now recouping his losses by selling his wheat on the black market. This appears to point to ccmpic ity on the part of the Chief of the Kharbar - AiwbL HJSSjlIxm MOG hTADLn, 8 . As the time for the provincial elections approaches, the political line-up becomes clearer. The chief candidates for the riPdit-wing parties include the RAIS-UL-ISLAi^, Head of the Munici pality, and SEYD ImaSROLLAH BANIS^DR, one of the principal mollahs. GH0LA1I H0SSJ2IN KHAN AMIRI, the nephew of AMR NEAAM, is the only garagezlu representative to have returned from Tehran so far. Consequently the whole burden of furthering the interests of his family has fallen on him, and his present existence is rather hectic. The most prominent left-wing candidates are KAIVAN and NAbOpTI, the manager of the. 'Ekbatan' Theatre. regard to the general elections also, there is much intrigue and manoeuvring for position. 9 . The new Chief of Posts and Telegraphs is HaVIpI. His 'redecessor, AHMAD dAHRAMI, used to allow telegrams accusing the police of misdemeanours to be read before despatch by the Chief of Police, Col. Fatemi r er and District. 10 MOHASSER ROWSHAN is reported to have succeeded ZbiN-UL- ABHDIN SADRI as Governor of the ’Selas' - i.e. Malayer, TuiserKan and Nehavand. Sadri kept order with a strong hand, but was ex tremely venal, noticably being the servant of MALM the Malles deputy for Malayer. The Chief of Gendarmerie ol ..ehavand has been trahsfered to the corresponding post in Lalayer. •Sconomic. 11 The excessively heavy snows which fell during.the early part of February to an overall depth of 3ft., with dnIts irc:n 10-15 ft. deep, not only caused much hardship to travellers, man;* of whom were snowbound for periods up to three weeks, but also disrupted the economic life of the city, “itt 1 ® f &lt;?° a H ® h * reached Hamadan from the villages, andthebreadsituationatone time threatened to be serious. The A.I.O.C. etoclcs of crude oil and gas-oil were exhausted, and when kerosene aid not their purpose, the bakers were obliged to ^venTof t0 bum wood, as they w-ere accustomed to ° th %, rnor h as requested plentiful supplies of fuel oil. Salahi, th 9 Governor, nas e ^ GHOhAH HOSSEIN BORDOR, the local a.I.O.--. ’ ^ ^ supplement the installation of further storage tan.es for gas on t-o the one small one at present in use. 12. Gholam Hossein Horbor is of the few^eopU in Ha^dan who ar« genuinely trying to relieve in sene measui-u ;.. . - 3 - of economic distress now afflicting large sections of tte community. lie is aiming at providing some form of work for the unemployed, not merely the dole. He is now engaged'on the thank less task of extracting contributions from various well-known personalities. After the many high-sounding philanthropic schemes of Agiir hezam, which usually produced but meagre material results, it is cheering to meet an honest endeavour to produce concrete Jjrenefits. Borbor admits, however, that he finds the universal Carrier of indifference and personal enmities and crass selfishness not only discouraging but practically insuperable. Borbor is one of the supervisors of the local orphanage. Within a short time he cut expenditure from 12,000 tomans to 5,000 tomans mo.nthly - only to find that under the regulations the orphanage administration he cannot transfer an economy effected under one head to expenditure on another item, for example to provide better food than the pre sent miserable allowance. Security . 13. 'T’he security of the city generally remains poor. The collusion of the erstwhile Chief of Police, Faterai, with the gangs of housebreakers and petty thieves did nothing to improve it. If the new Chief, Azadrad, lives up to his reputation and the favour able Impression he has created to date, then this may be remedied. British Interests. 14... Captain D.w. Pritchard, Hirings Officer, returned to Kemanshah on February 15th. 15. The Rev. Paul Seto, of the American Presbyterian Mission, arrived in Hamadan on February 20th, accompanied by his American wife. It is understood that Mr. Seto will study the language in Hamadanjprior to being posted elsewhere. • Li e^/rW Acting Vice-Consul, .Hamadan. 11th March 1946. Distribution:- Foreign Office. ^ H.M. Smbassy, Tehran. H.M. Consulate-General, Tabriz. H.M. Consulate-General, Ahwaz. H.M. Consulate, Kermanshsh. File.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0000f7_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/3685</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0000f7</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/3685</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 29/107(1) 'Hamadan: monthly diary'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1946/1947</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-09-26T22:05:01</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (51 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 53; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains copies of Hamadan monthly diaries from February 1946 to May 1947, by the HM Vice-Consul at Hamadan, sent to the Secretary of State for India by the Foreign Office.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>British Vice-Consul</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Hamadan</geographic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Secretary of State for India and Burma, United Kingdom</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0000f7#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>