<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000199_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-18T04:31:41.050Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">No.l/V.O. O- W -A- -A. WO. jjatec the let January 1935 To His Excellency Snaikh Sir Hamaa bin f Isa al Khalifah, K.G.I.E., C.S.I., Ruler of Banrain. After compliments, Just after Your Excellency left me this morning I receivea a telegram from our friend the Honourable Lieut-Golonel T.C.Fowle, Political Resinent in the Persian u ulf asking me to convey to Your excellency his best congratulations on the honour which His Majesty the king has been pieaseu to bestow upon you. 1 should also line to take this opportunity of repeating the congratulations which x was so delightea to give to.Your excellency personally this morning. Usual ending. ■M-Printed in England. (Aug. 1984.) (Message-Form 5/171). . CABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED. (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND? From / *2, No. of Words i -Date- To Time , m. Remarks-% .. © . ^ y* * ^ V U- ^ ' Ai ^^’J*^ ji ( &gt; - S S 1 -^-&gt; Vj o \ &amp; \J^\ : Or- &lt;S * 'Jj&gt; ■ ■ C ' V ' yj^-^ ' is l \^J* J- ^ «'^jL 'W u. i&gt;^ ^^Ok-xS^s' y ^ oj L* -A^ 11 ^ -A Translation of letter dated 25th Ramadhan 1353(equivalent to the 1st January 1935) from His Excellency Shaikh Sir Hamad bin f Isa al Khalifah,K.C*I.E. ,C.S.I.Ruler of Bahrain, to Colonel Loch Political Agent,Bahrain. After Compliments. X was gald to receive your kind letter Ho.l of 1935 in which you informed me of the congratulations of our friend the Honourable Lieut-Colonel T.C*Fowle,political Resident in the Persian Gulf to me on the occasion of the honour which has been bestowed on me by His Britannic Majesty the King. I again beg to thank his Honour and you for your everlasting sincerity and hope that the Almighty may give you every good fortune. Usual Ending. J.MNO.3/V.0. Political Agency, Bahrain. Datec the 2na January 1935. To His Excellency Shaikh Sir hamaa bin T Isa al Khalifah, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Ruler ol Bahrain. Alter Compliments, I am very pleasee to.inform Your Excellency tnat the Air Officer Commanaing British Forces in ’ira^ telegrapnea to me yesterday evening asking me to convey his neartiest congratulations on tne Honour which His Majesty the King has been pleased to bestow upon you. Usual Ending.I %NO.4/V.0. To Political Agency,^anrain Da tea the hru January 1 j35. His Excellency Shaikh Sir Hama bin T Isa ii 1 Rile.liian, o• o• i• j Huler oi Banrain. Aiter Complinents, I am very pleasea to inform Your Excellency that I receives a telegram from His Excellency tne Naval Oonimanaer-in- Chief asking me to say that His Excellency has heard with much pleasure of the Honour conferreu on you by His i.Iajesty tue King Emperor ana desires to offer his congratulations. Usual Enaing.No.5/V.O. Political Agency,Bahrain. La ten the 3ra January 1935. n To His excellency Shaikh Sir Hanaa bin T isa al Knalifan, K.C.i.e., O.S.I., Ruler of Bahrain. After Compliments, I am very pleaseu to inform Your excellency that I nave receiveo a telegram from the Senior Naval Officer in the Persian Gulf asking me to inform Your Excellency that the Officers ana men of the Persian Gulf Division join him in heartily congratulating Your excellency on the Honour conferred on you. Usual hneimr.(1 i Telegram G. T. C. / Dated His Excellency Sir F.H. Hunrphrys, G.C.m.G. , etc.etc. His Majesty*s Ambassador, British Eiribassay, Baghdad. Political Agent, Bahrain. Nil 4th January 1934. Please offer His Excellency the Shaikh of Bahrain my most sincere congratulations on honour which has been conferred on him by the King Hunrphrys % V ¥ *1 * (t H.C. Draft r.iace anu submitted for approval,please. o.1•Bo ^ 1 '0 No: /V'.O. Political Ajency,Bahrain La tec tile 5tn January 19B5. To IIis nxctllency Shaikii Sir iiamaa bin T Ioa ill Khalil'h, G.S.I., Ruler of Bahrain. After Compliments, I am very pleased to inform Your Excellency that I have received a telegram from his excellency Sir F.K.Humphrys, G.C.M.G., G.G.V.O., C.I.E., Kis Majesty^ Amhassaaor,Baghdad asking me to offer to Your Excellency his most sincere congratulations on the honour which nas been conferred on you by His majesty the xing. Usual Ending.fjj- Wi' ^ ^&gt;) v_^»&gt;) Jl ^'-X&gt;jjt__, ^ 1^ ' * o* ci^J^ V'^^eUJu V^ ^ iZ*** 0 &gt;\i ^t 5 ' ^ ^ c^. ^ Vo f \ ' °S*^ J cj' X- ‘ Vlr \&gt; l Translation of letter dated. 28tn Ramadhan^ 1353(equivalent to 4.1.1935) from H.E.Shaikh Sir Hamao bin isa al !'halifah,F.C.I.E.,G.S.I.,Ruler of Bahrain, to the Political Agent, Bahrain. After Compliments. 1 have receiver your kina letter No.5 of 1935 conveying the best congratulations of our friend His Excellency the Senior Naval Officer in the Persian Gulf to me for the honour which has been bestowed on me by His Majesty the Ping of Great Britain. This will, no doubt, be as a sign of his sincerity towards me. I request you to kindly convey my many.thanks to him for his kina feeling.No 1 26 Political Agency, Bahrain, the 6th January 1935, From Lieutenant-Colonel Gordon Loch, I.A*, Political Agent, Bahrain♦ To Sir, The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. i I have the honour to refer to your telegram Noj1277 dated the 1st January 1935 and to say that His Excellency Shaikh Sir Hamad bin ^sa Al Khalifah has written asking me to convey to you his warm thanks for your kind congratulations on the honour, which His Majesty the King has been pleased to bestow upon him* I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Lieut*Colonel, Political Agent, Bahrain.BY MR MAIL , ! C Lieut.Colonel Political Agent, Bahrain. NO *27 Political Agency, Bahrain, the 6th January 1935. From Lieutenant-Colonel Gordon Loch, I.A., Political Agent, Bahrain. To The Air Officer Commanding, British Forces in * Iraq, Baghdad . I have the honour to refer to your telegram No*1330 dated the 1st January 1935 and to say that His Excellency Shaikh Sir Hamad bin 'Isa Al Khalifah has written asking me to convey to you his warm thanks for your kind congratulations on the honour, which His Majesty the King has been pleased to bestow upon him. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient s ervant, LV . Lieut, Colonel, Political Agent, Bahrain, BY AIR MAIL. No: 30 Political Agencyi Bahrain, the 6th January 1935, From Lieutenant-Colonel Gordon Loch, I.A., Political Agent, Bahrain, To Sir His Excellency the Commander-in-Chief, East Indies Station, H,M*S, Hawkins at Basrah, I have the honour to refer to your telegram No:1106 dated the 2nd January 1935 and to say that His Excellency Shaikh Sir Hamad bin * Isa Al Khalifah has written asking me to convey to you his warm thanks for your kind congratulations on the honour, vi/hich His Majesty the King has been pleased to bestow upon him. 1 have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, r&gt;- r'N BY AIR ’'ML . No: 31 From @ Political Agency, Bahrain, the 6th January 1936. Lieutenant-Colonel Gordon Loch, I.A., Political Agent, Bahrain. To The Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf Division, H.M.S. Shoreham at Basrah* f r Sir, / I have the honour to refer to your telegram N 01 O 6 IO dated the 2nd January 1935 and to say that His Excellency Shaikh Sir Hamad bin •Isa Al Khalifah has /written asking me to convey to you his warm thanks for your kind congratulations on the honour, which His Majesty the King has been pleased to bestow upon him* I have the hoiour to bSj Sir, Your most obedient servant, 4 4^- Lieut.Colonel, Political Agent, Bahrain.NO. 61 Dated the 12th January 1936 I have the honour to refer to your telegram dated the 4th January 1936 and to say that Hie Excellency Shaikh Sir Hamad bin # Isa Al Khalifah has written asking me to convey to you hie warm thanks for your kind congratulations on the honour, which His Majesty the King has been pleased to bestow upon him* Your most obedient servant, Lieut*Colonel Political Agent, Bahrain* » His Excellency Sir Francis Humphrys, U.C.M.G*, 1.C.V.0*, K*3*E», C.I.3 His Britannic Majesty*s Amba&amp;Bi His Britannic Majesty*s Ambassador British Embassy, Baghdad * »\)o D.O. The Residency, Bushire ,10th January 1935. Cvd-AA. I enclose herewith a letter of congratulation on his recent honour to Shaikh Haimd which please forward to him. p. c.. lolitical Agent, Bahrain.—v. % D.O. No.48/V.O. The 22na January 1935. My uear Fowle^ ' ^ Will you kindly refer to your demi-official letter fto.GG datea the 10th January 1935. Your letter of congratulation was forwardea to His Excellency Shaikh Sir Hamad bin T Isa al Khalifah, who has askea me to senu you the enclosea reply. Yours sincerely The Honourable Lieutenant Colonel T.C.Fowle.C.B.S., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, B U S H i R E./ Telegram Gr-T-C* From Political Agent (on tour), Fowey. To Acting Political Agent, Bahrain. Unnumbered. Bated (and received ) 9th Feoruary 19b5. i Please inform Shaikh that Shaikh Sha^hout om Sultan sends hearty congratulations on his honour. Please try to have reply reach me oeiore U900 Sunday. - political &lt;rt.*Cut. /H r '✓y. ^^-y ^&lt;sjjy&gt;' (w&gt; v w i.y 1 Ji;&gt;^ | --1-3 — ’ ^ f- Ly&gt; vi \f&gt;y*? u ' '&gt; ( ^ifj’ '^&gt; irii IN. Translation of letter dated 6th Thul Qada 1353(equivalent to 10.2.35 from K.E.Shaikh Sir Hamad bin T Isa al Khalifah,K.C.I.E#,C.S.I.,Ruler of Bahrain, to the Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain. L After Compliments. / i I have received your kinu letter No.77 of 1935 in which you informed me that our friend Colonel Loch has communicatee to you the hearty congratulation of Shaikh Shaikhbut bin Sultan,Euler of Abu Lhabi to me on the honour conferred on me by His Majesty the King of Great Britain. I thank you for conveying this information to me ana hope that you will send them my best thanks. Usual Ending. J.M. 11.2.35I •» 'A Telegram T. C. i'rom Colonel G* Loch, v/arship Kowey* TO Acting Political Agent, Bahrain Ho Nil Dated 12th February 1S35. please telegraph if possible today reply from Shaikh Hamad to message of congratulations from Shaikh ShakhbutI'elegram From TO No. Dated Ci. T. c. Political Agent, Bahrain. Colonel C.Loch, '.varship Fowey. 39 The 12th February 1935. , ' g ' 1 Your telegram dated 9th February «/ Bhaikh Hamad asKS me in writing to convey his best thanks to shaikh Shakhbut bin Sultan -PoliticalsNo* 755 Dated the 2nd April 1937 CIRCULAR. His Majesty The King has been graciously pleased to approve that in Tuture all British Authorities shall address His Highness Shaikh Sir Hamad bin *Isa A1 Khalifah K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Ruler of Bahrain, by the title of 'His Highness' instead of 'His Excellency'. Lieutenant-Colonel, Political Agent, Bahrain. The Adviser to the Bahrain Government. The Director of Customs and Port Officer. The State Engineer. The Quarantine Medical Officer. The Sub-Postmaster. The Observer in Charge, Upper Air Observatory. The Eastern Bank Limited. Messrs. Gray, Mackenzie and Company Limited. Cable and Wireless Limited. The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limite&lt; Petroleum Concessions Limited. The Arabian Mission, ^ The Mukhi of the Hindu Community, ntj ■ i The Head of the Indian Bohra Community The Head of the Indian MuslimsHi i ■mi i : ! '•w S^ i.a. i:o.?sc D. tac tne ilnd April iJZ7&lt; Dear Smith, I Lnciosc l copy oi’ Circular Ivo# 735 dated the i’nci j priX 1J37 and request you kindiy to have it cir culated among the members of the Bahrain Petroleum Comp* ny limited* Yours sincerely. Smith, ] squire. Chief Coca! Hepresent tive. The Bahrain Petroleum Company limited. Be hr Lin*■■■■■ No. ?; &gt; The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to: The Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf Division, H.M.S. 'Shoreham” and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document (s); The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Golf. Dated... Reference to previous correspondence : Descript'nni of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Circular No, 7 d 5 dated the 2nd April 1037. Style of address of the Shaikh of Bahrain. i 1I No. 8*) - ! of 1362 Office of the Adviser to the Government, Bahrain Dated, Moharram 13, 1362 January 20, 1943 H. B. M f s Political Agent, Bahrain. Memorandum: - His Highness Shaikh Sir Salman bin Hamad AlKhalifah desires the enclosed letter to be sent to Lieut: Colonel W.R. Hay^through you^please. Enel.... S.Z.U KUiiu 'i 1' AIR '.’AIL No. 7G4 Political Agency| iirain, 14th April 1943 To Tlie Amr/ and Navy Stores, United Ssplanade Road, Fort, 'tomb- y. Dear Sirs, ill you plonse supply COO invitation c rds v/ith envelopes to match as described V low i~ Size and ciualit:/ : Same as, or as close as possible to, sample enclosed. -idee : Gold ednfed Inscriptions On 200 cards, as in sheet attached to sample card, in *old lettering with Residency crest in gold as in sample enclosed (or lesser size as may be convenient). On 400 cards, no inscription, but only gold crest. Envelopes : Gold crested 2. The cards should be posted to no and it is essential that they should reach Bahrain by the 25th May. if there is any doubt as to their reaching me by that date if posted ^y sea mail baey should be despatched by air mail. Yours faithfully,$ L^ q8 - y • ' L i 3 ARMY &amp; NAVY STORES LIMITED (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND) TELEPHONE 13 O A4 B AY TELEGRAMS 15 001 'ARMISTICE'’ POST BOX N9 5 TELEPHONE 2 5 001 TELEGRAMS 'ARMISTICE'’ HEAD OFFICE: 105 VICTORIA STREET, LONDON BRANCHES: CALCUTTA &amp; NEW DELHI. Ref: 0/27837/5A 28th April, 1943. AIR MAIL. The Secretary to The Political Resident In the Persian Gulf, c/o. The Political Agent, Bahrain• * In enclosing two proofs of the invitation cards for your approval and append below the cost:- To engraving a copper plate for Invitation cards 'A” at .. •• Rs.42-0-0 ”A” to copper plate, printing 200 Invitation caras in gold cresting complete with envelopes to match crested .. •• .. Rs.96-8-0 'B” 400 invitation cards without inscription but crested on top with envelopes to match crested Rs.111-3-0 A telegram stating 'proceed , A f and f B* in vitation cards will be understood as instructions to print off and forward by sea mall. We do not however anticipate that they will reach you by May 25th. We would require your express instructions and acceptance of all air mail charges which would be in the neighbour hood of Rs.300/- if you wish them sent by Air Mail. Dear Sir Further to your order No.764 we have pleasure We are, Lear Sir, Yours faithfully, Ara.’.Y &amp; navy stores limited. U - Enel: S.12I 8J O No. c ]jt&gt; -20/9. Political Agancy, —^ Bahrain* la tad the 5th R!ay 1943* To The Hon’ble the Political Has.ident in the Persian Gulf* Bushir?' • D Memorandum . Reference my telegran No. 144 dated the 4th May 1943. 2* I enclose a specimen Invitation Card as sent by the Army and Navy Stores and approved by me on your behalf* Qjt-' [Political Agent, Bahrain.■■■■■■ '.f. 1 ^ X&gt; — V/ ^ &gt; Tel G.T.C. &amp; From Britconsul , Bushire To Political 9 Bahrain No. 1015 la ted &amp; Recd.5-5~43 IMPORTANT Your telegram 144 May 4th. Sea nail repeat sea mail. 2. Please send here copies of your order and specimen of cards. ERITCONSULTO PREVENT MISTAKES ATTENTION 18 CALLED TO THE IMPORTANCE OF LEGIBLE WRITING. Printed in England. Aug. 1941. (4Q730 pads.) CABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED. (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND.) ** Charge. OFFICE STAMP AND DATE. Clerk’s Name, No. and Circuit and Time forwarded. No. - Official ' Instructions hrvieHiai^ 4^ No. Words Time InstrucWori to be _SjignaMe&lt;L TO Name Address IMPORTANT ARMISTICE BOMBAY YOUR A LB * TK * ^RIL 28th PLSASJi .:. PBOCSSD- AHD B UJVITA TIGS' CARDS AIT ID SHOT SEA MAIL POLITICAL 151 I mswt mat tfc. «*«.« Tttacrsm «•» ** •ww»r4»4 MklKt to tin cmSMsm prtatoS tm Sack *t toil h» •htok I sens to to toaaS. Signature of Sender — Telephone No (Not to be telegraphed) ' P ' 1CONDITIONS. • \ 1. The Company or any Telegraph Company or Government- Telegraph Administration, by whom this telegram is or would in the ordinary course of the telegraphic service be forwarded, may decline to forward such telegram although it has been received for that purpose ; but in such case the amount paid for transmission will be refunded to the sender at his request. 2. Neither the Company nor any Telegraph Company, or Government Telegraph Administration, by whom this telegram is or would in the ordinary course of the telegraphic service be forwarded, nor any of their respective officers or servants shall be liable to make compensation for aqy loss, injury or damage arising or resulting from non-transmission or non-delivery of the telegram, or delay or error or omission in the transmission or delivery thereof, through whatever cause such non-transmission, non-delivery, delay, error, or omission shall have occurred even though occasioned by the neglect or default of such Company or Administration or any officer or servant in their employ. 3. This telegram shall be forwarded in accordance with the provisions of the International Telegraph Regulations and the provisions of such Regulations shall be deemed to be binding between the sender and this or any Telegraph Company or Government Telegraph Administration by whom this telegram is or would in the ordinary course of the telegraphic service be forwarded. 4. The above mentioned conditions also apply to telegrams tendered to or delivered by the Company by telephone, over a private line, or by any other means whatsoever. NOTE.—Code words used in the text of telegrams must not contain more than 5 letters. The use of accented letters is not permitted in code words. By International Regulations, the sender of a telegram is obliged to produce the code from which the text or part of the text in code has been compiled if requested by the office of origin. ' // figures and groups of figures, including commercial marks containing figures and letters, are used in code telegrams directed to extra-European destinations, their number, reckoned in accordance with the Rules for charging, must not exceed one half of the number of chargeable words in the text and signature. Full information respecting code telegrams may be obtained from any of the Company’s Branches. : Ion.Th« first line of thle Telegram contains the following particulars in the order named :— Prefix Letter! and Number of Menage, Office of Origin, Number of Words, Date, Time handed in and Official instructiona—if any. Printed in England. Aug 1941. (9,000 pads) % CABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED. (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND.) CV46/W BOMBAYSUB 3^ l 8 ML KR ANTEN - LC POLITICAL AGENT BAHRAIN - EXPORT TRADE CONTROLLER DECLINES TO GRANT US EXPORT LICENCE FOR INVITATION CARDS MAKING FURTHER REPRESENT AT I Of* STOP YOUR STIPULATED DELIVERY DATE IN ANY EVENT x ' • ' . ; i IMPOSSIBLE PLEASE AGAIN CONFIRM SEA OR AIRMAIL ARMY ADM NAVY ST ' s D2a Jm/ieJuaC ' T tfe MARK YOUR REPLY NO ENQUIRY RESPECTING THIS TELEGRAM CAN BE ATTENDED TO WITHOUT PRODUCTION OF THIS COPY.i .3?. - f *T &amp;' 3 EXPRESS LETTER. From To Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, BUSHIRE. Political Agent, BAHRAIN. No.544-S. Dated the 16th June 1943. My telegram 1126 May 19th. I ! • Army and Navy Stores state invitation cards were despatched to Bahrain on 26th May in two parcels. Please retain against my arrival. Sd. C.G.PRIOR. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. ATTESTED. for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. *DEPARTMENT/OFFICE. Letter File No. Serial No. Draft Memorandum Telegram</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000199_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1674</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000199</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1674</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File No 20/9 Honours &amp; Ceremonials:- Corr. re: Grant of title of K.C.I.E, to H. E. Shaik Sir Hamad bin `Isa Al Khailifah, on 1st Jany 1935.'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1935/1943</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-12-10T12:46:25</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (62 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in chronological order from the front to the rear of the file. Folios 57- 63 are file notes.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 64; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 2-63; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains correspondence regarding the grant of the title of KCIE (Knight Commander of the Order of the Indian Empire) to His Excellency Shaikh Sir Hamad bin `Isa Al Khalifa. Letters of congratulation regarding the appointment were conveyed by the Political Agent in Bahrain Percy Gordon Loch to Shaikh Hamad bin ‘Isa Al-Khalifa. These were sent by British Officials and Gulf Rulers including the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, Trenchard Craven William Fowle, the British Ambassador in Baghdad, and Shaikh Shakhbut bin Sultan, Ruler of Abu Dhabi. There are also letters from Shaikh Hamad to the Political Agent asking him to convey his thanks to those who congratulated him.The file contains a circular dated 1937 that King George VI has approved that in future all British Authorities shall address Shaikh Hamad by the title ‘His Highness’ instead of ‘His Excellency’. The file also contains correspondence between the Political Agency in Bahrain, the Political Residency in the Persian Gulf and the Army and Navy Stores regarding the later supplying invitation cards to the Agency.The main correspondence is between the Political Agency, Bahrain, the Political Residency in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, Shaikh Hamad bin `Isa Al Khalifa, and the Army and Navy Stores.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>King of Bahrain</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Orders</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000199#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>