<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000419.0x0000d7_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-19T06:41:05.486Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">b&amp;ohrtft su III a 15763. • Anlave 1. (Signed and sealed) Salem ben Sultan. At the request of Sheikh Salem ben Sultan I hereby cer tify till that is written down in this paper. (signed and sealed) Abdul Rahman ben Fares Servant of Law. 25 In the name of merciful and almighty God. This document appears in two copies. Be it known to every body that I Salem ben Sultan ben Sagher El Kasemi have leased all the mines of oxyde of iron which are in the island of Abu Musa to the generous Haji Hass an ben Ali Semey y Abdulla ben Hasson and Isa ben Abdul Latif from to-day for any period they choose to possess the said minesy paying us annually 250 Dollars. I have also agreed with them against payment of a rent of $ 100 y - per annum to allow them to discharge mother of pearls shells if they desire it. I have permitted them to dig wells for workmen employed in the oxyde mines. I bind myself to show their employees of the oxyde mines protect ton-and benevo lence. Should I at any former date have made any contracts they are not valid,only this contract which is written in 2 identical copies holds good. This I hereby declare openly. Enforce from this 18. day of Zilkade 1315. Witness to this: 1) Set his hand Yoosef ben Abdullah 2) Set his hand and seal Abdul Latif ben Abdul Rahman 3) Set his hand and seal Ahmed ben Abdul Rahmen 4) I set my signature and seal to contents of this docu ment. Ahmed ben Sultan (Brother of Sheikh Salem) . 88507.An! age 3. In the name of .merciful and almighty (sd.and sld.) Seger ben Khalet. This document appears in two copies. In accordance with the contents of this contract I f Sheikh Seger ben Khalet ben Sul tan fi hi of of Shargeh 9 enter into partnership from this date with Haji Hasson ben Ali Semey f Abdulla ben Hasson and Isa ben Abdul Latif in the mines of oxjjde of iron in the island of Abu Musa which they have got in lease from Sheikh Salem for an annual payment of Z 250.-. for so long as the mines are workable and in lease.And I Sheikh Seger also agree to endeavour and render all assistance in my power fo?' facilitating the work of the mines.For instance if they wish to have boats for transporting and men. for working in the mines that could be available in Sha,rgeh t after settling their vxiges that they agree upon I bind myself to send with all quickest despatch to the island. I also agree to enter into partnership regarding the rent arranged with Sheikh Salem ben Sultan for # 100.per annum for discharging m. o .p. shells in the island of Abu Musa and whatever* expenses may be incurred in working the mines of the oxyde of iron they shall be borne by all the partners in the contract of the said oxyde mines and whatever the. nett profit may amount to f will be divided amongst them all. Be i t known Dated l.Rabi ul Sani 1316* \7i tness . Set his hand and seal Ahmed Ben Sultan (Brother of Sheikh Salem) Set his hand and seal Abdul Latif ben Abdul Rahmen Set his hand Ahmed ben Abdul Rahmen.4 , ; A, &lt; jnlagg 5« fw .vr 28 Contract between Mrjia&amp;san h&amp;n Ali Smey owner and holder of Ben Xussa Con- i cession and Robert IVoncKhaus in Lingah* L Hasson ben Semey agrees to deliver to far .Robert WonQ%hausf-&lt; s t Linoah during 4 years (four year's) beginning with 1 June t° 5000 * ■ * ^ 1906 every year SOOO^tons of 20 cats oxyde of iron of ~ne / J * island Ben Mussa,same quality as the 700 tons shipped by Mr. jJT# # Robert Wane)chaus in March 1906.Mf .Rob I’fbnckhaus agreek to m w ?, — take at least every year 2000 tors and if he wants so and there is sufficient good stuff on the island of which he ap- provek.up to 50QG tons yearly. The price is fixed at 15 sh.6 d.(fifteen shillings 6 pence) per ton of 20 cwts t usualweight conditions,fob -free on board steamer Ben Mussa, to be weighed on board* Hasson ben Semey gives the entire monopoly of Abu Mussa Oxyde to ^.Robert Wbnckhaus during the term of the contract he is rot allowed to self, or dispose of otherwise any quantity of Ben Mussa. during the term, of this it is agreed upon that Hasson is permitted to export to India far his account during this year what he has sold already in India, and which he gives as 700 tons (Seven hundred) ,arui besides that every year from 1907 about 5-6000 bags Of 1 cwts („our thousand to five thousand bags^Hassan ben Semey has to daily alongside if in bags 2uO tons,or in bulh 150 ton., wheather permitting .Pay/ment for every lot which is to shipped, half the amount when the lot is ordered and the other (it u . r . „ half when (it is being shipped. s Advance to be paid by ^.Robert Voenclchaim to Hasson ber Semey R S , 2000 . -(Two thousand) whenever Hassan mUs for itand receipt to be taKen for it .This advance to remain with Hasson ben Jemey until the end of this contract. Whenever this contract comes to an end Mr.Robert Woenck- haus\ haU the preferenc e for a new contract of Ben Mussa if he desires so, at the same price and condition or at any rate at the price of other serious buyers.Alcrte the English text of contract will hold good. Lingah,l s t June 1906. 3tgned:Hag&amp; Hasson ben Aly Semey&amp;Co.' i ■■TOlWlliilwit^ 11 j, i IfflP Anlag# 4ra. 29 • *&gt; -J i .o in the name of ..... . *3od. In accordance with the contents of this contmct we 9 who have mentioned our names in this contract^have taken into partnership Sheikh Jaker bin Khaled in the lease hold of mines of uxide of Iron in the Island of Abu Musa which we have taken in lease from Sheikh Salem bin Sultan for an annual payment of Jl H50 and $ 100 as vent if we discharge m.o.p.shells in Abu Musa for commercial purposes. Sheikh Saker has also arranged with us to render all possible assistance in his power in order to avoid any stoppage (delay) of work in the mines of the red oxide of iron;and whatever expenditure of the mines may amount to shall be borne by all the partners and the nett profits u&gt;:Ji be divided amongst them all.On this condition the contract is concluded.Be this knownl Ana aheUchSaker has the full power to get out of this partnership of the said Oxide of Iron, if ha chooses to do so. Dated Rubio Scxni 1316. (sd.and sld.) Hasson bin Ali Semey ye Abdullah bin Hasson Isa bin Abdul Latif. V/i tness (sd.and al l.) Abdul Latif bin Abdul Rahman. Anlape 4b . In the name of • • • vT ^ U/ * 3e it known to whosoever sees this paper that this partnership f regarding the oxide oj iron in which 1 9 in ac cordance with this document, transfer to YoasiJ bin Abdullah and same ds hts and he has the power to make me of it.I have nothing more to do with it.Prof its and losses concern himhim only arid unto him is due from me all possible assistance^ in case he meets with any difficulty in this.Be this Known Dated 17^ Ramazan 1316. (sd.and sld.) SaKer bin Khaled. Anlage 4c. In the name of God. Well:I f Yoosif bin Abdullah,sold to Haji Hassan bin Ali Semey ye all and entire share of oxide mines mentioned herein and which I have obtained f^om Sheikh SaKer bin Khaled.The the mentioned snare is nowdproperty of Haji Hassan bin Ali Semey ye and I renounce all my rights in the said Share.I have received payment of a sum of % 400 being the price thereof. Witness* Dated 15 th Shaban 131J. (sd.and sld.J Yoosif bin JOialed. (sd.and sld.) Abdul Latif bin Abdul Rahman. Anla ge 4d. ] 9 Haji Hasson bin Ali Semey ye hxxve sold to Mr.Th.Brown all and entire share of the oxide mines mentioned herein which I have obtained by purchase from Yoosif bin Abdullah and the said Share is now the property of Mr.Thomas Brown ana it is his and I renounce all rights to it.Prof its all losses concern him only.I have received &amp;s 6000 being the price of the share. Dazed 10 th October 1907. (sd.and sld.) Haji Hassan bin Semey ye. Anlage 4e. Diesen meinen Anteil heute mit alien Rechten und Verpfl ich- tungen gegen die Summe von Rs.ll 000 -elfzausend- an die Herren Robert Wonckhaus und Co.verKauft zu haben,bescheini- ge ich hiermit. Lingah ,16. Oktober 1907. ges: Thomas Brown. i aAnlaae 6. Shargeh 9 21 .Rabl ul Sant 1324. From Abdul Latif 'ben Abdul Rahmen to Hajt Hasson ben Alt After compl une/its .Your former and present letter have reached me and it gives me pleasure to note that you crre in good heal th.What you have written regarding the question of the oxide of iron which by the will of God you sold to Woencft- haus the German at 15/- a ton and arranged to deliver 2000 tons every year and all the expenses to be paid you his price being net- allright.I hope it is good.lt is a pleasure after all the trouble. Abdul la under all circumstances must be recalled to supervise the worK as it would not go on properly which may res mile a lease-held or any other engagements which might occasion any row.Our officials would be displeased and would not like it.You by the mercy of God are wise and will not show any negligence because in these days there are a lot of tricks played by people.In short this news gives pleasure in case we (net put into difficulties as in former Semey. without him.But abstain from engaging yowself in any contract years. (signed) Abdul Latif ben Abdulla Rahman.7) 31 /nlape 7. }Yom Abdul Latif To Haji Has can bin Ali Semeyye. After compliments. I inform you that my wish is that you send me a copy of the contract which has passed between you and. the Germans y repordinp the export of Oxide to Cal cutta, for it. having to all your gc Please send it soon because the Consul has asked me I hope Abdullah will soon arrive after finished work as desired and it be a pleasure of us to hear of his arrival. Please inform me of rod health always. I hold myself at your disposal. Dated 14th S 1324. (sdJAbdul Latif. nor*/r% Anlape 8, I'Yom Abdul Lot if bin Abur Rahman to Mage Hass an ben Ali Sameye. After compliments. Your respected favor has arrived and I have understood the contents, also the copy of the contract which you have made with the Germans for the sale of Ben Mussa Oxyde has been understood by me. My son Isa does not agree to the contract with these conditions and you neither consulted him nor did you send a copy of the contract before you concluded the oxyde-business with the Germans; so as to compare your ideas and work in concordance. Obviously, it is necessary that a partner engages himself only after consulting his partners, in order to avoid trouble. You have entered into this work without having his opinion, for this reason mu son Isa does not agree to the contract which exists between you and the Germans, because Isa fears the trouble that may arise in consequence of tak ing strangers into this busines. The cession (cessation^)of this contract would be preferable to its continuance. I have written you before not to engage yourself in the oxyde- business with the Germans because he fears bad consequences. Go says my son Isa, be this known to you. 8th Sihul Hadj. 1324. (sd.) Abdul Bat if ben Abdur Rahman.Anlaoe 9. Ltngah, 15th Shaabon 1323. Prom Hope Hasson ben Ali to Abdul Latif ben Abdur Rahman. After compliments. It is a long while since we have heard from you. I have written you a letter some time ago • ) and hope you have received it. Therein I informed you that 3 months previous I had sold to the Germans about 800 tons beaten oxyde as desired by them. In order to facilitate work I have sent mu brother Homed with coo lees to dig the oxyde and put it* into baps and up to now we have been waiting for bags but have not yet obtained a sufficient number* I hope after arrival of this quantity and approval of it they will arrange to take a quantity from us every year.ment is that the partners themselves only work as they have done for the last few years. It is not known that you gave lease-holds before this* This it was necessary to inform you so that you might know it and do something to undo all the trouble* (sd.) Abdul Lot if ben Abdur Rahman.' '/nlaoe 10. From Abdul Lot if to Hage Hassan ben Ali r 12th Safar 1325. After compliments. I have received your letter and noted contents. Vhen I received your letter saying that you had sold to the Germans of the oxyde of the island of Abu IJussa 2000 tons every year at 15/- per ton, my reply under date of 21 Rcbic el Thani 1324 shows that I agreed but it con tained a warning that your engagements should not resemble a lease hold or something which might occasion a row and which would displease our officials. We requested you to give us a guaranty that there would be no trouble, the mentioned letter is certainly in your possession, the con tents admit of no doubt. After receipt of the copy of the contract lohich we demanded frequently, on the 5 Dhul Kada 1324 and which was written in English and of which we acknowledged receipt on the 6 Dhul Kader 1324 and after we found somebody to translate it, we found that you had en tered engagements against which we had vxirned you and that you had bound yourself to a lease-hold, for which reason my son Isa does not agree to the contract which takes the working and management of the mines from our hands. V'e in formed you Of this before on the 8 Dhul Hadj when Isa saw the conditions of the contract and when you see the enclos ed translation of the contract you will understand that the. question is not as you have understood it, only a sale, but a lease hold against which we warned you. Sheikh Seger ben Khalet does not agree to your giving a lease-hold of oxyde to strangers of foreign powers and asserts that the arrange ment35 Anlane ii. From. Hage Hassan ben AlSemey to ben Abdur Rahman, 15th Safar 1335. After compliments. I have received you,r letter and noted contents, Reaarding the contract with the Germans, which you say is not as I have explained before sale of oxyde only, my friend,! am convinced that it is a sale of oxyde only for a certain period and a certain quantity eve ry year until the contract expires. It is not a lease-hold for the island. The apreement and conditions are as follows: He agrees to take every year a fixed quantity and we agree to dig it from the mines and deliver it as long as there is oxyde, just as it hax been customary before. Prom every- % body who sells something a sale contract is taken, this is not a leash-hold once for ever and you know that neither the 'Germans nor anybody else have any power over me. But perhaps you have been forced to this correspondence. The Germans bought oxyde only, nothing else, from the owners of • the lease-hold of the oxyde mines in Abu Mussa Mane ben Alt Semey f, Co. We have arranged tha if we deliver the oxyde in Lingoh and pay the transport expenses he has no objections and is quite agreeable and will not insist on going to the island ana possess himself of it. Also you wrote me saying that perhaps I aould cancel the contract, I spoke to him about it, he answered: 'if you say that we ha.ve intentions with the island, we shall give you a letter that we have nothing whatever to do with ft, we have only bought oxyde from the lease-holders of the ox Abu Mussa for a/ a fixed period, just os other* people buy from you. We do a lorroe business with all the merchants on the Persian and Arabian coast and have never had trouble with the people. If you do not accept this letter and you want to be releas ed from the contract allright -pay us for every ton 15/-- as per contract and also the advances which we have paid to | you, when you have paid us that we do not require the con- | tract anxl shall return it. We insist upon our rights,we ] are not here to play at doing business and we work and go ' in accordance with law. If you think it advisable please write to them and explain to them, verhaps they will meet you. I cannot see my way to do anything contrary to the sale conditions until the contract expires. You are the i lord of the learned 9 you knov) that I did this knowing that you were agreeable to it, the thing being done it is better to stop this dispute. When the Germans 'agree to give you a. letter according to your own '.inch,’saying that they have bought oxyde only from Hassan ben Alt Semey% Co. and have nothing to do with the lease-hold or the island, that settles everything. You know that such a sale in one item ; is not obtainable %v%ry day and we hcuve a large amount in-^ vested since the date of the concession; until now, who of the partners gave a single penny and if we donJi fell who will give us our money. You know that a sole is debarrass- | ing, when it is made it decreases the liabilities of the partners, when there is no sale the vartners must pay what ever the expenses are. After his arrival from Calcutta Ab dulla will close the books and show you everything, please inform Isa of this. (sd.) Hassan ben Ali Semey &lt;KCo.* y' Anlaae 12, lYom Sener ben Khalet to i laos an hen Ali Semey. After' compliments, V r e inform, you that Iso ben Abdul Latif has lodned o, complaint with us re par ding the oxyde mines in Abu Musso which have been, given in lease since ome years in your name and Isa ben Abdul Lot if and your son Abdulla in accordance with the document dated 18, Zulkada 1315, He has sent us the copy of contract existing between you and Robert Ylcnckhaus and presents a complaint saying that you have concluded this contract -without consulting him and after seeing it he does not agree to the conditions mentioned in the contract, and 1 also do not agree to this contract - under no circumstances. You have no right to give a. contract of such a nature and bind yourself and pos sess a third verson of all that the mines yield for a lorn period, without consulting us or informing us cd all. As we will sustain a loss by allowing this contract regarding the island of Abu Musso, which is in your hands, to continue and you have acted in this unauthorized manner on our behalf, we have now thought it advisable to with draw the lease.-hold from, you. Now I inform you by this letter so that you may know that the contract is expired between us and you have no right to make use of the mines in Abu Musso let this be known, 9, Muharrem 1325,37 /ml0^2 i'?&gt; I From Hasson hen /ll Semey to Sheikh Seger hen Kholet. After compliments. Your favor of this months date re ceived and contents noted. Regarding the letter in ihich Latif agrees to the contract with the Germans and at the same time warns us against giving a leasehold or some thing similar; yes I have not acted contrary to that letter and the Germans have nothing to do with the leasehold of , that island. I have only sold oxude of iron. VTien Abdul Lo ti f received answer to his letter it rroved to him that I had. not acted wrongly. I had only sold oxyde of iron. V’e are responsible for nothing else but the sale of oxyde of iron to the Germans. You say that I had stated that T o.m the owner of the island; how could I make such an assertion as I have taken in lease only the mine of oxyde of iron which is in the island of Abu Musa from Sheikh Salem ben Sultan and pay a certain sum as rent to Sheikh Salem every year according to the leasehold. But your statement that I had written that I am the leaseholder it is right and sale and management are in my heznds. The partners know well, that from the beginning of the concession the sale, expen diture* management and requirements have been duly looked after ho me and from the date of the contract the entire ma nagement has been in my hards and none of the partners hare interferred nor had they any right to do so unless I had acted contrary to lam. I quite admit that I am a British subject and abiding and do not deserve this unjustifiable interference ana you know that Germans have no other claim,but the purchase of oxyde for a certain period and you are ■ ■ - ^ ^ o; well aware that larpe amounts of our money have been invest ed in the oxyde mines. If vjc do not obtain sales how ore- we to repay the Germans and others. Go much was necessary. Compliments to all. &gt; V • r / &gt; ..tnlaye 14. L IYom hassan ben Ali Semey Co. to the British Consul General in Bush ire. After compliments. We keg to submit that on the 18th Muharrem 1325 we received a letter from Sheikh Seger ben Khalet chief of Shorgeh, saying that Isa ten Abdul Lot if has lodged a complaint with him to the effect that he does not agree to the contract which we have made with R. Wonck- ■ -i 1 hous, the German, asserting that it was made without his knowledge. Sheikh Seger also drops a hint that he wishes to withdraw the lease-hold, for the oxyde of iron mines in * • Abu Mussa which we leased from Sheikh Salem ben Sultan. We, being British, subjects and seeing that the letter of Sheikh Seger has no meaning, we thought it necessary to in- form you of this before they mispresent the matter to you. We hold the original lease-hold from Sheikh Salem ben Sul*- tan of 1315 to be continued for any period we desire; at tested by your agent Abdul Latif we accepted Sheikh Seger as a partner with the knowledge and evidence of Abdul Latif \ We made known our contract with the Germans and its con ditions in Arabic and English to Abdul Latif. Then we re- L eeived a letter from your agent dated SI Rebtc el Thani 1324 regarding the contract with the Germans, in that let ter he expresses his acceptance and gladness. We beg to enclose the copy of that letter. Also Jsa was infomed and agreedanr^d in tha auestion th?. letter of Sheikh Siaer shou's y ' ^ | that he intends to stop the work and make us suffer a loss, i for which reason we enclose copy of his letter before a dis- » ✓ pute arises. You are our protectors and it was necessary for i 1 us to inform you because all our transactures and contracts | were made with the knowledge and approval of Jsa and Abdul Latif and the original lease hold with their signatures are in our possession. Jf Abdul Latif had, not approved he v^ould have stopped me in the letter of iU Rebic el fhani and J j have only treated with the Germans with his approval and in our contract with the Germans we have sold oxyde only a rmrchandise is for every body the Germans and others. 22 Muharrum 1325. signed ffissan ben Ali Jemty u. Co.T • 39 Mime is* From Mr. Bill, First Assistant to Hage Hasson ban Ali 3&amp;rnzy. Aftav compliments. On the 12 March 1907-your letter to the consul was received, regarding the affair written to you by Sheikh Seger chief of Shargeh showing that he intends to withdraw the lease-hold for oxyde-mines which are in the island of Abu Mussa. The consul has requested me to re- ply that Sheik Szgor ben Khalet has sent a letter to the con sul ate regarding this affair.The matter has been submitted to the Government of Jndia and before receiving instructions from the Government the consul does not see his way to in terfere in this affair.This it was necessary to inform you. 29. Safar 1325.- IQ. April 1907. signed: First Assistant President Persian Golf.Anlape 16. From Sej&amp;r ben Khalet to Hassan ben Semey. After compliments. J have received your letter J&amp; noted contents. Regarding the complaint lodged with us by Jsa ben Abdul Latif concerning the oxyde in Abu Musa, you mention that your contract with the Germans uus made by his and his fathers knowledge 9 as per letter dated 21 Rebi ul Thani 1324. Jn the same letter he also warns you against entere~ ing engagements resembling a lease or binding yourself in such way as to occasion a row, he further mentions that you should go a sure way because his officials would not agree to it.The existing contract between you 4L the Ger mans and the conditions which you have bound yourself to are altogether contrary to the letter of Jsa 9 s father which you mention. The reason that we are frightened of your work is that it is not remote that the mines go out of our sphere* We entered into this with you knowing that you are British subjects. We did not. tell you to make contracts rath stran gers from foreign pouters without inf orming us to bind yourself. You have no right to make use of it and write on the head of the contract that you are the owners posses sors of the lease held in Abu Musa. To this we n^oer agree you are not allowed to take oxyde of iron from Aou fousa island on the condition vhich you have made, unless the business is put an a footing of which we need not fear the consequences. This you should know. 11 Safar 1325 signed Sheik Seger ben Khalet.Jf Anlage 17, 41 Jn the rt&amp;me of. „ e ............ God From, Salem bin Sultan To Harmd bin ali Semeyye After compliments. The man of my son Saker will a?^rive and has the facts in his head. Be this known to you. No date, signature or seal: Abdullah bin Haji Hasson states that on questioning Sheikh Salem about this note he replied he neither wrote it nor knew any thing about it.Arxlaoe 13_ Jn tha mum of, Qod hinga 27 th Rabia-avxil 1325 Prom Hasson bin Alt Semey ye To Sheikh Salem bin Sultan. After compliments. Tfie reason of writing this is that in these days our man came from the island and informed us that a man on behalf of Sheikh Baker vrith a note bearing no seal and protending that it was from you stopped the coo lies from digging oxide from the mines, stating further that this prohibition is ordered by 3. Saker. tie do not un derstand the interference of 3. Saker. Should this really be a fact, the action of 3. Saker is contrary to law. He has no right to raise any objections and, interfere viith us. He should remember that he, as you know, has been one of the partners who sold his share to us and for this reason we assert that he has no right to interfere with us no to stop the coolies from digging in the oxyde mines. He must know and recognize that the stoppage of work means a great loss to us as we even during the delay have to pay the coo lies their duly wages. We conjucture that this proceeding of S. Saker is without your knowledge and that you do not agree to these unjust interference and objections of his. As you know all the contracts A correspondence from the beginning till this day have been done by knowledge and approvalapproval of the British Political Agent, Abdul Lattf and all of you.Jt is astonishing that 3. Saker goes beyond his limits and interfere in a matter which has been concluded with the consent and approval of the British Agent. We have this moment written a letter to Khan Behadur 9 Political Agent Abdul Latif, because from the beginning of our lease-hold with you and others, have dom all by his knowledge and approval and because we consider him one of our partners and we wish to know his final reply. Really we do not want all these troubles and disputes but as you know, when necessity arises one is obliged to stand up and defend his rights which naturally entails a noisy dispute. We are compelled to address ourselves to our Government and claim whatsoever losses we sustain from him who inter feres. This action of 3. Saker is due to Ms jealousy of you and us, but we hope that so long as you are in exi st once we have every confidence and strangers have no rights over us. Jn these days my son Abdullah arrived from Jndia and intended to see you and pay his respects and now* awaits an opportunity. We beg you to inform, us of their object in this matter. signed Hasson bin Ali Semey ye 4 Co.Anlaoe 19^ Lingo, 28 Ratio avxil 1325. A letter was written by Hasson bin ali to Abdul Latif relating the incident occurred on the Jsland of Abu Musa which has already been fully described in the letter 18 to Salem bin Sultan. Jn addition Haji Hasson informed Abdul Latif that his son Abdullah had made a contract for 5 years for a quan tity of 400 tons to be delivered in Jndia every year. /Anlaoe 20,* Sharja 25 th Rabia Sani 132s. From, Abdul Latif bin Rahman To Haji Hassan bin ali Sermy ye Af ter compliments. Your letter reached me and J have no ted your good health. Regarding all what you state about the question of Sheikh Saker bin Khaladand his prohibition of your working Oxide -mines in Abu Musa, from what J gather from him he will not remove the prohibition unless he can make a clear arrangement rith you in this matter. He replies that the n Jsland of Abu Musa ,f is his property and so long as he cannot make suitable arrangements he con siders himself a loser. Jf he did not formerly interfere it was clue to the good understanding existing hetmen you but now he cannot leave the case alone as before because a stranger has entered therein and he is afraid that by and by the island will get out of his possession. This is his answer and you must know that J cannot at present in terfere in the matter as J see the question have become com.pl ieat&amp;d. signed Abdul Latif bin Abdul Rahman.T An 1 ape 2 1* Jn the name of. God From, Saker bin Khaled To, Hajt Hassan bin ali S&amp;mey ye After compliments. Before this J informed you to stop working in the mines of the red oxide of iron in the Jsland of Abu Musa; we understand you do not listen, therefore we send you just now on our behalf a cei'tain Jsa bin Ahmed who has a notice from us to you.We have instructed him to deliver the Notice to you in presence of the British Consw~ lar agent at Ling a against receipt. After this notice you have no claim on us.Be it known, to you. J am ready at your disposal in case of need. Dated 25 th Jhaban 1325.Anlaoe 22 . Jn the name of God: corresponding Jn accordance with oar contract dated 18 2ilkada 1315 to 11 April 1898 we agreed to lease the oxyde of iron mines situated in the island Abu Mussa to Rage Hass an ben ali S&amp;- mey t Abdulla ben Hassan and Jsa ben Abdul Latif* The con tract does not contain a clause authorising you to give the whole out put of oxyde of iron to one stranger with out our consent. Because Mage Hassan ben ali Semey made a contract vjith- out our consent with Robert IVbnckhaus in Lingah on the 1 st June 1906, and gave him right of purchase of all this out put of the mines in Abu Mussa;we informed the said Hage Has* san ben ali Semey in our letter dated 9. Moharrum 1325 cor responding to 21 st February 1907 that this lease hold da ted 18 Zilkada 1315 had expired and that he had no right to make use of the mines in Abu Mussa in future. We learn that in spite of our prohibition he still works the oxyde -mines in Abu Mussa and enjoys the profits. On this account v-e hereby proclaim to the said Hage Hassan ben Aly Semey and deniand from him the immediate cession of work in the mines and removal of himself his employed and all his mining implements from the island of Abu Mussa wi thin 10 days from the date that this notice reaches him.Let this be known. Written and dated 25 Shaaban 1325. signed Sheikh Seger ben Khalet ben Sultan el Gas semi chief or Lhargefa* Received in Lingah 2. Ramazan 1325.———65 British Residency and Consulate-General Bushire, ^ ^April 1910. Dear Doctor Listemann, in reply to your letter of today regarding the shipment of 400 tons of oxide by Haji Hassan bin Samayeh I beg to inform you that no ins tructions have been received from my Government. Colonel Cox, however, did see Haji Hassan bin Samayeh and I understand that^having received satisfactory assurances from him regarding Abdulla, he told Hassan thatysubject to confirmation by our Government, he agreed to the shipment of the 400 tons by the next convenient steamer as a special case. Yol Dr. H. Listemann Imperial German Consul Bushire.—No. I. E. Form No. 120. { '? 24 ! INDO-EUROPEAN TELEGRAPHS. (PERSIAN GULF SECTION.) Station. Received No. Date. /J2 ^ ^ &gt; j //, . 0 for Telegram • JV. B.-No inquiry respecting this Telegram can be attended to without the production of this paper. forlying ready for shipment in accordance with the agreement arrived at between His Maiesty f s and the German Governments to touch at the island with the result that the mineral was still there. lou stated that you have received instructions to ask His Majesty*s Government to direct Major Trevor to inter fere with the shipment, which would take place in accor dance with previous agreement. Sir C. Hardinge replied that no time would be lost in causing inquiries to be made into the matter. This has now been done and 1 have the honour to inform you of their result: In a conversation on August 9th, 1909, the German Vice Consul at Bushire informed His Majesty* s Counsul General that Messrs 176 nek halts wished to remove some more of the oxide accwnulated at Abu Musa, in o.ccordance with the agreel ment above referred to, and subsequently, in a letter da ted August 19th, explained that: C'est la compagnie mi- niere de Hajji Hassan bin Ali Someyye et Cie. qui veut expedier ces 400-500 tonnes d'oxy.de et c' est pour cette compagnie que la maison de 17cnckhaus s’ est adressee a ce Vice Consulat demandant son assistance.' Major Cox understood this passage merely to indicate Herr V/assmuss' wish to emphasise the view that a mining company existed in which Messrs Wdnckhaus had a share; and he therefore found nothing in Herr V/assmuss' remark to modify his previous belief that the proposed shipment was actually intended for the German film. It was on this assumption that I addressed to Count Metternich my note of November 13th last, informing His Excellency that the ship mentmerit might take place. It was not till late in February last that Major Trevor then in charge of Ilis Majesty' s Consulate General at Bu~ shire, realised that the proposed shipment was to be made *on behalf, not of Messrs Wdnckhaus, but of Hassan Somaiye which he considered to be a departure from the agreement above referred to whereby Messrs Vfcnckhaus alone are en titled to remove the island oxide already mined to enab 1e them to fulfil coward al obligations already assumed. Moreover, in spite of assurances given to His Majesty*s Consulate General that the date of the arrival of the stealr,er by which the oxide was to be shipped would be no tified in order to allow time for the necessary arrange ments to be made, no sufficient notification was received, and a practical obstacle was then placed in the way of the shipment. In these circumstances Major Trevor felt obliged to request the master of the steamer not to touch at Abu Mu sa, and this request was coup lied with. Permission has however now been given for the shipment of the oxide by the same steamer ( the Steamship iJaseri ,, J al though, strictly speaking, as it is made on behalf of Hassan and not to enable Messrs Vfcnckhaus to fulfil their contracts, it constitutes a departure from the agreement between the two Governments for the nonremoval of the mi neral from the island. The British authorities, in according this permission, have been influenced by consideration of the misunderstan ding which has arisen locally, and by a desire to eliminate a side issue from the main question, but the attitude 'which theyr—zn?-’ t h ey have assumed in this matter must not be construed as indicating that His Majesty's Government recognise any right on Hasson*s part to ship oxide to India on his own account or as prejudicing their case in respect of the general question under discussion between the two Govern ment o I have the honour etc ( For Sir Edward Grey) aez. Louis Mallet. jr. Ilia ui it Beziehu. 16. v.M. -C.N fung von Ox haus in L ingah auf dem Dampfer IJaseri Dem Kaiserlichen Konsul Herm L i stem ann Hochwohlgeboren Bus char zur Kenntnis. Der Reichskanzler Im Auf traceAuszug aus einem Schreiben des Kgl, Grossbrittanischen Generalconsulates in Bushire an Agha Bedder. Uebersetzung: a/ ’’With referee to the affair of Haji Hassan ben Someye &amp; Co, and his request for shipment of a further lot of oxyde accor ding to his letter dated 5th, Rabi’el Sani 1328 please inform him that the permission is stopped because I told Hassan and Abdullah in your presence the permission for the last shipment was given one year ago under the supposition that the oxyde was for Robert Wonckhaus &amp; Co. and I did not* think of withdrawing the promise I had given,but this holds good only for the last shipment and after that I will not give permission,because I have clearly explained to them the subject and I am now extremely astonished that Hassan should ask again. ROBERT WONCKHAUS &amp; Co., LINQAH.1 s Jjj b n o?{» o i V e r{o 3 ct u d 1 rx s jj * 1 i iiv m inealB-d fS •;ov ■'jfJlotrtoS a0fi&amp;cf6&gt;y'£9 *t8uni/ r'V : ir;i 3 'i;fX Ska ctsb hr.ago 1 In 1 a nonj : sb isk novtifoanifcsfts .nt r* .Ou. ■;v ; i;o :\Q ainad'ii'i'tfa8•“tO •lb ' &gt; xr^ r -A n:v itno*'';/- -•mXijrBncO ft93.‘.o 1 i'rjsK oli) rfc'iwJb jb^O nov •■ftjffjj us set9?3*t9cf8u *18nx9 v •’• . ■ d niW . ‘5m * . 5 , B • c rr * i-. HsG Bno ■. __ ; *5. . • aacT dBLCsi t 4^ ;•« ~ •tA ; 4 »• ,iv t na s • r:\. ’ •••' •••' t ^3- ;} S 93 efxfoJtrt 'tei'i : Xi: ; ni t *l -jO b ©^sruoS nnc:i iov noc.CesmeJb axn’ © Lr •■; u '4r r eXfc nijn . ,:r{ N-on enoBoIe^ToV a^l) tici •r y .*j j-SvtoI liiB'rc x &lt; ,:j ; nr . ziiolrt deux nadi^nxCo^:; il O Jh. * »^ JL * * ‘^ 'b lab byxO a/s 11 «»f» - - ; - ; &lt;3 , , £ t*- '«'*n ,^ 3^803 tim inkw a© £n*3^&gt;n'0- {o‘'j.on O J 1 rldoncw anl'i ' -;'r - • r -r ,-•. , m r •■t 4 5 en/j't oV T&amp;i -joernn S nr T •» ; pf ;-; 8 '18 v c X X* B 8 Bl&gt; ~ - r r 4 r; : JJU^ rj£l5EXO’$ sit lOl ocIg- £ 8-&gt;' h, 2 o n9 ; ^*v.v _ v- • 'V • -i. *4 4 “tr.xJ ©i:Jb n © nxC I non’tol a m. r; o •' f v; : d t ttfT t VV . ' • ■'• .ii'V t :a nsn9fiii35o:i8S n 8 ^nBr ? 'U ,-osnK n cfA Ins n ©h ~r.) '?J!&amp; • 3 nod nssaosK ?; *• atddB.l, ■ ■ snie 3 ' &amp;- &lt; v:Abschrtft zu III a 10967 No.30356/10. Foreign OJJice, Immediate. August 22ndl910. Your Excellency:~ I have the honour to acknowledge the receipt of your note of the 26 th ultimo relative to the demand of Messrs. Robert V/onckhaus and Company to be allowed to ship a further consignment of red oxide from Abu Musa. I venture to remind Your Excellency that in paragraph 28 of the ’’Complaint” of that firm against the Sheikh of Sharga f which was corrmunicated to His Majesty's Government in Herr von Stumm's note of December 31st 1907, it was im plied that the firm had commitments to the extent of at least Two thousand tons of oxide and that it was to enable them to meet the liability which was thus understood to ex- ist, that His Majesty's Government, in a memorandum dated January 10th 1908, consented to the removal from the island of the oxide already mined and ready for shipment. It was equally with this object in view that similar language was employed in the comiunications of July 4th and 23rd. That the real intention of His Majesty’s Government was to allow Messrs. Wbnckhaus, pending the settlement of the dispute, to remove only so much oxide as would enable them to fulfil obligations previously contracted, and not to place them in a position of unfair advantage over Bri tish subjects who were not to be permitted to ship any of the minreal at all, is proved by the authoritative statement of the British attitude contained in the memorandum of July 10th 1908 which forms the reasoned reply to Herr von Stumm's note above referred to. This statement is as follows:- ’’They 62774.They (i.e.His Majesty's Government) are prepared to use their good ojjices in order that temporary arrangement may be made whereby Messrs. Wbnckhaus will be enabled to pro cure a limited amount oj red oxide to place them in a po sition to julfil such contracts as they may have entered into before the cancellation of the lease”. That the firm long ago attained their object is proved by a statement made by the German Acting Consul at to the British Acting Consul General in an official letter dated March 1st. 1910 to the effect that had discharged the obligations which they had contracted by means of the oxide shipped on board the Steam Ship ’’Louise” (in April 1908) and by the fact, known to His Majesty's Government, that so recently as the spring of this year they still had Four hundred tons of the mineral belonging to that consignment lying unsold at Hamburg. In these circumstances, I cannot but consider that the demand of Messrs. V/bnckhaus constitutes a clear violation of the agreement arrived at by the two Govermients and thn the attitude of His Majesty's Consul General at Bushire in opposing that demand was not based on desire to create mere wanton obstruction but rather on a determination to carry out the intention of His Majesty's Government as ex pressed in the memorandum of July 1908. His Majesty's Government might therefore fairly have claimed to adhere ti the terms of that communication as expressing their real intention and to interpret in the light of it everything which they have elsewhere written on the subject. I.i view ..oweverof tne f act that language has been used m Notes to Your Excellency which can be interpreted as cn ex-174 expression of their willingness to allow the removal of all the oxide already mined and lying ready for shipment without reference to the specific requirenents of Messrs* Wonckhaus m connexion with obligations previously contrac ted, 1 have the honour to inform Tour Excellency that the will/ desired shipment be permitted and that Lieutenant Colonel Cox will be furnished with instructions in this sense. I venture dowever to express the hope that , in view of the explanations now given, the German Government will abstain from supporting any jurther requests of this nature which Messrs. Monckhaus may make. 1 presiune that the shipment referred to in the penulti mate paragraph of Tour Excellency's note as having been the object of obstructive action on the part of Colonel Cox is that which formed the subject of my note to Herr vcn Etihl- mm of May Gnd last. In that cormivYication the circumstan ces which gave rise to the attitude of the Consulate-Gene ral were fully explained and 1 feel confident that, if Tour Excellency will refer to it once more, you will adn.it that no fault can justly be found with the action of Majvr Trevor who was at that time officiating at Bushirc in Colonel Cox- absence . I have the honour to be, with the highest conside ration, Your Excellncy r s most obedient, (For Sir Edward Grey) gez. Louis Maliet.I213 ^ ^ Council for the judgement of the caee between Messrs Lynch Brothers ^ P A against Mulla All the represantative of Messrs Robert Wonckhaus &amp; C 0 which took place on Saturday the 3rd December 1910 &amp; 1st Zil Heja 1328. »t»»*» »i « »i'» »»««♦» »f»»t» n f» *» t» n With regards to the shipment of Mulla Ali the represantative of Messrs Robert Wonckhaus &amp; Co In the Nasserieh of Ahwaz for consignment to the above firm of Mohammerah per S/S Maiamir, that the Bill ol Lading of the second shipment which was in their possession vouchsafing the shipment of 97 bags gum,194 bags lin seed,&amp; 69 bags wheat adding 300 bags in all from which 58 bags I gum &amp; 24 bags linseed was found short( at destination) but according the clean B/L for the whole three hundred bags which is in their hand, they claimed the snid shortares from Messrs Lynch Brothers • But after making the necessary inquiries at Mohammerah Sc Naserieh ( Ahwaz) it was ascertained to us that , the shortage in question was left on the Quay by Messrs Lynch Brothers which v/as a part of Mulla All’s second shipment , who mixed Sc reshipped with his 3rd shipment ” while the clerk of the ship was ill Sc had gone on leave to nasrah, &amp; a new clerk was appointed in his place who was unaware of that part left on the Quey &amp; have been inserted in the B/L of the former trip, Sc therefore the new clerk repeatedly granted a B/L for the whole quantity ( including that which was left on the Quey)as a fresh shipment received from Mulla Ali. , »j i „ j ,g r '' v | tK For this reasons we have brought Mulla Ali with his •, partner Mubrouk for hearing their case at Nasserieh, and as this e~ 7'— caseis standing between Messrs Lynch Brothers Sc Mulla Ali of two caforeign subjects , eo that His Excellency Hasrut El Mulk took charge of this case on behalf of thd ^arkuzar with Haji Rais El Tujjar of Arabistan 8c other TTasserieh merchants who are * Agha naji Syed Ahmed Shuehtari ” Agha Mohammed Baker Behbahani M Agha Yousif Mutamid El Ra-yat w Agha Abdul Rahim Asphahani ' Agha Ammed Kaza rani * Haji Abdul Hassen Hewazawi ” Mirza Ibrahim Khan' &amp; &amp; there was also present the dragoman of the British Consulatewith Mr IrrC the agent of Messrs Lynch Brothersand Mr Abe3/his assistant 8c Mr Ja&amp;ob MuradEl Sheikh of Messrs Lynch Brothers, &amp; the case was proceeded in the present pf parties* It is proved to us that Mubarek Mulla All's partner was. working at Ramharmizd in buying gum 8 c linseed for the shipment gratua^lly to Mulla All's consignment through Arabs and Persians caravans for the shipment by the steamers to Messrs R.W 8c Co, 8c the said Mubarik has proved his purchases 8c shipments through caravans according to that of Mull as All’s shipment s by Malamir in examining these there was found in excess of the purchase 105 cwts gum , covering the shortages which Mulla All is claiming from Messrs Lynch Brothers against their B/L in his hand . The said Mulia Ali was defending that this excess was bought by himself at Nasserieh Ahwaz, besides that which was bought at Ramhermizd ' The meeting ( Mejlis) then asked Mulla Ali to prove his purcha at Ahwa,z, 8 c the said Mulla Ali named Mulla RidaBen Mashhadi Reda &lt;( Nadi Ali* 8c Mushhatted ,as witnesses, 8c said that through these three persons he has made his purchases at Nasserieh Ahwaz, When these three witnesses were ordered in the presence of the Mejlis &amp; were examined in present of Mulla Ali , they said that they knew nothing rega xiing this purchase, they further said that they only know thatthis Mulla Ali used to get gum &amp; linseed215 through caravans 1’rom Ranhani^d* &amp; he used to fill them in l a/ s &amp; forward them to Mohammerah , Then the Mljlis informed Mulla All whether he has informed his partnetr Mubrouk of his purchase at Hassfcrieh , Mulla Ali said yes, I have written him a letter about it, tfcen Mulbreifc was asked , who also said yes he wrote me that gum is obtainable at Nasserieh , asking me whether he will buy t &amp; therefore I wired to him that if it is sui^table le^ i.irn buy &amp; Mulla Ali relied immetiietely that he has bought • The Mejlis asked for the telegrams from the telegramjf office to be brought , they were examined by them &amp; found to be dated after the date of the 3rd shipment &amp; that was after the B/L was issued for the goods which was left on the uey{ out of the second shipment) &amp; it was in that time that Mulla Ali had informed his partner Mubarek of his purchase from Hasserieh , so that he may be able to charge the value to him.. Besides Messrs Lynch Brothers were able to prove through number of merchants &amp; innabi tents of that place , who gave witnes that Mulla Ali has not bought any gum at Hasserieh neither such stufl has ever arrived there, the y have further proved that the said Mulla Ali has Si.ii i e from Nasserieh per S/S Nasrat on the 17th Ramazan one bundle of spe cie containing Krans 4500. to the order of Haji Hassen ben Nabeat M Mohammerah, this was done about ten days after his 3rd siiipment &amp; b before the return of his partner from Ramharmizd• The councel asked Mulla Ali about this ( who was first denying same ) but when the agent of S/S Nasrat has well proved to him this , then he himself stated the fact • The mejlis then asked Mubarek if he knew anything about this specie, &amp; his reply was that he knew nothing before &amp; he just learned from the e„Lis Prom these indications it was proved for his remitting4. ROBERT WOlMOKHAUS this sum without the knowledge of his partner , which sum was the equavelent of the value of the short gum which he stated being bought by him at Nassorieh, 8 c has charged the valus to his partner 8 c Messrs Robert Wonckhaus &lt;fc&lt; Co • . Proves 8 c evidence on Mul La Ali are many , for all t . his answers while examining were fal&amp;g&amp; through which it has been proved on him 8 c t^iat Messrs Lynch Brothers are right in this V* claim as the shortages is likely equal to the B/L repeatedly taken by him, As regards the Linseed the councel has decided that the shor tage of this quality being done on the voyageof the steamer 8 c as one stuff being found stolen by Mulla Ali, so that no doubt he has destr&amp;gred this quantity of linseed in a certain way , &amp; it is ther^ fore decided that he has no right to claim for the shortages &amp; gave this j udgement accordingly* ClA*- jp* ^ % VtN-C v tA Muhtamid Ei Tijjar Ahmed Khoonsari Haji Said Hussein Haji Said Ahmed- Mohammed Ali , Haji Abdul Hassan, Mubarak Ben Oada Mohammed Baker Bahbahani. Mirza Ibrahimmi I —^lusnuirtiiies Amt. % 243 MrBear Major Trevor^ I have just received,from L ingah,informat ion that Colonel Cox,during his visit at that port,told Hage wassan Bin Samaye that there were no more objections to his shipping,in the name of the mining Company, the 40C tons of oxyde referred to in your official correspondence with Mr.Wassmuss;without Hage ^assan sub mitting to the conditions previously mentioned in the pforesaid correspondence.! therefore take the liberty of reminding you in this semi-official way, of Mr. Wassmuss' 1 request made to you in h s offi ial note HM 135,of March 33rd,i.e.to inform this V ice-Consul at e as soon as you had received, new oinstruc ions from your Government with regard to the aforesaid shipment.I shall be much obliged for your giving me the said information so that I may inform Messrs.W.at Lingah by th^-day's mail.3/. /^, //, Please see your refer -ence of 21st July regarding Hasean Samaiyeh's Account Books. When I enquired into his claim , I found that, according to him , the details were based mainly on his account books # which were not forthcoming • They had not been in his posses- -sion for several months ; were not in Lingah ; and he could not ascertain whether they were in Bushire , Busreh , or Sur- -ope • I informed him that I could not proceed with the cas ~l » f until he produced them • I did not mean that he must produce them here(unless they had turned out to be here already) and it was a misunderstanding on the part of the Residency A gent when he asked Hassan to send them here • I have explained to him that I did not want them here • Understanding that Hassan is now ready to produce them I will proceed with the enquiry at the first opportunity • I have had to make a reference letter No 315 , and will reply Dr H.Listemann • Imperial u erman Consul Bushi roI 288 ^ Absohrift Foreign Office, His Excellency August 12th, 1911 Count Mett erniah , Your Excellency:~ With reference to my note of August 22nd 1910, relative to the shipment of red oxide from Abu Musa, I have the honour to state that, according to a telegraphic report from His Majesty's Consul General at Bushire, the German Consul at that port has applied on behalf of Messrs. Robert Wonckhaus and Company for permission to ship as soon as possible, the balance of the mineral remaining on the shore of the island, which the Consul estimates at between three hundred and four hundred tons. 'The Consul has also anrr ied for permission to transport a further quantity of five hundred tons |rroi: the pit lie ad to the shore. As regards the first of these demands. I have the honour to observe that Your Excellency, in the first paragraph of your note of July 26th, 1910, stated that Messrs .Worekhai-is proposed to ship a further four hundred or five hundredjtons of oxide and that permission to remove this amount was accorded in my Note of August 22nd, Reports received from Lieutenant-Colonel Cox show t?hat the firm have already shipped as much as three hundred tons, that amount having been removed in May last, so that the maximum additional amount which s289 I they are strictly entitled to remove, in virtue of the permission given in my Note above referred to, is two hundred tons only. Hot wishing, however, to interpret too literally the terms of the permission in question, I refrain from raising objections to Messrs.Wonokhau 3*8 request and have the honour to inform Your Kxoelleuoy that a fcelegrari will be addressed to Colonel Cox stating that His Majesty*!* Government ha^e consented to the shipment of the balance of the heap. As regards the second application of the German Consul at Bushire -that for permission to transport a further five hundred tens of oxide from the pithead to the shore- I have the honour to recall Your Excellency •s attention to the penultimate paragraph of my note of A .. ’3 4/ i-j i'Oi id and to express the hope that this demand is not made with the support of the German Government. I would venture to add that the facts adduced in paragraph 5 of the same note appear to prove that Messrs.Wonokhaus have no ground for asking that such an application may be made. I have the honour to be, with the highest consideration. Your Excellency's most obedient,humble Servant, (For the Secretary of State) gez. W.Langley.I: Abschrigt . Uebersetuung der beiden beif(blgenden arabischen Schrift” N£1 &amp; 2 mit gleiehem Text. In the name of God f Of all who see this paper and know about the island of Abu Musa,we ask,to whom this island belongs and who of the ^rabic Sheikhs is the 0 owner,and what did he do in the past years with the boats etc.that stranded at Abu Musa and what has the owner of the ilsand arranged with the «nakhodagfw or with the proprietors of these boats and who are the owners of that island and in which manner have the cargos resued and brought out from the sea been divided.Please,tell usi Answer &lt;: Yes,the above mentioned island of Abu Musa is the territory of the »Johwassims»,but the real owner is the Sheikh Salim bin Sultan bin Segger el Ghasmi. With regard to above Questions about stranded boats and rescued cargos,these have been divided into two parts.One half has been taken by the »Nakhodas» or owners of the respective boats and cargos abdthe other half by Sheikh Salim bin Sultan and sometimes Sheikh Salim bin Sultan has given a part of his share to some of his subjects residing on the island. N01 .Signedrand sealed by Abdulrezak bin Abdullah Eahar. NS 2 signed and sealed by Khalifa bin Abdullah bin Sani Suedi at Jesire Sirri.(of the johwassim tribe.)331 Abschrift zu Ilia.17097/11. Foreign Office. London, December 6th , 1911. 'four Excellency: - I have the honour to refer you to my note of December 6th, forwarding a memorandum advancing arguments in reply to your communication of December 4th, 1909, on the subject of the claim of Messrs. Wbnckhaus in connexion with the shipment of red oxide from Abu Musa. 1 am confident that the German Government will not fail to appreciate tne cogency of the considerations urged in this memorandum in support of the attitude. assumed by His Majesty's Government throughout the discussion of this question. That, attitude is, in their opion completely justi fied by the facts elicited in the course of the further investigations which have been carried out since the re ceipt of Your Excellency's communication above referred to. They have, how ever, no desire to protract a, discussion which has already lasted about four years and thus still further to prolong the interrupt which an important com mercial enterprise hoc already suffered. His Majesty '.s Government desire to suggest to the Ger man Government that a compromise should be reached on the fol living 21270following lines: 1. His Majesty's Government recognising the desire of Messrs. IVonckhaus for some compensation on account of the interruption of their business as the result of the inabili ty of Hasson Samaiya to carry out his contract with them, are willing to facilitate the attainment of that object. They would accordingly suggest that the firm should be as ked to submit through the German Government a statement of their claim under this head. As to the amount of the los ses so incurred, 11 is Majesty's Government have so far re ceived no precise information. 2. Recognising further the desire of the firm to be restored as far as possible to the commercial position which they occupied at the moment when their operations were interrupted, His Majesty's Government will use their influence with the Sheikh of Sharga to procure from him the grcmt of a new concession to suitable persons to con- time the working of the mines, and will endeavour to ar range that the contract of jure first, 1906, should be allowed to run for a further period equal to that during which it was interrupted. That period was from October '2, 10th 1907 to June i u 1910. The contract might, for example, st st run from May V next to December 31 1914. If Messrs . WbnckhausWbnckhaus are reinstated in their contract as here pro posed, the only losses sustained by them under head (1) would appear to be those due to the delay in receiving their prof its on account of the interruption of the working of the mines. It''should he explained that in spite of any clause contained in the present contract, the parties shall not be bounds after its expiration to conclude any new- agreement. 3. His Majesty *s Government undertake to use their best endeavours to ensure that the firm should receive such sum in compensation as may finally be fixed. His Majesty * s Government have every confidence that the V good intentions which have prompted this offer will be appreciated by the German Government and that they will see their way to co-operate in the satisfactory settle- V ment of this protracted controversy by recomrr,ending to the firm concerned the acceptance of the proposed compromise. I have the honour etc* (gez. E. Grey. His Excellency Count Mettemich etc.I ■■■■I359 ROBERT WONCKHAUS &amp; Co., LINGAH Statement No. 1 : On the 20th. of Moharrem 1330 a man named Aheid, living on the island of Ahu Musa , came to Hage Hassan bin Ali Somaye and informed him that She-ik Segger had sent a man to Abu Musa to stay in the island as representative of Sheikh Segger and to act as administrator of the island on behalf of Sheikh Segger. Sheikh Segger proclaimed this to the inhabitants of the island and ordered his representative to expell the agent of Sheikh Salim from the island. From this date the island became property of Sheikh Segger and was lost to Sheikh Sal im bin Sultan. I, Aodulrezak bin Bahacr have been witness of the above statement signed : Abdulrezak bin Abdulla Bahar -de signed : -do - EKX Selman bin Hussein bin Derwisch.I*Statement No, 2 : In the name of God etc. At 2 o*clock p.m.( arable time ) of the 7th. of Safar 1330 we were stay4 ing at the house'of Hage Hassan bin Ali Somaye where two men, named Salim bin Ibrahim and Selman, both residing in Shargeh, were also present, accompanied by some other Shargeh people and Sh&amp;maai Salim bin Ibrahim told to Hage Haasah bin Ali Somaye that some days ago there had been a conver - sat ion between Sheikh Salim bin Sultan and Sheikh Segges bin Khalet bin Sultan regarding the island of Abu Musa, in consequence of which Sheikh Salim bin Sultan made a complaint on Sheikh Segger ( at the British Consu late in Bushire ? ) for the latter having taken possession of a^u Musa and for having sent this year a man to be his representative in A.Musa , who expelled the agent of Sheikh Salim from the island and moreover for having sent wheat seed to be sown on the same ground where Sheikh Salirr^ always used to sow his wheat, further for having sent word to Sheikh Salim to take away all his property ( horses, donkeys, implements etc. ) from the island of Abu Musa to the island or Tamb. Bor these reasons Sheikh Salim at once raised urgent protests ( to the British Consul at Bushire ? ) for the behaviour of Sheikh Segger and ask ed for the immediate removal of Sheikh Segger's men and property from the island. and Sir Sheikh Salim declared ; On the island of Abu Musa no one has a claim ex cept myself, as it is my own property, which I inherited from my father Sultan bin Segger. Before his death he divided all his possession between me and my brother Achmet. I got Abu Musa and Sir and my brother the country of ' Dibbi ' , as shown by a testament in my hands, the existence of which is knawn to the English people. When the consul ( Colonel Cox ) came to-settle the case of Jesire Soab he took me in a man-o-war from Has el Khema to Shargeh to have a meeting between me and Sheikh Segg^r. Segger came on board in the presence of the consul and I said to Segger that Abu Musa and Sir are my property and that I hold a document proving this and my rights were ascertained then and there. After my return to Has el Khema the son of Abdulatif, Isa, informed me that Sheikh Segger only wanted to keep his horses on the island for grazing, whereas now Segger wants to take possession of the whole island, but I will never allow him to do so, as the island is my own property. 5he above statement has been given at the house of Hage Hassan bin Ali Somaye by Salim bin Ibrahim and Selman, dated the 7th. Safar, 1330. I herewith witness the statement of Salim bin Ibrahim and Selman signed : Abdulrezak bin Abdulla Bahar The abo ve statement was given in my presence: signed : Kelfan bin Abdulla residing in M Hemrieh ' -do - -do - signed : Selman bin Hussein bin Derwisch.—(MaaV A kw 383 (ll/jfa</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000419.0x0000d7_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/10/320</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000419.0x0000d7</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/10/320</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>File 4949/1912 Pt 3 ‘Abu Musa Wönckhaus Lingah’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1907/1912</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-01-31T12:04:54</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ger</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">fre</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (402 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.The subject 4949 (Abu Musa oxide) consists of six volumes, IOR/L/PS/10/318-323. The volumes are divided into six parts, with each part comprising one volume. Part 6 (IOR/L/PS/10/323) is missing.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1 and terminates at the last folio with 403; these numbers are printed, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Correspondence exchanged between the German Consulate at Buschär [Bushire] (Helmuth Listemann) and others: the Lingah [Bandar-e Lengeh] representative of the German firm Robert Wönckhaus and Company (Herr H Rosenfeld; Herr Krumpeter); the British Political Resident in the Persian Gulf (Percy Zachariah Cox); German Government officials at the Auswärtiges Amt (Foreign Office) in Berlin; the German Embassy in London.The correspondence refers to a dispute relating to concession rights for the mining and shipment of red oxide at Abū Mūsá, originally awarded to a number of Arab merchants by Shaikh Sālim bin Sulṭān Āl Qāsimī of Sharjah in 1898, and part of which was subsequently acquired by Wönckhaus and Company in 1906. The dispute was sparked by the Ruler of Sharjah, Shaikh Ṣaqr bin Khālid Āl Qāsimī’s cancellation of the concession in 1907, and subsequent claims by Wönckhaus and Company and the German Government, over financial losses arising from the cancellation of the concession.The majority of the file’s correspondence is in German. Letters exchanged between the German Consul at Bushire and the British Political Resident are in French. In most cases, German correspondence is preceded by undated pencil notes written in English, giving a précis of the letter that follows.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of the German Empire</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>German Consul</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Abū Mūsá</geographic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Emir of Sharjah, Āl Qāsimī dynasty</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Robert Wönckhaus and Company</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Concessions, red oxide, Abu Musa</topic></subject><subject><topic>Concessions</topic></subject><subject><topic>Trade disputes</topic></subject><subject><topic>Mining</topic></subject><subject><topic>Ferric oxide</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000419.0x0000d7#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>