<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000602.0x00020c_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-07-31T10:19:31.596Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">BUCKINGHAM PALACE. 30th, May, 1945. 'h\j r W ‘ fl&gt;W C5W&lt; The King desires me to thank you sincerely for the set of Muscat postage stamps, issued on the occasion of the bicentenary of the A1 Busaid dynasty, which you sent with your letter to Lascelles of the 28 th. May. His Majesty is very glad to have these specimens for his Collection and is grateful to you for your kind thought in sending them. C/y\AsL*^ Lieut-Colonel D. de M.S. India Office* Fraser, CIE.,7-^1 r*&gt; COP\f— ,/n f Aid ,Lh* i RAOC &amp; D 4 / ^ INi;ARP ? j?2Ll|GRA|i| All otted to jilxt erna l DepaJtmentl - CoDies Circulated, C- 0 41472 (5) 1 Prom To GONPID ENTIAL CODE T RLP GRAM Political Agent- Muscat. Secretary of State for India. W/ j~- jiUc^u , v to Political Resident in the Persian Gulf (by post).. &lt;ktr^ 2(2, Dated Muscat, 10-45 hours, 27th November 1944 u Received 13.00 hours, 27th November 1944, No, S 1974, Addressed to Secretary of State for India, cony by post to Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Sultan of Muscat wishes the following message to be conveyed to His Majesty the King, B egins. 'It was with the greatest pleasure that I received Your Majesty's message of good wishes delivered on the occasion of bicentenary foundation of my dynasty, I reciprocate your good wishes and pray for the speedy end of the war and continued prosperity for yourselff .E nds. Suit an as ks me to convey his thanks to the for India for his kind message of good wishes.l SKOHsa 1 3994 3 IHWAKB TKLKG^ AM - v/ | 944 . {If in any case the communication ^&gt;f i *ime rr %^frrents of thin document to any person outside British or U.3. Go* 'ynment Service io authorised^ it must he paraphrased) Allot ted to External Bepartment OYPHKH TELEGR AM Prora Political Hesident in the Persian Gulf* f - Co Secretary of State for India* Repeated to Government of India and Muscato Dated Bahrein, 14ol5 hours, 15th November, 1944, .Received 13©45 hours, 15th November, 1944 0 % IMMBDIATN. Addressed Secretary of State for la repeated Government of India and IJuaeat. \ | ^ Youy telegram as(??I)a Hovem-ber l ai-.h 1 W i eceived partially corrupt© ^ j &lt;^0, f944 VT ^ lJNDl \ CPF IP . Please confirm that personal measage'^^'^ w P ar agraph No© B is from Secretary of State aor India® This telegram was correctly ©ncypheredol (if in any case the•communication of the contents of this document to any .person outside British or Government Service is authorised? it must be paraphrased). Allotted to External Department Copies Circulated C.X.P HER TE L EG RAM From r- Government of India? External Affairs Department. To Secretary of State for India* Repeated to Bahrain and Muscat. Dated New Delhi* S3.55 hours* 14th November? 1944» Received 23*00 hours* 14th November* 1944* IMPORTANT 14858. Addressed to Secretary of State for India repeated to Bahrain and Muscat. Residents telegram T.800 of November 4th. 2. If suggestion should be sent to the is accepted that personal message Sultan of Muscat by the Viceroy / fch.ro ug! 4 A .through f? Political Agent) following is draft of message to he conveyed. Begins■ Please aeeepfmy warm congratulations' on the occasion of bi-centenary of Al-Bu«Baid dynasty and best wishes 1 for the future prosperity of your ^ Highness house, Hnas,5 ~&gt;dr S f / DRAFT TELEGRAM X From: Secretar^ r of State for India,, To: Political Resident in the Persian Gulf 9 Bahrein. Repeated government of India, External Affairs Department. RejyesrtetTTPolitical Agent Muscat. Addressed Political Resident Bahrein. Repeated Government of India S' and Muscat. Your telegrams T/800 and 808, Following is text of message from H*M. ^ ^ r The King for delivery to Sultan of Muscat:- Begins: It gives me great pleasure to send my warmest felicitations upon Z' the celebration of the bicenten z ^ X /' x WiV ^ of ^our Highness's dynasty which^I trust z jgTnu long continue to rule over the Z z” z territories of Oman. The friendship and good.-',rill shown z' towards this country by Vour Highness / throughoutthroughout the present War has been a soxirce of deep^gratificatiofT to me during this bitter struggleI send ^ s' s' ^ ^ you cordial greetings and most sincere •wishes for your long life and happiness and for the prosperity of your House. Snds, ' /• / ^ / 2 e I shall be glad if the following 1 / X ^ X X ^ personal message from myself could also be delivered to Sultan:- Begins: On the occasion of the celebration of the bicentenary of your Highness*s dynasty I send you my warmest greeting and congratulations ^ X X together with ny best wishes for the future 0 Ends, Ti ' Ifr-d-C) copy to: Foreign Office, m ig44 ' ** Goloniay Office e n tt Golonia;v ^t * X# BUCKINGHAM PALACE. n 12th November 1944. My dear The King has approved the draft message to the Sultan of Muscat, enclosed with your letter of November 9th. Will you therefore kindly arrange for this message to be despatched. Yours sincerely, Lieut.-Colonel Sir Gordon Neale, KCVQ.,CIE., India Office.9th tik&amp;m&amp;mr, We understand fraa the Cblonial Office that it is proposed to seixl a oosea^ frefu King to tlse Sultan of S&amp;imib&amp;r on Moves:.her 2Q1h 9 on the occasion of the c©I mt ion of the bioentenary of the A1 husa *id dysiasty* M you iaey know, the dynasty la cocioon to both the liulers of Samlfear and Musoat, th© 3e ; oration of the two states tmving taken place in 1661. The aatan of feiscat isj h»vcvtjr j imlilx; Sahsibar^ an Indepentlent ituler , and la thematically ns.'Utral in the present ynx p thought ii© hoa provided us with, a number of facilities in his territoi^ 1 , particularly for the H*A*F, s i«oe a msm&amp;m is being sont'frora l:*H. to the Sultan Sansibar^ it would atscsii to Isr.Aiaery desirable that the occasion should be taken to sand a to Muscat. X should accordingly be grateful if you mild let m kmm v^hether H#M* ttouia be pleased / io agrt;e to this au^estion and if so / whether ii© would approve tht-j attached draft. {Sd.)Q. ME Ale- The Ht. I on. Sir Alan L&amp;seolles* K*C.B ## K.O.V.O. t C.M#G. $ UmO* § Biwkingboia i^iaoe.May I be permitted to add riy persionai congratidLations to the many messages you vdll be receiving on the oooasion of the auspicious bicentenary of your illustrious dynasty arid, my sincere good wishes for Your Highness- health and for the happiness of your people for many long years to come. Amery,Please refer to the papers at Ext. 4555/44* The Political Resident has now replied saying that he thinks a similar message should be sent from The King to the Sultan of Muscat, and we have received the text of the message which H.M. is sending to Zanzibar (Ext. 4879/44)* PrC'h'fri PbC$ % A draft letter to The King's Private Secretary enclosing a draft message to the sultan of Muscat is now submitted. A draft message from the Secretary of state to the Sultan in accordance with the Private Secretary's note of 26th October is also attached. H U t/i', A x ir- -A ?P&lt;Vt 4totw /fcVo /ivue^v^c^. DRAFT LETTER r OJ^ J0 Vie understand f^Wthe colonial Office /^ ^ s Proposed to send a message from Ju kiutj to the Sultan of Zanzibar on November 20th, gca the occasion the celebration of the bicentenary of the Al Busa*id dynasty* As you may know, the dynasty is common to both the Rulers of Zanzibar and Muscat, the separation of the two states having taken 1 2/y»ph^ place m 1861. /Muscat is, however, ■now r an r h iniependent Ruler, and is theoretically neutral in the present war, thou^i he has provided us with a number of facilities in his territory, particularly for the R.A.F. The Sooretary of~^lM4o oonoid'ere feut £ince a message is being sent from H.M. to u/yu ^ Crt/b*u~i the Sultan of Zanzibar, it Eiii ^desirable /thatwmmmmmm. I-L oc^ that ^ w lw ^lai 1 oTrg^shetJtM to Muscat* I should accordingly be grateful if you would let me know whether H*M. w±ii be pleased to VfUL Ji* J'yinhl**' T' St A- X&amp; approve the attached draft* imy warmest felicitations upon the celebration of the bicentenary of Your Highness* dynasty, which will, I trust. long continue to rule over the territories of Oman* JU friendship and goodwill shown towards this country by Your Highness throughout the nresent war has been a source of deep gratification to me during this bitter struggle* I send you cordial greetings and most sincere wishes for your long life and happiness and for the prosperity of your Rouse*DRAFT MESSAGE EROM THE SECRETARY OF STATE On the occasion of the celebration of the bicentenary of Your Highness' dynasty I send you my warmest greetings: tvyltCu. and congratulations aad best wishes for the future•- —IIEWARI f,oi C.O.^ SECjRET 713 (If in any case the comrminicat-ttel.aQntents v of this document to any person outside British or u»S« Government Service is authorised? it must ,he paraphrased)* departments C opies circ ul ated* W ' N B'i 5 om To Bated CYPHER TELEGRAM Political Resident in the Persian Gulf* Secretary of State for India* Bahrain? 15*20 hours? 5th November? 1944« Received 15*15 hours? 5th November? 3-944* IMPORTANT f?808 ' Paragraph No *5 of my te legram 800 T N ovember 4th * Owing to transport difficulties Political- Agent Muscat? would have to leave Muscat November lith and stay with Sultan a week before November 20th in order to deliver messages on that date* He wi-L.i therefore (? leave) Muscat November 18th to catch the next air se'rvice and actually ( l ? deliver) messages on arrival at Balalah morning of the Slsfc November repeat 21st November*Jo^L. I WARD TKLEGR^'I t ' s C: jr y O 3 SECRET 38581 (If in any case the communication of the conftents of thisdocument to any personj outside, British or U* 8 - Government Service is au^horibe®' it must he -■ n V • * t &gt; 0 ar ap hr asecU ; Allotted t o Externa l Departmen t Copies circulated . ••• ——— cypher TELE GUAM From Political Resident in Persian Gulf- Td Secretary of State for India* Rptd» to Government of India and Muscat* Dated Bahrain. 17*00 hours ? 4th November 1944* Received 19*15 hours? 4th November 1944* IMPORTANT* ~ ~ t Nor'T/800 * Addressed to Secretary of State for India re peated to Government of India and Muscat* Your tele gram 25501 October 19th* As Said Ben Sultan was most important of A 1 Bu Said rulers and held Zanzibar as vassal state of Muscat I consider that if message from King is sent to Zanzibar similar one should be sent through Political Agent to Sultan of Muscat* 2, I suggest a separate personal message of con- gratulation should also be sent through Political Agerr to Sultan of Muscat by his Excellency the Viceroy* 3* November gOth would be suitable date for delivery &lt; ;f b o t h rn a s s a ge s« c tic able 0 J- g .l c a 1 both messages could be conveyed to Agent when he goes to 3alalah to* /'/ / V*s* w f | _ &lt;!■ (? Downing Street, S.W.l. Jf Oototer, 1944 41113/44, A ' ■ Deab Harrison, r ^,.ari-ihL'.^£ere to my letter of 9th Octo'ber about the A1 BUsa’id Bicentenary, I now enclose the text of a message from the King to the Sultan of Zanzibar which has been approved by the King. It is proposed to telegraph the message to the British Resident in Zanzibar on 10th November or very shortly after, but it will not be delivered to the Sultan until 20th November, the day •- fixed for the local celebrations in my letter of A 9th October the reason for the selection of this date by Zanzibar* Yours sincerely, - i oCT 19^ . | • P.A.JC' HARRISON, BSQ,41113/44 DRAFT» CODE TELEGRAM BRITISH RESIDENT ZANZIBAR. Please convey the following message on 20 November from His Majesty the King to His Highness the Suitan f Begins* It gives Me great pleasure to send My warmest felicitations upon the celebration of the Bicentenary of Your Highness’s dynasty, which will, I trust, long continue to rule over the territories of Zanzibar. Great and enduring benefits, including the establishment of the clove industry, have been conferred upon Zanzibar by successive Sultans of the House of A1 Busa’id* Your Highness, ruling with benevolence and sagacity, has enhanced those benefits by advances in every field of economic and social welfare * The fiiben’dship and loyalty so generously extended to My Father and Myself throughout the thirty-three years of Your Highness’ reign, and especially through two long and bitter wars, will not be forgotten by My people in this country* I send you cordial greetings and most sincere wishes for Your long life and happiness and for the prosperity of Your House. End s * SECERUnder Secretary/ of State. Please see the Colonial Office letter of 9th October below. If The King is to send a message of congratulation to the Sultan of Zansibar on the Bi-Centenary of the Al-Busa *id Dynasty which is common to both Muscat and Zanzibar, presumably we should also arrange that he should send a message to the Sultan of Muscat, though, of course, the difference is that while Zansibar is a protectorate, Muscat is an independent state. We might, however, consult theJPolitical Resident, particularly about the date. A draft telegram is attached.OUTWARD TELEGRAM i (l-^ i'-- ^7 case the cornniuriicatioii of the oontents of t ha. s document to any person outside British or American Government Service is authorised^ it must be paraphrased* ) \ i ' ' | v | ■ * External Depar t ment SECRET / CYPHER TELECRAiT From: Secretary of State for India To: Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain. Repeated: Government of India, External Affairs Department, and' Political Agent, Muscat* Despatched: 19 th October, 1914. 23901 . Addressed Political Resident Bahrein, repeated Government 01 India and Muscat. l/|y telegram 20135 September 9 th* Question is under consideration of sending message of^congratulation from King to Sultan of Zanzibar. Message, if sent, would be delivered onJ20th November this oeing anniversary of date of accession of Seyyid Said Bin oultan in ^lSOb*^ This raises question whether, if message is sent to Zanzibar, similar one should be sent to Sultan of Muscat.' Please telegraph your views and whether you consider November 20th would be suitable date also for - Muscat* Copy to: C.O. M ” F.O.'' ? &gt; N w ¥ £- 0 . 'H'C \s u -. ' r INWAl^D \ TELEGRAM \ TISLEGtAM ; ■ /) 0 f . *!««»* f* suoms:^'' 35456 *wr.* r £4. 1 H in any case the communication of the contents of iis document to any person outteide British or? B«S. Government Service is authorised^ it ! must Be •* paraphrased) Allotted to External Department CYPHER TELEGRAM From Government of India? External Affairs Dept* ? To Secretary of State for India. Repeated to Bushire and Muscats bated New Delhi? 19*20 hours*, 11th October? 1944* Received 17o30 hours* 11th October* X944* 13151 . Addressed to Secretary of State for India repeated to Bushire and Museato Your telegram 2Qloh (sic -^ 20155) SeoGember 9tho Issue of Muscat stamps postponed to November Toth. So Please inform High Commiesioner for India*—. 1 ■ I Pi Downing Street, S« 9th October, 1 9kk* tv rw 41113/1*4. Deal? Harrison, ^ li t W : f 1944 j With reference to our telephone conversation this afternoon, I enclose a copy of a printed sheet issued by the Zanzibar Government concerning the coming celebration of the Bicentenary of the Al-Busa'id Dynasty* With regard to the suggestion that a message should be sent on the occasion to the Sultan of Zanzibar from the King, I understand that the India Office view is that, although it would not otherwise be proposed to send a message to the Sultan of Muscat from the King, it would be advisable to do so if the Sultan of Zanzibar is to receive such a message and that, if it is decided to send a message from the King to Zanzibar, you would like to see an advance copy of it* I informed you that the message, if sent, would be delivered to the Sultan of Zanzibar on the 20th November, the date on which the anniverary is to be celebrated, and you said that it does not necessarily follow that it would be appropriate to deliver a similar message to the Sultan of Muscat on the same date* You will see from the enclosed print that this date has been accepted in Zanzibar as being the anniversary of the date of the accession of Seyyid Sa’id Bin Sultan in 1806 to the combined Sultunate of Muscat and Zanzibar* /This P.A.K. HARRISON, ESQ.V * * This date has, however, presumably been chosen in Zanzibar because Seyyid Sa’id was the first Sultan to transfer his headquarters to Zanzibar in 1832 and was also the founder of the clove industry* The date, therefore, might not be particularlv appropriate for Muscat. I will let you know as soon as a decision has been reached with regard to sending a message from the King to the Sultan of Zanzibar. i » Yours sincerely.PRINTED BY THE GOVERNMENT PRINTER, ZANZIBAR. ZANZIBAR. BICENTENARY OF THE AL-BUSA’ID DYNASTY. Issue of Commemorative Stamps. An event of some importance in the Arab world is this year’s celebration of the 200th anniversary of the foundation of the Al-Busa’id Dynasty, to which belong the rulers of Muscat and Zanzibar, for it was in the year 1744 that Ahmed bin Sa’id Al-Busa’id drove the enemies of his country from Muscat (now the capital of Oman on the east coast of Arabia) and himself assumed the Imamate, restoring peace to a land which had for seven years been distraught by civil war and foreign invasion. Under the dominion of the Al-Ya’roby dynasty, predecessor to the Al-Busa’id, the Sultan Seif bin Sultan II, having been deposed by Sultan bin Murshid, was base enough to invite the Persians to support him against his usurper. The armies of Nadir Shah came in 1737 in greater strength than the Sultan Seif had intended and overran the whole country, bidding fair to reduce it to an alien yoke, had not Ahmed bin Sa’id, the Governor of Sohar, a town on the Al-Batinah coast some 150 miles north-west of Muscat, defied the invader with such good effect that he rallied to him the allegiance of every stout-hearted patriot. When in 1744 he recaptured for his country the city of Muscat, he had won for himself, as well by virtue of his personal qualities as by force of arms, the chiefdom of ’Oman. Thus was established the reigning house which, after two centuries, still demonstrates the tradition of sagacious and progressive rule which inspired its founder. The Imam Ahmed bin Sa’id married an Al-Ya’roby princess and exercised spiritual and temporal power over ’Oman, with his capital at Rastaq, until his death in 1783. After this event there followed an unsettled period when rival claimants strove for power. Weakened by division, tlie country was again in danger of falling victim to the opportunism of its enemies, when in 1806 by a bold stroke, Sa’id bin Sultan bin Ahmed, grandson of the conqueror of 1744, and now a youth of no more than 15 years, seized control of the State and commenced a reign of exactly fifty years, which was to prove his genius as soldier, sailor, statesman, and administrator, and was to bestow untold benefit,upon Zanzibar. The connection between Arabia and the East Coast of Africa may be traced at least as long ago as the seventh century B.C., although the earliest record of ’Omani Arabs visiting this littoral is towards the end of the seventh century A.D. For the next thousand years or more the East African Coast had a chequered and turbulent history, ’Omani dominion waxing and waning according to the extent of support received from Arabia. Ahmed bin Sa’id himself sent governors to the ports of Mombasa, Kilwa, and Zanzibar in 1750, and in the years that followed Omani influence continued to increase. Seyyid Sa’id bin Sultan maintained excellent relations with Great Britain, and in 1822 was concluded the first treaty directed against the abolition of slavery. In 1832 he transferred his capital from Muscat to Zanzibar and one of his first acts was, in 1833, to enter into a Treaty of Amity and Commerce with the United States of America; four years later an American Consulate was opened at Zanzibar. In 1841 a British Consulate was established there and its first Consul, Colonel Hammerton, was a very close friend of Seyyid Sa’id. It was upon the orders of this far-sighted ruler that cloves were planted widely in Zanzibar, an industry which has been the main source of the prosperity of this State during the past hundred years. Under Seyyid Sa’id’s rule Zanzibar developed into a commercial metropolis of East Africa and at the time of his death in 1856 the whole of the trade of East Africa was c’entralized on the town of Zanzibar. Seyyid Sa’id was succeeded in Zanzibar by Seyyid Majid bin Sa’id and in the year 1861 Muscat and Zanzibar became independent Sultanates under their respective rulers Seyyid Thweini and Seyyid Majid, both sons of Seyyid Sa’id. The age long trade and connection between the two sultanates has been maintained till this day and members of the Al-Busa’id Dynasty have continued to occupy the throne of both countries in unbroken succession.* His Highness the present Sultan of ZanzTar, Seyyid Sir Khalifa bin Harub, G.C.M.O., G.B.E., revered and beloved of his people, celebrated the Silver Jubilee of his most progressive reign in 1936. He has decided, in consultation with His Highness of Muscat, that the Bicentenary of the Al-Busa’id Dynasty shall be commemorated in Zanzibar on the 20th of November (the accession date of Seyyid Sa’id bin Sultan to the throne of this Sultanate) but that, owing to the war, the celebrations will be on a modest scale. To mark the occasion His Highness the Sultan has approved the issue of commemorative stamps. Their design, in which His Highness has taken a keen personal interest, comprises a Muscat dhow under sail between the coasts of Southern Arabia and East Africa, illustrative of the historical connection between Zanzibar and Muscat. The issue, which is being printed by Messrs. Thomas de la Rue and Co., will be of four denominations, viz. 10 cents, 20 cents, 50 cents, and one shilling. Sale of the stamps will open on the 20th of November, the day of the celebra tions, and will continue for twelve months unless supplies are exhausted earlier. The issue will be strictly limited and in no circumstances will it be reprinted.v'r' Downing Street, S.W.l. r* ^ -' August, 1944. 4704/4/44 . q r Y -~:r —. ^ \ 1 tj J£1 noi _ Dear Harrison,: ' i’ E | /* f $ Thank you. for sending, ud a copy pf the teiLegram ( No.lllOte of , the 25th Augusj t) fr^ig^h[e Govern- ment^bf India atfro^T'the : ''K q TOc , gi't stamps from which we note that September 15th is provisionally fixed as the date of issue. I am sorry to find that we have not been keeping you informed of the Zanzibar position, but now enclose copies of two telegrams rom which you will see that they arranged first for the celebrations to take place on October 2nd, and subsequently postponed them to the 20th November when it is proposed that their stamps shall be placed on sale. You will, I presume, wish to consider whether this will in any way affect the arrangements to be made in Muscat: but I should add that while the printers of the flh Zanzibar .A.K. HAHN I SON, ss ? d*4,111 111 M— - Zanzibar stamps have guaranteed delivery by the SOth November, they state that they are -too busy to be able to deliver earlier. Yours sincerely, 7^.51^— '[£.L.S**rr]INWARD TELEGRAM D* 14th A-ogust^ 1944* R 9 14th ” !i 15,00 hrs» iworntm? Ho« S19 My telegram No* 142 of 6th June, end of paragraph 3 and paragraph 3.? . A1 Busaid ISloentenary? Celebrations now fixed for 20th November, being the anniversary of the accession of Seyyid Said to the Sultanate* This date should allow the despatch of stamps by aea mail, but if receipt in Mombasa by the first week of /November osnnotbe assured, 70,000 oomplete ' set should be sent by air as soon as ready^ Copies sent to:- Crown Agents, for the Colonise*n mm rT« &amp;« O-^atefuI if you 'would traiiemit order to tbid Crown Agents, and inform me of your decision by telegram on proposal in paragraph 3» and probable date of arrival. Copies sent ton Crown Agents for the Golan lea-f L 1&amp;&gt; FILE CC ' . ; vV^ IHWAED TELEGRAM- t ! i 'x-J* C :h&lt;i 'T'liSO. Li 8 Jj|CKST (if in any case the eomrminicat|.on -of the contents ^ this document to any personj outside,Bnitis|i o Government Service is m thorisi paraphrased) A ll ott ed to E x ternal Denartme nt CYPHER ! E L e’ G* R I- From m TO 3 ias®t be ’■''OL (A **r&amp;*4 ’’f £&amp;*/» Government of India, External Affairs •********», lisp a rimer. Secretary of State for India Repeated to Political Resident in the Persian Gulf ani% Muscat*, Few Delhi* 01*85 hours; 25th August* 3.944 6&amp;TQ0 hours# 25th Augusts 1944* &lt;« •*« SMriUM. *&gt;*.* Dated Received 11106* - Addressed^to Secretary of State for India London repeated Political Resident in the Persian Gulf and Muscat. ij*L ' My telegram 4477*April 17th, Muscat stamps. ^Indian postage stamps over printed {J A1 Bu Said 1365 ,? in Arabic are under print and will be sent to Muscat shortly. September 15th has been provisionally M/ /fixed ? V/, ' s(y G/o».■ ■ fixed as date for issue of stamps, 3. Sale of over printed stamps will be confined to year 1944 only and unsold stocks left over on December 31st will be withdrawn and destroyed* If stocks of over printed stamps are exhausted before December 31st further quantities 'will not be reprinted and sale of ordinary postage stamps will be resumed. 4. Political Resident may kindly arrange necessary publicity in Muscat as regards introduction of these stamps. forDear Harrison, N Thank you for your letter of the 29th March about the proposal to issue special postage stamps in commemoration of the bicentenary of the Al-Bu-Said Dynasty. „ So far as Zanzibar is concerned it has been decided to go ahead with the scheme, and I enclose a rough drawing ‘of the suggested design which we have just received from the British Resident. As you will see, the design does not lend itself to the incorporation of a medallion portrait though it might be capable of adaptation in other respects to meet the requirements of paragraph 2 of the Government of India f £ telegram No. 2956 if^Tt should be decided to have a parallel stamp issue for Muscat. We should be grateful if you could return the enclosed drawing fairly soon as there is not much time to spare if the preparation of the printing materials for the Zanzibar stamps F.A.K. HARRISON, ESQ.stamps is not to be unduly hurried. The next step will be to instruct the Grown Agents for the Colonies ''to get Messrs. De la Rue and Company to quote for production with trial drawings based on the enclosed design. Yours sincerely, TR• T• Pnijli, ESQ*, C• B• E• , IMtG• \US4i' J l Downing Street /3 'April 1944 k. H Dear Peel In Seel’q ralagjnce pn leave I am writing, to -ikaiiiLv^bu for your letter Ext. 1444/44 of 7th April about the date of the founding of the A1 Bu Said Dynasty, and to send you a copy of a saving telegram which is being sent to the Acting British Resident in Zanzibar embodying the information contained in your letter. Yours sincerely4* Saving. From the Secretary of State for the Colonies. To the Officer Administering the Government of Date 1044. No. / Saving. / Yom’ eevlng telegram Ho. 33 of 24 4 h Febnr ry. Bi-centenary of A1 Bu Said Byneaty. end sanada^ (otli Lditionf l^O; Volume 11* Page 869 reads aa follows: ^Xa the reign of ftadir Shah the Persians invaded Oman end gained supremacy over the country for Borne 'ime hu^ were eventually expelled by Ahmad bin fa id* the Arab Governor of sohar* a town, on the Batinah Coefst about 150 miles Borth '.feat of Muscat* who contemptuously redacted fiadir Bhah*o claims to tribute* For this service Ahmad was elected Imam in 1741 and founded the present Bynaeiy of the A1 Bu Oeldis* He died^' in 1776 and was succeeded by hi® second son Said***# w 2* J •u Lorimer in hie f *0a&amp;e&amp;eer of the Persian Gulf* ometj and Central Arablegive® more dataila* and X enclose copies of relevant extracts* from which you will see that he gives the date as 1744* 3* This conflict of evidence was referred by the Beere-ary of state for India to the Political 11 aidin' in the Paraian Gulf in 1941. The Political Hesiden' spiled that the Sultan of Muscat was himself uncertain of the date* but that of conflicting authorities consulted evidence favoured Lorimer 1 a dote of 1744*INDE)| COPY Downing Street# .Maytth, 19bU» 41113/44- aV: Dear Peel, j *• AT 14 4 4 I wonder whether you will he able -fo turn up some semi-official correspQndencjeq^h^eh tdok place in 1941 between the India Office and the Colonial Office about the bi-centenary of the A1 bu Ssin-d dynasty common to Muscat and Zanzibar. The best reference I can give you is probably the telegram from the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf to , the Secretary of State_fQ£__Tnrl1,a Ho. bth__ October. 1941, a c0 ^ of whloh enclosed in Harrison’s letter to Rogers of 8th October, 1J41* You will see from the enclosed copy of a saving telegram from the British Resident in Zanzibar that he would like to have a summary of the evidence leading to the conclusion that the dynasty was founded in 1744 and not 1741* I see from your letter toPrior of 4th March, 1941, a copy of which was enclosed in Glauson s . letter to Thornley of 6th March, that Lorimer gives the date as 171+4, and the Political Resident s telegram of 6th October, 1941 says that JT® evioei _ favours Lorimer’s date. We do not seem to ha e A y of any work by Lorimer in our library, while ou edition of Aitchison is unhelpful as Volume XI aoes not deal ivith Southern Arabia at all. I wonder whether you would let me know ^ the full references and any other relevant Particulars R.T. PEEL, ESQ., C.B.E., M.C.which will enable us to reply to the British Resident. We propose to say that in 1941, the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf considered that the balance of evidence was in favour of Lorimer’s date* Yours sincerely, iCOPY. SAVING Prom the Acting British Resident, Zanzibar, to the Secretary of State for the Colonies. . y ate: 24th February, 1944* No. 33 Saving. Your telegram No. 134 December 3th 1941 Bi-centenary of A1 Bu Said Dynasty. Should be grateful to receive summary of evidence leading to conclusion that dynasty was founded in 1744 and not 1741 as generally recorded, so that correct facts may be published when bicentenary is celebrated this year. Am in communcaition with Political Officer, Persian Gulf, with view to arranging date of celebration acceptable to Sultan of Muscat. RAB*p/l'ihl SVL (^Ai) Repeated to Secretary of State for India® Dated Buahire* 1B«I50 hours ? 50th I/.arch^ 1944 0 Received 05.00 hours, Diet March® 1944, B2g. Addreeaed to Government of Jtndxa repeated to London- Your telegram 895b« Mar ch 16t.h » to India Office. //ff-r — In view of sultan of Muscat’s independent status* adoption of Zanzibar design but with Ills Majesty *3 effigy would obviously give rise to unfortunate * comparisons with Zanzibar issue®. 2, Sultan has asked for simple overprint of ?? .Al Bu Said 1363 n in Arabic on Indian postage stamp. Indian. Mint should have no difficulty in producing this and cost woul d be negligible. 1 ^Jeonr ••.end that Suit art’s wishes be met^ icidpntaxiy | these special Isb icb are very profi tabi e &gt; 'CW&amp;rnmeni or India, to ! INDIA OFFICE!/ 'MM. O. o. Eg. 1138/44. Pear Scott, ■^auld you please refer to the GoverBPeiftfc of XodicMs telegraai Ho# 2958, a copy of which we sent you or 18th March, about the suggested issue of postage stamps for Muscat to eottBMBnorate the bio^iteRaxy of the 4 l~BurSai&amp; dynasty. m rather doubt if it is in W worth pursuiag the ciuestion further, but before cessing to a final decision I should be grateful if you would let tae know whether it has been finally decided to issue ccssi aeiaorr.tive stamps for Z»ansibar, and, if thxs is vhe oris©, whether they are to be desigaeci t od printed i^ s the United Kingdcaa# Tours sincerely. E.L. Scott, Esu*, Ctolonfal Office, X#ondon, S.W.1, 4Ext&gt;1188/44, DRAFT LETTER. E.L. Scott, Esq., Colonial Office. ;Y \A ■ fa 1 1944' , « v rJ*r^~ ^?-7V^ r ~~ h DearSoott, ^ ; ¥i t.h rftfpren^n to m^ 1 lu LLe^^Of ''iSie ^6th Janumy, ]&amp;To&gt; -Sxt B 33V4^i i regarding the issue of postage stamps ^to commemorate the bicentenary of the Al-Bu-Said Dynasty, we have jaew heard from the/&amp;6verrment of India that the ^printing of a special'issue of stamps for sat cannot be undertaken in India. isibility of/&amp; set being countp^ The Goverlment of Indj ianzibar issu^with mid be gladyfo know, finally decided to issue commeniorative stamps for Zanzibar, and whethor f if J d’^.T I iAi^ 7 ^ this is the case .they are to be designed and printed in the United Kingdom. fr ji wRepeated to B'ashirs- Dated Bew Delhi, 19«45 he upb* 16th March, 1944- Received 00.30 hours* 17th March, 1944. 2958« Addressed to Secretary or htate repeated a*/^ to Bush ire. Your telegram Mo, 3675 Mobrua?/ loth owing to pressure of war worii special commenorauive cannot be undertaken*in India.if printed in United Kingdom special iseue would preaumabl^ be Beecies MMlPjzE Stamps probably with Z SuXtar^s effigy ore re print of ^Muscat 1 * on which would be inappropriate* Sd Possible plan appears to be for His Ma^est:/ f s Government to print Rupees 50,000 worth of etaups of a similar'design to Zanzibar issue but bearing His @ffigy rind clear indication that tneF’are * | Indian postage stamps. Stamps so printed viouli he issued to Muscat post office for sale during 1^44 and cost debited to Indian Doat Office administretlono dost- -Oi. production or this quantity may be _ lxexeyant xaotor and we doubt if it is really w^rth while ' iew of ^ he ' D'-^ (* INDEXED £4 V\ \ f' f Tf Downing- Street, o* W.|l. 41113/43j o.'bW Dear ^arrii 6 o &amp; T December, 1943, 1943 i In October 1941 we corresponded with you and Glauson about the date of the Bi-centenary anniversary of the A1 Bu Said dynasty, and as a result it was agreed that 1944 should be accepted, on the balance of evidence, as the appropriate date. ,/e have now had a telegram from the British Resident of Zanzibar enquiring tentatively whether the occasion would be regarded as suitable for the issue of commemorative postage stamps by Zanzibar. It is not clear^ whether he has yet consulted the Sultan in the matter, but it is probable that he will not do so until he has received our reply to his preliminary enquiry. We should like to reply that, provided the Sultan agrees, we see no objection to the issue of commemorative stamps, but before doing s o we should -i? r#LiSP|? e 9 9 DEC1943 ' »NDIA F.A.K, HARRISON, BSQ.r ,— be glad to be assured that the India Office has no objection to the proposal from the point of ^ view of possible repercussions the Persian Gulf. The matter is one of some urgency if the design of the stamps is to be settled and all arrangements made for their issue during the coming year, and we shall be grateful therefore for an early reply. Yours sincerely, £'E-L..Sc.oTtJ5 41113/41 S / &amp; ^ l' 34 { 1 s 4 1 Code Telegram TO ZAMIBkE TO: British Resident (Sir H, Pilling) THOM: Secretary of State for the Colonies, Sent 4th December* 1941, 20,SO hrs, IMMEDIATE qnc^ Your telegram No, 155. Following 1 ' from Parkinson s begins« ' In my letter to you of 8 th November sent by air mail I explained that after consultation with India Office it had been decided that 1944 should be accepted as bicentenary date. I also suggested that question of action then could Da deferred but that meanwhile you might let Sultan kno\¥ that after considering available evidence we have now ooma to conclusion that 1944 not 1941 should be accepted as bicentenary. Unless you sea strong reason to contrary we do not propose to arrange for any message to Sultan on 9th December. Ends,— — Colonial Office, Downing Street. 6 November, 1941. My dear Pilling, I had some correspondence ear^y this year with Stooke in which reference was made to the M-centenary anniversary of the A1 Bu Said %nasty as occurring this year, and in my last letter to him, dated 26th February, I said that we had it in mind to arrange for a message to be sent to the Sultan on the anniversary of his Aitee^&amp;ion Day in which reference would be made to the bi-centenary of his dynasty. Since then we have been inecorrespondence with the India Office who wrote to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf on the subject. As a result of this correspondence we have agreed with the India Office that, although 1741 has been given as the date of the election of Ahmad bin Said as Imam, the available evidence favours on balance 1744 as being the correct date of this event and that 1944 should accordingly be accepted as the date of the bi-centenary. Actually the anniversary appears to be attracting little or no attention in the Persian Gulf and, unless the Sultan of Zanzibar or his people are more impressed by it, it would seem questionable whether any special message to the Sultan in honour of the occasion is necessary or desirable. This question, however, can be postponed for further consideration in 1944. In the meantime it might be as well to let the Sultan know that we have now come to the conclusion after considering the available evidence, that 1944, and not 1941, should be accepted as the bicentenary anniversary of his dynasty. Yours sincerely, (sgd.) A.O C Parkinson. Sir Henry Pilling, K.C.M.G. OOPY SEN f l. t » - ENCLOSURE Hi WAIL LETTER No. 4 6 1 5 NOV 1941 FROM SECRETARY, EXTERNAL DEPT,, jNDtA OFFICEP.P.Turnbull, Esq. L^ar Turnbull, With reference to Olauson’s letter of the 31st October about the bi-centenary anniversary of the A1 Bu Said dynasty, I am enclosing a copy of a letter which Parkinson sent to Sir Henry Pilling on the subject, 7 Private Secretary.COLONIAL OFFICE, Downing Street. ^ November, 1941. Aw OUUL*. 'a. I had some correspondence early this year with Stooke, in which reference was made to the bi—centenary anniversary of the A1 Bu Said Dynasty as occurring this year, and in my last letter to Nim, dated 26th February, I said that we had it in mind to axx nge for a message to be sent to the Sultan on the anniversary of his Accession Day in which reference would be made to the bi centenary of his dynasty. Since then we have been in correspondence with the India Office who wrote to the political xiesident in the Persian G-ulf on the subject. As a result of this correspondence we have agreed with the India Office that, although 1741 has been given as the date of the election of Ahmad bin Said as Imam, the available evidence favours on balance 1744 as being the correct date of this event and that 1944 should accordingly be accepted as the date of the bi-centenary. Actually the anniversary appears to be attracting little or no attention in the Persian Gulf and, unless the Sultan of Zanzibar or his people are more impressed by it, it would seem questionable whether any special message to the Sultan in honour of the occasion is necessary or desirable. This question, however ; can be postponed for further consideration in 1944. In the meantime it might be as well to let the gultan know that we have now come to the conclusion after considering the available evidence, that 1944, and not 1941, should be accepted as the bi-centenary anniversary of his dynasty. | SIP HENRY PILLING, • 1 - f.l, V - «u tt3 ^ b fin compliments of L * *•»« (&gt; /uH&lt; * No . Wttfi U. S . 8 . In March last the political Resident in the Persian Gulf was consulted with regard to the observalic&amp;a# of the Bi-Centenary of the A1 Bu Said Dynasty, which rules both in Zanzibar and in Muscat (see P.Z.1105/41). It will be seen that the authorities differ on the question whether the Bi-Centenary falls in 1941 or 1944. The Political Resident’s reply (Ext.6308/41) shows that, (a) the Sultan is uncertain which is the correct date, though the evidence seems to favour 1944; and (b) no celebrations in Muscat are contemplated. In these circumstances we can surely agree to Lord Moyne’s proposal that 1944 should be accepted as the Bi-Centenary year, and it is suggested that the Private Secretary at the Colonial Office should be so informed. This department will then tell the Political Res i dent.21|3&lt;t ^ctoberL 1941. D r '~ s Glauson, Harrison recently sent to Rogers a copy of a telegram from the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf replying to Peel f s personal letter to him of the 4th March, a copy of which was in your note to me of the 6th March. After considering the question in the light of Prior f s telegram, Lord Moyne thinks that 1944 should he accepted as the hi-centenary anniversary of the Al Bu Said dynasty and he proposes to inform the British Resident at Zanzibar to this effect. Before doing so, however, he would he glad to know that Mr. Arnery is in agreement. RECo, POL Yours sincerely. ' &gt; OCT 941 INDiA OFFICE | Private Secretary M.J. Clauson, Esq.Ju^' 8 th October 1941. Dear Rogers, I enclose a copy of a telegram now received from the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf about the bicentenary of the Al Bu Said dynasty, about which you spoke to me the other day. Yours sincerely, p -a.k:.h. P. Rogers, Esq.Allot 1.6125 BSOIPHSR QP From ^PoTTRes- iB the Persian ^ Quits to s, of So for Xndi^. stated Risher 15-30 hre, 5th Oct, 1941. Received 17,45 hrs, 6th Oct.1941, X .15, /3/^ Addressed to S. of S. for India repeated Govt of India copy 'by post Muscat. Your tele gram 1 .2 $ 2X 9 dated 2nd October. Bicentenary of Ali Bin Said dynasty. 2. Sultan is uncertain of (&lt;? date)' and no local celebrations are contemplated but he has no objection to mention by o^Length of rule of his dynasty. 3. Of conflicting authori ties consulted evidence favours Lorimer s dat e 1944.P.Z. 1170/41 Copy Extract from Muscat Intelligence Summary No. 23 for the period from 1st to 15th December 1940. LOCAL INTBHESIS. 294. On the afternoon of December 4th the Sultan informed me that he had received news from Dhofar to the effect that his wife there had given birth to a boy. The Sultan was extremely pleased and said his son would be named Kaboos ( ). The event has caused general pleasure.your letter to Lieut.-Col. Prior enclosed. Yours sincerely. M.J. Clauson, Esq6 th March 1941. Dear Thornley, With reference to Lord Moyne*s letter of the 19th February to Mr. Arnery, you may like to have the enclosed copy of a letter which has been sent to the Political resident in the Persian Gulf about the bicentennial anniversary of the Al bu Said dynasty. Yours sincerely, (Sgd.) M. J. QLAUMi Thornley, Esq■ — — - — - - ■ o rG w y e ar- eun c3_ Ecicn onci s K w ® o 4 o o 4 !» ct ►J P tt 4 ct h tn 0 ct ct P ct ct 0 0 4 * ct 0 r P 19th February, 1941. About a month ago you forwarded to my predecessor the enclosed letter from Mr. Said-Ruete, in which he intimated that this year was the bicentennial anniversary of the Al Bu Said Dynasty. In the interval, the Acting British Resident of Zanzibar has been consulted, and he has now told us that, in view of the war and of the pressing need for the strictest economy, the Sultan does not propose to celebrate the occasion. But later in the year I think it might be appropriate if the King were to send the Sultan a message of congratulation and greeting on the anniversarjr of his Accession Day, and the opportunity might be taken to incorporate in the message some suitable The Right Honourable L.S. Amery, M.P.mmKMKKmmmmmmammammm — suitable allusion to the fact that the present year is the bice; ennial anniversary of the Dynasty.B. Sai d-Ruete •• qO .T£'- e ,^ s '• o Queen Hotel Harrogate January 4th 1941 Dear Mr. A m e r y, \ It occur©d to me \ that you might like to knov; - if not known already - that this year is the ■bicentennial anniversary of the AL BU SAID DYNASTY Ahmed bin Said was elected Imam of Oman in 1741 and became thus the Bounde (r of the Reigning Family. The present Sultan represents the 7th generation and is the 11th Ruler of Oman/Mnscat. Yours sincerely The Rt. Hoi L. S. A m e r y,M.P. - India Office - LONDON. S.W. 1 v t.e.cfj I t. o. ^sBrsTirtrs/ \ MtzMprt N°. &lt;yi67 of 1937. i. ■» 9 3 / The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to !• J.C*«alton hisquire, CB#,MC* ? The India Offi&lt; Jjondon* * ? I Ice, / 2* Major R*P*vVatts f IA #?; Political Agent, mscat, a.t Karachi. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents Office of the Political Resident in the Persian uilf, Camp, Bahrain* BSajxsboGcsKDd^tBcfibmmdpc^SfiSidS^ Dated.... J16th, /Augil?,t,. 1Q.37&lt; Reference to previous correspondence: A Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. i^emi-official letter Ro. C/166 of the 16th August 1937 to the Secretary to the Government of India, Externa.- Affairs Department, Simla* RECB. POL. DEPT. esfPia® INDIA wFFICEj Subject. Position and personality of the Sultan of ms cat*! f I* V k ?2!' t klsjJir-ki*. l '- A tyfc/Z -rt,^ f ^' , 'H'6 f f ; ^ pv titt) r ? ?f V~&gt; «^' I}*0*Ho*C/16ts • Office of the Political Hesidoat i la the Persian Gulf* i .,,. - Camp, Bahrain. Bated the 16th August 193?* I think a &amp;ote m Sultan of Muscat rmy he l^useat coming to the fore Bevialon etc* the position and personality of the use at the present juncture with in the matter of Oil* Treaty 2* As you are aware the present Buler omm to the tlirons in si^ewlmt peculiar circumstances* His father* Saiyid Tainsur, though a pleasant enough personality* ms averse to work and responsibility and for a number of years had been an absentee Baler refusing to visit hi© b'tate* This being so some arrangements for managing the affairs of the State had to be devised* A Council of Bsgeney ms formed consist* ing of local notables at the head of which was placed Bertram jThomas* of exploration fame, then financial Adviser to the Muscat Govenment* Thomas in the Council had the title^of' Wasir, and he and the Political Agent between them formed the government of the state to all intents and purposes* about 2 years after I had succeeded Muscat, naiyid Taimar insisted on abdicating, and the present Sultan came to the throne as a boy of about 22* He had a difficult position to mi* Thomas, while he had done the political side of his work well enough, had neglected the matter of finances, and the State was practically bankrupt* There were also signs of tribal unrest in various parts of the Muscat territories* The / The Kon’ble Lieut .-Colonel A *E*B •Parsons, CBE*,1B0*, Secretary to the Government of India, External Affairs Department, Dimla* Murphy as PoliticalThe mm mi%sm had la addition a crowd of ’’wicked imcles** all older than hia 9 one of bfow:a f daiyid Hamad, was Governor of the outlying district® of 3ohar f whare he had practically sat up an independent regime. The young Sultan had in fact a tough job on his hands, and, helped by me whenever I could, tackled it with considerable resolution. The first step which carried he took was to proceed to ioh&amp;r in the state gunboat,/a three-* j pounder gun and. formed the Muscat Ilavy^ with a detachment of the Muscat Infantry and a set of irons which he said he would place on his uncle if he proved recalcitrant I It was a bold move and a successful one. Hamad climbed down, was made Wall of Muttra, where he could be under the eye of the Sultan, and since then the ^wicked uncles’* have been well under control. 4* The Oultan also set about the reorganisation of the State finances with zeal arid not a little skill ~ he has quite a flair for finance, and assisted by Biscoe and myself brought the estate off the rocks. It is now financially in a comparatively flourishing condition. The Sultan is duly grateful for this assistance and has, 1 think, a genuine personal liking for me, which I certainly reciprocate, dating from the time when I was Political Agent at his State and we went through some difficult times together. At the same time the fact that - as explained hi paragraph 2 above - the State for some years was unavoidably run under British administration has made him all the more sensitive in the matter of British control. This attitude is only to be expected. The independence of small States is very much in the air these days and the Sultan naturally enough has these ideas as well as other Bulers* To pat the matter briefly he wants to run his own show, and we will have to humour him to some extent and, generally speaking, rida him on t&amp;# -i ... : • - • 5* akssawfei - -** - 1 mettle m The fact that h© tes asked of hisTreaty indicates «*» my Ma ®lnd is moving, and the further fact that - unlike the other Utatee to the Qulf - his State i# tote ■nationally independent, (he can have foreign representatives at Muscat if he likes - at one time there used to be American and French Consuls there - and could send representatives abroad if ha could afford than), mkeshis position a strong cme. ' 5. As will appear from my surarary of his history the Sultan has various sound qualities* he is shrewd and energetic, with a flair for finance, and has a will of his own. He has a pleasant personality, though very short to stature (about 6*8) bears himself with considerable dignity, and is endowed - 1 am glad to say - with a quiet sense of humour, which lightens the despatch of official business. He speaks excellent English, which he learnt at the Chiefs' College, Ajmere, where he was for sons tine. He is - as Biases pointed out to one of his letters - rather a lonely figure. His uneles, whom be would ordinarily consort with, are distinctly Inferior to him to intelligence (with the exception of Hamad already mentioned) and he has little to common with them. It would he an excellent thing if he married some educated Arab girl of good family * at present he has various concubines - one or two to uacat and one or two to flhofar, but no wife. The difficulty is that there is negro blood to the Saiyid family, and the other Haling families to the r 5ulf e. &gt; the A1 Khalifah of Bahrain, and the aubah of Kuwait, will not give one of their women to marriage to the Muscat Bwi ing fanily. I imagine the Arab families of Iraq, Syria etc. would feel the 6 , Having so far given the sultan a good 'confidential'I suppose X ought to put in something on the other sidle* He is extremely obstinate and once he has got an idea into his head it is voir difficult to get it out again. Also whilst fully alive to the value of assistance from His Majesty*« Government (which has been ferihces&amp;ing on various mm&amp;imm in various ways he is by no mm» too ready to reciprocate when his coM^peratiOfi i© needed by uss instances of this have occurred of late* further, having worked very hard at first at pitting his Gtate in order now that the State is solvent he has slacked off, and - as you are aware ** has spent much of his time at nhofar* an inaccessible area quite out of touch with his Capital and the rest of hi® territory* Bhofar, about ha If«• way 'between Muscat and Aden, is the most fertile district in the Sultan 4 © dominionsi and has the best climate, and Watts, who has visited it a couple of times by j Royal Air Bores plane, informs me that the Sultan has effected many improvements the ret buildings, gardens etc* this or course is all to the good,and 1 certainly don’t blame the Sultan for '* V ' u . I wishing to have © pleasant country seat to which he can retreat at intervale from the Muscat hot weather and the attention© of the Folitioal Agent end the Resident* But unfortoiately the Sultan’s retreats have been extremely prolonged* the last ! one, from which he emerged in mroh last, having extended to about 14 years* During these retreats nothing really import** j ant can be decided at Muscat, and both on behalf of Government, and personally 1 X have drawn the Sul tan* a attention to the undesirability of these prolon ©d absences, but I am afraid without much effect since next winter he proposes &amp; long tour to Japan, the United States of America and Europe* However, one must remember that he is still young, 37, that yotth the /i A l f E the time to see the world, and hope that he will 'marry and settle down' in a few years. * 1 m sending copies of tola letter to Belton and Watts. Yours sin^e''elu ? To'VYo-le* ^ sent under Printed letter !fo*C/167 the UBth August 2937# j /</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000602.0x00020c_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/2980</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000602.0x00020c</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/2980</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 20/21 'Muscat: Royal family - Note on the Sultan'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1937/1945</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-07-21T23:03:54</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (101 folios)</extent><extent>The file is arranged in chronological order.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 103; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Correspondence regarding the Muscat royal family, in particular the bicentenary of the Al Bu Said [Āl Bū Sa‘īd] dynasty.The majority of the papers concern the 200th anniversary of the Al Bu Said lineage attaining power in Oman in 1744. Several matters are discussed:the precise date on which to mark the eventhow to mark the event, including the issue of a series of commemorative stamps in Muscat and Zanzibar (where a strand of the dynasty holds power) and the discussion over design and quantitieswhether the British Broadcasting Corporation (BBC) should cover the event in some waymessages of congratulation from various figures, including King George VI of BritainAlso contained within the file:a note by Lieutenant-Colonel Trenchard Craven William Fowle, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, on the 'position and personality' of the Sultan of Muscat, Said bin Taimur [Sa‘īd ibn Taymūr Āl Bū Sa‘īd], dated 16 August 1937 (folios 98-102)report of the birth of the Sultan's son in December 1940 (folio 86)The principal correspondents include officials from the Political Residency in the Persian Gulf, Colonial and India Offices, and Buckingham Palace.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Buckingham Palace</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Commemorative stamps</topic></subject><subject><topic>Anniversary celebrations</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Persian Gulf Political Residency</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Colonial Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>British Broadcasting Corporation</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="family"><namePart>Āl Bū Sa'īd (Family)</namePart></name></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000602.0x00020c#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>