<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0001ac_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T06:02:55.367Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">(b) Ras-alKhaimah . The Wali reported to me taat shei^ih sultan bin iM Salem of Has-al Kiiaimah ha© writer hi- a lat er ciainiuj that the Baai Hauijah and that KUmaari section of tne Bani Shatair ar^ no ionger uxider tne Muscat Goverume t ana tnat he, Sheiicn sultan, claims them as his sutgecttu He proposes ^o Ityy an annual tribute of 600 Rupees odd. The Wali has not as yet ansv/eced thepretensious claim of the Sheikh of Ras-al Khaimah. (O) GENERAL . The wali stated tiat he personally was very giad to see the four ships anchoring in the bay, it would show that tne Muscat Government had the support of the British and the elfect would be to keep the shihuh tribes from giving trouble for a space. II AFTEKN00H MEETIUG On landing we met with a very cordial reception and were entertained at the wali 1 s fort. After the usual commonplaces a vexy ling complicated discussion touk place# (a) The first part of the discussion dwelt upon the questioiii of tne sheikh of Dibah* s conciliatory ad vances* The Wali repeated that they had come through the KUmazari, but that he was at a lose to reply to th. without instructions? the matter was dropped at hat point while the general talk jtook an unexpected turn. (b) The wali turned first to Mohammed bin sulai- man of Kumzar andfchen to sheikh Hilal bin Ali of hassab and demanded of them to tell him now in the presence of the Senior uaval officer ana his officers whether they had any treaty or secret understanding with tne Sheikh i ultan of Has-al-Khaimah, they entered a spirited denial of having made any such agreement or indeed of ntending to do so, but thej, (8a4®^&lt;0@®admitted that they had been friendly wi ua the Joswami which did not mean that they owed any ailggiance to Rascal -ilhaimah. ar the ^mentioned during the forenoon meeting tiiat he wished to speaa. to me private^ as totne advisability of taJcing taese two men witn him to Ras-al-Khaimah to seej£ an explanation of his demands from shielch Sultan, I began to see sojr.e day- li 0 ht through the general maae of intrigue. The sxoelient understanding which seemed to exiso between the Waii and ti ' e two Sheiishs now appeared to be less evident in the po litical sphere, in other words taewali distrtiated them. («) Having taken advantage of our presence to put this leading question to them, and having obtained a ropl'? which did not alte^ether satisfy him the wali Kept the con versation on general lines until the time arrived for him to dismiss the two sheinhs and the remainder of the company. He then unburdened his soul to me, put his real suspicions into words aaa asked for advice, (d) Prefacing his remarks witn an allusion to the ammedan xu i e tJiat no watel , is availabie to vvasll before prayer then sand is a suitable substitute, by which he was understood to suggest that if Mohammad bin sulaiman of rcumza a.nd Hilal bin Ali of Khaesab were not able of t-.eir own au thority to resist the pret-nsions of sheikh sultan of Has- al-iihaimah then they should fall back on he general b ,dy of their subjects for the necessary support, the ali prooee ded to describe what he thought was the true pos Won, ire suspects thAt th-e overtures of sheikh saleh of Dibah are not honest they are intended to throw off the scent of other more/important events, sheikh Baleh is in fact doing al in his pow^r to unaermine the sh-V &lt; shadowy influence of Muscat in the peninsular, in his work he is assisted by Hilal bin Ali ^ ****** Sulaiman who are making secr.t overtmr... t. SheiKh S uj.tan of aas-al iihaimah, while s^leh himself i B Sing to divert the talLs attention ^ persuading shei^x 3u x tol to write letters incorporating tne demands mentioned above, le) The wali has ta^en ste.s to get into touch withQ/i* SheikJa Saiela, and haa intended to write for insoructiuna from Muscat on tiais matter. He was advised by me to carry out iu5 iixteation. At first when Ras-aiKiiaima-n* s claim was put for- Q/U wara, he had thought of going t^ Hab-al-Khaimah with Hilal fci* Mohammea to seeK an ^xpianation, but his suspicions of txiese two individuals* attitude bein^ aroused f he deferred taking an^ action beyond informing the Muscat G-vernment and is now awaiting a letter from the Council. He is very strongly of t.ic opinion that the council should reply definitely that the tri bes are not to pay tribute to Ras-al-Khaimah and th; t it shoul take steps to reprimand sheikh Saleh of Bibah for his macLine - tions. Otherwise he is of the opinion that th- last veotise of tne Sultan's prestige in the ruso al jibal peninsula ..ill disappear. I agreed with him that he should contixiue to r - port on the whole question, to Muscat and should await the Council*s decision, rather than go himself to Rab-al- ijaimn in the company of two pecsons of seemingly doubtful inte^ri oy # (f) Xne sol® British subject resident in ^mssab mi .. of tne company, he gave it as his opixiiou that much of tne trouble was caused by the fact that th^e wali was trying to enforce a tax on the fisheries export trade. (g) This Indian merchant said tr de was bad, the people very poor, but he sougnt no assistance for the re covery of debts totalling 4 ,000 Rupee© which he s id v/ere owing to him. He explained that the people were so poor ^ley could not pay him at present, though if he had the money he would return to India. (h) some eight months ago this man do ght a dhow which was brought into Kha 8ti ab, having been aalwed when found drifting and abandoned on the high seas. The tranuaoUon was witneaeed by the &lt;6 then Wali and a oertifioate of ownerahip ana registration isauea to the Indian, who has repaired Wj veaaei ana ia employing it xn trade. Kow a claim »a a baea mde from iubai that th. Teasel belongs to people of that port who threaten t. seize it on the sea if met with or if it toucheu atDe^ai. He was toid tnat in tiie meantime he should endeavour m obtain coxifirnation of tne rttmour, for it is only a ruiaour, f that the sheiim of Debai ii^tenda to sei^e xt# (k) Q promisea to ma^eenquiries of the Residency Agent ana to report the natter to the Honourable the political Ke- sident • The Wali said tmt he intanded to seize tv/o Dabai dhov&amp; if the merchant's veLsel is detained at Debai» 11) 'i'he tribal matters referred to above I said v/oula be reported in due course to the Honourable the political Ke- sident and explained that he would iuall probability dec„l v /itla them in due course. (m) For himself the Wali wondered what offence he lu d co. iaitted against the Government that he should be regarded uy being sent to this out of theway place to live with a loaded rifle by his side amongst 'goats' not 'people'•A *Ji til Translation of a letter dated 25th Rabi al Thani 1350 (9th September 1951) from Saiyid Seld bin Taimur, President of the Council of Kinisters, Muscat State, to Captain R#G» Alhan, Political Agent and Consul, Muscat. BUSHfRf R h- Biib 1/(&amp;/$/ After Compliments CONf}DENTfyvL With reference to my visit to Khasab v/hicti/T vi/as ; able to 'iiTake through your assistance in one of Ships st the end of the la month, I take the opportunity of expressing my thanks to you. I reached the place and as I had already been informed found it peaceful and the people loyol to the G-overnment of the Sultan of Muscat and Oman. Enquiries were made as to the appointment of a new Shaikh for the Eani Hadieh tribe in place of the late Shaikh; this however was postponed pending my return to Muscat where T could better Judge as to the most efficient among the Shaikhs of the Bani Hadieh for the appointment. A temporary 3haikh has been appointed, but when a permanent one is selected, the ¥ali, who is representing us there, wi-11 be advised accordingly. There is nothing further to write in connection with this my journey but that affairs are satisfactory and it is hoped that there will be no further incidents. In conclusion I express my thanks to our Honourable Friends the Government for the assistance rendered in subjugating the rebels last year and restoring peace at Khasab. We wish that their assistance and favours towards the Government of the Sultan may continue and our friendly relations be strengthened. 13o.C-225. Political Agency and H.B.M's Consulate, Muscat, the 29th September 1931. Copy forwarded to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, for information. (1^00^ Captain, Political Agent and H.B»M T s Consul.V 1 p II vs % I ill. % Uated. 12til Sha'ban Io50x22na December 1931. vrom To. Shaikh Said Mn Maktum Ruler of WbaiEu Deloai The Hon f 'ble Cfolonel H.V.Blsooe. Political Resident/j in the P.G-ulf. Bushire Af ter 7ornp 1 iraen t s • I 'beg to oonfira my conversations with Your Honour in oonneotion with Shaikh Hasan when I reques you to give permission that he should leave Muscat and to come to &lt;114 in DeTaai and this you promised (to do )» X now he^ to trouble you hereoy re^ardii this matter and hereby give you and H.H.the Sultan of Muscat a complete undertaking and assurance that the said Hasan will never go to Khasa'b and that he and his family will be made by ttut- to reside in Debai and that they will send an agent to look after their date trees in Khasab. mm _3 ' ' A Vo.C^Cj Politicial Agency &amp; H.B.M's Consulate, Muscat, \^J^Uu March 1932. Ae To The Secretary to the Hon'tle the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. &gt;1 /I t Memo r and un . With reference to your letter No. S/-5 dated the 16th January 1932. I have approached the Sultan on the subject, who hss accepted the Shaikh of Debai*s security and has sent Shaikh Hasan to Dehai. Lt-Colonel, Political Agent &amp; H.B.1:'s Consul.£5/141. repeated to No G»T.G* » &amp; e saKien t, Bu siiir e, Saenior inaYal ufii cer &gt; a * warship 'ITiadS Henjaa Kadio, Commander warship 'Shoreham-, lien jam Radio, 464, Dated the Ist: August 1932. Im portant * correspondence ending with shorehami1135. please convey my thanks to Commander shoreham for naving got Hassan away from Khassab so promptly where his presence might have lea to serious complications as in April 1930. riassan having broken his parole, provided it is not against any guarantees which may have ceen given oo him or to Shaikh of Uehai 1 would be grateful if Shoreham could tase nassan on board and transport him to muscat there to be interned pending orders of the sultan. Jailing tnis Shaiith of ilebai should imprison him at jJebai • Kesident.-.V,, - &gt; - . - 3M'+I dp 0) From - The Residency Agent, Sh&amp;rgah To - Captain E.K. Gastrell, Secretary to the Eon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gull. iIo,^38. i^ted 4th august 1932. .0, H' Mth reference tc letter Ho .540 cl 22r(i l&gt;eceiiiber ^92J on the sutject ci Shaikh Hasan bin Kuhemmad who v;as under custody at Muscat and the request made by the Shaikh cl Debai ior his release irom there, 1 beg to state that the said Hasan lied from I&gt;ebai in a dhow sailing for Khasab. When the Shaikh ci Debai heard this news he at once started for Khaseb by his large launch in the is pursuit. They ^.11 arrived at Khasab. I enclose herev/ith a letter in original Irom the Shaikh of I^ebai to me pointing out how the case of Hasan was dealt with by him in the presence of the Commander of the Warship in which arrived Ibrahim bin Jumah on lehali of the Sultan of Muscat. u.Letter dated ist Rati ul Thuii 1351 ( ) irom Shaikh Baid bin i^aktum A1 Eashar, Chiel oi iebai, to Khan Bahadur Isa bin Abdul Latif, Residency Agent, Shargah. A.C . I he.\'e to inform you that 1 have returned from Khasab on the 27th Rabi ul Awal 1351 { /■ ?' 1% ). With regard to the case of Hasan bin Muhcjnmad. He arrived home at 3 o'clock at night (Arabic) and we arrived at 3 o*clock morning when discussion took place. He is quite insane and had no objection to return with me but his people are wild and quarrelsome. However he left lor Bokha at night. A warship also arrived at Khasab carrying Ibrahim bin Muhammad bin Jumah, representative of the Sultan oi kuscat. They wanted to see the man personally. We therefore went to -Bokha where the warship also arrived. The Captain and the doctor looked at the said Hasan and found that he is quite insane. T asked their advice as to whether they wish him to return to Bebal or to stay at Bokha and they asked my opinion. In my opinion it is advisable that he should remain at Bokha at present. Vv'e took Shaikh 1-uhammaa bin Ahmad bin Sulaiman as surety and he is now responsible for him. He obtained a document from him and stood surety. ,, ,11,111,111111-111 1 ——— i l*—■■W——* He is very sick. He is under our orders and will return to D e bai whenever we wish him to do so# A wise man 'siould not blame a r..an like Hasan isk his action, because he is neither uselul to himself nor to his shaikhdoia. Ee is not a man to play tricks, but hie people who called on him instigated him to do sc. 1 pray C-od that the end of the all airs may be good. I thank &lt;Jod that tre were successful in our journey and return. U.E.Enclosure to 'Shoreham's' Ho.56/? of Aug.^,.. Sectioii I DIBBAH. DIBBAH (Lat.25 0 uB 1 H, loiig.56 0 17' E.) is situated at the JUBCtioa of two shelkhdouia, the aorthern territory is occupied ty the SHIHUH tribe and is under the suzerainty of MUSCAT the nearest representative of that state heins 'resident at EHASAB, the southern territory though sho - .ra in Map II attached to P.G.lo as forming part of the Truclal Sheikhdoms v /ould appear in fact to be independent, its present ruler belli Sheikh RASCHID. (This pant is dealt '.ath 1 ter in Section III of this report.) The forts of 'xrth ruling Sheikhs ire visible from seaward, the boundary of the territories lying approx imately midway between them. 2. Some two months ago the ruling Sheikh of uort'iern DIBBAH died leaving three candidates in the field vflth claims to succeed him, viz, Sheikh ABDOLLA SULTAH aged bout 80 Sheikh MOHAMED MAIDI aged ibout GO Sheikh ZAID SOAH aged ibout 40. I had thought that these three •.Tare sons of the late Sheikh but there now p. ears to be some doubt .bout that, though it seems to be generally '.greed that they are of equal blood relationship. b. ABDULLA SULTAH and ZAID SHAH live at DIBBAH uh 1 early is July ZAID SIM AH with the concurrence of ABDULLA SULTAH prod dmed himself Sheikh. This was contrary to the wishes of the more stable elements of the population who protested to P the ne rest MUSCAT Government representative, the WAKE of L KHASAB, as also did Sheikh RASCKID, ruler of Southern DIBBAH, feariig that the resulting unrest would spread to his territoryl MAHOMED MIDI the third candidate fho lives near KHASAB aid the one with perhaps the strongest claims, hearing of these eveats at the same time as they were cor unicated to the WALI of KHASAB set out for DIBBAH to look after his interests ;.nd prosecute a campaigi in favour of his own candid ture . 5. This was the position when 'Shoreham' called at KHASAB on 18th July. 6. On arrival .t MUSCAT I informed the Acting president of the Council of Segency (Captain R.C-.E.W.Alban) of the state of affairs at DIBBAH aid handed to him the letters which had been written to the WALI of KHASAB by Sheikh ZAIB SIHAH S opponents at DIBBAH and Sheikh RASCHID. I also informed him that 'Shoreham' after calling at MUSCAT on her return from KHOR JARAMA would be visiting DIBBAH and that I /ould be of any assistance I could. 7. Accordingly on my return to MUSCAT I received a request from the Council of Regency to embark three representatives, Sheikh IBRAHIM bin MAHOMED bin JUMA and two lesser persons,and to convey them to DIBBAH and if possible KHASAB. 8. On arrival at DIBBAH Sheikh IBRAHIM, who had been authorised...Enclosure to 'Shoreham's' II0.56/7 of srd Aug.52. Rectloa I. DIBBAH. Costa . authorised to appoiat M0HOMED MAIDI Sheikh, despatched letters orderinc all three cacdidates f .r the Sheikhdom to report at KHASAB. It wis also decided to convey Sheikh RASCHID, ruler of Southern DIBBAH, there lla^o. 9. Shortly after arrival at KHASAB a message was received from MAHOMED MAIDI by the haad of his soi who had left DIBBAH 27th July (two days before 'Shorehams visit) statia: that he was ready to preseat htoself at KHASAB s sooa as directed to do^ so. 10. ZAID SI HAH h s i certain follo'.dBg of SHIHUH tribes- niea io KHASAB, «d these Sheikh IBRAHIM a4uressed oa aoth July. They agreed to sead their headraai to DIBBAH to briB^ iB Sheikhs ABDULLA SULTAH aid ZAID SIUAM asKiig for a period of six days in which to accomplish, the task.Eaclosure to 11 Shore!iim's 11 l?o»56/7 of 3rd Aug.l9S2. Section II &gt; KHASAB. (Lit.26° 12' H. Lou£.56° IG'E) While l, Shorebim u was proceedlic froia MUSCAT to DIBBAH Miother set of eveits superimposed themselves 02 those telited In Sectios I. I received your sisaalj JMZ of 28th July iufonnin: me that HASSAN, lite Sheikh ofKHASAB, had brokea parole, escaped from DIBAI a.Bcl l iisded it KHASAB ^Gti! Jiuy, closely followed. Dy the SheiRh of DIBAI, *00 is respossiMe for his custody. 2. OB irrival at KHASAB the Sheikh of DIBill called toeethei the not ihles and not seeiur HASSAM amoig them sett for him. HASSAB -«ho had enscouced himself ic the old_fort .Thicn nes a little way 'back amosc the date palms c-une ',/ithout demur. Ti^e Sheikh of DEBAI explained that he v /ould have to take him hack, to DIBAI md this HASSAH agreed to only -.slda, leave first to say goodbye to his relations. Tjie^^iK^of dibai acceted to this requ est iiformiig HASSAB xnax xney would ledve il ^ dSCT oT'the 1 ^tenia^. and that he would send a messe ger -/neB it was time to start. HASSAB duly left is compaay -,/ith the messenger but when about half way to the landing place three men who had 'oeei, occupyinthe old fort with HASSAB intervenea and carried him back alleging that he was too ill to travel. 3. This was the position whein 'Shoreham' arrived at KHASAB late on the afternoon of Friday,29th July. 4. The w at.t came off on ray arrival .nd put me wise to the situation and most of the following day was spent m intemew- ia:• the oresent Shiekh of KHASAB, HiiSSAB 'S more important relations, aid the Sheikh of DIBAI ad two young Sneikhs from aearhy who './ere workir^ 'fith him for tne retura of HASSAH. 5. The great difficulty in the way of arranging HASSAB'S departure was the plea put forwar' that he was sick and quite unfit to travel, ncl on these grounds those m tne house .ath hln refused to let anyone .pproach Mm. That he had ceome so much /orse vfhen he heard that he had to return to DIBAI n aturally made me suspicious. 6. When I saw his more important rel ations I expl died to then the conditions on which HASSAB had been allowed to leave MUSCAT* That I had no wish to harm his persor or nun. a .a n travel'-./ho was genuinely unfit to do so, but that I must receive definite assurance on this pom^ i rom my neaic u officer on some other fully qualified person. 7. I impressed on the Sheikh of DIBAI his responsibility in regard to HASSAB, and on the present Sheiku of KhnSaB his responsj bilit for controlling his people remmuug him Me action which had been fakea against his predecessor two yeais ago when he defied the authority of MUSCAT State. 8. Finally I Informed all those mentioned in paras. 6 and 7 tove that HASSAB was to be delivered ob board _the Sneilch of DIBAI's dhow or 'Shoreham' by 10CC the followisg day,^anu that in order that there should be 10 mistake about the tLie I*would fire a gus at 0950. 0. That evening the young Sheikh of BAKHAH (Lat.26 0 ^'B. • £&lt; who h is been very active in the su port of tne snexKn u6 ! ' of.b'H Enclosure to 'Slioreh^jn 1 s ! Ho.ow 7 of Srd A ul* Section II &gt; KHASAB&gt; Co!]ta &gt; of DIBAI came 02 'board asd informed me that HASSA11 1 s relations - ,-oiil' bo^ consent to 1 doctor seeinc hiu uu ler any ciron - st^ces/lt was OBly then toe that I leaded.that HASSAN. Had a considerable £ollowiig. Of .the 2000 iDlvibitants rfho -Live in KHASAB ud its iiamediate vicinity ,boat ir f of taem a^p -- eatly sympathised iriLta HASSAB. These were SBIHDH people who lived around rather thai in KHASAB. This lends support tothe theory that the iutertlOD vras to mke HASSAK Sheikh of DIBBAH. 10. That si it.SOth July, I burned a se .rchlij t on the vill e it icterviis giving; pirticul ir attentioa to HASSAK s house .nd fired soae rocks to revivify the h ippeEiiii,E of years ago I d the minds of the inhabitants. From reports received this ippeioS to hive had some effect. The next moraiiig the WALI informed me th it HASSAH 'Jfith three s] .ves 1 ! d Quitted his house at 2330 the previous evening lom be thought for BAKHAH; and a little later the Sheikh of PT ba t ca e on board (about 0920) and idformed me that he had engineered his departure, the Sheikh of BAKHAH hivin. seen him carried do»n to the shore and placed on ooard a dho^f bound for BAKHAH. l I -accordingly immediately proceeded to BAKHAH 'v /ith the Sheikh of DIBAI M Sheikh of BAKHAH on board and there in coiapay './ith ay medical officer sav HASSAH in the Sheikh of BAKHAH^s fort. My medical officer states that the man 1S rsdoubtedly very ill and should not be moved for the prese. t, thou h from his cursory examination he is ^ st-.te . precisely the nature of the disease from which he is suffenn &amp; . 13. For this reason I informed the Sheikl uf DIBAI that I would not insist on him being imaediately removed to DIBAI ■but that he must understand that he '.rould be held entirelj responsible for his safe custody and must gmrd him adeq ately. 14. i then sent the Sheikh of KHASAB back to inform t'e WALI iccordiDgly, &gt;nd that having seen HASSAB n the custody of the Sheikh of Dim I was no.r satisfied. 15. In conclusion I wo did like to c ac' .edge the h£^£ : aa-i advice which was given me by Sheikh TBBAHOl of Muscat ana ihS recovery^ fJASSAH. ^ t0 . lscertaiB dttS t how HASSAK was induced to leave, but apparently^it was tne ^eikh of KHASAB who succeeded in effecting .n entry into nis house.B it-* jfuxAr ^ r&gt; Tjiurw y*Cfi~ I 1 4 Enclosure to 'Shorehani t s Ho.56/? of srd Aug.1932.^ Section in . S' DIBBAH&gt; Sheikh RASCHID is forms me that though in his father^ and elder brother's time the Sheikhdom of southern DIBBAH •/ .3 linked to th it of SHARJAH, that is not iov ; the case. I KHALED bin AHMED I DIBBAH AHMED 1 ' 1 ABDULLA Mb AMED cousia of —L RASCHID (present Sheikh)' SHARJAH SAfMR 1 SULTAN (presest Sheikh) KO'./ :it UMM AL QUAIWAIH. ti at 02 SAGAR of SHARJAH dyinz (see 'Shoreh m^s' Ho.oO/l^ of ■ SOt' June issa). the f iraily moved to SHARJAH, his elder ALED oecomiii^ SheiRh - a represent itive ] brother KHALED to admiiister DIBBAH. beis' left 2. Wliea KHALED '/ is forced to leave SHARJAH (some 8 ye rs ■go?) he iEd ABDULLA migrated to UMM ALE QUAIWAIH vrtiile RASCHID returaed to DIBBAH. 5. RASCHID feels that he has iissufficieBt mthority to control this Sheikhdom and ./ithst aid the raids of Beighlwurisg trlDes, aad is no-/ askiBg if he can to placed under the suzeranty of MUSCAT or in a position analogous to that of the TRUCIAL Sheikhs. 4. I informed him that this was a m itter quite heyond my competence to deal dth, 'out that I fould inform you of his desires with a vie® to you informinj the political Resident if you saw fit.' ■ I '' ■ w&lt; '' iS'llLM Telegran From To Ho. 1115 i^ated 22nd received 23rd August 1932. G.T.C. 3enior ^aval Officer, ^Triad* Political Hesident, BusMre. .v'. j-ht Following from •Bideford 11 'begins Shaikli Itealiim 'bin Mahomed iDin Juma reports situation tiere quifet* Hassan has recovered and is still at Bakhah. Shaikh Zaid Sinan refuses to come here hut other two claimants \AC«JU&gt;C.d~ are here. Instructions have 'been from Muscat /V that matter is to he left in abeyance. Sultan can come here himself to settle it. I am giving Shaikh Ihrahim a passage to Muscat as he wishes to return there.* ends. ■ Senior Naval Officer. —o--~ J Post copy forwarded to the Political Agent, Muscat, for information. By Order, Confidential Assistant. Bushire. 24th August 1932. '' V't;1 Translation of letter j^o 124 dated 20th Ka^i al Thani . 1351 (24,6,32j from the Council representing H.H. tiie Sultan of Muscat and Oman. To Our esteemed friend Captain R.G.Alban, H,B,M f s Consul, Muscat. A. G. Ibrahim bin Munaiimad returned from jihasab ^ a warship yesteruay and informed us firstly about the Shaikhdom of Difca, that Zaid bin ainan bin lasir is still in the for is of uiba and that while he was departing from idiasab there assembled sfcme of Ku- ma^arsh shaikhs with the -ali asked f or'a' respite f6r six dsy«. to bring Zaid bin slnan to the ali of Khasab to showx obedience so that a ahaikn for uiba may be selected. he also informed us that it is true that Shaiich Hasan is at isonha. tie went to ahamza and Jaai ana agreed witn them to the effect that they should aadress for his return to iihasab. He has now returned to BoKha. Shaikh baid oi/i naKtum returned to uebai in the end of Kaoi ulAwai U st August) According to t.liat we see the stay of shaikh nafaan i u tnose parts with the Snihuh is not advisable. His stsj there might cause recrudescence of disorders and it would be more appropriate if he «e E e repatria- ted from those parts. This is sta ted for 'your Information. Sa. zubair bin Ali. r . ' Shihabjuetter j*o,204 dated tJrie 14th September iy32 from the Council of negency, i«i.uscat otate, to Captain R»G # Altan, roiiticai Agent cx&gt; consul, muscat. After oompliments* \7ith regard to bheiich nasan bin miihainniad ai bhehhl who escaped from uebal, we deem it necessary to state tnat, as you Know, he was sent away from Muscat at the suggestion of our friend tne British wOTernment 10 be handed over to Bheish caxd^ Din oniei of Debai, who guaranteea to the Government that he would not return tu Khasab. Sheilch Hasan is now at coKha wmch is near xOiasao ana one of its dependencies. He must not stay at Bokha and His iiighness nas instructed us to iniorm you that Hasan should not^iept near ishasaD. we Have already addressed you a letter *.0.124 explaining tne seriousness of the matter, bheiich Hasan should better be removed from soJcto. ihis is what had to be said and salaams*From To U0.8O8 -S of 1932. British Residency ^ Consulate-General, Bushire, the 26th October 1932. The ^on'ble Lt.-Colonel T. C. Fowle, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, The Foreign Secretary to the CioYernment of India, Hew Delhi* Sir 9 With reference to correspondence ending with this office telegram Ho.T.91 of 13th May 1930, I have the honour to report for yorrr information that Shaikh Hasean of Khassab having surrendered and been taken back to Muscat, had the mild sentence of about 22 months* imprisonment inflicted on him by the Muscat State* At the conclusion of his imprisonment His Highness the Sultan of Muscat intended that he should remain as a political detenu in Muscat* The Shaikh of Debai, however, interceded on his behalf and informed the late Sir Hugh Biscoe that he (the Shaikh) would give an undertaking that Hassan would stay at Debai under the surveillance of the Shaikh if he was allowed to go there* Sir Hugh Biscoe passed this request on to the Sultan, who agreed, and Hassan - having promised to abide by the terms of the undertaking » was permitted to leave Muscat for Debai* He stayed there until some months ago when on the 30th July telegrams were received to the effect that Hassan had left Debai secretly for Khassab* His presence there, apart from the undertaking which the Shaikh of Debai had given, in view of past events was of course most undesirab{cThe Qomaander of H.M.s.^Shoreham 4 * working in concert with the Shaikh of i &gt;ebai 9 who had followed Hassan» and some other local Shaikhs 9 succeeded in getting Hassan removed from Khassab to Bokha, a small port between Khassab and ^iebai. This prompt action on the part of the Commander of U,M.S»'Shoreham* 1 probably averted serious complicatlons 9 and I conveyed him my thanks through the Senior Kaval Officer. 2. The next step was to get Hassan back to Debai. As, however, the question of establishing the Imperial Airways* Rest House, etc., at Shar^ah was then urgent, I did not wish to have any more irons in the fire on the Trucial Coast at that particular time. But during my visit to the Trucial Coast at the end of August, I approached the Shaikh of ebai on the subject, ana found him inclined to treat his responsibility in the matter somenhat lightly. I enquired who was paying for the upkeep of Hassan and his family at Bokha. The Shaikh replied that Hassan was paying for this himself out of the proceeds of his gardens at Khaaaab which had not been sequestrated by the uscat State. I accordingly informed the Shaikh that if he failed to get back Hassan to Bebai in reasonable time, say, at the end of October, I would have to consider the necessity of suggesting to the Sultan that Hassan, having broken his word, should be deprived of his property, when the Qhaikhs of Khassab and Bokha would have to support Hassan and his family. The Shaikh then began to view the question more seriously, and a few days ago in reply to a message wiuch I sent to the residency Agent, Shargah, as to what action the Shaikh of Debai was taking in the matter of Hassan 1 received a reply that he had sent his brother to get him back, and on the 24th instant I received a telegram from the Residency Agent to the effect that the Shaikh of Debai had brought Hassan back to Jebai. This is satisfactory4.. so fari and I am considering the desirability of the next step of getting Hassan back to Muscat* I am sending a copy of this letter to the Senior % Haral Officer| Persian Gulf Birision. I hare the honour to be 9 Sir, Your most obedient servant, ^ ^ ^ M.-Cclonel, Political Resident in the Persian (iulf. Copy forwarded to the Political Agent, Muscat, for informati on. By Order. &lt;1. X &gt;■ f l.h *1'- J 'f.4 f I 11 ■«o.C/ 7^3 of 1932. The Political ^ency Sc H.B.M 1 s Consulate, Muscat, ^^^November 1932. mcy''. ^uh 7 To The Hon'ble the Political Hesident in the Persian Grulf, Sushire. V / Memorandum. Reference your letter K0.8O8 -S dated the 26th Octoher iy32, to the Government of India. H.H. the Sultan informs me that, as was decided at IChasab, Sheikh Hassan, late Sheikh of Khasab, has been sent to Muscat; he arrived here on the 17th instant. Juaj or, Politxcal Agent &amp; H.B.M f s Consul,v om - To Ho,892-3 of 1932. British Residency &amp; Consulate-General, Bushire, the 2nd Decemtoer 1932. (I» The Hon'ble Lt.Colonel T.G.Fowle,C.B.^., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf t The Foreign Secretary to the GoTernment of India, Bew Delhi* Subject s Shaikh Hassan of Khassab* r p sir, In continuation of my letter Iio.808-S of 26th October 1932, I have the honour to report that on a recent tour to Muscat I met at Khassab His Highness the Sultan df Muscat and the Shaikh of Bebai. The latter had got dis tinctly tired of his troublesome guest, and asked for per mission from His Highness to surrender the bail he had undertaken on his - Hassan's behalf, and to send Hassan back to Muscat. As this was exactly what His Highness and I wanted the former graciously accorded his sanction, and I have now had a communication from the Political Agent,kuscat, that Hassan has arrived there. The Hassan incident may therefore be said to be satisfactorily closed. I am sending a copy of this letter to the Senior Naval Officer,Persian Gulf division. V % 'A-. *sent under P.L. N0.893-S of 2/12/32, I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Lt.Colonel, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. P.T.Q.^1 ,M ' / iotc^sve,' dated ist jraaTiiiST ' /^- r EXTRACT FROM ^.BAHRAIN'S COKFIDEHTlAl DESPATCH i ay 6. The Shaikh also brought up the subject of Shaikh Hasan bin Muhammad of Khasaab, I enclose herewith a letter with regard to this matter. I told the Shaikh that I would forward the letter but would express no opinion on it. The Shaikh's real object ife that he is finding Shaikh Hasan^s family very expensive guests and would like to find some way of getting rid of them. XXX Copy of translation of letter dated 24th Rab'a al Auwal 1354 i.e. 25th June 1935) from Shaikh Said -^in Maktum, O.B.E., Ruler of Dibai to Captain G.A.Gole, Political Agent, Bahrain. After Compliments, I am writing to remind you about the case of Shaikh Hasan bin Muhammad. I request you to make such arrangements as would be useful for his release aid return to his home - Khassab, from which place he has been away for a long time. he is a family man and has children and other dependents, who have been coming to me frequently about this matter, the fact which makes me feel ^ity on them. Should he be released and allowed to return to his respective home - Khassab, I hold myself responsible for any ?ct which may be done bu him and is improper. I hope that you will do what you canabout the case of the aforesaid person, for whih act I ^hall remain grateful. Usual Ending.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0001ac_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/455</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0001ac</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/455</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Confidential File 35/141 Khasab'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1931/1935</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-09-19T00:05:49</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (32 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged chronologically from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: There are two foliation sequences. The sequence which should be used for referencing is circled in pencil in the top right corner of the recto of each folio. It begins on the first folio after the front cover, on number 1 and ends on the last folio of writing, on number 30.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Correspondence discussing the situation in Khasab and relations between Shaikh Hassan and the Sultan of Muscat. Includes some letters in Arabic and a family tree (folio 21) of the ruling shaikhs of Dibba and Sharjah. Also includes a letter from Saiyid Said bin Taimur [Sa‘īd bin Taymūr], President of the Council of Ministers, Muscat State, to Captain Reginald Charles Alban, Political Agent Muscat, describing his visit to Khassab where he found that a temporary shaikh had been appointed.Correspondents include Senior Naval Officer Persian Gulf; Saiyid Said bin Taimur; Captain Reginald George Alban, Political Agent, Muscat; Khan Bahadur Isa bin Abdul Latif, Residency Agent, Sharjah; Shaikh Said bin Maktum, Ruler of Dubai; Council representing His Highness the Sultan of Muscat and Oman; Trenchard Craven Fowle, Political Resident Persian Gulf.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><geographic>Khaṣab</geographic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0001ac#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>