<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000184_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T05:30:47.140Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">i&amp;mms -c' :« r s GEORGE THE SIXTH, BY THE GRACE OF GOD, OF GREAT BRITAIN, IRELAND AND THE BRITISH DOMINIONS BEYOND THE SEAS KING, DEFENDER OF THE FAITH, EMPEROR OF INDIA, &amp;C. , &amp;C., &amp;C. TO ALL AND SINGULAR TO WHOM THESE PRESENTS SHALL COO, GREETING I WHEREAS, for the 'better treating of and arranging certain matters which are now in discussion, or v/hich may come into discussion, between Us and Our Good Friend the Sultan Saiyid Said bin Taimur bin Faisal, Sultan of Muscat and Onian and Dependencies, relative to the conclusion of a new Treaty to replace the Treaty of Friendship, Commerce and Navigation, signed at Muscat on the 10th March, 1891, ^e have judged it expedient to invest a fit person with Full Power to conduct the said discussion on Our part in respect of Our United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland and in respect of India; Know ye, therefore, that We, reposing especial Trust and Confidence in the'Wisdom, Loyalty, Diligence, and Circumspection of Our Trusty and Well-beloved Sir Trenchard Craven William Fowle, a Lieutenant- Colonel in Our Land Forces, Knight Commander of Our Most Eminent Order of the Indian Empire, Commander of Our Most Excellent Order of the British Empire, Our Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, have named, made, constituted and appointed, as We do by these Presents name, make, constitute and appoint him Our undoubted Commissioner, Procurator, and Plenipotentiary in respect of Our United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland and in respect of India, for the purpose aforesaid: Giving to him all manner of Power and Authority toL h to treat, adjust, and conclude with such Minister or Ministers as may be vested with similar Power and Authority on the part of Our said Good Friend the Sultan of Muscat and Oman and Dependencies, any Treaty, Convention, or Agreement that may tend to the attainment of the above-mentioned end, and to sign for Us, and in Our name, in respect of Our United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland and in respect of India, everything so agreed upon and concluded, and to do and transact all such other matters as may appertain thereto, in as ample manner and form, and with equal force and efficacy, as We Ourselves could do, if personally present; Engaging and Promising, upon Our Royal Mord, that whatever things shall be so transacted and concluded by Our said Commissioner, Procurator, and Plenipotentiary in respect of Our United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland and in respect of India, shall, subject if necessary to Our Ratification, be agreed to, acknowledged and accepted by Us in the fullest manner, and that We will never suffer, either in the whole or in part, any person whatsoever to infringe the same, or act contrary thereto, as far as it lies in Our power. In fitness whereof We have caused Our Great ^Seal to be affixed to these Presents, which We have signed with Our Royal Hand. Given at Our Court of Saint James's, the Fifteenth day of November, in the Year of Our Lord, One Thousand Nine Hundred and Thirty-eight and in the Second Year of Our Reign.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000184_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/415</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000184</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/415</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 35/86 VIII Muscat Treaty'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1938/1938</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-09-18T15:12:17</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (5 folios)</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file consists of an envelope with a sealed document giving full powers to Lt Col Sir Trenchard Craven W Fowle to negotiate a new commercial treaty with Sultan Saiyid Said bin Taimur [Sa‘īd bin Taymūr], Sultan of Muscat and Oman. The document is signed by King George VI and has his royal seal.The envelope is inscribed: 'Full powers to Lieutenant Colonel Sir Trenchard C.W. Fowle, KCIE, CBE, to negotiate with the Sultan of Muscat and Oman and dependencies, in respect of the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland and also in respect of India.The document bears the Royal Seal and is signed 'George R.I.' The document starts: George the Sixth, by the Grace of God, of Great Britain, Ireland and the British Dominions beyond the Seas, King, Defender of the Faith, Emperor of India, &amp;C., &amp;C., &amp;C., To all and singular to whom these presents shall come, greeting.'</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="personal"><namePart>King of Great Britain and Ireland George VI</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">witness</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Treaties</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000184#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>