<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x00025d_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T09:38:24.293Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">INDIA OFFICE t WHITEHALL, 3.W. 1, P.Z. 307/35. 22nci January 1935. Dear Lefroy, I write with further reference to my letter i,r- ^, 1^5 of 17th January, p. Z.307/35, to say that we see no objection to the Company's accepting as the southern limit of their concession the line marked on the map of Qatar which-you sent us. Yours sincerely, J.G. LAITHWAITS. Lefroy, Esq., Anglo-Persian Oil Co. Ltd., Britannic House, Finsbury circus, E.C. 2.By Air Mail. p.z. J 19 H Z-y/tO INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, Z 5 JAN B55 m* i 3 Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy has been sent to by Mail. ^^^--Poxai^L-SprretRr-yj- Qovornmont of Indiciu The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. 3057INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL, 3.W. 1. p f Z.355/35. 17th January 1935. My dear George, Would you please refer to paragraph 7 of the record of a discussion with the A.P.O.G. on 10th January, copies of which were sent to you and to the Admiralty and petroleum Department under our printed letter p.z,271/35 of 14th January, which deals with the Company's request that we should let them know , . „ whether-feiBSS. regard the sou the rn_JJJBit^or their concession shown on the map^of Qatar of which they have let us have copies as satisfactory north (particularly in the Jebel Dukhan area) of the line which has previously deen recognised tiy H.M.G. as the southern tiounaary of Qatar and to which we are proposing to work as against Ibn saud. That line is, of course, more or less identical with the Qitar protection limit which was agreed last torch. I do not see any difficulty in these circumstances in its The line in question run li &amp; htly to the adoption/ Hendel, Esq., G.M.G., Foreign 01 fice.- 2 - adoption ty the Company as the soutnern limit of their concession, for, as we made clear to them in the discussion on lOth January, the limit of their concession need not necessarily be as extensive as that of the sheikh's territories recognised ty H.M.G. or of any protection which they might give to him. 3. It is arguable, on the other hand, that now that we have reason to believe that the Jebel Dukhan structure is likely to be petroliferous there might be advantage in the Company endeavouring straight away to secure a line running from the head of the Dohat as Salwa to just north of the Khor al Odeid and giving them at any rate tne northern part of the hills marked as Qern Abu Wail on their map. 4. On the whole, however, I think we should do best to reply to them in the terms of the draft enclosed? Satisfactory as it would be if we could include in their concession the small additional area referred to in paragraph 2, I am inclined to doubt, given the political complexities with which we are at present faced, if it is worth raising this issue, if we can reach a satisfactory agreement with Ibn saud as regards/regards boundaries on the basis of a line running from the head of the Dohat as Salwa to the boundary of Abu Dhabi, some small rectification of the area granted to the Company could no aoubt be considered. And in any event the additional area now under consideration would, if we secure the boundary at which we aim, fall outside the area of the Hasa oil concession. 5. I am sending a similar letter to seal at the Admiralty and the letter of which a copy is enclosed to Pirie at the Air Ministry, as the boundary question is, of coiffse, of Interest to both Departments. I am also sending copies of the correspondence to starling. Yours ever, GILBERT LAITHWAITE.Confidential. Office of the Political Resident I,.0.»o.C/17 of 1936. 1« • Dated the 23rd February, 1936. c jc^ I have been talking over the question of Qatar with Loch. At the moment Mylles of the A.P.O.C. is there negotiating for the oil concession with the Shaikh. He has been negotiating now for about a week and, though very wisely he is not hurrying matters, there should be some result I think one way or the other in the near future: i.e. either (^) he will have got the concession, or (B) the Shaikh will have refused to give it to him. 2. In the case of (A)^ The Shaikh will have to be presented with the Political Agreement between His Majesty f s Government and the Company« He may raise some objections to some of its clauses, but having accepted the Commercial Agreement, and being naturally anxious to benefit by its financial terms, his objections should be surmountable. 3. In the case of (B). Loch or I will have to approach the Shaikh, but before we do so it seems to me that I shall have to be authorised on behalf of His Majesty^ Government to inform him (the Shaikh) in writing to the following effect: (1) That though we do not intend of course to force him to give the concession to the a.p .O.C. -I. •C., under the terms of Clause V of his Treaty of 1916 he is again reminded that he is not permitted to give any concession without His Majesty 1 s Governments permission. (2) You will remember that when I saw the Shaikh last April / The Hon 1 ble Mr. H. A. F.Mete all; e, C.S*I.,C.I.£.,M.V.O., Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, New Delhi.April he said - vide enclosures to cay Express Letter No. C/179 of 6th April 1934 - that if the negotiations with the а . P . O . C . finally broke down, he would keep within his Treaty obligations by allowing any other Company that approached him to make a survey, etc. of his territory, and then - before actually giving the concession to them (provided they offered good enough terms) - would ask for His Majesty's Government's permission. It is obviously impossible to allow this sort of situation to materialise. To prevent it I should be further authorised to remind the Shaikh of what he said, and to point out that it would be merely a waste of time and money on the part of any Company to approach him, ard to make a survey, etc. unless they had first ascertained from His Majesty's Governrfient that permission would be given. 4. In addition to this warning to the Shaikh it might also be necessary to issue a similar warning to the California Arabian Standard Oil Company. б. However, we will hope for the best that Mylies will be successful in his negotiations. I am sending a copy of this letter to Laithwaite, and giving a copy to Loch. &gt;CONFIDENTIAL. No. C/18 of 1935. wrl The Hon'ble the Political ResiamtJ/t tjie Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to f 1. J.G.Laithwaite Esquire,C.I.E., The India Office, London• 2. Lieut.-Colonel Gordon Lochj Political,Agent, Bahrain. and has the honour to transmit to him a copj of the undermentioned docu ment ($). Office of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Camp, Bahrain. r v $• ■ 3 mi*® ' f *$ : imm$k Dated,. 23rd. .February. 1935 Reference to previous correspondence: Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Demi-official letter No. C/17 of 23rd February 1936 to the Foreign Secretary to the Government of India. • a s 1 c—8 2/27 and 29/8 Telegrara ^rorn G.T-C. H . M ! s Vice~Consul. Moha^merah, ri o Political Resident, p -ushire Uo 1400 Dated 23rd received 24th February 1935. CIegg of Anglo-FerBian ^il Company proppses to arrive Bushire evening of March 2nd in Company's aeroplane to discuss latest position of Qatar oil. He T /ill return with British Minister on March 3rd. .Please telegraph if convenient. Telegram From Political He si dent, Bushire, H,M f s Vice-Consul, Mohammerah. (KT.C. Ho 221. Dated the 26th February 1935. Your telegram 1400 of February 23rd. Very pleased to put up Gleggo BHITGONSULv? all communications to be addressed to the COMPANY ^)j^| J oJJ isf ji. GLO-PERSIAN OIL COMPANY, LIMITED. J S 0-&gt;. A LONDON and ABADAN. ^ ^ J d b - &gt;Aj — Aj^l? Q\ T elegraphic A ddress! 'ANGLOPERS.' .V CONFIDENTIAL. NO,- ABADAN, PERSIAN GULF. DATED- 6.tjb. February:,. 1.9.35. The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, The Residency, B U S H I R i*i. w/ Sir. 1 QATAR CONCE SSION NEG OTIATIONS. We have the honour to forward herewith, for your information and record, cooy of the latest Draft Concession dated 10th January 1935 which has been drawn up by our Principals, and has, we under stand, the unqualified approval of H^B.M's Government, We also attach hereto a sketch map of the Qatar Peninsula. Mr, C# G. Mylies left Basra for Bahrein by last week 1 s Slow Mail and will by now have arrived at Dohah to resume negotiations with H JS, the Sheikh of Qatar, Copies of this letter and its enclosures are also being forwarded to the Political Agent at Bahrein for his information and record. We have the honour to be, S i r. Your obedient servants, For ANGLO-PERSIAN OIL COMPANY, LTD End. 2, GENERAL MANAGERlOth January&gt; Q A T R . This is an AGREEMENT made on the day of 195 corresponding to day of 155 'between HIS EXCELLENCY SHAIKH ABDULLAH AL QASIM ATH THAN I, Ruler of QATR (hereinafter referred to as 'The Shaikh' which expression shall where the context so admits be deemed to include his successors and assigns) of the one part AND Charles Clark Mylles acting on behalf of ANGLO-PERSIAN OIL COMPANY, LIMITED (hereinafter referred to as 'The Company' which expression shall where the context so admits be deemed to include its assigns) of the other part. It is hereby agreed between the Shaikh and the Company in manner following Article 1 . The Shaikh hereby grants to the Company on the terras hereinafter mentioned the exclusive right throughout the State of Qatr to explore prospect drill for extract carry away export and the right to refine and sell petroleum naphtha natural gases ozokerite asphalt and the derivatives thereof hereinafter referred to as THE SUBSTANCES. If the Company discovers any minerals other than THE SUBSTANCES, such as gold, iron ore, coal etc., it shall have no right to take possession of the same, but must report the fact to the Shaikh, and the Shaikh shall have full right and absolute control over such minerals. Article 2. Subject to the provisions of Article 7 below, the Company may operate in any part of the State of Qatr as defined below but shall not operate on such religious lands, cemeteries or lands occupied by religious buildings as exist at the dateof signature of this Agreement or such normal extensions of such religious lands^ cemeteries or buildings as the Shaikh may indicate. For the purpose of this Agreement the State of Qatr means all territory ruled by the Shaikh shown to the north of the line on the map attached hereto. The period of this Agreement shall be seventy-five years from the date of its signature. Articl e '5. The Company shall make a thorough investigation of the State of Qatr by such methods as may in its opinion best enable it to ascertain its oil possibilities* In carrying out its operations under this Agreement^ the Company shall employ all means customary and proper and shall exploit its Concession by appropriate scientific methods. The Company undertakes to keep accurate plans, maps, records of wells drilled and such other data whether topographical, geological or of drilling as it is customary to keep and such material shall be open to inspection by the Shaikh or his duly authorised representative. The Company shall supply an annual report to the Shaikh of its operations under this Agreement. Article^. In consideration of the rights granted by the Shaikh to the Company hereunder, the Company shall make to the Shaikh the following payments during the currency of this Agreement :- (a) On the date of signature (b) On each of the first four anniversaries of the date of signature (c) On the fifth and each subsequent anniversary of the date of signature*... but after the commencement of exports of THE SUBSTANCES from Qatr the Company shall pay, instead of the annual sums mentioned in (b) and (c) above, royalties as specified below on THE SUBSTANCES exported from or sold for consumption in Qatr during the year ended 5 months prior to each anniversary of the date of signature with the proviso that such royalty payments will not in any year total less than. * u * . -5- (1) On all THE SUBSTANCES other than asphalt ozokerite and natural gas royalty per ton (22^0 English pounds) at the rate of.«„.. (2) On asphalt and ozokerite royalty per ton (22^0 English pounds) at the rate of (5) On natural gas royalty per 1,000 cubic feet at the rate of If the Shaikh shall require payment of royalties at any time other than an anniversary of the date of signature the Company shall on notice being given by the Shaikh pay such royalties as may have accrued up to a date 5 months prior to the receipt of such notice from the Shaikh and a reasonable time shall be allowed to the Company to effect the payment. Article_5. The Company shall measure all fluid substances exported from or sold for consumption in the State of Qatr by dipping of tanks or through orifice meters, and all solid substances by weight, and shall keep accurate records thereof to which the duly authorised representative of the Shaikh shall have access at all reasonable times. The Company shall submit to the Shaikh annually an accurate record of all THE SUBSTANCES exported from or sold for consumption in Qatr during each year. Article _6o The Company shall have the right subject to the provisions of Article 7 to construct maintain and operate such roads telegraph and telephone installations and lines wireless stations railways refineries harbours pipelines pumping stations workshops houses and other works as it may require solely for the purposes of its operations including the accommodation of its employees. The Company may likewise utilise without hindrance all such means of transportation by land air and water communication or operation as may be necessary for the 'effective conduct of its operations hereunder. The Shaikh shall have the right in case of need to use free of charge the Company 1 s roads telegraph telephone andwireless installations and railways on special personal services with due regard to the Companyts operations and in times of national emergency the Shaikh shall have full use free of charge of the Company's wireless and telegraph installations and railways for Governmental purposes. The Shaikh 1 s ships shall have the right to use harbours utilised or constructed by the Company, provided that such use in no way hampers the Company or interferes with the safety of its operations, of which the Company shall be the sole Judge. Article 7 » The Shaikh shall grant to the Company free of cost the unrestricted use and occupation of uncultivated land belonging to the Shaikh which the Company may need for its operations. Any other lands houses or buildings required by the Company may be bought or leased by it with the consent of and on conditions to be arranged with the proprietors thereof, but the terms of such purchase or lease shall not be in excess of those ordinarily current in their respective localities. The Company shall acquire only such land houses and buildings as are necessary for its operations under this Agreement, and such land shall at all times be less than the whole area of Qatr. The Company shall inform the Shaikh from time to time of the land houses and buildings which it requires to occupy for its operations, and land houses and buildings previously acquired by the Company from the Shaikh but found no longer necessary for its operations shall be returned by the Company to the Shaikh at a cost which shall not in any case be greater than that paid by the Company. Provided that all land houses and buildings owned by the Company shall be handed over to the Shaikh on the expiry or sooner determination of this Agreement. Article 8. The Company may take any water required for its operations free of cost provided that such water can be takenwithout damage or loss to any local inhabitants. Subject to the same conditions the Company may also sink wells and drill for and impound water to provide for the needs of its operations. In case of need^ the Shaikhs army or military expeditions may take free of charge such quantities of water as may be at the Company's disposal after satisfying its own requirements. Similarly, the people may take any such surplus water for themselves and their animals free of charge. Article^. The Company may take any soil clay gravel lime gypsum stone and any similar materials required for its operations free of cost, but it shall not prevent the people from taking their usual requirements of these materials. Article_10. In consideration of the payments agreed in Article k, the Company shall have the right to import water, petroleum, fuel, machinery, motor cars and lorries, aircraft, equipment, plant, timber, utensils, ironwork, building materials, medicines, office equipment and household furniture, and all other materials equipment and goods required by the Company or its employees for the purpose of its operations, but not for resale to others, and the right to export its petroleum and petroleum products and articles previously imported by the Company, free of customs or import or export duty or taxes or other charges. But the Company shall pay on all personal goods clothing and general merchandise and food supplies imported by it for the personal use of its employees the ordinary duty on goods of British merchants in force in the State of Qatr. The Company, its operations, income, profits and property shall be exempt and free during the period of this Agreement from all present or future taxes or charges of any kind.Artlcle__ll. The Shaikh agrees to give all necessary assistance to facilitate the carrying out of this Agreement&lt;, and also to exert his authority to protect as far as possible the Company*s personnel and property. The Company may appoint in consultation with the Shaikh and itself pay trustworthy guards to assist in protecting the property of the Company and its employees Article_.12. The Company shall have the right to transfer this Agreement to any other commercial Company but not to any Government subject to such Company being able to fulfil all the duties and obligations of this Agreement. The Company shall inform the Shaikh if it so transfers this Agreement. The Company shall be at liberty to form one or more subsidiary companies under its own control should it consider this to be necessary for the working of this Agreement. Any such subsidiary company shall so far as they are applicable to its operations enjoy all the rights and privileges granted to the Company hereunder and shall assume all the engagements and responsibilities herein expressed. Artic1e_12• The Company shall have the right to terminate this Agreement upon giving the Shaikh six months T notice in writing of its intention so to do. If such termination occurs within 55 years from the date of signature of this Agreement^ all lands granted by the Shaikh and any lands or buildings which the Company may have bought and any houses or buildings constructed by and other immovable property of the Company within the State of Qatr shall be handed over to the Shaikh free of cost. Wells actually producing at the time of such termination shall be handed over in such reasonable good order and repair as they then are.If such termination occurs after 55 years from the date of signature of this Agreement^ all the property of the Company in the State of Qatr shall be handed over to the Shaikh free of cost. Wells actually producing at the time of such termination shall be handed over in such reasonable good order and repair as they then are. On the expiry of this Agreement at the end of the period of 75 years provided in Article 2, or of any extension or renewal of that period all the property of the Company in the State of Qatr shall be handed over to the Shaikh free of cost. Wells actually producing at the time of such expiry shall be handed over in such reasonable good order and repair as they then are. Ar t • The Shaikh shall have the right to terminate this Agreements- (a) if the Company shall fail to make the payments referred to in Article 4 within six months of the date on which such payments fall due * Provided that if any such payments are in dispute by the Company the Shaikh shall not have the right to terminate the Agreement until the dispute shall have been arbitrated on under Article 16 and unless the Company has failed to comply with the decision of the arbitrators within three months of the date of such decision- (b) if the Company shall be in default under the arbitration provisions of Article 16. 4l£icle_15• No failure or omission on the part of the Company to fulfil any of the conditions of this Agreement shall give the Shaikh any claim against the Company or be deemed a breach of this Agreement insofar as the same arises from force majeure and if through such force majeure the fulfilment by the Company ofany of the conditions of this Agreement be delayed, the period of such delay together with such period as may be reasonably necessary for the restoration of any damage done during such delay shall be added to the periods fixed by this Agreement.. The necessary restoration of such damage will be carried out by the Company as expeditiously as possible. Article 16. If any dispute should arise between the Shaikh and the Company as to the interpretation of this Agreement or as to any matter arising out of it or with reference to the obligations of either party under it, such dispute shall, failing any agreement ' vw to settle it) v any other way, be referred to two arbitrators, one to be nominated by the Shaikh and one by the Company, Each party shall nominate its arbitrator within 50 days of receiving a request from the other party to do so. The two arbitrators shall thereafter choose a third arbitrator. But should they, or any other two arbitrators appointed instead of them by the two parties, fail to agree on the third arbitrator within 60 days of the request to arbitrate, then both parties agree to accept a third arbitrator nominated by the Political Resident. The award shall be made in accordance with the general principles of law recognised by civilised nations. The decision of a majority of the arbitrators shall be final. The place of arbitration shall be Qatr unless the majority of the arbitrators think otherwise. In giving a decision the arbitrators shall specify an adequate period of delay during which the party against whom the decision is given shall conform to the decision and that party shall be in default only if that party has failed to conform to the decision prior to the expiry of that period and not otherwise.Article_lZ« All labourers required by the Company in the State of Qatr shall be engaged from the Shaikh 1 s subjects or those whom he may recommend. But managers and skilled employees and clerks may be brought from outside^ and also labourers^ if suitable labourers in the State of Qatr are insufficient in number. The Company will not keep any employee of whom the Shaikh expresses disapproval^ but such disapproval shall not be expressed without showing due cause. Article^lS. The Shaikh and the Company declare that they base the performance of this Agreement on principles of mutual good will and good faith as well as on a reasonable interpretation of this Agreement. The Company undertakes to acknowledge and respect in every way the powers and rights of the Shaikh as Ruler of the State of Qatr. Article^lg. Nothing laid down in this Agreement shall prevent the Shaikh in any way from granting concessions to other parties for any article other than THE SUBSTANCES mentioned in Article 1^ provided that such concessions do not interfere with the rights or operations of the Company under this Agreement. Article ..20. The Company shall make all payments that become due to the Shaikh under this Agreement into the Shaikh 1 s account at the : - Bank in and the Bank's receipt shall be a full discharge for the Company in respect to the payment of the sum stated in the Bank ? s receipt. The Shaikh may from time to time designate in writing another Bank or Banks for the purpose of this Article,This Agreement which shall be binding on the parties hereto and their successors and assigns is written both in Arabic and English and all due care has been exercised to ensure that both texts are identical in meaning. If there should at any time be disagreement as to the meaning or interpretation of any clause in either text the Shaikh and the Company agree to settle the matter by mutual discussion^ failing which they will refer the matter to arbitration in accordance with Article 16„ A rti cle 22. The terms year month day as used in this Agreement refer to the solar calendar of England and to no other. In witness whereof the parties to this Agreement have set their hands the day and year first above written SHAIKH OF QATR In the presence of :- Representative of ANGLO-PERSIAN OIL COMPANY, LTD. In the presence of82/27 Telegram R. 27 From P©litical Resident, Busiiire. T q His Majesty^ Secretary ©f State for India, London* Bast copy to Government of India, Foreign and Political Department, lew Delhi, H: » «♦ Political A^ent, Bahrain* Ho. 224 Dated 27th February 1935* Reference penultimate paragraph of enclosure to your Printed Letter P*Z*6792 of November 2nd. (JATAR OIL refining clause. Grateful for confirmation that His Majesty^ Government have agreed that terms of this should follow clause 10 of Kuwait Government Agreement. - RESIDENT - Copy forwarded to Govt, of India and P.A., Bahrain, under P.L.^o. 21£US, dated 27th Februaiy 19 v &gt;5.Telegram R.27. From Secretary of State for India, London To Political Resident, Bushire* Copy by Air to Political Agent, Bahrain. No.640. Dated 28th February (received 1st-March) 19; Your telegram of 27th instant 110.224. Admiralty have agreed to accept refinery clause similar to that in Kuwait Agreement and understand that there will be no difficulty about pre-remption clauses on Kuwait model. l/t( ^'^7 -Secretary of State for India-(1) THIS AGREEMENT dated the fifth day i — — of March One thousand nine hundred and thirty four is made BETWEEN HIS MAJESTY'S GOVERNMENT IN THE UNITED KINGDOM (hereinafter called 'His Majesty's Go-verninent') of the one part and the KUWAIT OIL COMPANY LIMITED (hereinafter called 'the Company' which expression shall where the context so admits be deemed to include its successors and/or assignees) of the other part WHEREAS in the event of the Kuwait Oil Company obtaining a concession from the Sheikh of Koweit (hereinafter called 'the Sheikh') certain responsibilities will devolve on His Majesty's Government, the Company has agreed with His Majesty's Government as follows;- 1. THE Oil Company, any transferee Company and any subsidiary Company that may be created shall be and remain a British Company registered in the British Empire. 2. NOTWITHSTANDING anything contained in the Agreement between the Company and the Sheikh the obligations and benefits of that agreement shall not be transferred to any other company without the prior consent in writing of His Majesty's Government, and shall not be transferred to any company in which more than fifty per centum of the capital and voting power is directly or indirectly controlled by persons other than British subjects. 3. THE employees of the Company in Koweit shall at all times so far as is consistent with the efficient carrying on of the undertaking be British | subjects or subjects of the Sheikh. With the consent of His Majesty's Government, which consent shall not be unreasonably withheld, persons of other nationalities may be employed if in the opinion of the Company they are required for the efficient carrying on of the undertaking. NOTWITHSTANDING anything contained in the Agreement between the Company and the Sheikh, the importation of foreign native labour shall be subject to the approval of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. 4. ONE of the superior local employees of the Company shall be designated chief local representative of the Company in Koweit, The approval of His Majesty's Government shall be required for the person so designated. He will be ordinarily resident at Koweit and will be responsible for the Company's local relations with the Koweit authorities. These local relations shall always be conducted through the Political Agent at Koweit, except as regards routine commercial business, which may be transacted through the official representative (if any) whom the Sheikh may appoint under the agreement between the Company and the Sheikh, 5. SUBJECT to the terms of the concession the Company undertakes at'all times to pay due deference to the wishes of the Sheikh and to the advice of the Political Agent and the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. 6. THE right given to the Company by its agreement with the Sheikh to utilise means of transportation by air shall be subject to any general regulations for civil aircraft made by the Sheikh on the advice of His Majesty's Government, 7 • IN the application of the right given to the Sheikh by his Agreement * with the Company to make full use free of charge of the Company's wireless and telegraph installations and railways for governmental purposes in times of national emergency, the Sheikh acting on the advice of His Majesty's Government shall be the sole judge whether a 'national emergency' has arisen, 8. NOTWITHSTANDING anything contained in the agreement between the Company and the Sheikh the Company shall not have the right to use or occupy, and shall not include in the areas selected for the purposes of its operations, any sites which may have been selected by or on behalf of P.Z,1047/34 (27/2/34).the Sheikh or His Majesty's Government for defence purposes for aerodromes, aeroplane^ or seaplane bases or for wireless and tel installations or in connection with the development of harbours that with the consent of His Majesty's Government which shall not^be unreasonably withheld the Company shall have the right to use for purposes of its operations such harbours as may be developed by the s or His Majesty's Government if there is not reasonable harbour acco tion available elsewhere. Harbours developed by the Company shall under its complete and exclusive control, TELEGRAPH, wireless and telephone installations, if any, maintaii by the Company' shall be for use only in its business and as provided the concession, and shall be so constructed and operated that their operations shall not interfere with the operations of such wireless telegraph or telephone installations as may be established by the Shel or His Majesty's Government, THE Company declare that it is their intention, should they coasi that commercial conditions justify it, to erect a refinery at Koweit, and when the Company is satisfied that commercial production is assuri the Company agrees to examine with His Majesty's Government the questi of establishing a refinery in Koweit of suitable type and capacity. IN the event of a state of national emergency or war (of the exi ence of either of which His Majesty's Government shall be the sole juj His Majesty's Government shall have the right of pre-emption of all tl oil produced in Koweit in accordance with the terms of the schedule hei IN the event of notice of termination of the Agreement between tl Company and the Sheikh being given under the terms of that Agreement i the ground that the Company has failed to observe any of the terms of Agreement between the Company and His Majesty's Government, the arbiti tion provisions of the said Agreement between the Company and the Shei shall apply if the Company considers that notice of termination on sui grounds under that Agreement is not justified, IN WITNESS whereof Sir Louis James Kershaw, K.C.S.I,, C.I.E, i behalf of His Majesty's Government has hereunto set his hand and seal the Company has hereunto caused its Common Seal to be affixed the day year first above written, THE SCHEDULE above referred to Pre-emption Clause . In the event of a state of national emergency or war (of the existence of which His Majesty's Government shall be the sole judge) (1) His Majesty's Government shall have the right of pre-emptioni all crude oil gotten under the Concession granted by the Sheikh to tl Company and of all the products thereof and shall have the right to require the Company to the extent of any refining capacity it may hi Koweit to produce oil fuel that shall comply with the Admiralty specu tions at the time provided that Koweit Oil be of a suitable kind and quality for this purpose, (2) The Company shall use its utmost endeavours to increase so fa 1 reasonably possible with existing facilities the supply of oil and /or products thereof for the Government to the extent required by the Goveri (3) The Company shall with every reasonable expedition and so as avoid demurrage on the vessel or vessels engaged to convey the same, 1 its utmost to deliver all oil or products of oil purchased by the Government under their said right of pre-emption in the quantities at time and in the manner required by the Government at a convenient^pl 61 shipment or at a place of storage in Koweit to be determined by His Majesty's Government. In the event of a vessel employed to carry any oil or products thereof on behalf of His Majesty being detained on (2) ■PL., mrnu mmm,(3) ^tei as proii lei 7atl, lotion is i lentt^ ^ capatii 'ar (tf| ts tls I) 1 , iptiomfi :lie scfe;. lent tsiE if tliete lent, fti flyaDil ninatin:'. SJi, C m Wmli mm demurrage at the port of loading the Company shall pay the amount due for demurrage according to the terms of the charter party and/or the rates of loading previously agreed with the Company unless the delay is due to causes beyond the control of the Company, Any dispute which may arise as to whether the delay is due to causes beyond the control of the Company shall be settled by agreement between His Majesty's Government and the Company, and, in default of such agreement, the question shall be referred to two arbitrators, one to be chosen by His Majesty's Government (or the Political Resident) and the other by the Company, with power to appoint an umpire in case of disagreement, such arbitration to be held in England and to be deemed a reference to arbitration under the provisions of the Arbitra tion Act of 1889 (52 and 55 Vict.0.49) of the Imperial Parliament, or any statutory modification or re-enactment thereof for the time being in force, (4) The price to be paid for all oil or products of the refining or treatment of oil taken in pre-emption by His Majesty's Government shall be either (a) as specified in a separate agreement or (b) if no such agreement shall have been entered into, a fair price for the time being at the point of delivery as the same shall be settled by agreement between His Majesty's Government and the Company, or in default of such agreement by arbitration in the manner provided by the last preceding sub-clause. To assist in arriving at a fair price at the point of delivery the Company shall furnish for the confidential information of His Majesty's Government, if so required, particulars of the quantities, descriptions and prices of Koweit oil or products sold to other customers and of charters or contracts entered into for carriage and shall exhibit to His Majesty's Government original or authenticated copies of contracts or charter parties entered into for the sale and/or carriage of such oil or products. (5) His Majesty's Government shall be at liberty to take control of the works, plant and premises of the Company in Koweit, and in such event the Company shall conform to and obey all directions issued by or on behalf of His Majesty's Government. Compensation shall be paid to the Company for any loss or damage that may be proved to have been sustained by the Company by reason of the exercise by His Majesty's Government of the powers conferred by this sub-clause. Any such compensation shall be settled by agreement between His Majesty's Government and the Company or, in default of agreement, by arbitration in the manner provided by sub-clause 3, IED SEALED AND DELIVERED by ) said Sir Louis James Kershaw) )ehalf of His Majesty' L.J. Kershaw r(ofii sclr- )rnment in the presence of ) John Charles Walton India Office, Civil Servant. f pre-'' 3 SI# :lie ,tyiW, lir^; COMMON SEAL of the Kuwait ) tie Company Limited was hereunto) .xed in the presence of ) Mil A.C. Hearn Guy Stevens id bJ 1 H.T. Kemp carl'I i! DATED HIS MAJESTY 1 S GOVERNMENT IN T1 UNITED KINGDOM to - KUWAIT OIL COMPANY LIMITED AGREEMENT KouoeAlr relating to the IUuw . 11; Oil ConcelCONFIDENTIAL. No. 254-S Of 1935 2/7 The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to The Political Agent, Bahrain• and has the honour to transmit to him a copj of the undermentioned docn- meet (^). -STT British Consulate-General, BUS HIRE. ib— — Dated, 2nd March 1936 w\ 1 ^ ¥ &lt; % Reference to previous correspondence: / ^ ■ V- India Office telegram No.640 of 28th February 1935 Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. KUWnIT POLITH dated the Subject QAL AGREKi/lKNT 6th March 1934 vA tBUSHIRE, March Sna, 1955• a 4 I A B- Tlie result of C e C 0 %lles negotiations up to ?.6th February are summarised hereunder;- Reference - Draft concession dated 10th January. The Shaikh of Qatar's demands are I- ARTICLE 1 , To be redrafted in the same general sense ARTICLE 2 . The period depends entirely upon the financial terras. ARTICLE 3 . Reports to be submitted to the Shaikh on cemand. ARTICLE 4 « Royalty to be based on oil won ana saved as in nrevious draft® ARTICLE 5 , Copies of records to be submitted to the Shaikh on demand ARTICLE 6 P All imports to be through the oort of Dohah onlv, the port of export to be agreed. The Shaikh to have full right to use all facilities as anc. when necessary for personal or Government business. Aircraft subject to having special permission on every occasion. ARTICLE 7 . With regard to the acquisition of land there is to be no/ local Government, pressure exerted on the Company's behalf. Surplus land during period of agreement to revert to the Shalk free of charge. ARTICLE ft . The Company to drill two artesian wells free of charge. ARTICLE 9 . Actual requirements only - no right to export. (This refers to the Company's rights to use soil, clay, gravel, gypsum etc.). ARTICLE ,10 . !Pree imports - rigat to reexport to be cohered by special payment of additional royalty. ARTICLE 11 . Shaikh not responsible for loss or damage due to invasions insurrections etc. ARTICLE 1 ^.. Transfree Company subject to approval of Shaikh.3/ AKT ICLE12» y 1 (i5) Three 3/ears after comroenc ing operations only everything reverting free, ARTICLE 14 , Re-draft sense unalterea e ARTICLE lb . Force J&amp;ijuere in Qatar only. ARTICLE 16 . y&gt; Political Resident in the Gulf not agreed to (This was modified in a further telegram on the 28th February stating Political Resident accepted with the qualification Shaikh of Qatar will also approve of nomination). URTICLS l? a !To reason to be given for disapproval, ARTICLE 18 . Re-draft sense unaltered. ARTICIES 19 &amp; 20 o Agreed. ARTTCTJ. n. ra Agreement to be in Arabic only. ARTICLE 22 . Agreed. new article: . A local refinery to be built. (This demand was subsequently dropped by the Shaikh vide telegram of February 28th). Mylles rrtates he is continuing discussions but thinks the above are t/Le Shaikhs miinimum deraanc 9 s and will not be cropped or reduced by cash considerations. He will continue^to negotiate until about March 4th after which he proposes to vlsitAbadan for a discussion ano to await the reaction our London Principals. He also states Shaikh non refused to disc r n r . terms until all his neaanos in regard to general terms have been accepted. Sd. p.o. CIEfJf?yi^ extract Iroma note fiom Kr 0 C.C. Mvllea. gated 19 a 2.35 ? In the course of our conversation re: correspondence the Shaikh of Qatar said that Holmes had written suggesting he should come to «%atar secretly anc' make him an offer. The Shaikh said that he had not replied as he liked to do things openly. later I was informed that a letter had been written to Holmes (by Nasir al Mana) reporting that he had delivered Holmes 1 letter to the Shaikh, who refused to write a reply but told Nasir to tell Holmes. (a) He dia not agree to his coming to Qatar in disguise to make an offer for the Concession (b) He did not agree if he came to terms with us to with hold his signature for two months to enable Holmes to make an offer (c) He did agree to Holmep coming here immediately our option expired if he had not already come to terms with us, and that he would give Holmes preference over us in subse quent negotiations e ^Jas ir al Mana asked Holmes to send his proposals in writing at once, as he ana his cousin Saleh could guarantee to get the Shaikh to consider them and oelay coming to terms v/ith us until the opticn expires* I knew that Saleh al ISana was playing a double game and working for Holmes, but I thought Haj i Maharrmed and his son Nasir were well disposed people. If, however, Holmes is prevented from coming to Bahrain and Qatar then we shall be in a reasonable position,, If he does come, as he will agree to anything the Sahikh asks for these negotiations will cost us a very large sum.*B2/E7 Telegram G.T.C. From Vice Consul, Mohammerah. To Political Resident at Kuwait No. 1530 Dated 3rd (received 5th March) 1935. Following from Elkington begins. Mylles telegraphs that he has obtained extension of option until ICay 4th from Shaikh of fats Ends. BRITGOHSUL(2 IH Telegram R.27. F r om Political Resident, at Kuwait. To H.M.'s Secretary of State for India, London. Copy by Air Mail to Government of India, New Delhi, n tt ti tt ii political Agent, Bahrain. Dated the^Gth March 1936. Qatar Oil. Belles has obtained extension of option until 4th May. -Resident- (C0 ^df™S.C/^ 0V of 1/3/35)! ^ / Js--&gt;(§&gt; 82/27 Telegram R 0 27 From To No. T/24 Political Resident at Kuwaiti, H#M t s Yice-Consul, Mohammerah Dated the 8th March 1935. Following for Elkington begins* Holmes arrived yesterday and in course of conversation I said that I had heard 1 rumours• to effect that he intended visiting %atar shortly to negotiate oil with the Shaikh. Holmes replied that he had no intention of interfering in qatar until at all events your option had expired. In the meantime he would be busy in Kuwait with Kuwait Oil Company geologists® Ends# RESIDENT - ^ ^ . Co Py forwarded to the Political Agent, Bahrain under P.L.Ho. C.24, dated 8.3.1935.5^ ' 4 nnnfidential* EXPRESS LETTER* H o .C/26 of 1936 Office of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Camp, KUWAIT. 8th March, 1936. From - Political Resident, at Kuwait. To • Secretary of State for India, London. Copy 'by Air to Government of India, New Delhi, it ♦» w « Political Agent, Bahrain. Copy given to Political Agent, Kuwait. My telegram No»T#16 if 6th March. general position is that Shaikh before taking up financial terms of Commercial Agreement has raised various objections over other clauses some of which Mylles has succeeded in persuading him to drop while others still remain for discussion. . j 0 ^5/ provided by Mr.Clegg of the Anglo-Persian Oil Company. The Shaikh's demands in regard to Articles 12 and 16 would appear to affect His Majesty's Government either directly or indirectly. Article 12. This would give the Shaikh a veto on a transfer, suggested by the Iraq PetrolBum Company, and approved of by His Majesty's Government* Article 16. Unless both the Shaikh and the Political Resident agreed on the choice of an Un^dre a deadlock will result. 3. Anglo-Persian Oil Company informed me that from information received they believed Holmes had immediate designs of visiting Qatar to intrigue with Shaikh and asked me to prevent him doing so if possible. Holmes arrived yesterday and in the course of conversation (at which Dickson AW 2. Details of the position are given in attached Summary was /-2- 37 was present) I informed him frankly that I had heard 1 rumours 1 to the above effect. Holmes (whom I like personally whatever I may think of him officially) said that he appreciated my frankness and that he had no intention of visiting Qatar or of negotiating for oil there until at all events the Anglo — Persian Oil Company concession had expired. In the meantime he wcuLd be busy here with Kuwait Oil Company geologists. I am informing the Anglo-Persian Oil Company Abadan of this. 4 1 Pursuing a policy of frankness I aasked Holmes who he would act for when and xf he negotiated at Qatar. He made the following interesting statement. That he had in the last few months been approached by two 'one hundred per cent' British groups (who had since amalgamated into one group) to negotiate on their behalf in Qatar, but had told them there was »nothing doing 1 until the Anglo-rer si an Oil Company option had expired without their being successful in obtaining the concession. That if this occurred, more especially if the Americans were after the concession, he would certainly enter the field. 6. Holmes did not give me this information im confidence but 1 see no necessity for it to be passed to the Anglo- Persian Oil Company. 6. I did not ask him the names of his hundred per cent British backers but it is quite possible that they may be Traders under another name.- with Eastern and General and Arabian Development Syndicate elements added. 7. The situation is therefore as follows 5 (a) If Mylles concludes the Commercial Agreement then the Political Agreement between His Majesty's Govern ment and the Company will have to be presented to the /the Shaikh for concurrence. (b) If the Shaikh refuses the concession to the Anglo- Persian Oil Company then Holmes will enter the field and since his Company will he purely British (if on examination of their credentials this is found to he so) His Majesty's Government can give them their blessing. In fact such a Company would suit us better than the Iraq Petroleum Company for whom the Anglo -Persian Oil Company are acting since the Iraq Petroleum Company are only about one quarter British. sd. T.C.Fowls, Lieut. -Colonel# political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Attested. for Deuxcucutj w jlitical Resident in the Persian Gulf.82/27 Telegram PUl?. From Political Agent, Bahrain. To Political Resident, at Kuwait. No .45. Dated 7th received 8th March 1936. MYLLKS left for Basrah by air March 7th with re-draft by Shaikh who is inclined to introduce political matters into Commercial Agreement. Understand that after going to Abadan he may ask to come to see you. 2 # He tells me that Holmes has made definite advances to which Shaikh will not listen till time of Company's option (which has been extended to 4th May) is up. -^Political-fyv? By Air Mail. P.Z . //7^ 19_^' ^v'bjy Ub INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, 22 FEB 1935 u- Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy has been sent to ckj^s. ^ by Mail. yiiu Fuiu'.^n Scui'cUi^, Qovcynmcnt of India t The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. 3057@ ^■y INDIA OFFICE, 1WITEHALL, 3.W, 1 P,Z.1179/35. 19tli February 1935. Dear Mr. Howltt, Thank you very Mich for your letter of the 16th February, TWa/'BZ,We note that the Anglo-Persian Oil Company have now received authority from the sheikh of Qatar to establish a wireless station in Qatar and that you have informed your station at Bahrein that no objection is seen to the opening of wireless communication between Qatar and your Bahrein station. Yours faithfully, J. G. LAHHWAITS • L. Howitt, Esq., Cable and wireless Ltd., Electra House, Victoria Embankment, W.C. 2.82/27 (g) Telegram G.T.C. From H.M. f s Vice Consul, Mohammerah. To Political Resident, Bushire. No.1630. Dated the 12th March 1936* (Relayed under Kuwait telegram dated the 13th Ivlarch 1936). Following from Anglo-Persian Oil Company. Mylles at present visiting Abadan is anxious to consult you. Will it be convenient if he proceeds to Bushire by air March 16th or any day thereafter. -Britconsul- 'e le P-rarn l?roTn Ho. S88 Bated the Political Hesident, Bushireo H.M 1 s Vice-Coneul, Moharntnerah. 14th March 19 35. Your telegram 1530 of March 12th. j?ollov;ing for Anglo-Per siar) Oil Company, begins My movements at present uncertain will wire to-morrow. Snds. BHI^COHSTTL (, ■ ££_ 11(3r&gt;/^ By Air Mail. p.z . OFFICE, LONDON, 1 MAR 1935 INDIA Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy has been sent to o by ^ Mail - yiir Fnrri -;n SnnrntnrTj ^iriTrVmnrnt nf iniiii The Political Resident in the Persian Gnlf. 3057Telegram Prom To Repeated to Copy by air tf-ltq JUC. l A • H«M t s Secretary of State for India, London. Political Resident, Bushire. m* 825 jfolitical Agent, Bahrain. Mo. 826 Government of India, Foreign and Poli- -tieal Department^ Uew Delhi. Dated 13th received 14th March 1935. Anglo-Peraian uil Goiapany have reason to believe that Holmes has been in direct communication with the Shaikh of ^.tar who has how- ~ever refused to treat with him or agree to visit from him until after expiry of Anglo-Persian Oil Com- -pany option which has now been extended to May 4th. W q cannot presumably ensure that Holmes will not communicate with Shaikh throught local agent but you will appreciate importance of ensuring that he is not allowed to pay a personal visit. Secretary of State for India^ W t A a r?. A cl A s \— ' - ■&gt; L - f (&lt; f . /U Q^T&gt; ^ ^ INDIA OFFICE&gt; V LONDON, 3.W, L. Ry Air fciall . p,2»1580/35. lltbi Marcii 1935. My dear Powle Qatar Oil I enclose copy of a memorandum summarising /the correspondence between ]VJyll6s and the A.P.O.C. detween 26th February and 3rd March, which was left with me hy Lefroy on 5th torch. We discussed the points arising on the various articles with the following result; Article 1 . No comment, except that it seems desirable that both the A.P»O.C, and the India Office should see the redraft. . i Article 2 ^' Die Sheikh 's suggestion that the period must turn upon the financial terms is, of course, a matter of bargaining. Article 3 . Beports on demand. I gather that the Company see no objection. Article 4 . goyalty basis to be won and saved as in previous draft. This is the same point as arose in the/ ie Hon'ble Lt.Gol. T»G» Fowle, C,B.E., Bushire.I M- the case of Kowelt. It, again, is a case of 'bargaining. Article 5 . Records on derrand. I gather that the Company see no special objection. Article 6 . It is perhaps reasonable that imports should de through Dohah. If the main oil-dearing structure proves to de in the Jedel Dukhan it would -prima fa.cis de more convenient that a special port of export (probadly with a pipeline, as in Bahrein) should tie agreed on that side of the Qatar Peninsula and I gather that the Company would not see odjection to this. But the terms of the sheikh 's request are in any event quite reasonable, since the port of export is to de a matter for agreement between the Company and the sheikh. No difficulty arises, I understand, about the use of the Company's facilities for personal or Government business by the sheikh; nor does any special difficulty arise as regards aircraft. (Incidentally, if and when the Company obtain their concession and start to operate in Qatar, we shall have to consider securing from the sheikh an understanding in regard to flights over Qitar, etc. similar to those which we have obtained in Kowelt, Bahrein and Muscat. Article 7/Article T C Caere need lie no question of any Government pressure In regard to tiie acquisition of land, etc. I gather that the Company see no special difficulty ahout agreeing to reversion to the sheikh, free of cost, of land, etc, surplus during the period of the agreement. ! v, Article 8 . _^E &gt; tesian wells. I understand from Lefroy that the A.P.O.C, think it very unlikely that wells if sunk will produce fresh water. But here again I gather that the point is not one of vital Importance and that they are likely, if the Sheikh presses the matter, to agree to his request. Article 9 . I gather that no special difficulty arises over this. i_ \l? Article 10 . Imports to he free, hut right to re-export to he covered hy a special payment additional to royalty. This, I gather, will he a bargaining point, and attention is invited in connection with It to the Sheikh's demands in respect of Article 15 as set out In the summary of the telegram from Qatar dated 2nd March in the A«P.O.C. summary. Article 11 . I understand that the A.P.O.C. see no special difficulty ahout this. Article 12//. 4 - / ' / ■' trt .tcle 12 .- This proviso that transferee companies shall te subject to approval lay the Sheikh, coupled with the intimation on the same Article in the telegram ' ' from Qatar of'2nd March that only one subsidiary company .Pwill be permitted, is, I gather, taken rather seriously by the A.P.O.C., who are, of course, bound to transfer to the I.P»C. any concession which they may obtain. Ihe question was not discussed in any detail with Lefroy, but I gathered they have in mind the possibility of establishing a Qatar Oil Company which would be a subsidiary of the I.P.C, and to which the concession could be transferred to be worked, with the sheikh's approval, once it had been obtained by the A.P.O.C. ; \ \1 Article 15 . I gather that the Company have in mind a variation of the Sheikh's counter suggestion on this to the effect that termination will be possible only within three years of the date of the agreement (which is, of course, a very different thing from the date of the conmencement of operations). I pointed this out to Lefroy, but did not go beyond that in our conversation. The Sbeikh can be relied on to look after his own interests on this. ^ Vij Article 14 . It seems desirable that both we and the A.P.O.C. should see the redraft, though if it is a 'redraft/- 5 - T 'redraft without^iteration of the sense' no special difficulty ne^d lae anticipated. js. -T b Article IS; . 7 I gattker that the Company agree. Article 16 ;of telegram of aeth Petruary. Prom the telegram of 28121 Petruary you will see that the Sheikh has now agreed to the retention of the reference to the po litical Resident . &lt;yO Article ll ^-fhe company, I gather from Lefroy, do not at all like this and feel that if the sheikh is to toe at liderty to disapprove of 'acy employee' and if the Company are thereupon to de dound to dismiss him s they may find themselves in a difficult position. I said that here, as elsewhere, it seemed desiradle for the Company, if they wished to get this concession, to meet the Saeikh on all points that were not entirely fundamental, dut that possidly they might think it worth while asking lilies to get a rather clearer definition from the sheikh of the precise type of employee to whom he wished to de in a position to odject. He might wish for a completely free hand: he might, on the other hand, de chiefly concerned to de adle to odject to individual Arads or other native employees. I gather that the Company will prodadly do this. Article 18/Article 18/ Here, as in the case of Articles 1 and 14, it seems desirable ttiat H.M.G. and the A.P.0*0. should see the redraft, so as to ensure that there is in fact no alteration of sense. ■-f T-f Article 21 .-^Arg^the result of discussion with the Company it has already heen agreed that as the sheikh apparently knows only Arabic and has nohody in his service who has a fluent knowledge of English, there are special reasons for allowing the Arabic text to prevail. 2, 'question of lO'Cal refinery . The demand for a local refinery (which would have heen very acceptable to the Admiralty) appears to have been dropped (compare telegram of 28th February on Article 16 from Qatar). . 3. Telegram from Qatar of 2nd March . Article 11 . * . , I said to Lefroy that tha company, under the terms of this article, were already required to pay the wages of the guards who were to be appointed in consultation with the sheikh; that the sheikh under the terms of his Treaty was precluded from obtaining arms, save with the approval of H.M.G., but that H.M.G. would raise no objection to arms (after consultation with the political Resident), being imported in sufficient quantities to equip the guards, but for no other purpose, so long as this/- 7 - yy y m this was donp'through the proper channels. Article 15 ; I gather that the Company see no difficulty ahout force majeure involving delay of operations in Qatar only. We see no objection to payment in rupees. The question of annual payments in addition to royalty to cover exemption from customs duties, etc. and the right to re-export is a matter for bargaining. 4. As regards the substantial gift, I gather (though Lefroy will not probably wish to be quoted) that rumours, which are thou^h-t to emanate from Holmes, have been spread locally, the most moderate of which is to the effect that the sheikh of Koweit received 45,000 rupees as a perbonal gift on the conclusion of his contract, and that this has sent up the sheikh of Qatar's demands. The Company are, it appears, prepared to consider a substantial gift rather on lines. 5. It is most satisfactory that the company should^ obtains/an extension of the option until 4th May. 6. The Company appear to be a good deal disturbed about Holmes' alleged contacts with the Sheikh. Lefroy mentioned (again I am not sure that he will wish to be quoted) that it had been ascertained through the local postal authorities that a letter addressed by Holmes to the Sheikh had been received in Qatar and that other letters/•' 8 ' Letters addressed to the shelkti had heen received from Mohamed Yatt ^irn. They attach great Importance to preventing him from visiting Qatar If, as ivyiles remarks In his telegram, 'repetition of the Kowelt experience Is to de avoided'. 7, I am sending a copy of this letter to the political Agent, Bahrein and to the Government of India. Yours sincerely,Telegram from Qa t r, IT q .2, 26th February . The following is the result of negotiations to date. The Shaikh has raised all the points and several others raised with Chisholm see his letter of 1st November 1933, and claims he is free to do so in view of Chisholm T s letter of 17th December and that he gave no reason to suppose that he would modify his demands with regard to the general terms even if the cash offer was accepted. I am insisting upon obtaining his final demand with general terms before discussing his present cash demands. Article 1 he requires to be redrafted in the same general sense. ^ Article 2 . Period depends entirely upon financial terms. Article 5 . Reports on demand. Article 4 . Royalty basis to be won and saved as in previous draft. Article 5. Shaikh requires copies of our records on demand. Article 6 . All imports are to be through Dohah only, port of export j s to be agreed and the Shaikh is to have full right to utilise all facilities whenever necessary for personal or Government business. Aircraft agreed subject to having special permission on each occasion. Article 7 . No Government pressure with regard to the acquisition of land etc. Land etc. surplus during the period of the agreement reverts to the Shaikh free of cost. Ar ticle 8. Shaikh requires two artesian wells free. Article 9 . Actual requirements only without right to re export. Article 10 . Imports to be free but right to re-export to be covered by a special payment additional to royalties. Article 11 . Shaikh of Qatr is not to be responsible for loss or damage due to invasions, insurrections, etc. Article 12 . Transferee companies to be subject to the approval of the Shaikh. Article 13. Termination only after three years from commencing operations and everything to revert free. To redraft without alteration of the sense. Article 15. Force majeure in Qatr only. Arl^i cie 16. Political Resident not accepted.2. Article 17 . No reason to be given by the Shaikh for disapproval. Article 18 . To redraft without alteration of sense. A rticles 19 and 20 o Shaikh aocepts. Article 21 . Arabic text only to prevail. Ar ticle 22 . Shaikh accepts* An additional article is to provide for a local refinery^ discussions continue but I anticipate that the foregoing are the Shaikh's minimum demands and will not be reduced by considerations of cash. When I have obtained his final demands 1 will write fully to London and proceed to Abadan for discussion. Meantime telegraph your views for guidance. Telegram received 27th from Abadan . It is certain that Major Prank Holmes is in communication with Shaikh of Qatr to whom he has submitted definite proposals with the Shaikh is using as a counter to ours without disclosing the source 5 he has already applied to the Shaikh for permission to visit Q.atr but has been refused until the date of expiry of our option. It is essential to prevent Holmes visiting Q,atr if a repetition of the Kuwait experience is to be avoided. Telegram received from Qatr 28th Februar y. Article 16 . Shaikh accepts Political Resident with the qualification that he also will approve of the Resident's nominee and has dropped the demand for a local refinery. Telegram from Q,atr 2nd March . Article 11 . Shaikh demands that Company pay cost of arms. Article 12 . Only one subsidiary company permitted. Article 15 . Porce majeure involving delay of operations in Qatr only. Shaikh demands payments in rupees and in addition to royalty annual payments for exemption from customs duties etc. and the right to re-export. Also a substantial gift as in the case of Kuwait. I have obtained an extension of our option until the 4th May. Telegram from Q.atr 5rd March I am leaving on the 4th March for Bahrein and on the 7th by air mail for Abadan.a, , HU r^v &gt; By Aii* Mail. p.z . //v INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy has been seat to V ^ MaiL \ / The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. 3057F.Z» 1783/35. BRITAMIC HOUSE, FINSBURY CIRCUS, LONDON, E.G. 2- 13th March 1935. thwaite Esq#, 0.1.1^., Office, ¥. 1 Dear Laithwaite, Qatr. We have received further reports from Mylles indicating the difficulty of the negotiations, hut not as yet any actual redrafts proposed by the Shaikh. The Shaikh has told Mylles that Holmes had written suggesting that he should come to Qatr secretly and make him an offer. The Shaikh said that he had not replied as he was not like Ahmed of Kuwait but liked to do things openly* A reply was sent through Nasir al Mana' to the effect that the Sheikh did not approve his coming to Qatr in disguise, and did not agree that if he came to terms with us he was to withhold his signature for two months to enable Holmes to make an offer, but he did agree to Holmes coming to Qatr immediately our option expired (i.e. now alter May 4th) if he had not already come to terms with us, and that he would give Holmes preference over us in any subsequent negotiations# Nasir al Mana T asked Holmes to send his proposals in writing at once, as he and his cousin Saleh could guarantee to get the Shaikh to consider them and delay coming to terms with us until the option expired. The Shaikh's initial comments on our draft were largely not in the local Arabic but in modern and up-to-date Egyptian Arabic, and contain words and phrases unknown in Qatr. This was confirmed by Mylles 1 Arabic-speaking clerk who/V 2. who was 'born and 'bred in Cairo, You are doubtless aware that Holmes has all his translations and printing done in Cairo through a man named Hammond* I told you of the redraft which Mirza Mohammed had produced of the form in which our last draft would 'be used 'by Arabs of the Shaikh of Qatr 1 s type, and I enclose two copies of this draft, which is quite interesting as its contents seem just as effective as our English drafting- Yours, &amp;c», (Sgd.) L. LEPEOY.© P.Z. 1783/35. In fchs name of God, 'thg MsrcifvxXi ConipsxssiQn&amp;'ts* The reason for writing the deed of agreement .is: That We, Shaikh Abdullah bin Qasim ath-Thani Ruler of Qatr, on my own behalf and on behalf of my successors and assigns, and I, Charles Clark Mylles, agent for the Anglo-Persian Oil Company Ltd. have consented and agreed to conclude this Agreement for a full period of Seventy Five Years on the conditions set forth hereafter: and that the agreement has been completed between us on principles of good will and good faith, both of us praying God for success and relying on Him for help. finndition First. I, Shaikh Abdullah bin Qasim ath-Thani, grant to the Company, according to this agreement, the exclusive right to explore, prospect, drill for, extract, carry away, export and refine and sell petroleum, naphtha, natural gases, ozokerite, asphalt and derivatives thereof, throughout my State of Qatr; but if the said Company discovers other mines than the said substances, for instance if it discovers gold, iron, coal, etc. it shall have no right to take possession of the same, but must give me a report about them, and I shall then have full right to take possession of 'khe said mines without any opposition or obstruction. Condition Second. The aforesaid Company shall have full right -to operate in any part of the State of Qatr; but it is incumbent upon it not to operate on lands where religious buildings are found or on lands where religious buildings are constructed in future according to the general custom^ or on cemeteries existing in the different part of the State&gt; and I, Shaikh Abdullah bin Qasim ath-Thani will inform it of the existence of such religious buildings or cemeteries, so that it may know them. The phrase 'State of Qatr' means all the territories ruled by me, Shaikh Abdullah bin Qasim ath-Thani, and which are recorded on the North of the line on the map which we have attached to this/@ v* - 2 - this Agreement so that they may be known# Condition Third* The Company shall make a thorough investigation of the State of Qatr by such methods as may in its opinion best enable it to ascertain the existence of oil or its absence; and shall employ all means customary and proper and carry out the operation by appropriate scientific methods. It is also incumbent upon it to make the necessary maps and accurate records of wells drilled and such other data whether geological or of the drillings which are carried out by it. If I, Shaikh Abdullah bin Qasim ath-Thani wish to inspect these maps or records, or data aforesaid,it is obligatory on the Company to produce them to me or to any one whom I may depute for their inspection. Furthermore, it is obligatory on the Company to supply to me a report, every year, on the operations it has carried out according to this Agreement- Gondition Forth. In view of these rights which I have granted to the Company, the Company shall pay me:- Firstly on the signature of this Agreement Secondly on each of the first four anniversaries of the date of signature But if the Company discovered the substances mentioned in Condition First and commenced exporting them from Qatr the Company shall pay me fixed royalties instead of the sums mentioned in Clauses Second and Third and the said royalties shall be at the rates mentioned below and shall be paid to us by the Company on the above-mentioned substances which it has exported or sold at Qatr during the year ended 3 months prior to each anniversary of the date of signature: AND the rates referred to are these:- dv1 7 v7 - 3 - (1) On all the substances other than asphalt, ozokerite and natural gas royalty per ton (2240 English Pounds) at the rate of (2) On asphalt and ozokerite royalty per ton (2240 English Pounds) at the rate (3) On natural gas royalty per 1000 cuMc feet at the rate of * * On the condition that the total of the royalties which the aforesaid Company pays shall not be less than * every year. If we requi re an y moneys at any time other than the end of the year after the signature, it has 'been arranged 'between us that I should write to the Company on the subject and give it ample respite to make payment; and the Company undertakes to pay me all such royalties as may have accrued up to a date 3 months prior to the receipt of such letter from me- Condition Fifth. The Company shall measure all fluid substances exported from, or sold for consumption in the State of Qatr by dipping of tanks or through orifice meters, and all solid substances by weight, and it shall keep accurate records and accounts thereof. It shall submit to us a correct copy of these every year; and we shall be entitled to refer to these records at all reasonable times either ourselves or through a duly authorized representative* Condition Sixth* I, Shaikh Abdullah bin Qasim ath-Thani have granted to the Company the right to construct and operate roads, telegraph, telephones, and their lines, and the stations required for wireless telegraphs, railways, refineries, harbours, pipe lines required for the flowing of oil, workshops, houses for residence of its employees; and I have granted it the right to utilize means of transport/u - 4 - transport for the conduct of its operations, whatever such means 'be, whether 'by land, water or air; 'but if there 'be need for me to use the telegraphs, telephones and railways belonging to the Company for my personal business, the Company shall agree to this, and it shall not be entitled to demand any hire whatsoever from me. Should, God forbid, any great incident happen in my territories, I shall have the right to use the wireless and telegraph installations and railways belonging to the Company for my State affairs and it shall not be entitled to demand any hire from me at all. The ships belonging to us can use the harbours used or built by the Company ; but our ships must not hamper the Company* s operations and must do nothing detrimental to the Company's interest in any way; and the Company's opinion in this connection shall be the final opinion* Condition Seventh. I, Shaikh Abdullah bin Qasim ath-Thani have granted to the Company the right to use all the uncultivated lands belonging to us which the Company may require for its operations, to any extent it may desire, and I shall not demand any cost or hire from it. If the Company needs to acquire any other lands or houses or buildings it can purchase the lands houses, buildings, etc. or rent the same on such terms as may be agreed upon by their owners; but the value or rental of these shall not be m excess of the rates current in their localities. The Company shall acquire only such lands, houses and buildings as are required for its use according to this Agreement; and it is understood that the lands and houses taken over by the Company must be less than the whole area of Qatr. It shall, likewise, inform me, at all times, of such lands, houses and buildings which are required to be occupied for its purposes. But as to the lands, houses and buildings which/- 5 - which have been acquired by the Company and which are subsequently found no longer necessary, such lands, houses and buildings must be returned to us at a cost which shall not be greater than that paid by the Company. And we have naturally agreed that all the lands, houses and buildings owned by the Company shall be returned to us on the expiry of the period of this Agreement or before this Agreement be terminated with our mutual consent. Condition Eighth. The aforesaid Company can take any quantity of water which it may require for its operations without cost; but it is obligatory on it not to cause any loss or damage to any of the inhabitants* It can, likewise, sink wells and drill for and impound water to provide for the needs of its operations# Should any need arise for our armies or military expeditions to take any of the water under the Company^ contract, the Company shall allow this without cost. The remainder of the available water can be taken by the inhabitants for themselves and their animals without cost. Condition Ninth. The Company can take any soil, clay, gravel, lime, gypsum, stone and similar materials for its operations free of cost; but it shall not be jutified in preventing the people from taking their usual requirements of these materials. Condition Tenth. In view of the sums which we have agreed upon according to Condition Fourth, the Company shall have the right to import water,petroleum,fuel,machinery,motor cars and lorries,aircraft,equipment,plant,timber,utensils,iron work,building materials,medicines,office equipment,household furniture and all other materials, equipment, and goods required by the Company or its employees for the purposes of/\A - 6 - of its operations; but it will not loe permitted to sell these articles to others; and it has the right to export its petroleum, products and articles previously imported 'by it free of Customs, import or export duty or taxes or other charges; hut the Company shall pay the ordinary duty charged from British, merchants in the State of Qatr on all personal goods, clothing and general merchandise and food supplies imported 'by it for the personal use of its employees. And the Company, its operations, incomes and profits and properties shall he exempt and free from all present and future taxes and charges of any kind as long as this Agreement endures. Condition Eleventh . I, Shaikh Abdullah bin Qasim ath-Thani will afford all the necessary assistance to the Company for facilitating the carrying out of Vhis Agreement, and will likev/ise do all that 1 can to protect its employees and properties. The Company can, after consultation with me, appoint guards to assist in protecting the Company^s employees and properties. Condition Twelfth . If the Company desires to transfer this agreement to any other commercial company, it is permissible for her to do; but the Company is not permitted to transfer it to any Government; and it is necessary that the Company to which this Agreement is transferred should be able to fulfil all the duties and obligations of this Agreement. Similarly, if the Company finds it necessary to form another Company or subsidiary companies under its own control for the Yv T orking of this Agreement, it is permissible for it to do so. All such subsidiary Companies shall have all the rights and privileges which/@ - 7 - whicii we liave granted according to this Agreement, and shall undertake all the engagements and responsllDilities expressed therein. Condition Thirteenth. The Company can terminate this Agreement; 'but it is obligatory upon it to give me d%x months 1 notice in writing of its intention to do so. And if the said termination occurs within thirty five years from the date of signature of this Agreement, all lands granted 'by me to the Company and any land or buildings which have 'been purchased 'by the Company itself and any houses or buildings constructed by, and other immovable properties of the Company Y /ithin the State of Qatr shall be handed over to us without cost. And wells actually producing oil must be handed to us as they are at the time of delivery. And also if such termination should occur after thirty five years from the date of signature of this Agreement, the Company shall hand over to us all its properties in the S'Bate of Qatr, and similarly deliver to us wells actually producing, oil as they are at the time of delivery. And on the expirty of the period of this agreement, i.e. the seventy five years, which we have provided for in Condition First, or on the expiry of any period which may be added thereto, with our mutual consent, for its extension or renewal, the Company shall deliver to us all its properties existing in the State of Qatr without cost and shall deliver wells actually producing oil as they are at the time of ^-delivery. Condition Fourteenth . I, Shaikh Abdullah bin Qasim ath-Thani, shall have the right to terminate this Agreement in two cases Y/hich we shall state belOY\r:- Firstly, if the Company/ffi) - 8 - Company; fails to make the payments mentioned in Condition fourth 'within six months of the date on which such payments fell due. But if any dispute should occur on the part of the Company in regard -fo any payment, it will not 'be permissiMe to me to terminate the Agreement until it is arbitrated on under Condition Sixteenth and unless the Company has failed to comply with the decision of the arbitrators within three months from the date of such decision. Secondly, if the Company is proved to be in default under the arbitration provisions of Condition Sixteenth. Condition Fifteenth . If there happen to be force majeure and if the Company is rendered unable or held bade from fulfilling any of the conditions of this .Agreement, it will not be permissible for me to deem this accident as an argument against the Company or to interpret it as a breach of this Agreement. It is obligatory upon me, in that case, to add the period of the delay together with any period which may be necessary for the rectification of the delay according to reason and truth to the period fixed in this deed, and the Company shall proceed to make the necessary restoration of such damage as expeditiously as possible. Condition Sixteenth . If, God Forbid, any dispute should arise between me and the Company as to the interpretation of any condition of this Agreement, or as to any matter arising out of it or with reference to the obligations of either party under it, and if no agreement be arrived at by any other way, it is imperaitve, in that case, to refer the said dispute to two arbitrators, and I myself shall appoint one of them; and the Company shall appoint the other each of/© - 9 - of us appointing his arbitrator within thirty days of receiYing a request from the other party to do so» The two arbitrators shall then appoint a third arbitrator; 'but should the two arbitrators, or any other two arbitrators appointed instead of them, be unable to agree upon the third arbitrator within sixty days of the request to arbitrate, we ' \\ agree that the third arbitrator shall be appointed by the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. The award of of arbitration must be made in accordance with xhe general principles of lav/ recognised by civilized nations. And the decision of the ma-jority of the arbitrators shall be final. The place of arbitration shall be Qatr; but if it be deemed fit by the majority of the Arbitrators that the arbitration should be held elsewhere, the arbitration shall, then, be held at the place which is, chosen by the majority. The arbitrators, in giving a decision, shall specify an adequate period of delay in which the party adjudged should carry out the said decision; and that party shall be considered to be in default only if that party has failed to conform to the decision prior to the expiry of that period and not otherwise. Condition SeTenteenth. All the labourers who are required by the 'Company in the State of Qatr shall be employed from our subjects or from those persons who are recommended by us, but it is for the Company to bring managers and skilled employees and clerks from outside. Similarly, if the Company should not secure a sufficient number of suitable labourers in the State of Qatr, it can import these from outside. The Company is not justified to keep any employee disapproved by us; but we must not express disapproval except on valid grounds^ Condition EiRhteenth. X, Shaikh Abdullah bin Q,asim -ath-Thani declare that X conclude this Agreement on principles of friendship and/^ 0 • 10 - and goodwill and that I shall interpret this Agreement in a manner consistent with reason and truth; and I, Charles Clark Mylles, declare that the Company acknowledges the Shaikh*s authority and his rights as the Ruler of the State of Qatr and that it will respect those rights in every way, nondition Nineteenth , This Agreement shall not prevent me from granting concessions to other parties for any article other than the substances mentioned in Condition First; hut the terms of such concessions shall not interfere with the rights or the operations of the Company under this Agreement. Condition Twentieth. All the moneys due to me according to this Agreement shall he paid 'by the Company at the Bank in and when the Company takes a receipt from the said Bank, the receipt shall be a complete discharge for the Company in respect to the payment of the sum mentioned in the Bank's receipt. I may designate another Bank or Banks, as I may wish, to receive payments from the Company; and I shall inform the Company of this in writing. Condition Twenty First . This Agreement shall be binding on the parties, their successors and assigns, and has been written in Arabic and English and all due care has been exercised to ensure that both texts are identical in meaning. Should there be, at any time, disagreement as to the meaning or interpretation of any clause in either text, we and the Company agree to settle the matter by mutual discussion; failing which we shall refer the question to arbitration according to Condition Sixteenth. Condition/©) n( - 11 - n ondition Twenty Second. Tiae terms, year, month day as used in this Agreement refer to the solar calendar of England and to no other, .Agreement has 'been arrived 'between us on these conditions on the date mentioned at the prelude of this document; and in witness where we have set our hands thereto; and God is the 'best witness. Sfeiaikh Abdullah bin Q,aslm ath-Thani, Huler of Qatr. Charles Clark Mylles, Agent for Anglo-Persian Oil Co.Ltd. Witness Witnessall communicat-jqns to as a0dressed to thb company ^ j&gt;* j ' 'jj j'i* mft j rv ^ j lo-pessian oil company, limited, LONDON AND ABADAN. y »^ui At ^ j 5 «Sm) aS**'^ telegraphic apdress: 'ANGLOPERS.' ( GONFIDEFTIAL ) ABADAN, PERSIAN GULF. NO.- GM/X6ZL My dear Fowle. DATED-— 17tli March 1935. QATR N EGOTIATIONS. I am so sorry that Mylles was unable to make contact with you prior to your visit to India, as it would have given us the opportunity of consulting you with regard to the position at Qatr, especially in connection with those points which the Sheikh has raised vaiich are more of a political than a commercial nature. I enclose herewith a copy of our latest report which has been despatched to London from which you will observe that there are issues involved which are not strictly speaking within the province of a Commercial concern viz. Article 11 (protection), Article 17 (Rights of Foreigners to reside in Qatr), Article 18 (Trial of Foreigners in Qatr). We should be glad of your advice as to the attitude we should adopt towards the Sheikh over these demands and it would assist us if you could indicate the action you propose to take in the matter. In the event of a deadlock, the cause will undoubtedly be that the Sheikh's demands both general and financial will be such that we cannot regard them as reasonable or commercially justi fiable. I presume that under these circumstances H.M. Government would not per mit' the Sheikh to grant a concession on easier' and mo're''favourable terms to say 'the Standard Oil Company or any other go reign company. On the other hand, if the Sheikh were disposed ^Co^granf a 'concession on much easier and more favourable terms to a British interest e.g. the Eastern General Syndicate, would H.M. Government be prepared to intervene in our favour in view of our position in the Gulf and the fact that we are an Oil Company and not merely concession hunters. Yours sincerely ; af-o — Lieut-Col. T .C.W.Fowle, C.B.E., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bu shi re.82/27 Telegram R*27. Prom Political Resident, at Bahrain* H*M» f s Vice-Consul, Mohammerah» No*T/104 Dated the 4th April 1936 • /JV / r Following for Elkington begins: Your letter of 17th March. I presume that enclosure has been sent Home and is under discussion between your Company and India Office. In this case I do not think I can usefully give an opinion. Ends. -.Resident.VJ- Telegram xx ey'i, From Secretary of State for India, London. To Political Resident, at Bahrain. No.1076 Repeated Government of India, New Delhi. No.1076 Dated 3rd (received 4th) April 1936. f Your Express Letter dated March 8th Ko.C/26, i ?a- graph 7 (b). We think it most unlikely that any really substantial and purely British operating Company could take up concession in this area and are most anxious not to be faced with repetition of Traders episode. We wish therefore to leave nothing undone to' encourage Shaikh to clinch with the Anglo-Persian Oil Company as against negotiating with Holmes and his friends# In these circumstances we suggest opportunity might be taken before Anglo-Persian Oil Company option expires of indicating to Shaikh that his interests will best be served by granting concession to a concern which is well qualified to work it and of impressing on him again that His Majesty's Government will not be prepared to approve of grant except to a concern which is at least partly British. 2. Choose most opportune moment for such action having regard to progress of Mylles , financial discussions with Shaikh. We suggest you might discuss situation with him on his arrival in Bahrain# of which was sent by Company to you at Delhi by air mail of March 17th, please see record of conversation with Anglo- Persian Oil Company and Baylies of March 28th, copy sent to 3. As regards Shaikh's re-draft of concession, copy you /( 1 you and Government of India by air mail of March 29th. We will be consulting you in the immediate future on the question of jurisdiction referred to therein. -Secretary of State for India# (Copy given to Political Agent, Bahrain.)By Air Mail. p.z. ' \ INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, BUSH [REP in ~MOO - - - - _ ^ r. nozjw.. Date. if/ ix* mmmmamsacr- -- -.^ CONFIDENTIAL RECOSS^ Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy has been seat to JL=V b y ^ M ail. Gjir-nrninn nt nl Iniii i The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. 3057P,Z. 2156/35. BHITANNIC HOUSE, FINSBUHY CISCUS, LONDON, E.G. 2. 26th March 1935. J.G, Laithwalte, Esq., CIE., India Office, S#?/. 1. Dear Laithwaite, Qa.tr . Mylles returned yesterday afternoon hy air, and I enclose three copies of a translation hy Mirza Mohammed of the draft which the Shaikh of Qitr gave Mylles before leaving, as representing the Shaikh's views on the general terms. The financial terms have not as yet been discussed at all, and from what we can see they are likely to he difficult, as that old shaikh appears to he a very obstinate man and equally hard up in present circumstances. I am going through this draft with lilies and thereafter will discuss it with Messrs. Eraser and Agnew, and then make an appointment to see you on any points of difficulty, as lylles must leave next Tuesday to return to Qatr by air. As far as my personal views are concerned, after going through the draft with Mylles the point on which I find most difficulty is the second paragraph of *'' ■ULII ..., —I— || •Aruicle 15 relating to the submission of differences betifl/een foreign employees of the Company and inhabitants of Qp.tr to the Shara Courts in Qatr. Article 22 required a Petwa of the Qadhi before the shaikh was able to accept so irreligious a conception. Where3 @ Tftiere Mirza Motiammed has translat,ecl 'be justified' we shall probahly substitute 'has the right' which he has himself used in some places for the same expression in Arabic. Yours sincerely, L.LEPROY.I ■ i v %r ft 'i / ^ f ■ | /C \j SHAIKH O F QATR 1 S DRAFT, li MARCH ...19 . 1 TR ANSLATION BY KHAN BAHiPUR MOHAMMED. - - DRAFT OF &amp;ATR COMCESSIOM . This agreement was made on the day of 195 , corresponding to the 155 between His Excellency Shaikh Abdullah bin Qasim al-Thani, Ruler of Qatr, (who is hereinafter called 'the Shaikh', and this expression, whenever the contract requires shall include his successors and assigns), on the one part, and Charles Clark Mylles, on behalf of the Anglo-Persian Oil Co. Ltd. (which will hereinafter be called as the 'Company'; and this expression shall, whenever it is required by the contract, include its assigns), on the other part. Agreement is hereby concluded between the Shaikh and the Company as follows :~ Artlcle First. The Shaikh grants to the Company, in virtue of this agreement, and under the following conditions, the sole right, throughout the principality of Qatr, to explore, to prospect, to f 01&gt; to extract and to ship and to export and the right to ■ refine and sell oil and natural gases, ozokerite, asphalt and every thing which is extracted therefrom, which shall hereinafter be called 'the substances'. If the Company discovers, in the course of its investigation and general activities, any minerals other than the substances mentioned in the first article, e.g. gold or iron oxide or any other minerals, it shall not be justified to appropriate j the same, but must inform the Shaikh of their discovery; and the Shaikh shall have full right to, and absolute control over, those minerals which have been extracted; and he shall be free in granting concessions for the extracting of those minerals to any Company or Companies or to dispose of those minerals in any manner he considers to be consistent to his interests. Article Secnmi . Subject to the conditions of Article 7, below, the Company can operate in any part of the principality of Qatr as is- 2 - (@ * iefinsd bolow^ but it will not op6ra.t6 on pla .c6S sucli as roligious lands, cemeteries, lands occupied by religious buildings or by essential enterprise by their owners as may exist on the date of the signature of this agreement or any customary extensions of such religious lands, or cemeteries or buildings as may be pointed out by the Shaikh, The principality of Qatr means the whole area over which the Shaikh rules and which is marked on the north of the line drawn on the map attached to this agreement. The period of this agreement shall be seventy five years from the date of its signature. Article Third . The Company shall explore the principality of Qatr minutely by any methods which is the best in its opinion to enable it to ascertain the probable existence of the substances. And for the purpose of carrying out its works in accordance with this agreement, the Company shall employ all customary and proper means and shall carry out the examination by methods agreeable to the modern Scientific Knowledge. The Company shall inform fl.E. the Shaikh of all its operations in this connection from time to time. The Company undertakes to keep drawings and maps and accurate records of the wells drilled and such like data, whether they be topographical, geological or drilling, as it is customary to keep; and such information as these shall be open to inspection by the Shaikh or by his authorised representative.I Article Fifth . The Company will measure all liquid matters, at the time of their extraction from wells, either by dipping reservoirs or by means of measuring instruments, and measure solid substances by weighingj and it should supply the Shaikh with a copy of the register if His Excellency so demands. Likewise, the Company shall submit to His Excellency the Shaikh an account of the substances extracted by it for every six months and the authorized agent of the Shaikh shall have the right of inspection thereof at all reasonable times. Article Sixth. The Company may construct, maintain and operate roads and telegraph and telephone installations and their lines and wireless stations, railways, refineries and the ordinary ports situated at Dohah for importing its materials, and pipe-lines and pumping stations, workshops, houses and other things and works which are useful for it, as required for the purposes of its operations, and also the accommodations required for its employees, but excepting the places occupied by the enterprise of their owners, or those which it will be difficult for their owners to part with; and these are exempted. And the Company shall be justified to choos the port which may be suitable for exporting its substances; and it will likewise be justified in using all the means of transport required for its operations in accordance with this agreement, excepting aerial transport, which, on every occasion arising for jt, the Company must obtain the Shaikh's permission and consent thereto. And His Excellency the Shaikh shall have the full right to use those roads, the electric (telegraph) lines, the wireless installations.w elephones, and railways for his personal business and for governmental purposes, in case of need, free of chargej and the Shaikh shall have the right, also, to use all the ports used and constructed by the Company; and the Company undertakes to afford H.E. the Shaikh all facilities in this respect. Article Seventh . The Shaikh grants to the Company the use and occupation of uncultivated lands belonging to the Shaikh himself and which the Company may require for its operations, free, after an understanding is arrived at between the Shaikh and the Company about them, excepting the lands surrounding Riyan, as will be defined by the Shaikh himself. The Company will not be justified to acquire lands occupied by the enterprise of the owners thereof and also houses, places and lands which their owners decline to sell or to rent; and excepting these, it does not matter to use (other lands) if occasion arose. And the Company shall inform the Shaikh from time to time of the lands, houses and buildings which it requires to occupy for its enterprise. And the lands, houses and buildings already acquired by the Company and found by it to be un- necessary for it any longer for its business, shall be restored by the Company to the Shaikh free. Provided that all the lands, houses and buildings which have been acquired by the Company shall be handed over to the Shaikh free on the termination or prior to that, on the cancellation, free. Article Eighth . The Company may take any quantity of water which it may require for its operations, free of charge, on the condition that this will not cause any loss or damage to any of the inhabitants. And subject to the same conditions as have been specified, the Company can explore, drill and impound water to satisfy the requirements of its operations. In case of need, the Shaikh*s army or military expeditions can take, free of charge, any quantity of water available under the Company T s control, after its requirements are satisfied; and,- 5 - , k ^likewise, 'tli© inlia.bita.nts can talc© such surplus wat©!* for th.GniS6lv6S and their animals, free of charge. Article Ninth . The Company can take any earth, mud, gravels, lime, gypsum and stones and other similar substances which it requires for its operations , free of charge , but it will not pre vent the people from taking their customary requirements of these materials. The Company, however, must only take what it requires; and will not be justified in exporting any of these (materials) abroad. Article Tenth . In consideration of the sums agreed upon in the fourth Article, the Company shall have the right to import water, petroleum, fuel, machinery, motor-cars, lorries, aeroplanes, equipments, instruments, wood, utensils, iron ware, building materials, medicines, office equipments, household furniture, and all other things, equipments and goods required by the Company or by its employees for its operations; but not for sale to others; and it shall have the right to export its substances and their deri vatives and things already imported by the Company without Customs duty or import duty or export duty or tax or any other duty. The Company shall, however, pay the ordinary duty applicable to British merchants in the principality of Qatr on all the personal effects, piece-goods, general merchandise and provisions which it imports Tor the personal use of its employees. And the Company and its operations, incomes, profits and properties shall be exempt and Tree, during the period of this agreement, from all the present and ^uture taxes of any kind whatsoever.. Irticle Eleventh . The Shaikh agrees that he will afford the tecessary assistance for the enforcement of this agreement, and -hat he will use his authority to protect the Company's employees nd property as far as possible. But the Company shall also, tself^ take the necessary steps in this respect, namely that the haikh or his assign will appoint armed guards on his behalf and he Company shall pay the expenses for this and the cost of their' &lt;5 i rms; and th© guards should b© sufficiGnt in number and ©quipniGn't. nd neither does the Shaikh guarantee to the Company what may be aused by unforeseen circumstances, nor will he be responsible herefor. For instance should, God forbid, an attack be made by n enemy or any accident occurs in spite of him, through any ggressor, the Shaikh shall, in case of such aggression, use his ndeavour to ward off an aggression of this nature^ but he shall ot be responsible for any loss or damage thereby caused. rticle Twelfth . The Company has the right to transfer this greement to any other commercial Company^ but it will not be astified to transfer it to any Government whatsoever on the con- ition that the said Company shall be able to fulfil the obligations f this agreement and its engagements entirely. The Company shall iform the Shaikh if it transferred this agreement in the manner foresaid and obtain his assent and acquiescence. And the Company lall have the liberty to form a single Company, if it finds it ecessary, to carry out this agreement, and the aforesaid Company aall enjoy all the rights and privileges granted to the Company in Lrtue of this agreement. And it must bear all the engagements and ssponsibilities set forth therein. rticle Thirteenth . The Company may terminate this agreement if t finds it disagreeable for it to act upon the same; but it shall )t be justified to cancel it or to abandon it and to discontinue )erating it except after three years with effect from the beginning • operation, by giving six months' previous notice, in writing, to is Shaikh of its intention to do so. And if the said cancellation iculd take place within thirty five years from the date of signature • this agreement, all the lands granted by the Shaikh and any lands or lildings purchased by the Company and any houses or buildings con ducted by, and any immovable properties belonging to, the Company ■thin the principality of Qa.tr shall be surrendered to the Shaikh 'ee of charge. And the wells actually producing at the time of said cancellation shall be surrendered in a condition considered 1 be good and satisfactory, as they were at that time.o - 7 - 11 t I And if the SEid cancGllation should tak© plac© after 'thirty five years from the date of signature of this agreement, all the Company's properties within the principality of Qatr shall be surrendered, in that case, to the Shaikh, free of charge; and the wells actually producing at the time of the said cancellation shall be surrendered in a condition which is reasonably considered good and satisfactory, as they were at that time. On the termination of this agreement at the conclusion of the seventy five years, stipulated for in the second article, or the conclusion of any extension or renewal of its period all the Company's properties existing in the principality of Qatr shall be surrendered to the Shaikh free of chargej and the wells actually producing at that time shall be surrendered in a condition which is reasonably considered good and satisfactory, as they used to be at that time. Article Fourteenth . The Shaikh has the right to cancel this agreement in the two cases mentioned below:- (A) If the Company fails to pay the sums mentioned in the fourth article within six months from the date they fall due. Pro vided that if any dispute should be made by the Company in regard to any payment thereof, the Shaikh shall not cancel the agreement until arbitration takes place thereon in accordance with article sixteenth and unless the Company fails to comply with the award of the arbi trators within three months from the date of the said award. (B) If the Company is in default according to the provisions for arbitration set forth in the sixteenth article. Article Fifteenth . The Shaikh shall not hold the Company liable if default should occur on the part of the Company in carrying out or fulfilling the provisions of the agreement by the mere occurrence of force majeure which may suspend operation; but should any dif ference occur between His Excellency the Shaikh and the Company as to the existence or non-existence of such force majeure, the same shall be referred to arbitration, as provided for in the sixteenth article. And the Shaikh stipulates that the force majeure which maysuspend operation means that which occurs in connection with the Company's operations in Qatr and that nothing else must be taken into consideration and must npt be used by the Company as an argument in this respect. And the Company shall proceed to effect ropairs at the time when any damage, of any nature, takes place; and the period of the said delay, together with any period reasonably necessary for repairing the damage will be added to the period fixed in accordance J with this agreement. Article Sixteenth . Should any dispute occur between the Shaikh and the Company in regard to the interpretation of this agreement or of any matter arising therefrom or in regard to the engagements obligatory on either of the parties in accordance therewith, such dispute shall be referred to two arbitrators if no agreement can be arrived at for settling it by any other method, and the Shaikh will appoint one of them and the other will be appointed by the Company, Each of the two parties shall appoint his arbitrator within thirty days after receiving the demand therefor from the other party. The two arbitrators shall thereupon appoint a third arbitrator; but if the two arbitrators or any two arbitrators appointed instead of them are unable to agree upon the third arbitrator within sixty days from the demand for arbitration, the two parties agree that, in that case, the third arbitrator should be appointed by the Political Resident; and the Shaikh makes it a condition that he should agree to the third arbitrator. The award of arbitration shall be consistent with the legal, principles familiar to civilized nations. The decision of the majority of arbitrators shall be final; and the place of arbitration shall be Qatr. On giving any award, the arbitrators shall fix a sufficient time within which the party against whom the award is given, should carry out the said award. And that party shall be considered at fault only when he fails to comply with the award before the expiry of the aforesaid period and not otherwise. Article Seventeenth . The labourers employed by the Company must be from amongst the Shaikh T s own subjects or from amongst those(JJ) - 9 - U V approved by the Shaikh, excepting technical employees and the managers and clerks whom the Company may require and whom it cannot find in the country. And the Shaikh makes it a condition that no official should be accepted whose retention is disapproved by the Shaikh, if the Shaikh notices any irregular acts on his part. And it naturally follows that the wages which the Company pays to the employees from amongst Qatr people shall be reasonable. Article Eighteenth . The Shaikh and the Company declare that they base action upon this agreement on the basis of good faith and pure belief and upon the interpretation of this agreement in a manner consistent with reason. And the Company undertakes to acknowledge the Shaikh^s authority and his rights in his capacity as the Ruler of the Qatr principality and to respect them in every manner. If any dispute or quarrel should take place between any of the foreign employees of the Company and any of the Shaikh 1 s subjects, their trial shall be held before the Shaikh and in his Shara (Religious) Courts. Article Nineteenth . Nothing contained in this Agreement shall prevent the Shaikh in any manner whatsoever from granting concessions to other parties for anything excepting the substances mentioned in the first article provided that the said concessions do not interfere with the rights of the Company or its operations in accordance with this agreement. Article Twentieth . The Company will pay all the sums due to the Shaikh, in accordance with this agreement, into the Shaikh 1 s account in the Bank in and the receipt taken from that Bank shall be a full acquittance of the Company's liability for the sum mentioned in the Bank 1 s receipt. The Shaikh may, from time to time, appoint another Bank or other Banks for the purposes of this Article, and this shall be done in writing.—I II 111Ifit - 10 - (S&gt; \\ ; Article Twenty-First . This Agreement shall be binding upon both the parties and their successors and assigns; and it has been written in Arabic and English and all due care has been taken to make the two texts identical in meaning. And if any difference should arise as to the meaning or the interpretation of any article, at any time, the Arabic version is to be relied upon. Article Twenty-Second . The expression year, month and day used in this Agreement shall mean what is consistent with the English Solar Calendar and not any other. IN WITNESS whereof the two parties have hereunto set their hands and seals on the day and in the year mentioned in the preamble. Shaikh of Qatr.P.Z. 2253/35 INDIA Qjj'FIGS . Confidential . QATAR OIL. Note of discussion at the India Office 28th March 1935^ with representatives of the The Sheikh of Qatar r s redraft of the Qatar Commercial Agreement received under Mr. Lefroy ! s letter of 26th March to Mr. Laithwaite was discussed at the 1.0. on the 28th March. Mr. Lefroy, Mr. Mylles, Mr. Walton and Mr.Laithwaite y/ere present. 2. It appeared that the Company, (subject to the comments which follow), were prepared generally to accept the redraft in the form proposed 'by the Sheikh, and were in fact anxious to agree to it with as few alterations as possible in order to facilitate negotiations. Article Ij . The Sheikh had insisted on 'won and saved'. The redraft of this article on which the Company propose to instruct Mr. Mylles to negotiate is appended to this record. Article i4.(a) . It has already been agreed (Mr. Lefroy* s letter of 10th October 193U, on P.Z. 6327/3U) that signature must be ad referendum and subject to the approval of H.M.G. The point v/as made that in these circumstances it would be difficult, if not impossible, for the Company to make the first payment under the agreement immediately on signature. After discussion the best course seemed to be that Mr# Mylles should, immediately before signature and after the financial terms had been agreed, remind the Sheikh that signature was subject to approval and that in these circumstances the whole of the first payment could not be made immediately but that a payment on account of, say, Rs»50,000 would be made at once, and that the date of signature for the purpose of Articles 4(b) 5 4(c) and sub-paragraph 2 (i) and (ii) should be the date on/ 5 on. Thursday, A.P.O.C.2. on which the concession had been signed, subject to the approval of H.M.G. Article 11 ♦ The Company wMlc desiring not to make a difficulty in their negotiations oy raising an objection were somewhat apprehensive that the Sheikh might endeavour to secure armaments on an unjustifiable scale from them with a view to equipping his forces with machine g^ms, armoured cars, etc. for the purpose of repelling raids. ^ey would of course be most reluctant to involve themselves in any such commitment, not least because any provision of arms by the Company might expose them to international criticism. It was agreed after discussion that having regard to the provisions of Article 3 of the Qatar Treaty of 1916 and the fact that the question of what provision of arms, etc. was 'sufficient' was open to reference to arbitration, the Company could probably take the risk involved in accepting the Sheikh's redraft as it stood# Article 16 , Provision that the Sheikh's consent should be necessary to the third arbitrator. It was agreed to mention this point to the Political Resident. Mr. Mylles felt confident that the Sheikh (or his son) would in practice agree to whatever name the Resident suggested. The history of this proviso was largely that the Sheikh thought that its insertion would make it less likely that the Resident would nominate someone who would be entirely unacceptable to the Sheikh and under the influence of the Company. Article 17 . The question was raised of what action H.M.G, would take if the Sheikh, for some frivolous reason, were to require the removal of the Chief Local Representative. It was thought that this risk was one which could probably be faced. In practice it might prove necessary in such an event to bring political pressure to bear upon the Sheikh. Article/11 { , 3. ^ Article 1B » Sub-paragraph 2.' This was discussed in detail. Mr. Mylles stated that he had informed the Sheikh that the matter was one for H/;:.;. G. , into which the Company could not enter; that the Sheikh had taken the line that it had better go in the agreement .and that if objected they could then take it up with him (the Sheikh). The Company were strongly opposed to the acceptance of any such ' provision and were given to understand that it v/as obj ectionabk ; also from the point of view of H.M.G. who certainly could not agree to it. It was agreed that Mr. Mylles should inform the sheikh that the matter had been referred to Government, but that so far as the concession was concerned the Company could not accept a provision on these lines. The India Office representatives intimated that the question of cession of Jurisdiction by the Sheikh and a consequent Order in Council would be taken up, the main alternative courses of procedure being; (a) that the issue should be faced with the Sheikh as a condition of the grant of approval by H .M .G.; (b) that it should be taken up at once prior to signature of the concession, the Sheikh being informed that H .M .G. could not approve the insertion of such a condition in any concession. Mr. Mylles remarked that the Shara Law andtho penalties under it were strictly enforced in Qatar and that the point was therefore one of importance. 3. The Company stated that if they failed to reach agreement with the Sheikh within the time of the present option they proposed to withdraw Mr. Mylles a-nd make no application for a further option. They thought on the whole that the Sheikh and his son (who was playing an increasingly important part) were not predisposed to the Company and that they thought that they could expect greater support from H .M .G. with a British concessionnaire. But the Sheiich's financial demands were extravagant. They had no information as/I If 1/ ( 4. as to who might be behind Major Holmes, hut thought it probable that it was the Eastern and General Syndicate again. They thought it most unlikely that he was acting in any way on behalf of the Standard. The chances of the latter had not been improved by Ibn Saud's raising the boundary question, which had stiffened the Sheikh's attitude. 4. The Company's representatives enquired what the attitude of H.'M.G. would be if negotiations now broke down and if the Sheikh subsequently intimated his desire to grant the concession to another company on less favourable terms than had been offered by the A.P.O.C. It was pointed out to them that the attitude of H.M.G. to any fresh competitor must depend largely on circumstances; that there ¥/ere great difficulties in urging the Sheikh to give the A.P.O.C. what would in effect be a continuing option on the concession on whatever terms they were at this stage prepared to offer; but that in the first place, so far as the Standard of California were concerned, it seemed most unlikely that an American Company would be prepared to accept the British safeguards which the Sheikh was aware were a sine qua non of H.M.G.'6 approval to the grant of any concession, while so far as other companies who might comply with these conditions were concerned there seemed no reason why the Sheikh, if his negotiations with the A.P.O.C. broke down on the question of finance, should be prepared to accept less favourable terms from another company. The 'British safeguards' would of course ee of universal application. idia Office, 28th March, 1935.© if £ P.Z.2253/1935. Draft A rticle__4 In consideration of the rights granted by the Shaikh to the Company in acoordance with this Agreement the Company shall make the following payments to the Shaikh during the currency of the Agreements- (a) On the date of signature Rs. (h) On each of the first four anniversaries of the date of signature Rs. (c) On the fifth and each subsequent anniversary of the date of signature until the Company- declares it has found oil in commercial quantity Rs. (d) Thereafter the Company shall pay royalty on the Substances as followss (1) On all substances won and saved other than asphalt ? ozokerite and natural gases per ton (2240 English pounds) at the rate of Rs- (2) On asphalt and ozokerite won and saved per ton (2240 English pounds) at the rate of Rs. (3) On Natural gas produced and sold per 1000 cubic feet at the rate of R s » or a sum of Rs. .p.a.whichever shall be the greater. But no royalty shall be payable on any substances used within the State of Q.atr by the Company or its employees or on any water or foreign matter extracted with the oil. In consideration of the exemption from taxes^ dues and duties as provided for in Article 10 and the right/@ IV^ 2. right to re-export material vfhich had been previously- imported as is provided for in Articles 10 and 13, the Company shall make the following paymentss- (1) On each anniversary of the date of signature and until the Company declares it has found oil in commercial quantity Rs. (2) On each aniversary of the date of signature and after the Company declares it has found oil in commercial quantity Rs,I DRAFT ah^ 3s'. 2 9- 4 f /? ■ /v^~' This Agreement was made on the day 0 f 195 ^ corresponding to the 155 between His Excellency Shaikh Abdullah bin Qasim al-Thani^ Ruler of Qatr^ (who is hereinafter called 'the Shaikh', and this expression, whenever, the contract requires shall include his successors and assigns), on the one part, and Charles Clark Mylles, on behalf of the Anglo-Persian Oil CooLtd. (which will hereinafter be called as the 'Company'^ and this expression shall, whenever it is required by the contract, include its assigns), on the other part. Agreement is hereby concluded between the Shaikh and the Company as follows s- Article First. The Shaikh grants to the Company, in virtue of this Agreement, and under the following conditions, the sole right, throughout the principality of Qatr, to explore, to prospect, to drill for and to extract and to ship and to export and the right to refine and sell petroleum and natural gases, ozokerite, asphalt and everything which is extracted therefrom, which shall hereinafter be called 'the substances'. If the Company discovers, in the course of its investigation and general activities, any minerals other than the substances mentioned in the first article, e.g. gold or iron oxide or any other minerals, it shall not be justified to appropriate the same, but must inform the Shaikh of their discoveryi and the Shaikh shall have full right to, ...and absolute control over, those minerals which have been extracted| and he shall be free in granting concessions for the extracting of those minerals to any Company or Companies or to dispose of those minerals in any manner he considers to be consistent to his interests. Ar ticle Second,. Subject to the conditions of Article 7^ below, the Company can operate in any part of the State of Qatr as is defined below, but it will not operate on places such as religious lands, cemeteries, lands occupied by religious buildings or by essential enterprise by their owners as may exist on the date of the signature0 a V of this Agreement or any customary extensions of such religious lands, or cemeteries or buildings as may be pointed out by the Shaikh. The State of Qatr means the whole area over which the Shaikh rules and which is marked on the north of the line drawn on the map attached to this Agreement, The period of this Agreement shall be seventy five years from the date of its signature. Article Third. The Company shall explore the State of Qatr minutely by any methods which is the best in its opinion to enable it to ascertain the probable existence of the substanceso And for the purpose of carrying out its works in accordance with this Agreement, the Company shall employ all customary and proper means and shall carry out the examination by methods agreeable to the modern Scientific Knowledge. The Company shall inform H.E. the Shaikh of all its operations in this connection from time to time. The Company undertakes to keep drawings and maps and accurate records of the wells drilled and such like data, whether they be topographical, geological or drilling, as it is customary to keep; and such information as these shall be open to inspection by the Shaikh or by his authorized representative. Article Fourth, In consideration of the rights granted by the Shaikh to the Company in accordance with this Agreement the Company shall make the following payments to the Shaikh during the currency of the Agreement (a) On the date of signature Rs, (b) On each of the first four anniversaries of the date of signature Rs, (c) On the fifth and each subsequent anniversary of the date of signature until the Company declares it has found oil in commercial quantity Rs, (d) Thereafter the Company shall pay royalty on the Substances as follows:: (l) On all substances won and saved other than asphalt, ozokerite and natural gases per ton (2240 English pounds) at the rate of Rs,(2) On asphalt and ozokerite won and saved per ton (2240 English pounds) at the rate of Rs. (5) On natural gas produced and sold per 1000 cubic feet at the rate of Rs. or a sum of RSo.o,... p.a. whichever shall be the greater. I But no royalty shall be payable on any substances used within the State of Qatr by the Company or its employees or on any water or foreign matter extracted with the oil. In consideration of the exemption from taxes, dues and duties as provided for in Article 10 and the right to re-export material which had been previously imported as is provided for in Articles 10 and 15, the Company shall make the following payments (1) On each anniversary of the date of signature and until the Company declares it has found oil in commercial quantity Rs. (2) On each anniversary of the date of signature and after the Company declares it has found oil in commercial quantity Rs. Article Fifth. The Company will measure all liquid matters, at the time of their extraction from wells, either by dipping reservoirs or by means of measuring instruments, and measure solid substances by weighing^ and it should supply the Shaikh with a copy of the register if His Excellency so demand. Likewise, the Company shall submit to His Excellency the Shaikh an account of the substances extracted by it for every six months and the authorized agent of the Shaikh shall have the right of inspection thereof at all reasonable times. Article Sixtho The Company may construct, maintain and operate roads and telegraph and telephone installations and their lines and wireless stations, railways, refineries and the ordinary ports situated at Dohah for importing its materials, and pipe-lines and pumping statipns, workshops, houses and other things and works which are useful for it, as required for the purposes of its operations, and also the accommodations required for its employees, but excepting the places occupied by the enterprise of their owners, or thosewhich it will be difficult for their owners to part with| and these are exempted, And the Company has the right to choose the port which may be suitable for exporting its substances; and it will likewise have the right to use all the means of transport required for its operations in accordance with this Agreement, excepting aerial transport^ which 5 on every occasion arising for it^ the Company must obtain the Shaikh T s permission and consent thereto^ And His Excellency the Shaikh shall have the full right to use those roads, the electric (telegraph) lines, the wireless installations, telephones, and railways for his personal business and for governmental purposes, in case of need, free of charge; and the Shaikh shall have the right, also, to use all the ports used and constructed by the Company; and the Company undertakes to afford H.E. the Shaikh all facilities in this respect. Article Seventh, The Shaikh grants to the Company the use and occupation of uncultivated lands belonging to the Shaikh himself and which the Company may require for its operations, free, after an understanding is arrived at between the Shaikh and the Company about them, excepting the lands surrounding Riyan, as will be defined by the Shaikh himself. The Company has no right to acquire lands occupied by the enterprise of the owners thereof and also houses, places and lands which their owners decline to sell or to rent; and excepting these, it does not matter to use (other lands) if occasion arose. And the Company shall inform the Shaikh from time to time of the lands, houses and buildings which it requires to occupy for its enterprise. And the lands, houses and buildings already acquired by the Company and found by it to be unnecessary for it any longer for its business, shall be restored by the Company to the Shaikh free. Provided that all the lands, houses and buildings which have been acquired by the Company shall be handed over to the Shaikh free on the termination or prior to that, on the cancellation, free, fcticle Eiffh-t-.b . The Company may take any quantity of water which it may require for its operations, free of charge, on the conditionthat this will not cause any loss or damage to any of the inhabitants. And subject to the same conditions as have been specified, the Company can explore, drill and impound water to satisfy the requirements of its operations. In case of need, the Shaikh^s army or military expeditions can take, free of charge, any quantity of water available under the Company 's control, after its requirements are satisfied; and, like wise , the inhabitants can take such surplus water for themselves and their animals, free of charge. A rticle Ninth. The Company can take any earth, mud, gravels, lime, gypsum and stones and other similar substances which it requires for its operations, free of charge, but it will not prevent the people from taking their customary requirements of these materials. The Company, however, must only take what it requires; and shall have no right to export any of these (materials) abroad. Article Tenth. In consideration of the sums agreed upon in the fourth Article, the Company shall have the right to import water, petroleum, fuel, machinery, motor-cars, lorries, aeroplanes, equipments, instruments, wood, utensils, iron ware, building materials, medicines, office equipments, household furniture, and all other things, equipments and goods required by the Company or by its employees for its operations; but not for sale to others; and it ^hall have the right to export its substances and their derivatives and things already imported by the Company without Customs duty or import duty or export duty or tax or any other duty. The Company shall, however, pay the ordinary duty applicable to British merchants in the State of Qatr on all the personal effects, piece-goods, general merchandise and provisions which it imports for the personal use of its employees. And the Company and its operations, incomes, profits and properties shall be exempt and free, during the period ^ this Agreement, from all the present and future taxes of any kind whatsoever. fetj cle Eleventh. The Shaikh agrees that he will afford the necessary as sistance to carry out this Agreement, and that he will use hisauthority to protect the Company's employees and property as far as possible. But the Company shall also, itself, take the necessary steps in this respect, namely that the Shaikh or his representative will appoint armed guards of his own choice and the Company shall pay the expenses; and the guards should be sufficient in number and equipment. And neither does the Shaikh guarantee to the Company what may be caused by unforeseen circumstances, nor will he be responsible therefor. For instance should, God forbid, an attack be made by an enemy or any accident occurs in spite of him, through any aggressor, the Shaikh shall, in case of such aggression, use his endeavour to ward off an aggression of this nature| but he shall not be responsible for any loss or damage thereby caused. Article Twelfth. The Company has the right to transfer this Agreement to any other commercial Company; but it shall have no right to transfer it to any Government whatsoever on the conditions that the said Company shall be able to fulfil the obligations of this Agreement and its engagements entirely. The Company shall inform the Shaikh if it transferred this Agreement in the manner aforesaid and obtain his assent and acquiescence. And the Company shall have the liberty to form a single Company, if it finds it necessary, to carry out this Agreement, and the aforesaid Company shall enjoy all the rights and privileges granted to the Company in virtue of this Agreement, and it must bear all the engagements and responsibilities set forth therein. Article Thirteenth. The Company may terminate this Agreement if it finds it disagreeable for it to act upon the same; but it shall have no right to cancel it or to abandon it and to discontinue operating it except after three years with effect from the beginning of operation, by giving six months' previous notice, in writing, to the Shaikh of its intention to do so. And if the said cancellation should take place within thirty five years from the date of signature of this Agreement, all the lands granted by the Shaikh and any lands 0 r buildings purchased by the Company and any houses or buildings constructed by, and any immovable properties belonging to, the Company1 © 7- 1 ithin the State of Qatr shall be surrendered to the Shaikh free of Large'. And the wells actually producing at the time of the said ancellation shall be surrendered in a condition considered to be good and satisfactory, as they were at that time. And if the said cancellation should take place after thirty five years from the date of signature of this Agreement, all the Company 's properties within the State of Qatr shall be surrendered, in that case, to the Shaikh, free of charge| and the wells actually producing at the time of the said cancellation shall be surrendered in a condition which is reasonably considered good and satisfactory, as they were at that time. On the termination of this Agreement at the conclusion of the seventy five years, stipulated for in the second article, or the conclusion of any extension or renewal of its period all the Company's properties existing in the State of Qatr shall be surrendered to the Shaikh free of charge3 and the wells actually producing at that time shall be surrendered in a condition which is reasonably considered good and satisfactory, as they used to be at that time. Article Fourteenth. The Shaikh has the right to cancel this Agreement in the two cases mentioned below;- (A) If the Company fails to pay the sums mentioned in the fourth article within six months from the date they fall due. Provided that if any dispute should be made by the Company in regard to any payment thereof, the Shaikh shall not cancel the Agreement until arbitration takes place thereon in accordance with article sixteenth and unless the Company fails to comply with the award of the arbitrators within three months from the date of the said award, (B) If the Company is in default according to the provisions for arbitration set forth in the sixteenth article. A rticle Fifteenth, The Shaikh shall not hold the Company liable if default should occur on the part of the Company in carrying out or fulfilling the provisions of the Agreement by the mere occurence of force majeure delaying operation^ but should any difference occur between His Excellency the Shaikh and the Company as to the sxistence or non-existence of such force majeure, the same shall be8, referred to arbitration, as provided for in the sixteenth article. L Shaikh stipulates that the force majeure delaying operation means that which occurs in connection with the Company's operations in Qatr and that nothing else must be taken into consideration and must not be used by the Company as an argument in this respect. And the Company shall proceed to effect repairs at the time when any damage, of any nature, takes places and the period of the said delay, together with any period reasonably necessary for repairing the kamage will'be added to the period fixed in accordance with this Agreement. Article Sixteenth. Should any dispute occur between the Shaikh and the Company in regard to the interpretation of this Agreement or of any matter arising therefrom or in regard to the engagements obligatory on either of the parties in accordance therewith, such dispute shall be referred to two arbitrators if no Agreement can be arrived at for settling it by any other method, and the Shaikh will appoint one of them and the other will be appointed by the Company. Each of the two parties shall appoint his arbitrator within thirty days after receiving the demand therefor from the other party. The two arbitrators shall thereupon appoint a third arbitrator; but if the two arbitrators or any two arbitrators appointed instead of them are unable to agree upon the third arbitrator within sixty days from the demand for arbitration, the two parties agree that, in that case, the third arbitrator should be appointed by the Political Resident; and the Shaikh makes it a condition that he should agree to the third arbitrator. The award of arbitration shall be consistent with the legal principles familiar to civilized nations. The decision of the majority of arbitrators shall be final; and the place of arbitration shall be Qatr. On giving any award, the arbitrators shall fix a sufficient time within which the party against whom the award is given, should Carr y out the said award. And that party shall be considered at fault only when he fails to comply with the award before the expiry[ © 9 - . / 0 f the aforesaid period and not otherwise. seventeenth. The labourers employed by the Company must be from amongst the Shaikh's own subjects or from amongst those approved ]3y the Shaikh^ excepting technical employees and the managers and clerks whom the Company may require and whom it cannot find in the country. And the Shaikh prescribes as a condition the dismissal of any employed whose retention is disapproved by the Shaikh,, if the Shaikh has observed any irregular conduct on his part. And it I naturally follows that the wages which the Company pays to the employees from amongst Qatr people shall be reasonable. : Article Eighteenth. The Shaikh and the Company declare that they base action upon this Agreement on the basis of good faith and pure belief and upon the interpretation of this Agreement in a manner consistent with reason. And the Company undertakes to acknowledge the Shaikh's authority and his rights in his capacity as the Ruler of the State of Qatr principality and to respect them in every manner. Article Nineteenth. Nothing contained in this Agreement shall prevent the Shaikh in any manner whatsoever from granting concessions to other parties for anything excepting the substances mentioned in the first article provided that the said concessions do not interfere with the rights of the Company or its operations in accordance with this Agreement. I Article Twentieth. The Company will pay all the sums due to the |Shaikh, in accordance with this Agreement, into the Shaikh's account in the Bank in and the receipt taken from that Bank shall be a full acquittance of the Company's liability for the sum mentioned in the Bank's receipt. The Shaikh may, from time to time, appoint another Bank or other Banks for the purposes of this Article, and this shall [ done in writing. I feicle Twentv-First. This Agreement shall be binding upon both the f Parties and their successors and assigns; and it has been written in Arabic and English and all due care has been taken to make the two1. iO 10. !, ^ ex ts identical in meaning. And if any difference should arise as to the meaning or the interpretation of any article, at any time, the Arabic version is to be relied upon. | Twenty-Second. The expression year, month and day used in this Agreement shall mean what is consistent with the English Solar [ Calendar and not any other. IN WITNESS whereof the two parties have hereunto set their |hands and seals on the day and in the year mentioned in the preamble Shaikh of Qatr.GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. Department. H 0 ! EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). This is an ORIGINAL message sent hy A.IR MAIL which provides a means of communication more ' expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save t ime and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a officer of of ^ Resident in the Persian Gulf, ^35 NoC/98 of 1935 Dated U .7 Camp, Bahrain. ' me 7th April, (/ From To Political Resident, at Bahrain. Political Agent, Bahrain at In continuation of India Office telegram No.1075 of 3rd April 1936 to my address, copy of which was given you, I enclose herewith a letter from me to the Shaikh of ^atar, No.C/97, dated the 7th April 1936, together with a copy fo'r yo^r files. / 2. You will remember tliat in our conversation yesterday with Mr.Mylles we arranged that when Mr.M^ylles felt that an opportune moment had arrived he would send a wireless message to you consisting of the word 'Letter', you would then arrange to send the letter, with Saiyid /ibdur Hazzak, hy launch to Khuwair where Mr.Mylies would have a car wait ing in readiness. The day previous to your sending the letter you would wire the word 'Car' to Mr.Mylles. I S. 41 bp- 3. Please telegraph me when the letter is despatched. Attested• h- r- &lt;7.1^3^ sd. T.C.Fowle, Lt.-Colonel. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf • for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. (Designation) 825S&amp;P (M-i070) —14-9-34—'i O ,OC0.Telegram xx From Political Resident, at Bahraitu Secretary of State for India, London* Copy by Air Mail to Governraent of India, New Delhi• Gopy given to Political Agent, Bahrain* No.T/113. Dated the 7th April, 1935. 1 . r Your telegram of 3rd April No.1075. : Situation appears to be as in paragraph 7 of my Express Letter under reference and under neither (a) nor (b) would repetition of Traders episode seem likely. 2. With reference to last sentence of your paragraph one I have discussed matter with lilies and we are agreed that the best procedure wouldjbe for me to leave at Bahrain appropriate letter from me to Shaikh which will be despatched when Mylles intimates by wireless from Qatar that moment for delivery has arrived* -^Resident • (Copy given to Political Agent, Bahrain.) (Copy forwarded to Govt.of India under P.L•No*0/100 of 7/4/36).82/27 Telegram xx pTOin Dci-i e ocix j \j± uwcaoi- J-VJ. To Political Resident, Bushire. No.1127. Repeated Government of India, New Delhi. No.1128. Political Agent, Bahrain. No.1129. Dated 8th(received 9th) April, 1936. Secretary of State for India, London. My telegram of 3rd April No•1076 paragraph 3. Jq / QATAR OIL. . His Majesty's Government In agreement with Govern ment of India always regarded surrender of jurisdiction over (non-Moslem) foreign subjects as indispensable pre-condition of their consent to grant of any concessions by Shaikh under Article V of Treaty but in. the interest of forwarding negotiations between Anglo-Persian Oil Company and Shaikh have hitherto on your recommendation abstained from taking up this point with him (please see India Office letter to Foreign Office, P.Z. 628/34 of February 1st 1934 paragraph 2 (e)). It seems clear however in the light of Shaikh's demands that Shara Law shall govern cases in dispute between Company's employees and his subjects that issue must now be faced. His Majesty's Government suggest in these circum stances that (after brief interval of some (? days to enable) Mylies to resume his negotiations) you should yourself proceed to Qatar and inform Shaikh that His Majesty's Government have learnt of his proposal to Company on this point and (using whatever language you think fit) that you are instructed to make it clear that it is one which they cannot approve and that indispensable pre condition of their approval to grant by him of any concession to whomsoever it may be, is a definite-2- I {hv understanding regarding jurisdiction over foreign subjects on the lines of the Bahrain and Kuwait Orders in Council. It seems on the whole definitely more convenient to take point up at once and not after initialling of concession more particularly because Shaikh may, unless warned in time of attitude of His Majesty's Governmebt, endeavour to make inclusion of provision on his lines a condition of signature or an excuse for not signing within period of option. -Secretary of State for India-82/27 1*7 Telegram R#27» From Political Agent, Bahrain. Tg political Resident, Bushire. Ho» 58• Dated and received the 9th April 1936. „ v lles approached me yesterday with a request that if he made agreement with Shaikh it would be necessary for me to go to Qatar to witness his signature • Presume no objection* -Politicalo M The Political Agent, Bahrain, ■ CO^FlOENTiAL RECORDS \3lf Al Qatar Negotiations. i?5reauested by Colonel Fowle I enclose herewith a draft in English which gives the sense of the letter which ' am instructed to deliver to the Shaikh of iatar on resuniing negotiations with him. %hra in • I have the honour to be Yours obedient servant. sd/- C.C.! j x i ■ • 7th April 1935f¥) \1&amp;. Draft in English giving.the sense of a letter to be addressed to the Shaikh of Qatar. I have to inform you that I proceeded to London and referred to the Directors the various matters arising out of our discussions with regard to the oil concession for the State of Qatar. The Directors accept the demands as set forth in the ' -&gt; draft delivered to you on the 3rd March 1355, provided always that agreement is reached with regard to the finajicial terms and with the following exceptions. ^ ^ Ar ticle 11 . Cost of arms.-^'' ^ The words 'and the cost of their arms' cannot be accepted. The Company agrees to pay for the cost of armed guards which clearly includes the cost of their arms. The Company however being purely a commercial concern cannot agree to pay for arms separately and specifically. Article 18. Trial of foreign subjects.. This is a political matter and we are instructed by His Britannic !fe.1esty ! s Government that they do not approve of the inclusion of a provisioncof this sort in a commercial agreement. The Company however .ill be bound by any agreement on the subject which you may make with His Britannic Majesty's Government. I now enclose a draft of article 4 and request an interview so that I may offer you financial terms.82/27 and 33/51. Te R • 27 • From Political Resident, Bushire* To Senior Haval Officer, Persian Gulf, Repeated Political Agent, Bahrain. Ho •■340 ♦ Dated the 10th April 1936. I have received instructions from His Majesty's Government to proceed to Qatar • I propose arriving Bahrain by next down slow mail. Grateful if you could arrange for sloop) to take me thence to Qatar and back to Bushire via Bahrain. Probable stay at Qatar two days. Resident. Telegram R.27. From Political Resident, Bushire. lo Political Agent, Bahrain. No .341. Dated the 10th April 1935. My telegram of today No#340. I should like to take Abdur Razzaq with me. / ihl Your telegram of 9th April No .68^ No objection but signature seems unlikely before I proceed Qatar myself* ^Resident -82/27 and 33/51 R«27 • prom Senior ITaval Officer, Persian Gulf* To Political Resident, Bushire. No •0628 2/11• Dated 11th (received i2th) April 1936. Your i Sloop will be provided but it is desirable that she should be back at Bahrain on April 19th owing to great press of work incident upon our transfer. -Senior Haval Officer82/27 Telegram R* ^7 y vom Political Agent, Bahrain. To political Resident, Bushire Ho. 60. Dated lltii received 12th April 1935. Do you wish me to warn Mylles or make any arrangements. Also do you wish me to warn Shaikh. - POLITICAL - 15) i ,82/27 Telegram 27 From political Agent, Bahrain. To political R-esident, Eushire Ho. 62. Bated llth received 12th April 1935. Your Express Letter of April 7th, lo.C-98. V i( ^ r % qATAR OIL# In view of your forthcoming visit to Qatar should letter to Shaikh issue if Mylles telegraphs as arranged. POLITICAL -@) 8a/27 / Tele gram XX* JTom H.M*a Secretary of State for India, London • To Political Resident, Bushire* Copy 'by air Government of India, Foreign ani Political Department, :&amp;ew Delhi* Political Agent, Bahrain. Ho* 1167 Dated 11th received 12th April 1935* Your telegram of the 7th April,Ho*^113 # What we want to avoid is having to deal with mere conces si on-hunters v /ho would present themselves as 100^ British but if they obtained concession would then, after going through formalities of offering it to some substantial British Company (none of whom appear at present likely to be free to take it up or be inter- -ested in it) face us with request to agree to assign- -ment to a foreign oil company. In theory we would be entitled under our safeguards to refuse, in practice we mi^it find great difficulty in mainting our refusal. We are therefore anxious to concentrate on the Iraq Petroleum GSompany and give then all possible assistance. Secretary of State for IndiaTelegram R»27* From Political Agent, Bahrain• To Political Resident, Bushire No.63. Dated and received the 13th April 1936 IMPORTANT'' |U / \ Your ship arrives at one o*clock local time on Monday morning. Will you stay on board the night or come ashore at once. It had been arranged for Shaikh and me to call on Senior Naval Officer officially on Monday and thereafter Senior Naval Officer returns call and we proceed to witness ceremonial of hoisting of flag. Do you propose to participate. Please telegraph your intentions to enable me to make arrangements with Senior Naval Officer -Political. r?R. 27 Political Resident, Bushire# Political Agent, Bahrain, jU Your telegram of 13th April, Wo* 63# I will leave ship at seven hours. Please arrange transport accordingly for self and party. I should like to participate in ceremony. Resident* iml 82/27 Telegram R 27 FroiD Political Residenii, Bushire. ^ Political Agent, Bahrain, Ho* 363 Dated 13th April 1935. L ^ Yoiir telegram Ho* 60. Please inform Shaikh, and Mylles. I hope to leave Bahrain Monday evening. 2. Your telegram Ko. 62. I will take letter with me. Resident. /&gt;-1 XX Telegram pj.oja Political Resident, BKXfc±RR To Secretary of State for India, London Copy by post to Government of India, Hew Delhi- Copy given to Political Agent, Bahrain. No.T/117• Dated the 16th April 1936- Tmmediate Your telegram of 8th April I presume that I am authorised to give Shaikh in writing communication from His Majesty^ Govern ment ? He will almost certainly ask for letter. Please reply to Warship Fowey Bushireradio • ►Resident. ((Eopy given to Political Agent, Bahrain.)fvK 1 Telegram xx fyom Secretary of State for India, London. To Political Resident, H.M.S.Fowey, at Doha. Copy by Air Mail to Government of India, New Delhi. n « 11 11 w Political Agent, Bahrain. Ho.1208• Dated 16th (received 16th) April 1936. Important . Your telegram of 15th instant T/117. Aiiswer is in the affirmative. You may also if necessary remind Shaikh of terms of Article III of his Treaty if question of supply of arms by Company under Article XI of Commercial Agreement comes up. I understand Anglo-Persian Oil Company have made their attitude regarding supply of arms clear to My lies and you will doubtless consult latter. -Secretary of State for IndiaCONFIDENTIAL . No- c/113 tf 1935 • The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf 'presents his com pliments to The Political Agent, Bahrain. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment ^s). 2 # Letter No.C/97 of 7th April 1936 to the Shaikh of Qatar forwarded with my iL ^qpress Letter No.C/98 of 7th April 1936 is cancelled* Office of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, DOha * 6' Da ted . 18th, April.. 19.3,5..,. /If Reference to previous correspondence Description of Enclosure. / Name and Date. / 1. Letter No .C/109 of 17th .■.pril 1935 to the Shaikh of ^atar, /fx-* 2. Letter No.C/110 of 17th April 1936 to the Shaikh of Qatar. 3. Letter No.C/114 of 18th &gt; April 1936 to the Shaikh of ^atar. Subject. Qatar Oil.Translation o f letter Ho.6/64 dated the 14tli Muiiarram 1354 (i.e.18.4.35) from Shaikh 'Abdullah bin Oasim ath Thani,C.I.E., Ruler of Qatar, to the Kon'ble Lieut. -Colonel T .C .Fowle ,e.B .E., Politxcal Resident in the Persian Gulf. After Compliments, I have the honour to acknowledge the receipt of your letter dated the 17th April 1935 equivalent to 13th Muharram 1354, the contents of which I have duly noted. Reference Your Honour's advice that it would be in my Interests to grant the concession to a Conqpany like the Anglo-Persian Oil Company. I am very thankful to you for your valuable advice, and wish to inform you that I have always done fcy my best in order to pave the way for an agreement with this Company. Hence I have been negotiat ing with them for all this long period. Moreover I like them ftn ri prefer them to all (other) Companies. I have been as accommodating to them as far as possible. I am still regotiating with them andhope that we will come to an agreement, unless I find that they will not give me my rights and be unfair with me, in which case I would naturally refuse to accept terms which are less than what I am entitled to or which are of loss and harm to me. ' I would be within my rights to protect my rights and lose nothing of them and at the same time choose what would be in my interests and in that of my country. Ho doubt one knows his own affairs best. Usual Ending.Translation of letter No♦7/64 dated the 14th Muharram 1364 (i»e# 18th April 1936) from Shaikh •Abdullah bin Qasim ath Thani,C#I.E M Ruler of Qatar, to the Hobble Lieut •-Colonel T»C.Fowle.C»E.E M Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. After Compliments, /f ; Reference your letter dated 17th April 1936 equivalent to the 13th Muharram 1364. 2» Regarding the sub-paragraph of the draft of the Oil Concession which I gave to Mr. lilies. I agree to your demand (proposal) that disputes between British subjects British protected subjects and the subjects of non-Moslem Foreign Powers should be settled by the nearest officer of the High British Government i.e. the Political Agent, Bahrain, or his representative. 3. I also agree that tbe disputes between British subjects and the subjects of Non-Moslem Foreign Powers and my subjects should be dealt with by a Joint Court on irtiich I and the Political Agent, Bahrain, will sit, or on itfiich my representative and the representative of the Political Agent, Bahrain, will sit. The place and the sitting of this Court will be at Doha. As regards the subjects of Moslem Foreign Powers to whom you referred in paragraph 3 of your proposal, I, on my part, agree to your proposal about them, but will not be responsible for any objection which may be raised by their Governments. 4. I have agreed to these on the condition that the Government undertake to give their full support to me ari d -to my heir apparent, my son Hamad, when he succeeds me and that they do acknowledge him as my heir apparent and support him when he succeeds me. Usual Ending.Translation of letter lTo.8/64 dated the 14tli Euliarram 1364 (i»e.l8»4.36) from Shaikh # Abdiillah bin Qasim ath Thani, C#I»E&lt;», Ruler of Qatar, to the Hon^le LieirU-Colonel T,C*Fowle,C.B»E., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf* After Complinients, With reference to pur yesterday*3 conversation on the subject of the protection which the Government intend to extend to me on land (al~Barr) • I should like to know what sort of protection the Government refer to, and what method would they adopt which will ensure safety and protection on the sides from which trouble is expected. Much danger comes from the desert and trouble comes from different parts which also differ according to the then state of affairs at such ports. As no one can tell what the future would bring, it is necessary to know what measures the Government intend to take then when they grant me such protection# The Government may think tla t the trouble of which I am afraid will come from one side owing to the present state of affairs. It is, however, possible that some change might take place through the revolt of some of the tribesmen. What would the Govern ment then do, if, God forbid, something of this nature takes place. My intention is to find out the policy which the Government would adopt and the measures they intend to take then. Usual Ending.From Political Resident, Bushire. I p 0 Secretary of State for India, London. Repeated Government of India, Simla. Copy by post to Political Agent, Bahrain. Ko.372. Dated the 22nd April 1936 • Result of three days long conversations with 0^ Shaikh of Qatar has been as follows* ^ y ^ With regard to concluding paragraph ot your telegram of 15th April Ko.libs. l^Hes does not anticipate trouble in settling this with Shaikh and to latter I explained that it was for him and the Company to come to an agreement on the number of guards necessary. Shaikh himself drew attention to Article III o± Treaty. 2. With reference to external protection (vide paragraph 3 of my Express Letter No.C-179 of 5th April 1934) Shaikh now asked in .writing (a) whether His Ifejesty's Government would guarantee him protection from invaders of any sort (b) what actual measures His Majesty's Government would adopt. Object of Shaikh's query appeared to be to satisfy himself that in case of necessity His Majesty's Government meant business. \ 3. I replied verbally (a) that guarantee was against all comers but naturally referred to serious incursions not small raids. This the Shaikh /(1) / -2- W Shaikh thought reasonable► (b) That doubtless His Majesty's Government would use aircraft and other suitable means which appeared to impress him# 4. On this point I suggest I be authorised to reply in writing as in 3 (a) and (b) adding in order that assistance if necessary may reach him quickly landing grounds and W/T installation will of course be necessary in his territory as well as collaboration with him in obtaining early information of impending raids. This will cover Royal Air Force intelligence arrangements though I do not think it advisable at this stage specifically to mention Intelligence Officers. .5. With reference to your telegram No.1127 of 8th &amp;pril. Jurisdiction. Shaikh for some time persisted in his previous demand but finally gave me a letter in which he said he would agree to (a) disputes between British subjects British protected subjects and the subjects of non-Moslem Foreign Powers being settled by the Political Agent Bahrain or his representative (b) disputes of British subjects and subjects of non-Moslem Foreign Powers v/ith his own subjects and with the subjects of Moslem Foreign Powers being settled by a Joint Court at Boha on which he and the Political Agent or their representatives would sit provided that His Majesty's Government on their part undertook to (1) recognise his son Hamad as his heir apparent (2) accord himself and Hamad when the latter succeeded him full support in internal matters. 6. With regard to paragraph 6 (b).(B ■' -3- (1) excluded British protected subjects and explained verbally that while he wished subjects of Kuwait Bahrain and Trucial Coast to come under his jurisdiction all other British protected subjects would come under the Joint Court. (2) He added in his letter that with regard to subjects of Moslem Foreign Powers he would not be responsible for any objection which might be raised by their Governments.. 7 (a) Re; 5 (1). Previous recognition of any particular heir of any Shaikh is against policy of Government • (b) Re;5(2). This is objectionable as it would involve us to some extent in internal administration of Qatar and in supporting Shaikh and in his turn Hamad in any mal administration which they might see fit to carry out and for which we would bear the responsibility and odium. This clause has undoubtedly been inserted by Hamad who xs most unpopular in Qatar. (c) Re:6(1).1 do not think that we can meet Shaikh on this point as inter alia effect would be bad on the other Arab Rulers whose subjects were concerned. I imagine that main reason for this exclusion on the part of Shaikh is to avoid his subjects being sued for debt in the Doha Joint Court by subjects of other Arab Rulers expedaily Bahrain. 8. I suggest that I be authorised to write a letter to the Shaikh to the following effect: (a) /(a) that His Majesty's Government agree to a Joint Court at Doha but that as the Shaikh will realise we cannot discriminate between our protected subjects on Arab Coast and others and all such subjects must come under :(rV c t the jurisdiction of the Joint Court- (b) that recognition of Hamad cannot be given as such is against the general policy of Governments (c) that His Majesty^ Government cannot accord general support in internal matters since this would involve an undesirable measure of interference in his administration# His Majesty's Government however are prepared to support Shaikh and his successors in any difficulties arising from the presence of the Oil Company. (This is on the analogy of but is more U 0 comprehensive than the Letter of Assurance resaerodrome to Shaikh of Sharjah dated 22nd July 1932. I made this suggestion to Shaikh verbally but in his letter he asked for full support). 9 # Letter as welles Political Agreement between His Majesty's Government and Company would be taken by me personally to Shaikh for any necessary explanations. 10. Shaikh's attitude was friendly and undoubtedly policy of postponing these controversial political questions until now when Shaikh has immediate prospect of benefitting by increased financial terms of Company has been the correct « one 11. lilies who has conducted the difficult commercial negotiations with much skill patience and tact hopes to conclude them successfully in a few days. Should this occur, and should the political questions not be settled by May 4th date /date on which the Company's option expires, the ad r .of«rendum letters between Kylles and the Shaikh should keep the field clear from advances from other competitors. To peVp sure however I propose telegraphing to Political Agent Bahrain to vrite to Shaikh in this sense as soon as I hear that the Commercial Agreement has been initialled. 12. Copies of letters exchanged with Shaikh are being sent by post. If -Resident Cafa ox^i /&amp;f-6 ■ /ti, teGOVERNMENT OF INDIA; D kpabtmbn*; EXPRESS LETTER B,-—This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, se$$hy post I# save idegravhie expense and undue use of the wires, hd intended to he treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had hem ielegr&amp;phed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed us if U J um - been- so despatched,] fjoM - political Resident, Bushire • 0 - Secretary of State for India, London# Repeated - Government of Inaia, Simla, &amp; political Agent, Bahrain, h 301.S of 1936. fiotof 23rd April $$$ 6. 4 Hp .'V ; J ! Subject ; QATAR OIL* ^ Reference paragraph 12 of my telegram Ko •372, dated the 22nd April 1936. ^ i f jf^ P iPf I y' s 2. Copies of my letters Nos.C/109, C/110 and C/114, dated the 17th, 17th and 18th April 1936 respectively and of translations of | the shaikh of Qatar^ replies Nos.6/64, 7/64 ^ad 8/64, dated the 18th April 1936, are enclosed. ^ ^ J ' - . . 11\ h . 1 3* I should explain that while paragraph 4 of the Shaikh^ letter Mo.7/64, d- ted the 18th April i -936, does not specially state that the support asked for is in regard to internal matters the Shaikn made this clear to me in the course oi our conversations. sd. T#C.Fowle, |testea. Lieut • -Colone 1. ' * Political Resident in the Persian Jc aaU '- Resident in the Persian Gulf*Confidential D.O. No.C-92. POLITICAL AGENCY, KUWAIT. The 8th. April 1935. Just a line to let you know that Holmes In conver sation with me, yesterday, mentioned that he had it on very good authority that ,1 Miller ,, of the Standard Oil Company in Hassa, was making all preparations to have a go at Q,atar as soon as tile I.P.O. time limit (May 10th) expired. 2. If Holmes is not Inventing, this means that he will carry out his threat (made to you personally here if you _ ir .. . . ' /vAvrX. remember) of following rpad on the heels of the Standard Oil, if and when they show their hand. 3. Who, Holmes will represent^ then, I have not been able to discover yet, hut from hints which he occasionally lets drop, it would seem to he a British concern. 4. I wired you of the mysterious telegram which I got from Philby saying that he was due in Kuwait about 7th April - Today (8th April) he has not yet put in an appearance - The Shaikh naturally thinks he is coming to give support to the Saudi Commissioners and am inclined to think so too. There is just the possibility however, that he my be coming in connection with a Neutral Zone Oil concession: There are strange rumours that he has lately mixed himself up with the Standard ll The Hon'ble Lieut-Colonel T.C. Fowle, 0.3.a.. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, B U SHIRE. S2 Oil Company of California and is now one of their men. This is in the nature of a confidential^tip' only, so far. 5. You may rely on me to watch Philby if he turns up. 'Telegram XX. Political Resident, Bushire# TQ Secretary of state for India, London# S9W &gt;7 P 0S ,V Government of India, Foreign and Political Department, iyrg Simla# Political Agent, Kuwait. Political Agent, Bahrain# Bb. 383 Dated 23rd 4pril 193&amp;# My telegram of E3rd April, s&amp;# mz I^ragraph 11 and paragraph. 3 of my BxpresB Letter C^BS of 8th March. ^ -'U .i- 1^1 ~ ^okson writes that Holmes in course of conversation mentioned that he had it on good author. Miller of Standard Oil CompaJ^y, Hasa&gt; was making all preparations to approach Shaikh of &lt;j^,tar as soon as Anglo-Persian Oil Company option expired# Resident# (Copy forwarded to Govt .of India, P.A.Kuwait and P # A Bahrain under P.L.No.310-S of 23/4/359*v, ¥ m H.v Air INDIA OPPICE, LONDON, 3.W. 1. p.2.2368/35. j BI 'S U !RE residency^ /Wt/yss : ; 5tii April 1935. 'cG;JFiO^TiAL P.ECORPS My dear Powle, I write with reference to correspondemfe ending with the Secretary of State's telegraja No.1075 of 3rd April ahout the Qp.tar Oil Agreement to enclose U l,^uril 1 WTI'KMfn v'ai.-&gt; rrt■•&lt;■■■ copy of an extract from a letter from starling to Walton on the question of the national composition of the Iraq Petroleum Company arising out of the coranents on this point contained in paragraph 7(ti) of your express letter No. C-SS of 8th March 1935. Yours $incerely, ^ ^ ai leHon'ble Lt.Gol. t. G . Fowls,, G.B.E., Bushire. W uExtract from letter from Mr. p.c. Starling, petroleum Department, to Mr. j .c. miton, India office, dated 1st April 1935. The Resident remarks In paragraph 7(1)) of His express letter of Stii March, tnat the Iraq Petroleum Company is only about one-quarter Britisli. This is not the case, for, in addition to the ilnglo- Fersian shareholding, the Hoyal Dutch-shell holding must 'be taken into account. In the memorandum which I sent to Colonel Fowle in JVMy 1.933 on the position in Arabia and the Persian Gulf, I pointed out that the British shareholding in the Iraq petroleum company actually represents ahout 33f per cent. The Royal Dutch-shell group hold 23f per cent, of the capital in addition to the Anglo-Persian holding. This group works very closely with the Anglo-Persian Oil Company in the Iraq Petroleum Company, and their outlook and policy are so much British that for practical purposes we can almost regard the whole of their share of the capital as British. Further, while at present I agree there does not seem any prospect of the Iraq Petroleum Company allowing the Anglo-Persian and Shell to hold concessions in this area, I do not think we should rule out/ i !2 - out ttte possibility of this difficulty toeing removed in the future, or of some adjustment of the red line being made, which would have the same result.qh- 1 GONFIDEIITIAL all communications to be addressed to the c ompany L -persian OIL COMPANY. LIMITED, london and ABADAN, &gt;' ^rr &gt; ^ •j J J-si ^ &gt; ^ T elegraphic 'ANGLOPERS ; A ddress i .. ™ RS ' .) 4.AV' ABADAN, PERSIAN GULF. PATED gt T l7 AP^It 1935. il The Hon ! ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, The Residency, B U S H I R K. Sir, QATR CONC ESSION NEGOTIATIONS . We have the honour to forward herewith, for your information and record, a re-draft dated the 29th March 1935 of the Concession which we a3-e endeavouring to negotiate with the Sheikh of Qatr. \ IV^ f \ Subsequent to the despatch to you of our letter GM/1677 of the 17th March it was decided that Mr. My lies should proceed to London by the Imperial Airways 1 machine leaving Basrah on the 21st March to enable him to discuss with our London Principals, and also with the India Office, the various points on which agreement had not previously been reached in his nego tiations with the Sheikh. The enclosed re-draft is the outcome of* his visit. * He returned by the air mail which reached Basrah on the 6th instant and proceeded direct to Bahrein en route to Qatr and is due to arrive at his destination today. We will advise you of the result of his negotiations in due course. We have the honour to be, Sir, Your obedient servants. For ANGLO-IRANIAN OIL COMPANY, LTD., — 1 Enclosure. GENERAL MANAGER.QATR This Agreement was made on the day L 195 &gt; corresponding to the L between His Excellency Shaikh Abdullah bin Qasim al-Thani^ juler of Qatr^ (who is hereinafter called 'the Shaikh', and this expression, whenever the contract requires shall include his [successors and assigns), on the one part, and Charles Clark Mylles, on behalf of the Anglo-Persian Oil Co .Ltd. (which will hereinafter Lcalled as the 'Company'^ and this expression shall, whenever it [is required by the contract, include its assigns), on the other part. Agreement is hereby concluded between the Shaikh and the Company as follows s- I jrticle First. The Shaikh grants to the Company, in virtue of this Agreement, and under the following conditions, the sole right, throughout the principality of Qatr, to explore, to prospect, to pill for and to extract and to ship and to export and the right to refine and sell petroleum and natural gases, ozokerite, asphalt and jeverything which is extracted therefrom, which shall hereinafter be [called 'the substances'. If the Company discovers, in the course of its investigation and general activities, any minerals other than the substances mentioned in the first article, e.g. gold or iron oxide or any other minerals, it shall not be justified to appropriate the same, but must inform the Shaikh of their discovery^ and the [Shaikh shall have full right to, ...and absolute control over, those pierals which have been extracted^ and he shall be free in granting concessions for the extracting of those minerals to any Company or Companies or to dispose of those minerals in any manner he considers to be consistent to his interests. p jcle Second „ Subject to the conditions of Article 7^ below, the tapany can operate in any part of the State of Qatr as is defined plow, but it will not operate on places such as religious lands, Neteries, lands occupied by religious buildings or by essential pterprise by their owners as may exist on the date of the signature| 0 f this Agreement or any customary extensions of such religious lands, or cemeteries or buildings as may be pointed out by the gjjaikh. The State of Qatr means the whole area over which the Shaikh rules and which is marked on the north of the line drawn on map attached to this Agreement. The period of this Agreement shall be seventy five years I from the date of its signature o Third. The Company shall explore the State of Qatr jminutely by any methods which is the best in its opinion to enable it to ascertain the probable existence of the substances. And for the purpose of carrying out its works in accordance ffith this Agreement, the Company shall employ all customary and proper means and shall carry out the examination by methods agreeable to the modern Scientific Knowledge. The Company shall inform H.E. the Shaikh of all its operations in this connection from time to time. The Company undertakes to keep drawings and maps and accurate records of the wells drilled and such like data, whether they be topographical, geological or drilling, as it is customary to keep; and such information as these shall be open to inspection by the Shaikh or by his authorized representative, irticle Fourth. In consideration of the rights granted by the Shaikh to the Company in accordance with this Agreement the Company shall make the following payments to the Shaikh during the currency of the Agreement i ^ (b) | (0) (d) On the date of signature Rs On each of the first four anniversaries of the date of signature Rs On the fifth and each subsequent anniversary of the date of signature until the Company declares it has found oil in commercial quantity Rs Thereafter the Company shall pay royalty on the Substances as follows2 (1) On all substances won and saved other than asphalt, ozokerite and natural gases per ton (2240 English pounds) at the rate of Rs^(2) On asphalt and ozokerite won and saved per ton (2240 English pounds) at the rate of Rs. (5) On natural gas produced and sold per 1000 cubic feet at the rate of Rs. or a sum of RSo.o. ... p.a, whichever shall be the greater. But no royalty shall be payable on any substances used »ithin the State of Qatr by the Company or its employees or on any water or foreign matter extracted with the oil, In consideration of the exemption from taxes, dues and duties as provided for in Article 10 and the right to re-export material which had been previously imported as is provided for in Articles 10 and 13, the Company shall make the following payments (1) On each anniversary of the date of signature and until the Company declares it has found oil in commercial quantity Rs. (2) On each anniversary of the date of signature and after the Company declares it has found oil in commercial quantity Rs. Article Fifth. The Company will measure all liquid matters, at the time of their extraction from wells, either by dipping reservoirs or by means of measuring instruments, and measure solid substances by weighing; and it should supply the Shaikh with a copy of the register if His Excellency so demand. Likewise, the Company shall submit to His Excellency the Shaikh an account of the substances extracted by it for every six months and the authorized agent of the Shaikh shall have the right of inspection thereof at all reasonable times. Article Sixth,, The Company may construct, maintain and operate roads and telegraph and telephone installations and their lines and wireless stations, railways, refineries and the ordinary ports situated at Dohah for importing its materials, and pipe-lines and Piping stations, workshops, houses and other things and works which ar e useful for it, as required for the purposes of its operations, also the accommodations required for its employees, but excepting th e places occupied by the enterprise of their owners, or thoseI Lioh it difficult for their owners to part with; and these are exempted. And the Company has the right to choose the port L c h may be suitable for exporting its substances; and it will Uewise have the right to use all the means of transport required for its operations in accordance with this Agreement^ excepting aerial transport^ which^ on every occasion arising for it, the Company must obtain the Shaikh's permission and consent thereto* Ind His Excellency the Shaikh shall have the full right to use those roads, the electric (telegraph) lines, the wireless installations, telephones, and railways for his personal business and for governmental purposes, in case of need, free of charge; and the Ishaikh shall have the right, also, to use all the ports used and constructed by the Company; and the Company undertakes to afford H.E. the Shaikh all facilities in this respect. Article Seventh. The Shaikh grants to the Company the use and occupation of uncultivated lands belonging to the Shaikh himself and which the Company may require for its operations, free, after an understanding is arrived at between the Shaikh and the Company about them, excepting the lands surrounding Riyan, as will be defined by the Shaikh himself. The Company has no right to acquire lands occupied by the enterprise of the owners thereof and also houses, places and lands which their owners decline to sell or to rent; and excepting these, it does not matter to use (other lands) if occasion arose. And the Company shall inform the Shaikh from time to time of the lands, houses and buildings which it requires to occupy for its enterprise. And the lands, houses and buildings already acquired by the Company and found by it to be unnecessary f or it any longer for its business, shall be restored by the Company to the Shaikh free. Provided that all the lands, houses and buildings fich have been acquired by the Company shall be handed over to the ^aikh free on the termination or prior to that, on the cancellation, free, jfetic le Eighth.. The Company may take any quantity of water which p may require for its operations, free of charge, on the conditionpi this will not cause any loss or damage to any of the inhabitants Ud subject to the same conditions as have been specified, the Company can explore, drill and impound water to satisfy the requirements of its operations. In case of need, the Shaikhs army or military expeditions can take, free of charge, any quantity of water available under the Company 's control, after its requirements are satisfied; and, like- f isej the inhabitants can take such surplus water for themselves and {heir animals, free of charge. j rt.inle Ninth. The Company can take any earth, mud, gravels, lime, gypsum and stones and other similar substances which it requires for its operations, free of charge, but it will not prevent the people from taking their customary requirements of these materials. The Company, however, must only take what it requires; and shall have no right to export any of these (materials) abroad. irticle Tenth. In consideration of the sums agreed upon in the fourth Article, the Company shall have the right to import water, netroleum, fuel, machinery, motor-cars, lorries, aeroplanes, equipments, instruments, wood, utensils, iron ware, building iaterials, medicines, office equipments, household furniture, and all 'other things, equipments and goods required by the Company or by its employees for its operations; but not for sale to others; and it shall have the right to export its substances and their derivatives things already imported by the Company without Customs duty or ^port duty or export duty or tax or any other duty. The Company s ^ll, however, pay the ordinary duty applicable to British merchants to the state of Qatr on all the personal effects, piece-goods, laeral merchandise and provisions which it imports for the personal f Se its employees. And the Company and its operations, incomes, P r ofits and properties shall be exempt and free, during the period this Agreement, from all the present and future taxes of any kind 'hat soever. tocl e.. Eleventh. The Shaikh agrees that he will afford the necessary distance to carry out this Agreement, and that he will use hisjuthority to protect the Company's employees and property as far as possible. But the Company shall also, itself, take the necessary ste p S in this respect, namely that the Shaikh or his representative fill appoint armed guards of his own choice and the Company shall pay the expenses; and the guards should be sufficient in number and equipment. And neither does the Shaikh guarantee to the Company that may be caused by unforeseen circumstances, nor will he be responsible therefor. For instance should, God forbid, an attack itemade by an enemy or any accident occurs in spite of him, through any aggressor, the Shaikh shall, in case of such aggression, use bis endeavour to ward off an aggression of this nature| but he shall jot be responsible for any loss or damage thereby caused. jrticle Twelfth. The Company has the right to transfer this igreement to any other commercial Company; but it shall have no right to transfer it to any Government whatsoever on the conditions that the said Company shall be able to fulfil the obligations of this igreement and its engagements entirely. The Company shall inform the Shaikh if it transferred this Agreement in the manner aforesaid and obtain his assent and acquiescence. And the Company shall have the liberty to form a single Company, if it finds it necessary, to carry out this Agreement, and the aforesaid Company shall enjoy all the rights and privileges granted to the Company in virtue of this igreement, and it must bear all the engagements and responsibilities set forth therein. kticle Thirteenth. The Company may terminate this Agreement if it finds it disagreeable for it to act upon the same; but it shall have f right to cancel it or to abandon it and to discontinue operating p except after three years with effect from the beginning of deration, by giving six months 1 previous notice, in writing, to the Shaikh of its intention to do so. And if the said cancellation should take place within thirty five years from the date of signature of this Agreement, all the lands granted by the Shaikh and any lands 0r Gildings purchased by the Company and any houses or buildings instructed by, and any immovable properties belonging to, the Company( ithin the State of Qatr shall be surrendered to the Shaikh free of Lrgg* we ^ s ac 'tually producing at the time of the said i ^cellation s h a ll he surrendered in a condition considered to he Lod and satisfactory, as they were at that time. And if the said cancellation should take place after thirty |fi V e years from the date of signature of this Agreement, all the Company 's properties within the State of Qatr shall be surrendered, in that case, to the Shaikh, free of charge^ and the wells actually Loducing at the time of the said cancellation shall be surrendered in a condition which is reasonably considered good and satisfactory, as they were at that time. On the termination of this Agreement at the conclusion of the seventy five years, stipulated for in the second article, or the conclusion of any extension or renewal of its period all the Company' properties existing in the State of Qatr shall be surrendered to the Shaikh free of charge^ and the wells actually producing at that time shall be surrendered in a condition which is reasonably considered good and satisfactory, as they used to be at that time. irticle Fourteenth. The Shaikh has the right to cancel this igreement in the two cases mentioned below;- (A) If the Company fails to pay the sums mentioned in the fourth article within six months from the date they fall due. Provided that if any dispute should be made by the Company in regard to any payment thereof, the Shaikh shall not cancel the Agreement until arbitration takes place thereon in accordance with article sixteenth and unless the Company fails to comply with the award of the arbitrators within three months from the date of the said award. (B) If the Company is in default according to the provisions for arbitration set forth in the sixteenth article. I fcticle Fifteenth, The Shaikh shall not hold the Company liable if default should occur on the part of the Company in carrying out or billing the provisions of the Agreement by the mere occurence of f orce majeure delaying operation; but should any difference occur between His Excellency the Shaikh and the Company as to the existence or non-existence of such force majeure, the same shall ber eferred to arbitration^ as provided for in the sixteenth article. JL the Shaikh stipulates that the force majeure delaying operation jeans that which occurs in connection with the Company's operations L Qatr and that nothing else must 'be taken into consideration and Lst not be used by the C.ompany as an argument in this respect. And the Company shall proceed to effect repairs at the time when any Lnage, of any nature, takes place; and the period of the said delay, jtogether with any period reasonably necessary for repairing the Ijamage will be added to the period fixed in accordance with this preement. [ irticle Sixteenth. Should any dispute occur between the Shaikh and jthe Company in regard to the interpretation of this Agreement or of any matter arising therefrom or in regard to the engagements obligatory on either of the parties in accordance therewith, such iispute shall be referred to two arbitrators if no Agreement can be arrived at for settling it by any other method, and the Shaikh will appoint one of them and the other will be appointed by the Company, kh of the two parties shall appoint his arbitrator within thirty lays after receiving the demand therefor from the other party. The tiff arbitrators shall thereupon appoint a third arbitrator; but if the two arbitrators or any two arbitrators appointed instead of them |are unable to agree upon the third arbitrator within sixty days from the demand for arbitration, the two parties agree that, in that case, the third arbitrator should be appointed by the Political Resident; a nd the Shaikh makes it a condition that he should agree to the jthird arbitrator. The award of arbitration shall be consistent with the legal pinciples familiar to civilized nations. The decision of the majority of arbitrators shall be final; IP the place of arbitration shall be Qatr. On giving any award, the arbitrators shall fix a sufficient time within which the party against whom the award is given, should Car ry out the said award. And that party shall be considered at Nt only when he fails to comply with the award before the expiry11 *lofthe aforesaid period and not otherwise. Seventeenth. The labourers employed by the Company must be L r oin Shaikh's own subjects or from amongst those approved Uthe Shaikh, excepting technical employees and the managers and Lierks whom the Company may require and whom it cannot find in the Lountry. And the Shaikh prescribes as a condition the dismissal of jjny employed whose retention is disapproved by the Shaikh, if the jShaikh has observed any irregular conduct on his part. And it naturally follows that the wages which the Company pays to the I employees from amongst Qatr people shall be reasonable. (rticle Eighteenth. The Shaikh and the Company declare that they lase action upon this Agreement on the basis of good faith and pure belief and upon the interpretation of this Agreement in a manner consistent with reason. And the Company undertakes to acknowledge the Shaikh's authority and his rights in his capacity as the Ruler of the State of Qatr principality and to respect them in every lanner» trticle Nineteenth. Nothing contained in this Agreement shall prevent the Shaikh in any manner whatsoever from granting concessions toother parties for anything excepting the substances mentioned in the first article provided that the said concessions do not interfere fith the rights of the Company or its operations in accordance with this Agreement. jrticle Twentietho The Company will pay all the sums due to the Shaikh, in accordance with this Agreement, into the Shaikh's account p the Bank in and the receipt taken from that Bank shall be a full quittance of the Company's liability f.or the sum mentioned in the Bank's receipt. The Shaikh may, from time to time, appoint another pk or other Banks for the purposes of this Article, and this shall 16 done in writing. fei£l e_ Twentv-Flrst „ This Agreement shall be binding upon both the ? ar ties and their successors and assigns| and it has been written in pbic and English and all due care has been taken to make the twojgxts identical in meaning. And if any difference should arise as l[o the meaning or the interpretation of any article, at any time, ^ Arabic version is to be relied upon. I ^le Twenty-Second. The expression year, month and day used in Lis Agreement shall mean what is consistent with the English Solar Calendar and not any other, IN WITNESS whereof the two parties have hereunto set their jands and seals on the day and in the year mentioned in the preamble. Shaikh of Qatr.2U39/35 BRITANNIC HOUSE PINSBURY CIRCUS LONDON. B.C.2 5th April, 1935 J. Q* Laithwaite, Esq., C.I.E., India Office, S. W. 1. Dear Laithwaite Qatr. I enclose 6 copies of a draft dated 29th March 1935 which Mylles took out with him. The top copy I have had marked in pencil to show any variations from the original text as circulated of Mirza Mohammed^ translation of the Shaikh f s draft, which we discussed with you on the 28th March* Article U has been inserted into this draft in the form of the draft which I left with you on the 28th, In Article 11 the words 'for this and the cost of their arms' have been deleted at Mr. Fraser f s wish; the deletion is one of form rather than substance, since if we require 'armed guards' we do not expect to obtain them at the ordinary rate of wages to labourers - equally we do not propose to pay for a small army at the Shaikh T s sole discretion# In Article 18 we have deleted, in accordance with your wishes, the provision as to trial of 'foreign employees' of the Company in the Shara courts, but otherwise the .changes are I think in every case purely verbal. Yours sincerely. L. LEPROY.f? By Air Mail. $ 'iESIDENCY. I Date. resoros 9 INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, // Forwarded vvitli the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy has been sent to -a-4-i by AE M ail. . c; •fll^ Omj-ntriryj rrriYrriimi nt ul Imlui. The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. 3057INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALLs 3.W. 1. P.Z. 2457/35. 9th April 1935. Dear Lefroy, I write to acknowledge with many thanks your letter of the St&amp;'April ana the enclosed copies of the modified draft dated 29th Kkrch taken out to Qatar dy fcylles. 2. We suggested to the Hesiaent that it might de well defore your option expires to indicate to the Shsikh that his interests woula dest de served dy granting the concession to a concern who was well- qualified to work it, and from a telegram just received we understand that he has discussed the question with Mylles and that he has agreed that the dest procedure would de that a letter should de despatched from the Resident to the sheikh once IMyiles Intimates dy wireless from cgitar that the moment for delivery has arrived. Yours sincerely, J »G. LAIIHWAITE. Lefroy, Esq., Anglo-J?ersian Oil Co.Lta., Britannic House, Pinsdury Circus, E.G. 2.f Telegram xx From Political Resident, Bushire To Political Agent, Bahrain. No ♦387. Dated the 24th April 1936. Please prepare draft Arabic translation of Qatar Political Agreement vide India Office Printed Letter No. 1786/1803 dated 16th March 1934. You will find suitable Arabic expressions for technical terms in Bahrain Oil Concession and connected documents. 2. Reference Clause 9 and Schedule to Clause 10 see India Office telegram No.640 dated 28th February 1936 (copy by air mail direct to you) and my Printed Letter No. 264-S of 2nd March 1936. 1,1 ■' ■GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. ^1*1 Department. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). rvg,—This is an ORIGINAL message sent hy AIR MAIL which, provides a means of communication more expeditions than the ordinary mail and is cheaper tfaan the telegraph. It is intended tb be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it hadht^i telegraphed. To save time and to chviate formaliiies it u drafted in the form of a telegrim. i gt is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer o f the Department^ No. 322-3 Of 1936.^1*^.^ xxxxxx 26th april W 36. From To Repeated Reference xxxxxxxim Political Resident, Bushire. Secretary of State for India, London. Government of India, Simla. political Agent, Bahrain. ,with a request that the Arabic version of the enclosures may be checked♦ /ii jcl Subject ; Qatar Oil. Reference correspondence ending with my telegram No.372, dated the 22nd April 1936. I enclose herewith drafts of the letters proposed to be exchanged (with reference to the Agreement between His Majesty's Government and the Anglo -Per s iun Oil Company) with the Shaikh of Qatar in the event of the Commercial ✓ Agreement being signed by him and approved by His Majesty's 2jt&gt; Government. !Ehey are based on the Kuwait model# 2. It will be noticed that in the draft reply from the Shaikh no mention has been made of the non-attachment of these letters to the agreement, and of their non-publication. This was inserted in the Kuwait correspondence at the special request of the Shaikh. The Shaikh of ^atar has made no such request. Should the Shaikh of Qatiir make a similar request, and should His Majesty's Government have no objection, a suitable paragraph will be added to the (Signature) Shaikh 1 s / {Designation)Shaikh's reply. 3. I would be grateful for a telegraphic reply as to whether His Majesty's tiovernment (a) approve of the proposed texts of the lettersj and (b) have any objection to the inclusion in the Shaikh's reply of the additional paragraph referred to in paragraph 2 above, should the Shaikh make a request to that effect. 4. Should any other points involving alterations of substance arise in the course of conversations with the Shaikh, they will be referred to you by telegram. sd. T.C.Fowle, Lieut.-Colonel, political Hesident in the Persian Gulf. Attested for Secretary to the Political Hesident in the Persian Guli •Telegrain xx From s Secretary of State for India, London. To Political Resident, Buahire, No. 1304 Repeated to Government of India, Foreign and Political Department, Simla, No. 1305 Political Agent, Bahrain, No. 1306 Bated 26th received 27th April 1935. IMPORTANT. Your telegram of the 22nd April, No. 372 and Government of India's telegram of April 25th, So. 1059. QATAR OIL. 2. His Majesty's Government approve of proposals in paragraph 4 of your telegram with modification that for serious incursions n they would substitute w serious - and unprovoked attacks 11 . They assume however, that Shiakh fully realises (c.f. my telegram of March 2ncf, 1934 lo. 582) that they will expect him to take all reasonable steps for his own defence and for maintaining order within his own borders, a point to which they attach much import ance. 3. It is the case that our normal practice is not to grant recognition and His Majesty's Government would prefer maintaining this policy. On the other hand there have been exceptions (e.g. the present Shaikh of Bahrain was recognised as heir apparent in 1901). If, however, recognition of Hamad as heir apparent is essential to clinch matters, His Majesty's Government, subject to any furt herfurther views of Government of India, would be prepared to consider granting recognition as special case. (sine qua non of their recognition of any new Shaikhs would of course be full acceptance by him of obligations of ^atar Treaty of 1916, which there would be advantages if possible in converting into an M Heirs and Successors'* Treaty). Unusual nature of concession which this would represent, particularly in view of Hamad*s unpopularity, might be employed not only to clinch oil question but to rem difficulties over Jurisdiction, intelligence officers, etc. . i 4. Jurisdiction. His M ajesty*s Government agree that you should take line proposed in paragraph 8 of your telegram. You might also make play with objection taken by ^atar in 1920 to his own subjects falling under Bahraini jurisdiction (see P.G. 13 page 63, paragraph 10). They # are advised however that there is no strict construction 6f 'British protected persons 1 * and to that extent our hands are free. Nor is there event at the present time uniformity of practice in dealing with these matters in the Gulf, Jurisdiction exercised in Bahrain by His Majesty*s Government extends to subjects of moslems of foreign states including Gulf States as well as to other foreigners. In Kuwait on the other hand jurisdiction over subjects of mo siem foreign states including Gulf States vests in Shaikh. If for any reason it was thought desirable to concede this point in Qatar there are thus good precedents. / , _ 1 \y\ 5. Subject to remarks in paragraphs 3 and 4 above. His jesty*s Government approve of action proposed in paragraph 8 of your telegram under reply and agree that you should present letter personally.- 3 - 6» They are prepared to leave ti^i table to you but think it important to secure necessary assurances from Shaikh if possible before signature of oil agreement and in any event with minimum delay thereafter They feel strongly that our position wogild be much weaker in dealing with advances from other parties once Company^ option has expired. - SECRETARY OF STATE FOR IHDIA.82/27 TelagraiD R# 27 From Political Resident, Buahire To H#M , b Vice-Consul, Mohamraerah HO. 403 Dated 27th April 1935# Following for General Manager, An&amp;Lo-lranian Oil Company, Begins. Please telegraph latest news regarding Mylles' negotiations at Qatar* Ends. BRITC0H3UL -w1 ■ Telegram R.27» From H.M. *8 Vice Consul, Mohammerah♦ To Political Resident, Bushire. No .1200/28. Dated 28th (received 29th) April 1935• jft Referring to your telegram No.403. O Following from Anglo-Persian Oil Company begins: Our latest information indicates that Mylies and Shaikh likely to agree very shortly on points outs tand ing. Ends«. -Britconsul. f ^82/27 telegram xx From Political Agent, Bahrain To Political Resident, Bushire Ho. 70. Dated and received 29th April 1935• 10 Your telegram of April 25rd, No. 383. Miller said same to me on evening of April 8th, Mylles was present as far as I can remember» - POLITICAL - y82/27 Telegram xx From Political ^gent, Bahrain To Political resident, Bushire. Repeated to H.M*s Secretary of State for India, London. / Government of India, Foreign and Political department, Simla„ Ko. 72. Bated 29th received 30th April 1935. following from M$lles begins 0 Agreement reached date of signature not fixed* • POLITICAL - Ends.i 33/51 and 8^/27 Te le gram From To Repeated to 23b. 411 Dated 3Cth April 1935• Political Resident, Bushire# Senior Officer, Persian Gulf, H.M.S. Bideford, Bushireradio* Political Agent, Bahrain# tinder instructions from His Maje3tiy f s Government I have to visit IJatar# I reach Bahrain next slow mail and would be grateful if sloop could take me thence to Qatar P.M. 7 th May and bring me back to Bahr&amp;in. Probable stay at Qatar four dgys. Resident#82/27 Telegram R»27. From Political Resident, Bushire. To Political Agent, Bahrain* No.412. Dated the 30th April 1936. A z 4 My telegram of to-day No .411.. In order that Shaikh should have time to under stand Political Agreement(see my telegraan No»387 of 24th April) Abdur Razzaq should proceed to Qatar some days previously to explain it to Shaikh. I will wire when he should leave. 2. Your telegram No.72. Please telegraph immediately you hear that Agreement has been signed. -Resident.Telegram 'From To Repeated to 8^/27 xx» Political Resident, Bushire* H.M , s Secretary of State for India, London. Government of Iniia, Poreigta and Political Dgpartment, Simla. Ho* 413 Dated SOtli April 1935 /&lt;?? Your telegram of 26th April, Ho. 1304• I presume that Government of India are replying to your paragraph 3. 2. I propose leaving here for Qatar on 4th .Mayvl• In this connection please see paragraph 3 of my Express Letter Uo* 322-S of 25th April sent by air mail viiich should reach you on 2nd May # h Resident# (copr^ sent to Bahrain under p »L»No.368-S of 30/4/36.) JTelegram xx From To Political Resident, Bushire» Secretary of State for India, London Copy by post to Government of India, Simla « » t» » Political Agent, Bahrain,. No•415• Dated the 30th April 1936* Your telegram of 26th April No* 1304, paragraph 6 I understand that my letter to the Shaikh can be as followss (a) if necessary grant Shaikh^ request re: British protected subjects vide paragraph 6 (1) of my telegram of 22nd April No•372. (b) If necessary recognise Hamad as successor (subject to the views of Government of India) provided that he accepts in full obligations of Treaty of 1916 • (c) Promise internal support as in paragraph 8 (c) of my telegram quoted above* 2» I would of course make only such of the abcwe concessions as are unavoidable and will make as much play with them as possible• 3* I will take any opportunity that offers of converting Treaty into an 'heirs and successors' one provided it is not likely to delay achievement of immediate object i.e. Oil Concession. Please confirm - Resident. rovt .of India and Bahrain under (COpy ftE^No?358-S of 30/4/35.)ft&amp;J OONFIPENTIAL . No. 368-S of 1936. The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Grulf presents his com pliments to /I iic* 1. The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, Simla. 2. The Political Agent, Bahrain. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment (s). British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. 5^ ' Dated ... .30th, April.. ,19.3.5.., Reference to previous correspondence : *4, ft ^ &amp;r, Description of Enclosure, v Name and Date. ( 1. Political Resident's telegram ( No.403 of 27th April 1936 fo ( H.M.'s Vice Consul,Mohammerah. ( 2. H.M.'s Vice Consul,liiohainmerah's ( telegram No.1200/28 of 28th ( April 1935. ? ( 3. Political Resident's telegram ( No.413 of 30th April 1935. ( 4. Political Resident's telegram ( No.414 of 30th April 1935, to ( H.M.'s Vice Consul,Mohammerah. 5. Political Resident's telegram No.415 of 30th April 1935. Subject. £ rt yd Qatar Oil.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x00025d_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/631</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x00025d</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/631</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 82/27 VI (F 87) Qatar Oil'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1935/1935</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-05-16T00:09:24</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (221 folios)</extent><extent>The documents in the volume are mostly arranged in chronological order. There are notes at the end of the volume, (folios 210-214). The file notes are arranged chronologically and refer to documents within the file; they give a brief description of the correspondence with reference numbers in red crayon, which refer back to that correspondence in the volume.There is also a brief index at the beginning (f. 1v) indicating the main topics covered in the volume.</extent><extent>The main foliation is written in pencil, circled, and can be found in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. The numbering commences at the title page with 1 and 1A; then 2-21; 22 and 22A; 23-25; 26 is missing or omitted; 27-65; 66 and 66A; 67-127; 128, 128A and 128B and terminates at the last folio with 217. A second incomplete foliation sequence is present between ff. 29-160; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled, and can be found in the same position as the main sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The volume contains correspondence and telegrams between the Political Agent at Bahrain and the Political Resident at Bushire, the Government of India, the India Office in London and Anglo-Persian Oil Company (APOC) representatives in regard to the negotiations with the Sheikh of Qatar, ‘Abdullāh bin Jāsim Āl Thānī, for the oil concession.The volume contains numerous draft agreements on the Qatar oil concession and also a 'Sketch map of Qatar Peninsula' (folio 22).There are some letters in Arabic, to and from the Sheikh of Qatar.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Agent</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Emir of Qatar</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of India</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x00025d#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>