<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0001b5_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-12T06:04:00.965Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">STATEMENT OP GOLD PURCHASED AND SOLD \ Dil-Qad T2 4 Pcs. Buttons bought from Hassan bin Ali bin Saad. 14 3 Pinger Rings bought from Hamad bin Ali. 1 Arm Ring bought from bint Hamad. Loolu 15 Gold Ornaments used as Wavers on Womans Arab type Veil, bought from Yousuf bin Abdulla. Tola Anna Weight 0 - 7-0 1 - 2-0 3 - 2-0 7-4-0 15 1 Ear Ring bought from Aisha bint Saad. 0-2-0 ) Sold to Pragji Shoemaker ) on Dil-Qad 12th. ) ) Sold to Patma bint Abdulla ) on Dil-Qad 18th. ) ) Sold to Patma bint Abdulla ) on Dil-Qad 18th. ) ) I cleaned this very inferior ) quality gold and only 3-3/4 ) Tolas of pure gold came out. ) Have sold these 3-3/4 Tolas ) to Hanna Goldsmith on Dil-Qad ) 18th. ) Sold to Patma bint Abdulla ) (as mentioned above) on ) Dil-Qad 18th. V V TOTAL : 12-1-0 ALL SOLD AS ABOVE. N.B . Please note that there is no balance outstanding with me till today (December 27th. 1942). dAw65aR' 'EaS'S B. J MANAIAA, BAHREIN.Baiirain, 28tn. Dec ember 1942. To His Britanic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrain. Dear Sir, '* * I beg to inform your honour that I have done no transactions in gold bullion during the week ending 27th.December 1942.Translation of letter dated 28-12-42 froq? Ratooraal Kanayamal, Bahrain to the x Political Agent, Bahrain. • W # I beg to state that during this week I neither purchased nor sold gold. ITranslation of letter dated 28-12-42 from Ibrahim Uonoo, Bahrain to the* Political Agent, Bahrain. A. C. I beg to submit my statement of gold for this week. Tolas Annas. Gold bullion as per my letter of 21/12 292 15 ornaments ' M ' ' ' 36 2 3 purchased from Abdul Latif bin Ahmed of Manama on 22/12 sold to Korjiyeh Salman Shoah of manama on 24/12 on 24/12 purchased from Syed Abdulla bin Khalifa of Hidd on 25/12 Sovereigns as per my letter of 21/12 No purchases Russian gold pounds ” No purchases Turkish gold Liras ' No purchases American gold dollars No purchases Unsigned. 329 1 1 8i 329 9^- 9 . .15 319 ima ioF 15 318 11^ 19 6f . 338 §2s *f5 i j °\ Translation of letter dated 28-12-42 from Badr bayii and Khalid Sadoon to the Political Agent, Bahrain. A-C. I give below mystatement of gold (for this week) In stock Purchases Sales// ^ ./ 4 - Baiir6iin,4ta 0 January 19^3 To, His Britanic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrain. Dear Sir, I beg to inform your honour that I have done no fresh transactions in gold bullions for the week ending 3/I/I943. U'j t Yours ently, ■'X i ; ! Dil-Qad 21 24 24 Bahrein, January 4th. 1943 STATEMENT OF GOLD PURCHASED AND SOLD Tola Anna 1 Finger Ring bought from Hamad bin Abdul Rahman, o _ 5 _ o 5 Shirt Buttons bought from Hamad bin Abdul Rahman. 2 Arm Rings bought from Loolo bint Mshdix Khalifa 2 Ear Rings bought from Ibrahim bin Mehdi. 1-0-0 Various broken ornaments bought from Mr. Mohd Iqbal (Indian)? - 1 - 6 ) ) ) All gold weighing 15-7^/16 ) Tolas of unoleaned gold sold ) to Ibrahim Noonoo on Dil-Qad ) 25th. ) Total : ' 15 -' ?'- N.B . Please note that there is no balance outstanding with me till today (January 3rd. 1943). ki DaMOUaR DA55 w :• Translation of letter dated 4-1-43 from Ibrahim Konoo, Bahrain to the Political Agent, Bahrain. A. C. I beg to submit my statement of gold for this Tolas Gold bullion as per my letter of 28/12 Gold ornaments ' ' ' M ' __ Gobi ornaments purchased from Haji All Qassab of Manama on 29/12 Gold ornaments purchased ffom Syed Yusuf Bahrani of Manama on 29/12 Gold ornaments purchased from Ahmed bin Jasim of Manama on 29/12 Gold ornaments purchased from Ali bin Husain of Kerker on 29/12 Gold ornaments purchased from Ali bin Haji Ansari on 30/12 292 _4_5 338' No purchases Turkish gold Liras ' ' No purchases American gold d.liars” ' No purchases 25 3 week:- Ann as, 15 qA. k 8 11 10 Gold ornaments sold to Salih Elyahoo of 34C 13- Manama on l/l 17 11 323 Gold purchased from Mohd Ali Haji Hasawi of Manama on l/l 10, 323 isf Gold sold to Yaqob Ibrahim Gohin of Manama on 3/1 8 11 •/Gold 315 ii purchased from Damoderdas 3 of Manama on 3/1 15 7-h Gold pur chased from Ahmed Albaba of Manama through Hasham Abdu^i Nabi of Manama on 3/1 /if 1 2 331 ioi Sovereigns as per my letter of 28/12 161 No purchases 23^ Russian gold pounds ” ” ”To, His Britanic Majesty 1 s Political Agent, Banrain. Dear Sir, Bahrain, Ilth.January 1943. u ti. I beg to inform your honour that NO business in gold bullion being transacted by me during the week MfttoigxX ending lOth.Jan. 1943. Yo aith^Ully,I [Z* ^&gt;1 «&gt;* L* ^ 1 &lt;rO) t^V-e-*^ * O /V 1 ^^ Translation of letter dated 11-1-43 from Mohd. Adwani and Mohd al Bakir, Bahrain to the Political Agent, Bahrain. We beg to submit our statement of gold upto this date Purchases Sales In stock Nil Nil Nil. U.E. \* Translation of letter dated 11-1-43 from Badr Sayir and ^ Khalid Sadoon, Bahrain to the Political Agent, Bahrain. A. C. We beg to give our In stock Purchases Sales statement of gold below:- Nil Nil Nil U.E.Dear Sir, &lt; ^ V Bahrain,I8th.January 1943. His Britanic Majesty's Political Agent, BAHRAIN 0 I beg to inform your honour that no fresh transactions in gold bullion took place by me during the week ending I7/I/43 Yours ully,Translation of letter dated 18-1-43 from Ibrahim Nonoo Bahrain to the Political Agent, Bahrain. I beg to submit my statement of gold for this week:- Gold bullion as per my letter of 11/1 Gold ornaments ' ' ' ' ' Gold sold to Yusuf Khalil Moyad of Manama on 12/1 Gold purchased from Salman Sh:Dawod Iraqi of Manama on 13/1 Gold purchased from Hamad bin Yusuf of Manana on 13/1 Gold purchased from Ahmed bin Ahmed al- Khalifa of Manama on 13/1 Gold purchased from Haji Yusuf Bahrani of Manama on 13/1 Gold purchased from Elyahoo Nahoom of Manama on 15/1 Sovereigns as per my letter of ll/l No purchased Russian gold pounds ' No purchases Turkish gold Liras ' No purchases American gold dollars No purchases ' 340 12 3^ 327 3 2 i4i 15 4} 6Abdulaziz Ali bass a in Tele AfW: ABDULAZlZ BASSAM BAHRAIN. jjlxt ^o— m jr^.Uxji : Ol Al» Translation of letter dated 18-1-42 from Abdul Aziz al Ali al Bassam, Bahrain to the Political Agent, Bahrain. A * c * As regards gold. I beg to state that no purchase or sale took place.A Banrain,25ta.January i943. To His Britanic Majesty Bahrain. Bear Sir, f s Political Agent, J I beg to inform your honour tnat I nave done no fresh business in gold bullion transactions during tne week ending 24th.January i943. _ -- —^ --—— 'Tele address: M COHIN BAHRAIN Code Used: BENTLEY 1 S j &lt; Translation of letter dated 25-1-43 from Menashi Ibrahim Cohin, Bahrain to the Political AGent, Bahrain. A. C. I beg to state that the gold in py possession upto this date is as follows:- Sovereigns 110 Turkish Liras 3 Gold ornaments weighing 22 Liras. U.E.STATEMENT OF GOLD PURCHASED AND SOLD Muharram Tola Anna 12 12 14 18 1 - Pair, Ear Rings 2-12- 0 ) bought from ) Hamid bin Saaf ) (servant of ) Shaikh Salman) ) ) 1 - Nose Ornament 0-2-z- 0 ) bought from ) Hassan bin Ali. ) ) Broken Forehead ) Ornaments, ) bought from ) Shamoun Jew. ) ) 1 - Ear Ring 0-12- 0 ) bought from ) Mohd bin Najam. ) All this gold weighing 5-3/8 Tolas was sold to one Mohd Iqbal of Bapoo at 5 p,m. today. N,B . Please note that there is no balance outstanding with me till today (January 25, 1943). There had been no business during the previous week and hence no report was submitted. I hope it was quite in order. DAM0BAR DASS B. MANAMA, BAHREIN.1 v-^uP ) uO^eJ* e^j*^ * jr? s&gt; j^'oj 1 ^ b y^S^ Translation of letter dated 20th Muharran 1362 (25-1-43; from Abdul Aziz al Ali al Bassam, Bahrain to the Political Agent, Bahrain. \ C 'as regards the gold I beg to state that no purchase or sale of gold took place this week.Bahrain,1st.February i943 (~ His Britanic Majesty^ Political Agent, Bahrain. Dear Sir, I beg to inform your honour that I have done no transactions in Fold bullion during th$ week ending 31 st.January 1943. tr o ~ ft Translation of letter dated 1-2-43 from Ibrahim Nonoo, Bahrain to the Political Agent, Bahrain. 15 14i A.C. I beg to submit my statement of gold for this week: Tolas Annas Gold bolluion as per ny letter of 25/1/ 292 Gold ornaments M M ' ' ' ' Gold purchased from Abdulla bin Mohd.bin saif of Muharraq on 26/1 Gold purchased from Abdulla bin Ahmed of Dammam on 27/1 Gold purchased from I.lohd.bin Abdulla of Manama on 29/1 Sovereigns as per my letter of 25/1 ' purchased from Ilaji Adam Nejdi of Manama on 28/1 365 13t 1 7- /a —U_ 368 161 7 168 Turkish gold Liras as per my letter of 25/1 No purchases Russian gold pounds ' M ' ' ' ' No purchases American gold dollars ' ' ' ” M No purchases 25 29i 3Bahrain,8tJi.February ,943 jy o To His Britanic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrain. Dear Sir, I beg to infora your honour that I have done no business in gold bullions during the week ending 7th.Sa February 1943.Translation of letter dated 8-2-43 from Ibrahim Nonoo, Bahrain to the Political Agent, Bahrain. A.C. I beg to submit my gold statement for this week:- Tolas Annas. Gold bullion as per my letter of 1/2 292 15 M ornaments ' M ' ' u ' 7 5 368 9£ Gold bought from Abdulla bin Jasim of Manama on 2/2 3 2 Gold bought from Hasan bin Yusuf 1 of Manama on 2/2 15^ 37210£ Gold sold to Khalil Kano of Manama on 5/2 3 7i 369 3? Gold sold to Tuffaha bint Yaqob of Manana on 7/2 18 lOj 350 9 Gold bought from Oner bin AbdulLatif Eayandi of Manama on 7/2 12^, 351 Si- Sovereigns as per my letter of 1/2 168 No purchases Turkish gold Liras M ' M ' 25 No purchases Russian gold pounds ' ' ' ' 29^ No purchases American gold dollars No purchases 3Tele address: M COHIN BAHRAIN Code Used: BENTLEY’ S Translation of letter dated 15-2-43 from Menashi Ibrahim Cohin, Bahrain to the Political Agent, Bahrain. A.C. One sovereign sold to Abdur Rahman Sayyad and the balance is 1C9 Turkish Liras 3 Gold ornaments weighing 18^; Liras. U.E.% -j To His Britanic Majesty*s Political Agent, Bahrain. Bahrain, i 5th.February ',943 u Dear Sir, I beg to inform your honour that I have done no transactios in gold bullion during the week ending i4th.February i943. Yours .faithfully,His Britanic Majesty 1 s Political Agent, Bahrain. © Dear Sir, I beg to inform your honour that no fresh transactions made by me in gold bullion during the week ending 2 ist.February ,943- Yours/Obediently,If II—I ... - Abdulaziz Ali Bassam . Tele Add: ABDULA.ZIZ BASSAM. BAHRAIN. * ^ ^ 5 .^ 3 - \r W v l ^ * * Ak± Translation of letter dated 22-2-43 from iibdul Aziz al Ali al Bassam, Bahrain, to the Political Agent, Bahrain. A. C. I beg to state that no purchase or sale took place during this week. % U.E.■imin»i.iy|| Baarain,st .Maroii / »943« . 0- To His Britanio Majesty's Political Agent, Bahrain. Dear Sir, I beg to inform your honour that I have done no transactions in gold bullion during the week ending 2Bth.February '1943. Your diently,(Jr ^ b Batirain,8th.March '*943 To His Britanic Maoesty T s Political Agent, Banrain. o Dear Sir, I beg to inform your honour that no fresn transactions in gold bullions were done by me during the week ending 7/3/43-■■ ■ ~ &amp;&gt; bM Baiirain, 15th.Marcn '&lt;943. To His Britanic Majesty*s Political Agent, Bahrain. ’ Q Bear Sir, 1 beg to inform your honour that I have done no fresh transactions in gold bullion during the week ending 4 / 3 / 43 .Bahrain,22nd.Maron '943 To His Britanic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrain. Dear Sir, I beg to inform your honour that I nave done no fresh transactions in gold bullion during the week ending 21/3/&gt;943.To His Britanic Majesty's Political Agent, Bahrain. Dear Sir, I beg to inform your honour tnat I nave done no fresh transactions in gold bullion during the week ending 20/3/43*Tele addrejis : M COHIN BAHRAIN Code Used: BENTLEY’S Translation of letter dated 5-4-43 from Menashi Ibrahim Cohin, Bahrain to the Political Agent, Bahrain. The following gold is in my possession:- Sovereigns Turkish Liras Gold ornaments weighing 9 Liras U.E. /f syy:qt A 7/6 ^ f BASRAH Telegrams ; SAGNON Telephone No. 02-571 P.O. B. No. 2 To Shedmiri Ptnashi §ai)80h 3 Bahrain, , i2th.April j943. His Britanic Majesty*s Political Agent, Bahrain. Sir, I beg to inform your honour that no fresh transactions taken place by me in gold bullion during the week ending 11 / 4 / 1943 . Yours ently, iKlOz-)K /oxf © g) li'f) 4 Translation of letter dated 26th April 1943 from Menashi Ibrahim Cohin, Bahrain to the Political Agent, Bahrain. Upto the 19th instant the following gold was in my possession:- Sovereigns Turkish Liras Ornaments weighing 65 - Liras 106 4 Shipped to Iraq as per licence No.324 106 3 Sovereigns Turkish Liras Ornaments weighing Liras The balance now with me is one Eurkish Lira. U.E.BASRAH ^Telegrams : SAGNON Telephone No. 02-571 P.O. B. No. 2 To ihfiburi papgh : Cil/U ♦Y.oyv r : Ay' Bahrain,3rd.May, 1943. His Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrain . Sir, I beg to inform your Honour that I have done no fresh transaction in gold bullion during the week wnding 2nd. May,1943. Yours# Obediently, * jTranslation of letter dated 17-5-43 from Menashi Ibrahim Cohin, Bahrain to the Political Agent, Bahrain. A.C. The following gold is in my possession:- Sovereigns Turkish Liras 2 3 U.E.\ TrMmslation of lettei ^ated 17-5-43 from Ratoomal Kanayamal, Bahrain to the P.A., Bahrain. — A.c. I beg to state that no purchase or sale of gold took place during this week. U.E.EXPORT OF GOLD &lt;Sc SILVER RUPEE S: Specie: 1 st fortnight in Hay, 1941. Silver Rupees. Rs:l,38,300 : (exported to Pearling Bank) Sovereigns. Rs: NIL Gold(Bnllion)tolas. NIL Silver(Bullion) ' NIL Imports of Indian Currency Notes: 1 st fortnight in Lay. 194-3. : Indian Currency Notes:Rs:8,50 ? 000. Ref. No: PA/SF//’. i 2^ . r - m ^ I'M 1 st fortnight in Lay. 194-2. Rs: 1,00,000. ' NIL. tolas. NIL. NIL e 1 st fortnight in Lay. 1942. Rs:2,01,350, ^2r- Passed on to H. B. P's Political Agent, Bahrain, with reference to his No:C/904—10 of l^th September, 194-1. 7/ &gt; '' f n Dir prior of Customs and fort Officer, '■liir - — BASRAH Telegrams ; SAGNON Telephone No. 02-571 P. O. B. No. 2 ii he tori JP^nashi pajiegh Bahrain,24th.May, i343. H. B. M f s Political Agent, Bahrain . Sir, I beg to inform your Honour that no fresh transactions has been done by me in gold bullion during the week ending 23rd.May,t943. •a] Yours ntly, ■M _BiiSRAH ■* Telegrams ; SAGNON Telephone No. 02-571 P.O. B. No. 2 •Y.oW Bahrain, .4th.June, i943. H # B. M*s Political Agent, Bahrain. Sir, I beg to inform your Honour that no fresh dealing in gold bullions taken place by me during the week ending i3/6/1943.BASRAH Telegrams j SAGNON Telephone No. 02-571 P. O. B. No. 2 'VO (ft) »y.ovv Bahrain, 21st. June, i943. H. B. M*s Political Agent, Bahrain. Sir, I beg to inform your Honour that no fresh transactions in gold bullions were made by me during the week ending 20th.June, 1943.Abduiaziz Ali Bassam Tele AfW: ABDJLAZlZ BASSAM BAHRAIN. \T &lt;L- ^1-aJI &gt; a v—'xtf) | Translation of letter dated 19-7-43 from A.Bassam, Bahrain to P.A., Bahrain. I beg to state that the balance of gold with me at the end of this week is 302 Liras only. ik nttfBASRAH Telegrams ; SAGNON Telephone No. 02-571 P, O, B. No. 2 ihfdBuri Jlpashi Sapgh o •y.ovv jy^ H. B. M ! s Political Agent, Bahrain. Bahrain, 26th. July, 1943. Dear Sir, I beg to inform your honour that no fresh business being done by me in gold bullions during the week ending 25th.July, 1943 •77/0-/f Bahrein July 30th. 1943 To, His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent BAHRAIN Sir, Most respectfully I beg to state that I am a gold merchant and running this line for the past 25 years at Bahrein. I am now desirous to export gold to Iraq through The Eastern Bank Limited, Bahrein, who have asked me to first obtain an export li■cense from yourself. Therefore I shall feel highly grateful if you will kindly advise me your ruling on this enabling me to apply for the necessary export permit. Manama, Bahrein. Thanking you in anticipation, Your most obedient servant I beg to remain Sir,from R.Kanaysimiil, Bahrain to P.A. , i i Bahrain. I beg to state that no purchase- or sale of gold took place during this week. U.E,BASRAH Telegrams ; SAGNON # Telephone No, 02-571 F. O. B. No, 2 ^ ^ j*6A O •T_0VV jjiU« Bahrain, 9th.August,i943. H. B, M’s Political Agent, Bahrain ♦ Sir, I beg to inform your honour that no fresh transactions being made by me in gold bullions during the-week ending 8/8/43.(LZ6 %&amp; ^ Bahrain,23rd,August,i943. H, B. M's Political Agent, Bahrain. Dear Sir, I have the honour to inform you that no fresh transactions in gold bullions were done by me during the week ending 22/8/1943. %(g) ‘Lit Bahrain, 30uxi#August, 1943« B* M’s Political Agent; f Bahrain. Dear Sir, I have the honour to inform you that I have done no fresh transactions in gold bullions during the week ending 29/8/1943.Bahrain,12th.September,1943. Dear Sir, I have the honour to inform you that no ^reih transactions was made by me in gold bullions for the week ending today.Baiirain, 20th. Sept ember, i943« « H. B. M f s Political Agent, Bahrain. Dear Sir, I have the honour to inform you that no fresh transaction in gold bullion was made by me during the week ending yesterday.Bahrain,27th.September,i943. H. B. M f s Political Agent, Bahrain. Dear Sir, I have the honour to inform you that no fresh transaction in gold bullions took place by me during the week ending 26/9/43.BASRAH Telegrams ; SAGNON ^lephone No. 02-571 P. O. B. No. 2 ♦ Y — OV V Y ^:a.yfl H. B. M's Political Agent, Bahrain. Dear Sir, Bahrain, 4th. October, i943. I have the honour to inform youx that no fresh transaction in gold bullions took place by me during the week ending 3/»0/43. Yourstf. B. M's Political Agent, Bahrain. Dear Sir, I have the honour to inform you that no fresh transactions in gold bullion took place by me during the week ending 10/10/45. Yours yfaithfully,H. B. M’s Political Agent, Bahrain. r Bahrain,25th.October,1943. Dear Sir, I have the honour to inform you that no fresh transactions in gold bullions took place by me during the week ending 24/10/43. Y ours/Ob e diently,Translation of letter dated 26th Shauwal 1362 (26-10-43) from M.Adwany and M.Bakir Bahrain to the P.A., Bahrain. v ice rhe is; shauwal 1362 until this date, no gold Since'&gt;he issue of our letter dated ? itil this date transaction has 4 taken place. /y • Translation' of letter dated 13-12-4.0 Bahrain to the^P.A., Bahrain. from R.Kanayarnal, beg to state that no purchase or sale og gold rtook place this week. '. •' ITELE ADDRESS MENASHI C0H8N BAHRAIN C(J0£ USED BENTLEYS BAHRAIN No, ( PERSIAN CuLF ) :Lil &gt; v\ir Translation of letter dated 27-12-43 fro’r F.Cohin,Bahrain to the P.A., Bahrain. . a.C. I beg to state that the gold in my possession is 5 sovereig as previously reported. U.E.V* *7 v ’ 7 ^ Translatipn of letter datecT 27-12-43 from R.Kanayani .1 Bahrain to the P.A. , Bahrain. A. C. ; - ^ I beg to state that no,purchase or sale of gold took place during the week. U.E.V ✓ t^* 3^4. tv ^ ^ / _ ' r - ,&gt;»l— 5 cy_y X' - jp^ - Translation of letter dated 24-1-44 from R.Kanayarnal, Bahrain to the P.A., Bahrain. A. C. * I beg to state that no purchase or sale of gold took place during the week. U.E.G4i*iE§ (Ll)r (Lraetmt It^rnk, Ctmifi'iX ALL LETTERS TO BE ADDRESSED TO THE EASTERN BANK LIMITED. Telegraphic Address “EASTERTIDE'.' (incorporated in enolano.i Us//// lst February /// 44. The Political Agent, Bahrain* m, Dear Sir, SOVEREIJNS* lie have to advlee that there wae no appreciable fluctuation In the price of eovereigne during January, 1944, the price opening at R8*60 and cloelng at Rs*61* ft Manager*M 33 At Aj) Bahrain to the P.A., Bahrain* A.C. I beg to state that no purchase or sale of gold took place during this v/eek. U.E.&gt;V^-/ &gt;iv j J^4bW\, ' Traansl-ation of letter dated 20-3-44 from R.Kanayamal^ Bahrain to the P.A., Bahrain. \ A.C. I beg to state that no purchase or sale of gold took place during last week. U.3.TELE ADDRESS MENASHI COHiN BAHRAIN code used B E N T L E TV BAHRAIN ( PERSIAN CULF) civ No, O ^ ^ If J' O Translation of letter dated 27-3-44 from M.Cohin, to the P.A., Bahrain. Bahrain A. C. I beg to state that the gold in my possession is 5 sovereigns only.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0001b5_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/358</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0001b5</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/358</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 9/10 A II Exports of gold and silver from Bahrain - Weekly statements submitted by bullion brokers'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1942/1944</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-06-03T09:44:40</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (467 folios)</extent><extent>The papers in the file are arranged chronologically.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 469; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is also present in parallel between ff 2-468; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled, and can be found in the same position as the main sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains weekly statements showing purchases and sales of gold and silver received by the bullion brokers operating in Bahrain, often in Arabic with English translation. The reports are produced to comply with an order from the Political Agent in Bahrain for all the bullion brokers to produce a weekly report showing purchases and sales of gold and silver (see IOR/R/15/2/357).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Silver</topic></subject><subject><topic>Exchange rates</topic></subject><subject><topic>Gold</topic></subject><subject><topic>Exports</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0001b5#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>