<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000133_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-07-10T11:03:38.179Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">MANAGING AGENTS AND SECRETARIES INDUSTRIAL MISSIONS &amp; INTELLIGENCE TELEPHONE: KENSINGTON 1836 TELEGRAMS: KENPARTNA, 80UTHKENS, LONDON FOREIGN TELEGRAMS: KENPARTNA, LONDON COOES : A.B.C., 6TH EDITION BENTLEYS. LONDON DIRECTORS: CAPTAIN C. E. KENDALL COLONEL T. *. PRAGNELL, C.B.E., 0.8.0. GENERAL SIR JAMES MARSHALL-CORNWALL, K.C.B., C.B.E., 0.8.0., M.C. LIEUT.-COLONEL J. E. HANCE G. E. PECK, F.C.W.A. CHARLES KENDALL &amp; PARTNERS LIMITED KENSINGTON GORE, j tour 9^48 PLEASE REFER TO -j cm/ 21 . 12th April, 1948. LONDON, S. W.7 My dear Hanlson, Thank you for your note of 8th April, and I am indeed sorry that we shall not be working together in the Tuturel tfe have made a note that in future we should correspond with Mss vVaterlow in the Foreign Office. I should like to take this opportunity of letting you know how very greatly your unfailing kindness and help to us has been appreciated. I trust that there may be some opportunity of us meeting at intervals in the future. With kindest regards and once again with very many thanks. Yours sincerely, ^ /c; ^ (Captain C.K. Kendall). F.A.K. Harrison, Ksq., Commonwealth Relations Office, Downrig Street, S.W.l.i3xt. 9M/48 HU'uoUjkk 3tii April, 194 . Dear Miss &gt;aterl3vr, / v ^}e&amp;dird8‘ for inl'omut ion a oopy of the vgreeinent ^ befoseeii easrs* Charles ondall and J artners. Ltd. and Mr. el^rave regardIng/ieV 3 on wiled easra* racial ts act na au^ly agents of tfib dal ire in Government in the U. . &gt;o far as I ma aware tiiis Agreenent is etill in force. 2. Xou map be interested in the tema of the AgjPMnent in connection with the proposal to appoint supply agents to the Sultan of lluscat in this country. When v/e saw tine ^greeijent we did not much like Clause 2 which provides tiiat everything which the At ate requires in tills country should be supplied through ^ . Messrs. Aendalls. If applied literally tiiis .vould mean that in Z• :/ / the case of large orders, e.g. for the supply electricity w V'**/ generating plant,placed by the State Covermen^ liessrs . ^ * Kendalls would be entitled to a large CMnaiaeion for Wiffeig, . j r-rrr very little work or responsibility. In poi nt of fact, however, ijeridalla do not appear to nave insisted on the strict application of tiie -^greeiiunt on tills point. 3. With regard to the tern 'general representative 3 ' xm made it clear to botn parties that we did not understand it to cover'the recruitment of personnel for the Bahrein Government, 'e require the Bahrein Government to consult our JLocal political authorities before engaging any persons from this country as their employees. 4 * The address of hessrs. diaries endall &amp; Partners, ^td. ruv is 7, Albert Court, Kensington Gore, London, 3.V/.7* * nave told Captain Kvendall that we have now transferred resixjnaibllitg in regard to these matters to you. Yours sincerely. Miss C. hater low, f K. HARRISONouticJm Oi/ix^Lr dcmnuk; ext.jWab. t.,_ {fcOikrch 1948* Dear Mias Waterlow, I enclose herewith &gt;rt&gt;piea of letters / ' ) /^.Political Resident dated J^th December and 24 (with enclosures), le^arfddiv; the appoint 2 ngiSeer to the Bahrein Government. anuciry a State We made enquiries about possible candi^i^^:'ram the Ministry of Labour, and have now received the enclosed papers about a Mr.R.B.Rz^ancis, who so far can see, appears *a suitable person for the appointmenl^. Since however, we are handing over to the Foreign Office our responsibilities regarding the Persian Gulf, fran the end of this month, I think it would be better if we handed the papers over to you at this stage. Tou will no doubt wish for •Francis to be interviewed. Tou will of course appreciate that it will be necessary to consult the Bahrein Govemmerit before any corcndtaient is entered into. If I nay add my own comments, I would say that it is very important to obtain a good man as State Engineer for Bahrein, since it is by his attainnents, to a large extent, that the public at Bahrein Judge the efficiency of the State Government. If there are any other points on which I can help you, please let me know. Tours sincerely. Mi:s C.Waterlow, Foreign Office, London.S.W.l. F. A. K. KArx.-iSOWI.1INISTRY OF LABOUR AIID NATION AL SERV ICE Appolntrients Departnent, All further TECHNICAL. &amp; SCIENTIFIC REGISTER, oomaunicat Ions York House, should be addressed to Klngs’-vay, THE SECRETARY 3 London, W.C.2. and the following reference quoted:- -A Af - Telephone No: TEIIple Bor 8020 Date Dear Sir, Vacancy f Your Ref: r/4. m/3. The above vacancy has been recorded and every effort 7/ill be made to submit particulars of suitable candidates: Reference No* _ should be quoted on all future corre spondence • x 39013 / 1 / 1^229 Id 9/47 elA Form D. It is requested that in any further communication on this subject the under-mentioned letter and number may be quoted, and the reply addressed to — The Under Secretary of State for India, Political Department, India Office, London, 8.W. 1. No. P.Z. INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL, LONDON, S.W. 1. Sir, With reference to Foreign Office letter of No. , I am directed by the Secretary of State in Council to forward a copy of a letter from the Government of India regarding the appointment of as for at and to say that the Secretary of State sees no objection to the issue of His Majesty’s Exequatur. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant,■—V-'S Fair Copy Do&amp;r Bertram, Jil. Tori imL • it Cs, m have been asked by the Bolitloal eoldent In the j-eraian Gulf for eur aaalstanoe In finding a suooeasor to the state Engineer to the Bahrein Goverrsnenfc, whose term of of floe expiree in September this year* Parti aula re of the pay of the post and the type of man required are given in the letter of the 22nd January from the Political / Agent, Bahrein, a copy of which is enclosed* / We should be grateful for aiy assistance you can Ive us in the matter* 0 Vfr gmtrrfttl for riry njjlotmioe .yo&gt;» oan give ue -ie %hg; caattor^ u f e should of course hope that this jo would go to an I. 3 .J* officer and I should be glad to obtain any further information which you thiric it neoeasary to have* A note 'for persona preooeding to Bahrein ’ is enclosed* Yours sincerely, CScjd.) R JflSP£% T, J* Bertram K B q## Ministry of labour, Scientific &amp; Technical register, York House, W«C«2*1 m INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL, LONDON, S.W. 1. Sir, With reference to Foreign Office letter of No. , I am directed by the Secretary of State in Council to forward a copy of a letter from the Government of India regarding the appointment of as for at and to say that the Secretary of State sees no objection to the issue of His Majesty’s Exequatur. Form D. It is requested that in any further communication on this subject the under-mentioned letter and number Tnay be quoted, and the reply addressed to — The Under Secretary of State for India, Political Department, India Office, London, S. IF. 1. No. P.Z. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, The Under Secretary of State, Foreign Office. 3771b 300 5.35Form D. INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL, LONDON, S.W. 1. Sir, With reference to Foreign Office letter of No. , I am directed by the Secretary of State in Council to forward a copy of a letter from the Government of India regarding the appointment of as for at and to say that the Secretary of State sees no objection to the issue of # i. 4 His Majesty’s Exequatur. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, It is requested that in any further communication on this subject the under-mentioned letter and number may be quoted, and the reply addressed to — The Under Secretary of State for India, Political Department, India Office, London, 8. IF. 1. No. P.Z. The Under Secretary of State, Foreign Office. 3771b 300 5.35No. C/113. TO Tho Secretary tton'ble K'':*0UAUIW. Reference Residency endorsement No. 55-S, dated the 7th of January, 1948. 2. Information required is as follows:- (i) Basic pay ... **.1,100/- p.m. provident Fund ... 200/- p.ra. Pearness allowance according to rule (at present 15f of basic pay) Electric allowance ... 60/- p.m. Free quarters with furniture and a car are provided. 2* months leave after each 12 months service, first class sea or air passage on joining and after four years, and a return passage to India, or equi valent in cash, after each year. Agreement would be for four years, renewable. liote . An unmarried man aged not more than 40 Is preferred. (ii) The State rnglneer is in charge of the State Electricity Undertaking which includes power house and plant, new installations, dis tribution, wiring of Government premises and any electrical plant which is used by tho State. Ue is at present responsible for the Telephone system but in a fev; months the new automatic system will be Installed and from then the State will not be directly concerned with telephones. Ho is also responsible for tho shaikh Rained Bridge. The State Engineer is in charge of the 313 PQLI TICAL AGEftCT JUHHAIK. The n2nd January, 1948. to the the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf* Bahrain . /Transportrrwispoft j-epartasent arid fforKatops. All moicr •■•ohlcles belon,-;.tni 5 t5o Che State, but not those of the ituling family, are serviced and repaired in the Ooverncient garage. The workshops provide the equipaqnt for carrying out repairs to the plant and transport vehicles 'he Shaikh T^airad bridge is a mechanically operated swing bridge. Sd./- C.J. PfUTT political Agent, Balirain. ;r'\ . J. / - J. a* U. CAl i haU for Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain. NS. •m7 So Y* **« 1 ‘'' PRBSATW flULF RE SIDENCY the 9th January 1948 INDEXED N ? '1* . I JLU'i - r&lt;Ai -- Please refer to the last paragraph of your ^ letter No.Ext.2964/47 dated the 3Cth December, 1947 regarding the appointment of purchasing agents' for the Sultan in the United Kingdom. 2. It is proposed to discuss the matter with \ the Sultan on his return to Muscat c,f. my demi- official letter No. 1773-S dated the 11th October , 2* tr) i b- K.A.K^iTaFftson, Esquire, Commonwealth Helations Office, LONDON. S. .V. 1 'LB 1CONFIDENTIAL D.O* No,2115-0 BAHRAIN, ^he 4th December, 1947 INDEXED J^S I forward herewith a copy of a letter I have received from Felly with its enclosure on the subject of finding a successor to Leigh, the State Engineer to the Bahrain Government. 2. I have replied to Felly agreeing to the proposal in the first sentence of his letter. 3. As suggested by Felly I should be grateful if you would kindly be on the look out for suitable candidates and let us know if you find any. You will appreciate that it is primarily an electrical engineer that is required. E.P. Donaldson, Esquire, C.M.G., Commonwealth Relations Office, King Charles Street, Whitehall, LONDON, S.W.l ! LB 1Confidential. D.O. No. 20/30SF. Dear Jackson, EXT Adviserate, November 16, 1947. Leigh's service with the Bahrain Government comes to an end in September 1948. It is probable that he will wish to take leave during the summer of 1948 as he did not go away during 1947 and has leave to his credit. i think therefore that it is time vO begin looking for a replacement for Leigh. 7. ^he post is that of State Engineer but in xact this title is something of a misnomer as the duties consist oi running the electric undertaking, oransporl and the bridge, ue is not responsible for public^works which includes buildings roads and up- keep °i Government property nor is he concerned with oil inspection. 3. There is at present in England a dearth of Engineers and it may be diificult to find a suitable person. I propose writing to Callenders Cables Com pany wiuh whom we have had dealings for many years, and „o xiirrlees ijiciverton and Day, to ask whether they could recommend anyone, if we have no results from them I will insert an advertisement in some of the home papers, unless by any chance you can recommend any suitable candi date. Yours sincerely, Sd./- C. DALRY’/PLE BELGRADE G.N. Jackson, Esq., H-B'ivU's policicai Agent, Bahrain.tel. no. . 34B HOLBORN 3434 EXT. Ba P 5 /HESET /3639 xs ///. H indexed &gt;183 Ju+H 26:nfim Dear i-r. Hallowes, | ■y- Very many thanks for your letter dated 10th November,1947j regarding the appointment of an Assistant Engineer at Bahrein, AIR MINISTRY, p -5., ADASTRAL HOUSE, KINGSWAY, W.C.2. r T 4&amp;th November, 1947 I am grateful to you for informing me that the vacancy has now been filled and for your assurance that should others be required for employment in the Persian Gulf you will probably get in touch with me again* Yours sincerely. F.E.roRD. R. I. Hallowes, Esq*, Commonwealth Relations Office, Downing Street, Whitehall, S.W,1«SBHBMV 'J2 IS i' ^ L 00 DE \ W%% i ff r 5 i? vV ■'** *- * fi ’ j £■ * C . B s f INWARD TELEGRAM FRai: POLITICAL RESIDENT IN THE PERSIA GULP BAHRAIN TO; COMMONYvTLTLTH REH.TIONS CPFICE D. 6.00 p#m# 2nd Noveniber 1947 R# 6*p.m# 2nd Noveniber 1947 No. A/ 853 • Your telegra m No» 12508 of 17th October, Bahrein State Engineer. 2. Hill has been engaged by Bahrein Government and will sign agreement on arrival here. He is reported to have left Sudan for Bahrein via Bombay Expected date of arrival not known at present but will telegraph when he actually takes up appointment. Mrs Hill expected here in a fortnight.Cofli'ibiial IAU D.0.H&gt;.177a-a. Dear Stewart, Th« Hoal4ttnoy 9 Bahrain, the 11 th October 1947* L&gt;^ please refer te my en4e re ament Ke«1104*^ bated the 7 th June 1047, for** ruing a copy ef Donald so ?i # a letter Be* Ext*927/47 dated the 30th May, the enclosure to which 1 now fomard in original* 2. 1 did not hAYe an opportunity of meeting Keymer while I wae in London and I suggest that the beat course will be to give the Sultan particulars of both.Kendall and Keymer and let him see from which of them he can obtain the better terms* He might alee if he wishes advertise for an agent in the home papers but in these oircumstanceo 1 think he euuld be well advised te consult us before making a final selection. 3* If you see no objection you might perhaps die cues the whole matter with the Sultan when you next me t him and ascertain shat action if any ho proposee to take* If ho would like te leave it to us to select an arent for him so much the better. Yours sincerely, Sd. W.R.HAY. Major A*C* Stewart, O.D.is.., Political Agent, MUSCAT , Rii L,xxJb^ffifeffl^EtJoacxx EMt. 222Z/W7 J q Nafremlwr, 1^7 Dear Ford* Would you please refer to ooirest ondenoe resting with radbury's letter, J o. of 6th Au^uat to Reed about the appointaent ol' an Aasiatant 3tate I^ngineer a± Bahrein? 2* This vacancy ias now been filled, T:&gt;ut should offio. rs be rec|uired for other jobs in the Persian Gulf of tills nature, m siiall probably get in toudi with you again. 3* I am most i; irateful to you for your assistance in this matter. Yours sincerely. F.E.Foxd, Esq* '•A , Air Ministry (P5) # W.G.2.K B (11178) Wt.21321/P.248 6,000 (2 sorts) 7/39 A.&amp; E.W.Ltd. Gp.685 It is requested that m any further communi cation on this subject the unde?-mentioned letter and number may be quoted, and the reply addressed to — The Under Secretary of State for India, Political Department, India Office, London, S.H-M. P. INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL, LONDON, S.WA. U ¥(7289) Wt. 28767/8127 6m 9/46 C. A Go. 746(8) iflTRYjiOf^ LABOUR TIOSlAL SERVICE. / Any further communications should be addressed to THE SECRETARY, and the following reference quoted ^ ^ Tt hone No. : TEMple Bar 8020 1 ° 2^ Appointments Department, SCIENTIFIC REGISTER, ^OUSE, Kingsway, London, W.C.2. Date Dear Sir, iNoexeD Vacancy for fKCC\&gt; ^ 'UV 'ruMcc. MAnfi* Particulars are given overleaf of candidates submitted for your vacancy in respect of whom no result has been notified. Will you, therefore, be good enough to indicate the present position by completing column 3 overleaf. Yours faithfully, — t\&lt;+xl c- vup 3-ryoU^ &lt; • T.S.R.23 R. 5^0 • (. T.S.R.387/2/40Ext. 1958/47. Extract ffrom letter from Mr, Dal rumple Belpyave to Mr.ljarrison, dated 8th o ep t ember. 194-7. With reference to your 188^47 of 5/9/47 regarding the recruitment of personnel for the Bahrain Government, The only part that Kindall took in connection with the nurses was to try to obtain passages from here to Bahrain, He has never done any recruiting work for the Bahrain Government and I do not think that at present it is necessary for him to do so.CONFIDENTIAL CODS jrrom Secretary of State for ConEicnwealth Halations To Political Resident, Persian Gulf Despatched «9*10 hours, 20th August, 1947 Ko« 1 QQ 7 Z We have reccivea through Ksndall’s request for our support in obtaining sea passages on about October 1st for 2 nursing sisters engaged by Bahrein Government* 2* Has P*A. Bahrein been approached by Bahrein Government regarding this? We propose to inform Belgrade that in case of recruitment of personnel from this country H,M,G expect that their prior agreement should in all cases be obtained and that Political Agent Bahrein should also be consulted in accordance with standing arrangement which aleo applies to personnel recruited from any country outside Bahrein* Provided that H*&amp;*G*e prior consent is obtained In individual cases before final agreements are signed* We should not object to Kendalls performing agency work in this^ country connected with x^eoruitment* Do you agree?* ^ — INWARD TELEGRAM i-.X 1(.e ns^ Allotted io Svibfe^^ax D^^usriubi&amp;i^ WORD com, T&gt;0 1 r 19^ 14140, Political Resident In the Persian GolT .Secretary of State for India* Bahrain* 14*55 hours$ 12th August* 1947* 05©40 hours* 13th August* 1947* f^l To Dated Received No*A/62Q* Donaldson from Galloway* Your telegram No*10228 10th August* I know nothing about Kills and see no point in asking for a man from Sudan Government because he has been in Bahrain previously* This is particularly so since the Government of India on earlier request from Bahrain Government have found a suitable man*u, GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, r P»rgi flp On1f Resififinnv DKPABTD-CTT. • ^ Bahrain t&gt;“ EXPRESS LETTER [N % B % —This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been • so despatched,] J From Political Resident, Bahrain &gt;• 4 To Retaxandum, London. No. -59/9 Dated 8th Auexist, 1947.. rT* Reference your Express Letter No.ExtJ.499/47 dated the 24th July, 1947_ ' ? : 2. Particulars of four candidates suggested by the Air Ministry are being transmitted to the Bahrain G-overnment for their views. r 3. Letter Copy is enclosed of Government of India Express No.F.33(20)-E. 11/47 dated the 8th July, 1947, recommending one Major L.J. Lloyd, R.E. Major Lloyd appears quite suitable for the post but the views of the Bahrain Goverhment on his application have not yet been received. - REPGU - The issue of the above has been authorised. Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. /yha r S. 6. MFP—1407 S&amp;P—(M-2339)—25-5-37—300,000.v Gory of Foreign New Delhi Express Letter dated the Bth^July, 1947. No.f?S.T(20) K r -E. 11/47 19 Your telegram A/318 May 13th. Assistant Engineer for Bahrain Government. 2 # Engineer- in-Ghief redommends Major L.J. Lloyd, B. Following are his particulars /^ge : 39 years (Appears younger&gt; Medical Category : A.l. Married : Wife and family definitely not leaving United Kingdom. May be considered single for this appointment. 22 years experience in Civil and Constructional Engineering as follows belcher &amp; Son Ltd. Public Works Contractor* 1924-39 (went through workshops and .technical office and was Area Manager on leaving). Ford &amp; Weston Ltd. 1939-41 (Quantity jurveying). Royal Engineers 1941 to present date (War Office special enlistment). Very wide experience in all kinds' 0 { .building, construction, public works, roads, airfields tunnelling etc. Has corpleted nearly six years overseas Burma, Maidive Inslads) wit. a break Oi six months in United Kingdom last year. , Has been recommended for the appipintment also by Brigadier Garforth, Chief Engineer, Eastern Command', India. 2 Please telegraph whether Major Lloyd acceptable +.n Bahrain Government.Ttlegrams Inland : “ SUDANOLOGY, Telegrams Overseas : “SUDANOLOGY, LONDON.” Telephone: WHITEHALL 9921. L.0.3001.3/1158 . su MHG ^ /4, I DAN GOVERNMENT ^ EXT ''AGENCY IN LONDON, WELLINGTON HOUSE, BUCKINGHAM GATE, LONDON, S.W.I. 14th August, 1947. Receipt is ugust, 1947“ the to the Ludan. acknowledged of your Sxt. 1700/47 dated 13th contents or which to-day have been transmitted I am, Dir, Your obedient Servant, for Sudan A^enx m London . The Under Secretary of State for India, India Office, Whitehall, b/'.l.V- a«. 1720/4' A7. 1rX 4 &lt;fo~ 13th August, 15&gt;47* -s/ 1 as d i w-cted by the uecaret^ry of state to forward herewith, for the necessary action, a letter ad dressed to you by lT f licl^rawe, Adriser to the hBiiJiof Bahrein, I as, sir. Tour obedient Jerwant, ^ A, K. HARRISON The Sudan Agent, Wellington House, kwtfon,/ I From the Adviser to THE Bahrain Government. Bahrai n, Persian Gulf. 1, Queen* s Gate Place, S.W.7. ( jel: Jestem 11^15. ) Dear Harrison, I am loath to worry you when you are just back from leave and probably very busy, but I have seen Donaldson about the appointment of a new P.V/.D. Officer for Bahrain and, on his advice, called on the Sudan igent (v/hose Deputy I saw, he himself being on leave) about a Major Hills, who I want to get. confirm by letter what I told him verbally. Here is my letter and, if you approve, will you please send it on. I would like to see you and will look in after a day or two Yours sincerely. P.A.K, Harrison, Bsq.. xhe India Office, Whioehall, S.W.l. / Enc12 th Augua-t, 1947, .To* The Sudan Agent, Wellington House, .. £R)XA£Jlij Se ^«lf&gt; Frau 0. MLxy ifjle Belgiuvo, Saq*, Adviser to H* I« ’he K ilkh of 'aiirain (l, &lt;Jueen*s G»i.te Flaoe, S«W* 7 «) Sir, I have the honour to refer to ipy visit to you on Fi:u-u\/, August S'.;h, and ngy oonrersxtion with you regarding Major Stajilenr Hills, of the Sudan Oorenvaent Agricultural l^epartoent* I'he Bahrain Govemnient desires if possible to obtain tdie seryloes of xlajor Hills for the poet of Officer in Charge of ; tfaetesu Major Hills is known to the Bsh* ain OoTexnaent as, during the ir, sia spmt two years in Bahrain vhile in the Hoys! figlneers cloin^ the type of m&gt;xk for etiicli he is now ret;jired* If Major Hills oould oq xxzIqq. -od iroBi his present pout, he Bahrain Gknrenxsent is prepared to offer hfca an appointaaont and I wouM hezefore be grateful if you wuld forward this ^plication for his release to the anpxoprlate Authorities* Major Hills is at present on leave in the United Kin doa but ho is due, within a f«*r days, to return to duty in the iiitfan* The post vtiich the Bahrain Govermont visits to fill la now vaoant and various ptfclic eorics are ?^eing held qp until a as* Officer in Charge has been appointed* Should it be possible for Major Hills to be released i should be very grateful if Z might be informed as soon as possible, in order that ammipmants oan be made for his poesage to Bahrain or, if he cannot be released, so that I can consider other means of filling the Z hive the honour to be. Sir, Tour obedient Servant Belgrave.r 'p MINISTRY OF LABOUR AND NATIONAL SERVICE 3o Appointments Department, ( TECHNIC AL and SCIENTIFIC REGISTER T York House, ’ Kingsway, T n u \ Jn London, W.C.2. 172 Jf. : Phone : Tei^pl^ Bar 8020 Extension Y zt:M:m±Mi/o Any further communication should be addressed to THE SECRETARY quoting our reference number. &gt; . Dear Sir. Vacancy for. ^ %UL I enclose for your consideration particulars of candidate(s) for the above vacancy. The particulars given are based on the statements of the candidate(s) and references have not been taken up. If the candidate(s) appear(s) suitable for your requirements, you will no doubt wish to make your own arrangements for interview. When you have reached your decision will you please complete this form in the space below and return it to the above address as soon as possible. Yours faithfully, NAME OF CANDIDATE(S) RESULT:—Date of commencement, if accepted. If rejected, it would be helpful for purposes of future submissions if reasons could be stated. U/H/Tc .C'Gj, ■m/i-, 41 continue overleaf if necessary Date Signature Note :—Any candidate who is at present emyloyed in an undertaking scheduled under an Essssential Work Order must, in the event of acceptance for other employment obtain the permission of the National Service Officer to leave his present employment. T.S.R.23(Rev.) T.S.R.387/2/46 Wt. 44381/67728 10m 2/47 RP.4112Tel. No. Holborn 3434. Ext .?48. RS/P5/3639 AIR ^ j, / V/ %/ MINISTRY, (p.5) ADASTRAL HOUSE, KINGSWAY, W.C.2. iWlsIp b 6th August, 1947. Dear Ivir. Heed, / I am not quite sure whether I have submitted \ih • details concerning Wing Commander C^ker to you so would venture to submit hereunder brief details concerning him, for consideration in connection with the appointment in Bahrein. He is Wing Commander C.F.C. cSk Born 2.12T1902 Resides at} Hollywell, Cubert, He is married and was educated Lickey Halls-School H.M.S. Conway Rossall School Emanuel College, Cambridge er, B.A. Nr • Ne wquay,C or nwal at 1913-1916 1916-1918 1918-1921 1921-1924 1 His civil occupation was Assistant Preparatory School Master 1924-25 He was granted a Commission in the R.A.F. on 26.9.25 and left the Service in 1947. He is a qualified pilot and Flying Instructor Fully qualified and very experienced engineer with excellent administrative and organising ability. Expert knowledge 'of Aircraft, Motor Transport, Maintenance, workshop practice, Time study and Cost Accounting. Good knowledge of aerodromes and building construction. This candidate also passed the Accidents Investigation Course. A*H. Reed, Esq., India Office, Whitehall, 3.W.I.I believe that Wing Commander (Wter knows Group Captain L&lt;^4slightly# I should be grateful if you could consider him and let me know your decision in due course. Yours sincerely, for F.H. FORD. E R.ISTRI C? LA3QUH AID NATIQNAL SEHVICE All fjrtiier communications should be addressed to THE SECRETARY and the following reference quoted:- Tolephone No: TElIple Bar 8020 Appointments Department, TECHNICAL &amp; SCIENTIFIC REGISTER, York House, Kingsvvay, London, W.C.2. Deaa. Sir, • • / / iff Vacancy for tUtc Your Ref: _zS&gt;r//f^Ap The above vacancy has been recorded and every effort mil be made to submit particulars of suitable candidates: to . h. 4 2//^;/o Reference No should be quoted on all future corre spondence. Yours faithfully, JLs6k &amp;)/■ T.3.H.22. T.S.H.397/2/46 D&lt;: 90838/1/R.22 Im 3/17 LIII', ORY Qp CAP‘-^K. 2* 3. Ifr&amp;S r A.A.SIDCTH, 43 yoars, ^UALU- T IC/gm[ 0 : b.Sc (iing) ! Address Au^^ust and Sejj'fccaabQr) Circular Road, J Ca.itlerook, Co # i)erry, j N* Ireland* ) of Queens University, Belfast. June, 1923. Si lienee,- Auguet, 1923 - August, 1925, Hoads in N.Irolond as v ) Clerk of rfor; 2 * and ( 2 J Assistant to Surveyor* September 1923* Joined India Service of Engineers (Madras), &gt;crved as Assistant Executive Engineer 1923 - IfiEircsh 1931. Kxeoutive Engineer March 1931 - )©oeraber 1939 , Joined Anay in December 1939 and served until December 194L when recalled to Service in Civil Department and promoted to Superintending Engineer* ivosent Appointment* Superintending Engineer hoods* Salary about £2,100*0,0 per annua. irinciiial Wor].s executed:- hadura Water Supply and Drainage, Cost - £323,000* Gu.i.ibitor water Supply iroject* ' £230,000* - ost War* intenance and Inspection of roads about S 400,000 per annum* Kattalar Project, Construction Low Level Dum, 4,300* long and 2 mainOanals with Ji tributing Channels. £330,000. Madura General Hospital Project £125,000* a.MM Joined as Lieutenant in 1939. served as Assistant Garrison Engineer, Garrison Enginoay,Grade II Stiiff Offioor, C.h*d. and Deputy Chief Engineer in India, Burma and Assam, Main Roads construction for Army. Construction of Airfields for take off far China •Huap* Crossing fear u.S.A.Amjy. Construction and maintenance of large camp and Hospital I^rojects for an L.of C.^irea including water simply, drainage ana electrical supijly in addition to being Engineer Adviser to the S.C.C. Ai^a.TEL. NO. HOLBORN 3434 EXT. INDEX EL.’ its/29 48/p. 5. ^ Dear Li*. Reed, EXT 1 19 KJ v With reference ti. the -vaoetnoy-HPor an Assistant Station MINISTRY, (^ 5 ) ADASTRAL HOUSE, 3o KINGSWAY, W.C.2. £*• 23rd July, 1947. .5 jieer in Bahrein, may I submit hereunder brief particulars of the following candidate. He is:- Flight Lieutenant T.R, Beresford. of 2 Bton Villas, Bamp ton, Oxford, Born 18.12.1915&gt; married, one child. Obtained General School Certificate and has matriculated. Before joining the Service was employed as Production Inspector (Machine Produce} with Messrs, Harris Lebus Ltd,, N.17, from 1933-1940&gt; and as a Jig and r fool Production Inspector (Aircraft) from 1940-1941 W&amp; Oar Co. Ltd., Abingdon. Served as a pilot in the R.A.P.V.R. from 1943 until May, 1946. He is described as a satisfactory Plight Commander. I have told him that particulars of his service have been sent to you, and would be grateful if you would consider him, and let me know your decision in due course.Tel No. HOLBORN 3434 EXT. REP: P.5./RESET. Pear Mr. Reed, Many thanks for your ADASTRAL HOUSE, KINGSWAY, W.C.2. 11th July, 1947. ai^LiJe 3rd July, 1947 regarding . 4' ' ^ 4 / ^ ■ 1 — tiW^ va 5 a.Eyx/ I n,ne appointment as assistant State Engineer and Officer in Charge Public Works Department, Bahrain, and for the terms of contract embodied in the telegram from the Political Resident, Persian Gulf which was attached thereto. X have been through our available candidates and have got three possioles to submit to you for consideration in this connection. They are;- Plight Lieutenant T.R. Beresford , 2 Eton Villas, Bampton, Oxon. He was bom on 18th December, 1915, married with one child. Obtained General School Certificate. Has been employed as a Production Inspector (machine production] . with Messrs. Harris Lebus Ltd. London, N.17. from 1933 - 1940. He was also a Jig and Tool Production Inspector from 1940 - 41 with the M.G. Car Co. Abingdon,* Berks. Served as a pilot in the Royal Air Force from 1943 - 1946 and proved,.himself to be a satisfactory Plight Commander. I should perhaps add that he had pre^rious service in the ranks from March 1941 before being commissioned. Incidentally he has a knowledge of Spanish and French. „ faing • A.H. Reed, Esq., India Office, Whitehall, London, S.W.l.Wi nr Commander Q«F « Goaker , • 'Littlecroft”, Holy-well Bay, CuBert, Cornwall. Born 2nd December, 1902 and married. Educated at Rossall School and Emmanuel College, Cambridge. Obtained School Certificate with 5 credits and holds B.A. i^egree in engineering. For a year he was Assistant Preparatory Schoolmaster 1924 - 25. Granted a permanent commission in the General Duties Branch of the Royal Air Force on 26th September, 1925. Transferred to the Technical Branch in April 1940. tfas mentioned in despatches in January 1§42. Awarded the Symbol 'E* which as you know is our engineering Symbol in 1936. Took a two-year course in Engineering at R.A.F. School of Engineering, Henlow, Bedford, 1929 - 31. He passed the Advanced Engineering course at the R.A.F. School of Aeronautical Engineering and was Commanding Officer and Chief Engineer Officer of the R.A.F. in Bermuda, Chief Engineer Officer Headquarters No. 6 Group and served in the same capacity at Royal Air Force Stations in Canada. He has travelled widely in Middle East, Bermuda, West Indies, U.S.A. and Canada. He is an experienced lecturer and public / speaker, has excellent administrative and organising ability also an expert knowledge of aircraft, motor transport maintenance, ’ workshop practice and Time study and Cost Accounting. A good knowledge of aerodromes and building construction. He has indicated that he is prepared to accept an appointment abroad. /Squadron Leader- 3 - Squadron Leader IC.S. Hewson , ,r iVhitsbu y n , Orchard Rc ad, Kook, Surbiton, Surrey, and R.A.F. Station, Dish Born 11th July, 1908, married. Yorks. Obtained School Certificate with Distinction in machine drawing and in building design. Originally apprenticed to the Building trade with J. Offer and I Son, Kingston-on-Thames. Subsequent Manager with Thorogood Bros. (Builders) Surbiton, and Technical Adviser to Aixtistic Blind Co. Surbiton. Served in the ranks of the R.A.F.V.R. as an Air Observer for 5 years. Commissioned on 2nd September, 1939. Is still serving but is due to leave the Service shortly unless he is selected for and accepts an Emergency Service Commission. He is a fully trained and competent Air Controller and has indicated a preference for a civil engineering appointment. Incidentally he is a fully qualified Operations Officer. Thilst in the Service proved to be a sound Flying Control Officer who took a keen interest in the welfare of his men and was generally a reliable officer. L.A.C. C.V.B. Man , 33 St. John's Road, G-olders G-reen, N.W.ll, Speedwell 5880. . Bom 13th July, 1920 and single. Educated at the Grammar School Shoreham-by-Sea. Joined the Royal Air Force in 1938 and served for seven years as a Fitter/Armourer 1st Class. For 4 years he was in the M.E.F. and East Africa employed generally on maintenance work. He is studying for his National Certificate for Engineering (Mechanical). I am enclosing herewith a copy of three testimonials for this / candidate. I shall be glad if you would let me know your decision in due course. Yours sincerely, c /c^ (F.E. FORD.)A m Prom To Dated Received INDEXED to Bxternal Department. WORD GODS Political Resident in Gulf Secretary of State for India Bahrein p 12.00 hours, 28th May 1947 16.25 hours, 28th May 1947 fifl* A/SflQf Donaldson from Hay. !o tl loT? M y telegram A/318 May lst&lt; Tunnicliffe. —^ Successor for Efforts of Government of India so far unsuccessful. Is there any chance of your finding anybody?8222 INWARD TELEGRAM P V &lt; ti ■ si Allotted to External Deuartmpjit' From To Reptdo to Dated •Received EXf t* 1 s' n indexed b^ 4 v!&lt; WORD CODE ’ Political Residerf^-in the Po-rsian Gulf Government of Indie,- External Affaire Dspartmaiit India Office and copy to political Agent Bahrain Bahrain, 19*50 hours, 10th May 1947 01,50 hours, 11th May 194? &lt; No. A/318* Bahrain Government urgently require assistant State Engineer and officer-in-charge Public Works Department. 2. Terms of last incumbent were; ’ * (a) salary Rs 900 per month with annual increment Rs 50 up to Rs 1,200 per month, (b) Provident Fund rupees 100 per month* (c) Cost of living allowance Rs 135 per month (d) Free furnished quarters* (o) One and a half months furlough with one month of v ammaleleave for each year of service. (f) First class passage on joining appointment and if European to United Kingdom after 4 years service and first class return passage Karachi ea&lt;ih year except when United Kingdom passage due. (g) Free medical attention. (h) appointment for 2 years in the first instance. 3* Man without wife and family and below 40 years (.?preferred). 4* It is thought suitable incumbent might be available from Indian Public Works Departments Grateful if enquiry be ma de and re suit c ominuni c ate d* 5» India Office only. Replacement is required for Tunnieliffe who has been invalided home.' Grateful if (?enquiry) for suitable incumbent could also be made United Kingdom.I am not sure that I altogether agree with Economic Department about Messrs. Kendalls lack of efficiency over the water pipes business; they probably assumed that the India Offi ce would themselves have the necessary background information. Since Economic Department can suggest no alternative candidates I should think we might agree to Colonel Hay’s suggestiii* to the Sultan that he should get in touch witn Kendalls. I suggest a draft.Ext.927/47 DRAFT LETTER ./Lt. Col. W.R. Hay, CSI, CIE., Persian Gulf Residency, Bahrein. Would you please refer to your d.o. letter No. 651 -S Of 19th April of putting the Sultan of Muscat in touch with Messrs. KendalU ; We are not able to suggest the name of any other firm who would be willing to take on this work and, although tthere is perhaps something in the point that it is undesirable to give Kendalls a monopoly M** JtakA {nl/ m in the Shoilehdora^i', we see no objec tion to your putting the Sultan in touch with them. I am not sure, however, whether it would be a good thing for the Sultan to make a contract giving them the position of sole suppliers of goods from the U.K. as was done by Belgrave. I think/it would be as well if you warn I the Sultan that the supply of water pipes from this country is by no means easy # ajad jfn spite of intensified/i intensified efforts by Kendalls and ourselves it has not yet proved possible to secure an allocation of the pipes required by the Bahrein Government for their own water scheme.Mr Hnrrison -v I trust tnat you will iorgive tne delay m replying to you;* note, out in Thomson* s aDsence at Geneva I nave oeen very i&gt;\rd-pressed xor time. Moreover, I had nop§d to ue auie ^ * to give you tne xinal result ox tne Water Pipes tor Bahrein iUestion out tnis, niirage-ilice, seems to V! nisn into tne distance just when one appears to De approaching closest to it.The position tnat ootains now, is tnat 11 avenues nave ueen explored except tnat ui supporting an application oy KendOll* s direct to tne suppliers or tneir requirements (presumaoly Stewarts and Lloyds) and endeavouring to get tnem a prior place m tne queue. That,I am axraid is tne ocst that cau Do done. As regards tne question ox trn appointment ox Agents to tn^ Sultan ox Muscat, I do not reel tnat our opinion over here is or mucn importance in deciding ror or against the recommending.of Kendall* s for tnis worx, m that it nas oeen tne Eternal Deportment wnicn has nad tne most contact with tnem in tne past. For tnis reason, I am dinident in mentioning that I have not Deen impressed witn Messrs. Kendalls erricency in connection witn tne Water Supply 30 D, as it was only grter a numoer or telepnone calls, suosequent to tneir initial letter to tnis Office, .tnat I was cole to extract oacicground Knowledge sufficient to enaole ^ good case to oe put up to the Board or Trade, oltnougn even tnis appears to nave proved in vain. There is as you mention, tne iurtner cousideration relating to tne undesirability ox encouraging tne formation ox a monopoly,eitner oy allowing one firm to do ail tne Du sin ess or c*y countenancing tne signing or a restrictive contract. .1 am inclined to tne view tnat, if anotner iirm snould oe appointed as tne Sultan’s agents, a oeniricir-l stimulus to erriciency generally might come aDout, since it might tn,en o ^ Bi a period. O'.’ posoihle to form some idea or the -' mounts or energy and ousiness acumen tnat were oeing exerted oy the respective Agents in tneir errorts on oenalr or tne Persian Gull States. I an, however unsole to suggest native concern which might De willing to a ao W so. derln * TOOtner y ° U1 ’ Department the name or any alter- to taxe on the joo, and ■aicint ne in a position*: r? CONFIDENTIAL r; n D.O. Nq^651 - S. 1 ^ • r-ro-IT^ l ^*r^~* y!&gt; \\ ^ ^TV r- t PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCYf BAHRAIN. the 19th A|&gt;ril, 1947 V/hile at Salalah I discussed wii$h the Sultan the supply o£ pipes which he requires for installing a water/scheme at Sur and Suggested txf him that it would be worth his while to appoint an agent in the United Kingdom for obtaining his requirements there in the same, way as the Bahrain Government have done. The Sultan considered the idea a good one and I have been thinking of putting him in touch with the Bahrain Governments firm Messrs. Charles Kendall and Partners, Ltd. So far as I am aware the Bahrain Government are fully satisfied with “bhe work which this firm has done for them and it now knov/s all the ropes. At the risk therefore of creating a s'ort of monopoly I am inclined to recommend it to the Sultan. 2. Before I take any action, however, I should be glad to know your views. You may think we ought to give some other firm a chance. E. P. Donaldson, Esquire, C.M.G., India Office, LONDON.Scci'etaiy, Scononic Dept. In realy to r. Rurnbold*s note of 15th April, this Department is prepared to accept the responsibility for the work. 2, As regards the case of the water ^ipes for Bahrein, I have now had a further letter from Capt. Kendall, attached below. It looks as though the Board of Trade are not prepared to assist us in this matter. Perhaps the only thing we can do now is to try the Iron and Stee: Control Board again although I see that in reply to I'x. Thomson*s letter of 5th 1,larch they refer*us to the Board of Trade. However, a direct approach to the Iron ** and Steel board worked a year ago (see paragraph. 2 of Ken all*s letter of 2Ath ’ ay, 1916;. 77e are prepared to continue this correspondence from this Department, but as you have already spent so much trouble on this \ In any case the attached draft may be of use. The address 'iven is that advised by Messrs. Kendalls. ^ ^ ^ '*a -(k —*}}• Secretary, External Dept* I agree that it would now be the ^JEndia Office to accept the responsibility from the India rppiy Ccnmission fcr assisting Holloway Bros: and that the Political Resident be informed accordingly* With regard to the question of internal responsibility, it is understood from the India Supply Comnission that the work to be transferred would involve aid being given in exceptional cases of need in matters of procurement and shipment* The number of cases which fall to be dealt with is said to be less than one a month* It would seem that the amount of work concerned is very «*nan and is likely to diminish since the trade with the Persian Gulf territories is rapidly returning to normal commercial channels* Owing to the fact that the India Supply Coszrdssion took over the work 18 months ago this department is out of touch on matters relating to the working of quotas and controls, and would be very little better placed than the External Department to handle it* Furthermore we would not have the External Department’s advantage of appreciating the local background in the Persian Gulf. The position was quite different during the war when we did this sort of work for the J&amp;ii. External Department, because then we had a great volume of precisely similar work on behalf of India. In the present circumstances, therefore, I am inclined to think that the best plan would be for the External Department to accept the prime responsibility for handling this rather small block of work and for conducting correspondence regarding it, although if there are individual cases which you wish to refer to the Economic Department for advice, we shall do our best to give it to you* VVWU.Ammmm jammm fL SVIHT* (JKY JDS}y INWARD TELEGRAMS 5653 .lotted to External Department 9 IT CONFIDENTIAI, CODE; From Political Resident in the Persian Gulf To Secretary of State for India Dated Bahrein^ 13®10 hours, 29th March 1947 Received 12v20 hours y 29th.March 1947 Personal, Following for Donaldson from Hay*. &lt; ^lo^ Your telegram Noo 1384 Ja nuary 29th 0 2i Though contract between Bahrein Government, and Holloways was only recently agreed negotiations have been proceeding since before agreement with Kendall. Belgrave states Kendall knows all about agreement with Holloways and has raised no objectibi .Delay in replying is much regretted./ rm f*—— GOVERNilISN’T OF IN T D4A, __ Dkpartmikt, EXPRESS LETTER [N, B,—an ORIGINAL MESSAGE^ sent bf poet to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, bui intended to be treated, on receipt, with the eame expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] ac From REPGU, BAHRAIN. 4 To / RETAXANDUM, LONDON. Repeated FOREIGN NEW DELHI. POLITICAL, BAHRAIN. No. 96-90/1. Bahrain, Dated 13th January, 19 A7,* I enclose a copy of a letter No.B/SKM/lK dated the 5th December, 1946, from Holloway Brothers, (London) Limited to the Adviser to the Bahrain Government regarding Bahrain »»ater Supply Scheme, which is self explanatory. Holloway Brothers have taken on a contract for the erection of water storage tanks with a pump house and pumps and over 15 miles of asbestos cement piping to provide a main water supply tHJbughout Manama, the principal town of Bahrain, at a cost of £ 64,000/-. The firm will construct a house to accommodate their British staff while working here as it is probable that their engineers will remain in Bahrain for at least 18 months. 2. I shall be grateful if the India Supply Commission can be asked to assist Holloway Brothers in procuring and shipping the the material required. = REPGU = The issue of the above has been authorised. Under Secretary to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf• 4 MFP—1014 S*P—(M.1645)—29-11-39—400,000.Copy of letter No.B/SKM/EK dated 5th December, 1946, from Messrs. Holloway Brothers (London) Ltd., Bridge \7harf, Millbank, Westminster, S.W.I., to the Adviser to the Government, Bahrain. Manama Water Scheme* As you probably know, the supply of the principal constructional material in this country is at the present time controlled by the Ministry of Supply, and we have to obtain permission from them before placing our orders for the majority of the items we require for the above scheme• In addition, we have to obtain Export Licences from the Board of Trade before we can despatch to Bahrain. To enable our applications to be favourably consi dered, it is necessary for us to have in this country a Government Department, who have knowledge of the Contract, and who are prepared to answer any enquiries which night be addressed to them by the Ministry of Supply and/or the Board of Trade, and in effect, to act as a sponsor for the contract. Unless this procedure is carried out, we find it very difficult to obtain quick releases and shipment of materials, and our object in writing you is to ask if you will kindly advise - presumbaly the India Office - of the existence and extent of this contract, with a view to obtaining some assistance from them on the lines referred to above. We should also appreciate a copy of any communication you send in connection with this matter./ XT TELEPHONE; ABBEY 2827-8 TELEGRAMS: KENPARTNA-SOWEST. LONDON FOREIGN TELEGRAMS KENPARTNA,LONDON CODES: A.B.C'.S*? EDITION BENTLEYS, LONDON Q ^ 9 ^7 ... i. DIRECTORS: CART. C.E KENDALL PRAGNELLX BE ,D S O. G E PECK. F.C W A CHARLES KENDALL &amp; PARTNERS LIMITED 3 NORTH COURT, GREAT PETER STREET, LONDON, S. W. I PLEASE REFER TO CKI/21. 22nd January, 1947* My dear Harrison, I thought you might be interested to see the enclosed Quarterly statement which we send out to Baurain, showing the items we have been dealing with on their behalf and their present position. If you would care to keep this copy you may do so as we have a spare one here. Yours sincerely. F.A.K. Harrison, Usq., India Office, Whitehall, S.W.l.PU.-E -COPY, f E vt 1 1L2 pro To Rep -* .* -A. Q l - -. RXPRF^fi LETTISH . V &lt;€) f ^ * ia&amp;K l t°^ q 0 0 / i political, Bahrain. Foreign, New Delhi. Inpia Office, London/ (C/1046) .Pjolitical Resident, Bahrain.C/1047. Accountant General, Central Revenues, New Delhi.C/1048. No.c/1045. Dated the 17th September, 1946. Your Express Letter No^D.769- ! '^^^!r'~^.BPG/46 dated 24th August, 1946. Passage expenses P-f\. of Mr. and Mrs. Tunnicliffe. 2 * The sum of Rs.1,013.5.0 has been recovered from the Bahrain Government and credited to Accountant General, Central Revenues. 2 ( &gt;( u Sd./- J.E.H. HUDSON for political Agent, Bahrain. Attested. for Assistant Political Agen Bahrain. NSTelephone i MAYFAIR 7678, Telegrams ■ JET r * BRITISH IRON 8c STEEL COI ATION LIMITED. INLAND : EXPORSTEEL. AUDLCY. LONDON*. \ OVERSEAS : EXPORSTEEL. LONDON. DIRECTORS : THE RT. HON. THE EARL OF DUDLEY. M.C. (CHAIRMAN). ARTHUR DORMAN (DEPUTY CHAIRMAN). SIR 8. R. BEALE. K.B.E. J. B. COWPER. C.A. SIR JOHN CRAIO. C.B.E. SIR JOHN M. DUNCANSON. J. E. JAMES. O. H. LATHAM. A. J. PEECH. CAPT. A. H. READ (GENERAL MANAGER). b632 1 EXPORT DEPARTMENT. 7, PARK LANE, Your ref ^gt . 5-3 -72/46. LONDON, W.1 Sales, FTT/j our ref r. . (WHICH PLEASE QUOTE IN REPLY). 16th Au jast, 1946 The Under Secretary of State for India Department, India Office* London.S.W.l* Dear Sir, Bahrein State Government - Sections. Charles Kendall &amp; Partners Ltd. We are in receipt of your letter of the 15th instan t, enclos ing formal order from Messrs • Kendall &amp; Partners for about 56-J tons Joists, and note your remarks. We appreciate the desirability of meeting this requirement but our allocation has been taken up for the remainder of this year. Further, the Government has been forced to curtail Export deliveries during July,August, and s eptember, which will put an •xcaptionally heavy load on to Period 4, and even though there may be an improvement in Period 4 deliveries.some of the tonnages specified will have to be carried over into 194. • However, we are accepting this order for delivery in Period 2, 1947, subject to Government having issued to us Authorisation for the Period indicated. _ We have informed Messrs. T 'endj Yours fait! for BRITISH IROK &amp; AUG19W Partners accordingly. .ATI m LTD.MTM 29 Tel. No.: VICcoria 3811. Ext. Any further communication on this subject should be addressed . r' and tne following number if quoted : DlHoJCITQiiA.TK OP DISPOSALS (R.E) MINISTRY OF SUPPLY^g^ GT. WESTMINSTER HOUSE HORSEFERRY ROAD LONDON, S.W.I. quoceo: O’ It ! 5526 ^ Your reference 1 9tjh rLE COP v August , 1946 Dgws^ kr._ Harri&amp;QCUu.i In reply to y our letter d ated &amp;i&gt;'0 3rd August, it is the policy on disposal of surplus equipment that the manufacturer or his accredited agent has the first opportunity to hid. In the case of Caterpillar No. 12 Graders, these are offered to Messrs. Jack Olding &amp; Go., Ltd*, Hatfield, and up to date all machines have been disposed of to above firm. Messrs. Charles Kendall &amp; Partners were advised to keep in touch with Messrs. Jack Olding &amp; Co.hQ(c*j£ / y Ext. y*. 72 A6. !3/k August, 19m6. Gentlemon, I abi dirocted by the Secretary of State to refer to your letter to laosare* Charles Kendall &amp; Partners, Ltd., No. G-A/^920.S/lH of 5th JUly regarding an order for Scales placed on behalf of the -dofarcin Government; Bsrslan Gulf. In view of the desiriibiiity, on political founds, of crating the Bahrein Government’s orders for supplies froa this country, tiic ileoretary of State would bo grateful for anything you vati do with a view to expediting the delivery of thuae goods. I am, centlcmen; lour obedient Servant; I’STA. k. Harrison jjQGGrs. W. &lt;1 T. Avery, Ltd., Overseas Department; Soho foundry; Piiwinghwo*file -copy © CHARLES KENDALL &amp; 'PARTNERS~~’LIMITED aV'f /r. Ul 3 NORTH COURT, GREAT PETER STREET, LONDON, S.W.I { YOUR - CHI/21. PLEASE REFER TO nH Dear Hr,Harrison, The Bahrain State Government, Persian Gulf Supplies of STKEL SMJTIQNS,AM) SCALES V/ith further reference to the conversation which Captain Kendall had with you regarding the difficulty in getting orders accepted for reasonable delivery etc., he asks -hat we should send you copies of the orders we now wish to place for Steel Sections and scales. In 'the case of the Steel Sections, we have this morning received a letter from the British Iron and Steel Corporation (per copy enclosed) re uming our order. Hay we, therefore, ask if you will kindly lend your support to our request for these Sections, as you did formerly in April last. With regard to the Scales, we are asked by Bahrain to try and get an improved delivery promise, for you will notice that they mention 60 weeks and 45 weeks as being the best they can do. Thanking you in anticipation of any as si tance v/hich you can give us in an endeavour to get these goods through for the State Government of Bahrain. Yours faithfully, CHARLES KEHDALL &amp; PAK .NEKS LDCCTKD. ( for and on beb F*A.K.Harrison,Esq* India Office, Whitehall,S.W.1* MANA6IN8 AQENT8 AND SECRETARIES INDUSTRIAL MISSIONS A INTELLIGENCEfkitish iron &amp; sthel corporation lmtkd, Your Ref: CRl/l8 Our Ref: SALES/JG/VB Export Leps-rtment, 7, Park Lane, London, W.l. (dated) 8th ugust, ISk-G* Ivie^srs.Charles Kendall &amp; Partners Ltd, 3,Korth Court, Great Peter Street, Lono.on, S.W.l. Dear Sirs, THE BAHRAIN STATE GOVERNMENT, PERSIAN GULP : SECTIONS. We are in receipt of your letter of 7th inst., with order L.3A« which we regret having to re cum herewith as we are unable to accept meantime. Steel for export is under allocation from the Government, and our quota does not permit of further sales for delivery this year. Further the current curtailment by the Government of Steel deliveries for export makes the prospect of quoting for new business remote. We regret, therefore, we cannot give any indication as to when we shall be in a position to offer for 19V7 delivery. Yours faithfully, for BRITISH IRON &amp; STEEL CORPO ATION LTD. (signed) J. Grainger,COPY Fran : CHAELES KEKDALL cS: PARTI^SRS LIi-ZCTilD, 3,North Court, Great Peter Street, CEI/18 London, S • W # 1 • 7th August, lSh-6. Dear Sirs, THE BAH AIN S .'AIE GOVESl'lIviEN 1 !, PEl^SIAN GDIF, STEEL SECTIONS. Further to our order No.L.2?. of 6th May, 192 ^ 6 , we have now heard, fran ;he State Government of Balirain concerning the other items whach they required but about which we had to raise queries, as they had not given us sufficient infoimation to allow us to include the items on our order as above. We therefore enclose a further order No.L.34, da .ed ?th August, and trust that you v/ill be able to obtain the necessary allocation for this, and if so, perhaps you will be kind enough to advise us the Period allotted. Yours faithfully, CHA.Ho KENDALL &amp; PARTNERS LE ECTED. (signed) G.E. PECK. . DIEECTCB &amp; SECHEfAPY. The British Iron &amp; Steel Corporation Ltd, Export Department, 7, Park Lane, W.l.- -ra»' t ~ .'.'■wi''; ;• •• •. — •’■- 7' CONDITIONS ♦ 2. The quantity ordered must not be exceeded without our permission in writing and any charges incurred will be debited to the supplier. month must re^ch us at latest within five days of the end of the month. 4. We will not be responsible for orders unless tbey are issued on jjrinted forms duly signed. ^ » . 5. Immediate notification must be giver of any. anticipated delay in adhering to the schedule of deliveries laid down;1 • r\ CONDITIONS 1. Written acceptance of this order and the conditions govemjng it mpst be made 2. The quantity ordered must not be exceeded without our permission in writing having first been obtained as otherwise goods sent in excess may be returned and any charges incurred will be debited to the supplier. * 3 * 6. In the case of failure to deliver the goods within the stipulated time and in compliance with the above conditions, this order may be cancelledLt. Colonel A.G. Bell, R.E. D.R.E. 12, Gt. Westminster House, Horseferry Road, 52 yo/ztC, niAFT LETTER !NDEXJED Ext. Ttb-Ji* y4U -3 AUG 1546 je are informed by Messrs. Charles T&lt;V-f»V«y«-S Kendall and Oempany, Purchasing Agents in the United Kingdom for the Goverrment of Si iaf'i t-d4U-^ Vic €*J\ Bahrein, that they have been instructed to obtain for that Govemnent,if possible, a Caterpillar Road Grader and Scarifier from surplus Military stocks, and that they have approached you in this connection. I understand that your letter D.R.E. 12/A/GKC/141 of 17th June refers. # V I wrote to say that, if this equipment is available, this Office wculd like to give the application its support, as our policy in matters of this kind is to give ^ ^ 'k* 1 ® Persian Gulf Sheikhdoms whatever help we can^ t CvA ^ we can^ t CvA ~ cb/i* ^- ci*i kJuJi 4 3^U- l ^ti4rirt&gt;oere&lt;». TTA. K. HARRISON*' - 3 XI In 1932 the Government of India ordered that in all cases where Rulers of the Gulf States show a desire to engage the services of Europeans, and also of Iraqis, Syrians, Palestinians, Egyptians and natives of North Africa in positions of importance, a report should be made to them beforehand vide copy of P &amp; P Department letter attached. 2. I am inclined to think that these orders are now somewhat out of date and that it should be left to the Bolitical Resident to insist on prior information being given him of such appointments to such extent as he may consider necessary and to refer to H.M.G. and the Government of India only where the appointments are of outstanding importance (e.g. appointments of Chief Ministers or Financial Advisers) or when it is desirable to make enquiries regarding the antecedents of the persons to be appointed. For instance it hardly seems necessary to trouble the Government of India with prior information regarding the appointment of European nurses in the Bahrein State Hospital. Se*,. . (Sd.) W.R.Hay 20.7.46.DRAFT LETTER The Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Department, New Delhi, Ext.4985/46 2 c ml iw Copy Political Resident, Persian Gulf, I am directed by the Secretary a of State for to enclos^/copies of appointment of Mr. Tunnicliffe as Assistant State Engineer, Bahrein. , / P-nm to a ay fcha,t a sum of £76 has been paid by the High Commissioner and debited in his account with this Office in respect of the passages of Mr. and Mrs.'Tunnicliffe from Hull to Port Said. , A debit of £J6 has/been included/in the Inward Account Current /with/v\ Ik? ' file copy i ^9b5 loiq The Secretary^ External Department. 48 A sum of £7^:-:- has been paid by the High Commissioner, and debited in his account with this Office in respect of the cost of the passages of Mr, &amp; Mrs. R.D.Campbell Tunnicliffe from Hull to Port Said, on the appointment of Mr.Tunnicliffe as Assistant State Engineer, Bahrein. In reporting this amount to the Government of India for recovery from the Bahrein Government, perhaps you will be good enough to say that a debit of £76:-:- has been included in the Inward Account Current with the Accountant General, Central Revenues, for March 1946 (Final), under the head 'Miscellaneous: Items adjustable in India'. A copy of your letter would be appreciated by this Department. &gt; &lt;4-,^FILE 'SOPV Office of the »-&lt; Po^tfcajL Resident, Persian *' 3a!np» Bahrain, )th June 1946. 1 7« *''-¥*s**V V AGhlf , Please refer to your demi-official letter Ho. Ext . 3411/ 46 dated the 17th May 19 46 about the recruitment of European employees for the Bahrain Government. 2. Galloway has reached an amicable under- standing with Belgrave and the matter may be considered as closed* 3. I am sending a copy of this letter to Weightman. E.P. Donaldson Esquire, C.M.G., The India Office, LONDON.»*• FOREIGN T PILE copy E: ABBEY &lt;627&lt;8 fRAM8: KENPARTNA, 80WEST, LONDON FOREIGN TELEGRAMS: KENPARTNA, LONDON CODES : A.B.C., 6TH EDITION BENTLEYS, LONDON DIRECTORS : CAPT. C. E. KENDAU COLONEL T. W. PRAQNELL, O.B.E., D.8.0. G. E. PECK, F.C.W.A. CHARLES KENDALL &amp; PARTNERS LIMITED 3 NORTH COURT, GREAT PETER STREET, LONDON, S.W.I f YOUR / U CKL/21. PLEASE REFER TO ■ 24th Hay, 1946* Dear Hr.Karrison, The Bahrain itate Government, Persian Gulf. ESSEX BOARD, With reference to the conversation v/hich 'Jap tain Kendall recently had with you, regarding the difficulty we are experiencing in obtaining certain goods inquired by the State Government of Bahrain. You v/ill no doubt recall that you promised to support our applications v/here necessary. . We are very glad to report that the letter you kindly arranged to l send to the British Iron &amp; Steel Corporation in support of our order for Rolled Steel Joists, had the desired effect and enabled us to obtain \ a quota for Bahrain. We are now, however, in trouble over Essex Board, which we have ordered f ran the Thames Board Mils Ltd., and who have promised us delivery within two to three weeks providing we can obtain an Export Licence. We have this morning received a communication from the Expojij Licensing Department of the Board of T:ade stating that they are unable to grant us a Licence for the required Essex Board. We should be very grateful, therefore, if you would be kind enough to send the Board of Trade, Export Licensing Department,at t-, Fenchurch Avenue,E.C.3. a similar letter to the one which you sent to The British Iron &amp; Steel Corporation in support of our application. So that you may be fully informed on the mat er, we enclose herewith copy of our actual Application for a Licence sent to the Board of Trade on 1st May, and a copy of their reply received today. Thanking you in anticipation of any assistance you can give us endeavour to get the necessary Licence, Yours faithfully, (for and on behalf ofvjhe ;,ate_Go int A. K. Karri son. Esq* India ..Office,. S.W.I. tT . , ;.Ev Df^Balirain) AND SECRETARIES INDUSTRIAL MISSIONS 4 INTELLIGENCETelephone : l.Lansion House 4-555 BOARD OP TRADE. Export Licensing Department, 4,Fenchurch Avenue, Any communication respecting London,E.0.3* this matter should be add-.essed HE CON ROLLER quoting Official ief, 73 / 8296 / 76/21 Your ef. CIH/lB. Export of ESSEX BOARD to PERSIAN GRIP Gentlemen, With reference to your application for Export Licence referred to above, I am to inform you that your application has received careful consideration. I am, however, to express regret that a Licence cannot be issued for the Export of these goods. I am, Gentlemen, Your obedient Servant, (signed) W.W. Humphreys. Messrs.Charles Kendall &amp; Partners Ltd,Applicant’s reference No. CEL/18 COPY. BOARD OF TRADE Export Licensing Department Official reference No. PART I. Application for Export Licence TWO CARBON COPIES should in every case be attached to the application. Before completing this form, you advised to read carefully the instructions and notes on the back cHhEles ksnuall &amp; pakciiers lb, re ed Consignor’s PUTu’XiiJl’, and address.„... 3*North Court G-reat: Pe ter Street,S. f .l. __ Has any previous application for an export licence been made in respect of these goods or any part of them? If so, give the Depart-j mental reference number. No. 3. Have you a firm order for the goods? Yes. 5 . Give any information (other than that affecting ordinary business) in support of your application, e.g., details of Import Licence. Certificate of Essentiality or the like, or if approved by a U.K. Government Dept., quote Depart mental reference number and/or raw material permit number. 2. Are the goods manufactured and ready for shipment ? If not, at what approximate date will they be ready? 4. Proposed date of despatch of goods. Required by- the State Government of Bahrain,Persian Gulf in connection trith urgent Government building work. I HEREBY DECLARE that to the best of my knowledge and belief all the particulars in this application (including any accompanying schedules) are correctly stated, and I undertake that if a licence is granted to me, it shall be used solely icr the export of goods being my own property or the property of a person, firm or company named above as consignoi for whom I am authorised to act in this transaction as the sole responsible representative. I am aware that the exporter or shipper of the exported goods, if so required by the Commissioners of His Majesty’s Customs and m ust produce to them, within such time as they may allow, proof to their satisfaction that the said goods were duly delivered at the destinat.on named in the licence. For and on behalf of CHAHLES KBjD&amp;LL &amp; Form must be signed in accordance with the Instruction overleaf. If the signatory has been specially approved to sign applications on behalf of his firm, quote here official number of the letter approving him for the purpose. Signature Qualification LXLLBYGR. -IS-t-Maff., Date Applicant’s reference No. CRI/18 l&gt;ART II. BOARD OF TRADE Export Licensing Department Official reference No. (E) 1 his document will be effective as an Export Licence only when it has been validated by the Board of Trade For the purposes of any Order prohibiting the exportation of goods from the United Kingdom issued by the Board of Trade, under the Import, Export, and Customs Powers (Defence) Act, 1939, the Board of Trade * ^ mnui &amp; pas , rajs let ?jsd (Consignor s name.„.._..LXI).m]XxI...Xnaia.QX.-.B.Q.^-.(I...,.xlLG. jT;:rI. m VI r .u.e±»Eaaex) and address) t to export from any port in the United Kingdom, or by Post from a Head or Branch Post office (see note overleaf) of twelve months from the date of this Licence, to within a period luxury overseas, ^ the following goods, namely: Quantity [see instructions overleaf] Full description of the goods F.O.B. value of each item £ 106 cwrt S. . ES5LK BOARD (Gray) „ 4800 sq.ft. j/lfl’ per sq. C 400 ' ' B'xL'xyiff' _ _ _ _5600 ' ' 12' x U? x yi6” (Furnish 25^o Grorq) 114 - - J5&amp; Gro^p. 13 ) . • 0 • 0 • tn c\ H Total F.O.B. value by Order of THE BOARD OF TRADE. E. W. REARDON, Controller, Export Licensing Department. This licence is not an authority for doing any act the doing of which would, except under such an authority, constitute an offence of trading with the enemy. Dealings with persons who are enemies are prohibited under the Trading with the Enemy Act, 1939. The term 'enemy’ includes persons in ihe current List of Specified persons issued by the Board of Trade under Section 2 (2) of the Act194 M47293/3917 250M 1/46 JW 52-7562 Instructions for Completing this Form Non-compliance with these Instructions may involve delay. 1. Applicants for export licences are requested in their own interests to have the form filled up fully and correctly (preferably typewritten), and to give as long a notice as possible of their desire to export. In particular, they are advised not to put in hand the production of goods which will need to be specially manufactured for a particular order unless and until the export licence has been granted. 2. REFERENCE NUMBERS. Applicants should date and number their applications on the lines provided in Parts I and II and quote this date and number in any further communication (as well as the official reference number, if known). Further communications can be dealt with more expeditiously if they relate to one application only. 3. RULES TO BE OBSERVED AS REGARDS LISTS Or GOODS. In order to avoid delay the following rules should be carefully observed: (a) Not more than one item should appear on each line provided in the table. (b) Where the number of items exceeds the space pro vided in Part II, three copies of a schedule giving particulars of the additional goods should be furnished. (c) The information required under each heading should be given as accurately as possible. (d) Quantities and values must be given in the denomination used in the Board of Trade official Trade Returns, e.g., 'cwts.,'’ or “galls.,” etc., as the case mav be and not under vague descriptions such as “cases,” barrels,” “bags.” etc. WARNING. 4. SIGNATURE OF FORM. The declaration in Part I must be signed and dated by a person domiciled in the United Kingdom, otherwise the application cannot be accepted. The signature should be that of the applicant, or, in the case of a firm or company, that of a partner, director, secretary, or other person who is entitled to make such a declaration on behalf of the firm or company. In all cases the status of the signatory should be indicated. In exceptional circumstances applications m; l ~ lj be otherwise signed if reasons which are regarded ns adfciiuate are submitted, in writing, to the Export Licensing Depart ment and full responsibility is accepted for the person whose signature is allowed. In such cases the Export Licensing Department number of the approval musWl-e quoted in the space provided in Part I. Application must always be made by the merchant, manufacturer, or other person who is directly interested as consignor in the export and not by a forwarding agent or other person on behalf of the actual exporter. 5. IMPORTANT. DESPATCH OF LICENCE. The name and address of the person or company to whom the licence is to be sent must be inserted in the space provided below, and the application (except as otherwise arranged for individual trades) sent to: The Controller Export Licensing Department, Board of Trade, 4, Fenchurch Avenue, London, E.C.3. 1. Penalties may be imposed in respect of false statements in applications. 2. Goods subject to licence must not be sent forward for shipment without an export licence having been obtained. Heavy penalties (including the forfeiture of the goods) may be incurred for offences against the regulations. 3. There are restrictions on the importation of certain goods into some countries and the issue of this Export Licence does not relieve the consignee from complying with the regulations (if any) in force in the country of destination. 4. Where a licence is granted for the export of gooo's the licence docs not relieve the owner of the goods or the consignor or other person to whom the licence is granted from any responsibility to which he may be subject for any breach of law or regulations. * {see Note below) In case of non-delivery, return to EXPORT LICENSING DEPARTMENT. Board of Trade, 4, Fenchurch Avenue. London. E.C.3. * Insert name and address of person or company to whom licence is to be sent. The above space must not be used for the transmission of the application to the Export Licensing Department. OQ T J1 £-2 UK So '(Leo £ 'd a) 2 2 &lt;V £ w bib O O °.t! e G g 0-0 eSW toe*' -a u o-g PS 3 sS £ e O, hrX3 P .2 *o ‘V O ^ ‘V a.&gt; r-s V. x 3 ” 5 e j r* ^ -4 C ^ *3 O :! gstxiis S 'd iv: , 2 ot 'a! . ' ^ ^ - 0 S'd a&gt; JH OT &lt;u S x: 31^ c-S-gs T5 ° « xe £* &gt;&gt; - &lt;n « o.e.2 o c O ” s P o 3 e S p,'' c ” o S o o o £ wo Q-e « o os •p-&lt; 5 O 0^,4 jZ d 'd 5 s o-- 0,71 o &gt;&gt;o. JO V. OT d W O g 4- c CP o S. 53 -o a) ? S £ S bae-wj £ o S ^ m S Sr-i 135 3 &gt; ° o O?, o E «)«»-&lt; fl.S a. d ^ m O ff! O C3 &gt;&gt;W 71 o. &gt;.wc, bbg-g'Effp-gxw M® o o o e e 3 o g-w o a: go® b w o^ « v ^ ; r3:^g.2 3 2^3 - J C « &lt;V ^5 et*- 2 ^ i o c. -H ■-g iJ o' K H 5fa o O OTp fj pH ex ^ ^ ot ox o ^2 o &gt;&gt;P£ jso —oo® ex:h&gt;—'3oS2 0 '4)0® HET^SlH^g'OO-So'Sg- S S’ I'fe'd Wfa^ 3 02 o £ s * •rX s a&gt; pl|l 3-0 ^ - CD o o S OS'®--. 5 o 2 ^ 3 3 a o. 3Draft Paper. 0 department. csi- &amp;£. ■:u # &amp;~7-b) -^7 *. It Va / lo^ i ') i/^ &lt; L*yr J»J* * L^ys ^ , , \ 7 &lt;V j h/y ip Ext.g?^=A6&gt; ^/z/^/ /i tvuA jj ** jiUA** Jr A, ^ &lt; C^u uo. T hmre ni'^t^nn Irn-ffr i Jilmnn rhmit .yoig* d.o.letter No,338-3 of 29th March about the recruitment of European employees for the Bahrein Government by Belgrave while he was on leave in this country . and, with his concurrence,-5 am sending you the following ropIy»— 2* We had no intention here of short- circuiting the local political authorities by helping Belgrave to recruit staff and *? were certainly under the impression that he had already informed the Political Agent of his intention to recruit an Assistant State Engineer in this country, j CWe therefore secured the best advice available on Tunnicliffe*s engineering qualifications and went to some trouble c4olki++j in securing a passage for him. The now mnit«ien far the Bahrein jS* u An* ) H4*V» £ vjYjlyX/ Government Heepit'ily/was mentioned in the Political Agents telegram of the 22nd July 3o'tMo»P Xc 1945/s*^^© put Belgrave in touch with the dW •/£* IrTLu Overseas Nirrsing Association whs wore able to recommend a suitable candidate. ' (~of’ i+'tsk ,hkv\t*M+ meg really/no time to get the Political Agents view on the appointment befeare it” frW&amp;f A A AM*t6uF $ * In any case, I do not think (10337)' Wt.l4054/l\164 10,000 u/39 A.&amp; E.W.Ltd. Gp.685 (11704) \Vt.2009C/P.283 10,000 9/39 that could have questioned a /r eccmmendat ionPILE cnoy ^^^uPHrOyiTTIlL. 3 4 i i fas' s * 6*~@sS~T &lt;P*~ External Affairs Dep&amp;rtment, Nev/ Delhi 3, Die my 1946. Will you please refer to your letter No. Ext.2731/46 of the 23rd April 1946 in which you discuss Prior’s action in relation to the recruitment of Suropeen employees ty the Bahrain Government without previous reference to the Political Agent? I am inclined to agree with you that Prior has made rather too much of this particular matter, and strictly speaking he v#s not on safe ground in demanding that prior sanction should be obtained to the engagement of &amp;*itish or foreign personnel by the British Adviser of a n Asrab Huler. Indeed our letter of the 2nd March 1932 to which you refer recognises that fact by implication. On the other hand I should not like to see the imp r* ssion given that Belgrave or any one similarly situated need not consult the Political Agent on matters of this nature. The outlook of a man in his position is necessarily circumscribed and h&lt;? ought as a mattsr of course to consult His Majesty’s Government’s local representative who is a ole to take a broader and more detached view - and to appreciate possible consequences more clearly. Another case which Prior bes brought to your notice in his demi-official letter No. 1454-13/3-s. 23 of the 9th April 1946, though not strictly on &amp;1I— fours with the present issue under consideration, is illustrative of iqy point. 2. The obvious solution is of course a clear under standing ^ between the Agency and the Adviserate/knt the latter will always consult the former in such matters before finalising any agre ment. In the ordinary course of events such an understanding need not be in writing , but if I can rely on rather ancient memories of aahraifi x ,| I think I am right in saying that this is far from / being the first instance of its kind there and I in^gine need for Galloway to write to Belgr©ve officially has arisen from Belgrave’s disregard of such an understanding. 3. . In general therefore my view is that in the ordinary course of events mutual understanding of the importance of consultation is sufficient, that the formal communication which prior instructed Galloway to make to Belgrave is not o&amp;sed on any very sound -l oundation, but that if it succeeds in r^-establishing the- principle of prior consultation no hai^n has bs A n ~ done . -33/2-5.MANAGING AGENTS AND SECRETARIES INDUSTRIAL MISSIONS A INTELLIGENCE DIRECTORS : CAPT. C. E. KENDALL COLONEL T. W. PRAONELL, C.B.E., 0.8 0. 6. E. PECK, F.C.W.A. CHARLES KENDALL &amp; PARTNERS LIMITED 3 NORTH COURT, GREAT PETER STREET, LONDON, S.W.I RtfER TO { iT CKLl/21 3rd May, 1946. TELEPHONE : ABBEY t627-8 TELEGRAMS: KENPARTNA, 80WE8T, LONDON FOREIGN TELEGRAMS: KENPARTNA, LONDON CODES : A.B.C., 5TH EDITION BENTLEYS, LONDON Sir, The Bahrain State Govemmeni;, Persian Gulf. We have the honour to acknowledge receipt of your leister Ref.KXT.2924/M&gt;, dated 2 nd May, enclosing copy of letter of even reference and date, addressed by you on our behalf to ihe British Iron &amp; Steel Corporation. We are most grateful for your help in this matter and trust that the necessary Symbol will now be allotted for the supply of the Rolled Steel Joists required by the State Government of Bahrain. Y/e are, Sir, Yours faithfully, CHARLES KENDALL &amp; PARTNERS LIMITED Captain C.E.Kendall. DIRECTOR. E.P.Donaldson, Esq. Secretary, External Depar jnent, India Office, ,/hi t ehall, S.W. 1 •TELEPHOME : ABBEY *627-8 TELEGRAMS : KENPARTNA, 80WE8T, V FOREIGN TELEGRAMS: KENPARTNA, LONDON CODES : A. B. C., 6TH EDITION BENTLEYS, LONDON DIRECTORS : DAFT. €. E. KENDALL COLONEL T. W. PRAONELL, O.B.E., D S D. G. I. PECK, F.C.W.A. CHARLES KENMArfct~'&amp; ' PARTNERS LIMITED 3 NORTH COURT, GREAT PETER STREET, LONDON, S.W.I Kxt. 2619/46 CRI/21. 24th April, 1946, PLEASE REFER TO YOUR OUR Sir, The Bahrain State Government, Persian Gulf. ROLLED STEEL JOISTS. We hive the honour to acknowledge your letter of 16 th April# for wiiich we thank you. i&lt;e note the procedure regarding the allocation of iron and steel and freedom of action granted to the Industry u to Accept those orders which offer them the greatest long term of interest”. As the requirements of the Bahrain State Government are unlikely to offer a long term interest to the Iron and Steel Industry, it would appear that the chances of getting the small quantity of Steel Joists now required for urgent Government building work, are extremely remote. Yle have already been in touch with the British Iron and Steel Corporation, and it was at their suggestion that we are endeavouring to obtain the support of your Department in order to acquire an allocation for the Steel Joists' / required. In this connection, we at ach herewith copy of letter received by us fran tire British Iron and S eel Corporation. Y/e would respectfully suggest, therefore, if the Department consider that the Rolled Steel Joists are neces ary for the Bahrain State Government, that you should give us a recommendation with which we can go back to the British Iron &amp; Steel Corporation to place an order to meet the require*aents of the Y/e have the honour to be. Sir, Your obedient Servants, (for and on behalf and with the authority of The Bahrain State Government) X * As— \vy\ /Ujf ^ o\ O, T U- U- [, • ^ r~! tx. 0 X ^ luJ\ in) \o‘»\ ^ .C /r V. CHARLES KHIBALL &amp; PARTNERS LlidliED. The Sccretaiy, India Office,Whitehall, 3*W«1. Captain C.E.Kendall. DIRECTOR. / Enc. MANAOIHG AGENTS AND SECRETARIES INDUSTRIAL MISSIONS * INTELLIGENCECOPT. £ X T 2924 94R Kef: Sales FWT/KS. Dear Sirs, The British Iron &amp; Steel Corporation Limited, Export Department, 7, Park Lane, London, V/.l. 29 th March, 1946. 3AKIIA1II SECTICTiS. We thank you for your letter of 21st -arch and would inform you that the allocation referred to in previous correspondence comes under Symbol B.T.5. through the Board of Trade. We suggest that you endeavour to obtain official backing from t; e India Office, on receipt of ■which we will give the matter further consideration. Yours faithfully for BRITISH IROK &amp; STEEL COKPQRATION LTD. Me srs.Charles Kendall &amp; Partners Limited. 3, North Court, Great Peter Street, London,S.W.l.V Dmr iTior, Ext, 2859/^6. Would you ple&amp;ao rofer to your &lt;X*o m letter ?5o.l4f^-lj/&gt;. 3.2^ of 9th April rogardiqg tno agro«nwnt executed hy Bel^rave with Meesr ^^‘tiarlos Kendall and 1 arfcners Li/alted, A. ;*xLgre.va wrote to us on 17th Deoerber last enoloaluc tixi draft of an «groeeo?it with the fin* for the aoot port in tiie fotia finally executed excert that it proridod for the firm actli^ sl^Oy os .'Uroiiaaiqg agents, but not os egclusiwe purchasing a^renta, of to Balireiat C^T®r&gt;ioe»tt In this oounti^*. la referred the draft o^reoaen to the iegal Adviser and K. &lt;f; 0. Dopartiaaeit uere, and returned it to Beignare with certain draftlr^ suggestions. In our letter to him w suggested that it would be as well if he obtained ti*» ioUtlool Agant** u^reenent to the arbitration clause boftore tlie agreMHl was fixaally signed, mod suggested tint he would be able to do this cm hi return. we gathered subsoquently that the Ot^reenent hod b&amp;xi n*&gt; if in the light of our ooanents, and that in order to get it fixed up while he was hare (Belgrade was meet anxious that the firm should ge with the purohaging of the Bahrein Coremaent 9 &amp; urgofit requiraiont g) Belgmwe was proposing to sign the agreement, but to pronride in it that the arbitration clause should be subject to the agreement of th &gt; olitioal Agsnt. Tiiis e pe&amp;rs in the final text. 5. Uith rognnl to your oanwents, it is not strictly accurate to say that th© political Agent is to be an arbitrator. fhe proposal that he should appoint an arbitrator (e.g. acne iaaryer of experience in English oassaardal l«rj. In ax^' cose It doss not seem bo be neoessaiy, or eren correot, that an orbit ator shou?d rave the opportunity of acrutinisin; in advunoe an a^roa^ent on whiolt bo is expected to adjudicate. It would be even sore Improper if tiie arbitrator hod previously advised on the construction of the Inst run 10 ^ OJ A M OQ q * 4. With reference to paragraph 2 of your letter I oanoot boliepve that Bel grave did not realise that he had committed himself to obtal Ai ^he han 9 ble Sir G*Prior, K.G.X»^ t Persian Gulf Pea deo&lt;v, Buehira.iVs ^ iSxt.2859A6 DRAFT LETTER The Hon. Sir G. Prior, K.C.I.E., Persian Gulf Residency, Bushire •&gt;, ) f / 4 M At 1946 t J46 • - v .... v ' ^ . Dear Prior, j' ‘ • » v • ^ V «»• - - i ... Yfould you please refer to your d.o. letter No.1454-13/3*3.23 of 9th April regarding the agreement executed ty Belgrave with ifessrs. Charles Kendall &amp; Partners Ltd. 2* Belgrave wrote to us on 17th December last enclosing the draft of aji agreement with the ;i »/C w/ /x**- fin^in the form finally executed^ except that it provided for the firm acting singly as • V - .. v. ...a- . . « V. purchasing agents, 'but not as exclusive purchasing agents^ of the Bahrein Government in this country. We referred the draft agreement to the Legal Adviser and E^fc.O. Department here, and returned it to Belgrave with certain drafting suggestions. In our letter to him we suggested that it would 'be/mam t . be as well if he obtained the Political Agent* s agreement to the arbitration clause before the agreement was finally signed, and suggested that he would be able to do this on his return* We gathered subsequently that the agreement had been modified in the light oi^ comments, and that in order to get it fixed up while he was here (Belgrave was most anxious that the firm should get on with the purchasing of the Bahrein Government*s urgent requirements) Belgrave was proposing to sign the agreement, but to provide in it that the arbitration clause should be subject to the agreement of the Political Agent* This appears in the final text* , r £ t 3* With regard to your comments, it is incorrect to say that the Political Agent is to be an arbitrator. The proposal is that he should appoint an arbitrator (e*g. some lawyer of experience in English commercial law)* In any case it does not seen/seem to be necessary^or even correct^that an arbitrator should have the opportunity of scrutinising in advance an agreement on which jlr ^ Grvu* he is expected to adjudicate. ‘ . \ asUr\t&gt;&lt;'41!rJ lyjciS} S. p ^ 01 4* With reference to para. 2 of your letter I cannot believe that Belgrave did not realise that he had committed himself to obtaining all bis requirements from this country through the firm. Tho euurae of oanaliaing requireaents ^of^29th S entember. 192*^. We understand, however, from Captain Kendall that his fim are not intending to insist on this provision in every instance, but are at the moment more inclined to concentrate on obtaining the Bahrein Government's confidence ard good-will. As regards the amount of the should not ^regard this^oyself as excessive ~ (and/(and I am pretty sure that the firm do not do so) in view of the amount of work necessitated f even on quite small matters^by Government ccsitrols at the moment. In ai^' case the Bahrein Government are at liberty to terminate the agreement any time after the end of 1947 if they think they have made r€ a bad bargain. t With regard to your para. 3 our legal advice is that the agreement as it stands does not cover the recruitment of personnel., We have, however, made it clear to the film orally that the recruitment of personnel by them would not meet with our approval. You may wish a similar communication to be made to Belgrave if you think tArrvtk ^ , we are on sufficiently fim ground in doing so. Jn. I should like to add that our main object was to assist Belgrave in coming to an early and satisfactozy agreement to enable him to obtain for Kji Bahrein the goods of which we understood Bahreinj(r r to bd in most urgent need. On the financial side we thought that Belgrave should be able to look after/after himself, and in any case were doubtful of our powar of interference in a case where no political considerations appear to be involved# Cr€*. fLbrr*- I am sending a cop/ of this letter to India# Yet*** ** (Sgd) E. p/DONALDSO#Please see Sir Geoffrey Prior* s letter of the 9 th April below# I think it may be worth-while going some way back in the history of this business# * „ tffr 1# Colonel Galloway's telegram T /638 of 29th September^ (when he was Acting Resident) stated that he and the Political Agent ahrein ,were agreed that the Bahrein Gwemment' requirements should be canalized through onf^o^ercialr^charmel and that details of this caa^best be worked out on the spot (i#e# in London). (He also suggested an early meeting between Sir G. Prior and Mr.Belgrave. We passed this on to Sir G» Prior and he discussed the matter with Belgrave (my minute of 11th October) and told us only that he was intending to go into the matter further on his return to the Gulf# 'vJ+ys*? . //rye isuSu fuXfyx't nJvul /£ 2# On the 17th December (Ext# 68 / 48 ) Mr#Belgrave wrote enclosing a draft of an agreement with Captain Kendall.* s firm covering the formers acting as purchasing agents, but not as exclusive purchasing agents ; of the Bahrein Government in this country# We referred the draft agreement to the Legal Adviser and E#&amp; 0. Department and returned it to Belgrave with ccements# In our letter to him we suggested that it would be as well if he obtained the Political Agent's agreement to the provision for his arbitration before the agreement was finally signed and suggested that he would be able to do this on his return# I gathered subsequently from Captain Kendall that the agreement had been modified in the light of our comments and that in order to get it fixed up while he was here* Belgrave was proposing to sign the agreement but to provide in it that the arbitration clause should be subject to the agreement of the Political Agent# This was how it was finally signed and Mr#Belgrave seems at the same time to have agreed to the Company being made sole x /L W**- f(n ***** Ut' JiXL KLL4&gt; ] a* 4 #^ 4** f p- nt. /purchasing fr(r\(U t’ , (V*? k**?!' an fat /Li*. Jj *2 ' k sy . / . * jJjy • purchasing agents* 3* As regards Sir G» Prior* s comments, (1) as stated above we suggested that the Political Agent should be consulted on the arbitration clause in the agreement* This was left subject to the Political Agent* s agreement. (2) the Bahrein Government are to pay Messrs. Kendall five hundred a year plus an additional 2 ^' commission on the amount by which the total supplied in any one year exceeds £ 10 , 000 * There seems nothing particularly unreasonable in this. The Bahrein Government have a lot of orders on hand at the moment and £500 does not seem unreasonable in view of the amount of work necessitated by Government controls, etc. at the noment. I am doubtful whether the experience of the Government of India in regard to agreements by Indian States would be Particularly valuable in view of the special circumstances prevailing at the moment. Moreover the agreement is terminable by six, months notice after the end of next year. ( 3 ) I do not think the agreement could possibly be held to cover the recruitment of personnel but the Legal Adviser* s opinion on this might be obtained. 4. I suspect Captain Kendall has heard something from Belgrave as he has asked me to have lunch with him on Friday and will no doubt wish to discuss the question. $f'Uh- A-? *ir iUis* D.0.No. 1454-13/3.S.23. K - . A /. ' I l EXT 2859 04 Persian U ulf Residency, ^ Bushire, ^th April, 1946. f I enclose a copy of an agreement which Belgrave executed with a firm at home apparently after consultation with Harrison. We should have preferred to have been con sulted before it was negotiated, as the Government of India have experience of a number of Indian States who have made similar arrangements at home, and it would have been useful ^ to obtain their advice. You will have noticed that the ****1^^ l' Political Agent is to be^an arbitrator, and I feel that, he LX v&gt;' y ' r (H l(^ should have an opportunity of scrutinising in advance any agreements on which he is to be expected to adjudicate. 2. It will be seen from paragraph 2 that Belgrave has apparently bound himself to buy everything that the State requires in Great Britain and Northern Ireland through thjs firm even though it may be only a tooth-brush. He did not seem to realise this until I pointed it out to him, or to understand that he could not now order anything himself jbfsM***^ direct. The remuneration appears to me to be excessive, and in a normal year when expensive purchases of machinery etc. 4 ^ a sre not taking place the amount of £ 500 specified in para- ZSJ'»&gt; r -‘ 3 hi v-^ J j ' (f • graph 6 may greatly exceed the firms expenses. 3. I do not like the term n General Representatives*' in the second line, and feel that we should make it clear to both parties that we do not understand it to cover the recruitment of personnel. I am sending a copy of this letter to the Government of India.The Financial Adviser to the Sheikh of Bahrain. Dear Sir, We write to confirm that the terms upon which we will act as SUPPLY AGENTS AND GENERAL REPRESENTATIVES of the Bahrain State Government ( in this letter called 1 the Government*) in the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland ( in this letter called &lt;the territory’) as from the 1st January, 1946, are as follows 1) We will use our best endeavours to further the interests of the Government in the territory and will carry out and conduct on behalf of the Government such COMMERCIAL negotia tions and other business in the territory as may be required by you. 2) All requirements of the Government of whatever nature that the Government desires to satisfy by^,supply from or through the territory shall be passed in writing THROUGH US and we 1 endeavour to place orders or make other contracts AS INSTRUCTED BY YOU in your name and on your behalf for the satisfaction of such requirements. 3) We will provide, for officials of the Government who may be in London on temporary duty and without charge, such reasonable office and clerical facilities in our London Office as they may require in connection with their offic:a^ business• 4) We will pay our own day to -day expenses in connection with this representation but you will pay (a) any travelling, hotel and other expenses incurred by reason of our having to send representatives to any part of the territory or elsewhere outside a radius of 12 miles from our London Office for the time being necessitating their absence from our London Office for a period in excess of 8 hours, (b) packing, carriage, freight and other transport and shipping charges and insurance in respect of the shipment of goods, and (c) entertaining and any other expenses out of the ordinary course of our business that may be agreed between us from time to time. by you Expenses payable/hereunder shall be paid within one month of the date of the account which we will render to you in respect thereof. 5) As remuneration for our services you will pay us in each year calculated from the 1st January to 31st December the sum of £500 ( five hundred pounds } and a commission it the rate of 2± $ on the amount ( if any ) by which the total price of goods SUPPLIED TO YOU FROM THE TERRITORY BY OR THROUGH US in any such period shall exceed £10,000. 6) The said sum of £500 shall be paid to us by four equal instalments each of £125 ( one hundred and tw T enty-five pounds) on 1st January, 1st April, 1st July and 1st October, and as from the date AFTER which the commission referred to in / Paragraph (5) becomes- 2 - referred to in/ Paragraph (5) becomes payable, you will pay to us upon the placing of each order by us li % of the price of goods contained in such order, the remaining l-£ $ being payable by you at the same TIME AS YOU PAY FOR THE GOODS. 7) The expression ”price” shall include the price shown on the invoice rendered by the supplier to the Government and any sum in respect of packing, carriage, freight and other transport and shipping charges, insurance, royalties, discounts and commissions but shall exclude any commission payable to us and import duties. 8) All sums payable by you to us hereunder shall be paid in sterling at the London Office of the Eastern Bank Limited. 9) In the absence of instructions to the contrary all orders and contracts which we place for you shall be in your name and shall be expressed to be signed by us on your behalf and with your authority, and payment shall be madeby you in sterling at the London Office of the Eastern Bank Limited, against delivery of shipping documents, and particulars of the price as defined in Clause 7. 10) These arrangements shall continue in force until the 31st December, 1947, and thereafter until determined by either party not less than six months' previous notice in writing to expire at that date or any date thereafter. 11) This Agreement shall be construed in accordance with English Law and if any dispute or differences shall arise between us,the matter shall be referred in writing to AN ARBITRATOR APPOINTED BY the British Political Agent in Bahrain ( SUBJECT TO HIS AGREEMENT ) whose decision shall be final and binding on both of us. 12) Will you kindly signify your acceptance of these terms by signing the duplicate copy of this letter at the foot thereof, and returning it to us. Yours faithfully, for and on behalf of MESSRS. CHARLES KENDALL AND PARTNERS LTD., Sd. C.E. Kendall. Managing Director. On behalf of the Bahrain State Government I hereby accept the above terms and agree that such Government shall be bound by the conditions thereof. ^ Sd. C. Dalrymple Belgrave. Adviser to the Bahrain Government.&lt;r Draft Paper. Department. T^or. H T S' EXT. 2731/46 23 A 'R 1946 Will you please refer to Prior* refer to Prior’s d.o.letter of the 29 th March No.338-S about the recruitment of European employees | for the Bahrein Government without previous reference to the Political Agent. 2. We are content to be guided by the Government of India in this matter, but I cannot help feeling that Prior is making rather heavy weather over it. The letter of 2nd March 1932, of which he enclosed a copy, said that the Government of India 'consider^ it desirable' that they should be informed beforehand when the rulers of the Arab States wished to engage the services of Europeans but did not lay this down as a binding reauirement. 'Hus British adviser of an Arab ruler should^ for the engagement in this country of individual British subjects, ukrm about tH rh the political authorities in the Gulf 2 aonn ^*y form a Judgment. V W pity that fin has authorised Galloway to make an official communication to Belgrave in the sense suggested in paragraph 4 of this can hardly /improve (10337) \Vt.l4051/P.164 10,000 6/39 A.&amp; E.W.Ltd. Gp.685 (11764) \Vt.26696/P.282 10,000 9/39I enclose a copy of a letter No. C/258 dated the 6th March 1946 from Galloway regarding the recruitment by Belgrave ofJB uropean employees for the Bahrain S tate wi thout previous reference to the Political Agent. / 2. I discussed the question with Belgrave on my recent visit to Bahrain and did not find his explanation very convincing, and I was left with the impression that he merely brought in the India Office as a stalking horse to excuse his short-circuiting the local political authorities. 3. As will be seen from the enclosed copy of Foreign and Political Beaartment letter No. D. 839-N/32, dated the 2nd »» y x u arch 1932, the Government of India require that previous reference ’fit')' should be made to them in cases in which the Arab Shaikhdoms v/ish to engage the services of European staff. Apart from any other consideration, Belgrave has no legal training worth mentioning, and is frequently unable to detect defects in agreements until it is too late. I trust, therefore, that the India Office will discourage any future^such attempts by him to evade the control of the political authorities in the Gulf. 4. I am sending copies of this letter to Weightman and.Galloway and am authorising the latter to take the action suggested in paragraph 4 of his letter.D.0. No. C/258. The Agency, Bahrain, The 6th March, 1946, My dear Sir Geoffrey, Belgrave in his letter Np. 217-43 dated the 24th January, 1946 (copy enclosed), informed me that he had while in England, engaged a Mr Tunnicliffe as Assistant State Engineer for the Bahrain Government. On receipt of this information I pointed out to him that the employment of fo reign s ubjects by t he Bahrain Gove rnmen t was subj ect to confiemation by the Tr psiftency. ITe haS LhaTTlie had sought the assistance ornhe fridia Office in the matter, 2. Today I have received a letter in which he informs me that he has engaged a new matron for the Bahrain Government Hospital, and that the arrangements were made with the approval of the India Office. They also arranged her passage. 3. For Belgrave to engage State employees in England without reference to the political authorities is not only incorrect but it also affects Governments control in a State and also, from the local point of view, tends to teverse the relative positions of the Political Agent and the Adviser. Besides these aspects since the Political Agent is the arbitrator under the terms of the agreements between the State and the employees it is essential that we should be consulted. 4. I suggest that you may consider authorising me to write to Belgrave informing him that whatever assistance he might have received from the hands of India Office he must realise that his dealings with Government are to be directed through the correct channels, the Political Agent, and that he should submit proposals to this Agency before they can be considered final. Yours sincerely, sd. A.C.Galloway. The Hobble Sir Geoffrey Prior, K.C.I.E., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.COPY From To ^ \-i V ^ C ^ \V \%\^ y 'J&lt;r* &amp; ^ rt, \*^ 5 ^ v ^ v « ^ No. D.839-N/32 The Deputy Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, The Hobble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Dated New Delhi, the 2nd March 1932, Employment of Mr W.B.Steele as State Engineer, Bahrain. Sir, In reply to your letter No. 343 of 1932 , dated the 14th February 1932, I am directed to say that although the Rules contained in paragraph 56 of the Manual of Instructions to officers of the Political Department of the Government of India do not apply to the Arab States in the Persian Gulf, the Government of India consider it desirable that all cases in which the Rulers of these States show a desire to engage the services of Europeans (which may be understood as including Australians and Americans) should be reported to them beforehand. The same also applies to the engagement of Iraqis, Syrians, Palestineans, Egyptians and natives of North Africa in positions of importance. 2. The Government of India see no objection to the employment of Mr W.B.Steele as State Engineer, Bahrain. I I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, sd. F.V. Wylie Deputy Secretary to the Government of India.r tone No. : Whitehall 5140 Ext:94. ny reply should be addressed to— THE ASSISTANT SECRETARY, quoting reference letter and number IMP..i.v&gt;Q.Q./46 . Your Ref.:....G_L./2.1 . RLE COPY ' PRIORITIES DEPARTMENT, 'O* BOARD OF TRADE, MILLBANK, LONDON, S.W.I. i April, 1946. Dear Harrison You sent to me on the 6th April copy of your letter you had received from Charles Kendall &amp; Partners, Ltd., about the export of steel joists to Bahrein. I am told by the British Iron and Steel Corpora tion that paragraph 2 of this letter is incorrect, and that the suggestion that ci special allocation might be made by the Board of Trade to cover this order was made by Charles Kendall &amp; Partners, Ltd., themselves, and not the British Iron and Steel Corporation. The position however, is as I think you know, that the total availabilities of steel for export are divided each quarter among the various sections of the iron and steel industry, with complete freedom of action for the industry to accept those orders which offer them the greatest long term of interest* It seems clear in this case that the allocation given to the British Iron and Steel Corporation is /fullyfully taken up to the end of June, in wnich cae Charles Kendall &amp; Partners, Ltd., v/ii.1 have to endeavour to place tneir o-rder for later deliveiy. I should, however, like to nia^e clear that once the Board of Trade allocation*has been expended amongst various sections of ohe iron aiiQ soeel industry, g not possible to i.i?.ke ao-Qitional allocations uo cover any individual orders ^ Yours sine ^ ^ AMANAGING AGENT! AND SECRETARIES INDUSTRIAL MISSIONS A INTELLIGENCE -''X v / TELEPHONE: ABBEY 2827-8 TELEGRAMS: KENPARTNA, SOWEST, LONDON FOREIGN TELEGRAMS: KENPARTNA, LONDON CODES : A.B.C., 6TH EDITION BENTLEYS, LONDON FILE ^GPY ‘ (fS? DIRECTORS : CAPT. C. E. KENDALL COLONEL T. W. PRAGNELL, C.B.E., D.S.O. G. E. PECK, F.C.W.A. CHARLES KENDALL &amp; PARTNERS LIMITED For the attention of the Political Branch (lvIr.g,A.K.Harrison). Sir, ■'H-j SAigE OF BAHI^IN - HOLL^ID S'JEEL JOISJS. As the Accredited Supply Agents and General Hepresentatives in the United Kingdom for the State Government of Bali rain, we have the honour to inform you that we have been requested to purchase and ship, on behalf of the Bahrain State Government, Rolled Steel Joists as per schedule attached hereto. Upon application to the British Iron &amp; Steel Corporation Limited, we have been advised to seek a recommendation from your Department to the Board of Trade for an allocation sufficient to cover the Steel Joists required under Symbol B,T.5« We would, therefore, be grateful if you could give us autho ity with which to approach the Board of rade. We have the honour to be. Sir, :he necessary Your obedient Servants, CHARLES KSIUIlLL &amp; PAR ‘KARS LBUTHD.THE HIGH COMMISSIONER FOR COMMISSIONER FOR xNDIA, General _ department. ^isSi^FhouseJaldwych, LONDON, W.C.2^ mat to sunt sjttLaniheahhrz Burner Reference 270,1.21*56 • 7 th February 1946. Dear Harrison, With reference to your letter Ext, 6 899 dat ed the 20th December 1945. I write to let you~know that Mr.R.CampbeIT Tunnicliffe, accompanied by his wife, sailed for Port Said on the 30th January 1946 in the S.S.Empire Kitchener. Arrangements for the onward journey by Nairn Transport to Bahrein from Port Said have been made through Messrs T.Cook &amp; Son. Yours sincerely F.A.K.Harrison Esq., India Office, Whitehall, S.W.1./LEGRAMS: ALLE MOVE, STOCK, LONDJDN. CABLES: ALLENOVE,LONDON. CODE: BENTLEYS. • 3, FINCH LANE, (THREADNEEDLE street) LONDON , E.C. 3. ALLEN &amp; OVERY|. 45 i __I/'..IlD 16th January 19 46 ^'•K.A.Harrison, Esq., Political Department, India Office, Whitehall. S.W.l. jyu 1 1 Dear Sir, T Vith reference to our interview with 3 r ou in Hovomber last, we return as promised your copy of the Bahrein Order in Council 1915, ane x or the loan of which we are very much obliged. Yours faithfully Ends.Bxt. 684^45 \9-y^C. Dear Belgr&amp;'ve, I return herewith the ctar&amp;ft Afpreeuent with the Bast Anglian engineering Oaaiaijy with one or two minor suggestions ins-^rted in ink, cmkl Jn line 2 we have suggested 'simply agentf in place of 'uurchasing agents since as we understand it the fina Wfcill undertake enquiries and negotiations which 'foOEi not result in purchases* With regard to para. 11 our Legal Adviser has suggested that it might ^rhaps be better if it read ' shall be referred in writing to the arbitration of sooe person appointed in this behalf by the Political Agent whose deoj^ion etc*' It will no doubt be as well if you obtain the Political Agent 1 s agreement to the 0. Dalrymple Belgrave, jisq. # 1, Queensgate Place, \n London* provisioi^. v. .— *iV. ‘ ^-7 •4 y^ provision fcr his arbitration before the agreement is finally signed, and you will no doubt be able to do tbii on your return* flooidentally our attention has been drawn to the fact that the India Store l^eparhaent (of the High C oasis sioner* s Office ) has on occasion5in the past arranged for the purcbasiAg and shipment of stores ior ifie Bahrein Government* I do not suggest however that this need ailect the present agreeaent. Tours sinoox’ely. (^&lt;*0 f 9 A. K. HARRISON/ u . t * 'fa, Annuls /C i*** 10 $u y«*~ _ „ , xr /H^W'y 9 ^ ^ - /&gt;- ^ w A 5 *^ ^ ju A /u^* AvVW (k 14 $4-1 (X+*- / ■t ffr /ZhS 4^1 u ' e ~ l**- Usr *+~J C4r**+*u**'^ r?*.jt*sM»'r&gt; &amp;- r JC. &gt;~ft W.J? t ._ 7 //*'• ^v*- So far as I can judge - and I have no special knowledge of such matters - this seems all right subject to the alterations already suggested. But I would suggest '*supply agents” in place of 'purchasing agents' in line 2. The firm as I understand it will undertake enquiries and negotiations which may not result in purchases. The I.S.D. have probably more knowledge than we have of /agencyExtract from letter from the Adviser to the Bahrain Government dated 10.12.45. 3€- I am seeing the atron on Thursday and will fix up about her agj»ement. She would like to go out as-soon as possible. I am glad Tunnicliffe passed the Medical ( _x&gt;ara; I think he will be a useful man. Ke too wants to start for Bahrain as soon as he can get a passage^ he has a wife and wants to take her too. I think in the case of all three a sea passage is most suitable, if one arrives in ahrain by air, for the first time with one small suit case and baggage following many months later it is extremely awkward. I should be very grateful if you would ask the H. C. for India to help in ootaining passages at the first possible opportunity.sZZT&amp;Wt iP €^y&lt;5r/43 XO^^oember, 1945 Dear Mr* Tunnioliffe, I am pasEiin.n; on the cloth tug oo pcai f cams for certificatior* to r* K*C. Batten, Office of the High Ccxiiaisaioiiter for India, India Kou. e, Aldsr^ch, W.C.2,, wha, I have asked to arrange passage* for your self and, if possible, for your wife, I suggest that you should get into touch vTith Mr. Batten direct in regard to passports, visas and other details which will have to be arranged* R, Campbell Tunnleliffe, Ssq., 21 Beaumont Court, London, W*4* Tours sincerely, A. r. HARWONEXT- bHI/tS ^ December, 1945« Dear Batten, We should he gl*d if you would arrange a passage at an / early opportunity for Mr. Campbell Tunnicliffe, who haii been appointed Assistant State Engineer in Bahrein. The Bahrein Government would like a passage also to be arranged for Mrs. Tuimioliffe to accompany her husband. In the oase of a passage by way of India, Mrs. Tunnioliffe would presumably have to come under the Hardship Committee procedure and would not be able to go with her husband. The best solution would therefore seem to be to arrange for them both to go together to Egypt by sea and thence overland. Can this be done? If this cannot be arranged in the near future, oerhaps you wo Id arrange a passage for Mr. Tunnioliffe alone via India and Mrs. Tunnioliffe could then follow separately at a later date. \ e have not Mr. Tunnioliffe's address available but will arrange for you to be informed of this. Tours sincerely 9 K.C. Batten, Esq., India House, Aldwyoh, W.C.2. P.S. Since writing the above, I have had a letter from Mr. Tunnioliffe enclosing forms for supplementary /clothing1 •J - - - » * clothing coupons to b e certified. Will you kindly deal with this* You will see that Mr* Turmidiff4' s address is given on the forms. * 1 . :-0 t t * - n in A Li ■’ hi z •2' t x'i ■ ^ *-cLcjLec!L ^ ^ j't: A 17th November 9 1945* Dear Belgrave, I return herewith the letters from Mr. Tunnicliffe in connection with his proposed appointment as Assistant State Engineer at Bahrein, The Ordnance Consulting Officer here has commented as follows:- 'Judging solely from the statement of his qualifications and experience I should say that * Tunnicliffe would be quite suitable for the appointment. It will be realised that the range of duties is very wide and that it will not be possible to get a man who has had actual experience in all these branches. Mr. Tunnicliffe however, should be a general engineer of good experience and should be able to tackle the Job'. As regards a medical board, we could arrange this here and I have fixed provisionally Friday November 30th at 11.30 Perhaps you would confirm this in due course. Yours sincerely. HARRISON C. Dalrymple Belgrave Esq., 1 i^ueensgate Place, S.W.7.Mr. Harrison, Judging solely from the statement of his qualifications and experience, I should say that kIt. Tunnicliffe would be quite suitable for the appointment. It will be realised that the range of duties is very wide and that it will not be possible to get a man who has had actual experience in all these branches. Mr. Tunnicliffe, hov/ever, should be a general engineer of good experience and should be able to tackle the job. Brigadier, O.C.O. for India.A ■■■ I ——Hill. &gt; Any further communication on this subject should be addressed to— The Under Secretary of State for India, Department, India Office, London, S.W.l, and the following reference quoted:— Telephone :— Whitehall 8140. 1.0. Ext. No.. Telegrams :— Retaxandum, London INDIA OFFICE, \ WHITEHALL, LONDON, S.W.l.- Extract fran letter fran G» Dalryn?)le I have been having tallcs v/ith .^’he East iUiglian Engineering Go. whose name was iven to us I think oy you- am arranging for them to act as purchasing agents for the Bahrain Government for obtaining a juantity of things - a very varied list which we are in need of in Bahrain. i -1INDIA OFFICE Telephone :— Whitehall 8140. I.O. Ext. No. Telegrams :— Hetaxandum. London WHITEHALL, LONDON, S.W.l. il&amp; •p &amp; FILE COPY A, vx INV Allotted to Externa 4 8 y 4 iVRD TELEGRAM &gt;114: DepdrOalon t» CYPHER ’f ELB GRftM (0. T -P. ) From Political Resident in the Persian Gulf '^o Secretary of State for India Reptd.to Government of India and Bahrain Bated Shiraz, 11*45 hours, 29th September 1945 Received SO.30 hours, 29th September 1945 No »T/658 » ^ Galloway to Donaldson, repeated Oaroe and Pelly, letter Bxt*3256/45 *Tuiv 2 [a-.-, -j94 h and India Office express letter 3256/4-5* Augus': IQtho 2« I consider little progress can be made.until Bahrain Government 1 s attitude is clarified with Belgrave and early meeting between latter now on leave and Prior might be best solution, Pelly and I agreed that Bahrain Government ! s ( ?omission} ing reau.ureiuent s should be canalised through one cornmercial channel but details of this can be best worked out .on the spoto ^ Government of India vide theif letter ME/45 August 22nc.n nave agreed that Bahrain GoVer me nr should be urged to pursue a policy of deveiopment on which indeed Pripr, Pelly and self are all agreed and ^ ^this renders need for {? material) and proper arrangements on tec -ni'al side more i ressing. £FILE COPY / EXT I 80 ■ IM/AR D Allptted to BU&amp; QJ QASrr .mpr ^QPy ^to .External DeparimeffifT 1 &gt;• 7/ir felegram 26856 t. CQKFIDMTIAL CODE TELEGRAM Government of Indie, External Affairs Department. Secretary of State for India. Repeated to Political Agent Bahrain and Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. From To HeYy Delhi, 03o05 Hours, 16th August, 194 00.30 hours, 16th August, 1945. Dated Received 7207. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf has recommended import of 340 gallons of descaling solution required 'by State Engineer Bahrain Government- .Houseman and Thompson Limited Rugby state consignment is awaiting shipment. Grateful 5 export assistance can be granted urgently. Kite. POL KF f7 AUG 1945 INDIA QFFICcopy letter. CKC/LV4 19th July, 1945 m INDIA. OPB'IGJi MS. Dear Group Captain Leigh, Machine Tools . W e have now quite a number of answers to our preliminary enquiries for machine tools and equipment listed in your letter No.MHT/l /64 of June 21st, The disappointing thing from the gen eral. point of view is the length of time required ty almost all manufacturers for delivery of the majority of the tools. There is only one reasonably quick promise of delivery, and that is for a Swift L.3 Type Heavy Duty Centre Lathe, I accordingly sent you the sub-joined cable today, suggesting we should place a firm order for this tool on your behalf, as if a decision is delayed, we will in all probability lose it. I have seen Swifts Representative and discussed the matter with him, and they are quite confident that provided the dimensions of the tools are suitable for your require ments, it should give you every satisfaction and with this we agree. This particular lathe is one surplus to a batch recently ordered by someone else, HLT 'BAHRAIN GOVRRIMSNT, PERSIAN GULF. 'FOLLOWING FOR STATE ENGINEER RBLET MHT/l/64 TWENTTFIRST JUNE LIST MACHINE TOOLS ITEM 2 STOP IN CONTRA DISTINCTION GREATLY DELAYED DELIVERIES MOST OFFERS SWIFTS OFFER DELIVERY 6/8 WEEKS L .3 TYPE HEAVY DUTY 83 ' CENTRE LATHE BED 8 FEET ADMITTING 4 FEET BETWEEN CENTRES SWING 30'xl0' ARRANGED MOTOR DRIVE STOP FITTED TWELVE SPEED HEADSTOCK 13.6 to 300 RPM STOP PRICE INCLUDING 7^ HP MOTOR i+OO/W) VOLTS THREE PHASE FIFTY CYCLES £710 ACCESSORIES £ll 6 FOB ENGLISH PORT STOP IF REQUIREMENT URGENT ADVISE IMMEDIATE ACCEPTANCE HAVE WRITTEN FULLY REGARDING THIS AND OTHER TOOLS REQUIRED - EANGLIAN' • Taking the list of your requirements seriatum, I am sending you the general gist of the replies, on which a few queries arose as shown. In your last letter you gave me no indication of the aiative urgency of getting the tools out to Bahrain and if some are urgently required it might well be that we shall have to go tb the Machine Tool Control, with the backing of the India Office, to get the necessary priority and thereby expedite delivery. It would be very helpful if you oould give me some indication of your most urgent needs when reply ing to this letter.machine tools Itga, 1 .-.A1.-9X nearest Ceatre .L^the,. One quotation only received from Denham^ - delivexy 5 to 6 months - approximate cost £233 inclusive of electricial drive and packing F.O.B. English Port* Item 2 - 8'-10' or nearest Centre Lathe. Eight quotations - average delivery ll/l6 months, with the exception of Swifts - average price approximately £800 - average cost of extra tools £150 - average extra cost for electrical equipment GtyO - average cost of packing F.O.B. English Port £10. With regard to this item, will you please let me know the minimum length of bed, distance between centres, and swing you require. Item 3 - Radial Arm Dulling Machine. Several quotations received - average delivery 3/t- months - average price £350 - average for extras £ 50 - average extra cost for electrical gear £90 - average cost of packing F.O.B. English Port £10. Item h- - Sensitive Self-contained Drilling Machine. So fax only one quotation from Adcock and Shipley p delivery 3/A months - cost £98 - extra for electrical equip ment £15 - extra for packing F.O.B. English Port £7* Item 5 - Self-contained Shaping Machine. Two quotations - one from Butler, delivery eighteen months - cost £378 - extra for Electrical Gear £ 36 . Second quotation from Elliot - delivery four months - cost £121 - Extra for Electrical Equipment £31 - extra for packing F.O.B. English Port £20. Item 6 - Milling Machines. Several quotations - average delivery fourteen months- average cost £650 - average extra for tools £110 - average cost of extra electrical equipment £21 - average extra for packing F.O.B. English Port £15. Items? and 8 - Buffing Machine and Emery Grinder. Tip quotations - delivery 20 weeks - cost of tool average £200 - average extras £50 - average cost of packing FOB English Port £10. The largest machine quoted for is 12 ,, xl2 n capacity, which takes a blade up to 23 M long, but has astraight stroke of T' only. It occurs to us that the dimension x 14' shown on your schedule should be the length of the blade, but we would like to have your confirmation on this matter. Item 10 - Blacksmith 1 s Hearth etc. So far only one quotation - delivery 8/10 weeks - cost £46. Item 11 -Brazing Hearth etc. So far only one quotation - delivery 8/10 weeks - cost £37* Item 12 - Sheet Metal Working Tools. No quotations so far received. I had hoped ere now to have had an answer from you to my letter of July 4th, but no doubt one will come to hand within the next few days. In the meantime I shall look forward to hearing from you about the lathe from Swifts, and I think you would be well advised to take it. Yours sincerely. The State Engineer, The Government of Bahrain, Persian Gulf.3, I^rrtlr Cinrrt. (^r£at jPjet^r Str^t, SX&amp;A. Abbey 2627-8. GKD/L3/7 9th August, 1945 Dear Harrison, I would be much obliged if you would have the enclosed letter sent out to Bahrain by Bag. I enclose a copy for the purpose of record in your files. Confinning our conversation yesterday, I am hav ing a further copy made of my letter of 19 th July, which I will send over to you early next week. With kind regards. Yours sincerely. F.A.K.Harrison Esq., The India Office, WHITEHALL.1 - 7 V Ivp» ooor and autouatio ooir^actor tjrpe control gear, posh button an beads took* suitable for a supply &amp;£ UOO/l^O Volta, 3 base, 30 cycles* (b) Tools* Full ran^s of .;utt welded tuxning tods* «e feel it unadvlsable tc su^p^' -ungstxai Carbide Tipped Tools, o&amp;inc to Hie difficulty of grinding and the possible TeLy in sup plying replacements in the event of the tips getting dar^agocl* If time are any editions or alterations v&amp;ich you require to the above, poximps you wwCtd send me a calTLo* As sooc as you are able, X would be grateful if you would let laa know the meti^od you suggest should bo adopted for paying for this and future oxdLors, as tlic any, /liars rdll rocruiro cash against shipping docruDcsats. I can, of ooui’se, arrange to fijv- aaco the ;3uxobaee ci* the lath® xro have ordeiod ibcau Swifts, but wolHA be ^Lad to heave your peeposalc in due course* lours ainceroly. The State hnginuer. The teroni -caio of Bahrain,Mr, Harrison» External Department, . _ . . I am glad to see from the correspondence which Captain ' Kendall has sent you that he has not belied the good words which we spoke on his behalf. His letter of the 4th July to the State Engineer, Bahrein, strikes me as an extremely businesslike Vy* i document. May I suggest that you give Captain Kendall a copy I the letter dated 30th March from the Machine Tool Control, I have already put Captain Kendall on to Mr, Isaacs of the M.T.C. tr^ gT* but it might save seme time if he had a copy of the Machine Tool Control’s conclusions as given in March last. There is no secret about them. As regards the electric generating plant, U.K. manufacturers are rapidly having their order books filled up for a long period ahead. If it is desired to have anything reasonably quickly manufactured, there is no time to be lost. Deliveries to-day for heavy electrics would probably be quoted with at least two years* delivery. Perhaps this information might be passed on to the Govemnent of Bahrein. If they wanted a consulting engineer to give an opinion on the plant they might consider the employment of Messrs. Kennedy &amp; Donkin, 12, Caxton Street, S.W.1. This Company are in the throes at the moment of a scheme for the establishment of a consulting engineer's agency in India and would like to take the Persian Gulf and similar areas under their wing. Whether it would be necessary to employ a consulting engineer would depend, of course, on the size of the plant. Do you happen to know anything about this?ckc/li/5 3 f jQ0rtlj C^itrt, (^reat Si r££t r S.^I. l. Abbey 2627-8. 19th July, 194-5 &lt;£r CV Dear Harrison, I v^ould be very greatly obliged if you could have the enclosed letter, which is somewhat urgent, out to Bahrain by Bag. Yours sincerely. sent F.A.K. Harrison Esq., The India Office, Whitehall S.W.l.CKC/Ll/1 k*ii July, 1945 jjear a! agpwa^A^afasfi Vi tits, iabaaiflft- Xou latter Ho. -.li/i/dU ciatod 21st June, 1945&gt; ou.*o safely to hand on ^aturdsy last, ana X iuai^idiatoly sent you ths sub-joizisd cable, which I trust you zmaekmA in due ooursa: 'm&amp;jkLh &amp;jv^ai j*{£ tm&amp;XM ckiiy* yu^ja.inG pok ^xatk mmmm MiX/i/64 oatod 2i&amp;t 1945 jw m^uxse^v^afEb puluc Tiawww 4101 ^101* * k vV&amp;SS&amp;J 16 Kva^G Ijd-vKiv FuKaiv.Xi’li ^ur ^hXCXIir I'Ua-X.- mMLUJP I'ith rugaitl to tbs list of i'iachlne tools and other equipment for your 1 ittiug Shop, X am immediately ixaving enquiries put out to the well known suppliers of such equiisusits. Including the ones you mentioned, asking tivaji to let us have a general description and a? -education of v4mt they are able to offer, together with their earliest delivery dates and prices. Directly these are leceived I will arrange for detailed inspections of the most likely tools, hearing In mind the purposes for which they are required and having particular reg&amp;nl to the necessity for robust construction to stand \Mp to the work and ti^e conditions under widch tliey will be used. If you bo wish, I can then submit to you full details of all the replies we have received, but on the other hand it would probably save tin*and trouble if xm first eliriin&amp;ted the unlikely ones and send you particulars ouly of tliose 'which in our opinioti would be the most suitable* On Usla point you will no aoubt let me 'nave your instructions* I mo a little uncertain whether or not to gat in touch with the Institute of liachanioal JtigLneers, the ^eoretar^ of which 1^ know, in order to find out whether the other London Fim of Jdpiicors mentioned in your le tter aro putting out staHar enquiries and there-^ Hy overla,/ping ours* On consideration, liowevor, r&gt;os:iil3lo it Is better that I should not do so until I hear again from y£u as to : ^ exact position* I ii&amp;ve Just been lunching with bir Geoffroy nior, wdio is cognisant of the proposal that we should act as your K^resentatireo in the TV,, lie weiy clearly and coneiseJy put as into the plcturo of your general x^qui rencffito in the otate ana xiartloularly mentlniMwl I the position of the State LieotilGity undertaicing and its probable | future devfelofjastvh. I explained to air Geoffrey Vat we are in close touch with the aeotrical Indust^ in this oountaty, since Colonel 1 tasnell, she is a dxeotor of this ;&lt;xa?*tfiy is also on tiie doaxd of AdsooiateA ftlootrioal Induatriea, which as you j^rbbabi; ux*’’ controls 3*x»I ••, Metroi&gt;oli.tan Vicicers and a nuaber of other sbuilai oonoema* Hir Geoffrey suggested that I ^ould let you ioiow Cf theae connections aw\ in view of the awmeviiat ui-gent natures of the position that he would vexy kindly arrange with the India Oflloe that thia letter should be sent to you by the India Office Bag. wing to the long delay mider px^sent conditiona of getting deliver of ai^'thing, it would be mat helpful if you oould let us have early and full inf*Dina.tion as to wha.i you are likely to be re ,airing over the course of the next few years, eve n if on l,/ in a , general v/ay* This applies particularly to the 'levelcninent of tiie | IZLectrloity Undertaking and the sise end V amiT envisaged ftv. in- I ataHaticaru Incidentally, in oc&gt;iJ'»ootiian with other business we hawa in Ii-ciia, I an continually in touch with Mr* Harrison of tiie oilUical Branch in the India Office and also with *r. fhen^son, vdia, as I dars mk you know, is the Unison ’fl'ioer for Industrial ;;ur&gt;plles.©SC/XJ/1 July, 1915 - 2 - '^hore are a number of vifrlah we could ar ang9 tha trfmus and comitlctta to umierkato ^our ixyprusantation in ttie but at t&gt;ie iocmont it is a little to iwbj 0 tuoy concrete prorosal until wo know r&amp;thor jr»or® i'xaa you tins , coi&gt;e of the woric you would ilka us to undertake on your behalf. It is that apart fraa putting out diquxries, a«x rally collscting infoib- ation, ins'jacting and advitdng you an the Most suitable tooln,plant etc* that you would ultimately wish us to negotiate the beat poealble tettis mid purohasea for you, as well as carrying out all the necessaiy &gt;rooedure for obtaining export idoenoes^ shipping facilities, -usterns and other fouaalitlee which at jiresent are soiae- «h*t cootplicated* ^e wiiild, of course, bo prepared to do all this kind of work for you as well as undertaking any other duties which mi^it arise from time to time, either in connection with your own particular bspartnant o r indee d *»y At f &gt;&gt; ir nf the f tsto, We have a«|&gt;le iadlities in icndon for doing this kind of thing and you wlli no doubt let us know your ^yiahes when you have had time to ocnaider the matter. If it ^xuid bo any help in oaming to a deoision on these piinta, as well as any technical matters in connection with your re./Uirotaoaitii, wa would be quite prtriared to aeiid someone out to see you in order to discuss the beat mya and insane of getting things going* For your preliminary consideration we would suggest that suitable terns ni^it be arranged under one or a ootribinatian of the following:(a} A fixed sum per warm to oover full itspreaent&amp;tion and csqjeneea in oonneotlon therewith. (b) A rotaining fee per annttn plus oa. dsrlon an orders placed tlirou^i us. (o) On tliO heels of axpenoo&amp; plus oorsaisaion on orders placed. It is further sug^^eoto* li&amp;fc any arrangeeunt between us ahcxiM be for an intiial period of sc^r three years and renewable thereafter' for threo-j^eorly periods. Perhaps you will consider these suggestions and let us know vrfiich In your opinion v»criL&amp; be the raost gui’^ble line on tdiich to Vrosm an agrooBwaUbetweeax us. In tlie meantime, if there is anythinr, olse of sritf nature you eould like us to do for you in the countty, please do not hes itate to let US Ttfxr. lours finoerely. f he btate hangineezm ihe CkMMSNMRt of Bahrain, i^ereian fulf.con NO.lvIHT/V^ THE BAHtfAII. GCHteNi.IENT ELECi’RIC SUPPLY DEPT, STATE ENGINEER'S DEPAKTIviSDT^ The East ^nglian Engineering, ^ '3 North Court, , Vreat Peter Street, -London &gt;-&gt;, BAHRAIN. )ated: - 21st June, 19k5 Dear Sirs: Representation in the United Kinp-AQm. Receipt of your letter CEK/tiW dated 2nd May 194-5 is acknowledged with thanks and it is noted that you would be prepared to act on behalf of the Government of Bahrain in connection with their requirements for certain machine and hand tools. Previous to the receipt of your letter an enquiry had been made through a member of the Institution of Mechanical Engineers who in turn had notified our requirements to a London firm of engineers* xhis firm has not yet been contacted but it is believed they have been given a list of ^ our requirements through the Insitutution of Mechanical Engineers uo wnom uie writer 'also ntified the Government of Bahrain* s requirements. A copy of this which listed the bare outline only is now forwarded to you for informatuon. It is requested that you will obtain quotations and specifications for uhe supply of new equipment only and consider all dimensions quoted as being flexible provided the utility value of the tool or tools is not decreased. In this connection it is desired to state that robustness ol construct ion might be given special consideration as much of the work involved will be mainly of a rough and heavy nature on maintenance of Electricity Generating Plant, Ewing Bridge, .t.i.echanical Transport, x lour i&lt;iills, laoer ouppYy and Distillation etc. An earty reply will be appreciated to ^ether with your terms and condit ions of representation. Yours Mthfully, H.P.G.Leigh /G/Capt. mu 1 -&gt; JUL I945 State engineer I ~ UL. Government of Bahrain. ( sgd)H.x J .G.Leigh Enclosed also is a list of manufacturers of the machine and hand tools required. This was sent to the India Cifice, London by the Ministry of Supply, Hachine -‘•ool Control, Westminster S.u.l. It is thought that this information might be useful in connection with your enquiries.3, Cmirt, / t;() p (Jr^at [P^tjer Xrwniratt, S.Sl. 1. Abbey 2627-8. CKC/U/2 4th July, 1945 Pi^QIMAL Dear riarrison, ( / 4^/ further to our telephone conversation, I enclose here\^/ith a letter for despatch by Ba^'^bo Bahrain. I have left it open in case you would lil^xo see what is going on, and perhaps you will stick it up when you have had a look see. If in addition you would like a copy of it, please let me know and I will let you have one. Yours sincerely. P.A.K.Harrison Bsq., The India Office, Whitehall S.W.l.C !LE COPY fl OFFICE OF THE HIGH COMMISSIONER FOR INDIA. Address for Inland Telegrams — HICOMIND, ESTRAND, LONDON. Telephone—T emple Bar 8484. Cabie*—HICOMIND, LONDON. Plfase quote the under-mentioned reference, and address any further Deer Harrison, !945 ! With r9ference ,,,, irq v t'fSer Ext. dated the I9th December 1944 regarding Mrs.LeiRh T s luggage I write to let you know that the sum of £19:l6:-has been paid to Messrs. Escombe, McGrath &amp; Co. for forwarding the luggage to the port of embarkation. A copy of the firms account is / enclosed for information. Yours sincerely F.A.K.Harrison, Hsq., India Office, Whitehall, London, S.W.l.I COPY WE A9c/8 5 . 'JT 1 The High Commissioner for India, India House, Aldwych, W.C.2. In Account with ESCOM3E, MCGRATH &amp; CO., 120, Pall Mall, London. S.W.l. MRS.LEIGH To follov/ing charges in connection with shipment of 10 packages (Trunks &amp; wooden cases) per L.3.2477* December Sunday, l/th December - 5 cases: Transfer from Cloak Room to Parcels Office, and attendance until loading on to 1 p.m. train, Euston/Glasgow, Pees, porterages etc L.M..S. passenger train charge, Euston/Glasgow ♦ • • • Monday, l8th December - J trunks &amp; 2 cases: Transfer from Cloak Room to Parcels Office, and attendance at 1 p.m. train (refused loading) and subsequent attendance at 9*15 P-m. train and ensuring loading. Pees, porterages, and expenses .... L.M.S. passenger train charge, Euston/Glasgow • • • • Telephone trunk calls to Glasgow Office, of despatch - J (g) j/jd. Telephone call 21.12 to request Glasgow Office cancel Hotel arrangements, 21.12, as Mrs. Leigh had decided to travel per special train Collection of Bag at pre-censorship Office and delivery to Mrs.Leigh - Pares etc. Glasgow Office a/c Collection of baggage from Cloak Room, porterages, cartage to Dock, and porterage to Embarkation Q t,sre Insurance of baggage for for 2 months (ordinary risks) - S500 @ JO/- # Agency charges • • • • loth January 1945. per pro ESCOMBE, McGRATH &amp; CO. ( Sgd.) 8 4 14 10 17 2 11 J 7 1 7 5 10 1 £19 16Telephone: Blackpool South Shore 42085 Ext.2, S.475/45 7OT. India Store Department, Blackpool. V ' 3rd Uay 1%3* 3/C Dear Harrison, The Indian Trade Commissioner has sent me your two letters of 20th April and 1st May 1945, reference Ext. 1797/45, regarding the supply of workshop equipment to the Bahrain G-ovemment. I note that no further action is required. I may say that this Department has previously arranged the purchase, inspection and shipment of a quantity of stores required by the Bahrain Government. Yours sincerely. P.A.K. Harrison Esq., India Office, Whitehall, London, S.W. 1.Iff r| ADRIAN WORKS I.OWESTOFT ENG TELEPHONE.' LOWESTOFT SBO-I (PRIVATE BRANCH EXCHANGE) TELEGRAMS: EANGLIAN, LOWESTOFT CODES: A B C. SR 1 EON. BENTLEYS. PRIVATE EA'ST ANGLIAN EN COMPANY LIMITED A'' &gt; DIRECTORS pAPTAIN C.E. KENDALL (CHAIRMAN Sc managing director) 6 COLX)NeL T. W. PRAGNELL, D.S.O. fHE HON. P. F. REMNANT ( OU. :0 INEERIN(|j d | q/jg j c ^ 1 '- (but factors to the Adimralt\ War ( tffu oftQtetry '/ ^ ^ tot' 1 Bndm tim &lt; t&lt;. K / ^ OUR REF.. YOUR REF. csk/uy. Ext.1797/45. f \V 3, NORTH COURT, GREAT PETER STREET, LONDON, S.W.l. TELEPHONE: ABBEY 2627-8 TELEGRAMS EANGLIAN. SOWEST, LONDON FOREIGN: EANGLIAN. LONDON CODES: A.B.C. 6T“ EDITION, BENTLEYS, PRIVATE 2nd May 1945• Sir, We have the honour to acknowledge receipt of your letter dated 1st May 1945 which we thank you. We note that the name of our fiim has been passed to the Bahrain Government and that we should get in touch with them direct. We have the honour to be, Sir, Your obedient Servants, EAST ANGLIAN ENGINEERING COMPANY, LIMITED. C-. i/ y /Lol-. Captain CTST Kendall. MANAGING DIRECTOR. The Under Secretary of State for India, India Office, Whitehall, S.W.1.EXPRESS LETTER Fran; Secretary of State for India To: (go g(t4^3 A. rv / X &lt;7 Political Agent, Bahrain. ^3 MAY 1945 Reference my telegram ho. 0| Copy is enclosed herewith of letter from East Anglian Engineering Company Ltd. for information of Bahrain Coveraffient-y14502) Wt. 41647—P17I 25m. 12/44 G.S.St. Gp. 620 No. DEPTL. No. . ..1797/45.*. DRAFT TELEGRAM CODE CYPHER Mi/lJ (~ cJ$(~ 4 mJ!&amp;*&gt;*■** From Secretary of State for India To Political Agent Bahrain Repeated to Addressed Bahrain, copy to Bushire. ^ Express Letter Ext,1797 of 20th April. Understand that East Anglian Engineering Company, 3 North Court, Great Peter Street, S.1 ¥*Hri^/oe praparod to act for Bahrain Is) c&lt;\*4 • 'government. ^If suggestion is acceptable ■ State Engineer will no doubt contact firm direct. Meanwhile no further action regarding order in question is being taken here. SEND (ft**' 'h. DESPATCHED S-Js: 19.4? 0~{ i+QLict. 1797/45. 1st Kay 1945* s \ . * I ac directed by the 'eeretary of State for India to refer to India Office letter Ho* irt*1797A5 of the 20th April regarding the supply of work hop equipment to the Bahrain Ocvemment* From enquiries made by the i^ast nglian engineering Co., Ltd., it has since appeared that this Firm might be ready to act on behalf of the Bahrain Government in the matter in question. Since the fixm appear to be suitable to undertake the work/Cheer name is being suggested to the ahrain Government as a possible Agent in this Country. In the circianstances it is requested that no further action should be taken by your /Department The Indian made Commissioner, India House, Aldwych, WmCrnlmDepartment on India Office letter of the 20th Aprilj pending oonfixmation that the Bahrain Govexment will be prepared to make vise of the Dast Anglian Engineering Company in this connection, I am to express regret for any unnecessary trouble to which your Department may have been put* I an. Sir, * Your obedient Servant, « (^V- A K- HAR RISC'*V act. 1797A5 1st ay 1945. Gentlemen, ^ith reference to your letter QHX/ia of 1?th April regarding the caunercial representation in the United Kingdoei of states in India and the Persian Gulf, I an directed to say that the Bahrain State ngineer has recently been making enquiries regarding $ Finn in this Country who might act on behalf of the Bahrain ovexment in connection with an order of machine tools and workshop equipment. The name of your Finn is being passed on to the Bahrain Government with the suggestion that if they wish to pursue the matter they should corcnunicate with you direct. I am Gentlemen, lour obedient 'Servant, The Bast Anglian engineering Co., Ltd., 3, North court. Gt. Beter Street, S.W.1.India Office Mr, Harrison, External Depar-brent. A case was recently referred to you where the State Engineer of Bahrein had been trying to obtain information about the supply of certain machine tools from this country. It appeared, at the time, that should many such enquiries be received from Bahrein, a considerable amount of work might be involved in dealing with them and that it would be much more satisfactory if some agent could be appointed to this country who could deal with enquiries of this kind. In this connection you will be interested to see the attached letter from the East Anglian Engineering Co.Ltd, who apparently would be prepared to undertake work of this kind. Captain Kendall who is the Managing Director of this Company is known to this Office and would be, by reason of his background, a very suitable person to undertake the work. You may think it desirable to put the suggestion up to the people in Bahrein as there is no doubt that, if they agree to the appointment of an agent of this kind to act on their behalf, a great deal of work would be saved in this Office,ADRIAN WORKS LOWESTOFT ENG TELEPHONE. LOWESTOFT SSO-I (PRIVATE BRANCH EXCHANGE) TELEGRAMS: EANGLIAN, LQWESTOFT CODES.A.B.C. 5 ™ EDN.BENTLEYS.PRIVATE DIRECTORS CAPTAIN C. E. KENDALL (CHAIRMAN a, MANAGING DIRECTORy COLONEL T. W. PR AG NELL, D.S.O. THE HON. P. P. REMNANT EAST ANGLIAN ENGINEERING COMPANY LIMITED Contractors to the Admiralty War Office Ministry of Aircraft froductim -etc. 3, NORTH COURT, GREAT PETER STREET, LONDON. S.W.l. 1?th April 19if5 . TELEPHONE: ABBEY 2627-8 TELEGRAMS: EANGLIAN. SOWEST, LONDON FOREIGN: EANGLIAN, LONDON CODES: A B C. ST* EDITION, BENTLEY^, PRIVATE Sir, OUR REF.. GW/M. YOUR REF. Representation in the Uni t ed Kingdom . '.Ye have the honour to enquire from you whether it is possible that any States either in India or the Persian Gulf under the general administration of the Government of India may, either now or in the future, require representation in the United Kingdom in connection with Industrial Information and/or Supplies. Should such representation come under consideration by any State as being a suitable channel of communication between themselves and manufacturers in this country, we would very much like to offer our services in this connection. Y/e would point out that for some years now we have been Contractors to a number of Government Departments and have many connections with the Engineering, Aircraft, Electrical, Radio, Motor and Shipping Industries and their allied Trades. In addition, we would mention that the Directors of this Company all have personal experience of India and the Persian Gulf, in which countries they already have active connections.In the event of the above suggestions being of any interest to the Department, -we should be pleased to discuss the matter further vrith you at your convenience or to let you have any other infomation you may require. t ; We have the honour to be, * sib, ' Your Obedient Servants, EA.S‘1 AI7GLIAN GOMPAi&gt;IY, LIIvIIIED. &lt; * * A, * i f ' 1 11 - - - Captain C.E. Kendall. •AnAOii.G- DIRECTOR. . « ... t - o . h.. .• :I -O The Under Secretary, Economic &amp; Overseas Department, The India Office, London, S.YJ.1.% &amp; »o opf 1 Aj 1 797 04 You will see fran the paperaLhelcw* that- the State Engineer in Bahrain wrote to the Institution of Mechanical Engineers asking to be put in touch with seme individual or fim who could undertake to arrange supply of a range of machinery for the Government of Bahrain. The Institution seem to have passed the enquiry to the Machine Tool Control, who passed it on to the High Cannissioner* s Office, who in turn sent it to this Department«, At our request the Machine Tool Control have been good enough to furnish information as to manufacturers of the various machines, with ranges of prices in each case. These particulars may be of some help to the State Engineer. We took this action because we discovered that the Machine Tool Control could supply the information, although in the case of one item it is the Board of Trade and not the Machine Tool Control who are responsible. This is not likely to be the last enquiry of the kind that the new State Engineer will send heme and it is most unlikely that in a future case, particularly if equipment other than machine tools was concerned, we should be as fortunate in getting the information. Even so the information is not quite all that the State Engineer wants; he asks also for lists and no doubt wants firm prices. He also asks to be put in touch with some individual or firm who can arrange supply on his behalf. E.&amp; 0. Department is in no position to help him over this. There is clearly need for someone to make the preliminary enquiries and to arrange supply in such case's I do not know whether it is a matter which I.S.D. would take on, or whether the Bahrain Government have any sort of agent here, or whether there is some retired officer from the Gulf who would like to earn an honest penny/ F.A.K.Harrison, Esq., External Department.mmmm ^ ~ ^ £h+/CiZl ijrV li ti-kr- &gt; penny by acting as agent, either ad hoc or pemanently, in the same way as Captain Binstead acts for Mysore, or whether some firm of shipping or other agents should be recommended. I do not know whether the Indian Trade Commissioner at India House could offer any suggestions, or perhaps the Federation of British Industries could help. E.&amp; 0. Department have been happy enough to lend a hand in facilitating shipments to the Persian Gulf, but we cannot act as purchasing agents for the Bahrain Government, or undertake to find agents for them. I accordingly pass the papers to you for disposal. n hHWI/JS Telephone-VICTORIA 9040 ^ n Ext * 10 ° MINISTRY OF SUPPLY (Code V A.) Our Ref 29 M?ls?Zl05. ^ MACHINE TOOL CONTROL Your Ref 5 * 32604/45. ^ , 35, OLQ QUEEN STREET / 'Iglp' WESTIIINS^^SJ^itj -J' i C»- ( 30th f March, 1945 * T 7 A Deja^ Mr. Maflln, 3^ C,T f^' U * B ahrain State Bngineer T s Department . I | 945 Workshop Equipment. . , ^ — / With reference to your letter and enclosures of the . 26th instant and to our subsequent telephone conversations regarding the above, I have to confirm that in view of the incomplete nature of the details of the State Engineer's requirements, the difficulties in stating deliveries these days, the varieties of qualities of machines that can be offered against specifications and the fact that Price Control has recently been discontinued^ it is impossible for me to give anything but an approximation on each of the items which you ask for. However, in order to be as helpful as possible I append herewith the following information Item 1. 4’ Centre Lathes are being manufactured hy - Messrs. Denham's Eng. Co, Ltd. Halifax. Messrs. Myford Eng. Co, Ltd. Nottingham. Messrs. Gray &amp; Son, Ltd. London, E.C.l. Prices from these manufacturers would range approximatelv between £150 - £200. Item 2 . , . . 6-10 ,f Centre Lathes are being manufactured by - Messrs. Dean, Smith &amp; Grace Ltd., Keighley. Messrs,. Geo. Swift &amp; Sons, Ltd. Halifax. . Messrs. Denham's Eng. Co, Ltd. Halifax. Messrs. Colchester Lathe Co, Ltd. Colchester. P.H.Maflin Esq., India Office, 4, Central Buildings, Matthew Parker Street, /D.MitchellItem 2, Contd Messrs. D. Mitchell. Keighley. Messrs. Lang &amp; Sons, Ltd. Glasgow. Prices from these manufacturers would range approximately between .£400 - £600. Item 5. - * Radial Arm Drill - Manufacturers in this case an Messrs. Jas. Archdale &amp; Go, Ltd. Birmingham. Messrs. Wm. Asquith Ltd. Halifax. Messrs. Kitchen &amp; Wade Ltd. Halifax. Messrs. Adcock &amp; Shipley Ltd. Leicester. Prices from these manufacturers would range approximately between £150 - £350. Item 4 . Sensitive Radial Arm Drill - The makers will be the same as for Item 3. Prices would range approximately between £300 - £400. — ‘ ~~ ’ 4 Item 5. 10' - 12” Stroke Shaping Machine - Manufacturers in this case are - Messrs. Butler Machine Tool Co, Ltd. Halifax. • Messrs. B. Elliott &amp; Co, Ltd. London, N.W.10. Prices from these manufacturers would range approximately between £200 £350. . &lt; Item 6. Horizontal Milling Machine, Medium size, with vertical head and dividing head etc., - The makers in this case are - Messrs. J. Parkinson &amp; Son., Shipley. Messrs. E.H.Jones (Machine Tools) Ltd., London, N.W.9, Messrs. Alfred Herbert Ltd. Coventry. Messrs. B. Elliott &amp; Go, Ltd. London-, N.W.10. 4 4 ' + 4 Prices from the^e manufacturers would range approximately between £400 - £800. /Item 7-3 jd) Item 7 . Twin -/heel Buffing Machine - Manufacturers in this case are - » .Messrs. S. Wolf &amp; Go, Ltd. London, W.5. ^ Messrs. Black &amp; Decker Ltd. Harmondsworth, Middx. , Messrs. W. Canning &amp; Go, Ltd. Birmingham, 18. Prices from these manufacturers would be approximately £20. 8 . Twin V/heel Emery Grinder - Manufacturers in this case are - ^ Messrs. »F.E.Rowland &amp; Co, Ltd. Stockport. Messrs. S. Wolf &amp; Go, Ltd. London, W.5. Messrs. Turner Machine Tools Ltd. Birmingham. Prices from these manufacturers would be approximately £50. Item 9. 12' - 14” stroke Power Hacksaw - Manufacturers in this case are - Messrs. Ghas. Wicksteed &amp; Go, Ltd. Kettering. Messrs. Alfred Herbert Ltd., Coventry. Messrs.^New Fortuna Machine Co, Ltd. Bristol. Prices from these manufacturers would range approximately between £50 - £100. Item 10 . - . Blacksmiths hearth, complete with tools.- Manufacturers in this case are - ? . Alldays &amp; Onions Ltd. Birmingham. Messrs. Buck &amp; Hickman Ltd. London, E.l. Prices from these manufacturers would range approximately between £100 - £150. Item 11. Brazing hearth and Equipment. - The makers will be the same as for Item 10. Prices would range approximately between £50 - £100. Item 12. Sheet Metal Working Tools - Manufacturers in this case are - Messrs.F.J.Edwards Ltd. London, N.l. Messrs. Alex. Mathieson &amp; Sons, Ltd. Glasgow. Messrs. Jos. Rhodes &amp; Sons, Ltd. Wakefield. /Whilst4 - Whilst the term ^a range of Sheet Metal v/orking Tools is rather indefinite, I feel that estimating on say items at an.approximate average price of up to.£5Q eacn, a figure-of £200 would satisfactorily cover.these items* You will appreciate from the above that the suppliers listed against each item are not the full range of suppliers ani no doubt in the event of orders maturing for these^^ mlbhines you will place your enquiries on the full_ ran^ Oo. suppliers, in order to get the best possible deliveries that will exist at that time, . . The cost of the above machine tools approximates to a maximum in the region of £3,500, which I feel will quite reasonably cover the equipment proposed. For your information, none of these items come within the Nominated List of Machine Tools so you will be at liberty -to go ahead with your enquiries on the trade without further reierenc to this Control* In the case of Items 10 and,11, the two Hearths are the. responsibility of - * . ' Industrial Supplies Department,, Board of Trade, Millbank, S.W.l* • J V-/ V but the equipment with these Hearths, i*e*, the Anvils and tools etc., are the responsibility of - ♦ The Directorate of Hand Tools, Wergs Road, T^ttenhall, . . ? Wolverhampton, Staffs. Concerning the remarks of the Government of Bahrain regarding secondhand machines, it is possible to investigate our stocks of surplus secondhand machines at this address, but for purposes of ekport it is not looked upon with .very great favour to ship these secondhand machine tools overseas and it would be preferred if new machines from the above suppliers or their competitors were considered. . Trusting this gives some, at least, of the information you require. _ _ - Yours sincerely,■ Dear Waxtot 19^ • .teopca our tel^ohme oon e sixticoi I erolonc / a acrgy of a loiter iatcd 2?.th FBi&gt;rt«ry, C^/il/Sk froea ilie :3tete 13ogiaeer, ^vorriient of Ba. v ^*ain &gt; / tooeteor xsitii a list of zaachice tools etc. viiich be octtoitos tdll bo roq-iiretl in tiic first inetome in the local TOrkobope. lie desires to tenon’ vjhcther ncchinee are available , ebo can supply than and approadjaate prices am deliveries. There aa^' be one or teo iters which are not in your pro inoe. Will you kindly approach the branch concerned and embody the information in your reply? • I should be obliged if you would let rae have this Information as early as possible. Tours sincerely. (Sgd.) P- H. MAFLtN K* W. Isaacs, :sq., Machine Tool Control (K.G.), Old Queen Street, S.W.1.OFFICE OF THE HIGH COMMISSIONER FCfR'tNDIA. I Tetepi.dne— Temple Bar 8484. Address for Inland Tele ram^*-^i HICOMIND, iESTRA ND, LONDON' Cables —HICOMIND, Please quote the under-mentioned reference, and addressiany further communication to — L T2c04 THE HIGH COMMISSIONER FOR INDIA, L.O., I.A,P. DEPARTMENT, INDIA HOUSE, ALDWYCH,j LONDON, W.&lt;^. 2. and, not to any individual by name. Refen. ^ 5967 /GI Dear Maflin, 23 rd llarch, 194-5 I enclose for your information and necessary action a letter from the State Engineer of the G-overnment of Bahrain which was passed to me by the Machine Tool Control with the request that it should be forwarded to you for procurement action. Yours sincerely, P.H. Maflin, Esq., E. &amp; 0. Department, India Office, 4, Central Buildings, Matthew Parker Street, LONDON, S.W.1.efrt.64.0A:&gt; cc uary, I have read with interest the correspondence from Bahrein forwarded to ee under your endorsement !io« 70 »S about iss Hllson and Grroup Captain Leigh* \ I ar&lt;i glad that the reference to the Adviser eeema to ciear the India Office from ivirv, T3isleading ini or iation* I have also rnentionad the matter to Iniia Louse ho think it .ost unlikely that any official there would have told iss Wilson that she would be able to obtain everything in Bahrein* They suggest that ^ome confusion - ay have arisen over the limitation to 40 lbs. of the luggage which could acco tijany her by air. I do not think that there is any point in pursuing further this investigation as to who said exactly what to ho,n eight months ago. e will Jo our best to see that tlie next time onyort© is sent out to Bahrein from jiere they do not go unfier the wrong impression. ith regard to Leigh’s visas, he is really very naughty. He was told repeatedly what visas he vould need for Ills journey and stated specifically that his i assporfc was in order. Unfortunately we lid not realise the extent to which he had to be spoon-fed ami xt did not occur to us to inspect his Passport ourselves. V&amp;mm alooerefr (Sgo.) R. PEEL 'ihe iion’ble dir Jeoffrey idlor, .C.I. The Jesidenqy, Bashire.Mr, Harrison I spoke to Mr, Batten, who agreed that this was the best way of dealing with the matter, I said that we would write and confirm it* - , Should the file now go to the Accountant General? A previous reference to them about Group Captain Lei^^sDRAFT LETTER Major for r/fo'c Ext. 549 / 45 . -^T-fttoltinbothom, Eoq.y-r. I.E. , Q.B.fe-, ^ Po L“^ Age ^r . y 24 Flu 1345 I^jr dear «Yill you please refer to Tandy ♦ &lt; ^ r%A ^' letter of 18th January No. D.0.250-36/8.E. ^ Jfu ^U^v^Vvv^ I-t 3.S not. Vftmy ttnny -PrTr» n T •pp rQ ^ fi( -j nr - the cost of the transport of her luggage to the port of embarkation from Mrs. Leigh, we are auggecting to the Qffioe~of-the. high GoRHftisoionor that the expenditure should be included in an itemised account of the expen sod of Mrs. Leigh 1 s voyage which they will^/presen^/to the Bahrain Government through -bha Q^n^rnl Department -of this Office and the Accountant General ( Central Revenues. The Bahrain Government could then reclaim the amount from Mrs. Leigh. A. K. HARRISON 1nti 548 ( D.O.No.^'O -36/8.B. Poliiical Agency, Bahrain, ' 945 The^ 18th January, 1945. Will you please refer to your demi-official letter No.i£XT. 5667/44 dated the 19th December 1944? 2. I confirm that the Bahrain Government are prepared to pay the insurance premium on Mrs. Leigh’s personal effects up to an insured value of £ 150/-. They are not prepared to pay the cost of transportation of her luggage to the portjr t —•* *j+i f'' , . ’ i QOV’J^EKlfSkSEll'r or B&amp;HS&amp;XEf I °£cQr j STATE EN'GINtER'^ HEPARTMENt j / 04 c; r^T) NO.GL/ 11 / 64 B&amp;HttMN, PERSIAN GULF. ARABIA. Dated; 24th February,194b The Secretary, The Institution of Mechanical Engineers, Storey^ Gate, St. James Park, London, S.W»1. Dear Sir: I am writing to inform you of my arrival in the Bahrain Islands and of the commencement of my d ^ies as the State Engineer with effect from 2nd November ,1944, also to seek your assistance.Owing to the dilficulty in obtaining satisfactory repairs to Government machinery in £ the local workshops and the poor quality of the available machine tools, I have decided to organise workshop*in the State Engineer’s Department. This briefly embraces the State Electricity Scheme and electrical appliances,State Telephone System,Mechanical Transport,Flour Mills,Water Supply System,Bridges,etco in the first instance I propose to arrange these workshops in different localities, one purely for repairs to electrical equipment and one xor machanical repairs. For the latter, I shall require certain machine tools,hand tools and workshop equipment and I have been informed that it is now possible to obtain these in the United Kingdom ex-Ministry of Supply* i list of my approximate immediate requirements is forwarded herewith with the request that you will very kindly put me in touch with some individual or firm who would undertake to arrange supply on behalf of the Government of Bahrain, in the first instance it is desired to obtain op^rir- mation that the tools,etc., can be made available, and this information will be required by telegrem followed by written confirmation together with lists and prices. In accordance with normal practice, the political Resident in ^ne Persian Gulf will be requested to obtain the necessary certificate of essentiality and export license from the Government of India. Thanking you in advance for any assistance you may be able to render. . y SAB.CM- 6- ! Yours fc^Lthfully, Mm, V ^ qv'vAC 2 - * .. '*7 v5v ' . .vitf (Sgd) Stafte snraLneer, Government/or Bahrain*GOVERNMENT OF BAHRAIN. ELECTRIC SUPPLY DEPARTMENT. STATS DEPARTMENT FITTING &amp; MACHINE SHOP LIST OF MACHINE TOOTS,HAND TOOLS AND WORKSHOP EQUIPMENT (1) One - 4 n centre lathe, sliding, surfacing and screw cutting. Self contained, all gear head. A complete range of tools to be included. (2) One - 8'-10 M centre lathe to similar specification with bed gap. (3) One - Radial arm self contained drill with drills up to 1' or 1J'either Chuck or Morse Taper Shanks. (4) One - Sensitive self contained -ditto-with full range of drills. (5) One - Self contained Shaping Machine 10'-12' stroke. (6) One - Horizontal medium size self contained Milling Machine with vertical head and dividing head attachments, with complete range of horizontal, vertical and saw cutters. (7) One - Twin wheel self contained buffing machine. (8) One - Twin wheel emery grinder, self contained. (9) One - Power hacksaw 12'-14' stroke. (10) One t - Blacksmiths hearth,complete with tuyere,anvil and one set of smiths tools to normal range. (11) One - Brazing hearth and lamp with six months supply of brazing wire, silver solder, fluxes, etc. (12) Range of sheet metal working tools (hand and machine) latter to be hand operated, also medium size guillotine (foot pedal operated). Also, provided they ere fully serviceable,second hand machines would meet our requirements. The electric power supply available for the above machine tools is 230 volts,50 cycles, A.C. Single phase . 400-440 v olts , .ftp cvolea. A.Q. 3 phase.OFFICE OF THE HIGH COMMISSIONER FOR INDIA. Telephone—T emvlz Bar 8484. Address for Inland Telegrams— HICOMIND, ESTRAND, LONDO Cables —HICOMIND, LONDON. Please quote the under-mentioned reference, and address any further communication to — THE HIGH COMMISSIONER FOR INDIA. General department, INDIA HOUSE, ALDWYCH, LONDON, W.C. 2. JWCXKK K'KX'X'Xft'XXOTCX'X Refere G* 225 * 7* 1 /2600 • SECRET. Dear Harrison, 9th January, 1945. C/o 'V, With reference to your letter Ext. 5667 / 44 dated the 19th December, 1944* I write to let you know that Mrs. Leigh embarked for India in the s.s. ’’City of Exeter” on the 22nd December, 1944. Yours sincerely, F.A.K. Harrison, Esq.., India Office, Whitehall, LONDON. S.W.I.Batten, 2so., Office of the High Conrnissioner for India, India House, 19 DEC 1944 Dear Batten, 7ith reference to your telephone conversation with Miss Odgers, I write .to confirm that ~ - - arrange -A th a Shipping Agency to transport Ins. Leigh’s luggage to the port of /U* V y&amp;t' A*’’ /C - '' ' g ' - ——fr-Ai I:.a.— - i. :'.i» ' oAi ■ -• ».&gt;in ~ i •--A 1 I ' ' —T Yours sincerely, V -J^ CUA. Ext, 5667/A4 India Office, Whitehall, London, S.W. 1, \c^December, 19^ The High Commissioner f s Office who are arranging Mrs, Leigh's passage have asked us whether the coat of trans portation of her luggage to the port of embarkation and its insurance for the voyage will be met by the Bahrein Government.- I told them that I imagined that Bahrein Government would be prepared to do this as part of the expenses of Mrs, Leigh's voyagej but that I would confirm it from you* Could you kindly let me have ea&gt;nfUrination on the point? raurs alnoerefa. /~ F - A. K. HARRISON/ Major T* Hickinbotham, C.I.E,, O.B.E*, H*B*M* Political Agent, Bahrein* *After much telephoning I have arranged for Mrs.Leigh to interview 13:.Batten either tomorrow or Friday about her luggage, which consists of 5 packing cases of household stuff, a trunk of her personal belongings and a suitcase. At the moment Mr .Batten appears to be in favour of the luggage accompanying Mrs.Leigh. Mrs.Leigh*s passport is at the Passport Office and they are getting on with the Bahrein visa and the exit permit, pending the receipt of a letter from us in continuation of Ext.423o/44* They will post irt when completed • 15/DRAFT LETTER TTrie Director-General, Passport Office, Dartaoulii Street Sir, ^4 DEC 1944 With reference to India Office letter of 5rd October, No. Ext. 4230/44, regarding the application for a passport submitted in respect of I/rs.Kathleen Karguerite Alexandra Leigh, I am directed by the Secretary of state for India to inform you that a passage to Bahrein via India has now been obtained for bars .Leigh on or about the 21st December. I am to request that the necessary formalities with regard to her passport and s exit permit may now be coupleted and the documents forwarded to her at Spring Farm, Colgate, Horsham, Sussex. It is understood that as she is travelling by sea via India no visas are required other than for Bahrein '*• A? K. HARRISON(If in any case the cornmunioation of the contents of this document to any pers 913 ^ 0 utaide British or U.S.Govt* Berviv... is authorised* it must he paraphrased) Allotted . to Ext ernal Dept o CYfiiBR Prom political Agent* Bahrain, To Political Resident in Persian Gulf, Reptdo Secretary of State for India. Dated Bahrain, IB.SO hours, 11th December, 1944c Reed. 15oOQ hours, j11th Dec., 1944. IMPORTANT 1 096 7 ^'Addressed to Political Resident in the Persian Gulf repeated to London. India Office telegram No. SBOBB 10th peoembero Please book passage to India INDIA OFFICEVaO t N ^ 'AAkjULj* H Grindlay &amp; Company Limited Bankers and Agents. AFFILIATED WITH NATIONAL PROVINCIAL BANK, LIMITED. V L2ti Telegraphic address ‘ GRINDLAY, LONDON LONDON. BOMBAY. CALCUTTA. DELHI. NEW DELHI. KARACHI. LAHORE. MADRAS. PESHAWAR CITY. PESHAWAR CANTONMENT. QUETTA. SIMLA. COLOMBO. DIRECTORS REVOR J. MATTHEWS. R AUSTIN LOW. MALCOLM DONALD S. CAMPBELL. Q. C. WILKINSON. T. E. GRANT. H. E. GRIFFIN. IN REPLY PLEASE QUOTE /J r E f. ^HIPPINGjv.JKJ^ I 4 S.W.I. Mrs K.P.G.Leigh. Spring Frjrm, Cal gate, Horsham, Sussex. Pear Madam, We thank you for your letter dated 10th inst. confirming your visit to us on the 9th inst. in connection with your forthcoming journey to the Persian Gulf. For your information, it is not possible to send goods in advance by the Freight method, unless they have been sponsored by the Government bepartment concerned. In this case it would be the Economic and Overseas Department, India Office, S.W.l. We consider that these packages as describedby you should accompany you to the port when you have secured your passage. If you vill kindly inform us when you are leaving, we will gladly arrange to b as rl^s^ .^ou^ i n connection v/ith your embarkation,, should this Yours faithfully, for GRINDLAY &amp; COMPANY LIMITED / Manager, Shipping Department.* 4? IK./AyiD TKL3SRAM Allotted to Bxternal Deoartraent ( 55 ?) CONi^IDENTIAL CODS TSLI &amp; Prom To Dated Received No. T/892. E X'Jfe'l 083 . 5393 DRAM. —^icr Political Resident in the G^ lf. Secretary of State for India. Bahrein, 17.45 hours, 23rd November 1944. 20.30 hours, 23rd November 1944. Peel from Prior. I am informed that ’’India Office” told new Bahrein State engineer and nurses that they would be able to get ’’everything” here. In point of fact they can get practically nothing and have been put to great inconvenience* I would be glad If this could be borne in mind in future. Delayed owing to the need for repetition. Repetition telegram received 18.30 hours, 24th November 1944.m A Ext. 5196A4. dTC'T DlLiPT JETER K.C. Batten, Esq*, Office of tlie High Coranissioner for India India House, Aldwych, T ,7.C.2. l T NOV I944 Dear Batten, ’Till you please refer to ny letter of 3rd October, No. Ext. 4230/44, regarding a passage to Bahrein for Ivlrs. Leigh, wife of the State Engineer there? Ye have now received a telegram from the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf asking if a passage could be secured for her to Port (1.0. Said as soon as possible. Presumably her husband will be able to make arrangements for /(/,/» ' her onward journey from there* The Bahrein Government recommends this proposal and have agreed to pay the cost of her passage* ,'e assume it is easier to obtain a passage to Port Said than to India, and would be grateful if you could secure one for Mrs* Leigh/Bated Bahrain,- 13.55 hours, 14th November, 1044. Received 14*30 hours, 14th November, 1944. T/852 . Paragraph number 4 of my telegram No*T450 Bent ember 4 th. — Leigh is anxious for his wife who has spent most of her life in the Middle East to join him. He has been separated from her for over 3£ years on active service. Could Ministry of War Transport be asked, to allot her a pa,ssage by sea to Port Said? Cost is recoverable from Bahrain Q-ovornment who s*econsnend proposal*Cl 0. Accountant General HPg Please see papers flagged at A and B (paragrajh 8.) Group Captain 1 leigh has nov? left this country to take up appointment of State Engineer, Bahrain. The Bahrain Government have agreed to pa 3 r his passage, the cost of which has been met in the first instance by the Hi^: Commissioner and will be reclaimed by him from the Bahrain Government through your Department. Y r e should be glad if these papers could be returned to this Department as soon as possible. / ? oct 1944 i )Mr.Har^ 1 would like a letter from us to tidy up their files. ^ Jccjt 2. In the case of the Bahrein nurses, the High ^ Commissioner reclaimed the cost of their passages through the Accountant-General’s Department and the Accountant- ^ General Central Revenues. (This file will have to go to the Accountant-General before it finally cones to rest), I don t -enow whether Group Captain Leigh will have to poy for his air transport from Cairo to Bahrein, but if he does he will presumably reclaim from the Bahrein Government himself. 3* The Passport Office will not deal with Mrs.Leigh's passport or exit permit until they know she has a passage - then they are prepared to rush it through in a few hours. A letter, drafted at the request of, and after consultation with Mr.Little of the Passport Office is below. 4. I don't see how we can press the High Conmissioner Si ve a priority passage to Mrs.Leigh, especially as she will probably have to go via India. I Sign four drafts?. DRAFT LETTER F.E.Ford, Esq,, Air Ministry, Adastral House, Kingsway. _ 3 QQT Dear Ford, Will you please refer to your letter of 13 th September, reference P.5/Reset/756 regarding the appointment of Group Captain Leigh as State Engineer, Bahreini Leigh has now left this country and should arrive in Bahrein by the end of October, We are endeavouring to arrange that Mrs,Leigh shall join him ther»« »s soon ss -nossihls- F. A. K. HARRISON•$- ixJr DRAFT LETTER I H T.F.Harding, Esq., Office of the High Commissioner for India, India House, Aldwych, W.C.2^ ^ Copy^y I understand that Miss Odgers has had some conversation^ with you over the telephone about a Railway Warrant from Horsham to G-ourock for Group Captain H.P.G.Leigh, and I write to confirm that Group Captain Leigh’s railway fares in this country as well as his passage to should be reclaimed from the Bahrein Government through the Accountant— General’s Department of this Office. I- -V* ^ ^ ^ HA '' &lt;ISOf ‘ Hr. i.%. ' &lt; • ’ CL r-1 v V, L 'Vjv/w*DRAFT LETTER Qfyt. \ ^ 'iujl*. 5 fa *** ‘ ^ lv^&gt; fr*' t* 1 C C.-^r^^of^ fSTv K»C#B&amp;tt©nj Esq. y Office of the High Commissioner for India, India House, Aldwych, W.C.2, r 3 CCT ;344 Dear Batten, Will you please refer to Peel's letter of 21st September, No*Ext,4012/44- regarding Group Captain Leigh's passage to Cairo? Leigh has left his wife behind him in this country and is anxious for her to join him in Bahrein as soon as possible: he has been told that there will probably be some available for her. considerable delay before a passage can be made idf ^ We should be grateful for anything you. y ^ JuU i^U £ j’ivV f )5 cJa+C+5 could do to obtain a paooage fer Mrs,Leigh/but realize it will not be possible to give her very high priority. tX^ jr* a—A U &lt;J lS~U. &lt;4.0 £ ^ U* C^x ^ Se F - A - K. WARRfSONDRAFT LETTER The Director-General, Passport Office, Dartmouth Street, S.W. -3 OCT ^44 Sir, With reference to the application for a passport which it is understood has been submitted by Group Captain H.P.G.Leigh in Alexandra. Leigh, I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to inform you that Group Captain Leigh has left this country to take up the appointment of State Engineer under the Government of Bahrein, and^ arrangements are being made for his wife to join him, A further letter will be addressed to the Passport Office when a passage to Bahrein has been arranged for Mrs.Leigh, F. A. K. HARRISONMr, peel. PLo^MT- is~~^ A , Stw^Jt '^«S, ULo ‘ ^ &amp;aLm*^ Kt.^ I spoke to Group Captain Leigh on the telephone and told him that he would probably be sailing next Friday. He said that he is ready to leave at 24 hours notice and that his passport is in order. He has written to the pre-censorship people about his books but lias not had a reply. I might stir them up if he has not heard by next week? Leigh would like to have some sort of chit from us which he can show to his R.A.F. friends in Egypt to prove that his Journey is necessary. Mrs. Leigh has been to see me and seemed quite resigned to the fact that there wff&amp;Ld be some considerable delay before she can Join her husband. n £ fa*, - * . ., 7 ^ Or./'w A 1 /Ext. DRAFT TELEGRAM. GYHffiR XXX Fran: Seoi*etary of State for India. To: Political Resident, in the Persian Guli*, repeated to Political Agent, Bahrain. Yfui^ ^ q Your telegram of 20th September. Leigh \ 'S' has accepted terns,and leaves at the end of this Le&lt;v week by beat to Egypt whence he proposes to obtain air transport from R.A.F.Medical Board, India Office, 15th September 19 44. We have carefully examined iir. H. *oynt2-Gayaor .Leigh and find that he is physically fit for appointment as State Engineer, Bahrein . Col: tt.^.M-afer-Gcnm'alr, I.M.S. M}#*.:..Lieutenant-Colonel, I.M.S. (25396) Wt.28170/P.117 1,000 8/43 A.&amp; E.W.Ltd. Gp.685 (Form 117N)—Tel. No. Holborn 3434. Department P.5» AIR MINISTRY, Ext. Adastral House, P. 5/Re set/75.6 Kingsway, W.C.2. 13th September, 1944* Peel, Many thanks for your letter dated the 8th September, 1944* X am very pleased to hear that you are offering the Bahrein appointment to Group Captain Leigh, I am grateful to you for keeping us posted regarding developments* Yours sincerely*—* India Office, Whitehall, S. 741.IP'MEMORANDUM OF AGREEMENT made this B?]TWEEN His Highness Shaikh Salman bin Hamad IIA A1 Khalifah, Ruler of Bahrain Islands, Persian Gulf, on behalf of the Government of Bahrain, of the one part, and Grow CfiPT#iN'* B yV‘ 3 £&gt;tT forNTZ-U-ftYNoR of the other part, WITNESSETH that it is mutually agreed that the said Government of Bahrain will employ the said Mr# and the said Mr# will serve the said Government of Bahrain for a period of two years commencing from the on the terms specified on the Schedule of terms attached. IN WITNESS whereof the parties hereto have hereunto signed their names. Seal of His Highness Shaikh Salman bin Hamad Alkhalifah Countersigned .•#.#.. His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrain# Provisionally signed by Financial Adviser to the Government of Bahrain, on behalf of the said Government of Bahrain.I rang up the Air Ministry, Mr* Ford is on leave* His deputy said that it is in order for us to write to Leigh direct; they would also like us to write to Adams (apparently it is a frequent source of grievance that applicants only hear from the Air Ministry that their application has been unsuccessful) and also to the Air Ministry to clear the matter upb With regard to the Political Resident's telegram below, the Telegraph Branch say that our telegram 18781 was repeated to Shiraz, they are waiting for Cable and Wireless to confirm that it arrived there. The modifications in the Agreement do not appear to differ very much from the terms as stated at Ext* 2976/2(4: (a) The dearness allowance is increased from Rs*75 p*m* to Rs*120 p*m* (b) The petrol and oil allowance of Rs*85 P*m* is now given as a petrol allowance only* (c) The oil ganging fee is the same* (d) The 3 months' notice clause seems to be included in the first paragraph of the terms of service* If Leigh accepts a fixed salary of Rs. 1000, his total salary will amount to Rs*1435 P*m*sir* t Z writ* to Inftans you that tho Indio Offioo (iaa now boon nuthDriBod by tho (^ovormant of hafareio to o^Vor you on their bohalf the flppoint?MMit ^ ^toto Englneor at &gt;‘ ! u'«ixw X encXooo a &lt;&gt;aft Qi* /groerunt whloh it ia •Mggoetod ohould be .'armlly ooopXetod In due conmo if you aooopt the appointnent, tO’-©ther with the aoholule of the tome of nervice offered* Xh addition to the ealery and contribution to the rovl&amp;wit “undi Tjentioned in the latter locuraent, wo art Infomed by the 'karemoent of Bahrein that the eiiolumenta they now offer Include deamees aHormnoe of Ha* 120 per month petrol aUcrmnoo of Pa*85 per month and oil gorging iee of a* 130 nmth rsudLng a total of Pa* 1,250 per icactth* If you are willing to aoeept the epycintwent on theae tore* arrangements vdii he nade if possible to obtain an air passage to nhrein .or you at a very early date* It ia understood that arrangcr*mta t&gt;«i i*obab3y be made ibr the Bahrein qeerrrwnt to puy ymar vdfe's passage to nisi fron I^hrein should sh« decide to Join you there* riw/ 'roup Captain H*P*CU Leigh, Spring Farm, Col, ate.Sx-U3923/44 DRAFT LETTER CJ-roup Captain H*P.G^Loigh, Spring F aim, Colgate, Horsham, Sussex. ^8 sr? m# /c 9^*1^ Sir, r- I -saa-dabreoted to inform you that -fop-tho oppoiatment of State Higiiieiei uniqi I enclose a/menaorandum of the~ Agreement^te- be made between j/ourself the Gevoitment of Bahrein- together with the schedule of the terms of servio^i addition to the salary and contribution the Provident Fund mentioned in the the emoluments ef- thie 'Peot include de arness allowance of fe*V LuSti.l'V' Rs.120 petrol allowance p»»r- and oil gauging fee ofErt»3921/44 DRAPT LETTER F*E.Ford, Esq. , Air Ministry, Adastral House, ^ King sway, W.C® f 8 SCP 1944' Dear Ford, Would you please refer to your letter \ of 22nd August, reference P # 5/ReseV^^ and 756? We have now heard that the Govemnent of Bahrein are prepared to accept Group Cep tain Leigh for the post of State Engineer. I am writing to him direct forwarding him the terms of agreements . I ssn also writing to Warrant Officer Adams informing him that his application has been unsuccessful* Yours sincerely. (3gd.) R. PEEU ■Krt.3921/44 DRAFT LETTER Warrant Of floor D*M* Adams, Brentwood, Leicester Road, Sale, Cheshire# 18 SEP 1344' Sir, &amp; Ur, tUi^ v L,t L* C~*^ ir 1 d^ ( t ■ ^ X- ^ I I.'i aIs**'*' [ u f I an directed to inform you/that ^7 -&gt; your application for the aypoin Uiieirt of State Engineer under the Government of Bahrein jias proved unsuccessful and the lent hay nuw ^^eea^fniad# I am. Sir, Your obedient Servant, (3gd.) R. PEEL, £salary of Rb* 1*000 in lieu of RSoQOO rising by Rs»(‘?50) increments* 'V w . 4, If Leigh is engaged grateful if arrangements could be made to fly him to Bahrain at earliest possible moment* Political Agent Bahrain is prepared to arrange for Bahrain Government to pay (? Leigh) °s wife's passage to and from Bahrain*SCHEDULE OF TERMS OF SERVICE OF MR Terms andNature of Contract* Mr shall faithfully serve the Government of Bahrain as State Engineer in charge of the Bahrain Government Electric Scheme for the term of this contract which is for two years, the first six months of T «hich will be on probation, terminable by three months notice on either side, renewable, after its expiry, by mutual consent. Pa^ The rate of pay shall be Ha* 800/- (eight hundred rupees) per mensem rising by annual increments of H3*50/- (fifty rupees) per month per annum to Rs«l,000/- (one thousand rupees). Provident Fund, A sum of Rs.100/- (one hundred rupees) per mensem, or its equivalent in sterling, will be paid monthly into an account with the Eastern 3anic Limited representing the State Engineer’s Provident Fund, the proceeds of which will be handed over to the State Engineer on termination of the contract, Accomodation 0 A free furnished house shall be provided by the State or an allowance of Ks.lOO/- (one hundred rupees) per mensem shall be paid by the State in lieu Furlough, (a) Furlough will be earned on the basis of one and a half months per year’s completed and approved active service. Furlough will not count as active service for the purpose of assessing subsequent service or annual leave.jr one month, in at tod after each year’s^completed and appi servico; xt will be counted as active service for the purpose of assessing furlough due and it may be accumulated up to two months in all. (c) Full average pay will be drawn in respect of normal furlough and annual leave. (d) Leave rur r be granted in special circumstances and when no leave is due, without pay; this leave will not be reckoned as active service under the contract. Medical. Medical attendance will be provided for Mr. at State expense. Transport. A car shall be placed at the disposal of the State Engineer while on duty. passages. A first class sea passage will be provided for Mr. from the United Kingdom to Bahrain, on taking up first appointment. A similar first class passage will be granted on final termination of contract with the G-overnment of Bahrain. A first class sea passage for Mr. will be provided to and from Bahrain to Karachi, by the State, when travelling on State service or annua] leave. In the event of Mr. not availing himself of the annual leave to India, admissible under clause 5 (b) he will be permitted to utilise the value of such passage or passages towards the cost of any passage to Europe on furlough which, under the terms of this agreement the Government of Bahrain is not under obligation to pay.j “•he first cias^ re ferred to above shall be 0., 1st class C from Bombay to , and first class with food, from Bahrain to Bombay, triction of Trade. As long as Mr. remains in the service of the Government of Bahrain he shall not carry on an. trade or business on his own or anyone’ else’s behalf, or receive any remuneration for any services rendered to any other party without the previous consent of the Government of Bahrain which must be obtained in writing. lor the purpose of this agreement all dates and periods shall be those of the Arabic calendar which is the official calendar used by the State of Bahrain. Arbitrator. If any question arises under the contract, whether as regards the meaning or in other respects, the question shall be referred to the arbitration of the Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf and his decision shall be final. Re : Clause 4. Crockery and linen are not included.^ A DRAFT TELEGRAM, Fran: Secretary of State for Iniia. T 40 : Political Agent, Bahrain, repeated to Political Resident in ^ , the Persian G-ulf, Shiraz. I \ j ch * V' 'V C'S {) Addressed Bahrain, repeated Political Resident Shiraz. \ I 1 \ l I ‘ Your telegram Ho .717 August 34th. Bahrain State r / T\ ■ Engineer. No further candidates having cone forward : t /, 71 ! &gt; ; Selection Board (which included Galloway) interviewed , J 1\^\ Adams and Leigh. Board definitely rejected Adams as not sufficiently qualified. Leigh made very favourable impression. He possesses wide experience UHCLpft t'V *X, and has ooaeeteol qualifications for this appointment. He held appointment as Ghief Technical Officer, Middle administrative side. He is live wire and young for his age and has had experience of sort cf climate he will meet in Bahrain, as has also his wife. Board are strongly of opinion that he would be an outstanding choice; ll j comparing very favourably/with previous holder, and that ' one flight wait ;long before finding candidate of similar qualifications. P aoc j j @QD‘ — ' ^ i o') &gt;0 .■I Xb!* 1 IState Engineer T Bahrain. The present State Engineer, Mr. W.B. Steele, was employed by Messrs. Callenders Construotion and Cable Compary when the electrical installation at Bahrain was originally erected in &gt;L931, and was retained by the Bahrain Government as State ;ineer. There was also an Assistant Engineer who joined the kcryal Navy and has not be replaced. Mr. Steele is relinquishing his appointment for domestic reasons. jr The post is a responsible one for which administrative ^- s needed. The State Engineer is in charge of the power house and supervises the electrical installation. The » Royal Navy are lOpfj dependent on the State for lighting, wireless, air conditioning etc. The R.A.P. were also 100^ dependent for these services in May of this year but it is possible they are now only 500, but in addition they have direction finding instruments. Cable ai¥i Wireless Ltd. are 80/3 dependent on the State. Other duties include oil gauging, the telephone system, the Bahrain Government Fire Service, the registration of motor vehicles and the inspection of public vehicles, anti-malaria measures such as drainage, ai*l The terms offered by the Bahrain Government are:- Salary: • Rs.800 to Rs.1000 per mensem, depending on qualifications. Allowances: Provident Fund: Rs.UOO Light and Petrol: Rs. 85 Dearness Allowance: Rs. 75 * Oil Gauging (if undertaken): Rs.130 Free furnished quarters and car. Leave :- One month* s local leave per annum, passage to India /being. CrrJC-! r r» f being paid. Three months 1 leave to the United Kingdom on completion of two years' contract. ^ Passage:- Passage from fclace of recruitment paid on appointment and to the United Kingdom on completion of contract. Appointment to be for two years, the first six months on probation, ancl extendable for a further two years by mutual agreement. &gt; * Xiw&gt; WiJ 1 • wV ^ LOiC The two candidates for the appointment are Group Captain Leigh and ex-Warrant Officer Adams. Particulars of their careers supplied by the Air Ministry are attached. The Bahrain Government consider Group Captain Leigh is too old and are doubtful whether Warrant Officer Adams is sufficiently weU qualified; Brigadier Drummond has suggested that while Adams appears to be well trained he has had no practical experience, of being in charge of a power house. r[+ v •313X_Q 9;:T V sr.ii l. : c&amp; GO . nc '•ni'.ace-.re~ :as5sxsigpll .. : hasi^ jixe - v : • ..v -fl W . - . . X v/ol.' 36 ■ O'-GROUP CAPTAIN H.P.G. LEIGH, SPRING- FARM, COLGATE t H)RSIiAM, SUSSEX. (Telephone - Fey gate 251) Bom 4th January 1889 - Married, ^^'jated private tutor 1893-1897• Secondary School - Hanley - Staffe 18&gt;/-1900. Ellesmere College, Shropshire 1900-1903. Pupil to Engineers (Elec, Mech, and Loco.) 1903-1908. Assistant Foreman and Draughtsman to Marine and Elec. Engineers- 1908-1909. Served in ranks and with a commission in R.N., R.N.A.S., and R.A.F. from 20th April, 1909&gt; until 9th March, 1944&gt; when he retired from the Service. Has been employed mainly on engineering duties whilst in the Service. Is entitled to Symbol E X, A.M.I.MechuE., A.F.R.Ae.S., has been twice mentioned in despatches. Has taken Advanced Aeronautics Engineering Course at R.A.E. and Cambridge University (3 years). Has trained in Steam and General Engineering, but has since specialised in Internal Combustion Engines, including Diesels. Is described as an experienced and capable Technical Officer, hard-working, with a sound knowledge of Staff duties.EX-WARRAIIT OFFICER D»M, ADj^IS, BRENTWOOD, LEICESTER ROAD, SALE, CHESHIRE. Bom 25th September 1915 - Single. Educated Manchester Grammar School. ^opranticed with and employed by Metropolitan Viokers Electrical L^ipany, Trafford Park, Manchester. Has obtained Higher National Certificate in Electrical Engineering, and is awaiting the results of a further examination which, if successful, will entitle him to G-raduateship of the Institute of Electrical Engineers, the Ordinary National Certificate and Associateship of the Manchester College of Technology. Is also awaiting results of papers on a course in industrial administration Served in R.A.P. from 17th January 19W until he was invalided on the 12th July 194A after sustaining a joint fracture lower end right tibia and fibula with dislocation of ankle joint. ^as employed as a pilot and has flown approximately 400 hours on Manchesters, Oxfords, Ansons, Hamdens and D.H.82.A. His character and trade efficiency were exemplary and his general conduct and bearing were very good, although his ability as a pilot suffered as a result of his ankle injury. (The General Electric Company Ltd. are prepared to make him an offers but he has been advised by the Air Ministry to await the decision of the India Office before committing himself with them).Tel. No. Holborn 3434. AIR MINISTRY, Ext. 34$ P. 5/Reset,/ 646, Kingsway, W.C.2. s 10th August, 1944* Dear Mr, Harrison, Confirming my telephone conversation. I have now received the confidential record of service for Warrant Officer D,M, Adams who you have under consideration for a possible appointment as a State Engineer at Bahrein, I have already given you details of this candidates career. He served in the Royal Air Force from the 17th January, 1940, until he was invalided on 12th July, 1944, after sustaining a compound fracture lower end right tibia and fibula with discolation of ankle joint. His character and trade proficiency were exemplary. He was employed as a Pilot and has flown 400 hours (approx.). His general conduct and bearing were very good although his ability as a Pilot suffered because of his ankle injury. /For F.A.K. Harrison, Esq., India Office, Whitehall, 9 S.W.l. JtFor your confidential inform ion he has recently been interviewed by the General Electric Company Limited, and they were impressed with him and are prepared to make him an offer, but I know that he will prefer to obtain the appointment in India if possible. I have therefore advised him toawait your decision before committing himself with the General Electric Company. Yours sincerely.Tel. No. Holborn 3434. Err jML P,5/Reset/6if6 t. .. 75 g A Dear tr. Harrison, AIR MINISTRY, Adastral House, Kingsway, W.C.2. t 1 ' $ 22nd Angu st 1944 . Re:- Appointment as State Engineer Bahrein. Gonfirming telephone conversation v/ith your secretary this morning, I have asked G-/C Leigh and W/0 Adams to attend for an interview with you at 11 a.m. on Thursday 22hth August, at the India Office. I have also requested them to confirm v/ith you that they will attend as indicated above.Steto &gt;-:nr.ta*r. ahgnln. «; '■ Tht ppoacnt State Ivn^lnocr, Itr. W.LU Steele, tms a iploTed by .loflars. Jallerolerg OonetruDtlan and Oable Oaapnjqy ^aon Hw eleotrloal InetaHattoin at Bahrain ms originally ereotcxl in 1951, «id ma retained by the Bahrain Goveoronent ao State Ei*sineor. There m© aleo (m Assistant Engineer who Joined tlie Royal IJaty and has not be repieoed. ^1r# Bteole ia rdinqulshinE his appointnent for doneatla reasons. The post is a responsible one for which oduinUlarattve cbilily ia neodod. The State i^nginear is in ohsr^e of the power house and siipervlaeo the electrioal instaHatioru The Royal Navy are 3XX&gt;» dependent on the State for lighting* wire loss, air oonditianinb o^ 0, The ware also UO* dependent for those sar/loos in Bay of tills year but it is possible tlwy are now only 5Q , but in addition they have direction finding Instmwsnts* Oable and Wireless Ltd* are Oq; dependent on the State* Other duties incluio oil the telephona j^steia, t\m Bahrain Oovernuent Fire aervioo* the registratloii of raotor vehioles and the inspeotion of publio vehicles, antiHraalaria raeasnres such as drainage, and public works ~ road and bridge building* The tar is offered by the Bahrain Government are:- Salary: Rs.QOO to Rs.lDOO per nemeia, depend! rv, on qualifioationa - HcManees: Provident Fund: Rs*100 light and Petrol: Rs* 09 Dearness AUcwmnoe: Rs* 73 Oil Gmgiqg (if undertaken): Rs. ISO Free furr&amp;oheci (|mrters and cor. Loave:- Ono oontii* s looal leave per anran, passage to India /beingboi^g paid. ... . , . ^ ? Thro* aontiiB 9 loavo to tlie United lingcion on oompletion oC too ^oana* oonti-oct. Pasaaget- PesaR^e free place of reonziteient paid on appointaesnt and to the United Kingdom on ocxapletion of contract. Appointment to bo for too years, the first six raontha on probation, and coctoninble for a further two yeera by uutual &lt; igi'ocfisent* e &gt; ' C . .... # Dte too candidates for ite flppolzxineaxt ere Group Captain Leigh and m&amp;mamnt Officer Adaoa. I^ertloulars of their careers cupplled by the Air Ministry are attedhed. The Baio-ain rovemnent oonaider Groqt&gt; Captain Leigh is too old ^nd are do*£&gt;tfaL 'whether Warrant Officer Ada as is sufficiently well qualified; Brigadier Dnsaaond has suggested that while Adaras appears to be well trained he has bad no practical eaperienoe of being in charge of a poser house. . . - ' ' , C-_. . i.Zjih S«ptonb«r 1515 • Single, liduoated Monolvatcr Oremar bohool. ApproB-tiood with and ctaplojrod by lotropolitan Tldcttrs Blootrloal CJoapui^r, Trafford itork, M«nal»Bt«r. lias cfetalned IUgbRr national Oartifioat© In Slaotrloal Hr^liioortng, and is mmitiiv, ttie results of a further osamlTiation which* if auooesad?ul, will entitle bin to &amp;raduateehl$ of the Inetitute of :icotrical Engineers* the Ordinary national Oertifioate and Aseoolatoohip of the Manchester Oollege of ^eahnolof^7 X* also awaiting results of paper® on a course in industrial ndainistratian Served in 8-A.F. frao 17 th January 15^0 until he was invalided on the 12th July 1944 after sustaining a joint fraoture lower end right tibia and fibula with dislocation of ankle Joi *t« • as eaplop/ed as a pilot and has flown appnrdjriately 400 hours on ; r anciioator8* Oxfords* Amons* Itanirisns and D.JU r 52.A. His ohoiTioter and trade effloianqy t«re eococ^laiy and his general oonduot and boarii£ were very good, altbou^i his ability as a pllit suffered as a result of Ida arfclo injury. (The Oensral Sleotrio Ooapai^r Ltd. are prepared to twke him an offer, but he has been advised by the Air Ministry to await the dooioion of t* 1 10 India Office before ooitiitting himself with then) •. ^ ^ COPY &gt; r f3‘ Xls A A y***' 3644 d«44 INWARD Allotted to External Department CONFIDENTIAL CODE TELEGRAM From Political Agent, Bahrein To Secretary of State for India Reptdcto Political Resident in the Persian Gulf Dated Bahrein, 19c15 hours, 14th August 1944 Received 23*00 hours, 14th August 1944 2 D &gt; 1° •n &gt; c S CO m No,717. Addressed to India Office repeated to Political Resident, Shiraz* Reference India Office telegram 17489 Augu st IQth -3/^7 Of candidates offering Leigh is cor-’ids red *oo old, Adams is promising but it is ck - VI [ether he can be considered sufficiently Qualified itil he he has passed his. examinations. ' oat -ad' ^lid and responsible and includes administrative I- ities. Good general, education desirable, Bahrain J-&gt;veminent are loath to make appointment’! ''.. : the d o 'candidates offered- Bahrein Government wish you to ind 1 evi svj mdidates presented by Air Ministry and ...:-alty r ith view to appointment. If qualifierticno of themost suitable are forwarded by fast air mail decision will be telegraphed without delay* . Draft agreement is being sent by fast air mail.-■ Tel. No. Holborn 3434. 348 Kxt. ref. P • 5/Re s e t/646. VOUR REE. M—. f-V £%S® _ m r rnpY (^26) AIR MINISTRY, (P.5) me ■ j o r _... •^,t ADASTRAL HOUSE, KINGSWAY, \N.C.Z. July, 1944. )£ 19th ,y! Dear Mr. Harrison, ■ //e would like to rejeormnehd anotheij candidate to you xor consideration ir^ c^&gt;nn^dn wigh the appointment as a State Engineer at Bh-kwrein. —^ ^ _ He is ex-./arrant Officer D.M. Adams, v Brentwood, Leicester Road, Sale, Cheshire. Born 25th September, 1915, and is single. He was apprenticed with and employed by Metropolitan Vickers Electrical Company, Trafford Park, Manchester. For a time was Sales Engineer with the same lirm. Adams was educated at Manchester Grammar School, and has obtained the Higher National Certificate m Electrical Engineering. He is further awaiting the results of examinations. If he is successful he will be entitled to graduateship of the Institute of electrical Engineers, and the ordinary National Certificate and Associateship of the Manchester College of technology. He is also awaiting the results of papers of a course in Industrial Administration. He has flown 400 hours on Manchesters, Oxfords, Ansons, Hampdens and D.H. 82A. I have not yet seen his Confidential Record of /Service F.A.K. Harrison, Esq. India Office Whitehall,— •&gt; * Service, but I understand that he has a good record. I hope to receive confirmation of this from the Record Office in the very near future. Yours sincerely, tL F. E. FORD.Tel. No. H OI.BORN 3434. Ext. 346 Ref. 5/Re set/756, Vouk Ref. J ^5k' X ' v 0 n^o'A &gt; ii &gt;r I •'V./ »'V&lt; • ^ AIR MINISTRY, „ c *U-H * • 5* - • ADASTRAL HOUSE, KINGSWAY, W.C.2. :? i y ! j rv 14th July, 19A4. 944 Aar Mr, Harrison, Thank you for your further letter dated 7th July, reference EXT. 2976/44, , enclosing a telegram from the Persian Gulf relating to the appointment of an Estate engineer at Bahrein and for detailed information given therei n. May we recamnend the following candidate to you for consideration, he is:- Group Captain H.P.G. Leigh, Spring Farm, Colgat e, Horsham, Sussex, I am enclosing herewith a sheet giving particulars relating to this ofi icer s career. His confidential record of service states that he is an experienced and capable Technical Officer, hardworking, with a sound knowledge of Staff duties, I have infoimed this officer of pay, conditions etc, appertaining to this appointment, he has asked me to recomnend him /for P.A.K, Harrison Esq,, India Office, Whitehall, S,W.l, WECa, AM, OftPr 1 '' JUL INDIAa&amp;OUJe OBTAIN IU V* £• U LC-IU oFiUKG FARM. G tGME* HOftSHMU (Teler)hone - g(gy£ate 2!il)« Bom li/l/lBQ9 — ifarrled* Educated Private tutor 3i595-1897» Socondaiy B(Aool - Hanlqr - staffs 1897-1900* julleaniere College, dhropehire 1900-1903• Pupil to .ngineere (EleovMeoh* and Loco,) 1903-1908, Assistant Foreman and Jlraughtaman to Marine and 1 lee, Engineer® 1908-1909* Served in ranks an&lt;3 with a coramiesion in R,N., R,N,A#;&gt;,, and ?.h,F, fron 20th A )ril, 1909 until 9th iarch, 1944# Kho» he retired from the Service, Has been employed mainly on engineering duties whilst in the service. Is entitled to Symbol &amp; «, A,F,R,Ae,S« # has been twice mentioned in despatches. Has taken dvanced .cnonautics nj;ineerins Course at R, \,C, and Cambridge (Jniversity (3 years). Has traLitd in Steam and General engineering# but has since specialised in Internal Combustion ^Ingi es, including Diesels, Is &amp;&lt; scribed as an experienced and capable Technical Oi'ficer# hard working, vith a sound knowledge of otaff duties./ Any further communication should be addressed to— The Secretary of the Admiralty, London, S.VV.l ^ t. It — quoting 'JSi/..Q.. «JE i7QS3j..’hb on outside of the envelope as well as in the text. x°C\\ JL-z ^ x Jl n -7 u u u i I am commanded by My Lords Commissioners of tfee Adsliralty to refer XfU* , V /i/ /- to your letter of the 19 th May, 1944» EXT.2251/44 enquiring whether the Admiralty would be willing to release from Naval service a qualified engineer to fill the post of State Engineer at Bahrein. 2 My Lords note that the Secretary of State asks for the release of a qualified non-commissioned officer for this purpose. It would not be possible to spare an Electrical Artificer from the Boyal Navy owing to the shortage of suitable candidates for that rating, and further it is considered that an Electrical Artificer would be quite unsuitable for the appointment, which apparently requires a fully qualified Engineer with electrical experience. 3 If, however, full details of the duties required and terms of service can be forwarded My Lords would consider releasing an Engineer Officer, if a suitable volunteer could be found. I am. Sir, l (o ^ l w Your obedient Servant, The Under Secretary of State for India, Department, India Office, London, S.W.1. 7Sxt&gt; 2976AW Os. ^ « uly, 19 ♦ I am directed 'ey the Secretary of State for India to refer to India Office letter No. Ext* 225W: Pf t*he 19tli May, 192*4, and subsequent telephone conversation regarding tlie filling of the appointment of State ;.:n.qineer at Bahrein, and to / enclose a copy of a telegram from the Politioal Resident in the Persian Gulf •giving full information as to tie terms of the appointment* It Trill be seen that it is considered that the qualifications of Electrical Lieutenant vould be »egaap4ed mb- preferable to those of Electrical \rU.fioer. I nxau i % The Secretary, Admiral ly, :iite.aall, ,4 .1*£^^.7iAS July* 19U. Sir, .*-v J- I an directed by the Secretary of State for India to refer to your letter No. P5/iesettlernent of 21st June, 15N|4&gt; regarding the filling of the appointment of State Engineer at iiahrein, and to / enclose a copy of a telegram from tiie Political Resident in the Persian Gulf giving full information regarding the terms of the appointiiKnt. I am. Sir, Tour obedient Servant, F. A. K. HARRISON x The Under Secretary of ;tate. Air Ministry, s. .1,I FILE COPY *£ 2 XT r E. * INWARD TELEl mjd~ ' Allotted to External Department* L i c i g 83166 C ^ ' ^ CONFIDENTIAL CODS ' TELSGRAM Pcliticsl Resident in Persian Gulf*- Secretary of State for India* Bushire, 2l*00 hours, 4th July, 1944* 07*00 hours, 5th July, 1944* Prom To Dated Received 1557« Ycur telegram 14538 June 30th* Terms are as mi follows?- Salary Rs*800 to Rs*l,000 a month depending on qraalifications« Allowance etc» as follows 5 - Provident fund Rs a 100 s light and petrol R3*85, dear ness Rs»75 and if he undertakes oil gauging Rs»150, all a month* Free furnished quarters and car* One month ? s local leave, a year return passage to India ^ being paid* Appointment for 2 years first 6 months on probation* Appointment extendable after 2 years by mutual agreement* In addition to local leave 3- months ! leave to United Kingdom allowed on completion jmbf 2 years contract* Passage from place of recruit- g*|nent paid on appointment and to United Kingdom on comeletion of contract* m *- J 3* Engineer v/ould be required to supervise electrical r installation and,to be in charge of powerhouse* v r 3* Qualifications of electrical Lieutenant would be J. preferable*Telephone Any communications on the subject of this letter should be addressed to :— Y quoted and the following number quoted :— lesettlement* P5/&amp; Your Ref. ^ I am directed to refer to your letter dated. 19th May, 1944 regarding the possibility of the release from the Royal Air Force of a suitable Non-Commissioned Officer for the appointment of State Engineer at Bahrein. I am to state that it may be possible for this Department of the Air Ministry to recommend a suitable ex-officer or ex-N.C.O. for consideration in this connection. From time to time officers and N.C.O.s apply to this Branch of the Air Ministry for assistance in obtaining suitable employment when they are invalided or retired from the Royal Air Force, and s ome of them have good engineering qualifications. For example. Flight Lieutenant A.J.Anido, The Gables, Briff Lane, Bucklebury, Nr. Reading, Berks, born l?th April, 1890 and married. He is aB.Sc., A.M.I.M.E. and A.M.I.E.E. Considerable engineering and electrical engineering experience, practical teaching and consultant. It would however be most helpful if we could be given full information regarding the terms of the appointment, salary etc., in order that we may ascertain whether apy likely /candidates l* 1 ' The Under Secretary of State for India, India Office, Whitehall, London, S.W.l.EXT.2231/44 DRAFT LETTER '''’''Jr s ; l/~ - u , ^ u') ^ ^, Hr^' * 0 7.^ , ' 1 n. \%' t C^/C. k,.£. The Secretary of the Admiralty, S.W.l. Vs, (/m . 4 7 f. Sir, &lt;9 tQM I am directed by the Secretary of State W'« for India to refer to hi* letter No. EXT.1539/44 U of the 20th April on the subject of securing the services of Mr.H.D.Furber as State Engineer to the Government of Bahrein. As the Lords Commissioners of the Admiralty have been informed, it has since been ascertained that Mr. Furber is ..definitely unwilling to return to Bahrein and the suggestion for his re-employment in the above-mentioned capacity has therefore been abandoned. « Further enquiries for a qualified engineer ,,, to fill the post of State Engineer Bahrein have siftce been pursued^without success/and it has ***► been suggested by the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf that either the Royal Navy or the R.A.F., in view of their dependence on the icA- State for the supply of electricity, might be /willingwilling to release a qualified non-commissioned officer *&gt; to fill the post in question under the Bahrein Government. It is understood that the Royal Naval Establishment at Bahrein is at present entirely dependent on the State for the supply of electrical energy for all purposes, ♦ including light and wireless, and that the R.A.F. is also - « • at present likewise wholly dependent but their requirements may shortly be reduced. Messrs. Cable &amp; Wireless Ltd. are also dependent on Bahrein State for 80$ of their requirements of electrical energy. The Secretary of State would accordingly be ^atoful if the Lords Commissioners of the Admiralty would examine s I- - • the possibility of releasing a qualified Petty Officer to undertake the appointment of State,Engineer at Bahrein. A similar letter has been sent to the Air Ministry. pgd.) R- pEEU j Z' &gt; J -O L*. J.lo fj ' re 5 ' LvSEXT.2251/44 01 DRAFT LETTER The Under-Secretary of State, Air Ministry, Whitehall, S.W.l. cC Sir, I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to say that ,the post of State Engineer to the (Government of Bahrein having fallen vacant and all efforts to secure a qualified engineer to fill the appointment having failed, the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf has suggested that either the Royal Air Force or the Royal Navy, in view of their dependence on the State for the supply of electricity, might be willing to release a qualified N.C.O. to fill the post in question under the Bahrein Government. It is understood that the R.A.F. &gt;fetablishment at Bahrein is at present heavily dependent on the State for the supply of electricd 4 energy for all purposes, including light and wireless, though their requirements may shortly be reduced and that the Royal Navy is likewise /wholly1 wholly dependent. Messrs. Cable &amp; Wireless Ltd. are also dependent on Bahrein State for QQP/o of their requirements of electrical energy. Mr. Amery would accordingly be grateful if the Air Council tfould examine the possibility of releasing a qualified non-commissioned officer to undertake the appointment of State .Engineer at Bahrein. A similar letter has been sent to the Admiralty., 17146 \ Q 4 A COHPIDKKTIAL POPE TSLlgURAM Prom To Hepoated Dated Received Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Secretary of State for India, to Government of Indiac Buahire^ 18«I5 hours, 16th May, 1944. i 28,15 hours, 16th May, 1944. 1806. ^ Addressed to Secretary of State for India copy sent oy air mail to the Government of India. * Your telen ram No* 10970 May 12th* Bahrain State Knginaero Following is repetition of Bahrain telegram No* 453 May 14th&gt; Begins . Reference India Office telegram No.10970 May 18th. 2. Navy are 100 per cent repeat 100 per cent dependent on the State for electrical supply for all purposes i*e* light and wireless etc. R.A.F, at present 100 per cent repeat 100 per cent dependent hut b© only 50 per cent repeat 50 for A&lt;WLa»i2fcoj j/e plus direction finding, j-netrumentacGable irelsss JitpUBO per cent repeat BO per cent ! dejb^MAyLtn, Bnutj PplAOFriCtI F 1 L -- ,o &gt; 'VPvj. IHWABD TELEGRAM a. i External Department CONgIDEMTIAL CODE T 2031 L-* W lit n+H. 16182 Political Resident in Persian Gulf* Secretary of State for India* (^Repeated to Government of India, External Affairs Department.) Dated Bushire, 15.30 hours, 6thMayfl&amp;44. Received 18*30 hours, 8th May 1944* m * KoJU.9 . Addressed Secretary of State for India (^repeated to Government of India External Affairs Department.) My telegram Ko« 1011 April 28th, _ In view of dependence Of Royal Air Force and Navy in Bahrain on State for supply of electrical energy could service departments he approached for release of qualified engineer? A qualified nOn-commissioned officer would suffice. To Government of India only* It has been ascertained that Elliot is not qualified-Q&gt;S) r ^ 15010 00N FXDKH TIAL 00m From Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, To Secretary of State for India Repeated to Government of India, External Affaire Dept., Dated Bushire, 19.00 hours, 26th April, 1944. Received 22.30 hours, 28th April, 1944. No. 1011. -Addressed to London and repeated to Few Delhio My telegram 868 April 4th. State Engineer Bahrain. 2* Political Agent Bahrain reports that Furher has definitely expressed unwillingness to return to Bahrain (? full stop,omitted) To Government of India only. 3, A- Adviser to Bahrain Government has heard that one H.JaBllis at present wording in Sulphur Hines at Nok Xundi Koh-i-Sultan, Baluchistan may be suitable gratexbl if confidential enquiries could be made regarding his suitability and extent of electrical experience - if suitable could relief be arrangedsIEXT. 1539/44. DRA5T LETTER The Secretary to the Admiralty, Whitehall, S.W.1. *0 Sir, w ^ 0 ° I am directed hy the Secretary of State for India to inform you that a request has been received from the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf that the services of Mr. H.D. Furber may be obtained as State Engineer to the Government of Bahrein. Hn fry-Artr? Government of India&gt; Mr. Furber was previously employed by the Bahrein Government as Assistant State Engineer, being particularly concerned with the Electrical Department. It is understood that he has joined the Royal Navy since the outbreak of war and that his present address is Navy House, Port Said. In view of the commitments of the Bahrein Government to supply^*! electric^ mi,Ti ^\ *t. 153 S/4U Blr, I an directed by the fe eo etary of atote for India to infom you that a re^jueet haa been received from the olitioal Resident in the Persian ^ulf that the se vices of r. rt#R# ?urber pej be obtained as estate iginevr to the government of iaiireirw !r* J'urber wa» previously eiployed by the i&gt;a’\rcin Government as Aa Blatant State Engineer, being particularly oonoemed with the electrical Uepfirtaent# It ic understood that he has Joined the Royal Navy since the outbreak of war and that his present ad-bress. is Navy House, *brt S '^id* &lt; In view of the ocr. -.itmentB of the Jahrein Govemnont to supj)ly electricity at laiireln for the use of the Royal Navy, the Royal A r broe and ] lessrs. Cable and The Secretary to the Adrairalty, Wireles^/ Whitehall, S.W. 1** « .irclass it is ot^nsidercd essential that the post in question should be filled by a fully qualified engineer# The appointment has fallen vacant through the resigaatiojf''f the former occupant on aoccunt of serio** domestic difficulties, and efforts to fill the post fro-. Indi« h«v« failed^ In these oircnr.st^nces }'r. -‘mery very isuCh hopes that the lords Cat desioners of the Admiralty will be prepared to release Mr* ??urb«r for the aqpoitftmfHt if he ie willing to accept it. ' ‘ P / ^ ■ - v » Tf, therefore, no objection is sesn ' in principle to the release of Mr* iWber from the Royal Navy, the Secret«j'y of State for India would be grateful if an approach could be made to him to ascertain whether he is willing to return to Reforein to undertake the post of State Kni*ineer there* Ihe Bater*ein Oovermewt would then bo informed in order that terns of employment might be arrargued. /• I am. Sir, Your obedient Berv?mt *FILE COP - - Fo ib Hi.0 ^ .. INWARD TELEQ] •f. f &lt; Li J [944 COHPIDKNTIAXi GODa TKLBORAM 7 1J839 AXXottect to External Dspartment From Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. To Secretary of State for India. Repeated to New Delhi. Dated Bushire, 17.30 hours, 4th April, 1944, Received 08.00 hours, 5th April* 1944. 0 866 , Addressed to London repeated to New Delhi Saving. q 0 &lt;7 Mv telegram No.459 February goth. Relief for State Engineer } Bahrain. 2. Government of India inform me that no relief for Steele is available in India, and have suggested endeavours be made to secure release of Fuber, who was Steele 5 s assistant until he joined up. He' is efficient and capable and his present address is Navy House* (? Port) (? Said), 3, If Fuber is willing to return to Bahrain, I would be glad if^arrangements could be made to secure Ibis release from the Admiralty.m again. 5 . as they may have dif'x iciulty in iinhing obtaining the x^elease of a suitable man, 1 would ^ grateful for any assistance the Government ox Inaxa can give. If it is not possible to obtain anyone for permanent appointment, it may be possible co secure a man for the (lU 2 ?ation ox the ^ar ♦—Charges to pay _s. d. RECEIVED Central Telegraph Office, E.C.I. 1 \ PC From m ^ 15 ) y St bFEKTE/sTAtUP OFFICE POST TELEGRAM Prefix. Time handed in. Office of Origin and Service Instructions. Words: 80 80 10.9 SHERWOOD 11 SECRETARY POLITICAL DEPT INDIA OFFICE LONDON y NO MILITARY OBLIGATIONS WRIT ING = PURSER ♦, For free repetition of doubtful words telephone “TELEGRAMS ENQUIRY ” or call, with this form at office of delivery. Other enquiries should be accompanied by this form and, if possible, the envelope.file copy ^asttedjbo Political Bepaptmftnt. - Cppy to Wac Rtnff. P 4 1 9 11 19 o .9 j 3861. (52 groups) g-gjl^.J?„g.g„S_0_P __ T E L 5 G K /i «_ Political Agent, Bahr-ain, to secretary of State for India. Bahrain. 14.00 hours, 2nd September, 1939., 17.00 hours, 2nd September, 1939, X Bahrain Government's Assistant Engineer. H»B, JUrber, on leave, address:- Private Hoad Sherwood, Nottingham, has telegraphed for orders. 2. His duties both in Government Power House and Oil gauging are of great importance, but. Bahrain Government request you will decide and inform him whether he should return or ,ioin military service. From Dated fieceiredP.Z. 2737/34 1934. Extract from Intelligence Report of the Political Agent, Bahrain, for the period 1st to 15th April, 1934. 5. MOVEMENTS OF BRITISH SUBJECTS 2. Local Officials. (i) Mr.H.A.F.Fraser-Nash arrived from India on the 7th April, to officiate as State Engineer to the Bahrain Government during the absence on leave of MrB.Steele. (ii) Mr.W.B.Steele, State Engineer to the Bahrain Government, proceeded on leave to the United Kingdom by th Overland Route on the 9th April, accompanied by Mrs.W.B.Steele and child.No • 343 of 19 32 British Residency and Co nsula te-Ge ne ral, Busliire, the 14th February 19 32. From The Hon*ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, To The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, Uew Delhi. Smployment of Mr. W.B.Steele, as State Engineer, Bahrain. Sir, In order to properly supervise and manage the running of the newly erected Electric Installation at Bahrai&amp;,the Govern ment of Bahrain, have expressed their desire to engage Mr. W.B.Steele who was employed by Messrs Callenders* Construction and Cable Company in the erection of the plant. Mr Steele has shown his capabilities to the complete satisfaction of His Excellency the Shaikh of Bahrain who is anxious that Mr. Steele should continue to run the plant and be engaged as State Engineer. Moreover the Insurance Company*s Premium is smaller if the plant is under competent European supervision. After careful consideration by the Political Agent and the Financial Adviser to the Bahrain Government, I have been requested to sanction the engagement of Mr. Steele. The general terms of the contract are similar to that of other employees in Bahrain State but of course considerably less and is for four years in first instance terminable by three months' notice on either side. - ENCLOSUftb IN 1 INDIA FOREIGN SECTd NY’tt Mr. Letter No | Dated *3 MAR, 1932 f - Received i 1 MAR. 193? ! '' PMr. Steele is English and married and is considered by me to be most suitable for this post of State Engineer. I am not aware, however, whether it is necessary to obtain the sanction for or to report an appointment of such nature. In the case of the employment of Europeans who are not Government Servants, in a n Indian State, sanction can be accorded by the Resident concerned vide paragraph 53 of Manual of Instructions to Officers of the Political Department, and, a fortiori, since Bahrain is an Independent Principality, sanction is not required, but in view of the special circumstances, prevailing at Bahrain, I have thought it desirable to bring the matter to the notice of tne Government of India. The appointment has, of course, no political signifi cance and is purely of a technical nature and Mr. Steele is a suitable person for it. I have, etc., Sd. for Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.. i1815 ! ^o. 0.838-8/^6. Tiie Deputy Secretery to the yeroinent of India in the Jterei^x irnd Political Departiaentt The do n * 61 e the Political Be aidant in the Persian Oul f. dated &amp;ew delhi» the /l ^ P^rch 1D32, iVTiployraent of Ur. W.B # 3teel&lt; State acgimert Bahrain. • •. • • In reply to your letter Ho. 343 of 1932, dated the 14th iebrusry 1932, I an directed to eay that although the iule* contained in paragraph 66 of the hicual of I net ruotlone to officers of the Political xwpertnBnt of the Ooeernnent of India do not apply to the Amb Statee in the Perelan 3 ulf, the Sovernnent of India consider it desirable that ell oases in which the Rulers of these states show a desire Mgage the service a of huropeane (which may be understood as Including Australians and Americans) should be reported to them before he nd. The same also applies to the enga^nwct of Iraqis* Syrians* Palsstinsane* Egyptians and notiwe of iorth Africa in positions of importance. 2. The Government of India aee no objection to the employ ment of dr . /• 3. Steele a a State ingineer* Bahrain. I hare the honour to be* sir* Your most obsdisci Berraut* Sd. yeVwWyliSe Doputy ijscrotary to the Government of Indie.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000133_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/3742</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000133</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/3742</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 30/28 'Persian Gulf, Bahrein: Electric Installation, Engagement of an Engineer; Affairs of Assistant Engineer and General Question of Recruitment of European Employees by Bahrain Government'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1931/1948</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-12-14T22:22:33</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (322 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the inside front cover with 1, and terminates at the last folio with 624; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains correspondence between British Government officials, representatives of British contracting and building firms (including Charles Kendall &amp; Partners Limited and British Iron &amp; Steel Corporation Limited) and the Adviser to the Ruler of Bahrain, Charles Dalrymple Belgrave.The correspondence discusses a number of issues including the hiring of a State Engineer for the Government of Bahrain, the delivery of building materials to Bahrain and general discussions concerning the protocol for the hiring of European employees by the Government of Bahrain.The file includes a divider, which gives a list of correspondence references contained in the file by year. This is placed at the back of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Adviser to the Government of Bahrain</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Bahrain</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Recruitment</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000133#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>