<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0002cb_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T22:27:21.299Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">m Tin-it GOVERNMENT OF IND gOHFiDENTlAK Departme EXPRESS LETTER (AIR [N.B.— Thin is an ORIGINAL menage gent hy AIR MAIL which provides a means of expeditiout than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It \$in .en4e o ',_ 4 . on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To sare txmt an . formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It it authenticmted by the .ngnature of responsible officer of the Department.] No. c/431. To Office of the Political Resident &gt; i n Persian Gulf, YYOTiarv Ca-inp Karachi- Dated the 6th July 1938» The Political Agent, Bahrain, Repeated His Majesty's Secretary of State for India, London. The Secretary to the Government of India, External Affairs Department, Simla, Subject : Purchase of fish traps at Jufair. K Reference India Office Express Letter No.P.Z, 4187/38, dated the 17th June 1938. Please take necessary action. Sd. T .C.Fowle. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. ATTESTED, for Secretary Resident in the Persian to the Political Gulf o {Signature) {Besignatim) S. 44. mfp— 985 S&amp;P—&lt;M-1597)—27 11-36—10,000.•V ' y * &gt; FROM DATE THE SEBIOR R H.M.S. !! 11th July, 1938. (C GULF, Bahrain. HO .490B. f JH 1 i r -.v r-n TO ..THE POLITICAL AGEHT, THE AGENCY, BAHRAIN'. FISH TRAPS AT JUFAIR. With reference to your 971-3/22 dated 2nd July, 1938. This line was fixed on 5th July alter consultation v/ith the Superintendent of the Land Department and the owners of the Fish Trap concerned. 2. Temporary stakes which will he replaced hy permanent marKs have been driven in to mark the line and have heen inspected hy the Superintendent of the Land Department who is satisfied that they are in the correct position. 3. A diagram is enclosed. tUPTAIN SENIOR NAVAL OFFICER, PERSIAN GULF. I* S %r No. 1103-3/22. Political Agency, Bahrain, the 23rd July 1938 To The Superintendent Land Department, Bahrain. The Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf Division, informs me that the line of demarcation was fixed and marked on the 6th July 1938 after consultation with you and the owners the fish traps concerned. 2. Would you please confirm that this line was accepted by you on behalf of the Bahrain Government and by the fish trap owners? L Political Agent, Balirain. 9-v y\ iJl LAND REGISTRATION DEPARTMENT /f No. /21-B/LD/1367• Dated,27^ J/Awwal, 13o7. 2. July, 1938, To H. B. M'S Political Agent, Bahrain. Memorandum: //./?• Reference your letter No.1103-3/22 dated the 23rd July 1938. I confirm that tne line of demarcation was fixed and marked by the Staff Officer and myself in the presence of the owners and that it v/as accepted by the owners as well as myself on behalf of the Government of Bahrain. Superintendent, Land Department. Y.Z.y\ L!1 ;Jh : LAND DEPARTMENT. J2 I O • ft? /21-B/1357. Dated, ///? Shwaal, 1357. December, 1938. To Memorandum: H. B, M'S Political A^ent, Bahrain. J Reference your letter No.453-3/22 dated the 23rd March, 1938. I enclose herewith in original letter from Mozah bint Mohammad bin Saeed in connection with the fish traps ^aqsuaA 1 and •Urn Rati 1 , for disposal. Adviser, Government of Bahrain. Y.Z./ 3nc» 1I Transl?.tion of letter dated 8oh Siiawai, 1557 (1,1^.38) from Mozah biiit liuhammad bin Saced to tiie Adviser, Bahrain Government, Bahrain. ter c amplimentc. I bc-g to brin£ to your notice that in connection with the fich traps 'Urn Rati' and 'Maqsusa', you pro mised mc last year to pay the balance of their value ana the money of last lease. This year, I request that you will Kindly pay me u.e value and the lease money as you are a rare that. I am a woman and in need of what is due -to mc on account of value and lease of the said fish traps. I beg you to help me in this matter and let me know the result. Usual iunding.•v\ 4' i - e J'O ^VRTMENT. Tapoo No.697 and 698/1357. No. ^7 of 1357. Dated, ^Thulqa t da,1357. fij Deceml:)er »^38. To, H. B. M'S Political Agent, Bahrain. Memorandum: J Reference your letter No.1930-3/22 dated the 10th December, 1938. I enclose herewith two receipts in 4wplicate signed by the owners of the two traps in question for the amounts of Rs.1333/5/3 and Rs.266/-/- forwarded with your letter under reference. Superintendent, Land Depavtmi ■y h Y.Z./Snc. 4. 1GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. Department. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAiL). [N.B.— This is an ORIGINAL message sent by AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to he treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To gave time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department.] Bahr ain 9th January Dated t , the Politioal A , r' - / % yonr Kxpre«# letter KO. C/431 AsUd U»* 6th July X5&gt;3a. Reference jg^r. Purohaaa of Kiah imps at JUffelr* 2« Tha aufij of Hu 1699-6»3 In r«apaet of cowpanaation for tha raeaalnli\g one third portion of Det Hatl and aquan flah tropa at Jufalr haa baan aant to tha Advlaar to tha Bahwaln lovem»«ttt f who tha p«y»ant» I ancloaa two reoalpta (In trlpllcAta) • 53d/- H. w#l^!htmaa Polltloal Agent, Bahrain* -.ttgafd. (M ; Aaaiatant Political Agent, Buhraln* [_UIIL ii [Signature) 8.144. MFP—985 S&amp;P—(M-1697)—27-11-36—10,000. [Designation)j.L_yi ij\&gt; LAND DEPARTME / ' 'AT ' v ' O /21/1357. - ^j/.y.Dated,'^/^ Thulhajja, 1357. January, 1939. To, H. B. M'S Political Agent, Bahrain. iM. 21// Memorandum: Reference correspondence ending with your letter NO. 1920-3/22 of the 10th December, 1938. 5*f I forward herewith a letter, in original, from Ataitullah bin Abdul Rehman bin Abdul Wahab al Khalifa for disposal. He claims Rs.300/- being rent plus ?.s.2/- Fish trap license fee for txie last two years, during which period he was asked notTranslation of a letter aatea 2uth D/^aaa 1357 from Atiyatulla Abaul Haii/aan al-Khalifa to K-S* 'uhaimaa Khali 1 Director of the Tapu Lepartment, Bahrain# After compliments, I have to inform you about the Hadhra Urn-Ratal (fish trap) for one year from the ena of the pearl fishing season 1I.&gt;56 to the ena of the pearl fishing season 1357 and upto three months of the (fish) catching season, we hav e sola it for the last year at Rs. 150/- ana also Rs. 2/- tax against Haahras Um-Ratal and broken Haonras. This is for your information.No. ^7 -3/22 Political Agency, Bahrain, 6th February 1939 1^ To The Adviser to the Bahrain Government, BAHRAIN lemorandum / 1 ■ Reference your memorandum No. 1130 dated the 29th January 1939. 2. I enclose herewith a copy of a translation of the letter from Ataltullah bin Abdul Rehman al Khalifa, which you sent me in original. This does not appear to coincide with the last paragraph of your memorandum. 3. The trap Umm ^atal actually belonged to Voza b-int Muhamad Saeed. I do not, therefore, understand how Atal tullah could have sold the trap as he claims or can have any claim to compensation. 4. Tn any event since the trap has now been bought outright it is regretted that further claims cannot be entertained. Political Agent, Bahrain.INDIA OFFICE, WHIT HALL j S.W.I. P.Z.782/39. 10th February, 1939. Dear Jarrett, Would you please refer to your letter or. 15th June 1938 No.M.0421/58/38 about the 'buying out of tv/o fishtraps which interfered v/ith service requirements at the naval pier at Jufair, Bahrein? o . As you will see from the enclosed copy of an -tr ■ express letter from the Political Agent 7 Bahrein this dated 9th January ) transaction has now been completed. S':eps with enclosure ) will be taken in due course to recover the expenditure from the Admiralty when the amount has been notified to us by the accounting Authorities in India for recovery. Yours sincerely? (Sgd.) J P. GIBSON C.0. Jarrett, I]sq. , _ Admiralty, S.W.I.Office of the Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, H,M.S.'Shoreham' at Bahrain. NO.490T* \ 1st July 1939. Sir, I have the honour to inform you that I have had under consideration the question of guards for the Jufair Naval Base, At present five Naturs are employed in the Base, but they have given notice that they wish to leave this employment. My intention is to enter new men under the same conditions for a month 1 s trial. 3. These ITaturs have given considerable trouble, and this method of guarding the Base does not seem to be entirely satisfactory. It appears possible that the guarding of the Base might be carried out by the local police. The actual requirements are (a) a guard on the main gate until about midnight and (b) one man to visit and guard^various parts of the Base continuously during the night. 4. If you consider it feasible, I should be most obliged if you would approach the Adviser to His Highness the Sheikh and obtain his viev/s in this matter. Amongst other details, I should wish to know, of course, what charges would be made for such service. / I have the honour to be, A Sir, . Your obedient servant, ^■rv( CAPTAIN SENIOR NAVAL OFFICER PERSIAN GULP. The Political Agent, The Agency, BAHRAIN.x //^ ' -3/22. Political Agency, Bahrain, the 6th July 1939. From The Political Agent, Bahrain. To Sir, The Advisor to the Bahrain Government, Bahrain. Subject:-Provision of police guard at Jufair Naval Base. ive the honour to forward herewith a copy of a letter No* 490T dated the 1st July 1939 from the Senior Naval Officer in the Persian Gulf and to request you to let me know whether you are prepared to agree to the police taking on the guarding of the naval base at night. If you agree to the provision of a guard, I should be grateful if you would furnish/^stirnate of the initial and Tb, recurring expenditure would involve. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant. for Political Agent, BahrainFrom To No. Bahrain, / Dated, July 9, 19 C. Dalrymple Belgrave, Esquire, C.B .E., Adviser to the Government of Bahrain, Bahrain, Persian Gulf. H. B, M 1 s Political Agent, Bahrain. '^1 i S ir, I have the honour to acknowledge your letter No. 1121-3/2S dated the 6th July, 1939, enclosing a letter from the Senior Naval Officer in the Persian Gulf, re garding the provision of a Police Guard at Jufair, From your letter I understand that the guard would only be required at night. This would be difficult to arrange and I do not think it would be satisfactory. I would suggest a permanent guard consisting of 1 N.C.O. and four Policemen to be changed every month as is done in the case of all outposts including the Palace Guard when His Highness is in residence. 3- The guard would need a room in which to sleep, a cookhouse and water. They draw rations monthly and make their own messing arrangements. tf&gt; The rate of pay, which is the same as paid by the Bahrain Petroleum Company, is as follows:- IN.0.0. @ R3 42/- per month 4 Policemen @ Rs 37/- per month 42/- 148/- Rfl.190/- This amount includes all allowances, rations etc etc.No. 1160-3/22. Political Agency, Bahrain, tho 11th July 1939. From The Political Agent, Bahrain. To The Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, H.M.S. t, Shoreham ,, at Bahrain. Subject:-Police Guard at Jufair. Sir, -hi- SM. i I have the honour to refer to your letter No. 490T dated the lat July 1939 on the subject cited above and to enclose a copy of letter No. 1076/33 dated the 9th July 1939 from the Adviser to the Bahrain Government, under whose orders a police guard for Jufair would function. 2. I would suggest that before any decision is taken, the matter be discussed between the Adviser, you and myself. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant. d Political Agent, Bahrain. Hiffice of the Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, H.M.S.'Shoreham' at Muscat, 5th July 1939. I have .the honour to aclmowledge the receipt of your letter No.1150-3/22 dated 11th July, 1939, and to thank you for making enquiries in regard to a police guard for Jufair. The suggestions made by the Adviser to His Highness appear suitable, but before proceeding with this matter I propose to discuss it with the Commander-in-Chief, East Indies Station. I intend,therefore, to leave the question in abeyance until 'Shoreham' returns to Bahrain in September. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your obedient servant. i M CAPTAIN SENIOR NAVAL OPPICER PERSIAN GULP. 1 The Political Agent, BAHRAIN. a, H.M.S»Deptford» CONFIDENTIAL. From the Commanding Dateed 28th: July 1939, To the Clerk-in-charge, B RETURN STORES* ************* The follo^ring has been received from the Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf:- 11 Oiler War Afridi will arrive Sitrah approximately 9th;August. Return stores are to be embarked without delay complied with. These instructions are to be S /d. C.A.E.Stanfield. COMMANDER-IN-COMMAND . No. Tos- H .M. Naval Base, Bahrein Dated the 6th:Aug 1939. The Political Agent, Bahrein. The Director of Customs, Bahrein, The Quarantine Medical Officer, Bahrein. Forwarded for information. Clerk-in-charge, Naval Base, Bahrein^Officer No.490. Persian ' 24th September 1939» I au. i The attached copy of orders for Naturs which I have issued to the Clerk-in-Charge at the Base is forwarded for your information* I should be grateful if you would be so good as to arrange for somebody occasionally to inspect the Naturs and the Base generally when H.M,Ships sre not in harbour. The copy of orders in the Base bears the translation into Urdu on the left hand side of the page. The Political Agent, BAHRAIN. «The Jerildar and Hature are to be under the orders of the Clerk-In- Charge. The Jenldar la to be responsible for the cleanliness of the Naturs uartera# In the absence of H # M»Ships 9 the Political uXgent or hie representative will make periodical inspection visits to the Base* OreNatur is to be on duty continuously at the Gate and one between the shore end of the Pier and the Hoclcey Ground# The Jenidar is to ge round the Base at irregular times during the night# nature on duty are to be airoed with a rifle and five rounds of nmnunition and are to carry whistles. It is the duty of all ITatura to prevent (a) unauthorised persons from entering the Base. (b) Thefts of Qovemrient Stores. (c) Attempts at sabotage. (d) Removal of liauor. lien H.l!.Ships are present, the Hetur on duty at the shore end of the pier is to switch off the pier lighting when all beats have left. Any suspicious person found in the Base is to be called upon to halt and is to be questioned. Fireanns are to be used only in self defence or to prevent an act of sabotage. If asGistance is required Haturs are to blew their whistles to sinnon the remainder of the Guard. If further assistance is required, the Clerk-in- Charge is to telephone the Political Agent and State Police. In addition to Kis Excellency The oheikh and [is family, the following are to be allowed to enter the Dase:- (!)••—2— ORDe^fi ^ IIA^ (1) Bahrain CTOVernment and British Officiiilo ond mesnen^ars sent with their authority, (ii) Officers and lien of H .M .^oroes^ (iii) Katives using the right of way to the Hosaue* (iv) natives employed at the Base, (v) Katives attending fiah traps holding a pass signed by the Adviser to Government# (vi) Trade&amp;nen whose entry has been authorised by the Clerk-in-Charge. : In case of doubt the Hatur is to blow his whistle for assistance; the Clerk in Charge is to decide whether to pemit entry or not. All cars are to be stopped to confirm th^.t their occupants are pemit ted to enter the Base* Taxis containing natives leaving the Base are to be examined to sec that r*o liquor or Government Property is being improperly removed^ 24th aeptenber 1939 #its Confidential D*0» No. C/676 Dated th« 26th September 1939 I enclose herewith s copy of letter No» 490 dated the 24th September 1939 from Graham f the Senior Naval Officer. Could It be arranged for Byard and Shaikh Thallfah to xrake occaaional visits of Inspection to JVifalr and to send in a brief note to me after doing so ? Perhaps you yourself can occasionally find time to go down too» Hallows and I will also carry out occasional Inspections. Yours sincerely, Dalrymple Belgrave, Esquire, C .B .S. 9 Adviser to the Bahrain Government! Bahrain. A* P. A. to note.■ PS#' i2218-3/22• Political Agency, Bahrain, the 18th December 192 From The Political Agent, Bahra in. To The Senior Naval Officer Persian Gulf Division, H.M.3, 'Shoreham' Subject:-Fish Traps at Jufair- Umra Rati and Maqusa. Sir -f % // have the honour to refer to your letter No 490.B dated the 19th January 1938 and connected correspondence on the subject cited above, and to enclose herewith Title Deeds Nos« 305/68 and 306/6 c for the two fish traps which have now been registered in the name of His Majesty^ Government. I have the honour to be Sir Your most obedient servant for Political Agent, Bahrainr GOVERNMENT OF BAHRAtK CAWP OEPARTM E.HT. f ^ ) .697/57. etc / 7 J No. ' ' ' Dated, Safar, 1369 /p/f~ March, 1940 To H. B. M's Political Agent, Bahrain. Memorandum: .Hi T .fith reference to my letter No. 1093 dated 2nd Thulqaaa, 1358 (14th December, 1939) sending 2 title deeds of fish traps at Jufair, purchased by the British Government. I have not been able to trace the acknowledgement of the deeds and should be grateful if you would confirm their receipt or quote the letter acknowledging them.No•608-3 /22 Political Agencyi Bahrain# 18th March, 1940• To The Adviser to the Bahrain Govemuent, A U ^ . Memorandum . Please refer to your Memorandum No.179 dated the 17th »%«rch| 1940 1 2» The Title Deeds (Nos:306/68 and 306 /68) for two fish traps at Jir'air sent with youi* memorandura No. 1093 dated the 14th December, 1939, have been received. It is regretted that an acknowledgement was not sent to you at the time. for Political Agent, Bahrain^ A..iT Tel From To No. Dated Reed I b I i ^ • c • Political, Sharjah Political, Bahrain. 359 -v . 17.4.43 5/2. IS.4.43 Rice and wheat to value of Rupees 5171 Annas 5 were purchased in January by the r- Superintendent of Dubai Customs for Resident Naval Officer Khor Kuwai from whom I have just heard that he has not yet received the fund to pay this bill. 2. Can you arrange to expedite. POLITICAL % \ \ 11 - . INo# S/(^ -3/22• Political Agentfy Bahrain, The ^p!/&lt; April 1943 To The Naval Officer-in-Charge, Jufair Memorandum Ti- I encloses copy of a telegram lTo.359, dated the 17th April 1943, which I have received from the Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Sharjah, and would be grateful for such assistance as you can give in having the payment of the bill referred to expedited. • — for^olrtlcal Agent,Bahrain.H .M.S. OLD GOOoE, at Basra, 4th September, 1946. In accordance vfith instructions received fran the Comnianding Officer, H.I .S. JUFAIK, Motor vehicles R«N»30 aad R.N.33, were, on 30th August 194G sold to Mohamed bin Ab dulla of Manama, Bahrain. The sum of Rs900 was received from this person in respect of the purchase of the vehicles. Yours faithfully. H.B.ll. Political Agent, Bahrain Island. ' C j ^ - Supplj r Officer. ft* • i I mriM iINDIA OFFICE, Department. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). (N.B.—This is an original message, sent by air mail to save telegraphic expense, but intended to be treated on receipt with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. It has been drafted as if it were so despatched.) From the Secretary of State for India. To The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Repeated to the Government of India, External Affairs Department and the Political Agent, Dated 17th June, 1938. Bahrein. No. P. Z-i+l 87/38. V Al ■A r / r Please refer to your Express letter No. C/26k of the 21st April regarding the purchase of fish traps at Jufair. Copy is enclosed of the marginally noted correspondence7 P.Z.14-187/1938. Military Branchy ADMIRALTY, S.W .I. l4.0i+21/58/38 1 5th June, 1938. Dear Gibson, I write in reply to your letter to Seal, No. P.Z.2960/38 of the 5th May. We should be glad if you would arrange for the purchase of the remaining one third portions of the two fish traps mentioned in Weightman's letter of the 23rd March. % I am sending a copy of this letter to Brenan. Yours sincerely, (Sd. ) G. G. Jarrett. J. P. Oibson Kaq.., India Office, S. W.1.934-3/22 i. Political Agency, Bahrain, the 27th June 1938 The Acting Adviaer to the Bahrain Government, Bahrain* t Memorandua* With reference to the Senior Naval Officer's letter No« 490 B dated the 8th June 1938, copy of which was sent to you under my printed letter No# 869-3/22 of the 16th June, I shall be grateful if you would make the arrangements suggested in paragraph 2, and inform me so that I can tell the Senior Naval Officer# I suggest that July 6th might be a suitable day# for Political Agent, Bahrain. Lwmmmmmm y\ —uui LAND REGISTRATION DEPARTMENT. To No. 3?? /21-3/U)/1357. Date&lt;i ,-2 ^f .B/Thani, 1357. 4?$% Ju ne j 1938. H, B. M'S Political Agent, Bahrain. )■/ Sir, / v u Reference your letters No.869-3/22 and 934-^/12 dated the 16th and 27th June, 1938, respectively, addressed to the Acting Adviser. I have arranged with the owners of the fish traps to attend the demarcation of the proposed line on the 6th July, 1938. This better be done at low tide which will be between 8 and 10 a.m. on tnat day. I may please be informed if this time is convenient to the Senior Naval Officer. y I enclose herewith two cpoies of the statement of the owners which determines their jSastern boundary as up to the proposed demarcation line. A I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant. Superin oenuent, Land Department. Y.Z./Snc. 2./t3 Translation. We, Sayid Ahmad Sayid Alawi in my capacity as President oi' Ja'fariyah Wa^r Department which owns a fish-trap named Raqiqah which is a waql,and Haji Husain bin Ali hin Haji Husain resident of Makharqah quarter in Manamah, owiier of two fish-traps named Jiraiwah and Al Musambar both situated at Satwat al Jufair to the west of the pier of the British Naval Base, do hereby declare that we have no objection to the Senior Naval Officer at Bahrain to fix up boundaries separating the said pier and the iish-traps in 4uestion whethe by fixing wood or erecting pillars- .»e also uave no right to claim any compensation for the fixation of this distinguishing mark. Dated: 12tii Salar 1357s 13th April Sd. Sayid Ahmad bin Sayid Alawi President of Waqf Department. Thumb impression of:- Haji Husain bin Ali bin Haji Husain. Witnessed by:- Sayid Sai T d bin Sayid Knalaf. Muhsin al Tajir.-&gt;• No. 971-3/22. ■i /&gt; Political Agency, Bahrain, the 2nd July 19o8. The Political Agent, Bahrain. The Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf Division, H.M .S. Shoreham, Jufair. Pish Traq a at JufSxir&gt; Sir, fV 1 With reference to your letter No. 490 -B dated the 8th June 193S, I have the honour to inform you that arraivv—.lents have been made for the ovmers of/flah traps to attend the demarcatioi of the proposed line on the 5th July 1938. The Superintendent of the Lend Department proposes that this should oe done at low tide which will be between 8-00 and 10-00 A .M. on that dp.te. Would you please inform me if the time will be convenient to yo. 1 2, l enclose a copy of the statementj together n'ith its translation, of the owner which determines their eastern boundary as up to the proposed line of demarcation. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant, d- for Political Agent, Bahrain.I ■ * i r- Telephone message . From S.N.0., P.G., H. T '.S. Shoreham. To Political Agent, Bahrain. Dated 8th July 1938. (T.0.0. 1030) Request arrangement Ka&amp;E ma^be made for Staff Officer Cperati^ons to meet the Superintendent Land Department at 0745 Bahrain time tomorrow Saturday at the Jufair pier. Cn conclusion of this meeting a written report will be forwarded x on the §rea marked out the westward of t e pier. Ay tfa. IU ] e i V-ly\ Lit sjbl LAND REGISTRATION DEPARTMENT. No. -2 /21-B/LD/1357. Dated,^^/^. R/Awwal, 1357. 2 &amp; ^ May ' 1938 - u To, H. B. M•S Political Agent, Bahrain. \ Memorandum: \&gt; Reference to para 3 of your letter No .453-3/22 of 23rd March, 1938. The owners of the fish trap to the west of the Naval Pier at Jufair have now agreed to the proposed line of demarcation to consist of either wooden stakes or stone pillars erected at intervals of fifty feet or more. Adviser, Government of Bahrain. t776/3/22 The Political Agent, Bahrain, Presents his complimenU to : — The Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf Division, Shoreham, Bahrain. and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document (s) / w The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf. D&amp;ted 29th May 1938. Reference to previous correipondence: Agency endorsement No. 453-3/22 dated the 26th ^)ftcWl938. Description of Enclosure. ^ ^ . Name and Date. Subject. Copy of memorandum No. 244/2 rl -B/ LD/1357 dated the 26th May 1938 from Adviser to the Bahrain Government, Bahra in• Jufair Fish Traps.Ho.490 B. H.M.S. 'SHOREHAM', at Khor Kuv/ai. ^ne, 1938. NO vi ivvi W 0 V Sir, Fish Traps at Julair . . With reference to the copy of Memorandum Ho.244/21-B/LD/1357 dated 26th May, 1938, from the Adviser to the Bahrain .Government forwarded under cover of your Ho.775/3/22 dated 29th May, 1938, I have the honour to inform you that H .M.S.'Shoreham', will he at Bahrain from 4th July for about one week when this matter could he settled. 2. It is requested that arrangements may he made for the Superintendent of the Land Department and the owners of fish traps concerned to he present at the Haval Base at a convenient time during that week to decide on the line of demarcation between the traps and the Haval pier. 3. With reference to paragraph 4 of the Adviser's 1120/21-B dated 2nd March, 1938, information is requested as to whether the houndaries of these traps have heen fixed. Mr. H.Weightman. Political Agent, BAHRAIH. I have the honour to he, Sir, Your obedient servant, CAPTAIH. SEHIOR HAVAL OFFICER, PERSIAH GULF.869-3/22 The Political Agcut, Bahrain, Presents hig compliments to ; — The Acting Adviser to the Bahrain Government, Bahr -ain. and ba« the honour to send him a copy of the nndermentioned document («) with the request that he will supplythe information as soon as possible. The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf. D&amp;ted 16th June 1938. Reference to previous corrcipondence: Description of Enclosure. Name and Date Subject, Copy of letter No. 490 B. dated the 8th June 1938 from Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf Division, H.M.S. 'Shoreham' 1 . Fish Traps at Jufair</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0002cb_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1108</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0002cb</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1108</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 3/22 II Naval Station at Bahrain'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1938/1946</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-10-14T11:35:41</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (67 folios)</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Correspondence discusses matters relating to the Naval Base at Jufair, Bahrain, in the context of the redeployment of the naval stations at Henjam and Basidu on the Persian side of the Gulf.The topics include:Lists of persons employed at Jufair naval base.Arrangements for demarcating fish traps due to relocation of naval pier.Plan showing position of stake relative to Jufair Pier Light (folio 16A).Arrangements for entry into the naval base at Jufair including the 'naturs' system of night watchmen.Orders for Naturs at Jufair Naval Base.Correspondents include:; Charles Dalrymple Belgrave, Adviser, Bahrain Government; Superintendent, Land Registration Department, Bahrain Government; Clerk-in-charge, Naval Base, Bahrain; Atiytulla Abdulrahman al-Khalifa; George Ashmead Cole, Political Agent, Bahrain.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Royal Navy, HMS Jufair, Naval Base</namePart></name></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0002cb#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>