<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000419.0x0001a5_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-05-23T12:08:04.897Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">(Similar letter sent to '5 ^ ^- •) &amp;ZJ In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote No. W. 9 and address— The Under-Secretary of State, &lt;r &amp; Foreign Office, London. &lt; 3 O' THE (Jrider-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Under-Secretary of State for India, and, by direction of the Secretary of. State, transmits herewith cop ^ of the under-mentioned papers. Foreign 0jjice, 191S. Ueferenoe to previous correspondence : Letter to from Foreign &lt; )ffice : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject 1 o Xcruk d) 6 / Vvo. ’XOb ^ (^TiiO'U 201 S' 25%FOH 'IOH OFPICa, 23rd, 191 / My Lord, Monoisur caubon eallot! on tae this Jiftirnoon and opofco to kms • .1 oat tiiif? situation Milch soouod lllcoiy to to creatad in the Lanedi&amp;ta future by General dlsnby’s succebB In Palestine. The Turlcieh armies In that oountry nad apparently been now destroyed, and there aeameei every probability that Qoaeral -dlenby would fOnetrate into uyria, nyria, as Monsieur Ca ibon rsiiiinded me, was, by the dykoa-Flcet Agreament, within the Frmcti sphere ol irillueace, and it was extremely important from the Frmch point of view that this fact should not be lost ai^it of in any arrangements that donorai AXlenby t a» l»»Chief t ?ii ? ht itftfrf for tiie administration of toe country he waa presumably about to occupy, if* had a conversation of considerable len^rbh, in which u&gt;ir Mturk ^ykes, the joint author of %m .&gt;ykes- Ficot Agreement, took a p^rt, Kinfilly t 1 drafted for Monsieur Uambon 9 * guidmice the following stote^iant Ox policy, which seemed to me t* be required by the letter am; spirit of the Agre^iient: policy with regard to ^yrias ns&amp;Jiely that, if it should fall into toe sphere of interest of any ' uropean i ower. that |ils Sxeeilency, the IU b nt Honourabl*, The ^arl of Derby K.a # d.C.y.Othat lower should ha Prance. They also think that this policy should bo raade pariactly clear both in Frcaice and elsewhere. The exact course which should be followed by the two Governraents in case General Allenby takes hie forces late wyria should be Inraediately diecupsed in Parle or Lendut. But it is understood that in any event, wherever officers are required to cairry out civilian duties, these officers should \unless toe Prench Goverivisat express an opinion to the contrary) be French and not ntsllsh; without pre judice of course to the supreiae authority of the ootitDander- in-Chief wiiiie the country is in niilitary occupation. Monsieur Caabon, I gathered, regarded this stetsmsnt as accurate and adequate. I am with great truth and respect, My Lord, Your Lordship 1 8 a*«t ofcftdiant bumblo Morvrjat, ,Jgs [This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government, and should be returned to the Foreign Office if not required for official use.] * r&gt; o L.* $ O' O j Cypher helegram to oir R. Wingate (R'lmleh) Foreign OXrice. June 18th 1918! Mo. 780. • h\ 3,5 pxrw Qhestien in last sentence of your telegram will he considered by Eastern Committee to-morrow... Meanwhile you should impress upon King's agent that Jemal’s speech was delivered for purpose of causing disunion among Allies and published in Mustakbil the policy of which paper has been consistently French Annexationist in spite of repeated warnings of French Government*D e cyph er» Si r ic. vVi ngut e, (A1 exandrl a). June lotm 1918, D c 2*0.p.m, Ro 5,SOopano No *948* June 16th. 1918. Urgent King o± the Hedjaz who has apnurent'ly. only-pu seen in newspaper Mostakhil number 101 report or speech delivered by Jemal Pasha several days beioro tall oi Jerusalem, has sent rather a violent telegram to his agent here instructing him to make enquiries about alleged Anglo-French agreement and its scope. You will recollect that King was never officially informed of Sykes-Picbt agreement, .feent has asked me urgently to suggest a suitable reply which he can send to King’s telegram I have advised agent to say that Bolsheviks found in Petrograd Foreign Office record of old con versations and provisional understanding (not formal treaty) between Britain France and Russia early in the war to prevent difficulties between Powers in prosecuting the war with Turkey. Jemal either from ignorance or malice has distorted its original purpose.has omitted its stipulations regarding consent of native populations and safeguarding their interests, and has ignored fact that subsequent outbreak and success of Arab revolt and withdrawal of Russia had for long time past, created wholly different situation. Can I add that we regard agreement as dead for all practical purposes*[This Document is the Property of His B ritannic Majesty’s Government, and shp be returned to the Foreign Office if not required for official use.]Your letter r of January 5th regarding the French claims for specific co-operation in Palestine. The ''Agreement of December 1916' refers to the Conference held at Downing Street on December 27th, when it was accepted'that Picot was to look after French interests, as such, in Palestine and act as the channel for the G.O.C.'s communications with the blue area and area 'A'. Nothing more than this was decided on, and Sykes, whom I have consulted, regards the v/hole business as a 'try on' on the part of Picot.H- £ This Document is the Property of His fintannic idljesty’s GovernmeKt, and should b e ret urned to the Foreign Office when done with unless required tor official use.] ^rv Deoypher. D. R. No. 1556 RIUNCE . I’.iXljIT- ilY . Lord Bertie (P8,ri8). Becerloer 30th. L . OV • a 111 . 6.10 Polxlo Becoinber 50th, 1917. j Your telegra r n No. 3101 of Deconhor Both. French Government fully recognise necessity in present circumstances and in view of uncertainty of situation in Palestine of maintaining exclusively military administration in that region under supreme authority of General Alleiiby who is the responsih-Le head of the forces operating against Turkish f.rmy. They consider however that without modifying principle of that military organization it mignt do possible to evolve a scheme to give effect to agreements of Do ember 1916. They arc convinced that His Majesty* s Government who in nutumn 01 19-l 6 to ox initiative in inviting them to participate in organization of territories which might do occupied in Palestine will willingly seek moans to make that participation stand out cleanyp31AI- rihis Docnmeat is the Property o! His Britannic Majes^s Government, and shonld be returned to the Foreign Office when done with unless required fo r official use.] 1 j |TI ^ Cypher telegram %o Sord Bertie (Parle) Foreign .Ofifiee, Beeemher 20th, 1917. IQ.SQ.p.n. Nc. 3101. jucA Ur ^ Yeur telegram Nc. 1482 (ej Decenher t 15th. Adrninie traticn cf Palestine}. You should assure French Gcvernraent that His Majesty’s Government have every intention tc ahj.de hy terms cf agreement, hut that it would chvicuely he im possible tc establish a mixed administration cf tho nature contemplated sc long as the area in question continue*: tc be the scene of active military operation Repeated tc Cairo Nc. 1229,la any further ooiumuaiea- tkn on Hus subject, please quo*e No. w 2 / 1/53 /1917 and atkkess — The Under-Secretary of State Poreujn OTice, London. (&amp; The Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the t'p J^~cr Q and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith, cop pafer 7 of the under-mentioned Fnreign (tffice, M Reference to previous correspondence Letter to* from fcTdS w., 4 Aa - f / &lt;Ui | Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. cbcKjeCtf*** „ S^.CfhwfJejtj, (Similar lettei sent to iIZxfcfrcJc ^ 3 ]}x^C Itf ^ fyu'^vLysoylsJ J Anglo-Fkench Russian Agreement. 25 and 28. Mr. RICHARD LAMBERT asked (1) whether, as agreed in the Anglo- French - Russian Agreement of 2Jst February, 1917, France is to receive at the close of the War from the Turkish Dominions in Asia the seaboard of Syria, the Adana vilayet, and part of Lesser Armenia: whether it is still the intention of the Allies, and confirmed by the Allied War Conference, to fight on till this is obtained : (2) whether the Memorandum of Agreement, recently published in the Press, dated 21st February, 1917, between Russia, France, and England concerning the future of Asiatic Turkey is still binding on the Allies; whether by this arrange ment Russia is to receive the Erzerum, Trebizond, Bitlis, and Van vilayets, and Kurdistan down to the Persian frontier; and whether the objects in this agreement are the war aims of the Allies 1 Lord R. CECIL: No agreement of the nature mentioned was come to in the early part of this year. Such understandings with respect to Asia Minor as were come to between the Powers named did not involve annexations.|r fixate. My dear Shuckdurgh:- I send you, herev/ith, a Note from the French Ambassador, and a draft v/hich we have prepared thereon, relative to the proposed modification of • Article 10 of the Sykes-Picot Agreement. would you he so good as to inform me whether the India Office concur in the terms of this draft?accompanying copy of a note which has been addressed to Monsieur Gambon in the sense suggested in your&amp;c., &amp;c., &amp;c. copy.; Immediate. POREIOK OFFICE, Octo'ber 30th, 1917. 4 3 31 -W- Your Excellency:- In the course of the recent discussions between representatives of the French and British Governments on the status of the Kingdom of the Hedjaz, it has appeared that Clause 10 of the Agreement respecting Arabia, enclosed in Your Excellency’s Note of Fay 9th, 1916, might be open to the interpretation that a naval base could be established by a foreign Power on the mainland of Arabia. Such an interpretation would be of course entirely contrary to the intentions of the two Govern ments, and in order to make the position quite definite I have the honour to suggest that instead of the present wording 'ou construise une base navale dans les lies sur la cdte est de la mer Rouge' the following phrase should be adopted 'ou installe une base navale ni sur la cOte His est ni dans les lies de la mer Rouge'. I should be grateful if Your Excellency would let me know as soon as possible whether the Government of the Republic agree to this modification. I have the honour to be, with the highest consideration. Your Excellency’s most obedient, humble Servant, Excellency Monsieur Gambon, AvVlu,In any farther oommumu*- tion on this subject, pleoee quote No. /SSDlJ /1917 and addrose— / The Under-Secretary of State Foreign Office, London. !*■ P T' ■ -j v u K % The Undersecretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents UxsJtj q his compliments to the Secretary ^ ' falT and, by direction of the Secretar\ of State, transmits herewith cof y of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, . wn- Reference to previous correspondence f setter S' Foreign Of ice : from Description of Enclosure.In any further oonunumea- fon on this subject, please quote No. W /1917 I *hlreas — The Under-Secretary of State Fnrekin O'Tice, I^ond on. The Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the crftfc'Pft r a^( Q-yJ?. ^ ^asUS &lt; lf' t ^^ / and, by direction of ifte Secretary of the under-mrntioned r ' d / of State, transmits herewith cop paper Fn reig n (Office , . . ‘90■ Reference to previous correspondence Letter U ! Foreign Office: from Description of Enclosure. Name anti Date. Subject crw dc ED 23 CAL ' fSimilar letter sent to Scilf^c*. &gt; C 14 ]1. copy- (159558) Secret. MEMOMNDUM OH THl'I ASIA-MINOR AGRma'ITO . By Sir Mark Sykes . I believe that the time has now come when, in the interests of both Great Britain and France, discussion and inter-change of views would be desirable in regard to the Asia-Minor Agreement. I will assume that the map as regards Great Britain and France represents the spheres of economic and political interest which the two powers are ready to accord to each other. I do not suggest that we should in any way depart from the agreed geographical boundaries, out what I regard as of great importance is that the two powers should dis cuss frankly and freely the attitude they intend to adopt towards the populations inhabiting those regions. When the agreement was originally drawn up I think it was then in consonance with the spirit of the tine that certain concessions were made to the idea of nationality and autonomy, but an avenue was left open to annexation. The idea of annexation really must be dismissed, it is ' contrary to the spirit of the time, and if at any moment the Russian extremists got hold of a copy they could make | much capital against the whole entente; this is especially j | so with the Italian claim which runs counter to nationality, geography and common sense, and is merely Baron iuonnino’s concession to a chauvinist group who only think in bald terms of grab.I. In the first place v/e should settle the status of Hejaz and Arabia between ourselves and the French. : e recognise Hejaz as a sovereign independent state, while France herself dissociates from the rest of Arabia and leaves to us, as custodian in her eyes, the development and consolidation of the Arab race. IX. Secondly we ought to come to an agreement with the French as to our future attitude in regard to the areas A and B, and the blue and red areas. If we both agree not to annex but to administer the country in consonance with the ascertained wishes of the people and to include the blue and red areas in the areas A and B we shall be on much firmer ground at a Conference. If the French would boldly cane out with a recognition of Annenian nationality in the North and Arab nationality in Byria as a whole they would sacrifice nothing and gain much. III. With regard to Palestine we have to consider two important points:- ' l (i) Zionism and the dislike of the Jews to any form of Internationalisation and condominium. (ii) The French sentimental regard for Palestine. The only solution that I can see would be (i) To get Great Britain appointed trustee of the Powers for tlie adminisoration of Palestine o (ii) To grant France some position as patron or protector of ttie various Catholic institutions outside the Holy places. (iii) Jerusalem and Bethlehem put under an inter national hoard. (iv) Haifa to he an Arab port for Area B. I am well aware that this will he very ohjectionahle to the French, hut they really must he induced to settle matters up in their own interests. IV. As regards Syria the French should he prepared to accept the idea of autonomous States, one in the Lebanon andand one in the rest of Syria under French patronage, but under a national flag. Z-j,.(%}) V. If the French will not agree to such a joint policy then we should tell them - (i) That this is the policy we intend to adopt ourselves in Mesopotamia. (ii) That we will abide by our agreement, but it is up to them to make good - that is to say that if they cannot make a military effort compatiblB with their policy they should modify their policy. (iii) That we cannot prevent the Zionists, Amenians, and Arabs being hostile to the idea of annexation and that if a European Conference is held the French cannot expect us to support them in a policy which we do not pursue our selves. (iv) That we know that the Armenians and Jews will begin a vigorous agitation in America which will be supported by the Arabs. VI. -As regards Italy, if France and Great Britain agree to abandon the idea of annexation and to take up the idea of nationality, Italy must reduce her claim to a purely economic one and be content with an economic sphere in the area she has marked, which reduces that matter to an Italian-Turkish treaty. VII. I know that the bear's skin argument will be again raised, however, in spite of this I hold very strongly that we have certain big Entente War assets and Conference assets in the Arabs, Zionists and Armenians, that it is certainly our duty to get these people righted, and that it will be in our interest to get them righted on lines compatible with our economic and political interests. The Labour Conferences resolutions are a very good formula if they are put to the proper purpose, and what we may not be able to get by force of aims we may well get the substance of by negotiation if the national elements are on our side at the Conference. •anci 15-e ather hand if we have agreements of an ,at iw'drialist tendency, v;hich the nationalities dis- will he most probable that the Turk and the jerr ji will score heavily, keep suzerainty and the Baghdad- - rrn , and land us (Great Britain) in a bad peace position in the/Middle East, lacking both control and future security. The French will be nowhere as a people and as Government will be involved in a German-Turkish Financial web, and used as a constant irritant to'us in Egypt. I want to see a permanent Anglo-French Entente allied to the Jews, Arabs and Armenians which will render pan-islamism innocuous and protect India and Africa from ' the Tureo-Gexman combine, v/hich I believe may well survive the Hohenzollerns. (}, b. j© - . /« This Document is the Property o! His Britannic Majesty’s Government, and should be returned to the Foreign Office when done with unless required tor official use.] T n “7 * ! \ 'v I ~7 i 5 iLl POLITICM j Do cypher. Sir P. V. T ingato (Ramloh) Auf^ust 8th. 1917. D. l#4o p,rru R. 8 p.m« NO* 833* (R). August 8th* 3^17. A telegrem of which following is the gist was received frjxn its Paris corx^p&lt;«ad«crtr hy 'El attach jj-vd^^&gt;uhlishBd in that paper on August 4th. Begins* Paris papers have discussed passages in Lionsieur Ribot’s and Mr. Balfour’s speeches in reply to accur^^ which Dr u kichaelis hryugh + &gt; fxoiv&gt;» +y ' H+ ' afte ' 1 ^agr^moxxt, vOaich France made with imperial Government of Russia in February last, she would not be satisfied with return of Alsace Lorraine, but wanted to occupy Syria. l»i. Kibot denied accuaat.ion gainst prttaca vexing occupation of Syria and he brou^it in support of his evidence decision oi House of Deputies. M. Eibot finally stated that France oniy wishes to get back Alsace Lorraine to be indemnified for loss which she has undergone. He denied any Buggestion of occupation of Syria or any other country. The French papers declared thamaeivee In lull with Mens. BttoVs ^»eecn ; the French .n W had not punllsn.d tnr decision regarding Syria “»»• B,d of B - p-onsleur Derrenc-e roproacned denser here and raMteetlen of Buch a telegrac «,lcn he alleged had had an unfortunat^-axiact on pro-French__ Byrians/ Syrians here. It was pointed out by censor that as telegram emanated i'rom Paris it had naturally been presumed that French Censor had passed it as desirable for publication ■. I understand that Monsieur Ribot in a telegram to French agency in Cairo has denied having made any mention of Syria in his speech and Mens. Defranco is publishing a dementi in this sense. It appears therefore that fault lies with censor in Paris but I think it desirable to inform you in case subject is broached in London,Note on the ^n^).o • Ftmtico • Russian ^^reerfif nt about the hear hast. This Agfeefeent wa» dr ifted early in 1916. It favoured one of Uie three parties • France - as against the other two, not only in the quantity and quality of territory reserved to occupation or exclusive influence, nnd the concession of the best harbour sites in wyria, but also because France alone had not yet established rights by actual occupation to any part of her prospective allot* -went. and did not undertake to proceed within a specified period to establi^i such rights. Nevertheless the A/greement was ratified for, preaumbly, sufficient reasons of general policy which fnade it worth our while at tiiat time to so favour France, if these reasons exist at the present moment, find are equally cogent under the changed conditions of 1917, 1 have nothing more to eay, except to noint out (1) that the agreement left a large part of the &lt;urab area - the Peninsula of /Arabia Proper - unallotted, and that in thia we both had then, and hate atrenf^thened since, paramount intereata; and (2) that one party, hussia, has tiLteh apparently renounced her claim to a lor^e part of her allotment, which, therefore, haa become once more unsettled; and that much of this part is so remote and difficult to administer that neither of the other parties is likely to have ootn will and power to take up ite reversion. It will accordingly not improbably remain part of an Ottoman r.mpire, and give sufficient bulk and suhstanee to the latter to enable it to continue a lower with a Caliphate and mnmrwwrr a disturbing influence on Ui© lands allotted to i* ranee ourselves, lf t however, those reasonip sug eated above, are no lon^r eauiUy cogsnt, 1 would point out that inch water iuis run under tue brides thia paat year and a half, during all of which period, be itrir* toeradj the ^kM ranained in au8pena&lt;» of fiction, it not hating uo«n pooaiblo^ except perhaps in ooopot^da, for my of tho p Ttieo to realise their olaime* Net only has Hueaia ^ Ss dieturbed the ^reeroent by pr^f^ing to renounce inch of olaim t md w terica, mho hie strong inters at a in Asiatic iurkey, md espeoi illy in ^yria, and is likely in any case to have ctanocratie views auout U*e future of liberated Ctto ioii territories, has ueoo ie a party to bs considered in my ^yeeiseiit aoout Ui# hear taat, out also the position of one uenefioiory - ourselves - has been very greatly etreni tiiened boUi by the part m have played among the ^a*ibs in the i eja* and in esopotania, and by the open and insistent preference declared by tiie ionist Jews. ^hile, on the one hand, the vast mjority of such ar&amp;bs as look to Christian l ower at all for liberation now regard us as theirprincipal, or oven sole, champions (as do also ths '»jority of Urn Zionist Jsws ) a strong and increasing feeling has manifested itself in opposition to French penetration of any part of the jr ib area. of.- t- i 'olitical uo»unjssioner s f witen recently in Cairo, did all they L. i — L . 2 . could to modify this feeling ty oonvereationa and representation 3 to, leaders of divers sections of Arab-speaking peoples of all denominations; but, in spite of verbal assent, they had not left tu^pt before these sane leaders were reasserting reinforcing their anti-rrench propa^ pnda; while in Cairo we had ample evidence ( i can state its nature if required) that ths King of the nej&amp;z, if he had ever really understood what the wor* isaion- -ers said to him, was in no way minded to observe either the letter or the spirit of the €M^reement to which he was understood to have *4 consented.i'he reasons, one or rnore of which actuate each of the divers Arab parties, and bring all to a common anti-trench conclusion, are often inconsistent because those, wiio are Gloved by th«a, desire different political alternatives. Itou^y epeoklng there are three: 1. omplele iadepandoDce. ihia is relieved to b« feasible only by the less instructed, or the tore blindly fanatical. 2. utrlatl ilftfcaateaa. Lyiia in altern itive desired 4 by Uie majority of botii oalem a Christian Arabs on several fTounds e, . (a) ec&lt;ui8e it is believed that we should exploit *rah lands less selfishly than another l ower and be more willing to leave them one day to the i- •solvea, (b) because, under such conditions oyria and Arabia would form on© political economic whole with Kgypt a l eoopot uaia. a his ardent is paramount witii the Syrians resident in igypt, who fear above ?ill things to loae that field for exploitation which the country of their adoption has long afforded them.m ?J * k&amp;fomn I rgJtefitrifltu, un(l«r m Ihtilaf (Uecentr ai*aiion) achajw of a thorou$i pjoirv; kind, ^ar an tend by the Allied lowers. ihere has oeen a revival of Uiis idea ii/uong Syrians since some inkling of Uie provisions of our agreement witli the French r^ot abroad. Contributory causes are : (a) postponement of the allied victory; (b) belief that the lurks are becoming sufficiently exhausted and sufficiently apprehensive of their ultimate fate at the nands of Urn Central lowers, to be MNmable to Ute milatf (c) belief, nevertheless, Uiat, with Constantinople, a Calipiuite, and a lar &gt;e Asia i:inor territory left to her, iurkey will remain a lower, the protagonist of Islam, and inevitably of #reat influence even in Arab lands. 1 have been assured recently by good authority that Ihtilafwould no* bo riore palatablo to seventy per cent of the byri jib tn m tiie status proposed by our ofpreempnt. ihe above is a bare outline of the reasons which t I submit, c^ll ior 30f«e reconsideration of the Agreements But in subsittin^ tliem, i wish to add that i do not hold my of Uie followin views:- Q) ihat any section of tne ^rab people is capable at present of constituting a stable iniependent state, or of carrying on one witen constituted. % (2) . that it is desirable for us to asstfcne tutelage of all the Arab area, or even of .-uch mere of it than, at present, we do in f ict ’‘protect , this beia‘; understood to include all the parts of the Arabian Peninsula in which any Kristi (in rower h s a footing* (NJB. 1 would xld i alestine). (3) * ihat it is possible or desirable to exclude ranee from v lore or less equal territorial or economic gains under any revised agremfsit*( 4 ). ihat a peace should be made with iurkey which would leave imy part of the Arab ^rea under her direct control t or, indeed, under her better than nominal suxerainty, or aubject to any econo iic influence except that of the allied l owers. 9 July 1917LI VVU &gt; LEMG^AIvIDUM FOJ? TIE ITALIAN AI.BA3SADQR L 287 - j By the terms of Article 9 of 25th, 1915, Great Britain, France June_7th,l 91 7 0 the Treaty of April and Russia recognised that in the event of the total or partial partition of Turkey in Asia, Italy should receive an equitable share in the country 'bordering the province of Adalia, and that ohe zone to he attributed to Italy should be eventually defined taking into account the already existing interests of Great Britain and France in that region. In October 1916 documents were communicated to the Italian Minister for Foreign Affairs showing the agree*- rnents which had been reached between Great Britain, France and Russia regarding their respective zones and spheres of interest in Asia Minor, and various discus sions ensued between these three Powers and Italy regard ing the sphere which should be attributed to the latter according to the terms of Article 9 of the Treaty of April 26th,1915. No conclusion having been arrived at, the matter was further debated at the Conference of the Allies held at 3t. Jean de I/Iaurienne on April 19th,1917, at which the Prime Ministers of Great Britain, France and Italy and the Italian Minister for Foreign Affairs were present. As the result of this Conference the British and French Prime Ministers undertook to submit to their res pective Governments the claims of the Italian Government in Asia Minor based upon a map which was introduced at the discussion. (A reproduction of this map, which was&gt; b drawn roughly and which mur.t be nubject to accurate delimitation, is attached hereto; the Italian sphere is therein coloured green and the Italian sphere ci. in- fluence is marked 'C 11 ). An exchange of views also took place as to the situation which might result for the Allied Powers at the moment of peace with regard to the Ottoman Empire, and a formula was agreed to in this connection. His Majesty’s Government, after carefully consider ing the conclusions of the Conference at St 0 Jean de Maurierme v/hich were duly laid before them oy Mr * Lloyd George, agree conditionally to the zones of occupation and of interest respectively to be attributed to Italy as defined at that Conference and as shown in the annexed map. The agreement of His Majesty’s Government is, how ever, subject to the following conditions.- (1) . That the consent of the Russian Government be first obtained. (2) u That Smyrna, if eventually ceded to Italy, shall be a free port. (3) . That Italy make an increased effort to co operate with the Allies in arms against the common eneny, the nature of such effort to oe determined after con sultation between the General staffs of the Allies 0 It is further understood:- (1). That the interests of the other Powers already established in the different ZOilGa ^hall oe scrupulously respected, but that the Powers concerned these interests shall not make use of tnem as a means of /p U If hftfn eJiC&amp;A A✓ of political action and (2) bhau ii at the time when peace is declared, the total or partial possession of the territories contemplated in the agreements cone to between Great Britain, mance, loaly and Bussia, as to the disposal of a part of the Ottoman Empire, cannot he fully accorded to one or more of these Powers, then the interests of the Powers concerned will he again taken into equitable consideration, having regard to the efiorts made ’ey each of the Powers in the war. R* Ca . \ So'In auy further oommumca- !ion on this subject, please quote ion on tmo piviwv no. w /o 97 ' ^ Sc~^ %&gt; md address— The Under-Secretary „ Foreign Office, London. 2276 1917 The Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Secretary j f* and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith copy of the under-mentioned paper. * Foreign Office, J i-t , 1917. Reference to previous correspondence Jjetter Foreiqn Ollice: from Description of Enclosure. Name and I )ate. Subject. J'.; 71.^ y v 4-. ^ 0 3L&gt;\ / ibrrl' {Similar letter sent ton-lr~;ilat,ed to The Kin.' and War (la blnstr Cypher te leer'ire to Sir VMtodd (Korre) ^ Foreign Officer June Ist^l917r S r 30 prrv Russian Oharg^ d'Affaires now informs me that his Government object to the publication of any hote on the Asia Minor question. I have told him what has passed between us and the Russian Government on the subject, and he is to consult his Government again. In the meantime I cannot do anything further in the ratterr Repeated to Petro^rad Uo*1116rIn any further communica- . ion on this subject, pleaee quote So . w 95567,/! 1 v nd address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. ,er his compliments to the UMDER SECRETARY OF STATE FOR T[Jjia by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith copy of the under-mentioned paper. , for any observations which Mr. Secretary Cham berlain may have to ofier. f oreign Office, ■ *'M&gt; i cP.'iOT- May 30th , i9‘ Ik Reference to previous correspondence ( / 5 Letter, 10 Foreign Office: from Description of Enclosure. — Name and bate. Subject. Memorandum communicated by the Italian Ambassador, Italy and Asia Minor. May 11th, IS17. U3In auy further communica tion on this subject, please quote No. w /e&gt;224C]/(^(J in d address— P The Under-Secretary of Foreign Londvjir 2128 9 IT The Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents TLTXk his compliments to the ^ecrcta^y v 'fi* and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop UU of the under-mentioned paperT Foreign Office, Z? , '&lt;?'/• Reference to previous correspondence Utter} 0 Foreign Office : from Description of Enclosure. » Kama and Date. Subject. „ ,. x ^ ul ^ &lt;Cj V $ 0 ^ ^ ^ JUm c n A,. 33 ‘ U3 (Similar letter sent to• - .KXSG -THD ' , iUB CArJlTuT. &amp;) X Lord R. Cecil to Sir R. Rodd (Rome) Foreign odd ice j Rciy IQtjn* id 17 ])T0# 3.12 ♦ 7S 2 = 23 l Sir, I asked the Italian jWbassador to cane to see me this axternoon. I told him that, ^mediately alter our l==et conversation, I had sent instructions to our Representatives in Paris and petrograd to ask the Governments to which they were accredited to instruct their Representatives here to renew the conference on Asia Minor. But we had received a telegram this morning from Russia which led us to think that such a move in petrograd at the present moment would be very indiscreet, and indeed dangerous. I said that the new Russian Government were practically tne last hope securing any real assistance from Russia, mid that, if they went, there would be great danger of complete anarchy in that country. In these circumstances, it was absolutely necessary that we should take every step to strengthen them. ! did not conceal from the Ambassador that, in my view, any attempt to ratify xhe Agreement of ot. jean de Maurianne at this moment would be extremely some formula which would be sufficient to satxsiy Italian public opinion anl yet «ould not tie Russians* I s&lt;*;eeted tnat « flRdt say sc e thins T,‘bo sij,ocij 't.'iEti the Hussistn^ xt&amp;lisn,c^rh iirXuich Goverments were agreed in principle as to the Asia Minor question, tut that for the moment it was im possible to conclude a definite Agreement, I asked the Ambassador to suggest to Baron sonnino that he might draft some formula of that kind, I would try to draft one myself. The Marquis imperial! did not seem much surprised at this ccmrnunication, indeed he had apparently already informed his Government that he doubted the expediency of any renewal of the conference her., I T then hinted to the Ambassador uhew I thought it sulk possible that all the international agree- E I menus would- neve lo oe reviseclo This was a great shock to the Ambassador, He jumped to the conclusion that I meant that none of the advantage* poured to Italy would be insisted on, 3 told him teat that was not what I intended, but that I thought it Quite possible that we should have to reconsider all the questions involved, or at any rate express our readiness to reconsider them. He seemed very much disturbed at this intimation, but promised to convey it to Baron Sonnino, T pm etc.-, (Signed) Bodert CecilaClKCULATii.O TO THE Kill? jo3J THE V/aR Lord R. Cecil to Lord Bertie (peris) Forelan Oiiiee, May 19th.1917. Im O • o 00 . CaBILKT. My Lord, I asked the French i^moassador to corae to see me this enter no on, i:i order to explain to nim that, owing to the trend of events in Kussia, j. nad thour-ht it desirable to instruct Sir George Buchanan not to act on previous instructions to ask the Russian Government to take part in a furtner coniexei.ee here on the Asia Minor Question# M. Canhon said that he quite understood, and in deed agreed, that it would he uost haprudent to nu-ke such a suggestion to the Russian Goverm nt at the pres ent moment * • Vie discussed the Asia Minor question to some extent, and I told him that I thought the end oi it would he that the whole oi the Asia Minor Agreements would have to he revised, I am, etc. h \ (Signed) Robert Cecil*In any further communica tion on this subject, plcaae quote No. yt CJ. c^cskj' ind address— , T jnder-8eoretary of State, 'v Foreign Office, \ v TvOndoi^Xj'* 2 0 6 3 c? ( bs\ ^ &amp; The Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Secretary' Uk-T/ cfc/i/^cy ^ % £ Pi^SlA and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop y of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, ftAf t iQU' Jjetter, Foreign Office: from Reference to previous correspondence :— cj. /cj *3 S&gt; Description of h nclosure. Name anti I )ate. ' u - ft. fort, fts*. (2 7 Subject. i^Cudy' (Simitar letter sent to* o.i 19 J^oret. X \ \ Uir: - l£ &gt; ’I. h.u.UY, »oia*. t»y ii , 1V17. I uihV* tae nonour to report tn^t th« l iniai.tr for lorci^n Affairs said to te tnis raornini; t»iat it Hod boon sutfgastsd to ale tiiat Vnt oonforonoas in London on the Asia Li nor question slight now be r*KUD*d. ile said m was quite ready to aooept suen * propowition. Us could have wished that the new Hues! an ^ bass ad or had arrived* as he did not think that the Ohargft d 1 Affaires in London a*fried nuoh weight♦ But it right be a loni; ttoe before l . S»aonow took up his post. i;e would like one or two outstanding points* especially the question of the frontier with the &gt;rench sphere* to have beeji talked over first so that the results of the earlier conferences Blight be t ore or leus complete, he had already suggested that the /fabaosador in London should subrit a rap which he had n^d prepared on toe lines already indicated. But the Anbassador seeried rather reluctant to take up the matter with your department only* feeling that this eight not be appreciated. he felt considerable t isgivings *bout .ussia and what her attitude night bs. b. iiiliukow had given assurances as to toe maintenance of the existing pacts. But could he be sure of xiu o n losition in that respect ? * here nad ^lao been ihissi^i rapudiatiens of annexation, and explanations of these repudi ations* and again realfinriotions of the Right uonble. A. J. Balfour. O.i .i «* etc.* etc.* etc..of 't.id it wau difficult to icnow w^at tao final dooiwioo /ouid b« # If Russia vuoolHined mij auoh MMexat- i onu on tor on part, did udat £3«?«n tViat uh® would pro tent td«m on tha part of otKars ? Cr would t 5 ‘m stand -hat 'vad ilraad., ^boiled in * rean ^nt#, but rofuae to &lt;*nt*r into any n#rw on«s involving annaxationo ? It J3&lt;*« ** i to tnat «o far as dreat iiritain, . raaoa and Italy war« oonormad, thay had practically 001.0 to an understanding. Thera were one or two points still open* but in the la iin the issue had been settled. i*o doubt there wa© still tne subordination of what tuey nad agreed upon, to the ooneent of uueeia. Hut it would be hnrdly f ir on It'»ly to regard tne e^re^ente entered into between Great hritain md yrnnce as holdin : ; t;ood, whatever Kusel*** ultinate view au to tnnexationo r ii;ht be, ani for these two Powers to decline to oonfirc their understanding wit&gt;i Italy so far they were concerned on the grounds that Pussia would not now consent to it. ;.e ^uite under* stood that i ^ny points jaight n ve to be reconsilered, that tne hole irr an er en t was ver.y roble*. aticul, -uid that we had a lorvc way to travel to realisation of our eiios. But what eoncernei hir^ chiefly was to have an understandinwith Great Britain and I'rmce so far au they even were each of ther concerned, and if the circueiotonoss m » ie it necessary for Russia under ner present conditions not to coiiL.it herself at *11. This would suffice to enable niia to uoet the nar 1 i m ■ e^tary poijfltl oil here. Jie would not ma'ce any revelations or inforr the Ohnuber of the details of any n^reeniento v.’hich r.i;;ht be cor e to* But fie wanted to be able to say that so far ho the relations of Italy with Great ^ri t tin j rjd r^ncs were concerned, t'*ey had i et hiri in a c)&gt;irit with $*hich he had every reason to i.e satisfied.tt**i«iuflad* It ae could aiva uo£,e juoh aoourmnoa t this question would b« diapoued of, *nd hin poaltion would ba a strong ona• If on tba ot*n«r ^*md ha waa praoaad and atta* okad, ia pec tad U&gt; ba, and wao obliged to admit W *U aia na&lt;ioU^tiona iA.i ra» ainad inconoluoiYa, ha no nroapac - of bain^ able to continue *m office. &lt;*« taitfht rely on iiiu not to oGK&amp;iit iiny indiacrationa. Aa to what xmi appeared in tie iraca, be had no doubt whatever the Infomation had bean obtained in Faria. Italians returnin*; iron Mr?mam had a^kad Mb lueotiona which unde it quite pi iin to Mai that the indiucretiona md bean coc^caittad thex^a, snd f ie n^d no doubt that the membara of the In Ur-Farliw entaxy Conference now aaaei bled in F*&lt;ria would hwe heard all -about it. His quectionera had obtained nothin** from hiw. But he realised that the feeling anon** the public had now bee:! roused to ouon m pitch that toe cotflntf aeaaion could not naco without the critical moment arriving which he had done hia beat to stave off until now. It would not be tolerated that he should make no stite&amp;ent on the iaet occasion which would present itself before the end of the year, lie preeisaed that Great iJritain *nd /ranoe ooaeidered that their a^reementa held good, oo far as the two were concerned, whatever the attitude of Kusai* Bight b« towards thene questions* and it w ul4. surely not be fair that Italy ahould not hav# a similar understanding with theai at least as far aa they three were concerned. He thought they would recognise th«t thi i) wai:: equitable. If Husai* had fr^v foroe of oiroutnstvnooa to withdraw trots her fomar attitude, if she r|no longer hygu zo 1 .] u i tj 't on tho ponuosttion of Ooosit&lt;antinopX* whlcri the three AXlieo had agreed, that was her o rn affair, but he did not think it ought to prevent the three other Alliee ootalng to tsuoh under- fe, sv^dinge a» they thought to their own interest with regard to the *r**s where they renounced ooepetition with one another. I have the honour to be with the highest rsspeot. dir. Year vest obedient. humble servant.In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote no. w ^su^6jn m d address— / The Under-Secretary of 4|ate. - • e, sy £\ ■ Foreign Office, ^.V LondopvK »j37 \ \ / The Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his conipimients to the Se&amp;Aa-ry 7 fS $ ixAlpo and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop y of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, i-LA^ i (^ . ‘vn- Reference to previous correspondence J jet ter Foreign Office : from Description of Enclosure. Name and l)atG. •j, Sc X ^ ^ Subject. 9 (if &lt;/US U3 (Simitar tetter sent toJ Circulated to IJhe Kin^ and ’^ ay Cabinets No.108. foreign office. May 14th.1917 Sir: - The Italian nmhassudor came to see me to-day and spoke to me about Asia Minor. he read to ue extracts from a telegram from Baron Sonnino.. urging in the first nlace that the Conference of the four Powers should he resumed in London, and in the second place that, if the Russian Government refused on general principle to accept the agreement arrived at at St.Joan de Muurienne. the other three Governments might nevertneless conclude tne agreement as far as they were concerned. I told tils ambassador tiiot I «as suite willins toe Conference of tne four lexers should be resumed, but that 1 thought there »ould bo considerable difficult, in taking the line posted «lth regard to Russia. The Russian Government »ere a part, te the original mm* ment bet.eoh Russia, France and Great Britain, and it^ t, 0 ignore their views with xes- would toe very dixf^culu to i 0 pect to the new arrangement. Of course, if Russia „ , 0 „ or expressed her wlllineness that we asKed us to do so, o . twines ^ t would be a different state oi thing should do so, that 'ouici u. is ExcQllency The Right honourable Sir R.Rodd, G.C.k.G., G.C.V.O.. 6sc., &amp;c., mC.I tnen went on, speaking quite unofficially and privately, to say taut I thoug.it it quite possible that none of these agreements could be sustained if the Russian Government formally raised objection to annexa tions. I pointed out to the Ambassador that Smyrna really contained a very small Italian population, that the people who livek there were mainly either Greeks or Turks,, and that I was not aware of any reason to suppose that they would particularly wash to be annexed to Italy. Under these circumstances, I thought it quite possible that the whole of the Asia Minor agreements would have to be re-cast in the direction of converting what were to be annexations into spheres of influence, or something of that sort. I added that the case of Mesopotamia pre sented considerable difficulty, because British troops were in actual possession of it. Moreover, we had given a pledge that we would never leave Busra, as we had wished to re-assure the local Arab Chiefs, i should therefore have to discuss with my Colleagues what, if anything, could oe done with regard to Mesopotamia. The Ambassador did not immediatelt reject this idea, though he did not appear to relish it very highly. he asked that whether ne was to convey it to Baron oonnino? I said that ne ni &amp; ht do so, provided he explained I was speaking quite orivately and unoificially. I an, c-.c., Robert Cecil. (Signed)Decypher. Sir M. Sykes (Jeddah) May 4th # 1917• D. 11.30 a.m. May 4th, 1917. R. 8 a.m. May 5th, 1917. No. 19. Following for Sir R. Graham. Cox’s number T 13 90. Esyp^n version of agreement map contains material errors which have now been corrected perhaps Cox’s equally erroneous. If Cox has the small map only it would bo advisable to wire him particulars on a large scale map Clto which) he has access.Received at India Office 50th at 9 a*m. T* 1390. Papers regarding Arab State just received* Addressed Hirtzel, repeated Sykes.In Any further communica tion on this subject, please quote No W. 150406 /1916 »nd address— The Under-Secretary of State Foreign Ofiice, I&gt;ondon. SECRET. i n o j 'U The Under-Secretarv of State for Foreign A fairs presents his compliments to the Under Secretary of State for India and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith copy of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, August 2nd , 1916 . Reference to previous correspondence Letter Foreiqn Office: from J ^ Description of Inclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Russian Ambassador August 1st, 1916. Spheres in Asia Minor t 14 (Similar letter sent to B • of T •, D .M• I •» E • I .D •&amp; From Sir Arthur Hirtzel to Mr. Clerk,Foroipn Office, 19th July 1916. India Office. Whitehall, S.W. ?/. 136861. My dear Clerk, Thanks for your letter numbered as above. I-did not keep a copy of mine, but I fear I must have expressed myself badly. It was not intended to suggest a public statement now: but only to point out that if and when the agreement becomes public property it will be desirable to make it clear that the word 'proteger' does not bear the technical meaning of exercising a protectorate. It would be simpler to get rid of the word altogether by arrangement with the French, and, if anything is required in addition Po 'recomiaitre , substitute 'garantir' or something of that kind. Yours sincerely, (Sd.) A.Hirtzel.'/4 FOREIGN OFFICE. July 18th 1916. My dear Hirtzel, We have been considering the suggestion contained in your letter to me of the 13th instant relative to the desirability of some public statement being made such as would modify the expression 'proteger' as it appears in the Anglo French Agreement on the future Arab state. from the moment when this Agreement need be made public, and that it would be somewhat premature to make any further statement of our policy than that already made at the beginning of the War and the declaration contained in the pronouncement recently submitted to you and Cairo. Both Lord Crewe and Lord Hardinge share my view. I feel that we are still a long way(w. 189907/16) (S Foreign Oft ice, September 27th, 1916. Dear Shuckburgh:- As you are aware, we have recently arranged with the French Government that the words 'proteger' and 'protect' as applied to the Arab State in the exchange of Notes of the 9th and 16th of May last, shall he replaced by the words 'soutenir' and “up- hold'. We have since arranged that the words 'en tant que protecteurs de 1'Etat Arabe' and 'as the protec tors of the Arab State' which occur in article 10 of these Notes shall, on the same principle, be erased. This arrangement is embodied in an exchange of semi-official letters between Clerk and de[87247] Sir Edward Grey to M. Cambon. (Secret.) Your Excellency, Foreign Office, May 15, 1910. I SHALL have the honour to reply fully in a further note to your Excellency’s note of the 9th instant, relative to the creation of an Arab State, but 1 should meanwhile be grateful if your Excellency could assure me that in those regions which, under the conditions recorded in that communication, become entirely French, or in which French interests are recognised as predominant, any existing British concessions, rights of navigation or development, and the rights and privileges of any British religious, scholastic, or medical institutions will be maintained. His Majesty’s Government are, of course, ready to give a reciprocal assurance m regard to the British area. I have, Ac. E. GREY.[87247] Sir Edward Grey to M. Gambon secret.) • Your Excellency, Foreign Office, May 16, 1916. I HAVE the honour to acknowledge the receipt of your Excellency s note ol the 9th instant, stating that the French Government accept the limits of a future Arab State, or Confederation of States, and of those parts of Syria where French interests predominate, together with certain conditions attached thereto, such as they result from recent discussions in London and Petrograd on the subject. I have the honour to inform your Excellency in reply that the acceptance of the whole project, as it now stands, will involve the abdication of considerable British interests, but, since His Majesty’s Government recognise the advantage to the general cause of the Allies entailed in producing a more favourable internal political situation in Turkey, they are ready i o accept the arrangement now arrived at, provided that the co-operation of the Arabs is secured, and that the Arabs fulfil the conditions and obtain the towns of Homs, Hama, Damascus, and Aleppo. It is accordingly understood between the French and British Governments— 1 . That France and Great Britain are prepared to recognise and uphold an independent Arab State or a Confederation of Arab States in the areas (a) and ( 6 ) marked on the annexed map, under the suzerainty of an Arab chief. That in area (a) France, and in area (b) Great Britain, shall have priority of right of enterprise and local loans. That in area (a) France, and in area (b) Great Britain, shall alone supply advisers or foreign functionaries at the request of the Arab State or Confederation of Arab States. . 2. That in the blue area France, and in the red area Great Britain, snail be allowed to establish such direct or indirect administration or control as they desire and as they may think fit to arrange with the Arab State or Confederation of Arab States. 3. That in the brown area there shall be established an international administration, the form of which is to be decided upon after consultation with Russia, and subsequently in consultation with the other Allies, and the representati\es of the Shereef of Mecca. 4. That Great Britain be accorded (1) the ports of Haifa and Acre, ( 2 ) guarantee of a given supply of water from the Tigris and Euphrates in area (a) for area (b). His Majesty’s Government, on their part, undertake that they will at no time enter into negotiations for the cession of Cyprus to any third Power without the previous consent of the French Government. f&gt;. That Alexandretta shall be a free port as regards the trade of the British Empire, and that there shall be no discrimination in port charges or facilities as regards British shipping and British goods ; that there shall be freedom of tiansit for British goods through Alexandretta and by railway through the blue area, whether those goods are intended for or originate in the red area, or (b) area, or area (a) , and there shall be no discrimination, direct or indirect, against British goods on any railway or against British goods or ships at any port serving the areas mentioned. That Haifa shall be a free port as regards the trade of France, her dominions and protectorates, and there shall be no discrimination in port charges or facilities as regards French shipping and French goods. There shall be freedom of transit for French goods through Haifa and by the British railway through the brown area, whether those goods are intended for or originate in the blue area^ area (a), or area [b), and there shall be no discrimination, direct or indirect, against h rench goods on any railway, or against French goods or ships at any port serving the areas mentioned. 6 . That in area (a) the Bagdad Railway shall not be extended southwards beyond Mosul, and in area (b) northwards beyond Samarra, until a railway connecting Bagdad with Aleppo via the Euphrates Valley has been completed, and then only with the concurrence of the two Governments. 7. That Great Britain has the right to build, administer, and be sole owner of a railway connecting Haifa with area (b), and shall have a perpetual right to transport troops along such a line at all times. . It is to be understood by both Governments that this railway is to facilitate the connection of Bagdad with Haifa by rail, and it is further understood that, if the engineering difficulties and expense entailed by keeping this connecting line in the [462—8]o brown area only make the project unfeasible, that the French Government shall be prepared to consider that the line in question may also traverse the polygon Banias- Keis Marib-Salkhad Tell Otsda-Mesmie before reaching area (b). 8 For ‘i period of twenty years the existing Turkish customs tarift shall remain in force throughout the whole of the blue and red areas, as well as in areas (a) and (b), and no increase in the rates of duty or conversion trom ad valorem to specific rate^ shall be made except by agreement between the two Powers. . There shall be no interior customs barriers between any ot the above-mentioned areas The customs duties leviable on goods destined for the interior shall be collected at the port of entry and handed over to the administration of the area of destination. 9 j t s h a n be agreed that the French Government will at no time enter into any negotiations for the cession of their rights and will not cede such rights in the blue area to anv third Power, except the Arab State or Confederation of Arab States, without the' previous agreement of His Majesty’s Government, who, on their part, will give a similar undertaking to the French Government regarding the red area 10 The British and French Governments shall agree that they will not themselves acquire and will not consent to a third Power acquiring territorial possessions in the \rabian peninsula, nor consent to a third Power constructing a naval base on the islands of the east coast of the Red Sea. This, however, shall not prevent such adjustment of the Aden frontier as may be necessary m consequence of recent Turkish aggression. 11 The negotiations with the Arabs as to the boundaries of the Arab State or Confederation of Arab States shall be continued through the same channel as heretofore on behalf of the two Powers. . , . ,; 12. It is agreed that measures to control the importation of arms into the Arab territories will be considered by the two Governments. I have further the honour to state that, in order to make the agreement complete, His Majesty’s Government are proposing to the Russian Government to exchange notes analogous to those exchanged by the latter and your Excellency’s Government on 26th April last. Copies of these notes will be communicated to your Excellency as soon as exchanged. I would also venture to remind your Excellency that the conclusion of the present agreement raises, for practical consideration, the question of the claims of Italy to a share in anv partition or rearrangement of Turkey in Asia, as formulated m article 9 of the agreement of 26th April, 1915, between Italy and the Allies. His Majesty’s Government further consider that the Japanese Government should be informed of the arrangements now concluded. I have, &amp;c. E. GREY. v \ v[93696] 4 Sir Edward Grey to Count Bcnchendorff. (Secret.) Your Excellency, Foreign Office, May 23, 1910. I HAVE received from the French Ambassador in London copies of the notes exchanged between the Russian and French Governments on the 26th ultimo, by which your Excellency’s Government recognise, subject to certain conditions, the arrangement made between Great Britain and France, relative to the constitution of an Arab State or a Confederation of Arab States, and to the partition of the territories of Syria, Cilicia, and Mesopotamia, provided that the co-operation of the Arabs is secured. His Majesty’s Government take act with satisfaction that your Excellency’s Government concur in the limits set forth in that arrangement, and I have now the honour to inform your Excellency that His Majesty’s Government, on their part, in order to make the arrangement complete, are also prepared to recognise the conditions formulated by the Russian Government and accepted by the French Government in the notes exchanged at Petrograd on the 26th ultimo. In so far, then, as these arrangements directly affect the relations of Russia and Great Britain, I have the honour to invite the acquiescence of your Excellency’s Government in an agreement on the following terms:— 1. That Russia shall annex the regions of Erzeroum, Trebizond, Van. and Bitlis, up to a point subsequently to be determined on the littoral of the Black Sea to the west of Trebizond. 2. That the region of Kurdistan to the south of Van and of Bitlis between Mush, Sort, the course of the Tigris, Jezireh-ben-Omar, the crest-line of the mountains which dominate Amadia, and the region of Merga A T ar, shall be ceded to Russia ; and that starting from the region of Merga Yar, the frontier of the Arab State shall follow the crest-line of the mountains which at present divide the Ottoman and Persian Dominions. These boundaries are indicated in a general manner and are subject to modifications of detail to be proposed later by the Delimitation Commission which shall meet on the spot. 3. That the Russian Government undertake that, in all parts of the Ottoman territories thus ceded to Russia, any concessions accorded to British subjects by the Ottoman Government shall be maintained. If the Russian Government express the desire that such concessions should later be modified in order to bring them into harmony with the laws of the Russian Empire, this modification shall only take place in agreement with the British Government. 4. That in all parts of the Ottoman territories thus ceded to Russia, existing British rights of navigation and development, and the rights and privileges of any British religious, scholastic, or medical institutions shall be maintained. His Majesty s Government, on their part, undertake that similar Russian rights and privileges shall be maintained in those regions which, under the conditions of this agreement, become entirely British, or in which British interests are recognised as predominant. 5. The two Governments admit in principle that every State which annexes any part of the Ottoman Empire is called upon to participate in the service of the • Ottoman Debt. I have, &amp;c. E. GREY.«Zy [168743] The Marquess of Crewe to M. Cambon. Your Excellency, Foreign Office, August 30, 1916. I HAVE the honour to acknowledge the receipt of your Excellency s note ot the 25th instant, suggesting that for the words “ protect (‘ proteger ’) an independent Arab State,” which occur in the notes exchanged on the 9th and 16th Hay last, on the subject of Asiatic Turkey, the words “ uphold ( ; soutenir’) an independent Arab State should be read. _ . f In reply, I have the honour to state that I see no objection to the adoption o the word suggested by your Excellency, and I have accordingly caused the necessary alteration to be made in the original text of your note of the 9th Hay. I have, &amp;c. CREWE.* [207447] r » Viscount Grey to Count Benckendorff. Your Excellency, Foreign Office, October 23, 1916. IN reply to your Excellency’s note of the 1st ultimo, regarding the arrangement between Great Britain, Russia, and France, relative to the creation of an Arab State, or of a confederation of Arab States, and to the partition of the territories of Syria, Cilicia, and Mesopotamia, provided that the co-operation of the Arabs is secured, I have the honour to state that His Majesty’s Government take note of the reservation formulated by the Imperial Russian Government at the end of article 4 of the arrangement respecting the rights of the Imperial Government to grand cabotage in the Black Sea, and of the desire manifested by that Government that this question should be submitted later to a friendly examination by the Governments of the parties interested. I nQTTP rVP GREY OF FALLODON. * &gt; [462—13]6 co-operation of the Arabs is secured, and that the Arabs fulfil the conditions and obtain the towns of Homs, Hama, Damascus, and Aleppo. It is accordingly understood between the French and British Governments 1 . That France and Great Britain are prepared to recognise and frinout^^ independent Arab State or a Confederation of Arab States in the areas (a) and (b) marked on the annexed map, under the suzerainty of an Arab chief. That in area (o) France, and in area (b) Great Britain, shall have priority of right of enterprise and local loans. That in area (a) France, and in area ( 6 ) Great Britain, shall alone supply advisers or foreign functionaries at the request of the Arab State or Confederation of Arab States. 2 . That in the blue area France, and in the red area Great Britain, shall be allowed to establish such direct or indirect administration or control as they desire and as they may think fit to arrange with the Arab State or Confederation of Arab States. 3. That in the brown area there shall be established an international administration, the form of which is to be decided upon after consultation with Russia and subsequently in consultation with the other Allies, and the representatives of the Shereef of Mecca. 4. That Great Britain be accorded ( 1 ) the ports of Flaifa and Acre, ( 2 ) guarantee of a given supply of water from the Tigris and Euphrates in area (a) for area (b). His Majesty’s Government, on their part, undertake that they will at no time enter into negotiations for the cession of Cyprus to any third Power wfithout the previous consent of the French Government. o. That Alexandretta shall be a free port as regards the trade of the British Empire, and^ that there shall be no discrimination in port charges or facilities as regards British shipping and British goods ; that there shall be freedom of transit for British goods through Alexandretta and by railway through the blue area, whether those goods are intended for or originate in the red area, or (b) area, or area (a); and there shall be no discrimination, direct or indirect, against British goods on any railway or against British goods or ships at any port serving the areas mentioned. that Haifa shall be a tree port as regards the trade of France, her dominions and protectorates, and there shall be no discrimination in port charges or facilities as regards rench shipping and h rench goods. There shall be freedom of transit for French goods through Haifa and by the British railway through the brown area, whether those goods are intended for or originate in the blue area, area (a), or area (b), and there shall be no discrimination, direct or indirect, against French goods on any railway, or against French goods or ships at any port serving the areas mentioned. 0 . that in area (a) the Bagdad Railway shall not be extended southwards beyond Mosul, and in area (b) northwards beyond Samarra, until a railway connecting Bagdad with Aleppo via the Euphrates \ alley has been completed, and then only with the concurrence of the two Governments. t. That Great Britain has the right to build, administer, and be sole owner of a radway connecting Haifa with area ( 6 ), and shall have a perpetual right to transport troops along such a line at all times. It is to be understood by both Governments that this railway is to facilitate the connection of Bagdad with Haifa by rail, and it is further understood that, if the engineering difficulties and expense entailed by keeping this connecting line in the aiown area only make the project unfeasible, that the French Government shall be piepared to consider that the line in question may also traverse the polygon Banias- ixeis Marib-balkhad lell Otsda-Mesmie before reaching area (b). . oi a peiiod of twenty years the existing Turkish customs tarilf shall remain in ouc thioughout the whole of the blue and red areas, as well as in areas (a) and (b), a I 1 &lt; q 1 11 5 ) increase i n the rates of duty or conversion from ad valorem to specific rates Jl e ma d e except by agreement between the two Powers. nere snail be no interior customs barriers between any of the above-mentioned areas, the customs duties leviable on goods destined for the interior shall be collected at t le port of entry and handed over to the administration of the area of destination. .’ } s iall be agreed that the French Government will at no time enter into any negotiations ior the cession of their rights and will not cede such rights in the blue area to any third Power, except the Arab State or Confederation of Arab States, wit iom t le pievious agreement of His Majesty’s Government, who, on their part, will gi\e a sum ai undertaking to the French Government regarding the red area. 10 . 1 lie British and drench Govpi-nmpntg aa tBg. n f ^ 1 i sfinit** s la agiee that they will not themselves acquire and will not consent to a third Power acquimig temtonal possessions in the Arabian peninsula, nor consent to a third \/ZOi 7 HcTV w' Power constructing a naval base on the islands of the east coast of the Red Sea. This, however, shall not prevent such adjustment of the Aden frontier as may be necessary in consequence of recent Turkish aggression. 1 1 . The negotiations with the Arabs as to the boundaries of the Arab State or Confederation of Arab States shall be continued through the same channel as heretofore on behalf of the two Powers. 12. It is agreed that measures to control the importation of arms into the Arab territories will be considered by the two Governments. 1 have further the honour to state that, in order to make the agreement complete, His Majesty’s Government are proposing to the Russian Government to exchange notes analogous to those exchanged by the latter and your Excellency’s Government on 2()th April last. Copies of these notes will be communicated to your Excellency as soon as exchanged. 1 would also venture to remind your Excellency that the conclusion of the present agreement raises, for practical consideration, the question of the claims of Italy to a share in any partition or rearrangement of Turkey in Asia, as formulated in article 9 of the agreement of 26th April, 1915, between Italy and the Allies. His Majesty’s Government further consider that the Japanese Government should be informed of the arrangements now concluded. I have, &amp;c. E. GREY. [93696] No * 7 - Sir G. Buchanan to Sir Edioard Grey.—(Received May 17.) (No. 711.) (Telegraphic.) YOUR telegram No. 1010 of 15th May. . Minister for Foreign Affairs concurs in your proposal for conclusion of formal agreement between the two Governments. Petrograd, May 16, 1916. [93696] No- 8 - Sir Edward Grey to Count Benckendorff. YoT-'E^cellencv, Foreign Office, May 23 1916. I HAVE received from the French Ambassador m London copies of the notes exchanged between the Russian and French Governments on the 20th ultimo, by which your Excellencv’s Government recognise, subject to certain conditions, the arrangement made between Great Britain and France, relative to the constitution of an Arab State or a Confederation of Arab States, and to the partition of the territories of Syria, Cilicia, and Mesopotamia, provided that the co-operation of the Arabs is secured. His Majesty’s Government take act with satisfaction that your Excellency s Government concur in the limits set forth in that arrangement, and I have now the honour to inform your Excellency that His Majesty’s Government, on then part, in order to make the arrangement complete, are also prepared to r ® co «^ formulated by the Russian Government and accepted by the 1 rench Government tbp notps exchanged at Pctrograd on tbo 20tli ultimo. . r 0 ■ a In so far, then, as these arrangements directly affect Alellencv’s Great Britain, I have the honour to invite the acquiescence of your Excellency Government in an agreement on the following terms : 1. That Russia shall annex the regions of Erzeroum, Ihebizond Van and Biths up to a point subsequently to be determined on the littoral of the Black bea to the WeSt 2° f That‘the region of Kurdistan to the south of Van and of Bitlis between Mush Sert, 2 th] tottofX Tigris, ^re^Omar. ^crest-Uneof ^ - whud, the frontier of the Antb^hanWW^ shall meet on the spot.8 3 That the Russian Government undertake that, in all parts of the Ottoman territories thus ceded to Russia, any concessions accorded to British subjects by the Ottoman Government shall be maintained. If the Russian Government express the desire that such concessions should later be modified in order to bring them into harmony with the laws of the Russian Empire, this modification shall only take place in agreement with the British Government. _ i i ^ -n • 4. That in all parts of the Ottoman territories thus ceded to Russia, existing British rights of navigation and development, and the rights and privileges of any British religious, scholastic, or medical institutions shall be maintained. His Majesty’s Government, on their part, undertake that similar Russian rights and privileges shall be maintained in those regions which, under the conditions of this agreement, become entirely British, or in which British interests are recognised as predominant. 5. The two Governments admit in principle that every State which annexes any part of the Ottoman Empire is called upon to participate in the service of the Ottoman Debt. T . I have, &amp;c. E. GREY.In any further communica tion or. this subject, please quote No. W. 92148 /1916 and address— SECRET • 1 | ' w; &gt; ^ T^’^'Jnder-Secretary of State Foreujn Office, &lt; Ixindon. The Undersecretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the UNDER SECRETARY OP STATE FOR INDIA and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith copy of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Ojfice, May J9th , 1916 . Reference to previous correspondence: Letter ® rom Foreign Office: W. 80650/16 Of May 10th Description of Inclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Sir G. Buchanan, petrograd. No. 83, Secret. i April l/th. Customs duties in Russian sphere in Asiatic Turkey. (Similar letter sent to Board of TradePSTHOGRAD April 16 th 15J6*—^ Ho. S3 % ^ Vith reference to your telegram No* 604 of the 15th inetant, I have the honour to tranemit to you Herewith copy of a Lemornriduna comr-.unicated today by the Minister for Foreign Affair* to &amp;r Lindley on the eubject of transit righte throu^^i Russian territory* In handing this Memorandum to ILT Lindley* M* wazonoff observed that it was not to be considered an official corn'minication* In view of the instructions contained in your above mentioned telegram* Lindley received it without any observation* I have the honour to be* with the highest respect Sir* yomr most obedient, humble Servant* ( in the absence of the Ambassador ) The Right Honble oir ■.* Grey •* Bart** K*G** &amp;«P*** etc** fttc** etc****p rills Dacnmeiit Is the Property of His Britannic Majest y’s Gov ernment, and ahoiald be re t urned to the Foreign Office when done with unless required for official ass.] (87247/16) •pOT JTffCA L Cypher telegram to Sir G. Buchanan (petrogracl). Foreign Office, May 15th&lt;• 1916 0 2 P• - ;1 * No. 1010. 871 9 !6 \ 2 l A .t*' Your Excellency’s telegram ho. oG3 (ex Apill &lt;-Sth). French Emhassy have communicated to me text ox agree ment respecting Syria, Arabia, Cilicia etc., conducted between Prance and Russia, and I am on point of conducing formal agreement with Prance, on terms with which Your Excellency is already acquainted, respecting Syria end Arabia. To complete arrangement, it will he necessary tor * itj , ».,oieetv's Government to conclude Russian Government and His Mcjesuy + nn Riniiar lines to that between a formal agreement, on similar nn s modi a nrid I will submit a draft to Russian Bronco pjii ixUssio.} xiid x enn-n nq T lepm tbat Russian Goverment Ambassador here, as soon as I shcore this view© VJ\#n In Any further communica tion or. this subject, please quote No. W. 806S0 /I 9 l 6 and address— The Under-Secretary of State Foreign Office, ^ Ixmdon. f ^ SECRET. IS I / 813 19! 6 The Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the UNDER SECRETARY OP STATE FOR INDIA anc ^ by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop ies of the under-mentioned papeft. Foreign Office, May 10th , igi6. Copy to India 18 MAY 1916 Reference to previous correspondence: Letter Foreign Office: P.1152' Of April 1st ’oreign Otfice to Board of Trade, May 8th. loard of Trade to Foreign office, April 23th.Copy HI FOREIGN OFFICE, April 4th, 1916. (W. 62655/16). Immediate and Confidential i 1 81 3 Sir With reference to rny letver— -29th ultimo regarding the Anglo-French Arab Question, I am di rected by Secretary Sir Edw. Grey to transmit to you herewith, for the information of the Board Of Trade, a copy of a letter from the India Office relative to the reserves which might be made by His Majesty’s Government in regard to the territory to be acquired by Russia. I am to request that Sir E. Grey may be favoured with an early reply to my above-mentioned letter. I am &amp;c., (Sd.) W. LANGLEY The Secretary to the Board of Trade.BOAHD OF TRADE. Copy E. Secret. S.W. April 23th, 1916 Sir: I am directed hy the Board Ocff Trade to refer to your letters of the 29th March (W. 58401) and the 4th April (W. 62655) relative to the negotiations with Russia in respect of Asiatic Turkey, and also to the telegram (No. 80®) which was addressed to H. M.Ambassador at petrograd on the 13th April. The Board observe that Sir S. Grey has thought it necessary to accept without protest the decision of the Russian Government, as indicated in Sir George Buchanan’s telegrams Nos. 419 of the 25th March and 526 of the 12th April, refusing any concession with respect to the Customs and transit regime to be ap plied to territories acquired by Russia in Asiatic Turkey. The Board regard that decision as likely to create an unfortunate impression among British tra ders, and they feel bolind to record their regret that Sir E. Grey did not see his way to press the Russian Government more strongly in this matter. I am to add that the Board concur in the obser vations contained in the second paragraph of the In dia Office letter of the 1st April, copy of which was enclosed in your letter of the 4th April. I have &amp;c., (Sd.) H. LLEWELLYN SMITH The Under secretary of State Foreign Office.l Foreign ttlce. May titli, 1916. 8 . 5()65fVl6) Secret. 1 an directed b* Secretary Bir inward Grey to acknowledge the receipt of your letter of the 3£tfc ultimo, £ Secret, expressing the regret of the Board of xrade tiiat Sir K. Grey did not see hie way to press the uB^ian Government acre stronrly to make some concession regarding the Customs and r ransit regime to be applied to territories acquired by us - in In Asiatic Turkey. In reply ] am to state that, while 8ir £• Grey regards the Board’s regret at his decielon af 3 very natural, nc is nevertha.te»8 of opinion that t the moment when the whole situation in the f ear ast, In- cluding Persia anci Afgluudetan, had been *-iived by the advance of the KaaBi&amp;n forces in Asia , inor and I’ersia, and tthen the British position in Mesopotamia was what it is now known to S«»ve been, it would have been very inopportune to provoke sharp cortroverey with the fuacian Gover”imrnt about a contingency which must in evitably depend upon the fiml issue of the war. I am. Your most obedient humble Servant ^ Secretary to the Br)ard of TradeIritis Pocnment Is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government, a nd should be returned to the Foreign Office when done with n nless required for official aso,] EGYPT r POLITICAL r Decypher r Sir Hr IxLiahon (Cairo) May 4th r 1916 r Or 2 r 0 r p r I- ; r Hr 4 r 40 r p r r 0 r 3 ^9 r May 4th r 1916 r Ti \W°) Cor-y .8 MAY 1916 a Your telegram No r 339 r Although there is nothing in arrangement agreed on between Prance and Russia and ourselves as defined in your telegram that conflicts with any agreements made with or assurances given to Chereef and other Arab parties, I am of opinion it would be better if possible not to divulge details of that arrangement to Arab parties at presentr Moment has not yet arrived when we can safely do so without some risk of possible misinterpretation oy Arab s r It night be prejudicial to our present good rela~ tions and this is especially undesirable at the present moment,- Later on when events develop more in our favou we will be able to communicate terms of our agreement without this risk*. A similar reticence should of course oe observed by all partiesc With regard to attitude which it is decided to adoptadopt towards litoral ana anti-committee parties in Turkey ? I cannot ihelp feeling a little disappointedc Situation as far as we can gauge it here, does not yet appear one in which we can afford to disregard potential value of this disintegrating factor in Turkey^ Mustapha, representative here of Prince Sahaiidedin’s party, who has just returned from Athens, is now anxious to join the Prince in Switzerland and then proceed to Paris and London* I propose, unless you see objections, to permit him to do so as he may new he of more use there than here*-N. B. 222. ■JJus Document' is the properly o£ IIU Majetij/s Secretary of State joy India. SECRET. H?? I Correspondence with the Grand Sherif of Mecca. 1. 1 elegram to Mr. Clieetliam, Cairo, from Foreign Office, dated d4tli September 1914. No. 219. Secret. Folio win g from Lord Kitchener :— Intelligence report Gtli September, statement regarding attitude of Sherif of Mecca, fell Storrs to send secret and carefully chosen messenger from me to Sherif Abdullah to ascertain whether ‘‘should present armed “German influence at Constantinople coerce Calif against his will and “Sublime Porte to acts of aggression and war against Great Britain, he “ and his father and Arabs of lledjaz would lie with us or against us.” 2.-—Telegram from Mr. Cheetham, Cairo, to Foreign Office, dated 31st October 1914. No. 233. Your telegram No. 219. Messenger has returned from Mecca with letter from Sherif Abdalla. Communication is guarded, but friendly and favourable. Desires “closer union” with Great Britain, but expects and “is awaiting written promise “ that Great Britain will abstain from internal intervention in Arabia and “ guarantee Fmir against Foreign and Ottoman aggression.” Sherif himself in a secret conversation with messenger, expressed himself more freely and openly, saving “ Stretch out to us a helping hand and we will never aid these oppressors.” Messenger was received and treated with great consideration, it should be noted that Sherif Abdalla is only repeating without any additions proposals he made to His Majesty’s Agency on 8th January (group und ecy phe ra ble). lie ply is being prepared subject to your approval disclaiming all intention of internal intervention and guaranteeing, against external aggression only, independence of Sherifate. Messenger must leave Monday morning or week will be lost. Please instruct me at once. 3. Teleoram to Mr. Cheetham, Cairo, from Foreign Office, dated 31st October 1914. No. 303. Your telegram No. 233 of 31st October. Following from Lord Kitchener. Lord Kitchener’s salaam to the Sherif Abdalla. Germany has bought the Turkish Government with gold, notwithstanding that Kngland, France and Russia guaranteed integrity of the Ottoman Empire if Turkey remained neutral in this war. The Turkish Government have against the wish of the Sultan through German pressure committed acts of war by invading the frontiers of Eoypt with armed bands followed by Turkish soldiers which are now massed at Akaba to invade Egypt. If the Arab nation assist England in this war that has been forced upon us by Turkey, England will Guarantee that no internal intervention takes place m Aiabia and uill gi\e the Arabs every assistance against external foreign aggression. It may be that an Arab of the true race will assume the Caliphate at Mecca or Medina and so good may come by the help of God out of all evil' which is now occurring. s. :io?. A4.—Communication from Mr. Cheetham to Sherif Abdalla. After compliments and thanks. We iiave understood your reasons and acknowledge the justice of your request. So we have sent to Lord Kitchener (titles) who has replied as follows Salaams to Sherif Abdalla (titles). That which we foresaw has come to pass Germany has bought the Turkish Government, with gold notwith standing that Great Britain, France and Russia guaranteed the integrity of llie Ottoman Empire if Turkey remained neutral in this war. The Turkish Government have against the wish of the Sultan and through German pressure committed acts of war by invading without provocation the frontiers of E'-ypt with armed bands followed by Turkish soldiers which are now massed at Akaba to invade Egypt, so that the cause of the Arabs, which is the cause of freedom, has become the cause also of Great Britain, ff the Amir (titles) and Arabs in general assist Great Britain in this conflict that has been forced upon us by Turkey, Great Britain will promise not to intervene in any manner whatsoever whether in things religious or otherwise. Moreover, recognising and respecting the sacred and unique oilice ol the Amir Hosavn (titles) Great Britain will guarantee the independence, rights and privileges of the Sherifate against all external foreign aggression, in particular that of the Ottomans. Till now we have defended and befriended Islam in the person of the Turks : henceforward it shall be in that of the noble Arab. It may be that an Arab of true race will assume the Caliphate at Mecca or Medina, and so good may come by the help of God out of all the evil which is now occurring. It would be well il our Highness could convey to your followers and devotees, who are found throughout the world, in every country, the good tidings oi the freedom ol the Arabs, and the rising of the sun over Arabia. 5.—Communication, unsigned and undated, handwriting of Sherif Abdalla. Respectable and powerful Friend, After paying due respects, yours of the 12th Zil lloga lias been received with due honour and reverence, and we have taken it as a basis loi action and a reference for the present and the future. In accordance with it, and in view of its fidelity and accord, our country has come to hold most conscientiously to your suggestions, and has undertaken to carry out faithfully what we said in our previous letter and what we confirm in the present one ; and has avoided since our foregoing letter all that affects unfavourably your material and moral interests. Yea more, we are endeavouring to discourage any man who seeks to harm these inteiests any one of those who are outside the pale of the Hedjaz colony. If you could perceive our critical position in undertaking the matier you would know that we are doing that which is more important than the performance of that which is naturally imposed upon us, regardless of whether or not these negotiations take place and whether or not an agree ment is arrived at. It is so because religion which justifies it and which is the scle foundation of action, prevents us from working at once. But when the time shall come, and it is not far distant, we can not but accomplish it, even though the Ottoman Empire be not occupied and even though it should muster against us all its army. In closing, I would remind you that we act upon the words of him who said, “ Perform ye the promise ye make to God when ye pledge yourselves. We then pay to His Highness and yourself our best regards, requesting you to keep this correspondence secret until the right time should come.f).-—Shorthand Note taken by Messenger of a discourse by the Sherif of Mecca, which took place in privacy at night on the roof of his palace. Ali Hey, please impart my best salaams, faithfulness and friendship to Mr. Storrs, and my acceptance ol what his great Empire has on another occasion proposed. Ali, do your best to make Mr. Storrs understand that lie should not consider my answer as a breaking up of relations. It simply came late, and if she had granted our demand when we made it, things would have been better. The day will come when we will demand more of her than she is now preparing for us, and perhaps soon. Ali, inform Mr. Storrs that 1 am using all my political and material influence in spreading the British policy (influence) in my country as well in that of A1 Imam Yehia, as he is my friend and never acts against my advice. Ali, Turkey is weighing down heavily upon us, beyond the power of our endurance. We therefore oppose the execution of its commands and plans. Yesterday they were planning to send printed circulars or posters to the chiefs of the tribes for distribution among the pilgrims. We oppose the project with all our might and diplomacy; we have opposed it almost to the point of breaking up our relation (with them) ; and if the Mali had not returned upon his decision, relations would have been definitely broken up. And perhaps causes might spring up which would break these relations even before you arrive at your country ; and it might come to pass that the thing would be delayed some three or four or six months. Through my political influence, rebellion and disobedience had well nigh broken out among the Syrian corps. England will hear about my action, if not now, in the future. . Our relations with the Empire are waning, dying, even as a llickenng lamp whose oil had run out. r ,, . . , Ali the only thing that prevents me from rising against the 1 urkish Empire is the 'Moslem world, which now looks upon me and feels annoyed with me, especially under the present circumstances. Another reason is this, I cannot forget the favours the reigning house bestowed upon me. Hut the reins of power have passed from the hands of this famil \. Among the reasons which strengthen the hands of the Turkish statesmen and Cive weight to their influence and power is the interception of food materials from our land. This thing has caused great want there. More, they (Turks) have informed the people and the Bedouins that it was Britain which intercepted the' alms and thus reduced them to their pitiable Mi Bey we wrestle valiantly, spend much of our substance, and use all our'influence to calm down the country. Great Britain will learn of our efforts later on Now we cannot make demands; we simply play hei to Sate the question of grains (the coming in of grams). Be it as it may we shall not turn against her or aid her enemies, bhe shall see. I am bound by three lies; the Caliphate, and, as 1 hare aliea &gt; intimated, the favours which the reigning house Y^'™ d p ZTha the cause a s t0 t } ie religious tie, you see them now declaie openly that tlie c t you will perceive that religious matters have become lax. 1 herefore we are no longer bound to obey th(’ni. folmEiip but there no «pr*nnd tie concerns our obedience to the EatipUate, out mere no longer exists a Caliphate, and The SphikS^hiAat the rules'of the book of God should he enforced, and this they do not do. . intimated that the Turkish Government As to the third I have ahem . We therefore are has come to be nothing more than Enver ana (n 1 no longer bound to them b\ an\ tn4 Notwithstanding this I am of opinion that it will be better now to put off action. This is due to the reasons explained here above, and to the fact that it will be in our interests that this dela\ lie. Say, Ali, are you satisfied V Yes, sir. ^ 7.—Communication from Sherd of Mecca to Mr. Storrs, Oriental Secretary to British Representative, Cairo. To the dear honourable, may Cod protect him, I present to your dear honour my affectionate regards and respects, and hope that you will do your best to make the enclosed note, containing the proposed conditions, effective, as you are capable of doing. And in this connection 1 declare to you and your Covernment that you need not be anxious about the ideas of the people here, because they are closely bound to your Government by community of interests. Do not be at pains to send aeroplanes or men-of-war to throw reports and rumours, as was .done before, because the matter is now decided. Wh at we desire to beg you is to open the way for the Egyptian Govern ment to send the charitable offerings of corn for the Holy lands, be., Mecca and Medina, which were stopped since last year. For verily, the sending of this grain for this year and last would be an important factor in laying the foundations of our mutual advantage. This should suffice for a person of your grasp. In conclusion 1 offer you my best salaams and respects. 2nd Ramadan 1333 (Utii July 1015). Kindly do not trouble to send any correspondence until you see the result of our operations; except the reply to the note and its enclosure, which should be through the bearer only ; and, if you should think lit, give him a written token to make it easy for him to reach you when wc find it necessary. He is all right. Unsigned. 8.—Enclosed with foregoing. To his Honour, W hereas the 1 whole ol the Arab nation without any exception have decided in these last years to live, and to accomplish their freedom and grasp the reins of their Administration both in theory and practice ; and whereas they have found and felt that it is to the interest of the Government of Great Britain to support them and aid them to the attainment of their firm and lawful intentions (which are based upon the maintenance of the honour and dignity of their life) without any ulterior motives whatsoever unconnected with this object; And whereas it is to their fArabs’) interest also to prefer the assistance of the Government of Great Britain in consideration of their geographical position and economic interests, and also of the altitude of the above- mentioned Government, which is known to both nations and therefore need not be emphasized ; 1 or these reasons the Arab nation sees fit to limit themselves, as time is short, to asking the Government of Great Britain, if it should think fit, for the approval, through her deputy or representative, of the following fundamental propositions, leaving out all things considered secondary in comparison with these, so that it may prepare all means necessary for attaining this noble purpose, until,such time as it finds occasion for making the actual negotiations :— i'irstlij. England to acknowledge the independence of the Arab countries, bounded on the north by Mersina-Adana up to the 37' of latitude, on which degree falls Birijik, Urfa, Mardin, Midiat, Amadia Island, up to the border of Persia ; on the east by the borders of Persia up to the Gulf of Basra ; on the south by the Indian Ocean, with the exception of theposition of Aden to remain as it is ; on the west by the Red Sea, the Jeditenanean Sea np to Mersina. I'mgland to approve of the proclamation of an Arab Caliphate of Islam. Secondly. I he Arab Government of the Sherif to acknowledge that Lngland shall have the ])reference in all economic enterprises in the Arab countries whenever conditions of enterprises are otherwise equal. 1 hirdlij. —bor the security of this Arab independence and the certainty ol such preference of economic enterprises, both high contracting parties to oiler mutual assistance to the best ability of their military and naval forces, to face any foreign power which may attack either party. Peace not to be decided without agreement of both parties. V'ourthly .—If one of the parties enters upon an aggressive conflict, the other party to assume a neutral attitude, and in case of such party wishing the other to join forces, both to meet and discuss the conditions. h i ftidy .— England to acknowledge the abolition of foreign privileges in the Arab countries, and to assist the Government of the Sherif in an international Convention for confirming such abolition. Sixthly .—Articles o and 4 of this Treaty to remain in vigour for 15 years, and, if either wishes it to be renewed, one year’s notice before lapse of treaty to be given. Consequently, and as the whole of the Arab nation have (praise be to God) agreed and united for the attainment, at all costs and finally, of this noble object, they beg the Government of Great Britain to answer them positively or negatively in a period of 30 days after receiving this intimation ; and if this period should lapse before they receive an answer, they reserve to themselves complete freedom of action. Moreover we (ISherif’s family) will consider ourselves free in word and deed from the bonds of our previous declaration which we made through Ah Ell/' Undated and unsigned. q —f rom the High Commissioner, Cairo, to the bheiil llosayn (titles). A Iter compliments and salutations. We have thehonoui to thaiik\ou foi your frank expressions of the sincerity of youi feeling towuids England. We rejoice moreover that Your Highness and your people aie of one opinion, that Arab interests are English interests and English Arab. I o this intent we confirm to you the terms of Lord Kitchener’s message, which reached you by the hand of Ali Efl'endi, and in which was stated clearly our desire for the independence of Arabia and its inhabitants, togethei uith om approval of the Arab Caliphate when it should be proclaimed We declare once more that His Majesty’s Government would welcome the resumption of the Caliphate by an Arab of true race. W ith regard to the questions of limits, frontiers and boundaries, it would appear to be premature to consume our time in discussing such details in the heat of war, and while, m main portions of them, the Lurk is up to now in effective occupation; especially as we have learnt, with surprise and regret, that some ot the Arabs m those verv parts, far from assisting us, are neglecting this their supreme oppor tunity, and are lending their arms to the German and the lurk, to the new despoiler and the old oppressor. r,1,,. i 'if in* Nevertheless we are ready to send to Wmr Highness foi the .loh Citn s and the noble Arabs the charitable offerings oi I'-gypt so soon as lour I Holiness shall inform us how and where they should be deliy ud. \\ t an, moreover arranging for this your messenger to be admitted and helped on an}' journey he may make to ourselves. Friendly reassurances. Salutations. Sir. A. JL McMahon. (Apparently dated 30th August l.M&lt;&gt;.) Our last messenger, lide correspondence.0 f ,1 , rs-Mii.l of Mecca to His Excellency the JO.- ro '“‘^J^Y f X' Most Vfuiinei.t, the British High Commissioner in Etrypt; may God grant him success. With 'real cheerfulness and delight 1 received your letter dated H)th CO i nWo rtiitl, A „mist 1 ( .tl5), and have given it great consideration and Ssf'i 1 -rtr*' ' n i i A • itt inn witli regard to our essential point, ^'uls^’ecessary to .uake clear to Your Excellency our sincerity towards the illustrious British Empire and our confesston of preference for it in al cases aiid matters and under all forms and circumstances. 1 he real interests of the followers of our religion necessitate this. Nevertheless. Your Excellency will pardon me and permit me to say clearly'that the coldness and hesitation winch you have displayed in the cAeal V far ; tc nn( i honnd'iries by say n^ that the discussion of these question o dm limiuand^nndan^fiy ti ^ “ nd that they iire still in dte hamUof the Covernment which is ruling them, &amp;c„ might be taken to infer *' these' 1 hidts'and'boi!ndaries^^lemandei 1 are not those of one person whole we should satisfy and with whom we should discuss them aftei the “?s over, but our peoples have seen that the hie of them new proposal is hound at least by these limits and their word is united on this. Therefore they have found it necessary iirst to discuss this point with the Power in whom they now have their confidence and trust as a linal appeal, viz., the Illustrious British Empire. ■ (Literal translation of the above passage): “ And therefore they saw the discussion in it lirst the confidence and trust the axis of final appeal now and that is the Illustrious British Empire.” Their reason for this union and confidence is mutual interest, the necessity of regulating territorial divisions and the ieelmgs of their inhabitants so that they mav know how to base their future and hie, so not to meet her (England ?) or any of her Allies in opposition to t.ieir resolution which would produce a contrary issue, which uod loilml. (Literal translation of above passage as folloxrs): “The feelings of its inhabitants to know how to base their future and life for not to meet her or one of its Allies in front of their reso ti ton when the thing conies to a contrary result, which God forbid. For the object is, honourable Minister, the truth which is established on a basis which guarantees the essential sources ol hie m 'dure. , Yet within these limits they have not included places mtiabitea . a foreign race. It is no vain show of words and titles. May God have mercy on the Caliphate and comlort Moslems n it. 1 am confident that Your Excellency will not doubt that it ■ personally who am demanding of these Inn.ts which nichtdeon^ onr tact, hut that they arc all proposals of the people who, m shoit, belie are necessary for economic life. . Is this not right, Your Excellency the Minister . . i In a word, Your High Excellency, we are firm in our sincentj declaring our preference for loyalty towards }ou, whet h i } (Ml ar( with us, as lias been said, or angry. 1 * 1 , 01*01116 With reference to your remark in your letter above-mentioned that some ol our people are still doing their utmost 111 promoting the _ ke Turkey—Your Goodness (lit. “ Perfectness”) would not permit \ou this an excuse for the tone of coldness and hesitation w.th demands, demands which I cannot admit that you. as a man of sound opm o , will deny to be necessary for our existence; nay, they aie the cs essence of our life, material and moral. • , Up to the present moment, 1 am myself witli all m&gt; nng d c ‘ 1 . 1 ^V, 1 .Miich jn my country all things in conformity with the Islamic Law, all thingstend to benefit the rest of the kingdom, and f shall continue to do so until it pleases God to order otherwise. In order to reassure Your Excellency, 1 can declare that the whole country, together with those who you say are submitting themselves to Tureo-German orders, are all waiting the result of these negotiations, which are dependent only on your refusal or acceptance of the question of the limits and in your declaration of safeguarding their religion iirst and then the rest of rights from any harm or danger. Whatever the illustrious Government of Great Britain linds eomformable to its policy in this subject, communicate it to us and specify to us the course we should follow. . . In all cases it is only God’s will which shall be executed and il is God who is the real factor in everything. With regard to our demand for grain for the natives and the monies (surras) known to the Wakfs Ministry and all other articles sent here with pilgrims’ caravan, O High Excellency, my intention in this matter is to conlinn your proclamations to the whole world, and especially to the Moslem world, that your antagonism is confined only to the party which has usurped the rights of Caliphate in which are included the rights of all Moslems. Moreover, the said grain is from the special Wakfs, and has nothing to do with politics. . „ . , 4 . i If veil think it should he, let the grain of the two years be transpmted i„ a special steamer to .Teddah in an official manner, in the name of all the natives as usual, and the captain of the steamer or the special Mamm detailed as usual every year to hand it over on h,s arrival ffie port will send to the Governor of .Teddah asking for the Mamur ot the gram *&gt;t Jeddah or a responsible official to take oyer the gram and g-y the nec^a receipt signed hv the said Mamur, that is the Mamur of the gram hi., se 1 He should make it a condition that he would (? not) accept any receipt i captain steamer or the Mamur (detailed with the grain) i • .4 - t | 4 . • r finds anything contrary to ibis arrangement he ] ( Td warn them tint he will return home with the cargo. I hereupon ''’'iH'-b: »''' 29th Shawal ldd‘3. 9th September 1915. 11 From the High Commissioner, Cairo, to the Sherif of Mecca (with titles). 1 1 ffpr of 19 th ( ? 29th) Shawal with much pleasure lhavereceived yo.il letter oy Jt H sincerity have given me the and your expressions ol frieiuinnes. greatest satisfaction. T p,i f roin mv hist letter the impression | regret that you s,un ‘ M 1|mUs an d boundaries with coldness and that 1 regarded the question . pear p ( i t o me that the moment liesitation ; such was not the ca y-.no^ protitahly discussed, had not yet arrived when the) c° l | as ! | ett( , r that you regaril this I have realized, however ^ ^ nce . 1 have, therefore, lost no (fuestion as one of vital an I o 1 Britain of the contents of your lime in informing the Governmen ot Great cii(p U) ou their letter and it is with great “X cou lident von will receive w.tk behalf the following statement, uhich I am satisfaction. . . \i PV . lll( | re tta and portions of Syria lying to The districts of Merstna and Ale • n,,,,,; anc l Aleppo cannot be the west of the districts ot I a' ■ ' ■ [ ’ ] j Crom the proposed hunts said to be purely Arab, and should he eMltut and boundaries. . i xv ;t| 10 ut prejudice to our existing With the above (hose limits and boundaries and, m treaties with Arab duels, 1rtM'anl to those portions of the territories therein in which (ireat Britain is tree to act without detriment to the interests of her Ally, 1 ranee, I am empowered in the name of the Government of Great Britain to give the following assurances and make the following reply to your letter Subject to the above modifications, Great Britain is prepared to recognize and support the independence of the Arabs within the territories included in the limits and boundaries proposed by the Sherif ol Mecca. Great Britain will guarantee the Holy Places against all external aggression and will recognize their inviolability. . When the situation admits, Great Britain will give to the Arabs her advice and will assist them to establish what may appear to be the most suitable forms of Government in those various territories. On the other hand, it is understood that the Arabs have decided to seek the advice and guidance of Great Britain only, and that such Kuropean Advisers and Officials as may be required for the formation of a sound form of administration will be British. With regard to the vilayets of Baghdad and Basra, the Arabs will recognize that the established position and interests of Great Britain necessitate special measures of administrative control in order to secure these territories from foreign aggression, to promote the welfare of the local populations and to safeguard our mutual economic interests. I am convinced that this declaration will assure you beyond all possible doubt of the sympathy of Great Britain towards the aspirations of her traditional friends the Arabs and will result in a firm and lasting alliance, the immediate results of which will be the expulsion of the Turks from the Arab countries and the freeing of the Arab peoples from the Turkish yoke which for so many years has pressed heavily upon them. 1 have confined myself in this letter to the more' vital and important questions, and if there are any other matters dealt with in your letters which I have omitted to mention, we may discuss them at some convenient date in the future. It was with very great relief and satislaetion that I heard of the safe arrival of the Holy Carpet and the accompanying offerings which, thanks to the clearness of your directions and the excellence ol your arrangements, were landed without trouble or mishap in spite of the dangers and difficulties occasioned by the present sad war- May God soon bring a lasting peace and freedom to all peoples. I am sending this letter by the hand of your trusted and excellent messenger. Sheikh Mohammed Ibn Aril Arayfan, and he will inform you of various matters of interest but of less vital importance, which 1 have not mentioned in this letter. (Here follow the usual compliments.) 24th October 1915. 12.—Communication from the Grand Sherif of Mecca to the High Commissioner, Cairo. (Literal translation.) In the name of God the Merciful the Compassionate. To His Excel lency the most exalted and eminent Minister who is endowed with the highest authority and soundness of opinion. Mav God guide him to do lbs Will. I received with great pleasure your honoured letter dated 15th Xul Uijj (24th October 1915), to which 1 beg to answer as follows (L.) 1 n order to facilitate an agreement and to render a service to Islam, and at the same time to avoid all that may cause Islam troubles and hardships seeing, moreover, that we have great consideration for the distinguished qualities and dispositions of the Government of Great Britain—we renounce our insistence on the inclusion of the vilayets of Mersina and Adana in the Arab Kingdom. But the provinces of Aleppo and Beyrout and their sea-coasts are purely Arab Provinces and there is no difference between a ■ L a Pl 11 Aral); they are botli descendants of one forefather. ( ; Alosleins will follow the footsteps of the Commander of the Faithful — &lt; Mn.u ibn Khattab and other Caliphs succeeding him, who ordained in the laws of the Moslem faith that Moslems should treat the Christians as they tieat themselves, lie, Omar, declared with reference to Christians, “they will have the same privileges and submit to the same duties as ourselves.” they will thus enjoy their civic rights in as much as it accords with the general interest of the whole nation. (_.; As the ! rovinces of Irak are parts of the pure Arab Kingdom and weie m fact the seat of its Governments in the time of Ali Ibn Abu Talib, and in the time of all Caliphs who succeeded him ; and as m them began the civilization of the Arabs, and as their towns in those provinces were the first towns built in Islam where the Arab power became so great; therefore these provinces are greatly valued by all Arabs far and near, and their traditions cannot be forgotten by them. Consequently, we cannot satisfy the Arab nations or make them submit to give up such a title to nobility. But in order to render an accord easy, and taking into consideration the assurances mentioned in the fifth article of your letter, to keep and guard our mutual interests in that country as they are one and the same, for all these reasons we might agree to leave under the British Administration for a short time those districts now occupied by the British troops, without the rights of either party being prejudiced thereby (especially those of the Arab nation, which interests are to it economic andvital) and against a suitable sum paid as compensation to the Arab kingdom for the period of occupation, in order to meet the expenses which every new kingdom is bound to support, at the same time respecting your agreements with the Sheikhs of those districts, and especially those which are essential. (3.) In your desire to hasten the movement we see not only advantages but grounds of apprehension. The first of these grounds is the fear of the blame of the Moslems of the opposite party (as lias already happened in the past) who would declare that we have revolted against Islam and ruined its forces. The second is that standing in the face of Turkey, which is supported by all the forces of Germany, we do not know what Great Britain and her Allies would do if one of t he Fntente Powers were weakened and obliged to make peace. We fear that the Arab nation will then he left alone in the face of Turkey together with her Allies, but we would not at all mind if we were to face O ' the Turks alone. Therefore it is necessary to take these points into consideration in order to avoid a peace being concluded in which the parties concerned may decide the fate of our people as if we had taken part in the war without making good our claims to official consideration. (4.) The Arab nation has a strong belief that after this war is over, the Turks under German influence will direct their efforts to provoke the Arabs and violate their rights, both material and moral, to wipe out their nobility and honour and reduce them to utter submission as they are determined to ruin them entirely. The reasons for the slowness shown in our action have already been stated. (5T When the Arabs know that the Government of Great Britain is their Allv who will not leave them to themselves at the conclusion of peace in the face of Turkey and Germany, and that she will support and will effectively defend them, then to enter the war at once will, no doubt, be in conformity with the general interest of the Arabs. (0.) Our letter dated -9th Shawal 1333 (9th September 1915) saves us the trouble of repeating our opinions as to Articles 3 and 4 of your honoured last letter regarding administration, Government advisers and officials, especially as you have declared, 0, Fxalted Minister! that you will not interfere with internal affairs. (7.) The arrival of a clear and definite answer as soon as possible, to the above proposals, is expected. We have done our utmost in making con cessions in order to come to an agreement satisfying both parties. We knowthat our lot in this war will be either a success which will guarantee to the Arabs a life becoming their past history, or destruction in the attempt to attain their objects. Had it not been for the determination which I see in the Arabs for the attainment of their objects I would have preferred to seclude myself on one of the heights of a mountain; but they, the Arabs, have insisted that I should guide the movement to this end. May God keep you safe and victorious, as we devoutly hope and desire. (Cnsigned) Dated 27 el llijj 1333. (5th November 1915.) ]3 From the High Commissioner, Cairo, to the Sherif of Mecca. The Residency, Cairo. After customary greetings and acknowledgment of previous letter. I am gratified to observe that you agree to the exclusion of the vilayets of Mersina and Adana from the boundaries of the Arab territories. I also note with great pleasure and satisfaction your assurances that the Arabs are determined to act in conformity with the precepts laid down by Omar Ibn Khattab and the darly Caliphs, which secure the rights and privileges of all religions alike. In stating that the Arabs are ready to recognise and respect all our treaties with Arab Chiefs, it is of course understood that this will apply to all territories included in the Arab Kingdom, as the Government of Great Britain cannot repudiate engagements which already exist. With regard to the vilayets of Aleppo and Beyrout, the Government of Great Britain have taken careful note of your observations, but, as the interests of our Ally France are involved, the question will require careful consideration and a further communication on the subject will be addressed to you in due course. The Government of Great Britain, as I have already informed you, are ready to give all guarantees of assistance and support within their power to the Arab Kingdom, but their interests demand, as you yourself have recognized, a friendly and stable administration in the vilayet of Baghdad, and the adequate safeguarding of these interests calls for a much 1 idler and more detailed consideration than the present situation and the urgency of these negotiations permits. We fully appreciate your desire for caution, and we have no wish to urge you to hasty action, which might jeopardise the eventual success of your projects, but in the meantime it is most essential that you should spare no effort to attach all the Arab peoples to our united cause and urge them to afford no assistance to our enemies. It is on the success of these efforts and on the more active measures which the Arabs may hereafter take in support of our cause, when the time for action comes, that the permanence and strength of our agreement must depend. Under these circumstances I am further directed by the Government of Great Britain to inform you that you may rest assured that Great Britain has no intention of concluding any peace, in terms of which the freedom of the Arab peoples from German and Turkish domination does not form an essential condition. As an earnest of our intentions and in order to aid you in your eflors in our joint cause 1 am sending by vour trustworthy messenger a sum of 20,000/. 17th December 1915. (Customary ending.) (Signed) A. H. McMahon.11 14.—Communication from the Grand Slierif of Mecca to the High Commissioner, Cairo. In the name of God, the Merciful, the Compassionate, to Mis Kxcellency the eminent, energetic and magnanimous Minister. We received from the bearer your two letters dated 9th Safar (17th December 1915) with great respect and honour, and I have understood their contents, which caused me the greatest pleasure and satisfaction as they removed that which had made me uneasy. Your honour will have realised after the arrival of Mohammed [Faroki] Sherif and his interview with you, that all our procedure up to the present, was of no personal inclination or the like, which would have been wholly unintelligible, but that everything was the result of the decisions and desires of our peoples, and that we are but transmitters and executants of such decisions and desires in the position they (our people) have pressed upon us. These truths are, in my opinion, very important, and deserve your honour’s special attention and consideration. With regard to what had been stated in your honoured communication concerning El Irak, as to the matter of compensation for the period of occupation, we, in order to strengthen the confidence of Great Britain in our attitude and in our words and actions, really and veritably, and in order to give her evidence of our certainty and assurance in trusting her glorious Government, leave the determination of the amount to the perception of her wisdom and justice. As regards the Northern Parts and their coasts, we have already stated in our previous letter what were the utmost possible modifications, and all this was only done so to fulfil those aspirations whose attainment is desired by the will of the Blessed and Supreme God. It is this same feeling and desire which impelled us to avoid what may possibly injure the alliance of Great Britain and France and the agreement made between them during the present wars and calamities; yet we find it our duty that the Eminent Minister should be sure that, at the first opportunity after this war is finished, we shall ask you (what we avert our eyes from to-day) lor what we now leave to France in Beyrout and its coasts. I do not find it necessary to draw your attention to the fact that our plan is of greater security to the interests and presumption of the rights of Great Britain, than it is to us; and will necessarily be so whatever may happen, so that Great Britain may finally see all her own peoples in that contentment and advancement which she is endeavouring to establish for them now ; especially as her allies being neighbours to us will be the germ of difficulties and discussion with which there will be no peace of mind. In addition to which the people of Beyrout will decidedly never accept such isolations and they may oblige us to undertake new measures which may exercise Great Britain, certainly not less than her present troubles, because of our belief and certaintv in the reciprocity of our interests, which is the only cause that caused us never to care to negotiate with any other Power but you. Consequently, it js impossible to allow any derogation that gives I ranee, or any other Power, a span of land in those regions. I declare this and 1 have a strong belief, which the living will inherit from the dead, in the declarations which you gave in the conclusion of your honoured letter. Therefore, the honourable and eminent Minister should believe and be sure, together with Great Britain, that we still icmain him to our resolution which Storrs learnt from us two years ago, for which we await the opportunity suitable to our situation, especially in view of that action the time of which has now come near and which destiny drives towards us with great haste and clearness, so that we and those who are of our opinion, may have reasons for such action against any cnticisms or responsibilities imposed upon us in future. 1 our expression u we do not want to push you to an\ hast^ action which might jeopardise the success of your aim does not need any moie12 explanation except what we may ask for, when necessary, such as arms, ammunition, &amp;c. , . I deem this sufficient as I have occupied much oi your honours time. I beo- to offer you mv great veneration and respect. I nsigned. Dated 2f&gt; Safar, 1334. 1st January 1010. 15.—“ Verbal ” Message. (Written unsigned.) 1 It is unworthy of the greatness of tireat britain to think that we believe false rumours ; we know her justice, See. Sec., to her people. 2. You did well in allowing M. Sherif El Faruki to remain in Egypt; do not let him leave Egypt yet. 3. Money arrived. 4. Have written to the Yemen Zaidis to leave Eahej alone ; also to Somali Mulla. 5 X 0 t one camel of ours is going ; some have been taken Jrom the Kosseim and lbn Sand’s district; Sherif might have stopped Ibn Saud, but did not, being informed that he was friend of the British. V ill stop him if desired. 6. I have warned Senussi through Idris, but he changed his mind; disapprove of his action and will squeeze his Wakil in Mecca. 10.—Private from Sherif Abdalla to Mr. Stores. My dear and beloved Mr. Storrs, My father sends you his best greet ings and 1 verily confirm the bonds of my love and old friendship towards you and assure you that I am, indeed, exerting my zeal here as much as possible, as you are doing the same theie. (Signed) A. H. Undated. 17.—Communication from Sir H. McMahon to the Grand Sherif. The Residency, (After customary greetings.) Cairo. We have received with great pleasure and satisfaction your letter of the 25th Safar (1st January) at the hands of your trusty messenger, who has also transmitted to us your verbal messages. We fully realize and entirely appreciate the motives which guide you in this important question and we know well that you are acting entirely in the interests of the Arab peoples and with no thought beyond their welfare. We take note of your remarks concerning the vilayet of Baghdad and will take the question into careful consideration when the enemy has been defeated and the time for peaceful settlements arrives. As regards the Northern parts we note with satisfaction your desire to avoid anything which might possibly injure the alliance of Great Britain and France. It is, as you know, our fixed determination that nothing shall be permitted to interfere in the slightest degree with our united prosecution of this war to a victorious conclusion. Moreover, when the victory has been won, the friendship of Great Britain and France will become yet more firm and enduring, cemented bv the blood of Englishmen and13 l^renchmen who liave died sid&lt;i hy side lighting for the Cause of Right and Liberty. In this great cause Arabia is now associated and God grant that the result of our mutual efforts and co-operation will bind us in a lasting friendship to the mutual welfare and happiness of us all! We are greatly pleased to hear of the action you are taking to win all the Arabs over to our joint cause and to dissuade them from giving any assistance to our enemies, and we leave it to your discretion to seize the most favourable moment for further and more decided measures. You will doubtless inform us by the bearer of this letter of any manner in which we can assist you and your requests will always receive our immediate consideration. You will have heard how El Saved Ahmed el Sherif el Senussi has been beguiled by evil advice into hostile action, and it will be a great grief to you to know that he has been so far forgetful of the interests of the Arabs as to throw in his lot with our enemies. Misfortune has now overtaken him and we trust that this will show him his error and lead him to peace for the sake of his poor misguided followers. We are sending this letter by the hand of your good messenger, who will also bring to you all our news. With salaams. A. H. McMahon. 2f) Rabi al Awwal. 18.—Communication from the Grand Sherif of Mecca to the High Commissioner, Cairo. In the name of the Merciful, the Compassionate, to the most noble Ifis Excellence the High Commissioner. May trod piotect him. After compliments and respects. We received your Excellency s letter dated 25 Rabi al Awwal, and its contents tilled us with the utmost pleasure and satisfaction at the attainment of the required understanding and the intimacy desired. I ask God to make easy our purposes and prosper our endeavours. Your Excellency will understand the work that is being done, and the reasons for it from the following Firstlij --We had informed your Excellency that we had sent one of oui sons to Svria to command the operations deemed necessary there. \Ve have received a detailed report from him stating that the tyrannies of the Covernment there have not left of the persons upon whom they could depend, whether of the different ranks of soldiers or of others, save only a few, and those of secondary importance; and that he is awaiting the aim a of the forces announced from different places, especially Iron, the people of the country and the surrounding Arab regions as Aleppo and the south of Mosul, whose total nuinher is calculated at not less than 10(1,UOl by the estimate ; and he intends, if the majority ol the forces mentioned a e Aial&gt; to begin the movement by them : and, if otherwise, that is of the lurks or others he will observe their advance to the canal, and u hen they begin o fiMrt, his movements upon them will be different to what they expect. _ s Secondly —We purposed sending our eldest son to Medina uitli su n iui forces to strenotl.e. his brother (who is) in Syria, and with every possib.l.ty of “cupving the railway line, or carrying out such operations as circum stances niav admit. This is the .beginning of the principal movement, and we ara satisfied in its beginning with what we had levied mi gumrls o k^ the interior of the country quiet; they are of the people oM 'jaz o • ma'Y reasons which it would take too long to set forth, chiefly 'lit difficulties in the way of providing their necessities ' v h i secrecy a„d spee^ (although this precaution was not necessary) and to nake it easy to l g reinforcements when needed; this is fl) e . ^ ^en as understand. ' In my opinion it is sidic.ent, and ' f ‘ foundation and a standard as to our actions in the lace ol ; ‘ f . unforeseen events which the sequence of events may shove. It remains lo. ns to state what we need at present.14 Firstly .—The amount of 50,000 pounds in gold for the monthly pav of the troops levied, and other things the necessity of which needs no explanation. We beg you to send it with all possible haste. Secondly. —20,000 sacks of rice, 15,000 sacks of flour, 3,000 sacks of barley, 150 sacks of coffee, 150 sacks of sugar, 5,000 rifles of the modern pattern and the necessary ammunition, and 100 boxes of the two sample cartridges (enclosed) and of Martini Henry cartridges and “ Aza,” that is of those of the rifles of the factory of St. Etienne in France for the use of those two kinds of rifles of our tribes, it would not be amiss to send 500 boxes of both kinds. Thirdly. -We think it better that the place of deposit of all these things should be Fort Sudan. Fourthly .—As the above provisions and munitions are not needed until the beginning of the movement (of which we will inform you oflieially), thev should remain at the. above place, and when we need them we will inform the Governor there of the places to which they may be conveyed and of the in termediaries who will carry orders for receiving them. Fifthly .—The money required should be sent at once to the Governor of Port Sudan, and a confidential agent will be sent by us to receive it either all at once or in two instalments, according as he is able, and this ',■) is the (secret) sign to be recognised for accepting the man. Sixthly.—Our envoy who will receive the money shall be sent to Port Sudan in three weeks time, that is to say, he will be there on the Fifth of 1 9th March. Tamad Awal 1 , with a letter from us addressed to A1 Khawaga Elias Effendi saying that he (Elias) will pay him, in accordance with the letter, the rent of our properties, and the signature will be clear in our name, but we will instruct him to ask for the Governor of the place, whom you will apprise of this person’s arrival. After perusal of letter, the money should be given to him on condition that no discussion whatever is to be made with him of any question concerning us. We beg you most emphatically not to tell him anything, keeping this affair secret, and he should be treated apparently as if he were nothing out of the way. Ect it not b&lt; th ui^ht that our appointment of another man results from lack of confidence in bearer j it is only to avoid waste of time, lor we are appointing him to a task elsewhere. At the same time we beg you not embark or send him in a steamer, or officially, the means already arranged being sufficient. Seventhly.—Our representative, bearer of the present letter, has been definitely instructed to ensure the arrival of this, and 1 think that his mission this tmm is finished since the condition of thing's is known both m general and in detail, and there is no need for sending anyone else. In case of need loi sending information, it will come from us; vet, as our next lepiesentative will reach you alter three weeks, you may prepare instruc tions for him to take back. ^ et let him be treated simply m appearance. i^igiithly. Let the British Government consider this military cxpen- dituie m ar.coidance with the books which will be furnished it, explaining Iioav the money has been spent. ! o conclude, my best and numberless salutations beyond all increase. (Unsigned.) 14 Pabi al A kliar. (18th Febrnary 191b.) 19.—On separate sheet. 1. I lie} (the lurks) order us to expedite the journev of a group of Germans to the coasts of Africa (I think the shores of the Bed Sea) and we i ep icd consenting with all readiness. We await their letter. Upon their anna ..ere we will inform you by some secret means, explaining what is necessary about their journey and its destination.15 h- * ~~ssz *• b ' * 3. They asked us to send as quickly as possible 10,000 camels for transport to arrive w.thm 4o days, and we excused ourselves. -I. It is desirable, even necessary, to exercise close vigilance upon the coasts ol \emen, beginning at Leith, because of the moTiev sent to them through our country by Haia (for they are in great need) in o'rder that they may he reduced without trouble (actual lighting). 7 y b. The matter of our personal property 1 is not of great importance to us because, as they say, there is fallen into the trap something bigger than the bird (i.e., greater things are at stake). 0. It is imperative to keep the grain, with the remainder of the provisions and mu n it ions. 1 Sherif Abdalh to Mr. Storrs. To my good and dear friend, With the fingers of jpv and exultation I received your noble letter dated 1 Ivabi al Akhar (4th February) and I cannot describe my joy thereat, as it set forth true friendship and sure affection. Verily 1 am, praise lie to . God, in good health and spirits, and as you well know of a sincere intention and transparent honesty; and my hope, God willing, is the accomplishment of meeting and converse in the very near future, and have instructed the bearer to inform you of what is necessary. God protect you. Express our best greeting to the noble Oommissioner. 1 1 Habi al Akhar 1334. Abdalla ibn Hosayn. (18th February.) -1 •—Verbal message from the Sherif Abdalla to Mr. Storrs. * I hanks and messages. My lather is following up a policy which requires time, while I work out tiie practical details by means ol a secret council of Arab notables and Islamic dignitaries, the result of which he will soon perceive. We have written certain requests, which we hope will be granted without delay or loss of time. 1 request 3,000Z. for myself. assured that • verything is going forward excellently, and success is certain. I wish to make the Bedawin work properly and this requires money. I desire speedy despatch of letter to Idrisi, the matter being important. -2.—Communication from Sir A. H. McMahon to the Grand Sherif. (After customary greetings.) We have received your letter of the 14th Uabi al Akhar (18th Febrm i ry)&gt; duly delivered by your trusted messenger. We are grateful to note the active measures which you propose to take. We consider them the most suitable in the existing circumstances, and they have the approval of His Majesty’s Government. 1 am pleased to be able to inform you that His Majesty’s Government have approved of meeting your requests, and that which you asked to be sent with all haste is being despatched with your messenger, who is also the bearer of this letter. 1 This alludes to a verbal message sent to him on the occasion of the last visit of his messenger, informing him that his personal property in Egypt was being well looked after.Tin rpinaimler will be collected as quickly as possible, and will be deposited at Port Sudan, 'of 'lle pllces' to wldcll they —Lies who will cany out the orders Hi, receiving them. { ort h in vour letter, have been issued to tK=^;;Sndan, a nd he will arrange everything in accordance with your wishes. n i . vmir i as t letter has been duly facilitated lourrepresentai ever y assistance has been given him in Ins his journey to ; le w i t h good results. lU,S \Ve n haveiauged\hat on completion, he will be brought to Port Sudan, whence he' will proceed by safest means to join you, and report the results ° f h We' V take the opportunity, in sending this letter, to explain to you a We taKe ua t , i i wn c l e ar to you, and which might matter which othervvise mi© * various Turkish posts and have given rise to misunderstanam^. xi hostile t0 „ s , and who SmaU -Tt^be'platmno nTo-y to cur‘ navk interests in the Red Sea. We are said to be Pam o ^ ^ teke host ile measures against these posts may, therefoie, hm ; ^ strict instructions that every care must T t?Ven by on. shiiis to differentiate between the hostile Turkish garrisons !md the innocent Arab inhabitants, towards whom we entertain such ^'^W^dvtymi notice of this matter in case distorted and £ 1 ^ r^orts may 'u “ of the reasons for any action which we may be obliged to take. We have heard rumours that our mutual enenues are endeavouring o ; s . r xsssz* ll,,l h. Zj “ i Ihi. and, H In Mill ^™Mf. *M d °' «•, * able to arrange for the Arabs who lie between him and Syria to seize camels as they pass-a procedure which will be to ot^ mutua aiUantag.^ 1 am glad to be able to inform you that those misguided Aia Sayed Ahmed cl Senussi, who have fallen victims to the - f T' and German intriguers, are now beginning to seethe enoi ol . . ‘'j ^ are coining in to us in large numbers, asking lor forgiveness and f 'endship. We have severely defeated the forces which these intriguers nad col ected against us, and the eyes of the Arabs are now becoming open to the ueceit which has been practised upon them. .' . . T T)1 vV« in the The capture of Rrzerum and the defeats sustained by the i 1 kh Caucasus are having a great effect in our favour, and are greath hi Ip g the cause for which we are both working. „ , i i, ivhieh We ask God to prosper your endeavours and to further the woik you have taken in hand. 1 , ne „ T1( i In conclusion, we beg you to accept our warmest saint at 10 expressions of friendship. b Jam ad Awwal l-)34. (10th March 1916.)4 U 'wl fT hts PocBicsnt is the Property of H is B ritann ic Majesty’s Government. and should be returned to the Foreign Otfice when done with qaless reqnired for official use.] svf»y v'^-****i ^ 3 ((• w4 ’ * ^ JO Files only * Cypher telegram tp Sir H.IviacMahon (Cairo). Foreign Office, April 27th 1916. 7 p.m. No.339. (D), ■fJ Your t Gleg mas Nos. 284 and 286 (of 22nd and 23rd April. Arabs). Present position is as follows His Iviajesty’s Government and French Government de cided that subject to Russian concurrence French should have absolute freedom to annex or exercise control in an area bounded by sea coast from point 15 miles north of Haifa to Cape Anamur; on west by line from Tiberias to Killis excluding Damascus, Homs, Hama, Aleppo; on south from Killis through Birijik and Amadia to Persian frontier; on north by line following ±aurus to o-uiun and Bitlis to Persian frontier. Palestine west of Jordan to be International. Haifa and Acre to be British with 15 mile hinter land and railway right through International area. Vilayets of Bagdad and Basra to oe British if His Iviajesty’s Government so desire. Remaining area within above limits to oe indepen dent Arab State bisected by line from Tiberias t hr align Basra and Verdi to Koi* Northern half to oe French sphere of economic and political interest and southern half British, Monsieur Picot then proceeded to Petrograd to negotiate with Russian Government. Sir M*Sykes went tc adviseadvise Sir G.Buchanan. RussianHinister for Foreign Affairs objected to French area as outlined. Eventually Franco-Russian difficulty was adjusted as follows British area unchanged; International area unchanged; French sphere of interest unchanged hut of French frontier area district lying between Persian/and line from Bitlis through Sert to Zakhu became Russian in exchange for similar area between Kharput, Sivas and Kaisariyeh. Only outstanding question is status of French concessions in Russian area. Russians intend to regard their area as Russian territory. Reason of these alter ations are explained in my telegram No.287 (of 14th April). French intend probably to set up Armenian state including cities of Adana, Sis Zeitun,Sivas,Kharput, Diarhekir. French additions do not include any large Ottoman population, Armenians, Kurds and Circassian settlers forming bulk of inhabitants. Moreover Sivas has always been included in Armenian reform schemes for six vilayets. | Your reference to elimination of Turkish nation, is not clear. Vilayets of Brusa, Smyrna, Angora, Konia. Kastamuni andEskeshehr are untouched by Agreements in I question. Owing to new arrangement it is believed that fundamental divergence between Arabs and French regard ing Syrian littoral may be now adjusted. RepresentativesRepresentatives of Ottoman literals and anti- Committee party are now in Paris and have approached Lis majesty's Government and doubtless also French Government, His majesty's Government consider it dangerous to have any dealings with them. They should be told that if and when they come into power they should address themselves to Russian Government upon whom Turkish Government wantonly made war by treacherous attack: but that so long as they are powerless it is useless to discuss matters. I an in forming French Government of attitude adopted by His Majesty's Government. Representatives of Maronite party in Paris are actively in touch with French Government and may be issuing pro-French propaganda in United States of America and South America wherever there are large settlements of Syrians. Monsieur Picot will not be here for ten days at least. On his arrival I will mioim you of precise position of Allies in regard to the situation.—- fc: rrhis document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty^ Government, and should be returned to the Foreign Office when done with unless required for official use.] K/ ALiENPED CO PY Decypner, POLITICA L Sir H. McMahon 4 (Cairo) April 23rd,1916 # D. 9,5.p w m # H v 10 * 40 c p .m,, April 23rd B 1916 C. 28o ( Certain peace propoeale^'ar^ coming from Turkish opposition parties inspired, it is believed*Yby party • of Princd Sabaheddin 0 Views of Colonel Sadik Bey’s party are knovm to be not irreconcilable with these of Prince r , These proposals may therefore be taken roughly to represent views of majority and most important of Turkish opposition parties. Universal increase of anti-German and anti-committee feeling-throughout Turkey (?advance) of Russians and con sequent fear of dismemberment of Ottoman Empire and particularly attitude of Arabs vis-a-vis England and Prance have undoubtedly urged Turkish opposition to action, ccnsiderably moderating their demands to Allies and attitude towards Arabs^ Terms have been submitted by Mustaffa to Sir F.Elliot (sicTM.F.A.) are as fellows: 'To make peace at once and give up Arabia.Syria and Mesopotamia, if His Majesty’s Govern ment will guarantee them their present possessions in Asia Linar.- and Europe as well as Constantinople and Straits (free4 (0 ( (free passage'). Terms given by Llvstaffa here, and which T am for warding hy ne:ct mail, excluded Turks from Europe (rexcept) Ctnsfantincple itself agreed to neutralize passage from Black Be a to iuediterranean with forts dismantled, and to an Armenia in the East under Kussian suzerainty, I have every reason to believe therefore that their views are still very elastic, I gather we are not in a position to-day entirely to ignore and eliminate Turkish nation. Nor can we prevent Turkish parties making proposals to Arabs which owing to ancient ties and common religion compete with oui present proposals to and (?relaticns) with Arabs, I feel therefore that I should at once inform you of this matter. Terms appear tc me to offer a basis for further conversations under certain circumstances but would have tc be modified as regards Constantinople in deference to Bus si an aspirations. Sivus to French as communicated by Sir M.Sykes in your makes it rather difficult. Armenia was telegram No. £37 never considered to include Sivas,I [This Bocnment is the Property of His Britan nic Ma jesty’s Government an d should be retqrned to the Foreign Office when done wit h ^ flniess r e quired for official use.J IS EGYPT EQEIILQiL Dccypher. bir II. LcMaijOa. (Cairo) April 22nd. 1^16.. D. 5.50.p«nu April 22nd.1^16. R. 10 .oO.p.ra. i'lo« . Yoor telegram No. 287 and my telegram No. 278. I confess to being somewhat-.In the dark as to how matters stand, and I am unaware whether proposals out lined by Sir M.Sykes have received the approval of three Governments concerned or whether they are merely sug gestions as a result of his and Picot’s conversations in Petrograd. Alleged understanding at petrograd appears to ignore existence of Turkey and necessity, under any circumstances of providing an adequate hone for remnants of that nation if defeated. I am telegraphing in a day or two some observations on fresh developments which indicate that Turkish parties in opposition to committee of Union and Progress are already considering .peace ..terms Which, 1a certain circum- * stances,it might suit the Allies to consider. I feel &gt;k strongly that the presence of Monsieur x J icot in Egypt at the present juncture is undesirable and would inevitably excite very considerable elements which are hostile to French penetration of Syria and which we are using our bestgI s bent endeavours to keep in a state tt quiescence. Favour at 19 developments in Caucaucus and elsewhere v/ill undoubtedly make Arab and Turkish parties more easy to deal idbn and I deprecate raising the question ot byria at present with them* At the same time a satisfactory understanding on the subject between the Allies would be all to the good, and facilitate subsequent negotiations, and I trust I may be kept informed of the various stages to which that ’under standing may arrive,rhls Do cument Is the Prop erty of His Bri tannic Majesty’s Go vernment, and should be returned to the Foreign Office when d one wi th unless re quire d for official use.] O y HU SSI A. : 1434 H POLITICO , Decypher Sir Go Buchanan (Petrograd) April 11th.1915. D* 8 c 40 p.ia. April lit a. 1916. R. 2.45 p.m. April 12th. 1916. i\ o. 518. Secret. Iviy telegram No. 471. French Amoaesador has received instructions from his Government to insist on maintenance of Russian Government's concessions and other natural advantages which they had obtained from Turkish Government in Turkish territories Rur ia may annex. Privileges of religious and educational order(s) to he waived. French Ambassador considers these instructions make it impossi ble to accept as satisfactory note drafted by Russian Minister for Foreign Affairs in concert with Mg Pi cot in which material and moral privileges enjoyed by French are not clearly kept apart. He therefore asked Minister for Foreign Affairs to take back note until a new formula could be found. While agreeing to do..so Minister for Foreign Affairs was evidently put out and inclined to resent anything which might be considered to infringe Russian sovereign rights. Partition of most of Turkish Empire which is now under discussion seems to give rise to consideration of question ofI S'?) 4 oi Tu.rkiGh debt and manner in whicli interest due on it, is to be met if this partition takes place* Would it not be well to lay down general!, principle that every Power acquiring Turkish territory must assume proportionate share of Turkish debt. M* Ficot is ill with pneumonia and will not be able to leave for two or three weeks. Please inform Sir M* Sykes. 1 y / r &amp;7 7 J^v~&gt; [ This Docnment Is the Property of Hfs Britanni c M ajesty’ s Government. and should he retu rn ed to the ywcigii- jOUlct -wh en done with m i 5 ^ unless required for official use. ! 143* WS3U~- Decypher, Sir G. Buchanan ^^ D. 8.45 p.m. April 12th,1916. R. 9.25 a.m. April 13th.1916c No* 526. Secret^., Your telegram No* 681. Mr. Lindley called the attention of Minister for Foreign Affairs again to-day to the importance attached hy His Majesty's Government to free transit. His Excellency states that he had not replied to Memo I left with him on the receipt of your telegram ale ,'3 mentioned because he coulil only give a plain ^ ha4 n8V ' principle of free trensit and Her Internal lave did not recognize it* Mr. Lindley pointed out that transit facllion.es were habitually granted by every other country and that principle had been admitted by Russia in the case of Constantinople Straits and could be perfectly well extended to other Turkish territory taken over. His Excellency din nob ^ admit analogy between territorial waters and land and sa,. that it was quite useless to press the matter. Great Britain would have plenty of ways of access to Persra^ territory without sending goods through Trehizond or Oo.mr V ,, r Pnqqia French Ambassador Turkish territory annexed by Russia. , , f anp inv telegram Noo4lo) ouo mr* was without instructions (see my ueiegiau . ^-r-er his support would induce Russian Lindley douots whsMiCr ni.s ^.p,. , . t r-r ih&amp;i ^ VlfiV’Se &amp; \ Government to aui.'-j — uftPR^te,jpfhls Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government, and should be returned to the Foreign Office when done with nnless required for official nse.] 4 . V ! 0090/16). I - PILLS ONT.Y Cypher telegram to Sir G. Buchanan (Petrograd) Foreign Office, April 13th, 1916. 7.40.p.rn, No. a04. Your telegram No. 526 (of April 12th). I consider it undesirable to press Russian Government further on this question.pT Ms Bocnmeat Is the Property .of His Br itannic Maj esty's Government, / (C / \ and should be returned to the Foreign Office when done with unless required for offic ial use.] P JL “?■’ &gt; V J FILES ONL Y. Decypr^r. Sir G. Buchnn.rn. (Petrograd) April 8 th.1916* D. ll.lb.p.m, April 8 th. 1916 r h. 10,25.a.m, April 9thJ.Vli&gt; Ac497. Mnistcr ter Foreign Attairs to whom I ccnffenicated this 'v-morning, contents cf your telogrern 738 expressed much regret and said ho would inform Chic: cf General Staff of reasons which rendered it impossible for Lis Majesty’s Government to undertake suggested expo J cion to Alexandrotta., He admitted that question ought to have been raised at Military Conference hut could not explain why tliis head not boon done adding that he really did net knew what had been discussed at that Con ference. He urged if His Majesty’s Government could do nothing at Alexandrotta,they should at 'any rate send strong reinforcement to Mesopotamia, After enforced retiiumnnt from Galipcli Great Britain could .not afford to face loss of prestige in the Last which any serious loss there would inevitably produce, were British and Russian armies to bo I driven back by Turks consequences would be far reaching, ••c should be again confronted with grave situation in Persia and in the Last generally and we should have tc abandon 1 all hope of bringing in Arabs cn cur side, I said that I believed that difficulties of transport were sc great th.it it wae almost impossible for us to keep a largo force in Mesopotamia supplied with food andnarirnittee only. Cypher tele^ran t/O Sir G.Buchaiian (Petrogrud) •. Foreign Office. April 6 th 1916. 5 p.m. No. 738. &lt;q: , &gt;—* *' ft ii »' ml tv. Your ■telegram Uo.478 reporting wlmt Minister tor Foreign Affairs has said urging despatch of British force to Alexandretta. He are raising and equipping the greatest number of men for military service that are cornpatiole with maintenance of other services on which Allies and ourselves depond as absolutely essential to the prosecution of war. YJe reserve the very minimum of military force necessary for defense of United Kingdom and India; we have a force of limited size occupied in.Mesopotamia and another not large occupied in East Africa; the whole of the rest of our army we desire to use in the way most useful to support French and Russian military operations. With this object our Highest military authorities have lately attended conference at Chantilly that disposition of British army and its action might be co-ordinated with French and Russian military plans and views. At this conference French authorities pressed foi employment of greatest possible number of British troopstroops in Prance. To meet this view and to relieve shortage of tonnage which is greatly aggravated by maintaining large oversea force at Balonica we pro posed gradual withdrawal of some British divisions at Balcnica. This was absolutely vetoed by French authorities and also by Russian Ambassador at Paris and in deference to their views we gave way and British force is retained at faionica though it adds greatly to transport difficulties everywhere and oui military authorities believe it could be more usefully employed elsewhere. During these conferences at Chantilly and Paris not one word was said by Russian representatives as to desirability of action at Alexandretta, When it was decided to abandon Gallipoli Peninsula some of our highest military authorities pressed strongly for an expedition in region of Alexandretta but in deference to French and I believe also Russian views then we agreed to send ail we could spare to Salonica. We are immensely impressed by value to us and to the common cause of Russian - operations in Asia Minor and Persia but i would nos ' strongly urge Minister for Foreign Affairs to impress on military authorities that our numbers both of men and of transports are limited and that if we are to be given a decent chance of supporting Russian operations, the Russian views must be expressed at these military conferences at Chantilly or: wherever they are held and plans must be discussed and concerted There. All cur available troops are at urgent request of FrenchFrench and Hussian representatives now ad.located to France or Balonica and transport diificulties alone Liake it absolute^ impossible now to maintain an Allied base at Salonica and at the same time to establish any new base or undertake any new operations overseas. C/ m* y Britannic M atestv’R Government, 8lIld be retnrned to the Foreign O ffica when done with anless reqntred tor official uae. ] 7' , r' J A HUbSIA. POLITIC-ALl^, Decyp^e^* Sir G* Bochaimn, (PetrOorad), April 3rd, 1916. B. 9c20 p.rn. April 3rd, 1916 # B« 9,,40 a.m. April 4 V. 1 , 191b. No. 471. ♦ Secret. yty telegrain Nc. 382, First meeting ot committee appointed to examine various points raised was held a few days ago and a hitch has occurred owing to preach claims respecting railways or in part of territory which Military iVuthcrities wish to incorporate in Russian Umpire, seme members of the commission- advocated extension of Russian seaboard as far as oinope as well as incorporation of Rowanduz district. French Ambassador and Monsieur de Sa«onow had a rather heated arnrment ©n the subject yesterday, . On question being again raised in the course of conver sation this rooming I urged on Monsieur de bagonow import ance of our being able to clinch matters with Arabs at once. I trusted that Russian Government would therefore withdraw their claim to Rowandua to which I believed Arabs attachea considerable importance aid that they would adhere to on,., line recorded in my telegram to the s.uth of which we were to be left free hand to deal with tne question of an A Empire. Other matters (1)1- omitted)told him mi 0 ht be left over for discussion but if we were to bring in / Arabs this question must le set - »:&lt;be for to giHis Excellency snid he would lay the matter again he fore committee which would meet in four of five days 1 time anci he hoped tha' to give up RdvanctCo and British Governmen t it might he possible to induce them he might hwwevcr have to ask French ts tor guarantee against infiltration of Arabs into Russian territory*Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty^ Government, and should be returned to the Foreign Office when done with nnless required for official use.^ Following from bir m. bykes for Director of Military Intalligence. I will report fully on interview with Grand Duke regarding Arab question on my return, v^ith approval of Major Marsh I asked his Highness if he would, in the event of your so desiring, assent to an Arab specialist being attached to M£jor Marsh to vassist him with intercommunication with Arab prisoners and Intelligence work in North of Meso potamia. His Highness readily concurred. I suggested that Mr. Heard of the Levant Consular Service be selected, and granted temporal military rank. If Heard unavailable Fitz Maurice might suggest suitable man: good knowledge of Arabic, acquaintance with North Mesopotamia and FINDS 01 LY. Decypher bir G. Buchanan (Petro°rad) March 31 D. 8.40 p.m. March 31st.1916. March 31st.1916. R. 11.30 a.m. April 1st.1916. If you approve, appointment shoulu be ma.de as booh as possible, but officer should not proceed to Tlflis until I have had the opportunity of explain- soon as pose If you approve,^ y his ^^MP- t . j?J he P&gt;,&lt;) PC»‘ty of His Britann ic Majesty’s Government, and should be returned to the Foreign Office when d^^Ifb’ nnless required for official use.] . FIL^S QNLY.« Decypher Sir G. Buchanan (Petrograd) * April 1st.1916. D. 9.20 p.rn. April 1st.1916. R. 11.10 a.m. April 2nd.1916. No. 461. Following from Sir M. Sykes for Director of Military Intelligence, I hope to reach London April 7th Picot April 9 th. I hope MacMahon and Clayton approve con ference with Arab unofficial representatives London suggested in my telegram No. 377. Picot anxiouty to deal with question as proposed in above telegram. .v - v : k • ■ ” ^ I ^ At ^ / .Foreign Office, March 29th, 1916. /]/ ^ I i ti'L V (W. 58401/16) ♦ secret and Immediate,. Sir o **V f 104“) With reference to previous correspondence re garding the Aral Question, I a r a directed hy Se cretary Sir Edward Hrey to transmit to you herewith, for the information of Mr. Secretary Chamberlain, a copy of a telegram from His Majesty’s Ambassador at petrograd stating that the French Government have accepted under certain reservations the me morandum of the Russian Government, the substance of which was conveyed in Sir G. Buchanan’s tele gram No. 382 of the 17th instant, a copy of which was forwarded in my letter W.51736/16 of the 20th instant. Sir E. Grey would be glad to learn whether Mr. Chamberlain would desire that Sir G. Buchanan should be instructed to formulate similar reserves when replying to the Russian Government. A similar letter has been addressed to the Board of Trade. I am, Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant, The Under Secretary of State \ or**' 3°*^ ,&gt;y for India.Mil To Preirniis Docam ent is th e Pro perty of His Bri and should be returned to the Fore unless required for ottictai tannic Majesty^ Government, Foreign Office when done with ^ iiUSS IA, EQLI1IC4L. Decypherr Sir G. Buchanan (Petrograd) March 27th,. 1916. Dr 4 r 10 r P r TA. R, 7cl5,p,.m, NO. 435. (K). Urgent. March 27th. 1916. Secret. My telegram No. 382- Monsieur informs m that the French Government accept the memorandum of Russian Government dup tnat while informing them of this he proposes to reserve a. - concessions for railway construction and other advantagee ouch as religious missions granted to the French by tiiu Turks in any territory that Russians may acquire. Monsieur P. does not include customs regime in tuet-.e reserves. I should be glad to learn whether I should address a similar reply to the Russian Government. 1. anxious to leave for London (?and) parxs.LL HQ. 't ^ ^Thts Docume nt is t he Property of His Britannic Majesty ’s Government, a nd should be retnrned to the Foreign Office when done with unless required for official nse.] 4 1 l IT JSSTA &gt; POLITICAL,- TiiADiJ ALBtPEATY - Decypherr Sir G, Buchanan (Petro^rsd)^^ 191 ^ Dr Ir^Grpcl^r f \r Or 10 r p r March 24thr 1316r NOr 410 r I/Iy telegram HOr 400r I again spoke to Minister for Foreign Affairs to day on the subject of customs, but he showed no signs of favouring the idear Monsieur Picot informed counsellor to-day that he had no instructions to press this question on the Rus sian Government, but he hoped that he might receive such instructions. It might be as weU if the French Gov ernment be requested to instruct him to support my re presentations, I fear the Russian Government will never consent to continuance of present customs regime, and we should I think concentrate on transit which I antici pate will give considerable trouble. I pres.mo question of transit to Persia is to he dealt with Inter on as you have not raised it. Pending changes in Asia Minor will make It importantrDocnment Is the Property of His Britannic Majesty*s Government, and should be returned to the Foreign Office when done with nnless required for official use.] Decypher. L&gt;ir G. Buchanan, (hetrograd) Iviarcli 24th.l916r IviiniBter for Foreign Affairs h^mcled me this morning Aide-Lemoire stating tliat while taking act of Anglo- French arrangement Russian Government must formulate certain reserves as regards extension of proposed main tenance of Turkish Customs Tariff to territories in Asia Minor which Russia annexes. Economic and commercial interest of those regions are on account of their geographical situation so closely connected with those of Russia that it would to impossible to erect Customs barriers between them. On the other hand Russia is desirous to reserve her full liberty ci action with regard to them in order to utilise better her financial resourcos after the war t trom that^in-.force in the Empire. Aide Lemcire ends, I pointed out Aide-1'iemoire said nothing about ho. 419. (K). secret. My telegram 415 0 Russian Government moreover will for political reasons be obliged to incorporate complete provinces in question in the Empire, and could net consequently cvlmi-t e stabli shrnent of ~e xc eptTorrar &lt;]ue4iaia^systrem GAfforenr, transittransit rights to which His Hrgcsty’s Go r v r crnmant atto.chod ^rc at. imscntaucc :uii .ozrprcssod the liope that His Gxcel loncy would take tiioir vjisiies on this point at any rate into tavcurahlc considoraticn. Minister for Foreign Affairs replied that this v:as a question which concerned other no inhere of the Government more directly than himself and he could net express opinion on it. On my continuing to press him he said though lie could make no promises lie would act as an intermediary and submit to his colleagues in Council of Ministers any proposals which we might make on the subject«,Immediate and Confidential. 1044 \ The Under - Secretary of State t or Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Under-Secretary of State for India, and is directed by the Secretary of State to transmit the accompanying copy of A telegram , as marked in the margin. Foreign Office, Qa iqi 6 . (Similar letter sent to 6— ; 15 a ]fThis Document is the Property of 3is Britannic Majesty’s Government, and should ba returned to the Foreign Office when done with unless re q u ired for offic ial use.] 1044 ! 1 KUSBIA POLITI CAL Decypi^r^^irG- t Buchanan, (Peferograd) Mar a a .17^ D 0 8.59 0 Pom, March 17th a 1916. R.10 B 40 v ajn, Piarch -18th^l916^ Nc. 382 a (K). Secret. % telegram Nc, 370. liinieter fer Foreign Affaire handed French Ambassador and ms this moaning foD.lowing aide-memoire and begged that proposed agreement might he kept secret Anglo-French proposals 4?tcr) reibvoiw to dom&lt;^^ ^ mission specifically appointed to exchange views., and /&gt;*- only place as regards general (?problem) 6 . l a Russian Government are ready to declare thems^^s completely disinterested m the reKi® o0at ‘ of the line Arnadie.Ibn Omaii^ia-SeffieatWefe-Adana an&amp; would accept without difficulty any angle-French arrange- ment on the s^ah^oco., 2. Russian Govevrrnent insist on the necessity for v' * r 7 rvn^ rnqqqes of the Bitlis region o^. including in Russian ^cn~ P ab ^ '■iiE'ce Urmia and propose to cede to France in exchange territory in ..l^er^^.^mcaBiv^ Kharput Cesarea.aoverment agree to any proposal which should assure to all orthodox establishments in the Holy Land free exercise o ne religion and maintenance of their acquired and privileges •— — privileges and the admission 4 0 It is they hive no otjecticn iji principle~to ot oevisn Cclcnists tc the country, understood that the hussian consent to'. the .hove menticned (?pcints) remains suhcrdinane tc 'the realization ct her agreement vath rrance and Greet Britain regarding Constantinople-and Straits,J 2 Immediate and Confidential. (IV. 3/2&amp;Cj jigib.j &lt;p£ctrf, if. r-:-' R yv&gt;- The Under - Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Under-Secretary of State for India, and is directed by the Secretary of State to transmit the accompanying copy of a telegram , as marked in the margin. Foreign Office, AlClteh Zo* igib (Similar letter sent to I 15 a ]In Any further communica tion or this subject, please quote No. W. /1916 X r 8G and address— The Under-Secretary of State Foreifinn Office, ~ London. /&lt;f C/T / 9 I: The Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents //cX direction of the Secretary his compliments to the jvf JnJtA, of State, transmits herewith copy of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, x/litltcA, /y * f igid. Letter to from Reference to previous correspondence Foreign Office: Description of Inclosure. Name and Date. Subject. € cud M. Zf* . i JlcucA Similar letter sent to •Ia Under Secret Comn Unde] Secret Prev Ar~ In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote No, W. 48551 /1916 and address— The Under-Secretory of State yA^nreiem Office, London. SECRET &amp; HIT.DIATE. The Under-Secretarv of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the UNDER SECRETARY OP STATE FOR INDIA an d, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith copies of the under-mentioned /tWPff telegrams, for any observations which Mr, Se cretary Chamberlain may have to offer. Foreign Office, March 14th , 1916 . Reference to previous correspondence: Letter to from Foreign Office: Description of Inclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Sir G. Buchanan, petrograd. No. 344 of March 10th. No. 345 of March 10th. No. 351 of March 12th. No. 357 of March 13th. QUESTION. o Sir G. Buchanan. No. 575 of March 11 th. No. 578 of March 12th. No. 580 of March 13th. (Similar letter sent to d.m.i., B-i.r-[This Docnment Is the Property of Hi s Britannic Majesty’s Boremmemt g ad shouid be returned to the F oreign Office when dii^mT unless required for official use ] r p C T i VTTQ -I f liy ouJ. POLITICAL DGcypher* Sir Gc Buchannan (Petrograd), March 10uh.1916, 8.40 pern. March 10th.1916. R c 11.35 a.rrie March 11th, 1916. No. 345. (K), My immediately preceding telegram. In a short interview which French Amtess-ador and I had with M* de Sazonow teforc presenting Monsie^ Picot and Sir Mark Sykes to him my French colleague produced map and explained general character o± oui agreement. On M. de SazonoW showing very plainly he did not like extension of blue area so far eastward French ambassador said that His Majesty 1 s Government wished these districts to he French as they wanted buffer between them and Russians and were French to give them up British would insist on having them. I protested strongly saying that thoagh v/t. hc.d spe^-al interests in those districts we had consented to meii being French in order to be agreablo to French Govern, ment and that it was absolutely untrue that we wished French to act as a buffer between us and Russia. x was as I told M. de Saaonow instructed to conduct negotiations concerning our desiderata with him and when he had discussed general line of agreement with M» Picot and Sir ^ Syhes I would ash Mm to see me ? in order that I might make our attitude perfect,., , clear to him. V 'On leaving 'tills evening I iold my French colleo^jG .10 had %0 right to speak as ho has dene and on Ms reply ing •U»-b it was the only way ty Which he could secure consent of Russian Government to that part of agyno- ment I said I could not allow him.to make his Majesty's Government hear the whole hlame for it. It would create very had Impression here were impression to gain ground that wo had pushed me French wedge between us and Russia in tin in which Russia has a direct interest. Subsequently Monsieur Pi cot ar&amp; Sir Mark a,, •&gt; interviewed U. de Sasonow alone and Sykes informs ms Picot raised question of a buffer in somewhat similar terms. Sykes took occasion to inform Ministc. Foreign Affairs that there was no question of His Majesty's Government desiring any &amp;uch arrane ^ i j v, n f* P T'0 0 d F X* uill a. G till O. that it was a question wmer „ , s fllrTV , picot then dropped the subject. Russia alCIU. e J: xt, J UjThis Document Is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government. and should be returned to the Foreign Office when Tone with unless required for official use.l ' r iJ, * PI Tan (47088/16)* POLITICAL * Cypher Telegram to Sir Buchanan (Petrograd) Foreign Oftico, {larch 11th. 1916* 9c30*p«m. No* 575r (K)c Your telegrar^ No* 345. You should tell Minister tor Foreign Affair* that there has never been the slightest intention on the part of His Majesty’s Government to interpose a better between Russia and England in districts under con sideration* My despatch Ho. 36 and my telegram No, 394 clearly indicate our views, and you should top-cKs on Minister for Foreign Affairs that we abide by om assurances then given viz: that we have no wish to prejudice Russian interests nor to urge the Russian Government to make concessions in the districts whinh are of direct interest to them it they have any cb- jection to doing so*[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Misty's Government, and ( &lt;&lt;? ^ should be returned to the Foreign Office when done with, u nless req uired or official use. ] ’ ” r “ ’ r * f.* RUSSI A- poi;r:i3AL r (47032/16). Cypher T 3 le~rmn to Sir 0. [Buchanan (Petrogrod) foreign Office, iarch 12th. 1916. B.SO.p.w. v. ; or 570, (K) Your telegraw r,o. 344 (of 10th. .ore;.). Clause Mentioned should he substituted as you surest, ( 2 n^ ox K), 3. According to actual wording approved by v , ord&lt;? »-,y r rail' should be inserted after Committee, uoi^s jj ia - second Mention of liaiffa. (2nd of D).gJSBIA POLITIC AL, L Decypher. Sir. JO. Buchaman (petrograd). March 12th.1916. D. 11.15 p*nu March 12th. 1916. p. 11.55 a.m. March 13th.l916. No. 351. My telegram No. 345. in a conversation which I and Sir M. Bytes had with Minister for Foreign. Affairs yesterday afternoon I explained the attitude of His Majesty's Government with regard to provision cfnAnglo-French agreement in * terms of your despatch No. 56 and made it clear to His Excellency that what French Ambassador had said of our desire to create French buffer zone between us and Russia was entirely unfounded. I also i^ad His Excellency^ Cairo telegram No. xoZ in order show urgency of our coming to an understanding with \ --p p cri^oGiYiGn t/ that affects regard to that por-oion of agieenunv ^ a.j rr , Tri conversation wnich question of Arab co-operation. In ^ • rr 'r j 'iw Wench Amhassao.oi when ho had had in the morning wivh Fiencn ^ . p Y r G ii oncy had raised strong oj~ I was present his Lxcoi-oau/ • of •r’Iiug area so far Easo and Sections to extension - - was such a large one that- had said that the question • ial h0 0 „ u3 , ;-- ovor p al „ -u M council consist 6 of tno couensus and of of ropros-ntauioES der gave General examine it. In cider t Chl0f ° f ^ 4 “ u „o S t to His Excellency Huscisn ! time I v/ou-d &amp; bo QovcrnmentGovcrnmont should roservo for further discussion all those points in the agreement to wnich it Cook ex ception end express its acquiescence in the rest. His Excellency had also told French Ambassador that all that he cared about in Palestine was internationalis ation of the Holy Places and had told him that France might do as she liked with the rest. This as Sir it. Sykes would explain to him was not at all our view, p. de Sazonow replied that he had only been speaking for Bussia and that of coarse assent of all interested . T , + .,,.o P ^ to sui?h aii arrangement, would have to he ohWneu such irwr of the desideraua he personally saw no objection to of Kis iSij'sty's Government. i\u do saaonow* o con• , • Dc^nger which aroceoauo versa tion „Va Kronen ^aosMor v,ao » «nao — naras ^ a -fnr surrender of Baklan njiu by way of compensa.iu. - ‘ ^geq^ently made Eastern Kurdcstan. H. do sasonov lessen 1 f ' ' ' 1r1 ■ r to keep Turkey as suser- 1 . That ho would pref-r ain of Armenia. ia t0 be annexed to 2 . That he did not w^n *rm,n *i i 4.4 pp i r eaBons - Russia tor po— • co uld not be evacuated r? 'TViLit fir'^eroum 3 * ' h roV rimc nt desired to take as li-le ^ the-t Russia Gov.r.-. mc . territory host of Erzcr ^ ^ Franc0 might be compen- » - ~ B “ e r • o 10 ^'^ J - • sir M sated for area to th^. 0 XObiD w»- r- .. y * v-^ach. ^ request Sir n North oi ^a.n. sylc0Sasm*3 hcuM t&gt;e autborized to do so instead of leaving negot iations in the hands of Monsieur Pi cot. Monsieur Ed cot has a thorough knowledge of the question end is very accomodating so matters are not likely to ho facilitated hy such an arrangement. French Ambassador also remarked that his Majesuy^ Government apparently did not,like French Government, regard(ing) Agreement as definite and final hut rather as a provisional one and expressed some surprise at my not supporting French claims in their entirety. I replied that while 1 was ready to use my good o^fice^ to obtain arrangement satisfactory both to Russia and France I was precluded hy ay instructions from ins^ ing on Russian Government making concessions in dis tricts in which they were directly interested if they did not wish to do so- „ IS all ® for “ “ ' tr , i -a--ase fold 1'/ mned imMssador as report after the language nexa ./ ^ h rrsti pc. were I to supperu Frencn in my telegram 10 . ' 1 ^ think French extreme claims M* do 8,-- ^ ^ to us • Amhassador was ^.rdestan to the wish to give Kakxia^ FrancotP' 4,1 ^^Documenn^ttie Pro perty o f Hi s Britannic Majesty’s Gover nment Q^j and shouid bo retained to the Foreign Offlce~^hen d on ft with nnless required for official nse.1 ‘ r~ i &gt; U ■» J ’ BOUMArl l A IGLITICAL Cypher tolegram to Sir Buchannan (Bucharest)* Foreign Ofiice, March 13th*1916. 12.5 p.m. No. 580* Ivij’ telegram to you Mo. b'lf. (of 11th March). You may also toll Minister for Foreign Affairs that idea of claiming those districts for ourselves has never teen contemplated ty us as French Ambassador suggested. ;Th . &amp; X4 r -£This Documen t is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government. and should be returned to the Foreign Offtce when done with unless required for official use.] POLITICAL Decypher. Sir G. Buchanan. (Petrcgrad) D. 8.45.p.m. Larch 13th,1916, K. 9.2G.a.m. March 14th.1916. No. 357. (K). Ycur telerrain lie. 575. Minieter for Foreign Affairs thoroughly understands situation and is quite un-influencedd by French Amtossa&amp;cr.jThis Document is the Property of His Britannic MarestVs Government.1 -P? luted fov the use of the Cabinet. Fcbvucivy 1916. r CONFIDENTIAL. r ARAB QUESTION. IX fv, V7 ^ -vi Sir E. Grey, I SUBMIT for the consideration of His Majesty’s Government the results of the informal discussions which have taken place with M. Picot and after consultation with the competent Government Departments. It was found at the outset impossible to discuss the northern limits of the future Arab State or Arab Confederation unless the French desiderata in Syria were also examined, as M. Picot was unable to separate the two questions. I think, however, that the preamble to the proposals lays down with sufficient precision the fact that the proposals in regard to the Blue area, as well as to the Red area, are contingent on the fulfilment of certain essential conditions, and give full opportunity to the Allies, and especially to Russia, to have a voice in the final settlement of those parts of the whole problem. The four towns of Homs, Hama, Aleppo, and Damascus will be included in the Arab State or Confederation, though in the area where the French will have priority of enterprise, dm. You will see from Sir H. McMahon’s telegram No. 707 of the 20th November, 1915, annexed herewith, that it had been contemplated that this sphere would be reserved to the development of special French interests. There is one point which doubtless requires explanation, and that is the reference to Cvprus. The French consider that in according to us the ports of Haifa and Acre they are giving away “ acquired rights,” which had been granted to them unoer t e French loan to Turkey of 1914, and that they must have, therefore, an equivalent. It also appeared during conversation that they feared that the cession of Cyprus to Greece might be revived on some subsequent occasion, and that Greece might afterwards transfer the island to Italy. M. Picot, therefore, insisted on some guarantee against Cyprus being disposed of without the previous knowledge and ^concurrence of 1 ranee It is possible, as M. Pieot has been intoned, that ftsMa^s view such an engagement with favour, though AI. regard this question as an essential condition. Foreign Office, February 2, 1916. A. N. Sir H. McMahon to Sir Edward Grey.— {Received November 2t.) fo. 707.) Cairo, November 20,1915. ^^FOLLOWING from Sir AI. Sykes for D.M.O, No. 19 “ Your private letter of 5th November just receweffi vfe^ Following is best iticipating French difficulty, discussed t e si ua i reC rard to France and Great Britain, could get: but seems to me to meet the situation ^h rabs would agree to accept as approximate northc Prance granting her monopoly of hdiat-Zakho-Kowanduz. Arabs would d as-l^uded by Euphrates as .1 concessionary enterprise in Syria and Palestine S&gt;m bem to Maan . ,r south as Deir Zor, and from there to Deraa a ‘ o ^ concess ioimaire. Arabs would “ Hedjaz Railway as far south as ^ 1 ^ as ach isers and European employees m tins Whh reganl q—- erritory north of Greater A ^ bia ' ^'‘^nLliivat^lands to the south being British territory. [&lt; Arabs would agree to Basra t0 1 wit h Entente Powers— “ Arabs would be prepared to ma . i-pv Germany or Austria for period ' p.,, ' [0 ,01o Li SECRE „ Flirthcr a treaty of alliance with Entente Powers giving them freedom of movement in Greater Arabia and use of railways in Arabian area .or duration ol .e war. troops i u Atal territories to be on same footing as 1 n is i i00 ^ ■ j hostilities .. Entente trooos to evacuate territories on cessation ot nostiuues. “ Farukfinsisted that this was dependent on AW«ite landing troops at a point between Mer^ and Alexandretta, and making good Amanus lass or Ulieian Cxates. He tuither stipulated tin Sl ereef should not take action until this had been done. I agree that any other course is out of «,« question and that to call on Shereef or Arabs to take action until we had made above-mentioned pass, securV would be impossible. Faruki also urged necessity for immediate adequate action in the Gal, of Alexandretta, adding that if Kntente did not take his opportunity Hermans would ores.ail il len , ui Ai.ioA.ctuu &gt; &amp; . . - a t-qK a wnnli ui their own interests, be oh iPfid tr. iat it unteme aiu nuu j — coiitu tnein, and’ once Turks or Germans got into Syria. Arabs would, in their own luterests, be omiged to recoils*, situation. For my own part. I am sure that there can be no doubt ] ot Arabs merely troubling I mls situation, lor my own part, i am suie wiau ™ ... ., ... ^ J in advances on the Canal If we allow Turks into Syria, Arabs will side with them in order to obtain special consideration “ Germans have already suggested idea of Turko-Arabia on the same lines as Austria-Hungary. “ I will give observations on less important aspects in further telegram. Meanwhile, 1 a convinced of necessity for efficient action at earliest possible moment, to enable Arabs to move.” am 0^ creatior submit! convers departn It success State o Britain It satisfac France accomp Great I which r Empire 1. iudeper marked France, local lo; adviser; Arab Si 2 . allowed and as States. • &gt; o. tion, th subseq Shereei 4, of a gi His Ma negotia consem 5. Empire regards British those g and tin railway T1 and p i’acilith transit area, aa urea (l goods &lt; mentic 0. Mosul, with 1 concurL -L^- Jucument is me Pioperty ol His Britajinic Majesty s Govenimerit I SECRET. ln Greater )S in Arab sn Mersina( Jluted tha' out of tiie oned passes m the Gulf isiall them, Reconsider J ling Turks r to obtain Jungary. hilt- 1 , 1 am tove.” 9^ Tli6 hypotliosis tliat l rcinc6 aDcl Cxreat Britain are desirous of assisting in the creation of an Aiab State or C onfederation of Aral) States, the following proposals are submitted for the consideration of the British and Trench Governments, after conversations with M. Georges Ihcot and after consultations between the competent departments of His Majesty’s Government. It is understood that the putting into effect of these proposals is contingent on the $ successful assistance of the Arabs and their leaders in the establishment of an Arab State or Confederation of Arab States under the protection of Trance and Great Britain ; and on their active co-operation with the Allies. It is further understood that if the negotiations with the Arabs lead to a satisfactory result, the proposals respecting the special interests and desiderata of France and Great Britain respectively in the portions marked in blue and red on the accompanying map are contingent on the consent of the Russian Government, which Great Britain and France will endeavour to obtain, and dependent on the arrangements which may be made in the peace negotiations respecting the future of the Ottoman Empire. 1. That France and Great Britain are prepared to recognise and protect an independent Arab State or a Confederation of Arab States in the areas (a) and (b) marked on the annexed map, under the suzerainty of an Arab chief. That in area (a) France, and in area (b) Great Britain, shall have priority of right of enterprise and local loans. That in area (a) France, and in area (b) Great Britain, shall alone supply advisers or foreign functionaries at the request of the Arab State or Confedeiation of Arab States. -n • • i n i 2. That in the Blue area France, and in the Red area Great Britain, siia.i be allowed to establish such direct or indirect administration or control as they desire and as they may think lit to arrange with the Arab State or Confederation of ^ la &gt; States. in the ] 3 rown area there shall be established an international ad mi mstra- tion, the form of which is to be decided upon after consultation ^ subsequently in consultation with the other Allies, and the tept ' Shereef of Mecca. ^ ^ accorded (1) the t f Haifa and Acre ^guarantee of a given supply of water from the Tigris and Euphrates m ^ (“Ujuto His Majesty’s Government on their part undemkeAattl^ll^^ ^ negotiations for the cession of Cypius to any consent of the French Government. , f tl r itis i, 5. That Alexandria shall be a free port as regards iluics as Empire, and that there shall be no “ ^AhaU be fiidom of transit for regards British shipping and British goo », ia , . t | |e ];] lie area, whether British goods through Alexandretta an _ ‘ V pLa irea &amp; or (B) area, or area (A) ; those goods are intended for or originate m t , 4 ^ j st British goods on any and there shall be no discnimnation d.rec areas mentioned. against British goods oi ships a. an} p t J e o 0 f France, her dominions Haifa shall be a free port as regards he ade of pane or railway or and th^rT AS^ereT^ Heedom of facilities as regards French sh.ppnig and T mn ' d^ ^ through the Brown ’whether those goods are intended ^ on f!^ or ‘indirect, ‘against French ^rSy^gtsAtTgoodB or ships at any port serving the areas and there shall :s as regards French shipping am. rai ] wa y throng transit for French goods through Ha^andp^ in Ae Blue area, area (a) or area, whether area goods on any — „. _ mentioned. n i r) 0 ii, vnv qhall not be extended southwards be\on( 6. That in area (A) the Bagdad hr ‘ ' ‘ ‘ imt il a railway connecting Bagdad Mosul, and in area (B) nortpvpds beyond Samarp nn ^ then only wlth the with Aleppo via the Euphrates ' alley has been i concurrence of the two Governmen s. [232—1]2 ^ • • loo nVlit to build, administer, and be sole owner of a 7. That Great ^ n . ta111 area rp\ an d that Great Britain shall have a perpetual railway connecting m a i i ^ne at all times. right to transport troops along existing Turkish customs tariff shall remain 8. For a period ol } 1 tlie an d Red areas, as well as in areas in force throughout the ^ conversion from ad valorem to specific and (B), and no increase ^ 1)e ( ween the two Powers. rates shall be made [ l customs barriers between any of the above-mentioned There shall be no , • . j on goods destined for the interior shall be Xted tt the‘port oV'eutry, and handed over to the administration of the area oi ''hall be agreed that ^ tZ negotiations ior the cessi the° Arab State or Confederation of Arab States, area to any third lo ’ P f His Majesty’s Government, who on their part will without the P rev Xhwrrhe French Govehment regarding the Red area. glV6 iV'ThrBddsh and French Governments, as the protectors of the Arab State, .ball iree that they will not themselves acquire, and will not consent to a third Power hoCeTlalTnoTprJvent such adjustment of the Aden frontier as may be necessary 10 CO n Se k n hrn\godrtmns witteSa''to the boundaries of the Arab State or Confederation of Arab States shall be continued through the same channel as heretofore on behalf^of die tw^ measure s to control the importation of arms into the Arab territories wiU be considered by the two Governments.i airrainition together with 1100 fcoxea of amuaition for hie existing rifles. He says that supplies and munruiont, are not irsnediately needed hut should he stored at Port Sudan, until required 'by dim. Sdsrif f 1 s letter wdicn v^as written 'before fall ^ Erzerum was known indicates an important step in Arah movement against Turks. Although danger of serious attack on Canal is growing less, strength of our defending force ^ n0 -’ Men very much reduced end sympathy and co-epemticn of ffi.aba appears no lees desirahle to la# «» - d j. mvr VD of great value with while _o may ^ uj- e , , communications with Mesopotamia and operations country. I strongly urge that wa should b - assistance he retires and in fnis military here concur i GOnOUl a \ + p 1 £ r~ *t + nr ^50 COO sanctioned m y^u t-ic I may note that of,~oJ ( W “ n-n n&gt;%rj ooo is 6-414and t • gl ’ am 110 * 8 . ’ 20 coo is needed. I also recount sanction for on y 5 sonihdalla who asks for it grant of £3000 to Snerifu f on 6 ood erounds. ( ^ olll M about UO.OOO. Cost of suppll o 1 4 ., d ATI if sanction'. + a ruouIV rifles and amtuni 4 ~i,n Question how to suppi-Y , • - requires consideration, t tc India No. 1^' Addressed to Foreign OtfiP- _ ‘Decypheri sir g. Eucnanan (pefa-b;-.-fa ••’Oruary 28tli, D e 9.30 p.m. February 28tb,39^6. R. 11.25 a.m. February 29th 5 1913. No. 308. Your telegram No. 468. Minister for Foreign Affairs begs me to thank you for your message and to say it will give him the greatest pleasure to receive Sir M. Sykes.jT^Docn^ygJhe Property of His Britann ic Majesty's Government ang shoutd be returned to the Foreign Office when done with unless required for official nse.l X*'- BUSSIA t POLIT ICAL ,. (33028/16).. Cypher TelegrarA to Sir G&gt; Buchanan (patrograd) Foreign Office, February 23rd. 1916. 8.0.p.r,i. NOr 468;» Sc CI’G 0 o Your telegram Me- 278 (of 19th., February) I am ranch cbD.iged for Kindly forethought o Minister for Foreign Affairs but nevertheless I think it desirable that he should be in possession of all Phat has passed and have explanations given w nun. , + ■ DctrnPTad in a few days and Mark Sykes will proceed to Peoro„iad un ^ *1 in coOTunicafion with will at once place himseii m uui L Excellency,PU3SIA POLITICAL. Decypher Sir G-. Buchanari (Petrograd)» February 19th, D. 9. 50 pm February 19th, R. 10 am February 20th. No. 278t Ipy telearara No. 237. French Amba^^ador read Minister for Foreign Affairs this morning telegram from his Government announcing approaching visit of Monsieur Pucot and 3ir Ma.rk Sykes to comnTunicate agreement arrived at between us and French Government respecting projected creation of Arabian Empire. Minister for Foreign Affairs said that it would give him nnch pleaemio to receive these gentle men but if it was only question of securing his approval to this agreement that approval was already secured to us before hand. From what Hi* Excellency said my French Colleague and I gathered he did not wish to put our Governments to unnecessary expenditure of ending c.\u Missio- -Oi what wa°- an exchange of noocs.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000419.0x0001a5_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/10/526</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000419.0x0001a5</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/10/526</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>File 53/1915 Pt 5 'German War: Turkey; Arab Kingdom; the Petrograd negotiations'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1916/1918</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-01-18T11:19:36</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">fre</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (214 folios)</extent><extent>The subject 55 (German War) consists of 5 volumes, IOR/L/PS/10/524-527. The volumes are divided into 5 parts with parts 1 and 2 comprising one volume each, parts 3 and 4 comprising the third volume and parts 5 and 6 comprising one volume each.The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence for this description commences at the inside front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 216; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. A previous foliation sequence, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The volume comprises telegrams, despatches, correspondence, memoranda, and notes relating to the discussions (Petrograd negotiations) between Britain, France and Russia over the creation of an Arab Kingdom and associated zones of British, French and Russian influence in the event of the defeat of the Ottoman Empire.The volume includes (ff 51-59) a 'Note on the Anglo-French-Russian Agreement About The Near East' as well as three maps (folios 65, 122 and 205) accompanying correspondence about the extent of an Arab kingdom and associated spheres of influence.The principal correspondents in the volume include: the French Ambassador to Britain (Pierre Paul Cambon), Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, Sir Edward Grey; the Russian Minister of Foreign Affairs, (Sergei Dmitrievich Sazonoff); the French Ambassador to Russia, (Maurice Paleologue); ʿAbdullāh bin Ḥusayn al-Hāshimī; and Ḥusayn bin ‘Alī al-Hāshimī.The volume includes a divider which gives the subject and part numbers, year the subject file was opened, subject heading, and list of correspondence references contained in that part by year. This is placed at the back of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><geographic>Lebanon</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Insurrections</topic></subject><subject><topic>First World War campaigns</topic></subject><subject><topic>International conflicts</topic></subject><subject><topic>Maps</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Viceroy and Governor-General of India in Council</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>High Commissioner, Egypt</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Grand Sharif of Mecca</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="personal"><namePart>Sir 6th Baronet Mark Sykes</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="personal"><namePart>King of Jordan ʿAbdullāh I</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Arabian Peninsula</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Turkey</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Middle East</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Syria</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Iraq</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Muslims</topic></subject><subject><topic>Rebellions</topic></subject><subject><topic>Diplomacy</topic></subject><subject><topic>Boundaries</topic></subject><subject><topic>First World War (1914-1918)</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000419.0x0001a5#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>