<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x0000f5_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-18T02:52:03.377Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">/ The Political Agent, Bahrein# Memorandum. In his memorandum Ho.P* A/5/39235, dated the 2otli oune 1926 to this Office, the Controller of Military Accounts, northern Command and Rawalpindi District, Rawal pindi, asked whether an Indian Unitary Pensioner could be paid his pension at Bahrein, and in reply was informed that as the Political Agent, Bahrein, is under the Govern ment ot India and submits his accounts to the Accountant General, central Revenues, B e lhi, the pension could be paid at Bahrein by the Political Agent. The Controller of Military Accounts was, however, advised to refer the matter to the Accountant General, Central Revenues, which he did, and received a reply from the latter that there was no objection to the payment of the pension to the Indian Military Pensioner by the Political Agent, Bahrein, in accordance with the procedure laid down in Article 483 Civil Accounts C 0 de, volume II. unaer his letter Ho.P. A/5/97984, dated the 22nd September The Controller of Military Accounts Rawal pindi has now forwarded bhe descriptive roll of the pensioner 1920 ’ a c °Py of which letter with the descriptive roll in original I enclose for favour of disposal. By order Mi-Copy of letter No.P. A/5/97984, dated the 22nd September 1926, from the Ny # Agsistant Controller of Military Accounts, Northern Command and Rawalpindi District, Rawalpindi to the H 0 n’ble the Political Resident in the Persian C u if. Regarding transfer of pension of pensioner Bahadur Khanty With reference to your memorandum No* 1737 of 26 dated the 10th July 1926 I have the honour to forward here with the descriptive Roll of pensioner Bahadur Nhan No, 11896/12914 with a veiw to arrangements being made for the payment of his pension of its ,9/- per mensem with effect from the ley January 1926, at Bahrein a seaport in Persian B^lf, He has been paid in this District at Jhelum Post Office up to and for the 31st December 1925 as noted on page 4 of his Descriptive Roll, The amount paid to the pensioner on account of his pension should be debited to this office through the Accountant General Central Revenues, D e lhi, OoPy for information with reference to his letter No .P.N. 1269 /B.P.N, 17-26-27 dated the 26th August 1926 to the Accountant General Central Revenues, Delhi.No /ie/13 of 1020. The Political Agency, Bahrein Dated the 10th October 1920. To The Secretary to The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Menorandun . Please refer to your nenorandun No.2372 dated the 4th October 1920 forwarding the descriptive roll of pensioner Bahadur Khan. P•A./5/07984 dated the 22nd September 1920 from the Deouty Assistant Controller of \filitary Account*, Northern Command and Rawalpindi District, it is stated that the pensioner has been paid up to and inoludinfr 31st December 1925. The pensioner states that he has received payment up to and for 31st December 1924 only. This statement is confirmed by the production of the payment sheet in possession of the pensioner. It is probable, therefore, that a clerical error has beerj made in the descriptive roll. for transmission to the Controller of Military Accounts, Northern Command and Rawalpindi District for further enquiry and correction if necessary. In the descriptive roll and in letter No I am, M li i ufTTrt, returning herewith the roll Political Agent,Bahrein4 © No . Of 10 ^ . Britisn Kosidenoy &amp; Consulate u-eneral, Bu shire, ohe December . me Political Agent, BAHREIN. Memorandum A copy Ox letter No. PA/o/l24356&gt; dated uhe 2e&gt; ^h November 192^ &gt; from tne Controller of Military Accounts, Rawalpindi, tOgetaier with t^e descriptive roll, in original, of pensioner Nadir Kuan, is forwarded xxorevvitu for disposal. Please acknowledge receipt. B.y order. Captain, Secretary to the Political Resident in tne Persian crulf. I &gt;•i r No.PA/5/124355 Office of the Controller of Military Accounts Northern Command and Rawalpindi District. Rawalpindi , Dated 26th November 1926. fhe Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Dus hi re. Subject:- Transfer of pension papers of N a dir Khan. Dir, 1 have the honour to forward herewith the D e scriptive Roll of pensioner Nadir Khan N 0 .15056/3479, with a view to arrangements being made for the payment of his pension at Rs. 9 /- p.m. with effect from the 1 st S e ptember 1925 at Bahrein, a Seaport in Persian Gulf. 2. No payment has been made to him in this District as noted on page 4 of his roll. 3. -i-he amount paid to the pensioner on account of his pension should, please, be debited to this office, through the Accountant Dgnerai^ Central N e y e nues, D e lhi, quoting No.15056/3479, on the voucher, and the 1 st charge should be supported by the pensioner 3 Bast P^y Certificate which will be in his possession. 4. Hi s application requesting for the transfer of his pension is herewith enclosed. 5. Please acknowledge receipt. 1 have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Sd. Bhagat Ram. s Dy. Asstt. Controller of Military Account Northern Command &amp; Rawalpindi District. Copy forwarded to the Accountant General, Delhi, for information. Central Revenues,- -V (D No. X~ I J) of 19 . British Residency &amp; Consulate General, Bushire, the £] December i920« To The Political Agent, BAHREIN. Memorandum ... / Reference your memorandum No. 9b9/ifl/iS, dated the 10 th October 1920. Descriptive Roll of Pensioner Dafadar Bahadur Khan is returned herev/ith, the necessary correction having bean made on page 4 in respect of the date up to VThich the pensioner was last paid. By order. Captain, secretary 'Ihe Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. M.W.A.No. II /Wl* of The Political Arency, Bahrein Dated the 6th January 1021^7 To The Secretary to The Hon*hie the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bu.ihire, Nenorandun . I acknowledge receipt of copy of letter No. P.A• A&gt;/l24S55 dated the 86th November l n 26, from the Controller of Military Accounts, Rawalpindi together with the descriptive roll, in original, of Pensioner Nadir Khan forwarded with your memorandum No.2040 dated the 16th December 1026. Political Agent, BahreinNo /l'?/].* of IPg? To The Political Arency# Bahrein. Da f e^l the 15th January 1027. The secretary to The Hon*hie the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire . Meaoranduo . Reference correspondence ending with your nenorandun No.2015 dated the Oth December 10gi. As I have no copy of the Civil Account Code Vol.II» will you kindly send me a copy of Ar f icle 485» in accordance with which payment of pension is to be made? Will you also^send me pension payment forms if there are any srecial ones? a trj Political Agent, Bahrein.Civil Aooouj’ta code, volume n. Payments to Pensioners-, eto. Article.485. Payments to Indian Military Pensioners, when made throuph the Civil Department, are made as follows:- (1) 3y the Treasury Officer m ho will be furnished direct by the Officer Commanding the man's uhit with the descriptive roll ( I.A.F.A.339) of the pensioner, on receipt of which he will enter the necessary particulars in aoheck register and will retain this document as ling as the pensloner remains on his payment. On transfer of the pensioner to the payment of an other Treasury within the audit area of the same Controller of Military Accounts, the Treasury Officer will after completing the ' Particulars of transfer' on page 4, forward the descriptive roll (l.A.F.A.SfiO) direct to the Treasury Officer to whose payment the pensioner has been transferred. But if the transfer is to another audit area of the Military Accounts Department, the descriptive roll will be sent through the Controller of Military Accounts of the old District for transmission to the Treasury Officer concerned through the controller of Military Accounts of the new district. The pensioner will be furnished direct by the Controller of Military Accounts concerned with a pension certificate (I.A. F•A. 573 ) and a last pay certificate (I.A.F.A. 447 ) by the Officer Commanding his unit. The pension certificate(I.A.F.A. 378) is the personal property of the pensioner and must be produced by him on each occasion of drawing pension, when he Presents himself for the first time to draw his pension, the Pensioner will hand over the last pay oertifioate( 1 .a.F.A. 447) to the Tresury Officer which the latter will forward to C.nt.oiler of Military Accounts, in support of the first payment made to the pensioner. On transfer of a pensioner to th9 Payre,!t ° f aROthSr Pages 3 and 4 of his pension oertificate(!. a*F.A. 573) will be completed by the Tresury Officer.~ 2 — Note ^ 1. Irifllan Military penaionera, who are resident in the town of Madras, Banralore Cantohment# Secunderabad and Bolarum are paid by the respective Pension Paymaster^, Note.2. Further detailed instructions are jriven by the Accountant General in respect of these payments. Note.?. Head Tresury Officers are authorised fcxxr to renew Pensft&amp;vcertificates without referehce to the Controller of Military Accounts concerned, in cases in which the Pensioner’s certificate is lost, destroyed or used up. The renewed pension certificate should bear the old number and date and the old ones (if available) should be retained by the treasury Officer for one year and then destroyed. ( 2 ) Indian Military pensioners are also paid by Military Officers, Political A rents and by the Post Office under departmental rules.► V ¥ L nt 2 ^ssr- // (* No. I of 1927 . British Residency A Consulate General, Bushire, the February 1527* To The Political Agent, BAHREIN* Uemoranduia Reference your memorandum No, kj,/l6/lj&gt;, dated the 15 th January 1927« A copy of the Civil Account Code vclunie II, is forwarded to you b&gt; Registered Book Post for reference and return. There are no special pension payment forms for the purpose, and the payment should be made on an ordinary receipt stating the month or months for which the pension is paid. The charge should be debited to the Controller of Military Accounts, Northern Command and Rawalpindi District,, Rawalpindi, and a note made to that effect on that receipt. 'm 4* By order. Captain, I M.W.A o the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf,MO. /&lt;?3 /ip/ is Of 1027• The Political Agency, Bahrein. Dated the 9th February 1927. To The Secretary to The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. L'enorandun. Reference your nenorandun No.2B9 dated the Sth February 19£7 # the I return herewith, ^oopy of the Civil Account Code volune II forwarded therewith. The direction made in the’'' last para of your nenorandun is noted. Please acknowledge receirt. a /ii? Political Agent, Bahrein,l ■ No .A .3 .213 of 1927 British Residency &amp; Consulate-General, Bushire,the 22 nd February 1927. To The Political Agent, Bahrein. Memorandum. The copy of the Civil Account Code Volume II returned by you as advised in your Memorandum No,103/lB/l3 dated the 9 th February 1927 has been duly received.Petition dated the 12th April 1930, from No.2268 Pensioner Kavaldar Bahadur Khan 28th Light Oavalry, home address P.0. Saloi. Tahsil Pindadankhan, District Jhelum, to the Political Agent, Bahrain. kkE I beg to state that the period of my agreement of service in the Bahrain State Police has expired and I have to proceed to my home in India whence I am not likely to return to Bahrain. I therefore request that my pension papers may kindly be transferred to Post Office Saloi in the Jhelum District.Telegram Frorr To No. I.W. Code, Political Barein, Political T/uacat. 665. Bated the 15th April 1930. HawaldarBahadur Khan late of 28th Cavalxy known to ^uhedar Vajor Fateh Khan of yuacat Levies is kaaiss leavijig Bahrein police toda^ on terrrination of contract. He bears good cl^racter and is good instructor . As I believe Vuscat Levies want rore ren, perhaps Comrv'andant rrQtf care to see hir on this down rail with view to engageirent. He is available irrediately. Political.Ho. ~JOb Of 1930. Tho i/oliticuL Ag0aO7| Bahrain# Dried the^^^^ipril 1930. Prom Ca iain 0.G-.Prior, I*A., Political Agent, Bciirain. To The Deputy Commissioner, Jhelum. Gir, I have the honour to forward herewith the Descriptive Roll of the Pensioner Havaldar Bahadur Kiirn 10.3368 of Both Light Cavalry, duly completed, for favour of disposal. Kindly acknowledge receipt. The Pensioner now wishes to draw his pension at his native place, ^ost Office Saloi, Tahsil Pindadankhan, District Jhelum. He was employed in the State Police at Bahrain and the period of his agreement having expired, ho proceeded to India hy the slow nail of the 113th April 1930. I have the honour to he, Sir, Your most obedient servant. Political Agent, BahrainI 1 V WS 9 y I Office of the Acconntant-General, Central Revenues. Telegraphic Address : Accounts, India. All communications to be addressed to the Accountant- General, Central Revenues. iI/'H IMP Vn /i ° .fWERlAI. SECREYaR IAT BUILDINGS.^ t \ -- t, Ho vender 7^0 No. of Enclosures. ' 0 tiyemDplhi, the No. Ti-Bahrein 1S3^4*-3V726 From The ACCOUNTANT-GENEUAL, CENTRAL REVENUES, To The Political t, Bahrein Sir, I have the honour to refer you to vouchers Bos.7 ana 8 inciueea in the list of payments : 19 3} anc to request you to intimate Bilitary Peasion ^ccouc ts, northern Lahore District direct the number ane ^a:t of warrants issued in favour of the pensioners Hudar hhan ane Bahadur Khan ane the na:.ie of the treasury v/hence they drew their pension for the month of Febru to the fontroll er of ana ^astern m Incia. i have ToxnfKo: C - nt cP ■'■ u l u*0./7.3/ /16/13. Political IigGDay 9 Bahxmin* Dated the 9th Deoenber, 1S?30* From Captain C, G. irior, I. Political , Baiir&amp;int To Hie Controller of Military Pension Accounts, Torthem and Eastern Commands, Lahore District* Sir, I have the honour to refer to letter L T o*TA-3ahrein 1 of 30-31/726 dated the 5th l ovenb r, 1930, from the Accountant General, central Jievonues, ' ow Delhi, requesting me to furnish you direct with certain particulars in resi^oct of Pension ffarrauts of atife* Oian cjxj. * ctr Dan. As requested therein 1 have to inform you tliat Pensioner v Udir idian is tiie holder of rension Jertiiicate ' o#15056 that the payments made to him by this office are in accordance with letter f o• PA/5/134355 dated the ri&gt;th November, 1936, from the Deputy Assistant Controller of Military Accounts Northern Command and Rawalpindi District# No payments, in respect of his pension, were made to this pensioner in India, prior to his having drawn his pension at this office# The Pension papers of Pensioner Kavildar Bahadur Khan have since been forwarded to the Deputy Commissioner, Jhelum, from whom the necessary particulars may please be obtained# the 5th November, 1930# I have the honour to be » Your most obedient servant,</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x0000f5_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1510</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x0000f5</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1510</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>‘Miscellaneous 16/13 Pensions to Bahadur Khan &amp; Niadar Khan Levy Corps Havildars – Correspondence re –’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1926/1930</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-04-13T11:16:58</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">urd</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (22 folios)</extent><extent>The file’s contents are arranged in approximate chronological order, from the earliest item at the front to the latest at the end.</extent><extent>The foliation sequence commences at the front cover with 1 and terminates at the inside back cover with 25; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is also present in parallel between ff 4-22; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Correspondence relating to arrangements for the payment of Indian military pensions for individuals either residing in Bahrain, or who have worked in Bahrain and wish to return to British India. The file’s principal correspondents are: the Political Agent at Bahrain; the Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf; the Deputy Assistant Controller of Military Accounts, Northern Command and Rawalpindi District. The file includes an extract of the Civil Accounts Code, Volume II, entitled ‘Payments to Pensioners–, etc.’ (ff 12-13), and a letter (in Urdu with English translation) from pensioner Havildar Bahadur Khan of the 28 Light Cavalry (ff 18-19).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Controller of Military Accounts, Northern Command and Rawalpindi District</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Military pensions</topic></subject><subject><topic>Colonial administration</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x0000f5#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>