<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100023655811.0x000007_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T01:38:36.711Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">No. 266. Extract from the Proceedings of the Most Nolle the Governor General of India in Council in the Financial Department, under date the Wth January 1856. Read an Extract from the Military Department, No. 292, dated the 17th ultimo, forward-, ing for consideration and orders a letter from the Commissary General Bengal, No. 157, dated the 2nd October last, with enclosures, regarding the grant of a Pension to Bissembhur Ghose, Head Clerk of the Cawnpore Executive Commissariat Office. Read Military Auditor General's report on the above case, No. 446, dated 10th ultimo. Observations .—Bissembhur Ghose, Head Writer of the Cawnpore Executive Commissa riat Office, who is stated to have served Government for upwards of forty-one years, applies for a pension equal to two-thirds of his present pay, (Rupees 80,) in consideration of his long and faithful service, his having been twice in active service, viz. in the Nepaul War and Ilatras, and in consequence of his having performed the duties of the Head Assistant in the Cawnpore Commissariat Executive Office without enjoying the salary of the appointment. The Military Auditor General reports, that in calculating the average of the applicant's salary for the last five years, his pay as Acting Head Assistant has been taken into account; that the Rules allow of pension being calculated on the monthly amount of the salary or official allowance of an applicant on an average of five years previous to the date of applica tion, without reference to the permanency or otherwise of such salary or official allowance ; and that the Rules therefore are in favour of the applicant receiving a pension of Ru pees 43-8-0 per month, being a moiety, less fractions of less than a quarter of a Rupee, of his last five years' average salary. The Auditor General enquires whether the salary of an acting appointment is in future to be taken into calculation towards pension, or whether only the salary of the permanent ap pointment is to be taken into calculation, as it is evident, that at present both the acting and permanent official would claim the advantages arising from the average being determined on their respective maximum salaries, a measure creative of additional expense to the State. The Auditor General is of opinion, that the acting incumbent should receive the advantage of the salary of his acting situation in the calculation of pension, inasmuch as he receives the increased salary for performing the work of the absent permanent incumbent, and that a corresponding deduction should in future be made from the average exhibited in favor of the absentee. Resolution .—The Most Noble the Governor General in Council does not agree in the view taken by the Military Auditor General, as it would be hard to deprive an Officer on the permanent establishment of any portion of the average pay of his permanent appoint ment, because, for a part of the last five years of his service, when he might have been obliged to have been absent on leave, a substitute might have been appointed to act for him. The Military Auditor General's view is also opposed to the views of the Honorable the Court of Directors, set forth in their despatch in the Public Department, No. 48 of 1834, dated loth October, in which they approve of the principle, that 'claims to pension founded on occasional employment as a substitute for others on the fixed establishment of a Public Office are inad missible, as in that case Government would be recognizing two claims at the same time on account of one situation.'n L 2 ] Under all the circumstances of the case, His Lordship in Council resolves, that the pen- * From 1st Sept. 1850 to 26th Dec. 1853, sion in question be calculated on the ave- per month 'l 0 '!'!! 8 ! ^^ f.'* ^.T rs ! 2,987 14 5 fi ^d _ salary drawn by Bissembhur From 27th Dec. 1853 to 31st Aug. 1855, Ghose during the last five years of his 1 year, 8 months, 5 days, at 80 Rupees per service, and that he be allowed a pen- montl1 1,612 1 4 ^ sion of Rs. 38-4-0* per month, being a 60) 4,600 12 10 moiety, exclusive of fractions of less than i 10 1() a quarter of a Rupee, of the average of the fixed salary drawn by him during the ;) ^ last five years of his service. Order .—Ordered that a copy of the foregoing Resolution be forwarded to the Military Department, for the issue of the necessary orders, and that the original papers be returned, copies being kept for record in this Office. Ordered also, that copies of the Resolution be forwarded to the Governments of Bengal, Madras, Bombay, North-Western Provinces, and Straits Settlements. Ordered further, that a copy of the Resolution be sent to the Civil Auditor, Bengal. (A true extract) (Signed) C. H. Lushington, Secretary to the Government of India. No. 91 of 1856. Territorial Department. Finance. Forwarded to the Acting Civil Auditor for information and guidance, and for communica tion to the several Heads of Departments. (Signed) H. YOUNG, Bombay Castle, dth February 1856. Gffg. Chief Secretary, Territorial Department, Finance. CIRCULAR. No. 1262 of 1855-56. The foregoing is furnished for the information of ^ 02&gt;. • 'en n ot A. K, CORFIELD, Bombay } 11 th February 185G. Acting Civil Auditor.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100023655811.0x000007_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/150, f 13</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100023655811.0x000007</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/150, f 13</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Extract No. 266 from the Proceedings of the Governor General of India in Council in the Financial Department</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1856/1856</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-04-08T01:25:57</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 folio</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The extract concerns a pension awarded to Bissembhur Ghose, Head Clerk of the Cawnpore [Kānpur] Executive Commissariat Office, and an enquiry from the Auditor General as to whether salaries of an acting appointment should be considered admissible when calculating someone's pension award; the Governor General's resolution to this is outlined, along with a new calculation for the Head Clerk's pension entitlement.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100023655811.0x000007#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>