<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000163_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-12T02:10:09.041Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">1 \ \ 3) i Res. P. G. No. 32. No. of 19 British Resicf^rj^Sid Consulate-General, Bushire, the « _ 19 /*&gt;&amp; May 17 MAY 1936 A copy of the undermentioned paper is forwarded to : The Political Agent, Muscat, The Political Agent, Bahrein, The Political Agent, Kuwait, His Majesty’s Consul and Assistant to Resident, Bunder Abbas, His Majesty’s Consul, Kerman, His Majesty’s Vice-Consul, for information and guidance xxxxxxxxxxxxx No. , dated the uidance with reterenci XXXXXXXXXXT 5 Khorraiushatir, ict 19 xxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxxx for early report. for By order. Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Memorandum jaffftyxf rom the Government of India in the # , p Pepartment No Xb9-A/36 ’ dated the 25tll April 19 36 (Received with Foreign and Political Department endorsement No. , dated the 19 .) GrfPD—255 Resit. PG BushiM—4*9-30—1.500.Copy of Memorandum flo.P.59-A/36 dated tde 25th April 1936 from the Government of India in the foreign and Political Department. 'xhe Government of India are considering the desirability of supplying broadcasting receiving sets at remote stations and outposts with a view to make up to date news available, and in this connection would be glad to have the following information regarding the electric supply if any available at the Consulates or Agencies for which you are responsible in the following form:- la) Voltage lb) Whether the supply is A.0. or D.C. ana l c) Whether the supply is reliable and reasonably steady. If, as seems probable in many of these cases, there is no supply, or the supply is unreliable, it would be necessary to provide batteries, and in that case to ascertain whether arrangements can be made locally for charging. An early reply is requestedC’s P. P.—L (III) 129-500-4-31. No. 1351- 17/17 OF I 930 The Political Agency, Bahrain, 19th May Dated the 1936 * To The Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, BUSHIRE. MEMORANDUM. P Reference your printed letter No:1060-13/157 dated the 13th May 1936. 2. Electric Supply is available at Bahrain. The electric power station is run by the Bahrain Government. (a) Voltage is 230. (b) The supply is A.C. (c) The supply is reliable and steady. (d) No batteries are required. r for Officiating Political Agent,Bahrain.No:1365-17/17 Political Agency, Bahrain, the 21st May 1936. To The British Broadcasting Company Limited, London• Dear Sirs, Please send weekly to this Agency a copy of the Empire Radio Programme. 2. A draft for five shillings is enclosed. 3. Please note that we only receive overland mails fortnightly Erom Basrah, but bi-weekly by Imperial Airways. Please ensure that the programmes reach us in time. Yours faithfully, for Officiating Political Agent,Bahrain.u Trow - The Hon * 1)10 the Political liesident k in the Persian Gulf* To - The Toreign Secretary to the Government of India, Simla Memorandum Ho. ^^^ 15/167-11 Bushire, dated the 2b ^une 1936. W'*' Keference Por^^gn and Political Department Memorandum Ho. P.59-A/36 dated the 25th April 1936( 2. A statement giving the particulars of electric supply available at the Consulates and Agencies under the administrative control of this Residency is enclosed. 3. It will be observed that Kerman and Kuwait, while preferring batteries, lack: local arrangements for charging them. This could, however, presumably be arranged at Bandar Abbas and Basra respectively. 3d/- C.C.L* Ryan for Political Resident in th e Persian Gulf. Ho. Copy forwarded to /3Copy of letter Ho.F.59-A/36 dated the 20th January 1937 from the Government of India in the Foreign and Foliticel Department, New Delhi, to the Eon'hle the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Supply of tireless (broadcasting) Receivers, , with reference to the correspondence ending with your memorandum No. 1287/13/167-11, dated the 20th June 19o6, I am directed to say that the Government of India have after careful consideration decided to drop the question of supplying wireless broadcasting receivers to the Consulates and Agencies at remote stations and outpostsNo. 822-30/8. Political Agency, Bahrain, the 17th May 1939. 0 &gt; To The Residency Agent, Sharjah. Memorandum Please inform me whether you received the following from Messrs. Yueuf Abdulrahman Fakhroo, Bahrain, in good order:- 1. One Phillips Battery Receiver Model 289BV 2. One Willard Battery 6-Volt 116 amps. 3. One Willard aerial complete. (A for Political Agent,Bahrain. v y ■ ti iT ■ 'ii &amp; c.c. Original in/file l.a/25 - III page 25. Extract from Express letter No. C/213 dated the 23rd May 1939 from the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. (Received under P.R^s P.L. No. C/214 of 23rd May 1939) Provision of wireless receiving sets for Political Agencies on the Arab Coast. *** *** *** 4. In regard to the cost of such receiving sets. Owing to the low customs duty in the Arab States good sets can be purchased for about Rs 400. I recommend that this sum be put at the disposal of Political Agents, Kuwait, Bahrain and Muscat, for the purchase of sets, the type being left to their selection having regard to local receiving conditions. The Residency Agent, Sharjah, where there is no Ibcal electricity supply, should have a battery set costing Rs. 300. The total grant applied for is therefore Rs. 1500.( Original in C.O. file l.a/25*III page 239 ) Copy of Express letter No. 1496-13/167 dated the 16th November 1939 from the Political Resident. Provision of Wirelews Receiving sets. Reference this office printed letter No. C/214 of 23rd May 1939. 2. Purchase of wireless sets is hereby authorised. r(Original in C.O.File 1.a/25-III page 271) Copy of Express letter No, 1768-13/167 dated the 24th December 1939 from the Political Resident. Provision of wireless receiving sets. Reference my Express letter No. 1496-13/167 dated the 16th November 1989. 2. An extra provision of Rs. 400/- on account of the purchase of a wireless set is being made under 'Bahrain - C - 4 Contingencies - Office Allowance'- The expenditure should therefore be debited to your Office Allowance grant for the current year.(Original in file l.a/25) Spoken to P.A. who has agreed to the purchase of 1940 Phillips for Rs. 340/- and the sale of the old set to Mr. Rajagopalan for Rs. 50/- Sd/. S.M.S. 6/1/40if GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. Dkpabtmskt. EXPRESS LETTER [N. B % —This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphU: expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as \f it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been ^ so despatched,) From / To Britconaul, The Political Agent - Muscat The Political Agent - Bahrain The Political Agent - Kuwait No. - 13/167. r&gt;aled the 4th March ZS ^40 Supply of wireless sets to Political Officers, Persian Gulf, 1575-13/167 Reference this office express letter No.1708-13/167 1708-13/167 3rd December 1939 . 24th December 1939 , 24th December 1939. dated 2, I forward, herewith, a copy of letter No.T.A.8-6-1350, dated the 15th February 1940, from the Accountant General, Central Revenues, New Delhi, for information and necessary action. () to 3. The detailed cost of the wireless sets (including the set Bahrain only. purchased for the Residency Agent, Sharjah) should now be debited to His Majesty s doveminent on a contingent bill and a corresponding amount reduced from your Office Allowance grant. CA. /4. S. 6. MFP—1196 S&amp;P—(M-2302)—22-2-38—300,000.\k 2. 4. Details of the cost of the wireless sets purchased for your Agency (and Sharjah) should be intiaated to this office. RESIDBNT The issue of the aboTe has been authorised. Secretary, to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.f &amp; n Copy of letter No. TA8-6-1350 dated the 15th February 1940 from the Accountant General, Central Revenues, New Delhi, to the Secretary to the Hon*ble the Poli tical Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Supply of wireless receiving sets to officers in the Persian Gulf I have the honour to invite a reference to your memorandum No.125-13/167 dated the 23rd January 1940, to the Secretary to the Government of India, External Affairs Department, on the subject indicated above. It has been stated by you that the expenditure on the wireless sets is being debited to the office allowance of the offices concerned. As the cost of the wireless sets in ques tion will be borne wholly by His Majesty*s Government, ( vide Secre tary of States Express letter No.P.Z.7317/39 dated the 23rd Novem ber 1939) the charges on this account are to be passed on to the Secretary of State through the Remittance Account. In office allowance vouchers no details of charges are furnished. It is therefore, requested that the details of the charges on account of wireless sets and the month’s account in which they are included may kindly be furnished to enable this office to pass on the same -— m .—triMt^gg*****, u,jiWMI 0imv i—i n -— —-— •■umii.iMiji.jiajM..i. --xaggn'sji ■ ■■—mg to the Secretary of State through the Remittance Account and the charge on account of o: * •Jig-'? ■gfisfuir, tp&amp;ij'jvtftfxz tee allowances may also please be reduced. The charges which have not already been accounted for may kindly be shown separately in your accounts and not included under the office allowance grant.Telegram From To No. Dated. G.T.C. Political, Bahrain. Britcon&amp;ul, Bushire. 80 27th March 1940. Express My endorsement No.399 of 29th February and Letter No.887 of 4th March. ' ^74' 300/-cost of radio for Sharjah is being drawn on seperate contingent bill and credited to Bushire Unofficial account. Please adjust your office allowance grant accordingly. &lt;2 W\CGTC Telegram From To No.140 Dated 12th May, Political, Britconsul, 1940. Bahrain. Bushire ■ , r Your telegram No .A/194 of 10 th May. Rupees 400. Drawn on separate contingent bill in March debitable to His Majesty's Government.■*&gt; 1A ^ *** • ^ NO .494-8/6 British ii^encyjUharjah* Dated the 25th March 1944* &amp;) 'Z- f The Political Agent, Bahrain* Subject :- Government wireless sets and batteries at sharjah » rnUQMMm- There is a Zenith Badio here whicli was brought by v /Captain j.B.Howe^ flriKyahrain with two batteries when he was the political officer,Trueial coast. There is also the phillips'andT A ^ battery mentioned in the Besidency Agent r s memorandum bo *317-8/6 dated the 28th May 1939. The latter set was unserviceable when I took over but I have recently had it repaired by the British over seas Airways corporation and it is now/ working well. The zenith, however, requires 5 new valves which the b.O.A.C. can procure for me from India at a cost of bs*150/- approximately, if the set is repaired and not required in oharjah it may very well be of use elsewhere (e*g. i understand that the Lingah reading room is in great need of a set for publicity purpose#, i should be grateful for permission to spend Hs.150/- on repair of this set. 2o Of the 3 batteries one has been completely unserviceable for over a year and another is now so old that it becomes discharged very rapidly and I am informed that it should be replaced, 'ihe battery in the office pick-up is also defective and, I understand, cannot be repaired. Three 6 volt batteries are therefore required here if you agree to the repair^ of the Zenith set, otherwise two (one being a Ford battery for the car) will suffice* /b Political Officer,Trueial Coast*&lt; 24 )^ No./65Li -17/17 POLITICAL AGKNCY, : %HHAIN. Tho 1st Jiino 1944. To The Station Manager, British Overseas Airways Corporation, ; sharjah. !.Qiiorand\in . I should be glad if you would please obtain from India a sei: of spare valves for my office mdio(3eni*&amp;h) ♦ The details about the valves may bo obtained from i.ho Residency Agent, Sharjah, with whom the set is lying at present. 2. On receipt of the valves they may be handed over to the Residency Agent, along with your bill for T&gt;nyment. dated the 25th May 1944, from Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Sharjah. On receipt of the valves riease inform me and pay their cost to the station Manager, British Overseas Air jays Corporation, Sharjah. Copy f^rwa] Sharjah, with n/U&gt;. ^ &lt;fT - v - c &gt; L^^C. Fo papers about-the radios were available in E.C., C.C« or Publicity Cffice records. All English* Office invard registers for the past 5 years were seen, deposit account and Oo^rt. a&lt;x- ount registers were also seen and a clue (notes 4-6; wofte found in old record room. * 4 C.O. was again asked to go through their files and inward registers. /v, After all the relevant C.O. file since transferred to-^Public / ^ Relations Cffice was found and pages 11-20 were traced 7 from Budget file for 1939-40. This accounts for delay. The cost of Philip battery set was debited to P.R.c/ /r ' funds. Fo papers can be traced about Zenith set. -govt, and deposit A/c registers have been gone through^ A refee. to 3^3.register is suggested, so as to enable us to know to w^licm the radio belongs and to what account repair charges and cost of battery should be debited. As regards cost of battery for Philip set it will be //. debited to P.R.C. funds. Cost of battery for Cffice Pickup will be debited to the Pickup A/c maintained by the F.C.T.C. (page 19 file 17/21 refers). y*. / A PA 21/4/1944. 4. g ^ ^ b 1 -*- i4r J_. r fO. . U ^ 9 ' /3 r.r^ ert -T-.c. 'i.'? • W- ^ 'Ou-e. /A</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000163_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1620</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000163</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1620</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 17/17 Supply of Broadcasting receiving sets'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1936/1944</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-01-05T18:47:41</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (26 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 28; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 3-24; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file concerns plans for wireless broadcasting sets to be provided to the Political Agencies at Bahrain, Kuwait, and Muscat, as well as at the Residency at Sharjah, for the purpose of making up-to-date news available (with the cost of the wireless sets being borne wholly by His Majesty's Government).The file contains details of the electrical supply available at each consulate and agency under the Political Residency's control (as requested by the Government of India's Foreign and Political Department), as well as information about the availability and cost of wireless sets in the Arab states.Correspondents include the following: the Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire; the Political Agent, Bahrain; the Residency Agent, Sharjah; the Political Officer, Trucial Coast.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Agent, Trucial Coast</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Native Agent, Trucial Coast, Sharjah</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Persian Gulf</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Radio sets</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x000163#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>