<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100023550128.0x000001_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T19:50:26.994Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">- \)' V ' ir' i ; ETJPHMTES VALLEY ROUTE TO INDIA, IN CONNECTION WITH THE CENTRAL ASIAN AND EGYPTIAN QUESTIONS. LECTUBE DELIVERED AT THE NATIONAL ON THE 16TH 1882, BY SIR WILLIAM ANDREW, C.I.E., AUTHOR OF ' INDIA AND HER NEIGHBOURS ' ' OUR SCIENTIFIC FRONTIER,'' ETC., ETC. THE EIGHT HONOURABLE SIR BARTLE ERERE, BART., G.C.B., Gr.C.S.L, IN THE CHAIR. LONDON: W. H. ALLEN &amp; CO., 13 WATERLOO PLACE, PALL MALL. S.W. PUBLISHERS TO THE INDIA OFFICE. 1882. V: ff jfljHPnt'^ *•' \ ^ ^ Ti r-** (-?tr^3 * ,/ -^ v / ■Q B H ^ V.,&gt; EUPHRATES VALLEY ROUTE TO INDIA, in connection with the central asian and egyptian questions. By SIR WILLIAM ANDREW, C.I.E. The present position of affairs in Egypt forces once more to the front the necessity of having an alternative route to our Eastern possessions, even were the alternative an inferior one in every respect to that by the Suez Canal. Anything would be better than to leave our communications with the East at the mercy of such men as Arabi Pasha and his ignorant soldiers! He has but to sink a single vessel to obstruct the navigation of the canal, or to blow in the sides at certain portions of the embankment to make this magnificent waterway for ships of all nations as useless as a dry ditch. The political state of Egypt, taken in conjunction with the steady advance of Russia towards India, 1 *4 rouses once more the attention of statesmen and soldiers of France and Germany, as well as of England, to the route to India by the Euphrates Valley Railway. In the proposal to restore this ancient route— once the highway of the world's commerce, and the track of the heroes of early history—by the construction of a railway to connect the Mediter ranean and the Persian Grulf, we have at once an alternative route and an invaluable and perfectly efficient means of thwarting the designs of Russia, if they should assume a hostile character; of marching hand-in-hand with her, if her mission be to carry civilisation to distant lands; and of competing with her in the peaceful rivalry of commerce. Of all the lessons which recent wars have taught us, none is more emphatic than this, that hence forth the power of nations must be upheld by the knowledge and use of mechanical appliances. Among the most important of these are railways, as we saw in the Franco-Grerman war. A vaerue presentiment of this marvellous revolution had long existed, but it had to struggle against apathy and deep-seated prejudice. The true secret of national supremacy has, however, now been brought home with irresistible force to the most reluctant mind; and it behoves us to brace ourselves anew for a more determined progress, if we would retain the prestige and influence we have hitherto enjoyed as a great nation,6 and In the Crimean war we saw, with certainty, of where the power of the Czar first gave way. The ites telegraph and rail were the missing links in his armour. He had built fortresses of colossal ma^ni- e— tude, collected resources astonishing from their md variety and abundance; his generals were selected the with consummate skill, while over the persons and ter- property of his subjects he exercised unlimited an control. But, had the Czar been able to whisper itly his commands with lightning speed, and been obeyed sia, with promptitude, how different might have been the of result! The giant aggressor was, by a handful of ? to invaders, with telegraph and steam in connection ing with the bases of their operations, defeated and humiliated on the soil of holy Russia herself, ^ht Few facts bear more conclusive testimony to ce- the sagacity of the ancients, when the limited the amount of their geographical knowledge is re- les. membered, than the tenacity with which commerce ys, adhered to the direction given to it by them, and rue the readiness with which it returns to any of those mg channels when temporarily diverted by political ,11 d events, or geographical discoveries. The overland nal route from Europe to India, by the Isthmus of me Suez and the Red Sea, is certainly as old as the id; days of the early Phoenician navigators. The ^ a navigability of the Euphrates was tested long ;lie before Trajan ever sailed on its waters, and was as re-visited by the Italians in the eleventh century, and our own merchants in the days of Elizabeth,as tlie best way to the East; whilst the value of the Indus, as the shortest and easiest route for the commerce of India, not only with Central Asia and the North of Europe, but with the whole of the West, was fully recognised by the later Romans in the seventh century. When the rapid progress of the Mohammedan arms had wrested Egypt from the Byzantine power, and thus closed the overland route of Suez to the Greek merchants, they forthwith turned to other means, and sought out a new channel by which the productions of the East might be transmitted to the great em porium of the West. The route thus discovered was that by the Indus. The rich and easily stowed products of India were carried up by this great river, as far as it was navigable, thence transported to the Oxus, down which stream they proceeded as far as the Caspian Sea. There they entered the Volga, and sailing up it, were carried by land to the Tanais (the Don), which conducted them into the Euxine Sea, where ships from Constantinople waited their arrival. Various causes concurred in restoring liberty and independence to the cities of Italy. The acquisition of these, stimulated industry, and gave motion and vigour to all the active powers of the human mind. Foreign commerce revived, navigation was attended to and improved. Constantinople became the chief mart to which the Italians resorted. There they not only met with favourable reception, but7 obtained such mercantile privileges as enabled them to carry on trade with great advantages. They were supplied both with the precious com modities of the East, and with many curious manufactures, the product of ancient arts and in genuity still subsisting among the Greeks. As the labour and expense of conveying the productions of India to Constantinople, by that long and in direct course which I have described (the route by the Indus, the Oxus, the Caspian, and the Volga), rendered them extremely rare, and of an exorbi tant price, the industry of the Italians discovered other methods of procuring them in greater abundance, and at an easier rate. They sometimes purchased them at Aleppo, Tripoli, and other ports on the coast of Syria, to which they were brought by a route not unknown to the ancients. They were conveyed from India by sea, up the Persian Gulf, and, ascending the Euphrates and Tigris, q^s far as Bagdad, were carried by land across the desert of Palmyra, and from thence to the towns on the Mediterranean. The discovery of the long but easy route by the Cape of Good Hope, combined with the deadly feuds between the Christians of the West and the Mohammedan nations that held the countries of the Nile and the Euphrates, for a time diverted the stream of commerce from those routes. It has not been so, however, with the Indus to the same extent. If the revival of the Suez Route, and the8 wished for opening of the Euphrates railway as the highway to the East, are evidences of a return to old paths, the continuance of a commerce with Central Asia and Northern Europe by way of the Indus, and the two great gates of India, the Khyber and Bolan Passes, is a pregnant proof of the tenacity with which trade adheres to its old channels, and of the sagacity which originally selected that direction for the produce of the East. However great may have been the changes of masters and manners in the territories between the Indus and the Bosphorus, a portion of the tide of commerce has flowed, and does still flow, as it did in the seventh century. When the late Sir Alexander Burnes was in Lahore, in 1831, he found English broadcloth sold in the bazaar that had been brought, not from Calcutta, but from Russia; and, when he pene trated further into Central Asia, met, at Bokhara, with a merchant .thinking of taking an invest ment of it to Loodhiana, in India, where he could afford to sell it cheaper than it was to be had there, notwithstanding the length of the journey.' The countries which our future highway to India will traverse have been, from remote antiquity, the most interesting in the world. On the once fertile plains, watered by the Euphrates and Tigris, the greatest and most glorious nations of antiquity arose, flourished, and were overthrown. The earliest home of the genius of civilisation—the scene of9 the great events in the early history of the world, ^ to now shrouded in the dust of ages, or dimly dis- ith cerned through the long vista of many centuries— the the land of the Assyrians, Babylonians, and the Chaldeans; where the daughters of Zion sat and of wept; where lay the track of Xenophon and his old heroic 10,000 Grreeks—the centre of the conquests tlly of the Macedonians ; where once stood the proud i-st. capitals of the Sassanides and of the Caliphs, now of deserted and tenantless—these regions must ever 5en possess a fascination and interest for all mankind, ide The first city of the new earth was built upon the s it banks of the ' Great River.' The tower of pride, erected by the post-diluvian population, cast a in shadow over its waters. The Euphrates inter- jld sected Babylon, the ' Golden City,' the ' Glory of )m Kingdoms,' the great capital of the Chaldean le- Empire—now a desolation among the nations, her ra, broad walls utterly broken, her high gates burnt at- with fire. With Babylon are associated the names ild of Nebuchadnezzar and Belshazzar, of Daniel and re, Darius, of Cyrus and Alexander. The grand prophet of the captivity, and Peter the energetic lia apostle of the new era, had their dwelling within ;y, her walls. Ere even a brick was made upon the Nile, ce Nineveh and Babylon must have had thriving and is, busy populations. ty Twice in the world's history, mankind com- sst menced the race of civilisation on the Mesopo- of tamian rivers. Twice the human family diverged10 from their banks to the east, the west, and the north. Arts and sciences made the first feeble steps of their infancy upon the shores of these rivers. Verv early m history we know tliat Babj- lon was a great manufacturing city, famed for the costly fabrics of its looms. At a more recent date, the Chaldean kings made it a gorgeous metropolis; Alexander of Macedon made it the port of the Indian Ocean and the Persian Grulf, and he pro posed to render it the central seat of his imperial power. The countries through which the Euphrates flows were formerly the most productive in the world. Throughout these regions the fruits of temperate and tropical climes grew, in bygone days, in pro fusion. Luxury and abundance were universally diffused. The soil everywhere teemed with vege tation. Much of this has since passed away. Ages of despotism and misrule have rendered unavailing the bounty of nature. But the land is full of hidden riches. The natural elements of its ancient grandeur still exist in the inexhaustible fertility of the soil, and in the chivalrous character and bearing of many of the tribes ; and the day cannot be far distant when it is destined to resume its place amongst the fairest and most prosperous regions of the globe. The wondrous fertility of Mesopotamia was, in early times, carried to its utmost limit by means of numerous irrigation canals, with which the11 country was everywhere intersected, and some of the largest of which were navigable. These excited the wonder and interest of Alexander the Great, who, after his return from the conquest of India, examined them personally, steering the boat with his own hand. He employed a great number of men to repair and cleanse these canals. Herodotus, speaking of Babylonia, says :— ' Of all the countries I know, it is, without question, the best and the most fertile. It produces neither figs, nor vines, nor olives; but, in recompense, the earth is suitable for all sorts of grain, of which it yields always 200 per cent., and, in years of extraordinary fertility, as much as 300 per cent.' These regions need only again to be irrigated by the life-giving waters pouring down, ever cool and plentiful, from Arrarat—that great land-mark of primaeval history, now the vast natural boundary- stone of the Russian, Turkish, and Persian empires —to yield once more in abundance almost every thing that is necessary or agreeable to man. Many acres, now wasted, might be covered with cotton, tending to the employment of the millions of spindles of our land. It is not too much to say that no existing or projected railroad can compare in point of interest and importance with that of the Euphrates Valley. It will bring two quarters of the globe into juxta position, and three continents—Europe, Asia, and Australia—into closer relation. It will bind the vast population of Hindustan by an iron link with12 the people of Europe. It will inevitably entail tlie colonisation and civilisation of the great valleys of the Euphrates and Tigris, the resuscitation, in a modern shape, of Babylon and Nineveh, and the re-awakening of Ctesiphon and Bagdad as of old. It is by distance and difficulties of intercourse that the distinctions of creeds and races are chiefly upheld. Annihilate space, and the great barriers that separate peoples—the differences of manners and customs, of modes of tlfought and feeling, of doctrines and dogmas, of precepts and prejudices, that keep up these barriers—gradually disappear, as barbarism, superstition, and ignorance give way to the superior and irresistible force of civilisation, truth, and enlightenment. Although various routes have been suggested with the view of bringing Great Britain, by means of railway communication, into closer connection with India and her other dependencies in the East, and of securing, at the same time, the immense political and strategic desideratum of an alterna tive highway to our Eastern possessions, there is none which combines in itself so many advantages as the ancient route of the Euphrates—the route of the Emperors Trajan and Julian, in whose steps, in more recent times, the Great Napoleon intended to follow, when the Russian campaign turned his energies in another direction. The special advantages which render this route superior to all others are briefly these :—It is the13 most direct route to India. It is the shortest and the cheapest, both for constructing and working a railway, so free from engineering difficulties, that it almost appears as though designed by the hand of nature to be the highway of nations between the East and the West; the most easily defensible by England—both of its termini being on the open sea; and the most likely to prove remunerative. Both from an engineering and a political point of view, the Euphrates route undoubtedly possesses great advantages over any of the others which have been proposed. All the routes which have been suggested from places on the Black Sea are open to the fatal objection that, while they would be of the greatest service to Russia, they would be alto gether beyond the control of Great Britain, while the engineering difficulties with which they are surrounded are, of themselves, sufficient to exclude them from practical consideration. This has been fully established by the evidence of the witnesses examined by the Select Committee of the House of Commons, which, in 1872, inves tigated the merits of the various proposals for connecting the Mediterranean and the Black Sea with the Persian Gulf. In the course of the investigation by the Com mittee, it was conclusively demonstrated that the proposed Euphrates Valley Railway is an eminently feasible undertaking in an engineering sense; that the route of the Euphrates and the Persian Gulf14 is decidedly preferable, in respect of climate, to that of Egypt and the Red Sea; that, as regards the safety and facility of the navigation, the Persian G-ulf also has by far the advantage; that the pro posed undertaking would be of great commercial moment, and, if not immediately profitable, at all events, that it would be so at a date not far distant; and, finally, that it would be of the highest political, and strategic importance to this country. It is unnecessary to quote in detail from the evidence taken by the Committee, but, in order to show how authoritative were the conclusions in favour of the undertaking arrived at by the Com mittee, I may state that the engineering facilities which exist for the construction of a railway from the Mediterranean to the Persian Gulf were demon strated by the evidence of the late General Chesney, the veteran explorer of the route, by Captain, now Admiral Charlewood, of the Royal Navy, and Mr. W. F. Ainsworth, two of the officers attached to the Euphrates Expedition; by Sir John Macneill, Mr. Telford Macneill, Mr. W. J. Maxwell, Sir Henry Rawlinson, Captain R. F. Burton, and Captain Felix Jones. The advantages of the route, in respect of the climate and productiveness of the country to be traversed, were shown by the evidence of General Chesney, Mr. Eastwick, M.P., Captain Felix Jones, General Sir Henry Green, Colonel Malcolm Green, Mr. Consul Barker, and others. Mr. Barker, who had resided twenty-six years as Vice-Consul and15 Acting-Consul at Seleucia, Antioch, and Aleppo, and has, perhaps, as intimate an acquaintance with the country as any man living, stated in an official report, addressed by him to Lord Granville, that— ' A- railway through Mesopotamia, as a route to India, would not, at first, be productive of much income to a company from traffic, but in a few years—certainly before the railway could be finished—the cultivation of grain would increase a hundred fold, and would go on increasing a thousandfold, and would attain to a magnitude and extension quite impossible to cal- culate, because bad harvests are almost unknown in these parts, for there is always plenty of rain and a hot sun to ripen the corn. Populous villages would spring up all along the line, as there is abundance of sweet water everywhere. Cereals can be grown there so cheaply that no country the same dis tance from England—say, for instance, Russia—could compete with it at all. And, if Great Britain finds it necessary to rely more on the importation of foreign corn, where could a better field be found than the fertile plains of Mesopotamia, the cradle of mankind, which has all the advantages of climate, soil, sun, and water in its favour.' The facility of the navigation of the Persian Gulf was testified to by Mr. William Parkes, Consulting Engineer to the Secretary of State for India for Kurrachee and Madras harbours, and also in a correspondence published by Captain A. D. Taylor, late of the Indian Xavy. Mr. Edwyn Dawes gave some useful information of the great extension of commerce at all the ports of the Persian Gulf. The advantages of the proposed undertaking from a military point of view were placed beyond question by the evidence of General Chesney, of Sir Henry16 Tyler, R.E., and of those experienced soldiers, Sir Henry Green and Colonel Malcolm Green, and more especially by the weighty testimony of Field-Marshal Lord Strathnairn ; while its importance in a political sense was established by many witnesses, amongst whom I may instance my distinguished friend Sir Bartle Frere, the late lamented Sir Donald McLeod, Mr. Palgrave, General Herbert, late Her Majesty's Consnl-General at Bagdad, Mr. Eldridge, Oonsul- General at Beyrout, and, pre-eminently, the Great Elchi,' the venerated Lord Stratford de Redcliffe. Other nations, whose interests in the East are incomparably less than ours, either on political or commercial grounds, have, in recent years, made great advances in extending their communications in an easterly direction. The establishment of steam communication by the Messageries Maritimes on the route of the Red Sea, to Calcutta and other Eastern ports, shows the importance attached by the French to the extension of their commercial relations with the East. A Russian line of steamers has been established, to run between Odessa and Bombay by the route of the Suez Canal, and the Italians and Austrians are actively competing for a share in the Eastern trade. Even those who see no danger in the policy of annexation pursued by Russia, will admit that the Russian roads and railways now being pushed towards Persia and Afghanistan, if designed with pacific intentions, prove, at all events, the anxiety17 2 of the Russian Government to compete with ua for the trade of Central Asia, the Punjaub, and Northern India. But the carriages and trucks ostensibly designed for peaceful and commercial purposes are so constructed, as to be equally available for the conveyance of troops with munitions of war. It behoves us, therefore, to be careful that we do not stand still in the career of improvement, and be left behind in the race by other nations, however friendly. Political disturbance in Europe or in Egypt might at any moment deprive us of our communications with India via Suez. The canal, glorious work as it is, as has been already mentioned, might be easily and suddenly rendered useless by the sinking of a ship or by a breach in the bank. So long as the Indian Empire subsists, the connec tion between India and this country must be kept up. If that connection were interrupted for many months, the integrity of our Eastern Empire might be seriously menaced. England maintains her posi tion in India mainly by force of arms; and it is a principle, both of war and of common sense, to take the most efficient means at our command to keep open the lines of communication between the base and the field of operations. Hence the necessity of establishing an alternative route, even if it were not a better one. But that by the Euphrates, the most ancient of all, is at once the shortest, the easiest, and the safest, and it can never be superseded by any other offering superior advantages.18 Apart from the general question of the advantage, on strategic grounds, of possessing an alternative and accelerated route to our Eastern dominions, it is a matter of the greatest importance that, in case of an emergency we should be able to send troops to India at any season of the year. Viewed in this light, the Euphrates route presents a striking con trast to that via Egypt, which, during a portion of the year, could not be used for the transport of troops without a serious sacrifice of life, in conse quence of the excessive heat of the Red Sea. The Euphrates route, on the other hand, would be available for this purpose at all seasons. The substitution of Kurrachee for Bombay as the European port of India would, even by the Red Sea route, give us an advantage of some 500 miles ; but, if the Euphrates route were once established, the adoption of Kurrachee as the European port of India would necessarily follow, and India would thus be brought upwards of 1,000 miles nearer to us than at present; while, during the monsoon months, the gain would be still greater, as the route between the Persian Gulf and Kurrachee is not exposed to the severity of the monsoon, which, it is well known, renders a divergence of some 500 miles necessary during a portion of the year on the voyage from Bombay to Aden. Kurrachee is now in railway connection with Lahore, Calcutta, and Bombay, and, when the railway system of the Valley of the Indus is completed as far as the19 Bolan and Khyber Passes, and extended to Can- dahar, the safety of India would be ensured. May I be permitted to repeat the words which I ventured to urge upon Lord Palmerston upwards of twenty years ago, when I accompanied, in support of the Euphrates Yalley Railway, one of the largest and most influential deputations that ever waited upon a Minister:— ' The grand object desired is to connect England with the north-west frontier of India bj steam transit through the Euphrates and Indus valleys. The latter will render movable to either the Khyber or the Bolan, the two gates of India, the flower of the British army cantoned in the Punjaub; and the Euphrates and Indus lines being connected by means of steamers, we should be enabled to threaten the flank and rear of any force advancing through Persia towards India. So that by this great scheme the invasion of India would be placed beyond even speculation, and it is evident that the great army of India of 300,000 men being thus united to the army of England, the mutual support they would render each other would quadruple the power and ascendancy of this country, and promote powerfully the progress, the freedom, and the peace of the world.' The Euphrates and Indus lines together would, moreover, secure for us almost the control of the trade with Central Asia, enabling us to meet Rus sia, our great competitor in these distant fields of commercial enterprise, on more than equal terms. But it is not on commercial considerations that I would urge the claims of the Euphrates Valley Railway. It is on Imperial grounds that the scheme20 commends itself to our consideration. 1 believe that the establishment of the Euphrates route would add incalculably to our prestige throughout Europe and the East, and would do more to strengthen our hold on India than any other means that could be devised. If twenty years ago the subject was one of vital importance, how much more so is it now. From political complications in the Bast and our vast and rapidly augmenting commerce with India, our responsibilities in Asiatic Turkey have increased in gravity, and it is our duty, not merely to develop its resources, but to utilise it for our Imperial ends. An alternative route to India which shall make us independent of the Suez Canal is a national necessity; and when such a scheme will at the same time tend to the improvement of our relations with Turkey, and aid in the material prosperity of that country, its promotion becomes doubly advisable from a moral, a commercial, a political, and a strategical point of view. Although fully alive to the vast importance of the results which would accrue, not only to Eng land and India, but to the cause of civilisation generally, from the establishment of continuous railway communication between Europe and India, I cannot conceal from myself that such a project is too vast to be at once undertaken with any hope of success. But the Euphrates Valley Railway, as proposed, ;from the Gulf of Scanderoon to the21 Persian Gulf, has been specially designed with a view to its ultimately forming part of a through line from Constantinople to the head of the Persian Gulf, while it is capable, also, of being, in due time, extended eastward to Kurrachee, the port of India nearest to Europe. The line from the Mediterranean to the Persian Gulf has been demon strated to be eminently practicable and easy, which the other portions of the route between Constanti nople and India are not. While capable of forming part of a through line, it would, at the same time, be complete in itself, and independent of any dis turbances in Europe—the only portion, in fact, of a through line of railway which would be always, and under all circumstances, at the absolute control of this country. It would always be to this country the most important portion of any through line ; and, indeed, I believe a through line could not be constructed, except at overwhelming cost, without the assistance of a port in northern Syria. It would, moreover, provide us with a complete alter native route to India, and would thus at once secure to this country advantages admitted to be of the highest national moment. It is for these reasons that, during the long period in which I have de voted myself to the advocacy of the Euphrates route to India, I have thought it expedient to urge upon our own Government and that of Turkey the special claims of that section only which would connect the Mediterranean with the Persian Gulf.22 The objection that, although the Euphrates Valley Railway would afford us the undoubted advantage of an alternative, a shorter, and a more rapid means of communication with India, it would still leave a considerable portion of the journey to be accom plished by sea, and that, consequently, it would accelerate our communications with the Bast in a minor degree only, is sufficiently disposed of by the circumstance already pointed out—that a railway from a point on the Mediterranean, at or near Scanderoon, to the head of the Persian Gulf, would naturally form part of a through line of railway from Constantinople to India, if, at a future time, it should be considered necessary or desirable to construct the remaining sections. In the meantime the evils inseparable from trans-shipment would be more than compensated by the saving of time. But it must be borne in mind that the passage of troops or warlike stores through Europe from London to Constantinople would be impracticable in time of war owing to international law, and this undoubtedly points to the necessity of a port on the Mediterranean which, commanded by the guns of the British fleet, shall afford a safe terminus to the railway at all times. At the same time, it is to be observed that any possible acceleration of the journey between Europe and India, by the substitution of railway for sea transit, would be, relatively, much less in the case of those portions of the route traversing Asia Minor23 on the one hand, and Persia and Beloochistan on the other, than on the central section between Scanderoon and the Persian Gulf; the latter sec tion being almost level for nearly the whole distance, and therefore capable of being traversed at a very high rate of speed ; whereas, both in Asia Minor and Persia, the gradients would be so severe as to neutralise, in a great measure, the advantages ordi narily attaching to railway travelling as compared with that by sea. Fro rata to the power required, so is the distance. In other words, the proposed Euphrates Valley Railway would take advantage of precisely that portion of the route between Con stantinople and India where the greatest benefit would be derivable from the substitution of railway for sea transit, whether regard be had to the rate of speed attainable or the economy with which the traffic might be worked. A regular mail service being already in operation on the maritime portions of the Euphrates route to India—maintained, on the Mediterranean side, by French steam packets calling at Alexandretta, and between the ports of the Persian Gulf and Kurra- chee and Bombay by the vessels of the British India Steam Navigation Company—a railway of little more than 900 miles in length, from Scande roon (or Aiexandretta), on the Mediterranean, to Kowait (or Grain), on the Persian Gulf, is all that is required to secure for us the immense political and strategic advantage of a complete alternative24 route to India; a shorter and more rapid route than now exists, and one, moreover, which com pares very favourably with the Red Sea route, both as regards climate and the facility and safety of the navigation. Both Alexandretta and Kowait, the proposed termini of the railway, possess all the requisites of first-class harbours. The harbour of Alexandretta is one of great capacity; sufficient, according to Sir John Franklin, Admiral Beaufort, and others, to contain the whole navy of Great Britain. It is the safest harbour on the coast of Syria, and might be made available for the purposes of the railway at a very small outlay. The place is, at present, open to some objection on account of unhealthiness; but this dis advantage might be entirely obviated by drainage at a moderate expenditure. With the exception of the Beilan hill in the rear of Alexandretta, there is no engineering difficulty of magnitude throughout the whole route. With regard to the harbour of Kowait, near the head of the Persian Griilf, Mr. William Parkes, who was, at my request, by the liberality of the Indian authorities, enabled to examine the ports in the Persian Gulf, states, in an able report, ad dressed to me on the subject, that ' nothing could be more secure or favourable in any way' (than Kowait) &lt;k for ships of the largest size, whether to ride at anchor, or to be moored alongside a quay25 wall.' As a place for landing and embarking pas sengers, mails, and cargo, even without sea-works more extensive than a short jetty to bring a steam tender alongside, Mr. Parkes reports that Kowait ' was superior to Alexandria, to Suez, and to Bombay, before the completion of recent improve ments ; while, for an expenditure of from £80,000 to £100,000, a wharf of sufficient length to berth four steamers, of 3,000 tons each, might be con structed, and the railway brought down upon it, thus placing Kowait on a par, in this respect, with Suez as it is, Brindisi, or Dover.' Kowait is already one of the most important towns in the Gulf, and, according to Captain .A. D. Taylor, late of Her Majesty's Indian Navy, possesses more baghalahs, or boats of the country, than any other port in the Gulf which trades with India; and there can be no doubt, if it be adopted as the eastern terminus of the railway, it will, within a very short period, have an enormous trade of its own, irrespective of the through traffic passing over the railway. As regards the route which the railway should take between Alexandretta and the Persian Gulf, it is to be borne in mind that the great and primary object of the undertaking is the connection of the Mediterranean Sea and the Persian Gulf by rail way; and, the necessity of such a connection having been once established, the precise line which the railway should take would appear to be compara- 326 tively a* matter of less vital importance. I may observe, however, that, passing in the first place from Alexandretta, the proposed terminus on the Mediterranean, to Aleppo, a great entrepot of trade, the route from that place to the Persian Grulf having much the strongest arguments in its favour would appear to be that recommended by Captain Felix Jones, keeping on the right bank of the Euphrates for the whole distance, beyond the reach of inundations, and passing by way of Annah, Hit (the Is of Herodotus), the holy cities of Kerbela and Nedjef (or Meshed Ali), Semarwah, and Siik- esh-Sheyukh to Kowait or Grain, on the Persian Gulf. This line would not pass many miles from Bagdad. This city and the neighbouring holv places of Kerbela and Nedjef are frequently chosen by Sheeah Mahommedans as a residence, that they may be buried by the side of Hoosein, their favourite saint, whose tomb at Xerbela is the peculiar object of their veneration, and is annually bedewed with the tears of thousands. The burial- place of Ali Nedjef, though of inferior sanctity, is also held in great veneration. Pensioners of the Government of India, natives of the highest rank, frequently make Bagdad or Kerbela their adopted home; and, both from Persia and Hindustan, un told wealth has been poured into the coffers of the priests of Kerbela. The route which I have traced from Alexandretta to the Persian Gulf—besides being, probably, the27 shortest line obtainable—would obviate altogether the necessity and expense of crossing the Eu phrates. This line, moreover, regarded from a strategic point of view, would give the advantage of the interposition of two great rivers between the railway and an enemy advancing on the flank on which there would be the greatest likelihood of attack. The two termini, being on the open sea, would be, virtually, under the guns of our ships, and the value of the island of Cyprus would be demonstrated as a place d'armes. ' Sir Samuel Baker, in the Times the other day, asked if any one could tell him what was now the use to England of the island of Cyprus. Prince Bismarck was told by Lord Beacons- field at the Congress that it was meant, among other uses, to cover and protect the terminus of the Euphrates Valley Eailway when that inevitable overland route to India should be finished. Let Englishmen look to it.'—Berlin Correspondent, Times, 12th June, 1882. The opening up of the Euphrates route would afford an additional guarantee for the integrity of the Ottoman Empire; would tend, in a great mea sure, to a peaceful solution of the Eastern question; and would enable us more easily to discharge the grave responsibilities we have incurred in the vir tual protectorate of Asia Minor. The proposed railway would consolidate the dominions of the Porte, by bringing the ancient Pachaliks of Aleppo and Bagdad into closer communication with the seat of Government, The grand impediment to the28 improvement of the Sultan's dominions is the want of means of intercommunication j and no line would piomote more effectually their good government and prosperity, or do more to develop their really prodigious resources, than that which would lay open, to the energy and capital of the emigrant and merchant of the West, the extensive and fertile plains of the Euphrates and Tigris. ihe cost of the most difficult portion of the rail- way, surveyed and estimated for by General Chesney and feir John Macneill, and an engineering staff, Avas 7,500 per mile; my estimate has been higher, to make allowance for the fluctuations in the price of iron and other expenditure. As a chain is made in links, so must the railway be completed in sections; a line from Alexandretta to Balus would connect the Mediterranean with the Euphrates, and at once diminish the enormous freight paid on the conveyance of goods by camels, especially between Aleppo and Alexandretta. 11 we are to aid in the regeneration of Turkey, what more feasible plan presents itself than the development of the internal resources of her provinces which lie on the high road to India? Ihe first outlay to connect the Mediterranean with the Euphrates is £1,400,000. This first section, by opening up a practical, although a temporary, river transit, would test the whole matter in all human probability.' Local traffic will more than suffice to pay the ordinary interest29 on this section; but if Government are in earnest in their endeavour to ameliorate the condition of the Porte, a guarantee of 3^ per cent., or about £50,000 a year, on this small sum would be more than repaid by the enhanced prosperity which would most undoubtedly result to the population of this almost virgin territory, and the new marts which would be created for a commerce. One more link in the chain which rivets India to England having been forged, the strategic advantage of Cyprus would be conspicuously displayed, the com pactness and power of the empire would be greatly promoted, and we should be prepared for the coming struggle, which will not be m the i emote reo-ion of Central Asia, but in the less-distant plains o of Armenia or Mesopotamia. Let me recall for a moment to your notice the political inheritance said to have been bec[ueathed by Peter the Great to his successors in his will, whether genuine or apocryphal. ' We must,' says that remarkable document, which first became publicly known in 1837, ' incessantly extend ourselves towards the north, the Baltic Sea, and towaids the south, the Mediterranean. We must advance as much as possible towards Constantinople and India. Whoever shall reign there will be the true masters of the world. Lhercfore, wc must face continual wars, sometimes with Persia; create dockyards and emporiums on the Black Sea; take possession, little by little, of that sea, as well as of30 tlie Baltic, which is a point doubly necessary for the success of the plan ; hasten the downfall of Persia; advance into the Gulf of Persia as far as can be done, re-establish through Syria the ancient commerce of the East, and enter into the two Indies, which are the stores of the world. When once there, we can do without the gold of England.' The policy of Russia has certainly been in accord ance with the above. The old southern boundary of Russia in Central Asia extended from the Ural, north of the Caspian, by Orenburg and Orsk, to the old Mongolian city of Semipolatinsk, and was guarded by a cordon of Cossack outposts. In 1716, Peter the Great sent a force, commanded by Prince Bekovitch, to take possession of part of the eastern shore of the Caspian. Three forts were then built, though subsequently abandoned, after an unsuccessful expedition against the Khivans. More recently, since 1834, Russia has succeeded in firmly esta blishing herself on the eastern shore of the Caspian, where she has now four permanent posts, Fort Alexandrovsk, Krasnovodsk, at the mouth of the Balkan Gulf, Chakishlar, at the mouth of the Attruck, and the Island of. Ashurda. To the east she has crossed the Kirghis Steppe, and established herself on the Sir Daria or Jaxartes, which Admiral Boutakoff is said to have navigated for 1,000 miles in 1863. Thus the Russian frontier in Central Asia31 has been pushed forward, until her advanced posts on the east look down from the Tian Shan range upon the plains of Chinese Turkestan. In the successive campaigns which the late dis- tinquished conqueror and military ruler General Kaufmann conducted against Bokhara, against Khiva, and against Khokand, he greatly increased the Asiatic dominions and influence of Russia, while narrowing the zone of debateable ground which separated her from the countries under the govern ment or control of England. As the result of his success he exercised for many years almost un limited authority in Central Asia. He found no resistance to his advance in any quarter but the British Empire ; and consequently his whole policy assumed an anti-English complexion, and his court at Tashkend was more than suspected of being the source whence sprang all the difficulties which have beset British policy in the East during the last fifteen years. Tashkend was in the centre of a number of semi- barbarous, divided, and decaying states, ready to fall a prey to a strong and aggressive neighbour. The expedition to Khiva was the most notorious act of General Kaufmann's government. Count Schouvaloff assured Lord Granville, then English Foreign Minister, that nothing was intended by the expedition except to punish acts of brigandage, and that the Russians would not take possession of, or even for any length of time occupy, Khiva. 4 *32 General Kaufmann remained several months in Khiva, in spite of Count Schouvaloff's assurances, on pretext of re-organising the khanate. The re sult of the expedition was to make Khiva completely dependent on Russia. The absorption by Russia in succession of Bo khara, Khiva, and Khokand brought her into the close proximity of Afghanistan, and General Kauf mann seems to have next directed his ambitious designs to that quarter. The disposition of Shere Ali, who had become estranged from us, favoured his views. His emissaries were despatched into Afghanistan. The Russian Embassy, the reception of which by the Ameer precipitated the Afghan war, may be attributed to his instigation. But when the invasion of Afghanistan by the British troops took place, General Kaufmann found that his Government was not prepared to take any further aggressive steps. In thus pursuing her career of annexation, Rus sia but follows the natural policy of a great military empire; being forced, moreover, as Sir John Mal colm said, by an impelling power which civilisation cannot resist when in contact with barbarism. And thus is her influence established on the Oxus and Jaxartes. The Oxus, or Amu Daria, is a noble river, not easy of navigation, but, it is believed, capable of being made so. It will furnish a ready means of carrying the tide of Russian annexation eastward until it finds a barrier in the Hindoo33 Koosh. When Russia shall have established her self along the Oxus, her position will be at once menacing to Persia and India. From Chardjuy on the Oxus, there is a road to Merv, distant about 150 miles, and from Merv a direct road runs along the Valley of the Murghab to Herat, the so-called 'key of India.' Merv is, historically, a part of the Persian Empire, but, in these countries, it is notoriously difficult to define boundaries with any precision. Should Russia succeed in occupying ]^ erv —ag there is too much reason to fear that she ultimately will—and in converting the neigh bouring tribes into friends or allies, her position would be one which would necessitate still greater vigilance on our part. Surely, in the face of such facts as these, the time has arrived when England should rouse her self from the apathy of the past, and take steps to secure the incalculable advantages which would accrue to herself and her Eastern dependencies from the opening up of the Euphrates route, which would threaten the flank and rear of any force advancing towards India. The subject, important as it is in its bearing on the power and stability of the whole British Em pire, is one of absolutely vital moment to India; but it should not be forgotten that all our Eastern possessions would participate in the benefits which would accrue from the establishment of the Eu- phrates route.34 There is ample reason to believe that the pro posed undertaking would prove remunerative at no distant date; at the same time, the results sought are far more important than those which are usually looked for in a pecuniary investment. Why should we not regard the Euphrates Railway as the French regarded the Suez Canal before it was a commercial success ? In the words of a recent writer :— 'Nations may receive much larger returns for judicious outlay than any to be commonly looked for by shareholders ; for the results in material prosperity to be derived by a com munity from augmented facility of communication, from moral and political progress, and, above all, from an increased security for peace, far transcend in value any conceivable amount of dividends, and should be taken into account in determining as to the propriety of lending Governmental assistance in parti cular instances.' The general features of the projected Euphrates Valley Railway may be thus briefly summed up :— 1. It would connect the Mediterranean with the head of the Persian Gulf, between which and Kur- rachee and Bombay regular communication is now maintained by a line of powerful steamers, sub sidised by the Indian Government. 2. Making Kurrachee the European port of India in place of Bombay, it would save about 1,000 miles in the distance between England and India, and by the substitution of railway for boat transit would reduce the time occupied in the journey by one-half, i.e. to 10 days instead of 20 days.35 3. It would render it possible to maintain India with a smaller European garrison than is now necessary, and would thus reduce our military expenditure. 4. It would save the Government large sums, in sudden emergencies, by the facilities it would afford —and that at all seasons of the year—for the trans port of troops and stores. 5. It would enable troops from England to be landed at Kurrachee in about fourteen days, and in two or three days more at Lahore, Peshawur, or Delhi. 6. It would subject an enemy advancing towards the north-western frontier of India to easy attack in the flank and rear, and would render the invasion of India all but impossible. 7. It would make the resources of England so promptly available in the East that any hostile movement directed against us, whether from within or without our Indian frontier, might thus be effec tually checked before it could assume formidable proportions. 8. It would give our extensive military establish ments in India a direct influence in support of our power and prestige in Europe. 9. It would give England the first strategical position in the world. 10. It would facilitate the protection of Asia Minor by England. 11. It would relieve Persia from the predomina-36 ting influence of Eussia, by giving her access to a port on the Mediterranean. 12. It would be easily defensible by England, both of its termini being on the open sea. 13. It would be protected, on the flank most likely to be assailed, by two formidable rivers, the Euphrates and Tigris, whilst the possession of Cyprus by England gives us an admirable place d'armes for covering the terminus of the railway at Alexandretta or Seleucia. 14. The length of the railway, from Alexandretta, on the Mediterranean, to Grain, on the Persian Gulf, would be about 920 miles. 15. The country is admirably adapted for the construction of a railway, and the cost of the line is estimated at from £8,000 to £10,000 per mile. 16. The capital which would be required would thus be under £10,000,000. These views I have advocated for many years, they have been concurred in by Musuras Pasha, the Turkish Ambassador, and the late Mr. Brassey, and adopted in the report by the Special Committee of the House of Commons in 1872. In a recent discussion on the Euphrates Railway, Sir Henry Tyler gave it as his opinion that ' the Empire of India is a source of enormous strength and wealth to this country, and no more important measure for strengthening the empire generally could be devised than that of improving the com munication between the 34 millions of Great Britain87 and the 220 millions of our subjects in India. There is no better way of accomplishing that end than by constructing this railway.' Sir Henry Drummond Wolff observed that, 'dis guise it how we may, there is no doubt that our great enemy is Russia; and though we may diplo matise and negotiate, and put off the evil day, sooner or later we shall be hand to hand with Russia in the East.' Mr. J. L. Haddan, late Engineer-in-Chief at Aleppo, remarked that the Euphrates Valley Railway meets the great military requirements of run ning towards, but not parallel to, the Persian frontier; while the two great rivers protect its flank.' Some time ago the leading journal said ' the most important of all the railways talked of in the East is that of the Euphrates Valley.' From the East, India is stretching forth her hand to meet us there in an unbroken communication from Calcutta to Kurrachee on the Arabian Sea, 2,200 miles in length. Private enterprise has successfully, by a line of steamers, connected the Euphrates and the Indus, and the produce of the grain-producing countries of Mesopotamia is being diverted from the port of Alexandretta by the steamers of the Euphrates and Tigris Steam Navigation Company, which bring it down to the Persian Gulf. The Euphrates is now as navigable as it was when Chesney, more than 40 years ago, with calm38 heroism, took the soundings of the river, at the risk of his life, from the suspicion and fanaticism of the Arabs who accompanied him on the raft. One of the boats of the Euphrates and Tigris Steam Navigation Company ascended in May, 1879, from Feleugia, on the Euphrates, opposite Bagdad, to Balus, 43 miles from Aleppo, or about 130 miles from Alexandretta, on the Mediterranean, with 100 passengers and merchandise, without having met with any serious obstruction. The river being thus navigable would facilitate greatly the con struction of the railway Such marvellous improvements have been made in our railways and our steamboats, that I may safely say that mails by the Euphrates Valley Route from the Mediterranean to the Persian Gulf would be landed at Kurrachee within ten days after leaving London. From the earliest times Asia Minor and Meso potamia have been looked upon as among the wealthiest countries in the world. The mineral wealth is enormous which yet remains hidden in the bowels of the earth. They might produce cotton enough to clothe their neighbour Russia, as well as Turkey, yet, for want of transport, this and other vegetable produce lies rotting in the fields. The necessity for this railway has been demon strated by soldiers, diplomatists, merchants, and travellers, and it was specially approved by a Select Committee of the House of Commons in 1872 #39 The military and political value of the Euphrates line is a matter of extreme moment, and has a far more decided bearing on the defence, not only of Turkey, but of Persia, and the whole district lying between the Mediterranean, the Caspian, and the Indian Ocean, than might at first be supposed. So long ago as 1858, Field-Marshal Lieutenant Baron ^Cuhn Von Kuhnenfeld, Austrian War Minister, predicted that Russia would, in future, probably, try to satisfy her craving for an open seaboard by operating through Asia:— ' She will not,' says this distinguished authority, ' reach the shores of the Persian Gulf in oae stride, or by means of one great war; but, taking advantage of Continental compli cations, when the attention and energy of European states are engaged in contests more nearly concerning them, she will endeavour to reach the Persian Gulf step by step—by annex ing separate districts of Armenia, by operating against Khiva and Bokhara, and by seizing Persian provinces. . . . ' The most important lines which Russia must keep in view for these great conquests are— ' 1. The line from Kars to the Valley of the Euphrates and Mesopotamia. ' 2. That from Erivan, by Lake Van to Mossul, in the Valley of the Tigris, to Mesopotamia, and thence, after junction with the first line, to Bagdad. ' 3. That from Tabrez to Schuster, in the Valley of the Kercha, where it joins. ' 4. The road leading from Teheran, by Ispahan, to Schuster, and thence to the Persian Gulf. . . . ' Once in possession of the Euphrates, the road to the Mediterranean, via Aleppo and Antioch, and to the conquest of Asia Minor and Syria, is but short. ' It is clear that all these lines are intersected by the line of40 the Euphrates, which, running in an oblique direction from the head of the gulf north of Antioch to the Persian Gulf, passes along the diagonal of a great quadrilateral, which has its two western corners on the Mediterranean, its two eastern on the Caspian and Persian seas, and so takes all Russian lines of advance in flank. ' From this, it is evident that the secure possession of the Euphrates line is decisive, as regards the ownership of all land lying within the quadrilateral. It must, therefore, be the political and strategic task of Russia to get the Euphrates line into her hands, and that of her enemies to prevent her doing so at any cost. ' The great importance of a railway along this decisive line, which connects Antioch with the Persian Gulf, follows as a matter of course. It is the only means by which it would be possible to concentrate, at any moment, on the Euphrates, or in the northern portion of Mesopotamia, a force sufficiently strong to operate on the flanks of the Russian line of advance, and stop any forward movement. . . . ' It is true, at first, the aggressive policy of Russia in the East will only threaten the kingdoms of Turkey and Persia; but, as neither one nor the other, nor both combined, would be strong enough, without assistance, to meet the danger suc cessfully, England must do so; and it is certain that she must, sooner or later, become engaged in a fierce contest for supremacy with Russia. 'The Euphrates Valley Railway becomes, therefore, a factor of inestimable importance in the problem of this great contest. Even now, the construction of the line will counteract the Asiatic policy of Russia, for it will strengthen the influence of England in Central Asia, and weaken that of Russia. ' The growth of Russia in the East threatens, though in directly, the whole of Europe, as well as the states named above; for, if she were firmly established in Asia Minor, the real apple of discord, Constantinople, would be in imminent danger, all the commerce of the Mediterranean would fall into41 her hands, and she would command the canal through the Isthmus of Suez. ' Whatever the commercial value of the Suez Canal to Central Europe, there is no doubt that it is secondary in im portance to the Euphrates Railway, which affords the only means of stemming Russian advances in Central Asia, and which directly covers the Suez Canal.' We have seen that the report of the Special Committee* of the House of Commons advocates the plan which I have endeavoured to explain to you, based on the evidence of Lord Stratford de Redcliffe, Field Marshal Lord Strathnairn, Sir Bartle Frere, Sir Henry Eawlinson, the Consuls along the route, Sir John Macneill, and other competent witnesses, and by the distinguished explorer of the route, General Chesney, and his surviving officers. Looked at in every light, historically, politically, and commercially, the proposed restoration of the ancient route of the Euphrates, throwing open the portals of the East to the commerce of the world, and to the arts, the sciences, and civilisation of the West, is an in teresting and noble design, fraught with consequences of the highest moment to the destinies of our race. * In addition to deputations to Ministers, lectures, various publications in newspapers and otherwise, and the report of the Special Committee of the House of Commons just referred to in favour of improved communication with India, an Association was formed at Stafford House under the auspices of the Duke of Sutherland. This well organised and powerful association failed from attempting too much, endeavouring to obtain the support of Government for the gigantic design of connecting Constantinople with the Head of the Persian Gulf, instead of being satisfied with the construction in the first instance of a moderate section of the Railway.42 To plant industry and the arts where indolence and barbarism have hitherto prevailed—to hasten the day when the breath from the four winds, as foreshadowed by the prophet, will breathe upon the slain, and the dry bones will live; when 'the wastes shall be builded, and the desolate land shall be tilled, and men shall say, ' This land that was desolate is become like the Garden of Eden, and the waste, and desolate, and ruined cities are be come fenced, and are inhabited.' u So shall the waste cities be filled with flocks of men.' To accomplish this noble undertaking is the mission of England. Its fulfllment has already been too long delayed. Another nation, as Lord Beaconsfield, some years ago, took occasion to re mind us, is slowly, but surely, extending her power eastwards, and is gradually establishing a footing in military positions, from which she can at once menace our empire in the East, and diminish our power and prestige among the nations of Europe; and I would close this paper by urging my con viction, that if we continue to neglect securing the establishment of the Euphrates route under the auspices of Great Britain, we shall speedily find that the shortest, easiest, and safest route to our eastern possessions has fallen into the hands of our most powerful rival for commercial and political ascendancy in the East.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100023550128.0x000001_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>P/T 5553</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100023550128.0x000001</url><physicalLocation>British Library: Printed Collections</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>P/T 5553</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Euphrates Valley Route to India, in connection with the Central Asian and Egyptian questions. Lecture delivered at the National Club on the 16th June, 1882'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1882/1882</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-10-31T11:58:24</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (42 pages)</extent><extent>Dimensions: 218mm x 128mm</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Euphrates Valley Route to India, in connection with the Central Asian and Egyptian questions. Lecture delivered at the National Club on the 16th June, 1882Publication Details: London : W. H. Allen &amp; Co., 1882.Physical Description: 95 p. ; 8º.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>William H Allen and Company, booksellers and publishers, London</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">publisher</roleTerm></role></name><name type="personal"><namePart>William Patrick Andrew</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Railroads--Euphrates River Valley</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100023550128.0x000001#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>