<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100041798026.0x000001_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-09-25T11:22:30.953Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100041798026.0x000001_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>Delhi Arabic 1898</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100041798026.0x000001</url><physicalLocation>British Library: Oriental Manuscripts</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>Delhi Arabic 1898</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Sharḥ al-Mūjaz al-musammá ḥisāban yasīran شرح الموجز المسمى حسابًا يسيرًا</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1700/1799</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-03-27T22:02:35</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>Codex; ff. vi+200+ii</extent><extent>Material: Eastern laid paperDimensions: 227 x 160 mm leaf [145-155 x 75-85 mm written]Foliation: Eaastern Arabic foliation in black ink at middle of head margin; India Office Library foliation stamped in black inkRuling: No ruling visible; 13-17 lines per page; vertical spacing 9-12 lines per 10 cmScript:
                           Nasta‘līq; more than one scribe, changes of hand at ff. 86r, 111r, 128r, 136r, and 160r.Ink: Black ink, with lemmata in redBinding: India Office binding in purple clothCondition: Much insect damage, without loss of textMarginalia: Corrections and notes by more than one handSeals: ff. 1r and 199v</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Anonymous commentary on a treatise on arithmetic titled The Summary Called Easy Arithmetic (الموجز المسمى حسابًا يسيرًا), by al-Hadīyah Aḥmad ibn Mas‘ūd al-Ḥasaynī al-Hargāmī (الهدية أحمد بن مسعود الحسيني الهرگامي, d. 1175/1761-2). The text of the commentary (or perhaps of the text commented upon) was completed in 1150/1737-38 (see f. 199r, line 2, transcribed below).The lemmata commented upon are rubricated in some sections of the manuscript and overlined in others. The text contains numerous diagrams.Begins (f. 1v, lines 2-4):أحمد تحميد حمدًا فهو حامد تحميد ومحمد ألف محامد وبعد فهذا حل اقتباسي في علم الحسابوجل اقتناصي في هذا الباب في الرسالة تشرح (!) الحساب حسابًا يسيرًا وفي النسخةتتنسخ نسخه نسخًا كثيرًا فأقول بعون الله الكريم ...Ends (f. 199r, lines 2-5):... فتم الكتاب بعون رب العالمين في ألف وماية وخمسين من هجرة سيد المرسلين عليه الصلوةوالسلام وعلى آله وأصحابه الكرام وعلى عبده الضعيف العامي الهدية بن مسعود الحسيني الهركاميغفر الله له ولوالديه وأحسن إليهما وإليه ورضي الله تعالى عنا وعن جميع المسلمين بحرمة شفيع المجرمينسيد المرسلين صلى الله عليه وعليهم أجمعين برحمتك يا أرحم الراحمين ...Colophon (f. 199r, lines 5-6):... تمت الرسالة المسماة بحسابًايسيرًا من تصنيف قدوة المحققين زبدة المدققين مولوي مير سيد الهدية حسيني هركامي</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Arithmetic -- Early works to 1900</topic></subject><subject><topic>Mathematics -- Early works to 1800</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100041798026.0x000001#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>