<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000380_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T14:18:28.108Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">\ (&gt;V } p Te le rom H* . Minister, J edld^* Xo H. . secretary of Jt&amp;te for Foreign .affaire London* fo *103 Hepea ted &gt; oil tio il He wide lit, uehire. : 0 .i 6 OoTermoent of India, dw .Delhi. daYin^ * Dated 3Cth December received 3let December 1937. inis try of 'oreign affairs replied in a note (text by bag of December 29th} nhich hat? been supplemented by conversation® with fuaci. attitude of naudi Arabian foverument ie thisi (1) Until final aettlement a® to disputed area is concluded oil people from naudi siae will not enter it provided there is similar abstention by Company operating in crab state® on the 1 eralan 4ilf♦ ( 2 ) they have always been ready to oouolude agreement. Obstacle has been unwilllngneaa of Hie Majesty 1 a Govern ment to recognize ^actual situation of whit is in reality in possession and wider influenue ’ 1 of Ibn d a ud# Consequently (3) a® to proposed mission they aak whether His Majesty*a dovernroent do not share their opi don that it is advisable to agree u on frontier in rriaciple first by specifying either places or co-ordinatee. Lab,.! dakhsh, Khor al Ode id and Hifuk from motives of presti e exaceroated by poverty and smell of oil. Several paper® from nushire on files bear out Ibn d&amp;ud*s statement Ibn daud clings as tenaciously as ever to that/that 11 ie he and not our friend© who administers at least the first two of taints in dispute. 1 am mare that historical o ae oe« much further back ana th:t settlement by tribal in torch ui&lt;ge has been ruled on t. -hat 1 want to avoid is forcin,. issue while into rational situation is so disturbed and 1 thim. it would be worth while to refrain fro© proepeotin;.. ; in dleputed area and to dra^; out negotiation© and Wait better time a* Uould we not rt i‘ly in soruio of follow* lag para, raph V 3. Hi© Majesty* s ^vernment are i^lua to 1 tarn of instructs on© which have been given to ^11 Company operating in Hasu They cannot see hov it is possible to make any further concession in regard to a frontier which they adopt in accordance with customary and essential needs of a*&amp;b states concerned but in a spirit of conciliation they will see that 'll Romany operating in those states does not enter the disputed territory for the present. They do no t share view that proposed mission is pointless since their contention ic that d&amp;udl claim is based in part on incorrect topograph* ia&amp;l data. Object of mission would not be to bind either tide out to establish certain facte and Hie Majesty's Govern* ®«nt trust *%udi -crabian Government will agree to its aes* patch* 4. Use of phrase 4 for the resent* would ehow that His t ajesty 1 s (loverlament were not necessarily prepared to prevent prospecting in disputed area until conclusion of an agreement with Tbn laud. 5 5. The Hag will probably come to Jedda January 10 th or later to meet French High domm!ssioner from byria and i should like to be prepared with a reply on this subject but I know how complicated it is and if I have no instructions by then 1 will speak in ouch a way as will I ho e ensure that '&gt;il Company work in in Gaudi territory will not enter disputed© Tele gr as B -roo l s oli ticol Heeide it, Buahire• To H* '4 m ^eorttaJpy of State for ludlat London# Repeated H#t . Uinietcr, Jed&amp;a* So^y by air mail to Government of India* Hew ieIhi. i oli tical itgeat, B^ihr&amp;iu« Ro. 26 Sated the 6 th January lv 36 # / v Isdda telegram of 30th Jecamber .: v ?o#103 to foreign Office. SaTOI ?Hn.^rx:5H. I would oe grateful for references to Bu^hire paper® mentioned in paragraph 2 . 2 . I appreciate Bullard*a arguments but action suggested in firet two sentence* of hi® paragraph 3 cut® across rights of both Joispany and nhaikh under oonoeeeion agreed to by His Majesty’s So^extaatnt# proviso 11 for the preeent 1 * miohi in practice I fear mean until conclusion of agreement with Ibn ^aud, ae having conceded him this point now it might oe difficult to rescind it at any particular time in the future. 3. He# si eel on 1 entirely agx’ee. Only rea boo I caa see for Saudic to refuse it that they know ing they have bad 9Mt and wish to avoid - ’ -V' ftdfcd on the ground#CONFIDENTIAL. No. gi.s 0 f 1938 . (7 i The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to 1 ./Secretary to the Government of India, External Affairs apartment, .Hew Delhi. 2. Political Agent, Bahrain. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment (s). British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. h • \T anuarry • Reference to previous correspondence: Jedda telegram Ho. 10 of 9th January to Foreign Office Description of Enclosure. ll) Name and Date. &amp; 2 . ll) Jedda telegram Ho. 10 of 9 th January 1938 to For eign Office. (2) Political Resident’s tel egram Ho. 36 of 11th Jan uary 1938 to India Office.Teletpr&amp;in $rom H.M. Minister, Je&amp;da. To H*M* Secretary of State for foreign .affairs, London, L f o,iG Ivepeated l olitiaal Kesideut, Bushire • Ho. 1 Governinent of India, :5sw Delhi. Saving Dated 9th January received 10th January 1958 / Telegram Ho. 26 of January 6th from lolitioal Resident to India Office. ’’or references see hie telegram -%.T/iv of January 11th 1934 and telegram o. T/98 of April 5th 1934, I have not overlooked his demi-official letter 'to.a/157 of Kuroh 3Cth 1934. / as to paragraph 3 difficulty is that ^ ‘ IX Saudis maintain that among facts on ground are their administration and jurisdiction over j omission) . h.m, mi hut ;a, jkdda.CONFIDENTIAL. No. c/21 of 1938. s. Op The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to 1. Ttie Secretary to tne Government of India, External Affairs Department, New Delhi. 2. The Political Agent, Bahrain, y and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents (// Office of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Camp, Kuwait. Dated..Jan^y.. .X9.33, Reference to previous correspondence: Residency Printed letter No.bl-S of the 11th January 1938. Z~/J J Q \ &gt; 4.Y Description of Enclosure, Name and Date. Subject. Jedda telegram No.14 of the llth January 1938 to the Foreign Office. Saudi Frontier. v AThe Hon’ble the Pditical Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Political Agent* Bahrain. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents (*)• British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated. jSra.J’.ehruary. 193Q. M c '■&gt; [, iV Reference to previous correspondence: 4 i° •PS iH i9 .&lt; ' '■ J s \ ! Residency Printed Letter No.C/21, dated Ibth January 1958. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. 1. Enclosure in Foreign Office covering note dated 25rd December 19SY, No.E.Y^/gbayai. Z. Jedaa Despatch to Foreign Office No.187(1846/430/80), Subject, Saudi Arabia Frontiers. Wl XHo explained ti'mt a similar oa muniaatioa had boe... ado t &gt; Ibn 3 aud on this 'question thr )Ugh His majesty f s int&lt; r in Jodda; and he repeated that the oonse ;aenoas woalu bo lost onf oriunuto ami ombarr^^&amp;sing If th© a an any ware t, ext. t i&amp; its operations into either atar or -ba Uhabi terrltor; 03 shown on this .m.j* 6 * Mr* Hamilton ox plained that tiie Ooapany h.\d obtained from Xbn iaad a ruling how far the;/ could go* the last thing* they wished to do was to cause His Majesty 1 a lov©roaoat any embarrass^ nt» a.M the.- entirely appreciated ihe .. os it ion# The? had not at any t r*e crossed beyond the line on the aaapt ond tney would talcs careful note of the 1 os It ion for their future guidance* 7 * Mr* Ball&amp;ntyne» while appreciatln : the •' otio . of His Majesty 1 ® Oowernaent in giving the Oompcny t. , 1 b explamtion, sal i that he pre^uoed that Hi a iajesty # e aovemasnt were not trying to bind Xbn Saud in any way through the Job, any* His Meaning appeared to be that he aasusied triat Jis ® jesty f s doremnwimt would not represent to tbn j xd that ampaay had acce oted the line shown on the sketch eap a® the ,&gt;ontior f and that Ibn Baud was therefore bound by It* ' * -oniel explained that tuore coaid be no gu.nation of I .••n • aJ being bound by the actions of':, tai.;.- arty f J 1 b M ajesty 9 e lover:useut in regard to the frontier hue d eu eade perfectly clear to Ills Majesty* It would be toil m os si bio for Els liaJcety 9 e Oovcrnm^nt to mice any further concession to him* 7 * :r# Hamilton und r* .ailantyne n- t pee re-a to appreciate the sitnation, and to be gratoful for Um information and ex lamtiona that had been |iv«»a to them. ?)L tm Wb'lQ ,, J* *1. P3r *; oece Poort 1957^o.i87 . i 1846/430/65) British Legation, Jedda. X) December 28 th 1937 « I have the ho/our to transrriit herewith, with reference to my telegram h T o« 9 £&gt; dated December llth a translation of the note in v/hich the Saudi Ministry for Foreign Affairs reply to the note of v/hich I sent you a copy in my printed despatch ho* 175 of December 4th. There is a passage in the middle of the last paragraph but one { 'They do not believe that' the Gomp^hy*s employees v/ill go beyond what my Government believe to be within their territories' ) v/hich implies that the Company may operate in the disputed territory* I am sure that this is not what the writer meant and I am trying to clear up the point, but Fuad Bey is at Mecca and there is nqt time to settle the matter before the bag goes* 2* I ami sending copies of this despatch to the Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf at Bushire iNo*1847/430/ 85 ) and to the External Affairs Department of the Government of India ( N 0 .1848/430/65). I have the honour to be with the highest respect Sir, Your most obedient, humble servant, R.W. BULLARD* The Right Honourable Anthony Eden, M*C*, M*P., &amp; c # , &amp; 0 #| &lt;fcc*,'7 / Enclosure to Jedda Despatch hcu 18? 11846/43C/85) of 28«12»37. &gt;&gt; Translation * Minister for Foreign Affairs to His Majesty's Minister* o • 2/ 3/16 • Me c ca 16th Shawwal 1356 (DeceiDber 19th 1937 ) I s fir n i r ^ After Compliments » 1 '&gt; ^ I have the^fionour' h T o*195 of December 4th(lst Shaw^val 1356) regarding the to acknowledge receipt of your letter question of the frontiers between the Saudi Arabian Kingdom and the Arab Amirates on the Persian Gulf and the proposal of the -British Government based on information which has reached them to the effect that the geologists of the California Arabian Standard Oil Company have begun prospecting in the neighbourhood of 4asr Salv/a. You have been so good as to refer to the views of the British Government as to the frontier line in that region and to their readiness to reopen negotiations with a view to reaching a settlement on the basis which they have already explained to the Government of his Majesty the King, subject to the proviso that they trust that, pending a final settlement, the employees of C*A.3,0.C. will not go beyond the frontier indicated by the British Government* The British Government have moreover suggested that a joint topographical mission should be formed to ascertain the position of some of the natural features of the places situated near that line* The Government of His Majesty the King welcome the idea of opening negotiations with a view to arriving at a settle ment of the frontier line in that region* They have always /beenbeen ready to show their good intentions and disposed to come to an agreement and an understanding. i. am compelled however to observe to Your Excellency that the failure to arrive at an agreement in the past was not due to any lack of desire on the part of the Government of His Majesty to settle the question. Hie difficulty arose from their inability to agree to the renuxiciation of their established rights in the territories included in the definition of the frontier which they put for^a ward through Sir Andrew Kyan and which represented the moderate and reasonable minimum for their frontiers. Whenever an opportunity presented itself my Government has explained the essential reasons which compelled them to adhere to the frontier which they had explained in the note which was ^ communicated to Sir Andrew Ryan by tne Heputy ^Minister) for Foreign Affairs on 29/12/1353 (April 3rd 1935). As however ^ the British Government, in spite of the evidence and the „ w of them being the visit of Mr. Kendel last spring and the recent conversation between you and the Deputy ^Minister) for Foreign Affairs, still adhere to the frontier mentioned your above mentioned note, the Government of His Majesty considerate possibility of arriving at a final settlement very difficult so long as the British Government hold to their position and do not agree to the actual situation of what is in reality in the possession and under the influence of His Majesty the King. If however the British Government are prepared to open the subject and to seek a solution on the basis of the actual facts - a solution which would obviate the difficulty, nothing would be more agreeable to the arguments communicated to them on other accasions, the last /GovernmentGovernment of His Majesty Ag to the employees of C.A.S.O.C* not going beyond the places still in dispute. His MajestyGovernment had already explained to the Company*a reprsentative the actual situation as arrived at with your Government and had informed him of the points still in dispute, and they do not believe that the Company*s employees will go beyond what my Government believe to be within their territories, just as they believe that the responsible authorities in the Arab ami rate s on the Persian Gulf, for their part, will not allow the representatives or employees of the companies ox&gt;erating in their territories to cross the line laid down in the note to Sir Andrew Ryan, until a final agreement has been concluded between the parties concerned. As to the despatch of a topographical mission to fix the position of certain natural features in the areas in dispute, my Government does not know how those difficulties can be overcome which were explained by the Deputy (Minister) for Foreign Affairs in the conversation which he had with you on Friday December 10th (7th Shawv/al 1356) and would prefer to learn the opinion of the British Government, whether they do not share the point of view of the Saudi Government that it would be advisable to come to a filial settlement of the frontier, whether by specifying places or by specify ing lines of latitude and longitude, before proceeding to make a survey. I therefore beg you to be so good as to explain the point of view of my Government on the subject to the British Government and to acquaint me v/ith their views upon it. SD/ FAISALCONFIDENTIAL. NoC/119 of 193B, ^ n The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Political Agent, Bahrain, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents (s). British Consulate-General, BUSHIKE. Dated... J . 95 d H.M.S.Bideford, At Sea. Reference to previous correspondence: Description of Enclosure. 1. Name and Date. India Office telegram No, 3 46 of the 18th February-^ 1938, Foreign Office telegram No,24 of the 18th Februaf} 1938 to his Majesty’s* Minister, Jedda, Political hesident’s telegram jmo„1'/48 of the 25th February 1938, Subject. Saudi Frontiers/Vj A f Telegram 3r From 3ecretary of State for India* London. To Government of India, External Affairs Department, New Delhi. •Repeated Political Resident, on H.M.S.Bideford. No.346. Dated and received the 18th February 1938. Having regard to importance of Ibn Baud’s attitude to Great Britain both in matter of Palestine and in connection with issues formulating out of European political situation His Majesty*a Government have had under examination proposals which might help to secure his goodwill and remove possible sources of friction. One of the few possibilities for an advance in this direction is a settlement of disputed south eastern frontier of Baud! Arabia. Here agreement has so far proved impossible owing to the persistent claim of Ibn Baud to JM'IL ^A T C 3 H and T CHOR AX ODATD which His Majesty’s Government have so far refused to admit. It is des ired however to examine the possibility of making some further concession to Ibn Baud’s claims which might be conducive to an agreement upon frontier question. 2. A delimitation discussion has accordingly taken place among Departments concerned. It is of course realised that this same question was gone into carefully &amp; year ago and that no further concession to Saudi claim, apart from modification of frontier near 3UFDK, was then found possible. But question was then examined mainly as a part of frontier problem and not against background of wider issues of policy to which His »4ajesty*s Government now attach special importance. V■■■ mnmhmmkj 'Is V 3 Of tne two Saudi clame it is recognised that tilere ia no prospect of making any concession in respect of jebel Steksh which ia physically Part of JIBHL DUKHAN and therefore of Qatar and which is covered by oil concession granted with approval of His Majesty’s government to Petroleum Concessions (^Khor al udaid) snd question has been raised whether obstacles which have hitherto been held to prevent any concession to Ibn Baud in respect of this territory can by any means be overcorae apart from principal difficulty caused by ^ r ! recognition of the ownership of Abu Dhabi (see P ol i t i cal 'y'-X* Resident’s Kxpreaa letter of March i&gt;tn 1937 ^o.U/10 paragraph jso* 3 (ii)J, the objections to permitting Ibn Baud to occupy Khor al Odaid which have been advanced in the past were stated in Record of discussion at foreign Office with Saudi Repreaenta- i ^une 24th 1935 (enclosure in foreign Office letter of July 6th), The Service Departments here are of opinion that there are now no strategical objections to occupation of l&lt;nor al Odaid by Ibn Saud and I should be glad to nave your views and those of Political Resident on the question now far to the Bhaikh in 1906 was in unambiguous terms and should presumably be regarded as a solemn engagement. Any concession to Ibn Baud could therefore be made only by previous agreement with Shaikh, fhetner concession of Knor al Odaid would nave value as a factor in securing Ibn Baud’s goodwill and in bringing about a frontier settlement ia still an open qp cation and views of his Majesty’s Minister at Jedda on this aspect 1935 copy sent to India and Ruahire by air mail of political objections remain valid 5, The main difficulty however is constituted by y recognised rights of Shaikh of Abu Dhabi. The guarantee given are /mam •3- are being eought but idea obviously can only be peraued if ct'+) there ia a reasonable prospect of securing medium^greement and I shall be glad to have your views and those of Political Resident on the feasibility of approaching Shaikh and ccnsidcra-. tions which might influence him to agree to cession to I bn Saud of this part of his territory. There should of course at this stage be no consultation with Shaikh or nis family. 5. It is recognised that it would hardly be possible to ask Abu Dhabi to surrender his rights except in return for acme compensating advantage. As regards possibility of offer ing monetary compensation His liajesty’s fiovermnent would probably experience at any rate(if) no insuperable difficulty in making funds available for the purpose. It n&amp;s been suggested however that it might ce possible to demonstrate to Shaikh that it is in his own interests that there should be a settled frontier between his territory and Saudi Arabia that His Majesty’s Government have so far failed'to reack an agreement with I bn Saud owing partly to latter’s insistence on his claim to Khor al Odaid and that cession of this territory which is presumably of no material value to Abu Dhabi would be a price well worth paying for an agreed frontier. It is not contemplated that if Shaikh should agree to the fthor being handed to Ibn Saud the cession should take place except in exchange for a frontier settlement which Ibn Saud would agree to respect importance of such settlement to Abu Dhabi would be that it would set a definite limit to f&gt;&amp;udl expansion which it may perhaps be anticipated (compare last part of paragraph 5 of Hickinbotham*s letter of August 2?th 19 37 T/lO^-22/4) is other wise likely to increase towards Trucial Gbast and which failing a frontier settlement now may result in some years hence in more /-4 more «xt«nslve territorial claima on tne part of the Saadis posaibXy in tne direction of 3A: 7 A^n or in unfortunate and possibly dangeroun friction in tne event of discovery of oil. I should be glad to learn in this connection your present view of the danger of expansion of Saudi or .Tahabi influence on Trucial Coast hinterland and whether it constitutes a menace that 3hai^h(s) would be anxious to dispel at cost of cession of territory. ?. 7. If you think above and any ether considerations you may be able to suggest would be insufficient to persuade Shaikh without some degree of monetary compensation can you estimate what cash payment by Hie Majesty’s Government need in that case be required to secure his agreement 7 3. Further do you think Shaikh is likely to insist on a frontier settlement being acconyarmed by a guarantee of protection by His Majesty* a Government on landward side of his ^ ? /£&lt;u q**%**f** ) territory ** the possibility of giving {moat desirable clear - ness)has not yet been considered here and in view of its obvious difficulties would require very careful examination. 9. I should also be glad to learn your views on adequacy of a frontier settlement on a de facto basis (see paragraph 6 of foreign Office telegram of January 16th ( mat. ) tiio.24} In the event of Ibn Gaud being unwilling to sign a •definite treaty settling frontier. 10. It is of course at least posaible that Ibn Baud would refuse to commit himself in any way to a frontier which does not concede to him the J3BSL SMBH. There might in that case be some advantage in trying to secure a partial settlement ( ? ? U/W^wetfv * J which (mat. I ing for the time being tne hope of defining the /-5- the frontier in the neighbourhood of Jebel Naksh would establisn an agreed frontier running eastwards from Khor al &lt;3daid the surrender of which would still secure the definition v ne frontier of Abu I)hati• I should be glad to know whether yo&gt;i think this alternative worth persuing. It would of course onl; be a pis aller though it is a Vd is -advantage settling the more easterly part of the frontier and preventing Saudi ex pansion t owards haraimi• 11. X should be glad to nave your views and those of the Political Resident by telegram at an early date* If0 Xj0 - Secretary of State for India.3. H«M» *0 Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, London. H. M. * a Minister, Jedda. No.24. political Hesident, Busftire. No.5. Government of India, External Affairs depart ment, New Delhi. No. l. 13tJi February 1938. (Belayed under Bushire telegram &gt;Io. 112 of 20th February 1938). South .Eastern Arabian Frontiers. In view of difficult situation reeult ing from developments in Palestine (omission ?Hia Majeety^ Government) desire to see whether anything further can be done with a view to securing King I bn Baud' a goodwill. Various (? offers) of assistance have been considered but have all proved impracticable and only question where it may perhaps be possible to offer him some satisfaction seems to be tn&amp;t of South Eastern Frontiers. I realise this may seem trivial in comparison with major issue of Palestine but any satis faction which dis Majesty's Government could give Ibn 3aud here might help to tip the scale in our favour if matter were otherwise evenly balanced while so long as frontier question remains unsettled there are unpleasant possibilities of serious friction ( amt. ) any moment should oil oe found in disputed area so th t failure to settle frontier soon might equally tip the scale against us. £• A» regards Southern (Aden Protectorate) sector of frontier it is agreed that balance of advantage lies in post poning a decision. Central (Muscat) sector is governed by special / Telegram From To Bep eat ed Dated theapecial oonaideratlona and Ibn Sfeud does not aeem to attac a lamed late importance to it. Urgent problem tnerefore is Hortnern sector from DOHA? ^*3 SALya to parallel 22* 3. Only two points of serious dispute nere are Sm%L mmn and KWM AL OEDaID* Difficulties in the way of any concession over Job el '. a n. appear to c e insuperable since it has already been included with approval of His Majesty* s Government and before I bn Baud* s leeenruess on it was known in ^atar oil concession* 4* As regards Khor al Odaid you already know extent to which His Majesty's Government are committed to (?it ) and defence of Hhaikn of Abu inabi’s rights. Any territorial concession here can therefore only be made with Shaikh’s agreement and Government of India and Political Resident are being consulted in a telegram which is being repeated to you on the feasibility of obtaining this. 5. If Shaikh agreed to cession of Kftor al Odaid effect would be tnat( ? it would ^ive) I bn Baud north of parallel 22 practically entire line claimed in Saudi aote of April 3rd 1935 with a ole exception of Jebel haksa* Do you see any hop© of reaching complete or partial settlement of litrthem sector on this basis ? Or might offer of further concession (ai'tur categorical statements of hie Majesty’s 0 ov er ament t hat tne i r 1 &amp; s t off er was final} encourage I bn Baud to raise nie terms and to prove more difficult. 6* 2 appreciate that as he indicated last March I bn Baud may now be unwilling in view of Palestine situation to appear to sign away any Arab (? rights } to His Majesty* s Govern ment notwithstanding his hote of April 3rd 1935 and that % definite /-3« definite frontier treaty may tner®rore be unobt?i nable# But mignt it not be possible nevertneless to obtain eottlement on de facto basis on same lines as settlement of Trans Jordan - Hedja^ frontier embodied in first exchange of notes signed at time of Treaty of Jedda ? A personal guarantee by 1 bn Saud that ne would accept such a frontier aid would r ot attempt to extend nie autaority beyond it would be of greater value particularly if oil were found in tne neighbournood of new line* effect would be that apart from losing Jefce-i i akan to wnich ne has no substantial claim Ion Baud would lave obt4 ned his exact line in most important sector of frontier and that potential source of friction would be eliminated from Anglo-Ba’udi relations. 7. Fisase telegraph ( mat* 1 sooner on this suggestion. Possibility should not however be mentioned fey you to Saudi ov &amp;rn m ent) pendl w the receipt by his Majesty’s government of further Information as to ( mat* _) be done to Abu Dhabi’s attitude. y. i. -Peer etfcry of Sta^te for foreign Affairs.——W» IIIll WW'if Telegram S To From Polit ical Res ident, on H.H.S .Bidef ord # Government of India&gt; External Affairs Department New Delhi. Repeated Secretary of State for India, London. Copy given to Political Agent, Bahrain. No. T/48. Dated the 25th February 1938* India Office telegram No.346 of l8tn February and Foreign Office telegram to Jedda No.24 of 18th February. 2. Khor &amp;1 Odaid. There is at present no expansion of Saudi or lUiabi influence on True ial Coast and this being so there is no immediate menace which Shaikh of Abu Dhabi would be anxious to dispel at the cost of cession of his territory. Majesty^ Government would have to satisfy the Shaikh with a monetary compensation* This it is impossible to compute and could only be arrived at after considerable ^hag^ling 1 *. fore in Petroleum Concessions Limited Concession Company would presumably have to be cen suited prior to any cession of it. 5. Personally I venture to give tne opinion that the offer oi cash to tne Shaikh to induce him to surrender a £&amp;rt of his territory, whether ne accepts it or not, would have an unfortunate effect on our prestige not only In the Arab Sheikhdoms of the Gulf (in this connection see paragraph 9 of my Express letter No.C-71 of the 16th February 1938), but also probably in neighbouring countries including Saudi Arabia itself. In these In tnese circumstances I am of tne opinion that His 4 Khor al Odaid being in Abu Dnabi territory and tnere- quarters /quarters it jrould I am afraid be represented that His 'Majesty^ Government through fear of Bin Gaud induced the Shai^n, probably under pressure it will be said, to sell part of his territory, the integrity of the whole of which His ilajesty’s Government have guaranteed. • Rest dentCONFIDENTIAL. No/ 3 / 1 30 of 193 8, The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Political Agent, Bahrain, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents (s). Political Resident’s Printed letter No,0/119 of 25th February 1938. / Brit^h Qonsnlate-General, BUSHIKE, Dated 28th February 1938 Oarap, Bioai. Reference to previous correspondence: Description of Enclosure, Name and Date. Subject. 1, Jedda telegram No, 40 of 23rd February 1938 to^ Foreign Office, 2. Jedda telegram no, 41 of 24th February 1938 to Foreign Office,'‘‘I Telegram S From His Majesty's Minister, ‘'edda To H.M.'s Secretary of State for Foreign Affa irs, London. No.40. Repeated Secretary to tne Government of India, External Affairs Department, New Delni. No.2. Political Resident, Rusnire. No.3. Dated the 23rd February 1938 (Relayed under Busnire telegram ^o. 114 dated 25tn received 26th February 1938J. Important . # /, i) 9 i&gt; / ' Your telegram ^o.24 of 17th February, Saudi Government have replied to a Note which I sent them on 3rd February. They maintain that all concilia tion has been on their side in that they reduced their claims to minimum before putting them forward. They describe this frontier question as a matter of life and death* Secondly they hold though in moderate language to mutual abstention of proposal for Oil Com® nies which was (fliut, ) enclosure to my despatch ^0.12 of January 11th. Thirdly, to obviate confusion they would like to know what areas would be surveyed before they reply to proppsal for a commission. 2. Tne Note indicates offended feelings at being misunderstood but expresses 'readiness to discuss any practical proposal which will secure interests of both parties'. I reminded Fuad to-day that once or twice he had hinted at a compromise but had (mut . ) retreated on being asked what that meant. He admitted implicitly but said it was because they felt they would meet with a flat refusals if only they knew this was not so they might be able to make some pr oposals./proposals. I did not press this point nor of course d id I mention subject of your telegram i&gt;»o # 24. But could I not without waiting for decision on that telegram tell Saudi Government that although we have not been able to think of any way of reconciling opposing views if they have any practical suggestion because it does not (? state) the (mut,) in question we have put forward but will receive most sympathetic attention. It is possible their proposals might give us an idea and break deadlock and in any case I do not see that it could do ary harm. which the King attaches to this question which ne described would be sent home by bag as I thought His Majesty's government ought to see Saudi Government’s exact words. Thus King will nardly expect a speedy reply. But it would make a good impression if I could announce soon the readiness of His Majesty^ j (lev ernment to consider any ’’practical suggestion” particularly to make they can be sure that it will not be rejected merely as ( omission ? )ing in King’s mind and begged that for the sake of Anglo-Saudi relations we should see urgently whether something could not be done 3 4. I had already told Fuad that although I would Fuad Bey again spoke of the enormous importance telegraph you a full translation of their .Note ( omission ? ^ if I could do/while King washere February 26th to 29th (?28) ' ! for visit of Her Royal highness Princess Alice. -H.M. f 3 Minister, JeddaJHHHMMRHBHBHMHIi ■ / fM jproa Secretary or &amp;tat* for yorei^n Affairs# Jb(HKloii t fo ilia Majesty's Aabaesador# Jedda. «o.£9. He peat ed Secretary to the doreriuaeut of ladle, External Affairs Department, hew 3elal• ao.2# Political Resident on Sldeford. ho* Bated 26th February 1936. f &gt; ^ » ' (Relayed under Suenlre telegram ho. 120 dated 28th February 1938) four telegrama ho.40 and 41. It is unfortunately impossible at present to authorise you to announce that Hie Majesty's Oorernment will be &gt; ready to consider any practical suggestion since this would be inconsistent with their frequent statements tn&amp;t tneir last offer was final. But there would be no objection to your informing Saudi Oorernment that if they now have any practical suggestion to make his Majesty's Uovernm^nt will be prepared to hear what that suggestion is provided you can do so without any rigk of raising false hopes or giving the impress ion that possible concession on Xhor al Odeld has been receiving consideration. Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs ] t p m(fi) I Copy. (Received under Jedda Printed letter No. 146/546/14 dated the 11th January 1938). I\ T o. 12. TI457&amp;46/14) British Legation, u edda, January 11th 1938. Dir, In mydespatch No. 187 dated December 28th with which I had the honour to transmit to you a translation of the Saudi I ■ &gt; note on the question of the eastern frontier, I pointed out that the wording of the last paragraph but one of that note would allow prospecting in the disputed area from the Saudi side but not from the Persian Gulf side, and that I was trying to clear up this point. The wording seemed to me neither logical nor in accordance with what Fuad Bey had said to me in an assurance which I reported to you in my telegram No. 92 dated1 December 11th, I suggested to Fuad that if in the phrase 'They | do not believe that the Company’s employees 'will go b eyond what my Gove r nment believe to be within ' their territori es' the words underlined could be replaced | by a reference to the frontier as defined in the proposals of His Majesty's Government, the note would scoress what i under stood to be the Saudi Government's point of view. Fuad Bey however sent me a lett r dated December 25tn (translation-en closed) containing the proposal for mutual abstention from ope- j ; rations in the disputed area which I conveyed to you in my tele gram No. 103 of December 30th. 2, For some time I hoped to induce Fuad Bey to withdraw his letter of December 25th-'and to r eturn to the note of Decem- ber 19th with the amendment which 1 had proposed. It would -^^have been better for the Saudi Arabian Government to say 'we do not think our prospectors will go e ast of your 'line and we assume that your prospectors will not come 'west of ours', rather than to make the one d ependent upon IGHT H0NCURABL3 ANTHONY EDEN, L.C., T .P., &amp;c &amp;c &amp;c- 2 - the other, as they have done in the letter now transmitted to you. I have however been unable to secure the withdrawal of the note of December '25th with its proposal that mutual abs tention on the Saudi side should be dependent upon abstention on our side. Fuad Bey’s behaviour' 1 has been peculiar about this point. He admits that he/gave me the oral assurance re ported in my telegram No. 92*' dated December 11th. From one or two indirect r emarks he has made I can only conclude that Ibn Saud and Yusuf Yasin c oncocted the one-sided statement to whicl I objected, and that he could not induce the King to give in writing an unconditional assurance such as he had himself given me orally. However this may be, the letter of December 25th remains the last word in writing and I send it to com plete the record, though 1 shall quote if need arises the oral p- assurance given by Fuad on December 11th. 'rom what Fuad has said on more than one occasion, and from statements made by the Jedda manager of the California Arabian Standard Cil Company I do not fear that there will be any prospecting in the disputed area by the C.A.S.C.C. at present, 3. I am sending copies of this despatch and enclosures to the Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian DuIf Bushire (No,146/546/14) and to the Secretary to the Government of India, New Delhi (No. 147/M6/14). I have the honour to b e with the highest resnects Sir,. Your most obedient, humble servant, R.W. Bullard^closure to Jedda despatch No. 12 (145/546/14) of T anuarv 11th 1938, Translation, No. 2/3/20. Ministry of Foreign Affairs, Mecca December 25th, 1937. n \*\ Dear Sir Header, 1 have referred to the test of the second paragraph of the note sent to you on December 1.9th 1937 concerning the south-eastern frontiers, and I now explain the object (of that note) to you. ».(x The position of my government is clear in her adhering to and insisting on their established right over the whole of the tterritory bounded by the frontier defined in the note communicated to Sir Andrew Ryan on 29.12,1353 (April 3rd 1935) and consider that there is nothing to prevent them fl?om allow ing -.he representatives of the C.A.S.C.C, from making a g eolo- gical or topographical survey within that frontier especially if the news we have received is taken into consideration, that the r epreaentatives of the companies which are operating in the amirates on the Persian Gulf have violated that frontier. If however those governments agree to refrain from violating the frontier until a final agreement has been arrived at as to the places in dispute, my Government will be prepared to infom the representatives of the. company of the necessity not to violate frontier described by the British Government as the green line, either for drilling or for prospecting operations, vour s sin cerely, (Signed) Fuad Hamza lis Excellency Sir Reader Bullard, K.C.M.G., C.I.E., &amp;C &amp;C &amp;CCONFIDENTIAL. No. 1 d9-S The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Political Agent, Bahrain* and has the honour to transmit to him a eopj of the undermentioned docnmentSi (*). British Con ulate-General, BUSHIRE. ’March••1968, Reference to previous correspondence: Residency Printed Letter No*0/150 of 3rd March 193b, Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Jedda telegram No.56, dated 7th March 193b to Foreign ’ Office* Subject, Saudi Arabian Frontier \ V as His Majesty's Ambassaaor, Jedda, Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, Lonaon* No.56* Secretary to tne Government of India, External Affairs Department, New Delhi. No.4. Political Resident, Bushire. No.5. received 7th March Your telegram No.£9 of Bdth February. Eventually I decided against official action. I suggested to Fuad that he should give me his personal opinion as to to tne sort of solution which he thought might be acceptable to his Government and I would think it over and give my personal views on the possibility of its acceptance by His Majesty's Government. In tnis way neither Government would be committed. Fuad.took several days for reflection during which he probably sounded tne King. After much talk during which I had to steer him away from expressing a definite preference for Jabal Naknsh he put forward tnis as a solution which might have some hope of acceptance by Ion Baud: (1) His Majesty's Government to offer to abandon to Ibn Baud whichever of the two areas Jabal Nakhsh and Khop al Odaid they consider tne less important: / (2) Telegram From To Repeated Dated and(2) frontier to run through Sufuk wells which should be free of accessrto population on both sides, 3* I gave no nint tnat I thought a compromise possible and my reply to Fuad is to be personal. This to save King 1 s face in case of rejection. But I earnestly hope it will be possible to compromise and remove the only major difficulty other than ? Palestine tnat is still outstanding. I will not repeat all Fuad*s appeals as I know His Majesty*s Government are Anxious to do anything they can within reason at the prsent moment but will only remind you this a point on which Ibn Baud is terribly sensitive and that I beleive offer of this compromise would have a good chance of success. AMBASSADORCONFIDENTIAL. No&gt; 182-3 of 1938. n ^ * /V \ The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Political Agent, Bahrain* and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents (s). \ J ! 1* \ ' UO uO British Contulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated.l.atn.^.G.U. Reference to previous correspondence: Description of Enclosure, Name and Date. 1. CrOv?rnment of India telegram No. 370 dated ?6th February 19 2. Gov eminent of India telegram No.440 dated 9th March 1938* 3. Residency t elegram No. 140 dated 12th March 1938. 38. j Subject. Saudi Arabian Frontier.Telegram From Secretary to the G-overnment or India, External Affairs department, hew Jelhi. To Political Resident on H.M.S. Bideford. No.370. Bated and received 26th February 1938. L v Reference telegram from Secretary of State for India No. 34 6 of 17 th February. Saudi Arabian Frontier Negotiations. 2. Government of Indie will be glad to receive your views at an early date. FOREIGN C.V.A.jmBMHMMMIHMI 4 .v w* Telegram From To Repeated %.440. Secretary to the Governmeiit of India* External Affairs Department* ew Delhi. Secretary of State for India, London. Political Resident, hushire. Dated 8th received 9th March 1938. Your telegram So.346 of 17th February. \ X s . lie lations v/ith Ibn Saud. 2 , *Vhile we s^’mpathise with His Majesty’s Goveraiment 11 s difficulties arid appreciate desirability of reBJOving possible sources of friction with Ibn baud we do not consider that your tentative proposals regarding /hor al Odaid offer any hope of satisfactory settlement. Mowle has already pointed out in his telegram A t o.T/ 48 the very great difficulties attending an approach to Shaikh of Abu Dhabi on the lines you suggest and also grave political objections from point of view of our whole position on Arab coast of Gulf to any such bargain even if bhaikh could be persuaded to agree. We fully agree with Fowle*a arguments and are ourselves strongly averse from action on these lines. We are moreover extremely doubtful whether His Majesty’s Government’s position vis-a-vis Ibn baud would be in any way improved if we were able to offer him Lhor al Odaid. Apart from above we consider political objections /stated i \ ,stated in the record of discussion referred to in paragraph 4 of your telegram have still considerable weight and that it is undesirable to give a State such as Saudi Arabia an oulet on the l&amp;ruoial Ooast and to allow the chain of the Arab Shaikhdoms to be broken* 4* With regard to the points raised at the end of paragraph 6 of your telegram we see no reason to differ from the opinion expressed in paragraph 2 of Fowle*s telegram* 5* iolitleal Resident has recorded no views on the questions raised in paragraphs 7 - 10 of your telegram and without the benefit of his local knowledge we do not feel competent to offer useful advice* Government of IndiajMHMBSKMKKKBmmKmmmmmmmm /tT\ Tel egram Prom To Hepeated Copy by post Ho.140. S Political Heaident, Busiiire. Secretary to tne uovernnient of India, ■External Affairs Department, Hew Delni. Secretary of state for India, London. to Pol it ice 1 Agent, Bahrain. Dated 12th March 1938. j' Reference paragraph 5 of your telegram Ho.440 of 3th ?«archf If you agree I would propose postponing my comments on paragraphs 8 to 10 until His Majesty’s Government’s views on Jedda telegram Ho.56 to Foreign Office of 7th March are known. 3RITC0H5UL C . V * A •telegram T1 S tT From Government of India, External Affairs Dept., New Delhi. To Political Resident, Bushire. Repeated ( mut ) Secretary of State for India, London, Political Agent, Bahrain. No. 478 Dated and received 15th March 1838. v) Your telegram 140 dated March ISth. Relations with Ibn Saud. We agree. FOREIGNGonf Uent ial Ho.0/15S of 1958. Office of the Political •-etident in the Persian &amp;ulf, Oaaii&gt; Bahrain. ' ■' \\ The 22iid March 1058. ?r om The Hon oar a Die the X'olitical Fee Ideiat in the Persian Oulf. To Oopy to ?» His Majesty’s Secretary of State for Indiav London. The Secretary to the hovern^ent of India in the External .Affairs Department, Hew Delhi. Political Agent, Bahrain. 'X Mhor al odaid USMORAHBUM « ^ ^ ' P Wot information. I have given copies of your telegram Ho.348 of 13th ^ehruary 1938 and all subsequent correspondence to Political Agent, Bahrain. 3d. T.G.?OfLB Political resident in the Persian ^ulf. \ \CONFIDENTIAL. The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to The Political Agent, Bahrain. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment (s). Office of the Political Resident in the Persian Oulf, Bahrain. t i i X v V ■ Dated.. .3 jD£ h. .MaE ch . 19 .. Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. 1. 2 . 3. 4. 5. 6. 7. 8. India Office telegram No.561 of 13th March 1933. India Office Endorsement No.P.Z. 1302/33 undated. India Office letter No.P.Z.1211/33 of 3rd March 1933, with enclosures. Jedda telegram No.26 of 2l/l/38. Jedda telegram No.31 of 26/1/33 Foreign Office telegram No.16 of 27/1/38 Foreign Office telegram No.17 of 27/1/38. Jedda telegram No.36 of 31/1/33. K South-Eastern boundaries of Saudi Arabia. C0 %Telegram Fr am 3 Repeated To Secretary of State for India, London, Political Resident, Bushire. Government of India, External Affairs Department, New Delhi No.561 Dated and received 18th March 1938 Your telegram No.T/48. KHOR AL ODAID 2 It would facilitate examination of matter here if you could give some estimate however tentative of minimum offer of cash compensation which would have to be made to satisfy Shaikh if it were considered desirable to make an offer. successful or not to induce the Shaikh to cede Khor in return for monetary compensation would have an unfortunate effect on our prestige on Arab side of gulf. tifould there be any similar objection to an attempt to persuade Shaikh by use of arguments indicated in paragraph 6 of my telegram of February 18th No.346 without offer of monetary com pensation if it were considered desirable to make such an attempt ? » that you may have at this stage on questions raised in paragraph 8 of my telegram of February 18th and also for your preliminary views on feasibility of giving a guarantee of protection if shaikh is thought likely to be influenced by it. 5 . Would you see any obj€ gestion regarding Sufuk in paragraph 2 (2) of Jedda telegram of 3 I note your opinion that an attempt whether 4 I should also be grateful for any views March 7th No.56 ? Secretary of State fp r I ndi ai\z. izo 2 /.:b. incl’r m o In Fcreign Office Covering letter lfo.I*1063/19/)l dated 24th February^ 1950* * m : h . ? r~e!~o a Id an d Abu :.)h£\hl . Mr* bongriggf of l s otroleum Oonceaeione Ltd*« r-ivod rno yesterday in the course of a long convarsaticm an o' ”?atter8 in rrbla what the present position was regard in : the remtier* 2* I gave him a brief account of the position* 1 ex Gained t ,rt we regarded thfi legal position as established by the ilngi o-^urkish Conventions of 1915 and 1914, vftiioh defined the blue and violet lines* In practice, however t Ibn jaud had established his authority a long way to the east of throe lines, and, vm did not desire to insist on purely legal paper da iris over areas wandered over exclusively by tribes, such as the :furra, owing undisputed allegiance to Ibn Sand* on the other hand, vm had certain obligations to the uheilth of ;rtar and the Truelal sheikhs, end we had therefore made an off ; 'or to Ibn laud defining our saeocimum conoessi ms* tm hi-d told Ibn ,.aud and the standard Oil Ompeny of California tlmt vm would raise no objection to that Company operating* up to our naxinum line, but had warned them against crossing that line, ; , ich we had re-defined both to Xbn Send and to the Co xmny* 5* Hr* Longrigg then told me that the Sheikh of b . Dhabi wi'S proving extremely difficult to deal with and appeared to be In great awe of Ibn sand* X asked Mr* Longrlgg hov 'far he tin the Sheikh of Abu Dhabi*s effective authority extended* He re lied that it extended some distance inland but that the bheilth was fri htened of Ibn baud and tlmt his auth-^ rit v , ms very weak* 1 tried to draw Mr* Longrigg about the Ohelldh* s authority over the Xhor-el-Odeid area. Mr. Longrigg explained tint the . heikh of Abu Dtebi had stated that he regarded Me territory/£ « territory ps extend in* to the north o r&gt; the Khar, ;r.t the Co-'.'^eny were not much interested in this area, as, ! 5 om the geological point of view, it mm less then any other territory they ware dealing with, though one could* of courea t never absolutely exclude the poselMl ty vf oil brin;;: found* 4. 1 got the iiitpreeelon 9 f&gt;om what Ifr. Longrigg said* that the fheikh of bu Dhabi in fact exercised extr*e ely little authority inland* and that he depends entirely a our e .a ■art to maintain any sort of Independence vic-r—via 'bn inud* I could not make out father he had attmptod to define hie inland frontier** but a© i «C»!** appear to be less Intereoted in this area than in any other it -y be t iat they have not yet taken up the matter eerioualy* (sga*) n, 23rd February* 19d3«. &gt; P.Z.1211/38. CONFIDENTIAL India Office^ Whitehall, London, S.W.l. 3rd March, 1938. * i i djUi*/ ^ Copies are 'being sent to you and to the Government of 5 India oy this mail of telegrams which passed in January between tne Foreign Office and His Majesty's Minister at Jedda (Jedda relegrams 26, 31 and 36, and Foreign Office telegrams 16 and 17) about the South-Eastern boundaries of Saudi Arabia. None of these telegrams was repeated to you at the time, presumably because they followed on &lt;h Foreign Office telegram No.6 of the 11th January (referred to in Jedda telegram No.26) which was not an official telegram. A copy of this telegram is enclosed herewith for your information together with a copy of demi-official correspondence with the Foreign Office on the question of ■WTi' t? 0 Foreign Office dated 31st January; j the making of overtures to n . . . TI . _J’_ . F^ebruary, ) Petroleum Concessions Limited regarding the exploitation of the Jebel Nakhsh area. I am sending a copy of this letter and its enclosures to Metcalfe. Yours sincerely. * Hon’ble Lieut.-Col. Sir Trenchard Fowle, HUE H.B. M*Consul-General, a Bushire. / j3.l (Sgd.) J. P, GIBSOf ii. 2.567/38, m BX i • (K.V656/258/9X), Cypher telo tj raai to Jir a* Bullard* (Jodla). Foreign Olxice. January lit la, 1938* 10*p # m # lo.6. Your telegram Ko.103 jot )eeember 30ths South- gaotern Arabian frontiers/. Following from Cliphant: There are great difiioulties over course of action suggested in paragraph 3* £• Fact that His Majesty*s Goverriment ere prepared to acquiesce in Saudi Company operatiiig up to lino of their uoxixaum offer (i.e. iiiy&amp;dh line with lufuif moU1Xcation) on condition that that line is not crossed, cannot entitle Saudis to ask that Qatar Company shall not operate on Saudi side of maximum Saudi claim, which would be virtually conceding Saudi case. 3. But most aeriou® difficulty is that, when ettar oil concession was originally granted, before there was any x*eason to believe that Saudis meant to put forward such extensive claims, Jebei hakhsh, which had never, to our kno.ledge, been claimed by Saudis, was included in concession area as shown on the map attached to concession. Petroleum Concessions limited is not a purely British Company, but contains large French and United States interests, and latter represent United States groups hostile to Standard til of California operating in Basa. e will, however, see whether any overtures to the Company are possible* 4. At present then we cannot agree to passage in first sentence of communication proposed in paragraph 3 of your telegram, running: $, But in a spirit of coxiciliation they will/will sea that oil company operating in those atatee does not, enter disputed territory tov the present 51 • 5* :/; © ai,ree to the remainder ot the proposed communication, as regards the suggested topographical mission*I1«DIA OFFICE, WHITEHA.LL, S.W.l. 567/38. 31st January, 1938. Dear Baggallay, ' Would you please refer to your letter of the 25th January and to the drafts which you sent ^ne of two telegrams addressed to Jedda on the subject of the S.E*boundaries of Saudi Arabia. , V ■'' V/e concur in the draft rbply to the , inister ’ s telegram ho. 26 of the 21st January (F.0.ho.E.407/150/91). As regards the draft reply to his telegram ho.14 f (F.O.ho.E.220/150/91) we have no comments to make except with regard to the last paragraph. We did not know to what this paragraph referred, and we felt we could hardly agree to it without some further information. You have now given us this on the telephone and we understand that after consultation with Starling you propose to modify the latter part of the paragraph so as to indicate that there is practically no possibility of an arrangement being made between the two Oil Companies, and I have told you that we take no exception to the paragraph as so modified. We should, however, be glad to learn a bit more precisely what kind of 'co-operation” between the two companies is, or was, in contemplation. When the telegrams issue we should in the usual way send copies to the Political Resident and the Government of India for their Information, and as the paragraph referred to above would mystify the.a we would, of course, wish to be able to explain the actual position. We assume of course that in view, of our connexion with the grant of the Q,atar Oil Concession an# °ur responsibility for the operation of the Polit 10 ^* Agr^armt L. iiaggallay, Esq.., Foreign Office, S.-V.l. with/ \with Petroleum Concessions Limited we/would be consulted before any approach is made to the/Company, and, as I said in my letter to Brenan of the 23rd December, we should feel reluctant to approach them with the object of dissuading them from operating in an area in which His Majesty’s Government have recognised their concessional rights. Yours sincerely, (Sgd.) J. P. Gibsoni.2.1267/38 v ( .577/150/91). FOHEIGi. OFFICE, S.S.l. 10th February, 1938. Dear Gibson, In reply to your letter P.£.567/38 of the 31st January about the south-eastern boundaries of Saudi Arabia, I write to explain that the paragraph in our telegram to Bullard which you mention referred to a personal enquiry addressed to the Chairman of the Iraqi iotroleum Company. The enquiry was whether in the Chairman’s persDnal opinion it would be possible, so far as the Company’s own interests were concerned, for the Company to reach an agreement with the American company which holds the concession for eastern Saudi Arabia, whereby the two companies would dispose of the profits, if any, from the exploitation of the Jebel lakhsh area in such a manner as to render possible, merely so far as concerned the Company*s own interests, a change in the Qatar frontier. The answer now received is that no such arrangement is possible. In any case there would have been no question of talcing .the matter up with the Company with a view to positive action on their part, far less of taking it up with the Sheikh of uatar, without the concurrence of the India Office. $ i Yours ever, (Sgd*; Lacy Baggallay.ISncloaure in Foreign Office covering letter dated 25th January 1938. P.ZJ554 - 1938. Ho Distribution . Decypher. Sir R.Bullard (Jedda), 21at January, 1938. D. 9.15 a.m. 21at January, 1938. R. Noon. 2l3t January 1938. No.26. Your telegram No.6. I should be glad to know whether first half of third paragraph ia to be taken as a reply to my tel^ram No, 14 of January 11th which crossed your instructions. My informa- -tion is that Saudi Arabian Government claimed in September ( ? far more) than they do now though claim then was admit- -tedly nebulous. At present Saudi Arabian Government claim right to assume that disputed area is not covered by Iraqi Petroleum Coxapany’s concession. Would it not be well to tell them plainly that it is ? 2. We always and Saudis never have Blue Line in mind. To make this clear I should like to insert a fresh sentence in proposed note in place of words to which you object in fourth paragraph of your telegram M in offering to accept a frontier far to the east of what they consider legal boundary viz. the Blue Line His Majesty* s Government have shown a spirit of conciliation which they trust Saudi Arabian Government have not overlooked. ^ 3. I do not wish to send in note until after Shaikh of Bahrain has passed throqgh Jedd$ on January 22nd Saudi Arabian Government are behaving very handsomely about him. Pr on^From what I have heard from Fuad and manager of Californian Oil Company Ido not think there is any danger at present that company will prospect in disputed territory#Snclosure in Foreign Office covering letter dated 28th January 1938. P.Z.630 - 1938 No Piatribution . Decypher. Sir R.Bullard. (Jedda$ 26th January 1938. D.9.35 a.m. 26th January 1938. R.11.10 a.m. 26th January 1938* No.31. My telegram No. 26 of January 21st. The second half of paragraph referred to in my telegram No. 14of January taken by itseld is incorrect since Ibn Saud claimed Jabal Naksh and Khorel-Odeid in April 1935, but I suppose the difference is as follows. The paragraph must be read as a whole. The assurance is tied to definition of green line. It is clear that His Majesty’s Government considered nothing east of that line to be under discussion. Whether wording used was the best may be open to question but meaning is clear and obvious without intention to mislead and Saudi objection based on an isolated sentence over two years later cannot* e*m Snclosure to Foreign Office covering letter dated 28th January 1938. P.2.630 - 1938, (s.505/150/91) No Distribution. Cypher telegram to Sir R.Bullard (jedda), Foreign Office, 27th Janury 1938. 1Q.Q0 p.m. No.16. \ Lv v Your telegram No. 3l( of January 26th* south-eastern Arabian frontiers). I agreegenerally. 2. Paragraph 4 of Mr. Calvert? ;s letter of September 26th 1935 to Shaikh Yusuf Yasin was never intended to contain assurance that ^atar Oil Concession did not extend beyond maximum line claimed by King Ibn Saud. Relevant sentence makes it clear that southern limit of oil concession does not extend beyond ’’green line” from which in fact it lies some distance to the north. Second sentence to the effect that ’’concession does not therefore extend to any territory under discussion with Saudi Government” is merely a corollary of the first and was based on repeated assertions by His Majes- -ty’s Government that they were not prepared to discuss any concession beyond the green line. 3. Jebel Naksh had in fact been included in concession area before there was any indication that Ibn Saud intended to claim it and concession line was thought at the time to be well away from further extent of any serious Saudi claim, although it was realised that Ibn Saud had at times claimed practically the whole of Qatar Peninsula. 4. Although it is unfortunate that phrase used in Mr. Calvert•cs letter (which, however, exactly .foilowed Foreign Office/Office instructions) should have given the impression that ^atar concession did not cover any territory claimed by Ibn oaud, I distrust Fuad’s motives in asking these questions and should much prefer to avoid embarking on legalistic discussion which is unlikely to further solution. I can, hov/ever, only leave it to your discretion whether and if so how to reply to communication. . 5. Possibility of Petroleum Concessions Limited co- -operat ing with Standard Oil Company of California about ^atar Concession is being considered. But there is practi- -cally no hope of favourable outcome.Enclosure in Foreign Office covering letter dated 2uth January 1938. P.Z.630 - 1933 (305/150/91) 4 ^ Ho Distribution. Cypher telegram to Sir R.Bullard (JeddaO, Foreign Office, 27th January 1938. 10.00 p.m. Ho. 17. — /A to Your telegram Hoi 26 (of January 21st. South-east frontiers of Arabia). Reply to first sentence is negative. Precise meaning of paragraph 4 of (Mr.Calvert 1 s) letter of September 26th, 1935 (to Shaikh Yusuf *asin) is dealt with separately in my immediately preceding telegram. 2. As regards extent of King Ibn Saud’s claims in the past, see paragraph 3 of my immediately preceding telegram. 3. I should prefer not to become entangled in an argument as to validity of blue line, but I presume you thinic it important to mention it as snowing that we have gone to limit of concession. In the circumstances you may at your dis- -cretion amend your reply as suggested by you in paragraph 2 n of your telegram under reference. 4. I take it that terms of reply as hitherto quoted are not necessarily intended to represent its actual words and you will doubtless maxe wording as conciliatory as possible.Enclosure in Foreign Office covering letter dated 2nd February 1938. P.Z.787 - 1938 No Distribution. Decypher. Sir R.Bullard (Jedda?). D. 1.00 p.m. 31st January 1938. R. 3.50 p.m. 31st January 1938. No.36. Your telegram No. 16 of January 27th, paragraph 4. I distrust all Fuad’s motives but I felt it essential to give him at once our interpretation of our letter of December 5th 1935. There was no mistaking his extreme consternation and I have no doubt he had read the letter as an assurance that Jabal Naksh was not included in our con- -cession. He made vehement protests, reserves, etc., and gave me unnecessary warning to expect most violent reaction from the King, but I confined myself to the meaning of the letter in question and remind (ed him?) that we had all along made it clear that we regarded retention of Jabal Naksh and Khoral ode id as essential and said that I expected to be able to reply to Saudi letter shortly. I shall avoid mention of blue line. LQonf ident ial Mo. 0/189 of 1938 5 Office of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Bahrain, the 31st March 1938. !*r om x O Copy t o The Officiating Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. His Majesty's Secretary of Rtate for India, London. The Secretary to the Government of India in the Ijcternal Affairs department, Mew Delhi P ol it ic al Ag ent, Baiira in • um^iAXDm Khor al Odaid Reference memorandum Ho.a/l52 of 22nd March 1938 from this office on the above subject. 2* I should be grateful if all copies of correspond ence on the following subjects could be sent to Political Agent, Bahrain. 1. Eastern frontiers of Arabia. 2. Petroleum Concessions Limited's interests in '&lt;&amp;tar 3. Khor al Odaid and Abu Dhabi. .Jd. H. WGHTMAH. Offg. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf,*P.2.2076/1938. copy . (E 97l/lt&gt;0/91) No. 10 . Britan Legation, (339/54 5/16) Jedda. January 23rd, 1^35• \' \ y' \ Sir, X c f ^ In your telegram iiio.loy dated December ytn, ly37 1 nad the honour to receive your permission to tell the Jedda manager of the California Standard Arabian oil Company informally of tne present position in regard to the eastern irentier of baudi Arabia. I saw Mr. Lena/j&amp;m on Decemoer lltn 9 aiia ^ave xAim tne information in quest loxi. ne expressed nis tnanics , and said that the Saudi Government had already explained about tne territory in dispute and had told them not to enter it. ne added that while his Company naturalxy wanted the question to be settled and would be the better pleased the more the territory covered by their concession, they were very anxious not to enter disputed territory and nad given their representatives on tne spot strict instructions to that end 0 ne himself had wondered whether the prospecting party had perhaps entered the disputed area by mistake \ and caused the British Government to protest, since about six weeks earlier the Governor of riasa had suddenly recalled the prospecting prospecting party to Banaiyan. 1 said that the recall of tne 4 party could not be connected with the recent comaumcat ion of His Majesty^ Government to tue baudi Government, wnich had only just been made. le As I had spoken to Mr. Ijen&amp;n&amp;xu x or nm confidential information I was rather surprised when, a lew days later, tfuad Bey referred to tne matter, having heard of it from Mr. Lenahara. /Fuad Bey Right Honourable Anthony Bden, m.C., m.f., ., &amp;c., &amp;c•,Fuad Bey said tiiat tue King was hurt because our action suggested tn&amp;t we did not trust him to do what was right. 1 said tnat tnere wa.s no question of distrust, tfor did nis Majesty's Government arrogate to tuemseives t^e right, as jH’uaa Bey seemed to tninu tney aid, to give instructions to a foreign company operating in commercial Saudi territory. All over tne world tnere was^competit ion between British and American oil companies, and it was natural that information should be given tnem in such cases as tn&amp;t of tne Qatar frontier. Fuad Bey said tn&amp;t t.ue Saudi Government considered tnat tne frontier question was between Governments. They could not object to our keeping in touch with the united States Government on tne matter, if we wished to do so, but tney did object to our speaking to the company and tnereoy, as they considered, interfering in a matter which lay between t^era and tne Company, and tney would make a protest in writing. * * ^**** f *^ / 1 r* Q 3. By way of showing tne friendly attitude of tne Saudi Government Fuad Bey said tnat tne prospecting party n&amp;d entered the disputed zone but were given orders to witndr&amp;w on receipt of my note of December 4th. fnis is at variance with what Mr. Lenaham said, ana I am inclined to disbelieve it. 4. Enclosed is a translation of a written protest datea January lOtn but received on January 1/Vh. i am telling Fuad Bey tnat tne letter is being forwarded to nis Majesty's Government and pointing out tnat tuere is no question of our having discussed tne frontier question with tne Company, who were merely kept informed of the situation. 5 5. Mr. Lenanam professed great regret at having raised tnis issue by mentioning the matter to Fuad Bey, and excused himself on the ground tnat ne had not understood tnat 1 was speaking to nim coniidentially• mt. Lenaham is not intelligent and not always sober, and his excuse may oe genuine. On tne otner Fuad Bey /alreadyalready Knew un orriciaily irom iflr.Lenanaii tnat Tine foreign Office nad spoKen to Mr. Hamilton in London and was waiting 1'or ?jtr.Lenanan to get permission to tell nim so , oi'xicially so tnat ne could act on tne ini ormat ion. 1'ne wording or tne written protest suggests tnat Mr. Lenanan uas now ootainea tnat permission. According to mr. Lenanan, u'uaa Bey seemea personally annoyed to learn tnat communications nad passed beniiid nis OacK, and tnis agrees witn wnat one Knows of j?uad Bey. On tne otner nand tne suggestion tnat our communicating witn tne Company mignt be interpreted as indicating distrust of tne Saudi (xovernment mignt well nave come from tne ning. 6. I can only suggest tnat a written reply snould be sent to tne Saudi (xovernment repeating more or less wnat 1 nave said orally. Tne reply mignt say tnat tne communication between His Majesty's Government and tne California Standard Arabian Oil Company was not based on any distrust of tne Saudi Arabian Government but was in accordance witn tne prac tice wnere important oil companies, wnetner ox tne same or different nationalities, are operating in adjoining areas: and tnat His Majesty's Government nave nad no discussions witn tne Company, but nave merely conveyed information to tnem, and tnerefore regret tnat tne Saudi Arabian government snould taKe exception to wnat is a normal procedure intended to ensure tne maintenance or good relations between tne great oil companies and tne countries in wnicn tney are registered. I nave etc., Bd. R .W.BULLARDEnclosure to Jectda aespatcn iso.10 ^ 139/046/13] oi January 23 tu 1936. Minister lor foreign Aflairs, Mecca. 9tu Unu* ii ^u f aa, 1306. IQtn January, 1936. Your Excellency, Tne representative oi tne California Arabian Oil Company informed tne government of ni a Majesty tnat lour Excellency spoice to nim about tne present position of tne soutn-eastern frontier, as tne Foreign Office in London spoxe to tne Company^ representative Mr. Hamilton, in a manner wnicn mignt be interpreted as implying tne existence of doubts and suspicion as to nig Majesty’s attitude. iour Excellency is avare tnat tne question of tne irontiers cannot be discussed except between tne governments concerned. fne companies act according to tne instructions issued to tnem by tne governments concerned in tne territories (in question), and it is tnereiore mucn to be disired tnat tne company snould not be brougnt into tne question and tnat tne Britisn government snould avoid dis cussion witn tne Caliiornia company on a subject wnicn concerns tne Government of His Majesty alone. tne deputy Minister tor Foreign Aliairs Has explained to you tne interpretations wnicn mignt be placed upon tne interference of tne .Britisn government (in dealing) witn tne Company direct in tnis matter, and my Government tnereiore nope tnat tne Britisn Government will put tnis rignt in future. Signed• FAISALP.2. 2076/38 No. 101 (E 971/100/91) Sir, I nave Aad; under consideration your aespatcn no. lu (139/b46/13) oi* 23rci January in regard to tne activities oi tne Caliiornia Standard Arabian Oil Company m tne neign- bournood or tne E^atar frontier. 2. You will recall from Sir Jonn Simon’s despatcn So.112 of lytn Marcn 1954, tnat early in tnat year tne United States Embassy in Angora made informal enquiries of His Majesty’s Embassy regarding tne treaty instruments governing tne frontiers separating tne former ottoman Dominions and tne territories to tne east and soutn tnereoi. Some tnree montns later tne United States Embassy in .London made similar enquiry oi my department in c quhqx i on witn tixe aircraft wnicn tne California Standard Arabian Oil Company were tnen pr oposing to use I or survey woric over une area oi tneir concession in Eastern Saudi-Arabia, end it was discoverr ed tnat tne enquiries in Angora nad in fact been made in connexion witn tnis oil company’s concession. (See foreign Office despatcn to Jedda fio.166 of 2btn Arpil 1954). Care was taEen to explain to tne united States Embassy in fond on, tor tne iniormation oi tne oil company, tnat tne legal frontier oi Saudi Arabia in tnis area was tne “blue line' and tne Saudi Arabian Uoveminent were subsequently informed tnat nig Majesty’s Government naa made tnis communication to tne United States Government (Jedda despatcn no. 150 oi 2btn April 1954). 5. Since tnose communications nis Majesty's Government nave not informed eitner tne united States Government or tne Saudi Arabian Government tnat tney no longer regard tne 'Slue line' as tne legal rrontier or tnat tne oil company ls lr ee to FOREIGN ORFICE, S.W.l. 23ru Marcn, 195b. operate/*« © operate to tne east or tnat iiiie, rtis Majesty's &lt;joveriii(ierit v/ould, I reel, nave been justilied m protesting to tne Saudi Arabian Government wnen tney learnt tnat tne concession ary oil company, in spite or tneir original communication to tne Saudi Arabian Government, were operating in tne neign- bournood or ^asr-esSalwa. On tne contrary, out or dererence to King Abdul Aziz, and in tneir desire to do all tney couia to lac i lit ate matters ror nim and lor tne company operating m nis territory, iiis Majesty’s Government retrained irom making any complaints eitner to tne united States government or to tne Saudi Arabian Government and tney conrmed tneir actioii to inlorming tne interested representatives 01 tne oil com pany quite informally, tnat notwitnstanding tneir previous communications to tne united States ana sauai Arabian uov- ernments, tiiey v/ould raise no objection to tne company op erating to tne east or wnat nis Majesty’s Government still regarded as tne legal eastern frontier or Saudi Arabian territory. Tne only condition made was tnat tne company snould refrain from encroacning beyond tne maximum line wmcn His Majesty’s Government nad onered to King Abdul Aziz. 4 * Ileaveitto your discretion to maJse sucn use 01 tnis material as you consider appropriate in your reply to tne Saudi Arabian Government’s representations, wnicn may, subject to tnese suggestions, loilow tne line recommenced in paragrapn 6 or your despatcn. I am, witn great trutn ana regard, Sir, four obedient Servant, (i’or tne Secretary oi state) Sd. La cy Hagg all ay2* 2033/1938 Enclosure in Foreign Office covering note No # E 1251/3.50/91 Having received your final instructions about the eastern / f frontier of Southern Arabia, conveyed in your telegrams Nog* 16 and 17 of the 27th January, I addressed a note to the Saudi On account of the pilgrimage, which is now at its height, a reply 2« In my telegram No* 56, dated the 31st January, I had the honour to inform you of Fuad Bey’s obvious consternation on hearing the interpretation r/hich His Majesty's Government place upon the letter from Mr. Calvert of the 26th September, 1935. 4 | I transmit herewith a copy of a letter on this point which he has sent me, and a copy of my reply. Fuad Bey was, perhaps, disin -enuous in quoting from the Arabic translation of Mr. Calvert’s letter, when he knows that the Arabic is only sent unofficially in order to assist the Ministry for Foreign A: fairs. Nevertheless the wording of the Assurance** was misleading, and unfortunately the Arabic is even more misleading, as the word 'considerable', which has no exact equivalent in common use in Arabic, was rendered, by the temporary translator who, in the absence of both the regular translators, had been borrowed from the Sudan, by the word 'adhim', which means 'great'. dated 23rd March, 1938 EASTERN (Arabia) . COI^IPENTXAL. March 7. 1938 . Section 1. (E 1251/150/91) Copy No.116. Sir R. Bullard to Mr. Eden. - (Received March 7. ) (No.28.) Jedda, February 14, 1938. L Sir, / Government on the 3rd February. A copy of this note is enclosed is not expected for a few days. |x | COPY SENT TO3* If Sheikh Hafiz Wahfoa and Mr* Zada had kept as careful a record as was kept by the Foreign Office of a meeting with Mr# Rendel at the Foreign Office on the 27th Hovember, 1935, (Foreign Office despatch ITo* 346, dated the 3rd December, 1935), any misunderstanding created by Mr# Calvert’s letter of the previous September would have been cleared up* The first part of the Foreign Office record reads as follows:*- • .• ; 'On the 27th November, the Saudi Minister, with whom I had been lunching, raised the question of the south-ear;j?rn Arabian frontiers with special reference to the Qatar Oil Concession. I found that Sheikh Hafiz had not clearly realised the position about the concession and I explained to him, with the aid of a map produced by Mr*. Zada, that the concession was for a limited area which was described on a map attached to the concession, and that although, in one place, it extended slightly beyond the maximum frontier claimed by King Abdul Asiz, it did not, in fact, extend to what we regarded as the frontier between Qatar and Saudi Arabia. The limit of the concession in fact lay well to the north of the maximum line which we had been able to offer to King Abdul Aziz. There mm no question of an unlimited ’blanket concession’, as in the case of the Saudi concession to the Standard Oil Company of California, and in viewof our known views on the frontier question there could be no question of tne concession extending over territory the sovereignty over which was in any real doubt. 'Sheik Hafiz did not dissent from this explanation and did not pursue the matter further,' I have, etc,, R. W. BULLARD#Mmmmmmmmmarnmmm Enc loiiu^e 1. 3. Sir. Bullard to the minister for Foreign Affaire &gt; Mecca # (No. 22). Jedda, February 3, 1938. Your Royal Hi^mese, (After CompllmentB•) 1 have the honour to acknowledge receipt of your Royal Highness’s letter dated the 19th December last regarding the boundary between the Saudi Arabian Kingdom and the territories of the Sheikhs of Qatar and Abu Dhabi. I did not fail to communicate to my Government the views expressed in that letter as well as the substance of various conversations which I had with his Excellency Fuad Bey both before and after the date of the letter. In the course of the discussion to which your Royal Highness refers, which I had the pleasure to have with his Excellency on the 10th December, I learned that His Majesty’s Government had no cause to believe that the California Arabian standard Oil Company would take action In the disputed area, and I conveyed this information to my Government, who were very glad to receive this assurance* My Government, however, much regret to learn from your Royal Highness’s above-mentioned letter that the 8a* di Arabian Government attribute the failure to reach a settlement to His 1 ,■ g \ Majesty’a Government. As Mr* Rendel had the honour to joint out to His Majesty King Abdul Asia in person, my Government have repeatedly made concessions on this point, whereas the Saudi Arabian Government have been unwilling to abate their claim in the least. My Government are obliged to say, though with the most sincere regret,'that they cannot see how it is possible for them to make any further concession in regard to a frontier which they adopted in accordance with history and the essential needs of the Arab States concerned. They feel that in bringing the frontier which they are prepared to acceptbo much nearer to the frontier proposed by the Saudi Arabian Government than they had originally considered poissible they have shown a s|)irit of conciliation which they trust the Saudi Arabian Government have not overlooked. p 1 ’' As to the proposed topographical mission, I did not fail to explain to my Government the opinion set forth Inihe last paragraph but one of your Royal Highness’s letter. My Government have considered that opinion with the attention which they pay to ever y proposal made to them by the Saudi Arabian Government, but they do not find it possible to agree that the proposed mission would be pointless, since they believe that the claim of the Saudi Arabian Government is baaed in part upon incorrect topographical data. The sole object of the mission would be to establish certain facts, and my Government trust that the Saudi Arabian Government will find it po sible to agree to its despatch. With highest respects, R. W. BULLARD. Enclosure 2. Fuad Bey Hamsa to ir R. Bullard . (Translation.) Ministry for Foreign Affairs, Mecca pebruiary 5, 1933* Dear Sir Reader, As a result of your conversation with me last Sunday evening, the 30th January, regarding the correspondence going on about the abstention of the employees of the companies ox&gt;eratlng, whether in Saudi Arabia or in the Arab amirates, on the Persian Gulf from penetrating beyond the frontier to which my Government adhere, I looked up the correspondence exchanged/exchanged between Mr* Calvert and my collea ue, Yusuf Yasin, of the 26th September, 1935, and the 17th Jumsdi-al-Tliani (? Ra t 1ob), 1354, thinking that I mirht perhaps find in it what you mentioned to me in your conversation that evening6m subject), I am glad to draw your attention in this respect to the true facts that our Government always 1 desire that their relations with the Amirs of those teirritories (literally, directions) should be lasting relations of affection and friendship, and do not desire to restrict (literally, press upon) them and their affairs, and they (Saudi Arabian Government) showed their readiness to grant them areas (territories) to the utmost extent which can be granted, on the understanding that the whole of those domains were previously subject to the fathers and forefathers of His Majesty the King Abdul Aziz* As regards the legal rights to v/hlch you refer and to which the British Government pretend our Government cannot recognise and accept them and cannot consider them as basis for any discussion in connexion with those frontiers. In respect of the above, our Government therefore preserve their fullest rights in the territories and places which they cannot agree to renounce in favour of the Amirs of those territories, and (in regard to) all privileges or rights which may be granted at those reserved places, our Government cannot recognise or agree to then, and record their reservation in their regard. This is on the one hand, and on the other I am pleased to inform you that our Government are fully prepared at any time to discuss the settlement of the question of the frontiers in a spirit of affection and friendship to those neighbouring Amirs whenever discussion may be resumed on this subject. ” /v ' ' •, (The English of tills passage is taken from the translation which was sent to the Foreign Office in Jedda printed letter Ho*292 of the 16th October, 1955*) ( s ) K 1 „v.,S r ^ t Tills letter was apparently effective in inducing the British Government to issue instructions to Mr* Calvert to ) ’’Further Correspondence respecting Eastern Affairs”, Part XXXVII, No.47, Enclosure. address/* address to Sheikh Yusuf Ye sin another letter, dated the 26th October, in which he stated that 'Sir Andrew Ryan, who, as your Excellency is aware, is shortly arriving in Riyadh, will bring with him new proposals in regard to the frontier question. His Majesty’s Government hope that these proix&gt;sals will lead to a settlement'• ;V ' R| Sir Andrew Ryan did in fact bring new proposals which modified the previous ones. This shows that the position of the British Government as indicated by Mr, Calvert in his first letter of the 26th September, 1935, was not final, as I understood from you in your conversation, K &lt; The position of my Government regarding the frontier to which they adhere is explained in the note sent by His Highness the Amir Faisal to your Excellency on the 16th Shawwal, 1356 3the 13th December, 1937), They consider that it is within their power to authorise the employees of the California Arabian Standard Oil Company to penetrate right upto the line to which my Government adhere, and if you will refer to the last paragraph but one of that note you will perceive the fact* As a result of that, personal correspondence took place bet?/een us as to the meaning of that paragraph, and I explained clearly the intention of my Government, and at the same time I explained to you their readiness, when they should have received the agreement of the authorities concerned in the Arab anirates on the Pex # sian Gulf that the employees of the companies should not encroach upon the frontier to v/hich they hold, to refrain ffom authorising the employees of the California Arabian Standard Oil Company to pass beyond the Green Line, In the contrary case, they still insist on their opinion that there is nothing whatever to prevent them from authorising them to operate ri ht up to the line by which they indicated their small clairas from the Arab anirates. FUAD HAMZA. Enclosure 3/8 Enclosure 5 . Sir R« Bullard to Fuad Bey Hamza * Jedda, February 9 t 1938* My dear Fuad Bey, In replying to your letter of the 5th February I think it more useful to confine myself to the meaning of the letter of Mr* Calvert of the 26th September, 1935, as I tried to do in our conversation of the 30th January* I am sorry if the Saudi Arabian Government read the paragraph which you quote In a different sense from the sense in which it was intended by His Majesty’s Government* 1 notice that you quote the Arabic translation which was sent with Mr* Calvert’s letter* You are aware, however f that the official text of on cormiun.ications to the Ministry for Foreign Affairs is the English, which is signed by the head of the xjoat: the Arabic translation is sent for the convenience of the Ministry* The paragraph to which you refer reads thus:- f ’The southern limit of the oil concession granted to the Anglo-Iranian Oil Company by the Sheikh of Qatar does not extend beyond this 'Green Line’, but lies to a considerable distance to the north of it. The concession does not, therefore, extend to any territory under discussion with the Saudi Government”. (In the Arabic t anslation which accompanied this letter this passage was inserted in English*) This paragraph is comjjosed of two sentences* The second is merely a corollary of the first, and was based on repeated assertions by His Majesty’s Government that they were not prepared to discuss any further abatement of their claims beyond the Green Line* It is true that His Majesty’s Gover ment subsequently found t nemo elves able to propose the line which was ] ut forward by Sir Andrew Ryan at Riyadh, but that/R.W.BtJLL,l-!D. mtssem 9. thet Is beside the point for the moment. My point is that t ie paragraph quoted above expressed the position as it was on the 26th September, 1955, from the point of view of His Ma3 esty * s Government• I hope that this paragraph is now quite clear. Yours eincerelp.»*?4 ■ ■ v5tiling UN F9ffeicm OF? CA [This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Governme^Fr^ni^^ou^pSe'fetyrned to the Foreign Office if not required for official ^se. j 1 */ r% o i o r\ : From SAUDI ARABIA, Decypher. Sir R. Bullard (Juada).^^^ ^ 1938i D. 5.00 p.m. Fehruary 24th 1958, R. 2o 50 p.m. February 24th 1956, No.41. ^ . /** /N /'v /% /\ /\ /\ /^ /** s* b V telegram No.40 dated Fehraary 23rd was sent when only the first four paragraphs of your telegram Bo. 24 o.l Fe^nuo... j 17tn had Been decyphered hut my suggestion is not affected hy examination of the rest of your message. Now that you see possibility that our line might he modified to some extent It seems even more desirable to ask Saudi Government at once for their f, practical suggestions . Addressed to Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs No. 41, repeated to Government of India No.o.CONFIDENTIAL. No. c/24 5 The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to CM The Political Agent, Bahrain, and has k the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents ($), Office of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, at Bahrain. Dated.mfc. Asr.U.. m3* Reference to previous correspondence: Residency Printed letter No.c/232 of 10th April 1938, Description of Enclosure. Jedda despatch No.E 1759/l50/f dated 12th March 19 38, to the Foreign Off ice. Saudi Arabian Frontier.Copy. (3 1759/150/91) BRITISH LEGATION, JEDDA 9 SAUDI ARABIA, 12th March 1938. My dear Baxter, The Arab broker of a British firm here brought this rumour to the manager a few days ago: 'The California Arabian Standard Oil Co. are n dalighted with the discovery of oil in Hasa, but ’’they are urging the King to claim some ’British 'territory* in ^atar because they are afraid of 'British competition with oil that may be discovered Sthere.” I told Euad this and asked how he thought the tale had got about. He first said that perhaps someone had heard a vague story about the oil recently found in Kuwait, but he had to admit that the tale fitted the Jabal N&amp;khsh business too closely to be guesswork. Finally he got very red in the face and said that he must admit that C.A.S.O.C. attached great importance to Jabal Nakhsh. I said that that was no news to us, as their interest had been made clear two years ago and more. I have always held that the Saudi passion for Jabal Hakhah was purely economic, and I hope that the discovery of oil in Hasa may enable the King to renounce possible oil in Jabal Nakhsh, if something c$n be done about Khor el Odeid. Yours ever, Sd. R.W. BULLARD. . Baxter Esq., M.C.P.Z.2887/38 India 0 11 ice, Whiteliall, S. .7. 1 3rd May, 1938 / / Sir, In connexion with the recent correspondence on the subject of the South Eastern boundaries of Saudi Arabia I an directed by the Secretary of State for India to forward, for the information of the Secretary of State ior Foreign Aifairs, a copy of a note by Sir Trenchard Eowle containing his replies to the questions addi^essed r to him in the Secretary of State's telegram of the 18th March, No.561, (of which a copy was sent to you on the y\'-X ? ^ 22nd March under cover of India Office letter No.P.Z. 1677/38) relative to the possible cession of the Khor al Odeid to Ibn Saud. In the light .of this note, and of the viey^s expressed in the Resident's telegram of the .6th February, and in the Government of India's telega A'ram of the 8th March (copies of which were sent to you ' A , l f - ' respectively on the 28th February and 9th March, under cover of India Office letter numbered P.Z.1344/38 and 1600/38) the Marquess of Zetland is now able to express his considered opinion on the proposals which have been advanced for a settlement of the frontier separating Saudi Arabia from Qatar and the Trucial Sheikhs. 2. These proposals were put forward by your Department early in February as an outcome of the desire of His Majesty's Government for the investigation of various proposals for securing the good will of Xing Ibn Saud. It was represented that one of the most important outstanding questions between His Majesty's Government Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, S.W.l. and/and Saudi Arabia was that of the South Eastern Saudi frontier, ana that the removal of this source of friction would be a valuable contribution to the promotion of good will between Saudi Arabia and His Ihaiesty's Government in other matters. Agreement on the definition of the frontier has hitherto been founa impossible by reason of the insistence of the Sruai Government on their claim to three localities which, named in descending order of the importance apparently attached to them by Ibn Saud, are the Jebel liaksh, the Khor al Odeid and Sufuk. Since it is generally recognised that no compromise is possible in respect of the Jebel Haksh attention was devoted to the Khor al Odeid and to the possibility of reaching a satisfactory frontier settlement by the cession of this locality to Ibn Saud if the difficulties arising from the recognised rights of the Sheikh of Abu Dhabi could be overcome. 3. Apart from the desirability of reaching a satisfactory settlement of the disputed frontier, Lord Zetland fully recognises the importance of retaining and promoting Ibn Saud 1 s good will towaras His Majesty's Government. But he shares the Government of India's doubt whether the offer of the Khor al Odeid, if it could be made, would be regarded by Ibn Saud as ox sufficient value to affect materially the cordiality of His Majesty's Government's relations with Ibn Saud, whereas, on the other hand, an attempt to overcome the formidable difficulties in the way of arranging tne cession might well involve a grave risk of prejudicing British influence among the protected Rulers of the Gulf. It seems to him that nothing has happened in the pasto * IT year to invalidate the view expressed by .His Majesty's Minister at Jedda in his despatch No.47of the 27th March 1937 wherein he said that even if it were possible to induce the Sheikh of Abu fhabi to give up the IChor al Odeid to Ibn Saud he 'doubted whether the transfer would be worth the making since it would not give Ibn Saud the port he needs and we should have made a political sacrifice without gaining the advantage which I think we should stand to gain from any improvement in Ibn Saud 1 s economic position'. 4. With regard to the feasibility of arranging the cession of the IChor al Odeid it is accepted that the cession could not be effected without the consent of the Sheikh of Abu Dhabi, whose ownership has been acknowledged by a series of decisions by Government culminating in the guarantee given to the Sheikh in 1906. Lord Zetland would be firmly opposed to any suggestion that pressure should be exerted on the Sheikh to secure his consent to the cession. In the Secretary of State's view any question of a cession v/ould necessarily have to depend on the Sheikh's voluntary consent, and whether this would be forthcoming would obviously depend on the advantages which he would expect to derive therefrom. The political .V;. - f * vi Resident has pointed out in his telegram of the 26th February that there is no imminent menace of Saudi or Wahabi expansion which the Sheikh would wish to arrest at the cost of surrendering part of his territory, and in his view it would be necessary for His Majesty's Government to satisfy the Sheikh with monetary compensation if his consent is to be obtained. Sir Trenchara Fowle finds it impossible to hazard any guess as to the amount of such compensc ation/compensation that the Sheikh would be likely to accept. In his opinion it would have to be settled by a process of bargaining, and he can only suggest, in the light of the Sheikh 1 s dealings with letroleum Concessions Limited, that his figure would be likely to be high. But, even if His Majesty’s Government were prepared to make funds available for this purpose, any attempt to purchase the Sheikh’s consent is bonne, in Lord Zetland’s view, to have very unfavourable reactions on British prestige among the Arab Sheikhs of the Gulf, 5. There is also the further difficulty that the Sheikh might not unreasonably expect any frontier settlement achieved in return for a territorial sacrifice on his part to be accompanied by an assurance that the frontier would be respected, and might accordingly demand a guarantee of protection on the landward side of his territory. His Majesty’s Government would of course be able to promise the Sheikh diplomatic intervention in the event of violation of his territory, but it is not yet clear that he could be promised the more practical assistance which he might consider indispensable for the defence of his frontier. 6. Apart from the practical difficulties indicated above Lord Zetland feels that the suggested compromise is open to several other serious objections. In the Government of India’s view the traditional objections to admitting Sauai influence to the frucial Coast and to allowing the chain of protected States to be broken are still of considerable weight. The strategical importance of the air route along the Arab coast of the Gulf certainly seems to demand that there should be no weakening of8./ 5. British influence among the local Shaikhs. In Lord Zetland's view the cession of territory on the Trucial Coast to Ibn Sand - territory to which, it must be emphasised, he has no historical claim - would not fail to enhance his prestige, at the expense of that of His Majesty's Government, among the Trucial Sheikhs, quite apart from the pe rmanent opportunity it would give for the active extension of Saudi influence among them. Moreover, as the Resident ana the Government of India have pointed out, even if the Sheikh's consent were refused, the attempt to secure it, particularly if accompanied by some financial inducement, might easily create the Impression that His Majesty's Go ve r nine nr were anxious through fear of Ibn Saud to yield to his demanus. Such an impression would be specially unfortunate at the present time when the Sheikhs are in a difficult mood and show signs of thinking that His Majesty's Government's wishes can be disregarded with impunity. 7. While Lord Zetland regrets that it has so far proved impossible to reach agreement with Ibn Saud on the question of the frontier re sees no au.vantcigo, —O* tiio reasons given above, in attempting to reach a settlemeno ac the expense of one of the Rulers unuer His Majesty's Government's protection, ana he trusts that the propose.! will not be pressed. In His Lordship’s view the utmost possible concessions in regard to this frontier na^e already been offered to the claims of Ibn Saud, and he suggests that in the circumstances Iiis Majesty's Government should continue to take their stand on ohe offer that has been repeatedly described as iinal.6 . ^ * Copies ox chi s let/i er an cl enclosure are being seiii to the Colonial Oxxice, War Otfice ? Admiralty, Air Ministry Treasury and Petroleum Department. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, (Sgd.) R. PEtu/ Note by Sir Trencliard Fowl© dated 16th April, 1938. / c? (a) Paragraph 2 of Inal a Office telegram No.561 of \ } 22nd March. I am sorry that is is quite impossible for me to give any figure, even a tentative one. All I can say is that judging from the Sheikh’s demands of Petroleum Concessions Limit-ed in the matter of the oil concession, this figure would be a fairly large one. (b) Paragraph 3 of same telegram. I do not think that there will be quite the same objections against using the arguments suggested as against offering a monetary compensation, but the Sheikh (of Abu Dhabi), being an Arab would probably get the (erroneous) impression that in trying to persuade him to surrender part of his territory to Ibn Saud (1) we were frightened of the latter, and (2) we were trying to placate the latter at his, the Sheikh’s, expense. These impressions of the Sheikh would undoubtedly get about in Abu Dhabi and the rest of the Arab coast, and would, of course, do us no good. I have already reported (vide paragraph 9 of my Express Letter , &lt;P. 'Ar.-fiCS. No.C-71 of 16th February) that there are disquieting symptoms among the Trucial Coast Sheikhs and their people that they think the wishes of His Majesty’s Government can be disregarded more or less with impunity. (c) Paragraph 4 of the same telegram. The possibility of giving a guarantee of protection to the Sheikh would depend, it seems to me, on our power to implement the guarantee, which again depends on the views of the Service Departments, particularly the H.A.k. I think it extremely likely that in the event of a definite lUr frontier/mmmgmnmmmmmmmmmmmmmamm frontier being proposed as between Abu Dhabi and Saudi Arabia, the first question which the Sheikh would ask would be: 'Will His Majesty's Government guarantee it as against the Saudi Government?' (G) ParagrajMi 5 of the same telegram. I think there are objections to the line running through Sufuk Wells. The line in my view should leave the wells to Abu Dhabi. There is no objection to Sir Header Bullard's suggestion that the wells themselves should be free of access to the Saudi tribes. This in fact is common Bedouin practice in regard to wells.4963 2000 7.36 INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, ^ 6 i&gt;lM / JSM Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy has been sent to b y ^L MaiL The Forei,£?» Secretary, Governme nt of hidia^ -- The Political Resident in the Puruian On If'-5634/38 Enclosure in Foreign Office covering letter dated 3rd May 1938. Copy. (E 2777/150/91) No. 72(803/546/49) His Majesty’s Minister at Jedda presents his compliments to His Majesty’s Principal Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs&gt; and has the honour to transmit to him the under-mentioned documents. British Legation f Jedda. Z Kererence to previous correspondence: )ffice despatch No. 101(S 971/150/91) of 23rd March, 1938. 14th iipril, 1938 Description of Enclosure Name and Date Subject TO: Saudi Minister for Qatar frontier and oil company Foreign Affairs, note No. 75 of D4th April,British Legation, , Jedda• ^6/39) April li+th 1938* / I'V' I Your Royal Highness, After Compliments, I have .the honour to inform Your Royal Highness that I transmitted to my Government the unnumbered letter from the Ministry of Foreign Affairs dated Janua**y 10th 1938, regarding the activities of the California Arabian Standard Oil Company in the neighbour hood of the Qatar frontier, and that I have now received their observations on this point, which are as follows* In 1934&gt; when the said oil company was beginning its operations in Hasa, the Government of the United States of America asked His Majesty’s Government for information about the boundaries in those parts. His Majesty’s Government furnished the required information, and in particular, care was taken to explain, for the information of the oil company, that the legal frontier of Saudi Arabia in that area was the ’’blue line.” The fact that this communication had been made to the United States Government was duly conveyed to the Saudi Arabian Government in Sir ^ndrew Ryan’s letter No. 65 of April 28th 1934* Since that time His Majesty’s Government have not informed either the United States Government or the Saudi Arabian Government that they no longer regard the 'blue line' as the legal frontier or that they consider the oil company free to operate to the east of that line. His Majesty’s Government feel that they would have been justified in protesting to t e Saudi Arabian Govemment when they learned that the oil company, in spite of the above— mentioned letter to the Saudi Government, were operating/ J Royal Highness The Minister for Foreign Affairs, Mecca.i V ■ffqffffMBE'm [i ij n u i 2 . operating in the neighbourhood of Qasr al Balwa. On the contrary, out of deference to His Majesty King Abdul Aziz, and in their desire to do all they could to facilitate matters for him and for the company operating in his territory, they confined their action to informing representatives of the comi^any, quite informally, that notwithstanding their previous communications to the United States and Saudi Arabian Governments, they would raise no objection to the company’s operating to the east of the line which His Majesty’s Government still regarded as the legal eastern frontier of Saudi Arabian territory, on the understanding that the company would not encroacn on territory to the east of the extreme limit proposed by His Majesty’s Government to the Saudi Government* The action of His Majesty’s Government and of this Legation in conveying the information in question to representatives of the California Arabian Standard Oil Company was in accordance with the practice in cases where important oil companies, whether of the same or of different nationalities, are operating in adjoining areas, and His Majesty’s Government regret that the Saudi Government should take exception to what is a normal procedure intended to ensure the maintenance of good relations between the great oil companies and also between the countries in which they are registered. With highest respects, Sd. H.W* Bullard* * i&lt; * * * * ** Extract from P.A f s Note dated the 3rd June 1938 on his Visit to Abu Dhabi on the 31st May 1938• NOTE ON VISIT TO ABU DHABI. *** *** *** ** ** When I showed signs of leaving he raised two matters. The first was that the Liwa people had re ported that some Europeans or Americans with Saudi guards had come almost up to Liwa in three cars this April. They had been stopped by sand but the Arab guard had said they would be coming again in 'cars that run on sand'. I am not quite sure of the position of Liwa and will enquire from the Residency Agent. If, as I think, it is quite definitely in Abu Dhabi terri tory, I will take the matter up v/ith Mr. Thornberg, whom I have already asked to control the California Arabian Standard Oil Company* s geologists more effect ively.INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, £ % .(,-3g - Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy lias been sent to r* ) by Mail. The Foreign Secretary, Government of India. ^The Political Resident in tlro^l^ersian GulC 4963 2000 7.36© , 4417 / 193 $, \dv* : nclosure la Foreign Office covering letter So. £.£$ 99 / 150 / 91 , dwted June £4th, 1931. ^ 9 / 160 / 91 ) BRItlbH L&amp;GATI0H ilXDDA t eudl Arable l£th prll, 193$- * dear Baxter, la my lost coaveraatloa with ohslkh Heflx fahba before hie departure for England I ©poke of the various queationb on whloh we were trying to give Itm baud advice or aeelatance. shaikh Hafiz said that the King still felt very sore about the Qatar boundary, and unable to reconcile our attitude with our profession®. The King, according to shaikh Hafls, attributes the attitude of H.M. Governnent on this point entirely to the fact that the oil company operating In Haaa Is American, and feels this all the more unjust In that he repeatedly tried to get British oil interests to put in for a concession there. I said that our attitude was based on historical considerations going back long before the days of oil, and spoke highly of the California Arabian tandard Oil Company. The final decision will probably have been taken before this letter reaches you, but I send the Informat ton nevertheless 'to complete the record'. Yours die. , (a) u .Bullard '-.Baxter, Esq. , &amp;.CBy Air Mail. P.Z. 193?' \db INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, 6 JUL Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy has been sent to by Mail. - J Sea.f 'Z■ [E 2579/150/91), IMMEDIATE * Slrj POREISN OFFICE, S.W.l. 1st July, 1938. I am by Vlscduht Halifax ti request you to inform the Marquess of Zetland that he has darefully considered your letter P.Z.2887/38 of 3rd May, respecting the possibility of ceding to Ibn Saud, in order thereby to secure an agreed frontier between the Trucial Sheikhdtms and Saudi Arabia, certain territory adjoining the Khor-el-Odeid which at present belongs to the Sheikh of Abu Dhabi* 2* Lord Halifax fully realizes that the grant to Ibn Saud of access to the Khor-el-Odeid could not be guaranteed to have a lasting good effect upen his relations with His Majesty*s Government. It is unhappily only too likely that the necessity placed upon His Majesty’s Government of following a certain policy ip regard to Palestine may make it impossible for Ibn Saud not to work against them in certain circumstances, whether he receives satisfaction over his south-eastern frontiers or not. He has never made any attempt to conceal this possibility and the prospect of having it forced upon him has been .one of the principal motives behind his constant appeals to His Majesty’s Government to reconsider their policy* 3./ der-Secretary of State, India Office*5. But although it cannot he guaranteed that any concession which might be made over the Khor-el-Odeid would have a permanent effect in securing Ibn Baud’s friendship, there are strong arguments, in Lord Halifax's opinion, for making every endeavour to reach a final settlement of this in fact see great advantage in such a settlement even from the point of view of delations with Saudi Arabia* In His Lordship's opinion the position is different from what it was when Sir Reader Bullard expressed his doubts a year ago as to the advantages to be obtained from letting Ibn Saud have access to the Khor-el-Odeid, because His Majesty's Government have since then, and at a time when the general adopted the policy of setting up a Jewish State in a part of Palestine. The change which this has brought into the Middle must clearly do everything within their power at this present juncture to retain the good-will of Ibn Saud and - more important still - to strengthen his hand in dealing with his access to the sea at a new point on the Persian Gulf and could be represented as a success for his diplomacy would : help in both these directions. In any case the dangers of the present time are so great that no course of action which may frontier question at the present time. His Lordship would international outlook has become increasingly threatening, Eastern situation is fundamental and His Majesty s Government own people. A frontier settlement which would give him promote these objects can safely be overlooked.claim to the Khor-el-Odeid might with advantage he made even at the risk of considerable inconvenience in other directions, as for example some diminution in the prestige of His Majesty's Government in the Persian Gulf, although he is naturally desirous that no avoidable action should be taken which might have this result. But for the reasons given below he is not convinced that the — ■ action which has been proposed for the settlement of . - - - - the south-eastern frontiers of Saudi Arabia need in fact have a serious adverse effect on British prestige locally. 5. The position, as His Lordship sees it, is as follows. The Sheikh of Abu Dhabi controls a territory extending inland from the coast for an indefinite distance. In theory this territory may be regarded as having in the recent past extended, or at any rate as having been capable of extension, as far west as the Blue line of the Anglo-Turkish Convention of 1914 and as far south as the boundary, wherever that may be, dividing the territory of the Sultan of Muscat and Oman (whose territory has likewise been theoretically capable of extension to the Blue line) from the territories of the Trucial Sheikhs. In practice, however, the Sheikh has been unable to assert his authority over so wide an area and His Majesty’s Government have been obliged to recognise that at the utmost he has not asserted it further west or south than the so-called Riyadh line offered to Ibn Saud in 1935. The Power to whan the Sheikh has lost what may be called his/his reversionary rights to the area between the Blue line and the Riyadh line is unquestionably Ibn Saud, and he has lost them, not through any sudden act of conquest or intrusion, but as the result of a gradual forward movement which had probably begun long before the Blue line came into being* 6. If it were possible to regard the Riyadh line as a natural frontier to the west and north of which the authority of the Sheikh was firmly established, there might be no need to apprehend a further Saudi advance* But it is nothing of the kind. Apart from the probability that Ibn Saud is already the over-lord of the Inhabitants of the area lying between it and the Khcr-el- Odeid, the recent enquiries into the possibility of providing landing grounds in the hinterland of the Trucial coast for use by aircraft engaged on survey work do not suggest that the control of any of the Trucial Sheikhs over the interior is really effective, while it is known that Saudi officials have been able in recent years to penetrate as far east as Baraimi* Sven, therefore if there is no imminent menace of Saudi or Wahabi expansion upon the Trucial coast itself, It equally does not appear that further expansion towards that coast would meet with any obstacle. 7* It is, in fact, the nature of this expansion which lies at the root of the problem. Ib-n Saud f s advance has proceeded quietly but inexorably* f° r no apv*ar*ent/JKmmmammmmmmammmmmmmmm A n o apparent reason except that there has been nothing to stop it. It i reasonable to suppose that for a ruler of Ibn Baud's prestige it is easy to persuade desert tribes who are not under the control of any recognised ruler to say that they owe allegiance to himself, and unless some effective chec&amp; to this natural and even inevitable process can be devised, it is likely to continue through the years until Ibn Baud’s • , authority extends to the very outskirts of the Trucial ports. There are only two ways, so far as Lord Halifax can see, of preventing this. The one is for His Majesty’s Government to lay down a frontier unilaterally and declare their intention of maintaining it by force of &amp;) arms. The other is to agree with Ibn Baud upon a frontier which he will formally and openly recognise, and which he and his successors will thereafter be unable to disregard v/ithout providing His Majesty’s Government with grounds for opposing them with a degree of vigour which could not be justified in the present anomalous situation, 80 There can be no question but that the second of these alternatives is much to be preferred, if it can be achieved. It cannot, however, be achieved without the cession to Ibn Baud of either the Jebel Naksh, which is impossible, or the Khor-el-Odeid, which is only possible with the acquiescence of the Sheikh of Abu Dhabi. The position of the Sheikh being what it is, he would have every reason to welcome the establishment of a settled frontier, more or less following the Riyadh line, in return for/U' for the surrender of a small area of empty desert adjacent to the Khor~el — Ooeid for which he can have little or no use, hut which may have great value for Ihn Saud, both sentimentally and as a possible corridor for an oil pipe-line to the Persian Gulf, 9o Whether the Sheikh can be persuaded to see his own interests in this light is, however, a separate problem, and on the assumption (which has yet to be proved) that he will refuse to do so, two main ways of compensating him still further for the loss of some of his territory have been considered. The first of these is a money payment and the second is an assurance of supoort in the event of a serious attack from the landward side, 10* Lord Halifax shares to the full the distaste which has been expressed for a money payment, because it clearly imports a questionable element into a settlement which can be justified on its own merits and which the Sheikh of Abu Dhabi ought to accept in his own interests, i Nevertheless, if a money payment would secure the Sheikh’s acquiescence in a frontier settlement, His Majesty’s Government ought not, in His Lordship’s opinion, to hesitate to pay any reasonable sum which might be necessary. He notes that it is impossible for the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf to hazard a guess as to the sum which the Sheikh would regard as adequate compensation, but looking at the question from another angle - that is to say, from the point of view of the value of a settlement to His Majesty’s/jsm anBBSBnBnnm l Majesty's Government - he considers that £25,000 or even a larger sum would not he too much 8 11c The alternative, or additional, fom of compensation is an undertaking to protect the Sheikh in the event of a land attack from Saudi Arabia. Lord Halifax notes that in the opinion of the Political Resident the first question which the Sheikh would be likely to ask if approached regarding the Khor-el-Odeid would be: ’’Will His Majesty's Government guarantee this — '■ n ■ l '“' 'frontier as against Saudi Arabia?' His Lordship considers that if it were necessary to secure the Sheikh's concurrence, an endeavour should be made to meet to some extent his wishes on this point. The precise wording of any assurance given to the Sheikh would need consider» ation. It would clearly be undesirable that His Majesty's Government should undertake any responsibility for intervening if some tribal elements on the Abu Dhabi side of the frontier chose to repudiate the Sheikh of Abu Dhabi and to declare allegiance to Ibn Saud; nor could His Majesty’s Government accept responsibility for the prevention of tribal raids from Saudi Arabian territory across the frontier. The undertakings to be assumed by His Majesty's Government should be so worded as to apply only in the event of major aggression against Abu Dhabi on the part of the territorial sovereign on the other side of the frontier. 12. Lord Halifax is aware that assurances of this kind may seem to constitute an extension of the responsibilities/! responsibilities of His Majesty's Government. He realises that in particular strong objection is seen in many quarters to increasing the commitments of His Majesty f s Government in the Persian Gulf by adding to the existing obligations to defend the Trucial Sheikhs from aggression by sea an obligation to defend any one of them from aggression by land, and that the view has been expressed that if His Majesty's Government were to undertake such an additional commitment it might necessitate an adjustment in the forces of His Majesty’s Government in the neighbourhood of the Gulf. His Lordship cannot help feeling, however, that these responsibilities already exist and the additional obligation would be more apparent than real. 13. In the first place, the fact that the air route s ,! , ^ along the Trucial coast is a vital sector in the communications of the Empire means that His Majesty’s Government could not in practice allow any Power not under their influence to occupy any part of the coast or its immediate vicinity which was of importance for the air routeo The only uncertainty is at what point His Majesty’s Government are to consider that their position on the Trucial coast would be threatened® At present they a:.u f?cs so far as their formal obligations to the Sheikhs are concerned, to allow the predominant Power in the adjacent parts of Arabia to extend its influence as far as the Trucia} ports themselves. It is doubtful, however, whether His Majesty’s Government could even now 7 remain inactive/inactive while the authority of one of the Trucial Sheikhs was irreparably undermined in this way, while in the event of a serious attack from Saudi Arabia His Majesty’s Government wou^d in practice find themselves obliged to intervene to prevent the Sheikh from being overwhelmed« 14# In the second place, if any oil company hereafter wishes as the result of a survey to undertake active operations in the interior, it will not be able to do so unless it knows that the site of these operations lies to the north and east of a settled frontier* and once such operations had begun His Majesty Government would inevitably be obliged to interest themselves in the maintenance of that frontier- 15. Nevertheless, Lord Halifax is prepared to agree that every effort should be made to avoid the additional commitment involved in a definite guarantee pf any landward frontier which might eventually be fixed for the Sheikhdom of Abu Dhabi as the outcome of the present discussion and that the support of His Majesty’s Government should be limited to a promise to intervene energetically with Ibn Saud or his successors in the event of their disregarding the new frontier* 16. In the circumstances set forth above, Lord Halifax considers that His Majesty’s Government should endeavour to grasp an opportunity which may not recur of settling this most difficult of frontier questions and should to that end try to persuade the Sheikh of Abu Dhabi to part with the relatively small area necessary/rawiiiiimwi—HflM necessary to give Ibn Saud access to the Khor~el-(Ddel&lt;3 if possible in return for a settled frontier, hut if necessary with the added inducements of a promise of general good offices in matters relating to that frontier and a money payment. But the question still remains of what attitude His Majesty’s Government should adopt if all these inducements fail in their object. Lord Halifax would not for a moment dispute the view that it would be wrong to bring pressure to bear upon any Trucial Sheikh to act to his own disadvantage, merely in order to further the interests of His Majesty’s Government, But in this case the action proposed is manifestly not to the Sheikh’s disadvantage^ Moreover His Majesty’s Government are surely entitled to take into account the fact that without their protection not one of the Trucial Sheikhs could last for a day against Ibn Saud and to expect from these Sheikhs a greater degree of co-operation in matters affecting the interests of His Majesty's Government than many of them have seemed disposed to show in recent years* 17. This being so, Lord Halifax feels that in the event of the Sheikh of Abu Dhabi proving obdurate he should be informed that this is a case in which His Majesty’s Government must insist, in the interests of his people and successors, on his following their advice, in return for which they will promise to take up on his behalf all matters affecting his landward frontiers and (at/19./ J {at the dtseration of the Political Resident) a money payment, v-hich might be disguised as compensation for the loss of imaginary dues or revenues from the ceded territory. 18. The question of the effect which such an att itude might have upon the prestige of His Majesty’s Government in the Persian Gulf is one upon which Lord Halifax naturally expresses an opinion with diffidence. But he suggests that provided no injustice is done a show of firmnesE in such a situation ought not to diminish the prestige of His Majesty’s Government, but rather to enhance it. It may be argued that this might be so, but for the fact that to the Trucial Sheikhs it would appear that His Majesty’s Government were being firm with one of themselves because they dared not be firm with Ibn Saud. Lord Halifax recognises the force of this argument, but he sees no reason why the advantages to the Sheikhs of a settled frontier should not be understood locally. It might indeed be represented to the Sheikh of Abu Dhabi that Ibn Saud is the friend of the British and has throughout his career (unlike certain lesser Arab rulers of no importance who are ignorant of world affairs) shown himself consistently well-disposed to His Majesty’s Government and anxious in all circumstances to consult their interests; so that His Majesty’s Government, for their part, have no hesitation in asking the Sheikh to contribute his share towards an agreement which is considered to be advantageous to all parties.mam There remains to be considered the opinion expressed by the Government of India that there are political objections to making a breach in the line of territory under British control at present stretching along the coast of the Persian Gulf from Qatar to Muscat or to admit further Saudi access to the Gulf* The Service Departments are understood to be satisfied that there are no strategical disadvantages to be apprehended from Saudi access to the Khor-el-Odeid, and it seems clear that such access will not give Ibn Saud any greater opportunities for expanding his influence upon the Trucial Coast than he already possesses at the present time* On the contrary, a settled frontier between his territories and those of the Trucial Sheikhs would set definite limits to such expansion. Lord Halifax finds it difficult in these circumstances to form a clear idea of the nature of the political objections, and in any case these objections do not in his opinion outweigh the wider political advantages of securing a frontier settlement with Ibn Saud* 26* Copies of this letter are being sent to the departments represented on the Middle Eastern Sub committee of the Committee of Imperial Defence and to the Petroleum Department I am. Sir, Your obedient Servant, qg&amp;yfcAOV BAGSAOJWForwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy has been sent to by Mail.INDIA OFFICE, !!&gt; 4429/38, WHITEHALL, S.W. 1. 7th July, 1933. A Dear Mr.Longrigg, Will you kindly refer to your letter of the 24th June, PC.28/85, relative to the south-eastern boundaries of Saudi Arabia. As you are aware. His Majesty’s Government have taken steps to restrain the California Arabian Standard Oil Company from operating in territory south of Qatar lying east of the line which His Majesty’s Government have most recently proposed to recognise as the boundary of Saudi Arabia. As a necessary consequence they are obliged, pending a settlement of the disputed frontier, to refuse assent to the extension of operations by any Company from areas under their influence beyond the frontier line claimed by Ibn Saud. This of course has no reference to the territory covered by the Qatar Oil concession. Ibn Baud’s line has been approximately marked in red on your map, which I now return, while the line which His Majesty’s Government have most recently been prepared to recognise is marked in black. I am to ask that the information supplied herewith may be treated as confidential by your Directors. / Yours sincerely, Sgd. J.P. GIBSON. Longrigg, Esq. , Petroleum Development (Trucial Coast), Ltd., City-Gate House, Finsbury Square, E.C.2.f I'l V =429/1938. PSTROLSUM DBYELOPMERl ( TRUCIAL COAST) LIMITED. .28/85. CITY-GATE HOUSE, PIU3BTJRY SQUARE, LONDON, 1.0.2. 24th June, 1938 Dear Mr. Gibson, I -write in confirmation of our conversation in your office this morning. It is our understanding that Ibn Saud refuses to accept the 1913/14 'Blue Line 11 as being the south-eastern frontier of his dominions, and that he has refused to accept a number of alternative lines suggested by H.M.G. at various times. Although, however, no frontier has been ye fc agreed and Ibn Saud still claims territory east of the most easterly line so far suggested by H.M.G., nevertheless (as ue understand) H.M.G. have requested Ibn Saud to restrain tna standard Oil Company of California from carrying out prospecting east of E.M.G.'s last proposed line, and have also . requested the California Company itself in the same sense. You were kind enough to indicate to me on the map this line, which is Ii.M.G . 1 s latest offer end California’s interim prospecting frontier. As this line presumably represents, in the judgment of H.M.G., the limits of Ibn Saud’s justifiable claims to territory, it is assumed that all territory eastward thereof may be taken as lying neither within his dominions, nor (as an obvious consequence) within the California Concession of 1933 I write now to ask you very kindly to confirm this view, with ^its ■Gioson, Esq., India Office, T/h i t eh all, S . U. 1.i u 3 corollary Hi at- P.C.L. may carry out c;.l..t territory east oi that line, subjec necessary rights from the Rulers. It - prospecting over t to having obtained would be greatly appreciated if the line westward to which we may work could be indicated upon the attached map, which is sent you for thi? purpose, and there is any question of other lines, the observance of which should govern the Company s operations, if these also might be inserted, you too much trouble, but feel it I hope this will not give is essential for a clear understanding of the position. Anything which 37-011 tell us on the subject shall be kept, if you so desire, for the confidential information of our Directors. fours &amp;c., (Sd) Stephen II.LongriggIndia Office; Whitehall 3 S.W.l. .4621/38 22nd July, 1938 South Eastern Boundaries of Saudi Arabia. S telegram of the 8th March? No. 440? and connected correspondence on the subject of the South Eastern boundaries refer to the letter from the Foreign Office No.E.2579/150/91 of the 1st July? of which a copy was sent to you by the mail of the 6th July? and to request that he may be furnished as early as possible with the observations of the Government of India thereon. Resident in the Persian Gulf and to the Political Agent? Bahrein. of Saudi Arabia I am directed by the Secretary of State A copy of this letter is being sent to the Political I am? Sir? Your obedient Servant \ o PEEL; Secretary to the Government of India? External Affairs Department? Simla.jtmm CONFIDENTIAL . No. 464-3 The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to The Political .Agent, Af British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. A' 1 ' Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Jedda despatch (1466/ 546/56) of 4th July 1938 to the Foreign Office, with enclosures. Subject. Delimitation of south-eastern frontier of Saudi-Arabia. I:. -VBritish Legat i on, TTo.lS? (1466/546/56) Jedda. July 4th 1938. 1Z) My Lord, I have the honour to transra^herewith in translation a note from the Saudi Government, dated June 26th about the eastern frontier. It is a reply to the note, a copy A A% of which was sent/to the foreign Office with my printed despatch 110.72 (804/546/49) dated April 14th in which the right of His Majesty’s Government to keep the America^ oil company concerned informed of the frontier situation was reiterated, and it deals also in principle with the question of prospecting for oil in the disputed zone. It will be seen that the Saudi Government do no more than repeat their offer to refrain from prospecting in the disputed zone until a frontier agreement is arrived at provided that His Majes ty’s Government will ensure that a similar policy of absten tion is observed from the }atar side. 2. In my telegram No.56 dated March 7th I reported Fuad Bey’s ’’personal” opinion as to the sort of solution that might be acceptable to his Government. Fuad Bey went to 3yria on leave soon after that, and had I been in a position to give him my views on his opinion, the reply was to be sent to him there. It is possible that the Saudi Arabian Government have been waiting for such a reply, but their reference to Fuad Bey may have resulted from their consciousness that he is the only person in their employ who thoroughly understands the bilingual correspondence on this subject and can be trusted to write a clear reply. 3 / The Right Honourable the Viscount Halifax, K.G., etc. etc. etc.3 The deadlock is still Complete The only hopeful feature in the situation is that the California Arabian standard Oil Company are more and more inclined to believe that the oil field in Hasa is extremely rich. If this belief is well-founded Ibn 3aud *3 bitterness on the frontier question in so far as it has an economic basis, should diminish with time, though an increase in his income will not make him less touchy on the point of prestige. 4. On looking through the file I see that owing to a regrettable oversight the Saudi note which I summarised A.'bi' briefly in my telegram lie February 23rd w a s never sent to you. A translation is enclosed. I expect to proceed to England on leave in a few days, and this question can perhaps be considered once more while I am at home, though I have no useful suggestions to make. All we can do, it seems, is to revert to our proposal for a preliminary examination of the area in dispute, which is little more than a device by which we hope to convince the Saudi authorities that Jabal Nakhsh is an integral part of the small Jabal Dukhan range. If the invitation which I have received holds good and I spend a few weeks at Ibn 3aud f s camp in Hejd next spring, it might perhaps be possible to organise a visit to the Q,atar boundary for this purpose. b. I am sending copies of this despatch with copies of enclosures to the Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf at Bushire (Ho.1467/546/56) and the Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Department at Simla (Ho.1468/546/56J. I have the honour to be, with the highest respect, My Lord, Your Lordhhip’s most obedient, humble servant, 3d. R.7. BULLARDEnclosure to Jedda despatch Mo.13? (1466/546/06) dated 3.7.38 Ministry of Foreign Taif. June 26th. 1938. Affa irs, rx CA A His Excellency Sir Reader Bullard, \ 1 I regret the delay in .replying to your note Mo. /5(803/546/49) dated April ^4th 1938 due to the necessity of enquiring from the Deputy Minister for the Ministry of Foreign Affairs as to certain information which he has concerning the matter in question, while he, as you are aware, is on sick 1. , leave. Your Excellency’s note under reference has teen studied, and I am able to explain to Your Excellency the opinion of the Government of the Saudi Arabian Kingdom thereon. 1. The Government of the Saudi Arabian Kingdom have already informed the British Government of their non-recognition of the Blue line, and that they did not consider its existence as a proper reason for the surrender of territories and places which are under their control, and in their possession from ancient and in recent times. 2. Our Government do not recognise the validity of any orders which any Government may give to individuals or companies in their country. It is the right of our Govern ment and no one else to give such information. 3. His Majesty the King always desires - it is his habit - not to create any difficulty for his neighbours, and particularly for the British Government. He therefore hopes that the frontier question may be settled at their earliest convenience. 4* With a view to the obviation of disputes at the present time until after the conclusion of a definite agree ment with j)atar in respect of the delimitation of the frontiers, he is prepared to give special orders to the California Arab ian otandard Oil Company to the effect that they must not cross the Maximum limit of the frontiers aa proposed by the British Government, provided that , * l-U. .. Qatar undertakes to prevent n\£Oil Company in their territory from crossing the maximum limit as requested by our Government, until after the con clusion of a definite agreement in respect of the frontiers. If the British Government agree to this (solution) our Government is prepared to accept it. With highest respects, 3d. FEY CAL M ini s t er f or Por e ign Aff a ir s.No. 2/3/3 2 Mini 9 try for Foreign Mecca. February 16th 1933• Q A*\ Your Ejccellency, / v - I have received Your Excellency’s letter No.22(266/545 /24) dated 3rd February, regarding the south-eastern frontiers. The Government of His Majesty desire nothing better than to be in agreement with the British Government on every subject of common interest andt o have a complete understanding on all matters. They have already exerted and are still exerting their endeavours, as the British Government are aware, to settle every question in a manner satisfactory to both parties and calculated to secure their common interests. One of the points on which they have spent their efforts in order to bring the two parties nearer to each other is the settlement of the question of the south-eastern frontiers between Saudi Arabia and the Arab amirates on the Persian Gulf in a manner satis factory to all and calculated t o secure the lawful interest of both parties. You state that your Government have shown a spirit of great conciliation in the matter of the frontier to which my Government hold whereas the position to which my Government hold has remained unchanged. It is true that that is the apparent position, but if you will examine the spirit of conciliation actually shown by my Government it will prove to you that they nave gone very far indeed towards meeting the wishes of their friends the British Government. v/hen the question of this frontier was first raised in London and Jedda the position of my Government was clear, viz. that what they 4 hold to is all the territories which belonged to the fathers and grandfathers of His Majesty the King; and these of course include much wider areas than the frontier to which their claims were subsequently limited. As you are aware, the tr, ^ . Agreement/ nia excellency His Majesty’s Minister, Jedda.m Agreement of 1915 plainly recognises as belonging to His Majesty the King what belonged to his fathers and grand fathers. A satisfactory adhesion to the text of that Agree ment would make a large part of the Hadhramaut, Dhufar, Oman, Abu Dhabi and ^atar fall within the territories of His Majesty the King, and historical examination (of the facts) shows that the posts at Abr Bairami and DMfar and in the middle of }atran were Saudi posts founded by the forefathers of His Majesty the king in the last century. Nevertheless His Majesty the King, (was) desirous that there should be agreement and understanding with the British G-overnment, and that his friends among the Arab rulers on the Persian Gulf should not be deprived even though that should involve himself in material loss. All this caused him, after strong insistance, to limit his claims to the minimum, hoping (thereby) to put a decisive end to the difficulties. It never entered into His Majesty’s thoughts that what he mentioned would be a subject of argument and dispute. The line to which my Government holds represents the minimum of their legitimate and reasonable claim; consequently Your Excellency’s statement that the conciliation and concession have come from the British Government while the position of my Government has not changed indicates disdain for the Govern ment of Hi s Majesty and forget^fulness of the great sacrifices which they have made in renouncing in favour of the rulers of those neighbouring Arab territories wide areas whose ownership by His Majesty can be proved by every historical and actual right. It never entered into the thoughts of my Government to bargain about the frontier which they ^ut forward, for it was drawn after deep reflection and careful consideration? and it was on account of the insistence of the British Government that it was drawn so as to cover the very minimum of the just claims. Had my Government thought that it would be the subject of/fftbj V of discussion and bargaining, they would have taken up a different position, whereas they limited their claims to the minimum hoping that the British Government would not argue about it but would accept it as a just and practical frontier in the interests of both parties. I do not conceal from Your Excellency that my Government attaches the greatest im portance to this frontier and regards it as a very vital matter. Nay, more: I can say that this question is a question of life -a and death in connection with that part of His Majesty*s domin ions. They therefore regret exceedingly that the British Government do not appreciate their position at its true value; at the same time however they express their readiness to discuss any practical proposal which will secure the interests of both parties and obviate harm. As to the abstention by employees of the companies on both sides from encroaching on the disputed areas, theGf Deputy Foreign Minister, in his personal letter No.2/3/29 of 2/12/1356 (February 3rd 1938) explained the essence of the position to Your Excellency as my Government understood it, and in it he explained exactly how the matter stood. I hope that there may be sufficient explanation therein to help to clear up the present misunderstanding and to bring about a fundamental solution of the difficulties. As to the question of the appointment of a topograph ical commission, His Majesty’s Government, before giving a definite reply to the request, would like to enquire from your Government as to the areas required to be surveyed in order that the matter may be sufficiently clear to both sides and that the confusion which might result if the agreement were general and not precise may be avoided. I await therefore the opinion of your Government on the three points set forth above. 3d. Feysal.CONFIDENTIAL, No. C/4yO. ,3V The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to Tne Political Agent, Banrain, /• Y' f'' W and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents £e). Office of tne Political Resident in tne Persian Gulf, at Banrain. Dated.. Name and Date. Subject. Unofficial Note dated Saudi Frontier, tne 1st August 1938 by Sir Trenciiard Fowle, regarding Khor-el-Odeid.Kfrar-el-udeid, A See foreign Office ie tter 2579/lo0/91 f dated let July 1938 to India Office. !• ‘Ike steps to be taicen appear to be as follows. Jrirst His Majesty's Government will nave to decide wAetner to adopt generally jroreign Office*s prpposal or not. naving done tnis then before approacning tne snaiioi they snouid get from ibn i&gt;a*ud a definite statement in writing tnat snouid it be possible for them to persuade tne dhaiich to surrender hhor-el-udeid ne will definitely agree to tne proposed frontier. i'he only guarantee we nave at present tnat ibn Ha’ud would agree to a frontieriif ne received Ahor-el-Odeid is Fuad Hamza*s personal opinion given in Jeddan telegram Ho. 86 to Foreign Office 2. fhe Foreign Office (paragrapn 7 of tneir letter) envisage tne danger of Ibn Sa’^Od absorbing most or all ol the frucial Coast hinterland M up to tne very outskirts of the irucial ports** and tnerefore a fixed frontier would be to our advantage as well as tnat of tne ahaiFn of Abu Dhabi and generally tne anaiJcns of tne irucial Coast. This is true in itself but almost entirely on account ol oil possibilities in tnat area. If we were sure tnat tnere was no oil tnere* tnen ibn oa'ud's penetration to places liice Haraimi mignt be a nuisance but certainly would not nave tne importance it does at present provided he was Feptat a reasonable distance frox^/from tne coast# 3# But for tne lrentier to De of any use to us it seems to me tnat it must definitely Oe guaranteed in tne same way tnat tne Kuwait-Saudi or ^atar-Saudi boundaries are guaranteed# That is to say fcna* tne Shaikhs of botn tnese territories nave been guaranteed by His Majesty^ Government protection from agression across tneir frontiers# i'his howeeer tne foreign Office are not prepared to give witnout qualification. It is true tnat tney are willing to give tne same sort of guarantee to nbu iinabi as His Majesty^s Government nave given to Kuwait and qatar ^vide last sentence of tneir paragrapn 11}* but earlier in tHe sams paragraph tney say tnat 'it would clearly be undesirable tnat His Majesty^ Government snould undertaKe any responsibility ior intervening if some tribal elements on tne Kbu Dnabi side of tne frontier cnose to repudiate tne onaiicn of Abu Dnabi and to declare allegiance to ibn Sa^ud'. This is exactly tne sort of tactics tnat ba*ud would adopt for 'peaceful penetration' of tne frucial Coast Hinterland and it would ooxeaaxxy have to be made clear to ±bn £&gt;a r ud tnat any snifting of tribal allegiance would in nolw ay l give tne Haudi government any rignt wnatever beyond tne frontier fixed. 4o fne^ Foreign Office argue (tneir paragrapna 12 and 15) (a) tnat since in any case we have to guard the air route along tne Trueial Coast tne guarantee of Saudi tne Abu Dhabi/frontier would Hardly be an additional commitment# Jrurtner (b) tnat if oil is found (tneir Paragrapn 14) in tnebljaterlaud nis majesty*8 Governmentwould inevitably ce obliged to interest tneiuselves in t iie maintenance oi tnat frontier, witn regard to (a), f*or tne security of tnis route we would only nave to Keep Ibn Sa^ttd at a certain distance from the Coast but not necessarily from penetrating the ninterland at a considerable distance from it. Witn regard to (b) tnis argument certainly applies aQj£$r if oil is found* but not otnerwise. b* Tne Foreign Office suggest (paragrapn 10 of t neir letter) tnat tne sum of £ 25*000/-, or even more, mignt be paid to tne onaiKh of Abu Dnabi for the surrender of *.nor-el-Odeid. In paragrapn 5 of my telegram ho.T/48, dated 2otn February 193b, I gave my view tnat it was impossible to compete wnat sum tne bnaihn would be lively to accept* and wnetner £ 20*000/- is adequate or not I really cannot say. In paragraph 5 of tne same telegram 1 gave my vlews as to tne objections to our buying nnor-el-^deia from nim and 1 need not repeat tnese. 1 also gave some furtner views in my note of 16tn April 193b to Mr. (ribs on. 0. In paragrapn 17 of tneir letter tne Foreign Office suggest tnat in case tne bnaiicn of Abu Dnabi proves obdurate in rei using to sell nis territory his Majesty^ Oovernment must insist on his following tneir advice. l‘ne Foreign Office grounds for tnis proposed action are tnat wnile *it would be wrong to bring pressure to bear on any Fruci&amp;l snaiKn to actBy Air Mail. ’■Z- SJJtj 3/ f: INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, 19 AUG issa V-AA'' A Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy has been sent to by Mail. The Foreign Secretary, Government of India. - The Political Resident in th^-Fersian Grille - 4963 2000 7.36GOVERNMENT OP INDIA. Confidential. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL) Department. tf.B.— This is an ORIGINAL message sent by AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department ] Q/637 of 1938, 'Dated Simla Office of tne political Heal dent in tne Persian Oulf. the Camp, Kar&amp;oni* 1* lotn Septeiaber, 38* i rnm u* xxxxxx 0 X roe • The Officiating Political Reeident in the Persian Oulf f o - Hie Majesty*e Secretary of t&gt;tate for India, London • epeated Secretary to the Gorernaent of India, Reference y £ r - eternal Affair* Japartaant, /&gt;' xxxxx^cxxiix iiirala* . ^ Political Agent, Bahrain, with a copy of OoTemment of Reference correspondence reeting with Government of India otter fto#?«46-B/38, dated the 30th August 1938, on the above ubject* • I have not hitherto submitted my views since sir Trencnard owls intended to etate hie opinion verbally in London. In view f the last paragraph of tne Government of India letter, however, should perhaps submit that my views coincide in all respects ith those expressed by the Government of India. • I need only add two remarkss ^tftite apart from tne objections tated by the Government of India to the purchase of Knor-el-udeid *nd these are, I believe, sufficient to exclude tne proposal for urtnsr consideration), I do not hesitate to say that tne sndL jen of bu Dhabi would not, and - if he w^ed^ to survive - could not sell India letter i*o # y.46-ii/3a, dated tne 30th August 1938. 3ub. set i South Eastern boundaries of Saudi n Arabia. for / S. 44. ( Designation)dimwiTO—wiw for &amp; 25,000 or any comparable Bum. tn« furtiaar imucesaent of a settled frontier is bo qualified an to render it totally valueless to any Crucial Goaat nnaiicni tne nature of tiie / r . I' guarantee suggested in the foreign Office letter «o,G.2579/ 150/91, dated the let July 1938, allows in so many words for Saudi expansion beyond any selected frontier by precisely those tactics of * peaceful penetration** which Bin send has m adopted in the past and would continue to use in tn© future* sd* K* Jeightmatu ^ficlating relit leal Keside^t in tne Persian Gulf* Attested * for Secretary to the yolitie&amp;l F&lt;esident in the Persian Gulf.No. P. 46-H/38. a From To The Secretary to the Govern lent of Inhla in ttio external if fairs Department* The Under Secretary of State for India» India Officep £ Dated Simla t the 3^. lugoat 1936. South Eastern boundaries of iaudi Arabia. m-mummuI'W Mn mmmm mm tmnm iwwto 9 y I tm directed to ackiiow^d :© your letter Ho. P.S. 4621/38 of tii© 22nd July 1^38, on the above mentioned subject, in which you ask to bo furnished with the observa tions of the Government of India upon Foreign Office letter Mo. E# 2579/150/91 of Ui# 1st July 1938 addressed to tlie India Office. t «ot 2, The CrO^ermant of India fully appreciate the inportanoe of aocurinti, if poaaible, I bn baud's benevolent neutrality towarda Hi* .‘iajeaty'a 'loverarent’a policy in alestine and of removing any other grievance wnioh he may have % .ainat Ida 'ajesty's (Jovernment. They Jtave acooruingly re-exafainod ta.e letter in the li c ht of the fx^iajunta put forward by the -raijii Office and have c ;iven those &lt;tr, ,u- -juts all possible weight in considering ahsther they are justified in modify ing the viewa ex;ireaseu in their telegram No. 440 of 8th v .^rch 1958. A* the result of that ro-exa i/rvti *n t.«y have regretfully concluded that ti»ey oust adiierAto the position which they then adopted and isuit at;ain exoree* their un- compromieift opposition to the propoeal/nade by the Foreign Office. If f / 3. —-- 2 - 5, Tiiu 3rea»ons for &amp;iia conclusion my be suaxnnrised as follows { (a) The For@%a Office uiomelirm ad^dt that, even if I bn ;&gt;aud ware imucou by the cession of Khor-el- Kieid to aciree to a settled frontier vis-a-vxs the Truoial j&gt;Ui.Uw $ ine affect would aia'tliy be ^ermnent so far as Ii»i ;laud 9 e attitude to- wards tiie Palestine question is ooncarned* The QoTernment of India would further and state idat in tiieir opinion no gesture of fruandahip on the part of His ajaaty 1 * Government avail to prevent Ibn ^md mu Me suojocts from actively assisting tlieir coreligionists in ITile.aine, unless some ap easement of tific situation there can be taoured Mfore long by His llajeety 1 * Goverasent* Ibn baud’s present disposition id, s»o far as tlie Government of Inuia understand it, to avoid my zrietion with ureat Britain ana, if m does eventually uacide to add to His majesty’s UoVermont’s difficulties in Palestine, it will not be on account of chagrin at failure to obtain the iaetern and Southern Frontiers, which he desires, but because he is compelled to this aoiu*se by pressure from Uie Moslem world in general, whieh ize is not able to resist. The cession of Khor-el-Qdeid will not therefore, in the opinion of the Government of India have any material effect upon Ibn .laud’s behaviour with reamed to Palestine either in the imnouiate or the remote future. Theyhold this opinion the **iore strongly because they do not consider that Ibn Saud would be grateful or ^rould regard himself aa under any obligation to Ms Majesty’s CJovemasnt by reason of their allowing him to take territory which he regards as Ms by ngiit and not by favour f (b) The Government of India are by no means satisfied tmt the ojession of Khor-el-;Xieid woiild in result in tiie sstablisir^ent of a fixed and agreed frontier between laudi Arabia and the territories of the Sheikh of Abu Dhabi* ,ven —British prestige in the n nlf and in the iliddle :^st f since it would l)e regarded by all our dependents there as a surrender to I bn Uaud , s e^reeeion at tlie expense of one for whose interests m are responsible. The second n»thod ’r?ould in the opinion of the Hkwernnent of India create a •*oat unfortunate precedent, since it would be known to everyone in the Gulf that the Iheikh of Abu Dhabi had been paid a lar^e for ulo coraplrisanoe and it would be impossible in future for Kit* •Majesty 1 a Government to obtain be impossible to rrranpe the bargain, vhacii tiae Foreign faul that the bargain if concluded would not secure either a settled Frontier for the Trucial Bheikhs gainst Ibn ba«xi , 8 encroacteent or any alteration in Ibn ;aud 9 8 attitude towards eventB in Palestine. They therefore feel botind to reconnend that the proposal should be dropped. 6. A copy of this letter is bein^ sent to the ; olitiorJL (eaident in the Persian Gulf, from whom no oommntu on your letter Ho. P.Z. 4621/30, dated the 22nd July 1938, have dir. Your moot obedient servant 3d. II. .1.P. I etcalfe, Secret irv to the Government of India.By Air Mail. fiiO, P.z. bu-Hj 19 iQ INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, . 10.33, Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. fa- / /^/o. A copy has been sent to by Mail.(3 11/38. INDIA OF?ICI, ’WHITEHALL, 3. V. 1 . 7th October; 133Q- . fsl? Sir I am directed by the Secretary of State for ^ndia to Ti 11 t; r . Tj n. '-I refer to Mr. Baggallay’s letter of tne 1st Jaly? 110.11.2579/ 150/91? regarding the possibility of arranging bne cession to Ibn Sand of territory adjoining the Khor al Odeid, and to forward, for the information of the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, a copy of a letter dated the OOtl^^' ao August from the (government of India, and of a letter dated . ..... the 10tii September from the Officiating Resident m tue Persian Gulf? containing their latest views upon this matter* Lord Zetland? having carefully reconsidered the proposal in the light of the arguments advanced in the letter quoted above, finds himself in general agreement with the criticisms of the Government of India and especially with what is stated in paragraph 3(c) of this letter. He is impressed by the difficulty that the proposal could not be carried out without serious rish 01 damage, now ana hereafter, to the strength of the position of His Majesty’s Government in the Persian Gulf. There is a or example the danger that such a transaction mighc seriously injure their prestige by inviting doubts as to their aoility bo j^ouect the interests of the Sheikhs or by impairing their reputation for scrupulous ooservance of their declarations* Moreover, even if His Majesty’s Government were willing to incur these risks, the probability that tne proposed coooion of territory would materially influence Xbn Laud o attitude in the matter of Palestine is acknowledged to be remote and it/ Under Secretary of State, Foreign Office, S. ¥. 1 .A 1. o 2. it is not even certain that it would secure a settled frontier with the Trucial Sheikhdoms. The chance that such a cession would have any weight in determining Ihn Sand's policy in the event of a major emergency seems, also to he very small, while on the other hand the damaging effect of the cession on His Majesty's Government's prestige in the Persian Gulf would he felt all the more severely in the event of such an emergency. Lord Zetland hopes, therefore, that on further consideration Lord Halifax will agree that the proposal need not he pursued. Copies of this letter and enclosures are being sent to the Admiralty, far Office, Air Ministry, Colonial Office and Petroleum Department. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, (Sgd.) R./6 CONFIDENTIAL. No. 724-S of-1938. The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to 1* R.T.Peel 158quire, MC. , The India Office, London. j # 2. H. Veightraan Require, 103., Political Agent, Bahrain, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documentx^3§. 16th December 1938. British Consulate-Genera), BUSHIRE. Dated Reference to previous correspondence: ■ v Description of Enclosure, Name and Date. D.O. Letter No.723-3 of 16th December 1938 to the Secretary to the government of India, External fairs Department, New Delhi. Possible cession to Ibn Saud of territory adjoining Khor al Odeid.lann (Untied. »i ixvimi 3 the Heside^HS^ » BttBhire* thu 16th 'mceraber, 1938 # /l- ^ - 4.°' A' N s tv \r V Could pl«a«e refer to Indie Office Printed letter i.64U/3S f det«d the 29ih isovetafeer 195a t afith enclosure f on the subject of the yoeeible cession to I bn ttmuA of territory adjoining ^Itor al Meld. 0 g. I Jiad gone on ehort leave to In land beforr the Ooverraxaent of India letter dated the 50th %aguat 1954, lio* ?• 46-M/3Q, was received here, but ftightman In his letter Mo.0/657, dated the loth Beptedber 1954, expreeeed his vie^ thereon. I entirely concur with tne view of the India Office and with those of the Government of India and -ieight- man. (In this connection see also m views as expressed in my telegrams ^o.f/48, 'd^ted the Shth February 1954). In addition to the arguments already put forward, there is I thins the important fact that I bn dauu will soon have a flourishing oil field in ttasa and a port at Has Tana rah. there 1® all the more reason tnerefore to supper,c that the Khor al Ode id gift of the very doubtful port of have little or no effect on ifen Saudis attitude either towards Mu Majesty 1 s Government in general, or towards the settlement of the desired frontier in particular. # I am sending copies of this letter to f^el and /eightman. Yours sincerely, ad. T.C.Fowle. 'ubrey .Metcalfe, KOI I. ,031. ,HV )*, secretary to the Government of Xnaiu, eternal iff Hire department, Mew Delhi. « sent under Printed letter ^o.724-B of 16th ‘December 1953.Confidential 0 D.O, No. C/785-1.a/38 Dated the 20th December 1938. 3ub.1 ect s - Khor al Odeid I do not appear to have received a copy of the India Office Printed Letter No. P.7,. 6411/38, dated the 29th November 1938, referred to in Sir Trenchard’s demi- official letter to Sir Aubrey Metcalfe, Ho. 723-3 dated the 16th December 1938. C/ SO 2. If there is no objection, I should be grateful if you would send me a copy. Yours sincerely, t ain A.C. Galloway, ^ Secretary to the Honourable the Political Pesident in the Persian Gulf, BUSH! H 3 .By Aiy Mail. P.Z. 7540 103 ? ?r( a INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, 2f )L / ! ) l Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy has been sent to by Mail. - J SeaI M DISTRIBUTION. Decjrpher. Sir R. Bullard (Jedda), 25th November, 1958. D. 9.50 a.m. 25th November, 1958. “i R. 11.00 a.mo 25th November, 1958. Noc 175. IMPORT AN'll f Deputy Minister ior Noreign Affairs asked me, obviously on instructions, whether His Majesty's Government had taken a decision on his 'personal suggestion' about eastern frontier. I could only say it was still under consideration. eNCU.OSURE IN f^RMON OFFIOt^g CP»SltlNO LETTER i&gt;AT8DCONFIDENTIAL. The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to Aie Toll tical .tfahrain. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents (s). British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated...1938 Reference to previous correspondence Bahrain letter -. 0 • T/785-1 • a/38 01 BOth -Jecember / 19 36. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. India Office letter Bo.T.Z. ; 6411/38 of 7th October to the ’orei^n Office (enclosure! Thor al Ode id to 1,0. Printed letter of B9th November 1938),I t Z.6411/38 3ir India Office Whitehall, J.,/.i 7th October 19 38 I am directed by the secretary of State for India to refer to Mr. Baggallay’s letter of the 1st July. lo.13.2579/150/91, regarding the possibility of arranging the cession to Ibn baud of territory adjoiiiing the Khor al Odeia, and to forward, for the information of the Secretary ol State lor foreign .-iffairs, a copy of a letter dated the 30th august from the Government of ini ia, and a (^g oi a letter dated the 10th September from the Officiating Ueside nt in the Persian Gulf, containing their latest views upon this matter. Lord Zetland, having carefully reconsidered the proposal in the light of the arguments advanced in the letter quoted above, finds himself in general agreement with the criticisms of the Government of India and especially with what is stated in paragraph 3^c) of this letter. He is impressed by the difficulty that the proposal could not be carried out 'without serious risk of damage, now and hereafter, to the strength of the position of His Majesty’s Government in the Persian Gulf. There is for example the danger that such a transaction might seriously injure their prestige by inviting doubts as to their ability to protect the interests of the Shaikhs or by impairing their reputation for scrupulous observance of their declarations. Moreover, even if His Majesty’s Government were willing to incur these risks, the probability that the proposed cession of territory would materially influence Ibn baud’s attitude in the matter of Palestine is acknowledged to be remote and i t/ secretary of atate, ei gn Office,it is not eveii certain that it would secure a settled frontier with the Irucial dhaikhdons* The chance that such a cession would have any weight in deterrning ibn daud's policy in the event of a major emergency seems also to be very small, while on the other hand the damaging effect of the cession on His Majesty's Govern ment’s prestige in the Persian Gulf would be felt all the more severely in the event of such an emergency. Lord Zetland hopes, therefore, that on furhter consid eration Lord Halifax will agree that the proposal need not be pursued. Copies of this letter and enclosures are being sent to the admiralty, war Office, .iir Ministry, Colonial Office and Petroleum department. I am, dir, Your obedient dervant, dd • H • P1SLConfidential The Residency, I).0.Ilo»5-3 Bushire, the 3rd January 1939. Your demi-official letter Ho.C/785-l.a/38 of the 20th .lecenber 1938 in #iich you said that you had not received a copy of India Office Printed Letter NQ.P # z. 6411 of 29th November 1938. We have typed out a copy and sent it to you under our Printed Letter No#789-3 of 31st December 1938, but since the India 0»i, ice Printed Letter in Question was marked as being sent to India and Bahrain as well as here, if you have not received a copy by now I am desired by Sir Trenchard to ask you to let the India Office kn ow. * A copy of this letter is being sent to Peel. . '/eight man, Esquire, I.C.3 Political Agent, Bahr a in. * * sent under P.L,No.6-S of 3/l/39.By Air Mail. p.z. i' 1 3^ INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, V\- I- Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political I Department, India Office. ! • 'Eht FnrcTgn Soorotary, ri nynrmneilt of Indm? The Political J^d'ilonri in the Perfjian Gulf. 3681; 5861/150/91 [mportant . 19th January, 1939. Sir, With reference to your letter No. P. 6411/38 of the 7th October, I am directed by Viscount Halifax to inform you that he has now considered the views of the Government of India regarding the possibility of ceding to Ibn Saud, in order thereby to secure an agreed frontier between the Trucial Sheikhdoms and Saudi Arabia, certain territory adjoining the Khor-el-Odeid which His Majesty 1 s Government have in the past recognised as belonging to the Sheikh of Abu Dhabi. 2. Lord Halifax regrets that the Government of India should have felt it necessary to maintain their opposition to the proposal put forward in the Foreign Office letter of the 1st July 1938, whereby it might have been possible to reach a final agreement with Ibn Saud in regard to this frontier question. The rejection of the' Foreign Office proposal by the Government of India would appear to render it impossible to take advantage of the 'personal suggestion' made a year ago by the deputy Saudi Arabian Minister for Foreign Affairs, that a compromise might be reached if His Majesty's Government were prepared to abandon to Ibn Saud whichever of the two areas, Jebel Nakhsh and Khor-el-Odeid, they considered the less important. If His Majesty’s Government and the Government of India now refuse to discuss a compromise solution on this basis, it is not at present /clear ' Under-Secretary of State India Office,clear how a settlement of the frontier can he reached. 3. I am to point out in this connexion that while the Government of India are undoubtedly correct when they assert that the cession of Khor-el-Odeid to Ibn Saud would not in any way alter Ibn Baud’s attitude towards events in Palestine, it was not mainly on these grounds that Lord/ • Halifax advocated a solution on the lines proposed in the Foreign Office letter of the 1st July last. A settlement of this difficult;# frontier question was considered to be desirable for two reasons. In the first place the Secretary of State considered, and still considers, his proposals to be desirable on their own merits, and in the interests fbf the Trucial Sheikhs. Secondly, Lord Halifax feels that a settlement of this question is most desirable from the point of view of British relations with Saudi Arabia. /•mo 4^ It would appear from paragraph 3 (bj of the Government of India’s letter, that they do not regard the establishment of a fixed and agreed frontier with Saudi Arabia as likely to be advantageous to the Trucial Sheikhs. They suggest that Ibn Saud would be unlikely to respect a frontier line agreed upon between himself and His Majesty’s Government.. They think that even if Ibn Saud were prepared to agree to a bargain regarding the frontier, it is most improbable that he would keep his side of it. The Government of India, moreover, observe that the policy of Ibn Saud /ini ’ [U in recent years has been to advance his influence and his rule gradually and almost imperceptibly towards the coast, in spite of protests by His Majesty’s Government* It is, however, precisely in order to arrest this process of encroachment that Lord Halifax considers it to be desirable to establish a fixed frontier between the Trucial Sheikhdoms and Saudi Arabia. It is the absence of a frontier that has enabled Ibn Saud to extend his influence gradually over territories and tribes owning no allegiance to any other ruler* Hitherto the only boundary line in existence has been one fixed by His Majesty's Government which he has not accepted. It is unfortunate, but not altogether unreasonable, that in the circumstances Ibn Saud should have considered himself to be under no obligation to respect such a frontier* The position would evidently, however, be different if a new boundary line were established as a result of a freely negotiated agreement, and in the opinion of Lord Halifax there is no reason to suppose that Ibn Saud would not keep his side of the bargain in such a settlement, especially if the frontier thus laid down were a real frontier, that is to say if it did not include in Abu Dhabi territory any areas over which the Sheikh of Abu Dhabi did not exercise real and effective control. Lord Zetland will no doubt agree that one of the main causes of the frontier difficulties which have arisen in this part of Arabia in recent years has been the fact that His Majesty's Government and the Government of India have in the past given undertakings to local rulers recognising them as the possessors of certain territories, when those rulers had in fact little hold over the territories in question, or have since lost such /influence:/V influence there as they formerly possessed. So far as is known, all the encroachments of Ihn Saud hitherto have been not upon Abu Dhabi territory but upon empty territory, or upon territory occupied by tribal chiefs owning no allegiance to any particular ruler. 5. If the frontier remains unsettled, this process of encroachments will no doubt continue. It is provable that Ibn Saud will extend his rule over further territories towards the Persian Gulf, at least until he encounters tribes and territory over which the Sheikhs of the Trucial Coast exercise genuine and effective control. If this proves to be the case, it may well be found that Ibn Saud will be able to extend his rule up to the shores of the Khor-el-Odeid. Lord Zetland will remember that Ibn Saud has already, in his conversations with Mr. Rendel and Sir Reader Bullard in March 1937, claimed that no one but himself could keep order at the Khor-el-Odeid, and that when crimes were committed there it was to him that people applied for redress. 6. It is impossible to predict the action which His Majesty’s Government and the Government of India would be able to take in the event of the occupation by Ibn Saud of the Khor-el-Odeid district, but it is clear that, having regard to the general position in the Middle East, and to the international situation, they might not feel able to do more than make a diplomatic protest to the Saudi Arabian Government. In that event, the ultimate result might be fer more damaging to the prestige of His Majesty’s Government and the Government of India in the Persian Gulf area than the settlement proposed by the Foreign Office last July. /V. ]V7. Lord Halifax feels, moreover, that the problem should also he considered with due regard to its important effect on British relations with Saudi Arabia. It would appear that, except for the question of Palestine, this frontier difficulty is regarded by Ibn Saud as the most serious difference now existing between himself and His Majesty r 's Government. It is clearly of the highest importance to retain Ibn Saud’s good will if we are to retain our position in the Middle East in the event of an international emergency. If His Majesty’s Government and the Government of India, whenever the question is raised, show that their only wish is to leavu the matter in abeyance for an indefinite period, while refusing to admit Ibn Saud’s claims to the Jebel Nakhsh and the Khor-el-Odeid, it will be difficult to prevent Ibn Saud from feeling some resentment regarding v/hat he will regard as the arbitrary manner in which his claims have been treated. Moreover, in an international emergency, it will be all the more easy for the enemies of this country to influence Ibn Saud by promising him full satisfaction of his territorial claims if he will abandon his traditional policy of friendship with His Majesty’s Government. 8. Sir Reader Bullard has reported that this frontier question was raised with him during his visit to Riyadh in November, and that he could only say that the matter was still under consideration. It will be necessary now to decide on the reply to be returned to the Saudi Arabian Government when the matter is again raised. Lord Halifax hopes that it may be found practicable to devise some /alternativef v alternative solution of this problem which may offer some chance of an ultimate agreement acceptable to both Governments, and that it will not be necessary merely to reject the Saudi Arabian Government’s suggestions without advancing any practical proposals for a settlement* I am to suggest that immediate consideration should be accorded to this question, and that it might be discussed orally at a very early date* 9* Copies of this letter are being sent to His Majesty's Minister at Jedda, and to all the Departments represented on the Middle East (Official) Sub-Committeo of the Committee of Imperial Defence* I am. Sir, Your obedient Servant,ja INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy has been sent to ^ Mail.FOHSIQIt omcs, S.fi.l. 2492/108/Uli ath April, 19J9. iear ^alton, At til© ena of our letter E 5B61/150/91 of the Istii January, we Bu^eated that the question of the South- Eastern frontiers of Saudi Arabia ruight be aiecuseed orally at a very early aate with the object of finding a way out of the jiakhdue into which this question seems to be uriffting as a result of tne inability of His kajesty’s Government to agree to the cession to Ion Saud of the territory adjoining the lUior-el-Oueia. £. It assist the discussion of this problem if I set down in the present letter some ideas which have occurred to us for a procedure whereby this question might be, if not finally solved, at any rate prevented from reaching a dea&amp;look* d. It seema to us tnat, when two parties have uone all they can to reach agreement upon a point in dispute between them, and can do no more because each side has reached a point aw which it finds all further concession to be entirely impossible, the proper ana perhaps the only way of composing the difference is for the two parties to resort to the arbitration or mediation of some thirdpurty. 4. if in the present case anyone can thirds of a better solution or a better procedure*, or if the Saudi Arabian Government snows itself to be disposed to let the matter rest, we shall be only too glad; but we ourselves see no other procedure and we do not thinir we can rely upon the Saudi Arabian Government letting the matter rest inaefinitely. 2he ambitions of the oil companies on either side, if nothing else, may be too strong lor them* „ 5j &gt;C#ft ! altou, Esq., C#B. K.C.. ' India Office.■■■■■■■■■■HI i\ n • “Q realise, however, Uiut the idea of arbitration is In the present ease beset by many difficulties, Mach may be summarised under the following heads* iaj 2h© scope of the arbitration; ib) The nature of the arbitration? Co; The choice of the arbitrator; and (u; - the moot important of all - The effect of the offer or acceptance of arbitration upon our relations with the Sheihh of Abu Dhabi• 6. as regards (a;, we should clearly want to keep the scope of any arbitration within as narrow limits as possible• we might for instance start off by suggesting to Ion laud that if he were willing to accept what we had already offered for the rest of the South-Eastern frontier, e.g. the uat&amp;r section (including the loss of the Jebal tfakhsh i , the rent of the Abu Dhabi section, the huscat section anu the *oan A rotectorate section, we for our part would be ‘willing to submit the question of the hhor-el- Ode id to an independent judgment* it must be admitted, however, that this might not seem a very tempting offer to Saud. He might feel that he was being asked to accept what we offered everywhere else in return for at the most an even chance of getting what tie wanted rear the hhor-el- Odeiu. V. If this proved to be hi# attitude, it would be uifficult to deny that the same principle which applied to the unsettled problem of the Khor-el-Qdeid applied also to the unsettled problem of the frontier as a whole, and that for this as for other unsettmea problems arbitration was the right course. It might therefore be necessary for us to agree in the last resort that the whole frontier, if it could not be settled otherwise, should be submitted to arbitration;m ^ arbitration j ana mm siioula clearly Have to ue prepared in our o^a iainaa to agree to this from the outset* d. m regards tb) # a queation of fundamental importance at once arises: U) Is the arbitration to adhere strictly to legal principles, &lt;«ith the object of aeciding who in law in the rightful owner of the territory concerned? or id] la the arbitrator to proceea on more general lines, with the object of deciding who, taking all relevant considerations into account, (including the legal position, but only an one among several elements) ought, on the moat just and equitable solution, to be recognised as the possessor of the territory? 9. m the peculiar conditions of the area concerned, (k; would almost certainly be the more fair and the more sensible alternative, but (hj also raises b:: ecial difficulties in regaru to (dj, with which X will deal further on* 10* as regards \a) 9 we have no strong feeling about who the arbitrator (or arbitrators) should be* It would clearly be desirable to exclude France, Germany, Italy, Japan, the Soviet Union ana the United states of America, or nationals ox those States* Possibly there are some other States or nationalities whom we should also wish to exclude* If the list of our objections were a long one, we could make a list of States or nationalities which would be acceptable to us and ask Ibn Saud to make his choice* There would, we suggest, be no particular objection to having other modem Powers or Koulems included in the list* If a hoslem State or a moalem were selected, it or he would presumably/R 0 ! i ^ \ presumably nave to t«ike account of the Sheikh of Abu Dhabi’s feelings just aa much aa thoae of ibn Saua, 11. It is probable, however, that a State would in any case be an unsuitable choice, especially for alternative (1) in paragraph b; for (1) the Permanent Court of International Justice noula be much more suitable. If 1 bii Sand aid not like the Permanent Court, it might be possible to find a single arbitrator by agreement, or, if this proved impossible (or indeed for preference) three arbitrators, one selected by each aide (which would enable I'm baud to pick an Arab) and a President chosen by the first two. Ihe exclusion of certain nationalities could be made to apply to all three arbitrators or to the Preaidant only. IB. As regards (d), we understand to the full the difficulty in which the India Office or rather Hia majesty’s Government aa a whole are placed by the fact that we promisea the Sheikh of Abu Dhabi in 1906 that His majesty’s Government recognised the &amp;hor-el-odeid as being his territory and here prepared to prevent its occupation by anyone else. Hut the question must, we suggest, be regarded in the following light. Id. 'The dispute about the 1 hor-el-Ouela consists of two partsj- (i / an actual dispute between iiie majesty’s Government hb the representative of the Sheikh of Abu Dhabi on the one aide and Saudi Arabia on the other. (ii) a potential dispute between His majesty’s Government us the guarantor of the Sheikh of sbu Dhabi on the one side and the Sheikh of Abu Dhabi on the other. In other words His majesty ’b Government stand in relation to the Sheikh in two separate capacities* as the lower which.0 nhich is iiiternafcionaily reaponaible for his actions and as tne xower *fhloh io responsible to hijs only for the Khor-el~v)aeid. 14. To take U) first, the fact that His k&amp;jesty'a Govermrent told the Sheikh of Abu Dhabi in 1906 that they regaraea a certain area as lying in his territory does not in itself constitute proof that it aid lie in his territory or invalidate any olaiias which a third party luay have to it. If therefore a third party, e.g. Saudi Arabi, has claims to territory which is also claimed by Abu Dhabi His majesty's Government, in their capacity as the lower responsible for Abu Dhabi, must - if they are to act as sincere friends of Inc third party or even as ordinary good neighbours - take all reasonable stops to reach a just settlement, without regard to the difficulties which their actions may involve for them in their capacity of guarantor. 15. furthermore, in the present case an entirely non - pogausaun attitude is likely to prove Impossible, or at any rate moat inexpedient in the present state of world affairs. His Majesty's Government are in short in a position where they cannot afford to refrain from taking any reasonable steps which may still lead to a just settlement of this particular dispute and as there is such a step which it is open to them to take, i.e. an offer of arbitration, they ought clearly to take it. 16. To turn now to {Hi, if it is a fact that ills Majesty's Government cannot give Xbn Sauu what he auks, or even offer hum a procedure by which he stands a chance of getting «hat he auka if he can make out a good enough case, without thereby breaking, or taking the risk of breaking, a pledge to the Dheikh of Abu Dhabi, Hi a Majesty'a Government must eviuently find some way of compensating the Sheikh in other directions. what form this compensation might take need not, 1 think, be discussed here/19./ Iibto 9 but before beoidiii^ tliat Go&amp;ixms&amp;tica would ba not onlj expodiont lit would probably be? that in -any case) but also xuorally inoui^bent upon uo no a result of the pledge, we are entitled to consider what the pledge really ^eans. !?• f lhe pledge ia clearly a pledge to our beat ©ndeavourc to prevent the occupation oy any other ruler of aii area of undefined extent adjoining the Inor-el-Queid. auv the j»oi m. ol our ondoavours r-iuot equally clearly vary with the ciroUitiit&amp;nooa# If an attou.pt is siade by a third party to occupy the area by forcible methods, including for our present purpose «■&lt;hat X&amp; oosmonXy understood by ^infiltration”, w© are unaer an obligation to resist the attcuitpt by dorcx.ble methods (although, as we nave said in the official letter, w© uight find it alitost impossible to oarrj out this obligation ixi the present state of world affairs). If on the other hand an attempt is mad© to occupy the area by peaceful, that is to ©ay diplomatic methods, wo are, *e suggest, under an obligation to reuiot the attempt by diploxaatic moti^odo* But if as the result Of the employment of diplouatio method®, including, it may be, some form of arbitration or mediation, the third par ,y can make a goou claim to the area, surely me do not remain under an obligation to mulct the occupation of the area oy that party by forcible mothean. Id. In short. His to.Jonty's Government cannot uo more for their cl lent than they coula do for themselves in similar circumstances, and the client cannot expect His majesty *&amp; Government to do more on hie behalf than the intrinsic nwirita of his case permit. Hi© Majesty’s Government can legitimately u»e all their resources to resist aggroahiOfi| but tne client cannot expect them to refuse to entertain u peaceful method of settling an international dispute#\yS 19. Having aaia tui a much 1 ought to explain that U iB onXy in re « aru to alliern«Uve (1) in paragraph 3 that we put for*aru the propositiona •nucoiated in the last Tew paragraphs. £J0. 5 * c are e-&lt;ivi aed that, il the position is that I bn ^■aua cares to aispute the legal title of the Sheikh of Abu Dhabi arid to cA&amp;isi that he is in law the owner of the territory, the 1906 pledge cannot possibly ^e&amp;n that we are bound to resist Ibn Saud*® claim by force and to refuse to submit tiie legal question at issue to arbitration, which would be the normal ecuran. fo do so would be quite inconsistent with the professions which w© have made of our attachment to the principle ox the pacific settlement of international disputes. «-x• But we are also advised that the position is different if the arbitrator is free to take other than legal considerations into account, since in that case the arbitrator might decide that the Sheikh was the legal owner of the territory, and yet decide in favour of Ibn „aud on grounds which he considered to outweigh* the purely legal aspect. We do not claim that we could, consistently with the 1906 pledge, make the Sheikh agree to an arbitration which might produce this result. -B. .Alternative {1} must therefore be explored and this also has its difficulties. &amp;3* In particular, ibn S'mud might contend that in the circumstances an arbitration confined to purely legal principles would not be fair? and even if he aid eventually accept the idea, it might bo necessary, especially in view of the peculiar local conditions, to lay down certain legal principle® on which the decision was to be based. fhere might be great difficulty in agreeing upon those principles, especially as it might well &lt; be/be that if they were laid, down in a certain way, the aeci&amp;ion might be bound to automatically in favour of one aide or the other. *s4. *u®t ua acauime, however, that it would be posoible to agree that the Coiirt, or the arbitrator, was to decide the question at issue on strictly legal principles, but to be free in uoin^ uo to take into account all or any principles known to internetionax Xaw* Xix this case the Court would be free to take into account not only questions of recognition, such as the 1906 pledge, but also questions of occupancy anu effective control over greater or shorter periods of tixae» But where would the evidence be found for such i&amp;attera? It seems quite possible that the Court might Bay that neither side had succeeded in making good its claim. This being so, it seems to ue worth considering whether a combination of alternatives (1) and {£} in paragraph 8 night not be evolved, especially as (a) seems, as I have said, the fairer and more sensible alternative. It might be possible to arrange that a legal tribunal should be asked to any ..hether, according to the accepted principles of international law governing disputes to territory (which the tribunal might be left to define for itselfj such territory adjoining the Khor-el-Oueid as can fairly be comprised unuer the description 'Khor-el-baeid' legally belongs to i m the hheikh, (b^ Ibn Sauu or (c&gt; neither of the two, in the sense that neither could establish a title on *nese principles. xb. if the verdict were either (a; or (b j , that would put an eiid to the matter# But if it were (cj, either the tribunal or some other body (bocause in that event a purely legal tribunal might not be suitable) should/shoula aeoiae to whom the territory ought to 'belong, talcing into account all the relevant const aerations (which it might or ight not be necessary to specify}* a?. f fhie course would avoid the main difficulty about the l^Cb pledge f because the Sheikh could not lose the territory unless it were held that he could not establish a legal title to it, and perhaps not then; and the fact that the ultimate decision would, not depend on purely legal considerations might make it seem fairer to Ibn Baud although he has in fact claimed the territory on grounds which he would probably describe, if he thought about the point at all, as legal grounds* Eb. fte ao not suggest that we should be entitled to offer any form of arbitration without consulting our olietnt* On the contrary wo think it desirable that he should be consulted and that an effort should be made to persuade him that a settied frontier, based upon effective control, which Ibn laud had specifically undertaken to respect (and which His majesty‘s Government had specifically undertaken to guarantee, if it were decided that a landward guarantee were possiblei would be of much greater advantage to him than the present uncertain state of affairs. &amp;Vm The Sheikh might admittedly ask whether a guarantee by His majesty’s Government of his new frontier coulu be relied upon, seeing that their guarantee of the khor-el-Cdeid hau not sufficed lo retain it in his possession, or at any rate to prevent it from being exposed to the chance of passing out of his possession* Strictly speaking this question coula not be asked unless Hi© majesty *« Government had felt obliged to proceed to arbitration without the Sheikh*© concurrence, a situation which we may hope need never arise. But if it did arise, it could be represented that although His Majesty *0 Government might have abandoned one obligation they had only/only done ao in return for another muon more definite obligation of far greater extent and far greater practical utility, ana that in co far as a precedent was created a t all, it *#as a precedent which provided every safeguard for the interests of Abu Dhabi, dO. ,ai this, however, is looking a little far aheau, since his Majesty’s Government have not yet decided that a guarantee of the landward frontier of any of the ±racial hheikhs is feasible. All we ask at present is that the uheikh of Abu hhabi should be warned that His Majesty’s Government may find it necessary to agree that the question of his frontier, including the section near tne *Jior-e 1-tacid, should be submitted to some form of peaceful settlement such as arbitration; that if this proves to be the case His Majesty’s Government will support his claims to the utmost of their ability; and that if such an arbitration eventually loaves him, as it surely will, with a clearly aefined frontier which baud! Arabia has undertaken to respect, this will conduce far more strongly to the security of his Sheikhdom than the present state of affairs, SI. If the sheikh empresses strong objection to anything of the sort, or uska whether there will be any guarantee by His majesty's Government for the new frontier, the question **il^ have to be consiuered further, dk, I hope that you will be able to obtain the views of the Government of India arid the , olitical Resident upon these ideas as soon uo possible, I am sending copies of this letter privately to the Lapartmento represented on the Middle 3 ast bub-Committee. Yours sincerely, Ud,) C. BAXTER.By Air Mail. P.Z.JUU 19 ^ Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. 3681 Tho Foreign Secretary, Government ol India. The Political Beoidont) in the Peibiaii-^ulf.nnnraeapnpfi * 2325/39- hl I^'OIa OS'?ICS, fxli Jlni'Li'i.XjJ.j _1 LONDON; 3.7.1. 1 /th May, i939« 3.L. Boundaries of Saudi Arabia. A '* Jir, ith reference to your letter No. Fo46~n/ 38 of the 30th August 1938 and connected correspondence on the subject of the S.L. boundaries of Saudi Arabia, I am directed by the secretary 01 State to refer to the letter from the Foreign Office No. L.5861/150/91 of the 17 th January 1939, of which a copy was seno to you oy the mail of the 24th January, and to say that, in pursuance of the suggestion made in paragraph 8 thereof, the matter was discussed at an informal meeting between members of this Office and the Foreign Office early in February. At this meeting the Foreign Office representative put forward the suggestion that an offer should be made to the King of Saudi Arabia to submit the question of the 3.L. boundaries to arbitration, and he was informed that if the Foreign Office would state their proposals in writing, the .Secretary of State would be prepared, in consultation with the Government of India, to consider them. These proposals have now been received in the form of the demi-official letter dated 6 th April 1939 a copy of which letter was forwarded to you by mail of the 18th April. I am to request that the Secretary of State may be furnished with the views of the Government of India secretary to the Government of India, External affairs Department. on/jm &amp;&gt;'■ n% on the Foreign Office proposals for arbitration in this matter and in particular on the proposal put forward m paragraph 30 oi Mr* Baxter ? s letter that the Sheikh of A'bu Dhabi should be v/arned t.hai His ila jesty f s G-overnmen't may find- it necessary to agree that the Question oD his frontier, including the section near the Khor-el-Odeid, should be submitted to some form of peaceful settlement such as arbitratioiio co Py of this letter is being sent to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf and to the political Agent, Bahrein. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, (Sgd.) R. FEEUo nfidentiai. BSBHHRBDKHHRSHBH 11? GOVERNMENT OE [INDIA. Department, EXPRESS LETTER (N. B, This uan ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphie expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treat J on receipt, with the same expedition as if u had been telegraphed. To ™L]ZhZ] f ™* “ Fbom f Political Resident, Bushire, jt i t&gt; ' &gt; / Political Agent, Bahrain, Re, 523“S Dated 2nd June, 193it. Subject South Eastern Boundaries of Saudi Arabia. I / * Reference correspondence ending with India Office Printed Letter No.P.Z.^325 dated the 17th May 1^3^ on the subject of submitting the question of the ownership of Khor el Odeid to arbitration. /jU , 2. My preliminary views on Foreign Office letter No.E.2402/108/91 dated the 6th April 1939 to the India Office are as follows. (a) Why not let sleeping dogs lie, see paragraph 4 of the Foreign Office letter quoted above. It is now some time since the Saudi Government raised the question of the South Eastern frontiers, and amongst various important points which s. 6.- 2 - !$0 which Ibn Saud recently put forward to the Foreign Office this question was not included (vide letter dated the 2nd January 1^39 from Ibn Saud to Mr.Chamberlain, enclosure to India Office Printed Letter ho.P.Z.1327 of the 7th March 1^39; you have not received this communication but I will bring the file with me to Bahrain). It is quite possible that the Saudi Government are no longer their own at Has Tanura (vide my letter ho.723-£'elated the 16th December 1938 to the Government of India). (b) Kis Majesty's Government has no legal right to submit the question of the ownership of Khor el odeid to arbitration without the consent of the Shaikh of Abu Dhabi, and if His Majesty's Government finally decided to submit this question to arbitration this could not be done unless the Shaikh's consent had been obtained. Should the Shaikh refuse we would then have to inform him that should Ibn Saud take Khor el Odeid by force we would not oppose him. On the other hand if Ibn Saud refused arbitration then we would be bound to oppose any attempt by him to forcibly occupy Khor el Odeid - should he make it (This, as I understand it is the gist of para graphs 17 and 20 of the Foreign Office letter quoted above, which at first sight appear contradictory). (c) Apart from the legal point of view the practical political results of arbitration over a piece of territory which we had recognized as belonging to a particular Shaikh w r ould be deplorable whichever way the arbitration went, since of course none of the Rulers of the Arab Coast, or for the matter of that, of the Arabs outside the Gulf, would appreciate the legal technicalities interested in Khor el Odeid since they have produced-3- -4^ U produced by the Foreign Office (in this Connection see paragraphs 4 and 10(b) and (c) of my letter No.207-5 dated the 17th March 193^, copy sent to you under Printed Letter No.21i?-S dated the 20th March lb3b). (d) Once having submitted Khor el Odeid to arbitration we would find it impossible to refuse arbitration on other questions on the Arab side e.g. Iraqi pretentions to Kuwait (the Iraqi Government every now and then bring forward the argument that Kuwait was part of the old Turkish Basrah vilayet and therefore belongs to Iraq), the Persian claim to Bahrain and to Tamb and other Trucial Coast Islands. 3. Could you please have your views ready against my arrival in Bahrain in the form of a draft official letter to me which we can discuss and then compose my letter to Government. Sd. T. C. Fowle. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.■HBHM nnENTXAL,^ GOVERNMENT OF [INDIA. DaPARTMBNT, |%6 j EXPRESS LETTER [N.B y —This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed* To sate tir/bc ana j^, ' v, '»l*ties it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched.} From Political Resident, Bushire. To Political Agent, Bahrain. Ro. 535-S Dated the 3rd June, 193 V. Subje ct South Eastern Boundaries of Saudi Arabia. Reference paragraph 3 of my Express Letter No.523-3 dated the 2nd June 1^39. 2. As I shall not be visiting Bahrain until the 26th June please send me your views. Sd. T. G. Fowle. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. ATTESTED . ■ for Seci?4tary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. S. 6.grnBSTIAL GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, : Department. EXPRESS LETTER [N.B— This ism ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] From Political Agent, Bahrain. To Political Resident, Bushire. A 'o. C/372-1, a/38 Dated 7th JUne 1339 Subject t- South Eastern Boundaries of Saudi Arabia. Heference your Express letter No. 523-S dated the 2nd June 1939 on the above subject. 2. % vievs on the proposals made by the Foreign Office are stated briefly below. As you will see they correspond closely with the preliminary views stated in your Express letter under reference. (a) Whatever he may have felt in the past I do not believe Ibn Baud is now interested in Khor al Odeid. It is significant that he never so much as mentioned the name to me when he was in Bahrain although he did not hesitate to discuss Trucial Coast affairs. On the other h fl nd he was intensely loquacious about the California Arabian Standard Oil Company^ work in Hasa and also about possible concessions /- S. 6. MFP—400S&amp;P—(M-480)—26-7-34—2,00,000.- 2 - concessions over areas beyond the boundaries of that Company* s concession. He had just seen for himself an oil field in being at Dharan and much of the almost feverish exploration now being carried out by the Company north and west of Dharan; and he had, after travelling over much of Hasa, just opened Has Tanura — and, I believe, had recognised that no port up and down the Coast can serve Riyadh and the interior in a manner comparable to Kuwait* Consequently either as a poten tial oil-bearing area or as a port Khor al Odeid is no longer interesting to him. (b) If this view is correct, two alternative assumptions can be made. (i) That Saudi Arabian pressure in regard to the settlement of the boundary in general and the disposal of Khor al Odeid in particular is unlikely to be so strong that delaying tactics from our side cannot succeed — and they need only succeed for the life-time of Abdul Aziz himself. (There is, I submit, now no substantial benefit to us in pressing the question ourselves, for it must have been recognised by this time that the cession of Khor al Odeid will not affect Ibn Saud* s atti tude towards the Palestine problem). (ii) That an offer of arbitration In respect of Khor al Odeid alone will not be acceptable to Ibn Saud for the simple reason that that place by itself is not v/orth the effort involved. Consequently if arbitration is offered Ibn Saud will, I am convinced, demand the inclusion of Jebel Haksh at least and possibly other areas. The Foreign Office have acknowledged that we must be prepared to submit the whole frontier to arbit ration but do not appear to have recognised the implications. Are we, in short, to manoeuvre ourselves into identically the same position of weakness in respect of Jebel Naksh that we appear /-3- appear to be reaching in regard to Khor al Cdeid ? And is it recognised that the effect must be cumulative, for it would be unwise to assume that other Moslem countries with claims in the Gulf (however far-fetched they may be) will not seize on this precedent to demand that their claims also be submitted to arbitration ? Whatever might be the outcome, I submit that we cannot afford the devastating loss of prestige involved if we are compelled by our own precedent to abandon our guarantees to Arab States and to admit that the Persian claim to Bahrain and the Iraqi claim to Kuwait must equally go to arbitration. (c) I do not understand the assumption made in paragraph 29 of the Foreign Office letter under consideration that His Majesty^ Government might be obliged to proceed to arbitration without the consent of the Shaikh of Abu Dhabi. Surely His Majesty’s Government, who have no rights whatsoever in Khor al Odeid, cannot legally proceed with such arbitration in the face of opposition from the Shaikh of Abu Dhabi, the present presumptive owner. And since the Shaikh of Abu Dhabi will unquestionably oppose the suggestion and since there is no prospect of removing his opposition without according him the most unequivocal guarantee of protection of his subsequent landward bound€oc*y, I suggest that His Majesty’s Government will do well before going further to make up their mind whether or not they will and can guarantee any landward frontier. If the ansv/er is in the negative, then in place of the elaborate pro cedure now suggested as the means of handing over Khor al Odeid to Ibn Saud (the course of this correspondence unquestionably indicates that this is the objective) British prestige in the Gulf will suffer less by a plain and brutal breach of faith in respect of a comparatively unimportant area, i.e. by frankly advising /--4- A \v / &gt;0 advising Xbn Saud 'that, there will be no interference on our part if he occupies Khor al Cdeid, after which a boundary can be fixed in accordance with occupation. This plan would at least meet the “personal suggestion' made by Fuad Bey, vide Jedda telegram ITo* 56 dated the 7th March 1938, but needs only to be stated plainly to be rejected* Political Agent, Bahraint^Fl^TLik* wammmmamtm l ? Ko. F. 464^38. A copy of the unaermentionecL paper ia forwaraed to the Hon’ble Uie iolitical Hesiaent in the lersian Gulf f the lolitic&amp;l 4gent f Bahrain, olitioal for information, (in continuation of enaoroenient from it in •aian the Government of India in the External Affairs ily. Department No. F. 46-N/38, oatea tiie 1st September 1938). By order, etc.. Assistant Secretary to the Government of India* rnal Affairs Department, \ Simla, June 1939. Letter to His Majesty's Under Secretary of State for Inuia, No. F. 46-V38, oated the / S fc June 1939.No. F. 46-N/58. From The Secretary to the Government of India in the External iffaira department, To His majesty's Under Secretary of state for inaia, with your letter No. P.2.2325/39, dated the 17th May 1939, in which you aak for the views of the Government of India upon the suggestion made hy the Foreign Office for the submission of the dispute about Khor-el-Udeid to „,, arbitration and particularly on tlrie proposal that tlrie ' ’ Sheikh of ibu iiiabi siiould be earned of the possibility of a resort to arbitration* 2* The suggestion is an entirely novel one and its effect upon both Ibn Baud and the Sheikh of Abu hhabi can only be estimated in the light of the past history of the dispute. The Government of India have therefore again examined their records and I am to state the results of that examination* Since at least as early as 1877 ills Majesty’s Government or the Government of India have consistently maAintained that the Sheikh of Abu hhabi’s claim to Khor~e 1 •Odei&amp; was incontestable* In 1877 Turkish claims to the area were firmly resisted and again in 1681 the Chief of II Bidda was warned against any attempt to Lt h b c &amp;. hated Simla, Hie IS June 1959* SUBJECTj- South Eastern Boundaries of Saudi Arabia. Sir I am directed to refer to the correspondence ending annex! v i ■ .8t\l4-?A .0.-1 ssiryal lo fft*wvjV0O Site 0$ an? t vt ii r:.. *.j lii L 0 U «i i X.3 W&amp; jw. -S i * ft w -C V1 i'# f IX v iui&gt;iu io x lo ^xe«ttM0^c. ,Cmj; #rvit ^.v t £sim~. baJr&gt;u wit ^0 SQXl&amp;bmQti £i1ef*zlL iJJU03 » .. . X- •'«■» • Cf, t t »Wr£#t gii ' •»* ; ,1t&amp; S^dixto sons moqearxoo ml* o^Kxslex ui i&gt;3i$®xrx&gt; m I ... «sx fcftl Jo u.ti^iki*x ox'cr ^i&gt;.cr to m&amp;h io^ &amp;&amp;&amp; uov dviti+s nx d-.iu iOl ^ollID agj&amp;to r \ odJ rd shorn nosi4’s$ 3 &amp;ia s&amp;t aoqu b sniit j. Jxhs ^xlxuiaao A to 0®t¥iS'&gt;* 3CJ iiXiJOilS kd&amp;£k* Od&amp;. to £ht£^iia * tJi o&amp;8 3110 I»\roa rXsxiiaa as ax ixox^aa^a eux .;x n,:^ x^adu ;;o- :*o /x-xe-u e t ms duqq ncfl xto^u jootia 3iltf iO {Uudiu d&amp;±»U SIX' 7,0 JrUil 3i*J fli ec! ^ IiiO lo 8^X&gt;iaat odJ- x* aa I JboB abiaoei titotf bi*iu~t$xe ■- *a 20;uc ♦nox^finimea ^v r 3xi jiibal lo irx^iaxovo.. axi^ xo ^oofmxoToD e* v^-r. ;u uxaga bm hoj&amp;xeei ijlmll aiaw aeifi exit oi &amp;nis:lQ ■' J ,, ■.,- . .. •:,_•,] •; : v G ■_ • ; 3 2sa&amp;££* X‘FX - 2 from tiie corresj-iondence of }tter No * 102, aatea the 8th ^ril 1904,from 1904, which i s noted political Kesiaent m the Persian Gulf and nox,ea ,osur6S« h ^V&gt; liter No. l?9i-E.i., dated tne 3rd Juiie 1904 he Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, l enclosures. u itter No. 195, dated the 30Ui June 1904, from iolitical Resident in the Persian Gulf, ana .osures. title was given to in the margin. In 1906 a formal r guarantee of his P' is sent ia Office so?er sign irrs 3i M iugust the Sheikh and as recently as 1935, when Ibn Baud put formal a a claim to hhor~8l~Gdeid, he was told on more than one occasion by Mr. Hendel speaking on behalf of His majesty’s Government ana also by His Majesty’s minister at Jedda acting under instructions from His Majesty’s Government Uiat tliere could be no question of any concession in that area. In this connection I am to invite attention to paragraph 7 of telegram Ho. 70 from the Foreign Office to Hi* Majesty’s Minister at Jeddah and also to the records of conversations with Fuad Bey Ham&amp;a /which took place in London am Riyadh in June and November / y 'P1935. In view of these facts it would obviously come as * something of a surprise to Ibn Baud, if His Majesty’s ^WC’jjL* CX/W GoveriimenVoffer to submit the question to arbitration and he would look carefully at the implications before accept ing the offer. In the first place he would naturally consider what grounds he coula himself put forward or had advancea hitherto in support of his claim, iifter careful examination of the previous correspondence the Government of India find that Ibn Sand’s claim to nhor-el-Gaeid was first made in a statement enclosed with His Majesty’s minister Jedda’s despatch Ho. 109, datea the 7th April 1935 to the Foreign Office. Ho grounds in support of the claim are stated there out Sir Andrew Ryan recorded that Fuad Bey Hamza in oral discussion at the time based the claim on King Abdul Aziz’s aesire to stop smuggling through Khor-el-Oaeid into baudirArabian territory. In the London conversations which took place in June 1935 Fuad ney #».» xBey Hamza maintained that Ibn daud’a right to nhor-el- Odeid was baaed on the fact the place had in the past been well Known as a landing place for merchandise for the Haaa Coast. Finally in conversations held at Riyadh in Movember 1935 between Sir inarew Kyan ana Fuad Bey Hamza, the latter admitted the soundness of His majesty's Ministerfe arguments but re-affirmed the Saudi claim to khor-el-Odeid on the ground that it was economically necessary to Sauai- Krabia. None of these arguments can be regarded as 1 — . ■ c.--- ■ ' ' ' - t ... ..... material on wihicii to base a claim before any kind of impartial or independent tribunal and had Ifon Baud or Fuaa Bey any further grounds to produce, they would surely have done so before this. It may therefore be presumed that Ibn uaud, know^ir^, the weakness of his claim, would susxject that His Majesty’s government’s offer of arbitration was merely intended to defeat his claim and ha would either decline tiie offer or, if he accepted it, be annoyed at having been decoyed into an obvious trap. 3* The reactions of the Sheikh of ibu Jhabi to a proposal for arbitration are perhaps rather for trie Resident in the Persian Gulf to estimate than for the Government of India and Sir Trenchard Fowle’s comments have not yet been received. The Sheikh may not of course have any knowledge of Ibn Gaud’s claim to i.her-el-Odeid nor of the attitude hitherto taken up by His Majesty’s Government towards that claim but Pie must be aware of the support which his own claim has received from His Majesty’s Government against all other claimant/e for a great many years and also of course of the guarantee of 1006. It would therefore it seems come to him as a shook that His Majesty’s Government should suddenly decide to submit the question for decision to another authority and he would certainly suspect His Majesty’s Government’s motives ana see in the proposal a desire to resile from their .. • •their previous guarantee* He ^ould therefore probably decline to agree unless he was assured that the terms of reference would be such as to make it certain that the decision would be in his favour and against Ibn Baud. Quite apart however from the Bheikh's own reactions the Government of India cannot but feel that for His Majesty's Government to suggest or indeed to insist on a reference to arbitration of this question would have a very damaging effect on their general position in the Persian Gulf via-a- vi£ of the Sheikhs of the irab Littoral, since it would be interpreted as intended to surrender the interests of His Majesty’s Government’s weaker proteges, solely in order to secure the goodwill of a more powerful neighbour. This impression would be confirmed if the result of the arbitration was in of Ibn Baud and would not be entirely removed if the Gheikh were successful. The second alternative would in any case leave Ibn Baud unsatisfied ana there would be no improvement in the present situation from the point of view of either Ibn Baud or His Majesty’s Government. The Government of India are therefore of opinion that there is nothing to be gained by pursuit^ the proposal for a reference to an independent tribunal* 4. The views of the Resident in the Persian Gulf have not yet been received but a copy of this letter is being sent to him for information. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Sd/- H.A.F. Metcalfe, Secretary to the Government of India.EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAID. [N.B.— This is ora ORIGINAL message sent by AIR MAIL which provides a means of communioation more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To sane time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department.] Off ion of the Political Resident No* o */ in the Peraian »ulf, C/245 of 1939 oDated the Cawip* Bahrain* 19 xxxxxxx 30th June, 39. To XX Fro® - To Political Resident, Buahire, at Bahrain* His Majesty's Secretary of State for India, Xiondon* gmaatsd your 'The Secretary to the aorerruaent of lad lag f&amp;Ference-- External Affairs : epar unent, xxxxxxxxx Simla* The Political Agent* Bahrain Subject* South Eastern Boundaries of , f Saudi Arabia* Reference Goveraiitent of India letter l* o*i i* • 46-1/38. dated toe latti June 1939. X a^rue with tUe views expire sod therein. \ lbi&gt; 2. X have tile following oonraentw to oaicei ^ (a) Would it not he host to let the matter rest until the Saudi Government raises It,/id* paragraph 4 of foreign Office letter No.* 24*2/103/91, dated the 6th ^ April 1939, to the India Off ioe. It i* now some time sinoe tiie Saudi government raised tue queBtion of tue South a.astern frontiers, and amongst various important points which Ihn Saud reoentiy put forward to th* foreign Office this question was not included Ivies letter dated pm 2nd January 1939 from Ihn 3 a ud to Mr. Chamberlain, enclosure to India Office Printed / letter (Signature) (Designation)JCj&gt; &gt;\ ©f tka 7 tU Harak 1959^. It In %ultd |&gt;©sail&gt;I« ikat tua BauAi Crov^nfiimiit no longoj* intorootod in iJtior ol Odoid olnoo tkoy '^kiro a port of tkoir OT»n at Ra» Xanarm, vide lot tor M#7E3-.o dated iao tdtd Dooe^ar 19kS to tlio SoTornmeat of India* (to) It •eoms to j®e toat tkd Tntvlgn Office aeou^s that hi» kajoa ’ sa 9ovei naent liave the ri^ht in tue laet re oar t to ©ubmlt Vao question oi the ownership of Khar el odold to arbitration without the consent of the hh&amp;ixh of Abu Dhabi # ride paragraph a© of their letter quoted above* -'htrietly speakiu^ tiiia question ooula not be as&amp;ed unless His Hajeely ’» Covernmant iiad felt obliged to prooeeti to arbitration without ti^e huaijsli’e eoncurrene## a situation which we may hope need never arise** Xt is true that toy treaty the conduct of the Himi^h , e foreign relatione are in the hands of Hie hajeety f » 0overmmt tout this does not» In i%' opinion, entitle the latter to go to arbitration as the representative of the Shaikh without the latter*a consent* in other words if the &amp;ha&amp;h does not consent there can toe no arbitra tion* (c) /.part from the legal point of view the practical political results of arbitration over a piece oi territory which we had recognised as belonging to a particular Hhaikh would toe deplorable since of course none of the Ruler® of the Arab Ocaet, or tor the isatter of ta&amp;t, of the Ar&amp;oe oat sic a the half, would appreciate th* atgUMmts of the Foreign uftice. / *veiiMrm it the reauit of the arbitration were favour able ia the ShaUch, the mere faot that Hie MaJ«ety*a a&amp;rvrnmmt ha&amp; ocmeenteh to arbitration would have a meet damging effect on the reliance on us of all the /vrab Itulere in the Persian Gulf* In Vain connection see paragraph® 4 and 10 (h) and (c) of isy letter Ho.207-1 dated tlw 17th '%rch 1W. Once having submitted Kher el Odeid to arbitration we would* it seams to me* find it impossible to refuse arbitration on other questions on the Arab aide* e«g* Iraqi pretentions to huwait* ths lereiun o141js to Bahrain and to Abu ttesa and famb« The objections to opening the door to the olaima by interested parties for their settlement by arbitra tion need not be emphasised* sd. T*0*Jfewl«* Political Resident in the Persian Gulf* far fccre tary to the lelitioal Resident in the Per si an iulf*Bv AHr Mail. P.Z. ^ V \\ 4 '7 v f ( ! I INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy has been sent to by Mail. - J Sea The Foreign Secretary. _G.Overn.ment of lndia. The Political IfeirleiTriii the Peibian Chdf.58/1939 9100/1/39 &amp; V : -W l x Door Sir Bernard, With reference to our secret despatch of the BGth of January, I enclose a copy of a semi- off idol letter from the Foreign Office to the India Office* which discusses the question of referring to arbitration the difficulties outstanding with the GoYormnent of Saudi Arabia in regard to the South Eastern frontiers of Saudi Arabia* Would you be so good, as to let me know wliother you have any provisional views on the proposal so for as the Aden Protectorate sector may be concerned? Tours sincerely, ( 3ign-d) K.V♦BLAXIfE. iEUTlh AKT-GOLOlf \L 3IH BKBSIAHB HBXLX*T, n.C*M*G-,C.I.B.,0.3*B #lZ, 3958/1939 jkimi 31st 1939 Uj dear Blfocter, Will jou please refer to your secret letter of 26th April, 1939, with which you enclosed a copy of a semi-official letter from the Foreign Office to the India Office about the question of referring Saudi Arabian frontier questions to arbitration. the bounder- effected is that of the eastern pert of the Protectorate, and I have accordingly consulted Ingrema with regard to the question you have put# I enclose n copy of his reply, and I agree with what he has oaid# If we can be certain that the arbitration w ill be perfectly fair and impartial, I see no objection to it, but if there is any risk of considerations of political expediency being allowed to influence the decision, I should be against it* As for ns the Aden Protectorate is concerned Tours sincerely, (S ign ed) B # H»Hi HIT • -•I#Blaxfcer, Esquire Colonial Office*P,Z.3958/1932. SECKa . [[ 0 , 132 / 5 // 1 : ' . SHE HESHBEGr, MUKaXiIjA • ! 24th May, 1939. My dear 3ir Bernard, ©ina.; you for your secret letter of the 8th May regarding tZie proposed South Eastern frontiers of Saudi Arabia# Fortunately I am not called upon to discuss the mattei rdior al C'beid itself and I talce it that the c^uestion as it concerns us is whether the natter of what should be the boundary between the Hadhramout State and Saudi Arabia should be submitted to arbitration or not, and perhaps who should be eligible as arbitrators or not eligible. I ©a firmly of opinion that the inclusion of the Kurab, dei f ar, Aw amir, Msnahil and Mahra in the Irotectorate is legally and naturally right on tlie following grounds: (1) thoir dependence on treaty cliiefs by former ogreemento, (2) the geographical dependence of their areas on the Hadhrmasut itself and the general ^lie of the land’ 1 , i#e#, the existence of the natural boundaries between us and the Yemen and Saudi Arabia. (3) their economic dependence on the Eadhrariaut* (4) A ground that we have not taken into consideration before, namely that during the past two years our links with them and contact with them have become much clearer and this in pursuance of a definite wish expressed by His Majesty^ Government and of the wish of the people. (5) On the other side there are no reasons for neither Saudi Arabia or the Yemen have had any real contacts in recent history with these areas. I don*t see that we arc colled upon to take into consideration the independent Arab view, that/ 5H 3. HI1AED REILLY, E.C.M.G., C.IJ3., G.3.B.,-2 - that as rauch of Arabia as is possible should be in. independent Arabia w'l- ther it likes it or not. Holding therefore that our case is legally arid morally right, it v*ould be illogical to object to arbitration and I have no objection to it if these -.re the sort of grounds on vrhich the case is to be decided. But if it is to be within the competence of the arbitrator or arbitrator® to consider 'whether to make an equitable decision all round and to give territory from one of the parties on one side in order to make up for a bit retained by another or if ”expediency” is to be taken into account, then I would be strongly against it. Tou cannot expect, e*g. the Cju l eiti Sultan or a Sei«ar chief to think it reasonable that part of his territory should be put under Ibn S&amp;u&amp; in order that the Sheikh of Abu Dhabi )i v-uo Sultan of Muscat, or an Omani Chief should be satis.:.lad* As to arbitrators, X should think that if It is at a!3. possible, the matter could best be decided by the Permanent Court of International Justice. X do not think the arbitrator or arbitrators should be Muslims! t von if they were rt disinterested 11 Muslims, e.g. Iraqis, *hey would be far more likely to decide in fo.vour of Ibn Smd rather than in favour of a chief under British protection. I return Baxter 1 a letter. Yours cine,rely, (3d* ) W*H• IbGHAMS .Department, India Office.INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL, ■ P.Z.4199/39. I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to state, for the information of the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, that he has had under consideration, in consultation with the Government of India and che Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Mr.Baxter's official letter of the 19th January, Ro.E.5861 , and his demi-official letter of the 6 th April, No .E .2492/108/91, regarding the possibility of finding means to break the present deadlock in the dispute with Ibn Saud over the south-eastern frontiers of Saudi Arabia. 2. The views of the Government of India and of the Political Resident have been communicated in letters dated respectively the 15th June and the 30th June, copies of which are enclosed herewith. Neither authority has found it possible to support the proposed offer to submit the dispute to arbitration. The Government of India feel considerable doubt whether an offer of arbitration would be welcome even to Ibn Saud himself, and both % they and the Political Resident consider that, having regard to the nature of the relationship between the Arab Sheikhs and His Majesty's Government (a copy of the Resident's letter of 17th March 1939 on this subject, to which he2. now ref ers ? waf3 sent to you with India Office letter No* P »Z ,^110/clatecl the 28th April), the mere suggestion to the Sheikh of Abu Dhabi that His Majesty r s Government were contemplating arbitration in respect of territory which they had recognised as his for over 60 years would have a very damaging effect on their general position in relation to the Arab Sheikhs of the Persian Gulf. The Political Resident adds the warning that the submission of the Ehor al Odeid issue to arbitration would constitute a most dangerous precedent for the disposal of other claims to the territories of Persian Gulf Rulers who enjoy the protection of His Majesty T s Government. 3. Apart therefore from the substantial difficulties which would arise with regard to the choice of arbitrators and to their terms of reference and in respect of the scope of arbitration proceedings, Lord Zetland regrets that, in the light of the opinions of the local authorities, he cannot undertake to solicit the consent of the Sheikh of Abu Dhabi, which he would regard as a condition precedent to any further consideration of the suggested offer of arbitration. The Sheikh of Abu Dhabi stands to gain nothing from arbitration, for at present his position is guaranteed by His Majesty’s Government and he might well ask what security he would have in the future against encroachments on the rest of his territory, if he did ci.gr^ to arbitration and the award went against him, since nc might argue that the mere fact that His Majesty’s Government had been prepared to go back on their guarantee, in respect of the Ehor al Odeid showed that no similar Lord Zetland feels that/ undertakings could be relied upon.that to arouse doubts of this kind as to our good faith in the minds of the Arab Rulers in the Persian Gulf - and there can be no doubt that the feeling of uncertainty could not be confined to the Sheikh of Abu Dhabi alone - mighi' be no less dangerous at this juncture to our interests in the Middle East from the strategical point of view than the risk of dissatisfaction on the part of the Saudi- Arabian Government, if v/e maintain our attitude. He finds it difficult, moreover, to believe that a refusal to meet the latter’s wishes in this matter would seriously prejudice His Majesty’s Government's relations with Ibn Saud who, as the Political Resident points out, did not consider it necessary to refer to the frontier dispute in the letter which he addressed to the Prime Minister early this year. He would suggest, therefore, that this question should be allowed to rest where it is for the time being, in the hope that the Saudi Arabian Government will be content not to press the matter further. If, however, they should raise the point again and it should become necessary to give them a definite answer, it should in Lord Zetland's opinion be to the effect that aftci tnc fullest consideration His Majesty’s Government regret th.-t their undertakings to other Rulers render it impossible for them to entertain the claim of the Saudi-Arabian Go/er..men to territorial concessions in the Trucial Coast aro^.. Lord Zetland hopes that Lord Halifax will accept this ? to which after due consideration of all the circumstances he can see no alternative. 4. Copies of this letter are being sent to the Departments/4. Departments represented on the Middle East (Official) Sul Committee of the Committee - of Imperial Defence. I am, Sir,5 OUTWARD TELEGRAM C*rn fThis Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government, kept under Lock and Key.] and shbuld be — 1 ■ i i t &amp; 1/od L_ii±2_J ps i 1253/56/91. DISTRIBUTION , T°: SaIID I ARAB IA. Cypher telegram to Mr. Stonehewer-Bird, (jedda). foreign Office^ 22nd March, 1940o 2^50 a.m. No. 28o J j J j J j J J J j Jj J f My telegram liOc 20 of the 1st February 1939 [Frontier negotiations with the Yemen]. Unless you see objection please inform Ibn Baud that in response to a request irom the King of the Yemen His Majesty's Government have agreed to send a representative to Sanaa to negotiate a final settlement of the southern frontier of the Yemen, in accordance with Article 3 of the Treaty of Sanaa of 1934. Mr. Champion, who accompanied the mission to Sanaa has been chosen for this purpose and leaves Aden shortly* 2. The following is for your own information only. \ 3. The frontier which we desire is the frontier laid down in the Anglo-Turkish Convention of 1914 save (a; in so far as it has been modified by the status quo line of 1934 and (b) in so far as it may be agreed to make any further small rectifications of the frontier acceptable to both parties* 4* If as is likely, it is found impossible to reach a final settlement of the kind desired and the Yemeni Government raise the question of Shabwa and Al Abr, it is to be made clear that His Majesty ? s Government cannot agree to the cession of either of these places. It may however be necessary to offer the ’‘neutralisation'• of Ghabwa ana possibly in the last resort of Al Abr also*2* 5* But acceptance of ''neutralisation' will not mean that His Majesty’s Government admit that anything which they have done south of the 1914 line since 1954 has been in conflict with the undertaking which they gave in treaty to maintain the status Quo « They stand upon legal claim that Shabwa and Al Abr are in the Aden Protectorate. It will therefore be necessary, whatever form of ''neutralisation' may eventually be agreed upon (and even though His Majesty’s Government do not ask Yemeni Government specifically to recognise 1914 line) to avoid the appearance of abandoning the legal position. This will be necessary if only because our task of preserving, as agaixist Ibn Baud, what are regarded as rights of kheikhs under our protection in the neighbourhood of the Persian Gulf would otherwise become yet more difficult. Ibn Baud might moreover complain 'chat His Majesty’s Government were adopting a more accommodating attitude with the Yemen than with himself, with possibly embarrassing consequences- particularly in Persian Gulf area.X•a/38• Telegrain From To No. 447 3 • Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Resident, at Kuwait. Dated the 29th November 1941. Packer reports rumour that Shaikh of Qatar has conceded piece of Qatar territory in vicinity of Jabal Naksh to Ibn Saud. Packer is seeing Shaikh in a few days and v/ill question him on subject and report result to me. A further communication will follow. Humour seems somewhat incredible in view of Shaikh’s views vide letter No. C/38 dated 25th ?Tanuary 1935 from Colonel Lochu petroleum concessions ltd. Bahrain PERSIAN GULF. DO/SAA. 2/2760 L&gt;&lt;)hF IDiuinTIAL 22nd December, 1941. QA r mH BOOK PART Reference the rumours of which I spoke to you that the Shaikh of Qatar during his visit to Mecca had made some concessions to the claims of Ibn Saud amounting to agree ment that the Qatar-Saudi Arabian boundary could be on a line from Jabal Naksh practically due east. I broached the subject to the Shaikh of Qatar at Wajibah on Tuesday the 16th December. He was very definite in his statements that the matter of this boundary had not been discussed with Ibn Saud or any one else during his visit to Saudi Arabia on Haj and he was unaware of any fresh developments in this boundary question. He took the view that the map included in the Qatar Concession documents could be assumed as correct for the purpose of the Company^ operations. We have no records in our office on the situation between H.B.M.’s Government, Qatar and Saudi Arabia as regards this boundary. If the boundary in the Concession is not the final decision and particularly if the area it shows is likely to be decreased in any direction, it is important that we should know as our surveyors have been recently working near the boundary. In this connection, we should like to know if, in your opinion, it is permissible or desirable at this stage for us to put in some Company beacons to mark the boundary as shewn in the Concession.DO/SAA.2/2760 (contd.) + ^ ealize it; is possible that this matter is still under consideration by the India Office, and our London principals are kept informed. In these days, how- ^ Ve fvil takes J three or four months for us to contact our Head Office and get their views. Yours sincerely, Major R.G.Alban, O.B.E., H.B.M.’s Political Agent, Bahrain.* Telegram 3. From Political Agent, Bahrain To Political Resident, Bushire No. Sob Dated the 24th December 1941. My telegram No. 447 dated 29th November 1941. 2. Packer has seen Shaikh of ^atar who stated em phatically that this boundary had not been discussed with Tbn Saud during his visit to Arabia on Haj.and that he was unaware of any fresh developments in the boundary question. PoliticalDO/SA.. 2/2780 Dear QATAH BOUNDARY I send herewith a copy of the Qatar map shewing the southern boundary. The boundary on this map is the same as that shewn on the sketch map accompanying the Qatar Concession. This sketch map was signed by Shaikh Abdulla bin Qasim al Thani, Ruler of Qjatar, and C.C.Mylles. The same boundary is also shewn on the blue print marked R-6878. As already mentioned in my DO/SAA.2/2760 dated the 22nd December 1941, we have no records in the Bahrain office on discussions, if any, which have occurred between H.M. Government, Qatar and Saudi Arabia since the concession was signed, on the subject of this boundary. ' ~ f. ‘ Yours sincerely,40V b / GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, — Department. LETTER [N, B.-Tins an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to telegraphic expense and undue me of the wires, but intended to be treated, on reeei.pt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To sate lime and formalities it ivorded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] donflian-ial From Pciivical Agfcitt* Bahrain^ To Political Kaoidtent* Bushire. aVo, Dated 19 $ . Hth January 1942 - v\ 1 enclose herevviu* a cow of ?*. ciemi-official letter No- WSM.2/2760 diited the 22nd December, 1941, from Mr. Packer* Penager, Petroleuni Concasaions Limited, Bahrein. 2. Paragraphs 1 and 2 of the letter have already been dealt with, vide correspondence ending with my telegram o. 506 , i i dated the 24th December 1941. 3. In his paragi'sph 3, he sayss r If the boundary in the concession is not the final clecission and. par uxcularly it the ea it shov b is likely to toe dearer,sea in fn.y direction, it is importa nt that ve should too* i*i»a question of the south eastern boundaries with Saudi Ar-s.hi* has not been settled yet, vide correspondence enuing with India tffice le'.tei 1 2 3 ■ 0 • i *3. 41 9/3.) dated the 10th August 1939 and presumably we cannot therefore inform the Company that the boundary of the concession is the p r) r . \ final /. S. 5.- 2 - &gt; . V, v Jf Vl 4* final decision. The proposed boundary line, however, which would form tbs basis of the negotiations with the 3eudi Government begins well to the south of Jebal Naksh and runs thence in a south easterly direction well away from Khor el Ode id and rcu Dhabi teirutory* Ihe concession boundary on tae ocaisi hnna is that shown on the enclosed map and runs well to the north of the proposed boundary. It would be possible therefore to inform '^hc Company that the concession area is not likely to be decreased if and when boundary discussions are resumed. 4. As regards paragraph 4, the cons to mark the concession boundr erection of Company b@a~ ry may give rise to ques tions by the Saudi authorities but 1 see no reason why this should atop them since they are entitled to exploit their concession s.nd to mark its boundaries if required. Political Agent, Bahrain. ♦** vide telarra® ?'o. 112 dated the ISth November 11*35 from H#M* Secretary of -tate for Foreign Affairs, London. .Please refer to your demi-official letter No. D0/3.4.2/2780 dated the 10th January* 1942. 2. The matter has been referred to the Hon f ble the Political Resident, 3. I should be grateful if a second map of the con cession area could kindly be sent for our records. Yours sincerely, r i * S. V. Packer, Esq., Petroleum Concessions Limited, Bahrain.CONFIDENTIAL . No. iU~$ gf 194S % The Hon ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his Hia Mttjeaty’a Secretary of State lor India, London. Tne Secretary to tne Oovernnent ol India, External Allaire Department, Hew Delhi. Hia Majesty’a Miniater, Jeddah. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document (s). British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated..^94.2.* compliments to Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Bahrain telegram ho.447, dated tue 29th November 1942, to tne political Resident. Jabal fcalBh. * f %l\ Baiirain telegram ho.&amp;Od, dated tne 24th Deoeiaher 1942, to the Political Resident. Copy to political Agent, Bahrain ■fiD.O. No* C/181 The 8th February 1942, Will you kindly refer to Alban’s demi-official letter No* C/53 dated the 12th January 1942 ? 2* X shall be grateful if you will kindly send an extra copy of the map asked for, if you are in a position to do so* Yours sincerely, K* V* Packer, Ksq., Manager, Petroleum Concessions Limited, Bahrain*■fy ^0' DO/AY.1/2818 O- 1 ^ PERSIAN GULF. 9th February, 1942. Dear UjoAijutid^ O' 1 Reference your D.O. No.C/181 dated the 8th February 1942. I hope to be able to get a copy of the map in question within the next few days. Yours sincerely, E. B. Wakefield, Esq., I.C.S., The Agency, Bahrain.gpEKTIAl , &gt; ll The Rest den ciy, Bushire, 5th February 194E* tVcur IvoJlu^^AL Please refer to your predecessor's Racpress Letter Ltd* should be discouraged frees taking up these matters in war time and that if they consider it essential to take them up they should be pressed to do so in London to save as much correspondence as possible* will in any case be (a) that we can give them no guarantee that the southern boundary of their concession will ever be waried as the international boundary is unsettled, but that the line has been drawn well within the area ifoich we consider as belonging to the Shaikh of ^atar and that we shall certainly do our best in our interests as well as the Company*s to ensure that no part of the concession area is included within Ibn 8 aud*s dominions when the international boundary is finally determined, and (b) that while there is no objection to the Company * s working up to the extreme southern limit of their concession area, we are strongly opposed to the setting up of any beacons to mark the bound ary in order to avoid raising the question of the Ho*C/49, dated the 11th January 194E* 2* I am inclined to think that Petroleum Concessions 1 think the answer to the two points they raise / international R.BoWakefield Esquire, I*C*S*, Political Agent, Bahrain*«» 2 *» a 0 international frontier at a Moat inappropriate ^ent ana the poeeibility of giTing offence to Ibn Saud whose attitude towards ue during the war has been in every 'u&amp;Zf roost satisfactory. I co”id. not bowsver autborisfi vnti 4 - /-&gt; „„ aumorise you to give an answer on these lines without consulting His Majesty*s Government. j i . 4. With regard to (b) I would note that the case can be di stinguishst from that of the islands of Pasht Abu Saafa and A1 on which it has been agreed that the Bahrain Petroleum Company should set up prominent survey markers as there the Cwcpan; s ' r * rea&lt;i y to cease their operations if ibn Saud raises any objection. In the present case we cb not want anything to happen which may make it necessary to circumscribe the concession area which has already been definitely assigned to the Petroleum Concessions Ltd. with our own concurrence. 5 * 1 wil1 discuss the matter further with you on my next visit to B^nrain, hut if you agree with the views expressed in para 2 I suggeat that you do your best to ride Packer off the whole subject. I will also, if necessary, speak to him whan I come to Bahrain. * 6 « I am sending a copy of this correspondence to His Majesty # 8 Secretary of State for India, the Government of India and Hi s !£aj esty ♦ s Representative at Jedda. * under Printed letter H 0 . 156 -S dated 5th February 1942.tUT/# CONFIDENTIAL. No. 156-3 of 1S42. / 4^ ^ 'r ' nJy'- compliments to The Hon ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his )liments tn v 1* His Majesty 1 * Secretary of State for India, London* 2, The secretary to trie Oovernaaent of India t External Affairs Depart eat, new lolhl. 3. His ? f ajesty # s v inis tor, Jedda# and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document(s). 2* The imp referred to in paragraph 3 of enclosure 1 is that attached to the Qatar Oil Concession of l?th n$y 1935, forwarded with Residency Printed tetter fto«C/l§a, d ied the 22nd May 1336, to the India Office and the Government of India. British Consulate-General, BUBHIRE. ir* Reference to previous correspondence : '&gt; &amp; v-a Itesldonor Printed Letter Ho.21#3 of 12th January IMS. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. 1. Kxprets Letter Ho.C/49 of 11th January 1 l 42 from the Political Agent, Bahrain, with enclosure. 2. Letter rio.l65~3 of 6th February 1942 to the Political Agent, Bahrain. Copy forwarded, with Agent, Bahrain, for South Eestam ho r.d«UOB of Saudi AresLla. % U /1 compliments, to the /Political information. /7 DO/SA.2/8862 PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LTD. BAHRAIN PERSIAN GULP. 3rd March, 1942. Dear &lt;Jlt With reference to your DO.No.C/181 dated the 8th February 1942, I enclose another map of Qatar. It is not in very good condition but may serve your purpose until another one can be procured from London. Enel. E. B. Wakefield, Esq., H.B.M. f s Political Agent, Bahrain.Confidential D.O.No.C/141. \ Office of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Camp, Bahrain. Dated the 15th March, 1942. &gt; Please refer to my demi-official letter No.l55-S, dated the 5th February 1942. 2. Packer came to see me on the 14th March and I told him informally that (a) we should certainly do our best to prevent any encroachment upon the Southern boundary of Petroleum Concessions Limited^ concession area and (b) that Petroleum Concessions Limited could work right up to this boundary but * that it was inadvisable to set up anything prominent in the way of boundary marks. -^ 0^ 3. Packer told me that he had been somewhat alarmed by the repont that the Shaikh of Qatar had made territorial concessions to Ibn Saud, and that it was only this that had prompted him to ask for information about the boundary. The Shaikh's firm denial of the report had however re-assured him and I gathered from him that he was willing to drop his request for information, and that only such marks would be set up on the Southern boundary of the concession area as were necessary for the Company's operations. In the circum- no r.ply should b. to Ms l.ttsr of sad Dsosm- {■ &gt; 0 I ber 1941. 4. is. sending e oopf of this letter to the Secr.tery „f state for Indls, the Gov.rn.ent of Indi. end HI. MsJ.stysp. mmiMh, 5 # * .1 * loth vyyj, sir, lia twply to ycsm* letter, of th© 24th £%areh, Ho* ; * ■« j m diroot^i to inform you that ma ;.laJo 3 t/» s Ocvonncrt to the use of ?drcr«ft for transport or survey in tho oraian dulf mtm $ jparovided (a that the consent of tho .:-heish ■ o^nooriiod. ia obtaln^id beforehand and th© ov©r ^doli the Compawy wouid pr,&gt;poso to fly erpi&amp;ined to him, |b) that the olitrioal Resident in tho loraim iriiif or the Folitioal i-tmt O3«oomod is kO|&gt;t in cioae toueh nith the plane and is oonaulUid ae to the suitability of tho aircraft and equipment (o*g* «iroiee« •, which would in any mem oonf-.;^ to tho ti. -uiations rm^ms eir^orthinea^i etc. which apply in Bahrein &amp;*»*a*), (cj that any air survey ccigpaa^r which may be ployed is a British flm of undoubted repute under entirely British direction md mploy^ BtlUsh mttamlo at natives of the rah State concerned. 2* Ab regards the ai&gt;©cifio propoarda of the Company, v His Itajocty’s CommT.mnt arc cf opinira, after consul tin;: to Xonai poXitical authoritiee, that it wmM be best to postpone any air survey (or to use of a rcraft tm tranuport) on tho Trucial Coast until the coafteaclona have actually been obtained from tho luiors, the use of aircraft is provided far In to draft ooncossi^uj, tuid ^bm thoeo arc obtained tore v,ill be a certain obligation on the Rulers O'-^.merneii to oc^oporato in to' miter. But in tho jacanwhlle it v^juld not bo possible tc count on the RuXors* oo^per^dion caeccpt as a special favour (for which toy jssif^ht expect com return -, and it would appear undesirable at this to ask more favours of them tom is absolutely nMcecary. 3* The cme reasons egainst any teiediatc action apply to ;Uscat with greater force, in view of the fact that the negoti atlona/ fho lansglni: idxoctor, detroloum CommaXom Ltd*, City C&amp;tc House, Firyibury Square, E«C* 2.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000380_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/161</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000380</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/161</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 1/A/38 V Saudi Arabian Frontier Negotiations'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1937/1942</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-12-21T18:20:41</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (250 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in chronological order from the front to the back of the file, except where enclosures of an earlier date are filed after their relevant covering letter, and terminate in a set of notes (folios 237-249).</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1 and terminates at the inside back cover with 252; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is also present in parallel between ff 10-252; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled, and are located in the same position as the main sequence. A previous foliation sequence, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The volume concerns negotiations between the British and Saudi Arabian governments over the question of how to settle the eastern frontier of Saudi Arabia.The principal correspondents are: HM Minister, Jedda (principally Sir Reader William Bullard); the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf (principally Lieutenant-Colonel Trenchard Craven William Fowle); officials of the India Office, the Government of India, and the Foreign Office; and the Saudi Arabian Minister for Foreign Affairs (Amir Faisal [Fayṣal bin ‘Abd al-‘Azīz Āl Sa‘ūd]).The papers cover: the attitude of Ibn Saud [‘Abd al-‘Azīz bin ‘Abd al-Raḥmān bin Fayṣal Āl Sa‘ūd] to the frontier question; the boundary with Qatar; the boundary with Abu Dhabi; the British maintenance of the Blue Line as the frontier; the activities of the California Arabian Standard Oil Company (CASOC) in the area, including allegations of encroachment by the company to the east of the Blue Line (folios 104-105); the status of Khor al Odeid and Jabal Naksh, and their possible cession to Saudi Arabia; the effect on negotiations of British policy in Palestine; and the activities of Petroleum Concessions Limited, including the need to guard against encroachment upon the southern boundary of the company's concession (folio 229).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Saudi Arabia, Minister for Foreign Affairs</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Petroleum Concessions Limited</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Ambassador to Saudi Arabia</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>King of Saudi Arabia</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Arabian American Oil Company</namePart></name></subject><subject><geographic>Qatar</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Saudi Arabia</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Abu Dhabi</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Boundaries</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000380#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>