<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x00017c_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T11:56:16.157Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">/ C IS3 PERSIA. liakhtiari Offer of Military Assistance. (Note by Political Department, India Office.) 1. I he project of creating a force of Bakhtiari Levies was under the consideration of His Majesty’s Government in 1916-17. Captain Noel was a strong advocate of the scheme, which was supported by the Secretary of State for India, mainly as a means of building up British influence in the Bakhtiari country with a view to the post-bellum situation. The creation of the force was actually sanctioned by His Majesty’s Govern ment in December 1916, and on the 2nd February 1917 the Government of India were instructed to “ proceed at once ” with the project. In the following May, however, it was decided, on Sir C. Marling’s recommendation, to postpone action till the general political and diplomatic situation became clearer. In agreeing to postponement, the Secretary of State for India (Mr. Chamberlain) urged that “ the project should be “ regarded, not as definitely abandoned, but merely as postponed to a more favourable “ opportunity’' (India Office to Foreign Office, dated 25th May 1917). 2. The project was revived in March' 1918, when it was suggested that some of the officers and non-commissioned officers of the original Dunsterville Mission should be sent to the Bakhtiari country “ with a view to raising levies from the tribe and “ ensuring a friendly attitude on their part in the event of a forward movement being “ required from Shiraz to Ispahan.” The proposal found little favour either with Sir C. Marling, the Government of India, or the military and political authorities in Mesopotamia, and it was not proceeded with. The 3 * * * * * * * * * * 14 forward movement . . . . from Shiraz to Ispahan ” never materialised. 3. The objections to the proposal of March 1918 were mainly based on the probable attitude of the Bakhtiaris themselves. Thus, Sir C. .Marling considered that, the “ Khans would strongly object to appearance of officers and non commissioned officers in Bakhtiaristan ” ; the Commander-in-Chief in India urged that “ the primary factor is that we should do nothing to alienate the Bakhtiari Khans who . . . are independent, powerful and sensitive regarding outside interference ”; the Civil Commissioner, Baghdad, thought that the suggestion would not be “ acceptable to Ilkhani at present.” The project now under consideration is clearly differentiated from its predecessors in that it is based on a spontaneous offer on the part of the Bakhtiari Chiefs. It arises out of a proposal made by the Ilkhani to the British Vice-Consul at Ahwaz, as transmitted in Captain Wilson’s telegram of the 18th July, “ to raise at once and place at our disposal 5,000 good cavalry for service against the Kashgais or elsewhere.” Captain Wilson Inis since discussed the Ilkhani’s offer personally with the Vice-Consul, Ahwaz, and Dr. Young, the medical officer at the oilfields, who has a long and intimate acquaintance with Bakhtiari affairs. As a result, he has formulated the following concrete proposals : — (1) That the Ilkhani (Sardar Zafar) should lie invited to maintain a force of 1,500 men (1,000 of them mounted) under his own command ; (2) That another 300 rifles with 100 rounds apiece should be given him for the purpose (though this is not considered essential for the present); (3) That these arms should be prepared and sent to the oilfields for delivery in the autumn when the Ilkhani returns to the low country (it is not considered that any further arms woidd be required, except perhaps 30,000 rounds to replenish ammunition expended in the recent Bakhtiari campaign against the Kuhgelu); (4) That, in order to keep this force in the field, we should be prepared to pay Sardar Zafar from 8,000 to 10,000 lomans a month from now until such time as, having regard to the general situation in Persia, the force can be', safely disbanded ; S 18 40 8/18(5) That this expenditure should be supervised by the Vice-Consul at Ahwaz, who would not disburse unless satisfied of the proper application of the funds ; and (6) That no fixed sum should be mentioned to the Khans, but that the Vice- Consul should be given discretion to pay out amounts up to the above maximum. 4. The objects of maintaining the proposed force in the Bakhtiari country are summarised by Captain V ilson as follows : (1) To stabilise situation in Ispahan likely to become periodically precarious unless some such force is in vicinity. (2) To maintain authority of llkhani in Bakhtiari territories. This is the one effective means of protecting the oilfields. (3) The above force is a nucleus which could be doubled or trebled in emergenev, and could, under the leadership of the llkhani, or of his nominee from among young Khans, advance much further afield than Bakhtiari limits if necessary. With llkhani in charge there will be no question of force being used by us to acquire political or territorial influence, a possibility to which younger Khans are keenly alive. U* iiouu o J /1 \\ c:I General Officer Commanding, Baghdad. They have also received the “ cordial support” of the Government of India, who regard them “ns calculated to secure “ continued co-operation of Sardar Zafar and goodwill of bulk of Bakhhari tribe, and to provide a substantial check on discordant elements at Ispahan and elsewhere ” (Viceroy’s telegram of 31st July 1918). The only dissentient voice is that of bir C. Marling (see his telegram No. (104 of 30th July), who regards the proposals with “considerable misgivings,” and argues that the arrangement contemplated “ is in “ effect an engagement with Zafar personally, and not as llkhani, to retain him in office, in return for which he is to keep up a body of sowars to be employed in our “ interests.' This, in Sir C. Mailing’s opinion, is calculated to arouse the jealousies of the other Khans, and to produce a combination against Sardar Zafar which is likely to end m an appeal by the latter for our armed assistance. He apprehends that the proposal will “bring about a split in the tribe, the result of which would be insecurity on the Ahwaz road.” Replying to the Minister’s criticisms, Captain Wilson observed (telegram No. 0270, 31st July) that the objections advanced would “apply „ equaUy t0 . an y constructive proposals which have for their object the maintenance m powerful the Bakhtiari country or elsewhere of a party favourable to British interests After discussion with the local officers, he had come to the conclusion that the risk of a hostile combination against the llkhani “was remote and could be considered as negligible if he had the 1,500 sowars and our support.” He a-ain urged the adoption oi his proposals as “a constructive attempt to siabili.se''the situation in the Bakhtiari country and Ispahan,” and drew attention to the results pJese^ llte ffi ° UthS fr ° m the P° lic - vof active support to the A 4' 1 ' i&lt;! . T'cyion is now ripe for an early decision by His Majesty’s Government ii t le one hand it may be argued that the immediate emergency which the Ilkhani's oiiei was designed to meet has passed away with the defeat of the Kashin's and the no great hkcldi'ood of a r I ‘'‘'T' 3 ' sk ^ ion ia Persia; and thaf there seems woflThe essemiVfo uf \ n, n , COIlll,tlons ln '’Inch Bakhtiari military assistance RiHes in the Shiraz area (thoughTess' un’Lonnil'ufu!'™'one time beheved^n oASeXtsS zX^T^ff t0 i further -P~nts withPeSlir of committing successes over the Kuhgelu (to which our loan of a' mountain gun ^ 0 , ^1 krgoS o» sir C t'' : the Minister himself, in a telegram dated the 19th July P !' lllCll)le 1 h Y is to pay local leaders to nse their followers” - i 7 the only way to employ local forces llkhani and libegi have a strong party with them &gt; ^ ,'i * f iat&gt; according to his information, the provided the proposals go throuo-h the Khans are m-emlvlT 0 ^ no L '^ eet to the proposals, and that,, with the Russian troops in Ispahan. e&lt; ’ So on ^ as we ^’ish it, to work in harmonycontributed) lias not only put the tribe on very good terms with themselves, but has had an excellent effect upon our own relations with the Khans. The Vice-Consul at Ahwaz declares thaUhe Bakhtiari leaders “are with us to the last man and have the tube at their hack. Captain Wilson, while he takes a more sober view of the potential vaHe of Bakhtiari military co-operation, agrees that the Khans “are evidently very pleased with themselves and ready for anything.’’ Analogies drawn from the bonlh leisia Bines cannot be pressed too far. The South Persia Rifles are popular!} regarded in Persia as a foreign organisation imposed upon the Persian Government against its will ; and a handle lias thus been given for an agitation which has reacted to some extent upon the loyalty of the force itself. The proposed Bakhtiari force, which will have been raised at the suggestion of the head of the tribe and will remain under his personal command, will be in an entirely different position, faking till the cncuinstances into consideration, the Department is strongly inclined to the opinion that the present opportunity ought not to be lost, and that Captain A\ ilson s proposals, which have so heavy a balance of expert opinion in their favour, should be approved by His Majesty’s Government. 7. The proposals are strongly supported by the India Office Military Department. Sir Herbert Cox writes :— “ In certain eventualities we may find that a levy force of this kind which can live on the country and move with little or no transport would be invaluable. 1 here seems little or no prospect of equally good levies being successfully raised in West Persia, and we are not likely to get as good an offer again. I think that no time should be lost in accepting it, especially as it would be largely a mounted force. In view of the excellent effect produced on the Bakhtiaris by the Mountain Artillery section which co-operated with them against the Kuhgelus, it might perhaps be possible to arrange for a section to be made available for use with the proposed levy, and this might enable a few British officers and non-commissioned officers to be attached. These should be available from Dunsterforce. In addition to the advantages of such a force as stated by the Civil Commissioner, Baghdad [see paragraph 4], it would be valuable for protecting the south-west portion of the Kasr-i- Shirin-Enzeli road, and possibly might supply detachments for service beyond it. It will be remembered that Bakhtiari detachments under one of the minor Khans served with the Turkish forces on the Kermanshah road, and were intercepted and disarmed by our troops when returning to their own country. Also, such a force would keep the Kashgais in check along the Shiraz-Ispahan road. “It must be remembered, with reference to the South Persia Rifles, that the recent trouble was wholly in the Shiraz Brigade, largely composed of men who had served in the former gendarmerie officered by Swedes, and who had previously acted against us at Shiraz. Moreover, the South Persia Rifles are composed of units with European officers, whilst the proposed levy would under their own tribal Chief who would be personally responsible for them.” J. E. S. Political Department, India Office, 9th August 1918.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x00017c_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/18/C183</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x00017c</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/18/C183</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Persia. Bakhtiari Offer of Military Assistance.'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1918/1918</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-11-02T21:01:35</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (2 folios)</extent><extent>The file consists of one report.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence for this description commences at f 153, and terminates at f 154, as it is part of a larger physical volume; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. A previous foliation sequence, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.Pagination: the volume also contains an original printed pagination sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file consists of a note, written by John Evelyn Shuckburgh, Secretary, Political Department, India Office. It concerns a recent offer of military assistance, which was reportedly made to the British Vice-Consul at Ahwaz [Edward William Charles Noel, British Vice-Consul, Ahvāz, Iran] by the Bakhtiari [Baḵtīārī] Ilkhani, Sardar Zafar. The Ilkhani is reported to have offered to place at the disposal of the British '5000 good cavalry for service against the Kashgais [Qashqais] or elsewhere'.The file goes on to state a series of concrete proposals, formulated by Captain Arnold Talbot Wilson [Civil Commissioner, Mesopotamia], following his discussions with the Vice-Consul at Ahwaz. Wilson reportedly proposes that the Ilkhani should be invited to maintain a force of 1500 men under his own command, with the objectives being to stabilise the situation in Ispahan and maintain the authority of the Ilkhani in Bakhtiari territories.Also discussed are the views of Sir Charles Murray Marling [British Minister, Tehran] (who fears that the proposal will bring about a split in the Bakhtiari tribe) and of Sir Herbert Cox [Secretary, Military Department, India Office] (who strongly supports the proposals).Shuckburgh concludes that the Political Department is strongly inclined to the opinion that Wilson's proposals should be approved by His Majesty's Government, since Sardar Zafar's offer affords the British a favourable opportunity of committing the Bakhtiari tribe to their cause.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Ambassador to Iran</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>India Office, Secretary to the Political and Secret Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>India Office, Military Secretary</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Ilkhani, Bakhtiari tribe</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>British Vice-Consul, Ahwaz</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="family"><namePart>Baḵtīārī (Tribe)</namePart></name></subject><subject><geographic>Persia</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Ispahan</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Military strategy</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x00017c#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>