<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x00029f_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-07-17T14:50:35.195Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">(pw/f^ Draft Paper. POLITICAL V ' % ). / ; kb P.Z. 5383/36. ' ^7/ Department. © DRAFT Lt.Colonel P.Q. Loch, C.I.E., H.B.M. Consulate-General, Bushire. T2- LETTER. 19 AUG 1936 1^ D.O. to Forei D.O. from ” Office of Is t July. ” ' 25th ” / / ' 15 ' with enclosures. 2 u auu m ^ENCLOSURE IN WEEKLY LtuER 35 2 7 AUG 1936 FROM SECRETARY, POLITICAL AND . “intT DEnj»*SL |&lt;v. ^ ^ ttil Jr A jfa h- ' WKiAilij La//** ^ ^ M-cc^huJ- f x f fc'Cji. rx^^' 4 ^ My dear Loch, Will you please refer to the Resident’s official letter of the 3oth May, No.1119 about the action to be taken in the event of a slave manumitted in the Gulf being subsequently seized in Saudi Arabia and again reduced to slavery. I now forward for your . information a copy of correspondence noted in the margin which explains the attitude of the Foreign Offtce. As regards paragraph 2 of Sterndale Bennett’s letter, the arrangement is, of course, that when Ibn Saud introduces his new Slavery Regulations, His Majesty’s Government will (by means of an exchange of notes) renounce the right of manumission which they at present exercise at the Legation under the letters exchanged at the time of the Oje v Treaty of Jedda. f understand that final drafts of the Regulations and exchange of notes are at jresent under lU' consideration and^it is hoped to get to the stage of promulgation within the next few months. We shall of course receive, and let you have, copies of the documents when they are finally agreed with the Saudi Government. It/It seems clear that in any case of this kind which occurs after the promulgation of the new Regulations, i will he possible to make representations to tiie Saudi Government unlooa- it*oan trc nhown thef^ the S^ufU-s -Lr^ hnTrn n n T nn&lt; i» breach of idt) ) the Regulations. Each case will 4 accordingly have to be treated as it arises. It is, however, to be hoped that a** slaves manumitted at Bahrein will not A be foolish enough to return to the mainland, and you might possibly consid er lAt'f'KShV'Ol the desirability of upging this upon them at the time of manumission. I am sending a copy of this lett to Garoe and Hickinbotham. Yours sincerely. er ^Sgd.) M. J. CLAUSON© U (E 4072/599/25) FOREIGN OFFICE, S.W.l 25th July, 1936 ,R My dear Clauson, / Will you please refer to your letter No. P.^4375/36 of July 1st to Brenan about the action to he taken in the event of a slave manumitted in the Gulf being subsequently seized in Saudi Arabia and again reduced to slavery. As regards the point raised in paragraph 6 of Fowle*s letter of May 30th we should in present circum stances certainly be inclined to take up a question of this sort on the basis of Article 7 of the Treaty of Jedda. When the new Saudi regulations are published we shall probably, I suppose, if any breach of them comes to our notice, draw the attention of the Saudi Government to it in some way. But our action will obviously have to be considered, if and when a case arises, in the light of all the circumstances existing at the time. Yours sincerely. 0 7JUU936 O c Clauson, Esq, J.r* P.Z.4»7S/3«. India Oi'fiGG, Whiteiiiil | S • ^ «X 1st July, 1936a Will you please refer to the letter from the Political resident in the Persian Gulf dated the 30th Hay Wo. 1119 of 1936, a copy of v*i ich was forwarded to the foreign Office under India Office printed letter of P4th June P.Z.4375/36, regarding the action to be taken in the event of a slave i^anuraitted in the Gulf bein ; subsequently seized in Saudi Arabia a *d again reduced to si &gt;t very. Could you let me know what you think we should reply on the questions asked in paragraph 6 of Jowle^ letter. Is the answer to the first question Bo and to the second Yes ? Yours slnoepotp. (Sgd.) M. J. CLAUSON T• Y.Brenan ..oi •, Of fu .UQi* 0FFIG&amp;5 . / To Sir, ^y&lt;-\ (/ ill ^ No • of 10S6• -24 • '' • S'! yt) ' 4 3 / j c British Besidency &amp; Consulate-General, Bushire, the May 1936 ♦ ^o(C- From - The Hon’ble Lieut. -Colonel T.C.Fowle, C.B.E., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, His Majesty’s Secretary of State for Jndia, The India Office, London. Subject: Slavery. &amp; ff ' yU3- (4 I have the honour to report the following incident. 2. A certain slave, one ’Abdullah bin Sai’d,a Sa’udi subject - born in Najd, came to Bahrain from Dammam in Hasa about 3 months ago and applied to Colonel Loch for manumis sion. Since ’Abdullah was a foreign subject Colonel Loch referred the case to me, recommending manumission, which I Airhhorised. 3 # 1 Abdullah was accordingly manumitted, but towards the end of last month was foolish enough to pay a visit to Hasa as one of the crew of a dhow plying to Lakhbar (close to Dammam)• He landed to collect wood, and was forcibly seized in the presence of the local Mudir by relatives of his former master, one Saleh bin Ahmed Dosiri of the Dawasir tribe, the dhow returning to Bahrain without him. 4. Colonel Loch reported this occurrence, but informed me shortly afterwards that ’Abdullah had been released and had returned to Bahrain. The cause of ’Abdullah’s release was apparently that some one in Bahrain had written to the Dawasir in Dammam that a complaint had been made, and the Dawasir feared reprisals: they have property in, and frequently visit, Bahrain.- 2 - 5. The matter has thus ended satisfactorily, but in the event of similar cases arising in the future, and the manumitted slave not being returned, it may be worth while to consider what action - if any - we can take. Under Article 7 of the Treaty of Jedda Ibn Saud promised to co-operate by all means at his disposal with His Majesty’s Government in the suppression of the Slave Trade, and in his letter of May 19th Sir Gilbert Clayton informed Ibn Saud that His Majesty’s Government could not renounce the right of manumission of slaves by their Consular Officers: presumably from the context those Officers in Saudi Arabia. 6. Whether in order to obtain the release of a manumitted slave we couldjbase our representation on Article 7 of the Jedda Treaty, or whether we should adopt the attitude that if a Saudi manumitted slave is foolish enough to return to Saudi Arabia he should be left to take the consequences, are questions which His Majesty’s Government may like to consider and give a ruling on. I am sending copies of this letter to the Government of India, His Majesty’s Minister at Jedda and the Political Agent at Bahrain. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient humble servant, c.- Lieut .-Colonel. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x00029f_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/4095</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x00029f</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/4095</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 34/8 'Slavery and Slave Trade: Persian Gulf manumissions: Liability of manumitted Saudi subjects to be reduced to slaves again on return to Saudi Arabia'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1936/1936</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-03-28T09:47:18</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (5 folios)</extent><extent>The file is arranged in chronological order from the back to the front.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 7; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Correspondence between officials at the India Office and Foreign Office concerning what action might be taken if manumitted slaves from Saudi Arabia are detained upon their return to their country. The question is discussed following a report of such a case by Lieutenant-Colonel Trenchard Craven William Fowle, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf (folios 6-7).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author; correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x00029f#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>