<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0002fe_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T22:54:28.102Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">(!) HO.&lt;$Jvlo&gt;&gt; 4/4 POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN, | JC, August, 1945 August To The Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Rvesident in the Persian ‘^ulf, Bushire # MEuiORAKDUi4 S«» I enclose herewith, in duplicate, the budget estiiaates for this Agency for the year 1946-47. • for Political Agent,POi-mCAL ACi^i'ICY. BitKttAIH t Statement of details of provision proposed for pay of for the year 1946-47* Officers EstablishmentsPQLmOttL liii&amp;UilU ' Officers Statement of details of provision proposed for pay of for the year 1946-47* tabli shiu en t s^ ■ 0 . 3 . 4 '$ -ei/i a 1 The Sectary to th« Hon ’ble the Politic*! Hesii$at ia the 'PersUu Oalf'Jpre 3 «*ts his conaplimeats to 1) The Political Agent, Muscat 2) The Political Agent, Bahrain **' 3) The Political Agent, Kuwait 4) His Majesty*s Consul, Kerman 5) His Majesty*s Consul, Khorramshahr 6) His Majesty*s Consul, Bandar Abbas 7) His Majesty*s Consul, Shiraz 8) His Majesty*s Consul Ahwaz, aal is lirnt &gt;i ;t &gt; tn unit t) hin i opy of th» intiriBrntioa? 1 &lt;j ^ u Ln^Bt(s ) 4 with the remark that increased provision allowed under fixed and contract grants for the reason that it has been necessitated mainly by the conditions created by war is of a temporary nature. British Residency and Cousulftt©--G«nerftl BUSH I lit. the 10th j 1]ne( 1946. Ueferance to priviou* correspondence: • • • • Desc ip (inn * of Endow t 1 r. Name and Date. Subject. Copy of relevant extract from the Budget Estimates for 1946—1947..® n( mM . s--' £5-5 y Telegram Kn Clair. From political Hesident, Baiirain. Xo Hi a lianas ty f s Consul, Kerman. His Majesty^ Consul, Khoriamshahr* His Majesty's Consul, Ahwaz. His Majesty's Consul, Shiraz. Political Agent, Kuwait. Copy by hand to political Agent, Bahrain. No. A/H52. Dated the 7th October, 1946. Please telegraph urgently figures of expenditure f or * (a) first six months and (b) anticipated expenditure for remaining six months of current financial year. REPGUGOVERNMENT OF INDIA, Department, EXPRESS LETTER [N.D *—This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] From Political, Bahrain* To The* Secretary to the Hon , ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain* No. _ 4 / 4 Dated jgth October 193 46. Anticipated expenditure for remaining six months of current financial year as follows C-Bahrain * 1. Pay of Officers. Ss. 27320-0-0 2* Pay of Establishment Es. 11960-0-0 3. Sumptuary allowance. Ks. 1200-0-0 4. Compensatory allowance Es. 300-0-0 5* House rent Rs. 1930-0-0 6* Travelling allowance Es. 5000-0-0 7. Dearness allowance Es. 6270-0-0 8. War allowance Rs. 1580-0-0 9. Secret Service Expd. Rs. 125-0-0 10. Launch Grant Rs. 4000-0-0 11. Central Contract Grant Es. 1200-0-0 12. P A T.Charges Es. 6000-0-0 13. Office Allowance Es. 13000-0-0 14 Maintenance of A.C.Unit. Rs. 1200-0-0 15. Rents, liates A Taxes Rs. 1620-0-0 16. Passage contribution Total Rs. nil. 82695-0-0 B-Dubai Hospital 1. Pay of Establishment. Es. 2110-0-0 2. Travelling allowance. Ks. 1000-0-0 3. Dearness allowance Rs. 1100-0-0 4. Hospital contingencies A medical equipment. Rs. 1100-0-0 Rs. 5310-0-6 S. 6. MFP—SOI 6&amp;P—(M-820&gt;—23-7-36—300,000. P.T.ONO. 3^9? To 4/4 POLITICAL AGKNCY, -BAHRAIN, /1 ^Novemb er, 1946• The Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain. 4£i&lt;iORANDtl.l :- I enclose herewith the statement of anticipated excesses and savings in the budget grants of this Agency for the year 1946-47.To POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN, November, 1946. The Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain. MEndORANDUhl : - Reference Agency memorandum No.3679-4/4, dated the llth November 1946 forwarding statement of anticipated excesses and savings in the budget grants of this Agency for the year 1946-47. 2 * The reasons for excesses under C3(5)-Other Charges are briefly as under:- Launch Grant In view of developments in Qatar and on the True Lai Coast it is certain that the Agency launch will have to be used far more extensively for touring than heretofore, and it has therefore been found necessary to protide auxiliary sails and to t instal a proper galley, and lavatory accommodation for the Political Agent in the launch. The excess allotment is required to meet the cost of these items and also for the provision and installation of new bilge pumps in place of the old pumps which are worn out. Central Contract Grant The excess allotment is required to meet the cost of painting, whitewashing, and petty repairs to the Agency building. Office Allowance . The additional allotment is required to cover the cost of winter liveries for the Agency menial Establishment. The only cloth available last year was of such poor quality that the uniforms made of it have worn too badly to last a second year. They therefore need replacement now. Money is also required to meet electricity charges and the cost of the replacement of worn out electric fittings and rewiring in the Agency. s I* is also reauested that provision be made for payment of Rs. 5,950/- being the cost of the new Ford pick-up for the Truclal Coast 5 vide ray memorandum No. 3561-17/21 dated the 6th November, 1946. \ y v?- fo? Political Agent, Bahrain.Telegram From To tf.O. G. T.C. HjUlHb Political Resident, Bahrain. Political Agent, Kuwait, Political Agent, Bahrain (by Post) Political Agent, Muscat, H. M. Consul, Bushire, H.M. Consul, Kerman, H.M. Consul, Bandar Abbas, H.M. Consul, Khorramshahr, No* 1293 Dated the 11th Noymber, 1946. Please forward urgently your detailed statement of anticipated excesses and savings (giving full reasons) during current financial year. - REPGU - ML.GOVERNalENT OP INDIA, POL ITICAL A QKK CT, (A'- B ,—This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE^ sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue uve of the wires, but intefided to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] From Repgu, Bahrain. No. 5^7 -4/4 Dotted’ 5th February 19347. Flricti financial rovier . Following are excesses C-3 Allowances, hoi*.etc. Office Allowance. Passage Contribution Following are sayi?:gs:- C-l- Fay of Officers. C-2 Pay of iSstablishnent, P k T. Charges. K-3 Allowances, Ron.etc. Detailed statement follows. Ss. 5070/- ks. 4000/- fi. 2350/- is. 3575/* 900/- Lis. 4000/* Rs. 290/* - Political- 'Ihe issue of the above has been authorised. s. 6. MFP—601 H&amp;P—(M-HUO) Asstt. Political Agent, Bahrain. M-820)—23-7-36—300.000.J I ■ NO. - 4/4 POLITICAL AGriiNCT, BAHRAIN, February, 1947. 1 m To The Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain. MMORANDUU:- I- Refererce Agency express letter No. 399-4/4, dated the 5th February 1947. 2. I enclose herewith the statement of final excesses and savings in the budget grants of this Agency for the year 1946-47. I i&lt;A ^for Political Agent, Bahrain. Lum Cf mA-C-/vs, -o?-? cr/- (o ^ / ^ This represents our budget grants sanctioned by Bushire^ Compared with our budget estimates xfcxp for 46- 47, at pages 2 and 6^ The following observations are mad Bushire have sanctioned in full the amounts that we have asked under the various heads except under the head Dearness allce to permanent establishment. The sanctioned grar^ ^-mder this head is less than what we asked for by Rs.070$/-; presumably Bushire anticipate a reduction in D.A. after August up to which the present sanction lasts. But,for the war establishment they have sanctioned grant to cover the total D.A. that we asked for for the whole finan cial year. The abolition of the post of Interpreter/has been taken into account by Bushire in giving the sanction under the War mscablishment expenditure. Under Office allowance Bushire have sanctioned Rs.22,000/- while we askejd for Rs.20,000/- only; but they have remarked in the p.u.c. that 1 the increased.provision allowed under fixed and contract grants for the reason that it has been necessitated mainly by the conditions created by war is of a temporary nature*. For information,a statement is given below show ing the provisions under Fixed and Contract Grants for thd current financial year compared with the grants and expendi ture for the last year:- -r~j Bub-head. Grants asked for *46-47 t Sanctioned for 46-47 Initial grant for 46-46 Final grant for 45-46 Actual expenditure; for 45-46. Office allce. 20,000 22,000 20,000 ^ 28,500 • i 28,500 Launch Grant. 9,000 9,000 K 9,000 14,300 14,150 C • C • G. 1,600 1,600 1,600 5,590 4,750 &gt; i 7 The grants have been noted in the respective books. For information. P.A. \Ji ijIv. 1- J^\ v O v C 'Vv\ YCca n \jC C v'o VAAA OnWv* V-Xa , t)^ . A ^ / / . I/Ua^* J M OJ VvA &gt;-caaa“ ^7, 7?/o 4/t —</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0002fe_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1127</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0002fe</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1127</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 4/4 VIII Budget Estimates of Political Agency for the year 1946-47.'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1945/1947</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-09-17T12:01:34</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (34 folios)</extent><extent>The correspondence is arranged in chronological order from the front to the rear of the file, and terminates with a set of notes at folios 31-34. Circled serial numbers in ink and crayon, which occur throughout the file (red for incoming, blue/black for outgoing correspondence), refer to entries in the notes.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1 and terminates at the inside back cover with 36; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is also present in parallel between ff 2-26; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled, and are located in the same position as the main sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains the statement of budget estimates for the Political Agency, Bahrain for the financial year 1946-47, and associated financial statements and correspondence for the same period.The correspondence is between staff of the Political Agency, Bahrain, and the Political Residency in the Persian Gulf.The budget estimates cover expenditure on pay of officers; pay of establishment; allowances, honoraria etc.; secret expenditure; other charges; and the Dubai Hospital Establishment. Also included are detailed pay statements for officers and establishment; statements of 'K-Special War Charges'; statements of excesses and savings; and statements of modifications in the budget estimates.The correspondence consists of covering letters, and correspondence concerning particular items of expenditure, including an explanation of increased expenditure on the Agency launch (folio 20).The date range gives the covering dates of the principal items of correspondence; the earliest and latest dated additions to the file are entries in the notes dated 22 August 1945 and 11 May 1947 respectively.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Expenditure</topic></subject><subject><topic>Budgets</topic></subject><subject><topic>Food prices</topic></subject><subject><topic>Funds</topic></subject><subject><topic>Fees</topic></subject><subject><topic>Motor vehicles</topic></subject><subject><topic>Cost of living</topic></subject><subject><topic>Air force personnel</topic></subject><subject><topic>Army</topic></subject><subject><topic>Travel allowances</topic></subject><subject><topic>Coffee</topic></subject><subject><topic>Hospitality</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0002fe#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>