<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100048656966.0x000001_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-19T20:10:02.587Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">CONFIDENTIAL. Telegram No. 2270-E.A., dated the 27th September 1913. From—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department, Simla, To— Lieutenant-Colonel Sir P. Z. Cox, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Your telegram* dated September 19th, 1605. Director, Royal Indian Marine ♦Serial No 186 cannotf spare “Elephanta” beyond 30th f Enclosures of°Seriai No. 190. September. It is required for urgent work at Bombay where there are no tugs for hire. He considers that a whole-time steamer is no longer essential at Little Quoin and that Homer’s assertion that one is required is due to overstrain. “ Minto ”, armed launch or launches from Bunder Abbas and Bahrain, can be used by arrangement to do all that is required while during months of October, Novem ber and December when the weather is more favourable the sailing dhows which are used fot the conveyance of stores could manoeuvre themselves alongside without assistance of steamer. Further Gulf steamers could be warned to keep a look-out on Little Quoin. Under the circumstances it is impossible to direct retention of “ Elephanta ” at Quoin. Please ascertain and report what Homer’s definite re quirements are in detail to enable Director, Royal Indian Marine, to arrange for such assistance by steam vessel as may be required. In the meantime it is hoped that local arrangement can be made to prevent stoppage of work. From—The Secretary to the Government of India, Marine Department, To—The Director, Royal Indian Marine, Bombay. Your telegram^; 531 September 23rd and letter§ 6703 of the same date. Your From—The Director, Royal Indian Marine, . To—The Secretary to the Government of India, Marine Department. Reference Sir Percy Cox’s telegram 1605, 19th instant. ^ Elephanta with dummy hoppers are stopped owing to monsoon. Survey of dockyard ap proaches just completed shows five and half feet of silt since May, no other craft here can tow the hoppers, silt must be removed with all despatch or ships will not be able to enter and leave basin and docks. 30th September very latest date “ Elephanta ” can be spared. “ Minto”, “ Lawrence , armed launch or launches from Bahrein and Bunder Abbas can all be used by arrange ment to assist building. Homer has had warning to collect material needed be fore 30th September. “ Elephanta ” has been at Muskat cleaning boilers for fortnight, temporary attendance is only needed now at Little Quoin. Dredging must be continued, silt more serious than usual, probably owing to heavy rainfall. Letter posted to-day. . r . - . : No. 1323-5-M., dated the 29th September 1913. X Enclorsure I. § Enclosure II. orders to “ Elephanta ” to return to Bom bay confirmed. Enclosure I of Serial No. 190. Telegram No. 531, dated the 23rd September 1913. Serial No. 186. was lent to Persian Gulf during absence of “ Lawre'nce ” and when dredging operations €. 429F.D. 6 DEG 1913 -1..IgJilllg- «BSi 2^ Enclosure II of Serial No 190. No. 6703, dated the 23rd September 1913. From—The Director, Royal Indian Marine, To—The Secretary to the Government of India, Marme Department. With reference to my telegram* No. 531, dated 23rd September 1913, I have With rele e ^ ^ the honour to submit for your consideration ? * Enclosure I. the facts and circumstances that are re- levant to the continual use of withdrawal of the E. I. M. steam tug“ Elephanta ” from attendance at Little Quoin. When the inception of a light-house at Little Quoin was authorised it was ab- • solutely essential that a steanfvessel of some sort should be detailed to assist in the work as the island is a barren rock with no convenient landing place or means of landing stores, the former had to be manufactured by blasting away outlying rocks Wow the surface of the water before boats of any size could lay alongside It all and a platform had to be built with concrete to make any work at the water s edge possibleat all, after which cranes were erected to hoist the material up the face of the rock All this had to be done at intervals when the state of the sea ren dered landing work possible before building material to any extent could be con veyed from the dhows (in which it was stowed for transport) to the site of the light-house and dwelling quarters. . Verv little was known about the effect the winds from various points had upon the shore of Little Quoin and the whole matter was one of experiment attended wit a considerable amount of danger. It was obviously necessary that a whole-time IteX vessel should attend until some sort ot estab ishment ho.d been initiated Tnd the nature, possibilities and difficulties of the work realised and provided for. This has now been, I may say, satisfactorily accomplished. Dwelling quarters have been erected, the landing of stores made a compara tively simple matter, a condensing plant has been set up and ample supply of water tanks provided ; a sepoy guard has been attached to the island to prevent serious trouble with the coolies, signalling apparatus supplied, and building material should be quite easily landed in large quantities on days when weather permits, that should certainly provide work for 10 days or a fortnight at a time. Under these circumstances there appears to be no valid reason why a whole- time vessel costing Rs. 6,257 per mensem (including climatic allowances which I trust will be eventually sanctioned) should be allotted for the work, the expendi ture in which will, I am afraid, however carefully watched, largely exceed the esti mates of Mr. Hood, using the strictest economy, and I should certainly maintain, that a whole-time vessel at the present state of the work was an absolute waste ot money that cannot possibly be justified. That this is so may be deduced from the fact that the Elephanta has been awav from her station at Little Quoin for a fortnight to clean boilers at Muskat since the 2nd September although her Officer Commanding and Mr. Homer were warned on the 30th August that the vessel would be withdrawn at the end of Sep tember 1913. Aeain during the months of October, November and December the weather is more favourable about the locality of Little Quoin, and the sailing dhows which are used for the conveyance of stores, could manoeuvre themselves alongside the land ing places without the assistance of any steamer. Moreover, the number of calm days, as will be seen from Persian Gulf Pilot, pages 221,222 and 223, are few and far between at this time of year. Besides the above, the armed launch patrolling at Kishm is almost daily within signalling distance of the rock ; the Gulf steamers all pass within easy sig nalling distance and can be warned to keep a look out on the Little Quom. I he Bunder Abbas launch of 65 tons is only 37 miles away, and the Mmto, whose headquarters are Henjam, would, I am sure, be allowed by the Senior Naval Officer to pay occasional visits and render assistance if required. The “ Lawrence ” which is doing the duty of light-house tender until the new vessels are built, has, I am afraid, too much work to do amongst the lit and unlitr 3. buoys, combined with the Political Eesident’s particular work, to do more than pay an occasional visit. I think that Mr. Homer after the long isolation during the last 12 months and the early death of the only assistant that he has so far been provided with, has his nerves affected by the life and surroundings (I know when I met him at Tanb Is land he was suffering from insomnia), and I fancy this has something to do with his statement that an all-time steamer is essential; he might I think with advantage be ordered up to Abadan to settle with the Anglo-Persian Oil Company, about the light-house depot there, which I believe has not yet been even estimated for. Mr. Homer, I regret to say, has not communicated with me as to progress made since last April although ordered to send me a copy of his diary monthly; this I arranged with Sir P. Cox and Mr. Homer. To turn now to the dredging operations outside the Dincan and Bombay Docks and the Wet Basin, a very large amount of correspondence has passed between the Government of India and myself on the matter that need not I think be again re ferred to. But the outcome of it was that considering the great age of the dredger she must be nursed as carefully as possible in order to prevent a serious breakdown, and that the most economical as well as effectual way of removing the silt was to procure two dummy hoppers and work these in conjunction with the Elephanta who could satisfactorily do the necessary towing combined with her other dock yard work. This combination of dredger, hoppers and “ Elephanta ” has proved eminently satisfactory, except that owing to the heavy swell in the harbour during south-west monsoon the hoppers become unmanageable and the dredger has to dump the mud herself. The result of this is that after the monsoon months, the silt has gained on the dredger to a varying extent anddhis year * unfortunately has been of so serious a nature as to render 52 feet ' the return of the “ Elephanta ” an absolute necessity if the approaches to the dockyard are to be kept open at all. I should state here that I have no other launch to detail for the towing work even if their ordinary routine work would allow them to undertake it, as in the first place the hoppers are too heavy and unwieldy for any but a powerful tug to handle in the strong tides that exist between the dockyard and the dumping ground, and secondly the continuous traffic of all sorts of vessels in the same area would render these hoppers and any but a powerful tug that kept them well under control, a dan ger to shipping that I should not be justified in sanctioning. There are no tugs for hire in Bombay of any sort, those that are in existence being required for the work that they are kept for by the various Companies owning them. After consideration of the above features of the case, I trust that my oruers to the “ Elephanta ” to return to Bombay on the 30th instant may be confirmed, and that Mr. Homer may be directed through Sir Percy Cox to state what are his definite requirements in detail, when any assistance by steam vessel can be arranged for. Telegram No. 1670, dated the 29th September 1913. From—The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, To—The Secretary to the Government of India, in the Foreign Department, Simla. Your 2270-E. A.f I have called for detailed reasons from Homer but it may be several days before I can get reply. Mean- t Serial No. 189. w yi e i n reply to enquiry from me as to what help he could give Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf Division telegraphs as follows: Begins. Have already informed Director, Royal Indian Marine, that shortness of ships makes stationing of “ Minto ” indefinitely m the vicim y o Quoin Island most undesirable course to pursue from the point of view of blockade duties. I cannot guarantee adequate Quoin Island watch. I suggest reten ion of “ Elephanta ” until (?) when more vessels will be available. Bnds. In any case it is urgent that “ Elephanta ” should remain until Condenser is workmg on Quoin. On 26th September Homer was still awaiting boiler. If precipitate action is taken in removal of tender before an assured arrangement is arrived at for future I beg that I may be absolved from ? responsibility for any con re mps a may result. Rough weather may be expected in that part of Gulf any time afteri Lx 15th November and Bahrain launch is neither good enough sea boat nor is Native Driver in charge of her sufficiently competent for the duty. Addressed Government of India ; repeated Director, Royal Indian Marine. Telegram No. 1675, dated the 30th September 1913. From—L ieutenant-Colonel Sir P. Z. Cox, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, To—The Secretary to the Government of India, in the Foreign Department, Simla. My telegram* dated the 29th September, 1670. Following since received from * Serial No 191 Director, Royal Indian Marine to “ Ele- phanta ’ ’ telegram repeated, to me. Begins. Leave for Bombay on 30th September, leaving Little Quoin provided with necessaries as far as possible. Ends. No. 1323-6-M., dated the 1st October 1913. From—The Secretary to the Government of India, Marine Department, To—The Director, Royal Indian Marine, Bombay. Reference Sir P. Cox’s telegramf No. 1670, dated 29th September 1913, and Marine Department telegram J No. 1323-5-M., dated 29th September 1913. It is desirable that ‘ ‘ Elephanta ’ ’ should remain, if possible, until some arrangement has been made to carry out the services required. Please wire urgently what your proposals are. In the meantime, unless conditions at Bombay render recall absolutely imperative, you are authorised to delay recall. f Serial No. 191. j Serial No. 190. Telegram No. 2312-E.A., dated the 2nd October 1913. From—The Secretary to the Government of India, in the Foreign'Department, Simla , To— Lieutenant-Colonel Sir P. Z. Cox, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Please telegraph what precisely is the nature of the risks referred to in your ♦Serial No. 186. telegram, dated 19th September, No. 1605,* to which community on Little Quoin will be exposed by withdrawal of “Elephanta.” No. 556, dated the 1st October 1913. From—The Director, Royal Indian Marine, Bombay, To—The Secretary to the Government of India, Marine Department. Your 1323-6-M.,| 1st. Recall of “Elephanta” absolutely necessary to cope with t Serial No. 193. dredging work Consider occasional help from Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, also visits within signalling distance of passing British India steamers four times a week, both which I have arranged, sailing dhows for conveyance of stores, also occasional visits by “ Lawrence ” all that is necessary. Do not consider attendance of whole-time vessel now necessary. .. _ n D orTelegram No. 2329-E.A., dated the 4tli October 1913. From—The Secretary to the Government of India, in the Foreign Department, Simla, To— Lieutenant-Colonel Sir P. Z. Cox, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. My telegram§ October 2nd, No. 2312-E.A. Director, Royal Indian § Serial No. 196. Marine, telegraphs) | as follows: “Recall 11 Serial No. 197 . 0 f &lt; Elephanta ’ absolutely necessary to cope with dredging work. Consider occasional help from Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, also visits within signalling distance of passing British India steamers four times a week, both of which I have arranged, sailing dhows for conveyance of stores, also occasional visits by ‘ Lawrence J all that is necessary. Do not consider attendance of whole-time vessel now necessary.” Do arrangements satisfy require ments ? Telegram No. 1710, dated the 3rd (received 4th) October 1913. From— Lieutenant-Colonel Sir P. Z. Cox, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, T° f he Secretary to the Government of India, in the Foreign Department, Simla. Little Quoin. My telegram^ dated the 29th September, 1670. I have since If Serial No. 191 . received from Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf Divisbn, copy of letter addressed by him to Director, Royal Indian Marine, from Henjam after discussion of Quoin requirements with Officer Commanding, “ Elephanta, ” than whom obviously no one^ has better knowledge of actual needs at present. Communication entirely bears out essential need for whole-time vessel. At the same time Homer telegraphs that he posted full explanations of needs by last mail. He will require tender to (in) all December certainly andjpossibly end of January. It is also urgent that deputation of assistant asked for in my telegram* 1480, 26th * Serial No 169 August, should be expedited as Homer cannot supervise work at Tamb unless he has reliable understudy. As regards risk to community to which I referred, firstly notice too short; water condenser will not be working for fortnight; casualties from heat or accident; he has already lost 3 men; there is blasting work and other risky rock hewing work going on and large number(s) of workmen who are often difficult to manage and it is not safe to leave place without constant and assured means of communication which cannot be secured except by full-time vessel. “Elephanta” has been under constant steam for the purpose. Telegram No. M.-l, dated (and received) the'Lth October 1913. From— Lieutenant-Colonel Sir P. Z. Cox, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Muscat, To—The Secretary to the Government of India, in the Foreign Department, Simla. Your telegram 2329.f Occasional assistance from Senior Naval Officer, Per- t Serial No 198 s ^ an Division, and occasional visits of “ Lawrence ” will not mean anything that Homer can rely upon at all. Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf Division, cannot provide for regular assistance if he is to carry out arms traffic arrangements as at present in force. As regards “ Lawrence ” I have not had use of her since begin ning of May, and now she already has more than she can do to cope with my work and attendance on gas buoys which have been giving constant trouble. Mean while Homer estimates that there are 40 dhow loads of gear and material now awaiting shipment to Quoin and in a month’s time large quantity of building materials for Quoin and Tamb will require transport. If Government of India are not prepared to replace “ Elephanta,” I would suggest in order to avoid delay prejudice to light-house work is that Admiral may be asked to strike off “ Harold ” or “ Mashona ” armed launch from arms traffic work and place here whole-time on duty with Homer. Repeated Bushire.Telegram No. 1590-30-M., dated the 6 th October 1913. From—The Secretary to the Government of India, Marine Department, To The Director, Eoyal Indian Marine. Reference your 4463,{ Junfc 20th. Lantern for Jask. Have you any informa tion as to the Department which paid tor } Enclosure 2 of Serial No. 154. ,i • j • i — j o the existing lantern ? 1 l t 'V JMt- — Telegram No. 2382-E.A., dated the 10th October 1913. From—The Secretary to the Government of India, in the Foreign Department, Simla, To—L ieutenant-Colonel Sir P. Z. Cox, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. * * * • &lt; * Your telegram§ dated 26th August 1480. Government of Bombay are sending • i vn utt Fathali Ferozdin on trial for work undei Homer. He is experienced subordinate well acquainted with Gulf conditions. Gaur Narayan’s services not available. G. M. Press, Simla.—No. G. 429 F. D.—17-10-13.—H.—C.W.M.(copy) Telegram T From - Hie Secretary to the GoYerament of icffifcfcacc Bombay Public Works department, To - fhe Secretary to the Government of India, Marine department. Fo* 129-f. Dated the 27th September 1913. Yonr telegram 1254-35-M. , September 19th. Fathali Ferozdin is being sent on trial for work tinder Homer on consolidated pay Bs, 200. He is experienced subordinate well acquainted with Gulf conditions. Ho suitable man on permanent establishment available.■in mill214. No. 3045, dated Bushire, the 5th (received 13th) October 1913. From— Lieutsnant-Colonel Sir Percy Cox., K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, To—The Hon’ble Mr. J. B. Wood, C.I.E., Officiating Secretary to the Government of India, in the Foreign Department, Simla. With reference to the correspondence marginally cited, I have the honour to Resident to Foreign Department, No. 3075, forward, for favour of consideration, a copy dated the 23rd November 1912. of a further report from the Political Marine Department to Director, Royal Agent, Kuwait, on the Unsatisfactory mf Au S u»t 1913 . condition of the Kuwait buoys. 2. The Officer Commanding, R. I. M. S. “ Lawrence ” which has just returned from dock, has received no instructions for dealing with these buoys. I venture, therefore, to express the hope that the disposal of the matter may be treated as urgently as practicable. 3. I am forwarding a copy of this letter to the Director of the Royal Indian Marine for information. Enclosure to Serial No. 214. No. 357, dated Kuwait, the 28th August 1913. From— Captain. W. H. I. Shakespear, I.A., Political Agent, Kuwait, To—The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. I have the honour to invite a reference to the correspondence regarding the replacement or renewal of the Kuwait harbour buoys, ending with your Second Assistant’s endorsement No. 663, dated the 25th February 1913.2. I reported the unserviceable conditions of these buoys in my letter No. 448, dated the 7th November, and I fear that if their renewal is much further delayed, they will disappear suddenly ; when the navigation of vessels entering the port cr anchorage will be rendered seriously difficult. 3. While reverting to the subject I have the honour to suggest that if the present conical buoy to the north of Ras-al-Ajuza could be replaced by a gas-buoy, vessels would be enabled to enter the anchorage at any time even on the darkest of nights. While the fixed Red Light on the Agency Flagstaff is of considerable assistance, it does not by itself suffice to secure a safe entry to the anchorage at night when the present conical buoy cannot be readily seen. A gas-buoy in the place on the Ras-al-Ajuza conical buoy in conjunction with Lhe Agency Red Light would furnish the necessary marks for bearings for vessels to enter the inner harbour and anchorage with perfect safety. Telegram No. 2409-E. A., dated Simla, the 15th October 1913. From—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department, To Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Percy Cox, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Political Repident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Please see letters from Deputy Director-General of Stores, India Office, v gerial No 213 26th September last, and arrange for Little Quoin lantern materials being cleared within 48 hours of arrival of steamer at Henjaim\ 4 I r\a % 220 . Telegram Ko. 1323-10-M., dated Simla, the 14th October 1913. Froni The Secretary to the Government of India, Marine Department, To His Excellency the Naval Commander-in-Chief, Pulo Weh. Owing to silting of approaches Bombay Harbour, it has been imperative to recall, R. I. M. S. “ Elephanta ” from the Persian Gulf, where she has been employed on lighthouse operations. Homer considers^ replacement of “Elephanta ” by whole time vessel absolutely necessary, and in this he is supported by Sir P. Cox and Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf Division. Government of India would be glad if Your Excellency could detail either “ Harold ” or “ Mashona ” for whole-time lighthouse duty with Homer as long as exigencies of work require it, probably to end of January. Failing either of these vessels, would it be possible to spare “ Minto ” for the pur pose. Government of India would be glad if Your Excellency could see your way to help in the matter.221 . ,u, Telegram No. 1323-11-M., dated Simla, the 14th October 1913. From—The Secretary to the Government of India, Marine Department, To—The Director of the Royal Indian Marine. Reference correspondence ending your 556*, October 1st. Following received „ Q . . , T in(7 Rom Political Resident, Persian Gulf. * Enclosure of Serial No. 197. t&gt; ‘ at tvt t j .l i r\ , ^ Begins. No. M-l, dated 7th October 1913. Your telegram * * * * * with Homer. Ends. Admiral being asked whether “ Harold ”,Mashona ” or “ Minto ” could be spared until end of January for purpose. In the event of His Excellency agreeing to detail one of the vessels, please wire what would be the cost involved. Should Admiral be unable to concur, please be prepared to suggest other arrangements for whole-time vessel with cost. 223. Telegram No. 50, dated the 17th October 1913. From—His Excellency the Naval Commander-in-Chief, To-The Secretary to the Government of India, Marine Department. f Serial No. 220. house service. Ycur 1323-1of 14th October. Mashona 5 detailed for whole-time light- 224. Telegram No. 2459-E.A., dated Simla, the 21st October 1913. From-The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department, r f° Eieutenant-Colonel Sir Percy Cox KCTE pqt it&gt; in the Persian Gulf, Bushire! ’ ’ 0lltlCal ReSldent t Serial No. 200. whole-time lighthouse service. Your telegramt, dated the 7th October, M-l, “Mashona ’ detailed by Admiral for con Ho ilieCONFIDENTIAL. I ' No. 3052 , dated Bushire, the 5 th (received 13 th) October 1913 . From— Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Percy Cox, K.C I.E., C.S.I, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, To—The Officiating Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Depart ment, Simla. As I am leaving headquarters for Muscat, I have the honour, in case there may be any question on the subject during my absence, to submit copies of correspondence which has passed, vide list below, on the subject of Mr. Ho mer’s need for the assistance of a whole-time steam-tender in connection with the work proceeding at Little Quoin and Tanb Islands. Bushire Note. The above was drafted by the Resident before his departure for Muscat. L. F. BIRD WOOD, Captain, First Assistant Resident, {In the absence of the Resident). List of Enclosures. 1. Letter No. 6244 , dated 30 th August 1913 , from Director, Royal Indian Marine, Bombay, to Resident. 2 . Telegram No. 1557 , dated 12 th September 1913 , from Resident, to Mr. Homer. 3 . Telegram dated 16 th September 1913 , from Director, Royal Indian Marine, Bombay, to Resident. 4 . Telegram No. 1588 , dated 17 th September 1913 , from Resident, to Director, Royal Indian Marine, Bombay. 5 . Telegram No. 461 , dated 18 th September 1913 , from Mr. Homer, to Resident. 6 . Telegram dated 18 th September 1913 , from Director, Royal Indian Marine, Bombay, to Resident. 7 . Telegram* No. 1605 , dated 19 th September iQrS* f rom Resident, to Director, * Repeated to Government of India, Foreign Royal Indian Marine, Bombay. Department. 8 . Telegram No. 1608 , dated 19 th September 1913 , from Resident, to Mr. Homer. 9 . Telegram dated 20 th September 1913 , from Director, Royal Indian Marine, Bombay, to Resident. 10 . Telegram No. 1633 , dated 23 rd September 1913, from Resident, to Director, Royal Indian Marine, Bombay. 11 . Telegram dated 24 th September 1913 , from Director, Royal Indian Marine, Bombay, to Resident. 12 . Telegram No. 1647 , dated 25 th September I9I3&gt; from Resident, to Director, Royal Indian Marine, Bombay. 13 . Telegram dated 25 th September 1913 , from Director, Royal Indian Marine, Bombay, to Resident. 14 . Telegram No. 165.4, dated 26 th September 1913, from Resident, to the Senior Naval Officer. 15 . Telegram dated 27 th September 1913 , from the Senior Naval Officer, to Resident. 16 . Telegramf No. 2270 -E.A., dated 27 th September 1913 , from the Foreign De- . partment, to Resident. f Not reprinted. 17 . Telegram dated 27 th September 1913 , from “ Fox” to Director, Royal Indian Marine, Bombay.18. Telegram dated 28 th September 1913 , from Director, Royal Indian Marine Bombay, to “ Fox” ' 19 . Telegram No. 1669 , dated 29 th September 1913 , from Resident, to the Senior Naval Officer. •Not reprinted. 2o ' Telegram* No. 1670 , dated 29 th Sep- tember 1913 , from Resident, to Foreign. 21 . Telegram dated 29 th September 1913 from Director, Royal Indian Marine Bombay, to “Elephanta,^ Hanjam. ’ 22 . Telegram dated 30 th September 1913 , from Director, Royal Indian Marine Bombay, to Resident. ' ’ 23 . Telegram dated 30 th September 1913 , from Director, Royal Indian Marine Bombay, to the Senior Naval Officer. 24 . Telegram No. 505 , dated 2 nd October 1913 , from Mr. Homer, to Resident. 25 . Letter dated 29 th September 1913 , from the Senior Naval Officer, Haniam to Resident. J ’ 26 . Telegramt No. 2312-E.A., dated 2 nd October 1913 , from the Foreign Depart- t Not reprinted. ment, to Resident. 27 . TelegramJ No. 1710 , dated 3 rd October 1913 , from Resident, to Foreign $ Not reprinted. Department. 28 . Letter No. 475 , dated 23 rd September 1913 , from Mr. Homer, to Resident. Letter No. 6244 , dated 30 th August 1913 . From-r-The Director, Royal Indian Marine, Bombay, To—The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. I have the honour to inform you that the “ Elephanta ” will be required for work in Bombay at_end of September and her officers will be required for their ordinary duties during the trooping season. I am therefore ordering Lieutenant noiihf 3 '^’ ? ffiCer Commandirl g. t0 P'ace as much material as possiffie on Quoin before then, and 1 trust that what more is required can be done with the assistance of the vessels that are stationed in the Gulf as in the case oi lanb Island. Telegram D. T., No. I557&gt; dated 12 th September 1913 . From—The Political Resident, Bushire, To— Mr. C. J. Homer, Hanjam. “ Elenhanta^'’ m end ^ ar ' ne j WriteS that he wants to withdraw that can hi mefh September and suggests that your requirements after that can be met by vessels^ stationed in Gulf as in case of Tanb. ™ municate your views and wishes to me. Please com* Telegram, dated 16th (received 17th) September 1913. From—Director, Royal Indian Marine, Bombay, To—-The Political Resident, Bushire. Telegram No. 1588 , dated 17th September 1913 . From—The Political Resident, Bushire, To—Director, Royal Indian Marine, Bombay. reply Please^noltnn a -^ ^th. I wired Homer, and await his reply. Please postpone decision pending receipt of it. €Telegram No. 461 , dated (and received) 18th September 1913. From—M r. C. J. Homer, Hanjam, To—The Political Resident, Bushire. Your 1557. Impossible continue work on Quoin without whole-time services of steam tender; if this cannot be granted request that work on Quoin be shut down. Telegram dated 18 th (received 19 th) September 1913 . From—Director, Royal Indian Marine, Bombay, To—The Political Resident, Bushire. Your telegram dated 17th September No. 1588. Owing to “ Elephanta ” being urgently required for dredging operations regret must recall her end of September. Telegram No. 1608 , dated 19 th September 1913 . p rom —The Political Resident, Bushire, To— Mr. C. J. Homer, Hanjam. Your 461. Have sent following to Director, Royal Indian Marine and Government of India. Begins :— * * (same as enclosure No. 7) * * * Ends. Telegram &gt; dated (and received) 20th September 1913 . From—Director, Royal Indian Marine, Bombay, To—The Political Resident, Bushire. Your telegram dated 19th September No. 1605. ' Elephanta has been away from Quoin for I think 14 days this month after my warning Homer that she had to leave station 30th September. No diary from Homer has been received since March last and I have been without any information regarding progress of work; now that distilling plant is at Quoin whole-time attendance does not appear necessary. Have informed Government of India of urgent necessity of return of “ Elephanta;' and expense of hire of substitute would have to be specially sanctioned as buildings are much outside estimates. Telegram No. 1633 , dated 23 rd September 1913. From—The Political Resident, Bushire, To—Director, Royal Indian Marine, Bombay. Your telegram of 20th. During ' Elephanta’s ” absence the British India Steam Navigation Company were good enough at my particular request to instruct their commanders to steer close enough to Quoin to see Homer s signals in case of emergency. Fortunately none arose, but Homer was a good deal hampered by inability to communicate for 15 days. The reason for cessation of his Diaries is that he has, been too constantly occupied to indulge in them. The position is that we have got an excellent man pluckily carrying out a work which is full of difficulty and anxiety. A very little more worry due to misdirected economy would probably bring about a general breakdown and it seems to be our duty to see that he gets his reasonable requirements,wmm &amp; Telegram dated 2 ^th (received 25 th) September 1913 . From—Director, Royal Indian Marine, Bombay, To—The Political Resident, Bushire. Your telegram dated 23rd, No. 1633. Please inform me how far construc tion Quoin Lighthouse has progressed. Your reference to Homer’s health sug gests his visiting Abadan to confer with Oil Company about Lighthouse de-p6t, as regards which I have had no information since I saw you at Bushire. Telegram No. 1647 , dated 25 th September 1913 . From—The Political Resident, Bushire, To—Director, Royal Indian Marine, Bombay. Your telegram of 20th and 24th. Regarding work at Quoin and prepara tion Abadan plans, your office has details of progress up to 16th July —vide my letter 2395 of 27th July. I visited Quoin a fortnight later and found same works proceeding. Ship bringing lighthouse stools is now in Gulf and should have reached Quoin and superstructure was to leave London about 15th September. As you know the mechanic sent out by Messrs. Chance died in August from effects of heat and the Assistant from Burmah whom I again pressed for on Homer’s behalf on 26th August has not yet been deputed. Homer knows he has to go to Abadan as soon as possible, but until he gets responsible Assistant on whom he can rely I do not see how he can leave Quoin. But I am asking him to telegraph actual state of work and immediate plans and will communicate again on receipt. His health is good so far as I know. Telegram dated (and received) 25 th September 1913 . From—Director, Royal Indian Marine, Bombay, To—The Political Resident, Bushire. Your telegram dated 23rd September No. 1633. “ Elephanta ” was only necessary for inception of work at Quoin ; cannot see that she is still required. Cannot get on without her at Bombay. Can you arrange with Senior Naval Officer for necessary visit and towage to Quoin; I cannot take action as I am not informed of requirements. Telegram No. 1654 , dated 26 th September 1913 . From—The Political Resident, Bushire, To—Senior Naval Officer, Radio, Jask. Director, Royal Indian Marine, requires “ Elephanta ” and in spite of my advice to the contrary is not willing to replace her. Supposing l cannot induce Government to supply whole-time tender for lighthouse work, what, if anything, could you arrange for periodical visit and towage of lighter between Hanjam and Quoin. Telegram dated (and received) 27 th September 1913 . From—Senior Naval Officer, Radio, u Fox ”, To—The Political Resident, Bushire. Your telegram of yesterday. Have already informed Director, Royal Indian Marine, that a shortness of ships makes stationing of “ Minto ” indefinitely in vicinity of Quoin Island a most undesirable course to pursue from point of view of blockade duties. I cannot guarantee adequate Quoin Island watch. I suggest retention of “ Elephanta ” until middle of November when more vessels will be available.Telegram dated 27 th (received 28 th) September 1913 . From—“ Fox, 31 Radio, Jask, To—The Political Resident, Bushire. (Addressed Director, Royal Indian Marine.) Please state probable date on which a vessel to attend occasionally on Quoin work could be dispensed with. It would be possible under prevailing conditions to arrange this duty to be carried out until 20th October but not later. Addressed Director, Royal Indian Marine, repeated Resident. Telegram dated (and received) 28 th September 1913 . From—Director, Royal Indian Marine, Bombay, To—“ Fox, ” Radio, Jask. (Repeated Resident, Bushire.) Mail steamers passing Quoin Island on certain days according' to British India Steamship Company’s programme; if visiting vessels could be within^ sig nalling distance on some of other days of the week as convenient and also signal to Hanjam periodically to ascertain if any stores are awaiting conveyance to Quoin and (group undecypherable) is required (group undecypherable) (do) es not anticipate stores except provisioning. Addressed Fox, repeated Resident. Telegram No. 1669 , dated 29 th September 1913 . From—The Political Resident, Bushire, To—Senior Naval Officer, Radio, “ Jask Your telegram of 27th. The work at Quoin will be going on for the next three months and I do not see how Homer is going to carry on without pretty constant communication with Hanjam during that time. I have asked him to telegraph his detailed requirements and reasons Telegram dated (and received) 29 th September 1913 . From—Director, Royal Indian Marine, Bombay, To—“ Elephanta, ” Hanjam. (Repeated Resident, Bushire.) My 6245. Leave for Bombay on thirtieth September leaving Little Quoin provided with necessaries as far as possible. Addressed “ Elephanta ”, repeated Resident, Persian Gulf. Telegram dated (and received) 30 th September 1913 . From—Director; Royal Indian Marine, Bombay, To—The Political Resident, Bushire. Your telegram No. 1670, dated 29th September. Continual attendance of R. 1 . M. S. “ Minto ” or armed launch not necessary; R. I. M. S. Elephanta has been detached for fortnight before condenser arrived at Quoin. Weathers now getting fine and cooler. Your special request • • • • • • officers to receive extra pay as lighthouse ten( ^ eT ’&gt; t ^ ls . un e / C0 ^ a _* i : t order to Pet it R I M S “ Lawrence ” should do work such as occasional vis Quoin!° ^Notice'of withdrawal of R. L M. S. &lt;; Elephanta” was given m my letter dated 30th August last No. 6244. Action 18 n0 , * r)er u aDS Naval Officer, Persian Gulf Division, wires can assist till 20th 0 «°ber , pe P R.l.M.S. “ Lawrence’’can do what is necessary between that and oth November. R. I. M. S. “Elephanta” leaves today. Conductor, laj , reports boiler landed on Quoin 24th September. C8;FD* Telegram dated (and received) 30 th September 1913 . From—The Director, Royal Indian Marine, Bombay, To—The Political Resident, Bushire. (Addressed Senior Naval Officer.) Government of India have approved withdrawal of “ Elephanta ” 30th Sep tember. Homer has sufficient building material for some days. Dhows should in fine weather be able to convey further supplies of materials. Addressed Senior Naval Officer, repeated Resident. Telegram No. 505 , dated (and received) 2 nd October 1913 . From— Mr. C. J. Homer, Hanjam, To—The Political Resident, Bushire. Your 1648. Am in perfect agreement with your reply to Director, Royal Indian Marine. Drawings of Abadan Depot will be completed by end October ; most of them ready now with exception buoy shed and shipway—please see my letter No. 474, dated 20th instant to Commander “ Lawrence ” asking for certain information from Oil Company. Lighthouse site levelled and foundation work commenced, hope complete foundation by end October. Dressing of cliff face construction boat harbour and landing, collection material permanent buildings in hand. Am busy on surveys and estimates for lighthouses called for by India. Impossible proceed Abadan till after October unless work here is to be stopped and workmen sent away. Dated 29 th September 1913 . From—The Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf Division, H. M. S. Fox, ” Han jam, To—The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. I have the honour to enclose, for your information, a copy of a lengthy communication made to the Director, Royal Indian Marine, on the subject of the untimely withdrawal of “ Elephanta ” from her present duties as Lighthouse attending vessel. No. 1 - 118 , dated 29 th September 1913 . From—The Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf Division, H. M. S. “ Fox, ” Hanjam, To—The Director, Royal Indian Marine, Bombay. In amplification of my several wires of the last three days and especially that despatched this evening (September 29th) I beg to make the following observa tions on your proposed withdrawal of “ Elephanta ” and on the state of progress at, and requirements generally of Quoin Lighthouse. 2. The “ Elephanta ” arrived at Hanjam from Quoin this evening, and the following information is the outcome of an interview with her Captain which took place at my request before “ Fox ” left Hanjam at 9 P.M. 3. I wish to state at the outset that the facts below mentioned have been elicited as a result of direct answers to my direct questions, and that the Cap tain of “ Elephanta ” is in no way responsible for some perhaps apparently unnecessary delay in carrying out his duties which to my knowledge he has performed with zeal and to the utmost of his ability. (1) The transport facilities of Hanjam are very meagre ; the Contractor (Gelladari) is most inefficient and the number of dhows available is totally inadequate. I may mention privately that his replacement by some business like and efficient Contractor is under my urgent consideration, and will I hope be shortly effected.(2) Apart from provisions a mass of building and other material, most of which still remains to be embarked \ox Quoin includes 120 tons or more of san (pending delivery at Quoin, work has been stopped). Two-six ton cranes (lying on shore at Hanjam). A large quantity of stores at Karachi. 6.000 bricks and a^quantity of firewood from Bundar Abbas. 20 tons of coal (lying on shore at Hanjam). A quantity of “ hutting ” material from Lingah. 10.000 rupees from Masqat. fV) The embarkation of all these stores is far from half the battle which chiefly consists in overcoming the difficulties of delivery at points wiU give some idea of these difficulties (due to sea, and wind and weather) which are not likely to decrease as winter approaches : («) (*) Sea is usually rough with strong wind while the tide runs from 4 to 6 knots at times. Normal rate of discharge of cargo at Quoin can only take place about one day in a fortnight. On other days it maj; be possible to work cargo with difficulty for a few hours during the day. It is usually impossible to communicate (as regards disembarkation of stores, etc.), and sometimes for four days consecutively. Of The condensing plant of Quoin is not likely to be in working order 4 forafortnightorso, possibly more, therefore water has to be frequen y taken to vicinity of Quoin on the chance of delivery proving possible. (5) It is undesirable to accumulate telegrams either to or from Quoin. (6) Occasional attendance of a vessel on Tanb Lighthouse is still required —this duty is being carried out by “ Elephanta. ( 7 ) It will be clear from the foregoing that the duties of the attending vessel are by no means a sinecure. lf “f ^° st be in const ant daily, or reasonable period, say before ready immediately to seize any at most 48 hourly attendance in order to be r a X dlsembark . opportunity of however short duration of getti g » f &amp; Aua U st the “ Ele- ation. I will only mention here that during the month 0 f AV&gt; s t, the phanta-s ” duties of attendance on Q^eXee Tavs she onk Proceeded to fn for every day excepting three, and on these three days sne y p anchorage for the purpose of coaling and effecti g p (8) (a) As regards the most suitable nature of vessel for the work required, the “ Elephanta ” is undoubtedly the best. (h \A lame vessel of the size of “ Minto” of larger cannot safely remain in clise vtcinhf; whilst anchorage (with such bottom) is out of the question; also her steamboats are two small for either towage purposes or even y in the sea and tides usually obtaining. (c) An armed launch is more or less suitable as regards size, but is u way self-contained and has_to return for water ree 1 wou ] d entirely phanta ” ; added to which is the obvious fac “ ha V he npr y Der f ormance of remove her from her proper sphere of operations or r J ers which she has been armed and pieced temporarily under my 0 d . 4. In view of the foregoing regrettably lengthy remarks, I trust^that ^he situation will now assume in your eyes a somew ^ recent date were which is apparently assumed therein when p j 0 b v iously most desirable despatched, and that you may still find it possible-it is obviously —to retain “ Elephanta ” in her present duties.5. A copy of this letter is being forwarded, for information, to Commander- in-Chief, and to the Political Resident, Bushire. No. 475, dated 23rd September 1913. From— Mr. C. J. Homer, Officer in Charge, Persian Gulf, Lighthouse Works, Little Quoin, To—-The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. With reference to my telegram No. 461, dated 17th instant I have the honour to report in detail my reasons for stating that the work here cannot be carried out without the services of a steam tender. 1. I am not in communicationwith the mainland and cannot make my requirements known at will. 2. The weather off the Quoin is most uncertain and tides treacherous. No country boat will willingly attempt to make the island without the aid of a steam tender, nor will they remain at anchor off the island after sunset. The wind often blows here for days together from one direction, as it has been doing recently from the southward, and communication by means of country boats between Hanjam and this island would under these conditions be very slow and costly and the work would take months to complete. 3. There is no shelter for boats when it blows hard, as it often does here, and no matter what the direction of the wind, the smallness of the island com bined with its rounded shape causes the seas to sweep round to the side which in a larger and differently shaped island, would be the sheltered side. In these conditions boats cannot remain at anchor off the island, and it may happen that a boat or boats anchored off the island laden with stores on experiencing bad weather, which generally comes up very suddenly and without previous warning, would have to leave immediately without being able to discharge the stores, and be driven out to sea, taking days or perhaps weeks to return. Or if they can get under shelter on either mainland, the Arab boatman when lying in a snug harbour will be in no hurry to leave it. The entire area of the island is barely 3 acres in extent. On this area are resident at present nearly 190 souls, w r ho have to be kept provided with food, fuel and water all of which have to be brought to the island in country boats. In the event of any serious illness, or perhaps an epidemic, arising it may be days or even weeks before assistance could be obtained, and for this reason if no other, the regular services of a steam vessel are absolutely essential. There are large quantities of building material to be landed both at Tanb and on this Island in the near future and there are also all the lighthouse parts k°‘u ,e an( ^^ very soon.^ I hope also very shortly to have the construction of ui dings at Tanb and Quoin in hand simultaneously and must have means of rapid transport between the two places. The arrival of the condensing plant will remove my anxiety about the water supp y on Quoin but a constant supply of coal will have to be landed for work ing the plant. My accounts and returns to the Public Works Department have to be sub mitted regularly and be certain dates. Mails and money orders have to be receued and despatched. Money to meet expenses has to be drawn every month from the Masqat Treasury in time to allow of payments being made and accounts closed and submitted within the period of a fortnight, etc. . Th ere is no comparison between this island and Tanb with regard tb con- ditions or living facility of landing stores, and maintaining communication. e a er is an island of over four square miles in area affording good and ample s e ter to vessels in the worst of weather, and country craft invariably go. there or shelter as also do the armed launches when in the vicinky. For this reason was a ways able to keep country boats at the Island and use them at any time for communicating with either Lingah or Hanjam.M ^— It is true that Naval ships often visited Tanb while I was there and afforded me a certain amount of assistance in delivering and conveying telegrams, but they did not assist as regards transport work except on a very small way on two or three occasions. The “ Philomel” on her way up from - Bombay brought some explosives. The “ Odin ” supplied me on one occasion only with 3 tanks of fresh water. The “ Karanja ” or the “ Miner ” brought 6 mule saddles from Lingah and on one occasion towed one of my boats from there to Tanb. This is all that the Naval ships ever did in the way of transport for the work on Tanb. The majority of the material and also the workmen for that place were landed directly by British India Steamers or were conveyed by the country boats from Lingah chiefly, but sometimes also from Hanjam. As I have already stated, there will be a great deal of work being done in the construction of the buildings on Tanb shortly and this will he going on simultaneously with similar work and a great deal of additional work including the construction of the lighthouse on Quoin and large quantities of material will have to be landed at both places. I am firmly convinced therefore that work at these stations cannot be satisfactorily carried out, if at all, without the unin terrupted services of a steam tender. Without such aid the loss to Government will be enormous and it is impossible to say when the work will be completed. An important point to be considered is the moral effect which would result among all, hands on Quoin Island by the withdrawal of the tender. That sense of security which now exists will be destroyed and a constant feeling of anxiety will prevail which might easily lead to a panic under certain conditions. In view of the facts stated above, I trust the Director, Royal Indian Marine will reconsider his proposal to withdraw the R.I.M.S. “ Elephanta ” or if the withdrawal of this vessel is essential that another suitable vessel be sent to relieve her before she is withdrawn. tD8iFD—44—GCBP Simla&gt;Telegram No. 1590-M., dated the 20th October 1913. ^ From—The Secretary to the Government of India, Marine Department, To—The Director, Royal Indian Marine. Reference Political Resident’s letter* No. 3045, October 5 th, copy of which sent to you direct. Kindly expedite re placement Kuwait * Serial No. 214. f Serial No. 226 in Part I. cause of delay. In reported that you had made arrangements for replacement. buoys and intimate February! l ast you Dated Simla, the 22nd October 1913. From—The Deputy Secretary to the Government of India in the Marine Department, To—The Director, Royal Indian Marine. I am directed to acknowledge the receipt of your letter No. 2789, dated the 21st April 1913, in which you recommend the grant, under the usual conditions of climatic and boat-cruising allowances at the rate of Rs. 2 - 4-0 a day, respectively , to the officers of the Royal Indian Marine tug “ Elephanta”, whilst ’employed on the construction of lighthouses in the Persian Gulf. 2. In reply, I am to say that the Government of India having given the matter their careful consideration regret that they are unable to sanction the admission of climatic and boat-cruising allowances to the officers in question. They are, however, pleased, as a special case, to sanction the grant of a deputation allowance of Rs. 2-4-0 a day to each of the three officers of the Royal Indian Marine tug “ Elephanta ”, for the period she is employed on the construction of lighthouses in the Persian Gulf. 3. The expenditure involved will be debited to the Persian Gulf lighting and buovine scheme. Telegram No. 1323-15-M., dated the 23rd October 1913. From—The Secretary to the Government of India, Marine Department, To—The Director, Royal Indian Marine, Bombay. Reference Marine Department No. 1323-11-M.,{ dated the 14th October. Following dated 17th October received from Admiral. Begins — 50 Your 1323-10- M.,§ of 14th October. “Mashona ” detailed for whole-time lighthouse service— Ends. ^Serial No. 221 . § Serial No. 220. C482FD* Enclosure 20 of Serial No. 232. tug no further action is necessary. Please report cost involved in employment on lighthouse work. Reference your No.* 584, dated 14th October, regarding hire of Enclosure 2 of Serial No. 232. Telegram No. 584, dated the 14th October 1913. From—The Director, Royal Indian Marine, Bombay, To—The Secretary to the Government of India, Marine Department, Simla. YourJ 1323-11-M., 14th instant. Am in communication with Port Officers X Serial No. 221 . Karachi about hire of tug and will inform you as soon as details are obtained. Tamb lighthouse was built without whole-time steamer with little material delay in con sequence. ^ Great delay is experienced in loading]dhows at Henjam owing to short age of coolies making whole-time attendance of steamer uneconomical. Letter being posted to-morrow. Enclosure 3 of Serial No. 232. No. 7195, dated the 15th October 1913. From—The Director, Royal Indian Marine, Bombay, To The Secretary to the Government of India, Marine Department. W ith reference to letter§ No. 475, dated 23rd Sepetmber 1913, from Mr. C. J. § Enclosure 28 of Serial No. 228. Homer, Officer in Charge, Persian Gulf . . Lighthouse Works, Little Quoin, copy for warded to me by the First Assistant Resident and His Majesty’s Consul, Bushire, under Ins letter No. 3053, dated 5th October 1913, I have the honour to observe as follows:— Pai agraph 1. British India steamers call off Little Quoin four times a week on purpose to ascertain Mr. Homer’s requirements and difficulties. He has a signalman and signalling plant on the island.Paragraph 2 .—The cause of the delay in doing the work up to date has been the inability of the local contractor to obtain coolies to load the dhows, if it had not been for this, stores for building, coal for distiller, lime-burning and cooking, could have been landed in sufficient quan tities to keep Little Quoin going for a month at a time. There is no prospect of any improvement in this matter. What should be done is to fill lighters with material, as coolies can be obtained, select a suit- •It. I.M. S. “ Minto ' could be spared to do this. able .&lt;% and them across to Little Quoin, discharge and bring them back and leave them to be filled again at Henjam, or if sand is required it can be obtained at either Khor Kuwai or Tamb Island as most convenient. Paragraph 3 .—This of course might happen anywhere, certain delays are caused by bad weather. Water is produced by a condensing plant and food can be provided to the amount there is storage room for. The British India steamers call as I have said four times a week off the island; the statement that days or even weeks before assistance could be rendered is quite without foundation. There certainly is a large amount of building material to be landed and no doubt a whole-time steamer would be a convenience but is not, I maintain, a necessity so long as the endless delay in loading the lighters continues, an occasional tow when the dhows are full being all that is required. Mr. Homer has up to now had no qualified assistant to superintend work and cannot carry on building operations in two places at once. He should have an assistant who understands building and the way of working native labour; until he has this, the work cannot go on simultaneously at both places. Paragraph 6 .—ALUiow full of coal, say 200 tons, would last 28 weeks; the words “a constant supply” afe misleading. Paragraph 7.—I fancy the submission of these accounts has been very irregu lar and if the means of communication is irregular the accounts must necessarily be so also. It is hardly a reason for a whole-time steamer. Paragraph 10 .—Simultaneous work cannot go on satisfactorily at both Tamb ^ and Little Quoin while only one qualified engineer is there to super vise both places. To get the work finished in reasonable time another officer subordinate to Mr. Homer should be sent to Tamb Island. The words “enormous loss ” are I think too indefinite to be taken serious notice The cost to the lighting scheme of the attendance of the Elephanta is already norted to the Gfovernment of India, and unless some means is devised of filling nows for her to tow, in quicker time than at present, her whole-time attend- ace would prove anything but economical. The buildings to be completed are—quarters for lighthouse keepers and store- at Tamb (not yet commenced)-temporary clay huts and godowns are being ed sbnilar in construction to the usual residence of the natives m these parts- e lighthouse foundations at Quoin, the living quarters at Quoin, the lighthouse enSt at Abadan, consisting of store-houses, slipway house for spare buoys, cables ud moorings, and dewelling quarters for crew at Depot. Mr Homer has these three undertakings to complete and has up to the present , • • j. of oil It is far more work than one man can cope Vvirh, e n is feeling Reflects of over-work and anxiety, both of which are accentuated by L very unpleasant conditions of life at Quoin. He has been there during the ottot months of the year, is not in good health and should, I consider, have change. TTiP Vmilfbno's at Tamb can quite easily be accomplished without a whole-time The buildm be rapidly completed if dhows were procured ndfillh with the building material beforehand. Mr. Homer has an idea of sending tone from Quoin to Tamb for building purposes, but the difliculties of dischargingstores on Quoin is I consider quite sufficient reason for not depending on material produced on Quoin for embarkation and conveyance from that place to Tamb. It would certainly cause far more delay and exaggerate the difficulties he complains about at present. The above is one of the reasons that Mr. Homer adduces for the whole-time steamer to keep continuously plying between the two places. As I have stated in my letter* No. 6703, dated 23rd September 1913, the • Enclosure 2 of Serial No. 190. accumulation of silt in the approaches to the Dockyard must be most energetically dealt with, and with the plant the Government of India have sanctioned for the work, viz., the “Elephanta” dredger and two dummy hoppers, otherwise they cannot be kept open. The absence of the “Elephanta” during the last two months has seriously interfered with this work and it cannot be delayed any longer; the temporary assist ance at Quoin could perhaps be arranged with the Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, as I understand the Arms Traffic is at present almost at a standstill.’ Telegram No. 600, dated the 21 st October 1913. From—The Director, Royal Indian Marine, Bombay, To—The Secretary to the Government of India, Marine Department. Your telegramf 1590-M., 20 th. As no information regarding Henjam and Char- f Enclosure. will be returned on receipt of reply. bar lights available here, have referred to Director, Persian Gulf Telegraphs, and file[No. 3114, dated Bushire, the 12th (received 20th) October 1913. From— CAPTAIN R. L. Birdwood, I. A., First Assistant Resident (in the absence of the Resident), To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department, Simla. In continuation of this office letter, No. 1877, dated the 15th June 1913, ^ I have the honour to forward, for the No. 620 , datea the 7 th cto er 1913 . information of the Government of India, a copy of a report by the Officer Commanding R.I.M.S. “ Lawrence,” regarding the work done on buoys in tihe Persian Gulf since the return of that vessel from Bombay up to 30th September 1913. 2. A copy of this letter, with the enclosure, is being forwarded to the Director of the Royal Indian Marine. India, Foreign Secretary’s N° j 4 . M, dated 30. UCT 19132 r/ No. 620 , dated 7 th October 1913 . Statement of condition and of 'work done on bnoys by R.IM.S. “ Lawrence 30th September 1913. for quarter Place. Bandar Abbas Bushire Number and description of buoy. Do. Abadan Shatt-al-Arab Bahrain Bushire Old Buoy No. 11 No. I! No. 2, L. G. B. Date when first laid. rath June 1913 N 0. 3, L. G. B. No. 1, L. G. B. No. 5, L. G. B. No. 2, L. G. B. Bushire Abadan No. 3, L. G. B. Date when last overhauled. 14th August 1913 6th April 1913 nth February 1913 April 1911 30th April 1913 16th April 1913 24th September 1913 Detail of work performed during quarter, and report on ..condition of buoy. 6th April 1913 Buoy^and mo0rjngs,r;enewecj anjd landed at Abadan. Given one coat, red p^int above water line, checked buoy’s position and. found it correct. Examined buoy, as it was reported as not occulting, Burners carbonised and mechanism not working cleaned burners and altered light to a fixed light (so as to insure the buoy not being run into) as the mechanism could not be repaired. This is a temporary measure till the buoy can be taken in hand at end of month, Lenses were cleaned, thick coat of sand and dust and salt removed from the outside. Examined and found correct and cleaned lenses which were covered with a hard coat of sand, dust and salt. 19th, 20th, 21 st September. Landed buoy, sinkers and cables. As there was a strong tide this work could only be attempted at slack water. Two tons of carbide, one keg purifier and one box of spare parts brought on board for charging Bushire buoys. Officer Commanding H. M.S. “Sphinx' reported to me by signal at Faothat the buoy was not working. On the way to Bahrain stopped and anchored off the buoy, sent away the working party and officers. Found that the burners were choked, renewed burners and lit the light and cleaned lenses. Light burning well at 8 p.m. when the vessel proceeded on her voyage. We had great difficulty with this buoy, partly owing to a nasty jcbble on the water making boat work dirficult, and the mechanism itself not working. Lantern was detached and brought on board, two valves ground in and the mechanism cleaned and readjusted. Lantern fixed in position and lit. Burning well and to time. I proceeded into Bahrain and informed H. B. M.’s Consul that the light was burning correctly. On returning about 6-30 p.m. found the light nearly out and not flashing, I anchored, sent away boat and tried various adjustments. Got the mechanism to work to 15 dark 3 light, but as it was reported that one pipe was leaking badly I decided to remain the night, and if necessary change the lantern. We timed the light throughout the night. 15 and 3 at midnight, 7 and 3 at 3 a.m., and 3 and 3 at 6-30 a.m. this morning, evidently it would have stopped altogether in a few hours. This proves the mechanism is at fault and will have to be repaired when time permits. I decided to relieve the lantern altogether with the spare one we carry on board when at buoy work. This is an occult* ing light instead of a flashing, but better than no light at all. When the mechanism is repaired it ought to be replaced as soon as possible, 26th September. On the vessel’s arrival light wa&amp; reported as not working. Sent away steam cutter to examine and report. Boat had to return owing to Shamal having sprung up and making a nasty sea, making it impossible for boat to lie alongside buoy. 27th September. Party away at daylight, examined buoy ; generating no gas, as the buoy has been lit fot seven months, conclusion is that the carbide has been expended. Examined this buoy on the way back to ship, bignt fitful and erratic. Probability is that the carbide u finished, as this buoy is due for charging now. 29th September. Landing carbide and bringing s P at ® ordinary buoy, chain and sinker for replacing No-. 3 buoy, Shatt-al-Arab, which has disappeared.Place. • Number and description of buoy. Date when first laid. Date when last overhauled. Detail of work performed during quarter, and report on condition of buoy. Shatt-al-Arab No. 1 Buoy 30th September. Anchored off the old outer bar buoy (No. 1 buoy) and as it was low-water and I could not lay No. 3 buoy, sent away party to add extra length of chain to make this buoy (No. 1) watch properly. ^ used two odd lengths of the old cable from Bahrain ; this was successful and the buoy is now watching properly, cleaned and gave it a coat of red paint, the staff and cage has at same time been carried away, did not replace this as had no spar on board fit for the purpose. As the buoy is now an ordinary std. hand buoy and not used for ‘ making” the Port, 1 don’t think it will be necessary to replace the staff and cage again^as it is easily seen from the gas buoy or Turkish Lt. vessel. Note ,—The channel at the outer bar, Shatt-al-Arab, has shifted slightly to the eastward. No. I buoy is now being used as a port hand. When time permits the channel should be surveyed and No. 1 buoy placed into the proper position. Engineer Harvey and two men left behind at Abadan to assemble and charge spare buoy for replacing No. 2 L. G. B. at Bushire. (Sd.) G. H. FINNIS, Bushire, 7 th October igt 3 . Officer Commanding R.I. MS.' Lawrence: C85FD— 44— 33-10-13—GCBP Simlar/' Any further communication on this subject should be addressed to THE SECRETARY, TRINITY HOUSE, TOWER HILL, LONDON, E.C., and the following letter and number should be quoted: ' l B. Telegraphic Address :— DIOPTRIC, FEN. LONDON. Bouse, Imtiou, (6.C. 5 th. Hoy ember 1913. I i 't / 2 v y ff a 7 ! 7tX lh&gt; J Sir, The attention of the liilder Brethren has been drawn to the issue of M The London Gazette** (Uo.28769 dated the •v 31st October 1913), containing an account of an accident which occurred on the 14th April 1913, whilst the Acetylene- gas Lighted Buoy at the Shatt-al-Arab Outer Bar in the Persian Gulf was being re-charged at its station with Carbide of Calcium, and as this and other Acetylene-lighted Buoys and the instructions for working the same were sup plied through the medium of the Trinity House at the request of the India Office, I am directed to state that the Elder Brethren will be much obliged if the Secretary of State for India will favour them by causing full details of the occurrence to be obtained from the Persian Gulf and transmitted to me for their information. \ I S’***.,*. ' 6 N0V1913 The Under Secretary of State, India Office, Whitehall, Your obedient Servant,Enclosure to para. 24 of General Despatch No. 10 J (Army)) dated the 21 st August ig/ 3 . Enclosure No. 1. No. 5391, dated Bombay, the 26th July I 9 I 3 - From—The Director of the Royal Indian Marine, To—The Secretary to the Government of India, Marine Department. I have the honour to forward the accompanying correspondence relative to the bravery and presence of mind of Shaik Mohidin, Tindal of Stokers, 2nd class, who at great personal risk and under circumstances of peculiar danger went _ to the rescue of 1st class Stoker Shaik Mahomed who was in great danger of being burned to death on the occasion of the charging with Acetylene gas of certa ^ n buoys in the Persian Gulf. The circumstances of peculiar courage displayed by this petty officer are in my opinion worthy of recognition, and I would therefore strongly recommend for the favourable consideration of the Government of India that he may be awarded the Albert Medal of the 2nd class for the deed of gal lantry performed by him. Recharging the Shatt-al-Arab Puter Bar Gas Buoy at Fao about 8 -lo a.m. on the 14th Ann' 1913, an explosion took place by which Sha.k Mahomed, who was tending the canvas chute inside the cage, was knocked senseless through the shock of the explosion and thrown to the opposite side of the cage away from the manhole A as per sketch attached. The canvas chute G being on fire both in and outside the cage causing manhole door A to be in a mass of flames. The Stoker Tindal, Shaik Mohidin, who was not on this duty but had ob served the accident and had seen the officers on this duty knocked down ; ran forward jumped from the lower boom on to the buoy got through the flam s nto the cage by door A, pushed the burning chute aside and dragged the man out puttinf him into the water on the weather side of the buoy and holding him there until the boat came to his relief, he had nothing to hold on to, but the angle irons D as the slots were nearly all in or amongst the flames. fP. C. H. LANE, Lieutenant, R.LM. Witness. \ J. B. BEGGS, Assistant Engineer, R.LM. i_D. G. L. WILLIAMS, Gunner, R.l.M, Approved. G. H. FINNIS, Lieutenant, Commander, R.I.M.S. 'Lawrence'. '«*’ &lt; zx&amp; zzzx r :har tJc officer of the day had just been rounds and reported all correct. Lieutenant Lam, Assistant Z lanvaTchu te, 6 Shaik' Mahomed, Stoker, , st class, on the buoy, keeping the canvas ' hUt Thew’ritten reports of the above officers attached. 322AD~—. ^ ^ — 2 The explosion occurred about 8-10 a.m., the above officers who were at the side rail were hurled right across the deck by the force of the explosion, bar shock, and bruises, none of the officers were injured. First class Stoker Shaik Mahomed, who was on the buoy at the moment of the explosion, was badly injured—statement of injuries sustained attached; all his clothes on fire, and, if it had not been for the extreme presence of mind and bravery of Tindal of Stokers, 2nd class, Shaikh Mohidin, who jumped on to the buoy, w r ent through the flames, 8 to 10 feet high and brought 1st class Stoker Shaik Mahomed, out of the cage; this man, who was half senseless and could do nothing to help himself, would have been burnt to death. We humbly bring to your notice this extremely plucky action of Tindal of Stokers, 2nd class, bhaik Mohidin, and if it can be recognised in any way, it would be only what the man deserves. The explosion, we are of the opinion, w^as caused by a small quantity of gas generated in the chute and this was ignited by a spark caused by the falling carbide. &amp; We should beg to point out that in the book of instructions on the manage ment of gas buoys in the Persian Gulf, 1912, paragraph 3^, page 10, it is distinctly laid down that buoys are not to be reached whilst in the 'water. Gas must have generated in the buoy, though in a very small quantity, otherwise the explosion could not have taken place. We saw the oil used for treating the carbide tested at the Abadan Labora tory and it flashed at 175 0 , which is considered perfectly safe. Abadan; ijth April igr^. G. H. FINN IS, Lt. } President. T. G. J. HARVEY, Engineer^ &gt; Members. A. GRAY, Sub-Lieutenant No. 1320 , dated Bushire, the 24 th April 1913 . From The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, To—The Director, Royal Indian Marine, Bombay. I hare the honour to forward, for such action as you may consider calie No. 211, dated 14th April 1913^ w ith enclosures, j 01 *’ a co py of a communication receive Tinda 2 ! - , VhTik MohidT ‘but ‘for Cbich'W mlnd , a ' d P ,uck ° f the Stok, authority! ° f ^ ' -rde/sp^c Indi a \A r he f FZign n Lynment fthlS Ie “ er ^ enc,osures ‘o the Government c No. 211, dated Fao, the 14th April 1913. From—Lieutenant G. H. Finnis, R.I.M., President, To-The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. I regret to report that this morninp’ at ahnnt £ lm outer bar light buoy, an explosion occurred by which .st Stoker stkh Mohfm3 was senously burnt. Lieutenant Lane, Assistant Engineer Beg^s and Gunner Wilhams who were at the ship’s side, placing the carbide into The canvas chute were knocked down and thrown amidships by the force of the explosion. fl : ,m«T h ?n r!n t, S - t !l e e ?P los ,' on ’ 1 went on deck and took charge. Seeing that flames to the height of 10 feet were coming out of the buoy, 1 had the buoy dropped astern and sand thrown on to smother the flames. T ^ !lowed ; t k urn out, a minor explosion took place when just astern, so I would not allow anyone to approach it till after 10 a.m. for safety. On examination we found that the carbide inside the generator was perfectly untouched, i 4 a cases were packed before the explosion took place. . 9 n seem g this \ would not allow the other 6 carbide cases to be packed in, as it is, nearly certain, the explosion was caused by the crude oil supplied to us by the Anglo Persian Oil Company for soaking the carbide in before charging. The explosion, I am of opinion^ was caused by a small quantity of gas gene rated in the chute and this w r as ignited by a spark caused by the fallinsr carbide. J 6 I beg to point out^ that in the Book of Instruction on the Management of gas bouys in the Persian Gulf, 1912, paragraph 35, page 10, it is distinctly laid down that buoys are not to be recharged whilst in the water. Gas must have generated in the buoy, though in a very small quantity, otherwise the explosion could not have taken place. I saw the oil used for treat ing the carbide tested at the Abadan Laboratory and it flashed at 175 0 which is considered perfectly safe. I tried the buoy and found it as far as I can judge to be in working order, only damage being done to 8 wooden slots and the canvas chute burnt. I have fitted new slots and the canvas chute can be made on board. I consider that we have been exceptionally fortunate in the fact that the above officers were not seriously injured or killed. Copies of the evidence of Board of Enquiry on the accident are forwarded. Dated Fao, the 14 th April 1913 . From—Lieutenant P. C. Lane, To—The Officer Commanding, R.I.M.S. “ Lawrence I have the honour to report that this morning, having been working on the Gas Buoy since 5-30 a.m., and all being ready for charging same at 7-30 a.m., I was helping Second Engineer Beggs at this wmrk when buoy w’as nearly charged, an explosion occurred which came straight up the chute knocking myself and Mr. Beggs the other side of the deck, the man on the buoy was knocked down and badly burnt, would probably have been burnt to death but for the pluck and presence of mind of Tindal of Stokers, 2nd class, Shaikh Mohidin, who jumped on to the buoy and dragged the man out of the cage, put him in the water and held him till a boat came. Previous to this, 1 had given orders that no smoking was to be done or matches used near forecastle head, foreflat or crews’ quarters till gas buoy had been dropped astern. The officer of the day went round a few minutes before the explosion occurred and all ports were shut, on starboard side forward. My opinion on the explosion is, we had been given oil of a low flashing point and not the same as last time. This oil is being tested. Every precaution was taken during the filling of this buoy,Dated Fao, the 14th April 19* From—Sub-Lieutenant L. E. BRIARD, To—The Officer Commanding, R.I.M.S. “Lawrence”. I have the honour to report that at 7-30 a.m. this morning, I took over the duties of O. O. W. at 7-45* 1 was on the forecastle head and saw Lieutenant Lane, Assistant Engineer Beggs and Gunner Williams with two or three stokers and lascars engaged in charging the gas buoy, one man was inside the cage on the buoy. I heard the 1st Lieutenant give orders that there was to be no smoking in the foreflat, crews’ quarters, or in the foc’sle head, until after the buoy had been passed astern, and that all ports on the starboard side were to be closed down. After reporting 8 a m , I went round the foreflat and saw that the ports were closed, also no smoking was taking place, I then went off on to the bridge, as I reached the top of the ladder I heard an explosion and looking forward saw smoke rising from the buoy, so I immediately ran down and reported to yourself that an explosion had taken place in the buoy. Fire stations were then piped, so I took up my station aft. Dated Fao, the 16th April 1913. From—Assistant Engineer J. BEGGS, R.I.M., To—The Officer Commanding, R.I.M.S. “Lawrence”. 1 have the honour to report that work of recharging the outer bar buoy was started on Friday, nth instant, a.m. On Saturday morning the generator chamber was opened in order to remove the residue of the old charge of calcium carbide and to prepare the chamber for a new charge. After working on this buoy for five or six hours it was decided owing to a strong breeze springing up to disconnect the buoy from its moorings and take it in tow to Fao, where the work could be carried out with more safety. Luring the towing the generator chamber and main sea valve were open. On Sunday morning, work was again started to remove the residue from the chamber and was done in the usual manner and according to instructions from book, this was all removed and the chamber was thoroughly cleaned and dried before work was knocked off at about 5 p.m. The buoy was brought alongside the ship at 5 30 a.m. on Monday and the chamber was examined and found to be thoroughly dry, it was then prepared in the usual manner for receiving the charge of calcium carbide, 1 e , by means of a map ; the sides of the generator were covered with a coating of crude petroleum. The carbide tins were opened and crude petroleum was poured in and the tins rolled to ensure that all carbide came in contact^ with the oil, as by soaking the carbide in oil the danger from explosion is minimised. The canvas chute used for recharging was then placed in the chamber allow ing about 4 feet to rest on the bottom, to form a cushion for the falling carbide. As the chamber filled, the chute was shortened still allowing the same length to rest on the carbide. The man was placed on the buoy to tend the chute and guide the carbide into its place. . ^ I was P res ent during the whole of the charging operation and can certif that all the carbide placed in the chamber was well covered with oil. Fourteen am a half drums weighing a cwt. each were expended in charging the buoy and eacl piece was dropped in separately, it was at this stage, at about 8-15 a.m. whei the explosion occurred; the operation having been in progress about li hours the flames shot up to a height of about 4 to 5 feet enveloping the canvas chute The injured man wa 5 removed and the buoy was passed astern and flames allow ed to die out. At 10 am. when the buoy was examined the carbide in thsjsasssr S,*ss ssm 31*5 quite fresh, showing that there had been no fir^ ; ’A untoucllftc ^ anc ^ clearly proving that the explosion must have t^J comes dampTt geneses aceSe gas'tl^h whf^ ^ dry ’- bU t t ,r hen 11 be ‘ contact with a lio-ht or snarl of 1 course 'g 01 ' 6 lf brought into contacr wun a ugnt or spark. 1 he carbide appeared to be very drv and if the explos,on occurred through dampness, it must either have been thefa.df of ^he carbide being wet or undetectable or the oil that was used for mling with the carbide had a bad percentage of water mixed with it, as the atmosphere was drv SllstXSLl 0 t As D b a e r S k 0 mS y h k,10WledgeCa r ' conta^r:^ whilst charging. A spark may have originated through one of the pieces of ClSgte™”,! 1 ,l ' ”*““• llh ' b “»r«*l-L-d to a i } rece ' ve( ? ^ he 01 ] ^om the Assistant ^Manager, Anglo-Persi/n Oil Company Abadan, who informed me that the quality was ihe same as that previously sup plied for charging the Bushire buoys which was said to have a flash of 150 but should 01 of a lover flash point have been supplied, this would render an explo sion possible and so may account for the accident. P ^This is the fourth buoy that I personally charged and the work was carried out in exactly the same manner as in the other three and every precaution against carlessness and naked lights was observed. Dated Fao, the 14 th April 1913 . From—Gunner D. G. L. Williams, R. I. M., To— Lieutenant-Commander G. H. Finnis, Commanding R.I.M.S./'Lawrence”. I have the honour to report that this morning, on turning to at a.m. work was commenced on the gas buoy. After hauling buoy up to starboard side foe sle head under derrick, it was canted on on its side. Second Engineer Be^s made an inspection of lower end, after which the buoy was lowered. He then gave necessary orders for cleaning and preparing the carbide chamber'’ for recharging. At 7 a.m. the operation of recharging was commenced by the . oecond Engineer Beggs. J The f 1 Lieutenant and myself were assisting. Previous to recharging being started, the 1 st Lieutenant gave orders to have all square ports starboard side forward, lowered, and all round ports in crew’s quarters starboard side closed, giving at the same time verbal orders to the O. 0. Watch to see them closed. Smoking was prohibited forward until such time as buoy w^as dropped astern. r At 8-10 a.m. an explosion occurred, one stoker who was on the buoy inside the cage being severely burnt. The canvas chute (for filling and the wooden bars of cage caught fire, the waste oil on buoy also, ignited). I saw the 1 st Lieutenant being thrown across the deck, second Engineer Beggs dropped to the deck with the force of explosion. I myself felt the shock very severely. Orders were given to drop the buoy astern and for the hands to go to fire quarters in both of which evolutions I was at my station. To the best of my knowledge the cause of the explosion emanated from the buoy itself and was not due to sparks from ship’s funnel, matches or through any carlessness. I saw nobody smoking in the vicinity. The recharging was being carried out in my opinion in as safe a manner as circumstances would allow. Each piece of carbide being placed in the canvas chute provided for filling by hand. Further, I beg to state that during my commission in this vessel, I have been present on each occasion that this buoy has been recharged and every precaution has been always taken to ensure safety as was done today._—- &gt; AM 6 Dated Fao, the 14 th April 1913 . From— ■’Assistant Surgeon F. H. AS0UITH, I.S.M.D. To—The Officer Commanding, R. I. M. S. “Lawrence”. I have the honour to submit the following report being the results of my examination of 1st Class Stoker Sheikh Muhammad, Patient was admitted to hospital this morning, suffering from extensive burns of the anterior surfaces of the head and neck, upper part of abdomen, lower extremities and the fronts and backs of the upper extremities. The burns vary from those of the 1st to those of the 3 r d degree. The shock sustained must have been severe as when brought in patient was quite pale and shivering with a week pulse and cold extremities. Although the burns are extensive and involve such a large area, the prog nosis seems favourable, owing to patient’s excellent physique. : c: V ' ; Hi . i rnoo f (liiSfi® jpearv lilerSecreta feetairofSCONFIDKNTIAL. (+120 (No. 364.) Sir W. Townley to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received October 19, noon.) v i YOUR telegram No. 434 Tehran, October 19, 1913. (October 19, 1 p.m.) I am assured by the Persian Government and the Treasurer-General that there is no intention of establishing a light on Larak Island, and that, should it be at any time considered desirable to do so, advice and assistance of His Majesty’s Government will be sought. 20 [1119—286][This Docmnent is the Property of ffis Britannic Majesty's eovftrnmAnf ] n PERSIA. CONFIDENTIAL. [46084] No - l- Sir Edward Grey to Sir W. Townley. (Telegraphic.) Foreign Office October 15 1913. PERSIAN Government are reported to be contemplating establishment ot Persian light on Larak Island in accordance with, proposals urged by Belgian customs officials at Bunder Abbas. ^ . P ... tj- You should remind Acting Minister for Foreign Affairs of position ot llis Maiesty’s Government in the matter (see my telegram No. 177 of 7th April), and press strongly that to carry out such project without previous understanding with His Majesty’s Government would be inconsistent with prescriptive rights of this country, which are well known to Persian Government. [1898 p—3] t'-N tv | Eacltawr* ' JT * ■ '• tndiu. j A'o. 3 7 c'. v. ’ 11 SEP ibtj No. 2629, dated Bushire, the 31st August (received 8th September) 1913 (Confidential). From— Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Percy Cox, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department. I have the honour to communicate the following, for the information of the Government of India, in connection with the general question of the lighting of the Gulf. 2. At a meeting recently convened at Bandar Abbas by the Director of Customs—a new broom, Monsieur Willemsens—reported by the Consular Clerk (in the absence of His Majesty’s Consul) in the accompanying diary entry (enclosure 1), certain proposals were put forward of which it will he convenient for Government to have early information, I attach a copy of that portion of the “ Avant projet” containing them (enclosure 2). 3. It will he seen that a proposal, doubtless emanating from Monsieur Hepiere, Captain of the “ Persepolis ”, to whose activity we were indebted for * Vide correspondence ending with my letter the Russian Consulate lilghts which No. 1579, dated the isth May 1913 recently gave us some inconvenience,* was recommended to the Persian Government some 18 months ago for a 15-mile Persian Light on Larak Island and two leading lights on the Customs Plagstaff at Bandar Abbas.” A Persian Light on Larak, in any case, would be an inconvenient intrusion on our scheme and opposed to our prescriptive claim to control the lighting of the Gulf; and I beg that the Government of India will be pleased to consider whether His Majesty’s Government should not be advised to discourage the proposal respecting Larak, and to put fresh pressure on the Persian Government with a view to obtaining from them the same friendly recognition of our right to control lighting as has been accorded us by the Porte. The personnel of the Belgian Customs and Monsieur Hepiere are perfectly well aware of our attitude in these matters, but clearly cannot be relied upon to be influenced thereby. I am sending a copy of this communication to His Majesty’s Minister. oi. Extract from Bandar Abbas Diary, No. 28, for the week ending the 9th July 1913. 122. At the request of the Director of Customs a meeting of local British Indian and Persian merchants was held in his office on the 4th July to discuss certain changes which he intends to make for extending the present pier to facilitate landing of cargo and regarding the appointment and respons ibility of the Hamal Bashi here. The Director had officially requested the Head Clerk of this Consulate to attend the meeting. The time appointed was 8 a.m., hut the Director and most of tbe Persian merchants were not present there before 9 a.m., when the Director asked one of his clerks to read out his proposals in Persian. It took nearly three and half hours to read out and explain the proposal to merchants. The latter asked the Director to allow them time and to hold another meeting later on to enable them to consider and discuss the matter. Avant Pro jet, D’organisation des services de dechargument, de chargement, de remise au service de la douane, de manutention en douane, et de livraison a domicile des colis debarques au port de Bender- Abbas, par les steamers. Un examen prealable et rapide des installations maritimes, nous fait decouvrir, que le port de Bender-Abbas Avant propos. n , egt s jg na |£ aux nayires par aucun phare, que son entree est des plus perilleux et que la majorite des Commandants des steamers retardent leur arrivee en rade de Bender-Abbas, jusqu’a la pointe du jour. ■■CONFIDENTIAL. Sir Edward Grey to Sir W. Townley (Tehran). (No. 177.) Foreign Office, April 7, 1913, 2T5 p.m. ’ YOUR telegram No. 145 of 4th April: Advance for Ears. As regards lighting and buoyage of Persian Gulf, His Majesty s Government consider that, unless there is reason to think that Persian Government will now accept proposed stipulation as to formal agreement in terms set forth in clause L ot my telegram No. 113 of 8th March, best course will be to withdraw it altogether Wiien informing Persian Government that it is withdrawn, you should add that His Majesty s Government regard themselves as possessing prescriptive right to control of lighting and buoying arrangements in the Gulf, which, if occasion arose, they wouic no oxiiorcG* • Arrangement arrived at regarding your supervision of expenditure is sufficient. As regards Bahreinis and trucial subjects, you should make statement m sense ol last paragraph of my telegram No. 113 of 8th March. Subject to the above conditions and tender system for purchases, you may draw on Imperial Bank of Persia and may pay over first months instalment ot .bars advance.CONFIDENTIAL. Sir W. Townley to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received April 4, 3 p.m.) Tehran, April 4, 1913. (No. 145.) R. (April 4, 1*40 p.m.) YOUR telegram No. 173 of 3rd April. I understood your telegram No. 133 only to authorise verbal communica tion which, has been made in that sense. I will now send in note on the same lines. British consul at Shiraz telegraphs that colonel of the gendarmerie is pressing for money. When may I expect views of His Majesty’s Government upon proposals of Persian Government respecting the buoying and lighting of the Persian Gulf ? I have again pressed question of Bahreinis and subjects of the Trucial chiefs. 1 Minister for Foreign Affairs has agreed to an arrangement to be made with Treasurer- General which will secure my supervision of expenditure.- COPY* A i* * jf- k ' c ^ y v ; /r ;) * 21a la I Enclosure *-*' 7 Fi /, 'V./ (T, ^ ' l W&gt; w 3 (' ’• from FortY” S?-c~etzry t I at aw E From - Captain R&lt;&gt; I* B.irdwood f First Assistant to the Political Resident in the Persian GrUl£ t Bushire, To 2!he Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department, Simla* Ho# 1488, dated and reed* the 28th August 1913* Ho new lights have 'been supplied at Henjam and Charhar# Your telegram dated 19th August t 1934&gt;^B#A#, however is not quite clear to me as no recommendations regarding replacement of lights have been made by Gunter♦ Action recommended in paragraph 2 of letter t quoted was Residents suggestions#e, p'”'.,? r ' r * w A. / u • 16120. I. 694. 10,000.—5/1913. [961/12.] Departments are requested, if they suspect that far? fainy mistake in this telegram, to communicate i mmediately with the Private Secretary mkhe^Phrliamjntary Under Secretary of State ' COPY OF TELEGRAM. From Viceroy Dated 5 September 181S Received at London Office 6 2 Foreign Secret. Your telegram of tte 6th August. Lights in the Persian Gulf. Nevi lights have not yet been supplied at Qhahbar.and Henjam. Patter is maer consideration.&gt; &gt; COPY i TO FOReiQN J SEP 1913 fe. No. 1253-E.A., dated Simla, the 10th June 1913. From— L. W. Reynolds, Esq., C.I.E., I.C.S., Deputy Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department, To— Lieutenant-Colonel Sir P. Z. Cox, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. I am directed to acknowledge the receipt of your letter* No. 1805, dated the * Serial 9, part I. 1 . lth August 1912, regarding administra tive and financial arrangements connected with the scheme of lighting and buoying in the Persian Gulf. 2. The Government of India concur in your proposal that for the present the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf should function as the Chief Lighting Authority and ex-officio Inspector of Lights. Once, however, the political problems are solved and the Lighthouse tender is in being these functions will be exercised, in con^j^ation with the Political Resident when necessary, by the Director, Royal Indian Marine. In these circumstances the Government of India f do not consider the deputation of a special officer for the purpose necessary as proposed by you. 3. In order to avoid delay in payments the Government of India authorise the Political Resident to incur contingent charges on account of the scheme. 4. A further communication will be made to you as soon as possible regarding the allowance to officers which is referred to in paragraph 7 of your letter under reply.) * 'W5* No. 1877, dated Bushire, the 15th (received 23rd) June 1913 From—L ieutenant-Colonel Sir Percy Cox, K.C.I.E., C.S.L, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department, Simla. In continuation of my letter No. 1381, dated 30th April 1913, I have the „ 00 „ , „, w honour to forward, for the information of No. 288, dated 28th May iqi 3. ^ r t v r the Government 01 India, a copy 01 a report by the Officer Commanding, R.I.M.S. “ Lawrence/'' regarding the work done on buoys in the Persian Gulf previous to the departure of the ship for Bombay. 2. I am sending a copy of this letter with the enclosures to the Director of the Royal Indian Marine. No. 288, dated 28th May 1913. From—The Officer Commanding, R.I.M.S. “Lawrence,” Bombay, To—The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. The attached copies are forwarded with compliments to the Political Resi dent, Persian Gulf. Submitted now, as vessel will be in the hands of the dockyard.Statement Place. Bushire, Outer anchorage. Outer Bar, Shatt-al- Arab. Outer Harbour, Bahrain. Jadum Shoal, Bahrain. f condition and of mrk done on buoys by RJ.M.S. ' Laurence ” for quarter June jgi3. Number and description of buoy. Date when first laid. Gas, white occult ing. February 1913 Gas Buoy Date when last overhauled. March 1 II ••• Gas flashing white Gas flashing red... April 29th 1913..T April 6th, 1913 April 15th, 1913, April 15th, 1913... H.M.S. “Sphinx” will report date. April 6th, 1913 Detail of work performed during quarter and report on condition of buoy. This gas buoy was reported to be not occultin? C rn. perly on April 6th, examined lamp unshipped, broiLI on board occulting chambers examined. The bur found choked with carbon, and grit from purifier cha ' ber. Lamp cleaned, new burners fitted, replaced a!!i relit. na On April 7th, ran down and examined'Inner Harbour gas buoy. Found all in good working order, cleaned lenses. w | Hoisting gear of lamps. Residency Flag Staff, reported as not working satisfactorily, attended to and fitted^ April nth, 1913, picked up carbide at Abadan and proceeded to Outer Bar. Removed lamp same evening. April 12th, proceeded alongside buoy, up ended emptied out all loose carbide. (Note.—At least three cwti of this was good carbide and in my opinion would have burnt for another two months easily, making the life of the buoy 9 months instead of 7 at the very least. At noon unshackled buoy and buoyed moorings, as there were indications of a kans, towed buoy up to Fao, April 13th, cleaning buoy, condition of this buoy under water was good* growth removed, counterweight at tended to and cleaned, painted with a good coat of water line paint. Cage painted black, 4 new slats fitted. Buoy was dropped astern 4 p.m. owing to a kans blowing. April 14th, charged the buoy, explosion took place, no material damage done, finished charging and fitted lamp, tested all night, lamp burning well. April 15th, towed buoy to Outer Bar, shackled on moorings and examined same in good condition and not worn at all, let go from moorings and lit lamp. Note. —This buoy should be relieved next time it» due for charging. Has been over two years in the water—see book of Instructions. Commenced getting both Bahrain gas buoys ready on April 17th, while the boilers of this ship were being cleaned out, etc. All valves seatings were overhauled and examined before charging. These buoys were charged, laying in an horizontal position, well out of the water and whfen ready the Anglo-Persian Oil Company’s crane was used for lifting and placing into the water. Lamps fitted and tested. The outer harbour buoy flash ing correctly. Jadum shoal working at 7 secs, light 15 secs, eclipse instead of 3 and 7 respectively. April 27th. Left with Outer harbour buoy in tow. April 29th and 30th. Laid buoy and lighted lamp, picked up old buoy on board, and used its moorings, and 2? to 3 ton anchor, for New Kaseifa shoal buoy, conical black, staff and cage. Picked up Kaseifa old buoy on board with moorings and proceeded to Abadan. May 2nd. Landed the two old buoys at Abadan. Condition of these buoys, bad, pitted badly and full of holes that have been plugged by wood and putty. Hardly worth repairing in my opinion. May 3rd. Working at buoy getting off moorings, etc., to ship, May 4th. Left at daylight for Bahrain. Vessel had to put into Bushire owing to break down of engines. May 15th. Handed over all gear and gas buoy to Officer Commanding H.M.S. “Sphinx” also a spare anchor for West spit buoy j left instructions that all the assem bling gear (spanners, etc.,) to be packed in a box, ad dressed Officer Commanding “ Lawrence ” and len at Bushire. During our stay at Bushire, party ashore to set up lanyards of rigging of the Flagstaff, fitted bottle screws, lightning conductor, etc. (Sd.) G. H. FINNIS, Lieutenant, R. /. M., Commanding- C 31 FD- 44 —SS-tj-lS-GCBPSiml*Telegram No. 1323-2-M., dated the 27th June 1913. jr rom —The Secretary to the Government of India, Marine Department, T^The Director, Eoyal Indian Marine, Bombay. ^ ^ of Eeference correspondence ending yom ^ ’ conn ection with construction » Serial U. 0 f Uglithouscs. Please state what arrange- aents have been made and cost thereof.a 127 . No. 5 (P.G.), dated the 22nd March 1913. From—The Director of the Royal Indian Marine, To—The Secretary to the Government of India, Marine Department. In consultation with Sir P. Z. Cox, and after duly considering the amount of extra work entailed on the R. I. M. S. “ Lawrence ” and her officers in connection with the lighting and buoyage of the Persian Gulf, I have the honour to recommend that the officers of the ship should be granted the allowances suggested by Sir P. Z. - in qp ti Cox in his* letter No. 1805, dated the 11th ena o. , ar . August 1912 , instead of the extra duty pay at present sanctioned. The overlapping of the duties connected with the Political Resident’s despatch vessel and those entailed by the lighting and buoyage is frequent, and it is not easy to differentiate between the two ; besides which the officer commanding the vessel who has all the responsibility of lighting and buoyage (being the superintendent of the scheme) is not under the Marine Regulations entitled to any extra duty pay, and although a very considerable amount of extra work has been and will have to be undertaken by this officer over and above his duties as officer commanding of the Political Resident’s despatch vessel, no remuneration can be received by him under the existing conditions. The other officers of the ship though now paid while actually at work on laying out buoys, do not receive any extra pay while navigating the ship from place to place. During the inception of the whole system, I find the “ Lawrence ” is almost continually on the move, and as the small amount of expenditure proposed takes the place of the upkeep and maintenance of the lighthouse tender, I would recom mend for your approval that these allowances be sanctioned from the present date, and be debited to the lighting and buoyage of the Persian Gulf. 130 . Telegram No. 1535-E.A., dated Simla, the 10th July 1913. From—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department, •pQ—The Hon’ble Lieutenant-Colonel Sir P. Z. Cox, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. My telegram,{ dated 21st June No. 1373-E.A., Lighthouse at Tamb. Estab- t Serial No. 113. lishment of light should be communicated § Serial No. 127 , Part i. to Foreign Consuls.as proposed in your letter No. 3314,§ 13th December last, paragraph 4. C287FD131. -fc . • * ~ • .» Telegram, No. 380, dated Bombay, the 28th June 1913. jr rom The Director, Koyal Indian Marine, Y 0 Secretary to the Government of India, Marine Department, Simla. v i qoq o m * Time 27th As no suitable launch was obtainable on hire Your 1323-2-lYl., Jun . ^ - Eiephanta ” * Serial No. 123. wa s with considerable inconvenience to service detailed to assist in lighthouse construction work in Gull to meet urgent necessity. Annual cost “ Blephanta ” Rupees seventy thousand six hundred and forty-eight.In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote IL and address letter to— The Secretary, Admiralty, Whitehall, London, S.W. % Sir. Admiralty, %j s kJ xJ | i s t, August 191* . With reference to the telegram d^ted Henjara ^Oth Varch 191? 3 , forming enclosure to serial No 89 of the printed correspondence respecting the lighting and buoyage in the Persian Gulf, forwarded by you on the 10th ultimo, I am commanded by my Lords Commissioners of the Admiralty to enquire whether the lights referred to have yet been establish ed at TTenjam and Charbar, and, if so, whether particulars as to their exact locality, elevation, visibility, etc, can be furnished. (he Under Secretarv of State, India Office. Sir, Your Obedient Servant, S.W. 1 COPY TO FOREIGN OFFICE | 5 SEP1913 RECEIVED 2 AUG 191 INDIA OFFICERegister No. PUT AWAY With h Minute Paper. $ Secret Department. Letter fromc^v Eec. 7 c &lt; / Date. Initials. SUBJECT. Undersecretary Gj JdLj , (Xhb o cr^* Secretary of State Committee Under Secretary Secretary of State 'is i.UU ^ vi Previous Payers : V ' V J(^ c/ Copy to FOR INFORMATION.Enclosure ’ ' ..t frrrn For'' - a ^nry, Inuia. no. 25k 19 JUN1913 89 \ it A dL VhJ G J i b No. 1546, dated Bushire, the 17th (received 26th) May 1913. From— Lieutenant-Colonel Sir P. Z. Cox KCTE -i the Persian Gulf, ’ * U1K ’ C - SJ -’ Polltlcal R€8ld ^t in To—The Hon’ble Lieutenant-Colonel Sir A. H. McMahon G C V 0 K C I E Simla’ SeCretary t0the Govemment of India in the Foreign Department,’ ' In continuation of my letter No. 642, dated the 23rd February 1913 I have the honour to state for the information of the Government of India that ’in ronlv to enquiries from this office the Director, Indo-European Telegraph Department Persian Gulf Section, has informed me that the lantern to which reference is made at page 142 of the Persian Gulf Pilot is not of a sufficiently reliable pattern to *— the southern tower being fitted with l7gT\ t how a f hnhTtt 0 °®“ a lantern from which a light is shown if pre- i g ^ow a light when required, and ' ’ ' ’ - n P re he recommends that the entry* in regard thereto be deleted. viously arranged for by telegraph. 2 i , H ®' Tin f. r , e ? ard *°, tlle declared policy of His Majesty’s Government in legaid to the lighting of these waters, the discontinuance of any existing light can on y be regarded as a retrograde step, but at the same time I hesitate to ask Gov ernment to incur further substantial outlay in this directiorpending compll: tion of the scheme at present m hand. I venture, however, to suggest that the Director, Royal Indian Marine, be asked to endeavour to obtain m Bombay m inexpensive new or second hand lantern of the type used as head lights by ships and that if such is available, the telegraph office at Jask be supplied therewith 13 ^ 1 - ■ R e - i n replacement of the existing lantern which the Director, Persian Gulf Telegraphs states to be unsatisfactory.^* 104 clndt“1r e l Catalogue Nm To! pHtHsT ^ lantern ’ With aStlaI bUrner ° f ConJmridTinTfbief ° In rt ‘n' W ^ h enclosure to His Excellency the Naval rSSSfT^lS Karachf. 0 * 01 ’ ^ ^ ^ to The Director, fDirector, Persian Gulf Telegraphs to sident, No. 57-30, dated 30th March 1913. Enclosure of Serial 89. Telegram, dated Henjam, the 30th Malek4£43 COPY TO FOREIGN OFFICE /tfJUL1913 V ^ 1 From IS. E. Indo-European Telegraph Department, Persian To-Dmurn^^K^iRU-. Z. Cox, K.C.S.I., C.I.E., Political Resident in the Lights at Henjam^and Charbar were supplied in November 1907. Thev are for use for the ‘ ‘ Patrick Stewart 5 ’ when she comes to those places at night Lamps are Ditmar s gate lanterns, astral burners, 104 candle power No 7879 of Catalogue No. 10, plate 85. They are not satisfactory ^ 93 Telegram No. 1206-E.A., dated, the 3rd June 1913. From—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department, Simla, To—The Hon’ble Lieutenant-Colonel Sir P. Z. Cox, K.C.I.E. CIE Pol,Heal Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. ’ ‘ ’’ * Serial 89. Your telegram* dated the 23rd May, 925, Little Quoin lighthouse. Now that it has been decidedf to adhere to Little Quoin site do your instruc- t Serii 90 . tions to consign stools to Homer, Heniam ^ r v still hold good.n CONFIDENTIAL No. 1579, dated Bushire, the 18th (received 26th) May 1913, From— Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Percy Cox, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Political Resi dent in the Persian Gulf, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department, Simla. In continuation of my letter No. 1214, dated 13th April 1913, I have the honour to forward, for the information of the Government of India, a copy of Telegram from His Majesty’s Minister, Tehran, the marginally cited telegram which has to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, since been received from His Maiesty’s 0.19, ate it ay 1913. Minister at Tehran, with regard to the lights shown at the Russian Consulate-General. Telegram P., No. 198 , dated (and received) 16 th May 1913 . From—His Majesty’s Minister, Tehran, To—The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. His Majesty’s Ambassador at St. Petersburg has sent the following com munication to the Foreign Office, dated May 14th :— &lt;f With reference to your despatch No. 63. I have received an aide memoire from the Russian Government stating that instructions have been sent to the Russian Consul General at Bushire to the effect that he should not display anything in the nature of marine lights in the Russian Consulate-General there but only such lights as may be required to illuminate the immediate surround ings thereof. Telegram, No. 1004, dated Bushire, the 4th June 1913. From—The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department, Simla. Your telegram* dated 3rd. June, 1206-E.A., the reply is affirmative. * Serial 93.\ FfiClO; '¥■ U -Z/;, k 'S r |« •'‘- -w OA s *^v . v ‘-&lt; ^•U m t ^ i I ^* v/ ’ 13^ ; COPY TO FORRO-i uv- | 18 JUN1913 No. 940 , dated Bushire, the 23 rd (received 31 st) March 1913 . From— Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Percy Cox, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, To The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department, Simla. In continuation of my letter No. 434 , dated 9 th February 1913 , I have the honour to enclose, for the information of the Government of India, copies in original of further old correspondence regarding the buoying of the Shatt-ah Arab which I have received from the Political Resident in Turkish Arabia, Baghdad, who informs me that the above are all the papers on the subject which he has been able to trace, the Vizirial letter, unfortunately, not being forthcoming. 2 . I beg that I may be favoured with Letter from the Political Resident, Baghdad, to Governor General dated 4th October 1861. Letter from the Political Resident, Baghdad, to Governor General, dated 4th April 1862. Letter fiom the Political Resident, Baghdad, to Governor General, dated nth June 1862. Letter from the Political Resident, Baghdad, to Governor General, dated 5th August 1862. Governor General, to the Political Resident, Baghdad, dated 9th Zilhaj 1278. Letter from the Political Resident, Baghdad to the Government of Bombay, dated 5th October 1861, No. 81. printed copies as usual. Dated Baghdad, 4 th October 1861 . From—A. B. KembALL, Esq., His Majesty’s Consul-General, Baghdad, To—H ir Excellency Ahmed Towfik Pasha, Governor General, Baghdad. Your Excellency is apprized of the difficult navigation of the mouth of the Shatt-al-Arab and the dangers therefore which vessels generally though furnished with pilots and particularly large vessels, incur in attempting to cross the bar. On one or two occasions the Commodore commanding the British squadron in the Persian Gulf has endeavoured to alleviate the evil by placing buoys to mark the channel but owing to the want of proper care and attention or owing perhaps to the acts of mischievous persons the buoys in question have been lost or have disappeared. The frequent and almost unavoidable grounding of vessels in consequence between the entrance to the river and the dry banks off Fao having attracted the attention of the Bombay Government I have been instructed to impress upon Your Excellency the necessity of renewing the said buoys as well with a view of securing vessels from the risks and probable injury of grounding in bad weather as of saving time in making the passage to Basrah, and to invite Your Excellency to make arrangements for their effectual protection in future. I have the honour accordingly to bring the subject to Your Excellency’s notice and to suggest that instructions should be issued to the Turkish Administration and Naval Authorities at Basrah to afford their best aid and co-operation in a matter of such serious importance to the commerce of both Turkey and England in the Persian Gulf. / fcrW' Dated Baghdad, the 4 th April 1862 . From —A. B. KembALL, Esq., His Majesty’s Consul-General, Baghdad, To— His Excellency Muhammad Namik Pasha, Governor-General, Baghdad. Adverting to my letter to your predecessor under date 4 th October 1861 , I have the honour to submit to Your Excellency an Amer-nameh which has reached me on the subject of buoying the channel leading from the sea to the Shatt*al*Arab. Dated Baghdad, the nth June 1862 . From— A. B. KembALL, Esq., His Britannic Majesty’s Consul-General at Baghdad, To His Excellency Muhammad Namik Pasha, Governor General, Baghdad. in reply to Your Excellency’s letter dated 9 th Zilhaj, I have the honour to express my acknowledgments to Your Excellency for your ready co-operation in 142 the arrangements proposed for buoying the channel leading from the sea to the Shatt-al-Arab. Your Excellency will find however on reference to my letters that Your Excellency is in error in supposing that I specified 6 buoys or any number of buoys as being requisite for the purpose, nor am I in a. position now to submit to r Your Excellency any definite proposition on this subject seeing that I am myself ignorant of the number of buoys required. Under these circumstances and believing that the four buoys alluded to by Muneeb Pasha are in fact new ones, not long since placed on the banks by His Majesty’s squadron in the Persian Gulf. I propose to transmit a copy of Your Excellency’s letter under acknow ledgment to the British Resident at Bushire with a view to his consulting the Naval Officers on the spot and to his acquainting me for Your Excellency’s information, as well with the steps which have been taken, as with the necessity or otherwise for those which Your Excellency has proposed. Should Your Excellency desire it after the lapse of the hot months I will request the Commander of His Majesty “St. Comet’’ to associate himself with the Turkish Naval Authorities for the purpose of examining and reporting upon the state of the buoys. Dated Baghdad, the 5 th August 1862 . From—A, B. Kemball, Esq., His Majesty's Consul-General, Baghdad, To— His Excellency Muhammad Namik Pasha, Governor General, Baghdad. I have the honour to submit to Your Excellency a skeleton chart of the channel leading to the Shatt-al-Arab which I have just received from the British Resident in the Persian Gulf. It seems to be the opinion of the British Naval Officers that the buoys now placed 4 in number are sufficient and that they require merely to be represented of a red colour. After the hot w r eather the Resi dent at Bushire will detach a vessel to Basrah for the purpose of substituting for the anchors by which the buoys are now held, certain old guns now lying at Maghill, and notice of her coming will be duly given to Muneeb Pasha, Governor of Basrah, with a view to his deputing a Turkish officer, if Your Excellency should think proper, to be associated with the Commander of the said vessel on this duty. Translation, dated gth Zihaj 12J8. In conformity wdth your suggestion for the maintenance and repair of six buoys to mark the channel leading to the river at Basrah for the convenience of navigation Muneeb Pasha was instructed to repair those that might require repair and to add as many others as might be requisite. The said Pasha in reply writes to me by this opportunity that the 4 buoys at present existing are not in need of repair further than that the paint being worn off they must be repainted but that two additional buoys must be made for which anchors are required. The said anchors (he adds) are forthcoming in the Basrah Dockyard and the requisite c am cable can be manufactured there, yet as the cause of the destruction of uoys is owing to the crew of boats coveting and stealing the anchors, he con- si ers it the safest course to sink some of the old unserviceable guns now available a asr ah in lieu of anchors.fts however sheet iron is not procurable at Basrah W 6 J^ ecessar y buoys nor are the artificers there competent to Muneeb Pasha proposes that the said buoys should be made at the aghdad Foundry and forwarded to Basrah where the chains and guns and other ma ena s will be supplied for the purpose of placing them at the requisite spots, n consequence of this communication the necessary steps are now being taken ino. 01 , dated oaghdad, 5 th October X U w A 4 From A. B. Kemball, Esq., Political Resident, Turkish Arabia, T °—The Secretary to the Government of Bombay in the Political Department. Hnn’M./vf h0n ° Ur Sta . te for . the information of His Excellency the e Governor in Council that in conformity with the instructions conveyedH' to ■ *act taiw eral, BajIJii chart oi i Mi' and tlist iiktkb iubsti!ntii|ii not \j^i isb,Gorei nr ititeiMfo IkM ci [Dsano^ jnsc in your despatch No. 2328, dated 25th June last (received by me on the 25th ultimo) I have placed myself in communication with the authorities at Baghdad and Basrah—the Governor of the latter place being now here—regarding the pro* posal to buoy off the bar and channel of the Shatt-al-Arab between the entrance to the river and the dry banks oft Fao, and have received from them satis factory assurances of their willingness to co-operate in this measure. I think it right, however, to add my opinion that its efficiency and success in every particu lar must depend upon our own exertions. The little real control exercised in this quarter by Ottoman Governors as well as the limited tenure of their office (the plans and policy of the present incumbent being too often ignored and subverted by his successor) and the absence of any River Police or even of an effective Turkish vessel in the lower Euphrates must render the action of these officers in such cases nugatory if not undesirable, and though as a matter of form I purpose to solicit His Majesty’s Ambassador at the Porte to procure a Vizirial letter con firming their responsibility I believe that the supply of the buoys in question, their transport to the sites indicated and the arrangements necessary to their preserva tion in future must be undertaken by ourselves. In the last respect^ it must be sufficient perhaps that the Commanders of all vessels of war visiting Basrah should be directed to examine and report upon the state of the buoys, a standing order to this effect being also included in the Sailing Instructions of the Com mander of the schooner “ Georgiana” which vessel is now monthly engaged^ in conveying packets between Basrah and Bushire, and as an additional precaution in the event of the temporary withdrawal of the “ Georgiana ” I would avail myself of every favourable opportunity to depute the “ Comet ” to the bar of the river for the purpose stated. On former occasions that buoys have been placed to mark the channel leading to the Shatt-al*Arab I understand that their disappearance has been attributed to the ill-will of the pilots located on the island of Kharag whose means of subsistence seemed to be threatened thereby, but so desirable in every point of view must still I conceive be the maintenance of an efficient body of pilots that I presume no intention to exist of superseding their employment in the case of British vessels and a notice to that effect would doubtless reconcile them to the intended arrangements. With respect to the last paragraph of Lieutenant Chitty’s letter 1 incline to think that some account should be made of the shifting of banks during an interva of four years the buoys referred to having been placed during the Persian War and that contingencies of this nature must at least be worthy of attention hereater. Resident in the Persian Gulf. CiFD—oo—7-4-13—GCBP SimlaTelegram, No. 726 D., dated the 18th March 1913. From—The Foreign Secretary, Delhi, To—The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Your telegram, 8th March, 415. Little Quoin. Action approved. Telegram P., No. 519, dated the 16th (received 17tb) March 1913. From—The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, To—The Foreign Secretary, Delhi. Lighting and buoyage of Persian Gulf. Reference Minister’s telegram which was repeated to you on 12th instant under my No. 453, and Secretary of State’s telegram to Viceroy of 15th instant repeated to me in reference thereto. It is essential that lighting arrangements on both sides of Gulf should be controlled by same management, and I strongly deprecate any Anglo-Persian Commission ; nor does there seem to be any need for weakening our position in such a way. The third light-house was only item in regard to which we required any co-operation from the Persian Government. Let us leave the Persian Government out of the question as heretofore and drop this item for the present, if they are intractable in regard to it and if pressure cannot be brought to bear and if neither Kais device nor Shah Alam alternative (which were both seriously considered by Lighting Committee —vide page 2 of their report) are regarded favourably. There is no urgent necessity on navigational grounds. Meanwhile, without attracting any more serious attention from the Persian Government than they have shown in past 50 years, all other items ' have been put in hand. Probably in this case as in many others what diplo macy cannot effect will be effected by lapse of time. Telegram, No. 196, dated the 14th March 1913. From—The Assistant Director, Royal Indian Marine, Bombay, To—The Secretary to the Government of the India, Marine Department. Confidential. Reference your letter 72—151 M., 4th July 1912. Buoys ready for despatch. Please wire sanction to despatch. Telegram, No. 197, dated the 15th March 1913. From The Assistant Director, Royal Indian Marine, Bombay, To—The Secretary to the Government of India, Marine Department. Confidential Reference your telegram, 595—46 M., 13th instant. jDaniam buoy. New moorings will be completed next week. Shatt-el-Arab 196^14d/ 1 * an t* t Sanctl0n to des P atch Jask buoy awaited—wte my telegram, ? 3 fv/n &gt; s n 1 ( ■■ I1 I Telegram No 860-D., dated the 29th March 1913. From The Secretary to the Government of I^dia in the Foreign Department, Delhi, Tc-=-Lieuteant-Oolonpl Sir Fergy Cox, E CJ.E,, e.S.L, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bnshire. Your letter 608, February 23rd. Bushire Residency lights. Your action in engaging suitable man locally on Rs. 25 a month approved. Telegram P., No. 6.-210, dated the 29th March 1913. From —The ^Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department. To^LiRUTENANTrCoLONEL Sir Pbrcy Cox, E.C.I.E, C.S.I., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Please expedite reply to Secretary of State’s telegram of 17th instant regarding lighthouse at Little Quoin. Telegram, No. 609 E.-A., dated the 1st April 1913. From—The Foreign Secretary, Delhi, To—The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Reference telegram from Secretary of State for India, 18th March, tt-nouse mechanic. Please act accordingly.Telegram Ho.610, dated the 30th (reed.31st) March 1913* From - The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, B u s h i r e. To The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department, Simla* Your telegram 210-C* Nature of surface of newly proposed site is apparently precisely the same. Difference in height between the two sites &amp;an be seen from Persian Gulf Pilot. Mir* Hood of Trinity House visited both places and will probably (be) able to answer Secretary of State for India*s question. Failing that, I would suggest that Trinity House be asked to state precisely what they want to know and that on receipt of reply Senior Naval Officer be asked to take Homer there to examine and report*rUl AWnY Reference Paper. Political and Secret Department. Register No. ojS/n ‘n 191 S. Referred to ^ iqij ^£&gt; of) Cj? ^&lt;1 x 1^305. 1.2430. 500.— 11/1911.lir. Trinity House to India Offic e . Trinity Jtousu, P^iSIAM GULF. 2Sth April 1913. I um iri/arTivd by Haasrs. Thunae th&amp;&amp; ths i r&amp;caiv&amp;d from Bombay on the 25th instant a request to forward direct instructions for the maintenance of the Lights for Tcmb Island, Little (no m, ana the Lightship nou) being built. I thought it ibest to inform yon that tliis commnication ho a been received from the Director of the Fur inn and to state that the instruct ions will he prepared and forwarded as soon as possible. instructions for the erection of the worn at Tomb Island have already been forwarded to the Persian Gulf. It will be sane little time before I can comply with the request with regal'd to the other stations, as the work has not yet be*n finally app ro v&amp;d. I a/a, dc., (Signed) T. Matthews. C ' ^ 2 MAY 1913 SECRETARY'S N2 18 mrnmm.,, ■am -V ss* ? ^ ^ u | o ! Bnclosvre ? ' ■ ++ er from F r '~ ' India. A'C - i/ii i, d**is' 20 i vl A h I ^ « 0 Telegram No. 263 , dated (and received) the nth February 1913 . From—The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department, Delhi. Following lights were established 9th February at Bushire. Firstly, outer anchorage in 23 feet distance 4*2 miles bearing S. 84 W. from Residency flagstaff: gas buoy showing an occulting white light 10 seconds. ^ Light 7 seconds dark 3 seconds 300 candles. Secondly, inner anchorage in 17 feet distance of 2-5 miles bearing N. 53 W. from Residency flagstaff : gas buoy showing an occulting red light ten seconds. Light seven seconds dark three seconds 300 candles. Addressed Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, and repeated to Foreign Office, Minister and Director, Royal Indian Marine, for Admiral,Telegram No. 270 , dated nth (received 12 th) February 1913 . From—The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department, Delhi. My telegram No, 263. Have notified British shipping agents but in absence of reply to my despatch dated 13th December, No. 3314, I have taken no fur ther annunciatory action. Addressed Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, and repeated to British Minister, Tehran, reference my despatch No. 95, and Foreign Office, reference my despatch No. 13, Political, 13th December. Telegram P., No. 271 , dated nth (received ! 2 th) February 1913 , From—The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, To—The Secretary, Foreign Department. (Repeated to Foreign Office, London^ Please refer to my telegram of the 9th instant, and despatch from His Majesty’s Ambassador at Constantinople No. 898, dated the 24th October. I have just received copy by post of the despatch from Consul at Basrah to His Majesty's Ambassador at Constantinople dated 4th February in which former reports that Turkey’s lightship is in imminent danger of foundering on the strength of the information supplied by the “ representative of the lighthouse administration.” Until the vessel discussed (Viceroy’s telegram of 2nd November to Secretary of State for India) takes shape is it not possible that we could take opportunity to send some hulk of our own there forthwith to act as lightship ?CONFIDENTIAL. c&gt;. No. 434, dated Bushire, the 9th February 1913. From— Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Percy Cox, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, To—The Hon’ble Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Henry McMahon, G.C.V.O., K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department, Simla. In continuation of my telegram No. 260, dated February 9th, I have the honour to report for the information of the Government of India that whilst ex amining the records of this office with a view to obtaining details of the airange- Vide Residency letter No. 3101, dated 24th ments made foi the buoying and light- November 1912 . ing of Bushire harbour since 1863 by His Majesty’s ships and the Government of India my attention was drawn to inci dental references on the record to correspondence which has passed under flying seal through this office between the Government of Bombay and the Political Resident in Turkish Arabia, with reference to the buoyage of the Shatt-al-Arab bar. 2. I therefore asked the Resident, Baghdad, to be good enough to furnish me with such correspondence on the subject as was available in his archives : this he was good enough to do, and I now have the honour to submit for the information of Government, a precis of correspondence, so far as I have had access thereto, upon the subject since 1861. 3. It will be seen that the bar was first buoyed by us during the war of 1857 in order to facilitate the passage up river of His Majesty’s transports: and that the buoys then laid down were renewed in 1862 by the Government of Bombay, under whose instructions the Political Resident in Turkish Arabia had applied to His Majesty’s Embassy for a Wazirial letter to the Governor-General of Baghdad, directing the latter to co-operate with His Majesty’s ships to this end. 4. The Wazirial letter is not very explicit, but read in conjunction with sub sequent correspondence which passed between our representative at Baghdad and the local authorities, it is clear that the Turks were kept fully and explicitly in formed of all our proceedings in the matter, and that so far from raising any ob jection, they promised us every assistance and co-operation, although they abstained themselves from taking any active measures in the matter. 5. Two documents of some interest and importance are not at the moment available, viz. : (1) From the Political Resident in Turkish Arabia, Baghdad, to the Gov ernment of Bombay, No. 81, dated 5th October 1861. (2) The original Turkish text of the Wazirial instructions and subsequent correspondence on the subject between the Governor-General and the Political Resident in Turkish Arabia. I am requesting the Political Department of the Government of Bombay, to whom I am sending a copy of this letter, to be so good as to obtain from their records, and send to Government and myself, copies of the first mentioned paper ; while in regard to the second I am inviting the Acting Resident at Baghdad to be so good as to ascertain if the correspondence is available in his office, and if so to supply copies. I am sending copies of this letter with enclosures to His Majesty’s Foreign Office, to the Political Secretary to the Government of Bombay and the Political Resident in Turkish Arabia. C724FD 24. *’&gt; Precis of the history of the buoyage of the (1) QUENT TO 1857, (2) Bahrein. Shatt-al-Arab subse- In letter dated Busliire March 27th 1861, the Commander of His Majesty’s steamer Zenobia (Indian Navy) addressed the Senior Naval Officer in the Persian Gulf recommending that the Shatt-al-Arab be buoyed, and stating that the buoys then on the bar were in a very bad state of repair. The Commander-in-Chief of the Indian Navy transmitted the proposal to the Government of Bombay with his support and suggested that the subject be brought to the notice of the Turkish Government. No. 4(58, dated nth June 1861. . The Mowing resolution was passed upon his letter by the Government of Bombay. “ This proposal approved, the papers to be transferred to the Political Department with a view to the necessary negotiation.” The Political Department addressed the Political Besident in Turkish Arabia No. i:328, dated 25th June 1861. ment on the subject. on 25th June 1861 requesting him to enter into negotiations with the Turkish Govern- The Political Besident in Turkish Arabia replied to the Government of Bombay No. 81 , dated 5th October 1861 . under flying seal to the Political Besident in the Persian Gulf. A copy of this letter is not at present traceable.* Captain Felix Jones, the Political Besident in the Persian Gulf in transmitting this letter addressed the Government of Bombay on matters of detail connected No. 49, dated 23rd October 1861. TP^ ee P an( ^ care buoys, and stating his opinion that “ he attributed the breaking adrift of those laid down in the expedition to the Euphrates in 1861f to fair wear and tear of sea and weather and not to the ill-disposition of the Kharag pilots ” harmless people who were aware that there was no intention of superseding them in their occupation by buoying the channel. No. 226, dated 16th January 1862 . follow :— The Government of Bombay replied to the Political Besident in Turkish Arabia as t Thus in original: appears to be a copyist’s error for Bushire. I am instructed to state that the project of maintaining buoys for the proper navigation of our vessels on the passage be tween Busreh and BaghdadJ is generally admitted to be most desirable. Bearing in mind also the probability of steamer communication being shortly established between India, the Persian Gulf and Busreh, and the increase of trade which may be anticipated in consequence, the Honourable the Governor-in-Council is of opinion that the advantages to be derived from the measure would sufficiently warrant the whole of its estimated outlay being borne by the British Govern ment. “ The Commander-in-Chief of the Indian Navy will accordingly be re quested to take the necessary steps for laying down the buoys and for efficiently maintaining them in position, seeking your co-opera tion and that of the Besident in the Persian Gulf in carrying out the proposed arrangement. “ (4). I am at the same time desired to request that you will apply through the British Ambassador at the Sublime Porte for a Wazirial letter as proposed in your communication under acknowledgment *Note .—Political Department, Bombay asked to provide a copy. ■\Note .—In a report dated December 24th 1861, the Commander-in-Chief of the Indian Navy reported that the buoys on the Shatt-al-Arab bar, then 2 in number, were all that were left of several buoys laid down by His Majesty’s ships during the Persian war for the purpose of guiding vessels of war and transports up the river. 3The Political Resident in Turkish Arabia endorsed this despatch as follows to His Majesty’s Vice-Consul, Busreh, under date 25th April 1862. « * * * yi r Rogers is informed that assurances have been eiven by Namik Pasha of the willing co-operation of the Turkish authorities in the manner desired by the British Ambassador ” end in acknowledging its receipt to His Majesty’s Embassy he stated that judg- ana m a g s j n g f rom the assurances of His Excellency No. 14, dated 23rd April 1862 . Namik Pasha, he had every reason to be- lieve that the co-operation of the Turkish authorities would be afforded for the purpose of buoying the bar in the manner desired by His Majesty s Embassy. In the meantime, the Political Resident in Turkish Arabia had addressed His Majesty’s Ambassador at Constantinople No. so, dated 9th October 1861. stating that in conformity with the ins- * Dated 4th October 1861 enclosed to Am- tructions of the Bombay Government, bassador in above despatch, copy not available, he had addressed a letter* to His Excel lency Ahmad Tewfik Pasha and sending an extract of his despatch (No. 81-82, dated 5th October 1861) to the Government of Bombay, requesting His Majesty’s Ambassador to procure a Wazirial letter to the address of the Governors of Baghdad and Busreh in the sense of his communication to Ahmad Tewfik Pasha. His Majesty’s Ambassador repliedf transmitting a Wazirial letter to the Governor-General of Baghdad, directing t No. 3, dated 22nd February 1862. him to co-operate with His Majesty’s Naval officers in placing and repairing the buoys necessary to mark the bar and channel leading to the Shatt-al-Arab. Lieutenant-Colonel A. B. (afterwards Sir Arnold) Kemball shortly afterwards addressed the Government of Bombay No. 25, dated 1st April 1862. reporting receipt of the above despatch, and of a Wazirial instruction to the Covernor-General of Baghdad, in which that functionary is directed to co-operate with His Majesty’s Naval officers in placing and repairing the buoys necessary to mark the bar and channel leading to the Shatt-al-Arab. He enclosed the follow- Ongmai Turkish note not traceable. j n g translation of the “ Wazirial Instruc tion ” in question. “ No. 156. From the Ottoman Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs to His Excellency Namik Pasha, dated 11th Shaban 1278. “ Enclosed for your information is the copy of a translation of a despatch received from His Majesty’s Ambassador regarding the repair when necessary of the buoys placed at the mouth of the Shatt-al-Arab with a view to facilitate the navigation of the channel. Reference having been made to His Majesty’s Consul-General at Baghdad on the subject of putting the said buoys in a good condition and of obtaining the materials necessary thereto, and it having been proposed that assistance if need be should be rendered to this end by the British squadron, and since it seems certain from the representations made, that the said buoys, if left in their present state would not be secured from injury, you are hereby desired accordingly after making due enquiries on the spot to take the requisite steps, for repairing the buoys in question and for preserv ing them continually in good condition, reporting to us the result.’* The following is a translation of the note from His Majesty’s Ambassador referred to above :— “ From His Majesty’s Ambassador at Constantinople'to the Ottoman Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, dated November 12th 1861. “ Instructions have been received by His Majesty’s Consul-General at Baghdad from Bombay regarding the maintenance of buoys at the entrance of the channel leading to the Shatt-al-Arab, and the adop tion of measures for preserving and protecting them, with a view tohis entering into negotiation with the local authorities on the sub ject, His Majesty’s Consul-General accordingly addressed a letter to His Excellency the Governor of Baghdad under date 4th October 1861 of which a copy is herewith submitted to Your Excellency. “ Should the suggestion of His Majesty’s Government meet with concur rence, I request that I may be furnished with a Wazirial Instruc tional in the sense of the above letter either to the Governor of Baghdad or to the Mutasarif of Busreh, for transmission to those functionaries in order that timely precautions may be taken, and in that case I may assure Your Excellency that every assistance will be afforded by His Britannic Majesty’s Government and by His Britannic Majesty’s Naval forces in that quarter to further the end desired. On June 19th 1862, Colonel Kemball wrote to the Besident at Bushire enclos ing a letter from the Wall of Baghdad on No. 14, dated 19th June 1862. su i)ject of the buoying of the channel, together with his reply thereto. They ran as follows In conformity with our suggestions for the maintenance and repair of six buoys to mark the channel Dated 9th Zilbaj 1278 = 6th June 1862. leading to the river af Busreh for the convenience of navigation Munib Pasha was instructed to repair those that might require repairs and to add as many other as might be requisite. The said Pasha in reply writes to me by this opportunity that the four buoys at present existing are not in need of repair further than that the paint being worn off they must be repainted but that two additional buoys must be made for which anchors (he adds) are forthcoming in the Busreh Dock yard and the requisite chain cable can be manufactured there. Yet as the cause of the destruction of buoys is owing to the crews of boats coveting and stealing the anchors he considers it to be the safest course to sink some of the old unserviceable guns now avail able at Busreb in lieu of anchors. As, however, sheet iron is not procurable at Busreh wherewith to make the necessary buoys, noi are there artificers competent to make them, Munib Pasha proposes that the said buoys should be made at the Baghdad Foundry and forwarded to Busreh where the chains and guns and other materials will be supplied for the purpose of placing them at the requisite spots. In consequence of this communication the necessary steps are now being taken here. Reply. (Dated 11th June 1862). In reply to Your Excellency’s letter dated 9th Zilhaj, I have the honour to express my acknowledgments to Your Excellency for your ready co-operation in the arrangements proposed for buoying the channel leading from the sea to the Shatt-al-Arab. Your Excellency will find, however, on reference to my letters that Your Excellency is in error in supposing that I specified six buoys or any number of buoys as being requisite for the purpose ; nor am I in a position now to submit to Your Excellency any definite proposition on this subject seeing that I am myself ignorant of the numbers of buoys required. Under these circumstances and believing that the four buoys alluded to by Munib Pasha are in fact r ew ones not long since placed on the banks by His Majesty’s Squadron in the Persian Gulf, I propose to transmit a copy of Your Excellency’s letter under acknowledgment to the British Resident at Bushire, with a view to his consulting the Naval officers on the spot and to his acquainting me for Your Excellency’s information as well with the steps which have been taken as with the necessity or otherwise for those which Your Excellency has proposed.m m A \ I v. No. 15, dated 16th July 1862. Should Your Excellency desire it, after the lapse of the hot months, I will request the Commander of His Majesty’s steamer “ Comet ” to asso ciate himself with the Turkish Naval authorities for the' purpose of examining and reporting upon the state of the buoys. In forwarding the above communications to Bushire Lieutenant-Colonel Kemball remarked that though he believed Namik Pasha to be quite sincere in the intention he announced, it would not be prudent to count too confidently upon its execution, and expressed the apprehension that the Naval authorities at Busreh might not be competent to lay down the buoys efficiently. The Resident at Bushire replied on the 5th July to this communication stat ing that as soon as suitable vessel was available to send up to Busreh he would invite the Turkish Naval authorities to co-operate with the British Naval Commander in the laying of the buoys but pointing out at the same time that the bar had already been fuhy buoyed by His Majesty’s ships ; four buoys from Bombay were duly laid by His Majesty’s ships. On 16th July Colonel Kemball wrote to Bushire that His Majesty’s ship “Berenice” had landed 5 old guns at Busreh to be fitted to moorings for the four buoys in place of anchors, and that only four being needed, the 5th was to be returned to Bombay ; he enclosed at the same time a copy of the following note which he had addressed to the Wali of Baghdad. I have the honour to submit herewith to Your Excellency a skeleton chart of the channel leading to the Shatt-al-Arab, which I have just re ceived from the British Resident in the Persian Gulf. It seems to be the opinion of the British Naval officers that the buoys now plac ed, 4 in number, are sufficient and that they require merely to be repainted of a red colour. After the hot weather the Resident at Bushire will detach a vessel to Busreh for the purpose of substitut ing for the anchors by which the buoys are now held certain old guns n^w lying at Magil* and notice of her coming will be duly given to Munib Pasha, Governor of Busreh, with a view to his deputing a Turkish officer, if Your Excellency should think proper to be associated with the Commander of the said vessel on this duty. A proposal to place a beacon on the Shatt-al-Arab bar was raised by Colonel Pelly in his letter No. 95, dated December 5th 1862, and subsequently referred to in his letter dated 22nd June 1863 and 23rd July 1863. On 23rd July 1863 Colonel Pelly made proposals to the Government of Bom bay for the retention at Busreh of a suitable quantity of spare gear for buoying purposes. He further stated that “ there was a beacon put ashore at Fao during the war. This the Arabs have made ver to the Sheikh of Koweit, under alleged orders from this Residency : no such orders are on record. I am now writing to the Sheikh of Kowuit to return the beacon, when I will cause it to be erected at the entrance of the Shatt-al-Arab on a two-fathom bank.” In the same communication he adverts to a request made by him for a spare hulk, which was misconstrued into a demand for a new vessel by the late Naval Department. Resolution No. 2894, dated nth September His proceedings were fully approved by ises. the Government of Bombay. On 21st November 1863, Colonel Pelly asked the Government of Bombay to send up a 24' buoy by next Government vessel: a first class buoy with a 28 cwt. mooring anchor was accordingly sent up on 27th February 1866. ( 0This buoy was carried away in December 1868 and stranded on Bubian but was replaced in March 1869 : a second buoy was stranded on Halul Island in the same year and the Sheikh of Abu Dhabi asked to send it to Bushire. The Residency Agent reported that he found it on Jazirat-al-Jarnain : subse- % quently the Chief of Abu Dhabi alleged that the buoy had been destroyed by the boatmen of Khalifa bin Salim of Debai. The provision of a new buoy to replace it was sanctioned by the Bombay Government. These Shatt-al-Arab buoys were washed away in 1880 and the Government of India decided not to replace them. The Turkish authorities placed a buoy on the bar on the 15th May 1880, but it was also washed away on the following day and apparently not replaced. Messrs. Gray Paul &amp; Co. in reporting the fact, remarked that it was the first buoy that had been contributed by the Turks. One of the same buoys was washed away on January 14th 1887 and stranded on the Arab Coast, 50 miles east of Koweit {i.e., somewhere on Bubian Island) ; Sheikh Abdullah bin Sabah was accordingly asked by the Resident to take care of it. Buoys were put down by British India Steam Navigation Company in 1891, 1894, 1899, 1902 and 1903. A buoy was placed by the Royal Indian Marine ship ' Lawrence ” in 1900 to replace the outer bar buoy, which had gone adrift. II.— Bahrein. In 1874 the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf suggested to the Govern ment of India the desirability of placing a large buoy at the entrance of Bahrein harbour ; the proposal was approved by the Government of India, and the Gov ernment of Bombay were requested to take the necessary steps through the British India Steam Navigation Company. At least two buoys were, however, apparent ly laid down by Government, as in 1879 the Commander of His Majesty's ship “ Beacon ” mentions the existence of an “ outer ” buoy, both in need of repair, and states that he believes them to be the property of the British India Steam Navigation Company (which would not appear to be the case, though they were no doubt laid by one of their ships), whilst in a later letter the Resident men tions 4 buoys as needing replacement. The Government of India, however, had ruled in 1875, in case of the buoys on the Shatt-al-Arab bar, that they could not be replaced at Government expense, and this ruling was quoted by Government as applicable equally to Bahrein. In 1882, the Political Resident again addressed the Government of India in connection with the loss of a Government buoy at Bahrein, stating that he had been privately informed that it was in contemplation to replace certain of the buoys in the Persian Gulf, and submitting that “ the right of control of all buoys in these seas might possibly be of advantage in certain contingencies. ” The Government of India replied, however, that “ it was not at present the intention of Government to replace the buoys in the Persian Gulf.' Buoys were subsequently laid by the British India Steam Navigation Com pany and maintained by them until taken over by the Government of India. G. M. Press, Simla.—No. C-724 F. D. —18-2-13.—44.—M.D.No. 154-A., dated Delhi, 10th February 1913. From—E. M. Cook, Esq., I.C.S., Under Secretary to the Government of India, Finance Department, To—The Comptroller and Auditor General. I am directed to inform yon that it has been decided that all expenditure for lighting and buoying the Persian Gulf incurred by the Marine, Political and Public Works Departments will he debited to Civil (Political), and that the accounts officers of the Departments concerned will be held responsible for auditing the expenditure incurred in their respective departments and will pass on the charges to the Comptroller, India Treasuries, for final adjustment. The Comptroller, India Treasuries, will then bring all the charges together and debit the moiety to be met from Indian revenues against a minor head^ 4 Light ing and buoying of the Persian Gulf *’ to be opened under the major head « 25—Political ” in the India estimates. The moiety to he met by the Imperial Exchequer will he passed on by him to England through the remittance account.L Telegram No. 328 ; dated (and received) 23rd February 1913, From Lieutenant-Colonel Sir P. Z. Cox, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Political Resident m the Persian Gulf, Bushire, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department, Delhi. Your telegram of 12th January 20-C., and my telegram dated 22nd February 3^1. In order to enable work to be commenced on Little Quoin immediately mechanic arrives measures need to be taken at once for construe- non of safe landing space on rock for storage of fresh water and for construction temporary quarters for workmen and staff by local labour before hot weather commences. Whole-time service of steam tender for joint use of Little Quoin and iamb works has thus become essential. Additional material and staff also required m regard to whom Public Works Department authorities are being addressed separately.^ As regards steam tender “Lawrence” is already fully occupied with buoying work and my own requirements and cannot possiblv assist, moreover she will soon need to be docked. Would suggest a launch such as “ Karanja ” be detailed for light-house work pending arrival of Imlit-liouse tender need for which is becoming daily more lively. Addressed Foieign; repeated Director, Loyal Indian Marine, for Secretary to Government of Bombay, Public Works Department. Telegram No. 330, dated 23rd (received 24th) February 1913. From-LIEUTENANT-COLONEL Sm P. Z. Cox, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department, Delhi. I beg to invite attention of Government to present position in regard to various items oh lighting and bouying scheme and to beg that action in regard to them may be expedited. Firstly lighthouse tender, tnh? my telegram of 23rd February 328. She is already needed badly for current work which is being delayed there being no prospect of provision during next few months. I would suggest despatch of suitable vessel for temporary use in connection with care of bouys, light-house erection and wireless installations. Secondl y Kuwait buoys, vide ray despatch dated 23rd November 3075. Early replacement is very necessary. Ihiidiy Bahrain unlit buoys, vide my despatch of 13th October 2594. New moorings not yet received. Fourthly Shatt-el-Arab buoys. Two of these require early replacement, vide my despatch of 13th October 2599. Fifthly Jask Pro No. 590 in Secret E„ October 1912, Nos. buoys, vide first enclosure to Foreign 51 ' 3 ' 620 Department endorsement 1729-EA, 2nd August. Lastly I hope that early decision may he reached on the subject of my despatch dated 11th August 1905. Lawrence is now almost continuously employed in connection with lighting and buoying scheme and the adjustment of miscellaneous expenditure and undefined responsibility in connection with the establishment of lights is causing inconvenience. Addressed Foreign; repeated Director, Ptoyal Indian Marine. Telegram No. 334, dated 24th (received 25th) February 1913. From— Lieutrnant-Colonel Sir P. Z. Cox, K C.I.E., C.S.I., Political Resident in the Pesian Gulf, Bushire, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department, Delhi. My telegrams 321 and 328 repeated to you through Director, Loyal Indian Marine. In order to enable work to be carried on on Little Quoin, Homer requires services of fully qualified subordinate accustomed to class of work to be done. He specially recommended obtaining i y wire services of Air. I. U. R. Narayan, Supervisor, Light-house, Burma. Indents for additional labour and plant will be sent direct to Indus right bank. Homer’s recommenda tion has my support and I trust that services of 1. If. L. Narayan or failing him of other capable experienced supervisor will be obtained as early as possible. Lepeated Foreign, Delhi ; addressed Secretary to Government, Bombay, Public Works Department, who will kindly repeat to Director, Loyal Indian Marine, Foreign Department will kindly take any action that will facilitate and expedite deputation I. U. L. Narayan by Govemment, Burma. C.92FD— 30-5-3-13—GCBP Simla.1 nr I From Viceroy, 29th March 1913. Foreign Secret. Your telegram of 15th March. Lighting and buoying of Persian Gulf. We agree that proposals of Persian Government in their present shape are quite unacceptable. Cox strongly deprecates acceptance of suggestions for an Anglo-Persian Commission, on ground that it is essential that lighting arrangements on both sides of Gulf should be controlled by same management. We agree. The acceptahce of such a commission would, in effect; be a surrender of our present position, and partial admittance of Persia would be opposed to principle of our policy, viz., to secure from her, as opportunity offers, recognition of our prescriptive rights to control buoying and lighting in the Gulf. Moreover, participation of Persia might lead to preferment of similar claims on the part of Turkey. In the circumstances Cox recommends that, as there is no urgent necessity on navigational grounds for immediate erection of lighthouse on Sheikh Shuaib Island, this item should be dropped for the present. As all other items in the programme have been put in hand without attracting any more serious attention from the Persian Government than they have shown in the past 50 years, we support Cox’s view. The project could be revived later if a suitable opportunity occurred, or it should be found possible to provide funds for provision of a lightship instead of the proposed lighthouse. Vide paragraph 3 of India Office letter of 14th October 1912 to Foreign Office.Minute Paper. PUT A\N' fc v Secret Department. •Sjjf Letter from ^ w Dated Rec. v ? /3 1915 Date. Initials. Under Secretary Secretary of State Committee /(f /f (XaA ?sIy&lt; ff Under Secretary Secretary of State SUBJECT. U^{aJL; zA - Aa^u^.[Tins Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government,] Lieutenant-Colonel Sir P. Cox to Sir Edward Grey.—[Received March 1.) (No. 6. Confidential.) gi r Bushire, February 9, 1913. IN continuation of my telegram No. 260, dated the 9th February, I have the of the Shatt-el-Arab bar by British authorities since 1857. I have, &amp;c. P. Z. COX, Lieutenant-Colonel, British Resident in IN continuation of my telegram No. 260, dated the 9th February, I have the honour to report, for the information of the Government of India, that whilst examinino' the records of this office with a view to obtaining details of the arrangements made for the buoying and lighting of Bushire Harbout since 186 3 by Her Majesty’s ships and the Government of India, * my attention was drawn to incidental references on the record to correspondence which has passed under flying seal through this office between the Government of Bombay and the political resident in Turkish Arabia with reference to the buoyage of the Shatt-el-Arab bar. 2. I therefore asked the resident, Bagdad, to be good enough to furnish me with such correspondence on the subject as was available in his archives , this he was good enough to do, and I now have the honour to submit, for the information of the Government, a precis of correspondence, so far as I have had access theieto, upon the subject since 1861. , . . nocr7 . 3. It will be seen that the bar was first buoyed by us during the war ol 1857 in order to facilitate the passage up river of Her Majesty’s transports; and that the buoys then laid down were renewed in 1862 by the Government of Bombay, under whose instructions the political resident in Turkish Arabia had applied to Her Majesty s Embassy for a vizierial letter to the Governor-General of Bagdad, directing the latter to co-operate with Her Majesty’s ships to this end. &gt; . . 4. The vizierial letter is not very explicit, but read in conjunction with subsequent correspondence which passed between our representative at Bagdad and the local authorities it is clear that the Turks were kept fully and explicitly informed of all our proceedings in the matter, and that so far from raising any objection they promised us every assistance and co-operation, although they abstained themselves from taking any active measures in the matter. 5. Two documents of some interest and importance are not at the moment available, viz. :— (1.) From the political resident in Turkish Arabia, Bagdad, to the Government of Bombay, No. 81, dated the 5th October, 1861. . . . (2.) The original Turkish text of the vizierial instructions and _ subsequent correspondence on the subject between the Governor-General and the political resident in Turkish Arabia. I am requesting the political department of the Government of Bombay, to whom I am sending a copy of this letter, to be so good as to obtain trom their records, and * Vide residency letter dated November 24, 1912. [2839 a— 1 ] B ASIATIC TURKEY AND ARABIA. [March 1.] CONFIDENTIAL. Section 1. D [9670] No. 1. honour to enclose, for your information, a copy of a letter with enclosures, which I have addressed to the Government of India, on the subject of the buoying and lighting the Persian Gulf, and Eis Majesty's Consul- General for Pars, &amp;c. Enclosure 1 in No. 1. Lieutenant-Colonel Sir P Cox to Government of India, (Confidential.) Bushire, February 9, 1913. Sir.wmmmmmmm Jn 2 send to Government and myself, copies of the first-mentioned paper ; while in regard to \ the second I am inviting the acting resident at Bagdad to be so good as to ascertain if \ the correspondence is available in his office ; and, if so, to supply copies. I am sending copies of this letter with enclosures to His Majesty’s Foreign Office, to the political secretary to the Government of Bombay, and the political resident in Turkish Arabia. I have, &amp;c. P. Z. COX, Lieutenant-Colonel, British Resident in the Persian Gulf, and His Majesty's Consul- General for Pars, &amp;c. Enclosure 2 in No. 1, Precis of the History of the Buoyage of the (1) Shatt-el-Arab subsequent to 1857; (2) Bahrein. (1.) Shatt-el-Arab. IN a letter dated Bushire, the 27th March, 1861, the commander of Her Majesty’s steamer “ Zenobia ” (Indian navy), addressed the senior naval officer in the Persian Gulf recommending that the Shatt-el-Arab be buoyed, and stating that the buoys then on the bar were in a very bad state of repair. The commander-in-chief of the Indian navy transmitted the proposal to the Government of Bombay with his support, and suggested that the subject be brought to the notice of the Turkish Government. The following resolution, dated the 17th June, 1861, was passed upon his letter by i the Government of Bombay- \ / “ This proposal approved, the papers to be transferred to the political departmeut, with a view to the necessary negotiation,” The political department addressed the political resident in Turkish Arabia on the 25th June, 1861, requesting* him to enter into negotiations with the Turkish Govern ment on the subject. The political resident in Turkish Arabia replied (the 5th October, 1861) to the Government of Bombay under flying seal to the political resident in the Persian Gulf. A copy of this letter is not at present traceable. Captain Felix Jones, the political resident in the Persian Gulf, in transmitting this letter, addressed the Government of Bombay (the 23rd October, 1861) on matters of detail connected with the upkeep and care of the buoys, and stating his opinion that he attributed the breaking adrift of those laid down in the expedition to the Euphrates in 186If to fair wear and tear of sea and weather and not to the ill- disposition of the Kharag pilots, ’ harmless people who were aware that there was no intention of superseding them in their occupation by buoying the channel. . The Government of Bombay replied (the 16th January, 1862) to the political resident in Turkish Arabia as follows :— .... I am instructed to state that the project of maintaining buoys for the proper navigation of our vessels on the passage between Bussorah and Bagdad| is generally admitted to be most desirable. Bearing in mind also the probabilitv of steamer communication being shortly established between India, the Persian Gulf, and Bussorah, and the increase of trade which may be anticipated in consequence, the honourable the Governor in Council is of opinion that the advantages to be derived from the measure would sufficiently warrant the whole of its estimated outlay being borne by the British Government. I he commander-in-chief of the Indian navy will accordingly be requested to take the necessary steps for laying down the buoys, and for efficiently maintaining * Political department, Bombay, asked to provide a copy. f Ina report dateu December 24 , 1861 , the commander-in-chief of the Indian navy reported that the buoys on the bhatt-el-Arab bar, then two in number, were all that were left of several buoys laid down by Her Majesty s ships during- the Persian war for the purpose of guiding- vessels of war and transports up t Thus in original; appears to be a copyist’s error for Bushire.them in position, seeking your co-operation and that of the resident in the Persian Gulf in carrying out the proposed arrangement. “ (4.) I am at the same time desired to request that you will apply through the British Ambassador at the Sublime Porte for a vizierial letter, as proposed in your ^^communication under acknowledgment.” The political resident in Turkish Arabia endorsed this despatch as follows to Her Majesty’s vice-consul, Bussorah, under date the 25th April, 1862 :— “ . . . . Mr. Bogers is informed that assurances have been given by Namik Pasha of the willing co-operation of the Turkish authorities in the manner desired by the British Ambassador.*” And in acknowledging its receipt to Her Majesty’s Embassy (the 23rd April, 1862) he stated that, judging from the assurances of his Excellency Namik Pasha, he had every reason to believe that the co-operation of the Turkish authorities would be afforded for the purpose of buoying the bar in the manner desired by Her Majesty’s Embassy. In the meantime the political resident in Turkish Arabia had addressed Her Majesty’s Ambassador at Constantinople (the 9th October, 1861) stating that, in conformity with the instructions of the Bombay Government, he had addressed a letter* to his Excellency Ahmad Tewfik Pasha, and sending an extract of his despatch, dated the 5th October, 1861, to the Government of Bombay, requesting Her Majesty’s Ambassador to procure a vizierial letter to the address of the Governors of Bagdad and Bussorah in the sense of his communication to Ahmad Tewfik Pasha. Her Majesty’s Ambassador replied (the 22nd February, 1862) transmitting a vizierial letter to the Governor-General of Bagdad, directing him to co-operate with Her Majesty’s naval officers in placing and repairing the buoys necessary to mark the bar and channel leading to the Shatt-el-Arab. Lieutenant-Colonel A. B. (afterwards Sir Arnold) Kemball shortly afterwards addressed the Government of Bombay (the 1st April, 1862) reporting the receipt of the above despatch, and of a vizierial instruction to the Governor-General of Bagdad, in which that functionary is directed to co-operate with Her Majesty’s naval officers in placing and repairing the buoys necessary to mark the bar and channel leading to the Shatt-el-Arab. He enclosad the following translation of the vizierial instruction in question :—'f “From the Ottoman Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs to his Excellency Namik Pasha, dated 11th Shaban, 1278. “ Enclosed for your information is the copy of a translation of a despatch received from Her Majesty’s Ambassador regarding the repair when necessary of the buoys placed at the mouth of the Shatt-el-Arab with a view to facilitate the navigation of the channel. ‘‘Reference having been made to Her Majesty’s consul-general at Bagdad on the subject of putting the said buoys in a good condition and of obtaining the materials necessary thereto, and it having been proposed that assistance, if need be, should be rendered to this end by the British squadron, and since it seems certain from the repre sentations made, that the said buoys if left in their present state would not be secured from injury, you are hereby desired accordingly, after making due enquiries on the spot, to take the requisite steps for repairing the buoys in question, and for preserving them continually in good condition, reporting to us the result.” The following is a translation of the note from Her Majesty’s Ambassador referred to above :— “From Her Majesty’s Ambassador at Constantinople to the Ottoman Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, dated November 12, 1861. u Instructions have been received by Her Majesty’s consul-general at Bagdad from Bombay regarding the maintenance of buoys at the entrance of the ^ channel leading to the Shatt-el-Arab, and the adoption of measures for preserving and . * Dated October 4 , 1861 , enclosed to Ambassador in above despatch ; copy not available. | Original Turkish note not traceable. [2839 a—1] B 24 protecting them, with a view to his entering into negotiation with the local authorities on the subject, Her Majesty’s consul-general accordingly addressed a letter to his Excellency the Governor of Bagdad, under date the 4th October, 1861, of which a copy is herewith submitted to your Excellency. “ Should the suggestion of Her Majesty’s Government meet with concurrence, I request that I may be furnished with a vizierial instructional in the sense of the above letter, either to the Governor of Bagdad or to the Mutessarif of Bussorah, for transmission to those functionaries, in order that timely precautions may be taken, and in that case I may assure your Excellency that every assistance will be afforded by Her Britannic Majesty’s Government and by Her Britannic Majesty’s naval forces in that quarter to further the end desired.” , On the 19th June, 1862, Colonel Kemball wrote to the resident at Busliire, enclosing a letter from the Yali of Bagdad on the subject of the buoying of the channel, together with his reply thereto. They ran as follows :— Letter from Vali of Bagdad, dated 9th Zilhaj, 1278 (June 6, 1862). “ In conformity with your suggestions for the maintenance and repair of six buoys to mark the channel leading to the river at Bussorah for the convenience of navigation, Munib Pasha was instructed to repair those that might require repairs, and to add as many others as might be requisite. The said pasha, in reply, writes to me by this opportunity that the four buoys at present existing are not in need of repair further than that the paint being worn off they must be repainted, but that two additional buoys must be made, for which anchors, he adds, are forthcoming in the Bussorah dock yard, and the requisite chain cable can be manufactured there. Yet, as the cause of the destruction of buoys is owing to the crews of boats coveting and stealing the anchors, he considers it to be the safest course to sink some of the old unserviceable guns now available at Bussorah in lieu of anchors. As, however, sheet-iron is not procurable at Bussorah wherewith to make the necessary buoys, nor are there artificers competent to make them, Munib Pasha proposes that the said buoys should be made at the Bagdad foundry and forwarded to Bussorah, where the chains and guns and other materials will be supplied for the purpose of placing them at the requisite spots. In consequence of this communication the necessary steps are now being taken here.” Reply dated June 11, 1862. “ In reply to your Excellency’s letter dated 9th Zilhaj, I have the honour to express my acknowledgments to your Excellency for your ready co-operation in the arrangements proposed for buoying the channel leading from the sea to the Shatt-el- Arab. T our Excellency will find, however, on reference to my letters that your Excellency is in error in supposing that I specified six buoys or any number of buoys as being requisite for the purpose; nor am I in a position now to submit to your Excellency any definite proposition on this subject, seeing that I am myself ignorant of the numbers of buoys required. Under these circumstances and believing that the four buoys alluded to by Munib Pasha are in fact new ones not long since placed on the banks by Her Majesty’s squadron in the Persian Gulf, I purpose to transmit a copy of your Excellency’s letter under acknowledgment to the British resident at Bushire, with a view to his consulting the naval officers on the spot, and to his acquainting me for your Excellency’s information, as well with the steps which have been taken, as with the necessity or otherwise for those which your Excellency has proposed. “ Should your Excellency desire it, after the lapse of the hot months, I will request the commander of Her Majesty’s steamer c Comet ’ to associate himself with the Turkish naval authorities for the purpose of examining and reporting upon the state of the buoys.” In forwarding the above communications to Bushire, Lieutenant-Colonel Kemball remarked that though he believed Namik Pasha to be quite sincere in the intention he announced, it would not be prudent to count too confidently upon its execution, and expressed the apprehension that the naval authorities at Bussorah might not be competent to lay down the buoys efficiently. The resident at Bushire replied on the 5th July to this communication, stating that as soon as suitable vessel was available to send up to Bussorah he would invite the Turkish naval authorities to co-operate, with the British naval commander in the laying of the buoys, but pointing out at the same time that the bar had already beenfully buoyed by Her Majesty’s ships. Four buoys from Bombay were duly laid by Her Majesty’s ships. Oh the 16th July Colonel Kemball wrote to Bushire that Her Majesty’s ship “Berenice” had landed five old guns at Bussorah, to be fitted to moorings for the four buoys in place of anchors, and that only four being needed the fifth was to be returned to Bombay ; he enclosed, at the same time, a copy of the following note which he had addressed to the Vaii of Bagdad :— “ 1 have the honour to submit herewith to your Excellency a skeleton chart of the channel leading to the Shatt-el-Arab, which I have just received^ from the British resident in the Persian Gulf. It seems to be the opinion of the British naval officers that the buoys now placed, four in number, are sufficient, and that they require merely to be repainted of a red colour. After the hot weather the resident at Bushire will detach a vessel to Bussorah for the purpose of substituting for the anchors by which the buoys are now held certain old guns now lying at Magii, ' and notice other coming will be duly given to Munib Pasha, Governor of Bussorah, with a view to his deputing a Turkish officer, if your Excellency should think proper, to be associated with the commander of the said vessel on this duty.” A proposal to place a beacon on the Shatt-el-Arab bar was raised by Colonel Pelly in his letter dated the 5th December, 1862, and subsequently referred to in his letters dated the 22nd June, 1863, and 23rd July, 1863. On the 23rd July, 1863, Colonel Pelly made proposals to the Government ot Bombay for the retention at Bussorah of a suitable quantity of spare gear for buoying purposes. He further stated that— “ there as a beacon put ashore at Fao during the war. _ This the Arabs have made over to the Sheikh of Koweit, under alleged orders from this residency : no such orders are on record. I am now writing to the Sheikh of Koweit to return the beacon, when I will cause it to be erected at the entrance of the Shatt-el-Arab on a 2-fathom bank. In the same communication he adverts to a request made by him for a spare hulk, which was misconstrued into a demand for a new vessel by the late naval departmen . His proceedings were fully approved by the Government of Bombay (resolution dated the 11 th September, 1863). ~ j. r d v 4 .^ On the 21st November, 1863 , Colonel Pelly asked the Government of Bombay to send up a 24-foot buoy by next Government vessel; a first-class ^ uo y&gt; Wlth a ^ 8 - cwt - moorino- anchor, was accordingly sent up on the 27th February 1866. This buoy was carried away in December 1868 and stranded on Bub an, but replaced in March 1869 ; a second buoy was stranded op Halid Island m the same year, and the Sheikh of Abu Dhabi asked to send it to Bushire. , The residency agent reported that he found it on Jazirat-al- Jarman ,subsequen y the chief of Abu Dhabi alleged that the buoy had been destroyed by the boatmen of Khalifa-bin-Salim of Debai. _ . , -o i The provision of a new buoy to replace it was sanctioned by the Bombay GQYernment g ^ away j n 1880&gt; and the Government of India decided not to replace them. The Turkish authorities placed a buoy on the bar on the &gt;5th May, 1880, but it was also washed away on the following day and apparently not replaced. Messrs. Gray, Paul and Co. in reporting the fact remarked that it was the first buoy that had been contributed by the Turks. , One of the same buoys were washed away on the 14th January, 1887, and stranded on the Arab coast, 50 miles east of Koweit (t.e. somewhere on Bubian Island); Sheikh Abdullah-bin-Sahab was accordingly asked by the resident to take Car&lt;3 Buoys were put down by British India Steam Navigation Company in 1891, 1894, A buoy was placed by the R.I.M.S. “ Lawrence” in 1900 to replace the outer bar buoy which had gone adrift. * * The Euphrates and Tigris Steam Navigation Company’s depot above Bussorah.( 2 .) Bahrein. i In 1874 the political resident in the Persian Gulf suggested to the Government of India the desirability of placing a large buoy at the entrance of Bahrein Harbour ; the proposal was approved by the Government of India, and the Government of Bombay were requested to take the necessary steps through the British India Steam Navigation Company. At least two buoys were, however, apparently laid down by Government, as in 1879 the commander of Her Majesty’s ship “ Beacon” mentions the existence of an “ outer ” buoy, both in need of repair, and states that he believes them to he the property of the British India Steam Navigation Company (which would not appear to be the case, though they were no doubt laid by one of their ships), whilst in later letter the resident mentions four buoys as needing replacement. The Government of India, however, had ruled in 1875, in case of the buoys on the Shatt-el-Arab bar, that they could not be replaced at Government expense, and this ruling was quoted by Government as applicable equally to Bahrein. In 1882 the political resident again addressed the Government of India in connec tion with the loss of a Government buoy at Bahrein, stating that he had been privately informed that it was in contemplation to replace certain of the buoys in tho Persian Gulf, and submitting that “ the right of control of all buoys in these seas might possibly be of advantage in certain contingencies.” The Government of India replied, however, that f&lt; it was not at present the intention of Government to replace the buoys in the Persian Gulf.” Buoys were subsequently laid by the British India Steam Navigation Company and maintained by them until taken over by the Government of India. $dr' ' fllHj /{&amp;z* I aieti-i-cite. In any further communication on this subject, please quote no. 11480 / 13 . and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. Sir _ to W Foreign Office March 13th, 1913 With reference to previous correspondence regarding £100,000. an Anglo-Indian Advance of One hundred thousand pounds to the Persian Government for the gendarmerie in the province of Pars, I am directed by Secretary Sir Edward Grey to transmit to you herewith, to he laid before the Marquess of Crewe, a copy of a telegram from His Majes ty^ Minister at Tehran, on the subject of the conditions connected with the advance. Sir E.Grey would be glad to receive Lord Crewe*s observations on the Persian Government's memorandum re garding the lighting and buoying of the Persian Gulf, and is of opinion that it is desirable to accept these proposals if His Lordship considers tnat this can be done without any sacrifice of British interests I am. Sir, he Under Secretary of State, India Office. --Jr ■CONFIDENTIAL f ZJ i '—) Sir TV. Townley to Sir Edward Grey.— (Ecceived March 11, 5*45 p.m.) The Ministei lor horeign Affairs states that the Persian Government agree that a special account shall he opened at the Imperial Bank of Persia for the gendarmerie of Fais. ^ Secondly, that expenditure shall be controlled by treasurer-general, who shall authorise all payments to be made from fund after consultation with Swedish colonel. Ilurdly, that I shall pay treasurer-general the entire sum in one cheque. Fourthly* that necessary funds shall be remitted to the financial agent at Shiraz by treasurer- general for transmission to Swedish officer commanding there. Fifthly, that monthly budget shall be drawn up by colonel commanding at Tehran with the assistance of the treasurer-general and after consultation with officer in command at Shiraz, who will on his side take counsel with the financial agent there. Sixthly, that system of purchase by open tender of supplies for gendarmerie shall be established. I have replied that my instructions only permit me to make monthly payments, but I would point out that if this plan is adhered to it will be hard to call upon the the Persian Government to pay interest on the entire sum from date of its payment to Persian Government. All the moneys will pass through European hands, and both I and consul at Shiraz will be able to make our opinions heard, should it be necessary without this appearing in a document in a manner that might lay the Government open to criticism. Lighting and buoying of Persian Gulf. Minister for Foreign Affairs has submitted memorandum which he says contains the utmost he has been able to get the Cabinet to accept. Following is the summary :— 1. The Persian Government is disposed to cause lighthouses to be built and buoys to be placed on or in the neighbourhood of Persian islands, to be determined later in agreement with the British Government on the following conditions : firstly, British engineers shall be engaged by Persia to carry out the construction of lighthouses. 2. On completion of the construction the working and maintenance of the apparatus will be entrusted to British employes specially engaged for the purpose. 3. Should the Persian Government require funds to meet expenses to be incurred, His Majesty’s Government will be asked to make the necessary advance. 4. Interest and amortisation of such advance will be met by tolls leviable from shipping. I rather gather that vagueness of detail is intentional in order to leave us a free hand without appearing to do so. 1 said that I would submit the scheme, but I held out no hope of its being found acceptable. I am repeating the second part of the above to Bushire. COPY TO INDIA 8ECLE [ ARY’S NffJJ |■..jr- ;'n:r Sir Edward Grey to Sir W. Townley (Tehran). (No. 113.) Foreign Office, March 8, 1913, 2*50 p.m. 10UR telegram No. 90 of 6th March : Advance to Persian Government. The l00,t00Z. for the gendarmerie is ready, but cannot be advanced until you have obtained more satisfactory replies to our demands :— 1. Acceptance of our proposal respecting control over expenditure and respecting the tender systems for purchases. 2. A written arrangement respecting the lighting and buoying of the Gulf. We would not insist on mention in this question of policing territorial waters otherwise than for necessary protection of lights and buoys provided that you had a verbal assurance that no question will be raised to our prescriptive rights in the Gulf generally. / 3. If we take note of the Persian Minister for Foreign Affairs’ assurance not to alienate any Persian islands in the Gulf to any foreign Power it might be quoted hereafter as an admission on our part of Persian rights in Bahrein. It should therefore be made clear that His Majesty’s Government maintain their attitude in regard to the protection of Bahreinis’ trucial rights, and, in refraining from pressing their request for Persian recognition of this claim, do so only on the under standing that their rights will not be disputed in practice. V PHICONFIDENTIAL. Sir W. Townley to Sir Edward Grey.—{Received March 6, 11 a.m.) Tehran, March 6, 1913. {March 6, 11'25 a.m.) (No. 90.) YOUR telegram No. 95 of 19tli February. , , I have had great difficulty in inducing the Cabinet to consider conditions attached to advance of 100,0001. for the Fars gendarmerie. It is argued that the Cabinet on taking office knew they had got to grant two railway concessions and mining concessions, but that they could not discuss any other conditions affecting Persia s national status until the Medjliss has assembled. _ On my representing the gravity of the situation which would be created were no funds available for the maintenance of the gendarmerie, and after discussing the matter three times in the Cabinet Council, the Minister for Foreign Affairs told me yesterday that he thinks an arrangement as to the control over expenditure m accordance with your wishes can be made. o-pndflrmerie There will be no difficulty in arranging that the purchases for the gendarme e shall be put up to open tender, but it will be very hard to secure other conditions .&lt;«•&gt;« w*,. and buoying of the Gulf, which will entail leasing of parts of certain islands, is of revenues^of TheTo'* are^o be charged fo'r existing and future advances as to whether or no interest of the loan can be secured thereon.CO ]N FID £ JS11AL Sir Edward Grey to Sir W. Townley {Tehran). (No. 95.) R. Foreign Office, February 19, 1913, 4*45 p.m. YOUR telegram No. 70 of 15th February: Advance of Fars. 1. I agree. 2. If Colonel Merrill could be employed I see no objection, as he is not a subject of a European Great Power. My impression of your holding a different opinion from Major O’Connor respecting military force for Government was based upon your despatch No. 159, third paragraph from the end. Am I right in supposing that the expenses in connection with it are calculated in the estimate for administrative purposes ? 3. I agree as to method of preparing budget and paying colonel. At least 30,000L should be earmarked from the general joint advance for the purposes of administration in Fars, and we could not advance more than the sums already indicated. 4. I shall be glad to hear further as to security and interest. If any means of repayment from provincial revenues could be arranged, it would facilitate discussion with the Treasury, especially in view of advantageous arrangements made by Russia respecting repayment of last advance. 6. I am pressing India Office for answer. 282—509] ••X .. CONFIDENTIAL. r' 6 / '''s. Sir W. Townley to Sir Edward Grey.—(Beceived February 15 , 2 T 5 p.m.) Tehran, February 15 , 1913 . (No. 70 .) R. (February 15 , 1 p.m.) YOUR telegram No. 76 of the 12th February. I have sketched roughly to Minister for Foreign Affairs conditions under which His Majesty’s Government are disposed to advance 100,000L to Persian Government for special services connected with Fars. His Excellency expressed himself as quite ready to come to an arrangement on line suggested. Before proceeding further I would venture to submit certain observations on the proposals. 1. I am strongly of opinion that any financial assistance rendered _ to the gendarmerie scheme should be kept quite apart from any help that may be given for administration of promise, in spite of the fact that two schemes dovetail into each other and the one stands a poor chance of success without the other. 2. I have expressed myself badly if I have caused you to understand that I do not agree that Governor-General should have force of his own. I am of opinion that such a force is most necessary. AYhere O’Connor and I. disagree is on question as to foreign officers for that force. He is in favour of British officers. I consider Swedish officers or officers affiliated to gendarmerie are more desirable. I have suggested Colonel Merrill, an American, who stayed on after Shuster left. 0 Connor concurs in this suggestion, but wants him to be seconded from gendarmerie. This seems to me undesirable, though his work would be obviously of an independent nature. g budget in Fars is estimated at close upon 8,0001. a-month, and administration budget at rather more than the same figure, so that it is evident that sum would not suffice for all purposes. I think budget should be preparecl here, but amended bv officer commanding, Shiraz, in concert with financial agent and British consul, and that money should be paid under my sanction through the treasurer-general to colonel commanding here for transmission to Shiraz. This would ensure suitable and effective control. I am of opinion that the 100,0001 should be set aside for gendarmerie, to be paid in monthly instalments and, say, 30,000Z. be advanced separately for Fars administration to enable Governor-General to carry on till end of June, or earmarked out of the advance of 200,000Z. Minister of the Interior is of opinion that all efforts of Persian Government should be turned to the restoration of order m the south. 4. Question as to proper security and interest is receiving attention, but 1 fail to see why the Russian Government should object to advance being secured on loan, as the increase to nearly double its present strength of the Cossack brigade is to be made as soon as the loan is issued. , p , e j 5. I consider money devoted to the formation of a strong force under the Governor-General’s orders can justifiably be held to have been expended for t e purpose of securing order on trade routes, because, as stated above, gendarmerie and local force must co operate in suppressing disturbances and brigandage. 6 Governor-General is most anxious to receive your answer to request lorwarded in my telegram No. 34 . for 2,000 rifles and ammunition, as he cannot proceed with training of his recruits without the arms. [ 282 — 421 ]—^ I CONFIDENTIAL. \ Sir Edward Grey to Sir W. Townley (Tehran). (No. 76.) K. Foreign Oljice, February 12, 1913, 10'50 a.m. YOUR telegram No. 64 of 10th February : Advance for Fars. You are authorised to inform Persian Government that His Majesty’s Government are most anxious to assist them to restore order in Pars by means of the gendarmerie, and are prepared to contribute to the financing of the administration, apart from their contribution to an advance on account of the loan, on the following conditions:—• 1. That the conditions laid down in paragraph 2 of your telegram No. 627 of 10th December are observed ; 2. That, subject to any observation you may have to offer, the gendarmerie budget should be drawn up by Swedish commanding officer at Shiraz, and agreed to by His Majesty’s consul and the financial agent in consultation, and, when this is done, that all actual payments should be made by the Swedish commander; 3. That the conditions proposed by Sir P. Cox should, if possible, be obtained as modified by the Viceroy. It would, however, be better to omit all mention of the Karun. 4. That all purchases for the gendarmerie should be put up to open tender (see Sir P. Cox’s despatch No. 1, Commercial, of 17th January). 5. That proper security and interest can be arranged. The Russian Government would probably not agree to this separate and purely British advance being secured on the loan. Can some arrangement be made to secure it on the revenue of the province (see your telegram No. 20 , paragraph 2), and what can be done about interest^ I should be glad to have your final opinion as to what sum monthly will be sufficient to ensure the proper organisation and gradual increase of the gendarmerie force, as well as the amount of the contribution which will be required for ordinary administrative purposes by the Governor-General. M’e presume that 8,000L a-month would suffice for all purposes. I observe that you are not in agreement with Major O’Connor as to the necessity or utility of the Governor-General having a separate military force, and 1 appreciate your reasons, but if the Governor-General desires for reasons of amour-propre to have a small force of his own, it may be necessary to fall in with his views and endeavour to make it serviceable. It would not be right to use any of our money for this force unless it was really essential or contributory to the main object of securing the trade routes. I should like you to discuss this with Major O’Connor, and endeavour to come to some agreement. You should also inform Major O’Connor that our object is to avoid an expedition in the autumn, and that as an alternative we are prepared to do all in our power to assist the Governor-General to uphold and extend his authority, that we will recommend to the Treasury the immediate loan of the sum of 100,0001 in monthly payments for this purpose, but that if we do this we must know on what the money will be spent because our only justification for lending it is the need of securing the trade routes. [282—298] M \CONFIDENTIAL. Sir W. Townley to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received February 10, 3’40 p.m.) Tehran, February 10, 1913. (No. 64.) (February 10, L'20 p.m.) THE 15,000L alluded to in the last paragraph of your telegram No. 46 was advanced for the financial requirements of the administration of Ears. It has always been earmarked in a budget that has been framed in such a manner as to allow the administration of that province to be carried on till 21st March, when as represented in my telegram No. 20 , further funds will be urgently required. . Minister for Foreign Affairs is very anxious to know what answer I have received respecting gendarmerie proposals. I have returned an evasive reply, but may I now proceed to, on the assumption that the 100,000Z. will be forthcoming, and negotiate for as many as possible of the conditions proposed by His Majesty’s consul-general at Bushire, to protect our interests in the Gulf as modified by Government of India ? If I do this it will be tantamount to declaring that His Majesty’s Government do not intend to take any active measures in the south for the present.CONFIDENTIAL. Sir Edward Grey to Sir W. Townley (Tehran). (No. 46.) Foreign Office. January 30, 19J3, YOUR telegram No. 32 of 26tli January : Persian finance. A large loan snch as the Persian Government desire cannot be floated, or even seriously considered, till some measure of order is restored, and all that can be done is to advance just enough to keep the administration going and subsidise the gendarmerie in Pars. . . As regards the advance for general purposes, we must wait and see how much the Russian Minister of Finance can be induced to give, and then, when the two railway concessions are granted, advance an equal sum. You will have seen fiom Sir G. Buchanan’s recent telegrams repeated to you that Russian share is unlikely to amount even to 250,000/., still less to the 300,0001. desired by the Persian Government. As regards the gendarmerie in Fars, we are ready to advance 100,000/. as soon as 15,000/. advanced last December is all used up, paying, say, 8,000/. a-month (of course under proper control as to its expenditure), for the purpose of protecting the trade routes in the south, till that sum is exhausted (see your telegram No. 17 of 12th January, last paragraph). You should, however, obtain from the Persian Government m return for this advance as many as possible of the conditions proposed by Sir P. Cox to safe guard our legitimate interests (see your telegram No. 31 of 26th January), as modi ed by Government of India in their telegram of 24th January to India Office. (Repeat to St. Petersburgh, No. 78.)CONFIDENTIAL. IV. Townley to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received January 26, 7 p.m.) „ Tehran, January 26, 1013. (N°. 3-.) _ _ (January 26, 7 p.m.) NEW Cabinet is bolding daily meetings to discuss railway concessions. Minister for Foreign Affairs assures me that he is confident that the matter will be settled within the week. His Excellency says that British proposal would be much more acceptable if it could be announced that the line would be carried on to Hamadan, but he expresses earnest desire that, should any negotiations in this sense be opened, it should not transpire that this is the wish of the Persian Gfovernment. Whilst discussing this question Minister for Foreign Affairs impressed on me most earnestly that Persian Government have immediate need of 600,000i. as an advance upon the loan, which it is hoped will be for 6,000,000L, to be paid in five annual instalments of 1,200,000b each. On my asking whether the advance asked for on account of the Fars gendarmerie was to form part of 300,000b [sic] which it is hoped that His Majesty’s Government will advance, he said that Persian Government would prefer that this should be separate advance payable out of the second instalment of loan, the 600,000b wanted immediately being considered as the first half of the first annual instalment of 1,200,000bIndia Office, London, 22nd March 1912. f Secret, No. 9. To His Excellency the Right Honourable the Governor General of India in Council. My Lord, ing in connection with lights and ment, dated the 27th April 1911, attention was buoys at Sheikh Shuaib, &amp;c. drawn to the fact that it would he necessary to Persian Gulf. Questions aris- In the telegram of Your Excellency’s Govern- • • •. t i • • • 7 i.i.i rr , 1 a *ii/~vii i i i * buoys at Sheikh Shuaib, &amp;c. approach the Persian Government in connection with the proposal to place a lighthouse on Sheikh Shuaib Island. I enclose, for your information, copy of correspondence 0 with His Majesty’s Minister at Tehran upon the subject, and request that I may receive your observations by telegraph on the 2. It is also for consideration whether, in replying to the Persian Memorandum, any mention should be made of other items in the scheme (copy enclosed), such as the fact that it is proposed to lay buoys at Jask (item No. 1 in the List), Bunder Abbas (Nos. 3 and 4), and Bushire (Nos. 7 and 8); and, as regards the lighthouses at Musandam (No. 2), and Tamb Island (No. 5), and the buoys at Bahrein (Nos. 11-13), I should be glad to learn whether you contemplate obtaining any formal authority, either now or later, from the local Chiefs for the establishment of lights and buoys, and for the levy of light dues at some future time if thought desirable. The position as regards dues will become clearer, vis-a-vis of Turkey, if negotiations which are about to be begun on the basis of the British Memorandum of the 29th July last (extract enclosed), should be Successfully concluded. The extract, so far as it relates to the Shatt-al-Arab, covers the case of the light vessel (item No. 9) and the lighted buoy (No. 10), which it is proposed to establish in that locality. 3. As Your Excellency is aware from the papers forwarded in recent letters from the Secretary, S. 144. A • Sir E. Grey’s Despatch to Sir G. Barclay, Secret, No. 210, dated 31st October 1911. * Sir E. Grey’s Despatch to Sir G. Barclay, Secret, No. 119, dated 27 th September 1911. Sir G. Barclay’s telegram to Sir E. Grey, No. 511, dated 21st October 1911. Memorandum handed to Sir G. Barclay on the 8th February last, and in particular on the effect, if any, upon our position locally, if we appear to be acting as the delegate of Persia and no longer on our own account as the Power which has hitherto made itself responsible for the safe navigation of the Letter from Foreign Office, dated 14th March 1912, with enclosures. Gulf.ENCLOSURES. Enclosure No. 1. Sir Edward Grey to Sir G. Barclay. No. 119. Secret. Foreign Office, Sir. 27th September 1911. I transmit to you herewith copy of a letter* and its enclosures from the India Office, respecting 191* Indm 0ffl ° e lettel ' ° £ 15th September the proposal for the buoyage and lighting of the Persian Gulf, with the details of which you have been kept acquainted by the print sent to you in the Secret Series. You will observe that the scheme now recommended by the India Office includes the erection of a lighthouse on the island of Sheikh Shuaib, at an estimated cost of 8,000L For this it will be necessary to approach the Persian Government. You should therefore take an opportunity of explaining the matter to them ; but if, in your opinion, the present moment is not a favourable one, you should use your discretion as to when the communication should be made. I may add, for your informal ion, that, in accordance with the suggestion contained in paragraph 2 of the India Office letter, I am requesting the Lords Commissioners of His Majesty’s Treasury to accept a moiety of the necessary charges as a charge against British revenues, in view of the importance of the matter and the necessity for speedy action in order to forestall possible action by another Power. * I am, &amp;c., Sir G. Barclay. E. Grey. Enclosure No. 2. From His Majesty's Minister, Tehran, to Foreign Office, No. 511, dated 21st October 1911. P. —Please refer to your Despatch No. 119. I have addressed Consul-General, Bushire, as follows :— “ I have received instructions from the Secretary of State for Foreign “ Affairs to approach Persian Government in regard to proposed liglit- “ house at Sheikh Shuaib at an opportune moment. I should be “ obliged if you could inform me whether site proposed belongs to “ Government or to private owner.” Enclosure No. 3. Sir G. Barclay to Sir E. Grey. No. 210. Secret. Tehran, Sir, 31st October 1911. I have the honour to acknowledge receipt of your Despatch No. 119, Secret, of the 27th ultimo, directing me to approach the Persian Government with regard to the erection of a lighthouse on the island of Sheikh Shuaib.I think it would be wise to postpone nny action heie in this matter for the moment. The increase of our Consular Cruards has aroused some degree of suspicion, and I shall wait a while befoie carrying out your instructions in the hope that this feeling may diminish. I presume that a few weeks delay will not prejudice matters, and that in any case I shall be informed before the construction of the lighthouse or any preparatory work on land is begun. I have, &amp;c , The Right Hon. H. Barclay. Sir Edward Grey, Bart.. M.P., &amp;c., &amp;c., &amp;c. Enclosure No. 4. Foreign Office to India Office. No. 10,156. Eoreign Office, gi rj 14th March 1912. With reference to your letter of 15th September last, I am directed by Secretary Sir E. Grey to transmit to you herewith a copy of a despatch from His Majesty’s Minister at Tehran relative to the proposed erection of a lighthouse on the island of Sheikh Shuaib. Sir E. Grey would be glad to be furnished with the observations of the Secretary of State for India on this despatch. I am, &amp;c., The Under Secretary of State Louis Mallet. for India. Annex. Sir G. Barclay to Sir E. Grey. No. 28 (Secret). Tehran, Sir, 9th February 1912. With reference to my Despatch No. 210, of 31st October last, I have the honour to report that on the disappearance of the Mejliss I thought the moment a favourable one for approaching the Persian Government in regard to the lighthouse on the island of Sheikh Shuaib, and on the 17th ultimo 1 mentioned the scheme to the Minister for Foreign Affairs requesting the Persian Government to authorise Sheikh Ahmad Hamadi of Mugam, the Chieftain of the Island, to grant the site for the lighthouse. His Excellency promised to consult his colleagues in the Cabinet and to give me an answer shortly. On the 31st ultimo I enquired as to the decision of the Persian Government, and His Excellency replied that no definite decision had been taken, but that he thought that there would be no difficulty about the lighthouse provided it were constructed and worked by Persia. 1 pointed out that this was not what was desired. The buoyage and lighting of the Persian Gulf had for many years been in British hands, and it would be undesirable to make an exception in the case of the lighthouse on Sheikh Shuaib, besides which if the lighthouse were worked by the Persian Government which had no experience of such matters there could be no guarantee that it would be efficiently done. His Excellency appeared to be under the impression that the cost of the erection of the lighthouse would be 4,000L, and I therefore told him that we estimated the initial cost at 8,000/. and the running expenses at 400/. a year. His Excellency took note of what I said, and promised togive a definite answer in a few da 3 ’s. He added that in any case the lighthouse would have to fly the Persian flag, and I told him that personally 1 thought there would he no objection to this. Yesterday I received a visit from the Chef de Cabinet of the Ministry of Foreign Affairs who handed me the accompaming memo randum of the terms on which the Persian Government were prepared to consent to the construction of the lighthouse. I do not know how far His Majesty’s Government would be prepared to accept these terms. I explained to Moin el Yezareh, the Chef de Cabinet, that the question of light dues in the Persian Gulf was a large one and had not yet been considered. It would, I presume, be difficult to levy separate dues for one particular lighthouse, and should His Majesty’s Government consent to the Persian Government’s bearing the cost of the construction and running of the lighthouse, some arrangement would have to be made whereby a certain proportion of the total dues eventually collected in the Gulf would be paiid to the Persian Government. I have, &amp;c., The Right Hon. G. Barclay. Sir Edward Grey, Bart., M.P., &amp;c., &amp;c., &amp;c. Memorandum. 1. The Persian Government authorises the erection, at their own cost, of a lighthouse on the coast of Sheikh Shuaib Island, for the convenience of navigation in the Gulf. 2. Prior to the work being put in hand, the contractors will submit to the Persian Government the rough estimate of the outlay (the Cahier des Charges) and the plan of the structure. 3. The upkeep and superintendence of the lighthouse, as well as the working of the apparatus, is temporarily delegated by the Persian Government for convenience sake to the Anglo-Indian naval officers. 4. The cost of such maintenance will be borne by the Persian Government, who will be previously furnished with an approximate statement of the annual expense. 5. The Anglo-Indian naval officers will be requested to collect the tolls (beaconage) on behalf of the Persian Government, and keep the accounts. 6. In each year, two months after the 1st of Hamal (21st of March), a statement of accounts showing the receipts and expenses of the previous year will be handed to the Persian Government, 7. The receipts will serve to cover the expenses of administration and will, moreover, constitute a sinking fund for the capital expended in building the lighthouse. 8. The regulations concerning the working of the lighthouse, the manner in which the tolls will be collected, and the amount of such dues, will be submitted to the Persian Government, who will have the right of inspection. 9. The Persian flag will permanently fly over the lighthouse.Enclosure No. 6. Extract from British Memorandum to Turkish Government, 29th July 1911. “ Certain difficulties have recently arisen in regard to the buoyage of the Shatt-al-Arab. For a great number of years British shipping has, owing to its volume, been predominantly, and until recently almost exclusively, interested in these aids to navigation. For over 50 years the work of surveying, buoying, and lighting the river has been carried out by British agency to the general satisfaction of all concerned. “ in these circumstances His Majest}^ Government have some difficulty in appreciating why the Ottoman Government have taken exception to existing and long-standing arrangements; but, being desirous of dealing with the difficulty in a spirit of conciliation, they would propose to the Ottoman Government the appointment of a small riverain commission, comprised of a British and a Turkish representative, with an engineer to be mutually agreed upon. This commission would superintend all matters pertaining to improvement of navigation, and it would likewise superintend the requisite periodical surveys. “ As regards the rest of the Persian Gulf, on the other hand, the Turkish Government, so far as they are concerned, would recognise the right of Great Britain (a) to control surveying, lighting, buoying, and pilotage ; (b) to police its waters ; and (c) to conduct all quarantine arrangements.” S. 144.1 9 o Letter tronxz^ ^ Dated Bee. &gt;0 &lt; = ^-£&gt; &gt; . Date. Initials. SUBJECT. Under Secretary Secretary of State Committee Under Secretary Secretary of State , . ? ■ Copy to g / jl J.O. 4 FOR INFORMATION.mm C' i £. 13 No. 80 , dated Bushire, the 12th (received 23 rd) January 1913 . From-— Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Percy Cox KCIF P 9 T t&gt; rf i -j j. • the Persian Gulf, JSL,u - L ‘ Ji *i L.S.I., Political Resident m To-The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department. ?JZ s v ±:s s gg'sscis - L ’- “ *-=» Royal iXn Marine': 01 ’ 7 ° f thiS letter WUh encl ° 9Ure to tho DireotOT of th « Statement of condition and of work done on unlighted buoys by B. 1. M. S, “ Lawrence ” for quarter 31st December 1912. Place Number and description of buoy Date when first laid Date when last overhauled Detail of work performed during Entrance to Shatt-el-Arab River. No. 2 Black, Connical, Channel. 23rd November 1912. Ditto. This buoy was laid on the date stated. quarter, and report on condition in place of the one found to be missing of buoy. ori or about the 18th November 1912, which had only been put down in May 1911. It is practically impossible that the missing buoy could have been broken adrift by bad weather, but doubtlessly was fouled and either sunk or torn away from its moorings by a vessel grounding near it or run into by a ship making the passage during dark ness. P. V. de Burgh, Commander, R. I. M. t Commanding R. I. M. S. “ Lawrence **. / *&gt; \&lt;/Y Fo&lt;*9ign OJioe P/eM—No, 667 —3(L1*13—44 :1913 r.;•HP 1913 I Bnctossit' ? j C , - vr j 1 j _ : v - « , 6 FEB .9)3 FIGid. No. 3231, dated Bushire, the 1st December 1912. From— Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Percy Cox, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Political Residen 15 in the Persian Gulf, To—The Hon’ble Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Henry McMahon, G.C.Y.O., K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department, Simla. In continuation of my letter No. 3105, dated November 24th, regarding the • erection on the British Residency Flagstaff at Bushire of 2 dioptric lanterns as lead- in*? lights, I have the honour to address Government with regard to the recurring charges which will be involved by their care and upkeep. »: 2 . In my letter No. 1273, dated the 19th May 1911, in which I first suggested the provision of such lanterns, I mentioned that the recurring cost of the single lantern at Kuwait was Rs. 15 per month, on the assumption that if more than one lamp was provided, the recurring cost would be proportionately higher. I note, 1 however, from Government of India teie- Beceived under Foreign Department En- m d a ted May 13th to the Secretary dorsementNo. 1053-E. A., dated 18t ay ^ j.j ie recurr i n g cost has been 1912, given as Rs. 15 per mensem for 2 lanterns. 3 I would venture to point out that the cost of oil will be double, i.e., Rs. 10 r,er mensem, whilst as regards their care and upkeep, I find on investigation since the “rival of the lanterns that it will not be a sufficiently safe and efficient arrange ment to entrust this duty to any member of the menial staff of the Residency m Addition to his normal duties, and that it will be necessary to entertain a spec.a Tw the work I shall endeavour to enlist local talent for the purpose at „tul «,Wv of Rs 20, but should I be unable to obtain a suitable candidate, I shall beobliged to ask the Director of the Royal Indian. Marine to obtain a man for me in Bombay. T fPn m pan time pending the issue of orders in connection with the local In the m c f • } ^ eme I beg that the Government of India will be pleased financing of the Laghtmg bcneme, i d g ^ the Comptrollei . India Trea _ i , Vide Residency letter No. 1805, dated 11th guries? to pass bills up to Rs. 30 per mensem 'bV^/'M Au g U3 t 1912 . for the “Care and maintenance of two dioptric lanterns at Bushire. . „ . I am sending a copy of this letter to the Director of the Royal Indian Marine, Bombay. Telegram No. 1254-4-M., dated Simla, the 17th December 1912. Fr om-The Secretary to the Government o£ India, Marine Department, To—The Director, Royal Indian Marine, Bombay. Your 717, ^o{ ^ku^of^AssistMffiEngineer in Persian Gulf C623FD ^.ilTelegram No. 1470, dated the 22nd (received 23rd) December 1912. From—The Political Eesident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department, Simla. My despatch dated 11th August 1905. I trust (?) decision may be arrived at an early date. Lawrence is now constantly employed in connection with light ing scheme and non-adjustment of contingen texpenses disbursed locally is some what inconvenient. 68m, i ii No. 595-33-M., dated Delhi, the 21st December 1912. p rom The Secretary to the Government of India, Marine Department, To—The Director of the Royal Indian Marine. I am directed to invite attention to the letter from the Political Resident, Persian Gulf, No. 3075, dated the 23rd November 1912, a copy of which was sent to you direct, regarding the condition of the buoys at the port of Kuwait and to request that you will be so good as to furnish the Government of India with your views on the subject at an early date. s ^ BeReference P.1149,&lt;Scc.) , relative to the Persian Gulf Light ing Scheme, it is stated on page 4 that the Oil for the Light Houses in the Persian Gulf 7 which it was thought the Anglo-Persian Oil Company could supply from their local works^should comply with the following specification,viz:- ♦'Specific gravity not less than 0.810, nor greater than '0.820 at 60° Fahrenheit; flashing point not less than 145°, 'nor higher than 160° Fehrenheit, &amp;c. H A sample of this oil has now been received and tested in the Experimental Room here, and its flashing point is found, as the result of three mean readings, to be 108° Fahrenheit and the specific gravity 0.81, which is satis factory, bu^owing to the low flashing poin^the oil is not suitable for the incandescent oil burners arranged to be installed in the Persian Gulf Light Houses. The Director of Stores India Office, Whitehall,V I Q In these circumstances I eoa to enquire what steps, if any, it is desired that the Trinity House shall take in the matter. I am, Hr, Your obedient Servant,B. 187. This Document is the property of the Secretary of State for India in Council. SECRET. MEMORANDUM ON THE LIGHTING AND BUOYAGE OF THE PERSIAN GULF. Charts :— (lp Chart to accompany the Report of a Committee on Lighthouses for the Persian Gulf, dated 29th April 1909.” (Pol. 3620/1909; cop?/ sent to Foreign Office and Admiralty 1st September 1909.) (2.) Persian Gulf Mouth of the Shatt-al-Arab Piverf' the tracing that accompanied the letter of the Director of the Royal Indian Marine to the Secretary to the Government of India, Marine Department, No. 3270, dated the loth May 1911. (/OZ. 4013/1911 ; copy sent to Foreign Office and Admiralty, 10th August 1911.) Scope of the Memorandum. 1. The question of the Lighting and Buoyage of the Persian Gulf is part of the Jarger question of British policy in the Gulf and neighbourhood, which is outside the scope of the present Memo randum. It is enough to remark that the advance of the Bagdad Railway and the activity of Turkey in the waters of the Shatt-al-Arab have recently brought the lighting and buoyage question into greater prominence. For some t&gt;0 years the buoyage of the Gulf has been maintained by British enterprise, namely that of the British India Steam Navigation Company, and now that it seems likely that railway communication will be opened with the Persian Gulf via Asia Minor, it is urged with some force that Great Britain, the predominant maritime Power, should in the interests of British and Indian trade endeavour to improve communication with the head of the Gulf by sea. There are many references in our papers to the difficulties of navi gation in the Gulf, especially by night, owing to incomplete surveys and defective lighting and buoyage. Inter-Departmental Conference of 17th July 1908, and Report of Sub- Committee of Committee of Imperial Defence. Pol. 2680/07. * Present:— Rear-Admiral A. M. Field, F.R.S., Hydi’ographer to the Admiralty. Captain E. J. W. Slade, M.V.O., Director of Naval Intelligence. Mr. J. E. Ferard, Assistant Secre tary, Political Department. Letter of Admiralty to India Office, 1st October 1908. Pol. 3881/08. 2. The question of lighting and buoyage first came up in a practical form when a proposal was made by the Hamburg-American Company, in the early part of 1907, that they should contribute to the upkeep of the navigation buoys maintained in the Gulf by the British India Steam Navigation Company. It was believed that a political motive lay behind the proposal, and the suggestion was therefore made that the British Government should itself take over the buoys from the British India Company. An Inter-Departmental Conference’^ held at the Admiralty on the 17th July 1908, recommended in their Report, dated the 19th September 1908, that this action should be taken, and, further, that lights and buoys should be provided on an extended scale at Muscat and2 various places in the Persian Gulf. Meanwhile, the Government of India had independently re commended the holding of a local enquiiy with the same object, and their proposal received^ the approval of a Sub-Committee of the Committee of Imperial Defence, from whose Report, dated the 26th January 1909, the following is an extract : — Letter of Government of India, Foreign Department (Secret), No. 156,13th August 1908. Pol. 1646/08. “ 4. Lighthouses and Buoyage. “ While it is desirable that, if the British “ shipowning Companies press for additional “ navigational lights in the Gulf, all reasonable “ steps should be taken to meet their wishes, yet, in “ view of the limited volume of the trade at present, “ the Committee do not recommend that any “ considerable expenditure that could not be “ recouped by light dues should be incurred under “ this head. But they are of opinion that it would “ be worth while to incur the expenditure involved “ in the proposal now under consideration, to send “ a Commission to collect information, consisting “ of the Senior Naval Officer, the officer in charge “ of the Indian Marine Survey, and an expert to be “ obtained through the Trinity House. This “ Commission would also deal with the question of “ buoyage. This proposal has the support of the “ Inter-Departmental Committee (Foreign Office, “ India Office, and Admiralty). The cost will be “ that of the expert and incidental expenses; “ the other two officers receiving no extra pay.” The Treasury afterwards agreed to accept as a charge against British revenues a moiety of the cost of the enquiry. (A sum of 35SL 14s. Id. is now being claimed from them on this account.) Letter of Treasury to Foreign Office, 27th January 1909. Pol. 2928/09. Pol. 843/11. 3. The Committee*' presented their Report on the 29th April 1909, and a summary of the lights and buoys proposed by them is printed as Appendix I. Briefly, the 3 T recommended (para graph 7 of Report) the establishment in the Gulf of 13 lightst in all (in addition to buoys), and of these seven were named as those most urgently required, viz., in order of importance,-- (1.) Shatt-al-Arab Bar, light vessel and four buoys. (2.) Musandam (Little Quoin). (3.) Muscat. (4.) Bushire. Shaikh Shuaib. Ras-al-Mutaf. Tanb. Kubbar Island (Koweit). Ras-al-Arz (Koweit). Bahrein. (11.) Lingah. (12.) Debai. (13.) Bunder Abbas. The Committee further recommended (para graph 12) the provision of a lighthouse tender, and (paragraph 15) of a depot at Koweit. (5.) ( 6 .) (70 ( 8 .) (9.) ( 10 .) Report of Committee of Enquiry, 29tli April 1909. Letter of Trinity House to India Office, 1st June 1909. Pol. 3503/09. # Members :— Major P. Z. Cox, C.I.E., Political Resi dent in the Pei*sian Gulf. Mr. D. W. Hood, A.M. Inst. C.E., Trinity House. Commander S. Litchfield, R.N., H.M.S. Sphinx. Commander W. G. Beauchamp, R.I.M., of the Marine Survey of India. t Positions shown on chart referred to at head of this Memorandum.Supplementary Report by Mr. D. W. % Hood, 28th June 1909. Pol. 3620/09. 4. The question of estimates was dealt with in a Supplementary Report by Mr. D. W. Hood, the expert in lighthouse construction, whose services on the Committee had been obtained from the Trinity House. The Summary with which his Report concluded is printed as Appendix II., and, in view of subsequent correspondence, it is useful to note the cost of two items in particular, viz., 30,000/.. initial, and 5,000/. annual recurring, for a new lighthouse tender, and 22,000/. initial, for a depot at Koweit. The general financial effect of his estimates is apparent in the following extract from a letter addressed by the India Office to the of the 7th August in which the Admiralty had commented on the Committee’s own Report:— “ It will be seen that, apart from any expendi- “ ture on the purchase of land for lighthouses or “ for other works, the cost of the entire scheme “ proposed by the Committee, including the pro- “ vision of a lighthouse tender, is estimated by “ Mr. Hood at 158,150/. initial, and 10,745/. annual “ recurring expenditure; or, if certain savings are “ effected by the conversion of a Royal Indian “ Marine vessel into a lighthouse tender and by “ modifications in the system of lighting, at “ 107,500/. initial, and 9,280/. annual recurring “ expenditure. The cost of an alternative scheme “ on a smaller scale, to include provision of the “ lights recommended in paragraph 7 of the Com- mittee’s Report as those most urgently required, “ is estimated at 120,550/. initial, and 8,720/. annual “ recurring expenditure—or, if savings of the kind “ mentioned above are effected, at 92,300/. initial “ and 8,515/. annual recurring expenditure. “ The expenditure involved in the Committee’s “ recommendations, even when limited to the “ smaller scheme, is very considerable. It was “ clearly laid down by Lord Morley, in the letter to “ the Foreign Office of the 22nd December 1908, “ proposing the appointment of the Committee, that “ the question of giving effect to its recommenda- “ tions must be governed by financial considera- “ tions, and the Lords Commissioners of the “ Treasury, in their letter to the Foreign Office of “ the 27th January 1909, were unable to hold out “ any prospect of a contribution from the British “ Exchequer towards the cost of any lights. In “ these circumstances, and in view of the necessity “ for rigid economy in Indian finance, Lord Morley “ is not prepared to consider at present the question “ 0 f giving effect to the Committee’s recommenda- “ tions. He proposes, subject to any observations “ the Lords Commissioners may have to offer, to “ inform the Government of India accordingly.” A copy of the letter addressed to the Admiralty was forwarded to the Foreign Office with a request for their observations. Pol. 3620/09. Admiralty on the 1st September in reply to oner 4 5. In reply, the Foreign Office concurred in the view that it was impossible at the moment to cany into effect the full scheme recommended by the Committee, but they urged as a first step the taking over of the buovs of the British India C ompanv. The Admiralty also agreed, and, after some further correspondence, the assent of the Freasury was obtained to the equal division between British and Indian revenues of the estimated expenditure involved in this proposal, viz., 1,000L initial as payment to the Company, and 1351. 6s. Sd. annual recurring, in respect of future maintenance, lire deed of assignment that was ultimately executed on the 9th February 1911 provided for the transfer to Government of the full number of 15 buoys and one beacon (at Bahrein) that had belonged to the Company, on the understanding that a portion of the sum of 1,0001. should be refunded later, in view of the fact that certain buoys had been reported as missing at the time when the deed was executed. It was arranged that for the future the buoys should he maintained by the Royal Indian Marine, who were also to be responsible for replacing the missing buoys except one—the “ Lawrence ” buoy—that was no longer required owing to the shifting of the Shatt-al-Arab channel. Adoption of modified proposal for taking over buoys. Letter of Foreign Office to India Office, 4th October 1909. Pol. 4058/09. Letter of Admiralty to India Office, 19th October 1909. Pol. 4132/09. Letter of Foreign Office to India Office, 20th July 1910. Pol. 3704/10. Pol. 2990/11. Letter to British India Steam Naviga tion Company, 7th February 1911. Pol. 2904 b/11. Secretary of State’s Secret Despatch No. 22, llth August 1911. Pol. 3997/11. Telegram to Viceroy, 5th January 1911. Pol. 4388/10. 6. During the time when the transfer of these buoys Activity of Turkey in the Shatt-al- to Government was being arranged, reports were Arab, and laying down of a British furnished by His Majesty’s Consul of meetings held at lighted buoy. Basrah on the 21st and 28th June 1910, at which the Pol. 3624/11, also 3259/11. local German community had supported projects for the lighting and buoyage of the Shatt-al-Arab by Turkish agency. Further, the Turkish Com modore stated that he would ask his Government to undertake the lighting of Fao and the outer bar of the Shatt-al-Arab without any charge on shipping. At the instance of Colonel Cox, it was decided as a counter-measure to place an acetylene gas buoy on the outer bar, at a cost estimated not to exceed 600Z. initial, plus 40Z. annual re- Letter of Foreign Office to Treasury, curring, in respect of maintenance. Of this 2nd August 1910. expenditure the Treasury agreed to defray a Letter of Treasury to Foreign Office, moiety as before, the political aspect of the matter 6th August 1910. being strongly urged on them by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.* The placing of the buoy was expedited on news being received from Con stantinople that a scheme for buoying and lighting the Shatt-al-Arab had been submitted to the Turkish Minister of Marine. 7. A further development took place a little later when the Commander of the Turkish guard- ship in the Shatt-al-Arab declared that he had categorical instructions to lay down buoys and that the matter had been rendered urgent by the constant complaints of German vessels. Instruc tions were thereupon issued by the Government of India to the Naval Commander-in-Chief that the British buoys should be laid down without regard roi. a/yu/iu. * The claim submitted by the British India Company for the buoy and a supply of carbide amounts to 616Z. 8s. lOd. Pol. 3997/11. Letter of Foreign Office to India Office, 20th January 1911. Pol. 2887/10. Continuance of Turkish activity. telegram, 24th February Pol. 363/11. Viceroy’s 1911.* The point was later raised whether the Turkish huoys should not be removed if found to constitute a danger to navi gation. Telegram from Admiralty to Naval Commander-in-Chief, 2nd March 1911 Pol. 8242/11. Letter of Foreign Office to India Office, 2nd March 1911. Pol. 3089/11. British, and Turkish Lights and Buoys in the Shatt-al-Arab. Pol. 1023/11. Pol. 825/11. to the Turkish buoys, that any interference with our existing buoys should be prevented, but that the Turkish buoys when placed should not be removed as we had no right to remove them.' :i: * The instructions were later approved by His Majesty’s Government. 8. The activity of the Turkish authorities still continued. Reports were received of their plans for supplying pilots at the mouth of the Shatt-al- Arab, for a lighthouse at Fao, a light-vessel near the outer bar, and the laying of further buoys. The chart, referred to at the head of this memo randum, which accompanied a letter of the Director of the Royal Indian Marine, dated the 15th May last, shows the situation at last arrived at. According to this information there are now in the Shatt-al-Arab five Turkish buoys and one Turkish light vessel, while the British buoys are seven in number, of which one is the lighted gas buoy referred to in paragraph 6. According to a telegram from the Naval Com mander-in-Chief, dated the 22nd April last, the position of these lights and buoys is as follows :— Pol. 1149/11 : 4832'! 1.. Pol. 1990/11: 4832/11. British Buoys. Turkish. Buoys. Light Vessel. High seas - 5 2 1 Turkish waters 1 3 — Persian waters 1 — — The Turks, it may be added, have issued formal notices to Mariners regarding their lights and buoys, and have even been reported from time to time to be intending to tamper with the British buoys. Quite recently we have heard also of Turkish proposals for the dredging of the Shatt-al- Arab bar. The Conservancy of the Shatt-al- Arab. Memorandum to Turkish Government, 29th July 1911. Pol. 3912/11. Letter of Admiralty to India Office, 29th April 1911. Pol. 3425/11. t Vide— Letter of India Office to Foreign Office, 5th May 1911. Pol. 3425/11. Letter of Foreign Office to India Office, 8th May 1911. Pol. 3484/11. Letter of India Office to Foreign Office, 12th May 1911. Pol. 3484/11. Viceroy’s telegram 16fch 1911. Pol. SSG/ll. . _ .Letter of Admiralty to India Office, l/tli May 1911. Pol. 3535/11. Letter of India Office to Foreign Office, 3rd June 1911. Pol. 830/11. 9. The whole question of the conservancy of the Shatt-al-Arab was thus forced to the front, and in a letter to the Government of India, dated the 24th March last, the Naval Commander-in-Chief reported that the situation was becoming an impossible one:—“The only solution,” he continued, “would “ appear to be the formation of an international “ commission on which Turkey, Persia and Great “ Britain would be represented .... It may “ prove necessary to admit German and Russian “ representatives on the conservancy, but I am “ strongly of opinion that this would be a lesser “ evil than to allow the Turks to have the uncon- “ trolled management of the waterway.” It is unnecessary here to follow the course of the corre- spondencef that ensued upon the Admiral’s sug-G gestion. The decision ultimately arrived at hy |hs Majesty’s Government is defined in the lollowing extract from a memorandum communicated to the Turkish Ambassador on the ^9th July last - : — “ Certain difficulties have recently arisen in “ regard to the buoyage of the Shatt-al-Arab. For “ a great number of years British shipping has, “ owing to its volume, been predominantly, and “ until recently almost exclusively, interested in “ these aids to navigation. For over fifty years the “ work of surveying, buoying, and lighting the “ river has been carried out by British agency to “ the general satisfaction of all conci rued. “ In these circumstances. His Majesty s Govern- “ ment have some difficulty in appreciating why the “ Ottoman Government have taken exception to “ existing and long-standing arrangements ; but, “ being desirous of dealing with the difficulty in a “ spirit of conciliation, they would propose to the “ Ottoman Government the appointment of a small “ riverain commission, comprised of a British and a “ Turkish representative, with an engineer to be “ mutually agreed upon. This commission would “ superintend all matters pertaining to improvement 5 ‘ of navigation, and it would likewise superintend “ the requisite periodical surveys. “ As regards the rest of the Persian Gulf, on the “ other hand, the Turkish Government, so far as “ they are concerned, would recognise the right of “ Great Britain (a) to control surveying, lighting, “ buoying, and pilotage ; (6) to police its waters ; “ and (c) to conduct all quarantine arrangements.” Pol. 3912/11. * This was in accordance with the recommendation of a Report by the Sub-Committee of Imperial Defence, dated the 14th July 1911. r 10. it is proposed now to describe in greater detail the projects at present before His Majesty’s Government for the lighting and buoyage of the Persian Gulf. In a letter to the Government of India, dated the 25th February 1911,it was strongly urged by the Naval Commander-in-Chief that certain of the lights and buoys that had been recommended by the Committee of enquiry should be provided with out delay. Correspondence ensued between the Foreign Office, the Admiralty, and the India Office, with the result that on the 15th September last a letter was addressed to the Foreign Office requesting that the Treasury might be moved to accept as a charge against British revenues a moiety of expen diture, estimated according the most accurate data obtainable at— £ Initial - - - 47,600 Annual recurring - _ 2,490 for the provision of— (1) An acetylene gas buoy and one light-vessel in the Shatt-al-Arab ; (2) Lighthouses at Musandam (Little Quoin) Tanb Island, and Shaikh Shuaib Island ; and (3) A light vessel for Bushire. Projects now under consideration for Lighting and Buoyage of the Persian Gulf. Pol. 501/11. * Copy included in selection of printed correspondence enclosed in letter to Foreign Office, dated 15th September 1911, of which copy sent to Admiralty 16th idem. Letter of India Office to Foreig'n Office,- 15th September 1911. Pol. 1402/11.Pol. 1599/11. It w as further explained that a lighthouse tern lei, an essential part of the scheme, might have t°. P e provided at an estimated cost of e(),000h initial, and 5,000L annual recurring. Particulars of the expenditure are printed as Appendix III. In a subsequent letter dated the 18th November 1911, it was recommended that in addition certain buoys should be laid at an estimated expenditure of— Jnitial - - _ 2,800 Annual recurring - _ 210 Particulars in Appendix IV. A further communi cation was promised as to the lighthouse tender. Question of the Light vessels in the Shatt-al-Arab, and at Bushire. The Lighthouse Tender and the Depot at Koweit. Pol. 4591/11. # Cost of light-vessel—9,500L initial, and 650/. annual recurring. t Cost of light-buoy—600/. initial, and 40/. annual recurring. Pol. 3616/11. Pol. 1538/11. Telegrams to Viceroy, 19th October and 16th November 1911. Pol. 1599 and 4591/11. 11. In a letter dated the 28th October 1911, the Treasury drew attention to certain points in con nection with the scheme, but expressed their readiness to bear a moiety of the charges connected with the provision of the acetylene gas buoy in the Shatt-al-Arab, and of the lighthouses at Musandam, Tanb Island, and Sheikh Shuaib Island. They questioned, on the other hand, the necessity of the light-vessel- proposed for the Shatt-al-Arab, and urged the substitution of a light-buoy f for a light- vessel' at Bushire, in view of certain observations made in Admiral Slade’s letters to the Admiralty and the Government of India, dated the 11th May and 6th August respectively, which seemed to iudicate that less expensive proposals might suffice. Correspondence is still proceeding with the Government of India as regards the suggestions made by the Treasury, also as to the provision and cost of the lighthouse tender. Another item of expenditure that must apparently also be provided for is that of the depot which the Committee recommended should be located at Koweit for gas-works, the storage of buoys, &amp;c. In Mr. Hood’s estimates a capital sum of 22,000b was entered on this account, but presumably the expenditure will be considerably less in view of the more restricted character of the lighting and buoyage proposals now under consideration. In any case no allowance need be made in respect of the maintenance of the depot, since charges on this account are included in the estimates given in Mr. Hood's Report of the cost of the several lights. Summary of maximum possible 12. Assuming, for the sake of completeness, that expenditure. the lights and buoys recommended in the letters of the India Gffice of the 15th September and 18th November 1911 {see paragraph 10 above) were all provided (without the adoption of the Treasury suggestions), that a lighthouse tender were procured at a cost of 30,0001. initial, and 5,000b annual re curring, and that a depot were equipped at the full8 capital cost of 22,000^., the resulting expenditure would amount to— . £ Initial - - _ _ 102,400 Annual recurring - - 7,700 It will be noted that a large proportion of this expenditure, both initial and annual, is represented by the cost of the lighthouse tender. 13. At this point mention may be made of two projects which though not directly connected with the subject of this Memorandum may yet entail considerable expenditure . of a somewhat similar kind. In the first place, it is proposed to carry out certain surveys in the Persian Gulf that may entail the employment of a Royal Indian Marine vessel for several years. The Government of India have been asked for information as to the cost and duration of the operations, in order that the Treasury may be approached as to bearing a moiety of the charge. Secondly, the provision of wireless telegraph stations in the Persian Gulf has recently been considered, and, subject to the concurrence of the Foreign Office, the Secretary of State in Council has approved a scheme estimated to cost approximately 19,087k initial, and 4,647k annual recurring. This expenditure also would be equally divisible between British and Indian Revenues. 14. The question whether any part of the expenditure to be incurred in the lighting and buoyage of the Persian Gulf could be recouped by means of the levy of light dues has frequently been raised in our correspondence, but the matter presents great difficulties, and it has been strongly urged that the inception of the lighting and buoy age scheme should not be delayed pending a satisfactory solution.* In a letter + dated the 29th March last, the Foreign Office wrote as follows on this subjectThe suggested levy could not be “ carried out without the consent of the Powers “ whose flags are flown by the vessels navigating “ the Gulf, and such consent would not be forth- “ coming except on conditions implying that very “ international control which it is the aim of His “ Majesty’s Government to exclude.” I he point has again been touched upon in the correspondence between the Treasury and the foreign Office, and the position will become clearer if ever negotiations on the basis of the British Memorandum to Turkey of the 29th July last (paragraph 9 above) are successfully concluded. J. E. F. Political Department, India Office, 28th December 1911. Two connected questions:— (1) Sur veys; (2) Wireless Telegraph Instal lations. Telegram to Viceroy, 18th 1911. Pol. 4638/11. November Letter of India Office to Foreign Office, 13th December 1911. P. W. 1911/11. Question of Light Dues. * Vide Letter of Naval Commander-in- Chief to the Government of India, dated 25th February 1911. (Pol. 501/11). Telegram of Political Resident to Go vernment of India, dated 17th March 1911. (Pol. 3304/11). 4 Letter of Foreign Office to India Office, dated the 29th March 1911. (Pol. 3241/11). Letter of Treasury to Foreign Office dated 28th October 1911. (Pol. 4591/11).A MHBH &amp; A P P E N D I C E S. APPENDIX I. (Referred to in paragraph 3.) ?orepOfc. Extract from Report of a Committee of Enquiry on the Lighting and Buoyage of the Persian Gulf, dated the 29th April 1909. (Pol. 3503/09.) Summary of Proposed Lights and Buoys. Lighthouses and Light Vessels. Buoys. Place. *• Position. Range in Miles. Character. Position. Description. Muscat Jask10 APPENDIX II. (Referred to in paragraph 4.) Extract from Supplementary Report by Mr. I). W. Hood, dated 28th June 1909. (Pol. 3620/09.) SUMMARY. To complete the first seven liglits as recommended by the Committee of Enquiry, in conjunction with the establishment of the Lingah and Debai Port lights, would probably necessitate the following expenditure : — Lighthouses, Ac. First Cost. Annual Maintenance. £ £ Steam tender ----- 30,000 5,000 Depot at Koweit, equipped with gasworks, storehouses, 22,000 Distributed buoy yard, spare light vessel, spare buoys, cables, Ac. throughout this column. Shatt-al-Arab light vessel and four buoys 11,900 810 Little Quoin lighthouse - - - - 12,500 400 Muscat lighthouse 8,000 350 Bushire light vessel and one buoy - 10,100 690 Shaikh Shuaib lighthouse 8,000 400 Ras-al-Mutaf light vessel 9,500 650 Tanb lighthouse - - - . 7,500 350 Lingah Port light - . . . 600 35 Debai Port light ... 450 35 Total - . . 120,550 8,720 To complete the first seven lights recommended by the Committee of Enquiry, m conjunction with the establishment of Lingah and Debai Port lights, but adopting the simplest alternatives for the steamer and Bushire, would probably involve the following expenditure : — Lighthouses, Ac. First Cost. Annual Maintenance. Steam tender: Adaptation of existing ship (say ) Depot at Koweit, equipped with gasworks, storehouses, buoy yard, spare light vessel, spare buoys, cables, &amp;c. Shatt-al-Arab light vessel and four buoys Little Quoin lighthouse - . _ Muscat lighthouse - - . . Bushire lighthouse and two buoys Shaikh Shuaib lighthouse Ras-al-Mutaf light vessel Tanb lighthouse - . . _ Lingah Port light Debai Port light Total - - _ £ 2,500 5,000 22,000 Distributed throughout this column. 11,900 810 12,500 400 8,000 350 9,350 485 8,000 400 9,500 650 7,500 350 600 35 450 35 92,300 8,515 Pnrmoi 1 fw ^P ^ le . w ^°^ e °| lights in the Persian Gulf, as recommended by the Committee of Enquiry, would probably necessitate the following expenditure11 of Enqui Annual raughontlii Steam tender Depot at Koweit, equipped with gasworks, storehouses, buoy yard, spare light vessel, spare buoys, cables, &amp;c. Shatt-al-Ai'ab light vessel and four buoys Little Quoin lighthouse - - - . . Muscat lig’hthouse - - . Bushire light vessel and one buoy - - _ Shaikh Shuaib lighthouse - - . Ras-al-Mutaf light vessel - - _ . Tanb lighthouse - . . . Lingah Port light - - - . . Debai Port light - - . . Kubbar Island lighthouse - . . _ Ras-al-Arz lighthouse - - - . Bahrein, two light vessels and two buoys Bunder Abbas, lighthouse on Kishm and one buoy Unlit buoys for Jask, Bunder Abbas, Koweit, and Bahrein, and re-construction of Bahrein beacon. Total . . . £ 30.000 22.000 11,900 12,500 8,000 10,100 8,u00 9.500 7.500 600 450 8.500 3,000 16,700 8,100 1,300 158,150 £ 5,000 Distributed throughout this column. 810 400 350 690 400 650 350 35 35 400 100 980 440 105 10,745 To complete the whole of the lights in the Persian Gulf recommended by the Committee of Enquiry, hut adopting the simplest alternatives for the steam tender and the Bunder Abbas, Bushire, and Bahrein lights, would probably necessitate the following expenditure : — Lighthouses, &amp;c. First Cost. Annual Maintenance. £ £ Steam tender: Adaptation of existing skip (say) 2,500 5,000 Depot at Koweit, equipped with gas works, storehouses, 22,000 Distributed buoy yard, spare light vessel, spare buoys, cables, Ac. throughout this column. Shatt-al-Arab light vessel and four buoys 11,900 810 Little Quoin lighthouse - - - - 12,500 400 Muscat lighthouse - - - - - 8,000 350 Bushire lighthouse and two buoys 9,350 485 Shaikh Shuaib lighthouse _ . _ _ 8,000 400 Ras-al-Mutaf light vessel _ _ . 9,500 650 Tanb lighthouse ------ 7,500 350 Lingah Port light - - - - 600 35 Debai Port light ----- 450 35 Kubbar Island lighthouse - - - 8,500 400 Ras-al-Arz lighthouse ----- 3,000 100 Bahrein, two buoys - - - - Bunder Abbas, port light on Larak and one buoy 1,350 85 1,050 75 Unlit buoys for Jask, Bunder Abbas, Koweit, and Bahrein, and reconstruction of Bahrein beacon. 1,300 105 Total . . . . 107,500 9,280 Bearing in mind the relative navigational importance of the lights tabulated in the previoiis table, they might be divided into groups to facilitate constructional requirements, as follows :— First Year. Alterations to existing steamship - - - Gas buoys for Shatt-al-Arab - - Light vessel for Shatt-al-Arab - - - - { Spare light vessel - - - - Portion of depot and spare buoys, and equipment for light vessels _____ Muscat lighthouse - - - Lingah Port light _ _ _ _ _ Debai _ _ _ _ _ £ 2.500 2,400 9.500 9,500 S. 126. fSecond Series. Portion of depot - Ras-al-Mntaf light vessel Little Quoin lighthouse - Tanb lighthouse Larak Port light Euphrates Shoal gas buoy £ 5.500 9.500 12,500 7.500 450 600 Total £36,050 Third Series. Completion of depot - - - Shaikh Shuaib lighthouse - - - Bushire lighthouse - - - - - Bushire, two gas buoys - - - _ Kubbar Island lighthouse - - - - Ras-al-Arz lighthouse - Unlit buoys for Jask, Bunder Abbas, Koweit, and Bahrein - - - - - Two gas buoys for Bahrein, and reconstruction of beacon - - _ _ _ £ 2,000 8,000 8,000 1,350 8,500 3,000 800 1,850 Total - _ _ _ . £33,500 Showing combined total of 107,500b Should a more elaborate and efficient system of lighting the approaches to Bahrein be adopted, it might form a fourth series. APPENDIX III. (Referred to in 'paragraph 10). Statement of Lights enclosed in letter of India Office to Foreign Office, 15th September 1911. (Pol. 1402/11.) 1. 2 . 3. 4. 5. 6 . Locality. Nature of Proposal. First Cost. Annual Maintenance. Remarks. Shatt-al-Arab (а) One acety lene gas buoy at inner bar. (б) One light vessel. £ 600 9,500 £ 40 650 See Mr. Hood’s estimate on p. 8 of printed report of 28th June 1909. Ditto, p. 8. Musandim (Little Quoin) One lighthouse 12,500 400 Ditto, p. 5. Tanb island One lighthouse 7,500 350 Ditto, p. 6. Ditto, p. 7. Sheikh [Shuaib One lighthouse 8,000 400 Bushire One light vessel 9,500 650 Ditto, p. 8. Total - 47,600 2,490 One lighthouse tender. 30,000 5,000 Ditto, p. 2. This is pro vided for on the as sumption that the Patrick Stewart can not be employed. Grand Total - 77,600 7,490APPENDIX IV. (Referred to in paragraph 10 ) List of Buoys enclosed in India Office letter to Foreign Office, 18tli November 1911. (Pol. 2599/11.) Place. Position. Description. Approximate Cost as stated in Mr. D. W. Hood’s Report, 28th June 1909. Initial. Annual Recurring. £ £ Bahrein Ras Kaseifa One lighted 600 40 West Spit One lighted 600 40 Off Jadum One unlit 100 15 Bushire Inner anchorage One lighted 600 40 Bunder Abbas* Off shoals E. of Kishm One lighted 600 40 Anchorage at Bunder One unlit 200 20 Abbas. Jask 2 miles N.W. of Jask One unlit 100 15 Point. Total - 2,800 210 * The first scheme set out in the Summary to the Report of the Committee, dated the 29th April 1909, is here adopted.2ns A B. 187a. This Do cument is the property of the Secretary of Stale for India in Council. SECRET. SECOND MEMORANDUM ON THE LIGHTING AND BUOYAGE OF THE PERSIAN GULP. (In continuation of the Memorandum, dated the 28th December 1911. B. 187.) Charts :— (1.) u Chart to accompany the Report of a Committee on Lighthouses for the Persian Gulf, dated 29th April 1909.” (Pol. 3620/1909 ; copy sent to Foreign Office and Admiralty 1st September 1909.) (2.) Persian Gulf Mouth of the Shatt-al-Arab River ,’’ the tracing that accompanied the lettei of the Director of the Royal Indian Marine to the Secretary to the Government of India, Marine Department, No. o270, dated, the Ibth May 1911. (Pol. 4013/1911 ; copg sent to Foreign Office and Admiralty, li)th August 1911.) Scope of the Memorandum. 1. It may be useful to explain, in continuation of the printed departmental Memorandum of the 28th December 1911, the present position of the scheme for the Lighting and Buoyage of the Persian Gull, adopted as the result of the local enquiry held in 1909. A convenient starting point is the summary of maximum possible expenditure,” described in paragraph 12 of that Memorandum in the following words : “ Assuming, for the sake of completeness, that the lights and buoys recom- “ mended in the letters of the India Office of the “ leth September and 18th November 1911 (see “ paragraph 10 above) were all provided (without “ the adoption of the Treasury suggestions), that a “ lighthouse tender were procured at a cost of “ 30,000L initial, and 5,000L annual recurring, “ and that a depot were equipped at the full “ capital cost of 22,000h, the resulting expenditure “ would amount to initial 102,400L, annual “ recurring 7,700L” Modifications in India Office scheme. Letter of Treasury to Foreign Office, 6th June, 1912. P. 2306/12. Viceroy’s telegram, 5th February 1912. P. 416/12. Viceroy’s telegram, 15th May 1912. P. 1838/12. 2. The “ Treasury suggestions ” above referred to were that a light vessel proposed for the Shatt- el-Arab should be dispensed with, and that a lighted buoy should be substituted at Bushire for a light- vessel. After some correspondence the Treasury withdrew their objection to the Shatt-al-Arab light- vessel, but, as regards Bushire, it was decided that a lighted buoy (at the outer anchorage in addition to that for the inner anchoTage) would be sufficient. In another important respect the scheme described in paragraph 1 was modified, viz., in the elimination of the spare light-vessel (cost 9,500L) that had been included as part of the equipment of the depot (cost 22,000Z.) S. 186 . AScheme as ultimately sanctioned. 3. The items of the scheme as ultimately sanctioned were, therefore, as follows : Light, &amp;c., and Locality. Approximate Cost as stated in Mr. D. W. Hood’s Report, 28th June 1909. Initial. Annual Recurring. Lighthouses (3) :— £ £ Musandam (Little Quoin) - 12,500 400 Tanb Island 7,500 350 Shaikh Shuaib Island - 8,000 400 Light-vessel (1) :— 9,500 650 Shatt-al-Arab Buoys :— (a) Lighted (6) :— 600 40 Shatt-al-Arab* (inner bar). Bushire (inner 600 40 anchorage). 600 40 Bushire (outer anchorage). 600 40 Bahrein (Has Kaseifa) Bahrein (West Spit) 600 40 Bunder Abbas (off 600 40 shoals East of Kishm). (fe) Unlit (3) 100 15 Bahrein (off Jadun) - Bunder Abbas 200 20 (anchorage). 100 15 Jask Lighthouse Tender (Persian Gulf). Lighthouse Depot (Abadan Island). 30,000 5,000 12,500 Distributed over the cost of the several lights. Total 84,000 7,090 * In abeyance, see paragraph 6. It is in addition to the British lighted buoy already laid in the Shatt-al-Arab (outer bar). See paragraph 6 of earlier Memorandum. Thus the sanctioned scheme includes three light-houses, one light-vessel, six lighted and three unlit buoys. These are in addition to the lighted buoy provided for the outer bar of the Shatt-al-Arab in 1911 and the unlit buoys taken over from the British India Company.| It was subsequently decided that the cost of two dioptric lanterns for Bushire (see paragraph 11 below) should be met from savings out of the total figures here given. t Paragx-aphs 5 and 6 of Memorandum dated the 28th December 1911. Letters of India Office to Foreign Office, 28th May and 27th September 1912. P. 1803 and 3095/12. 4. By good fortune it was found possible to The Lighthouses, obtain for the Tanb Island lighthouse the plant that had been ordered for a lighthouse for the Colonial Office. The construction of this light house is consequently well in hand. The plant for the lighthouse at Musandam has been ordered, but will not be ready for several months. As regards the Shaikh Shuaib lighthouse, there has been a hitch, owing to the fact that the conditions attached by the Persian Government to the erection of a lighthouse on their territory are , unacceptable His Majesty’s Minister at Tehran is T ,Ai e jGAm! im Oetobe/'bS being consulted as to approaching the Persian ‘ p. 4100/12.3 * 6. Itisi ioy abjjiiij Seepnp|k{ to M' Septeut® Government once more with a view to the grant of a concession—say, a lease for 99 years—which would allow a lighthouse to be built and worked by His Majesty’s Government. If it were not for the expense, a good way out of the difficulty would be the substitution of a light-vessel for the proposed lighthouse. The cost of the lighthouse, as stated above, is 8,000h initial, and 400h annual recurring. The corresponding figures for the cost of a light-vessel, according to Irinity House estimates, are 9,500L initial, and 650h annual recurring. (The Indian authorities have, however, stated that they could themselves build a light-vessel for 1,080/. less, he., 8,420/., see paragraph 5 below.) . 'V The Light-vessel. 5. On the recommendation of the Government Viceroy’s telegram, 15th May 1912. of India the light-vessel for the Shatt-al-Arab is P. 1838/12. being constructed in Bombay Dockyard, where light-vessels have been built for the Bay of Bengal. According to latest information, it is' anticipated that a saving of 1,080/. may he effected on the sanctioned estimate (9,500/.) The iron mast, lantern, &amp;c. are to be sent out from home. Xjll The Lighted Buoys. Telegram of Secretary of State to Viceroy, 3rd April 1912. P. 1149/12. * Vide draft Convention forming An nex 2 to the Memorandum communicated to the Turkish Ambassador 18th July 1912. P. 2783/12. 6. Five lighted buoys have been sent out (in addition to the lighted buoy provided for the outer bar of the Shatt-al-Arab in 1911). The sixth, intended for the inner bar of the Shatt-al-Arab, is not for the present being supplied, in view of the negotiations opened with the Turkish Government for the establishment of a Shatt-al-Arab Navigation Commission.* The Unlit Buoys. Telegram of Secretary of State to Viceroy, 27th May 1912. P. 1838/12. The Lighthouse Tender. Report of Committee, 29th April 1909. para. 12. Letter of Director'of the Royal Indian Marine, 31st August 1912. P. 3707/12. 7. The unlit buoys are, like the light-vessel, being constructed in Bombay Dockyard on the recommendation of the Government of India. 8. A matter in which no progress has yet been made is that of the lighthouse tender. The Committee that reported after local inquiry in 1909 on the lighting and buoyage of the Persian Gulf regarded it as imperative that a specially constructed steamer should be provided to act as a lighthouse tender, and Air. 1). W. Hood, the expert member of the Committee, wrote in his Supplementary Report:—“ I estimate her cost, “ delivered in the Persian Gulf, after construction “ in England, at 30,000/. The Indian Government “ from their own experience will be able to estimate “ what her annual maintenance would be in the “ East, but it would probably amount to about “ 5,000/. per annum, inclusive of wages, repairs, “ coal, stores, and all charges.” These figures—initial expenditure 30,000/., and annual recurring 5,000/.—represent the maximum estimate sanctioned by the Secretary of State in Council and the Treasury, but the plans received from India are for a larger vessel than that contem plated, undone that would cost very much more to maintain. The matter is still under consideration.The Lighthouse Depot. 9. It was first proposed to locate the lighthouse depot at Koweit, but this plan was abandoned in favour of a site on the land leased by the Anglo- Persian Oil Company on the island of Abadan, near Mohammerah. Details are about to be investigated locally, but the conditions contemplated are, briefly, that land up to a total of two acres should be rented at ll. an acre for 49 years from the 29th May 1912, the period of the Company’s own lease, and that the Company should carry out certain works recommended by the Trinity House,* supply oil (if in accordance with specification), and erect the necessary oil tanks. It is hoped that the result of the local investi gation will enable work at the depot to proceed without delay. An appreciable saving should apparently be effected on the cost of the depot, as originally estimated, through the employment of the Anglo-Persian Oil Company’s agency. Letter of Foreign Office to Anglo- Persian Oil Company. 19th October 1912 P. 4069/12. * Letter of Trinity House to India Office, 25th April 1912, paragraph 13. P. 2182/12. Letter of Trinity House to India Office 7th October 1912. P. 3881/12. Letter of Trinity House to India Office, 25th April 1912. P. 2182/12. 10. In accordance with the recommendation of Trinity House, certain stores for the depot are being sent out from England, viz 2 spare lighted buoys. 2 spare lanterns. 3 sets of spare buoy moorings. It is also in contemplation to send out a'craffA. 11. Mention may here be made of the supply of two dioptric lanterns for the Residency at Bushire at an estimated cost of approximately 124b initial expenditure, plus 2| per cent, for Trinity House charges, and 24b annual recurring. The Treasury took exception to the supply of these lanterns outside the sanctioned programme, and explanations were furnished by this Office. 12. In a letter to the Foreign Department, dated the 11th August 1912, Sir P. Cox has called attention to “ the regrettable consequences, both political and economic, that might result from the failure of any* light, even temporarily,” and, with a view to placing future administrative arrange ments on a satisfactory footing, has suggested that for the present the Political Resident should be theb chief lighting authority in (he Grulf and ex otjicio Inspector of Lights,” and that pending the provision of the lighthouse tender the officer commanding the R.I.M.S. “Lawrence” should be gazetted “ Assistant Inspector of Lights.” He has also suggested a scale of allowances for officers and men of the “Lawrence” employed in lighting and buoyage work. The views of the Government of India on these proposals have not yet been received. Any extra expenditure on this head may perhaps be met out of savings effected on other parts of the scheme. Stores for the Depot from England. Letter of India. Office to Trinity House, 15th October 1912. P. 3903/12. Letter of Trinity House, 7th October 1912. P. 3881/12. Two Dioptric Lanterns for Bushire. Letter of India Office to Foreign Office, 28th May 1912. P. 1803/12. Letter of India Office to Foreign Office, 27th September 1912. P. 3095/12. ' i;' . Future Administrative Arrangements. P. 3599/12. J. E. F. Political Department, India Office, 8th November 1912.No. 2594, dated Bushire, the 13th (received 21st) October 1912. From— Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Percy Cox, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, To The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department, Simla. I have the honour to forward, for the information of the Government of India, a copy of reports which the Officer Commanding the “ Lawrence ” has Nos. 761 and 762, dated the 6th October 1912. ^ flighted buoys at Bahrain. 2. It will be seen that he reports that the moorings of all three buoys are defective; that two are out of position, and that the condition of one, the Kasaifah Shoal buoy, is bad. It appears from the statement enclosed in Trinity House letter, dated March 26th, to the India Office, that two of these buoys will be replaced by lighted buoys, the Jadum Shoal buoy being the only one of the three that will eventually remain. Seeing that the lighted buoys for Bahrain have already been made and should to the buoys which are to be replaced, but I have transmitted an emergent indent for new moorings for the Jadum Shoal buoy to the Director of the Royal Indian Marine, on receipt of which it will be carefully re-laid. Extract from a letter No. 761, dated 6lh October 1912, from the Officer Commanding RIMS &lt;c Lawrence”, Bushire, to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Regarding the outer buoy at Bahrain, I refrained from lifting these moorings entirely 6 but the upper end which I inspected shows one link of the cable so much worn that one could not now be surprised at the buoy parting from its moorings. Enclosures to letter No. 761, dated 6th October 1912, jrom the Officer Commanding, T 71/C O ** T s* /i tw nnn r*n anchor and not secured in any other way. Buoy was found to be O'? miles out of position and doubtless drifting back and fore with every spring tide. . . . Should be entirely removed and new buoy and moorings put in its place. Buoy lies well over instead of being vertical. Overhauled 2nd-3rd October 1912. made, at my request, on the condition of Vide letter from Trinity House to India Office, No. 1873, dated the 23rd July 1912. leave England very shortly, if they have not already been shipped, it seems scarcely worth while taking any action in regard R.I.M.S. “ Lawrence ”. Bahrain. Kasaifah Shoal Buoy {black). F. DeBURGH, Lieutenant, R.I.M., Commanding, R.I.M.S. “Lawrence.” 2—32 t *!. Enclosure to letter No. 761, dated 6th October 1912 from the Officer Commanding, R.LM.S. “Lawrence”. Bahrain. Outer Buoy—carrying mast and basket — Bed — Conical. Buoy .—In very good condition, but lying very much on its side after over haul, instead of being in a vertical position. Cable .—Only a few fathoms of upper end seen and this part shows some links studless and worn from 2\' down to 1 1 - 6 // and one link, in a bad nip worn to 1' only. A large double overhaul knot in upper end of cable, and it is presumed this was originally put in to give extra weight to buoy, to make it assume a vertical position in the water. A shamal blowing and no other moorings available in the event of present ones parting, the remainder of chain and anchor were not lifted. Buoy was in its right position as chartered. Overhauled 3rd : 5th October 1912. F. De BURGH, Lieutenant, B.I.M., Commanding, R.I.M.S. “Lawrence”. Copy of a letter No. 762, dated 6th October 1912, from the Officer Commanding, R.I.M.S. “ Lawrence,” to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. In reply to your remarks regarding complaints that some of our buoys are diffi cult to pick up from a navigating point of view owing to them not “ watching ” vertically, I have the honour to state that the 3 Bahrain buoys and the “ old outer bar” buoy, Shat river, all of which are large conical buoys, are insufficiently weighted through being moored in shoal water; were they in deep water with about a length of chain weighing 25 or 30 cwts. this would be sufficient to keep them upright. It may be said until the recent overhaul each of these buoys was fairly vertical and such was the case at Bahrain, especially during high water, but simply owing to the fact that the moorings of each buoy were so foul of its anchor, that there was no play in the chain to allow of anything but a vertical position for the buoy ; also silt gradually deposits on the chain lying along the bottom and assists in tautening it up between buoy and its anchor. To make these conical buoys watch efficiently it will be necessary to moor them with sinkers and not anchors, and with just sufficient chain to allow of buoy watching vertically at highest tides in a moderate sea. As an alternative each buoy could be weighted at its lower end either by water inside it or mooring chain doubled or trebled. As you are' aware, beyond scraping and painting the buoys and clearing the moorings, we have not tampered with them in any other way, so the blame of the buoy ’ not watching vertically should be placed at the door of those who originally laid them. G. M. Press, Simla.—No. C. 498 F. D.—25-10-12. -44 J.N.B.i No. 2599, dated Bushire, the 13th (received 21st) October 1912. From —Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Percy Cox, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department, Simla. I have the honour to attach an extract from a report by the Commander of the R. I. M. S. “ Lawrence ” on the condition of the buoys on the Shatt-al-Arab bar, pany, dated the 7th February 1911, enclosure 17 to Foreign, Department No. 505-E.A., dated the 13th March 1911. pany, dated the 7th February 1911, enclosure • librrmrv 1Q11 from tho 'Rritish India 17 to Foreign, Department No. 505-E.A.. dated m Pebmary iy 1 1 irom tne DritlSU India Vide Schedule attached to letter from India from which it will be seen that the three Office to British India steam Navigation Com- buoys, which remained from those taken over T'\o T~t xr /d t f-k/d F L n TP Cibvr'n n lOll /-vn /-»1 - - /» . -m -m —. • • -« -r — • Steam Navigation Company, are all in an unsatisfactory and inefficient condition and require early replacement. 2. In view of the importance of maintaining the efficiency of our buoyage scheme, particularly at the present juncture, I beg that Government will give early consideration to the replacement of these buoys. 3. I am sending a copy of this letter with enclosure to the Director, Royal Indian Marine. 1. Place. —Entrance to Shatt-al-Arab river. Descriflion. —Outer bar buoy ; red, conical (formerly a B. I. S. N. Co.’s buoy). Date when first laid. —August 1909. Date when last overhauled. —August 26th to 28th 1912. Remarks : —Chipped, scraped and painted 2 coats of composition all over and 1 of red lead. Pin of mooring shackle worn f' and not renewed. Moorings being found too short for the depth of water, an additional 3 fms. of 1 T V' chain cable was added. Should be adequately weighted when opportunity offers, so that it may watch fairly vertically. 2. Place. —Entrance to Shatt-al-Arab river. Description. —No. 4 black, conical (from B. I. S. N. Co.) Date when first laid. —July 1908. Date when last overhauled.—2Qih to 31st August 1912. Remarks. —Scraped and chipped. Painted with 1 coat each of composition, read lead and black. Buoy too old and thin to thoroughly chip. Should be re placed early as liable to sink if bumped by any boat, etc. 3. Place. —^Entrance to Shatt-al-Arab river. Description. —No. 7, black drum or cylindrical shaped (from B. I. S. N, Co.) Date when first laid. —April 1907. Date when last overhauled.—August 31st to September 2nd 1912. Remarks. —Scraped and chipped. Painted with 2 coats red lead and 2 of black. This buoy is of no recognized shape for a channel buoy and might be re placed by a conical one when practicable. No, “ 7 ” painted in white figures on buoy. Statement of condition of work done on unlighted buoys by R.I.M.S. “Lawrence ” for quarter ending 30th September 1912. G. M. Press, Simla.—No, C« 498 F, D,— 25 - 10 - 12 .— 44 .—J.N.B.321 * Enclosure I- tetter from Fcre'-o sVcre^ry'TiatlTa He. O 4|, dated 1 AUUlidi. \ C ° Py ° f l le t% r i ^ 0tt fe ls Excellency the Haval CommandeT- a-CM.1. E«« Indies 3jll « ro ,, to t „. s ., !rjl&gt;rjr to ^ 191 Government of India, Marine Department. Ho. dated Diyatalawa, the 16th June 1912. 1462/x.B. ‘ &gt; •t N With reference to Marine Department letter No. 72/146-M. of 21et May 1912, on the subject of the lighting ^ and buoying of the Persian Gulf, and requesting my remarks on the substitution of a light ship on the shah Allum Shoal tne proposed lighthouse on Sheikh Shuaib Island and the levy oi. dues, - be pleased to lay the following observations before Sis Excellency the Viceroy and Governer-Geaeral of India in Council, « ■ &gt; 'ciiyj ^ A llght vessel on s bah Allum Shoal would not be factory. The shoal is rock, a bad holding ground.and the vessel could not be anchored on its shoalest part on the sea in a SJbutiiiale Moreover it is out of the track usually taken by vessels navigating the ^ruxf. A 25-mile light would not be practicable, as it would necessitate a mast 300 feet high and a lantern weighing several tons. The usual range of light vessels us from 8 to 11 miles. Stiffs Bank would be a better 'a? 19AUG1312 posfltion. The holding ground is more suitable and the -Ji off* bank■bunk Lore nearly in the usual track of shipping, and a light vessel placed there would he a valuable aid to ships on passage though of little use for local navigation, the latter is of minor importance it is recommended that, rather than submit to the terms of the Persian Memorandum, it would he better to substitute a light vessel on Stiffe Bank for the light on Sheikh Shuaib, and thus keep the lighting of the 3ulf in our own hands. S. It is considered that no question of the levy of dues should be raised at present, The lighting of the Gulf should be entirely British and should be considered as one more illustration of the disinterested nature of British action in the Gulf, and as a means of strengthening our position later on should the construction of the Baghdad Railway raise questions which might tend to compromise it.Confidential^ FO* 1446 of 191E. Irrom lieutenant-Colonel Sir Percy Cox t ,C ♦ 3 . 1 . t Political Resident in the Persian, lulf, So She Ron 1 hie lieutenant-Colonel Sir Henry McRahon, I.C.Y.C., Secretary to the Government of India in the foreign Department f Simla, Dated Bushire, 14 th July 19 IS♦ Sir t With reference to foreign Department letter t ..o* 14iS-R.^« t dated the Snd h , I have the honour V 3 to request that the unlit huoys he consigned to - She Officer Commanding R* X* M* S. 'Lav/rence', C/o Slie *haglo-Persian Oil Company t A h a d a n. 1 have, etc., 3d* p. h* Cox, Lieutenant-Colonel, Political Resident in the Persian GulfCOM ... bixo i 30 52 Pul «way with ite ■■ ?, &lt; 1 l, I Si 2 ^ Ifo. 1442-E.A., dated Simla^the End July 1912 (Confidential) Prom - The Deputy Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department, To Lieutenant-Colonel Sir £• Z. Cox t K.C.I.S. ,C *S.I., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire With reference to the telegram from His Majesty’s Secretary of State for India, dated the 27th May 1912, a copy of which was forwarded to you with the endorsement from this Department, Ho. 1157-B.A. (Confidential), dated the 1st June 1912, I am directed to enquire to whom the 1 &amp; unit Buoys should he consigned after completion hy the Bombay Dockyard. Telegram Ho. 352, dated the 13th June 1912 From - The Director, Boyal IndianMarine, Bombay, To The Secretary to the Government of India in the Marine Department. ( Your telegram 72 M., 9th. Have arranged purchase one ton carbide, but, as British India Steam navigation Company decline to convey it in their steamers, am negotiating freight with other local shipping companies. Will report further action. Telegram ITo. 366, dated the 21st June 1912# The Director, Royal Indian Marine, Bombay, The Secretary to the Government of India in the Marine Department. My telegram 352, 13th instant. Re sident, Bushire, having’ having nov/ intimated receipt hy Consul at Llohammerah of carbide shipped hy Director-General Stores, for Shatt-el- j Arab gas huoy, no further action necessary. Do•72-151 M. , dated (and received) Simla,the 4th July 1912. Prom - Offg.Deputy Secretary to the Government of India in the Marine Department, To The Director of the Royal Indian Marine. In continuation of Marine Department Memorandum Do. 72-149 M. , dated the 6th June 1912, I am directed to for- ol /O vo T ward the accompanying copy of a tele- bated the 27th ! May 1912. I gram from the Most Hon^ole the Secretary ! of State for India and to request that the work of construction in the Royal Indian Marine Dock yard, Bombay, of the unlit 'buoys for Jask, Bandar .Abbas and Bahrein, may be put In hand at once. The buoys should not, ho?/ever, be despatched to the stations men tioned without a reference to the Government of India. 2 . I am to add that the cost of the buoys in question will be shared equally between the Imperial and Indian Governments, the Indian moiety being debited to the Royal Indian Marine Estimates.-Jl — Any further communication on this subject should be addi-essed to THE SECRETARY, TRINITY HOUSE, TOWER HILI, LONDON, E.C., and the following letter and number- should be quoted: I. 219 5 ^^Telegraphic Address-- DIOPTRIC, LONDON. imiOun. (6.C. 30th July 1912. I f b i 2 -J Dir Agreeably co the request containec- in v C ur letter of uj. .5 25tii Instant, P.2883, I am directed to transmit, for under tarate cove communication uo tlie Groveminent of India drawings in dupli- r • / / cate^showing in detail the construction of a Second Class Can Buoy and a Fifth Class Conical Buoy, with specifications &gt; together with a separate drawing of the Hast and mounting applicable to both types of Buoys. I an, Dir H Your obedient Servant, 31 JULim2 IKDI^ oFF ' _) Under Secretary of State for India, India Office,1 In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote ItoT- icte lb0 7 and address— 6. - Si The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. T/ie Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Undersecretary of State for ^ and y by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop \ of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, iifsuii, i / , 19 J ■r. f .'-v ’ ' » - ^ 1 Reference to previous letter , o Description of Inclosure. Name and Date. Subject.BRITISH EMBASSY 71. Ime^ial. 735) . CONST AMTINO PLE. April 3rd 1912. Sir With reference to my despatch No.52 Commercial of March 12th, I have the honour to forward herewith a Despatch, as marked in the margin, from His Majesty's Consul at Basra respecting the position of one of the British buoys. I have &amp;c. (Signed) Gerard Lowther. Majesty*s Principal Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.12. BRITISH CONSULATE, BASRA. March 8 th 1912. 1 Sir: - With reference to my despatch No.10 of the 12 th ultimo, I have the honour to transmit copy of a letter received from the Officer commanding the Royal Indian Marine Ship 'Palinurus', containing his observations on the British buoy which formed the subject of the Vali's ^/v letter to me No. 119 of February 11 th last. In view of the line taken by the Vali in his letter I do not think any useful purpose would be served by my corresponding with him locally on the subject, and I refrain from transmitting to His Excellency a transla tion of the Commander's reply pending your instructions on the subject. I have &amp;c., (Signed) F.E.Crow. , 5 Excellency 3 v The Right Honourable Sir G- .A.Lowther, G.C .M.G., C.B., &lt;5 101 &amp;c ., &amp;c., &amp;c.d&gt; mmmm mtmm PBbMHMM 504. 296 ROYAL INDIAN MARINE SHIP ’’PALINURUS”, K 0 W E I T. February 24th 1912 With reference to your Nob. 16 and 17 of 1912 and telegram, previously received I have the honour to state that the buoy referred to (No.2 British) see chart No. 1235 is not out of its place nor do I consider it un- 1 necessary as stated by the Vali of Basra. In view of the fact that I have surveyed the river entrance in 1911 end again in 1912 I am in a position to maintain that No.2 buoy is placed in the most advantageous posi tion to keep deep draft vessels clear off shoal A&amp;ter on the port hand when entering and that No.l (Turkish buoy) if anything is misleading as it is inside our buoy. I gather from the copies of correspondence forwarded that no action is contemplated on our part and I shall therefore refrain from moving thd inner bar buoy (British) which is slightly out of position and which I had proposed moving back to the position shown on chart No.1235. jj ta (Signed) Britannic Majesty^ Consul, Basra. I have &amp;c., Watford Taylor. Commander R.I.M,S.'Palinurus”.(COPY) Eo* 342 oP 1912. (Confidential)''J - British Residency end Oonsnloite General. T? ushire 24th Pehriiary 1912. Prom To Sir, In continuation of this office telegram ITo. 112, * dated the 11 th Pehru&amp;ry 1912, 1 have the honour to forward, for the information of the GrOYernment of India, a copy of ”o. 8 , dated 12th February 1912, with enclosures. T the conumnication J. H* Bill, Esquire, First Assistant Resident, (In the absence of the Resident), The Hon’ble Lieutenant Colonel Sir Henry HcHahon, C.C.y.C., Secretary tc the Government of India in the Foreign Department, Calcutta. marginally noted received from His Majesty , s Consul at Basrah, regarding one of our buoys on the Ghatt~el~Arab Bar. I have, etc..0 P Y . 1 3Jo • 8 . Dated^ Basrah, lEth February 1912, Forwarded, to the Besident at Bushire with the compli ments of the undersigned. j. 1 • T? Or or, rv His Majesty’s Consul, British Consulate, Basrah, 12th February 1912. Bo. 10* Sir, T 7 ith reference to my telegram Bo. 18 of the 10th instant, T hcye the honour to transmit herewith enclosed translation of a letter received from the Vali of Basrah, objecting to one of our buoys and stating it should be removed and not replaced. I luve not replied to this communication but have * y sent a copy of it to the Vali ITo. 119, dated 11th Felrutiy 1912. T ]f Besident at Bushire t -nd the ^Polinurus 11 for their information, together with a copy of my telegram above mentioned. Under the circuiiistances I think it would be better to leave matters as they stand. I have, etc*, 3d/« F* S. Crow, His Majesty’s Consul. His Excellency the Bight Hon’ble 2 ir Q*.^Lowther, 1.3. hi., 0*B., hC., wC., Constantinople.Trails let ion. Tali of B&amp;srah to His Majesty^ Consul, Basrah, ITo* 119. Januc iy 2 9 /February 11, 1912. I explained to you verbally a short time ago the state and position of the buoys in the Fao Channel. In r, letter novr received fro Comme^fdore at Basrah he states that there is no need of the buoy which is placed in front of our first buoy, starting from the lightship and lying In Let. 1*29 50 06 and in Long. E* 48 42 55 from our buoys, which have been placed in the channel for the safety of navigation and it endangers navigation and should be removed- remcv is re X have the honour to state that when t/iis buoy is* ed it is not to be replaced, as the Maxine Department ady and prepared to plfce 'buoys hereafter on our part at the points desired for ensuring the safety of navigation.In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote and address— The Under-Secretary of State, ^ Foreign Office, London. The Under-Secretary of State:'for Foreign Affairs presents hts compliments to the Under-Secretary of State for , and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop f of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, I’X , 19 ^ ■ A Reference to previous letter: A 23 MAR 1312 Description of Inclosute.- , Name and Date. Subject. sift) . S'X * (y * -t-' n' ? ■ .. er-J V.- ■ ^ / ■ ' /• H [12]52. 'msrci&amp;l. .474) BPITI3H EMBASSY CONST A14TINOPLE &gt; March 12th 1912. Sir:- I have the honour to forward herewith a despatch, as marked In the margin, from His Majesty's Consul at Basra respecting the position of the British buoys. I have exc., (Signed) Gerard Lowther. i-S Majesty's Principal Secretary of State for foreign Affairs, &amp;c., (SgC ., Gr.BRITISH CONSULATE . 10 . BASRA, February 12th 1912. Sir:- With reference to my telegram No. 18 of the 10th instant, I have the honour to transmit herewith en closed translation of a letter received from the Vali of Basra, objecting to one of our buoys and stating it should be removed and not replaced. I have not replied to this communication but have sent a copy of it to the ‘ esident at .mshire and the ''^alinurus' for their information, together with a copy of my telegram above mentioned. Under the circumstances I think it would he better to leave matters as they stand I have &amp;c., (Signed) i.s Excellency The Fight Honourable/ 3°^ slation. 1912 Vali of Basra to His Majesty’s Consul Basra No. 119 January 29th/?elDruary 11th 1912. I explained to you verbally a short time ago the state and position of the buoys in the Fao Channel. In a letter now received from the Commodore at Basra he states that there is no need of the buoy which is placed in front of our first buoy, starting from the lightship and lying in Latitude N. 29 50 06 and in Longitude E. 48 42 55 from our buoys, which have been placed in the channel for the safety of naviga tion and it endangers navigation and should be re moved. I have the honour to state that when this buoy is removed it is not to be replaced, as the arine De partment is ready and prepared to place buoys here after on our part at the points desired for ensuring the safety of navigation-i Telegram - P« \^V 4 From - The First Assistant to the Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, To —- The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department, Calcutta. No, 112* Dated and received the 11th February 1912. Consul, Basrah, telegraphs on February 11th. Begins. I have been asked by the Vali to point out that one of our buoys is out of position and might mislead. I informed ’ T Palinurus ff , but on asking the Yali to specify he replied that he wi33: AHHtbC consult Commodo^ but would not allow buoy to be replaced. It seems therefore useless for me to interfere. Repeated to Bushire for communication to n Palinurus' and sent to His Britannic Majesty 1 s Ambassador at Constantinople.Telegram. Prom - J* H* H* Bill, Ss^uire, First Assistant to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bnshire, To —— The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department, Calcutta. Fo. 122 Dated and received the 11th February 1912. Resident's letter, dated 19th May 1911, 1273 and Admiral's letter, dated 6th August 1911, 1462^X-0. Russian Consulate General flagstaff has been re-hoisted and Consul has obtained from Russia and lights at night 2 powerful lanterns Simplex automatic make burning an 'incandescent' light. Russian and Turkish Consulates now show 4 lights all night arc* lo^s and Shipping Companies are making enquiry. It appears therefore that early decision very desirable.Comraander-in-Chief’s Office, Bom’bay, 14th February 1912. Ho.58/1460 X B. With reference to the telegraralffrom the First Assistant to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, addressed to the Foreign Department, No. 122, dated 11th February 1912, relative to the navigational lights displayed at the Russian and Turkish Consulates at Bushire, be pleased to lay the following remarks before Eis Excellency the Viceroy and Governor General of India in Council. I 2. The question of the necessity for the provision of a light at Bushire was raised 3 years ago by the Committee upon the lighting and buoying of the 'Persian Gulf which reported in May 1909, and the matter would appear to be still under consideration, for as far as I am aware, orders have not yet been given to provide the light. In the meantime, according to the above quoted telegram, other Powers have stepped in and our position is no longer so strong as it was before. A similar thing has happened at Bushire as occurred in the Shatt~al~Arab, and if Great Britain should attempt to claim navigation in the Gulf, the reply will probably be that she necessarynecessary, that other Powers have hatf to act for themselves for the safety of their own ships, and that therefore Great Britain 1 claim is worthless. 3. I would therefore very strongly urge that action be taken immediately to show that we are in earnest about improving the lighting of the Gulf# I recommend that in any case the light buoy for Bushire be ordered and installed as soon as possible# The work on the other main lights should also be put in hand without delay, and the light buoys for Bahrain should be ordered so as to forestall any possible action by other Powers at that place# I have, etc•, Sd/~ Edmond W# Slade, Bear Admiral. The Secretary to the Government of India, Marine Department#*A, ' ■ S. 'CN i t i i iim [Confidential^ : ieos o s o o I ^ No. 160, dated Bushire, the 28th January (received 6th February) 1912. absence of the From—J. H. Bill, Esq., First Assistant Besident (in the Resident, To— The Hon’ble Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Henry McMahon, G.C.V.O., K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department. With reference to the correspondence ending with the telegram from the Government of India in the Foreign Department, No. S.-661 of 4ith Novemher 1911, regarding the erection of a permanent tide pole near the fort of Haji Sultan on the Persian hank of the Shatt-el-Arao, I have the honour to forward for the information of Government a No. 9-C„ dated the 16tli January 1912. n ^ 4 j. ^ copy of the commumpcation marginally noted received from His Majesty’s Consul at Mohammerah on the subject. No. 9-C., dated Mohammerah, the 16th January 1912 (Confidential). From— Major L. B. H. Haworth, His Britannic Majesty's Consul for Arabistan, To—The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. With reference to the correspondence ending with your No. 3010, dated the 25th Novemher 1911, I have the honour to state that the Commanding Officer, H.M.S. “ Odin,” after consultation with the Officer Commanding, R.I.M.S. “ Palinurus,” decided that the tide pole was unnecessary.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100048656966.0x000001_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/10/439/2</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100048656966.0x000001</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/10/439/2</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>File 50/1914 Pt 3 'Persian Gulf: lighting and buoying; miscellaneous papers'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1914/1920</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-03-30T16:18:50</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 item (167 folios)</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This item contains papers relating to the establishment and maintenance of lighting and buoying facilities in the Persian Gulf as part of British efforts to create a maritime navigation infrastructure in the Gulf.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100048656966.0x000001#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>