<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x00016d_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-18T04:08:09.569Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Collection No. Pro*. berial Noi. 9 mzJL9*-32222,* DISPOSAL OF CERTAIN ELECTRIC GENERATING EQUIPMENT ORIGINALLY ORDERED FOR INSTALLATION IN CONSULATES AT BANDAR ABBAS 2ND BUSHIRE. Previous References. Later References. MICROFILMED DOCUMENT DO NOT PHOTOCOPY USE IOR NEC S. 97 (Unbleached.) R. P.—5S62-A-P113—19-2-42—1,00,000. .\\\v^ - IaA* D. 0. No. 5-2/7 ^ . Dated Bahrain, the /3 June, 1947. I'tM. No S3fe6 &amp; CJ?—... I am desired to say that unless alternative purchasers can be found, it may be necessary in the near future for the Resident to cancell orders for certain electric generating Equipment of which details are enclosed• These sets were ordered some time ago for installation in the Consulates Jut Bunder Abbas and in Bushire. If the orders are cancelled, cancellation charges amounting to £ 500 will be incurred for one set alone* 2, To avoid this, I am desired to enquire whether P* C. L. or any one else in Bahrain would be interested in purchasing them from this Residency, alternative ly, perhaps the Shaikhs of Dubai or Ajman might be interested. Dubai wanted two much larger units to provide current for the whole of Dubai Town, but he is not likely to get them for 3 or 4 years. He might like to embark on a more modest scheme until the major one can be executed. He could probably get these machines installed with the help of B. 0. A # 0*8 engineer^ or of the Oil Company. The Shaikh of Ajman, I believe, wants one set to light his fort and residential quarters near by. 3 . According to the correspondence, manufacture was w^ll advanced in February and, had no question of cancellation arisen, delivery was contemplated in April, 1947. t'K'Vj' / C. J. Pelly, Esquire, I.C.S., Political Agent, Bahrain. • ^PARTICULARS OF SETS. Two 12 K. Watt 450/500 direct current 3 phase compound wouTd generators direct coupled with 25-30 B.H.P. Ruston Diesel vertical engine. R. P. M. about 600. Complete with static balancer for 3 wire service. The equ pment to be arranged for parallel operation and provided with 2 generator panels, 2 feeder panels and one water cooling tank to service both engines. The fuses for the feeder circuit will be 25 Amps. The generators are with water cooling system. Price. Roughly £ 2,500 for the sets. May be a little extra for tank pipe work. Length of cable between shunt field and feeder panel and switch boards. One K. W. Set compound wound 3 phase direct current, 450/500 Volts with heavy oil Ruston or Crosby vertical Engine direct coupled not exceeding 600 R.P.H. with or without overhead water cooling tank. The cost is roughly Rs. 15,000/-.Political Agent, Bahrain POLITICAL i-iGrlNCY, BAHRAIN. -17/29 The June, 1947. The Residency have on order from England certain electric generating equipment, of which details are enclosed. This equipment is now not required by them. 2 . Please find out and let me know if any one on the Trucial Coast is interested in purchasing this equipment from the Residency. Perhaps the Shaikhs of Dubai or Ajman might be interested. 3 # A ccor( iing. to the correspondence, manu facture was well advanced in February, and delivery was contemplated in April 1947.Political Agent, Bahrain POLITICAL AGKNCY, BAHRAIN. The June, 1947. A Petroleum Concessions Limitedj B a h r a _i_ _n » The Residency have on order from England certain electric generating equipment of which details are enclosed. As this equipment is not now required by the Residency, I should be grateful to know It your Company are interested in purchasing it. Accord ing to the correspondence, manufacture of this equip ment was well advanced in February,and delivery ,vas contemplated in April 1947. 2. Would you kindly let me have your reply as early as possible. No.l-0^17/29 To The Manager, v yPOLITICAL AGiiNCY, BAHRAIN. No. VO^-17/29 The June#: 1947 To The Adviser to t B a h r a _! ji MBMORANDUIil * The Residency have on order from England certain electric generating equipment of which details are enclosed. As this equipment is not now required by the Residency, I should be grateful to know if the Bahrain Government are interested in purchasing it. According to the correspondence, manufacture oi this equipment was well advanced in February, and delivery was con- temolated in April 1947e 2. Would you kindly let me have your reply 2. would y as early as possible? Political Agent, BahrainNo. /? of 1366 Office of the Adviser to the Government , Bahrain Dated, 6th Shaaban, 1366 June 24, 1947. viV. ‘ 5 ^ H. B. M f s Political Agent, Bahr ain. ^ ' k Memorandum: - Reference your memorandum No.2088-17/29 dated 22nd June 1947. I regret the Bahrain Government are not interested in the generating equipment. Ag. Adviser to the Government.CODES: BFNTLEY’S SECOND PHRASE PETROLEUM DEVELOPMENT (QATAR) LTD. Directors: N. A. Gass. V. oe Mbtz. W. Fraser. C.B.C.. C. S Guuberkian ( formerly armen.an ) G Uegm-Jones J. B. A. Kessler ( DUTCH ), R. oe Montaiou, D. A. Shepard, R. V/. Sellers, J. Skliros. BAHREIN PERSIAN GULF LP-18/6509 29th June 19+7 H.B.M's Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir, r SIDENCY D.C. GEMERATING EQUIPMENT We thank you for your memorandum No. 2089-17/29 dated the 22nd June 194-7 offering us the above equipment, but regret to inform you that we find we cannot make any use of it, which would Justify its purchase. Neverthless we are grateful to you for giving us the first opportunity of this offer. Yours faithfully, For &amp; on behalf of PETROLEUM DEVELOPMENT(QATAR)LIMITED MANAGER. PBND.O.IJo. 1 ' 4 - 8 '! -17/29 Th« 29th July, 1947. Will you pl«aaf fefer to Rosidfincy iciiil xdtter No#5- 2/792 dated the 13th June, 1947, regard- ing the electric generating equipment on order from iSngland* 2. I have approached the dahrain Government, Petroleum Concessions Ltd*, Saleh al Man! of Qatar and the Shaikhs of the Trucial Coast, and regret that no one wishes to purchase this equip- Major U.I. Pettigrew, Secretary to the Hon*ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain.(!!) No.725.0131 The Political Agent, Bahrain. Memorandum. British Agency, Sharjah. Dated 20th July,1947. Reference your memorandum No. 2090- 17/29 dated 22nd June 194-7. 2 * Neither the Shaikhs nor the people of the Trucial Coast are interested to buy the electric generating equipment. *</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x00016d_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1630</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x00016d</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1630</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 17/29 DISPOSAL OF CERTAIN ELECTRIC GENERATING EQUIPMENT ORIGINALLY ORDERED FOR INSTALLATION IN CONSULATES AT BANDAR ABBAS AND BUSHIRE'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1947/1947</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-01-06T18:18:05</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (13 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in chronological order from the front to the rear of the volume. Circled serial numbers (red for received correspondence; blue/black for issued correspondence) refer to entries in the notes at the rear of the volume.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 15; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 2-6; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file documents the Bahrain Political Agent's efforts to find a new owner for some electric generating equipment that was ordered from England by the Political Residency in the Persian Gulf. In order to avoid having to cancel the order (and pay a large cancellation fee) the Residency requests that the Political Agent make enquiries in Bahrain and elsewhere in the Gulf, in the hope of finding a buyer for the equipment, which was intended for the consulates at Bunder Abbas [Bandar-e ʻAbbās] and Bushire but is now no longer required. The file contains the Political Agent's correspondence with the following: the Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain; the Residency Agent, Sharjah; the Adviser to the Government of Bahrain; the Manager of Petroleum Development (Qatar) Ltd; the Secretary to the Ruler of Qatar, Salih Al-Mani' [Ṣāliḥ Āl Māni‘].</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Native Agent, Trucial Coast, Sharjah</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Adviser to the Government of Bahrain</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Emir of Qatar, Secretary to</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Bushire</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Electricity supply</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x00016d#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>