<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000517.0x0003bc_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-11T11:07:21.185Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">I .&gt; \ In any further communication, on this subject, please quote No. J 2464/128/16 and address— not to any person by name but to — “The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W.l. a* far*' ^ * cjfat; e-W- Foreign Office. S.W.l. INDEXED Sir, . LL u/tf- April, 194( 15921 * am direo't ed Sec v Bevin to refer ^o demi-officTal ^etary ^^W lletter No. 2179-S of the 18th December rrorn tne Political Resident, Persian Gulf, about the '‘Star of Mex', and to enquire whether any further information is nav available. * I am. Sir, Your obedient Servant The Under-Secretary of State, Commonwealth Relations Of!ice RECEIVED 16 APR 194G COMMONWEALTH Relations officeCONFIDENTIAL ; Political Agency, Muscat. D»0. No.C.592 - 19/3-G 30th November 1947 Dear Sir Rupert, 1865-S dated the 29th October 1947. Will you please refer to your D.O. Letter No. 2 . I visited Sur leaving Muscat on November 26th and spent an interesting day seeing the town and exchanging calls with the Wali and four principal Shaikhs, Nasir bin Mohammed, Hamad bin Khalfan, Salim bin Nasir and Abdullah bin Nasir. before I was due to leave Muscat I received a letter from Saiyid Ahmad bin Ibrahim, Minister of the Interior, asking if I would be good enough to give passage to two of his men whom he wished to send to Sur on urgent business. I saw no object in refusing but have the feeling that their business was primarily to find out mine. I was in any case closely shepher/ded throughout my visit and unable to find out anything fresh in connection with the '^tat of Mex u incident. 3. I think my visit caused some curiosity and shortly Yours sincerely Sd/- A. C. Stewart.■m • FiL r* &lt;ibO COMFIDEWTIAL Ho 1 * D.O. No.1864-S 19- SIAN GULF RESIDENCY BAHRAIN . A. G b t the 29th October, 1947 iP v ' 1+1 inoexeo J-gX. %uw ''V Please refer to Galloway’s demi-official letter No.l518-S dated the 19th August, 1947, about the 'Star of Mex'. 2 . I forward herewith a copy of subsequent correspondence with Stewart, I am afraid that as Stewart indicates there is little hope of obtaining any further reliable information about the case until the Sultan returns to Muscat. He was supposed to be returning in November but I have heard a rumour that he now proposes to remain in Dhofar until the P.C.L, survey party arrive there which will not be till January. / E.P. Donaldson, Esquire, O.M.G., Commonwealth Relations Office, LONDON. S.W.l *LB»/ CONFIDENTIAL THE RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN, ^ D.O, No.l51D“S the 194h August, 1947 Dear Stewart, With reference to correspondence ending with Hudson’s memorandum No«.C.405-19/3-G, dated the 14th July, 1947 I enclose copy of my demi-official letter No.l518-S of today to Donaldson, 2. I should be glad if you would visit Sur after the close of the monsoon and enquire into the matter there. 3. You will not fail to realise the importance to the Muscat Government of the value of establishing the truth of the Wali of Sur’s assertion. Nevertheless, in making your enquiries you will, of course, keep an open mind. Yours sincerely, Sd/- A.C. Galloway. . Major A.C. Stewart, O.B.E., Political Agent,D.O. No.C.546-19/3-G Political Agency, i Muscat, |19th October, 1947 Dear Sir Rupert, Will you please refer to Colonel Galloway's demi- official letter N0.1519-S dated the 19th August 1947- Zonly 2 , I did not fail to realise the importance to the Muscat Government of establishing the truth of the Wali of Sur's assertion mentioned in paragraph 2 of my letter No.C.128-19/3-G dated the 17th February 1947 and whilst I was on the spot with all the witnesses present, made the most thorough enquiries, I also pointed out the Muscat State representative the importance of establishing the truth of these assertions. In spite of my endeavours, however, I was not able to collect any precise evidence, nor indeed was I greatly sur prises since it seemed to me most unlikely that a dispute of this nature between the Wali and the Master of the vessel would have teken place in public and in the presence of witnesses. On the whole I was inclined to believe the Wall's assertion that he protested against the discharge of the cargo by other than his own people, if only for reasons of cupidity since it is clear that if he had control of the working of the cargo any profits accruing legally or illegally from this work would come to him alone and would not have to be shared with other parties. 3. In the months which have intervened since the 'Star of Mex' went aground, very little if any of the looted cargo appears to have been recovered, I attribute this, and indeed it is the general belief, to carruption amongst Muscat State officials who were sent from time to time to carry out enquiries into the event. It therefore seems to me that if I now proceed to Sur to make further enquiries I am not/unlikely to obtain more precise evidence than I was able to obtain on the spot at the time of occurence, but am also likely to come against considerable opposition from State officials who would probably assume that I was making my enquiries in an attempt to build up a case against the State, rather than, as in fact would be my purpose, in the interests of the State. In the circumstances would it be preferable to let the matter of further enquiries stand over until the Sultan's return and then urge him in his own interests, to make a more searching investigation ? Personally, I doubt if it will ever be possible to obtain reliable and irrefutable evidence as to the Wali's assertion. He was in any case suspended from his appointment shortly after the incident. Yours sincerely, Sd/- A.C. Stewart. The Hon'ble Sir Rupert Hay, KCIE. , fiSQ). , Political Resident, Persian Gulf, BAHRAIN 'LB*P.Q. Mo.l 8 gS -8 S PBRSIAa QUiF ^S lDiiNCY, BAHRAIN . the 29th October, 1947 Fleaee refer to your denl-offlciel letter No,C/546- 19/3 dated the 19th October, 1947, about the ••Star of kex'* hope of obtalninc further infortcctlon In this case until the Sultan returns to Muscat but I would suggest that you should take an early opportunity of visiting Sur in the ordinary course of your duties but not with the avowed object of making enquiries into the 'Star of Me** case and see what farther information if any you can pick up there. I aw inclined to agree that there Is little Yours sincerely S/- W.R. Hay • ♦ Major A.C. Stewart, 0,£.K Political Agent,II * | THE RESIDENCY, , BAHRAIN, ^EXT the 19th August 1947. yjJZ ilk No.Sxt•1231/4Y dated the 5th June 1947 to Hay about the 'Star of Mex'. 2* Hudson, who has been unable to visit Sur owing to the prevalence of the monsoon, reports that it has not been possible to confim definitely that the Wali of Sur t s assertion is true* I am asking Stewart to visit Sur After the close of the monsoon at the end of September and to enquire into the matter* 3* In the meantime the Alexandria Navigation Company have asked the Muscat Government through Gray Mackenzie and Company to confirm admission of the liability for damages and loss sustained to ship f s personnel, cargo and property through looting* A copy of Gray Mackenzie's letter is attached* 4. Hudson adds that he understands that no reply will be given to this letter mtil it is referred to the Sultan and that in any case it is most unlikely that the Muscat Government will admit any liability. E*P* Donaldson Esquire, C.M.G*, Commonwealth Relations Office, King Charles Street, Whitehall, LONDO NGRAY MACKENZIS ANB CO. UL. Ko.Ca£C/73 Muscat, 23rd June 1947. The Secretary to H.H. The Sultan of Muscat &amp; Oman, Musca t. Dear Sir, s.s. 'Star of Mex.' The Alexandria Kavigation Coy., S.A.E. Owners of the above vessel, vide their letter of 29th April 1947 , received here on 15th instant, write to us as under: 'Further to our to/day’s letter, and with reference to your yesterday’s cable, we enclose herewith copy of our telegram sent to the Minister of Foreigi Affairs, Muscat, together with copy of our letter of the 22nd February to the same Department, holding them responsible for all losses and damages sustained to ship’s personnel, cargo and property as a result of the attacks, at the same time reserying all our rights for adequate compensation in respect thereof. We shall» therefore, request you to maintain our claim asking the local Government Authroilies to con firm admission of their liability for damages and loss sustained through looting.' We therefore take this opportunity in asking Muscat Government to confirm admission of the liability for damages and loss sustained to ship’s personnel, cargo and property through looting. We await to hear from you at an early date. s Thanking you. Yours faithfully, Sd. For Gray Mackenzie &amp; Co.,Ltd., Agents for Ship Owners. Copied. RHL.'Y 1+ .14) FOREIGN OFFICE, S.W.l. 2nd i T une ? i 947 # (j. 2155 / 503 / 16 .) RESTRICTED INDEXED iO*£j €± 4 ^. With reference to your letter NOV Ext•906/47 of 29 th April, to telegram No. 526_of 29th April from the Political Resident, Persian Gulf, and to his express letter No. 757-S of the 29th April, about the looting of the 'Otar of Mex', it seems that since the Egyptian Government have not yet taken diplomatic action vis-&amp;-vis the Eultan of Muscat, no official Foreign Office legal advice need be tendered for the moment. 2. This, however, is roughly the line we should take. The only ground on which the Sultan ought to pay compensation would be if, given the character of his territory and the locality where the incident took place, he and his officials and police did less than they might reasonably be expected to do to protect tto .Up. 3. This can we thi/nk be judged better on the facts by the Politica^Ofgioor in the Persian Gulf than by departments in London. But the main issue - and we should be grateful if you could ascertain the fact of the matter on this point - is whether the Wali/ T.A.K. Harrison, Esq.., India Office.K Wali of ^ur 1 s assertion is true, namely that all_ the damage was done because the Master of the 'Star of Mex” over-rode the Wali’s advice not to invite the tribesmen on board. If this is true, it looks as though the Master is to blame. There seems still to be a little doubt however in the minds of the people in the Persian Gulf. When this is cleared away, our own views will be clearer. sCONFIDENTIAL F R From To No, ‘ Dated PERSIAN GUDF RESIDENCY ' ^ l^’^AHRATN. i gx^g-ASgpg ^ Political Resident, Persian Gulf His Majesty^ Secretary of State for India, LONDON. 757 - S. the 29th April, 1947. Your express letter No. Ext.71 8/47 , dated T X' L , ) \'vthe 14th April, 1947. n Star of Mex ,, .~ - “ ' ( 4 ^ 2. Sultan^ Secretary has informed Political Agent that all that was received from Egyptian Government was a request for report on incident and on steps taken to protect vessel. Following this a telegram was received from the owners stating that they held the Muscat Government respon sible for loss of ship and cargo. 3. There is little likelihood of any compensation being paid. 4. Political Agent reports that cargo which remained intact in vessel has been discharged and sold by ship f s Agent and that cargo off-loaded by Master before he abandoned ship has been recovered. 5. Muscat Government guards are still on vessel, but ov/ners appear to be taking no action to salvage vessel and State will probably remove guards before monsoon when vessel is likely to break up. 6 . A copy of paragraph 2 of this express letter is being forwarded to His Majesty's Ambassador, Cairo. Sd. W. R. HAY. Political Resident, Persian Gulf, ATTESTED for Secretary to M^he Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.INWARD TELEGRAM ^ INDEXES E1L£ n n pmi 9 • ■■i || A llotted to External DePartmerH; ^ CONFIDiilNTIAL CODE 7$95 jfrom To Dated Received 526* /iwtj 3 ] k . Political Resident in the Persian Gulr ' Secretary of State for India Bahrein* 13c45 hours? 29th April 1947 Reference your Express 'letter No* |pcT 7 ; ft/a r 7 April 14tho Star of Mex» 2« Please see paragraph Ro* 3 of my demi-official letter No® 605-S April 16th« Political Agent new reports Sgypt 1 an• ^overnment have only ashed for a report of incident and steps taken to protect ship and that owners have telegraphed stating they hold Muscat Government responsible for loss of ship and cargOo More detailed reply to your express letter follows by poste ' . • * - . /lc* fa ^ DRAFT LETTER. M H T&gt; Riches, Esq., Foreign Office, S.W.l. %- £ 9 APR 194? April, 19A7&lt; Dear Riches, Would you please refer to your official letter No. J.1098/502/16 of the 2nd April about the looting of the « 'Star of Mex'. 2. I enclose a copy of a letter we have now received t from the Political Resident from which it appears that the Sultan has received notice from the Egyptian Gove run ent that they hold him responsible for the loss both of the vessel and of her cargo. The Political Resident asks for pomraents on the U* legal aspect of the case. The facts of this case are reported in the Political Agent*s telegram No. C/71 of 17th February as ,is i V' amplified by his letter No. C.128-19/3-G- of the same date of which you have received copies. /The Sultan of Muscat is, of course, an independent A /\\r'Sovereign, but in practice he relies on us a great deal for- afivice and conduct of Mo foreign relations, and we feel that we- should be prepared to offer him advice on the legal aspect*^ of ttofcf case if he asks for it. /We- 2 - f fa**** ) Vfe should be grateful, therefore, to have the views of your Legal Adviser on 4&gt;ho oas«, so that we can send these to the Political Resident for the purpose of giving the Sultan the advice if he asks for it* f fi/GA/X J'£*• L 2 I am sending/ cop^p of this letter to/the Ministry of Transport and the .Board ofjpjaftg* f //*/&amp;- ^ Yours sincerely, ^ HARRlS^j^Please refer to correspondence ending with ^OO my printed letter No* C/99j dated the 31st March* 1947* 2. While at Salalah I advised the Sultan to get all available evidence regarding the loss of the ’'Star of Mex' and the looting of her cargo carefully recorded. 3 . Since we left Salalah Stewart has told me that the Sultan has already received notice from the Egyptian Government that they hold him responsiole for the loss both of the vessel and of her cargo. 4 . The Sultan as an independent sovereign will presumably have to fight his own battle with the Egyptian Government but I think we should be ready to offer him advice. I know practically nothing about maritime law. Would it be possible for your legal expert to let us have his comments on the case ? I think practically all the facts are given in the reports I have sent you but if any further information is required I will do my best to supply it. 5 . If the Egyptian Government and the Sultan fail to reach an agreement is there any tribunal to which the case could be referred ? 6 . On the 9 th April we sailed close inshore and had a look at the 'Star of Mex'. She is lying alongside the beach and the waves are breaking over her but she appears to be still intact and has not heeled over. She will presumably break up when the monsoon starts. 7 . I understand that Messrs. Gray* Mackenzie, acting for the owners have removed most if not all of tne cargo that remained on her. I am told that this action is irregular as once the ship was abandoned she and her cargo became the property of the Sultan and he ought to have arranged for the disposal of the cargo. 8 . I am sending a copy of this letter to His Majesty's Embassy, Cairo. India Office, LONDON.f x — — FSl y9.c /? gq © Persian Gulf presents his compliments to - 1) His Majesty's Secretary of State for India, . / India Office. London. ^ 4 mw Cl &lt;k f-o ' J I i , ~ | r ,^- India Office, Lgn^g, l/ Ma J est y* s Ambassador, Cairo . hi/l, 3) The Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document. OFFICE OF THE POLITICAL RESIDENT, PERSIAN GULF, aboard H.M.S. 'Wildgoose', At Sea, dated the 31st March 1947. Reference to previous correspondences DESCRIPTION OF ENCLOSURE Demi-official letter No.C.128-19/3-G dated 17th February 1947 (and its enclosure) from the Political Agent, Muscat, to the Hon'ble the Political Resident, Persian Gulf, Bahrain. SUBJECT: STRANDING OF S.S. 11 STAR OF MEX MCONFIDENTIAL NOt Cgg S rlg/a-G^ POLITICAL AGENCY, MUSCAT, Dated 17th February 1947. Dear Colonel Hay, 17 th the 17th February 1947. Please refer to my telegram No.C.71 -dated Following is a more detailed report concerning the ship u Star of Mex 1 '. 2. We arrived at Ras al Khabb at dawn on the morning of the 16th and sent a boat ashore with Saiyid Faisal bin Said and Pludson, who accompanied me as representatives of the State. When they arrived on the 'Star of Mex 11 , they found only the Wall and three or four of his guards on board, though it was apparent that the ship had been pretty well stripped of all fittings. They brought the Wali back on board H.M.I.S. 'Dhanush 11 , where we heard his story of events as follows: Shortly after H.M.S. Wren*s departure on the 6 th, a storm arose and fearing that the ship would break up, the master and the crew landed and camped on the shore. The next day the storm abated and though the ship had changed its position considerably, it was still intact, so the master again boarded the ship. In the meantime messages had been sent to Sur to fetch lighters to dis charge the cargo and also to Gray,Mackenzie &amp; Co., Ltd., Muscat, to send assistance. As a result of these messages, lighters arrived from Sur on the 11 th and after some bargaining regarding the payment for their services the master agreed that the lighters and crew would be entitled to 1/3 share of any cargo salvaged by them. On this basis, approximately 180 motor tyres and 70 bags of sugar were discharged and sent off for Sur. After the departure of . the first lighters, the Master entered into an engagement with the local Shaikh to send on board 60 or 60 tribesmen to work the balance of the cargo. The Wall swears that this engagement was entered into against his advice. Whether this be true or not, the tribesmen were allowed on board on the morning of the 14th at a time when the crew were on shore under the protection of the Wali*s guards. It is the Wali's story that after arriving on board, the tribesmen saw sugar and coffee beans which had been damaged by water. They asked the master if they could have this and their request was granted, having attained so much for nothing, their natural cupidity was aroused and they commenced ransacking the ship. The Master and the Wali were still on board, but were unable to control the situation. While the ransacking was going on, a launch carrying the Agent of Gray, Mackenzie together with a representative of the Customs at Muscat, arrived on the scene with instructions from the ship's owners requesting the Master not to abandon the ship and to report about the assistance he required. « The The Hon'ble Lieut.-Col. W.R. Hay, CSI., CIE., Political Resident, Persian Gulf, ' BAHRAIN.The master, however, found the situation to be out of control, and since his crew were already standing by in a launch sent ashore by the B.T.C. Tanker 'British Destiny', he decided that he could do nothing further and abandoned the ship himself. So far as I can gather, neither the master nor his crew suffered personal interference, nor were they prevented from taking their own personal effects with them. 3. I find it hard to believe the Wali*s state ment entirely, but at the same time I feel it is unlikely that the incident would have taken place had (a) the owners been more expeditious in arranging for aid to be despatched to the ship and (b) if the master and the crew had remained on board with the guards provided by the Wali, and taken steps to prevent any tribesmen from boarding the ship. It is possible, however, that after the first storm, the master felt the ship f s position to be too insecure to justify him in retaining the crew on board. 4 . I was not able to establish who was first back on board the ship after the storm, if. as I presume, the master boarded first,the point is in itself unimportant, but if it was a Muscat subject, it is possible, I am not well up in salvage laws, that the ship could be regarded as a derelict and as sucn the prize of the State. 5 . I was not in possession of the ship's manifest and I was therefore unable to estimate the extent of the looting. One and two 'tween-deck hatches had however been entirely emptied and all the ship's fittings of value had been removed. No.3 hold containing coal and the lower hatch of No.l hold, containing corrugated iron sheets, appeared to be intact. No.2 hold was flooded as was the engine room and the whole ship was in an indescribable mess. The Captain and the Chief Engineer of H.M.I.S. 'Dhanush', who inspected the ship, were of the opinion that the ship could only be salvaged with the aid of a properly fitted and heavy salvage tug. Even then, the task would be difficult and rendered more so by the fact that the engine room was flooded. It was also considered that the balance of cargo being heavy and difficult to shift without winches could only be salvaged at great expense, which would possibly not be justified. The Agent of Gray Mackenzie, who is also the Agent for the owners of the 'Star of Mex', and whom I took with me, is reporting to his principals at this aspect of the matter. 6 . The Sultan's representative has placed the wreck and the balance of its cargo in the direct charge of the Wali and his guards, and has told him to endeavour to recover as much of the looted cargo as possible. Since there appeared to be no further action I could take, I returned to Muscat on the 17th morning. 7 . I attach a copy of a telegram despatched by Gray Mackenzie's Agent this morning. Yours sincerely, (SGD.) A.C. STEW ARTCopy of telegram dated the 1947, from Messrs. Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Cc fJV v/ l7th February J, Ltd., Muscat, to Messrs. Gray Mackenzie &amp; Co., Ltd., Basrah, Star of Mex both boilers engine room flooded depth one foot above floor plates furnace full sea water. Our opinion Basset Trawler undesirable. Watch No.l tween-deck one steel boat lowerhold iron corrugated sheets hatch No.2 tween-deck one steel boat lowerhold under water hatch No.3 tween-deck coal lowerhold unknown general cargo. Hatch No.3 deck one motor truck (Geeb). All fittings ropes cabin doors and removable articles taken. Ship sinking facing sea both anchors heaved up. Salving cargo difficult hatches one and three being in unsheltered position. Salving only profitable provided arranged with local government fixing salving charges at certain percentage of cargo salved. We consider total loss.'A In any further communication on this subject, please quote N ° j. 1098/502/16. and address - I laoTRI 0 TiaD not to any person by name but ‘°' .kaO^ 6,0 'The Under-Secretary of Stale, ' 'V bir, ,ui Foreign Office. Q 'T '1 o» • _L • Foreign Office, London, S.W.l. EXT 2'710 1 l 9 v? j 2 nd Apri 1,19!]-?. ^ V fie V I an di rec t 3 7 ,1-S of 6 ! iV, Attlee to refer to desxjatch STj-lQk? from the Political ^Resident in the Persian Gulf, enclosing a copy of ^ Political Agent, Puscat’s telegram, No, C/71 cf ^ ' 17th Pehruary, about the looting of the 'Star of 'Ilex' . 2, I am to request that the Political Agent, Muscat, be asked to inquire unofficially if there is any likelihood of compensation being paid to the ovmers of the 'Gtar of Mex'* and whether the Egyptian Government have taken diplomatic action to secure such compensation. For your information, this request is made because the cargo of the Star of Lex was, it is understood, insured with British underwriters. 3 * I am sending a copy of this letter to the Board of Trade and suggest that a copy, of the MOl Political Agent’s telegram Ho. C/71 of 17th February be also sent to themT ' ~ I am, Sir, Your obedien ’vant, The Under Secretary of State. India Office.2**1 ^ ^ • jfo. 33 i.fO INDEXED Ud 7 *9 / \9^ j The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his complimeiits to - 1) His Majesty's Secretary of State for India, The India Office, LOhDOh , 2) The Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Department, NEW DELHI , 3) His Majesty's Ambassador, CAIRO , and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the ^ undermentioned documents. t k ' S N% / cShi ft tiU * / ^7 Q tiU PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY, v y 7 ^ BAHRAIN. Dated 18th February 1947. Reference to previous correspondence: { Residency telegram No.208 of 18t h Feb. 1947 . DESCRIPTION OF ENCLOSURE Political Agent, Muscat's telegram No.C/71 dated 17th February 1947. NPG.~ ~i mmm ii ||iy^ 33/134 Telegram From To Q Political Agent, Muscat. Political Resident, Bahrain No.C/71. Dated and received 17th February 1947. IMPORTANT I arrived Ras Kabba at dawn on 16th and found Wall of Sur with his guard on board 'Star of Mex'. There were no tribesmen on board and it seems they had made off the night before after stripping ship of all fittings and looting one and two hold tween deck hatches. 2. Wall’s story is as follows. tyres and 70 bags sugar (figures all approximate) were discharged and despatched to Sur, Master agreeing to pay one-third of cargo for services of lighters and crew. 3. On 13th Master entered into engagement with local Shaikh against his (Wall’s) advice to supply sixty tribesmen to transfer balance of cargo to lighters. Early on morning of 14th tribesmen were allowed on board and immediately asked for sweepings of damaged cargo (sugar coffee etc.) which they were allowed to have This incited them to loot. Crew were at the time ashore under protection of Wall’s guards only Wall and Captain being on board and Wall found himself unable to control situation. Gray Mackenzie’s agent arrived on board during morning and gave Master letter from owners asking him not to abandon ship. But Master declared situation to be out of control and as boat of tanker was standing by left with his crew. They apparently all took with them their own personal effects and their departure was not impeded. 4. So far as I could judge, whether or not Wall's story is true it would have been extremely difficult for tribesmen to board ship if Master h^d not agreed to let them on board to work cargo and I think to this extent Master is to blame for what followed. 6. Sultan's representative has instructed Wall to recover as much of looted cargo as possible, I doubt if he will succeed; he has also instructed him to stay on board with his guard until relief can be sent and see that no further looting takes place. 6. Tribesmen have already taken nearly ( ? omission ) cargo which can be readily moved and I think it unlikely that they will return and since there was nothing further I could do have returned to Muscat. 7. It seems unlikely that ship could be salvaged unless aid of heavy salvage tug is forthcoming soon. Even then task would be difficult. Task of salvaging balance of cargo which is coal and corrugated iron sheets would also be difficult and expensive. Gray Mackenzie's agent is submitting report to owners on salvage aspect. 8. I understand Master had two machine guns on board and took them with him ( ? omission ) he left. On 12th lighters arrived from Sur and 180 motor POLITICAL - NPGINWARD TELEGRAM ^5 N L * 19 :) Perm,. US. •Bepy.US» Ass t. US * s US. for Burma Asst.US'for Burma PS* to SS. PS. to US. PS. to Parly^ US Mr. Turnbulls Mr. Joyce. Resident Clerk. Ot' ■ ^ WARD C ODE Political Resident In the Persian Gulf Secretary of State for India ^ la&gt; Affaire ^ept. and H.M.Ambassador., Cairo Bahrain 16.41 hours, 18th February, 1947 19.40 hours, 18th February, 1947 . From To Rptd.to Dated Received 208 In continuation of my tele^rflrn pfn a k Star of Mex. Political Igenffl^eoorta'tLt ?th ' fltttrL 0 ^' 0 r hlch can be readily moved and ship's have r-turnei tn®^ 1 ? 0 ^' 1 by l00al ^ihestnen who' nave returned to their homes, Wall of Sur and hie, guard are now on board. Balance of cargo comists dr^bt? 1 ! iron sheets and it ?s hiv,^ 1 11 U oan be salvaged. Looting aopears to ' allovv^ft th6 f8Ult ° f the “ho ’ aJlowed tribesmen 0 n boa.3 fo unload cargo. Crew • /w ereV / were not in any way molested and left with their personal belongings intact* Copy of Political Agent’s report foilows by post*INWARD TELEGRAM rr ! Allotted to hJxceji ‘ CovjiQQ to : Penn* US* Depy.bS. Aast *US 5 b * US,for Burma Asst•US. for Burma . f-s. - C su. PS* to us» PS 4 iO Uar.lj ,Uv M&gt;:u Turnbull Mr w Joyce* Res i deat Clerk«. WORiJ C DDF a) i .,/5 From To * \i f ^ ‘ 4 Political Resident in the Persian :luli' ary of Sijat e f t hj 4 - 2 ^ z &gt; Bahrain, 17*00 hours, 17th February 1947/^ Reptd*to Government of India and H.M. Ambassador, Cairo hated *G Received 19,-20 hours, 17th February 194? v t. &gt; No♦201a * % 194^^1 * B.3*C, announced on 16th February that Star of Mex had been looted off Bahrain. 2* Facts are as follows. Star of Mex a cargo vessel owned by Alexandria Steam Navigation Co*, Alexandria, with an Egyptian ore// proceeding to Basrah ran aground just sou - h of (?Ras al Had) in Muscat territory on or about 1st February* Reports having been received that Master required (?agsistant to) (?rem©vei Arab guard who had boarded /■©sseJ Wren proceeded to.spot to render assistance, Midi tary Ad v.i aer to Sul.tan also went to r.p&lt; t in launch* H.M,B, 7 ea /a-s unable zo get' /shiship off and left 7th February after giving Master v such assistance as was possible#, Sultan's representatives were then on hoard and promised to prevent pilfering and arrange local supplies. . Crew abandoned ship on 14th February apparently | fZTl from fear of local Arabs and went aboard British Destiny a tanker outward bound from Gulf* On 15th February a report was received from Muscat that armed Arabs were looting ship and Sultan's representatives were unable to control situation# political Agent at Muscat has proceeded to spot in H.M.I.S. Dhanush and further report is awaited from him*Np,9 22^5 The Hon * ble the t ical HRe-^ident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to - 1) His Majesty* s Secretary of State for India, ^ The India Office, London , 2) The Secretary to the Government of India, External Affairs Department, New Delhi , 3) The Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document, with the request that the Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, will please convey the expression of the appreciation of His Highness the Sultan together with that of the Hon*ble the Political Resident, to the salvage party. rfju PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN. Jr?- • Dated the 26th October 1946. Reference to previous correspondence: Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf*s memorandum No.PG.166 dated 26th March 1946 (to Political Resident only). DESCRIPTION OF ENCLOSURE Political Agent, Muscat*s telegram No.C/432 dated the 21st October 1946. SUBJECT: REMOVAL OF WRECK OF t *DAHPU tl FROM LUSCiJ KAKBOUKTelegram G.T.C. From Political Agent, Muscat, To Political Resident, Bahrain. No.C/432. Dated and received 21st October 1946. 3) My express letter No.C.368-16/19 May 6th. 2. Vi/reck of ,, Dahpu ,, has been sunk in deep water off Muscat harbour and^is now clear. Most of salvage party have left. 3. Sultan would be grateful if his appreciation and thanks for this work could be conveyed to His Majesty*s Government and to Naval Authorities directly concerned. 4. The bearing of salvage party throughout operation was most praiseworthy in view of intense heat of Muscat*s summer and lack of shore facilities. If you consider appropriate grateful if appreciation of this can be conveyed to Naval Authorities concerned.EXT.2^lA4 ( 5 P Extract from Ivluscat Intelligence Sumnary No.6 for the period from l6th to 31st Narch, 1944* SECURITY 6l. Reference paragraph 45 this series. Survivors have now reached Salalah. Their story is that there were altogether two dhows from Nuscat and one from the Eadhramaut. The submarine surfaced sometime after dark and first machine gunned and then rammed the dhows. They were carrying cloth. The two dhows, Sugarpasa and IJalti are still missing, but the authorities in India have been unable to trace the enemy broadcast alleging that they had been captured. —Exr.ii&amp;sAii- a n L ^ 2 , ^ Extract from l^luscat Intelligence Summary Nc*ij. for the period fran l6th to 29th February, 1944* SECURITY 45. It is reported from Aden that one Muscat dhow has been sunk by a submarine and another believed sunk by the same means in the Arabian Sea. Survivors have landed at Socotra. It is also strongly rumoured that about two months ago Radio Saigon broadcast the capture of two other dhows, Sugarpasa and Malti. These dhows were on their way to Muscat from Zanzibar and have been missing for scene months. It has been suggested to the Naval Officer in Charge, Bombay that the offices which monitor these broadcasts are approached for confirmation.k/-. Mr, ^ fa J s ^ J. ^ . ? &amp;rj^b 'T. -/te'^*^ ' C ^ ‘ StA^ &gt;,/, Please see the passage marked 'A* of the Treasury* s letter of the 22nd June. The Treasury seem to be quite right on this point. The reason for my inserting the words to which they draw attention .was that in the casc-A-C the 'special payments referred to in Secti^ . 5 of the note at PZ.2967/40 (flagged ♦X* on collection 29/86 attached), this phrase was used in accordance with the recoosiiendation in paragraph 24 of C. I.D. paper ME(0) 294 of February 8 1939 y flagged in , collection 30/160. However, I do not think we need confuse the Treasury by drawing attention to this now.32 DRAFT LETTER R»L«M. Barnes Esq., Treasury, Whitehall, S.W.1 Ext. 2782/tiu X/ 0 Dear James, 19 Jill 1944 Thank you for your letter No, S. 45336 of the 22nd June about compensation for Muscat! Coolies killed or injured in the s. s, You will now have seen a copy of our telegram No, 14544 of 30th June to the Government of Tndifl on the subject. With regard to the penultimate paragraph of your letter we agree &lt;ytk naaon»ideration with your understanding that the allocation of special wartime expenditure in the Persian Gulf should be settled after the war as a separate issue and should not be related to the allocation of wartime expenditure generally between the U,K. and India, ^You will remember he whole question of the division between^ nd the U.K, of normal peace-time e^Jenditure in Persia and the A Also due to come up for m after the war^J Persian Gulf conside I am sending a copy of this letter to Wikeley at tty* Foreign Office. F.A. K. HARRfSONKV'-a &amp; I do not think we need take exception to ''he terms of the Foreign Office letter in this matter. No doubt the settlesiient finally reached regarding the incidence of this reserved expenditure will be between the Treasury and the India Office and there should be no difficulty in providing, at the time for anything due to the Government of India to appear on the xncLia Office Vote if this is felt to be the more convenient course. There seems to be no particular reason why this case should be ret erred to the Advisers. XFour Be/erence?^——?^^/^ Treasury Reference S-A5336. Dear Harrison, G O r i ^ x TREASURY CHAMBERS, GREAT GEORGE STREET, LONDON- S.W.l. 4Z 22nd June, 1944. n ‘ ^ i s b cs , I refer to your letter of 2nd June about compensa tion for certain Muscati coolies who were killed or -f jured in the S.S. Dahpu, a Norwegian ship on time charter to the Ministry of War-Transport, when it was torpedoed by an enemy submarine in Muscat Harbour on the 28th June 1943. As you are doubtless aware, we are very averse from giving compensation for fait? de guerre, either in British territory or to allies like Egypt or Persia and I am afraid that wecannot accept the implication that H.M.G. *8 assurances of protection to the Sultan carry with them a complete and automatic insurance against loss caused by enemy attack or in the course of defence against such attack. We recognise, however, that Muscat is in a rather special position and in view of the political considera tions which you urge, we are prepared to agree to the proposed payment in this case, provided that it is made clear to the Sultan that we are not thereby committed to pay automatically if other incidents occur. A We agree that the expenditure may be classed as special wartime expenditure in the Persian Gulf, the allocation of which between Imperial and Indian revenues is to be determined after the war. I note that you suggest that such allocation is to be in accordance with the general principles which may govern the allocation of war expenditure between the United Kingdom and India, but as we understand the position, P.A.K. Harrison, Esq., India Office. I RECd. POL. KPT. /any i 2 I. JUN IP ■ • i INDIA OFFICEr (_ M ft H r \ *1 ACTION ■ &lt; pnent would be ad hoc and not defence expenditure generallyr’- ’ I l ^6 V ^Ui any Persian Gulf settlement would be ad hoc and not necessarily related to defence expenditure gen era 11^^ I am sending a copy of this letter to Eyres of the Foreign Office. Yours s in c ere ly, 4 — &gt;- v..- . sw ■ ISecretary, Financial Pyfrartment . ^ Please see the minutes flagged xt X below. We have since telegraphed to the Government of India and the Political Resident asking for more information on the lines suggested in Mr* Grists note of the 11th May and I now attach a revised draft to the Treasury based on their replies. Do you concur in tie draft please?Ext. 23 94/44- DRAFT LETTER. R.L.M. James, Esq., Treasury. Dear James, I enclose a copy of a telegram from the Government of India (a copy has already been sent to the Treasury officially) regarding compensation for * &gt; \/ ** jf/At certain Museati coolies who were killed or wounded: , Esq.^# ign^ff ice. 4 in the S. S. Dahpu, a Norwegian ship on time charter ,/ ¥ *4 '.vV to the liinistry of War Transport, when it was torpedoed by an enemy submarine in Muscat Harbour on the 28th June 1943* We have since ascertained that these coolies were not part of the ship* s crew but were employed partly by the landing contractors, Messrs. Oman Trading Company, .and partly by Messrs. Gray Mackenzie, the shipping agents, and that the ship was in fact neither loading nor unloading at the time of the accident. Since the coolies were not part of the ship* s crew it is not possible to look for their compensation under the rules relating to merchant seamen. The Government of India’s proposal is therefore for an ex gratia payment on the groundof the assurance of protection against external aggression given by to the Sultan of Muscat at the beginning was then informed in connection with the agreement that was drawn up between himself and whereby he undertook, in return for certain payments, to afford them certain facilities in the present war, that G-. reaffirmed their readiness to protect his from the war” (see papers forwarded under our P.Z. 7^4/4^ of the 12th February 192tO). The incident in which these Muscati coolies were killed clearly resulted from such external aggression, and we agree with the Government of India that the Sultan of Muscat is entitled to compensation in respect of expenditure in the Persian Gulf, the allocation of which between Imperial and Indian revenues is to be determined after the war in accordance with the general principles of the war. The Sultan (who is an indep endent / neutral) \ territories from any external aggression resulting /whichwhich may govern the allocation of war expenditure ? between the United Kingdom and India. The Political Resident is pressing for an early decision, and I should therefore be grateful if you would let me have your reply as soon as possible. I am sending a copy of this letter to Eyres/ Ex:t.239yV^ DRAFT LETTER. 2.M* Eyres, Esq, Foreign Office. Dear Eyres r a JUN 1944 I enclose a copy of a letter we have sent to the Treasury about condensation for certain Muscati coolies killed or injured when the S.S. Dahpu was torpedoed in Muscat Harbour on the 28th June 1943. If you agree with our line that the Sultan is entitled to condensation on the grounds of ’s assurance to protect his territories fran any external aggression resulting from the war we should be -fflOB-t- grateful for any support you are willing to give us vis-a-vis the Treasury. Yours sincerely, p. A. K. HARRISON tAllotted to External Department* /V^ fJof- SECRET 18391 r~'. CYPHER TELEQRAM (O.T.P.) Prom To Repeated Dated Received Government of India, External Affairs Department* Secretary of State for India, to Political Resident in the Persian Guilf* New Delhi, 23*55 hours, 26th May, 1944. 06.00 hours, 27th May, 1944. 7155. Paragraph No.1 of your telegram 11294 dated May 16th. Dhapu. Both presumptions confirmed* tm. mk- 5 ■ &gt;MAYiS 4 A IN pi A QFf &lt;S6) v»v Allotted to Fx’Ora l 1 o Repeated tp Dated Received file copy ± IKv/ARD TELBORAM OT°* ^ * • &gt; Q ' V 0 !- £.w o ^ Externa l Depart ment SECaET 18222 CYPHER TELBGRAiii -M#a 4 4 \ , ■^rv-’w —■ v^uiuuRaujaara Political Resident in the Persian Oulf* Secretary of State for India* Government of India* Bushire, 18«00 hourn, 25th May 1944, 03,30 hours* 25th May 1944* Ha, 1249* Addressed to Secretary of State for India repeated to Government of India* . Paragraph No,2 of your telegram No,11294 \J]0 May 17th. Dahpu* ~' 2* Ship Naidu neither loading nor unloading stores for H.M.S, at time of incident. Landing boat coolies employed by landing contractor Messrs* Oman Trading Company other coolies by Gray Mackenzie.Overseas Dept© E.&amp; 0.3113/44. Economic &amp; 25th April, 1944. Dear Reay, ^ Would you please refer to your letter ox che 11th October 1943, G/GM/5850/4267 about the Norwegian vessel H Dah Pu e ' We have now received a telegram from the Goverzment of India stating that the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf requests sanction of compensation at the rate of Rs.600 each to 25 Muscat coolies who were killed and at the rate of Rs.100 eacl to two who were wounded when this vessel was The Govemnent of India propose to sanction these awards provided H.M.G. agree to the amounts being debited to special war expenditure in the Persian Gulf. I should be glad of your views as soon as possible. sunk. Yours sincerely, (Sgd) L.E. LeBurn H.M. Reay Esq., Ministry of Pensions, Blackpool.MINISTRY OP PENSIONS, Norcross, Blackpool, Lancs# Ref.No.G/Gen/5850/4267 4th May, 1944# Your Rcf.E.A 0.3113/44# Dear LeBurn, the 25th ^&gt;ril you wrote to Reay re gaming a number of Muscat coolies who were killed or injured when the ”Dah Pu' was lost by enemy action in Muscat Harbour on the 28th June last# The H Dah Pu' was a Norwegian vessel but as at the time of her loss she was on time charter to H # M, Government members of the crew who are British subjects or British protected persons come within the provisions of the Mercantile Marine scheme, Norwegians and other nationals being outside of the scope of the scheme# As Oman is not a British Protectorate or British mandated territory we cannot authorize compensation under the scheme in respect of Muscat coolies; moreover it seems to me that in all probability these coolies were not members of the crew but were engaged in loading or unloading the vessel# The 'Dah Pu' was only 1,974 gross tons and she would hardly carry such a large complement of native seamen* Unless you have any information to indicate that the arrangements relating to war expenditure in/ L.E. LeBurn Esq., India Office, 4, Central Buildings, Matthew Parker Street, S.W.1#the Persian Gulf would cover casualties of this nature I suggest that you take iqp the matter with the Norwegian Shipping and Trade Mission, 1A4, Leadenhall Street, E.C.3. as they may be able to make g rant s from their funds# I have passed copf _ ' of the correspondence to Broadley of the Ministry of War Transport and you may care to have a word with him. Yours sincerely, (Signed)f 4 / (St) Mr. H ary ^son / ^ ^ Financial Secretary ^V* LfStviMf «V** jiU t) f^UUi ^Vr MjJS is ;4 On 28th June the s.s. Dahpu, a Nor-fregian ship owned by Messrs. Wallen &amp; Co. of Bergen, requisitioned by the Royal Norwegian Government on the outbreak of war* and held by the Master on its behalf, was torpedoed and sunk in Muscat harbour* 25 Muscat coolies who were working on board as stevedores were killed and 2 wounded* The Political Resident has now requested sanction for compensation at the rate of Rs.600 each to be paid for the 25 Muscat coolies killed and Rs.100 each for those wounded. The Government of India have agreed to sanction this payment if the amount may be classed as special war time expenditure in the Persian Gulf* The allocation of this expenditure between Imperial and Indian Revenues is to be determined in accordance with the general principles which may govern the allocation of war expenditure between the U.K. and India* So far the chief items under this head have been the appointment of additional staff in the Gulf and special payments to the Shaikhs. It is proposed to write to,the j oraOffice requesting theift. to obtain ffroaouiy approval of this payment and their agreement to its allocation as special war expenditure in the Persian Gulf* 0 s / , A ' rK-M o* iSUs -j ^ fL/ *£ '’Ljf -V U^tnM^L ^ VkHf, ? u\, 't, ■ j r«-— i c. r. ^ b-tt c*r%~**4^-***-c f ^. -I*?/” ' '4 IK-r/ZtO Stee: *7/ u 4 * &amp; 'Oi \ ^ Uk J M- c To K. and 0. Deioartment • CYPHER TELEGRAM (O.T.P.) From Government of India* External Department* To Secretary of State for India. Rptd.to Resident in the Persian Gulf. Dated New Delhi* 15-45 hours, 2lst . Received 465 3&lt;» 23*45 hours, 21st April, 1944 Addressed Secretary of State for India repeated to Resident Persian Gulf. Foreign telegram No«6079 dated J uly 25th 1943. * ^ c *^~ ^ ^ Political Resident requests sanction of ^ compensation at the rate of Rs.600 each 'liq 21?. iviUgcal. t//&gt;7‘-/o.^oolies killed and at the rate of Rs.100 each to 2 —- wouncTed in~sinking of Dahpu. Government of India propose to sanction payment if His Majesty 1 s Government^Wt. 47681/P.5893 4/42 3.000 pads H.E.J. Ltd. 51/4655 MESSAGE . • f i v' ' * From S.N.O.^ Persian Gulf. Naval Gupher (X) by W/T. I RECEIVED: — Date Time 21.9.43. 2024. Addressed Admiralty. Repeated G. in G. Eastern Fleet. IMl'ORTANT. Muscat Levies salvaged 12 pounder gun ex S.S. DAPHU sunk in Muscat Harbour 28th June Political Resident Persian Gulf recomAends presenting this gun to state who would greatly appreciate it. I consider this politically desirable as offset to sinking of ship in their harbour. 2. Request early approval as gesture would lose effect by delay. Politieal Agent Muscat reports gun in bad condition. 200651Z India Office(Mr. Harrison). e ^&gt;&lt;* 7 «//. t 2 3* Uo \\JL CO^ .o HVVARD TEL EJR AM. SECRET 88785. (If in any case the communication of the contents of this document;.to any person outside Government Se^ice is authorised, it must be paraphrased). AIK?x ted to External Department . (Jbpi.es circulated, CYPHER TELBjRAM. * ! From To Government of India, External Affairs Dept. Political Resident Bushire. Repeated to Secretary of State for India and Political Agent Muscat;. New Delhi, 04.35 hours, 26th July, 1943. 11.50 hours, 26th July, 1943. Dated Reed. ' §079. Addressed Political Resident Bushire repeated to Secretary of State and Political Agent Muscat, Muscat ^telegram 0/810 of July 5th not repeated India Office. Oahnu sinking. (Secretary of State telegram 2115 of 5qHfcU&lt;£3ept ember 29th 1939 refers). Assurance to Sultan of I Muscat of protection against external aggression. Commander in Chief E.P. desires that His Highness (? should be) informed tTuffT (? Japanese) have repeatedly attempted to attack British and Allied shipping in North Arabian Sea, but owing to success of our patrol measures it is only very rarely that attacks have developed. He may also be told that air and surface forces in Gulf of Omar.' have recently been augmented in order to provide additional protection to territories in this area.&amp;Xt« 533S/4v 118^ Oapraln 'Earner of tho • &gt;% * • arT*iv»4i Jmrm on {rovffmmnt offlciala fmds&amp;rchanta* Bfrxeft on the June • / 11 • • • nnhpu anchored in tt tm.?* »o ir nt 3 a. . on the &gt;m1ni’ of the ^ th Jum • 0 a«rn« a tre enloua ox losion occurred in ?^o*3 hold of tho chip an'l her stern half 3j&gt;nfc rapt 11 f tq the U.«r o r ho • The Political ^gent and the Agency Surgeon at once left for the Oohpu in the Ape no/ whaler. Throe survivors f one with his leg blown off, were pi ked up on the way* The ahlp'a Mater # ^hpnpin&amp;dar Buhre, wae found in hln .cabin sorting nut pap re. c opinion at once that a to -©do aa4 .cimsed the ex loelon and it neaped possible, if that were thp. caso, that it would be followed by ahelliog and a hear ding party* The ship's sesret papers were acoorlinrly - t. r ovorb^rd in a closed bag with a 8ini&lt;cr attached. The p lltloal gent then left the ‘)ah 3 U and sen signals referring thh laiidant to all son orne . Srquirtee during the day, and those still going on, have not revealed with any certainty that a submarine was sighted near Muscat nor is there any real abidance that the track of a torpedo was seen before the ©7 loslon* rhe theory 1 scussed hem ii that tl was soma explosive (such as a tine borfb;* plaoed in the ship at a previous portj but so for nothing has been discovered to s ^atantlats thi°* It i &gt; tl,u theory which is favoured by Ssiyid Shaimb bin Faisal, the Muscat Minister for external Affairs, '/ho vrtTl not consider/cons Her the jossth; lifcy that the vnr c aid coi e In lose proxl Ity to v sc t. &gt; ring the lay of the 8* th June the eurvivore and as wuch ae poasihle of the move a’ la vsluahlee of the ehi^ v/ere salvagtH. The total casualties were j frHeBlni? b e 1 lev ad cunti e:.! ^eadT * Ship’s crew (All Indian) Muscat Coolies working as 14 * stevedores 26 The Co npounder of the . Agency Hostital. 1 v^orpeee ere still being found washed up on shore* h. Whaler Atmosphere arrived on the evening of the WOth June and her Commander f T«t« ^Oemmander Fslwasaf r # . ’t. # conducted an examination of the wredt with the it teal Agent and the 'Xnhpu ’ a Comnandcr on the ming of the 30th June. By that time the whole length of the Ship had settled .on *ho harbour bed, and only her forecastle, bridge deck, foremast, and funnel are now shoeing over w iter* The force of the explosion waa such that iebrte waa hurled into the Agency Tennis )&gt;urt behin i the Agency and* a piece of it broke the verandah of the Treasury Officer’s house on the sea front* The ship war anchored at only ?l-3/4 cables length from the Agency* i. T. ^ohpu was a N m r egian ship owned by leonrs* oil: n ^:o* t &gt;f B^ r n and retnileltloned Vy t e Royal N &gt;nreglan hove rnment on t He outb3^eak of War and held by the Master on its behalf. separate reports have been suV Itted. , um*/FILE COPY M, FOR ilGis OFFICK, A L • *v • 1 • arth august, 194 ^ In the second paragraph of his loiter to ^ou of the 4th August, W^^cox suggested that we night he ahle to give you some infornation about our policy on the ipuestion ol Reparations. Our policy on Reparations - or Restitution, as it is apparently now called — is being worked out, but Ministers have not yet agreed^ on the paper to be submitted to Sir* William Jowitt’s Committee. In any case, this draft paper will probably only deal with Germany at present. I am sending a copy of this letter to Wilcox. Yours sincerely, H-vh, R.X .Peel, India Off i^^WUG 1942■r Your EeMmce-MMrn&amp;1.35&amp;2/ ^ '1'vte.^my Reference s. 50148 . X ^6 i:&gt; &lt;y TEEASUBY CHAMBERS, GREAT GEORGE STREET, LONDON, S.W.l. V &gt; 4th August, 1942, i Dear Peel, \\&lt;&amp; I have now taken over Syers*s work at the Treasury and am accordingly replying to your letter of the 28th July about compensation in respect of the loss by enemy action dhows belonging to Koweit and Qatar. V/e agree that (a) and (b) of paragraph 4 of the Political Resident’s letter seems correct. As regards (c), we agree that it would be undesirable to hold out hopes of reparation which may not be capable of fulfilment. I myself do not know whether any definite policy on the question of reparations has been worked out (but Eyres, to whom I am sending a copy of this letter, may have more precise information) but in any case I should doubt whether it would be possible at this stage to say how that policy would apply to damage in Koweit and Qatar. Prom the penultimate paragraph of your letter I take it your view is that any compensation on charitable or political grounds would be a matter for the Government of India, and not a charge on the Imperial Exchequer. You have incidentally, in your letter to me of the same date (Ext. 2£8l/42), raised the question whether Bahrein and Koweit may be regarded as covered by the statement of our post-war intentions in respect of war damage in the Colonies as set out in my letter to Creasy of the ?th July. Our first reactions are that it would probably be difficult to include places like Bahrein and Koweit in the Colonial Empire for this purpose, but we are looking into the question and I hope to send you a definite reply in due course. Yours sincerely, c.h.h. Uju£ R.T. Peel, Esq., C.B.E., M.C., India Office.\ (C't' Piruinc Secretary External Secretar i f 1 I ^- 0 no ^ think tliat this Department is much ccrcerned, _he proposed ansv/ers to (a) and (b) are, as far as I can jud^e, right. I have some doubt aibout (c) for I have no recollection that K.LI.G. have made specific reparation a psrt oi their policy, .n regards paragraph 6. the question seems to be one entirely of political expediency. Perhaps ;; ie foreign Office end Treasury should be consulted rather than ohe i.,.’*7.T., who hardly seem to have any interest in the matter. /A 6% j (c J .To X&amp; GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. Department. ivdia direct I/EXT E XPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). ? y v.' / 0 fN.B .—This is an ORIGIN AL message sent by AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the. signature of a responsible officer of the Department.] No. 381-S BUSHIRE, Dated the -NrvrBdln-' 16th May, 19 To H#M* Secretary of state for India, London*' Repeated The Secretary to the Government of Inaia, External Affairs Department, New Delhi* The Representative of India on the Middle East War Council, Cairo* The Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf Division The political Agent, Kuwait* The political Agent, Bahrain* The Political Agent, Muscat* COMPENSATION EOK LOSS BY ENEMY ACTION * Two dhows ene belonging to Kuwait and one to Qatar were recently sunk in the Indian Ocean by Japanese action* I have no official information of this but the crews were recently repatriated by a mail steamer and have naturally spread the story far and wide causing considerable consternation in Gulf circles* The dhows were so far as is known engaged in private ventures* The Political Agent Kuwait has enquired what attitude he should adopt if the question of compensation by His Majesty*s Government for the loss of the Kuwait dhow is raised* 3* Kuwait is regarded as a belligerent in the present war vide Beckett*s minute referred to in the enclosure to India Office letter No*p*Z•3144/38 dated the Igth May 1938 and by analogy it would ^ appear that Qatar must also be regarded as a belligerent* This however would appear to make little difference to the practical aspects of the case * u 4* The correct answer tothe point raised by the political Agent Kuwait is perhaps (a) that no.compensation is payable by His (Signature) Majesty’s S. 44 . MFP— 1048 S&amp; P— ( M-2042 )— 17-12-37—20,000. (Designation)- 2 Majesty*s Government as the dhows were not plying on their behalf (b) if any immediate relief is necessary the responsibility for providing it rests on the Kuwait Government and (c) that His Majesty*s Government will do what they can to exact reparation on behalf of the Kuwait Government from the Japanese Government after the war# 5* Kindly telegraph whether the answer suggested in the above paragraph is the correct one or if not what answer should be given# 6# whatever the answer may be I consider that the possibility of some relief being afforded from Government funds either on charitable grounds or for propaganda purposes in cases of this nature should not be totally excluded# Sd, W*R# Hay# Political Resident in the Persian Gulf ATTESTED if for Secretary to the political Resident in the Persian Gulf# #</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000517.0x0003bc_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/847</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000517.0x0003bc</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/847</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Ext 4226/43 ‘Compensation to Arabic Shaikhdoms for Losses by Enemy Action (Sinking of S.S. Dhafu); Sinking of dhows belonging to KOWEIT, QATAR, MUSCAT (Grounding of "Star of Mex")’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1943/1948</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-03-30T10:24:53</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (68 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 70; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains policy papers discussing whether the British Government should pay out compensation for dhows lost by the Persian Gulf States as a result of enemy action. The file also discusses whether compensation should be paid to coolies killed as a result of the sinking of the Norwegian vessel SS
                           Dahpuin Muscat harbour by a Japanese submarine on 28 June 1943; the British Government had given the Sultan of Muscat assurances that his state would be protected from external aggression.A single post-war incident has been included in the file: the looting of the Alexandria Steam Navigation Company ship
                           Star of Mexin February 1947. The ship was stranded near Ra‘s al Khabba: see folios 21-22 for a detailed report on the incident by Andrew Charles Stuart, Political Agent and Consul at Muscat. The majority of the papers are concerned with establishing whether the Muscat Government is liable for paying out compensation.The file does not contain any papers for the years 1945-1946.The main correspondents are the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf (Lieutenant Colonel William Rupert Hay) and officials of the India Office – Commonwealth Relations Office from August 1947. The file also contains input from the Foreign Office, the Government of India, and the Treasury.The file includes a divider which gives a list of correspondence references contained in the file by year. This is placed at the back of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>SS Daphu</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Star of Mex</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Wali of Sur</namePart></name></subject><subject><geographic>Ra's al Khabba</geographic></subject><subject><topic>War compensation</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Sultan of Muscat and Oman, Āl Bū Sa'īd Dynasty</namePart></name></subject><subject><geographic>Muscat</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Looting</topic></subject><subject><topic>Second World War (1939-1945)</topic></subject><subject><topic>Shipping</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000517.0x0003bc#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>