<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100030967198.0x000001_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T21:51:23.004Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100030967198.0x000001_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>Or 6489</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100030967198.0x000001</url><physicalLocation>British Library: Oriental Manuscripts</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>Or 6489</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Kitāb al-mi’ah fī al-ṣinā‘ah al-ṭibbīyah كتاب المائة في الصناعة الطبية  Masīḥī, ʻĪsá ibn Yaḥyá مسيحي، عيسى بن يحيى</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1694/1694</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-05-31T10:50:48</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>Codex; ff. i+378+i</extent><extent>Material: Eastern laid paperDimensions: 240 x 130 mm leaf [165 x 70 mm written]Foliation: Eastern Arabic foliation in black ink; British Museum foliation in pencilRuling:
                           Misṭarah; 23 lines per page; vertical spacing 14 lines per 10 cmScript:
                           NaskhInk: Black ink, with rubricated headings and overlinings in redBinding: British Museum red half-leather bindingCondition: Minor water damage; some folios mutilated and repaired (see especially ff. 1-4 and 369-78)Marginalia: Notes and corrections by more than one hand</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Medical encyclopedia by Abū Sahl ‘Īsá ibn Yaḥyá al-Masīḥī al-Jurjānī (أبو سهل عيسى بن يحيى المسيحي الجرجاني, d. 401/1010), one of the teachers of Avicenna (Abū ‘Alī ibn Sīnā, أبو علي بن سينا, ca 980-1037).The work is divided into 100 books (كتاب), a list of which is found on ff. 4r-6v.The text finishes at f. 376v and appended to it is a short text called the 'Explanation of what the author Abū Sahl al-Masīḥī said about simple medicines' (تعريف ما ذكره المصنف أبو سهل المسيحي من الأدوية المفردة; ff. 376v, line 5-378r).A marginal note reading 'تم بلغ بحمد الله تعالى' is found at the end of many books and elsewhere (beginning on f. 6v [without تم]). The final such note is found at the end of the main text (f. 376v), where it forms part of a longer inscription which reads as follows: 'Finished and completed with praise to God the Most High, with much weeping over a copy that is full of errors, in the month of Shawwāl 1105/May-June 1694' (تم بلغ بحمد الله تعالى بقدر الدمع مع المنتسخ المغلوط في شهر شوال 1105). Although the function of these notes is not specified, they are probably collation notes, which would explain the complaint about a 'copy full of errors'. The hand of the notes, however, does not appear to be that of the main scribe. However these notes are to be interpreted, the date in the final note, Shawwāl 1105/May-June 1694, may be taken as a terminus ad quem for the production of this copy.Main Text Begins (f. 1v, lines 2-6):الحمد لله رب العالمين والصلوة والسلام على سيدنا محمدوآله أجمعين قال أبو سهل عيسى بن يحيى المسيحي هذا هو الكتابالأول من كتبنا في صناعة الطب وقصدنا فيه أن نتكلم فيما يجبتقديمه قبل الشروع في علم الطب مما يكون مدخلًا إليه والله تعالىهو المعينMain Text Ends (f. 376v, lines 1-4):... والفواكه الرطبة وتدسيس الماء في أشياء لا يعرف أوصبه في حلقهقهرًا وذلك إذا أخذ يفزع من الماء ويحقن عند ذلك باللبن وما لشعيرودهن البنفسج هذا آخر كتاب المائة والحمد لله أولًا وآخرًا وظاهرًاوباطنًاAppended Text Begins (f. 376v, lines 5-7):تعريف ما ذكره المصنف أبو سهل المسيحي من الأدوية المفردةاقحوان نورة اسارون عيدان دقاق إلى غبرة وسواد اقاقياعصارة القرظ افسنتين حشيشة يشبه هشيمها زغب الفراخAppended Text Ends (f. 378r, lines 7-10):... خولنجان قطاعخشبية ذراريح حيوان يشبه الذباب ذنب الخيل نبتذو خصل كطاقات الشعر من جانبيه يكون قدر شبر وأزيدغاريقون أصل نبت همش أبيض تمت الرسالة</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="personal"><namePart>‘Īsá ibn Yaḥyá Masīḥī</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Medicine--Early works to 1800</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100030967198.0x000001#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>