<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000019_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-07-03T16:34:18.169Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Draft Paper. /-H P.Z.840/36. ?J 't Department, The Under Secretary of State, Foreign Office, S. W. 1. 8 FE1 Sir, V 6 'Tol 'KtJ /tRe&gt; r- tt-s j‘p c Ef!CL r LETT 1 R | No. 7 13 31936 FCC X AMD - - Fl £Lj A- : ^ rvJAxh Iff TO, I. (^UJ/a^Uaci t ^ iM ****»£! ^ rJu* (kaA,/) 7 /, Gio~tofc %t&lt;r c/i n : nu Sf Ti u It i t* MVKttJ-* $ I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to refer to Foreign Office letter of 19th November, No.E.6522/5/34, regarding the licensing of foreign vessels employed in Persian waters. The Marquess of Zetland, after consultation v/ith the Government of India,^ agrees with the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs in approving the advice given by Mr. Knatchbull-Hugesson to the Acting Political Resident in paragraph 3 of his despatch of the 16th October, No.445j and it will be observed from the letter noted in the margin that the local representative of the Mesopotamian Iranian Corporation, Ltd. , has already applied to the Persian authorities for registration of the 'Garmsir'. In regard to liability far commandeering£j4r j t-would appoar^jUiat-a vessel bearing Briti^h^fegistration is list necessarily^ adversely affected by ^“‘•^^/the mei^efact of taking out a licence, ^ H/f&lt;/ ttu CmToiM jft** * tfu f: O, rd] His Lordship thorcfore agrcco wit h T 7^ ^'//iC i OjECla ouYtt uktUia tub — tho-CogrpTfiry / o^-Stcttc for- Foreign Aff^J^s '(7' 4, &gt;89 5000 12.35 V 7 that it is unnecessary at this stage to A undertake a more detailed investigation of this question.Confidential. GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. 3 5 '/ Department. V • '/v ' EXPRES S LETTER (AIR MAIL). [N.B. Thi&amp; is an ORIGINAL message sent by AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been tele raphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department,] No. 18-3 of 1936. Bushire, 6 th January, 56, Fr om To Political Resident, Bushire. voverriment of India, hew Ue &gt; Repeated Secretary of State for India, London. H u * / Sub t 1 ect : Licensing of foreign veesile employed in Persian Waters. Reference correspondence ending with Foreign and Political Department Express Letter So.P.437-B/35 of 7th December 1935. 2. Acting on the suggestion referred to in paragraph 3 of despatch Ko.445, dated the 16th October 1935, from Minister, Tehran, to Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, the local representative of the Meaopotp.mia-Iran Corporation Ltd. has applied to the Naval Authorities for registration of the 'Garmsir*. Further, as observed in paragraph 5 of the same despatch, the fact of taking out a license would not appear to affect the status of a vessel bearing British registration nor to render it any more liable to commandeeri than at present. In the circumstances there would appea’ (Signature) s. 44. VTFP—1013S&amp;P—(M-1323)—30-10-33—lO.CHX). (Designation)- 2 - to be no adTanta^e in not complying with the regulation for liceneing. ad. T.C.Fowle, Lieut.-Colonel. Political Heaident in the peroian Oulf • Att es t cd. fbr Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Sr■■■■■■ ■■■■■■EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). [N.B .—This is an ORIGINAL message sent by AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more Your Express letter No.P*Z.8373/35, dated 25th November 1935 and Bushire Express Letter No. 18-S of 1936, dated the 6th January 1936. Licensing of foreign vessels employed in Persian waters. 2. We agree with Political Resident and have no further observations to make. expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been teleraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department.] No.F.437-N/35 JXIt3L_ ,, New Delhi’ I ^'' January 7936. Dated To Secretary of State for India, London Repeated Britconsul Bushire. The issue of the above has been authorised (Vv Deputy Secretary to the Government of India {Signature) S. 44. {Designation)GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. Porei^r and Political Department. V..’ p z. Q n Q V EXPRESS LETTER {AIR MAIL). i r ! ■ [N.B. Thie is an ORIGINAL message sent by AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended, to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been teleraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department.} No. 5 , .437-.1 J/o5, COimD^tfTI AL. Bated , the New belhi 7 n December fg 35, Brit consul Bu shire* Repeated Secretary or State for India, J M, Secretary of State f s Repress letter Ko.P.Z*8373/35, dated the 25th llovember 19 35. licensing of foreign, vessels employed in Persian Waters. 2. Government oi India will be glad to receive your views at an early date. The issue of the above hag been authorised. [mm. pol. sept. 18 DEC ,935 ND1A OFFICE 0-ix &lt; &gt;c ’ (Signature) Deputy Secretary to the Government of India. (Designation) / s. u. MFP—826S&amp;P—(M.1070)—14-9-34—10,000.0** . INDEXED Iii^any farther communication on this sidiject, please quote no i£ f ts'/zt* and address —not to any person by narne, but to— “The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. 1 . f WDIAZDIREnT© jTzTT^ 8456 THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs pues^nts his ^ compliments to JC&amp;t. ^ ^ and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop 4- of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, -p'* - • ' i. ?3?&gt; ■ Reference to previous correspondence : ^'2. )~o £ 6S'zx/s / 34- el n%s/-i&lt;i' A ' Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. — J**1aa+-a_No. 4 77 - - I P.Z. Ji) British Legation, p 7 -7 E 6734 • ir ’ s Hovember 1st, 19 35 18 NOV 1935 His Majesty's Representative presents his compliments to His Majesty's Principal Secretary of State of Foreign Affairs and has the honour to transmit herewith, copies of the documents mentioned in the subjoined Schedule, on the subject of flying of flags by foreign vessels in Iranian ports. Reference:- Foreign Office despatch no. 513 (E5913/5/34) of 8 th October, 1935. Despatch Wo. 107 of November 1st, 1935 to the Honourable the political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bus hi re.From Secretary of State To Government of India, F.&amp; P. Dept, Repeated Political Resident, Bushire. Tehran despatch of 16th October, repeated to you No.218 and to Resident No.100, and F.O. letter of 19th November, copy by to■day 1 a air mai1^ Licensing of foreign vessels employed in Persian waters. Have you any observations to offer? (Si.) J. C, WALTQELINDEXEP In any further communication on this subject please quote ^No. E 6522/5/34. d address— not to any person by name but to— “ The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W.l. [ i&gt; xT ! 8373 1935 J L jNDi^X)lRECT(g) / ri'Wv&amp;LaL utiT' A ' - JkL'ts Foreign Office. S.W.l. 19th November, 1935. /*/ \J \ Sir, QJl V; With reference to Foreign Office letter E 6016/5/34 of October 16th, enclosing a copy of a despatch from His Majesty’s Minister at Tehran regarding the flying of their national flags by foreign vessels employed in Persian waters, I am directed by Secretary Sir Samuel Hoare to transmit to you herewith, for the information of the Marquess of Zetland, the accompanying copy of a further despatch from Mr. Knatchbull-Hugessen regarding the licensing of such vessels. 2. Subject to the observations of Lord Zetland, Sir Samuel Hoare proposes to reply that the advice given by Mr. Knatchbull-Hugessen to the Acting Political Resident, as recorded in paragraph 3 of the despatch, is approved. 3. With regard to the question of commandeering, Sir Samuel Hoare believes that it is unusual for vessels to be requisitioned in foreign ports in time of peace, but he is advised that this practice applies primarily to sea going vessels, and that at first sight there is no reason why vessels, such as tugs and launches, regularly working within the confines of a foreign port, should not be subject to requisition to the same extent as foreign-owned motor cars, lorries, or beasts of burden. This aspect of the question The Under Secretary of State, India Office.question cannot, however, affect the point which has now arisen, namely whether the 'Garmsir” should comply with the regulations as regards taking out a license or obtaining a number; and, subject to the views of Lord Zetland, Sir Samuel Hoare is disposed to doubt whether it is necessary at this stage to undertake a more detailed investigation of the problem raised in paragraph 5 of the despatch. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant,jilo* Briti m Legation, tii October, 1^3^. Tehran. Sir, With reference to ay despatch Lo. 402 of September 30th, and to previous correspondence in regard to the regulations concerning the flying of flags on ships in Iranian waters, I have the honour to inform you that the deputy Manager of the Mesopotamia Iran corporation at Buahire received during the course of last month a politely worded letter from Colonel Bayeador, stating that the a.a. 'Garmsir* was not observing ti.e regulations and adding that she could not be used after jotoiber 8th unless she did so. 2. The *Gs^raalr T, has not, in fact, flown the lied Lnslgn since August 1st last, and while it was Just possible that Colonel Bayendor was referring to her house flag which she still flies, the probability seemed to me that the difficulty was due to the fact that her owners had not yet obtained a licence for her to operate froa the naval authorities or customs (see Article 5 of the first enclosure to ay dsqpatsli ha. 332 of July 26th last;. n the matter being reported to ae by the Acting Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, 1 enquired of Hi* isjesty's Vice-Consul at Mohamnerah whether craft belonging to the Anglo-Iranlan oil Company and the Mesopotamia Iran Corporation had yet been lleenaed and, if so, what form these licences toolc. captain chaunoy replied that, ualeaa /the ight Honourable Sir Samuel Boare, Bart., Q.C.S.X., etc., stc., etc.. The Foreign office.tiie Issue of Iranian registration numbers could be seici to imply licensing, none of these craft had been licensed. He further stated that, in pursuance of Circular Letter of November 12th, 1954, from the Mohaiaaerah iort Officer (of which a copy was enclosed in ay despatch No* 74 of February 12th last), the iotglo-Iranian Oil Company in respect of its craft which operated on the Karun only, the Mesopotamia Iran corporation and others had submitted lists and applied for permits* Since then the Anglo-lranian il Company had haard no more. The remainder had sent their craft for inspection and numbers had been allotted to the and painted on* No document of any sort had been issued to their owners and there had been no further interference with them* 3 # Admittedly the circular in question safera only to craft plying on the iarun, but tha later regulations provided for the licensing of all foreign-owned craft operating in Iranian waters, and it tharefora seemed llicely that the authorities at Buahlre would follow the same precedent* I accordingly telegraphed to Colonel och advising him to suggest to the Mesopotamia Iran Corporation representative, who was himself anxious to fulfil the necessary formalities, that he should at once apply to the Customs for a licence in accordance with the regulations* He could then write to colonel Bayendor stating that he had done this add adding that he presumed that all was now in order* I further informed Colonel Loch that the position might have to be modified eventually in the light of your 1 m truetions on the general question of the regulations* 4 . i have now received from captain chauncy a despatch, transmitting the text of a further circular which has been issued by Colonel iayendor in clarification and /amplification- a - a»plif!cation of that forwaraed under cover of my despatch Ho* 332 of July 26th last. A copy la enclosed herein. You will see that captain hauncy is of opinion that all that the Iranian authorities desire la that foreign owned craft operating in Iranian waters should obtain a licence to WQric t carry an Iranian number and abstain from flying a foreign National Flag. Under the latest regulatlons 9 exemp tion is acoordsd to foreign owned vessels which operate between Iranian and foreign ports on conaition (d) that they do not spend more than four months in a year in Iranian waters f and (b) do not transport cargo in the internal waters of Iran. The meaning of this second condition is somewhat obscure but 1 do not think it can be held to apply to coastal trade. The authorities probably only have in mind the loeal transport of passengers and goods on such rivers as the Xsrun* 6. There remains one further point whloh deserves consideration. Colonel Cooh has expressed his fears lest the Iranian Government may gradually demand that the * , Ga^*ei^ l, be transferred from British to Iranian registration and suggests that she might even become liable to be eommandeered on occasion by the military authorities. So far as I can judge* the painting of an Iranian number on her bows should not in any way affeot her status as a British-registered vassal* nor can I see in logic that the issue to her of a local licence to operate should give the military authorities any more right to commandeer her than they may have at present. At the same time I meet confess that I share Colonel Loch f a apprehensions that the military may now in fast feel better able to oeunmandeer her in ease /of- 4 - of noma than th«y did whan she wore the Red iineign Md carried ao Iranian nuaher. The general position aa regards the right of the military to commandeer British-own eu nine of transport is soaewhat obscure# hut in 1930, when there were numerous complaints from British lorry owners, we confined our representations to the manner in which requisitioning was carried out and no attempt was ;iude to dispute *the right of any Government to requisition transport in times of crisis* (see Sir R* U Clive’s despatch No, 278 of June 24th, 1929). The Iranian authorities, if faced with a direct question, would probably argue ti at, they had aa much right to requisition transport on sea as on land, and if they do not hesitate to commandeer foreign- owned lorries, they are unlikely to refrain from commandeer ing, if necessary# for sign-owned ships. «fhat the riguts ot foreign shipping would be in such s case I aa not in a position to say# but I venture to suggest that the question is one which deserves examination with particular reference to tiie present regulations. I am sending copies of this despatch to the Foreign &amp;eo etary to the Government of India (No. to the Acting political Kcslds nt in the Persian Gulf (Rsu 1^0)t to Hie da^esty’a Consul at Ahwas (No. 41), and to the Senior Haval Officer in the Persian Gulf (No. 111. .). I have the honour to be with the highest respect. Sir# Your moat obedient, humble servant# (Signed) H.M. Knatchbull-Hugessen.io* 649♦ British Vlos^CcmsulstSt Mohammerah. (jctoher the 4th, 1955* Sir, I have the honour to foz*wara s copy of s translation of Iranian circular Motiee ho. 6330, oateh the 16th September 1936, supplied to me by ^esopotauis Iran Corporation, Plaited, for your information. Article XI (b) of this notice coverft the Registration of craft, and from observation at this poat I am sure that Registration and carrying of numbers allotted and non-flying of Foreign national Flags is all that the Iranian authorities are pressing for (see my telegram 1400 of and instant where I report that no effort has been made to expedite or Insist on the issue of hleenoes or surrey Certificates although required by regulations). It appears quite clear to me therefore that, if oarmelr does not bear an Iranian registration number (and I presume from Buehire telegram 90/824 para. 6 that it does not), this is what sarangyar Bayendor is referring to when he states that Oarmsir has not complied with the regulations. I am sending a copy of this despatch to Bashirs (Ho. 860) and a further copy together with copies of the relative telegrams to Ahwas (Ho. 861). I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, (signed) F.O.L. Ghauney. ilia Majesty's Vice-consul. his Majesty*s Minister, Tehran.( GOVY ) No. 6330. Uated 83-6-14. (16-J-36). NOTICE, In continuation of Circular No* 2849 dated 25-£-14 16-6-56) f as some mi suader standing has occurred due to a is trans lation of the text of the Circular in question it is hereby explained and notified as under: I* Article 1 and 2 of circular No. 2249 are epecially for craft owned by Iranian subjects* II. Ae per Article 3 vessel belonging to foreigners or foreign companies arriving at Iranian coaftts or internal waters with the intention to work in the said waters must (a) obtain permission from the Naval author!ties 9 or in their absence, from the Customs representative, to work in the relative port. (b) observe the regulations in connection with craft belonging to Iranian subjects in each and every respect and are not allowed to hoist their National flags* III* Those vessels belonging to foreign subjects navigating between Iranian coasts and porta abroad are exempt on the following stipulations Firstly: The whole period of stay in Iranian waters during the year should not exceed four months. secondly: Not to transport any cargo in the internal waters of Iran. IV. Vessels belonging to foreign fttj&amp;axattm diplomats ars exempt from these regulations. (Signed) Lt.-Col. Bayendor. Offg. O.C. southern Naval Forces.INDEXED In any farther co In any farther communication ^^this subject please quote no.E 6016/B/34. and address— Foreign Office. but to— “ The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W.l. /-s With reference to Foreign Office letter E 5913/5/34 of the 10th October, concerning the Persian regulations governing the flying of national flags by foreign vessels in Persian waters, I am directed by Secretary Sir Samuel Hoare to transmit to you herewith, for the information of the Secretary of State for India, a copy of a despatch from His Majesty^ Minister at Tehran on the same subject. 2. I am to explain that this despatch has crossed Sir Samuel Hoare’s despatch to His Majesty’s Minister at Tehran, a copy of which was sent to you under cover of the Foreign Office letter under reference. 3. Similar letters have been addressed to the Admiralty and Board of Trade. I am. Sir, Your obedient Servant, The Under Secretary of State, India Office.(E 60I6/5/o4) COPY No. 402 British Legation, Tehran 20th September, 19«55 Sir In the fifth paragraph of my despatch No. o32 of July 26th last, I stated that I was giving Monsieur Motaaedy full particulars of the s.s. H Oa^meir , ' in the hope that the authorities would agree to exempt her from the scope of the recent regulations regarding the flying of flags on ships in Iranian waters. I now have the honour to enclose a copy of Monsieur Motamedy’s reply which shows not merely that the Iranian (k&gt;vernment regard the rt Garmsir M as a craft plying for hire in Iranian waters end therefore falling within the scope of the regulations, but that the intention seems to be only to exempt those vessels which operate between Iranian and foreign ports. 2 . I am sending copies of this despatch to the Foreign Secretary to the Government of India (No. 198), to the Acting Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, at Bushire (No. 92), to His Majesty’s Consul at Ahwez (No. 08 ) and to the Senior Naval Officer in the Persian Gulf (No. 104.M). I have Ac., (Signed) H.M. Knatchbull-Huge b sen The Right Honourable Sir Samuel Hoare, Bart., G.C.S.I., etc., etc., etc., The Foreign Office?ptember. 196b, Translation: From Monsieur A« Motamedy of the Iranian Ministry for Foreign Affairs# addressed to His Majesty’s Minister# No* 2289 dated 12th September# 19d5 (2U Shahrivsr, 1^14). My dear Minister# I did not fail to communicate to the competent quarters the contents of Your Kxcellenoy’s note of a&amp;irdad 8 th last (July 31st) regarding the state of the motor boat 'Garmsir”* 2. The reply received is to the effect that the 'Garmeir* forms part of the hired boats which are engaged in taking posts and passengers in Bushire. It (the 'Garmsir') can only be regarded as one of the boats working outside Iranian waters on condition that# instead of working between the shores and the ships# it should ply between Iranian ports ant foreign ports and it does not perform any service in Iranian ports or territorial waters* 3. It is true that the said boat is travelling occasionally to Basrah# but such visits are often made for the accomplishment of necessary repairs# and in Iranian ports it is engaged ordinarily in carrying out private services. Compliments. Yours &amp;c.# (Signed) A. Motaaedy.INDEXED *In any further communication on this subject, please quote ^ H®. &lt;5 rt f 3 /-T/iv anu address —not to any person by name, but to— • “The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. 1 . THE Under-Secretary of State for complimer ts to v , and, by direction of the Secretary of State transmits herewith cop of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, lo -fUs C^c^o , 193 Fi ireiun! QlMiFs presents his t ¥ • % /« u-t' Reference to previous correspondence : ?' a . sCzM^ £ 4 &amp; &amp; L4- / »'/ ^ Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject.w No. 513 rwwiiii wnm$ s.i. x 8th October, 1936 (B 6913/5/34). I93_5 J Sir flth refereace to your telegram No.10 Saving of Sad August and to previous correspondence regarding the flying of flags by foreign vessels in Persian ports, I have considei'ed the possibility of making representations to the Persian Government on the grounds that the Regulations of July 7th are contrary to inter national practice. £• It appears that the flying of their national flags by harbour-craft based on foreign ports is not entirely without precedent. I am informed, for example, that, although no foreign tugs are known to be based on United Kingdom ports at present and although with the single exception of the 'Garmsir* none of the tugs and launches at present employed by the leading British shipping companies in foreign ports fly the British flag, a Butch tug was in I9kj6 employed for some time on the Tfeames under the Dutch flag, and that up till 1934 the depot ship maintained by Imperial Airways Limited in the harbour of Jiirabella in Crete flew the British flag. In neither of these cases was any protest made against the flying of the foreign flag, although in the case of the Dutch tug His Majesty’s Government were finally obliged, in deference to the representations of the Thames watermen, to get rid of it by refusing to issue the permits which its crew were held to require under the Aliens Act. 3./ .atchbull-Hugessen, &amp;aq., C.i .G#, etc. , etc., etc.. Tehran.There appear* therefore to be some ground for maintaining that the Persian regulationa are unusual. On the other hand they do not appear to be contrary to any express provision of international law, and X am advised that a British vessel such as the w Oarasir M would not contravene the Merchant shipping Act or any British law by complying with them. This being so. His isjesty’s Government are hardly in a position to maintain that the Persian Government have no right to make regulations for the flying of flags by foreign vessels based on their ports. 4, in view of these considerations His Majesty’s Government consider that nothing would be gained oy ^eKi *g a protest against the unusual nature of these regulations, or by attempting to insist upon the right of the 'uarai^ir to fly the Red Knsign should the representations which you reported in paragraph 5 of your despatch H0^538 of July kidth not meet with a favourable response. 5 # i share your opinion that it would in any case be undesirable to raise the question of the proper width of territorial waters in connexion with these regulations. X am, etc. (For the secretary of state) (Sd.) CM. RktfDBL.thought it worth vftle to ra e e protect, it ?ould enable us to claim that the Persian action it? contrary to normal international practice* Certainly we would not object to the flying of the national flag by foreign ship* based on our ports, though objection miiht be raised on other rounds m was done in the c?i©e of the Dutch Tug employed on the Themot in 1926* never theless the point la not important , and in view of the line wuich the Admiralty hove tavern we are willing to concur in your letting it rest* I tw\ sending co ies of tills leti^er to Claus on st the Indie Office and ^eal at the Admiralty* fou'S sincerely, fSgd ) N. A. GUTTERY,M.U35*7/3&amp; Military Jrancii, xmahm, s.&amp;.i. -4 luth .iepteraoer 1936. hy dear daggallay p I writs iu reply to your letter IiO.E.5u&amp;3/b/34 of the 38tri August on the subject of the Persian flag regulation, to say ti,at we concur in your view that having regard to Guttery 1 » letter it is iapoBsible to make an effective protest. This being so, we feel that it would be unwise to couple it up witu the f 3armsir incident. As tae Garmsir' flew her flag for some time after the incident honour has been satisfied - unless we go out of our way to couple tae new regulation* witn tae incident. Clauson at the India office and Guttery at the ooard of irade. I am sending copies of this letter to Yours sincerely.r r Please see Mr. Baggallay’s letter of the 28th August to rae* and the further paper (P.Z.6028/35) in regard to the 'Garmsir' incident on the separate file 'below. I have spoken to Mr. Seal of the Admiralty on the telephone. His personal view appears to coincide with the view that I have expressed in the attached draft letter to Mr. Baggallay 'below, 'but of course he still has to submit to his higher authorities. On the whole it seems 'best to keep the question of the regulations, in regard to which we really have no leg to stand on, apart from the incident question.-i Draft Paper. iV POLITICAL ^2, ^33/ Department. H.L. Baggallay, Esq., Foreign Office, S. W. 1. AJ'V 'CLOSURE IN WEEKLY fcETTER 37 12 SEP 1935 • i SECRETARY, POLITiCAL AND — DEPT. INDIA OFPIOE 9 SEP 1935 My dear Baggallay, Would you kindly refer to your letter of the 28th August, No.5023/5/34* Subject to anything which the Admiralty may have to say, we are inclined to the view that it is desirable not to link up the 'Garmsir' incident case with the Bahrein regulations in regard to the flying of flags by local craft. In regard to the latter, we seem to have very little ground for any protest against the new Persian regulations, and there might be a good deal to be said for accepting them gracefully. A- The still unsatisfactory attitude of the Persian Government in regard to the '’Garmsir' incident is a matter which, as you say, we shall have to consider further. ' —&gt; / Qm* Mm) im*! Cn iJj/Hi Jf fci* COPY SENT (Sgd.) M. J. OLAUSOh? 3761 5000 5.35OE/**-' (E 5023/5/54) 26. ft % t ^ Ul Lu -j 2 -J c in O Lu &gt;- ; id 0 V o V o UJ &lt; CD l ^ CM ' \— a. I- !.U UJ m K&gt; 3 * ^ J £ ^ My dear Clauson, On August 13th I sent a letter (E 4627/5/34) to Guttery of the Board of Trade asking him to make certain enquiries regarding the extent to which harbour craft employed by foreign shipping companies normally fly the national flags of the companies in question, and at the same time sent copies to you and to Seal (though I regret to have to admit thao I did not indicate this fact in the letter itself). I now enclose a copy of Guttery 1 s reply, from which it appears that the ,, Garmsir M and the A*P«Q*C. launches at Abadan are the only harbour craft known to fly foreign flags. With regard to the A.P.O.C. launches however, Tehran telegram No. 9 (Saving) of August 1st ^ (which was circulated to the departments concerned on August 14th - E 4888/5/34) and our earlier information from Persia suggests that these launches fly the Red Ensign in Iraqi waters, but not in Persian waters. For practical purposes therefore the question at issue is confined M.J. Clauson, Esq.p confined to the 'Garmsir'. 2. In these circumstances the draft telegram to Tehran 'circulated in our letter E 4884/5/34 of August 4th has become somewhat inappropriate, at any rate as far as paragraph 2 of the draft is concerned. The answer to that paragraph seems in fact to be that while the issue of regulations on this subject may or may not be unusual, the practice which the. regulations forbid is distinctly unusual; and that it would therefore be almost impossible to make an effective protest on grounds of precedent. 1 3. In the meanwhile you will see from our letter E 4929/83/34 of today’s date that the 'Garmsir' incident is making little progress towards a satisfactory solution. V/e may or may not be able to make further representations about this case - I do not want to enter into that point here - but the practical question which we have to ask ourselves is, I think, this: would failure to obtain adequate reparation for the 'Garmsir' incident be a reason for making representations about regulations in which, apart from their indirect and probably accidental connexion with Lieutenant Darayazda’s conduct on a certain occasion, we feel no great interest and seem to have no real groundr 0^0) for making representations? 4. I should he glad to learn how you view the question before I submit the papers here. The matter is not urgent, as the 'Garmsir' has ceased to fly her flag pending a final settlement, but we do not of course want to leave Tehran too long without a reply to their telegrams. 5. I am sending a similar letter to Seal and a copy to Guttery.t r &gt; •&gt; Copy (E 5023/5/34) M»10386/35• 1 6038 : i i i [9^35 MERCANTILE MARINE DEPARTMENT , BOARD OP TRADE, GREAT GEORGE STREET, WESTMINSTER, S.W. 1. 17th August, 1935. Dear Baggallay, With reference to your letter of the 13th August in regard to the new Persian regulations governing the flying of their national flags by foreign vessels, I had previously heard from Grimshaw of the enquiries which you wished us to make in regard to (a) the extent to which British tenders, launches, etc. operate in foreign ports and fly the Red Ensign, and (t&gt;) the extent to which foreign tenders, etc. operate in United Kingdom ports. As regards (a), we have been in touch with the Marine Superintendents of the following London firms Anglo Saxon Oil Co., Furness Withy &amp; Co., Ellerman Bucknall Line British India Line P. &amp; 0. Line Burma Oil Co. Union Castle Line Orient Line Blue Star Line Shaw Savill &amp; Co. British Tankers Ltd. Royal Mail Co. New Zealand Shipping Co. The only Companies which own small harbour craft abroad are the British Tanker Co., who have certain harbour tugs at Abadan (Iran) that are understood to fly the British flag and not to have been interfered with by the Iranian Authorities, and the British India, which own the ’’Garmsir', about which the present trouble has ariseh. Until recently the P. &amp; 0. Company had a tender stationed at Yokohama which flew the British ^/lag, but this tender has now been sold. Some time ago, the Blue Star Line had H.L. Baggallay, Esq,had a tender in the Argentine, hut that tender was registered as an Argentine Ship and flew the Argentine flag. In regard to (h), we have made enquiries in London and Southampton, hut we have not heen able to trace a single foreign vessel employed at either port. I hope this information will be sufficient for your purpose, hut if there are any further enquiries you would like us to make, we should, of course, he happy to make them. Yours sincerely, (Signed) N.A. Guttery.52. 'vIDEXED With the compliments of the Admiralty Ref,Wo, li.03372/35. Your Ref, Wo, The Under-Secretary of State, India Office, S.W.l.M.03372/35.^ 19 5 5 28th ..agust, 5 Sir. 1 th reference to your letter Ko.ii.4884/5/34 dated 14th ^ugust, I am comBanded by my Lords Commissioners of the admiralty to state for the information of the Secretary of State for foreign affairs that they concur in the terras of the draft telegram which it is proposed to send to Tehran on the subject of the recently promulgated Persian Regulations regarding the flying of flags by vessels plying in Persian waters. a copy of this letter is being sent to the India Office and the Board of Trade. I am. Sir, Tour obedient Servant, The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, a. &gt; «1« DM/vv? :)CE o In any further communication ^ this subject, please quote No. S 4 trirM- A / ^ ^ and address— not to any person by name, but to— 1 /'v The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. 1 . tf't A*' ^ / ,, THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to f Ljl, a-v ; and, by direction of the Secretary of State, 1/ . . transmits herewith copy of the under-mentioned paper, together with the draft of the reply which it is proposed, subject to the concurrence of ^ , to return thereto. Foreign Office, lu- l\ Reference to previous correspondence Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. D&lt; /V s / '^1—^ INDIA OFFICE Similar letter sent to 19-'.O.r. 5000 4 I 21 (6056 e) Anj-C^ -La-^7 . 'l -iv ^ P.COPY , (E 4884/6/34) HU DISTRIBUTION . Decode telegram to Mr.Knatchbull-Hugesseiu Tehran. 2h&amp; August, 1936. D. hy poet. 2nd August, 1936* R. 1.00 p.m. 12th August, 1935. Ho.10. Saving R. Following from Consular Officer at Bushlre telegram No.80 August Istt 'begins:- Addressed to Minister Tehran telegram No.80 repeated to Senior Naval Officer Persian Gulf telegram No.671 copy by post to Government of India. Agent of Mesopotamia-Persian Corporation has now received instructions from his Bombay principals that Garrasir should not fly red ensign till the question has been settled. Garmsir went out to mail steamers on July 29th and 31st flying the red ensign without incident. 09090909090909090No. 23 4834/6/54• Draft. August« 1936 Telegram. Despatched Mr. Knatchbull-Htigessen, Tehran. Your telegram Ho. 10 (Saving) /of 2nd August. Flying of flags by foreign vessels British law by con^lying with Persian regulations and it does not appear that these regulations can be held to be contrary to international law. ground that regulations are unusual will be considered when further information as to practice of harbour launches owned by foreign steamship coo^anles in this country and elsewhere is available. This information may take some little time to collect. 3. It is certainly desirable to avoid raising question of territorial waters* 4. I note that Oarmsir has been CYPHER. in Persian port§7 and previous despatches. Gaimsir would not contravene any 2. question of making representations on instructed/KB(S 4637/5/36) P.Z. 5661 I935 i/KsldmUl* tj&amp;aJLK/titf 15th August, 1956. D6ar (Jotteffy, v;ith reference to our letter s 4&amp;2V/&amp;/34: of 30th atilsr, enclosing a com of a despatch from Tehran regarding the new Persian regulations governing the fljrirs of their national flags by foreign voosels, and in oonfirmstioii of our telephone conversation of some dayo ago, 2 write to say that at the meeting which &amp;!r/s 3 uosed this Question at the Foreign Office on 1st Avgust, and which was attended for a part of the time hy Crimshow and Brandon, the representatives of the Admiralty, Indio Office and Foreign Office who were present decided that altheugb the ^Gartasir' is an unusual cace, inasmuch aa she worlds at Bushire, trat is registered at Calcutta, while moot harbour launches arc registered in the port in which they m&amp;u It would nevertholeso be moot helpful :lf the Board of Trade could collect information as to the practice regarding the flying of flags 'by harbour laonohos e.'l.acn3hare* The particular pointg/ R.A.Oattery* Esq.points on $hiah it me saggeeteS that infojKaation TOtiia l&gt;e mofnl wet*e 5 if l eo^x^etl^a (ft) to wltot ©stent is it tfte custom for tondere* launoheo, etc. oraed or operated T&gt; 3 ? Britiaii Dteamhip eospasiioe in the ports of the principal foreign countries to fly the Red Snsign (or other tom of the National Flag}? fb) to what extent is it the custom for teadorc, lamOiieOj oto» owned and operated hy foroi^p steaosMp ooe^anies in the ports of the United Kingdom to fly sooe form of their national flags? It was also suggested that information as regards (a) he collected t&gt;y applyis^ to the offices in lon&amp;c i of sane of the leading steamship cor^anieoj rather than hy instituting estansii?e enquiries abroad* 8 * •;*© eimll he most grateful for any help you can give us* sixseretfCOPY * 4874/5/34) No*352* BPmSH LEGATION, 26th July, 1935 TEHRAN. Sir So34&gt; *' With reference to my telegram No.236 of 21st July I have the honour to transmit to you, herewith, a revised translation of the recently issued regulations regarding the flying of flags on ships in Iranian waters. This translation has 'been made from a copy of the regulations which has been supplied to me by the Ministry for Foreign Affairs and differs in one or two not unimportant respects from that enclosed in for Foreign Affairs that Articles 1 and 2 apply solely to Iranian vessels and are on the analogy of the regulations which forbid the flying of the Iranian flag on privately owned motor vehicles. Article 3 contains three separate points (a) Foreign vessels calling at Iranian ports may continue to fly their national flag, as at present; but (b) foreign-owned craft which ply solely in Iranian ports and waters and which operate for profit shall not have the right to fly a foreign flag; (c) craft affected by point (b) must, moreover, obtain a licence to operate from the naval authorities or, failing them, from the Customs. Article 4/ Honourable amuel Hoare, Bart, G.C.S.I., etc., etc., etc., my despatch No.303 of 12th July. 2. It has been explained by an official of the Ministry Foreign OfficeArticle 4 exempts vessels owned by diplomats from the scope of the regulations. 3* The Ministry for Foreign Affairs are enquiring whether Article 4 also covers Consular officers and I have strongly urged that exemption from the regulations should in any case be extended to them. Otherwise, we only appear to be concerned with Article 3. point (a) calls for no comment; the object of point (b) according to the explanation of the Ministry for Foreign Affairs is to bring purely local craft into line with motor-cars, on which foreigners occupying private positions are equally not allowed to fly their flags. (I would add in parenthesis that Consuls are allowed to fly the flag of their country on their motor-cars). I have been assured that this new order is not specifically directed against British shipping or against the s.s. H Garmsir” in particular, but rather against dhows belonging to Iraqis, Koweitis, etcetera, of which a considerable number are said to ply for hire in Iranian ports and waters. It would appear from the third paragraph of Mr. Watkinso^s despatch enclosed in my despatch under reference that British-owned local craft at Mohammerah and Abadan, and even the stern wheelers which ply up to Ahwaz, do not, in practice, wear any flag; so the situation there, in fact, remains unchanged. The only British vessel which I know to be affected is accordingly the s.s. H Garmsir u at Bushire. I am informed by the Political Resident that she is a sea-going tug of forty tons registered at Calcutta and is used in the service of the British India Steam Navigation Company, Ellerman (Line) and Bucknall, the Peninsular and Orient Company, and the steamers of the Japan-Bombay Conference. Being, however, the property of the British India Steam Navigation Company, she is only used in the service of other lines at the discretion/discretion of the agents. She has on several occasions proceeded to Basra and is not, therefore, an entirely local craft; hut she is principally used for the carriage of mails to and from the British India steamers. Her work lies between the jetty and the anchorages out at sea and she does no harbour work in the strict sense of the term. Normally she tows no barges and, when not attending steamers, she lies at anchor. I have been assured by an official of the Ministry for Foreign Affairs that there is no risk at present of the authorities taking forcible action to compel the Garmsir to cease flying the Red knsign, but you will be aware from the penultimate paragraph of my telegram No. i«36 that my recommendation is that she should wear no flag pending a study of the regulations. 4. Point (c) of Article 3 is stated by the Ministry for Foreign Affairs to mean that foreign-owned craft must obtain licences-to ply for hire in conformity with certain regulations issued in 1929 and which have never caused us any concern except on the occasion last winter when they were cited in support of a demand that the Royal Indian Marine boats at Henjam should be numbered. A translation of them is enclosed herein but, so far as I can see, they seem to be innocuous. 5. I am sending Monsieur Motamedy full particulars of the 'Garmsir” and of the use to which she is put in the hope that the authorities will issue instructions that she is to be exempted from the regulations. I should be glad of your instructions, however, as to whether, in the last resort, she should or should not conform to them, and as to what line I should adopt with regard to British-owned craft in general. It would presumably be possible to argue that the * f Garmsir nTranslation: Circular of the Ministry of War (General Staff of the Army) addressed to all owners of craft. CIRCULAR. To all owners of Craft: Craft of every description must observe the following regulations in regard to the flying of flags in Iranian coastal and inland waters. 1. No craft may under any circumstances fly the national flag on ordinary occasions. 2. Only on general Iranian holidays may small boats fly the Iranian national flag. 3. Craft belonging to foreign nationals may continue, after having entered Iranian coastal waters, to fly their flag, but if they desire to work in Iranian ports, they shall not have the right to fly the flag of their Government. Moreover, they should obtain a special licence for working in that port from the local naval authorities, or in their absence from the Customs authorities. 4. Small boats belonging to diplomatic representatives are exempt from these arrangements. 5. The provisions above-mentioned will be put into force from the 15th Tyrmah, 1314 (7th July, 1935).TRANSLATION: 3./ REGULATIONS RELATING TO THL DRIVING OF BOATS . Passed by the Council of Ministers on the 1st Mehr, 1308 (September Jd3rd, 1929). Article 1 : Those boats are authorised to accept passengers which satisfy the following conditions:- 1. They must possess a licence. 2. They must possess appliances and a sail for navigation and a sufficient supply of rope for use in emergencies 3. They must possess a lamp and apparatus for extraction from the water. 4. They must possess a special number issued by the Polic&lt; Department. They must be directed by a person possessing a certificate. Article I I: In times of bad weather boats are, generally speaking, exempt from transporting passengers and from movement; except in the case of large boats which carry four oarsmen. Article III : A boatman must satisfy the following conditions:- 1. He must be not less than twenty years of age and must be in good health. 2. He must possess an official licence. 3. He must be familiar with all the Articles of the Regulations concerning the driving of boats. 4. The photographs of drivers of boats must be affixed to the licences issued to them by the Police Department. Article IV : The duties of a boatman will be as follows 1. A boatman may not refuse a passenger while he is stationed at the landing-place. 2. A boatman may not entrust his boat to persons who do not possess licences.3. A boatman, at the time of sailing of a ship, may not place himself on the line of the ship’s course. 4. He must light his lamp at dusk and must keep it alight until he is off duty. 5. He must always have his badge and his number attached to the front of his hat, and must have his certificate and licence always at hand. 6. He must conduct himself politely and properly with the passengers. 7. The boatman will have no right to stop during his course without the assent of his passengers. 8. After landing his passengers he must inspect his boat as necessary and if he finds articles which the passengers have forgotten he may hand them over to the passengers against a receipt if he knows them or if they have not proceeded far from the boat; otherwise he must hand over the forgotten articles at the earliest moment to the Police Office. 9. Boatmen are bound always to have at hand the regulations which specify the tariff, in order that if the passengers so desire it may be shown to them. Article V: Passenger boats are absolved from transporting the following persons and articles, except in cases where the Commissioner of Police permits their transport in cases of necessity 1. Corpses. 2. Goods which may pollute the boat. 3. Persons in a state of drunkenness and madness who are beside themselves. Remark: If corpses are transported, the boat must be disinfected after the act of transport, with the knowledge of the police and the municipal health office. Article VI: The number of passengers and the amount of luggage which may be transported in passenger boats !• Every boat is forbidden to accept more passengers and luggage/luggage than are specified in its licence. Remark : The local police will appoint the number of passengers and the amount of luggage which every boat may transport, and will inscribe the same in the licence. 2* Each passenger is entitled to transport with him up to two Tabriz mans (about 13 lbs.) of luggage; and if he wishes to take more than two mans he must pay the fee in accordance with the tariff which will be laid down for each port. 3. Children from the age of 5 to 10 years will be charged half price, but if more than ten years of age they will be accounted one passenger. 4. Boatmen will have no right to tout for passengers at landing places. 5. A boatman who enters a landing place in order to stop there must station himself at the rear of the other boats which are there already. 6. Boatmen must take their turn of duty for guarding landing-places in accordance with the rosters prepared. 7. If ever a boatman wishes to relinquish his employment, either permanently or for more than a period of three months, he must hand over to the Police Department his badge and number and he will have no right to navigate a boat again until he receives his badge and the number of a licence from the Police Department. Article VII : At the beginning of each year the office of the National Police Acininistration will determine, for each port, the places for landing passengers from boats and the rates of transport. The Council of Ministers, in its session on the 1st Mehr 1308 (September 23rd, 1929) passed these Regulations Relating to the Driving of Boats, comprising seven Articles.go DISTRIBUTION• Decode* Mr, Knatchbull-Hugessen, 1st August, D* By post 1st August, R. 1.50 p*m. 12th August, No*9 Saving* (Tehran)• 1935* 1935. 1935. My despatch Ko.322* Vice Consul Mohammerah who is here on a visit says that Anglo-Persian Oil Company's launches etc. fly the red ensign in Shatt-el-Arab but not in harun. Addressed to Foreign Office go.9 Saving, repeated copy by post to Government of India, Bushire and Senior Naval Officer.•W' jNrrxnn In any further communication on this subject, please quote No. E tr ^ /r ^^^nd address —not to any person by naJme; hut tot— *“ The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. I. A 21 f) THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to ^ ^ v y and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith copi ^£&lt;7 of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, Jo Hv ’ 193 ' ;&gt; ' Uo. Reference to previous correspondence : jT ^ ^ Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. 4 f Similar letter sent to -Awv/l'V 14—6130 11686 (2) /\ /j~ s-ilV y m —o &lt;j ^ —' f.r a-ipY 30 3 « , h r British legation, Tehran. 12th July , 1935, fir, I h&gt;ve tn© honour to transmit, herewith, a copy of a despatch from His Majesty's Consul at Ahwas enclosi^ the text of regulations issued hy Colonel Bayendar, acting Ooiamandant of the Iranian Favy, in regard to t r \e fi_ying of flags on vessels plying in Iranian waters. 2. As Hr. Tatkinaon points out, the meaning of these regulations^is at present very obscure. I have, therefore, inatructed him to obtain t*e fullest possible details and report again to me. In particular, I have asked him to find outs (a) whether Articles 1 and 2 apply only to harbour craft and vessels plying solely in Iranian waters; (b) what the requirements are with regard to the issue of lioences under Article 3; and (c) whether Article 4 exempts foreign Consular officers as well as Diplomatic representatives from the scope of the regulations. 3. Mr. Wetkinson has now informed me by telegram that the Officer in Charge, } ohamperah, states that Article 3 applies to small craft permanently stationed in Iranian ports, and not to tankers or merchant vessels loading or unloading. Hxcept as regards the formalities connected with t e issue of licences, the meaning of this/ ''he Bight Honourable °.ir lamuel Ho are, Bart, .C.S.I. , etc. , e oc. , etc. , rl he Foreign Office.this Article eeeuiB now, therefore, reasonably clear and itia at any rate certain that it covers the case of the launch 'Gameir”. It is naturally impossible ti say with certainty whether these regulations are a retort to our protest over the incident in which Lieutenant arayazeda forced the crew of that launch to lower the 'ed Ensign, but I strongly suspect that this if- so. I have no information ac to \^hat the T'esopotamia Iran Corporation propose to do over the 'Garmsir*, but is is impossible to exclude the of an incident if she continues to wear the British flag after July 23rd, the date on which the regulations enter into force. I should therefore be most grateful if you would furnish me with instructions by telegraph as to what action, if any, I should take in regard to that launch and any others similarly affected. ■ itu regard to the regulations in general, I have received a telegram from the Political Resident who states tnat both he and the Senior 1 aval Ofiicer are of opinion that, whether or not they apply solely to harbour craft, they appear to be without precedent and against international custom and usage, especially if they apply to harbour craft registered in foreign ports, such as the 'OerLioir* 1 . 'his may well be so, but I would point out that in this country the actions of the authorities are seldom guided either by precedent or by international custom, and that in my opinion it will be difficult to secure their modification unless we can show toat they directly conflict with international law or with the provisions of any British regulations concerning the flying of flags on British-owned vessels. I am aware that under the Merchant hipping Act, 1894/^ • d) • oaa to Vbu l •Huges en. 1894, British ships are ooapollsd to hoi*t their fls*i when entering or ‘leaving a foreign port; hut I do not Know whether t v ie applies equally to email creft, eueh ae tenders, whioh are baaed on a foreign r&gt;ort or to British vessel• whieh ply peraanently or mainly in foreig waters, fcfr. atklneon eta tea that Britieh-ewned liarbour oraft and even the larger vee el a whio v ply between Abadan and Ahvas normally wear no flav, at al l ami It i» a oeordingiy not im. oaaible that in part at any *ate thr rtg laUona aay even prove irmosuou* in practice, &amp;« A» eoon as I asi in receipt of feah partioulara troi r, %^ticinaon f I ©hail have the honour to address a furti.er de spat eh to you on this subject# .&amp;n*hlle # at X fttwt already £aid, I should be aoat grateful for telegraphic if strictions with regard to the position &gt;f t);e ’h^raiir’’* h'juld ear, nearer the date of entry into force of the •egulatione, that the e is any likelihood of praotioal dif loul ties arirfhg or of an incident, I would ask tij# Minister for orelgn Affairs to s ee re t**e despatch of instruction* that they thould not e brought Into effect until T have h&amp;i time toreeeive your Inatruotions* 6« a, sending ooplee of t his d espetoh, with its enclosure, to t c foreign ?eorctary to the Government of I mils (no, iW? , and oopiee without -he enclosure to 'die Mcmoureble the . &gt;lltioai nldent in the essian ulf ( o,iS), and a copy to Kla Majesty’s Consul at Ahwax, under cover of ay de^pstot to hta j o*^6, I hrve, etc.,No. 66. BRITISH CONSULATIS, . Air AZ, 2nd July, 1935. Sir, itb reference to xay despatch No. 46 of 9 last, t orwarding ohacKaerah Port .emulations, I have the honour to enclose herewith translation of a further circular from she Naval -uthorities which lays down rules for the use of flags on vessels in Iranian porta and inland waters. This appears to be complementary to the regulations referred to in the correspo donee ending with your despatch No. 101 of December 5, 1933. ;. This circular was sent to me by the Anglo Iranian Oil Company with a request that I would advise them as to the position of their British-owned craft. This includes tankers, paddle steamers, tugs, launches an t a variety smaj.1 craft. I told the General Manager that in my opinion the best course was to wait and cee nether the Authorities endeavoured to apply the regulations to any of the craft based on Abadan It did not at first occur to him or to me that they were intended to apply to merchant vessels or tankers. This point has been raised by the Political Resident, who has received a copy of the circular, presumably through the Agents of the British India Steam Navigation Company. Tnatohbull-Hugaesen, Tnq. , C.II.GL , '*is Britannic Majesty's rinieter, etc. , etc, , e tc. , British Negation, ehran. 3. —3 ^he r eguletlons are far from clear and are possibly quite acceptable if only to be applied to locally operated harbour craft, which, in practice, never flies any fla* at a 1 !. 'his applied equally to the stern-wheelers of up to 300 tons, which ply between Abadan and Ahwaz in the service of the Anglo Iranian Oil Company and of the Mesoptamia Iran Corporation Limited, which have never used the red ensign for many years. These latter will be exoected to fly an Iranian flag on public holidays. Thin seems a reasonable requirement, though I do not consider that it should be flown aft, which is the position reserved by custom for the national flag of the vessel. 4. Ho distinction is made in the preamable nor in Articles 1 and 3 of the Circular between vessels under a foreign flag, under the Iranian flag (if any such exist), or under no flag at all; nor between large craft and small. In Article 3, visiting vessels are mentioned but it is not clear whether a tanker or merchant ship temporarily delayed in an Iranian port would come under the ban, nor whether work refers only to harbour services or also to coastal voyages between Iranian oorta. At Abadan the matter is further complicated by the ^hatt el Arab question. 5. In view of these uncertainties I have replled unofficially to the Ahwaz Manager of the An ,lo Iranian Oil Company asking for fuller information to be obtained from the ft aval Authorities. A copy of my letter to Mr. Haworth is attached. At the same time I informed/informed the General Manager at Abadan that, although I will gifdly give him advice, my personal opinion must not be ta'cen necessarily to represent the official views of Fis ilajesty’s Government. I have also informed Mr. Ikington of the substance of the letter addressed by the President of the Board of ^rade to the Foreign Office on lovember 8, 1933, and of Sir Reginald Foare'e despatch to -he Foreign Office, dtted September 6, 1933. G. Colonel Bayendor has now left for a tour of three or four weeks in the Bulf. I nder these circumstances uhe Anglo Iranian Oil Company have decided chat they will not ask for further Explanations for the present, the raore so as they think it advisable not to be bound down by too precise regulations. 7 * I am awaiting a report on this question from the .Mesopotamia Iran Corporation Limited. • A copy of this des atoh, and of its enclosures is being sent to the Honourable the olitioal Resident in the Persian Gulf at Bushire Fo.1075. I have, etc., (Srfd) A. J. TJATKIHSON. h.b.; o nau: s rf CH-.-zia-n*COPY TRANSLATIO N.g , No. 2849. . 1)0 'fc© f j o • &lt;5« 14* 16,6.^5. OIROULAH TO ALT, ^ ATSR T -AN i QHT Q^HKR3 &gt; later transport should strictly observe the following regulations for using flags in the Iranian shores and inland waters. 1. 2. ■3* 4. 5 , !&gt;o.water trans ort is entitled to use National fla^s on ordinary occasions. On Iranian public holidays only the Iranian National flag may be used by all boats. Foreign water transport may keep on their own flags when arriving at Ira nian shores, but if they wished to work in Iranian ports, they would not be entitled to use their own Govern ment’s flags. Moreover, they are required to obtain from Naval or Cus toms Authorities a special licence to work at the port ooncerned. Launches owned by Diplomatic represen tatives are exenpted from these regu lations. The above regulations shall come into force as from 31st ’ir S'ah '23.7.35). Sgd/- BAYENDOR, Lieut. Colonel. Acting Commai.dant^Southern Naval Force&amp; V -A v Department. PARLIAMENTARY NOTICE. Session 193^ - 3s ti 6' Date. Initials. HOUSE OF COMMONS. Under Secretary Question For j 37 1 93^_ Parliamentary Under Secre tary. Secretary of State *24. Mr. Herbert Williams, — To ask the Secretary of State,for Foreign Affairs, whether his attention has been drawn to the action of the Iranian government in forbidding ships to fly their national flags when in Iranian waters; and what representations he proposes to make to the Iranian government on the matter. [ Wednesday 41 July.\ MINUTE OR SUGGESTED REPLY.17 NO U1GTKIBU i” I ON. Dscypher, M:o 0 KnapoLbull Hugescen (Tehran) e July 15th 1935, D, By post, July 15th 1935. R, July 25th 1935. No. 7. Saving, A A /» ». /*. A A A /&gt; A A /. A A A A A A My despatch Noc303 of July f2th« Following telegrcan received from Political Resident in the Persian Gulf July 13th* Begins H Addressed to Tehran No* 71 copy oy post to Senior- Naval Officero My telegram of the 4th instant No,G9o Have there been any developments? Local Bolo agent has written to me that he is being pressed by his Bombay principals for information as to what action is being taken 'to ensure that British vessels ore not interfered with by Persian naval authorities contrary to international practice*'« Addressed to Foreign Office, repeated to India No„3 Saving and Ahwaz No.I SavingoNO DISTRIBUTION. Decode. Mr. Knatchbull-Hugessen, (Tehran), 15th July, 1955. D. By Post 15th July, 1955. 25th July, 1955. No.8.Saving. (R) 0 “O-O-'O-O-O-O-O- Addressed to Bushire No 3 103, Your telegram NOo71o I have forwarded regulations to Foreign Office by bag and asked for telegraphic instructions and have also instructed His Majesty's Consul at Ahwaz to obtain further particulars as to meaning of regulations» I informed Minister for Foreign Affairs today of above, pointing out that lav; of nations imposed the duty upon every State having a maritime flag to stipulate by its own laws the conditions to be filled by vessels sailing under its flag* I added that, for instance, the Merchant Shipping Act of 1894 prescribed that every British ship must fly its flag when entering or leaving a foreign port* It was therefore essential that meaning of these regulations should be clearly undeiotood and that they should be studied by competent departments of His Majesty's Government- As this would take some time and as it was most important to avoid an incident in the meantime (especially a fresh incident involving Garmsir) I asked that entry into force of regulations should be postponed until they had been studied in London* Copy by post to Senior Naval Officer, Foreign Office, Government of India and Ahwazor ■ &gt;r INDEXED In anj further communication on this subject, please quote No. ^ if ^ i S’ *L{~ ■ ~ J address —not to any ptrton by name, b ( ut to— “The Under-Secretarj of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. 1. I “V / \ —mtllA DIREC'j^ vVvHvtHVVH THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to vP &gt;7 and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop^ , €^o of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, 3' ,193 4 . Tf '/l Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. \^V\, Similar letter sent to 14—6130 10712 (a) ^-~-j .NO DISTRIBUTION Decode. Mr. Knatchbull-Hugessen, (Tehran), 21st July, lS55o D« 10.15 p.m. 21st July, 1935. R. 2.25 p.m. 21st July, 1935. No.236. (R), —O-O—O—0“O”0—O-'O— My despatch No.303 and my telegram No.103 to Bushire copied hy post to you. Ministry of Foreign Affairs have now explained that articles 1 and 2 of regulations apply exclusively to Persian vessels. As to article 4 I have emphasised that exemption should he given for consular as v/ell as diplomatic officers^ Only point of immediate importance is therefore point three and this apparently only in relation to Garmsir as local craft of Anglo-Persian Oil Company and Mesopotamia-Persia Corporation which range up to 200 tons have for years flown no flag. Ministry of Foreign Affairs explain that object of regulations which are not specifically aimed at Garmsir is to ensure that small craft carrying on purely harbour traffic shall not wear flags and they quote analogy of motor traffic on land which would not be allowed to fly the flags of foreign nationalities. Garmsir presumably comes within this category as she plies only at Bushire though only in connexion with British India liners and not for general hire. Ministry of Foreign Affairs have expressed view in conversation that if Garmsir sailed to a foreign destination (were it only for an occasional visit, e.go to Basra) she would not come within regulations but if she plies only in Persian waters she is covered by them© Point regarding territorial waters should I feel be avoided. We might contend that Garmsir goes to outer anchorage and is ipso facto absolved from regulations 0 But thisthis argument would raise the whole question of territorial waters c Ministry of Foreign Affairs have not asked for suspension of regulations as they hold the view that my request was based on misapprehension® They imply however in conversation that there is no risk of sudden incident over Garmsir® Regulations come into force on July 23rd«. Final decision as to whether Garmsir should conform to regulations cannot he taken until legal points are examined, viz. whether Persian treatment of harbour craft on analogy of motor vehicles is justified and whether under British law Garmsir would be (?allowed to) conform., I must await instructions from you on these points. In the meantime in spite of confidence expressed by Ministry of Foreign Affairs as to improbability of an incident, I feel possibility cannot be excluded. I can only suggest therefore that pending final decision Garmsir should wear no flag; it being explained that this course is being adopted in order to be as conciliatory as possible and without prejudice to final decision® Alternatively she might proceed to Basra for a few da^s if not inconvenient to the Company’s schedulec In spite of existing doubt as to legal position I do not feel matter is important enough to provoke serious dispute; moreover until position has been thoroughly considered we may not be certain of our ground® Addressed to Foreign Office No&gt;256, repeated to Government of India No.153, Bushire No.105, ALwaz No.10 and Senior Naval Officer^I &gt; i g ') COPY NO DISTRIBUTION Decode. Mr. Knatchbull-Hugessen (Tehran). 21st July, 1935. D. 10.15 p.m. 21st July, 1935. R. 10.40 a.m. 22nd July, 1935. No.237. (R). My ■telegram No.236. My despatch No.303 which left hy last hag gives the text of the new regulations concerning flying of flags in ships plying in Persian waters. Article 3 prescribes that foreign vessels may continue flying their own flags on arrival in Persian waters hut Persian Ports and waters may not fly foreign flags. Addressed to Foreign Office sent to India No.237. that foreign owned craft operating for profit solely inAny further communication should be addressed to— The Secretary of the Admiralty, London, S.W.j quoting “ L-r-No V.) A dmiralty, S.W.1. 9th July_ 193* . transmit herewith copy of the undermentioned paper. &gt; From whom date and Humber C. in C., Bast Indies Tel. timed 0610/6. This letter has been sent to: Foreign Office. India Off! cej War Office. Air Ministry.Ml3162/6823 7.34 lOOpds 200fms CT&amp;CoLtd Gp605/1. MESSAGE. 7 o n IN Received :— CJ • ill 0 • i»W I fi’^ i 4; i; * Time S 01. G.G.ic) i ndalrulty. rwiiuftifife iutJtoBufc,e i.ip xur iniorsiatiya^danwwNI .a . Ktitt inaioe £394^ jN**vy ci'fiue fcCKbsgr fr m-s.ri.O. i I. JT d ^ 4u li iU 1X • cXcraaoe J^.O.C.» . .X• N* &gt; c5»5 X’aci Jaiy it la proh&amp;bjL# ta.at rxutrxotiori ©a m^urinev enoi t n is oiOjf intetuimil to mypiy to aarbuur orult. Tulitioul It^idtitit luan refcritod qubation tw 4ioi®ttr. ^rdci oout.8 iQt,o zorcte ’ird July. itraiton actiua pr* aucit^ to te fetqui 1 to Cur&lt; oir nffatr l^ui ytur • 0610/f«.r-CRELL , (v't Any further communication should be addressed to— The Secretary of the Admiralty, London, S.W.l A 6 1 L.P.—No. 8 dmiralty, S.W.l. quoting ' M , 4th July /n? 5 - L 1955 - 1-7 ' r (/• 'x?. UO JS 7^ The Secretary of the Admiralty begs to transmit herewith copy of the undermentioned paper. From whom C. in C., East Indies. Date and Number Tel. timed 0545Z/2. This letter has been sent to: India Office . Foreign Office. War Office. Air Ministry. 1 S' INDIA OFFiCEI a - Ml3102/6823 7.34 lOOpds 200fmfi CT&amp;CoLtd Gp 605 / 1 . MESSAGE. &lt;b c f From 0. in C. East Indies. IN - 6 1 5 Received :— Date 4.7.35. Time 1306. GYPHiiiR G.Gr.(G) • Addressed Following message is repeated for information to Admiralty. ADDRESSED F.O.C., repeated C. in C. East Indies, S .K .0. Persian Gulf, From Kavy Office, Bombay. Messrs. MacKinnon Mackenaie state that report has been received from their agent at Bushire that all ships British and foreign have been ordered to haul down ensign in Iranian territorial waters. Order signed by Bayendor and came into force on 1st July. Consul General Bushire informed and understood to be taking necessary action. 05452/2. 1st Lord. 1st S.L. 2nd S.L. 3rd S.L. 4th S.L. D.C .13.S. A «C .13 • S . CIVIL LORD. PARL. SEC. SEC. BAVaL SEC. P.A.S.(S). D .0 .D.3 • D.B.I.2. M.6. D. of P.7356/3: SECRET M.02715/33 ADMIRALTY, S.W.l 13th November 1933 Sir, I am commanded by My Lords Commissioners of the Admiralty to transmit for the information of the Secretary of State for India in Council extracts from reports of proceedings of the Commander-in-Chief, East Indies Station in H.M.S. HAWKINS, ships of the East Indies Squadron and Persian Gulf Division, covering the period April to August 1933. I am also to enclose a copy of a letter without enclosures, which has been sent to the Commander-in-^hief, East Indies and the Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, concerning the question of the flying of the Persian flag by foreign merchant vessels visiting Persian ports. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant (SD.) S.H.PHILLIPS The Under-Secretary of State, India Office, S.W.lM.02715/33 ADMIRALTY, S.W.l 13th November, 1933 Coinmander-in-Chief, East Indies Station. Copy to: Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf. With reference to submission dated 5th August, No.139/587 from Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf uivision, and paragraph 7 of his report of proceedings dated 22nd July, No.129/587, concerning the question of the flying of the Persian flag by foreign merchant vessels visiting Persian ports, I am to transmit for your information copy of various correspondence, as noted hereunder from which it will be seen that the Persians stipulated that the flag should be hoisted in Persian Ports , thus making an official regulation of what has hitherto been an act of courtesy. Government of India letter dated 2nd June, 1933, No.92 M./1/33. Admiralty letter N.S.2244/33 dated 15th June 1933 to Foreign Office. Foreign Office letter dated 30th June, 1933, No.E.3196/ 2885/34. Admiralty letter M.01989/33 dated 18th July, 1933 to Foreign Office. Mr. Mallets despatch dated * 1 ' T Foreigi Office letter dated BY COMMAND OF THEIR LORDSHIPS (SD.) S.H.PHILLIPS.OCi . OF f L 1 Extract enclosure No*5 in East Indies letter Ho # 578/E*I.156 of 22nd August f 1933. 7. Anongst the correspondence shown me by the Honourable the Political Hesident, I saw that a request by the Persians had been made that British merchant ships should fly the Persian flag at the fore in Persian waters as 'an act of courtesy”. The Board of Trade agreed that this was sometimes the custom. AS nQ itrier I nor any of my officers had ever heard of it (and if it is so, it is certainly a custom a naval officer should know), I made enquiries of several British merchant captains who also were ignorant of it. As a result of Persian sensitiveness, a ship visiting Abadan en route to Basrah, for instance, is expected to fly the Persian flag instead of the •Iraqi flag (»Iraq being the next country to be visited). I point this out as it is quite likely that a visiting ship might get involved with the Persian authorities. Moreover, it may be misleading to those who, like myself, are accustomed to the normal practice, and may not be aware of such a custom as has been suggested. It may perhaps be considered a small matter, but trivialities in the Persian Gulf sometimes have a habit of assuming importance and it would seem desirable that the senior Naval Officer should be informed of such matters. v OTHER PEHSIAN INCIDENTS ♦Any reply to this letter should addressed to— THE SECRETARY, Board of Trade, Great George Street, Westminster, S.W.l, and the following reference number quoted:— M.6554/33 . BOARD OF TRADE, O Great George Street, Westminster 0^ 1933 10th November, 1933. The Board of Trade present their compliments ; to The Secretary of State for India-in-Council / and beg to transmit herewith for information copy of a letter dated 8th November, 1933, «f--k)-day 2 s--dorteywhich they have caused to be addressed to The Under Secretary of State, Foreign Office, S.W.l. Reference to previous correspondence (if any):— ENCUJSUiti M Os N0.4iS] 16 NOV. 1333 FROM SECRETARY, POLITIC'L AMD SECRET DEPT. INDIA OrFiCE OOPV SENT TO. . B.6032. Wt.22105/2371. 3000. 2/32. 'NVy. &amp; S. Gp. 6!3.Telegrams—“ SHIPMINDER, PARL, LONDON.' Telephone—WHITEHALL 5140 Ext. Any further communication on this subject should be addressed to :— Assistant Secretary, Mercantile Marine Department (address as opposite) Mercantile Marine Department, and the following number quoted :— M.8554/33. Ji . JU* Board of Trade, Great George Street, Westminster, S.W.l COPY 8th November, 1933 Sir With reference to your letters of the 5th September (E.5042/2885/34) and 21st October (E.5740/2885/34) and enclosure regarding the flying of the Persian flag on foreign merchant ships calling at Persian ports, I am directed by the board of Trade to state, for the information of Secretary Sir John Simon, that, so far as they are aware, no country other than Persia insists upon the flying of the national flag by foreign vessels calling at the ports of the country in question. The Board are advised, however, that, as an act of courtesy, it is a common practice for a ship regularly trading to a country to fly at the Fore that country's national flag when entering port. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your obedient Servant, (Signed) G.E.BAKER. The Under Secretary of State, Foreign Office, S.W.lfNP^XED In any further communication on this subject, please quote N °- e j^q-. and address —not to any person by name, but to— ‘The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. 1. ' p.z. 16814 a hA THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs -rpresents his compliments to UULj- a-nd, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop^Ax® of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, 0 Jt, , 1933 • 0 V 1 ’ A Reference to previous correspondence f\. ^ i&lt;(*a is er^ is ^ Description of Enclosure. &amp; Name and Date. Subject. ^O- irt Qck'iA. 'ry^scA-cX^Ji ENCLOSURE IN V, i,- ITtlt No. A3 26OCT. 1933 ^ROM SECRETAKY, POLITICAL AND SECRET DEPT. INDIA OFFICE Similar letter sent to 14-6130 8755 (2)COPY (E 5042/2685/34) Mo. 398. British Legation, 6814 GULHEE. 1933 August 12th Sir With reference to your despatch No. 305 of July 24th last I have the honour to transmit herewith a copy of a letter from His IvIajesty T s Consul at Ahwaz regarding the flying of the Persian flag ly foreign vessels in the Shatt-el-Arat. It will he observed that ships lying in mid-stream off Abadan are apparently not interfered with. y.n') { As reported in Sir R.Hoare's telegram No. 10 saving, I have asked the Ministry for Foreign Affairs for the text of the regulations under which the circular was issued. I have so far been unsuccessful in obtainirg a definite reply but I am continuing to press the responsible official for an answer 3. I am sending a copy of this despatch to His Majesty T s Consul, Ahwaz (No. 74). I have, etc. , (3d.) V.A.L. Mallet. The Right Honourable 3ir John Simon G.C.S.I., etc., etc. , etc., FOREIGN OFFICE.r ^ 29th June, 1933. Dear Chancery, With reference to our telegram No. 23 of the 27th instant. We forward copies of correspondence with the Anglc-Persian Oil Company and with the Mesopotamia Persia Corporation limited regarding the flying of Persian flags ly vessels in the Shafcfc- el-Arab, the Port of Aladan and the Port of Mohammerah. The Anglo-Persian Oil Company state that, in reply to Major Bayandor*a letter they undertook to see that their own vessels and others coming to fuel for whom they act as unofficial agents would fly the flag when actually moored alongside Abadan jetties as soon as supplies of such flags could be made available. The question of mid-stream was shelved and no attempt has been made to interfere with ships 'intending to come alongside' as threatened in Major Bayandor's letter of April 10. The Mesopotamia Persia Corporation Ltd. state that British India ships now fly the Persian flag, under instructions from Bombay, when moored in mid-stream off Mohamnerah for loading or unloading operations. Yours ever, AHWA2, The Chancery, Br it ish Legati on, Tehran.Copy of an Express letter No. 427-3 dated the 24th April 1933 from the Hon T !le the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf and His Britannic l&amp;Jesty T s Consul-General Pars Hhuzistan etc, Bushire to His Ivlajesty's Vice-Consul, Mo ham me rah. Attached notice was issued on the 16th April 1933. Please telegraph (XX) whether similar notice has teen issued at Mohammerah and, if so, on what date. Translation of a circular No. 354 dated the 27th Farwardin 1312 (16th April 1933) from the Deputy Commander of the Southern Force, Persian Imperial Navy. As some of the ships which are arriving at the Persian ports seem to have no Persian flag hoisted on the front flagmast irrespective of the regulations, it is hereby notified that the necessary instructions may be given to their ships concerned on this respect in order to avoid any misapprehension. Telegram XX From Britoonsul, Mohammerah. To Political Resident, Bushire, No. 34, Dated. the 28th April 1933. Reference your Express letter No. 427-3 of 24th April. Yes in Abadan but not in Mohfmmerah. About same date. Despatch follows. Britc onsul.CCMPIMTTIAL. No,362. r* British Vice-Consulate, Mohammerah, April 26, 1933. To Sir, With reference to the Hon'lle the Political Resident in the Persian (Julf T s iiixpress letter l^o.427-S dated the 24th April 1933 I have the honour to report that a similar circular regarding the hoisting of the Persian flag has 'been issued in Abadan but so far not in Moh T rah. 2. The regulation affects only tankers and other cargo and passenger ships of all nationality vhich wish to come alongside the quays in Abadan. It does not refer to men-of-war or ships anchoring in the river. 3. The instructions were issued about two weeks ago by the Persian Commander - Major Bayandor - direct to the Companies concerned, and not through 1iie local Governor or Consul. Consequently I am unable to give the exact date at present. I have, however, called for a copy of the circular from the Anglo Persian Oil Company which I will forward, but in the meantime I think it is safe to assume that the date is the same or, more certainly, that the circular is the outcome of the same move. 4. The Anglo Persian Oil Company tankers are at present carrying out the instructions. Messrs the Anglo Persian Oil Company inform me that enquiry from their London /Office The Secretary to the Hon r ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.Office elicited the reply that, though rare, some other countries insist on the same practice being observed, fhey have, therefore, cieyed the instruction without protest. 5* One Norwegian ship was not allowed to load as it had no Persian flag. The Captain eventually obtained one from the Anglo Persian Oil Company. I have , e tc ., (Sd,) F.C.L.Chauncy, His Majesty's Vice-Consul.Copy of a letter No, T^zlzj dated the 13th May 1933 from Messrs the Anglo-Persian Oil Co, , Ltd. , Atadan to Eis Majesty’s Vice-Consul, Moham^erah. «dth reference to your recent enquiry, we beg to infoim you that we received a communication dated 10th April last from the Commandant of the Imperial Southern Navy in which we were requested to issue instructions to vessels visiting Abadan 'to comply with the International Regulations with regard to flying the Persian flag whilst in port.” It was added that in the event of a ship not complying, it would not be allowed to come alongside to take oil. 2. The question has been raised previously and on the last occasion, about 12 months a go, the local Director of Customs was requested to obtain from the Authorities in Tehran a copy of the regulation in which it was stated that the flag must be flown. 3. Nothing further was heard of the matter until receipt of the letter of 10th April above referred to when we decided to instruct our own vessels, which were in possession of the necessary flag, to fly it at the foremast whilst alongside jetties only. We pointed out, however, that we had no authority to issue similar instructions to the Masters of vessels not owned by this Company and that a number of them would not on the next visit to the port be in possession of the Persian ensign. A letter is, however, addressed by us to such vessels, as their agents, advising them that it is the practice in this port to fly this flag whilst vessels are alongside jetties. 4. On 25th April, the S.S. 'BUCCINUM”, a Norwegian vessel, arrived here for the first time since the practice of flying the Persian flag has been instituted. The Director of Customs boarded the vessel, and as there was no Persian flag on board the Master was informed that the crew would not be / per mi ttedpermitted to land. later instructions were given ty the Director to the Customs representative on the jetty to prevent the connecting up of pipeline so that the vessel could not commence to load her cargo. 5. We immediately interviewed the Director who then agreed that, as the vessel has had no opportunity to obtain a Persian flag, he was prepared in tiiis case to withdraw his restrictions, but would not do so when a vessel came here for the second time without a flag. 6. We pointed out that no difficulty would arise if proper flags could be purchased in Abadan, but as the vessels did not always proceed to ports where the Persian flags could be obtained or made up in time, and as proper bunting is not available locally, we would have to obtain a supply cf flags from home for issue to vessels against payment, and in the meantime we would endeavour to ma&amp;e up flags from such material as was available locally. 7. .«e would add that the circumstances of this case were reported to our Tehran Office, and that we shall shortly be in position to supply flags to all vessels which require them. - --OOHPIBjJJTIAL. British Vice-Consulate Ho. 8/5/400, Mohsmnerah, May 16, 1933, P.Z. IS 33 J Sir with reference to your Express letter ^o.471-3 dated the 6th May 1933 I have the honour to report that all the information I have been able to gather on the subject is contained in a letter I have now received from Messrs the Anglo Persian Oil Company, Limited, Abadan, a copy of which is attached. 2. It would appear from this letter that Messrs The Anglo Persian Oil Company, Limited regard themselves as the agents of all ships visitng Abadan for oil and have taken it upon themselves to notify them of the regulation and to supply the flag where desired. 3. As no appeal, notification or reference of any sort has been addressed to me I have taken no steps in the matter at all, beyond reporting the issue of the recent circular of the Officer Commanding, Persian Navy in my fortnightly diary. Moreover from the Persian view point as Vice-Consul at Mohammerah I have no position in Abadan. 4. with regard to the Norwegian vessel 'BUCCINUM” it would appear that so far the Captain has made no protest of any sort. 5. The regulation has not been circulated in Mohammerah, but I have noticed several British India Steam Navigation Company's ships and one German ship flying the Persian flag when anchored off Mohammerah in the Shatt-el-Arab (Iraq water). I have, etc., (Sd. ) F.C.L.Chauncy. His Majesty's Vice-Consul To The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.Copy of a letter No.302/3 dated the 20th May 1933 from the Anglo-Persian Oil Company, Limited, Abadan to His Majesty's Vice-Consul, Mohamrnerah, We have the honour to acknowledge receipt of your letter No.6/5/396 of the 16th May and as requested have pleasure in enclosing herewith a oopy of the communication received from the Commandant of the Imperial Southern Navy, together with a translation thereof.Trans la t ion, ¥o7^a2. 12th Farvar&amp;in April 1C, 1933. According to rsports I have received steamers arriving for oil at Abadan, both Company and non-Company do not hoist the Persian flag, in accordance with international usage, at the time of their arrival. Therefore I shall be glad if you will kindly instruct your shipping Department to inform incoming ships of the arrangements. (sicJ In the event of any ship not complying with this Law (sic), it will not be allowed to come alongside and take oil. (3d.) Beyander, representative of the Commander-in-Chief of the Southern Eaval Commani, To The Anglo Persian Oil Company, Limited.Copy of D#0. letter No.437, dated 25th May 1933, from His Majesty’s Vice-Consul, Mohsmmerah to His ^O^sty’s Consul for Khuzistan, Ahwaz. I understand now from Messrs the Mesopotamia Persia Corporation, limited, Mohammerah, that the Senior Naval Officer of the Persian Navy (MSajor Bayandor) has written to Mackinnon and Mackenzie (the British India Steam Navigation Company's Agents) in Bombay informing them of the regulation regarding foreign ships flying the Persian flag, and that they are now observing this regulation in respect of Mohammerah as well as Abadan. So far, however, no notice has been circulated in Mohammerah and I do not know whether the ships fly the Persian flag off Mohammerah of their own accord or by • I am getting details from Sunter of Mespers here. orderCopy of a letter No.LOC/EOO dated the 27th May 1923 from Messrs the Mesopotamia Persia Corporation, Limited, Mohammerah to His Ma;jesty r s Vice-Consul, Mohammerah. In reply to your letter Ho. 6/5/433 of the 24th instant we have to state that no instructions have been received by this Office frcm the Persian Authorities regarding the flying of the Persian flag in the Port of Mohammerah, but we have observed recently that this Company's steamers now fly a Persian flag on the foremast and we understand that a request for this to be done was made by 1he Senior Haval Officer of the Persian Southern Fleet to this Company r s Agents at Bombay. This information has not however been obtained from an authoritative source in view of which we are today writing to Bombay, On receiving a reply we shall again communicate with you. British Vice-Consulate, Mohammerah, No. 6/5/451 May 29, 1933. The foregoing copy is forwarded to The Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. His Majesty T s Consul for Khuzistan, Ahwaz. for information. (Sd.) F.C.L.Chauncy. His Majesty's Vice-Consul.Copy of a letter Uo.LOC/331, dated the 17th June 1933 from Messrs The Mesopotamia Persia Corporatl on. Limited, Mohammerah to His Majesty’s Vice-Consul, Mohaamerah. In reply to your letter Ho.6/5/433 of the 24th ultimo and further to ours of 27th idem, we enclose herewith copy of a letter which has teen received ty this week’s mail from this Company's Agents in Bombay.(COPY) Ho, 230. BRITISH INDIA ST-cIAM NAVIGATION COMPANY, Vy UMITSD* (Incorporated in England) Bomtay, 6th June, 19 33. Dear Sirs, ^ith reference to your letter No.MM/203 of 27th ultimo forwarding a copy of a letter from K.B.M's Vice- Consulate at your port, we would inform you that on learning from Bushire Agents that the Persian Naval Office had drawn their attenoion to the fact that the Company's steamers old not fly the Persian Flag when arriving at Persian. Ports, we issued instructions to the Commanders of the Fast anl Slow Gulf Mail steamers to see that this is done in future. Yours faithfully, Pro. MaclcLnnon Mackenzie &amp; Co. Sgd. AGENTS. Messrs The Mesopotamia Persia Corporation Ltd,, Agents, B.I.S.N.C., Ltd., Mohammerah.COPY (E 5740/2885/34) British Legation, Grulhek' 6 th September, 1933, Sir, In continuation of n$r d.esp8.tch No, 396 of August 12th, I have the honour to report that the head of the Jtoglish section recently told a member of ray staff that he had, as requested, made enquiries about the issue of the circular regarding the misting of the Persian flag by foreign merchant vessels visiting Persian ports. The reply he had received, as v»as only to be ejected, ms that this was a nrtter within the discretion of the Persian Grovemraent and that other States had similar regulations. 2 , It appeared th^t there were no internal regulations and in fact it is clear trom the terms of Ifeijor Bayondar^ communica tion to the Anglo-Persian Oil Company that he meant international regulations, 3 , Sheyesteh was told again that it was very unusual for states to make regulations about the flying of their flag by foreign vessels, although the practice \ms not unknom, and it was also suggested to him that the orders mi^it have come more appropriately from the local Governors than from Major Bayondar, He made the excuse that Persian officials were still very ignorant of maritime procedure, but I do not anticipate that any change in the present regulations will be made, 4, I am sending copies of this despitch to the Acting Political Resident in the Persian Gulf (No,134), and to His Majesty^ Consul at Ahwaz (No,79), I have, etc,, (3d.) V.A.L.Msllet. The Right Honourable Sir John Simon, G.C.S.I., etc,, et c,, etc,, The Foreign Office,&amp; E 5740/2665/S4 POREIGU OmCE 21at October, 1933 .iith reforence to Foreign Office letter No* fi 5 042/2665/^4 of the 5th September I am directed by Secretary Sir John Simon to transmit to you herewith, to be laid before the Board of i'rade, the accompanying eo y of a further despatch from His Majesty^ Chargfc d* .ffaires at Tehran regarding the flying of the Persian flag by foreign merchant ships calling at Persian ports* 2* In this connexion I am to re most you to draw the attention of the Board to a statement, contained in the third enclosure to Foreign Office letter No* S 5042/2685/34 and attributed to the Anglo-Persian Oil Company, that although the practice now required by the Persian naval mthorities is unusual, some other countries insist on a similar procedure. 3* 5ir John Simon will be glad to learn whether this statement ij correct, and if so, what oth^r countries insist on the flying of their flag by foreign merchant vessels calling at their ports. 4. Copies of this letter are being sent to the Admiralty and Inoia Office. I am. Sir Your obedient Servant (Sd.) G. W„ RET,'DSL, The Secretary to the Board of Trades 3 C li a T . M.01969/33”. 16th July, 3 Sir, tfith reference to your letter No..3.3196/2885/34 of 30th June, 1933, concerning the recent Persian notifica tion that foreign merchant shipping should fly the Persian flag on entering Persian ports, I am com landed oy My Lords Commissioners of the Admiralty to acquaint you, for the information of the iecretary of State for foreign Affairs, that it has now been ascertained from the British Tanker Company that their local representative at Abadan, who acts as Agent for the Admiralty (and other) Oilers, is lending an appropriate flag to each such vessel when it reaches the wharf. This arrangement satisfies the Persian authorities. 2. My Lords propose to allow this procedure to continue and in the circumstances the need for the precise instructions suggested in paragraph 3 of your letter enclose! does not seem to arise. 3. Copies of this letter are being sent to the Board of Trade and the India Office. The Under Secretary of State, Foreign Office, ► L I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, d, S. BARNES.'-A*-*-, fyi Copy to India Office, Tehran and Bush Ire . IN No. 92-M. 1/33. (Soveminent of India© Department of Commerce. FILE CQPY^ • ... . r'° ^ ,»U,3i Simla, the 2nd June 1933. Fran A. N. Fury, Ssquire, B. A.* L. L. B., Offg. Assistant Secretary to the Government India* To The Principal Officer, Mercantile Marine Department, Bombay, Karachi, Aden, Madras, Calcutta Sc Bangoon District. I Ihe Nautical Surveyor Mercantile Marine Department f Chittagong* Flag to be flown by foreign merchant shipping in Persian Waters. I am directed to say that the Government of India have received information that a circular has been issued by the Deputy Commander of the Persian Navy to Shipping Agents at Bushire and at Mohamerah that fdredgn merchant shipping must by the 5th June 1933 fly the Persian flag in Persian Waters •according to regulations* I am to request that the information may be communicated to owners and Agents of ships concemed in your District, in case any inquiries are received on the subject. OcC.’rt £ 1 A K’ y ^In any further communication on this subject^please P z. no. and address —not to any person by name, but to— “The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, Londo tub o THE Under-Secretary of 3 &gt;l ' ®'^ 1 ' e * 8 n Affairs presents his compliments to and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith copses of the under-mentioned paper. &lt; 7j jAj 1 A/'O Foreign Office, V , 193i . Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. &amp; t 4 )o 30 ^ f ENCLOSURE IN WiifLKLY 1 *' 1 No. 27, 6 JULIES from secretary, POLITICAL AN1&amp; |£QRLT DEPT. INDIA OFFItE COPY SENT TO 3 JULf^ X Similar letter sent to .INDEXED CONFIDENTIAL. No .6 P.Z. .60?-S/25 B or 1935. 3777 '■N . JS??- (j&gt;/ f rhe Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf pi’esents his com pliments to 1. His Majesty’s Secretary of State for India, London, flo.607-S. 2. The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India,Simla. JNo.60?-S. 3. Hie Majesty’s Minister, Tehran. Ho. 25 B. and has the honour to transmit to him n copy of the undermentioned docu ment (s). British Residency and Consulate-General, BTTSHIRE. Dated.. 33 Reference to previous correspondence Busnire Printed letter HO. 601-S of 2nd June 1933. Description of Enclosure. ( 23 B.} Name and Date. Letter Ho.LOC^OOwdpted the 27th May 1933, from the Mesopotamia Persia Corporati Limited, Mohammerah, to his Majesty’s Vice-Consul, Mohammerah. Dr- 27 Subject. Flying of the Persian Flag by foreign vessels entering Persian ports.indexed ~ In any further communication on this sufjjeeffpTease quote f -3 N «- £ (su, and address— not to any person by tyitne, but to— “ The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. x. ' - 71 (/w INDIA LlhECf THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to He lUAn and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith copvja^© of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, , 1933 . ■ n1 Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. f nX: Name and Date. Subject. V\. V( 30^ ?^o . Similar letter sent to r ^ 14-6130 8181 ( 2 ) CLoOwvfcrCOPY SENT BY AiR MAIL t)/b/S) A4) ENGLOscmr No. 25 FROM SECRETARY, POLITICAL SECRET DEPT. INDIA OFFICE — A 22 jUN.1933 . A 40 Admiralty Ref .Ho. N.S. 2844/35. Your Ref, No.16th June* 1966. dfcted the 14th June, 1963# on th® subject of the reoent Persian regulation that foreign merchant shipping must fly the ersian flag in Persian porta# I am commanded by My Lords Commissioners of the Adairalty to state, for the information of the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, that Their Lordships have recently had under Their coneider^ ation the question of whether this regulation should be complied with by Admiralty oilers at Abadan. As Their Lordships believe the custom to be merely s matter of courtesy# without any special signifi cance# Ihey sre disposed tc accede to the Persian request. They would, however# be glad to receive the views of the Secretary of Jtate for Foreign Affaire on the matter# aince it might be argued that the procedure involved some degree of recognition of Persian territorial rights over Iraqi waters. In the meantime arrangements are being made for Admiralty oilers tc csrry a Persian flag for this purpose. The Under Secretary of State# Foreign Office, ° - 1 / Copies¥ Copies of this letter are being sent to the Board of Trade and to the India Office. I am, Sir, Your obedient Serrant, 3 , &amp; &amp; BARNES,The Hon ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his coin pliments to (1) His Majesty’s Secretary of State for India, London, Ho. 601-S. (2) The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, Simla, Ho. 601-S. (3) His Majesty’s Minister, Tehran, Ho. S3-B. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment (s). only. Name and Date. Subject. 1. Communication Ho. 302/3, dated 20th May 1933, from the Anglo- Persian Oil Comoany, Limited, Flying of the ^ersian Abadan, *ith enclesure. Flag by forwifcn vessels 2. B.O. letter Ho. 437, dated 25th May 193 3, to Mr. Consul entering ^rsian ports. Wat kin son. 12 JUiHlij;Copy of a letter Ho. 302/3, dated the 20th May 1933, from the Anglo-JPtersian Oil Coraoany, Limited, Abadan, to His Majesty's Vice-Consul, Mohamraerah. We have the acknowledge receipt of your letter Ho. 8/5/398 of the 16th May and as requested have pleasure ** * ?9i-£S2l25. e ^ in enclosing kzsx herewith a copy of the cofununication received from the Commandant of the Imperial Southern Havy, together with a translation thereof. !12th Fartardin. April 10th, 1933, The Anpio-Persian Oil Company, Limited, According to reports that I have received steamers arriving for oil at Abadan, 'both Company and non- Company are not complying *i th jdBfe the internatioml regulations with regard to flying the ^rsian flag whilst in port. Therefore I shall be glad if you will kindly inform your Shipping Department to give order to all ship to comply with the above regulations. In the event of any ship not complying joc it will not be allowed to come alongside and take oil. SD/ Beyander.British Vice-Consulate , D *0, Ho • 437 • My dear Watkinson, I understand Aow from Messrs• the Mesopotamia Persian Corporation, Limited, Mohammerah, that the Senior Haval Officer of the ^rsian Navy (Major Bayander) has written to Mackinnon and Mackenzie (the British India Steam Navigation Company’s Agents) in Bombay informing them of the regulation regarding foreign ships flying the Persian flag, and that they are now observing this regulations in respect of Mohammerah as well as Abadan. So far, however, no notice has been circulated in Mohammeraih and I do not know whether the ships fly the n ersi8r flag off Mohanmerah of their own accord or by order. I am getting details from Sunter of Mespers here. Tours ever, 8D/ P.C.L. Chauncy. Mohamme rah, 25th May 1933. A.K. Watkinson, Esquire, His Majesty’s Consul, Ahwaz.INDEXED -5 emmrrmrm,. No. 081-S/21 B or 1^55. : • / i j ^%|MH kW%' ' ft The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to !• His Majesty’s Secretary or fc^tate ior India, London. / The Foreign Secretary to the lioveminent or India, Simla. 3. His Majesty’s Minister,Tehran* ao. OSl-S. - HO. 21 B. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment (s). British Residency and Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. \7 /llr# Dated ....ZU%. .Mey.. 19.35...... 1*0(1) Tehran telegram Ho.9-*Saving or 30th May 1933 to FOREIGN OFFICE. Reference to previous correspondence : To(2) • H Ho.30 or 30th May 1933. v Description of Enclosure. To(3) •• ” Ho.41 or 30th May 1933. Name and Date. 1. Persian Naval Circular Ho.354 of 16th April 1^3^ Persian Naval Circular No.489 of 18th May 1933. Subject. Flying of the Persian flag by foreign vessels entering Persian ports.fty Ai r ITail . No. 533-3 of 1933. Ibe lion ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to His Majesty's Kecretary of State for India, London, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. jf ~e le pram . {ic. 6 € cJ^^.) Ho 3 f /£V *\ COPY {&amp; 56S9/5529/34) BO. 474. BRITISH LEGATION, TBHRAB, September 26th, I9&amp;0* Bla Majosty's Representative prerente his ooapiiments to ai« Majesty’s Principal Secretary of State of foreign Affaire and has the honour to transmit herewith, copies of the documents mentioned in the subjoined Schedule, on the subject of British merchant vessels arriving at Persian ports and the question of their Hying the Persian flag. 'VT* D.O. letter Fo. 140/502-3 dated the 18th September 1930, from lieutenant Colonel Bisooe, His Majesty’s Consul General at Bashire.00 PT BY AIB MAIL. B*0«Bo«l40/602-S of 192K)» Bxitiah Be8id«noy v Bushire, the 18th Septemhei, 1930• Bear ri* Bobeit, The Acting Governor recently sent me a private letter stating that British merchant vessels arriving in Persian ports did not fly the Persian flag and as it was 'one of the principal international rights founded upon courtesy 11 to fly the flag of the country at which a ship arrived he as iced me to inform shipping companies that henceforward merchant vessels arriving at Persian ports should fly the Persian flag as long as they were in a Persian port* I had never heard of any such custom myself and as 'LUPIN' happened to he here when this peculiar request was received I atkred the c&amp;ptain whether he was aware of any such custom and he told me that he had never seen this done in any country, the only exception being some of the large Atlantic liners, who he believed sometimes hoisted an English or American flag when entering an j&amp;glish or imerioan port, more to please their passengers than anything else* It was certainly not however an international custom* Where the Persians got this idea from I cannot imagine and as the request was put forward privately it is probable that they are not sure of their ground* I enclose for • • • Sir Kobert Olive, K.Q.M.O., H.B.M’s Minister, British legation, T8H2AH• ,,,,,^3..^8) for your information a copy of the ropiy I have sent to tho Acting Governor and I have tbonght it desirable to inform you of this matter in ease it is raised at Tehran. Youre einoerely, (Signed) H.7. BISCOB.COPY / 18th September 1930* Dear M« Shahruai, 1 am obliged to you for your letter of the 14th September 1930 and for your hind enquiries. I am glad to say that I am gradually getting better bat it will probably take two or three weeks before X aan go oat. As regards what you write aboat the flying of the Persian flag by merchant vessels while in a Persian port it would appear that Yoar Excellency has been mis-informed. I had never heard of any saoh custom or of this being done.anywhere. As I had been told that Your Excellency had mentioned this matter to khan Bahadur I made special enquiries regarding it from the Captain of £.M«S. 'LUPIft' who was recently here. He informed me that it was not customary for merchant vessels to fly the flag of tho foreign country when entering a foreign port. Your excellency will therefore realise that it is not possible for me to ask British ships in Persian ports to fly the Persian flag. in any oase a request of this sort should be addressed to His Majesty's Minister at Tehran and not to me. Yours sincerely, (Signed) H.Y. BISCOS. His Bxeellenoy Mirsa Jusain All khan Sh&amp;hrusl, Acting Governor of the Gulf Ports A Islands, Dashti and Dashtisten, MBSSXB*P.54(&gt;7. Wt. 14024. 11/31. Wy. A S. © Forwarded with the Compliments of the Assis^nt Secretary for the Mercantile Marine Department of the Board of Trade. hJiHl iajlimta ^ 3$ * Board of Trade, Mercantile Marine Dept Gt. George St., m Lon London, S.W.l.Board of Trade, Great George Street, Westminster, S.W.l. M.14335/30. 6th November, 1930. Sir, With reference to your letter of the 30th October, (£5629/5629/34), transmitting copy of a despatch from His Majesty^ Representative at Tehran regarding a suggestion of the Persian Government that British merchant ships, arriving at Persian ports, should be requested to fly the Persian flag, I am directed by the Board of Trade to state, for Mr. Secretary Henderson*s information, that although as an act of courtesy British vessels occasionally fly the flag of a foreign country on arrival at a port of that country, it is by no means a common practice, and certainly there is no international custom of this nature. In these circumstances the Board concur in the terms of the reply which has been sent by the British Resident to the Persian Government. I am to add that under Section 74 of the Merchant Shipping Act, 1894, a British ship is required to hoist her national colours on entering or leaving any foreign port. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your obedient Servant, (Signed) G. £. BAKER. The Under Secretary of State, Foreign Office, S. W. 1.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000019_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/3470B</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000019</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/3470B</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 28/64 ‘Persia. Flying of Flags in. Persian Regulations re. flying of flags by foreign merchant vessels in Persian Ports.’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1930/1936</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-03-27T22:05:14</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (141 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the inside front cover with 1, and terminates at the last folio with 142; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Correspondence concerning the introduction of regulations by the Imperial Persian (Iranian) Navy relating to the flying of the Persian flag by foreign merchant vessels in Persian ports. The correspondence covers: the new regulations and their implications for British commercial interests such as the Mesopotamia Persia Corporation Limited and the Anglo-Persian Oil Company; acceptance and implementation of the new regulations; translations of the regulations concerned, signed by G H Bayendor, In Charge of the Southern Naval Forces of the Imperial Persian Navy.The file’s principal correspondents are: HM’s Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary in Tehran, Hughe Montgomery Knatchbull-Hugesson; HM’s Vice-Consul in Mohammerah [Khorramshahr], Frederick Charles Leslie Chauncy; George William Rendel and Lacy Baggallay of the Foreign Office.The file includes a divider, which gives a list of correspondence references contained in the file by year. This is placed at the back of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Docks and harbours legislation</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>British Vice-Consul, Khorramshahr</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Islamic Republic of Iran Navy</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>British Legation, Tehran</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Flags</topic></subject><subject><topic>Merchant shipping</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000019#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>