<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x0001b6_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T11:57:27.491Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">B 0 [This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty s Gov^mmeati Printed for the use of the Foreign Office. September 1905. CONFIDENTIAL. (8193.) jNo. 1. Director of Military Operations to Foreign Office.—(Received July 29.) (Secret.) THE Director of Military Operations presents liis compliments to the Under secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, and begs to forward for his information the Report and sketches compiled by Captain E. W. S. Mahon, R.E., who was dispatched to examine the country adjacent to the Kb or Abdullah at the head of the Persian Gulf, with a view to reporting on the places which appeared most suitable as termini of the proposed Bagdad Railway, in accordance with conclusion 1 of the sixty- seventh meeting of the Committee of Imperial Defence, held in London on the 22nd March, 1905. 2. Major-General Grierson would be pleased if he could be informed whether there is any objection to a copy of this Report being furnished to the Intelligence Branch of the Indian army, and should the report be printed he would be glad to be furnished with six copies. Winchester House, St. James’s Square, London, July 29, 1905. Inclosure in No. 1. Report (with Maps) on the country adjacent to the Khor Abdullah, and places suitaole as Termini of proposed, Bagdad Railway, by Captain E. W. S. Mahon, R.E. July 1905. (Secret.) THE terminus of the Bagdad Railway could be made at either of the following places :— 1. Bussorah. 2. Fao. 3. Um-Kasr. 4. Warba Island. 5. Koweit. (a.) El-Kathama; (b.) Bander-es-Shuwaik. There are no insuperable difficulties to be met with in reaching any of these places, and the cost of construction per mile (exclusive of permanent way) would be comparatively slight. There is thus no technical objection to any of the above places becoming the terminus of the railway, I propose to discuss the merits of each. Bussorah, situated up the Shatt-el-Arab, about 67 miles from the bar, is the present distributing centre of trade for Eastern Turkish Arabia, and is likely to remain so. It is the limit of navigation for sea-going vessels. [937] B9 The great hindrance to Bussorah commercially is the bar of the Shatt-el-Arab, which, in its present condition, is only available for the passage of vessels of 15-foot draught at ordinary high tides and of 18 feet at “ high springs.” I attach a jdan of the bar copied from a survey made recently by Mr. Burgess, chief officer of the British India Steam Navigation Company, from which it can be seen that, with a very little dredging, the channel could be made available for vessels drawing 24 feet at high springs. The length of shallow water is at present but little over half-a-mile, and by com parison with previous charts it will be seen that the tendency is for the stream to cut a channel for itself through this shallow portion. If the channel were once cleared, very little assistance would be required to keep it so. Tf this were done the chief drawback to Bussorah as a commercial port would be removed. Merchandize, both export and import, is at present carried between Bussorah and Bagdad by shallow river steamers and native craft. It is unlikely that this mode of transport would be in any way affected by the railway which, under ordinary circumstances, would be unable to compete successfully in the matter of rates. The majority of the passengers would, however, probably prefer the rapid train service to the slower journey by boat. Politically, Bussorah would, I consider, be badly situated as the terminus of the railway, as it is on Turkish territory, and therefore under Turkish control for Customs and other regulations. In the event of war between Turkey and the Power owning the terminus and dominating the trade, it would be, for topographical reasons, a very difficult place to defend. By seizing and holding the river channel the Turks could sever communi cation with the open sea, which their adversaries would not be able to re-establish without great difficulty. Fao .—There would be no technical difficulty in connecting Pao with Bussorah by rail. It is situated on the right bank of the Shatt-el-Arab, about 8 miles from the bar. The line would have to skirt the date plantations on the side away from the river (a 5-foot embankment would suffice) and come down to the river just north of the telegraph station. At this point there is deep water (7 fathoms) close in to the shore extending for over a mile. Land at the station side would be expensive as it is all date plantations, but there are no engineering difficulties to overcome. The objections, from a railway point of view, which apply to Bussorah, apply equally to Pao, with the added objection that there is at present no trade there, and it is extremely unlikely that firms already established at Bussorah would remove to Pao; all their interests and connections with the native traders are in the former town, and there would be no advantages to counteract the increased cost of transport between Fao and Bussorah, which would be out of all proportion to the cost of transport between Bussorah and outside ports. lao also is on Turkish territory (although the land is mostly owned by the Sheikh of Koweit), and therefore liable to the same restrictions and regulations as Bussorah. The trade of Mohammerah on the Persian side of the Shatt-el-Arab has also to be taken into consideration, as it is likely to increase considerably when the communi cation between the upper Karun and the interior of Persia is improved as proposed. Steamers proceeding to Bussorah call at Mohammerah. The merchants of Mohammerah —a Persian port—would never transfer their interest to a Turkish port at Pao, so that steamers would still call there. l ao's one advantage over Bussorah is its proximity to the sea ; communication with it could lie more easily maintained in the event of trouble. Um-Kusr is the name of a small creek at the head of the Khor Abdullah. It is claimed by the Sheikh of Koweit, but the Turks have built a fort and maintain a small garrison about Z miles up from the mouth of the creek. The creek is about 3 miles long by half a mile broad, narrowing at the end. At about a mile from the entrance on the west bank there is a narrow strip of land lying above high water. It is about 300 yards by 30 yards, and separated from the general high ground by about 400 yards of shallow' sw'amp. The w r ater is deep close in shore, and a landing stage could be easily erected along it and connected3 to the high ground to the west, which could be made the site of the railway terminus. There would he no difficulty in bringing the alignment to this point from Zobeir by practically following the road. The chief advantages of Um-Kasr are that— 1. It is accessible at all times to ships drawing 18 feet, and, by a little dredging at the east end of Warba Island, this could be improved so as to make it accessible to ships drawing 21 feet. 2. Ships can get close to shore and be unloaded direct. 3. The creek is land-locked and protected from storms. The objections are— 1. The available combination of deep water and dry shore only extend for a short distance, about 300 yards, and considerable dredging and banking operations would have to be undertaken to improve it. 2. The creek is narrow, and would only accommodate a limited number of ships of any size. 3. Bussorah would still remain the trade centre. As noted above, the railway is unlikely to be able to compete successfully wdth the river traffic between Bagdad and Bussorah, and it would be considerably cheaper to ship goods direct at Bussorah than to rail them to Um-Kasr before doing so. There still remains the merchandize from above Bagdad which may be caught by the railway. If this was still carried by the railway to Bussorah it would probably be unloaded there in preference to incurring the extra railway freights to Um-Kasr. I have no information as to the amount of trade to be expected from above Bagdad. 4. There are no habitations at Um-Kasr and no business connections, so that it is unlikely to become a port of any size. 5. Special arrangements would have to be made for the protection of the port against raids. Warba Island is situated in the Khor Abdullah to the south-east of the Khor Um- Kasr. It is separated from the western mainland by the Khor Salem, a narrow creek 100 yards broad at the north end, widening with swamps to three-quarters of a-mile at high water at the south end. The Khor Abdullah to the south of Warba Island would afford a fine anchorage for a large number of ships, and is accessible to ships of 24 feet at any time ; it is land-locked and well protected from storms. The ground at the south-west corner of the island slopes steeply and there is deep water close in shore. The island is flat and sandy with low scrubby bushes, the general level is about 10 feet above high water, hard and dry. There is probably no fresh water obtainable, but brackish water should be found near the surface. The railway could be continued from Um-Kasr along near the shore skirting the high ground, cross the Khor Salem at its north end, and continue on to the south west corner of the island; the only obstacle is the crossing of the Khor Salem which could be effected with girders supported on screw T piles. Warba Island would be a better position for a railway terminus than Um-Kasr, as the anchorage is larger and the firm ground broad and continuous along the shore of the island. There is plenty of room for building: all materials would have to be brought to the place. All the objections on the score of trade applicable to Um-Kasr apply equally to Warba Island, and the trade of Bussorah is not likely to be transferred to this port. The difficulty of fresh water could be overcome by the use of condensing machinery, if the requirements warranted the expenditure. - Both Um-Kasr and Warba Island are claimed by the Sheikh of Koweit, and it would be possible to ensure that no unnecessary restrictions and Regulations should be imposed on the port. The country bordering the Khor Abdullah is low and swampy so that a hostile force could not effectively command the approaches to these ports. Warba Island would be more secure against raids than Um-Kasr.-- ^ 4 ? re » two P° ints , on the shore of Koweit Harbour which are available as possible sites for the terminus of the railway, viz • 1. El Kathama. 2. Bandar-es-Shuwaik. i Kathama is the name of the shore and anchorage at the west end of the arbour ; the anchorage is capable of accommodating a large number of ships of -4 teet draught. There is no deep water close in shore, and cargo would have to be t'mhvhour by meanS ° f ll ^ hterSj unless a P iev ot ‘ about a-mile is built out into The anchorage is well sheltered from the “ Shamal,” or north wind The shore consists of firm salty sand, sloping up towards the hills bordering the ha y bo V r * These llllIs terminate in abruptly broken sandstone cliffs, oU0 to /°. 0 feet which extend for several miles along the north shore. A good site for a station could be found on the slope below the cliffs. t0 . the broken and irre o ul ar nature of the cliffs it would he extremely dilhcult if not impracticable, to find an alignment to climb them ; and the approach to tA ivathama must be along the slope on the north shore. In order to effect this, the alignment from Zobeir would skirt the high ground Um j K : ds1 \ Y nd fobow do . wn to tbe west of the Khor Sabiya (which separates AuLrvan TAand from the mainland) and turn round on to the northern side of the harbour; this would all be easy going, practically a surface line throughout, and no engineering difficulties to overcome. &amp; ’ cbief Ejection to El Kathama as a railway terminus lies in the fact that, as mth Um-Kasr and Warba Island, there is no trade existing there, and would stand a i smaller cnance or competing with Bussorah owing to the increased lead. It is too far (19 miles) by road from Koweit to derive any benefit from the proximity or that town, and special arrangements would have to be made for the protection of the port against raids. Bandar-es-Sfiuwaik is a creek to the south-west of the town of Koweit, formed by die mainland on the east side, Kurein Island and the mud flat on the western side. It is about sea miles long by 4 cables broad, and has a depth of 36 feet throughout ^ C8 P* at th ? entrance, where it has a depth of 12 feet low-water springs, witb/a rise oi 12 feet, giving at least depth of 24 feet at high-water springs. Ibis could probably be much improved bv dredging. Inside of 12 feet right round Koweit, the bottom consists of a layer of rock h mud^nd^anfl 1 ^ )em ® bmestone with coral formation ; the rest of the bottom e™tf f the fai ’ ^ ° f the Creek could be utilized for ships as it at present / f l p aCmg , ,I100r 1 ln S P° sts both sides of the creek ; those to the east to 1Dteaded to nioor ships alongside the bank (as there is deep water right close up to it) and those on the mud bank to the west for warping ships in and out Further improvements could be added as required, but the entrance to the creek should be carefully buoyed for the deepest channels. The shore at this point is admirably adapted for a railway terminus : it slopes gradually to a flat plain 20 to 30 feet above high sea level; the soil is firm sand. Jr 1 Kafhama the alignment would pass Jehara and follow the road to Jvoweit. ^ ^nere arc no engineering difficulties to overcome. 111 tbe ^her instances, a railway at Koweit would have no effect on the trade ° -^ ussor ^h. 1 here is, however, at present a certain amount of trade between Koweit and the interior, and also between Bagdad and the interior direct; the railway between Bagdad and Koweit would considerably shorten the route and would probably catch most of the trade diverting it through Koweit. 1 The interior of Arabia is reported to be a richly cultivated country, which would probably repay opening up, and if it should in the future be decided to do this Koweit would be the nearest point on the Persian Gulf to start from. With proper communications trade would increase and, moreover, the trade between the interior and the Tied Sea w ould probably be diverted to the Persian Gulf if increased facilities were given. 1 .. m + a ^ owe ^ W0ldd Probably catch the major portion of the outside pilgrim ili c to Kerbela, and a continuation to the interior would reap the benefit of aA'ast pilgrim route to Mecca.The town itself would inevitably expand enormously under these influences. Agencies would he more readily established in a town than in an uninhabited spot like Um-Kasr or Warba Island, and the town would provide the accommodation necessary for native passengers. Owing to the proximity of the town the terminus could be easily protected from raids. As the port would be under British protection it would remain an open port, and he free from unnecessary regulations and restrictions. Fresh water could be obtained by condensing machinery. The entrance to the harbour should be lighted with the following lights :— 15 mile light, south-east end of Failaka Island, 15 mile light on Ras-el-Arz, 7 mile light on Ras-el-Ajuza, to enable the harbour to be entered at night. Conclusion. (a.) From an engineering point of view Warba Island is the best position for a railway terminus and port. I would place Um-Kasr next, and Fao third, with Koweit (Bandar-es-Shuwaik) fourth. There are no engineering difficulties to prevent Bussorah being made a terminus. Land along the river front would be expensive and ships cannot come close in shore, so that transhipment would have to be by lighters as at present. (b.) As regards trade Bussorah is undoubtedly the best position for the terminus, as it is the terminus of sea-going vessels and is capable of improvement. Any line beyond Bussorah to the Gulf would be practically a branch line; and after Bussorah, Koweit is the only place where any trade could be expected, at least for several years. The Power holding Bussorah as a port, would control the trade of north-east Arabia which is at present almost entirelv British. (Signed) E. W. S. MAHON. July 24, 1905.mm</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x0001b6_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/18/B165</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x0001b6</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/18/B165</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Report (with Maps) on the country adjacent to the Khor Abdullah, and places suitable as Termini of proposed Bagdad Railway, by Captain E W S Mahon, RE July 1905'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1905/1905</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-10-31T00:49:25</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (5 folios)</extent><extent>Foliation: The foliation for this description commences at f 13, and terminates at f 17, since it is part of a larger physical volume; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is also present in the bottom right-hand corner of the recto of each folio. These numbers are written in pencil, but are not circled. Pagination: This section of the volume also contains an original printed pagination sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The report, printed for the use of the Foreign Office, was compiled by Captain Edward Willoughby Sandys Mahon, Royal Engineer on 24 July 1905 to identify places suitable as termini of the Baghdad Railway. He advises Bussorah [Basra] as the best place, for strategic and commercial reasons.The report contains two maps:'Sketch Map of the Mouth of the Shatt-El-Arab' (f 15);'Koweit Harbour' (f 16).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Baghdad Railway</namePart></name></subject><name type="personal"><namePart>Edward Willoughby Sandys Mahon</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Shatt-el-Arab</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Bussora</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Koweit</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Railways</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x0001b6#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>