<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0001af_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T06:07:19.806Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">microfilmed document DO MOT PHOTOCOPY USEJ Dated. Behradun the 10th Habl'-uu-Thani 1350 (a4th | August 1931) yroin &amp; Taimur 'bin i'aisulo. Sultan of Muscat and Oraano To» Major T.C.rovrleo. Officiating Political Resident in the Persian Gulf• Bushire* fcV v After Compliments^ I have the honour to acknowledge receipt on the 22nd August 1931 of your letter dated the 17th August 1931 (8th Rahi f -us-Thani 1550). I understood what you mentioned therein from the beginning to the end and have likewise received the full powers documents drawn up ^ on my behalf for the modification of the treaties with my friends the two Governments of France %nd the United Btat^ of America as required by me* f f Yes,as I have already explained in iiiy letter dated the 12th Jamada-as-Thani 1349( 6th October 193 0) regarding viy reqviest for interference by my friend| the (British) Government in this matter by discussing it with the two Governmentso.l have approved the modification you senA vide drafts 11 A 11 and I signed the full powers documents and senJr three copies to the Secretary for foreign AfrHirs to the Government of India in the foreign and Political Department,Simla as desired by you, also a copy of this* reply of mine. I am thankful to you and offer my gratitude to the Government for their kindness in bestow ing attention and regard to the interests of the Muscat State^ Should the desired agreement be arrived at betv/een the empowered person representing me and the representative of my friends the two Governments namely the Republic of France and the Government of the United States of America then there would be no term in writing the modifications in the French language for the French1 2 Lj t /'and in English for the Government of the United States of America# I uhiil.I accept the sane^txid I send to you herewith a copy of It and sent another to Museate This is what was to be said and I always expect the continuance of frien^and unity betweerjboth sidesoI Dehradun the 10th Rabi'-us-Thani 1350(a4th August 193^ Taimur bin Faisulo.. Oultan of Muscat and Oman S^outaju His Sxoellency tVie Kiniatci.' for Foreign Affairs to the Government of India in the Foreigh and Political Bepartment* Sinilao, After Compliinentso hjW frttO, U» I have the^forward to Your Excellency six copies of full powers documents in connection with the modifications of the treaties existing 'between the Sultan of Muscat and Oman,and the two Governments of France ^nd the United States of America which,as desired 'by the officiating Political Hesldent in the Persian Gulf,Bushire,are to sent 'by ] me to you early^These I have signed and have put my seal on them®. I also send to you a copy of my letter to the officiating Political Resident in the Persian Gulf &gt; Bushire for your information#. Dated* From* JL.0 *Hhereae # for the butter treating of ami arranging certain matter© which are now in dlecuaeion, or which my cone into di ecu anion, between u© and the ^reaident of the i &lt;*renoh T^epublic relating to Comsaeree and navigation* have Judged It expedient to Invest a fit peraon with mil Power to conduct the said diocusslon on our part; mov ye 9 therefore, that we. repoaing eapeciaX Trust and Confideiicc la the wledoa. Loyalty, diligence, and Circumspection of of Hie Majesty the iClng of areat Britain, Ireland ami he Bxltlah inmlnlona beyond the 6eaa # j^peror of India, have naned, ©ade, conatltuted am appointed, as we do by these Presents naiae, mice, conatitute and appoint hl» uur undoubted Cosaalaaloner, Procurator, am Pleni potentiary for the purpose aforesaid. Giving to him all manner of fower and Authority to treat, adjust, and conclude with such Minister or Ministers as fflay be vested with similar Power and Authority on the part of the President of the French Hepubllo any Treaty, Convention, or Agreement that may tend to the attainment of the above-mentioned end, and to sign for Us, and In Our name, everything so agreed upon and concluded, and to do and transact all such other matter® as may appertain thereto, in as ample manner and form, and with e^ual force and efficacy, as We wuraelvea could do, if personally present7 r present; Kngaging and - xohiuIih ;. upon our word, that whatever things shUX be so tren«acted atKl conoXudsa by our eald ^oimissloner # Procurator, anal FXenipotentiary ohaXX* Subject if neaeseniry to Our &gt;ia tin cation, be agreed to, aoknowIeUgefl and accepted, by Us In the fuXltrst manner, and that we elXX nerer suffer, either In the vihoXe or in part, any person i&amp;atsoever t© infringe the same, or aet emtrary thereto, as f&amp;r a® it lies in our j^ownN Xn witness hereof its have caused our ueaX to be affixed to thsoe ^resents, which we have signed with uur hand. Given at ydP*^ the day of TfcUu, in tii® lear of tlm Mejira% Whereas* for the better treating of and arranging certain matters which are now in discussion, or which may come into discussion, between Us and the President of the United States of America relating to Commerce and MaTiga~ tion, we hare Judged it expedient to invest a fit person with Full -Power to conduct the said discussion on Our part Know ye, therefore, that We, reposing especial Trust and Confidence in the wisdom. Loyalty, uiligence, and Circumspection of of Hie Majesty the King of Great Britain, Ireland and the British Dominions beyond the Seas, Kmperor of India, hare named, made, constituted and appointed, as we do by these Presents name, maJce, constitute and appoint him Our undoubted Commissioner, Procurator, and Plenipotentiary for the purpose aforesaid* Giving to him all manner of Power and Authority to treat, adjust, and conclude with such Minister or Ministers as may be vested with similar Power and Authority on the part of the President of the United States of America any Treaty, Convention, or Agreement that may tend to the attainment of the above-mentioned end, and to sign for Us, and in Our name, everything so agreed upon and concluded, and to do and transact all such other matters as may appertain thereto, in as ample manner and fozm, and with equal force and efficacy, as We Ourselves could do, ifIf personally present; Engaging and Promising, upon Uur Word, that whaterer things shall be so transaoted and concluded by Our said Coxamissioner, Procurator, and Plenipotentiary shall, subject if necessary to Our Ratification, be agreed to, acknowledged and accepted by Us in the lUllest manner, and that we will never suffer. either in the whole or in part, any person whatsoever to infringe the same, or act contrary thereto, as far as it lies in Our power* In witness whereof We have caused our Seal to be affixed to these Presents, which we have signed with Our Hand. Given at xfit-cl*' /\0the /Xz day of in the Year of the Hejira and in the Year of uur ReigniSLAELJ^ COMglSSMTlAL, Ho. S'.225-11/29,, BUSHiR' RS8105NCY. Dfih ih/n CO^ri ; itH Th\I rit00B0&amp; A copy of the undermentioned paper is forwarded to the Hon f de the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf for information, with reference to his letter So. 499*3 of 1951 # dated the 17th August 1931o By order, etc.# Assistant Secretary to the Government of India* Foreign and Political Department, * Simla, The J/r/' August 1931* Letter to the Under Secretary of State for India&gt; So, J.225- H/29, dated the August 1931o/ /O o&amp;yj.i no. *\aa6-Va». From The foreign .ieoretary to Ui« Governtnent of X a 4 i^t To the Under a&amp;cretaxy oi' utate i'or ia4i»t * Political ^epaitiaentt inaia )ffic # London* 3 A/- Uated iiala, tiie August 1951* 3ucj«cti- ^vision of uscat tariff* v 1 str, ^ V Itii reference to letter froo* yi® uon 1 Die tne political asiaent in the Persian .ulf» ^o» 499*3 of 1951# aatea the 17th August 19311 copy of which was seat to you with my weekly letter ..o» 118(a) 4« » dated the 24th ^uguat 1951 # I m directed to forward four copies of the docwaent of full powers duly signed by Mis ui^hness tiie Dultsm of Muscat together with a copy of the Sultan's Arabic letter to a J or xowle (with translation)! in wuieh Uiss sultan agrees to the texts of the trench and American treaties ceixig in j'rencn and nglish respectively* I am to add that the word •Koyal* has been omitted from the document of full powers as in the opinion of the overn^ient of India although it appears in the Muscat American treaty of 1833 it is not properly applicable to tne 3ultan of kuscat* X have the honour to be« Sir# Your most obedient servant f 3d/- M. B. Howell, Jfereign &gt;ecretfiiry to Uie Governeient of inaiaF-2. DOMINIONS OFFICE, DOMING STREET 8237/9. 7th August,1931. / V Sir, y With reference to your letter No. P.Z.4736/31 of the 4th August, regarding the proposed revision of the tariff provisions of the Coninercia.1 Treaty of 1891 with Muscat, I am directed by Mr. Secretary Thomas to transmit to you, to be laid before the Secretary of State for India, the draft of a despatch which it is proposed to send to His Majesty's Governments in Canada, the Union of South Africa and the Irish Free State on the subject. It is also proposed to send a copy of the despatch to His Majesty's Government in Newfoundland and the Government of Southern Rhodesia, 2. I am to enquire whethet Mr. Wedgwood Benn concurs in the terras of this draft. 3. A similar letter is being sent to the Foreign Office. I am, etc. (Sd.) R.p. 'l s eman. P UNDER SECRETARY OF STATS, INDIA OFFICE.it ■ DRAFT AN AD A frQT 07 SOUTH APRIGA ^ Downing Street ffRH PlglS STATS August, 1931. (t y &gt; ' 0 o-? Y» f r ' ull , With referejace (To 1 only) my despatch No.421 of the 28th of July. (To 2 op I v the Governor General's desbstcir¥b. 174 oT'tTie v 20th of April,1922. (To 3 only) my aespatcii Ko. lob ol the 2otli of JuiyT' on the subject of the Commercial Treaty between Great Britain and Muscat, signed on the 18th of March,1891, I have the honour to state, for the information of His Majesty's Government in Canada ? that the question of the Union of South Africa the Irish Free State. the revision of the tariff provisions of the Treaty has been raised. 2. Article 6 of that Treaty provides that the Sultan shall peimitted 'to levy a duty of entry not exceeding 5% on the value of al^ goods and merchandise, of whatever description, imported|by sea from foreign countries into His I-Iighness's dominions and no higher import duty s'nall be claimed from British subjects than that which is paid by subjects or citizens of the most favoured nation'. Article 3 of the Treaty of 1833 between the United States of America IAmerica and Muscat provides that 'Vessels of theUnlted States of America entering any port wltnln the Sultan's dominions shall pay no more than 5% duties on the cargo landed', and Article 4 of the same Treaty that 'American citizens shall pay no other duties on export or Import tonnage than the nation the most favoured shall pay'. Article 10 of the Treaty of 1844 between Prance and Muscat provides that 'no duty exceeding 5% shall he levied on goods imported by French vessels... If a vessel of other nrtions Imports any goods into the territories of the Sultan of Muscat, and pays less duty than 5%, the same duty only shall be levied on similar goods Imported by a French vessel ' 3. The continued existencebf Muscat as an independent State is largely due to the financial and moral support of His Majesty's Government in the United Kingdom, who are thus specially interested in its position. The financial situation in the State, which has for some time been serious, has lately become critical, and careful examination has led to the conclusion that a relaxation of the restrictions imposed by the Treaties referred to above, which would admit of an increase in the rate of tariff on Imported goods, alone affords any prospect of improvement. A formal request for ohe revision of the tariff provisions of the tiiree treaties in Question has been received from theItj the Sultan, and the French Govemraent have intimated their readiness to consider proposals on the subject. The Government of the United States of America on being approached indicated their readiness to agree to the grantof full tariff autonomy to Muscat in return for the grant of general most favoured nation treatment. But investigation showed that the difficulties involved in acceptanceof this demand were likely to he so considerable that, particularly in view of the acute financial position, it would be preferable, at any rate for the moment, to concentrate on securing the concurrenceof France and the United States of America in an increase in the maximum import duties leviable by Muscat under her treaties with these countries, 4. His Majesty's Ambassadors at Paris and Washington have accordingly been instructed to take the matter up with the French and United States Governments on the basis of the despatches enclosed. Having regard to the most-favoured-nation provisions of the Muscat Treaties with France and the United States of America, it is clear that, were the Governments of those countries to accept these proposals, no benefit would ensure to Muscat unless a corresponding modification were approved of the tariff restrictions embodied in the Treaty with Great Britain of 1891. British and Indian trade in any case far outweighs in importance theimportance the trade with Muscat carried in French and American bottoms, and tariff modifications wMch, while covering French and United States ships, left it in its present position would he of'little real value to Muscat. In these circumstances, in the event of France and the United States of Merica agreeing to an increase in the maximum tariff rates leviable from 5 to 10% (25% in the case ■ of alcoholic liquors and tobacco) His Majesty's Government in the United Kingdom are, for their part, prepared to modify the tariff provisions of the Trea/ty of 1891 ,to ^ corresponding extent . 5. If the outcome of the negotiations with France and the United States are successful, it is proposed, subject to any observations which His Majesty's Government in Canada may desire to offer, to proceed with the proposed mocfification of the Treaty of 1891. 6. This despatch is being sent to Canada No. the Union of South Africa No. and the Irish Free State No, I have, etciq to* 1126# K 4045/267/91) ?OH IGH OPFIC . . 1. 11th August # 1931. \ Y' lr / With reference to my despatch Ho* 1567 of the 12th MoTember last. I have to Inform you that the Muscat State was end ©ed in Sir Lindsay's despatch No. 1590 of the ^th October. 2. As a result, the Council have come to the conclusion that they cannot accept the provisions ewhodied In the last sentence of the amended version of Article 3 of the treaty of 1855 'between the United . .tates and Muscat (article 1 of the United tates Government's draft new treaty) which the tate Department oropose. It will he observe ti fro® the enclosed copy of a telegram from the Political ealdent in the Persian Gulf to the Government of India that the Muscat tate uouncil see object ion to the gx'unt of mo et-favour e do nation treatment to United tatea citizens in respect of residence and establishment, since it would oermit United tates missionaries etc. to reside wherever Britlah Indian merchants re established. Ihe conditiona in many parts of the Muscat tate are such that it would be imoracticable to all w non-Moslems to reside there. The tate Council are also onnosed both to the grant to United ; tates citizens of moat-favoured-nation treatment in respect of the adminiatratlon of •• 0 * Osborne, i^sq. , C.M.G., etc. , etc., etc. Washington,of Justice (whioh would pre&amp;a .ubly involve the concoasion to them of the extraterritorial right■ enjajed by British subjectsj, and to the proposed provision regarding the exploitation of natural r©sources* 3. Sine® the madlflcatloa of the prorifsion© in treaties btotwrnn Muscat and foreign pow«r@ dealing with tlm aBadMW tariff- rata was firi^t mooted, a further rmrked deterioration hae taken place in tim fXnanm&amp; of Maacat* Efforts have been made in the past year to reduce expenditure wherever posaihle. Bone the less a substantial budget deficit seeme certain. The necessity of increasing the tariff-rate has thus become one of considerable urgency. 4. In th®t?e clrcametaneeE it is considered beet to concentrate, for the time being at an,? r--te t on securing the simple modification in the existing treaty ^rovisione neceasary to permit of an increase in the 'maximum rates of the Muecat tariff. It in therefore proposed that the United States CsOTernBent should be approached with a viewf to obtain their consent to such a modification of article ^ of the Onited States - Muscat fre&amp;ty of IB'M &amp; b will permit of the iery by the Muscat St&amp;te of a duty of ten i&gt;er cent on all good® Bate alcoholle liquors and tobacco, for which a maximum rate of twenty fi^e per cent le now proposed. 0. In view however of the fact that the United states aov^rnment'e proposal for the grant of tariff autonomy to uscat in return for general moet-firrotired-nation treatment for United State© citizens etc. wae put forward only after consultation with lie Majeety's Government and with the Muscat State, and in view moreover, of the fact that the objections taken by the Muscat StateII 7. State Gouneil to th© United States Government 1 &amp; draft treaty arim from a aisinclination to extend to United States eitizons privileges enjoyed by British nationals, the question of the manner in which thi® new proposal shoald be ©mbmitted to the United States Government is somewhat delicate, 6 # to enter into details as to the provisions of the United States draft treaty which are nnaoceptable t» likely merely to lead either to objections on the part of the United States Government or to . ossibly embarrMsimg gE-geationa for overcoming the difficulties seen by the .iuaeat Council* while leaving you discretion on this point, I coaeider therefore that the best course would be merely to inform the State department that after a earefui examination of their draft treaty the Muscat State Council have reluctantly come to the- conclusion that the negotiation of such a treaty would present a variety of difficulties, the solution of which would inevitably .involve gre % delay, and might well entail negotiations with other governments, and that since, on the other hand - tor the reasons explained in fare graph 3 above - an. increase in the Muscat tariff has no^ become a matter of more iminediate urgency, it is desired to negotiate, in the most expeditious manner oesible, the simple modification of the existing treaty between the Onlted states and Muscat referred to in par ./.graph 4 above. You may add that His Majesty*8 Government in the 'Onlted jtingdom are, for their part prepared, subject to the concurrence of the United States Oovernment and the French Oevernmant, who are aleo being approached in a aimilar ^enee, in the necesaary treaty modification, correspondingly to modify their own treaty of 1891 with the State of Muscat.7» Should it be possible for the Baited States Qorertm&amp;nt to consent that thia modification ahou'id he effected by a simple exchange of notes, whiHi wouia. Wmm operative at cmce 9 this method womlt doubt lees bet raeet the ease* in that event it would appear ©mffiaieat that they should address to you a note to that effect, which should also embody the amended version of Article 10 of the Treaty of 1833 oontaimd in article 1 of the draft treaty enclosed herein. la your note of reply ^ou would thou merely inform the United State© Government that lis Majesty's Qoverimient in the United KiJ^dom, acting at the request and on behalf of the uultmx of Muecat, agree to the modification of the treaty mt forth in the united States government *e note# If the United Statee Goveriment are able to eeiiour in thia aoura#,, you should eubmit to m for approval drafts of the aote^ which they would be ready to exchange# B* If, however, thle \&gt;rooedura Should be impracticable, you should propose to the United states QOTerraent the conclusion of a treaty In the form enclosed herein, to be accompanied by an exchange of notes bringing the treaty into force provisionally upon signature in anticipation of ratification# Smek a treaty eould most easily be signed bj you on behalf of Muscat and rteps are being taken to furnish you pith full powers for thle purpose, lesaed by the ultan of Museet# The (rovernmont of India are consulting lie Highness on the suggestion that the treaty, if negotiated, should be drawn up in the English language only and shall inform you in due course of the reeult* 9# k copy of a despatch which ie being addressed to lisHis kajesty f b in ^arin regarding th© propoeod modification of the treaty of 1844 between Franoe and Muscat is enclosed hereia for your iafomatloa# I tm, with gr@at truth, Slr t lour obedient Servant t (for the Secretary of Stat#) '\i:J^-grj3d) O. W. BAXTER.z /3^q- ^7/A lAii ! I Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. For the laformation of he Political Resident, Bushire^ I ndia O ffice, W hitehall, L ondon , S.W. 1. A copy has been sent also to the 4098 maat of India.CONS TDBNTI AL. • L h KO. J.225-K/29. Be? J ' ^iO|NCYj On it / 3 f ^ n/^/: GGNriDcH .iw i-.u j A copy of the undermentioned papers is forv/arded to the Eon*'ble the political Eesident in the Persian Gulf for information. * Copy forwarded under Bushire P.L.No 614-S of 14/9/31 to Political Agent, Muscat for information. By order, etc», Assistant Secretary to the Govermient of India. Foreign and Political Department, Simla. The ^/^September 1951. /\ f! 1. Letter from the Dominions Office to the India Office, Ko.8237/9, dated the 7.8.31 with enclosure. 2. Letter from the india Office to the Dominions office, Ho. p.5079/31, dated 12th August 1931,,. h vV- (with 1 s .C.).'hh &gt;1 CONFIDENTIAL c No. r.225-N/29 nTRE^DtNCYj Ret Dmt. /v/ ? / / 2 7?/ GCHriOis A copy of the undermentioned paper is forwarded to the Hon^le the Political Resident in the Persian Gull for information in continuation of endorsement from the Government of India in the foreign and Political Department No. P.Z&amp;b dated the 3lst August 1931. By order, etc», Assistant Secretary to the Government of India Foreign and Political Department, Simla. The September l9 r 61. &lt;y y 1 , / V •X - • Despatch from the Foreign office to His / esty's Ambassador, France, No. 2008, dated the 1.' lith August 1931, %ith enclosure. ' C0Py nnri!f de ^ 1°^ Political , Mus cat, for information, under out P.L.No 627-S of 24/9/31 1*1th 1 Spare Copy),COWlDmTlAL . ITo. F.225-1T/29 BUSHiRE RcSIDtNC V. ft 61 Ai. ML fitutjoio ^ A copy of the undermentioned paper is forwarded to the Hon^le the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf for information in continuation of endorsement from the Government of India in the foreign and Political Department No .F. 225-13/29, dated the 9 th September 1931• V By order, etc. } (z' 1 t — Foreign and Political Department, Simla» _cr The 3^ September 1931. Letter from the Foreign Office to the Dominions Office, No.E.4110/267/91, dated the 26th August 1931. (with 1 S.C.) CoRy forwarded to the Political Agent, ISusTfat, under P.L.No 659-S of 9/10/S1 for information.■ 'In,3 Confiden tial lTo.F.225-ir/ 2 9 BUSH '^E /V Dsie... RESIDENCY. ! A-^7 GGHflOfiThii SECoiJDS- A copy of the undermentioned paper is forwarded to the Hon x ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, for information, in continuation of endorsement from the Govern ment of India in the Foreign and Political Department, No. J , «22 d -H/29, dated the 30th September 1931. K/ By order, etc., r .. Assistant Secretary to the Government of India. \\\ ^ Foreign and Political Department. New Delhi; The October 1931. Letter from the India Office to the Foreign Office, No. P.Z.3807/31, dated the 18th September 1931. ( 7/i til ±- spa re c opyIndia Office ®hi tehall, Ho.P.Z.3807/31 Sir, London, S.W.I. 18th September . J ^ |C| With reference to your letter a.4045/267/91, dated 12th August regarding the proposed modification of the Muscat Treaties with France and the United States of America, I am the information of the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, copy of a letter received from the Government of India, togeth with a translation of a letter addressed by His Highness the Sultan of Muscat to the officiating Poli'tical Resident at Bushire, from which it will be observed that His Highness concurs in the suggestion tliat the proposed new treaty with France should be in French and that with the United States of America in English. I am at the same time to forward Full Powers signed by His Highness to enable His Majesty's Representatives at Paris and Washington to sign the new treaties on his behalf and to request that, with Lord Reading 1 s* concurrence, they may be, transmitted to His Majesty's Representatives at those places in the event of it transpiring that the Governments of France and the United States of America are unwilling to agree to the desired modification of their existing treaties with Muscat being effected by a simple exchange of notes. directed by the Secretary of State for India to forward, for I am, Sir, Your obedient servant, Sd. J.C.Walton. To The Under Secretary of State, Foreign Office¥ A copy of the undermentionea papers is forwarded to the Hon'tle the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf for information in continuation of endorsement from the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, No.F.225-N/29, dated the 28th October 1931. r _ i By order, etc., \ f/M Assistant Secretary to the Government of India. M reign and Political Department, New Delhi, The ///£ November 1931. 1. Letter from British Embassy, Washington, to the Foreign Office, No.1410, dated the 10th September 1931, with enclosure. 2. Memorandum from British Embassy, Paris, to the Foreign Office, No.1040(55/4/31), dated the 29th September 1931, with enclosure and its translation. (with i' s,o.KP.Z. 6128/31) Enclosures in Foreign Office covering letter No. E 4804/267/91, dated 25th September, 1931. ♦ 1410 ^^ BRITISH EL'BASSY, WASHINGTON, D.C., September 10th, 1931. My Lord, With reference to your predecessor's despatch No. 1126 (E 4045/267/91) of the 11th ultimo I have the honour to transmit herewith a copy of the note regarding the proposed modification of the Treaty of 1833 between the United States and Muscat, which I left to-day with the Under Secretary of State. 2. A new Treaty could not of course be concluded without the consent of Congress which is not likely to meet before December next and might even then defer consideration of the matter for a considerable time, I am by no means sure that, even with the best will, the Department of State can negotiate sn exchange of notes of the kind suggested without Congressional approval, but I urged upon Mr. Castle the need for early action in the matter and he promised to let me know shortly what the United States Government could do to meet the wishes of His Majesty's Government in the United Kingdom. I have the honour to be, ' with the highest respect, Your Lordship's most obedient, humble Servant, (Sgd.) D G OSBORNE fMost Honourable The Marquess of Reading, G.C.B., G,C.S.I., Etc., etc., etc., H.M. Minister. OAv 2,4 j 1 OCT. 1 U- FROM StCRETARY, POLITICAL AND PHOR ET DEM'. INDIA OFFICE j]mo« 304, Sir: With reference to Sir R. Lindsay's note Mo. 377 of October 7th last I have the honour to inform you that I have now received a reply from His Majesty's Principal Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs in regard to the draft of the Treaty which the United States G-overnment are prepared to conclude with the Sultan of Muscat for the purpose of modifying the provisions of Article III of the Treaty of 1833 between the United States and Muscat. 2. I am instructed to state that after a careful examination of the draft treaty the Muscat State Council have reluctantly come to the conclusion that the negotiation of such a treaty would present a variety of difficulties the solution of which would inevitably involve great delay and might well entail negotiations with other Governments. 3. Since the modification of Article III of the Treaty of 1833 between the United States and Muscat was first suggested, a further marked deterioration has taken place in the finances of uscat. Efforts have been made in the past year to reduce expenditure wherever possible. Nevertheless a substantial budget deficit seems certain and the necessity of increasing the tariff rate has thus became one of considerable urgency. 4. In these circumstances it is earnestly desired to negotiate in the most expeditious manner possible a simple modification of the existing provisions of Article III of the Treaty of 1833, which would permit of the levy by the Muscat State of a duty of ten per cent on all goods save alcoholic liquors and tobacco for which a maximum rate of twenty five pei cent is now proposed. His Majesty's G-overnment in the United Kingdom hope that the united States Government will consent to this modification being effected by a simple exchange of notes which would become operative at once. They are for their part prepared/3* prepared, subject to the concurrence of the United States Government and the French Government, who are also being approached in a similar sense, correspondingly to modify their own Treaty of 1891 with the State of Muscat. I have the honour to be, with the highest consideration, Sir, Your most obedient, humble servant, (Sgd.) D.G. Osborne, His Majesty's Minister. Honourable henry L. Stimson, Secretary of State of the United States, Washington, D.C,1040. »/4/31) His Majesty's Representative at Paris presents his compliments to the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs and has the honour to transmit to him the under-mentioned, documents. British Embassy, Paris 29th September 1951 Beference to previous correspondence: Foreign Office despatch No.2008 (S.4045/267/91) of August 11th, 1951. Description of Enclosure Name and Date SuhJect From the Ministry for Foreign Affairs, 29th September, 1931. Proposed modification of Treaty of 1844 'between France and Muscat. ' ' ) 'J- A ch! Uvf T ranslation, Ministry for Foreign Aftairs. French Bepubiic. Paris, the 29th Septeinber 1931 • By note No.513 dat^ea the 17th August 1931, the British Embassy informed the Ministry for Foreign Affairs with reference to the note which was addressed to them 'by the latter on the 15th October 1930, of the desire expressed 'by the Government of Muscat regarding the proposed modification of article 10 of the treaty of the 17th November 1844, for the enhancement of import duties to a maximum of 10 % on all goods except alcholic 'beverages and tohacco, on which a maximum import duty of 25^ is suggested. At the same time, the British Embassy intimated that, subject to acceptance of these modifications 'by the French Government and that of the United States, the British Govt* would 'be prepared, on their side, to modify their treaty with Muscat accordingly. The Ministry for Foreign Affairs has the honour to inform the Embassy that, subject to acceptance by the United States, the French Government is prepared to accept the proposed modification, except in regard to all alholic beverages. In respect of the latter, they are of opinion that the 25^ duty suggested should be applicable only to beverages of 25 proof and above. They are however prepared to accept the suggestion made by the Embassy in regard to the procedure for the modification of the treaty and they have no objection to the amendment being made by a simple exchange of letters, when the Governments concerned are agreed as to the text of these documents. The British Embassy, Paris.'^ b if-o CONFIDENTIAL. ^ No,F. /(ij /$■ I t A copy of the undermentioned paper is forwarded to the Hon t 'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, for information. i % By order, etc., (/yw' Assist^mt secretary to the Government of India- eign and Political Department, Few Delhi j n^' The ' November 1931. 1. Despatch from the Foreign Office, to British Embassy, Paris, Ko.2477, dated the 7th October 193l # 2.Despatch from the Foreign Office to British Embassy, Washington, ITo # l592, dated the 7th October 1931. ZtrifUA 1 (0 *iM } flu. fv. U]- J. ^ 7- -f (With 1 spare copy).Ko.2477, (B. 4 803/267/91) Q$ Foreign Office, S.W.I. 7th October 1931, My Lord, With reference to my predecessor^ despatch Ho.2008 of the 11th August, in regard to coranercial relations 'between Prance and Muscat, T transmit to you the accompanying copy of a letter from the India Office on the subject. 2. Your Lordship will observe that His Highness the Sultan of Muscat has concurred in the suggestion that, if the French Government prefer that the proposed modification of the Muscat tariff should be effected by means of a treaty in the form enclosed in Mr. Henderson f s despatch under reference, that treaty should be in the French language alone. 3. I also enclose the Full Powers, signed by the Sultan of Muscat, under which you are empowered to sign the treaty on behalf of the Sultan, in the event of that procedure being preferred by the French Government. The name and designation of the person to whom the Full Powers have been issued have been left blank for subsequent insertion so that delay be avoided if you should happen to be absent from Paris when the treaty is ready for signature. His Excellency The Right Honourable Lord Tyrrell, G.C. m .G . ,£.G.:B., etc., etc., etc., Paris. I am, etc., (For the Secretary of State) Sd. C.w. BaxterNo.1392 (E 4803/267/91) Foreign Office, S.W.I. 7th October 1931. Sir, With reference to my predecessor*8 despatch No.1126 of the 11th August, in regard to commercial relations between the United States and Muscat, I transmit to you the accompanying copy of a letter from the India Office on the subject. 2. You will observe that His Highness the Sultan of Muscat has concurred in the suggestion that, if the United States Government prefer that the proposed modification of the Muscat tariff should be effected by means of a treaty in the form enclosed in Mr. Henderson^ despatch under reference, that treaty should be in the English language alone. 3. I also enclose the Full Powers, signed by the Sultan of Muscat, under which you are empowered to sign the treaty on behalf of the Sultan, in the event ^of that procedure being preferred by the United States Government. The name and designation of the person to whom the Full Powers have been issued have been left blank for subsequent insertion so that delay be avoided if you are no longer in charge of His Ma t jesty , s Embassy when the treaty is ready for signature. I am, etc., (For the flfts Secretary of State) Sd. C.W. Baxter, F.H •A. G.Osborne, Esq. , C.M.G., etc., etc., etc.. Washington.BRITISH KMBAS8Y, /' ^ •' WASHINGTON, D.C. t 6385/267/91) | j ■ | , -• ■ October 15th, 19s1 I ^ - Ltrt i Bear Kastem Pepartlent, | Our despatch No» 1608 of today's date about Muscat. It may be useful to review the possibllitiee as we see them from here. (l) We feel that the remarks of Mr.Cotton as f V ^j reported in our despatch No. 960 of June 15th, 1950, | and his letter of which a copy was enclosed with our ^ K despatch No.966 of June 16th, 1930, were intended as a hint to the Muscat Government (and to H.M.G.) to go ahead and make 'limited, non~discriminatory H increases in duties on goods imported into Muscat, leaving the question of modifying United States Treaty rights for subsequent consideration. United States trade with and interest in Muscat are so small that the State Department might perhaps have obliged us by failing to protest# Mr#Cotton, however, was rather inclined, to throw out suggestions of this kind in his efforts to be helpful, without perhaps taking full account of the difficulties the^ might cause, and it was no doubt the safest course to try and get the U.S.Government to agree to a new treaty, as you instructed us to do in your despatch No.1162 of August 5th, 1950. Subsequent correspondence has led to the present note, which shows that the State Department is now only prepared to give assurances that no objection would be offered ern Department, Foreign Office, London, S.W.i. . ^ f- MlHb offered to the collection of higher duties on American goods imported into Muscat. (a) If the Muscat State Council is in a position to negotiate a treaty along the lines suggested 'by the U.S.Government # (b) pending approval or rejection of the treaty by the United States Senate, (c) on the understanding that the Muscat State Council would, in its turn, furnish assurances that pending the same period American nationals in Muscat would receive the treatment specified in the proposed new treaty. In other words, it is no longer possible to act on Cotton's original limit without running counter to the expressed wishes of the U.S.Oovermaent. (2) We feel very doubtful if we shall ever succeed in getting the State Department to present to Congress for approval any new treaty which does not embody general most- favoured treatment for American nationals. (3) It seems to us conceivable that the wording of the old treaty affords a loophole for raising duties on American goods imported into Muscat without infringing American Jegal rights. Article III of the treaty of 1833 says that 'Vessels of the United States entering any port within the Sultan's dominions shall pay no more than five per cent duties on the cargo landed....' and the whole article seems to us to refer only to goods landed from American vessels, not to goods of American origin. The effect of Article 10 of the French treaty seems to be much the same. Perhaps there are large numbers of French vessels trading to Muscat and perhaps it is important for revenueM-l revenue purposes to be able to raise the duties on goods landed from these veBeels. If such Is the case, then it wouk; seem necessary to secure a modification of treaty rights, since Article 10 of the French treaty gives most-favoured- nation rights to French vessels ©nd their cargoes. But if ■/'•j such is not the case, and if, as we believe, very few : ■ j/i ' American or French vessels ply to the Persian Gulf» then it would seem possihle to raise the outies on American and French goods imported into Muscat on vessels of other nationality without infringing American or French treaty rights. (4) Yet another way of getting round American rights without negotiating a new treaty was suggested in our telegram No. 163 of April 8th, 1930. Coula we not argue by analogy V from the Convention of Saint Germain that the limitation imposed by the treaty of 1853 on the right of the Sultan of Muscat to raise duties on goods imported into his territory is now obsolete, and that he cannot be expected to confer on U.S.nationals exclusive rights which they do not enjoy under the treaty of 1833 in exchange for the consent of the U.S. Government to the removal of this limitation? Perhaps these suggestions, which we offer very tentatively, are futile; they are only inspired by the desire to be helpful and by the feeling that it might be possible to circumvent an obstacle difficult to surmount by a frontal attack. Yours ever, CHANCKRY.Confidential, No.P.225-H/29. A copy of the undermentioned paper is forwarded to the Hon'ble Lieutenant Colonel H.V.Biscoe, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, for inf onaa tion in continuation of endorsement from the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, No* P.225-13/29, dated the 1st December 19 31. /*3 By order, etc.. Assistant Secretary to tlie Government of India Foreign and Political Department. Mew Delhi; The ^ ^December 19 31. Letter from the British Embassy, Washington, No. 16 08, dated the 15th October 19 31, with enclosure . (With l spare copy). with enclosure (Copy/forwarded to the Political Agent, Muscat, under P.L # No.0.40 of l^th December 1931),Ho. 1608. British Bmbaasy, W* sh i ngton, D. G • &gt; My Lord, October 16th, 1931 I have the honour to transmit herewith copy of the reply of the United States Government to the note of v^iich a copy was enclosed with my despatch Ho. 1410 of September 10th last, regarding the proposed modification of the Treaty of 1833 between the United States and Muscat. Z* It will be observed that, according to the present note, 'it is not the policy of the United States Government to negotiate new treaties providing for the levying of specific rates of import duty on goods of American origin 0 , and that the United States Government 'would be prepared to consider the modification of article III of the treaty of 1833 only on the basis of most favoured-nation treatment.' It seems clear from the context that most-favoured-nation treatment should, in the State Departments view, include most-fa vour ed-na tion treatment of United States nationals in respect of the matters specified in the Departments note of October 4th, 1930. 3» In these circumstances no useful purpose would, presumably, be served by adopting the procedure suggested in paragraph 8 of your despatch Ho.1126(E4045/267/91) of August 11th last, and proposing to the United States Government the conclusion of a treaty in the form enclosed therein. 4. I should be glad to receive instructions as to the reply which I should return to the present note. I have the honour to be, with the highest respect. The Most Honourable The Marquess of Reading, G.G.3., 35tc., Eto., Etc. My Lord, Your Lordship's most obedient, humble servant, Sd. D.G.Osborne, H. M.Minis ter . 0.3., G.G.S.I.,5° Department of State '; Washington, sir » October 10,1931. I have received your note No» 304 of September 9, 1931, with further reference to the proposed modification of Article III of the Treaty of 1833 between the United States and Muscat# It is noted that the Muscat State Council has come to the ❖ conclusion that the negotiation of the draft treaty enclosed A v &lt;V \with the Department's note of October 4, 1930, would present difficulties and that His Majesty^ Government hopes that this Government will be prepared to consent to a modification of the provisions of Article III by means of an exchange of notes which would become operative at once* The Department fully appreciates the desirability of enabling the Muscat State to increase its revenues in order that it may proceed in its orderly development* As was pointed ^ V ^ ^ out in the Department's note of May 23, 1930, this Government has no objection in principle to the increase of customs duties in Muscat, provided that such duties are non-discriminatory* In view of constitutional requirements, however, the United States is not in a position to enter into an exchange of notes the purpose of which is to amend an existing treaty. Such a purpose could be effected only by the conclusion and ratification of a new treaty. It is hoped therefore that the Muscat State Council will be able to reconsider the possibility of negotiating such a new treaty along the lines of the draft submitted with the Depart ments note of October 4, 1930, in which case the Department To i/viA^I w0uld Mr. F.D.G.^sborne, C.M.G., Minister Plenipotentiary, Charge d*Affaires ad interim of Great Britain. (.»/would be glad to consider any minor amendments of the draft wiiich the Council might desire to propose. It should be pointed out, however, that it is not the policy of this Govern ment to negotiate new treaties providing for the levying of specific rates of import duty on goods of American origin, and that it would be prepared to consider the modification of Article III of the treaty of 1833 only on the basis of most- favoured-nation treatment. If the Muscat State Council is in a position to negotiate a treaty along the lines suggested the Department would be prepared, in view of the financial situation in Muscat, and as an exceptional measure, to give assurances that no objection would be offered, pending the approval or rejection of the treaty by the United States Senate, to the collection of higher duties on goods of American origin imported into Muscat than those provided for in Article III of the Treaty of 1833. Such assurances would be given, however, on the understanding that the Muscat State Council would, in its turn, furnish assurances that pending the same period American nationals in Muscat would receive the treatment specified in the proposed new treaty. Accept, Sir, the renewed assurances of my high consideration. For the Secretary of State: Sd. W.R.Castle.V r J, D.O.No.C-S?^ political Agency &amp; Consulate BUBHIHl R£vS iv&gt; /?»« '/vi' ^ ^SHe M 1 I ^ Muscat, the^I^December 1931. Please refer to para (4)^of letter from Chancery, British Embassy, Washington, of 15th October to Eastern Department of Foreign Office, forwarded to me under your endorsement Ro.C^Sl of 13th December. 2. You will remember that you enquired what the Treaty of Saint Germain was, and that I was unable to reply. I have looked up such Treaty compilations as we have here and have been unable to trace it. From the wording of the Chancery letter I imagine that it is some post-war Treaty whose analogy may help us. The point is, however, somewhat academic as presumably we intend taking action as indicated in Chancery's para (3). Hon*ble Lieut.Colonel H.V.Biscoe, I.A., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire.No.F.225-^/89. tin f I h;i $£&amp;$(&amp;• | ii ■—m i in iiiiiii Tin mi— ■iiri &gt;w-^f A copy of the undermentioned paper is for ward eo. to the Hon'lDie the Political Hesiaent in the Persian Gulf for information in continuation of endorsement from thi 'Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department Luf y ' No.F.225-N/29, dated the 9th December 1931, and for favour of comment at an early date. By order, etc., IfVwy ' 4^ Assistailt Secretary to the Government of India Mi 2ign and Political Department, New Delhi, Che Ll^~ January 1932. Demi-official letter from G.1,Rendel, Ssguire, Foreign Office, to J .C.Walton, Esq.. , India Off ice , No . E. 5355/267/9 i, dated the 4th December 1931, with enclosure. (with l s•c.. )FOREIGN OFFICE, S.W.I. r . . 5 T 5.7593/1931. 4th Deoember, 19.31. - s. 5355/267/91) IflDSNTIilL. Dear Walton, 11th rererenoe to Earner's letter to Donaldson No. S.5355/267/91 of the 31st October, a'bout the proposed, modification of the United States-Muscat Treaty, I write to send, you our comments on the Washington Chancery's ^ ^Letter of the 15th October, which we have now examined in detail. In the first place, we think that, though the State Department's note is not very explicit, the Washington Embassy are probably right in their view that it would be extremely difficult to induce the United States Government to conclude a new treaty which did not include provisions according general most-favoured-nation treatment to American nationals - at least within any reasonable time. Now that the point has arisen it is hard ly likely that the United States Government will lightly abandon it. In any case they would almost certainly want to know the exact reasons why Muscat cannot give United States citizens full most-favoured-nation rights, and, although we may ourselves regard those reasons as adequate I doubt whether they would appear equally convincing to the United States Government. If however you feel that a reasonably strong case can be made, we should of course be glad to discuss the point further. I ^ Under (3) and (4) of the Chancery's letter of the 15th October, two suggestions are made for getting over the difficulty which has arisen. The first is that the proposal to modify the French and United States treaties should be dropped, and that ther ate of the tariff should be raised against all goods other than those covered by the relevant articles of these treaties: i.e. against all _ goods pal ton, Esq.. ,0.B. ,M.O.1*4. o goods other than those importea into J.uscat in French and United States vessels. In that event, goods carried in Dutch vessels /i/ould, presumahly, also have t/O he exempted from the increase in the duties in view of the most favoured-nation provisions of the Netherlands-Muscat Treaty. — xou v;ill r ■■•jr .i'; I, men this proposal was consideredf that it vvould 'be undesirable to put the French, Americans and Dutch in a privileged position, which, we thought, it would he more difficult to get them to abandon later on when the new duties had come into force and they had 'begun to profit hy their exemption. (See paragraph 3 of our official letter E 6207/166/91 of the 31st January,1930). t jr t This argument was a valid one so long as there seemed a chance of bringing the United States and France into line in time to get the new duties imposed on all goods alike without undue delay. But if, as seems to he the case, we have now reached a deadlock with the United States Govern ment in regard to the modification of their treaty, and if there is consequently no hope of securing a modification of the French treaty, this consideration no longer alto gether applies. Indeed, by waiting for United States concurrence for what may prove to be an indefinite time, we may only be uselessly preventing Muscat from imposing duties without further delay on what may s till prove to ba the bulk of her imports (i.e. on goods imported in ships not flying the United States, French or Dutch flags), and thus redressing her finances at a moment when they are in a critical condition. The suggestion in (3) of the Ohancery*s.letter may, however, be open to the objection that importers would and coula arrange for a large part of the imports into Muscat to be brought in in vessels flying the French, United States or Netherlands flag. The Resident in the Persian Gulf could no aoubt gilre an opinion on this point. But P.y 6 But if it were found, that this was 'being done on a scale which was defeating the purpose of the new tariff, presuma bly the tariff could he lowered again, and we should he no worse off than■ we are now, while Muscat would have at any rate made some money meanwhile. Indeed a possible solution would he to make the increase definitely provisional or temporary. Under (4) the Washington Chancery suggest that use could perhaps he made of an argument hy analogy from the St.G-ermain Convention. I enclose a copy of the Washington telegram of the 8th April, 1930 referred to and of our reply. It was at that time considered undesirable to argue with the United States Government that the St.G-ermain Convention involved the supersession of the restrictive provisions of the United States- Muscat Treaty of 1833 in respect of Zanzibar; it was therefore impossible to use the argument 'hy analogy' in connection with Euscat. The position is still much the same. The question whether His Majesty's Government should approach the United States •Government stam±esagkxtfe[&amp;± with a view to their participating in a proposal to extend the St. Germain Conven tion for a further five years is now under discussion (see foreign Office letter to India Office No.J.3139/21/60 of the 17th November). Our . Egyptian Department, who deal with Zanzibar questions, tell us that it would be undesirable to attempt to use the argument suggested in (4) of the Washing ton Chancery's letter until the United States Government, if His Majesty's Government decide to approach them, agree to participate in the extension of the St.Germain Convention and until the extending protocol is signed and comes into force. This the Egyptian Department think, would inevitably take a long time. It seems therefore that the Washington Embassy's second suggestion is impracticable - at any rate for the time being You will no doubt let me know if you would like to discuss this difficult question with us orally. Yours &amp;c., (Sd) G.W. REN DSL.(£ 1847/433/91) Deoypher. Sir R.Lindsay (ISashington) 8th April 1930. D. 5.00 p.m. 8th April,1950. E. 9.30 a.m. 9th April,1930. Uo.163. Your despatch No.384 of March 18th and correspondence ending with Sir E.Howard's despatch 1^0.2,131 of November 15th 1929. The Senate on April 3rd ratified the convention of St. Germain with a reservation regarding arbitration of disputes arising thereunder. I should be glad to learn (a) whether you consider that this ratification may be held to involve supersession of provisions of 1833 treaty regarding raising of level of duties in Zanzibar similar to provisions of 1902 convention and if so whether I should address United States Government accordingly;(b) whether in view of purposes for which convention of St. Germain was concluded ratification might by analogy be used in support of contention that United States should insist on maintenance of similar provisions as regards Muscat.■st 1847/433/91) Cypher telegram to Sir H.Lindsay(Washington). Foreign Office, 26th ApriljIQSO, 3^00 p.m. Uo.219. Your telegram No.ie3(of 8th April: American Ratification of St. Germain Convention). Though it is our view that the Convention of St. Germain supersedes conflicting stipulations in previous treaties, all that at present appears necessary or desirable is that Your Excellency should remind the State Department that your predecessors note of 31st January, 1929 is still unanswered. Should the reply when received prove to be unsatisfactory, we could then argue that Article 2 of the Convention, according to our interpretation of it, releases us from the restrictive provisions of the Treaty of 1833. Argument by analogy in favour of similar concession by United States Government in regard to Muscat cannot therefore be used at present. You should take up the Muscat question without delay but without using this argument.Secretary of Stat® for India Government of India, foroi^i &amp; Political Departraont. 34th B cemtaer, 1931• Your telegram Mo. 1352-3 deteti 17th May and sub sequent oorreapondenoo retarding Mtteoat tariff. Please see fOreij^i Office derai-officl^il letter Ho.S. 5355/267/91 dated 4th Deceriber, 1931, copy by air mail of 11th December. It appesjrs til me that, if esrly effect is to be given to desire of Muscat tate to incre-we tariff rates, two coxirBa^ an©n:- (a) that proposal to modify French and Cnited States treaties should be dropped, and that the rate ol the tariff Kbovld be raised againet all goods otliar than those carried in ITenoh and American bottoms and those covered by the Commercial Declsration between uscst and the Sether-feh -ds of 1877. fftis course would, of course, involve modification of Article 6 of An#o-Muscat Treaty of 1091. (b) to s^res to the American deramid for most-favoured nation treatment in respect of nationnls as sell as of goods. Objections to (a) are stated in para. 8 of Foreigs Office letter No. I 6207/166/91 dated Slst January, 1930 end para. 4 of your telsg^MB Ho.1352-3 dated 17th May, • 931. Objections to (b) in Politio 'l Resident 's telo{-r*n N0.T .34/35 dated ISth February, 1931. It does not ^jnenr that any of these objections is insuperable. As regards (a) there is force in considerations advanced in Foreign Office letter of 4th December, 1931, and their suggestion that theft the incresse should be definitely provisiensl, at any rMte in the first insttance. F.Z. 7593/31 This/Ldential. BY AIR MAIL. Government of India. Foreign and Political Department. Express L e tter . Ml It From To Foreign, New Delhi, Political, Bushire. No.F. 225-N/29 m ..A-****-*-'-' '• Dated the 11 January 1932. Heferenoe Secretary of State for India's express letter No.P.Z.7593/31, dated the 24th Deoemher 1931, copy of whioh was sent to you direct. Muscat tariff. 2. The Government of India would he glad to receive your views at an early date. Issue of the ahove has 'been authorised. py, Deputy Secretary to the Government of India (h*V yFrom To EXPRESS L S T T B R, RESIDENT 9 Bushire* Foreign 9 New Delhi* (Repealed to Secretary of State for India, London) • Ho.75-S of 1932* Bushire, dated the 12th February3S3J Refer nee Foreign and Political Department Express Letter ^o*F*225-H/29 f dated the 11th January 1932. Muscat Tariff. 2. I would firstly emphasise that it is very desirable that arrangements should be made to enable the Muscat State to increase their tariff rates at an early date. The State is just keeping its head above water at the present time, but only by starving the administration and reducing expenditure to an absolute minimum. In tMs con action please see my despatch SO.70-S of 12th February 19 32. 3. Reference Secretary of State for Indian Express Letter j5io.P.^.7593/31 of 24th December 1931. I am strongly in favour of proposal (a), namely, that tariff rates should be raised against all goods other than those carried in French and American bottoms and those covered by the Commercial Declaration between Mhecat and the Netherlands of 1877. 4. The risk of the situation being exploited by special shipments in French or American ships seems to me very slight. The ...-2- ✓ The trade of Muscat is chiefly with India and I cannot conceive that either the volume of trade or the relatively small difference in tariifs on certain articles would justify the despatch of a special steamer to MuscaU Ho American or French vessels call there at present and I believe there is only one dhow now left at Sur which has the right to fly the French flag# 5 # X think proposal (b) t namely f to agree to American demands for mos t-favoured-nation treatment in respect of nationals as well as of goods, would be most distasteful to the Muscat State# Apart from the practical objections outlined in my telegram No,34/35, dated the 15th February 1931, we must take into consideration the question of amour propre which always looms large in dealings with an Oriental State# The State would certainly feel that they were being asked to make a very large concession for a very small quid pro quo , since, as pointed out aiove, the risk of shipments in American bottoms is very slight# While in practice the Political Agent would probably intervene in any natter affecting American missionaries the State would dislike openly having to surrender their present jurisdiction# 6# If proposal (a) is approved is it necessary definitely to emphasise that the increased tariff rates are provisional ? Unless a state has definitely bound itself by treaty not to increase rates for some specific period it would seem that all tariff rates are provisional and that every State has the right to raise or lower them as suits its own interests from time to time# His Majesty's Government are doing this at present in England and the French Government have just put on a 15^ surtax on British goods. Any tariff imposed at Muscat would necessarily be more or less experimental in the first instance and modifications would doubtless be introduced from time to time as experience or circumstances showed to be advisable. Definitely ###4 &amp; Definitely to emphasise fact that increased rates were provisional might, I think, lead to misunderstanding and create uncertainty in the minds of merchants, who would probably think that rates would be lowered to previous level after a short period and might delay ordering goods# ad/** V. Biscoe, Lt«Colonelt Political Resident in the Persian Gulf AT TESTED ( Under Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.2^ ■': M. (&gt;1 j;.U. Ho. 77-S. of 195^. British Hesidency and Conuuia te-General, UuBhire, i2th jj'ebruaxy 1952. Under Article 9 of the Muscat Commercial Treaty, duty is payable on the value of the gooes according to the market price at Muscat, do they levy it on this or on the invoice value? X merely */ . mention the matter because it was 'brought to my notice the other day in Bahrain / where X isas informed that formerly duty used to be charged on A.r.u.C. kerosene at, I think, Ks. 5-8-0 a tin, the invoice price, but that now they had started levying duty at Hs. 5/- a tin, market price in Balirain, and Muscat vaould clearly be entitled to adopt the same basis of valuation. It is a small matter but X have thought it just as well to bring it to your notice. 1 think the enhanced tariff rates will go through fairly soon. They are giving up the idea of trying o get the con sent of the French and Americans, etc., and are now proposing simply to raise the rates on all gooas other than those imported in drench or American bottoms ; tile best solution really in my opinion, liow wmm we have not got to consider foreign powers there is not likely to be vmy undue delay. Lieut.-Golone 1 r.O.W. Jtovvle, C.ii .J., Pol i ti cal \gen t, Mus c at.(r^ a IK HAIL. Ko •i. 225-K/&lt; A copy ol the undermentioned paper is forwarded to the lion'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gull*, for information, vvith reference to his Express letter No.75-S of 193a, dated the 12th Pehruary 1952. order, e tc., Assistant Secretary to 'the Government of India. foreign and Political Department, New Delhi, The March 1932. xelegraBi to the Secretary of State tor India, London N0.66S, dated the 1st March 1932. d. /&lt;},3' I fa. kTelegram R., No. 669. dated 1st March 1932. Viceroy (F. &amp; P. Deptt.), New Delhi. From . Secretary of State for India, London To \ correspondence endlne wl« EesWenfs Exprese Letter SO. , 5 - S of 1632, dated 12® P en ma r,. 19 3 2. »Beat | tar ' f ' mile .e are Inclined to think teat Besldent pornane exaf-eerates objections to course (b) referred to In your Express letter of Mtk December. 1931, No. P.Z.^ '/ &gt; in view of urgent necessity of restoring stability finonces .e tblnk It bettor In first Instmce to adopt course (a) on understanding which would haye to be made quite clear to Sultan that we reserve rlpht to ash for reduction of tarn w orlKlnal figure If events should prove that Treaty ad.m- tage is being exploited hy beneficiary nations. 3. We suggest that opportunity he taken of renewal of Treaty (vide our telegram of 10th February, No. 264 -N.) to introduce necessary araEndment to article 6. Copy forwarded to Political Agent, Muscat under P.L. No 14f -S dated 14/3/32. P.S,V., 0. and N. M..S.H.79 © OOiMBRClAL HSLATIOKS &amp; TEBATISS fl-EPAE9JIM'T, BOARD Oi 1 Tr.ADE, P.Z, 2183/1932, GHEAT SEOEGE STEiET, LONDON, S.W. 1. 2835 ^ 3;L ' April, 1932. Wlti, reference to your letter of the 15th March, (P.Z.1361/32) regarding the tariff provlsl ons of the Coimaerelal Treaty of 1891 between the Unitecl IClngaom aid Maacat, 1 sm directed by the Board of Trade to state that, any proposal which would give a preference to goods carried In French or Amerlcm vessels over goods carried In British vessels Is open to the greatest objection and one to which the Board could not In any circumstances agree. It is, and | has been the policy of His Majesty' s Govermaent to secure the removal of flag discrimination wherever it occurs. It may be of Interest to the Secretary of State to know that the effect of the rebate In the Customs Import and export duties In Portugal on goods Imported in Portuguese vessels, which have been In force since 1921, has been to i transfer the bulk of the trade to Portuguese vessels. The I most serious representations have been made by the snipping interests of the United Kingdom against this policy, and His I Majesty's Government have under consideration retaliatory action against Portugal if the discrimination is not removed within a measurable period of time. It wuld be wholly | inconsistent with their policy to endorse any proposal such as that uade in your letter under reply, 1/ nder-Secretary of State, adia Office, S.W.I.I am to adu that according to tlie uscat trade returns for 1928/29. the latest available, there were imported into Muscat goods to a value of £343,917 of which £258,589 worth came from India. The Board can see no reason why, if the present proposal were adopted, it would not be possible to charter a vessel or vessels under the United States or Jrench flags to carry these goods, in which case the object of the proposal would be completely frustrated, A copy of this letter has been sent to tli© foreign Office, I have, , (Sgd,) T.G, JEKKINS.Copy, o» a /4/i 05 MusGAt &amp; Oman Groverninent Pinance Ministry, Muscat, dated Gth. April i93a. To Tne -folitical Agent &amp; H.r-.M's Consul, Muscat. Memorandum. Subject: Aggflissment of 5^ Advalorem Customs duty Reference your No.0-51 dated 22-2-32. The ad valorem customs duty is ta^cen on the wholesale rraricet price of goody imported into lluscat when such goods are sold wholesale, otherwise at Retail prices. 2* The Customs are in possession of current market rates and assess the duty payable on imports accordingly. As the raaricet rates are not always correctly ascertainable it is the custom to add certain percentages to the invoice value of goods to arrive at these rates. Some of the goods for which such percentages are being added to arrive at the wholesale cost price at Muscat are # — (i) Cotton piece goods when not imported in bulk invoice value plus (ii) Silk -do- -do- (iii) Confectionery &amp; tinned provisions -do- 25^ Sd. H.G.Alban, Captain, Financial Adviser,Muscat. A KyBy AIR MAIL saniAiL Forwarded with tho compliment b of the Secretary political Department, India Office, for the infomation of the Political Resident.Buahire, India Office, Whitehall, London, S,W,1 0 Copy sent to'IDSFTIAL. 3^1 l\H No .F.225-N/29. A copy of the undermentioned papers is forwarded to the Hon'hie the PoLitioal Besident in the Persian Gulf, for information. \ By order, etc. , Assistant Secretary to' the Grovernment of India. oreign and Political Department, Simla, The ^ 3^ April 1932. C 1 • Letter from the India Office to the Foreign Office, No.P.Z. 1361/32,dated the 15th JJarch 1932. 2. Letter from the India Office to the Board of Trade, No.P.Z.1361/32, dated the 15th March 1932. 3. Demi-official letter from M.J. Cla^son jSsg., India Office to C.M. Dixon, Esq., Colonial Office, No. P.Z.1361/32, dated the 16th March 1932. C&gt;v/r / )If is requested that in any further communi- xtion on this subject the under-mentioned letter %d number may be quoted, and the reply Idressed to— 5228 INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL, The Under Secretary of State for India, Political Department, India Office, London, S. W. 1. LONDON, 8.W. 1. j' Z* 1361/32, . inarch, ly32 # Sir I am directed by the 3«cret^y of State for India to refer to your letter O»: ; ; # r r # aa35/01 t of the th June l^^L, regarding tlx© tariff provieiono of the CojiMereisl Treaty of 1691 botrreen Great Britain and Musoftt* The United atf.tos Government has ui:.ce intimated its unwillingness to negotiate new treaties ;• rorriding for the levying of s:i&gt;eeific rates of Import duty on gooas of iaaeii oan origin and will only consider the modification of its Muscat ' treaty on the baais of most-favoured-nation treatment. As this lavaires a demand which is unacceptable for the accord cf 'noe t-favoared-nation' treatiiient to United States nationals as well as to United States i ode, the Secretary of State, after eorisultatio a with the Governiuont of Xijuiia, now pro ■oees, subject to the concurrence of the Secx-etary dt Stat© for foreign Affairs, to abandon attempts to secure a modiflcatim of the Muscat Treaties with trance and the United States of America. But as the financial positic i i , the ^uacut St te is st 11 acute 3ir Sanuel Hoare la anxious to persevere with the proposal to moai fy the Treaty of Muscat vd th this countiy of 1891 so as to allow an increase in the .-.i&amp;xLnuia tariff rates leviable frcm 5% to lOjt In the case of alcoholic liquors and tobacco). British gooas would retain 'mas t~ favoured-nation' treatment as against all goods except those conveyed in the vessels of France, United States of Aimxi ca am the Netherlands (goods conveyed in whose vessels under the Cos orciaL / Seerc tary # Jocrd of Trade., Ho. D. 1673-13/32 # gonfidential. BUB''' ^ s^r. OSNC v • rom 2^)- nuHOfeiiiFlAL teSWOSi To The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India The Under Secretary of S&gt;tate for India, Political Department, India Office, i 2. I fi £ !• c Dated £imla # the // May 1932 # Subject-Abolition of the Council of Ministers at Muscat, Sir, I am directed to refer to letter from the Hobble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf # ■V U Bo.216-S of 1932 f dated the 7th April 1932, a copy of I ^ ^hich was sent to you direct, and to say that the Govern ment of India are in general agreement with Political Residents views in regard to the policy to be pursued in future dealings with the Muscat State, They agree that the present Sultan should be encouraged to take an active part in the administration of the State and to rule the State on Arab lines with as little interference in internal affairs as possible, 2» The Resident in paragraph 6 of his letter attributes to the Government of India expression in theirMi«ir telegram Ho.fifla of the let Karch 1932 of the view that he had psrhape oxapperated the Sultan's dee Ire to safeguard the dignity of hie Utate, I am to explain that the rewarke in that telegram were intended to sur -eet that in the opinion of the Goveraaent f India the Political Reaidant had perhape exafgerated the objectlone to the prant of coeWfavaured-nation treatment to the United States of Aaerica in reepeot of pergonal statue for their euhjecte and not that he had sade an oreretateaent of facte which were within his knowledge. 3« The Government of India have also read with interest the diaoueeione held by the Political Resident with Hie Hlghneee the Sultan rerarding the poeeibllity of denunciation by the Mueoat Etate of her Treatise with - oreign lowers. They had already given thie question their careful cone id?ration and had arrived at the following provisional oonoluelone. ihile the Muscat Treaties both with i'mnce and America are drawn sub eaecie peternit«tlt-. the authcritiffe agree that all treaties are to be understood ae having a tacit condition that they reasala only valid Ms. atantlb,us.. Until the Great War it could not be said that there has been any material variation in the position which would Justify denunciation of her treaties by Husoat, Since the Great '-Tar there has bean a tendency in all countries to raise tariff ratee and it might be hold that in respect of the relevant Articles these two • reatiee things had now changed bo much that denunciation of those Articles would be Justified. But/are apparently any where on record in which denunciation has not heen preceded either by internal revolution or violentConfidential . So,389-S of 1932. British. Residency &amp; Coasulate-Cxeneral, Bushire, the 10th June 1932. From - The Hon'ble Lt. Colonel Sir H, V.Biscoe,K.B.S., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. To - The Foreign Secretary to the G-overnment of India, SII£U. Sir, I have the honour to inrite a reference to letter ^o. 2835/31 of the 4th April 1932 from the Board of Trade to the Under Secretary of State, India Office, regarding the Muscat Tariff. 2. In that letter the Board of Trade begin by stating that 'any proposal which would give a preference to goods carried in French or American vessels over goods carried in British vessels is open to the greatest objection and one to which the Board could not in any circumstances agree 1 *. I would respectfully submit that in this case there would be no practical preference but merely a theoretical one, since there are actually no French or American vessels carrying goods or trading in those parts. A preference which exists only in theory and not in practice can surely be ignored. 3. In support of their contention the Board of Trade quote the analogy of Pcrtugal, and state that the effect of rebate on goods imported in Portuguese vessels has been to transfer .../*1 -2- transfer the bulk of the trade to Portuguese vessels. I would submit that the case of Portugal has no analogy with that of Muscato In the case of Portugal there were presumably other ships standing by to carry the goods: in the case of Muscat there are not, and if there are no other steamers stand ing by to carry the goods the trade cannot be transferred to them. 4. The Board of Trade, howeyer, point out that in 1928-29, the latest year for which they hare figures,there were imported into Muscat goods to the value of £ 343,917, of which £ 258,589 came from India, and they state that they see no reason why it would not be possible to charter a vessel or vessels under the United States or French flags to carry these goods, in which case the object of the proposal would be completely frustrated# The import figures for Muscat for the last two years are as followss 1931-52 . 1950-51 . Steamers ». £■ 177,000 £ 170,000 Sailing craft . ' 109,000 11 112,000. It will be seen that nearly 40^ of the goods are not imported in steamers at all, but in sailing «af11 it makes little difference, in many cases, to a merchant in Muscat whether his goods take a week longer to reach Muscat, and the rates by sailing craft are considerably cheaper. Assuming that an enterprising Hindu merchant chartered a French ship to come to Muscat, the maximum volume of trade that he could hope to obtain would be about £ 170,000, since even with a small tariff preference in his favour he could not hope to compete with the sailing craft, especially as dhows convey goods direct to the smaller ports such as Sur, Sohar, etc. It seems to me, if I Biay say so, in the highest degree improbable that it would be worth .. #-3- IV worth while to charter a French or American vessel for this very small volume of trade, and still more improbable that any of the merchants who deal with Muscat would be capable of financing a transaction of this nature, and monopolising the entire trade of the State. However, if the suggestion embodied in telegram Ho»669 of the 1st March 1932 from the Government of India is approved, even this risk,which I can not but regard as almost entirely theoretical,will, I submit, be adequately guarded against, since the authority given to the Muscat State would be at once abrogated if United States, French or Dutch ships took advantage of it. I am sending a copy of this despatch to His Majesty's Secretary of State for India. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, ATTESTED. 'ft-lb- ^ . dential Assistant. I#t. Colonel, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. J Copy forwarded to the Political Agent, Muscat# i/S J?'*0 ifidential. lib No, F. 225-01/29. w ifrrf inh A copy of the undermentioned paper is forwarded to the 1 Hon , ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, for info rirtation. BUSHIFE, ^fc^DENCY. out m.q- By order jetc., GGHhl'^TiAi BfcOOHuS. j Assistant Secretary to the Government of India. Foreign and Political Department, S ^ M L A; The frfyjxily1932. Letter from the Board of Trade, London, to the India Office, No.C.R. T.2835/31, dated the 28th May 1932. (With 1 spare copy.)No•C.R.T.2835/31 Comraercial Relations and Treaties Department, Board of Trade, Great George Street London, S^W.1 # 28th May 1932. Sir With reference to your letter (P.Z.2527/32) of 25th I£ay with regard to the proposal to modify the rates of import duty chargeable in Muscat, I am directed by the Board of Trade to state, for the information of secretary, Sir Samuel tEoare, that they concur in the proposals contained in your letter to the Foreign Office enclosed v ;ith your letter under reply. A copy of this letter is being sent to the Foreign Office and the Dominions Office, I have,etc.. Sd/- T.St.quintin Hill Under-Secretary of State India Office S.W.I,tn# -tiecet trtiutim i&amp; in feet very similar to that on which Ihn tarn mftiimm »f Wm Crown ©avife^d in ®r) Opinion giv^n on May «r th, 1909 in r^gsrd. to the .Anglo-Vem«u^lan treaty of 1--54. In tuat o ,&gt;lni n III# 0 Uccrfc, although atoi tting that the point was not cle^r, ttw Tiew that treaties of a commercial nature, which contain no exprcsfife provision a governing termination, could nevertiiele6.a be detemined, upon reaaonabXe notice. In the caae of the .■uacat treaties, the isaue woislci be aomewnat complicated, sine® the queation slight aria«i whether, if some of the provision® of the treaties are clearly not of a commercial but of a permanent character, the treaties muet stand or fail &amp;&amp; a whole, or whether it would be potalble to denounce aoM of tiAeir provisions only. on the whole, however, if the matter is considered on the basis of strict law, it seeiss likely that th« xiucfit State could, uyon giving reasonable notice, denounce these treaties with France and the United Btetes, or &lt;• t lea^t the provisions in them whicii are of a coi&amp;murcial nature. It appears doubtful whether, as tue Government of India suggest, the natter |C ^ turns on the clausula w rebus sic stantibus 1 *. At any rate, if it were decided to endeavour to denounce the trestles, the arguments set out above would probably be stronger than those fo nded on the clausula 'rebus sic stantibus^. hile the preceding paragraphs deal with the position from the strictly legal point of view, T am to add that tlr John bimon con. iderrnroa the politicfti standpoint any attempt to denounce these treaties on behalf of the . uscat State would be likely to give rise to difficUities with the French and United States Governments inForwarded with the compliments of the Secretary.Political Department, India Office.for the inforaatioa of the Political Reaident.Buehire, India Office Whitehall, London 1® Copy sent toK 39SI/4/91 1 Q. ■ i i f o / i 19 ^ 0 s«w»x» 16th ABgaat* 19M Sir ?,itli r^ftiy^e® to For©i^a. OfTi©® l@ft8r Mo* I, 2094/4/91 oT th© Eitli Jim© regarding th© Maseat fariff, 1 am directed % Secretary Sir John Simon to transmit to you, to b@ laid bafora Secretary Sir Samuel loare t the accompanying copy of a despatch from Ei© kajeety'a Ambassador at Paris intimating that th© French Government are ready to fall in with the '.latest proposals advanced by His Majesty's Qovermaent with a view to enable the : uscat Government to increase their present tariff rates# a cop:/ of a despatch which ha® been addrt. sed to lord fyrrell in reply to this report after semi-official consultation with the India Office is also enclosed herein* £• It will be observed that the French Government, in the la. t paragraph of their note of the 3rd Aurruat, point out that they have at oresent no represeatative in Muscat and request the good offices of His ^ajesty*# Govermaent to tr n&amp;mit to the Sultan 1 © Government th© necessary notification on th© subject. The Secretary of State coneidera therefore that th© coiamunication which it is proposed that Hie majesty f 8 Government should addrese to th© Sultan of Muscat on their own behalf should now be drafted, and th t it should thereupon be communicated to the French Government ®ith an enquiry whether they concur in a similar communication mutatis aiatandis beihg addressed to the : lias cat Government on their behalf by th© British representative in : uecat# I ^der•Secretary of state, India Office#3# Sir John Simon considers it desirable, for reasons of expediency as well as of coartosy, that the French Government should be given the opportunity of coneorring in the actual, term© of the co. monicatlon which it la proposed to address to the Muscat Oovernnent on their behalf. 4* Copies of this letter are being sent to the Dominions Office and Board of frade* I am Sir t Your obedient Servant, (Sd G. W. H EN DEL, ...,-1 t Ulwoa P-L t|l4-4 ;CM 0 Mo.l07j5. (56/7/^2) British EmhaBuy, P^HXS. August Jth* 19*42 Sir With reference to your despatch Ho*15^7 (B.259V 4/91) of June 22nd regarding the proposed modification of the Muacat treaties, I have the honour to transmit to you herewith a copy of a memorandum from the dnietry for Foreign Affairs in reply to ray representations # in which they express the readiness of the French aovernment to fall in with the proposal© of xiia Majesty^ ilovcrmaent in this matter. 2* I would venture to ©uggeet that in taking note of this comamnication, X saay he authorised to convey to the Ministry an expression of the appreciation of Hie Jajesty^ Goveminertat the French Goveniment^e attitude. I have the honour to he, with great truth and reapect. Sir, Your most obedient, humble Dervaiit, (Signed) TYRRELL. Ight lionorahle, r John Simon, a.O.B.I. , K.G.V.O. , M.P. , etc. 9 etc. 9 etc. S1V^ &gt;81/4/91) FORKIQH OFFICEt S.W.I. 16th August, 1932 My Lord, I have received Your Lordehlp's despatch Ho•1073 (56/7/38) of the 5th August informing me of the readiness of the French Government to fall in with the proposals of His Majesty's Government for the modliication of the tariff provisions of the mscat treaties. 2# I approve your proposal to convey to the French Ministry for Foreign Affairs, in taking note of their ae^orancium of the 3rd August, an expression of Hi® Majesty* s Government's warn appreciation of the French Government's attitude in this matter* 3» I hope shortly to be able to transmit to you the araft of the communication which, subject to the French Government*s approval. His Majesty's Government will propose to make to the Sultan of uscat on their behalf* A copy of a letter which has been sent to the India Office on this point is enclosed herein for your information* ►llency p Sight Honourable Lord Tyrrell, G.C*M.G., K.C*B., etc,, etc#, etc., Paris. I am, with great truth and respect My Lord, Your ' xcellency* s obedient Servant {For the Secretary of tate) nP.2.4971/32. \ Important . 3-h August 1932, Sir, f. In reply to your letter of the 16th August,No.E.3981/4 /91, I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to say that lie notes with much satisfaction the readiness of t the French Government to fall in with the latest proposals | advanced by His Majesty^ Government with a view to enabling [ the Muscat Government to increase their present tariff rates. 2. I am now to enclose drafts of the communications which subject to Sir John Simon 1 s concurrence might,it is suggested, be addressed to His Highness the Sultan of Muscat [ by the Political Eesident in the Persian Gulf on behalf of I His Majesty^ Government and the French Government. The latter draft will, of course, be subject to the concurrence ; of the French authorities, which will no doubt be sought through His Majesty's Representative in Paris. ; 3, On a minor point arising out of the wording of the draft British note, I am to say that the letter of 9th March 1 1930 received from the Sultan of Muscat, requesting a modification of the limitations on his fiscal freedom, referred to the Treaty with His Majesty^ Government of 1839. That Treaty was, in fact, abrogated and replaced by the Commercial Treaty of 1891, and the limitation of the Sultan 1 s freedom to impose a tariff in excess of 5% ad valorem in the case of British goods is at present governed by Article 6 of th6 Treaty of 1891. In view of this, paragraph 1 of the draft letter makes no reference to the date of the Treaty of Commerce, but paragraph 3 makes it clear that the Treaty der SeoreUary of Stat©, 111 foreign office, s.wa.in question is the Treaty of 1891. 4. A copy of this letter has been sent to the Board of Trade and a copy of a letter which has heen addressed to the Dominions Office is enclosed. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, ; ^ J ' C ' ^ALTOit Porwarded with enclosures to the Political i ^gent, Muscat, under P.L.No.^^^-5 dated 6th Sept, 1952.P.2.4971/32. m Impo rtant. A ^, Angus t 1932. Sir. With reference to Foreign Office letteir of 16th August, No#E.398I/4/91, on the subject of the Muscat tariff, of which a copy is understood to have been sent to the Dominions Office,! am directed by the Secretary of State for India to forward for the information of the Secretary of State for the Dominions copy of a letter which has now been addressed to the Foreign Office, A ^5 2. In the India Office lettet of 25th May, P.Z.2527/32,the suggestion was made that a communication should be addressed,in due course to the interested Dominion Governments (the Commonwealth of Australia and the Union of South Africa have of course, withdrawn from the Commercial Treaty of 1891) in regard to the modification of the Muscat tariff. I rju to suggest that now that the French Government have agreed in principle to the proposals made to them on behalf of His Majesty's Government in the United Kingdom, a communication of the nature in question might suitably issue. The matter is one of considerable urgency and if no objection is seen I am to suggest that any communications to the Dominions might be made by telegraph. Copies of this letter are being sent to the Foreign Office and to the Board of Trade, I am. Sir, Your obedient Servant, Under Secretary of State, Dominions Office, (Sd. s J. 0. WALTON. S • W, 1, • /i^M P. Z.4971/32 DRAFT . Your Highness, As Your Highness is aware, Your Highness 1 predecessor. His Highness Saiyid Taimur Bin Faisul, K.C.I.E., CiS.I., on the 9th March 1930 requested His Majesty's G-overment in the United Kingdom to approach the Goverment of the French Republic on his behalf with a view to obtaining a revision of those clauses of the Treaty of Commerce between the Imam of Muscat and His Majesty the King of the French dated 17th November 1844 and ratified on 4th February 1846, under which the customs duties which may be imposed on goods imported by French vessels are restricted to 5% ad valorem . 2. As Your Highness is aware it has proved necessary to seek a different method of securing for Your Highness the relief in question. I am now instructed to say that His Majesty 1 s G-overment have been requested by the Government of the French Republic to inform Your Highness on their behalf that no objection would be raised by them to an increase of customs duties to ICF/olOfo on goods imported by French vessels into Muscat (25% on tobacco and on alcoholic liquor of 25 or more degrees under proof) despite the provisions in Article 10 of the Treaty of 184:4 which Treaty shall remain in force. The concurrence of the Government of the French Republic in action on these lines will, however, be subject to the unde rs tand i ng: (a) that a similar increase will apply to ships of all other nations, except those of the United States, which are protected by Treaty, and those of the Netherlands, wtiich enjoy simple Most Favoured Nation treatment; and (b) that if any ships so protected in the opinion of the Government of the French Bepublic exploit their Treaty advantage to the detriment of French trade or shipping the right of withdrawing this acquiescence immediately is reserved by the Government of the French Bepublic* 3, I am to request Your Highness to be good enough to inform me whether you are prepared to accept the understanding in question.Ilk 4971/32. DRAM. Your Highness, As Your Highness is aware. Your Highness* predecessor,His Highness Saiyid Taimur Bin Faisul, K* G*I.E.,O.S.I.,on the 9th March 1930 intimated to His Majesty's Government in the United Kingdom that the necessity had arisen for increasing the customs duties of the Muscat State for revenue purposes. His Highness requested His Majesty 1 s Government in the United' Kingdom to approach the Governments of France and of the United States of imerica respectively on his behalf to obtain a revision of those clauses of the Treaty of imity and Commerce between the United States of America and His Highness Said Syed dated 21st September 1833 and the Treaty of Commerce between the Imam of Muscat and His Majesty the King of the French dated 17th November 1844 and ratified on 4th February 1846, under which the customs duties which may be levied on goods imported by vessels of those countries into1^1 into Muscat are linited to 5^ ad valorem . His Highness further requested that the tariff provisions of the Treaty of Coininerce made 'between Her late Majesty Q.ueen Victoria and the Sultan of Muscat might 'be modified in the same sense. 2. Tour Highness is also aware that the United States Government have found themselves unable to agree to the modification of their Treaty of 1833, save on conditions which Your Highness has not found acceptable. His Majesty 1 s Government in the United Kingdom and the Government of the French Hepublic have therefore considered the other methods by which, in so far as they are concerned, steps could be talien to meet Your Highness 1 wishes. 3. A separate communication is being addressed to Your Highness on behalf of the Government of the French Republic. I am now instructed to inform Your Highness on behalf of His Majesty's Government in the United Kingdom that no objection would be raised by them to an increase of customs duties to 10fo (25% on tobacco and on alcoholic liquor of 25 or more degrees under proof) despite the provisions of Article 6 ofof tlie Treaty of Coinnerce of 19 March 1891, which Treaty shall remain in force. The concurrence of His Majesty^ Government in action on these lines will, however, be subject to the understanding: (a) that a similar increase will apply to ships of all other nations, except those of the United States, which are protected by Treaty, and those of the Netherlands, which enjoy simple Most Favoured Nation treatment; and (b) that if any ships so protected in the opinion of His Majesty^ Government in the United Kingdom exploit their Treaty advantage to the detriment of British trade or shipping the right of withdrawing this acquiescence immediately is reserved by His Majesty's Government. 4. I am to request Your Highness to be good enough to inform me whether you are prepared to accept the understandings in question.-— 1 mmlU^ -2,4319/32. 18th August,1932. Sir. In reply to Sir E.Howell 1 s letter of 11th May, ij D.1673-H/32, I am directed 'by the Secretary of State to say that he agrees with tbeGovernment of India in their general acceptance of Sir Hugh Biscoe T s views as set out in his letter of 7th April, No. 215-S, in regard to the policy to be pursued in future dealings with the Muscat State. 0 WU-f K 3^ ^ f 2. Tiie D ecretary of State sympathises witl: the desire of the Sultan of Muscat, as recorded in paragraph 5 of Sir Hugh Biscoe's despatch of 7th April, to be at liberty to modify or to determine the treaties of 1833 and 1844 with the Government of the United States and the French Government respectively. Those treaties were concluded in circumstances very different from those which prevail at the present day and the attitude of the new ruler in regard to them is understandable. In the light of the observations in &gt; / o &gt; paragraphs 3 and 4 of the Government of India* s letter under reply, enquiries were accordingly made of the Foreign Office as to the possibility of denunciation or modification. The observations of the Secretary or s tate for Foreign ACTairs are contained in Foreign Office ecretary to the Government of India, Foreign and Political Department, Simla. letter1^ A. m letter of 19th July, Ho. E. 3243/4/91, of which copies were sent to the Government of India and to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf by the mail of 21st July. It will be seen that while, in Sir John Simon f s opinion, it seems likely that on the basis of strict law the Muscat State could, upon giving reasonable notice, denounce its treaties with France and the United StateS, or at least the provisions in them which are of a commercial nature, the political objections to any such action on its part are substantial. The Government of India, in their letter under reply, had already expressed their apprehension that the denunciation of the treaties would inevitably be attributed to the influence of His Majesty 1 s Government and not to the spontaneous policy of the Sultan of Muscat, that it ?/ould be regarded as almost an unfriendly act and would certainly cause resentment out of all proportion to the advantage to be gained. The Secretary of State is in agreement with these views, which, as will be seen, are in accord with the conclusions of the Secretary: .of State for Foreign Affairs, and the position being as it is he is forced to the conclusion, though with much regret, that no advance is possible in this matter at present (save, of course, to the extent to which provisions in the treaties may be modified by negotiation and mutual consent), and that the. Sultan should be iven no encouragement to contemplate unilateral denunciation either of the whole or of the commercial clauses only of the Muscat treaties with France and the United States. 3. A copy of this letter is being sent to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, I am. Sir, Your obedient Servant, (Sd.) J. C. WALTON.Confidential No. 640-S of 1932 Gopy forwarded to the Political Agent, Muscat, in continuation of this Ofrice Printed Letter No.570-S dated 12th August 1932, for information only. If His • u lghness the Sultan raises the question again, /fe matter should referred to the Hon'hie the Political Besident. By Order for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. British Residency and Consulate-General, Bushire. Bated 9th September 193® o Muscat tariff treaties Letter No. P.Z.4319/32, dated 18th August 1932, from the Secretary of State for India to the G-overnment of india in the foreign and Political department.3^ {ofr coroiasiOTiAL. Prom Ho.J'.i70-]j/32. The Foreign Secretary to the Go varment of India • ^ ^ated Simla, the k M 0 The Hon*ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, September 19 32 I *m directed to refer to India Office letter Ho. . Pe 2* 4319/32» dated the IStli August 19 32, copy of wfrich Tflfas sent to you direct, and to say that future dealings with the Mi scat state should be conducted in accordance with the views expressed in the late Sir Hugh Biscoe's despatch lo. 215-3 of 1932, dated the 7th April 1932. 2. i am to add that the Sultan should be given no encourage-ment to contemplate unilateral denunciation either by the whole or of the commercial clauses only of the Muscat treaties with France and the United 3tate s. Copy forwarded to the Political Agent, ^usoat, for information only, under P.L.No. 732-S of 30tti 3ept. 1932. I have the honour to be Sir, Your most obedient servant Ibreign Secretary to the Government of India,C0F5IDENTIAL. I WO.F.225-1T/29. A copy of the undementloned paper i s forwarded to the Hon'tie the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, in continuation of endorsement from the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, Ho. F. 825-11/29, dated the 5th July 1932, 2. No action should be taken on this communication which is sent for information only. i*,, By order, etc., moHvii Assistant Secretary to the Grovernment of India. Foreign and Political Department. S i m 1 a ; The 6^ Oototer 19 32. Letter from, the Dominions Office to the Minister for External Affairs, Irish Free State, Ho. 182( Confidential) dated the 2nd September 1932.y p.Z. 5400/32. \0&gt; Enclosur e in Dominions Office covering letter dated 5rd September 1935, Ho, 8327/29. IRISH mm STATig. No. 182. CONFIDENTIAL. Downing Street, 2nd September, 1932. Sir, I have the hon^our to acknowledge the receipt of - J [ a your despatch Ko.124 of the 19th August stating that f /V- His Majesty's Grovernment in the Irish Free State have no observations to offer on the proposed modification of the tariff provisions of the Commercial Treaty with Muscat of the 18th March, 1891. 2. I should explain that, in reply to the representations of His Majesty's Ambassador in Paris, based on the despatch enclosed in Mr.Thomas' confidential 1 / '■ ' despatch No.216 of the 5th September, 1931, the French Government intimated that they were prepared to consent to a modification of their treaty so as to permit the levying of higher Gust cms duties on goods imported into Muscat in French vessels, provided that the United States Government gave their consent to a similar modification of their rights. Negotiations with the United States Government have however proved unsuccessful since it is now their general policy not to enter into fresh arrangements providing for the levying of specific rates of import duty on goods of United States origin and they are unwilling to make an exception in this particular case. Their attitude is, in brief, that they cannot be a party to any revised scale of duties but that they would have no objection to the grant of full tariff i ——•— ——gftit on omy/ Minister for Bxternal Affair8,ENCLOSURE Ki W ch . Irish Free State. No. *36 SEP. FROM 8ECRETARV, / SECRET DEPT. tKOU OFFICEjU^ autonomy to Muscat on terms which provided for the grant of most-favoured-nation treatment to United States nationals and goods. These terms the Muscat Government have already rejected as unacceptable, since they would involve the grant of special privileges to United States citizens, such as are at present enjoyed only by British and French nationals. 3. The difficulty caused by the United States treaty is however purely formal, as no United States vessels at present participate in Muscat trade, and there is no prospect that any will participate. Since His Majesty's Government in the United Kingdon do not consider it proper to urge the Muscat Government to grant a substantial political concession, the idea of which they dislike, in return for an arrangement designed to obviate a purely formal difficulty, the proposal to modify the existing treaties has been abandoned. The financial situation of Muscat, however, still makes it imperative that the customg rates should be raised, and it has therefore been necessary to consider seme other means of attaining the end desired. 4. The procedure now favoured by His Msjesty's government in the United Kingdom and the Government of India, after consultation with the French Government, is that a note should be addressed on their behalf by the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf to His Highness the Sultan of Muscat to the effect that despite the provisions of Article 6 of the Treaty of 1891, which Treaty will remain in force, no objection will be raised to an increase of customs duties to 1($ (2®£ on tobacco and on alcoholic liquor of SB or more degrees under proof). It will be stated that this acquiescence is only given on/IU1 on the understanding (a) that a similar increase will apply to the ships of all other nations, except those of the United States, ^hich, as stated in Mr. Thomas 1 despatch of the 5th September, 1931, are protected 'by a Treaty of 1833, and of the Netherlands, which enjoy most-favoured nation treatment (To) that if any ships so protected exploit their treaty advantage the right is reserved of immediately withdrawing this acquiescence. The draft of the note which it is proposed to address to His Highness is enclosed. 5. This proposal has been submitted to the French Government who have intimated their willingness that a note in similar terms and subject to a similar understandfing should be addressed to the Sultan on their behalf, and as there is no French representative in Muscat, they have requested the good offices of His Majesty's Government in the United Kingdom in the matter. 6. His Majesty's Government in the United Kingdom feel confident that in the present difficult circumstances the above policy will commend itself to His Majesty's Government in the Irish Free State and they trust therefore that His Majesty's Government in the Irish Free State will be willing to authorise the presentation of a similnr note to the Muscat Government on their behalf. 7. As the question is now one of urgency it would be appreciated if intimation of the wishes of His Majesty's Government in the Irish Free State could be given at an early date. 8. A similar enquiry is being made of His Majesty's Government in Canada. His Majesty's Government in the Union of South Africa have already signified their desire to withdraw from the Treaty. I have, etc., (Sgd.) J.H.Thomas.8337/29. \J C%.Lx Oivi ^ • t5ent 2.50 p.m. SCth August 193S) IMPORTANT. 3S[0.89. Confidential . ,r My despatch'of the 5th September, 1931, Uo.505 Commercial Treaty with Muscat. The French Government consented to a modification of their treaty rights on the lines which we suggested subject to the concurrence of the United States Government in a similar modification of their rights. Negotiations with the tJ. S.Government have however proved unsuccessful since it is now their general policy not to enter into fresh arrangements providing for the levying of specific rates of import duty on goods of U.S.origin and they are unwilling to make an exception in this particular case. Their position is therefore that they cannot be a party to any revised scale of duties but they would have no objection to the grant of full tariff autonomy to Muscat on terms which provided for the grant of most-favoured-nation treatment to U.S.nationals and goods. These terms the Muscat Government have already rejected as unacceptable, since they would involve the grant of special privileges to United Stp.tes citizens, such ^s are at present enjoyed only by British and French nationals. The difficulty caused by the United States treaty is however purely formal, since no United States vessels participate in the Muscat trade and there is no prospect that any will do so. We do not consider it proper to urge the Muscat Government to grant a substantial political concession of which they dislike the idea in order to obviate a purely formal difficulty caused ^y/| oil by a treaty whicb in this respect ia out of harmony with present day conditions. On the other hand the financial situation of Muscat still renders an increase in the customs duties imperative and we have accordingly had to consider some other method of attaining the end desired. The procedure which we now favour, after consultation with the French Government, is that a note should he addressed to the Muscat Government to the effect that, despite Article 6 of the 1891 Treaty, which Treaty will remain in force, no objection will be raised on behalf of His Majesty's Oovernr-ent in the United Kingdor and the Government of India to an increase in the customs duties to 10^ (25% on tobacco and on alcoholic liquor of 25 or more degrees under proof). It will be stated, however, that this acquiescence is subject to the understanding (a) that a similar increase will apply to ships of all other nations, except those of the United States (which, as stated in my despatch under reference, are protected by Treaty) and of the Netherlands (which enjoy most-favoured-nation treatment) (b) that if any ships so protected exploit their Treaty advantage the right is reserved of immediately withdrawing this acquiescence. As stated above, no exploitation is expected from United States vessels, and we are also satisfied that none will come from Butch vessels. We have approached the French Government on these lines and they are willing that a note in similar terms and subject to a similar understanding should be addressed to the Muscat Government on their behalf by the local British representative. We/We are confident that in the present difficult circumstances above policy will commend itself to H.M. Oovernment in Canada and we trust therefore that they will be willing to authorise the presentation of a similar note to the Muscat Government on their behalf. As the question is now one of urgency we should be grateful for the earliest possible reply by telegraph. A aimilnr enquiry is being made of His Majesty* s Government in the Irish Free State. His Majesty's Government in the TTnion of South Africa have already signified their desire to withdraw from the Treaty*5753/32, Enclosure in Dominions Office coverins letter Jo.8327/33 dated 21st September, 19 32# Telegram from the Secretary of State for ISxternal Affairs Canada to the Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs, Dated 19th September, 1932. (Received, Dominions Office, 10.50 p.m. 19th September, 1932). { XS jJ &lt;&lt;^ Important.V Ho.133o Confidential, Your telegram dated 30th August, No.89. The Canadian Government authorise the presentation of note on their behalf to Muscat Government on the lines of note set forth in your telegram under reference. ENOtOSU.-ig IN T~' No. ess p QCIr „ ^ SgC R £T ARy SECRET DEP t 'u.«. V al copy SENT To /wyOx.;C op^ of Appenaix *■ of uszette of mdia v extraordinary; aaxea ine 13th October i95&lt;i« Xhe convention of iat .uermsin-en-^aye, 1919, is tlie last of three international agreements, the other two being the General Act of merlin, ^885, and the General Act and .Decla ration of .Brussels, .890. .hese instruments are commonly referred to as the -uoiago iasin ireaties-, though their operation extends far beyond the uongo jjasin. contain provisions relating to a variety of subjects including the suppression of slavery and the slave trade, the navigation ol certain African rivers ana the protection of life and property in Ainca; out the only provisions of importance for the present purpose are those which provide for commercial equality between the nationals of the signatory states in an area extending rignt across Africa, ana including what is now tne whule oi the Belgian wongo, iienya, Uganda, tanganyika, Zanzibar, ana ayasailftna, part of northern Rhodesia, and parts sunounaing j-iench, Italian and Portuguese territory. / the ijerlin Act provided for a regime of complete free trade in this area, .ne arusaela Act ana declaration modified this provision *y allowing auties up, to xO per cent subject to the Proviso that there shoula oe no uiscrimination in favour of aay ihe Convention of at. (iermain removed the limitation* tne amount oi tne auties that could be levied but proviual specifically against any form of discrimination. Xhe parties to the merlin Act ana to tUe general Act and •beclarottion oi isrustele were ureat Britain, Belgium, xtaly, i'oitugal, ™ ce , uerfflany&gt; Au8tria&gt; ^ «ussia, xurKey, ^ ana .orway. lh e paxtie8 to tlle of ^ ueriB6in &amp;re ^itam, the ^^0™ and mdi loweT^' ' rtUSai ' ^ ranCe ' ana ja P an - As between these latt, 8 ^ 'oaveation of a t. Germain abro jates the earlier instru- - instruments-instruments• f The convention of a t. Oermain provided that the sig natory rovers ehoula teaseemcle at the end of ten years fro ra its coming into force in order to introduce into it such modifi cations at experience mignt have shown to be necessary, awards the ena of this perioa of ten years the position .as careful^ consioereu hy n.s ^jesty-s uovernment in the .nited kingdom in consultation with trading and shipping interests and with iixs Majesty representatives in the uolonies concerned, .he general consensus oj opinion at the time was in favour of main taining the existing position. After this review of the matter nis Majesty's Government in the united kingdom informed the other Powers parties to the invention that they saw no occasion for holding a inference i^edia te^. .hey accordingly suggested that it should be ppstponed until 19 35. .ome of the .owers accep. ted this proposal and others sent no reply. ms majesty's Government were asked in the House of ^ords ^n June .932, whether the continuance of the .ongo . as in .reatieJ vas m accordance with the present policy of the ..pire. and if not what steps were being ta^en to effect their denunciation, .orfi Templemore•s reply on beh&amp;lf of the uovernment included statements hey v. ere giving their earnest consideration to the whole Lfcteclaiiy as re ^ aras . ts bearing on uttaBa and otter taiciug place, ana ^ that he was informed that 6 tt0Ula ^ ratil - — international oostacles in the of 'ngmg the present regime to an ena. (sd; J.c .ij, urate. Secretary to the uovernment of India.v - / / t AIR }ilAlL . P. 2. s By -gSA-ma. fC- Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office, for the information I of the Political Resident, Bushire. India Office, Whitehall, London, S.W.I. Copy sent to 1/ oP.z. 6648/32 Enclosure in Dominions Office Covering Latter No.8327/33 dated lat Novetaber, 1934,. IRISH FRES BTAI1 No. 214. Downing Street, 29th October, 1952. Sir, I have the honour to refer to my Confidential despatch Mo.162 of the 2nd September, regarding a suggested increase of Customs duties in Muscat, and to state, for the information of His Majesty's Government in the Irish Free State, that His Majesty's Government in Canada have expressed concurrence in the procedure outlined in my despatch and have requested that a similar note may be addressed to His Highness the Sultan of Muscat on their behalf. 2. The Government of India are anxious, in view of the acute financial situation in Muscat, that the necessary action should be taken without delay and, in the circumstances, it would be greatly appreciated if intimation of the wishes of His Majesty's Govern ent in the Irish Free State could be given at as early a date as possible. I have, etc., (Sgd. ) J. H. THOMAS The Minister for External Affairs, Irish Free State.357 / AIR MAIL. By — /; I I Olte' ^'eSMSHTiAl sFFiDEHCYjJ ntjb^ Forwarded with tiie compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office, for the information of the Political Resident, Bushire. India Office, Whitehall, London, S«W,1. Copy sent to&lt;D ! ^ P.Z. 7111/32. Enclosure in lioiainions Office covering note dated 23rd November, 1932. DOMING STHEET. 23 Hovember, 1932 # /■ ^ / Bear Walshe, I wonder if you could let m© know whether we xaajj/ shortly expect a reply to our confix a nti al despatches Xio«182 of the 2nd September and No.214= of the 29th October regarding s suggested ineree.se of Custoias duties in Muscat. The Government of India, to whom the financial situation in Muscat is a matter of serious concern, are pressing for the earliest possible action to be taken and an intimation of the wishes of the Irish ffree State Soyernment would be greatly appreciated. Yours, &amp;e., {Sgd. ) C.W, 13HS ESQ. (1/^ 1V 3 ! p.z. ? AIR IliLIL SSA=i£±$$ O Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office, for the. information of the Political Resident, Bushire. India Office, Whitehall, London, S.W.I. Copy sent toP.Z.7717/32. Downing Street. 8327/35. 20th December,1932. /• \l Dear Gilbert, Your letter No.P.Z.7111/32 of the 10th December about the Muscat tariff, I am thankful to say that the / receipt of the enclosed despatch from the Irish Free State has relieved me from having to answer your hypothetical ^TConTTl question. You will no doubt agree that the despatch i 1.12.54!. J very satisfactory, and we assume that there will be no difficulty about sending a note to the Sultan in the form of the Free State draft. I enclose also a draft note, which might suitably be sent on behalf of the Canadian G -overnment in accordance with their telegram of the 19th September, of which copies were sent to the India Office on the 21st September under reference 8327/33. I am sending copies of this letter and enclosures r to Helm at the Foreign Office and Jenkins at the Board of Trade. Will you send us copies of the communication which you will no doubt now send to the Government of India? Yours ever, (Sd. ) T.A.Cluterbuck P. S. The Irish Free State are rather 'touchy 11 about the phraseology of the notes which they draft themselves, so I hope it will be possible for the Political Resident to conform to their exact wording. (copy with copy of enclosures sent to Muscat under P»L.]?o.55-S of 19/1/33).P.Z.7717/32. . A VkA ^50. Despatch No,162 . CONFIDENTIAL. DEPARTMSHT OP EXT]2HNAL APPAIRS, IRISH PREE STATE. 15tli Decenber, 1932. Sir, A P 5 I have tjie honour to refer to your confidential despatch No.214 of the 29th OctolDer, regarding a suggested increase of Customs duties in Muscat, and to ask if you would be so good as to arrange to have the Political jSegitigjrt in the Persian Gulf address a Note in the terms of the enclosed draft to His Highness the Sultan of Muscat* I have, &amp;c # , (Sd) EAMOH DJS VALERA* Minister for External Affairs $it Honourable The Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs, Downing Street, LONDON , S.W.I.___________ mmm* on.' r DEPARTMEifT OP SXTERUAX APPAIRS, 5 .7717/32. IRISH PHEE STATE. Your Highness, I have the honour at the instance of the Government of the Irish Pree State to inform Your Highness tnat no objection would te raised iDy them to an increase in the Customs duties of the Muscat State to on tobacco , , 55 ^ ^ ana on alcoholic liquor of S5 or more degrees under proof) despite the provisions of Article 6 of the Treaty of Commerce 0 .1 19th March, 1891, concluded 'by Her Majesty^ the ^ueen of Great Britain and Ireland with His Highness the Sultan of Muscat, which Treaty the Government of the ^rish Pree State have hitherto regarded and will henceforth regard as continuing to he of full force and effect between them and Your Highness. 2, The concurrence of the Government of the Irish Pree State in action on these lines will, however, be subject to the understanding;- (a) that a similar increase will apply to ships of all other nations, except those of the United States, which are protected by Treaty, and those of the Netherlands, which enjoy simple most-favoured-nation treatment; and (b) that if any ships so protected in the opinion of the Government of the ^rish Pree State exploit their Treaty advantage to the detriment of the trade or shipping of the Irish Pree State, the right of withdrawing this acquiescence immediately is reserved by the Government of the Irish Pree State.Draft Note to the Sultan of Muscat. Dominions Office. Your Highness, I have the honour to inform Your Highness, at the instance of His Majesty's Government in Canada, that no objection would be raised by them to an increase of customs duties to 10% (259o on tobacco and on alcoholic liquor S S -b** of or more degrees under proof) despite the provisions of Article 6 of the Treaty of Commerce of 19th March, 1891, which Treaty shall remain in force. The concurrence of His Majesty's Grovernment in Canada in action on these lines will, however, be subject to the understanding: (a) that a similar increase will apply to ships of all other nations, except those of the United States which are protected by Treaty, and those of the Netherlands, which enjoy simple Most Favoured Nation treatment: and (b)(b) that if any ships so protected in the opinion of His Majesty's Government in Canada exploit their Treaty advantage to the detriment of Canadian trade or shipping the right of withdrawing this acquiescence immediately is reserved by His Majesty's (xovemnent in Canada.a h^ s v r 814/4/91) P. Z. ;i22 I '^J v 1 !&gt; FOHEIIG-N OFFICE, S.W.I. 3rd January, 1932. A V. V.y Lord, g-^jr-i OSURE. IN FOREIGN OFFICE COVERING LETTER DAT ED _—^ &lt;P n Witli reference to my despatch Ko.l7Qg (F&gt; 3981/4/91) of the 16th August regarding the proposed modification of the Muscat treaties t 1 transmit to Your lordship the accompanyinp drafts of the note on this subject which His Majesty's Government propose to address to the Sultan of Muscat on behalf of the French Government and of that which they will address to His Highness in their own name. E. I shall he glad if you will comunicate both these drafts to the French Government and will inform me as soon as possible whether they concur in the terms of the note which it is proposed to present on their behalf. I am, with great truth and respect, My lord. Your Excellency^ obedient Servant, (For the Secretary of State) a . v ' PTT 1 No. 2 .12 JAN.! 1933 FROM 8 £0fi £TAflY # PyLN a AHD SECRET DEPT, IHJIA OFFICE ■ oellenoy f ^ p Sight Honourable li^-f. ^ v/-^/ 3^ (^.0^- cf, | lord Tyrrell, tt .C.M.S. , K.C.B., (fo - q-/^- etc., etc., etc.. i-aris, i yv/h k-l»22/V 9i ' French Hota. P.Z.4971/23 DRAFT. Your Highness, As your Highness is aware. Your Highness ? predecessorp His Highness Saiyid Taiiaur Bin F^isul, E.C.I.E*. C«8oIft» on the 9th March 1920 requested His Majesty r s Government in the United Kingdom to approach the Government of the French Republic on his behalf with a view to obtaining a revision of those clauses of the Treaty of Commerce between the Iiaam of Muscat and His Majesty the Zing of the French dated 17th November 1844 and ratified on 4th February, 1846, under which the customs duties which may be imposed on goods imported by French vessels are restricted to 5^ ad valorem* 2c2® As Your Highness is aware it has proved necessary to seek a different method of securing for your Highness the relief in ^uestion^ I am now instructed to say that His Majesty's Government have heen requested by the Government of the French Republic to address to Your Highness on their behalf a communioation on the subject similar to that which has this day been addressed to you on behalf of His Majesty S s Government in the United Kingdomo I am therefore to inform Your Highness on behalf of the Government of the French .Republic that no objection would be raised by them to an Increase of customs duties to lofo on goods imported by French vessels into Muscat (26j5 on tobacco and on rr u , r o alcoholic liquor of 35 or more degrees under proof) despite the provisions in Article 10 of the Treaty of 1844 which treaty shall remain in force.. The concurrenceooncurrenoQ of the Government of the French Republic in action on these lines will, however, be subject to the understandings (a) that a similar increase will a Pply to ships of all other nations , except those of the United States^ which are protected by Treaty, and those of the Netherlands, which enjoy simple Most Favoured Nation treatment; and (b) that if any ships so protected in the opinion of the Government of the French Republic exploit their Treaty advantage to the detriment of French trade or shipping the right of withdrawing this acquiescence imraediately is reserved by the Government of the French Republic# M. wi-f-y 3^ ]British Note. cZ.4971/3S &lt;k Your Higtinesaj As Your Hi^hnesis is aware# your Highness 1 predecessor, His Hifchneas Sui^id Talmur Bin Faisul, K a C,IaE., C.S^I., on the 9th March 1930 intimated to His Majesty's Government in the United Kingdom that the necessity had arisen for increasing the customs duties of the Muscat state for revenue purposes. His Highness requested His Majesty's Government in the United Kingdom to approach the Governments of France and of the United States of America respectively on his behalf to obtain a revision of those clauses of the Treaty of Amity and commerce between the United States of America and His Highness Said Syed dated Slst September 1833 and the Treaty of Commeroe betweenjV between the liaam of Moocat and Hie Majesty the King of the Pronch dated 17th November 1844 and ratified on 4th February 1846, under which the cuetoma duties which may be levied on goods imported by vessels of those countries into Kascat are limited to dfo ad valorem His Highness further requested that the tariff provisions of the Treaty of Comoerce made between Her late Majesty Queen Victoria and the sultan of Muscat mi^ht be modified in the same sense* Your Highness is also aware that the United States Government have found themselves unable to agree to the modification of their Treaty of 1833, save on conditions which your Highness has not found acceptable. His Majesty 1 © Government in the United Kingdom and the Government of the French Republic have therefore considered the other methods by which, in so far as they are concerned, steps could beni be token to meet Tour HiglinesB 1 wishes. So a separate common ic Action is being addreaeed to Your Highness on behalf of the Government of the French RepublicI am now instructed to inform Your Highness on behalf of His Majesty^ Government in the United Kingdom that no objection would be raised by them to an increase of customs duties to 10^ (25^ on tobacco and on alcoholic liquor of 26 -or-iaore degrees under proof) despite the provisions of Article 6 of the treaty of Commerce of 19 March 1891 P which freaty shall remain in force» The concurrencs of Kis Majesty's aovernment in action on these lines will, however, be subject to the understandings (a) that a similar increase will a Pply ^0 ships of all other nations^ except those of the United States, which areare protected by Treaty, and tho^e of the JTwtherlands, which enjoy simple Mo«;t Favoured Nation treatment; and (hj that if any shipe bo protected in the opinion of His Maje&amp;ty'b Government in the Onited Kingdom exploit their Treaty advantapa to the detriment of British trade or shipping the right of withdrawing this acquiescence immediately is reserved by His Majesty'a Government.fjOUgXaEKTIAfc . V^ No.C/^^ of 1»33. The Political Agency &amp; K.B.SI's Consulate, Kuscat,7th March 1»33. /7. From l U8 HWg WyMNgL ^ ^V r i » , '■ r. Ifejor G. E. IT, Bremner, M.G., I.A, Polxt^cal Agent &amp; H.B.M 1 ^ Consul, Muscat. To The Hon^le tjae Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Buahire. Subject s- Increase of Customs duty in Muscat State. Sir. KVlk i have the honour to f orward herewith a copy of a letter dated 4th IJarch 1933 received from His Highness the Sultan on the a'bove subject. 2. It is obvious that His Highness cannot increase the Customs tariff on British imports till such time as the general increase of duty has been agreed upon by other Governments who are parties to a treaty with Kuscat State. 3. Negotiations are at present in progress with these Governments and conversations appear to -ave reached an advanced state. 4. in the meanwhile it would seem most inadvisable for His Highness to announce an increase in the existing Customs duties.,! at this stage^even should those Governments who have been approached afford their assent. 5. Primarily, trade is only just showing a slight tendency to improve. Secondly, at many of the more remote ports in IvSiscat State it is comparatively recently that the Customs duty now imposed has been successfully enforced and accepted, perhaps as a necessary evil, by the local trader. To increase the existing tariffs in these circumstances would therefore seem to be fraught with difficulties and trou bles which could m no way be compensated for by a dubious in crease in State revenue./7&gt; '/• X propose to i&gt;oint out these facts to His Highness privately and X am convinced he wxll see the logic of them when they are expxamed to him. b. Meanviiiiie^ as it is unlikely that the result of tne negotiations referred to in paragraph (3) above will mature 'before His Highness 1 departure for Phofar, the likelihood of any early action by the State is remote, I have the honour to be» Sir, Your most obedient servant, Maj or, Political Agent &amp; H.B.M's Consul* Muscat.letter dated 7th Dhil ^deh 135! (4th March 1933) from H.IU the Sultan of Muscat &amp; Ctean, to Major C.E.U .BreMner. M.C.. Political Agent &amp; H.B.M's Consul, Muscat. A* C. You are well aware that my father approached your Government on the subject of increasing the Customs duty and authorised our friend the Government to address the French and American Governments who have treaty with my State to that effect. It is uat a long time since the question was brought up hut so far nothing has transpired. You are aware the had financial position of my Government. ITow I would only like to know if our friend the (ioverment would agree to my increasing the Customs duty as was explained in my previous communications which X do not mention in this letter. I request you to submit my request to the Government as soon as possible. I am confident that the Government will agree to increasing the Customs duty as they have the interest of my Government at heart for which X m always grateful to them#•e.Z./V ForwardetT' with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office, for the information of the Political Resident, Bushire. India Office, Whitehall, London, S.W.I. Copy sent toz. 1249/33 IHDIA OFFICE WHITEHALL, S .W.I. IMMEDIATE. 10th March 1933. Would you please refer to Foreign Office letter Ho.E 1015/1015/91 of 3rd March, a copy of which, was sent to the Board of Trade, regarding the proposed increase in the Muscat tariff. You will have seen that the French Government have now agreed to the dra^t .-note which we propose to address to the Sultan on their behalf subject to amendment of the passage about alcoholic liquor which was founded on a misinterpretation of their note of 29th September 1931. It is clear from that note and frcm the French note of 20th February 1933 (copy enclosed with Foreign Office letter under reference) that 'boissons titrant 25°' are intended to represent the minimum strength of alcoholic liquor subject to the 25^ duty, and it is therefore suggested that the relevant passage in the notes to be presented on behalf of the French Government and of His Majesty 1 s Governments in the United Kingdom, Canada and Irish Free State, after amendment in the sense desired by the French, should read '25%' on tobacco and on alcoholic liquor of 35 or less (not more ) degrees under proof'. I understand that Nash of your Industries &amp; Manufactures department, with whom Cronbie of this department has discussed the point, agrees that the less degrees under proof the stronger the liquor. •G.Jenkins, Esq., M.C., Board of Trade, S.W.I.Ill 2, 2. We should be grateful if the Board of Trade could confirm this and let us know as soon as possible whether they agree with the alteration of the notes to the Sultan-in the sense desired by the French Government. I understand that the Dominions Office are waiting for the views of the Board of Trade before agreeing to the alteration of the Canadian and Irish Free State notes. We hope that it will not be necessary to consult the Irish Free State about this small amendment, since we are now very anxious to get the Muscat tariff question disposed of expeditiously. 3. I am sending a copy of this letter to Clutterbuck and Warner. Yours sincerely. a. c A ■ n™. JtST-S fa./n-s y -2.^/3?,./ Vo P 0 Z *1249/33 FOREIGN OFFICE, S.W.I No.E 1015/1015/91 # 3rd March, 1933. With reference to Forei©! Office letter No.E 6814/4/91 of the 5th January, regarding the proposed modification of the Muscat treaties, I am directed by Secretary Sir John Simon to trajismit to you, to be Md before Secretary Sir [ Sainuel Hoare, the accompanying copy of a despatch from His ^ majesty 1 s Ambassador at Paris enclosing the observations of ^ Lr the French Government on the draft notes to be addressed to IV^j the Sultan of Muscat on behalf of His Majesty's Government in the United Kingdom and the French Government respecting the proposed increase in the Muscat tariff. 2 9 It appears that the fifeare intended by the French Government as the minimum strength of dutiable liquor to be imported into Muscat has been wrongly interpreted since its \ | first proposal in their note of the 29th September, 1931, (a copy of which was sent to the India Office under cover of Foreign Office letter No.E 4955/267/91 of the 6th October, 1931), Sir John Simon sees no objection, so far as this department is concerned, to the emendation of the two draft notes in the sense proposed in the note of the 20th February from the French Ministry of Foreign Affairs, and I am to suggest that, if Sir S # Hoare and the Board of Trade (to which department a copy of this letter is being sent) share this view, the draft notes should now be sent to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf for communication to the Sultan of Muscat at an early date* 3. A copy of this letter is also being sent to the Dominions Office. I am, etc. fcder Secretary of State, India Office.I ' v&gt; .1249/33 copy. (S 1015/1015/91) No.248 (55/3/33) Hie Majesty's Representative at Paris presents his coraplintents to the Secretary of State for Poreigi Affaire, and has the honour to transmit to him the undermentioned documents. British Embassy, Paris, 21st February, 1933. i' Reference to previous correspondence: Foreign Office despatch No. 9 (E 6814/4/91) of 3rd Janu Descri-ption of Encloeure. Name and Date. Subject. Prom: Proposed modification of Ministry for Foreigp Affairs, the Muscat treaties. Paris. 2)th February, 1933,COHPIDEKTIAL, ^//if No.C/80 of 1933, The Political Agency &amp; H.B.M'e Consulate, Muscat, 21st March 1933. I i 11 i ■ From 1MM. Major Co U» Bremner, Political .Agent &amp; HoB.M's Consul, M u s e a t« To The Hon^ble the political Resident^ in the Persian Gulf, Bushire® he. 'jjihi flONflfit 't i mi itiOSBii Subject;- Increase of Customs duty in Muscat State. Sir, Ijl ; I hove the honour to acknowledge receipt of your telegram Ho.175 dated 16th March 1933ft 2. I represented my views to His Highness at an inter- Tiew on the ISth instant. 3. The Sultan was most grateful for the expression of my opinion with which he was in entire agreement® 4. His Highness informed me that it was not his inten tion, even when the assent to the increased rates of duty was received, to put up the tariff all round. He proposed to gradually raise the duty on certain non-essentials such as intoxicating liquorsi tobacco, silks &amp;c as a tentative measure and thereafter to reflect before making further additions to the list of goods to pay enhanced rates. 5. I consider that His Highness' attitude in the matter is excellent and shows considerable wisdom and foresight. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, A Major 3 f' i 1 ^ 0lltlcal Agent &amp; H.B.M'e Consul, Musest/ u / P. 2,1448/33. I.H.I. 142/33. M dpr*' TQ ' ^ - \ ' /bo ard o p trads s USHTRFmE SI DR NC V^J ^ GRS^T GiiOHGii STHSST, S.W.I. i&amp;rch 1933. Wdear Lalthwalt^ ( flDKfi; ' NmMoom ] I have again gone Into tiie question the agreenient about the proposed increase In the Miscut tariff, about ;/(f' which you wrote to me yesterday (P.Z. 1249/33). we were already considering the matter when your letter arrived, * since it seemed to us that the French conversion of 25 degrees In their scale into our scale was arltbmetlcally wrong. 25 degrees of the French scale is equivalent in our scale to about 55 degrees under proof, not 35 as is stated In the enclosure to the despatch from Paris. I asked Johnstone whether he had any iaeans of checking the accuracy of the copy, but he tells me that the original of the French reply is In Paris, and they will have to get the matter looked into there. I am sending him a copy of this letter, and on receipt of it he will no doubt make the necessary enquiries. 3o far as we are concerned we should accept the wording you suggest, subject to the substitution of 55 for 35, that is to say - *25% on tubaceo and on alcoholic liquor of 55 or less degrees under proof.* An alternative solution would be to substitute a reference to the French scale for the reference to our own scale, and the provision might then be '25% on tobacco and on Icoholic liquor containing 25^ or more by volume of alcohol.* For political reasons, however, the Foreign Office would no aoubt prefer to stick to our own scale rather than aaopt the French scale in a diplomatic document. You/ i Laithwalte, Esq-, Inula Office, Whitehall, 3.W. 1./ You will no doubt have observed that the French proposal will let In their wines at the lower rate of duty and that practically speaking the only alcoholic liquors which will pay the higher duty &amp;re spirits. Since we ourselves make a distinction of the same kind in our duties, I do not think we could very sell object, but in view of the lapse of time I think that anyhow we must accept the position. The Canadian and Irish Free State Governments have accepted toe draft note - afaich was obviously wrong in this particular - without any comment, am I should think that it would be quitSiynnecessary to consult them before making the alteration, though no doubt their attention should be called to it when the final note is conmunicuted to them. Ihe point is, 1 Should think, of no practical importance to them. 1 an aending a copy of this letter to Clutterbuck ana Johnstone. Yours, etc. (3d.) T.G. JSNKINS. (Copy forwarded to Muscat under P.L.Ho.353-3 of 8/4/44). Ref.our p.l.No.255-3 of 21/3/33. ^ ^'79,hmam. ■, ^ r- No. P. zijw V, No. P. 225-N ' v bp«™i I A C0 P y 0 - 1 1:118 undermentloifeta^paper Is fonmrded to I one Hon'Me the Political Resident In the Persian Gulf, i In continuation of endorsement from the Government of India In the Foreign and Political Department No. I 225 -iI. /29, dated the 24th Pehruary 1933. ho action should he taken on this communication which Is forwarded for Information only. By order ^etc., Assistant Secretary to the Government of India Foreign and Political Department, New Delhi; The Apr 11 1933 * m ! , 0 Letter from the Foreign Office to the India Office Ho. E. 1015/1015/91, dated the 3rd March 1933 with il enclosure.By \Hk imt MAIL - SFJi^tguTT, Forwarded, with the compliments of the Secretary Political Department, India Office, for the information of the Political Resident, Bushire. India Office, Whitehall, London, S.W.I, Copy sent to fcon 1 P.S. 2097/35. Ilnnloaures in Foreign Office Letter Ko.S.1821/1015/91, dated 11th April, 1933. | FOREIO® OFFICiS, 821/1015/91). S.W.I. 10th April, 1933. Bear Jenkins, As agreed in our con?ersation to-day over the telephone regarding the proposed nodi fie lion of the yusest tariffs, I send yea herewith copy of the letter from the Paris Chancery on this subject trans itting a copy of the last French note. 2, The following diffieultiee strike in this note:- (a) To take the last fir«t, it looks frosn the concluding sentence as if the French had not understood how the 'proof' seal* works. They suggest that when we give *95 or leoe degroea under proof ae the strength of dutiable liquor, we really mean 'or isarft*« Unless ti ^y want to make weak liquor and not stron - liquor dutiable, I do not roe hor this can possibly sake sense. (b) On the other hand, they say that they would be eontont if 35 degrees under proof nd not 55 degreos sere aade the taxation limit. As this is represented ae a coiressdon, it gives the impreanion that they do realise which way the scale works, i.e. that in dropping from 55 to 35 degress t eyare acteitting duty free liquor of a strength 20 degrees greater than we propose. (c) Lastly, there is the question of the actual limiting figure. It was at the request of the French UmWM &amp; TM t at we accepted the figure 25 (centeaiwal) x degrees (see the French note of the 20th February, a copy P»Jenkin8, Esq. ,M.C., Board of Trade.of Ihloh wan onclosed in our official letter to ' So * E 1018/1015^1 of the 4th March), it was deoided that the Snglith equiralent of this figure was 55 dogrea# under proof. The Frenoh admit this but now say that they would be content with 35 degrees under nroof. 3. It seer., to ua that if Cabin could exnlain the matter to the French, this tanrle ceuld be straightened out quickly enoa-h. In point of fact we are only trying to express their desiderata in ten s of our scale. Will you let me know what you think on this point, when you haye oom-idered the Fremh note? I should be Tatoful if you could let mo iwwe an early answer, as I understand that the Canadian and Irish Free State '-ower-saents have to b® consulted about any alteration in the draft notes to the Sultm, and the India Office are anxious to despatch this question fuickly seiding copies of this Letter to Laithwaite and (%d.) K. R, JOHNSTO®.)4&gt; British Msaasy 1821/1015/91) /V33). Paris. April 6th, 1933 My dear Christopha Yftur latter E I'41/105/91 of the 23rd/ instant reg-rdiyi : the proposed modifiotion of the i. : usoat treaties. 2. s duly drew the attention of the comerai al relations departraent of the Ministry to the errors which had crept in both on their side and on ours with re -ard to their scale for assessing the strength o fliquor and our use of the terms 'under* and 'over-proof'. We asked than to treat the jsatter »« urgent. 3. Althou gh from your letter the matter seeiaed a comparatively eiir.ple one, they have no* re slied in a note, copy of vhieh I enclose, fro:. ufaioh it will bs aeon that they do not a-^ree with the point of view of the Board of Trade as e pressed in Jenkin'a letter CRT 142/33 of the 11 i?) 11th March. As the question seems a highly technical one I mtherefore referring it to you one® a tain, and perhaps you will get the Board of Trade to say where it is that the French have prone wrong. It is clear that there ia a confusion somowhere, hut I do not quite ssee at the moffient how to clear it up. Yours ever, (%i.) OLIfgH HARm iwner, Esq., i forei'jn Office.: tf r- 3^ P OOHFIOENTM T SE00SD8- j Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office, for the information of the Political Resident, Bushire. India Office, Whitehall, London, S.W.I. Copy sent to■I *° cl SS 4°hX in i5'5. 0 lo!9l4'9! ri ° s P.Z.2592/23. COPY SENT 9449/9 | m^AW'fromthe Secretary of. State for Dominion Affaire to the Secretary of Stats for External Affairs,Canada, and the Minister for External Affairs Irish ft'eo State (by lag). (Sent 7 p.m. 2nd May, 1933) Important. I Confidential. |;,\V | Canada telegram of 19th September No.133 Irish i\ Free State despatch of 15th December NV.162 Muscat tariff. I 11 haa been found that owing to difference between Sngiiah [ and Inefcric 8yBtems of raea-suring strength of spirits the type of alcoholic liquor on which permission is to be given to leTy CU8toma dut y U P to 2%should not be described in draft note on behalf of United Kingdom to the Unseat Government as 'of 25 or wore degrees under proof', fords '25 or more' are I be in- corrected to -55 or less-, and similar correction ia being made in note to be presented on behalf of Prance. Do you agree to same correction in note on your behalf? As matter is very urgent and presentation of notes has already suffered unavoidable delay, we should be very grateful for a reply, if possible, by 6th Kay. Canada No .46 also sent to the Irish Free State. I /^Vr w ^ ^ &gt; fy. / Sli - J&amp; $ p.z.2674/1935 £nelosur es in 10. Sf ^ L'. iee i 9 5r ring letter No Telegram from the Secretary of state for External Affairs, Canada, to the Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs. Dated 7th May, 1935. Received Dominions Office 7.0 p.m., 7th May, 1935, Immediate, k. 4 - Ho.55. Your telegram of 2nd May Confidential N0.46. Canadian Government concurs in change suggested. mmJ' ck-/' f ^ y 7/ ^. y&lt;*1p 7/50. Despatch No Con fident ml. MBkMMBIt OP KaTSHMAL AFFAIRS, IRISH FREE STATE. 4th May, I935. Sir, /P' ' I have the hWour to refer to your Confidential Telegram of the 2nd May, 1955, with regard to suggested increases in the Customs Duties of Muscat, in respect of which the Government of the Irish Free State have already expressed their readiness to co nsent. 2. Uy Government will be quite agreeable to the correction indicated by your telegram being made in the j: , te2:t of the Hote enclosed witn my despatch H0 .I62 of the 15th December, I932, for presentation to the Muscat Government, viz. The correction b^ substitution of the words '55 or less' for the words '25 or more', with reference to the number of degrees under proof of alcoholic linuor imported into Muscat, it being understood that the metric system of measuring alcoholic strength is to be adopted in the present case as preferable to the English system. f I have, etc., (ScU) Eamon de Talera, Minister for External Affairs. ■ RIGHT EONQURABLfe THE SECRETARY OF STATE FOR jJ...MINI ON AFFAliio, DOMING STREET, LONDON, S.W.I. ^ f'v'r-I f L\^ IV i Downing Street, 8th May, I955 pISTER ^ISH IRIoH li-HivE STATE no,8^. OGmpiDmniAh. Sir, I have the honour to acknowledge the receipt ox your confidential despatch Ho.54 of the 4th May, expressing the consent of His Majesty's Government in the Irish Free State to the correction indicated in my confidential telegram of t he 2nd May, being made in the text of the draft note to the Muscat Government enclosed in your confidential despatch N0.I62 of the 15th December regarding customs duties in Muscat. The correction will be made accordingly. 2* I should explain that the intention from the beginning has been that the Muscat Government should be permitted to levy a higher rate of duty on stronger alcoholic liquor, the strength above which the higher duty should be leviable being alcoholic liquor of 25 or more degrees measured on the metric scale. This was erroneously express ed in my confidential despatch K0.I82 of the 2nd September last and in the draft note of which a copy was enclosed therein as rT 25 or more degrees under proof % and t h© error has only recently been discovered. It is proposed that the strength of alcoholic liquor on which the higher duty should be leviable should be expressed in the nomenclature of this country whereby the equivalent of '28 or more degrees' 1 on the metric system is '55 or less degrees under proof'. I have, etc., FOB £XT13IAL AFFAIRS, (Signed) J.H. THOMAS. FREE STATE. yic/ /WCW aV- .-C ■ /^9, Sjj) —Sa -J? f.L rr^- C. f F- ^FD. udt. /?• 1 Z6 'SS^/z'?, &amp;(' 9 /2 3S- /l£^&lt;-*jt^cjc^ stir/fu*/- , S C ■ £&gt;' 7 ']h J-L-A? C.Uo•^/'/y'/v^j/ /7 / ( V, ^ tu^a, /w ia^ 9 - h ifj' J. o. ^ I r- ^i-jqijsi, ■j-irf. J). £yU^ ■ W-F'^'' ^h, 4 V'A %■ I/V- /-&gt;M'/^, ^7 V'/ 3 /SJ( Reference 15, 16 ana 17. Foreign Office suggestions are (1) to raise the cmty on goods not Imported in American, French and Dutch vessels. they think you. can say vmetner there is much risk of importers evading the increased duties by importing in such vessels. India Office do not think th/ere is much risk of this. (2) to use an argument by analogy from the St. x Germain Convention. They themselves think this impracticable and India Office do not mention it as a possible course. India Office suggestions are (a) the same as Foreign Office (l). / (b) to agree to tne American demand for most-3o/4-dtr A/6 y U' ^-3 i htl'o-f- i'/ / ^A 4^ nafVnlaT 0Urea r]ation treatment in respect of nationals as well as of gooas. From &amp;aj or Fowle's D.O. letter No. C-288, aated cOtn December 1931, it would, appear that he contemplates action on Foreign Office, (l), i.e. Inaia Office (a). I believe I am correct in saying that you do not think that there is much risk of importers using American, Frehch or Dutch bottoms to any great extent. In 1920 the number of dhows entitled to fly the French flag was ten. I think - though. I am uhaole reaaily to quote authority - that their number now is not likely to exceed 4, if as much as that. More over the tariff coula be lov/ered again if the experiment is not a success. The objections to India Office (b) are contain -ed in your telegram No. 34, aated Ibth February 1931. In regara to Inaia Office (b) (li) I would mention that the A.P.O.C. obtainea a concession from the Sultan in 192b, explored portions of his territory ana tnen allowed tne concessionfeo lapse as they apparently did not find the results promis ing. I regret the aelay in submission. I spent somt time trying to find a copy of the Convention of St. Germain, then overlookea the papers aunng the last tour ana the pressure of work which resulted. V /Vf 7 7's , f L Hi 7^-i /i/t-J Si</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0001af_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/458</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0001af</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/458</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Muscat Tariff Treaty'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1931/1933</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-09-18T15:12:30</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">fre</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (234 folios)</extent><extent>Foliation: The foliation sequence commences at the first folio and terminates at the last folio; these numbers are written in pencil, and can be found in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. A second foliation/pagination sequence briefly runs between ff 207-211A; these numbers are written in blue crayon, and can be found in the same position as the main sequence. Circled index numbers written in red crayon can also be found throughout the volume. Foliation errors: 1, 1A, 1B, 1C, 1D and 1E; 9 and 9A; 10 and 10A; 15 and 15A; 23 and 23A; 41 and 41A; 68 and 68A; 177 and 177A, 211 and 211A Foliation omissions: 25</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Correspondence relating to negotiations over revisions in the tariff questions relating to the proposed tariff treaty with Muscat. Includes correspondence relating to negotiations with France, United States, Irish Free State and Canada, as well as, letters in Arabic with translations in English from Taimur bin Faisal [Taymūr bin Fayṣal], Sultan of Muscat, giving full powers in representing him in the negotiations.Correspondents include Taimur bin Faisal, Sultan of Muscat; Trenchard Craven Fowle, Political Resident, Persian Gulf; Major Ralph Ponsonby Watts, Political Agent Muscat; Major Claude Edward U Bremner, Political Agent Muscat; John Charles Walton, India Office, Whitehall. A. Wiseman, Dominions Office, London; Maurice J Clauson, India Office, London; Henry Lewis Stimson, Secretary of State of the United States, Washington.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Treaties</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0001af#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>