<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x00008e_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T04:47:02.760Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">\ »»/» F? HP X ]'© A # f ' M • 4 -| 1 it • ; Copy of mamorandum No. 2472&lt;a/16, datod the 13th June 1945, fray the Han'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf to the Under Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Department, New Delhi. Subject *- Continuance of the post of Personal Assistant to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Reference your memorandum No. 8(4i)~i&lt;i/43, dated the 27th July, 1943. 2. Sanction for the post of Personal Assistant expires on the 31st December 1945. It is requested that orders may kinily be issued for the continuance of the poat on the existing terms for a further period of two rears with effect from the let January, 1946. /VaV K f^Uo, 4° J } %QSL~ w „ / • J-_ ^ 4 - V 4 &lt;»- ' (^o^vV ^ please see xniiru.'fcs at; 11/42 and 11'. G-i'bson , s note of the 16th June, 1939 flagged at X. r fhe Governnent of India appear to have sanctioned the continuance of the post of Personal Assistant to the Political Resident in the Pers^axt Gulf for a further period of two years, under the present arrangement^ whereby H.K.G-. and the Government of India can sanction diplomatic and consular expenditure in Persia ana the Persian Gulf up to fl, 0 ; 0 per annum. CO. 5 3/ wOopy of memorejidiim ifo* 1078-64/144 dated tile 27tii June 1943 from tile iionTble ^ the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, d ’*- Bushire to the Secretary to the Government pp*&gt;^L of India in the External Affairs EepaTtment, Hew Delhi • . — r © £f (4H . Continuance of the post of Personal Aesietant to the non’ble the Poli tical Resident in the Persian Golf. Reference Express Letter ho-E-S^Sl^- 4/4X-dEte&lt;3 the 20th ^.ril 1942 from the Government of India in the External Affairs Department. 2* Sanction for the post of Personal Assistant expires on the 3ist December 1943. It is requested that orders may kindly be issued for the continuance of the post on the existing terms for a further period of two years with effect from the Isx January 1944* Hari 24/7* I INDIA letter 13-8' ;9 !O- - Jk 9 VMder 3 eoretmrj te tke Qermrwmmt •f Isdia i* Ute EzteraiX Affair* Dmptt * - ltom 9 *l* ike Political Reoideat is mo Persia*! Ghlf* Mm*r*mdwm Mo. 8 ( 41 ).y* 3 * /y Dated Mew Dolki, tMe 5 ? July 1943 . in tfeo Peral am dilf. Reference your Memorandum Mo. 1078 - 4 ^/ 144 . dated the 27 Hi June 1943 * 2 . Sanction of the GbTernor GenorrJ. in Oouneil is accorded to the continuance of the post of Personal Assistant to the Political Resident in the Persian 3 ulf on the existing terns for a further period of two years with effect from the 1 st January 1944 * (Sd*) V.B. Arte ? r Ruder Secretary to the Qovemment of India. Karl 24/7.i / GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. ' External Affairs Department. ^ A T.OTTER (AIR MAIL) . KjO. r^r % NoJF.8(8i3bE/ii^ \\ To Dated New Delhi, the I2.&lt;t February *42, 1625 ! iretaiy of State for India, |, LONDON . SUBJECT : Continuance of the post of Personal Assistant to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf* Reference this Department it. Express Letter N o»F»8(81)-E/41, dated the' 17th November 1941* 2. Grateful for early reply* THE ISSUE OF THE ABOVE HAS BEEN AUTHORISED. for Secretary &lt;othe Govt* of India. us* «90f -h!mji copv 0 © quote » and address-^-• not to any person by nar \e by nar \e .4 “V T7 rA Foreign Office. The Under-Secretary of state,’' Foreign Office, London, S.W.l. 1942 th March, 1942. Si^v With reference to India Office letter (Ext.11/42) of the 3rd February, I am directed 'by MI*. Secretary Eden to state, for the information of the Secretary of State for India, that sanction has been obtained for one half of the cost of maintaining the post of Personal Assistant to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf to be charged to Imperial Revenues for a further period of two years from the 1st January, 1942. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, The Under-Secreti India Office.Please see previous submission at P.Z.7889/39* llie post of Personal Assistant to tlie Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, v/ith an allowance of 200 rupees per mensem ,was sanctioned for three years in 1928 and this sanction has been renewed periodically ever since. The duties of the Personal Assistant appear to be mainly social - the entertainment of Persian officials and Foreign Consuls and the charge of the house and Camp furniture. He also acts 'as a reserve for cyphering for the Under Secretary, either when sick or when he relieves the Secretary'. (P.348/28 flapged in bound volume attached). The post has been held, from time to time, by probationers of the Indian Political ServiceT The present incumbent is not known. ■ r&gt; hvJT tK*, Qjjvt. ^ 0 *jl. fe OlaJXcuy^ji. ikju %*. Sauction was last granted for a period of two years as from the 1st January 1940. The Government of India have now written agreeing with the recommendation by the Political Resident that the post should be continued for another two years on the same terms. As the reasons for which the post was originally sanctioned are still valid it is proposed, subject to the concurrence of the Foreign Office and the acceptance of a moiety of the expenditure involved by the Treasury, to agree to this extension. A draft letter to the Foreign Office is submitted accordingly. H, . ?/, Fcy^CLA^U^joJ ^/V Covicc^a ?Ext, 11/42. DRAFT lETTSR Under Secretary of State, Foreign Office, S.W.l. /X, Sir, V 3 3 FEB 1942 /ith reference to Foreign Office letter I To. K.4116/1284/234 of the ~Jth March, 1940, concerning the post of Personal Assistant to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, I am directed by the Secretary ^of State for India to forward for the GcrY^S~idUj\&amp;£oys &lt; infoffaation of the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs a copy of an Express Letter from the \ ( Dated tlie 17 tli ITovember ) Government of India on thi^ grrb-ject uf the continuance of the appointment for a further period of two years from the 1st January 1942. Subject to the concurrence of Mr. Eden and to \ of* H &lt;D ^ ie acce P^ anoe ‘^ le Ro^ds Commissioners^of a moiety11 External Al^fairs Department. ft 4*0 0 J His Majesty's Secretary of State for inaia, London* Continuance of the post of the Personal Assistant to the political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Reference correspondence ending with your telegram RNo.1190, uated the 12th March 1940, 2. Sanction to the post of personal Assistant to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf expires on the 31st December 1941. As the reasons for which the post was originally sanctioned are still valid, political Resident recommends its continuance for a further period of two years with effect from the 1st January 1942, on the same terms. Government of India agree and request sanction. THE ISSUE (F THE ABOVE HAS BEEN AUTHORISED. Under Secretary to the Government of India.INDEXED COPY In any further communication on this subject, please quote ^o. K 4116/1284/234 and address— not to any person by name but to— Foreign Office, London, S.W.l. I Foreign Office. S.W.l. 7th March, 1940. Sir, With reference to India Office letter P.Z. 1137/40 of the 29th February concerning the post of Personal Assistant to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, I am directed by Viscount Halifax to state for the information of the Marquess of Zetland, that he agrees that a moiety of the expenditure involved in the retention of this post for a further period of two years as from the 1st January, 1940, should be a charge on Imperial funds. ( 9 MAR 1940 I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, The Under Secretary of State, India Office. RECo. POL. DEPt. -8.V1AR 940 INDIA OFFICE I .i&amp;&gt; JLTsJZ 2,1.. Q0VERNMENT-©f^NDIX7'\ .JL • —^ ** External Affairf) ipartmeaty EXPRESS LETT MjVlL). “Aia ^ . T ift ts an ORIGINAL message tent by AIR MAIL rohich provides a means of communication more expeditious than the ordinony mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities 1 1 is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department.] v * j No. Dated New Delhi the February 1$ 40*. To secretary of state for India, London. fiiilQSQSLOT Subject:- Continuance of the post of tne Personal T Assistant to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Keference Foreign express letter No.F.8(81)-S/39, dated IHyic, the Dth December 1939. L. The Government of India would be grateful if a reply to the above communication could kindly be expedited. The issue of the above has been authorised. {Signature) {Designation) HECft. PQL.ttS n fj ; £. 44. MFP—1813 8&amp;P—(M-2617)—21 -4-37—15,000.Register No. P.T. Political Department. Letter Telegram from Dated b-c&lt;s Rec. I £ fa* Formally acknowledged Previous Papers :— 1480 1000 10.26FILE COPY GOVERNMENT OF INIC ! IA 7339 SXmNiiL AFFAIRS Department. g T ^ Jd jq ($ EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MA Pff.B.— This it an ORIGINAL message Stint hu AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department.'] No. F. 6(61) -E/39. Bated To 'Mew Delhi the 6 December 2939. The Secretary of State for India, L.QJOULMjl SUBJECT:- Continuance of the post of the Reference my po: Personal Assistant to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. i Reference correspondence ending with your express letter No* P.1*6896/38, dated the 12th October 1938* 2. Sanction for the post of Personal Assistant to Political Resident in the Persian Gulf expires on the 31st December 1939. As the reasons obtaining at the time of the original sanction of the post continue to exist, Political Resident recommends continuanc of the post for a further period of two years with effect from the 1st January 1940 on the same terms as those previously sanctioned. The Government of India agree and request sanction. 3. It will not be possible to arrange for the duties of the Personal Assistant to be carried on by a probationer of the Indian Political Service during the present emergency. The issue of the above has-been authorised* RECd. POL. DEPt. 18 0801939 INDIA OFFICE Under Secretariate (Signature) of Incia. ulttUo 3. 44. ifFP—1013 SAP—&lt;1&lt;-201^&gt;—21 -4-37—15,00* (Designation)9 5319a 5000 10.36 ■Reference Paper accountant-general 1 s Department Letter No. A.G.8312/39MI Rec. 193 IJ/NJerred to the Secretary, Political — 16th day of Department. June, 1939. Please see the last paragrapn of the letter from this Office to the Accountant General, Central Revenues, dated 13th April 1939 and his reply, paragraph g, which ignores our request for information as to the admissibility of the deductions in question. Have you any iniormation on this point, please? (SD.) D.W.TAIT. P.Z. 3761/39. The post of Personal Assistant to the Political Resident dates from 1927. You will see from P.2318/28 that it exists on a temporary basis (the latest extension, P.Z. 6896/38, carries it up to the end of 1939) and that the total divisible cost is not to exceed Rc&gt;. 200 p.m. The position, I think, is that the pay of a probationer sent to Bushire for training is not included in D. &amp; C. expenditure because he does not fill one of the D. &amp; C. appointments; but the probationers referred to below performed the duties of Personal Assistant for a time and drew special pay on that account, and this special pay etc. is included in the D. &amp; C. divisible expenditure. See P. Z. 3048/36. (SD.) J.P.GIBSON. 16.6.f ' ' i i-ilc wOHY.^ •• Copy of* iixprtibS Lottisr Imo® 1.7^0^ cicil/GQ. oOijfi September 1938 from Britconsul, Bushire to Foreign, Simla. &amp; V.k. Understand from Ncrwef, Nathiagalli^ tnat Howaon has been posted as Personal Assistant. $e Piave asked Iranian Consul, ijirachi, to grant visa ana have asked Howson to comrnunicate with you should xi© encounter difficulty in obtaining same m xiar&amp;chi. It is requested that assistance in obtaining a visa may be given if necessary. _ IN INDIA foreign secretary’s letter ott r DA To RECEIVED 2 3 -12' 1938 Iv ry; 'T' Frcan - The Military Secretary, Army headquarters, India, Sirala&lt; To - Headquarters. Hamlpindi district. (§&gt; Ho. 01732(k.S.4). dateu tlie 10th October, 1956. The att&amp;cnea application form for a passport is for^araed for completion, as soon as possible, by Lieutenant . R. Howaon, 2/6th Cfur-iha rifles, vsho has been selecteu for appointment to the Indian Political service subBtantively on probation, and has been posted as iersofA&amp;l Assistant to tne Political Resident, rersian Gulf. After completion, tne form, to&amp;etner witn two copies of Lieutenant Howaon's photograph, and his present passport, if any, snould be forwarded to tii© Secretary to the GoTernment of India, External Affairs Jeparhiient. do/- It. drake, for . ilrbaxy becretary. Copy to j- Headquarters, Northern Command. The Secretary to Uie Government of India, External Affairs Je A .artment.Cojy of an Express Letter from the Headquarter#, Rawalpindi, Jiatrict to the Military Secretary, iXiuy Headquarters, India, Hew :jfelhi. He. 53-3-1, dated uie 15tl*i October 1038. Reference your Express Letter Ho* C1732(k#L.1 4), datea 10th October 1958. Intimation has been received from the Officer Oonmandir^, Je^ot, 2nd Battalion, 6tii Gurkha Rifles that lieutenant J . R. HowBon departed for ^.araohi on the after noon of 7th Gctobax* 1938, to take up the appointment as i erson&amp;l Assistant to tne lion 1 ble the r olitical i^esraent in the Persian Gulf. 2. Lieutenant Lowson proposea to etibark at Aar&amp;chi for 1 ti:e Lersian Gulf in the Rail Steamer 'ELErHinTA' vkiicii sails fro*:* narachi on 15th October 1938. 3. In the circumstances, the application form for passport in respect of Lieutenant howson, is returned herewith incomplete. Copy to :- Headuuarters, Horthem ^o^iand.INDEXED In any further communication on this subject, please quote and address, No ' K 11395/10641/234 iZT' not to any person by name. Foreign Office. but to— “ The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. i. s.w.i. 6th. October*, 1938* A- Sir, With reference to India Office letter P.Z. 5614/38 of the 31st August, I am directed by Viscount Halifax to state, for the information of the Secretary of State for India, that he has obtained the sanction of the Lords Commissioners of His Majesty’s Treasury for the continuance of the post of personal assistant to the Political Resident in the Persian G-ulf for a further period of two years from the 1st January, 1938, half the cost involved to be met from Imperial funds. Your obedient Servant a Sir, /{J] The Under-Secretary of State India OfficeMI P—1048 S&amp;P-(M-2042)—17-12.37—20,000. file cop\T p - Z ' 5614 \ QOVEt NMENT OF INDIA. I933 j Department. ^External Affairs EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). [N.B. This is an O RIGINAL message sent by AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the. signature of a responsible officer of the Department ] No. E. 9 (39) -E (A)/38. Dated Simla 7i / l mi CCaC SCECSB7EE the - August To ^ &gt;■ The Secretary of State for India, London. if/38. IS Subject:* Continuance of the post of Personal issistant to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. n V' / ry 30 Reference correspondence ending with your letter No.P.Z*3048/36, dated the 28th May 1936. __ 2* Sanction for the post of Personal Assistant to Political Resident in the Persian Gulf expired on the 31st December 1937. Political Resident has, however, incurred expenditure on the post in January and February 1938 on the ground that the reasons obtaining at the time of the original sanction of the post continue to exist, he recommends continuance of the post for a period of two years from the 1st January 1938 on the same terms as those previously sanctioned. Government of India agree and request sanction. 3. When circumstances permit, the duties of the Personal Assistant will be carried on by a probationer in the Political Department as agreed to in your letter referred to in paragraph 1 above. The issue of the above has been authorised. 3 DydO VIGNI 8£6i9nv 01 U13 TM ‘tM (Sign* Under Secretary to the Government of India. zs') onr&gt;- I S. 44. Designation)© Minute Paper. 72 Department. F. 1 2593 ! 1936 The Goyernment of India’s letter of the 16th April puts forward a meticulous point which it would hardly seem necessary for them to have raised. The position is that there is standing sanction for the post of Personal Assistant to the Political Resident at a cost (divisible between Imperial and Indian revenues) of Rs.200 per mensem (see P.Z.8026/35). There is also an arrangement whereby, when a probationer of the Political Department is ^nvojrrod, he is posted to this appointment, and a saving is effected because the expenditure involved when a probationer is appointed is only Rs.150 per mensem./jw olLc ?.Z . It seems clearly unnecessary in these circumstances for the Government of India to come home for sanction to each appointment of a probationer, especially as they seem to change fairly frequently. Financial Secretary , Accountant-General, Do you concur in the draft reply to the Government of India?Draft Paper ?. z. Department, The Secretary to the Government of India, F. 6b P. Department, Simla. \ V. 4599 5000 2.36 2,8MAY W56 Sir, I am directed by the Secretary of State to refer to your letter of the 16th April, No.D.1196-E/36, on the subject of the grant of special pay and customs compensatory allowance to Lieutenant J.B. Howes while performing the duties of Personal Assistant to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. In this connection I am to enclose, for the information of the Government of India, copies of the correspondence with the Foreign Office on the proposal put forward in the Government of India’s Express Letter of the 28th October, No.D.3489-E/35. 2. As the Government of India will observe from this correspondence, H.M.G. are aware of the arrangement whereby the post of Personal Assistant is filled by a probationer of the Foreign &amp; Political Department^ wfropc circumstances permit. As the expenditure involved is less, when a Political Department probationer is employed, than that sanctioned by the India Office Express Letter of 20th January, 1936, the Secretary of State does not consider that reference need be made to him in the case of each new Personal Assistant appointed so long as the present arrangement remains in force^The IPoreiptfi Secretary to the (lovernrrjent of India in the Foreign and Political Department, To The Under Secretary of State for India, Lond on. Dated Ne?. Delhi, the /(o^ April 1936. Grant of special pay and customs compensatory allowance to Lieutenant J. 3. Howes' of the Political Department. 1 Sir, I am directed to invite a reference to the correspondence ending with your express letter Ho. P.Z. 423/36, dated the 20th January 1936 in which the continuance of the post of Personal Assistant to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf was sanctioned for a further period of two years with effect from the 1st January 1936. 2.' The duties of Personal Assistant were entrusted to Lieutenant R. D. Metcalfe, a probationer in the Political Department who was placed under the Political Resident for training in 1934-35 and during the period he did the duties of Personal Assistant he was granted a special pay and customs compensatory allowance of Ks. 100/- and Es. 50/- respectively for the reasons rriven in the memorandum from the Foreim and Political Department No. F. 26(6)-F./35, dated the 15th August 1935, aa copy of T.hich was forwarded to the India Office vide Foreign Secretary*s letter ITo. 127-M, dated the 15th August 1935* Lieutenant J. 3, Howes, another probationer in the Political Department under training* in the Persian Gulf took over the duties of Personal Assistant from Lieutenant Metcalfe on the 24th October 1935, and a similar concession may be sanctioned for Lieutenant Howes for the period from the 24th October 19 35 to the 4th April 1936, during- which he performed the duties of Personal Assistant to the Political Resident, the expenditure involved being met in moieties bv His Majesty’s Government and the Government of India. 3 # The Government of India further recommend that the allowance be fixed for the post of Personal Assistant to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, when held by an officer of the Political Department thus obviating the necessity of a reference to the Secretary of State in Council in the case of each new Personal Assistant appointed• t I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant, for Foreign Secretary to the Government of India.In any further communication on this subject, please quote I uiilo SU.UJLL'U) No. K 208/208/234 and address— not to any person by name Foreign Office. but to— “ The Under-Secretary of State,” S.W.l. Foreign Office, London, S.W.l. 16th January, 1936 Sir, 17ith reference to India Office letter IJo.P.Z.8026/35 of 2nd December ,1935, I am directed by Mr.Secretary Eden to state, for the information of the Secretary of State for India in Council, that he has obtained the sanction of the Lords a further period of two years, from 1st January, 1936 of the post of Personal Assistant to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf on the existing terms, half the cost to be met from Imperial funds. 2. I am to add that Mr.Eden has taken note of the fact that, where circumstances permit, the post of Personal Assistant is filled by a probationer of the Poreign and Political Department deputed for training in the Persian Gulf at Bushire. Commissioners of His Majesty 1 s Treasury for the continuance for I am Sir, Your obedient Servant The Under-Secretary of State, India Office.P. Z. 8026/35 Draft Paper political Department. DRAFT LETTER. 2 Sir, I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to refer to the Express No. D.3489-E/35 of 28th October, a copy letter No. P.Z.8026/35 of 11th November, regarding the proposed extension for a further period of two years from 1st January 1936 of the post of Personal Assistant to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. 2. The Secretary of State in Council agrees with the recommendations of the Political Resident and of the Government of India, and subject to the concurrence of the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, and to the acceptance of a moiety of the expenditure by the Lords Commissioners of His Majesty’s Treasury as a charge on Imperial r^vemie-s, he proposes to approval •£ them. 3. Secretary Sir Samuel Hoare will note F.C. letter from the Government of India, of which was forwarded with 1.0. printed approved council' that, wheaHf circumstances permit, the post 3 0 NOV 1935 of Personal Assistant is filled by a L Political Probationer deputed for trai nirg A in the Persia! Gulf at Bushire. /APPROVED Toin-r POLITICAL &amp; SOCIAL FINANCE. COMMITTEE 39:58 5000 7.353 ji \'\ ^ GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. Soreigri and Political Department. EXPRESS LETTER (AIRMAIL). \lY3&amp; - ' ^ Qs&gt; P.Z. ' Civ 8025 1935 1 [N.B.— 7‘hie isan ORIGINAL message sent by AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, . on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been teleraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities \t is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department.] No^. 3489-E/35. Dated _ the New Delhi October i.935 . To The Secretary of State for India, London* 31V' V ^. A Reference correspondence ending with your telegrar/ Ho* 1318, dated the 18th Tay 19 34. Sanction to post of Personal Assistant to political Resident in Persian Gulf expires on 31st Recember 1935* Political Resident represent* that grounds for original sanction of post still hold good and recommends its retention for further period of two years from 1st January 19 36. We agree and request sanction. 2. When it is possible to depute a Probationer in the Political Department for training in the Persian Gulf at Bushire, the duties of Personal Assistant are also entrusted to him and the post of Personal Assistant as such is kept in abeyance. The Probationer draws special pay and compensator} allowance of J^.100 and 33*50/- per month in addition to substantive pay on the analogy of special pay and allowances drawn by other members of the political Department serving in Persian Gulf, vide memorandum from the Government of Indi? in the Foreign and Political Department ITo.F. 26(6!-E/35, dated 15th August 1935. As ; however ; it is not certain that it will always be possible to send Political probationers (Signature) to.... S. 44. MFP-825S&amp;P—(M-1070)—14-9-34—10,000. (Designation)continued on the existing terms for the present. m) The issue of the above has been authorised. Addl: I&gt;eputy Secretary to the Goiternmcait of India* VS. —V &lt;-L, &gt; ' v 1 D i ^ _ s [ in the ^ertign #nd political^l)ep*rt»«ntt To • The Hon^la the Politic®! ^eeident In the Memor anduaa ilo • F. 26 {6) - i/35 • Dated iml* # the August PeT?i»nA^-i0UMTl G^Nb ‘ 947 : tcX ,t10 r- H if\ (°/ Oront of epeoial^ay and Cu^tone Coj»pwn8atory a ilowanoe to Lieutenant VD* U^taslfe of the '‘olitioal Lep^rtr^ont pleoed under tr»iGin e v under the Political Henidfnt in the Pereian auii # yvl aas^^* h(^ vf-j i Reference your letter f»o*A*B«317/64/144 # dated the 21st April 1935. 2. The Governor General in Council ia piee ? .ed to anction the grant to Lieutenant R.D.Metcalfe of the Political Department for the period he did the duties of Personal Assistant to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf* of a special pay of Ra. 100/» p.ns. on account of unhealthinees of the Gulf ciimatfi. As Mr. Metcalfe got f~ee feoard and lodging there is not sufficient justification for granting him a customs coupenea;ory allowance of Re. ICO/- p.m* The Governor General in Council is* however* pleased to sanction the grant to him of a cut toms compensatory ailowanee of Re* SO/* p.m. 3* The extra expenditure involved should he divided equally between His Majesty’s Government and the Indian revenuee • a the appointment of Lieutenant Metcalfe as personal / eaiatant obviated the nece^eity of filling the temporary post of ihe Personal Assistant on Re. 200/- p.m* which ie equally divisible. d/- H.Trevelyan« Under Secretary to the Govt'rraaent of India' J mm fNDEXED In any further communication on this &gt;'~Nect, please quote No.K 6127/4890/234. and address, not to any person by name, but to— “The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. i. Sir, Foreign Office. S.W.l. 29th May, 1934. / » -Vt) M . \\ \ / With reference to India Office letter No.PZ 2442/34 of April SOth, I am directed by Secretary Sir John Simon to state, for the information of the Secretary of State for India, that he has obtained the sanction of the Lords Commissioners of His Majesty’s ‘treasury for the continuance for a further period of two years, from January 1st 1934, of the post of Personal Assistant to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf on the existing terms, half of the cost being met from Imperial funds. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, The Under-Secretary of State, India office. I* 1 30 MAY 1834 3 1 MAY 19 34 INDIA Orr 5 !“ r~ • r-INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL, 3.11. 1. - &lt;y, nn^t.-jaL* r ♦ Z*5Q&lt;dO/34. Bt-h toy 19o4. ly dear i^owle, Many Uiantes for your personal telegram uj #465 of the 5 th tiiy about the Personal Assistant. ;.e wrote to the Foreign Office supporting the proposed extension of the post for a furtner t*o years from the 1st January 1934 on 30th April ana nope very soon to get a reply. The Government of India have asked us to telegraph the decision, ana v&gt;e will repeat our telegram to you. Yours sincerely, J.G. LMTHWAlTn. The rion’ble Lt.coi. X.C.W. Fowie, The Aasiaency, Bush ire.ir'iL ;_XED ikt/dia. FILt COPY (36 words) n 5 / i ! 302Q 81 | [ 1954 p a c Q D J, -0.„A J From Political Resident in the Persian Gulf to Beeretary of bit ate for India* Dated Bushire, 5th May, 1G34, Received 5th May* 1931, l'd5 pom. .1 ^ ( W. 455 c Personal« Fowls to Laithwaite^ I trust post of my persons! assistant, about&lt; which Government of India have wired Secretary df State and which will relieve me ot many petty details at time when I am very vuehed, will oe continued.Draft Paper. P.Z.&lt;i44ii/34. political Department. © r DRAi 1 '! bOTTLa . U. 3 . 3 ., F.O' i Scuosure .R m ' APPROVED COUHCIL 30 APR 1934 f/i 2531 5000 2.34 3 0 APR 1934 Sir, I am directed by the s/s ior I. to refer to the express letter of 2nd April 1934 from the G.of I., a copy of which was forwarded witn I.O. printed letter No.p.Z.2442/34 of 13th April, relative to hie proposed extension of the post of Personal. Assistant to the Political Resident in hie Persian Gulf for a further periou of two years from 1st January 1934 on existing terms. 2. The 3/3 in C. agrees with the recommendations of the Political Resident and the G.of I. and subject to the concurrence of the s/S for F.A. and to the acceptance of a moiety of the expenditure as a charge on Imperial revenues by the L.C. of H.M. Treasury, he proposes to telegraph approval of them. (Sd.) J. C. WALTON. approved joint pormo.. ^° ECiAt - finance committee. APR 19,J413 APR 1954 .$2) GOVERNMENT OP INDIA, foreign and Political Department. f 'T . / |'24 4 2 EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAILL 1934 — [N-B. J his is an ORIGIN A L message sent by ATE MAIL which provides a means of communication m.ore expeditious than the ordinary mail and, is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to he treated, on receipt, with the, same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department.] f I No. D.674-E/34. .2 1 *' April 2934. The Secretary of State for India, London* 1A Reference correspondence ending with, your telegram dated 25th January 1952 Ko.296. Sanction to post of Personal Assistant to Political Resident in Persian Gulf expired on 31st December last. Political Resident has represented that grounds for original sanction of post still hold good and that it^bfe extended for further period of two years from 1st January 1934 on existing terms. We agree and request your sanction by telegram. c The issue of the above has been authorised. AddliDeputy Secretary to the Government of India. % V;aS m INDIA!) FFICE ( Signature) S. 44. DCfT—441S&amp;P—(&lt;a.7l2)—28*9-29—5,000. {Designation)I'/ In any further communication on this subject, please quote No. K 859/859/234 and address, but to— not to any person by name. Foreign Office. “ The Under-Secretary of State,” S.W.l Foreign Office, 22nd January, 1932. Sir, With reference to your letter P.Z.7655/31 of December 29th last I am directed hy Secretary Sir John Simon to inform you that he concurs in the recommendation of the Government of India that the post of Personal Assistant to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf should be continued for a further period of two years and that sanction has been obtained from His Majesty’s Treasury for the charge to Imperial funds of expenditure for this Rupees 100 . purpose of the sum of one hundred rupees a month as from January 1st,1932 I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, The Under-Secretary of Sta India Officew Ih DST/AW, (25 words) 6847 e BBCODS Off TELEGRAM . from Government of India* Foreign and Political Department* to Secretary of State for india 0 Dated Delhi* 11th Deoemher, 1931^ Received 11th December* 1931* 7*16 p 0 m, tf so? 3° 1408»r,B Q Reference correspondence ending with your telegram dated 29th January* 1930* No*350 e Sanction to the post of Personal Assistant to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf expires on 31et December* Conditions have not changed since original sanction was given and In view of present vexatious import restrictions in Persia* Political Resident recommends extension of the post on existing terms for a further period of 2 years,, Wo agree ©nd request sanction by telegram*</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x00008e_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/3580</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x00008e</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/3580</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 29/23 'Bushire: post of Personal Assistant to the Political Resident'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1931/1945</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-06-20T22:02:02</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (58 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 60; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file concerns the post of Personal Assistant to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.The file covers:Government of India recommending extension of post of Personal Assistant to the Political Resident, from 1931 until the end of the file, in 1946letters notifying of the appointments of Personal Assistants.The file is composed of internal correspondence between the Foreign Office, the India Office, the Government of India, and the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of India</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Persian Gulf Political Residency</namePart></name></subject><subject><topic>Diplomatic service</topic></subject><subject><topic>British</topic></subject><subject><topic>Consular services</topic></subject><subject><topic>Recruitment</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x00008e#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>