<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00012f_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T18:10:17.835Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">0 &lt; 2 ^ Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf. PA-364. August 18, 194^. His Britannic Majesty*s Political Agent The Agency, Manama, Bahrein Island. 'HOOD RIVER' File 630.3 Dear Sir: I am desired hy the local Representative of The Overseas Tankship Corporation to advise you of the substance of a cable received August 15, 1948, f^om Mr. H. B. Stoval, Manager, Caltex Oil (Aden) Ltd., as follows 'S/S 'HOOD RIVER' WILL SAIL TO-DAY HAVE TWO NATIVE PASSENGERS FOR POLITICAL AGENT AT BAHREIN CONTACT POLITICAL AGENT AT BAHREIN MAKE SATISFACTORY ARRANGEMENTS TO LAND EITHER OF THE FOLLOWING BAHREIN LIGHT VESSEL OR RAS TANURA S/S 'HOOD RIVER' WILL KEEP YOU ADVISED DATE OF ARRIVAL BOTH PLACES PIEASE ADVISE AUTHORITIES RAS TANURA FOR SPECIAL PERMISSION TO LAND IN CASE YOU PREFER LANDING RAS TANURA.' In this connection, the following radiogram has just been re ceived from the Captain of the S/S 'Hood River', which is scheduled to arrive at the Bahrein light vessel on or about August 19, 1948:- ' CONTACT SIR RUPERT HAY POUTICAL RESIDENT BAHREIN TO ARRANGE IAUNCH MEET VESSEL AT BAHREIN HGHT VESSEL THURSDAY TO TAKE TWO ADEN DETECTIVES TO BAHREIN (STOP) WIRING EXACT ARRIVAL UGHT VESSEL LATER (STOP) ADVISE WHETHER LAUNCH WILL MEET OR NOT.' t I assume that you will advise the Captain of the S/S 'Hood River' direct'of arrangements for the disembarkation of the two Adenese passengers. For R. M. Brown, Chief Local Representative, The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited. Confidential. BAHRAIN RECEIPT.Telegram. &amp;n Clair. F rom# Political, Bahrain. To, C.S. 'Hood River'. No. 61. Dated the 13th August, 1948. From Political Agent, Bahrain. Am arranging launch to meet you light vessel Thursday. Awaiting hearing your exact arrival. Political Message telephoned to office from Cable &amp;)Wireless D/F Station. From. S.S. Hood River. Bahrain light vessel 1.30 p.m. MasterEn Clair. Political, Bahr£iru S.S. ^ood River* Tele^raqj. From. To. No. 514 Dated the 20th August, 1948. Unable to understand failure to contact launch which was at light vessel from 1030 hrs to 1535 hrs. Have asked AhAMCO oflload passengers ship side Has Tanura and bring them here direct. PoliticalDated and received 21st August, 1948 b - - STS En clair Master, s.s. 'Hood River'.Bahrain Radio. Political Agent, Bahrain. Nil. Yours yesterday. Vessel at anchor half mile off Bahrain Lightvessel from 1350 hours to 1615 hours. Definitely no launch sighted at Lightvessel or in vicinity. = MASTER =CONFIDFNTIAL. D.O.No.c/l''}. D?ted 17th August 1948, Dear Kearney On consideration I think you are right about there being no neces sity for a letter to the Master of the s.s. “Hood”. I have however written a sort of certificate which whoever brings the launch to the s.s. ,, Hood ,t could show to the Master or his pas sengers if necessary. I send it herewith. Yours sincerely Mr. B.J. Kearney, Bahrain Reprrsentative Arabian American Oil Co Bahrain.17th August, 1948. The Arabian American Oil Company have arranged that the launch brought by the bearer of this letter will take two Adenese from s.s. 'Xlood’ 1 to Bahrain.wm &amp; CONFIDEMTI/lL . political agency, BAHRAIN, S.O.No.C/R-187. Dated 27th SeptemVer, 1948. Dear Colonel Galloway, I have been trying to arrange to send back the two Adenese gentlemen to Aden and find that they can go by aeroplane from Dhahran on October 10th or by tanker from here on October 13th. ■ After their prolonged stay here, they naturally wish to go by the former method, tut it would be more expensive and the Governor of Aden specifically asked that they should be returned by tanker. I should, therefore, be grateful if the circumstances could be telegraphed to him and his consent obtained to our returning the two men by air and to the payment of their fares by that method. Yours sincerely, His Excellency Lt. Col. A.C. Galloway, CIE, OBF., Political Resident, Persian Gulf, BAHRAIN.HHHHHHHHHHHIHHHHHHHIHHHHIHMHMH confidential . (S1/13/48) . PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY , BAHRAIN . 5th. October 1948. Will you please refer to your S.O letter No. C/R-187 of 27th September regarding the repatriation of two Adenese ? 2. I have suggested to the Governor of Aden that the men should return by Air, but he prefers them to travel by sea. 3. Would you, therefore, please arrange their passage on the tanker which is due to sail on t 13th October and let me know the name of the ship and its expected date of arrival in Aden, in order that I may inform the Governor ? C.J.Pelly, Esqr, Political Agent, Bahrain. *DD» Confidential. TUHRATN RSCEIPT-^^ D i e . P * ^ o-{ K f\' odU**- , Ccx^TwJ) fux&amp;e o^- LLaMpp &amp;Q. &lt;LO % 'I' 6 'URGENT CONFIDENTIAL . NO.C/R-20P. POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN, Dated 17th OctoVer, 1948. Dear Dredge, D lease refer to S.0.No.(91/13/48), dated the 5th Gctoter, 1948, from Col. Galloway to Pelly, regarding the repatriation of the two Adenese. 2. It was not possible to repatriate the Adenese by tanker on 13th October as Bapco in formed me that the tanker had been diverted from Bahrain. 3. Bapco now inform me that they can arrange to fly the two Adenese from Dhahran on 21st October at a cost of £56/- inclusive of both, and that there is no tanker until the 28th - and that is not certain. 4. In the circumstances I have asked Bapco to book air passages provisionally for the 21st, but I should be grateful for your early sanction that these men may be sent by air as proposed. Yours sincerely, Major A.L.A. Dredge, MBE, Secretary to His Excellency the Political Resident, Persian Gulf, BAHRAIN.CONFIDENTIAL. (91/16/48) PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN, 29th October, 1948. /&gt; 5 . f*' Will you please refer to Hudson’s letter No. C/R 202 of 17th October regarding the two Auenese policemen? 2. The proprietor of the Taj Manal Hotel, an Indian named Mulchand, trading under the name of Kumar, has submitted a bill for Ps.3,250 for their accommodation from 23rd August to 25th October. This works out at a rate of P.%25 per head per day inclusive of meals and would appear to be quite exorbitant and more than we should reasonably ask^Aden Government to pay. 3. I should be grateful for your views on this rate, particularly in comparison with those of other similar lodging^ houses in Bahrain. y C.J. pelly, Esq., O.B.E., Political Agent, Bahrain. ba ' TF'' ^4© CONFIDENTIAL S•0•No.C/R-223• POLITICAL AGENCY, • BAHRAIN, Dated 8th November, 1948 Dear Dredge The rates mentioned in your semi official letter No.(91/16/48), dated the 29th October, 1948, for the board of the two Adenese Policemen, are far too high and are twice those charged by the other hotel keeper whose rates I hove obtained. They are as follows: (a) Lodging &amp; boarding for Arabs Rs. 12/8 per capita per day (b) -do- for Indians Ps.15/- (c) -do- for Europeans Rs.20/- 2. I recommend that Kumar should be paid half of his bill 'in full settlement'. Yours sincerely, Major A.L.A. Dredge, MBE, Secretary to His Excellency the Political Resident, Persian Gulf BAHRAIN.GOVERNOR'S OFFICE, ADEN, 23rd November, 1948. Sir, I have the honour to refer to Your Excellency's letter 91/7/48 of the 18th September and to express my thanks you gave in endeavouring to trace the criminal involved in the 'WHITAKER' case. It was naturally a great disappointment to me too that the Aden detectives had no success in their investigations, but I naturally felt in my duty to investigate every possible report and rumour and, as I say, I am most grateful to you for your co-operation. I am, Sir, Your obeuient Servant, Sd/- Illegible. GOVERNOR. His Excellency Lt. Col. A.C. Galloway, CIE., Political Resident, Persian Gulf, Bahrain. OBE., (TRUE COPY)D.O. No, (91/13/43) dated the 5th October, 1948, from P.R, —Mi—III IIMI 1 ———————— Please inform the Adenese and arrange with Mr, Sword for their return by Tanker, ltd. C.J.P. 6/10/48 Spoken with Mr, Sword who will inform me of ’’a' above on Saturday, H.M. has been told to have Adenese here on Saturday. ltd. J.1S.H.H. 7/10/48 2 Adonese - j^epatrlation_t.Q- ^iden» Bapco inform me they (^an arrange air passage 3 from Dhahran on 21st (cost £.56 inclusive of both). I have told them to book provisionally but I presume we must inform Residency ? Papers in C.tD. I believe. ltd. J.R.H.H. 16^ 10/48 17^ Secretary has confirmed that P.R. has to the two Adenese being sent by air on the 21st. He will not be writing. Bill for the passage will be sent direct to Residency by Bapco. I am telling II.M. to make the necessary arrangements 7. as regards travel. ltd. J.E.H.H. 13/10/43 no objection l&lt;y4 ^ /</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00012f_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/860</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00012f</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/860</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 37/3 Adenese detectives in Bahrain'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1948/1948</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-07-09T21:20:10</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (18 folios)</extent><extent>The papers in the file are arranged chronologically. There are file notes at the end, on folios 18-19. The notes are arranged chronologically and refer to documents within the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 20; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains correspondence and telegrams between the Political Agent at Bahrain, the Political Residency in the Persian Gulf, the Governor of Aden and Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited (BAPCO) representatives; regarding a visit of two Adenese policemen to Bahrain to investigate on a crime, and arrangements for their repatriation.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Bahrain Petroleum Company</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Governor of Aden</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Aden</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Criminal investigation</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00012f#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>