<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000047_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-09-25T15:58:18.033Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Previous File: Next File: General Heading I OR: kJptS ) Itpfij POLITICAL (EXTERNAL) DEPARTMENT COLLECTION No 2# IOO File 72 - \ M tAjL Jpv &lt;r*sty. Notes: A YEAR. / 19 i'J . P.Z. ^(&gt;4 This File contains the following papers : ^ / / / U-h-Lz. *130. ft33. 7i^A, / iQjr - p-z . 19 19 19 19 P.Z. P.Z. 19 . P.Z. P.Z. P.Z. 19 . P.Z. Papers may be removed from or placed within this File only by the Political Registry. . 500 11.35 4204bSir Stephen Oaselee, K.C.M.G., C.B.a Copy. (K 6064/6064/34) London. 3016 13th October, 1938. Dear Sir Stephen, With reference to my letter of the 15th January,1937, and to your acKinowledgraent No. L 340/340/4J5 of the 19th January, 1937, I shall be most grateful if you will be kind enough to let me know whether peraiasion can be obtained for the supply of the maps of Iran mentioned in ay letter, for transmission to Teheran. Believe me , etc (Signed) F. - abilV^' Vi l India Office F.Z.5835/37. Wh i t e iia 11, S. W. 1. ^7th September,1937 I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to refer to your letter of 24th March,No.E.1665/1665/34 and connected correspondence regarding the supply to the Government of Iran of those sections of the 4 miles to 1 inch Survey of India maps of Iran mar iced Dated 6th August letter from the Government of India on the subject / Hr.Eden will observe that the Government of India have carefully reconsidered the whole matter but are unable to agree to the release of the reserved maps. I am however to draw attention to the fact that the Survey of India maps covering the same area to scale 16 miles to 1 inch are available, and that in most instances the sections of this map are of more recent date than those of the scale 1/25^440. 3. The question of the application of the Afghan Government for copies of the reserved maps covering \ Afghanistan is being referred to the Foreign Office separately. 4. A copy of this letter is being sent to the War Office and Air Ministry. I am. Sir Your obedient Servant (Sd.) H. A F. RUMBOLQ The Under Secretary of State &gt; ENGLOSURE IN AIR MAIL LETTfeft NO. in »! el &lt;=1 . FROM S^OfiETMY, POLITICm. *ND Foreign Office S.W.l. St.Wi r:PT. INDIA OFFftEjr ah ::ul. COPY No.?. 394-N/37. From The Deputy Secretary to the Grovemment of India in the External Affairs Department, To His Majesty’s Under Secretary of State for India, Political Department, India Office, London. Dated Simla, the -2 6 ‘ August 1937. Subject Proposed supply of certain maps of Iran to the I Iranian (Government. Sir, With reference to the last para, of express letter from the G-overnment of India in the External Affairs Department No. D. 2550-N/37, dated the 8th July 1937, I am directed say that the whole policy concerning w For Official Use Only” maps of Persia and Afghanistan has been reviewed afresh in the light of the remarks made by His Majesty’s Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs in Foreign^ Office letter No. E. 1565/1665/34 dated the 24th March 1937, a copy of which was received with the India Office letter No. P.Z. 2006/37 dated the 15th April 1937. 2. The Government of India regret their inability to deviate from the past practice and still adhere to the view that the value of these maps as military maps is such that, in spite of any embarrassment that may result from withholding them, their supply to the Governments of Iran and Afgha nistan should be refused. In the circumstances they consider that.... ( ' x 2- c 2- -') r&amp;Go. POL. 3 .SEPl 837 i INDIA OFFICEthat the supply of these maps to other G-ovemments, e*g* that of the United States of America, should also be refused. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Deputy Secretary to the Government^ of India,India Office, -Jr'. ' 5 &gt;7 _ ’ P.2.4730/37. Whitehall, S.W.l. 27th July, 1937. India to refer to your letter of the 24th March, No.E,1665/1665/34, and connected correspondence, regarding the supply to the Government of Iran of certain Survey of India maps in the category ’’For official use only”, and to forward for the information of the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs a copy of an Express Letter from the Government of India on the subject. 2. In the circumstances I am to suggest that a reply to the enquiry of the Iranian Charge d 1 Affaires should if possible be delayed. A further communication will be made to you as soon as a decision is reached by the Government of India on the general question. . Copies of this letter are being sent to the War Office and Air Ministry. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, (Sgd.) M. J. 6LAUS0N The Under-Secretary of State Foreign Office, S.W.l. No. 3 0 2 9JUL 1937 FROM SECRETARY, POLITICAL Alto SECRET DEPT. INDIA OFFICE■■■ 0 GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. External Affairs Department. P. 7 .1 4730 i ,1937 EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). iZ 7 CoX 1 [N B .—This is an ORIGINAL message sent by AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, toith the same expedition as if it had been teleraphed. To save time and to obviaU formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department.] D.2550-N./37 simla Dated the % 4- July 7937. To His Majesty's Secretary of State for Ir3ia, London. T Proposed supply of certain maps ox Iran to the Iranian Government ^ 'i Ik/ X Reference express letter from the Govern ment of India in the External Affairs Department No.D.2550-N./37, dated the 30th June 1937. The Government of India regret that they are unable to agree to the supply of the maps mentioned in paragraph 1 of Foreign Office letter No.E.1665/ 1665/34,dated the 24th March 1937 to the Iranian Government at the moment. The whole question of 'For Official Use Only' maps is however being reconsidered and a further communication will be sent in due course. • •••••••« The issue of the above has been authorised.By Air Mall» Confidential* D* 0. Ho* ?• 435-P/35* oi P.Z. 3704/37. External Affairs Department, SIMLA. 22nd May, 1937. Supply of i' maps to the Afghan G-overnment. Dear Rumbold, Please refer to paragraph 3 of your demi-official letter No.P.Z.1175/37, dated the 22nd February, 1937. 2. I am desired to say that the 4-mile to l’ 1 maps of Afghanistan are 'For Official Use Only”, and the G-ovemment of India are therefore unable to accept the proposal for the supply of these maps to the Afghan Government. In this connection I am to forward a copy of Fraser-Tytler f s letter to Sir Richard Maconachie No.D.314-F/33, dated the 13th May,1933. i' The million sheets of Afghanistan are, however, on sale to the public, and there is no objection to the Afghan Government purchasing as many copies of these as they wish. 3. A copy of this letter is being sent to Fraser-Tytler. Yours sincerely. H.A. F.Rumbold, Esq. , India Office, London. (Sd. ) W. R. HAY.GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. External Affairs Department. » i 4 4 6 ° ^ o / EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). A I \j^r [N.B.—TAm wan ORIGINAL message sent by AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been teleraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department.] NoD.2550-N/37. ^ Dated TrxKYnat* the 3~o June 19 37. To His Majesty^ Secretary of State for India, London* &amp; ft Reference your express letter No*P # 2*2006/37 dated the 16th June 1937 regarding the Iranian Goverament*s request to be furnished with copies of certain maps of Iran* The question is still under cons ideration and a reply will be sent very shortly* The issue of the above has been authorised* Deputy Secretary to Ihe Govemmenji of India*In any further communication on this subject, please quote JV No - £Jr and address— not to any person by name, but to— ' The Under-Secretary of State,’ Foreign Office, London, S.W. 1. r W t THE Under - Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to ^ ^ ^ and begs to enquire, by direction of the Secretary of State, whether an answer may shortly be expected to the Foreign Office letter No. /66 of the ^ ■ respecting tftiz rj (fcjzmm Mm 7 , Draft Paper, p.z. 2006/37 POLITICAL m Department. The Secretary to the Government of India, External Affairs Dept., Simla. d/- 24.3.57. A- (U4U^ ^ ^ I 4 ^ h - So ^ to %S Puhtts u^juuf yy fauMvl , ' V&lt;am litU* khdfc* % &lt;o h %n,v 15 tL 04^1 m Sir, I am directed by the Secretary of State to forward for the information of the Government of India a copy of a letter from the Foreign Office regarding the Persian Government’s request to be furnished with copies of certain survey of India maps which are in t he category / 'for official use only'. The question of the supply of ft maps to the Afghan Government has already a been taken up demi officially with the Government of India. I am to enquire -whether, in the light of their foktUx consideration of question and of the observations made by the Foreign Office, A the Government of India still adhere to their view that the present classificatxn tft Puhe% of the remaining maps in the category A 'for official use only' must be maintained. (Sgd.) J, OLAUSON sMinute Paper. political Department. H Mr. Glauson, You will probably wish to deal with this yourself. You may like to have the following Note regarding discussions with the Commandant of the Afghan Air Force on the subject of maps. On 22nd December the Afghan Minister asked the Foreign Office whether the Air Ministry could make available to the Afghan Government fifty sets of maps of Afghanistan on the scale of 4-miles = 1-inch, and if these were not available then the maps in use by the R.A.F. The point was subsequently discussed between Mohammad Ihsan Khan and the Air Ministry, and on 10th February Squadron Leader Darvall wrote to the former and said: 'Regarding maps of Afghanistan, we have ascertained that there is a 4 M to the mile scale map of Afghanistan in existence which is printed in India, based on a very old survey of Afghanistan and published at the price of Rs.l As.2 per sheet. Eighty of these sheets comprise a complete map of Afghanistan. Whether it is still in print or not, we do not know. There is also a 16-mile to the inch series comprising eight sheets at Rs.3 per sheet. This map is also published in India, and it is probable that stocks are maintained and available. We suggest that the question of supply of these maps should be taken up in India on your return to that country where details will be immediately available, and we do not anticipate that there will be any difficulty in your being provided with them.' * On 22nd February I wrote demi-official^y to Major Hay asking him to let us know whether the Survey of India are in a position to sell to the Afghan Government one hundred sets (the Afghan demands/demands having meanwhile arisen) of the 4-miles to 1-inc map of Afghanistan, or, failing that, what map they recommend the Afghan Air Force to use. At the same time I wrote to Squadron Leader Darvall informing him that only one or two sets of the maps of Afghanistan required are available in this country, and that we were asking the Government of India whether the Survey of India can sell the Afghan Government one hundred sets. It is possible that Squadron Leader Daryall has passed this on to Muhammad Ihsan. I ooo ^fr-mnNote of 27th February ttefc the Foreign Office informed the Afghan Minister, in reply to his Note of 22nd December, that an enquiry has been sent to the Government of India regarding the maps of Afghanistan which his Government requires. ’lousiy hsidvon the' same da^j-fhe /O %c In any further communication on this subject, please quote O No. E 1665/1665/34. and address— vett to any person by name but to— “The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W.l. © ') n (&gt; r c u ^ J ! 9 3 7 Forkign Office. S.W.l. 24th March, 1937. Sir, I am directed hy Mr. Secretary Eden to transmit to you, :Cor the information of the llarciuess of Zetland, the acco : panying copy of a letter from the Persian Chargd d'affaires ashing for permission for his Government to purchase thirty- tuo sheets of the nap of India and Adjacent Countries published oy the Survey of India on the scale of 1: 253,4-40. The sheets in question are those covering Persia which are still retained for official use only, and are presumably sheets No. 22 K,J_,0,F; 23 I, J,K,L ,1/K,0,F; 28 C,D,H; 29 A,B, C,D,E,P,H; and 50 A,B, C^DjE^PjG/I^L, with one other sheet the identity of which is not immediately apparent. This request follows on similar enquiries addressed by the General Officer Commanding the Troops at Kerman to His Majesty's Consul at Kerman and by the Persian Consul-General in India to the Government of India. 2. Lord Zetland will be aware that the number of sheets of this series retained on the 'For Official Use Only u list was until recently much larger, but that as the result of semi-official correspondence between the India Office and Foreign Office regarding the supply of certain of these sheets to an American archaeologist named Schmidt, the number was i eciucec: t,o che thirty—one or thirty—two now in (question ^see cor-res^oiauence ending with Mr. Clauson’s letter P.Z.5812/3&amp; of the 19th August, 1956 to Mr. Baggallay). o. Mr. Eden's view which has already been expressed in the semi-official correspondence, is that since it is common knowledge/ The Under-Secretary of State, India Office,knowledge, not only amonr London nap-sellers, t&gt;ut a none foreign governments, that in addition to the sheets of this series that are on sale to the public there also exist sheets xhich are similar to the others in most respects, out are retained for official use only, it is preferable to place the whole of the series on sale to the public rather than to excite the suspicions of other governments in circu:et&lt;-.rces here no gxound for suspicion really exists. 4. Mr. Eden fully appreciates the reasons which have been advanced against this course in the case oi the sheets covering the eastern part of Persia, which is a possiole line of advance for an army attaching India; but in view of the fact that the continued withholding of these sheets is bound to engender a degree of suspicion in the minds of the Persian Government • hich is likely to become increasingly embarrassing as time goes on, I am to suggest that the Government of India should be invited to consider afresh whether the value of these maps as military maps is such as to render it impossible to supply the Persian Government with a number of sets for their own confidential use. 5. I am also to draw attention to the correspondence which has recently tahen place about the supply to the Afghan Air Force of sheets on the scale of 1: 253,440 covering Afghanistan (see India Office letters P.Z,1174/ 57 of the 20th February and P.Z. 1175/37 of the 22nd February), from which it appears that the Commandant of the Afghan Air Force was informed while in this country that there is not likely to be any/any difficulty in regard to the supply of these sheets fron India. I'r. Eden trusts that it will he possible to supply these sheets to the Afghan Government and the corresponding sheets to the Persian Government. 6. Copies of this letter are being sent to the Jar Office and Air Ministry, I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant,Copy (E l6bj/1665/34) -J 0 J Imperial Iranian Legati 16th January, 1957 Sir, I have been asked by my Government to obtain for them three copies of the Map of Iran, scale 1/253,440, published by the Survey of India, On making enquiries, I find that 3£ sections of this map are 'For Official Use only” and cannot be supplied without the prior sanction of the Chief of the General Staff, Army Headquarters, Simla, I am writing to ask if you think it would be possible for you to help me to obtain this permission, I shall be most grateful if you are able to assist me in the matter. Yours very truly, (Sgd.) F. Nabil Iranian Charge d*Affaires, Sir Stephen Gaselee, K.C*M,G,,</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000047_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/3511</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000047</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/3511</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 28/100 ‘Persia. Supply to Persian Govt of certain Survey of India maps in the category “For official use only”’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1937/1938</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-06-14T22:02:29</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (28 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 30; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Correspondence and papers relating to a request made in January 1937 by the Iranian Government to the British Government, for maps of Iran from the Survey of India, currently marked as being for official use only. Much of the correspondence is between the Foreign Office and India Office/Government of India, and discusses: precedents to the request (specifically, a request for Survey of India maps from the Afghan Government in 1936); the Government of India’s refusal of the Iranian Government’s request in August 1937, due to the continued military importance of the maps in question; a long delay in responding to the Iranian Government’s request, which remained unanswered until November 1938.The file includes a divider, which gives a list of correspondence references contained in the file by year. This is placed at the back of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Access to information</topic></subject><subject><topic>Maps</topic></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Survey of India</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of Iran, Pahlavi dynasty</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of India</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Iran</geographic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000047#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>