<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000212_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T20:07:38.231Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">No# 3664-1/53. From Political Agency, Bahrain, The 9th September, 1945. C.J. Pelly, Esq., O.B.E., I.C.S., Political Agent, Bahrain. To The Hon'ble the Political Resident In the Persian Oulf, Bushlre, Camp, Shiraz. Sir, \ ^ haV L th L^ r to refer to y our endorsement No.2747- 6V^7 dated the 9th July, 1946, and to report as follows:- 2 * Clerical Estab^i peace estabnsKf- 01 ' 1031 3taff are SUrplUS to the U; 3 Upper Division clerks in the English Office. t 'in the Confidential Office. ^ c; 1 m , , clerk in the Political Officer Trucial Coast's Office. 3. Of these the following should be retained n«Tnn«n^nfi v for reasons given belowt- * (a) 2 Clerks in the English Office. Rea^pn? Tliere is no record keeper or stenographer in the English Office, both of which are urgently required. For years little attention has been paid to the records here with the result that they are in a state of confusion - made a great deal worse by war conditions. A reeord keeper is required to get and keep them permanently in order. The Assistant Political Agent is overworked at present and has to waste his time writing routine drafts, ne needs a stenographer. (b) 2 Clerks in the Confidential Office. The pre-war establishment consisted of a Confidential Clerk and a stenographer only. fpu is a full time occupation. The following figures will* demonstrate the Increase of code and cypher work (figures of groups are not available). £ele£££C£.. 1938. 1944. Co(ie .. 136 520. Cypher .. 142 576. Code. 38 523. Cypher .. 252 633. In addition to one clerk therefore who should be retained for cypher work, one is required as record keeper and despatcher. Peqeiptg. Issuer.In 1938, 1711 letters were received In the Confidential Office and 799 issued. In 1944 the figures wore 3139 and 1948. (c) 1 Clerk in the Political Officer, Trucial Coast's Office. Recxson : In peace time| pre-war, there was no provision for a clerk for the flnglish work in the office. The Residency A^ent cannot and should not be expected to do the filing, draft ing and typing of the Knglish Office work and a clerk is essential for that v/ork. Anticipated increase of activities on the Trucial Coast makes his retention more and more essential. 4« The following posts could be reduced as soon as control of trade with the United Kingdom, United States of America and India is abolished. One clerk in the English Office. Gazetted JSstfiblishment . 5. Political Officer^ Trucial Coast . The post is at present sanctioned till the end of war or the end of February,11946, whichever is earlier. It should only be reduced if replaced by an Assistant Political Agent. This is desirable. The Residency Agent's post might then be abolished. Way A^ow^eg. 6. The following pre-war posts have been upgradedi- i) 3rd and 4th clerk in English Office, ii) Confidential Clerk in Confidential Office, iii) English clerk in Political Officer Tvucial Coast's Office. I recommend that the Confidential Clerk's upgrading to Special Grade should be retained aftar the conclusion of war, and do not propose to comment on the grading of the others which will presumably be dealt with by the Secretary as a matter of general policy. 7. Dearness Allowance at 50 per cent which has been sanctioned until 31st August, 1946, should be retained until such time as the cost of living returns to prewar standards if ever. 8. Spflfilal Special pay of Es.60/- per mensem for Superintendent has been sanctioned for the duration of war. This allowance might cease when the office returns to peace establishment. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most ' t servant, Political Agent, Bahrain. C.'/ r; r~\ Hahr^in Receipt No - Ml rut &gt; ..f t r.^?.r. Telegram, From. To. Repeated. ^ • Govennment of India, New Delhi. H.M f s Consul, Bushire. H.M f s Representative, Tehran. H.M 1 s Consul, Meshed. H.l^s Consul, Kerman. H.F's Consul, Khorramshahr. H.M's Consul, Bandar Abbas. Political Agent, Kuwait. Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Agent, Muscat. No. 204 No. 8046 ''ii 4 I I / Dated the 14th and received 15th September 1945. •- - Foreign Express Letter No. J.80-A/45 June 5th and August 29th. K-Special T .Var Expenditure. Termination of hostilities renders reduction of war-time expenditure imperative. Please imtimate immediately reduction in establishments and other expenditure that can be, made under the above / head before October 31st when term for all war-time expenditure expires.No. 3419-1/25 Political 1 Agency, T^ahrain, 27th August, 1945. To:- Thc Secretary to the Hon f ble the political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Rushire . Memorandian . Reference the attached application from Mr. Carrau. Faintenance a l lowance . 2. I recommend he is allowed to dravj the above allowance H*. 5/- per diem for the period 2nd to 18th April, 1945, both days inclusive, lovemment of India, External Affairs Department memorandum Ho. F.27(30-K/45, dated the 3rd February, 1945, in case of Hr.ylafiz refers to the claim in question. 3. 1 )carness al lovvancc. This office lias no information as to whether such an allowance is admissible but I understand it has been drawn on occasions by other clerks. If so, I recommend Mr. Carrau is allowed to draw dcamess allowance for the period 16th December, 1944 to 3rd May, 1945. 3d/- R.S.R. Rird. for Political Agent, Bahrain.The Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to His Majesty^ The Political The lolltlcal The Political Hla Majesty's His Majesty's Ills Majesty's Consul Agent 9 Agent, A^ent. Consul, Consul, Consul, General, Meshed. Muscat. Bahrain* ^ Kuwait* Kerman* Khorrarashahr. Bandar Abbas* and is directed to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents. British Residency and (-onsulate-Greneral,' BUSHIRE. |JJ r * &amp; Dated Hth 'Ctobf^r, 1.9^ , »'^* Reference to previous correspondence ; Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Telegram No* 15ii4 dated the 8th October, 1945, from the Political Resident, Hushire, to the Government of India, New Delhi* Subject. G.A*M* K - Special var Fxpendlture*Telegram Code. From Political Resident f Bushlre# To Government of Indiai New Delhi# Copy to Sub Offices# No#' 1624# Dated the 8th October, 1946# Your telegram No# 8046 September 14th# K - Special War Expenditure# 2. (larlcal ..stabl j.shaent. As 1 see It, though war is over, all controls except censorship remain and work so far from lessening remains at much the same level due to re•adjustment to peace-time conditions while oil interests are hurrying to catch up with development retarded owing to the war# This does not apply to all posts and because of relaxation of censorship and decrease in some branches of activity I feel I can make the following reductions in the interests of economy t - Upper Division Clerks Ximshi Special Grade Interpreter 6 1 1 3, I recommend that as at present the Lower Division posts should be held in abeyance and in their stead Upper Division posts retained# It has been emphasised in my letter No# 1829 • 79/263 dated 2Cth April, 1945, that it is impossible to obtain the right type of men for our clerical cadre on lower Division rates of pay# If the pay of clerks recruited on Upper Division scales reverts to Lo^er Division scale we shall be faced with resignations wbich will nullify our efforts t.^ build up a satisfactory cadre# 4 # I also recommend that Special Pay to certain Head Clerks and Confidential Clerks should continue until conditions become normal# « 5 # I also recommend that the post of Extra Assistant to Consul Kerman should be continued as the Consul must have a responsible officer to hold charge of the Confidential Office and cyphers especially when the Consul tours in his extensive district# . It is frequently necessary for the Consul to hold additional charge at Bandar Abbas at short notice making the presence of a reliable assistant at Kerman essential* r M '1 \ Ml. I ■ * GOVERNMENT OF INDIA . vv - .r-MfotsO AS-ii e P a^ ^ n,en ^• ..jxXVd - 2rj&gt; ,o« EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). &gt;vl\ [N.B.— This is an ORIGIN A L message sent by AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department.] No. 4114 - 67/16. Bu /i^; re Dated the 12th October, 1945. 10 . Ba'irain ■ . To FOREIGN NEW DELHI *$315' , j A,,.;..#..• ••• • ' Subject : Grant of daily allowance for enforced halts at Karachi or Bombay when returning from leave. Reference paragraph 3 of memorandum No. F.27(3)-E /45 dated the 3rd February, 1945, from the Government of India in the External Affairs Department, New Delhi. 2, It is recommended that a daily allowance of Es 5/- be sanctioned, for the number of days noted against each, to the following members of this Residency staff who were forced to wait for varying periods at Bombay or Karachi before they could secure passages on return from leave to Join duty. They w^re all non-residents of Bombay or Karachi and were put to considerable expense. r 1 J Name and Designation Native place Length of Period for which in India stay in daily allowance Bombay or is recommended. Karachi Mr. M. Bird, Officiating Confidential Clerk, Kuwait. Calcutta 20 days 13 days Mr. J. A. N. Carrau, Officiating Confidential Clerk, Bahrain. Calcutta 24 days 17 days Mr. S. K. Moorthy. Officiating Treasury Accountant, Bushire. Trivandrum (South India) 19 days 12 days Mr. K. V. Rajagopalan, Officiating Head Clerk, Bushire. Chidambaram (South India) 32 days 25 days Mr. V. B. S. Manian, Officiating Copyist, Bushire. Cuddalore, (South 10 days 3 days S. 44. The issue of the above has been authorised. mfp—1015 s&amp;p— (M-1870)—9-2-39 ^&amp;)oSecretary xo tbre Politica^f Resident ^ ^ in the Persian Gullr. £ -i^ll 1\l ll SANCTION ORDER No. 132. In accordance with the powers vested in him under S. R. 73, read with Appendix 13, the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf is pleased to sanction full daily allowance being drawn by Mr. N. Srinivasan, Officiating Stenographer, Bahrain, for the period 14th to 23rd August, 1945, both days inclusive, and half daily allowance for the period 24th August to 2nd September, 1945, both days inclusive, being the period during which he had accompanied the Political Agent, Bahrain, to Shiraz. 2. The prolonged halt was necessary in the interests of public service and entailed extra expenses. By order, for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. BRITISH RESIDENCY AND CONSULATE GENERAL, • i BUSRIRE. ' L t^Uri : * the 12th October, 1945. s ' Qytr/ (D No# 4119 - 63/54. Bushire, the 12th October, 1945. CcDpy to the Political Agent, Bahrain. g.a.mo^atio ' V^ ^|io SANCTION ORDER No. 134. The Hon f ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf is pleased to sanction under Fundamental Rule 49 (b) the grant of 20 % of the presumptive pay and 20 % of the Special pay of the post of Third Clerk, Bahrain, to Mr. M. Y. Siddiqi, War Establishment Interpreter, Bahrain, for carrying out the duties of the Third Clerk, Bahrain, in addition to his own duties from the 27th March to the 24th August, 1945, both days inclusive. , f/t' ' /' j ary to the Political Resi/Te 4 ri 4'Vi n TD^i^rn-? ' for Secretary zo the Political Res^flent in the Persian Gulf. BRITISH RESIDENCY AND CONSULATE GENERAL, BUSHIRE. the 15th October, 1945. No. 4165 - 63/54. Bushire, the 15th October, 1945 Copy, with compliments, to the Political Agent, Bahrain, with reference to his memorandum No. 4027 - 1/10 dated the 26th September, 1945. It has been the established practice not to give more than 20 % of presumptive pay to clerks holding additional charge of another post. G.A.M. .. . ' -no. vie POLITICAL AGjaNCY, BAHRAIN, November, 1946. To % The Secretary to the Hor^ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire . MEMORANDUM J? Reference your endorsement No«41C5-63/54, dated the 15th October, 1945, forwarding sanction order No.134, dated the 15th October, 1945 authorising 20^ of presumptive pay and 20% of the Special Pay of the post of the 3rd Clerk, Bahrain, to Mr.M.Y.Siddiqi. 2. Ur.Siddiqi has now claimed dearness allowance on the presumptive pay. Under F.R. 49(c) a Government servant may draw such compensatory allowance as the Local Government may fix. No dearness allowance was fixed by the Hon f ble the Political Resident in the sanction order referred to above. If dearness allowance is admissible to Mr.Siddiqi the rate at which it should be allowed may kindly be fixed. ' 10No. 4838 - 67/29. BRITISH RESIDENCY AND CONSULATE GENERAL, BUSHIRE. the 19th December, 1945 0 To The Political Agent, . ~ \ Bahrain. va ;-* . . vjb 1 b No MEMORANDUM Reference your memorandtim No. 4874 - l/l€ dated the 26th November, 1946. 2, Dearness Allowance on 20 ^ of tlje presumptive pay and 20 ^ of the special pay of the post of Third Clerk is admissible to Mr. Siddiqi. Dearness Allowance should be calculated at full rate up to Rs 200/- of pay and house rent and at half rate above Rs 200/- up to Es 600/-. for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. G.A.M.k r Bahrsi J/ 6 BRITISH RESIDENCY' CONSULATE GENERAL, BUSHIRE. IS' No. - - 67/16. Dated the 12th January, 1946. A copy of the undermentioned paper is forwarded to The Political Agent, Bahrain. The Political Agent, Kuwait, in continuation of this Residency endorsement No. unZ - 67/16 dated the 12th October, 1945. wSiV \o By order. for Secretary to tWpblitical Resident in the Persian Gulf. ENCLOSURE Memorandum No. F.27(48)-E/45 dated the 29th November, 1945, from the Under Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Department. G.A.M.By air Mall From - The Under Secretary to the Government of Indl« in the External Affairs Department. So - The Hon'ble the Political Resident In the Persian Gulf. Memorandum No. F.27(48)-E/45o Dated Simla, the 29th November, 1945. Subject : Grant of dally allowance to certain members of the staff of the Persian Gulf Residency for enforced halts at Karachi or Bombay. Reference your express letter No. 4114-67/16 dated the 12th October, 1945. 2. The Governor General in Council is pleased to accord sanction to the prpposal mentioned in the above-quoted letter subject to the condition that the dally allowance of Rs 5/- per diem will be reduced to Rs 2/8/- per diem in the case of persons who were not accompanied by their families during their enforced halt. 3. The extra expenditure involved during the current financial year should, as far as possible, be met by reappropriation from within the sanctioned budget grant. Sd. P. N. Krishnaswamy, ' Under Secretary to the Government of India. Copied. G.A.M.D.O. No. C/119. POLITICAL AGENCY, Bahrain, the 31st January, 1946. My dear Sir Geoffrey, With reference to your request to Bird for figures concerning monetary receipts in the Agency I enclose a note which he has compiled. \ I think it is safe to estimate that a falling off in receipts from the sale of stamps is not likely to take place, but probably receipts against fines will. 3. As regards raising the fee for Certificates of Identity, I agree with Bird in thinking that perhaps /our suggested figure is a little high. I recommend a revised fee # of Hs.2/a/- per Certificate of Identity for a single ;£3Ssk and Rs.3/8/~ for one valid for one year. Yours sincerely,« V . !• v /hen the Political Resident was last In Bahrain he said that to support any proposals wo mi^ht put forward to the Government of India for increased establishments in the Gulf it would be useful if we could show that the revenue accruing to the Goveminent of India had increased during the last few y^ars* I have therefore compiled some figures which may be of interest. 2« Revenue accrues from our Consular, Notarial and Judicial duties and in the following table I have giv*n figures for the \ / first two items together because, in practical notarial receipts are very small compared to those from passport /rork. 3. I have separated fines from Judicial. The relevant figures are as followsi- Year. Consular &lt;&amp; Notarial, at anro 3. Judicial, Fines. 1937 Rs. 17679-14-0 Rs. 3094—8-0 1938 18706-6-0 2660-13-0 1939 17778-14-0 i 6611-6-0 1940 22630-9-0 . . 4139-9-0 1941 19306-8-0 2847-13-0 1942 16273 —4 *0 4734-3-0 1943 11030-0-0 6141-14-0 17171-14-0 18716-12-3 1944 22660-4-0 *74830-0-0 97480-4-0 26476-13-9 1946 42697-12-0 13177-0-0 66774-12-0 26068-16-6 ♦ Includes Court fees of Rs«62543/- in one estate case. 4. The revenue from our Consular duties for the last two years exceeds the total revenue from Consular and Judicial activities together in pre-war years by a large figure - in 1946 it was more than double that for any pre-war year. % In 1938 Consular receipts for visas issued to subjects of the U.S.A. amounted to Ks.1806/- and in 1946 to fis.234-30/- tfith the opening up of ths Arabian American Oil Compnay's field InSaudi Arabia I think we can anticipate no v^ry appre~ .clable failing off in the 1946 figures, 6. The increase in fines .iay be attributed to off nces against war-time regulations and should not be exoected to continue at the present hi^i figure. The Political Resident mentioned that he had in mind proposing that the charge for Certificates of Identity should be raised from Fe.l/- to Rs.6/-* I can find no p.ps. in either the C.O. or dl.O. on this question but the number of Certificates of Identity Issued by this Agency appears to be on the Increase e.g. In 1943 we issued 282 1944 w 313 ♦ 1946 ' 563. Bearing In mind that the majority of travellers who use Certificates of Identity are not overburdened with wealth, I think that R3.a/- oer Certificate of Identity would be a bit too expensive and su r ,gtist might be a more appropriate charge. ?• I have not obtained figures for the Trucial Coast but if required we can easily do so. ki l-i (I / Lf ^ . As regards 7 above the rruclal Coast give tholr total figures for the sale of court-foe scamps and other receipts as 1943 Rs. 1,170.4.0 1944 ' 1,139.8.0 1945 ' 1,765.4.0 Trucial Coast receipts are on the increase and this may be expected to continue with the development of oil activities.Telegram From To No, Dated GTC (i) x I Secretary to the Political Resident, Bushire. Political Agent, Bahrain. . % A/171 2nd received the 3rd February, 194 -6. • ••••• Please report for the information of the Government of India detailed Justification for contin uance of additional special pay of Rs.^O/- per month to Head v Clerk and Rs,35/- per month to Confidential Clerk/ for cypher work, =BRITAIN= AMO. Bahrain Receipt ■ ifce y S r 2 ■J Telegram From To No. G* T. C. Britain, Bushire. Political, Bahrain. A/177. Dated the 2nd February and received 3rd. Government of India are of opinion as censor work has considerably diminished and control measures are generally being relaxed there is room for further reduction in temporary War Establishment which can be made forthwith. 2. With this end in view please conduct a detailed examination of work in your office and forward your recommendation supported by detailed statistics of work for say past four years. No. Britain, .Date.. .J. * . 4^No. Dated G.T.C. Political, Bahrain. Britain, Bushire. 98. 7th February, 1946. fx* av Your telegrams A/171 and A /177 dated February 2nd. ^■y 1. Maximum reductions possible in War Establishment are those given in ray letter 3664-1/53 dated the 9th September, 1945 and until the following war measures are withdrawn I cannot spare even the one clerk from the English Office:- Civil Requirements Programmes for India and connected work, local export licences, currency export restrictions, food supplies, dollar recommendations and U.S.A. and U.K. programmes, air priority work, ship's export licences and navicerts. Since the end of the war the only repeat only two war measures which have been terminated are censorship and Import Assistance Recommendation for the U.K. and U.S.A 2. Following statistics for 1938,1942, 1943, 1944, 1945 are quoted in support. a) English Office . Letters inward 2951, 3185 , 5449 , 6713,§7219&lt;, Letters outward 2029 ? 2332, 2988, 4018, 5303. Telegrams inward 106, 275, 667, 845, 928. Telegrams outward 187, 287, 518, 885, 913. b) Confidential Office. Letters inward 1711, 2662, 3250, 3139, 2215. Letters outward 799, 1986, 1848, 1945, 1176. Telegrams inward 152, 964, 1179, 1096, 761. Telegrams outward 199, 884, 899, 1156, 626. . Note. Decrease in figures for 1945 are due to transfer of certain files to English Office. Confidential Office is at present handling an average of 125 bags per month. 3. Superintendent's special allowance is justified on the grounds of complexity of duties and increase in work vide para 2 above. In this connection see your telegram No.A/420 dated 2nd March, 1944. 4. Confidential clerks special pay was sanctioned on grounds of increased responsibilities which show no sign of* - decreasing due to post-war developments in Oulf. 5. Please see my demi-official letter No.C/119 of the 31st January, 1946, (being despatched on Falmouth) which demonstrates increase in Passport and Judicial work in this Agency and also of Increased revenue accruing. Cases tried in 1938,1942, 1943, 1944, 1945 are as follows:-IJ I , / 7 Va^ V SANCTION ORDER NO.33 The Hon 'ble the Political Resident ir the Persian Gulf is pleased to accord sanction to the continuance, on the existing terms, of the undernoted temporary t blishment upto the end of February 1947;- B USHI RE 1 Superintendent, Class II, Gazetted. 1 Naval Cypher Clerk ( Special Grade) S Special Grade Clerks. 8 Upper Division Clerks. 1 Additional Shroff 2 Night watchmen. BANDAR .xBBAS 1 Upper Division Clerk, r r I I \ \ 1 Upper Division Clerk 1 Munshi 2 Ghulams ( peons) KH OBRaMSH AH R 1 Cypher Clerk ( Special Grade) 1 Munshi ^.lUaC.iT 2 Uppor Division Clerks(one Cypher clerk and one Confidential Clerk) 1 Munshi BAHRAIN v 6 Upper Division Clerks. KUWAIT 1 Additional Confidential clerk. SHaRJAH ^1 Upper Division Clerk. 2o The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf is also pleased to sanction the continuance, on the existing terms, of the undernoted temporary establishment up to the end of Slst March 1946, after which date these posts will be abolished BUSHI RE 2 Upper Division Clerks. I 7 ^ K &gt;./ 1 J ft A \ FC Ms- V- \)T.* 1 ; , CU r ^ - 1 \ Co pf r* S. The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf is also pleased to sanction the continuance of the special pay of E3.50/- p.m. to the Superintendent Bahrain, up to the end of February 1947., • I 4 A A ' * / Secretary to,the in the p BRITISH RESIDENCY AND CONSULATE GENERAL, BUSHIRE. the 14th February, 1946, ical Resident Gulf.- 2 7 9/ - 63/42. BRITISH RESIDENCY AND CONSULATE GENERAL, BUSHIRL. th® 14th February, 1946. Copy to s - 1. The Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Department, New Delhi, (in duplicate). 2. The accountant General, Central Revenues, New Delhi , 3. The Political Agent, Muscat. (in duplicate) 4. The Political Agent, Bahrain, (in quintuplicate). 5. The Political Agent, Kuwait. (in duplicate), 6. His Majesty's Consul, Kerman. (in triplicate). 8. lis Majesty's Consul, Bandar Abbas (in duplicate). 7. His Majesty r s Consul, Khorramshahr (in duplicate).Ij0&lt; 938-1/16. political Agency, Bahrain., March^ 24th 1946. A copy of Me und e men ^ o|f 13 Sharjah. k &gt; V 5 for Political Agent, Bahrain. Enclosure. Sanction order No.33 dated the 14th February, 1946 from the Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire.30- Extract of para 6 of Office Order datud the 23:d .jxrch, 1946, issued by the Residency &amp; Consulate uonorai, bushire The following postings and confirmations are raade with effect frou the 1st ^arch, 1^46:- XXX X XX 6. iir.timU* Joshi, Clerk, Hajkot Agency, is coufirwed in the Lower division, as 4th Clerk, Bahrain* —. Telegram From To No, Dated £1 GTC Secretary to the Political Resident, Bushire Political Agent, Bahrain. A /766 17th and received the 18th Hay, 194-6. • ••••• Government of India have asked again that the entire position of the temporary establishment in the Persian Gulf should be reviewed in detail with a view to retrenching as many posts as possible and result together with detailed statistics of work in respect of each post, year by year, since it's ? inaururation communicated to them before the end of June 1946. 2, Please conduct a detailed examinations in work in your office and forward your recommendations, so as to reach me before June Ijth 194-6. =BRITAIN=No.l782-i ^.y^, i To Political Agency, Bahrain, The 5th June, 19^6. The Secretary to the Hon f ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. h *10 m n^i Memorandum , Reference your memorandum No ,185 dated the 10th January, 1946, to the address of the Residency Agent, Sharjah, a copy of which was sent to me under No.l86. 2. Since the transfer of Mr. Jassim Barduli to Muscat, in September, 1944, Mr, Hamad bin Ali, Officiating Head Munshi of this Agency, has translated all Arabic letters receiyed here for the Bushire Residency, and has attended, and does attend to the Arabic work of the Hobble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, during the latter^ frequent tours in Bahrain. The extra work performed by Mr. Hamad bin Ali in this connection has been considerable, and I therefore recommend that under F.R.49 (b), he may be allowed to draw 5C$ of the presumptive pay of the post of Arabic Munshi, Bushire, with effect from the date on which it became vacant on 15th October, 194-5. 3, I have recommended 50^ presumptive pay, as in actual fact, Mr. Hamad bin Ali was performing many of the duties of that post long before it officially became vacant, since the various officiating incumbents succeeding Mr. Jassim Barduli had no knowledge of Arabic. Political Agent, Bahrain. h c.No.1896-1/16. Political Agency, Bahrain f The 16th June, 1946. The Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Kesldent in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, Camp, Bahrain * imaamma* i : Reference your telegram No•A/766 dated the 17th May, 1946, on the subject of the temporary establishment employed at Bahrain and at Sharjah. 2. Bahrain. Six posts of Upper Division Clerks have been sanctioned up to the end of February, 1947. Two of these were created vide Foreign^ Express Letter No.F.64-Ii/ 39 dated the 21st July, 1939, two vide Express Letter No.F.8 (22)-2/42 dated the 8th June, 1942, and two vide telegram No.496/A dated the 1st April, 1944. Their duties are in briefI - (A) English Office^ (i) Record Keeper. This post was separated from that of the Passport Clerk (4th Clerk) with effect from 1st November, 1943, as both the passport and record work had Increased considerably (for statistics of passport work please see Appendix A). The Record Keeper is at present in charge of 660 current files and some 460 closed volumes. He does the docketing and filing and has to take out and replace the files in their proper places in two separate rooms as there is no farrash capable of doing this work. The Record Keeper also deals with the considerable and increasing correspondence in connection with the issue of liquor permits. 137 permits were sanctioned last quarter and in addition supplementary lists are issued from time to time. Approximately 60 applications per quarter are refused. This is official ousiness, since,31 - 2 - under the State laws, only persons licensed by the Political Agent| are allowed to have liquor in their possession. (ii) Import Assistance and Exchange Control Clerk. 'v S Sixtythree files are entirely dealt with by this clerk. Merchants visit the office daily to make verbal enquiries regarding import and exchange control matters. The work of this clerk is likely to increase further for the reasons given in paragraph 4 below. He also attends to the purchase of N.A.A.F.I. stores for the Residency staff, and their packing and despatch to Bushire. (iii) Civil Supplies Clerk. This Clerk attends to the following!- (a) Civil Requirements Programme (half yearly allotments and correspondence regarding supplies from India for Bahrain, the Trucial Coast, Qatar via Bahrain). (b) Correspondence with the British Supply Mission in connection with grain supplies for Bahrain, Qatar and the Trucial Coast. (c) Bushire Residency workt- (i) Maintenance of account, making of local payments etc. (ii) Stamping and posting of official and private registered mails sent from Bushire. An average of 126 official registered letters are dealt with per month. (iii) Remittance of money orders. (iv) Correspondence regarding drafts with the local bank and subsequentXposting of these drafts on behalf of Bushire Residency. (v) Making local purchases on behalf of Bushire Residency and arranging their packing and onward despatch. Payments made during the last two months weret- April, 1946 Rs. 5,487-12-6 May, 1946 4,064-12-6. : (d) Preparation of statistics for the Annual Trade Report. I3 5' 3 Correspondence relating to all the work aientioned * above is dealt with, typed and filed by this clerk. He also does the encoding of telegrams concerning (iv) Despatch Clerk# . There has been a steady increase in the amount of diplomatic mail handled by this clerk, an average of 126 bags having been received ana despatched in recent months# Mails are collected and despatched from the British Overseas Airways Corporation almost daily, and for security reasons this work has to be done by the despatch clerk. He also makes out way bills, sorts mail, and arranges for the receipt and delivery of mail belonging to the Bahrain Govern ment, the Public Relations Office, and the local Service authorities, all duties which are responsible and onerous# This clerk also deals with navicerts, applications for which continue to increase with the growing volume of shipping now coming into the Gulf, nearly 40 navicerts having been issued by this Agency during the four months January - April, 1946# (v) Cipher Clerk, and Record Keeper# There has been a decrease in telegrams but I still require the services of a clerk who can look after my codes and ciphers when I go on tour, and I anticifxate that there will be an increase in cipher traffic when I take over as Reporting Officer upon the departure of the Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, from Bahrain# This clerk is, however, already kept busily employed# As record weeper he handles a total of 576 current files and 313 closed volumes, dockets and files all papers, and also helps with the typing in the Confidential Office# (C) Public Bala-Ions Office. (vi) This post is vacant owing to the death of Mr# M#Y. Siddiqi# his cases# (B) Confidential Office.■/ ,r 3? - 6 - 5 # Much work still remains to be done on our records despite the attention bestowed on them by my predecessor - and a reduction or staff now would lead to a loss of system in maintaining records. The Record Keepers both in the Confidential and English Offices are at present so occupied with routine work that they have little time left in which * to improve the state of their records# 6* In paragraphs 3 and 4 of his letter No»3664-l/53 dated the 9th September, 1945, my predecessor suggested that when trade control was abolished one temporary post could be retrenched while four temporary posts (two in the English and two in the Confidential Offices) should be retained permanently* I do not agree to the abolition of this post and suggest that it should be retained permanently# With the expansion of the office the work of the Accountant has automatically greatly increased and to cope with his work he is forced to work long hours out of office time# Similarly the Passport Clerk is greatly overworked. I con sider that in order that their efficiency should not be impaired, they should be relieved of some of their present work by this additional clerk, as soon as his other duties will permit# 7. The Persian and Urdu censorship work, on which Mr# M#y« Siddiqi was mai^Ly employed in the Public Relations Office, ceased with effect from the 4th October, 1945* This Clerk has since died and I have already recommended in my memorandum No#1631-1/23 dated the 20th May, 1946, that the post should be retrenched# 8# strerJah* The posts of the Political Officer, Trucial Coast, and his clerk are temporary and I endorse the recommendations made in paragraphs 5 and 3 (c) of my predecessor's letter No#3664-1/63 dated the 9th September, 1946, except that I do no t agree that it will be possible to abolish the post j 5 li• 6 - 27 of Residency Agent# The tempo of the work on the Truclal Coast is likely to increase considerably during the coming years 9 and it seems probable that it will later become necessary ^ augment the Political Officer, Trucial Coasts staff still further# In my viewi therefore, it will continue to be essential for him to have a reliable Arab assistant* In the absence of the Political Agent, Bahrain# ir LV s ' % BRITISH RESIDENCY AND CONSULATE GENERAL, BUSH IRE « ^ w No. Zclti -63/17. Dated the 22nd M a y, 1946. A copy of the undermentioned paper Is forwarded to The Political Agent, Muscat The Political Agent, Bahrain- The Political Agent, Kuwait H&amp;e Majesty's Consul, Kerman His Majesty's Consul, Khorraashahr His Majesty's Consul, Bandar Abbas with the remark that position ra ay he reviewed in September and recommendations sent to Bushire the Budget Proposals for 1947-lc48, ^ - yv .v v By order, L Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. F.^IGLOSURE PCopy of Express Letter No. F.2 7 (5 3 )-R/45.dau e d the 1st April, 1S46 from the pSli^a! the External Affairs Department to the Poli Resident, Persian G-ulf, ij^sture# ^vq SARMAJ f £2£I' KROV TO OOVBRHMKHT OF INDIA, KTW.KHAL AfTAinS Wk'-'TW. BYPRFr.S LKTTEB. FORf.IOK, Simla. ^1* BHITAIH, Biishlr®. No. ?.27(53)»K/45. Dated Slala, th« l«t April, 1946. Subjecti- of 3n ag i A i imra to th&gt; clerXa of the gulf ^ on cyiU^rM to e^rtaln Head ClTfci/ Referfeace your express letter Ho# dated the 11th Pehrti®ry f 1946. ^ 2, Sarction la accorded to the continued of special paya mentioned In jov^ru rnt of India f External Affairs Department Sxpress Letter No. F.27 (53)-S/45 f dated the 8th January, 1946 up to the end of February f 194f # 3 # The position should be kept under constant rerlew and the results of your rerlew, together with your recowaondatlons, should f If you consider lt^ necessary to continue these special pays beyond Feb ruary 1947, be cocmmlcated to the Govermaent of In&lt;* J when you approach the© for budget provision on this account during 1947-1948• The issue of tte above has br»en authorised. 3DA P.N. KRISHKASWAMY 9 Under Secy, to the Gort. of India.•Rajkot, 30th April, 1946, Mr. Navalshank^r M. Joshi, B.A,, LL,3., having been confirmed in the Persian Gulf Residency Clerical Cadre, his lien in this Residency Clerical Cadre is terminated with effect from the 1st March, 1946, 3d, J.R. Cotton. Secretary to the Resident at Baroda ^ for the States of Western India and Gujarat. Copy to The Accountant General, Bombay, The Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf for information with reference to his letter No. 1203-63/54 dated the 23rd March, 1946. The Accounts and Finance Officer, Rajkot. Sd, Illegible, for Secretary to the Resident at Baroda &amp; for the States of Western India and Gujarat.'If - \io Telegram From To No. Dated GTC His Majesty's Consul, Bushire. Political Agent, Bahrain. A/872 18th and received the 19th June, 1946. My telegram No.'A /766 May 17th.lTemporary Establishment. 2. Please expedite- submission of your recommendations. =BRITAIN= _ . _ I.R.458 AMO.4^ No. 1990-1/16. Political Agency, Bahrain, The 23rd June, 1946. A copy of the undermentioned papers is forwarded tox The Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, Camp, Bahrain^ for fayeur jjiformation. for Political Agent, Bahrain. List of paafers forwarded. 1. Copy of telegram No•A/872 dated the 13th June, 1946, from His Majesty^ Consul, Bushire, to the Political Agent, Bahrain. 2. Copy of telegram No.356 dated the 22nd June, 1946, from the Political Agent, Bahrain, to His Majesty^ Consul, Bushire, if 4^.I^« U, SANCTIOM ORDER NO. 108 In exercise of the powers conferred on him onasr f # a. tLe Hon'ble the Political Resi dent in ths Persian Gulf, Bushire, is p]eased to sanction the grant of 50^ of the presumptive pay (inciuaing special pay) of the pest oi Arabic Munshi, Bashire, to Mr. Hamad bin All, officiating Head Munshl, Bahrain, for carrying out the duties of Arabic Munshi, Bushire (Camp Office, Bahrain), in addition to his orm duties from the 15th October, 1945, to the 26th Dec^nber, 1 ^45, both days inclusive, for iThich period the post of Arabic Munshi, B'shire, remained vacant. Bahrain Receipt ^ H BRITISH HEaiDBNCY Alii) COUSULATjii-G&amp;a&amp;iUL, BUSH IRS* The Srd August, 1946. No. 2^2^-64/46. Bashire, the Srd August, 46, Copy to The Accountant General, Central Revenue^, New Delhi. The Political Agent, Bahrain,The Agency, Bahrain, October 13, 1946. To The Political Agent,, Bahrain. Sir, I beg to say that I have been transferred to this Agency in the beginning of 1940, when I was posted as 3rd Munshi. On 2nd August, 1942 I was confirmed as 2nd Munshi and posted to officiate as Head Munshi. Ever since I have been holding this posted, and now I have completed more than four years. During this period I have carried out my duties to the best of my ability and to the , satisfaction of my superiors. I shall therefore be much obliged if you will kindly recommed me to the Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf for confirmation in the post of the Head Munshi, Bahrain, which ±x has permanently been vacant since a long time. I have the honour to be, Sir, ; Your most obedient servant. Head Munshi, Agency, Bahrain. Political Agency, Bahrain. 14th October, 1946. Forwarded and recommended. „ .v Political Agent, Secretary to the Hobble the ^Bahrain. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, \ ^ Q Bahrain , ^ 1■ * Mr. Hamad bin All, Second Munshl, Baiu^ain. and officiating Head Munshi, Bahrain, has been confirmed as Head Munshi, Bahrain. Flth effect from the S&gt;4th October, 1946. Secretary to in the PERSIAN GtTLF RPSIPEHCY, BAHRAIN, the 29th October, 2^46. No, ?388 - 64/46♦ Banrjiin, tne ^th October j 1946* Copy to ; - T ie Accountant Oenex^ai, CencraX Kevenues. New Delhi, The Political Agent, Bahrain, with reference to his endorseuiGnt No, 3377/1/6. dated the 14th October, 1946.The Secretary to the Hon , ble, the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Bahrain. Through The Political Agent Bahrain. Sir I beg to state that for the last two years and a half I have been working as the Second-Munshi of this Political Agency. Daring that period I have carried out the work of the Court Clerk in the Court of the Indian Assista t to the entire satisfaction of r.y superiors. The following is an extract of the Court inspection report dated 18th Kovember, 1946 i- 'Records are in general neatly maintained and the Court Clerk was able to produce all papers called for without delay or difficulty ... the general work of the Court appears satisfactor-. Court discipline is excellent'. As the post of the Second-Munshi is vacant at present I request that I may kindly be confirmed in it I beg to remain, Sir, Your most obedient servant. M.A. Mansury Dated, 10th December, 1946 7^9(y /* IIO- No. 4 (152)-E. VI/4t&gt; ; , . .o^v^rjoiirs't of istbla FINAXCE DEPARTMENT A t « m ' Delhi the 12th N»vemher, 194ii OFFICE MEMORANDUM S ubjeot:— Ccmverwrn of a proportion of temporary posts under the Central Government into permanent ones . ^ ^eadvittjo 1 ' the M.O.G. Committee, the Co-ordination Committee of the Cabinet hav&lt;- decided that a start should be made to convert a proportion ol temporary posts into permanent ones. This is to be done on tie basisofthe volume of work which, on a rough estimate, may be regarded at of a pentaneRt ekaraeter im e«k Department and its attached and subordinate formations. f+ . 2 -iJ he De Partmonts are now requested to prepare and place before the Establithment Proposals Committee of the Finance Department, their proposals in this direction. The Establishment Proposals Committee will, on the basis of the information thus furnished, endeavour to form an approximate estimate of tke f)er*a«.ent fce«t« likely to be required in the Departments concerned which it will proceed to sanction. 3 It is recognised that certain difficulties stand in the way of estimating the total volume of work in each Department which can be accepted as of a permanent character, for example, the framework of the Central Sec retariat organisation is likely to undergo changes in the light of the recommendations in the Tottenham Report suggesting an increase in the number of officers and a reduction in the strength of Superintendents and Assistants and as a resul^f constitutional changes, a very much reduced sphere ot administration may possibly be reserved to the Centre. On the other hand the Departments may feel that they cannot be expected to maintain efficiency unless a reasonable proportion of posts is placed on a permanent looting. These factors are mentioned to im press on departments the need for caution in framing their proposals. uirerawatte tem ^ &gt;0rar ^ P 05 ^ 8 sanctioned since the start of the war may have been for any of the following re' (o) More or less permanent additions to the work of the Departments, arising out of the extension to their previous activities, or the addition of items of business. (6) For work related directly to the prosecution of war including controls wkiek it has been decided to dis. continue (or relax) after the 30th September 1946. (c) Work arising out of war conditions but expected to continue after the wav for an appreciable period or to continue more or less permanently, including the work relating to powers taken by the Centre on subjects in the Provincial List in the Government of India Act, 1935. 5. Departments should group their present temporary staff in the three categories indicated above while com- pletmg the enclosed statements which have been drawn up to ensure uniformity of presentation to the Establish- ment Proposals Committee of the Finance Department. In certain Departments whole sections or branches will lall into one or other of these three categories. Where an entire Department is itself on a temporary basis, and it is not proposed to make it permanent, though it includes permanent officials in the sanctioned strength, a covering note should be submitted to the Establ^hment Proposals Committee as to the Department's idea' on the ultimate disposition of the peimanent group and any addition thereto that is now proposed. 6. Departments should compile their statistical material in the enclosed statement, section bv seetien ihe sectional statistics (statement I) should, cover :•— (0) Grade of employees. (6) Scale of pay ot grade. (c) Number of post s in each grade as on 1st April 1940 (if the Department or formation, did not exist on lixat date, the statistics should relate to the date on which tke Department, ete. was started) (d) Number oi posts in each grade now (on lit November 1940| split ketween permaneat and tem porary. (e) Proposals as to how many of the temporary posts are to be made permanent *ew. (/) Reasons in brief for the proposals in («). These sectional statements should each be supported by narrative reports setting out fully the justiJication for ^kmg that num^r of temporary staff permanent. In the case of old sections (i.e., those that existed on or before 1st Apnl 1940) the narrative should explain (a) the reasons for the present expansion of staff over the pre-war level, (1) the formula, if any, adopted for gauging requirements, (c) whether the section is likely to (i) revert to pre-war strength or fall below it, or (i$) continue at present strength, or (u») expand beyond it, and (W) what was the peak figure of employment and when ?GOVERNMENT OP INDIA, POLITICAL AGiSNCY, D kpartment , BAHRAIN. EXPRESS LETTER [JS. B % —This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by -post to save telegraphic expense and undue me of the wires, but intended to he treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if il had been telegraphed. To nare time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had bo&amp;u to despatched*] F rom POLITICAL, BAHRAIN. To Fu^PGU, BAHRAIN. No. 4162-1/16 hated the 23rd December ,^46 • Your endorsement No.3714-63 /65 dated the 13th December, 1946. 2. The statements are returned herewith duly completed. 3. The following are my recommendations:- (a) All the six temporary upper division posts (five in Bahrain and one in Sharjah) should be made permanent. The reasons for this have been explained in Agency letter No.3664-1/63 dated the 9th September, 1945, and memorandum No.1896-1/16 dated the 16th June, 1946. Statistics of work handled in the various sections during the years 1939 to 1946, and up to the 31st October of this year, are given in the attached statements. (b) Consequent on the increase in the responsibility and work of this post, the appointment of Confidential Clerk should be per manently raised to Special grade. (c) The two lower division posts of Third Clerk and Fourth Clerk should be permanently raised to upper division as it is impossible to obtain efficient men on the present lower division scales of pay. = POLITICAL = The issue of the aoove has been authorised. iy/ Asstt. Political Agent, tP/tr Bahrain. S. 6. TP mfp—-501 s&amp;p—(m-siio)—23-7-36—300,000. ^ G. i+oIf Ifa H Persian Qulf Residency, Bahrain* No.68-63/17. Dated January, 1947. A copy of the undermentioned paper is forwarded toi The Political Agent, Muscat, The Political Agent, Bahrain, The Political Agent, Kuwait, His Majesty's Consul, Bushire, His Majesty's Consul, Kerman, His Majesty's Consul, Khorramshahr, His Majesty's Consul, Bandar Abbas, 1 in continuation of this office endorsement No.20^.63/17 dated the 22nd May, 1946. . % oA . for Secretary to ;the Political Resident, Persian Gulf. r* Enclosure. Memorandum No.F.27(39)-E/46 dated the 21st December, 1946, from the Under Secretary to the Govt, of India in the External Affairs Department, New Delhi, to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain. Subject: Continuance of the grant of special pays to clerks in the Persian Gulf engaged on confidential work and to certain Head Clerks. Reference item (b) of para 4 of your express letter No.3221-63/17 dated the 9th October, 1946, on the above-noted subject. 2. Sanction of the Governor General in Council is accorded to the continued grant of special pays mentioned in the Government of India, External Affairs Department, acpress letter No.F.27(53)-E/46 dated the 8th January 1946, up to the end of September, 1947. 3. The position should be reviewed before the expiry of the present sanction and the results communicated to the Government of India well in time. C* \i Persian Gulf Residency, Bahrain* No # 69-63/l7. Dated the 9th January, 1947. A copy of the undermentioned paper is forwarded to: The Political Agent, Muscat, / The Political Agent, Bahrain, v His Majesty's Consul, Bushire, His Majesty's Consul, Kerman, His Majesty's Consul, Bandar Abbas, His Majesty's Consul, Khorramshahr, for Secretary to^tlle^ Political Resident, Persian Gulf. Enclosure, Memorandum No.F.27(52)-E/45 dated the 23rd December, 1946, from the Under Secretary to the Government of India in the ^ External Affairs Department, New Delhi, to the Hon'ble the ^ * Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain. Subject: Temporary upgrading of lower division posts to upper division in the Persian Gulf. Reference item (a) in para 4 of your Express Letter No. 3221/63/17 dated the 9th October, 1946, on the abovenoted subject. 2. Sanction is accorded to the continuance up to the end of September, 1947 of the arrangements sanctioned in the Govern ment of India, External Affairs Department, telegram No.9078 dated the 23rd October, 1943, excepting the post of Upper Division Clerk at Kuwait for which no budget provision has been asked for. 3. The position should be reviewed before the expiry of this sanction and the results of the review communicated to the Government of India well in time. C.No.496-1/16 Politicdl Agency, Bahrain The 13th February, 1947 To The Secretary to the lion'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gu-if, Bahrain. Meaorandum : In view of their special technical qualifications, it is usual for stenographers in Government offices to be given a separate shorthand allowance. It is requested that sanction be obtained for the grant of a similar allowance of Ms.SS/- p .m. to the Confidential stenographer of this Agency. At present the Confidential stenographer drawsjthe sarae rate of pay and allowances as other clerks in the Confidential Office, and receives no special allowance for the additional tech nical qualifications he possesses. Further the grant of a special shorthand allowance would, in my opinion, act as an inducement to other clerks in the cadre to qualify as steno graphers. There are at present very few of this category in the Persian Gulf Clerical cadre. 2. It is recomuended that, if possible, this allowance be sanctioned with retrospective effect from the 4th March, 1945, the date on which -Ir. N. orinivasan, the present incumbent of the post, took over cUarge. Dearness allowance, at the rates sanctioned from time to time, should also be admissible in respect- of this special allowance. for Political Agent, Bahrain TPPERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY BAHRAIN No. 5$^ -63/42. S' ^ March, 1947. The Political Agent, MEMORANDUM Bahra in. Your memorandum No.496-1/16 dated the ISth February 1947. 2. While sympathising with your desire to increase the incentive to members of the clerical staff to become proficient as stenographers, I do not feel that the present is an opportune time to apply to the Government of India for special allowances of this nature. It is regretted there fore that your proposal cannot at present be supported. It will however be borne in mind in any general re-organisation of the Persian Gulf clerical cadre that may take pjace^in the future for Secretary to the Political Resident,.Persian Gulf. &lt;laD.O. No.C/372. The 20th of March, 1947. Dear Colonel Hay, As you may remember, two of the temporary clerks in the Confidential office of this Agency, Ringrow and Smales, have applied for appointments in the Kuwait Oil Company, and I am forwarding today an application from one Scihadevan of my English Office requesting that he be recommended for a job in P.C.L. It seems likely that as soon as they are able to leave, and that time may not be far away, our clerks holding temporary posts will go; and it is, of course, impossible not to sympathise with then - and indeed if we cannot offer them permanent employment ourselves, we should do our best to obtain it for them elsewhere. Most of the men who were recruited during the war have done us very well often in somewhat trying circumstances. 2. The point, however, which I am anxious to make is that if v /e lose our temporary staff in the present state of our cadre, the result in this Agency, at any rate, will be that we will be unable to compete with a very large part of our work. I would, therefore, request that the Government of India be urged most strongly to accept without further delay the recommenda tions made in my Express Letter No.4162-1/16, dated the 23rd December, 1946; and that confirmations in the permanent posts thus created be taken up as soon as possible. Yours sincerely, Sd./- C.J. PELLY The Hon»ble Lt-Col. W.R. Hay, C.S.I., C.I.E., political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain. NS.r mm f&gt; mm* w,. '/v , D.O.No. 8Aty -63/63. H n PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY BAHilAIN 7th April, 1947. As sorae one a fairs'prevails among the staff about their future I am directed to say that Colonel Hay is doing his best to find out what will be the future of the ministerial staff of the Persian Gulf cadre and will forward with such recommendations as he considers fit, any application for employment in the Indian Foreign Service. Colonel Hay proposes to discuss the whole matter when he goes to Delhi. 2. Meanwhile Colonel Hay is v not willing to assist any further applicants for non-Government employment. Temporary clerks may apply direct for such employment if they wish and if a reference is made to him regarding their characters he will reply suitably, S. I am to say that there is no objection to your bringing the above information to the notice of your clerical establishment. C.J.Felly, Esq., O.3.E., I .C.S., Polittal Agent, Bahrain. v ■ %»■ Bahrain Rece( ^ I From - The Under Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Department, To - The Hon 1 ble the Political Resident in Persian Gulf, BAHRAIN. Memorandum No. F.27(3)-E/47. Dated New Delhi 3, the (/(s March 1947. Subject:- Continuance during 1947-48 of temporary post of Special Grade Clerk in lieu of Confidential v Clerk, Bahrain, . / r Reference your express letter No.132-63/15, dated the 21st January 1947. 2, Sanction is accorded to the continuance, on the existing terms, of the temporary post of Special Grade Clerk, in lieu of the permanent post of Confidential (Upper Division) Clerk, Bahrain, up to the 29th February 1948. 3 # Necessary provision has been made in the budget for 1947-48. Sd/- P.N. Krishnaswamy. Under Secretary to the Government of India. VV No. 7^7 -63/17. Persian Gulf Residency ' Bahrain April, 1947. Copy forvarded to the political Agent, Bahrain, for information, witiaxiaf«xsLKij£Rxisx fei* Secretary to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf*it Persian Gulf R«sid#ncy, BahrAin. Dat«d 19th May, 1947. v v U. n 1171-CS/SO ll\ ^ J ±4 ^ as: ^ r * Q r«f«r to the correspondence resting with this Residency memorandum No. 1103-39/30 of the 10th May, 1947, and to say that, if there is a case for the creation of a new post of passport clerk for the Bahrain Agency to enable you to take over the issue and renewal of passports on behalf of the Residency, Colonel Hay will be glad to put it up to the Government of India- 2* lo assist him to do so, I am desired to request you to provide him with statistics of passport work done in the Agency and revenue earned in the past two years, also with an estimate of the additional work, likely to be involved by the work now to be performed on behalf of the Residency. Any other cogent reasons for requiring an extra clerk may also kindly be given. C. J. Pelly Esquire, O-B.E., Political Agent, Bahrain. EMB.D.O. Ho. 1851-1/16 Dated the Slst May 1947 VYlll you please refer to your demi -official letter No. 1171-30/30 dated the 19th May 1947. o statistic* passport work done in this Agency, and of the revenue accruing from consular functions have 3^ already been given to the Besidency in our expx'ess latte. ^ No. 4162-1/16 dated the 23ru Doceiaber 1946 and demi -official letter No. C/119 dated the 31st January 1946. Consular revenues amounted to Bs« 40|023-4-0 during l^MG. 3 # The Agency passport clerk is already heavily over worked and can only keep up-to-date with his files by working 1 J X W long after office hours ©very day, during office hours, much of his time is spent in dealing with verbal enquiries from the general public, a type of work which It xs not possible to record in statistical form. If therefore pass ports are to be issued from this Agency at least one more clerk will be required in the passport ofi. ice to prepare ^he accounts and returns concerned with them, in addition to the actual preparation of the passports theiaselves; and later, as the activities of ARAMCO and PCL continue to increase, it is probably that further additional staff will be needed. 4 # Pelly has seen and approved the draft of this letter. Yours sincerely, O/G • 16$ G.N. Jackson, iisquire, M.B.ci., Secretary to the xion f ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain.D.O.No.1512-63'54. PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN. The 1st July, Will you please refer to our. conversation regarding the appointment of a 'Passport Clerk' 1 for the Agency, Bahrain ? ^ f 2 * Mr. K.R. Mani who arrived from India on the 29th June, 1947, has been instructed to report for duty in your office, will you let me know as soon as possible whether he or some other clerk is to be shown as Passport Clerk, in this connection please see the order (copy enclosed) creating a temporary post of Passport Clerk. SWA, C. J. Pelly, Esquire, O.B.E#, I*C*S., Political Agent, Bahrain. S660 S ?. 0- ^ v/ K0» 60 of 1947 . SANCTION QKDER d The Ho&amp;'ble the politleal Resident Xm the Persian Golf is pleased to sanetioa the ereatioA f for the period from the 1st June, 1947, to the 29th February, 1948, of a temporary post designated 'PASSPORT CLERK', Political Ageney, Bahrain, on the following rate of pay and allowances i- UPPER DIVISION Pay - Rs« 120-6-150-10-250. Golf Allowance (Special Pay) - Rs. 35/-, House Rent - Rs. SO/-. Dearness Allowance at the sanctioned rate. Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf PERSIAH GULF HESIDEHCY, BAHRAIN. The 1st July, 1947* SWA, Copy to t !• The Accountant General, Central Revenues, - N«w Delhi.* ' L 2* The Political Agent f Bahrain. X. J*1 POLITI ^L w iUCT, .1!. D.Q. Wo.l-J/I ViG e 10th July, 1947. ST- Will you please rcfar to your demi- official letter No.1612-63/54 dated the 1st July, 1947, to Jr. Pelly. 2. It is suggested that Mr* Ghulaa ii .alder be shown as Passport clerk t and Mr. Kani as officiating Fourth clerk. The latter reported here for duty on the morning of the 6th July $ 1347, oj c Major G.I. Pettigrew, Secretazry to the Hon^le the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf| Bahrain.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000212_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1003</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000212</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1003</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 1/16 II Clerical Staff: Establishment, Proposals for Increase or Decrease; Rulings Regarding Pay and Allowances, and Promotion'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1945/1947</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-01-15T00:02:57</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (70 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in chronological order from the front to the rear of the file. Circled serial numbers (red for received correspondence; blue/black for issued correspondence) refer to entries in the notes at the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation system in use commences at 1A on the front cover and continues through to 71 on the back cover. The sequence is written in pencil (except for ff.3-4, which are written in red crayon, and ff.21-23, which are written in blue crayon) and appears in the top right hand corner of the recto page of each folio. ff.19 and 20 need to be folded out to be read. Foliation anomaly: ff.1A, 1B. Numbers forming part of the foliation sequence, but which are used as pagination numbers: 10, 54.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains papers relating to the following subjects:proposals by the Government of India for reductions in the numbers of temporary staff as a consequence of the end of World War Two, June to September 1945;allowances for clerks making enforced halts at Karachi or Bombay when returning from leave, October to November 1945;pay and dearness allowance of Third Clerk, October to November 1945;monetary receipts of the Political Agency, Bahrain for the years 1937 to 1954, January 1946;continuation of special pay to Confidential Clerk, February to April 1946;summary of duties of members of temporary establishment at the Political Agency, Bahrain, with statistics of work, 1939 to 1946, covering letters, telegrams, export permits, and passport and consular work, January to December 1946;request for grant of shorthand allowance to Confidential Stenographer, February to March 1947;creation of post of Passport Clerk, February to March 1947;other papers relating to the clerical establishment, including pay, appointments, composition, and numbers.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Bahrain Political Agency, Clerical Establishment</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Bahrain Political Agency, Clerical Establishment, Third Clerk</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Bahrain Political Agency, Confidential Stenographer</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Bahrain Political Agency, Confidential Clerk</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Bahrain Political Agency</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">creator</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Agent</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">creator</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Personnel</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000212#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>