<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000129_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T11:54:43.399Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">/ [This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Gnvpmmont ’ [A] PERSIA. CONnDENTIAL. [January 13.J Section 14 . [ 2204 ] No. 1. [2763 n—14] Memorandum by Mr. Parker respecting Pailway Construction in Persia. THE general idea which underlay the Anglo- Russian Convention respecting Persia was that the old policy, based on suspicion and resulting in reciprocal obstruction, had, after an ample trial of ninety years, failed to bring adequate and lasting advantage even locally either to Great Britain or Russia. The immediate object of the Convention was to lessen friction : but it was not intended to stop at this, and, having regard to the political conditions prevailing in Persia, and indeed to the existence under the Convention of a “ neutral ” sphere, the obvious corollary of abandoning mistrust £nd opposition, and an essential factor to the success of the new policy, was to be sought in the growing co-operation of both countries. Sir A. Nicolson When therefore the Russian Government No. tentatively laid before His Majesty’s Government December 1, 1909, the project of a Trans-Persian Railway, asking and subsequent . . . . .. ... . . despatches. especially that they should not decline to investi gate the question of joining the Russian and Indian systems, it was felt that there were many considerations which rendered inexpedient a point- blank refusal: the artificial obstacles which, for many years, had been raised by Great Britain and Russia to railway development, and simply amounted to “ sterilizing ” Persia, could not be indefinitely justified or maintained in the face of altering conditions, such as the discovery of rich mineral deposits in many parts of Persia, the projected extension of the Bagdad Railway to her very frontiers, and the expanding interest of foreign Powers in the shipping of the Persian Gulf; moreover, His Majesty’s Government had no longer any power to oppose railways in the Russian sphere (which occupies more than half the distance from Russia to India); nor could they, under the terms of the Convention, veto possible extensions of Russian concessions into the neutral • sphere, which is not an exclusive preserve of B rBritish enterprise ; if, on investigation, the project of a trunk line should prove practicable and likely to be carried eventually into effect, British association with the undertaking would be mani festly advantageous, enabling us to condition the alignment and secure equal treatment for our trade, whereas an attitude of detachment might promote a Russo-Grerman combination, effecting an acceleration of the project in a manner most detrimental to our interests, and not only to our interests in Persia. These points are merely stated here to explain the course of action which His Majesty’s Govern- ment adopted ; they will presently be examined, with other considerations, in greater detail. In May 1911 His Majesty’s Government in formed the Russian Government that, after con sultation with the Government of India, they were prepared on certain conditions to assent in principle to the project of a Trans- Persian Rail way, and to agree to the initiation of negotiations between the British and Russian groups concerned, making it clear at the same time that they ex pressed no opinion as to the financial aspect of the question, which primarily was the business of the promoters. It may be mentioned parenthetically, and will subsequently be discussed more fully, that nego tiations had meanwhile (since the end of 1910) been proceeding between Russia and Germany respecting railway developments in Asiatic Turkey and Persia; the possibility that these negotiations might take a turn not wholly com patible with British interests had served to emphasise the drawbacks which, as already indi cated, might be involved in a purely negative attitude towards the Trans-Persian project. In March 191*2 the position of His Majesty’s Government was further detined in two letters to the British group of the promoters: these letters made various reservations, but the essential point to note is that the promoters at that stage were represented merely as a Societe c?Etudes — a syndicate formed to survey and investigate— and that freedom of action was reserved to His Majesty’s Government pending consideration of the report of the Soci^t^. All, therefore, that His Majesty’s Government had committed themselves to so far in regard to the project was this : they had agreed in principle to a junction of the Indian and Russian railways ;mm but this theoretical assent, wliich was expressly coupled with certain conditions made in the military and commercial interests of Great Britain and India, was subject to the junction of the two systems being financially practicable, for His Majesty’s Government carefully refrained from holding out any prospect of a guarantee. In the autumn of 1912 the Russian Foreign Minister visited this country and, influenced by certain developments in the progress of the Bagdad Riiiway system, his Excellency Urged that the British and Russian Governments should move a step further in the Trans- * [The Germans, under the “Potsdam” Persian project*: the Russian Government had d -&lt; led that * ™ ™P-^e to link up does not do so within a prescribed term their system with Tehran ; a concession to build U bran ° h thlS line might therefore be Sought by the Society d’Etudes, who at the same time might apply for an option for the wdiole Trans- Persian Railway. His Majesty’s Government agreed to support the Socidtd in this course at Tehran, subject to all reservations already made, and on condition that the option, if obtained, should be “ limited,” that is, that construction should not proceed beyond the Russian sphere until such time as His Majesty’s Government should consider it both politic and feasible. M. SazonofF accepted this position ; and it was unequivocally agreed to by the British group in October 1912, An altered situation has, however, just arisen owing to a declaration of the British group that they are unwilling to send a representative to negotiate at Tehran unless His Majesty’s Govern ment will modify to some extent their attitude of reserve, and agree to support them in securing an option, not merely for a main line, but for branches and maritime facilities also. It is in these circumstances that the question has been referred to the Committee of Imperial Defence ; and, as it is no doubt felt that such a course will facilitate the work of the Committee in making recommendations on the points sub mitted, the occasion has been taken to reopen the whole question, including that of our agreement to the scheme in principle, ab initio. This fresh examination of the question is not unwelcomed by the Foreign Office ; but as there may be points overlooked or insufficiently empha sised, the following notes have been prepared:—If, as seems not unlikely, the Trans-Persian railway in its entirety should prove financially uninviting, it cannot be overlooked that the scheme is not necessarily one indivisible whole, and dr prendre ou h laisser as such. Portions of the line, principally perhaps, within the Russian sphere but not improbably in the neutral sphere as well will be carried out eventually, whether or not there is British participation. If attention be confined for the moment to the Russian sphere : here is an extensive region where British commerce is considerable now and might in the future be increased, but where, under the terms of the Anglo-Russian Convention, British subjects are debarred from railway enterprise, except by consent of the Russian Government. It may possibly be objected that the line from Yezd to lehran is not a natural artery of British trade: but the Trans-Persian project, so far as the Russian sphere is concerned, is not confined to the main line, it comprises branches from Tehran to Khanikin, and from Ispahan to the main line. It is of great importance that the large British trade which enters Persi«a vi4 Bagdad should receive equality of treatment on any line which may be built from Khauikin to Tehran. . . The Board of Trade have represented, in regard to other railways, that it well-nigh impossible to insure against inequality of treatment unless there is an adequate representation of British interests on the board of management. The Russian Government in regard to this railway propose British participation, and the percentage of British representation on the Board is a point in regard to which His Majesty’s Government have made full reservations. The most effective way of precluding manipulation of rates would perhaps be (a) an agreement with Russia to this effect combined with (h) the establishment ot an international “Rates and Traffic Committee” whose function would be to arrange and enforce a table of rates, and there could be machinery for appealing to an impartial expert if decisions were not unanimous. No. 2. It is urged that British and Indian trade depends on railways running inland from the sea-board, and “ that if we have these we may be able to compete in north-west and north Persia with Russian goods imported vki Astara, or German goods imported vik Khanikin.” Such competition in north and north-west Persia does not appear very promising if our railways from the Gulf stop short, as they must do, on reaching the Russian sphere, and if, by declining to participate by in the Trans-Persian project, we reject any share in the management of, or control over the freight charges upon, the lines in the Russian sphere : camels and caravans are not likely to prove efficient means of transport where the trade rival has a railway at his service. No. 3. Again, it has been urged that a Trans-Persian Railway, “ with its long run through the wilderness from Karachi,” will not enable us to compete in north and north-west Persia. The journey through the wilderness does not, it must be conceded, seem likely to contribute to this resultwhat may, however, contribute to successful competition is the possibility that Indian and British goods can be sent by sea to Bunder Abbas, and thence be conveyed, without break of bulk, to the very heart of the Russian sphere. Should there be a branch from the Trans- Persian line to Bushire (though there may be objections to this on other grounds) there would be a choice of ports for the disembarkation of goods destined for through transport to north-west and north Persia. No. 4. Three further points of alleged financial disadvantage in the Trans-Persian Railway scheme have recently been submitted for examination :— (a.) The feared loss to British shipping by diverting the mail subsidy from a British Company to one which will be intemationaL (b.) If Bunder Abbas becomes a great port it will grow at the expense of Bombay and Karachi. (c.) The sections of the railway between Karachi and Bunder Abbas would involve a dead loss to Indian revenues, as part (in British Baluchistan) must necessarily be built by the Government of India. (a.) The mail subsidv argument is familiar from the Bagdad Railway controversy ; it is plausible, but it is doubtful if it will bear closer examination. So long as the sea route remains the quickest the mails will continue to be conveyed by sea. When the Bagdad route is completed and if, as is probable, it is more' expeditious, the public will mark Indian correspondence “ via Vienna,” and the Post Office, as in the case of the Siberian Railway, will adapt itself to the common-sense of the public. The question at issue will not be, then, whether the mail subsidy should be paid to a British Company or an international railway: it will be, should it be paid to a German Railway Company or to an international one partly British ?conAoilVre^lpe^^w* deTeI W g f a pOT * are I,ot tie P ei ‘ d ™t ^lely the built from Buuder AbC to Ka^Yira^ deVeI °P ment ma - v ale&lt; &gt; ^out if a line ie that Hji ,0S8 t0 t IndiaU revenue *from the line to Karachi reata on the assumption they wfoiTy 7 aLent V edT?h- P ' edSe&lt; i t0 a &gt;, nctiu ' the indian and Ka.s.an syrtems politic and feasible’ lla^n^ ? n * nC 'Fi 6 ’ a ' ld the . oon8umi nation is dependent on being both respectfng fiZm aTliab Hlvii^i!* V* ** made ^ HiR Government to build the section\', P • t;fl’ R T d J?r ‘ ^ “ e&lt;! F 0 , W tlie GoTe ™“'8it India can be called upon of ^ linrbetween Bn de, baluchistaii: indeed, having regard to the nnre.nnnerative character discovery of creat imner.l we 1th t?''* ,{ ta '? ebl ’ % ' 8 ''x'j'r improbable, in the absence of a built by the Government of India^n^Britwh^BalnobistMi.** '' OUld a “ y l0 ' 8 ° n tUe Se0ti ° n No. 5. Railin’, 0 P ? mt n ,I ? 1S mere, y for the sake of argument, tliat a Trans-Persian Ra hvav project w likely m whole or in part to be realised, can we gain any strategical or political advantage by participation? h • suategu.ai 01 and li.ik ‘?“ C l:! d r d f ijJ a ; ,th&lt;,riti&lt; ? thMt if we can determine the alignment 1 leak of gauge, a d if we can lay down other conditions, then, even if we are not in a position to render wholly innocuous, we shall yet be able to blunt, what in ^me quote s is considered a potential weapon of offence. ’ fc quarttis is r n n l!!’ f ierefore ’. P ar | lcl P at i 0 ii will secure this advantage, it is desirable strategically, unless it can be shown to involve greater disadvantages in other directions. ° Yezd • ‘b^t 8 Tn b «r d J aWbaCk u ° ur P artic ; i P atiou ina 7 hasten the advent of the line as far as 5oint’ if W ' P a !' tlcl P^e or not, the Trans-Persian line is ultimatelv going up to t ie lunits of the Russian sphere, and when once the line is built so far it will be a natural development if Russian trade expands into the neutral spLre Such expausT.n splm^atnl'^sthT 1100 ’ 1 n 7 i 1,0 iollowod b - v a prolongation of the Russian line into the neutral election J tH d b ° U ° Se ' Se °PP 08ed t0 thc Convention of 1907 we could raise no By parhcipation now we might stipulate that no such extension of the Trans-Persian line into the neutral sphere should be m the direction of the alleged danger-point, Kerman. We should , h F’'‘ n ! 1 '. e ' v t '' cu , t of P{uss,a becoming hostile, have ample warning before an extension ivtenZ F 1 bft /“ d 1-. lf ’ on ? he hand, we abstain from parHcipation, a Russian nfvaM Pnm 7 ' 0 meet ,be deVe, 0 P' ,eDto “ f tade ' and 8ha11 ha - I urnill ff to the political side what aro the advantages to us of participation ? eraily ®P eakln ^ . may be said that co-operation with Russia is, when practicable w f 18 a p atural ih « Anglo-Russian Couventioli, and ithas much to' thp V j ^ ^t meiely m 1 ersia where it affords a chance for a comprehensive settlement of - e ^hole railway question, but also m the larger sphere of European politics. M. Sazonoff, f a mfc;niC) iaudum dated the L &lt; th beptember, 1912, has expressed the view that, if the request for an option were made to the Persian Government by the French and Russian groups alone such a procedure ‘ produira.it une impression ties facheuse, et serait, sans doute, utilisee comme milice dun dissentiment profond entre la Grande-Bretagne et la Russie.” What, on the other hand, may be the result of refusing co-operation ? It may be to bring- about a Russo-German combination, first commercial and then political, in the ’ Middle East! .’h a ^p^surnmation would be far reaching in its consequences, and could not fail to evoke serious nugiyingg; and it would, in the event of trouble between England and Germany to say and^Russia ^ eft6Ct8 ^ Lu^0pe, ex P 0fle ludia to th e risk of a combined attack by Germany • * T 7°. objections suggest themselves: it may be urged that German and Russian inteiests m the ..uddm East are so divergent that a reconciliation is virtually impracticable, and it may be urged that the existence of a Trans-Persian Railway would be no safeguard against such a combination should it become a fact. &amp; &amp; 1 he answer to the first objection is that the Potsdam agreement has shown Russian and German interests m the Middle East not to be irreconcilable. The substance of agreement was (a) Russia undertook not to oppose the Bagdad Railway; (/j) Russia undertook to link Tehran with the Bagdad Railway at Khanikin, and Germany secured the concession from Tehran to Khanikm in the event of construction by Russia not commencing within a prescribed term ■ (c) Germany recognised Russia’s special interests in North Persia. ' ’ It is easy to see how this agreement might develop if Great Britain were to meet Russian advances tor railway co-operation by a nun pessumus attitude. Russia might seek to divert German activity from the Khanikin-Tehran concession to the neutral sphere, where Russian intei ests are less important, and the change would be effected at British expense. As to the existence of a i rans-Persian Railway being no safeguard against a Russo-German combination, the argument advanced should rather be that if Great Britain and Russia, by a well-considered scheme of co-operation, have earmarked desirable concessions, forming connecting links in a possible Trans-Persian line, then there is less scope for a Russo-German combination. [ 2763 n —14] ~ ™No. 6. Finally, is the Trans-Persian Railway inevitable ? It has recently been argued with some force that it is not: and if by a Trans-Persian Railway is understood the junction of the Indian and Russian railways then, except perhaps as regards the distant tuture, the conclusion seems correct. But it does not necessarily follow that many of the lines which might ultimately form connecting links in a trunk railway are not inevitable, and perhaps this distinction has not been sufficiently brought out. It is presumed that a railway is only inevitable if it is certain that it will pay, or if it is necessary to the parties concerned for commercial or political reasons. It these tests be adopted, a fair case can be made out to show that the greater part ot the Trans-Persian project is inevitable. It probably is so from the Russian frontier at Astara to the shores of the Persian Gulf and to the limit of the British sphere at Bunder Abbas. The parties concerned are India. Persia, Russia, and Germany. The advantages to Indian and British trade of securing railway access to north-west and north Persia have been touched upon already. The British Resident in the Persian Gulf has expressed the belief that both Indian and British trade would benefit by the projected railway, and find new openings. As regards Persia, Sir P. Cox, in the light of local experience, has stated “it cannot but be supposed that the general effect of the railway would be to improve the administration, develop the country, and increase the capacity of the Persian market.” It has, on the other hand, been argued that Persia, while likely to benefit greatly by British railways from the Gulf, has nothing to gain by the extension of the Russian line e;ist of Yezd: but surely this estimate makes insufficient allowance for the administrative advantage of connecting the Central Government at Tehran with the outlying provinces by direct communication. As regards Russia, it can hardly be denied that she would derive benefit from commercial access to the shores of the Persian Gulf. As regards Germany, it would seem that a large portion of her trade is likely to come by sea, and to pass up inland from the Gulf. It is urged, however, that it a Trans-Persian line is inevitable it will not be the Russian project, but a German extension from Khanikin to \ ezd, which is likely to rain the Russian scheme, on the ground that the Germans can and will effect a short circuit. This criticism appears to refer to a through traffic from Europe to India: it is not quite clear why it is held to be shorter via the German than via the Russian route, nor why the Germans can be so assured as to obtaining the extension to Yezd, but even if they do obtain it there is no palpable reason for concluding that a Russian line from Tehran to Yezd, and a possible extension of that Russian line to the Persian Gulf, should be ruined by a German line coming trom a totally different direction, Khanikin. The upshot seems to be that, even if His Majesty’s Government adopt an attitude of detach ment, a great portion of a Trans-Persian project seems so likely to be carried out as almost to justify the epithet of “inevitable.” It remains to consider what the attitude of His Majesty's Government should be : they have agreed to support the Societe at Tehran in seeking for a “ limited ” option for a railway across Persia : that is, an option which, outside the Russian sphere, is not to be exercised until His Majesty's Government consider it politic and feasible. It seems advisable that the attitude of His Majesty’s Government should be comprehensively defined, for purposes of record, in a communication to the Russian Ambassador; this communication should contain, as an enclosure, a copy of the proposed reply (vide infra) to Sir W. Garstin; it should in particular recall that one of the reservations made by his Majesty’s Government from the first was that there should be absolute equality of treatment over the whole system, and it should suggest that, before an application for an option is ?nade at Tehran, the British and Russian Governments should formally signify to — ^—— — —* [It will obviously be more difficult to get the principle accepted if we wait till the option is secured; and, as we know from previous correspondence that the Moscow merchants are opposed to equality of treat ment, we had better get the principle formally accepted before the Russian Government are faced with a formidable agitation in favour of differential treatment.] each other the acceptance of the principle ot such equality, as unless it is so admitted (which to us the Russian Government have not yet expressly done), there will be much adverse comment in this country. As the Russian Government have already admitted the principle to Germany in the “Potsdam” agreement about the Khanikin-Tehran project, they could not reasonably refuse to do so to us. The reply to the letters dated the 9th and 20th December from Sir W. Garstin might, it is submitted, be on the following lines :— In the first place, answers should be given to the four specific questions, (a), (6), (c) and (d), asked in the former letter. (See Appendix No. 1.) [2763 n—14] (a.) That His Majesty’s Government have expressed themselves as prepared, on certain conditions, to assent in principle to the project of of a Trans-Persian Railway. That those con ditions are, inter alia, that the line shall not be prolonged beyond the Russian sphere until, and in such measures as, His Majesty’s Govern ment shall consider it both politic and feasible; that the main line from Yezd must enter the British sphere at or near Bunder Abbas and must not be aligned via Kerman; that there must be a break of gauge at Bunder Abbas if the line passes east of that point; that His Majesty’ Government undertake no financial guarantee in regard to the project; that there shall be fair and adequate representation of British interests on the board of management, and a proper percentage of construction orders secured to British contractors; that absolute equality of treatment in all respects shall be guaranteed to British and British-Indian trade passing over the whole system; and that certain branches, to which further reference will be made, shall be secured to British concessionnaires in the neutral and British spheres. (h.) That the answer is in the affirmative, though His Majesty’s Government trust that such progress may be made in regard to a well- considered scheme in the south as will render possible an early and if possible simultaneous start in con st i*uction there. (c.y That His Majesty’s Government are com mitted : that the concessions in question are the Blinder Abbas-Kerman one in the British sphere D8 (which would have to be purely British-controlled), and certain lines (other than the one projected from Mohammerah to Khorremmabad) which, m view of the predominance of British trade, should be preponderatingly British though not devoid of a substantial international participation both in construction and management. (d.) That His Majesty’s Government would be prepared to recommend to the parties interested in the projects (other than the Mohammerah- Khorremmabad line) in the neutral sphere that it would be subservient to British interests il they would effect an amalgamation with the British group of the Soci^ d’Etudes, who, in consultation with His Majesty’s Government, might then arrange the degree and nature of the foreign participation in question. Beferring then to Sir W. Garstin’s letter of the 20th December, it might be intimated :— 1. That His Majesty’s Government would agree to enclosure (A) (see appendix No. 2) on condition that the words “ d’As tar a k Guattar are omitted (as there is no need to specify this to the Persian Government pending the survey), and on condition that the Societd definitely accepts the position that the question of maritime facilities to be granted in Southern Persia, and of the control of such port or ports, must be the subject of agreement between the British and Persian Governments. 2. That His Majesty’s Government would agree to enclosure (B) (see appendix No. 2), subject to the insertion of an additional clause to the effect that a permanent “ Bates and 1 raffic Committee shall be instituted to enforce, by whatever means may be most effective, absolute equality or treatment over the entire Trans-Persian system, that British interests shall be adequately repre sented on this Committee, and that, in the event of disagreement, there shall be. a right of appeal to an impartial railway expert. A. P. Foreign Office, January 13, 1913.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000129_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/18/C131</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000129</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/18/C131</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Memorandum by Mr. Parker respecting Railway Construction in Persia'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1913/1913</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-09-29T21:11:41</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">fre</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (5 folios)</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence commences at f 28, and terminates at f 32, as it is part of a larger physical volume; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the bottom right corner of the recto side of each folio. Pagination: the file also contains an original printed pagination sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The memorandum considers whether British participation in the proposed Trans-Persian Railway would be in Britain's interests. To this end it considers possible advantages/disadvantages to British trade, finance, and her strategic/political interests.The appendix (folio 32) contains an extract from a letter from Sir William Edmund Garstin dated 9 December 1912. It also contains two enclosures (in French) from a letter — also from Garstin — dated 20 December 1912.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><geographic>Persia</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Railways</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000129#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>