<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100050681569.0x000001_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-12-10T11:34:15.941Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100050681569.0x000001_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>Or 8296</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100050681569.0x000001</url><physicalLocation>British Library: Oriental Manuscripts</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>Or 8296</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Taḥṣīl al-ṣiḥḥah bi-al-asbāb al-sittah تحصيل الصحة بالأسباب الستة  Tiflīsī, Ḥubaysh ibn Ibrāhīm تفليسي، حبيش بن إبراهيم</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1200/1399</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-11-20T22:03:06</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>Codex; ff. i+179+i</extent><extent>Material: Western laid paperDimensions: 182 x 133 mm leaf [130 x 85 mm written]Foliation: Eastern Arabic foliation in black ink, British Museum foliation in pencilRuling:
                           Misṭarah; 21 lines per page; vertical spacing 16 lines per 10 cmScript:
                           NaskhInk: Black ink, with rubricated headings and overlinings in redDecoration: NoneBinding: British Museum bindingCondition: Defective at beginning and end; ff. 1-18 mutilated and repaired in lower edge corner without loss of text; ff. 135-179 mutilated and repaired in upper edge corner without loss of text; stains and foxing; large dark stain on ff. 170-176Marginalia: Few by more than one handSeals: f. 175r</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Treatise on hygiene by means of the six non-natural causes of health and disease by Abū al-Faḍl Ḥubaysh ibn Ibrāhīm ibn Muḥammad al-Tiflīsī (أبو الفضل حبيش بن إبراهيم بن محمد التفليسي, fl. ca 1200).The manuscript is defective at beginning and end.Begins (f. 1r, lines 1-4, defective at beginning):فالصبيان لما كانت رطوباتهم كثيرة لأجل النشو لم يجر أن (؟) يفصدون ولايسهلون إلى أن يلغوا إلى السنة السابعة والرابعة عشر لئلا يمتنعنشوهم ويبطئ وهم فإن افتقروا إلى إخراج الدم حجموا لأن حرارتهم الغريزيةمنكسرة السورة لأجل كثرة الرطب ...Ends (f. 179v, lines 19-21, defective at end):... وإن كانت بعيدة فلا تعالجها بالحديد بلبالأدوية ولا تعجل بعلاج الحديد من قبل النضح لأجل شركة هذا العضو باالأعضاء الرئيسية فإذا خرجت المدة فقطر في الرحم دهن ورد ولبن</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="personal"><namePart>Ḥubaysh ibn Ibrāhīm Tiflīsī</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Medicine--Early works to 1800</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100050681569.0x000001#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>