<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000555.0x00027d_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-20T06:57:20.928Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">INDEXED » In any further communication on this subject, please quote n »'£ ■ h’iOl^boh'o and address —not to any person by name, but to— * The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. 1. &gt; , S'* ' (D fl/- h&amp;pjp THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Adairs presents his compliments to '-dLx 4 jIa^(X)La-J xexdt-GLS^ A v a nd, by direction of the Secretary ot State, transmits herewith cop f of the/' uhdeppfytioned |paper. l c Foreign Office, ^ • } 1940 . IJ Reference to previo Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. 1-tcLdcK XO &lt;4| ^C.- Subject. cLsis&gt;tXjo'pA^4^Jr CxJ? . ENCL0$tme IN AIR MAIL LETTER No; 8 2 0 FEB 1940 w PROM SECRETARY, POLITICAL DEPT. INDIA OFFICE i* ENCLOSURE IN WEEKLY LETTER NO. -8 2 2 FEB ;J40 &lt;5* FROM SECRETARY, POLITIOAL AND SECRET DEPT. INDIA OFFICE Similar letter sent to RECp. POL. OEPt. 12FEB1940 6 INDIA OFFICE 20577899 mcmnhor £9th* 9 193®. M? t«ord, I haw the honour to tranaait to you Mr*®with a oopy of m Interasfclng report which. I hmm rmeiv&amp;d tram Mr* a« Qmr$» who i» no# ^tatlon^a &amp;t iiiyacLh ana haa had a recent opi-wt.inity of studying fcy pereoml inspection the m'b&amp;ot or* the report* vln* the egrioultural 4 evolox»ient of o. water mif-pXy at r.fcar^* noai* Riyadh* uamtirm® known m ^tha hott«»- pooXe of KharJ '• It will 'bo «otm that Mle Majesty hlng Abdul .b*is tnkes a great j^rsoml interest in this mhoim, which* if miooes^ful* will omfmr mrmxymt benefits upon a large area in the neighbourhood of tho pools* 2 . An Iraqi engineer who^a vmm was given as Ur* Ahaed Mueeh hao lately been In Jodda with the object of taking del ivory of i*mm agricultural machinery for the imping operations? he left here a tan onyo ago aaoaapeniod by the Iraqi Gbnrgd d’Affaires in order to return to KharJ raid nosiet in the engineering ox&gt;e rations* &lt;/rom hovel t a report ho.s boon rocelved that eight hundred 'boge of grain tar© boon imported for sowing* mit little enthusiasm wae thought to exist for the projmt &amp;mm th© local po.iJUiy.tion because they thought that any profits wouXa bo a;&gt;i« k oprMtod by the ' Ing in tones, and thnt In any cue© previous afctes^ti* at agriculture at KharJ bad failed* a* frm Iraq however more optimism baa ‘tern reported* and the work of the A*a,;i ehgin^re has* it in acid* attracted isearly one 'hundred and fifty fomiliee of the holt '■■Ww tribe* / « dh# '..ight nmxmrable the Vimmnt loilfajt* K. 0 * fV 1940; J a &amp;«etiosi of the AX &lt;iiyyad of uivnmlyeh, followea by fifty farslliom of tho tribo from the JmgfamF&amp;h &gt; „adha# #rofs an /.Ulrica© tr«n^^rt ©i^lneer who had reeontXy vial ted I l^ard that tli4i surf a a© of the water in the principal w«ila wa© aoma throe laindrmi asid f ifty foot below ground level* the depth of water bf*tng about an ©&lt;g»&amp;l distancei ho added that in opite of the oonetant griping m% of large oi water the level of water r^alned practically mohanged* 4* 1 am forwarding copied of thia doep^toh to Hie Ma40wty v 8 i^haasador at Bagdad (51id/d?4A4) * to the Honour- able the olitleal Keeident in the Bereian Half (3149 574.H-4) ami to the rolitieal /'gent at Koweit (51dO/d74/'k4)* I have the honour to bo* with the hi;-heat rwapeet, rly hwd, 'four hox &gt; ds-hip , c moat obadlent* humble servant*mlomtre to Mr. n . a# TmtV* temimtoh i*ro fmmfow &lt; 9%h* to ^ 1 *. Mrott# iler^ are «caa« notea on the visit to HHAEJ which mw he of Interest. fcoout 3 hours* It passes cut of Riyadh in an easterly on the ©&amp; 0 $ and on tiio west aM goin^; on down the sandy bottom of the '-nidi HAHXFA. '&amp;*» iiim rati oajiped at the old fort built by hi a ^mu-lfathex* F«iisal f where is almost corneleted a 'inch bigger new fort, with 11 vijig quarters looking out above t'm walls* Mo ,e&amp;oh ^Irson we paissed through tlm wallod village of ilL.il IYa. **r&lt;m -’’irsan, at the foot of low hills* one looks out over the alsaoafc &amp; ntlmious lines of date palm gardens wMo t are hilaimlya and ‘/auw«a. 3n the foreground ami to the southwards is the new estate* 1 should gue?*s that m far about ea&lt;X&gt; acres hmo ¥een newly developed* Everywhere about in the area • you will notice from the ms# the confluence Of the tributaries imd the ^adl f!ani0i here - there is water tiadergmmd but ^hAt has poiialble the new iievelofsaent are the six great springs near m# 4* (behind which are ruins, perhaps the ;fite of the ancient capital of the kings of Ytraasm)# springs are in;revive* .'heir pools are some thirty yards across t*nd very deep. Th© water la warn in winter' 7 and *cko 1 in ®umraer , * &gt; ana slightly uspleasant to taste, - sulpharcuo^ cn the biggest pool «w the waters of wliioh IM1 the apy^armoe ef. ; boiling - two ,HLd2hiXMf 5® .{..•■* pumiditg engines with i‘f f intake SMI are Installed* HM J ^BAL there are two f, ■ vgf rorai' from It one ~ 'i ■and amdy dirsstioa - towards about pt. i:49 on the Million sheet (0*as of 19 ^} then turns southwards towards AfL-vY, leaving IIITH / engines/ thmmihM engine8 one of 6 ami ana of is H.* ., intalw i?ipe 3'. Cn the next biggest pool the ifesa al time are yet no engines and th&amp;m -mr® wild duck au^ong th« wnt#i» is cmducttfd by cerfKmt lined or «tonc miilt oomiuit® on to the fluXdn* Vlm&amp;mnm well built stone Hansom* i,e. pXmm wtmi'Q are alulcea to .^rmit t^ie running off of the water to the fields on either side at Intervals. tewing first began a mnth ago. The first ^ork was mcior* tansii mo out 4 tuoathe ago* 1 1 reoslves the personal attention of ..Mullah ^ulairam {Minister of Flnajawie), who is there at the morasnt« There are »o®e aosen Irakis - working farmra end i^chan* los, .ind if it is they who wrote the mport which was ublished it i&amp; ?3o woMcr it ms not very technical or really descriptive, fhey aro not Iraqi Oovernmnt servants hut working r^n , ami doing fery well 1 should think* fhoy see® irnmnmltf interested end keen* fh© water level do© reaped about a mot re to start with but biwaye recovers its level s few bsurs aftsr one otigiti© is turned off. (llie 'aborigines insist that the level rises at the 1st* ami idth. of the lump month! oaullah .ailaimm could not confirm but the King does so. It seems imlikely but ^pimrmtly in true). The tractors known in arable a* 'T)]: - (rather con- .fusing at first when they began spsaklng of the umcnrnt of petrol th© dlrestar* on the estate drsnic!} - sr© avT^fX.,wU&lt; .useriasn as ws tlis am:dsrs and sterilisers. The Im^ries were Osman* uropa being grown or sxpsrimentsd with include wheat, barley, sugar-beet and all the vegetables grown in Iraq. Two agricultural experts from California University ere on there way out, having been arranged for by the oil company, c.a. d.o.c. he whole tiling i» rathec im-reseive* The very mtuhvr lim-i of the dividing banks between the fields stretching* away in th di atanoe — the activity - Up tractors ©hugging their way IPPPP the eeeip* The m&amp;k at mr- springs and old wells* planted alrr-ady with( 2 &gt; 3 *1 “O rv i ( 1 THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY of HI ^BRITj.iftNIC MAJESTY’S GO VERNMENT EASTERN (Arabia). CONFIDENTIAL. R1 9 F5 vJ s cLU 938 !■ June 8 , 1938. Section 2. [E 3334/1698/25] Copy No. iSir i?. Bullard to Viscount Halifax.—(Received June 8 .) (No. 100.) My Lord, * Jedda, May 17, 1938. IN my despatch No. 41. dated the 7th March. I reported the promulgation of a Saudi regulation governing the residence of foreigners in this country. I now have the honour to report the settlement of various small difficulties which arose out of the application of the regulation. 2. The complaints which I mentioned in a l ater despatch, No. 59 , dated the 30th March^have been met by a decision, which was published m the Vmm-al- Qura oi the 13 th May, to the 'effect that foreign students who can show by documentary evidence that they are following courses in religious instruction will be exempted .from payment of the fee, though in other respects they will have to comply with the provisions of the regulation. This welcome concession is stated in the newspaper notice to have been decided upon in response to requests made to the King by many such students. It may be true that some direct appeals were made to the King, but my Netherlands colleague made strong representations on the subject, in writing. My own intervention was confined to the private talk with Sheikh Yusuf Yasin, which I have already reported. 3 . My reading of article 13 of the regulation (see paragraph 4 ot my despatch of the 7th March) was correct : the authorities had intended to keep the national passports of foreigners and only to return them when the owners wished to leave the country. As soon as it became clear that this was the intention, I sent a private letter to the Amir Faisal suggesting that the retention of British passports was perhaps due to misapprehension of the regulation by the authorities concerned, and explaining that a British passport is considered to be the property of the Government by whom it is issued, and that the United Kingdom and other countries register aliens without finding it necessary to retain their passports. After a considerable interval His Highness replied that the passports had been kept only because the preliminary formalities took a long time, and promising that orders would be issued for the passports to be returned to their owners. this explanation has now appeared as an official notice in the Umm-al-Qura, which states that the passports will be returned when the residence permits are issued. This satisfactory result is not attributable entirely to the private representations from this Legation. At least one other Legation (that of the Netherlands) protested officially, though I hear that both the French and the Italian Ministers stated that they proposed to take no action. ' . „ 4 About a month ago the Governor of Jedda sent me a list ot ntteen persons, who, he said, were undesirable Indians, were entirely without papers and had no position and no work. He alleged that under the lesidence legulation thev could not remain in Saudi Arabia, and asked that His Majesty’s Legation should issue emergency passes to them and repatriate them. There is no provision in the regulation that covers such cases, though article 6 provides for the withdrawal of a permit from an undesirable, and article 27 allows the deportation of a person who fails to apply for a residence permit within the prescribed period, or who makes false statements or produces false documents; but m any case there were other grounds for refusing to comply with the Governor’s request. I reminded him that His Majesty’s Legation arrange every year for the repatriation of Indian pilgrims who are destitute, and said that, if any of the fifteen peisqns in question fell within that category, I was prepared to consider their repatriation if they applied to the Legation; but I said that I could not accept responsibility for the repatriation of undesirables, which I considered to be the business of the Saudi authorities. The Governor accepted this point of view without demur, and it is possible that the alleged Indians, who. I understand, are none of them recent pilgrims and are all without visible means of subsistence, have been sent [330 h—2]SI© ( A\ THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY’S GOVERNMENT P. s r / 1 Zj , EASTERN (Arabia). ' * w / 77 | April 25, 1938. CONFIDENTIAL. 1 L ^ ;\ir j Section 3. [E 2340/1698/25] Copy No. 118 Sir R. Bullard to Viscount Halifaw.—{Received April 25.) (No. 59.) My Lord, Jedda, March I HAVE the honour to inform you that the regulation on the residence of foreigners in Saudi Arabia, of which I transmitted a translation in my despatch No. 21 dated the 7th March, has aroused great indignation among the communities of foreign Moslems resident in this country. As Ibn Saud frequently asks the advice of His Majesty’s Government and begs for frankness in our dealings with him, I felt it right to mention this subject to Sheikh Yusuf Yasin, in the course of a recent interview. 2 . I began by repudiating any desire to interfere in the internal affairs of Saudi Arabia, and explaining that I was speaking personally. The Legation, I said, had invited British subjects to comply with the provisions of the regulations, and whenever any objection had been raised, as by certain British Moslems in Mecca, we had explained that the registration of aliens was compulsory in most countries, and that it was not out of the way to charge a fee for the work involved. Nevertheless, it could not be denied that many foreign Moslems objected to the regulations on religious grounds, as drawing a distinction between one Moslem and another, and implying that certain Moslems described as aliens had not the right to be in their Holy Land. It was not for me to comment on such claims, but only to inform the Saudi Government, as a friend and a well-wisher, that the regulation had aroused great hostility, and that it was to be expected that persons hostile to the Saudi Government might profit by the occasion for propaganda purposes abroad. 3. Sheikh Yusuf Yasin thanked me for these remarks. The Government were aware of the hostility which the regulation had aroused. The object of the regulation was merely to enable some check to be placed upon the residence of foreigners who continued to reside in Saudi Arabia with no ostensible purpose and whose activities might be undesirable. Instructions were being issued to the police to be very lenient in the matter of fees and to exempt any persons who were really poor, and it might be that after the experience of a year or two the fee could be reduced. I reminded Sheikh Yusuf that he had told me not long before that if the oil wells in Hasa yielded a good revenue the King’s first object would be to reduce the charges levied on pilgrims, and I suggested that the Saudi Government might wish to examine the charge for residence permits from the same point of view. The proposed charge of 10 riyals (about 165 . 8 d.) for a residence permit had, I admitted, aroused criticism, but the Legation had met such criticisms, as it met those frequently levied against the Saudi charges levied on pilgrims, by the explanation that Saudi Arabia had little agriculture and no industries, that the Saudi Government had to perform many services for pilgrims, and, in particular, to maintain law and order (which it did admirably), and that it was natural that charges should be levied in return for these services. 4. It is possible, then, that the Saudi Government will endeavour, by leniency in the levy of fees, to make the regulation less unpalatable to the many thousands of foreign Moslems who live in the Hejaz, principally in Mecca. In my earlier despatch I said it was difficult to believe that any serious attempt would be made to apply the regulation to the penniless African pilgrims who remain on from year to year, and there are other communities whose members could not pay so heavy a fee as 10 riyals without great hardship. My Netherlands colleague tells me that there are hundreds of Javanese students in Mecca who live thirty or forty in one house and cannot afford to spend more than 3 or 4 riyals (from 55 to 65 . 8 d.) a month on food. [280 bb—3] ^1$. 12 5. I took the opportunity to point out to Sheikh Yusuf Yasin the obscurity of the second article in the regulation, which defines permanent residence as a stay of more than one year £&lt; in addition to the period allowed in the passport.” Sheikh Yusuf Yasin said that he believed the reference was to the period of validity of any Saudi visa the passport might bear, but nearly all the foreigners in this country are pilgrims who have travelled on pilgrim passes, which do not require a Saudi visa. However, that is an obscurity which can be amended easily. 6 . Copies of this despatch are being sent to the Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Department at New Delhi, his Excellency the Governor of the Straits Settlements at Singapore, and his Excellency the Governor of Nigeria at Lagos. I have, &amp;c. E. W. BULLARD.© ) Wo. 181. (E ES98/1698/25) FOREIGN OFFICE, S.W.l. 11th May, 1938. Sir, I have received your despatch No.41 of the T'th March (491/269/4) in regard to a recently enacted Saudi regulation governing the residence of foreigners in Saudi Arabia, 2, I approve your action as reported in paragraph 2, in bringing the regulation to the notice of the British community and in inviting them to comply with its provisions. 3, In reply to the enquiry contained in paragraph 3 of your despatch I have to inform you that the position of the official staff of Diplomatic missions in this country in regard to registration is as follows; 4, It is the practice in this country to grant exemption from the police registration provisions of the Aliens’ Order of 1920 to:- (l) Accredited Heads of foreign Diplomatic Missions, their familiea, and the members of their domestic staffs, residing with them; (ii) Members of the official (diplomatic or clerical) staffs directly employed by Heads of Missions and under their orders in their diplomatic/ Sir Reader Bullard, K.C.M.G., G.I.E., etc., etc., etc.. / Jedda) diplomatic capacity and the members of the families of such officials; (iii) All foreign consular officers whose appointments have been notified to the Secretary of State through the diplomatic channel by the foreign government concerned and have been recognised either by the grant of The King’s exequatur or by His Majesty’s Government formally; and subordinate consular officials de carriers provided that such officials are certified by the Head of the Mission as belonging to the salaried consular service of the foreign government concerned, that is to say, appointed by that Government and not by the Head of the Consulate in which they are employed. I am, with great truth and regard. Sir, Your obedient Servant, (For the Secretary of State) \ w • *-» &gt;• \/ , 'T Eh .A 1^ 1 *' 1 ' ■■ I iwsm—— W4 'Osua al of April l*t of' a • Ion oonoernla^ %hm wiiolesaX# ana retail trad# In medicines, dru t $, medical re.-aretlone ana herbs*'* the regulation, which must have been ea lea straight fram the statute-book of some highly organised state, is far too elaborate to be s piled ro erly In this country, ana I should hardly have; thought it worth reporting but for one article which reads da follows? Article SI* fhe sale of ro rletery medical pr« 4 .aretiene imicrted from abroad is prohibited, unless previous era!salon for the sale has been obtained, and the rublie health department shall not authorise the sale without first taking s, ecimens and ascertaining the eom*osltion# the effective medical substances which they contain, and the method of use. i* auoii British proprietary medical articles a® to be found In this country must oawe e very small sale, but as even that small sale may be held u , if only for a time, by the remulgstisn of this regulation, I have thought the matter worth re sorting* 5* a copy of this des. etch i© being sent to the Department of Overseas frado (Ho* 11* ( Voo/teVQ/k )• 1 have, etc*, (Sgd) H*f* Bullard. the might honourable the Viscount iislifajt, R*a*, SC# , OsO * , g;C *tb iunication on this ^abject, ]h«ase quote---j»^~ «#■' —«t iLu/^e/x. | p. 2 »y person by name, bu^to— | •y of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.VV. : | ,l | INDIA DIRECT NT* G CONFIDENTIAL In any further communication^on this ^{ibject, ])&gt;ease q^ot© No and address —not to any “The Under-Secretary C. O : , THE Under-Secretary of; State_ tor . Foreign Affairs presents his % compliments to direction transmits herewith cop and, by direction the Secretary of State, of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, , 193 /. Reference to previous correspondence : a L^l Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. IZcH ifrTHIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY’S GOVERNMENT N o EASTERN (Arabia). CONFIDENTIAL. [E 1698/1698/25] March 28, 1938. Section 3. Copy No. Sir R. Bullard to Viscount Halifax.—(Received March 28.) (No. 41.) Jedda, March 7, 1938. 1 HAVE the honour to transmit herewith a translation of a Saudi regulation governing the residence of foreigners in this country. Every foreigner over 18 years of age who wishes to reside in Saudi Arabia for a period of more than one year in addition to “ the period allowed in the passport” must take out a Residence Permit and pay certain fees. Provision is made in article 6 for the withdrawal of such permits from certain classes of persons and their deportation. Large numbers of foreign Moslems, particularly from Malaya and the Dutch East Indies, will come under this regulation, which may well prove a little complicated to apply, the Saudi police and other officials being what they are, amd it is difficult to believe that any serious attempt will be made to apply it to the penniless African pilgrims who stay on from year to year. The regulation may even be vitiated by article 2 , which gives a definition of permanent residence based on the hypothesis that the national passport “ allows ” the holder to reside for a given period in Saudi Arabia. However, the regulation is being brought to the notice of the British community, who are being invited to comply with^its provisions. J 3. I should be glad to be informed, with reference to article 12 of the regulation, whether the official staff of diplomatic missions in Great Britain are obliged to register as aliens or to comply with any similar regulation 4. The wording of article 13 suggests that when the Saudi authorities issue a residence permit to a foreigner they keep his national passport The Legation will resist any attempt by the Saudi police authorities to keep the passports of British subjects. r 5. I am sending copies of this despatch and of its enclosure to the Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Department New Dehli • his Excellency the Governor of the Straits Settlements, Singapore- and hk Excellency the Governor of Nigeria, Lagos. 1 I have, &amp;c. R, W. BULLARD. Enclosure. From the Mecca Umm-al-Qura No. 686 of the Dhu’l Qa’ada, 27, 1356 (January 28, 1938). Residence Regulation. (Translation.) A DECREE has been issued ratifying this regulation and bringing it into Article 1. Any foreigner of more than 18 years of age who desires to reside permanently m the territory of the Saudi Arabian Kingdom must anplv to the pohce authorises with his passport together with an application form as indicated m article 4 . , Art - . 2 - .T emlan ? n ‘ ^idence means a stay of more than one year in addition to the period allowed m the passport. ■ [255 ee—8]2 Art. 3 . The Police Department shall issue to any applicant for permission to reside (in Saudi Arabia) a book entitled “Residence Permit” containing ail the particulars given in the passport of the applicant, together with nis photograph stamped by the police department, and all the particulars given m the form referred to in article 4 . Art. 4. The application form must be accompanied by two photographs aiid contain the following particulars :— (a) The object of residence. (b) The period of residence. (c) The number, date and place of issue of the passport. (d) The nationality and origin (? race). (e) The town of intended residence. (/) The quarter in which (the applicant) desires to live. (g) The names of the members of the applicant’s family mentioned in his passport and particulars concerning them. Art. 5. The Police Department shall keep a record of all the particulars giwen in the residence permit in a register entitled “ Residence Register,” and afnx beside these particulars the photograph of the applicant with his signature or thumb print thereon. Ait. 6 . The proper authorities may withdraw the residence permit from the (classes of) persons referred to in the following paragraphs :— ? eisons w ho commit acts tending to a breach of the peace. {b) Persons whose continued residence the Governments thinks undesirable. •V H P° lice authorities shall warn persons from whom residence permits have been withdrawn to leave the country within fifteen days subject to their being under po ice supervision during the period (of delay) granted to them. Directors of police m the provinces sLll not warn any persoi to leave yuthout asking for permission from the Administrative Governors who on their part shall obtain instructions on the subject from the Vicerov’s Office Thp headquarters of the Police Department sha^l be notified of hTsTr [nfo maGon and purposes of record. uuounation Art. 8 . In case of force majeure the period of (delay granted to) the ner&lt;™ from whom the residence permit has been withdrawn may be extended hevn 3 fifteen days by order of the Viceroy’s Office in the canitaf and in itfl. - d by an order of the Administrative Governor provided that it i« K P^ ovince s order from the Viceroy’s Office. provided that it is based on an A.rt. 9. The period of validity of the residence mpvrriii ic i • i SiribAf 1 ° n eXPlry by means 0f - on paySX mentioned 1 !!, artide 4 dUudgmente pronounced^ courts*ag^nsUhe whose names are shown in the residence register. a &amp; amst the persons Art. 11 . The Police Department shall give a residence nermii f who may have lost his permit and shall endorse it thus P t to an y° ne v • ' ^ ive u n in P la Cf of permit No. . , dated which has been lost. , f 5° m th , e P ersoa concerned half the original fee Ait. 12 . Diplomatic and consular representatives and thpir- -p -r exempt from the obligation to apply for residence permits d The nfif ^ 'f « ar ? diplomatic missions shall be treated on a reciprocal bas!T ’ ffiClal aff ° f i-rA 13 ' ,° n the expiry of the period allowed to the applicant h„ d. , , notify the police authorities accordingly and forward tAi a? h * hould permit, and they shall hand him his pasfport if he prof oses to We h6 residl t nce another residence permit if he applies for one gudhi? 1 i ? a ’ . or ^ rant after the legal formalities havebfenfeffeted ^PP^ation is sanctioned Art. 14. The fee for the form referred to in article 4 q • The fee for the residence permit retred to PlaStreS - m article 3 is Art. 15. The fee 10 Saudi riyals. d afys, o'v~-“ sr 8 fifaas t sr• u»Art - An y person who intentionally changes his name and gets a permit an^ a ^eim made out in a false name or holds a forged or falsified permit or h-rrn 1 ’ whether the forgery has been done by his own hand or indirectly, shall be pliable to a hue of from £1 to £5 gold or to imprisonment (for a term) of not less tnan one week or more than one month. 1 18 ' • P erson w h° connives with another person who intentionally conceals his identity, and bears witness on that person’s behalf to an untrue statement, or knowingly guarantees anyone who dares to conceal his identity, s all be liable to a fine of not less than £2 or more than £10 gold or to imprison ment (for a term) of not less than six days or more than two months. Al ^- The police authorities shall warn persons whose period (of residence) has expired. Notice shall be given during the month preceding the Phe period and shall be made by means of an official document entitled Warning.” Ar P ^ 0 - An y person who stays on after the expiry of the period allowed his passport and fails to apply to the police authorities within ten days shall pay double the residence fees unless it is established that he had a legitimate excuse. Art. 21 . The Police Departments in all localities shall forward to police headquarters every year statistics showing the number of foreigners who have received permission to reside (in their respective districts), and the Director- General of Police shall forward to the competent authorities a general list of persons permitted to reside in the kingdom. Art. 22 . Any foreigner who desires to stay for less than one year after the expiry of the period allowed him in his passport shall apply to the Passport Office and have his passport endorsed. Art. 23. The police authorities may endorse the passport of any person who applies for permission to stay for less than one year and collect from him 5 Saudi riyals. Art. 24. Every foreigner who was resident in the Saudi Arabian Kingdom before 1356 A.H. (March 13, 1937) shall present himself to the police authorities within four months after the promulgation of these regulations and furnish the following particulars :— (a) His name, surname, occupation, place of birth, age, origin (race), nationality, and his place of residence before coming to the Saudi Arabian Kingdom. (b) The date of his arrival in the Saudi Arabian Kingdom. (c) His place of residence in the Saudi Arabian Kingdom and the occupation which he follows. (d) The names of the members of his family who are residing with him and particulars concerning them. Art. 25. The police authorities may request that official documents in support of the correctness of his statement be produced by any person giving such particulars. Art. 26. The persons mentioned in article 24 shall produce to the police authorities, with the afore-mentioned particulars, the passports or laissez-yasser on which they entered the kingdom. Art. 27. If any person fails to present himself to the Police Department during the period mentioned in article 24 or produces false statements or documents, the competent authorities, after the necessary investigation, shall deport him from the kingdom and execute the requirements of the regulations. Art. 28. The police authorities shall give residence permits to the persons referred to in article 24 and apply all the regulations concerning them. Art. 29. The Directorate-General of Police shall apply these regulations with effect from 1357 A.H. (March 2, 1938).hu k C r In any further communication on this subject, please quote w n°. 21~ and address not to any 'person by name, fmt to ’ '‘The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.Vi . a t a . L 60 THE 'i, 0 , K,L l,l 9 jgZ„ 'fL fA ft &amp; transmits herewith cop Foreign Office, nd, by directioh of the Seoreta of the under-mentioned paper.i (2 ' ™ IS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY’S GOY1IRN EASTERN (Arabia) . CONFIDENTIAL. iaIenJt 6 0 1937 February 1 , 1937. Section 1. E 702/702/25| Copy No. - j • , No 4 , Sir R Bullard to Mr. Eden.—(Received February 1 .) Sir r pTTT? p . Jedda, January 10 , 1937. iv/r lormation of a National First-Aid Society was reported in Us h f P No- 267 of the 28th i 9 3 35. Since that date 7C ^ q b f- en SOW ? nd somewhat uncertain, but from fairly frequent ^ ^ the ceutr«l the P 1 f S 'V 1 ™ been evident that ’ despite some initiaf set-backs, the cential committee has been active m promoting the objects of the society principally m Mecca. A. branch was formed in Medina in April 1936, but attempts to establish one m Jedda have so far come to nothing, although Sheikh Muhammad Surur is reported to have lent his influential support. . r 1 fuS?-’ t . he organisation has been promised annual financial support by the King, the Amir Feisal, Sheikh Abdullah Suleyman and others volunteers and donations have been called for, and, according to the Indian medical officer of the Legation, a promising start appears to have been made Premises have been secured m the Haram itself and certain essentials of equip ment installed. It is stated that two motor cars, one motor cycle and several bicycles, equipped with simple first-aid outfits, are attached to 'this post which consists of severa rooms (one for minor operations), offices and a small lecture- r0 1 0I ^A Dr ' Abdul Hamid was impressed with the cleanliness and neatness of what he saw. j A n Pmids are derived not only from donations, but from a special stamp duty of 4 piastre levied on all letters sent through the Saudi post The society s plans are reported to include the establishment of a hospital in Mecca and the completion of the hospital at Taif, which has been for some considerable time under construction. These plans are somewhat ambitious in comparison m h the socmty s modest resources, but it is reasonable to hope that the society will be able to render useful assistance to the Public Health authorities during the forthcoming pilgrimage season. &amp; 4- I am sending a copy of this despatch to the Government of India Department of Education, Health and Lands. I have, &amp;c. R. W. BULLARD.@ 21 (MDeXED f f j»’ ;/'• In any further communication on this subject)' please quote * * ■ V 1 and address —not to any person by name,Jnut to — £ f ^ “The Under-Secretary of State/’ Foreign Office, London, S.W. 1. s ^7 / / ' \ lL UJ '6 j'“ 7 ^ THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents hi^ r / compliments to and, by direction of the Secretary of £ transmits herewith cop *_^t-of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, y) S^&lt; n. Reference to previous correspondence : description of Enclosure./ (733A 6 / 8 ). Sir, ffie eacloairee in Mr, Hope ( ill's des»v&gt;atoh to the orelgn 0 flee Ho,SIS of Ne 16th 1038 relative to the constitution of this oountrj included at E a decree !m‘bai::,&amp;h®d on 13th 1980 providing for the reor^nlontlon of the I#©gialattvo couneil* ITom ®rmounae:ients which have a ; geared in the local piroaa aizic© Hay 193S this hodF fwulcl hoivcvar, :::ore intorcotlag as an oroan* siiiehf in a ora ordered constitution than the country at present possess#© t develop into a ouneil of State than as a i*©aUy effective or authoritative decent In the present ©yetci of &amp;&amp;v-®mmn%+ l have not therefore troubled our department with any spec id reports on its activities and I should not do so nm *mt for two features In aru40anc^.mts m&lt;ie recently 2* The last regular session of the 'fouridl, deserit&gt;od as the fourth, ended on Hard* 23rd the last day of the foal era year 1334# - It wae reconstituted at fro : iniroh 2fth by a decree is®.ted three da^ a earlier and publ ,slted on farch 28th# t have adverted in another eounoxion to the in the new MMMtt of Abdn 2 &gt;*i: : auf 44iiMN3M|| for erly one of the 5 .ost active conepiraiors abroad a,caim;t Ibn Sand* Th® point to vh-ch I now Slave to tow attention is that the decree prescribes that the now session shall last for one year* fills would appear on the face of it /to taourable Anthony Man# M* •. »» . . ., dO* , &amp;C## fSc« during success ivo It is#to involve a constitutional change fro, \ the system of tm :,ear seaslona, 3* to mon*e i^rfieartsnt is that in a speech by the King on the opening of the new aossion# he said that he fad ordered the preparation, during the new session of the Legislative at m regulation providing for an anmal meeting of representatives of ever/ district of the Kiagdc at pilgri/mge tl e, in order to strengthen the borals 'between the people arid the Oovew : ^ent- At a later meeting the council adopted an address to His which has isen published with s good deal of other • mttei- relating to the 'mneil and its past end future activities. fhe moot interesting doeu mi is the portion of the Amir Pep-cal’a speech, ^hen the addr-eoo was being considered. In which he dealt with the pr-opoaal for an a nual national mne bly. He ca^plained that of each a: rami pilgri age. Ho just if ed the shoi’tnes© of this period by r^Perring to the inconvenience wh^ch would be entailed* if represents wxves fro i re ote places wove retired to absent the selves far longer from their ho. ms and to the ins'll ty of the Oovemv.-jent to boar the sts-ain of heavy e^wn&amp;iiure. He added, however* tliat at the end of the oath’s session* a permanent bod^ would be set up (a sort of committee of the Atmo bly appai'ently) to consider the vimm &amp;Q» osrpissrod by the Ascef ly* 4* It regains to be seen what* if anything* will co o of this project. it vocalln the abortive eacj^ri-. :ent described in co ; responder\ce endiiig with y despatch Ko.8V9 of July 10th 1901. On that occasion the n Hatiorial conference” mo composed of represontativeo of the Hejas toviiie only. It m&amp; intended to bo aimual Xm,t the urban the reproe-entativee t/ould eet for one onth on the ocean ionmpvmmxt&amp;Uvm mm m -mtmt f^actloas and ttm ms mrmr mmmmfo'l&amp;L I vms neaatlm In thia G&amp;mmx&amp;i &amp;po&amp;Gh, mde W tlio Elng at a hmugiot in Mecca on April 14th» It CO. JBiotod lareoly of religious @3sliortaUo^» Mt it mfQrv*&amp; to Mb den ire for greater direct contact with Mn pc^ople, no that he might toow thiir doeirea and that th&amp;j should Isaow of Ms xu^oceodings and Intentions# With this oh;)ect he deolai^ed his Intention of receiving any one fho liked to visit hin 'between 6 end 9 p*m# in tlie overling mid rtated that in his absence the Viceroy would receive viol tore in hie place at Mecca or faif # m the case might he# if this echo e should 00 se into practical effect f it jould he in so *© sense an ©xta^iBion to the He .las of the traditional system in Kejd# vjhoro the King receives tribal personages and the like very streelr* I have the honour to he with the higtieot respect # Sir# Your most ohodlent# !m blc aervaritt‘^INDEXED p anj furtller communication on this subjectJolease quote ■tnd address not to any person by naMeJhvJio— ' ^ ° -Ihe Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. 1. r P 7 7964 INDIA DIR EC tjX C THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Mairs presents hi compliments to 'T '*d£(~C+^CjL. and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop^t*; of the under-mentioned paper. P hi Foreign Office, ^ 193J i at Reference to previous correspondence :THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY’S GOYERNMENT EASTERN (Arabia). y CONFIDENTIAL. I /964 1935 October 14, 1935. Section 3. [E 6149/6149/25] Mr. Calvert to Sir Samuel Hoare.—{Received October 14.) (No. 267.) Sir, Jedda, September 28, 1935. THE tendency of the Saudi Arab Government to introduce into this country certain features of an administrative nature borrowed from more highly organised States, particularly in regard to public health, sanitation and the like, has been previously reported on more than one occasion. This ambition would appear to have prompted the formation of what is officially designated as “ The National Humane First-Aid Society of the Saudi Arab Kingdom,” the regulations concerning which have recently appeared in the Mecca newspaper the Umm-al-Qura. I do not consider that these regulations are of sufficient interest to forward to you—they concern, briefly, the objects for which the society was founded, i.e., to render aid to victims of accidents, to sick persons and to assist the medical services in the event of the outbreak of epidemics; its organisation; its revenues, which are to be derived principally from donations and subscriptions, and from the sale of special issues of postage stamps; its flag, which is to be green and red; and its membership. The U?nm-al-Qura of the 13th September announced that a committee had been formed *'and a chairman elected. There seems to be no doubt that this organisation, though unofficial, will work under fairly close governmental control. 2. I am sending a copy of this despatch to the Government of India, Department of Education, Health and Lands. I have, &amp;c, A. S. CALVERT.I ~ I iiii i ii lidlMlT' ■MMBi ■HfaiHM* i In any finrther communication on this subiect, please quote N». fJT-'j’/S'Zsc/Jr. , and address —not to any person by name, but t&lt;y— The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.\^ A 5938 v 1934 j THE Under-Secretary of State^or Edreign Affairs presents his compliments to and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop^*-s» of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, ^ , 193/t* • s') 1 ? Reference to previous correspondence : O 3b Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. 14—6130 10292 (2) Similar letter sent to ffv y/ i 2291, Wt. 16213/7530. 3000. 8/33. Wy.P.C. 613 . -^V /* INDEXED Any reply to ^his letter should be ad ^sed to— THE SECRETARY, Board op Trade, Great George Street, Westminster, S.W.l, and the following reference number C.R.T.6983/34. r O. *7 jy 7^ BOARD OF TRADE, CO 1 -A- n Jt -jl * | } * .y Great George Strhet, r o ~ *). C'i • A_&gt;- CJ' ^ ') / Westminster, llSCfci. 3 'JLZL Alth September, 1934 I*' ,/?A The Board of Trade present their compliments t0 The Secretary of State for India-in-Council and beg to transmit herewith for information copy of a letter of to-days date which they have caused to be addressed to The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, S.W.l. „ ENCLOSURE IN WEEKLY LETTER 3 8 20 SEP 1934 - FW SECRETARY, POLITICAL AND SECRET D EPT. INDIA OFFICE Reference to previous correspondence (if any):COP Y ® 3 ? Any further communication should be addressed to :— THE ASSISTANT SECRETARY, at the address given opposite. The following letters and number should be quoted:— C.R.T. TelegrljjHffi?J$i 0 f‘ 3 sS • COLAST A, PARL, LONDON. 1 eh., jone No.: Whitehall 5140 . COMMERCIAL RELATIONS AND TREATIES — — - DEFARTMENT, BOARD OF TRADE, GEORGE STREET, LONDON, S.W.1. 5837 “! I934 J 11th September 9 1954t With reference to your letter K 521u/5^lo/25 of the 3rd September transmitting copy of a despatch from iiis Majesty’s Charge d’affaires at Jedda regarding the compulsory purchase of licences by persons wishing to trade or practise other professions in ^audi Arabia, 1 am directed by the board of Trade to state for the informal to of beeretary &amp;lr John bimon* that they concur in hi a proposal to instruct Mr. Calvert to take no action with the &gt;audi Government in the matter* Copies of this letter are being sent to the India Of flee and the Department of Overseas Trade* 1 have the honour to be, blr* lour obedient servant. The Under-Secretary of ^tate. Foreign office, »&gt;* N • 1 • JBigjrved) A. E. OVERTON.I 52X0/5210/25 FQfcfcl® OFFICE, I am directed by Secretary Sir John Simon to transmit to you to be laid before the Board of trade the accompanying copy of a despatch from His Majesty *8 Uhargd d‘Affaires at Jedda regarding the compulsory purchase of licences by persons wishing to trade or practise other professions in £&amp;udl Arabia* 2, The treaty concluded between this country and the and $ejd on the 20th May, 1927 does not appear to contain any provision with which the imposition of this tax on British subjects would conflict; and it will be observed that Mr* Calvert states that the tax appears to be neither oppressive nor discriminatory* In these circumstances lir John iSimon proposes, subject to the concurrence of the Board of Trade, to approve Mr* Calvert^ proposal to take no action with the Saudi Government in the matter. 5. Copies of this letter are being sent to the India Office and to the department of Overseas Trade* X am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, The Secretary to the hoard of Trade n2 m- Woolly .^rnin 3 f 13 SEP 19343 ^ r ' Ho.243. (8278/1271/5). I li \ vy-'V 2 .4 1 ti ’ INDIA DIRECT BjrltiaH ^©gatioa, AUG 1934 j J©€da, 31st July 1934, &amp;lr% l he?© th« honour to submit herewith a translation of an official communique published in the ®rm Al qura of the 13th July, relative to the issue of licenses to persons engaged in trade and f so It states, “in other professions*. 2. It will h# observed that the regulations provide for a graduated tax of two pounds t one pound, ten shillings or five shillings, to be paid annually and to be levied on firms or Individuals in accordance with their apparent importance. The tax is, of course, in pounds gold. 3. I am at a loss to understand the reference to other professions and believe that the use of the expression does not commote the distinction normally conveyed in the United Kingdom. In any case, regulations regarding the practice of medicine have already been published and formed the subject of Sir Andrew «yan f s despatch Mo.209 of the 6th July, 1953. 4. 1th regard to the Sa'ii&amp;l Arab government neither oppressive nor exception to them with taxes now introduced by the , they would appear to be diacriminat^Up and to take the &amp;&amp;•udl authorities The Might honourable, sir John 2&gt;lmon y , K.u.ft©., /would,woul&amp;t it is result in rstker gratuitously stimulatixig anti**ror©iga leeling* I would ttierefor© prefer# su^jeot to your instructions* to refrain from action with the Ba'u&amp;i GoTernment in this regard. 5, I am sending copies of this despatch to nil ixcelleney the Viceroy of India (foreign and Political Department}* Government of India (Department of Muc&amp;tioa# health and Lands) and the .Principal Secretary of ^tate for foreign Affairs# Departmeat of Overseas frade* I have the honour to he with the highest respect# ulr# four most obedient# humble servant# A. B # GALT St*Extract from the Mecca umm al-qura Ko*500 of 1st MaM ath-Thani 1353 (13th July 1934) Official BegulatioH in respect of licences to practise trade or other professions. I* This regulation will he entitled “Regulation concerning licences to practise trade and professions*. II. Any body practising a trade or any profession in the Kingdom of Sa*udl Arabia should obtain a licence from the finance Departments in the city where he practises his occupation* III. A committee shall he constituted in every one of the cities of the Kingdom of &amp;a*udi Arabia, consisting of the Municipal Council and a representative of the finance, to act as indicated in Article XV. XV. The Committee referred to in Article XIX in every city shall classify commercial houses (firms), shops and stalls and other occupations into four degrees t 1st, $nd, 3rd and 4th in accordance with the Importance of the commercial houses, shops, stalls and professions. The duty of this committee ends with the accomplishment of this work. V. Any one wishing t© practise any Kind of trade or profession should apply in writing to the Amir of the city in which he wishes to work. The application will he referred to the Municipality which will issue a decision of its Council fixing his degree in order that he may he given the licence from the finance accordingly. VI. A sum of two pounds in respect of a licence of the 1st degree, one pound in respect of the 2nd degree, half a pound in respect of the 3rd degree andand a quarter of a pound in respect of the 4th degree is to he collected annually for the grant or renewal of the licence* VII • The said fees shall he collected in full from the people of the 1st and 2nd degrees at the beginning of every year, and shall he collected in four equal instalments from the people of the 3rd and 4th degrees. VIII, The provisions of this regulation do not abolish anything indicated la the regulation concerning registration of companies issued on I4th Muharram 1345 under ho,144* It will remain valid as well as the provisions of this regulation.r copy , (F 5334/5210/2§) NCK246. (2308/1 .1/6). British Legation, Jedda. 6th August, 1934. Sir, X have the honour to refer to Mr, Stonehewer Bird^ despatch Mo. 120 of the 3rd August, 1928, relative to the registration of companies in this country, end to transmit to you herewith a translation of official communique Mo, 15, published in the l/mm-al-Qura of the 20th July last. 2. The communique, which is one of several recently issued by the Oaudi authorities on a variety of subjects, contains, it will be observed, the reprint of two articles of the Lecree for the )egiatration of Companies of 1928. This reminder to firms In » e audi rabia of the penalties attending failure to register in accordance with the regulations In force, would suggest that hitherto the provisions of the regulations h^ve not been very closely observed. 3. I am sending a copy of this despatch to the Principal Secretary of ftat© for Foreign Affairs, department of Overseas irade. I have, etc., (flgned) A,8. Calvert The Fight honourable, Fir John Simon, G.C.S.I., K.C.V.O., etc., etc,, etcT&amp;AtiSLATXOR. O^TCIAL CO^MUigQUE No. 15 . In vidw ol the f&amp;oi that some commercial comj^nles have not yet been registered In accordance witn the decisions or the regulati ons of he^istratlon of Companies Issued on_16th Kuharram^ 1547 tinder rlo, 144 . we republish the two articles relating to this subject. fjgticle Y IX . Any company, partnership or society failing to register within the period 1*1 ^ed by this regulation will be charged double fees and will be liable to be deprived of the privileges enjoyed by other companies who hove duly obtained certificates of registration /rtlcle XV . (b) Commercial Company is an association of more than on© person for purposes of trade* (c) In this regulation the word Company includes any association, society or its agents or any duly accredited person.Notes. Minute Paper. Register No. P.Z. SECRET. POLITICAL DEPARTMENT. Dated ‘ J 193 Dec. Date. Initials. SUBJECT. To Under Secretary Secretary of State... Committee •y.vivD Under Secretary Secretary of State.... Copy ot' to5*rom The Assistant i n To TTo , T 1 . 346-h/3^ Secretary to the Go the foreign and Pol 7484 . v4 r nrne I nil a Si r, The Chief Secretary to the Government of Bombay, Political Depa rtment* Pa dra s. Bengal. the United Provinces* the Punjab* Burma . Biha r a nd C ri asa . the Central Provinces- Assam. the Uo rth T/est Prontier Provi nee * The Hon’ble the Agent to the Governor General and Chief Commissioner in Baluchistan. The Ho n 1 bl e the Chief Commissioner of Ajme r-Me rma ra . The Chief Commissioner, Coorg. The Chief Commissioner, Delhi. The Ho n’ bl e the Re si de nt a t Hydera bad. The Hordble the Resident in Mysore. The Hon’ble the Agent to the Governor General in Central India,. The Hon’ble the Agent to the Governor General in Rajputana. The Hon’ble the Agent to the Governor General in the States of Western India. The Hon’ble the Agent to the Governor Ge ne ra 1, Pun j a b States. His Majesty’s Consul General and Agent of the Government of India in Kho ra san. His Majesty’s Consul for Sis tan and Kain. The Resident at Baroda. The Resident in Kashmir. The Resident at Gwalior. Hi s Ma j e s ty ’ s Co nsul Ge ne ra 1, Ka sh ga r. The Agent to the Governor General, Madras States. Dated Hew Delhi, the - November 19 32. it h it n » ii it h v it n n n i» ?i ii it u it Change of title of King Ibn Baud's Kingdom. b-&gt; 5 1 I am directed to inform you that by a royal decree dated the 18th September 1932, His Maj esty King Abdul Aziz(lbn Baud) has changed the style and title of the 'Kingdom of Heja z and of Kejd and its Dependencies' and of 'King of the Kingdom of Hejaz and of Be i d and its Dependencies' to those of 'Kingdom of Saudi Arabiya? (khmlakat as - Saudiya al Ara biya, literally' the Saudi Arab Kingdom') and 'King of the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia'. The change is a purely formal one and entails no special recognition nor alteration of flag. ENCLOSURE U FOREIGN SE -\!n 34 !0V. 1932 12 DEC. ,j32 I have the honour to be, Sim*, Your ijabjsV qfbe &lt;j.ient serva nt, Sd.R*A.Hill* As si s ta nt sa c re ta ry Go ve r nme nt of I ndia14—6130 7690 (2) In anv further eorr communipation on tins subject, please quote No.t 1 and address—wo^ to any person by name,, but to- “Tbe llnder-Secretarv of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. 1. o THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his ^ and, by direction of the Secretary of Stajjfe, ^ and, by direction oi me oeuieuttij ui ^ transmits herewith cop , Jt&gt;i of the under-mentioned paper, Foreign Office, . . An Vi ' i f ' ' I lo ^ , 19SZ . Reference to previous correspondence er^^v^oOc. Description of Enclosure. 0 Name and Date. Subject. \ r V. Similar letter sent to .3 THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY’S GOVERNMENT EASTERN (Arabia). ' .3 f 3 2 November 21, 1932. - CONFIDENTIAL. Section 2 . [E 6085/1484/25] No. 1. Mr. Hope Gill to Sir John Simon.—(Received November 21.) (No. 427.) Sir, Jedda, October 19, 1932. I HAD some conversation on the 15th October with Fnad Bey Hamza on the subject of the task devolving on the Council of Ministers by virtue of the Royal decree of the 18th September. We did not touch upon the actual change of the country’s title to “Saudi Arabia,” but Fuad Bey offered a few remarks on the future Constitution. 2. He thought that the council had two years’ work ahead of it to draw up a new Constitution and to replace all the old legislation with modern laws. He was going to advocate a kind of “ States-General,” to be summoned annually by the King from among the leading men of the country. After discussion of past experience and future policy, this body would annually leave an Executive Committee to carry on the work of legislation and government. He considered that the post of Viceroy should be replaced by that of Prime Minister. The Shari’a would be maintained as the common law of the country. Plus qa change 3. As regards succession to the throne, Fuad Bey declared that the King had already made it known that his eldest son should succeed him. The Council of Ministers would simply give formal and constitutional shape to this decision. I have, &amp;c. C. G. HOPE GILL. [627 x—2]ty ■J- 5cP In any further communication cn this subject, please quote No - t \^s and address—«oi to any person by name, but to— i he Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. 1. y . / J r&gt;&gt; o ^ J* j - ij £ THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to Jt* U/wAm ^i^cLcx v and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith copM of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, 2&gt;l D(Jt &gt; , 1932 INDIA DiREGT v ff' A i. 33 Reference to previous correspondence C.fc. Description of Enclosure. bs'if £ 7? Name and Date. Subject. (V^/v\ Similar letter sent to , V..O I4—6130 7441 (2)COPY (E 5587/1484/25) No.408 (2875/256/25) His Majesty’s Charge d’Affaires at Jedda presents his compliments to His Majesty’s Principal Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs and has the honour to transmit to him the under mentioned documents. British Legation, Jedda. October 1st, 1932. Reference to previous correspondence: Jedda Despatch No.401 (2828/256/19) of September 25tn, 1932. Description of Enclosure Name and Date. Subject. To Viceroy of India. No.126(2874/256/25) of 1/10/32. Change of style and title of the King and Kingdom of Hejaz-Nejd. Distribution as in last paragraph of despatch.Britioh egation, •i'edda* October 1st*, 1958* U iwy ,ord f I have the honour to Inform Your Excellency that, by a oyal decree dated eptcmber 18th*, King 'Abdul Vusiss (Ibn Sa ud) has changed the style and title of the 'Kingdom of Be^&amp;ss and of He;Jd and its bependencice** and of &lt;f idng of the Kingdom of Hejgus and of He 3 d and its Dependencies 11 to those of •Kingdom of SaMdian Arabia' (limlakmt as-Ga’udiya al drably a, literally 'the Sa*ddi Arab K-ingdom'; and 'King of the Kingdom of Sa’udian Arabia'* 2* The change is a purely formal one entailing no special recognition nor alteration of flag* It is to be followed y a reform of the constitution and a declaration regarding the succession to the throne. 3* I am sending copies of this despatch to hie to whom I have already fully reported on the change, to the British representatives at Cairo, Khartoum, fort rudaa, Aden, Addis Ababa, Sheikh, dagos, Jerusalem* Baghdad, Bushi re, Singapore, Kuala umpur, and to the Senior Daval Officer in Ked ea tloops* 1 I have the onour to be* m -ord, Your Excellency's obedient servant. tope oilu. his Excellency, The Viceroy of India-r Copy No.407 (2847/55/35) (E 5274/5274/25) 0 His Majesty's Charg6 d'Affaires at Jedda presents his compliments to the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, and has the honour to transmit to him the under-mentioned documents. British Legation, JEDDA. September 27th, 1932. Translation of 'Umm-al-Qura’' Review of the year. Description of Enclosure Name and Date SubjectQATW maalrtSSOH OF F :OM ' HO.405 th© 16th Jurafida al 01a f 1361 (aeptosher 16th# 1932). Under the above heaolnij appears a leading article to the effect that the |ura ,, newspaper has completed eight years of 1%» life and gives a brief suamary of Important events that took place during the past year. Ihe chief events referred to are the following {«* iMjm&amp;L J mwL* The Government deputed a political mission headed by the Amir Feysal to visit ttie capitals of the Governments with whom Diplomatic relations have been established# for the purpose of strengthening the bonds of friendship. The mission spent more than three months on its journey. 1. Diplomatic relations have been established between the Government of this country and the Italian Government, with whom two treaties (of Friendship and Commerce) have been concluded. 2 . Treaties of Friendship have been concluded with the Yemen# France, Syria# th e Lebano n and Afghanistan* 3* The oovernaent have become a party to the pact of Paris known as the * Treaty for the Renunciation of aggressive War% 4. The Government have adhered t&amp; the Armaments Truce for one year# beginning November 1931 and ending in October 1932# 5. The Government accepted an invitation to attend the * JSisarmament Conference held at Geneva# sent their Minister at London to represent them there and sent an explanatory memorandum concerning the state of armament in this country* 6 . The Government joined the International Health Jureau at Paris arid signed the Canitary Convention concluded at Home in 1997, 7. Settlement of disputes with the neighbouring sister (Yemen)A n * w ^ ouncii has been i’oraed and named i iajlla el TaJuCUU k Council oa' iiinlatejw) wiioee President is the Aafr s-'eyai . A 3i&gt;ocial regulation has been made for it, requiring that its member* ue jointly responsible before ilia Majeoty the King for the general policy of the country# MaLatey of the Interior. .. j -he general office of the Viceroy has been divided into two parte, one annexed to the office of the Council of itlnistere and the other remaining where it was arid called 'Ministry of the Inter! or rt # ■e.ialatlve As the session of the Legislative Aaeembly had AeterodMf 7 , m s iiejeety the King gave ordera for a new session to be opened.*' He delivered a speech at the opening of the new session and granted the assembly the asm authority as before, urbanization of One of the chief matters to which the Government gave much of their attention this year, has been toe question of finance and the overcoming of the crisis. They have very carefully organized tuc iinanciai. affairs, relying for their expenditure on the funda mental revenue of the country. .hey divided the income into lour divisions: one for the pay of Government employees, one for debts, one ao a reserve fund and one for unforeseen expenses. All finance treasuries have been attached to the general treasury. Other arrangements, including reduction in all expenditure have ueen made, he Gakfilat al ;;aliya' has been raised to a .Ministry, for which a special regulation has been made and will be published when obtained. Public Gecurity. fhe incident of Ibn ..ifSuu, who has been entirely defeated, has not been allowed to cause disturbance etc. ^are of Pilgrims. | I Great care has been taken by the Legislative Assembly to arrangements ensuring the comfort of pilgrims and to draw up a generalgeneral Hot of dues Imposed on pilgrims, mxch reduced from those imposed In past years* It has also prepared instructions and advice which will to© published in all languages in the form of a booklet and distributed free to pilgrims# Ihe Government became a member of the International Health bureau at laris, establiehed in accordance with an International Convention concluded at lone in 1907# •whe Government WM9UMK&amp;s .ve also lately selected the toirector-General of the Health Department to represent them at its meetings which miXI be held in Paris on October 28th next* Dr# imhammad al ILhashugji has completed his studies and become a specialist in X-rayeu ^he building of the hospital which the wealthy Syrian, ustafa Bey Bssodin has promised to build is being started# .ensateojt. Four night schools iiave been opened at Mecca and a day school ha© been opened at imi’tb&amp;a, Mecca# .- j .oate ;&gt;elfcyaQte. Wireless installations have been erected at al Hasa, ureyda, pebdk, and Ug,air, and a big wireless station of 6 K#W# power has been completed at Mecca# Certain instructions as to the parcel post have been issued* Foetal money orders can be obtained for India, Aden and Palestine# Omm&amp;&gt; fhe Government have completed a general census in all the Hejaa cities# /urloulture. In order to encourage cultivation, the Government have decided to bring machines at their own expenses and distribute them amongst farmers against payment by instalments* Kew wells have been dug, repairs have been made to the old reservoirs at Mecca and along the road, said a new well lias b© e n sunk at Ka’m&amp;n#■■■■ In any further communication on this subject, please quote ) No. IE \ \U S ^ \2a' and address —not to any person by name, but to— “The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. I. ■y JLJ A. &gt;- * .. 'w/ A. /-' iiv-Cr^ THE Under-Seeretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop vi/&gt; of the under-mentioned paper. .« o. Foreign Office, ^ 0 tb , i93z . |v^ Reference to previous correspondence : V- 0 .Uhr E Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. No. *&amp;£ 20 OCT. 193 ; FROM 8ECRETA R y, POLITICAL A jECRET Dept, INPU OFFICE h,0i’iA' &lt; dL5-o A; THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BiBITANNIC MAJESTY’S GOYERNMEN1 O EASTERN (Arabia). CONFIDENTIAL. .o P77 October 6, 1932. Section 1. [E 4868/1484/25] No. 1. Sir John Simon to Mr. Hope Gill (Jedda) (No. 335.) '' Sir * wtttt ^ , Foreign Office, October 6, 1932. WITH reference to your telegram No. 180 of the 22nd September, I transmit to you the accompanying copy of a note from Sheikh Hafiz Wahba announcing that the description of the Dominions of King Ibn Saud is to be changed as from the 22nd September to the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia.” This English rendering of the new Arabic title was decided upon after considerable consultation between the Minister and my Department and I request that you please will use it as the official English translation of the new name. I am, &amp;c. JOHN SIMON. Enclosure in No. 1. Sheikh Hafiz Wahba to Sir John Simon. Sir, Hejaz and Nejd Legation, September 22, 1932. I HAVE the honour to intimate that in accordance with the wishes of his subjects His Majesty King Abdul Aziz has graciously consented that his kingdom be called the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia, instead of the Kingdom of the Hejaz and Nejd and its Dependencies. This new name is to operate from this day. I have, &amp;c. HAFIZ WAHBA, Minister of the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia. [599 f—1]^ In any furtliev communication cn this subject, please auote i No. JT^iU^ / Idrgty [ if and address— not to any person by piame, but to—| “The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. I. o f I I Hlii Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to y ^ cLvOUt' and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop ^ of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, OcQfa I?'*', 193A . l^&gt; L&gt;3 Reference to previous correspondence Ojjl/la JUm* (a* 4^0-01 jr 2^ Description of Enclosure. Similar letter sent to 14-6130 7441 (2) i u k ? , *j 4 o i yuu~ .) ITo«401« (83SE/856/19) # JISBDA September . f 193S. I p. Sir, with refereneo to my telegrame Ko&amp;«180, 181, and 182 of September 22 , announcing the formal adoption of a new style and title by Ibn Sa’tld for himself and this country, 1 hare the honour to transmit herewith translations of 2 (1) A circular mmorondwi from the Ministry of Foreign Affairs to the foreign representatives dated September 21 and covering (2) a certified copy of Royal Decree l?o»2716 of September 18 which makes the change effective as from September 22 and charges the Council of Ministers with the elaboration and submission to His Majesty of a new Constitution, a rule of succession to the throne, and a system of government* And (3) an extract from the Mecca 'ilmm-al-aura' of September 16 explaining the genesis and execution of what Is described as a popular movement of appeal to the King and giving the text of the four leading petitions as telegraphed to Rlyftdh* 2* ihe *Umm~al-^wa H of September 23 publishes the text of a number of other petitions and avers that Xbn 3a*tid received In all over 700 such petitions at Rlyftdh* I will not weary you with them, except to say that they seem to emanate from all quarters and all classes, also from the guild , among them the jewellers, brokers, tax collectors, criers to prayer, tent makers, butter sellers, butchers, tinsmiths, upholsterers, and eunuchs* The petitions which 1 enclose are themselves sufficiently wearying, but I have reproduced them in full to show their exact nature* The first, and the best reasoned, is signed by Fuad Hamsa and 15 of the moot prominent citizens His Majesty's principal He or ct ary of State for Foreign Affairs*citizen® of Mecca and Jedda, the second, a ahoa?t one, by 28 leading pereonalitiea of Mecca, Including a few Sharffa, the third, equally short, by representatives of 6 Hejazl tribes and the tom of I’abdk, and the fourth, the most ebullient, by ’Abdullah Ouleyolln and a niaed bag of 02 Hejdis, ilejazia and domiciled Indians, Javanese, and Hadhramls# 3« It la of particular Interest to note that, according to the n Umm~&amp;X~Qura n of September 25, the sequence of event® was as follows t~ first, a general canvictlon was come to throughout the country that the He j&amp;a and liejd, so united In the face of recent events, were brothers; than, the 16 signatories of fund Hamza 1 a petition met at T&amp;tf and elaborated its details; they thereupon telegraphed to their friend© and colleagues throughout the country requesting their support; result, w the news spread like lightning, the whole nation arose and held meetings and after long discussions decided to cooperate and sent telegrams to lit© Mai esty the King Imploring him* • « ~ to grant, in short, the request© formulated by those 16* 4 * In ©pit© of it© widespread nature, the secret of this move was well kept and it came m a surprise to the foreign resident© and representatives. It can safely be stated that it was no popular movement, box*n of impulse, but erne stage-managed either by the King and his officials, or by ?uad Hama and soee of the latter with the King*© knowledge and consent* Before ever the petitions were sent, it wm generally realised that the answer© had already been decided upon* Only that concerning the succession to the throne gave rise to ©peculation* ^hi© difficult question the King has temporarily ©helved for study by the Council of Minister©* Its outcome is entirely problematical#o*o*tfc&gt;i-: j &amp; GXhS* A 7 fit $ m tar m t can at present surmise. Urn main &lt; reasons for this unification - the word 'tauhfd* la aomewhat significantly used, which also epi tool see the prime fahhihl tenet of the ^eneaeee^ of uod * are (1) dynastic* to ocnaoUdate the Hejaa as a 8a*Mi possession, to the final discouragement of Baahlmlte or republican aspirations; (2) financial, to ©over the absorption of the resources of the lie j as in those of He id and perhaps to facilitate the publication of a single Sa’ddi budget of a kind that may create confidence in the money markets; (3) imperial, to assimilate l As*ir yet more closely to the Sa’ddi rule; and (4) to some extent, constitutional, to enable juristic minds like Fuad Hamsa 1 ® to clear away at a blow the tangled undergrowth of the dual Kington mid m% about building a tidier and more critic-proof edifice of state# / 6, 'Union Bay' - 'M It is already called’ was celebrated m September 22 with parades of yelling schoolboys and a reception by the iisfr of Jedda of the foreign representati ve©* At iieeca the Viceroy publicly thanked the population for their ss&amp;&amp;1 and sincerity and he came the next day to Jed&amp;a, where the foreign representatives and local notables were Invited to meet him at tea* 1 confined myself &gt;y~ requesting hla to convey my personal respects to He Majesty* respect. I have the honour to be with the highest Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant,T'Wmrji'nQih lUnistry of Foreign Affairs. 20th JtamMa aX Ola, 1551* 21st September 1932* of the ©hanging the Bam© of the Kingdom* 1* His Mai eoty the King issued a royal decree on the 17th Jum&amp;da al 01a 1351 (September 18th) under Ho.2716 announcing the change of the name of the Kingdom of the Hejas and Re^d and its Depen dencies to another, the 'Kingdom of Sa'ddlan Arabia', and of the present title of His Majesty to that of 'King of the Kingdom of Sardian Arabia'*# ibis change will come into effect as from Thursday the 21st OtunMa. al 01a 1351 (September 22nd). 2. The reasons for this change and Its immediate and future effects liave been explained in the gracious royal decree. 1’he Ministry of Foreign Affaire need not further explain the royal decree for, as is mentioned in article 3 of the decree itself, this change will not affect the treaties and international agree ments and obligations existing between this country and other friendly and allied countries. 3. The Ministry of Foreign Affairs has pleasure in forwarding herewith a true copy of the gracious royal decree to which reference is made, hoping that it will be conveyed to the authorities concerned for their information, so that they may use the new title and address in future official communications. MECCA* Dated 21st Jumdda I, 1551* (22nd September, 1932) ’ Sealed (Ministry of Foreign Affairs, iecoa). 25/10/2. 'O i § ^ - &lt;* i \ p-, ^ p i Hemorandum in respect Mdressed to the Jritish Legation dedda*h } TiiAHSLA'XIOS, 30YAI. DSOKEE Ho.2716 of 17th Jtimfida I, 1361 (* 18th September 1952)• iiftei* placing cur reliance on God* and as a result of the telegrams sent to us 'by all our subject® in the Kingdom of the Bej&amp;s and of Xfejd and its Dependencies # in accordance with the public desire in our country, and wishing to unite the parts of this Arab Kingdom, We decree the following$- 1# -he name of the Kingdom of Hejas and Kejd and ita Dependen cies shall be changed to that of the «rdLngdom of Sa’&amp;dian Arabia’ 1 (MaalaJcat f at ably at ao-Sa f dOiya) and our title shall in future be 'King of the Kingdom of 8a*&amp;dlan Arabia”* 2m The change shall take effect as from the date of its announcement (» September 22nd)* 5* This change shall not affect the treaties and international obligations and agreements, which will remain effective and binding* neither shall it affect the contracts and agreements made with individuals, which will continue to be effective* 4* All previous regulations, instructions and orders given by ua shall remain in force after this change* o* The organisation of our present Government, whether in the He Jan or in He jd ©net its Df-pendencies, will provisionally continue in its present form until a new organisation la laid down for the whole Kingdom on the basis of the new unification* 6# Our present Council of Ministers shall start immediately to lay down a basic constitution for the Kingdom, a rule for and succession to the thr-one,/a regulation for the organisation of the Government, and shall submit them to us for our orders* The President of our Council of Ministers has the right to add to the members of the Council of Ministers any person or persons of intelligence, while the above mentioned regulations are being prepared, in order to benefit from their opinions and to obtain enlightenment from their knowledge* a*8* We choose Thursday the 21st of JumMa 1, 1351, the first day of the eguinox, as the day on which shall he announced the unification of this /gpab Kingaom* May ood grant success* (liven in our Palace at Eiyidh on this 17th day of JimUda I f 1351* Oignature* , Ahdul ’Azfz* I rue Copy.TBjMl&amp;nm OF SXTEAOT FROM U14I-AL-QUHA Ho*405 '&amp;$%'$&amp; 15th el 01a, 1561 (16th September 1952)* 'AJ^m^jmirnsaSL' 1 • petition forwarded to H1 b Majesty the King to request the changing of the name of the 'Kimmu OF r fHS mZAZ~W£3to mV ITS D^Hi)WOIBS w to that of the n KINGDOM OF SA'ODIM ARABIA”, the laying down of a Constitution and (the establishment of) succession to the Throne * Recent incidents will oh have taken place in the Hejas and bejd have liberated energies arid strengthened hearts and caused the people of the Hej&amp;z and He jd to be more watchful and better warned and seriously to endeavour more than they did before to realise their aims and those of the Arabs in general# A few days after the close of those incidents, such as are sincere towards the Arabs and their problem were seen to be endeavouring to realise an aim, to the realization of which the Arab world 1ms long been looking forward# These sincere Arabs and those who have been striving for the unification of their (the Arab) world, finding that the Kingdom of the Hejaz and that of liejd are one indivisible part and one inseparable body and that the present name given to them, namely 'the Kingdom of lie jaz-llejd and its Dependencies', is a name inapplicable to this unity and foreign to that object - the object of Arab unity which they sought to realize - for all these reasons they, townsfolk and 3eduin, rivalled each other in the holding of assemblies to consider the question of the unification of the name of the two Kingdoms in a name more applicable to the sense of Arab unity which they so wish for and desire# After long discussion they agreed upon the fact that the best name by which to realize their wish was that of 'The Kingdom of Sa’ddian Arabia'# Bo they submitted petitions to His Majesty the King,Kingf requesting the realisation of their wish and the granting of their request. We publish herewith such petitions forwarded in this respect as we have been able to secure, and we pray that God may guide the competent authorities in the right way for the welfare and prosperity of the Arab nation in general. (1) In the Hame of God, the most Merciful, the Compassionate. There is no Might nor power save in God, the High, the ureat* praise be to the One God. On this day, the 12th Jim&amp;da al 01a, 1301 A.H.(13th Sep tember) the undersigned have gathered to discuss and consult upon a question concerning dignity, honour, grace, union and harmony, and to take a decision in this respect and to submit it to His Majesty tm King 'Abdul 'Asia ibn Abdurratea&amp;n al Peysal &amp;1 Sa’&amp;d, may God grant him success and prolong his reign. God the most Almighty has distinguished this country from its sisters, the other Arab countries* It is thus the most honourable, the highest ranked, the most strongly peopled, the most populous, the most independent, the best capable of facing calamity and evil-doing and the readiest to pursue beneficial and profitable ends. God has granted its people distinctions of which others have been deprived. Thu® they are one Arab race in origin, in custom®, traditions, religion, obedience (Isl&amp;m) and history* The whole country can thus become united and be on© completely united race. Its people can be one nation, without difference between those who come from the Tlhfima, Hejd or the Kejass, from the Bast or the West. This being the state of the country and its people and this being Its distinguished position amongst all other countries inhabited by Arab®; and as its present govern mental systems do not tally with the nature of the unity posses sed by it and its people; and as it® present name, 'The Kingdom of the Hejaa-bCjd and its Dependencies' does not express the racial3, V 3?aciuXf goand national uni uy which should appear in it, 'but only exhibits certain naiaea of geographical regions of the Arab lands which fail to represent the actual fact referred to above, and does not reflect the wish which the people of this nation have in their hearts namely the union of and agreement between all Arabs of different countries and from remote homea; and as the abovc-meationed systems of government do not show the general connections which exist between the inhabitants, neither do they Indicate the joint obligations which exist between them, for the dignity and honour of the country (a© taa demonstrated by the cooperation shown during the recent Ibn Bifida happenings), while they should show real union between the two important parts of the Kingdom under the ©hade of His Majesty the King - the present people most humbly submit to Ais Majesty their earnest desire and request that he may be pleased to issue his imperial decree sanctioning the change of the present name of the Kingdom to one more appropriate to actual conditions, more indicative of future aims, and one more clearly commemorative of the one who was the cause of this unification and agreement, namely the person of His Majesty the redeemed King; changing the name of the ?&lt; Kingdom of the Hejaz- Kejd and Its dependencies to thau of the ? *Kingdom of Sa’ddian /rabia 1 *, which designates the countries inhabited by those Arab© whom God haw helped -lis Mejoety the King 1 Abdul*Aziz as-Ba’&amp;d to bring to union. And a© stability, permanence and steadfast- nes® are amongst the principal condition© to which nations aspire in their political and social life, without which they cannot hope to face contingencies and mishaps, and without which no country or nation can stand firm, as is seen in the history and fall of nations, governments and countries which have neglected such grave matters, petitioners humbly beg liis Majesty the King, may God prolong \iXb life, to grant another request, to the effect that His Majesty may be pleased to issue his gracious order approving the drawing up of a constitution (litj(lit5 M regulation of government^) and the succession to the throne so that everyone, friend or foe, near or far, may know that this sovereignty is firmly established and cannot be disturbed by storms or events. His Majesty, may God prolong his life, is the best qualified person to appreciate the important matter, its far- reaching benefits within and without the country, and the consoli dation of its moral and material state. We pray that God Almighty may help His Majesty the redeemed King, for the welfare and prosperity of the country. Signatures. 1. Fuad iiamsa. 2. Sileh Shata* 3. ’Abdullah ash-Sheybi. 4. Muhammad Sharaf Ridha* 5. ’Abdul Wahhab, If&amp;ib al Haraia. 6. Ibrdhfm al Fadhl. 7. Muhammad ’Abdul Qader Itigherbi. 8. Rashfd an-Hftsir. 9 * Ahmad B&amp; Mja. 10# ’Abdullah al Fadhl. 11. Khtlid abu al Wahid al ^arqtani* 12* Muhammad Sharaf ’iidndn. 13. lUttld Ruweyhi. 14. Huseyn M Salima* 13* Muliammad Sileh Hastf. 16. ’Abdul Wahh&amp;b ’Attir. (2) His Majesty the redeemed King ’Abdul ’Asia ibn ’Abdurrahmin al Feysal &amp; Sa’dd, Rlyidh* We have learnt that our brethren in the cities of the Hejaz have submitted petitions to Your Majesty requesting Your Majesty to agree to the change of the present name of the ’’Kingdom of the Hejaz-Hejd and its Dependencies” to another, namely the ’’Kingdom of(s ^ of Sa'Mian Arabia” and the drawing up of a constitution and succession to the throne* As we think that this is advantag eous for the Moslems and their country, m join our brethren in this request, adding our voice to theirs, and request that Your Majesty may be pleased to grant this request* May aod preserve Your Majesty* (28 Signatures - chiefly ueccawls). (3) His Majesty the redeemed King 1 Abdul 'hztz ibn Abdurrah man al Fey sal %X Sa^d, Riyadh* (^tactly similar to the preceding petition}# Signatures s On behalf of the Aeni Mdlik tribe (8 signatures)* On behalf of the uhdml&amp;i- (S signatories)* On behalf of the Sahr&amp;ns- (4 signatories)* on behalf of the haw&amp;rlth:- (2 signatories)* On behalf of the moibeyHn:- i \ (2 signatories)* V On behalf of the Fhaqlf ash-Bhara’#- (1 ftignetonr)# On behalf of tabdks- (1 signatory)* (4) In the Kerne of God, the most Merciful, the Compassionate* 'Oh l ord, upon thee we rely, and upon thee we depend and In Thee we end.' 9 i-iis Majesty the King of the Kej&amp;z-Hejd and its Dependencie f Abdul V&amp;sifc ibn * Ab&amp;urrahm&amp;n al Fey sal Al Oa^d, may God preserve him. On,« 6 . On Wednesday evening the 14th Juatda «1 Ole, 1351,( 15th September), petitioners ecsapeted in signing this telegraphic petition declaring their earnest aims for the realization of which the capital of Islam, the place of the Revelation and of the Inspiration, and the source of light in the universe has been striving namely H Arab Unity”, to which their sincerest men have been looking forward since the time the heart of this peninsula, which pulsates with the Witness (that there is no deity but Allah and that Muhammad is his prophet), which represents the reason for the existence and the unification of the worshipped Lord, and which calls for cooperation and collaboration in uplifting the word of God, has been the capital, the established glory and the justification of this religion* Your Majesty, the Arab land over which Your Majesty's sacred flag flies has never shown such absolute submission, such sincere love and such devoted loyalty to any other ruler, however powerful he may be, as to the one whom God Almighty has helped and caused to bring to it peace, security and prosperity and in whose hands he has placed its religious and worldly guidance, namely His Majesty King 'Abdul 'az£z the First, the Hawk, the Master and the one who has laid the foundation of the civilization of the Artib* and who is renewing their history and uplifting their standard. Truly this is the fact which the just have realized and at which the sincere are pleased but the jealous are displeased. It is a fact recognized by the unfriendly, and it may be invoked by the Arabs if they wish to benefit by their ready circumstance and to seize the opportunity thus tendered, which the Arabs have not seen since their sun set, until to-day. nothing could prevent us. Your Majesty, from expressing to you the aims which we have in our hearts for the welfare and happiness of our country and nation except our failure in the performance of our duty or our misuse of the blessings bestowed upon us by God, such as our ears, our eyes and minds. We acquit God of any failure on our part to ^predate the blessings we enjoy in this brilliantm) 76 ori Hi ant era for our souls, wealth and honour, or If we deny the public and personal distinction with which iod has distinguished you, and which history will welcome and glory will surround* 'The Arab lands which now enjoy Tour Majesty’s just rule and prevailing honour have now become, thanks and praise be to God, a considerable power from which the light of Islam has spread all over the world and out of which the moon of the message has risen* l^rom among its people brave heroes have gone out and travelled about in the Hast and the West* It still cleaves to the book of Allah and the traditions of His prophet, may the blessing and peace of God be upon him, renewing its first condi tion under the shade of your successful progress arid your pnofitable state* God knows that every word written in this telegram comes from the depth of our* hearts, is dictated by our belief and is instinct with the ready and earnest desire of advice given for the sake of God and hie prophet, for the Imfim and all Moslems* Your Majesty, we are moved to submit our desires by absolute seal and sincerity for our religion, our nation and our Arab country. We have no doubt that Your Majesty, being the greatest guide of this nation, will realize before anyone else the benefits of union and agreement and the avoidance of every cause of separation that may habitually have occurred or arisen from the events of past times* fe now most humbly beg and implore Your Majesty to realize the aims of your people and loyal subjects by declaring the unification of the happy Arab countries, known as the 'Hejazl-Hejdi Kingdom”, and by causing them to be one United Kingdom amalgamated with each other and to be of equal effect in every good way, so that their endeavours may always cooperate to secure benefits and avoid harm, to the satisfaction of God and His prophet, the raising of its rank, the defeat of its enemies, the safeguarding of its dependencies against all danger, and as a proof to the whole world that any evil attempt from any direc tion whatsoever will end only in failure, since the Hejez is the brotherbrother of Kejd from the reltgioua, national and territorial points of '/lew arid is not less than its brother in sincerity and devotion for the maintenance of this Kingdom under the aegis of their redeemed throne, as to which practical proofs have been given In every event* f@ request that the Kingdom may be entitled the 'Kingdom of Sardian Arabia” in glorification of its position, in honour of its people and in the name of its greatest leader, the renewer of the time of Fardq,* We also request that it be simultaneously declared in all parts of the Kingdom, that the authorities concerned within and without the country be notified, that the day of its announcement be a memorable day in all cities, that the nation be allowed to celebrate it with lawful ceremonies, and that Your Majesty may issue your high decree for the establish ment of a constitution and the succession to the throne* So that friends and enemies may know that the Arabs are a living nation striving after their interests and elm without hesitation and undivided* God help the pious and the benevolent* May God preserve Your Majesty a treasure for the Arabs and Islam* Slngatures: (’Abdullah Suleyra&amp;n and 82 co-signatories)*„ / INDEXED In any further communication on this subject, please quote no, &lt; V-f and address —not to any person by name, but to-A “ The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S 'VI. I. P. Z. ' 6903 1935' n li-li ■isi': THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to an( ^&gt; by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop^s? of the under-mentioned paper. x t ^ yv^ ^ Foreign Office, c?- £ (' r %^C. (19 32 . pc •i'l 0 '* Beference to previous correspondence : * Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. ItrT of S^U-, c^ou.n^ f r t dott* TU.iP'b if Zb* /t j^-Cyf&lt;^c£oy*i . *0 , IJ I If. iyi«w»yi-ii ENCbOSUp IN WEEKLY LETTER NO.'e40, 6 1 Jd. 1932 FROM SECRETARY, POLITICAL AND SECRET DEPT. INBIA OFFICE 14—6130 7441 (2) Similar letter sent to C-*?, Pr.M.&gt; [This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government, and should be returned to the Foreign Office if not required for official use.] D. 6 o 30 p.m. 22nci September, 1932. B. 6.05 p.m. 22nd September, 1932. No. 182. Wty telegrams Nos. 180 and 181, Movement has been well stage managed. At Govern ment’s special reception today I oliered personal con gratulations. Do you wish me to convey His Majesty’s Government’s iormal recognition? Prom HEJAZ -NE.TD. Decypher. ^Sir A. Ifyan (Jedda). 4uxJl 22nd September, 1932.Q (E.4847/1484/25,) P. Z. ; £903 NO DISTRIBUTION. Code telegram to Mr. Hope Gill, (Jedda), Foreign Office, 26th September, 1952, 7.00 p.m. No.125. (R). -O —0~*0“0 -0 -0 -o '-0 - Your telegram No.182 (of September 22nd - new name for King Ihn Sand's dominions). According to precedent no formal 'recognition” hy His Majesty's Government of mere change of name is called for. Personal congratulations which you have already offered are therefore sufficient. If matter is raised you may explain in sense of first sentence./ , In any further communication on this subject, please quote No - t —* and address —not to any person by name, but to— ' “The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London,'S.W. i. / , * 7 ( L v.. / THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreigi Affairs presents his compliments to and, by direction of the Secretary of State, (^i 'B - transmits herewith copviL6 of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, 11. , 193 Reference to previous correspondence : ff IT . .C Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. — \ NO. S3S L AsiOj 1 # C'V lirtx |. V 26 SEP 1932) # V 'v' ^' ~ - --_rr ,v&gt;'' Similar letter sent to ^.vv v o. o_ 0. 0,^. 14—6130 7441 (2)[This Document is the Property of |Iis .Britanttic jjlajesty’s Government, and should be returned to the Foreign Officer^! ^ot required for official use.] ' ? 2 From H5Ja2)?r.&lt;JD» - Docode, H.M’s Charge aires (Jedda) 22nd Beptcmher 1932, . .. D. .-4.30 p.m. 22nd Septemhcr 1952. , R. 5.05 p.m. ? 22nd Beptemper 1932. -No. 180. (R). Ministry of Foreign affairs have to-day communicated (under circular memorandum) royal decree signed Riyadh September 18th gist of which is as follows:- preamble - after reliance on God, as result of telegrams received from all our subjects in accordance with public wish and in order to unite sections of this Arab kingdom, we decree (D Name of Kingdom of Hejaz Nejd shall be changed X to Kingdom of Saudian Arabia and our title of King of King dom of Ssndian Arabia. (2) Change to take effect from day of announcemento (3) It will not affect existing treaties, agreements, obligations or contracts, (4) /dl existing regulations etc.'remain in force. (5) Existing government organisation to continue until new organisation is built on basis of this unification. (6) Council of Ministers to prepare forthwith and submit to us constitution for king’s rule,’succession to throne and organisation; of government. (7) Council may co-opt suitable member^-for this purpose. (8) September 22nd first day of equinox chosen as date of announcement of unification, see my immediately \ following telegram.ir Council of Ministers by Royal command published in the ‘ £ Umm-al-Qura of the 11th March, a translation of which was transmitted to you m my prm letter No. 136 onheJ9th^Marck^_^ budget, presumed ^ Heiaz however, was published in the 1 Umm-al-Qura of the 16th January^ A translation was transmitted to you under cover of my despatch No. 36 of the 21st JariuarU^ haye certa i n i y ], een man y derogations in practice from the terms of the Constitution of 1926, and probably not a few mo , d f c ^\ on l“ ted constitutionally, and published m some form or another, but those enumei ate above are all tLtcan now be precisely traced, in the ^sence of any official gazette or other compendium, and with the assistance of the Hejazi Ministry for l oreig Affairs The Under-Secretary for Foreign Affairs has stated m semi-official correspondence on the subject that Part IV of the Constitution has lapsed since the abolition of the post of Inspector-General, but he has been unable to indicate the date or exact nature of the modification. I would refer m conclusion to the comment made on the status of Asir in paragraph 5 (i) of Sir A. Ryan s despatch No. 180 of the 15th May, 1931. I have, &amp;c /-« ry :?.-J a Ho.313* C &gt; r\ JEDDA, J Sir, May 18th, 1933. bo/ix&amp;M llth reference to Sir A*Hyan*s despatch Ho# ^&gt;8 —of the 3rd July last* regarding the proposed compendium ©f the constitutional law© of the world, I am at length in a position to furnish a reasonably comprehensive survey of the constitutio if al measures affecting the Hejaz and mid and its Dependencies whihh have been promulgated since the establishment of the Sardian regime# | \jutt * S» In his despatch Bo#27B of the 20th October 1939, ^ ^ Mr# Bond enclosed a translation of the Ueimi 1926 Constitution, or 'Oragmlo Instructions'* or 'Fundamental Mules', as it is also sometimes styled# I have the honour to transmit herewith marked 'A', an amended translation which has now been made from an Arabic text of the Constitution ©ofmmmieated to this Legation by the Ministry of Foreign Affairs# 3# The first important change In the Constitution occurred on the 29th January 192V, when the Sultanate of Bejd and it© Dependencies was made a Kingdom and was formally united with the Belas under Ibn Sa f dd as King of the Belas and of Be|d and it© Dependencies# A translation of the text of the royal decree as published in the 'timm-al^ura' of the 8th April 192? is attached, marked '3% 4* In June 192? a Committee of Inspection and Improve ment was constituted by royal command* A translation of the i relevant extinct from the ^ura' of the let July is f attadied, marked 'C tt * 6 * HI© Malesty’s Principal Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs*0 On the 9th X9S7 and on the reoomendati on of thi© Committee, ^ticXes 28 to SI of Part XV of the ConotitBtion regarding the legislative Asaemhly, were modified# / translation of the amending regulation published in the ^Urnsv-aX-aura” of the 15th tlUly 1© attached, marked ”D«. Xn July 1928 thl© regulation was superseded by a similar regulation, which made no reference however to its L predecessor but only to Part IV of the Constitution# A translation of the text of the new regulation as published in the aura M of the 13th July 1928 is attached, marked 7* An undated regulation conceiving the Directorate- General of Finance and referring, by implication only, to Articles 20 to 82 of the constitution, was published in the w Um~&amp;l~Qura w of the 81st September 1928# a translation is , attached, marked W F% In October 1930 the Pilgrimage Committee, as defined by Article U of the Constitution, was modified by royal command# A translation of the text published in the tf Dmm-al-aura M of the 8th October 1950 is attached, marked w O rt # 9# In December 1930 a 'Ministry” of Foreign Affairs was established by royal command in place of the 'Directorate', with relation to but without reference to Article© 17 to 19 of the Constitution# a translation of the text published in the 'DEss-al- iura” of the 19th December 1930 is attached, marked 'H M * 10# In January 1958 a Council of Minister© was constituted by an undated decree published in the w I3mm-al^ura H of the 16th January, a translation of which was transmitted to rto you under cover of ay despatch No# 118 of the 5th March* This decree incidentally affected (1) Article 8 of the Constitution# modifying and defining the functions of the Viceroy’s Officej (2) Article 11# hy mentioning a new Mnistry# that of the Interior $ and (5) Article 2? of the Constitution, hy vesting the control of military affairs in the presidency of the Council instead of in the person of the King* A fifth member was added to the Council of Ministers by royal command published in the ,,T jmm-«a-,|ura” of the 11th March# a translation of which was -yi x \ transmitted to you In my printed letter Ho* 156 of the 19th March* ll« the text of the first national budget, presumed to apply only to the liejas however# was published in the rV^sra^ of the 16th January* a translation was transmitted to c8P*\ 0 ^ ^ you under cover of my despatch Ho* 36 of the 21st January* 12# there have certainly been many derogations in practice from the terms of the Constitution of 1926, and probably not a few modifications have been made constitutionally and published In some fora or another# but those enumerated above are afci that can now be precisely traced, in the absence of any official gaaette or other compendium# and with the assistance of the Hejasi Ministry of Foreign Affair®. The Under-Secretary for Foreign Affairs has stated in semi-official correspondence on the subject that Part XV of the Constitution has lapsed since the abolition of the post of Inspector-General# but he has been unable to indicate the date or exact nature of the modification* I would refer in conclusion to the comment made on the status of Astr in paragraph 5(b) of Sir A.Ryan’s despatch Ho*ISO of the 15th May 1931* I have the honour to be with the highest respect# Sir# Your Most obedient# humble Servant# w* m* MOPi* v Ihii*# j&amp;e\ ^1 &amp; «A% WMMXm* Had« in Octobea? 1929 1 mended in May 1932 from text coisnannicated by He^aaii Ministry of Foreign .affairs*) The following Regulation© were promulgated by a Royal Decree dated 2iet Safer 1345 (29th August 1926)# sm-i* .fee. ^msa^ss» Article 1 * The Kingdon of the Heims with its known boundaries is one and indivisible and cannot be divided or separated in any way* Article 2 * The Arabian Kingdom of the Bejas is a Royal (Malikiya) Legislative (Bhdriya), Moslem country, independent in all its Internal and foreign affairs# Article 3 * Mecca is the capital of the He^aa Kingdom* Article 4 * The Arabic language is the official language of the Kingdom# PART II* fffAgilvaLofeaAc&gt;a« Article 3 * The whole administration of the Kingdom of the Hejas shall be in the hands of HI© Majesty King ’Abdul 9 Aziz the First, Ibn ’Abdurrahman al Feysal Jll Sa’dd* His Majesty is bound by the Shar'fa law©* Article 6 * Judgement© in the Kingdom of the He jam shall be given according to the Qu’r&amp;n and the Bunmat of the prophet#Article 7» 1 Viceroy shall he appointed hy His Majesty, and as many directors and chiefs as are necessary for the administration of the Kingdom# Article 8# as the Viceroy 1 s Office Is the General Authority from which all Government Departments and the various sections of the administration depend, every director and chief of Department will he responsible to it for the proper conduct of affairs within his province# The Viceroy 1 © Office is responsible to His Majesty the King# tMUBBh gte. Affairs _oi' of the iigjas, . Article 9 # The Affairs of the Kingdom of the Hejas shall be divided into six fundamental ports, thus 5 - (l) Shar'fa Affairs. (s) Internal Affairs# (3) Foreign Affairs# (4) Financial Affairs* (5) Public Education# (6) Military Affairs# (1) Shar'ie ASi’aXra, Article 10* Shares Affairs comprise everything connected with the Shar'ta Judges, the two Holy Sanctuaries, Wakfs, Mosques, and all religious foundations. (2) Internal Afi&amp;tPB. Article 11. Internal Affairs comprise Public Secux^ity, Tele graphs, Posts, Public Health, Municipalities, Public Works, Commerce and Industry, Agriculture, Minerals and all private establishments. Internal Affairs in all their aspects shall be directly managed by the Viceroy's Office#Article ia » as the Vieero 2 r f 8 Offi&lt;« is responsible for the good adBinistretion of internal affairs, the Directors of the Depart ments of public Security, Telegraphs, Foots and Public Health must carry out their duties within the limits of the orders and regulations issued to them by the Viceroy’s Office# Article 13 # The Directors of the Municipalities will carry out their duties as prescribed in the regulations which will be promulgated in connection with the Municipalities and their organisation^# The Municipality of the Capital will be attached to the Department of Internal Affairs, and the other Municipalit ies will be attached to the senior local administrative official# Article 14 # The Pilgrimage Committee will, under the presidency of the Viceroy, consist of all the Chiefs of Departments connected with the pilgrimage and of a number of notables who will be nominated by Hie Majesty the King# Article 15 # The Pilgrimage Committee is fully authorised to examine everything in connection with the pilgrimage and pilgrims, to carry on every form of investigation and to take any measures which are necessary and desirable* Article 16 # All decisions made by the Pilgrimage Committee shall be enforced by the Viceroy after they have been sanctioned by his Majesty the King# (3) FOPet^a Affatm- . Article IV # Foreign Affairs comprise the proper execution of the foreign policy of the country# They will be divided into four sections; political, administrative, legal and consular* Article 13# The Administration of Foreign Affairs will be assigned by Ms Majesty the King to a person sufficiently compe tent and qualified to carry out its special duties* irticle 1 $ •( 6 ) Article .3.9 * The Directorate of Foreign Affairs will be directly connected with the Royal Residence, but it will carry out the orders of the Viceroy in connection with the administrative and consular sections* (.41... J-inmcia.. .Agfalgg. Article 00 * Financial Affairs comprise the organisation of the different revenues of the Kingdom and of its general ea&amp;enditure* They are subdivided m follows?- (a) Directorate of Finance# (b) Financial officec in the Dependencies# (c) Accountancy offices in those official departments which collect revenue* (d) Customs Administration# Article 2'U The Directorate of Fintince with its different branches mentioned above will be attached to the Office of the Viceroy# Article .SB* All finance officials are responsible according to their grade, for the proper iponduct and organisation of financial affairs. (Si PiAUs .SfeeaMoa # Article as* Public Education comprises the spreading of science, Education and the Arts and the opening of libraries, schools and educational Institutes; great care being given to the principles of the Moslem religion throughout the Kingdom of the Be^as# Article 84# Public Education shall be administered by a Direc torate attached to the Office of the Viceroy# Article 25 * a law for public education shall be decreed and shall be brought into force gradually# Elementary education shall be free throughout the Kingdom of the Ilajaa#0 aiMMi ,\rticXe.36# Military Affairs comprise everything which safeguard© the strength and prestige of the Kingdom both at home and abroad# Art!el®. 27# His Majesty the King will deal with everything concerning Military Affairs * MfflLmJSSfi i'V0 jr't- H The Legislative Assembly# The Council of Medina# The Council of Jedda# District Councils# Tribal and Tillage Councils# •aw x.erdulfctlv e .Asegntto Article 28 # A Council ©hall be formed in the Capital under the name of the 'Legislative Assembly” (Majlis ash-Ghdri) • This Assembly shall consist of the Viceroy, his Advisers and six notables# The latter must be able and competent persons and will be nominated by Hi© Majesty the King# Article 29 # The Legislative Assembly will meet once every week, or more often if necessary, under the presidency of the Viceroy or of one of his Advisers, in order to examine everything passed to them by the Viceroy’s Office and to discuss and confer thereon# Decisions will be taken according to the majority of vote©* Article SO# Heads of Department© will, whenever necessary, attend the meetings of the Legislative Assembly at the invitation of the Viceroy’s Office, and whenever anything concerning their Depart ments 1© being discussed# Article 51 # All decisions taken by the Assembly should be put into effect after they have been passed by His Majesty the King through the Viceroy and after their sanction by Hi© Majesty# AdalaletPatl-ge ■JAdpAnlp Native .CouRsy^. Article 32 # A Council shall be elected la Jedda md Medina respectively and ahall be called the °Administrative Council^# This Council will consist of the Governor * his Assis tant, the chief official© and four notables, the latter of whom will be chosen and nominated by Hi© Majesty the King* Article So* Each of the two Councils to be formed under the terms of the preceding article, will meet once a week or more often if necessary, under the presidency of the Governor or his Assistant, to examine affairs and matter© concerning each Council respectively, and to take decisions thereon according to the majority of vote© given* Article £4 * In accordance with Article 31 of these Regulations, all decision© taken by the two Councils above-mentioned will be passed to the Viceroy who will in turn pas© them to His Majesty the King for sanction* Once they are sanctioned by His Majesty the King, they must be put into effect* Article 38 * .All decision© and regulations after being sanctioned by liis Majesty the King and registered in the Royal Secretariat (Bfwtn) will be passed to the Viceroy’s Office which will put them into effect. The Viceroy 1 8 Office will notify all depart ments and sections of the Administration# Article 36* A© regards the notables chosen to sit in the Legis lative Assembly according to Article 8G, and those chosen for the Councils of Jedda and Medina, according to Article 32, their term of office will expire aftei* one year’s service, after which other members will be elected* Article 37 * Former members are eligible for re-election.Article 58 , A Council eliall be elected in every District under tiie presidency of the local Chief* These Councils will be com posed of the assistant to the Chief and the chief officials# together with certain notables# The Council will meet once a week or more often# Article gff# The function of the Councils to he formed under the terns of the preceding Article is to investigate and discuss any note© and official matters transmitted to the ©aid Council© by Sheykh© of the Districts# and to take decisions regarding them# Article 40 # Decision© taken by District Councils are to be trans mitted to the Governor (.lairsmaq.lm) of the Province# who in turn will pas© them to the Viceroy* The latter after noting his remarks upon them will submit them to the King for sanction# Once sanctioned by the King they will be put into effect# Tribal Article 41# In every village and in each important Tribe there shall be a Council under the presidency of its Sheykh# consisting of the Shar* £a representative and two notable©# to deal with questions of administration etc*, in accordance with the regulat ions which will be made for the organisation of provinces# Districts# Villages and Tribes# Article 43 * Village and tribal Councils are to be held responsible for everything within their respective jurisdictions before the higher authorities# according to the preceding article* m'LJL* A&amp;oc»mtft Qttkm* Article 43 # The Account© Office shall be formed in the Capital and) and shall consist of one president and three members who will be nominated by Hie Majesty the King* They will be chosen from among competent persons who are experts in accountancy and financial matters and they will be attached to the Office of the Viceroy* MtlCle. M* The primary function of the Accounts Office is to inspect all departments which bring in revenue and to control the general expenditure* according tojd the general budget regulations* Article 45 * Ho sums whatsoever are to be paid from the State Treasury before they have been approved by the Accounts Office* as is laid down in the special regulations, with the exception of sums the payment of which may be ordered by Ets Majesty the King* Article 46* The Inspectorate-General is charged with the inspec tion and control of aH Government Departments and all official transactions * in order to ensure the prox&gt;er conduct and organisa tion of affair®• Article 47* The Inspectorate-General shall be entrusted by His Majesty the King to a person of great efficiency and experience - — who will carry out special duties* Article 48* The Inspector-General will be directly attached to the doyal Residence* He shall carry out an inspection of the Districts when necessary* and shall appoint an Insr&gt;ector for each District if and when necessary* Article AO , The Incpector-G:%oral and the District Inspectors have the right to inspect all Government Departments* to investigate them and to control their affairs at any time* to stopJ stop axiy transaction uhlch imp be ccmtpary to the rule© and regulations* to suspend temporarily any offending official* and to ask for his trial by the Courts so that sentence may he passed and a complete investigation carried out# Article 50# The Inspector-Oener&amp;l has the right to ask for the replacement or the dismissal of any official who is proved to he incompetent and unfit for carrying out his work; this should he done by comunieating with the authorities concerned in the engagement and dismissal of officials* Article 51 * The Inspector-General must submit to His Majesty the King report© on the inspections and investigations he has carried out# Article S£3 f* District Inspectors will submit their reports to the Inspector-General * who in turn will submit them to His Majesty the King* Article 55* The District Inspectors will submit to the Inspec tor-General at the end of each month a report cm the state of affair© in their respective Districts; the Inspector-General after making his observations on each* will submit it to His Majesty the King* Article $4* All Head© of Departments are to render all necessar; assistance to the Inepeetor-General or the District Inspectors; they must also comply with any orders given by the Inspectors within the ©cope of the rules and regulations* Article 5b * Any official not complying with the preceding article* and whose failure to comply with it is proved* will be severely punished without regard to his grade or position# PART VII*&amp;&amp;&amp; aerabeirB of Councils and all Government eiayployees must possess the follcming qualifications t~ (1) ^hey should be subject© of Hi© Majesty the King* (2) They should be properly qualified and competent* (3) They should be of good character and of good address# (4) They should not have forfeited their legal Ghar’fa rights# Article 37# Persons not His Majesty 1 © subjects, whose employment is considered necessary, may be employed under contract for limited period© and under special conditions# Article 5ff # Any employees entering the service of the State under the term© of Article 56, have their rights and honour guaranteed by the State* 'Xc ■teticle 59* Mm es^loyee who show® efticiency and application in hi© work shall met be transferred to another Department without hi© consent* mm Wfi 110 whose/ innocmee of any charge brought against him is proved before a Court ©hall be dismissed from his employment* Article 6i* A ©pedal law shall be made regarding Government employees, setting forth the nature of their eiaployment,praaotion, salaries, rights, functions, grades, dismissal©, pensions, trial®, and everything in connection with the same* ,&amp;«gL MO* ag^ Aj^J?ipRl..Q.Q.MACilS * Article 6s* A Council slmll be formed in each of the municipali ties of Mecca, Medina, and Jedda, and ©Mil be called the M General’’General Municipal Council”• /irtlole 63* Its rae&amp;bers shall be landlords, membera of special crafts and professions which will be mentioned in the Municipal Regulations, and notables, who will be appointed by His Majesty the King or* Hi© Viceroy after their names have been put forward for membership of the General iimleipal Council. Article 64+ 1'he memberehip of persons elected for a General Municipal Council will not be considered valid except after the approval of Hi© Majesty the King* Article Go* The members of the General Municipal Council shall not exceed twelve in number in the Capital, sand eight in Medina and Jedda. Article 66 * Any person ibected as a member of a Municipal Council must be a subject of His Majesty the King, of not less than thirty years of age, and should be capable and competent jawaaoae, able to read and write Arabic well. He must be in possession of his legal and Shsr'fa righto and known to be of good conduct* /.rticls 6?* The General Municipal Councils will meet once every month, or more often if necessary, ftn&amp;er the presidency of one of the members, who will be elected at each sitting* ,,pticle 66. The General Municipal Councils have a full right to examine everything in connection with the Municipalities and to pass resolutions to ensure their good administration and order, Article 60 . The resolutions passed by the G eneral Municipal Council in the Capital should be transmitted to the Viceroy* b O ffice, while, in the case Of Jedda and Medina, they should be forwarded to the Office of the Governor, who after investigating them should submit them to the Office of the Viceroy# The latter in turn will submit them to the Legfctlative Assembly who after investigationinvestigation and endorsement will pass them to His Majesty the King through the Viceroy* Article 70 * the Directors of the Municipalities must act in accordance with the resolutions passed by the General Municipal Councils and approved by His Majesty the Klng 9 and should carefully comply with them* Article ri* the General Municipal Gmmctle have the right to draw up 9 modify or Increase when necessary, the municipal budgets They can do ©o after obtaining the approval of His Majesty the King as laid down in Article 69# Article 72 * A© the Directors of the Municipalities ©re respon sible to the General Municipal Councils, they should be prepared to answer in detail any enquiry or question put forward by the members in accordance with the regulation which will be drawn up regarding the organisation of the Mimicipalities# Article 73 * Members of the General Municipal Council© shall conform to the terms of the foregoing articles and. to those of the Regulation concerning Municipalities which Is to be issued* Article 74* The period of membership of the General Municipal Councils is three years, after which new election© must take place in accordance with Article 63* Article 73 * Former members are eligible for re-election* Article 76* Membership of the General Municipal Council is honorary* mLJ&amp; rwilclpaX Adalnlotration GoimL%iem . Article 77 * In every Municipality there shall be a Committee composed) oo^o©©a. of the Director of the Municipality ana other heads of its different sections# Article 78 # The function of these committees Is to investigate the ways and means for executing the resolutions passed fcy the General Municipal Councils, to examine carefully all papers and document© etc#, which are passed to them and to take whatever decisions are necessary# /j£tfcle 79 # Administrative cosaaittees should meet twice ©very week or more often if necessary# S5 Safer 1345#THAHS1UATX0H OF BXTRAOf FROll HO* 131 DATED 6th Shawwtl 1346 1 (8th 1027)* ,9L .iia praise and thanks he to Ood# Prayers and peace he upon the heat of hie creatures, liuhanmadj may God have Mercy on hi© family and friends* T the Grace of God t whftS ny T-ord and Father, HI© Majesty the ring, arrived at the capital of Nejd and Its dependencies, delegation© from all parts of the country came to Riy&amp;dh to meet him# A great meeting was held under the presidency of my tiord and Illustrious grandfather, the Xaftm , Abdurrahmfin, and it was decided In that meeting that the Sultanate of Hejd and its Dependencies should become a Kingdom under the name of w Kingdom of Kejd and Its Dependencies‘ , , thereby raising Its rank and placing It amongst powers end Kingdoms, so that it may take it© proper position amongst them and have a suitable place in the history of the Arab Moslem nation of which it is a part* The meeting declared. His Majesty my Lord and Father, ’Abdul ’Asia ibn 1 Abdurrahaln al Feysal 11 Ga’dd, King over it and submitted till© decision to His Majesty who agreed to their request and issued Hi© Royal Order a© follows *- *A® a result of the petition made to Us by those of Our 'subjects who have power to loose and to bind (i*e« ,the Chiefs 'and Authorities) in the Sultanate of llejd and its Dependencies '¥« have ordered that the Sultanate of Hejd end its Dependen ce! es shall become 'the Kingdom of Hejd and its Dependencies', 'and that Our title shall henceforward be 'King of the Heja© 'end of Hejd and its Depejidencies'* We pray that God may 'grant U® success and help in Our endeavours to fulfil tills task*of Helpers’ 1 # * Abdul King of the He^az aiid of and its Bopendencieo* X therefore stand amongst you declaring that news, and I praise God and thank Him for His help and favour and I ask Him to help Islam and Moslems and Assist His Majesty in uplifting the Islamic and Arab World# God is the best Helper and we leave everything in His hands* 2nd Bhawtl 1345. 'task* He is the best 25 th Ha jab 1345* 29th January 1927# 4th April 1927**0% mHSLATIQB OF EXTRACT FHOH *02£t-AL~ lURA^ HO.X33 BASED 1st miharrarn 1346, (1st July 1927)# We have received the following from the Viceroy’s Officet- His Majesty the King, sealous in the interests of the Hejaai nation and persistent in his efforts to afford comfort to pilgrims, has issued his gracious command for the formation of a Committee called 'Committee of Inspection and Improvement* which will concern itself with the following*~ 1# The investigation of all complaints which may he raised against any Government Department or any Official in those Departments* 2# The study of the general administrative state (7 of the country with a view to deciding what has Been proved good by e^erience, and to Improve whatever needs improvement* The Committee is ready to Investigate any complaint, general or particular, or any beneficial suggestions and to adopt any intelligent ideas tending to Increase the happiness and welfare of the country and the nation* All communications should be addressed to the Committee of Inspection and Improvement, Jlyid Barracks*8 * © lol *D'» THAHBLATIOH OF BXTJiACT FSOM 'OMH-AI^iOaA' K0.13S DATSD 15«i ?athari&gt;«a 1346, (ISth *Oy 192?)* conoernlng Ahe LeAslatlve ;,s B ecbIy » ’AMttl 'assIz ®bn AbdurrahaSn al Foysal Xl Sa'Hd, after taking cognisance of the fourth part of the Organic Instructions and of Our orders issued at the beginning of Muh&amp;rrm concerning the formation of a Committee for Inspection and Improvement, and as a result of the petition submitted to Us by the said Committee have issued the following orders Article !• The Legislative Assembly shall be formed of eight Members to be selected in accordance with the rules mentioned In the following articles# Article 2,« The President of the Legislative Assembly is the Viceroy and he may bring with Mm to the meeting© one of Mo Mvieers, but that Adviser will not take part in the discussions# In the absence of the President either Ms assistant or one of Ms Advisers win preside over the Assembly* Article £# The election (sic) of limbers of the legislative Assembly shall be a© follow© s- 1* Pour member© shall be selected by the Government after con sultation with mm of excellence and experience* 8# Four member© shall be appointed by the Government without consultation and two of these member© ©hall be Heidis# article 4* The period of membersMp of the Legislative Assembly is two years, and half the member© (whether selected or appointed)shall be changed each year* Members are eligible for re-election on the expiration of their period of membership* Article 5 * Members of the Legislative Aasexably have to fulfil the following conditions:- 1* They must be over flK year© old*53* They mat he men of experience and knowledge* 5* They must not have had any legal sentence passed on them smirching their honour* and they must not he bankrupt* 4* They shall he of good conduct* The following will he referred to the Assembly by the Government* a* Budgets of Government De^artsiexits * the iiunicipality and ,,1f Ain Suheyda’ 1 * h* Licenses for economic schemes and schemes of development* c* Concessions and oconmXc and financial schemes. d* Expropriations for public utility* e* Introduction of laws and regulations* f* Increase in budgets of Departments during the year# g# Unforeseen expenditure in Government Departments amounting to more than £100 and arising during the course of the year* h* Decisions concerning the employment of foreign employees* U Contracts with companies and merchant© for the purchase or if sale of Government materials hit exceeding £M0* Article 7 * The Assembly shall be divided into two Committees* each of which will study the subjects referred to it by the Secretary of the Assesbly and give its views thereon* then the Cosamittee will exchange the papers in their possession and the result will be submitted to a general meeting of the Assembly for final decision* Article ::* Four members dad the ;&gt;rosidcat will constitute a a two-thirds majority of votes is necessary for the taking of a decision* Article 9* The Assembly ©hall meet twice each week, for ordinary meetings; it may meet more often at She invitation of the President* whenever necessary* The two Committees may meet at time© other than those appointed for a meeting of the Assembly* Article 10* The Assembly may draw the attention of the Government to anyany error in the appiieation of the Laws and Regulation©* . M.cie 11 * If the Government present a scheme to the /yssenhly which rejects or modifies it and the Government do not concur In its action, the Viceroy ha© the right to return the scheme to the Assefnbly with m ©Kplanation adequate to satlcfy the Assembly of the true intention of the Government and of the necessity for the Assembly changing ito decision* If the Assembly still refuses and maintains its former amsndnenta, it will be for His Majesty the King to take the final decision in the matt a?* The Assembly will also refer to His Majesty, through its President, for his approval, any scheme decided by it where one month has elapsed without the issue by decree of the Royal assent* Article ,lg* The Chief of a Department must be invited to attend any meeting of the Assembly when a matter relating to that Department is under discussion by the Assembly* This rule should always be followed# Article. M * A capable secretary is to be appointed for the Legislative Assembly for the organisation and arrangement of the work of the Assembly* He shall receive and classify the papers j prepare the agenda for each meeting and inform the Members of the Assembly of it at least one day before the meeting# In addition the Assembly ©hall have one or two clerks as may be necessary# Article 14 * The King hm the right to dissolve the Assembly or to change its Member© or to diemie© them* Article 15 * These decisions are to take the place of the fourth part of the Organic Instructions relating to the Legislative Assembly# Given on the 9th ifuharram 1346* 9th July 19g?#TKM,, ,A?iO!4 Y KXtliACT FROM. m. 106 IFMI&gt; mth 1547 ( 13th 4uly 19*8 )♦ the Legislative Atustsmbly ill be com»titut©d of the number of to bo limited by royal decree* fhe .'. resident of the ^gislativo Assembiy is the Viceroy. A permanent reprosontativo of the Viceroy will b# appointed by nis Majesty# Another representative will bo chosen by the Assembly to act in the absence of tne first representative* Legislative Asaeably will be two years* Article 4 * Leaders in the Legislative Assembly .*ust fulfil the following conditions. (a) Be xiot less than twenty five years of age* ( b) ba men of experience and Knowledge* (c) ..*Qt have been condemned for any alshonouring thing &gt;md not bankrupt* (d) Of good conduct. article b * The fo lowing will be referred to the Assembly by the Ooverx^anti (») budgets of Oovernmcat departments, of the Municipality ana of * Ain Lubeyda”. (b) licences for economic schemes and schemes of aevelopmunt* (c) Concessions and economic and financial schemes. (a) Lxpronri.'.tione for public utility. (e) Drawing up of laws and regulations* (f) Increases in budgets of departments during the year / :&lt; r t i c le i a . The period of membership of the -b— _____Cg} Unfortssti^n experidilure in Qoy^vtmunt Cicpar‘taants amounting to oora than ona iian4red pouiids and arising during the course of the year. (h Decisions concerning the employment of foreign employees. «i} Contracts with companies or merchants for the purchase or sale of things required by Government departments (sic) if exceeding two huisired pounds. Article 6. The Assembly will be biviued into two committees t each of which will study the subjects referred to it by the President and submit its reoommendmtions to h general meeting of the Assembly for final aecision. Article 7 . Two thirds of the members of the ■Assembly together with the , resident will constitute a quorum and decisions will be maue according to the majority of the votes of those present. Article 6. The Assembly will meet daily to consider the questions laid before it. Article 9. The Assembly is to draw the attention of the Government to any lapse in the application of the laws and regulations submit ted (to it). Article 10. if the Government present a scheme to the Assembly, which the latter rejects or snodifiea, and the Government do not concur in its action, the Viceroy has the right to return the scheme to the Assembly with an observation adequate to satisfy the Assembly of the true intention of the Government and of the necessity tor the Assembly to change its decision* If the Assembly still refuses and maintains its former amsiidaenas, it will remain for ills Aajeaty the rang to ta,»e the final use 1 b ion in the matter. The Assembly will aluo refer to I Majesty through its l’resident for his approval s tg rthsmt decided by ot where two months have elapsed without tne issueiSBUiJ toy uecrets of the coa^cnt, article i:u The chief of the department or his z*epreeenta11 ve mmt be invited to attend any meeting Of the AsaesTbly when a matter relating to that departtuent ia under dlacuaelon toy the Ass#«ttoly« This rule «h- old always be followed* ar ticle 1&amp; - A capable secretary for the Legislative Aaseatoly 1 b to toe appointed for organising the clerical work end receiving, arranging, Bumiaaristog and eistrltouting, at least one day before the meeting la held, the agenda era n up toy the ^roaident for each meeting. Clerks will toe appointed for the -ssuimbly as necessary. Article , 1b. The ding has the right to dissolve the Assembly or to change any one of its members at any ti«e. arti c le 14. *di»l©«a are to vc-placs the section of the fourth division of the fundamental rules relating to the Legislative Aaaeiably.TRANSLAfflOH OjP SXTRACi; PROM 'TJUM-AL-QORA' Ho. 195 BASED m Kabf* 11, 1347, (21st September 1928). ^ igafeiAffl ^osss^m i&amp;s.m£ssS2zsis=SSBss&amp;s£. mm (Reference Articles 20,31, &amp; 32 of the Constitution). Article 1 . The Directorate-General of Finance (Vafctlat al Mfillya al ’AaaJ in the capital is the general authority in control of the Finance Offices of the Kingdom of the Hejass. Article 2* The seat of the Directorate-General of Finance is Mecca, the capital of the Hejaa* Article 3 # The Directorate-General of Finance is divided into two branches, the Directorate-General of Finance (Mu&amp;iriya If&amp;liya) in the capital and the Chief Finance office (Hatsat al Amwil) in Jedda* f. Aticle 4 » The ©eat of the Directorate of Finance is Mecca; to it are attached Ttif and all the revenue departments of the capital# The Chief Finance Office at Jedda supervise© the Finance Offices at Medina, Yaribu*, Al Wejh, Rtbegh and Al Utth* Article 5 # The Finance Offices at Tabdk and Al t Ula are subordinate for all purposes, to the Finance Office at Dhabd, while the Finance Office at Dhabd is subordinate, for all purposes, to the Finance Office at Al Wejh* Article 6 # The Finance Of lice at Umm is subordinate for all purposes to the Finance Office at Yaribu f • Article 7 # The Directorate-General of Finance, in it© capacity a© the sole authority in charge of the Finance Offices and Accountancy Office© attached to it and responsible to it, is composed of two parts viss- A# A clerical office (Qalan Takrfrdt), which i© responsible for all work in connection with Financial Communications and news* B# An Accountancy Office (i)fwdn Kuh&amp;aab&amp;t) which is responsible for all accounts in the capital and in Jedda and its dependent Offices# It shall keep a register of all the districts and a budget( 6 ) budget register to control separately the accounts of all depart ments and their dependencies with a view to checking the revenues* It shall be responsible for checking the monthly revenues of all Departments and for ensuring that the payments due to the Treasury are duly made* It shall eomment on any increase or decrease in revenue, giving reasons, and it ©hall present to the Directorate- General of Finance a monthly report on the Government revenues* rticle 8 * Revenue and Sa^enOlture. (1) All Departments which collect Government revenues must forward their monthly takings during the month to the local Finance Officej w ether in the capital or in the provinces, as is necessary* , These Departments are*- Customs; Quarantine; Telegraphs; Post©; ^ Excise (Tafarfjfa); Harbours; Passport Offices; notaries Public; Beyt al Mil; Offices for licensing cars; Stamp issuing Offices; Condensers, and so on* (g) The Auqif Administrations are dependant, in their financial transactions, on the Finance Office* They cannot spend money from their funds without a decision of the Auq&amp;f Committee, nor before obtaining sanction for the expenditure* They should for ward to the Finance Office their accounts each month* The Finance Offices have the right of controlling these Administrat ions (Auq#f) at any time* ( 3 ) The expenditure of the Auq&amp;f Administrations at Mecca, the salaries of the servants and teachers in the Holy Moeque and other Mosques, and any expenditure concerning Auqaf will be met from the Treasury of the Auqaf administration at Mecca. (4) The expenditure of the Auq&amp;f administration at Medina, the salaries of the servants and teachers in the prophet’s mosque and other mosques there, and all expenditure concerning Auqif, will be met from the treasury of the Auqaf administration at Medina* (5) The expenditure of each Auqftf administration in the provin ces, the salaries of servants and teachers in the mosques, and all expenditure concerning Auq&amp;f will be met from the relevant Auqllf treasury*(6) If a deficiency occurs in the Auq&amp;f treasury in Mecca 9 or in any Auq&amp;f treasury in the provinces, the Finance Department will meet the deficiency and regard the money so spent as a loan to the Auq&amp;f* (?) Hone of the Departments which collect revenue have the right to spend any sum whatsoever for any purpose whatsoever from their treasuries* If they stand in need of any necessary expenditure they must apply to the Finance Office for sanction in accordance with the|tr ‘budgetary allowances* Article 9 * Orders given hy the Viceroy sanctioning expenditure are of two kinds vlsst- (1) Orders given for the expenditure of monies, which the Finance Department must put Into effect, and (2) Orders referred to the Finance Department for necessary action, payment on which should not he made without investigat ion and further reference to the Viceroy’s Office* Article 10 * Should any Departments submit to the Finance Office a list of expenditure some of which is included in the budget and some of which is not, the Finance Office^ shall meet the former expenditure hut shall refuse to meet the latter until it receives an order to do so* Article 11 * Verbal orders given by Kis Majesty the King will be confirmed In writing by the Royal Dlw&amp;a to the Department con cerned and to the superior authority from which that Department depends* Article 1,^ * The Directorate-General of Finance has the right to control the Municipalities, from the financial point of view, wherever necessary* Article IS * All Departments which collect revenue must submit to the Finance Office, in the first week of each month, a detailed account of the previous month’s expenditure, giving an explana tion of their income under different heads* The Finance Office will control this account, checking it against the instructions Issued concerning it* Article 14 * All Departments which collect revenue must collect that revenuerevenue when It Tails due 9 without more delay than le necessary for the collection of the taxes# The responsibility for tills rests with the Director ofn the Finance Office concerned# Ho* * Article 15# SHK exemption froa taxes such as Customs, excise, passport fees etc#, is permitted except in cases sanctioned by His Majesty the King or ills Viceroy* Article 16* The Finance Administration and all other administrations shall draw up a list of exemptions that have been sanctioned so that the competent authorities may be informed of them# Article 17 * Taxes which have been imposed in accordance with instruc tions given cannot be increased or decreased without a Eoyal order* No new taxes or dues can be imposed without a Royal order* Article 13 * Any merchandise may be imported into or exported from the Hejas except articles the import or export of which has been prohibited by His Majesty the King or his Viceroy# Article 10 * Should a diminution occur in the takings of any Department which collects revenue, the Direetorate-ueneral of Finance must present to the Viceroy’s Office a report explaining what steps should be taken to stop the diminution, so that the Viceroy’s Office may issue instructions as to v/hat should be done# Article SO * The method of receiving payment of revenue or of meeting expenditure must be in accordance with the Hejaz-Hejd Coinage Regulation (23A/2B)# /irticle 21 # Government Departments depending from the Finance Adminis tration which are allowed to contract (with private individuals) for Government purpose© (lltis&amp;m), must put the contracts up to auction each year so that tenders may be made in accordance with the regulations which will be made later# Article 32# The Directorate-General of Finance shall appoint at the beginning of each year a special committee to consider the ren ting of Government property, necessary repairs and Alterations, Article 23* The Finance Office© must control the takings of all Departments collecting revenue, and check their income and accountancy so as to safeguard the rights of the Treasury# EachBach Finance Official Is responsible for carrying out his work In accordance with the Instructions given to him “by his superiors* The Directorate-General of Finance must issue the necessary instruc- ' J tions to coordinate financial procedure in all Departments* Article Ho Department which collects revenue and is subordinate in It© general financial transactions to the local Finance Officer may communicate with any other Department on financial Question© except through its superior authority* Article 25 * The Directorate-General of Finance shall make a supplementary regulation concerning stamps* explaining what financial transactions are exempt from stamp duty* .Artl,.cle,„M» The Directorate-General of Finance will issue a regulation dealing with public auctions and tenders* Article 37 * The Directorate-General of Finance will issue a regulation dealing with Government purchases* Article All Government officials in all posts shall give help when necessary to the Finance officials in the collection of Government revenues* Article 29 , Bxpenditure will be divided into three classesi- (1) Sanctioned expenditure, such as salaries sanctioned in the budget* which is to be paid by the Finance Office each month in accordance with the sanction* (2) Allowances specified in the Budget for special purposes* which will be paid by the Finance office at the recxuest of the Department concerned* Should a difference arise between the Finance Office and the Department concerned as to whether the payment should be made or not, the matter shall be referred to the Viceroy*© Office for settlement and for a decision as to whether the payment should be made or not* (3) Extraordinary Expenditure* which is not to be met without an order from Hi© Majesty the King or the Viceroy* Article 30 * If it ie found necessary to imur urgent expenditure before sanction has been obtained from the competent authorities* the Finance Officials may lend the local Governors (al Hu3$kim al fdfiriyyin) _ v , m ,td&amp;riyyln) a sum not exceeding the latter’s salary f whereupon they (the local Governors) must immediately obtain sanction fr&lt;aa their superior authority* tt sanction is not given,the bum advanced will be deducted from their salary* Article 51# Finance Officials not in telegraphic communication with the central authority who are faced with the necessity of spending a sum before recefrving sanction for it, may pay the sum provided it does not exceed the amount of theii 11 monthly salary* If sanction is not obtained from their superior authority f the sum expended will be deducted from their salary* Article Departments which collect revenue are not entitled to pay the salaries of their employees out of their treasury* Yhey met hand over those funds to the Finance Office and will receive their salaries and allowances from it in the same manner as Departments which do not collect revenue* Article The Viceroy’s Office will inform the Directorate-General of Finance of any appointments dismissals or transfers of emp loyees so that the relevant dates may be registered* article 34 * Funds remainding in the hands of the Municipalities after budgetary sanctions and other necessary expenditure have been met will be deposited at the end of each year in the treasury of the Finance Office* Article 3.Q * Necessary repair® and reparations to Government houses* buildings and Auq&amp;f shall be put up to public tender so that those who wish may undertake them according to the conditions and regulations laid down* Article The Directorate-General of Finance must construct two ©tores, one at Mecca and one at Eedda, for keeping all Govern ment property* Bach of them shall be under the care of a specially appointed official who shall keep a register of all articles taken from and put into the store, so as to safeguard the rights of the Treasury* Article 37* Contracts mad© for supplying the Government with articles from abroad or for undertaking repair© etc*, must be effected throughthrough a special Committee selected the Directorate-General of Finance and appointed by the Viceroy(s Office* The Comiaitt- ee 1 © principal ©eat will he in Jedda f and It will he established and will function in accordance with a special regulation to he issued for the purpose* Departments must submit their budgets to the Directorate- General of Finance so that they may be studied and checked as a whole by the budget Committee; they must be forwarded to the viceroy’s office for necessary action at least two months before the end of the financial year* mm® illicit* luvery finance official who has in his charge Government iunds/* or valuable articles must give a guarantee in money, or must get someone to give a guarantee, in proportion to the amount# in hie charge for which he is responsible* ,4fi* verbal of telegraphic orders sanctioning expenditure are not valid unless confirmed by an official comuni cation in writing*nr* mABSLATIOB OF MEACT FEOM HO* 32.5 BATED the 29th Hajah* 1349 (191^ Dsceaber 1930)* Organisation of the Ministry of Foreign Affairs# A. High Royal Oomnend ha© teen issued changing the title n directorate of Foreign Affairsto t+ Ministry of Foreign Affairs” and appointing HI© Royal Highness the mtv Feysal, Viceroy of His Majeety the King# to the post of Minister in addition to that of Viceroy# and appointing Fuad Hfltrafla as Hnder-Secretary for Foreign Affairs m froa Tuesday the 26th Rajah 1349 (16th Beoemher 1930)# (Reference Articles 17, 13, and 19 of the Constitution#)COPY OF iOVY Ho. 36. (E 366/165/85) j J- Rttarjr Slot, IPS'’. 811* IItli z^t&amp;ronm to despatch Ho# 432 of Scomber SB, I hfive tae honour to olato that the Um-f:l-S;urr of Janttary 18 published the text of wh-t purporte to he a budget for the lunar year beginning HIid ♦bfn 1,1350, 1#©# Deoe^tber 11, li: ; 81# I enclose a translation of the finance law and attached ststenant, as pubilcdied# It will be observed tlie.t there lo c- discrepancy of Piastres miri 486,458 between the Items and the tot-1 shorn* 5:h *Phe publication of this enactment met be regarded m a distinct advance# She budget is nevertheless merely m estimate of expand!toe under various heads* It is assumed that iv venue will be r vailablo to meet this exuen- ditirre hut no attempt ir made to ©atimet© the- anticipated revenue from varlor.® sources* It is not stated whether the budget ap/llcm to the He^as or to the whole of Ibn Sa’ud’s doiainions* 5# I had mm conversation regarding the budget with Fu.r-.a Bey llaasa on January 19, when I wm discussing the position in regard to certain Bi^itleh cl; to* I congratulated hira in tlie stop forward m&amp;,c by hi;. Government. 1 observed that, while the i mount ©; .r~mr.rk©&amp; for the pigment o:f debts did not appear to be eau of the to to, m we had boon led tc expect, it was nevertheless a embat- ntlal sum, vis*, £ gold 150,000 on the assumption thrt Piartren JClri meant gold His Majesty 1 © Principal Secretary of State for foreign Affairs*gold ptmt&amp;m nt the rate of 110 to the g gold. He had told ?ae Inaidc ntally the previous eveniiig that the aoverment 3mew exn-..:tly the emo mt of their liahilitie© up t° the hog inning of the financial I otiggeeted that as they were in this happy position rnd had now er.*remarked a definite som f which they preenmhly knew would he availahle, loi' p. ying off the dehta # they should he in ® position to give concrete indications to their creditors of tlie Inst Imcnta which they intended to pay and the dates on which payment mi^ht ho eapeeted* 4 * Bey explained that the amount ear-marked for dcoto iiore in reality e greater proportion to anticipated receipts than would appear, fixoh of the e^ependiture shown in W I iaetreo f'lri' would in fact he inmirred in silver* Otherwise, he aefnitted, the budget would not balance at all. *S'ic 10, f&gt;0Q f 000 plant res miri alloei ted to debt wore, however, gold pies tree m x had supine ed* T refrained from contient on the singularity of a budget which lumpa -lastree 'Iri whether gold or silver in a single statement, at r tine when the Government have practice 1 the pretence that Oliver riyele are still at the old legal parity of 10 to the £ gold* &amp;• ''ey seemed to have no illusions r-c to the uncertainty of the revenue prospects . I mm mainly concer ned with the operation of the moratorium implied in the decision to treat all debts up to the beginning: of the fimmt l year as a floating debt to be paid off by instalments, ihen X pursued this topic, he told me quite cheerfully that. If things went badly, the Government would be umble to pay nnd would have to go on from one moratorium to\}l to roiothor# He suggested that after all# If mnoy did not come In# It would he owing to mnntm for which the Oovexm«mt had bo reeporus# nmmlng no douht that reveme must depend on the volune of the pilgrimage, which would he determined hg erUBOB 'beyond the control of the Oovemment* 6* -fhere is much to he a aid for JOind Bey* a point of view d$&amp;pite Its apparent levity* I fear# however# that the public. 1 tion of this eo-ealled budget# although interesting m m indicia tion of the wish of the Government to put their house in order# will ir vo little effect on the practical fin nee of this country for the coming year# ?# I am sending copies of this despatch md enclosures to the Departiaent of overseas iVedo# the Seorot.r-&gt;ry to the aovemont of India in the Foreign and Politics,1 Pepartsont His i-alosty’c ■ High Gamisaioners at Bagdad and Jemsalem air:. Ills jostle Political Resident in the Persian Gulf* 1 have da*# (Signed) Andrew Ryan*: ViwmA'nai: of pbo no.3?s dateb lamary 15th, imtu (7/®/l&amp;m), Budget Pegul^tton. fox* tiia flnr-ncir’l y©nr eoTOoneing froia 1st ■^'Wn 1550 and ending on 30th T&amp;. joh 1340 (aio ? 1351)* A High Xiecroe h^a just ‘been issued sanctioning Uw Qmertmtmt budget negui&amp;tion fox 1 ' the iinenoi^. 1 wlxioh ooBssoncee iron 1st Bhrdfctn 1350 ee follows!- 1* ’fhe iundn specified for Government Departments for the fin' no ini ye r beginning from 1st She f bin 1550 nd ending ^Qtii kiij&amp;b 1351 9 rc mentioned in the attooheo- lists amount to 100,44s, 1344 Piastres ’i iri. 2*. f £he f revenuor. of the Government for the present yer^r mentioned In Article X and in the et : ; §d list® also amount to 106,44*3,§44 Piastres v iri. 3* There mat be strict complifoioe witli all the orders-, acts and fixr nclrl j*cgalationa in force regarding the 10. mu' 1 reduction of salaries end the 50$ reduction of some of the annual 4. There aasat be strict compliance with nil orders acts and financial regulations regarding the method followed in the past of paying out, receiving, entering, recording, affixing of at' mpe and keeping end checking of aeocunts* 5. Tliere suet be strict compliance with the decision of the Council of' i ini®tore Bo. 3 dated 21/^/1350 regarding the enforcement of tlm budget regulations for the present financial year* 6* The Finis try of Finance, the Director-General of the Treasury anw the Herdo of the* competent Departnents are authorised to put into effect the provision© of this regulation, each in v/fcrt concerns him. The . irJLster or Finance mat prepare the final accounts- and submit them at the end of the financial year in their final tom*© I ‘5) ^tfeHSIilglOri 0? Jliaci ' FHOLl Ui&gt;M-AL-(,PiU, 110.054 of 25/9/31 (12/5/1350). The Eighth Year . Praise be to Gcd. Prayer and Peace be upon Muhammad the gracious prophet who was sent a precursor to the world. Last week was the end of the seventh year since the establishment of ,T Umm-sl-Qura ,f , and we now receive the eighth year with effect from today's issue. We praise and thank God for the help and blessings He has bestowed on us for the service of the religion of Islam and this safe country. He granted us this precious opportunity with a view to enabling us to proclaim the realities of the religion and the secrets of this innocent case, which is the adherence to the belief of the good ancestors. ,T Umm-al-$ura'’ was the best means of proclaiming these realities, since they were surrounded by fences of lies and delusion. We thank God for the satisfactory results of our endeavours, so that the world has become aware of the realities of the case of the ancestors' belief, which is in accordance with the Holy Boom and the traditions of His Prophet. The truth appeared and the lie died. This is our line of action since the first number of 'Umra- al-Qura' was issued and we will continue it. The seventh year of 'Umm-sl-Qura' has expired. It was full of the various schemes which were carried out oy the Government of His Majesty the King in the Holy land, in spite of the economic crises all over the world. The first of all the functions which were carried out by the Government was to make Treaties of friendship with s o me /some of the other Governments, the recognition by the United States of America of the Kingdom of Hejez- Nejd and its Dependencies, and the establishment of two Legations, one in Holland and the other in Iraq, of a Consulate in Java and other diplomatic matters -which may strengthen the friendly relations between this country and other countries. The cession by As-Sayid at Hasan at Idrisi of Asir to His Majesty the King also took place in that year end the former’s territory has become one of the countries of His Majesty the King. The assembly of the National Conference was one of the important functions. It was assembled in Mecca during that year and will be held at the beginning of every year in accordance with the order of His Majesty the King, with a view to enabling the Government to understand the needs of the nation. The conference carried out the task which was laid upon its shoulders and enacted several decisions, the majority of which were put into force, while others are still under discussion. The Government paid special attention to the matter of facilities for Muslim visitors to the Holy Mosque and made many improvements which will greatly comfort the pilgrims. The Government also established telegraphic communications, a school for wireless training in Jedda, for which a mission was sent to England for training, and brought fifteen wireless machines which they have attempted to erect in the main stations in the Kingdom, so that the country will be linked with the means of communication the advantages of whichmm—mmcannot be denied &gt; &gt; 3 The Government brought a geologist who examined certain places and the result was hopeful; they made , a contract with this engineer with a view to bringing e 9 assistants and machines for the purpose of producing these treasures which are still buried, digging artesian wells for irrigation and other important economical matters which will be of great advantage to this country. The Government issued several regulations to various departments, so as to put this work under a proper system, and for other public affairs which will cause comfort to the nation. This is but a brief word i n the improvements which were completed in the last year. ;/e now receive the new year and the Government have other schemes for improvements which will take effect shortly, if God be willing. If the reader follows the news of the improvenaents which have been completed in the time of His Majesty the Ming, year after year, he will find that the country is on its way to success and prosperity and that it will reach one day, by the blessings of God and the favours of His Majesty the Ming, the objective of progress and prosperity to which Muslims and Mrabs incline.In any further communication on this subject, please quote No. and address- “The Under-Secretary of State,” FoMign Office, London, S.W. r. communication on this subject, please quoi *&gt;• v3^19) s —not to any person by name, but to—- 4^; ni&gt;- 701 ( (930 I y/sM rf A J k THE*^lmcler-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his m compliments to -secretary oi acate lor roreign Anairs preseribs ms ^ \t A e j,Kdia and, by direction of the Secretary of State, % # transmits herewith cop| jy, of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, ~JJdtJV€w.iafiY 1930'. Reference to previous correspondence : X il/' [) vO&amp; mm.* October 18 .h, 1930* r&lt;&amp; Sir, ffee ur&amp; rt of October 3rd &gt; ttbllsbet a smtaary of %b&amp; Eolaa-MoJA QoTornaent *8 acMowiaont® daring the ?a«t twelvo monthe which I think it maj bo useful to record briefly, if somwhat literally* as follows; i. mm&gt;xm (1) fhe ^CBtablishsaent of olitical contact^ with Germany, Poland, Persia, and Afghanistan, i.e. the recognition of the leJajs-HcJd Oorermaent. (3) fhe conclusion of treaties with Qermany, Turkey, and Persia* (g) The meting of king Ibn aa'ud with king Faisal in the Persian Gulf which laid the foundations of a settle ment of past difficulties between this country and Iraq and onens up a hopeful view of the future. (4) The raising by Foreign Powers of the rank of their representatives at dedda to that of Minister. (6) The establishment of a Hejas-Nejd legation In iondon. ii. iKMEafic (1) Hoyal opening of the new legislative Council. {2} Defeat of rebels, restoration of complete internal order, and reorganisation of the Police* (3) Reformation of Government .Departments and constitution of an Inspectorate of Departments* (4) Improvements of facilities for pilgrims and constitution of a Pilgrimage Committee. (&amp;) Increase in the number of schools and of scholars sent to study in Egypt. (6) Establishment of a Government Motor repair shoo and of the 'Xlswa** carpet factory at Mecca* ( 7 ) importation by Government of well machinery which has encouraged private individuals to follow suit* (8) Publication and free distribution of a work on agriculture written b a. prominent Medina land owner* ( 9 ) lie Majesty*8 Principal secretary of State for Foreign Affairs*. COPT. (1 8981/4309/91) Mg 387*(9) organisation, of the army end ? arch see of aeroplane e and mm war material* (10) Organisation of a motor oatal sorvica, erection of new telephone lines, preparation of scheme, of wireless comarU cation* (11) Batifloation of agreemento concluded at the London foetal Congress of 19E9. . (12) Construction of new reeerToire at Mecca and repair of ' existing system at a in ^ubaida, so that water for pilgrims is now plentiful* (12) Street-widening at Muna, road repairs on the &lt;aain pilgrim routes* and introduction municipalitlea ef motor sprinklers for the streets and of fire engines* (14) Decision to establish up to date slaughter houses. (15) Constitution of an Improvements Committee to study electric light, water and mineral development* (16) Introduction of modern hosrital a? liances of all hinds and despatch to Barone of two doctors to study X-rays and bacteriology. (17) Establishment of a hospital at Bahra and orders for more elsewhere, introduction of motor unbalances, and printing said distribution of pmmphlsts containing medical*advice in the different pilgrim languages. (18) Survey of the Median-*. 1 tfla, Medina-*adi Slrhan, and Me cea-Xhuralba roads - not an imposing catalogue of national achievement but an indication that the will to improve exists even though the means arc still woefully lashing - or misused* I have, etc., (Signed) 0.0. HOm 01Lh.In any further commuijication on this subject, please quote no. M and address —not to any 'person by name, but ter “The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. i. 7 i i b 1 THE UJjP^Seoretary of State for Foreign Affairs j&gt;ref compliments to \ and, by direction of the Secretary of State, ^ transmits herewith copat of the under-mentioned paper. ^ A ^ Foreign Office, IJ 4, 0 t^iobcv , igaD'. Reference to previous correspondence L^XC r, z A^7|^i39l9l 4 l ^ s Sf h &gt;*vj r Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. ty&amp;V\. it-K H 4 &gt; 62-4 ov Similar letter sent to JO 14—*1388 B ( 2 )Ho. 26t« SlF, XEDim. iiaXWlf, 1930. The of September 6 isublished a leMlng article explaining how individual coraplaint© ®ay he suoraitted to Ihn Ga*u&amp;* It throws an interesting side-light m his rule# 2# The editor affirm© that no complaint addressed to I!is majesty 1© neglected, whether it in volve© hundreds of thousands of pound© or only twopence- halfpenny. Vlhoever ha© a complaint to make may either adilras© the King hy post or telegraph or hand a letter to his Chamberlain at the Palace or ©eek an audience of Hi© * ajesty, which will he given, or present his petition in person if he happens to see Ion 3a*ud In the street* every r&gt;etition sent to the King is read by Mm, headed to hi© Diwan for registry and report, and returned to him for hi® dec!®ion. He may then refer it to the Sharia Court or to the Viceroy for further enquiries but ho eventually delivers hi© own judgment. The hour© of 7-50 to 9 a.m* are set apart for hi© people 1 s petitions. 3. The article conclude© by contrasting the general rule of Rings and potentate®, who are surrounded by courtiers whom it i© necessary to flatter and cajole, with the ywemml rule of Ring Abdul AM©, who keeps his official® in their proper place. 1 have the honour to be with the highest x*espeet. Hi© lajcsty*® Prinei;pal secretary of State for Forslim Affairs* air, Tour moat obedient, humble Servant, c.s.hopi aiu,.Notes. Minute Paper. Register No. SECRET. POLITICAL DEPARTMENT. Dated Rec. 19 Date. Initials. SUBJECT. To Under Secretary Secretary of State... Committee / ic , / v f ' S' Jic jcu }, Under Secretary Secretary of State... Copy of to FOR INFORMATION. ^ . «&gt; f^ TK-At ooaMfflMt OCT 1930 Previous Papers - 4407b 1000 3.30' L. THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC M AJESTY’S fCT EBNfH^T: EASTERN (Arabia). CONFIDENTIAL. s 1309/4309/91] Angus t2D SEdTION,3^ ^ » 'iz? .w&gt; U No. 1. Sij' A. Ryan to Mr. A. Henderson.—(Received August 11.) (No. 18L) Sir, Jedda, July 22, 1930. YOU are aware of the difficulties under which the more purely diplomatic work of this post is carried on. They are most painfully borne in on a person who is trying to build up a stronger British representation here than has been possible in the past. They result from the facts that the Legation is confined to Jedda; that the King, personally inaccessible except on rare occasions when he comes here, is both in theory and in practice the sole controller for Foreign Affairs; that the Ministry for Foreign Affairs, such as it is, is in Mecca; and that the Acting Minister, who can at least discuss questions though he can take practically no J decision, has to divide himself between fairly constant personal attendance on the King, now that the latter is at Taif, the management of his office at Mecca and occasional visits to Jedda, made at short notice and at irregular intervals. Fuad Bey Hamza—he prefers the “ bey to the “ sheikh,” I understand^—has been in Jedda for the following periods only, since I arrived here on the 6th May :— The 8th May when he returned from leave and proceeded direct to Mecca. Morning of the 17th May, when he came with the King to receive my credentials, until the afternoon of the 18th May, when he went to Mecca to rejoin the King. The 27th May to, I think, the 29th or 30th May, a short visit without the King. The 7th to 12th June, in attendance on the King with whom he arrived and left. The 11th July to the 18th July, without the King. Otherwise my personal intercourse with Fuad Hamza has, been confined to conversations by telephone, and the telephonic service is only moderately efficient. 2. The difficulties of doing business are somewhat increased by imperfections in the organisation of the Legation, but these are our own concern and will come within the scope of a separate report. The other difficulties are more important as regards diplomatic work proper. Opportunities of discussing really serious questions with the King are reduced to a minimum. When he disappears into the blue, and so far as he is concerned even Mecca and Taif are the blue, we cannot count on any early opportunity of following up the discussions in personal conversation with his Minister, except for an occasional enquiry over the telephone. When Fuad Bey does visit Jedda, outstanding business of importance has to be brought up to date in a frantic rush. There is no time at all to discuss the numerous minor matters, which form the subject of notes, but which it should be possible for members of our staffs to discuss personally from time to time in order to promote the settlement of tiresome little questions and to relieve their chiefs. 3. I thought it desirable to make a statement of the whole subject to Fuad Bey on the 17th July in personal conversation. He had spoken hopefully some time before of the likelihood of Europeans being allowed access to Taif. On other occasions he had mentioned to me a plan for holding weekly diplomatic receptions at his office here and told me something of the difficulties which he himself experienced owing to the King’s exigencies and aptness to upset plans. We had that morning been discussing “ Bon Voisinage ” with Iraq and had reached a point at which I had said that the King’s attitude might impel His Majesty’s Government to instruct me to seek an audience before going on leave. The ground was thus well prepared. 4. I was careful to say and to repeat at least once that I had no reason to complain of the treatment extended to me personally. The King had shown me the most distinguished consideration. When I was fortunate enought to get a chance of talking business with Fuad Bey, I was treated in the same manner and found myself face to face with a Minister of great ability. But I reminded Fuad Bey that the King had desired a Legation and had told me himself that one of his objects was to be able to open himself freely to a responsible senior official. I analysed the situation on the lines of the earlier paragraphs of this despatch; laying some stress on the impossibility of dealing with minor questions except by nofes and reminders. 193 1—1] EFAOdURH. FHOM [N WEEKLY LETTLrv 18 3£EL1950l secretary, political AH0 RET DEPT. INDIA OFFICEIn this connexion I said that all I knew of the Foreign Office in Mecca was that, according to the Hejaz Constitution, it should be organised in four sections. I had never set eyes on the heads of those sections and was uncertain as to their existence. In any normal country I should have the advantage of their acquaintance and members of my staff would be able to see such of them as dealt with our business. ^ I contrasted my position with that awaiting Sheikh Hafiz Wahba, who on the eve c f .6 departure had spoken to me cheerfully of escaping from the heat of London to Wle seaside and perhaps later running up to Scotland. Such happy anticipations inspired envy in the breast of an opposite number compelled to stew in Jedda all the time; but I went further. Suppose, I said, that King George assumed the sole direction of our foreign affairs; that the Foreign Office were moved to Oxford; that it were considered essential, in deference to the ancient Christian traditions of that place, to exclude from it Moslems, Brahmins and the disciples of Confucius; and that Hafiz Wahba were confined to London and the suburbs; would the Hejaz Government then think that they were justified in the expense of maintaining a Legation in Great Britain ? 5. In the course of my statement I referred again to the possibility of my being instructed to ask for an audience of the King. I said that if this happened my only proper and polite course would be to ask to be received at Taif, as Ibn Saud was in residence there and I had no official knowledge that it was closed to foreign repre sentatives. In conclusion, I told Fuad Bey that my statement was of a purely personal nature, intended primarily for his own consumption. The matter might not be ripe for submission to the King, but I begged him to remember what I had said if one of these days I did ask for an audience at Taif or if, at some future date, His Majesty’s Government conceived doubts as to the utility of maintaining a Minister here. 6. Fuad Bey is supporting a great burden, and in most ways impresses me more favourably than I expected. He listened to me carefully and welcomed, I think, a frank connected statement. At the end, he said that my criticism was justified. He was himself conscious of the defects of his machinery. He had not wished to trouble the King prematurely at a time of great preoccupation, but he had now prepared a scheme for the consideration of His Majesty. He added spontaneously that the Ministry for Foreign Affairs ought to be in Jedda. I have, &amp;c. ANDREW RYAN.nft Copy, (E 4657/4509/91). No. 218. JEDDA, August 11th, 1930. 0 Sir, In my despatch No. 184 of June 28th, I recorded a personal conversation with the Acting Minister for Foreign Aflairs regarding the conditions governing diplomatic work in this country. One of my various reasons for choosing the moment of that conversation for a strong expression of views was that since the King went to Taif he was known to have been giving much of his time to questions of reorgan isation Oi the administration of the Hejaz as well as to the revision of legislation. Comparatively little information lira, however, 'been made public regarding his new administrative plans, except as regards changes in the personnel of various departments like customs, municipalities, law-courts and certain committees, matters of considerable local interest, but not important enough to record in a despatch. When Fuad Bey came back to Jedda early in August, lie himsell returned to the subject of arrangements for . oreign affairs. He told me on August 3 by way of a personal though not very confidential statement, that the long talked of decision to make the Amir Faisal Minister of Foreign Affairs had been definitely taken. He, Fuad, would remain as second-in-command. The Ministry would be really organised in four sections, as soon as men could be found to act as their heads. When they were complete, the heads of Sections responsible ior relations with the foreign missions would be. . . * His Majesty’s Principal Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.be either resident or constantly accessible in Jedda, it was not clear which. He himself would carry on the Jedda work until this could he arranged. The reorganisation would soon he publicly announced. 1 welcomed this statement, provided it did not mean that I should he thi^own hack on heads of sections for the handling of important affairs. Fuad Bey reassured me on this point and said that he expected to play much the same role vis a vis of the foreign represent atives as before. I said that as a personal matter I should have preierred not to have had another intermediary besides himself between me and the King. ^ 0n th is Fuad Bey made the most interesting part of his statement. The King he said was overtired. He was at last listening to his doctors and trying to ease off, with a view to being able to reign rather than to rule. It was therefore proposed to delegate extensive powers to the Amir Faisal, who is to remain Viceroy of the Hejaz and who will now take over much of the King T s work in respect of foreign affairs. ^ is hardly credible that Ibn Sa f ud, masterful and restless as he is, should abdicate so much of his real power as the foregoing suggests but it will be interesting to see what balance is achieved under the ne?/ arrangements. ksb. already been announced in the 'Umm-al-- Q,ura ox July 18 that one of the decisions taken during the recent conferences was to constitute in t he Diwan a political department under Sheikh Yusuf Yasin. I asked Fuad Bey whether this new department would also be concerned. .concerned with foreign affairs. He replied that it was being created to provide a single channel in the King's Palace system through which matters dealt with in the Ministry of Foreign Affairs would pass. This is as it may be, but it is obvious that Yusuf Yasin will be in a strong position to ventilate his views, especially as Ibn Sa'ud probably reposes more trust in him than in Puad Hamza, to whom he probably clings more because of his utility and undoubted ability than because he has complete confidence ±n him. I consider it an exaggeration to regard Yusuf Yasin and Puad as so closely united in what has been called the 'Syrian group,’' as to see eye to eye on all matters; and Ibn Sa'ud might well use the former as a check on the latter. I have, etc. (Signed) ANDREW RYAN.From PUT AWAY .WITH Vf Government of Madras• Ho •921. .Diwan Bahadur To J•Venkatanaray&amp;na Bayudu Garu, B.A., B.L« f Secretary to the Government of Madras, The Foreign Secretary to tbe Government of India, Foreign and Political Department# Dated Fort St.George, the 25th February 1929. Sir, Pilgrimage to the Hed^az - Regulations for the distribution of charities in the ledjaz « Letter Ho-F.149 (Y)-H/26 - F &amp; P Department - Government of India, dated the 15th November 1928 - I am directed to say that in the matter cf the proposed Regulations for the administration and distribution of charities in the Hedj&amp;z this Government consulted the Commissioner of Police, Madras and the District Magisti'ate of the districts in which there is a large Muhammadan population. All the officers consulted approve generally of the suggested regulations and this Government agree with them. 2. I am in this connection to bring to the notice of the Government of India certain suggestions which have been made by some of the officers and gentlemen consulted on the subject. A summary of these suggestions is given in the appendix. ,losure IN £H3N SECRETARY’S No. 23 \ MAR. 1929 ig APR-1929 I have,etc., Sd/- J.V.Faray&amp;na, Secretary to Government.. Ippendix Summary of suggestions - Regulations regarding distribution of charities • Hedjaz - HCRTH ARGOT . The Government Khazi at Vellore agrees to the proposed regulations subject to the conditions that (l) the High Commission should be composed of Mussalmans and (11) no expenditure should be incurred on behalf of the members of the commission either in the , matter of pay or otherwise. \ SOUTH ARGOT . The District Magistrate, South Arcot states that subsidiary rules have to be framed in pursuance of the regula tions in regard to the practical y^orking of the commission such as the qualifications of the High Commission the procedure to be adopted in case of difference of opinion among the members and other matters of detail. R/JvC&amp;P Am TRI CHIHOPOIiY . The District Magistrates, Ramnad and Trichinopoly suggest that Muhammadans should be elected as members of the oommission. MADRAS . It is suggested by some of the leading Muhammadans consulted.- (l) that the commission to be constituted should consist of pious l&amp;ihammadan gentlemen recognised as religious authorities on Koranic Law, ( 2 )V ! 1|1 (2) that arrangements be made for publishing from time to time pamphlets giying information regarding facilities afforded for the journey and the funds necessary for the purpose, (5) and that sufficient emphasis sh;uld be laid on the fact that neither the investment by the donor nor the administration of the endowment should under any circumstances be against either the spirit or the letter of shariat law* The Government Kazi of Madras suggests that a meeting may be asked to be convened by the Jiddah Government calling on the representatives of allrthe sects to bring in their objections to the laws of different sects which are opposed to their sects and a compromise is made among all the sects by drswing common shariaths (Laws) for the purpose of the administration of the charity property to be accepted by all the sects, as till then the Bill under reference will be of no avail* Letter from the District Magistrate, horth Arcot to the Secretary to Government, Law Department L.Dis• ho« &amp; 149^0/28 dated the 31st December 1928* '~T '•'A * ,\ V Pilgrimage to Hedjah - Regulations for the distribution of Charities in the ffedjah - Govern ment Memorandum Xo.6784/c-l, dated 29th November 1928 - ' ' ' ’ ~. r; The opinion of majority of the leading members of l f i ^ - the Muhammadan community in this district is in favour of ; the proposed regulations for the administration and distri- bution of charities by a commission to be appointed by the % Government of India. Two leading Musalm&amp;n Bench Magistrates at Ambur do not howeverhowever wish Government interference in the matter of charities which should he distributed in accordance with the wishes of the donor. But this objection can be met by article 12 of the proposed regulations. 2. The Government Khazi at Vellore agrees to the proposed regulations subject to the conditions that (l) the High Commission should be composed of Musalmans and (ll) no expenditure should be incurred on behalf of the members of the Commission either in the matter of pay or otherwise. The other educated Musalmans consulted do not propose any such conditions but are in entire agreement with the proposed regulations. There seems to be no objection generally to introduce the regulations in question. Letter from the District Magistrate, South Arcot, to the Secretary to Government, Law Department dated the 6th January 1929 Ho.L.Dis.C.3-10430-28. Pilgrimage to the Hedj&amp;z - regulations for the distribution of charities in the Hedjaz report - submitted - Government Memorandum Ho.6784 C-l, dated 29th Hovember 1928. The regulations seem to be acceptable to the pilgrims and are necessary. Subsidiary rules will of course have to be framed in pursuance of the regulations in regard to the practical working of the commission such as the qualifica tions of the President and other members of the High Commission, the procedure to be adopted in case of difference of opinion among the members and other matters of detail.Letter from the District Magistrate of Hamnad to the Secretary to Government, Law Department dated the 11th January 1929 No.D.Dis* 6176-28# Reference - Government Memorandum Ho.6784 G-l, dated the 29th November 1928 - The regulations under contemplation are good and l suggest that Muhammadans should be elected as members of the Commission* Letter from the Collector of Madras to the Secretary to Government, Law Department, dated the 30th January 1929 Ho.A-1 Ho.2833/28. Pilgrimage to the Hedjaz - Regulations for the distribution of the Charities in the Hedjaz - Govern ' ment Memorandum Ho.6784/C-l, dated 29th Hovember 1928. My Tahsildar reports that the proposals made for the control and distribution of Charities in the Hedjaz have the general approval of the leading Muhammadans of Madras and they consider it to be a very desirable and much needled Regulation. They express the hope however that the Commission to be constituted will consist of pious Muhammadan gentlemen recognised as religious authorities on Koranic Law and will seek the advice and assistance of His Majesty the King of Hedjaz in carrying out their duties. 2. The pilgrims to Mecca undergo at present several hard ships owing to the exactions of Bedouins, who are in charge of Camel transport from the port Jeddah to Hedjaz - a distance of about 300 miles. These pilgrims get frequently stranded at Mecca, as the stock of money they possess becomes depleted on account of this unexpected expenditure. To prevent these hardships, Government publish from time to time warnings to the intendingintending pilgrims and refuse to allow them to proceed unless they possess a return ticlcet and a minimum surplus amount for expenditure* The appointment of a Commission will be a source of considerable helj&gt; to such helpless pilgrims not only in the matter of pecuniary assistance, but also in assessing their needs and warning them against ill advised journeys with slender resources» It is probably desirable therefore that the scope of the responsibilities of the Commission should be enlarged, and arrangements made for their publishing from time to time - either along with the accounts relating to the administration of the Aquaf &amp;1 Haramain as provided for in the articles of the Regulation or separately - pamphlets which may serve as a guide to the intending pilgrims, both in the matter of facilities afforded and difficulties to be experienced en-route and in the matter of funds that they should possess to meet the various charges to be incurred in the ?»ay and at the Shrine. 3. If it is possible to regulate the transport charges from Jeddah to Mecca, it will be a boon to the pilgrims. But the subject may involve political complications and cannot probably be taken up without consulting the Hedjaz Government. But the Commission to be constituted will have a great force behind it in as much as it will be controlled by the Viceroy; and, their representations may not go unheeded. At any rate, they will be in a position to put forth with considerable emphasis before the Hedjaz Government the needs of the pilgrims and point the direction in which the reforms might be required. 4- As the pilgrimage is essentially a holy one and undertaken by intensely religious Muhammadan gentlemen, they are not likely to tolerate the violation of the Shariat even the slightest. For instance, if the funds of the donor or the amountsamounts expended for the 'benefit of the beneficiary have the faintest tings of ’interest 1 , as destinguished from capital, for its source, the holy gurx purpose with which they undertake the pilgrimage is believed to be frustrated. Hence sufficient emphasis should be laid, the Muhammadan gentlemen say, on the fact that neither the investment by the donor nor the administration of the endowment should under any circumstances be against either the spirit or the letter of the Shariat law. 5. The letter received in this connection from the Govern ment Kazi of Madras is enclosed. Letter from Haji Kazi Moulvi Mohammed J&amp;sihuddin, Govern ment Kazi of Madras, to the Tahsildar of Madras dated the 30th January 1929* \ Reference Regulations for distribution of charities in the Hedjaz - opinion called for - \K |y' The existing practice is that every sect of Islamic v religion such as Sunnis, Shias and Wahabi etc., have their separate representatives in Mecca for the administration of the conditions laid down by a donor of a particular sect. The Shariath law of particular sect is, as it is, opposed to that of a different sect in certain points. In consequence, quarrels now and then arise at the places to be benefited by the charity between the representatives of the sect to which the donor belongs and those of different sect. The Jiddah i Government have introduced the Bill under reference with a view to put / an end to such quarrels to have complete control over the charity property. Even by the introduction of the Bill under reference the\ &gt; \ quarrels already countenanced cannot be put an end to unless N I ■f: the Shariaththe Shariath of different sect which are opposed to each other are discussed and laws common to all se®?t are drawn up before hand. To this end I would suggest that a meeting may he asked to he convened by the Jiddah Government calling on the represen tatives of all the sects to bring in their objections to the laws of different sect which are opposed to their sects and a compromise is made among all the sects by drawing common Sharlaths (laws) for the purpose of the administration of charity property to be accepted by all the sects. Till then the Bill under reference will of no avail. Letter from the Collector of Trichinopoiy to the Secretary to Government, Law Department,dated the 10th Fe bruary 1929, No .L.Dis. 10882-28. References- Government Memorandum Ho. 67840-1, dated 29th November 1S2S - I I see no objection to the proposed regulation and have no remarks to offer except that as regards the personnel of the commission, it would be better if it consists of Muslims only.4 &lt;j- —— M D0.F.51-B. { I Fro® The Deputy Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department* To His Majesty’s Agent and Consul, Jeddah* Dated Few Delhi,the ZIO ' March 1929* . Regulations for the distribution of charities in the Hodja** \ Sir* In continuation of my letter ho*F*51*S f dated the 26th February 1929, I am directed to forward, for information a copy of a letter fro® the Government of Madras, law (General) Department, Ho*921, dated the 25th February 192 9, with enclosures* I have the honour to be* Sir* Your most obedient servant, / Sd/- J.G.Acheson, Deputy Secretary to the Government of India,V D.O.Ko.F.Sl-H, iroreign and Political Department Pew Delhi, the ^ March 1929* Regulations for the distribution and administration of charities in the Hedjas* Mr- ALn^kcidcr- 'Ain*, Please see my official letter ho*&amp;l**R of today* X fear we have been passing to you rather a mass of correspondence on this subject* borne of the Local Governments appear to have misunderstood the position and regarded the regulation as still in the draft stage^* Possibly however their comments may be of some use to you should the regulation come under you have an opportunity of making suggestions* Yours sincerely, 3d/~ J.G*Acheson* F.n.v,* Z tonehewer~Bird, Esquire, Hie Majesty*s Agent and Consul* Jeddah*10 Al&gt; l-19!$ * H0.1173-P. Government of Bihar and Orissa. Political Department Prom r/Vo Sir, i '' s H.K. Briscoe, Esquire, C.I.E., ; JK Chief Secretary to Government, | 2276 i ' j The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India. Patna, the 17th February 1929. Subjects— ^Regulations for distribution of charities in the Hedjaz. With reference to letter I3o.F. 149(V)-H/26, dated the 15th November 1928, from the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, I am directed to say that the Provincial liaj Committee, 'wno were consulted in the matter have recorded the following opinion - H (T) that the regulations regarding the distributions of charities in the Hedjaz be approved subject to the proviso that one representative of the Indian Muslims be put on the proposed committee; (2) that the said representative should be an Indian Muslim from amongst the permanent residents in Hedjaz e.g. Haji Obardur Rahman or Haji Abdul Jabbar or any member of his family'. 2. The Hon’ble Khan Bahadur Sir Saiyid Muhammad Fakhruddin, Minister of Education, who was also consulted, considers it desirable that a representative of the Indian Muslims should be associated with the Commission, especially when donations or wakf given by Indian Muslims are involved, but that it may be left to the Hedjaz authorities to choose such representative. The view expressed above by the Hobble Sir Fakhruddin will no doubt,.receive all due—ee^nsideration from the Government ENCLOSURE IN of India. INDIA FOREIGN SECRETARY'S Letter No. 1 ” M- •Dated 28 FEB. 1929 Received f B MAR. 1329 ^ iMt. I have, etc., Sd. H.K. Briscoe, 'hief Secretary to Government./ / JTP1 I w \ ■v ✓ From To J _fcin &gt; ^ |5l Ho .F, 51-^29 • The XJeputy Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, Mci&gt; Afajes6ys ingest and Consul, Jeddah. Sir, Dated Hew Delhi, the &lt;2 6 February 1929* Regulations for the distribution of charities in the Hedj&amp;z* In continuation of ray letter Hq.F. 51-H # dated the 14th February 1929, I am directed to forwax*d, fox' such action as you may deem desirable, a copy of a letter from the Government of Bihar and Jrissa, Political Department, H0.1173-P, dated the 17th February 1929* X have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, ♦ S. Sd. dVrCV/V' Ay, fKn^oi! j y Deputy Secretary to the Government of India. i.j «I I &gt;4 ^ f V’) | / ^ K&gt; 1930 / atirin^^ , Letter from the Le.dut/ i^ec-re.Lar/.-to the Government ed the of Bengal, Political Department, Do.14798-P., 1st December 1928. i 0 APL 1929 I'l'^ 'V I am directed to refer to the foreign and Political Department letter ho.F-149(V)-N./26, dated the 15th November 1928, regarding the regulations for distribution of charities in the Hedjaz and to say that the Governor in Council suggests that publicity should be given to the regulations. He nas no other remarks to offer on the subj ect. &lt;*p :: 2 T - &amp; Copy of a letter Miscellaneous Department No.345V 28, dated Rangoon, the 29th December 1928, from the offg. secretary to the Government of Burma, Judicial Department, to the Secretary to the Government of India, Foreign ana Political Department. Regulations for distribution of charities in the Hedjaz. With reference to your letter No.F.149(V)-N/26, dated the 15th November 1928, on the subject noted above, 1 am directed to say that the Local Government has no remarks to ofier on the royal decree laying down regulations for the distribution and administration of charities in the Hedjaz. ^ am t 0 add that a press communique in English on the subject v/as issued to press generally and copies thereof were forwarded to Commissioners, the Commissioner of Police, Rangoon, and various Mahomedan Associations.Copy of a letter NO.7380-C., from C. ViT. A. Turner, Esquire, General Department, G.I.E., I.G.3., Secretary to the Government of Bombay,/ to the Foreign Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department^ ^^(ii ik io*'. N/26, dated the 15th November 1928, I am directed by the Governor in Council to forward copies of the correspondence *1. Letter from the Commissioner of Police, ) noted in the 2. Memorandum from the Commissioner in Sind ) no.15827,G, dated the 23rd December 1928,; it appears that Subject:- Regulations for distribution of charities in the Hedjaz. Y/ith reference to Mr.Inglis’s letter No.F. 149-(V)- Bombay, no.4183 PP/5, dated the 26th December 1928. margin from which and accompaniments. that the regula tions framed by the Government of the Hedjaz for the distri bution of charities in that country are not acceptable to the Muhammadans in the Bombay Presidency.Office of the Commissioner of Police, Bombay. No.4183/PP/5 of 1928. Prom The Commissioner of Police, Bombay, The Secretary to the Government of Bombay, General Department, Bombay. Bombay, 26th December 1928. Subject:- Regulations for the distribution of Charities in the Hedjaz. Sir, With reference to the Government endorsement, General Department, no.7380-C, dated the 4th instant, I have the honour to state that the Haj Committee, Bombay, 'strongly protest against the control by the Hedjaz Govern ment, as regards administration -and distribution by a special Committee appointedby them, of all Indian charities and gifts for the following reasons:- 1. As soon as a Waqf (trust) is made, its subject matter becomes the absolute property of God and cannot, therefore, be transferred, exchanged or sold. 2. The wishes of the donor become law and the Mutawalli appointed becomes the trustee. 3. Any interference as regards income and benefits accruing therefrom must be solely in the interest of the beneficiaries mentioned in the Waqf. 4. The laws of Shariat are interpreted by different sections of Musalmans in various ways. 5. The Qazi or the King can only interfere with a Waqf when mismanagement or misappropriation of the trust occurs, in which case the Mutawalli appointed by the donor to administer the trust can be dismissed. 6. These conditions as set forth above have always been observedobserved by the British Government in its dealings with Muslims in the British Empire. 2. The Haj Committee suggest that the Hedjaz Government should introduce a lav/ similar to the Waqf Act in India v/hich in no way interfers with religious questions connected with the administration of Waqf properties and charities. If this was done there could be no objection. At the same time they object strongly to the idea that any money sent from India to be distributed in the Hedjaz in charity should be in any way controlled by the Hedjaz Government according to its lights and according to the donor’s wishes. I have, etc., 3d/- P.A.Kelly, Commissioner of Police. Immediate. Prom No.1799 of 1928. Pilgrim Department, Karachi, 18th December 1928. Khan Saheb Abdul Qadir Umar Khan, Protector of Pilgrims, Karachi, To The Collector of Karachi, Subject:- Regulations for the administration and distribution of charities in the Hedjaz. Sir, With reference to your endorsement no.6878-G,dated the 14th December 1928, I have the honour to submit herewith a copy of the minutes of the meeting of the Haj Committee, Karachi,Karachi, held on the 18th December 1928, on the above subject. 2. The question is a very difficult one. I am afraid the Regulations will not be acceptable to Sunnis and Shias. The doctrines of the Shariat as interpreted and followed by Sultan Ibn Saud and his Maulavis differ considerably from those as interpreted and followed by Sunnis and Shias. Sunnis and Shias will never agree to the charities allotted by them for certain special objects, which according to them are in accordance with the Shariat but v/hich according to Ibn Baud’s Wahhabi doctrines are contrary to the Shariat, to be diverted by him to other objects which according to him are in accordance v/ith the Shariat but which are contrary to the doctrines of the Shariat as interpreted and followed by the founders or * donors. Sd/~ Abdul Qadir Umar Khan, Protector of Pilgrims, Karachi. Ro.6478-G of 1928. Karachi, 19th December 1928. To Copy submitted to the Commissioner in Sind with reference to his endorsement 15827-G, dated 12th December 1928. 2. The matter is not one in which an useful opinion can be offered. Prima facie it would appear that the charities should be administered in accordance with the wishes of the donors. 3d/- Por Collector of Karachi. The Commissioner in Sind.J Proceedings of the meeting of the Haj Committee held on 18th December 1928, at the Office of the Protector of Pilgrims, Karachi, at 9.30 A.M. to consider the Regulations of the Hedjaz Government for the administration^ and distribution of charities in the Hedjaz. The following gentlemen were present at the meeting:- 1. Haji Abdul Ghani, Chairman, 2. Khan Sahib Qazi Abdul Aziz. 3. Sirdar Abdul Chaffur. 4. Mian Fakir Muhammad Khan. 5. Seth Haji Abdul Shakur. 6. Seth Mian Muhammad Amin. 7. Haji Moulvi Ilias. 8. Mr. Abdul Rahman, Bar-at-law. I Proposed by Khan Sahib Qazi Abdul Aziz. Seconded by Mian Fakir Muhammad Khan. Resolved that the Government should not interfere with the charities, grants and allowances, including Aukaful Haramain, as already exist or shall come into existence hereafter, v/hich should be administered and distributed according to the wishes and instructions of the donors, in accordance with doctrines of Shariat as followed and accepted by such donors. II Minutes of the last meeting were read and confirmed. Karachi, 18th December 1928. Sd/- H. Abdul Ghani. Chairman, Haj Committee, Karachi. No.15827-G. General Department, Camp of the Commissioner of Sind, 23rd23rd December 1928. Submitted to Government with reference to their endorsement no.7380-C., dated the 4th December 1928. The Commissioner agrees with the Protector of Pilgrims but doubts whether in practice any Indian Muslims will really create trouble about this matter. It was probably a mistake to raise the question. 3d/- W.F.Hudson, Commissioner in Sind. To The Secretary to Government, General Department, Bombay.Viceroy* The camreiHcicn mil publish a list of douatio^s received and .monthly statements of account iopy of th.tr. despatch and its enclosure a. oi'i.n: a * id r e 3 s e 0 1 0 t h e B e c r e t a 1 y 4-'V-, e vlovernment o f in oh Foreign and Political Department and the CoJ.Gniai in, f . oimryp -1 . .0-. O; 0 O Jl. O ts ♦ ' V. - ere nonoox I I f. !' 1 one mane 3 1 ; ' - r. r Annex,.. Regu1ati 0 ns regarding the distributicn of Ch a r 1 1 1 e Art iclepL .— This regulation is to be entitled ’‘•Distribution and Administration of Charities Regulation” * Article 2*-- The terms used in this regulation will have the following meanings K / \ V ^ / Charity comprises all acts of benevolence* ( 0 ) The beneficiary of the haqf is the place or person to whom is allotted, the income of that Waqf. (c.) Allowances and grants are monies paid to the needy in acts of benevolence. (d) The word charity includes anything in the way of grants or aliowances * (e) The high commission for the distribution*and administration of charities is the commission constituted in accordance with this regulation* Article 5 «— Charities, grants and 0 ilowances will be uistributed irrespective of tneir sources in accordance .with tliie regulation, . Tti c le 4 . - - All charities and contributions reaching this country from abroad will be disbursed by the High Commission to be constituted in accordance with this regulation. ai u iQ-t -0 o *~ uiiai i uies ^ grants ana allowances received from the Aukaf al Haramain will be controlled by the high commission and disbursed through them in compliance with tns conditions laid down by founders r subscribers and donors»th® donor unless they are contrary to tno Sharia. (2&gt; If the disbursal is left to the discretion of the Commission, it will use its best endeavour to secure the objects of the benevolent founder. ° me Central High Commission shall forward to the Government every three months a detailed report giving a summary of its work, the amounts of money received -m tneir dis oursal, snowing now ana to whom they Have been disbursed. cle 1 &lt; 0 .li cne iounder or donor made a condition 00 ^ ae ihct tnat disbursal should be under the control of certain persons representing him, tne Viceroy can issue an order nominating the said persons to the central High Commission for tne purpose of sharing in the dis tribut ion . of the amounts to be spent urr der Ills con trol. His participation wi11 e nd vvi uiiou t t ae issue of a - special order to that effect W: .ien the 0 '■J i 3 ^ .i. (j n.&lt;i, 0 compieted the .e autiiority to v/hich the ue will control its distribution of the sum in question Artide 1 o • — The Viceroy is • Central High Commission T »vill refer, work and inspect its records. Article 3.4»— ^he Central High Commission will always publish cue amount oi money received and. will circulate n su^aary or its monthly accounts for public inspection. ^ i ^ * my viceroy will appoint the officials xsquired for tiie worx or the coiomission* A.d.l' f 9 j r -u he Viceroy will issue the necessary instructions for the execution of the work in accordance with the terms of this regulation. Ar^iole l? .-- The Viceroy will be responsible for the app liet r 0 nIn any further communication on this subject,/please quote / No —&lt;-^ 6 S / H oZH Q( and address —not to any person by name, but to— “ .rne Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Ofjfce, London, ^W. I. r n nv a c\ [i '-I L ~r Q THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents ^tis compliments to ^ direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop gj^ of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, //■Q-fi Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure.[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Maiestv's Government.! 3 EASTERN (Arabia) . CONFIDENTIAL. b r\ o ^ o o d August 14, 1928. Section 1. , JB 4031/4031/91] No. 1. Consul Bird to Sir Austen Chamberlain.—{Received August 14.) (No. 119.) Sir, Jeddah, July 29, 1928. I HAVE the honour to transmit herewith a translation of the Royal decree just issued governing the composition and functions of the Legislative Council. 2. The Viceroy is the permanent president. A permanent vice-president will be nominated by the King, and a second vice-president will be elected by the members of the council. 3. The number of members composing the council will be limited by Royal decree, and the period of membership will be two years. Members must be not less than 25 years of age, be men of education and experience and must not have been convicted of any crime or be bankrupt. 4. The council will deal with the budgets of Government Departments and of municipalities. All concessions, economic and financial schemes and all Government contracts exceeding £200 will be submitted to the council, as will all questions regarding the engagement of foreign employees. 5. The council will be divided into two committees, each of which will study the questions referred to it and submit its recommendations to the final decision of the council. 6. The council will meet daily. Two-thirds of the council constitute a quorum, and decisions will follow the vote of the majority. 7. If the council reject a scheme submitted by the Government, the Viceroy may call upon the council to reverse its decision, and, if it refuses to do so, may refer the question to the King for final decision. 8. Where a scheme submitted by a Government Department is under discussion, the head of the department will be present at the deliberations of the council. 9. The King has the right to dissolve the council or to make changes in the membership at any time. 10. The most interesting clause from the point of view of the foreigner is article (5) (i), which lays down that any Government contract exceeding £200 must be submitted to the council. If adhered to, this decision should go far to ensure that Government contracts are not, as has so often happened lately, the subject of personal arrangements between members of the Government and their friends. 11. I have addressed a copy of this despatch and its enclosure to the Govern ment of India and Singapore. I have, &amp;c. F. H. W. STONEHEWER-BIRD. Enclosure in No. 1. Organisation of the Legislative Council. (Translation.) Article 1. The Legislative Council will be constituted of the number of members to be limited by Royal decree. Art. 2. The President of the Legislative Council is the Viceroy. A permanent representative of the Viceroy will be appointed by His Majesty. Another repre sentative will be chosen by the council to act in the absence of the first representative. Art. 3. The period of membership of the Legislative Council will be two years. Art. 4. Members in the Legislative Council must fulfil the following conditions :— {a.) Be not less than 25 years of age. (5.) Be men of experience and knowledge. (c.) Not have been condemned for any dishonouring thing and not bankrupt. (d.) Of good conduct. [539 o—l]Art. 5. The following will be referred to the council by the Government:— (a.) Budgets of Government Departments, the municipality and “Ain Zubeida.” (b.) Licences for economic schemes and schemes of development. (c.) Concessions and economic and financial schemes. (d.) Expropriations for public utility. (e.) Introduction of laws and regulations. (/.) Increases in budgets of departments during the year. {g) Unforeseen expenditure in Government Departments amounting to more than £100 and arising during the course of the year. (A.) Decisions concerning the employment of foreign employees. {i.) Contracts with companies or merchants for the purchase or sale of Government materials if exceeding £200. Art. 6. The council will be divided into two committees, each of which will study the subjects referred to it by the president and submit its recommendations to a general meeting of the council for final decision. Art. 7. Two-thirds of the members of the council, together with the president, will constitute a quorum, and decisions will be made on the majority of the votes of those present. Art. 8. The council will meet daily to consider the questions laid before it. Art. 9. The council is to draw the attention of the Government to any lapse in the application of the laws and regulations submitted. Art. 10. If the Government present a scheme to the council, who reject or modify it and the Government do not concur in their action, the Viceroy has the right to return the scheme to the council with an explanation adequate to satisfy the council of the true intention of the Government and of the necessity of the council’s changing their decision. If the council still refuse and maintain their former amendments, it will remain for His Majesty the King to make the final decision in the matter. The council will also refer to His Majesty through its president for his approval any scheme decided by them where two months have elapsed without the issue by decree of the Royal consent. Art. 11. The chief of the department or his representative must be invited to attend any meeting of the council when a matter relating to that department is under discussion by the council. This rule should always be followed. Art. 12. A capable secretary for the Legislative Council is to be appointed for organising the clerical work and receiving, arranging and summarising, at least one day before the meeting is held, the agenda drawn up by the president. Clerks will be appointed for the council as necessary. Art. 13. The King has the right to dissolve the council or to change any one of its members at any time. Art. 14. These decisions are to replace the section of the fourth division of the fundamental rules relating to the Legislative Council.In any further communication on this subieeU please quote-1 and tigress —not to any person by name, but to— “The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, fi.W. I. 4 7 THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to j^Lx. ^ f the Seci and, by direction of iretary transmits herewith cop (ju of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, 2r-f ' • , 192 Reference to previous correspondence Description of Enclosure.COPY JIDDA. (E 4289/4289/81) Ho* 124* r&gt; £ Aia^ust ?, 1928. $ir, With raferenoe to paragraph 3 of my despatch jgo. 121 of Augaet 3, I h«ive the honour to transmit herewith a \o ^ translation of the royal decree laying down regulations for the distribution and administration of charities in the Hejaz. I 1 he decree was published on July 7. 2. Under the regulations all charities and gifts whatever their source are to be administered and distributed by a special commission appointed for the purpose. In administering or distributing charities the commission will comply with the conditions laid down by the donors provided that such conditions are not contrary to Shariah law. In cases where a donor or founder of a charity nominates a repre sentative to control the digtrlbution or disbursement of monies subscribed for any charitable object, such representative may, by order of the Viceroy, be attached to the commission until such time as disbursement is completed. 3. The commission will consist of a president and four members appointed by and under the control of the Viceroy. The commission will publish a list of donations received and monthly statements of account. 4. A copy of this despatch and its enclosure are being addressed to the secretary to the Government of India in the foreign and Political Department and the Colonial secretary* Singapore. I have, etc., (3gd.) P.H.W. STOHMMM Blitf). His Majesty^ Principal Secretary of State for foreign Affairs.^eiroXationa regarding the distribution of Charities . Article !• tghie reflation is to bo entitled 'Distribution MWIWl'MIiattflNMl 'ril«nWl'WMlMMlimin =- • and Administration of Charities He^ulation'. Article g. The terms used in this re miction will hare the following meanings: (a) Charity oomprisea all acts of benevolence. (b) The beneficiary of the Vfaqf is the place or person to whom is allotted the income of that Wa$£. (o) Allowances and grants are monies paid to the needy in acts of benevolence. (d) The word charity includes anything in the way of grants or allowances, (e) The high commission for the distribution and administra tion of charities is the commission constituted la accordance with this regulation. Article 3. Charities, grants and allowances will be distributed irrespective of their sources in accordance with this regulation. Article 4. All charities and contributions reaching this country from abroad will be disbursed by the High Commission to be constituted in accordance with this regulation. Article 5. Charities, grants and allowances received from the Au&amp;af al tfaraavaio will be controlled by the high commission and disbursed through them in compliance with the conditions laid down by founders, subscribers and donors, provided these conditions are not contrary to the shariah. Article 6. Charities, allowances and grants will be considered to be in accordance with Bhariah if they are spent in one of the following ways;V (1) In the relief of destitute and distressed Moslem travellers# (2) In opening shelters, feeding places, schools and hospitals. (3) In the proporgation of religious teaching and Islamic knowledge. (4) In benevolent acts other than those mentioned above. Article 7. a high central commission is to be established consisting of a president and four members apoolnted by the yiceroy. i'iiis commission will be called the High Gommission for the administration and distribution of charities, grants and allowances and will sit in Mecca and its wor&amp; will be the distribution of charities, grants and allowances in accordance with this regulation. Article 8. fhe said High Commission has the rignt to ask the Government when necessary to have subsidiary branches attached to it whose work will be the distribution of the amounts allotted to the places where the branches will have been established. Article 9. fho Government will pass any monies It receives as Aukax al Haramain together with other contributions, charities and allowances to the High Commission. Article 10. fhe High Commission will keep a strict account of all sums passed by the Government or received direct in any way. f ihe disbursal of such amounts will be as follows; (1) if the sum is specified for a certain place, it will be necessary to observe the conditions made by the donor unless they are contrary to the Hharia. (£) If the disbursal is left to the discretion of the Commission, it will use Its best endeavour to secure the objects of the benevolent founder. Article 11. I'he central High Commission shall forward to the Government every three months a detailed report giving a summary/summary of its work, the amounts of money received and their disbursal, showing how and to whom they have been disbursed# Article ia« If the founder or donor made a condition to the effect that disbursal should be under the control of certain persons representing hi , the Viceroy can issue an order nominating the said persons to the Central Hiflh Commission for the pur post of sharing in the distribution of the amounts to be spent under his control. Hie participation will end without the issue of a special order to that effect when tbs commission has completed the distribution of the sum in question# Article 13# Th&amp; Viceroy is the authority to which the central High Commission will refer# He will control its work and inspect its records. Article 14# ihe Central High Commission will always publish the amount of money received and will circulate a summary of its monthly accounts for public inspection# Article 15# The Viceroy will appoint the officials required for the work of the commission. Article 16. Ihe Viceroy will issue the necessary instructions for the execution of the work in accordance with the terms of this regulation. Article 17# She Viceroy will be responsible for the applica tion of this regulation and the Government departments will see to its execution. Article 18# This regulation will come into force from the date of its oublioation</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000555.0x00027d_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/2099</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000555.0x00027d</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/2099</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 6/33 'Hejaz-Nejd: Internal Administration and Constitution; Various Laws.'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1928/1940</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-04-26T10:42:25</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (193 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the inside front cover with 1, and terminates at the last folio with 194; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 2-193; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file concerns matters relating to the administration of the Kingdom of the Hejaz and Nejd (later Saudi Arabia). It contains correspondence discussing laws and regulations passed by the Hejazi/Saudi Government.The early part of the file (1928-1929) contains copies of translations of various royal decrees regarding the following:The appointment of a commission to oversee the distribution and administration of charities in the Hejaz.The registration of companies in the kingdom.The composition and functions of the Legislative Council.This part of the file contains a significant amount of correspondence from local government officials in British India, which discusses how the regulations on the distribution and administration of charities in the Hejaz might affect Indian Muslims. It includes concerns raised by representatives of Indian Muslims in Bombay and Karachi that the Wahabi interpretation of Sharia law on the subject of charities does not coincide with Sunni and Shia interpretations.Later correspondence discusses the reorganisation of the administration of the Hejaz in 1930 and the new designation of Ibn Saud's dominions as the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia in September 1932. This part of the file includes the following:A copy of a translation of the Hejazi constitution or 'fundamental rules' of 1926, together with copies of translations of subsequent regulations and notifications amending or superseding certain articles of the constitution.A copy of a translation of a royal decree marking the change of name of the Kingdom of the Hejaz and Nejd to the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia.Details of various Saudi Government regulations, such as those regarding the registration of companies in Saudi Arabia and those relating to the governance of foreign residents in the country.Reports of the formation of the Saudi National First Aid Society in 1935.Details regarding the reorganisation of Saudi Arabia's Legislative Council.The file's principal correspondents are the following: the British Agent and Consul, Jedda (Hugh Stonehewer Bird); His Majesty's Chargé d’Affaires to Jedda (Cecil Gervase Hope Gill, Albert Spencer Calvert, and Alan Charles Trott successively); His Majesty's Minister at Jedda (Sir Andrew Ryan, succeeded by Sir Reader William Bullard); officials of the Board of Trade, the Foreign Office, and the Government of India's Foreign and Political Department.The file includes a divider which gives a list of correspondence references contained in the file by year. This is placed at the back of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of Hejaz and Najd</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Decrees</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Chargé d'Affaires to Jeddah</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Ambassador to Saudi Arabia</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>British Agent and Consul General, Jeddah</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of India, Foreign and Political Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Board of Trade</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of Saudi Arabia, Āl Sa'ūd dynasty</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Kingdom of Nejd and Hejaz</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Saudi Arabia</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Regulations</topic></subject><subject><topic>Charities</topic></subject><subject><topic>Constitutions</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000555.0x00027d#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>