<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000127_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T04:08:43.932Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">L ^elegran Code From BritconRj1 Hohammerah 5 To Political Resident BuPhire Repeated Minister ^ehrrji No. 68 Dated and received the 7th September 19P9. I?tME T)XATK. Governor GenerpJ. has visjted Mohammerhh and discussed Bahrein question with me. He says he hrn no orders from Tehran reference to exemption from registration and denies Bahreinis right to complain to me of forcible registration as he is saying that all Bahreinis are Persian subjects and liable to punishment fa: complaining to British ConsiO.at^. m. He states that Haji Hamid had comitted political crime. Latte^jfias been deported to Iraq and Ke^s of his shcn a,reWith thepolice. Reply to all my protests isfthat I have no right to interfere as Bahreinis are Persian Subjects. Govennor General also stated that rule that governs arbitralpcry p.rrest and ijnprisonment by police does not 'VPP-ly ^ r) Political suspects. Police can thus imprison anyone at wil3 by stating that he is a Political suspect without warrant of arrest. I queried this statement. He was also under that impression that safeguard on3y applied to Europeans. He finally agreed to telegraph to Tehran for orders in regard to registration of Bahrejnis, Request that you will intervene as contin- * ued ill treatment of Bahreinis and our apparent helpleoneix are having very bad effect locally. A , v Mv general impression is that the (U ^ X Persian Government means to carry out the registration and prevent complaints to me by intimidation. - lift iTC 0 NfUL -1.. Kr * L CQNFIDBNTIAL. ■ • \ a y\ / Prom No. 2/29/5 of 1923 H, B. M*8 Vice-Consulate, Kohaaimerab., the 5th September 1929, Captain E. W. Fletcher, Acting; British Vice-Consul Mohamrierah /tag A/o To The Hon 'ble Lt, Col: C, C. J. Barrett. C. S. I, , C. I. S. , Politicel Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bu shire. Sir, y In continuation of my letter No. 2/29/795 dated the £5th July 19 29 I have the honour to report that since ray arrival here I have received numerous visits from Sahreinis, of whom theie ey ovteriAJ ^-^wa»n Bin tfe tan'UAQUBafitt- resident^ in Kohc 'ii' erah, Abadan and Gusbeh. These visits v;ere all made in order to complain of the harsh treatment which Bahrein!s now receive from the local - - Persian authorities in general and from the police in particular. In view of the instructions of the Minister that nothing should be dene to bring the Behreini question to a head I advised all Bahrenis to keep quiet, to wear Pahlevi dress, to conform tc Persian regulations and on no account to flaunt their claim to British protection. At the sgune time I took advantage of the rood relations then existing between myself ani the Governor of - - Ltohamnerah to intercede for them unofficiall}'. On August 3th the Governor of Mohamnerah privately informed me that he was about to issue orders for all Persians v^ho had not yet done so to register themselves &amp;s Persian subjects and to take out Persian nationality papers. He told me that, as he had orders to consider Bahreinis as Persicir^ subjects, this order would apply to ell Eahreinis. furthermore, wnatever the ultimate fete of Bahrein, Ba ireinis once re &lt;:i ~tered, would ever after be regrrded as Persian subjects. As t-.is registration also involves th signature of a document duly ftnessed r.ttestir/ tc :ie volurtFr- adoption of Pp-r g ^^ '-2- e volv.ntary adoption of Persian ne.tionp3.ity by the person 'ho signs it, it at once occurred to me that the Persian la/yvvjt'vt^ Go.en- might use this as an *yaoiu3nt ir support of their claim to ccisnbc Bahrein, It would 'be s simple .natter for t'. c 'n to draw attention to t universal desire of the B^hreini residents of Mohamnerah. to adopt Persian nationality. I therefon -ele^raphsd to jrou in the hope that the matter mirlit v e taken up. Through the good will of the Governor I was able to secure two respites for the Behreinis 'but finally the Governor said that he dared not delay further. He ^ave me the impression --at the Chit ' of Police, who is excessively ant -2ritieh would make trouble for him in high quarters should there be any - - fu ther postponement. Accordingly on about August 20th forcible r^istra- tier r +v ie ensu^*^^ few days three well 'known Bahrein!s namely Haji Abood, Ha ji Cbeid Derazi and Haji Liohamed Sale a, It zs Fhi^fan were taken to the Begiptrati m Office by the police and forced to register themselves as Persians, This threw the ^ahretni community into a ^reat state of alarm and several Bahreinis came to me to ask my advice. Realising that any further appeal to tne Governor would be useless I asked the Consul Ahwaz to interview the Governor General, This he did and I was informed that enforced registration would be stopped. I then telephoned to the Governor of Mohammerah who stated that he would issue the necessary - - instructions. Inspite of this however on August Slst and September 1st attempts at intimicU A on '-ere made. On the 31 st August Ila ji Hamid Bchreini who is much disliked by the police for the leading part he has played in protesting- against the tyranny of the police towards his compatriots, was threatened. On September 1st Seyyid Tama ~ahre ini was taken to the Registration Office and(f aix'. /arsatened with expulsion from Mohaimnerah if h® did not take out Persian nationality papers. He, however,stoutly refused, 'By dint of repeated telephoning to the Governor I was a 'ble to settle matters once more. Tiie Consul Ahwaz again a ^proec .eel the Governor General v/ho prc^ is- 3 ! to make enquiries. On the morning of September 2nd, however, the Corsul Ahwaz Informed me that the instructions which the ?.Iini ster of Court at Tehran had prcMi ^ec' our ''inirtcr send Iramedi? 4 '?!— had not reached the Governor General, Further the Governor Gcnersl declared hat all complaints made to me 'by the Bchrcinis were false*This, I uay remark, is the invariable reply to any - - complaint made 'by me on 'behalf of British subjects or Travis against Persian officials. Personally I am satisfied of the truth of the Baiireinis' complaints, and I cm surprised that, knowing the retribution awaiting them at the hsnds of the police, they still dare to make any resistance, I do not think that the Governor is e party^to this intimidation but his hand is forced by the Chief of Police who, I em sure, is N only too delighted to cause difficulties between myself and the - - Go ve rno r, I have asked the Consul Ahwaz whether the forcible registration of Hrjl Obeid Barezi, Kaji Renamed Saleh and Haji Abood can be cancelled, but I understand that the Governor- General does/ not consider this Ssi'o11*^e, Haji Abood Mn'! i'cc tlic ol^LT tco f ri.tened to make ar:y protest, but as t' two others have sent re written statements could the question of ca.rc o llation of t .ieir registra^tion be taken up? I anticipate further difficulties when the New Law Persian Hationality/passes the Majlis, this law all persons resident in Persia who do not possess proof foreign ^atj ra-itj aic to be considerea as Persian subjects. These-4- Tlieaa B&amp;lireinis when called upor -o .s P-T^- will te forced to produce their Eritieh passports or C 3 rtifi- cates of Identity to prove their claim to exemption. :t seems extremely protatle that the local authorities, unl^s checked, will confiscate such papers on the pounds that Bahrenieacxx are Persians and as such have no right to posses these documents. Such a proc edl^ would, I feel, result in endless co tions. In conclusion I would respectfully^ point out 4._ _vr, + ort 'R ;? 'h*v'H nip is having thrt my apparent helplessness to protec. - - very had effect locally. Several Bahreinis, nstahiy HaJi Jaesim. a lea^inf merchant, have already taien the line of least resistance and become Persian eutjects, ar.d it is o on the whole surprising that so mary ourtiras and persist in complaining to me when they know that every visit to the Consulate entails more unwelcome attention from the Persian police. A copy of this despatch is heing forwarded to r.E.LlaJ sty'? Cot sul/ for Khuiietan,Ah', az. I have the honour to 'be. Sir, Your £1 ost o^edient seivantj c - p crti?, Acting British Vice-C:^. - .CONFIDENTIAL. KO, 2/29/ /0 3/ of 1929 H,B.M'b Vice-Consulate, Mohaomerfth, the 7tii September j.9 29 From gypV,! - - r cSID^NCY. Captain EVW,Fletciier, Acting British Vice-Consul /tag. Nu. . y 1) — i c ' f'lSj RfcCOHOS. Mohauimerah To The Hon* ole Lt. Col :C, C. J. Barrett;, C, S. I,, C, I. E. , Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Bushire. Sir mi- In continuation of my telegraai No. 63 dated the 6th September 19 29. I hare the honour to report that H^ji Hamid is a respectable merchant here whose only crime appears to hare 'been to petition ta. this Vice-Consul ate and the Sheikh of Bahrein on the treatment metec out to Bahreinis, I happened to 'be riding along the river front on the evening of September 4th and I passed this man. He saluted me,^a rare occurrence in Mohanmerah, 15 minutes later I was informed that a few minutes after saluting me he had 'been arrested. No charge was preferred nor was there any warrant of arrest, was taken to the common prison normally reserved for prisoners condemned by the courts. Bail and conversation with relatiares were refused. It was only on the arrival of the Governor-General on Septamber 5th that his relatives were allowed to bring him food # The Governor treated my protests with levity and refused to inform me of the man» s crime. The general impression now widespread is that this man, who was threatened by the police some days ago and by the Governor 3 weeks ago for daring to visit the Consulate, wa^ arrested because he saluted the British Vice-Consul. I w opi .ior left there. On my remonstrating with the Governor General on Septem- ber 6th the latter stated as follows; (1) Bahreinis being Persian subjects would be punished for making complaints to a foreign 0onsul, (2) The British Vice-Consul had no right to intertsre with Persian subjects. that On September 6th he was was also encouraged by police propaganda, taken across the * Iraq frontier in a car and© I (3) The man's crime was^olitical 1 '. More than this he would not vouchsafe, (4) Persians suspected of political almes would be arrest'e imprisoned,refused 'bail and interviews with their friends at the will of the police without the warrant of a court. In reply to my remarks that this was not in accordance with the Persian police regulations the Governor General replied that political suspects come under different rules. I replied that in that case it was strange that a whole section of the ordinary Penal Code should Toe devoted to political offences, (6) Finally the Governor General said that inspite of the Minister of Courts statement to our Minister that compulsary - - registration would 'be stopped he could not delay it again as he had no orders. I argued for a long time without effect and I was only successful in rescuing the keys of Haji Hamid'a shops from the predatory clutches of the Persian police. In my opinion the Persian Goverrment have instigated this move and have deliberately failed to issue the necessary instructions* They hope by these means to intimidate all Bahreinis into M^itoW^^ n and to demo nstrate once more the hollowness of British protection. Reports have already reached me of orders to Bahreinis to register themselves and I have advised Bahrinis so w\ ordered to cross to Iraq by stealth and remain there for the next few days. In respect of the alaiiiiiTTg; prospect opened up by the Governor General's nvreregarding political suspects whereby it would appear that the local police claim to be able to imprison and deport any foreigr^/ subject at will and without reference to any court of law or Consular representativc f wyiWiie, wl sepalutL I need only say that an 1 Iraqi has ^ , Cm- ^ already met with this fate. His crime as far as I am eortain lay in the fact that the Chief of Police was indebted to him. The result of this fresh display of Persian arrogance an* camM * will be as if the Persians still claim tha' Kconid la a Persian subject-the ^Irsq: G^Temment-Heiirl eurelyi 1 /^, that Eaji Hamid is a Persian subject the »Iraq Government will surely object to 'being a dumping ground for Persian political /v exiles without any passport papery. On the other hand if the Persians counter this protest 'by saying that the man is a - - it the Bahrejpi it will be a tacit admission that the Bahreinis resident Xoduantszek Persia are not Persians. 4 1? hi fn I have the honour to be. Si r. Your most obedient servant, [jiJ x Captain, Acting BritishbVice-Consul, Copies of this despatch are bein^ forwarded to K.M'8 Minister, Wan and H.B.M's Consul for Khuzistan, Ahwaz. V* - •19/109. .Hushire, 10th September 19?,9. Lear Fletc: to .toma or to Minister direct, I have decided that I can do no 300-.I bv intsrveni] j *.t thi^ fta-ge, I have already intervened twice and persuaded the Government of India to suT^port my intervention on the second behind one of his H impresnions'', but, you will notice, gar® no promise. -able opportunity offers T shpJ .l xjrj oin the fray with another protest against Persian action. So long as the Bahrain sovereignty question remains unsettled, we shall make little progress. Yours sincerely, Sd/- C.C J. BARRETT. occasion. The result was that vainovrtache left Keep me Informed of the situation and If a favour- (V .G .M 1 erah).19/109 / 'Cxtract frorn D«0. Ie tter from Capt ain_ ?letcher ^ ^ c%/ ^ 8 th Sep teiober 1929. Dear Colonel, The Baiirainis are ocrearnlng. iWe told them to flee to Iraq and theae fools, Persians, now threaten to deport them the re.if they don't register. This is amusing asit is tantamount to renouncing their assertion that Bahrainis are Persian subjects. Haji Hahid — so proclaims our dear friend, Rais-i-rNazmieh, was deported for being H a spy of the British 1 '. Even he could not make them I hope I haven't been too cantankerous with the dear Persians over these incidents, but ever since the protests made by the Persian Government about our helping the rebels there has been a marked change in feeling here. My unfortunate Interpreter is watched day and night and if he goes into a shop, the shopkeeper is summoned by the police and asked what the interpreter wanted. 1 am stiill under surveillance and have got to know my watchmen quite well by sight. What a country ! really swallow the 'saluting' yarn '. 1 hope that 'ehran will move soon as all this is bad for our prestige.COHPIPEMTIAL. k*^ f\l i ti 'l NO. 2/29//of 1929 H.B.M's Vice-Conaulate, Mohan me rah, the i^th September 1929 From Captain E.W .Fletcher, Acting British Vice-Consul Mohammerah, Mrnui To The Hon 1 'ble Lt:Col: C.C. J. Barrett, C.S.I. / Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Sir, | In continuation of my letter Uo, 2/29/1031 dated the 7th September 1929 I have the honour to report that I was noti fied on the morning of September 13th by the Governor of Mohamme. rah that orders have been received not to harrass ra- weirds, ihe Governor informed me that he would issue the necessary instruc tions in order to stop the enforced registration. As far as I know between 10 to 20 of the leading Baiireini^ merchants have been forced to register tiiemseiioa. I am preparing a list of these persons which I will forward when completed with the request that the Persian Government may be induced to cancel their registration. This I consider most necessary to preserve the's .i»t_s quo' and to avoid plecine these Pahreinis, who were oo-erced, at a disadvantage vis-a-vie their more fortunate compatriots. Although this is satisfactory yet the illegal and unjustifiable arrest and deportation of Haji Hamid, whom the local Bahrein! merchants regard as their leader has absolutely terrorised and dispirited all Bahreinis. »ith the example of Haji Hamid's fate before them they feel that the only result of resisting the demands of the police and of asking the Consulate for help is to increase their own difficulties and to eajjose themselves to imprisonment and deportation.(&amp;) B Furthemore my house and the Consulate are closely watched day and night. My servants even complain that people, especially Bahreinis and Iraqis are afraid of being seen talking to them in the 'bazar. It is therefore very difficult for anyone to come to see me, I anticipate that the local chief of police, who has never yet paid the smallest attention to the Governor's orders and indeid scarcely treats him with ordinary respect, will still 6 endeavour surreptiously to worry dticeni these unfortunate Bahreini He evidently hopes 'by surrounding me with his spies and by intimidating all Bahreinis and 'Iraqis who come to see me to render me powerless to intervene, I cannot therefore urge too strongly the absolute necessity of inducing the Persian Government to allow Kaji Hamid to return to carry on his trade in Mohammerah. In my opinion this, this alone, can prove to Bahreinis in particular and British protected persons in general that British protection still stands for something in this part of the worlds Secondly I am convinced that so long as irresponsible police officials suffering from acute anglophobia complicated are allowed to remain in Abadan and Mohsanmerah so long will there be a succession of incidents calculated to embitter relations between ourselves and the Persians. I therefore request that representation be made to the Central Government to secure the removal or promotion of these 1 zealous' off icials, I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant. ^ Captain, Acting British Vice-Consul,CONFIDEHTIAL. Wo. 135/446-S. of 1929. British Kcsidency and Consulate-General, Buahire, 16th September 1929. Sir, I have the honour to forward a copy of a report, Mo. 2/29/1091 of the 14th September 1929, receiT- ed from the Vice-consul at Mohammerah regarding the harassment of the Bahrainis at that port, and the de portation of their leader Haji lUmid. In pursuance of the Minister of Court*8.pro mise to you (mentioned in your telegram ao. 117 of the 11th September 1929) orders have been issued to did- continue the harassment of the Bahrainis, but it would appear that the cancellation of any deportation orders passed against Haji Hamid is necessary before the status quo «an be considered to have been restored. It will be seen that Captain i'letcher further complains that he himself, his staff and the Consulate are closely watched day and night. he informs me that he now knows his guards very well by sight.j-^ C^K state of affairs such as this cannot fail to have an extremely bad effect on the Arab coast of the Gulf, where we rely so largely on our prestige to main tain our position. I recommend therefore that if you see fit, the attention of the rersian Government should be called to a situation vtoich, if it has not alreadydone so/*\/ 'V - 2 « so, must soon create a scandal at Mohajamerah and there after throughout the Gulf. A copy of this despatch is toeing sent to the Foreign Secretary to the Governraentjof India. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient, huiable serrant. cJl 4 H.lHs. Consul-General for ifras, Khuzistan, etc., &amp; Political Hesident in the Persian Gulf. A copy of the foregoing is forwarded to the British Vice-Consul at Mohammerah for information, reference his letter Ho. 2/29/1091 of the 14th instant Attested: v \ \ ic# for Secretary to the Political Hesident in the Persian Gulf. Bushire» 16th September 1929.Extract from demi-official letter dated the 1.3th September 1929 from Captain 75.W. Fletcher, Kohanmerah, to The Fondle Lt.-Gol. C .G .J. Barrett, C.S.I., C.I.E., Political 'Resident in the Persian iHIPE RtSlDFNCY. No. . r - ./b iMMiUtt.TwL teCUliliS. jiiy Thank you very much for y Governor has had orders not to worry the Balirainis but I'm afraid the damage is done. .No Iraqi or Bahrain! dare come near me and I 'm watched by thepolice the v/hole time. It is pretty sickening as if only the registration had been stopped straight off, Haji Hamid, is theleader of the Bahrainis here would never have been arrested and deported. I feel that I've been made a fool of by these slimy Persians I I do hope that the Chief of Police is shifted. Though orders have been given it is 1 think pretty clear that the police mean to carry on intimidating Iraqis and Bahrainis but hope to terrotise them so much that they dare not come to me to complain. Hence the guards round my house. I actually had three soldiers visiting my compound 3 times in the night but a word to the Governor has kept them away now. The Governor General got hold of Haj i Jassim, a leading Bahrain! here, and caned him for allowing Bahrainii to come to complain to me and far causing such a row. J I wish to Godour people in Tehran would insist on H j Hamid's being brought back and on our people enquiring into the police methods used. 1 go on fightinh btat the concentrat ed espionage is defeating me.Oonfidantial. No.2/29/1111 of 1929. Vice-Gonsulate, Mohaiamerah,20th September 1929. ij'rom Oartain L. /.Fletcher, A^-.British Yice-Consul MohammBrah, P£?IDSNCV. V To ^ | ^ W hhg.'i iai RtCCilCS. I Sir, The Hon'bleLt-Ool.C.G.J.Barrett, G.S.I., C.I.E. rolitical Resident'in the Persian (}ulf, B U S H I R E. .\\ P lAl ^ith referenige to my despatch No*2/29/1091 dated the 14th September and my telegram No.73 dated the 16th Sep- teraber 19(d9, I have the honour to report that the Bahreinis are not now being molested^ The new Rais Sejil Ihwal (chief registration officer) is advising them not to state that they were force J. to register but the Bahreinis so advised do not appear to be paying much attention to him. k list of the Bahreinis who were forcibly registered is attached# Until the Consul,Basrah, informed me of the seizure of Hal i Eamid's / pas sporty I was una.-/are of this fact. J *4iuL 4- a . wh'k- jiii- A copy of a petition from Haji Hamid is attached. I am personally quite satisfied that the only reason for his expulsion was that by his action he prevented the 3ah- rsinis from becoming Persian^ subjects, and I do not for one moment believe that he was engaged in any political intrigue. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obe ient servant. (^V ^ptain. Ag« British Vice-Consul.Copy ! Basrail ISth September 19 1929. To Sir, H# Bali's Coneul^ Mo iiamme rah. I -ave the honour to infom you that on the 6th instant p.m. I Wi. elvti, ; g i n the c and suddenly a Police cs-e and told me that the Eaie wants you I went with him and san Mr Peroze Di n was sitting at Haji Jetha godown I asked hin to ^ accompany me to the Police Station but he replied me go with the -olice I siiall come behind you I went with tho « you i went witn the police and saw the ^ais presented him my sincere salute hut vw j xu^ere saxute but his answer was calling ^e names against the rules of Wlquette and told me you want to spoil the Persian Government and I told him how am I going to spo il the Persian Goyerment when I am a poor man trying to earn -y daily .read and told me not to speak and orders me to prison, tne inspector searched ma he took out from my pocket one watch and chain one Cigarette box full and a box of matches and my shop keyeand re '- Bained ^ ^il for 4 full nights and one day at last a police came took me from the Jail and put me in a taxi and told ^ 1 haVe n0 rigllt t0 come Country but he took my passport from me by force may I very kindly request yourtx P.indness as to allow me to call t a ck to Mohaimerah to support me when I am away from my house and this is exactly according to laws when a man has been deported from his country innocently tie should be supported until such time is ellapsed and the all reason was because I use to report to the British Consulate and all this trouble I met with it i^for the only love of the Britiah Government and was trying my utmost to your subjecte and those who are under your protection and if it was not for ^e 311 V ' 0Uld haTe Changed tileir Nationality I may very kindly request your kindness a. to help by returning back to ^nmerah I --'lay add that I received from the C. I. D. Off leer Mr Inayatr ^ Inay&amp;tullashali the Bum of Rs 30/- thiry rupees and t&lt;o days ago the British Consul at Basrah had send for me and told me not to worry as I have already informed all those concemai and in short time you shall return 'back to your country if your kindness knew that my return will 'be soon I shall be highly obliged to your kindness to let me know so that I may 'be ready to your service and oblige I have the honour to be, Sir Yours obedient servant 3d Haji Hamid Behraini c/o H, B.^'s Consul, Basrah-No. 5'3 5^/5'. of 1348 Office of /the Adviser to the Government. Be hie in. B? ted, 19th P/Th ny 1348 To H. 3. M's Political ngrnt, Bahrai... Memorandum H. E. Shaikh Hwd is anxious that the Bahrain Government should commence issuing regular book passports as soon as possible o' t l sfc'Ti e style as us cat* you v .ould inform us whether th ^re is any objection to this being done. ^he passports woul similar to those of Fuacat with necessary alterations. . dviser to the Government, Bahrain,Ho. t~S of 1929. iiritiah Hesiaeacy &amp; Gonuuiate-iienejal, iiUBhire # the ZQth September 192J. To The Political Agent, Bahrein (at Karachi)# Memoranduu. Reference memorandum from the Adviser, -bahrein iitate, to your address, Ko#5^7/15, dated 19th it /Than^ 1546, The Muscat Government Issue single 0 sheet passports, not in book form. 13y order, Captain, Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Copy to the Indian Attache, jsahrein, with reference to hie memorandum So.1130 dated tne 23id Sept^iter 1^9. H iiCONFIDENT TAL. /J? Ko. 2/29/^ of 1929 H, B, M's Vice-Consulate, Hohammerah, theVlfk September 1929, From To Captain 3. W, Fletcher, Acting British Vice-Consul Mohamine rah. The Hon 1 'tie It-Col; C. C, J, Barrett, C. S. I # ,C. I.E. , Politics^. Resident in the Persian Gulf f Bushire, Sir, k In continuation of my letter No. 2/29/1111 dated the 20th September 1929 I have the honour to report that the Persian police deny having confiscated Haji Hamid'e passport, 2, I saw Haji Hamid in Basra on 25th September 1929. He stated that the Persian Consul asked him to visit him* On complying the Consul stated that there would be no difficulty in granting HaJi Kamid permission to re-enter Persia if he wrote a letter tl'u fellowiutjh Uiiiuia acknowledging (a) That as Bahrein belonged to Persia he, as a Bahreini, was a Persian subject, (b) That he would willingly register himself as a Persian subject on his return to Mohammerah. This move on the pert of the Persian Consul appears to be prompted by the protest made by the Administrative Inspector on the subject of the deportation of Haji Hamid ^to 'Iraq without notificaticr j 3, Haji Hamid assures me that he does not intend to comply with the request of the Persian Consul, I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant. A \ / '&amp; .a. CLL **j *&gt; t- C /u Captain, Acting British Vice -Consul. t ■: R4/L Dated 27th September, 1923. No. C /II3 Office of the Political Agent, Bahrain. { at Katachi) BUSH 'PT P^SIOrNCY. J From To Captain G.G.Prior, I. A. Political Agent, Bahrain. The Hon^le the Political Resident, in the Persian Gulf, Eushire. fc**iuQi. ■ i.-i ftc€l Sir, &lt;i ^y I have the honour to say that tv /o months ago I forwarded a petition from one of the leading Bahrainis in Muhammerah regarding the hardships of their lot, and the inaoility ol the British Consul to protect them. This petition was addressed to His Excellency Shaikh Hamad, and invoked his aid. He gave it to me asaying that he was certain that txie : ritish Govern- ment would help the Bahrainis. It appears from recent telegrams that I have received that this hope is a vain one. 2. The leading Shia Bahama have now requested the Advi ser to remind me about this petition, as «hey say tuat their relations are subjected to innumerable vexatious restrictions and regulations in Muhammerah, a^-d are also obliged to wear Pahlevi hats. I understand, from other sources tiiau txie^y are in hourly danger of being forced to sign Persian nationality papers and permanently becoming Persian sibjects. 3. I understand that our lac^: of support of Bahrain suo- jects in Persia is principally based on the fact that Bahrain is not a British Protectorate, and were it so the British Gov ernment would be bound to protect tLem as i^ protects the sub jects of Indian States. The legal fiction that Bahrain is imi in an independent state may serve our purpose, but it can not be said to be founded xs fcE in honesty, and I do not think that any Arab is deceived for a minute by a policy which, while manipulating the resources 01 Bahrain in our interests, decline to protect its subjects, to allow them to protect themselves or to ally themselves with other states who might do so.Page 2. i?' ^ 4. In the last decade v/e have intervened in Bahrain to an % extent which would have raised a storm of protest in any In dian state. V/e have deposed the Ruler, deported his rela.- tions, fixed the customs tariff to suit our interests, forced the State against its will to grant a customs rebate to our ally Bin Saud, involving trie State in a loss of a lakh of ru pees annually, deprived the Ruler of jurisdiction over all foreigners, and decided what Europeans he may and may not em ploy. We have refused the State a free hand with their min- ea^rl resources, and have been guided in the matter soiijc almost entirely by our own interests, finally the ruler of this 1 inde pendent ' state is not to be allowed to correspond with the Oil Company working his concession except through the inter mediary of the Political Agent. 5. It should not be supposed that tiiis is in any way a set off for expenditure incurred by ti.e British Government in Bahrein, for with tne exception of a small annual contri bution to a charitable dispensary which has a political value, the British Government have incurred no expenditure upon the Islands at all. In 1926, when it was necessary to send two platoons of Indian Infantry to restore order, the State met all expenses incurred to the last anna, and when at the same period, a Naval detachment was quartered in the /-gency, the State even paid for cooks for them. The State is under no \ obligation for the establishment of a wireless Stattion, for it is the only one that pays in the Gulf, nor for the Indian Post Office which brings in an annual profit of over -0,000 rupees per annum to the Indian Government. 6. It is perfectly clear that Bahrain is in no sense an independent state, and il v/e wish to maintain a rep^taoion for fair dealing on the -~rao Co^j^t, we must not o.8ic*ult in our liabilities, and must pay the price .hich our acts of sover eignty incur. Upon my return I shall be asiced by Kis Excel lency what is being done to protect . aharna in . Luhamnierah, am I reouest that I may'be informed what reply I should give him. If there be no objection I request that a copy ci this des-No. 116 British Legation, Tehran, September 26th n His Britannic Majesty's Representative presents his compliments to His Majesty's Consul -General a t Bushire and transmit herewith, copies of the documents mentioned in the subjoined Scheduli^J^;— Reference Note to the Persian GoverH- llamadi Haji Abood ment, September 2&amp;th,1929. Bahrein!. Copies have been sent to t and Ahwaz. he Foreign Office, Baghdad,r\ No . \\\^ ,^U' A Confidential HIS Majesty's Ag: Consul at BASRA presents his compliments to r : 1 ne political Resident, Bush ire, and has the honour to transmit to him the nndftr -mentioned documents. B ri tish... .y.P.Q j .. BASRA eptember 50^1925... j Hcfevence to pvcvious covrespoude7ice: Basra despatch No. 1016 dated September 9J929 Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. \ «. v' Copy of despatch No.1104 dated September 50,1929 f r om this Consulate to H.M.Minister, Tehran. Ref: Confiscation of Passport of Ali (Haji (Abdul) Hamid) British protected person, subject of Bahrein State, by the^Persian authorities.3o. 1104. yilf-ldcntisU British Consulate, B A S 1 A, tepteubcr JO, 19-?• Sir, /f-i 2 ' '.1th reference to ay doenetch lie, 101 J af t epteaber 9th MgarAlng the treataeat Bote&lt;l out by the /ere lan authorities at ; ohaa.aerah to a certain Sahreini, I have the honour to transmit to you herewith a translation of a letter »hloh I have reoeivea regarding the action taken in this case by the Persian Consul at Basra. The gist of this letter was sent to you in ay telecraa of eptea'. er 2Cth. , 7, 1 regret that a confslon occurred, by which the aaiae of the complainant was giwen in ay t eepaich taifier reference as All son of Ilaji Bms14» His real ntme is i aji ( Mul) llaaid. J, 1 hare applied a «y tests that I cog Id think of to his sto r y, and believe it to be sabatantlaliy accurate, tiiouf 'h I have no doubt the Persian Coesul woul «i deny s good deal of it. There were of course no witnesses at the interview, though plenty to the fact of its hevirip taken place. Bat not only does the account fit well with what Captain Fletcher has told ae of the present situation in ! oluuusereh, but there seeias to ae to be intornol evidence in its favour. For instance, the reference to T .uqta and ielhiyah would hardly have occurred to a aan ulster, tieh Lcgt' llon,Translation of mMms&amp;ss letter from llaji Haaid Bahreinl dated 26th September to H .B.M's Consul, Basra. *' ''ti' 'I beg to report that on the ?3rd Kepteaber 19f9» the Persian Consul, Basra, sent for me, and w :;en I went to him, he questioned me as follows:- Q - Are you a Muslim? A - Yes. Q - Are you a Shi'a? A - Yes, Q - Do you pray? A - Yes. Q - I do not think that you are a Muslim, as a Muslim should be the subject of a Muslim Government. You know that the people of Luqta and Salhiyah in spite of the lostes they suffered thereby, changed their nationality and became lersian subjects. The Iraq Government brought great pressure to bear on them in order t o prevent them from chang ing their nationality, but they bore all their hardships and said they were Muslims and therefore wanted to become Persian subjects; consequently they did change their nationality and became Persian subjects. You Bahrainis who live in Persia and call yourselves Muslims are friendly with an infidel ('Kafir') Government and at variance with Islam. And for this very reason we have treated you (all) harshlyharshly and banished you frosi our country so that you should change your nationality anc; become Persian subjects, so that the English should not meddle with Bahrein and claim that Bahrein belongs to India. ■ o you know why you have been turned out of liohaamerah? Ho. I did not do anything which deserved banishment from the place where I lived. I have received a report from hais-al- iiazmiyah, Mohammerah, in which he tells me that y u are a helper of the British Government. The most important incident occurred oil September 4th, when you were sitting that evening in the coffee shop which was full of men, and, on t .e British Consul happening to pass that way riding, got up from your seat and saluted him. This is a thing which affects greatly^the political situation of our Government, and yet you say you d id not do mything of consequence; this was the whole reason. If you want to return back to 2 ohammerah, submit an applictition and say: 'I a B hrefiiii and ui Bahrein belongs to crsia, I shall be obliged if you will please grant a passport for the journey to rohammerah'. On your doing this, I will issue you a passport' and will give you letters to the Khuzistan Government, and you will return back to the place of your resid nee well respected.'Telegram P.ilo .^555-S, dated, the 22nd August 1929. \ From - Viceroy (Foreign and Political Department), Simla To - Secretary of State for India, London. Bahrein passports. We recommend Shaikh suould be allowed to issue permits for use on Arab Coast of Gulf^ and for .Bahrainis travelling to destinations outside the Gulf and to Persian ports passports similar in form to those issued by civilised countries. Our special position at Bahrain makes it desirable that passports should be endorsed by Political Agent, but he need not concern himself with permits. This is in reply to your telegram 1871 of 12th June.Telegram P.No.2926, dated 21st (reed. 22nd) September 1929. ^rom - Secretary of State for Inaia, London. To - Viceroy (Foreign and Political Department), Simla. ■si His Majesty's Government approve your proposals / ( contained in your telegram Ko.2556-S of the 22nd ultimo. regarding issue of permits and passports to Bahrainis by Shaikh.Confidential. Mo. J -S. of 1929. British ncsidency and Consulate -General, Bush ire, 12th October 1929. A copy of the under -rnenUone^ iwper is forwarded to the Political Acent,**&gt; Bahrail^for ir.formtlon. reference thi» office meraorandum Ho. 496-S. ?f the Ist October 1929 to the Indian Asnistant at Bahrain, a copy of which wan forwarded .to V s By Order, '^1'° for Secretary to the Political Hesident in the Persian Gulf. Subiect: Oppression of Balirain subjects at —— Moharimerah. -t Bote from H.JI'a. UiniBter at ^ehrwi to the Persian Governsnt dated the 26th September 19^9. UJeceived under endoromaent Ho. 116 of 2oth September 1929 from Tehran) | ^ _Translation of a petition dated the ^9th Septemoer idZd from Haji Hamid Banreini at Basraii to h. B, k's Vice-Consul I^oha^me rari. I 'beg to inform you that I was summoned 'by the Persian Consul at Basrah on the 25rd September 1929 and asked whether I am a Mohammedan and a 8hia end whether I pray, tfhen I replies in the affirmative he told me that he did not think so. He added that if I were a Mohammedan I would not consent to be a British subject but on the contrary prefer to be under the protection of^onammedan Government. He exuorted me to follow the example of the people of G-ata and SalMyeh ^ho cein^ Mohammedan inspite of great loss and pressure from the 'Iraq Government preferred to come under the protection of tne Persian Government, He stated that Bahreinis are residing in Persia and claim that they are Mohammeaans but tiiat they are under the protection of a Kafar Government which is against Mohammedans. The Persians are therefore hard on the ^ahreinis and deporting from Persia so that they may change ti.eir nationality and become Persian subjects. This is done in order that the hfiiyrl ri Government may not claim that Bahrein belongs to them. After that he asked me whether I know why I was deported from Mohammerah, I replied that I haa not committed any offence which merited deportation. ^He stated that the Hals- YIASKAAJ i-Nazmiyeh of Mohanmerah had iwfothat 1 was helping the British Government ano that on the 4th September 19^9 when the British Consul was riding past a coffee shop I saluted nim the presence of the crcv-JLin the coffee shop. This the Persian Consul said constituted a big crime against the Persian Govern ment. He then asked me what I intended 'vO ao and told me that if I wish to return to Mohammerah I should peition to him stating that I am a Bahrein!, that Bahrein belongs to tne Persian Government,that I am a Persian subject and that I shoul ask for a Persian passport to return to Mohammerah. Then he said he would give me a Persian Passport with a letter to the Governor General. Sd/-HAJI HAMID.^3 Translation of a petition dated the 29tii September 19Z9 From. HaJ i haiaid at Basrah to H. E, L's Vice-^onsul,Moiiaiiimerah., m I beg to inform you that on the 15tli September ldZ9 I sent a letter to your goodsel^, regarding my return to Mohammerah, I had asked you either to arrange for me an allowance for my expenses or to allow me to change my nationality as I cannot put myself into further trouble, your goodself is aware that I am a business man and ti.at my shop is closed; I have last about RsiOOO/- and my family is in great difficulty in Mohammerah, I therefore beg to request your goodself to help me, I unaerstana tnat the Rais-i-Kazmiyeh has stated that he has not taken my passport; he nimself forced me to open the shop and to bring out the passport and he himself took the passport fro a me by force in the presence of Safani Dendashti and Mirza kurteza Knan photographer. When I requested him to return ti^e passport he refused to do so. I request your goodself to take back my passport from the Nazmiyeh. Sd/. Haj i Hamid.Copy in translation of a letter from r -ushar -ul-Julk, the Persian llinister for foreign Affairs, addressed to tiis Majesty 1 s Minister, Tehran. No. 1^E79 dated Dalve 8th 1^0^ (28th January, 1925). Tvlonsienr le llinistre, On Aghrah 27th last (Noveraber 19th 1924) Mr. Monson had addressed me a letter Ho. ^04 in connection with a certain Hainadi the son of Haji Abood, an inhabitant of Bahrein. The matter was referred to the Consulate at Basra for enquiries. I beg now to state that it appears from Mr. Monson's letter that, as Hamadi the son of Ilaji Abood has obtained a British passport in Bombay, he is considered as a (British) protected person and they want the Persian official to visa his passport for his coiran^ to Persia, while, according to a report received from +he Persian Consul at Basra, Hamadi, the son of ilaji Abood, is one of the indisputable Persian subjects who had proceeded to India where he obtained, by misrepresentation, a British passport. Besides, there is no doubt that the man cannot be an inhabitant of India since he has an Arabic name, and he has always been recognised as a Persian subject. Your Excellency will admit that the visa of a foreign passport means recognition of the nationality. But, how can a Persian official give visa to the passport of a person whom he recognises as a Persian subject ? I avail e to., (Signe d) LIushar-ul-Uulk.Co P5 T i n translation of a note from the Direotor-'^eneral of the . inistry for foreign Affairs to His I'ajestr's .minister, Tehran. Ho. 80 78 dated Uehr 20th 1^08 (October 12th t 1929). Monsieur le Llinistre, In reply to four Excellency's two notes of Shahrivar 19th last (September 10th) No. ^10 and Kehr 4th (bepteraber 26th] No. ^42 I have the honour to state that in regard to liaji Kamadi son of Ha^i Abood I have enquired about ^he facts from the Governor of Khuzestan through the Ministry of the Interior as I was ignorant of the details. If it is found out that a British passport has been issued to him in India, which has been rightly confiscated, the passport will be sent to His Majesty's legation for return to the issuing office. At this Juncture I deem it necessary to invite four Excellency's attention to Llirza Hassan Khan Mushar's note to Mr. llonson, the then British Charge d ? Affaires dated Lalve 8th 1^0^ (28th January 1925) No. 1^279, purporting to the Persian nationality of the said Hamadi in question. Your referring to the discussions going on with His Highness the Minister of the Court in the course of Your Excellency's note ITo. ^42 gives me occasion to point out that the said discussions in no way alter the views of my Government in regard to the British authorities not being entitled to interfere with the affairs concerning the Bahreinis. I avai1 e tc., (Signed) Hassan Ali Khan CJhaffari.Copy of 'Minute' by Sir R.Clive. Haji Abood Bahreini. I gave him (Teymourtache) copy of note of September 26th to Persian CJovernment. 2. He said only possible official reply to this note was that Persian Government did not admit our right to protect Bahreinis in Persia. 3. I said there were three separate points in our note: A. Return of confiscated passport. B. By what right had this man been dumped into Iraq G. I expressed the hope that the man would be allowed to return to Mohammerah. 4. le promised to settle A. t to enquire into B., and to look into possibilities of C. 5. He said he believed note from Persian Government was on its way on basis of paragraph 2. I said surely we could settle this on an unofficial basis so that the man could return, (see paragraph 4). H.H.C. 13/10/29.* ft GONFIDKNTIAL No. ^ ^ -Li. of 1929. British Rosidency and Consulate-General, Bushire, ^ October 1929. A copy of the undermentioned papers is forward' to tho Political Agent, Bahrain, for information in con- -tinuation of this office endorsement No. 517-3, dated 12th October 1929. By order, for secretary to the Political Besident in the Persian Gulf. 1. 2. 3. Suh.lect. Oppression of Batoain subjects at l/o hammer ah. / t» From Persian Minister for Foreign Affairs to H.I/*s. Minister, Tehran, No. 13279, d. 28.1.25. From Director General of the Ministry for Foreign Affairs to H.li's. Minister, Tehran, No. 8078, d. 12.10.29. W Hinute by Sir B. Clive, dated 13.10.29. ^719/109 7^ Telegram From To Hep ea ted H* Senior ^aval Officer, -Triad- Bushireradio Political Resident, Eushire, No 84, II. ^*s. Minister, Teheran. No 33. Dated 3rd reed 4th. Novemher 1929. U rgent , Following from Vice Consul Kohammerah 'begins, I^a^i Haiaid Bahrein! who returned to llohaiiimerah from Basrah with Persian passport has now been arrested and put on hoard steamer -Vasna- for Bushlre governor informs me this was done in accordance with orders from Teheran Acting Vice Consul . Ends • Senior Naval Officer, Telegram From To No li03. Dated ^.th November 1929, B. Political Resident, Bushire, Vice Consul IJohammerah. Ypur telegram No 34. Haji Hamid. Presume Sir R. Clive has heen informed. ::as he suggested any course of action. ? Resident. No.IX'b'i Confidential HIS Majesty's Ag: Consul at Basra presents his compliments to The Political Resident, Bushire and has the honour to transmit to him the under-mentioned documents. -•5p British P.O^SUlate, BASRA ? _ he under-mentiom iwiM. /&gt;. 4* l f' Uj.fflliti. I'IaL RECORDS* -U i October 29, 19 29 Reference to previous correspoiidence: Basra despatch No. Til5 dated September 50,1929 Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Copy of despatch No.1231 dated October 29.1929 from tnis 1 ' Consulate to H.M.Minster, Tehran. \ \, V ' Kef: Confiscation of Passport of Ali (Haji (Abdul) Hamid) British protected person, .subject of Bahrein state, by the Persian authorities.i t • • gntial British CouBulate, BASRA, 'Iraq# Octotoer 29, 19 5* Sir, With reference to ay eocf ifleatlal despateh Ko. 1104 of Beptember 3 (; . ' nu previous correspondence, I have u -e honour to report a further development In the case of iiaji Hnaid Bahrain!. 2, A few days ago the Ad«ini6trativ» Inspector informed me that he unders auc that the Persian Consul had received instruc tions to issue Travel Permits, containing no mention of nationality, to persons helievec to possess dual nationality who required to travel to Persia. I verified the fact over the telephone, and the Persian Consul told B e that he oonslclered Bahralnis to come under this ruling. I specifically mentioned the case of Kajl Kamid, and he promised to issue such a Travel Pe«lt if requestea. 5, I then instructed Haji ilaaid to apply for the permit, and he did so. The following day, October r /th, he returned and showed me the following documents:- on. the U) ^n^t 'iSod 0 * ■b the Consul. In his application Hail Haaid clearly H. M. Minister, British Ration, ,2. clearly stated that he was a Bahralni, born at Bahrain, and dcslreci a permit to travel to Mohamerah. He said nothing about nationality. 5. Nevertheless the ersian Consul, in the nassport, described hi^i as 'Mohamerahi', and gave his birthplace as llofaAfttterftlu That is to say, he affirmed over hi» seal aiid aifmature a statcsaent which he well knew to be A false. The case has been discussed often enough between us to preclude any possibility of a mistake. Further, in spite of his promise to ©e that he would issue a document containiug no mention of nationality, he slipped in, under the heading n Heligion M , the words*Mllliet-i~ Irani', presusaably hoping that I would not notice them. 6* The letter to the ohaaiaerah authorities containe a good deal of verbiage about Haji Haiaid # s ,, criaea tf f his repentance for the«, his mhmisBion to the Pdrsian fiMMnriU •»&amp; aore to tite sa^e effect. 7, I have not discussed the iaatter with the Persian Consul since seeing the passport. 1 felt there was little to be gained by ay doing so, and I could hardly have done so without Bore or less pointedly giving hia the lie, which Z thought it inadvisable to do. I told Haji Haaid to point out t^c wrong birthplace.birthplace, aad ask for it to bealterea, but I cannot say whether he has done 30. He has now returned to ohaaiacmh, and Dr. Lincoln inforae ae that he has proaptly been pnt under close police Burveillance, on the ground that he possesses a British passport (lesued by jae) as well as the new Persian one. 8 t I sua sendiag copies of this despatch to the Foreign Office, His Majesty's High Coiaialaeioner for ' raq, the Political Eesident, Bu shire, and his Majesty's Vioe-Consul at ohaiamerau. I have the !ionour to be, sir* Your Eiost obedient, husble servaiit, E. iUGM SLLISO*. ACTISO BRITISH Cf®BUL./&lt;r/M Telegram E. From To. v !To 35. Dated 5th Noveiober 19 29. Yice Consul, Mohaimnerah. Political Resident, Eushire. Urgent. 4 1 grain !To 1103. Your telegram following from Hinster, 'begins:. £ rt I return Teheran November 6th and will speak to Minister of Court chout treatment of Haji Hamid. Persian attitude in regard to Bahreinis as defined to me 'by Minister of Court Is as follows;- In case of official representations Persian authorities will assert Persian nationality of all Bahreinis and refuse to admit )«r rig! t to intervene. On the other hand Minister expressly said that Persian Government were j nxious jfo avoid contentious tissue pending result of my negotiations anu would, ceas^ registration of Bahreinis and other forms of pressure.^ you might speak unofficially to Governor i ahout Haji Hamtd, explain attitude of Persian Government as expressed 'by Minister of Court and sx$1&amp;±r express hope that Eaji Eamid may 'be left in pe^ce, without making any representations on his hehalf or of course in an^; way admit ^Lnfe that we accept Persi? n Off teal contention. Lincoln, •5 /V crl^r ^ &gt;■No. 127 C. The Agency&gt; Bahrain. 4th November 1929. Dear Colonel Since my return many of the Bahama headed 'by the Q,adhi have been to see me to complain about the treatment their relatives have undergone at Muhammerah. The ^adhi sopke unpleasantly plainly, and inquired why, if we said we would pro tect Bahrain* we did not do so. I was somewhat embarassed by it and told him that great improvement had been made in their * condition, to which he merely replied that they should never have been allowed to fall into that condition. to reflect upon my colleagues but I think you ought to know at any rate what they feel ) that the good work the'new consul 1 { apparently Fletcher ) did will now come to an end and that with the return of the*old one* their trouble will begin again. They spoke very plainly and tlaid that their informants who wrote JtialtiZ, - from Basra said that they coulfl expect nothing from the 1 old one * as he was too intent on the interests of Persians, and took no notice of their complaints, and that it was a waste of time to go to him. result has been to make a breach between the Bahama and the Per sains, which is not altogether unprofitable, and to make them better disposed to the Shaikh for representing their grievances (x±i to you I list of Bahama at Debai who have complaints, and he requests that since we are supposed to protect them will I please look into the matter. Will you please let me know, by letter if possible how I stand in the matter They all seem much afraid ( it is not my duty There is much feeling about it here, and the Ahmed bin Khamis has been to see me with a Yours sincerely19 ' Telegram. Code. 'From - Brttconsul, ITohammerah. To - Kesident, Bushire. No. 86. Dated and received 11th November 1929. Understand Haji Hamid proceeded Karachi presume you have or will inform minister. Family request good offices of Commissioner of Karachi. * Britconsul.19/109. Telegram P* T?PQjfi political xlesident&gt; iSusLiire. To H. r's. Minister, Teheran. No 126. Dated 13tli November 1929. Haji Hamid Bahraini proceeded to Karachi. This is second time he has 'been dexjorted, and on this occasion it appears to have loeen under direct orders from the Capital in spite of Teymourtache expressed desire to avoid contentions issue. Anti Persian sentiment in Bahrein is seriously exacerbated hy these actions ot Persian authorities. I trust it will 'be possible to induce Persians to refrain from them pending outcome of negotiations. The foregoing refers to your telegram of 5th November from hammer ah and Mo hammer ah* s telegram No 33 of 3rd November. Resident.n No. l'^ CONFIDENTIAL HIS Majesty's Consul at Basra presents his compliments to The Political Resident, Bus hi re, and has the honour to transmit to him the under-mentioned documents. BU' Bnto^.Consulate., BASRA. A fhi. A I Ni« .. 'j/b'li' Vj FIAL fitOGiiDo. j llovenber 22 9 * Reference to previous correspondence: Basra despatch No. 12&gt;5 dated October 29, 1929- Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Copy of despatch No. 1555 dated 22-1 1-1929 together with its enclosures from this Consulate to H .M.Ministe Tehran. Confiscation of Passport of Haji Hamid Bahrein!, British protected person, subject of Bahrein State, by the Persian Authorities. (V^ w r I- 1 . / *British Con»iil»te, BALE A, *1 r • 4* SoTe after 22» l!?2i&gt;. Sir, 70 In contixuMtion at m» Vico-tonsul Ellison's despatch lio. 12^1 of the 29th ultiao reieting to tie •xperiAneos of lisji Hamid Bahreini, I have toe aonaur to traasait to you herewith a oopy -traAalKtiOB of a letter which I have received i 'raa this unfortunate ansa relating the vicissitudes through which he has passed since his return to lohsamrah froa this port on the ai t .ht of the 23th October. 2» You will observe tnat Uaji ItJid was subjected to the aost absurd police supervision upon his retom to iihamer&amp;h which, des -ite promises, acciM-diiig to his statement, of a return to the noraal, culainated in a sudden and sroitrf-ry expulsion which resulted in a grand tuur of t-e Persian Gulf ana beyond, terainatiaa eventually la Sura vhere, apea ay iaterveution / ilia Authorities have aaovn c msideration and courieaj' in allying Hail He,aid to take up his residence. • At the yxatent j.&lt;uict Haji lieaid, bewildered if not aowt^, j a... appear to bo satitficd to settle d^wn in Baara 'far ever' with his fnaily, end there the H. r. •iniater, British Legation, —a Translctlon of letter dated 15th Kove^ber 1929 froa Hajl Haald Bahrelni to H.B.M'a Consul,Basra 'I beg to state that on the 24th October 1929 I took a Passport and a letter froa the Persian Consul at Basrah, and went to Mjhaamerah on t he 27th October 1929* The Persian Consul had told ae that I should return to lohaaicrah* t iat I would be i llowed to stay * KDr there respectubly as before, but 1 ehould not tlsit the British Consul. lie further asked ae to write to hist in cose I vas in trouble and that ho (the ersian Consul) would try end help ae. ^ f I reaehed 'Johaaaersh on the ni:;ht of the 2 ith October, when the ersian /iuthorities placed a police guard with ae, who acoo apanied ae to ay house and stayed with ae (in ay house) for 5 tys. 2. A Persian who knew of ay interriew with the Persian Consul at Basrs, seeing ae under police-watch, went to iissra and told the Persian Consul Basra of fay trouble. On this, the Persian Consul sent ae a letter for the Eartip (the Governor), end talked over the telephone with the Persian Autaorities in ! ersia to allow ae to open ay shop, and on the 5Oth of October I was allowed to open ay shop at Mohaaaerah. The letter which the iersian Consul had sent to ae for the Eartip was conveyed by me to hiia through iay brother, vsho in an interview was told by the Jartip that the AuthoritiesAuthorities in Mohtuaaierah htd been informed on the telephone that all police watch should be removed from mc # ancl that I ahould be allowed to open my ahop# 5, On the 5rci ol ove.^ber, the T cis-al- MazlalyBh seat for ae and ordered to leave for Bahrein by the aail steaaer ttie eanie day. In anss-er, I told hi a that the steeaer leavixig there on the }rd was not ct llirig at Bahrein, to which he replied;- 'You aust leave by 'to -day* t jaail and go to Bushlre froa where 'you of n go to i chrein» The '.aia —al— Ki .1 liyeii did not allow ae tJ aove froa there and forced ae to sail the saac day. Then the Bteuraor reached Bushire, 1 was ifrsld to lf&gt;nd tuere, fearing the tietit.icnt oi the eraian Authorities at that end. 1 hen I reached Karachi the iissport Officer there took ae to the police Btation, and asked ae why I was travelling without a passport. I replied that I had been turned out froa Mohtiaaerah by the Persian Authorities by force, who d ic not allov ae to go hone to fetch ay passport. Later on, he (the assport Officer) sent ac with a eons table to the Courts, who recorded ay stateaent, and fined ae R e.15/- and let ae go. In the lUth Koveaber, I was cm lied by the Authorities who put ac on bot &gt;rd the #« s •' v ai'ele and told ae: 'Since a passport was issued to 'you at Basra, you shoul- go bf ck to that 'plrcc. n I arrived here yesterday, and was sent under police custody oy tiic ssisi. nt assport Officer, Basra, to the i ort Police '-tation, Ashar,Ashar, v ;h«re I «a held up. 4» Elr, you know case fulls well fr'- beglanins to end, and 1 request you haably to arrange to let ae etay in iiasra» ' intend to lire tk here forever with ay family, who will 3oin rue. 5. A b regards ay passport, I shall oe obliged if you will please ask the fohsiaaerah Consul to Mre 4% directed to .^asra if he has sent it to Karfchi, and in crse it is in i4ohaaaerah still, he aay ask ay brother to produce it to hi a for despatching it to you. Under the oircuaetancee, I request that I aav kindly be allowed to stay lis Baaia.Stateaent of llaji iUwaid iiahrclni with regard to his Tiiiit to the rersian Con»ul«t« on tae 27th )ctober 1929 with a view to get ti\t paes-jort leBtiea to ila by the crsitn Comui Surlhg the aaae aonth, corrected. q . Did you go to the eraien Comulate on the 27th October to get the partlculftra in your peasport issued to you by the ! ersian Consul, iasra, re. your national atatua, corrected, and, if so, did you succeed in your object? A* Yes. I went to the ' ersian Cons uate on the 27th October 1929, and had an interview with the Consul, who told ae to sec his Heed Clerk, Ali Kfieadi, incynnection with the passport. On tals, I e ppro# ched All Lilend! and re&gt;i esteO bl;3 to correct fay passport to read therein t.'iat I was a Bahreiai and wee born at Bahrein and not, as stated in the pass ort, M Mohaajaeraoui, corn at 'ohaaicrah'. He said in reply 'Toa ere a well known Ban P elni 'and it does not aatter to y -u aoch, what is 'stated in your passnort. If any one fl que Bt Ions you on this point you can tell him 'that All Effendi wrote it in toe passport, 'and thnt there was no necessity to c jinge 'the wordias as already written In your 'ps»s :xwt.' I repeated ay request again and again, wny tines, but with no awail. in short he put ae off by stating that ae would not ohaare the wording, as it was not naoevMr, at .11. ^ ^ ^ Uahraiai. 19-11 -29.# - 2 - described ao 'of Uohammerali' instead ol as '01 Jfajiriiin • 4^ A few days after his return to 'omnuaerah how ever he was again arreuteo by the J^ertuan voiice, put on board the British inuia mail steamer and ordered to go to Bush ire. Not unnaturally in view of hir ill-treatment Haji liaiaid aid not winh to land at another Pereian port and proceeded to Karachi, though he liad no paBBport. Un arrrvai at Karachi he wao, according to hia own statenient. % arreuted by the 3inci police, hailed before Uie Cour^r. ana fined • It/- for a contravention ol the paauport regula tions. Finally on the 10th Hovenber he was orOered to leave Karachi and was put on board the SS, VAKKLA ana tola cu return to Basrah since a passport (presumabiy relerence ic to the travel permit issued by the Persian Consul; had been issued to him there. I regret that my telegram to you regarding aiv did not reach you in time: I heard that he )«d been put on bo^rd a ste«w»r for Bushire, and it was only several days later that 1 was au4e to ascertain that he had not landed here but had proceeded to Karachi* 5. yrom the preceding account however it will be seen that Haji Hamid was not to olane, and is on the contrary deserving of sympathy for the gross ill-treatment lo which he nas oeen subjected at the hands 01 the Persian authorities. In the cireumstances 1 ohoulxl be mucu obliged if the fine imposed upon him could be refunded, should this be possible. If so, I should be glad if it could be remitted either to me or to His Majesty's Consul, Basrah, for payment to Haji Hamid, who has now taken up his residence at that port. Also I would venture to ask that if any persons arrive at Karachi who claim to be Bahrain subjects but are not in possession of Britinh passports, a reference should bew ! ^ From No. P p 483. Political Departiuent• Gamp or the Commissioner in Sind, 16th January 1930. „ , f y|JW(r:-c R£8l D r- G A Thomas Esqaire, C i E, 1 C S, .j^ Commissioner in Sind; f- 1^, To lit* The Honoarable Lt. Colonel H V Biscoe, i A, Political Resident in the Persian Galf, Bashire. 3j'bJectHaji Hamid Behrani. Treatment accorded to - Sir, With reference to your letter no. 661-8, dated tne 27th November 1929, on the sabject noted above, I have the honoar to forward a copy of letter no. P P 2, dated the 20th December 1929, from the Superintendent of Police, Karachi Head Quarters, explaining why Haji Hamid Bahrani v, as prosecuted and fined Rs. 15/- under the Passport Eules. in view, however, of the facts stated in your letter, I am sending to you ^or payment to Haji Hamid a sum of is. 15 by ?Joney Order from funds placed at my disposal by Govern ment . 2. The request made in paragraph 6 of your letter has been noted. i have the honour to be, Sir, ^ IT- ^ ^ T,- ^ u\S Mu* Jn^f ¥our most obedient servant. for Commissioner in Sind. m- 3111No. PP. 2 of 1929. Kapachij ^Oth Deceiiibei &gt; 1929. To, 1 h6 Comiuissioner in Sind, ^r^LlTAViT ,,p - 4e3 ' a ' tM Subject;- Haji Hamid son of Haji Abood, Bahreini. Sir, I have the honour to report that Haji Hamid Haji Abood arrived in Karacni irom Mahomuierah by the S. S. 'Vasna' on the 7th ultimo. He had no passport or permit for India in his possession. On being questioned by the Passport Checking Staff, instead of mentioning the fact that he was the victim of ill-treatment at the hands of the Persian authorities, he adopted a defiant attitude and told the Police that he . was no,„ rogue but a well known man in the Gull;, J may mention that previous correspondence regarding the impounding of this man's passport (vide your N os. P.P.-483, dated the 20th September 1929 and the 7th October l 989 respectively) did not ask for unity toi HaJi hamid from the Passport Regulations, ^nd, in these circumstances as hiR 4.. , as nis destination should have been Bus hire find not Kflr^w^vri u iiarachi, he was prosecuted in the court of the Honorary Magistrates, Bench 'B', Karachi, on the 8th November i 9 2 9 and fined Rs. 15/- under the Passport Rules. He W..S provided with a passage to Basrah by the v British Iddia Steam Navigation Company on the loth November 1 9 2 9 . The telegram dated 13th November i 929 frojB the Hon , ble tlie political Regldent in the Persian Sulf was communicated to me on the 14th November and was therefore too late to be acted upon.- 2 - 2. AS regards paragraph 5 of the letter accompanying your reference under reply, j have the honour to ^ the District Magistrate, Karachi, is the authority to ap p i y to the Judicial Commissioner's Court for a revision of the Lower court's order and refund of the fine, m that event the Public Prosecutor for Sind or one of his assistants ' will have to appear in the matter, and the cost to Government for obtaining a refund win he more than the original Tine itself. ^ have ordered the PaRenoy^ i ^ Passpoit Checking Staff to e refer the case of Bahreinis arrivinD- u/i + g wi tihout passports in future for orders before taking action against them. I have etc., Sd/- h , Stanley Superintendent of Police, Karacni Head Quarters,CUh^l^tilA^. kp # v j 0 of i§60 fi« B. M* 0 Vict-Con«ulate # nohennier^h, tii« 17th Pebru&amp;ry 13JO 3ir # I hare th« honour to inform you that 1 te«celT «d a rlsit from the Ooveraor of AVaian thisi morninp who oomplainad that Bahreinis wer^ being induced to re^isMr themaelvee aa Ira^i ns.tionala by the ' Irai iroiics Officer at Pao. He report® tnat Abbas nlffer.di who is the Chief of Police at Pao is interesting niHself in this particular aorement und he quotes the instance of the filio*fln£ fahreinis who aei^trwere enticed across the river frox ^usba and advised to become Ireqi subjects and bsked to endeevour to influai^ce others:* ifibrahi&amp;i of Kahr Alam Mehdi of ^ahr Mahtook Zair Mohd of Kahr Aufi Sayed Shornash of Hahr Abu hamid Jttllah Ayoob of Jiahr Ard^shar The ^ovtjrnor ia moat anxious that Immediate enquiries be made and that Abbas Sffendi be severely reprimanded and advised to desist from his bigh handed actions and She ^ahreinis concerned be persuaded to return to their hOTies at ^usba, 1 suggested th«t pCy £AjXj pei'hapa ^hi-a reason for crofising ov^r to Fao was tnat they were being harrassed and forced to register themselves as Persian subjects, but tiae Governor stinted txiat this was not the case. It is quite poeelble however|that the Bahreinis finding themselves at the present tims watnout a definite national status are endeavouring to transfer their allegiance to the Iraq Oovsrn- ment, ihe Governor added that the question of their nationalit was one which was yet to be decided by our respective Government and THS A£&amp;lftI3TKATIV3 IKSP^CTORCopy of memo rand urn No. 1390/(A, dated the 21st I^amadhaii 48, from the Adviser to the Bahrain Government to the Poli tical .^gent, 3ahrain. ' BU£K!r ~ RESIDENT / ft*. Ho ^*&lt;1 O h .' I?'-' N . mwrlOttTIAL fcCOilGS. i iiith reference to previous corresponaence on tue subject of Persian oppression of Bahrain subjects in Moham- merah ano ^badan, I enclose a letter forwaraec to me by Syed Ahmad bin Syea Alawi which may be of interest to you. No. 311 Political Agency, Banrain, Date a the^^Febr. 1930. Copy forwarded for info ma ti on to the Secretary to the Hon T ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire with reference to the corresponaence ending with his No. aated the /-/£&gt;— 1929. It woula appear that tlie Persian Government are not observing the status quo as they have undertaken to do. Politicar Agent, ~aur&amp;in K/-translation of letter d?ted 1st Ramadkan 1348, from Ha^i Hamid al-Haj Abooa Bahrani, Ashar, Basrah, to Syed Ahmad oin Syed Alawi, Bahrain. After Compliments. Before this, we have forv/arded you many letters, but have not received any reply for sane. I have to draw your kind at tention to the fact that the numerous letters which I send you did not refer to me only, they refer to all Baharina community residing- in Mohammerah and its suburbs ana Abadan ana its sur roundings, as they are in a very bad condition owing to the op pression, injustice and carelessness effectd to them by the Persian Government. »hen any Bahrani is seen holding a Mazwiyiah he is taken by.the policeman to the 'Nadhmiyiah' and the head of the 'Nadhmiyiah' will rebuke him by way of abusive language and then he will take ten Kirans from him and release him. The Baharanis are not disobeying Government oraers at all, they are wearing Persian clothes. But the ^ersi^ns hate the Bahi^ana element, and so they are dealing with them in this way. Please approach your local Government and the Adviser, perhaps for the sake of your ancestors, something will be oone to free them from th^se oppressions. 1 heard from some of my friends that they received a proclamation from Bahrain which was signec by the Adviser, in it was mentioned that all oppressions shoula be removed from being effected to the Baharanas. Nowadays the pressure on Bah^anas have been increased, the Persian Government ————————— ^ never signs the passport of a Bahrani, whether be it/registered one or an ordinary one. ^ny one who leaves for Basrah has to take 'Taskarat Morror' in adaition to the British passport which he holds. Now, no 'taskaras' are ^iven before producing a guaran the tor that when holc.er reaches Basrah, he shoula not change/clothes which he wears in Zo hammer ah, if any one wore a 'chaf iayiah' and 'agal' at Basrah, his guarantor nill be fined five thousand krans Sir, please inform your Government of the above, though it would be difficult for you to do so, as the Bahranas who live in Persia are unable to acquaint you of these, by letters owing-owing to the severe pressure caused to them by the Persiaa Government. Please senc the reply tlx rough the British Consul, Basrah. U.E. K.B. If you wish to sena me the reply direct, you can senc the reply by my following auaress. Haji Eamid Bahrani, Opposite luUsafirkhana Farhat Club, ushar, Basrah.No. 95-3 of 1930. British Residency and Consulate-aeneral, Bushire # 13th March 1930. The Political A^ent. Bahrain. Memorandum. Reference your endorsement flo. 319, dated the 28nd February 1930. i I have rec ntly visited Mohaianerah personally and. made particular enquiries about the treatment of Bahrainis therei and 1 have ascertained that the staterients con- tained in HaJ i Hamid's letter to Rved Ahmed bin t'yed Alawir are largely exaggerations and in some cases in correct. The local Persian authorities are maintaining the modus vivendi, and there is no active oppression of Bahrainis. The present position is admittedly incon venient to Bahrainis when they wish to leave Persia, inasmuch as they have to provide themselves with two passports, a British and a Persian one; but l have hopes that the question of the status of Bahrain will be finally settled very shortly and if so all these difticulties will automatically disappear. HaJ i Ham id * s statement that before a 'taskarah' is issued security lias to be given that the holder \;ill not / change his clothes when he reaches Basrah is, i believe, entirely xk incorrect. Attested : SD/ H. V. Biscoe, Lieut.-Colonel, Political Resident in the Persian gulf. Capt., for Secretary to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf. ,Wg-J! * i ®A /// No. 24. 'f British Legation, Tehran, 25th February, 19^0 &gt; His Britannic Majesty's Representative presents his compliments to His Majesty's Consul-Oeneral at BUSHIRE and transmit herewith, copies of the documents mentioned in the subjoined Schedule. Reference Mr. Selous'e despatch Ho November BEnd, 1929. 7 T &gt;&lt; • 1355 of / To His Highness Teymourtac he. Minister of Court, dated 25th February, 1930. Copies have been sent to Foreign Office, Baghdad, l.Tohainmerah and Basra. Ha^i Hamid ibn Haji Abood Bahreini of Mohammerah.Ho. 124 -S- of i.930« From To Britiah ^'ediaency COiiuuiate-aeiiural, iiubiiir-j, the r J ^Jiarcii i.y30» The iioa'Lle trie political -ue^iuoat in tne Persian Gulf. The Coirmdsaioner iii iii^a, KARACHI. Sir, /t' with reiereuce to your letter Uo.PP.485 datca tne 16/22nd January iy50 f I have tne honour to inform j ou tnat the money order ior Rs.lb/- has since been received# I wish to express my thanks for tne trouuic . ou have taxten in this mtter. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant. iiJL Captain, for Political Kesident in the Persian Gulf,Rs» 1 ^» M 3 -y )I9 No.XH^. . BRITISH CONSULATE, BASRA, IRAQ. Sir, I have the honour to acbhowledge receipt of your despatch No. 125-S of the 21st instant enclosing fifteen rupees for del-very to Haji Hamid Bahreini in respect of the return of the fine imposed upon him 'by the Authorities in Karachi for 'breach of passport rules, and to - enclose herewith Haji Hamid's receipt for the sum in question. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant, A .. n 'A The Hon'ble the Political Resident and Consul-General, British Residency &amp; Consulate-General, BUS )y dc SHIRE,M±l2/z. RECEIVED from li. B. M. Consul 3 Basra the sum of fifteen rupees being a refund of the fine imposed upon me at Karachi for breach of the passport rules. Basra, Signature of Haji Hamid cajN Dated the 25th March,50* Ba ireinjl. A'o*-* yr:\ , : \ i&amp;t fn iuzNo.78.G of 1930# The Political Agency, Bahrain. Dated the, 17th May 1930 (f^j 3'/i7V From Captain G.G.Prior, I.A., Political Agent, Bahrain. To The Hon * hie the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Subject:- Permission granted to the Shaikh of Bahrain in issue permits and passroorts to his subjects. sir ' - S 1 With reference to your endorsement No .506-S dated the 10th October 1S29, I have the honour to inform you that the Bahrain Government will commence to issue their passports and certificates of Identity from 1st June 1930. I have the honour to be, Sir, lour most obedient servant. , Politick! Agent, Bahrain.w\ GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. p 0 1 i 11 oal r,pnjPfB^BT tt KNT. EXPRESS LETTER yO 7\ IN.B. — Jhis is an OBIOINAL MESSAGE, se»&lt; by post to »ave iplegraphic expense and undue use of the mres, out wjwdea to le treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as % fit tiad been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and • signed as if it had been so despatched. \ FaoM -oliti oa' Bahrain# To Resident, Bushire. No. I I Dated 13th July WiO Shiah Qadhi of SANABIS Ali bin Musa states that he has heard from BAHAMA resident at GUSBA ( opposite FAO ) that perse cution of Bahama cornnmced there. Would be glad if inquiries could he miK made in matte aalPO—FP—596DCP-T8&amp;P—C-IW?)—-iW. 000 *BXPRB SS ISTTSR . From To Resident, Bmshlre* Brltconsul, Uohamoierah* Uo. 366-S. Bushlre, dated 23rd July 1930. Political Agenti Bahrain baa heard that Saharna resident at Gueba opposite Fao are lieing persecuted* Please make enquiries and report. RESimNT. ^ ' For Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Oulf #COl.yiJ^TIAL. To No. c/r^/77/ i'^o.. h,B. li ' s Vice-Consulate, rail, the 8 t.u August 19o G. li.p oecretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in t^e Persian Gulf.EU3HIR5. A».kO U4. V ■» . AxU^l., 4 1^1 . Refeionce Express letter l^o.565-S. dated the ^ord July 1930. I visited ti.e Governor of Abadan and had a lengtiiy discussion with hiiu on the subject of the alleged persecution of Bahrainis resident at Gusba. The Governor stated that there was absolutely no truti: in this rumour. Gusba -was under his jurisdiction and ae had not ' heard of a single instance^nor had „e received any complaint. He said t-:at he v/as willing to make enquiries, even though Bahrainis were considered to be Persian subjects and not under British protection, if I could cite one^Tase £:ivin{; details « such as naiues etc,. I told him that I did not wish to discuss the subject of the status of Bahrainis, but I should be £;lad if he would institute enquiries and prevent any persecution. H.B.^» - Consul. ^ P J/•} Pdi L+tST- ■ 'J. JoyTelegram: From; To: No. Dated: a. Political Resident, Bushire Britconsul, Mohammerah 920. 15th October 1930. Your 48. Would certificates of identity assist these people. Persians would presumably not admit their validity , and would not grant exit visas. - resident - Telegram R- • Tr rcm H.M's. Vice-consul, Mohammerah Tc Political Besident, Bushlre. No. 49. Datec 17th receivea Ifith October 1930. Your telegram No. 920. They are secretly going to Basrah vataont Certificates of identi obtaining Persian exit vicas. asssist their entry into Iraq ^ICE CONBTJI.19/109. Telegram From To No.927. Dated 19th October 1930. R. Political Resident, Bushire. Vice Consul, Mohaminerah. Your telegram Ho.49. Have referred matter to Teheran Resident. 53'7 Telegram From To Bepeated 19/109. R. Political Resident, Bushire. H. M^s.,Minister, Teheran. No. 96. G -overnment of India, Simla. No.925. Dated IStti Octo'ber 1930. Following trom Mohamnierah 'begins:- (here insert text of Mo hammer ah telegram No. of 14th Octo'ber). Ends. C/O-/v3 Resident. Telegram P. From Political Resident, Bushire. To E. M^s. Minister, Teheran. No.97. Repeated G-ov eminent of India, Simla. No. 926. Dated 18th Octo'ber 1930. Consul informs me these certificates are required to facilitate entry into Iraq.* There is no great difficulty in getting out of Persia without exit visa. There is strong feeling in Bahrein regarding treatment of Bahreinis in Mohammerah and I have received several representations on subject. If they are conscripted feeling will 'become very acute and Bahrein Government may retaliate hy for instance refusing to recognise foreign nationality of those persons of Persian origin who definitely settled in Bahrein many years ago. Effect would he that such persons would then 'be subject to jurisdiction of Bahrein Courts and not to that of Political Agent as at present. Possibly if hint to this effect c -^ould 'be given to Persians an arrangement could he arrived2- arrived at lay which these Bahrainis would not in practise 'be conscripted. The foregoing refers to my immediately preceding telegram. Resident. Post copy forwarded to Vice Consul, Mohaminerah. By order, for Secretary to the Political fiesident in the Persian Gulf. Bushire lath October 1930. ff/*'19/109. Telegram P. Y Tom Political Pesident, at Mohatnmerah. To H.M*e• Minister, Tehran, Repeated Government of India, New Delhi. No. T-lll. Dated Slst October 1930. Pressure is being brought on Bahrainis to register as Persian subjects, and some of them came to see me today. Following Incidents have occurred / recently. Security has been taken from two men that they will appear, one today and one witnm four days, to take out Persian papers. A third was im- -prisoned for 24 hours and then took out papers under pressure. Police authorities have confiscatea one passport issued by Consul, Basrah, to one Bahraini and a certificate of identity issued at Mohammerah to another and a certificate issued by the Shaikh of Bahrain to a third. In view of the undertaking given by Minister of Court that Persian authorities woulc cease registration and other forms of pressure pending result ^ of negotiations, vide telegram of 5th November 1929 sent by Minister to me through Vice Consul, Mohammerah, I trust it will be possible to get urgent oroers issued to local authorities to cease registration and maintain status quo. RESIDENT. F06t The Political Agent, Bahrain, w M' b Vice Consul, Mohammerah. By order, c V'o f or Secretary to the Political Pesioent in the Persian Gulf. Mohammerah, . Slst October 1930.K I &gt; 1'' D .O .Ho. T.79 tf 1930. Office of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Camp, Husoatf Dated the 27th November 1930# n i Please refer to your telegram No* 1659 of the 24th November 19 30, asking me to send you the substance of my reply to the deputation from tbe Qusbah Bahama by Abdul Razzaq. Your telegram reached me just after Abdul Razzaq had left» I told the qusbah Bahama that a number of them had acquired property in Persiat that, as they well knew, foreign subjects were not allowed to held property in Persia, and that it was therefore very difficult for us to assist them while they thsmselres were Yielating Persian laws. 1 went en to say that, in my opinion, those Bahama who had definitely settled in Persia and acquired property there and established themselves permanently in th: t country wou^d be well adyised to accept Persian nationality. They could not have the advantages of residence in Persia without the disadvantages. I concluded by saying that, as regards those Bahama who had net acquired an property in Persia, I had, when at Mohammerah, wired to the Legation mentioning that they were being pressed to take out Persian nationality papers in connection with the census operatioi now in progress, and asking them to have instructions sent to the local authorities in Mohammerah not to bring pressure upon them in this respect at the present time in accordance with Toymour- tache v s verbal assurance to Sir Robert Clive. The Vice Consul at Mohammerah told the Deputy Governor there about this, and aske him to refrain from any action against these Bahama until a repl had come from Tehran, and he agreed to do so. Up to the present I have received no reply from Tehran. Capt.C.G.Prior,!.A., Political Agentt Bahrain.Ho. 173 f int- i J, ' British Legation, 3U? 1 -'— 'r'pin^Nc v *- /6 V '&lt;? lO'? Ab /s, t . dcUUr# Tehran, November 5th, 19 30 His Britannic Majesty's Representative presents his compliments to His Majesty's Consular Officer at Bus hire an d transmits herewith copies of the documents mentioned in the subjoined schedule. V V \y Reference / T Resident 1 s telegram ^o^all dated the 31.10.1930 despatched from Mo h amine rah. Note to the Persian G-overnment November 4th,1930. Copies have be the Government at Mo hammerah. en sent to the Foreign Office )f India and to H.M.Vice Consul Treatment of Bahreinis in Persia. Mi: iuxi^ 'a/,*.-r j Ho. 186 British Legation, /W -ESiDENCV. [ On (7^ COrtriDc,^ 1iiLOOfiDS TBflicor; ~~ Novemljer 29th, 19 30 . His Britannic Majesty's Representative presents his compliments to His Majesty's Consul-general for observations at Bis aire an( j transmits herewith/copies of the documents mentioned in the subjoined schedule. )33 Reference Tehran despatch No. 173 dated the 4th No vember,19 30. lkv&gt;w Note the Persian Government, No. 21772/ 71012141 dated the 22. 11. 1930. Copies have been sent to t of India and to II.M.Consu y u ; V Bahrein and the Status Quo he foreign Office, the Government ar Officer at Mohammerah.-Persian lUnlster for Foreign Affairs to Charge d f Affaires. 1st Azer 1309 (November ^iindml930) Wo. 21772/71012141 Uonsieur le Charge d*Affaires, I beg to aoknowledge the receipt of your esteemed Kote of Aban 13th (November 4th 1930) regarding the passports of Bahreinis. With regard to the statement you make that certain reports have been received \jy you in which certain acts of Persian local officials in the Persian Sulf are mentioned in regard to the treatment of Bahreinis, you sry that these acts are contrary to the promise which was given to Sir H.Clive on September 9th that 'so long hs the Oeneral Treaty is in suspense, the Status iio will be obse ved M I have the honour to reply that no acts contrary to the rights of the Persian Government and the ordinary procedure in force, or of the Status ^uo to which you refer have been committed on the part of the Oovernment or of Persian officials. The conditions and arrangements for the journeys of flahreinis to Basrah and other ports have been as follows for more than 25 years A pass (jawaz) or travel pass (Ilm we Khabar) was al'ays given to Bahreinis and the British officials signed (visaed) those passes, but according to reports received on Farvardin 16 1309 (April 5th 1930) the British Consular Officials in the Persian oulf have begun to act contrary to that arrangement. Firstly the British Consulate general in Bushire instructed Mespers Company not to accept Bahrein! travellers for Basrah and elsewhere if they were travelling on travel pasues; only people in possession of official passports were to be accepted on board ste-mers. Subsequently-2- Subsequently on Ordibeheaht 12th # 1309 (May 2nd, 19^0) the 3ritish Consul in 'tohaianerah informed some Bahreinie inhabit ing lohaomerah who wished to go to Basrah and had ^jone to the Consul for a visa to their travel passes or in order to obtain a pass that 'they raust take out official passports valid for 'five years at a price of Rupees 6 and that a pass or a visa on a travel pass could not be giv^n'. ithout mentioning reports or complaints from the Hhia 1 population of Bahrein regarding the hardships which theji suffer and the hindrances placed in the way of other Persians going to or coming from Bahrein and other places, I am sure that, when you take into consideration the above reports received by my Government - all of which are true - you will agree that if acts contrary to the measures in force or the maintenance of the Status Quo have been committed, Persian Officials have not done so. On the contrary the whole efforts of the Persian Government and of its officials have been directed to upholding the rights of the Persian Govern ment in accordance with the laws in force, but unfortu ately if the British officials in the Persian Gulf have acted in a cense contrary to the rights of Persia and especially con trary to the agreement made for the maintenance of the Status Quo* iJiother proof that (Persian) officials have not acted in a sense contrary to the Status quo is that, as the Persian Government considers Bahrein as Persian territory, Bahreinis are naturally reckoned as Persian subjects and in consequence there is no need to oblige Bahreinis to accept Persian ^ nationality. The only thing is that if Bahreinis wish to submit to Persian officials passports or other proofs which are contrary to Persian nationality, Persian officials will not/vv ^ -3- not aooept (such documents) but oonsider thea as contrary to the Status quo. In view of the above f I trust that you will take immediate and energetic steps so that British officials in the Qulf will refrain as formerly from interfering in the affairs of Bahrein!s and will mend those ways which are contrary to the undertaking of that honourable Legation and I shall be happy if you will inform me as soon as possible of the results of the steps taken. (Sigaed) Feroughi. ^ / r y Ij. i-v T~— — Conlldential, ^O.168/650-S of 1930. British Residency &amp; Consulate-Greneralp Bushire, the 15th December 1930. Sir 9 I have the honour to acknowledge the receipt of your printed letter Jsio.l8fe f dated the 29th KoTexaber 1930, enclosing a copy of a note from the Persian Government, dated 22nd November 1930, Ho.21772/71012141, regarding the Bahrainis. 2. I do not know whether it is proposed to send a reply to the Persian note, but in case it should be proposed to do so, I would submit the following comments on it for your information. . 3. The Persian note begins by contending that the Persians have not violated the status quo, but that it is the British officials who have done so, and they quote as an exrmple the fact that for the last 25 years Bahrainis i have travelled to Basrah and other ports on a pass ( jewaz ) or travel pass ( Ilm we Khaoar j and that British officials signed these passes* 4. It is n&gt;t quite clear what concern the journey of a Bahraini to Basrah is of the Persian Government, ana I think that what they are really driving at is that formerly Persians travelled to Bahrain and 'Basrah on informal travel documents. If this assumption is correct, then I would point out that, as you are aware, formerly foreigners of all kinds entered Persia either without travel documents of any s Cherge d'Affpires, British Legation # TKHRAK. kindkind or on Tarious irregular documents 9 such as, travel 4 passes, certificates of 'identity, pil 0 rim passes, etc. This practice the Persian GoTernment have tht-mselves stopped and they now insist on all foreigners being equipped with regular passports. The 'Iraq passport requirements have also been tightened up. It is largely in order to enable their nationcils to fulfil the passport requirements of other neigh bouring countries that the Bahrain Government and the Muscat State have also tightened up their passport system and now insist on foreigners being in possession of regular pass port^ /ises by a ritish consulrr officer acting on behalf of the Brhrain or Muscat Government in the ■ame way as they used formerly to ^rant vis^s on behalf of 'Iraq ana iii^ypt at places where those states had no consular representatives. The Bahrain Government are therefore only doin G exactly what the Persian Government have done and partly at any rate^ because the Persian Government have aone it. 5« The point at issue really is that the Persians will not grant an exit vis#/ for persons proceeding to Bahrain but will only grant an n llm we Khabar n « This is a document authorising travel from one Persian port to another, and / this document cannot be vise by a British consular officer i or Bahrain, neither will the 1 ahrain Government admit its validity as a passport. If however a Persian presents a regular Persian passport and applies for a visa ^ot ahrain it is eiiven to him. This Consulate-General has not instructed the i esopotamia Persia Corporation not to accept Bahrain! travellers for Basrah and elsewhere if they were travelling on travel passes* The British India Steam Navigation •...-3- Navigation Comprny in th«ir own interests take steps to ensure that intending travellers arc provided with documents enabling them to land at the port of destination before allowing them to come on board. 6. The note then mentions reports or complaints from the Shia* population of Bahrain regard^n^ the hardships which they suffer. In this connection I can only say that on each occasion i visited Bahrain, the Shia* priests of Bahrain have complained to me bitterly of the haraships inflicted upon the Shia' Bahrainis in Persia, and have never once complained to mt of any hardship suffered at the hands of the Bahrain Government. The note t 0 ®® on to say that the pro&gt;f that the Persians have not acted contrary to the status quo is that as the Persian Government consider Bt hrain as Persian territory, Bahrainis are naturally reckoned as Persian subjects and in consequence there Is no need to oblige ^ahrainis to accept Persian nationality. This of course begs the whole point at issue, which is that the status of Bahrain is at present under discussion between the British and Persian Governments and with it the nation ality of Bahrain subjects, and it was agreed between the Minister of Court and Sir Robert Clive that until this question had been decided, no pressure should be brought upon Bahrainis resident in Uohammerah to accept Persian nationality, and the matter should be kept in suspense* ?• I pm sending copies of this despatch to the -v Foreign Secretary to the Gove nment of India and to His Majesty 1 s * W- twT-!' o7'V^ hIf / *1 British Legation Ko. . Tehran 19th De c ember, 1930 /7^ 5 1 s//0 ^ Sir I transmit to you herewith copy of a note which I have received from the Minister for Foreign Affairs in connection with your recent visit to Bahrein. A translation of the newspaper article to which His Highness evidently refers is also enclosed for your information. as soon as possible, with £ report dealing fully with each of the allegations contained therein in order to enable ire to reply to the note. In view of several recent protests made by this Legation at the instance of yourself and cf His Majesty's Consul at Ahwaz in connection with reports of ill-treatment of Bahrein!s in Persia, you will, I feel sure, realise the expediency of demonstrating conclusively that on our side we have strictly observed the status quo in respect of Persians in Bahrein. 2. I shall be glad if you will furnish me I am. Sir Your most obedient Servant Lieutenant -Colonel H.V, BisCoo, His Majesty's Consul General, Bushire.11 •• v From the Persian Minister for Foreign Affairs, addressed to His Majesty's Charge d 1 Affaires. Dated Azer 26th, 1309 (17th Dsoember, 1930). Ho.26041/7101214. Monsieur le Charge d'Affaires, According to information received, which has also 'been reproduced in the papers. Colonel Biscuit (Biscoe), the consul-General of the honourable British Government in Bushire had, at the time of his arrival at Bahrein, made the following statement to Persian merchants there in the course of his private meeting with them;- 'Bahrein is (an) independent (State) and you, who for more 'than 30 years are living in Bahrein are, in accordance with 'the rules in force, considered as subjects of Bahrein..,' The Persians have been very much affected by this statement. (It is also reported that) on Aban 7th (29th October 1930) when the Consul-Greneral had gone to inspect the Government departments in Bahrein, he (the Gonsul- General) had instructed that the Persian staff (employees) should be dismissed from the departments. He (the Consul-General) (is also said to have) had long private conversations with a Persian Mujtahed called Sheikh Aya which, as conjectured by correspondents (sic), form part of a series of activities started by the Oonsul-General aiming at annihilating the rights of Persia and Persians. While taking the foregoing into view, you will see tha^ apart from the fact that such acts are entirely in contravention with the maintenance of 'Status quo', to which you make an allusion in your note of Aban 13th (4th November 1930), the dismissal of Persians from the /GovernmentCrovernment departmonts is considered as a kind of unjust demonstration against the Persians resident in Bahrein. I have, therefore, the honour to state that I am looking forward for emphatic and urgent instructions to be issued to the Consui-General to abstain from taking any such actions which are contrary to undertakings and justice and to strictly observe the maintenance of 'Status que' , I shall also be very grateful if you would be so good as to inform me at your earliest convenience of the result of the steps taken in the matter, I avail myself of the opportunity, etc., (Signed) Perought.Translation from the Itila f at of December 2nd, 1930, of an article entitled 'A Series of steps taken to destroy Persia*8 Rights'• To the honoiiratole Editor, Some days ago Colonel Biscuit, the British Consul General in the Gulf, arrived in Bahrein from Bushire with two men of war which are generally anchored off Bushire. Sheikh Hamad, the so-called acting Governor of Bahrein went on board the ship to receive him and they came ashore together and in accordance with the instructions issued, a salute of 11 guns was given by the Government of Bahrain. An hour after the arrival of the Consul General in Bahrein the merchants and guilds were invited to the Consulate and the Consul General received each guild in turn and talked to them # The Persian merchants were received privately and were told that those of them who had been in Bahrein more than 30 years were considered as subjects of Bahrein because in accordance v/ith the rules and regulations persons who had inhabited a locality for ten years were accounted subjects of that place; the Persian merchants refuted the statement of the Consul General and said that they were Persians and subjects of Persia and Bahrein was their property and that therefore they did not agree with the statement made by the Consul General. The Consul General then said 'Yes, you are Bahreinis even if you are Persian subjectsThe Persians were anxious on hearing these words and kept silent and soon after they dispersed. The Consul General thought that the people of Bahrein were without knowledge of events and imagined that as soon as he had said that they must give up Persian subjection and take out Bahrein passports they would i; /immediately(jZ) immediately accept and give up the lionour of their Persian nationality. Verily British agents in Bahrein are trying as much as possible to force Persians to give up their nationality and are preparing the ground for depriving Persia of its rights over Bahrein, hut the Persians are alive to this plan and are watching events with open eyes for they know Bahrein and the Bahrein Islands to be Persian and will hold out in the face of coveteousness and threats; only a number of Arabs and Sheikha, for purposes of personal advantage, hang on to them (the British). talks of the Government of BahreinI But everybody knows that after the dismissal of Sheikh Issa bin Ali al Khalifeh there was nobody and there was no trace of any Government. Why? Only rarely is the seal of Sheikh Hamad bin Issa al Khalifeh, the deputy Governor of Bahrein, seen beneath some decrees. But really if you ask who is the Governor of Bahrein, when was he elected and where is he actually, nobody will be able to answer you because this Governor is a marionette whom nobody recognises officially. Colonel Biscuit visited and inspected the Government offices in Bahrein and ordered that all Persian employees should be dismissed. If the British pray that we in no wise mix up in the Government of Bahrein and aver that the latter has a separate and independent Government which is run by the Sheikhs and seize hold of this pretext as an answer to Persia, what name can you give, pray, to such a situation? What is the meaning of interfering in the affairs of Bahrein? Yes, Colonel Biscuit came to Bahrein with new orders and arranged affairs in accordance with the instructions he had received# Colonel Biscuit, the British Consul General It was the 17th of Aban (November 8th) that /YesterdayI -V Yesterday there was a protracted meeting between bheikh Ali Mujtehid, who inhabits the village of Sinabinis (one of the villages of Bahrein) and Colonel Biscuit. Sheikh Ali Mujtehid is an old man who is also paralytic and of some influence. They sent a car for him and he came to the Consulate in the Gonsulftfieneral*s car. The meeting lasted in secrecy for about two and a half hours and nobody heard the secrets of this interview but one thing is sure and that is that they are starting plans to harm and destroy the rights of Persia and Persians. It is rumoured that as in the year 1341, they wish with the help of Sheikh Ali Mujtehid to sow discord again between Bahreinis and Arabs and foster internal strife because the Arabs of Bahrein are strenuously opposed to the present system of Government and do not recognise officially the Government institutions, and this opposition of the Arabs is to such an extent that they refuse to send their children to the schools of this puppet Government of the British: for this reason they wish to rouse the Bahreinis against the Arabs. Another condition which has aroused the hostility of the Arabs and in which they do not acquiesce is that regarding the law courts, for they dislike submitting to the law which is administered by British agents. During -chese days an Indian name Khan Bahadur Seyed Sadiq, formerly assistant in the British Consulate at Bahrein, has arrived, and it is rumoured that the British wish to cancel their former judiciary and are now forming % the basis for a judiciary to function under the direction of the aforementioned aeyed so that the whole of the inhabitants of Bahrein will be subject to the laws of his court. Briefly, since the day that the Persian / Government IGovernment took certain steps regarding its claim to possess Bahrein and appealed to the League of Nations, the British have interfered more than before in the internal affairs there and are preparing plans and stratagems for furthering their objects, but at the same time they are tfying to do it in the name of the Government of Bahrein^ Colon«l Biscuit has lately bought a large plot of ground near the Mahriq fort and is starting to erect an important building there, and it is rumoured that the centre of the British Consulate General will be transferred to Bahrein. Contrary to former times, nearly every day or every other day British Government planes visit Bahrein, The building known as Quarantine, which belongs to the deposed Sheikh Issa bin Ali al Khalifeh, has been bought by the British Government for Rupees 15,000 and it has been made the aeroplane centre. Finally, the freash steps which the British Consul General is taking, both openly and secretly, mark a new chapter in Bahrein and all Bahreinis, especially we Persians, are opening our eyes and looking on with interest at his actions to see how far they will go. Of course our honourable Ministers are paying attention to the situation and will not allow the obvious rights of Persia in Bahrein to be trampled on» To-day Colonel Biscuit went to Qatar with his warships, but will return to Bahrein in a few days. (Signed) Mun'emi.• rl /k l* &amp; Ho.176/675 -3 of 1930. British Residency &amp; Consulate-General, Bushirei the 22nd December 1930• Sir, ^ith reference to your despatch 5o # 198, dated the 19th December 1930, transmitting a copy of a note received from the Ministry for Foreign Affairs, In connection with ujy recent visit to Bahrain, I have the honour to state that the allegations therein nade are absolutely incorrect in every single particular, while the version of the visit given in the 'Itila^t' can only 'be described as purely unadulterated fiction from beginning to end. I will deal with the statements seriatim. 2. Soon after my arrival 1 received visits from Arab merchants, Hindu merchants and Persian merchants. I did not make to the letter any stt- tement to the effect that those who for more than 30 years had lived in Bahrain were in accordance with the rules in force considered to be Bahrain subjects. The interviews lasted about a quarter of an hour in each case and to the best of my recollection the conversation was confined to the usual polite enquiries about the state of trade, etc. 3. The next statement is to the effect that I inspected the Government departments in Bahrain on the 29th October and gave orders for the dismissal of the Persian staff. Firstly, I was not in Bahrain on the 29th H.B.M*s Charge d'Affaires, British Legation, T e h r a n. October;•2» Ootoberj I arriyed there on the 8th Hovember and left on the ilth Noyember; I did not Inspect any Government department in Bahrain; I did visit the Police barracks and spent about tan minutes at the Customs, diacussing various matters yvith Mr* de Grenier f the Director of Customsi and also said a few words to his clerical staff, who are nearly all Indians and whom he presented to me. I gave no ordare of any kind that any Persian should be dismissed from any department• Jha whole atory is a complete and entire fabrication from beginning to end. 4* I did not have a long private conversation with a Persian Mujtahid called Shaikh /ya. Several of the local priesthood called upon me and it is possible that Shaikh Ayp may have bean among them. I aaw a very large number of people and do not remember their names. In view of the fact however that 1 was exceedingly busy, each interview waa limited to about a quarter of an hour and conversation was confined to the customary platitudes. The only interview that I can recall with any of the kazis waa one with the chief Shia 1 kazi, who complained for the second time to me of the oppression suffered by his compatriots at Mohammerah at the hands of the Persian authorities. 5. It seems hardly necessary to discuss the article in the 'Itila'at'. It is a series of lies from beginning to end. I have only been able to discover one accurate statement in it, and that is, that the quarantine building has been acquired by the Royal Air Force as a rest house. Every other statement made in that article is untrue except# of coursa 9 the fact that, as stated above, I did see some of the kazis and Shaikh All (presumably this is the same man ..... man ae Is referred to as SlAlkh /^a by the Itinistry for Foreign ffalrs) may have been among them. So visit however took place in secrecy or lasted two and a half hours: on the contrary they all took place in the middle of the morning and lasted about ten minutes or a quarter of an hour. I hrve the honour to te 9 Sir, Your most obedient, humble servant, fc JfM Lt.Colonel, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf and s Consul*General for Fars,Etc»Confidential* K7 Ko.684-S of 1930. British Residency &amp; Consulate -General, Bushire, the 30th December 1930. A copy of the undermentioned papers is forwarded to the Political /gent, Bahrain. The Hon'ble the Political Resident would be L .lad if the Political Agent could find out who the Bahrain correspondent of the rt Itila , at H is. By Order, *p u. Capt., % Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Subject:- Persian claim to Bahrain. J 1. despatch IJo. 19d f dated the 19th December 1930,from H # B. Ws.Charge d'ffaires,British Legation,Tehran, with enclosures. 2. Despatch » o .176/675- S of 22nd December 1930, to H.B.M's Charge dV ffaigpe8,British le ation,Tehran. PnVBritish Legation, Tehran, January ^nd,19^1. Ho. 3 Monsieur lo Ministre, I did not fail to transmit to Lieutenant Colonel Biscoe a copy of Your Highness* note ho. 26041/7101214 of Asser 26th 1S09 (Deoembftr 17th 19 ^0), whioh contained a series of allegations regarding that officer's recent visit to Bs-hre in* I had indeed, seen previously in the 'Ittila -at' an article containing similar allegations, but had not con sidered it necessary to take any action in the matter, since like almost all reports concerning Bahrein which have appscrcd recently in the Persian press they were so evidently untrue and dictated by malice, £. Frorr Lieutenant Colonel Biscoe's reply of which I have thought it best to furnish Your richness with a trans lation, it will be seen that every single statement in the report received by Your Highness is untrue; nor could such His Highness 'lirisa Hohataod All Khan Fcroughi Unistor for Foreign Affairs.m v -2- ouch stat©raents possibly have been made in good f Pith thou^ in error. Whoever is responsible for the renort in question was evidently actuated oy trie basest motives. I raey add - merely as a sidelight on the general accuracy or otherwise of these reports - that His Britannic Hajoaty 1 a Political Resident in the Persian Gulf is refer red to throughout as 'Colonel Btt^cuit ' a mistake which v^as reproduced, some- v /hat to my surprise, in Your Highness 1 official note under reference, though Lieutenant Col onel 3iscoe ho i-ds !;is Imperial ^a^esty's exequatur as Consul General for Bushire. 3. I also sent to ris britannic Majesty's Consul-General a copy of Your Highness 1 note No.£1772/7101^141 of November 2Hnd t which contained other and more general complaints regarding the treatment of Persian pub^ects in Bahrein, in that note it was alleged among other things that the recent introduction of Bahrein! passports, and consequent refusal of His Britannic 'f jesty^ Consular Officers to visa n ilra-o- ichabar'i 4 T * M ■ K ichabar' pas: ©a, ooiiBtituted &amp; violation of the status quo. I beg leave to point out in reply that until reoent years foreigners of all kinds were per mitted to enter Persia either without travel documents of any kind or on a variety of irregulrr doaurarnts such as travel passes, oertifioates of identity and co on. rhis practice the Persian Oovernrnf*nt have themselves put a stop to of lale f an i the 'Iraq Government have taken siiuilar ^teps. It is largely, therefore, in order to enable their nationals to ooaply with the passport countries regulations of neighbouring/ that the Oovernwent of Bahrein, like the f;tate of 'usual, htve been obliged in their turn to insist on the production of regular passports. In so doing they have ioroly followed the lead of the Imperial Governaont taid the letter's action has, indeed, left them no alternative. In point of fact His Britannic Majesty 's Conr.ulate General at Bus hire has not, as alleged, advised the 'esopotamia Persia Corporation not to accept travellers for Basrah who can only produce travel passes: the British India steam Navigation Company havehave in their ovm interoet taken steps to oneure that intending travellers are provided before starting with such valid dooutaento as raay enable them to Irncl at their port of destination. 4. Tn the saroe note Your Highness refers in somewhat general teras to the hardship© vhioh the ^hia copulation of Bahrein are s ^id to suffer at the hands of the Bahrein fTovernfiient. I shall be haopy, ae always, to investigate proper ly subrtantiated individual complaints, but in the meantime T be^ leave to quote Lieutenant Colonel Bi80oe*6 comment on the passage in ruestion ;- 'I can only say thdt on each 'ocjafioa I visited Bahrein the ^hia 'priests htve complained to me bitterly 'of the hardships inriicted ui)on :;hia 'B &amp;hreinis in ^ersia, and have never 'once coP;)i; ined to me of any hardship^ 'sufferea at the hanae of the Bahrein 'Oovernment For the ui'tiscut , therefore, I am forced to conclude that the complaints Ti lerr^d to in Your Highneas' note emanate from the sane tainted source v ^hich was responsible for the article in the 'Ittila-at n p and are, like that article, founded on nothing more than a desire to embitter Anglo-Persian relations from motives of personal interest, I av^il 'ayselfm ^f this opportunity to renew to Your Highness the assurance of R^y highest consideration. (Signed) R.C?PARR^SIOENCY. '*///*/ KAtiOth T tAw iscwnM- p British Legation, Tehran. 10th January, 1931, u 13,» .r ■/t/? / Sir, I transmit to you herewith a copy of a complaint received from the Ministry for poreign Affairs concerning the alleged expulsion of certain Persian subjects from Bahrein. 2 # I presume this report to be as lacking in all foundation of fact as other similar reports recently received from the Persian Ministry for Foreign Affairs in connection with Bahrein, but in order to enable me to reply in definite terms I shall be glad if you will be so good as to investigate the matter and acquaint me with the result of your enquiries. I am. Sir, Your most obedient Servant, i The Honourable Lieut-Colonel H.V.Biscoe, I.A., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf ana His Majesty's Consul-Gene ral at Bushlre.Mohammeraht the 18th Kanuary 1931&lt; I am ••ndiiifc you a copy of a letier received from Parr^with cnclosurea. The Resident will be glad if you would furnish yVv*^' him with a report to enable to eply* Capt.C,G.Prior t l«A.» p litical Agent 9 Bahrain*Cotif Ideiui. 1. Ho .ll/40 -S of 1931. British Hesldency 4 Consulate-General, Bus tire, the 31st January 1931. air. 1 ^'ith reference to your despatch I'o#7, dated the 10 fch January 1351, forwarding a copy of a protest received by you from the Unistry for foreign Affaire, concerning the alleged expluaion fr^ra Bahrain of certain Pers-an subjects, I hare the honour to forward for your information a copy of a report I/) I** I by the political iigent, Bahrain, on yach of the pereons naiaed. ' will Je observed tiiat all .he above persons are novr present in li&amp;hrain with i;he one exception of -iirza Husain who is unknown th^re, and that the report uade -o them is thus totally without foundciti^a, and as inaccurate as all the other reports thet they receive 1'rom their correspondents in the oouth. / I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most o edient, humble servant, Lt» Colonel, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf Jc H # B#ii*s Jonsul-General lor i 4 ar8,etc» s Chnree d *Affaires, British Legation, X e h £ a n &lt;No. 16. P BUSHinE rt£31D£NCY tU( Dtu. . iuj co.NfiOt'iTiAi itfiORoe' Beitish Legation, l/^l Tehran, /' n n- February 21st, 19 31 - His Britannic Majesty's Representative presents his The Honourable the Political Resident in the compliments to His Alaiesty's , _ t Persian H-ulf and r Consul-general at Bush ire. and transmits herewith copies of the documents mentioned in the subjoined schedule. f- •(.I Reference Bushire despatch No. 11/40 -S of 31st January 1931. Memorandum to the Persian GoYernment Feb. 21st,1931. Bahrein,m Britinh Ltgatlon, Tehran, Fe anu&gt;ry SXet, 19Si. S In ite tWfaonmciuia Jio.li7»94/71om4 of January 6th 1331 th« Inisiry for Foreign /.ffalrs Infftrrsed Hie Brituaalo Majeaty'a Legation that nooortlins to a roport roo«iv«d, ai* poraooe, (whose were given) hfcC been expelled fro« 3«hreln. -The neno rand urn ooatttlned virions references to the alleged Persian overelgr.ty of B&amp;fireln, sad lis Brlttunlo (.mjesty's Lection Is thoroiore obliged, In the first plane, to realod. the Klnlatry for Foreign Affairs that His .i ilunclo eJeoty'B Oovermaent do not ndalt, nor h-ivo tuuy aver •d'aitted, the erolon olalm to the aovorelgaty Of the lalands In question. The Legation ii ui, iwvertheie««, forwarded a oopy of this complaint to the folltioal ;i«ent In Bahrein, and now encloses herewith a tranelatlon of that of fleer's reply, from whioh it wili oe seen thti tlte report receirad by the inlatiy for KoreigB Affairs was without the leant foundation: with the exception of one person mentlon- od therein, vhoae identity Is nnJtnown to the Buhreini authorities, all the IndiTiduals alleged to have been expelled ire residing as heretofore In Bahrein. in these cirouiastaflces Kls Britaanie «aJeety»B Legation has the honour to request that a thorou^i investigation be aade Into the origin of so Idle and mischievous a report. The imperial Onistry for Foreign Affaire.r Ho J / -- U ^r 7r SIDENc y foi Beitish Legation, Tehran, February H5th, 19 21 a ■v/ V PO^Sc''^ . «eu^' ] His Britannic Majesty's Representative presents his The Hon.The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf and compliments toy^His Majesty's Consul-Oeneral at Bushi re and transmits herewith copies of the documents mentioned in the subjoined schedule. Reference - Despatch to the Foreign Office with enclosures February 25th,1931. Bahre in.-8- in In aot/the vle^ of the undertaking made by the honoup- -ble ^rltiah oyernaent In respect of the uaintenaace of the sii! tus quo , the very question of Introduotlon of passports in Biiirein (whloh has come Into being after the undertaking in question) is eviuent ooutravention with the explicit ftext of) the undertaking end, as it la gathered fron your ''' ■' lli &gt; ! » 'nose aotions are being taken in Bahrein without che siinction of the honourabie British Gorernment, I fail to understand the oanae of me unaertaking mi-de for the maiviten- vnoe of tiie ''suiitiug w jlu j&amp;nrein* ^ regerde th£ wttitement made in your note under reply CO the erfeot that 'His oritonnic Majesty's Consul-Oeneral in BUiihire luis not, us alleged, aoTiaeo the Mesopotaala r*r«la. 'Corporation not to aeoept troTeliers for assrsJi who oen only prouuoe tr«Tel paa^es: the British India -team fiuTigatlon -ompnnj . ye j.n their o-vn interest taken steps to ensure 'that iu'.en&amp;ing ura/eilera ere pj-ovided before starting with uuoh valid dcouweirts as may enable them to land at their 'port o. &gt; aatinntion , i have to say taat these statements anfl rguneucs have m^e m *oi*« us tool shea since l) the Company'n interests oonsiet xn aeoiu-ixtg travelling fares find that every £.i.ep .a.AO.', thsy (tht Cou»4,;iiay; wiuh to take should be taken only for this end und not for anything else, 2) it would be tun icivnt for cue Com^uny to extu^iae the seal and signature Of the i^ereian Govejfiment ofilciais in the «raiua 3ulf well as the t i^ture of the Britiuh offioials so as to make bure of the validity oi cravellers' doouaents and that beyond this the Company has no right whatever (sic). 3) it l e , m exclusive right, of the Ooveraaent to decide about the issue of all kinds of doouments suoh as -Jewazes' {passes; or passports to their subjecs intending to travel and that the ri^t of the Consular officers of the country to whose-4- territory the travellers are proceeding would toe to exaaine such documents and make sure of their vtiidity and to leeue a visa thereto. The interventioij of th'&gt; Hi vi^aticn Company into the policy and rules of the com triea who 1rnue pftpcea or paesoorts hH the case may be to their subjeotn travollers o* of the oou tries to /hose ports travellers arfj entering; is orly rn \inreH8onable p.nd unprecedented one# 4) s it is aMmt tvonty ^ive year a since the Bahrcinis are trt-veiling on '.lewfeees' 1 and ,t llra-o-ichabar ,, pusses, a practice which has beon afpreel to by the honourable British^ Ooveroment, why rhculd this practice appear to the CoflApaJQ;v to be invalid or causing inconvenience at the port ox' gjestlnation ? D) 1 hy the Consul-(Teneral of the honourable British Government has not wished to warn the Company against the latter^ error and tiisobedienco (arbitrary attitude). In any case, now that th^ British teau navigation Coapany are acting at their own will and do not respect the rules ant reTulations of the Imperial Go vernaent in the ^ersisn (*ulf waters nor do they honour the undertakings of the honourable British Government for the raainteuanoe of the 'status quo', it would be the duty both of the Persian ooverment and the honourable British Government to make the Company realise their limits and duties. Apart from all these facts, in case the consular officers of the honourable British Oovernment have, in accordance with the undertakings of their Government, respec' ed the present situation (the 'status quo') and that it is only the Company who, contrary to this, (ire acting at tiieir own will, it vunild all the same be desirable if you could caube enquiry to be made from the British Consul at Kohaimaerah with a view zo finaing out according to what instructions and the reason for which-5- wnioh ho has stated {&lt; a it is snown from the official report rooelved from the Pursinn Government official dated sfand 18th 12)8) to the inh^bituntB of Bahrein residing at !ohaj«nerah that tiie letter should, when travellini? to Basrah, get official p.iasporis froai tue Consulate valid for 5 years at the cost of Knpees £• kb regards th« statoaont aade in the report from the Consul General of the honournV.e 8riti^i Government to the effect that che Sbia jriests have oojaplained (to hia) of the hardship inflict od upon 3hia Bahrsxnio in Persia, T have to say chat complaint on the part of Shi as of the hardships inflifioted in a Shia country is ao surpriftiug that 1 hardly coneider it defensible. It was sfuoh opportune if the oomplainants had mentioned to the Consul ate-Q^nerfU. one of the instances of tneir complaint for being sufcstantiateC (eic )• I am looking forward to be informed of the result of the actions and enquiries vhioh ar&lt;j to be made in the inatter from the ^itisli India navigation Goapany find the British Consulate at ^chaauMrah• I a-?ail myself etc. # (ti gned ) Ferou^hi~t« 'oontrttry to th« regulations in foree ^or th« aai »t0n«iio« of the statue quo 'hTe been commit ted 9 they ^rere not committed by 'erelaa officials, on 'the oontr&amp;ry, the whole efforts of -the pertiuft Oorernaiwit wsul of their ,f offloi iXs have been direatedl towards upholding the rights of the Persian 'Government In tiooordanoe with the M l^s In foroe •••«••' tuad e^&amp;ln : Another proof that (.erslan) offlolailf W iuwe not rested In a sense contrary 'to the status quo is thut, t*« the * 'ersian OoTremment ooaslder Bsiirein ••as Persian territory, Bahreinis are naturrlly reckoned us lerelan ^subji ots # «*«In other words f the i-erpinn (Government appear to Interpret the aseuranoes in uestion fcs entit ling them to ignore ooapletely the oontentiono of the other party to the dispute, ^nd to treat Bahreinis in eveiy way as Persian subjects. 3# That being so, it follows logically that the Bahrein OowimiNftt on their side are entitled to a precisely aiailar interpretation, ^d are justified in applying to sahrelnif whatever ^neaatires they way deem expedient* The Persian (SovernrQent have/CN '■■J 111'' 1 1%^ British Legation, ??v3iDeNc£ No. 46. Daic iqju/H Tehran, 7th April, 19 31. His Britannic Majesty's Representative presents his The Honourable The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, and compliments to^Eis Majesty's Consul General at Pushire and transmits herewith copies of the documents mentioned in the subjoined schedule. Reference Tehran P.L. No. 16 of 21,2.1931. ?o The Foreign Office. No. 150 of 7th April, 1931. 4/$ Treatment of Bahreinis by the Persian authorities, and the Bahrein passport regulations.Telegram From To Fo. 32 Dated 15th. received 21st. April 1931 ictln^ Consul, Ahwaz. fiolitical Resident, Bushire, ITN Following sent to Minister, fl „ Telegram No. 10 dated 20th, April. A number of BahreiniJ raerch ?r ,rits petitioned Vice-''*** -Consul , lldhAmnerc-h, saving that thirty Bahrein subjects were|being conscripted for the Persian army and asking for help. In fact, nineteen names have been published c j &gt;ld these men are to report on April 22nd. to ^electionoard.. ^en are virtually Bahrein subjects but out of (. . . . .)have taken Persian nationality papers. They have been told to report (for?) orders since they are Persians. I presume nothing can be done on their ft behalf. Please confirm. At h-.i/r^ . Acting Consul, Ahwaz. Political Resiaent, Bushii'e, From To No. 8 Dated 25rd. received 24th, April 1931 m Following sent to Minister. Telegram No 11 dated April 22 rd. ^ Second sentence, second paragraph my telegraa No 10 is ' Ken are virtually Bahrein suDjects tut out of necessity have taken out fersian national!tj papers.' Meaning Is , that none wished to do this, hut some registered in order to get employment and some due to pressure from authorities. Acting Consul.I * *4^ Hi lei CUiaaDiiX.TlAjU BU-: ! o. Z/W/J/ of 1^1. H, J ,M* e Vice-Coiisulate, N'C v ' ] i-ioiiammermh, the 20 th April 1951, l 7/i- h ' OCmOEATML 7^ Z)«/6 'H V To His Majesty*s Consul for Khuzistan, A h w a z. f ^ iiefnorandura. fx • i / ^ rN 5 iieferci ce ^ur conversation at your visit to h J uohaivnerah, I forward, the petition I have received from some leading I ahreini merchants be^irif, assistance for tne exeiiption o{ ! aiirein subjects from bein^ conscripted, 1 have obtained the names of some of those wuo are liable to be called up on kLnd April 1951, but understand taat ail heve taken out Sijil Awwal (Persian Nationality Papers; and tiiis was done some time ago witu the sole intention of either obtaining employment or of beirife able to travel to Iraq or other ports of Persia, I shall be {lad if you will kindly inform me if these men are liable for conscription, and if they should obey the sunmons. hi e U y's Vice Consul, CJl 1J . . Ia-m. I' 0 - Copy witu copy of petition is forwarded to tne 1 on'ble the Political Uesident, iersian Gulf, fur inforuation,Telegrami Fr om: To: No. Dated: should accept Persian nationality papers. As I could hold out no hope of preventing their 'being imprisoned if they refused I recoinmended that they should do so, but should in each individual case register protest at Hohmnmerah Vice Consulate rs proof they were acting under compulsion. They asked that representations should 'be made that they should not he conscripted until question of their nationality h^d been settled. I trust it will be possible to assis.t them, to this extent. - P.esident - uvl .'j. Political Residentj^ohammerah H.B.M* s Minister, Teheran Copy to: TT^M* s Consul, Ahwaz n ' H.M* s Vice-Consul,!.Tohaiiimerah ' by air mail to Govt.of India. T. 64 2nd May 1931. Eahrainis have soi^ht my advice as to whether they Copy forwarded to H.M 1 s Consul 3 Ahwaz,for inforrnatio to K.M*s Vice-ConsuljMohammerah, fo^ information. Camp, Mohammerah, the 2nd 'ay 19 31. 2nd Hay 19 31. r / , &gt; ------ Bahrain ' '' *»' -&lt; Attested: Confidential Assistant, British Hcsidency and Gonsulate-tieneral 4 th May 1931. 'Confidential, . v,,: N0.235-S of 1931. British Residency &amp; Consulate-General, Bushire, the 5th May 1931. The Hon*hie Lt.Colonel H.V.Biscoe, I.A. f Political Resident in the Persian Gulf The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, Simla* Sir. I have tie honour to address the Government of India regarding the treatment of Bahrain subjects resident in Khuzistan. Many of these Bahrain subjects have been settled in Khuzistan for 20 or 30 years and some of them longer. They fall within two categories^ (a) agric Itarists who have acquired date gardens and are chiefly settled in the Gusba area opposite Pao near the mouuh. of ohe Shatt-al-Arab; and (b) petty merchants, s:iop-ksepers, etc» ,who live in Mohammerah town. 2. When the Persian authorities started some years ago on their present reforms and required all Persian subjects to register themselves and to wear certain prescribed clothing, the question arose of the nationality of these Bahrainis. The Persian authorities, in support of th«ir claim to Bahrain, contended that they were -ersian sucjects and Drought considerable pressure upon them ... From. - To-2- them in Tarious derious mannerB to register as Persian nationals. The Bahrainis for some time resisted these efforts and the matter was ultimately referred to His Majesty's Legation and was discussed 'by Sir Robert Clive with the Minister of Court. In this connection I would invite a reference to Sir Robert Clive* s despatch llo. 476 of 18th September 1929 to His Majesty^ Principal • i Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, of which a eopy was sent to the Grovernment of India. In that despatch His Majesty's Minister reported that he had receired an assurance from Teymourtache that, pending a solution of the Bahrain question, the Bahrainis should be left in peace. I regret to report that, whatever instructions to this effect may hare been issued by the Persian authorities at Tehran, the local authorities in Khuzistan hare certainly not acted up to them. His Majesty's /ice Consul at Mohammerah informed me itotot during the winter of 1929-30^the Bahrainis were being subjected with every kind of petty annoyances in Mohammerah that the ingenious minds o^ uhe Persian police could devise and that great pressure was being put upon them to adopt Persian nationality. When I went to Bahrain in December 1929, strong representations were made to me by the local Shia* priests regarding the treatment accorded to Bahrainis in Mohammerah; and on each occasion that I hare visited Mohammerah I have received deputations of Bahrainis seeking my support against the Persian authorities. 4 » most flagrant case of ill-treatment of Bahrainis at the hands of the Persians is that of one Haj i ...Haj i Hamid. Shis individual wag deported to * Iraq by tiie x-ersian authorities and his case has formed the subject of repeated representations lay His Majesty 1 ® Minister, but so far without effect. On arrival at Basrah, after having been taken to task by the Persian Consul for his lack of patriotism in saluting the British Vice-Consul at MohanL-ierah in a public place, he was promised a safe conduct on condition that he asked for a passport as a Persian subject. He refused to comply with this demand but submitted a request for a passport giving his national status as being that of a Bahraini born at Bahrain. A few days later the Persian Coneul told the British Consul at Basrah that he had received authority to issue to persons of dual nation- ality who wished to proceed to Persia special permits, making- no mention of the nationality of the individual concerned, and th.cit in his opinion Bahrainis were to be considered as coding within this category. However, the passport issued to Haji Hamid by the Persian Consul described him as being a ,, Mohammerahi' , , born at Mohammerah. With this docu ment HaJi Hamid returned to Mohammerah where, however, two or three days later he was arrested by the Persian authori ties and put on a ship for Bushire. When the Vice-Consul at Mohammerah enquired the reasons for this action he was % told that it was done under the express orders of the Central Government. Haji Hamid naturally did not desire to get off at Bushire, where he would assuredly have been arrested, and proceeded to Karachi. On arrival there, as e was not in possession of a passport, he was fined Hs.15/- by the local police and put on board the steamer and sent back to Basrah, where he still is. I have since taken ...tdLtmsr. L , r -4- / i 1 ' ■» i 110 fit taken up his case with the Commissioner in Sind who kindly obtained for me a refund of the fine imposed on this un fortunate individual, who however is still at Basrah unable to pursue his normal commercial activities at Mohaminerah. 5. When I visited Mohammerah in October last» further specific cases of pressure being brought to bear on Bahrainis came to my notice and were reported to His Majesty's Minister and the Government of India in my telegram Ho.T # lll of 31st October 1930 ( copy enclosed for ready reference).' Ag a result of that telegram urgent representations were made to the Persian Government by Mr. Parr in his note of 4th November 1930, but hitherto without effect, and the Persian authorities, so far from in any way modifying their previous attitude or attempting to implement the assurance given to His Majesty 1 s Minister, have been more active than ever in harassing these unfortunate people# As a result of their action and the apparent powerlessness of the British authorities to protect them a number of these Bahrainis have accepted Persian nationality papers whereupon the Persian authorities have gone further and have promptly conscripted the younger members of the community for service in the Persian army, and His Majesty^ Vice Consul, Mohammerah, where I recently proceeded in order to discuss this matter, informed me that some 30 of them had been sent off to Ahwaz. His Majesty's Acting Consul at Ahwaz referred the matter to His Majesty's Minister, but has been informed in reply that, as these individuals had taken out Persian nationality papers, nothing could be done for them. On the other hand two Bahrainis by name Jafer and Aziz, aged respectively 17 and 24, sons of one Abdul Syed an ...an undoubted Bahrain subject, refused to accept Persian nationality papers and were imprisoned on the 28th April 'by the Persian authorities. They were still in prison when I left Mohammerah. His Majesty^ Vice Consul had attempted to intervene informally with the Governor of Mohammerah on their behalf y since there had been a working kst arrangement with the Governor that while he would accept official representations from the Vice Consul on behalf of Bahrainis he would be willing to listen to informal representations on their behalf, but on this occasion Dr• Lincoln received a verbal message from the Governor that he would not discuss the question of Bahrainis with him either formally or informally# I* The leading members of the Bahraini community came to see Me when I was in Mohammerah and asked me what they should do# As I was unable to hold out any hope for them that the British authorities would protect them, the only advice that I could give them was to accept Persian nationality papers under ptotest and to register their protest at the Vice-Consulate in each individual case so that when the question of Bahrain is ultimately settled there will be a definite record in the case of each individual that he registered under compulsion. These Bahrainis, as explained above, come under two categories - agricultiiirists and traders. The former category do not, I think, deserve much sympathy. I have informed them on several occasions that under Persian law foreigners are not allowed to own agricultural land. It is true th&amp;t in Shaikh Sir Khazal Khar^s days this law was not enforced in the case of Arabs in Khuzistan, but tho se ...* ! ' I • /? iv ♦ ^ f • ^— • -6- those days are now past and the Persian law on the subject is well-known, I believe, to every foreigner. I have told them that, as long as they are infringing the Persian law, it is not possible for me to do anyting for them; they are seeking to get the best of both worlds; the advantages of Persian nationality without its drawbacks. This they cannot have. They should, I think, be informed that until they divest themselves of their agricultural lands they cannot claim the privilege of Bahrain nationality. 9. The others however are on a totally different footing. Foreigners are allowed to own shops, warehouses, and dwelling houses, and that is all that most of these individuals possess, and in view of the fact that we control the foreign affairs of the Bahrain state, and are responsible for the protection of their nationals abroad, I would strongly urge that it is incumbent upon the British Government to put an end to the persecution of these Bahrain subjects. I need hardly say that our powerlessness to protect Bahrainis is most strongly criticised in Bahrain and has a bad effect on our general position on the Arab coast. 10. As a means of bringing pressure to bear on the Persian Government I would suggest that unless they undertake definitely to release those Bahrain subjects already conscripted and to cease at once their further persecutions of Bahrainis in Khuzistan until the question has been finally settled^ they should be informed that the special privileges at present enjoyed by Persians resident ..resident in Bahrain, under which they are subject only to the jurisdiction of the Political Agent and not to that of the Bahrain authorities, will be discontinued, ad that they will be treated in all respects as Bahrain subjects. I doubt whether the ruling authorities in Persia are Tery deeply interested in the fate of their compatriots in Bahrain, but 1 think they would regard the abolition of the capitulations ( if I may so describe it) in Bahrain as a blow to their amour propre an d I doubt if it would be necessary to put the threat into execution* In practice, it would probably be more conrenient in the first instance merely to make a Bahrain warrant operative in the case of Persians resident in Bahrain and then arrange with the Bahrain authorities to hand them oyer to the Political Agent for trial. This howerer is an administrative detail which could be considered later in the improbable event of some action of this kind being necessary. 11. I am aware that there are large considerations ¥ involved in this question, but I would urge that it is in cumbent upon His Majesty^ Government to take measures to protect a community who are entitled to claim their protection. I trust therefore that uy representations will receive a sympathetic hearing and that something will be done on behalf of these people. 12. I am sending copies of this despatch to His Majesty^ Secretary of State for India, His Majesty^ (£).._ ^ 'an, Minister at Tehran, the Political Agent, Bahrain and His ^ x Majesty f s Consular officers at Ahwaz and Mohammerah. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant, Lt.Colonel, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. ' fair Ai fjr'rjr &amp; ' « hi. IV. Si 111 i /,Confidential, of 1931. British Residenoy &amp; Congulate-General 9 Bushire, the 5th May 1931. /£ -v'' Sir, I hare the honour to forward herewith for the s information of Jiis Majeaty^ Gorernment a copy of my despatch ^ o#235-S of today*s date and of its enclosure to the Foreign Secretary to the Goyernment of India regarding the treatment of Bahrain subjects resident in Khuzistan* I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient, humble servant, //V Lt.Colonel. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Secretary of State for India, India Office, London.^,^11 ■■ ! ' ' {/\\ fcu njiyv 7 Extract from Private and Personal letter of 4/5/31 from the Political resident, Bushire to Sir Robert ^live, H.Il 's Minister, 'Eehran. x x t Do you think there is an^ possilDility of doing anything for the .bahrainis in Mohammerah? There are two classes those who own agricultural land and those who work as pett^ shop-keepers, etc. I have ^definitely informed the former that I have very little sympathy for them. They have infringed Persian regulations 'by aouiring *££ ^^ricultural land and are trying to gel the best of h th worlds, i.e. the advantage of Bahrain and Persian nation- -ality. I understand some of them ar tryimg to dispose of their lan^and return to Bahrain. Anyhow they have not got much enc )uragement from me. As regards the second category there is nrt the smallest doubt that the Persians have oppressed them and have forcibly compelled many of them to take out nationality certificates. I have given concrete cases of this and now two of them are in jail lor refusal to do so, and the Persians have brought mat- -ters to a head 'by conscripting them. It is a matter which I think should he brought to the notice of H.L.G. and I am about to write a despatch on the.subject of-w- which I will send you a copy. -te are definitely respon- -sible the protection of Bahrain!s abroad since we control the foreign relations of Bahrain, and I must say they have a legitimate grievance . I should therefore be grateful if something could oe done in the matter. All they asked for was that Shpuld not be conscripted until the question of their nationality had been settled ThiSfreally what Teymour promised you.No. (jM- ryi^o Ag: British Consul at Basra presents his compliments to Tile Hon'blc Lhe F ) 1 i ical HGsident and, C on c.u 1-General Bush ire and has the honour to transmit to him the under-mentioned documents. BASRA April 30 » , Reference to previous correspoyidence: Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Copy of Basra despatch No. 5 0 '£ even date to Bahrein. Bahrain! refugees at Fao/tQ« 5« Sir, British Consulate, BASRA, I r e q, April )0, 1931. I have the honour to inform you that as a result of incr ased actiTity on the part of the census and conscription officials :a ihuzistan, some thirty or forty B hreinis of ailitory age, who »ere resident in (.asha, have recently crossed the bhatt-ol-Arab and taken refuge in Fao. 2. As these men entered the country without visas they were detained by the Iraq Police and brought to Basra. The local authorities have however now decided not to take proceeoings against them and have permitted them to return to Fao. 5. The refugees have submitted petitii to this Consulate requesting that they may be allowed to return unmolested by the Persian authorities to their homes in Qasba, or that their families may be permitted to join them 4. They have been Informed that as this Consulate is not accredited to the Persian Govornment no steps can be taken by me in the sense of their request* Their petitions have been ]olitical Agent, IAHUJBIM.2. been forwarded in original to His aajeety's Vloe-Consul, Hohaaaera, for such action as he may think fit. 5. A copy hereof is being sent to His Majesty's Principal Secretory of Etate for Foreign Affairs, His Sicellency the High Coaaissioner for Iraq, H. M. Hinistei at Tehran, 'i'he liw 'ble The olitical Resident and Consul-Oeneral, Bushire, H, M. Consul, Ahwaz, and H. M. Vice-Consul at Kohammera. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your aost obedient servant. J. C. O'Dwyer. Acting British Ccn sul.*■ t - A : - Witn reference to your letter P.Z.493/3i of the 27th January, I am directed ty Mr, Secretary rienderson to transmit to you, to te laid before the Secretary of State for India 'V.r- ^ t ' the accompanying copy of a despatch from His Majesty^ Charge A d'Affaires at Tehran, enclosing copies of correspondence recently exchanged 'between Mr. Parr and the Persian Ministry of foreign Affairs relative to the passport regulations of the Bahrein Government and the treatment of Bahreinis in Persia. 2. Mr. Henderson proposes subject to Mr. Secretary Benn^s concurrence, to approve the terms of Mr. Parr , s note of the 25th February to the Persian Government. 3. A copy of this letter is being sent to the Colonial Office. I am, etc., (Sd). G. W. Rendel. . The Under Secretary of State,a Resident, .bushire. political j^gatyxwar^raVct* Telegram - G.T.Gode. From To - political Agent, Bahrain. No* - 300 Bated the 9th Ms^y 1931. Your telegram dated the 7th May Reply being sent uy next mail. -RESIDENTConfidential. D* C)« No# 243«»S« Please refer to your telegram dated 7th May asking whether anything has tronepired# The Incident you reported in your telegram of the 23rd io only one of several that have occur&lt; | red recently# Some days a^o Colonel Biscoe paid a short visit to ^ohammerah and while there he received a deputation from Bahrain!s seeking British assistance. As a result of what he heard Colonel Biscoe has addressed both the Government of India and His lajesty s ir is j in Tehran, but I doubt whether much will come of it and I fear the position of Bahrainis in Persia will remain much as it is at present until the vexed question of their nationality has been Capt.C.G.Prior # I#/•* Political Agent» Bahrain* ,/ British Residency # Bu8hire t the 9th May 193!•No. 55. British Legation, Tehran, May 1st, 19 31 CCNRuvtT^u .itOC^SS His Britannic Majesty's Representative presents his The ilon. the political Resident in the Persian Gulf and compliments to/4lis Majesty's Consul-General at Bus hire and transmits herewith copies of the documents mentioned in the subjoined schedule. \ Reference i if 1 Despatch to His Majesty 1 s Vice-Consul at Mohammerah, o. d dated 1st May, 1931. HaJi Haraid ibn Haji Abood Bahreini«o # 2/29/lQ&gt;/lQb Of 1931, ty b H.M* ( Vice- i-oiiohamittrpii, i&gt;ete&lt;i til* 14th 1 »y 1931. ir 3ir, 71th reference to your d«apatch lo. ^ d.at«d the l«t ay VJZ1, forwarding a copy* of th# Persian GoY«nllixent , • reply to your note on tlie subject of Kajl Hamld J ahrelnl, 1 iiara the honour to lubmlt the foliowing obsarvatlona In 3tpt«iat)«r i9k9 1 was on laaTa but from dsapatche# written by my successor Captain jfletcher, Jajl iiamld was on the 6th aeptenber 19^9 taken across the •Iraq frontier In a car and left tne re to find h&amp;s way to i as rah, I hare now had this rerlfied by this Vice-Consul ate Mlraa and ot^ier Bahreinls (relstions and friends of Hajl Hafnld) all of whoco state tnat he was put In a car and escorted by a policeman to the ♦Iraq frontier where the driver was riven orders to take him to Basrah. I am prepared to believe all these statements in preftrence to the report of the loiice Authority at *ohaBi»erah # whioh is mendaeious. As iiajl haaid Baiueini is still at Basrah 1 have discuesed tnis subject wiih His Majesty^ Consul tasre and asked iiim to obtain a statement and forward it to you with his observations, as Uaji hanid is in the best position to give details of his deportation. 11M) Translation of a^undated petition (received on the 14th May 1951) from some of the Bahreinis of Gusba to His Majesty 1 s Vice-Consul, Mohammerah. We beg to report to you that 4 nights ago the Governor of Gu3'ba sent some men to our houses and took by force from us, up to now 45 Certificates of Nationality of Bahrein which we had, and has given us very much trouble, 3 of our headmen are still detained at Ahwaz, The Governor states tnat tnese 3 Headmen will not be released until all the Bahreinis of Gusba hand over their Certificates of Nationality to the Governor, Kow as we are in great trouble, we report the matter to you with the request to nelp us in the matter, or to order ua to hand over our Certificates of Nationality. Several of us have escaped to Pao and to Basrah, leaving our faniilies at Gusbah, we request, therefore, to take action and zxidtK release us from this great trouble. (sa) ^li ibn Huasain, Seyid Mehdi ibn S.KhamiB Seyid Saleh ibn S,Khai'i8 Seyid Jaffar ibn Khaaiia,Translation of a petition datef the llth Jay 1931 from so-na of the Bahrelnii of Gualna to His Majesty's Vice-Corsul, Moharmnerah, We beg to report to you regarding the Bahreinis residing at Gusba who were arrested by the Persian Authorities, and by your kind assistance they were released. We are very much thankful for all your f assistance, Kow our headmen heve been ordered by the Governor that ail the Banreinis who kslxm are in possession of Certificates of Nationality of Bahrein, must nand them over to the Governor within 7 days. After wnich they will be taken away from them by force, and made CKftw. take Sijil Ahwal. If they refuse to take Sijil Ahwal, they will be deported and all their property etc. will be confiscated, 3 of our headmen named Seyid Ahmad Ibn Seyid Uajid, Seyid Salah Ibn Seyid Yousif and ehdi Ibn .iatoog nre a till detained at Aawaa. We do not know why thyy Iiave been detained there up to now. Y^e are still at Fao, a^ we afraid to return to our place at Ousba. Wo and our family are in great trouble. We beg to request you to help us in the Blatter, and release us from this trouble by taking necessary action for our return to our place at Gus ^ia, awaiting for your kind assistance, Seyid Kizwan 3/0 Seyid Kaz4m, Ibrahim ibn Sal eh, Abood ibn Abdullah, Mahmood ibn Abdullah, Abdul Sada ibn haji Ibrahim, Salman ibn Ahmad, (Sd) M H M ***«19/109 Telegram R. From H.M # s Consul, Ahwaz. To Political Resident, Sushire, No 9 ■^ated 19th. received 20th. ^ay 1931. —^Oour telegram ^o 295 dated May 8th. ^Govermnr -General returned from Tehran 17th. and I called yesterday evening. When I spoke ahout ©ahrolnis he replied Bahrain is Persian Tsrritory and that inhabitants are Persian subjects. He said therefore he could not dis- -cuss anything concerning these people with me nor was t K he ahle to disclose to me- instructions received con cerning Persians and for same reason he could not tele graph to Tehran. ^ J * /J. rti «. movements ('*VvVV y here. j Your telegram No 61-T of April 29th. The two men are still in prison and have s*-. Britconsul. V i 1 C''' *'5 The aho^e telegram^repeated to E.^'s MigtSter, Tehran &gt;1 r under our Noyfel9 dated 2ist. kay 1931, with reference to his telagram No. 23. Post copy fomaraed to the Political Agent at Bahraij for information. Attested: British Bus hire, 2l0t May 1931 Confidential ABsistant, idency and Consulate-General&lt; INDIA OFFICE, .miTEHALL, LONDON, S .r .l. Fo.P.Z.1693/31 llf^i ipril, 1931. ^ I Sir, In reply to your ietber of 19tji !uarch No. E. 1131/455/91, i am airectea 'by the Secretary of State for Inoia to say that he concurs in the proposal of the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs to approve the terms of !!r. Parr's note of the 25th February to the Persian Government on the subject of Bahrein. t A copy of this letter has 'been sent to the Colonial Office. I am. Sir, Your obedient Servant, (Sd) J.C. iaIton. The Under Secretary of State, Foreign Office.- p O 19/109 Telegram From XX^. Government of India, Foreign &amp; Political Department. Simla. Secretary of State for India, London. Political resident, Bushire. Mol383-S H.M # s Minister, Tehran. No.49-T No 1383-S Bated 21st. received 22nd. May 1931. To Hepeated to rj VviV 'vcx/v) v fx*. &lt; with reference to his telegram No 83 &lt;u of May 14th. of May 5th. 4 ill Political Hesident's despatch i^o 235-S Treatment of Bahreinis in Khuzistan. Provided that His Majesty's Grovern- ■(XW -ment are satisfied^Persians disregard of their own undertakings justifies departure on our part f from maintenance of status quo. lOe recommend action he taken as suggested in paragraph No.10 of Hesident's despatch. l \ V Foreign.Confidential * No :C/56. From:- BUSH Rr 'ESi^'-'CV fat ■JUfT Dfiit. n/tfu GOHFIDt'iTUu .tLvjO^OS Political Agency, Captain C .G.Prior,I. a., Political Agent ,Bahrain. The Hon T ble the Political nesident in the Persian Gulf., Bushire. r /O I have the honour to refer to your despatch No:235-S dated the 5th May 1931 to the Foreign Secretary to the Government of India,and to say that the treatment of Bahama in Muhammerah has aroused considerable resentment in iiaiirain particularly amongst the Shiah sections of the population. fy\k&gt; 2. With regard to para 10 of the above mentioned letter, 1 would suggest that use might be made of the additional threat to abolish the Pahlavi cap in Bahrain and close the Persian schools if the Persian Government do not cease their persecution of Bahrain subjects in Persia. Recent events have shown me that the ruling authorities in Persia take a deep and urgent interest in the affairs of their nationals jL in Bahrain,and I feel sure that a prohibition of the head gear so closely associated with His Majesty Riza Shah would strike their amour propre in a most sensitive spot. I have the honour to be Sir, Your Most Obedient Servant, Political Agent, Bail rain.19/109 * * Telegram ■From To XX. Repeated to H.M's Minister, Tehran Goveinment of India, Foreign &amp; Political Department. Simla. Secretary of State for Foreign At fairs, London. NollO. Political Resident, Bushire. No. 32. Dated 26tti. received 27ttL. ^ay 1931. Bushire con(|iiential despatch Ho. 235-3 to you, dated Kay 5th. Bahreinis. z}^' 9 I trust suggestion in paragraph 10 will 'be seriously considered. Persian Government have shown continuously had faith in their treatment of Bahrainis in Persia and I consider, subject to your views, that we are justified in warning Persian G-o^ernment that Persians in Bahrein will cease to have privileged position if present treatment of Bahreinis in Persia continues Olive.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000127_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/322</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000127</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/322</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 19/109 V (C 32) Bahrain Relations with other Foreign Powers'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1929/1931</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2013-11-26T11:06:31</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">fre</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (271 folios)</extent><extent>File is arranged in chronological order, from earliest at beginning of the file to most recent at end.</extent><extent>Formerly a bound correspondence volume, the file's pages have been unbound and are now loose.Foliation starts on first page of text, top right hand circled number. Ends on last page in volume. There is another pencilled, uncircled system that starts on f.2.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains correspondence between British and Persian government officials regarding the harassment and mis-treatment of Bahrainis resident in Persia, notably in the town of Mohammerah (present day Khorramshahr).Much of the correspondence concerns the arrest of a Bahraini trader named Haji Hamid and reports that the Persian government was forcing Bahrainis to give up their Bahraini nationality and adopt Persian nationality. A petition from Bahrainis resident in Persia (addressed to the British resident) is contained on f.215.The file also contains correspondence related to an incident involving Bahrainis in Iraq being forced to adopt Iraqi nationality.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="personal"><namePart>James Orton</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="personal"><namePart>Francis Warden</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="personal"><namePart>Hugh Weightman</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="family"><namePart>Āl Khalīfah (Family)</namePart></name></subject><subject><geographic>Khorramshahr</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Bahrain</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Būshehr</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Foreign relations</topic></subject><subject><topic>National Economy</topic></subject><subject><topic>Religious conflicts</topic></subject><subject><topic>Rights of states</topic></subject><subject><topic>Arab nationalism</topic></subject><subject><topic>Social reform</topic></subject><subject><topic>Economic reform</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000127#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>