<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000602.0x00036e_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-05-23T13:09:36.710Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">86 (Translation.) The Minister for Foreign Affairs. lour Excellency, . Rome, April 16, 1988. 1 have the honour to inform your Excellency that the following Declaration regarding Lake Tsana was signed to-day by Lord Perth and myself as Annex 5 to the Protocol which Lord Perth and T have also signed to-day:— T t “ Jke Italian Government confirm to the Government of the flu Jl 1 ” gd ? I ^. the as8urance given by them to the Government of the United Kingdom on the 3rd April, 1986, and reiterated by the Italian Minister for Foreign Affairs to His Majestv’s Ambassador at Pome on the 31st December, 1936, to the effect that the Italian Government were fully conscious of their obliga tions towards the Government of the United Kingdom in the matter of Lake Tsana and had no intention whatever of over looking or repudiating them.” Further, I have the honour to inform your Excellency that the Italian Government for their part declare that they agree that the assurances given to the Government of the United'Kingdom in the above. Declaration concerning Lake Tsana apply equally to the Egyptian Government. I avail, &amp;c. CIANO. Mostafa El Sadek Bey to Cotint Ciano. Legation de S.M. le Roi d’Egypte a Rome, Your Excellency, Apri i 16j 1938&gt; I have the honour to acknowledge the receipt of your Excellency’s hlote of to-day’s date, which reads as follows I have the honour to inform your Excellency that the following Declaration regarding Lake Tsana was signed to-day by Lord Perth and myself as Annex 5 to the Protocol which Lord I erth and I have also signed to-day :— t- -1* *,^. G Italian Government confirm to the Government of the United Kmgdom the assurance given by them to the Government ot the United Kingdom on the 3rd April, 1936, and reiterated by the Italian Minister for Foreign Affairs to- His Majesty’s Ambassador at Rome on the 31st December, 1936, to the effect that the Italian Government were fully conscious of their obligations towards the Government of the United Kingdom in e matter of Lake Tsana and had no intention whatever of over looking or repudiating them.’“Further, 1 have the honour to inform Your Excellency that the Italian Government for their part declare that they agree that the assurances given to His Majesty’s Government in the above Declaration concerning Lake Tsana apply equally to the Egyptian Government.’’ I shall have pleasure in communicating this information to the Egyptian Government. T avail, &amp;c. MOSTAFA EL SADEK. (iii) EXCHANGE OF NOTES BETWEEN THE UNITED KINGDOM, EGYPT AND ITALY REGARDING THE SUEZ CANAL. Lord Perth to Mostafa El Sadek Bey. British Embassy, Rome, Your Excellency, • April 16, 1988. I have the honour to inform Your Excellency that the following Declaration regarding the Suez Canal was signed to-day by the Italian Minister for Foreign Affairs and myself as Annex 8( 6 ) to the Protocol whicli we have also signed to-day :— “ The Government of the United Kingdom and the Italian Government hereby reaffirm their intention always to respect and abide by the provisions of the Convention signed at Constantinople on the 29th October, 1888, which guarantees at all times and for all Powers the free use of the Suez Canal.’’ I have the honour to communicate the above Declaration to Your Excellency as the Representative of the territorial Power concerned. I avail, &amp;c. PERTH.Perth and myself as Annex 8 to the Protocol which Lord Perth and I have also signed to-day :— “The Italian Government and the Government of the United Kingdom hereby reaffirm their intention always to respect and abide by the provisions of the Convention signed at Constantinople on the 29th October, 1888, which guarantees at all times and for all Powers the free use of the Suez Canal.” 1 have the honour to communicate the above Declaration to Your Excellency as the Representative of the territorial Power concerned. I avail, &amp;c. CIANO. Legation de S.M. le Roi d’Egypte h Rome, Your Excellency, April 16, 1988. 1 have the honour to acknowledge the receipt of Note of to-day's date in which YYtur Excellency informed me of the Declaration regard ing the Suez Canal signed to-day by Your Excellency and His Majesty’s Ambassador at Rome as Annex 8 to the Protocol which you and Lord Perth have also signed to-day. I have the honour to inform Your Excellency that the Egyptian Government, as the territorial Power concerned, take note of the intention of the Italian Government and the Government of the United Kingdom and associate themselves therewith. I avail, &amp;c. MOSTAEA EL SADEK.The Under-Secretary of State, India Office. I am directed 'by Viscount Halifax to invite reference to Foreign Office letter No. R 2541/23/22 of the 29th March, and to transmit herewith a copy of a despatch from His Majesty 1 s Ambassador at Rome containing the observations of the Italian Government on the proposals of His Majesty’s Government in the United Kingdom for the surrender of British extraterritorial jurisdiction in Ethiopia. 2. It will be seen that the general attitude of the Italian Government is that they would prefer to deal with most of the matters mentioned in the British draft Heads of Agreement in the negotiations envisaged in the two concluding paragraphs of the Protocol signed by Lord Perth and Count Ciano on the 16th April, 1938, which formed part of the agreement of that date between the Government of the United Kingdom.and the Italian Government (Treaty Series No.31 (1938), Cmd.5726). If the procedure suggested by the Italian Government were adopted, the effect would be that the provisions of any agreement reached with regard to these matters would be reciprocal as opposed to unilateral* 3. So far as the third article of the British draft Heads of Agreement is concerned (which provides that British subjects and British protected persons shall not perform in Ethiopia ' dU/V 10 .2.4 4 2-0Ethiopia any form of military services voluntary or compulsory and shall not he compelled to furnish money or service in lieu of military service), the British desiderata in this respect have already been met under that clause of the Bon Voisinage Agreement between the United Kingdom, Egypt and Italy, of the 16th April last, (see page 32 of the Command paper referred to above) which states that nationals of the other Party shall not be enrolled in the native troops, bands or formations of a military nature maintained in the Sudan, Kenya, British Somaliland and Italian East Africa respectively Lord Halifax is therefore of the opinion that there is no objection to the omission of Article 3in the British draft Heads of Agreement from any agreement ultimately reached with the Italian Government on the subject of extra-territorial jurisdiction in Ethiopia. 4. The fifth paragraph of the British draft Heads of Agreement deals with the rights and privileges of consular officers and corresponds, to some extent, with Article 12 of the Anglo-Italian Commercial Treaty of 15th June, 1883, the extension of which to Italian East Africa, on conditions to be established, will, under the Anglo-Italian Protocol of the 16th April last, form one of the subjects to be discussed between His Majesty f s Government and the Italian Government after the instruments annexed to that Protocol have taken effect. Indeed, the fifth paragraph of the British draft Heads of Agreement respecting extra-territoriality in Ethiopia is to the same effect as the concluding sentence of Article 12 of the Treaty of 1883, although it adds the proviso that British consular officers in Ethiopia shall enjoy treatmentri G / M. JL* ^ J and privileges not less favourable than those accorded to British consular officers in Italy. Lord Halifax considers that it would be difficult to reject the Italian suggestion that this matter should be dealt with in the course of the negotiations contemplated in the Protocol of the 16th April last; but he is in some doubt whether, in that event, it will be possible to secure the provision that British consular officers in Ethiopia shall enjoy the same treatment as similar officers in Italy, as he is not clear whether Italian consular officers in other parts of the British Empire can be accorded the same treatment as Italian consular officers in the United Kingdom. 5. Lord Halifax would also draw attention to the two concluding sentences of Article 5 of the British draft Heads of Agreement, which provide that British consular officers in Ethiopia shall have the right to visit in prison any British subject or British-protected persons wno are in prison prior to sentence being passed upon them, and that communications from British subjects and British-protected persons to British consular officers will be forwarded to them. Lord Halifax considers that His Majesty’s Government should endeavour to secure these d esiderata and, if the Secretaries of State for the Hone Department and the Colonies agree that His Majesty’s Government can accord reciprocity in this matter to Italian consular officers in territories under their control, he would j r : ■ rfN r in the negotiations contemplated in the Anglo-Italian Protocol of the 16th April last, provided that they receive an assurance from the Italian Government that the latter are prepared to agree forthwith, in principle, to the provisions mentioned in the two sentences in question. 6. With regard to questions of extradition, Lord Halifax does not consider that the sixth article of the British draft Heads of Agreement is of great intrinsic importance. He would suggest that it he represented to the Italian Government that this article might stand in the eventual agreement, hut that this suggestion should not he pressed in the event of the Italian Government taking the opposite view. 7. The questions dealt with in the second article of the British draft Heads of Agreement (which mostly concerns statut personnel ) are not, in the view of Lord Halifax, such as would, ordinarily he dealt with in negotiations on commercial matters, hut they are such as His Majesty’s Government might reasonably request should he set down and agreed to at the moment when, as a result of the termination of British extra territorial jurisdiction in Ethiopia, British nationals in that country are transferred from the jurisdiction of His Majesty’s Courts to those of the territorial authorities. He considers, therefore, that the Italian Government should he pressed to examine the provisions of Article 2 of the British draft in detail, and to include some provision on those lines in the ev entual agreement regarding the surrender of British extra territorial jurisdiction in Ethiopia. 8. The counter-proposals of the Italian Government alsoalso affect the first article of the British draft Heads of Agreement, which dealt with the formal renunciation of British extra-territorial jurisdiction in Ethiopia, with the treatment of pending cases, and with judgments and decisions given hy the British Consular Courts. This article should he read in conjunction with the draft note to he addressed hy His Majesty^ Ambassador at Rome to the Italian Minister for Foreign Affairs, a copy of which was transmitted in the Foreign Office letter under reference. With regard to this matter, Lord Halifax is of the opinion that the Italian Government might he informed that when His Majesty's Government presented their draft of the note from Lord Perth to Count Ciano they realised that the Italian Government might take the view that British consular jurisdiction in Ethiopia automatically terminated with the establishment of Italian sovereignty in that country, and that as His Majesty’s Government were, in fact, ready to renounce any claim to continue it, they thought it unnecessary to examine such an Italian contention; and the draft of the note from Lord Perth to Count Ciano was rather carefully prepared so as to render it acceptable to the Italian Government and not to prejudice their point of view. The Italian Government would he informed, on the other hand, that they cannot expect His Majesty’s Government to accept the date of the 9th May, 1936, inserted in the first paragraph of the Italian draft, because, although His Majesty's Government were willing to renounce British extra-territorial jurisdiction in Ethiopia, they couldcould not be expected to agree to such renunciation as from a date prior to their recognition of Italian sovereignty over Bthiopia, and still less to agree that any automatic cessation of British extra-territorial jurisdiction in that country took place prior to that date. In this connexion it would be explained to the Italian Government that, although the British Consular Courts in Bthiopia have, since the 9th May, 1936, actually been practically in suspense, formally they have remained in being. It would be represented to the Italian Government that the point at issue cannot be of any great importance to them, since His Majesty’s Government are renouncing British extra-territorial jurisdicfckn in Bthiopia; and His Majesty’s Government therefore ask the Italian Government to agree that cases which, at the date of the signature of the agreement, were pending in His Majesty’s Consular Courts in Ethiopia should be dealt with by those Courts. His Majesty’s Government would further suggest that sub-paragraph (a) of Article 1 of their draft, by which they renounce all claim to the exercise in Ethiopia of extra territorial jurisdiction, might remain in the agreement, since it facilitates the position of His Majesty’s Government and is not inconsistent with the Italian view of the situation. Apart from the question of date, the first paragraph of the Italian draft does not vary very greatly from sub-paragraph (b) of the first article of the British draft, except for the last sentence of the Italian draft; and Lord Halifax is of the opinion that, subject to consultation(J3435/320/1)» regarding the question of the future of His Majesty’s Crovemaient towards the ad aini strati on of justice in ‘Sthiopia* I hove the honour to inform you that | a ;ree with the opinion expressed that we should be very t£&lt;rtful in intervening in tfie judicial sphere» except in those cases where ordinary diplomatic or consular representations are called for on behalf of m aggrieved British subject or company. There can be few countrie s where foreign intervention or even criticism is more easily resented than in Ethiopia* or where such resentment is rnOjTe sullenly and effectively mode to recoil on^the critic. Vhile tht number of British vdvisers and helpers in every other department of the -thiopian Government grows steadily less» partly on account of their propensity to dwell upon the unpalatable truth in matters of departmental concern* theVpresent British judges of the High Court# by ste;dily pur suing an even tenor in their daily work nd their relations with Ethiopian judges and officials, appear to be suiting all and offending none (except of course the unsuccessful litigants who come before them). The Iresldent of the High Court, Mr. A. F. N* Thavenot, expresses from tine to time his appreciation of the capabilities and legal acumen of many of'the Ithiopien judges who work with him and under him# and he retains the goodwill and personal interest of His Majesty the Emperor# who recently told him that his suggestions for a larger and better High Court building were beings favourably considered# and that a sum off pounds sterling one hundred and fifty thousand was being provided for tiie , cons traction as soon as possible. 3. The Ministry of Justice has been fortunate so far in having at its head one of the most intelligent aid reasonable of the new generation of higher officials here# but it is to be regretted that since his marriage to the -mperor’s only surviving daughter# Afa Mesfin Andargai Masai is said to have devoted much less time and interest to his office and Ministry ^ generally. The Vice-Minister Ato Ambai similarly neglects his post, and control is passing to the Director-General, a young and impulsive official named Memberai* . 4 # Following a co vers? tion with the First Secretary oi tills location last week. Mr. Thavenot has written a further and Hich Court, a coov of which is enclosed. Hie letter shows that■MHi 0 . * k#i - 2 - many handicaps which it will be a slow and difficult task to remove. There is little practical evidence that either the mperor or the i in'ster of Justice are sincerely keen or atoia to carry out their promises of improvement» and it will be &lt; seen that neither of them are above suspicion of being ready to interfere with justice when it suits them. If to this attitude is added the indifference or hostility of some officials* as mentioned in my despatch No.105 of 14th September last* it is clear that too open intervention on our part might defeat our own ends by causing resentment against the British judges now guiding the work of the High Court. 5. As regards the implementing of Article IV of the Anglo- gthiopien Agreement of December 19th. 1944» Mr. Thcvenot points out that if ell litigants*in the High Court were to 1 avail themselves of their right to demand the presence of a foreign judge (a right of which most are probably ignorant), a total of at least ten foreign judges would be necessary, and in his opinion are not likely to be provided by the present Ethiopian administration. The question of the appointment of new foreign judges will, however, arise sooner or later, and much confusion will be caused if the present trend of replacing British advisers and helpers by American or other foreign-trained personnel is continued in the case of the High Court. I have the honour to be, Vith the highest Tl'espect. Sir, Your most obedient humble Servant, (S gd.) R. G. hom vq&lt;C 0 I Y | The High Court, Addie Ababa. ■ . l - 19th February, 194-5. My Deer Cook, “With reference to our conversation on February 14th, and oiy memorandum of September-1 st 1944&gt; I think it may be useful if I put upon record some additional observations. In the first place, my memorandum was, as you know, prepared for the Emperor, and had therefore to be drafted with tact, ior I was conscious of the danger that I might antagonize H.M. by too great insistence on reform, or too candid criticism of the present system. The memorandum was, therefqre, H the truth and nothing but the truth”, but was very far from being ”the whole truth”. There can be no doubt that the establishment of the High Court has been welcomed by the bulk of the population. The people regard it as a bulwark against the arbitrary acts of the executive authorities, and as a protection against the almost insane injustice which reigns in many of the outlying provinces. Indeed they tend to ask for my interference petitions and complaints are almost invariably addressed to me and not to the Court - in matteis which 'are not justiciable. On the other hand the Court is regarded with suspicion by the executive authorities of all ranks, and in some'cases that suspicion becomes active obstruction. H. -I. supports the Court, and told me, when I had an audience in September, that he would deal.with any official who obstructed the Court, but it is obvious that, unless some serious question of principle is involved, I cannot be continually asking for his intervention. Moreover his support has definite limits, and does not preclude him from personal interference in cases in which he is interested for political or other reasons. The so-called Political Court was supposed to be abolished by the Administration of Justice Proclamation, but, as recent events have shown, it is still very active. It must also be borne in mind that no Ethiopian, whether he be a doorkeeper or a Minister, is willing to admit that he has no power in any matter whatsoever, and in consequence aggrieved litigants, as well as Ministers whose departmental actions have been brought before the Court, are continually soliciting the assistance of the Ministry of Justice. In two cases involving large sums of money I was asked by the Minister of Justice why the judgement was what it was. I took a firm line, and he applogatically said that the matters had been brought to the notice of the Emperor, and the judgements were duly executed. In another case the Minister, without any legal authority whatever, gave an order suspending the execution of a judgement. The matter was brought to my notice by the judgement creditor, 'and I at once saw the Minister, havir^ taken the precautj.6n to let it be known indirectly that I was prepared to resign. * He at once withdrew the order.I fear* however* that there inust be a great aany cases in whi'ch pressure is brought to beer upon the Ethiopian judges, and of which I never h. ar* With regard to the judges it is perhaps not suf iciently rellized that they have no legal training, and are quite ignorant of the ..ost elementary principles of civil law end procedure* Cne at leas' of -he ii^h Court judges cannot write and can herdly read, while their ignorance of any lenguage but their own pre vents theta from attempting to improve their legal knowledge* With one notorious exception* who seems to enjoy Palace favour, I have no evidence of corruption in the High Court* but all the judges allow litigants to approach them privately* and indeed it is quite usual to set a judge arrive at Court hand in hand with a litigant* It is difficult to teach them anything, for they are quite content with the existing system and do not think that they have anything to learn. The judges ere underpaid and their position confers no prestige, while the pay of the clerical staff comperes unfavourably with that in oth'r Hinistries* end there is undoubted corruption among them. In the* provinces the judges ar* notoriously corrupt, and the object of a provincial judge JLs to amass as much money as he can, until he is removed and soaeone else allowed to get a share of the loot. One of the chief methods of/extortion, adopted by both judges and Governors in the provinces, is to keep persons accused of crime, as well as their relatives, in gaol without trial, and at the same ti ae to seize their property. Unless a friend or relative can bring the matter to the notice of the High Court, the arrested persons remain in gads which are little be iter*than death-traps, until the required ransom is forthcoming. ' I can see little prospect of improvement in the provinces until couuiiunications art opened by road. With regard to the future of the High Court I may point out that none of the recommendations in my memorandum have been carried out; and, although H.i.• told me recently that it was intended to build new Courts, I think that in the present financial situation i hey will remain un Chateau d’Eepagne. In fact the building of new Coir ts in Addis Ababa is a far lees urgent matter then the repair or- rebuilding of provincial Courts, and an increase oi pay for interpreters and translators, which will enable us to engage competent men. tiy impression is that promises by H.1.1., or by the Minister of Justice, mean very little, ^xtra-territoriality and Consular Courts having been abolished by a stroke of the pen, instead of in stages as a reward of improvement; as was the case in Siam, there is little incentive to /remedy.- 3 - reuiedy abuses. As an example I may cite the question of a Civil Code, which is urgently needed. None of the Ethiopian judges seem to be aware of a law of torts, and they are completely ignorant on such matters as bills of exchange, bankruptcy, agency, and commercial law in all its branches. I*i September I raised the quest/ion , of a Civil Code with the Emperor, and he said that he regarded it as urgent. I pointed out that it wouli require V S expert foreign advice but suggested that it might:be possible to save time by adapting some foreign co^e* Nothing whatever has been done since then, though! I have mentioned the subject on several occasions t® Jthe Minister of Justice. With regard to European judges, und^r the new Anglo-Ethiopian Agreement all litigants, whether Ethiopians or aliens, are enti led to claim trial before a European judge. When the negotiations were in progress the Vice- Minister of Justice asked my opinion of the formula which was eventortally adopted. I told him that it would mean the anointment of at least ten foreign judges, at a coat of not less than £ 16,000 a year, and he acquiesced; but I do not believe that there is sny intention whatever of implementing that clause in the Agreement, for it is probably hoped that the great majority of litigants will remain ignorant of their rights. Mr. Wigan*s contract expires next October and Mr* Marein’s in September 194b, and I understand that they do not propose to renew them. My co tract expires on January 14th 1946. As at present a vised I am prepared to renew it, but I have received no intimation whether Government proposes to offer me a new contract, or not. Meantime since last Msy I have been doing the work of the Judicial Adviser as well as my own. I have no objection to the work, but it is inconvenient for ifle to advise oter departments or the Police on matters vhieh may come before me in a judicial capacity. The .iinistr^ of Justice hive taken no steps to obtain a Judicial Adviser to replace Mr. i/iathew, who left in May, despite repeated promises from the Minister. These notes are, I fear, very disjointed, but I shall be very happy to give you any further information you may need. Yours sincerely, (signed) A. F. ThavenotCONFIDENTIAL ^7/ THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY’S GOYERNMJ .V ABYSSINIA. CONFIDENTIAL. -/ 'J 2103/1/1] 4J0 q co Nuor /uo/ % MS June 9, 1944. ( SJ — ^ 0 , I. rf'. Jy Section isfry ' sM+S/ mzt- 3 oC; J 7 Copy ift. -A Arf Mr. Cook to Mr. Eden. y of '' Copy fo, Foi-^jpn, Aifhrrr 3 (Received §th June.) 'J (No. 114.) _ jCL 1944 Sir, Abaoa, 29th May, 1944. WITH reference to my telegram No. 294 I have the honour to transmit to you herewith a copy of the note Jated 55th May, addressed to me by the Ethiopian Vice-Minister for Foreign Affairs, giving three months’ notice of termination of the Agreement and of the Convention of the 31 st January. 1942. in accordance with the provision contained in Article All of the agreement. 2. In handing a formal acknowledgment of the notice to the Vice-Minister for Foreign Affairs the next day, I tried to sound him as to the reasons for his decision at this juncture, but without result. Ato Aklilou tended to assume a defensive attitude, saying that the Ethiopian Government were fully entitled to terminate the agreement, which no longer corresponded to the present situation, but stressing that they had no desire in so doing to terminate the special relations existing between our two countries. On the contrary, as he had repeatedly told Mr. Howe and myself during the last four months, it was his earnest wish to see a new agreement concluded as quickly as possible. For the first time Ato Aklilou mentioned the possibility of British counter-proposals to the Ethiopian draft agreement submitted in January last. 3. As I mentioned in my telegram No. 296, this legation had received no intimation of the intention to give notice as above, although the Oriental Counsellor and myself are in frequent contact with various members of the Government and with the advisers. We know, however, that in the almost daily confabulations of the Council of Ministers, in which so little is achieved, the question of the agreement forms a constant topic of anxious discussion, and it is this which no doubt contributes to the Emperor’s own anxiety to see quicker progress made over negotiations for a new understanding between our two countries. It is no secret that there are two parties or schools of thought as regards the value of close attachment to the British connexion, and it is rumoured that the Crown Prince (whose relations with the Emperor are now said to be much better than in the past) has expressed himself very strongly over the decision to give notice of termination of the present agreement. 4. A copy of this despatch is being sent to the Minister Resident in the Middle East. I have, &amp;c. F. A. G. COOK. .cx CXo. IX -/ ■ 7 . Enclosure. Vice-Minister for Foreign Affairs to Mr. Cook. Sir, Addis Ababa, 2bth May, 1944. REFERENCE is made to my note of the 12th January, 1944, in which was set forth the position of this Government in regard to the necessity of replacing the Agreement and the Convention of the 31st January, 1942, at the earliest possible moment, by a new agreement more consonant with the realities of the present situation, and with which was communicated a draft agreement trans mitted in the name and behalf of His Imperial Majesty. In communicating the proposal for a new agreement, His Imperial Majesty was acting in complete accord with the stipulations and spirit of theexisting agree ment which provide that His Majesty the Emperor make the proposals for a new treaty to replace the present agreement, and that if the replacement is not effected within two years from the date of the existing agreement, the latter would be subject to termination on three months’ notice. [54—29]2 It has ever been the sincere belief of this Government that, in following the procedure provided for in the Agreement of 1942, it would be entirely practicable to expect that their proposals should form the basis of a new agreement, and such remain to-day their desire and expectation, notwithstanding the absence of an expression of views of His Majesty’s Government in the United Kingdom in regard to the proposals of January last. As you are aware, during the ensuing months, this Government have earnestly hoped for and sought to obtain such/ expression of views, is the confident belief that from such negotiations there might be evolved a new agreement which would reaffirm the strong and lasting bonds of mutual interest and friendship which will always assure close and sincere collaboration between our two countries, in war as in peace. The passage of time has in no way lessened the force of the considerations which my august Sovereign and myself have already, at various times, had occasion to set forth to His Britannic Majesty’s representative, and which necessitate replacement at the earliest possible moment of an agreement which no longer corresponds with the realities of the present situation. In consequence, I have the honour to transmit to you by the present, and through you to His Britannic Majesty’s Government in the United Kingdom, in the name and at the order of His Majesty the Emperor, my august Sovereign, and conformably to the provisions of Article XII of the Agreement of the 31st January, 1942, between our two countries, notice of termination of the Agreement and of the Convention of the 31st January, 1942, between the Empire of Ethiopia and the United Kingdom, upon the expiration of a period of three months from the date of the present notice. I wish, however, at this time to emphasise the fact that although the passage of time no longer justifies further delay in regard to the termination of the present Agreement and Convention, it is the sincere and earnest hope of His Imperial Majesty’s Government that negotiations for the new agreement on the basis of the draft proposal may promptly take place so as to realise the hope at all times entertained by this Government for the conclusion of such an agreement before the termination of the Agreement and Convention now in force. It is in this spirit that I solicit your best efforts to that end. Accept, &amp;c. AKLILOU, Vice-Minister.1942 No. 908 i L, J*. KyjJ.Zt FOREIGN JURISDICTION - xJUmk Ethiopia^t&gt; v / . v* i/i A. The King’s Most Excelle.nt Majesty in Council. Whereas His Majesty The King has agreed to the termination of the jurisdiction which by treaty, grant, usage, sufferance or other lawful means. His Majesty had in Ethiopia: And whereas provision is at present made for such jurisdiction by the Ethiopia Order in Coimcil, I934( a )» an d as regards appeals by the Eastern African Court of Appeal (Amendment) Order in Council I 934( b ): And whereas it is therefore expedient to abrogate the said Ethiopia Order in Council and the said Eastern African Court of Appeal Order in Council, 1934 : And whereas the Governments of Canada, the Commonwealth of Australia, New Zealand, the Union of South Africa and of India have requested and consented to the making of this Order as regards 7 those interests with which they are respectively concerned: Now, therefore, His Majesty, by virtue and in exercise of the powers in this behalf by the Foreign Jurisdiction Acts, 1890 and I 9 I 3( C )» or otherwise in His Majesty vested, is pleased, by and with the advice of His Privy Council, to order, and it is hereby ordered as 1. The Ethiopia Order in Council, 1934, and all Rules and Regula tions made thereunder, the Eastern African Court of Appeal (Amend ment) Order m Council, 1934, and the application to Ethiopia of the Foreign Jurisdiction (Military Forces) Order in Council, 1927(d), and of the Foreign Jurisdiction (Probates) Order in Council, 1935(e), are hereby T t lis ° rder ma y be cited a s the Ethiopia (Termination of Juris diction) Order, 1942 . And the Right Honourable Anthony Eden and the Right Honourable Viscount Cranborne, two of His Majesty's Secretaries of State, are to give the necessary directions herein. Rupert B. Howorth (a) S.R. &amp; O. 1934 (No. 360) I, p. 595. (b) S.R. &amp; O. 1934 (No. 217) I, p. 649. ( c ) 53 &amp; 54 Wet. c. 37 and 3 &amp; 4 Geo. 5. c. 16. (d) S.R. &amp; O. 1927 (No. 359) p. 478. (e) S.R. &amp; O. 1935 (No. 896) p. 522. LONDON PRINTED AND PUBLISHED BY HIS MAJESTY'S STATIONERY OFFICE r° ^ Purchased directly from H.M. STATIONERY OFFICE at the following addresses: York House, Kmgsway, London, W.C.2; 120 George Street, Edinburgh 2: 39-41 King Street, Manchester 2; 1 St. Andrew’s Crescent. Cardiff- P (4345r) Wt. 9—1 375 5/42 D.L. G 80 Chicl or thn INDIA OFFICE.from Letter 19k.h. Under Secretary Secretary of State ... Corrutfittee Under Secre^iry Secretao/of State '? ■ i /f Initials. SUBJECT. ETHIOPIA. Agreement and Military Convention between the United Kingdom and Ethiopia FOR USE BY DEPARTMENT ONLY. mi?: The objects of H.M*G.'s future policy in Ethiopia are set out in the confidential memorandum immediately below, .which is recomriended for perusal. An'*Agreement and Military Convention has accordingly been drawn up and signed at Addis Ababa on 31st January, 1942* by H.M. the Emperor of Ethiopia and Major-General Sir P.E. Mitchell on behalf of the Government of the United Kingdom.# It is to remain in force until replaced by a Treaty between the two countries. If not replaced within two years, it may be terminated thereafter by either party giving three months’ notice. The provisions of the Agreement are briefly as follows Article I. Diplomatic relations to be re-established and conducted through a British Minister Plenipotentiary who will take precedence over any other foreign representative accredited to the Emperor. T&amp;c Article II . /Services of British Advisers to the Enperor and his administration| a British Commissioner of Police| Police Officers etc., British Judges and Advocates to be lent to the Emperor at his request. Article III. The jurisdiction and administration now exercised by British Military Tribunals and authorities to terminate as soon as they can be replaced byftilthiopian civil administration. Vaid to the Emperor with certain attendant conditions. Article V. ■ Jurisdiction over foreigners to be exercised by Ethiopian Courts according to the draft Statute in the Annex. Any foreigner to have right of trial by the High Court with at least one British Judge sitting as a member of the Court. Article VI. The Emperor to enact trading with the enemy laws as advised by HJtf.G. Article VII . Custody of prisoners of war to be in the hands of the British Military authorities. Article VIII . H.M.G. to endeavour to secure the return of Ethiopians, (and artistic works etc.) now in Italian hands. Article IX. British Military authorities to conduct any military operations with full emergency powers granted by the Emperor• Political Seca^etary. For information. 6- Article X « The Emperor not to conduct external military operations against British military advice. Article XI . Rights of freedom of passage to be granted to duly registered British civil aircraft. Regular passenger, mail and freight air service by British Air Transport Organisations to be permitted to operate in Ethiopia. Foreign aircraft not to be permitted without H.M.G.'s concurrence. The Military Convention is not detailed in this minute as it is of more interest to the Military Department, who may wish to read it in full. Military Secretary. U '2/V/^■Fxt.1001/42. DRAFT LETTER. W.E.BeckettEsq., C.M.G, Foreign Office, S.W.l. t\ r , ,4* Qy*' llMAR !94? Will you please refer to your letter of 25th February 4^nnm l mibcL'uQ) fc ^~' on the subject of Hie draft Ethiopia and China Orders-in-Council? I enclose copies 'tfain-x. To Goverraient of India Eo.3789 datedof telegrams 2&amp;th Fobruary and No.3982 dated 4th March.) which we have sent to the Government of India, and write to confirm that if recitals referring to all the Dominions go into the Orders, we shall want the Government of India specifically mentioned, but not otherwise. futile wncer^Jy. (SgcL) R. Ptt L P &lt;v S-Yours sincerely. on~ 1 also enclose a copy of a letter which I have written to the Dominions Office about a second China Order, In this case the Dominions v/ill obviously have to be consulted. In case, however, you wish to r telegraph to the Government of India a resume of the ' fche second China Order, my letter to Kimber will give you the material. R.T. Peel, Esq., C.B.E., M.C., India Office. R8Co.POL.CEPT. ?5 FEB 942 i OFFICIIV/HKREA8 Hio Uajeoty The King ha© agreed to the termination or the jurlortiction which by treaty t grant, uaage, BUfferance or other lawful means, Hie Majesty had in Ethiopia: and VJHKIIBAS prowls ion is at present made for such jurisdiction by the Ethiopia Order in Council, 1934, and as regards appeals by the Eastern African Court of Appeal (Amendment) Order in Council, 1934: and WHKKKA8 it is therefore expedient to abrogate the said Ethiopia Order in Council and the said Eastern African Court of Appeal Order in Council, 1934: therefore Bis . aj^rty, tyf virtue and in f exercise of the powers in thio behalf by the i Foreign Jurisdiction Acts, 1890 and 1913, or otherwise in His Majesty vested, is pleased, by and with the advice of his Privy Council, to order, and it is hereby ordered, as follows:- 1* The Ethiopia Order in Council, 1934, and all Etiles and Hegulations made thereunder, the western African Court of Appeal (Amendment) Order in Council, 1934, and the application to Ethiopia of the Foreign Jurisdiction (Military Forces; Order in Council, 1927, and of the Foreign Jurisdiction (Probates) Order in Council, 1935, are hereby abrogated* 2. This Order may be cited as the Ethiopia (Termination of Jurisdiction) Order, 1942. And the Eight Honourable Anthony Eden and the Eight Honourable Lord ^oyne, two of His Majesty! Secretaries of State, are to give the neceasary directions herein.JONFIDENTIAL. [ J 865/66/1 ] Enclosure. cc ■ Cs) MEMORANDUM. I K NT 871 Poi.icy for Ethiopia. S12 THE fundamental of His Majesty’s Government’s policy for Ethiopia is that it shall be re-established as speedily as possible as a native State under its own ruler, involving His Majesty’s Government in a minimum of political responsibility and be as light a burden as possible on the British exchequer. During the war at least and in order to secure certain minimum military safeguards financial aid is to be given to the Emperor. This in turn will provide a means of keeping some hold on him whilst enabling him to set up and control his own administration with the help of a body of suitable British advisers. Our plan for future action must be regulated by our requirements, which can be conveniently divided into two parts: ( 1 ) transitory (duration of the war), and ( 2 ) long-term. f I.— Transitoi'y. 1. Control and organisation of sufficient armed forces for the Emperor to enable him to assert his authority for the good government of the country according to Ethiopian standards. This will he accomplished by a Military Mission and a British Commissioner of Police. [Article IT of Agreement and Article 2 of Convention.] 2. Control and use of the railway until all Italians and our own troops have been evacuated. This is to be obtained by the continuance of the British military administration of it. [Article 9 of Convention.] 8 . Use of ihe main communications. [Article 9 of Convention.] 4. Control and use of the high power wireless station at Addis Ababa. [Article 9 (e) of Convention.] * 5. Assurance that the Emperor will not fail in his declarations to work hand in hand with His Majesty’s Government. The sanction of the purse should ensure this, for the Emperor cannot run his government without financial aid and he knows that the first victim of a serious revolt would be himself. 6 . In order that any pressure His Majesty’s Government may wish to bring to bear in respect of our wartime needs shall not be offset by obdurate subordinate officials, it is desirable that His Majesty’s Minister shall at all times have direct access to the Emperor without the — — ^ vxauiv vaa jccaijciaj W V t_&gt;l. furnish the requisite shipping (they have agreed to do this), there should he no insuperable difficulty. This is desirable on political grounds. But it may be necessary to allow some discrimination in the case of technicians of the fitter and machinist grades, where they are doing work in connexion with our w r ar effort. II— Tjong-term. I. The long-term interests of His Majesty’s Government in Ethiopia were exhaustively- examined and fully set out in the report of the Interdepartmental Committee (Maffey Committee') on British interests in Ethiopia of June 1935 [J 2381/17/1]. Thev were and, in'essence, still are : — (i) an independent Ethiopia, on Imperial Defence grounds; (ii) control of the water issuing from Lake Tsana by a barrage under the direction of the Sudan Government: 11632a(iii) treaty arrangements, safeguarding the tributaries of the Blue and White Niles - (iv) the British-protected tribes in Somaliland to enjoy unimpeded use of their habitual grazing grounds across the frontier into Ethiopian territory; (v) minor frontier adjustments on the borders of British Somaliland, Kenya, and the Sudan for better administration; (vi) open door for trading; (vii) (additional to the recommendations of the Maffey Committee), the question of the disposal after the war of the Italian colonies of Eritrea and Somalia cannot properly be answered without most careful consideration of the repercussions such disposal would have on the position of Ethiopia itself and of its security from external aggression. Broadly, it would seem reasonable to assume that a return to Italian administration would lead inevitably to a revival of intrigues for the reconquest of Ethiopia at some near or distant date. Suggestions on the action needed to obtain the ends desired by His Majesty’s Government I.— Transitory. , 1- ( a ) ^ Military Mission is provided to organise and train the Emperor’s new army. The Convention lays down that this Mission shall be under the orders of the General Officer Com- manding-in-Chief, East Africa, until the British military obligations end. Thereafter His Majesty s Government will endeavour to provide officers to continue the work, but as a Mission to the Lin per or, who would have to p&amp;y for it. The directions given to the Commander-in-Chief, East Africa, are to the effect that the Emperor s forces shall be built up only to a state which the Ethiopians themselves can keen up attei British financial aid ceases. It also appears desirable that these forces shall not be armed in such a manner as might render thorn a standing menace to the defence units which he surrounding British territories desire to maintain after the war. It has been arranged that the Emperor s forces shall, so far as possible, be equipped only from captured Italian booty. kIi V 6 Agr “ pl '? vides that there ^a 11 be British police officials.' Their fw, Zh u t W? up - an e , ffic,er *P ollce L force- Jt is ’ however, desirable that the number of them shall be kept low in order to limit the friction to which foreign control of Ethiopians will Gewoft^mmeffi-. ^ ^ be ^ —full? selected from th? ^ntt station a^iddfslhl 6 , 6 ^! 8 !; niiUt .ahy.necessities in Ethiopia subsist, the railway and wireless station at Addis Ababa will be maintained by the British military authorities But when the thf rconoTlfEXomo l? 0UDtry ’ an 6 ° f the contin ^n Ce of these services, useful to the economy of Ethiopia, will arise. The Ministry of Information are now examining the Question ^t^^tr^uS 0 r rr eed8 f f he W , ireless Th e difficult,ii of personal of highly skilled men rennire l 6 ’' ° l e&lt;&gt; h nica P eo P^ e may be attracted and the number iL % ■ d men required is small. In the matter of material, on the other hand the ffifficulty will probably be very great indeed. Engines and rolling-stock are of French or Italian ThT' ivi the 8 P eclflcatlons ar © to continental measurements The equipment for the Addis Ababa high power wireless station is nil Tfolior, u i ’ i e e&lt; l ul P meni 101 T ' ne services will be Mmost impossible to obtain and^lta^ ^ re P lacement9 for both these place. It might be a good thine if +he Vr g0 , d 1 ( . ea of wear mu8t have already taken engineer at an early date to advife him ab^/the future o^th^T 8 -’' ^ t a , k ? f 8 qua , lified run bv the Army There mav Ho ■ i r , re these services whilst they are being sight must not be lost of the fact that Indian engineer. At the same time clear rights, against which it is believed that the pr ° pe r t V ° f ' French company with problem and le should be wise 14 iS a ^ right lines. Nevertheless, we shairexiwcf'thV’Vd^ to l&lt;ee P the Emperor on the we may avoid having to use it For fh?s reolt V” f mpl ^ their skill and tact so that prospective Advisers with the object of selecting thns'^ ' !,nlst , er , W|11 doubtless be careful to vet ooject ot selecting those men who have shown a faculty for gettingon with the Ethiopians. Frank discussions with the Emperor would probably disclose the names of 'men who might start off in the confidence of the Emperor himself. In the matter of the proper employment of the funds with which we shall be financing the Emperor, it is desirable that the financial adviser shall have a rather special position. This must be provided for in the contract between the Emperor and the financial adviser. No especial difficulty need be anticipated here, for in the past the Emperor’s financial adviser had the position of principal adviser. Admittedly he was a man (an American) of remarkable talents and great adaptability. # In order that there shall be no suspicion that our gift, by subvention to the Emperor is a Greek gift, it is generally conceded that we should inform the Emperor at the outset that His Majesty’s Government will make no demand for repayment of the costs of the campaign or of the subsidy. The Minister should give the Emperor a letter to this effect wdoen he presents his credentials. 4 . The Emperor’s authority must be the fulcrum on which our financial lever, if it has to be used, must operate. In order that it shall not be weakened we must be careful not to allow him to interpose a “ Government ” to whom we should have to address ourselves. Our special position justifies us on insisting that His Majesty’s Representative shall deal only and directly w-ith the Emperor. 5. A good deal of bad b lood ,.uji{&gt;aa rs -aliv ^rl y to have been m ade (possibly this was inevitable i in view of the original basis of our relations with the~T?thTopians). It is therefore most desirable • that very strict instructions shall be issued to all British military and civilian officials and to soldiers, British and colonial, enjoinng them not to quarrel with or slight the native inhabitants. Intercourse with the Italians should be restricted to official contacts. There is much to fear I from Italian intrigue to poison Ethiopian minds against Great Britain; official Italian wireless I propaganda has been directed on these lines. II.— Long-term. (a) As soon as possible after the Agreement covering the transitory period has begun to operate and before the sweetness of His Majesty’s Government’s financial aid has worn off, discussions should begin on the subject of the control of the Lake Tsana w'aters. The question of certain frontier adjustments desired by the Governments of Kenya, Sudan, and British Somaliland may be more conveniently left until the peace settlement, when the problem of the frontier of Ethiopia as a whole will call for a solution. In the meantime, so far as the Ogaden is concerned, we should work for the maintenance of the present position. Idle question of the control of the Tsana waters was, before the Italian occupation, a subject for lengthy negotiation. In 1984, the Ethiopians demanded, as a price for the right to build a dam, the construction of a road from Addis Ababa to the Lake. 1 he cost of this was estimated at about £8(X),(X)0; about the same as for the construction of the dam. This road has since been built by the Italians. The Emperor may thus seek other compensation and may revert to the suggestion, which was never taken up, that the Sudan should pay a water rental. The Sudan would probably reject this on the ground' that they would b£ undertaking a liability in perpetuo and that such a payment for river water is unknown in international custom. A possible line of approach might be that the Emperor should consider the grant of facilities on Lake Tsana as a reward to us for restoring him to his throne. It must be borne in mind, although His Majesty’s Government will conduct the negotiations, that both the Sudan and Egypt must be brought in on a consultative basis. (b) If when the time comes to take up frontier discussions it should prove possible to adjust the frontier between Ethiopia and British Somaliland in such a manner as to include in British territory the habitual grazing grounds of the British-protected Somalis, then the seasonal migrations would no longer be the source of perennial disputes that they have hitherto been. (c) Ex-Italian colonies : it has been suggested that these colonial territories might be returned to Italy at the conclusion of peace. The effect of such a restitution would certainly lead to a revival of Italian designs in East Africa, which the Fascist party energised but did not originate. This would be most objectionable.- *-r. If these Italian colonies are not to revert to Italian rule, what should happen to thein. On the one hand, the declarations of His Majesty’s Government, the Atlantic C harter, and the fact that the territories in question have no encouraging economic future, rule out a prolongation beyond the war of our administration. On the other hand,, there is a good deal of ethnical confusion which would render the establishment of local native rule difficu . Nevertheless, there are some elements of cohesion which might be profitably developed. Among suggestions for the future regulation of our policy may be mentioned the following. (i) carry the Sudan frontier down into Eritrea in order to refute die Beni Amr now in Eritrea with their brothers in the Sudan. (There is a difficulty here inasmuch as the Eritrean Beni Amr have been converted to a considerable extent to Christianity, whereas those in the Sudan have kept to Islam) ; (ii) recreate the old kingdom of Tigre by attaching Eritrean Tigre to Ethiopian Pigre : this would bring Tigre up to the Beni Amr borders and make a tidy frontier with the Sudan, but would leave the Danakil area of southern Eritrea: this could be dealt with ^ on the lines proposed below for the Somali tribes; / &gt; (iii) set up minor sheikhdoms, or Sultanates, on the lines of the Trucial States in southern Arabia for the Danakil and Somali tribes in Italian Somaliland. The Danakil (or Dankali) have maintained fair solidarity in two federations (Asaeimara and Adeemara) and should present no great difficulty in the selection of two native overlords. Alternatively they might be incorporated into the Sultanate of Aussa as a part of the Ethiopian Empire. This, incidentally, would bring the port of Assab into Ethiopia. The Somalis, on the other hand, are split up into rival family groups which would probably render geographical division awkward because of the mingling which has taken place. The Sudan may need some persuasion to undertake the administration of northern Eritrea (Beni Amr) for the region is unproductive and arid for the most part, but the unification of the Beni Amr would, perhaps, present countervailing advantages. It is too early to formulate plans for the creation of Dankali and Somali sheikhdoms, but if the principle involved were to be approved, appropriate steps could be taken to create the right atmosphere and the political structures at an early stage in order that the changes at the peace settlement would follow r as a natural sequence of administrative arrangements. III .—Jurisdiction over foreigners. Although this matter is not one that has been considered as a direct British interest, it will seek to resuscitate the Klobokowski Treaty, which formed the basis of the form of extra territorial jurisdiction for foreigners up to the Italian occupation. By the Agreement now to be signed judicial safeguards are provided for the foreigner by a reform of Ethiopian legislation under the guidance of a British judicial adviser and by the option open to the foreigner to have his case heard in the High Court, on the bench of which at least one British judge will sit. Experience alone will show how this system works in practice, but it cannot be assumed that a British judge can be maintained indefinitely. It is possible that some uncertainty regarding the country, and, if this is so, the uncertainty will be beneficial. Foreign Office, January 20, 1942.Sir, ^ *** ^ ^ V* I transmit to you herewith copies of a' White Paper (Crnd. 6334) reproducing the texts of the Agreement and Military Convention signed on behalf of His Majesty’s Government in the United Kingdom and by the Emperor of Ethiopia on the 31st January. I also enclose a copy of a Departmental Memorandum setting out the lines which His Majesty’s Government in the United Kingdom propose to follow in respect of their policy in Ethiopia. It is intended that this memorandum shall serve as a guide in our future relations with that country in matters directly touching British interests. I need not emphasize that this document is confidential, but it is hoped that it may be of use to you as providing a background for answers to questions put to you on the subject, which has aroused some interest abroad. I am, with great truth and regard, Sir, Your obedient Servant, ANTHONY EDEN. His Majesty’s Representative at (03/1942) 11632 23409—7Agreement and Military Convention between the United Kingdom and Ethiopia Addis Ababa, January 31 , 1942 Presented by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs to Parliament by Command of His Majesty LONDON PRINTED AND PUBLISHED BY HIS MAJESTY'S STATIONERY OFFICE To be purchased directly from H.M. STATIONERY OFFICE at the following addresses: York House, Kingsway, London, W.C.2; 120 George Street, Edinburgh 2; 39—41 King Street, Manchester 2; 1 St. Andrew’s Crescent, Cardiff; 80 Chichester Street, Belfast; or through any bookseller 1942 Price 3^. net |4jK m : t u &gt;4ENT AND MILITARY CONVENTION r EEN THE UNITED KINGDOM AND ETHIOPIA. Addis Ababa, January 31, 1942. BETWEEN HIS MAJESTY’S GOVERNMENT IN THE KINGDOM AND THE EMPEROR OF ETHIOPIA. Majesty the Emperor of Ethiopia, Conquering Lion of the Elect of God (hereinafter referred to as His Majesty the XV 7t J P ut; on record His gratitude and that of His people for r' g and generous aid He has received from the Forces of His IIIUJL.UT I'TTe King of Great Britain, Ireland and the British Dominions beyond the Seas, Emperor of India (hereinafter referred to as His Majesty The King), which has enabled Him and His people to recover their national territory; and Whereas His Majesty the Emperor, true to His coronation pledges not to surrender His sovereignty or the independence of His people, but conscious of the needs of His country, has intimated to the Government of the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland (hereinafter referred to as the Government of the United Kingdom) that He is eager to receive advice and financial assistance in the difficult task of recon struction and reform; and Whereas the Government of the United Kingdom recognise that Ethiopia 'ij mTL n an&lt; ^ i n&lt; l e pendent State and His Majesty the Emperor, Hailb Sellassie I, is its lawful Ruler, and, the reconquest of Ethiopia being now complete, w ish to help His Majesty the Emperor to re-establish His Tovernment and to assist in providing for the immediate needs of the Nov', therefore, His Majesty the Emperor of Ethiopia in person, and Major-General Sir Philip Euen Mitchell, Knight Commander of the Most is inguished Order of Saint Michael and Saint George, upon whom has been conferred the decoration of the Military Cross, Chief o Uica Officer, on the Stafr of the General Officer Commanding-in- ne , ast Africa, being duly authorised for this purpose by the Government of the United Kingdom, Have agreed as follows : — Article I. accredited to His Imperial Majesty.k AGREEMENT AND MILITARY CONVENTION BETWEEN THE UNITED KINGDOM AND ETHIOPIA. Addis Ababa, Januanj 81, 1942. AGREEMENT BETWEEN HIS MAJESTY’S GOVERNMENT IN THE UNITED KINGDOM AND THE EMPEROR OF ETHIOPIA. Whereas His Majesty the Emperor of Ethiopia, Conquering Lion of the Tribe of Judah, Elect of God (hereinafter referred to as His Majesty the Emperor), wishes to put on record His gratitude and that of His people for the overwhelming and generous aid He has received from the Forces of His Majesty The King of Great Britain, Ireland and the British Dominions beyond the Seas, Emperor of India (hereinafter referred to as His Majesty The King), which has enabled Him and His people to recover their national territory; and vvnereas ms majesty tire Hmperor, true to His coronation pledges not to surrender His sovereignty or the independence of His people, but conscious of the needs of His country, has intimated to the Government of ie united Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland (hereinafter referred to as the Government of the United Kingdom) that He is ea^er to receive advice and financial assistance in the difficult task of recon struction and reform; and Whereas the Government of the United Kingdom recognise that Ethiopia u T and .. mde P® n f enfc State and Majesty the Emperor, ail^ Sellassie I, is its lawful Ruler, and, the reconquest of Ethiopia being - mv complete, wish to help His Majesty the Emperor to re-establish His lount ™ 1 ” 611 and t0 aSS ‘ St in P rovidin g for th€ immediate needs of the Now, therefore, His Majesty the Emperor of Ethiopia in person, and Maj^r General Sii I hilip Euen Mitchell, Knight Commander of the Most is m^uis lec ider of Saint Michael and Saint George, upon whom PnhV i ni£ 0nferred , the &gt; decoi,ati °n of the Military Cross, Chief r) - /'U c {I’. ou * ie . Staff of the General Officer Commanding-in- GnlJ™ ^ A /'f a ’ T ^ eing dul y authorised for this purpose by the Government of the United Kingdom, Have agreed as follows : Article I. re-established ami ns between the United Kingdom and Ethiopia shall be accredited to HL vr !? 0 ’, lct ® d through a British Minister Plenipotentiary potentiarv anorprlif rl j eS tb^ blmporor and an Ethiopian Minister Pleni- Lon t 't H ‘ S * Ma l e8ty T,le Ki ' 8 - be appointed as the Emperor agrees thal f °T 0 I this A greenient. His Majesty The Kins shall f!L 1 1 a Dl P lo matic Representative of His Majesty accredited ^HisImpeSl ^ ^Article II. (a) His Majesty the Emperor having requested the Government of the United Kingdom to assist him in obtaining the services of British subjects (i) as advisers to himself and his administration; (ii) as Commissioner of Police, Police officers and inspectors; and (hi) as judges and magistrates, the Government of the United Kingdom will use their best endeavours to assist His Majesty the Emperor in this matter. The number of such British subjects, their salaries, privileges, duties and powers, and the appointments they are to fill, shall be the subject of separate agreements between the Contracting Parties. (b) Plis Majesty the Emperor agrees not to appoint advisers additional to those referred to in paragraph (a) above except after consultation with the Government of the United Kingdom. Article III. Subject to the provisions of the Military Convention concluded this day, and of Article VII of this Agreement, the jurisdiction and administration exercised by British military tribunals and authorities shall terminate as soon as they can be replaced by effective Ethiopian civilian administration and jurisdiction, which His Majesty the Emperor will set up as soon as possible. Nevertheless, British military tribunals shall finish any cases then pending before them. The Ethiopian authorities will recognise and, where necessary, enforce decisions previously given by British military tribunals. Article IV. (a) His Majesty the Emperor, having intimated to the Government of the United Kingdom that he will require financial aid in order to re-establish his administration, the Government of the United Kingdom will grant to His Majesty the sum of Pounds Sterling one million five hundred thousand during the first year and Pounds Sterling one million during the second year of the currency of this Agreement. If this Agreement remains in force for a third year, the Government of the United Kingdom agree to pay to His Majesty the Emperor the sum of Pounds Sterling five hundred thousand in respect of such third year, and if for a fourth year, then the sum of Pounds Sterling two hundred and fifty thousand shall be paid in respect of that year. Payments will be made in quarterly instalments in advance. (b) His Majesty the Emperor agrees for his part that this grant shall absolve the Government of the United Kingdom from any payments in respect of the use of immovable property of the Ethiopian State which may be required by the British forces in Ethiopia during the war. (c) His Majesty the Emperor agrees that there shall be the closest co-operation between the Ethiopian authorities and his British Advisers, to be appointed in accordance with Article II (a), regarding public expenditure. (d) In order to facilitate the absorption into Ethiopian economy of the funds to be provided under paragraph (a) above, and to promote the early resumption of trade between Ethiopia and the surrounding territories, His Majesty the Emperor agrees that in all matters relating to currency in Ethiopia the Government of the United Kingdom shall be consulted and that arrangements concerning it shall be made only with the concurrence of that Government. Article V.r 4 ? which His Majesty the Emperor will promulgate forthwith and will main^ tain in force during the continuance of this Agreement, except in so far as it may require amendment in any manner agreed upon by the parties to this Agreement. (b) Any foreigner who is a party to any proceedings, civil or criminal, within the jurisdiction of a Regional, Communal or Provincial Court, may elect to have the case transferred without additional fee or charge to the High Court for trial. Provisions to this effect shall be included in the Rules of Court. (c) In the hearing by the High Court of any matter to which a foreigner is a party at least one of the British Judges mentioned in Article II (a) shall sit as a member of the Court. (d) His Majesty the Emperor agrees to direct that foreigners shall be incarcerated only in prisons approved for the purpose by the Commissioner of Police appointed in accordance with Article II (a). Article VI. (а) His Majesty the Emperor agrees to enact laws against trading with the enemy in terms proposed to him by the Government of the United Kingdom. ( б ) His Majesty the Emperor accepts full responsibility for seeing that private enemy property is dealt with in accordance with international law. His Majesty agrees to consult with the British Diplomatic Representative as to the measures to be taken to this end. Article VII. His Majesty the Emperor agrees— (a) That all prisoners of war shall be handed over to the custody of the British Military Authorities, who will evacuate them from Ethiopia as soon as possible, and (b) That he will enact such legislation as may be required to enable the General Officer Commanding-in-Chief the British forces in East Africa and officers acting under his authority to exercise such temporary local powers as may be necessary for the administra tion, control and evacuation of Italian civilians in Ethiopia. r Article VIII. The Government of the United Kingdom will use their best endeavours— (a) To secure the return of Ethiopians in Italian hands, and 1 b) To secure the return of artistic works, religious property and the like removed to Italy and belonging to His Majesty the Emperor, the Ethiopian State, or local or religious bodies. Article IX. ^ In areas in which the General Officer Commanding-in-Chief the British forces in East Africa may find it necessary to conduct military operations against the common enemy in future, His Majesty the Emperor will, at the request of the said General Officer Commanding-in-Chief, declare a state of emergency and will confer on the General Officer Commanding-in-Chief the powers resulting from such declaration. Any legislation necessary to secure these powers will be promulgated by His Majesty the Emperor. The Ethiopian Government and local authorities will give such aid and con currence to the General Officer Commanding-in-Chief as may be needed.' Articlk X. His Majesty the Emperor agrees not to conduct any external military operation which, in the opinion of the General Officer Commanding-in-Chief the British forces in East Africa is contrary to the joint interests of Ethiopia and the United Kingdom. Article XI. (a) His Majesty the Emperor will accord freedom of passage to, in and over Ethiopia to duly registered British civil aircraft, provided that such regulations governing air navigation as may be in force in Ethiopia are observed. (b) His Majesty the Emperor will permit a British Air Transport organisation or organisations, to be designated by the Government of the United Kingdom, to operate regular Air Services to, in and over Ethiopia for the carriage of passengers, mails and freight. For this purpose the said organisations shall he permitted to use such aerodromes, ground equipment and facilities as are available, and to provide such other aerodromes, ground equipment and facilities as may be necessary. (c) His Majesty the Emperor will not permit foreign aircraft other than I British to fly to, in or over Ethiopia without the concurrence of the Govern-1 ment of the United Kingdom. Article XII. The present Agreement shall enter in force as from this day’s date. It shall remain in force until replaced by a Treaty for which His Majesty the Emperor may wish to make proposals. If it is not so replaced within two years from this date, it may thereafter be terminated at any time by either Party giving three months’ notice to the other to this effect. In witness whereof the undersigned have signed the present Agreement and affixed thereto their seals. Done this thirty-first day of January 1942 in the English and Amharic languages, both of which shall be equally authoritative except in case of doubt, when the English text shall prevail. (L.S.l HAILE SELLASSIE I. (L-S.) P. E. MITCHELL. ANNEX. Draft Administration of Justice Proclamation. Part I.— Preliminary. 1. This Proclamation may be cited as the Administration of Justice Proclamation. 2. The following Courts shall be established in Our Empire and shall be constituted in the manner hereinafter described and shall exercise the powers conferred on them by this Proclamation over all persons in Ethiopia: — (a) The Supreme Imperial Court. (b) The High Court (•e) The Provincial Courts. (d) Regional and Communal Courts. - i J6 Part II.— The Supreme Imperial Court. 1 3 . The Supreme Imperial Court shall comprise the Afa Negus as President, together with two judges of the High Court, who shall be nominated by the President of the High Court for the hearing of any appeal from the High Court. No judge shall be nominated by the President of the High Court to hear any appeal in any case upon which he adjudicated as a member of the High Court. When in any matter the members of the Supreme Imperial Court are not unanimous, the opinion of the majority shall prevail. Part III.— The High Court. 4. The High Court of Ethiopia shall comprise such number of judges as We may from time to time think necessary, of whom one shall be designated the President. The High Court shall contain such number of judges of British nationality as We shall consider to be desirable. 5 . No person shall be appointed by Us to the office of Judge of Our High Court unless he is a regularly qualified legal practitioner or is certified to Us by by Our Minister of Justice to be qualified for such office by reason of long judicial experience or sound knowledge of law. 6 . We may also appoint from time to time fit persons as additional judges of the High Court for the trial of particular cases or for a specified period or while holding any specified office. 7 . The High Court shall have full criminal and civil jurisdiction in Ethiopia according to law. 8 . The High Court shall be deemed to be fully constituted for the hearing of any matter when it comprises three judges, and where in any matter the members of the Court are not unanimous, the opinion of the majority shall prevail. 9. The High Court may sit at any place within Our Empire as may be convenient for the despatch of business. 10. An appeal shall lie to the Supreme Imperial Court from any decision of the High Court when acting as a court of first instance, in the manner laid down in Rules of Court. 11 . No sentence of death shall be carried into execution unless confirmed by Us. Part IV.— Provincial Courts. 12 . In each of the Provinces of Our Empire there shall be established a Provincial Court, which shall comprise such number of provincial judges appointed by Us as We may from time’to time think necessary. One judge of each Provincial Court shall be designated the President. 13. We may also appoint from time to time fit persons as additional provincial judges for the trial of particular cases or for a specified period or while holding any specified office. 14. A Provincial Court shall be deemed to be fully constituted for the hearing of any matter when it comprises three members and where in regard to any matter the members of the Court are not unanimous, the opinion of the majority shall prevail. 15. A Provincial Court may sit at any place within the Province for which it is constituted as may be convenient for the despatch of business.7 16. —^(1) The jurisdiction of a Provincial Court in its original jurisdiction shall be limited: — (a) In criminal matters to— (i) imprisonment not exceeding 5 years. (ii) fine not exceeding 2,000 M.T. dollars. (iii) corporal punishment not exceeding 20 lashes, and shall extend to any combination of the above punishments. (/}) In civil matters, to cases, the subject matter of which does not 0 exceed 2,000 M.T. dollars. (2) A Provincial Court shall have such jurisdiction to hear appeals from Courts established under Article 18 of the Proclamation as may be prescribed by the warrant of any such court and any decision of a Provincial Court on appeal shall be final. 17. An appeal shall lie from any Provincial Court as a Court of First Instance to the High Court in the manner laid down by Rules of Court and any decision of the High Court on such appeal shall be final. Part V.— Regional and Communal Courts. 18 Notwithstanding the jurisdiction of the High Court and the Provincial Courts it shall be lawful for Us to establish by warrant under Our hand other courts of criminal and civil jurisdiction which shall be subordinate to the Provincial Courts. Such warrant shall define the Constitution of the Court, the area within which the court exercises jurisdiction, the law to be administered and shall impose such limitations upon the jurisdiction and powers of the court as may appear necessary. Appeals shall lie from courts established under this article ^ to such court or courts as may be specified in the warrant establishing a Court. Part VI.—Assessors. 19. Any Court constituted under this Proclamation may, if it sees fit, sit with two or more suitable persons in the capacity of Assessors. Assessors shall be entitled to put any relevant question to any witness and, at the conclusion of the case, shall give their opinions on the facts in issue, but the Court shall not be bound by the opinions of the Assessors. Part VII.— Rules of Court. 20. Rules of Court may be made, with the approval of Our Minister of Justice, by the Afa Negus in respect of the Supreme Imperial Court and by the President of the High Court in respect of any other Courts established by this Proclamation for the purposes of— (a) Regulating the administration of the Court, and the institution, conduct and hearing of proceedings therein. (b) Regulating the admission, conduct and discipline of legal practitioners. (c) Regulating the selection and duties of assessors. (d) Regulating the committal of criminal cases from lower courts to higher courts. j +• (e) Regulating the imposition and recovery of fines, the award ot imprisonment in default of payment and the procedure relating to execution and attachment. (/) Prescribing forms. (g) Fixing fees. (h) Regulating the general administration of justice.8 Part VIII.— General. A 21. For the better examination of laws submitted to Us for enactment there is hereby established a Consultative Committee for legislation, which shall comprise Our Judicial Adviser, the President of the High Court, and three persons having recognised legal qualifications or being qualified bv reason of long judicial experience and sound knowledge of law to be especially appointed by Us. The duty of such Committee shall be to draft laws upon Our directions or to review the draft of any proposed law. No law shall be submitted to Us for enactment unless it is accompanied by it certificate signed by a majority of the members of the said Committee certifying that the law to which the certificate relates is not repugnant to natural justice and humanity and is a fit and proper law to be applied without discrimination to Ethiopians and foreigners alike. 22. When any law has been enacted by Us it shall be published in the Official Gazette of Ethiopia in the Amharic and English languages, and shall come into force from the date of publication in the Gazette or from any other date which may be specified in the law. 23. Nothing contained in this Proclamation shall prevent the hearing and settlement of minor disputes in any manner traditionally recognised bv Ethiopian law until such time as regular courts can be established for the hearing of such disputes by judges duly appointed by Us on the recommendation of Our Minister of Justice. 24. It is hereby declared that no court shall give effect to any existing law which is contrary to natural justice or humanity, or which makes any harsh or inequitable differentiation between Our subjects and foreigners.MILITARY CONVENTION BETWEEN HIS MAJESTY’S GOVERN MENT IN THE UNITED KINGDOM AND THE EMPEROR OF ETHIOPIA. Whereas His Majesty the Emperor of Ethiopia, Conquering Lion of the Tribe of Judah, Elect of God (hereinafter referred to as His Majesty the Emperor), and the Government of Great Britain and Northern Ireland (hereinafter referred to as the Government of the United Kingdom) desire to provide for certain matters relating to mutual assistance as Allies in the struggle against the common enemy, and have decided to conclude a Military Convention for this purpose. Now, therefore, His Majesty the Emperor of Ethiopia in person and Major-General Sir Philip Euen Mitchell, Knight Commander of the Most Distinguished Order of Saint Michael and Saint George, \ipon whom has been conferred the decoration of the Military Cross, Chief Political Officer, on the Staff of the General Officer Commanding-in- Chief, East Africa, being duly authorised for this purpose by the Government of the United Kingdom, Have agreed as follows: — Article 1. (a) In this Convention the expression “British Forces” includes: — (i) every person subject to the Naval Discipline Act, the Army Act or the Air Force Act of the United Kingdom, or the corresponding enactments of other parts of the dominions of ’ His Majesty The King of Great Britain, Ireland and the British Dominions beyond the Seas, Emperor of India (hereinafter referred to as His Majesty The King), wdio is stationed with, or attached to, the British Forces which are present in Ethiopia in accordance with the provisions of this Convention; (ii) every civilian official of British nationality accompanying or serving with the said forces in Ethiopia, or the Expeditionary Forces Institutes, who is either granted relative status as an officer, or holds a pass designating his civil official status, issued by the Appropriate British Authority as hereinafter defined, and is paid from the funds of any part of the dominions of His Majesty The King or the Expeditionary Forces Institutes; and (iii) wives and children under 21 years of age, of the persons mentioned in paragraphs (i) and (ii) above. (iv) members of any Allied Forces serving in Ethiopia under the British High Command. (b) The expression “ Appropriate British Authority ” means: — (i) in the case of members of the British Naval Forces, the Senior British Naval officer for the time being within Ethiopia, or if there be no British Naval officer within Ethiopia, a General or other officer for the time being commanding the British Troops in Ethiopia; (ii) in the case of members of the British Land Forces, a General or other officer for the time being commanding the British Troops in Ethiopia; (iii) in the case of members of the British Air Forces, an Air or other officer for the time being commanding the Royal Air Force in Ethiopia.0 10 (c) Any authority given to, or any act or thing to be done by, to or for, a any Appropriate British Authority, may be exercised by, or done by, to or™ for, any other person for the time being authorised in that behalf according to the custom of the particular service of His Majesty The King. (d) The expression “British Cantonment’’ means all the areas and places allocated to the British Forces, and includes any temporary camps and bivouacs established by the British Forces for their use, and also camps established for prisoners of war or for Italian civilians pending evacuation. Article 2. (a) The Government of the United Kingdom will provide, at their own cost, a Military Mission for the purpose of raising, organising and training, the Ethiopian Army. The duties and privileges of the Military Mission shall be the subject of instructions from the General Officer Commanding-in- Chief, the British Forces in East Africa, to the Head of the Military Mission, which shall be agreed upon between His Majesty the Emperor and the General Officer Commanding-in-Chief. (b) The Military Mission will be retained in Ethiopia until His Majesty the Emperor no longer requires its services, or until the British forces in Ethiopia mentioned in Article 6 below are withdrawn, whichever is the earlier. When the Government of the United Kingdom cease to provide the Military Mission at their own cost, they will use their best endeavours to assist His Majesty the Emperor to obtain suitable officers to take the place of any members of the original Mission who do not remain in Ethiopia. (c) The Ethiopian Army mentioned in paragraph (a) above shall be armed and equipped so far as possible from booty taken from the Italian forces in the course of the campaign in Ethiopia. Article 3. The areas specified in the Schedule attached hereto, and such other areas and places as may be agreed upon between the Parties either in addition to or in substitution for the said areas and places, shall remain under British military administration to the extent which, and so long as, the General Officer Commanding-in-Chief, the British Forces in EasC'Africa, in consultation with His Majesty the Emperor, considers necessary. Article 4. (a) The Government of the United Kingdom will maintain, and the General Officer Commanding-in-Chief, the British Forces in East Africa, will have under his command, such Police Force as in the opinion of the said General Officer Commanding-in-Chief, is necessary in respect of the areas specified in Article 3. (b) Having regard to the special circumstances existing in Addis Ababa and of the responsibilities undertaken by the Government of the United Kingdom in respect of Italian civilians, the Government of the United Kingdom will maintain, and the General Officer Commanding-in-Chief, the British Forces in East Africa, will command such Police Force as ! e considers necessary for the safety and good order of the town of Addis Ababa until such time as the Police Force to be raised by His Majesty the Emperor is able to assume these duties. His Majesty the Emperor wi enact such legislation as may be necessary to confer upon this 1 ohee Force the powers and status which it requires.)e done by, to or for, a ay, or done by, to orW that behalf according The King. s all the areas and ny temporary camps ' use, and also camps i pending evacuation. provide, at their own ^anising and training, Military Mission shall leer Commanding-in- lead of the Military rlajesty the Emperor Ethiopia until His or until the British withdrawn, whichever d Kingdom cease to y will use their best otain suitable officers Mission who do not i (a) above shall be iken from the Italian reto, and such other the Parties either in places, shall remain diich, and so long as, Forces in East 'Africa, aders necessary. maintain, and the rces in East Africa, a the opinion of the ry in respect of the iting in Addis Ababa ment of the United merit of the United tianding-in-Chief, the Police Force as he the town of Addis sed by His Majesty sty the Emperor will er upon this Police t (c) Until the British Forces are withdrawn from Ethiopia, the General Officer Commanding-in-Chief, the British Forces in East Africa, or the General Officer Commanding the British Forces in Ethiopia as his representative, shall have the right of direct access to His Majesty the Emperor, and shall take precedence immediately after the Diplomatic Representative of His Majesty The King. Article 5. His Majesty the Emperor agrees that the part of the territory of the Ogaden which was included in the former Italian Colonial Government of Somalia shall, during the currency of this Convention, remain under the British Military Administration of Somalia. Article 6. The Government of the United Kingdom shall have the right to keep such military forces in Ethiopia as they think necessary. The rights and immunities in Ethiopia of these forces and of the Military Mission referred to in Article 2 are as defined in this Convention. Article 7. Without prejudice to the fact that British cantonments are upon Ethiopian territory, the said cantonments shall be inviolable and shall be subject to the exclusive control and authority of the appropriate British Authority. Article 8. His Majesty the Emperor consents to the enjoyment by the British Forces of— (a) complete freedom of movement of personnel, vehicles, animals and materials between British cantonments, and generally such freedom of movement elsewhere as such forces enjoy in the United Kingdom; (b) the same rights as to camping, billeting and security as the rights which such Forces enjoy in the United Kingdom; (c) the right to generate light and power, and to search and bore for or collect water for use in British cantonments, and to transmit and distribute such light, power and water between the place of generation or collection and any British cantonment or between British cantonments by means of cables, pipes or in any other way whatsoever; (d) entry into and departure from Ethiopia of members of the British Forces at all times without let or hindrance, subject only to the production of a certificate showing membership of the British Forces in cases when such members do not arrive or leave by a service aircraft, service transport or as a formed body under command of an Officer, Warrant Officer, or Non-Commissioned Officer; (e) the use of roads, streams, lakes, waterways and other bodies of water for personnel, vehicles, animals, materials or waterborne craft on the service of His Majesty The King, without payment of any dues, tolls or charges whatsoever; (/) the same immunity regarding the official correspondence of the British Forces and their couriers as is enjoyed in international law by the Diplomatic Representatives of foreign States; (ff) the right to establish and carry on Army postal services for the handling and conveyance of all correspondence of the British Forces. — '12 Article 9. G * The General Officer Commanding-in-Chief, the British Forces in East Africa, may, for as long as he deems necessary: — (a) Continue to use and occupy without payment any immovable property formerly belonging to the Italian State which he still requires. His Majesty the Emperor will also make available to the Government of' the United Kingdom any other such property which is needed by the British lorces. (b) Construct and maintain such additional buildings, defences, roads, railways, water supplies, wireless transmitting stations, telephones and telegraphs as he considers necessary for military purposes. (c) Continue the British military operation, management and main tenance of the Franco-Ethiopian Railway. (d) Continue the operation, management and maintenance of the high- power beam wireless transmitting station situated at Addis Ababa, together with the remote control stations, receiving terminal stations and all apparatus belonging thereto, and such existing telegraph and telephone installations as are required for the British Forces. (e) Continue to control and operate, whether by requisition, contract or other means, such privately-owned vehicles as he may need for military purposes and for the maintenance and evacuation of the Italian civilian population. Article 10. Subject to the provisions of Article 2 (c), booty taken by the British Forces in the course of the campaign in Ethiopia will be retained by them. Article 11. (a) In view of the fact that the speed and range of modern aircraft necessitate the use of wide areas, the Emperor will accord permission to the British Air Forces and the Air Forces of the Allies to fly in Ethiopia wherever they consider it necessary. (b) In view of the fact that the safety of flying is dependent upon provision of a large number of places where aircraft can alight, His Majesty the Emperor will secure the constant maintenance and availability of adequate landing grounds in Ethiopian territory, in addition to those subject to Article 3 of this Convention. His Majesty the Emperor will accede to any request from the Appropriate British Authority for the construction, at the cost of the Government of the United Kingdom, of such additional landing grounds or the extension of existing landing grounds as experience may show to be necessary. (c) His Majesty the Emperor will accord permission for the British Air Forces and the Air Forces of the Allies to use the said landing grounds, and, in case of urgency, will, at the request of the Appropriate British Authority, cause the Appropriate Ethiopian Authority to undertake such w r ork at the cost of the Government of the United Kingdom, as may be necessary for the safety or repair of aircraft, or will agree to such work being carried out by the General Officer Commanding-in-Chief, the British Forces in East Africa. (d) His Majesty the Emperor will give all necessary facilities for the passage of the personnel of the British Forces, aircraft and stores to and from the said landing grounds.* 13 * (e) His Majesty the Emperor freely offers every assistance to British or Allied aircraft in distress. Article 1*2. His Majesty the Emperor will provide for the continued operation of so much of the legislation enacted by the British Military Authorities as is considered bv the Government of the United Kingdom to be necessary tor the security 'of the British Forces in Ethiopia. His Majesty will also at the request of the Government of the United Kingdom enact and enforce such further legislation as may be required for the security of the said Forces. Article 13. His Majesty the Emperor will at the request of the General Officer Commanding-in-Chief, the British Forces in East Africa, requisition and hand over to the British Forces any private property outside the areas referred to in Article 3 which may be required by these forces, subject to the reasonable needs of Ethiopia. Article 14. (a) Save as hereinafter provided, no member of the British Forces referred to in paragraphs (a) (i) and (a) (iv) of Article 1 shall be subject to the criminal jurisdiction of the Courts of Ethiopia, and no member of the British Forces referred to in paragraphs (a) (ii) and (a) (hi) of Article 1 shall be subject to the criminal jurisdiction of the Courts of Ethiopia in respect of any criminal offence committed in any of the areas referred to in Article 3. ..... (b) No member of the British Forces shall be subject to the civil juns- diction of the Courts of Ethiopia in respect of any matter arising out of his official duties. If any civil proceeding is instituted against a member of the British Forces before any Ethiopian Court, notification of the proceedings shall forthwith be given to the Diplomatic Representative of His Majesty The King, and no further steps shall be taken in such proceedings until sixty days have elapsed from the date of notification. This period shall be extended for a further term of one hundred and twenty days if the Diplomatic Representative of His Majesty The King states in writing to the Court that it has not been possible to conclude the necessary investigations in the above time. (•c) A statement in writing to an Ethiopian Court by the Diplomatic Representative of His Majesty The King that the civil proceedings in respect of which notice has been given arise out of the official duties of a member of the British Forces shall be taken as conclusive evidence by the Court of that fact. (d) No member of the British Forces shall be committed to prison m default of satisfaction of any judgment or order of any Ethiopian Court or tribunal, until the sanction in writing of the Appropriate British Authority has been obtained. Article 15. Any claims in respect of reparation for damage or injury caused or alleged to have been caused, by any person or persons forming part of the British Forces, in any matter arising out of his or their official duties, shall be referred in the hirst instance to the Appropriate British Authority. Any difference of opinion shall be referred to a Joint Claims Commission, to be set up in case of need by the Appropriate British and Ethiopian Authorities. Any claim in respect of which the Joint Claims Commission fails to reach agreement shall be settled by the parties to this Convention.Article 16. ( (а) The Appropriate British Authority will, on receipt of an application signed by the appropriate official of the Ethiopian Ministry of Justice, surrender any person not being a member of the British J 1 orces and who is within any British cantonment or reserved area, and against whom a warrant of arrest has been issued in respect of any offence triable by an Ethiopian Court. ( б ) Every application for the surrender of an offender under this Article shall be accompanied by a certified true copy of the warrant of arrest and by such information as is available regarding the identity and whereabouts of the person whose surrender is desired. Article 17. The appropriate Ethiopian Authority will take all possible steps— (a) to search for, apprehend and hand over, any member of the British Forces who is claimed as a deserter or absentee without leave, upon request made in writing by the Appropriate British Authority; . (b) to prosecute any person not being a member of the British Forces who is accused of an offence in relation to such Forces which, if committed in relation to the Ethiopian Army, would have rendered him liable to prosecution, if such an offence is not within the jurisdiction of any British Military Court; (•c) to detain and hand' over to the Appropriate British Authority any member of the British Forces in Ethiopia who is notified by the Appropriate British Authority as having committed an offence or who has come into conflict with the Ethiopian Authorities in any manner. Article 18. (a) Members of the British Forces shall be liable to arrest by the Ethiopian Authorities only in such circumstances as are specified in paragraphs (a) and (c) of Article 17. (b) When any member of the British Forces is arrested, the following procedure will be adopted: — (i) notification of the arrest, giving the name and other particulars of the person arrested, together with information as to the nature of the offence for which the said person was arrested and the evidence in support of the charge, will be sent forthwith to the Appropriate British Authority; (ii) the alleged offender will be handed over on demand to the Appropriate British Authority. (c) When it is alleged that a member of the British Forces has committed an offence for which he has not been arrested, particulars of such alleged offence, together with the statements of any witnesses, will be sent with all convenient speed to the Appropriate British Authority. (d) Where a member of the British Forces is charged with the com mission of an offence and evidence is available vchich appears to substantiate the charge, the Appropriate British Authority will cause such member to be tried for the offence by an appropriate tribunal of the British Forces, and will in due course arrange for the Appropriate Ethiopian Authority to be informed, through the Diplomatic Eepresentative of His Majesty The King, of the result of the trial. Where, however, the Appropriate British Authority considers that for any reason it is desirable for a member of the British Forces to be tried for a15 ^^criminal offence by an Ethiopian Court, he may give a certificate in writing to that effect, and thereupon such Court shall have jurisdiction, notwith standing the provisions of Article 14. Article 19. The British Forces shall be entitled to send an armed escort to any part of Ethiopia for the purpose of taking over and escorting to British canton ments or reserved areas any member of the British Forces arrested under the provisions of paragaph (a) or (c) of Article 17. Article 20. (a) The appropriate Ethiopian Authority shall, at the request in writing of the Appropriate British Authority, take all reasonable steps to secure the attendance of persons amenable to its jurisdiction as witnesses before any of the tribunals of the British Forces in Ethiopia convened and assembled by the Appropriate British Authority. (b) The Government of the United Kingdom will take all reasonable steps to secure the attendance of any member of the British Forces as a witness in any proceedings before any Ethiopian tribunal, upon application being made to the Appropriate British Authority signed by an authorised official of the Ministry of Justice or the President of the tribunal concerned. Article 21. (a) His Majesty the Emperor agrees that- where any person not being a member of the British Forces, who has been ordered to attend a tribunal of the British Forces under Article 20 (a), is accused of any of the following offences, such person will be prosecuted before the appropriate Ethiopian Court, that is to say: — (i) being duly summoned makes default in attending; or (ii) refuses to take oath or make a solemn declaration legally required to be taken or made; or (iii) refuses to produce any document in his power or control legally required to be produced by him; or (iv) refuses when a witness to answer any question to which the tribunal may legally require an answer; or (v) is guilty of contempt of the tribunal by using insulting or threatening language or by causing interruption or disturbance in the proceed ings of such tribunal; or (vi) when examined on oath or solemn declaration before the tribunal wilfully gives false evidence. (b) Similarly, the Government of the United Kingdom agrees that— (i) any member of the British Forces referred to in paragraphs (a) (i) and (a) (iv) of Article 1; and (ii) any member of the British Forces referred to in paragraphs (a) (ii) and (a) (iii) of Article 1 residing in any British cantonment or reserved area; who is ordered to attend an Ethiopian tribunal under Article 20 (b) and who commits any of the offences above specified, shall be prosecuted before the appropriate tribunal of the British Forces. Article 22. (a) Members of the British Forces who are owners by Ethiopian Law of real property in Ethiopia shall pay the same taxes, registration and transfer fees as do Ethiopian subjects, in respect of such property and its produce.16 (b) Members of the British Forces shall pay any taxes or registration fees for the time being in force for any privately-owned vehicles used on any public road in Ethiopia which are paid by Ethiopian subjects. (c) The British Forces, the Expeditionary Forces Institutes and all other official canteens of the British Forces shall pay at most favoured rates for all services rendered by departments of the Ethiopian (jovernment 01 any municipal or local authority. i * (d) Save as above provided, British cantonments or Reserved Areas, the British Forces and the individual members thereof shall be immune from all direct taxation, import and export duties and all registration fees or similar charges, unless there shall be an agreement between the Govern ment of the United Kingdom and His Majesty the Emperor to the contrary in regard to any particular tax or charge. (e) The Government of the United Kingdom shall have complete freedom to import, export or move within Ethiopia any vehicles, goods, stores or materials of any kind belonging to the Government of the United Kingdom or any Government of the dominions of His Majesty The King. (/) Where any vehicles, goods, stores or materials upon which import duty has been paid on entry into Ethiopia are purchased in Ethiopia in bulk at wholesale rates by the Government of the United Kingdom, or by any Government of the dominions of His Majesty The King or by the Expeditionary Forces Institutes or any recognised Military, Naval or Air Force mess, club or institute, a rebate of any import duty paid thereon shall be payable by the Emperor. Article 23. This Convention shall come into effect with the Agreement signed this day between the Government of the United Kingdom and His Majesty the Emperor, and shall, subject to any other agreement between the Parties, continue in force so long as the said Agreement continues in force. In witness whereof the undersigned have signed the present Agreement and affixed thereto their seals. Done this thirty-first day of January 1942, in the English and Amharic languages, both of which shall be equally authoritative except in cases of doubt, when the English text shall prevail. (L.S.) HAILE SELLASSIE I. (L.S.) P. E. MITCHELL. Schedule. 1 . A continuous belt of Ethiopian territory 25 miles wide contiguous to the frontier of French Somaliland running from the frontier of Eritrea to the Franco-Ethiopian Railway. Thence south-west along the railway to the bridge at Haraua. Thence south and south-east, excluding Gildessa, to the north-eastern extremity of the Garais Mountains and along the crest of the ridge of these mountains to their intersection with the frontier of the former Italian colony of Somalia. Thence along the frontier to its junction with British Somaliland. 2. All land within Ethiopia occupied by the Franco-Ethiopian Railway and its appurtenances.WO DISTRIBUTION. P. dZ. 7854 1938 The Bari of Perth. (Rome). 4th November, 1938. D. 7.05 p.nio 4th November, 1938. R. 9 9 30 a.m. 5th November, 1938. ?S* 3 5 Your despatch No.1555. Memorandum has been prepared for communication to Italian Government on lines indicated but I have some doubt as to substitutional words ’’before conviction” for words ’’prior to sentence being passed upon them”. Might not text now proposed be held to mean that our consular officers would have the right to visit in prison British subjects only if they were convinced that the latter were guilty and would therefore be convicted. Further does not the word ’’conviction'* imply an assumption of guilt before judgement. It appears to me that words ’’prior to sentence” omitting perhaps words ’’being passed upon them” would not te.chnipal.ly be open to such an interpretation and might therefore be preferable. I trust that you do not consider it essential that exchange of notes on this subject should take place simul taneously with signature of document bringing Anglo-Italian agreement into force (see third paragraph of your Despatch N o.475_ of March 28th). I doubt whether this is now possible if proposed time table is to be adhered to and it seems diflicult to press Italian Government over much since we are only now about to reply to observations sent me in a personal letter from Gount Ciano dated May 18th (see my Despatch No. 504 of May 25th.).im (J, 41^0/158/1). 7854 1938 ka rnmtmmmmmmmmmmmmmrnm ?:'0 DISTRlBUllUli» telegram to The harl of i J erth ? (Rome), foreign Office. November 10th, 1958., 12.20.p.m. No. 490. IMPORTANT. oOo Your telegram No . 695 [ Of November 4th: surrender of British extraterritorial rights in Ethiopia]. Instead of w r ords '’before conviction' 1 in Article 5 of the British draft heads of agreement, memorandum should include a request that the Consular Officers should be given the right to visit ''prisoners in prison who have not yet been convicted'. This would cover persons who have been imprisoned but whom it i not intended to bring to trial. whilst it is not essential that exchange of notes on this subject should take place simultaneously with signature of document bringing Anglo-Italian treaty into force, nevertheless you should forward your memorandum urgently to ilinistry of foreign Affairs and try to obtain some assurance before the above-mentioned exchange of notes takes place which will show that* Italian Government agree in general to substance of your memorandum even if points of detail remain to be settled later.NO DISTRIBUTION Decode and The Earl of Perth, (Rome). 14th November, 1938. D. 11.30 p.m. 14th November, 1938. R. 9.30 a.m. 15th November, 1938. No. 709. 0:0:0:0:0 (R Negins). Your telegram No. 490. Ministry of Foreign Affairs will send a note tomorrow accepting in principal the criteria indicated in my communica tion to them and memorandum enclosed therein which were based 7iTb3&gt; on your des P atch N o. 1555. The note will add that in negociations which will shortly begin it is understood that the two parties will be actuated by a spirit of friendly understanding. Full text to 'Which I have agreed will follow by telegram saving. (R ends). [? Gp.omtd. short time given them Ministry of Foreign Affairs proved most accommodating and helpful.COPY V. 7854 1938 (J 4255/150/1) . r\ m DIGTHIBUTloy. Code telegram to the Karl of Perth (Rone). Foreign Office, 17th November, 1938* 7.25 p*ra. No. 498 (R). Your telegram Ho* 709 (of November 14th: surrender of British extra-territorial jurisdiction in Kthiopia)• Please express, in whatever manner you think best, my appreciation of the most sccom odeting and helpful attitude shown by the Italian Ministry of Foreign Affaire in this matter.'■'COPY (J 4312/158/1) No.1034 (449/14/38) itish Embassy, Rome, 16th November, 1938. My Lord, With reference to my telegram No.693 of the 4th November, regarding the cessation of British consular jurisdiction in Ethiopia, I have the honour to transmit herewith a copy of my Note to the Ministry of Foreign Affairs of November 11th, together with a copy in translation of the note from the Ministry of Foreign Affairs, which was handed to a member of my staff on November 15th. I trust that you will find its text satisfactory. I have, etc., (Sgd) PERTH. The Right Honourable Viscount Halifax, K.G., G.C.S.I., G.C.I.E., etc., etc., etc., Foreign Office.COPY 449/10/38 r^\ Rome, 11th November, 1938, My dear Minister, Sir Noel Charles in a letter dated May 25th wrote to thank you for your letter to me of May 18th (217254/48) containing the views of the Italian G-overnment on the proposals of His Majesty^ Government in the United Kingdom for regulating the cessation of British Consular jurisdiction in Ethiopia, and informed you that these views were being submitted to the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs for his observations I have now received a despatch from the Secretary of State containing hie views on this question. Lord Halifax observes that the Italian Government would prefer to deal with most of the matters mentioned in the draft Heads of Agreement which I submitted to you on April 2nd, in the course of the negotiations envisaged in the Protocol of the 16th April, but that with a view to dealing with certain practical problems they would be willing to accept an agreement containing 'transitory provisions', suggestions for which are embodied in the counter-draft enclosed in your letter to me of May 15th. The Secretary of State remarks in the first place that it is clear that if the procedure suggested by the Italian Government were adopted, the effect wouldbe that the provisions of any agreement reached with regard to these matters would be reciprocal as opposed to unilateral. IThile anxious, so far as possible, to meet the wishes of the Italian Government in this matter, he does not consider that it would be possible in the circumstances for His MajeBty’s Government to agree to reduce the provisions of the proposed agreement to so large an extent as the Italian Government desire. He has, however, considered very carefully how far it is possible to meet the Italian point of view, and after consultation with the interested departments of His Majesty’s Government certain conclusions have been reached which are embodied in the attached memorandum. This memorandum, as you will observe, first considers articles 2, 3, 5 and 6 of the British draft agreement, and concludes, in this connexion, (a) that His Majesty’s Government have no objection to omitting Articles 3 and 6 of their draft, if the Italian Government wish; (b) that in return for an assurance from the Italian Government regarding the reciprocal right of consular officers to visit persons in prison and to receive letters from them His Majesty’s Government are willing to leave the subject dealt with in paragraph 5 for subsequent discussion; and (c) that, for the reasons explained in the memorandum they feel that provisions corresponding to Article 2 in the draft should be included. FinallyFinally, the memorandum considers in detail Article 1 of the British draft, and, for reasons which are explained, urges that the Italian Government should accept certain amendments in their counter draft which will Bring it more into line with the provisions contained in the Article in question. Believe me, etc., (Sgd) PERTHIn view of the fact that the British desiderata put forward in Article 3 have already been practically met under that clause of the ”Bon Voisinage' Agreement of the 16th April last, which stated that nationals of the other party should not be enrolled in native troops, bands or formations. His Majesty’s Government are prepared to meet Italian wishes and to omit this Article# Certain matters such as the use of the word 'nationals” in the 'Bon 'Voisinage' Agreement, as opposed to the words 'British 'subjects' and 'British protected persons' used in Article 3 of the draft Heads of Agreement, and the question of the provision of money and service in lieu of military service which figures in Article 3 but is not referred to in the 'Bon Voisinage' Agreement may require subsequent clarification. However, as the 'ensemble' of Article 3 corresponds closely to one of the standard commercial treaty articles. His Majesty’s Government consider that these matters can well be discussed during the proposed commercial negotiations and any doubtiul points be cleai ed up then. Article 6. His Majesty’s Government are willing to agree to thearticle 5. The fifth article of the British draft Heads of Agreement deals with the rights and privileges of consular officers and corresponds, to some extent, with Article 12 of the Anglo—Italian Commercial Treaty of the 15th oune, 1883, the extension of which to Italian Bast Africa, on conditions to he established, will, under the Anglo-Italian protocol of the 16th April last, form one of the subjects to be discussed between His Majesty's Government and the Italian Government after the instruments annexed to that protocol have taken effect# Subject, therefore, to the provisions of the following paragraph. His Majesty s Government raise no objection to this Question being left over to be dealt with on a reciprocal basis in the course of the negotiations contemplated in the protocol of the 16th April last. Special reference, however, is invited to the two concludingsentences of this same Article (bo#5 of the British ca-aft Heads of Agreement) which provide that British consular officers in Ethiopia shall have the right to visit British subjects or British protected persons who are in prison prior to sent ence being passed on themHis Majesty's Government attach importance to the desiderata put forward in these two sentences and could only consent, therefore, to the omission of Article 5 as a whole on condition that they receive an assurance from the Italian Government that the latter agree in principle that the provisions mentioned in the two sentences in Question shall be included in the instruments resulting from the future commercial negotiations in a reciprocal form. His Majesty's Government also wish to state that on considei ation /theythey now think it preferable that the words ’’prisoners in ’’prison who have not yet been convicted” should be substituted for the words ”in prison prior to sentence ’’being passed upon them”. Article 2. His Majesty’s Government feel that it is very desirable that in any agreement regarding the surrender of British extraterritorial rights in Ethiopia some provisions should be included on the lines of Article 2 of the British draft Heads of Agreement. The questions dealt with in this Article, which mostly concerns statut personnel , are not such as would ordinarily be dealt with in negotiations on commercial matters but are, in the opinion of His Majesty’s Government, such as they might reasonably request should be set aown or agreed to at the moment when, as the result of the termination of British extraterritorial jurisdiction in Ethiopia, British nationals in that country are transferred from the jurisdiction of His Majesty’s Courts to those of the territorial authorities. The Italian Government, therefore are urged to examine in detail the provisions of Article 2 of the British draft and to agree to include some provisions on those lines.PART II The Italian Counter Proposals* The counter proposals of the Italian Government affect chiefly the first article of the British draft Heads of Agreement which deals with the formal renunciation of British extra-territorial jurisdiction in Ethiopia with the treatment of pending cases and with judgments and decisions given by the British Consular Courts. The Article in the draft Heads of Agreement is of course intended to be read in conjunction with the draft note to be addressed by His Majesty’s Ambassador at Rome to the Italian Minister for Foreign Affairs, a copy of which was also handed to His Excellency, Count Ciano, in April. With regard to this matter, His Majesty’s Government would wish the Italian Government to know that when they drew up this draft they realised that the Italian Government might take the view that British consular jurisdiction in Ethiopia automatically terminated with the establishment of Italian sovereignty in that country and that as His Majesty’s Government were, in fact, ready to renounce any claim to continue it, they thought it unnecessary to examine such an Italian contention. The draft of the note from Lord Perth to Count Ciano was therefore carefully prepared so as to render it acceptable to the Italian Government and not to prejudice their point of view. On the other hand. His Majesty’s Government will not be able to accept the date of the 9th May, 1936, inserted in the first paragraph of the Italian draft, because although His Majesty’s Government are willing to renounce British extra-territorial jurisdiction in Ethiopia they cannot be expected to agree to such renunciation as from a date prior...prior to their recognition of Italian sovereignty over Ethiopia, still less to agree that any automatic cessation of British extra-territorial jurisdiction in that country took place prior to that date* In this connection His Majesty*s Government wish to explain that although British Consular Courts in Ethiopia have since the 9th May, 1936, actually been practically in suspense, formally from the point of view of His Majesty’s Government they remain in being. It is hoped in fact that the Italian Government will feel able to regard the point at issue as of small importance to them, since His Majesty’s Government are renouncing British extra-territorial jurisdiction in Ethiopia; and that they will accordingly agree that cases, if any, which at the date of the signature of the Agreement were pending in His Majesty’s Consular Courts in Ethiopia should be dealt with by those Courts. His Majesty’s Government also hope that the Italian Government will consent to the retention in the Agreement of sub-paragraph (a) of Article 1 of the British draft, by which His Majesty’s Government renounce all claim to the exercise in Ethiopia of extra-territorial jurisdiction, bis Majesty’s Government feel that this clause would facilitate their own position, while at the same time not being inconsistent with the Italian view of the situation. Apart from the question of date, the first paragraph of the Italian draft does not differ greatly from sub-paragraph (b) of the first article of the British draft, except for the last sentence of the Italian draft, and His Majesty’s Government are prepared in all the circumstances to agree to the last sentence of Article 1 of the Italian draft and to the consequent closure of the British Consular courts in Ethiopia on the 1st July, 1939, at the latest. T he...No* 238358/99. ROME, 15th November, 1938*XVII. Dear Ambassador, I refer to your letter of November 11th, No. 449/10/38, relative to the cessation of British consular jurisdiction in Italian East Africa. It has been immediately submitted to a general examination. I'o meet the desire expressed to me, I have no difficulty in informing you now that the Italian Government accept in principle the criteria indicated in the letter referred to above and in the enclosure thereto. In the negotiations to be undertaken in the near future, it is understood that the two parties will be actuated by a spirit of the most friendly understanding. (SIGNED) CIANO. Minister for Foreign Affairs.With, reference to the late Lord Stanley’s Confidential Circular telegram B. No.368 of the 4th October, I have the honour to transmit the accompanying copy of a despatch to His Majesty’s Ambassador at Rome regarding the surrenderor British extra-territorial jurisdiction in Ethiopia. I have, etc., ;$»gped) MALCOLM MacDOWrtlLS^No. 1555. (J 3322/158/1) FOREIGN OFFICE, S.Y/.l. 25th Oeto'ber, 1938 My Lord, I have had under consideration Sir Noel Charles*s despatch No. 504 (449/5/38), of the 25th May, containing the observations of the Italian Government on the proposals of His Majesty's Government in the United Kingdom for the surrender of British extraterritorial jurisdiction in Ethiopia^ 2+ From this despatch and its enclosures I observe that the Italian Government would prefer to deal with most of the matters mentioned in the draft Heads of Agreement in the course of the negotiations envisaged in the Protocol of the 16th April, but that with a view to dealing with certain practical problems they would be willing to accept an agreement containing ’’transitory provisions*', suggestions for which are embodied in the counter draft enclosed in the despatch under reference. 3^ It is clear that if the procedure suggested by the Italian Government v/ere• adopted, the effect would be that the provisions of any agreement reached with regard to these matters would be reciprocal as opposed to unilateral. While anxious, so far as possible, to meet the wishes of the Italian Government in this matter, I do not consider that it would be possible in the circumstances to reduce the provisions... His Excellency The Right Honourable The Earl of Perth, G.C.M.G., C.3., etc., ©ijC., etc., Rome.provisions of the proposed agreement to so large an extent as the Italian Government desire. I have* however, considered very carefully what concessions can reasonably be made to the Italian point of view and after consultation with the interested departments of His Majesty’s Government certain conclusions have been reached which are embodied in the enclosed memorandum. This memorandum indicates, as you will observe, (a) that Articles 3 and 6 may be omitted. (b) that in return for an assurance from the Italian Government regarding the reciprocal right of consular officers to visit persons in prison and to receive letters from them, the subject dealt with in paragraph 5 may be left for subsequent discussion; (c) that provisions corresponding to Article 2 in the draft Heads of Agreement should be included; (a) that the Italian Government should be urged to accept certain amendments in their counter draft which will bring it more into line with the provisions contained in Article 1 of the Heads of Agreement. I shall be glad if Your Lordship will now reply to Count Ciano's letter of the 18th May on the lines indicated in the memorandum. I am, with great truth and respect, My Lord, Your Excellency’s obedient Servant, (For the Secretary of State)'M $ MMMdM th&amp;t it in alwisniy the mietmai for foreign eoremlnr offieere In British coionlel epentefieiee to t&gt;« given the ftem trentnient ee the/ reeeive in the United Klegteeh In Xivtlft however the ftogwintMitt f Italian Ceneete ia restrieted to town® unier the Anglo«ItaXiaci convention of the XSth June. 1914# The faction of the treetaent of eoneuler offieere in t J ?e Domini one eeeXi mt epoeer to eriee ne the eoarareiel negotiations eavteegen vlXX only oov^r relations heteeen itaXlan East rifrlaa* on the ©ne hantlf end the United Kir^to» f India eat the colonial 3epe*de«»eiee 9 on the other# apeelal mention, here he eerte of the two eeneXedtag aontcmoee of thte mum Article (go 9 5 of the British ifeft Bee^fi of Agreeaeat) e*H#h provide that British consular otttmmm in ithioria * x all have the right to visit British etifcjsete or Britiah protect ©a. pereoris wo are in prison prior to sentence Being g&gt;a$*od on thea» In the flr«!t pl«tef-» it le m« thoeght preftrahls that the words ^tjefore eonviotion^ should Be substituted tor ths words ^Before eenteaee* and this HmmMM Be made el^ar to the Itnltm flaoernaenU In the second plaec* it sewas that no diffie«atr eeet Be entiolpnied so to the grant of reel greet tg in this natter of prison visits a^ ecaaenleetieae from per eons in prison* as it is thought By His gsjiest/’s aeeer was el to bs iaportant to ash# sure that tbs rmt forward in these two sente^ea »h uld : e aecuredi# Me Hajesst/** Covern^eT^t eould onl/ esnsent to the oateslcm of t* r e rest of Article © Urea their draft Head* of Agrssasot on. eoniitlett that the/ receive an sssursnee fJWi the rtalien Bevsrassist th«it the Isttor are premiered, to sgrev., forthwith In prlneipls that the rfuvtstesMi asntieMi in the two eentsneee in question shell Be insludsd in the instruments resulting froa the future ©aaawpciai negotlstlons in a reciprocal fora* e. /tHfem pr^tieuXigr in tvwmlly ttw? remain in It *K&gt;uX&lt;i i&gt;# rapreaantad to th« rtallmn owarnma it t?‘at tha point at ift&amp;ac mim^t hut ®t my great i^&gt;ortanoa t ? thm »tnm Hit aovor^iont ara ronou^ioiiig British t ra ter ri tor lai Jnria ilotion in Ethiopia aiii tho I tali an Qowrtwmnt ahoaU tharaforn i&gt;* aa^ac! to agrea that eaoaa 9 If «Hl4h at the date of the aignatnre of the AgraettMt were jpMUag in hie hajeaty* a c^nauiar CMNVta in Ethiopia ahould he dealt with W thou# coarta# 9* The Italian MtWTWMnat ehouid alee he a®:&lt;ed to eoneent to the retention in t e itgewa—nl of OTil pa»wgraph (a) of trtiele 1 of the Britlah draft» har whieh Hie wajesty*e oowertre^nt r®na&gt;ma® all claim to the eaerciee in xthiopia of extraterritorial ^wrie^ietion# It la felt that while not feeing inconel at ent with the Italian wiew of t?^e eitoat Ion* thia elettse would feel mate the poaitlon of Hie Majesty's Power went* Apart from t e t|aeation of date, t e fi rat paragraph of the Italian draft deee not differ greatly froa well'»era praph (a) of the ft rat article of the British draft* except for the taat eeateaee of the Italian draft# and Hie Wajeaty'e Government,who have eonaaited Hie Haje^ty'a Oonewl- General at Addle Afeaoa in the matter* are prepared in all the eirctJHsifctariee# to agree to the last eentonee of Article 1 of the Italian draft and to the eeaaequeat closure of the British coneular courts in thlopia on the let duly# 193G* at the latest* The Italian Oovernfnent may be eo informed* 10* rhe eeeonft article of the Italian draft hgrmmnt, though covering mm' t e nmm grownd ae that eovcred by eub- paragraph (e) of the first article of the British draft Heads•A Important, 1696, Your telegrarri No. 1828, Octot)er 18th, Surrender of British extraterritorial jurisdiction in Ethiopia. We have no comments.0SS&gt; The Under Secretary of State for the Horae Department presents his compliments to the Under Secretary of State, India Office and by direction of the Secretary of State transmits herewith a copy of a letter which has been addressed to the Foreign Office on the subject of the surrender of British extra-territorial Jurisdiction in Ethiopia (India Office reference P.Z. 4081/38). 590 cNCLOSURE IN AIR MAIL LEITHH No. ^ d m-IO-a* • FROM aeoftr-AftY, ’OUTIOAl -43 HOME OFFICE, WHITEHALL 8th October, 1938With reference to your letter of the 15th September (J3322/l58/l) on the subject of the proposed surrender of British extra-territorial jurisdiction in Ethiopia, I am directed by Secretary Sir Samuel Hoare to say that he concurs in the terms of the draft despatch and of the memorandum enclosed therewith which it is proposed to send to His Majesty's representative at Rome on this subject. A copy of this letter has been sent to the India Office, Dominions Office and Colonial Office. I am. Sir, Your obedient Servant,any further communication on this subject, pleas^'quote son by ndme, but/to— ^ \ No. X an address —not to any berson “ The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. i 933 airs presents his THE Under-Secretary of State compliments to ILa/Ow- (rj ^taM, j*/ , and, by direction of the Secretary of State,, transmits herewith cop &lt;00 of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, Q-d- , 193 ?. 1 Reference to previous correspondence : pj b'tfi l-d- h)tl~ A/o, 7332. 2 ./ , / 3 '« / /l /[Atp'.IS 1 *' Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. i&gt; C&amp;l0*Xall bifr-a'i dtl-b.r F 43/lgK. bH?, CUiGUL/XR TKLEORAK To the Oovei^nmants of Canada., Co;.iincn\ k ea11S &lt; jVusy ralia New Zealand, Union of South Africa and Kir© (fcy 'hag) (Bent 10.30 p.m. , 4th October, 192B.) Circular Bp No*368. Confidential. My telegram of the 14th April, 1937 Circular B. , No.38., Extra-territorial rights in Abyssinia. Draft Heads of Agreement in terras indicated in the telegram under reference were duly communicated to the Italian Government. In reply Italian Government have now stated that they consider that British consular jurisdiction in Abyssinia automatically terminated with the establishment of Italian sovereignty there, that is, as from 9th May, 1936. Ota this understanding they are willing to accept an Agreement containing ^transitory regulations' with a view to dealing with practical problems arising from the cessation of British consular jurisdiction. These regulations should provide only for the settlement of civil and commercial cases already pending before British Courts. For this purpose the Italian Government have submitted a dx^aft Agreement which is substantially as follows. Begins. Article 1 corresponds to sub-paragraph (b) of Article 1 of the United Kingdom draft, but confines the continued jurisdiction of British Consular Courts to such cases as were instituted before them prior to the 9th May, 1936, and provides that cases still pending before these Courts on the 1st July, 1959, shall be transferred to Italian jurisdiction 0 Article 2 corresponds to sub-paragraph (c) of Article 1 of the United Kingdom draft, but contains no provision corresponding to the second sentence of that sub-paragraph. Ends* The Italian Government would prefer that the matters covered by paragraphs 2, 3, 4 and 5 of the United Kingdom la - rKingdom draft should he dealt with in the negotiations envisaged in the two concluding paragraphs of the Protocol of the 16th ''“April, 1938« (Treaty Series Ho* 31 of 1938 P Cmd- 5726, enclosed in Circular despatch C«» No*.89 of the 26th Aprils) The effect would thus he that the provisions of any agreement reached, with regard to these matters would he reciprocal as opposed to unilateral» Although unwilling to reduce the provisions of the proposed agreement to the extent desired hy the Italian Ooveriment, His Majesty’s Government in the United Kiixgdom are prepared to male© certain concessions and are willing tc modify the original draft agreement on the following lines:- (a) Article 3 has already ‘been practically covered hy that clause of the 'Bon Voisinage' Agreement of 16th April which stated that nationals of the other party should not he enrolled in native troops, etc© The word ?, nationals ,i as opposed 6ho words 'British su'tojecta' and 'Bx*ltish protected persons' used in the United Kingdom draft, might conceivably he held to relate only to persons belonging to the territories in respect of which the Agreement was concluded by His Majesty s Government in the United Kingdom, i«Oo Kenya, Sudan and British Somalilando This matter, however* together with the question of the provision of money and services in lieu of military services which is not referred to in the Agreement of the 16th April, may be clarj-fied during the proposed commercial negotiations envisaged in the Protocol cf the 16th April. In the circumstances, therefore. Article 3 may be omitted from the proposed agreement. (b) Article 6 is of little intrinsic importance and may also be omitted. (c) Article 5 corresponds to some extent to Article 1 ■ the Anglo-Italian Commercial Treaty of 15th June? 3.883, the extension of which to apply between Italian East Africa on the cne hand and the United Kingdom, India and Colonial Dependencies etc. on the other, is to be discussed with tb*. ItalianItalian Government in accordance V7ith the Protocol of* 16th April. His Majesty's Government in the United Kingdom are therefore ^epared to leave the subject of Article 5 for subsequent discussion in return for an assurance that the provisions contained in the last two sentences shall be included in the instruments resulting from the future commercial negotiations in a reciprocal form. (d.) The Italian Government should be urged to agree to the inclusion in the Agreement of provisions corresponding to Article 2 of the United Kingdom draft. (e) The Italian Government should be asked to consent to the retention in the agreement of sub-paragraph (a) of Article 1 of the United Kingdom draft* They should be informed that His Majesty’s Government in the United Kingdom are unwilling to renounce extra-territorial jurisdiction as from the 9th May. 1936, and should be asked to agree that cases which were pending in British Consular Courts at the date of signature of the Agreement should be dealt with by these Courts. Apart from this question. His Majesty’s Government in the United Kingdom are prepared to accept Article 1 of the Italian draft. (f) Article 2 of the Italian draft may be accepted subject to the inclusion of the provision in the second sentence of sub-paragraph (c) of Article 1 of the United Kingdom draft* His Majesty’s Government in the United Kingdom propose to instruct His Majesty’s Charge d Affaires at Horae to reply to the Italian Government on the above lines*mm Fii ~E (foRY Communications on this subject should be addressed to— The Under-Secretary of State, Dominions Office, 6 S 5 5 j Subject :j P Downing Street, London, S.W.l, ^ and the following number quoted * Reference to previous correspondence : jtt f S'' Letter f the JJu 77T m iuifir Office of the 1 / ir,m &lt; in ifiri //. Transmitted by direction of the Secretary of State for \ / / V Dominion Affairs. A copy has also been sent to the t/o Dominions Office, Downing Street, 193 26 SEP 1958 (•13*6) Wt. 25174—3707 20,000 10/37 T.S. 695 -n i ism r~' r - ^ -z^ * ^ &gt; P.48/119 i i * ! ; \ * — w &gt; :! . ll aepteinber, 1958. Sir, With ro^srenoe to /our letter iio«J«55L2/’15G/l oT the Ifcth September # I am directed to trsnsait to you, to be laid before Viscount Halifax, tbe draft of a telegram which it is proposed to address to ilia Majesty's OoTernnents in zhe Dominions regarding the eurrdnuer oi British extra-territorial jurisdiction in Abyseinia, and to enquire whether he concurs in its terms* 2* It is not desired to offer any observations on the draft despatch to Hie Majesty's ChargS d'affaires at Horde enclosed in your letter. 3. Copies of this letter are being sent to the India Office, Home Office and Colonial Office. 1 am, dir, Your most obedient servant, (Signed) G, W. DIXOflftt THS UND3R S3CRKTARY OF STATE, FjRKIOH OFFICE. iJ ■ -•qRA^T TaUSQRAM Circular iwiw*. Confidential* SXYKIUJ^ OTTAWA KIKDL1 ^ CAHhKRHA QOVSRKOROSKBRAL V/KLLINOTON PRIMUS PRETORIA BSTKRO DUBLIN (By Bag) My telegram of the 14th April 9 1937 Circular B* No. 38. octra-territorial rights in Ahysainia. Draft Heads of ^igreement in terns indicated in the telegram under reference were duly comoiuni- oated to the Italian OoYernment. In reply Italian OoYernment have now stated that they consider that British consular Jurisdiction in Abyssinia automatically terminated with the eetabliehment of Italian sovereignty there f that is* as from 9th May, 1936. on thie understanding they are willing to accept an Agreement containing ’transitory regulations** with a view to dealing with practical problems arising from the cessation of British consular jurisdiction. These regulations should provide only for the settlement of civil and commercialcases already pending before British Courts* For this purpose the Italian Government have submitted a draft Agreement whleh is substantially as follows. Begins. Article 1 corresponds to sub- paragraph (b) of Article 1 of the United Kingdom draft 9 but confines the continued jurisdiction of British Consular Courts to such cases as were instituted before them prior to the 9th May, 1936, and provides that cases still pending before these Courts on the 1st July, 1939, shall be transferred to Italian jurisdiction* Article 2 corresponds to sub paragraph (e) of Article 1 of the United Kingdom draft, but contains no provision corresponding to the second sentence of tiist eub-par&amp;graph* Ends. The Italian Government would prefer that the matters covered by paragraphs 2, 3, 4 and 6 of the United Kingdom draft should be dealt with in the negotiations envisagedetc* The word 'nationals' aa opposed to in the two concluding paragraphs of the Protocol of the 16th April, 1938. (Treaty Series No*31 of 1938, CRkd*h726, enclosed in Circular despatch C*No*89 of the 26th April.) The effect would thus he that the provisions of any agreeinent reached with regard to these matters would he t reciprooal as opposed to unilateral* Although unwilling to reduce the provisions of the proposed agreement to the extent desired hy the Italian Government, His Majesty's Government in the United Kingdom are prepared to malec certain concessions and are willing to modify the original draft agreement on the following lines:* (a) Article 3 has already been practically covered hy that clause of the 'Bon Voiainage' 1 /igreeraent of 16th April which stated that nationals of the other party should not hs enrolled in native troops.■S' - -V 1 ■KK'- raatter 9 however, together with the queetion of the provision of money nnd services In lieu of military services which Is not referred to In the Agreement of tie 16th April may be clarified during the proposed commercial negotiations envisaged in the protocol of the 16th April* In the circumstances, therefore. Article 3 may be omitted from the proposed agreement* (b) Article 6 la of little Intrinsic Importance and may also be omitted* (c) Article 6 corresponds to some extent to Article 12 of the Anglo-Italian Commercial Treaty of IBth June, 1883, theextension of which to apply between Italian East Africa on the one hand and the United Kingdom, India and Colonial dependencies etc. on the other, is to be discussed with the Italian Governient In accordance with the Protocol of 16th April. His Kaiesty's Ooverment in the United Kingdom are therefore prepared to leave the subject of Article 5 for subsequent discussion in return for an assurance that the provisions contained in the last two sentences shall be included in the instruments resulting from the future commercial negotiations in a reciprocal V form. (d) The Italian Government should be urged to agree to the inclusion in the Agreement of provisions corresponding to Article 2 of the United Kingdom draft. (e) The Italian Government should be asked to consent to the retention In the agreement of sub-paragraph (a) of a rticle 1of the United Kingdom draft. They ahould he informed that Hie Uajeety’s Oovemnent in the United Kingdom are unwilling to renounce extra-territorial Jurisdiction ae from the 9th May, 1956, and should he asked to agree that oases which were pending in British Consular Courts at the Oats of signature of the Agreement should he dealt with hy those Courts* Apart from this question. His Majesty's Government in the United Kingdom are prepared to accept i*rticle 1 of tuc Italian draft* (f) Article 2 of the Italian draft may he accepted subject to the inclusion of the provision in the second sentence of sub-paragraph (c) of Article 1 of the United Kingdom draft* Hie Majesty's Government in the United Kingdom propose to instruct Hie Majesty's Charg$ d*Affaires at Rofae to reply to the Italian Government on the above linesI am directed by Viscount Halifax to acknowledge the receipt of your letter PZ 4081/3S of 18th July. In regard to the three points raised by the Marquess of Zetland in paragraphs 3, 4 and 5 of his letter, I am to point out: (1) that every effort will be made to secure the acceptance by the Italian Government of provisions on the lines of Article 2 cf the British draft Heads of Agreement; (2) that, while the need to proceed on the basis of the provisions of the Anglo-Italian Convention of 15th June, 1914, will doubtless be kept in view when the question of reciprocal treatment for Consular Officers comes to be dealt with as part of the negotiations envisaged in the Protocol of l^th April, it would not appear to be necessary to raise the point with the Italian Government at this stage; (3) that Lord Halifax is inclined to the view that the word ’’nationals” in the c Bon Voisinage 1 Agreement would cover all nationals of the Contracting Governments. On the other hand, there seems to be a faint possibility that it might be interpreted in the sense suggested by Lord Zetland. As paragraph 3 of the Heads of Agreement corresponds closely to one of the standard commercial treaty clauses, Lord Halifax feels, however, that this question, together with that of the furnishing of money and services in lieu of military service ?service could without doubt be covered by the further commercial negotiations envisaged under the protocol. In these circumstances Lord Halifax hopes that Lord Zetland will agree that Article 3 may be omitted from the draft Heads of Agreement and that, on the understanding that the matter will be raised in the course of the commercial negotiations no endeavour should be made for the moment to secure the acceptance of such a provision by the Italian Government. 2. A draft despatch with enclosure containing the instructions which it is now proposed to send to His Majesty^ Representative at Rome is enclosed herewith, and Lord Halifax will be glad to learn in due course whether Lord Zetland concurs in its terms. 3. • A copy of this letter is being sent to Home Office, 'Dominione Office, and Colonial Office. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant,J 3322/158/1 Draft. Sir Noel Charles, Rome. No F. 0., September , 193 Q Sir, I have had under consideration your despatch No. 504 (449/5/38), of the 25th May, containing the observations of the Italian Government on the proposals of His Majesty^ Government in the United Kingdom for the surrender of British extraterritorial jurisdiction in Ethiopia. 2. Prom this despatch and its enclosures I observe that the Italian Government would prefer to deal with most of the matters mentioned in the draft Heads of Agreement in the course of the negotiations envisaged in the Protocol of the 16th April# but that with a view to dealing with certain practical problems they would be willing to accept an agreement containing ”transitory 'provisions”, suggestions for which are embodied in the counter draft enclosed in your despatch under reference. 3. It( 3. It is clear that if the procedure suggested by the Italian Government were adopted, the effect would be that the provisions of any agreement reached with regard to these matters would be reciprocal as opposed to unilateral. While anxious, so far as possible, to meet the wishes of the Italian Government in this matter, I do not consider that it would be possible in the circumstances to reduce the provisions of the proposed agreement to so large an extent as the Italian Government desire. I have, however, considered very carefully what concessions can reasonably be made to the Italian point of view and after consultation with the interested departments of His Majesty’s Government certain conclusions have been reached which are embodied in the enclosed memorandum. This memorandum indicates, as you will observe, (a) that Articles 3 and 6 may be omitted. (b) that in return for an assurance from the Italian Government regarding the reciprocal right of consular officers to visit persons in prisontn (c) that provisions corresponding to Article 2 in the draft Heads of Agreement should be included; (d) that the Italian Government should be urged to accept certain amendments in their counter draft v/hich will bring it more into line with the provisions contained in Article 1 of the Heads of Agreement. I shall be glad if you will now reply to Ciano^ letter of the 18th May on the lines indicated in the memorandum.Heada of Agreement for the surrender &amp;£ extraterritorial rights In -tMflP t.fo. (») Omission of rUcjea g a nd,.i. 8® tar as Article 8 Is concerned, British deaiderata have already been practically met under that clause of the *Bon Voisinage' Agreement of the 16th April last, which stated that nationals of the other party should not be enrolled in native troops, bands or formations, and there would therefore appear to be no sufficient reason against meeting Italian wishes to the extent of omitting this Article* It has been pointed out, it is true, that the word 'nationals” used in the 'Bon Voisinage' Agreement, as opposed to the words 'British 'subjects' and 'British protected persons' used in Article 3 of the draft Heads of Agreement, might conceivably be held to relate only to persons belonging to the territories in respect of which the Agreement was concluded by the OovernmentGovernment of the United Kingdomt i»e* Kenya f the ' ui^an and British Somaliland* It has also been observed that the question of the provision of money and service in lieu of military service which figures in Article 5 is not referred to in the 'Bon Voisinage' Agreement* 2* These matters may require subsequent clarification. However# as the * ensemble’ of Article 3 corresponds closely to one of the standard commercial treaty articles it should be easy for these matters to be discussed during the proposed commercial negotiations and for any doubtful points to be cleared up then* In these circumstances it is thought that# as stated above# His Majesty's Government need not scruple to agree to the omission of Article 5 in toto * 3* Article 6# concerning extradition, would not appear to be of any great intrinsic importance and may be omitted* 4. (t&gt;) Proposed cnUaglon o f .Article 5 In return for certain .Bj 3 *s.l£led_undertuKlngBJffithe Italian. aov9rnsieq£ . The llfth article of the British draft Heads of Agreement deals with the rights and privileges of consular officers and corresponds» to some extent § with Article 12 of the Anglo-Italian Commercial Treaty of the 16th June, 1883, the extension of which to Italian East Africa, on conditions to he established, will, under the Anglo-Italian Protocol of the 16th April last, form one of the subjects to be discussed between His Majesty’s Government and the Italian Government after the instruments annexed to that Protocol have taken effect. Indeed, the first sentence of the fifth article of the Heads of Agreement is to the same effect as the concluding sentence of Article 12 of the Treaty of 1383, except that it adds the proviso that British Consular Officers in Ethiopia shall enjoy treatment and privileges not less favourable than those accorded to British Consular Officers in Italy. Subject to what is said in paragraph 5 below•7 no objection is seen to this matter being left over *^be dealt with on a reciprocal basis in the course of the negotiations contemplated in the Protocol of the 16th April last. I hare ascertained in this connexion that it is already the custom for foreign coneular officers in British Colonial Dependencies to be given the same treatment as they receive in the United Kingdom* The question of the treatment of consular officers in the Dominions would not appear to arise as the commercial negotiations envisaged will only cover relations between Italian East Africa» on the one hand* and the United Kingdom, India and the Colonial Dependencies, on the other. &amp;• Special mention must here be made of the two concluding sentences of this same article (No* B of the British draft Heads of Agreement) which provide that British Consular Officers in Ethiopia shall have th« right to visit British subjects or British protected persons ivv Ka „ iurWunA. ( Hu 0| JIaCiAl* Cer*A-vdA v* /WaJ tv J/aAju* ^ flu fS*persona who are in prison prior to sentence being passed on them. In the first place f it is now thought preferable that the words 'before conviction' should be substituted for the words ’’before sentence' and this should be made clear to the Italian Government. In the second place# it seems that no difficulty need be anticipated as to the grant of reciprocity in this matter of prison visits and communications from persons in prison. As it is thought by Kia Majesty’s Government to be important to make sure that the desiderata put forward in these two sentences should be secured^ His Majesty*s Government could only consent to the omission of the rest of Article 6 from their draft Heads of .greement on condition that they receive an assurance from the Italian Government that the latter are prepared to agree forthwith in principle that the provisions mentioned in the two sentences in question shall be included in the instruments resulting from the future commercialcommercial negotiations in a reciprocal form 6* (c) The n»ed fo r the Inclusion In any agreement regarding the aurrender of British extraterritorial rlghte In Ethiopia,of provision* on the lines of Article g of the British draft Heads of ;rr^eiaent» The question dealt with in this Article, which mostly concerns statut personnel * are not such as would ordinarily be dealt with in negotiations on commercial matters but are, in the opinion of His Majesty^ Government, such as they might reasonably request should be set down or agreed to at the moment when, as the result of the termination of British extraterritorial jurisdiction in Ethiopia, British nationals in that country are transferred from the jurisdiction of His Majesty^ Courts to those of the territorial authorities* The Italian Government should, therefore, be pressed to examine the provisions of Article 2 of the British draft in detail and to include some provisions on those lines In the eventual agreementagreement regarding the surrender of British extraterritorial juriadiction in thiopia. Hie Majesty*e Secretary of State for India lays particular stress on the need for making every effort to obtain fro* the Italian authorities satisfaction in this matter of statut personnel * 7. (d) The need to aaHe certain adamant and aaendaente to the Italian OaTcrnmentVs goiter.draft In order to„brlns It mox-S,in.tg lj-.aS.JlUL.the B i ritleh iii dra^t Meads,of,.^reement. The counter proposals of the Italian Government affect chiefly the first article of the British draft Heads of Agreement which dealt with the formal renunciation of British extraterritorial jurisdiction in Ethiopia with the treatment of pending cases and with Judgments and decisions given toy the British Consular Courts* The Article in the drwft Heads of Agreement is ofCount Ciano in April. With regard to this matter— the Italian Government should toe informed that when His Majesty’s Government drew up this draft they realised that the Italian Government might take the view that British consular jurisdiction in Ethiopia automatically terminated with the establishment of Italian sovereignty in that country and that as Hie Majesty’s Government were* in fact, ready to renounce any claim to continue it, they thought it unnecessary to examine such an Italian contention. The draft of the note from Lord Perth to Count Ciano was rather carefully prepared so as to render it acceptable to the Italian Government and not to prejudice their point of view. 8. The Italian Government should be informed, on the other hand, that His Majesty’s Government will not be able to accept the date of the 9th May, 1936, inserted in the first paragraph of the Italian draft, because although His Majesty’s Government are willing to renounce British extraterritorial jurisdiction in Ethiopia theythey cannot be expected to agree to such renunciation as from a date prior to their recognition of Italian sovereignty over Ethiopia* still less to agree that any automatic cessation of British extraterritorial jurisdiction in that country toofc place prior to that date* In this connexion it should be explained to the Italian Government that although British Consular Courts in Ethiopia have since the 9th May* 1956, actually been practically in suspense, formally they remain in being* It should be represented to the Italian Government that the point at issue cannot be of any great importance to them since Bis Majesty’s Government are renouncing British extraterritorial jurisdiction in Ethiopia and the Italian Government should therefore be asked to agree that cases, if any, vhieh at the date of the signature of the Agreement vere pending in His Majesty’s Consular Courts in Ethiopia should be dealt with by those Courts* 9* The Italian Government should also be asked to consent to the retention in the AgreementAgreement of sub-paragraph (a) of Article 1 of 14 ^ their^*raft» by which tj*ey renounce all claim to the exercise in Ethiopia of extraterritorial jurisdiction* It is felt that while not being inconsistent with the Italian view of the situation# this clause would facilitate the position of His Majesty’s Government. Apart from the question of date# tlie first paragraph of the Italian draft does not differ greatly from sub-paragraph (b) of the first article of the British draft# except for the last sentence of the Italian draft# and Eis Majesty’s Government#who have consulted His Majesty’s Consul-General at Addis Ababa in the matter# are prepared in all the circumstances to agree to the last sentence of Article 1 of the Italian draft and to the consequent closure of the British Consular Courts in Ethiopia on the 1st July# 1939# at the latest. The Italian Government may be so informed. 10. The second article of the Italian draft Agreement# though covering much the same groundground as that covered by sub-persgraph (c) of the first article of the British draft Heads of Agreementf contains the proviso* with regard to judgments delivered and recognised by the judicial authorities* that they shall 'contain 'no provisions contrary to public order'. Such a qualification would appear to be out of place and, in view of the previous proviso in the Italian draft 'within the limits of their 'competence', superfluous, but the matter would not seem to be one of any great importance and Hie Majesty's Government are prepared to accept this proviso. On the other hand, the second article of the Italian draft Agreement melees no mention of judgments in the former Special Court of Kthiopia and it la considered that the retention should be urged upon the Italian Goverraent of the provision in sub-paragraph (c) of Article 1 of the British draft Heads of Agre went, to the effect thfct judgments and decisions previously given in cases where British subjectssubject* and British protected persona or BritiA company's are concerned, by the former Special Court of Bthiopia will be recognised by Italian tribunals and enforced in the same manner as judgments and decisions giyen by the British Consular Courts in Ethiopia# The two concluding paragraphs of the aecona article of the Italian draft Agreement may be accepted. 11* It is noted that the third article respecting true copies of the judicial records of the British Consular Courts In Ethiopia corresponds to the last sentence of sub-paragradh (c) of the first article of the British draft Heads of Agreement. It ^ay therefore also be accepted.■ ■ _ ■ - • r .; ECO I m vnd&amp;* ed file copv (~t.£ any further communication on this subject, please quote N °- Tasao-.Wj/i and address— hvS to any person by ndnte, bi^ to— “The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. i. 6451 I938 THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to kloL C^j U'cttt j^f &amp;v\oUk and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop of the under-mentioned paper.* n^ 1 Foreign Office, 193V . Reference to previous correspondence : N«. P. 2 .fr 0 g|;ig 0 ^ .{(My • Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject.J 2**d/lbQ/l. wok im vwrxm, 16th f 1953* air 9 1 am uiractau by Vlsecmnt nnllfax to acknowledge the receipt of your letter 46638/53 of the 18th August, concerning the surrender of British extrsterntorisl jurisdiction in Ethiopls* i&gt;erd Hslifsy is glsd to note that as it is already the practise for foreign consular officers in the Colonial dependencies to receive treatment similar to that accorded to thee in this country there la unlikely to he any difficulty about Meeting Italian aeaiusrata In this respect* He ale© notes with pleasure that m&gt;* Secretary iscDonsld will be prepared to ask ths Colonial aovernaents to asks arrangements in regard to prison visits and ooavunioations from persons in prison of s kind likely to me t legitimate Italian requirements. g # A draft despatch with encloaurs containing the Instructions which it is now proposed to ssna to His Majesty’s Represent at ive st ie enclosed herewith, ana Lord Halifax will be glaa to learn in due course whether Mr* secretary MaeLoneld concurs in its terms. 3* A copy of this letter is being sent to the n i® Office* dominions Office and home Office. 1 e» f Sir# Your obedient Servant, (Sd.) D V KELLY The Under-Ge;retary of State, Colonial Officetemitm mnm u.v.x. Itth 19&amp;8. '&gt; IP# I «jk &lt;lr«Qt*4 by vueount H Xifax to oo^stowloiigo t io raooipt of your lot ior F 40/109 of tho 17th Juno with regard to the ourrondwr of British extro~territoriel Jurisdiction in 1 thlopio* «ubim on to state that the •eeunptiona contained in poregreph 9 of that letter ore correct* 9* no rogarao paragraph C # Lord Halifax incline* to tho view that tho «o*4 w nation«lo w in the mn Voioinago^ greeaent would cower all rationale of the Contracting vioweryimentai on the other haau* there aeema to ho o faint poaalhlllty that it night be Interpreted aa relating only to those belonging to the territories in respeot of which tho ngreonont was concluded by the Oovernaent of the United 'ling a on. e paragraph 4 of the Hoaus of Agreanont oorreaponaa olosoly to one cf the atanuard ooanercial treaty clauaeo» Lord Halifax feels sure that this question, together with that of the furnishing of money ana serwice in lieu of military service eould b# aiaouaaed auriag the oemeerolal negotiations snvissgou in the Protocol of the 16th April, and he wouli aug#:est that this might be pointed out to the Lorn 1 nlona Oovsrnmonts, as an explanation of om *** reaeona for tho omission cf Article 4 cf the drsft Heads the Uttusr-keerstary of dtatc, /»♦ dominions Office,&lt;mm/w &gt; 3ir t 2 am airtotod ay &gt;eor«tai^y HMDoottld to ^duiMlou^-e the receipt ol ymu letter So*J 21&amp;6A&amp;&amp;/1 of the 10th of * uae* on the mibleet ol the px^^pooea sur. eaaer ef British eoctroterrltorial jui isdlctl^n la Ethiopia, eusd to roqueet you to lafom Vlacouat iialU'&amp;» that he la la general agreement with the views eapreased la that letter* 2* ilth xegard to the tuestloa relaed la tlie fourth paragraph of your letter, X am to explela that it Has been the practice for many years to arra*4ge that foreign consular offleers in the Colonial lependenoles receive treatment similar to that accorded to them In thin country* c- py ox a clreular des mtoki -.•a t,.is subieot. Issued to Colonial Oover^saonts in 1931, is enclosed* 3* Pith regard to the gjuestioa raised in the fifth i^aragraph of your letter, Mr* ftaeDoa&amp;ld will be prepared to ask colonial Oovcr^vaeats to arreoage that (if the aHOoh cKOdSHPi^f V? CTA», rOHhlOV ajp^lCJUV Mo ^ c - The Under Secretary of State for the Home Department presents his compliments to the Under Secretary of State, India Office and by direction of the Secretary of State transmits herewith a copy of a letter which has been addressed to the Foreign Office on the subject of the surrender of British extra-territorial jurisdiction in Ethiopia (India Office reference P.Z. 4081/ZS'i.C 0 PY HOME OFFICE, WHITEHALL. S.W.1. U- OirC. It i4th August, 193d 590,978/4. Sir, I am directed by Secretary 31r Samuel Hoare to express regret for the ^elay In replying to your letter of the 10th June, 1938 (J 2156/158/1) on the subject of the proposed surrender of British extra-territorial jurisdiction la Ethiopia antf to say, for the information of Viscount Halifax, th«t he is in general agreement with the views expressed in your letter and desires to offer observations only upon the following points The fifth paragraph of the British draft Heads of Agreement provides that British cons ilar officers shall have the right to visit in prison any British subjects or British protected persons who are under arrest or in prison prior to sentence being passed upon them. Bo far as concerns the question of the grant of reciprocity in this matter to Italian c .naular officer** in this country, these words seem somewhat too widu, since they would include case* of convicted persons In respect of whom judgment h s be^n respited until a later sessions of the convicting court. As Lord Halifax will oe aware the existing prison standing Orders allow facilities to a foreign prisoner awaiting trial or on reiaand to receive a visit, if he so desires, from a represent stive of his embassy, legation or consulate, out there is no such provision for the case of convicted prisoners, and in such cases the question would fall to be dealt with in the light of the circumstances of the individual case. If, as air &gt;a:nuol Hoare presumes, the Tht Under Secretary of itate, FOREIGN OFFICE.intention of this p rngraph of the draft Hea of ^recment la to preserve the right to visit in prison prisoners who have not yet been tried, he think* that it would be sufficient, and would be in accordance with the existing arrangement in this country, if the word ’•conviction* wer substituted for the word '•sentence ’ in this par^gra h. As regards paragraph 6 of the draft Heads of Agreeirient the position, as ^ir oarauel Hoare understands it, ia that when Italian sovereignty over Ethiopia is recognised the existing Extradition Treaty with Italy will aprly as oet een His Majesty’s Oominions and Ethiopia, and so far as he is aware it is not inten ed to substitute fresh arrangements, though it may be that some mino * amendioenta are la contom lation. It would therefore appear that paragraph 6 should be co/ifined to questions of extradition between Ethiopia on the one hand, and British Protectorates and mandated territories on the other; and that accordingly the word “sovereignty* should be omitted in the third line of this paragraph* * c °Py *'his letter la being sent to the Colonial Office, India Office and Dominions Office. I am. Sir, Your obedient Servant6474a Wt 22530/P 144 10,000 9.37 TOP the/ tel The Under Secretary of State, Foreign Office, S.W.l. enclosure in air mail lltter no. x 4 %*&gt;■!■%% FROM SECRETARY, POLITICAL AND SECRET DEPT. INDIA OFFICE Copy to India with copy of P.O.letter. 19 ^ m 8 Sir, I am directed hy the Secretary of State for India to refer to your letter of the 10th June, No. J2156/158/1 relative to the observations of the Italian Government on the proposals of His Majesty*s Government in the United Kingdom for the surrender of British extraterritorial jurisdiction in Ethiopia. 2. I am to state in reply that the Marquess of Zetland is in general agreement v/ith the views of Viscount Halifax as expressed in your letter. 3. With reference to paragraph 7 of your letter I am to say that Lord Zetland attaches particular importance to the conclusion of a satisfactory settlement in respect of questions of statut personnel and trusts that every effort will he made to secure the acceptance hy the Italian Government of provisions on the lines of Article 2 of the British draft. 4. With regard to the question of reciprocal treatment for consular officers dealt with in paragraph 4 of your letter I am to invite reference to the provisions of the Anglo-Italian Convention of the 15th June,i.914, forritish India of the of Commerce and ,h June, 1883, and to and*s view the Italian Government asis that those rticular the on restricting the appointment of Italian Consuls in India to seaport towns, will continue to have effect. 5. Lord Zetland ohservesfrom paragraph 3 of your letter that Lord Halifax is of opinion that there is no objection to the omission of Article 3 in the British draft Heads of Agreement for the reason that the British desiderata in this respect have already been met under the Bon Voisinage 'Agreement of the 16th April between the jUnited Kingdom, Egypt, and Italy. Bsfugg n-enti n r tn thi n-r-r*w Lord Zetland would be glad of an assurance that the term * ' '’nationals” in the Bon Voisinage * i Agreement wft-M not, as regards British £ nationals,^ be interpreted as relating only to those belonging to the territories (viz. Kenya, Somaliland and the Sudan) in respect of which the Agreement was tytL concluded by the United Kingdom. Further the Agreement does not appear to satisfy ^ m the British desideratum that British | subjects shbuld not be required to furnish mdney or service in lieu of military service,, and as the matter may yell have importance for Indians in Italian/the extension to British India of the Anglo-Italian Treaty of Commerce and Navigation of the 15th June* 1883* and to say that in Lord Zetland’s view the negotiations with the Italian Government must proceed on the 'basis that those provisions, and in particular the provision restricting the appointment of Italian Consuls in India to seaport towns, will continue to have effect. 5. Lord Zetland ohservesfrom paragraph 3 of your letter that Lord Halifax is of opinion that there is no objection to the omission of Article 3 in the British draft Heads of Agreement for the reason that the British desiderata in this respect have already been met under the Bon Voisinage ’Agreement of the 16th April between the I United Kingdom, Egypt, and Italy. Befnjse a r rTentinr t^ thw Lord Zetland would 1^4 H &lt;4 ft &gt;4 X’U If * be glad of an assurance, that the term * | 'nationals'* in the Bon Voisinage Agreement w*£4 not, as regards British h nationals,^ be interpreted as relating only to those belonging to the territories (viz. Kenya, Somaliland and the Sudan) in resuect of which the Agreement was I concluded by the United Kingdom. Further * ^ the Agreement does not appear to satisfy ^ L :the British desideratum that British subjects shbuld not be required to 'Tiilitary service,, and as the matter may .veil have importance for Indians in \6474a Wt 22530/P 144 10,000 9.37 TOP (/ Italian East Africa, Lord Zetland would suggest that an endeavour should be made to secure tie acceptance of such a provision by the Italian Government. 6. Copies of this letter are being sent to the Home Office, Colonial Office and Dominions Office. (Sgd.) R. PEEU&amp; P. 48/109 Sir, 7 June, 193d* I an directed by Lord 3tsmlf*y to ac nowled^a the r*KK&gt;ipt of yo»ii* letter of th^ 10th (J*^156/168/1) v/ith regard to the u\xrrtm&amp;&lt; r of British entra^territorial jurisdiction in ;thir, ^ia* is. UP regards the generml pro osul of the Italian Gov^mrvent referred to in imi^rarjh d of your letter, it is observed that the final paragraph of the I rotoeol of the 16th April contaj'pluteU negotiations on Uie subject of eo?w;r©i&amp;l relations bc-tw.-en Italian *,aat .Xfrica and the ini ted Kin^oom* India and British Colon i^o, uverseas Cerrito ides* Protectorates arid ISendsted T rr i tories adiinistered by the uov mment of the Ignited Kingdom, fhaoe nogotiationa w uld acco 2 *dingly not cover coi-T^ercial illations between Italian .ast ^frica and the Dominions. It is presumed that any reciprocal sMcrtakings, whioh mi-,ht have to be given in these negotiations, e*g. in i'egard to the eiatters referred to in paragraphs 4 and 5 of your letter FOSSXGtf OFFICEletter would not apply to the Dominions, and that* in accordance with the usual practice» eTei’y effort would be made to ensure that any benefits secured for British subjects should apply to all British subjects* irrespective of the part of the Empire with which they were connected* On this assumption. Lord Stanley agrees that the procedure suggested by the Italian &gt;overument might be adopted to the extent Indicated in your letter* 3* Am regards paragraph 3 of your letter* it is observe that the Agreement between the United Kingdom* Lgypt and Italy, referred to 'nationals of the other party*' and, since the party to the Agreement on the British side was the Government of the United kingdom of Great Britain ana Bjorthern Ireland* It would seem open to doubt whether this expression could be regarded as having the same extent a» the tern 'British subjects' which it was proposed to employ in any agreement on the subject of extra territorial jurisdiction* Moreover, the Agreement of the 16th ripril does not appear to -over the furnishing of money or service in lieu of military service which it was proposed to cover ia the AgreementAgreement relating to extra-territorial Jurisdiction. Unless, however, any or the JDo.ainion Ooverztuents, who will naturally be informed of what is proposed, should press that provision should be made to cover British subjects belonging to that Dominion, Lord Stanley sees no objection to the omission of Article 3 of the British draft Heads of Agreement. 4. Lord Stanley concurs in the views expressed in paragraphs 6-10 of your letter. 5. ^ord Stanley would be glad to be informed when replies have been received from the other Department© to whom your letter was a dressed, in order that the Dominion OovernmeRts may be informed by telegraph of the reply of the Italian Oovernuent and of the action which it is proposed to take as a result. 6. Similar letters art; being sent to the Colonial Office, India Office and Uomt Office. X am, -Sir, Your most obedient servant.Treaty Series No. 31 (1938) AGREEMENT BETWEEN THE UNITED KINGDOM AND ITALY consisting of a Protocol with Annexes and Exchanges of Notes II BON VOISINAGE AGREEMENT and Exchanges of Notes between THE UNITED KINGDOM, EGYPT AND ITALY Rome, April 16, 1938 Presented by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs to Parliament by Command of His Majesty LONDON PRINTED AND PUBLISHED BY HIS MAJESTY’S STATIONERY OFFICE lo be purchased directly from H.M. STATIONERY OFFICE at the following addressee Adastral House, Kingsway, London, W.C.2; 120 George Street, Edinburgh 2; .26 York Street, Manchester 1; 1 St. Andrew’s Crescent, Cardiff; 80 Chichester Street, Belfast; _ or through any bookseller 1938 Price 9^. netCONTENTS. ■ :cUU. 1.—AGREEMENT BETWEEN THE UNITED KINGDOM AND ITALY CONSISTING OF A PROTOCOL, WITH ANNEXES ^ AND EXCHANGES OF NOTES. W Page 1. Protocol ... ... ... ... ... 4 2. Annex 1.—Reaffirmation of Declaration of January 2, 1937, regarding the Mediterranean, and of the Notes exchanged on December 31, 1936 8 3. Annex 2 .—Agreement regarding the Exchange of Military Information 10 4. Annex 3.—Agreement regarding certain areas in the Middle East ... ... ... 12 5. Annex 4.—Declaration regarding Propaganda ... 20 6 . Annex 5.—Declaration regarding Lake Tsana ... 20 i Annex 6 .—Declaration regarding the military duties of natives of Italian East Africa 22 8 . Annex 7.—Declaration regarding the free Exercise of Religion and the Treatment of British Religious Bodies in Italian East Africa 22 9. Annex 8 .—Declaration regarding the Suez Canal ... 24 10. Exchange of Notes.—Strength of Italian forces in Libya 26 11. Exchange of Notes.—Italian assurances in regard to policy in Spain, Spanish posses sions overseas and the Spanish Zone of Morocco; and United Kingdom intentions concerning the clarification of the position of Members of the League in regard to the situation in Ethiopia ... ... ... ••• 28 12. Exchange of Notes.—Treaty for the Limitation of Naval Armament, signed at London. March 25, 1936 ... ... ••• 30II.—BON VOISINAGE AGREEMENT AND EXCHANGES OF NOTES BETWEEN THE UNITED KINGDOM, EGYPT AND ITALY. Page (i) Bon Voisinage Agreement between United Kingdom, Egypt and Italy ... ... ... ... ... ... ... 32 (ii) Exchange of Notes between the United Kingdom, Egypt and Italy regarding Lake Tsana (see Document No. 6 above) ... ... ... ... ... ... ... ... 34 (iii) Exchange of Notes between the United Kingdom, Egypt and Italy regarding the Suez Canal (see Document No. 9 above) ... ... ... ... ... ... 37I. —agreement between the united kingdom AND ITALY, CONSISTING OF A PROTOCOL WITH ANNEXES AND EXCHANGES OF NOTES. Home, April 16, 1988. No. 1 . PROTOCOL. The Government of the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland and the Italian Government, animated by the desire to place the relations between the two countries on a solid and lasting basis and to contribute to the general cause of peace and security, have decided to undertake conversations in order to reach agreement on questions of mutual concern; and the said conversations having taken place; His Excellency the Right Honourable the Earl of Perth, G.C.M.G., C.B., His Majesty’s Ambassador Extraordinary and Plenipotentiary at Rome, and 11 is Excellency Count Galeazzo Ciano di ( ortellazzo, Minister for Foreign Affairs, duly authorised for that purpose by their respective Governments, have drawn up the present Protocol and have signed the Agreements and Declarations annexed hereto, each of which shall be regarded as a separate and self-contained instrument:— (1) Reaffirmation of the Declaration of the 2nd January, 1987, regarding the Mediterranean, and of the Notes exchanged on the 31st December, 1986; (2) Agreement regarding the Exchange of Military Information, (3) Agreement regarding certain Areas in the Middle East; (4) Declaration regarding Propaganda ; (5) Declaration regarding Lake Tsana; ( 6 ) Declaration regarding the Military Duties of Natives ol Itaian East Africa; , , (7) Declaration regarding the free Exercise of Religion ana Treatment of British religious Bodies in Italian East Atnca; ( 8 ) Declaration regarding the Suez Canal. The said instruments shall take effect on such date as the two Governments shall together determine. Except in so far as any them contain provisions with regard to their revision or dura 1 ° n ’ ,i of the said instruments shall remain in force indefinitely, bu s either Government at any time consider that a change o cir ^ stances renders the revision of any of these instruments neces the two Governments will consult together with a view to su revision.«T MS* '•&gt; A. C i 2 i 'V %&amp;VX j Uv ttfcXfi SO llX *4 v *a .. • si.v &amp;$&amp; $ £&amp;', 6 The two Governments agree that, immediately after the taking effect of the said instruments, negotiations will be opened, in which the Egyptian Government will be invited to participate so far as all ouestions affecting Egypt or the Anglo-Egypt!an Sudan are concerned, with a view to a definitive agreement on the boundaries between the Sudan, Kenya and British Somaliland on the one side and Italian East Africa* on the other; and with regard to other questions affecting reciprocally (a) Italian interests on the one hand and British, Egyptian or Sudan interests on the other hand in the ^ above-mentioned territories, and (b) the relations between those territories. These negotiations will also include the question of commercial relations between the Sudan and Italian East Africa. It is also agreed that negotiations between the Government of the United Kingdom and the Italian Government will take place as soon as possible on the subject of commercial relations between Italian East Africa and the United Kingdom, India, and British colonies, overseas territories, protectorates and mandated territories adminis tered by the Government of the United Kingdom, including the subject of the application, on conditions to be established, to the whole of Italian East Africa of the Treaty of Commerce and Navigation signed at Rome on the 15th June, 1888. These negotiations will be inspired bv the common desire to further commercial lelations between these territories and to ensure adequate facilities for trade. Done at Rome, in duplicate, the 16th April, 1988, in the English and Italian languages, both of which shall have equal force. PERTH. CIANO.% 8 (') Cmd.5348. u /-c - ^ m*m a ^ 4 . •ysa*I No. 2 . Annex 1 . REAFFIRMATION OF THE DECLARATION OF JANUARY 2, 1987, REGARDING THE MEDITERRANEAN, AND OF THE - NOTES EXCHANGED ON DECEMBER 31, 1936. ^ The Government of the United Kingdom and the Italian Govern ment hereby reaffirm the Declaration signed in Rome on the 2nd January, 1937,0) regarding the Mediterranean, and the Notes exchanged between the two Governments on the 31st December, 1936 , 0 ) regarding the status quo in the Western Mediterranean. Done at Rome, in duplicate, the 16th April, 1938, in the English and Italian languages, both of which shall have equal force. PERTH. CTANO..ftoi;* i -b* .voL | Olfi, . ■- .ui-4 , JCj.fO;-.f i Jr»|?w MO wvw ^3 4&amp;&amp;s »« aitri t|i&lt;M| w;a£ati-- -•ySOt.- ♦ii^iiSi:: :C • ^ i s &gt;ilt j? ^ i 0 ^ol® * . '• r ‘ wpi* si r 4U «mrc^s i^xfao uia oon'i $rr « Hi #* -um bmsn&amp;ttti &amp;&amp; ^b@ i-r aa&amp;Sf^ii&amp;’nn Hi i'i^i ^ • b- m - -ftdi D-J- ^tt S. •;• b £«k1 -Mi. * ^5 * . : t 4i - * a , i? S-VU^ - v.v $ life2Kf© a '■:♦ ®- : 10 No. 3. Annex 2 . AGREEMENT REGARDING THE EXCHANGE OF MILITARY INFORMATION. The Government of the United Kingdom and the Italian Govern ment agree that in the month of January each year a reciprocal exchange of information shall take place through the Naval, Military and Air Attaches in London and Rome regarding any major prospec tive administrative movements or redistribution of their respective naval, military and air forces. This exchange of information will take place in respect of such forces stationed in or based on— ( 1 ) overseas possessions of either Party (which phrase shall for this purpose be deemed to include protectorates and mandated territories) in or with a seaboard on the Mediterranean, the Red Sea or the Gulf of Aden, and (2) territories in Africa other than those referred to in para graph ( 1 ) above and lying in an area bounded on the west bv longitude 20 ° east and on the south by latitude 7° south. Such an exchange of information will not necessarily preclude the occasional communication of supplementary military information should either party consider that the political circumstances of the moment make it desirable. The two Governments further agree to notify each other in advance of any decision to provide new naval or air bases in the Mediterranean east of longitude 19° east and in the Red Sea or approaches thereto. Done at Rome, in duplicate, the 16th April, 1938, in the English and Italian languages, both of which shall have equal force. PERTH. CIAN0.Annex 8. f ANGLO-ITALIAN AGREEMENT REGARDING CERTAIN AREAS IN THE MIDDLE EAST. The Government of the I nited Kingdom of Great Rritain and Northern Ireland and the Italian Go\eminent, bein' desirous of ensuring that there shall be no conflict between their respective policies in regard to the areas in the Middle East referred to in the present agreement, beincr desirous, moreover, that the same friendly spirit which has attended the signing of to-day’s Protocol, and of the documents annexed thereto, should also animate their relations in regard to those areas, have agreed as follows:— Article 1 . Neither Party will conclude any agreement or take any action which might in* any way impair the independence or integrity of Saudi Arabia or of the Yemen. Article 2 . Neither Party will obtain or seek to obtain a privileged position of a political character in any territory which at present belongs to Saudi Arabia or to the Yemen or in any territory which either of those States may hereafter acquire. Article 8. The two Parties recognise that, in addition to the obligations incumbent on each of them in virtue of Articles 1 and 2 hereof, i is in the common interest of both of them that no other Power s ou acquire or seek to acquire sovereignty or any privileged position o a political character in any territory which at present belongs to ban i Arabia or to the Yemen or which either of those States niai hereafter acquire, including any islands in the Red Sea belonging to either of those States, or in any other islands in the ^ to which Turkey renounced her rights by Article 16 of the ^ ea ^ 0 Peace signed at Lausanne on the 24th July, 1928. In particular ey regard it as an essential interest of each of them that no o e Power should acquire sovereignty or any privileged position on part of the coast of the Red Sea which at present belongs to bau Arabia or to the Yemen or in any of the aforesaid islands.Article 4. (1) As regards those islands in the Red Sea to which Turkey renounced her rights by Article 16 of the Treaty of Peace signed at Lausanne on the 24th July, 1923, and which 'are not comprised in the territory of Saudi Arabia or of the Yemen, neither Party will, in or in regard to any such island :— (а) establish its sovereignty, or (б) erect fortifications or defences. (2) It is agreed that neither Party will object to:— (а) the presence of British officials at Kamaran for the purpose of securing the sanitary service of the pilgrimage to Mecca in accordance with the provisions of the Agreement concluded at Paris on the 19th June, 1926,( 2 ) between the Governments of Great Britain and Northern Ireland and of India on the one part, and the Government of the Netherlands, on the other part; it is also understood that the Italian Government may appoint an Italian Medical Officer to be stationed there on the same conditions as the Netherlands Medical Officer under the said Agreement; (б) the presence of Italian officials at Great Hanish, Little Hanish and Jebel Zukur for the purpose of protecting the fishermen who resort to those islands; (c) the presence at Abu Ail, Centre Peak and Jebel Teir of such persons as are required for the maintenance of the lights on those islands. Article 5 . (1) The two Parties agree that it is in the common interest of both of them that there shall be peace between Saudi Arabia and the Yemen and within the territories of those States. But, while they will at all times exert their good offices in the cause of peace, they will not intervene in any conflict which, despite their good offices, may break out between or within those States. (2) The two Parties also recognise that it is in the common interest of both of them that no other Power should intervene in any such conflict. Article 6. As regards the zone of Arabia lying to the east and south of the piesent boundaries of Saudi Arabia and of the Yemen or of any future boundaries which may be established by agreement between (*) (*) Treaty Series No. 26 (1926). Cmd. 2741.in the Government of the United Kingdom, on the one hand, and the Governments of Saudi Arabia or of the Yemen, on the other: (1) The Government of the United Kingdom declare that in the territories of the Arab rulers under their protection within this zone : (a) no action shall be taken by the Government of the United Kingdom, which shall be such as to prejudice in any way the independence or integrity of Saudi Arabia or of the Yemen (which both Parties have undertaken to respect in Article 1 hereof), within any territory at present belonging to those States or within any additional territory which may be recognised by the Government of the United Kingdom as belonging to either of those States as a result of any agreement which may hereafter be concluded between the Government of the United Kingdom and the Government of either of them; (b) the Government of the United Kingdom will not undertake, or cause to be undertaken, any military preparations or works other than military preparations or works of a purely defensive character for the defence of the said territories or of the communications between different parts of the British Empire. Furthermore, the Government of the I nited Kingdom will not enrol the inhabitants of any of these territories, or cause them to be enrolled, in any military forces other than forces designed and suited solely for the preservation of order and for local defence; (c) while the Government of the United Kingdom reserve the liberty to take in these territories such steps as may be necessary for the preservation of order and the develop ment of the country, they intend to maintain the autonomy of the Arab rulers under their protection. (2) Ihe Italian Government declare that they will not seek to acquire any political influence in this zone. Article 7. The Government of the United Kingdom declare that within the limits of the Aden Protectorate as defined in the Aden Protectorate Order, 1937, Italian citizens and subjects (including Italian com panies) shall have liberty to Come, with their ships and goods, to all places and ports, and they shall have freedom of entry, travel and residence and the right to exercise there any description of business, profession, occupation or industry, so long as they satisfy and observe the conditions and regulations from time to time applicable in the Protectorate to the citizens and subjects and ships of any country not being a territory under the sovereignty, suzerainty.I 1 protection or mandate of His Majesty The King of Great Britain Ireland and the British Dominions beyond the Seas, Emperor of India. I Article 8. (1) Should either Party at any time give notice to the other that they consider that a change has taken place in the circumstances obtaining at the time of the entry into force of the present Agreement, such as to necessitate a modification of the provisions of the Agreement, the two Parties will enter into negotia tions with a view to the revision or amendment of any of the provisions of the Agreement. (2) At any time after the expiration of a period of ten years from the entry into force of this Agreement either party may notify the other of its intention to determine the Agreement. Any such notification shall take effect three months after the date on which it is made. Done at Rome, in duplicate, the IGth April, 1988, in the English and Italian languages, both of which shall have equal force. PERTH. CIA NO.*20 No. 5. Annex 4 . DECLARATION REGARDING PROPAGANDA. The two Governments welcome the opportunity afforded by the present occasion to place on record their agreement that any attempt ft by either of them to employ the methods of publicity or propaganda ^ at its disposal in order to injure the interests of the other would be ^ ft inconsistent wifh the good relations which it is the object of the ^ present Agreement to establish and maintain between the two Govern ments and the peoples of their respective countries. Done at Rome, in duplicate, the 16th April, 1988, in the English and Italian languages, both of which shall have equal force. PERTH - CIANO. lor qm pul agl chf ed ital No. 6. Annex 5. DECLARATION REGARDING LAKE TSANA. Tke Italian Government confirm to the Government of the 1 nited Kingdom the assurance given by them to the Government of 1’as the United Kingdom on the 3rd April, 1986, and reiterated by the 199 Italian Minister for Foreign Affairs to His Majesty’s Ambassador at all’ Rome on the 31st December, 1936, to the effect that the Italian 199 Government were fully conscious of their obligations towards dell the Government of the United Kingdom in the matter of Lake Tsana del and had no intention whatever of overlooking or repudiating them. o ri Done at Rome, in duplicate, the 16th April, 1938, in the English and Italian languages, both of which shall have equal force. it a l PERTH - CIANO. I t‘22 I No. 7. Annex 6. DECLARATION REGARDING THE MILITARY DUTIES OF NATIVES OF ITALIAN EAST AFRICA. The Italian Government reaffirm the assurance which they gave in their Note to the League of Nations of the 29th June, 193G, that &amp; Italy on her side was willing to accept the principle that natives of * Italian East Africa should not be compelled to undertake military duties other than local policing and territorial defence. Done at Rome, in duplicate, the 16th April, 1938, in the English and Italian languages, both of which shall have equal force. PERTH. CIANO. No. 8. Annex 7. DECLARATION REGARDING THE FREE EXERCISE OF RELIGION AND THE TREATMENT OF BRITISH RELIGIOUS BODIES IN ITALIAN EAST AFRICA. \\ ithout prejudice to any Treaty engagements which may be applicable, the Italian Government declare that they intend to assure to British nationals in Italian East Africa the free exercise of all cults compatible with public order and good morals; and in this spirit they will examine favourably any request which may reach them from the British side to assure in Italian East Africa religious assistance to British nationals; and that as regards other activities of British religious Bodies in Italian East Africa in humanitarian and benevolent spheres, such requests as may reach the Italian Govern ment will be examined, the general line of policy of the Italian Government in this matter and the principles of legislation in force in Italian East Africa being borne in mind. Done at Rome, in duplicate, the 16th April, 1938, in the English and Italian languages, both of which shall have equal force. PERTH. CIANO.• No. 9. Annex 8. DECLARATION REGARDING THE SUEZ CANAL. 1 he Government of the United Kingdom and the Italian Government hereby reaffirm their intention always to respect and V™™' 0 ™ ° f the Convention signed at Constantinople on the 29th October, 1888, which guarantees at all times and for all Powers the free use of the Suez Canal. Done at Rome, in duplicate, the 16th April, 1988, in the English and Italian languages, both of which shall have equal force. CIANO.• 3 A No. 10. EXCHANGE OF NOTES BETWEEN UNITED KINGDOM AND ITALY. Strength of Italian Forces in Libya. (a) Count Ciano to Lord Perth. II Ministro degli Affari Esteri. Eccellenza. Roma, 16 aprile 1938-XVL Nel corso delle nostre recenti conversazioni Yostra Eccellenza ha menzionato la questione dell’ammontare delle forze italiane in Libia. Ho 1’onore di informare Vostra Eccellenza che il Capo del Governo ha disposto nna dirainuzione di tali forze. I ritiri sono gia incominciati in ragione di 1000 uomini alia settirnana e saranno continuati in ragione non inferiore a tale cifra finche gli effettivi italiani in Libia raggiungeranno il piede di pace. Cio che rappresentera in definitiva una diminuzione degli etfettivi in Libia di non meno della meta delle forze esistenti al momento dell’inizio delle conversazioni. Voglia gradire, &amp;c. CIANO. (Translation.) The Minister for Foreign Affairs. Your Excellency, Rome, April 16, 1938. During our recent conversations Your Excellency has referred to the question of the strength of the Italian forces in Libya. I have the honour to inform Your Excellency that the Head of the Government has given orders for a diminution of these forces. Withdrawals have already begun at the rate of 1,000 a week and will be continued at not less than this rate until the Italian Libyan effectives reach peace strength. This will constitute an ultimate diminution of these effectives by not less than half the numbers present in Libya when our conversations commenced. I avail, &amp;c. CIANO.Lord Perth to Count Ciano. British Embassy, Rome, Your Excellency, April 16, 1938. I have the honour to acknowledge the receipt of Your Excellency’s Note of to-day’s date in which Your Excellency informed me of the intentions of the Head of the Italian Government with regard to the progressive diminution of the Italian forces in Libya. I shall have pleasure in communicating this information to His Majesty’s Government in the United Kingdom. I avail, &amp;c. PERTH.First, the Italian Government have the honour to confirm their full adherence to the United Kingdom formula for the proportional evacuation of the foreign volunteers from Spain, and pledge them selves to give practical and real application to such an evacuation at the moment and on the conditions which shall be determined by the Non-Intervention (Committee on the' basis of the above- mentioned formula. I desire secondly to reaffirm that if this evacuation has not been completed at the moment of the termination of the Spanish civil war, all remaining Italian volunteers will forthwith leave Spanish territory and all Italian war material will simultaneously be withdrawn. I wish thirdly to repeat my previous assurance that the Italian Government have no territorial or political aims, and seek no privileged economic position, in or with regard to either Metropolitan Spain, the Balearic Islands, any of the Spanish possessions overseas, of the Spanish zone of Morocco, and that they have no intention whatever of keeping any armed forces in any of the said territories. I avail, &amp;c. CIANO. No. 11. (b) Lord Perth to Count Ciano. British Embassy, Your Excellency, Rome, April 16, 1938. In reply to Your Excellency’s Note of to-day’s date, I have the honour to take note of the reaffirmation contained therein of the assurances which Your Excellency has already given me, during the course of our recent conversations, regarding the policy of the Italian Government in connexion with Spain. His Majesty’s Govern ment in the United Kingdom, to whom I shall not fail to transmit this communication, will, I feel sure, be gratified at its contents. In this connexion I hardly need to remind Your Excellency that His Majesty’s Government regard a settlement of the Spanish question as a prerequisite of the entry into force of the Agreement between our two Governments. I have further the honour to inform Your Excellency that His Majesty’s Government, being desirous that such obstacles as may at present be held to impede the freedom of member States as regards recognition of Italian sovereignty over Ethiopia should be removed, intend to take steps at the forthcoming meeting of the Council of the League of Nations for the purpose of clarifying the situation of member States in this regard. I avail, &amp;c, PERTH.( 6 ) Lord Perth to Count Ciano. British Embassy, Your Excellency, Rome, April 16, 1938. I have the honour to acknowledge the receipt of Your Excellency’s Note of to-day’s date in which Your Excellency informed me of the decision of the Italian Government to accede to the Naval Treaty signed in London on the 25th March, 1936, so soon as the instru ments annexed to the Protocol signed this day come into force, and in the meantime to act in conformity with the provisions of the aforesaid Treaty. I shall have pleasure in communicating this decision to His Majesty’s Government in the United Kingdom. I avail, (fee. PERTH.It4 (H) • v JL£ . . *i l ” EXCHANGE OF NOTES BETWEEN THE UNITED KINGDOM EGYPT AND ITALY REGARDING LAKE TSANA. Lord Perth to Mostafa El Sadeh Bey. lour Excellency, British Embassy, Rome, April 16, 1938. I have the honour to inform your Excellency that the following Declaration regarding Lake Tsana was signed to-day by the Italian Minister for Foreign Affairs and myself, as Annex 5( s ) to the Protocol which Count Ciano and I have also signed to-day :— “ The Italian Government confirm to the Government of the United Kingdom the assurance given by them to the Government of the United Kingdom on the 3rd April, 1936, and reiterated by the Italian Minister for Foreign Affairs to His Majesty’s Ambassador at Rome on the 31st December, 1936, to the effect that the Italian Government were fully conscious of their obliga tions towards the Government of the United Kingdom in the raattei of Lake Isana and had no intention whatever of over looking or repudiating them.” ■further, I have the honour to inform your Excellency that His Majesty s Government for their part declare that they agree that the assurances given to them in the above Declaration concerning Lake Tsana shall apply equally to the Egyptian Government. I avail, Ac. PERTH. (') See No. 6. Mostafa El Sadeh Bey to Lord Perth. Legation de S.M. le Roi d'Egypte Your Excellency, a Rome, April id, 1938. have the honour to acknowledge the receipt of your Excellency’s Note of to-day’s date, which reads as follows :— I have the honour to inform your Excellency that the o Declaration regarding Lake Tsana was signed to-day v the Italian Minister for Foreign Affairs and myself, as Annex 5 o the liotocol which Count Ciano and I have also signed to-day :— . Government confirm to the Government of the United Kingdom the assurance given by them to the Governmentconsultation with His Majesty’s Consul-General at Addis Ababa, His Majesty’s Government might agree to the last sentence of Article 1 of the Italian draft and therefore consent to the closure of the British Consular Courts in Ethiopia on the 1st July, 1939, at the latest. 9. The second article of the Italian draft agreement covers, it will be seen, much the same ground as that covered by sub-paragraph (c) of the first article of the British draft Heads ol Agreement. The Italian draft, however, contains the proviso, with regard to judgments delivered and recognised by the judicial authorities, that they shall 'contain no provisions contrary to public order'. It appears to Lord Halifax that such a qualification is out of place and, in view of the previous proviso in the Italian draft 'within the 'limits of their competence', superfluous; but he is not inclined to attach undue importance to the matter. In the second place, the second article of the Italian draft agreement makes no mention of judgments in the former Special Coart of Ethiopia, and Lord Halifax considers that the retention should be urged upon the Italian Government of the provision in sub-paragraph (c) of Article 1 of the British draft Heads of Agreement, to the effect that judgments and decisions previously given in cases where British subjects and British- protected persons or British companies are concerned by the former Special Court of Ethiopia, will be recognised by the I^ a li a n tribunials and enforced in the same manner as judgments and decisions given by the British Consular Courts in Ethiopia. He does not consider that objection need be taken® Hi taken to the Vvo concluding paragraphs of the second article of the Italian draft agreement. 10. The third article of the Italian draft agreement, respecting true copies of the judicial records of the British consular courts in Ethiopia, corresponds to the last sentence of sub-paragraph (c) of the first article of the British draft Heads of Agreement and does not, in Lord Halifax^ opinion, call for further comment. 11. I am to enquire whether the Marquess of Zetland is in agreement with the views expressed in the preceding paragraphs of this letter and whether he has any observations to offer on the matter generally. 12. Similar letters are being sent to the Colonial Office, Dominions Office, and Home Office. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, V. c. • ^ J a*-Copy. (.T 3156/158/1) (449/6/38) . I IMk British ’Embassy ^orae. 25th May, 19 58. My Lord, In my telegram No. 301 of the 3rd April I had the honour to inform you that I handed the draft texts enclosed in Your Lordship*s despatch No. 475 of the 2Rth March (P. 2541/B&amp; / ?P) on the subject of the surrender of extra territorial jurisdiction in Ethiopia to the Italian Minister for Foreign Affairs. Count Ciano’s reaction r'ae to ouestion the necessity for an agreement of this nature. 2 I have now received from Count ci Rno the personal letter and its enclosures of which I have the honour to transmit translations herewith. A copy of the draft Italian agreement is al.-o enclosed. It will be observed that there is a general objection to the draft prepared in your Department on the ground th»t it implies tiv*t British Consular Courts still enjoy jurisdiction in Ethiopia and provides for the abolition of that jurisaiction, whereas the Italian Government maintain that these rights were extinguished upon the esteblishment of Italian sovereignty lover Ethiopia, that is, upon the 9th May, 1936, and therefore do not exist. Lhe Italian /ovem^ent are nevertheless billing to agree to certisn transitory provisions with a view to dealing with the practical problems * T hich arise/ etc., e tc., FOPETOIf nppTCEarise. They therefore orooose * courtter-d aft to renlace Article 1 of the Foreign Office draft. As the oueetions involved are mainly of a legal character I hesitate to offer any comments on th&lt; suitability of the Italian draft. Z, The Italian Government further propose that the Questions regarding the treatment of British subjects dealt with in Articles 8-5 of the Foreign Office draft should be examined in connexion with the negotiations provided for in 'the l^st part of the Protocol'. The last oeragraph of the Protocol deals exclusively w ith commercial Questions, while the oenultimate paragraphs deals inter alia with 'other 'questions affecting reciprocally (a) Italian interests on 'the one hand and British, Egyptian or Sudan interests on the 'other hand in the above-mentioned territories (i.e, the 'Sudan, Kenya and British omaliland and Italian Fast Africa; ’and (b) the relations between those territories'. Presumably the Italian Government have the penultimate paragraph chiefly in mind. Prime facie , however, it seems doubtful whether the Protocol was ever Intended on our side to cover the questions dealt with in the present draft agreement which deals largely with the question of personal status and nationality. 4. I have the honour to request Your Lordship’s instructions as to the reply which I should return to Count Ciano. I have etc., (Signed) Noel Charles. (for His Majesty’s Ambassador).Ts$! Copy. ?&gt;l r ’S54 / 4B. r&gt; Ministry of Foreign Affnira, Home. 18th May, 19 8. PET? IQ^TAL. Dear Ambassador, &gt;urlng the recent Ttalo-British conversations Ymr Excellency handed to •ne for examln^t’on a draf t *Tote, with relative Annex, -hich Tour Excellency w&gt;uld prooose t° send me on the day of the entry into force of the It«lo-Engl1sh Agreements of 16th Aoril last, regarding the cessation of British Consular Jurisdiction in Ethiopia. ith reference to this ouestion, I transmit herewith to Your Excellency a Memorandum containing certain considerations regarding the contents of the above-mentioned Annex, to which is attached a draft agreement, for examine tion. Believe me etc., (Signed) CTANO.HTirsm OF POPKIO’T AFKAIR3. Su. Med. Ill P. z. 4 Q 81 | ' bjf b MSMORAJfXWII. Parngro^h 1 fa-b-e) of the Annex to the draft Oote of the British Kmhassy refers to the transitory regime m'hieh is designed to regulate the ceesation of British jurisdiction in Ethiopia. The Foyal Government consider tht the agreements with the Government of the ex-Ethiopian Empire and the usages in virtue of which certain foreign 'owers exercised consular jurisdiction in Ethiopia became extinct from the date on which the Ethiopian territories were placed under the full and direct sovereignty of Italy. Having made this clear, the Foysl Jovernment concur in th# opportuneness of laying down in common agreement with the British Government certain transitory regulations designed to regulate the cessation of British consular jurisdiction in Ethiopia in such a way as to t!*ke into account the practical exigencies which this cessation entails. According to the ooint of view of the Eoyal Government, these regulations should only have as their object the future of the civil and commercial cases which were already pending before the British courts and the recognition by the Italian authorities of the decisions of these tribunals. A draft agreement regarding these regulations is attached (Enclosure N. 1), 2. In the Annex to the draft Note, communicated by the British moassy, provision is also made for other regulations (oara raohs , #4,6,' which concern the treatment of British subjects/V Cl . V A . I V. &lt; i 6UP ■i v e .b$v .r- Tlo t\Wfb srfJ* of xsnnA 9iif tc (o-cf~B^ X rfo^i^a'ie' «t . oiri”* | #*1 xtClsa v t od: oS 'tyBRdm rieiJti r *&gt;n3 Aittfri* to creJtJ*£!3»r&gt; orfX oi m ji^l f •« #4d a ^Xanro Xn^niavo Ip^ov; ait? Gl et»-,s» ».i r bn* vtioxl naicotdt ,-x.:&gt; 3 s 1c avr;, ‘faXraflre fta&amp;Xo't 'xs&gt; a^iewc n^ ranc nia#*iao do Ur-- tc oi. X'ii v' «t; *ti*b *ilj Me*st fortixo .it«po.j(f ^ici JtdP at ac JoJthi .Hi/t XXxil od* %mbm ^ ao^ , »X f ' , aai^p^t i»X nelcrolrfX. ^4. /ir’iiiw Gl 'ZVOflOQ trr&amp;f'Wi&amp;ve £px c ' X al.- ‘ &amp; B \rtVf* : fat* nrffcC' r nvofc :.- ; nX';#»X 1c as^nanrt'xocf’O s^j fcaitv Nsfe nrottfsif s 111 vnr. tvwiS nlod'tpa Jna^navrX /fa ^X^C ,.X,t rr^if :•• ..• ^r ? - 'l l inr- ii iJtJX ii tc noKt -asor a' OJ cinf oX ap p nr ptcnX/i^ nt .allsJns rroXtaaaar a rf.i rotHm «• tom*$txa f ,tus3wmavo0 X»\cj arfcf tr. wal/ 'H Icier i&gt;flj cj ^rjXbnoooA ©wlff^ ^rfl -&gt;vpil -,Xn»- hLv* dr- sneXlaltw^ aa»4l /rf’rr^c \ an©w ffolitir 8 •«© I • tonar-r-rr vtr X^v v ^ »rfl 'ic nplXall ©41 ’cef ftctHfl&amp;osan &gt;41 |&gt;rta . l .'i rr ite/lXnX' aifj netOFtf »a£«Mttrtflil ©fiailJ aarelateae irll tc a©X; itciilra *•'.I. :f 3 pa-lrn^) teHaalla al acellaXa^a - ! imggf . adl yd baler? Lmrrop t aloJ»! llanb a4i oj xaitaA aid uI am tteXif^a'i faille not aber oaXs et note Ivone , XBan&amp;m rtatlinf •yot 6it&amp;r wc 1# The British Consular' Tribunals on the ter itories of Italian Hast Africa which previously forced part of thiopia shall continue to be entrusted, until definitive settlement is reached, with such civil and commercial cases as were regularly instituted before them prior to May 9th, 1936. The Italian Authorities, with the object of facilitflt5.ng for the British Consular Tribunals the settlement of these cases, shall lend their assistance, in conformity with the Italian lawg, to tiu British Consular Tribunals in the completion of the documents of enmilry (examination of the partite, recording of evid nee, etc.). Nevertheless, cases which on ^Tuly 1st 19:59 may still be pending before the British Consular Tribunals, shall be transferred, in the condition in which they are nt the t me to Italian Jurisdiction. 9. definitive judgments in civil and commercial cases, pronounced by the British Consular Tribunals in Ethiopia within the limits of their competence, shall be recognised by the Italian Judicial authorities as having the authority of a &gt;provided that they contain no provisions contrary to public order. Subject to the s^me condition, the said ^’idgements shall be declared enforceable by the Foyal Court of Appeal of Addis Ababa, on the reemest of the competent British Consul or at the instance of the interested party. The definitive character of these judgments shall be established by certificates issued by the British Consular authorities.a .J **ril no .dzrjct 1 -: r-M^aar r. r &gt; &gt;' -&gt;.-i * .X to #*m tommat %lwfGJtv&amp;%qi itetriw mo frit i ia«»I to 0 iiXrrit w USat % &amp;mi jn&amp;ns &amp;d cJ mmlJam IXsxla b js^o ls cfl8 Xivio dova tUlv t L'&amp;£if&gt;*&amp;n at tnnmo£i}®m Xti* oi ?*iol‘3c( Jbs^frXX^afrl 'tX’xmJLtr&amp;mfi 0 * 10 ^ an to fni’dc aili it^tf t a9i^i ^oilX^A 3XCY •T&gt;5&lt;2£ tommolJ toe odf mlentnfi^xf n^LuenoC r aliiTifi &amp;iJ lot ilioBt X^taf-roln^o nl fOOtimfsiamn **1 i nol i r«^e t ae^s» to almMrffrtf *1 Ir aroO naiXXn aJ ,8^rX aBiXsXI oxii rf3“Xw ) vix ; n;'» to k!fm&gt;r&gt;-t*tci'&gt; ids tr nctJ-Ir^ce art.: ni . .o?..j t 0orr to ^01^*1008*1 , rXiaf/ to y^- fal ^Xx rrc aoX aooao * ao^XofU , *i^vo'- ; £Xp 48 9 8X8mr(fHY i«Xi snoO Moll’ll -^riX ^nrl: iioct ec XX tie arts $m 0 *?^ if&gt;td&gt; nt 0 c i t tbit 00 $&amp;3 at scf .rr'-liolXtlTii fr^tX^XI c ^- sr i «aoooo Imtsnommc' her. ' tv to t v ..Jnv-Td ' f tvM irr^tor alqri^I «1 oXoidftfl^Y *10 aroO rfelJi^S t dJ ftoofljfofjoxq boslfr^ooo*! ©cf XXori® oor;?^ og^foe *i.t'.ul^ te ol t«lX f&gt;rft rrMtl--? %$ ki&lt;'dttr n sitlv-J e - solJl tci J-xro Xalottif' nrllp^I art; x&lt;- anelolvotc t Jpli-^rroo •JOIU' .t &gt;.1^ balilvoir . f av' 0 tc .*1 -fc xc oi. Ici O Oj I'-'T^ftOO e. 4 'fts , r , »^bi niS »n £v iAn-s &gt;r:'c ^xt: 4 03 d ,: - : X*8&lt;t^A tr $ %». »r loxo &gt;. ^ fd - 3 X 0 ifjoTro’-fff? f&gt;o*x«Xoo^ od XXodo d&amp;X^ *1 &gt;. t to Xa H^o 4 ! dX no 1 3&lt;f.«€f alJbA/ to .Xte^c fedX . . r ., XXod^ »X03»ifex/f. &gt;e-jAi tc r i*Jc;s*xo4&amp; 3vtX tnt't -fc ©dr ••te r r.,f».o^ dsrxi*iP odX *icf aai ^oottlXTi^o f ©;;; tl&amp;nS 90 on' . aoiX x w TcnJi bIn any further communicadon on this subject, please quote no. ^atr^/isv/i and address —to any person by name, but to— &lt;2D The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. i. THE Under-Secretary of State for T^Si'elgn^Ttfftiirs presents his compliments to J&amp;ju ^ y( cdl j&lt;t fiuA+A and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith copju? of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, i 0 y* &gt; im • Reference to previous correspondence : J..0. jEiXtu; Mo ■ fr cfy ^ (U?3i 1.0. &lt;Wtt/No.R Description of Enclosure. &gt;7 Name and Date. Subject. t KildUo 14 1) &gt; 0 u.o 6130 15588(4)Telegram (en clalr) to Mr. Stonehewer-Bird (Addis Ababa.) Foreign Office June 8th, 1958. 6 p.m. No. 52. *: % #;*•**$*•. ^ si • Hi My telegram No. 2u of 1957 [surrender of British extraterritorial jurisdiction in ithiopie]. Italian Government have been approached regarding formal abolition of British extraterritorial jurisdiction in Ethiopia and have suggested, inter alia , that cases which, on the 1st July 1959, may still be pending before the British Consular Courts snail be transferred to Italian jurisdiction in the condition in which they are at the time. I am inclined to agree to Italian suggestion fnd therefore to consent to the closure of our Courts on the 1st July 1959 at the latest. Do you concur? W;i HNO DISTRIBUTION, Decode. D. R. No, 78. Mr. Stonehewer Bird, (Addis Ababa). 16th June, 1938. 5.00 p.m. 16th June, 1958. 9.30 a.m. 17th June, 1938. (R). 0 : 0 : 0 : 0:0 Your telegram No. 52. I see no objection to proposed closure of Consular Court. Acting Consul Harrar also agrees. In both courts number of pending cases should be very few. Assurance will no doubt be obtained against reopening of cases previously disposed of. In a different category are cases before the Mixed Court, which have been closed since the Italian occupation. Some 25 are outstanding at Harrar and many more here. On the other hand many parties both British and Ethiopian have disappeared. In the past year no single interested British subject has approached me regarding a Mixed Court case. But should parties wish to pursue such cases they should presumably do so before Italian Courts. I have no knowledge about the disposal of archives etc. of the Mixed Court. Addressed to Foreign Office telegram No. 78 June 16th; repeated to Harrar telegram No. 20.t 1938 | . i ■ IM |„|„ W M „,| ,4-T No. 115 FOREIGN OFFICE, S.W.l. (J 2411/158/1) 21st Jime, 1938 Sir With reference to your telegram No. 78 of the 16th June, I am directed by Viscount Halifax to transmit herewith a copy of his despatch No. 475 of the 28th March last to His Majesty’s Ambassador at Home, together with a copy of Lord Perth’s despatch No. 504 of the 25th May and a letter to the Colonial Office of the 10th June last, on the subject of the surrender of British extra-territorial jurisdiction in Ethiopia. 2. I am to enquire whether you would desire to suggest any alteration to the terms of the provision in Article 1(c) of the British draft Heads of Agreement enclosed in the despatch No. 475 to Lord Perth regarding the recognition and enforcement of judgments and decisions previously given in cases where British interests were concerned in the Special (Mixed) Court of Ethiopia, and whether you have any other observations to make on the matter generally. I am, Sir Your obedient Servant W. Stonehewer-Bird, Esq., O.B.E., etc . 9 etc., etc., Addis AbabaNo. 475. FOREIGN OFFICE, S.W.l. 28th March, 1938. (R 2541/25/22) My Lord, I have received and read with interest Your 'ZooS', Lordship's despatch Ho. 249 (1 /155/58) of the 10th March describing your interview of the 8th March with the Italian Minister for Foreign affairs, in which you opened with Count Ciano conversations on all matters outstanding between His Majesty's Government in the United Kingdom and the Italian Government. 2. I observe from paragraph lb of this despatch that when you mentioned to Count Ciano the question of the surrender of extra-territorial jurisdiction in Ethiopia as one of those which would require to be dealt with after Italian sovereignty had been recognised, Count Ciano replied that he assumed extra-territoriality would legally cease with the recognition of sovereignty* You should take an early opportunity of informing Count Ciano that I agree that British extra-territoriality in Etiiiopia should be abolished, but that in my view this should be done by agreement, and that there are certain matters requiring settlement which should be dealt with in the agreement. (These matters were briefly referred to in Annex 9 to Part IV of the. Instructions transmitted to/ His Excellency The Right Honourable The Earl of Perth, G.C.M.G., C.3., etc*, etc., etc. Rome.to you in my despatch l T o, 2)7 of the 4th March) The most convenient method of concluding an agreement with the Italian Government on this subject would appear to be by exchange of notes, and in this connexion I enclose the draft of a note, covering Heads of agreement regarding the matters to be settled, which it is proposed should be addressed by Your Lordship to Count Ciano when the appropriate time arrives, namely on tiie day when recognition of Italian sovereignty over Etniopia is formally accorded. I think that these texts should be submitted to the Italian Government as soon as possible and chat tney should be discussed as part of the present conversations, since they deal with a question which arises because of the proposed recognition of Italian sovereignty, though it will be convenient that they snould not be included as one of tae instruments covered by the proces verbal but should be a separate exchange of notes which will come into force at trie same time. *.s there may be some technical points arising out of the discussion of the drafts it is desirable that discussion should begin as soon as possible. 4. I am sending a copy of this despatch to His Majesty’s ambassadors at Paris and Cairo. I am, with great truth and respect* My Lord, Your Excellency’s obedient Servant* (For the Secretary of State) &lt; b.) e. M. B. INGRAM,continue to ezerolee thie extra-territorial Jurisdiction; but they consider that there are eertaln natters with regard to Ita teralnatlon whleh should be settled by agreeaent with the Italian Oevernaent. flic arrangeasnte which Hla wajsety # Oovernaent oonelder should be aade In this connexion are set eut la the annex to this note, and J have the honour, under Instructions free ay Oovernaent, to enquire whether the Italian Ooveroaent are In agreeaent with Its terse.n m judgment of those tribunals 0 Judgments and decisions previously given in cases where British subjects and British protected persons or British companies are concerned by the former special court of Ethiopia will be recognised and enforced in the same manner® Copies of the records of the British Consular Courts in Ethiopia will be supplied on request to the Italian authorities if they are required by them in connexion with any subsequent case,, 2» (a) British subjects and British protected oersons of native African origin or orginatlng from the Arabian paninauia wiU toa aubjeot to tht sama tribunals in Sthlopla as Italian colonial sub loots.paragraph, who are Moslems*. (h) Other British subjects and Britidi protected persons shall he subject in Ethiopia to the same tribunals as Italian citizens*, in matters of statut personr -•, the law of the British territory or of the territory under His Majesty’s protection from which they originate shall be applied by the tribunals in Ethiopia to the British subjects and British protected persons referred to in this paragraph# (c) por the purposes of the interpretation of paragraphs (a) and (b) *&gt;V* -2\ (d) The tribunals in Ethiopia shall he open to British subjects P British protected —1 persons and British companies on the same conditions as to Italian citizens, Italian colonial subjects or Italian companies as the case may be and they shall enjoy the same guarantees for the protection of person and property^ 3 0 British subjects and British protected persons shall not perform in Ethiopia in any form of military service voluntary or compulsory. They shall not be compelled to furnish money or service in lieu of military service.conferred cn any British subject or British protected person in Ethiopia other than with his consent given after attaining the age of 21 years. (b) Nothing in the preceding paragraph of this article affects the right of the Italian Government to confer Italian nationality on women married to Italian citizens or colonial subjects or on persons born in Ethiopia after the date of this agreement. 5. British consular officers in Ethiopia shall enjoy treatment and privileges not less favourable than those accorded to British consular officers in Italy or to -consular officers of any third Power in Ethiopia. They shall have the right to visit in prison any British subjects or British protected persons who are underof His Majecty the King of Great Britain Ireland and the British Dominions beyond the seasp Emperor of India shall remain to he regulated by arrangements to he ooneluded aub se que n tly 0 7c For the purposes of this arrangement; (i) the expression ’'British protected ’’person' means a person enjoying BritishI aft directed by secretary liecDonald to refer to your letter iSo. J.4577/8/1 of HiC 3bth December 1? st, regarding the proposed surrender of British Consular jurisdiction in Ethiopia, ana to request you to inform the Secietar^ of State for Foreign fffuirs that he has no observations to offer on the terms of the drtift note from the Deri of ferth to Count Ciano and the ^eeds of agreement annexed thereto. Copies of this letter ere being sent to the Colonial Office and Indie Office. I am. Sir, four most obedient Servant,Jt is requested that in any further communi cation on this subject the under-mentioned letter and number may be quoted, and the reply addressed to — The Under Secretary of State for India, Political Department, India Office, London, S.W. 1 . P- Z. 439/38 4113 3 FEB 1938 INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL, LONDON, S.W. 1. Is t February, 1938 *&gt;2 FFB1938 Sir, With reference to your letter of the 30th December, No. J.4577/8/1, relative to the proposed surrender of British Consular jurisdiction in Ethiopia, I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to state, for the information of the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, that, subject to the insertion (to which it is understood there is no objection) of the words 'or of the territory under His Majesty’s protection' after the words 'British territory' in paragraph 2(b) of the annexure, he concurs in the terms of the draft note which it is suggested might in the circumstances stated in your letter be addressed by His Majesty’s Ambassador at Rome to the Italian Minister for Foreign Affairs. I aifr&gt;^3ir. Your 'bfc^dient Servant, fUe LslQvl. 'flic CSgd.) J. P, GUBSON 'fit!CLOSURE IN WEEKLY LETTS# No. - 6 i 0 FEB W38 rom £-:c:’.'.tary, wlitical am&gt; iJECRLT DEPT. INDIA OFFICEDear Gibson, Thank you for your letter No.PZ.8451/37 of the 18th January about the surrender of British consular jurisdiction in Abyssinia. We have no objection to your second proposal for the amendment of the phrase in paragraph 2(b) of the annexure to the draft note enclosed in our letter of the 30th December, i.e. the insertion after the words ’’British territory” of the words ”or of the territory ’’under His Majesty’s protection”, although we do not think it is strictly necessary. We would prefer this amendment rather than the alternative one suggested. I am venturing to send copies of this letter and of yours of the 18th January to Bigg at the Colonial Office and Cockram at the Dominions Office. IT' t AI am directed 'by Mr. Secretary Eden to invite © reference to my letter No. J 3302/8/1 of the 9th August last to the Under-Secretary of State for the Colonies, a copy of which was forwarded in the Foreign Office letter of the 10th August last regarding the proposed surrender of British Consular jurisdiction in Ethiopia. 2. The Secretary of State is of the opinion that the most convenient procedure by which such surrender might be effected would be an exchange of notes between His Majesty*s Ambassador at Rome and the Italian Minister for Foreign Affairs to which the Heads of Agreement already agreed upon interdepartmentally might be annexed. I am accordingly to enclose for any observations which The Marquess of Zetland may have to offer, the draft of such a note from the Earl of Perth to Count Ciano, annexing a copy of the Heads of Agreement in question. A note from Count Ciano in reply, stating that the Italian Government were in agreement with the terms of the annex to the note from Lord Perth, would be considered as constituting an agreement in the terms of the annex in question between His Majesty*s Government in the United Kingdom and the Italian Government. 3. Mr. Eden, however, desires to defer any approach to the Italian Government in this matter pending the/ \5eeklt lh ••Prcm: The Pari of Perth. To: The Italian Minister for Foreign Affairs. territorial jurisdiction should not continue 7 when Ethiopia is under Italian administration. Under the new conditions. His Majesty*e Government have no desire to continue to exercise this extra-territorial jurisdiction; Your Excellency, As the Italian Government will be aware, 1 ’ - ’ ■ v- .. .. -•• • ■ ' ■ ,v. . under the previous regime in Ethiopia His ' * ■ ’ \.i , V* * •! Majesty's Government in the United Kingdom by agreement with the Ethiopian Government and by custom, have exercised extra-territorial jurisdiction in Ethiopia over British subjects and British protected persons, as well as over the n; tionals of certain third Powers who did not possess Consulates in Ethiopia. His Majesty’s Government have noted t’^e view of the Italian Government that this extra- 3ut they consider that there are certain matters/matters with regard to its termination which should he settled by agreement with the Italian Government• The arrangements which His Majesty’s Government consider should be made in this connexion are set out in the annex to this note, and I have the honour, under instructions from my Government, to enquire whether the Italian Government are in agreement with its terms1 COPY. (J 3855/8/1) 1. (a) His Majesty*s Government in the United Kingdom renounce all claim to the exercise in Ethiopia of extra territorial jurisdiction. (b) The British Consular Courts will not entertain any new cases. Pending cases already commenced may be terminated including the hearing of any appeals from decisions in first instance. In order to enable the British Consular Courts to finish these cases as soon as possible, the Italian authorities will lend their assistance if necessary to the British Consular 1 Courts in securing the attendance of witness or parties, etc. As soon as the pending cases and any appeals therefrom are completed the Ethiopia Order in Council 1934 will be repealed, and the British Consular Courts in Ethiopia closed. (c) Judgment and decisions given by the British Consular Courts in Ethiopia will be recognised by the Italian tribunals in Ethiopia as having the force of res judicata and be capable of execution in the same manner as a judgment of those tribunals Judgments and decisions previously given in cases where British subjects and British protected persons or British companies are concerned by the former special court of Ethiopia will be recognised and enforced in the same manner. Copies of the records of the British Consular Courts in Ethiopia will be supplied on request to the Italian authorities if they are required by them in connexion with any subsequent case. 2. (a) British subjects and British protected persons of native African origin or originating from the Arabian peninsula will be subject to the same tribunals in Ethiopia as Italian colonial subjects. In matters of statut personnel Moslem law shall/shall he applied hy the trib nals of Ethiopia to British subjects and British protected persons referred to in this paragraph who are Moslems. (b) Other British subjects and British protected persons shall be subject in Ethiopia to the same tribunals as Italian £ citizens. In matters of states personnel the law of the British territory i rom which they originate shall be applied by the tribunals in Ethiopia to the British subjects and British protected persons referred to in this paragraph. (c) For the purposes of the interpretation of paragraphs (a) and (b) above, (i) a person shall not be deemed to originate Ironi a territory of which he is not a native although he may have been born there; (ii) status personnel shall be deemed to include all questions relating to (l) marriage and the proprietary relations between husband and wife, (2) the guardianship of minors and maintenance of children, (3) legitimacy, (4) inheritance including wills, (5) capacity. (d) The tribunals in Ethiopia shall be open to British cubjects, British protected persons and British companies on the same conditions as to Italian citizens, Italian colonia]. subjects or Italian companies as the case may be and they shall enjoy the same guarantees for the protection of person and property. 3. British subjects and British protected persons shall not perform in Ethiopia in any form of military service voluntary or compulsory. They shall not be compelled to furnish money or service in lieu of military service. 4* (a) The status of an Italian citizen or of an Italian colonial subject shall not be conferred on any British subject or British protected person in Ethiopia other than with his consent given after attaining the age of 21 years. (b) Nothing in the preceding paragraph of this article affects/(ii)/ affects the right of the Italian Government to confer Italian nationality on women married to Italian citizens or colonial subjects or on persons born in Ethiopia after the date of this agreement. 5. British consular officers in Ethiopia shall enjoy treatment and privileges not less favourable than those accorded to British consular officers in Italy or to consular officers of any third Power in Ethiopia. They shall have the right to visit in prison any British subjects or British protected persons who are under arrest or in prison prior to sentence being passed upon them. Communications from British subjects and British protected persons to British Consular officers will be forwarded to them. 6. Question of extradition between Ethiopia and territories under the sovereignty, protection, suzerainty or mandate of His Majesty the King of Great Britain, Ireland and the British Dominions beyond the seas, Emperor of India shall remain to be regulated by arrangements to be concluded subsequently 7. For the purposes of this arrangement:* (i) the expression ’’British protected person” means a person enjoying British protection by virtue of his connexion with a territory under the protection, suzerainty or mandate of His Majesty the King of Great Britain, Ireland and the British Dominions beyond the seas, Emperor of India. In addition the four persons whose names are set out in the annex hereto shall possess the status of a British protected person together with their wives and, while still minors, their children. This status will not extend to their children after these reach the age of majority.X u&amp; directed by Mr. Secretary Orasby Qore to aCKnowledge the receipt of your letter Ho.J.3302/8/1 of the 9th August, with which waa forwarded a copy of the revised draft heads of agreement regarding the proposed surrender of British consular Jurisdiction in Ethiopia, and to request you to inform Mr. Secretary iSden that he concurs in the revised text in its present fora, i.e* including tne further amendments detailed in Mr.Laabert's semi-official letter to Mr. Lee of the 17th August. 2. It is assumed that the Secretary of btate will be Kept informed of any negotiations wnich may taKe place with the Italian Government on this subject. I am, 8ir, Your most obedient servant, THE UKDEfat 8EGRKTAKY OF STATS, FOREIGN OFFICE.FOhiilOT OKKTCJ., B.W.l. j &gt; , ’/. Attest, 1V&gt;S'-. I C, I CJ / ‘iould you pi ease refer to our official letter Ko. J &amp; 5 CB, 8 1 of the 9th August about the aurren&amp;er of British Consular juriedletIon In KthloplaV our* attention has been drawn to the fact that th« text of the draft heads of agreement encloaed in that letter does not provide for a email alteration which Becitett and the lomlnlona Office repreeentatlvef; (cookram and, I think, llxon), aubee uently to the Intordepartaental meeting oi the B* rd February laet, agreed ou^ht to be made to Article 7 (H)# to the effect that, for the words 'under the law of any part 'of the doralnlone of Hie Majesty eto. M should be aubatltuted the werde 'under the law of any of the 'territories of HU tajesty etc.' Beckett i« away at F*Gt. bee, Kaq. Colonial Office.at the woaent and X myself do not exactly knov why thte elteration was agreed upon, but I understand that heclett was eapliatic that it ou^ht to he aade. (X think that one reetion wat; to make it quite certain that the Article in question would not apply to the Pmminiona)* feould you therefore kindly make the mecemaary amendment in the text eiKsio^ed in our letter of the 9th August* I am sending a copy of this letter to Coekram at the Dominlona Office and to tombold at the India office.,i55) Copy* (j 5*08/8/1). X. (a) Hia Majeaty , o Gov«pnm«nt In th« anitod Kingdom ranounw ell claim to the exorciao in Kthiopia of oxtorritorial j upi»1 let ion* (p) The British Consular Court* will not entertain &amp;ny ne* cases. Pen^ln^ caaea already eommeneed ay be terminated inoluding the hearing of any appeal* fro?* deciaiona in first instance. In order to enable the British Consular Courts to finish these cases a* so m as possible, the Italian authorities will lend their assistance if necessary to the British Consular Courts in securing the attendance of witness or parties, etc. As soon as the pending cases and any appeals ther'efrom are completed the Ethiopia Order in Council 1934 will be repealed, and the British Consular Courts in Ethiopia closed. (e) Judgment and decisions given by the British Consular Courts in Ethiopia will be recognised by the Italian tribunals in Ethiopia aa having the force of res Indicate and be capable of exec it ion in the same manner as a Judgment of those tribunals. Judgments and decisions previo ialy given in cases where Bri'iah s.ib1eets and British protected persona or British companies she concerned by the former special court of Ethiopia will be recognised and enforced in t e same manner. Copies of the records of the British Consular Courts in Kthiopia will be supplied on request, to the Italian authorities if they are required by them in connexion with any subsequent case. 2. (a) British aub ecta and British protected persona of native Afrie n origin or originating 'rom the Arabian peninsula will be subject to the same tribunals in 'thiopia as Italian colonial subjects. In matters of stotut personnel Moslem lav shall/shall be applied by the tribunals of Ethiopia to hrltl*fc subjects and British protected persons referred to In this paragraph r&lt;ho are Moslems* (b) OthBritish subjects and British protected persons shall be subject in Ethiopia to the aam tribunals as Italian cltlsens* In matters of a tatut personnel the law of the Britiah territory from which they originate shall be applied by the tribunals in Ethiopia to the British subjects and British protected persons referred to in this paragraph. (c) For the purposes of the interpretation of paragraphs (a) and (b) above, (i) a person shall not be deemed to originate from a territory of which he is not a native although he may have been born there; (ii) statut personnel shall be deemed to include all questions relating to (1) marriage and the proprietary relations between husband and wife, (9) the guardianship of minors and maintenance of children, (3) legitimacy, (4) inheritance Including wills, (h) capacity. (d) The tribunals in Ethiopia shall be op*?n to British sub eels, British protected persons and British companies on the same conditions as to Italian citizens, Italian colonial subjects or Italian companies as the case may be and they shall enjoy the same guarantees for the protection of person and property. 3. British subjects and British protected persons shall not perform In Ethiopia in any form of military service voluntary or compulsory. They shall not be comoelled to famish money or service in lieu of military service. 4. (a) The status of an Italian citizen or of an Italian colonial subject shall not be conferred on &amp;ny British subject or British protected person in Ethiopia oth^&gt;r than with his consent given aftsir sttainin r the age of 91 years. (b) Nothing in the preceding paragraph of this article affects/fcffecte th« right of the Itell&amp;n Ooyernment to confer Itellan nationality on *‘Oinen r»arrie« to Italian eltlsene or colonial •uhjeota or on persona born in ’thiopia after the date of this agreeraent. 5* Brltleh consular officer* in Ethiopia shall enjoy treat?r«nt and priTilegea not laaa favourable than those accorded to hrlti h consular officers in Italy or to consular officers oi any third Power in Ethiopia. r hey shall hare the right to visit in prison any British subjects or British protected persons who are under arrest or in prison prior to sentence being pas ed upon thera. noTnmunioationa from British subjects and British protected persons to British Consular officers will be forwarded to them. 6* Questions of extradition between SthiOftia and territories under the sovereignty, protection, suzerainty or mandate of His Majesty the King of Great Britain, Ireland and the British Dominions beyond the seas, K&amp;peror of India shall remain to be regulated by arrangements to be concluded subsequently. 7. For the purposes of thia arrangementj (i) the expreesion ^British protected peraon* :&gt;ieans a person enjoying British protection by virtue of his connexion with a territory under the protection, suzerainty or mandate of His Majesty the King of Great Britain, Ireland and the British Dominions beyond the seas, ^peror of India. In addition the four persons whose names are set out in the annex hereto shall possess the status of a British protected person together *ith their wives and, while still minors, their children. This status will not extend to their children after these reach the age of majority.'ll (11) H Brlti«h compuny** man* any corporate body Incorporated un-lar tha law of any part of tha dominions of His Majaaty the King of Great Britain, Ireland and the Irltieh Dominions beyond the seas, mpesror of India or of any territory under hie protection* suzerainty or mandate* i&gt;OFFICE OF THE HIGH CG/ 1 MISSIONER FOR CANADA, D T' ) • • - f CANADA HOUSE, (31 1 | LONDON, S. W. 1. r - .. -7 J June 17, 1937. s_&gt; / i Dear MacLeod, With regard to Telegram Circular 31.B.8 concerning extra-territorial rights in Abyssinia, I have now received a note from Dr.Skelton, Under-Secretary of State for External Affairs, confirming my earlier message to the effect that the Canadian Government had no observations to offer on the proposed agreement. Yours sincerely, (sgd) U B. PEARSON. J.R.S. MacLeod, Esq., Dominions Office,Your telegram of tine 14th April Circular 51 H og 33 Extra territorial rights in Abyssinia. * overnnent in the Union of ooutli Africa do not think it necessary to signify their concurrence in any iorna]. manner in regard to abrogating privileges unti.*. now &gt;,.joyed by Uritisli subjects in 3tliiopia. »e have no oh;) ec tion to nak e &lt;» % i : -•IN nfeXfcO ubje Communications on this should be addressed to— The Under-Secretary of S^ ate, Dominions Office, Downing Street, London, S.W. 1, and the following number quoted:— * Jr » a 672 j Subject 2,0. 6r owing numoer fit?]It o : J&amp;CL •/tfai/axcaJ’ ■j / V\b&lt; Reference to previous correspondence: Letter ,^ Cr_ the Dominions Office of the - from - s? Transmitted by direction of the Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs. A copy has also been sent to the Dominions Office, Downing Street, 9 (] m * 193 V /, (R5953) Wt 32346/3586 20,000(4) 2/36 H &amp; Sp Op 640TELEGRAM HEW 2EALAHD From the Government of New ZealajuA© Lated 19th April 3 1937c Received 10-9am 19th April s 1937« No* 48© Confidential* yourtelegram of the 14th April Circular l&lt;;\\ B« No«38 lonfidentiala Sbstra territorial rights in Ahyesinia* Hie Majesty*s Government in New Zeale.nd are grateful for the information contained in the telegram hut have not observations to offer on the proposed agreement*... 251 9 7 I CIRCUL^ TELEGRAM To the Governments of Canada s Commonwealth of Australia p New Zealand, Union of South Africa and the Irish Free State (t&gt;y « bag). (Sent 6 p 0 Eio , 14th April, 1937*) Circular B. No*38, Confi&amp;entialo ?«£y Confidential Circular despatch E* No. 62 of 2nd November, 1935. Extraterritorial rights in Abyssinia. His Majesty’s Government in the United Kingdom have under consideration the position, under the Italian regime in Abyssinia, of the British Consular Courts set up under the Ethiopia Order in Council 1934&lt;. The Order in Council and the courts in question constitute the machinery of the extraterritorial Jurisdiction hitherto secured for British subjects and protected persons in Ethiopia. Now* however 6 that Italian civil and criminal law and Jurisdiction have been introduced, the need for protecting British subjects and protected persons from the effects of Ethiopian la?/ no longer obtaine. Since the Italian occupation of Addis Ababa in Hay last, British Consular Courts have found it increasingly difficult to function, and have in fact been on almost continuous vacation, partly owing to the Italian attitude that extraterritorial rights no longer continue to exist. Moreover, extraterritorial jurisdiction at present depends not on any British-Ethiopian Treaty but on the provisions of the Franco-Ethiopian Treaty of 1908 the benefit of which has been enjoyed by custom only, and which is not regarded by His Majesty’s Government in the United Kingdom as belonging to that class of Treaty whose provisions are inherited by the new overeign in default of agreement to that effect* i n tiethe Italian authorities will not agree to the continued exercise of such jurisdiction in Ethiopia* In all the circumstances His Majesty’s Government In the United Kingdom propose to repeal the Ethiopian Order in Council 1934» subject to satisfactory arrangemente with the Italian authorities in regard to the few cases pending In the British Consular Courts, and certain other matters, and to enter into an agreement with the Italian authorities for the surrender of British consular jurisdiction in Ethiopia, and the closing of the British Consular Courts- The following are the matters which His Majesty’s Government in the United Kingdom consider should be covered in the proposed agreement, 1, (a) Hia Majesty’s Government In the United Kingdom renounce all claim to the exercise in Ethiopia of extraterritorial jurisdiction* (b) The British Consular Courts will not entertain any new cases. (c) Judgments and decisions given by the British Consular Courts in Ethiopia will be recognised by the Italian tribunals in Ethiopia as having the force of res judicata and be capable of execution in the same manner as a judgment of those tribunals. Judgments and decisions previously given in cases where British subjects and British protected persons or British Companie s are concerned by the former Special Court of Ethiopia will be recognised and enforced in the same manner. 2. (a) British subjects and British protected persons of native African origin or originating from the Arabian peninsula will be subject to the same tribunals in Ethiopia as Italian colonial subjects. (b) Other British subjects and British protected persons shall be subject in Ethiopia to the same tribunals as Italian citizens. (c) The tribunals in Ethiopia sha^l be open to BritishBritish subjects, British protected persons and British Companies (to be defined as in article 5 (2) of enclosure to my despatch Circular B No,29 of 11th March) on the same conditions as to Italian citizens, Italian colonial subjects or Italian Companies as the case may be and they shall enjoy the same guarantee for the protection of person and property. 3. British subjects and British protected persons shall not perform in Ethiopia any form of military service voluntary or compulsory. They shall not be compelled to furnish money or service in lieu of military service, 4* (a) The status of an Italian citizen or of an Italian colonial subject shall not be conferred on any British subject or British -protected person in Ethiopia other than v/ith his consent given after attaining the age of 21 years. (b) Nothing in the preceding paragraph of thie article affects the rights of the Italian Government to confer Italian nationality on women married to Italian citizens or colonial subjects or on persons born in Ethiopia after the date of this agreement. 5, British consular officers in Ethiopia shall enjoy treatment and privileges not less favourable than those accorded to British consular officers in Italy or to consular officers of any third power in Ethiopia. They shall have the right to visit in prison any British subjects or British protected persons who are under arrest or in prison prior to sentence being passed upon them. Communications from British subjects and British protected persons to British consular officers will be forwarded to them. 6. Questions of extradition between Ethiopia and territories under the sovereignty p protection, suzerainty or mandate of His Majesty the King of Great Britain, Ireland and the British Dominions beyond the Seas, Emperor of India, shall remain to be regulated by arrangements to be concluded subsequentlysubsequently. As there is no question of the relinquishment of rights enjoyed 'by British subjects under anjr previous treaty His Majesty’s Governments in the Dominions may not think it necessary to signify their concurrence in any formal manner in the abrogation of the privileges previously accorded to British subjects in Ethiopia (see in this connection paragraph 6 of my Circular despatch B r jpo29 of 11th March). I should be glad to be advised at a very early date whether His Majesty’s Governments in the Dominions have any observations to offer on the proposed agreementoForeign Office. S.W.l. 26th February 1937..^ \d\ With referenc e to ^Office letter I^o.J 640/B/l oJ the lltn ^eoruary, I am directed by Mr. Secretary Eden to transmit herewith a copy of the draft heads of agreement for the surrender of British consular jurisdiction in Ethiopia, which has been drawn up as a result of the interdepartmental meeting held on this subject at the Foreign Office on the 23rd February last. 2. Mr. Eden understands that steps win now be taken to obtain the concurrence of the various Dominion Governments concerned in the terms of the enclosed draft. On being informed by the Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs this concurrence has been obtained, a further letter .ill be sent to the India Office on the subject. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, The Under-Secretary of State, India Office. IN^AIR No. 9 irl MAR 1937 FROM StCR&amp;l.'-Y, POLITICAL AND SECRET DEPT. INDIA QFFWf880 / 8 / 1 ) J :, ■/ 13 5 3 i©3: / 1. (a) His Majesty 1 s'Government in the United Kingdom renounce all claim to the exercise in Ethiopia of exterritorial jurisdiction, (b) The British Consular Courts will not entertain any new cases. Pending cases already commenced may be terminated in cluding the hearing of any appeals from decisions in first instance. In order to enable the British Consular Courts to finish these cases as soon as possible, the Italian authorities will l£nd their assistance if necessary to the British Consular Courts in securing the attendance of witness or parties, etc. As soon as the pending cases are completed the Ethiopia Order in Council 1934 will be repealed, and the British Consular Courts in Ethiopia closed. (c) Judgments and decisions given by the British Consular Courts in Ethiopia will be recognised by the Italian tribunals in Ethiopia as having the force of res judicata and be capable of execution in the same manner as a judgment of those tribunals. Judgments and decisions previously given in cases where British subjects and British protected persons or British companies are concerned by the former special court of Ethiopia will be recognised and enforced in the same manner. Copies of the records of the British Consular Courts in Ethiopia will be supplied on request to the Italian authorities if they are required by them in connexion with any subsequent case. 2. (a) British subjects and British protected persons of native African origin or originating from the Arabian peninsula. 7peninsula will 'be subject to the same tribunals in Ethiopia as Italian colonial subjects. In matters of statut personne l L'oslem law shall be applied by the tribunals of Ethiopia to British subjects and British protected persons referred to in this paragraph who are Moslems. (b) Other British subjects and British protected persons shall be subject in Ethiopia to the same tribunals as Italian citizens. In matters of statu t personnel the law of the British territory from which they originate shall be applied by the tribunals in Ethiopia to the British subjects and British protected persons referred to in this paragraph. (c) For the purposes of the interpretation of paragraphs (a) and (b) above, (i) a person shall not be deemed to originate from a territory of which he is not a native although he may have been born there; (ii) s tatut personnel shall be deemed to include all questions relating to (l) marriage and the proprietary relations between husband and wife, (2) the guardianship of minors and maintenance of children, (3) legitimacy, (4) inheritance including wills, (5) capacity. (d) 'Fhe tribunals in Ethiopia shall be open to British sub jects, British protected persons and British companies on the same conditions as to Italian citizens, Italian colonial subjects or Italian companies as the case may be and they shall enjoy the same guarantees for the protection of person and property. 3. British subjects and British protected persons shall not perform in Ethiopia in any form of military service voluntaryor compulsory. They shall not he compelled to furnish money or service in lieu of military service. 4. (a) The status of an Italian citizen or of an Italian colonial subject shall not be conferred on any British subject or British protected person in Ethiopia other than with his consent given after attaining the age of 21 years. (b) Nothing in the preceding paragraph of this article affects the right of the Italian Government to confer Italian nationality on women married to Italian citizens or colonial subjects or on persons born in Ethiopia after the date of this agreement. 5. British consular officers in Ethiopia shall enjoy treat ment and privileges not less favourable than those accorded to British consular officers in Italy or to consular officers of any third Power in Ethiopia. They shall have the right to visit in prison any British subjects or British protected persons who are under arrest or in prison prior to sentence being passed upon them. Communications from British subjects and British protected persons to British Consular officers will be forwarded to them. 6. Questions of extradition between Ethiopia and territories under the sovereignty, protection, suzerainty or mandate of His Majesty the King of Great Britain, Ireland and the British Dominions beyond the seas, Emperor of India shall remain to be regulated by arrangements to be concluded subsequently. 7. For the purposes of this arrangement: (i) the expression 'British protected person' means a person enjoying British protection by virtue of his connexion with a territory under the protection, suzerainty or mandate of Fj_s Majesty/ FIMajesty the King of Great Britain, Ireland and the British Dominions beyond the seas, Emperor of India. (ii) 'British company' means any corporate body incorporated under the law of any part of the dominions of His Majesty the King of Great Britain, Ireland and the British Dominions beyond the seas, Emperor of India or of any territory under his protection, suzerainty or mandate.&amp; V fv/l 1 I attended a meeting at the Foreign Office on 23rd February, at which representatives of the Foreign Office, Colonial Office and Dominions Office were present 3 besides myself. The meeting reached agreement on the heads of agreement enclosed in the Foreign Office letter of 11th February, subject to the minor amendments shown in T.vC'iO.fc. o paragraphs 2(a) and 5/ I do not think that we need consult the Government of India further in the matter. The Colonial Office representatives expressed doubt regarding one effect of paragraph 2 J whereby Indian merchants domiciled at Aden will be treated as Italian citizens, while Arab merchants domiciled at Aden will be treated as Italian colonial subjects. On the other hand, any attempt to remove this differentiation would result in a differentiation between Indians domiciled at Aden and Indians domiciled elsewhere. It would also create substantial drafting difficulties. I said that if the Harney Office pressed the point we should probably have to oppose them, and I do not think that we will hear any more about it. ^ aw% V ©O ^ ^ Dvv^xviaVw^ 1. (a) His Majesty*s (joveriiment ia the United Kingdom renomice all claim to the exercise in Ethiopia of exterritorial jurisdiction, (b) The British Consular Courts will not entertain any new cases. Pending cases already commenced may be terminated in cluding the hearing of any appeals from decisions in first instance. In order to enable the British Consular Courts to finish these cases as soon as possible, the Italian authorities will lend their assistance if necessary to the British Consular Courts in securing the attendance of witness or parties, etc. As soon as the pending cases are completed the Ethiopia Order in Council 1934 will be repealed, and the British Consular Courts in Ithiopia closed. (c) Judgments and decisions given by the British Consular Courts in Uthiopia will be recognised by the Italian tribunals in Ethiopia as having the force of res .indicata and be capable of execution in the same manner as a judgment of t iose tribunals. Judgments and decisions previously given in cases where British subjects and British protected persons or British companies are concerned by the former special court of Ethiopia will be recognised and enforced in the same manner. Copies of the records of the British Consular Courts in Ethiopia will be supplied on request to the Italian authorities if they are required by them in connexion with any subsequent case. 2. (a) British subjects and British protected persons of natirve- African ta? Arabian including Moslem British protected persons belonging to Palestine and Transjordan,will be subject to....2. to the same tribunals in Ethiopia as Italian colonial subjects. In matters of statut personnel Moslem law shall be applied oy the tribunals of Ethiopia to British subjects and. British pro tected persons referred to in this paragraph vino are Moslems. (b) Other British subjects and British protected persons shall be subject in Ethiopia to the same tribunals as Italian citizens. In matters of statut personnel the law of the British territory from which they originate shall be applied oy the tribunals in Ethiopia to the British subjects and nritish protected persons referred to in this paragraph. (c) For the purposes of the interpretation of paragraphs (a) and (b) above, (i) a person shall not be deemed to originate from a territory of which he is not a native although he may have oeen born there; (ii) stat ut perso nnel shall be deemed to include all questions relating to (I) marriage and the proprietary relations between husband and wife, (2) the guardianship of minors and maintenance of children, (3) legitimacy, (4) inheritance in cluding wills, (h) capacity. (d) The tribunals in Ethiopia shall be open to British sub jects, British protected persons and British companies on the same conditions as to Italian citizens, Italian colonial subjects or Italian companies as the case may be and they shall enjoy the same guarantees for the protection of person and property. 3. ^British subjects and British protected persons shall not perform in Ethiopia in any form of military service voluntary or compulsory. They shall not be compelled to furnish money or service in lieu of military service. 4. (a) The status of an Italian citizen or of an Italian colonial subject shall not be conferred on any British subject5. * or British protected person in Ethiopia other than with his consent given after attaining the age of 21 years. (b) Nothing in the preceding paragraph oi this article affects the right of the Italian Government to confer Italian nationality on women married to Italian citizens or colonial subjects or on persons born in Ethiopia after the date of this, agreement. a. British consular olticers in Ethiopia shall enjoy treat-* ment and privileges not less favourable than those accorded to British consular olficers in Italy or to consular officers of fO an y third Power in Ethiopia. ' The y s h a H have the right to visit in prison any British bo _ Questions of extradition between Ethiopia and territoles under the sovereignty, protection, suzerainty or mandate of His kajesty the King of Great Britain, Ireland and the British Dominions beyond the seas, Emperor of India shall remain to be regulated by arrangements to be concluded subsequently. 7. For the purposes of this arrangement: (i) the expression 'British protected person' means a person en joying British protection by virtue of his connexion with a territory under the protection, suzerainty or mandate of His Majesty the King of Great Britain, Ireland and the British Dominions beyond the seas, Emperor of India. (ii) British company' means any corporate body incorporated under the law of any part of the dominions of His Majesty the King of Grectt Britain, Ireland and the British Dominions beyond the seas, Emperor of India or of any territory under his protection, suzerainty or mandate./T Flag C. The following are the answers to the Secretary of State’s two questions: (a) The effect of the Foreign Office draft of 24th December was to provide that British subjects originating from the Union of South Africa (whether white, Indian or negroes) should be subject in Ethiopia to the same Courts as Italian citizens (and not, like African and Arabian natives, to the same Courts as Italian Colonial subjects)* The Dominions Office, however, took the view in their letter of 31st December that South African negroes should be treated like other African natives, and^in the new draft Heads of Agreement received in Foreign Office letter of 11th February^the Union of South Africa is no longer excluded from para.2(a). Under it British South African subjects of non-African or Arabian origin (including Indians) would be treated like Italian citizens. (b) I have discussed this question with Sir H. Pearson Where any tribunal has to adjudicate upon a point of foreign law, what that law is has to be proved to it as a question of fact. Thus in cases in which an Italian court had to apply Hindu personal law it would presumably take expert evidence regarding what was the law on the point at issue; similarly7t*i the case -of Moslem law, although Italians have no doubt had some experience in Eritrea, Libya and Somaliland of the application of Moslem personal law. O •v'V'l ( f . L.3J^ oS\\\ 'Cc&gt;\JL» &gt;D.tA OWV. Y&amp;&gt; - x#' oV ‘■- I /a,.. ,kAII tter i^FFHt957 ‘ T Epy. IMDj^ Ci-Fi’cJE With reference to Foreign Office letter No.J 128/8/1 of the 22nd January, I am directed by Viscount Halifax to transmit herewith a revised draft, which has been prepared in this department, of the Heads of Agreement for the surrender of British Consular jurisdiction in Ethiopia. 2. It appears to Viscount Halifax that the most convenient procedure would be for this draft to be discussed at an early date at an inter-departmental meeting, and a suggestion in this sense will shortly be made to the India Office. 3. A similar letter is being addressed to the Colonial Office and Dominions Office. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant,(J £40/8/1) 1* (a) H*M*Ctov«rnincait In the United Kingdom renounce all claim to the exercise in Kthiopia of exterritorial Jurisdiction. (h) The British Consular Courts will not entertain any new cases. Pending cases alre idy com menced may be terminated ineluding the hearing of any appeals from decisions in first instance. In order to enable the British Consular Courts to finish these cases a© soon as possible* the Italian authorities trill lend their assiatance if necessary to the British Consular Courts in securing the attendance of witness or parties, etc. As soon as the pending case© are completed the Kthiopia Order in Council 1934 will be repealed, and the British consular Court© in Kthiopia closed. (c) Judgments and decisions given by the British Consular Courts in Ethiopia will be recognised by the Italian tribunals in Ethiopia as having the force of roo judicata and be capable of execution in the same manner as a Judgment of those tribunals. Judgments and decision© previously given in oaees where British subjects and British protected persons or British companies are concerned by the fomaer special court of Bthlopia will be recognised and enforced in the same manner. Copies of the records of the British Consular Courts in Kthiopia will be supplied on request to the Italian authorities if they are required by them in connexion with any subsequent case. 2. (a) British subjects and British protected persons of native African or Arabian origin, Including Moslem British protected persons belonging to Palestine and Trane Jordan, will be subject to/to the same tribunals in Ethiopia ae Italian oolonial subjects. In matters of atatut personnel Modem law shall be applied by the tribunals of Kthiopia to British subjects €md British protected persona referred to in this paragraph who are Moslems* (b) Other British subjects and British protected persona shall be subject in Ethiopia to the same tribunals aa Italian citiaens* In matters of statat personnel the law of the British territory from which they originate shall be applied by the tribunals in Ethiopia to the British subjects and British protected persons referred to in this paragraph* (c) For the purpose© of the interpretation of paragraphs (a) and (b) above, (1) a person shall not be deemed to originate from a territory of which he ia not a native although he may have been born there? (il) fttatut pers onnel shall be deemed to include all questions relating to (1) marriage and the proprietary relations between husband and wife, (2) the guardianship of minors and maintenance of chi dron, (S) legitimacy, (4) inheritance including wills, (5) capacity. (d) The tribunal© in Ethiopia shall be open to British subjects, British protected persons and British companies on the same conditions a© to Italian eitiaenB, Italian colonial subjects or Italian companies as the case may be and they shall enjoy the same guarantees for the protection of person and property* 3* (British subjects and British protected persons shall not perform in Ethiopia In any form of military service voluntary or compulsory. They shall not be corbelled to furnish money or service in lieu of military service* 4, (a) The status of an Italian citiaen or of an Italian colonial subject shall not be conferred on any British subject or British/British px»otect€Hl person In Ethiopia other than with his consent given after attaining the age of 31 years. (h) Nothing in the preceding paragraph of this article affecto the right of the Italian Government to confer Italian nationality on women married to Italian citizens or colonial subjects or on persons born in Ethiopia after the date of this agreement. 5. British consular officers In Ethiopia shall enjoy treatment and privileges not less favourable than those accorded to British consular officer© in Italy or to consular officers of any third Power In Ethiopia. they shall have the right to visit In prison any British subjects or British protected x^rsons who are under arrest or undergoing punishment# 6# v.uestlona of extradition between Ethiopia and territories under the sovereignty* protection* suseralnty or mandate of H.M. the King of Great Britain, Ireland and the British Dominions beyond the «$eas* Emperor of India shall remain to be regulated by arrange lents to be concluded subsequently. 7# For the purposes of this arrangement* (I) the expression ’British protected person* means a person enjoying British protection by virtue of his connexion with a territory under the protection, suzerainty or mandate of H.M. the King of Great Britain, Ireland and the British Dominions beyond the seas* Kiaperor of India* (II) ^British eomoany* tmexw any corporate body incorporated under the law of any part of the dominion® of H#M. the Kinr of Great Britain* Ireland and the British Dominion© beyond the sees* Emperor &lt;f India or of any territory under hia protection, suzerainty or mandate#Minute Paper. P.Z. 725/37. Department. \S^ Extra-territorial jurisdiction for British subjects and British protected persons in Ethiopia has always been claimed effectively under Article 7 of the Franco-Ethiopian Treaty of 1908 (flag ’S' below) The Italians do not admit that extra-territorial rights continue in the present circumstances and the Foreign Office do not consider that the 1908 Treaty is binding upon them in default of an Agreement to that effect. The Foreign Office therefore propose formally to surrender British Consular jurisdiction and to repeal the Ethiopian Order-in-Council of 1934^which provided the machinery for the exercise of that jurisdiction, subject to a statutory arrangement with the Italians on certain matters. Draft Heads of Agreement have Vn* f O- been drawn upj^to i\^serve as a basis for discussion (flag 'O' below). * The Legal Adviser points out that it is desirable to aim at securing for British Indian and Indian States subjects (1) the same treatment as will be accorded to Europeans, i.e. treatment as Italian citizens and not as Italian Colonial subjects, and (2) the application of the law of their domicile in matters of statut personn el^ wQC c.«JXcu.’^ . (marriage, inheritance, wills, etc.) Provision for these two matters is made in the draft Head 2(b) ? but it is evident that their importance will require to be stressed,partly because the Dominions Office have suggested a redraft which tiham, and partly because His Majesty's Charge 7 d'Affaires at Addis Ababa has pointed out that the Italians aim at’V I 2 . maintaining a sharp distinction between white and coloured people (flag ’D 1 ). Failure to secure these objects will be likely to lead to agitation in India and it is important to ensure that failure to secure them, if any, should be laid at the door of the Italian administration* There seem to be no other points to suggest for agreement. The Order^in-Council of 193$ contains provisions for the registration of British Indian subjects in Ethiopia, but this procedure can be continued after extra-territorial jurisdiction has been surrendered under standing Consular instructions* The Government of India concur in the proposal to repeal the Order and consider the draft Heads of Agreement to be suitable• A draft letter to the Foreign Office on the above lines is submitted for approval. 14 • • 3,7 Legal Adviser: Secretary, P. and J. Department: Do you concur in the attached draft? \ r e.(^A^ ^*0 tC«.e*Vr ^ \&lt;U. Cs\,\ vi. a y&gt;vX-ct&gt;^ to '-avct LVT cteAj- uy V 0 a\A^VS ^ a^KC. ^tCsX eW-aJct, ^ . L Cx^vs. (SI PTHTl LINDIA OFFICE, P.Z. 725/37. WHITFHALL, S.W.l 22nd February, 1937. Sir, 1 am directed by the Secretary of State for India to refer to your letter of 11th February, No.J.640/8/1, and connected correspondence regarding the proposed surrender of British Consular jurisdiction in Ethiopia. 2. Lord Zetland concurs m the proposal that, subject to satisfactory arrangements being made with the Italian Government, the Ethiopia Order-m-Council, 1934, should be repealed, and considers the draft Heads of Agreement forwarded with your letter of 24th December to be generally suitable. 3. His Lordship attaches importance to securing that British Indian subjects and the subjects of Indian States shall be accorded under the new regime the same treatment as Italian citizens. He observes that His Majesty's Charge d'Affaires at Addis Ababa indicated in paragraph 8 of his telegram No.744 of 10th December that there may be difficulty in securing this object, but he suggests that it should be strongly pressed, in order that if His Majesty’s Government are unfortunately unable to obtain their desiderata in this respect, the onus should be squarely placed upon the Italian Government. 4. It is noted that a revised draft of the proposed Heads of Agreement has been prepared, and v/ill be discussed at an interdepartmental meeting. The Under Secretary of State, Foreign office, S.W.l 5 ./■pi M \M v /• Draft Paper. Department. The Under Secretary of State Fore Office Igll V-L-LX^, S. W. 1. 5 :J 19c 5000 10.;j6 2 F£BJ957 Sir, I am directed hy the Secretary of State for India to refer to your letter 11 IxA/* 6vo//// of 24th ■Doocmbor , No. J« &amp;966/dQ28/-l, and connected correspondence regarding the proposed surrender of British Consular jurisdiction in Ethiopia. 2. Lord Zetland concurs in the proposal that^ subject to satisfactory arrangements being made with the Italian Government^ the Ethiopia Order-in-Council, 1934, should be repealed, and considers the draft Heads of Agreement forwarded with your letter of 24th December to be generally suitable. 3. His Lordship attaches importance to securing that British Indian subjects and the subjects of Indian States shall be accorded under the new regime the same treatment as Italian citizens. He observes that His Majesty's Charge d'Affaires at Addis Ababa suggeot^d in paragraph 8 of his telegram No.744 of 10th December that there may be difficulty in securing this object, but he suggests that it should be strongly pressed j in order that if H.M.G. are unfortunately unable to obtain their desiderata^ the onus should be squarely placed upon the Italian Government. lr f! $V H^&amp;- Lordshrip ^gtr^consiaers,-it ^ 4^ ^ ^ 4 ^ ^a 4. H jr^-Lordsb-ip- ^ajrgtr~conside r s^-Tt desirable to preserve the application of the law applicable to Hindus, Moslems, etc. of Indian domicie in matters of statut personnel , and in this connection supports the suggestions in paragraph 6 of Mr. Heberts’ telegram No.14 of 8th Japtfary. 5. A copy of this letter is being sent to the Colonial Office and the Dominions Office.[X.B.-Thxsi, an ORIGINAL menage sent ly AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, j aWe txped'tion as if it had been telegraphed. To save t me and to obviate formalities it xs drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department.} 0 y v • No.F. 10-2/37. Dated —^* M ** 1# ' _ t~hs&gt; New Delhi* ine January 7^57 , Reference telegram No,^4 da ted 5th January 1937.- Repeal of Cthiopean Order in Council - The ..Government of India have no ^ objection to the proposed repeal of the Order in Council subject to a satisfactory agreement being concluded with Italian authorities. They consider the draft Heads of Agreement enclosed with Foreign Office letter NoJ.8966/4028/1, dated 24th December 1936 to be suitable* The issue of the above has v been authorised, 'additional Deputy Secretary to the Government of India. P 3 L S£Pt. | 3 OdANlSSZ INDIA OFFICE'Y In any further communication on this subject, please quote No. J 126/8 A and address— not to any person by name but to— “ The Under-Secretary of State,’' Foreign Office, London, S.W.l. Foreign Office. S.W.l. 22nd January, 1937. Sir, i I am directed 'by Mr. Secretary Eden to transmit herewith copy of a telegram from His Majesty’s Charge d T Affaires at Addis Ababa, in which Mr. Roberts offers his observations upon the draft Heads of Agreement, a copy of which was enclosed in Foreign Office letter No. J 8966/4028/1 of the 24th December, 1936, for the surrender of British Consular jurisdiction in Ethiopia. I am also to enclose copies of Mr. Roberts* telegrams Nos. 744 and 745 of the 9th December last. 2. In view of the extensive nature of Mr. Roberts* suggestions, Mr. Eden considers that it would be advisable not to proceed with the matter until all the departments concerned have furnished their observations on the text enclosed in the letter from this department under reference, and until the Second Legal Adviser (who has been dealing with the subject) returns early next month from Cairo. 3. Similar letters are being addressed to the Colonial Office and Dominions Office. I am. Sir, Your obedient Servant, 7Ml . i Pollov/inc are my observations for v/hich I am in great measure indebted to His Majesty’s Consul at Addis Ababa on text in your telegram No* 593** 1. In first place drafting in paragraph l(b) does not correctly state the position as regards outstanding civil cases* So far as civil suits are concerned, 'position is not that they could be finished immediately, but that there appears to be no objection to conceding jurisdiction in all of them without safeguards, while retention of jurisdiction in the only case of importance may be complicated by the fact that the plaintiff is a French firm; in the matter of appeal the draft also fails incidentally to mention administrative cases* 2* I would still recommend a clear sweep of capitulations if the Italian Government will, in respect of the only civil cases in v/hich safeguards are desirable, namely outstanding insolvent and administrative cases, agree to proposals ade in paragraph 4 of my telegram No* 744, . 4 4 nrW together with following additional safeguards. With a view M km to tf* ■ V ■ •••to continuity of procedure and with the object of liquidating cases transferred to Italian jurisdiction in accordance with principles of informal agreement, v/hich have governed their liquidation, up to now reached, assurances should be called for that special care will be taken in liquidation draft finally to give effect to any recommendations, juridical/ or otherwise, made in statements implied in (b) of paragraph V 4 of my telegram No. 744. The Italians should accept in each case the /? onus/ of furnishing to Consulate-General a report upon it, presuming finally liquidation becomes due, showing in detail manner in which such liquidation is to be effected and that liquidation shall not become effective until report has been endorsed by the Consulate-General. Assuming that these safeguards which are deemed to interpret ,r suit able arrangements” contemplated in third sentence of your paragraph l(b), are accepted and that capitulations are abolished entirely, I suggest the following amendments in the text of your telegram: (a) add at the beginning of first sentence of paragraph 1(a) the words ’‘subject to provisions mentioned below” and (b) omitting paragraph l(b) altogether. In its place should, I suggest, be substituted an enumeration of the safeguards mentioned in paragraph 4 of my telegram No. 744 with the two additional safeguards suggested above, or a reference to them if it is preferred to include them in an appendix or separate protocol. 3. If these safeguards can only be secured in modified form or even if they are not accepted at all, I would still prefer to surrender jurisdiction except in respectrespect of certain insolvent and administrative cases of the nature described in amendment to Article 1(b) of Order in Council referred to below. There should not be more than half a dozen cases in all. To do otherwise has in my opinion the disadvantage of delaying indefinitely the closing of Consular Courts and repeal of Order in Council (though this latter must in any case await hearing of an appeal in Court of Appeal for Eastern Africa due next June unless repealing instrument makes special provision for it) and of leaving complications (e.g. subsidiary actions in Italian Courts that might or might not be feasible) the existence of which is not counter-balanced by compensations. Assuming consular jurisdiction is maintained for completion of insolvent and administrative cases, limited to those of the nature described below, I would propose the following amendments in text of your telegram: Article l(a), to avoid misunderstanding I suggest adding at the beginning of first sentence words ’’subject to exceptions referred to below” and at the beginning of second sentence the words ”on one or other mentioned in section b of this Article”. Article 1(b) section to read: ’’there are no criminal cases pending at present time and no civil cases in which His Majesty’s Government in the United Kingdom are not prepared to surrender the jurisdiction except certain insolvent and administrative cases that admit of early liquidation or that for their final liquidation involve only matters of routine and distribution of assets in hand”. I would also see no objection, if it wore helpful, to the addition of a sentence to the following effect ”if these cases havehave not been finally liquidated within a reasonable period, His Majesty’s Government will give favourable consideration to any representations on the subject received from the Italian Government in the spirit of present agreement Z? as a? final surrender of capitulatory rights', 4. In Article l(c) I suggest adding at the beginning the words 'Judgment and'. Mention should also be made of special court Judgments and agreed decisions described in paragraph l(b) of my telegram No. 745, which are of importance. 5. Article 2 (a) and (b). Under present drafting Arabs of Palestine and Transjordan would enjoy status superior to those of Arabian peninsula. I suggest adding after 'Arabian peninsula' in section A the words 'or Palestine or Transjordan'. To avoid ambiguity in section B the word 'other' should be repeated before words 'territory under his protection, rule or mandate' and after these words should be added 'and those originating from Union of South Africa'• 6. As regards statut personnel it seems to me open to objection to adopt different standards in section A and section B which has the anomalous effect of confining this provision to Moslems in certain territories and in them only and also ignores similarly located British persons of other religions. I would therefore suggest deleting second sentence of each section and making a separate section which could follow the wording of present second sentence of section B except that the last word should read 'article' instead of 'paragraph'. But I confess that I should prefer/T\ in place of somewhat vague term ’'matters of statut personnel ” (which moreover reads strangly in an English f text) that it may be the more precise phrase of Article 68 of Order in Council of December 2nd viz. ’’matters relating to marriage, inheritance, wills, family relations, and other matters involving religious law or custom”. 7. Article 2(c). The v/ords ’’native of that territory” appear ambiguous, their sense being shown only by words which follow; their most natural sense would surely be ’’person born in that territory”. I suggest as an alternative ’’person belonging to one of the native races of that territory” which appears to fit the case of Article 2(a). But applicability of provisions of Article 2(b) is not clear to me and possibly reference to this section should be omitted. Its effect as regards Article 2(a) is presumably that e.g. a white British subject born in Kenya will be treated not as an Italian colonial subject but more favourably as an Italian citizen under Article 2(b). Since however treatment stipulated in latter is the more favourable of the two provisions of article 2(c) would seem to be inapplicable to that section. 8. Article 3. This appears to imply that His Majesty’s Government have no objection to voluntary enrolment. British subjects or protected persons voluntarily enrolled would however in the event of war incur penalties under Foreign Enlistment Act. In addition there is more immediate danger that (as has recently happened with members of local levies) they might desert owing to dissatisfaction with their pay or conditions of service and be fusilladed en masse, . Ity ^jS\ \JLxX It would if possilDle I submit be preferable to agree that they shall not be eligible for any form of military service# 9# Article 5 first paragraph. Context suggests that treatment and privileges contemplated are solely those relating to the fulfilment of the duties of consular officers in protecting British subjects and that their personal privileges and immunities are not here envisaged as not being relevant to the subject of agreement. If so this might advantageously be made clear. /2 groups omitted/^s would fall to be defined elsewhere and would I hope include customs franchise as recommended in my despatch No. ^ 202 . 10. Second paragraph. It is I submit important (unless this is held to be contrary to international usage) to stipulate for right to visit British prisoners in their cells in order that Consular officers may satisfy themselves of conditions under which British prisoners are detained. 11. In conclusion I note that you presumably do not consider it appropriate to cover in present agreement subjects mentioned in paragraphs 9 D and E of my telegram No. 745.V «gt* Your telegrams Nos 0 535 and 556. After consultation with His Majesty's Consuls at Addis Ababa and Harrar my views are as follows. (1) Authorized vacation having expired I suggest pending further decision vacation should now be extended until January 1st. (2) Time suggested by you for undertaking negotiations for termination of our extraterritorial rights would appear to be most opportune. (3) Following is reply as regards Addis Ababa to question (A) of your telegram No. 536: there are no criminal cases pending. Of four civil suits pending, three are of no importance in respect of your present enquiry; in the fourth [grp. undec.] no hearings and no interlocutory orders apart from an order setting aside a previous order dismissing the case. So far therefore as these cases are concerned I see no real objection to conceding jurisdiction. (4) There are four outstanding insolvent cases of which three are of importance. Two of these are not due for liquidation for several months and the third is a complicated case that may require much time to wind up. Outstanding administrative cases amount to five. All present certain pecularities militating against early liquidation. As regards both insolvent and administrative cases, I do not see in principle why British interests should be pre judiceda, / A- p^judiced by a cession of jurisdiction provided (A) Italian courts accept and act on preliminary decisions of Consular Court e.g. appointments and orders of official assignees and administra^ tors, (B) an agreement is reached either (1) for presentation to Consular Court by official assignees or administrators of an up to date statement shov/ing position of each case, to include a statement of accounts, such statement to be accepted by Italian courts, if passed by Consular Court, as basis lor any iuture process, or (2) in the absence of an official assignee or administrator, or at the discretion of the Consulate in any particular case (e e g&lt;, in that of a defaulting olticial assignee or administrator) for presentation of such a statement by Consulate to be likewise accepted, (C) subject to statements mentioned under (B) (1) being passed, arrangements are made either (1) for release of official assignees and administrators from further liability if they wish to be relieved of their duties, or (2) subject, I think we should admit, to approval of Italian courts, for their continued functioning under the same terms oi remuneration as before if they wish to continue in office and (D) in one insolvent case in which official assignee has filed an appeal for hearing in court of appeal for East Africa next June, appeal shall go forward and Italian courts be bound by its results (assuming this court of appeal itself wall not consider changes of capitulatory regime affect' its own competence). (5) Position is much the same at Harrar where the only pending cases are three civil suits and three insolvent cases. My general recommendations therefore hold good for that court also. (6) As regards paragraph (b) of your telegram I think it important 7 -important that archives of the Court at both Addis Ababa and Harrar should oe retained at these Consulates for the purpose menGioneo. 'ihere will doubtless be several cases in which reference to archives will be necessary and I should deprecate handing archives over in toto to Italians. (7) As regards paragraph (C) of your telegram I think in respect of personal status v.e should endeavour to secure accept ance of modus operand! stated in second paragraph of Article 68 of Ethiopian Order in Council of 1954 unless this point is already completely covered by Italian colonial legislation or practice (please see Article 5 of decree enclosed in my despatch No. J.55 in^so far as Mohammedans are concerned). Provisions of th&lt;:,t paragraph ere confined to members of non-Christian communities, but presumably the principle is not applicable to Christians at any rate to the same extent. (8) As regards equality of rights (last phrase of your telegram has been received slightly corrupt) Italian attitude will doubtless be governed by their published decrees notably that quoted in my preceding paragraph which makes certain class distinctions as also by such precedents as may have been establish ed in their older colonies. Wnle Europeans and the like will be m harmony with Italian system of justice all others will in criminal cases come in the first instance before the Governor of AddlS AbslDa 0r hls tribunal (see decree), in civil cases however cise pio^eduj.^ which would be applicable to various categories our people io at present somewhat obscure as decree quoted distinguishes between 'Colonial Subjects' (i.e. persons belonging to Libya, Eritrea or Italian Somaliland) and 'Natives' in which it at variance with nationality provisions in Article 28 of decree4. I , RnY ^ [3U vt&gt; ^decree enclosed in Rome despatch N o. 719; and it is not clear to which of these categories British Somalis and members of other races not forei-n to Ethiopia (Article 7 of decree of May 29th) would be assimilated# As regards those who are not classed with Europeans but belong to races foreign to Ethiopia, notably British Arabs or Indians, it would seem that cases in which they are involved would fall to be judged by the G-overnor of Addis Ababa (or presumably of province in question), thus bringing them into a category between that of natives and that of Europeans. While we could not I think in particular claim for British Somali Arc.os etc., treatment diiferent from that accorded to other peiscns of similar race we should, I would suggest, endeavour to establish that (a) persons belonging to British colonies, protectorates and mandated territories (other than white British subjects, who would be treated as Europeans) should be assimilated («'U\ colonial subjects (this is quite probably the present ^ intention); (b) British Indians.also should if possible be assimilated to Europeans (I understand this is at least to some extent the case before the courts in French Somaliland); in view however of sharp distinction which Italians aim at maintaining between white and coloured people this will need to be strongly pressed il success is to be obtained. (d) Other points that occur to me as being for consideration are (a) validity of existing Consular and special court judgments. These should be accepted as executory without necessity of a fresh suit to enforce them# A fortiori there should be no question of reopening before Italian Courts matters already settled by Consular and Special Courts. A case where this is beingbeing attempted has been reported from Harrar, (b) Similar acceptance as regards agreed decisions reached between Abyssinian Government representative and His Majesty’s Consul in pursuance of 1S33 arrangements (Addis Ababa despatch WW^,No. 61 of April 4th) for execution of old judgments. (The decisions establish amounts due in respect of certain defective civil judgments). (c) Prevention or control of enrolment of British subjects in Italian Colonial Army. (d) Extradition matters. (e) In view of recent experiences and different continental conception of criminal procedure, some understanding that favourable consideration shall be given to any Consular application for immediate or early trial of British persons accused of crimes. (f) Better prison arrangements and regulations, and facilities for Consul to reiiew British prisoners in their cells. Present arrangements are lamentable.46668/36 Sir, I directed 8y Secretary Onrisby Gore to aeKnowledge tne receipt of your letter i^o.d966/402c./l of the 24th Ueceiiiber, 1936, coneeruing the proposed surrender of Britisn Coaaulur jurisdiction in iitniopia, anc to request you to inform iir.Secretary ^den that tue draft heads of Agreement forwarded with your letter have been carefully examined in this Department* *''• unueretood that the Secretary of State ior Dominion Affairs nas suggested that certain amendments should be made in paragraph 2(a) (b) and (c) of the draft heads of agreement. Mr.Ormeby Gore agrees generally with the amendments proposed; but further consideration has be^n given, in consultation with the DoalRieiM Office, to the wording of paragraph 2(a)* it is now considered that (having regard particularly to the inm Uh u£L. SAGHKTAaY OK woiuaQa oi^ficd. possiblepossible position of inhabitants of Palestine) it would be preferable if paragraph 2(a) could be amended to read as follows:- 'British subjects and British protected persons of native African origin or being natives of the Arabian peninsular will be subject to the same tribunals in Ethiopia as Italian colonial subjects. In matters of statut personnel Moslem law shall be applied by the tribunals of Ethiopia to British subjects and British protected persons referred to in this paragraph who are Moslems.’ It is understood tnat the Secretary of State for Dominion. Affairs concurs in the proposed revised wording quoted in the preceding sentence. The Secretary of State has no other observations on the draft Heads of Agreement. Steps will be taken in due course to revoke the £ast African Court of Appeal (Amendment) Order-in-Council, 195*, by wnich appellate jurisdiction over Ethiopian Consular Courts was vested inin His Majesty’s Court of Appeal for eastern Africa, inis action would. However, be deferred until the insolvency cases mentioned in para, rapn 1(b) of the draft xieads of Agreement have been concluded, 4, Copies of this letter are being sent to t e India Office and tne tominions Office. 1 am. Sir, Xoav * 108 1 obedient servant. &gt; r :\ » • ; w. f»,ooo aMifiMM I? TCommunications on this subject should be addressed to— The Under-Secretary of State, Dominions Office, Downing Street, London, S.W.l, and the following number quoted :— QQfX^J r Subject: ^ Reference to previous correspondence : Letter the a Office of the U' i; f^G/4-6av &gt; Transmitted by direction of the Secretary of State for Dominion Affairs. C^tXS ! A copy fcaa algrj sent to the $5 JAN &gt;937 political and ^ 8ECRE1 DEPT. INDIA OFFICE tuccor.u \ io. 4 from t Dominions Office, Downing Street, 3; DEC ’935 193 A; (IU006) Wt 19610/3279 20,000(4) 10/34 H &amp; SP Gp 6406109a, 20/7. U H , w v_/ / December, 19.^6. I am directed by Mr. Secretary MacDonald to acknowledge the receipt of your letter J .8966/4C28/1 of the 24th December, on the subject of the proposed surrender of British Consular jurisdiction in Ethiopia. 2. The effect of paragraph 2 of the Heads of Agreement as drafted would apparently be to subject natives of the Union of South Africa to the same tribunals as Italian citizens (unless indeed it was intended to differentiate between the treatment of British subjects originating froa the Union of South /fries who sre n t natives and that of British subjects originating fro® the other Dominions - a distinction which would appear tc be illogical in principle). Mr. MacDonald would therefore prefer that the treatment of natives of the Union of South Africa should be assimilated for the purposes of this Order to that of othor African natives. The amendments S' VHUtfo S&amp;ChfTAiiT OF STATE, FOBEICH OFFICS. j %&gt; amendnients which he would suggest for the purpose are shown in the enclosed draft telegram to Dominion Goirernnients which reproduces in considerable fullness the draft heads of agreement (except paragraphs 2 (aUb) and (c) which have been amended) end I am to enquire whether &gt;‘r. Secretary den concurs in these amendments and also in the draft telegram. 2. A copy of this letter is being sent to the Colonial Office and India Office. I am, Sir, &gt; Tour most obedient servantlai'T EXTRliI*. ^ OTTAYiA KINDLI&amp;K CANBiU^iA COVSI^OhGT^sJi At WELLINGTON P KIMUS PHOTO IA EST-HO DUBLIN Circuler B. No Uj Confidential Circular despatch T5. N’o • 62 of 2nd November, 1975. n, xtreterritorial rights in /'byssinia. His Vcjesty’s Government in the United Kingdom have under consideration the position, under the Itelisn rdgirae in Abyssinia, of the British Consular Courts set up under the Ethiopia Order in Council 1924. The Order in Council and the courts in question constitute the machinery of the extraterritorial jurisdiction hitherto secured for British subjects and protected persons in thiopia. Now, however, that Italian civil and criminal law and jurisdiction have been introduced, the need for protecting British subjects and protected persons from the effects of Ethiopian law no longer obteins. Since the Italian occupation of Addis Ababa in l ay last, British &lt; onaular Courts have found it increasingly difficult to- . - to function, and have in fact been on almost continuous vacation, pertly cwinp to the Italian attitude that extraterri torial rights no longer continue to exist M oreover, the provisions of the Fran co- Ethiopian Treaty of 1908, on which extraterritorial jurisdiction at present depends, are not regarded by His Majesty’s Government in the United Kingdom as belonging to that- class of Treaty the provisions of which are inherited by the new sovereign in default of agreement to that effect, and in any case the Italian authorities will net agree to the continued exercise of such jurisdiction in ’Ethiopia. In all the circumstances His Majesty's Government in the United Kingdom propose to repeal the Ethiopian Order in Council 1934, subject to satisfactory arrange,ente with the Italian authorities in *- &gt;.: '• r-K *•' Hj HH-»r=r*' Foreign Offic S.W.l. 24th Decemher, 1936. r ilEC.'^3b | IrvUv?’ i’»3 28DE3C1sae IND”' OFFICE I am directed by Mr. Secretary Eden to state tnat he has had under consideration for some time the position, under the Italian regime in Ethiopia, of the British Consular Courts which were set up under the Hj uhiopia Order in Council, 1934. 2 - As the Marquis of Zetland will be aware the Order in Council and the Courts in question constitute the machinery of the extraterritorial jurisdiction which has hitherto been secured for British subjects and otected persons in Ethiopia, since it was manifestly impossible for the latter to be subjected to Ethiopian law, and m any case the benefits secured to French citizens under Article 7 of the Franco-Ethiopian (Klobukovsky) Treaty of January 10th, 1908, have always been effectively claimed for British subjects and protected persons also. ■'ith the introduction, however, of the Italian civil and criminal law and jurisdiction into Ethiopia, it was clear that the need for protecting British subjects and protected persons from the effects of Ethiopian law no longer obtained. Since the Italian occupation of Addis Ababa last May, and owing to the attitude of the Italian authorities who do not admit that ex-territorial rights continue in present /circums t ance s, IN^AIFt MAIL LETTER io. 513 The Under-Secretary of State, Office. 28 DFCJ936 ID CEC .E t DEPT. INDIA r nc prcircumstances, the British Consular Courts in Ethiopia have found it increasingly difficult to function and have, in fact, been on almost continuous vacation; and this vacation has now been extended until January 1st, 1937. Moreover, the provisions of the Klobukovsky Treaty upon which extraterritorial jurisdiction at present depend; do not, in Mr. Eden’s opinion, belong to that class of Treaty the provisions of which are inherited by the new sovereign in default of agreement to that effect; and in any case the Italian authorities will certainly not agree to the continued exercise of such jurisdiction in Ethiopia. 3. In these circumstances Mr. Eden has reached the conclusion that the best course would be for the Ethiopian Order in Council, 1934, to be repealed, subject to a satisfactory arrangement being arrived at with the Italian authorities with regard to the cases (which are in fact not numerous) pending in the British Consular Courts, and certain other matters. I am accordingly to transmit the accompanying draft Heads of Agreement for the surrender of British Consular jurisdiction in Ethiopia, and to ask that Mr. Eden may be furnished, at a very early date, with the observations of Lord Zetland thereon. 4. I am to add that the question of the form which the agreement should take is at present reserved and the present draft is prepared with the object of reaching conclusions on the substance of the conditions which His Majesty’s Government should put forward. b * Similar letters are being addressed to the Colonial Office and Dominions Office. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant,•V. Copy. (J 8966/40^8/1) l(V^ ^^VYVtO, (a) H.M. GoYernaent In the United Kingdom renounce all claia to the exercise in Ethiopia of exterritorial jurisdic tion. The Ethiopia Order in Council 1934 will be repealed, and the British Conaular Courts in Ethiopia closed. (b) The British Consular Courts will not entertain any new cases. There are no criminal cases pending at the present tlae and no civil cased which cannot be finished immediately except certain insolvency cases. These insolvency oases may be completed in accordance with the Ethiopia Order in Council Including the recourse by appeal in cases allowed by that order unless suitable arrangements can be made at an earlier date for their completion by the tribunals of Ethiopia. (cj Decisions given by the British Consular Courts in Ethiopia will be recognised by the tribunals in Ethiopia as having the force of res judicata and be capable of execution in the same manner as a judgment of those tribunals. (a) British subjects and British protected persons originat ing from any territory in Africa or the Arabian peninsula# except the Union of &gt;outh Africa, will be subject to the &amp;ame tribunals in Ethiopia as Italian colonial subjects. In matters of statut personnel Moslem law shall be applied by the tribunals of Ethiopia to British subjects and British pro tected persons referred to in this paragraph who are Moslems. (b) British subjects and British protected persons originating from any other territory under the sovereignty of H.M. the King or any territory under Hla proteotlon, suzerainty or mandate, shall be subject in Ethiopia to the same tribunals as Italian citizens. In matters of statut personnel the law of the British territory from which they originate shall be ^tovyuo, t appliedapplied by the tribunal* In Ethiopia to the Brltlah subjects and British protected peraonu referred to In this paragraph. ■“ (c) For the purposes of the Interpretation of paragraphs (a) and (h) above a person shall not be deeaed to 'originate from' a territory when he la not a native of that territory although he may have been born there. (d) The tribunal* in Ethiopia shall be open to British subjects and British protected persons on the same conditions as to Italian citizen* or Italian colonial subjects as the case may be and they shall enjoy the tame guarantees for the protection of person and property. 3 . British subjects and British protected peraone shall not be subject in Ethiopia to any fora of military service or compelled to furnish money or services in lieu of military service. 4. (a) The status of an Italian citizen or of an Italian colonial subject shall not be conferred on any British subject or British protected perton in Ethiopia other than with his consent given after attaining the age of 21 years.. (b) Nothing in the preceding paragraph of this article affects the right of the Italian Government to confer Italian nationality on women married to Italian citizens or colonial subjects or on persons born in Ethiopia after the date of this agreement. 6. British consular officers in Ethiopia shall enjoy treatment and privileges not lea© favourable than those accorded to British consular officers in Italy or to consular officer® of any third power in Ethiopia. They shall have the right to visit in prison any Hrltlsh subjects or British protected persons who are under arrest or undergoing punishment. ' f . Aka</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000602.0x00036e_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/3328</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000602.0x00036e</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/3328</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 25/23 'Orders in Council: Ethiopia: Repeal of the Ethiopian Order in Council, 1934; Surrender of British Consular Jurisdiction'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1936/1945</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-11-29T22:47:48</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">fre</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (374 folios)</extent><extent>The file is arranged in chronological order from the back to the front.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the inside front cover with 1, and terminates at the last folio with 375; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Correspondence, drafts, minute papers, and memoranda concerning the repeal of the Ethiopia Order in Council, 1934. The decision to surrender extra-territorial jurisdiction is discussed following the Italian occupation of Abyssinia. Inter-departmental discussion of the decision and of the text of a provisional agreement with the Italian Government as a form of replacement constitutes the bulk of the file. These exchanges are between officials at the Foreign Office, India Office, Dominions Office, Home Office, and the Government of India, External Affairs Department. Further correspondence is from the British Legation in Addis Ababa, British Embassy in Rome, and officials from the Governments of Canada, Australia, New Zealand, the Union of South Africa, the Irish Free State, Italy, and Ethiopia.Included in the file are documents used for reference purposes, including:A copy of 'Treaty of Friendship and Commerce between Ethiopia and France', 1908 (folios 372-375)Copy of 'Treaty Series No. 31 (1938) - I - Agreement between The United Kingdom and Italy consisting of a Protocol with Annexes and Exchanges of Notes; II - Bon Voisinage Agreement and Exchanges of Notes between The United Kingdom, Egypt and Italy' (folios 120-139).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>British Legation</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Home Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Dominions Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>British Embassy, Rome</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Indian Political Service, External Affairs Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000602.0x00036e#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>