<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000094.0x000094_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T22:09:29.047Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000094.0x000094_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>Or 5593</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000094.0x000094</url><physicalLocation>British Library: Oriental Manuscripts</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>Or 5593</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Kitāb istī‘āb al-wujūh al-mumkinah fī ṣan‘at al-asṭurlābكتاب استيعاب الوجوه الممكنة في صنعة الأسطرلاب  Bīrūnī, Muḥammad ibn Aḥmad بيروني، محمد بن أحمد</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1300/1399</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2013-10-19T00:00:56</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>Codex; ff. ii+89+iii</extent><extent>Material: PaperDimensions: 235 x 135 mm leaf [185 x 120 written]Foliation: Museum foliation in pencil; Arabic numeral foliation in black ink in upper right-hand corners of versosRuling:
                           Misṭarah; 21 lines per page; vertical spacing 10 lines per 10 cmScript: NaskhInk: Black; rubricated headings; tables and diagrams in red and blackBinding: British Museum bindingCondition: f. 3 damaged and some words missing from last two lines; light water damage towards foredge and head, re-inked in placesMarginalia: infrequent marginal corrections and headings added by later hands</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>One of only three recorded copies of an influential treatise on the construction and use of astrolabes by Abū al-Rayḥān Muḥammad ibn Aḥmad al-Bīrūnī (أبو الريحان محمد بن أحمد البيروني, ca 973-1048) containing 122 diagrams, 7 tables and 1 space for a diagram or table left blank and marked بياض صحيح ('correctly blank'; f. 20v).Begins (f. 3v, lines 1-7):بسم الله الرحمن الرحيم رب يسر ولا تعسرالأنفس الصافية ذوات نراع واشتناق إلى تصور الموجودات والإحاطة بها على الإطلاق فلذلك تلتفت إلى ما يزيدها روتفا (!) وبهاوتنبعث إلى ما يكسبها صفًا ونقًا كنفس الشيخ أيده الله التي صفتمن درن الطينة وخلصت عن كرر الطبيعة بل اتحدت بكلية النفوسوأشغلت بالمعتول (!) عن المحسوس فلا يقصد من العلوم إلا ما يكونمعلومه أفضل معلومEnds (89v, lines 5-8):ووصلنا كل واحدة من تلك بالفلس حتى يكون لعروض كثيرة ويكونأحسن في الصورة بل لو ثمٮ (!)الصفيحة باقطار بدل التربيع وفعل به ذلكاحتمل أفأما كثيرة وقاربت أن نعم العروض في العمل إن شاء الله وتمامهذه الآلة تم إنجاز الوعد بما وعد به والوفاء بما صمته بعون الله وتوفيقهThe fore-edge and lower margins of f. 89v contain verses in Persian written by a hand other than that of the main scribe.The diagram on for 83v shows the internal gears of an astrolabe. This diagram (although not this copy of it) is thought to be the earliest depiction of the internal gears of a hand-held device. See Hill, 'Al-Bīrūnī's Mechanical Calendar', 1985.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="personal"><namePart>Muḥammad ibn Aḥmad Bīrūnī</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000094.0x000094#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>