<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000358.0x00028b_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-18T07:53:14.905Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">SELECTIONS FROM THE RECORDS OF THE GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, FOREIGN DEPARTMENT. No. CCL XXIV. : Foreign Department Serial N o. 35. ADMINISTRATION REPORT OF THE PERSIAN GULF POLITICAL RESIDENCY AND MUSCAT POLITICAL AGENCY FOR 1889-90. fubltslwb bt&gt; ^utliDfitn, CALCUTTA: OFFICE OF the superintendent of government printing, india. 1890.CALCUTTA: GOVERNMENT OF INDIA CENTRAL PRINTING OFFICE, 8, HASTINGS' STREET,No. 158. From To C olonel E. C. ROSS, C.S.L, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, and Her Majesty's Consul-General for Fars, W. J. CUNINGHAM, E sq ., C.S., Officiating Secretary to the Government of India, Foreign Department. Bttshiee, the 23rd June 1890, S ie, I have the honour to submit the Annual Administration Report of this Residency for the year 1889-90, arranged as under : part i. —General Summary. Appendix A. —Genealogical Table of Chief Arab Families of Persian Arabistan. B . Table of Eliyat tribes of South-Western and Central Persia. C.—Notes on Cholera in Persia, by Surgeon-Major T. Ffrench Mullen. )5 D.—Meteorological Tables. Part II.— Resume of Muscat Affairs, by Surgeon-Ma^or A. S. G. Jayakar. iii. —Trade Report of Persian Gulf for 1889. Appendix A.—Tabular Statistics. Part IV.— Trade Report of Muscat. Appendix A,— Tabular Statistics. 2. Eequesting to be supplied with tlie usual number of printed copies of this Report. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant. E. C. ROSS, Colonel, Political Besident, Persian Gulf.ADMINISTEATION REPORT OP THE PERSIAN GULF POLITICAL RESIDENCY AND MUSCAT POLITICAL AGENCY tor 1889-90. P ART I.—GENERAL SUMMAEY. 1.—OMAN-MUSCAT STATE. The Annual Report of the Muscat Political Agency for the past year has been prepared by Surgeon-Major A. S. G. Jayakar, and forms Part II of this compilation. It may be convenient to add here that His Highness Seyyid Peysal-bin- Turki was, on the 6th of April 1890, formally recognized as Sultan and ruler of the Muscat State, under orders of the Government of India. 2.—OMAN-PIRATE COAST. During the year, a coalition was formed by the Chiefs of Shargah, Umm- u ! tzi • v.nu-PTT ^ el-Kawain, and Ras-el-Khaimah in opposition to Eas-el-Khaimah Chief, Hameyd-bin- ^ i It n i Abdullah Jowasimi. Abu Dhabi and Debay, and in March the Ras-ei- Khaimah Chief paid a visit to Shargah. The Chief of Ajman called at Shargah at the same time, and, being to a certain extent neutral, was asked to mediate in view to the maintenance of peace between the rival States; this office he, however, declined. In the early part of the year correspondence went on between the Chiefs of TT , TT • n.-. AT, . V Abu Dhabi and Umm-el-Kawain, the former urg- Abduikh ai-bu T h . 16 ' 1116 in ing the latter to join him in an expedition against Shaik Jasim of El-Katr, who, on the other hand, wrote to Ahmed-bm-Abdullah claiming his assistance. This Chief decided to take no side in this quarrel, but later he joined the Shargah coalition against the two southern States. In April 1889, Shaikh Eashid proceeded to El -Bereymi, where he mediated j - v. rv t b k-.i t &gt;* tt j between two factions of the Naeen tnhe and effecte Ajmahn Chief, Rashid-Bm-Hameyd ' ... Ai-Bu-AU. a reconciliation. Shaikh Eashid remained on friendly terms with the Chiefs of the Shargah confederacy, hut from having been asked to mediate between them and their southern neighbours, he appears to have abstained from ac ivc pai quarrel.6 ADMINISTRATION REPORT OF THE PERSIAN GULF POLITICAL In the early part of the year (April 1889), Salim-bin-Sultan, ex-Chief of siiargah ciuef, sakar-din-Khaiid Shai s^ahj oii^anizecl an attack against the place, Jowasimi - which fell through. Subsequently the Chief, Shaikh Sakar, became reconciled to his uncle Salim, and received him into favour and made him his Wazeer. As regards the warfare between Abu Dhabi and El-Katr, the Chief of Shargah decided to remain neutral. In the summer the seeds of a quarrel between Shargah and Debay were sown by raids committed by some Bedouins of the Manaseer tribe who are in some degree dependents of Debay and of Abu Dhabi. In February some camels belonging to Debay were mutilated in Shargah limits, and redress being refused, relations between these two States were broken off. By means of the good offices of the Residency Agent, hostilities were averted and a meeting took place between the rival Chiefs in February, when an agreement was concluded. The quarrel, however, was renewed the follow ing month. On this occasion Abu Dhabi made common cause with Debay, and Shaik Zaeed marched with a force to the assistance of the Debay Chief and encamped at Semeyyah between Abu Dhabi and Debay. The Chief of Debay has latterly allied himself with the cognate Beni Yas Debay chief, Rasheed-bin-Maktoom tribe of whom Shaik Zaeed of Abu Dhabi is head. Ai-Bu.Faiasa. ^ ^ Consequently he has incurred the hostility of Shaikh Jasim of El-Katr, who has forbidden the people of Debay, as well as of Abu Dhabi, to land on the Katr coast, for trade or other purposes. ^ P ers ^ an authorities of Bunder Abbas complained that Persians resid ing at Debay were not kindly treated, and requested that the British Agent might be instructed to protect them. Orders were issued to the Residency Agent to exert his influence with the Oman Chiefs to induce them to treat all classes of persons residing in their territories kindly and justly, so that no cause ot complaint should occur. The border warfare between the Beni Yas Chief and his allies on the one Abu-Dhabi chief, zaeed-bin-KLa. iS ' t ^ 0 ) and Shaikh Jasim on the othor, continues un- leeiah Bern Yas. abated 1^0 u-xi In April Shaikh Zaeed led a force towards El-Katr and advanced to Karah, neai ic 01 ers o 1-Hasa, and there plundered the Bedouins friendly to Jasim ot a number of horses and camels. From Karah the Beni Yas force marched to Hojair, a fort m which a number of the Karah Bedouins had taken shelter, but the place was not invested nor attacked. Shaikh Zaeed decided not to advance to Katr, and returned to Abu Dhabi. Very few lives were lost in this expedition on either side, but the Beni Yas captured a considerable number of camels. Reprisals were of course made, and in June Hameyd -bin-Mana, El-Man- soori, a follower of Shaikh Jasim, led a marauding expedition towards Oman and carried off some camels belonging to the Deroo, and Al-Bu-Shamis tribes, allies of the Beni Yas. Shaikh Jasim also headed an expedition in the summer, but it was unsuc cessful. In August a considerable section of the Al-Morrah tribe bound themselves by compact to act in concert with the Beni Yas against Katr raiders. His Highness Sayid Abdul Aziz, uncle of the Sultan of Muscat, has recently proceeded on a visit to the Chief of Abu Dhabi. It will be observed that the mutual relations of the various «trucial ,, Chiefs were at the close of the year rather unsatisfactory, but all have re spected their engagements to the British Government.-70 r RESIDENCY AND MUSCAT POLITICAL AGENCY FOR 1889-90. The Residency Agent at Shargah has furnished the following estimate of the number of pearl-fishing boats sailing from Pirate Coast ports Ramss .... Ras-el-Kliaimah , Jezirat-el-Za^ab , , , Umm-el-Kawain u • Himriyah .... Ajman .... Shargah, Hijrah, and Khan , Debay and Jumeyra Aba Dhabi and dependencies T otal 10 35 25 55 20 40 350 950 355 1,840 The various Chiefs derive the chief part of tlieir income from taxes levied on the boats and their crews. These taxes are of two kinds called ' Taraz ' and 'Nowb.' The former is a sum varying from four to seven dollars, levied from each individual of the crew and divers of pearl boats. By the ' Nowb ' the Shaikhs receive one-half of the profits of every boat sailing from their ter ritories. Boats proceeding to the Bed Sea fisheries pay one sum varying from 30 to 60 dollars. 3.—EL BAHRAIN. The islands of Bahrain have continued to enjoy tranquillity and pros perity under the rule of Shaikh Eesa-bin-Ali. A number of families of the Naeem and Salateh tribes crossed from El- Katr and have settled in Bahrain. In the last year's report allusion was made to the excavations of Tumuli of the ancient necropolis on Awal Island by Mr. and Mrs. Bent who, it may now he remarked, consider that their researches went to confirm the statements of ancient writers that the Bahrain Islands were the original home of the Phoeni cians. These islands have peculiarities, such as the warm springs and bright running streams, in contrast with the neighbouring arid deserts, which we may easily conceive to have peopled the groves with deities and caused them to be regarded as the ' Holy Islands.' A celebrity of the sort would account for the growth on Awal of the vast necropolis referred to. 4.—EL-KATR. The feud between Shaikh Jasim -bin-Mohammed, Bin Thani, and the Chief of Abu Dhabi, has continued unabated, and the former's eagerness to strike a blow at his enemy led him to despatch some boats, with armed men and muni tions of war to El-Sila, a place without the recognized boundary of Katr. Shaikh Jasim, when called upon to reply to this charge, attempted to justi fy bis action by asserting the place to be within his jurisdiction. Under orders of the Government of India, Jasim was warned that a repetition of similar irregularities would lead to serious consequences. The Turkish garrison of El-Bidaa was, during the year, reinforced, and it is understood that the eommandant has orders to repel any attack on the town hy Shaikh Jasim's enemies, but not to operate beyond four hours march from the walls. Shaikh Jasim has the title of ' Kaim -Makam ' or Local Governor of Katr, on the part of the Turkish Government, and is supposed to be under tbe orders of the Muteserrif of Hasa. In July the latter official, Akit Pasha, visited El- JJidaa in a Turkish gunboat, and the first interview between His a.xcellcucy8 ADMINISTRATION REPORT OF THE PERSIAN GULF POLITICAL and Shaikh Jasim took place in the house of Mohammed Bin Abdul Wahhah. Jasim came, attended by a force of about six hundred armed men on foot, and sixty or seventy horsemen and camel riders, many of whom carried Henry- Martini rifles, which were ready loaded. The Muteserrif had only his personal attendants with him, the Turkish soldiers being within their fort. A second interview of a more private description occurred at Shaikh Jasim's residence, and on this occasion the Muteserrif informed Jasim that Katr being Turkish territory His Excellency desired to introduce a proper administrative system, and establish a custom house. Jasim opposed these measures, and threatened to resign his office of Kaim Makam if the Muteserrif persisted, on which the latter asked for a written resignation, which Jasim at once furnished. It appears that Jasim complained of the want of support he received from the Turkish Government, especially with reference to his coercion on certain occasions by British authority. He also handed over to the Muteserrif all the correspondence with the British authorities. Attempts of the Turkish authorities to establish quarantine at El-Bidaa were opposed and prevented by Shaikh Jasim. In October, messengers from ' Ibn Rashid, ' Emir of Shammer, arrived in Katr, bearing a present for Shaikh Jasim, consisting of horses, mares, and camels. It appeared that Ibn Rashid's object was to induce Jasim to operate against the Almorrah Bedouins, whose conduct has displeased him. The principal raids and counter raids between Katr and Oman have been mentioned under the previous, heading. There seemed reason to believe that Jasim had become somewhat weary of the strife and would welcome mediation for peace. The Chief of Bahrain was moved to sound him, but the result was unfavourable. One piracy attended by loss of life was committed off the Katr coast on a Bahrain boat, the culprits being of the Beni Hajir, residing in Katr. Shaikh Jasim recovered the property plundered, but the robbers 0 were not arrested. The Chief of Bahrain has not considered it expedient to press the matter further. 5.—NEJD AND EL-HASA. The Emir Mohammed ' Ibn Rashid' exercises paramount authority over all Nejd. In the autumn Abdallah-bin-Eeysal was permitted to return to Riadh, but later it was reported that both Abdallah and his brother, Abdur Rahman, had died at Riadh. Needs not to be said what impression this created. The Muteserrif or Governor of El-Hasa, Akif Pasha, is energetic in his administration, and his active measures have greatly repressed robberies of caravans by the Bedouin tribes. A notorious freebooter known as Ibn Rezey- zan was surprised and put to death between Ojair and El-Hasa. Several robberies of boats lying in Kateef Harbour occurred durjnff the year, for which, of course, no redress could be obtained. 6.—FARS AND PERSIAN COAST. The Government of Pars has remained in the hands of His Royal Hio-hness the Motemid-ed-Dowlah. with Haji Naseer-el-Mulk as his ' Pishkar.' D Shahzadah Nowzer Mirza having resigned the Government of Dashti and Dashtistan, Mohammed Hasan Khan Sirteep was appointed to the vaeant post. Those districts were, during several months, in a disturbed state, owing to cuds between local Chiefs, notably those of Borazjan and Angali.9 His Excellency the Saad-ul-Mulk has continued to hold the government of the Persian Gulf Ports and Islands, including Jask. Chevalier Keun de Hoogerwoerd, Consul-General for the Netherlands at Bushire, proceeded to join a new appointment at Bankok in May, his acting successor being Mr. W. Groeneweg, of the firm of Hotz and Son. M. Piat, Vice-Consul foi i ranee at Pushire, proceeded on leave to Prance, leaving the Vice-Consulate in the charge of Haji Mirza Hoosain, the Dragoman. The Imperial Bank of Persia having effected an arrangement for the with drawal of the new Oriental Bank Corporation branches from Persia, has opened a branch in Bushire, and the new Oriental Bank Corporation has closed busi ness there. Mirza Ismail was appointed Deputy Governor of Lingah, and Mirza Hadi, of Bunder Abbas. A detachment of 50 soldiers was stationed at Lingah. Major E. Bruce, Bengal Cavalry, arrived for the purpose of buying mules for Government and succeeded in obtaining over 800 animals, mostly pur chased at Ispahan and Tehran. In the summer epidemic cholera having appeared at Bussorah andMoham- merah, some cases were imported into Bushire by Captain Hughes, of the Bombay and Persian Steam Navigation Company's steamer Mobile, before quarantine could be established. Owing to the exertions of Surgeon-Major T. Pfrench Mullen aided by Mr. Apothecary Rodrigues, the disease was pre vented from spreading, and subsequently the Persian authorities, advised and assisted b^ Dr. Mullen and subordinates, established quarantine which saved Bushire 5 and probably most of Persia, from the epidemic. An interesting memorandum, prepared by Dr. Mullen on this and previous outbreaks of cholera in Persia, &amp;c., will be appended to this report. 7.—PERSIAN ARABISTAN. The steps taken during the year towards the establishment of the commer cial route from Mohammerah to Central and Northern Persia have still been chiefly of a preliminary nature. Nevertheless, the progress made, thoughts anticipated, slow, is real. The position of the English commercial agents in Arabistan and Shushter is improved, and the good relations they have suc ceeded in establishing are highly creditable to themselves and advantageous for trade. At Mohammerah the Governor of Arahistar. the Nizam-es-Saltanah, has huilt a Government house, a landing place, and a public bath. At Ahwaz (Bunder Nasiri) buildings are in course of construction, and at Shushter a large amount was spent in repairing the great bridge of Valenen, but unfortunately the arches which bad b-cn repaired were swept away by a flood of the river (Shateyr). A Company has now been formed in London which will undertake the construction of roads from Ahwaz to Barujird, and Tehran, w., i a oranc o Ispahan, and a tramway is to he made from Bunder Nasin to A:,waz. The stern wheel steamer Shmhm has been presented to His Majesty the Shah by Messrs. Lynch and is bow running on the Upper Karun. Theie is every reason to expect that merchandize in considerable quantities will soon be sent by this route. Two cases of piracy on British Indian vessels occurred in the Shat-el-Arah river, and all attempts to trace the perpetrators failet . Mohammerah suffered severely from epidemic cholera, which also visited Arabistan generally, and Shushter. ^10 ADMINISTRATION REPORT OF THE PERSIAN GULF POLITICAL 8.—PERSIAN BALUCHISTAN. During the absence from Persia of His Majesty the Shall last summer, a serious insurrection occurred in this province. It appears to have arisen from the cruelty and misconduct of the Governor of Baluchistan, Abul Path Khan, who seized several Baluch Chiefs in a trea cherous manner and offered outrage to their women. For some time the chief town, Bampur, was in the hands of the insurgents, and the Persian Governor besieged in a neighbouring fort. Acting on information conveyed through Her Majesty's Legation, the Amin-ul-Mulk, who had been left in charge of affairs at Tehran, ordered the Persian Governor of Baluchistan to be deposed, and Sirteep Zeyn-el-Abedeen was appointed to relieve him. Every opportunity was taken by the British officials to urge the disaffected Baluch Chiefs to avoid committing themselves to revolt, and eventually quiet was restored. The petty Governments are still in a somewhat unsettled condition, and it is difficult to ascertain what persons are really in authority in the various dis- iricts. About Jaslv, disturbances have been created by certain relations of Meer Abdul Nubbee, who is still a prisoner in the hands of the Persian authorities at Bushire. 9.—SLAVE TRAFFIC. A considerable number of fresh African slaves yearly reach the northern coasts of Arabia, both by sea and by overland routes. During the past vear a lew Africans were liberated from slavery through the exertion of our Native Agents. Three were brought by sea to Umm-el-Kawain, and being demanded, were handed over to the Residency Agent by the Chief and liberated. , ,, At r . StlarSa i 1 ' a Nak,10(la attempted to carry two female Africans in slaverv to the Persian Coast but the Agent interfered, and eventually both women were sent to Muscat and liberated. In September information was received that seven fresh African slaves had )een imported to Lmgah from Soor. Every effort was made to get hold of these persons and have the importer punished, but the action and attitude of the Per sian officials completely frustrated all attempts. Curiously enough the dallal SISKSSSISS.* 4 ^ -'« His Excellency the Saad-ul-Mulk subsequently issued a notification to the effect that persons engaging in slave traffic will be punished, and the farmer of authorities. 48 ^ ^^ 03368 0f im P 01 - tation to 'Otice of the In October the Residency Agent at Bahrain reported that persons, returned from the Mecca pilgrimage, had brought a larger number of slaves than usual some by sea and some by land. This was brought to the notice of the CMef of Bahrain, who acted loyally and traced 15 slaves, 8 males and 7 females, who had b X^ u fj the^ht a h 1!eSidenCy Steamer was despatched to Jialnam toi these Atncans, who were manumitted at Bushire. 10.—ROYAL NAVY VESSELS. Her Majesty s ships Kingfisher and Sphinx were stationed in tlie Gulf Com- manders Lindsay and Boldero, each in turn being senior naval officer 'on the service' Her MaTestvVsh^Jf r nd yisited the Gulf on 8 P eeial .vice. ® Majesty s ship Manner, Commander Arbuthnot (senior officer) joined the station at the end of March 1890. 'mcei;.suininer, 1 ^ 3 trej. residency and muscat political agency for 1889-90. 11 11.—POLITICAL APPOINTMENTS. On 28tli December Lieutenant W. Stratton relieved Captain P. J. Melvili as First Assistant. On 31st March Lieutenant Stratton lianded over charge of duties of First Assistant to Mr. G. Lucas. March. —Mr. G. Lucas, Uncovenanted Assistant to the Political Resident, was appointed to be Extra Assistant to the Political Resident with effect from the 26th December 1889. March. —Mr J. P. Sequeira, Head Clerk of the Office of the Political A^ent at Muscat, was appointed to be Uncovenanted Assistant to the Political Resident and Treasury Officer with effect from the 26th December 1889. 12.—OBSERVATORY. Meteorological observations have been recorded at the Bushire Observatory with regularity, and the results are appended in tabular form. The summer was again trying, and again the rarity of severe gales in the autumn and winter of 1889-90 was remarkable. Bushire, The 11th June 1890. E. C. ROSS, Colonel, 'Political Resident. lol it • i lili i •; ;|: B 1 —RESIDENCY AND MUSCAT POLITICAL AGENCY FOE 1889.90. APPENDIX C TO PART I. CHOLERA IN PERSIA. 1821. The epidemic of 1817 starting from Lower Bengal reached Bombay in August . n 0Ut a£resl1 there in the year under notice. Cholera routes Pers,a. On the 8th Jnly 1821 it was prevalent at Muscat and in the same month at Bahrain. Moved up to Shiraz from the coast On the 20th August it appeared at Bunder Abbas and on most probably. ^ August at ^ stacked the Persian army before Bagdad in thp cmma Passed up the Euphrates and Tigris. A - / ^re x.a &amp; aaa m tne same month, August, and broke out also in several places in Turkey in Asia in this and next month, September. Probably entered by Urumia first 1823. —In July cholera was epidemic in the Tabriz Dis ' ter by K'™'' 1 '''- trict and cu to Resht. Later in the year it was pretty geue- rally spread over all Persia. —The epidemic covered all Persia and extended to Alexandretta and along- the coast of the Mediterranean; also along the Caspian shores to Astrachan, where it disappeared. 1829. The epidemic which started from Bengal in 1826 passed into Afghanistan and Bokhara and Khiva in 1829. From Herat the epidemic Entered from Herat by Meshed. passed to Meshed and right across Northern Persia, through Tehran and Tabriz. 1S30. —Cholera was prevalent over all Northern Persia, along the western shores of the Caspian and up into Central Russia. 1831. —The epidemic ceased in Persia, but passed across Europe, reaching England in October. It is held by some authorities that this invasion of Europe was not due, as I have above described it to be, to an advance from India, through Persia and South Russia, but to an advance from Mecca, where the disease had been brought by pilgrims from India by way of Egypt and Turkey in Europe and thence across the Continent. Entered from Bokhra and Afghanis- iS4o.—Cholera raged iu Central Asia and Bokhara, and tan via Herat and iieshed the 1829 Cabul suffered very heavily in 1844. In 1845 the epidemic r ' )Ute ' reached Meshed from both Bokhara and Herat. 1846. —Cholera was epidemic over all northern Persia. Dr. Milroy records its appearance at Tehran in May 1846, and says that men in many cases suddenly dropped down in a state of lethargy and died in two or three hours without vomiting or convulsions. 1847. —Cholera was epidemic over all Persia. Passed into Europe and to America in following year 1848. Entered Southern Persia from the Cholera was epidemic over all the Bombay Presi. shores of the Persian Gulf probably. dency in 1850, and in 1851 over all Southern Persia. Prevailed in the Gulf and up the 2855.— Cholera prevailed in the Persian Gulf and up the Euphrates and the Tigris to Baghdad. Tigris to Baghdad. Probably the epidemic entered both _ZS5o.—All Persia was coveied by the epidemic and it from the Gulf shores and from the appeared in many places in Russia. Baghdad direction as in 1821-22. In 1854 this epidemic spread all over Europe and America. 1865. —Cholera was epidemic over Bengal as high as Cawnpore in 1863 ; in 1864 the epidemic spread over the Central Provinces and a part of .a i d r r t h.?e t p e a,'S'n 0 p te' the Bombay Presidency. In 1865 Bombay Presidency suffered road between Bunder Abbus and from the epidemic over nearly its whole area. In the end Shiraz - of May the disease moved along the Mekran Coast and reached Meenow, some 60 miles east of Bunder Abbas. It was said to be prevalent at the same time at Kassab on the Arabian Coast. I have no further record of this epidemic till August when Lingah and its neighbouihood suffered very heavily. It was said at the same time that the disease was moving up the caravan road between Bunder Abbas and Shiraz. There seems to have been no advance of this epidemic beyond Lingah on the Persian Coast of the Gulf; I have no record of what followed the outbreak at Kassab on the Arabian Coast.16 ADMINISTRATION REPORT OF THE PERSIAN GULF POLITICAL The above History may be cousidered as that of the Persian Gulf offshoot of the 1863-64 epidemic started from Bengal. There was another and more important offshoot of the same epidemic, wliich burst into life at Mecca and Medina in the end of May or beginning of June of this year, havino- been carried to those places by pilgrims from India. The outbreak was a severe one. Returning pilgrims carried the disease with them. Reyahj the capital of the Wahabi country, suffered heavily, as did Aneyza and other towns there. The epidemic moved on by Jahr or Jaharah, and on the 25th or 26th August broke out at Duaseh, on the right bank of the Shat-el-Arab, some 40 miles below Bussorah. On the 8th September cholera appeared at Basra and soon became very severe; it was said 5 per cent, of the population died of it! Koweit and its neighbourhood suffered severely about the same time as Bussorah. The epidemic passed up the Euphrates through Syria to Aleppo and up the Tigris to Diabekr and throughout Turkish Kurdistan. This is precisely what occurred in the epidemic of 1846. In October the epidemic became dormant. 1S66. The epidemic of last year which ceased in October, broke out in March of this Entered Persia by Urumia and pro- y ear ) and advanced over two routes. One extendino- over and r 0SS E r pe ' it t, England in April fr.; Rotter- f „ . , „ ... damand to America m May (or June). The other route followed by the ep.dcm.e was from Turk.sh Kurdistan or from the Baghdad Provinces into Pers.a near Urumia and beyond Tabriz. The country ail round Tabriz suffered heavily, but the disease passed no further in an easterly direction. 1867. The cholera which became dormant in the Tabriz District in October or Novem- All Persia suffering. ber ' a ® t y ear broke out in the spring of this year and moved • ^ steadily across Northern Persia through Tehran to Meshed. This epidemic must have extended to Central and Southern Persia also, I think though I have no record of its having done so. Notice t ?. -a , ^ , tnougn Tehran that Cf all Persia has been declared infected/'' ^ 681 eDCy Bus hire from The great &lt;c Hurdwar epidemic' occurred on the 13th and 14th of Anril nf fT,- from Hurdwar was carried by returning pilgrims far and wide. ^ anfSdTn\r.tL b tel h nd? 8 e S! vaf uf^rts ofpeSa^ 0f thiS year Gh0lera appeared in Up to the middle of 1868 ebolera had moved across Persia in a direction from west toeast eioTkr^ ^ HUrdW ' r r* 'f ' 0 k Sa y. tbat from ^'T 111 18d6 by Urumia and beyond labnz it passed steadily across to Meshpd t n t t a reverse movement set in : a body of pilgrims returning westward from Meshed in thnl month carried the disease with them and it soon covered pit Nn .fl f ed m thafc the Baghdad Pashalik. Cholera was at the Ze tIL prevfleut i^ NorT India and in Afghanistan. ^ ^ v0lt ^ ein and Western Paurel and some Russian writer 5 ? Imlrl flsaf «« j westward above alluded to, was simply a carrying back by ^i^ririrZ ohT^on^fet' 1 in fact a new invasion. The grit outbllk^ 1868 ^ collected, occurred on the 12th to Hth A mil Cr 0a ii • u ^ milllon! &gt; of pilgrims had 1867; the pilgrims scattered panilst!iclL 0^1^ Ib'tb A^f and 3 ': Uiem in all directions (Bryden laughs this idea to seorn but, Lverthelesr^a widerbd.^d They carried it into Afghanistan, where it rao-ed from T„l v seems most likely it was the cholera beeoming donnlnt in September 1867 wWeh anCl z^Tz; lhesp ' ns o£ 1868 a ' d foiiowi 's the — — HeLXs Macnamara holds, I think, that the Tehran cholera of 1867 was an ofW,„ t r TT , W ar epidemic, but an examination of the dates and facts above given seem tome to I h' is mistaken and that the story as above given is the true oneRESIDENCY AND MUSCAT POLITICAL AGENCT FOR 1889-90. 17 1869 .-ln the spring, cholera broke out at Ku m (south-west of Meshed) aud at Kashan All Persia suffered. ^ e weei J ; s P a ^ an an( i Tehran). It appeared at Tehran in , T i * fi « 4. j une ana is said to have caused 50 deaths daily. It broke it' ''' 1 ' a,b -' • | ' ! - '• setj : vn;; It was at Kazeroon m the last days of July and reached Bushire on 13th October. In this month there were some cases at Kier in South Russia. . ^.-Cholera was prevalent throughout Trans-Caucasia and to the Persian Frontier below Envan, but 1 have no record of its appearance in Persia. Nearly all Russia south of St. Petersburg was this year affected by the epidemic. 1871- Cholera appeared at Bushirc on the ISth February and clung to the town and The Gulf ports suffered, and late in neighbourhood till the middle of March (the town, to., was the year cholera entered from Baghdad crowded with sufferers from the famine and amono-qf fham by Kermanshah as in 1821-22, 1852- was ffp phipf mnrfol.'fTr r\ j • n i 53, 1866 probably. chiel: mor tahty. On one day in February, 41 deaths from cholera occurred). In the first days of April there were cases of cholera at Bussorah. About the middle of April there was a small outbreak of cholera at Bushire, which ceased by the 19th. On May 18th cholera was raging at Fao. In May a TuiLish expeditionary force, collected at Bussorah, suffered from cholera. It took cholera with it to Koweit, whence it spread through and across Arabia as I shall tell lower down. In June cholera deaths were reported on the 28th as occurring at Lingah. In July, the last week of, there was a small outburst of cholera at Bushire. In August cholera was bad at Bahrain and amongst the pearl fleet; the disease was said to have been brought by the Turkish force before spoken of. The cholera brought from Bussorah to Koweit, as above related, in June 1871 spread through Eastern Arabia. It appeared at Hayel in Northern Arabia in the middle of June. From Hayel it moved southwards to Khaiber and thence to Medina and Mecca, reaching the former in September and the latter in November. In August 1871 cholera was severe in Baghdad and in the Province of Azerbijan in Persia. 1889. —Cholera appeared in the Hye (about the Shatra) in the last days of Jtdy. Before Cholera entered Persia from Bagh- this outbreak nothing was known of cholera having occurred anywhere nearer than India within the preceding months of the year. Since then, Dr. Browski, a medical officer, serving the Turkish Government, by which he was ordered to enquire into the origin of the epidemic, claims to have discovered that occasional cases of cholera had occurred in Bussorah at least four months before the outbreak in the Hye. August 5th the first case of, and death from, cholera occurred in Bussorah, and about the same date (or before it) at Nazarieh on the Euphrates. By the 12th August all Bussorah was affected and the epidemic continued till the 2nd September. The last death from cholera in Bussorah was on 13th September, but occasional cases and an odd death occurred about the date gardens and date-packing stations, up to, at least, the 20th October. 13th August. —The first case of, and death from, cholera, occurred at Bushire; this was a passenger ex steamer Mobile which left Bussorah on the 10th August and arrived at Bushire on the morning of the 12th ; she landed 57 passengers, coolies, and the corpse of a man who bad died (of cholera) at sea the night before. Five deaths occurred amongst the passengers brought by her, two deaths amongst Bushire people resident in the houses wherein these cases occurred, and one case in a man landed from the mail steamer Kilwa. Eight deaths in all: the last occurring on the 23rd August, August 18th or thereabouts the Turkish Quarantine Officer at Fao died of cholera, and it is said the epidemic was sharply prevalent there. 20th August, —About this date cholera appeared at Baghdad. 24th August.—Hthe first case and death occurred at Mohammerah on 21th August. dad by Kermansbah and up the Karun by Ahwaz and Shusbter and probably these two invading movements met beyond Khoramabad or at Hamadan or Kermanshah. r I: I: II 111 :li ill jil fi I 11 if: : 1 ii II tl; II If- 111 % S '18 ADMINISTRATION REPORT OF THE PERSIAN GULF POLITICAL 26th August. —On this date, it is said, the first case and death occurred at Ahwaz, On this date and the following I heard 74, and 104 deaths occurred from cholera at Bagh dad (Lieutenant Murray). 29fk August. —First case occurred on this date at Shushter, followed by occasional cases up to 15th September, when the disease became severe and continued severe to 8th or 11th October. My information is that there were 369 deaths amongst the troops, and 16 in the Governor's housshold, and nearly 2,000 in the town and surrounding district. The Official Re- ports to Tehran gave the total number at something like 400 !! It almost looks as if the Offi cial Report only took notice of the deaths amongst employes of the State, and of the Governor, to judge from a comparison of the official, and my private reports. Same date, 29th August, Deyer, Bardistan, and Tahiri. September. —First week. First cases occurred in Dewitz near Behbahan ; in Shah Abdullah and in Hindiun. First case at— Mohammerah, 24th August. In this week or in last week of August, Dizful suffered Ahwaz . 26th „ Sliushter 29th „ new -n- Dizful,—Last days of oeptevibeT /sOf/^.-—r irst case at Kermanshah continued there August or first days to 20th November (at least), of September. ' 3rd October. —Mulayar near Hamadan had first case. Outbreak lasted till 3rd or 4th December. About this time Kassr, Sherein, Serpul, and Kerind were declared free from cholera but 2 deaths from the disease occurred at Keriud, on the 10th, said to have been pilgrims. loth October. —About this date there were 4 deaths at the village called Bariki, some 50 miles south of Bushire. A native of this village was in Bussorah earlier in the month. On the day on which he left Bussorah, he says, he found in one of the streets a bundle of woman's cloth, ing, which seemed to him good enough to be worth taking. He took them, was 4 days in a native boat on the journey to Bariki. On his arrival he gave the bundle to his women, and 4 days thereafter all four got cholera and died. The inhabitants of the village scattered and no other cases occurred. 16th Oc/fofo/.—Cholera appeared in the village near Mulayar. mh October. Cholera appeared at Hamadan ; only occasional cases occurred up to llth November when it became sharply epidemic. There was continuous hard frost for over a fort night from the 22nd October, but this did not stop the epidemic. 2m October. Cholera bad again at Behbahan ; 29 deaths said to have occurred to-dav there from cholera. J October. Towards the end of the month cholera was said to be raging at Koweit. mh November, Khoramabad. Cholera said to be diminishing here, but ra-in .ges round. 0 5th December. Naharwend lost 2 out of 5 cases, and on the 6tb lost 3 out of 9 cases. APPENDIX D TO PART I. TABLE No. 1. Table showing Force and prevailing Directions of Winds and recorded Rain-fall at Bushire for the year 1689-90. O a P eecentage op each dieection. M onth. o a &gt;&gt; *ce M ^3 o fl OQ 23 OJ D ^ ^3 C X £ c . 3 S3 O QQ a s 3 03 X o c R ain. c: « S r* -♦J J* a -M* a* •£ ^ '2 - O £ a&gt; cs 03 Q c a&gt; co £3 3 X go cS +3 C o s April May J une July 1889 » ... 224 185 259 153 11 3 6 5 47 55 51 34 13 8 14 22 8 10 7 33 6 5 4 2 3 10 3 3 2 3 1 10 6 8 Inches. Cents. 0 o 0 12 0 o 0 0P art II. ADMINISTRATION REPORT OE THE MUSCAT POLITI CAL AGENCY AND CONSULATE EOR THE YEAR 1889-90. The official year now under report was rather an uneventful one in the Political. Political history of Oman. The rumours regarding a probable rising of the Hinawee tribes, headed by Sayid Abdul Aziz against the rule of the Sultan, which prevailed towards the end of the previous year and which seemed to subside for a time, took a more definite shape about the end of April, so that the Resident, who arrived here on the 26th of that month for the purpose of recognizing His Highness Sayid Eeysal as Sultan of Muscat, had to postpone doing so, under the unsettled state of affairs then existing. Nothing, however, resulted from this attempt of the Sultan's uncle to invite the Sharkiyyeh tribes to join his cause, and excepting an intertribal quarrel between the Beni-bu-Ali and the Jenebeh. at Sur, the province of Oman seemed to be tranquil again. About the end of the year 1888, His Highness the Sultan was compelled, owing to the strained relations existing at the time between the Beni-bu-Ali and the Jenebeh at Sur, to send a deputation with the object of effecting peace between the two tribes. For a time they remained on peaceful terms, but the latter having killed one of the Beni-bu-Ali, fresh hostilities broke out between them in May 1889, which resulted in a fight of some importance. His High ness Sayid Eeysal lost no time in sending his steamer ' Sultani ' with Sayids Badr-bin Seif and Nasir-bin-Muliammad, and Shaik Shamis-bin-Hasain to the scene of action, and in inviting both parties to Muscat to settle the dispute between them amicably. Shaik Abdullah-bin-Salem, the Tamimeh of the Beni- bu-Ali refused for a time to accept any terms short of the surrender of four lives of the opposite party, but eventually agreed to a truce for a year, the question of compensation remaining unsettled. The state of political tranquillity which was reported to exist at the begin ning of June was not destined to last long. On the 13th of July Sayid Abdul Aziz wrote to the Political Agent and the Resident expressing his intention of attacking Muscat shortly, but nothing occurred till the end of the month to show that he would succeed in making an attempt to carry it out. Aided, however, by some of the Hijrin, he managed at last to collect a few men with whom he marched to the Kahza Pass where he was repulsed by the Sultan's garrison ; the little invading party having in consequence dispersed, Sayid Abdul Aziz had to fall back upon Samad. After this defeat and discomfiture of Sayid Abdul Aziz, the aspect oi political affairs seemed again to take a tranquil turn; and although owing to his restless nature vague rumours of another attempt on his part were in circulation, no event of any importance occurred until the 24th December, when the Political Agent reported of an affray having taken place in the Dahireh between the Beni Kelban and the Naeem on one side and the Beni- Ali on the other, in consequence of the latter having some time back waylaid a party of the Beni Kelban and killed eight of them. Although no reliable in formation could be obtained as regards the actual severity of the fight or the numbers of the killed and wounded, the result of the fight seems to have been decidedly against the Beni-Ali.24 ADMINISTRATION REPORT OF THE PERSIAN GULF POLITICAL About the same time fresh rumours of another projected risin^ of the Sharkiyyeh tribes reached Muscat and Shaikh Saleh-bin-Ali, who, strange to say, has remained faithful and friendly throughout to the present Sultan, wrote on the 26th of December warning him of their design. His Highness Sayid Peysal, now believing in the rumours, lost no time in reinforcing the '-arrisons of Muscat and Muttrah whilst Shaik Saleh sent a direct message to t^e Chiefs in charge of the several passes to prepare for the enemy. As it was sunnosed at first that Sayid Ibrahim-bin-Keis of Eustak would join the coalition of the tribes, and lend his assistance to the scheme, the Sultan made his prepara tions accordingly, so that about the end of January he had nearly 2,000 men at his command. In the meantime, Shaik Hamud-al-Jahafi who seems to have een the prime exciter of this revolt, proceeded with about 150 men from the Sharkiyyeh and reached Rustak on the 7th of January, where he evidentlv pre- iled upon Sayid Ibrahim to give countenance to the cause by sending his the 80118 of tlle late Iman ^ ^ i* I J '' as . e^^ently Sayid Abdul Aziz's intention to take a more direct H ip e ,l 0 'it nea ' ^ uttral1 ' where by a previous arrangement be was to ioin tbe advanced party beaded by Shaik Hamud, but after makm-, fruitless at the night of tlie inn, ° n tIle J;iatl ° eh . attacked a hamlet near Burkeh on dering 0 the country around ''' r 'Ti af ^ rn ' ards set about raiding and plun- minds of the garrisons euTrdint fh Plre 00Urage and zea! iEto ^e Aziz falling back upon lamad ^he Z' ^d by Sayid Abdul danger nearer home Rashid rptn i 'f S Vr''' ' -^fuscat to deal with the iug with him 500 men of the ral ^ the 16th Januar y' partly to watch and partly to keen thet T' 6 n0W P0Sted at Wat t a yeb sightcdness of this policv w as ho~ ^ S f0rCe m check - short- new reinforcements refused to fiodit or f.,1 0 '' 1 a ' l l ,a, ' 0 ' t ' fo! ' ou the one hand the tribesmen on the opposite side and ou tl.P 6 h ' 7 f' 0 ' a ' ainst ''eir own tioned in Mnseat were afraW to LaS th^' 1 ^ ^ tribes sta - Hamud, lest their departure might give thp H . p0 and naareh a &amp; ain st Shaikh coabbon against them and placing the Snltan inTwoU p^shfon In^r' ' taking advantage ^ ^ Abdul A^now made his appearance with 17 men in thp S ^ from tlle P ass es. suddenly reported to be on the 20th of Januarv fan , 7 Ilear :Pan -i ah and was The Snltan was therefo compeUed t^ 5 ; ^ Way t0 j0in Hamud ' s P ar ^- ingly on the 26th, whilst he sent hh v P ' ™ 0re t active cou ^. and aecord- himself proceeded in person by sea to Sce^Xcre th^em^ 111 Pahad by laIld ■ be quartered. The news of these men^v^ i T 7 Was su PPosed to being carried out, so that on bis arrival -.fs HrT t lready P receded their Seyyid Abdul Aziz and Ham„l Z . Sultan fouild «'at both returned to Muscat, leaving the land nartv In0re lnIand; 1,6 therefore 0 land now commanded by Seyyid PahadRESIDENCY AND MUSCAT POLITICAL AGENCY FOR 1889-90. to deal with the enemy who kept on retreating as the other party advanced The development of tins new feature in Omanee tactics was not calculated upon by the advancing party who had to carry on the pursuit till the enemy found himselr within the friendly precincts of Eustak. As it seemed pretty certain now that although Seyyid Ibrahim had &lt;nyen a friendly refuge to Seyyid Abdul Aziz and his followers at Eustak, he had no intention of co-operating with him or of giving him any active support and accordingly as no reason remained for maintaining such a large force to 4atch any further development of Seyyid Abdul Aziz's scheme, the Sultan wisely paid off and dismissed most of the men and directed his brother to leave Jimmeh where he was encamped and to fall back upon Burkeh whence he could ^ easly watch the enemy's movements. Eor the next few weeks the situation remained unaltered, and, although various rumours were in circulation, nothing beyond a few intertribal raids, mainly incidental on the disturbed condition of the country then existing,' occurred. About the beginning of February the Rahabiyin attacked a Hinawi caravan consisting of men and property belonging to the Yal-Wahibeh, the Habus and the Duekeh, in retaliation for the raid committed on them by Hamud-al-Jahafi on his first advance to the Batineh. In this encounter the Rahabiyin succeeded in killing six men and in carrying off 40 camels. This incident might have led to serious complications, had not His Highness the Sultan succeeded in time to effect a truce between the parties. When Sheikh Hamud-al-Jahafi first visited Kustak, it was more than surmised that he had succeeded in winning Sayid Ibrahim over to the cause, and as under those circumstances in all probability, the latter would have first attacked Sohar or any other Batineh Ports, it was necessary to reinforce the garrisons in all these places. The Wali of Sohar, Sayid Hamud Bin Nasir, in vited the Naim to his assistance, but by the time they could arrive Sayid Abdul Aziz and Sheikh Hamud were gradually retreating towards Eustak, and it was apparent that Sayid Ibrahim had no intention of attempting to at tack Sohar or any other place. The Wali, Sayid Hamud, finding himself now freer to act, led the new reinforcements to Wadi Kasim with the object of co operating with Sayid Fahad with whose party he was eventually ordered to fall back upon Burkeh. The Naim, however, rather suddenly left that place and found back their way to Sohar, plundering the Yal-Saad on the way and committing raids near Sohar itself for which reason Sayid Hamud had to be sent by sea to quiet and dismiss them. After the retreat of Sayid Abdul Aziz and Sheikh Hamud from the Batineh, the former remained at Eustak till about the end of March when he left for the Shamal or the Pirate Coast with the object of visiting Sheikh Zaid- bin-Khalifeh at Abu-Dabi. Sheikh Hamud, however, not contented with the share of plunder which had already fallen to his lot in the Batineh, occu pied himself with his usual pursuit of raiding until being deserted by most of his followers and unable to retrace his steps to the Sharkiyyeh in safety with out an escort, on Sayid Abdul Aziz's departure for the Shamal, tendered his submission to Sayid Badr-bin-Seif who was left in charge at Burkeh after Sayid Fahad's return to Muscat. His Highness the Sultan deeming it advis able to accept it allowed him to return to the Sharkiyyeh in the company of a Gafri Chief. Thus the close of the official year under report saw another effort of Sayid Abdul Aziz's to incite the people of Oman to revolt against the present Sul tan and to accept him as their ruler instead, and, like its predecessois, in fius- tration, a result which, while it clearly indicates the weakness of his own cause.ADMINISTRATION REPORT OP THE PERSIAN GULP POLITICAL also strengthens the belief that His Highness Sayid Eeysal has now fairly earned the loyalty and support of his subjects. There were no seizures of slave dhows during the year. The number of fugitive slaves that sought freedom at the Consulate during the year was 51, of whom 35 have been liberated under treaty stipulations of 1873, and 16 were dismissed. Lieutenant W. Stratton held charge of the office of Political Agent and Official changes. Consul from 1st April to 4th September when he proceeded on privilege leave, and again on his return from leave from 20tb October to 16th December when he was relieved by Major C. E. Yate, C.S.I., C.M.G., who held charge from that date to 28th March 1890. Surgeon-Major Jayakar held charge from 5th September to 19th October during the absence of Lieutenant Stratton on privilege leave, anda^ain from 29th to 31st March. A. S. G. JAYAKAR, Surgeon-Major, In charge Political Agency&gt; Muscat, W tory.27 P art III.—REPORT ON THE TRADE OF SOUTH PERSIA AND THE PERSIAN GULF FOR THE YEAR 1889. The year 1889 was a comparatively prosperous one for South Persia in its commercial aspect. Not only was there marked increase of the volume of trade, hut good profits were, on the whole, realized by those engaged in it. As one instance in proof of the increase referred to, it may be mentioned that the Bushire customs yielded a revenue of about 40 per cent, in excess of that of the preceding year. Much attention has been directed to Persia as an outlet for European manufactures by the opening of the River Karun to international traffic, the visit of the Shah to Europe, and the formation of the Imperial Bank of Persia. Possibly the attention so attracted may have led to the shipment to this country of goods on a scale somewhat disproportionate to the present actual consumption, and some check may be anticipated unless new forces at work in the country add speedily to its general prosperity. There was a considerable increase in the import of cotton goods, chiefly of British (Manchester) manufacture, but, on the whole, results were not so satisfactory to merchants as in the year 1888. Owing to a 44 corner ' in cotton, prices in Manchester rose considerably, and for a time no corresponding rise occurred in Persia. On the collapse of the cotton f4 ring' in 1889, the position improved, and the market became firmer. The piece-goods imported were largely of the costlier descriptions, and towards the end of the year the markets were somewhat overstocked in more than one article of staple goods, and it was feared that re-action might ensue in the cotton trade daring the current year. However, the good harvests of 1890, and consequent increased prosperity amongst peasantry and nomads, may avert that evil. My attention has been drawn by Messrs. Malcolm, of Bushire, to the re marks on Russian red chintzes, contained in my last trade report, which re marks require correction. For it appears that the so-called Russian chintzes are really of English manufacture, and acquired the name of 4 Russian from having been originally introduced into Persia through Russia. In the same way, there are chintzes known as ' Austrian ' which are entirely of Manchester manufacture. The fact of the so-called ' Russian' goods being imported through Bunder Abbas is accordingly, if anything, a favourable indication I am informed by a leading English merchant that he recently observed Man chester eoods in the bazars of Tehran which, bearing Indian marks, had un- JVletals ' collapse of the Paris Copper ISyndica^e reieasea large stocks of that metal, and a sufficient portion was taken by Persia with satisfac- Imports. be still more satisfactory. tory results. d i28 ADMINISTRATION REPORT OF THE PERSIAN GULF POLITICAL The quantity of sugar imported early in the year was comparatively small, and this, combined with enhanced prices abroad, caused for a time a considerable rise in prices in Persia, but towards the close of the year, freer arrivals at lower rates caused a fall in prices. It appears that French loaf sugar (beet) keeps the lead, though both German and Austrian sorts are freely taken. It is observed that the large quantity of candles imported is chiefly from Holland, from which it would appear that English manufacturers are unable to provide a suitable article at a cheap rate. A decline in the price of gold threads having occurred, inferior qualities are said to be supplied, and Russian gold threads have acquired a superiority in the markets over those of other countries. Candles. Gold threads. Exports. A considerable area was under cultivation in South and Central Persia, but Gra . n the grain harvests of 1889 disappointed expect ations owing to scanty rain-fall in the latter months. The quality of wheat brought to Bushire was inferior in colour and in size, and the admixture of barley was excessive. Owing to low prices in European markets, cultivators in Persia realized but small returns. The prohibition on export of grain imposed in the autumn of 1888 was never entirely withdrawn, and shipments could only be made on payment of special ' fees ' in addition to the regular duty. Capricious and unnecessary prohibitions of exportation of grains from Persia are of frequent occurrence, and tend greatly to hamper trade, not only in this particular branch, but in all others. Such embargos have also an inju rious effect on the country and population. If they were strictly enforced the' results would be ruinous to all, and, in absence of satisfactory regulations it is necessary in the general interests to pass without remonstrance' irregularities which add to the incomes of the official classes. If some more satisfactory system could be introduced and enforced, it would he a boon to trade srenerallr, and relieve it of a burden and constantly recurring annoyance. It is obvious how convenient the present system is to local officials. The opium crop of 1889 was a good one, but the demand for the drug in Opium. Europe has fallen off, and most of the Persian opium n , . .. was sent to China. Prices in Hong-Konff were uni form throughout the year, and profits moderate. The tobacco trade of South Persia has been chiefly in the hands of Syrian Tobacco. merchants. It was by no means remunerative, by * Ti. • , a11 acco «nts, in 1889, and some losses were in- curred. It is understood that an English or European Company has acquired a concession for a tobacco 'regie' in Persia. The quantity of wool exported was up to the average. Some shipments were made to Bombay, .London, New York, and The exporters naid I,,VI, „ • arsei les ; but most of the wool was sent to Bussorah. P '' i - — - b -«» The cotton trade is on the increase in South Persia, and is chiefly in the Hands of Persian merchants who ship to Bombay, finer Indian qualities destine'd for Europe' 8 ' 311 ^ bou 8 ht for witl1' « ^ IF roii ne Al 18 C0,I1 Piritij tabr^'N ported is id ssian e markets Central Pi 1 disappointed Jlin colour and in si; ^ prices in E autumn ui 1555 ra 0 made on tation of grains lamper trade, not •e strictly enforced I story regulations, ili nstrance irregukfe 3me more satisfacta oon to trade geml oyance. Itisote nand for the teE ;ans remuMBtH some losses Company ^ ige, Some si idon, New ,1 was sent to ^ farmers: .oli**'.! oug. EESIDENCT AND MUSCAT POLITICAL AGENCY FOR 1889-90. 29 The carpet trade receives more attention from European exporters than formerly, and the manufacture in certain districts Carp6t5, 18 co ntrolled by European supervision, with good results. 0 The stimulation of the trade in Persian gum which was mentioned in my Gum. report for 1888, has been arrested in consequence , ^ , of lar ^ er su Pplies of good qualities being obtain- able in Egypt and the Soudan. The Persian article has been scarcely inquired FearUfisheries. The Arab population of the shores of the Persian Gulf and its islands look forward to the period of diving operations (about 100 days of the hot season) as the chief event of the year. To them the pearl-take is their harvest, and in this all classes, from Chiefs to domestic slaves, are personally interested. During recent years these ' harvests ' have been abundant, whilst at the same time prices of pearls have been rising. Consequently there is a visible increase in the prosperity of the Arabs of this littoral, and larger vessels are built than of yore. I reckon that in round numbers nearly 2,000 boats of all sizes are engaged on the pearl banks from tbe Pirate Coast, from Bahrain say 1,500 and from El-Katr, Koweit, &amp;c„ about 1,000—a total of 4,500 boats. It is not an excessive estimate to suppose that 30,000 men are thus employed. The take of pearls in 1889 about equalled that of the preceding year. Tonnage and freights. During the first part of the year, whilst exportation of grain continued, there was a moderate demand for tonnage in London, but later, the prohibition on the export of grain, coupled with the outbreak of cholera in Bussorah, limited the quantity of cargo obtainable. Freights ranged from 30s. to 35s. at Bushire during the grain export operation. Exchange, Exchange on London varied from 34J to 36 kerans per pound sterling, and was not subject to any violent fluctuations. Kerans fluctuated from 230 to 252 per one hundred rupees. Banking Agencies. The branch of the new Oriental Bank Corporation in Bushire is reported to have done a fair business. The Imperial Bank of Persia opened at the capital is about to establish branches in other towns including Bushire, buying out the Oriental. Opening of the Karun River route. Considerable progress has been made on the Karun, and the relations between the commercial agents and Persian officials and people are much improved. A suitable river steamer is now on the upper river, and a company lias been formed to construct roads for wheeled carriage and bridges from the Karun to Ispahan and Tehran. Impediments and requirements. In the first of this series of reports (for the year 1873), as well as in sub sequent trade reports, allusions have been made to the difficulties which are experienced by foreign merchants carrying on business in Persia generally, and to certain measures which seemed requisite in order to place British and British Indian trade in the south of Persia on a fairer footing. a sil mi! 1 1 ! » is I ;30 ADMINISTEATION REPORT OP THE PERSIAN GULP POLITICAL Amongst the suggestions then being considered were : The openino- of the Karun Eiver Route; establishment of a British Agency at Yezd; revised commercial treaty; administrative reform, in view to facilitate recovery of just claims from Persian debtors. The two first of these proposals are in fair way of realization, and other measures not thought of in those days are now faits accomplis. With the advance of trade, however, the need for administrative reform is becoming still more strongly felt, and in this respect no progress has been made, and the terms used to describe this want more than fifteen years ago are still applicable. The evil threatens to assume dangerous proportions, from the increased tendency to fraudulent declarations of bankruptcy, under the facilities afforded by the venality of officials. These, as often as not are selected for their absorbtive qualities rather than for administrative qualifica tions or high character, and when a dishonest Persian debtor decides to free himself from his liabilities to foreign traders on easy terms, he finds his own officials ready with sympathising though not disinterested assistance In such cases, and unfortunately they are common, all efforts to obtain full justice must a ' for l ou find Judge leagued with the accused and custodiam quis custodiet ? 1 If any method can be devised to provide for the just hearing and speedv settlement ot claims of foreigners against Persian subjects, it will greatlv benefit trade generally. 5 J Increase of Trade. Notwithstanding all difficulties, during the last twenty years (a eompara- tively dark period before the light of European enterprise so suddenly and recently shed on Persia), the trade of the south of Persia has steadily increased. u ging from our returns, the value of imports and exports of Bushire in creased m fifteen years (from 1873 to 1888) by about five millions of rupees In a period of 10 years (from 1878 to 1888) the trade of Bunder Abbas in creased to a similar extent. Prom the present time a fresh departure ma y be reckoned, the old order changes, and more rapid progress may be anticipated. E. C. ROSS, Politicul Hesideut in the Persian Oulf Busiiike a ' d M Consul-General for Pars. The 20th May 1890.a lie &gt; eil &lt;yalj, Na JSa ; 6l '% 56(1 for ad tt S res Pect no 10re tianfift, [:&gt;■* 'ustrafa ibiord, I10 findj Stance, 'n full justice ^ nd tiGariflff aiw 'tSj it ?l]l (Mjr years 3 so s steadily increi ts of nillions of rips, lunder Abk in- ieparturemayk be anticipated, Persian Gulf ure a- RESIDENCY AND MUSCAT POLITICAL AGENCY FOR 1889 90 APPENDIX A TO PART III. consisting of the following tabular statistics: 1. Return of principal articles of export from Bushire, during 1 the year 1889. 2. Return of principal articles of import into Bushire, during the year 1889. 3. Table showing total value of all articles exported from, and imported to, Bushire, to and from foreign countries, during the years 188H and 1889. 4. Return of shipping at the port of Bushire, in the year 1889. 5. Return of British shipping at the port of Bushire, during the year 1889. 6. Return of foreign shipping at the port of Bushire, during the year 1889. 7. Statement showing the quantity of opium exported from Bushire from 1st January to 31st December 1889. 8. Statement showing the customs and other revenues farmed by the Governor of Bushire, for the year 1889-90, 9. Return of principal articles of export from Shiraz, during the year 1889. 10. Keturn of principal articles of import into Shiraz, during the year 1889. 11. Return of principal articles of export from Lingah, during the year 1889. 12. Return of principal articles of import into Lingah, during the year 1889. 13. Table showing the total value of all articles exported from, and imported into, Lingah, to and from foreign countries, during the years 1888 and 1889. 14. Return of shipping at Lingah in the year 1889. 15. Return of principal articles of export from Bunder Abbas, during the year 1889. 16. Return of principal articles of import into Bunder Abbas, during the year 1889. 17. Table showing the total value of all articles exported from, and imported into. Bunder Abbas, to and from foreign countries, during the years 1888 and 1889. 18. Return of shipping at the port of Bunder Abbas, in the year 1889. 19. Statement showing the quantity of opium exported from Bunder Abbas from the 1st of January to the 31st of December 1889. 20. Return of principal articles of export from Bahrain, during the year 1889. 21. Return of principal articles of import into Bahrain, during the year 1889. 22. Table showing the total value of all articles exported from, and imported to, Bahrain, to and from foreign countries, during the years 1888 and 1889. 23. Return of shipping at the port of Bahrain, in the year 1889. 24. Return of principal articles of export from the ports of the Arab Coast at the Persian Gulf, during the year 1889. 25. Return of principal articles of import into the ports of the Arab Coast of the Persian Gulf, during the year 1889. 26. Table showing the total value of all articles exported from, and imported to, the ports of the Arab Coast of the Persian Gulf, to and from foreign countries, during the years 1888 and 1889. 27. Return of shipping at the ports of the Arab Coast of the Persian Gulf, in the y ear 1889. ■ -Sif w&gt;w.g&gt;li»pP aet IV.—MUSCAT TRADE REPORT FOR THE YEAR 1889-90. Ihe returns of the trade of Muscat have been furnished hy the Customs farmer and cannot be entirely depended upon. The figures as given, however, compare very favourably, especially under the head of Imports, with those for the previous year. The total value of imports amounted to 19,97,726$, showing an increase of 1,40,456$ over that of the imports in 1888-89. This increase was principally observed in the imports of rice, wheat, coffee, cotton fabrics, twist and oil from India. There was a considerable falling off in the imports from other countries, viz., the Persian Gulf, Mekran Coast, South Arabia, Africa, the United States of America, Mauritius, and Singapore. The total value of exports shows also an increase, but a slight one of 3,505$ over the total of the last year; the increase occurred principally in dates and cotton fabrics. There was, however, a decrease in the export of rice and Ame rican cloth. A. S. G. JAYAKAR, Surg eon-Major, In charge Political Agency, Muscat.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000358.0x00028b_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/V/23/58, No 274</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000358.0x00028b</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/V/23/58, No 274</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>‘Administration report of the Persian Gulf Political Residency and Muscat Political Agency for 1889-90’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1890/1890</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-10-31T02:23:06</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (30 folios)</extent><extent>The report is arranged into a number of sections and subsections, with statistic data in tabular format directly following written sections. There is a contents page at the front of the report (folio 199) which list the report's contents.</extent><extent>Foliation: There is a foliation sequence, which is circled in pencil, in the top right corner of the recto of each folio. It begins on the first folio, on number 198, and ends on the last folio, on number 227.Pagination: The volume contains an original typed pagination sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Administration Report of the Persian Gulf Residency and Muscat Political Agency for 1899-1900, published by the Office of the Superintendent of Government Printing, India (Calcutta), forming part of Selections from the Records of the Government of India, Foreign Department, and based on reports sent to Government by the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf and the Political Agent at Muscat.The report is divided up into a number of sections and subsections, as follows:Part 1, is a General Summary (folios 200-203) written by the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Edward Charles Ross and divided up as follows:1. Oman-Muscat State,records recognition of His Highness Seyyid Feysal-bin-Turki as Sultan and ruler of the Muscat State by the Government of India.2. Oman-Pirate Coast, gives summary of relations between the various ruling families on the coast and contains a list of the estimated numbers of pearl-fishing boats sailing from Pirate Coast ports.3. El Bahrain,contains summary of events in Bahrain including reports that a number of members of the Naeem and Salateh tribes from El-Katr [Qatar] have settled in Bahrain.4. El Katr, includes details of feud between Shaikh Jasim-bin-Mohammed Bin Thani and the Chief of Abu Dhabi and reports on relations between Katr [Qatar] and the Turkish authorities.5. Nejd and El Hasa,reports that Emir Mohammed "Ibn Rashid" exercises authority over all of Nejd and comments on the energetic administration of the Muteserrif (Governor) of El-Hasa. Also records robberies from a number of boats in Kateef (Al Qatif) harbour.6. Fars and Persian Coast, summarises political developments in the region and mentions a summer cholera epidemic that is discussed in greater detail in Appendix C.7. Persian Arabistan,summary of political and trading developments in the region, also mentions Cholera epidemic in Mohammerah [Khorramshahr].8. Persian Baluchistan, summary of political developments in the region, notes the cruelty and misconduct of the Governor of Baluchistan, Abul Fath Khan.9. Slave Traffic,summary of the status of slave traffic in the region, records details of some slaves manumitted by the Residency.Part 1 contains the following appendices (folios 204-208):A) Genealogical Table of Chief Arab Families of Persian Arabistan;B) Table of Eliyat tribes of South-Western and Central Persia;C) Notes on Cholera in Persia, by Surgeon-Major T. Ffrench Mullen;D) Meteorological Tables.Part 2,is a resume of Muscat Affairs (folios 209-210) written by Atmarim Sadashiv Jayakar, Surgeon-Major, In Charge Political Agency, Muscat. The resume provides a summary of political and military developments in Muscat throughout the year.Part 3,is a Report (folios 211-212) on the Trade of South Persia and the Persian Gulf for the Year 1889, written by the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Edward Charles Ross. Part 3 contains the following appendix (folios 213-221): A) Series of Tabular Statistics tables related to trade in the region.Part 4,is a Muscat Trade Report for the Year 1889-90, the report (folios 222-227), written by Atmarim Sadashiv Jayakar, Surgeon-Major, In Charge Political Agency, Muscat, contains a number of detailed tables related to trade to/from Muscat.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Agent and Consul, Muscat</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><name type="personal"><namePart>Thomas Ffrench Mullen</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Persian Gulf</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Muscat</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Agriculture</topic></subject><subject><topic>Trade (practice)</topic></subject><subject><topic>Meteorological data</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000358.0x00028b#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>