<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0000d9_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-05-23T13:40:54.548Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Previous File POLIT General Heading Sub-head Notes YEAR 193(o . P.Z Sir Papers may be remov jiigfuiirvQF^ilO O : T i': k i ^ 6 i«t» % OM11ISSIONER FOR INDIA 2'e^^p’—B lVocpo »L South Shote 420?5. -^Lt&amp;communication on this fu Address for Inland Telegrams — INDIAMEN, BLACKPOOL ddresscdko — I 1 mu INDIA STORE DEPARTMENT, BLACKPOOL. yiD&amp;mmxwixttx±Kklw^ S • D® 0* 5756/45 •FBD. Please quote in your reply your re f. ; EXT*3881/45* Deaj? Hajari son. 6 th December 1945* \'(lth reference to your letter da.ted the 1st December, regarding the spares for Crossley Engines in the Povrer House of the Consulate-General., Bushire, I am sorry I did not make it clear that I had already taken up the question of deliveiy with Crossley Bros* Ltd. In spite of ny representations regarding the urgency of the supply, I could not obtain aiything better from them than the premised completion date of six months* 1 ttfe. POL DEPtf'p 7- DECt94 c / INDIA OFnCE l sincerely, . F.A.K* Harrison Esq*, *2 External Affairs Department, India Office, Whitehall, LONDON, S*.7*1*OFFICE OF THE HIGH COMMISSIONER FOR INDIA Address for Inland Telegrams — INDIAMEtf, BLACKPOOL Telephone — BLACKPOOL South Shore 42085. — Any communication on this subject to be addressed la — I t J xj&amp;BcraszxxQBxaraxsxxx INDIA STORE DEPARTMENT, BLACKPOOL Please quote in your reply 3«57 EXT.3881/4-5 • Your ref.: j; Deex Harrison, 94o .I ®* 3 22nd November 1945« With reference to paragraph two of your letter dated the 20th August, we have at last managed to plane a contract with Messrs* Crossley Bros* Ltd*, for the spares for Crossley engines in the Power House attached to the Consulate General at Bushire. The tender for the spares was not received until the end of October* The contractors now say that owing to their veiy heavy programme they cannot promise completion in less than six months* I have informed the Political Resident in theMr. '.arri, ^ a&gt;”h|r trj.o. ,J' / ? Please see express letter from Bushire , below. I think we must assume that these parts are required for a different engine from the one which it is hoped to replace by the new Crcssley Generator which was for the Residency main office, (hxt. 1963/44)• Q. dfl-cJ. ^XLlU,ii-AFT TELSG-RAM — Lj 5 India Store Department, lilackpoolo ijear Dell, * you please refer to your letter 5 ft . : o.v/.D.907/d4«PHD of 5th July regarding the supply of a diesel generator set for ivV // ^ ^ far iA*t /tvvWO ushire . ‘ 11 ^ p ' ''' 1 the plant has hoen despatched, ,/e ai’e now inf ormec by the Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf that in his express letter i.o# 55/923 of 18th July he requested the High Corunissioner to purciiase spaare parts for the Crossley engine? in the Pqwer house attached to the Consulate General at Bushire, These spare parts are urgently required as the present engines - 7 hich are very old are continually breaking cown, I assume that these parts are required for a different engine from that which it Z* MGmSFILE, GORY C7J SH A /y£\ j&gt; S'-, (A\ B v - GOVERNiTEKT OE &gt;P1A. 1JPAKTM1NT, T&gt;, s O / ^ EXPRESS LETTER i 3o(J 1 | -ihis is an ORIGIN AE MESS AG 1^, tent by post fa save telegraphic expense and\ undue \ use of the tyire*, bat intended to be treated, on receipt, with V^inwi feyaetfUiog oA if it had been telegraphed Tc save time and formcUuies it u worded and sty bed a* if a kiJ. bet* to despatched,] From Britain, Bushire. To Retaxanduia, London ■ # No. 55/925. Bushire, Dated the 18th July, 19*5•. The High Coinuissioner for India has been requested in my Express Letter No. 55/923 dated the 18th July, 1945 (copy enclosed) to purchase spare parts for Crossley engines in the Power House attached to the Consulate-General at Bushire. 2 . I shall be grateful if the highest possible priority shipping space can be provided as these spare parts are very urgently required. The engines for which they are required are very old and are continually breaking down causing considerable dislocation to our lighting and power arrangements.G0VERN1IENT OF INDIA. Dbpaetmhnt, EXPRESS LETTER [iV. B, This is an ORIGIN AM M NSSAG gent bp post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and jomnalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] Britain, Buushire* The High Conaaiesioner for India, London* So - 66/ ' Bus hire, theJuly, i.'46*. Oh this Consulate-General requesting the Government of India in the External Affaire Department to supply spare parts for Crossley engines, the latter directed us to place orders for their supply on one of the two Panel Importers in India quoted in their letter Ho* D. 882 -a/ 46 dated Simla the 5th April, 1946* These Panel Importers now intimate that the spare parts required are not stocked by foreign agents and suggest procurement direct from Croscley Brothers Ltd*, Qpenshaw, Manchester II, gigland* 2* I be grateful therefore if you will kindly arrange to purchase from the manufacturers the spare parte for Croesley engines as in the list attached, and to despatch them at the earliest possible date to Bus hire* The parts are moat urgently required as the engines arc continually breaking down* 3* The India Office has been requested to provide high priority shipping spacs* 4 . Expenditure Is adjustable by the Accountant General, Central Revenues^ Hew Delhi by raising a debit against this Residency under the head 60-Civil Works-External Affairs* 5 . % shall be glad if you will kindly telegraph through the India Office as soon as the spare parts are shipped from the U* K. Britain* The Issue of the above has been authorised* v Secretary to the Political Resident Y18/7* 101 ^ s&amp;p (M-1645) 29 - 400 , 000 . ^ the Perwian Gulf.- - ! K«. 65/ ^ Copy forwarded to the Under Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Department, Simla, with reference to letter Ho. nil dated the 21st Hey. 1946. from Messrs Kilburn and Company 9 4 Fairlie Place. Calcutta, agents in India of Crossley Brothers Ltd., x»eacL with Foreign, Simla letter Ho. D. 882 —a/ 46 dated the 6th April, 1946, for information. Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf* h vn &amp;El A 1. , A 10 . 11 . List of sparo parts of Crossloy Engines 113160 and 113161-Typo F. 0. fi. I ngines No. Nomonclaturo of the articloB. Big end Bearing complete wiih bolts and nuts. Exhaust valves (all steel). Admission valves i.e. air valves. Exhaust Air valve springs. ' ' ' bodies. Fuel pump complete. Fuel springs complete. Lubricator complete. Cylinder liners with necessary oil tubes 9 packings and rubber rings. Piston complete with rings 9 gudgeon pins and brushes. Outer bearing without pedestal. 88 ' Quant|ity required. 5“Pairs. 6 Nos. 6 ' 6 ' 3 w 2 w 2 ' 2 ** 2 2 2 Pairs. Part II. Fitting materials and tools required. 12. Wheel valves 2* diameter for water pipe linesT 13. N egleweewM 14. H wJwewHHe 6 Nos. 4 ' with both end double flangers complete. 15. Pipe 4 N diameter length 18' to 20'. 16. Couplings 4*. 17. Unions 4”. 18. Anti friction white metal for the bearing 9 superior quality. 19. Soft-tin or Ranga for tinning up the bearing shells before they are fitted with white metal. 20. Flexite l.e. soldering paste. 21. White lead (for pipe jointing). 22. Main bearings l.e. crank shaft bearings. 23. Piston rings (compression). 24. ' * (oil). 25. Gudgeon pins bushes. 36. Copper or steel pipes connections for fuel pump. 27. Flexible coupling bolts complete. 28. Half compression valves cosqplete with body. 29. Bolts and nuts complete (for big end bearings) 30. Copper washers for fuel sprayers and lubricator. 1 ' 1 ' 6 ' 1 ' 1 Cwt. 1 lb. 1 ' t Cwt. Sets l.e.4 Pairs. 1 Dozen. 6 Nbs. 4 ' 1 Dozen. 2 ' 2 Nos. 1 Dozen. 2 » each kind. Yll/7. /L f &lt;/ office! 'tlephout&amp;fy.KC In^tfnnuntca \r C A. CO 3C THE HlfiH COMMISSIONER FOR T j -3- ACKPOOL South Shore 4|085. Ext. Telephqi A n^^Sfftnunication on this subject ixmaD5mcxm.± ! Address for Inland Telegrams — INfolAMEN, BLACKPOOL ■91 be addressed to KK3CC STORE DEPARTMENT,'; ^. BLACKIp Please quote in your reply ^ OL. oaHUOMvJ. Your ref ^EXT. 1187/45. Dear Harrison, 5th July 1945. 0.0. With reference to letter dated the 28th June 19k5&gt; the Diesel Generator Set for Bushire has now been approved excepting for the oil cooler* It is proposed to ship the plant without the oil cooler, which will folla^ but it is not expected that particulars of despatch will be available for two or three weeks. Yours sincerely. F.A.K* Harrison Esq., External Departmen India Office, LONDON. S wd/a Whitehall, VJ A 9 V / f I • (XPr. JUL. 1945 OFFICE(/ 2 * /xrc V-7 OFFIC MCA CO 3&lt; THE HlfiH COMMISSIONER FOR INDI TeUphom^^L\CK?OOl, South Shore 4$085. Ext....» A n^^nnunication on this subject t ? be adSvessed to ifaO Address for Inland Telegrams — INDIAMEN, BLACKPOOL 91 INDI^jj Sj^ORE DEPARTMENT, BLACKPOOL. Please quote in your reply .S.QiZl?^-0 PBD* j 'B.u ^ (IdbnsJ . You, 1187/45. Dear Harrison, 5th July 1945. no. With reference to my letter dated the 28th June 19^45&gt; the Diesel Generator Set for Bushire has now been approved excepting for the oil cooler. It is proposed to ship the plant without the oil cooler, which will follay but it is not expected that particulars of despatch will be available for two or three weeks. Yours sincerely. F.A.K. Harrison Esq., External Department, India Office, V/hitehallTJ LONDON. S.Y/.1. JUL 1945 ^OlA OFFICE/ LETTER FROM INDIA No. Dated 1H C 4 CO 30000 - 8 * 4 5 OFFICE OF THE HIGH COMMISSIONER FOR INDIA X Address for Inland Telegrams — INDIAMEN, BLACKPOOL Telephone —BLACKPOOL South Shore 42085. Ext....' DIRECTOR-GENERAL, * INDIA STORE DEPARTMENT, w'A BLACKPOOL.; ^ 0 i yMmyims&amp;mmMzxx&amp; ' ' 45 t / w Please quote in your reply WD.».. 9.0..X/44 Bl) • Your ref.: EXT.1187/45. 28 th Dear Harrison With reference to your letter ; ITo: EXT. 1187/45 dated 20th June 1945 to ? “^- ' West, the Deisel Generator Set for ‘/^/V Bush ire has not yet been shipped. The engine has been tested at Crossleys and the performance is generally satisfactory. 30 / The Inspecting Engineer was not satisfied that the type of oil cooler supplied will be effective under site conditions and the matter is now under discussion with the contractors. I will inform you as soon as a probable date of shipment is known. Yours sincerely. F.fl.K. Harrison, Esq., External Department, India Office, Whitehall, LOUDON.S.W.1.H C 4k CO 30000 OFFICE OF THE HIGH COMMISSIONER FOR INDIA. 7 ; Addres* for Inland Telegrams — Telephone —BLACKPOOL South Shore 42085. Ext INDIAMEN, BL^^KPOOL Any communication oh this subject to be addressedjo — 1 a tke. f? IqWZ' ,01 ^Tm^REPARTMENT, '' ^ BLACKPOOL Please quote in your reply _ • 0^7 9ti -o;. l9 ; :-5. ^ 1 M o / 1 aM.m taaMMutwam, bvmm: Your^ref. inon J Deax Karri |o youf* letter ds.ted the 7 th IIsxch^^i^^^^SSSaBa^brder placed with Messrs. Crossley Srothers Ltcu , for c. diesel electric generator set for Bushire, there ha.s been sone delay in delivery of the electrical equipment. The contractors no 7 . r say, however, that this equipment is well in hand and that they expect to have it ready for test by the riddle of this month* If the result of the test is satisfactory, the plant should be ready for shipment one month later. Yours sincerely.v m AIB MIm..- From - The Under Seqy. to the Goyarnmant or India in the tetarnal Affaire Department, Simla, To - - The Hon'ble the Political Ha aidant' in the Persian Gulf, Buahire. X. Memorandun No. F. 132-A/44. ; Dated Simla, the ^ lh&gt; August 1944. tz / / f f*, r* r ^ Cj Subject:- Establishment of a P.W.D. Electrical and Mechanical Workshop at Bushire. P y' ) O/ J. KX ■ cJCAJ&amp;r* Reference your letter No. FWD-63/101# dated the 2nd July 1944* I u 1(1'2* In the circumstances explained, the GoTernment of India are pleased to sanction the establishment of a P.W.D. Electrical and Mechanical Workshop at Bushire at a cost not exceeding Rs. 5,000/- for equipping it with plant and tools and also the creation of a temporary post of a Itatamud: Mechanic in Charge up to the end oi February 1945 or the termination nu War whichever is earlier, in the first instance, on the 0£-following rates of pay and allowances i «..•«« ..«•• Pay. ..••• Free quarters or House rent allowance. Customs Compensation allowance. .. Special Pay iQulf Allowance).•••.. Dearness Allowance. •••••••. •••.• Rs. 150-10-200 Rs. 30/-/- p.m. fe. 25/-/- p.m. fis. 7fi/-/- p^B. at the current rates. a.g. 17655 1944 Suitable reduction in the rate of pay should be suggested in due course, if the post has to be continued after the war. 3. The expenditure involved, which is debitable to W 50-Civil Works', should be met as far as possible, from lithin the sanctioned budget grant at your disposal for the current financial year, failing which It may be included in the &gt;view of i idia in tl failing which it may i ant to*'be submitted by you to the Government of Department of Labour in December next. Sd/- V.B. Arte, Under Secretary to the Govt, of India. Copy, with copy of letter replied to forwarded to the Department of Labour with reference to their si u.o. No. E31/55, dated the 24th July 1944.Copy of a latter Vo* pvvD-63/101, dated the 2nd July 1944 fron the Hon*bid the political Resident in the Persian Gulf to the Secretary to the Gere meant of India in the Hxternal Affairs Departaunt, jfe« Delhi* Subjects- Hstablishnent of a p.e*D* Hleetrioal sad Meohanieal WorkBhof^t Bu shire* In the year 1930 the Persian Golf Independeat (P.w.D*) pi vision was reiuoad, presumably en grounds ef economy, to the rank of a Sub-Division. At tne sane tine the Hie Ctrl eal and Meohanleal bub-m vision wag reduced to tne r”nk of an Hie Ctrl cal and Mechanical Section and the gub-Bi vl slonai Off leer In charge was replaced by a pi nt driver (Mr* Roberta) ae Xleetrlesl and Mechanical Aeeiatant* It has not befen possible to ascertain hoe the Hleotrloal and Mechanical sub-Dlvision was orgrnised prior to the arrival ef Mr* Roberta but it appears that the officer in charge of the SleetriedL and Maohanloal gtib-Bi vision was ds pen dent for the pur posse cf repairs etc., on the military workshops and surplus stores whith were located in Rushire after the Great ¥' r of 1914-18* Mr* Roberts was in poseeeelon of his own aet of tools and workshop plant (including lathee) and during the period he held the post ef Hleotrieal and Mechanical Assistant and until discharged in October 1949 he heed these teele and plant for the repair and maintenance of Government property* On uis departu © last year Mr* Roberts sold hjs tools and plant with the result that the present Hleotlreal and Mechanical Assistant has been It ft without the me&lt;3B8 to repair or maintain the pdwer house engines, eleetrloi installations etc* ^ 8* The executive Engineer in charge of the dub-Division has, during the last nine months, mads a survey of ©11 Government property in the charge of the public Works Department in Bushire and reports that the absence of a properly equipped forkehop has been largely iesponslble for the deterioration of the pea or house engine and for the present bad state of repair of the electrical and meehanlod. installations* the Government of India will recall th&lt; t they have recently had to sanction the purchase of a Croesiey Heavy Oil Hnglne and 16 K#w, generating set for the Rahman! main power house and a 10 H*P* Rust on engine and generator for MM Bushire Residency town office* the Bxeoutive Engineer considers that had there been a proper workshop and a quailfiedneohanie in charge of it the old engines could have been kept in good repair for at least another five years* Wnt**x Unfortunately it is not only the power house engines which have deteriorated from lack of workshop facilities and at present the whole electrical installation i*e* supply lines, wiring interior and external, fans, switches, lights, etc*, all require constant attention and repairs* It may alee be recalled that in 1937 the drinking water distillation plant broke down and oould not be repaired* This state of affaire has been continuing for nearly fifteen years and the maintenance of the power house and electrical and mechanical installations is no longer possible with the existing facilities and staff. Concurrently with the arrival of the two new engines and generators the Jbt risk ef the loss of Govt* money will be further increased* The Govt* of India have reeently sanctioned the purchase of a 3 ton truok for the Bu shire P*W*D*, and a 3 ten truck and a 16 ewt* truok for the Residency* If theee vehicles • which it is essential to keep in running order - are^o be maintained then the provision of a ^-ehopjta even mere necessary than in previous years* 3 . To meet theee diffioultlee and to obviate further waste of Govt* money the Bxeeutlve Engineer has proposed that a Public forks Deptt* workshop in charge of a qualified mechanic should be established in Bashirs at the earliest possible date* Me suggests that the workshop should be opened ae soon ae the new Electrical and Mechanic* Assistant arrives and he has already begun/&lt;/ - t . ^gua tc collect goilc of ttL« more •secntlal tools. A sun of Rs# 5,000/- am 5c required la t&amp;e current financial yoer to •quip the *orfcuiop wlta plant end tools. *• The BzeoutlTS iinglneer has also following proposal* la reap set of the terse mechanic in charge of the' workahcpt- subaltted the of serTloe of the (a) The post to he permanent and not on the work-eharged establishment list. (h) pay in the eoafte of 150-10-200 House rent allowanoe or free quarters. Customs Compensation allowance* Special pay (Oulf Allowance.) Doarneha Allowance at the current S R*. 190 “iO “800 iH. ft. 30 83 Tv- I ratesi fis. 75/-/- The annuel expenditure will seount to 5120/- which sum cannot he met from the existing sanctioned budget demamd. 5. Prom the foregoing paragraphs It is &lt;&amp; ar that the immediate establishment of a public Works Dsptt. workshop and the appointment of a mechanic in charge are essential. Co Torment hare already suffered nfeoael dor able lose ot mono* owing to the lack of workshop facilities and'It would,be false economy to endeavour further to maintain valuable Government property without the neoeosary equipment or staff. The Executive Engineer who has, stnoe his arrival in Bush!re, made a thorough*survey of Govt, property in the charge of the publle Works Dsptti has stated that unices a workshop is ostabliahment at m early date ho cannot hold himself responsible for the efficient maintenance of’ the existing engines, the two new engines or the electrie&amp;l installations, in thsee elreumst&amp;ncee I strongly endorse his proposals and recommend thrt the eanotion of theOovt. #f India te the establishment of a w rkshop find the employment of a mechanic as outlined in paragraphs 5 and 4 abeve, be communicated at a very early date, ••a**DRAFT LETTER. Ext. 4858Aii. h W.F. West, Esq., India Store Department, Blackpool. Dear West, Will you please refer to your letter of 27th October last No. WD. 907 /RRB., regarding the order placed with Messrs. Crossley Brothers Limited for a Diesel Electric Generator Set for Bushire ? We should be glad to learn whether you can confirm that this order will be completed next month.L * » OFFICE OF THE HIGH COMMISSIONER FOR INDIA. / , / ds&gt; Blackpool South Shore 42085. Ext. ...3..* An&gt; communication on this subject to be addressed to— THE DIRECTOR-GENERAL. ilNDIA STORE DEPARTMENT, BLACKPOOL. and not to any individual bv name. A/S \ Address for Inland Telegrams —• INDIAMEN, BLACKPOOL. Please quote in your reply V/D* 907 /.'f32&gt; • Your ref. EXT.*,247l/41. W T : 4 47th October, 1944. Dear Harrison, Contract No.D.907/6969/30.5.44. Diesel Electric Generator Set for Bushire - Messrs. Crossley Brothers Ltd. Further to Thompsons letter of the 20th October, I enclose a letter dated 13th October, in original, from the Electric Construction Co.Ltd., addressed to India Office v&gt;hich the Military Department have forwarded to us due, no doubt, to firm* s failure to quote your reference. \7e have taken a copy of this letter 1 or our file, and in the circumstances stated by them we have telegraphed Bushire as follows:- 'Your telegram dated 13 October S 166 generator set now anticipated ready February butywill endeavour to expedite delivery as much as possible”. F. A.K. Harris on Esq., Political &amp; External Dept., India Office, LONDON, S.W.l. Ycurs sincerely.THE ELECTRIC CONSTRUCTION COMPANY LIMITED (ESTABLISHED 1882) MS. LJH. TELEPHONE * WOLVERHAMPTON 21455 (7 lines) e\c\c REGD TRADE MARK HEAD OFFICE AND WORKS : BUSHBURY ENGINEERING WORKS WOLVERHAM PTON TELEGRAMS : “ELECTRIC. WOLVERHAMPTON” ^3th October, MANUFACTURERS OF ALU KINDS OF ROTATING ELECTRICAL MACHINERY, STATIC TRANSFORMERS, MERCURY-ARC AND METAL PLATE RECTIFIERS. SWITCH AND CONTROL GEAR. PJ. 356 . OUR REFERENCE 4- ^ YOUR REFERENCE CORRESPONDENCE TO BE ADDRESSED TO THE COMPANY, NOT TO INDIVIDUALS. fhe Under secretary of State for India, ^ India Office , Whitehall, LONDON, S. W. 1. 17 OCT 1944 Dear Sir, CR03SLEY BROS. LTD. SUB-ORDER R. 5511$. ' • We are In receipt of your letter of the 5 th Inst., with reference to the 16 -KW Generator, panel etc. we have in ^ f hand for the above. We find that this equipment is due to be completed by the middle of February. Satisfactory progress is being made, and we expect to oe able to complete by the due date. We shall use our best endeavours to complete earlier if possible, but invview of our present heavy commitments, we cannot promise to do so. Yours faithfully, THE ELECTRIC CONSTRUCTION CO.LTD. , 2 5 OCT 1944 | yr .. T- L &gt; f / r- iTOF Works Superintendent.. , f/.\ (J H C &amp; Co Ltd — 30m-5-44 ^ ^ ' OFFICE OF THE HIGH COMMISSIONER FOR INDIA. *' ' —— ■ II ■■■ ■— ^9 Telephone—ptfyKPo Anyjwfonjpncation on this subject to be addressed to — POOL South Shore 42085. Ext. 'Address/or Inland Telegrams — iilNDTAMEN. RLACK] • INDIAMi ;N, BLACKPOOL. ^ india^sj^r^; dew|r'i^i^ [, &gt; j BLACKPOOL. Please quote in your reply Vlj#D* 90l7/4|+^RRB. Your ref. :— ^ ' EXT,2471/41* Dear Harrison, 20th October 1944* Contract No.D.907/69 69 / 30 .5.44. Diesel Electric Generator Set for Bushire - Messrs. Crossley Brothers Ltd. With reference to the above generator set, we have now received a telegram from Bushire as follows? 'E /166 MY TELEGRAM E/102 JUNE 15TH PLEASE TELEGRAPH WHETHER. ENGINES HAS BEEN DESPATCHED DELAY ISfCAUSING GREAT INCONVENIENCE'. 2. In this connection will you please let me know whether Messrs.Electric Construction Co. have replied to your letter EDCTJy86/44_ dated 5 th October, a copy of which you forwarded to us, and if P.A.K,Harrison Esq., Politcal &amp; External India Office, LONDON, S.W. 1 . • » so/- 2 - ,/^S so whether they are alile to effect an improvement in delivery. We will then reply to Bushire. Yours sincerely, ♦ *2L&gt; H C. * CO. 10000 - 5 - 44 OFFICE OF THE HIGH COMMISSIONER FOR INDIA. Address for Inland Telegrams — Blackpool South Shoke 42085. Exi . INDIAMEN, BLACKPOOL. Any communication on this subject to be addressed to — THE DIRECTOR-GENERAL, INDIA STORE DEPARTMENT, BLACKPOOL. and not to any individual by name. Please i v te in your reply ^* ?? Q* 9 ^/RRB • Your ref 19 th October, 1944. Dear Harrison, Contract No,D.1621/ 96 / 1 2.7.44 for Oil Engine Set etc. With reference to your letter of the 13 th October the position is that no improvement in delivery has been found to be possible. Messrs. Ruston &amp; Hornsby require a Generator and Control Panel in connection with our contract. They have placed an order on Messrs. Lancashire Dynamo &amp; Crypto Ltd. and delivery has been promised by the end of February 1945. They sought the assistance of the Directorate of Industrial Electrical Equipment and we have been infomed by the D.i.E.E. that no improvement in delivery can be made owing to the firm’s heavy commitments on work of national urgency and that very little could be gained by transferring the order to another electrical firm. Messrs. Ruston &amp; Hornsby have however confirmed that they anticipate completing our contract in February, as originally promised. Yours sincerely, F. A. K. Harrison, Esq., Political &amp; External Department, India Office, Whitehall, LONDON. S.W.1.-27) CTT .4496/44 DRAFT Ii,TTER 'B.U. At.to. Mil O.o. ’A *F.West,Esq•, India Store Department, Blaci^ool. •- / 13 OCT 1944 y, '/O. &gt;•'7 i/4/r &lt;6/ /O. L&gt; Dear 'West, Will you please refer to your letter of 1st August to the Director of Royal / ‘^ r Engineer Equipment at the Ministry of Supply, reference 5.D.C.96/44.RRB, regar ding an order placed with Messrs* Ruston &amp; Hornsby on behalf of the Bush ire Residency for an engine and electric generating set’? We have had an enquiry froa the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf asking the present position with regard to the supply of this engine and generator, arifl. BVal'^''bi 5 0 lcid to leari'? 7 ^ fc+n * ' has nrovf;^ yr-.c-o-imo rl .^tr, n-r rl ^ T T F - A. K. HARRISONOFFICE OF THE HIGH COMMISSIONER FOR INDIA. TV/^Aow*?—B lackpool South Shore 42085. Ext 3 .».. Any communication on this subject to be addressed to — Address for Inland Telegrams— INDIAMEN, BLACKPOOL. INDIA STORE D INDIA STORE DEPARTMENT, BLACKPOOt- Please ''em your reply W-P* 9 Q 7 ■ Your ref. XSiXT* 183 eptember, 1944. Dear Harrison Contract No. D. 907/6969/30. 5.44. Diesel Electric Generator Set for Bushire - Messrs. Crossley Brothers Ltd. Will you kindly refer to my letter dated 25 th July, 1944* SD0/6969/43&gt; regarding the placing of the above Contract, and of the delivery offered by Messrs. Crossley Bros. Ltd., by December,1944. It now appears that completion may be held up due to non receipt of electrical equipment which the firm have ordered from the Electric Construction Co.Ltd. , 16, John Dalton Street, Manchester, 2, under their Sub-Order R.55119. The delivery offered by the Electric Construction Co.Ltd. , is 26 weeks from about the end of July (early February 1945). We have approached the Electric Construction Co.Ltd., with a view to obtaining an improvement in delivery without much success. They have stated that they see no possibility of shortening the delivery period, but that they would keep the order closely before them, and if at a later date it is possible to expedite matters they would assuredly do so. A F.A.K. Harrison Esq. , letter/ Political &amp; External Dept., India Office, LONDON, S.W.1n ri letter from India Office will no doubt be of man* assistance in hastening supply, and perhaps you will be good enough to drop them a line. Yours sincerely,^ HL£ CO ^ OFFICE OF THE HIGH COMMISSIONER FOR INDIA. Blackpool South Shore 42085. ext 3 ^ Any communication on this subject to be addressed to — TH£ 0RECTOR-GENERAL, t INDIA STORE DEPARTMENT, i Address for Inland Telegrams — 1/2 INDIAMEN, BLACKPOOL. and not to any individual by name Please c 'e in your reply 96/44. RHB. Your ref. .^55/RK9 /Dv/* BLACKPOOL j • I 9-4 Sir, August, 1944. Contract No. D.1621/96/12.7.44 7 Oil EnpdLne Set Etc, for Bushire, I am directed to invite reference to your letter dated 24th May addressed to India Office and to inform you that on receipt of confirmation from the Board of Trade on 3rd July, the above contract was allotted and Messrs. Ruston and Hornsby were asked to proceed with supply and to forward a quotation. A quotation has now been received and is found to be generally satisfactory. Pina’s prices are therefore being accepted, but with regard to delivery they state as follows:- 'It is noted that this order is placed with the authority of the Industrial Supplies Department Board of Trade, Millbank, S.W.l. as given in their letter dated the 2nd Ju3y/44 reference I.S. under present coramitinenta we expect to be able to effect delivery in February 1945 T The final delivery date will be determined by the Flnistry of Supply (Branch R.E.9), Melbourne House, Aldwych, W.C.2., and will depend upon the relative urgency” of the demand in relation to the War effort.' The Director, . , Royal Engineer Equipment, Ministry of Supply, R.E.9*, Melbourne House, 8 th Floor. AL1OTCH, London, W.C.2. /It wasIt was assumed in ‘'/lew of the urgency of the requirements that an engine would he :iade available imaediately but in view of firm’s remarks, I shall be obliged if allocation can be arranged so to enable Messrs. Ruston &amp; Hornsby to effect a substantial improvement in delivery. I am. Sir, Your obedient Servant, Director-General, India Store Department. Copy for infonoation forv.'arded to P.A.K. Harrison Esq., Political &amp; External Dept., India Office, LONDON, S.W.l. yi. F- WEbT (Ref. EXT. 2205/44. ) and . „ . , . ♦ * The Assistant Secretary, Industrial Supplies Department, Board of Trade, Ullbank, LONDON,S.W.I. (Ref. I.S. ? June 1944)'1A r Allotted to a»and S.Re-partment^ Copy to External Department* f ^LE COPY INWARD TULK^RAH ^ *«r * □71 — £-■, A 2 Yvom To Dated Reoeived COHFIDENTIiVL 00»E TK 1 6695 f 57 ^ jtf Government of India# External Affairs Dept* J /V Secretary of State for India# p* - Hew Del hi f 16th Felixtiary# 1944. 19 0 00 hour's# 16th February# 1944. 1771. Supply Department (? letter No* ) WII'-S16(69) December 24th. Item 4. Grateful if special assistance could be given to secure priority and shipping space for one* of Kelvin engines with spare parts and accessories urgently required by Sheifch of Koweit#OFFICE OF THE HIGH COMMISSIONER FOR INDIA. )MMI3p TVfc/^on*—B lackpool South Shore 4208 s. ^xt. 3 ^ /!«&gt; communication on this subject to be addressed to — 1 TH^- RECTOR-GENERAL, INDIA STORE DEPARTMENT, BLACKPOOL| no/ any individual by name. Please quote in your reply 3. l}. 0* 6969/43 RRp* Your ref/~4 EXT.. 2471/41. * ‘ ^ Dear Harrison, Address for Inland Telegrams — INJQiAMEN, BLACKPOOL. 14 '' 1 O D ^ '■ 25th July 1944. ,L, With reference to your letter o: 22nd July the position is as follows. the Byahatti T s letter to the Ministry of Supply to which you make reference, relates to our contract D. 907 / 6969 / 30 .5.44 placed with Messrs.Grossley Dros. X.*L.d. for a Diesel Electric Generator set demanded in letter No. P\/D. 55/oO dated 14.1.44 from, the Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. The outstanding queries regarding the electrical equipment have now been settled and the firm are proceeding with manufacture. Delivery is expected to be available in December and we will press firm to bring forward this delivery date if at all possible. The Ministry of Supply have stated that they cannot assist any further. The Ministry of Supply letter dated 24th .uay to you relates to a demand from the British Consul General, Bushire, in telegram No. A/558 dat&amp;d 24.B.Uh for a generator set in conneSlicM'i with wnlch the Board of irade have allocated a Ruston &lt;3: Hornsby engine. Delay occurred in the receipt of confirmation from the Board of Trade regarding this allocation. On receipt 01 this confirmation on the 3rd June, we asked Messrs. Ruston &amp; Hornsby to proceed with /Ui-J F.A. K. Harrison, Esq., Political &amp; External Dept., India Office. Lnnrinn v 1. L Li**r. our ./C ontract.O C3 v cntract No. D.1621/86/12.7.44 and to forward quotation. Their reply has not yet been■ received and we are reminding firm to-day by telegram. We will let you know further in this matter as soon as we have firm T s reply. Yours sincerely,wm-j EXT. 21^7 z 0 ^ DUiPT li^m E.H.Thaanpson, Esq.., India Store Department, Blackpool. a a juu^ 4 Dear Thompson, -47411 ^DU please refer to Byahatti' s Yett^er ’to' fHe k Ministry of &gt;Wt£&gt;plyv ’ *Stv. U Vv J&gt;. 1L ?» 17, Ik 'b No. SDO.6969/43 K&amp;B&gt; ox'Ist^juhe, and to . ; c .. Ministry of Supply letter to this \ — # —, , Department of 24th May, a «copy of v/hich vTas sent to jom on 6th June, regarding electrical equipment required by the Bushire Residency. As we understand it, one Rus|(ton &amp; Hornsby engine, type l.YHR has been made available for immediate despatch to Bushire ,and the Ministry of Sup ply have been asked to arrange allocation as early as possible for the supply by Messrs. Crossley of the rest of the electrical /equipmentS' !LE COP r OFFICE OF THE HIGH COMMISSIONER FOR INDIA. Telephone — BLACKPOOL SOUTH SHORE 42085 . EXT Any communication on this subject to be addressed to — ; . TjfcHt/ ^LRSfCTOR-GENERAL, ! /* “ • INDIA STORE DEPARTMENT. , C. % | BLACKPOOL. and not to any individual by name. «% y I O/i 4 Please quote in your reply £ # £ .0 # 6960/43* HUB. - - Your r?^ 255/lffi9/U^, Address for Inland Telegrams — INDIAMEN, BLACKPOOL. lat June 1944* Sir, Inden t frcti ^the_ Bri tis h He sidei’c y an d Con sulate Ge tieralB us hire, for Cross ley F.0.K,2 . I rrpe engine e tc. With reference to correspondence ewiing with your letter dated 11th April I have to infom you that confirmation was obtained from Biisliirc tliat Messrs. Crossley*s altemr.tive offer of a 3-cylinder, vertical 1X1^5 ty;)e engine would l&gt;e suitable for thoir rciiiuirenents. The firm wrre accordingly asked to forward a quotation for a complete equipment. This quotation has now been received but some points in connection YTith the electrical equipment require clarification. The mechanical ;x&gt;rtion of their tender was, however, considered satisfactory aixl tiiey Iiave aocordingjy been asked to proceed with supply under this De, artnent’s contract J T o* D.9CT7/G969/ 30.5,44, The deli vox*/ now qjrosaised by fim is six months after receipt of necessary autiiorization enabling them to proceed. This is an improvement on the delivery previously estimated by them, i,e, 8-9 nonths, A further telegram lias, however, /been The Director, Itoyal Engineer 'Equipaent, Ministry of Supply, It#E,9, Melboui'ne House, .ALDW x 8 i i, Q JUN \MD\k QFHCE! x x^ / - \; I'v \ been received from Btatfdre I'eq.uesbin^, urgent des^wtch of engine at. hot weather has begun and the old engine is deteriorating further. Ih the circunotanoer, it will be greatapprecia ted if allocation aan 'be arranjled vvitii e vi^Tw to enable Messrs. Irossley Bros., to bring forward the deliverer date as much as possible. I am, bir, * Your obedient Servant, Sgd. R. R. BYAHAni Dire ctor*vrene ral, India Store Department. j Copy for information forwarded to;- Political &amp; External Dept., India Office, Whitehall, * * * LONDON, S.W.I. (P.ef. Ext. 1771/44.)• MGS. Ex„122. Tel. No.—Temple Bar 3036 Telegraphic Address— “Splymin, London.” Any farther communication on this subject should quote the following number ^ 255/KE9/DV/. Your Ref. Ext*2205/Vw ! 'rvwv£§&gt; MINISTRY OF SUPPLY D.R.E.E. 8th Floor, MELBOURNE HOUSE, ALDWYCH, W.C.2. 194.„4 Mu Sir, \^i Ti 24u7 ^ . refer fco your letter dat ed the 22nd inst 0 under reference yT/ 2205 / in connec tion with the? sup ply ii&gt;E 4n Oil /Engine and Generator for the BrrBonsuite-General and Residency at Bushire, I confirm my telephone conversation with Mr. Harrison on the 23rd inst. stating that arrangements had been made through the Board of Trade for the supply of a Ruston &amp; Hornsby Engine Type 1 Y.H.R. for this purpose. Mr. Taylor of the Board of Trade is communicating with the Director-General, India Store Department, Blackpool, stating that this Engine is available for this purpose. i r &gt; Your obedient Servant, cretary of State for India, f Whitehall, S. W. 1. NEC*. ML. 1 ®' 3 TMAY1 0 ' 1 ■* &lt;pia .yf aas. India Office Copy to J. W. Taylor Esq., Board of Trade,?&gt; aRjiFT LjiTTaiR 3.0. SXX. 2205/44-. W 44 no. A3 % y\ To: The Director, Royal Engineer Eciuipraent, iiinistry of Supply, Melbourne House, Aldwych, ¥.0,2. Sir, n I am directed to refer to your letter r No•255/KE9/DW dated 28th April to the Office of the High Commissioner for India, India Store Department, regarding the supply of an oil engine and generator nroenfrly. »o-quinod for the British Consulate-General 0 / and Residency^Bushire. u y 1 0jxtd^) / (^) 0 ' ^ frying to the breakdown of the existing engine kJL ' -v the main Offices of the Residency are now without electric light and fans* In view of the extremely oppressive enervati-ng climate of Bushire daring awf»r-montho it is eooential for 7 the new engine Slv\^ reach there as^ soon as possible / cu^ttie Secretary &amp;X( ^ ^t‘db it* of S cate would/be grateful Hi* ^onln ynnr rood ^ k offiooe ^/to exp^dii&gt;^ delivery, &amp; picE J.— 201 - 10 - 41 . pi p ^.QPV ? THE HIGH COMMISSIONER FOR INDIA. ■ / ■ INDIA STORE DEPARTMENT, BLACKPOOL. 15 th May 1944. L * Telephone : South Shore Blackpool 42085. Dear Harrison, Indent for Oil Engine Etc With reference to your letter dated 11th May and further to paragraph 2 of Byahatti’s letter to you dated 2nd May, we have received no further information in this matter from the Ministry of Supply to whom we have just sent a reminder. With regard to early delivery it would appear that a letter from India Office to the Ministry of Supply may be of great assistance. Their reference is letter No. 255/RE9/DW dated 28th April,1944, and the address is Director, Royal Engineer Equipment, Ministry of Supply, Melbourne House, Aldwych, London, W.C.2, Yours si v F.A.K. Harrison Esq., Political &amp; External Dept., India Office, Whitehall, LONDON, S.W.I.Ext, 196V hk* &lt; 1 19^4* Dear Thompson, With reference to your letter Ho*S D.O,6969/4v5 --'RB of 2nsJ May, 1 -yarding the pur cl ms© of electrical equipment for tlio Residency, Bushire, we have new received a further telegram from the Political Resident, referring to his telegram of March 24-th, stating tliat Ime main offices of the Residency are now without fans or electric light and asking us to do whatever possible to expedite the despatch of the engiuie. ^ E.II*Tlxsirpson, Esq., India Store Department, Blackpool.I am sure that you are already doing your utmost in this direction, but it may perhaps be worth emphasising the dei* 5 ndence of the Residency on electricity to mitigate the discomforts of the extremely oppressive climate at Bushire. Yours sincerely.m m H k° ■ || 1963/^4 DRArT let-isr JS.H* Thoms^on, Esq., India Store Department, Blackpool. Dear* Thomson, With reference to your letter No.S.DO 69^9/43 RRB of 2nd May, regarding the purchase of electrical equipment for the Residency,we have now received a further telegram from ^ £ fan ^ HuM'L 2if; ^* er the Political Resident^stating that the main offices of the Residency are now without fans or electric light and ^fv i?i&gt;uV ^4^ tv t , ■- jvx ^r asking vnnij/the despatch of the engine, may bo ujqjo j-ifed. &gt; 1 the order with l f 01 * anytfiing that you can do to has tew the delivery *'‘1 I am glad to leamfrom Mr. Bynfe^fcti's letter of 2nd I should be gratepal,therefore,if would pi srs. Crossley Br^s* as soonyaa possible, Lng that you ^an do to engine, V* May that the Board of Trade to arranging an early required by the Residency. been approached with a view ocation for the second engine I'eqrs sincerely, ) zak haMflNMMNifei IV, {1A Mr. Han 1 9 V The Bus hire Residency seems to require two sets of electrical equipment. As the order for the first engine has not yet been placed with Messrs. Crossley I doubt if it can reach Bushire this summer, 'tfith regard to the second, I am not clear whether the Board of Trade allocation would be for its manufacture or its supply, in any case there will probably be some delay. As the I.S.B. have the matter in hand I doubt if there is anything further we can do at the moment.*2S In andition to Crossle?, h, I . no anc gene ator va.:c! T vas subiect of ; y telegram No. E/26 of 17th March, the Government of India In External Affairs Department, in their telegram ' T c. 414 AE of March 18th, have now sanctioned purchase ' in United Kingdom of engine and electric generator 'or Residency main office, Bwshire. 2. Grateful if you r r ill purchase and export suita' le plant tc Bushire at very earliest possible date. 3. Specifications of plant required are as follows Oil engine o' about ten repeat ten or 12 repeat 12 Brahe Horse Power preferably diesel with two hundred and thirty repeat- two hundred and thirty volts direct at direct current generator and between six repeat six and eight repeat eight 1 ilowatts ireferably rainshaft coup1in- drive or complete with pulleys. Plant should be complete in itself with switch board volt and amp meters, water cooling tanbs of capacity 2000 gallons, water and exhaust piping, essential spare parts, an-d set of tools. Engine made by Huston of Lincoln preferred if available. 4. Please as 1 suppliers, to forward Blue print o^ mlant lay cut by air mail in advance of plant. 5. Expenditure is adjustable by Accountant General Central Revenues, New Delhi.J * ' TELEGRAM From To No. Dated G.T.C. Brltconsul, Bushlre. Retaxandum, London. f\[5(oO ! 24th March, 1944’ &lt;2 O Reference para 6 of my telegram No.^A/558 r ^ ^ ^ 1 —| ^ —j - to High Commissioner for India Copy passed to you. 2. Grateful if high priority shipping space can be provided so that Residency main office is not deprived of electric fans during summer. • BRITCONSUL -Address for Inland Telegrams — itfDlAMEN, BLACKPOOL 48 JWpA&lt;w«—B lackpool South Shore 42085. Ext. \ 5 Please quote in your reply S J1.0.6969/+3.ERB. YojTNf.:- Sxt. 1771/44 2nd 2nd May 1944 „ Dear Mr. Harrison, Further to Mr. Thompson^ letter of today’s date, I enclose a copy of a telegram dated 29th April 1944 which has Just been received from Bus hi re in reply to our telegram dated 25th April. We will now take the matter up with Messrs. Crossley Bros. Ltd. and obtain a quotation with a view to an order being placed. With regard to the engine, etc. demanded in telegram A/558 dated 24th March 1944 from Bushire, a reply has now been received from the Ministry of Supply, Royal Engineer Equipment. They have taken the matter up with the Board of Trade with a view to arranging an early allocation. Yours sincerely. F.A.K. Harrison, Esq. L-»XV.* JL ^ Political &amp; External Dept., India Office, Whitehall, LONDCXT, S.W.l.COPY S.D.0.6969/43. RRB. DECODE OP TELEGRAM Prom - Political Resident in Persian Gulf, Bushire. To - D.G*, I.S # D., Blackpool. Dated- 29.4.44., Bushire. Re^d.-1.5.44. Blaclqjool. E/60 Your telegram dated April 24th number 10172 Crossley 3 cylinder vertical BWB 3 850 RIM direct coupled preferable generator should be direct coupled? site altitude is? sea level maximum shade temperature 98 repeat 98 Fahrenheit? relative humidity? rise-s to up to 90 per cent repeat 90 per cent climate is generally humid cooling tank-s can? not be provided locally?OFFICE OF THE HIGH COMMISSIONER FOR INDIA. Address for Inland Telegrams — INDIAMEN, BLACKPOOL. Any communication on this subject to be addressed to — THE DIRECTOR-GENERAL, INDIA STORE DEPARTMENT, and not to any individual by name. BLACKPOOL. Pleas«~ '' ote in your reply . S*D#0# 6969/43. RRB. ! n / ^ 2nd'May 1944 Your ref. •1773/44 Dear Harrison, With reference to your letter dated 28th April 1944 to Dell, the position is as follows (a) In a letter P.W.D-55/80 dated 14th January 1944 we received a demand from the British Consul, Bushire, for 1 F. 0 .E .2 type Crossley heavy oil engine, a generator and a generator panel t • • • • • * (b) In a telegram A/558 dated 24th March 1944 we received a demand from the British Consul General, Bushire, jo^/ for one oil engine of 10 - 12 H.P. and a 230 volts , i D.C. generator fifa. With regard to (a), after consultation with the Director, Royal Engineer Equipment, Ministry of Supply, Melbourne House, Aldwych, W.C.2. (ref. 255/KE9/ DW; and Messrs. Crossley Bros., Ltd., Openshaw, Manchester, 11. (ref.WN/OC) we /forwarded a telegram dated 25th April to Bushire (copy enclosed). A reply to / that telegram has not yet been received. With regard to the delivery stated therein, Messrs. Crossley Bros, have stated as follows 'Bearing in mind our present very heavy conmitments in regard to both particular sizes of engines mentioned above, we could not expect to forecast a delivery period earlier than 8/9 months from receipt authorisation to enable us to proceed'. /With regard F.A.K. Harrison, Esq., Political &amp; External Dept., India Office, Whitehall, LONDON, S.W. 1GQPY OF CODE TEIEGRiiM. From - Director-General, India Store Dept., Blaclqpool. To - The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Datec^ 25.4 .44. 10172 Your telegram dated 16th March E.26 F0E2 type engine out of production can supply Cross ley 3 cylinder vertical BWB3 850 RHI direct coupled or single cylinder horizontal 38 BHP 330 RBI direct coupled or belt driven delivery 9 months are these acceptable if so state 'type preferred and v/hether generator to be direct coupled or belt driven also give site altitude maximum shade temperature and relative humidity also whether cooling tanks can be provided locally.EXT, 1771/Vf. IvIr,Harrigon - The E &amp; 0 Department have heard nothing further from the IoSoD, about this, and are doubtful -whether anything can be done to hasten delivery, though they consider it worth while talcing the matter up 0 *) a o. 'Js ^ ^ 1 2 , a- It ^ WY&gt; DRAFT LETTER, P eB « Dell, ijSQ_c , India Store Department, Queens Hydro Hotel, Blackpool® %u, tyf) A no. l xr APR 1944 Dear Dell, With reference to ray letter of the 21st March, Ext ,1072/44, regarding the purchase of a Grossley Heavy Oil Engine, and other electrical equipment for the Residency, Bushire, we have now heard from the Political Resident that he understands from you that delivery pay bo delayed for several months. The Engine is urgently required as the existing Engines are deteriorating, in fact^ one will be out of action for five week^and a breakdown would deprive the Residency and other customers of light, fans, and refrigeration, J f ^ We' should be grataful ; therefore, : ^r tiny thing -7 early delivery of this • A ) F &gt; A - K- HARRISONM Ia) , Jsi. A * •; tJ i # ,, . ^ /CtAvJ f1 ^ ('^£5 ^ A t£'( tM \ -j “? “/-? ^ 1 'rft TK WARD 1 TBLBQRAJj l till 14(354, ! .Allotted to External Department. L( ~ T 1944 WORD CODE TELEGRAM r ' From To Dated Receiyed Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Secretary of State for India. Bushire, 09.00 hours, 21st April 1944. 14.30 hours, 21st April 1944. IMPORTANT. No. E/(?51) . My telegram E/26 dated March 17th. for Residency Electric Supply. Engine fx-r 3o&gt; 2. High Commissioner for India in his telegram No. 10,115 dated April 16th states delivery unlikely for several months. 3, I applied for sanction to purchase this Engine etc. in June last year. (Corrupt' group) A-existing eng ires have further deteriorated and one engine certain to be out of action for five weeks. The new engine is urgently required and I should be grateful if you would press for its shipment at very early date. r*W\I F!( p O Tmv.ASP TKLEOHAM y ^.-Lp j'fc ed to Extern al Depart 1 ~ ^ 1 1 I Q44 4054. ; From To Dated Received TELEGRAM Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Secretary of State for India. Bushire, 09.00 hours, 21st April 1944. 14,50 hours, 21st April 1944. &lt;j IMPOR TANT . No. E/(?51). My telegram K/26 dated March 17th. for Residency Blegtrlo GuuijI^ / M rig me High Commissioner for India in his telegra m No. 1 0,115 dated April 16th states delivery unl ilcely^for several monfchs. ;;;° . I applied for sanction to purchase this Engine etc* in June last year. (Corrupt group) existing engines have further deteriorated and one engine certain to be out of action for five weeks. The new engine is urgently required and I should be grateful if you would press for its shipment at very eariy date.5T&gt;) MT.1072/^ DRAFT I1STTHR. P*B. Dell, Esq., India Store Department, Queens Hydro Hotel, Blackpool. Dear Dell, V/ill you please refer to your letter to No. S.y.O. 69 6&lt;f/A 3 ' PBp.j Thomson of 3^d Larch^ regarding the pure has© of a Grossley Heavy Oil Engine, generating set, and generator parcel for the Residency, Bushire. (. 10 . As this equipment is destined for the Persian Gulf it does not come under the parcel Scheme, and the order may therefore he placed direct. The Resident is anxious that the highest / shipping priority should be accorded to this material since it is urgently needed to ensure that the Residency is not deprived of electricity and fans during the summer. , I understand from the E. d 0. Department here that you should be able to arrange 7 / shippingExternal Department, Please see letted from India Store Department, Blackpool. Q44 Blacl I should be glad of any informationwpi jjjjiiia OFFICE 0? THE HIGH COMMISSIONER FOR Ilf)I India Store Department, Blackpool. s S.D.Oi 6969/4-3*FBD. Dear Thomson, 3rd March, 1944• I have received a letter No* FWD-55/80 dated 14th January, 1944, from the British Residency and Consulate G-eneral, Bushire, asking that we shall purchase a Crossley heavy oil Engine of the 'F.O.E. 2' type, a generating set of 16 K*W# ccHiioound wound, 3-wire D*C. 450/500 Volts and a generator complete for the Residency Bushire. The Government of India in the External Affairs Department in their letter 120-//43 dated 12th November, 1943&gt; have sanctioned the purchase. I shall be glad if you will let me know whether we may proceed to place the order direct or whether this equipment will come under the ^anel Scheme. Yours sincerely, (Sd.) P.B.Dell. J. Thomson, Esq., O.B.E. , M.M*, India Office, Whitehall, LONDON, S.W.l.Bxt.772/44 '.No-t ^ «rch, '1944* Dear Thompson, We are informed by the Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, that in his Express letter No,' P.V *D»-55/80 of 14th January he has requested the I igh Commi ssioner to purchase a new Crossley Heavy Oil Engine, generating set and generator panel for the Residency Bushire. The Resident is anxious that the highest shipping priority should be accorded to this material, since it is urgently needed to ensure that the Residency is not deprived of electricity and Thompson, Esq,, fans/ India btore Department^, queens hydro Hotel, Blackpool,tans during the sunrier# • &lt;. I understand from the ♦ &amp; 0« Department hej*e that you should be able to arrange shipping priority as requested for this consignment, but if you require any support from us I should be glad if you will let me know* I am sending a copy of this letter to the Office of the High Com. issioner* Yours sincerely. UOr/ \ No. 120-A/43. E A I , ! Prom &gt; / 307 | The Under Secy* to the (fort* of India ‘ in the External Affairs Department 9 Simla- ■» /i To The Hon^le the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, flaafrirg. Dated Simla 9 the November 1943. SUBJECT:- Electric plant at Bushire* Sir. I am directed to refer to your letter No. 964/3/ P*W.D* 9 dated the 5th June 1943 and to say that, in the circumstances explained, the Government or India agree to the purchase of a new Crossley heavy oil engine, together with &amp; generating set (and a generator panel; of the specification described in para* 5 of your letter under reference* As no such electric plant is available in Lidia* the necessary arrangement may be made by you to obtain It direct from U*K* through the High Commissioner for India* 2 f The expenditure is chargeable to the head 'SO- Civil Works-Central-A* Original Works-Buildings: A*2.-Minor Works'* The Government or India authorise you to incur the expenditure in anticipation of the provision of funds* Every endeavour may kindly oe made to meet as much of Expenditure as possible by reappropriation from within your current year’s grant* The amount which cannot be so met may be included in your Review of Grants which is due in the Department of Labour in December next* 3* In accordance with the existing arrangements agreed to by His Majesty’s Government in regard to the method of classifying the capital expenditure in Iran and the Persian Gulf, the total expenditure on the purchase of the new plant which, it is hoped, will be more than &amp;• 2,5007- will be a charge on Indian revenues, but the maintenance' charges will be shared in moieties between the Government of India and His Majesty's Government* I have the honour to be, Sir 9 Your most obedient servant, Sd/- 7.B* Arte, Under Secretary to the Government of India*N*. a/384, datgd r &gt;cd. Ibth) Qritconaui, duahire. Foreign* New Delhi* Jr. tJZ.'ftSTi »« at Ifrans 8 per unit; and to var* i- !r 1 o witiiout reference to you to correspond *ioh 12 annaa rate* whenever nece^sdry* r*** ,OC| ~-jCt 3 ./&gt;c. ril i ijNOjA - tlTlcR -• --ZiveiD' 1 4-8^1942Tale^pr&amp;m Ho. o-i/Caiap, datad dimla^^the 26th May Froa:* Forei^, Sifala t To:- Britconaul, Buahire. Tour tolograra Ho. a/ 384 of 14th flay. Your proposal to fix rata for alactric charges at 8 Krafts per unit approved. You are authorised ta to vary rate in the future to correspond with 12 aijms par unit when ver necessary.'? In any further communication on tl^j^subject, please quote 2846/1535/2; and address— not to any person by name but to— I ^ ”■*' i „ i /! ( i 's ider-Secretary of Stabs,” 1 £.j 7 ' The Under Foreign Office, London, S.W.l Foreign Office. S • iY • 1. 22nd Inarch, 1941. if* ^ Sir, With reference to your letter p.Z. 398/41 of the 10th February I am directed by Mr. Winston Churchill to inform you that a moiety of the cost of the installation of 4 D.C. Ceiling fans complete with regulators in government buildings at Bushire, ^ amounting to 1370 rupees will be accepted as a charge on Imperial funds. % I am. Your Sir, obedient Servant, The Under-Secretary of State, India Office. ..m''*' ,i1 ' !l|eo».*ow.0*FT. 2 4WAR 941 INDIA OFFICErr i.o98/41. The Under Secretary of state, Foreign Office, Si, 10 feb 1941 I an directed by the Secretary of state for India to forward, for the information of the secretary of state for Foreign Affairs, a copy of a letter from the Government of India on the subject # of expenditure on certain electric / Dated 22nd October, 1940.) installations in Government 6^0** 1\u. Fu+t / buildings at Bushire, and to that a moiety of y I# SlUjl\tly CmcUJ of i&gt;cc) the cost involved^ may be accepted as a charge upon Inpe rial reve nues• fan} ft a, 4^ W&lt;ii iwtfui by fo, bflud' wiWtu MfarJ), tf’Flu fyl, a&gt;U i4i will be that the accepted principle of obtaining the prior t^notiun of H.M. G. 4e expenditure exceeding ^100 was not observed, in frM'g—caee. The Government of India have, however, taken ste^s to 'flu Corrtd broczdiUK L* falloujcci ensure that feriiuilag- oasos—4o not—oo-eur in future. 'Ifo - «*&lt;! '&gt; J P OI8SOWa ZlVlUfrO . sUflXL Cyrtv* gj. fU t-ioo tc W&gt; c4--i Ci fi** AvcU. 5^&gt;cvvt toAftvv^f' ”^tvi f NO.F.5-V40 From To The Secretary to the in the External ”,U|C ^,U ts^tUo. ^f c ) The Under Secretary of State for India, India Office, London, S.U.1. —B.Y ‘T’V ' v 'y 1^. ^ • (?s) t a rav^ ■jovesciiUiQof bndia 7^' J^fairs DepartiJent, J vjifr*' /&lt; 9 Dated Hew Delhi, the October 1940 Additions and alterations to the electric installa tions in Government buildings at Bushire. oir, . % t directed go scate txiat during 1933, under a mis caiman interpretation of the Central Public works Deoart- ment^Code rules, the lion 1 ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf^ accorded sanction to the installation of 4 , fans, complete, v/ith regulators in Government ouilaings at Bushire at an estimated cost of Hs. 1,400/-. x-ue actual expenditure incurred on this account amounted to Rs. 1,370/—. 2 - . ghe attention of the Political Resident has been arawn to the iact that sanction to this expenditure was not «viL,nin ms power and that a prior reference^should have been made to the Government of India. The Political Resident as a .result has now issued instructions to ensure that such a mistake v/ill not occur again. v L , ■ tc l\Ux\$e(f * J 3 v. , , In accordance with the accepted principle, the expenditure involved is divisible in moieties between the Government of India and His Majesty’s Government, and I~ am, .^ e f’ e ^ r 1 e 5 n /°, rec l u est that the approval of the latter xxx tooear nalx. the expenditure involved may kindly be obtained ana communicated to the Government of India as early as possiole. J I have the honour to be, Sir, four most obedient servant, | yj ior Secretary to the Government of India, —‘5 bJ / 1937 \ Gommmr of indi i i D&amp;AXMm OF INDUCT.a ^ &amp; LiBOUH. Public v.orka Branch* Teldtprfim No*AVl* Dated Hew Delhi, the 23rd January 1937 The Handle the Political Reaident in the ? ersian &lt;ulf, , I Bushire* Reference your letter No.81/D9/3, dated the 13th January to Foreign* Please telegraph iraaodiately how zauch expenditure could be incurred this year on renewal electric wiring Bushire buildings if additional grant is given and intimate wh&amp;t portion of it could be met by reappropriation* &gt;0 iKh.Telegrnm* Britconsul, Bushxre# Secretary Bepfirtment of In&amp;uetriea and Labour (Public Works Branch). Dated Bashir© the 27th January 1937 eceived Mew Delhi the 28th January 1937 • * • ♦ • Your telegram 4W1 of 23rd January. Mo .jj-penditurg can be incur red tins year in view of shortness of time for getting materials but if sanction to incur liability is r.-mted arrfju araent can be t;ade to pvt the work in hand.Foreign and Pclitical Department* F I'D a-J- V » From Foreign, New Delhi* To Britconsul, Bushire. Dated New Delhi, the f( February 19D7 Renewal of electric vnring in Government buildings at Bushire. Reference correspondence ending with your telegram to Works, dated the 27th January 1937. 2. In the circumstances the Government of India authorise y»u to place the necessary orders for the Stores required for the work in anticipation of formal sanction to your budget estimates for 1937-38 under r 41-Civil Works-Central-Non-Voted’ subject to the following conditions (1) that the stores ordered are not delivered before the commencement of the next financial year so that payment therefor will not require to be made before the 1st April 1937 and (2) that the expenditure will be accounted for against the allotment of Rs.28,000/- which will be placed at your disposal during 1937-38 under ’Civil Works’ for minor works. » » *- • The issue of the above 1ms been authorised. Under Secretary to the Government of India.■■■■PK GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. Department. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). [N.B—7'ii. &lt;. «» ORIGINAL message sent by AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save t ime and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department.] No. ?! 59/; Bushlr« 'h ■irte. 5 Dated ji&amp;ijami’ the / 3 Jajmaty ' P.Z. 79 37. tx From - Political Besident, Bushirc s ’434 To - Foreign, New Delhi Bepeated to Secretary of State fd ^ /^ondj )n Subjectt- Benewal of electric wiring in Government Buildings at^Bushire* Beferenoe ^ correspondence ending with India Office Express Letter 3687/36 of 8th December 1936 sent to me under their Printed letter of same number and date* 2* I note that the Government of India are advised by their technical officers that the existing wiring is in a dangerous state, and should be renewed with the least possible delay (vide paragranb 3 of Government of India f s Express Letter No*F # 86-A/35 of 17th September)* Considerable time has elapsed since Mr* Croad made his original recommendations on this point, and pre sumably the wiring is now in a still more dangerous state than it was then. I would be grateful therefore if I could be given immediate sanction to put the work in hand instead of waiting for the budget estimates for 1937-38 as intimated in the Govern ment of India letter quoted above* RESIDENT. The issue of the above has heen authorised*In any further communication on this subject, please quote No. K 13223/6486/234. and address, not to any person by name, but to— “The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. i. Foreign Office. S.W.l. 4th December, 1936. Sir, ^'With reference to India Office letter P.Z .7005/36 of November 4th regarding the renewal of the electric wiring in the Government buildings at Bushire, I am directed hy Mr. Secretary Eden to state, for the information of the Secretary of State for India, that sanction has been obtained for the acceptance as a charge on Imperial revenues of a moiety of the cost of renewal, estimated at 12,327 Rupees. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, The Under-Secretary of State, India Office.TTs t rs GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. Department. A » T^&gt;. T T ^ T ^ ^ w W «X U Xj X X x . i 7 n p ? / UL EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). TAis t’a an ORIGINAL message sent by AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It it intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save t ime and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department^ N °' F.86-A/36. Simla r7/ &amp; Dated mxm the /7 ' To September i93e&gt;. His Majesty's Under Secretary of State for India L 0 N D 0 N. Renewal of electric wiring in nenewtu. uj. wj.euoi.Lu xu f G-overnment buildings at Bushire. ly It . t /) In March 1935, the Government of India decided that opportunity should he taken of the visit of Mr. Croad, Superintending Engineer, Central Public Works Department, to the Gulf while proceeding home on leave, to inspect and advise outlie them in connection with the buildings as well as other %orks in progress or proposed in the Persian Gulf. Accordingly Mr. Croad inspected the buildings at Muscat, Bahrain, Bushire and Kowait and put forward certain useful suggestions, which are being examined separately in consultation with the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. 2. In connection with the Government buildings at Bushire, Mr. Croad reported inter alia that throughout these buildings the electric wiring was bad.. Mostly the wiring was done in 1919 and is about 17-18 years old. The present position is that the rubber insulation has perished in places and the wires are exposed and besides being dangerous, the installation affords a considerable leakage from this cause, and consequent ly it is considered absolutely necessary to change the exist ing wiring at an estimated^os^o^ Rs.12,327/- (rupees twelve s. u. MFP—367 S&amp;r—(M-508)—15-7.35—10,OCO. {Designation) } N D i A n - ’■thousand three hundred and twentyseven). The expenditure involved is chargeable to 'Repairs' as distinct from 'original Works' and as such, it is divisible in moieties between the Government of India and His Majesty's Government. It is, therefore, requested that the consent of His Majesty's Government, may kindly be obtained to share the expenditure in moieties, and communicated to the Government of India at an early date*. 3. The question of the transfer of the Bushire Residency to Bahrain is under consideration, but until the necessary buildings have been constructed in Bahrain it will not be possible for the move to take place. For about two years, therefore, the buildings in Bushire will be in use and the Government of India are advised by their technical officers that all the existing; wiring which is in a dangerous state should be renewed with the least possible delay. Ihe issue ol the above has been authorised. for Foreign Secretary to the Government of India-</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0000d9_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/3655</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0000d9</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/3655</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 29/79 'Bushire: renewal of electric wiring in government buildings'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1936/1945</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-09-25T10:50:39</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (86 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the inside front cover with 1, and terminates at the last folio with 87; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file concerns the Political Agency in the Persian Gulf, in Bushire.The file covers:renewal of electric wiring of the government buildings, 1937additions and alterations to the electric installations in Government buildings, 1940purchase of engine and electric generator for Residency, 1944.The file is composed of correspondence between the Political Residency in the Persian Gulf, the Foreign Office, the India Office, the Government of India, the High Commissioner for India, the Ministry of Supply, and the Electric Construction Company Limited.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>High Commissioner of India to the United Kingdom</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>British Legation, Tehran</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of India</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Persian Gulf Political Residency</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent; subject</roleTerm></role></name><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0000d9#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>