<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000255_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T09:26:20.363Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">'1 T-x Uu&gt; Confidential B.O.Ko. 104 -3 :f 1935 T H-'. RiilGI DSNG Y BU HIRE, 1st February 1933. Please refer to your letter 1^0.18 of the 26th January 1333 on the subject of the Shaikh's visit to England as the 'guest 1 of the Eastern aid General Syndicate Personally I do not think it is a very dignified thing for a Ruler to make a foreign tour as the guest of a Company. If the Shaikh does intend visiting England this year he ^ill have to decide whether he wants to ma- e the visit officially or unofficially, and if the former then there may be difficulties if he is to be the 'guest* of the Eastern and General Syndicate. I presume he will make up his mind about the Eastern and 'enercl Syndicate's invitation when he has decided as to which Company he will give the Concession. Lt.-Colonel H.R.P.Dickson,01 .E., Political Agent, 1 Kuwait.ae^^aks:-. - -• ' • ' - —- mrn* 10 of 1933. .British . es laenay &lt;Sc Consulate -General, Bushire, the 2nd February 1933« .19. -.0 /: : I \ ( tsbias/. iBoictilo j - e.ri/ oj \ j '3st'9T09'} ^ ol .Hut) nb^s19 r - 9nv + ai KU^AIT OIL ao^c^aiow. Sir, with reference to correspondence ending with this office printed letter Ho,8, dated the 31st January 1933, I have the honour to state that if His Excellency the 3na ikh of Kuwait decides in favour of the Eastern and General Syndicate 1 fear that his decision will largely have been influenced by his feeling that His Majesty's Government have not sufficiently implemented their undertakings to him in respect of his date gardens in 'Iraq and the trade blockade of Kuwait by the baudi Government. x am sending a copy of this letter to the G -overnment of India *sent under ?,L. No. 119-3 of 2/2/33, tc I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient humble servant, ^ - Lt.-Golonel, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, X ,W His Majesty's Secretary of State for the Colonies, tkh; colonial office, i .o n d o n,. P.T.C82/1T 86/1. ' '/ Telegram XX From Secretary of State for the Colonies, London. To Political Hesident, Bushire. No. 2. Dated 4th received 5th February 1933. f- / IWORIAKT. / You will have seen from the last paragraph of my telegram No. 9 of 22nd December that we had hoped that in the light of Petroleum Department's memorandum and discussion with you and Dickson, the Shaikh would have felt ahle to make an early, if not necessarily an immediate, decision as 'between the competing companies on a 'broad view of the financial and other major con- -siderations involved. There seems some danger now that the decision may 'be unduly delayed and the position complicated 'by discussion of the details of the draft concessions with the competitors. This would 'be like- -ly, incidentally, to raise important points in connect- -ion with safeguards and also with such questions as Telegraphs, Eailways, exclusion of certain areas, etc., on which the advice of E.M's. Government will he required I shall 'be glad, therefore, if, unless you see objection, you will point out to the Shaikh the desirability of avoiding discussion of such details until he has reach- -ed a dfecision between the competitors. 1 . You will also ebxxxb doubtless ensure that the Shaikh gives the representatives of the Companies clearly to understand that it is condition of discuss- -ions that he may,after as between the compet -ing companies has been taken, require amendment of draft agreement on any points on which H.M's. Government82/1 &amp; 86/1. Kei; i\ 3 f.f® &lt;0 s Telegram Erom To No. 2* XX H.M*s, Secretary of State for the Colonies, London. Political Resident, Bushire Dated 4th received 5th February 1933 n't* IMPOKTANT. [ You will/have seen from the last paragraph of my telegram No. 9 of 22nd Decemher that we had hoped that in the light of Petroleum Department's memorandum and discussion with you and Dickson, the Shaikh would have felt ahle to make an early, if not necessarily an immediate, decision as between the competing companies on a 'broad view of the financial and other major con- -siderations involved. There seems some danger now that the decision may he unduly delayed and the position complicated hy discussion of the details of the draft concessions with the competitors. This would he like- -ly, incidentally, to raise important points in connect ion with Sd .feguards and also with such questions as Telegraphs, Bailways, exclusion of certain areas, etc., on which the advice of H.M's. Government will he reguireci. I shall he glad, therefore, if, unless you see objection, you will point out to the Shaikh the desirability of avoiding discussion of such details until he has reach- -ed a dfecision between the competitors. 1 . You also Ksxxzx doubtless ensure that the \ Shaikh gives the representatives of the Companies clearly to understand that it is condition of discuss- . . . -ions that he may,after gtoBWSWiWar as between the compet -ing companies has been taken, require amendment of draft agreement on any points on which H.M's. Government recommend him to insist ( see last sentence of penultim- -ate paragraph of my telegram of 22nd December, Ho. 9. 1 This■MUM I This proviso in itself amkes detailed discussion of any 'but financial and general features of draft concessions useless at this stage. I presume Shaikh can he relied upon to keep Political Agent generally informed of the course of discussions with representat* -dves of the Companies. Please telegraph whether Shaikh has shown any indication of taking any decision, and if not, whether he is likely to do so in the near future.- 7 x r / / ^ On receipt of your telegram of 14th January the Eastern &amp; General Syndicate were informed (l) that you had telegraphed asking that they he advised that you had presented to the Shaikh the comments of H.M # s. Government on their proposals and those of the Anglo Persian Oil Company, and [Z) that you had notified the local representative of the Anglo Persian Oil Company ftiF 0 ' of the position. 3 The foregoing refers to your despatch No. 5E of E7th December and your telegram of 14th January on the subject of Kuwait Oil, SECRETARY OF STATE h f. /I ( ■ 't 'i FOR THE COLONIES.82/1 &amp; 86/1. m 0 Telegram P Prom Political Resident, at Bahrain. Secretary of State for the Colonies, London To No. T-13 Dated 6tli Pehruary 1933 The necessary action has either already 'been taken or is 'being taken through the Political Agent, Kuwait, with whom 1 am commuhicating 'by air mail and who will telegraph reply to your paragraph 3. I am writing hy air mail leaving Bahrain 9th Jehruary. The foregoing refers to your telegram No. Sx E of 4th February. BSSIDBNTmtmm T T Ml rnSSmk*-- iKKTIAL. GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. Oitlce of the Political Resident in the Persi EXPRESS LETTER (MR MAIL). [N B-— This is an ORIGINAL message sent hy AIR MAIL which provides a means of communicate expeditions than the ordinary mait and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended tb on receipt, with the tame expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To sate time and formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated hy the signal responsible officer o f the Department,] No. 0-13 Dated ., the 5t.h F e bru ary To iiecretary of State for the Colonie (Copy, with copy of correspond en of IndiaK i ^ Ij.S, 'R pfprpnPA ' ' telegram No. 2 of 4th February. Both Shaikh and competing companies bargain possible from thfeir respective points course involves financial negotiations, and i guite out of the question for the Shaikh to m -ion on the first proposals submitted to him iBjcxaca: attempt to hurry ^he Shaikh into an in and thus short circuit the negotiations woulc^ to 'by the Shaikh himself and regarded by whic the concession as exercise of undue influence is precisely the accusation which H.M's. Gov^ wish to avoid. i V f. 2. I informed the Shaikh when at Kuwai' company he gave the concession to would have safeguards to he imposed by H.M's. Governmenti as you will see from the attached enclosure, warning in more detail, which also covers the raised in your telegram. {Signature) Political .Resident in the At t OS t ecU ( Designation) 8 44 t in the Persian Gulf./' mnxL. . GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. tteoafitoM- Oitice of the irolitical Resident in the Persian Grtilf. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). [NB .— TAts is an ORIGINAL message sent hy AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more expeditions than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended tb be treated, on receipt, with the tame expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To sate time and to obviate formalities it it drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated hy the signature of a respontihle officer o f the Department.} No. ^ Gamp, ijajarain XtX W CXUl9 Ju/dii X d dm 11 Dated the 5^^ February 19 ZZ* To H.ik's, Secretary of State for the Colonies, London. (Jopy, with oopy of correspondence, to (Government of India)* PpfprpTlPA ' tjfcz telegram No. 2 of 4th february. Both Shaikh and competing companies wish to make hest bargain possible from their respective points of view, which of course involves financial negotiations, and it was therefore quite out of the question for the Shaikh to make a quick decis- -ion on the first proposals submitted to him hy companies. Any isyxxK attempt to hurry the Shaikh into an immediate decision and thus short circuit the negotiations would have been objected to by the Shaikh himself and regarded by whichever company lost the concession as exercise of undue influence on our part, which is precisely the accusation which H.M*s* Government naturally wish to avoid. I informed the Skaikh when at Kuwait that whichever company he gave the concession to would have to agree to certain safeguards to he imposed by H.M's. Government. I am, however, as you will see from the attached enclosure, underlining this warning in more detail, which also covers the other points raised in your telegram. {Signature) x.0. 10 , LK . Political .Resident in the Persian Gulf. Attest ecU ( Designation) 8 44 ^ t in the Persian Gulf.DSNTIAL. GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. Office of the Political Resident in the Persian EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). N B.—This is an ORIGINAL message sent hy AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication expeditions than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph- It is intended tb he il on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and to f formalities it it drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated hy the signaturi responsible officer of the Department.^ No. C-14 • Gamp, Bahrain, Dated r, the To Political Agent, Kuwait* 6th February I enclose herewith following corres Colonial Office telegraia No. 2,of 4/2/33 Pol. Kesdt's. H ' T-13 ^ 6/2/3 H 11 Express Letter * C-13 M \ I ,c&gt; / 6 7 XSL i 2. ' ^ You will recollect that during my 1 we informed the Shaikh in the sense of paragr Letter to the Colonial Office. In order, h this warning please write to His Excellency a \ should the Anglo Persian Oil Company or the S Syndicate approach him on points which are li discussion on such questions as Telegraphs, of certain areas, etc., he should avoid discu until he has decided to which of the two comp grant the concession* Should he feel dou any point put forward hy either of the compan any of the •reserved subjects * he should ask can communicate with me. 3. Please remind Shaikh to keep you ge course of discussions with representatives of Reference paragraph 3 of the Gollani without pressing the Shaikh please ascertain and telegraph me repeating to Colonial Office Attested. e :-k -A ary to the Political JJie Persian Gulf. DCFP—33S&amp;P—(G-37)—25-5-31—15,000. {Signature) Sd/ • T Political Hesident in (Designation)GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. DSNT1AL. iiepaptment. Office of the Political Hesident in the Persian Gulf. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). N B.— This is an ORIGINAL message sent hy AIR MAIL which provides a meam of communication more expeditions than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended tb be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It it authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer o f the Department.] Camp, Bahrain &gt;10. u-14. Dated the February 19 53 y^; To Political Agent, Kuwait, / |1 i £2 6 I enclose herewith following correspondence :- / Colonial Office telegram No. 2,of 4/2/33 to Pol, j^esat. Pol. Hesdt's. H H T-13 ^ 6/2/33 H Colonial Office * * Express Letter * 0-13 H M ^ ^ ^ 2. ^ You will recollect that during my last visit to Kuwait we informed the Shaikh in the sense of paragraph 2 of my Express c. Letter to the Colonial Office. In order, however, to underlir^ this warning please write to His Excellency and point out that \ should the Anglo Persian Oil Company or the Eastern &amp; Ceneral Syndicate approach him on points which are likely to lead to discussion on such guestions as Telegraphs, railways, exclusion of certain areas, etc., he should avoid discussing such details until he has decided to which of the two companies he is going t grant the concession. Should he feel doubtful as to whether any point put forward 'by either of the companies infringes on any of the 'reserved subjects* he should ask your advice and you can communicate with me. 3. Please remind Shaikh to keep you generally informed of course of discussions with representatives of companies. Beference paragraph 3 of the Colonial Office telegram, without pressing the Shaikh please ascertain how the land lies and telegraph me repeating to Colonial Office. Attested. Sd/- T.C.FOWLS. ary to the Political |£e Persian Gulf. DCFP—33S&amp;P—(G-37)—25-5-31—15,000. {Signature) Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. (Designation)CONFIDENTIAL. No. 0-15 of 1933. The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, and lias the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment (s). BritislrRB^idency frntt- BtJtSffllTE:- CaiGp, Bahrait), / Dated..^ft.• W' Reference to previous correspondence : .Bushire x'.L. No. 1/62-3, dated 27the Decem'ber 19S2. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Political liesident's telegram No T-10, dated 14th January 1933. Colonial office telegram ho. 2, dated 4th February 1933. lolitical ±veBiaent*s telegram No T-13, datea 6th February 1933. Political Resident's Express Letter No. C-13, dated 6th February 19 33. Ditto, No. C-14, dated 6th Feh- -ruary 1933. Subject. / n 3 . i. {rl Kuwait oil concession. L ■MQZ/1 &amp; 86/1. Telegram X. Eepeated To Yrom Political Agent, Kuwait Political Besident, Bushire. H.M t s« Secretary of State for ttae Colonies, London Fo. 33. Dated lltb. received 13th February 1933 The Shaikh of Kuwait shows no indication whatever of arriving at a decision ksek nor, according to him, is he likely to do so for several weeks. He made it clear that he would resent any attempt to hurry him. At the same time there are unmistakeahle indications that he is moving in the direction of the Eastern &amp; G-eneral Syndicate and is only prevented from surrendering to them now 'because of his nervousness of the reaction of H.M # s. Government. The foregoing refers to your Express Letter Ko. 0-14 of 6th JFehruary / POLITICALConfidentia Political Agency, Kuws Dated the 1st February /&gt;' f- i •wy \ '--si i-Ho F-*i J''* I have'recently^ and once again^ 'been going the enclosures which you forwarded to me under your co] No.C.12 dated the 14th January 1933, 2. I have been particularly impressed with thi references made by the Air Ministry and War Office to j ; letter ITo.lI.02977/22 dated the 18th November 1932 to t Office, I have a rather uncomfortable feeling that go wrong and the Shaikh gives the Oil Concession to I«Ia Tin ~ I shall be told that I ought to had the 'sense' to mak A somehow to the Shaikh, the Admiralty, Air Force and An of views in the matter, even though officially I was f( to advise or guide the Shaikh in the way he should go, order to cover myself somewhat, therefo it be possible for you, do you think, to forward priva say Walton or Laithwaite, a copy of my confidential D.(j dated the 28th December 1932. This will .show them tha' in December last felt considerable doubts on the wisdon letting the Shaikh decide things for himself, without J him advice or guidance, 5# 1 shall be grateful for a line in reply to :he Hon t ble Lieutenant-Colonel T.C.W.Fowle, C.B.E,, 1olitical Resident in the Persian Gulf Bush ire.11 Confidentia: ^-g-r^ToCNCY^ «7 L M. ^ yU» D.O.No.24 Political Agency, Kuwait. Dated the 1st February 1933, f\f i C c4 L '/ l/^f i -Gl f ' 1 : -%l I ■ liv F-H (/•Hl I have recentli;-^ and once again^ 'been going through the enclosures which you forwarded to me under your confidential No # C.12 dated the 14th January 1953, 2. I have been particularly impressed with the several references made by the Air Ministry and War Office to Admiralty^ letter No.M.02977/32 dated the 18th November 1932 to the Colonial Office. 3. I have a rather uncomfortable feeling that if things go wrong and the Shaikh gives the Oil Concession to Llaior Holmes I shall be told that I ought to had the n sense' to make known A somehow go the onaikh, the Admiralty, Air -i-'orce and Army points of views in the matter, even though officially I was forbidden to advise or guide the Shaikh in the way he should go, order to cover myself somewhat, therefore, would it be possible for you, do you think, to forward privately to say Walton or Laithwaite, a copy of my confidential D.O.No.218 dated the 28th December 1932. This will show them that I also in December last felt considerable doubts on the wisdom of letting the Shaikh decide things for himself, without our giving him advice or guidance. 5# 1 shall be grateful for a line in reply to this. 'he Eon'ble Lieutenant-Colonel T.G.W.Fowle, C.B.E., Iolitioal Resident in the Persian Gulf Bush ire.■ mt-i ' J ~~7SmSS* }V SSCR3T* I\0 • So« From To MHftfiEHTIAl HEQ0RB5. Political Agency, Kuwait* Dated the 2nd February 1932, Lieutenant-Colonel F.R.P.Dickson, G.I.S., P olit ical Agen t, Kuwait s The Eon*hie the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, B u s h i r e. K U W -tl I T OIL. Sir, I have the honour to report the following interesting conversation which took place between Shaikh- Abdullah as-Salin and myself on the 30th January 1933. IU 2* Shaikh Abdullah is as you know the son of^ late Sul^r of Kuwait and is first cousin of Eis Excellency Shaikh i Ahmad the present Ruler, 3« Be stands out from among other members of the Shaikhly family, in common sense and general ability, and together with the present Ruler, may be said to be the only man who reads newspapers, and takes an interest in world affair^ 4. Shaikh Abdullah had been absent in camp during 'ID' holidays which fell on 27th and 28th January this year, and only returned to Kuwait on the evening of the 29th # According to custom therefore I called on the morning of the 30th to congratulate him on the M ID M festival and on the con- f elusion of the fast of Ramathan* 5* After the usual greetings and subsequent polite nesses, ohaiKh Abdullah said 'Jiat he wished to discuss with me and in strict confidence the question of the n Cil Concession''Oil Concession', He had a ri^rt he said to be heard, as he was the senior member of the A1 Lubah family after the iluler, and any oil concession that was given was not going to benefit the present Ruler'alone, but would affect the whole of the Al Sub all family numbering soms 200 souls. ®• shaikh Abdullah then commenced by complaining that the Shaikh was oondLue^ing the present oil negotiations in far too much/secret, and that he had so far consulted no one in the State, let alone any members of the family* He followed this complaint up by certain observations, which for convenience sake I have enumerated below in the form sub-paragraphs® (a). He accused His Ivla ^jesty's Groveminent of doing a very wrong and immoral thing in allowing the Shaikh the free hand that he had been given in the matt er f His LIaJesty t s Government seemed not to have realized that Shaikh Ahmad was little better than an ordinary Bedoui^ in mentality &gt; and to throw the whole responsibility on him for deciding between the merits of the Anglo- Persian Oil Company and Eastern and General concession Syndicate*s f /was unfair. (b). it was not possible for the Shaikh to come to a right and proper decision, when he was expected to pit his poor brains against Western Experts, and especially against the brains of'a super cunning schemer' (his words), like Major Holmes. (c/» His Majesty*s G-overnment were evading their proper responsibilities, as the Protecting Power, when they confined their advice to petty points connected with financial benefits, and maintained a mysterious silence as to the policy it were best for the Shaikh to follow, in the interest of his people, and that of future relations with the Protecting Power.(d). Shaikh Ahmad was little more than a child in this matter, and His Majesty^s GoTernment should most certainly havo advised him clearly and definitely that it was to his interest, and that of his successor and decendents to accept the Anglo Persian Oil Company*s draft concession, ard 'turn down' that of the Eastern and G-eneral Syndicate's* 'If a child was going to fall down a well' (to use the Shaikh's words) it was the nurse's business to seize and stop it, it was not sufficient for the nurse to call to the child and say it must itself decide whether falling down the weix was to its advantage or other wise. (e)» In the present instanibs His Majesty's Govern- . ment, even if indifferent to the fate of the Ruler, should consider the other members of the family as we 13 as the people of Kuwait, (f). It was ind^ference of this kind that in the past had so often led to trouble and bloodshed, in Arab States# Shaikh Abdullah then gave it as his opinion that Shaikh Ahmad was definitely moving towards giving the oil concession to llajor Holmes. His reason for saying this was that Shaikh Ahmad had not received fair treatment nor been supported by His Majesty's Government, in the matter of the Date Gardens and the Blockade, and today believed, (or was taught to belu^/c by Hajor Holmes), that if a strong American concern got into Kuwait, it the concern, would see to it, through its own Govern-r ment, that sufficient pressure was brought to bear on Great Britain as would insure better treatment for himself the Shaikh, and a stronger line being taken where Iraq and Bin Saud were oonoerned. In other words that he would have someone to pla'v off against His Majesty 's Gov61111.16at . { In this connection see my D.C.II0.SI8 dated 28th December 1938). F'tl f 'S— 8 # When I asked Shaikh Abdullah to whom he himself thought the T, Cil Gonc3ssiorx n should be given, he replied^To the Anglo-Persian Oil Company of course'. On my enquiring 'Why'? he said 'Because Great Britain is our friend, and has always been so, and the Anglo,Persian Oil Company is part of Great Britain - Kuwait stands to benefit by strengthening her ties with His Majesty's Government, and conversely has every thing to lose by putting herself in to the hands of foreigners'. When I asked how was it that the Ruler did think A like him? He answered 'Because he is a man who does not look far ahead, and honestly be'lieves today that it will be to his advantage, if he can get a strong ally in the shape of an American Company, who will be backed by its GovernmentV Shaikh Abdullah, as I rose to go confided to me that, as soon as he saw definite signs that the Shaikh was going to yield to Llajor Holmes* blandishments, he intended inter viewing him and giving him a piece of his mind in the hopes of possibly shamming him into changing his policy even at the last moment. At present he said it was quite useless to talk to or advise his cousin as the latter would only retort that he had been got at by the Anglo-Persian Oil Company. I consider the above sentiments of Shaikh Abdullah worth reporting to you, as they show that a considerable party in Kuwait disapproves of the Shaikh's 'close' methods, and will I certainly have something to say if he decides to favour Major Holmes* concern. At the same time one cannot in any way count on Shaikh Abdullah or his powerful following, being able to turn Shaikh Ahmad from a decision once formed* The latter is too strongly entrenched in power for that to happen. In the meantime Shaikh Ahmad has given me no indication as to the way he is going to jump, I according to orders am maintaining my 'Owl' like silence, which does not seem to be helping on matters mucho I have the honour to be, POLITICAL AaaNT.raniAIT.Jk y t Obedient servant,©IJUSHiRf SESiDKNCy. i A«( / [ QQNB^ MM l HiruMOS -» &lt;i&lt;«n .. A copy of the undermentioned paper is forwarded to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf with reference to correspondence ending with his endorsement Ho,982-S, dated the 21st December 1932» 2. 'No action should be taken on this communication-which is forwarded for information. By order, etc., Assistant Secretary to the Government of India, foreign and Political Department, &gt; T ew Delhi; The j ' February 1933, Note by L, Oliphant, London Foreign Office, to Ray Atherton, Esquire, U.S. Embassy, London, dated the 22rd December 193 2,r' t O PORKIUN pPP ICB^S.V/a I 23rd Deceiaber, I§^2. Ve have made enquiries about the point which you mentioned to Vansittart yesterday morning in connexion with the question of the proposed Koweit Oil Concession. As you know, it concerns a number of different departments of His Majesty's Government and at every stage complicated inter-departmental discussions have been necessary. As Vansittart told your Ambassador in his , , v / -v ' ' ' letter of the Xlth November? the document embodying the ^ result of the examination of the two draft Concessions submitted by the Eastern and General Syndicate and by the Anglo-Persian Oil Company respectively had s at that d^te, been already despatched to the British Authorities in the Persian Gulf. But I fear that the suggestion in Vansittart'9 letter of November 11th that this document would within a very short time of its receipt by them be communicated to the Sheikh for his consideration was somewhat over optimistic, Further inter-departmental discussions have had to take place in the interval ? and have thus caused some further delay in the communication of the document to the Sheikh. I have now done all I can to speed matters up 5 and the local British authorities should now be in a position to proceed in the matter with the Sheikh in the very near future. I Atherton, Esq.,I am so sorry for this racent and quite unexpected fidditional delay which has arisen but ■vhich has new 'been tersiinated. (Signed) Lancelot oliphant./y/ K suddenly confronted with ar widerttandiB^ between ths ^ lo Persim Oil Ccmpsny and the kimricmt thp re^uH of Yihidi would be to make it rwmm&amp;rr to ask tlm Sheikh'r approval to the introduction of a really effective ^eri can inters&amp;t withoitt hiB luwinr. any option to choose between competing companies; mid if there if- any ri^k of this, it may be thot^ht well to warn Cadman of tfie possible difu cultiee tell in advance# 5 # x m sending copies of this letter to Starling and l oore. Y orir b si no b rely , J ( 0. LAiTHWAITE.P.2. 439/33. 30th January 19 33, irtazi t. Sir, / In reply to year letter of the 21st January, No, 18119/ 33, on the s lib j 0 c t of t li e Z owe it oil coricess ion, I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to say that, as Sir Philip Gunliffe-Lister is aware, he has throughout been of opinion that it would be preferable if possible to postpone discussion of the details of tija concession to be negotiated with the Sheikh of Koweit by the successful competitor for the Koweit concession until His Excellency has taken a definite decision in favour of one or other of the competing companies on a broad view of the financial, and other major considerations involved. Once such a decision has been taken, it could be followed by detailed negotiations, with which the local representatives of His Majesty's G-overniTEnt could be closely associated and in the course of which steps could be taken to advise the Sheikh as to the points wMch it was desirabJB to cover either in his own interest or in that of His Majesty T s (Jovernmoi t. Subject to the vie TO- of the other interested Departments, the Secretary d State for India is inclined, therefore, to suggest that vhile conveying general approval to the course of acticn proposed by Colonel Powle in paragraph.4 of his despatch No.52, of 27th December 1932, Sir Philip Gunliffe-Lister, if he sees no objectloa/ f-il f• der-Secretary cf State, olonial Office, 3. W. 1.objection, might also inform the Resident that His Majesty^ G-cv ernment are anxiois that a definite decision shaild be tiicen by the Sheilch as between the competing companies m th as little delay as possible; that he aid the Political Agent, Koweit should do what they caa to encourage him to take such a decision on a broad view of the financial and other major considerations involved^ and that in principle it would be preferable to postpone examination of the details of a concession until such a decision had been taiieru 03ie Resident might be instructed that in these circumstances the local, representatives of the Anglo -Persian Oil Company (and of the Eastern and General Syndicate if and when a similar questicn arises in respect of their applicati cn) should be warned that while they can initiate and conduct negotiations without further reference to His Majesty 1 ^ Government on the basis of their provisional drafts, tlicBe drafts in their present form would require amendment in ^ various particulars in the event of the Sheilch deciding in favour of the competitor concerned, but that His Majesty s Government propose to postpone communication of their views on the points in question to the Sheikh until His Excellency has reached a decisicn as between the applicants iot an oiX concession and the preparaticn of a final, draft can more profitably be undertaken. 2, Copies of this ,]e tter are being sent to the Foreign Office and Petroleum Department. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, (Sd.) j. a wALim18126/33. Downing Street, 1 7 1 h J a nuary, 1933. Sir, I am directed by Secretary Sir Philip Ounliffe-Lister to refer to the letter from this Department (No.98026/11/32} of the 14th October regarding the application of the Eastern and General Syndicate Limited for the grant of an oil concession in Kuwait, and to inform you that a telegram has been received from the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf in which he requests that your Syndicate may be informed that he has now presented to the Bhaikh of Kuwait the comments of His Majesty's Government on their proposals and those of the Anglo-Persian uil Company. E. The Resident has notified the local representative of the Anglo-Persian oil Company of the position. I am etc., : v Sd) O.G.H.T-illiams. STEM AND GENERAL SYNDICATE LIMITED.CONFIDENTIAL. No. 148-/; of 1933. The Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The xolitical Agent, Kuwait, and is directed to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents, for inf orrrr ti on. British Residency and Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated .l&amp;th. •iJ'.c.br uax^... 19 Reference to previous correspondence ; Bushire printed letter No.C/15 of 6th February 1933 Description of Enclosure. h.* Name and Date. '1 Foreign Office letter dated the 23rd December 1932 to Ray AthertonjEsq#,U.S.Kmbassy London. Foreign Office letter JSo« E 6830/12l/91 of 30th Jecerabe:* 1932 to Sir John Gadman. Letter No.E 25/12/91 of 31st December 1932 from Sir John CiLd-iV man to the Foreign Office. India Office letter No.P.Z.31 ./ 33 of 19th January 1953 to tht Foreign Office. India Office letter No.P.Z.43^/ 33 of 30th January 1933 to tht Colonial Office. Colonial Office letter No. 18126/33 of 17th January 1933 to the Secretary ,iiast^ rn and General Syndicate. eoi. M Kuwait Oil Concession t % i n V -^ % ■' ' v ? *&gt;[ ■' 17 D.O. Ko. 159-^. of l..'5S. The residency, .^slxire, loth ''eeruar^ 1953 ^ !i r Your didifil-ofrioial letter No. 24, of 1st February. There is no need for you to toe uneasy» and If the Shaikh eventually presaata the Eastern ^ oreneral Syndicate with the concession it is largely due to n.M's. Government them es elves, firstly because they refuse to give the Shaikh a lead In the matter ana, secondly, tor the reasons given in i^y despatch to the Oolonlal Office, No# 10 of 2n«l February, copy forwarded to you. Lleut«0ol« .JPickBon, C.I.I. | irolltical Agent, Kuwait. t'jiConfidential lie. 35. To rom v I J' political ilgency, Euweit, lated the 15th ITebruarv 193^ »U§H1FF Fff^OiHCY. hn- 9th.. I? i i.n ^/^'V , QONftflWTiAL SEOOm The Hon'hie the political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, Lt. Col, H, '.1. Lick son C.I.2. Political Agent, Kuwait. ' f Kuwait Oil' t I lir Jith reference to your Express letter No.C14 Dated 6th February 1923, and enclosures. I have the honour to forward copy of the Unrlish and Arabic letter which I transmitted to His Excellency the Sheikh in accordance with the instructions given me in para 2 of your letter, together with his reply. S, As regards your para 3, you will notice that I have requested His Excellency the Sheikh to keep me generally informed of the course of his discussions with the representatives of the A .P .O .G. and Eastern General Syndicate. I think however that both H .II.G. and you should know that in this matter of the ''oil concess ion^ the Sheikh, from the commencement of the business, has adopted a curiously close attidude, as far as I am concerned, and has never iret asked me ray advice or confided to me any of his difficulties. This is unfor tunate, seeing that in other matters I appear to have his complete confidence.9 -j • 3. This state of affairs I put down directly to Major Holmes T influence, who nore than ever o p Irte would seem to have gone out of his way to encourage t$e Sheikh to look upon himself,(Major Holmes) as his 'fidus ^chates' and mentor. 4. It is a curious fact that when llajor Holmes is absent fromrluwait, the Sheikh at once becomes his reasonable self a^ain and is ever ready to visit me and discuss matters of state. But as soon as I-ajor Holmes returns he seems to become the victim of some sort of hypnotic influence, and is afraid to come near me . He instead becomes a constant visitor to I.-ajor Holmes' house* 5^ I have little doubt that this rather disturbing state 'airs is due to the ideas eh Llajo^ .Dimes fills his mind. 6In this last connection, 7 har 7 it from the Sheikh himself recently that rajor ^'olmes on his lest return from England, told him, as a fact, that m t.'.e verv near future the Colonial Cffice would ceese to have anv further say In Huwait affairs and that the -oieirn Office alone would deal with his interests. He would seem also to have implied that the Government of India would recede into the background, and largely leave i uwait to herself, llajor Holmes indeed mentioned this same thing to me, stating that he had had it from a high Governr^eiit Official in London. 7 ^ You will realize no doubt what a danger ous effect such talk would have on the sim ; le mino. the Sheikh especially when coming from the very man who is trying to get a concession for the ^uneric^ns, E'nd m ~o is for ever hinting that the ?T arch villain of the x S the»Colonial Of fice, who are represented as being chiefly against him.Wt- 1 3. 8. -.s I have not unfrequently said before, la3or T:r olraes is p remarkably clever man, and kno^s the psychology of the ..rab better perhaps than any one I know of today» One of the methods he employs both to im press and to win confidence, is that of makOnr out that he possesses powerful backers in London and ^nerica, who can always be counted on to counteract the machinations J -'- 3 local Political Cffioers, who i.i t': - made cut to he retrograde sortbof eople, feeat on keeping local Rulers in leading strings; ^le rei30'~al of the original''British Kationalit^r Clause' was of course represented to have been his, Tag or r olme s * doing, and the providing of sensational 'news,' such as that mentioned in para 6 shove, is merely done to support thfi impression he wishes to convey, namely that he, Iiajor ''olin.es, has much influence in Government circles in London and so gets inner knowledge of what is going to happen, 9. The Sheikh as you know is a simple person at heart and though he prides himself on having the shrewdness of a professional politician, in actual fact he possesses little more than the suspicious cunning inherent in every ITejdi or Bedouin Sheikh: It is not difficult therefore for him to fall a prey to the clever tactics of Ha3or Holmes, 10. In conclusion I give below some observations on the oil situation as it stands in ICuwait today, which may assist you to .understand what is going on. (a) The Sheikh^would like to give the oil concession to the Eastern and General, Syndicate today, but is afraid of doing so lest he offend H .ivx.G-. (b) The Sheikh is playing a lone hand, and t takes no ones advice at all, nor would any of his leading merchants be able toy *•1 \ 4. to proffer any advice of value, seeing that nine tenths of them are indebted to him finanoialy, and have not the courage to say what might not please. (c) None of the members of the Sheikhly house take: any hand in the G-overnment of the State, so their counsel is not sought, (d) The Sheikh at the moment believes that it is not in his interests to have the A.x'.O.C. in his country for two reasons Fi rstly , because he thinks they do not intend to work the concession.(This is some of Holmes t propaganda). S econdly , his independance mi^ht be threat ened if he were to set up a concern, backed by G-overnment,in his State. (Also obviously Holm.es* propaganda). (e) ./hat the Jheikh cannot understand and vrtiat he frequently harps on in course of conver sation, is the fact that since H.IC.G. raised no objection to the Americans getting in at Bahrain, why are they so averse to the same Americans coming into Auwait. (f) ICajor Holmes daily preaches that the Sheikh should not be afraid of consequences, but take his courage in both hands and decide in his favour. That he liajor Holmes, will see that he does not get out of favour Yfith H .M.G. for doing so. Xi, 1 have thought it worth while to repor the above, to sssist you in visualizing the troubles and doubts which today assail the Sheikh. 12, Lastly and for your information Holmes left for Bahrain on 12. E. 3S. b3r steamer andand Lr Jllkinrton of the visited ICuwait on 11.2.35. to make the acquaintance of His Excellency the Sheikh. ! T r Slkington left a^rain on 13.2.35., after a vain attempt had been made by myself to arrange a lunch at which both Lajor HoliD.es and llr Slkington would be present. The courage of the former would appear to have deserter; him at the last moment. have the honour to be Jir 'Your most obedient servant Political -.gent, .'uwaitc L^scM:. Translation of a letter (confidential) From Lt. Col. H.P.P.Dickson C.I.S. Political Agent ICuwait. To His Excellency Cheikh Sir ^hmad al-Jabir as-Jubeli, IZ.C.I.J., G.L.I. , Ruler of Ifuweit, Mo. 54. Dated the 12th February 1933. Aft er comp1imen t s t .Vith reference to the conversation ?7hich I had with ^^our Excellency on Friday the 10th February last. I have the honour to inform, your Excellency that I have received an express letter ro.C.14 dated 6th''/ / r ' February 1933 from the Kcn T ble the rolitical Resident in^ the Persian Gulf Bushire,in Yrhich he directs me to remind you of the conversation which he had with your Rxcellency on his recent visit to ''uwait, and asks me to point out that should the representatives of the inglo Persian Oil Co., % Ltd., or the Eastern and General Syndicate Ltd.,approach you on points which are likely to lead to discussion, on such difficult questions as Telegraphs, Railways, Exclusion of certain ^reas etc., Your excellency should be careful to avoid discussing such details, until ''our Rxcellency has finaly decided to which of the two companies Your Excellency proposes to grant the Oil Concession, Should Your Excellency feel in any way doubtful, as to whether any point put forward by either of the Companies infringes on any of such ^ reserved'subjects' 1 , Your Excellency should ask my advice, and I will refer the mattero n p matter to the Hon'ble the Political Resident for his nilin Lastly I an desired by the IIon T ble the Political Resident to remind your Uxoellency to keep me, your friend, generally informed of the progress of Tour Sxoellency's discussions with the representatives of the two Oil Companies. Usual ending. signed. H.R.P.Dickson Lt. Col. ol it i cal ^gent, IZuwai t. \Translation oi a J or. 'Identical letter . From - His Excellency Sheikh ^ir Ahmad al-J'ebir as- Gab ah, K. G. I • lu., G. o. I • , Kuler of lluwai t. To - The Political ^gent, Zuwait. Ho.S/SSS-IU Dated the 19th ohauwal 1351 (14th February 1933). After compliments, ./ith the hand of pleasure I have received your confidential letter No.34 dated 17th Lhauival 1351 (12.2*33.) conve^/ing what the Hon r ble the Political Resident /-y I' i • '' K in the Persian Gulf had written in his express letter Ho.C/M dated 6th February 1933, in continuation of the conversation which His Excellency had with me on his recent visit to Kuwait on the subject of thB discussion with the represen- , ^ tatives of the imglo Persian Oil Go. Ltd., and the Eastern General Syndicate Ltd. To the end, I have noted your state ment and understood it. Please be so good as to inform the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf that we shall be very careful to avoid, the difficult questions you mentioned or whatever may require the least precaution, and are likely to have an unfair effect on our interests and the future of our country® But as His Uajesty's Government has left the question of the concession to our Judgment, as the Eon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf informed me in his confidential letter No.6 dated 14th January 1933, k we are depending on this, and will also take into consider-consideretion the coraments of Eis lIa.iesty T s Grovernnent on the various articles of the concession, as conveyed to us in your confidential letter iTo»2 dated 8th January 1933• .7e feel confident that His Majesty^ Government has no other intention than the prosperity and welfare of ourselves and our country. Further, Your Excellency may 'be quite assured that I rely on you, my friend, more than on myself and of course should I have any doubts, which must of necessity arise in such affairs, I would consider it most essential that Your Excellency be approached before they be definitely settled. Usual ending.aim at t: e following:- (a) the tr^afer of the oil interests at Bahrein to the Buraah Oil Co pany (b) any Anglo-American arran^a.ent includim Hasa as well as Koweit and (o) ma-ing it a condition that British influence must predominate in any Anglo-American combine. 6. T .ey consider that in any case it should be made clear to Sir John Cad .an tuat a bargain on a 50/50 basis at Koweit alone without adequate compensatin ■: advanta :es elsewhere would not be regarded as satisfactory by H.M. Gk)vem-: ent. 7. : y Lords assume also taat the safeguards set out in Colonial Office te!e^ra. to the Political Resident in the Persian G-ulf of 9th l.ay 193?, Mo.3 Confidential, will be insisted upon, whichever mrty obtains the conceosion. 8. Co )ies of this letter have been sent to India. Office, Col.onial Office and Petro 1 earn Depart ent• I am, etc., (Sgd. ) J. S. BAHMES Copy forwarded to I .A,Kuwait, under Bustiire P .L. No. 185-a, dated 22-2-33.62/1 &amp; 66/1. Telegram En clair. From Political Agent, Muscat. To Political Pesident, on 'TRIAD M . No. 21. Dateu ano receivea klxX 27th February 1933, From Elkington, begins. Following from Sir John Caaman, begins. I shall be on board Gulf mail steamer- calling Bushire 22nci March. bhoulct very much like to meet Political Resident if he can possibly arrange. I can probably oelay steamer for a short time if necess -dry. ends. POLITICAL. U. ^ 1 (nMfkr SI Telegram En clair. From Political Resident, at Muscat To Elkington, Anglopers, Abadan. Ho. T-17. Batea ^ atea 2nd March 1932. Following for Sir John Cadman, begins:- Shall be verypleasea to see you on boar 22nc larch. ends. RESHDSM 1 •82/1 &amp; 86/1 Telegram XX o Prom Secretary to Resiaent, Bushire. To Political Resident, at Muscat» No. 149. Dated and receivea 2nd March 1933, Your uem-off icial letter No. 104-&amp; of 1st February to Political Agent, Kuwait. letter No. 39 of 19th February intimates tnat Shaikh is personally aisinclinea to accept the Eastern &amp; General Synoicate f £ invitation to Lonaon but that his excuse ?»ould come easier if he receiveo an otlicial letter to the effect that H.M's. Government did not yuite like the idea of his first visit to England as Ruler being made in an unofficial capacity, as the necessary honours coulu tot then be possible. telegraph hira a tactful message to the above effect, which he could convey to the Shaikh in writing as ■ 1 y verbally instructed. Lombardi, Director @f Standard Oil Company, are expectea at Kuwait on 2nd March en route for Bahrain, returning to Kuwait 9th March to stay with Shaiih for unknown Political Agent, in his confidential ft Political Agent suggests that you should Jansen, writer of invitation, ana per iod. POLITICAL. r. i^ UL- &lt;^(nrir ,s 6 -o. ^ 4*^I ■ ^ 86/1. Telegram R^S?. From Britconsul, Bushire To Political Agent, Kuwait. No. 150. Dsted the 1st March 1933. Gist of your Confidential letter lIo.39 / / telegraphed Resident, Muscat, under ^0.149. - BRITCOXSUL - • » ^ •Telegram Fr om Tc No. T-21 82/1 &amp; 86/1, P, Political Besiuent s at Muscat Political A.ge rt , Kuv/a i t * Dated 3rd March 1933 / Your letter ITo® 39. t A.t convenient opportunity you could explaintW^^ to Shaikh that If he visits England as guest of Syndicate there may he difficulties about treating his visit as official. RESIDENT.Confidential No.59 The Agency,Kuwait. Dated the 19th February 1 . Pi/I... . * ®.i - J q 1 0 H.H.P.Dickson G,1.3, Political Agent, Iluwait, To - The Hon T ble the Political Resident in the Persian G-ulf, Bushire. IHJIBHiRP ^ES^DfNCY. ^7' ^7/V3&gt; Q0HH9i&gt;»TiAL Mmi tf Invitation to Fis J^cellency the ^heildi by the eastern General Syndicate to -proceed to LondonV I ^ 1 \ \i o 4 Sir, In continuation of my Confidential No.18 Dated 26th January 1952. I have the honour to forward Unglish translation of a letter No• 2/824-xi, Dated 20th Shawal 1351 ( 15.2 .53) which I have received from His Excellency the Sheikh. It speaks for itself. 2 m For your information, I called on v His Excellency on the 14th February and carefully explained the gist of your Confidential D/0 No.104-^ of 1st February last,(which only reached me on 10th Febi This to an ordinary person would have been sufficient of a hint. The Sheikh however while thanking me for same, said that he proposed writing an oxiicial letter on the subject, as in a matter of 'is nature, he considered it his duty to first find out as to what the wishes of were, through you.2. 4. He added that he personally was dis inclined to accept the Companys invitation, hut that it would come much easier for him. to gracefully make the necessary excuses, if he got an orficial letter from you to the effect that • difl not quite like the idea o^ his first visit to England as Ruler of Kuwait, being made in an unofficial capacity, as it would prevent them 'paying him the necessary honours due to his Status. ' I do not know what your views are, but if you could see your way to give me an official letter or telegram, on the above lines, 3 think the sheikh wi-ul definitely not accept the invitation. It may interest you to know that Mr.Jansen, the writer of the invitation to the ^heidi, and I.Ir.Lombardi a Director of the standard Cil Coy will nass through Kuwait by air en route to Bahrain on Snd —arc - * Major Holmes proposes to accompany him f^om here, an... al^ three will return to '.uwait and stay with the cheikh, 9th. March, i-fter that Lr.-Jansens and I r • Lombardis movements are uncertain. The above news was given to me yesterday by the Sheikh and was confirmed by • -ajo^ Holmen, 7 The Sheikh apparently has not the courage to give Mr.Jansen a direct ^o- to his invitation, so hones for a letter from you, under cover of which he can get out of his predicament. This is rather typical of him. 0^ There is of course the danger, which no doubt you will recognize, that your reply will be shown to I/Ir.Jansen who may accuse you of bringing undue Influence to bear on the Sheikh, this I think must be risked, as it is clearly our duty to prevent the Sheikh accepting a privateprivate invitation of this sort. 9. Looking at things from every angle, am inclined to think that the best course, if you will pardon my making the surr-estion, wald be for you to telegraph me a tactful message to be delivered to the Sheikh in answer to his letter; this I could deliver verbally or in writing as you ordered me. I have the honour to be. Your most obedient servant, J4^ Col «' v Political Agent, IZuwait,^rc-nslxtlm of c oon^icentlal letter&gt; From - His Excellency Sheilch 31r Ahmad al~Jabir as-Gabah E.G.I.E., C.3.I., Ruler of Kuwait. To ~ The Political x^^ent, Kuwait. ITo .2/0^4—-1. Dated the 20th 3hauwal 1351 (loth February 1933). Af t or com.pliment s 5 V/ith reference to the verbal conversation which I had with your Hxcellency yesterday, Tuesday, regarding the letter which I have received from the President and the Manager of the Eastern and General Syndicate, Limited, London, in which they invite me to visit Lngland next summer at the expense of the said Company. I have not given them any definite reply yet, as it is my intention to approach Your Excellency beforehand, in order that you may enquire from His Ivla ^esty r s Government and let me know their wishes in this respect, for I cannot do such a thing,(accept the invitation) without first obtaining their consent and approval. Usual ending.Dear Colonel Fowle, ABADAN, PERSIAN GULF. \ 27th February, 1933. &lt; I / I have Just received a telegram from Sir John Cadman informing me that he will arrive by the fast B.I. mail due at Mohammerah on the 23rd March. Sir John also meeting you at Bushire on the 22nd ! arch, and you to find out v /hat as':s it T-. if there would be any chance of men the ship calls in at that Port Ghauncy has very kindly telegraphed your movements may be about this date. i am afraid that it will be impossible for Sir John to land at Bushire, nor can his arrival here be delayed as he must catch a special air connection which has now been arrang for his onward passage to Teheran. He is hoping, therefore, that you may find it possible to meet him on board in which case he could probably delay the ship's sailing for half an hour or so should this be necessary. If you will be so good as to let either X know if you can so arrange to meet Sir John, I liim on his arrival at Bombay. Chauncy or will inform Yours sincerely, Lieut-Col. T.C.W.Fowle, The Residency, Bushi re.82/1 &amp; 86/1 r\ ) \^T Telegram P. Erom H.M's. Secretary of State for the Qolonies, London. To Political Sesident, Pushire. Dated 14th (received 15th ) March 1932. 11 Private and Personal . Anglo-Per si an Oil Oompany have also strongs- urged desiratsiHty, in their interests / of meeting Shaikh mx iBimediately over date gardens and 'blockade. While, however, we are doing our utmost in interests of Shaikh to expedite decision, 1 fear it would he optimistic to hope for settlement in near future. Moreover, anxious as we are that Company should secure this concession if this can he done without violating outT pledges to the Americans, I feel that it is most Mx important to deal with it on a commercial 'basis and that their 'best hope of securing it lies in making an offer to the Shaikh definitely more attractive than that put up 'by the Syndicate, in which event I hope that he would not he so shortsighted as to allow either of ahove questions to influence his decision. Oompany are accordingly 'being informed that removal of political ohstacles cannot 'be looi(ed for in the near future hut that in any case question is, in our view, one to he dealt with essentially on a commercial hasis and that it is for them to consider what steps they should take to cogmter activities or offers of their competitors. As regards time factor, position is now rather altered. We were originally anxious to secure the earliest'possible decision. But a new factor has since heen introdticed hy cancellation 'by Persian/Persian Goyerrmient of Anglo-Persian Oil Compariy Concession and conneeted developments. This must inevitalDly handicap the Company in their negotiations, while Shaikh, on his side, may well wish to see the outcome of the sue renewed discussions 'between the Company and the Persie-ns 'before finally committing himself to the Anglo-Persian Oil Company; in any case it appears from your |ix reports that Shaikh is (k anxious/to take decision in his own time. So far as we are concerned, therefore, tbere is for the present no ohjection to the Shaikh^s postponing final decision for some time longer and continuing process of 'bargaining with 'both parties, 3* We attach great importance to 'being kept in closest possible touch with activities 'both of Company and Syndicate and shall he glad if you could arrange for fortnightly reports giving full details as to any developments from Dickson, despatch No. 10, dated 2nd JTehruary, Kuwait Oil, The foregoing is with reference to your Eis Majesty's Secretary of State for the Colonies... ^ ■ / &amp; % &amp; H 1 &lt; o CO FIBEMIAL . D.O.HO.230-S of 1933* The Residency, Bus hire, the 17 th March 1933. / / I ■ ^ f ! ■ s /•* /' Please refer to paragraph 3 of the Secretary oi State's Private and Personal telegram to me of 14th March on the subject of Kuwa.it Oil. 2 # I have 'been reporting developments as they occurred, my last comiiiunicati on being my Printed letter .^o» 16 (176 -3 to the Government of India), dated 21st February 1933. I am, however, asking Jickson to send me fortnightly reports, which I shall pass on to you# -nything oi importance will, of course, be reported separately with the least delay. ij ] jV i 3, In this connection X would invite attention to my ? Printed letter itto.ly (220-S to the Government of India), L. (%* dated the 16th March, in the enclosure to which Dickson reports two journeys of the Shaikh of Kuwait across his Southern boundary, ostensibly for hunting, in company, amongst others, of Holmes' ♦jackal*, Mohammed Yatim. The latter*s presence suggests that the journeys may have been connected with the Question of oil concessions in the Kuwait-Hejd Neutral ^one and in Hasa. 1%, . y 4 # Under my Printed, letter Mo# 64 i k 982-»i3 to the 'i ql- P Government of India), dated 30th December 1932, I reported that Holies had delivered to the Shaikh a message from the Eastern and General Syndicate inviting him to London as their/ C. G. Parkinson,Esq., G.M .G., O.L.E., Colonial Office, London.-2- their guest during the coming summer. This was confirmed are as he would not accept the invitation without obtaining their consent and approval, the fact being of course that he wishes His Majesty's Government to bear the onus of a refusal. I have told Jickson to explain to the Shaikh verball .7 that if he visits England as the guest of the Syndicate there may be difficulties about treating his visit as official, which I hope Director of the Standard Oil Company, passed through Kuwait by air on 2nd March and, after spending some time at Bahrain, returned with Holmes on the 14th March to Kuwait, where they ere the guests of the Shaikh for some time. I met both these individuals-while calling at Bahrain a few days ago on my way back from Muscat# They did not talk any business with me. I am sending a copy of the telegram referred to and of this letter to Metcalfe demi-officially# will ride him off Janson and Lombardi, the latter reported to be a 1 A 1 )i cog ■IDBSTIAL . The Residency, D # 0.H o .23£- S of 1935. B ub hire, the 17th Larch 1935. I enclose herewith copies of a Private and Personrl telegram dated 14th -larch 1933 from the Secretary of State for the Colonies and of my derai- \ i ( &gt; official letter Ko.230 -3 of to -day t to Pnrkinson. Will you please send me the fortnightly reports mentioned in paragraph 2 of xsj letter, reporting Immediately howeer, anything of importance. Lt.-Colonel H,R.P«Dickson f C.I.E*, Political Agent, K u w a 1 t.\ Telegram XX J'rom Political Resident, Bushire, To Government of India^oreign and Political Department, 'New Delhi, Repeated Secretary of State for India, London, Ho. 138, Dated the 20th March 1933, DSMI -OPFIGIAL. If increase in the salute for the Shaikh of Kuwait vide your letter of 25th January to the India Office could be granted it might have a favourable effect on Shaikh in the matter of Kuwait Oil, RSSIDS1TT - I:&gt;i o,246-o of 1933 , Copy with compliments forwarded to the Political Agent, Kuwait, for information, . By Order. for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, i82/1 &amp; 66/1. Telegram en clair. From Slkington, Basrah. Unnumbered Dated and received 20th March 1933. Following for Colonel Fowle. Sir John Cadman telegraphs expect arrive Bushire 8 a.m. ^Tckdnesday twenty second, as this possibly inconvenient to you suggest you accompany him Abadan or alternatively meet him here, iii latter case 1 will endeavour send tug although owing absence one of our tugs Q,ishm it will be difficult at the moment, alternatively I may be able to arrange aeroplane, for reasons you will understand ^ir John most anxious see you as soon as possible. Grateful if you will telegraph reply urgent. -SIKINGTON- Telegram en clair. From Political Resident, Bushire. To Gadman, Vasna; Elkington, Agglopers,Abadan. Unnumbered Dated the 2l3t March 1933. Addressed Sir Jtohn Madman Vasna repeated Elkington. Reference his telegram 20th March. Will come on bto^rd five thirty which will give us couple of hours for discussio u -Resident-82/1/&amp; 86/1 Telegram enclair ■^'rora Political Resident, Bushire# To Sir John Cadman, Steamship Vaana, Henjamradio Dated the 20th March 1933, Much regret cannot meet you as your ship is in quarantine. Resident -82/1 6c 86/1. Telegram En clair. From Political Besident, Bushire. To Blkington, A.P.O.G., AlDadan. No. 197. Dated 23rd March 1933. Your message of 22nd. When does Sir John Gadman leave Ahadan ? Would it he possible for me to i**# Hindi an or Behhehan ? I am making inquiries here regarding route up to there. RESIDENT82/1 and 86/1. Teleferam - enclair. From - Anglo-Persian Oil Co.Ltd. ^badan. To - Jackson, Z^eigler, Bushire. Unnumbered. Dated 23rd ^received 24th ) March 1933» Following is for Resident# Your telegram 197. Sir John Cadman leaves 26th March. Road via Behbenah or Hindian impassable. Strongly advise you not to attempt this route under the circumst&amp;nces. Sir John Cadman feels that this is unnecessary to cause you so much troible. Sir John Cadman making hurried visit Kuwait by air Saturday as he feels no efforts should be spared ensure British interest. - Anglopers -es/l &amp; 86/1 '} Te legram From Messrs, Anglo-Persian Oil Company, Abaclap, To Messrs. Ziegler &amp; Goo, -Bushire. Dated 26th (received P^th } March 1933. (Passed on to Residency by Ziegler &amp; CO.) TTrpe nt . Following for Resident. Reference your ielegram 198. Much regret cannot postpone departure. Very sorry that I (we?) cannot meet. Shall look forward to doing so on the next occa8ion6 My visit ( mu t ) satisfactory hut not conclusive. However feel position much strengthened. Cadman. Anglopers. //^7 f 82/1 &amp; 86/1 Telegram R % 21. Prom Political Agent, Kuwait, jtolltical Eesident, Bushire. To No. 60. Dated 27tli received 28th March 1933. Sir John Gadman, accompanied 'by General Manager, A..P.0.C;, Ahadan, and staff, visited Kuwait Saturday 25th March hy air and had long conference with Shaikh. Prom subsequent con- -versation with Sir John Oadman I learnj that all cards were put on the tahle and that quite exceptionally generous financial terms were offered to induce the Shaikh to grant the concession to Anglo Persian Oil Company immediately. The Shaikh responded 'by saying that he must consult Holmes,jThus MXsrfcxxaxKg confirming what 1 have always maintained, that the Shaikh was under some sort of obligation to HolmesTj Sir John Cadman assured me that he would return to the charge as soon as the Tehran situation permitted. Sir John Cadman returned to Ahadan the same evening. POLITICAL. Li A/V .C (t&lt; (Z &amp; .82/1 &amp; 86/1 '7 / / / I Telegram H. Z'j Prom Political Resident, i3ushire. To H.M's. Secretary of State for the Colonies, London, ,V Cp-py by ooat to - The foreign Secretary tti the Government of India, -New Delhi, No. 5. Dated S6th March 1933. Following dated 27th March received from the Political Agent, Kuwait, begins. Sir John Cadman, accompanied&lt;by Beneral Manager, Anglo-Persian Oil Company, Abada^ and staff, visited Kuwait Saturday 25th March by air and had long conference with Shaikh. From subsequent conversations with Sir John Cadman 1 learnt that all cards were pmt on the table Xfti and that quite exceptionally generous financial terras were offered to induce the Shaikh to grant the concession to Anglo-Perwian Oil Company immediately. The Shaikh responded by saying that he must consult Holmes. Sir John Cadman assilred me that he would return to the charge as soon as the Tehran situation permitted. Sir John Caflman return to Aba dan the same evening. Ends. - Resident. UvW (p*. ^ h 2#/3 .GONfflD-^NTIAL. Political Agency, Kuwait♦ No-53, ^ In Dated the 2End Llarch 1933, fj? u /- ^ , 'X 4 / | \ \ BUBHiRc f'~ ■■•'U -V' \ * : yvi Lt.-Colonel H .R .P .Diokson, C.I.2., I.A., ^ I et%:;:;£w m kbt-S' . Political Agent, Kuwait; To The Hon T ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, B U S H I R E . Invitation by The Eastern &amp; General Syndicate Ltd. to Shaikh to visit England, Sir, I have the honour to forward for your information and that of His La jesty* s Government, the following corres pondence: - (a) Letter, in original, dated the 19th March 1933 from Mr ♦E.W*Janson, Chairman &amp; Managing Director of the Eastern &amp; General Syndicate Ltd. to myself; (b) My reply (Confidential No*51J dated the 20th March 1933. 2. Mr.Jansor^s letter speaks for itself. 3. For your information as soon as I received Mr. Janson T s communication I called on the Shaikh and asked him if the contents of the letter were correctly stated. He replied that they were: Mr. Jan son, he stated, had, on his arrival back in Kuwait from Bahrain enquired whether he (the Shaikh) could give him a reply to the invitation of his firm,of 13th January last to visit England (see my Confidential No.l8)dated the 26th January 1933,): that he (the Shaikh)had replied that he had referred the matter to His Majesty's Government through the Hon 1 ble the Political Resident. Mr.Janson had then said that he wished to make the invitation a personal one now, and hoped that he (the Shaikh)would visit London as his r private guest* and not as/as the guest of the Company during the coming Summer; that he (the Shaikh) had replied expressing his thanks and pleasure at the idea of seeing England, 'but pointed out that he could in no way accept until His Majesty's Govern ment had been consulted and given their permission, this because he was under Great Britains protection, and so under definite obligations as regards leaving hisState» 4. I have given the Shaikh's reply at length as I think you should @e aware of his side of the case. 5. I do noHaiow what is behind this new move of the Eastern &amp; General Syndicate, but I should imagine that Mr•Jans on has changed the wording of his invitation to the Shaikh both to disarm the Shaikh and to meet pos sible objections of His Majesty's Government,. 6. I personally think it would be highly undesirable on political grounds for the Shaikh to visit England as the guest of a private individual. It is 'not done' in the Arab East and will be widely misunderstood. 7. The Shaikh has only to be clearly told that His Majesty's Government would be quite unable to recognise him or do him the honour due to his rank whilst in England, if he were to accept a private invitation of this sort; and I feel sure he would gracefully back out of the project. As in other matters, all he wants is a definite indication from His Majesty's Government of their wishes. 8. I aay add that the contents of your telegram No.T.21,dated the 3rd March 1935 were duly passed on to the Shaikh by me. All he remarked was that presumably the Political Resident will reply to his official letter by a / similar missive. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, ' Lt.-Colonel, Political Agent, Kuwait.Eastern and General Syndicate Limited. RAPHIC ADDRES8 : ND, CANNON, LONDON. 1 directors. w, GAMBLE. W.JANSON. RCY TARBUTT. Kuwait• 19th, March 1933• To. Leiut -Col; H.R.P.Dickson, His B, Ma j 1 s Political Agent, K U W A I T. Dear Colonel Dickson, Some time in December Major Holmes on my behalf, invited H. E, the Shaikh of Kuwait to visit England during this Summer as the guest of my firm, now however since being a guest of His Excellency I have asked him to be my personal guest. I shall -upon my return to London- advise the Colonial Office of the invitation to His Excellency and so wish to inform you so that if there be any official object- / ion you can make it known to me either here or through the Colonial Office in London. I may add that His Excellency has expressed to me his keen desire to accept my invitation and his wish to see England this Summer, Yours sincerely. \ \mM'mr-imAU lolltloal -f-noy.Kwalt. P.O.'io.51. Datoo the 20th ■ arch 1933. iv.y dear r » J an so n, I have to aofcuowledge r'?coipt of jour letter dated the 19th Marah 19S5, in which you inform m® that as a result of yovisit to uwalt you have ciecided to altar the form of your Invitation of 13th anuary last to His ^oellenoy the -h&amp;iKh of K\iwalt, and that you now have asked him fco be your' personal guest in London curing the a-uimer of WdZ instead of being the guest of the Eastern k General ^ynclcate, which was the form your original invitation took. In reply X write to say that obi 'or^arclln^ your letter, In original, to the the Political Resident in the Persian ^ulf for the consideration of T !ls ^ejeety * s Govern^mt and a reply will, no doubt, he received in duo oourne# Yours sincerely, Sd. H.R.P» Dickson. Sanson .'.squire. Chat man t Mamging Director, Eastern General 3un&lt; i oate.S»ji *f&gt; CO:.FIDEi:TIi\L . Downing Street, % ^ v- v •&gt; • March. 19 5o« ^ v //3 - J ^ \ . a ( ;I [SUSHIRS ■IE9&lt;DS NCY. ^ ^ : 7 h- - ^V' i « I *»« H^W-V-- ■ — -/ — / GOKFiQE^' :^ iEuGBDS 1Cuwait 0 i1 Concession. I write to let ; r ou know the t Sir John Cadi;;an called recently to see Sir Samuel Wilson on this matter. Sir J'. 0adman wanted to know whether any influence could ce 'brought to he r on the Shaikh to give the con cession to the Anglo-Persian, as the Anglo-Persian had come to an agreement with the Gulf Company that if the Anglo-Persian obtained the concession they would work it, and the Gulf Company would have a 50 per cent sh re holding. Sir J. Cadman also enquired whether a decision on the matter could 'be held up until he got dack from Persi a. Sir S. Wilson has replied to Sir J. Cadman that His Ilajesty's Government are committed to a policy of not influencing the Shaikh, and that it would nor 'be possible to go 'back on that. As regards nolding matters COLONEL T.C. FOWLE, C.B.E.GONFIDMTLtiL Political Agency, Kuwait. r~i ^ +- V, /--» O O *--1 T ' -v* T /'i r \ No. 52 From Lt .-Colonel H.R,P.Dickson, G.I.E,, I.A., Political Agent, Kuwait; To The Hon T ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf , B u s h 1 r e , I have the honour to report that Lr.Janson, Chair man &amp; Managing Director of the Eastern &amp; General Syndicate, Ltd., accompanied by Major and Mrs. Holmes arrived from Bahrain on the 14th March and took up their quarters at Dasman Palace as the guests of His Excellency the Shaikh, 2. Mr. Lombardi , one of the Directors of the Standard Oil Co. Ltd., arrived from Bahrain by Imperial Airways on the 16th March and also stayed with the : ;uler, 3. I am unable to say how long Mr.Janson intends to stay in Kuwait. 4. Mr.Janson and Major Holmes paid the usual official calls on the Agency on 17th March but as yet Mr.Lombardi did not think fit to do so. The latter person left for IRAQ, on 19.3.133, Visit of Messrs Lombardi and J an son to Kuwait Sir I have t he honour to be, Sir ^four most obedient servant - * ' Lt.-Colonel, Political Agent, Kuwait vssSECRET. ; Political Agency,iluwait. ■*j co- ^Dated the 2End March 1932. NO. z&gt; o f ^ 6 i M From Lt ♦-Colonel H.H.i ♦Dickson, '^♦I.E., I^A^, Political Agent, Kuwait; To The Hon'hie the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, BUSH1R3 • tihiss QiA - Activiti es of I^a.i or iio3-iiies. ( I — Sir, I have the honour to report that on the ISth Instant and in Hie absence of . ajor holmes at raKrain, His Excellency the Shaikh mentioned casually to me at a dinner party in my house that Major Holmes had prepared or was preparing two new draft Oil Agreements to replace the one already submitted by him last year and which was commented on by His Majesty's Government. Owing to the presence of other guests I could not pursue the subject at the time. 2. On the 14th March Mr .Janson accompaniea by Major and Mrs.Holmes returned from Bahrain and were taken to Dasman Palace where they stayed as guests of the Shaikh. 3. On the 14th March I called on His Sxcellency and on the completion of certain business which I had to transact X reminded him of his conversation at my dinner party and asked if he could give me any details of the two new draft agreements which Major Holmes was supposed to have prepared* 4. The Shaikh apologized for not having mentioned the matter before and said that the facts were as follows: That he had, prior to Major Holmes's departure for Bahrain on 9th March (with Mr .Janson) asked him to put up two new draft concessions (twin) in place of the old single - , one /one that he had put forward: (a) One to comprise 1200 square miles which was to be reserved for British interests; (b) One to comprise 400 square miles to be reserved for American interests. That Major Holmes had demurred for two days, and then agreed to try and carry out his (the Shaikhs) wishes; That after some preliminary fencing I.Iajor Holmes had further agreed I that the 'lump sum down*, which the Eastern &amp; General Syndi cate would be willing to pay the Shaikh on his signing each of the new draft concessions would be the same, namely Rs.45,000 for each separate concession (a) and ib), other subsequent payment being the same also in each case; That | in this way he (the Shaikh) would get Hs.90,000 straight away as a first payment, which figure was superior to anything the Anglo Persian Oil Company had to offer. Lastly the Shaikh said that he thought that the existing draft Agreement of the Eastern &amp; General syndicate, as it stood even, was a superior one to that of the Anglo Persian cil Gorrij.anv • 5. After expressing some surprise at this new move of the Shaikhs 1 opined that it was impossible for two sepa rate concessions to be granted to two companies in his small state. To this the Shaikh replied that he uhougnu it was quite vossihle that such two companies would doubtless come to some agreement with each other. I did not pursue the sub ject further. 6. Before leaving I mentioned to the Shaikh that I proposed asking Major Holmes for the two ne// drafts he had prepared. The Shaikh raised no objection but pointed out that I should ask in my letter n for the two drafts which the Shaikh had asked should 'be prepared , . 7. I, accordingly, addressed Major Holmes officially under letter No*.50,dated the 22nd —arch ana asked nim if he would kindly furnish copies of his new drafts -or .-is majesty '' ———,—, .—.—, —^ ^•• i 'i' ■ . . 1 ■ ' ' 1 11 'l' _ . _ l ■■ l ■ ■ . -r - — i ^ iii———».i ■ ■ ■ ..i ■ ■ i ■■ ^ _- 3 - Ma j e s ty' s Gov eriuae nt T s and your inf ormati on • 8. A copy of this letter together with Major Holmes's reply and a subsequent letter No»56,dated the 22nd March which I addressed to Major Holmes are enclosed for your inform, ation. 9. You will note that Major Holmes, in his reply to my first letter, as good as declines my request and leaves it for the Shaikh to give me copies of the drafts, when all points at issue had been agreed upon. At the time of writ- ing Major Holmes has not replied to second letter. x 10. In conclusion I think the Shaikh has got his idea of a double or twin agreement wither as a result of advice from Baghdad or as a result of his recent meeting with Bin Saud in the Desert, which from later corroborative evidence, I am now almost certain, took place, i am in clined to the former theory. 11. The Shaikh's object, as I see it, is to put him self right with His Majesty's Government by apparently offering the larger concession of the two to British in terests, and the smaller to the iiinericans. ^.n reality his intention would appear to oe to try and arrange for an Anglo American group to take up and work any concessiori finally taken up. prefers 12. It is unfortunate that the Shaikh,/at this juncture, to keep me in the dark as to his re&amp;l intentions. I put this down to the influence of Major -olmes and the interested advice he continually receives from that person. 13. Major Holmes and Mr.Janson have suddenly decided to fly to-morrow (23.3.33.) to Cairo and have a further conference with Mr.Lombardi of the Standard Oil, i cannot say, at present, whether they are trying to drag him into the Kuwait business or whether their conversations are con nected with Bin Saud and uejd Gil. I rather fanc&gt; thcxt the/_ 4 - that the latter is the correct answer and that Major Holmes will try and go on from Cairo to Jeddah. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, ' -Lt,-Colonel, Political Agent, Kuwait. MGL&gt; 5. Y3S. ~ &amp; U J~. s J'Copy of confidential letter No.50,dated the 21st March from the Political Agent, Kuwait to Major Frank Holmes, Eastern &amp; General Syndicate, Kuwait, ,oCo — I understand from His Excellency the Shaikh that at his request you have prepared and submitted to him two new ' twin ' draft Oil Agreements for his consideration, as alternatives to the single draft Agreement, already in possession of His Excellency and His majesty* s G -overnment» 2. 1 further understand that the main features of these new draft agreements are as follows:- (a) The first is to be confined to British in terests and embraces an area of 1200 square miles (b) The second will be reserved for American interests and embraces an area of iS 400 square miles. 5. If I have got my facts correct and I have not mis-understood His Excellency the Shaikh I should be glad if you will let me have copies of the above two fresh draft agreements, for submission to His Majesty's Govern ment and the Hon'ble the Political resident and, if pos sible, before you leave for Cairo.Copy of letter dated the 21st March 19 52 from Major /rank Holmes, Eastern &amp; G-eneral Syndicate Ltd», Kuwait to Lt.-Colonel H*RJ?*Dickson, 0.1.E., I.A #J Political Agent, Kuwait. — oOo--' I have received your letter No.50 marked con fidential dated the 21st March 1935 in which you request me to ?, let you have copies of the fresh draft Agreements' As you have marked your letter ?T Confidential' it therefore precludes me from discussing your letter with his ilxcellency the Shaikh and I feel that the above course should be my procedure. More especially as the Shaikh will, no doubt, forward to you a copy so soon as he has agreed all points at issue. Your facts are only partially correct.Oopy of Confidential letter 1:0.56, dated the 2Snd March 1933 from the -olitical Agent, Kuwait to Major Frank Folmes, The Eastern Sc General Syndicate, Kuwait. — 0O0 -- I have the honour to acknov^ledge receipt of your letter dated the 21st instant, for which I tender my thanks. 2. The 'Confidential' marking of my letter No.50 dated the 21st March has not the meaning attributed to it by you, nor is there any objection to your discussing it with. His Excellency the Shaikh. 3. ois indicated in my letter No.50 my information was based on a conversation which I had with His Excel lency the Shaikh himself, who was verbally told by me that I proposed addressing you on the subject. 4. I note from your letter that my information is only partially correct. 5. In conformance with the normal procedure I shall be glad if you will let me have copies, for my own information and that of the Hon'ble the Political Resident of any new draft oil Agreements as and when you present them to His Excellency the Shaikh.CONFIDENTIAL. No. 24/264-0 of 1933. The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com- pliments to His Majesty* s Jecretrry of otate for the :oloni es,London. 'o.24. The Foreign Secretary to the Governiuent of India,New ^elhi. Ivo.284-S and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment (s). British Residency and Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated 27tlrS laT'Oh* 1' :•)• * 3; Reference to previous correspondence : Uusbire prlntad 2lBt FebrlMlr » l93a ' Name and Date. ^ Letter No. 58 of 22nd trrch ^ 1933 from the Political \gent, Kuwait, wi th enclosures# r Subject. OIL ACT i.V ii i L a .- j OF IIAJOi HOL : Copy with cOdipliments forwarded to the political Agent, Kuwait, for information.Telegram R. from 3?olitical Hesident, Bus hire. To H.M's. Secretary of State for the Colonies, London. Copy by post to ~Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, Hew Del hi« ITo. 6. Bated ?9th March 193 3, Kuwait Oil . Shaikh has informed Political Agent that at Shaikh's request Holmes had prepared two fresh draft/ concessions to replace Syndiaate's present draft, one to cover area of 1200 square miles to be reserved for British interests the other to cover 400 square miles to be reserved for American interests. -Payments under both drafts are the same initial payment in each case being Rs. 45,000. Report posted 28th March.^ Resident. No. P93-S of P9th March 1933 issued to Governmert of India and Kuv;ait.CONFIDENTIAL. No. SQ3-'' of 1933. i he Hon bio the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to The ^oreirm necretarv to (xoverTmerl of India, New &gt;lhi, The ^o 11 *■ i cal Ape n t f ■ aw ait, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment British Residency and Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated 59th March 1033. / Bufihire n, 1. . 0 R4-' of P^th ' ! ar Description of Enclosure. Reference to previous correspondence : ? of ^th March 193 3. Name and Date. Subject. Tele£ran ^o. 5 o^ P9th 'arch '33 to the Colorial Office, Lender?. Km?a it Oil,f. mfP I lENT IAL . 1I0.S13 -3 of 1933. Britisii Residency &amp; Consulate- : 3enerax, Busnire, the 3lst Marofi 1933. I ' Frora The Hon*ble Lt.-Colonel T.G.Fowle, C. i oliti cal Resident in the Persian u-uxi, jo _ The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, Hew Delhi. Subieot: Visit of Shaikh of Kuwait to^ngland as guest of the Eastern and General Syndicate Limited. Sir, I have the honour to report that some time ago Colonel Dickson forwarded me a letter addressed to him from His iixcellency the Shaikh of Kuwait, a copy of which i enclose, and which explains itself. Later Colonel Dickson informed me that the form of the invitation had been changed and that a fresh invitation had been issued in the re-me of Mr. Janson, ( a copy of whose letter to Colonel Dickson is enclosed), one of the Directors of the Syndicate. Presumably this tod been done to give a slightly less 'company' flavour to the invitat ion, but to all intents a.nd purposes it comes to the same thing. On Colonel Dickson enquiring from the Shaikh as to the correctness of Mr. Janson's letter. His Excellency con firmed it, and added that he had thanked Mr.Janson for his invitation, but ted informed him that he could not accept unti His Majesty's Government had been consulted, and given their permissi on,/-2- 4/ permisai on a 2, Wi til regard to His Excellency^ letter of 15th February, I thought it best to try ana settle the matter informally and so asiced Colonel .Dickson to take a suitable opportunity to explain verbally to the Shaikh that if he visited England ?-s the guest of the Syndicate there mignt be difficulties about treating his visit as official. This hint was duly passed on to His Excellency whose only remark - so Colonel .'Dickson informs me - was to the effect that presumably the Political Resident would reply to his official letter by a similar missive. 3, Both Colonel Dickson and I think it distinctly un desirable that the Shaikh should visit England as the 'guest* of either the Syndicate or Mr. Janson. On the other hand the days, in my opinion, have definitely gone by when we can keep the more important Arab Rulers of the Gulf - so lon^ as they adhere to the terms of their treaties with us « in leading strings. I think in the long run we are likely to get more from them by - whenever possible - letting them make the their own choice, with/ensuing consequences. I think it is probable too that His .l^xcellency will show whatever official reply he receives to the Syndicate. I have had these various considerations in mind when drafting the reply, which I en close, to the Shaikh 's letter of Ibth February, and which I suggest I be authorized to send. I would have preferred to settle the matter informally as in paragraph 2 above without troubling Government on tne subject. As, however, the Shaikh has insisted on making 'heavy weather 1 of the question, and on receiving an official reply * one has to be sent, I therefore thought it best to submit a draft before replying.-3- 4. I would be grateful for telegrapftic approval of the above draft. In the meantime I have instructed Colonel Dick son to inform the Shaikh that an official reply on tne matter will be sent to him in due course. This will keep the matter in suspension for tne present. I am sending a copy of this letter to ilis Majesty's * Secretary of State for India. sent under P.L. N0.314-S of 31/3/33. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, tc Lt.-Golonel. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.DRAFT LETTER TO HIS EXGBLLEITCY THE SHAIKH OF KUWAIT. After Compliments, The Political Agent, Kuwait, duly for warded to me Your Excellency's letter of the Ibth February to him on the subject of an invitation which the Itestern and General Syndicate Limited have extended to you to visit Kngland this summer as tneir guest and at their expense. Your ilixcellency stated in tnat letter that you had not given any definite the result of reply pending/ n enquiry from His Majesty's Grove nment as to their wishes in the matter, and whether they gave their consent and approval. In a further letter Colonel Dickson informed me that he h d received a letter from Mr, Janson, one of the Directors of tne Eastern and General Syndicate Limited, stating that the invitation for Your iixcellency to visit England had now been changed to an invitation from Mr. Janson himself, instead of from the Syndicate. To this invitation - so Colonel Dickson informed me - Your Excellency had given the same reply as to the invitation from tne Gon^any. I am directed by His Majesty's Government to reply to Your Excellency as follows# While a Ruler of a State often pays short visits to an Oilfield, or a factory, belonging to a Company for the purposes of inspection, it is unusual for a Ruler to visit for the purpose of pleasure and change of air a foreign country where the Company has no »vorks of its own to show him, and to permit that Company, or one of its members, to pay the expenses of that visit. But if Your iixcellency wishes to visit/visit England as tne guest of tne Eastern and General Syndicate Limited, or of Mr. Janson, you are of course at liberty to do so, and tnere is no question of His Majesty's Government's wishes, approval or consent. Should Your ii.xcellency, however, visit England in such circumstances, His Majesty's Government under stand that it will be unofficially, and that Your Excellency will not expect to be received officially with the honours customary on an official visit. Usual Ending.CONFIDENTIAL . No316.S of 1933. f Lr ^ iL^ The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to The Political Agent, Kuwait^ and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of th^ undermentioned docu ment (ijf! with a request that he v/ill merely inform the Shaikh at this stage that an official reply will be sent to him on the matter in due course. British Residency and Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated . ..3.1.s.t. .March. .1.93.3.... Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Letter ^o .313-S of 31st March 1S33 to the Foreign Secretary t o the Government of India, with copy of the draft letter to the Shaikh. Visit of Shaikh of Kuwait to England as guest of the Eastern and General Syndicate Limited.CONFIDENTIAL. No. 317 -S of 1933. The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to The Foreign secretary to the Government of India., .New Delhi, The Political A^ent, Kuwait. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment V. 8 / rr&gt; 4 ' 3* ! British Residency and Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated — 5 Is.t. . J aarcii..l.95u... r- J . U Ah 1 ^ Reference to previous correspondence : Bushire printed letter iJo.288-S of 28th March 1935. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. 7 Letter iio. 18119/33 of 2nd March 1933 from the Colonial Off ice. Subject. Kuwait Oil Concession,64/27 5c 32/1 -86/1. Telegram XX, From India Office jt To Political ReBiaent, Bvshire. Ho. 849. Dated 1st received End &amp;pril 1933. x^idOHAL . Following from Laithwaite for Fowle. Your personal telegram of 1st April. Airways tmH^teen asked to facilitate passages for you and family 'by air mail arriving here 18tli. As one of the principal subjects for discussion will 'be Kuwait oil we agree as to desirability of your visiting Kuwait if possible, and would have no objection to postponing arrival here for a week if essential for this purpose. In any case it is important that ohaikh should not take decision on Kuwait oil during your absence and your visit to Kuwait may make it possible to put this beyond aoubt. We should be grateful in this connect- -ion if you could let the Shaikh know, in whatever manner you consider desirable, that once he receive^ the fresh drafts concessions referred to in your telegram No. 6, dated 29 th It arch, to the Jolonial Office, we shall be ready to advise on them as in the case of the concessions previously put forward by the Syndicate. We regard it as most important that he should, in fact, ask us so to advise. Please let us know what you decide. 3SGBBTAHY OF SIATE FOR INDIA.CONFIDENTIAL. N o .328-S of 1933 The Hon'ble the Political Resiaent in the Persian Gulf presents his coin- pliments to The Political A.gent, Kuwait, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment for information only . British Residency and Consulate-General, st j 1 t»ttc1tttr» m BUSHIRE. Buahire printed letter l&gt;lo er Bo J§tT 0 S/ 0 OT 0 fa^ e mi e . n0e : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Secretary of State for India London^s personal telegT -am Uo.349 of 1st Apyll 1933. Kuwait Oil Concession (oITe le gram XX. From H.M's. Secretary of State for India, London, To Governinent of India, Foreign and Political Department, no, 850. Repeated Political Hesident, Bush ire, Ho. 851. Bated (and received ) 1st April 1933. Import an t « Resident's demi-official telegram of 20th March 1933, No. 188. SALTJ^KS. His MaJ esty has approved of proposals in your letter of Jamaary P5th. Please instruct Resident accordingly. - his m.:msrr f 3 sechb^ary of S^A'^ K)R IKDIA.64/27 and 82 /1 -86/1, Telegram xx From Govenament of India,Foreign and Political Deptt.. New Delhi, To Political Resident, Bushire, No. 859, Dated 2nd ( received 3rd) April 1933. v'-iX k-l/f ' /I &lt;' ' PRIVATE. f, a i Your telegram of 27th March, No.208» Secretary of State expects you to arrive home by air on 18th April. '/ou should arrange accordingly. Meantime Minister at Tehran and Secretary of State are being addressed for official sanction to your deputation. Authorities at home however consider it of greatest importance that you should return to Gulf not later than air mail of May 6th in view of present stage of Kuwait oil negotiations, postponing your leave until later in the summer. - Foreign -82/1 &amp; 86/1 Telegram IU27. From Political Besident, Bushire, To Vice Consul &gt; Mohammerali. No. 234• Dated 3rd April 1933. , f- \ ' PKRSONAL AND CCN?IIjE^IAX . Please inform Elkin^tori privately of contents of my telegram No, 231, adding that I am leaving Kuwait for Baghdad 'by R.A.F, plane on the morning of 11th April and would 'be pleased to meet him anywhere en route if he would Hike discussion. TOWLETown and 82/l. Telegram xx From Government of India, Foreign and Political department, Hew Delhi. To Political Resident, Buahire. flo. 86y. Dated 3rd ( received 4th ) April 19 35. ^ 4 ' -K- (Preamble mutilated: reference obviously is to Secretary of State's teie t rram ^o.Bbl of 1st April 1933). Personal salutes for present Shaikh of Bahrain and Shaikh of Kuwait. Please take action accordingly. - FCKEiiaH - -t^ hr- r- e.rf/i t., dj •?- j 12 ■ i ((/&gt;■^■77 U.i &lt;?, *&gt;(% CONFIDENTI AL. 16th March 1955• lAfM (?(&gt;' L'l; ^w/jo LJEE^ My dear Fowle, In continuation of my confidential letter of the 2nd March about the Kuwait Oil Concession, 1 enclose a copy of a letter sent by Sir Samuel Wilson on the 15th March to Mr. Hearn of tne Anglo-Persian Oil Company. This is the letter referred to towards the end of paragraph 1 of the Secretary oi State's private and personal telegram sent to you on the pJ ' 14th March. TV ^ rv.A_X_N&gt;v- (Copy with copy of enclosure sent to Kuwait under P.L.No.335-S of 4/4/35j-.Ref• our p.l.^o.328-S of 2/4/33, / A?7 y l/ i f tenant Colonel T.C. Fowle, C.B.E., a&amp;D 00i*F 11^,1!TIaL«. Colonial Office, l/owniag Street, S. , .1. /s' haroh, 19 ;5. ws you are iio doubt aware, I recentl, had some discuseion and oorrespondenoe with Cad ^an about the iCuYie.lt Oil Concession, In the course of the discussion Cadman referred to certain political difficulties bet-ween the Sheikh and His i ajesty' s Government ana enquired whether there was any prospect of the early removal of these difficulties. Unfortunately there is no such prospect, though we are of course concerned to dispose of them as rapidly as may be; and since we are committed to a policy of not influencing the Sheikh, the question is one essentially to bo dealt wita on a commercial basis. My object in writing to you now is to say that so far as we can judge, the sheikh is not likely to be much moved by the difficulties in question if the Anglo-Persian Oil Company out up an offer iARI, jiSQ.offer which, viewec oomiuercially , is definitely very much better than that put up by the ■'•astern and General Syndicate, and in these circumstances it seeras to us to be for the Company to consider what steps should be taken to counter the activities or offers of their com otiters in .uvait.82/1 • Telegram 3?roitt Political Resident, Bushire^ To Political Agent, Kuwait. No. 239. Dated 5th April 1933. ..•# A ; h C/ ^ ' My printed letter No.328-S of 2nd April. I propose to inform Shaikh on arrival that I expect him to seek ( as he did in the case of the earlier draft concessions submitted by the Anglo-Persian Oil Company and the Syndicate) advice of His Majesty's Government on twin draft concessions prepared by Holmes, wnich are in tiie nature of fresh praposals on which he will require advice of His Majesty's Government. I shall also ask him to give me copies thereof to take with me to London to obtain such advice for him. If you see no objection please inform Shaikh verbally accordingly so that copies may be prepared in time. Shaikh's personal salute has Just been raised to eleven guns at my suggestion. I meant to convey this to him officially myself but if you think that it would affect his attitude favourably in the matter of above please inform him verbally adding that I will bring official confirmation myself. - Resident -8S/1 Telegram ^«S7. From H. M * s, Vice-Consul, Mo hammer ah. To ^oli ti cal Resident, Bushire. No. 33. Dated 5th (received 6th ) April 1933, -4' r ' Your telegram No. 234. 'frollowinf? from 331kington, begins : i would very much like to meet you. Basra or Shaiba would suit me best if also convenient to you. Can you telegraph me time and where« Perhaps you would breakfast with me at Galpin's if Basra. Ends. - BHITCONSITL. Telegram Prom Political Resident, Bushire. To Air Officer Commanding,Ii*aq Command, 3agdad. No. 243• Dated 6th April 1933. Many thanks for aircraft. Can machine land at Shaibah for an hour en route to Bagdad to enable me to see ElkingtOn of Anglo-Persian Oil Company ? - ResidentHV 82/1 Telegrrim Fr om To Unnumbered, Dated 8th April 19 33 en clair Political Resident, Bushire Elkington, Anglopers, Abadan I leave Kuwait early 11th April and arrive Shailaah probably about 6 a»Tn. where I will xand if you can meet me otherwise not. Please telegraph me at Kuwait. ^ PCXCLS -| BUSHiRf ntWMNCV [• K 0 0)U (a. y 1&gt;1 ^ OONHWTUl HtUtMi()6 &gt; Points discussed rlth His SxceXlsncy Sheikh of Kuw It on 10th April 1933 th« Hon tie, the Political Resident. c:r '-Sl&gt;'-'c.Kzen. 1. P.R. asked Sheikh not to make any decision rlth regard to the competing oil Companies until the P.R. r-'tu:- led fron 3n-:land {toth May) 1Q 7 .T Sheikh gladly agreed, 0 » 'he P.R. s?ld he understood from Col, Dickson that the two irafts mentioned by the Sheikh (see Cjt. A&gt;ictvsons 1 ei.^.0r --o• '&gt;? o-^nd Msrch) were now out o^ d-.te, '■ Ince r:r ,S. had informed Col, Dickson that Sir J. Caclnmn on his recent visitjto Kuwait, h d m de a further , and apparently final offer, which was distinctly in advance of anything hithertoo offered by Col, Fowle said that he would be grateful if before Sheikh accepted any proposal from either Company, he (H.S.) would submit the draft proposal for H # M . Cts advice, as he had already done in case of initial proposals. Col, Fowle asked the Sheikh to submit the proposal to H.M.G-e without indicating to the Company propos ing it , that he (H.3.) intended giving it to them* The Sheikh agreed immediatly to thie suggest ion, -nd said that it had always bf-en hi' intention to dc 'o, ' T ot . The point of t Is request is t -.t th Sheik tov 'o reason might like to accent s ' T or c ;offer {comn•&gt;;rcirl 1 y) from the i.G-.S., because olxHolmes 1 Qcxi: t' vt influence over him, or because ?iolmn-£ is prepared to give him a secret gratuity, which would not appear in the published agreement, or because H.E. might like to interest the American G-overnment in Kuwait,with the object of playing off HaM.CK versus the American G-ovt. If however H.E^as he has prom ised, submits the final pronosal f^om either Company for the advice of , the latter in the above contingency^ would be quite at 1 ibert:'-in th:. form of advice^to point out that th pronosal which the oheikh was willing to accept from the E,G-.S,P. z. my 1955 &gt; BRITANNIC HOUSE, FIN3BURY CIRCUS, LONDON, i:.0.2. 17th March, I935. Dear Sir Samuel Wilson, I haye to thank jou for your letter of the 15th March on the subject of the Kuwait Oil Concession. I am writing to-day to 3ir John Cadman on this and other suojects, and my letter ahould arrive at Abadan on the 23rd of this month, which is the probable date of his own arrival therefrom Bombay, I know it is his intention to consider the whole Kuwait position in the light of the very latest information, - both local aid external, - immediately he arrives in Aba dan; your letter on the subject will therefore reach him in good time for the information you give to be of immediate use to him. lours, etc., ( Sd .) A .0 . HBAEIv . Sir Samuel Wilson, G .C ,M.G . ,K .0 .B •, etc., Colonial .ffice. Downing Street, S.W.I. (Copy sent to Kuwait under p # L.No.368-S of 11/4/32). Reference our p.l.No»335 -S of 4 /4 /33, (j, tbh ■82/1 &amp; 86/1 From foreign Secretary to the Government of India. New Delhi. To Secretary of State for India, London, Repeated Political Resident, Bus hire. No. 948. ])ated ISth (receiTed 13th ) April 193:5. I Bushire letter No. 313-S, dated 31st March 1933. SHAIKH OF KUWAIT'S VISIT ^0 ENGLAND. o- x / - 2. We concur in terms of draft letter which the Resident proposes addressing to the Shaikh and recommend that the Resident he authorised to send it. - FOREIGN. (Copy forwarded to Kuwait under P.L,IJo.377-S of 13/4/33). Ref.our p.1.^0.316.3 of 31/3/33 i o(Copy, without enclosure^, sent to Kuwait under P. L.No.392-3 of 19/4/33) .Ref.our P.L.No. 368-S of 11/4/33. O 7^ Colonial Office, J' / y Dovm i ng Str e et, 19/33. a ; W i March, 1933. Dear Colonel Fowle, n In Parkinson 1 s absence on leave, I am sending you a copy of a letter from i^r. Hearn of the •h 1933« ^ Anglo-Persian Oil Company, relative to the Kuwait Oil Concession. A copy of Sir Samuel Wilson's letter of the 15th of March was sent to you in Parkinson's letter of the 16th of March. / /' ^: Yours sincerely,CONFIDENTIAL, NTo ' 430-S of 1933. The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to The foreign secretary to tae Government of India, SIMLA. Che Poli t ical A^ent, Kuwait. The * oiitiCc, i .i, eiit, kiiirain. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment (s). &gt;/ British Residency and Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated 24th April 1933, Reference to previous correspondence ; DescrTptTotTof Enclosure. Name and Date. Bushire telegram l*o.B, / S dated the 24th April 1^33 to His i^ctjeaty^s Secretary of Btate for the Colonies, London. Subject. liovements of LaJ or Holmes of the .Astern and (reneral indicate limited.8S/1, 86/1 icy 'i Telegram X« From Secretary of State for the Colonies, LoMon fo Political ResMent, Bushire, No. 3 # Repeated -Political Agent, Kuwait. Dated 26th (received S7th ) April 1933. COH?IDB]f r, IA L. Your (telegram ) ITo. 8. Now Holmes has returned Shaikh has no douht consulted with him on the latest offer by the Anglo-Persian Oil Company reported in your telegram No. 5. Please instruct the Political Agent to approach the Shaikh without delay and ascertain tactfully and unofficially, without giving the Shaikh impression that we are unduly interested, H(olme8 reaction to the Anglo-Persian Oil Company, and any indication as to Shaikh's present attitude. This information is required, if possible, for discussion in London with Resident on 3rd May. - SECERTelegram jrom Political Resident, Bushire. To Political Agent, Kuwait. Ho« 324. Dated the 27tii April 1933. Please take action accordingly and telegraph report to me repeating to Secretary of State for Colonies. Foregoing refers to Colonial Office telegram No* 3 * - RESIiJENT -82/1 86/1 Telegram B-'SV. jYom Secretary of State for India, London. y 0 Political Resident, Bushire. No.1050. Eepeated Government of India, Foreign and Political Department,Simla. No.1051. Dated the 28th ( received 29th ) April 19 33. i Government of India telegram of 12th April, 948. Subject to following verbal amendments, His .Hi Majesty*s Government agree to despatch of draft letter to Shaikh of Kuwait included in Bushire despatch dated 31st March, 313-3, and would be glad if it could he despatched without delay. (a) paragraph 4 line 1 for fcfc® 'often pays rt substitute 'occasionally pays'; (b) paragraph 4 line 3 for 'it is unusual' substitute 'it would be most unusual'; (c) paragraph 4 penultimate sentence before words 'at liberty to' omi t words 'of course' and omit aords 'and there is no question of His Majesty's Government's wishes, approval or consent'. - Secretary of State for India-CONFIDENTIAL. No. 446-3 of 1933. f\c The Hon'ble the Political Hesident in the Persian Gvilf presents his com pliments to The Political Agent, Kuwa it, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment (s). &gt; V 'OA w V'A ' --iv I I, ^ British Residency and Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. R r • /' ' Ajj. — ^ SHife / Dated.... • i , 9 , 3 , 3v Reference to previous correspondence BUSHIRE PHI TED LETTER N0.377-S of 13TH APRIL 1933, h&gt; ti2. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. f 11/ 0 -CM 1. IHDIA OFFICE telegram No.1050,dated the 28th April 1933. 2. Letter of 29th April 1933 to the Shaikh of Kuwait, for favour of delivery. 3. Copy of (2) for Agency record. Shaikh of Kuwait's vi sit to ENGLAND.&lt;pi' rnCRST. No. 80. ■-r 1 % / I / Political Agency, Kuwait» Dated the 27th April 1935# From I/U-Cloael H^R^P^Didcson^ I.A #&gt; j'^ wmtNil 'i i« Wtiim &gt; i ■ v • —m-- ■- Polttioal Agent, Kuwait^ 1 Kf f l ■ '»i v» _ 7.7^ To j DM- The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian G-ulf, Bush ire % Oil Situation Rei&gt;ort for 2nd Fort night of April Sir, With reference to your demi official letter N0.2S2-S, of 17th March 1933 I have the honour to report that nothing of an unusual nature occurred during the first fort- nl#xt of April, which coincided with the period ^tha Major Holmes was absent in Egypt and Jeddah. Local Oil matters were entirely overshadowed by the arrival of H.M.S. 'Enterprise and the Persian Gulf Squadron and the round of entertainments that had been arranged. My fortnightly reports on the Oil Situation will , therefore start from 15th April - the present being the first of the series• I note that anything of an important nature should be telegraphed to yoxu ARRIVAT. OF KHMT BA.E1P ^R ABDUL LATIi? pttj ARTOTT. .TALIL , PIRSCTOR OF r-nsTOMS AT KOWAIT. (a) This individual, an elderly and very shrewd person has been residing at the court of His Majesty King Bin Saud for the last 3 years in sort of voluntary exile. He arrived back from Riath via Bahrain early in April, and after the King had proceeded to Mecca. Ostensibly/ I r P 11 I 1 ' i/ ~ 2 - Ostensibly this person returned to visit his family 'who reside in Kuwait and also to make his peace 'with the Shaikh from 'whom he had 9 3 years previously, parted under a cloud. In reality there is evidence to show that he knows more about Oil matters than he possibly cares to di vulge • whether he has actually been given any sort of mission by Bin Saud has yet to be proved, but his frequent references to the tt free hand** which the King has given him to compose certain differences with Kuwait, provided the results will benefit him (the King) financially, make one suspicious. On the other hand the worthy Khan Bahadur, who ostensibly, is very pro British, may have failed to obtain \ a good enough jjiob from the King in Saudiyeh, and had there fore decided to return to the home of his fathers to see whether he could make good by pushing A.P.0.0. interests as opposed to those of Major Holmes. He certainly en deavoured to enlist the sympathies of the A.P.O.C. on his arrival at Bahrain from Nejd, through their Agent Mr.Yusuf Kano,0.I«S.,M.B»E # , (Vide Bushire telegram 206,dated 27.3 # 55 # ) and outwardly appears very anti American and Major Holmes in particular. The above remarks are made in the form of a digres sion in view of what follows# (b) K.B.Abdul Latif, after two preliminary calls, at which no business was discussed, had a long interview, with me on E4th April 1933 and among other things made the following interesting statements connected with recent Oil events:- (1) Major Holmes ohly went to Jeddah to try and get an Oil Concession in regard to the Kuwait Neutral Zone - this he (Abdul Latif) had got to know privately through Mohamed Sulaiman , Bin Saud's Finance Minister. (2) Major Holmes was shrewd enough to know that if+ ou 1 ld , set Bln Saua to agree to glverf him the Neutral Zone, then the Shaikh of Kuwaits consent would, follow as a matter of course, for on } y t0 a:£ Press the wish to Shaikh theTlatter wou^^affSi®!^. 1118 aPPrOVa1 ' alld (3) Should (l) and (2) above happen, then Bin S^d would certainly follow up matters by urging the Shaikh of Kuwait to give the Kuwait oil con! to S A PO £ th « E ff ,tern ^ General Syndicate and not n f as it would be impossible to have one *™i-h 0 W^ ny ^ in the Kuwait Neutral Zone and another next door in Kuwait territory. Obviously both must go together. 7 (4) The Shaikh of Kuwaits journey into the Southern desert on 30 th Februaiy and 25th February accom- pann-ed by Major Holmes confidential Secretary was for the purpose of meeting the King or his son buad, the intention being to prepare the ground for the submission, by Holmes, of a draft proposal for a concession for the Neutral Zone. (See this Office Confidential Report No.44,dated b.3.3S.)to Bushire) I tlli ® visi1: Holmes received a telegram (18th March), from Bin Saud inviting him to Jeddah. (6) The Shaikh of Kuwait, who clearly at heart was anxious to give the concession both for Kuwait and the Neutral Zone to Holmes, himself originated the plan and suggested to Holmes that he should so for the Neutral Zone first, get Bin Saud on his side and then get the latter to press him (the ^ a -f' C&gt; rxT : ^ W8 ' i ?' t 9^S rant . tlle Kuwait concession to himself (Holmes) • The Shaikh believed that with Bin baud supporting him, he need not fear His Majes1y , s Government's subsequent annoyance, if he agreed to this form of pressure. (7) Only fear of His Majesty's Goremment, or moral suasion from Bin Saud would ever make the Shaikh grant the Kuwait Oil Concession to the a .P # 0.C # This being so H»M»S»Grovemment must either bring quick pressure to bear on the Shaikh to grant the concession the way they wanted it to go, or the A.P»0»C f must forestall Major Holmes in the Neutral Zone, get the concession for that piece or territory from Bin Saud and get the latter to bring pressure to bear on the Shaikh, where Kuwait was concerned# i' : i * ■ As the first proposal could probably be ruled out it was absolutely vital to the A.P.O.C. that they should, througji Longrigg in Jedda or other special representative (the latter for preference) go w all out n for a concession in the Neutral Zone without delay. (8) Lastly Bin Saud intended giving no answer at all to aity of the Jedda concession hunters till the end of May or early in June COMMENTS. In my opinion the above statements are worthy of Arab careful thought. They were put in typically/roundabout fashionfashion, but I am neTertheless inclined to agree with most of what the late Director of Customs told me. It is so obvious to the mere onlooker that the Shaikh^s interests lie in the direction of the British company that nothing but a belief that it will be to his advantage politically, if the Americans get into Kuwait could make him see things otherwise. This, I believe, is the crux of the whole business. One must not forget that the Shaikhs mind, as that of all Nejdis, works by devious and tortuous routes. II. ARRIVAL BA.CK OF MAJOR HOIMBS&gt; Major Holmes returned to Kuwait frcm. Jedda on 27th April 1923 (via Cairo and Imperial Airways). He called on the Agency on 22nd April 19^5 and among other points, mentioned the following facts (a) He had been Invited to Jeddah by Bin Saud. (This confirms my telegram No.58 of 23»3«33). /I S ■ ■&gt; (b) He had not attempted in any way to get an Oil concession out of Bin Saud for the whole or part of Sau , diyah, but was after something else, which he could not divulge to me. (Obviously the Kuwait Neutral Zone). (c) He had not seen the King, but only the Finance Minister Mohamed Ibn Sulaiman who appeared very grasping and did not impress. (d) He had only remained 3 days in Jeddah during whicb time he had submitted his official proposals, for the thing he wanted, in writing, and had addres sed these to the King direct. (e) He had met Longrigg, Twit eh ell, Hamilton, and Philby (and Mrs .Philby). The first he thought, would 'cut no ice with Bin Saud as he had definitely the wrong personality': (His Words). The second twotwo he already knew. Philby he was much impressed with, especially his talented wife. (f) He added that a Swiss and Italian were also at Jedda, both after *011*. (g) Prom ?liat he had gathered whilst at Jedda, Bin Saud intenied collectiDg all applicants* draft conces sions, and would study these at his leisure* Bin Saud would, however, decide nothing till the end of May# He certainly would not tell the various concession hunters this. (This confirms what K .B.Abdul Latif said to me). (h) He (Major Holmes) was sending his wife home frcm Kuwait by first available air mail (probably 4;th May) (This may presage an early departure on xiolmes's part also, ana rather suggests my belief that nothing will be settled till ttie cold weather sets In again). COMMENT. (a) Althougi Major Holmes is supposed to be 'persona non grata' with Bin Saud, it would be unwise to suppose that for this reason his chances of getting a concession for the Neutral Zone from the King were poor. The astute Bin Saud, who always takes the 'long view', might easily think it well worth his *hile to back Major Holmes in order to assert his influence over the Shaikh of Kuweit by forcing him to give Kuwait also to Major Holmes. To the Arab world thi- would mean that Kuwait was under his (Bin Baud's) pc^i ^.al control, much as Qatar is believed to be. Such a move would not necessarily be unpleasing to the Shaikh either, even though he might make some sacrifice financially, (b) Again, also it must not be forgotten that the Shaikh, early in March, asted Major Holmes to prepare a new j „ imder which 1200 square miles would draft 'twin* concession, under wm go to the British.^sq^rf 8°to Ihe Americans, thrVugh- 6 - /&gt; / f also throngti Major Holmes. (See my report No.58,dated 22.3• S3 to the Political Resident). Clearly the 400 square miles refereed to is the Neutral Zone. This seems to confirm the belief of K.B.Abdul Latif, that the Shaikh of Kuwait actually had in mind, and had deliverately planned that Bin Saud should bring pres sure on him to give Kuwait to the Eastern &amp; G-eneral Syndi cate and not to the A.P^O.C., believing that His Majesty's Government, who were always afraid of hurting Bin Saud T s feeling, would realize that the Shaikh was not to blame. No doubt he would arrange that Bin Saud should put the case clearly and firmly to His Majesty^ Oovemment, that as the Neutral Zone had gone to Holmes, it would be clearly against his (Bin Sauds) interests if Kuwait went^to anybody else. Holmes would then offer Kuwait to a ^British group and the Neutral Zone to the imeri cans. In reality tt would mean the Americans getting ooth. III # TTRrRTJNG-S OF THE PEOFLS OF KUWAIT. In the meantime the people of Kuwait and the other members of the family of A1 Subah, are angry with their Ruler for delaying so long orer this business. They all would like to see the A.P.O.C. get the ocnoession, but are powerless for reasons mentioned in my Confidential report No.35. dated 15.2.33. For ready reference I repeat below some of the observations which I made then. They still stand. srL=« '«■' &gt;» hi * Majesty's Government. (bl The Shaikh is playing a lone band, and takes no local advice at all, nor would ^ ° f o ^ 8 leadinsc mercbants or nobles be able to profe^ anj that nine tenths of them are in- advice, see ng ^ have not the deoted to him f 1 mio-ht not nlease. They think courage to say what migbt not pxease. that it is upto His Majesty's Government to doto do the advice giving. (o) None of tlie members of the Shailchly House take any hand in the Government of Kuwait State, and their counsel is not sought. (d) The Shaikh believes that it is not to his interest to have the A.P.O.C, in his country for 2 reasons: Firstly , because he thinks they do not in tend to work the concession, inspite of all the A.P.O.C. say (This is Holmes's propaganda obviously) Secondly ,be cause he thinks his independence might be threatened if he were to set up a concern backed by His Majesty's Government in his state. (Also obviously Holmes^ teaching). (e) The Shaikh would like to believe that as His Majesty^ Government made no stand, when faced with the ♦'fait accompli' of the Americans getting into Bahrain, it is not very likely that they will make much fuss if the same Americans get into Kuwait. He, nevertheless, is not sure on this point in view of the many strong hints which he has received from different quarters, and being some what of a moral coward, he is nervous. (f) Major Holmes undoubtedly preacBues that if the Americans got into Kuwait they would be a powerful asset, since the Shaikh could always play them off against His Majesty's Government with the result that he would gain fairer treatment from both IRAQ and Bin Saud. IV. I enclose a copy of a secret D.O. No.74,dated the 17th April 1935, which I recently sent to the Special Service Officer, Basrah. It may help to throw lign. on ! some more obscure points. i ■ I have the honour to be, I Sir, Your most obedient servant. Lt.TCoX., Political Agent, Kuwait Mr .Chisholm of the A.P.O.C. tola me last night that/that he proposed seeing the Shaikh to-day (87 # 4»33.) and was going to ask that he (the Shaikh) should give him a letter to Bin Saud to the effect that if he (the Shaikh) gave the Kuwait concession to the Anglo Persian Oil Company j he would also, as far as he was concerned, raise no objec tion to the A.P.O.C. taking out a concession for the Neutral Zone, and trusted that Bin Saud for his part agreed, also. This decision of Mr.Chisholm was come to before being aware of what I had written above• 0O0- YSS»/ Copy of secret demi official letter No.74, dated the 17th April 1933 from Lt.-Colonel H.R.P.Dickson, C.I.E., Political Ageat, Kvnrait to Flight Lieutenant E.Howes,M.C., Special Service Officer, Basrah. '►oOo— Thank you so mucla for your letter No«l/BS/34, am dated 20th March which I/most ashamed to say I never answered; (owing, believe me, to very heavy work) and again for your No»IX)/l4/lI5 of the 10th April just received. 2# As your first letter is somewhat out of date now I will not reply to it. 3. Reference your second letter - Your news entirely corresponds with what I was able to get here, though in view of later happenings I am now inclined to believe that Shaikh Ahmad and party met Bin Saud himself rather than his son Saud. 4. The fact that Mohamed Yatim (Holmes Confidential Jackal) accompanied Shaikh Ahmad on his 1st journey (2gth to gSrd February) and again on the second journey (25th to 27th February) was the most suspiciote part of the whole business. 5. If I am right, and the meeting with the King did take place, two things were certainly discussed: (a) Bin Sauds desperate need for money: (b) Oil questions. 6. Under (a) it is not beyond the bounds of possi- bility that Bin Saud asked for a loan and in return offered some relief from the blockade. If was discussed, also with the intention of getting money, the presence of Mohamed ^atim was significant. 7. The following later events, I think, did much to prove the correctness of my earlier suspioioas:- (al On 18th March Bin Saud wired to i-Io.aaes io come to J eddahat once if he wished to be a bidder for N#Jd Oil concessions;(b) Holmes, Lombardi (Standar OilBirector) and Mohamed Yatim flew to Cairo on 19tli March; (c) Holmes and Mohamed Yatim went to Jeddah about E4th Inarch, v /here they still are; (d) Abdul Latif bin Abdul Jalil recently re turned from Riath and told me that Bin Saud was absolutely determined to close the Nejd door to Kuwait, even tighter than it has hither to been closed and was about to set up a tt wire- less Tt at Haffar al Batin and strengthen his # frontier guards: The news was in the nature of a threat and intended for Shaikh Ahmad's con sumption. It points, I think, to the fact that Shaikh Ahmad refused to supply money to Bin Saud at the meeting referred to, unless the Blockade was declared entirely off, which made the King decide on showing still less mercy to Kuwait than heretofore. 8. You heard, no doubt, that last month Bin Saud got £10,000 (or Rs.10,000) out of the Shaikh of Qatar and has now asked the people of Hassa to pay a yea^s revenue in advance. ——oOo — P&gt;S. Salim al Muzaiyin went to Riath and back about the time you mention; he confirmed all points you mentione#32/1 and 66/5, Telegram X jrom Political Agent, Kuwait. To Political Resident, Busnire, 1^0.84. Repeated Secretary or State for the Colonies,London, Dated 30th April ( received lat May ) 1933. Colonial Office telegram No.3. Shaikh consulted Holmes yesterday on the latest offer of Anglo-Persian Oil Company. According to Shaikh, Holmes immediately made higher offer making condition which was agreed to that he be allowed to submit new draft concessions under which northern naif of Kuwait should go to British and southern half to Americans. Shaikh said that he was enquiring from Anglo-Persian Oil Company if they better Holmes* offer. added he was ntt in the slightest hurry to arrive at a settlement which inclines me to believe that he is now waiting to see what Bin Saud does. In my opinion Shaikh more than ever favourable to Holmes who, there is little doubt, went to Jedda to negotiate separate concession's) for Neutral Zone with the concurrence ^ and approval of the Shaikh. Bin Saud apparently has not decided anything yet but should (be^ I-/ fr-f succeed in his obi ect Ms chances of getting Kuwait concession will clearly be greatly increased. Shaikh mentioned that Holmes flies to London on 4th May to meet prominent American Oil Magnates arriving shortly. - POLITICAL -82/1 lelegram Political Besident, Bushire. Political Agent, Kuwait. Ho* 346• Dated the 2nd May 1935. J Please post paraphrased copy of your telegr of 50th ultimo,No.84. - Residenty^/l 5c 36/1, Teleg ram ^ - oin Secretary of State for the Colonies,London. To Political Resident, Busliire. -Mo. 4 . Repeated Political Agent, Kuwait. Dated 4th ( received 5th ) May 1933. H Q KPIDEFTI /X * Kuwait telegram No.84 to Bushire. Please instruct Dickson if Holmes has already submitted draft nev/ twin concessions, to endeavour to obtain copy from Shaikh before Fowle's arrival m Kuwait on llth lay. -Secretary of State f cr the Colonies - « • 4 9 • 9 Telegram X. From Political Resident, Bushire. To Political Agent, Kuwait, flo. 356. 3)ated 5th May 1933. M'' Colonial Office telegram of 4th May. Please take action accordingly. - HBSIDKNT.SECRET . POLITICAL AGENCY, No. 87. ^p) KUTSAIT. AH .H 4 b Dated the 3rd May 1953. From Lt•-Colonel H»H # P♦Dickson, I»A # , Political Agent, Kuwait; To The Hon*hie the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, B U S H I R E . IsV f Jk Sir, V V ' ' As ordered in your telegram No.346, dated 2nd ■v May 1933, I have the honour to forward, herewith, a copy of l— ' my telegram No.84 of 30th April, duly paraphrased. 2 # Regarding the last paragraph of this telegram - Holmes now tells me that he cannot get accommodationbn the / west-hound plane leaving Kuwait on the 4th May, so will have to go on that leaving on the 11th May. Should however, he fail to ge^seats then, he will go overland via Mosul and Istamboul. This information, I think, should be telegraphed to London, provided you see no objection. 3. The latest Oil developments, as reported in my telegram No.84, are interesting and I think clearly show that the Shaikh, by having been given the very free hand he has, is going further and further away from the direction in which His Majesty's Government would like him to go, for the simple reason that he interprets •enforced neutrality* on my part as weakness on the part of His Majesty's Govern— ment, with the natural result that he tends daily to get more and more under the control of Holmes and farther and k farther/away from my inf luenc © • 4 0 This state of affairs is unfortunate, but so long as my hands are tied in the 'way they are, and I am also de prived of weapons with which to figjit imerican intrigue (I refer to the failure to settle the Kuwait blockade, the question of taxation of the Shaikh^ date gardens, and the Faddaghiyeh Case) , I see no great hope of the Shaikh being persuaded to look with greater favour on the A«P»0 # C., than he is at present doing* The contrary indeed, is the more likely contingency* 5. I have had occasion to mention before, that we are to-day dealing with a weak and as often follows, very obstinate individual in the Shaikh of Kuwait, who though I outwardly charming and pleasant, has all the steady cunning of the Nejdi; while on the other side of the picture the man who has got so much influence over him to—day, namely Major Holmes, Is a person of strong character and most convincing personality. 6* There is little doubt in my mind that the shaikh has been taught to believ-e(by Major Holmes) over a period of several years now, that 1 (a) His Majesty's Government cannot be entirely relied upon to fight his battles for him. (b) That His Majesty*s Government have let him down in the past, and will let him down in the future, because expediency largely governs policy to-day; (c) That American influence in Kuwait (as represented by an American concern backed by the United States of America) will insure him a new born independence with greater security from the attacks and bullying tactics of Bin Saud and IRAQ; {d) That the A .P.O.C. with its British Government connection, will always be a dangerous company to have in his country. c 7. It remains to see what will be the outcome 3./outcome of Holmes's latest move. I personally tliink that some time ago he was given carte blanche by his American backers to 'top' any offer made by the A.P.O.CU and that in the present case he has f off his own bat* offered a quarter of a million rupees; and wants now# to ^o to London to get his offer ratified^ 8# The Shaikh adroitly avoided giving me the figure offered by Holmes when I asked him what it was - a minor point perhaps, but one showing that he tries these days to keep me in the dark as far as possible, where Oil negotiations are concerned: one sees the hand of Holmes in this# I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Lt.-Colonel, Political Agent, Kuwait♦ 7SS.Telegram (Paraphrase). From Political, Kuwaiti To !• Secretary of State for Colonies, London S# Resident, Bushire. No* 84. Dated the 30th April 1935» Addressed to Resident No*84 repeated to Secretary of State for Colonies, reference Qolonia dffice telegram yesterday on latest offer of A # P # 0^C» Shaikh told me afterwards that Holmes at once made a higher offer than that of his riveils, making one condition only, which he (the Shaikh) had agreed to, namely that he (Holmes) be sill owed to submit a new draft concession under which the Norfchera half of Kuwait state should go to a British group the Southern half to an American ditto* Shaikh added that he was that day enquiring by letter from Mr.Chisholm of the A.P*0.C«, if his Company would better Holmes's offer. He emphasised that he was now in no hurry at all to arrive at a settlement, which now inclines me to believe that he will wait to see T&amp;hat Bin Saud does at In my opinion Shaikh more than ever favourable to Holmes, who, it is now practically certain, went to Jedda recently to negotiate separate oil concession fo^ Kuwait Neutral Zone, with the full coiourrence and approval of Shaikh. Bin Saud as far as I know has not decided any- thing as yet, but should Holmes succeed In his object, his chances of getting Kuwait concession will clearly be His Excellency the Shaikh had a talk with Holmes Jedd^be greatly increased. Shaikh mentioned that Holmes was to fly to London on 4th May to meet a prominent American Oil Magnate who was shortly in England. i i oOo- I; fi'(I nnNFI DENTIAL. POLITICAL AG3NCY, No. 93 • KUWAIT. i '■ / a (ye Bated the 9th May 1933. Cif ^ From Lt.-Colonel H.R.P.Dickson, C.I.E., I.A., i' Politi oal Agent, Kuwait; / 1/ \ The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, B U S H I R E . Oil Interests. Sir, With reference to Colonial Office telegram No.4 dated the 4th May and your telegram No.355, dated the 5th May 1933, instructing me to take action on same, I have the honour to inform you that I called on His Sxcellency the Shaikh on the 6th May and asked him verbally if he could let me have a copy of the new draft ^twin' concession (i to British and i to Americans), if such had been prepared by Major Holmes. His Excellency replied that Holmes had not yet prepared a draft copy, and probably would not do so, until after he returned to England (now fixed for 11th Lay). 3. His Excellency further pointed out that Holmes could not have had time to prepare such draft, and that so long as both the Eastern &amp; General Syndicate and the A.P.O.G. were bidding against each other, it was not reasonable to expect either side to submit a new draft, each time they put a fresh bid forward: This part of the negotiations must of necessity be done verbally. 4. His Excellency added that once the last bid had/ ill h - 2 - had been made, and hie (The Shaikh) had decided to which company to give the concession, then would be the time for him to order a draft to be prepared. This when completed he would submit to His Majesty^ Government, for their approval, or for them to make any ad ditions or alterations they might desire to make. After receiving back this final draft from His Majesty's Government, he would proceed to grant the formal concession under final fair copy. 5 # The Shaikh spoie somewhat excitedly during the above conversation and appeared to me to be anxious to con vey that impression that we should let him alone in the preliminary details of trying to get the Eastern 8c General Syndicate A.P.O.C. to bid against each other. 6. At the same time I am still of the opinion, as expressed in paragraph 7 of my despatch No.87, dated the 3rd May, that Holmes either offered the Shaikh a quarter of a million rupees on his own responsibility, having found out what his rivals had offered, or told the ShaiKh that he was prepared to top the A.P.O.C# offer by Rs.50,000/— straight away, but required time to fly home to get his offer officially ratified by his principals,the Americans. He clearly did not dare to make a n firm offer' in writing. The Shaikh knew this and being favourable to Holmes, expres* sed his willingness to let the matter stand at that. He immediately wrote to the local representative of the A.P # O.C. saying that their offer had been beaten, and asked if they bad anything further to say. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, T Lt.-Colonel, Polit leal Agent, Kuwait VSS.Telegram I.F.O. Fxcm Resident. To Secretary of State for India, Lordon. No. T -l. Dated the 15th l ay 1933. A.P.0,0. inform me that Shaikh of Kuwait has intimated to them that he has decided to suspend negotiations far Oil Concession for the time being, and will let both parties know when he is ready to resume them. ; ost copy to ^ov errmient of India. - HESI DEI-IT- oOo- j (?-£■ ft t&gt;i Ar /C4H) ^ SI ANGLO PERSIAN OIL GOMMY LIMITED, KIBYAIT^ Dated the 14th May 1933• j BUSHiRF F? ; : ^iDSNCY To - - ^ i j A h The Political Agent, l^'&gt; r —— - * - - ._ ,j Kuwait ♦ Sir, We have the honour to transmit to you, herewith, a copy of our letter dated 14th instant to His Excellency the Shaikh of Kuwait. We have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servants, Sd»A#H.T»Chisholm, FOR ANGLO PERSIAN OIL CO.LTD♦ oOo——-D iNGLO PERSIAN OIL CCMPANY LIMITED, KUWAIT. Dated the 14t}i May 1935. CDNFIDSNTIAL. His Exoellency Sir Aimed Aljabir Alsabah, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., RUL3R Qg KUWAIT. Your Excellency, ?/e beg to acknowledge with thanks Your Excellency^ letter No»R/958 dated the 89th April 1953 addressed to our Representative Mr^Chisholm, in reply to which, we now have the honour to confirm our caiversation with Your Excellency this morning regarding the decision of Your Excellency to suspend all negotiations concerning an Oil Con cession in Kuwait Territory for the time being and until further notification is received from Your Excellency. We note that Your Excellency has already communicated the same de cision to Major Holmes, the Representative of the Eastern &amp; General Syndicate,also# We are most grateful for the expression of Your Excellency s views with which we were honoured at our interview with Your Excellency to-day and we will now await the further noti fication referred to above in accordance with Your Excellency's wishes. We are addressing copies of this letter to the Political Agent, Kuwait/Kuwait and to Sir John Gadman as agreed with Your Excellency^ We beg to remain, your Excellency's obedient servants. Sd. S.H.O.Slkington, GENERAL MANAGER, FOR ANGLO PERSIAN OIL CO • LTD.COLONIAL OFFICE, DOWNING STREET, 29th April, 1933. ''Cf* DENCV. 1 GDNROEVtMl itiious Dear ColoneL, i enclose a provisional record of the meeting held last Wednesday regarding oil matters in the Persian Gulf. I should be grateful if you would let me know what amendments you would like to suggest. CVv h^cww5: ^ ain siting similarly to Rendel, LaithwaitE Starling, and Moore. Yours sincerely, TENANT-COLONEL T.C. FO'CLE, C.B.E.Siiould 'b© gi-7en. It ^fouxd cbvlouely 'oe desira'ble to select a moment -when two offers were In the tield of •wjaich the -Uiglo -Per elan waa definitely the better onee But 'by s el eating any suoh moment to give the SteiMi advice or to suggest to him that he B&amp;crald. ask tor it ? we mlflit eaBilj be mouued hy the Merioanis of hsTlng, as it were, brought down the hammer prematurely, siaoe the i ^aerioane would no doubt contend that they vroyxl d have 'been ready to go one better than the &gt;vnglo &amp;, rer8A^n offer had they been given more time® Moreover 9 ix ! -he Shaikh aooepted our adTlee and decided against, the Morlcnns, be would no doutst, in informing liajor Holmes (who would inform the Americans) of his deoislon, %sy U father tbe rssp'onaiTsility for the Seats Ion -in His 1 QoTemment so that some kind of protest from th-s Amsrioans would prot&gt;ably 00 ».tui»ifca'»).»®« 6. Mr. Park in eon mi lasted that a copy &lt;sx oar letter to the Shaikh should ha oOTBWnioa'o^d co -'ttcd States GoTsrnmsnt. The letter would set out xn oj.sar terms vfay the British offer was thought so b=. «.&gt;- better, and would advise the ShaiKh. in the intereste of his Principality, to acoept ite , tnis mi ©it be done, and ? c Mr a RendeX agreed aio.v k *.*,- said that tho Foretgn Gi'fioe had it might oTsntually adTisahle if not to puhli^.^ ot&lt;»s (loTernment An^e the any rate to let the Jn^en offtolal oorreepondeaoe on ttize a*#* t ' 8- StHUSfi ^ reSB9d 00,86 ^ ^ „ prve useful purpose. such b eouree would n . to estimated from the ^he 'mlue of a oonoees ^on J ^financial point of Tiew, and .he technical as well as t^v. - ^ no difficulty in imrolTing Mericana would prohahly - J --I 0 % His Majesty^s Government in teohni . van^e^i. arguments as to the respective merit a of the ri^al offers. He pointed out that the Petroleum Department had already examined eonorote proposals put forward hy -jbe two oonpetlng Oompaaies, and had found taa;t., on V:alaj;( «, the British proposaie offered the greater adTantages in the Shaikh. U£zJ^*tMk tha ¥iew that this was not a matter wnxch ooiXXc u km to srMtratlon, or made the supj^ct oa legal pyooecHi . 'gBo All tJia-t could 'b® r© qui red of us was Lciat our actio,: (aould he justifiable on gener&amp;l grounds o*. equity, and i- : nild ''oe wltCtiln the framework of our pledge . In other wci e, if our adviee to the Shaikh were given 'bona fide on • is merits of the propo s&amp;X8 put to him, and if we oould pu ; ; If neeeaoary f a reasonable defence to ©how that :a I i ct Ttolated our pledge^ it would probably net foe ae 'j us-wy to take aay protests w© might receive from the- r : iltsd k : tate^ Government too ' seriously- 10. Capta in i icore : d ' H*X t.ie Admiralty felt that, so long as cur advise 5^' ^ n &lt; 1 ? ^iven on tlae merits of the oaBe. all Xeoitlm r; pre?irir • on the Shai &amp;h might 'be used. 11c a is 'brought up %:\ » question of wSien the limit of the present bargain!n. s lilce'lr ' ® reaohed. Li euteaant ^ Pol one! Fowl e : jested A iftt ^he limit would 'be with the purse o of th rivals*- «&gt;., SS4^ watered a oaveat that to adopt any ■ particular i m^t i&lt;or yenduring definite advioe to the Sh^mi one war or the other mig^t 'be represented as a viol i.t.ion of our pledge. 12. In the course of the disouesion it merged tha'- the ShaiKh raioJit possibly be waiting &gt;»a eTents In Persia in connection with the Anglo-Psrsian Oil dispute before comingcoming to a deolsrion* in reply tiQ a que at Ion as to the latest information regarding pooame sharing arrangemmits between the ^gla-Persicm Oil Comply and tihe Mellon Group f Li'said that, so far as he kxim, Vxv mi'r^-'ylon wau that, if the Anglo-Persian Oil Company t . ccm seaion, ^an arrangement would be made for the fCmrin^ of ylie marketing and dietrIbuting side of the conaexn on i fifty fifty 'basis« Ilr c Starling; said tnat t.ai g ^ith his information and he had also l&amp;ean informed 'by Sir John Cadman that the An$La~ Persian Oil Company were determined, if possible, to seour e the e ane © a s: on» 14 c cute-na'^; :v qioa gl , ^gwi© suggested that it would faoilitate !•: -la^ssion of the question if we knew what -were u-ajcx Ho.linf;? 4 re«actions to the latest Anglo-Par83an offer• Major Holmes had now returned to Kuwa^'' ono t&gt; - r:n%l :-■. would certainly hy now have consulted i-dr-i regardlrig the offer© He therefore thouglrl that the ^olitioal /-..^ent might he instructed to approach the ShaiKr- and '\so r ;rtr!in the present position© T Sh^ meeting concurred ).b this suggestion, and ths terms of. a tele grass to the Acting Hesident In tne Per&amp;i.an Gair were agreed© A copy of this telegram as it issued is attached tc t.Ms r.-cord, and it- ''as arranged a further meet In should he held on uie ^ra which the position oouXa he further considered in the liglit of any information received in the meantime from Acting Henident© 15. . wo cthsr watt we bearing on *** oil » 0SitiiOn in Kuwait were discussed, nassely» ra fa) ii I m1 ll&gt; OIL . ■ Mlo.r llQlmsB* rssidenoe in Bahrein, Mr. Laithwaite attention to Gandition C of the Agreement of the 12th of June I93O, and to Major Holtfi -ea 1 failure to conform with the terms of that Condition- The question had been the auh.lect of ocrrespon^snce with Mr, Ballantyne end the Polltioal Resident in the Persian Gulf. Ur* Laithwaite asid that, in the li^ht of discussion with Colonel ^owle^ he thought it was for consideration whether the time had not oome when His Majesty*a Government should take notice of Major Holmes' activities and consider whether some action should not he taken in the matter. He appeared to he the representative in the Gulf not only of the Bahrein Petroleum Company,, but of the Eastern and General Syndicate ? end to spend much of his time a./aj 7 from Bahrein conducting negotiations for concessions in other parts of the Gulf- Sveryhody, he thought, ma agreed tha^j the woriing of Condition C made it clear that Major Holmes ought to spend if not the whole any rate the hulls of the year, say ten months^ in Bahrein s aid while it ml^ht be said that he had not au present bean absent from Bahrein at any time v/hsn he ^as needed^ an instance had just occurred m which Ma^or Holmes haS approaohad the Political Agent in regard to an extaision q S the Company's prospeotins liosnce, ana, having aelcoa for a reply wittin a oertain period, had gone oft elsewhere without leaTing any addreas* -n a further point the sotins Political Resident had juat informed.. '-■ 4 L -MJSS , IU oontreventlcn of tha t efm , of , h , agre , a . ntj ^ in oorrespcndenoo ntb th. .''inanalal .VdTiaer, jahr^ir, In r8 L ;. !.ii t.. the jiahrein oonceaeloa. Ttoja. though possibly aaoh infornsx oorreaponfleno* had taken plaae in tihe past, was in fast a breaah of the agreatwnt, whloh fflafia it clear that all eowwmloatlonfl between the British Hesiflent c*n6 the Sh&amp;ikhaiust pass through the Political authorities. Ks act thiu.k: that Major Holmes was re^ardea^ either by the looal British author!ties in uhe xerCs-uXf^ or Dy the Dspsrtinents oonoerned in London, as a particularly satlafaotory indiTidual, He was under tL«j impress ion, too . that the Colonial Cfcfifio® had had reason to h^lieTe that Kajor Holmes was not entirely persona ^rata to the Amarioan Syndloate. He therefore su^g^st&amp;d that Mr P Ballantyne might be told that Mjcr Holmes 8 aotiTlties were not regarded frith favour hy His Majesty^ Groyemmentj that it was essential that a representative of the Jompany should be oontinually resident in Bahrein and that a surest!on might be made to Mr. Ballantyn© that another representatiTe shuuld be appointed in his place* 17. Lieutenant--Colonel i'owle said that he thought that either the Manager of the Bastern Bank, or of the Mesopotamia-Per si a Corporation would probably mQlre quite a satisfaotory looal represe .ntatiTe of the Companyc Both these persons were British subjects, 18. Mr. Blester pointed out that at the time that the Agreement of the 12th of June, 195^» Tir:AS u ^ a dlsaussion with the Company, Hajor Holmes was looked uponupon ^'ith f&amp;vour, and hia appointment as the first local repreaentetive of the Company was, in faot^ mde at the instance of His Majesty^ aovarnment^ The position had, of course, ohangedl, hut it would bare to be remembered in dealing with Mr, Ballantyne that it was His Majesty's Soyernment, and not the Company, who wanted Major Holmes appointed. -*■ ^i n on saxft o.Aat xt would he necessary to explain to Mir*» Ballantyne that his interpretation of Condition C was not accepted » l*e» it was not a one-sided arrangement as Mr* Ballantyne suggested^ nor was it a sufficient answer that Major Holmes had Ijeen available (if this w^re the case) ?/heneYer the Bahrein authorities had happened to want him there.- In view of Major Holmes' aotivities during the last three years s and in particular his long absences from Bahrein, it might he desirable to raise at the same time the question of getting him replaced by some other more suitable person 9 But before deaiding upon suoh action s Mr.,. Parkinson said that he thought the Golonial Office should get out a clear statement of the facts as to Major Holmes' appointment etc. Hr. a Laithwaite said that the India Office would be glad to assist in drawing up a statement, Nationality Companyjs Bmnloyees in Bahreiru 20. fhe Political Resident's confidential Seepatoh, Bo.21 of the 218 1 of March, ?^aa discussed, and it was agreed that up to the present thex^e had aeen no grounds11 a grounfls on which it could reasonably be prssseathat an- fe' oonsiderabl© number of the Company» e employee should De British subjects or British protected parsons. }^ p hov^eTer, pointed out that more Srilllp-f worlc was likely to b© unSertak^n .'frois now onwards that there ware araliable at present Quite a number of expert drillers who were British suhjeots 9 and who were seeking employment. He undertook to let. the Colonial Ofj.io© haT@ aOifie details on t^iis matter p in order that the Company might be approached and urged to .^ire employment to some of these people, as their work ej:tan3© and called for additional staff. Amendments to the Third SphedulQ (Mi ning ' LeasTTof''tih?^ Tq25 Conceaaio n.. Officiating Political Resident's Confidentia l lie spat o hT So 726 of the'/1 h of Apr i 1 , 21, Lieutenant -Qolonel Fowle obserTed that when the time came to make amendments in the third schedule or to allov? an increase in the area ever whlo 'i the Company desires to seoure mining rights, there were a number of points of importance which would need coneideration^ 22 ' Starling said that the Petroleum Department had dr^wn attention to a number of these points in their letter of the 25rd of December, 193 1 - ii 23. Ga^taia Moor e observed that the Admiralty were anxious that proTision should be made giving the Shaifeh the right of pre-emption in emergencies, and requiring that a proportion of the oil should be refined&gt;v&gt; refined in idahrein, or in British territory; also the Admiralty were anxious that the position of the naral bass at Bahrein, if auoh a base ware to he oonatruotad should be safa-guardeao 24 - Captain Moore undertook to haT© a latter 8®nt to the Colonial Office on the last-mentioned point, and Mr. Starling said that he would arrange that th® mamoraMum already being draftea in Petroleum Department shouxfl cover ell points which needed oonsideration. 25. It was aeoidea that the position should be further aisousse^ in the light of the oosagjunioationa promised 'by the Admiralty end -the ?str j I ouip ^aparti^.ent ^ if reoeiYe^, in tiaae^ at the meeting arranged for the 3rd of may. 1118 OH IH QATAR c 26. The Yiews expressed in India Office letter ini to the Colonial Office of the 1st of Deaeuteer„ 1932% 1 CJL.' Niere discussed fl an^ it was agreed that formal approTal should be given to the agreement reached l3at?/een the I m- 02 shaikh and the Anglo •Persian Oil Company ^ It was also agreed that the Political Keaident should be informed that it would b.e anneoessary to a raw the Shaikh ? s attention to Articles 7, 8 and Q of the treaty of 1QX6. It was hovireTer pointed out that the Petroleum Bepartieent had not yet mac!e their comments on the Political Resident's despatch, Ho^59 ^ Ssptetsher, 1932, and Mr. Starling undertook that the ^©troleum Department's ohserrations should 'be sent to the Colonial Office officially at an early date. On receipt! I' ' ib^ r«o»ipt of th®M, &amp; reply to the despatch woula be flrafted in the Colonial Office, ana oiroulatsa for oorionrrenoe. IT. OIL IB 11-3. OI KjV.AIT? ZOHB. 27. Tba oonoessloas mad@ to th@ Eastern ana OtoeraX Syndicate in 1923 and 1224 were mentionea, Kr. fturfclnson tiuit tlie position was not fer.y olaar # bat all the rights whiah the syndloata iiafi in these areaa had been transferred to the Eastern Gulf Oil Conpony for a nooinal sua. It appeared that, in faot, the oonoesaions must liave lapsed, and there was a 0onxllot of b tatewent as to the actual grant of the Kuwait Keutral 'one oonoession. It was understoocl that the present negotiations going on in Jed5a, in which various Interest* were oonoerned and in whioh^pparently Major HqIms hbs tafclnj a p^t, re3-ateS to the Hasa area* ,|.v%c PETROLEUM DEPARTMENT victoria 9310. ^ndvst, PARt, L ondon. ■ N o.i- P.D. parl , L ondon. (Mines Department), Dean Stanley Street. Millbank, xi if\ i' ^Westminster, London, S.W.I. Dear Colonel powle, As promised, I send you herewith a copy of a note of our recent talk to which is attached a short memorandum on the present position, according to our information, in regard to Oil Concessions in Arabia and the Persian Gulf. In the latter aocument I have dealt with the question of the Iraq, petroleum Company Group Agreement. Yours sincerely. '•■Col. T. C. W. Fowle. C.B.E 'Ua Office. UtehBU, s.'w. 1,: .:eLio rr ^idun f or Colonel Fov/le. Oil Concessions in Arable r^-i d the Persian Gul f. The position in Arabia and the Persian Gulf Area., so far as the information in the possession of the petroleum Department goes is as follows (1) Kowait. The Anglo-Per si an Oil Company and the Eastern and General Syndicate (representing the Gulf Oil Corporation of America) hrve 'both applied for a concession, and are engaged in submitting rival offers to the Sheildi viio still has the matter under consider^ tio:- (2) Hasa. On May 6th, 1923, the Sultan of Nejd, AMul Bin Saud, granted an oil concession covering the Province of Hasa (including the .;,atif and Jubail rreas; to the Eastern and General Syndicate, - : informs ti on is available as to -he the r this has lapsed, hut in vie v. oi the length of time T/hich h s expired it appears prooaole that it has done so, according to f telegram .Tom Sir A. Ryan (jedda) of March 22nd, 1935, negotiations for an oil concession in Hasa have oecn i- 1 ocee ^i ^o oetwe (1) The Standard Oil of California, and (2) The Iraq. Petroleum Company, represented cy Lon. rig '..iA ^uc .e^ris Major Holmes has also recently visited je^-da cat not clear on whose account he is , &lt;■ ci: i^^ thi (3) T.euti-al Zone (South of Koweit). Onjfey 17th, 1924, an oil concession was granted jointly hy Ton baud and the Sheikh of Koweit to the Eastern and The present position in regard to an oil cu-co.-io^ mi vnotpr- and General Syndicate, this area is not known. T he Ea.-. uer.- -i 1 Q97 transferred any 'by an agreement of 20th r.oveinD ■ , 5 eights which it might possess or accmire o_ A/ni - ^e reinstated in Hasa or the Keutral .uo^e, or • v+ op mire in Koweit to the Eastern concession which it might st .c. . ^ j Gulf Oil Company.(4) Bahrein. Concession secured 'by Bahrein Petroleum Company (Standard Oil Company of California) and oil met with in trial iDoringSo (5) Q.atr. The Anglo-Persian Oil Company acting as far as the petroleum Department were aware at the time on their own 'behalf, recently secured an exclusive option from the Sheikh to carry out geological investigations for a period of 2 years. Any concession which they may secure will for the reasons mentioned below probably have to be on behalf of the Iraq. Petroleum Company. (6) Muscat . The Anglo -Persian Oil Company obtained a concession in 19^5 to prospect .-or oil for a period of two years with the right to a mining lease, but this concession has now lapsed. i 7 ) MoKalla. The Anglo -Saxon Petroleum Company started negotiations for a concession in — - * 0 ^ the matter was not proceeded with as they lec -ehed the conclusion that the prospects of discover i^o je uro..cum were quite unfavourable. (8) Jedda. (Hejaz, West Coast of Arabia,) Two American engineers (Twitchell oraneh, /e re- y , . . • _ _ onri the Petroleum Department carried out investigations, cdu- tnc 4-* -fVip Ansrlo ''Pe r si an brought the matter to the notice o- Oil Company. It is regarded as important that every endeavour should be made to enable Britisn inceicbto themselves in the Persian Gulf Area. Lhu complicated by the fact that t he Anglo -P ersia v n.r &gt;)pqt suited to undertake Company who are ge o graphic all j 1 ^ i , t I tt wr luded from operating development worx, are virtuaJ • the Iraq petroleum in this area excerpt as a nomi^ -^(no) Company. The same remarks ap ly to the Shell. The circumstances which hsve led up to this position are as follows: Pos ition of the Iran Petroleum Company . The Turkish Pet rol emu Company (now the Iraq Petroleum Company) was formed i n 1912 when the Deutsche Bank became associated with the National Bank of Turkey and the Anglo -Saxon Petroleum Company (Royal Dutch-Shell group) in order to press certain claims to oil rights in Baghdad and Mosul, including those attached to the Baghdad Railway Concession. The chief rival of the new Company at that time was the Anglo-Persian Oil Company which had for some time 'been in negotiation with the Turkish Government. In 1914 an Agreement was entered into providing for trie reconsti tution of the Turkish i -etroleum Company, . l rom which the National Bank of Turkey withdrew, tne nev participants 'being the Anglo-Persian Oil Company, - jO / j , the Anglo-Saxon Petroleum Company and the Deutsche Bank 25$ each. This Agreement also provided that the three groups should give undertakings not to oe interested directly or indirectly in the production of oil in the Ottoman Empire in Europe and Asia except in i--gypt, Kov.ei t or the Transferred Territories, except through the Turkish Petroleum Company. This Agreement was signed by tne ^ritish and German Governmeiits, and by the groups co-ucer the Turkish Petroleum Company was theu predominantly British, this arrangement had the effect o^ oecurin^ whole of this area to interests which were predominantly British. After the entry of American and trench intereot into the Iraq. Petroleum Company after the wf.r, the arrangement as regards non -competition between the groups-4- composing the Iraq Petroleum Company was continued in an agreement between the groups,, entered into in 1928. This was a private agreement between the groups with which the British Government was not concerned. Under this Agreement a line was drawn round Arabia, Palestine and Asia Minor, which excluded Koweit and the Pars an Islands, but included Bahrein and which defined an area within which the various groups constituting the Iraq Petroleum Company agreed that they would not seek for or obtain oil concessions otherwise than through the Iraq Petroleum Company or its nominee. The position as regards the distribution of capital in the Iraq Petroleum Company is as follows: i Anglo-Persian Oil Co. Royal Dutch Shell French Group American Group C. S. Gulbenkian 23.75/13 23.75'&gt;o 23.75/0 23.75 l /o 5.00 100.00 In 1932 the American Shareholding in the Americen group was held in the following proportions: L y of New Jersey 41 ^ fo 2 Standard Oil Comijany Gulf Oil Corporation of Pennsylvania Standard Oil Company of New York 41 4 % 16% % As the Royal Dutch Shell is 60% Dutch and 40$i British, the British shareholding in the Iraq Petroleum Company now only represents shout SZ^i.The Irag Petroleum Company -is tecluiically a British Company, as in Article &gt;-2 o Convention with the Government of Iraq, the ^omp i.y De and remain a British Company, registered in Great Britain, and the Chairman must he at all times a British suojcet. One question which arises is whether H.M. Government can he expected to afford the same measure of support Inaq Petroleum Company as it could in the old days when itwas a British Company in fact as well as in name. As the American oil interests have large groups outside the Iraq, petroleum Company as well as inside they are at an advantage and it may 'be necessary to support the Iraq petroleum Company as against a purely American concern. This does not hov/ever affect Koweit as it is excluded from the 1928 Agreement and it only makes it all the more important to see that the Anglo-Persian Oil Company secure the Koweit concession. Petroleum Department. 1st May, 1933. /y^T DENTlAL, r Note on interview 'between Colonel powle, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, and Mr. Starling, Director of the petroleum Department. \ 1 a on Colonel powle called at the Petroleum Department 19th April 5 1933. Mr. Giffard was present during the later part of the interview. Colonel powle informed Mr. Starling that he had seen the sheikh on the way over. He had unfortunately missed meeting Sir John cadman, 'but he learned full details of the discussion which sir John had had with the sheikh from Mr. Elkington, the General Manager in Persia of the Anglo -Persian Oil Company, and the Sheikh had also informed him of what had transpired. On the whole he felt rather happier ahout the situation. After making a very good offer to the Sheikh, Sir John Cadman had suggested that the Sheikh should now agree to give the Anglo-persian Oil Company the concession. The sheikh had x-eplied, however, that he was unahle to reach any decision until he had disciiosed matters again with 2/ajor Holmes. Colonel powle ^.a^d h Buggested to the Sheikh that when he had reached the stage of wishing to reach a decision he should, without informing the parties, submit the latest drafts of the concessions to H .M. Government for their advice, finally made up his mind. The Sheikh said he would this. ^ v&gt;Tr sheikh had shown buch a Mr. Starling inquired why the nolonel powle replied leaning in favour of Major Holm • that it was partly 'because the Sheikh had a pers for Major Holmes, and partly because he helieve n rnaicQ the Sheikh a K a jor Holmes may have promised ^ r.nt HDDear in the Agreement. substantial payment which wou JHe also believed that Major Holines had. represented to the Sheikh that it would 'be to his advantage in his dealings with H«Government il American influence v/ere brought into Kuwait. Colonel powle had done what he could to impress on the Sheikh that it was in his interests to look to the British Government, but in view of the attitude H.M. Government had taken over the question of the oil concession he thought the sheikh felt that H.M. Government would have no serious ground for complaint if he were to give the concession to the Eastern and General Syndicate. Colonel powle said that he had no doubt that if H.M. Government addressed a letter to the sheik instructing him to grant the concession to the Anglo-persian Oil Company, he would comply with such a request, but it would be impracticable to send such a letter without it also being communicated to Major Holmes. There would, he suggested, be nothing to prevent H .M. Government from telling the Sheikh that in their view the offer sutmitted by the Anglo -Persian Oil company was tetter, if we were satisfied that this was the case. Mr. Starling referred to the proposal which had been mentioned in a recent despatch that the country should be divided between the Eastern and General syndicate the Anglo-Persian Oil Company, the former getting about 400 square miles and the latter about 1,800 square Colonel Powle said he thought Major Holmes was responsible for this suggestion and it might be a move intended to leave the Eastern and General syndicate a bargaining counter in the event of the Anglo-Persian Oil Company heing given the major part of the country. Mr. Starling said he thought it would be useful to get particulars-3- 175 areas which were in contemplation. Colonel Powle said that an effort had been made to get details of the proposal. The Sheikh had agreed that Major Holmes might be approached but Holmes had so far declined to give particulars. Colonel powle said he would make anotner effort. in reply to a further question as to the possibility of establishing a refinery in Kuwait if oil were found,. Colonel powle said that at present there was no satisfactory water supply available and water was brought by barge from Iraq.. He also mentioned that a few years ago the area of Kuwait had been reduced, which was another grievance of the Sheikh. A neutral zone between Kuwait and Hasa had 'been established over which the sheikh and Jbn Saud had joint rights. In a general discussion on other areas in the Persian Gulf, Mr. Starling said that some anxiety was felt at the persistent activities of American oil interests. Prom a British point of view the situation was complicated by the fact that the principal British company, the Anglo-persian Oil Company., was prevented from securing concessions in these Gulf areas, apart from Kuwait, because they were parties to an agreement among the groups in the Iraq petroleum Company which was designed to prevent competition between these groups. Colonel lowle asked that he might, for his own information, be furnished with a note of the position and Mr. Starling undertook to suppiy this. Colonel powle explained that, as political Resid 5 he was not concerned with Hasa, which formed pai Von Saud* s territory and was dealt with by Sir A. Ryan Jedda. He was, however, responsible for Kuwait anthe remainder oi 'the Arabion Coast (including Qatar). from Qatar round to Dhofar in the South. As regards Bahrein, Colonel Powle said that the Bahrein petroleum Company had drilled two successful oil wells, and a third well was in course of drilling. There were ample supplies of v/ater on Bahrein Island which was obtained from artesian wells, although already there was thought to 'be some danger of these supplies heing depleted as a result of waste. He haa learnt confidentially from Holmes that the American interests concerned might wish to dispose of their rights in Bahrein Island as they apparently foresaw some difficulty in finding a market for the oil. As, however, oil had now been proved, they would 'be likely to demand a high price. Colonel Fowle mentioned that the Eastern and General Syndicate had displayed some interest in the Farsan Islands in the Red Sea, some years ago, however, the shell Company had paid £10,000 in cash for the oil rights and had spent a good deal of money in test drilling, without result. The Parsan Islands now came under the jurisdiction of I'bn Saud, After some further general discussion had taken place, Mr. Starling said that he had been very pleased to have had the opportunity of meeting colonel powle. It would be necessary to defer, until the meeting to be held with the other Government Departments concerned on &lt;;6th April, the further discussion of the attitude to be adopted y H,M. Government towards the Sheikh of Kuwait, Before leaving. Colonel powle was introduced Sir Alfred Faulkner, Under secretary for Mines, who said that after the Inter -departmental meetings had conclud he would hope to have another opportunity oi seeing Colonel powle.flfMFIDSK'ITAL, No. 104. / &gt; From %y\ / ***% ■ in nt POLITICAL AGENCY, KUWAIT. Dated the 20th May 1933. To i*M. ' / '/to Lt•-Colonel H.R.P.Dickson, C .I .E., I. A., Political Agent, Kuwait^ The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian G-ulf, B U S H I R B . Suspension of Oil Negotiations i n Kuwait. Sir, I have the honour to forward, for your inform- at ion, and that of His Majesty's Government, copies of the following correspondence, {English only):- (a) Letter No.Nil, dated the 14th May 1933 from Mr.E.H .O.ISlkington, General Manager, A.P.O.C., Ltd., Abadan, to His Scoellenoy the Shaikh; (b) Confidential letter Ko.99, dated ^ e H l® th May 1933 from Political Agent, _aiwai Excellency the Shaikh; (c) Translatioji or ^'h S ' Kuwait® 2. ffrom (c) above you will note that the Shaikh confirms that he has suspended all negotiations Oil Concession with both the Hepresentatives of A.P.O.C. Ltd., and the Sastern &amp; Generel Syndicate. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant&lt; xy ty* vi Lt .-Colonel, Political Agent, KuwaitCopy of Confidential letter No.99, dated the 18th May 1953, from the Political Agent, Kuwait, to His Excellency the Ruler of Kuwait. oOo— I have the honour to refer Your Hxcellency to ^.£1^11^0^ s confidential letter, dated the 14th Hay to Your Excellency, a copy of which was sent to this Agency by Mr.Ghisholm the same day, for placing before the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the i 'ersian Gulf. 2 # I am directed by the Hon T ble the political Resident to write and ask Your Excellency to be so good as to confirm that you have suspended all negotiations concerning an Oil Concession in Kuwait Territory ior the time being, and until further notification is received from Your Excellency. 5. I am further directed to ask ,r our Bzoellenoy, also to confirm that your abovementioned decision has been duly communicated to Major Holmes of the Eastern &amp; General Syndicate by Your Excellency.Copy, in translation, of Confidential letter No. R.2-/969, dated the 19th Llay 1935, from His Excellency the Huler of Kuwait, to the Political Agent, Kuwait, OoO In reply to your Confidential letter No.99, dated the 18th May 1953, I have pleasure in confirming to Your Excellency that I dulir communicated to ooth parties, the suspension of negotiations until such a time as I may desire to reopen the same •'£ V' 1 1 r.niniTSSHTIAL. Ho.109. POLITICAL AGENCY, KIKUIT. Dated the 25th May 19 53, From t iwiQitT iAi. Ktatm \ i i\ To Lt ^-Colonel Dickson, G.I,E # , I.A., Political Agent, Kuwait; ■-v.. The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, B U S H I H E . Oil Activities of Major Eofcmes, Sir, Yfith reference to my confidential despatch No. 104, dated the 20th Kay and enclosures, I have the honour to report the following interesting incidents in connection with Major Holmes return to Kuwait froa Bahrain on 17th May. 2. I, la jar Holmes was met hy his local representative Mohamed Yatim, who remained closeted in a cdbin with chief for over an hour on the oteamer, before landi 6 S. On Monday 22nd May Major Holmes called on me . - orae polite coimonplaces, I asked at the Agency, ana after some p 4*0+ the Shaikh had suspended him what his plants were now all Oil negotiations rt sine die'. 4. r,:ajor Eotoes M « sharply a.M «.t I I T ,,0^ it on the authority of the he knew seeing that I he.d ^ vatim had telegraphed to him Shaikh that his man liOhamed . ■ 13th May and in a very lengthy (Major Holmes) at Bahrain + goo/- had told him of the Shaikh s telegram costing Hs.^o^/ f U f ■ C' -t ' decision/ I I v V II %■ &gt; - 2 - deci sioao 5. liajor Holmes at once, and very angrily, denied tliat lie had been told anything at all about the Shaikh's decision either by a telegram or letter or verbally; An obvious n falsehood ,r of course, seeing that he did not leave Bahrain till the 15th l ay, and even had he not re ceived his Agents telegram it was ridiculous to suppose that he had been in Kuwait from 17th May to the 22nd r^lay and learnt nothing. 6 # Major Holmes went on hotly to assure me on hi^ pli^Lted' word that he knew nothing, end had been told nothing. He then seemed to lose his head altogether, and started abusing the Shaikh, yourself, myself, the British Government and above all the A .P .O.C., vowing vengeance at us an in rather scandalous manner. At any other time X would have turned him out of my hou^e .or saying half what he did, but as X hoped to get something out of him, X let him be. ^ust wait', he said, 'and see r*+- who are behind me, wilJ- o . what the American Government, who „ + h - n ten vet, that he would He then shouted that he was not beate ye ,. nf all the world, and that get his concession in spi •&lt;- xannld enter the lists them- then th. American Oovaramnt • n4 . t= W ,h selves and send a repre^o + a fair do with the Shaikh and their Oil Company got a tan His Majesty's Government. , +&gt;lis rather interesting 7. Having volunteered . 011 -iflenly calmed down, an piece of information, he ~ ^ ;1 =t t-ange seeing that X had an told anything, was dou f ^ Q-hnilch. dated the 19T;h May o official letter from the o , iar ties v, t h (the Shaikh) bad informed both P firming that he (the , t,,, SI » al0e, • , (the A.P.O .C. and the -as - that tiie Oil negotiations had been suspended, until such time as he (the Shaikh) decided to reopen them agaip» 8 # This seemed to sober Major HoLaes completely, and he left me saying that he would discuss the matter with the Shaikh, #10 was dining with him. 9. The same evening at 8 p.m., and whilst the Shaikh was at his house, I received a note from Major Holmes, worded as follows:- Dear Dickson, The question of my being informed about the postponement of any discussions regarding the concession, is this way: His Excellency informed my ReiDresentative, 'who wrote me to Bahrain, and he has now told me the position, 'v ?hich is in accordance with what you told me. I remain etc., Frank Holmes. 10. This being a very lame way out of his 'lie'. in my opinion, I decided to see the Shaikl^/on the 23rd May, at 9 a .m., so as to clear up the whole matter: His Excellency after listening to my story of Major Holmes 'denial' with interest, remarked, 'Not only did Holmes lie to you, but I made him admit to me last night at dinner, that he had lied: He could not do otherwise, seeing that Mohamad Yatim, his Agent, was at dinner also, and in Arabic, which Holmes does not understand, that he had sent him full details by wire to Bahrain on 13th May, my decision and had fully explained the position on the Kuwait. 22nd May. lag Brandy **. e above sto:y. with reluctance, not anything disparaging about Major to enable you to appreciate the 12. I mention the above stoiy. because I wish to say anything dispa Holmes Qharaoter, but to enable /ou local/A* - 4 - local situation, and the methods of the man we have to deal with. 13, The fact that 'rogues sometimes fall out n even in the presence of kings, is also anusing, 14, The point of the above incident is clearly the following: Major Holmes came to see me (knowing all along that the Shaikh had suspended negotiations) in order to try, by a process of 'bluff',to find out,whether the Shaikhs suspension of the negotiations had been his own idea or had been insnired or dictated by you as a result of your visit to London# Much capital would, of course, have been made, if the second al ternative had been correct: Clearly be was out get some form of admission out of me to use against both of us. Heedless to say he failed. He lost his temper as a result of the news whicb I sprang on Mm * that I had received a letter from the shaikh, 4 days previous to his visiting me, confirming that he had informed both parties of the suspension of the negotiations^ ^vi-i when he tried 15, Major Holmes next efj-or uas v. i ptter and verbally, the -large scale' to borrow from me by let ter a ^ the Feutral Zone and North Hassa map of Kuwait, showing the ^ « cow of which you in detail^, which I made las ye &gt; „ all tlie persuasive powers he possesses possess* He used all w ie this end, but naturally did not succeed. 1 . ■ wnimes. as already reported in 16. On 24th May, Major _ -a. Kuwait for England my telegram No. 106 of date lef Baghdad, Mosul and the iTisibm r lp1 ;ter to me, ^ markedly courteous letter In a last ana ttiat npft by car for B asra &gt; J».t b.f0P. !.» ^ .. tor .11 he hoped to see my wife in onall my kindness to Ms wife wlien he was away in Jedda. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, !r h^ 'Lt.-Colonel, Political Agent, Kuwait TSS.• 4' ^ if. - a- Telegrani P. ~ ~~ jj - obj H •¥' s • Minieter, Jedda* f 0 Secretary of State for Forei^i Affairs, London, Ho* 110. Repeated Political Resident, Bushire, Uo. 124. Dated 5th recei-ved 6th June 1933. y Your despatch No# ISO. TOAD informed me confidentially and spoke to me yestetday that Ibn Saud had addressed Shaikh of Kuwait a letter regarding commercial relations #iich contained proposal^ of nature to give Shaikh some satisfaction. He added tlmt King had been impressed by news of distress ful local situation and that if his letter produced good result proposal would in due course he put forward, officially. Fuad did not say through what channel this would 'be done. It may 'be better not to use this information with Shaikh unless he notifies Political Resident of receipt, of letter. In my opinion, this new development must be con sidered in the light of two possibilities, viz. (A) King mayZgenuinely anxious to compose hie differences with all his neighbours or (B) He may think he has ShaiKh sufficiently at his mercy to establish political ascendency over him hy wort of direct agreement. In this connection see recent reports from ^ Political Resident especially that regarding Ilm message to Shaikh in Jehruary and latter's journeys into ^ejd. - RYAN.:v| 1 - '7 ^ ' nnUFIDjSNTlAL No.34 of 1935 Britisu xiesiciency c. Consulate- G-en eral, 3l T iiil .E, the 8th June, 1953. SUBJbaT ; Kuwait Oil. Sir, - In continuation of my telegram Ho.T-1, dated the ' 15th May, I have the honour to report that I have ^ received a letter from the irolitical Agent, Kuwait, to the effect that on the 22nd May, aoout a week after Major Holmes had a .rived from Bahrain, the latter called on the lolitical Agent, who in the course of conversa tion asked him what his plans were now uuat -is Excellency Shaikh Ahmad had for the present suspended oil negotiations with 'both companies. Major olmes pretended to be fair-ly startled, and saio U had received no information to that eiiect. udonel Dickson pointed out that he himseli had 'been inior^eu l)y His Excellency that his - j ajor • olmes Kuwait agent * one M 'ohamed. Yatim - had telegxaphed the oe'' to Bahrain on the 13th May* Major Holmes protested strongly that he had received no information whatsoever either 'by telegram, letter, or vertally. Colonel Dickson went on to point out that this was strange as be had received an official letter, dated the 19tU Kay,/ ! ®jesty 's Secretary of State for the Colon es, The Colonial Ofiice, London»'C; ( 11 -2- May, from the Stiaikh confirming that he (the Shaikh) bad informed 'both parties (the Anglo-Persian Oil Company Ufilted and the Eastern and General Syndicate Limited) of the temporary suspension of oil negotiations* kajor Holmes departed saying he would discuss the matter with the Shaikh# 2. Major l olmes* denial of having received the news 'being obviously a falsehood, Colonel Dickson thought it as well to clear up the matter with the Shaiktu The following is Oolonel .Dickson's account of the interview. rt Eis Excellency after listening to my story *of Major Holmes ^ *de]S^ial ,, with interest, remarked, only did Holmes lie to you, hut X made him aomxt to ae last night at dinner, that he had lied, he ooula not do otherwise, seeing that Mohamed Yatia, his gen , was at dinner also, and told me in AraMc, wUlcla Holmes does not understand, that lie had sent him full details l)y wire to Bahrain on 13th May, oi my decision and had fully explained the position on the steamer, to bis ehief' { on the arrival of the latter at Kuwait). •The Shaikh added tbat he had told ^ ajor Holmes that he had made a 'great and serious mistake-, and further volunteered the remark thaw perhaps tod Doen drinking Brandy'. 5. What object Major Holmes tuout,-^ lie w0 gain hy his clumsy and ineffectual falsehood toow. I merely report the incident a -&gt;1- on/I r y&gt;'- -3- on Major Holmes• mentality and methods of conducting liis negotiations* I am sending oopias of ttiis despatch to His Majesty 's Secretary of itate for mdia and ^he CrOTemnient of India. 1 have the honour to he # Sir, Your most oheciient, humhle seiTant, ^ Lieut.-Oolonel, Political Resident in the Persian £ulf« n^' Jci/e-4 CONFIDENTIAL. 0 SOi 631- J of 1932. #' The Hon ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to 1- His Majesty* : Secretary 1 la to for i.Du XSi j - jTliion. £• The 1'or Cxi-, -coretary to tUe uovoi-niaent ol ItKiia, :ifula. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermenlioned docu ment (s^. British Residency and Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated, Reference to previous correspondence fl Bushire Printed leivar 532- of i.i'jb^■ Description of Enclosure. Name and Date, /I Bustiire despatch Ho. 34 oi 8th June 1953 to Fis Majesty's Secretary of Btate for tLe Colonies. Copy, with copy of 0 with compliments to Kuwait, for i Subject. KUWAIT OIL. iclosure, forwarded the Political Agent, formation.j ^ y No. 646-S of 1933. British Eesidency and Consulate-General Bushire, the 12th June 1933. from * The Hon # hle Lieut.-Oolonel T.O. Fowle, O.B.E,, Political Resident in the Persian CJulf, To The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India Simla. 1933, 1 have the honour to state that Colonel Dickson has informed me that His ijxcellency the Shaikh of Kuwait has stated to him verbally that &gt; the Shaikh, has definitely refused the invitation of the Eastern and General Syndicate» 1 am sending a copy of this letter uo His Majesty's Secretary^*of State for India. I baT* 'be honour to lie. Subject : Shaikh of Kuwait' s v isi t^to Ingland . Sir, With reference td correspondence dnding vvith India Office telegram No. 1050, dated 2dta April fa7-* ( *7- Sir, ^ -5 aftTVant &lt; Political0 fUjii '-♦V-Jt COPY SENT TO- 5:jJL final tlecori o' .. journal froti Xh* 26tli April) held e.t tll» Colooltl Ofti:.® on the 5ra of Kay, icxx m t© disousB v; ; • 'tlons relating to oil in the Fersian Halt. IR5S5NT&gt; Mr, Parkins on Mr .Blaxter Mr.James Mr &lt;. Rend el Mr fi Johnstone iir,LaithT;aite Captain koore Mr,Starling Colonial Office, Foreign Office. India Office. Admiralty. Petroleum Department Lieutenant Colonel Political Resident in the Fowle, Captain Prior lereian Gulf. Indian Polltioal Department w o ^.4* * a- -—- — .r , 4 \ (lately Politioal Agent at Bahrein,: I. KUV-AIT, 1. Mr. larkinson oallefi attention tc 1 at telegram from Kuwait reporting tbat, on being by the Shaikh regarding the last offer by the inglo- Persian Oil Company, Major Holmes had immediBtelj ofj-e + that he should be more fa^ourahle terms, on the 4 ^ 0 ^ r-^nax^on allotting the allowed to submit p. new drs^t cone 'Dr'-i'fiwli and the southern northern part of Kuweit tc the 3 i f part tc the Americans® 2. General dieouasion regarding -.ntenti behind this new proposal showed that there is reaeon to h^ve discovered,, as a J,eoU believe that fejor Holmes w&amp;y ^'' ofi9: of bis explorations for water, that, one area lias more o:l 'bearing possioilitles than the other, and that it is nol out of the question tlaat the part to be allotted to the British might be comparatively unremuneratIve« From information prsYiously reoeivea from the Shaikh it Is understood that the British area would compris® 1&gt;ZQ0 square miles an3. the .American area 400 square miles, mc that the initial payment in the case of each separate conoeseion would 'be Bs.4b,000« 5. Mr. Parkinson asked whether it would he rr nfff i ii~r~i -r— r'—rrr— practicable or advisable for His Majesty's Government to intsrrene at once on Iftie ground tnat tl^e new propo^ai !&lt;'» divide Kuwait territory was unacceptable. Mr. Rendel was Inolined to th-ihk that to taic tiiia line might place ua in a somewhat invidious pooV.icn. Moreover, he saw some difficulty in interrenina at this stage when we were uaaware of the exaot nature of the proposal and had not yet learned the reactions of the Anglo-Persian Oil Company. In s&amp;s deairahlSj before tendering further adTloe to tfcs to wait until the respective offers of the coveting Companies might he regarded as more or less ilnal. 8, Ir. reply to a question said „ leSl t w poasitxe, .» ae^rs. ,rtnolrt«.. ' «« «' 11 ' tfctt M™it ™. too to M oo».a«, wo Oil It —t. 1&gt;0««'. '• *'•* ' miction, =»«- . - 'notinst in Bahrein. Bahrein was con- wish to acquire a looting *• nr, K-i^iit and we should, therefci e, siderahly smaller than Kuwait ana + „ watch events in Bahrein 'oefore vetoing u. well advieed to vnxzcn evwuu© . n,, the ground of the amallneea of new proposal unerel^ ^ Kuwait. a ^ i Kumit. Subject, Iio^veirer, to drvelopneiata in Balu^;.a t he saw no reason wliy His Ma j a sty 's Govern.ment should not adopt, such -an attitude with a certain measure of Justification. 6c Tli6 suggestion ms made that the Slaai&amp;h should loe told that he must accept the adTloe of His liajesty 1 ^ Government on technical matters. It was pointer out, that the Shaikh had, in affects flatly contradiotea advice tendered W His Majesty 5 s Government on the technical aspects of the two original draft concaaslons oy asserting that, in Ms opinion, the Syndicate'e offer, aa it stood, was the better. f.After eome disouseion it was Bgre«a ti.at i» would not 'be within the toma of owx pledge to ■'»»*«'■ the Shaikh aocepting our advice, even in teehaioai rM*Ue*' lie could only give tola our advio® and warn hla that Dy disregarding it he would he endangering hla own intereste. T.i au tanant-G olongl J^ ae ezprssoed the n** Sb.aiMa would prohaWy aooep» advice wandered 8. T.^utenant.Colo nel ^ae alao said that the ro^nvwere -being kept well a'oreast of Anglo-Persian Oil company all development Se .. ae '»= M * W «• °'' n! •. ■„ doM u.lll ' l'- 4 '• nothing could oe done, usitxj . -twin' concession proposed hy Major Holme., and that x. 4-a »f.nd a telegram to the Acting would be deeirauie i •from the ... &amp;e draft should be obtained ^rorn tn . Resident asking tha^ the dra. _^ • Vi-i ci sirrival at xvU^aiv. ^ fhe He si dent on his Shaikh, ready for wie t T fWAlX aEUTBSujONS. ,j that recent information from ■jn Mr. Parkinson said that reo ' I ri Queo tton of a concession in the J eddnh showed that tn . ■ neutralIll, HlTAii. 14. yze meeting had some further discussion about oil in Qatar s Guring which it emerged that, in addition to the action approved 'by the meeting on the :&lt;6th of April, the Shaikh should he reminaea of his obligation under Article IV of the 1916 Treaty not to grant any concessions in respect of his territory without the approval of His Bajeaty's Government, I'he ietroleum Department would also take a suitable opportunity to bring the position unofficially to the notice of the Anglo-Per eian Oil Cc^.peay 15. In the course of the discussion th« pofiitiOB of the Iraq Petroleum Company in respect of oil conoesslmn in the Persian Gulf -as mentioned, Starling explained that ^atar was one of the territories in the Persian Gulf in which the members of the Iraq letroleum Company group had under taken net to seek concessions without the approTal of the other saemtrers. I' the ir-.Q . - • U-'.U' Company insisted in standing on the Agreement -.hit; mean that any eoneession obtained ^y saw lei^.an Oil Company iH Qatar would have to be passed on to the Iraq Petroleuni Compsny. In these circumatanoes, we had tc face the possibility that ^fae Company, whioii although e British Codjp s , l ai - foreign Interests, od^ht eTentw'.L .v ' a fa the Gulf. fli» retrolwa. DepartBont hun SOBe tlEi * thought ttet It Ight be desirable for the whole question to be crousht under rariaw so that all the Departmenta oonoarned &lt;al S ht be -ble to consider the tnatter en3 jtf■ Starliri.^ enguiret whether it could be considered bythe Middle Basteru u)&lt; - ; nee of the CouiiaiUee of Imperial Defence. i^re v-aa always the possibility that the Irsg Petroleum Cotanany would take the line th&amp;t their hands Fere full in Iraq and that they would not interest themselveG in these ssialler areas in the Gulf. In that ©rent they might allow the Anglo Persian Oil Company which was very interested in the Sulf to take up ooneeesions. (Since the meeting the Petroleum. Department has learned unofficially that there are indications that seme of the Groups in the Iraq Petroleum Company are not disposed to support the Iraq Petroleum Company T s efforts to secure a concession in llaea), 16. Mr„ Par'£inson said that he thought the Middle Eastern Sub-Committee could deal with the matter, U a memorandum were submitted by the Petroleum epui tu'-ut. # alternatively there could he an interdepartmental discussions It was agreed that the Petroleum department should initiate any action that might required in this connection as and -hen uhey thought by way of a meiaorandum which would be sen-^ in ^he instance to the Colonial Office. XV. BAEIEIN. A, Bgtenslon of P'r AmendrnQnta to Mining _ij£.|l§Q• 17. The meeting first fiisoussefl whether the Coopany ia exititXefl to an estensioo of their prospecting j-icenoe under Article 1^' o: ^ ..r.-emen . ^ i n pri attention to the Political Agent at Bahrein nau ^ wnrd ,T entitled' in a act that the Company had useu vu theirtlieir letter of the 4th of April, The woraing; of .Article IV provides that an exten a ion of the prospecting lioenoa up to two ye rs may be grantea if the Shaikh on the aflvioe of the Political Reaident is satisfied that such 'n extension is justified. The Acting Resident has stated in a reoent telegram that the interpretation is not 'quite free from doubt'« It was therefore decibel th.'t^ on the whole, it would be better to obtain le, .1 advioe on this point, and that auoh advice ho.d better be sought from tie Treasury Solicitor. In the tjeantime, however, the discussion would proceed on the assumption that the Corapsny J|er^_not entitled to an extension. l3* In connection with this point Gap t^in n ..-^riojl said that Mb,or Holasa ^ows quite well that the Company oe met t er.'ension as a right, ! ---nu tLat he had in fact, urged the Americans to be content with the one year's extension already grantsti. Ciiptain Prior unlerBtand s that the relatioas bo^ween the Atnerioons ood Mujor Uoluies are not -■ cordial as they might be. 19, The BeetJing than diaoussefl the alternative proposal submitted by the Company that in return for the r fg ht. to eeleot 200,000 instead o? ^ &lt; ' re - , th«y should M the S*S* laoreased annual V^nU and a loan to he repaid fro® royaltias- 20, Mr. S^crliv.&gt;i said that on hal^noe he hou 0 1&lt; .OU. M better «et t. &lt;•» ««•. Be eointed out --»«&gt;« «' ' asas they slaoula done under the terms of the 1925 Agraaiaent ? selectareas when they took up their prospeoting licence, and it would, in his opinion, better to insist on their taking out a mining lease f which would invol% 7 e the selection of ere^s, and thus leave the field open for another Company, fharo were, in fact, recent indioationa that the Anglo-Persian Oil Company were interested in Bahrein. 21. Some doubt was felt as to the actual area affected by the concession- The right of exploration had he en 'throughout the whole or the territories art ax his (the Shaikh's) control', e.na the prospecting licence should have be an granted oree 'areas to be seleotaa by the Company' ■■ Aoonrate information regarding the suee of the whole of the Shaikh's dominions was not aTail&amp;h n, but Caotaia Prior auggested that a figure of I'jo.OOO &gt; ■&gt; i ; would be sowewhere near the mark. Captain Prior alfeo said he tos giwn to understand that drilling uould carried out in the open sea at a depth j.5 23. It was generally agreed that it vuiuld u~ better not to permit n extension of the Company's area, but that another year's extension of the prospect ins u,,,.. a.ouid » .».!««•■ «'»» ° f the mining lease should he new uelcen• Hr &gt; Parlcinaon. tlien ajjlsed the views of the meeting regardinf; tlie ^loxi which^ according to unofficial information, the Hofcrein Goyerment had put forward, that in return for the grant of vine year 9 9 extension the Company ahoula maice hira a loan of Rs^O^OOO., repayable from royaltiea when the latter exceeded one laJsh in the year. Re thought the suggestion was worth consideration aa the terms of repayment would preclude the Shaikh from getting into financial difficult lee with the Company. 24, After some discusaion it //as decided thas the question of the grant of an extension in return for a loan to the shaikh should he linked up with the amendments which His Hajesty 3 s GoYemment desire to see introduced into the mining lease 6 25. As regards the desired amendments to the raining leaae, ;.ir. otarllna said that he dia not anticipate that the Company would raise strong objections ospacially as the Agreement had already bean altered to the advantage of the Company. He explained thot it would have been out of place and ovflToersome to overload the agreement in the first place with detailed provlsiiaa which would only apply if and when the exiotence of oil in commercial -^ri -n^oTPd. This stage had now quantitxes naa oee^ p-o. • ^ •onv.^pin and all the amendments 'foeen reacned in v. j-n# . , , .. 0 nptrol eum Department were sucn as are suggested by the r ?e ^roieuui, -s jt' 4rt pi /Tr^aments co'^exin^ ^ commonly found in agr-u^u^v arsao-t. J y 26- Captain Moore said that the Admiralty attaoiied great importance to securing the right of pre-emption and introducing provisions for a proportion of the oil to be refined in Bahrein5. He explained tl at ^rm y*AACl/» •£***£ / bl'y-v -rA^CL^Jty AdinirQilty punp'OQoo oru^ oil ^rao of no tc I iic . 1 Car-taia Prior said that the Shaikh has already QTinaeo some interest in the question of oil refining in Bahrein* 27=. It was finally agreed that a draft letter to the Company should be prepared in vhe Colonial. for the concurrenoe of the other interested BepartsaantBo. The letter would laake an offer, as from the Sjaaildi of Bahrein, of one year ! s extension of the prospecting licence from the 2nd of December 19$3 in return for which the Company would be asKed to agree to (a) A substantial loan to the Shaikh (i.e. in effect # advance royalties) to be repa.U^ without interest, from royalties o\ x .. period of 5 to 5 y® ars when t]ie l8tter exceeded one lakh in the year. ('b) The amendments to the mining j-ea^e suggested by the Petroleum Department. iii»« approrea «». «»or&lt; »'« ' 0 « 1 ' M ' ' ,11, Peretan Ciulf tor .to '» .utMl.L. «»= ^ '' '' lo« no. M » '* M ''' ' 1«. for noeo.lR.lons 'l.n .M Oonponj. B. Prillera.. 28, ^ that ' ln 4118 firEt plac9 he proposea to teV* up tMe question orally with 1 j, r Lorobeo-ai, Bho tefi Just asked for an Mr, Ballantyne ond ^r,i.Oiautu interviewf)'A &gt; interview. ^^.1 Uolmes 3 Reg idenng^jm B&amp;Jirein« *r® v Hf$£t,mentioned that Captain Prior fcacl ©xpr^osefi ujie opinion that, if Major E o I giqs were required to reside in Bahrein for^ a ayten montha in ©very year, lie Vjou I^ probably resign the appoiatmant t il onxy for reasons of health* If this was so^ insxateno© on suoh a period of residence inight well |&gt;a the easieat way out of our diffioultiee. Mr. Blast er mentioned that it had feeen understood from oral discussions with the Company 1 s representatives that they would prefer to avoid a fize^ period 'being laid down during which their local Representative must reside in Bahrein. 30. Mr. Parkinson said he would prefer not to take any action in this matter until he had had an opportunity of studying the atateeient of the facts which was to 'be drawn up as the result of the discussions at the meeting of the 26th of April.HOTS on the Kuwait Oil situation as 1 see it in the light of His Majesty's Minister^edda's telegram EoJ.24, dated the 5th June 1932, to Bushire U10 to London). I. The news that Bin Saud has addressed a letter to the Shaikh of Kuwait propounding certairjpro posals of a commercial nature which can he counted on to giTe the Shaiicb satis faction, is most important, and as i read it means that jfin Saud is now definitely going to enter the lists in the matter of H Kuwait Oil'. It entirely confirms what 1 rather foresaw was coming, ride my Confidential letter Bo.80,(copy forwarded to Colonial Office (No.28), Government of India and His Majesty's Minister,Jedda (*io.4t&gt;4-S; under Bustiire Printed letter dated the 2nd May 1953), dated the 27th April, to Bushire, although the granting of the Hassa Oil concession to the Standard Oil Company, not then visualized, some what confuses the issue, 3, I think we may for a start, disabuse our minds of the idea that the king has any sort of 'feelings' for the distreeeed condition of the people of Kuwait, seeing that it is hie blockade of the last 10 years which has hrou^it them to the pass they are in. 4. In my view possibility (B) as envisaged hy His Majesty's Minister, Jedda, is the correct interpretation of -vtoat is going to happen, and the king now thinks the time ripe for estahli shing his political ascendancy over Kuwait/to ^ ] -3- Kuwait under the guise of an Oil agreement, The plan of caiapaign to 'be adopted (part of vjhich v;e have seen develop as helowj will, 1 Relieve, l)e somev/hat on the following lines s- ( a ) It has 'been pretty clearly established now that •rahen the Shailch went into the Keid desert on the 20th and 25th February last, (see my Secret J^o. 44, dated the 5th March 19 33 - copy forwarded to -'T- p Colonial Office (^0-19), Government of India and His Majesty's Minister,Jedda under ^ Bushire Printed letter dated the 16th March 1935 - he met the king himself who was then 80 miles north of Hafar al Atz, hunting,! or possibly his son the Amir Saud, not Saud al Arafa as reported at the time^. At this meeting details of the mode of procedure to be adopted were, 1 believe, discussed, arai cp.i i.e probably emanated from the Shaikh of Kuwait in the first instance• (b) The Shaikh probably pointed out that Kuwait was on the verge of collapse due to the blockade and must obtain relief. The king expressed willing, riess to afford such relief provided the Shaikh would Join forces in an Oil agreement, details of which would be submitted later. Both States would thus benefit equally• (c) The Shaikh probably went on to say that in the matter of the competing Oil Companies at Kuwait /on the whole was rather inclined to lavoui Holmes/Holmes and his American 'backers. (d) The king no douht replied that he also favoured the Americans before the Anglo-Persian Oil Company and that if the Shaikh and he combined to keep the Anglo-Persian Oil Company out, not only would both reap an advantage, but he. Bin Saud, would be pre pared to relax the blockade and champion Kuwait in her difficulties with f Iraq» (e) Behind the Shaikh's mind was the pleasing idea of getting relief from the blockade, and assisting Major Holmes and his Americans to get into Kuwait, Behind Bin Saud *5 mind was the plan to get the Standard Oil Company (also Holmes; into the Mss. Kuwait Keutral Zone, and then using this as a lever, get them into Kuwait as well, which would give him the ascendancy he had for so long sou^it over the Shaikh of Kuwait. Then followed certain moves in the game which we know subsequently took place# (a^ Bin Saud invited certain foreign Oil Representatives to come to Jedda to negotiate an Oil agreement, etc. (b) Major Holmes who represented the Eastern and General Syndicate Limited in Kuwait and the Standard Oil in Bahrain was also invited by special telegram to go to Jedda# This he did. As a result of negotiations mentioned in (6) above, the Hassa Concession has been given to the Standard Oil Company of America,/MUM ii tm America, vide Jedda telegram of 20th May 1933,l^o*108 to Foreign Office, 122 to Bushire)&lt;» 8 # There is little doulDt in my mind that the Hassa Concession in respect of area, especially, 'will he virtually the same as was given to Major Holmes in 1925 and which later lapsed. The important point for us to consider 'being that it will almost certainly have included in it the Kuwait Keutral Zone» 9 # The next step will clearly he for Bin Saud to get the Shaikh, of Kuwait to give his consent to the Standard Oil working in the Beutral Zone.. 10. Bin Saud, in the letter which he has now addressed to the Shaikh, of Kuwait, (Jedda telegram Bo.124 to Bushire, dated 6th June 1933}, will no doubt suggest to the Shaikh that he has noticed the distressed condition of Kuwait with pain, and that he will he prepared to ease off the blockade at once either entirely or in part, if he, the Shaikh, will agree to give his consent to the Standard Oil working the Neutral Zone* Probably also he will suggest that the Shaikh receive a certain share m the oil profits o.. the Hassa concession, as a result of meeting him m this matter. 11. Any difficulties that might have arisen 'between the Eastern and General Syndicate Limited and the Standard Oil (both represented by Holmes} in the matter of the exploita tion of the Neutral Zone have probably already been arranged; and Holmes * visit to Bin Saud at Jedda was no doubt partly connected with such adjuBtment. 12./ ■ v ■ ■ ■r. ' V 0? -5- 12# Bin Saud will no doubt nov; expect the Shaikh, as per plan alreadjr made, to reply agreeing with his request,Un spite of the fact that the Political Resident on his recent visit to Kuwait reminded the Shaikh that he must make no decision in regard to the Neutral Zone without reference to His Maj esty T s Government J • 13» The Shaikh will no doubt secretly give his consent to Bin Saud and then tell His Majesty's Government that he desires their permission to agree to Bin Saud T s conditions, seeing that the benefits to be gained will be of such -vital importance to Kuwait. 14. Bin Saud for his part will doubtless guarantee the Shaikh to get His Majesty's Government to put no difficulties in the Shaikh^s way. 15. Bin Saud at one stroke will (aj please Kuwait by settling the blockade question (lo) please His Majesty's Government by so doing (cj get the Americans into the Heutral Zone* 16* Then will follow the last and final move* Bin Saud will pro hah ly then inform the Shaikh that it will be quite impossible for him, the Shaikh, to give the Kuwait Oil Con cession to the Anglo-Persian Oil Company, and that he must settle the matter in favour of Major Holmes and the Ameri cans - his official reasons will be that to have the Standard Oil working alongside of the Anglo-Persian Oil Company as rivals in the same area will create an impossible situation. It will further be pointed out that the sus pected oil is in North Hassa and the Neutral Zone, and the port/-6 port of Kuwait will be needed for the export of such oilc !?♦ Lastly it. will 'be pointed out that the prosperity of Kuwait will be assured for all time with (a) the blockade remoyed; (b) a percentage of Oil revenues from Hassa going into the Shaikh's pocket; (c) the Shaikh getting all the profits from, his Kuwait proper oil profits# 18♦ It may at this stage be even suggested as a further 'bait 11 , that if the Standard Oil (Holmes; get Kuwait as well as Hassa, all profits from Hassa, Neutral Zone and Kuwait may he pooled between Kuwait and Saudiyeh# 19. The final result, if everything goes according to plan, will be a elose rapprochement between Kuwait and Saudiyeh, and the secret transference of our political ascendancy over Kuwait to Bin Saud» Mor will the honour and prestige of Kuwait, in the eyes of the Arab world, be impaired« The above is I think not very far short of what is in the wind to-da3/» crux of the whole business lies, to my mind,in the Neutral Zone. On no account must this be allowed to be used as a pawn by either Bin Saud, the Shaikh of Kuwait, or Holmes, without His Majesty^ Govern ment's permission, for whoever gets the Neutral Zone will clearly get the Kuwait Oil concession# This is certain. (£&gt;frd 0 ) '^.'K.lP.Mckson, Lieut•-Colonel^ HJSHIRE, Jfolitical Agent, Kuwait. Dated the 7th June 19 33.V* A U, comimwnAL. British Residency &amp; Consulate-General, BUSHIRE, the 16th June, 1933• Mo. 39 of 1933. SUBJECT i Kuwait Oil. Sir, In continuation of correspondence ending with my telegram No. 11, dated the 10th June 1933, 1 imve the honour to enclose a copy of a letter Uo. B (1), dated the 7th June 1933, from Colonel Dickson, giving cover to an ^■■p rw 1 interesting note forecasting the probable trend of events in the struggle for the possession of the Kuwait Oil Con cession. If Colonel Dickson is correct, and personally I think that most likely he is, we must expect some important developments. I am sending copies of this letter to the GoTernment of India and His Majesty's Minister at Jedda. I have the honour to be, Sir, Tour most obedient, humble servant, cfl Lieut.-Colonel. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf* v-ic His Majesty's Secretary of State for the Colonies, The Colonial Office, _JL_o_nji_ 0 .Jij L&gt;Telegram 82/1, 86/5. Stom Eolitlcal Agent, Kuwait. To Political Resident, Bushire. No. 122. Bated 19th received 20th June 193S. lour endorsement No. 644-3. Letter from 11m Saud arrived 16tti June and was at once stxown to me. Letter is so obscurely worded as to 'be almost untranslatable. Contains nothing about ( ? omission 'oil* ) but makes following suggestion for settling blockade dispute. Shaikb to raise his sea customs to same figure as that existing in King^ Has a ports { i.e# from 4 to approximately 70^ ). King in return to take only 'Khawa', or tribal tax on caravans going into the interior at rate collected in Ibn Easchid^ time by certain tribes { which would total &amp;». 3 per camel). His Majesty urges Shaikh to settle business privately and not through H.M's. Government, who are not to be trusted. Portions in brackets are my comments. Shaikh of Kuwait showed me his proposed reply, which states that he is unable to raise his existing customs tariff for obvious reasons but will co-operate to the best of his power by manifest or other system if King will adopt the reasonable course of placing customs posts along the frontier line. POLITICAL AGiSNT.Telagram 5S /. 54 ' 3 2A. 86/3. from Political Ageut, Iuwait* To Political ^siuent 9 Bii8hir@# Ho# 122. iiatea 19th roceivea 20tli June 19'6Z. y K$ lour eiKlorsement Mo. 644-3. Letter from Ita daud arrived lath Juti© and was at once shorn to me. Letter is so obscurely corded as to 'be almost untranslatable. Jontains DOttiing about ( ? omission 'oil* } but makes following suggestion for settling blockade dispute. iliai&amp;h to raise bis sea customs to same figure as that existing in King 's Hasa ports ( i.e. from 4 to approximately 70^ ). King in return to take only 'Khawa', or tribal tax on caravans going into the interior at rate collected in Jbn tascbid's time by certain tribes { w&amp;lcb wouM total iw. S per oaeelj. ^is iiaje^t^ urges 3haikH to settle business privately and not through i . •s. .Jovernment, who are not to be trusted, iortions in brackets are my comments. Jhaikh of Kuwait showed me his proposed reply, which states that he is unable to raise bis existing customs tariff for otvlous reasons Out will oo-operate to the Uest of his power by manifest or other system if King will adopt the reasonable course of lacing customs posts along the frontier line, ir OLITlOAL AO-HST.9%ll t- ^V r V ^ ^ I # X. Secretary of State for the Colonies, London. Political Resident, Byshire. received 21st June 1953. Tlease telegraph 'briefly summary of your discussions with Shaikh of Kuwait regarding oil and 'blockade. I shall also he glad to receive as soon as possible 'by air mail full account of these discussions. Dickson should continue to furnish fortnightly report of oil position. You will appreciate that it is most important that Sis lajesty's G-overnment should he kept in closest touch with all developernents on these questions. Secretary of State for the Oolonies &amp; Telegram Prom To No 7 Dated 20thsent5^ 53/54 and 8S/l, 7ele ^ram X Vrom Political Resident, Bushire, ^ecr^tary of State for the Colonies, London• Ho. 14, T&gt;ated the 21st June 1933, yf ^ / Your teleftram 7, / lo OIL , Most Important item in discussion was that ShaiWi asked me to confirm that he was free to choose between the two rival Companies. I replied in the affirma tive 'but added that this did not apply to Holmes proposed divisions of territory (see Kuwait telegram 84 of 30th April) and particularly to the Neutral Zone. Before committing himself on these points Shaikh should inform His Majesty's Government. Aa in his proposals Holmes had doubtless made inclusion of Neutral Jfone a sine qua non Shaikh on this account or possinly Influenced by considera tions auggested in J'edda Savingram of 1st June presumably thought it best to gain time by temporarily stopping bidding from both parties as reported in my telegram T-l of 15th May. Despatch on Oil from 'Hickson posted to you by last bag. Though Dickson's letter to Shaikh did not after all mention oil as Dickson asiwimes in his despatch I think letter is probably right in his main prognostications. g. BLOCKADE. Regret I had little time to discuss this subject with Shaikh. Dickson is engaged in extracting \h] ^ from ShaiMi decision as to which of the three courses he is proBosing to follow. ^or latest developraent see my tele- , gram 13,of 00th June. 'dHt - HBSIDENT -r CONFIDENTIAL. ^ T() 694-^ of 1953 f The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to 1* The 'oreipr Secretary to the ^overnfnent of India, ^inla. P. r, he oliti Aftent, Kuwait. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu- Bushire .of 16th .Tune 1933. ment (s). British Residency and Consulate-Greneral, RUSH IRK. Dated Pint June 1933. Reference to previous correspondence : Name and Date. Subject. !♦ Tele ^o«7 of 20th June 1933 from HI b MaJesty'R Secretary of State for the Colonies* S. Bus hi re telerraw Ho.14 I of Plat June 1933 to Hia Majesty's Secretary of Btate ^or the Colonies. Kuwait Oil and BlockadeqoaglDEKTI/X. No,715-b of 1933« British Keaidency ic Consulate-General, Bushire, the 23rd June, 1935. To The Political Agent, Kuwait. KUj/AXT-MEJ-D HBUTRAL z,OIIE OIL COKCESUION OFJL924. p^nR^mniK. The following' is an extract from paragraph 15 of the record of a meeting held at the Colonial Office on the 3rd May 1933 (copy forwarded to you under Residency Printed Letter Uo.668-S t dated the 15th June 1933), at which 1 was present. 'The Resident should also take steps to discover 'what had actually happened in 1924, when a 'concession in the Neutral Zone is said to have 'been granted to the Eastern and General Syndicate.' 2. I was not able to enquire into this matter at Kuwait on aay return from England# ^'ould you kindly ascertain the required information from your records and, if you set no objection, by aeizlng a auitable opportunity to make a verbal enquiry front His iixooXXenoy the shaikh of i-uwait, and repoit to me. The Residency records do not contain more definite information than that reported by the Political Agent, Kuwait in his telegram II0.IO6-S, dated the 6th April 1924.; The poUlr at issue is whether this concession, if granted, has definite^ lapsed. Tide paragraph 10 of the Conference record, it wouKi- also be interesting to know what the proposed clauses were which, as far as our records show, were never produced by tht Shaikh./--Jd- Sbalkh* It would not be advisable» however, for you to raise these two points with the Shaikh at present, but if you merely ask him whether he signed the concession he may Tolunteer more information of his own accord. / / Lieut.-Colonel, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. X-, I \ \noinrrDMTiAE. So. 43 of 1933. British Residency &amp; Consulate-Generait Bus Mrs , the 27th .Tune 1933. t; r Subject : Kuwait Oil, Sir, In continuation of my telegram No. 14, dated the pf 21st June 1933, I have the honour to report that in addition to the item mentioned in that telegram, in the interview which Colonel IHckson and I had with the Hhailch I took the of opportunity of reminding the Shaikh/the considerations contained in your telegram No # 9, dated the S2nd December 1932, i.e. w the Bhaikh should he made fully aware,i.e. by oral explanation, that if concession is granted to Eastern jl, and General Syndicate it means that It will 'be transferred to a Company controlled by foreign capital even though nominally British and subject only to whatever measures of over-riding British control may hereafter be decided upon; while concession to Anglo-Persian Oil. Company will ensure entire British control 1 '. I also reminded the ShaiMi that whoever got the Concession His Majesty's Government would have various safeguards for inclusion in the agreement o The Shaikh - so Colonel IHckson informed me - had again shown signs of trying to keep him - Colonel ickson - in the dark about the Oil negotiations. I again reminded the Shaikh of the necessity of keeping the 'olitical Agent informed on this matter (in this connection see paragrajti i 2 of ay fficpress letter Mo.C-13. dated the 6th February 1933/ h Majesty's Secretary of State for the Colonies, TTie Colonial Office, London.1933 (copy forwarded to the Govemnent of ^ndia under ■Residency Printed letter No«C~15 of same date)* 2, I asked the Shaikh how he felt ahout the cccmiunica tion which I understood Bir John Gadman had macie to him on tV^e latter's visit to Kuwait: i^e# that if the concession went to the American Company the Anglo-Persian Oil Company Limited - in their own interests - would he compelled to make a local 1 oil war 1 on the said Company® 'Tie Shaikh confirmed that this communication had heen made to him hy Sir .Tohn Cadman, and also hy Mr* llkington, who was then in Kuwait, hut that he - the Bhaikh - felt that this concerned the American Company and not himself. ^he Company (suppos ing they got the concession) would have to pay him the sums, and the royalties, due under their agreemeni t anit i - h reason of the 1 oil war 1 they were unable to carry on +heir work, their plant, etc. - under the agreement - woulc^ become his property, and he could lease the concession to some other Company. ''here seemed to me a good deal in what the Bhaikh said. 3. I informed the that I had heard that there was otmelderahle dieeatiBfaction amongst the mroerouB memDere of hie family as he «as keeping them completely In the dark as to hie oil negotiations. He was, the TMler, hut in these days public opinion counted for a good deal, and public opinion in Kuwait was represented largely hy the Suhah family. Whichever party he finally ezre the concession to. would it not he wise to take this # 4»Tf/'» Viis confidence ^ 'he ^naikh • public opinion ' more into his con-xaei replied/replied that he never consulted his family on any matter. (This is quite true; it is one of his weaknesses that his rule is a w one man's show ^, unlike that of the? 3ultan of Muscat, for instance, who makes use of the members of his family to assist him in his administration). As far as the Oil Concession was concerned, said the Shaikh, whatever decision he came to, he would see to it that his familj^ followed suit. The Shaikh 1 o attitude in this matter did not appear to me a particularly sensible ore, hut I did not pursue the matter further. tion 'between the tItrI parties, suppoeinff they decided amonfret themselves at any stage that this T-oiild he nore economical than to continue bidding against each other. He seemed to he confident that whatever happened in this direction he could manage affairs to his own advantage. I am sending a copy of this despatch to the 4 I asked the Shaikh how he felt ahout an amalgama' Government of India I have the honour tc he. Sir, Your most obedient, humble servant. Lieut.-Colonel, Political Resident in the -ersian GulfGOVERNMENT OF INDIA. /I I Department, EXPRESS LETTER rJV 7 .J?.—is an ORIGINAL MESS! A av * v telegraphic expense and undue me of the wires hut Inio 'T'- to le treated, on receipt, with been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worried ' ^ rigved as if it had been so despatched^ ed and 4- jom iirf y Political, n ' ■ i&gt; - ' ■ ■ cxat Bahrain. SI D£ NCY^.^J in G Resident, Bu shi re. UUNrrUcnilAl ntuu ptd:- po li ti cal,Kuwai t. •C/228. Dated 25th June 19$Z&gt;\ Shaikh of Kuwait in conversation told Adviser to Bahrain oTernment that Bin Sa^d had given American Oil Company concession Ter territory♦ He was very heated about it and said that if thought they could drill in his territory they were mistaken. 2, Shaikh thought it curious that Company should take up ^cession from Bin Sa'ud 'and heirs' as Sa^udi Arabia would collapse kis death if not before. 3. Shaikh also rather Is/boured to Adviser idea of kinship and r iend8hip between Kuwait and Bahrain as opposed to Kajd and said that ^re had never been hostilities between Kuwait and Bahrain as theije been with Kajd. 4 » I understand that Muliammad Yatim,Major Holmes» man,is applying visa for London. He has had a telegram from Major Holmes in London Addressed Bushire,repeated Kuwait. ^C^FP-sgeBCF-iS&amp;P—CG.lSOTj—7-4-17—?i00 ) 000. jieut-Colonel. iPolitical Agent,Bahrain./ ^ ST- government of indta, iritlsh iiesidency and Gonsulate-General, Bushire fN* T j * This is an ORIGINAL MJiSSAGB, sent hy post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, hut intended to be treated, oa receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been tcler/raphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and siyi ed as if it had been so despatcheds\ From Political Resident, Bushire. To Political Agent, Kuwait. 780-S. r Doled SOtti June m 3 Your telegram of 28th June Ho. 134. Please enquire from the Shaikh of Kuwait on his return what territory he was referring to. i e may possibly have meant the Neutral Zone. Reply hy post will suffice unless Shaikh refeired to Neutral Zone. • 3d/- T.C.Fowle. Lieut-Ccl. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Attested. for Secretary to the Political Kesident in the Persian Gulf. S. 6 a MIK.// Confidential, / MM2BANDLJM' KOWSIT OIL. iv-r. otarimg oi the Petroleum Depci.rtment and kr, Pieam oi the Anglo-Persian Oil Company called at the India Office on gnd June to discuss infomaiy the latest developments In the Kowelt oil concession and to consider the line to oe taken. Mr. Hearn read telegrams from the local rupieseaoativcs ox olie 0»C• in the Persian Gulf. From these teleen a^iio i u cippreo. unau one Sneikii had -eiv.graphed a message oi congratulation to Bir John Cadman on the satisfactory outcome of the A^P.O.C. negotiations in Persia and had received an. extremely cordial reply, the loccol effects ox wiiich had 'been considerahle. The local. •0«^« repie^entatives mQicated tiiat in 'one light of th Sheikh 1 s reactions to this reply they thought there was some possibility of very rapid developments in the near future as regards K owe it oil. Prom remarks dropped by the Sheikh they thought, indeed, that there was some possibility of his making a statement of interest on or aDout tne time of the King's Birthday. H.E. had further touched on the possibility of a visit to England and the Question wiietner if he came as trie guest ox the A.P»0»C. he would be recognised officially. The local ropxeoenoatives o x tne Company w ere anxious go Know vvnetnei anything encouraging to the Sheikh and likely to make him take the decision desired by them could be said and in particular whether they might be authorised to offer him a visit and to make any statement as regards official recognition in this event. 3. Mr. Hearn had recently attended an Inter departmental meeting in connection with the steps being taken/ i s c■oaken oy tne A.P.O.C. and the I.P.c. to secure a definite concession in Qatar at which the general position seems to have been discussed with some freedom. Mr. starling hah, opai txoui uiiis ? given nim generally to understand the pobiuioii as regards Koweit. I said in the first place, that -o xuo uiib King's birthday, the Sheilch had received a vyiy recently and there was, 1 understood, no qutis uion of un iinmediate further honour for him. The oujecoions xrom the point of view of our understanding with the United States Government to giving him a special further iionoar at tnls juncoure were patent. Mr. Hearn said he fully appreciated this. iio re^rds the visit home ? I 'briefly referred to the d-ubCuooio.aD v'viiicn nad previously taken place, of the general bcjnst- ul vvnich iv.r. ne^rn was aware. I said that, anxious as we might he on general grounds that the A.P.O.C. should succeed in getting tnis concession, we were quite definitely tied by the undertakings we had given to the United States Government to give a fair field and no favour and that it was obviously most important to ta k e no step which could admit of misinterpretation. In these circumstances it was impossible not to feel that if the A.P.O.C. were now formally to invite tile Sheikh to England and he were to accept, and if on top of tiiis H.Iv!.J. were to extend official recognition to him and possibly offer him some hospitality, taat the Americans, probably already by no means satisfied of our bona fiaes . would regard it as a deliberate attempt on our part to exercise influence, in a manner contrary to our undertakings, in favour of the British company concerned, flalle 1 coula not say what the view of the Foreign Office was likely to be, it 23eiiied improbable that it woula differ from this and I thought ^ in the circumstances definitely preferable that the greatest caution should be exercised as regards any suggestion of/of an invitation by tne A.P.O.C. If they decided In favour giving sucn an Invitation before the abeikn had made up his mind about the concession I aid not think that official recognition of the sheikh during his visit could be accorded by K,M.G, 5 ' 11 ' on the ot ^er hand, the Sheikn were, as the teiegrums read by Mr. He am suggest a a might, in the view of the local representatives of the A.P.O.C., he possible, hy any chance to make up his mind in tne immediate future in iavour 01 tne A.P.O.C., the obstacles to a visit home and to ofiicial recognition of the Sheikh during such a visit would oe vtiv suustantialiy reduced. But even in such circumstance it vvould seern deiinitely preferable from the point of view of our relations wim the American Government that no visit shoula take place until a decent interval after the grant of the concession to British interests. Mr. Hearn after some lurtncr discussion agreed that, having regard to the position adoptee v^Sr^-vis tne United states Government by H.M.G.. it was unaesimble to take any attitude different from that suggested in tne conversation and proposes, I understand, to reply to nis representatives in the Persian Gulf that the greatesu care must be exercised as regards any extension of an invitation; tnat it snoula not be used at this stage; and uhut in tne event of the Sheikh granting the concession to A.r.a.a. iu Vvouid oe preieraole that the visit, if it took place, snoula be only after a decent interval. 6 ' :Qatar concession . Mr. Hearn alluded to the discussion which had recently taken place about Qatar. I said, that I had been on leave during this meeting and was not nilly aware of the position, but a brief discussion took Pi^ce. ivir. Heam, who had previously referred to the ^ssiDility of some arrangement between the A.P.O.C. and the Gulf/« 4 - u-uij. Oil Company, under which ths exploitation ol the Ko we it concession, if it went to the A.P.O.G., should be cnoiicly conaucted by trie A*P.O,C. , the Aiaerican interests hcivin^ a. snare in distribuoion onlyj and had also referred to oiie iocoiiu acquisition oi the riasa concession by the Suaiidard uil Company, hinted at possible difficulties over saieguards in connection with ^atar, particularly having regard to the international interests represented on the Ireq Petroleum Company. The French, in particular, might see cOiio-Laaiovolu ciiil iculty aoout any right of preemption in the event of mr. 7. I so,id that, while I did not know what had taken place in the previous discussions, it was only fair to say uh-t, ou as could be Juaged, the question of safeguards in respuct of tue Q^tar oirea was likely to be of great importance. having regard to the position of tne Sheikh, his treaty conrnitments and possible difficulties about jurisdiction, it woula be unfair to hold out any hope that they were likely to be easy to surmount. A different position might- arise, indeed, if the A.P.O»C# were to develop the Qu-tar concession, foreign companies having a distriDUuing interest only ana till personnel, etc. being British. (Sd.) J.G. LAITHWAI'IE. 2nd June 1953.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000255_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/623</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000255</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/623</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'D 93 KUWAIT OIL A.P.O.C. (82/1 VI) and E. &amp; G.S. (86/1 IV)'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1933/1933</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-05-16T00:09:18</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (259 folios)</extent><extent>The documents in the volume are mostly arranged in chronological order. There are notes at the end of the volume, (folios 237-244). The file notes are arranged chronologically and refer to documents within the file; they give a brief description of the correspondence with reference numbers in red crayon, which refer back to that correspondence in the volume.</extent><extent>The foliation is written in pencil, not circled, and can be found in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.The numbering commences at the title page with 1, 1A, 1B, 1C and 1D; then 2-23; 24 and 24A; 25-45; 46 and 46A; 47-110; 111, 111A and 111B; 112-154; 155 and 155A; 156-176; 177-178 are missing or skipped; 179-185; 186 and 186A; 187-215; 216 and 216A and then it carries on until 245, which is the fifth folio from the back of the volume.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The volume contains correspondence and telegrams between the Foreign Secretary to the Government of India and the Secretary of State for the Colonies in London, the Political Resident at Bushire, the Political Agent at Kuwait and and Eastern and General Syndicate Limited (E.&amp;G.S.) representatives. The main subject is the negotiations for oil concessions in Kuwait between APOC and Eastern and General Syndicate Limited, represented by Major Frank Holmes.The volume also includes some letters, in Arabic and in translation, from and to the Ruler of Kuwait, Shaikh Aḥmad al-Jābir Āl Ṣabāḥ, and correspondence regarging him being invited to visit London as guest of the Eastern and General Syndicate (folios 73-74). On folios 155A-166 'Final Record of a Meeting held at the Colonial Office on the 26th of April, 1933, to discuss various questions relating to Oil in the Persian Gulf', regarding Kuwait, Bahrain and Qatar.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Agent, Kuwait</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Emir of Kuwait</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Eastern and General Syndicate Limited, oil company</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Secretary of State for the Colonies, United Kingdom</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of India</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="personal"><namePart>Frank Holmes</namePart></name></subject><subject><geographic>Bahrain</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Kuwait</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Sitrah</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Sitra</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>New Delhi</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Sharjah</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Concessions, Oil, Kuwait</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000255#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>