<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100024054342.0x000026_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T22:19:28.933Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100024054342.0x000026_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/25, ff 21-22</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100024054342.0x000026</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private
            Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/25, ff 21-22</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Letter No 7 of 1822 from William Bruce, Resident at
               Bushire to Francis Warden, Chief Secretary to the Government, Political Department,
               Bombay</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1822/1822</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-10-02T10:59:25</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>2 folios</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The letter is reporting a complaint made by the Shaikh of
            Bahrain, Abdella bin Ahmed [‘Abdullāh bin Aḥmad Āl Khalīfah], against Rahma bin Jauber
            [Raḥmah bin Jābir]; the latter is accused of having launched two attacks against the
            Shaikh's people during the pearl diving season in 1821. It is further reported that
            the Shaikh of Bahrain claims he has put off retaliating through fear that his actions
            will be mistaken as piracy by the British, but explains that he has the means to do so
            should they consent to him taking action.A counter complaint presented to the Resident by Rahma bin
            Jauber's son is also being reported; it is claimed that a battile belonging to a
            tribe under Rahma bin Jauber's protection has been taken by the Shaikh of
            Bahrain's men.It is explained in the letter that the British will have
            difficulty restraining the mutual aggression of these two chiefs. It is also noted that
            it is going to be difficult to distinguish between piracy and acts of aggression (in
            other words, warfare), as defined by the British.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100024054342.0x000026#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>