<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00036f_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T23:45:00.897Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">m&amp;nmammmmmt o/t Bahrain. No % of 1926. Political Agency, Dabrain. Dated the 1st I.iay 1026. 1 (^)© From, ’ a j or* t 0 • i'- • Dal y» I..*,.fO.X«F.», Political Agent, Bahrain To, H.B.M *3. Consul, Danaecus. oir » I have the honour to request your find assistance on behalf of the Municipality of Marian eh of which Municipal Council the under-signed is an ex-officJo nerber. • r hen i^i Damascus last year, I noted that the houses were numbered (if I recollect correctly), with Arabic numerals on enamelled plates. Would you be so good as to inform me v/here such numerals for house numbering can be obtained,and,if possible, the cost thereof and if it would not be inconvenient might I trouble you to send me a sample number? I apologise for troubling you in this matter and your assistance will be much appreciated. I have the honour to be , Dir, Your most obedient servant, MaJor^C.I*E., H•B•M’s.Political Agent,6 c jbvr/asf V /♦/. ^ , -&gt;1 British consulate, Damascus, 27th July 1926. £) -'&lt;0 Sir, in reply to your letter dated the 1 st May last, I have the honour to confirm to you that the houses in Damascus are numbered with enamelled plates, bearing both Arabic and Roman numerals. These plates were obtained in I 9 I 9 from a certain Mr. rsac Kohn of Alexandria who is understood to be an Austrian. There is little doubt, therefore, that they were originally manufactured in central Europe. The cost of the supply of 31,000 plates to the Damascus Municipality worked out at 13.1/2 Egyptian piastres per plate. I enclose herewith a sample plate as requested. I am forwarding a copy of this letter together with another sample plate to the comptroller General, Department of overseas Trade, London, in case some British firm may be able to supply a similar article at a cheaper price, if any British fims are interested, they will no doubt communicate with you on this matter. I much regret the delay in replying to your enquiry. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your obedient servant, • f Major c.K. Daly, r. a. , C.I.E ff.B.M.'s political Agent, bahradt. H.M. Acting consul.% \ Ko. /e /4 of ipgg. Political Agency, Bahrein. Dated the 26th August 1928. Prom/ Major C*K.Daly, I.A.,O.I.E., Political Agent, Bahrein. To H.B.M's Consul» Danascue• Sir, I have the honour to acknowledge, with thanks, the receipt of a sample enamelled plate kindly sent with your letter dated the 27th July 1926. I am much obliged to you for your kind aosiptance. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant. Political Major, Agent, Bahrein.; . r't rlS ?V &gt;r.OCtO^ ' I^o. 3 / ^) 0 f 1926* British Residency &amp; Consulate-General, Bushire, the 28th September 1926, A copy of the undermentioned paper is forwarded to the Political Agent, Bahrein, for Information, with reference to letter dated the 27th July 1926 from His Majesty 1 s Acting Consul, Damascus, to l^aj or C.K.Daly, C • -l « xii • By order, Captain, Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian G u lf, Better Bo ,23568/1926, dated the 20th August 1926, from Department of Overseas ira&gt;de, Rondon, to the Under Secretary of State, India Office, L 0 ndon,(Received with India Office endorsement Bo. P.2787, dated the 26th A u gust 1926.) ^ / ^JT , LiAA, 1/u 1^6.— .Ml i—i IV. P.2787. 7 better from Department of Overseas Trade, dated 20th August 1926, Ho.23568/1926. Department of Overseas Trade, 35 Old Queen Street, Dondon, 3.7/. I. 20th August 1926. 3ir, I am directed by Hr. Michael 3amuel to inform you that a despatch has recently been received in this Department from the Acting British Consul at Damascus transmitting a copy of a letter which he had addressed on 27th *^uly last to Hjs Majesty’s Political Agent at Bahrein in reply to an enquiry from him as to the source whence Damascus house number plates were supolied. A copy of Ifr.Vaughan Bussell’s letter to Major Daly on the subject is transmitted to you herewith foi^our information. 2. ^Sfeple plates, which are enamelled(white figures on a royal blue background), similar to those sent to Bahrein from Damascus were enclosed in Mr. Acting Consul Vaughan Russell’s despatch in the hope that manufacturers in this country might be able to supply enamel plates of the requisite kind at suitable prices to the Political Agent at Bahrein. 3. These requirements were conveyed by this Department # to the Btocal Enamelled Tile and Iron Co., Ltd., of D&amp;llow Street, Burton-on-Trent s.nd to Messrs. Gamier &amp; Co., Ltd., of 84-5 P a rringdon Street, B.C.4. Replies were received from Messrs.Garnier &amp; Co., stating that they are having a sample made which they intend to submit with their quotation to Major Daly, and from the Stocal Bnameiled Tile The Under Secretary of State, Tndia Office, S.W.I.- II. Til© and Tron Co# 'to 'the ©fleet that they dre going very carefully into the matter and intend to write to I^ajor Daly with a view to securing the order if possible. 1 am therefore to request you to be so good as to instruct Hi s Majesty’s Political Resident in the Persian d^if to iniorm the Political Agent at Bahrein of the action taken on his enquiry to the Acting British Consul at Damascus, and of its result. 1 am, e oc., (Sd) Cecil C. Parrer, for the Comptroller-General. MAA.Eastern and General Syndicate Limited. BAHREIN AGENTS: A. &amp; M. YATEEM BROS. CABLE ADDRESS: Easgensynd, Bahrein.” ^ I'd ^ October 1925 CODE Broom HALLS To His Excellency, Shaikh Hamad bin Isa Al-Khalifa, Bahrein. Your Excellency, I returned to Bahrein a little over a v/eek ago and during this interval I have been engaged principally in observing the Manama Well which my company recently sank for Your Excellency^ Government. I would like to lay before Your Excellency a few points being my ovm opinion and that of the Company’s Geologists: Dr. A. Heim and Professor Madgwick,with regard to this Well and the sources from which the water is derived. and tapping the Spring Water Bearing Zone of Bahrein, having roughly as its centre the town of Manama. our Geologists found any evidence or indication of an artesian depression lying within the Water Bearing Zone on the Manama side This Well was sunk with the object of striking It is well to clearly understand that neither of of the island In order to avoid interfering with any existing P.T.O.( 2 ) supply of water on the Bahrein Island, the Manama Well, (as would be the case with other wells that Your Excellency may deem it wise to sink ), was located with a view to intercepting the Spring Waters doubt that the amount of this Spring Water which discharges int&amp; the sea must be very great. The object of any well-sinking must be to intercept and tap this water before it reaches the sea.In the Manama Well we have been successful in doing this as witnessed by the splendid flow of good quality water now issuing from this bore hole. order that sweeter water may be obtained than that which at first issued from the Manama Borehole, that the Borehole should be deepened to 600 feet. This suggestion if acted upon might have * far reaching and disastrous results. of Bahrein is supplied is without doubt quite fresh and pure where it enters upon its long underground journey to Bahrein* As this water nears the surface, it has to pass through a coral-limestone band heavily impregnated with sal^; and it is from this that it partly receives its salty contamination. The Waters of Bahrein travel from their source, underground and undersea between two which at present discharge into the sea. There can little It has been suggested ( by whom I do not Know), that in In order that Your Excellency may apprecite the dangers involved in this suggestion I would like to lay before Your the following considerations:- The source of the water from which the Water Bearing Zone P.T.O(an upper and a lower) impervious bands or layers of Strata. The impervious bands or layers of Strata are what keeps the Bahrein * Waters free from salt contamination, but not entirely free, small leakages of salt water into the fresh water channel as the fresh water approaches the surface are inevitable. The 'point to bo stressed is that to pierce by boring the lower band or layer of impervious Strata, ( above which the fresh water flows below the surface of the land and sea) would be to jeopardize the fresh water supply of the whole area adjacent to the borehole. The salt water would in my opinion be given access to the fresh water channel- and the harm done could hardly be calculated. I would also stress the fact that so long as boring operations are carried out under Government control, expert advice, and supervision,there is not the slighest danger that any harm can be done. In fact by the judicious boring of wells, the fres&amp; water supply of the Bahrein Islands could be greatly augmented and much of the fresh water now flowing to waste into the sea could be intercepted and utilised for both drinking and irrigation purposes. Promiscuous boting for fresh water on the Bahrein Islands by irresponsible persons should be strongly discouraged by the Bahrein Govemmentand boring only allowed under permit from the Government, and carried out under expert supervision. Ot-herv/ise, should the lower impervious Strata be pierced and uncontrolled salt water admitted to the fresh water channel the harm done may well be irreparabl e. It should be recgnised by P.T.O.(4) law that the fresh waters below ground are the property of the Bahrein Government and should be controlled as such. It is inevitable when water is first struck by means of a borehole as was the case with the Manama Well, that the water will contain a large percentage of salt. This is due to the fact that the rocks, through which the borehole passes to reach the Water Bearing Channel, are heavily impregnated with salt. Before the water struck can be freed of salt the borehole and rocks adjacent thereto have to be washed or scoured out by the water rising in the bferehole. The process of scouring the borehole to fre*e it from salt is a gradual one and takes several months to perform, large amount of salt; but after flowing freely for several months and thus given time to scour the salt out of the borehole, the salt contents of the water have gradually decreased, and the small amount of salt still present in the Manama Well water v/ill almost disappear during the next twelve months and the water will thus become still better for drinking purposes. few months the water becoming less salty and almost free after flowing a This has been demonstrated in the Manama Well. When the water was first encountered in this Well it contained a It will however always contain a trace of salt and magnesi which is owing to a slight contamination of the Spring Water previc us to their entering the borehole. This contamination, which is very slight, as Your Excellency will see is beyond human control. In conclusion I would point out to Your Excellency that P.T.O.T (5) my advice is to have a valve placed on the Llanama Well and so make it possible to control the flow of water. The water at present issuing from the Manama Well is very good and will continue to improve as time goes on. My Company feels sure that Your Excellency will recognize that it has carried out both the letter and the spirit of its contract in regard to this Well, after a controlling valve has been affixed thereto. I cannot oppose too strongly any suggestion that the Manama * • Well should be deepened. This involves such serious risks not only to the water of the Manama Well but also to xka adjacent waters that my Company would not feel justified in carrying out the work of deepening either the Manama Well or any other well sunk within the Bahrein Water Bearing Zone without first securing from Your Excelleh . -cy and Your Excellency’s Government most stringent guarantees that my Company would not be in any way responsible, should disaster result from such work. In my opinion, and it is also that of the Company’s Geologist -s any prospecting for fresh water at a greater depth should be done outside the Bahrein Water Bearing Zone as at present located. The writer considers that there is a fair chance of success in finding an independent supply of fresh water at■a depth outside the Spring Water Area. One place for instance where one may expect to be successful in finding a deeper supply of fresh water is the Sakhir and Hanani area. This water it is considered likely would P.T.O( 6 ) / © be of an artesian depression source and no£ Spring Water; however there can be no guarantee of succes o in this work. Your Excellency may wonder why the depth of 600 feet was mentioned in the contract as the limit (if necessary owing to having failed to strike water before reaching that depth) to which the two Wells contracted for should be sunk. The reason was this that until a bore had been put down it was unknown at what horizon the upper impervious layer of strata would be encountered. It was calculated that the depth v/ould be approximately 300 feet below the surface, but to insure against disappointment the depth of 300 feet was doubled, hence the depth of 600 feet arrived at. The l.lanama Well demonstrated that the upper impervious Strata lies at a depth of about 200 feet and that at a depth of from 200 tp 240 feet a good supply of fresh water exists. The depth of the lower band or layer of impervious Strata is below 240 feet and we know that c we can pierce into the water boring channel between 30 and 40 feet without touching the lower impervious strata. This is the excellent and useful information that the boring of the Manama Well has added to our knowledge of the Bahrein Water Bearing Zone. To drill wells within small limits any deeper than the Manama Well is to take undue risks which are/ not justified in an£ way, as there is no evidence or indication, within the Bahrein Water Bearing Zone, as at present located and defined that any additional fresh water supply exists below the supply already encountered and which has given such excellent results, both as P.T. 0.I(7) regards the quality and quantity of the water in the Manama Well. Trusting that this letter may be clear to Your Excellency, and should Your Excellency require further information I shall be glad to supply it. I have the honour to remain, Sir, Your Obedient Servant,Of 1927 Ho • Political Agency, Bahrain, Dated the June, 1927. To The Adviser, Bahrain Ltate, Bahrain. hEMORAHDUM . Please find herewith an application in original dated the 18th June, 1927, (which please return) fron Messrs Goverdhandas Dharandas and Co., conplaintng about Baladiyah subordinates* in connection with weighnent of rice.Ho, of 1346 Of floe of the Adviser to the Government, Bahrain, Bated 3rd Maharam, 1346. To The H. 3, M 1 s Political Agent, Bahrain, Memorandum . With reference to your letter Bo. 532/27 of the 29th June 1927, I enclose herewith cheque for Bs. 6/-, Rupees Six Only, being telegraphic charges incurred by you on behalf of the State. Adviser to the Government, Bahrain,No .571 Of 1927, Politipal Ag«ioy, Bahrein 1 1 ^ Datad the ' ^ July 1927. 0 ) ill &amp; r To The Adviser , Bahrein State, Bahrein. Memorandura . I acknowledge,with thanks, the receipt of a cheque for Re.6/- sent with your raeraorandura No.8/1316 dated the T rd Muharran 1345. Captain, Political Agent, Bahrein. f : 'i 2 ^Ml S\ No © Secretariat. Bahrain. Dated To. H.B.M’s Political Agent. Bahrain. c UEUnRANBUM. yY' A With reference to your Memo No 526 of 25/6/27. I beg to inform you that I have enquirejd carefully into the complaint of Messrs Goverdhandas Dharan^rs and I am of the opinion that their complaint is unjustiiied and that they . imported short weight rice and were treated fairly and accord to the rules of the Biladya. I have seen all the documents referred to and have discussed the matter with the committee of merchants who attend to questions of rice shortage. The complainVants themselves signed the weighing slip which showed that in the five bags which were weighed there was a total shortage of 17/i lbs. As there was no doubt about this the board did not rew r eigh the rice. When the importers themse€w6o admit and sign for the shortage there is no reason for a second weighing. The statement about the consignment of Abdul Aziz Bassam is entirely incorrect. In the first place his import was flour, in this there was a small shortage, 7/^ lbs in 5 bags, for which he paid a fine of Rs 12/8. Some other bags of his, containing an entirely different import, were released at once. I have seen the accounts relating to tnis and they bear out the statement of the Committee. The matter of weighing R.E. imports has been replied to before. It has been decided that the same rules shall apply to R.E. imports as in the case of other imports. This was agreed upon by the Municipality with full approval of the Govt. In order to prevent these constant complaints l have suggested that an official of the Customs staff shall be present at the weighing who, as well as the Importer and the Mumcipai clerk, will sign the weight certificate. If the complainant can be sent to me I will tell him again what my Opinion is of his complaint. Adviser. db - Bahrain State. l ^ t ^ * '-r i- 7/ .GOVERUMENT OF BAHRAIN x/u. t j.uuxi x\«.ux ajl xnany To Bahrain. Sir, I have the honour to inform you that at a recent meeting of the Manama Municipal Council an order was passed that all dogs, privately owned, should he licensed. Licenses, in the shape of metal numbered discs, oan he obtained from the Municipality on nayment of Rg. 5/- each, this being the annual amount. Steps are being taken to destroy all unlicensed rfiWOV/^ tsr-i 1 T 'K/-N -Cf . I have the honour to be, Sir, Your Obedient Servant, Adviser to the Government, Bahrain. l^/lO&gt;% ~ar- Bahrein Bated the 8th September 1929. To, .-V x E.B.M*s Political Agents, BAHREIN. 'Sir, / 0 V 2- With reference to the Z% Baladeyah Surtax collected by the Director of Customs,on their behalf on the import of tobacco and its • products we the undersigned most respectfully beg to submit that on the 10th and the 15th August last,we had communicated with the Directo: of the Customs on the subject,and the attached are the true copies of the Director’s reply which now forward for your honours perusal. In this connection we would draw your honours attention to the fac that since the Customs duty on all imports of cargoes other than the tobacco and its products is baised upon the rate of 5#ad volarem we therefore can not see any reason as to why there should be an additio nal surtax on the tobacco and its products and we would emphatically say that this is nothing but an injuctice to have such a tax imposed on a particular commodity and let the other commodities free from such an imposition. Under the circumstances explained above,and in accordance with the Director’s letter of the 13th August last, the last paragraph of which reads as •THAT THE TAX SI THEREFORE A MUNCIPAL TAX,AND NOT THE GOVERNMENT TAX* we the undersigned therefore shall feel extremly grat eful if you will kindly move this matter on our behalf with the Balad eyah , Manamah and have this additional tax removed,as soon as possible Applogizing for intruding upon your honour valuable time and for the trouble given. We beg to remain, Sir, Your most obedient Servants yBahrein 11th August 1929 r“N / The Director Of Customs &amp; Port Officer, B A H B E I B. Dear Sir, We shall he glad if you will kindly inform us whether the Z% tax collected in addition to the ordinary 5% Duty on the i~ mpolrt of tobacco and Cigarettes,is the State Government Tax or the Municipal Tax. We shall he glad to know whether the instructions for th&lt; Z% extra tax collected hy you are from the State Government or from the local Municipality? Thanking You in anticipation. We are, Dear sir, Yours PaitfullyNO. G/ 16/108 THE CUSTOMHOUSE, BAHREIN, 13th AUGUST,1929. 8th R/AWAL,1348, (g) ft Messrs. Abdulla Aujan &amp; Brothers, And Other Merchants, r\ G-entlemen, I have to thank you Tor your communication of 1 the 10th instant which relates to the Baladiah Surtax of charged in al imports of tobacco and its products, and to inform you that this tax was imposed 'by the Baladiah Council of Manamah, and was noti fied to the Customs for collection by their NO.281/5 of 1346. The tax is therefore a municipal tax, and not a state Government tax. t am, Gentlemen, Yours faitfully Director Of Customs And Port Officer, BAHREIN. wa£&amp;Bahrein 14th Agust 1929. The Director Of Customs And Port Officer, BAHREIN. Dear Sir^ We are in receipt of your favour No. C/16/108 of the 15th instant and thank you very much for the information contai ned therein. as the tax referred to therein is only Municipal Tax and and has nothing to do with the state Covernment Tax, We shall he glad to know whether you would allow us delivery of the Tobacco and its products without our paying the same. Thank ink You in anticipation, We are,Dear Sirs, Yours faitfully, ABDULLA AUJAN &amp; BROTHERS ON BEHALF OF THEMSELVES AND OTHER AIGNATORIES. /The Custom House, BAHREIN Elst August, 1929 16th R/Awal, 1348 No» 19/1 22&gt; Messrs. Ahdulla Aujan &amp; Brothers, and other signatories, BAHREIN.. Grentlemen, of tohacco imports on which full Customs dues have 'been paid and in regard to the surtax of two per cent thereon, levied 1 the Municipality of Manamah, and collected hy the Customs on their hehalf; I have enquired im to this, and I understand t] the resolution for this surtax was passed hy the Manamah Bali iah with t.‘ surtax, or the mannef in which it is levied, the Best course would he for you to address a petition on the subject to H.B.Mfc f Political Agent, Bahrein. In reference to your letter regarding the delivery I am Gentlemen Yours I’aitfully BIBECTOB OF CUSTOMS AKB PORT OFFICER BAHREINt V ~~ '@) Ho. of 19:39. The Political Ajency, Bahrein, Dated the izffi eptembor ||B . Forwarded in original ( to be returned) to the Adviser Bahrein Croveminent, Balirein, for information and favour of any remarks he may have to offer# Indian Assistant, ^ In the absence of the 0 '' Political Agent,Bahrein, Peietien dated 8th September lS. f j9, : rom Messrs Abdulla Aujan A Bros., and others, \ 'Cfi ^ GOVERNMENT OF BAHRAIN. No. So t 3* Of 1348 Office of 3 Adviser to the GovernFient, Bahrain. Dated, 14th R/ihany 1348 To H. B. M f s Political Agent, Bahrain. Memorandum Tith reference to the enclosed petition which I return. The tax is a municipal one and was instituted with the approval of the then acting Political 2 .gent Cantsin £L Iban. I admit that owing to the method of collecting it, it may appear to be an infringement of the agree ment by which the Bahrain Government guarantees that the customs rates shall be only 5%. I suggest that the tax should be collected entirely by the Municipal authorities. I understand that the Hon f ble the Political Resident expressed his views on the subject last summer, so I suggest that the mat J er should be referred to him. Adviser to the Government, Bahrain. Enclos.Sk K. 4J 1929 Office of the Political Agent,Bahrain* Dated KaraaHi 30 th Sep*;taber*1929» (US) To The Advisor, Dahrain Goverrment, Bahrain* &amp;oa ora r*durq/ Please refer to your letter Ho. 506/3 dated the I4tl B/Thani 1349 . The is^poeition of the Salad 1 yah our tax of 7f$ on tobacco is corjtrnry tc th^j Treaty obii^atiwna of the Bahrain Governrcnt arid c-innot be continued in its present foi*a. I would be gl*:.d if you wovad instruct the Director of Cuctoisit to discontinue its collection at a date convenient to you, and infona tli-, .b.sladiyah accorctirgly. Should they desire to collect it themeel^ee in come other form, they will no doubt move the Bahrain Government in the matter* ' 71 . Political Agent,Bahrain* P: A •H* 0 s^ /3 h \ -i A y t...BAHREIN, 5th November 1929. To. H.B.M's Political Agent Bahrein. Respected 'sir / ' Tfe, the -undersigned, merchants of Bahrein, humbly and respectfully beg to submit that the new orders issued by the Director of Customs with regard to the inspection of Rice, Tobacco and Grhee by the Lfiinicipality, if put into practice, will cause us detention, trouble, inconvenience and loss, as we would explain below:- ' • 1 pect the goods by the Municipality means nothing but delay and trouble to us, as we have to go in search of the officer in charge of this duty in each individual case. He is seldom to be found readily and when found he has some excuse or the other of his own to delay the inspection. (2) . Wh*n the goods (especially Rice and tobacco) are put out from the shed and awaiting inspection by the Muncipal Officer it entails risk by having the goods lying in the open exposed in rainy season, as in case of sudden rain, they get damaged and heavy loss is caused. (3) . Once the goods, particularly Rice, are weighed and appraised by the Customs Authorities, we do not see any further need for the same procedure to be repeated again by the Baladiyah, but on the contrary it is merely a source of extra trouble to us. (4) As regards Ghee, we have no objection to the inspec— ^i orL ' 3 T 'the Municipality as there is every possibility of mixed ghee being imported from Basra and other places, but this should be done^without the necessity of our having to go in search of the Municipality Officers. order of the Customs may For this act of kindness we shall ever remain grateful.L No PA/G/.^^4$ H.B.M's Political Agent BAHREIN. THE CUSTOMHOUSE, BAHREIN. 5th November, 1929. 3rd J/Thania, 1348. S) m MEMORANDUM: - 'n ^ * In view of the interest taken by the Manamah Baladiah in' (1) collection of a local octroi rate on tobacco, (2) the prevention of sale of mixed ghee in Manamah and (3) weighment and inspection of bags of rice brought for sale in Manamah, I was requested to make suitable arrangements for the Baladiah 1 s inspection of these imports, after such had been passed by the Customs; and I accordingly took the simplest method of asking the KaHamah importers to lodge a triplicate copy of the Bill of Entry with the Baladiah, so that their officials might make such inspections etc., as they may wish. I published a notice to this effect, a copy of which I lodged at the Political Agency for your information. I understand that certain merchants have lodged with you a protest against this Customs Order on the ground that an inspection etc of these imports by the Manamah Baladiah officials would cause them some inconvenience, and asking that the order may be withdrawn. In this connection I should like to remark that I have no desire at all to make any unnecessary regulation which might hinder the speedy and simple clearance of cargo; and I am most anxious not to be concerned in local municipal concerns. The reason for issuing the order was an act of neighbourly courtesy to the Manamah Baladiah to assist them, and, I hope, to simplify their inspection of goods brought into the town of Manamah for sale retail, and no more. I can of course appreciate that the local tradesmen would not wish their business affairs to be known too much outside the Customs, and possibly this is the reason for their action. DflSjCTOR OF CUSTOMS, and PORT OFFICER. BAHREIN. sla / 1 &lt;Uv No. / of 1929. The Political Agency, Bahrain# Dated the ^ Ma November 1929# To The Merchants, Bahrain# G-entlemen, I have read your memorial with attention and have to say in reply that I understand the Municipality are willing to alter their arrangements to meet your wishes to some extent. it is your business to bring home as forcibly as possible to the members you have elected, that they are acting contrary to your wishes and that you hold them responsible for actions which are injurious to you in your business# you should approach them and continue to press your points home until they modify them# Unless the Public bestir themselves in these matters they cannot expect me to do so# I wish you to clearly understand, however, that If you wish to make them amend proposed bye-laws, lours faithfully. Political Agent, Bahrain#</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00036f_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1208</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00036f</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1208</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 6/4 Stores for the Bahrain Municipality; Municipal Tax and Dues'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1925/1929</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-08-26T18:08:12</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (47 folios)</extent><extent>The file is arranged chronologically from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 49; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 4-28; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.A previous foliation sequence, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains correspondence relating to administrative, legal, and fiscal matters connected to the Manama Municipality. The correspondence is between the Political Agency at Bahrain, British Consulate at Damascus, Manama Municipality (also referred to as the Baladiyah), Political Residency in the Persian Gulf, Adviser to the Government of Bahrain (Charles Dalrymple Belgrave), Frank Holmes of Eastern and General Syndicate Limited, Director of Customs and Port Officer at Bahrain, and a number of Bahrain merchants.The file covers several matters, including:the sourcing and purchase of numerals for housing and street signs in the town;complaints by merchants about customs procedures and the imposition of surtaxes by the municipality;numerous orders of the municipality, such as licensing for dogs, lighting for boats and bicycles, and calls for offers to build a new road in Manama.Folios 12-18 are a report into water sources and quality, and suggested methods of extraction, by Frank Holmes on behalf of Eastern and General Syndicate Limited.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Municipal government</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>British Consulate, Damascus</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Manamah Municipality</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Eastern and General Syndicate Limited, oil company</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Persian Gulf Political Residency</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="personal"><namePart>Frank Holmes</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Manama</geographic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00036f#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>