<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000419.0x000179_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-05-23T15:42:11.535Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">NOT FOR DIRECT PHOTOCOPYING COPIES MAY BE ORDERED FROM pmo The causes of our expulsion from Kerman were, in my opinion, three-told I. Our weakness in Teheran. II. The pernicious example of the evacuation of Isfahan. III. Our weakness in Kerman. I. Our weakness in Teheran has to ao with hifh politics’’. I only know that the result in the provinces was that no definite, explicit orders could he obtained from Teheran in support of our side. When - after much telegraphing and conversations over the wire, we did get an order, it was vague and general in its terms, and so worded that anything or nothing could be made out of it, according as the reader wished. H. It may have been a political necessity for us to evacuate Isfahan, but it is undoubtedly true that this evacuation gave the Persians the idea of clearing us oat. If v/e had not set the example in .Isfahan, I am convinced that the Persians would never have thought of it. It true that the advanced party in Persian politics had discussed - as a kind of unattainable and hopeless ideal- the thought of their country being let alone m political matters by England and Russia, but this, I think, had very little to do with clearing out ohe various foreign communities in the different towns o Persia. III. In Kerman our position has been undemined by our lack of information as to what was going on m Persia. It was not thought worth while to keep us informed, for instance$ (S' instance, as to wliy we had. taken Bushin©* Conset^uenolj,' we had no information to give our Persian friends when they asked us about it. The Germans and the local newspapers gave out that we had taken the pla.c© bj/ xoroc-, and, in the taking, had killed so many hundred Mahornedsn men, women and children, taken some hundreds away on ships, and our soldiers had violated innumerable Mahomedan women and girls. To all this we had no answer to give. We knew that we had taken Bushire, and that was all we knew. Consequently, when our Persian friends asked us 'What’s this? Are the English become as great thieves as the Russians now? Why have you stolen our town of Bushire?' We had, perforce, to remain dumb. Whilst the German was distributing; his ’news’ free to the Persians’ houses twice daily, the British Consul cut off the Rs.10 monthly which he had been contributing towards the cost of distributing a summary oi Reuter’s telegrams in Peisian, saying he had been ordered to retrench. Kerman was thus left, at a critical time, without any distribution of our news among the Persians. I offered to undertake the work of answering the German lying placards which were daily pasted on the City gates, if the Consul would bear the expense. But he would not agree, saying the Persians did not believe the German placards. The trouble is that they did believe them, and, as they had no contrary information, there is no reason why they should not have believed them. Our Consul too was undoubtedly weak. He wa.s not in good health, and appeared to be on the verge of a nervous breakdown.breakdown. He scarcely ever ventured out of the Consulate, and never was out after sunset. He conducted all his business with the Governor General throu^i the Hawab, whom no one trusted. The Governor General seemed to think that he could, do as he liked with Colonel Ducat, and certainly he got a goodly sum of money out of him under one pretence and another.12 Telegram, No. 966, dated the sddtk (received 27thj April 1916. From—M ajor A. P. Trevor, C.I.E., Deputy Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, | ^ To—The Secretary to the Goverlment of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Simla. My telegram, dated 25th Apri^ 965, has been repeated to Sykes. | 121 Telegram P., No. 268 C., daied the 26th (received 27th) April 1916. From—His Britannic MajestyVConsul, Sistan, To—The Secretary to the Gover|ment of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Simla (repeated $o Baluchistan). Baluchistan telegram of April|24th, and your telegram, 107 S., of the 26th April, if 1 were in toucn «ritn Byer, I would certainly have referred to him, but all I have received iiom him since April 4th is one belated en clair and one undecypherabie message. Two recent telegrams from Kerman seem to show that all may not be ufell there, as Governor urges Sykes to come quickly and &amp;r-Governor refuses to leave. There might certainly be risk for small party in these circumstances. There is really no cause for^ anxiety in Sistan and Kain. Levies are perfectly contented. Even Baluch raiders, I am told,We addicted to firing in the air. Dehaneh Baghi is now in telegraphic communication with Bam and Kerman so i hope to get early news through Eahreh abiut .Rigan. 122 No. 647, dated Karachi, the 14th (received 22nd) April 1916. P rom The Director, Persian Gulf Section, Indo-European Telegraph Department, To The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment. I have the honour to forward, for your information, a copy of a Beport on the Evacuation of Kerman, submitted by Mr. J. W. Tanner, Superintendent in this Department. Enclosure. Report on the Evacaation of Kerman Station submitted by Superintendent J. W. Tanner. Pheliminaey. To understand clearly the events which lead up to the evacuation of Kerman, or, to be more correct, the expulsion of the British and .Russian colonies from Kerman, it is necessary to understand something about the principal persons concerned. (1) The Governor-General of Kerman provinces, Sardar Zafiar, a Bakhtiari. He was sent to Kerman, 1 understand, by request of the British Minister, Tehran, and was supposed to be strongly pro-British. Beyond giving us guards for the Telegraph and Bank buildings and for the personal protection of the Manager, imperial Bank of Persia, and myself during the last tew days in Kerman, and providing us with an escort to the coast, he did absolutely nothing for us or for the British cause. He was exceedingly prolific in promises out never translated his words into actions. I think everyone in Kerman, except perhaps the British Consul, was convinced that the Governor-General was taking money from both sides. A neutralAgainst all levies in Sistan simultaneous action should be taken. Simply disbanding these men will only result in forming a body of discontented armed men no doubt of poor spirit but despite this with power for mischief owing to their possession of arms. Disarming these levies may stir up the feeling of the country against us, but the men Will be rendered more or less harmless. Half-hearted measures, so it seems to me, should not be adopted at a time like the present. The Consul has-been asked by me to advise whether any immediate military measures are necessary with regard to the position in Sistan. Addressed Chief, General Staff, Simla ; repeated General Staff, Quetta. * 117 Telegram P., No. 109 S., dated th^ 26th April 1916. From—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, Simla, T 0 —Lieutenant-Colonkl Sir Percy Sykes, K.C.I.E., C.M.G., Bunder Abbas (repeated to Sir P. Cox, Basrah, Major Trevor, Bushire, and Minister, Tehran). Presence of a large party of Germans at Rigan is reported by Dow- subsequent to their defeat at Kerman. 118 Telegram P., No. 317-223-0, dated the 23rd April 1916. From—-The General Officer Commanding, Force “ D ”, A. H. Q., through Basrah, To—The Chief of the General Staff, Simla. ; Clear line. Tinder No. 1873 B., dated 22nd April, General Officer Com manding, Bushire, wires as follows :— Begini. Please send to Colonel Twigg, Commanding detachment for (of ?) Bunder Abbas, any instructions you have for him direct to Bunder Abbas, as he would like to know something of what he is to do when he gets there and from whom he is to take his orders. Bad weather has delayed embarkation, but to-morrow evening detachment will probably leave here. Ends. Will you please communicate direct with Colonel Twigg at Bunder Abbas, as this detachment is outside the sphere of action of Dorce &lt;s D This telegram, which is addressed to Chief, General Staff, with reference to his 47830, dated April 10th, has been repeated to Bushire with reference to No. 317—218-0 of 1-lth April, in which was contained a precis of the telegram from Chief, General Staff, No. 47^30, referred to above, and to General Headquarters, with reference to telegfam of 23rd April, No. 68—0. Telegram P., No. 1879 B.-M., datedHhe 23rd April 1916. From—The General Officer Commanding, Bustoire, To—The Chief of the General Staff, Simla, i The following, addressed Chief, General Siaff, Simla, has been repeated to General Headquarters. JForce for Bunder Abbas sails to-night perfH. T. “ Campanello 119 Telegram P., No. 50236, dated th$ 24th April 1916. From—The Chief of the General Staff, Simla To— Lieutenant-Colonel Sik Percy Sykes, K.C.I.E., C.M.G., Bunder Abbas. The communication which follows is for ^lolonel Twigg and also for your information: Begins. You and the detachrpent under your command will come under the orders of Brigadier-General S| ~ ~ ' arrive at Bunder Abbas. Ends. r P. Sykes from the time youIS subiect who was in a position to know and in whom I have great confidence, when discussing the matter told me most emphatically, ‘ I know he is doing 80 ’\ (2) The “ Karguzar ”, Mostam-ul-Mulk. The Karguzar is an official appointed hy the Persian Government to faci litate business between Persians and Foreign subjects. This man was strongly anti-Foreign and later became more particularly anti-English. t . Instead of facilitating business with foreigners he impeded it by such acts as instructing Persian debtors how to declare themselves bankrupt with regard to their British creditors, and sending a Pars! debtor to take “Bast ” (religious sanctuary) in the house of a Persian Mulla. Finally no European merchant could deal with him and requests were made by the British and Russian .Con suls for his dismissal. But this man had a father-in-law in the Foreign Office at. Tehran, and for two years or more it proved to be beyond the powers of the British and Russian Ministers in Tehran to obtain the dismissal of this obnoxious official. Reference to my weekly and other political reports during the years 1914-15 and 1915-16 will show that I was continually representing the danger to British interests accruing through this official being allowed to J e mam m Kerman, and mv reports throughout the summer of 1915 intimated that he was politically active in the German interests, and was doing our cause much harm. (3) Hossein Ali, “Mofatish ” (Inspector) of the Post-office. This young man, speaking French fluently, was sent on a tour ^ of inspec tion of the Post Offices throughout Persia by M. Molitor, the Belgian lost- Master-Geueral of Tehran. Soon after his arrival m Kerman he began to mix in political matters. He was strongly anti-Foreign. In the first interview that I had with him, before there was any trouble in Persia he suggested to me that it would be better for Persia if all Europeans cleared out of the country and left Persians to manage their own affairs. This man was a great friend, I believe a relative, of the Karguzar. After he had succeeded in dismissing the Post Master of Kerman, he himself always opened the post-bag, took out what letters he liked, and, accompanied by the Karguzar, took them to the so-called German Consul’s house. °I reported these matters to the Director, Persian Section, and that this Inspector was mingling in political matters, and was becoming a source of danger to us. M. Molitor replied to me through the Directoi, Persian Section, “ J’ai parfait confiance en lui The sequel will show that this confidence was not justified. (4) The Rais-i-Mo’aref, the master of the boys’ school set up in opposition to the C. M. S. school. This man was strongly “ Democratic ” and actively anti-British. (The term “ Democrat ” in Persia implies “ revolutionary or Anarchist. Ihus the political murders committed in Tehran in connection with the start of the con stitutional movement were all committed by so-called ‘ Democra s. ) The Rais-i-Mo’aref was close friends with the Karguzar and the Post Office Inspector, and attended all seditious meetings in Kerman. (5) The Gendarme native officer. The Swedish officers with the bulk of the Gendarme force left Kerman in the snrin 0, of 1915 leaving some 60 or 70 men under the charge of a native officer. This officer soon displayed anti-British proclivities, and at our request he was relieved by another native officer sent from bhiraz. This man was also pro-German. He came to Kerman m charge of an escort that brought some Germans from Shiraz to Kerman vi&amp; Lake Nens, with a deviation south of the regular road on a visit to some tribes. Be regarded himself as the servant of the Germans, sending detachment of Gendarmes as escort with any German who travelled trom Kerman.G =1 1 LU The Gendarme force in Kerman was not under the orders of the Governor- General, and he professed to have no control whatever over it. He also said the Gendarme officer openly opposed him, and applied to Tehran that the force might be withdrawn from Kerman entirely. Several times in my weekly political reports I called attention to the dangerous pro-German activities of this Gendarme officer. ' ' * ’ ‘ — - (G) The Rais-i-Tahdid was also mentioned as having taken an active part in the events that led up to our expulsion from Kerman. I had no dealings with him and am not aware what part he took. (7) Herr Zugmayer who came to Kerman as the German Consul, but held no exequatur and was unable to obtain one from Tehran. The Governor-General at first refused to permit him to enter the town arranging a house for him outside the wall. But after threatening to use force if necessary to prevent the German from taking possession of a house in town he withdrew his opposition when the German showed a bold front, and with drew the men he had posted to bar his progress. The Governor-General also, at first, refused to permit the German fla*? being hoisted, but the flag was actually flying over the “ Consulate ” for several weeks before we left Kerman. » I0r Zugmayer some years back, spent some time in Baluchistan as a naturalist and visited our Panjgur station. He is said to have a knowledge of the Baiuch language and to possess first class maps of Baluchistan and Sisrnn. He occupied himself in Kerman with enlisting men, and kept posters on l 6 SlfoKcTassel i- 11 ' 6 ““ t0 apply t0 him for * (a) Men with their own horses and rifles.—Pay Krs. 240 monthly. ($) Men with horses but no rifles.—Pay Krs. 180 monthly. (c) Men with rifles but no horses.—Pay Krs. 120 monthly. As far as I am aware, Herr Zuarmayer **plaved the r a aware that he took any action against us. ° ‘ am no ^ influence on the revolutionary party who demanded our expulsion? 168 ‘ amWS Section II. Events that led up to the evacuation, shots^at kflle^^rukh^haK'c^mSn oft^e^A^ii^KhanT 38 aWakeDed ^ .the 0 ^ 1 ^an Lmed^scorrHe'hiLefl h°‘ t0 S ° int ° ^ ^ ^ ViSit8 ’° r and v.iKrtlif - SeveduS who^itua^Tf 61 ^ WCnt t0 the and to sleep at his house that night IhTsliT t0 St ^., t0 L People who Enow him describe him as enthvW a ctlara cter. a T^r s t ri? d f H shof - s «i ““'parukh^ShahT'a 1110 ' ^IdT’ t0 d° k Consulate!^ haruKh bhah in a moriband condition was tak-Pn fi i Assistant burgeon F, G. Steinhofl. Hr. Hodson tZ rM q h ° USe ot our and agreed with Dr. Steinhofl that notnine- could ht doctor » vvas man, who died about two hours after beinf shot t0 SaVG the W0UIlde(i Surgeon Steinhoff was at the Consulate when evenin ^ Assistant calling on the Consul with reference to the murder Governor-General wasDr. Steinhoff afterwards came and reported to me that to his surprise there was evidently no intention on the part of the Governor-General to apprehend the murderers, who were said to be well-known. » 1 • Recognising that if this were the case the lives of the other British subjects would not be safe, I interviewed several members of the British Colony, and it was agreed that I should see the Consul and impress upon him, on behalf of the colony, the necessity of strong action being taken to appre hend the murderers. Accompanied by Dr. Steinhoff I called on the Consul on Wednesday, 8th December, and laid these matters before him, pointing out that things were developing badly in Kerman for the British cause. The local Persian newspaper was daily vilifying our country and stirring up bitter feelings against us. The German was posting lies on every gate of the city [the latest being that the English and Russian Ministers had fled from Tehran and that they had reached Kasvin wdth their respective colonies. That the Baluchis had captured 6,000 British (not native) soldiers, that the Turks were about to retake Basrah and that the Bank of England had been destroyed.] I concluded by asking the Consul if we — the British Colony — could do anything to strengthen his hands. The Consul replied that he had done all he could think of but that he could get nothing done. The Governor-General was lavish in promises, but when action was required he failed to take it, requiring explicit orders from the Cabinet at Tehran before doing anything. Such orders were not forthcoming, hence nothing was done. It was decided that the Governor-General should be invited to meet representatives of the British Colony at the Consulate on Eriday, the 10th. I reported to representatives of the colony the results of my interview with the Consul, and the colony drafted a message to His Britannic Majesty’s Minister through the Director, Persian Section, explaining the situation, pointing out the danger that was looming ahead, and asking that the Consul’s hands should be strengthened and that urgent and explicit orders should be wired to the Governor-General instructing him to take immediate and urgent steps to apprehend the murderers of Earukh Shah and to take such other action requisite for maintaining order in the town, assuring the safety of British subjects, and the maintenance of British prestige. On Eriday evening representatives of the colony met the Governor- General at the Consulate. As spokesman for the party, I put the following points to him and quote his replies thereto:— I That our fellow subject and friend, Earukh Shah, had been murdered in his Governorship, and that, although the murderers were well-known, no steps had apparently been taken for their arrest. I pointed out the danger that must inevitably arise to other British subjects if this murder was left unavenged, or ignored, by the representative of the Persian Government. I asked°him to offer a reward for the apprehension of the murderers. He replied that he was doing all in his power. He said he had sent men in several directions following up clues and hoped soon to make some arrests. He accepted my suggestion and said that next morning the town should he placarded with notices offering a reward of Krans 3,000 for the production of the murderers of Earukh Shah, either dead or alive. II I requested him to call out the Persian subjects who were being enlisted and armed by the Germans, asking him “Against whom are these men being armed ? It against Persians, then you, as the representative of the Persian Government, must interfere and compel their disarmament. If they were being armed against Poreign subjects, t lien again he should interfere, as Persia is not at war with any country, and no foreigner had a right to arm Persians against another Poreign friendly nation. I asked him if he knew what would happen to him, supposing he went to Germany and tried to enlist and am Germans against Germans or againstsome nation with which Germany was at peace ? He replied that failing orders from Tehran he could do nothing in this matter. Moreover, the affair was now too big for him, as the Germans had as many men as he had, and if he acted against them there would be much bloodshed. I retorted that it was scarcely possible to dam a river when it was in flood but it was easily confined at its source. The arming of the German retainers had been carried out under his own eyes and he had taken no steps to prevent it. III. I asked him to arrest and deport the Karguzar, Inspector of Posts, Rais-i-Mo’aref and others, and to get the Gendarmes removed from Kerman* arguing that these were matters within his power as Governor. These people* were working against the peace and welfare of his Governorship; it was his business to maintain order and to arrest all sedition-mongers, and special powers or explicit instruction were not required. He replied that as regards the individuals named he could not arrest them without clear and explicit orders from the Cabinet at Tehran. But as regards the Gendarmes he had already requested their withdrawal, and orders had been received for their transfer to Ispahan and that they were now engaged in selling their furniture, &amp;c., by auction. IV. I asked him to stop the Germans from placarding the town with their lies regarding the internal affairs of Persia. I produced, and Dr. Stein- hoff read, one of their latest notices in which the statement was made that the English and Russian Ministers with their colonies had fled from Tehran. I asked if he believed that this was true ? He replied that he knew it was untrue. I pointed out that, being posted on the city gates, these notices had, or appeared to have, his official sanction and were doing British interests incalculable harm in this city. In reply he promised that he would prohibit the placarding of the notices in future, and that if they were posted he would order the police to tear them down. V. We asked him why he permitted the local paper to vilify our country in the manner it did almost daily. He promised to send for the Editor as soon as he got back to his house, and prohibit the publication of such articles in future under pain of confisca tion of the paper and printing press. . ^- e i n sisted that the Manager of the Bank and myself should not go about without an armed guard, saying that he would not be responsible for our safety if we disregarded his request. (After this we were both accompanied by armed Bakhtiaris whenever we left our houses or offices.) The meeting then dispersed under the impression that some little had been one towards improving our position in Kerman. Our hopes were doomed to disappointment. The same evening we heard that Yezd had been seized by ^ f. V ermaIls ’ aT1( ^ learnt that the Gendarmes auction sale had developed into a political meeting. When the auctioneer‘‘put up” the first article, a priest stood up and called down the curses of God on whoever bid for the goods of the 3endar- mene force. He said, “ 1'hese men were engaged to defend us, it would be a sin and ashame if they were permitted to leave. The Governor-General only wanted to get rid o them so that he could have everything in his own hands. . Consu 8 y. ele backing up the Governor-General in this matter and J' 6 an ^flastmg disgrace to natives of Kerman if they did not oppose T ,en a Ip Ue i G ™ da ™f ”• Other speakers followed in the same strain. onnL th! q e ' i WaS T? fo ;. y ' dunte&lt;:1 's to join the Gendarme force to oppose the expulsion of the Gendarmes. Many were enrolled. I am not aware whether rifles were served out to them or not but in the matter of uniforms 7 Wer6 C ° Uld flght 38 Wel1 in ’ P laiQ clotlies 39 As night drew on many people who had attended the “ auction leave and go to their homes, Many of them were prevented doing ” wished to so, almostforcibly, by the Gendarmes who had prepared, and now served out, dinner for a very large party. Here a peculiarity of Persian revolutionary movements should be noticed. In other countries revolutionaries are compelled to attack Government offices and threaten, or take possession of, the seat of Government before they can gain the points for which they are contending. In Persia it is only necessary for a crowd to assemble in some building or garden, and, for some inexplicable, perhaps psychological, reason, the Governor-General, or even the Shah if he is concerned, trembles with fear and becomes utterly incapable of coherent thought or energetic action. Thus the Persian Constitution was won by a big crowd assembling in the British Legation in Tehran. The Governor-General of Kerman, though a half-civilised Bakhtiari, was no exception to this rule. His own Secretary told me that he was “ walking in his garden trembling like the leaves of trees ” and vowing what he would do when this affair was over. He took no action to save the situation. He did not attempt to disperse the assembly in the Gendarmerie, neither did he prevent the assembling of a much larger crowd next morning. A few Bakh tiari, with rifles, across the road leading to the Gendarmerie would have effectively prevented a big crowd congregating there. But he did nothing, not even when emissaries from the Revolutionary committee (formed of and by the persons named in the first part of my report) went to the Bazar and compelled the shopkeepers to close their shops and go to the Gendarmerie. Throughout the day the agitation was kept up, deputations from the Gendarmerie were sent to fetch Persis, Jews, Mullas, certain Khans, represent atives of all trades and even school children. A deputation sent to the Governor-General obtained from him a telegram addressed to the Cabinet at Tehran withdrawing his opposition to the Gendar me force, and requesting that it might be permitted to remain. By this time the speeches in the Gendarmerie, of which there was a con tinuous flow, had taken on a different complexion. Newspapers from Shiraz had reached Kerman telling how the Gendarmes there had acted towards the British Colony. The questions now put by the speakers were, ' Are we less than the people of Shiraz ? Are we not as patriotic as the other towns of Persia ? Can we not do as they have shown us how to do ? ” The meeting was continued throughout the night. Next morning, Sunday, December 12th, together with the Manager of the Imperial Bank I was asked to go to the Consulate to meet the Governor-General. At this meeting the Governor-General told us that he could not stand against the will of the people. He could fight one man, ten men, 100 or 1,000 men, but he could not fight against the whole city, and he was compelled to do whatever they wished. They had sent him a deputation during the night insisting that all English and Russians should leave Kerman. He professed himself ^helpless in the matter and said that he was compelled to agree to their demands. They were now preparing an ultimatum to this effect to be present ed to him on his return, but he would guarantee our lives and safety as far as the coast. The Governor-General, it will be seen, had no intention of protecting us if we remained and we could not protect ourselves. Moreover, it was now generally known that the Germans had seized Yezd and taken the British prisoners, and that they would arrive in Kerman in a few days time to do the same thing. 'We were, therefore, compelled to accept the Governor-General’s intimation that we had to leave Kerman. He promised to provide transport for us and to send a sufficient escort to see us safely to the coast. We asked him if he would personally take over and seal up our offices, &amp;c. He refused to take any responsibility in this matter, saying that the town was now in the hands of the ** idillet ” (Representatives of tne people) and that they would doubtless make all arrangements.■BW'TWf' 18 I intimated that I wished to proceed to Sistan with all the telegraph staff The Governor-General said that this was rather difficult as only camels could go that way and his sowars would not be able to accompany us. Moreover the Baluchis were raiding, and the presence of our large party would be sure to attract them, but he would see what could be done in the matter. At the Consul’s request, Mr. Taylor and I conveyed the news to the other Europeans that we were to clear up and to assemble at the Consulate with whatever luggage we wished to take with us. Section III. The Evacuation, The remainder of Sunday was spent in collecting and arranging for the disposal of Government and private property. Mr. Chase took down and packed all the instruments except the set actually working, the intention bein- to take them with us to Sistan. 3 On Monday morning, December 13th, soon after I reached the office a deputation from the “Millet” came to me with a note from the Governor- General saying that this committee had been sent to take over the telegraph office from me, and requesting that I would hand over everything. Similar letters and deputations were sent to the Manager of the Bank the Doctor of the C. M. S. hospital, and the Master of the C. M. S. school ’The Karguzar and others took over the Imperial Bank. The Bais-i-Mo’aref took over the C .M. S. school, and another committee took over the C, M. S. hospi- The Governor-General also wrote me that he had been informed that I had caused several of the instruments to be dismantled and requested me to replace them on the table to save trouble with tiie “Millet”. I had no option but to acquiesce. The committee appointed to take over the Telegraph Office consisted of md two or three Persian Telegraph clerks. the Inspector of Posts {vide page I) and that w'eTa^onTln C w ^ OU 1, St0r ?. list8 showin S the instruments and stores that we had on hand, but when the list was produced they said that it was aud de “ al ; ded a summar y- Finally, the number of instruments on each table was counted and entered on a form, thus : and so on. 6 d ° Uble Cim ' ent translation table witb (so many) instruments” commi Wee of 'Millet ” ^ lDSpeCt0r ° f P ° Sts ‘ 0 be si S“ ed b ? the s »P™me •Mil^n^,“tX^ Ught b y k and re,urned to me with the remark 'The Millet say that they have not given receipts for anything they have taken over not even the money in the Bank, so wW should tLy give y/u receipt, ? ” Mr Chase, after taking a list of the contents, sealed up the instrument cupboards But the Inspector of Posts broke the seals, saying ' We wTsea things up if we wish them sealed ^ 3 W1U seal At the first test on this morning the lines were found to be interrunted quite close to Herman and the Gholam (Lineman) had been sent out P He returned about noon in a very bedraggled condition, limpin- and Ids clothes badly torn and bringing with him a lar^e cloth full nf i i c • , cAot shawls with which the wires had been tied Aether beaten and abused bv men watching the line and tnl 1 ti ^ ^ eeri if he again ventured under the line. 0 After this we a 'In 6 wo “ ld be ^ ot Sub-Section Gholams, who did not venture near us aimin'^ 01 l^n 1° • the . V * th instrument room where the committee was assembled°and inti- I ° 1 'i'' t0 t 'o his load as the first fruits of the ' Millet ” in Kerman »na d , Ut ? , and acumen in expecting to earn revenue from a Teleirrknh if' ex f'! n l ll&lt; ' of tllp ^ ordeiei to be destroyed. lele S rd P h which they had The day was spent in sending to the Consulate tenfs nn/l ct j * of the reco.ds and books, also pads and other stores likelv ^heT f f''''’ Sistan. M, Cane cleverty concLled the l.depart^nunln^Vmut^dgot them away under the very noses of the committee, the ammunition was also got away in the same manner. Dr. Steinhoff sent his medicines, cupboard and hired furniture to the office where they were stored in the furniture brought from my house. It had not been possible to give morning, the committee objecting the lii es were totally interrupted “ mirror room ” with the office and hired translation on the instruments since the to our touching the instruments, and on both sides when we handed over. Hosseinhoff, a merchant of well-known pro-British sympathies, was shot at this day in the Bazar, his arm being broken by a bullet. At about 12-80 a.m. that night, whilst sorting out and packing my official and private papers, &amp;c., I heard someone at my front door. As there were no servants in the house, I went to the door myself carrying a hand lantern. On reaching the porch I saw by the light of the lantern that the large double doors, which I had double-bolted an hour or two before, were wide open and that I was looking down the muzzles of three rifles held to the shoulders of three Gendarmes, who stood in a row on my doorstep. They instantly pulled their triggers and I thought that I was practically a dead man. The rifles clicked, but were evidently not loaded. I rushed towards the men and pulled the doors together, endeavouring to bolt them. There was something between the doors so that they would not bolt, so I braced myself against them and shouted for my wife to telephone for Bakhtiaris to come from the office. This she did, and after a time l succeeded in fastening and barricading the doors. A party of Bakhtiaris came and slept at my house for the remainder of the night. I presume the incident was carried out with a view to frightening me, and to show me that although I went about guarded by Bakhtiaris in the day time, yet the “ Millet ” could reach me if they wished. Mr. Cane, Mr. Chase, Dr. Steinhofl: and Mr. Bottomley went to the Con sulate on Monday about noon and did not return to the office again. On Tuesday, 14th, the Consul gave orders that all British subjects must sleep that night at the Consulate. I went to the office for a short time in the morning and made final arrangements about the menial staff, preparing a list showing the pay due to each of them. The “ Millet ” undertook to pay them according to this list. At the request of the “ Millet ” and the Governor-General it was arranged that Local Service Signaller Mr. A. Alexander should remain at Kerman, staying in the office as our representative. I instructed Local Service Signaller Mr. C. W. Edwards at Bam to arrange for camels to take him to Sistan along with us, and to endeavour to arrange for about 100 camels for our transport beyond Bam. I o-ave Probationer Z. Minas, a Persian subject, the option of remaining at Kerman or accompanying us to Sistan. Re begged to be taken, as his brother, his only relative in Kerman, was leaving, and he was afraid to remain alone. I took his case to the Consul who agreed to his accompanying us. The two P. C. clerks, Persian subjects and employees of Persian Tele graph Administration, begged to be permitted to accompany us. One of them, on Monday night, had been robbed of everything he possessed, except the clothes that he wore. The Governor-GeneraPs Secretary told me it would be hioffilv dangerous for them to remain. I could not undertake the respons- ibilitv of taking them and referred them to the British Consul, who finally agreed that they should accompany us. Later on the Governor-General sent a^ain specially to me requesting that these two clerks might be taken away ^Ith us, or he would not be responsible for their lives. On the Monday the committee in charge of the Bank would not permit us to draw out any cash, but, I believe, owing to the intervention of the Governor-General, on Tuesday Mr. Taylor informed us that we were to be permitted to draw out our private balances. As I had several different accounts running at the Bank, I sent in cheque* to withdraw all my balances, and included a cheque for the balance ot the Government cash which stood to my credit.T=' I i t, thlS cheqUe Sot thTOa Z h with the ot,i er 9 , and I received Kran. 11,918-80 Government money (about £200) in cash. This sum in silrerS (notes were no longer current) was too heavy to take with me on a W journey, so I asked Mr. O. Brandly of the Oriental Carpet Manufacturer a suiss subject, to take it over together with my surplus private cash ami to give me drafts op Bombay in exchange. Ue a greed and^t once took “tav the coin, which it would hare been very unwise to have kept in mv Hn ^ overnight. Later, Mr. Brandly told me that he had given the “ Consul ’’ an undertaking that he would not take over any British Govern 11 ment cash or property. But I persuaded him to accede to my request and gave him a letter to cover him in which I referred to the cash as my private funds. He then gave me drafts on London and on Bombav On Tnesrli,, night the whole of the British Colony slept at the Consulate andalllhe l l, gS a ge was assembled there, the Governor-General supplying a laro-e Bikh tiari guard. Mirza Ahmed Khan, the Superintendent oT perlian Teleg^nh ' had been seized and imprisoned by the “ Millet ” two or three days before U.is’ I sent 0 the Governor-General and asked him to do what be could for him and before leaving Kerman had the satisfaction of knowing that he wss released and was then in the Governor’s palace. Mirza Ahmed Khan had been very true to us and gave us much useful information. He consistentlv efused to pei mit the German to send messages in cypher, as only properly accredited Consuls are permitted to do, although he was cornnelh^ hv tl7 Minister of Telegraphs, Tehran, to accept messages in cypher fo? the German f! • C °i nt fr r ^ re e ulatlon s of the Persian Telegraph Administration I think Mirza Ahmed Khan’s services worthy of some recognition at i ' i of the British Government. He already holds a British Medal for ffoo^ work on construction of the Central Persian Line. g d 0 k On Wednesday morning, the 15th instant, the Consul formally forhndp mo .tempt to go to Sistan. savino* flint tu^ i* „ .,. me to attempt to go’to Sistan, sayi^-tKaV“i,m^^7‘^Xl v He 8 ^ 'nto certain disaster i? Baluchis and The Governor-General also sent to me savino&gt; thqt ™ x zt ::r and again his men, not having camels, could no? proceed beyond B^m 1191 tbem ’ he would 1 ' proceed' tmS ^ Wh ° had travelling together in that direeUon ’ Bu^ i found ^^7 ^reed to onr to arrange to go by that route and was comneUedtot, f n K u aTk the English Colony. ^ lta t0 &amp;0 to ^ uri der Abbas with It amounted to this that the Govern nr -11 . v escort, and that all of us had to travel in the same direction. pr ° Vlde 0nIy one sent to me for the keys of mystoief&amp;« t 7' 'Tf the 1Vle ' ra P h Office would give me a receipt for them. This they refused 6 Thf^ Up if they the Governor-General asking him what was^to he ,1,7 Tl “ ere “P on 1 '’rote to responsible for the property at the Telegraph Offie e d ^^1^1 W t ? 1° P held sorry he could not help me, but that the “ Millet»» e P lle . t | that he was we must all do as they requested, therefore it was advlsabl^ ? ' P ° Werful &gt; and over the keys. I did so, telling the committee wh ,717 w f e t0 hatld forcibly took possession of other people’s property without 757 ° f pe ° pl , e wh ° ledgment. P ^ tit giving an acknow- Mr. O. Brandly, the Swiss subject mentioned above Wi i, mumcation with Herr Zugmayer, I understand at the reon. J J ' 1 7 COm ' with reference to our departure and Zugmayer had nromk^i 7 7 Ur Co ' sul &gt; his best to prevent any attack on “ the women and oUldren ” inheh^t'e 1 ' 1 ^ About midnight on Wednesday niirlit Mr Brnnrllvr . S00n * nephew, came to the Consulate to say that he had received hy his Zugmayer to the effect that he could not understand why the British 0 C »Colony was taking so long to get off, they were incurring great danger, the people were getting impatient and beyond control, and he feared that he would, not be able to keep his promise regarding the women and children if we delayed much longer. He suggested that the women and children should be started off at once, We sent back a reply that we were quite prepared to start as soon as transport was provided, we had intended and hoped to start on Thursday morning, but that the Governor-General had not, as yet, produced a single animal for transport. Also we had no intention of sending the women and children first. When they went, we should accompany them. Mr. Brandly at once took this reply to Zugmayer. The general idea was that Zugmayer wished to separate us from women folk so that an attempt might be made to take the men prisoners, following the example of Shiraz. 'Thursday afternoon and evening camels, mules and donkeys hired through the Governor General were coming into the Consulates. Contracts were made at the rate of Krans 90 per donkey, Krans 120 per camel and Krans 180 per mule for the journey to Bunder Abbas via Jiruft. Messrs. Cane and Chase took up the duties of transport officers, had the luggage sorted out, and the camel caravan with an escort of Bakhtiaris started at sunset. Next morning, Friday December 17th the British Colony started from the British Consulate, the Russian Consul with his Cossacks joining us and accompanying us. Every man openly carried a rifle and supply of ammunition, there were 39 rifles in all, not including the Bakhtiari guard. At Sarvestan we found Mr.C.W.E.Edwards from Bam with his wife and three children awaiting us. They had been practically expelled from Bam, a committee taking over charge of the Telegraph Office. They went on with us to Bunder Abbas. Nothing of interest occurred on the way except an alarm at midnight on December 25th when the Bakhtiari guards fired several shots and some of them ran through the camp calling everyone to arms. All the men turned.out except the Armenians, who said they got ready and remained in their tents until they were called. It appears that some six or seven men had been seen by one of the outposts, and that when they did not answer the challenge-* the guard fired on them, whereupon they fled. Our party consisted of:- Race Men Women Children ToiaT. ' English 10 7 6 23 Russian 10 - - 10 Greek 1 - - 1 Armenians * 8 5 7 20 Indian Sowars R - - 5 Persian (Nawab) 1 — 1 TOTAL 12 13 60 * 2 men, 2 women, 4 children British subjects, 1 Turkish subject, remainder Persian subjects. Including the Bakhtiari and Afshar guards mounts there were 92 camels, 26 mules, 132 donkeys, and about 100 horses, totaltotal 350 animals. The day before reaching Bunder Abbas was a pouring v/et day, otherwise fine weather was experienced throughout although naturally, it was cold on the mountains at this time of the year. We reached Bunder Abbas on January 10th and found that Vice Consul Mr.W.Howson had made all possible arrangements for our comfort. One of the Russian Cossacks having develooad small pox on the road, it was not considered advisable that any of the Russian party should embark on the transport. They were therefore left at Bunder Abbas. An Armenian clerk employed in the Bank, ,his wife and three children embarked on the hired transport 'Bankura' on the morning of the 14th January. We dropped Colonel Ducat at Muscat on the 15th and reached Bombay on the 20th. The Telegraph contingent, except Assistant Surgeon Steinhoff. left Bombay on the 25th on the Departmental Cable steamer 'Patrick Stewart', and arrived at Karachi on Friday 28th January 1916. (Sd.) J.W.Tanner. Superintendent, late of Kerman Sub Division.[ 12 ] In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote No. ifOUtZ /W and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. t 2 (2 C f' ■ ^ G U , 9 = o 7' J The Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Undersecretary of State for and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop 4/h of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, ynjuj it &gt; I 9 I 5 Letter Reference to previous correspondence: Foreign Office: &amp;' 3,3 u/i Description of Inch sure. Name and Date. IAiaSvlLq I/^ plcl S'?* hLm^c/iSf Subject. £ », - ftte? fts&amp;sy* (Similar letter sent to[This Do cument is the Frap erty of His Britannic Majesty’s Go?einaaeBfc3 PERSIA AND CENTRAL ASIA. ^ CONFIDENTIAL. [April 26.] Section 2. [50142] No - l - Sir IT. Townley to Sir Echmrd Grey.—{Received April 26.) ( s f r a 56 ' ) Tehran, March 31, 1915. WITH reference to my despatch So. 11 of the 3rd instant, I have the honour to forward herewith translation of a further note which I have received from the Minister for Foreign Affairs on the subject of the German subjects deported from Mohammera j, to which I have returned no answer. I have, &amp;c. WALTER TOWNLEY. Enclosure in No. 1. I Note communicated to Sir 11. Townley by the Persian Government. (Translation.) Tehran, March 20, 1915. IN view of the authentic reports received by the Foreign Office, I have to point out to vour Excellency, in pursuance of ray note of the 20th February last, the lamentable impression made on my Government by the sequestration ol the properties of Herr Holz at Mohammerah, and those of Herr Heimlich at Ahwaz, and am bound to renew mv protest against the repetition of such actions on the part ol a iriendiy Power and neighbour in time of peace and in a neutral country ; I have at the same to remind your Excellency that such measures amount to a breach ol lersias neutrality, and will cause her both moral and material damage, the responsibility lor which will legally rest with those who were guilty of the breach. Havino* full confidence in vour Excellency’s good-will, I request you not to allow the neutrality of Persia, which His Britannic Majesty’s Government ought to have respected in the most friendly maimer, to be further infringed, and to send peremp ory orders to the south for the restoration of the above-mentioned properties to the Persian authorities at Mohammerah and Ahwaz. Awaiting a satisfactory reply. I avail, &amp;c. MUHAMMAD IBRAHIM GHA1FARI. [2402 cc—2]Reference Paper. — Register No. M. 16689/15 Political and Secret Department. 191 Referred to the Secretary, Political and Secret Department, 14th May 1915* iqj Mote Verbalii from Imperial Foreign Office to U.S.A.Embassy relative to the report that Herr, Listemann, the German Consul at Bushire, has been made prisoner, and requesting new of his whereabouts. For his information and any observations. Mr.Listemann,formerly German Consul at Bushire, was handed over to the Military authorities in India for internment in that country in April 1915. He is presumably at Ahmednagar but there is no actual information as to this. (sd) E.G.Barrow. Secretary, Military Department, 7C. Seen. I attach papers containing the latest information available in the Political Depart ment concerning the internment of Dr. Listemann. The Military Dept, is aware of the circumstances which led to the arrest of Dr.Listemann and other Germans at Bushire: they were made subject of a comm i attached. to the Press, of which a copy is (sd) J.I.Shuckburgh. 15/5/15 / 17653. I. 1380. 500.—9/1914.19 46 / ■ Telegram It., No. 548 B., dated (and received) the I7th March 1915. From—The Hon'ble Lieutfnant-Colonel Sir Percy Cox, K.C.I.E,, C.S.L, Political Eesident in the Persian Gulf, Basrah, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Delhi. Following from Busbire, 16th March:— “Begins. Yesterday another Besidency messenger was stopped by gendarmerie and searched on ground that he was bearing letters from British. “German Consul papers show gendarmerie are hand in glove with German(s). They are at this moment urging Khans to attack Bushire and their presence in south is a menace. Ends. Sent to Minister and Shiraz.” Addressed to India ; repeated to India Office. I 2. Telegram R., No. 555 B., dated (and received) the 17th March 1915. From—The HoiPble Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Percx Cox, K.C.I.E., C.S.L, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Basrah, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department. Following from Shiraz, 17th March :— “ French Consular Agent called early this morning to inform me that he has best reason to believe that Governor-General is acting treacherously and that in his opinion situation is extremely menacing. Please inform Officer in Command of gendarmerie and request him to telegraph urgent instructions to Pravitz that in the event of disturbances he should do all in his power to ensure protection of life and property of foreign subjects. Addressed to Tehran ; repeated to Basrah, Bushire. ” Addressed to India; repeated to India Office. 3 . Telegram R., No. 94 C., dated the 17th (received 18th) March 1915. From— Captain W. G. Niale, First Assistant to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Delhi. Sir P. Cox’s telegrams 533 and 534 B. I beg to inform Your Excellency that I consider the immediate recall of Swedish officers to Tehran and the with drawal of the gendarmes from the south an urgent necessity. My reports still show that the Swedish officers are continuing to stir up the people to immediate hostilities against the English. But for them I believe the present agitation would die down and until they go I cannot say that the landing of troops at Bushire for the immediate safety of the inhabitants is unnecessary and yet the very fact of troops being landed here would undoubtedly revive the general agitation against us. A transport is now anchored at Bushire—it is required elsewhere—and yet with Swedes active against us in my immediate vicinity I hesitate to say that I do not require it. If they are at once rendered powerless, I believe w r e can avoid the landing of troops and the widening of our military responsibility. I submit these facts for Your Excellency’s consideration and trust I may he informed at earliest opportunity of what action has been taken by the Central Government with respect to gendarmerie. Addressed to Minister; repeated to India, Cox, Shiraz.Telegram R., No. 95 C., dated the 17th (received 18th) March 1915. From— Captain W. G. Neale, First Assistant to the Political Resident in tu Persian Gulf, Bushire, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Delhi. F General Staff, Basrah, has ordered Officer Commanding Troops, Bushire, to land 200 men here immediately from transport and let ship proceed on’its way. I have instructed Officer Commanding Troops on transport to land no troops and stand by. I consider immediate landing of troops unnecessary and impolitic as certain to revive general agitation. At the same time in view of Shiraz report and my own knowledge present activities of the Swedish officers I consider troops should be within easy reach. From reports received I think Borasjun conflagration will subside if fresh fuel is not added, but the Swedes are doing their best to stir it up. If Ti%an will immediately take strong action as to Swedes and gendar- mene generally, I believe we should be justified in letting the transport proceed with all her troops on board. r I fully realise the transport is wanted elsewhere and should be glad to know when at the latest she must leave here. Please see my immediately preceding telegram. J Addressed Cox; repeated Foreign. Telegram R., No. 561 B., dated the 17th (received 18th) March 1915. From—The Hobble Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Perct Cox, K.C IE C S I Pnli- tical Resident in the Persian Gulf, Basrah, ' ^ To-The Secretary^ 0 the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart- lQl.-, I fJi aVe n re 5f ned following telegram, No. 64, dated the 10th March 1915, from the Foreign Office, addressed to Tehran and repeated to myself • „ “!; er T? noe y° ur telegram No. 94. If you feel assured that Sirdar Jang r suh a d p v iTouTdT g 1° ou , r , wishes ’ 1 would be incliued t0 o£fer hi ^ Percy Cox as to the nrorw^W t0 , re0ei¥e - V0Ur Tiews “&lt;1 ‘hose of Sir i X / S t0 i P T ^°^ ble effect such action on the Sheikh of Moham- merrah and on other Bakhtiari Khans, respectively. ,, Monam Telegram R., No. 562 B., dated the 17th (received 18th) March 1915. From The Hon'ble Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Percy Cox KCTF r&lt;5T pi- tical Resident in the Persian Gulf, ’ C S -Iv Toll- To—The Secretary to the Government of India in thp PW j t, iv , Department, Delhi. the Political Keference Foreign Office telegram 94, 16th March, to you. It is essential that Sirdar Bahadur as reuresentino u i -i participate in any subsidy given. These two Khans with branc 1 l1 sbouI(1 would then be in a strong position in tribe and I see no Zon ge “r ral *, SUPPOrt of other Khans should give us serious inconyeniener 0 ^! 0 ^ * he , en Ty be squared by Khans above mentioned. To be of use howev J , d bt must be promptly concluded. ’ er ’ arraD gements tbe assumption that political relations with Persia dn a into a declaration of war, I would suggest one thousand pounrk dn doveio P Khan: expenses for the maintenance of any tribal troom pm i ^ n ,^ or eaCl1 Eakhtiari limits and a promise of further favours later on accordnu?? outsbie rendered. This subsidy should suffice to secure the?r co-opemion TTe21 extent of guarding the pipe line(s) as far as Wais or Whwaz and keeping their people aloof from joining any local rising against us or the Sheikh of Moham- merah. It seems unlikely at present that tribe will get bitten with Jihad fever, hut if they did, it is improbable that Khans would be able to control them at any price. Should a state of war supervene, then the above arrangement would not suffice, and I am of opinion that immediately it is decided that war is inevi table, we should start at once to secure the adherence of Bakhtiari and Sheikh of Mohammerah by offer of treaty, guaranteeing their local autonomy and protection after the war, and by making any immediate cash payment that might be necessary. Probably none would be needed in the case of Sheikh of Mohammerah, except perhaps a loan. Any negotiations which take place with Khans in Arabistan must, I think, he done by me, but I venture to suggest that, if His Majesty’s Minister can trust them, he should sound Khans in Tehran without delay. Addressed to Minister; repeated to Foreign Office and Government of India. m In r- Telegram P., dated the 17th (received 18th) March 1915. From— His Majesty’s Secretary of State for India, London, To—His Excellency the Viceroy, Delhi. His Britannic Majesty’s Consul at Shiraz and all other Consuls Southern Persia are, I presume, well provided with funds for secret service, view of attitude of Persian Government, this is probably the only, not the best means to securing tribes and other measures required. by our interests, and’it may prove fatal to success if delay is incurred in obtaining sanction in each. c£isG» It is* suggested by Marling, who is on his way to relieve Sir W. Townley that a Political Officer should, if necessary, be specially detailed for the purpose of countering German moves and negotiating subsidies. Telegram P., No. D.-S. 326, dated the 18th March 1915. From— His Excellency the Viceroy, Delhi, q 0 His Majesty’s Secretary of State for India, London. Bakhtiaris. Please see telegram No. 562 B., dated 17th March 1915, from Sir P. Cox, repeated to His Majesty’s Secretary of State for Foreign We support proposals made by Cox and we are prepared to share the expenditure that will be involved. „ ^ r, Repeated to His Britannic Majesty’s Minister, Tehran, and Sir P. Cox, Basrah. Telegram R., No. D.-S. 327, dated the 19th March 1915. From —The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, Delhi, To—The Hon’blk Lieutenant-Colonel Sib Percy Cox, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Basrah. It is important that our Consular Officers in South Persia should be well provided wifh secret service funds at present juncture. They are accordingly authorised to incur expenditure without sanction in excess of their allo meius as may be necessary to secure tribes and other measures required by ourinterests. Do you or other officers require remittances of cash from India ? ( ) To sir p. Cox only. (Marling, who is on his way to relieve PrJ'f' i no? i lit, •n own e y» suggests that, if necessary a Political Officer should be specially detailed for purpose of neootiati™ yie b w S d ?) S aDd C0Untenns Germau moTe9 in South Persia. What are your Addressed Basrah; repeated Bushire, Shiraz and Hohammerah. — w- — Telegram P., dated the 19th March 1915. From—* His Excellency the Viceroy, Delhi, To—His Majesty's Secretary of State for India, London. „„ * &gt;erSia ;, Hef f enc ® y™r telepram of 17th instant. Consular Officers in S uthern Persia hare been authorised to incur expenditure on secret service in excess of their allotments without sanction. And as suggested, we have under consideration the question of the deputation of a special political officer // ■ Telegram R., No. 563 B., dated the 17th (received 18th) March 1915. From The Hon'ble Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Percy Cox KCIF P9T Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Basrah, ’ C.S.I., T °~ The ment to DelM. the G ° Ternment of India io and Political Depart- teleJamN^^T 4 ehran ’ f’ March -.-Begivs. Reference Cox’s teie 0 ram Ao. o33 B. Arms and ammunition in question were desnatphod frnm here some weeks ago ostensibly for Ispahan, where they should have arrived bv now. Some were dropped here and there on the road Perhaps CotuT Telegram R., No. 33, dated (and received) the 18th March 1915. From—His Britannic Majesty's Minister, Tehran 1'°—fhe Secrecy to the Government of India m the Foreign and Political Depart- My telegram No. 109. I am officially assured that most cafecnorical ordprc Tiowa n Governor-General of Pars and to Officer Commanding g^ndarmZe^t^M possible steps to maintain order. ^ rmene to take all _ Searching enquiry is being instituted into char&lt;&gt;-es against th» .. ^ which Government believe are totally unfounded '’offmer rv* gendarmerie has been closely cross-examined and has exprissed grLtoT mandlnS 'T* accusations. expressed greatest amazement at Addressed to Foreign Office; sent to India, Basrah, Bushire and Shiraz. n. Telegram P., No. 566 B„ dated (and received) the 18th March 1915 From—The Hon'ble Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Percy Pnv tt o r r, ^ « T Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Basrah, ' k.G.I.E., C.S.I., To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and PnlT i rt ment, Delhi. b and p °htical Depart- I have received the following telegram, dated 16th Maroh -n • OfficePlease see Buchanan’s No. 298. Conclusive evidence is Cuilhed bySir P. Cox in his recent telegrams which have beep repeated direct to you of the campaign conducted against us by Wassmuss. Pugin appears scarcely less dangerous. “ It appears essential to curtail their activity and internment by Persian Government would probably be entirely useless. «You should consult your Russian Colleague as to the measures which could be taken either to check activitv of these two individuals or for arresting them. It must be clearly understood by you that measures must not be countenanoerl, far less adopted, which could directly or indirectly instigate or even suggest their assassination. Such methods would be viewed by His Majesty’s Government with abhorrence. ” Repeated to Bushire, Telegram R., No. 567 B., dated (and received) the 18th March 1915. From—The Hon’ble Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Percy Cox, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Basrah, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Delhi. Poliowing from His Majesty’s Representative, Tehran, 97, 17th March. Begins. Your telegram, 50. I have made a vigorous protest to Prime Minister and I have demanded instructions be at once sent to Governor-General and gendarmerie to preserve order. I have held Persian Government formally responsible for damage that may be done to British interests should a disturbance with violence occur. Prime Minister promised to send at once necessary orders. Repeated to Basrah and Bushire. Ends. /«r Telegram R., No. 568 B., dated (and received) the 18th March 1915. p rom The Hon’ble Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Percy Cox, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Basrah, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Delhi. Polio wing from Shiraz, 17 th March :— Begins. Major Pravitz sent a telegram over Persian wire some days ago to Persian Gendarmerie Officer, Borasjun, instructing him to prevent landing of British troops at Bushire if possible. Addressed Tehran ; repeated Basrah, Bushire. Ends. Addressed India; repeated India Office. Telegram R., No. 572 B., dated the 18th (received 19th) March 1915. Prom The Hon'ble Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Percy Cox, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Basrah, To The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Delhi. Pollowing from Shiraz, 56, 18th March :— Begins. Two very unsatisfactory telegrams have been received here from Tehran. Pirstly, from Hierta (? Hjalmarson) stating that numerous complaints have been received from various Legations regarding political action of i/ewcianwene which have caused Commandant much astonishment and he has informed authorities concerned that in his opinion they are unfounded.Gravity of situation in the south is due almost entirely to presence of Swedish officers. Without their support and active incitement Persians would soon cool down and Wassmuss by himself would find it very difficult to stir up the people to any action. Dangerous aspect of affairs is due to existence of armed force under officers hostile to us and Russia, and they can at any moment create ircident which will drag Persia into the war, precisely as Germans forced hostilities on Turkey. It would seem, from Treasurer-General’s telegram referred to in my telegram, No. 56, that Persian Government are not averse from submitting themselves to German and Swedish influences. Unless the Swedes can be brought to hook, I regard the consequences as inevitable, and denouement of plot will take place, whenever German Charge d’Affaires considers moment favourable. No action by local officers can be of any avail on situation, and result depends on what degree of diplomatic pressure can be exercised at the capital. But I also think that defeat of the Turks at Ahwaz, and fall of Constanti nople, would probably upset the German and Swedish plans. Addressed to Tehran ; repeated to Basrah and Bushire. Ends. Repeated to India Office. Telegram R., No. 571 B., dated (and received) the 18th March 1915. From—The Hon'ble Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Percy Cox, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Basrah, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Delhi. My telegram, No. 523, 15th March. Incriminating material regarding Eisenhut is now forthcoming and Officer Commanding Transport has been instructed by General Officer Commanding to make him prisoner also. Insinuate (?) three individuals are in different category to prisoner of war. Their offence as residents of country which was then peaceful and neutral practically involves incitement to murder or abetment of such incitement and seems to be much on a par with piracy by sea. Will the Government of India therefore consider whether they should not he treated as criminals. General Officer Commanding concurs. Telegram R., No. 576 B., dated (and received) the 19th March 1915. From—The Hon'ble Likutenant-Colonel Sir Percy Cox, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Basrah, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Delhi. General situation. My telegram, 10th March. Gurna.—On Tigris side no change. Bloods still out. Turks remain encamped a few miles above us, but with reduced force. Crude attempt has been made during last few days to float (mines ? ) down on to His Majesty’s ships. On Euphrates side above Gurna, riverain tribesmen who had submitted to us and were settling down are showing signs of nervousness owing to recent news of strong Turkish reinforcements coming down for advance on Basrah. Basrah .—Our outpost at Shaiba, ten miles away, has been strengthened. Turco-Arab force threatening it also continuously receiving additions to its strength, and is now reported to consist of 5,000 regular infantry, 500 cavalry, about 5,000 Arabs and 12 guns. One or two skirmishes have occurred between reconnaissance parties in which we have incurred trivial losses, but in which our own artillery is believed to have inflicted heavy loss at longrange. Turkish force is receiving supplies by waterways through marsh these communications are now being blocked by light draught river ho fitted with field guns which have done considerable damage to their boats 318 Arabist **.—Tribal situation in south has somewhat improved. Rebel* of Chab at Fallahia, held in check by presence of His Maiestv’ ships at Marid, have not yet made the expected move towards Ahwaz. DesuV ary hostilities continue between the loyal and disaffected tribes in Jarat* Hindia districts but call to Jihad seems to have little effect. At Ahwaz Turco-Arab force is encamped about ten miles (off) and i also believed to have had reinforcements; they do not, however, seem to b 8 disposed to attack, yet it is expected that very soon they will ’have either to advance to Karun or else retire to Karkha owing to exhaustion of water supply where they are. Haji Rais reported to-day, 18th March, news received from reliable correspondent in Shuster to the effect that Vali of Pushtikuh himself had reached Upper Karkha near Shush with a very large force and is accommnipH by well known Mujtahid from Kerbela. ^ News from Djzful and Shuster towns is good. Numerous exhortations received from Mujtahid of Mesopotamia, but they have had no effect. Ends Addressed to Government of India; repeated to Minister, India Office ^ Southern Persia officers by post or telegraph. Telegram R., No. 97 C., dated (and received) the 19th March 1915. From-CAPTAiN G * ^ EALF &gt; Assistant to the Political Resident in the .Persian Gulf, Bushxre, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Denart- ment, Delhi. ^ Foreign telegram, No. 327 D.-S., 19th March. 1 -«”* iM ' k -»'»«*»» Addressed to Cox; repeated to Foreign iHrr ' Telegram, No. 544 W., dated the 20th March 1915. G °— nt of Foreign and Political To-The Secretary to the Government of Bombay, Political Department, Bombay. Dr. Lindersf Ilerr Td'* 311 ?0nSU1, Way » ■ Vareova ', T,*y tato” !'''' ££»% incriminating correspondence Unless military authorities have had Xot instructions regarding them, please have Listemann, Linders and Eisenhut ken under police restraint pending further orders Th^ i u U , 1 ,, c , communicate with any one. ^ sbould not be allowed to Telegram P., dated the 19th (received 20th) March 1915. From-His Majesty's Secretary of State for India, London To—His Excellency the Viceroy, Delhi. the EesfdenHn Bushire’T^X^ram^Vdgv B ed a he r] re fi S! t Vi t n h S the substanee of No. 500 B„ also the text of the^eman 10^^ whlt' St thre6 o£ Resident’s Nos. 532 B., and 531 B. but the^vnrri f c 1 y ere re P eate( i ln the the end of the message were omitted. Sir A Tnwni ,0m /f 011 !^ S . to telegram the words “ win over ” should be “ iiivolv.f”^^^ w it the latt ? r the translations other small inaccuracies. The commnt.L, 1 ? d , tbat tll . ere are . m the arrest of the Germans and the seizure of thefr , q u d ° eS n0t mentlon telegrams as having come into our possession. P P erL y» but speaks of thoseTelegram, No. 1101, dated the 22nd March 1915. From—The Secretary to the Government o£ India in the Home Department, Delhi, To The Secretary to the Government of Bombay, Political Department, Bombay. Continuation telegram, No. 544 W., of 20th instant, from Foreign. Governor^General in Council directs internment of Listemann, Dr. Linders and Herr Eisenhut under the Foreigners’ Ordinance and that they should be made over to the military authorities for purpose. With permission Governor in Council kindly issue necessary instructions and telegraph full names of parties concerned in order that formal orders may be made out. Telegram, No. 2682 W., dated the 26th March 1915. Prom The Secretary to the Government of Bombay, Political Department, Bombay, To The Secretary to the Government of India in the Home Department, Delhi. Your tele^ram, 1101, 22nd March. Helmuth Listemann, Theodore Linders and Carl Eiseuhut made over to military authorities. M^esrs. Gertrude Eisenhut sent to hostile women’s camp, Belgaum. 37 No. 1202, dated Delhi, the 3rd April 1915. From—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Home Department, T 0 The Secretary to the Government of Bombay, Political Department. With reference to the correspondence ending with your telegram, W . da tod the 28th March 1915, I am directed to enclose, herewith, for Theodore Linders and Carl Eisenhut, three subjects of the German Empire. No. 1204., dated the 3rd April 1915. ORDEE. No. 1203, dated the 3rd April 1915. Endorsed by Home Department. Copy, with a copy of the order, forwarded to the Army Department, for information.In any further communication on the subject, please quote no. 44068/15. and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. o Sir:- (£&gt; I &gt; 1/ p; T Foreign Office Lpril 22nd, 1915. ' ' i I am directed by Secretary Sir Edward Grey to acknowledge the receipt of your letter of the 1st instant P.1187/15, relative to the measures which should be taken to counteract the activity of German agents in South Western Persia. In reply, I am to transmit to you, herewith, a copy of a telegram from His Majesty* s late Minister at Tehran, and to state that Sir Edward Grey shares Sir W. Townley*s view that the capture and deportation of German agitators would probably have a precisely opposite effect to the result desired. He hesitates for this reason to express concurrence in the action suggested in your letter under reply. In regard to the enquiry contained in the last paragraph of that letter, I am to state that the Govern ment The Under Secretary of State, India Office.(44068/15) Government of India would, in Sir Edward Grey's opinion, be entitled to place any Germans who have been deported from Persia, under the same restrictions as those to which enemy subjects interned in India are now subjected. Their treatment as prisoners of war appears to be largely a question of nomenclature, and presumably the Government of India intend merely to place them in prisoners camps as i distinct from actual incarceration in gaol. I era, Sir, Your most obedient, humble servant,CONFIDENTIAL. PERSIA Sir W. Townley to Sir Edward Grey.—iBeceioed April 14, G-50 p.m.) Tehran. (No. 158.) . 14 ’ 1915 ’ 11 A - M ’) YOUR telegram No. 90 of 12tli April. . , i I am strongly of opinion that capture and deportation of German agitators irx friendly natives would have precisely opposite effect to the one desired. It would serve to inflame feelings of public against ns. bhere are signs that German propaganda is losing ground under influence exerted from here, and 1 think that d treated with contempt it would die a natural death. It seems unlikely that Germans will openly venture into what is a strictly Britishs phere. At present moment it appears to me essential to await developments. Government is certainly endeavouring to o-uide public opinion in a sense more favourable to us, and both lurks and Geiman are playing into their hands. Any act of violence would militate against creation o better feeling. (Very Confidential) . , , T V Occupation of Kasr-i-Shirin by Turks may entirely change situation. I saw Prime Minister this morning. Cabinet is now discussing question, ^ . o ' means improbable that Government will adopt attitude that will pnno ve } . ' declaring war. Persia may even declare war herself, and would probably do so f it were felt that financial and material support of Great Britain and Russia coulc n COUn Unp°ro'voked violation of Persian territory without excuse of presence in district of either British or Russian troops has aroused great indignation in Cabinet. 467- S5P’CM 'If lo|&lt;f 516 A From Sir P. Cox, Basra, 19th April 1915. (Addressed to (Government of India, repeated to India, (\jfic , (R.) 908 B. Following from Shiraz, 18th April. “ My telfegramj^^. |8^ | Signaller, Kazerun, B reports Khan of Kamarij has sent away wonieii and' ‘ children and is preparing to resist gendarmerie. It is said that some of Kashgai’s tribesmen will assist him. There is, in fact, makings ol serious disturbance, which, once begun, will spread rapidly and may involve all Fars. If Persian Government really wish to avert consequences, they should send urgent instructions for recall of expedition. Addressed to Tehran, repeated to Basra, Bushire.”/ In any further communica- ion on this subject, please quote No. Utfjj /,9,s and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. 1 The Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Undersecretary of State for and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, / l 12 1 Reference to previous correspondence: Letter to from Foreign OJJice: Description of Inclosure.37, X'j byk , ,(&lt;f I 'roin i Sfr P. Cox, Basra, 1 9th April 1915. (Addressed to Government of India and repeated to India Office.) (R.) 909 ?&gt;. Following from Shiraz, 17th April. “Zugmayer has telegraphed from Sultanabad to Commandant Gendar merie here, requesting him to transmit message to VV. to the effect that Z. and Griesinger were leaving for Ispahan I7tli April, and expected to arrive there 25th April, and asking that \\ . should communicate to them at Ispahan. “They seem to take it for granted that Swedish officers are safe medium for transmission of their communications to one another. Addressed to Tehran, repeated to Basra, Bushire.” ■■ ;~i t From Sir P. Cox. Basra, 20th April 1915. (Addressed to Foreign, repeated to India, Office.) (R.) 919 B. Following from Shiraz, No. 92, dated 20th April. “The pestilential Wasmuss has written encouraging letter to Mullah at Bushire and is doing his best to stir up Bushire as well as Shiraz. He signs himself as Consul. “ He has also issued notice in last number of local paper here -&amp;}■ German Connoh; hardly havr 1 venture to suggest protest should be made to Persian Government against \\ asmuss styling himself German he has not been accepted as such by German Government. Teheran.” ix -L+d*, ('ousel when Addressed to 1 1 624ut r.vvr.y Answer so Sir J. Do Reo 435 No, 54, cirtM 1915 • ^ i It is understood that Herr Wasstnass is still at Shiraz but I am not aware that his consular appointment has been recognized by the Persian (lovemment. It is understood that t ie Persian authorities have rot interfe-c-i wit' hi? liberty® A j*' /From Sir P. Cox, Basra, tith April 1915. [Addressed to Government of India, repeated to India Office.) W (R ) 759 B. Following from Shiraz, 7 7, dated dth April ^ “ Reference Bushire’s 43-288. 1 have frequently spoken both to the Governor-General and Pravitz regarding the attitude and proceedings of Persian gendarmerie officers, and although both have assured me that their political ^activities would be checked, and although formal orders to this effect have been issued by l\, no other measures of any kind seem to have been taken and these officers continue to conduct active campaign against our interests in co-operation with W. and the democratic party here “ i r ecrret to say 1 have lost any belief 1 originally had m l . s pro es- sions of 'neutrality^ If these were sincere he could by now have taken effective steps to enforce attention to his orders and to punish disobedience. Not only has he not done so but his own attitude is most ambiguous and unsatisfactory, and he himself spreads absurd reports regarding deleats oi the Allies, German victories, &amp;c. “ There can I think be no doubt whatever that he as well as othei Swedes is cognisant of German plans and is working hand-m glove with them to destroy our influence in the South and to embarrass us in even possible wav. I receive daily many proofs of this. I heir early withdrawal Fs in my opinion imperative for the preservation of our interests m Southern “ Addressed to Tehran, repeated to Basra and Bushire.From Sir P. Cox, loth April 1915. (Addressed to Government of India, repeated to India Office.) (R.) 825 B. Following from Shiraz dated 12th April :— “ Your telegram 792 B. “ As you know definite proofs are difficult to produce in such cases. 1 will try to formulate situation briefly. “ I know as a fact all Swedish officers who have been and who are at present in Fars are pro-German and that they have openly .expounded their views both to Persians and Europeans. Captain Killander, for instance, told me himself that he regarded all Reuter’s news as [group omitted] and all German news as absolutely accurate, and that he had so informed his Persian officers and others. Major Pravitz lias recently given out that England is blockaded, Amir of Afghanistan assassinated and many other such rumours all calculated to do us injury. And 1 could quote many similar instances. With regard to Captain Oertingren I have received information from four different sources regarding his anti-British propaganda at Kazerun. I have seen letter written by financial agent there to acting controller of finances, Shiraz, an Armenian, giving detailed account of O.’s interview with Nasred Diva. This letter, which was written by Persian subordinate to his chief, entirely corroborates informal ion received from our telegraph signaller and from Stas. 1 also tackled Governor of Kazerun, who was present at interview in question and who is now on visit to Shiraz, on the subject a few days ago, and he admitted substantial accuracy of accusations. “ There is also suspicious affair of arms and ammunition referred to in Bushire telegram 90 G. which has not yet been explained as far as 1 know. “ Then whole of Persian gendarmerie officers are rabidly pro-German and anti-British. They openly associate with Wassmuss and have committed themselves in many other ways. I have ample proof of this and it cannot be denied even by Swedes themselves. “ So even if we give Swedish officers credit for wishing to restrain their Persian officers we must at the same time admit that they are incapable of doing so. Major Pravitz in conversation with me this morning told me some 800 men of Fars regiment of gendarmerie are of Turkish origin and that if there were rising in south or if Turks advanced beyond Ahwaz nothing could prevent them from rising also. “ If then we suppose Swedes are not purposely conducting campaign against us in German interests, actual consequences of their pro-German attitude are same as far as we are concerned as if they were doing so ; and gendarmerie under these officers constitutes a very serious menace to our interests in Southern Persia and to neutrality of country in general. “Addressed to Cox, repeated to Tehran.”r p DELn i . 47G The -*r March 1915 I am desired to forward, for information, a copy of a decypher of a telegram sent by the Persian Foreign Minister to the Persian Ambassador in London relative to the situation in Persia. Lr Arthur Hirtzel, K. C. B., Secretary, Political Department, India Office, London?y-v 0 orth of ushire. x Astermann * ilisenhut? Prom Muain-ud-Dauleh (Foreign Minister), Teheran. To The Persian Ahoassador, London. No. 270, dated the 10th March 1915. Captain Neale, the British Vice-Consul, as 0 a result of intrigues, took steps in Bander Big with the object of effecting the arrest of M. Wassmuss, the German Consul. The latter fled and arrived safely at Burazjan. They brought his effects and household furniture, which are said to have been considerable, with another German and the Persian Interpreter, to Bandar Kig and embarked them on board a British vessel, but they are sending back the Persian. The Captain (Neale) also followed Wassmuss to Burazjan. News x comes from Bushire that they seized the German Consul in one of the squares of the town in the company of the Chief Merchant and took him on board a British vessel. On the other hand the British Embassy whites in a friendly manner, asking me to protest and stop Wassmuss' actions and that the Government of Pars should keep an eye on what he does. If you consider the matter rightly, these actions (i.e., British) are the same as those which the Russians have done in the North and which we expected the British to stop, ihey themselves have now done exactly the same thing and in spite of Persia's declaration of neutrality, expect Persia to remove the official representatives of lermany. To-day, if it were proved that Persia and had forsaken her neutrality, to maintain which she nas mde such great efforts, she would meet with very great calamities, which would result in nothing short of ge/neral disorder, the breaking up oj. the State andMake strong representations revolution in the country, and ask for the recall of the Consul of the (Gulf) Ports, trie restitution of Wassrnuss 1 property, and the return of Holst, Here, too, I arn writing a letter of excuse to the Embassy (German).CONFIDENTIAL. (No. 158.) M^ 1; _ (April 14, 1915, 11 a.m.) YOUR telegram No. 9() of 12tli April. I am strongly of opinion that capture and deportation of German agitators by friendly natives would have precisely opposite effect to the one desired. It would serve to inflame feelings of public against ns. There are signs that German propaganda is losing ground under influence exerted from here, and 1 think that d treated with contempt it would die a natural death. It seems unlikeR that Geimans will openly venture into what is a strictly Britislls phere. At present moment it appears to me essential to await developments. Government is certainly endeavouimg to o-uide public opinion in a sense more favourable to us, and both links and Geimans are playing into their hands. Any act of violence would militate against creation of better feeling. (Very Confidential) . , . . . T Occupation of Kasr-i-Shirin by Turks may entirely change situation. _ I saw Prime Minister this morning. Cabinet is now discussing question, and it is w no means improbable that Government will adopt attitude that will provoke lurkey into declaring war. Persia may even declare war herself, and would probably ylo so it it were felt that financial and material support of Great Britain and Russia could in- Unprovoked violation of Persian territory without excuse of presence ,u district of either British or Russian troops has aroused great indignation m Cabinet. ; 407-851'4% (So TO BE i^ TUltt^D TO FOREIGN OFFICE UMLSSS Pni? OPFICIAL U3F,. ^ j| /. g K 1 Pi,i^lA. POLI TICAL. (44068/15). Cypher lele^rau to i.ir, Parlin^ (Toneme,n) Foreign Office, April 16th. 1915. 7.15.p.m. No. 92. Sir U. Tovrnley*8 telegram no. 158 (of 14th.. April Persia’s attitude). If possibility foreshadowed in penultiaate paragrap were to become a reality, Persia, could certainly count on support of His majesty’s Government, both financially and so far as the military situation rendered it pos sible, materially. You miuit let Prime mi: lister know confidentially that above is your private opinion. Repeated to Petrograd, Ho. 626. GC 3 f t n(41914/15). POLlTiGAL . Cypiie^ Tele^ajfi to Foreign Office, i ; Q. lOO* (P) • . Howard (Stockholm) iFpr i 1 161 xi • 1915. lo.0.p•m* Your teleg^cmi Ho, 90 (of 4tn, April, owe ties in Persia) «&gt; You should express to Sv/odisli. idiniete^ for Foreign Affairs cordial appreciation of His liajesty 1 s Government at His Excellency's willingness to give effect, so far as. lies in his power, to their wishes. His l.iajesty’s Govenijment for their part will he pre- pared to guarantee such officers against reasonable loss from breach of contract, provided they resign their ap pointments and leave Persia without delay. You should at the same time thank His Excellency for the friendly sentiments which have animated the Swedish Government on the subject ever since the officers first went to Persia, Repeated to Retrograd, Ho. 629. . Ho. 93CONFIDENTIAL. S * Sir Edward Grey to Sir W. Townley (Tehran). PERSIA (No. 90.) Foreign Office, April 12, 1915, 6‘15 p.m. SIR P. COX’S telegram No. 660 b of 27th March : German agitators. India Office enquire whether I see any objection to Government of India instructing their officers in British sphere to try to arrange, with friendly native help, for capture and deportation to India of Germans who may enter our sphere. They add that Soulet might be of use for similar purpose in Fars. There are obvious objections to the scheme, which I am unwilling to support. Can you suggest any alternative course which would, without violating Persian neutrality, possibly restrict or frustrate activity of German agitators in south of Persia ? Ai 0 - 7 GiVV' i ; 4(57—771]—ip— Immediate and C ijidential. S2i The Under - Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Under-Secretary of State for India, and is directed by the Secretary of State to transmit the accompanying copies of Cl. telegram , as marked in the vZ' 6APR1915 tjATjr '[This Document is the Property of|His Britannic Majesty’s Government, and 5^ should he returned to the Foreign Office when done with unless required for official use.] Decypher c Sir W. D. 1.20 # p.m, R. 7.30,p.m. ' r&gt; N PERSIA. ! A h 4 O POLITICAL*. c. T ownle y (Teheran) V April 3rd. 1915. No. 142. (R' ) ® His Majesty’s Consul at Shiraz reports that Governor General still continues to associate himsell openly with Wassmuss and German party. I caused representations to he made to Minister tor Foreign Affairs yesterday and myself personally saw prime Minister. His Highness asserted that he had sent categorical instructions to Governor General, Pars. I replied that this was further proof that his re call is imperative as from latest information in my possession it was clear that His Excellency pays no at tention to his instructions. Prime Minister replied that he was ready to recall Governor General hut that it was difficult for him to do so unless lie had something hy way of compensation as a quid pro quo to offer public opinion. . In a conversation in which very plain speaking was indulged in I pointed out in answer to His Highness’s assurances that Cabinet was imbued with most friendly sentiments to Great Britain that coincidences are un fortunately against Persia..; and that they may combine to shake the faith of Persia’s English friends in her sincerity. No-one, I said, would realize better thanHi 3 Highness what the loss of British sympathy might mean to Persia. as coincidences I cited that, whereas all that is possible appears to he done for Germans, Persian of ficials in whom vie have confidence such as the Sheikh of uohamnerah, Haidar Khan of Bender Rig, ,Governor of Bushire and Deputy-Governor of Bunder Abbas are not only not supported, but are harrassed and bullied. Also Swedes, who were formerly roundly abused because of their insubordination to ministry of the Interior, are now the darlings of the Cabinet, because tney are openly pr o-German, whe reas 3e1gians, who are our Allies aublicly attacked in the uedjliss and tne press, are and are being hounded out of the country by the systematic hostility of the Government. prime Minister endeavoured to defend himself, but,. I think, realises that these unfortunate 'coincide^ made his case a poor one. nis one remedy for all evils is recall of Russian troops. I replied that this could not be done now end added that I was inclined to think that, if carried out, it would be accepted as a sign of weakness and would make bad worse. Repeated to Petrograd and Basrah.Bring up again on Reminder sent 4 Bring up on \ 'CP' ! From Sir P. Cox, ISth VawFTmSr' {Addressed Government of India, repeated to Minister, India Office, and Southern Persia Offices by post or telegraph.) (R.) 576 B. General situation. My telegram 10th March :— Gurna.— On Tigris side no change. Floods still rSt. Turks remain encamped few miles above us, but with reduced force. Crude attempt has been made during last few days to float GpW/ts down on to His Majesty’s ships. On Euphrates side, above Gurna, river tribes who had submitted to ns and were settling down are showing signs of nervousness owing to recent news of strong Turkish reinforcements coming down for advance to Basra. Basra. —Our outpost at Shaiba, 10 miles away, has been strengthened. Turco-Arab force threatening it also continues to receive additions to its strength, and is now reported to consist of 5,000 regular infantry, 500 cavalry, about 5,000 Arabs and 12 guns. One or two skirmishes have occurred between reconnaissance parties in which we have incurred trivial losses, but in which our own artillery is believed to have inflicted heavy loss at long range. Turkish force is receiving supplies by waterways through marshes ; these communications are now being blockaded by light draught river boats fitted with breech-loading guns which have done considerable damage to their boats. • Arabistan. —Tribal situation in south has somewhat improved. Rebel Chab at Fallahia, held in check by presence of H.M.SiA^M MctnA , has not made the expected move towards Ahwaz. Desultory hostilities between the loyal and disaffected tribesmen in •larrahi and Hinclia districts, but the call to Jihad seems to have little effect. At A Won, | - p Turco-Arab force is encamped about 10 miles (•? away) and is believed to have had reinforcements ; they do not, however, seem to be disposed to attack yet, it is expected that very soon they will have either to advance to Karim or else to retire to Karkha owing to exhaustion of water supply where they are. Haji Rais reported to-day, 18th March, news received from reliable correspondent in Shuster to the effect that Vali of Pushtikuh himself had reached Upper Kcv-HALa. , near Shush, with a very large force, and is accompanied by well-known Mujtahid from Kerbela. News from Disful and Shuster towns is good. Numerous exhortations received from Mujtahids of Mesopotamia, but they have had no effect.•^0 [This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government, and should be returned to the Foreign Office when done with unless required for official use.] PERSIA. POLITICAL. Do cypher. Sir V/. lownley (Teheran) D. 3.0.p.m. R. 8.45.p.m. No. 97. hiarch 18th. 1915. r-.- '■ ? * y ! r-', i.,. i*ollowin^ from His majesty's Consul at Tabriz march 12tii. Begins W telegrams Nos. 11 and 12. Reports communicatre&lt;i to me by my American colleague have been brought here fro.., Dilman by Armenian to the ef fect that two days previous to Russian occupation of that place some 800 Christian men and boys were massacred by Kurds who it is alleged were Persian subjects and insti tuted by lurks. ny Russian colleague to whose notice we brought uhe above has had no comaunication on the subject from Russian Authorities at Dilrnon but has telegraphed to tne latter to enquire. In the meantime and in view of vom serious situation of refugees the at Urumia numbering over 10,000 and of American and French missionaries in whose charge they are, my United States Colleague after consulta tion with us is endeavouring through United States minister at Tehran to communicate with the United States Ambassador at Constantinople with a view to the- latter being informed of urgency of matter and taking such action as he may con sider necessary. (?This) seems to be all that can be done here unless Persian Government should be in a position to exercise pressure on Turks.[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government, and should be returned to the Foreign Office when done with unless required for official use.] f f J PERSIA DEPARTMENTAL DecypAer, Sir VJ. Townley (Teheran) D» 10*30 a.m* R. 2,45 P*i^* March 17on, 1915 No. 106 (R) My telegram No. 97. Following from His Majesty's Consul at Taoriz Begins: Report of massacre referred to in my im~ mediately preceding telegram is confirmed oy Rus sian Vice Consul at Oilman. Exact numbers are not given but he states several hundred bodies have been discovered in wells and other places and are being buried under the supervision of Russian troops Repeated to Petrograd.[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty's Government, and should he returned to the Foreign Office when done with unless required for official use.] PERSIA. Decypher of telegram from Sir w. Townley (Tehran) d. 10.30 a.m. J Marcli 17th, 1915. r. 5. - p.rn. No. 107. R. W immediately preceding telegram.. . Following from His Majesty's consul at Tabriz. My telegram No. 13. My United States colleague has been asked by Dr. Shedd Of the American Mission at Urumia in a letter of March 1st whether he could not go to their assistance. The latter who is ready to go has consulted my Russian and French colleagues and myself, but we are unanimously of opinion that it would be impossible for him to get there as the Russians cannot guarantee his safety beyond their own lines and that only means of affording relief is by direct action by United States at Constantinople f and by pressure on Turkish Ambas sador at Tehran. The account given by Dr. Shedd is not reassuring for though the report that 800 persons had been massacred at . Urumia is unfounded it appears that some three v/eeks ago forty refugees who had been imprisoned by order of the Turk ish Consul were executed outside the town/on accusation of having borne arms against the Turks without any proper investigation, Shedd says, as to whether this was so- or not. This was followed two or three days later by shooting in cold blood of 50 men at the village of Culpassan where women and girls were also violated chief offenders in tnis respect being apparently Turkish regulars. There has_been great mortality owing to sickness amongst &gt; refugees while he estimates that 800 persons have been killed_in_tno Urumia district since the occupation by Turks in January.^ Persian Governor he adds is doing his best but tne Turkisn Consul does nothing though very profuse in promises. I have made verbal and written communications to Persian Government as have my Russian and French col leagues Repeated to Petrograd; ■ r ' ' 1 / [This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government, and should be returned to the Foreign Office when done with unless required for official use.] (3 P i n U ^ PSitSlA. T.,/rTT r^r i .1. 1 t JmjLjj Decypher of telegram from Sir VJ. Townley (Tehr d. 5.25 io.m. on) X . 11.10 p-.m. No. 96. B. 12th March,1915. lorces, numbering about 14,000,have defeated Turkish Kurds at Dilraan, the latter losing about 300 men and large quantities of stores and ammuni tion. It is said that there were about 10,000 Turkish troops engaged. Maragha district is in hands of nussians and Turco-Kurdish troops are reported to have retired from Miandoab behind Biver Jagatu.Tiie Secretary of State for India communicates the following :— Documentary evidence has reached His Majesty’s Government proving' conclusively that German consular officers in Persia and the agents of the German firm of Wonckhaus have been engaged in intrigues with the object of facilitating the Turkish invasion of Persia and of raising the tribes against Great Britain, thus flagrantly violating Persian neutrality. For example, not only were the agents of Messrs. AYonckhaus at Ahwaz and Mohammerah found to be in direct communication with the Turkish troops, but an elaborate plot has been discovered of which Afghanistan, the frontier, and the Indian Army are the objective. Herr Wassmuss, who was formerly German Consul at Bushire, and has recently been appointed German Consul at Shiraz (where Germany has no commercial interests and has not hitherto had a consul), was the prime mover in this. It is now known that he was at Cairo shortly before the war, and in Constantinople when war broke out. Accompanied by four other Germans and four Indians who were sent from. Berlin to join him at Constantinople, he made his way to the Persian frontier, and thence to Shiraz. Among his effects was a box containing several thousand violently inflammatory pamphlets in English, Urdu, Hindu, Punjabi, and Sikh languages, addressed to the Indian Army, calling on them to take the opportunity to throw off the hated yoke and rise and kill their officers. A long appeal to Mussulman soldiers in India was also found, urging them to join in jehad. This person is now at Shiraz awaiting instructions frpm the German Legation at Tehran. Not less discreditable is a correspondence which has come into our possession between the German Legation and the Consul at Bushire. Some time ago a large consignment of arms and ammunition arrived at that port, and was hurriedly and secretly conveyed up-country by the Swedish officers of gendarmerie. The following telegrams were exchanged :— From German Legation to German Consul, Bushire. “Thanks for news regarding arms. Please henceforth do not manifest any further interest. Weapons will be fetched away for our secret object.” From German Consul to German Legation. “ Weapons were fetched away some days ago by Swedish officer. My promotion of this affair has remained inconspicuous throughout.” Light is thrown upon the “secret object ” by the following facts. The German Consul had been in communication with the Persian Sheikh Rais Ali of Dilwar, a coast town some miles to the south of Bushire, regarding a proposed attack on the latter place which Rais Ali was apparently anxious to begin at once. The German Legation telegraphed as follows on the 19th February:— “ Reference telegram No. 25, dated Tehran, 1st instant, regarding undesirability of immediate action by Rais Ali, and the absolute futility of independent action. Please hold him well in hand, and assure him Confidently of a movement in the spring. If you really think him reliable and consider that circumstances are ripe for action there, would it be a good thing to make out a plan secretly with him which would be combined with an already arranged secret action led from here, and would at the same time win over all Persia ? As soon as possible I will let you know secretly further on this matter.”18354. 1. 14i. 10,000.- 2/191*. [211/H.] COPY OF TELEGRAM. n- From Sir Po C«x X Dated Ba»ra 0 ISth March 1915 Received at London Office 1*20 a 0 m 0 (14tb) ft!* 500 Bo It appears frt» Wasemas 1 papers that he was is Caire shortly Before war *nd in Constantinople when war Broke out, H» was amdo leader of Mission to Persia and Afghanistan for the purpose of stirring up trouble agpinst us e . Other sierhero of Mission wero mr (1) NioderEmyer, (2) Herr Schonerarn, (3) Boiler, (4) Cohen, a Jew 0 Schonemarm was recently reported fro» Kasrishirin; it would he useful to ascertain where ethers are 0 Few Indians were also sent from Berlin to join Wasssmss in Constantinople Apparently plan of operation was for Mission to split up into seteral directions* Wasstmss’s particular destination Beinc Afghanistan and frontier with incidental Mission to Indian Amy®. Afghanistan figures largely in his papers and newspaper cuttings* According to them Afghan Army is well oquipped and trained under Turkish instructors and is now sitBilisod and ready to join Turkey and Persia and only Roods efficient loaders- Poaing aa dswaa a Censwl in a neutral country and By this means carrying such a mission, ie nothing more than a pirate® If the Persisn Gertc decline to take action i» regard to him and if lie ahould start from Shiraz eastward, I suggest 1 O'Connor (?) should Be authorised te spend B» e 10,000 to |pt Mm shet on the way* Addressed to India, repeated.to Minister, India Offx&amp;e, Buohire*Shiraz *[ he Under - Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Under-Secretary of State for India, and is directed by the Secretary of State to transmit the accompanying copies of cl- telegram , as marked in the Foreign Office,CONFIDENTIAL. 1 o i r Sir TIN Townley to Sir Edward Grey.—(Deceived March 8, 7 p.m.) Tehran. (No. 88.) ^ {March 8, 1915, 10*45 a.m.) 5’0 r JR telegram No. 58 of Gtli March. Generally speaking, I still hold to view expressed in my telegram No. 82 of 20th February that it is most undesirable to stir up public feeling against us as it was stirred up against Russians m Azerbaijan by arrests of Germans, but officers in the south are best judges in particular cases. My information as to intrigues of these Germans is derived from common knowledge forwarded to me by your local representatives and supported by their personal observations rather than on documentary evidence. I am of opinion that Wassmuss is the most dangerous case, and this classification seems to be shared by Sir P. Cox (see his telegram No. 416 of 6th March received yesterday); his path at Pusht-i-kuh, Shuster, Behbehan, and Ramuz has been marked by successive additions to enemy’s forces. Moreover, His Majesty’s consul at Shiraz much fears the effect of his arrival there. As regards German consul at Bushire, though I am aware that he has been intriguing with Arab side of the Persian Gulf and in correspondence with Wassmuss, I think situation is probably sufficiently in hand there for us merely to watch him and. keep him from doing any harm. Case of Germans at Lingah appears to be similar. So-called German consul at Kasr is now at Kermanshah, and, in view of good attitude of Governor-General and Sinjabis, dislike entertained of Turks there, and Salar-ed-Dowleh’s departure, I am inclined to think him comparatively harmless. Dr. Pugin at Ispahan continues to intrigue, and has been stirring up Moslem feeling against Bahais. I hear that Persian Government intend to recognise him as German and Turkish consul. I have protested strongly. Apart from other considerations, arrest of these two latter seems to me impossible. [341-699]ICONFIDENTIAL. v Sir IF. Townley to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received March 8, 6-40 p.m.) PERSIA (&amp;J ^ /-xrv -r. Tehran. (*°. (March 8, 1915, lO'SO a.m.) MY telegram No. 87 of 7th March. Minister of the Interior has [? sent to] tell me that Government are taking all possible steps, and they have hopes that they have stopped many from joining the disaffected Arabs. Persian Government learn that Wassmuss has been sent on and robbed of all he possesses on the way to Borasjun. He has disappeared from view. I have no confirmation of above myself. (Repeated to Bushire and Sir P. Cox.) i id' \ cl 6^ Csi— i' COPY OP TELEGRAM 18351. I. 145. 10,000.—2/1 #1». (211/M.] From Dated Received at London Officep 14 I Q i S FOREIGN SECRET TELEGRAM^ .V Secret Department. From Sir P. Cox, 10th March 1915. (Addressed Lidia ; repeated to Minister, [? Tehran, and] India Office.) 444 B. General situation. Ahwaz. On evening of 7th March General Officer Commanding, Ahwaz, increased detachment at Ahwaz by 70 men, including 20 British troops,' which gives sufficient stiffening to Sheikh of Mohammerah’s people! Unfortunately Europeans at Ahwaz had already vacated in the morning. Attitude of Muhaisin is now reported to have improved, whilst Bavi Sheikhs have recommenced overtures for peace. Position at the fields remains satisfactory. Reported presence of party of Pushtikuh tribesmen in vicinity of Shush is confirmed, but it is not yet certain whether they really intend to join Turks or are only out to loot on their own account. Dr. Young reports unrest amongst Arabs between Dizful and Shuster, who are being incited to rise, but Sirdar Jang has given assurances that rising will not be allowed to materialise. Bani Turuf are said to be dropping away from Turks since the fighting on 3rd March. Telegraphic connection with Ramuz and Behbehan is at present interrupted, but as regards Jihad information which reaches me does not tend to show that it is meeting with very warm response, notwith standing professed fears of the Powers that be at Tehran who continue to sit with “ folded hands.” I am taking energetic steps by telegraph and by letter to disseminate suitable news and exhortations to all centres concerned. There is no change at Gurna and little to report on Euphrates side, but military reports seem to indicate that Turks are likely to take offensive against the Basra outposts before long. In all three directions time is in our favour, as the Arabs will become disheartened by inaction and it will be difficult to keep them mobilised when the time comes for tending their crops.CONFIDENTIAL PERSIA Sir W. Townley to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received March 3, 9*30 p.m.) /XT . Tehran, March 2, 1915. (No. 86.) ^ ^ (March 2, 2’10 p.m.) WASSMUSS, formerly German consnl at Bushire, is about to arrive at Shiraz, accompanied by a son-in-law, Sawlat-udan-Dowleh, and Nasir-ul-Mulk. He claims to be new German consol there, but Government know nothing about his appointment, though it would be hard to refuse recognition of him when request is presented to Persian Government. His Majesty’s consul foresees that he will cause trouble, and adds that new Governor-General is very pro-German, Kawam secretly unfriendly, and Sawlat shifty and untrustworthy. Major O’Connor thinks they are sure to come under Wassmuss’s influence, and that his arrival raises the question of keeping Swedes in an acute for m . He suggests that, if it were possible to dispense with Swedes, it would really be in our interest to do so, but recognises that gendarmerie must be maintained and the difficulty of getting other foreign officers to take it over at present moment. He expresses opinion that British officers would be best, but thinks that it would require force to back them at first. He also suggests Merrill as capable officer, who could take over gendarmerie of Pars if Governor-General goes. Failing these alternatives, he proposed that commandant at Tehran should be pressed to warn his officers that they must maintain really neutral attitude, and reluctantly allow themselves to become agents of German propaganda. This has already been done and assurances received that Swedish officers will be warned. At the same time it was impressed on me that Swedes are not so generally pro-German as is supposed, and one officer, who has been accused of showing his bias, called on me to-day to say that he is of French origin and has all his family ties in England, and could not be called pro-German. All are probably anti-Russian. It would appear to me a most unfavourable moment to change foreign officers of gendarmerie. British officers are probably not available, and to impose them on Persia at present moment would make a bad impression. Task is too big for one American officer. I venture to [? provisionally] suggest that Swedes be maintained, and won to our side by pecuniary assistance. Distribution of money could be made through Legation and [? consuls] as before. [341— 360]Immediate and C nfidentiaL put away The Under - Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Under-Secretary of State for India, and is directed by the Secretary of State to transmit the accompanying copies of telegram , as marked in the margin. H . /±' Foreign Office,No.58. (24546/15) PERSIA. Political. Cypher telegram to Sir W. Townley (Tehran) Foreign Office, March 6th, 1915. 8.40 p.m Sir P. Cox’s telegram of February 23rd repeated to you. India Office consider that first three paragraphs of Sir P. Cox's telegram do not necessarily show complicity of German Consul General at Bagdad, since after action of Russians at Tabriz conjecture was obvious that we should deport Germans from Arab is tan. Moreover they are not in possession of all the documents incriminating Consul at Bushire. They feel therefore that it would not be justifiable to remove German Consul and V/onckhaus agents except from actual area of military operations, though they would be prepared to do so if I were satisfied that such action would not react unfavourably on general situation in Persia. what are your views, and is the evidence in your possession (see last paragraph of your telegram No.82)Minute Paper. t ^jr-o-n* v\ I' . O' OA Register No. Put away with., Secret Department. ! !±) Bate. Initials. iMled (j Rec. fritL. SUBJECT. 1915., Under Secretary Secretary of State Committee Unger Secretary Secretary of State c °py to Viy Ctcbn^y. FOR INFORMATION. I ^1/LtA (fj~ Lvr^L y Cv C/MAM Ctm Mr Previous Papers :X ( Copy* ) Telegram. P« Proa- Sanking, Ahwaz* | c Addreaged Tehran, repeated Besident Muhaiimareh. Uo. 66/225. Dated 11th Hovember 1914. \\i Wj J i-lier© is a nuaour bore tibai 5hszban has fasen ^ivan a khilwat by the Turks and eneoura^ed to stir up trouble in Fort hern Arabistan* I hare written to Sirdar Jan^arning hia that Ghazban^ obJeotiT© aaj^ be the Oil Coapany^ Works and that he should therefore instruot tribes in Tioinity of Fields that they should render without delay any assistance that the guards r; may require* I suggest that Shaikh of Muharamareh should arrange for Arab mounted patrols along the pipe line and road from Dara Khasina to Abgah # whioh suffered most at the time of Gha*ban f s last depredations* Oil Company has also been warned to take precautions as regards these sections* As Abgah is point most exposed to Ghazban^ raids* I 1 a hare suggested that the Bakhtiari guard there be increased in consultation with the Officer Commanding the main guard at the Fields* Banking. Bepeated to India by post from Bushire Bovember 13th 1914*4 18354. I. 145. 10,000.—2/1915. [211/14.] 382-Bo R COPY OF TELEGRAM. From Sir P = C*I„ Ba»r4„ * ^' «\tNjL Dated 4thI3I5 o Received at London Officers 35 ^.,i'an (?) Lin® 3 IntuitG^nfirnati by r• ®no«at §f ifirtar^® b® m© liy Sheiklis between Guma and Amara indicate with little ienbt that we hare n© serieua a^eesitien te antieipat# in that Airectien f#r the jirtsento Rmtottaa iiaa.„ Aoeerdins tc military inffrmti^ there ar« \\% t® new •erne si^ht battalions between Nasrie and Baara p but these, feur babtaliens and a large but flue tutting fere© ef Arabs are established seme 16 miles west of Basra but ar# belieTed t« have received instructions not t® attack jedding arrival ©f mere tr®®TjiSo Attack on Basra by this fore© ni&amp;y be expected at any time but their movenients admit ef their being watched fr©m day t* day so that there is n* likelihetd of surprise P Karun line. Considerable feree of Turks estimated at about I e OGO together with large but fluctuating ftree ef Arabs has established itself 10 miles w sst of AhwaSo Former appear t® be gradually gaining in strength. As regards this force, Turkish Ambassador at Tehran has definitelv given out that their intention is outflank us at Basra* General Barrett has dene what he has found possible locally to prevent situation getting out ©f control But I can , . ^ t nther that ^rave possibilities of rapid deteriorating m resulting from Turkish intrusion in'® Arabistan are not yot fully appreciated* Position described in rry telegram Nd^W-- “ ® has since developed to the following extent* Disaffected Bavi have Awtod Tjooccupied Wais* Shaikh of Mohammera^ force at Ahwaz has been(3) RifliB, his #th*r l*oal traapa, tha cantinfpnt fram Rhadaaia and tha Carps af Frantiaraman af whith wa hara fcaard.. ft have ranturad to amkAthaae auteeationa in Tiaw of rafaaal of our propoaal that Indian troopa now in E|ypt should ha returnad for tha aarriae and the probation of Indian interaata in Mesopotamia and at Aden. Our military resources in India hare now been reduced to the bed-rock and we are only able to reinforce Barrett with such items as 2 battalions which will be replaced by 2 battalions from China, the 7th. Hariana Lancers and a second heaiy battery now on tlpir way to Basra, 1 battery Territorial Artillery and possibljja battalion of Nabha Imperial Infantry. Ve share your view that it is impmx*. imperative that Barrett's forces should be increased to 2 divisions. You are no doubt aware that since the outbreak of war we have sent overseas 6 divisions of infantry and nearly 3 divisions of cavalry while in return 33 battalions of British Infantry we have received 35 battalions of Territorial infantry of mixed value. India has therefore done her duty to the Bupire and it is quite impossible in view of situation on the Frontier and in interior to do more. It is of no use to sucsest to us that we should take further risks in India. We have heavy responsibilities towards European and Native population that cannot be lichtly act aside. Oar eonclusion uro ? therefore is that though we at one with you in thinking that Barrett's foree should be increased to at least 2 divisions we * are raafele in consequence of eer fienerosity towards H. M* forexment in the early stages of the war to find the necessary troops to eoaiplete them and that responsibility rests with H. GeTexment net merely te find the necessary additional troops hut for any consequences that may arise due to their refusal te allow India the use of her own troops ts protect her own interests*U.S.of S. F.O. fUu^) IMMEDIATE. gj.p ^ ^ c/\j I ^ l v I ain directed by the S.of S. for I. to forward, for thejinform- a tion oi the S.of S. for F.A. copy of a telegram that has been received from the G.of I. re garding the activity of the German consuls at Bushire and Bagdad. As regards the first 3 para graphs, the Marquess of Crewe doubts whether the inference drawn by Sir P.Cox from the action of the German consul general at Bagdad is necessary. In view of the measures taken by the Rus sians at Tabriz, it was an ob vious conjecture that we should deport German subjects from Ara bia tan, indeed wer r, -did— As regards para.6, Bushire telegram of the 12th Nov. was V enclosed in Mr.Grant’s letter of the 10th December (copy of which, numbered P.8, was sent to you on the 2nd Jan.last) and action was taken upon it by H.M.Minister Tehran, as indicated in his tele gram No.334*of 16th Nov.last. But Lord Crewe has not seen the documentary evidence to which Lt.Col.Knox refers, the letter to Herr Eisenhutt, referred to in para.8 of Capt.Keyes’ letter of the 4th Nov. not being included among the enclosures in Mr.I Grant’s letter of the; 26th Nov.. (copy of which, numbered P.492-3, was sent to you on the 21st Dec.). The rest of the correspondence proves nothing conclusive against the German ) consul at Bushire. It is of course, highly probable that German consuls and subjects have behaved in the manner suspected, both in Persia and elsewhere; but Lord Crewe is inclined to doubt whether, even in Persia,, it would be justifiable for H.M.G.to remove them, except from the actual area of military operations. If, however, Sir E.Grey does not share this scruple, and is satisfied that their removal would not react unfavourably on the general situation in Persia, H.L. would be glad that it should be effected. WT.I.HoMerness,I * COPY OF TELEGRAM. icaroy. ,0 tfXi From Dated Received at London Office TO T K o 183S4, I, 14d. 10,000.- 2/1918. [211/14,] 1 O 1 z: 3 i &amp; 1&gt;M* {3 3 ai&gt; oreic/i 8 secret iploy Feb ary iho Cox tel f There reached 113^1 diYie r Vi le orinn; a coiiTmijinication sent by G-emian Consul-General at Bagdad employes of CTonck^iaus at Mol ’Military event &gt;o En f ' lish Till tab ou nnsor secretly to &gt;r There you Till receive furthe 2*.' The bar also contained correspondence for Comjn Consal at Busin re and a c oi ifivtun i cat ion from a ?nt ai* jncklip ’ji D aMiidAi oo ms coiuraae ax&gt; aii 1 \aoeci Januaxr lowi j .11 vnnco he states that he has enlisted at Bagdad and kxx is leavin, and my meet addressee unexpectedly but cannot say how f O Turks from Effra did a&amp;t cross frontier until Januai^- ffid; so that the first coL-aiiunication shows that German Consul-General at.Baaxlad knew five clays before that Turkgs intended to use Persian territery and that he realisei that we should be justified in making ffarmn prisoner*. Second conniunication shows 5enck!i&amp;us agent* are enlistin f in the Turkish sawy and are a party to the Turkish ho still (against ?) Persian territory * 1 submit that above 0 taking ah eonjuncti.on wioi otatoment of Turkish to Bakhtiari in TiTOley’* sec: in removing Geix, troops , fer fxa*., Bushiro and Germ■ . J Sir W. Townley to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received February 21, 4*55 p.m.) /VT a , x Tehran, February 21, 1915. (No &lt;3. Secret.) (February 21, 10*40 a.m.) IN answer to personal protest made by Bakbtiari Kbans against Turkish menace to their country, Turkish Ambassador has replied they need be under no alarm ■ that Turks will not advance against their country; and that sole object of inroad into Persian territory is to get behind English position at Basra. A confidential agent, whom I hope to send shortly to Bagdad to collect military information, tells me that he has a Mullah brother with Turco-Arab force in Arabistan where he says there are large numbers of clergy of Nejef and Kerbela who have been compelled to accompany Turks in order to induce Shiah population to join Jihad. (Sent to India and Bushire.)ORDINANCE No. Ill of 1914. \_20th August, 1914.~\ An Ordinance to provide for the exercise of more effective control over foreigners in British India. 24 &amp; 25 Viet. 3, 67. [Published in the Gazette of India Extraordinary of the 20th August, 1914.~] TIT HERE AS an emergency has arisen which makes it necessary to provide for the exercise of more effective control over foreigners in British India; Now, therefore, in exercise of the powers con ferred by section 23 of the Indian Councils Act, 1861, the Governor General is pleased to make and pronmigate the following Ordinance. 1; (1) This Ordinance may be called “ The Short title Foreigners Ordinance, 1914.” ' and oxtenfc (2) It extends to the whole of British India including British Baluchistan, the Sonthal Far- ganas, the district of Angul, the Shan States and the Pargana of Spiti. 2 . In this Ordinance— Definitions [II of 1864. has the same meaning as in the (a) “ foreigner Foreigners Act, 1864. (b) “ prescribed ” means prescribed by rules made under this Ordinance. 3. (7) The Governor General in Council may by Rower to Order prohibit or regulate ' {a) prohibit, or regulate and restrict in such departure manner as he thinks fit, the entry of residence foreigners into British India and their ° 0icigue ' s - departure from British India; and [Price one anna and nine yiesl]The Foreigners. [ordinance m (b) regulate or restrict in such manner as he thinks fit the liberty of foreigners resid ing or being in British India. {2) In particular and without prejudice to the generality of the foregoing power orders under sub- ^ section (i) may provide— (a) that no foreigner shall enter into or depart from British India, save within such period and by such route, or by such port or place as may be specified in such order; (b) that foreigners shall be prohibited from entering or remaining in any specified area in British India or shall only be permitted to enter or remain in British India or any specified area therein sub ject to such conditions and restrictions as the Governor General in Council may impose; and (c) that foreigners residing or being in British India shall remove themselves to and remain in any specified area, or if such an order is necessary for the public safety, or in the interests of the State, that such foreigners shall be arrested and interned or confined in such manner as the Governor General in Council may think fit. 4. Any foreigner who contravenes or attempts to contravene the provisions of any order made under section 3, shall be punished with imprisonment of either description for a term which may extend to three years or with fine or with both. Householder 5. (l) The Governor General in Council or any residence of local Government may, by notification in the any foreigner Gazette of India or the local official Gazette, as the to prescribed case ma y be, direct that within any area specified authority in in such notification, every householder in whose house a foreigner is residing either temporarilv or permanently shall forthwith report to the prescribed authority in the prescribed manner, the name of 2 Penalties. specified areas.The Foreigners, [ordinance hi, 1914 .] 4 CALCUTTA . PRINTED By SUPDT. GOVT. PRINTING, INDIA, 8, HASTINGS STREET. Saving of powers under existing law. Power of exemption. Bar of jurisdiction of Courts. British India either by name or in virtue of his office. 9. Nothing in this Ordinance shall be deemed to affect or derogate from any power which may be exercised under the Foreigners Act, 1864, or under any other law for the time being in force in respect of foreigners generally or in respect of foreigners who are subjects of a State which is at war with His Majesty. 10. The Governor General in Council may exempt, either absolutely or conditionally, any foreigner or any class or description of foreigners from all or any of the provisions of this Ordinance. 11. No order made under section 3 of this Ordinance shall be called in question in any Court. HARDINGE OF PENSHURST, Viceroy and Governor General.‘I ORDINANCE No. VII op 1914. '» j ®S © I -v [14th October, 1914.] An Oi dinance to JiHiGiid tlio Foreigners Ordinance, 19 ] 4 . Ill of 1914. 24 &amp; 25 Viet., c.67. m of 1914. [Published in the Gazette oy India Extraordinary of the 14th October, 1914.] W FFREA S an emergency has arisen which makes it necessary to amend the Foreigners Ordi nance, 1914; Now, therefore, in exercise of the powers con ferred by section 23 of the Indian Councils Act. 1861, the Governor General is pleased to make and promulgate the following Ordinance. /* Ordinance may be called the Foreigners short title (Amendment) Ordinance, 1914. 2. In section 3, sub-section (2), of the Foreigners Amendment Ordinance, 1914, hereinafter called “ the said Ordi .. of section 3, nance,” the following amendments shall be made, oSS namely— (a) in clause (b), the word “ and 55 where it occurs for the second time shall be omitted; (b) after clause (c), the following shall be added, namely:— “ and (d) that foreigners residing or being in British India, shall be prohibited from carrying on trade or business or from dealing with any property, moveable or immoveable, or shall only carry ou trade or business, sub ject to such conditions and restrictions [Price one anna and three yies.]Foreigners {Amendment), [ordinance vii, 1914 j 3ALCTTTTA : PRINTED BY SUPDT. GOVT. PRINTING, INDIA, 8, HASTINGS STREET.. Insertion of new section, after section 3. Power as to Companies and Associa tions. Amendment of section 4, Foreigners Ordinance, 1914. as the Governor General in Council may impose or shall deal with any such pro perty in such manner as the Governor General in Council may direct.” 3. After section 3 of the said Ordinance the fol lowing section shall be inserted, namely— “ 3A. The power conferred by section 3 may be exercised, so far as the same may be applicable, in respect of any company or association, or body of individuals whether incorporated or not, of which any member or officer is a foreigner and which has an office, agency or place of business in British India.” 4. (1) Section 4 of the said Ordinance shall be renumbered section 4, sub-section (1), and in the said sub-section as renumbered, for the word “ foreigner ” the word “ person ” shall be substituted. {2) After section 4 (1) as renumbered, the follow ing sub-section shall be added, namely :— c ' {2) Where a company, association, or body of individuals has done any act which is an offence under sub-section (I), every mem ber or officer of such company, association or body who is knowingly a party to such act, shall be deemed to have committed an offence under the said sub-section.” HARDINGE OF PENSHURST, Viceroy and Governor General.cosy 19802/15. &lt;ir:- fitowpiy ttim. 1915. L ljk^ V. .ip I wn directed by secretary olr Edward Grey to acknowledge the receipt of your letter of the ieth instant, enclOBixig the draft of a telegnm* wiilch you desire to send to your representative at Teheran regard' ing the situation in ^outh ..eat i an is. In reply, 1 m to Inform you that . ir r,. ;;rey concurs in the terras of the proposed telegem to ir, tacleen. 1 am. Your most obedient. humble servant, , ^ued; Eyre d. Crowe. The Ghaiman, &amp;iglo-i ereian uil company, Greshaia liOuse, 24 Old Broad street,copy. ( 19802 ) Urgent* ANGLO-PERSIAN OIL CaiPANY, LIMITED, GRESHM HOUSE, 24, OLD BROAD STREET, LONDON, E.C. 18th February, 1915. Sir:- I beg to hand you copy oT a telegram received from our Agents at Mohammerah, and enclose draft of a telegram which subject to the approval of His Majesty’s Government, we propose sending to our Representative at Teheran. (Signed) I have the honour, &amp;c., C. Greenway. Chairman. Under Secretary of State, Foreign Office.Copy of telegram from strick Scott md Company, Limited, Loiismmerah, to Anglo-Persian Oil company, Limited, London dated 15th February, 1915 . Further British troops proceeded to Ahwaz yester day total Forces now approximately 2,500. At the instigation of Sheikh of Mohamrnerah and Political Resident Persian Gulf Persian Government have been asked to instruct Bakhtiari Khans undertake guarding Pipe Line &amp;c., as far as Waiss and send troops to Ahwaz it would be of assistance if A.P.o.c. London made similar representa tions to Persian Government on the strength of Clause No.14 D , Arcy Concession.DRAFT TELEGRAM TO H. W. Maclean, Teiieran. Secret Cypher Mullasani Arabs neighbourhood Bundiquir vvaiss have risen and perpetrated much damage Pipe Line and Turkish Forces and other Tribes threatening ' Ahwaz. Position very critical. Request Persian Govern- ^ ment instruct Bo-khtiari Khans provide irnrnediately sufficient force guard Pipe Line to Waiss and also to send strong force gendarmerie to Ahwaz to ensure protec tion Company’s property in accordance with Clause 14 Concession.COPY OF TELEGRAM. From Sir P 0 Cox Dated 18th February 1915 Received at London Office o o £ V/f 10 , 305B. Arabistan situation. In continuation of previous telegrams 261, 262, 13th February. \ ^ N Increase of force at Ahwaz has had immediate effect, Muhaisim have been stiffened thereby and Sheikh of liohammera is now sanguine as to their remaining staunch and even assuming the offensive against Bawi, while Chaab Bawi and Bani Turut, contingent show signs of disintegrating and individual Shaikhs are beginning to make pacific overtures to Sheikh of Mohammerao Small patrol of our Cavalry on right bank came in contact with hostile Arabs yesterday eleven miles inland* A somewhat dubious message has reached me from Shushtar by telegraph 0 apparently from Sardar Jang, in reply to ray telegram 0 It is in much same terms as his reply to Sheikh of Kohammera as reported in my telegram 262 0 British Vice- Consul, Ahwaz will proceed however to fields as soon as road is passable and endeavour induce cooperation Bakhtiari Khans* Addressed Tehran, repeated to Foreign and Secretary of - State for India , i pPERSIA . W &amp; &amp;B. J [ • ' ' - mlitarv Deeypiier of telegram from sir W.Townley ' Teheran (d„ 3,50 P-m. r„ n p.m. February 16th, 1915 ) No. 70 Fflfaway vAih3.§lytj. Very secret. Minister for Foreign Affairs tells me that Djavid. Pasha has been recalled from Bagdad and that a German calling himself (group undecypherable) Hussein Bey or Pasha has arrived to take command of army. His Highness called my attention to adoption by Germans of Schiah Moslem Moine el Vesareh, Minister for Foreign Affairs' son and chef-de-cabinet has promised to get me con fidential information from Persian Consul at Bagdad about the numbers and movements of Turkish troops. Addressed to Foreign Office, sent to India and Bushire.'£1 155 In any further communication on the subject, please quote n.. 17976/15. and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, I % London. &gt;&gt; M o40 Mediate. I s Foreign Office February 17th, 1915. sir:- I am directed by Secretary Sir Edward Grey to transmit to you, herewith, to be laid before the Marquess of Crewe, a copy of a telegram from His ^ • Majesty's Minister at Teheran, regarding Turco-German Sir E. Grey would be glad to receive such observations as His Lordship may desire to offer on the points dealt with by Sir W. Townley.ti f\ CONFIDENTIAL. Sir W. Townley to Sir Edward Grey.—{Received February 15, 6‘30 p.m.) (No. 67.) I YESTERDAY Tehran, February 15, 1915. {February 15, 5'28 p.m.) ^ communicated to Minister for Foreign Affairs substance of Sir P. Cox’s telegram of 13th February respecting the situation at Ahwaz and necessity of instructing the Bakhtiari Khans to send sowars to protect pipe-line above Wais, and to Ahwaz to show that they are co-operating with Sheikh of Mohammerah to repel incursion of rebel Persian and Turkish Arabs. I ^ at the same time told Minister that I had every reason to believe that Vali of Pusht-i-kuh had made an arrangement with Turks diametrically opposed to the spirit of the declaration of neutrality made by Persia. I also took occasion to inform His Highness that it had come to my knowledge that Herr Schoenmann, so-called German consul at Sultanabad, now at Kasr-i-Shirin, had been endeavouring, in company with two Turkish officers, to get the Sinjabis to promise Turks a free passage through their territory. I impressed on Minister that such action on Schoenmann’s part makes it impossible for Persian Government to accept such a man as German consult Sultanabad. Minister expressed concurrence with my views, and added that appointment of this individual had not yet been put forward by German Legation, but that Persian Government is much perturbed at rumoured intention of German Government to send consuls to various places, amongst them Shiraz. _ . His Highness said he had no knowledge of Vali’s defection, but would make enquiries. I reminded him that I had brought rumour to his notice some time ago, when he had made same answer. .' . . Respecting Bakhtiari [? he said] that he must submit matter to Prime Minister, but that instructions had already been issued to Khan to move to protect oilfields and to assist generally to maintain order. _ . . . T I remarked that these vague instructions were clearly insufficient to-day, and 1 pointed out that good faith of Persian Government would surely come under suspicion if Turks and Germans and Persian preachers of Jihad were allowed to do what they liked, and no steps were taken to make it patent to all that Government is as sincerely neutral as it orofesses to be. , -i n His Highness protested vehemently that the Government could not be suspected of siding with [group omitted : ? Turks], and that energetic measures have been taken to stop public demonstrations and prevent preaching of Holy ai. This is true in Tehran and partially in other places. (Addressed to Foreign Office and Bushire.) fr ? ‘A 4 19 FEB 191517a76. 1.1694. 10,000.—11/1914. [1.211.] COPY OF TELEGRAM. Fbom Pc, CoXj Mohammerah Dated February 29JR,, Received at London Office r 222B* Situation at Aftwaz 9th February %s Shaikh of Mohammerah reports ? Turkish Government are now at Khafajiyah. Arabs mostly at Kut Saiyid Ali waiting for canoes to cross Karkhaho Officer Commanding 7th Rajputs is pressing for reinforcements which G 0 O 0 C 0 is considering possibili ty of sending Q All quiet at present at Ahwaz* No further action on part of Bawi who are not in themselves formidable^ but some of Chab of Fallahiyah have also shown signs of disaffection and about 200 have proceeded join Bawi* According to news from oil fields 7th February position there is quite satisfactory and normal* Addressed Foreign^ repeated Viceroy D s Camp, Tehran and Secretary of State for India*X — j 17976. 1. 1094. 10,000.- 11/1914. [L Sll.] COPY OF TELEGRAM. P I Cox, From Dated Received at London Office 52^ ^ \&gt; ffS /j %2 •e Tr 4 yf 11,44 (R) F^llswing fr§m Tica-Ctnsul at Ahwaz, February 6tho 'Eaiihtiari Khans arrived at the fields February 5th e I have had guards strengthened and have wired for money te be sent to fields from Ispahan as it is impassible to send frem here c I do net anticipate any fanatic treuble amongst Ba*ciiuiario In view of arrangements made I do net consider fields in danger if the Khans remain loyal, o Addressed to India^ repeated to India Office«&amp; J ou 17976. L 1634. 10,UUC.- COPY OF TELEGRAM. I From Sir Ptrcy C#x. Dated 7th. February, 1915. Received at London Office Midnight. 1915 .4 (R.) ify telegram ef yesterday. Consul at Mehamnerah reports by telegraph accerding te Oil Company’s clerk Ahwaz pipe broached in tire places Qraneh and near Wais. At any rate ia k oil ceased to reach Abadan between 5 and 5 yesterday afternoen. Refinery can go on working for one month if no crude oil.17976. 1. 1694. 10,000.- 11/1914. [L 211.] From Dated COPY OF TELEGRAM. X Viceroy, 7th February 1915. Received at London Office 10.56 p.m. Foreign, secret. Ahwaz. Cex reports February 5th:- (R) 'Developments came quickly and matter was dealt with urgently on telephone. Vice-Consul considered situation so imminently urgent owing to spread of Jihad movement, instigated by Turks and Chasban from Amara, that it was unsafe for Europeans to remain even until the arrival of Comet and they were withdrawn by Shushan January 31st and arrived at Mohammera safely. Carman representative at Wenchhaus at Ahwaz who was known to be in communication with enemy elected to remain which is in itself evidence of his complicity. Since then a battalion of Native Infantry has been sent up and is encamped at Aminia on opposite bank to Ahwaz. Sheikh of Mohammera sent up about a thousand of his own particular tribesmen whom he hopes will be against Jihad, but the powerful Bawi tribesmen who were also mobilised have refused to oppose movement if they have not actually joined it On February 2nd warrant officer of Comet was snot dead in the street by a Baluchi fanatic in Deputy-Governor’s employ. Since then no further developments have been reported As soon as Sheikh expressed inability to guarantee security of Europeans and Secretary ox State ordered a battalion to be sent t© Ahwaz to maintain order and resist expected raid by Turks from Bisaitin it was decided Germans could not safely be allowed to remain at Ahwaz or Mohammera. They were therefore placed under restraint and given a passage to Basra. Their property houses and offices were sealed by local authorities and by a British officer. Correspondence seized is, in the case of agent at Ahwaz, named17945. I. 1371. 10,000.- 9/1*14. [I. JU.l COPY OF TELEGRAM. Fkom Dated Received at London Office Heimlich, so incriminating as i® justify his treatment prisoner of war# Case of lUohammera agent, named Holst, still under consideration,'CONFIDENTIAL. Tetrograd, February 4, 1915. (No. 139.) (February 4, 9'40 p.m.) YOUR telegram No. 168 of 3rd February: Turco-Arab advance in Sontb-West Persia. Minister for Foreign Affairs has not the slightest objection to proposed despatch of troops. 512 i I3|5_J * RUSSIA 1*44-227]iVo CONFIDENTIAL. i v ■I - 1 / PERSIA Sir W. Townley to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received February 4, 5*35 p.m.) Tehran. (No. 52.) (February 4, 1915, 11*30 a.m.) MY telegram No. 47 of 3rd February . I could get no definite announcement from Minister for Foreign Affairs as to how the Persian Government would view a British expedition up the Karun, but he allowed that it was only natural, if it was seen that Persia could not protect interests that Great Britain is obliged to safeguard. Instructions have been sent to withstand Turks, but I gathered that Prime Minister and some other members of the Cabinet are afraid lest Persia may consequently find herself at war with Turkey. Foreign Minister himself is much more bellicose, and gave it as his opinion that Turkish advance must be resisted at all cost. He was personally responsible for warning in last clause of telegraphic instructions to Persian Ambassador at Constantinople. Your telegram No. 30 of 3rd February, since received. I have already informed both Prime Minister and Minister for Foreign Affairs that the “ Comet ” and “ Shaitan,” with guns and troops on board, have proceeded to Ahwaz. No protest was made. If I send in an official note on the subject it is sure to call forth some foolishly worded, querulous reply that will be annoying, without, of course, causing us to change our attitude. I will now make a similar verbal communi cation stating that the 7th Rajputs are proceeding up the river, and would propose not to send in an official note [? unless it] would appear from Persian answer that situation demands such a communication. (Sent to India, Bushire, and Mohammerah.)/ [•This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty's Government, and should be returned to the Foreign Office when done with unless &lt;&amp; required for official use,] O it r' h ^ • I i ^ RUSSIA, (13645/15) o M.LITAi^Y. CVDher telegram to Sir G.Buchanan (petrograd). Foreign Office, February 5th, 1915. 11.55 p.m No.183. &amp;iv U*Townley’s telegram No «52 (ol 4th February« Karun operations). You night communicate substance oi second para- graph verbally to Russian Minister lor Foreign Affairs. Cypher telegr am t o Sir . j.Iownley (Tehran) Foreign Office. February 5th, 1915. 11.55 p.m. No. 38 Your telegram No. 52 (of 4th February. Troops in Southern Persia). I approve your confining yourself to verbal intimationsofTtas Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government, and R3 ) should be returned to the Foreign Office when done with unless required for official use.] PERSIA MILITARY Copy. Decypher, Sir W. Tov/nley (Teheran) D. 8 a.m. R. noon. 1st February, 1915. No. 44. My inineciiately preceding telegram. Consul at Kermanshah reports that it is rumoured there that the Vali oi Push(t-i-kuli?) has joined Turks. I have told him to send special messenger to make sure. Persian Government have received no information in this sense. Prime Minister promised me to-day to inquire at once of the Governor-General of Arabistan but said that he did not credit report as the Vali has of late acted most loyally towards Government. Addressed to Foreign Office, Sent to India, Bushire, Mohanrnerah./ CONFIDENTIAL Sir W. Townley to Sir Edward Grey.—(Received February 1, 1-45 p.m.) FKRBIA , , Tehran, February 1, 1915. (No. 43.) R. P^J (February 1, 8 a.m.) MY telegram No. 32 of 28th January. Prime Minister, who has just called on me, informs me that necessary orders have been issued to Bakhtiaris to co-operate in defence of oilfields should Turco-Arab advance continue. His Highness expresses his conviction that forces on spot would suffice to safeguard oilfields and check inroad. Khans here had already sent instruc tions to Sardars to protect oil fields. (Sent to India, Bushire, and Mohammerah.;-i 8 6 From Sir P. Gox, 1st February 1915. (Addressed to India ; repeated to India Office.) File two river gunboats reached Ahwaz .list January, and all is quiet there to now. ■.■vjpoiwuijji uRegister No. Pat awry, w^th - Minute Paper. L+01 Secret Department. ^ . 0 . Under Secretary 4 Secretary of State Committee Under Secretary Secretary of State[This Documents the Property of His Britannic Majesty's Government, ana ■ * hom be retnm ed to the For eign OffirP wh on ..,,v required for official use.] |77 EMia . c , 5 C0py ‘ •fiQLmn.AT. Cyphur tolugram to Sir V. Tovmloy (Tohoran) Poroigii Oiiico, 4 p.ra. 31st Januarj', 1915. • I' T o. 27. Suer u' Yoiir uulugram No, (01 28 th January. Thro atoned Turkish invasion oi SN'N Persia). It is most dosirahlu that His Majesty’s Government should do punctually inionned oi measures contemplated hy Persian Government in consequence of 3 r our represen tations. It is also important to know what attitude Persian Government would be likely to adopt in the event of its becoming imperative to dispatch a British lorce up the Karim for protection of oil fields and pipe line!COPY OF TELEGRAM. 17S76. 1. 1694. 10.000.—11/1914. [1.211.] From Ur P. Cox Dated Basra, 29th. January, 1^15* ^ No* Received at London Office 7:2i 17c B. My telegram 150 B. Ahwaz. British subjects have imi withdrawn last night, expected Mehammerah this evening. Present jsitien oil fields satisfactory. fuller report will follow. Addressed Foreign; repeated to Viceroy's Camp, Tehran, Bushire and S, tf S. for l v No. 2 Received at London Office 8:11 p.m. 175 E. In amplification of my telegram 172 B 0 British Flee wisul at Ahwas having expressed conviction situation was getting worse id withdrawal of British subjects imperative, they ware embarked on the l '3huahan ,^ yesterday in the evening as reported and havs now arrived Mahansnerah* British Indian subjects and B&amp;gi&amp;d Christians who wished leave were also bretupat away simult meeusly in other craft. •turned to Amm,z. Bex ©re leaving he consigned houses and offices of iah subjects to Governor*s guards and warned them he wfuli (? return) “a few hours,, British subjects withdrawn consist of 31 m&amp;l** and 1 lady rerr&amp;ining at fields are about 20 in number. Position at fields ht no present cause for anxiety. Natives are friendly and Bakhtiari Vi3 on the point of arriving on annual visit and guards have been ^ngthened. I hope that presence of strong armed launches MomeV* and titan 11 together with 800 of Shciirh f B own tribesmen will serve to prevent hting at Ahwas and perhaps atop development of movement or at any rate - prevent) it from extending beyond Ahvmz towards oil fields orCOPY OF TELEGRAM. X From Sir P (k? Dated 26th, January, 1915* Received at London Office 10:33 o n ^37 g 9 Genera,] sit ®f the 27 th, is as ft Hews. 17976. 1.1694. 10,000.-11/1914. [1.211.] Aidr®as#i t* Far^igj ? Repeated t# Tahrar. Private Secretary t» Vioerey. ana iiy&gt;ia 351 sn n th© night Pram Ahwaz Vice-Consul reports U-day that large section af the ptpulatitn will undoubtedly join Jihad whan it reaches Kprunj and that Q^v^niar, who carrots n© 'weight, has now informed him that he cannot rely local tribesman nor answer for the saf&amp;ty of Europeans if thoy remain longor* Withdrawal &lt;sf British subjects has been •pposod by vicc-C&lt;m 8 ul but it would haws far* reaching results and is new under iisoussien. Meanwhile tm armed launches Coni©t n and w Shaitan M ha\ r @ started for Ahwaz 3/1 d. 800 Shaikh { g own tribesmen with two maxim guns l-^ave te-morrow, On Nasrie ai-i^ J 1 had is sni tribssmsn hirod. by Turks numbering seraral thousands in all have mm mebilisMig for n&lt;miz days, ha/e new crssssd the Euplirates and are beginning to move m Bs^ra by land. On Gurna side, Turks zrn nm in considerable fores a few mu$t bo mil#s above us and according t% natiw inf oration xxiianagt planning an attack #n Gurna in force simultanseu^ly with Arab attack m Basra but the fact that they are digging theiasslvos in suggests that th^ir intentions a.r« defensive rather than offensive for tho present Guma is vary strtng, and as regards mtvamsnt from Nasris zay information that tribal contingents are not pulling together and are short of ammunition; but after recent 'aaskai experience it is net safe te und&amp;r-raie their fighting valu^ r - their fanaticism is aroused mi as reported my telegram G £ Q &amp;o$z net feel abl© in these sireumstances te deplete' -- 'V Imm ediate Q%iftdential. The Under - Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Under-Secretary of State for India, and is directed by the Secretary of State to transmit the accompanying copies of telegram , as marked in the ' ? Foreign Office, jj-a*\.asf, 1916 '-[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government, and should be returned to the required for official use.] Foreign Office when done with unless PERSIA 0 Political, Do cypher telegram 'from Sir Townley (Tehran) cl» - pjn u January 28th, 1915. r, 11 I did not repeat Colonel Cox's telegrams Nos.157 and 141 from Basrah as I presume you have received them from India Office, Minister for Foreign Affairs was with me again when I received them. I therefore communicated substance of their contents to His Highness, I urged that no time should he lost in taking neces sary steps through Bakhtiarijg or otherwise to protect British subjects and property more espe cially oil fields. His Highness replied that the matter would receive immediate attention and that Persian frontier would be defended though this, he added, might (group undecypheratio ? mean) war with Turkey. Representations, he said, have already been made to Turkish Ambassador here and at Constantinople. Position of Persian Govern ment is very delicate as pro-Turkish or rather anti-Russian movement has attained such dimensions that it is doubtful if a declaration of war wou-a be approved by people. I have also telegraphed uo Sirdar Jang and Sirdar Bahadur calling upon them upon receipt of orders from Tehran to do their utmost to protect British property. I will also move Sirdar Assad and Samsam-Es- Sultaneh who are here, in same sense. Repeated to India and Basrah.Put away with 3 ^ 1 ^ 'Ig Secret Department. Letter from Dated Re^ 191 Formally acknowledged Date. Initials. Under Secretary i 'fX/y^s Secretary of State iS' 1 1 W&gt;/j Committee / Under Secretary ... .1 - SUBJECT. ^ //csi yks6$&gt; hr\AVtrrntsrdq h\ . o(vif\cC&lt;£ &lt;fj~ fcrfrjx# / ^*' \ ’-....V i j )PY TELEGRM FROM SECRETART OF STATE TO VICEROY, ARMY DEPARTMENT, DATED 27th January 1915. 1603. Your H. 3012. The position regarding the irko-Arab menace both on the Euphrates and the Tigris ides seems more threatening while thw Pipe line in the iwaz direction may be an object of attack at an early te and there can be no doubt that the Turks are sending Enforcements to Baghdad. Under these circumstances I ithorise you to despatch the 12th Brigade to the Shatt f you think fit and also a regiment of Cavalry if so isired. In any case it might be prudent to send a ivalry regiment to Karachi in anticipation. I presume tips with horse fittings are now readily available, iiat are the regiments composing 12th Brigade and who arnmands it I will let you know if my colleagues sanction roops being sent to Karun Valley.Immediate and (^ifidential. The Under - Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Under-Secretary of State for India, and is directed by the Secretary of State to transmit the accompanying copies of c\ telegram , as marked in the Foreign Office,MILIIaHY. j£M Decypher. 6ir Xownley (Teheran), D. 10.40 p.m. K, 3.15 p.m. Mo. 28 (R). January 26th, 1915. Following from air r. Cox:- **Following from Vice-Consul at iuiwaz:- Two letters received from oheikh of iVoham?nerai agent at Bisaitin, 20 miles M.n, of Hawize dated night of 23rd and morning of 24th. He reports that one Turkish Cavalry Regiment and one Infantry Regi ment with the oheikh Ohaspan of the leni Lam and a large number of arabs crossed river and laudeo at Markal 20 miles from Bisaitin on January 23rd and snould arrive at Bisaitin to-day. Beni Bmuturuf have all joined in response to i.ullan's cry of noly war. It is thought that raid may be mace towards Ahw&amp;z or v ohamaierah or possibly oil fields, deputy «* • Governor of Ahwaz says it will take ten or fifteen days to mobilise Sheikh’s forces. Addressed to Foreign Department, India*. I nave communicated substance of the above telegran to Persian Government and have urged steps be taken to protect British interests in far off oil i fields from any possible injury.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000419.0x000179_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/10/482</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000419.0x000179</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/10/482</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>File 3516/1914 Pt 5 'German War: Persia; situation in Arabistan 1915'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1915/1916</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-12-16T11:46:32</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">fre</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (196 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the volume.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence for this description commences at the inside front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 198; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The volume concerns events that happened in southern Persia and in the territories of the Shatt al-Arab, during the First World War. The main focus is the protection of oilfields.The volume covers:The Arab movement in Mesopotamia.Possible despatch of troops to the Kārun river and to Ahwaz [Ahvāz, Iran], to protect the oilfields.Spreading of the jihad movement amongst Arab tribes, seceding from Sheikh of Mohammerah [Khorramshahr, Iran].Withdrawal of British subjects from Ahwaz.Pipeline and telegraph line damaged by Bawi tribe near Ahwaz.Sheikh of Mohammerah's defeat of the Bawi tribe, in February 1915.German intrigues, and the arrest and deportation of the former German Consul at Bushire and of German agents.Russian defeat of Turkish forces at Dilman, Azerbaijan, in March 1915.Turkish occupation of Kasr-i-Shirin.Movements of German agents; protest of Persian Government against.Evacuation of British and Russians from Kerman.The volume’s principal correspondents are: Thomas William Holderness and Arthur Hirtzel, India Office; Eyre Alexander Barby Wichart Crowe, Foreign Office; Charles Hardinge, Viceroy of India; Walter Beaupre Townley and Charles Marling, British Ministers at Tehran; Percy Cox, Political Resident in Persian Gulf; Edward Grey, Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs; Strick, Scott and Co; Anglo-Persian Oil Company.There is a letter in French within the file, from the Swedish Minister for Foreign Affairs.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><geographic>Kārūn River</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Dilman</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Kasr-i-Shirin</geographic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Ambassador to Iran</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Viceroy and Governor-General of India in Council</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Emir of Mohammerah</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Anglo-Iranian Oil Company Limited</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Mesopotamia</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Persia</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Karbala</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Arabistan</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Ahwaz</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Shatt al Arab</geographic></subject><subject><topic>First World War (1914-1918)</topic></subject><subject><topic>International relations</topic></subject><subject><topic>Mesopotamian Campaign (1914-1918)</topic></subject><subject><topic>Oilfields</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000419.0x000179#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>