<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0002c4_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T11:21:53.103Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">.0 ■m ^ , CONFIDENTIAL. TREATIES AND AGREEMENTS . between THE BRITISH GOVERNMENT and CERTAIN ARAB RULERS AND AGREEMENTS BETWEEN THE SAID RULERS • INTER SE AFFECTING THE BRITISH GOVERNMENT. 10r neg microfilmed document do not photocopy use MANAGER GOVERNMENT OF INDIA PRESS, CALCUTTA 4 1926mm H mmTreaties and Agreements between the British Gov eminent and Certain Arah Rulers, and between these Millers, Inter Se. Serial No. Title, Date. 1 Treaty between the British Government and 'Abdul f Aziz bin 'Abdur Rahman bin Faisal Al-Saud, Ruler of Najd^ El Hassa, Qatif^ etc. December 26th, 1915. 2 Treaty between the British Government and Shaikh Abdullah bin Jasim bin Thani, Shaikh of Qatar. November 3rd, 1916. 2{tf) Letter from Sir P. Cox postponing enforcement of Articles 7, 8 and 9. Do. i m Shaikh Abdullah's notification prohibiting Arms Traffic. Do. 3 Treaty between British Government and King Faisal. October 10th, 1922. 4 Treaty and Undertakings in force between the Government of ^Iraq and His Highness the Sultan of Najd (Mohammerah Convention). May 5th, 1922. 5 Boundary Convention between the Shaikh of Kuwait and His Highness the Sultan of Najd. December 2nd, 1922, 6 Memorandum from His Excellency the High Commissioner for 'Iraq, to the Political Agent, Kuwait, regarding boundaries of Kuwait. April 19th, 1923. 7 Agreement between the British Government and His Highness the Sultan of Najd and its dependencies regarding the Najd Trans-Jordan frontier. November 2nd, 1925. 8 Correspondence relating to the demilitarisation of Kaf referred to in paragraph 2 of the above agreement. November 1st and 2nd, 1925. 9 Agreement between the British Government and His Highness the Sultan of Najd and its dependencies regarding the Najd-'Iraq frontier. November 1st, 1925. 10 Correspondence regarding the date on which the above agreement comes into effect, the extradi tion of refugee tribes and the settlement of claims arising from past raids across the Najd- 'Iraq frontier. October 19th, 20th and 31st 1925. November 1st and 2nd, 1925.Treaties and Agreements between the British Government and certain Arab Rulers, and between these Rulers Inter se. No. 1. I n the name of G od the M erciful, the C ompassionate. TEEATY BETWEEN THE BRITISH GOVEENMENT AND 'ABDUL f AZIZ BIN 'ABDUE EAHMAN BIN FAISAL AL -SA'UD, EULEE OF NAJD, EL HASSA, QATIF, ETC., DATED THE 26 th DECEMBEE 1915. 'Preamble. The High British Government on its own part, and 'Abdul 'Aziz bin 'Abdur Kahman bin Faisal Al-Sa'ud, Euler of Kajd, El Hassa, Qatif and Jubail, and the towns and ports belonging to them, on behalf of himself, his heirs and euccessors, and tribesmen, being desirous of confirming and strengthening the friendly relations which have lor a long time existed between the two parties, and with a view to consolidating their respective interests—the British Govern ment have named and appointed Lieu tenant-Colonel Sir Percy Cox, K.C .S .I., K.C.I.E., British Eesident in. the Persian Gulf, as their Plenipotentiary, to con clude a treaty for this purpose with 'Abdul 'Aziz bin 'Abdur Eahman bin Faisal Al-Sa'ud. The said Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Percy Cox and 'Abdul 'Aaiz bin 'Abdur Eahman bin Faisal Al-Sa'ud, hereafter known as ' Bin Sa'ad,' have agreed upon and con cluded the following articles;— I The British Government do acknow ledge and admit that Najd, A1 Hassa, Qatif and Jubail, and their dependencies and territories, which will be discussed and determined hereafter, and their ports on the shores of the Persian Gulf are the countries of Bin Sa'ud and of his fathers before him, and do hereby recognise the said Bin Sa'ud as the Independent Euler thereof and absolute Chief of their tribes, and after him bis sons and descendants by inheritance ; but the selec tion of the individual shall be in accord ance with the nomination by the living Euler) of his successor; but with the proviso that he shall not be a person antagonistic to the British Government in any respect; such as, for example, in regard to the terms mentioned in this Treaty. (J.wsjL* JI Jar IJjjtJlaxc j j | 'I ^ ti axbaJ/ ^ ^ iiUj} jOluij ^ JJ ^j(jLA-vu) ^ iiUfik-I ^JJ| AJOljjJl kj | CtJou: ^ uXJ Vjxi&amp;y | iDjciJl ^ f' '-ky ^ J^xJb lxaxj ^ ItXXC j ij&gt;xs }S'lb - jjxjm j) vj.-axs Icxiu ^ Laily Oj*.** ^ Ax * | J^aAJ) a)f ^ j Uik ^ j) wJukiiJI J , iSMr* * '• f j iX/jj w A Jw.a.Jj ^ ( ,U V^l 4 j'-ax I j . Ujilfu .a ^ ^-V! bjm*,) UI AA.la. ^jxx.x) jk*« ! 6.jyj - JiiM t /» 'ijjf f ( JII In the event of aggression by any Foreign Power on the territories of the countries of the said Bra Sa'ud and his descendants without reference to_ toe British Government and without giving her an opportunity of communicating with Bin Sa'ud and composing tbe matter, the British Government will aid Bin Sa'ud to such, extent and in such a manner as the British Government after consulting Bin Sa'ud may consider most effective for protecting his interests and countries. III Bin Sa'ud hereby agrees and promises refrain from entering into any corre spondence, agreement, or treaty, with any Foreign Nation or Power, and further to give immediate notice to the Political authorities of the British Gov ernment of any attempt on the part of any other Power to interfere with the above territories. IV Bin Sa'ud hereby undertakes that he will absolutely not cede, sell, mortgage, lease, or otherwise dispose of the above territories or any part of them, or grant concessions within those territories to any Foreign Power, or to the subjects of any Foreign Power, without the consent of the British Government. And that he will follow her advice unreservedly provided that it be not damaging to his own interests. V Bin Sa'ud hereby undertakes to keep open within his territories, the roads leading to the Holy Places, and to protect pilgrims on their passage to and from the Holy Places. VI Bin Sa'ud undertakes, as his fathers did before him, to refrain from all aggression on, or interference with the territories of Kuwait, Bahrain, and of the Shaikhs of Qatar and the Oman Coast, who are under the protection of the British Gov ernment, and who have treaty relations with the said Government; and the limits of their ferritories shall be hereafter determined. ^Lc ^ ^ !3l ^'1 ^Ij Jj*mj yf) d-xifc ItljJ AyHM- Sxi - dXIU/* ^ Jai^' r i* * * .. L/;^I 1 —'J 0 u/l - iU£ I ijyS &amp;*..) A' J*** ^ o' j o) ii/ 4 ! ;! c SaLi-' jUrl ijy ^»-'} blc. .J! ,i Jl O.v^a:'! I ,9 - V O &gt; ' J s-&gt; &lt;-&gt; j pyxs vj' J iiJ.o 1 J^l ajUs solcX^-I iy.^c UK^ liyXAM ^ y j - cx*j (.&lt;&gt;jk5 iSiiis- 1 j 0^ I 4- ^*^.')VII The British Government and Bin Sa ! ud agree to conclude a further detailed treaty in regard to matters concerning the two parties. Dated 18th Safar 133^ corresponding to 26th December 1915. (Signed and Sealed) ABDUL 'AZIZ AL-SA'UD. P. Z. COX, L t.- C ol., British Resident in the Persian Gulf. CHELMSFORD, Viceroy and Governor'General of India. This Treaty was ratified by the Viceroy and Governor-General of India in Council at Simla on the 18th day of July A. D, one thousand nine hundred and sixteen. A. H. GRANT, Secretary to the Government of India, Foreign and Foliiicoi Departments V uMj - JLflJjiloJ) irrt* I ^ j 9No TREATY BETWEEN THE BRITISH GOVERNMENT AND SHAIKH 'ABDULLAH BIN JASIM BIN THANI, SHAIKH OF QATAR, DATED THE 3 ed NOVEMBER 1916. Whereas my grandfather, the late Shaikh Mohammed bin Thani, signed an agreement on the 12th September 1868 engaging not to commit any breach of the Maritime Peace, and where as these obligations to the British Gov ernment have devolved on me his successor in Qatar. I I, Shaikh 'Abdullah bin Jasim bin Thani, undertake that I will, as do the friendly Arab Shaikhs of Abu Dhabi, Dibai, Shargab, Ajman, Ras-ul-Kbaima and L T mm-al-Qawain, co-operate with the High British Government in the suppression of the slave-trade and piracy and generally in the maintenance of the Maritime Peace. To this end, Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Percy Cox, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, has favoured me with the Treaties and Engagements, entered into between the Shaikhs abovemen- tioned and the High British Govern- rnect, and I hereby declare that I will abide by ttie spirit and obligations of the aforesaid Treaties and Engagements. II On the other hard, the British Gov ernment undertakes tha,t I and my subjects and my and their vessels shall receive all the immunities, privileges and advantages that are conferred on the friendly Shaikhs, their subjects and their vessels. In token whereof, Sir Percy Cox has affixed his signature with the date thereof to each and every one of the aforesaid Treaties and Engagements in the copy granted to me and I have also affixed my signature and seal with the date thereof to each and every one of the aforesaid Treaties and Engage ments, in two other printed copies of the same Treaties and Engngements, that it may not be hidden. III ind in particular, I, Shaikh Abdullah, have further published a proclamation, forbidding the import and sale of arms into my territories and port of Qatar; and in consideration of the undertaking into which I now enter, the British dXilcVVC iUjs* ^1 ^ axJI iux^l ^ yiO) wftjUcJ} ^* j I AiJlair b Uti ( |) i I axL-! j vjlzi) ; j v^^ J ' rb j' Jir* ^0) , o)*&gt;ifcL*J) flLei) - b y '*r ^JI djjjilXill d^jk.)) &amp;.^J| ( H ) ; ^j 3 . ) ^ 0 .ir osiiiAJ i ; A*. v&gt;5 iLjo . 7'* ^^ij 1 di ~^l ii&gt;f| Cl&gt;ltXitiL*&lt;J( i^xxf iX? i, USf 01 ^ ^J| ic: s^ax) oI^aUJI ^ ^ ilixj , ' 11 ^ ^ J J j UUxf j &lt;^4*5! j fis.3 jtilxi5 Government on its part agrees to grant me facilities to purchase and import, from the Maskat Arms Warehouse or such other place as the British Government may approve, for my personal use, and for the arming of my dependents, such arms and ammunition as I may reasonably need and apply for in such fashion as may be arranged hereafter through the Political Agent, Bahrein. I undertake absolutely that arms and ammunition thus supplied to me shall under no circum stances be re-exported from my territories or sold to the public, but shall be reserved solely for supplying the needs of my tribesmen and dependents whom I have to arm for the maintenance of order in my territories and the protection of my Frontiers, In my opinion the amount of my yearly* requirements will be up to five hundred weapons. IV I, Shaikh 'Abdullah, further undertake that I will not have relations nor corre spond with, nor receive the agent of, any other Power without the consent of the High British Government; neither will I, without such consent, cede, to any other Power or its subjects, land either on lease, sale, transfer, gift, or in any other way whatsoever. V I also declare that, without the consent of the High British Government, I will not grant pearl-fishery concessions, or any other monopolies, concessions, or cable landing rights, to anyone whomsoever. VI The Customs dues on the goods of British merchants imported to Qatar shall not exceed those levied from my own subjects on their goods and shall in no case exceed five per cent, ad valorem. British goods shall be liable to the pay ment of no other dues or taxes of any other kind whatsoever, beyond that already specified. VII I, Shaikh c Abdullah, further, in parti cular, undertake to allow British subjects to reside in Qatar for trade and to protect their lives and property. VIII I also undertake to receive, should the British Government deem it advisable, an Agent from the British Government, who shall remain at A1 Bidaa for the transaction of such business as the British Government may have with me and to watch over the interests of British traders, residing at my ports or visiting them upon their lawful occasions. *Aote. la original Treaty in the English version the word ' early ' has been written for 'yearly by' slip of the pen. Jsr' ^ y iS*.) ,b Uatlaj} ^*11 ^ .^9 aJjjJj JjjJb OIjo i' ^jJ| iili. j j iaa^ jj&gt;v oD(ar , '| ^jI.IOI ^J| byu*. ^ («•) i jxc u iajijj jlO)| jXc ^5° ^1 ^ ) I a UU j ^ - ^ ; l juljokj j| )) ^0 ^ (9) ^Lc *—(1) u/' ^ ^ ^ l J 1 ^ ^ I/® ^ (***■) 1 ^ ^ « L^^aa. a^ju'I is^Duc dJJIaxc liti (y) Jaj jki ^5 iJjjJI ^ Jx5) ^1 ^4*j'! v.llij.r j (A) dJjdJf j-Iaj |»&gt;| ^xJ! JilAjI &gt;1^ 3) Jjiji ^ic axSj^Jf j Ub| j vjjdWl j txj diiJjuJl jjlxxJI ^5 ^xx/l^J) - tixi) l ^xLaljJIIX Further, I undertake to allow the establishment of a British Post Office and a Telegraph iustaliation anywhere in my territory whenever the British Government should hereafter desire them. I also undertake to protect them when established. X On their part, the High British Gov ernment, in consideration of these Treaties and Engagements that I have entered into with them, undertake to protect me and my subjects and territory from all aggression by sea and to do their utmost to exact reparation for all injuries that I, or my subjects, may suffer when proceeding to sea upon our lawful occa sions. XI They also undertake to grant me good offices, should I or my subjects be assailed by land within the territories of Qatar. It is, however, thoroughly understood that this obligation rests upon the British Gov ernment only in the event of such aggres sion whether by land or sea, being un provoked by any act or aggression on the part of myself or my subjects against others. In token whereof I, Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Percy Cox, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, and I, Shaikh 'Abdullah bin Jasim bin Thani, have respectively signed and affixed our seal to this original document and four copies, thereof. Dated 6th Moharram 1335, correspond ing to 3rd November 1916. (Signed and sealed) 'ABDULLAH BIX JASIM, Chief of Qatar. P. Z. COX, Ma jor-General, Tolitical Resident in the Persian Gulf, (Signed) CHELMSFORD. Viceroy and Governor- General of India, This treaty was ratified by the Viceroy and Governor-General of India in Council at Delhi on the 23rd day of March A.D, one thousand nine hundred and eighteen. (Signed) A. H. GRANT, Secretary to the Govt, of India, i Ot eign and Political Department, jloj tiJ i ayiU (q) ^ J** ji^i ; of^ALAj) ZjUj d-ij.jd&amp;Vt txtJ) alaJ!. ((♦) U*'* ^jjf OJU j ISUJI J V* ^ ; Ul J/ JS J J ; ^uj) - 'ijSlai] UJUm.) fJ^H (.xuib C'' 1^1 (( j) ^ l^xcf-we JI pixjj ^ tisij jlaS ^Ix ikslsjj} ' ^ ^ y* b tj'| v»JUj ^Xr j ; U i£ ; Ux^l dJ ajjaxr r irro r u , - IIII ^9 AL'Ioa*0 No. TRANSLATION OP A LETTER ADDRESSED BY POLITICAL RESIDENT, PERSIAN GULF, TO SHAIKH OE AL QATAR. After compliments. —Whereas Your Honour has to-day entered into and signed with me on behalf of the British Govern ment an agreement or treaty, with the object of cementing the relations between the High British Government and your self and whereas Your Honour has ex pressed the opinion that the time has not yet come for giving effect to Articles (7), (8) and (9) which relate to :— (i) The admission of British subjects to Qatar for trade. {i%) The admission of an Agent on behalf of Government. {Hi) The establishment of Post and Telegraph Offices in your terri tory. Therefore I, on behalf of the British Government, accept your opinion and hereby inform you that the British Gov ernment sees no present necessity for the execution of these measures and will refrain from pressing for them until some future time when the need for them shall be manifest, and that effect will not be given to these articles without full con sultation with you and the obtaining of your consent. And whereas you have represented to me that you and your dependants possess a good many slaves from of old time, pre vious to this Treaty, and that it would be difficult if the officials of Government were to interfere between them and their masters, accordingly I inform you that I recognise how you are placed in regard to this question and that supposing that you accord your negroes fair and just treatment there will not be interference on the part of Government representatives in the matter. This is what had to be explained and may God preserve you. P. Z. COX, Lieutenant-Colonel, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf- Dated A1 Bida ; 3rd November 1916.—- (Moharram 6th, 1335). 7 2(a)' aW) 6iSi)&gt;[xs° y SJoUaJjiJI fZjxc j ) (v) OI^JI s-97 ^ (^); ( A ); j]a3 buy| J^5 (1) J) wliiJU J/ 5 (0 ^ (r) &amp;jljJJb li| Ajjir jlui c^&gt;yi D ^J| J SxilXi t/* (J oa J! j-juaj D O«J ojtJ; ^CCUJ) jj ^ijb by^A^il ^1 ^ ) ftyy* 1 bib ^cuai WU ^lo^l j ^/jJkXC ^ji/ebiJ f|jb &lt; jj JU &gt;U j Uib ''iJiilc j aJj-iU* 'iL»[*y* r^ij (Sd). P. Z. COX. - ^ I q n yyy'y ^ . A (fTO ^ Jlj'-W}No. PROCLAMATION. Eo it known to all who may see this ; Whereas it has become known to ns that traffic in arms into British India, Persia, Kuwait, Bahrain and the Trucial Coast is prohibited. I, the undersigned, 'Abdullah bin Jasim bin Thani, Shaikh of Qatar, have decided to do all in my power to assist the British Government in putting a stop to this illegal traffic, and I hereby declare that, from the date of this proclamation, the importation and sale of arms, cartridges, and all munitions, into our territory, and the exportation of the same to other places, are absolutely prohibited. All arms and ammunition, imported into Qatar territory or exported therefrom, will, in future, be liable to seizure and confiscation. That it may not be hidden. (Signature and seal of) 'ABDULLAH BIN JASIM AL THANI, Chief of Qatar. Dated at A1 Bida; 6th Moharram 1335 (Srd November lUIG). 2(b). • Lba' dJI ^ KJ- iiifaxc ^x&amp;ll aliol ^1^*1 jki &amp;J ^axuJI HxQxJj dJ^Jl i 6 J^ gjjfc ^J) iXijS?'] J hy^- a; Uf ^j| ul* j J5 f^4, ^lj ^ Lcj *s* tyi/* ^oLail^ j \a' 3 ^J| tox*e}l • Jii'l ,^311)1 ^15 ^ AUI J.XC Mi ^ 19 No. 3 TREATY BETWEEN HIS BRITAN NIC MAJESTY AND HIS MAJESTY THE KING OF 'IRAQ. His Britannic Majesty of the one part : and His Majesty the King of 'Iraq of the other part; Whereas His Britannic Majesty has recognised Eeisal Ibn Hussein as consti tutional King of 'Iraq : and Whereas His Majesty the King of 'Iraq considers that it is to the interests of 'Iiaq and will conduce to its rapid advancement that he should conclude a Treaty with His Britannic Majesty on the basis of alliance: and Whereas His Britannic Majesty is satisfied that the relations between him self and His Majesty the King of 'Iraq can now be better defined by such a Treaty of Alliance than by any other means: Eor this purpose the High Contracting Parties have fippointed as their Pleni potentiaries . His Majesty the King of the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland and of the British Dominions beyond the Seas, Emperor of India ; Sir Percy Zachariah Cox, G.C.M.G., G.C.I.E., K,C.S.I., High Commissioner aud Consul-General of His Britannic Majesty in 'Iraq: His Majesty the King of 'Iraq : His Highness Sir Saiyid c Abd-ur- Bahman, G.B.E., Prime Minister and Naqib-al-Ashraf, Baghdad : Who, having communicated their full powers, found in good and due order, have agreed as follows :— Article 1. —At the request of His Majesty the King of 'Iraq, His Britannic Majesty undertakes subject to the pro visions of this Treaty to provide the State of 'Iraq with such advice and assistance as may be required during the period of the present Treaty, without prejudice to her national sovereignty. His Britannic Majesty shall be represented in 'Iraq by a High Commissioner and Consul-General assisted by the necessary staff. Article II. —His Majesty the King of 'Iraq undertakes that for the period of the present Treaty no gazetted official of other than 'Iraq nationality shall be appointed in 'Iraq without the concurrence of His Britannic Majesty. A separate agreement shall regulate the numbers and conditions of employment of British officials so appointed in the 'Iraq Govern ment,#0? 10 A) Hole 111. His Majesty tlio Tving of Iiaq agrees to frame an Organic Law for presentation to the Constituent Assembly of Iraq and to give effect to the said law which shall contain nothing contrary to the provisions of the present Treaty and shall take account of the rights, wishes and interests of all populations inhabiting Iraq. This Organic Law shall ensure to all complete freedom of conscience and the i roe exercise of all forms of worship, subject only to the maintenance of public older and morals. It shall provide that no discrimination of any kind shall be made between the inhabitants of 'Iraq on the ground of race, religion or language, and shall secure that the right of each community to maintain its own schools for the education of its own members in its own language, while conforming to such educational requirements of a general nature as the Government of 'Iraq may impose, shall not be denied or impaired. It shall prescribe the constitutional pro- cedure whether legislative or executive, by which decisions will be taken on all matters of importance, including tho^e involving questions of fiscal, financial and military policy. Article IV — Without prejudice to the provis'ons of Articles XVII and XVIII ot this Ireaty, His Majesty the Kins of Iraq agrees to bo guided by the advice of Ills Britannic Majesty tendered through the High Commissioner on all important matters affecting the international and nnancial obligations and interests of His ^ T nl0 t Ma j?!*y ft* tIle whale period of this Treaty His Majesty the Kin- of Iraq will fully consult the High Commis sioner on what is conducive to a sound thTS I® 1 P0lic y and wi!I —r- the stability and good organisation of the na /J Cf f p the ' Xra q Government so long as that Government is under financial obligations to the Government of His Britannic Majesty. M ^ the King Of Iiaq shall have the right of representation Phws 1 ? SUCl1 other wP'tals and places as may be agreed upon by the High Contracting Parties. Where His Majesty the King of Iraq is Tot rep^ sented he agrees to entrust the protection ot Iraq nationals to His Britannic Maiestv moMajesty has agreed to a X? I app r ot n t- undertakes to'useh^ goof S tostu/c11 the admission of 'Iraq to membership of the League of Nations as soon as possible. Article VII.—His Britannic Majesty undertakes to provide such support and assistance to the armed forces of His Majesty the King of 'Iraq as may from time to time be agreed by the High Con tracting Parties. A separate agreement regulating the extent and conditions of such support and assistance shall be coneluded between the High Contracting Parties and communicated to the Council of the League of Nations. Article VIII. —No territory in 'Iraq shall be ceded or leased or in any way placed under the control of any Foreign Power; this shall not prevent His Majesty the King of 'Iraq from making such arrange ments as may be necessary for the accom modation of foreign representatives and for the fulfilment of the provisions of the preceding Article. Article IX. —His Majesty the King of 'Iraq undertakes that he will accept and give effect to such reasonable provisions as His Britannic Majesty may consider necessary in judicial matters to safeguard the interests of foreigners in consequence of the non-application of the immunities and privileges enjoyed by them under capitulation or usage. These provisions shall be embodied in a separate agreement, Avhich shall be communicated to the Council of the League of Nations. Article X. —The High Contracting Parties agree to conclude separate agree ments to secure the execution of any treaties, agreements or undertakings which His Britannic Majesty is under obligation to see carried out in respect of 'Iraq. His Majesty the King of 'Iraq undertakes to bring in any legislation necessary to ensure the execution of these agreements. Such agreements shall be communicated to the Council of the League of Nations. Article XI. —There shall be no discri mination in 'Iraq against the nationals of any State, member of the League of Nations, or of any State to which His Britannic Majesty has agreed by treaty that the same rights should be ensured as it would enjoy if it were a member of the said League (including companies in corporated under the laws of such State), as compared with British nationals or those of any foreign State in matters concerning taxation, commerce or naviga tion, the exercise of industries, or profes sions, or in the treatment of merchant vessels or civil aircraft. Nor shall there be any discrimination in 'Iraq against goods originating in or destined for any of the said States. There shall be freedom12 of transit under equitable conditions across 'Iraq territory. Article XII. —No measure shall be taken in 'Iraq to obstruct or interfere with missionary enterprise or to discriminate against any missionary on the ground of his religious belief or nationality, provided that such enterprise is not prejudicial to public order and good government. Article J:///.—His Majesty the King ol 'Iraq undertakes.: to co-operate, in so far as social, religious and oilier condi tions may permit, in the execution of any common policy adopted by the League of Nations for preventing and combating disease, including diseases of plants and animals. Article XIV. —His Majesty the King of 'Iraq undertakes to secure the enaet- ment, within twelve months of the com ing into force of this Treaty, and to ensure the execution of a Law of Anti quities based on the rules annexed to Article 421 of the Treaty of Peace signed at Sevres on the 10th August, 1920. This Law shall replace the former Otto man Law of Antiquities, and shall ensure equality of treatment in the matter of archaeological research to the nationals of all States members of the League of Nations, and of any State to which His Britannic Majesty has agreed by treaty that the same rights should be ensured a^ it would enjoy if it were a member of the said League, Article XV, A separate agreement shall regulate the financial relations bet ween the High Contracting Parties. It shall provide, on the one hand, for the transfer by His Britannic Majesty's Government to the Government of 'Iraq of such works of public utility as may be agreed upon and for the rendering bv liis Britannic Majesty's Government of such financial assistance as may from time to time be considered necessary tor Iraqi and, on the other hand, for the progressive liquidation by the Govern ment of'Iraq of all liabilities thus in curred. Such agreement shall be com municated to the Council of the League of Nations. 0 Artwle j^/.—So far as is consistent with his international obligations His Britanuip Majesty undertakes to place no obstacle m the way ol the association of t he otate of 'Laq for customs or other purposes with such neighbouring Arab states as may desire it. Article XVII. —Any difference that may arise between the High Contracting laities as to the interpretation of the provisions of this Treaty shall he referred13 to the Permanent Court of International Justice provided for by Article 14 of the Covenant of the League of Nations. In such case, should there be any discre pancy between the English and Arabic texts of this Treaty, the English shall be taken as the authoritative version. Article XVIII. —This treaty shall come into force as soon as it has been ratified by the High Contracting Parties after its acceptance by tile Constituent Assembly, and shall remain in force for twenty years, at the end of which period the situation shall be examined, and if the High Contracting Parties are of opinion that the Treaty is no longer required it shall be terminated- Termi nation shall be subject to confirmation by the League of Nations unless before that date Article VI of this Treaty has come^ into effect, in which case notice of termination shall be communicated to the Council ol the League of JNiiiions, Nothing shall prevent the High Contract ing Parties from reviewing from time to time the provisions of this Treaty, and those of the separate Agreements arising out of Articles VII, X and XV, with a v iew to any revision which may seem desirable in the circumstances then exist ing, and any modification which may be agreed upon by the High Contracting Parties shall be communicated to the Council of the League of Nations. The ratifications shall be exchanged at Baghdad. The present Treaty has been drawn up in English and Arabic. One copy in each language will remain deposited in the archives of the 'Iraq Government, and one copy in each language in those of the Government of His Britannic Majesty. 1$ WITNESS OF WHICH the res pective Plenipotentiaries have signed the present Treaty and have .affixed thereto their seals. Hone at Baghdad in dupli cate this tenth day of October, One thousand nine hundred and twenty-two of the Christian Era, corresponding with the nineteenth day of Safar, One thousand three hundred and fortv Hijrah, ^ P. Z. COX, Sis Britannic Majesty's Eigh Commissioner in 'Iraq, 'ABH-UK-RAHMAN, Naqib-al-Ashraf of Baghdad and Prime Minister of the 'Iraq Government,No. TREATY AND UNDERTAKINGS IN FORCE BETWEEN THE GOV ERNMENT OE 'IRAQ AND H. H. THE SULTAN OE NAJD, SIGN ED AT MOHAMMERAH ON THE 5 TH MAY 1922. In the name of God the Merciful, the Compassionate. With a view to securing friendship and good relations between the two Govern ments of 'Iraq and Najd. We, the undersigned delegates, ap pointed by His Majesty Eaisal, I, King of 'Iraq, and by His Highness 'Abdul Aziz ion Sa'ud, Sultan of Najd, and its dependencies, and by His Excellency Major-General Sir P. Z. Cox, G.C.M.G., G.C.I.E., K.C.S.L, His Britannic Majesty's High Commissioner in 'Iraq in order to draft a Treaty between the 'Iraq and Najd Governments, have agreed upon the following articles :— Article The tribes known as the Muntafiq, Dhafir and Amarat, will belong to 'Iraq. Both Governments, that is to say the Government of Iraq and the Government of Najd, guarantee mutually that they will prevent aggression by their tribes on the tribes of the other, and will punish their tribes for any such aggres sion, and should the circumstances not permit cf such punishment, the two Gov ernments will discuss the question of taking combined action according to the good relations prevailing between them. (ft) The Najd delegate having refused to accept the boundaries asked for by the 'Iraq Government, the following prin ciple was laid down :— According to Article 1 (a) the Muntafiq Dhafir and 'Amarat tribes belong to 'Iraq, similarly the Shammar Najd belong to Najd. The wells and lands used from old times by the 'Iraq tribes shall belong to 'Iraq and the wells and lands used from old times by the Shammar Najd shall belong to Najd. In order to determine the location of these lands and wells i-Jar j ^Jl IjJSJ Jjx*, j ajr 'iolac - ^ ^ J[rV - ^ ^ ^ ^ ■ r 1 ' jt^JI Uiiuj W *oUl y[^e ^ ( ' ) U|^ (31^1 hla.X'* ^j oI/*-' ^ . ^Jl ^ic UAj.]!,&gt;i,c ob»jk*j w -iotj J LkAa-cL-j ^ UiytifcS i) ^1 yjSxJ v - j ^ jo I j D L-JjcU'e J&gt;\9 ^ ( »-» ) lyxlla jja 'J ^xaJaJI^ jSi&amp;e ( | ) ^1^5 ^J1 j^Jai dil ^Jl As* J** y J' ^ ^jJ) as* Ous J j&lt; J h (J ^IJ v+h*-' J+band to fix a boundary line in accord ance with this principle a Committee shall be formed consisting of two persons with local knowledge from each Govern ment, and presided over by a British official selected by the High Commission er ; the Committee will meet in Baghdad to fix the final boundaries, and both parties will accept these boundaries with out any objection. Article 2. —The two Governments, 'Iraq and Najd, guarantee to ensure the safety of the pilgrim routes and protect pilgrims from every kind of molestation so long as they are within their boundaries, as has already been guaranteed by the Sultan of Najd to His Britannic Majesty's Government in Article 5 of the Treaty between them. Article 3.—(a) The two Governments agree that commercial intercourse shall be free from restrictions, and that each Government shall treat merchants be longing to the other in the same way as it treats its own merchants. (b) Raw or manufactured products of Kajd when imported into 'Iraq, and similarly raw and manufactured products of 'Iraq when imported into Najd shall be subject to the same tariff as prevails in the case of other friendly countries, in respect of import, export, transit, and re-export duties, and all other Custom jaiatters. (c) The two Governments shall have the right to increase their Customs duties and to levy fresh local and special tax ation not in force at the present time, provided that such alteration shall be similar to those enforced against other friendly countries. Each Government shall inform the other of any regulations issued by it in these matters. Article 4. —The two Governments agree to freedom of travel in their respective countries for purposes of trade or pilgrim age, pro7ided that travellers are in pos- (Jjlaj! U} IjiJ) ^ &gt; - iu*la.aJ| Cl/J' ^ ; jfyle vJ.ifc.Ifc&gt; O* iJJ iiilLa. i.'tjSis-' .A* 3 OJiyXj Ui' aaJtl'l xjUJ| - j'aaJ &amp;A*Ja,kj| OUJ ( t-j ) j ijLcLwJj^ ijjljkijaJl OIL/*t_*^J) i*j(j asij J) oUi)f Cl&gt;^yasxy* ^iJ| Lai ^ * ofjjLalfj olojiyf J ) | 6-X£j.S wOif-S J ^ J M l/ c OUJI ^Lc oUajJl*/® ^laJU (J./ ^ I ' ^j s ^lyi xoiji J/*^) kf**session of passports issued by their own Goyernment, Each Government shall inform the other of any regulations issued by it in this matter. Article 5.—Any tribes belonging to one of the countries which settles in the other country shall pay grazing fees. Article 6.-1x1 the event (which God forbid) of a breach in the relations between either of the Governments and the British Government, this treaty shall become null and void. Signed (at Failiyah near Muhammerah), on Priday, 7th Ramadhan, 1340, equal to May 5th, 1922. Delegate of the King of 'Iraq, King Paisal, I, Minister of Communications and Works, (Sd.) SCJBIH. Delegate of His Highness the Sultan of Najd and its Dependencies, 4 Abdul 'Aziz ibn Sa'ud. Secretary to His Highness, (Sd.) AHMAD A L THANAIYAN AL SAOUD. Delegate of His Excellency the High Commissioner of His Britannic Majesty. Secretary to His Excellency, (Sd.) B. H. BOURDILLON. xjU ) aJLJI )) iJ-Aflk. |j) &gt; i-c j &gt;, W* o/ /# &amp;•***' fy} j wLJUj J aJ| . dlJiyt kz/'-j '''*' h (JwAii (3^*''' Jj»l O^Xam I Al^laijXJ ji*** 0^.9. AM J' ^UJI ^o 'xJ I 'i^ 3 dX.'«l-i' 5 jXi j L i* POSTCRIPTION. • ^ 1. This treaty shall not be valid until ^ ^i, ^ it has been ratified by Their Majesties the .... .... ^ ..... ... .. t ruler of 'Iraq and Najd, and by His ) u-J &lt;j • a Excellency the High Commissioner. . ^lw( ^oiJf17 2. The delegate of Najd guarantees that, pending the decision of the Com mittee which will meet in Baghdad, the tribes of Najd will not attack the tribes of 'Iraq. aj) wI : Uitj KING OF 'IRAQ. (Seal) FAISAL IBN AL HUSAIN. THE SULTAN OF NAJD AND ITS DEPENDENCIES, C ABDUL 'AZIZ IBN 'ABDUL EAHMAN AL SA'UD, has agreed to the Articles oj this Frotocol, (Seal) &amp;jJ»laj'D| «jJl&gt; o)^ , jlc o^*.w. ! ! v*' A L In the name of God the Merciful, the Compassionate. This Protocol defining the boundaries between the two Governments of 'Iraq and Najd is appended to the agreement made at Muhammerah on the seventh day of Ramadhan, the Blessed in the Year 1340, which corresponds to the fifth day of May of the Year 1922. Article 1.—{a) The frontier from the east begins at the junction of the Wadi al 'Aujah (W. el Audja) with Al-Batin, and from this point the Najd frontier passes in a straight line to the well called Al-Wuqubah (El Ukabba), leaving Al- Lulaimiyah (Dulaimiya) and Al-Wuqubah (El Ukabba) north of the line, and from Al-Wuqubah (El Ukabba) it continues, N, W. to Bir Ansab (Bir Unsab). d.iys-'l ( JJV;/'! ) oi' iUsSU^'l ^ J**' {J* •» l ,p|i ^ yjr' ; ) pXsiijMje kA. ( j x * JU-W ) i (jX) - L -fLa'}] jii Ljji .i J)U«i19 'Iraq wells for water, provided that these wells are nearer to them than those within the Najd boundaries. Article 3. —The two Governments mutually agree not to use the watering places and wells situated in the vicinity of the border for any military purpose, such as building forts on them, and not to concentrate troops in their vicinity. Article 4.—The delegates of the two Governments have agreed to the above terms of this Protocol and have affixed thereto their signatures in £ ITqair, on the 12th day of Eabi 4 II, 1341, corresponding to December 2nd, 1922. J r' 1 ^ J| .JtX jlfllj slfj) '?S | ^ ^ J ) Jf-iu) %&gt;.aJ ( iwiyi ) iijUJl u^V-;(Jyyv* H ) ^ () jAXJ i;o)*jd£ n-- ^ ; jJUJUUI; j v— gJt 4JJ)j u/^'b - fjijj] Representative of His Majesty the King of 'Iraq. (Sd.) SUBIH, KING OF 'IEAQ (Seal) PAISAL IBN AL-HUSAIN, Eepresentative of His Highness, Sultan of Najd, (Sd.) 'ABDTJLEAH SA'ID DAMBTJJI. The Sultan of Najd and its Dependen cies 'Abdul 'Aziz Bin 'Abdur Rahman al Sa'ud has agreed to the Articles of this Protocol. ^ t** ♦Asii ,j^aJL&lt; (JV' iSbsttM lj.ii *1L20 In the name of God the Merciful, the Compassionate PROTOCOL NUMBER. TWO. Article 1. —Whereas the two Govern ments of 'Iraq and Najd have mutually agreed upon the definition of their respec tive boundaries they further agree that should any tribe or section of a tribe which is outside the boundaries of, and not subject to either Government desire to offer its allegiance to one of them, they will not prevent it from doing so. Article 5.—Whereas the Customs duties in both countries are mutually known, all merchandise exported from, imported into, or passing through the territory of either country, shall be sub ject to these recognised duties and Cus toms regulations. Both Governments further agree mutually by all means in their power to put an end to the practice prevailing among the tribes of taking Khawah. Article 5.^The dnly appointed dele gates of both Governments have agreed to the foregoing clauses of this Protocol and have set to it their signatures in 'Uqair, on the 12th day of Rabi' II 1341, corresponding to the 2nd of Decem ber, 1922. Representative of His Majesty the King of ' Iraq, (Sd.) SUBIH. KING OF 'IRAQ, (Seal) FAISAL IBN AL HUSAIN. Ptcpresentative of His Highness the Sultan of Najd, (Sd ? ) 'ABDULLAH SAID DAMBUJL The Snltan of Najd and its Dependen cies 'Abdul 'Aziz ibn 'Abdnl Rahman al Sa'ud has agreed to the Articles of this Protocol. (Seal) Translator's note. The referenees are to Map Asia 1,000,000 Geographical Section, General Staff. War Office, 19iT-18. The spoiling of the place names in brackets is that given in the abo\e Map. UftAj) S» •A*' 5 ^ vj' ^ 0) y ^ ^ vj' - I v joU« rWcj' dir*' JI l { Lj* ^ &gt; .war I vJ- {r) ^ ^Jxi] J|^))l^^3c 5 U/- U^ jo | i |^*kib kiL-yi^ ^ illcl . j SlI U a'ool ^ ; Jfjhj- jy£ ^yo SjJLc ^ul pyi ^Aa*JI ; aio «—aiil) I s r r r ij 3 ^ kj** &lt;Ajc ^yo ^lc yijx))j.X£21 No. 5- u KUWAIT—NAJD BOUNDARY CONVENTION. kijc -5 ^Xi on the West ridge called the East by In the name of God the Merciful, the Compassionate. The frontier between Najd and Kuwait begins in the West from the junction of the Wadi al Aujah (W. al Audja) with the Batin (El Batin), leaving Eaq'i (Rikai) to Najd, from this point it con tinues in a straight line until it joins latitude 29° and the red semi-circle referred to in Article 5 of the Anglo- Turkish Agreement of 29th July 1913. The line then follows the side of the red semi-circle until it reaches a point terminating (sic) on the coast south of Kas al-Qali'ah (Eas el Kaliyah) and^ this is the indisputable southern frontier of Kuwait territory. The portion of territory bounded on the North by this line and which is bounded by a low mountainous Shaq (Esh Shakk) and on the sea and on the South by a line passing from West to East from Shaq (Esh Shakk) to 'Ain al 'Abd (Ain el Abd) and thence to the coast north of Eas al Mish'ab (Eas Mishaab), in this territory the Governments of Najd and Kuwait will share equal rights until through the good offices of the Government of Great Britain a further agreement is made between Najd and Kuwait concerning it. The map on which this boundary has been made is Asia 1—1,000,000, made by the Eoyal Geographical Society under the direction of the Geographical Section General Staff and printed at the War Office in the year 1918. 'Written in the port of 'Uqair and signed by the representatives of both Governments on the second day of December 1922 corresponding to 13th of Eabi' al Thani, 1341. (Sd.) Abdullah Sa'id Damluji, Eepres- entative of H. H. the Sultan of Najd. (Sd.) J. C. More, Major, Political Agent, Kuwait. I have agreed to the contents of this agreement. Seal, Sultan of Najd and its dependencies, 'Abdul 'Aziz bin 'Abdul P^ahman as-Sa'ud. I have agreed to the contents of this agreement. Seal Hakim of Kuwait, Ahmad al-Jabir as-8ubah. [Translator's note, —The spelling of place names in brackets is that used in the rfiap referred to ia the treaty,) bjic^siyi! I5 ^ ^ « LyJ) ' JaA. Li-'b HoUb l^jJ) 1^1 55 M (Jj^l kar 1 ! ^ HIT *** J-aJ yf^) Jfiy't )JUJu i | _J J I h - « -All &gt;» \ L *1 ^ .!. ^ &lt;i^ j 1 c/' 6 V r* ^ ' ^ r ] ) JL-i JLLJI ; 'Wl fjJdi I WjUU) U^i L4J j SJ O ^ LSLajj -'1 J V */C J iy*^l I ' : l &lt;c ' ijjj ,s:' | iJLjl,**'') Sjjjk) iUf-Ldl jjjj n 1 a ^ ^ ^ ^) ^/* ^ ir (jUjJ} 1 ^rr ^ f irt^t Ji5 ^ V;^' ! ^IkL- d^ls£ aJJMxc vjuJltix* ^ iSx24 Ko. 7. AGREEMENT BETWEEN THE EHITISH GOVERNMENT AND HIS HIGHNESS THE SULTAN OF NEJD AND ITS DEPENDENCIES REGAEDING THE NEJD-TRANS- JOEDAN FRONTIER. T hk H adda A geeement. The High British Government on its own part and His Highness ' AbduM-'Aziz ibn 4 Abdn'r-Eahman Al-Faisal Al Sa'nd, Sultan of Nejd and its Dependencies on behalf of the Government of Nejd, on his part, in view of the friendly relations which exist between them, being desirous of fixing the frontier between Nejd and Trans-Jordan and of settling certain questions connected therewith, The High British Government have named and appointed Sir Gilbert Clayton, K.B.E.. C .E.j C.M.G., as their Commissioner and Plenipotentiary, to conclude an Agree ment for this purpose with Sultan * Abdu'l-* Aziz ibn ' Abdu'r-Bahman Al-Faisal Al Sa'ud on behalf of Kejd. In virtue of which the said Sultan 4 AbduVAziz ibn 4 Abdu'r-Hahman Al- Faisal Al Sa'ud and the said 8ir Gilbert Clayton, have agreed upon and concluded the following Articles Article 1.—The frontier between Nejd and Trans- Jordan starts in the north-east from the point of intersection of meridian 39 0 E and parallel 32 C N, which marks the termination of the frontier between Iseid and 'Iraq, and proceeds in a straight line to the point of intersection of meridian 37 C E and parallel SlWN, and thence along meridian S7 0 E to the point of its intersection with parallel 31-25 N. From this point, it proceeds in a straight ^ lino to the point of intersection of meridian 3&amp; C E and parallel 30 N, leaving all pro- iecting edges of the V\ adi Sirhan in Kejd territory; and thence proceeds along meridian 38 0 E to the point of its inter- section with parallel 29 3o N. The Map referred to m this Agreement is that known as the ' International Asia Map, 1: 1,000,000. Article 2. —The Government of Nejd undertake not to establish any fortified post at Kaf or utilise Eaf or the district ii its neighbourhood as a military centre; and should they at any time consider .it r ecessaiy to take exceptional measures m the neighbourhood of the frontier wnh a view to the maintenance of cruer or for25 anv other purpose, involTing the concen tration of armed forces, they engage to notify Ilis Majesty's Government without delay. The Government of Nejd undertake to prevent, by all the means at their dis posal, any incursions by their forces, into the territory of Trans-Jordan. Article 5.—In order to avoid misunder standing over incidents which may arise in the neighbourhood of the frontier, and to promote mutual confidence and full co operation between His Majesty's Govern ment and the Government of Nejd, the two parties agree to maintain constant communication between the Chief British Representative in Trans-Jordan or his delegate and the Governor ©f the Wadi Sirhan. Article 4.—The Government of Nejr undertake to maintain all established rights that may be enjoyed in the Wadi Sirhan by tribes not under their jurisdic tion, whether such rights appertain to grazing or to habitation, or to ownership or the like ; it being understood that those tribes, so long as they reside within Nejd territory, will be subject to such internal laws as do not infringe those rights. Tjie Government of Trans-Jordan undertake to extend identical treatment to Nejd subjects who may enjoy similar established rights in Trans-Jordan terri tory. Article 5. —The Governments of Nejd and Trans-Jordan severally recognise that raiding by tribes settled in their terri tories into the territory of the other State is an aggression which necessitates the severe punishment of the perpetrators by the Government to which they are subject and that the chief of the tribe committing such aggression is to be held responsible.' Article 6.—{a) A special tribunal shall be set up, by agreement between the two Governments of Nejd and Trans-Jordan, which shall meet from time to time to enquire into the particulars of any aggres sion committed across the frontier between the two States, to assess the damages and losses and to fix the responsibility. This tribunal shall be composed of an ecjual number of representatives of the Govern ments of Nejd and Trans-Jordan, and it^: presidency shall be entrusted to an ad ditional person, other than the aforesaid representatives, to be selected by the two Governments in agreement. The decision ot this 'nbunal shall be final and execu- tory.26 {b) When the tribunal has fixed the responsibility, assessed the damages and losses resulting from the raid, and issued its decision in that respect, the Govern ment to whom those found guilty are subject shall execute the aforesaid decision in accordance with tribal customs, and shall punish the guilty party in accordance with Article 5 of the present Agreement. Article 7, —Tribes subject to one of the two Governments mav not cross the %/ frontier into the territory of the other Government except after obtaining a permit from their own Government and after the concurrence of the other Government; it being stipulated, however, in accordance with the principle of the freedom of grazing, that neither Govern ment shall have the right to withhold such permit or concurrence if the migra tion of the tribe is due to grazing necessities. Article 8. —The two Governments of Nejd and Trans-Jordan undertake to stand in the way, by all the means at their disposal other than expulsion and the use of force, of the emigraiion of any tribe or section of a tribe from one of the two countries into the other unless its emigration takes place with the know ledge and consent of its Government. The two Governments undertake to abstain from offering any present of whatsoever kind to refugees from the territories of the other Government, and to look with disfavour on any of their subjects who may seek to entice tribes belonging to the other Government or to encourage them to emigrate from their country into the other country. Article P.—-The Governments of Nejd and Trans-Jordan may not correspond with the Chiefs and Sheikhs of tribes subject to the other State on official or political matters. Article 10. —The forces of Nejd and Trans -Jordan may not cross the common frontier in the pursuit of offenders, except with the consent of both Governments. Article 11. —Sheikhs or tribes who bold an official position or who have flags showing that they are the leaders of armed forces may not display their flags in the territory of other State. Article 12.—¥ xqq passage will be granted by the Governments of Nejd and Trans-Jordan to travellers and pilgrims, provided they conform to those regulations affecting travel and pilgrimage27 which may be ia force in Nejd and Trans- Jordan. Each Government will inform the other of any regulation issued by it in tins matter. Article 13. —His Britannic Majesty's Government undertake to secure freedom of transit at all times to merchants who are subjects of Nejd for the prosecution of their trade between Nejd and Syria in both directions: and to secure exemp tion from Customs and other duty for all merchandise in transit which may cross the Mandated Territory on its way from Nejd to Syria or from Syria to Nejd, on condition that such merchants and their caravans shall submit to whatever Customs inspection may be necessary, and that they shall be in possession of a document from their Government certify ing that they are bona fide merchants; and provided that trading caravans carrying merchandise will follow estab lished routes, to be agreed upon hereafter, for their entry into and their exit from the Mandated Territory; it being under- wtood that the above restrictions will not apply to trading caravans whose trade is confined to camels and other aninmls, or to tribes migrating in accordance with the preceding Articles of the present Agreement. His Britannic Majesty's Government further undertake to secure such other facilities as may be possible to merchants who are subjects of Nejd and who may cross the area under British Mandate. Article i^.—This Agreement will remain in force for so long as Ills .Li'itannic Majesty's Government are entrusted with the Mandate for Trans- Jordan. Article 15. —The present Agreement has been drawn up in the two languages, English and Arabic, and each of the high contracting parties shall sign two English copies and two Arabic copies. Both texts shall have the same validity, but in case of divergence between the two in the interpretation of one or other of the Articles of the present Agreement, the English text shall prevail. Article 16.—The present Agreement will be known as the HAD DA Agreement. Signed at Bahra Camp on the 2nd November. 1925 (corresponding to the 15th llabi' Thani 13M). (Signed) GILBERT CLAYTON, 'A'BDU'L-'AZLS.No. 8- CORRESPONDENCE RELATING TO THE HADDA AGREEMENT. His Highness 1 AldiCl-'Aziz ibn 'Ahdur- Rahman al-Faisal A.I Sa'ud, Sultan of Nejd and its Dependencies, to Sir Gilbert Clayton, K.B.E., etc., llis Britannic Majesty''s Commissioner and JPlenipotentiary. T eanslation. Bahra, 14th Ptabi' Thani 1344 (1st November, 1925). Y our E xcellency, In the Agreement relating to Trans- Jordan and Nejd provision is made for an undertaking on our part not to fortify Kaf or to make it a military centre. In one of our conversations, I asked Your Excellency to elucidate the meaning of ' fortifications,' and you explained that the construction of a wall round the villages concerned, according to the custom prevailing in the desert for the prevention of thefts and raids, as well as the construction of a military barrack for the housing of Public Security troops and the placing of a gun or a few machine-guns according to the require ments of public security, would not be considered as being fortifications of the kind which we undertook to abstain from erecting ; but that such works would be considered as necessary for the preserva tion of order. The object of the present letter is to obtain clear confirmation of that from Your Excellency so that we should be perfectly explicit about our undertakings and leave no room for such misconstructions as might arise from the intrigues of mischief-makers. Respects, 'ABDU'L-'AZIZ IBN 'ABDU'R- RAIIMAN IBN SA'UD.Sir Gilbert Clayton. KB.E., etc.) His Britannic Majesty's Commissioner and Flenipotent iary, to His Highness 'Addu'l 'Aziz ihn ^Abdu'r-Rahman al-Faisal Al Sa'ud, Sultan of Nejd and Us Depen dencies. Eahra Camp, 2nd November, 1925. Yom H ighness, I have the honour to acknowledge receipt of your letter of the 14th llabi' Thani 1344 (1st November, 1925)relating to the interpretation of Article 2 of the Hadda Agreement. In reply to Your Highness' enquiry, I would confirm the verbal statement I made in a recent conversation with Your Highness, namely, that it is difficult for anyone to define, fully and in detail, what is to be understood by the word ' fortification ' in such a manner as to cover all possible eventualities ; and that the best interpretation of that Article would be that which conforms to the spirit as to the letter of the Agreement, and rests on a sincere execution of its terms. For instance, if you desire to erect a wall, as is usual, or barracks for Public Security men other than military forces, or a small gun or a few machine- guns intended to repel brigands and aggressors, it will undoubtedly be open to &gt; ou to do so, provided such preparations do not exceed the bounds of what is re quired for the maintenance of order, and do not constitute, in the judgment of the British military authorities, a menace to Trans-Jordan. I have, etc., GILBERT CLAYTON. His Highness Sultan 'Ahdul-'Aziz ihn 1 Ahdu*r-Rahman al-Faisal Al Sa'ud, Sultan of Nejd and its Dependencies, to Sir Gilbert Clayton, etc., His Britannic Majesty s Commissioner and Plenipotentiary. T ranslation. Bahra Camp, 15th Kabi' Thani 1314 (2nd November, 19^5). Y our E xcellency, With reference to the discussions which have taken place concerning traders -who® 30 are subjects of Trans-Jordan, I am not aware of an established and customery road used for passage through the Wadi Sirhan by traders from Trans-Jordan. Should it appear, however, that subjects of Trans-Jordan have an established and acknowledged right, recognised by those who are expert in such matters, to ply their trade from Syria and Trans-Jordan to the southern portions of Trans-Jordan by way of the Wadi Sirhan, then we hereby undertake to extend to them the same treatment as is extended to subjects of Nejd by the Government of Trans- Jordan in their transit to and from Syria. (Sealed) 'ABDU'L^AZIZ IliN 'ABDU'R-EAHMAN IBN SA'UD. ^o. 9- AGREEMENT BETWEEN THE BRI TISH GOVERNMENT AND HIS HIGHNESS THE SULTAN OF NEJD AND ITS DEPENDENCIES, B asra A greement. Translation. Whereas with a view to securing good relations between the two Governments of 'Iraq and Nejd, a Treaty' known as the Muhammara Convention was agreed upon between those two Governments and signed on the 7th Ramadan 1340 (corresponding to the 5th May, 1922), and Whereas the aforesaid Treaty was supplemented by two Protocols, known respectively as Protocol Number I and Protocol Number II of the Muhammara Convention, which were signed at 'Uqair on the 12th Rabf Thani 1341 (correspond ing to the 2nd December, 1922), and Whereas the aforesaid Treaty and Protocols have beep duly ratified by the two Governments of 'Iraq and Nejd, and Whereas in Article I of the aforesaid Muhammara Convention the Govern ments of 'Iraq and of Nejd have guaran teed mutually that they will prevent aggression by their tribes on the tribes of the other and will punish their tribes for any such aggression and, should the circumstances not admit of such punish ment, the two Govenwaaents will discuss31 the question of taking combined action according to the good relations prevailing between them, and Whereas it is considered advisable by His Britannic Majesty's Government and by the two Governments aforementioned, in the interests of friendship and good relations between the two countries of Jraq and Nejd to come to an agreement regarding certain matters which are outstanding between those two countries. We, the undersigned, His Highness Abdu i-'Aziz ibn 'Abdu'r-Rahman al- Faisal A1 Sa'ud, Sultan of ]S T ejd and its Dependencies, and Sir Gilbert Clayton, K.B.E., C.B., C.M.G., the duly accredited Commissioner and Plenipotentiary of His Britannic Majesty's Government, who lias been empowered to come to an agree ment and sign on behalf of the 'Iraq Government, have agreed upon the following articles:— Article i.—The States of 'Iraq and Nejd severally recognise that raiding by tribes settled in their territories into the territory of the other State is an aggres sion which necessitates the severe punishment of the perpetrators by the Government to which they are subject and that the chief of the tribe committin 0 ' such aggression is to be held responsible. ^ Article 2—(a) A special tribunal shall be set up, by agreement between the two Governments of 'Iraq and Nejd, which shall meet from time to time to enquire into the particulars of any aggression committed across the frontier between the two States, to assess the damages and losses and to tlx the responsibility. This tribunal shall be composed of an equal number of representatives of the Govern ments of 'Iraq and Nejd, and it. presi dency shall be entrusted to an additional peTson, other than the aforesaid represen tatives, to be selected by the two Govern ments m agreement. The decisions of this tribunal shall be final and executory, (5) When the tribunal has fixed the responsibility, assessed the damages and losses resulting from the raid, and issued Jts deemon in that respect, the Govern ment to whom ttiose found guilty 'are subject shall execute the aforesaid decision m accordance with tribal customs, and . ball punish the guilty party in aecord- anoe with Article 3 of tie pLentTJee- liiidc 5.—Tribes subject to one of the two Governments may not cross the32 frontier into the territory of the other Government except alter obtaining a permit from their own Government and after the concurrence of the other Govern ment ; it being stipulated, however, in accordance with the principle of the freedom of grazing, that neither Govern ment shall have the right to withhold such permit or concurrence if the migra tion of the tribe is due to grazing neces sities Article 4. —The two Governments of 'Iraq and Nejd undertake to stand in the way, by all the means at their disposal other than expulsion and the use of force, of the emigration of any tribe or section of a tribe from one of the two countries into the other unless its emigration takes place with the knowledge and consent of its Government. The two Govern ments undertake to abstain from offering any present of whatsoever kind to refugees from the territories of the other Government, and to look with disfavour on any of their subjects who may seek to entice tribes belonging to the other Government or to encourage them to emigrate from their country into the other country. Article 5.—The Governments of 'Iraq and Nejd may not correspond with the Chiefs and Sheikhs of tribes subject to the other State on official or political matters. Article 6. —The forces of 'Iraq and iSejd may not cross the common frontier in the pursuit of offenders except with the consent of both Governments. Article 7.—Sheikhs of tribes who hold an official position or who have flags showing that they are the leaders of armed forces may not display their flags in the territory of the other State. Article 8. —In case one of the two Governments were to call upon tribes residing in the territory of the other State to furnish armed contingents, the said tribes will be free to respond to the call of their Government on condition that they betake themselves with their families and belongings in complete tranquility 0 Article In case of a tribe were to emigrate from the territory of one of the two Governments into the territory of the other Government and were subsequently to commit raids into the territory in which it formerly resided, it will be open to the Government into whose territory this tribe has immigrated to take from it adequate guarantees on the understand ing that, if a similar aggression were to be repeated by the tribe, those guaranteeswould be liable to confiscation, without prejudice to the punishment to be indict ed by the Government as provided in Article I, and without prejudice to whatever impositions may be decreed by the tribunal specified in Article 2 of the present Agreement. Article 10. —The Governments of ' Iraq and Nejd undertake to initiate friendly discussions with a view to concluding a special agreement in respect of the extra dition of criminals in accordance with the usage prevailing among friendly States, within a period not exceeding one year from the date of the ratification of the present Agreement by the Government of 'Iraq. Article 11. —The Arabic version is the official text to be referred to in the inter pretation of the Articles of the present Agreement. Article 12. —The present Agreement shall be known as ' The Bahra A^ree- ment. Signed at Bahra Camp this fourteenth day of liabi' Tliani 1344, corresponding tu the first day of November, 1925. (Sd.) GILBERT CLAYTON. (Sd. and Sealed) ' ABDU'L-'AZIZ. Ko. 10. Correspondence relating to the Bahra Agreement. Memorandum. Presented hy His Highness the Sultan of Nejd after the sixth meeting to Sir Gilbert Clayton, etc., His Britannic Majesty's Gommissioner and Plenipotentiary. Translation. 1st Eabi c Tliani 1344 (19th October, 1925). I have the honour to inform Your Excellency that the Government of Nejd are still of opinion that it is necessary to examine the possibility of extraditing criminals, in the hope of ensuring peace on the frontier and of preventing all disturbers of the peace effectively. My Insistence in this matter is due to the particular experience I have, and to my knowledge of desert conditions. My first object is to prevent any rivalry or friction from arising between the two Govern-34. ments, and in this I am actuated by three maia motives:— (a) religion and honour, which com pel us to act truthfully and in keeping with our pledges; (J) our special ties of friendship with His Majesty's Government, which make it incumbent upon us to take a far-sighted view; (c) our desire to live in peace, quiet and amity with our neighbours the State of 'Iraq. 2. I am of opinion that the Agreement which you presented for discussion this morning, although it may achieve some of the purposes for which we strive, does yet leave the door open to a great number of troublesome incidents of a kind of which we have had cause to complain in the past. In particular, I have submit ted to you the following incidents as being of the kind which habitually occur in life in the desert:— (a) what should the attitude of the Kejd Government be if an 5 Iraqi tribe, having committed a reprehensible crime involv- ing killing and plunder, were to take refuge in Nejd; and what would the same Govern ment's attitude be if that refugee tribe were to commit the same crime, notwithstand ing guarantees being taken from it; (d) what should tbe attitude of each of the Governments of 'Iraq and of Nejd be if a Nejd tribe, having been punished by the Nejd Government for a raid into 'Iraq were to take refuge into 'Iraq and then to raid Nejd from ' Iraq, as was done by those tribes who had taken refuge with Nejd and then gone over to 'Iraq, after the well-known incidents connec ted with Yusuf Sa^un ? I beg that you will examine these questions carefully. After considerable experience, I see no effective way of cir cumventing the trouble other than that Nejd and 'Iraq should both admit the principle of the surrender of criminals, and that criminals, having perpetrated a crime in their country should be preven ted from seeking refuge into the other country. Measures based on any othfet principle would not in my opinion, shut the door on the dissensions of which we all complain; and I ask that this state-6o merit of mine should be put on record so that it may be referred to in the future, and so as to set my conscience at rest in case such incidents, of the kind which we deplore and would prevent with all our efforts, were to recur. Usual respects. (Sealed) ' ABDU'L-'AZIZ LBN £ ABDirR-RAHMAN IBN SA'Uth Sir Gilbert Clayton, etc., His JBritcmnic Majesty's Commissioner and Plenipotentiary y to His Highness ' Abdu'l-'Aziz ihn ' Ahdu'r-Uahman al-Faisal AI Sa'ud, Sultan of Nejd and its Dependencies. Bahra Camp, The 20th October, 1925, Your Highness, I have the honour to acknowledge receipt of Your Highness' communica tion of 1st Rabi' Thani (19th October, 1925), and I note that Your Highness is of opinion that no agreement is likely to establish security on the frontier and put a stop to raiding which is not based on the principle that either Government at the request of the other Government should return, if necessary by force, any tribes or portions of tribes which may cross over into its territory. 2. As I have repeatedly informed Your Highness in our conversations, the 'Iraq Government is unable to subscribe to this principle, which it deems contrary to Arab traditions and impracticable of execu tion. I have also informed Your High ness that His Majesty's Government, after careful consideration of the facts and of the views put forward by Your Highness and on your behalf in the past, have reached the same conclusion. That being so, I regret that I am unable to adopt the principle which you recommend. 3. On the other hand, I would point out to Your Highness tbat the draft Agreement which I presented to you recently goes far towards meeting your own views in the matter, and that in drafting it I have endeavoured as far as possible to reconcile conflicting opinion. It is based on what, in the view of His Majesty's Government, is just and fair to 'Iraq and Nejd and to the tribes con cerned ; and I feel sure that, provided it is loyally carried cmt, peace and stability36 on the border ought to prevail, and that any disputes arising from the aggressions of tribes, even in such complicated in stances as those mentioned by Your High ness, will be capable of settlement without real difficulty by the two Governments of ' Iraq and Nejd acting in sincere co-opera tion. 4. With regard to Your Highness' misgivings as to the efficacy of an agree ment such as I have proposed, I rely with full confidence on Your Highness' re peated assurances of good-will and sincere desire for peace and order on the frontier. I have, etc., GILBERT CLAYTON. Sir Gilbert Clayton, K.B.U., etc., His Britannic Majesty s Commissioner and plenipotentiary ^ to Ihs Highness 4 Abdul-'Aziz ihn ' Ahdv? r-Bafiman cd-Faisal Al Sa'ud, Sultan of Nejd and its Dependencies. Bahra, The 31st October, 1925. Youe Highness, 1 have the honour to recall that in one of our recent conversations I spoke to Youi Highness about the necessity of settling the question of loot and losses resulting from past raids by tribes from ' Iraq and Keid, and we agreed that it would be necessary to lay down general principles and formulate a procedure for the satis factory settlement of this question. 2 In accordance with our agreement, Taufiq Bey Suwaidi, the 'Iraq representa tive, has discussed the question with Sheikh Hafiz and Sheikh Yusuf, and they have come to a preliminary agreement on the subject. I have the honour, there fore, to request that Your Highness may, if you see fit, signify to me your concur rence in the following proposals (a) That the 'Uqair Conference should be taken as the start ing point for reckoning the looses claimed respectively by ' Iraq and Kcjd on account of the raids which have taken place between that Conference and the date of ratification by the 'Iraq Government of the Bahra Agreement. O j ) That the tribunal provided for in Article 2 of the Bahra Agreement should be chargedwith the task of enquiring inta the claims of both sides and of assessing compensation due for the losses resulting from raids taking place during the ahovementioned period, with out prejudice to the other duties which this tribunal will have to perform in the future. (c) That this tribunal should be as sembled and should meet within a period not exceeding six months from the date of the ratification of the Bahra Agreement by the Government of 5 Iraq in accordance with their constitutional laws. I have, etc., GILBERT CLAYTON. Sis Highness ' Ahdu'l-'Aziz ihn £ Ahdvlr- Bah mail al-Faisal Al Sa'ud, Sultan of flejd and its Dependencies, to Sir Gilbert Clayton, K.B.E,, etc.. Mis Bri' tannic Majesty's Commssioner and Ple nipotentiary. T ranslation. 14itli Rabi* Thani 1344 (1st November, 1925). Respects. I have the honour to acknowledge receipt of your letter dated the 31st Octo ber, 1925, relating to losses and loot. I fully endorse the agreement arrived at between Sheikh Hafiz Wahba and Sheikh Yusuf Yasin and Taufiq Bey SuwaidL Compliments. (Sealed) ' ABDIJ'L-'AZIZ IBN ^BDITR-RAHMAM IBN SA'UD. Sir Gilbert Clayton, etc.. Mis Britannic Majesty's Commissioner and Tlenipotentiary, to Mis Mighness *Ahdu'I-*Aziz ibn ' Abdvb r-Uahman al- Faisal Al Sa'ud, Sultan of Nejd and its Dependencies. Bahra Camp, 1st November, 1925. Your Highness, I have the honour to inform Your Highness that I am instructed by His38 Majesty's Government that the Agreement which has been concluded between Your Highness and myself in regard to certain frontier questions which were outstanding between the Governments of Nejd and of J Iraq, and which was duly signed on the 1st November, 1925, cannot become oper ative until it has been formally ratified by the Government of ' Iraq. The Agreement will be transmitted without delay by His Majesty's Govern ment to the Government of 'Iraq with a request for early ratification, and the date of that ratification will be notified in due course by His Majesty's Government to Your Highness as the date on which the aforesaid Agreement will come into opera tion. I shall be grateful if Your Highness will kindly acknowledge receipt of this letter. I have, etc., GILBEET CLAYTON. His Highness Sultan *Ahdu i l- t Aziz ibn 1 Ahdu*r-Uahman al-Faisal Al SaMid, Sultan of Nejd [and its Dependencies, to Sir Gilbert Clayton, K.B.E,, etc.. Sis Britannic Majesty's Commissioner and Plenipotentiary. T ranslation. 15th Rabi' Thani 1344 (2nd November, 1925). j T our E xcellency, Respects. I beg to acknowledge your letter dated 1st November, 1925, relating to the date on which the 'Iraq-Nejd Agreement is to come into force, and to say that this has been noted. Respects. (Sealed) 'ABDU'L-'AZIZ IBN 'ABDTJ'R-RAHMAN IBN SA'UH. mgipc—s6—xi-ii—'18-9-26—200.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0002c4_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/733</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0002c4</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/733</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Treaties and Agreements between the British Government and Certain Arab Rulers and Agreements between the Said Rulers inter se Affecting the British Government'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1926/1926</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-08-27T00:16:12</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (23 folios)</extent><extent>There is a list of the treaties and agreements recorded towards the front of the volume, on folio 3.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence commences at 1 on the front cover and terminates at 25 on the back cover. These numbers are written in pencil, are enclosed in a circle, and appear in the top right hand corner of the recto page of each folio. An original printed pagination sequence is also present in the volume. The following folio folds out: f. 15.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The volume is
                           Treaties and Agreements between the British Government and Certain Arab Rulers and Agreements between the Said Rulers inter se Affecting the British Government(Calcutta: Government of India Press, 1926). The volume contains transcripts of treaties and agreements dated 1915 to 1925 relating to Najd, Qatar, Iraq, Kuwait, Trans-Jordan, and Kaf.The texts of some of the treaties and agreements appear in both English and Arabic in vertical parallel columns.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><name type="family"><namePart>Āl Bū Sa‘īd (Family)</namePart></name></subject><subject><geographic>Najd</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Kuwait</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Qatar</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Al Jufayr</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Az Zallāq</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Ra's Tannūrah</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Kuk-I-Mund</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Zellaq</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Ras Tannura</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Kūh-e Mand</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Treaties</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0002c4#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>