<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0000f0_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-05-23T13:41:19.497Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Previc Next Gene: Sub-f NotesT.0.0.1845 Dated 12th (received 13th) July 1947. T.0.R.0715. / M ^ Your telegram 4107 May 26th- t o Bushire. Dearness and ration allowance' to iVohamt'.erah menial staff. 2. Consul Mohanmerah reports that there has bt^en no decrease in prices of essential commodities. I recommend continuance of this concession at existing rates for a further period of 3 months. 3. Grateful for telegraphic sanction. r~ a. a. 16492 r I 1947 J* Copy of letifer No. 360-66/12, dated the 10th February, 1947, from REPGU, Bahrain, to FOREIGN, New Delhi. BRITAIN, Khorramshahr. / 3 'jx SUBJECT: Grant of increased dearness allowance' to the Menial Staff of the British p^ps^ilatej, Khorramshahr. ^ ) \ Ref eren ce telegram Ng._9623 dated the 11th November, 1946, from the Government of India in the External Affairs Department. 2. I forward copies of Express Letters Nos. 1114-4/6 and 54-4/6 of the 19th December, 1946, and 18th January, 1947, respectively from Hie Majesty^ Consul, Khorramshahr, with their enclosures. 3. I consider that His Majesty’s Consul, Khorramshahr, has made out a very strong case and I support the recommendations made in para 3 of his letter No.1114 of the 19th December, 1946. I trust that the Government of India will be able to see their way to accepting these proposals in full and should be grateful if their orders could be communicated to me with the least possible delay by telegram. 4. Efforts will be made to meet as much of the expenditure involved as possible from within the sanctioned budget grant at my disposal for the current financial year; and the balance which cannot be so met will be included in my final statement of savings and excesses due shortly for submission to the Government of India. =REPGU= r The issue of the above has been authorised » (f ■ for Secretary to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf. Copy forwarded for information to His Majesty’s Consul, Khorramshahr, with reference to his Express Letter No.54-4/6 dated the 18th January, 1947. /. 1 . ■2 V v 1 M /1 / A. Gr. 9316 1947o d) Copy of Express Letter Lo*1114-4-46 dated the l^th December 1946 from His Majesty's Cons i ol, Khorramshahr, to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain. Subject:- Grant of increased dearness allowance to the menial staff of the British Consulate, Khorramshahr. T • — • • • Reference:- Your telegram ho. A|1186 dated the 14th Kovember. 1946. The A.I.O.C. Limited have had to tighten up their 2 regulations and have informed us that they will not be able to supply rations to the staff of this Consulate with effect from 1st January 1947. The Company have increased the wages of their peons and the minimum is now between Rilas 38 and 50 per day. As a result of this increase in wages the cost of living has risen steadily and it is impossible for our peons to make both ends meet on the wages they now receive* 3. In the circumstances I stpgnfeLy recommend that they should be given an increase as follows:- (i) Increase of 50&gt; in basic pay as sanctioned in your telegram referred to above. (ii) Dearness allowance at 100/&gt; for those on pay from Rials 300 to 450 and 75&gt; for launch driver. (iii) Ration allowance of Rials 300 for married staff and Rials 200 to unmarried. 4. Grateful if Government of India’s sanction to increased rates as proposed above with effect from the 1st January 1947 be communicated to me telegraphically.t / (D 1947 from Britain, Khorramshahr, to Repgu, Ba 1 - — -'- Copy of Express letter No* 54-4/6 dated the 18th January Menial Staff of the British Consulate Reference your telegram No* A/32 dated 13th January,1947 2. I enclose herewith a statement indicating the losses which the married and bechelor members of my menial establishment are suffering as a result of the withdrawal of ration facilities by the A.I.O.C* The items enumerated are those supplied- by the company to their peons and which the members of our menial staff have hitherto been able to obtain from that source. The figures showing the amounts consumed of each item are based onlthe average minimum requirements of the married and bachelor menials respectively and are in all cases well within the rationed limit set down by the Company in respect of its menials* 3. As will be seen from the statement, the ferrashes have now to pay much higher prices (which are still, if anything, on the increase) in the local market for these items and, at the same time, continue to make other essential recurring payments e.g. House Rent at not less than Rials. 200/- per room per month, fuel etc. This is causing considerable hardship to them, and they feel that it will be impossible for them to carry on unless their emoluments are increased sufficiently to cover their normal minimum requirements. These menials have been loyal to Government at a time when the labour problem in this area was most acute and they have so far borne their financial difficulties without much complaint, though they have had the option of leaving our employment at any time for a more lucrative one, with many more facilities, with the A.T.O.C. But I must repeat that unless their pay and allowances are now brought to an adequate level, I shall be confronted with a mass resignation. The prospects of obtaining suitable replacements are extremely poor.* In view of the expansion in the work of this Consulate during recent years, it is not possible to suggest a reduction in the number of menials as a measure of economy, in order to facilitate the grant of higher emoluments to the remainder. 4. Though the increases in the salary and allowances recommended in my Express letter No. 1114 of 19th December, 1946, do not bring the emoluments of the menials into line with those of their contemporaries in the A.I.O.C and do not altogether compensate them for the losses they have incurred as a result of the stoppage of A.I.O.C. supplies, they will at least leave this Consulate with the services of a reasonably happy menial staff and I urge most strongly that the sanction of the Government of India to the increased rates of pay etc., as recommended in my above-mentioned Express Letter, may be obtained urgently and telegraphed to me before the end of January, 1947. Sd/- V.W.D.Willoughby His Majesty's Consul, Khorramshahr.v Telegram G.T.C, Ko. 3550 dated 8th May 1947 /37^ 1947 F}7ora To.. Foreign, New Delhi. •..•..•Britain, Bushire. Your telegram 311 May 2nd. 2 . In modification of orders contined in Foreign telegram v 2446 March 28th, sanction accorded to grant of increased dearness allowance to Khorramshahr menial staff at 100^ for those on pay from 300 to 450 Riyals and 75% for launch driver for six months from 1st January 1947 subject to review thereafter and to any adjustment necessary on the basis of Central Pay Commission’s recommendations. Question regarding increase of ration allowance under consideration. Sharma'V INDIA 0?FTCF.. Telegram G.T.C. No. 4107 Dated 27th May 1947. From*• • • • v »•«• t # ## Fortlgiii Nov Delhi* To* ••••«•••••••••••*aBrltflilnf Bushlm* Repeatedi Consul, Mohaatmerah*. •••••••••* Foreign telegram 3660 May 8th* 2* Sanction also accorded to grant of* Increased ration allowance of Ralls 300 to married and Rials 200 to unmarried menial staff at Khorramshahr for six month* from 1st January 1947 subject 1 to review thereafter and to mm $ any adjustment necessary on ths basis of Central Fey Commission’s recommendations. ' ijijk (\*/. TELEGRAM G.T.C. No.2466 dated 28th March 1947.^ From Foreign, New Delhi. To Repgu, Bahrain (Repeated Britain, Khorrarashahr). Your express letter 360-66/12 February 10th Dearness allowance for Khorramshahr menial staff. Question regarding proposed increases in dearness allowance and ration allowance under consideration. Meantime sanction accorded to the continuance of increase of pay and dearness allowance sanctioned in Foreign telegram 9623 November 11th 1946 for six months from 1st January 1947. Sharma/ m,Telegram No.A/310 dated Buahip-the 16th Feb.’44. [ ’ i 7' ' ,| v Froffi.--.** Britconeul, Bushire.- To Foreign, New q^ Your telegram No.ll60-V^ f 13th 1943, Dearness Allowance to ministerial establishment. \ \qa&amp; 2. From preliminary examination it appears that existing rate oi dearness allowance ior Mohamrnernh(Khorramshahr), Kerman and Kuwait will * have to be increased. Question is being lurther examined and it will take come tims bei ore the final recommendations can oe made* I reauest telegraphic sanction for continuance of dearness allowance at all posts at existing rate Irom March 1st 1944 to August 31st. FORE! i s i A-™ 1 r --r2-.--~~ ♦ from let September 1943 True i a 1 a. 11 the alxjve percentages to be subject to terms and conditions specified in Foreign ttiemoranduia No. lb(II)-E/43 dated 14th May 1943 and egress ^ letter No. 18(XX)-V43 dated 12th August 1943. 5. Since the ministerial staff h&amp;ve been losing heavily for several months I request th&amp;t the orders of the Government of India be communicated to me by telegram. - Britconsul - B.M. 13/4/44Enclosure in India Foreign Sooret ry’a Letter No*26 dated 6th Nevesdber 194-3 received 14th Janury, 1944- Ext* 209/44- By 1 ir Hail* Government of India, External Affairs Department. Express Letter. From: Foreign, Simla* To; Britconaxil, Bushire. No. 18(1l)-E/43* Dated Simla, the 21st Septevaber 1943* Subject;- Grant of increased rates of dearness allowance to staff serving in certain areas of the Persian Gulf* In confirmation of Foreign telegram No* d4~VCamp dated the 21st Septeidber 1943 sanction is accorded to grant of following increased rates of dearness allowance to ministerial and non-superior staff, gazetted and non-gazetted, serving in areas specified below with effect from 1st May 1943 *- Area Rate of dearness allowance . Kerman •«•••.••*• 75?^ Bushire * • • • 65 &gt; Khorramshahr • 85^ Grant of above allowances will be subject to terras and conditions specified in Forei^i memorandum No. 18(11 )-2/43» dated 14 th lfe.y 1943 and Express Letter No* 18(11)- */43&gt; dieted 12th August 1943* 2. Government of India regret that they are unable to sanction your proposal for grant of increased rate of dearness allowance to staff in Kuwait. TUB ISSUE OF THE ABOVE HAS BEEN AUTHORISED. (s^d.) V. B. Arte, Under Secretary to the Government of India.■ ^ BXT.208/ijii Copy of an Express Letter No. 1320-64/149* dated the 2nd August 1943 from the Eon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bus hire, to Foreign, New Delhi. Subject: Scales of nav of the First Interpreters. Reference memorandum No. 18(149-E/43, dated the 14 th May 1943, from the Government of India in jthe External Affairs Department, in which sanction was accorded to the up-grading of the two posts of Interpreters instead of the three as proposed in this Residency's letter No.194“64/222 dated the 6 th February,1943• 2. Since the senior Interpreter on the Arab side is posted at Muscat (where there is a very large volume of judicial work involving the claims of British Indians against the local population, and much landed property is owned locally by them) and since this officer was specially qualified for Muscat, one post on enhanced pay has been allotted to this place, where moreover the climatic conditions are exceptionally severe. The other has been allotted to Khorramshahr where the competition from the Oil Company and the American forces is most formidable. 3. There now remains the post of Interpreter at Kuwait where great difficulty has been experienced in both engaging and retaining the right type of Interpreter, whose integrity and loyalty have to be above criticism for obvious reasons . Two of the incumbents of this post resigned in the brief period of two years prior to.January 1943, and since the issue of this Residency's letter referred to above another incumbent of that post has also resigned. It is clearly becoming impossible to recruit the right type of man for Kuwait and to retain him after recruitment on the present low rates of pay. 4* For the above reasons , and for others which will occur to the Government of India, I strongly recommend that the Government of India reconsider their decision and pass orders for the up-grading of the third post of First Interpreter. THE IS: UE OF THE ABOVE HAS BEEN AUTHORISED. /Copy' ’ I 4 , - * B^^AirJwail. Copy of an Express better No. l 8 (j 4)-^^3 dated 8 th September 194 $ from Foreign, ew e Brit consul, Bushire, *=••*• ssiss rr\ Reference yonr express 1= tter No.1320-64/149- dated the d August '1943* , sanction is accorded to th« ^'faHo-lO-^^itt Sfect =* interpreter from Hs .120 6/4 duration rom the date of issue of these “'f'^f^^^owever , continue f the war. The incumbent of this post wxll. cadre ratfcS 0 receive the allowances at the ordinary vei Tve extra expenditure involved in the current year should ; met^from within the sanctioned budget ^ant. THE ISSUE OF THE ABOVE HAS BEEN AUTHORISED.? * y* / ^ ^ %*fL*^* rfj id Telegram No« Ao632 f Qeted the 22nd May 19^3® V; ^ From:- Britconaul, Bushire, ^ j •-•' ^ '• - To 2 - - Foreign, Simla* ^ | J '} ’7 Continuation of my telegram 318-A, dated 20th April 1943* I Q/1 / f 2. Consul Moliammerah is facad with mass resignation from office staff and private servants owing to better prospects offered by Americans* Every effort to enforce RERRIC rate has failed* In view of tne urgency of this case I have sanctioned increase in wages proposed by Consul Mohammerah in anticipation of your approval. This will entail additional allotment of Rs„ 3,600 under office allowance grant and Rs« 400 under launch grant iisz during the current financial year* Every effort will be made to meet increased expenditure*Telegram No* 522-E, Dated the 31st May 1943* ^/ From:- Foreign, Saw Delhi, . ^ To:- - Britconsul, Bus hire. * / l&gt; j Your telegram A/632 of May 22nd« Mohammerah staff* Your telegram 318-A of April 20th asiaxs referred to not received* Please repeat and also furnish detafiU of increase in wages allowed* Telegram No* A*749, Dated the 14th June 1943 (reed, 15*6,43») From:- Britconsul, Buahire, Toi- - Foreigii, New Delhi# Your telegram No, 522-E of May 31st, 13 members of inferior establishment on wages ranging from Krans 200 to 300 p,m* have been granted 1005$ dearness allowance and one Launch Driver on pay Krans 400 p#m, 755'o allowance. In addition all above nave been granted graded military ration consisting tea, sugar and flour (coursest), bachelors Krans 75 and married men Krans 120 p,m« ENCLOSE INDIA Y'S I F 'I ! r. /i / From •• The UndQr Sqcy* to th© Govt* of Inciia. in the External iffaira Department, To - - The Hon f ble the Political Resident in the Persian G-ulf, Bushire* Memorandum No* 18(35)-B/43* Dated Simla, the 2&amp;fd July 1943* Subiect:- Grant of enhanced rate of dearness allowance to the bobk menial staff of the Consulate General,; Khorramshahr. Reference correspondence ending with your telegram No* A*926, dated the luth July 1943* 2 0 Sanction is accorded to the yrant to the 7 inferior establishment in His Maj3sty f s Consulate General, • Khorramshahr, of dearness allowance at the followirg^enrianced rates with effect from 1st May 1943,3V till the end of Feby*1944 or the end of war wkiKiatoxx whichever is earlier:- Those on pay ranging from Krans 200 to 300 p«m«:~ 100 % of basic J&gt;ay. One Launch Driver on Krans 400 p,m*:- 75% of pay Sanction is assura: also accorded to the grant to the staff specified, in addition to the above, free rations costing at tne maximum Krans 120 p*m* in the case of tnose who are married and Krans 75 p.m* in the case of those who are unmarried* 3 # The extra cost involved should be met so far as possible from within the sanctioned budget grant.i^xt. 6535/43° ¥o\xr ref i K ^b^lh/ 10163/234. Our ref: E.637V f ^» dir. Treasury* S.W.l. 30th November 1943• In reply to Mr. Allohin* s letter of the 13th instant I am directed by the Lords Oommissi oners of His Majesty o Treasury to request you to inf or a the Secretary of State for Foreign Affaire that they sanction the charge to imperial revenues of a moiety of the expenditure involved in the grant as frcn the 30 th September last of dearness allowance paid to certain staff in the Persian Gulf subject to there being no material decrease in the cost of living. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, Sgd. G.H.M. Wiloox. The Under Secretary of State, Foreign Office, S.W.l./3. By Air Mail Government of India, External Affairs Department. « a ^ LSTI-ER. Prom: Foreign, Simla. TOi Britconsul, Bushire. No. 18(11)-*2/2f3» Dated Simla, the 12th August 1943* SUB.TEG’T:- Oontinuanoe of Dearness Allowance to the ministerial establishments in the Persian Gulf including gazetted ministerial staff. Assistant Gm^eons and F.»7.D.Staff. In confirmation of Foreign telegram No. 6 i*Z|jO, dated the 4-th August 1943 sanction is accorded to continuance of the dearness allowance sanctioned in Government of India, External Affairs Department, mttaorajidujn No.I3(ll)-iA3, datad the 14 th Jtojr 1943 and telegram N 0 . 646 -K, dated the 23th June 1943&gt; to the Ministerial establishments in the Persian Gulf (including Gazetted Ministerial staff), Asst. Surgeons and P.W.D. staff, for a further period of three months with effect from 1st July 1943* The question of further oontinuanoe of the allowance will be taken up after receipt of sanction of the Secretary of State which is still awaited.fn arc, I 8.^1. 14th I^cember, 1^45* ^vr, fftth p«f 4 *Nine# to India o&lt;* letter ! XU Bf* ?/ 4 a of th« Srd November # I «* directed by Mr# Secretary iden to at^te that sanction he a bee?i obtained for the charge to I«i:^irial revenue a of a moiety of the ex enditure involved in the grant aa from the d th 8 epte^ber last, of dearneaa allowancea paid to certain clerical establishments on the eralan 0ulf 9 the grant# to b# continued Indefinitely subject to there being no material decrease t n the coat f living* I am, Sir, Tour obedient Servant, *fSd.) A. B. HU OH* The Dnder-aecretary of State, India Office*■2M/M Poraign Office K 1297^10153/25^. S.W.l 26th October 1943 Sir With referenoe to Govwniaeirt of Indie telegram No»B023f a copy of which was forwarded to this Department under India Office reference Ext. 5399/43 the 25th Septoraber, I am directed by Mr. Winston Churchill to inform you that sanction has been obtained for the charge to Imperial revenues of a raciety of the expenditure involved in the grant, as frorr the 1st Kay 1943, increases in the dearness allowance paid to staff serving at Kerman, Bushire and Khorra shahr. I am. Sir, Your obedient Servnt Sgd. E. ALL01HN The U der 3eore ary of State India Office.India Office, Whitehall, , S.W.l. Ext.5907/43- 3rd Noveni)er 19^-3* I «a directed by the Secret^' of State for India to refer to Foreign Office Letters No. K 1188^/10163/23^ of 28th September and No. K 12972/10163/234 of 26th October regarding the grant of dearness allowances to certain staff serving in the Persian Gulf, and to enclose a further telegram froin the Government of India, No.9053 of 23rd October, fron which it will be seen that they have provisionally sanctioned the continuance of the allowances up to the end of February 1944* Subject to the concurrence of the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, and to the acceptance of a moiety of the divisible expenditure involved as a charge upon Imperial revenues, the Secretary of State for India proposes to approve •the Government of India* s action and to authorise than to continue the allowances in question for an indefinite period after February 1944 subject to there being no mate ial decrease in the cost of living. A oopy of tills letter is being sent to the Treasury. I am. Sir, Your obedient Servant, The Under Secretary Sgd. R. FSEL* of State, Foreign Office.' act.saso/i^, ^ / ;; Treasury, S.W.X. Tour Ref: K.1217^/1015V 254- 16th Ootober 1943- (bo* Ref: E*6373/^* Sir, In reply to Mr. Hutoheon* s letter of the ?th instant I am directed by the Lords Ocraaisoioners of His Majesty’s Treasury to request you to inform tie Secretary of State for Foreign Af fairs^ that They snuction the charge to Imperial revenues of a moiety oi expenditure involved in the grant, as from 1 st l ay last, of increases in the dearness allowances paid to staff serving at Keroan, Bushirt* and Khoramshahr. I am. Sir, Tour obedient Servant, (Sgd.) d.VilooK. The Under Secretary of State, Foreign Offioe, Downing Street, S.W.l.rr f foreign Office, K.ll8a^l0163/23i^ 2Bth J3eptaaber 1943 Sir, With reference to Indie Office letter I5xt. 29^9/43 of the 5th August and to Government of India telegram No. 6714- of the 12th August regarding the great of dearness allowanoes to the clerical establishment in the T^ersian Gulf, t am directed by Mr* Secretary Eden to inform you that sanction has been obtained for the charge to Imperial revenues erf* a moiety of the expenditure involved and for tiie continuance of the allcwarees for a further period of throe months from the 1st July 1943* I am. Sir, Tour obedient Servant, (Sgd.) A.B. Hutoheon. The Under Secretary of State, India Office.Allotted to External Department* ^ CONFIDENTIAL CODE TELEGPAM From Government of India, External Affairs Department, To Secretary of State for India* Dated Nev? Delhi, 19*45 hours, 22nd September, 1943 Received 03*00 hours, 23rd September, 1943* 8025* External Affairs Department telegram 6744 of August l2tho 2o Owing to further increase in cost of living in the Persian Gulf increased rates of dearness allowance subject to existing terms and conditions sanctioned to staff serving in the areas specified below as indicated with effect from May 1st 1945* Kerman 75 per cent* Bushire 65 per cent* Khoramshahr Q5 per cent* 3* Please telegraph approval and expedite sanction asked for in External Affairs Department- letter 18(11)-E/43 of May 14th and telegram quoted above*7/ COPY S'- Copiet already teat : )L S*a Mail Kith Secy., p biter Ho f \ , ,, ■id. * cz S ** '4 1 3 _._ „ Copy of a lattar No. 194-64/222, dated the 4th Feby., 1943 from the Hon'ble the Political Resident inthS Persian- Gulf to the Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Department, New Delhi. oooooOOOOooooo &gt; ' r ,, ,, IJiave the honour to addreaa the Government of India on tne subject of the scales of pay of the first interpreters at Muscat, Kuwait and Khorramshanr. These are at present three posts in the ordinary grade of the vernacular cadre, viz*, fis* 120-6-240, plus Rs* 50A in allowMces, and it is proposed that they should be raised to the specialgrade of Rs. 250-10-300. The allowances may, however, be lelt at the ordinary vernacular cadre rate, instead of raising them to correspond with those paid to the Head Munshis at Bus hi re Cfc. 90/-, plus Customs Compensation Allowance of Rs. 25/-) or Banram (Rs. 65/-). 5,*. The reason why it has become necessary to put forward tms proposal is that the value of good interpreters has been iorced up by the prices which Oil Cojipanies and other concerns are prepared to pay for them, with the result that instead of getting one highest quality of men in point of intelligence, trustworthiness and personal character, the Residency is now e^sewhe 9 a ttract those who are unaole to obtain employment r, ,. In last half-year, no fewer than 3 out of a total oi i ordinary grade interpreters have resigned from the cadre, even ohough it meant forfeiting their pensionable service, because other fields offered them more qttractiwe opportunities. iqis is sufficiently serious, and it is still more serious that we should have been unable to recruit men of a sufficiently high standard to replace them* We have been compelled to engage Con a temporary basis) raw youths who are, admittedly, able to about routine office work; but who are entirely unsuited for the really important side of vernacular work in 7 th®se countries. u competition we have to face, it tnat the Anglo^Persian Oil Coropany pay even their junior xxtBxjsKBitgx interpreters from 160 to 240 tomans (worth s J: 1 Shtiy more than the same number of rupees at the present rate of exchange): while a senior man would receive about 400 tomans with many valuable concessions. In Kuwait (where the Oil uorapany do not employ interpreters) ordinary Arab clerks on routine duties are paid from Rs, 166/- to fc/210/- and rereiva free accommodation, light, fuel and water when employed at the w flich. are outside KuwaitlowS? The cpmpetitipn of the oil companies, far from decreasing in naace oime is likely to be greatly enhanced since the war^as restricted ’nen ir an?it S iq R Hn^i C 0 ^ 39 qU ? n Hy/ h ? ir d9raand for this type of now’baf^ ,r ? 0 ^ tant we ahould secure good men no oetore they are all taken up by our KsmgKfcrfcbi con^etitors. ,Althougil Muscat is not at present exuosad to thn aftlr thi°w fl ^ nnH°+h C ° ,r ? any ’ probable that it wifi be raaponaibla ditiea 31 ™^ihSr i 1 a r a l 2 re.“Bl'SLh‘ a f„SS iCUlarl: ' that this post should, be jag* interchangeable with tna crthars^ u rins..- 2 - ?• To get the right type, we must bo able to offer the prospect that after some years’ service in the ordinary vernacular grade, a man may obtain a special grade P 9 st giving him an income comparable to that which he could obtain elsewhere. At present certain special gr^de posts have been created tor the duration of the war; but no men worth having are attracted by th© prospect of a few years temporary service, ana then unemployment in the postwar world, 8 , This war has shown even more clearly than peace-time events the continuing importance of the Persian Gulf to India, and the necessity of a liberal policy m the staffing of its cadres; and I therefore urge upon the Government o- India the desirability of revising the pay of these posts are proposed above. A proposition statement is attacned, ana lo is hoped that a telegraphic sanction may be given.Telegram No. 56-S/Uarap Jated the 6 th May 1943. From:- Foreign, Simla, To: — Britconaul, BuBhire. . Your letter No. 194-64/222 of February 6 th. Interpreter 3 . Government of India agree to upgrade to repeat two posts only from grade fe. 120-6-240 to grade Es. 250-10-300 p.n, the allowances remaining at ordinary vernacular cadre rate. Letter follows.of i ’artof £\t ^; 0 Telegram No* A/689, dated 3*4. Telegram No. A/689, dated October 1942. Frr)m 2 Britconaul, Buahire, To: Foreign, New Delhi. Request telegraphic sanction of one additional temporary clerk (Lower Dixl^ion) Mohammerah where vast ins ease of work makes expansion of staff vitally necessary. Letter in mail. Telegram No. 36-S/Camp. dated the 23rd October 1942. From: BorForeign, Simla, Britconsul, Bushire. Your telegrap No. A 689 To: October 9th. Temporary lower division clerk for Khorramshahr Consulate sanctioned up to end of February 1944 or termination of war, whichever is earlier. Kindly intimate terms on which clerk actually engaged to enable Grovernment of India to make budget provision for next year./ U 1 &lt;$X) Express Letter from the Hon'ble the Political Resident iu the Persian 3ulf No.552-79/63, deted the 14th April 1943. Gonaul, Khorramahahr, has applied for sanction for an extra JNar Establishment clerk to enable himi to ibpe with tt^ enormously increased work by war j time activities in that area&lt;/S^ A i r~ 1 “7 0 f2. In aupport of his app .gures -- StrofT, iTiXqudtes fofloij 11QCT1945I «*&lt; ' ifi gui'ea 111 ! lOM-o I ^ ' Issues and Receipts in t he\ Conf id ential Office from July mZ to Tebryai-y 194^ V tT^s.'y f i 9^3 MoritfiTyl df -o Last Six Months.) 1941. &gt; Last bix Months*) 1942. ) 1943. Lettl£r£ rtrelefrrams .Total. - Receipts. Issues. 301. 136. 230. 260. b31.) 396.)^'* Receipts• Issues. 431. 2i6. 423. 265. 1335 *81. / Receipts. Issues. 407. 327. 37*. 320. 781.j1428 647.) Receipts. Issues. 171. 109. 134. 86. ? 499. 194.) ***’' 156. 223. °7 // to 'TA 238. 250. A- ^^ 3. With this increase in the work, Consul, Khorramshahr, has actually only one man in his confidential office instead of jr , ) —'t^o, since the departure of Mr .Lester to fill the post of Extra 1 QlQ ip 0Assistant, Herman, in December 1942. • 1 A /'• .iv, •, T vy, -n nm n ri rxVi .QfiV t • Di Vn \ ^ /M 14. Consul, Khorramshahr, goes on to say &gt;- _ * “Bearing in mind the fact that at least 86£ of the /\ ' telegrams issued and received are in code 6r cipher and are often required to be decoded at any time of the day or night out of nonAal office hours, whilst much of the other work involved in the Confidential Office must be carried out expeditiously and efficiently, even though it may not in peace time have been usual for. such posts as this to have a cipher clerk at all, I am of the opinion that it is quite impossible to continue for any prolonged period with one clerk only. I have made every effort to re-organise my office and reduce unnecessary correspondence and so economise in staff, but the nature of the work definitely demands a clear division between the secret and confidential office andtk-f**^' office, and one clerk is insufficient for the former. Hence I request that an extra war Establishment clerfc-suitable for employment in the Confidential Office with ciphers and as ® typist or preferably a steno-typist may be sanctioned.” 5.* I support the application and request that sanction for a temporary Upper Division post may be given by telegram as difficulties of recruitment in India, and the delay of getting men, when recruited, to their posts, owing to the lack of passenger ships, render an early decision most desirable. Telegram to the Hobble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf (Repeated to H.M.’s Consul, Khorrarnsnahr) No. 527-C, dated the 24th May 1943. Your 552-79/63 April 14. Temporary Upper Division Clerk for Khorramshahr Consulate sanctioned on usual terms up to end of February 1944 or termination of war or date of filling vacancy caused by transfer of Lester whichever earlier. ™T»tfi CEWEO ■S” 134-3From: The Under Secretary to the Goverment of India in the External Affairs Depart, lent. To: Tho Iion*ble the Political Resident in the ersian Gu3jf. /femorandum No. 1S( 11) -i/43* Dated Simla, the U^th May 19h3. Subject:- Grant of dearness allowance to tlie olarioal eatablishraant in the Persian Gulf. * * Refereiice coiYespondence ending with the telegram from the Uoverment o£ India in the External \ffairs Departnent No.53-}i/Oamp, dated, the 29th April 19^3. 2. Sanction is accorded to the grant of dearness allowance, with retrospective effect from the 1st August 19^v2 until the end of June 194-3? to the clerical staff of the Tersion Gulf Residency et the following scales Area. Percentage of dearness allowance calculated on pay? special pay and all allowances excepting customs compensatory allowance. These allowances are admissible at the rates given above on bO/i enoluaents of the staff (excluding customs compensatory cq allnwance) up to Rs. 200/- p.m. and at half the rates on the 7Qh x^o^ion of their emolixoents exceeding R3.2011/- p.m. up to a maximuii of Rs.500/- p.m* only. 3* The above sanction is provisional tind is subject to confirmation by His sjesty* s Government in so far as the expenditure is divisible. 4-* The Government of India would however omphasiae tijat they should not be expected in future, to give sanctions with retrospective effect as it is against their policy; the present case has been trea ted as very (i) Arab Coast (i eluding Bahrain, Trucial Ooast and Kuwait. (ii) Bushire, Bandar Abbas and Kerr an. (iii) Khorrai :s}iciiir. /special.TREASURY a^AifiBIJRS 18th September f 1943 K.6375/10 Hie Lords Cosmls 3 loners of Hie Majesty's Treasury present Their compliments to the Secretary of State for India, and beg to transmit herewith for information copies of letters of today's date which They have caused to be addressed to the Foreign Office.K.10165/10165/234 ^ E.6573/10 18th September* 1943. Sir* I have laid before the lords Comaissioners of Kis l^ajesty'a Treasury Mr*Hutoheon v 8 letter of the 27 th ultimo relative to the grant of dearness allowances to the clerical establishment in the Itersian Gulf. In reply I am to request you to inform the Secretary of state for foreign Affairs that My Loris sanction the charge to Imperial revenues of a moiety of the expenditure involved in the grant of the allowances in question and in their con tinuance for a further period of three months from the 1st July*1943. I am * e tc• (Sed) C •H.M.WILCC3X. The Under Secretary of State* Foreign Office, Downing Street* S.W.1.Telegram Ho. A-75? dated Buahire the 15th June 1943• Fra,''.: To* Brltconsul, Bush ire Foreign, New Delhi, Reference your c»zr.orandUD No.18(11)-e/ 43 dated 1 'ay 14th, Dearness allowance. Accountant General, Central Revenues has ruled that Ministerial Gazetted officers are not entitled to deamesa allowance, icy intention (vide say telegram No. a/ 148 of Feb,11th ^▼ioualy that they also should receive dearness allowance since pay scales up to Rs. 5 C 0 /- were provided for and it was assumed that they were included in terms •Ministerial establishments' which Government of India (presumably in error) have altered to 'Clerical establishments' in their above-mentioned memorandum. Any other course would result (? gr.cGrr,) in very great hardship apart from the fact that they might find the^elves drawing less pay than their Juniors in Ite* responsible posts. a. Indians, with less than 5 years experience, in 0.K.C.C. Bushire are paid Rs#4C0/- p.m,, plus overtime pay, free servant, qui itore, electiicity, wntor and transjort, wlich have a very substantial value. Treasury Officer, Bushire, has 25 years Govenwent Service but only concession ho receives is h use rent. 4* I therefore request Cfcmraaent cf India to issue urgent telegraphic orders sancticning payment of dearness allow nee to Ministerial Gazetted staff. Telegram 1 .o.a,/ 759 dated Busl.ire the 15 th June 1943. VrcMt Britconsul, Bushire. To* Foreign, New Delhi. Your aecjorandwa No. 18(11 )-e/ 43 of May 14 th. Defirness allowance.2m Kon-Llnistorlal andtec nioal staff i .w.i;. such as Superrisorst Overseers t Draftsiaen* Electrical and I echanical Assistants are, like ministerial establishment, equally hard hit by rises in the cost of living* 3* Grounds for recacjnending dearness allowance stated in my telegrams Ko*a/W of Eeb. 11th. and Ko.aM 2 of April 14th apply equally to above personnel and I request sanction f'ranting de.'xness allowance retrospectively on the same sca^ be acccr e by telegram. pari 26 / 6 . Telegram Jo* 64^*3 dated the 23 th. June 1^4^• gra&amp;s Foreign, New Delhi. To: Brltcenaul, Tkishire. Your telegrams No .A*757 and Ko.A.*759 °f June 15 th. Dearntsa nllowimce. Sanction accorded to grant to (1) Public Works Department subordinate staff (2) gazetted ministerial establishment and (3) Aasiafcint Surgeons* of dearness allowance on terms and conditions specified in Foreign Memorandum No.18(11)-f/ 43 hay 14th. pari 26 / 6 .4 EXU4595A3 India Office, Whitehall, London, • 1* 23rd August, 19^3* Sir, I an directed by the Secretary of State to refer to India Office letter No. Bxt. 2965/43 of the 5th August regarding the grant of dearnens allowance to the clerical establishment in the Persian aulf, and to enquire when an answer may be expected. I am. Sir, lour obedient Servant, (bd.) K.W.R. Luntoy. The Under Secretary of State, Foreign Office, S.W.l.? Vy* V 1 ' U&gt;/ IM/AHD TELEGRAM 31252. Hotted to External Dopt# 9^3 ^ GQN^ID ^TIAL code telegram Prom Government of India* External Affairs Dept* * To Secretary of State for Indiao Dated New Delhi* 16.25 hours, 12th August, 1943. Received 07.00 hours, 13th August, 1943. 6744. Foreign letter 18(ll~E/43) of May 14th. 2 * Pending receipt of your sanction dearness allowance to Persian Gulf staff 'being continued for further period of three months from duly let 19430&amp; ( ( i Olix&lt;J L u . Copy of a memorandum No* 1189-26/196, dated W; the 10Vn OBtober 1942 from the Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Grulf t 9 the Deputy Secretary to the G-overiament of India in the External Affairs Department, New Delhi. iNDEXi* , Sttm — **• ? ^..4 %■» _ _ lOl ~JL.i Reference Oovernment of^Ij Affairs Department memorandum No*80 dated the oth October 1941* e? 6 v*. ‘v* f L la, Kxtarnal Sanction is requested for the extension of the post of Cypher Clerk, Khorramshahr for /further period of one year from 1st March 1943. T rh n -°:c, 'Tw» 7 , Copy of a memorandum No. 3211-2/42, dated 7 ® . Cs^ the 11 th December 1942 from the Under Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affaire Department to the Uon'ble the Political Resident iV£. s 1 ^ in.the Persian Grulf. u i ^ ^ucyect:- Continuance of the post of Cypher Clerk in the Khorramshahr Consulate. r\ A y&gt;i las j Q i j i■ Raference your memorandum No. 1189-26/196, datedIDth October 1942. 2 * .. .Sanction is accorded to the continuance on the existing terms, of the post of Cypher Clerk m the Khorramshahr Consulate for another year upto the and of February 1944 or till the end of the war, whichever is earlier. x Necessary provision is being raadejji the budget estimates for 1943-44. ^fjjT FOR tV n 14 — 'UTTER reived 0-7-1943 VL^XlEXT.2969/2l3 INDIA OFFICE, 'Aiirr-HiAiL, S.W.l. 5th August, 1943* I an directed by the Secretary of State for India to forward herewith a copy of a letter froic the Government of India regarding the grant of dearness allowance to the cleri cal establishment in the Persian Gulf. 2. It will be seen that, in view of the urgency of the matter, the Government of India have sanctioned, provisionally and pending ' approval by F.M.G., the grant of dearness allowance on the aoaleo recomaanded by the Political Resident and shown in paragraph 2 of their letter, for the period Auguet 1st, 1942 to June 50th, 1943. Ifcey eatiuat© that the additions 1 cost involved will amount to some Rs# ? 6,800 ( 15 * 760 ) a year, including expen diture in respect of permanent staff At Bahrein and Muscat, which is not divisible but is borne entirely upon Indian Revenues. 3. subject to the concurrence of the Secre tary of State for Foreign Affairs and to the acceptance of a moiety of the divisible ex enditure involved as a charge upon Imperial /fee venues The Under Secretary of State, Foreign Office, S.W.l.X (Sgd) R.J 1 X 3 . Revenues* the Secretary of State fear India proposes to approve the Govern ment of India’s action and to authorise them to continue the allowances in question after the end of the period for which they have been sanctioned by the Goverrmont of Incia and which han already expired • 4* A copy of thio letter is beine 'ient to H*M.Treasury* ^EXT .2969/45 go^Adentlfll Ho.l8(H)-i',/43. Ftoelij Ttie Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Department. * Toi The under Secretary of state for India, India office, London. Dated Simla, the 14th ttiy, 1943. Subjectt Grant of deer ness allowance to the clerical establish* ment.in the Persian Gulf. Sir, I am directed to address you on the subject of grant of dearness allowance to the clerical establishment under the Persian Gulf Residency. 2. Hie lion^ble the Political Resident in toe Persian Gulf repr sented that toe cost of living in the Persian Gulf and Iran Lad increased tremendously on account of the conditions created by the war ansi toe grant of relief, by way of a dearness allovanoe, to the clerical establishment was a matter of urgent necessity. Also that it was difficult for him to find personnel for toe temporary war appointments on the existing emoluments and that sac* of the permanent staff had resigned and it was difficult for him to retain toe ethers unless relief wasgranted immediately. On the basis of the comparative statement, furnished by the PolitiCcil Resident, of prices of essential articles of consumption at toe cosanencement of the war and in the autumn of last year, at toe various pi oes at which the staff are stationed, toe percentage increases in cost of living per head over that in 1959 work^ out to be about 150 to 26 c. The Political Resident also reported that Foreign Office had sanctioned liberal ratos of dearness allowance (at 170 &amp; since June 194L and at 20GJC e toce February 1945 for Mtl&amp;chic) for toe /low2 . low paid staff in Iran with effect frcrc June 1942. he recoiianended the grant of dearness allowance to the staff in &lt;Hi«?iiQn at the following scales with effect from 1st August 1942 1 - * Percentage of dearness allce Area. (D cprfe is ea^pqrioatprx A ( 2 ) ( 3 ) 40^ Allowances at the rates in column 2 to be (i) Arab Coast (including Bahrain *Trucia1 Coast and Kuwait. admissible on eskolusients of the staff up to Be. 505 S 20 C/- p#ci. and at half (ii) Bush ire. Bandar Abbas the retes on the portion of their emolUBients and Kerman. 7055 exceeding Bs.20C/* p.f-» (iii) Khorrarastahr. up to a soaximum of Bo . 500 /- PJB. only. 5, The Govemaent of India, in view of the circumstances -iven above, a^xee with the Political Besident that V e grant • of dearness at tiie scales proposed by him is necessary and in view of the urgency of the natter, have sancti&lt; ned his proposals provisionally with effect from 1st August 1942 (the date from which dearness allo-anoe has been sanctioned ior lo# paid staff in India) till the end of June 1943, pending approval of Fis Majesty's Government. The extra co;jt Involved, in the above proposals will amount to about Rs• 7 ^^^h&gt; 0 / 4, • (including t* r t m respect of peiraenent staff at Bahrain and Muscat, expenditure m regard to which is not divisible and is entirely borne by the Government of India). 4* I am to requeot that the sanction of I is Majesty’s Government to the above proposals laay be obtained and conveyed to the Government of India by telegram. I have, etc. (Sgd) V.B.AHTE. for Secretary to the Government of India,Co/V. Copy of a letter No. 517-v'9/63, dated the 16th May 1942, from the Secretary to the Hpr^ble .he Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, to the Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Department. Subject:- Provision of additional rmnshis for the Persian Gulf. 479' i | I am directed by the Resident to say that provision exists for the post of a special grade raunshi at Muscat. In the Residents opinion, it is not necessary for this post to be special grade, although a war establishment munshi is certainly necessary at Muscat. 2. It is requested therefore that the following proposals may be sanctioned. (i) retrenchment of the special grade post at Muscat, giving a saving of Rs. 315 per mensem. i(ii) Creation of three ordinary grade vernacular posts. The necessity for these is as follows (a) to replace the special grade raunshtat Muscat; (b) to provide a war establishment munshi at Khurramshabr, for whom His Majesty^ Consul, Khurramshahr, has asked on grounds of the increased work connected with publicity and the development of the report; (c) to provide a war establishment munshi at Busnirt, where our increased interest in the country, the development of the supply Bxlxxaxig route to Russia, Publicity work and extensive touring by junior officers, have produced a bulk of work too large for our present munshis to handle. The cost of these three posts would/Rs. 555/-, the nett additional financial sanction required therefore being Rs. 240/- per mansam. 4 4. It is requested that sanction may be given by telogr am. I,t need not be a r 30 sad how greatly the importance of the Persian side of the Gulf has increased since the original sanction for vvar establishment posts was given.Government of India, Internal Affairs Department. smm MHiffi. From Foreign, Simla, To Britconsul, Bushire. No. 8(22)-El/41, dated Simla, the 1st July 1942. Reference this Department telegram No. 17-^/Camp, of Juno 29th. 2 # Sanction is accorded to tne abolition of the special grade post of Munshi at Muscat which is presumably the post of interpreter there carrying the special grade pay of Rs. 250-10-300 plus Special pay Rs. 50/-/- p # m, and louse rent Alice. Rs. 40/-/- p.m., and fck to the creation, for the period up to the 28th February 1943 or the end of the war, whichever is earlier, of three posts of Vernacular Munshis (one each for Muscat, Khorramahahr and Busiiire) on the foll^e&amp;Lng emoluments:- r.» ay . .. .. .« • • .. ..Rs. 120 —0—240 p.m*eac Gulf allowance. . .. .. ., Rs. 25/-/- p.m. each. House rent allowance Rs. 30/-/- p.m. each. Customs Compensatory allowance (in the case of xmorramshahr and Bushire only). .. ,. Rs. 15/-/- p.m. each, 3* The extra expenditure involved should be met from within your sanctioned budget grant for the current year. 4. The presumption made in paragraph 2 above may kindly be confirmed. THS ISSUE* OF THE! ABOVE! HAS BEEN DULY AUTHORISED. .,d/- V,3. Arte, Under Secretary to the Govt, of India.Corjr — From - Britconsul, Bushire To - Foreign, New Delhi. No. A-318. Dated 21st(and reed 22nd) April 1942. Reference vour exrrese letter No.F.1B(2)»m/ 42 larch let. Kermnn and I'ohammerah ask sanction to provide 50f/30^ allotments required as follows:- Kerman Is.lbO0 Bandar Abbas £.850 Tohammerah F3.1200. 3. I am sending them b&amp;r post a copy of your express letter under reference with the copy of tide telegr^* From - Forei^i, New Delhi. To - Britconaul* Bushire. No.2-£/Caii*&gt;. Dated the 30th April 1942. Your telegrar A-318 April 21st. Please confirm that allowance will be percenta^^e of original rates of pay viu© yuur memorandum No and will be in lieu of compensatory allowances now being paid and that 505» increase is intended only for those drawing not more than 250 Krans. From - Britconaul, Bushire. To - Foreign, New Delhi. Your telegram No. 2-IJ/Camp April 50th. Both points confirmed. From - Foreign New Delhi. To - Britconaul, Bushire. No.5-Ii/Cacap. Dated the 20th May 1942. Your telegram A-351 May 3rd. proposals sanctioned.4 From The Under Secretary to the Government of India in the external Affairs Department, To - The Hon’ble the Politioldi Resident-'in' 11C D X \J.v7I I u ITT TfXXTT Persian Memorandum No. F.8(50)-E/41. i ^ ^ j Dated New Delhi,the ! ^ December 1941. r'\ r^, s subject:- Temporary post of Cypher Clerk in f-. Britannic Majesty's Vice Consulate, Khorr&amp;mshuhr. iSs 2 Reference your telegram No.A-404, dated the 12th December 1941. 2. Sanction is accorded to the continuance on the existing terms of the post of Cypher clerk in His Britannic Majesty’s Vice-Consulate, Khorramshahr, till the end of February 1943 or for the duration of the war, whichever is earlier. Necessary provision on this account is being included in the budget estimates for 1942-43. Sd/- Xxfccxixtao L.A.C.Fry. Under Secretary to the Government of India.A letter has been received from-the Government of India enclosing correspondence with the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf on the subject of the appointment of a cypher clerk at Khoramshahr. Owing to the great increase in both H confidential and oynh-e-p- work occasioned by our recent activities in Persia, the Government of India, at the request of the Political Resident, have appointed an Anglo-indian cleric trained in the Central Cypher Bureau to assist the Vice-Consul at Khoramshahr, and now write to obtain sanction for^tbe appointment, 'The expenditure oil whicrff^in the first instance, is divisible between Imperial and the- Indian Revenues&lt;%ILE COPY ' -&gt; i i W ^GONFID^JTIAL ^ m AIR MAIL. 6141 Fr om To EXPRESS Foreign, Simla. ■V ; '• / T t)F XMDIA. rc Department. L E T T 3 R. /*Uo His Msy esty* s Secretary of Sta^e for India, London. (Repeated Britconsal, Bushire. ) No.D.267-E(c)/41. Dated the^J^^September *41. Reference enclosed copies of correspondence X with the Political Resident Persian GuOf. The expenditure involved is divisible between His Majesty^ Government and Indian Revenues and exceeds £100/-' per annum, but sanction of His Majesty^ Government has been anticipated in view of urgency of matter. It is requested that this action may be approved by telegram. THE ISSUE OF THE ABOVE HAS BEEN AUTHORISED. Under Secretary to the Government of India. S.P.i. EXPRESS. Reference para. No.6 of ay i telejp^at l' Ao .354T July 2Q “til • I hope you will be able to procure immediately European Cypher Clerk to assist Vice Consul at Khoramshahr who is already in difficulties owinj to consequent increase in volume of telegrams arri work of secret nature and v\ho has at the moment no proper confidential staff. Telegram R No.3996 dated 2nd August '41. From - Foreign, Simla. To - - Prior, Shiraz. Your telegram T-361 of 30th July. Khoramshahr. No European available but Anglo-Indian bachelor aged 27 trained in Central Cypher Bureau willing to go. If acceptable wire terms offered. Telegram R No.T/413 dated (and reed.) 13th August r 41. From - Prior, Bahrain. To - - Foreign, Simla.. • • • Your telegram No .3996 August 3rd. 2. Offer accepted, terms are;- (a) Pay Rs.250-10-350. (b) Special pay Rs.50. (c) Customs Compensatory Allowance Rs.25. (d) House rent (Rs. (Gr. omitted) 40? 3. Grateful if clerk concerned could be sent immediately to Khoramshahr via Basra by air as pressure of work very heavy.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0000f0_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/3678</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0000f0</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/3678</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 29/101 'Khorramshahr: clerical staff'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1941/1947</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-09-28T14:45:36</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (62 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 64; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file concerns recruitment of staff at the HM Vice-Consulate at Khorramshahr.The file covers:appointment of a cypher clerk, 1941rates of dearness allowance to staff serving in the Persian Gulf, 1943-47.The file is composed solely of internal correspondence between the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, the HM Legation at Tehran, the HM Vice-Consulate at Khorramshahr, the Treasury, the Foreign Office, the India Office, and the Government of India.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>British Vice-Consulate</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of India</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>British Legation, Tehran</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Treasury</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Recruitment</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0000f0#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>