<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000239.0x000147_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T15:23:41.020Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">V VI* CONFIDENTIAL. , i Si Serial No. REPORT 0N . l'* !) ■ -• n.Jn,'•'/n I Minor operations undertaken by the South Persia Rifles from the 28th March to the 25th June 1917. GENERAL STAFF/INDIA. Case No. 19068 F.O. SIMLA GOVERNMENT CENTRAL BRANCH PRESS 1917 .'Diary No,,70349.) Despatch No. V, dated Shiraz, the 23rd Augu.t 1917. From —Brigadier General Sir Percy Sykes, K.C I.E., C.M.G., Inspector General, South Persia Rifles, Shiraz, To—The Chief of the General Staff, Army Headquarters, Simla. 1 have the honour to forward, as attachments herewith, details of certain minor operations which have been undertaken since my last despatch, No. 28-C., dated aSth March 1917. I endorse the remarks cf the Officers Commanding at the various posts from which these operations were undertaken. 2. The general policy followed, in the distribution of Indian I roops and South Persia Rifles in Southern Persia, is to maintain garrisons at certain im portant centres, strong enough to undertake offensive and punitive^ operations against villagers or tribesmen who can be proved to have taken part in robberies and disturba ices on or near the main roads. The result of recent minor opera tions has proved a strong deterrent to habitual robbers, and there are akeady considerable improvements in the direction of the restoration of law and order. The so-called democratic, but really anarchical, movement in the north of Persia, coupled with the unfriendly attitude of the central government, are the main factors which are at present hampering more rapid progress, by causing uncertainty for the near future. 3. A complete scheme for the organization of the South Persia R.fles and for essential items of a programme of building and improvements in communica tions, was forwarded on the 9th August to all the authorities concerned. Fight ing units and ancillary services are being organized on the lines laid down in this scheme, pending its sanction. The total strength of the South Persia Rifles {s' at present somewhat less than 6,000 of all ranks. The rate of recruiting is now somewhat slow, as men of inferior stamp are rejected and as the percentage of rejections on medical grounds are very high. Quite 80 per cent of the recruits who come up have to be rejected. The limit of existing accommodation has^ been passed already, and efforts are being directed mainly to training the men now available, and to weeding ' out. undesirables. Units are being drilled and trained in squadrons, companies and battalions, and some progress has been made in mu.^ketry. Five new subalterns have arrived via Bandar Abbas, and 25 from England are en route via 1 ehran. 4. In April 1917, when the new staff officers arrived, the re-organization of Force Headquarters was undertaken. The General Staff, Adjutant General, and Quartermaster-general’s branches are compk-te, with clerical establishments. The arrival at Shiraz of the Chief Financial Adviser with seven trained accounts clerks, and the Assistant Director of Medical Services, on the 9th A/gust, will now enable these tuo departments to be put on a satisfactory working basis. The Department of Supply and Transport has been hindicapped by t he wide areas, distant outposts, bad roads, and scarcity of local supplies. I he Supplv a id Transport Corps clerical establishment has consisted hitherto of a few untrained and inexperienced clerks, who have proved incompetent. A list of personnel, to complete departmental and other requirements, has been sent to Army Headquarters, India, and when they arrive, in the autumn, departmental services at Force Headquarters and Brigade Headquarters will be on a satis factory basis. A mud-brick post is being constructed at Siidabad, suitable lor half a battalion of South Persia Rifles. This will be completed in September. The plan of a mud-brick post at Niriz for one company South Persia Rifles and motor details, has been approved by me, and its construction will be undertaken very shortly. These tw r o posts are essential, for accommodation and for security^ Local labour is employed and the cost is not great. 1 he men cf the Burma Mounted Infantry have constructed a small mud-brick post near Tarum, which will probably suffice for the present. C 609 Gs£* 2 6. The following tracks, suitable for the passage of motor vehicles, have been constructed: — 1. Shiraz to Aminabad (near Isfahan) (217 miles). 2. Shiraz vid Niriz to Saidabad (239 miles). 3. Saidabad to Kirman (112 miles). ^ 4. Saidabad southwards towards Tarum, for about 30 miles. Work is now in progress and there are no great difficulties as far south as Hajiabad joo miles). 7. I have the honour to attach a list of British Officers, Warrant Officers, and Non-Commissioned Officers, and of Indian Officers, Non-Commissioned Officers and men, who have rendered specially meritorious services. Copy of the foregoing for information, to - His Britannic Majesty’s Minister Plenipotentiary, and Envoy Extra ordinary, at the Court of the Shah of Persia, I ehran. List of Appendices accompanying despatch No. V, dated 2jrd August IQ 1 ?* No. I. Operations against robber tribes near Abadeh. No. 2. Report on the Meshed-i-Murghab engagement.' No. 3. Report on the action of Kafta against the Kurshulli. No. 4. Report on the Banak and Khurrami engagements. • # No. 5. Report on the affray at Deh Chah. — \ *3 Operations against robber tribes near Abadeh, May and June 191J. 1. On 8th May, information was received by the Officer Commanding at Abadeh, Captain Lilly, South Persia Rifles, that a band of 30 Qashqai robbers had carried off 35 sheep and 4 donkeys, and had been located at a place 10 miles from Abadeh. Forty-five South Persia Rifles sowars] were promptly sent out and surprised the robbers numbering 70 or 80 in all and including 30 mounted men. The rob bers took to the hills, but. a running fight was maintained until dark, when the robbers got away. Ten of the robbers are known to have been hit. All the stolen property was recovered. 2. On 10th June, 15 South Persia Rifles and a few South Persia “ Tufan- gchis ” when escorting a postal waggon and caravan, were attacked by 30 or 40 Qashqai robbers, between Shulsistan and Yezdikhast; a fight ensued, the robbers being eventually beaten off with a loss of one man wounded. 3. Onthei2th June, Captain Lilly received information, at 10 A.M., that a caravan had been carried off that morning at the same spot where the fight took place on the 28th May. The following men belonging to the escort were killed in the defence of the caravan :— No. 123 Sarbaz Mohamed, South Persia Rifles. No. 127 Sarbaz Reza Ghuli, South Persia Rifles, (dangerously wounded since died of wounds). The robbers had 2 men wounded and one horse killed. Captain Lilly at once went in pursuit of the robbers with 60 South Persia Rifle sowars. They caught up the robbers, who were afterwards identified as Kashkuli (Qashqai), about 3 P.m. The latter had been reinforced to a strength of 200 mounted men and with footmen besides. A fight ensued at about 700 yards range. The enemy was forced to abandon 2^ donkeys, including 18 laden with wheat, and also one rrare. T.he robbers lost 2 killed and a few wounded. The South Persia Rifles casualties were 1 horse wounded and 2 horses died of exhaus tion. Captain Lilly’s force covered over 50 miles during the day. This officer, in his telegraphic report of the 14th June, recorded his appreciation of the action of the British non-commissioned officer instructors in the following words “ The British non-commissioned officers behaved splendidly ”. G. P. GRANT, Major, General Staff, South Persia Riffles. Report on the Meshed-i- Murghab engagement on 1st June 1917. The mounted column of the Dehbid detachment consisting of Headquarters and 1 squadron, Burma Mounted Infantry (Major V. P. B. Williams and Lieu tenant W. R. Morley) with some two hundred loaded baggage animals, left Madar-i-Sulaiman at 4*3° A.M. on ist June 1917J ^n route for Meshed-i- Murghab. At about 5-45 a.m. the advance guard patrols were on a line about 2 miles south of Meshed-i*Murghab. Situated 100 yards east of the caravan road, on this line, was an Arab encampment, numbering from 40 to 50 black tents. A scout, working dismounted, on the extreme left, suddenly came on to an Arab who, on seeing him, took cover, deliberately loaded bis rifle and was pre paring tp take aim. The scout, seeing this, rushed the Arab, seized his rifle, and asked him to explain his action. ’I he Arab could give no satisfactory explana tion^ The scout then pulled down the lever of the Arab’s rifle, released the cartridge, and told him to come with him to his Sahib, who would decide what to do in the matter. The Arab replied-—“ All right, I will come along with you to the Sahib (I would mention that this scout is a Punjabi Mussalman and has Shiraz ; The 22nd August 19174 a simple colloquial knowledge of Persian. It would also be noticed that the Arab had ample opportunity to realize what he was up against). The scout, giving the Arab the benefit of any doubt there may have been, let him go. 1 mmediately the Arab bolted off east towards the Arab encampment, the scout following him on foot. He reached the encampment well ahead of the scout and took refuge in one of the black tents. A • ' The Indian Officer commanding the advance guard, with two sowars, rode into the encampment and enquired from the scout what had happened. The Indian Officer was then joined by two South Persia Rifle sowars, who accompanied the column. A crowd gathered round. My Indian Officer demanded that the above mentioned Arab should be given up in order that he might be brought before the O. C. Column. This was refused. No force or threatening action was resort ed to. The Indian Officer immediately sent me back a report. Threatening to shoot a sowar cannot be tolerated. Futhermore, in view of the fact that the encampment flatly refused to sunender the man amicably, although they knew full well what had transpired, I ordered that he be arrested and brought before me. In the meantime, many Arabs, with rifles, cleared from the encampment and took up a position some too jyirds or so to the south-east. The Indian Officer commanding the advance guard on receipt of my order dismounted two sowars one South Persia Rifle, and one Burma Mounted Infantry, who commenced to search for the said Arab. At this juncture Lieutenant Morley joined the search party. The Arab was seen hiding in a tent; he did not wait to be caught but bolted towards the other Arabs of the encampment to where they were h position, with the two sowars close on his heels The Arab, as he ran, turned round and fired point-blank at the two sowars. On this, the Arabs in position, opened a regular fusilade on my men in the encampment and on my column, which was then flush with the encampment. Those in the encampment very narrowly escaped being hit. Two bullets fell within a foot of Lieutenant Morley. Lieutenant Morley then withdrew the men from the encampment and joined me for orders Immediately after commencement of fire some women of the encampment deliberately drove a large flock of sheep in amongst my column, causing tremen dous dust and confusion. Several animals dropped their loads and broke away. Bullets were dropping amongst the baggage animals. Luckily none were hit, but it transpired that some six or seven sheep and goats were hit. I dismounted three troops in a nullah by the road-side. Baggage animals I got together in order and sent them on to Meshed-i-Murghab, under escort of one troop, with orders to halt clear of the village under load, keeping in communication with me by signal. I then returned to my dismounted troops. From the first shot fired by the Arabs up to this moment, 10 to 15 minutes had elapsed. During the whole of this time the Arabs had kept up a continuous fire. But their fire nad not been returned by any of my men. This tribe had no cause whatsoever to treat my column with hostility and such hostility shewn by them, knowing .from the beginning who we were, were points which decided me to assume an offensive and punish them. I ordered Lieutenant Morley to take Jemadar Pertab Singh and No. 4 Troop, to charge through the encampment, dismounted, to the Arab position. jnos. 2 and 3 Troops, I kept in support by the side of the caravan road. No. 1 Troop had been sent off previously in charge of the baggage. 1 posted look out sentries 200 to 300 yards west and south of my supports to guard against the possibility of other tribes joining in. From the supports I rounded up 350 head of sheep and goats and a few other things, and sent them off to my column at Meshed-i-Murghab. No. 4 Troop, as it emerged to the east of the encamp ment, was met with a burst of fire from its front and right front, after which the rabs fled to the hills about 1,000 yards to the south-east, firing as they A treated. They took up a position on the top of the first ridge. As No. 4 rp oop was crossing a river at the foot of this ridge, it was subjected to a very Tr V y fire. On its commencing the ascent, the Arabs vacated the first ridge, beaWhen Lieutenant Morley topped the first ridge he again came under fire from the Arabs in position on a second higher ridge. This ridge was also taken by No. 4 Troop, only to come under fire again from the Arabs on a yet higher ridge, which had also to be taken. At this juncture I moved my supports to the first ridge, south-east of the Arab encampment. My communications were thereby made more secure and I still commanded the Arab encampment. Lieutenant Morley then called up his led horses and followed up the Arabs mounted. As the advance proceeded the Arabs appeared to thin out in a most extraordinary way. The chase continued to a point about 3 miles east of the Post road, whence a turn was made south, wheeling on to Madar-i-Sulaiman. Thence turning north, Lieutenant Morley extended his troop over about one mile of country searching for any stray Arab. One Arab of this encampment, without a rifle, was found hiding and seized, but it will be difficult to prove if he was implicated. During the chase, one rifle was picked up, and also one cartridge belt full of empty fired cartridge cases. During Lieutenant Morley’s advance, my look-out sentries reported two horsemen and three or four dismounted men appearing on the hills about a mile away to the south-west. On seeing my supports they disappeared after a very short time; evidently members of another tribe. Lieutenant Morley joined me at about 10 A.M. It was miraculous that there was not a single casualty on our side. Four Arabs were wounded; two severely and two slightly. Lieutenant Morley and Jemadar Pertab Singh put down the number of Arabs actually engaged in the fight as 30; I myself counted over 20. The Arabs had been thoroughly scattered all over the country ; I had 350 head of their sheep and goats and had captured one of their rifles. This I considered sufficient punishment for their behaviour. I then proceeded to Meshed-i-Murghab. This tribe is the Pharsi Shevani, a section of the big Kutti tribe, and which, I understand is in a kind of partnership with the village of Khurrami. The Khan of the Kutti is by name Sher Khan, now reported at Farukh, 3 fursakhs east of Sivand. The Pharsi Shevani section of the Kutti separated itself from Sher Khan a short time ago. It belongs to the Qawam-ul-Mulk. About 5 months previous to this the Qawam-ul-Mulk imprisoned 22 men of this very section of the Kutti tribe for robbery. I am told they are imprisoned in Shiraz. On the evening of the 31st May 1917. the Arabs, with whom I had the encounter, stole some sheep and goats from Quadrabad. Some 40 of the 350 sheep and goats I captured have been recognized by villagers of Dehbid as originally belonging to the people of that village. I am informed that the man responsible for the affray is Mir Mahmud, son of Jamal. Abdul Majid was another name given to me. The whole of the countryside appear to be in terror of these Arabs and are delighted that they have been taught a lesson. The only man who did not seem pleased was Mir Mehdi of Madar-i-Sulaiman, Rais-Tufangchi, who, I understand, is entrusted with the safeguarding of the road from Quavvamabad to some little distance short of Sartun. He tried to excuse the Arabs in every way, and has been spreading reports to minimise their action. Lieutenant Morley, Jemadar Pertab Singh, and the 4th troop, Burma Mount ed Infantry, took the first three ridges in most excellent style under continuous fire. That nobody was hit is a matter of extraordinary good luck. The chase was carried out by them in a most vigorous manner. It is practically certain that the Arabs who naturally know every inch of the ground, scattered and hid. Lieute nant Morley reports that the Burman pony was marvellous up and down the hills V. P. B. WILLIAMS, Major, Commanding Burma Mounted Infantry* over very rough country. Dehbid ; The gth June igi7&gt; ■ \ I'M- ) C609GSB6 Report on the action of Kafta against the Kurshulli ) Gala nan Kashgai and Bassari. At the end of May 1917, a few days previous to the arrival of the Dehbid Column in Dehbid, the Kurshulli had robbed 600 sheep and 'oats from the inhabitants of Dehbid, Shahrabad, Abrquh andj Mihrabad. The Kuluntur of the Kurshulli, by name Attor Khan, had been asked to return the stolen pro pel t), but had continually evaded by promises which were never fulfilled. Furthermore, very many complaints with respect to various other robberies were received from the raiyat against this tribe. It is held in greater dread than any other tribe in this area, which is saying a great deal. It would be as well to mention that it was the Kurshulli which threatened our supply column from Mihrabad in June last, which resulted in the Puzeh-i-Siah operations by the Burma Mounted Infantry 0119th and 10th June 1917. The Kurshullis consist of something over 300 tents or families, and possesses roughly 120-150 rifles of both Martini and Mauser patterns. Through constant robberies its kalantar, Attor Khan, has amassed much property.^ He pays tribute to the Saulat-es*Su!tana at Isphahan, who inherited this tribe throu'h his wife, the daughter of Haji Nasrullah. . &amp; It was finally decideo to send out a punitive column from Dehbid to punish the Kurshulli and recover the stolen property. Information as totne exact position of the Kurshulli and the.topography of the country which it covered was so scarce, that it took many days to' piece together information, which could appear sufficient for the formation of any plan of action. ^ It was important that everything should be done withouttheknow- ledge of tne Kurshulu, and therefore every possible precaution was taken. Nevertheless, Attcr Khan had apparently been on the lookout for trouble for sometime, and cnc of his spies managed in some miraculous way to brin' h m mformahon; consequently news of the coming of the punitive column was known to Attcr Khan in plenty o^ time to arrange a well planned reception. To make matters worse, information obtained as to the position of the tribes and the topography of the country turned out to be so incorrect that difficulties were very greatly enhanced. . J Map I was maoe ouc on information obtained before the column left Deh- * M aP 2. A comparison with the correct map ... ,. .. . , , wili give an idea of the difficulties in res pect .0 this which tne column had to contend against. It also shows the pro posed general plan of operations formed previous to the departure of the column from Dcnbid. It should be especial ! y noted that the Bassari tribe the east of the Kurshulli—a vital mistake. was reported well to At 3-0 P.M, on the afternoon of the 4th July 1917, a punitive column com posed of :— 1 squadron Burma Mounted Infantry (Lieutenant W. R. Morley). 150 rifles phis 2 machine guns and sections, 124th (Queen’s Own) Baluchistan Infantry (Major C. A. Chaldecott and Captain I R Gregory). j* • Medical Details. (Major J. W. Ulius, I.M.S.) Officer Commanding the Column, Major V. P. B. Williams, left Deh bid for the Kurshulli via Banak and Mushkun—the shorter and easier route via Khurrami and Kishlak was avoided to ensure greater secrecy. At 5-45 P.M., idem, the column arrived at Banak ; at 9-30 P M. it reached a point | mile S. S. E. of Mushkun. A halt w 7 as made here for one hour A start was again made at 10-30 P.M. At 1-40 AM. on 5th July 1917 the column arrived at what, according to the information of guides, was supposed to be the * ,*7 * * position of assembly agreed upon. A study of the maps will show how hope- lessly incorrect distances and directions had been given by the Guides. At this point the Kurshulii encampment was expected to'be within 2 ^miles in a S. W. direction. To settle on a position of assembly closer than this with the moon at lull would have been dangerous. Already the column bad marched 41 miles further than was estimated. Consequently doubt as to the remainder of the distance, and in fact as to all information entered my mind. I therefore_ decided to give the western attack to the Burma Mounted Infantry, and to increase the strength of the southern attack. K was well that these changes were made. At 2 A.M., 5th July 1917, Major Chaldecott with 75 ri fies, 124th Baluchistan Infantry left the position of assembly in a south-westerly direction. His main objective being to surround the encampment in which At tor Khan was supposed to be (Map i-C.) and capture him. This party would afterwards form the southern attack. All other attacks were to hinge oq Major Chaldecott’s attack. At the same time Lieutenant W. R. Morley with two troops, Burma Mounted Infantry kft in a W. N. W. direction to verge round and form the W. S. \ . attack. The remaining 75 infantry (less baggage guarc) under Captain J. R. Gregory, with 2 machine guns and sections, 2 ' troops Burma Mounted Infantry (less baggage guard) I reserved for the direct eastern attack. 1 he northern face was purposely left unguarded, in the hopes that the Kurshulii would be foiced to retreat that way, it being clear open country for three miles. Strict orders were given to all ranks not to molest the Bassari tribe unless it showed open hostility. I remained at the position of assembly a good half hour to give Major Chaldecott and Lieutenant Morley time to get well on to their positions so that all three attacks might be simultaneous. I left the point of assembly at 2*40 A.M. idem, being led due west and not south-west as was expected. It was not till 4-0 A.M., that the encampments came into sight one mile to the west. It ■ was ^then obvious how completely wrong all information had been ; and not a smgie feature of the ground or positions of the encampments could be recognized. Furthermore, to make matters worse, when I thought to surprise the enemy, I was met with long range fire when in column of route. There was not a sign of either Major Chaldecott or Lieutenant Morley, and it was only too cleaAhat they had also been led astray. Information had said that there was a very old fort near the Kurshulli main encampment, walls flush wuth the ground and only 2-3 feet high, whereas I ob served one mile to the west, a hill 200 feet high, rising sheer out of the plain, on the top of which weie the high walls of an old fort well loopholed. The southern western and northern walls appeared intact^ the eastern wall was broken, but this was reinforced by other smaller walls inside, the remains of dw T e!!ings. On the slopes of the hill on all sides were the walls (intact) of the numerous^ houses of an old village. There w r ere no roofs. These walls rose in tiers up the sides of the hill to the foundations of the fort; each wall was well loopholed at the top so that men could fire over the heads of those firing from the wall beneath*them. This fort, by name Kafta, was occupied by the Kurshullis in force, ready prepared. ’ . J On being fired on I deployed and came into position 1,000 yards E. S. E- of the fort, and decided to wait in this position till I could pick up communication with Major Chaldecott and Lieutenant Morley. The enemy from the fort kept up a desultory but continuous fire and picked up the range very fairly well. At about 4-30 A.M. Major Chaldecott appeared 1J miles to my south-east, coming down the slope of the hill on to what his guide had led him to believe was the position of Attor Khan’s encampment. At the same time I notic*ed much running to and fro between an opening in the hills and the fort in a S. VV. direction from the latter. This was judged to be the enemy’s line of communication with the hills, where my W. S. W. attack should have been launched at dawn had not the guides failed. My plan was then to isolate the fort from all communication with the hills, culminating, jf necessary, in an assault on the fort.8 Jemadar Pertab Singh, with one troop Burma Mounted Infantry was des patched to cut in on this line of communication, and at the same time to clear the large encampment near the south of the fort and prevent more men rein forcing the already large garrison in the fort. Lieutenant Morley, in the meantime had been going steadily in a W. N. ^ Westerly direction at a fast pace, keeping clear of a continuous line of encamp ments on his left. His guide was uncertain whether these encampments were Kurshulli or Bassari ! It was 9 miles from the position of assembly before he came to the end of the encampments and was able to swing round to the south. To make certain, Lieutenant Morley picked out the largest encampment, promptly surrounded it, and had some 75 sowars and tufangchis at his mercy. The headman came running out, threw his hat and rifle down in token of surrender and asked for peace. Lieutenant Morley ascertained that this was the Bassari tribe; adhering to orders, he left them unmolested and turned E. S. E. It transpired afterwards that the Bassari had sent the Kurshulli some 30-40 tufangchis and a good supply of ammunition to help them against us.^ It was truly unfortunate that this was not known then. Nevertheless, Lieutenant Morley’s prompt action decidedly put a stop to any more reinforcements being sent to the Kurshulli by this tribe, a very valuable point gained. Major Chaldecott, on coming down on to the plain, cleared a small Kurshulli encampment to the south, driving the men to the hills. There was no sign any where of Attor Khan’s encampment ; it turned out to lie in the main encampment to the south of the fort. Major Chaldecott then verged round west and cleared another small Kurshulli encampment. At this juncture he was met with a heavy fire from the hills to the south. He changed his direction to the south to meet this fire, which proved to be that of the Kashgais, the Galazan tribe headed by Kalandar. Jemedar Pertab Singh with his troop carried out my object to a certain extent in his direction, but he was under such a heavy fire that I sent orders to him to withdraw and join up with Major Chaldecott, who was being heavily engaged by the Kashgais in positions on the hills. Major Chaldecott then drove the Kashgais well into the hills towards the main ridge. (See Map 3.) It was about 5-^0 A.M. that Lt. Morley first appeared coming from the west. He took up a position about one mile W. S. W. of the fort overlooking the S. W. approach to the fort. He was in position about 6 A.M. From here he engaged the enemy (who proved to be Bassaris) udio had come to the foot of the hills to his right flank and drove them well into the hills. This finally isolated the garrison of the fort. Major Chaldecott’s attack had been most effective. He now considered, however, that it had been driven far enough. He, therefore, informed me by messenger to this effect, I sent word to him to join me. For 2J hours the troops with me in position 1,coo yds. E. S. E., had been under intermittent fire from the fort. In spite of there being no cover what soever in the plain nobody was hit, which was most lucky. I had kept the garrison of the fort w T el! occupied with periodical bursts of fire keeping them well under cover and disturbing their communications. At 6-30 A M. Major Chaldecott joined me with his infantry and Jemedar Pertab Singh’s troop. He formed up his infantry on my left flank. Separating the Kashgais and Bassaris in the hills from the Kurshullis in the fort had been accomplished. Nevertheless the enemy were far from beaten, and still held all the commanding positions. The fort had to be attacked and taken; a difficult proposition, since I had no guns and the troops had now been on the march and underarms for 15J hours ; the Infantry had covered :— Major Chaldecott’s party 40 miles, Captain Gregory’s party 33 miles and the Mounted Infantry from 40—46 miles. They had all been engaging the enemy for 2|- hours. The men were dead tired and hungry ; but to feed them w r ould have meant a retirement out of range, w'hich would have been fatal. In spite of all this the troops answered the call in a magnificent spirit. Under the prevailing circumstances I considered it most essential to get every available man into the firing line, in order to bring as large a volume of fire as possible to bear on the fort and also for the moral effect.My dispositions for this final phase were as follows : Major Chaidecott s infantry to attack from the S. E., and E. with the machine guns in the middle ; three troops, Burma Mounted Infantry from the N. E., one troop, Burma Mounted Infantry to be left under cover to the west of the fort cover ing the line of retreat of the garrison to the hills to the S. W. This line of retreat was purposely left open. The attack was arranged for 7-30 A.M. (Vide Map 4.) When preparations and movements were commenced for the attack, Major Chaldecott was suddenly attacked from his left rear by a party of Kashgais, who had come down from the hills to the north of the Imamzada. These were driven off with despatch, but all formations were shifted round 10-15 ^gerregs towards the north in order to clear IMajor Chaldeco^t s left flank* The directions for attack were finally, three troops Burma Mounted Infantry from the N. N. E , 124th Baluchistan Infantry from E. N. E. and^ S. E.^ by E., with the machine guns in the middle of the infantry ; one section of infantry being dropped back on Major Chaldecott’s If ft flank. Jemedar Pertab Singh with one troop Burma Mounted Infantry was directed into position about 900 yards to the west of the fort. His position was under cover from^ the fort and from our own fire, and was also 1,000 yards from the enemy’s line of retreat (Vide Map 5). The attack commenced at 8 A.M. by alternate rushes of troops and sec tions from the right. Fire was first opened at 1,000 yards range. The order liness, evenness and spirit of this attack were truly magnificent. No. 3138 Havildar Boota Khan, 124th Baluchistan Infantry in charge of the machine guns did most excellent work, bringing his guns into action at four distinct ranges during the attack. The Kashgai and Bassari tried to assist the fort by coining down from the hills, so ne firing on to the left of the line and some on to Jemadar Pertab Singh. The volume of fire brought to bear on the fort, and the steadiness and determination of all must have weakened the nerves of those in the fort, for, when the line fixed bayonets, at about 100 yards from the foot of the hill on which the fort was situated, the garrison thought it safer to evacuate. This they commenced to do in one long stream to t'te S. W. Major Chaldecott’s left platoon and one machine gun on the left and two troops Burma Mounted Infantry on the right picked up the range at 900 and 1 000 yards on to the retreating enemy. Here also Jemadar Pertab Singh’s troop on the west came in most useful and did good execution. The old Kaftafort and village was thus taken and the enemy completely routed. Operations ceased at about 9-30 A.M. The troops therefore, had been 18--hours underarms, 13 hours continual marching, and immediately follow ing this 5^ hours continual manoeuvring and fighting. The whole of the column, both men and ponied, was then brought into the fort and buildings immediately beneath it. At 11 A.M. all ranks got their first taste of food. All the Kurshulli’s valuable stock, viz :— cattle to the number of 182 and 9 (nine) donkeys had been col’ected in the fort. These were all captured. About 100 of the enemy’s tents with belongings were collected together and burnt in full view of all three tribes, who had now taken sanctuary on the hills immedi ately to the south of the Imamzada. The enemy were permuted to remove their deadj an.l wounded. Both Major Chaldccott and Lieutenant Morley had had opportunities of cap turing many hundreds of sheep, but they let them alone because it was impossible to distinguish between the sheep of the Bassari and those of the Kurshuili, and capture of the former might have led to complications. In the afternoon I sent word to Attor Khan that if he gave up the 600 stolen sheep I would hand back the 182 heads of cattle and 9 donkeys, a far more valuable property, and that I would also stop the burning of the tent?. However, he was too cowed and scared to do anything. C603GSBThe total number of Kurshullis, Kashgai and Bassaris engaged against us throughout the fight was 500 fighting men with 300 rifles. These numbers are from several reports, and the lowest figures are quoted. Casualties :— Enemy. —Killed ... ... ... ••• 2 3 Wounded Exact number not known. Our Own Killed ... ... ••• ••• * Wounded ... ... ••• ••• 2 Also one machine gun mule wounded. The superb dash and spirit in face of all difficulties, the magnificient feat of endurance of all ranks under my command were worthy of the very highest praise and commendation. In these operations it is difficult to single out specific acts of bravery—each and every man behaved splendidly. It was, and is broadly known, that the column arrived at the end of an ex ceptionally long march expecting to surprise an enemy, who on the contrary were thoroughly prepared and held the advantage on all sides. Furthermore, the Kurshulli, themselves the worst and most feared tribe in this area, were helped by the Kashgai and Bassari, two very powerful tribes. In spite of all these advantages a crushing defeat was inflicted. The result has been that the moral effect of these operations amongst other tribes, both large and small, has been enormous. * * * Dehbid ; ^ J. p. B. WILLIAMS, Major, The 14th July igij* ) Commanding Dehbid Punitive Column. Report on the Banak and Khurrami engagements, dated i8th-igth June igij. On the afternoon of the 18th June 1917, about 3-45 P.M., news was brought to Dehbid by two Persian charvadars that a caravan of 500 donkeys, of which they formed part, had been looted on its way from Abadeh to Ahmadabad. It was reported that 30 donkeys with loads had been looted from this caravan by robbers who were estimated to number 15. Agreeablv to the orders of Lieutenant-Colonel E. F. Twigg, Officer Com manding, Dehbid, 1 troop, Burma Mounted Infantry (Lieutenant W. R. Morley) left Dehbid for Banak at 5-15 P.M., 18th instant. The two Persian charvadars concerned accompanied this troop. At 7-25 P.M. it arrived on the high ground to the east of, and overlooking Banak. Reconnaissance showed that there were 40 to 50 black tents in the low ground immediately to the east of Banak. From movement in the encampment it appeared that the Arabs were preparing to break camp. The Persian charvadars asserted that these Arabs were the robbers. The ground Surrounding the Arab encampment was much broken^ up by ravines and streams; darkness was rapidly closing in. Lieutenant Money, in consequence, realized that one troop was insufficient to prevent them getting away. He immediately sent back to Dehbid for reinforcements. Jemadar Gulzar Singh, Burma Mounted Infantry, with 15 rifles was then sent around to the old buildings of Banak village to the west, Lieutenant Morley remaining in his position. Strict orders w T ere given that there was to be no firing unless absolutely forced, the object being to prevent the tribe getting away, and seizing the headman. Owing to the darkness and difficult nature of the ground, it was 8-15 P.M. before Jemadar Gulzar Singh got into position. One or two of his men were seen by the Arabs who, without hesitation, deliberately fired. This fire was not returned, jemadar Gulzar Singh advanced slightly down towards the encampment. I heArabs, who outnumbered him, charged him, firing as they came. It was then that Jemadar Gulzar Singh first opened fire. The Arabs immediately retired followed up by Jemadar Gulzar Singh, Lieutenant Morley joining him in the encampment with the rest of the troop. The general confusion in the dark and the interference of the women, enabled the Arabs to break awav in a south easterly direction. They were followed up for over a mile, but here the courage of the Persian tufangchi, who was acting as guide to Lieutenant Morley, failed him, and he refused to go further. Lieutenant Morley returned to his original position overlooking the encampment. On the way back he rounded up all cattle, etc., he could find, and herded them in the hollow to the east of his position. From amongst this booty the Persian charvadars recognized one of their looted donkeys. Casualties of the enemy in this engagement are not known. Lieutenant Morley’s message asking for reinforcements arrived in Dehbid at 9 P.M., 18th instant. Two troops, Burma Mounted Infantry. (vlajor V. P. B. Williams) left at 11-30 P.M. on the same date. Two platoons 124th Baluchistan Infantry were ordered to follow up, leaving Dehbid at 4 A.M., 19th instant. The march at night to Banak (10 miles) was over very broken ground and the road for the greater part of the way, was most difficult. At 2 A.M. Major Williams arrived at a point about f- mile east of Banak, i.e., about \ mile east of Lieutenant Morley’s position. Neither party was desirous of making any further movement which might give away the presence of so many men, since it was hoped that the Arabs would return to their camp, and an attack would be made on them at dawn. Unfortunately the encampment was found to be deserted at dawn. At 4-15 A M., Major Williams, joining up with Lieutenant Morley’s troop, searched the country to the west and south-west. There was no sign of the enemy. He returned to Banak at 6-30 A.M. to pick up the infantry. The two platoons, 124th Baluchistan Infantry (Captain Gregory) arrived at 7 A.M. Their arrival was delayed owing to the tufangchi guide having led them astray. A signalling post had been established at Dehbid and communication was picked up at 8-30 A.M., and a report sent in to the Officer Commanding Dehbid by helio. The force was hidden out of sight in a hollow about ^ mile east of Banak. This deceived the Arabs since two men, thinking the coast was clear, sneaked back to their tents. They were both captured. At 10 A.M. Major Williams sent one troop B. M. I. and 12 rifles 124th Baluchistan Infantry direct back to Dehbid in charge of all booty and the prisoners. With the remainder, 2 troops B. M. I. and 40 rifles 124th Baluchis tan Infantry, he decided to return to Dehbid via Khurrami, this being the general line of retreat of the Arabs ai.d the way to sanctuary for them. At 3 miles the ruined village of Hosainabad was reached, but no sign of the enemy. After passing this place, and within 2 miles of Khurrami, several isfilated men were observed through glasses to be stealthily making for the open country both towards the north-east and south, and hiding in ravines and behind sangars. All of these weie speedily captured. The majority were eventually let go but the more suspicious were retained. About one mile from Khurrami, a scout reported an Arab tribe hurridly on the move south-east of that village. At the same time much movement was observed towards the south-east, in the river bed immediately below that village. The time was then 12 noon. Major Williams detached one troop, B. M. I., (Lieutenant Morley) to stop all these movements, and with instructions not to fire unless absolutely compelled. On entering Khurrami, Major Williams found it practically deserted, but some 200 men were collected at a short distance outside the village. ^ 1 hey refused to give any help, in fact the attitude of this village was most unfriendly, suspicious and almost hostile. I he village was then thoroughly seaiched. Five rifles and a good deal of ammunition were found. Exper.ence has shown that Arabs, when on the run after being attacked, hide their rifles whenever opportunity occurs, sometimes in extraordinary ways, even to burying themI 2 hastily in the ground. Furthermore the village of Khurrami is suspected of being in partnership with the Farsi Arabs, in fact it is mostly inhabited by Arabs. It was therefore quite possible that these rides were the property of the robbers hurriedly discarded in their retreat. All the men of the village were then collected together and were informed that the rides would be returned to the owners on their coming to claim them with the kalantar, who would be held responsible for rightful ownership. Two only, up to date, have been satisfac torily claimed and returned. One or two men have been up to claim rides of quite a different pattern from those taken. In the meantime Lieutenant Morley overtook the tribe which was on the move. Me called on them to stop. The women obeyed but the men bolted off to the east and from the first hill they came to deliberately fired on the troop. Jemadar Pertab Singh, with half the troop was then sent to skirt the ground to the north*east, to cut them off, Lieutenant Morley keeping in his original line. Jemadar Pertab Singh got in rear of the Arabs and engaged them, capturing li prisoners and killing or wounding g. The chase altogether lasted for 6 miles, when it was abandoned. Many animals were captured. From amongst these one of the looted donkeys was recognised by the Persian charvadars. Lieutenant Morley returned to Khurrami at 2-30 P.M. At 3 P.M. the whole force returned to Dehbid, where it arrived at 5 P.M. The tribe concerned is the Hossain Ali section of the Farsi tribe (Qutti). It numbers altogether some 500 tents. The total number of livestock captured in the engagements of the 18th and 19th instant, is as follows :— Camels ... ... ... ... ... 61 Donkeys Sheep and goats ... Mare (with foal) ... Bullocks Total number of prisoners taken was 18. Our own casualties ... A 7 / 74 4^5 1 8 r Dehbid ; Tfie 24th June 191J .) V. P. B. WILLIAMS J/rf jor, Commanding Burma Mounted Infantry, Report on Affray at Deh Chah ; Captain Masters, 16th ^Rajputs ; dated 25th June 1917. In May 1917 95 cattle had been carried off by men of the village of Deh Chab, 20 miles north of Niriz, from the District of Pariz. Also one sowar S. P. R. had been looted of his rifle, horse, accoutrements and clothing, and the inhabitants of Deh Chah were suspected. 2. Captain Masters, 16th Rajputs, when proceeding on escort duty to Niriz, was ordered by Major Wagstaff, Commanding at Saidabad, to endeavour to recover the stolen property. 3. Captain Masters attempted to obtain the cattle through the local autho rities, but after 3 days fruitless delay, informed the Governor of Niriz that he would go himself to Deh Chah and recover the property. 4. On the morning of the 25th June, Captain Masters, escorted by— 13 men of 21st Lancers (Consular Guard), 25 rifles, 16th Rajputs,13 and some of the Deputy Governor of Niriz's tufangchis, marched to Deh Chah He had previously notified his peaceful intentions towards the villagers through the Governor of Niriz, and, when nearing the village, sent ahead some of the Deputy Governor’s tufangchis to w’arn the villagers of his approach. He was met by a crowd outside the village, but as they had not brought the cattle Captain Masters announced his intention of proceeding straight to the headman’s house, and of waiting there. Soon after 5 or 6 shots were fired from the village at Captain Masters’ party. 5. Captain Masters extended his men and attacked the village, which, with the aid of rifle grenades, was soon cleared. 6. In this attack, one man of the South Persia Rifles, No. 22, Ali, was severely wounded. The villagers lost 10 men killed. One woman was accidental ly wounded by a stray bullet. 7. As a further punishment for their treacherous conduct, 4 cattle, 19 donkeys and 4 horses were taken from the villagers, and their bhusa stacks set 8. Captain Masters mentions Naib Sayid Ali Khan, South Persia Rifles, for “ very good work throughout ”. 9. This prompt action has had the effect of deterring other local robber •bands from raiding in Sirjan. on fire. G. P. GRANT, Major, General Staff, South Penia Riffles. C609GSB— 00 ~ 2541017 — GC BP BimU</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000239.0x000147_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/MIL/17/15/33</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000239.0x000147</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/MIL/17/15/33</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'REPORT ON minor operations undertaken by the South Persia Rifles from the 28th March to the 25th June 1917.'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1917/1917</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-07-18T23:01:58</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (10 folios)</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence commences at the front cover with 1 and terminates at the inside back cover with 12; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located at the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. Pagination: the volume also contains an original printed pagination sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file is a printed report, consisting of a despatch from Brigadier-General Sir Percy Sykes, Inspector General, South Persia Rifles, to the Chief of the General Staff, Army Headquarters, Simla, which provides details of five minor military operations undertaken against tribes in southern Persia. Five sketch maps appear at the end (ff 9-11).The report was published in 1917 by the General Staff, India, and printed at the Government Central Branch Press, Simla.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Chief of the General Staff, India</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">recipient</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>South Persia Rifles, Inspector-General</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government Central Branch Press, Simla</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">publisher</roleTerm></role></name><name type="personal"><namePart>Sir Knight Percy Molesworth Sykes</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Military operations</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000239.0x000147#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>