<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>qnlhc/12952_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-05-03T15:01:50.600Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><physicalDescription><extent>79 items</extent><extent>72 pages ; 21 centimeters</extent></physicalDescription><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><originInfo><dateIssued>1883</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-05-03T14:56:40</dateCaptured></originInfo><titleInfo><title>Commercial Law of Egypt</title></titleInfo><identifier>qnlhc/12952_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>12952</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/qnlhc/12952</url><physicalLocation>Qatar National Library</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>12952</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><abstract>This volume, Qanun al-Tijarah (Commercial law of Egypt), contains two printed works, the commercial and the maritime codes of Egypt. The two documents are extracted from a more comprehensive but unidentified work, possibly covering civil procedure and the criminal code. Each title is preceded by the order of Egyptian ruler Khedive Muhammad Tawfīq authorizing publication and implementation of the law. The first title, Commercial Code, includes definitions of terms and focuses on debt and bankruptcy. The second title, Maritime Code, covers ships operating under the Ottoman flag and the rights and duties of ship owners, officers, crew members, and passengers. Also included are provisions for required documents, insurance, and leasing. The laws came into effect in 1883 and were printed the same year at the Bulaq Press, the Egyptian government’s publishing arm. Egyptian law, like imperial Ottoman law, was based on European, mainly French, models. It was applied by the so-called Mixed Courts in the context of increasing internationalization of trade and under the influence of the Great Powers. The codes promulgated here remained in effect until a further legislative revolution occurred in the 1940s. Codified laws such as these operated concurrently with Islamic law governing personal matters, such as marriage and inheritance.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Ship</topic></subject><subject><topic>Maritime law</topic></subject><subject><geographic>Cairo</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Commercial law</topic></subject><subject><topic>Ottoman Empire</topic></subject><subject><topic>Commerce</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/qnlhc/12952#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>