<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0001c6_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-12T04:52:23.124Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Si■■■■ ■■MMMMtia CONFIDENTIAL No.g/752 . I ► The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persia** Gulf presents his compliments to The Political Agent, Bahrain, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the under mentioned document CO for report. Persian Gulf Residency Camp, Bahrain, Dated 1946, Reference to previous correspondence Description of Enclosure. Name and Date Tehran Embassy Letter No. C3.167/103/46 dated 19th July 1946 and enclos. Subj ect. Alleged illicit trade between Bail rain and Iran.$ &lt;T) British Embassy, T eh ran. 19th July 1946. G3.167/103/46 . Dear Residency, The enclosed copies of a letter dated 22nd June 1946 from one La ohamed Kawesh to II is Majesty’s Ambassador and of the Commercial Secretariat’s minutes on it, are sent for your information and for any li^ht you can throw on the allegation of lr. Kawesh. Yours ever, 2d. J.3.SOMERS C0EK3. Office of the Political Resident, Bahra in • Mohamad Kawesh. Tehran 22nd June 19 46. Kawesh Inport and Export. Bahrain. Jo His Excellency H.B.M.’s Ambassador in Iran, Tehran. Your Excellency, I, the unaersigner, Mohamed Kawash, merchant in Bahrain, have the honour to infom you that having been tor 13 years at Bahrain, I came now to Iran to me t my brothers and sisters and during this time I requested the Iranian Government to grant me the permission tor delivery to the customs house of Bushire 25 tons tea - Indian origin and 15 tons sugar from Bahra in. , ^ _ . s .l hese goods are given' fre i by the Bahrain Eood ^ontio 1 f ice, lI.B.M.’ s consulate in sahrain and are intended for the purpose of Barter business. I wish to import to Bahrain Poods tuff, Sheeps, Oxes, Pirewood and ndible fats. Ihe Iranian Government is willing to give me tne above permission with the condition that H.B.h. ’s emioassy in Tehran would give me a non-quota cor if i ate for the above foodstuff, that they are being freed by' ne ^^ ira,lri Control Office and the quotas will not ue deducted by M.E.S.G. from’the Iranian quotas. v I should be most obliged if Your Excellency .vould grant me such a certificate as otherwise my position will be such that I would be obliged to sell the tea and sugar in question to trie Iranian Government with a price wni ca will ruin my whole fortune, which I being a faitliful citizen of Bahrain unaer the protectorate of British Empire, have gained with honest and truthful work during many years in Bahrain. ° I have the honour to be Sir, Your Excellency’s most obedient servant, ^gd. Llohamed Kawesh.^(9 lONij'IDHIITIAL 3 X-'N Subje c t: M ohanmied Kav ea h of Bahrain • !• This merchant was int6y$\dced to this Secretariat by the British Consul-General at Bush ire, and assistance requested for him to get permission from the Persian Government for the importation, extra to quota, of 2b tons of tea and 15 tons of sugar. 2. Naturally, I told the enquirer thu^t the hmbas y, having written to the Persian Government in very certain terms that no importation of sugar and tea, extra to quota, would be allowed, it was impossible for the Embassy now to itiaxe an exception on his behalf. 0. hr. Havesh tnen told me the whole story which he said was so secret that Vie haa been unable to divulge it previously. xn Banrain and its dependencies, there is a great shortage of livestock (sheep, go-its &amp;hd cows), cooking fat and firewood. There are no trees, of course, along the Arab Littoral. The Political Agent, Bahrain, recognising the need for the importation of livestock, fat and firewood, obtained from the Indian Government a special quota allocation of tea and sugar for importation into Iran. The accruing funds were disbursed in the purchase of live-stock, fat and firewood which, through Tangistan (the territory almost due hast of Bushire which reaches the Persian Gulf at several small ports) was smuggled in lighters across the Gulf to Bahrain. Presumably the informant infers that the Political Agant, recognising the impossibility of getting the Persian Government to permit the export of livestock, fat and firewood from the Southern Provinces of Persia, has blinked at the smuggling traffic which has gone on. 4. According to the informant, the official tea and sugar sold to him for the purpose of obtaining funds in Persia, was actually smuggled through the small ports of Lilvar and Lavar. 5. The applicant states that the presence of the Tudeh Party in Bushire has now prevented this perfectly satis factory and illegitimate trade and he has been forced, therefore, in order to obtain livestock, fat ana firewood for Bahrain, to apply for permission to import the 25 tons of tea and 15 tons of sugar supplied through the auspices of the Political Agent, Bahrain. 6. The Persian Government has told him that he may import the tea and sugar so long as tnis secretariat will state that those quantities are extra to Persia’s quota ex world supplies and he now wishes us to do this. 7. whether) you will decide that this alleged semi-official transaction shou d have the bles ing of this arnbasay and ask for special dispensation regarding this tea and ugar, is, of course, none of my affair. I my say, however, that from tilings said to me by Mr. Kavesh, I gather that he has served us in the Gulf in one or two otner interesting ways. Mr. Kavesh claims that he received a special pas.; from the Political Agent, Bahrain, to enable him to come across from Bahrain to Bushire in nis own lighter - which lighter is now left in hie care of Mirza Ghulam iios ein Ha* in wno is the head interpreter in Buslii-fe. T eh ran, 25th July 1946.D*0 No.C/1031 The 12th September, 1946 ^Dear Belgrave, H.B.M. *s Ambassador, Tehran, was recently asked to grant a 'non-quota certificate' to one, Mohammed Kawash of Bahrain, to the effect that a consignment of 25 tons of tea and 15 tons of sugar which the latter had taken across with him to Persia was released by the Bahrain Food Control Office, and that these amounts will not be deducted by the Middle Bast Supply Centre from Iranian quotas. I attach a copy of his letter to the Ambassador. 2. Mohammed Kawash was subsequently Interviewed by the Commercial secretary of the Embassy, when he told the latter that the official tea and sugar sold to him for barter purposes was actually smuggled through the small ports of Dilvar and Lavar. 3. I should be glad to receive your comments. Yours sincerely In i ^ C.D. Belgrave, Esq., C.E.E., Adviser to the Bahrain Government Government, BahrainITo.Adv/c/ 88 T1 IS CUSTO^Si OL 312; 8AI:RiJI.; 13th 3Q^ tender, It 46 . , The Adviser, The G-overnniaxit of Banrain, Bahrain. honor an dun ; - eference attached, frou our records over the last sin months, i;ohai..ed Khnash has ii ported goods into Bahrain, which have earned hin barter. Tea Sugar as vuider Sugar 30 bags or 3 tons Tea 28 cases or P ton, these figures fall a long way short of the figures mentioned by Kawash. I can only presume that this gentleman has ^ *v - su^—^ H- -&lt;■ tea in tnc. smal^. villages or alternatively has purchase barter chits from here which have not been shipped in his name. , but Sugar and Tea find their ray into Persia not only from Bahrain, but from the Trucial Coast and huwait, there fore there is nothing to suggest that ga-wasi^s consignment is entirely ex Bahrain Barter Stocks. No certificate can therefore be 'iven. ^T'’Vr'mrn otp J*-/A. 'W Jl‘ A PORT OFFICER, UIN.rnmn iiii.iJIi'1 - D.O. No. c/1127. 7l fB The 7th of October, 1946. Dear Belgrave, please refer to your deral-offlcial, letter No.1982-60SP dated the 21st September, 1946, to Hudson* 2. X should be grateful If you could give me, as soon as possible, In the form of a Note, all the information you have regarding Mohammed Kawashes past and present history and activities. Yours sincerely, a C.D* Belgrave, Esq., C.B.E., Adviser to the Bahrain Government, Bahrain * NS.GOVERNMENT OF BAHRAIN, SECRET. D.O.No. ■»i A Adviserate, October 22, 1946. / Reference your D.O.No. C/1127 dated 7th October 1946. Mohammed Kawash came from Bushire to Bahrain in June 1932, having, according to his own story, had to leave Bushire in hurry because he forged a cheque there. Perhaps this fact could be verified. He arrived with no money and for some time existed on the charity of local Persians. Later he obtained employment as a messenger, a peon and then was employed as a clearing agent, at the customs, by some of Persian merchants. For a while he was of some use as an informer to the State Police, being in contact with low class Persians and Bahama he was able to sell information about liquor and drugs. Several Jews, Persians and Bahama were convicted on information which was supplied by him. At this time he applied for Bahrain nationality, to protect himself against any consequence of the affair in which he was involved in Bushire. He was granted Bahrain nationality in 1935, the reason for his departure from Bushire was not known to me. Kawash then started a business importing fresh and dried fruit from Persia, he had worked before as the agent for one Saleh bin Abdulla Saleh but they quarrelled and,through Kawash,Saleh got a prison sentence. On another occasion Kawash was used by some merchants who had a grudge against the Baladiya to create trouble with the municipal officials, which he did successfully. Being an intelligent man without any scruples he has usually taken part in other peoples’ quarrels in order to gain advantage for himself. For some time he was employed as an informer by the Agency but he followed the way of most informers by threatening people that if they did not do something for him he would tell tales against them. He used to boast about the stories which he told at the Agency to the detriment of the Bahrain Government and the Municipality. A good many people were exceedingly afraid of him. During the war he prospered exceedingly and is now reputed to be worth several lakhs of rupees. He bought barter tea and shipped it to Persia and there is very good reason to believe that he did 2 /-~ 0*5 Confidential. BAHRAIN RECEIPT.V 1 a great deal of smuggling, sometimes filling tea chests with more valuable goods than tea, but he was never caught. Much of the cloth which was to be smuggled out by the Political Resident’s farrashes is said have He belonged to him. g. Kawash is now in partnership with one Ali Dashti, once a schoolmaster in the Persian School and now ostensibly in the export trade but actually an active smuggler. ^ A few years ago Kawash , who takes an active part in Shia affairs, was mainly responsible for a fracas between the Police and the people who were taking part in the Muharram procession. The Bahrain Govern ment, owing to his various undesirable activities^ decided to revoke his nationality and his Bahrain passport was taken from him. lo Since conditions in Persia have changed he is no longer afraid of visiting that country and he recently went to Tehran, via Abadan, but he still fights shy of Bushire. l\' In his smuggling activities he and Ali Dashti are connected with Shaikh Ali bin Abdulla bin Isa and he is able in this way to contact Shaikh Abdulla bin Isa. He owns property in Bahrain and has built a house on land 6n Manama which he bought. He trafficks in opium but does not use it himself. Although in every way a most undesirable member of society, combining intelligence with dishonesty, I have never had any information which might lead me to suspect that he is politically inclined. Captain H.D.H. Ranee, H. B. M’s Political Agent, BahrainCONFIDENTIAL No.C/1210. POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN The 29th October, 1946. To The Hon»ble the political Resident in the per: ' MEMORANDUM . Reference your printed Letter No.c/752 dated the 25th August, 1946. 2. The Adviser informs me as follows: 'Mohd. Kawash came from Bushire to Bahrain in June, 1932. According to his own story he had to leave Bushire in a hurry because he had forged a cheque. He arrived with no money and for some time existed on the charity of local Persians. Later he worked in turn as a messenger, a peon, and a clearing agent at the customs for some Persian merchants. He also made money by selling information about liquor and drugs to the Bahrain police, and there is reason to believe that the Agency employed his services for a short time as an ’informer 1 . (Mr. Bel- grave states that this was in Major Alban's time). In 1935 to protect himself against the consequences of his Bushire mal-practices he applied for, and was granted, Bahrain nationality. The Adviser informs me that he did not know at the time the reason for Mohd. Kawash's leaving Bushire. and dried fruit from Persia. He had previously worked as agent for another importer, Saleh bin Abdullah Saleh, but they quarrelled and Kawash was instrumental in getting the latter a prison sentence. During the war years he prospered exceedingly and is now reputed to be worth several lakhs of rupees. Tie is in partnership with one, Ali Dashti, once a school-master in the Persian School and now ostensibly in the export trade but actually an active smuggler. Kawash also trafficks in opium, but does not use it himself. Both partners are connected in their smuggling activities with Shaikh All, son of Shaikh Abdullah bin Isa, the uncle of His Highness. He owns property in Bahrain and has built a house in Manama on his own land. In every way a most undesirable member of society, he^is both intelligent and without scruples. He has often made use of this to interfere in other people's quarrels in order to benefit himself. He caused trouble with the municipal officials on behalf of some merchants who had a grudge against the Baladiyeh, and, a few years ago, was mainly responsible for the fracas between the police and some people who were taking part in a Muharram procession. For this he was deprived of his Bahrain nationality. Tie is an active Shia, but there is no information to show that he is politically inclined.” 3. In 1943 an Increase in the tea and sugar quotas of the Arab Sheikhdoms was made for barter purposes, and Mohd. Kawash was one of the importers who bought barter tea and sugar from the Bahrain Government in order to make these barter purchases for Bahrain, it is suspected that he sometimes filled tea Soon after this he started a business importing fresh /chests- 2 - \\ chests with more valuable goods than tea, but he was never caught. A copy of Kawash»s letter to H.B.M.*s Ambassador, Tehran, has been sent to the Adviser for' his comments, and I enclose a copy of his reply, it will be seen from this that the Bahrain Government are of the opinion that no non-quota certificate can be given Kawash. I agree. 4. Kawash left Bahrain in October 1945. He was given the usual Certificate of Identity by this Agency. He has recently returned, and talks of closing his busi ness here and moving with his family to Tehran to do business there. Sd./- H.D.H. RANCH. Political Agent, Bahrain. ATTESTED . . for Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain. NS.PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN. the 24th October, 1946. To The political Agent, Bahrain. MEMORANDUM £ | . Referep^fe this Residency printed letter No. C/752, dated the 25th August, 1946. 2. An early reply is requested. i - ... . i ■ -■ ■ ■ -COI^IDBBTIAL. Reference your orders of yesterday regarding Mohammed Kawosh. I have found that the above Mohammed Kawosh came from Iran about 13 years ago. When he left Iran he was demanded by the Iranian Authorities on account of some mischief, probably political intervention in internal affairs. He came here penniless, but he started business on commission, and later on he got some capital from one Abul-Qasim, an Irani and Engineer in Bahrain. Before the war his financial position was very weak, but during the war his trade increased and he has saved a fair capital. About 1940-41 he owned a landed property in Bahrain, so he naturalised himself as a Bahrain subject. In 1942-43 he made trouble during Muharram days, where upon his Bahrain nationality was withdrawn by the Bahrain authorities, but later on it was given to him. Recently he has returned from his visit to Iran, and decided to close ud his business here and remove his family to Iran. It is said that he Is going to start business in Teheran. During the time of his business, he has been considered as an ordinary merchant without recognition or priority on others bji the Departments in Bahrain please.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0001c6_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/375</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0001c6</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/375</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 9/31 Report that illicit trade between Bahrain and Persia is encouraged by the Political Agent Bahrain'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1946/1946</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-06-04T00:12:16</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (16 folios)</extent><extent>The papers in the file are arranged chronologically. There are file notes at the end, on folios 15-17. The notes are arranged chronologically and refer to documents within the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 18; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 3-13; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled, and are located in the same position as the main sequence. A previous foliation sequence, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains correspondence between the Political Agent at Bahrain, the British Embassy at Tehran and the Adviser to the Government of Bahrain, concerning allegations of illegal trade between Bahrain and Iran by a merchant from Bushire, who was responsible for smuggling sugar, tea and opium into Bahrain, and who is believed to be employed by the Agency as an 'informer'.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>British Embassy in Iran, Tehran</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Iran</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Tea</topic></subject><subject><topic>Smuggling</topic></subject><subject><topic>Opium trade</topic></subject><subject><topic>Sugar</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0001c6#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>