<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000358.0x00026e_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-18T07:52:56.885Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">SELECTIONS 4 ^ / PEOM THE RECORDS OF THE GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, FOREIGN DEPARTMENT. No. CCXLV. F oreign D epartment S erial N o. 20. ADMINISTRATION REPORT OF THE PERSIAN GULF POLITICAL RESIDENCY AND MUSCAT POLITICAL AGENCY FOR 1887-88. fhiblislub bi; JUithovitij. CALCUTTA: PRINTED BY THE SUPERINTENDENT OF GOVERNMENT PRINTING, INDIA. 1888.F rom To No. 189. C OLONEL E. C. UOSS, C.S.I., JPolitical Rssidcut in the JPerslcin Gulf, aud Jlct* Britciuuio JHcijssty's Oousul»G'6}ievctl Jot FciiSf H. M. DURAND, E sq ., C.S.L, Secretary to the Government of India, Foreign Department, SIMLA. B ushire, the 14th June 1888. S ir, I have the honour to submit the Annual Administration Report of this Residency for the year 1887-88, arranged as follows P art I.— General Resume. Appendix A.—Meteorological Tables. Part II.— Resume of Muscat Affairs, compiled by Surgeon-Major A. S. Jayakar. Appendix a.— Biographical sketch of the life of Seyyid Sultan Bin, el-Imam Ahmed, by Colonel S. B. Miles. Part III.— Report on Trade of Persian Gulf for 1887. Appendix A.—'Tabular Statistics. Part IV.— Report on Trade of Muscat. Appendix A. —Tabular Statistics. 2. I would draw attention to the historieal sketch which Colonel Miles has kindly placed at my disposal. It is interesting and valuable in a political point of view, especially so at the present important epoch of the history of Oman. I would be obliged for twelve copies of this paper printed separately. 3. Bequesting to be supplied with the usual printed copies of the general report and some separate copies of the trade reports and tables, I have the honour to be, S ir, Your most obedient Servant, E. C. ROSS, Colonel, Political Resident, Fersian Gulf,ADMINISTEATIOJST REPORT OF THE PERSIAN ( J ULF POLITICAL RESIDENCY and MUSCAT POLITICAL AGENCY for 188T-88. P aet I- genebal stjmmaey. 1.—MUSCAT STATE. 1. The Political Agency at Muscat continued during the year under review to be under Lieutenant-Colonel E. Mockler, but owing to the deputation of that officer on special duty to Baghdad, and his subsequently obtaining privilege leave, the annual report of the Agency has been drawn up by Surgeon-Major A. S. Jayakar, SJ. It will be observed by those who may peruse this report that a very dangerous combi nation against the Sultan was nipped in the bad and entirely frustrated by the rapid and decided action taken by the Political Agent, Colonel Mockler, and myself, with the sanction of the Government of India, on the occasion of the capture of Soweyk by Seyyid Ibrahim-bin- Kais. The speedy settlement of this matter had a very beneficial result. In acknowledging the detailed report on the subject, the Secretary to Government conveyed the satisfaction of Government in the following terms: a I am to inform you that your proceedings in this matter are approved by the Government of India.' 2.—'OMAN PIRATE COAST. 3. The petty independent States situated on the north-western coast of 'Oman, with which we have intimate relations, arising from treaty engagements in connection with the maintenance of peace and order on the seas, are six in number:— (1) Ras-el-Khaimah, ruled by Shaikh Hameyd-bin-'Abdullah, who belongs to the tribe El-Kowasim, commonly pronounced Jowasim. This tribal patronymic is derived6 ADMINISTRATION REPORT OF THE PERSIAN GULF POLITICAL i Kasim whence Kasimi the adjective forra, and the from an ancestor named ^ o£ j fol . K is a local vulgarism c ol eohve P E1 T KoW Jowas;m have been a powerful tribe in the.r day, and are w.dely employed. T ^ ^ they enJ0yed a now to be found on the , 188 7 the position of Deputy position of much consideraUon. Dp to the ) Governor of Lingah was virtually hercd.tary m the famdy. • • i i. u /%-P oomi Ariliic s©nil* Persisto derivation) (2) Umm-nl-Kawain {Full. Gawam, sa.d to be of semr-Ar , has for Chief Shaikh Ahmed -bin-'Abdullah of the tube Al-bu Ah. (3) 'Jjman, under Shaikh Kashid-bin Hameyd, also of the Al-bu-Ali. (4) Shargah (more correctly Sharkah) under the Kowasimi Shaikh Sakar-b,n-Khahd. (5) Ma S . ruled by Shaikh Rashid-bin-Maktoom, of the tribe Al-bu-Falasah. which is cognate with the greater Beni-Yas. (6) Abn Mem, under Shaikh Za'ced -biu-Khaleefah, Chief of all the BeniAas, and the most powerful and influential of the'Trucial' Chiefs of Oman. 4. The several Chiefs, on the whole, gave satisfaction as regards their engagements to Government, and the only troublesome case which occurred was the plunder of some boats, which were lying at anchor in the sheltered bunders of Hasiyan, Ghantoot, and Ghanac m, y Bedouin Arabs, who swam off and attacked the vessels from the shore. 5 Two of the boats which were plundered in the bunders of Hasiyan and Ghantoot belonged to subjects of the Chief of Shargah, and the third, plundered in Khor Ghanadhir, belonged to Ras-el-Khaimah. The assailants were said to be Bedouins of the Monasir tribe, and from the fact of the places named being admittedly situated within the strip of coast nominally under the Chief of Abu-Dhabi, it was a question whether Shaikh Za'eed should not be held responsible for the outrages. It was alleged that the Monasir tribe are amenable to the authority of the Beni-Yas Chief, and that if he chose to exert himself he could exact reparation for the outrages referred to. 6. The point was a nice one in itself, but I felt that it should not be considered solely on its merits, but that the general political situation and contemporary occurrences in other parts of the Persian Gulf should be kept in view. It has not appeared to me clearly established that the Mona.sir, who were accused of the outrage, are really subject to the authority and control of Shaikh Za'eed, and it must be borne in mind that similar robberies have been frequently happening in places under the authority of the Turkish Government, without- any attempt at redress. 7. It has appeared to me that it would be impolitic, in these circumstances, if not unfair, to adopt a harsh course towards the Chief of Abu-Dhabi in this matter. Beyond an appeal to his pride and sense of justice no further action has been taken. 8. The ' Trucial' Chiefs remained at peace one with another during the year, but Shaikh Za'eed of Abu-Dhabi, was, in May 1887, engaged in hostilities against a section of the Dhowahir tribe of Bereymi, who had opposed themselves to his influence at that place. The Beni-Yas Chief was victorious and returned to Abu-Dhabi in May, bringing with him as prisoners Shaikh Sauced Bin Ali and another Shaikh of the Dhowahir tribe. 9. His Highness Seyyid Toorkee endeavoured to send succour to the Dhowahir in the shape of money and ammunition, but his action was taken too late in the day. 10. In the month of September a band of marauders of the Monasir tribe made a raid in the vicinity of Shargah, and carried off eight women and children and several camels and horses.residency and muscat political agency for 1887-88. 7 11. In the month of September, the Residency Agent at Lingah reported that Haji Ahmed Khan Sirtip had sent a small party under Shaikh Hasan, the Chief of Kishm, to the island of Sirri with orders to erect a flagstaff and hoist the Persian flag thereon, and Her Majesty's Ship Ranger reported that the Persian flag was flying on the island in question. 12. The Islands of Tamb, Sirri and Bu-Musa, situated midway between the Persian and 'Oman Coast, have been for generations hereditary possessions of the Jowasim Arabs, those of the tribe who settled on the Persian Coast, having always been admitted to share in the rights attaching to these tribal possessions. The island of Sirri has been hitherto superintended by the principal Jowasitni Shaikh of Lingah, who has been usually Deputy Governor of that port and district under the Persian Government. 13. It was always understood that the Jowasimi Shaikhs of Lingah administered the island of Sirri in virtue of their position as Shaikhs of the Jowasimi tribe, not in consequence of then- office of Deputy Governor of the Persian district. The hoisting of the Persian flag at Sirri, therefore, constituted a complete alteration of the status as regards that island, and the Arab Chief of Shargah lodged a protest and remonstrance against what he considered annexation by Persia of an Arab posression. The whole question was referred to Her Majesty's Legation at Teheran and has continued to be the subject of diplomatic correspondence. 3.— EL-BAHRAIN. 14. The Islands of Bahrain did not wholly escape from the disquieting influence at work in the Persian Gulf during the year under review. 15. Owing to the attitude assumed by the Chief of El-Bidaa, Shaikh Jasim bin Muham- mad bin Thani^ and the virtual encouragement given by him to his turbulent dependents of El-Katr cases of piracy commenced to occur off that coast in the month of July, chiefly ou vessels belonging to Bahrain. Simultaneously the Beni Hajir robbers, who have been so long the pest of the seas and coast adjacent to Bahrain, recommenced their depredations ou Bahrain vessels in the waters about El-Kateef, within the jurisdiction of the Turkish authorities. For years bands of Beni Hajir robbers, harbouring chiefly in the districts under Turkish territory, have preyed on the native craft plying between Bahrain and El-Kateef, occasionally extending their operations further to the eastward, always hitherto with entire impunity. « Armati mare exercent, semperque recentes juvant prsedse, et vivere rapto' 'armed they harass the sea, ever delighting in fresh robberies, and living on the spoil.' 16. During the past summer the policy at first adopted by Shaikh Jasim encouraged bands of these marauders to sally out to sea from the K.ati Coast, as well as fiom the recog nised Turkish territory, and the matter became serious. About half a dozen piracies were reported off the Katr Coast and as many more in the Turkish waters. The latter cases were reported to the Turkish authorities through the British representative in Turkish Arabia. 17. As regards the piracies occurring off El-Katr, it appeared necessary to adopt some more direct measures in order to check the progress of those disorders. The Chief of Bahrain, Shaikh Esau bin Ali, in August addressed me a letter complaining of the injuries and losses suffered by his subjects from these piracies, and begging for protection and enforcement of security by sea, failing which he asked to be allowed a free hand to avenge himself on the robbers. 18. In the month of July, during my visit to Muscat and the Batineh Coast, I had deputed Khan Bahadur A. R. Hakim to El-Bidaa, in Her Majesty' Ship Sphinx, to make certain inquiries into the conduct o£ Shaikh Jasim, and on my return, having received STr. Hakim's report, I decided to despatch the First Assistant Resident in the Residency steamer Lawrence to El-Bidaa, with orders to remove thence all British Indian subjects, and to warn Shaikh Jasim 1 would hold him responsible for disorders and outrages occurring within, or by persons issuing from his district.8 administration report of the persian gulf political 19. I also requested the senior naval officer to keep one vessel of war stationed at Bahrain. 20. On receiving the full reports of the investigations conducted by the First Assistant and the Native Agents on the Katr Coast and Bahrain, it appeared to me obvious that the outrages and disorders which had occurred were the result of the attitude of Jasim in Muhammad bin Thani, who, for his own purposes, had desired and brought to pass the unset tled state of affairs on land and on sea, and it appeared to me highly necessary, firstly, that some decided action should be taken to restore confidence, and, secondly, that such action should touch Shaikh Jasim's personal interests, otherwise it would be ineffectual. 21. On the I7th of August I proceeded to Bahrain in the Lawrence in order to consult the Chief and concert measures. Having received information that certain specie and pearls, to the value of some R2U,000, was then in Bahrain, I asked the Chief if he would be willing to lay an embargo on the consignment at my requisition. The Chief immediately assented, and the property ^was formally sequestrated, and the First Assistant proceeded in Lawrence to El- Bidaa, and informed Shaikh Jasim of this measure, and my reasons for taking it. 22. As soon as Shaikh Jasim realised that unpleasant consequences to himself were likely to ensue from the disorders he had encouraged, he bestirred himself, and in a short time the piracies were stopped and order restored. 23. Eventually Shaikh Jasim appointed an Agent (his son-in-law) with powers to con clude terms with an Agent appointed by me for the settlement of British and Bahrain com plaints against him. A sum of R6,390i having been paid by Jasim's Agent in compensation to the British Indian and Bahrain sufferers from piracies and other outrages committed by Shaikh Jasim's dependants, his property under sequestration was released, and he was informed that the previously existing friendly relations would be resumed. These proceedings were approved by the Government of India. 24. On the 19th February, His Excellency Nafiz Pasha, Wali of Busrah, appeared off Bahrain in the Turkish corvette Johaff and anchored for one night. No communication was held with the shore and the vessel proceeded to the Katr Coast the following day and did not again visit Bahrain. 4.—EL-KATR. 25. Circumstances combine to render our relations and dealings with the chief Arab autho rity residing on the Katr Coast peculiarly unsatisfactory and delicate. In the first place the Chief referred to. Shaikh Jasim bin Muhammad bin Thani, who is regarded by the British Government as an independent Arab Shaikh, to a certain extent bound to respect the regulations for maintenance of peace by sea, is by character and disposition a most troublesome person to deal with. Secondly, he usually avows himself a subject and officer of the Turkish Govern ment, which has appointed him &lt;£ Kaim-Makam,^ or Deputy Governor, of El-Katr. Like the notorious Shaikh Muhammad bin Khalifah of Bahrain, Shaikh Jasim has coquetted in turn with the various powers in his neighbourhood, according to the whim of the moment, or pressure of circumstances. 26. In the summer of 1887 Shaikh Jasim appeared to be much dissatisfied with his Turkis patrons and their proceedings, and intimated that he had withdrawn from El-Bidaa, and takei up his residence at a place called Dha'ayen, near Semeysamah, and exercised no further author ity in El Bidaa. 27. It soon appeared, however, that there was no sincerity in this statement, as Shaikl Jasim, through his sons and relatives, continued to exercise a baneful influence over the affaii- of El-Bidaa, which eventually culminated in disturbances and outrages. 28. Shaikh Jasim, alarmed at a proposal to establish a custom-house at El-Bidaa wa anxious to diminish the importance of the port and, with that end in view, planned to o-et ri. of all the foreign traders, British Indian and Persian.residency and muscat political agency for 1887-88. 9 29. At the given signal the Bedouin Arabs of the vicinity entered the bazaar o£ El-Bidaa and plundered the shops o£ the Persian dealers residing there, driving them all from the place. The British Indian traders on this occasion were protected by Shaikh Jasim's relatives, but their turn was to come. 30. In the month of August two Indian traders were wantonly and cruelly wounded bv the Bedouins in El-Bidaa, and immediately afterwards piracies commenced off the coast of Katr. 31. In the summary of Bahrain affairs it has been stated how these disorders were eventually checked, and it is only necessary here to remark that compensation to the wounded Indians was included in the amount levied from Shaikh Jasim. 32. No redress has been obtained by the Persians for the losses sustained by them during the plunder of El-Bidaa, when all the Persian traders were forced to remove from the place; but an appeal on the subject was made by the Persian to the Turkish Government. 33. The Wali of Busrah, Nafiz Pasha, visited El-Bidaa in the corvette Zohaff in the month of February and promised Shaikh Jasim a title and decorations. A supply of coal also has been sent to El-Bidaa by the Turkish authorities, and the Turkish guard at that place is about to be strengthened. 34. The usual petty and desultory warfare has occasionally been kept up between Shaikh Jasim's adherents in El-Katr and the Monasir and other Bedouins of the border land of ^Oman. 5.—NEJD AND EL-HAS A. 35. Subordinate to the Turkish 'Wilayet' of Busrah is the somewhat pretentiously Ne j d termed Government of ' Nejd.'' The Mutaserrif holding this post has his head-quarters at Hoofoof, the capital of El- Hasa, and his charge is really restricted to the province bearing the latter name. To the westward between El-Hasa and Nejd (or the 'uplands') intervene the 'Dahna' or ' Nafood,' the great red sand dunes, and at present these mark the limit of Turkish authority. To the north-west of Riadh, the capital of Central Nejd, is the flourishing province of 'the mountain,' Jebel Shammer, ruled by Muhammad ibn Hashed, who more or less owns alle giance to Turkey. The Wahabee Amirs of Riadh have long been weakened by family dis sensions and isolation from the seaboard owing to the Turkish occupation of El-Hasa. 36. Up to last year, Abdullah bin Feysal was recognised as Amir, or head of the Al- Su^ood family, but his authority was limited to Riadh itself. 37. Last autumn intelligence was received that his nephews, the sons of Su'ood bin Eeysal, had seized and imprisoned Abdullah, and there were rumours of an intended assem blage of tribes in view to an attack on the Turks in El-Hasa. 38. Letters were written by Muhammad bin Su^ood to the Chief of Bahrain and to the various Arab Shaikhs of ■'Oman, announcing his accession as Amir of Nejd. But the triumph of Muhammad bin Su^ood was short-lived, for the more powerful Amir of Jebel Shammer, Muhammad bin Rashed, speedily marched against him up to the gates of Riadh, which place capitulated after a short defence. Abdullah bin Feysal was then released and re-instated, and Muhammad bin Su'ood retired to El-khorj. It seems, however, to have been arranged that Abdullah should accompany Muhammad bin Rashed back to Jebel Shammer, his younger brother Muhammad bin Feysal acting as Governor of Nejd, assisted by an Agent of Ibn Bashed. 39. Thus, the authority of Muhammad bin Rashed has apparently been extended over a large portion of Central Arabia, and is now supreme from the confines of Syria to the great red sand desert east of Nejd. 40. The forces of Ibn Rashed are too formidable and well appointed to allow of any suc cessful resistance on the part of the adherents of the Wahabi Amirs, and it is of some importance to note that the Shammer Chieftain is, nominally at least, the vassal of Turkey. He at once communicated the news of his victory to the Turkish authoritieSj by whom it was received with the utmost satisfaction. B10 ADMINISTRATION EEPORT of THE PERSIAN gulf POLITICAL „ - pi fr„ sa durino- the past year was Muhammad 41 . The Mutasemt, or ^E.-Has. J been aud his El-Haso. successor is named Rufa at Beg. project will prove successful. 6.—FABS AND PERSIAN COAST. 43 Up to the mouth o£ February the proviuee of Far^ generally continued to b e under the supreme control of His Royal Highness the Zil-es-Sultan. At Shrra. that Pnnee s son, the Jelal -ud-Dowlah, was nominally Governor of that town and the dependent distuc s, administrator heiug ihe Sahib Diwau. Behbahan, Bushire and districts Lar Darab Jehrum, fee., remained subordinate to the Central Ears administration, but Lmgah and Bunder Abbas with their dependencies, were separated from the rest of the province of Tars, » nd e ~ d to the supreme control of His Excellency the Amin-es-Snltan, Minister for Home Affairs, Finance, &amp;c., and virtually the Prime Minister of Persia. 44. In February it was announced that His Royal Highness the Zil-es-Sultan had been deprived of all his governments excepting Ispahan, and orders were received at Shiran direct ing His Excellency the Sahib Diwau to make over his duties and repair to lelnan wi is Royal Highness the Jelal -ud-Dowlah, 45. It appeared that the entire province of Fars had been transferred to the Amin-es- Sultan, who had nominated His Royal Highness the Ihtisham -ud-Dowlah Governor of Shiraz and the central districts of Fars, whilst the seaports and islands were entrusted to Muham mad Hasan Kban, now promoted to the title of Sa ad-ul-Mulk. 46. The outlying districts of Bushire (Dashti, Dashtistan, &amp;e.) have been given to Prince Nowzer Mirza. 47. The districts about Shiraz have been in an unusually unsettled state during the year owing to the mismanagement of the Sahib Diwan and of his sou, the Motemin-ul-Mulk. 48. There was a bitter feud between the Sahib Diwan and his nephew, the Kowwam-ul- Mulk, and in May the Kowwam-ul-Mulk was summoned to Ispahan by the Zil-es-Sultan^ and immediately imprisoned. Subsequently he was subjected to detainment merely, and released on payment of a sum of 60,000 tomans. 49. Dissensions also broke out between the Sahib Diwau and his brother Haji Nasir-ul- Mulk, who for a short time held the Governorship of Bushire and its districts. 50. On the fall of the Government of Fars last spring, both Kowwam-ul-Mulk and Nasir- ul-Mulk were taken into favour. The former proceeded to the capital and was made much of and decorated, and eventually returned to Shiraz with the newly appointed Governor His Royal Highness Ihtisham-ud-Dowlah. The Haji Nasir-ul-Mulk became Peshkar, or Minister, for the province, and it is probable that disorders and disturbances will now be everywhere suppressed. 51. In August an Eeliat, Chief of the ' Koti ' Arab Eeliats, named Reza Khan, who had been imprisoned in Shiraz, was rescued in a very daring manner by his relatives with two or three hundred armed sowars. An officer and several of the prison guards were shot down and • Reza Khan pulled over the wall by ropes, let down, and carried away clear of the town i Various expeditions were sent to capture Reza Khan, but all were discomfited and returned un successful. He has lately surrendered himself to the Ihtisham-ud-Dowlah and been pardoned. 52. Two pitched battles occurred in Jehroom and Darab districts between Arab and Baharloo tribes, the latter being aided by a battalion of Sirbaz and two guns. These disturb ances were originated by the Motemin-el-Mulk, son of the Sahib Diwan, aud about 150 persons were killed on both sides. 53. The Eel-Begi of the Kashgar Darab Khan was in May arrested and taken to Ispahan on a donkey, laden with chains, and subjected to extreme ignominy. After being kept inRESIDENCY-AND MUSCAT POLITICAL AGENCY FOR 1887-88. 11 manacles for some time at Ispahan he was released and presented with a dress of honour. The nature of his offence did not transpire. 54. In December a party of miscreants attacked a clerk of the English telegraph depart ment and his wife close to the wall of Shiraz soon after dusk, and wounded the latter severely- Many arrests were made, but it was very doubtful whether the real culprits were ever reached. The object of the outrage was undoubtedly to discredit the Sahib Diwan and his administration? and attract attention to the misgovernment of the province. Eventually a sum of five thousand kerans was paid to the injured parties as compensation, by no means a satisfactory termination of the affair. 55. At the commencement of the official year His Excellency Haji Nasir-ul-Mulk was Governor of Bushire and its districts, but he shortly after- Bushire and Districts. wards proceeded to Shiraz, leaving Haider Kooli Khan as his Deputy at Bushire. The latter, who made a favourable impression, was soon after appointed Deputy Governor of Behbahan, and the current duties of the Bushire Government were there upon, in May, entrusted to Haji Ahmed Khan Sirtip, whose name has figured in preceding sec tions of this report. 56. Owing to the previous year's scanty harvest, prices rose at Bushire to nearly famine pitch, and the outlying districts were in an unprosperous, consequently an unsettled condi tion. This was aggravated by intrigues conducted from Shiraz, in view to compassing the dismissal of Nasir-ul-Mulk from his position of Governor. 57. In the course of these differences several changes of District Zabits were made, and serious disturbances were at one time apprehended. 58. In July His Excellency Haji Nasir-ul-Mulk returned from Shiraz to Bushire by the Firozabad route, bringing in his train Jemal Khan, Chief of Dashti, and having an escort of 400 sowars and 200 infantry soldiers. 59. The Nasir -ul-Mulk's stay on the coast was, however, brief. The intrigues of his brother, the Sahib Diwan, and the other influential members of his family prevailed, and His Excellency had no choice but to resign the Government and hasten to Shiraz. Whatever com plaints may have existed against Haji Nasir-ul-Mulk, I am bound to acknowledge his invari able personal and official cordiality and obliging assistance to myself and to this Residency. 60. His successor was Prince Nowzer Mirza, grandson of Hasan Ali Mirza, Firman- Firma of Fars, who, on the death of his father Fath Ali Shah, became an aspirant to the throne of Persia. This new Governor arrived at Bushire in August, and established cordial relations personally and officially with this Residency j intrigue was speedily at work against this Prince, who in October left the town and tendered his resignation on account of strong censure telegraphed by the Amin-es-Sultan on mendacious information. He was, however, persuaded by His Royal Highness the Jelal-ud-Dowlah to remain at his post for the time. Subsequently, on the recall of His Royal Highness the Zil-es-Sultan, and consequent change of Government in Fars, His Excellency Nowzer Mirza was recalled to Shiraz to make way for the newly appointed Governor of the seaport Towns and Districts, Muhammad Hasan Khan, Sa'ad-ul-Mulk, 61. In the month of November Mirza Muhammad Khan, Motemed-el-Wizarah, the Agent of the Persian Foreign Office at Bushire, having become entangled in matters of custom-house accounts, was imprisoned in his house, and deprived of food for two days, by a local official placed over him. In fear of his life the Foreign Agent managed to force the guard placed over him, and fled to the British Residency, where he took ' bast/' or sanctuary, pending appeal to his Chief and Government. After much delay and correspondence, it was arranged that he should proceed to Tehran for investigation of his case. He was dismissed from his post, and his successor is Najaf Kuli Khan, a person of no standing nor of much experience. 62. Bushire was visited in October by the Austro -Hungarian training corvette Fasana, and in December by the Italian despatch gun-vessel Bapido. 63. In the spring of 1887 Captain Vonblumor, a Russian officer of Cossacks, now in the Shah's employ, visited Ispahan, Shiraz, and Bushire on a tour of inspection. b 212 ADMINISTRATION REPORT OF THE PERSIAN GULF POLITICAL 64, A Russian ex-officer of Cossaoks. named Notovitch, visited Busfiire in the winter, and caused some excitement in Persian circles by his free utterances of alleged designs o ussia ao-ainst England, and the projects entertained hy that power in concord w.th 1 crs.a for actm, against us in the direction of the Persian Gulf, on the expected early occurrence of war between the two greater States. 65 In the previous year's report it was stated that, although the population of Lingah were in favour of their Arab Deputy Governor, Shaikh Lingah and Bunder Abbas and were in lavuux u • o -i. J Islands. Kadtheeb, his tenure of office was precarious. So it proved. The Persian authorities, in pursuance of a recently adopted policy, had resolved on the abolition of the system of Arab Governors at Lingah, and the abasement of the ruling Arab family. 66. Haji Ahmed Khan was entrusted with the task of capturing Shaikh Kadtheeb, aiiu on the 11th September succeeded in surprising the Shaikh and effecting his object with very slight loss of life. 67. Shaikh Kadtheeb was carried to Bushire, and the property of the family virtually con fiscated. A Persian official has been since placed in charge of the oidinaiy administiative duties at Lingah. The present Agent is Mirza Hedayet Khan, a man of moderation and sense. 68. Barracks were erected at Lingah and a body of 200 Persian Regular Infantry placed there, much to the distaste of the inhabitants, some of whom prepared to leave the place and settle in other parts of the Gulf. A considerable number of families actually migrated to the adjacent coasts and islands. 69. In July a person named Yakub-bin-Bashir, who had been placed at Lingah in the capacity of ' Mufettish,' that is collector of intelligence or informer, by the Persian authori ties, preferred false accusations of a serious nature against the British Government Agent at Lingah, and also forwarded misrepresentations of my own action in the matter of claims against divers at Sirri Island. The Persian Government adopted the reports of this Agent, and made formal complaint to the British Legation. The absolute falsehood of the charges against our Agent were proved beyond question, and eventually the matter was allowed to drop. 70. The annexation to Persia of the Island of Sirri, which was effected from Lingah, has been noticed under Arab Coast affairs. 71. The Persian authorities proposed placing garrisons of Persian soldiery on Kishm, Larek, and other islands, as well as at Lingah and Bunder Abbas, and so much alarm was caused to the inhabitants that many Arab families fled from Henjam. The intention of the Persian Government was, however, abandoned as regards the islands. 72. The administration of Bunder Abbas was during the past year very unsatisfactory and discouraging to trade, the introduction of Persian soldierv Bunder Abbas. . , J to the place was unpopular and unnecessary, but the Sirbaz have recently been withdrawn. The Foreign Office Agent at Bunder Abbas, Mirza Ismail Khan, was relieved by Mirza Ali Khan. 7.—PERSIAN ARABISTAN. 73. Shaikh Mizal Khan, Governor of Mohammerah, being engaged in a feud with the ' Nassar ' Arabs, obtained the assistance of the Persian Government vessel Persepolis. 74. Proposals have continued to be made to various quarters in view to opening the river Karun to navigation, but no progress has been made. 75. A new Persian Governor has been appointed to Arabistan. This personage was tormei-ly entitled the Sa'ad-ul-Mulk, and has now been promoted to the title of Nizam-es- Saltanah. 76. The friends of the present Arab Shaikh and Governors have misgivings for the future. Like the Shaikh of Liugah their position may be precarious.EESIDENCY AND MUSCAT POLITICAL AGENCY FOR 1887-88. 13 8.—PERSIAN BALUCHISTAN. 77. At Gwadur the Wali or Governor, Saif-biu-Sayid, was removed by His Highness Seyyid Toorki in January, and Muhammad-bin-Suleiman appointed in his stead. 78. Government lost a trusty and valuable servant by the death of Mir Jehangir, Native Assistant at Gwadur, on the 17th November. From long- personal acquaintance and official relations with Mir Jehangir, 1 can testify to the great and wholesome influence he exercised in Mekran, where he was universally respected. A man of his stamp is usually not to be re placed. Munshi Abdul Rahim was appointed on probation to carry on the duties of Native Assistant. 79. In the matter of the Firozabad raid of 1886, mentioned in last report, it was decided by Government, on the recommendation of the Agent to the Governor-General, that no com pensation need be paid the Perso-Baluch complainants; but some articles of loot which had been recovered were tendered to Mir Mowladad, Chief of Sirbaz, and rejected by him with a protest against the alleged injustice of the decision referred to, and a threat of reprisals on the Rinds. 80. A complaint has been made by the Chief of the Perso-Baluch district of Balm that a person, named Mir Nawab Sadazi, residing at Mand, had raided into Bahu, and carried off a number of camels and buffaloes, and subsequently plundered a Persian caravan on the road to Sirbaz. The value of the property stolen is estimated at R375, and the last-mentioned out rage is said to have occurred in October. Reports were made by Mr. Ffinch to the Political Agent, South-Eastern Baluchistan. 81. Two cases of plunder of Hindu traders in Persian Baluchistan are still unsettled: the first, which is called the Sirhad plunder case, occurred in 1884. The complainants were desired to proceed to Kerman to lay their case before the Persian authorities. They did so, but with no result other than incurring additional loss through their expenses in travelling, 82. During the past year, a Hindu trader of Dizak, named Dhormu Mulchand, was stripped of all his property and flogged by order of the Persian Governor of Baluchistan, Abul Fath Khan, and his female and other relations carried off and imprisoned at Bampur. This case, which has been taken up by Her Majesty's Minister at Tehran, is still pending. 83. In April 1887 Zeyun-ul-Abidin Khan Sirtip, Governor of Persian Baluchistan, was dismissed, and Abul Fath Khan Sirtip succeeded him. 84. It appears that the Chief of Dizak, Dilawar Khan, has been seized and imprisoned at Bampur. 85. The following are the present recognised Chiefs of districts : — 86. The inhabitants of Gwetter, who had mostly emigrated on account of oppression, have returned, and the place is as thriving as of yore. 87. At Jask the Persian Governor Mirza Hidayet, who had given every satisfaction to the English Telegraph Department, was replaced by Mirza Ali Khan, who is also conciliatory. 88. In February, the Malek-et-Tujjar of Bushire visited Jask with a detachment of troops and the Persian flag was hoisted and saluted. A large guard of Persian Regulars were posted at Jask, but owing to difficulty in rationing them they were withdrawn, and at present there is a guard of Irregulars only. 89. In October Mr. Ffinch reported much increase of wilful damage to telegraph material in the Jask districts owing to the hostility of the people to Persian authorities. 90. In the same month an affray occurred at Jask owing to some Baluchis of the neigh bourhood refusing to pay tax on produce. They were overpowered and made prisoners, and there was some panic owing to threats of a rescue. Eventually the Baluchis were punished and released. Mir Mowladad . Mir Muhammad Ali Mir Din Muhammad Sirbaz and Kasrkand. Bahu. Dashtyari. Mir Sayid * Khan Mir Hussain Khan Geh. Rudbar. * The late Chief Mir Hote, father of Syed Kban, died in July 1887.u administration REPORT of THE PERSIAN GULF POLITICAL 91. Since then matters seem to have goue on qnietly at Jask. 9.— OBSERVATORY. 92 . The nsual tables shoeing the meteo^ogieal . , . mi 1p weather was not severe and a good uaim out^ i start earth q uakes ^ Boshi. on Hth and M «. Novemhe.-. 10.—SLAVE TRADE. 93 Her Majesty's vessels on the Gnl£ Station made the nsua! efforts to intercept slavers mnnin' cargoes from Africa to 'Oman, bnt without success. It appears that a small numbei o£ vessels manage to elude the cruisers and to land cargoes of slaves on the Oman Coast, but llt of the slavers (small craft), land the slaves far to the south -west, where n„ crmser patrol, and the slaves are subjected to the long march thence overland, thus addmg to the.r hardships. U.—OFFICIAL APPOINTMENTS &amp; NAVAL ESTABLISHMENTS. 94. J6th April iSS7.—Mr, A. R. Hakim, Assistant to Political Resident, returned from three months' privilege leave. 95. 16th April 1887.—Ut. P. J. C. Robertson, First Assistant, proceeded to Busrah to assume charge of that office. 96. 1st hdy 1887. —Captain Ravenshaw joined as First Assistant Resident. 97. 3rd September Mr. G. Lucas proceeded on three months' privilege leave, and rejoined 1st December. 98. Her Majesty's Ships Osprey, Sphinx, Kingfisher, Ranger, and Turquoise were on the Station during the year 1887-88. The latter joined on 27th February and is the senior officer's ship. 99. The I.M.S. Lawrence arrived from Bombay, 19th April, proceeded to be docked, 6th September, and returned, 12th November. (Sd.) E. C. ROSS, Colonel, Folitical Resident, Persian Gulf,RESIDENCY AND MUSCAT POLITICAL AGENCY FOR 1887-88. 19 Pabt ii.-administration report of the muscat poli tical agency for the year 1887-88. Political. —The official year now under report commenced with an unusually quiet condi tion of the province of ^Oman, and with the exception of an attack made by Zaeed bin Khaleefah on a section of the Dhowahir tribe at Bereymi for attempting to throw off their allegiance to him, nothing of any political importance occurred until the beginning of June. The Sultan, to prevent the Beni-Yas from being established in power at Bereymi, sent the Dhowahir assistance in the shape of money and ammunition, but unfortunately the ' Dar- as-Salam ' which carried it, arrived too late at Sohar to thwart Zaeed in his object, and he suc ceeded in carrying off two of the Dhowahir Shaikhs as prisoners to Abu Dhabbi. In the early part of June Shaikh Suleiman-bin-Seif, with the assistance of the Nizari Arabs of Ziki, and principally through the treachery of one of the garrison, seized the fort at Birket -al-Moze, drove out the Wali Saeed-bin-Sultan at Ameyri, and, taking advantage of his unopposed position, proceeded immediately to Ziki. On the news of the fall of Birket-al- Moze reaching Muscat, the Sultan had three Nizar Shaikhs, who happened to be here at the time seized and thrown into prison, and anticipating Suleiman^s advance on Ziki sent rein - forcements and provisions for the garrison there, under Seyyid Hamud-bin-Nasir, but Shaikh Suleiman had taken the precaution of garrisoning the principal places on the road, so as to prevent the much-needed help from reaching Ziki, and Seyyid Hamud had consequently to fall back upon Somail. Notwithstanding these marked acts of disloyalty Suleiman-bin-Seif excused himself to His Highness the Sultan by pleading the oppression of the Wali against the widow and sons of Seyyid Muhammad-bin-Hilal, as a plea for his capture of Birket-al- Moze, and His Highnesses action in imprisoning the three Nizar Shaikhs as his plea for advanc ing on Ziki. While affairs were progressing in this unfavourable manner in 'Oman proper the dis affected tribes of the Sharkiyah, as usual under the leadership of the Arab rebel, Shaikh Saleh- bin-Ali, were trying to form a general coalition of all the Hinawee tribes, and now, en couraged by the success which Shaikh Suleiman had met with. Shaikh Saleh, not only opened an intriguing correspondence with that Chief, but actually had an interview with him with the object of gaining him over to the general Hinawee cause. The plan of action, had it suc ceeded, was evidently to aim a blow at the Sultan's authority in several places at the same time, and to harass him and weaken his power, so as to enable the rebels, among whom Seyyid Abdul Aziz, the Sultan's brother, was one, to dictate their own terms. As a prelude to this general plan, Seyyid Ibrahim bin Kais took by surprise the town and fort of Soweik on the Batineh coast on the night of the 1st of July, and was threatening to take the town of Mesnah, when the Sultan, fearing that the force he had sent with his three sons and Seyyid Bedr-bin-Seif, would not be sufficient to arrest his progress and to oust him from his position, and having therefore requested the help of a British man-of-war, the Resi dent arrived from Bushire on the 9th with orders of Government to afford Seyyid Turki's force the required support, if necessary, and, proceeding to Soweik, demanded on the following day the unconditional surrender of the place from Seyyid Ibrahim. Seyyid Ibrahim, who was at first not aware that the Sultan would be granted this assist ance, now finding his position awkward, although expressing his readiness to abide by the wishes of the British Government, begged hard to be allowed to retain Soweik if only to avoid the disgrace consequent on such an easy and unconditional surrender, but, seeing that the Resident was prepared to support the Sultan actively in recovering the place, promised to evacuate it and to retire peacefully, the Resident in return for his friendly assent agreeing to request Seyyid Turki, conditional on his maintaining a friendly attitude towards the Sultan, to restore his subsidy, which had been stopped some months ago for several acts of disloyalty. His Highness the Sultan, being grateful for the Resident's action, expressed his willingness to restore Seyyid Ibrahim's subsidy, and the Resident returned to Soweik on the I2th, when the place was handed over to the Sultan's garrison at night, the Resident proceeding imme diately afterwards to Bushire. This demonstration of our policy had the desired effect, for soon afterwards news was received that the scheme for a general Hinawee rising had failed, but Shaikh Saleh, now dis comfited by his failure in this direction, turned his side altogether and wrote to Muhamraad- c 220 U.-M... .1 Msrh, .«.™s M. » '• Hisl ''f; 1 'to.™ at Ziki, which he had fortified evidently with the eventual object o£ laying the fort there, and retired to laaoof. On the 25th of July Her Majesty's ship Banger arrived from Eas al Hadd with two Un tne -som or j uy J r , , r , A TO i Qf i Ki^ib orio-mally a Fakheedeh of Hindus from Sur, who. having' complained that the Awlad b.as j &amp; . y . _ p ,, • the Jenebeh but now unde. the paction of^the Ben^WAli, had ktL-irudiug the immediate surrender e£ the Hindu and the pnuishment o£ the offenders could reach Shaikh Abdullah bin Salim and Muhammad bin Majid of the Beu.-bu- Ali, they had, on hearing of the outrage, out of friendly feelings or t ic ri is ovemmen and for His Highness the Saltan, of their own accord imprisoned five of the Awlad assi j and restored the kidnapped Hindu to his community at Sur. The murder of Shaikh Muhammad bin Majid, the Tameemeh of the Beni-bu-Ali, in the month of August, by a man of the Sinadeh section of the same tribe, followed immediately after by the murder, in revenge, of Shaikh Yusuf bin Ali of the Sinadeh by Hamud bin Majid, was an event disastrous both to the tribe and to the interests of the Sultan. They were among his staunch and tried friends, and ever ready with their swords in his cause. Shaikh Yusuf took a leading part at the siege of Muttrah in 1871 on behalf of Seyyid Tuiki, and could always be depended upon in an emergency. Fortunately for the tiibe, Shaikh Abdullah bin Salinas house being a fortified one, he was able to ward off an attack made by the Sinadeh in revenge for the murder of their Shaikh, bat the tribe could ill afford to lose two such powerful Shaikhs as Muhammad and Yusuf at any time, whilst just then the relations with the Beni-bu-Hasan were so highly strained that His Highness, feeling greatly concerned at this unsettled state of affairs in Jaalan, deputed Seyyid Nasir bin Muhammad and Hamid bin Jvarir, who succeeded in pacifying the Beni bu Ali, and effecting a peace between them and the Ben- bu-Hasan. Shaikh Abdullah bin Salim was elected by the former as their Tamimeh. The peace, however, thus hurriedly concluded between these two most important tribes was not destined to last long, for in the month of September the Beni-bu-Hasan, having killed one of the Awlad Kasib in retaliation for the murder of one of their number, fresli hostilities com menced between them and the peace of Jaalan was once more disturbed. They have now agreed to a truce arranged between themselves, which it is to be hoped may have a more lasting effect. In the month of October fresh rumours of an intended Hinawee rising reached Musca^ but as they were principally due to Seyyid Abdul Aziz's sudden visit to Shaikh Saleh at Bidiyyeh, which had evidently no political meaning, they soon subsided on his return to Samad. H is Highness Seyyid Turki, who had lately suffered a good deal from one of his old complaints, left on the 13th November for Gwadur, and returned on the 2nd of December, having somewhat benefited by the change. The distant possession of Dhofar, which has always been a source of trouble to the Sultan, once more showed signs of disloyalty, and early in January a letter was received from Suleiman bin Hamid, the akeed of the garrison in the fort there, who was left in charge of the place by the Wali Seyyid Muhammad bin Suleiman on his departure for Muscat in September, stating that on trying to seize a murderer for punishment the people had resisted him, and that he had eventually to retire into the fort. The Sultan lost no time in preparing an expedition, consisting of 200 men, which left on the 13th in his steamer Sultani with his two sons Feysal and Fahad, Seyyids Nasir bin Muhammad and Bedr bin Seif, Shaikh Shamis bin Hasan and Suleiman bin Suwelim, the newly appointed Wali; but by the time the Suliani arrived at Dhofar affairs had resumed a peaceful aspect, and, instead of meeting with any resistance, the Muscat party on landing found a very cordial reception, so that the only task left for the expedition was to seize five of the Shaikhs, the ringleaders of the disaffected party and to bring them as prisoners to Muscat. On her return voyage the Sultani had to take shelter at Ras Madrikeh owing to her supply of coals being exhausted, and the delay thus occasioned in her return caused His Highness the Sultan to be so extremely anxious about the safety, of his sons, that the Political Agent requested Captain Brackenbury of Her Majesty's Ship Turquoise on the 22nd of February to proceed in search of her. The Turquoise, after giving the necessary help to the Sultani to enable her to resume her voyage, returned to Muscat on the 27th of February, and the Sultani, with the main body of the expeditionary force follow ed on the following day. }RESIDENCY AND MUSCAT POLITICAL AGENCY FOR 1887-88. 21 On tbe 4th of March His Highness Seyyid Bargash bin Saeed, Sultan of Zanzibar, arrived for the benefit of his health, but after a profitless stay of more than a week at Gala, near Bosher, returned to Muscat, and left for Zanzibar on the 17th of March at the recommendation of the Civil Surgeon, whom he had consulted about his disease. He lived only six hours after his return to Zanzibar, and, the news of his death having been received on the 30th of March, general mourning was observed for three days. During his short stay here the late Sultan of Zanzibar made a present of ii50,000 to his brother Seyyid Toorki. The Resident visited Muscat on the 9th of June, and a second time in July, on the occasion of Seyyid Ibrahim's capture of Soweik. Official changes, —Lieutenant-Colonel S. B. Miles, on being appointed Political Resident at Udaipur, handed over charge to Lieutenant-Colonel E. Mockler on the 16th of April; and the latter, on preceding to Bagdad on special duty, handed over charge to Surgeon-Major Jayakar on the 26th of February. Slave Trade. —On the 22nd May 1887, the boats of Her Majesty's Ship Kingfisher seized a slave-dow off Muscat, which was brought in for adjudication. There were four slaves on board, but they were all landed at Kurryat before the seizure. A court was held on the 25th and the dow was condemned. The number of fugitive slaves that sought redress or freedom at this Consulate during the year was 37, of whom 28 have been liberated under the provisions of the Treaty of 1873, and 9 were dismissed. A. S. JAYAKAR, Surgeon Major, In charge of Political Agency, Muscat.22 APPENDIX A TO PART II. SKETCH OF THE CAREER OF SEYYllTsULTAN BIN AHMED OP MUSCAT. B y COLONEL S. B. MILES. j-i, ai 'Rnrv Sn'ppdv—succ66dGd tliatoftbG arebeh about parnotis^XVand courage rescued his country from the hnmiliatiou of fore.gn eooquest, and restored it to its dignity as an independent State. , , . , , . It was in 1741 or 1742 that the Imam Sai£ bin Sultan, the Ya'arebeh, having een epose by his relative Sultau bia Marshid. sent to Persia to beseech aid in dispossess,ng h,s nva a recovering his throne. , „ , . ,r^ i Nadir Shah, who had long entertained the notion of annexing El Bahrain and Oman, and of extend ng his power over the Persian Gulf, and who, with this design in view bad already comrnenced 0 the creation of a navy by the purchase of ships from the Dutch and by causing others to be constructed at Surat, eagerly embraced the opportunity now afforded him of in e - ference in the affairs of 'Oman, and he lost no time in making preparations for the invasion of Eastern Arabia. The Governor of Shiraz, Mirza Taki Khan, was entrusted with the command of the Persian fleet, and he at first pretended to loyally assist the ex-Imam, Saif bin Sultan. Having gained possession of Muscat however, he attempted to conceal his object no longer, and commenced operations for the reduction of 'Oman to obedience. He succeeded in over -running the country, and fought a great, but indecisive, battle under the walls of Sohar, in which Sultan bin Murshid was slain; but his efforts to reduce that fortress failed. After spending the greater part of the year 1743 in contesting the supremacy with the Wali of Sohar, Ahmed bin Saeed, whose conspicuous skill and ability had given him the general lead of affairs, Mirza Taki Khan, becoming hopeless of the final success of his enterprise, and disappointed in his expectation of enriching himself, made a truce with Ahmed and returned to Persia early in the year 1744. The garrison left in Muscat soon after surrendered and was treacherously massacred, and the liberation of 'Oman from the Persian yoke was then complete. The result seemed to be due solely to the genius of Ahmed, and for the service he had rendered no reward appeared to be too great; the former dynasty was ignominiously thrust aside, and Ahmed bin Saeed was elected Imam by general acclamation. Some time previous to his death, the Imam Ahmed had nominated his eldest surviving son, Saeed, to succeed him, but as Saeed was known to be of a soft and retiring disposition, the selection was not universally approved of, and some of the younger sons were emboldened by their father's increasing feebleness in his later years to rebel against him. In the month of February 1781, Saif and Sultan, who were uterine brothers, having gathered a small following, succeeded, by seducing the commandants, in getting possession of the forts Merani and Jelali, at Muscat, the guns of which they turned on the town, and soon laid in ruins the houses of the Governor and principal inhabitants. The Imam marched down from Rostak to restore order, and began by removing the tra ders and their goods to Muttrah for safety. He then invested the forts, but his sons, being well supplied with provisions, and in expectation of aid from the pirate Chief of Ras-el-Khyma, Shaikh Rashid, continued to hold out. In this assistance the brothers were disappointed, although Rashid appears to have been sincere in his promise of help, and after a siege of three months, during which the Hindoo and other traders sustained a loss of nearly three lakhs of rupees, the forts were surrendered to the Imam, on his granting an amnesty to the garrisons. On the 26th December of the same year Saif and Sultan rose again in rebellion. They proceeded to Burka with a few adherents and slaves, surprised and captured their brother Saeed, brought him down in fetters by boat to Muscat, and threw him into a dungeon in Fort Jelali.RESIDENCY AND MUSCAT POLITICAL AGENCY FOR 1887-88. The old Imam had no sooner heard of this outrage than he started from Rostak to procure his son 's liberation, reached Naaman on the 1st January 1782, and marched on to Muscat, where he accomplished his object without much difficulty ; but the graceless youths Saif and Sultan again went unpunished for their offence. On the 15th December 1783, the venerable Imam Seyyid Ahmed died at Rostak full of years, after a calm and uneventful reign of nearly forty years. He was succeeded bj his son Saeed, who was elected Imam without opposition. This election was a bitter disappointment to Saif and Sultan, whose mother was of the Jiboor tribe, and who cousequently deemed their claim to the succession greater than Saeed^s. Disgusted at the turn of events, and doubtless fearing Saeed^s resentment at their past treatment of him, they resolved at once-to quit ; Oinan and remain away until better times should dawn for them. Whereupon Saif sailed away to East Africa, from whence he never returned, while Sultan retired to Mekran, where he is said to have resided for some years. Saeed had not long assumed the reins of Government, when disorders and disaffection broke out, and his utter incapacity to rule became manifest to all. Within two years a meeting of Shaikhs and Kadhees was held at Mesnah, where it was resolved to elect Kais in his stead. But this scheme was foiled by Saeed^s elder son, Hamad, an energetic and able man, who thenceforward assumed charge of political affairs, and conducted them with firmness and suc cess until his death in 1792. Saeed, though content to leave power in the hands of his son, did not care to resign it to his brothers, and on Hamad's death desired to resume control, and perhaps for some time did so. But Sultan, who was then residing at Burka, and whose influence and prestige in the country were undoubtedly superior to those of his brethren, felt that his opportunity was now come, and he was not the man to let it slip by him. With a sudden spring at Muscat he got possession of that town before Saeed or Kais could march out of Rostak and Sohar to oppose him, and having the general voice of the Ghaffirees in his favour he was soon master of the situation, but the game was not yet ended. The brothers united their forces and made a vigorous attempt to recover Muscat, but without avail. The struggle, however, continued for many months, the Ainawis generally sup porting the Imam, while Sultan had the Ghaffirees on his side. Eventually, a conference of deputies assembled at Burka, where a convention was concluded, by which Saeed retained Rostak with his title of Imam. Kais was given the appanage of Sohar, whilst Sultan was to have Muscat, Burka, and other forts, with the direction of the political affairs of the country. The date of this arrangement, which restored tranquillity to the country, is somewhat uncertain, but it probably took place early in 1793. Seyyid Sultan was born about the year 1755, and during his childhood had dwelt among the Bedouins. His mother was a relative of Muhammad Nasir el Jabri, who was at that time looked upon as the leader of the Nizar, and this explains the cause of Sultan placing his chief reliance upon that faction, although his own tribe was Yemani. Sultan, on assuming power, at once fixed as a residence upon Muscat, the unrivalled posi tion of which in 'Oman as a port, and as a natural fortress against external and internal foes, made it a far more suitable capital than Rostak, Nezwa, or Sohar. He accordingly took up his abode in the Gareyza, or cathedral, a large and substantial building erected by the Portu guese in 1530, and here for the next seven years he resided. When Sultan left 'Oman in 1784, after the succession of Saeed to the Imamate, he had sailed to Gwadur on the Mekran coast, from whence he had proceeded to Kalat to implore the protection of Nasir Khan. This had been accorded to him, and he had been presented with the village and half the revenues of Gwadur for his maintenance. Here he had remained until a reconciliation had been effected some years later with his brother Saeed through the intervention of the latter's son Hamad, when he felt it safe to return to 'Oman. Almost his first act after coming to power was to despatch a Wali with a suitable force to Gwadur to occupy that place on his behalf and to build a fort. The name of this Wali was Saif bin Ali, who, in accordance with further instructions he received from Sultan, subse quently surprised and took possession of the village of Charbar, about a hundred miles to the west of Gwadur. With his ambition fed by this success, Seyyid Sultan's next enterprise was a naval expedition against the Beni Maeen of Kishm and Hormuz, which he appears to have24 ADMINISTRATION REPORT OF THE PERSIAN 0' - r I JLU ■..bniLinon, [he ■ of Sevyid ' l '- 1 f y r b . Gb«™w of Bu.:],, At this time, and f.r some years previous, the Stalkb or me Maeen ^ Govern . Abbass and its dependencies, the revenues of whicn he La ment for a fixed yearly rental. ., ^ , r , The result of the war was thus doubly advantageoas to Seyyid Su.tan, lor e now assumed the position of the Sha.kh as regards bis relations with the Pers.an Government, and ^fter some negation, obtained a tirman in his own name from the Sbah by v.rtue of wh.cb and of suecesslve fi:mans Bunder Abbass remained a dependency of Muscat for h-e-^rten, of a century. As Persia and'Oman were at .his time (1794) on bad terms, Seyy.d Sultan had, no doubt, to submit to pay heavily for tb.s concession; the peace now concluded however lasted until 1797, when a rupture took place, and Baba Khan sent orders to the -haikh of Bushire to collect a land force to be shipped at Mobammerah for an expedition against Muscat. Beyond desultory skirmishing nothing appears to have resdted :rom these oruers, as the Shaikh probably had no means ot carrying them out. In December ] 79S Seyyid Sultan commenced hostilities against the Pashalic of Busra, and with a view to preserve his territories from insult during his absence from Oman on tiiis expedition, made a truce with the Kowasim of Has el Khyma, with whom he had been for a long time past at war. The Pasha of Busra heard of the preparations at Muscat with apprehension, having no ships at his disposal capable of contending with tne Arab fl^et. He, tne.tf .•?, solicited from Mr. Samuel Manisty, the British Resident, the assistance of two English cruizers in protect ing his town from attack, promising in return certain advantages in the wa\ of trade. The Indian Government, however, were at this time not in a position to forsake their attitude of neutrality, or to make enemies of any of the Gulf powers, and they, therefore, instructed the Resident to refrain from doing more than offering good offices in bringing about an amicable settlement with the Ruler of 'Oman. Mr. Manisty accordingly mediated, and shortly after was able to effect a reconciliation. Sevyid Sultan, during his career as Ruler of 'Oman, had to perform no more important act than to make his choice, which he was at this period called upon to do, between the two great rival European powers then contending for the mastery in India, France and England. In the time of the Imams Ahmed and Saeed, French influence, owing to the brisk trade and constant communication that took place between 'Oman and Mauritius, as well as to the personal influence of Monsieur Rousseau, the well-known French Consul-General at Bagdad, who had long maintained friendly relations with Rostak, was predominant in 'Oman, and the Governor of the Mauritius, M. Malartic, took care to maintain this ascendancy by sending valuable gifts of cannon, &amp;c., to the Imam. The harmony of this entente had been interrupted for a time by the unjustifiable capture, in June 1781, of the Imam's 50-gun ship, the Salih, by Captain Desohiens, commander of a French privateer, but on the Imam's repeated representa tions, a small vessel had been despatched by King Louis in 1790 in charge of Captain Mac- camara of La Thetis in substitution of M. Deschien's prize, an act of courtesv which had completely re-established friendly relations. On his usurpation of power Seyyid Sultan continued this friendlv intercourse and for some years appears to have been guided in political affairs by his French physician. The Great French Revolution, however, which occurred at this epoch, diverted the atten tion of that nation entirely to home affairs and their prestige declined in the east until the middle of the year 1798, when the sudden appearance of a French army in E^ypt and the brilliant conquest of that country by the young General in command again drew the eyes of Onentals to their deeds. The Egyptian expedition appeared to give Napoleon Bonaparte the opportunity he had so long and ardently sighed for, of satisfying the cravings of his ambition, »nd he allowed his imagination to run riot in dreams of eastern glorv. One of these dreams was to lead his array back to France through Constantinople and Austria, annexing the one and crushing the other on the way. Another scheme was to march across the Syrian desert, Mesopotamia, and Persia, like Alexander to the frontiers of India, to conquer that Empire for France or for himself. It was in pursuance of this latter project (which he continued to cherish for years afterwards) that General Bonaparte despatched emissaries and letters to various Oriental potentates, among whom were Tippu Sahib and the Imam of Muscat with a view to gam allies and assistance in the enterprise. Twelve days before he started from Cairo on his Synan expedition, he wrote the following letter to Sevyid Sultan, enclosing one to Pu, in whlch he t0 deli ver Mysore from the iron 'yoke of England. This letterRESIDENCY AND MUSCAT POLITICAL AGENCY FOR 1887-88. 25 was the favourable answer to his constant appeals to the French Government for aid against the English which the misguided Tippu had been for so many years expecting. But it was too late, Tippu was now at the end of his career, and, as it happened, the despatches never even reached Muscat, for they were intercepted on the way by an English man-of-war. Dated Cairo, the 25th January 1799. To— T he I maxtm of M uscat. I write you this letter to inform you of the arrival of the French army in Egypt. As you have always been friendly, you must be convinced of our desire to protect all the merchant vessels you may send to Suez. I also beg you will forward the enclosed letter to Tippu Sahib by the first opportunity. (Sd.) BONAPARTE. The alarm felt by the Indian Government at the undoubted influence of the French in 'Oman, the dread lest it should extend over the Gulf, and the apprehehsions everywhere inspired by Napoleon Bonaparte's military genius and restless activity, led the Governor-General of India, the Marquis of Wellesley, to instruct the Resident at Bushire, Mirza Mehdi Ali Khan, to enter into a political engagement with Seyyid Sultan, having for its object the exclusion of French influence from 'Oman territory. Mirza Mehdi reached Muscat in September 1798, and the Treaty which he negotiated was signed on the 12th October following. It comprised seven articles and contained, besides the engagement to exclude Frenchmen from the Imam's territory and French ships from his ports during the prevalence of war between English and French, provision for the establish ment by the East India Company of a factory at Bunder Abbass with a guard of 700 or 800 Indian troops. Though it was not mentioned in the Treaty, Seyyid Sultan further made a special request that an English officer should be sent to reside at Muscat on behalf of the Com pany as his adviser. Seyyid Sultan was thus the first Prince in the peninsula of Arabia to enter into political relations with England, and it is satisfactory to note that the friendly relations then initiated have from that day to this continued to strengthen and increase. During the year 1799 Seyyid Sultan was engaged in consolidating his power in 'Oman and in dealing with internal dissensions. Among the tribes that were disaffected to wards him were the Daroo of El Sharkujeh and the Beni Naim of El Dhahrieh, both of which he succeeded in subduing and bringing back to allegiance. Having at length tranquil- lised his own country, he was able to turn his attention to foreign enemies, and, first of all, he resolved to concentrate his strength against the Uttoobees of El Bahrein, who had refused to pay any longer the tax levied upon all vessels passing from India to the Persian Gulf. This tax had for one and a half centuries been paid to Muscat by all craft, foreign as well as home, sailing through the Straits of Mussendom, and as the revenue it used to bring in was consider able, Seyyid Sultan was not inclined to allow the refusal of the Uttoobees to pay the impost to pass without chastisement. He accordingly sailed in the Gunjawa frigate, with three square-rigged ships and sixty bughlas, to attack El Bahrein, and in a sea-fight that took place shortly after captured three of the Uttoobee vessels. In the meantime the Uttoobees, being aware of their inability to resist the naval power of 'Oman, had hastened to place themselves under the protection of Persia by paying the Shah the tribute for El Bahrein for the preceding year. Seyyid Sultan heard of this action on the part of the Uttoobees at the time when he was preparing to land his troops on that island, and he lost no time in entering into negociations with Persia himself. Being foiled in his attempt on El Bahrein, he occupied the island of Karrack, which he offered to farm from Persia at a yearly rental and pay five years in advance. This offer, however, was declined by the Persians, who continued to take the part of the Uttoobees, and Seyyid Sultan eventually relinquished further operations against the tribe on payment by them of a portion of the arrears of tax due. The failure of this expedition appears to have caused the abandonment of the tax, which we do not afterwards hear of. Not long after the conclusion of the Treaty by Mirza Mehdi in 1798, reports reached the Government of India to the effect that, notwithstanding his engagements, Seyyid Sultan had resumed friendly intercourse with the French, and the interception of General Bonaparte's D26 ADMINISTRATION EEPOKT OP THE PERSIAN GULF POLITICAL «• j• ^ The immunities in favour of letter swim M hi-vf Wn looted « p ^ g |tan wfre ^oooJingly sospsnded foo sera - - -• - r Cpooi. M.M. -iU loo. Bombay 1° «.• »-W ^ Selbv and arrived at Muscat on the 8th January 1800. Besides the stag attached to the Mission to PCTsia ; ^'rthe'equeX Assistant Surgeon Bogle, o£ the Bombay establishmen ' ' Resident on behalf made by Seyyid Sultan ^ Mir^a Mehd. AU ad - ^ ^ _ 0{ td WthfooveZT tie toTn Saif-bi^Muhaimad, who came to call on Captain sa?jr— •. srs ^rftTinTdayy 'and'theThaving landed Dr. Begle and installed him in h.s appomt- ment, set sail for Hormuz in search of Seyyid Saltan. , . , , On the 18th January, Captain Malcolm sighted and boarded the Gunjava off t e is an of am and having produced his credentials and delivered his presents, proceeded at once t S' the purport olhis mission. He told Seyyid Sultan how much tl.e Ind.an Govern- ment regretted he had leagued himself with the French, and hoped he would see that it was his besiT policy to ally himself with the English, poinWg out that, as all the ports of In . from Surat to Calcutta were in the hands of the English, Muscat could, w.thout drffieulty, be escTuded from all participation in the Indian trade if the Bntish Government were so d.sposed. Seyyid Sultan did not take long to decide. Placing Ins hand upon his breast, be said he desired nothing better than to cement an alliance with the English to the exdusion o enemies and he offered to sign then and there the treaty that Captain Malcolm had seen empowered to conclude. The treaty thus entered into bears in fact the same date and con- Xts of only two articles, one confirming the engagement of 1798, and the second providing for the residence of a Political Agent. It was in this year, 1800, that the warlike tribes of Nejd in Central Arabia were first seen in ^Oman. These tribes, impelled by the fanaticism engendered by the doctrines of a religious reformer Shaikh' Abdul Wahhab, after whom they are now called Wahhabees, had already overrun 'and conquered nearly the whole of the rest of the Peninsula, and the Amir Abdul Aziz, eager to expurgate the heresy of Ibadheeism from the. land of 'Oman, was now pre paring to turn his arms eastward and spread his views of the true religion by the swoid. After taking El Hasa and Katif his troops crossed the Sabkhah marsh and pushed on to El Bereymi, subduing or scattering the Bedouin tribes on the way. The leader of this expedition, which consisted of a large camel force and seven hundred cavalry, was El Harik, a bold and skilful General, who immediately began the erection of a fort there, to serve as a basis for his operations and campaigns against the inhabitants ot El Dhahireh and of the rich valleys and lowlands of the Batineh. This invasion of their country by the dreaded Wahhabees created intense excitement throughout all 'Oman, and Seyyid Sultan, with his usual energy and spirit, lost no time in assembling the tribes and moving up to oppose their advance. Having allied himself with Shaikh Saki the Kasimi, he marched through the Wady Jezze as far as El Bereymi, but in the contest that ensued with the enemy the 'Omanis appear to have been worsted, and Seyyid Sultan, finding he could not expel the intruders from hi Jow, made a truce with El Harik and retired to Sohar, where he dismissed his troops. In 1801 the island of El Bahrein, which has ever been on account of its rich pearl fishery the chief bone of contention for the peoples round the shores of the Persian Gulf, was again the object of Seyyid Sultan's ambition, and was invaded, and this time successfully, by a grand naval expedition from Muscat, the Uttoobees being driven out, and the island occupied by the 'Omani troops. Saif bin Ali, who had already done good service on the Mekran Coast, was appointed Governor and Commandant. An attempt was then made by Seyyid Sultan to capture the town of Kowait, where the Uttoobees had taken refuge, and homage was demanded from the Shaikh, but the enterprise was a failure. Nor did El Bahrain remain long in the possession of Muscat; a few months later it was retaken from Seyyid Salim bin Sultan, then a boy of twelve, who had replaced Saif bin Ali as Governor, by the Uttoobees, who succeeded in surprising the garrison.RESIDENCY AND MUSCAT POLITICAL AGENCY FOR 1887-88. 27 In this year Assistant Surgeon Bogle was succeeded by Captain David Seton, of the Bom bay Army, who was appointed to act under the title of Resident at Muscat, and who assumed charge of his duties towards tlie close of the yeai. The expulsion from El Bahrein was a disappointment to Seyyid Sultan, whose ardour for military enterprises appears to have been unquenchable, and who now resolved upon prosecut ing the Uttoobee war in earnest. Saif bin Ali was again despatched with a strong naval force to the island, which, in part, he succeeded in re-occupying. But, though he made good his footing, Saif could not entirely expel the enemy, and Seyyid Sultan, feeling his strength unequal to their subjugation, supported as they were at this time by the Wahhabees, now determined to call in the aid of Persia. With this object he despatched as envoy one Shaikh Ali, by way of Congoon to the Prince Governor of Shiraz, with costly presents, to procure the cooperation of that Ruler in a great expedition against the Uttoobees. Seyyid Sultan wrote also to Shaikh Nasir, the Wali of Bushire, requesting him to use his influence with the prince in obtaining the required assistance, and enclosing a blank sheet of paper with his (Sultanas) seal on it, to be filled up with any conditions the Persians might impose in return for the military assistance they were to give. Seyyid Sultan, however, did not wait for these re -inforcements, but early in June 1802, having determined on conducting operations in person, set sail with a formidable fleet of ships and bughlas for El Bahrein. Landing in force, he attacked the Uttoobees vigorously but without gaining much success, until two months later, his appeal to Shiraz having been favourably received, a body of 200 horse and 2,000 foot embarked at Bushire to join him. The result of the combined forces acting against the tribe was that the latter were com pelled to submit and acknowledge the supremacy of 'Oman; the aggressive attitude of the Wahhabees at this time, and the consequent necessity of withdrawing a large portion of his army for home defence, alone preventing Seyyid Sultan from prosecuting the war until he had completely expelled the Uttoobees from the island. His navy, however, had the satisfaction of 'so far destroying the Uttoobee war craft that by the end of October 1803 their piratical depredations were entirely at -an end. In May 1802 Captain Seton was compelled by ill health to return to Bombay on twelve months' leave, the Company's native broker being left in charge of affairs. Captain Seton returned to Muscat, and resumed charge as Resident in June 1803. Though it was as much as he could do to protect his own country from the Wahhabees Seyyid Sultan was too magnanimous to refuse an appeal which appears to have been made about this time to him to aid in repelling the Nejdeans, who had invaded the Hejaz, and were threatening the Holy Cities. Taking with him presents of money and munitions of war for the Shereef, he embarked with Shaikh Muhenna El Yaareby and others on board one of his ships in January 1803, and set sail for Jedda. . A small military contingent appears to have been also prepared and despatched to Jedda at this time, but if so, it was not commanded by Seyyid Sultan, whose object in going himself was to perform the pilgrimage at Mecca, which he duly accomplished. The Regency appointed to act during his absence was composed of his elder son, Salim, his relative Muhammad Nasir El Jabri, and Muhammad Khalfan. Soon after his departure, his nephew, Seyyid Bedr, who was then residing at Hibra, a village near Nakhl, proceeded to Muscat with a few followers and concealed himself in the house of Seyyid Majid, the brother of the Wali of the town, and endeavoured therefrom to seduce the commandant of Fort Jelali from his allegiance. In this intrigue Seyyid Majid, who was disaffected, lent his aid, but the attempt failed, and Seyyid Bedr, having been denounced, was barely able to effect his escape. Tradition relates that he was being smuggled into Jelali in a large box, but was detected by one of the Hindu traders, who reported the matter to Seyyid Salim. At all events Bedr got clear off, and made his way, first to Ajman, from whence he pro ceeded to Zobura in Katar, and sought protection from the Wahhabees, whose tenets he adopted. With their help he subsequently, on two occasions, made an attempt on Muscat, but, failing in this, he at length determined to make a journey to Nejd, where, in 1804, he had an interview with the Amir Saood, who gladly received him. Though the small force despatched to the Hejaz could have done but little to help in stemming the tide of Wahhabee invasion, the knowledge of Seyyid Sultan's act of hostility and the ^presence of the 'Omanis in the ranks of his enemies so exasperated the Amir Abdul- 4zeez that on his return from the campaign he declared war against Muscat, and despatched d 228 ADMINISTRATION REPORT OP THE PERSIAN GULF POLITICAL orders to EI Bahrein, Koweit, and Ras El Khyma to fit ont their fleets to sconr the Gulf against 'Omanl commerce. To these orders the Uttoohees and Kowasm demurred, as the pea y season was now commencing, and all their men were engaged, and they accord.ngly repre ented to the Amir that they conld not abandon their occupation, but the commands were repeate m so peremptory a manner that the tribes no longer hesitated to obey, and the pearl flshery that year was abandoned in favour of piracy. Th6 news / the ^ S mt ™ ' ^tbT iv 'ha of aggressions by sea, as well as by land, induced the Persian Government and the Pa ha of Baghdad to ally themselves with Seyyid Sultan against him. In the naval war that followed Sevyid Sultan personally took an a ctive part, and did his utmost to protect his own coasts and commerce from the insults and ravages of the piratical fleet; but his success was not great. His allies had, after some show of assistance, left him in the lurch, and he was now threatened with an invasion by land. In this critical position, Seyyid Sultan deemed it best to try and propitiate his enemy. He accordingly despatched a mission to Derayeh, and purchased a truce for three years by the payment of a large sum of money, the promise of a yearly tribute of 12,000 dollars, and the establishment of a Wahhabee Agent at Muscat. The Amir, however, had no intention of relinquishing his grasp on 'Oman, even on these humiliating terms. He took advantage of the truce to re-inforce El Harik at El Bereymi, and, shortly after, perfidiously broke it by ordering his General to march. El Harik at once poured down into the Batineh, where he committed unspeakable atrocities, and easily overpowered the resistance he met with fiom the disunited tribes in his path. Seyyid Sultan, on hearing of El Harik's movement, hastily gathered as large a force as he could muster, and a battle took place in Wady Heimali above boweyk, in which the Omanis were routed by the Wahhabees. This was the first great disaster experienced in 'Oman at the hands of these fanatics, and Seyyid Sultan was constrained by the alarm felt everywhere to call a council of war at Barka to discuss a plan of operations. The Shaikhs of tribes of both actions assembled there agreed to combine against the common enemy, and it was arranged that each tribe should contribute its quota and assemble at K.habooreh on a certain day. El Harik after, the affair at Heimali, retired towards Sohar, to which he laid siege, and there quietly awaited the advance of the army of defence Seyyid Sultan was raising, and which soon numbered 12,000 men. At this juncture the news of the death of the Wahhabee's Amir Abdul Aziz, who had been assassinated at Derayeh in October, reached El Harik at Sohar, and the advices he then received of affairs at home induced him to raise the siege and retire without delay to El Bereymi. Relieved from the pressure of their exacting masters, the Kowasim speedily made peace with Seyyid Sultan, and the 'Omanis, unacquainted with the real cause of the sudden dis appearance of their foes, ascribed it to their own superiority in numbers or to the success of the negociations that had been carried on by Seyyid Sultan with El Harik. When the death of the Emperor Paul dissolved the treaty for the joint Franco-Russian invasion of India overland, Napoleon determined that the substitution of French supremacy for English in India should follow as a natural consequence upon the subjection of England itself, for which purpose he at once began to make preparation. With this grand scheme before him Napoleon, towards the close of the year 1802, while the treaty of Amiens was yet in force, selected one of his ablest Generals, Decaen, to be the Captain General of the French possessions in the East, and despatched him with Admiral Linoi's expedition, which sailed from Brest on the 6th March 1803. The mission of General Decaen was to observe closely the position of the English in India in their relation to the Native Princes, and to prepare the way for the French conquest and occupation of India by procuring full information as to the state of affairs and extent of armament required. After visiting Pondichery, General Decaen fixed upon the Island of Mauritius as his head-quarters and post of observation, and on establishing himself there immediately despatched M. de Cavaignac in the Atalanta frigate to his destination. This M. de Cavaignac had been appointed by Napoleon Agent and Consul for France at Muscat, and as his mission had the same object in view as that of General Decaen^ to whom he was subordinate, it may be as well to transcribe here the concluding paragraph of the long letter of instructions written for the General's guidance by Napoleon, which indicates clearly enough that the scheme for the conquest of India had not been relinquished, and that Decaen might possibly be entrusted with the enterprise— The mission of the Captain General is, in the first instance, a mission of observation, politieal and military, &amp;c., but the first Consul, well informed by the Captain General, upon whom he relies for the punctual'RESIDENCY AND MUSCAT POLITICAL AGENCY FOR 1887-88. 29 execution of these instructions, may perhaps place it in his power to acquire a great glory which prolongs the memory of men beyond the duration of ages.' The Atalanta frigate, a famous ship in her day, was painted a bright yellow colour with white mouldings, and was one of the swiftest and handsomest vessels of her class in the French navy. She sailed from Mauritius on the 5th September 1803, and reached Muscat on the 3rd October. On anchoring in the cove she was boarded by the Wali, who, on being made acquainted with the purport of M. de Cavaignac^s mission, informed that gentleman that Seyyid Sultan was absent in the interior, being engaged in operations against the Wahhabees; he promised, however, that immediate intimation should be sent to him of the Atalanta s arrival, and, in the meantime, offered M. de Cavaignac the hospitality of a house on shore. At this time the Resident, Captain Seton, was absent on duty, having sailed in the Ternate in the beginning of September for another part of the Gulf, and^he French envoy, therefore, had a fair opportunity of making friends with the leading Arabs, and of pressing the advantages of a French alliance. It was in his favour also that the commercial intercourse so long existing with Mauritius had caused the formation of a strong French party in the town, as he was able to depend on the influence of these partizans at the palace, and it was from them that he first learned of the existence of the treaties of 1798 and 1800. Congrataluting himself, therefore, on the opportune absence of his adversary, the English Resident, M. de Cavaignac entertained for some days high hopes of procuring a favourable reception and of succeeding in his mission. Seyyid Sultan returned to Muscat on the morning of the 12th October 1803. He had been engasred in contending and negociating with the Wahhabee General, but on receiving his Wali's letter had started at once for Muscat, firmly resolved upon the course he would adopt with Napoleon's agent. The captain of the Atalanta, on hearing of Seyyid Sultan's arrival, sent two of his officers to convey his respects and compliments, and to ask for an interview. The officers were civilly received, and on being questioned as to the object of the Atalanta's visit replied that it was desired to establish a French Residency at Muscat, and that an officer appointed to act as Consul by the French Government was on board the vessel. The same afternoon Seyyid Sultan sent two Arab officials on board, with instructions to acquaint the Captain and M. de Cavaignac that His Highness could not receive a French Agent and Consul on account of the engagements recently entered into with the English, and that he declined an interview to discuss the subject; but that, as he wished to remain on friendly terms with the French, his harbours would always be open, as before, to their vessels, and that he would be happy to listen to any proposals they had to make on commercial matters. In dictating this diplomatic message, Seyyid Sultan was no doubt actuated by a keen regard for his country's interests. While fearful of offending the French, the remembrance of Captain Malcolm^s arguments and the momentous events that had occurred since his (Malcolm's) visit, such as the evacuation of Egypt by the French army, and the triumphs of Lord Lake in India, had created a deep impression on the Prince's mind, and must have convinced him more than ever as to the incomparably greater importance to the Arabs of the English over the French alliance. The tone of the message must have shown M. de Cavaignac the hopelessness of argument and representation on his part, as he does not appear to have again sought an interview, but it was a bitter disappointment to him, for his Arab friends had made him sanguine of success, and be had doubtless been anticipating in his mind the approbation of Napoleon. Reluctant, however, to abandon so easily the mission with which he had been charged, he waited in the harbour for one more day and then, under cover of the darkness of midnight on the 13th, the Atalanta's broad sails bore her out of the port, and by the morning she was nowhere to be seen. This attempt closed for the time French' political intercourse with Muscat, and it was not renewed until Seyyid Saeed sent a mission to the Isle of France after the murder of Seyyid Bedr in 1807. But the French privateers nevertheless did not cease to make Muscat a rendezvous and base for their operations against British shipping in the Persian and 'Oman Gulfs, and great was the depredation committed by them. During the ten years of Seyyid Sultan's reign, from 1793 to 1804, the loss inflicted on British trade in the Indian Ocean was not less than 250 lakhs of rupees, or about three millions sterling.30 ADMIXISTBATIOS BEPOKT OF THE PERSIAN' GULF POLITICAL Sevvid Sultan and the Muscat or taken to Lt^t^tt^r^asTornnTlBOe that the Marine In^nce Offices in India intprffred to check this traffic. i t &gt; i* v. interrereu ^ ^ v ^fwopn Frfnch and English cruizers in Many -.anded &gt;. Captain ^ Arab waters. In governuei „ ,* Mn^at and after a long combat succeeded encountered a French privateer of superior force off Muscat, and in beating her off and chasing her away. f , • t lQ 1*03^^ ST-d swr n a' k tLV^ ^utun^beloogmgtoTe'same'service. Lememe then proceeded to the Mannt.us, but f T the Gulf early in ISOi, and committed great havoc until &gt;ovember of that year, ZZt was hLelf captured by the English fngate Concorde, which had been sent out in search of him. _ „ Sevyid Sultan was well aware that the suspension of hostilities on the part of El Hank was onl temporary, and though the large force collected m the Bat.neh d.spersed on the retiremen of the enemy from before Sohar, he began at once to make fresh preparat.ons acain^t the renewal of the storm. With the object of re-opemng negoc.at.ons w,tb the Pasha 'i Baghdad for an alliance, and of concerting operations with the Turkish Commander, Seyy.d Sultan despatched one of his ships to Busra ^ before he could leam the result of this move he found himself already engaged with the Wahhabees by sea and land. The Amir Saood bin Abdul Aziz had adopted his father's scheme for the complete con- nuest and annexation of 'Omai., and had on his accession issued orders to £1 Hank to push on a^ain to the Batineh. At the same time, November 1803, the war fleets of the Uttuk and Kowasim were sent abroad to sweep the Gulf against the Muscat trade, and began by making a descent on the Island of Kishm, which they overran and pillaged. It does not appear that Seyyid Sultan's mission to Baghdad resulted in any joint action with the Turks. The Pasha was profuse in his promises of assistance and co-operation, but though equally desirous to see the Wahhabees crushed, he preferred to wait and see the 'Omani Prince exhaust himself in opposing them. Seyyid Sultan's appeals to the Government of India were similarly unsuccessful/ He^was left to bear the brunt of the war alone. Under a weak ruler 'Oman would almost certainly have succumbed to the invader, but Sultan never relaxed his efforts nor spared his resources in the defence of his country, and his indomitable courage and activity infused a spirit of resistance into his countrymen that enabled them for years to keep their foes in check. Until his untimely death in the following year, Seyyid Sultan seems to have been engaged in an almost continual struggle with Saood's troops, and though he was able to pre vent their advance up to the capital, he could never dislodge them from their main post at El Bereymi nor expel them from the country. It was in September 1804- that he left 'Oman for the last time on a naval expedition in the Gulf. Having collected a fleet of thirteen other ships and war dows, he embarked on board the Gunjava and cruized in search of the piratical fleet that had done so much to injure his commerce. He then sailed for Busra, where he wished to ascertain the extent of the military pre parations being made by the Turkish Pasha in accordance with his promise for operating against the Wahhabees. Disappointed and indignant, however, at his reception there, he did not remain long, but turned his face homeward and set sail down the Gulf. On his way he transferred himself to an Arab boat, or bateel, in order to land at Bassidore, and while in this almost defenceless position was attacked by three piratical dows belonging to Ras El Khyma, before anv of his fleet could discern his danger or come to his assistance. His assailants were Kowasim, at this time in league with the Wahhabees, and, as usual, at war with Muscat, but that they attacked with the set purpose of taking the life of the 'Omani Chief is somewhat doubtful. Seyyid Sultan fell at the first onslaught, with several of his attendants, and the pirates, on finding what they had done, fled at once to escape the vengeance of the Muscat fleet. The various dates mentioned for this event are the 14th, 17th, ISth, and 2(.Hh November 1804, but the exact date is not of importance. He is said to have been buried at Lin^ah. •RESIDENCY AND MUSCAT POLITICAL AGENCY FOR 1887-88. 31 The news of Seyyid Sultan's deathlcaused, as may be imagined, intense dismay throughout ^Oman. Threatened as the country was by external foes, the people seemed to be stunned by the loss of their great leader, and for some little time the attitude of all parties was one of expecta tion. But such a condition of affairs could not last, and it was not long before Sultan's brothers, Kais and Muhammad (for the Imam Saeed had died the previous yeay), rose in arms against their nephews, Salim and Saeed, the only point in whose favour was the possession of Muscat. Sultan's death, however, affected not only his own country; it created a great alteration in the state of politics over the whole Gulf. The general consternation at the disappearance of the warrior, who had alone actively opposed the common foe and disturber of public peace, caused everv Chief to prepare to defend himself, not knowing his friends from his enemies, while the Kowasim and Uttoobees, being no longer held in check, became more daring than ever. At this time November, the pirate fleet consisted of eleven war dows and thirty-three trankeys, to which were soon added two brigs, the Trimmer and Shannon, taken from the English. A month later the pirates rose to the audacity of attacking a vessel of war. This was the Mornington cruizer, which had been despatched from Bombay to protect the English trade in the Gulf, and though she succeeded in beating off her assailants it was not without difficulty, for they were superior in force. In character Seyyid Sultan is said to have been resolute and energetic. Fond of military expeditions, and always open-handed, he was universally admired by his people and his pres tige in the country equalled that of his father. He seems to have been quite as able as his better known son, Saeed, and was certainly of a more noble and less sensual disposition. Seyyid Sultan's claims to the gratitude of his countrymen were certainly great. In addition to his efforts to keep the Wahhabees at bay, he had made his country more respected abroad than it bad been for a century and a half, and had greatly extended his dominion by the acquisition of territory on the Persian Coast. He was, moreover, unceasing in his endea vours to develop the commerce of 'Oman, and by fixing his residence at Muscat had done much to raise that city to the position of being the chief emporium of trade in the Persian Gulf. In East Africa Seyyid Sultan had little opportunity of extending his rule, as he was too much engaged in home affairs to be able to pay attention to it, and matters there remained in the same state as they were left by Seyyid Hamad on his visit to that coast in 178^. Zanzi bar Island had continued to be governed direct from Muscat, while Mombasa remained in dependent and undisturbed, though the Wali, Ahmed bin Muhammad, wrote in 1793 to acknowledge Seyyid Sultan s suzerainty.32 ADMINISTEATION REPORT OP THE PERSIAN GULP POLITICAL p art iil-eepoet on the tbade op south persia foe the yeae 1887. Owing mainly to great dearness of grain in in a state o£ stagnation. The rain all in eonse.uently short and scanty (about 5| inches at Bus ir ), ^ ' i i npr 1^4 nounds and of barley to 12 krans for the same quantity. This led io the regm 1 wag dall and aar e m nn CT ative In thesec .rcumstanoes trade.n all articles ot^ V ^ shiraz havin!? st0 p ped during t f ° th t ma ny sma llermerchants, already weakened by the depressed state of rrtrie f ml ~t y Fortunately, however, at this juncture matters took a ml favourable turn, and the increase in prices of opium helped to aver further misfortun . The diminished amount of importations of piece-goods, sugar, &amp;o., doubtless caused favourable fluctuations in the native markets, and the latter part of the year was more satisfactory to merchants than anticipated. Probably this does not imply so much a material increase of profits as a saving of losses, owing to reduced and more cautious operations, but towards the end of the year considerable sales of Manchester goods were made at improved prices. The year 1888 opened with much more hopeful prospects in every way, a good and seasona jle 1am a J justifying expectations of an abundant harvest this year. 'Exports. The opium crop was one of the smallest recorded for several years, and owing to a brisk demand in the European and China markets prices increased 0pium - considerably, the results to those engaged in this trade being highly satisfactory, and proving the saving of several Persian merchants. The adulteration of Persian opium, formerly extensively practised, has now greatly decreased, and when lots are rejected it is probably from lack of skill in the manipulation or other causes. The tobacco crop was fairly large. This cultivation is gradually increasing, but hitherto a large proportion (nearly one-third it is said) of the crops is Tobacco. spoiled by early rains and bad weather. To avoid this serious loss the cultivators are having recourse to early sowings with some success, the crops being gathered at a correspondingly earlier season. The grain crops in South Persia, as well as in Turkish Arabia, having been so scanty, prices remained very high, the interdict on exportation of grain was kept on, and, as before mentioned, supplies were imported from India to Persia. So far as the chief ports were concerned, the embargo was observed, but the petty chiefs of districts north of Bushire found it to their interest to prevent the cultivators of their districts from sending their wheat and barley to the Bnshire market, and compelled them to use Bunder Reeg, whence quantities of the grain were shipped to Busrah and other ports. This, of course, enhanced the scarcity and dearness of grain generally. The cotton crop in South Persia was comparatively large Cotton. and prices higher than for some time past, owing to a good demand in Bombay. Imports, The returns show again a decrease in the import of these goods, but an improvement set Manchester goods. in durin &amp; the latter months of the year, which is expected to continue and strengthen during the current year. A decline is also visible in the importation of loaf sugar. This is understood to be due Sua . ar&gt; to two causes—firstly, the large losses sustained on shipments in previous years ; and, secondly, large arrivals of sugar from Russia, which reached as far as Ispahan, a market hitherto supplied from Bushire. The competition between English and Mauritius sugars on the one hand, and Russian and other beet sugars on the other, may possibly be affected by the abolition of bounties, if the measures contemplated are observed as regards Persia. Large losses were experienced inRESIDENCY AND MUSCAT POLITICAL AGENCY FOR 1887-88. 33 iTTiected importations of French sugar, and tlie agent of the Russian firm of Marseilles at Bunder Abbas lias closed bis office. The importation of sugar from Germany has been discontinued. In the two previous years a decline in the trade in copper was noticed. A Syndicate Metals. in London having established a ' corner' in this article, prices in Europe and other parts of the world have been sent up to a remarkable degree, and of course this has affected the Persian trade. Owing, however, to large stocks on hand in Persia, prices did not advance to a corresponding extent with those in Europe, and sheets of copper have actually been re-shipped from Bushire to Bombay and London. Persian dealers doubt the durability of the Syndicate, and hesitate to speculate until the stocks of copper in Persia have been disposed of, hence the failure to force up prices in Persia to the level ruling in Europe. Owing to scarcity and dearness of grain, there has been a larger importation o£ rice from India than usual. Eice. S/lipping. The number of steamers for Persian ports was unusually small. Owing to there being no exportation of grain, the regular vessels plying sufficed for general trade, and few other steamers would have called at Persian ports but for the demand at Busrah on account of the date business there. Pilgrims also were less numerous than usual, probably owing to distress from depression of trade; but a large proportion went overland, instead of by sea, Freights were fairly good and steady. Exchange. Exchange, on the whole, ruled lower than in 1886, fluctuating between 33| krans and 351 krans per £ sterling. The value of the kran in relation to the rupee has improved. The value of rupees averaged under 245 per cent., a less rate than in the preceding year. This is thought to be due to the Herat krans having been sent out of the country. Customs. The Malek Et Toojjar of Bushire farmed the customs of Shiraz, Bushire, Lingah, and Bunder Abbas with the district revenues of the last two places for the year 1887-88 at krans 21,50,000. These were sublet as follows :— Krans. Shiraz customs ........... 2,80,000 Bushire 8,00,000 Lingah .i.e......... I,10,t)00 Bunder Abbas ............ 6,00,000 Districts of Lingah ........... 90,000 „ Bunder Abbas.......... 2,50,000 T otal . 21,80,000 The trade during the year having fallen off, as already explained, much loss has been suffered by those who engaged in these speculations. In connection with the trade between India and Persia conducted through Bunder Abbas, I subjoin some interesting notes furnished to me by Lieutenant H. B. Vaughan, 7th Regiment, Bengal Infantry, dated Yezd, 3rd March 1888. The advantage which would accrue to British commerce from the establishment of an agent at Yezd to protect British commercial interests at that centre, is urged with justice by Lieutenant Vaughan, and has been referred to in previous reports : — j t . ' Since the introduction of the Telegraph and Post Office Yezd has become an important centre of trade, its population, inclusive of ad jacent suburbs, being about 100,000. ' The government of the district is farmed out for 250,000 tomans, and the customs for 47,000. ' The imports are Indian goods, as well as English, of all descriptions, amongst which are yarns, piece- j ^ ^ goods, prints, sugar, sugar refined, copper sheets, thin slabs, lead, iron, condiments, chinaware, glassware, spices, green tea, Indian tea, and Singapore tea, ' These imports come chiefly from Bombay through Bunder Abbas, and after a sufficient quantity has been taken here for local use, the remainder goes on from this city to the following places ;—Meshed, Tehran, Kushan, Sabzawar, Birzand, Toon, Tabas. Exportg ' The exports of Yezd are opium, cotton wool, madder root, curamin seeds, almonds, walnuts, pistachio-nuts, &amp;c. E34 ADMINISTRATION REPORT OF THE PERSIAN GULP POLITICAL ' There are about 16 naturalised '^t aZf fhTtrde'of this place with Bombay through British subjects. Bunder Abbas passes. ' These merchauts, owing to their unprotected state and the conseqnent insecnrity of their lives and proper- ty, are afraid to invest ™ re tba ' whomatkast half the trade passes, is still worse : they are 9 „ito7n h ;r^ endangered, and sometimes even sacrificed, owing to the pcrsecnt.on which they experience at t ' ,e ban ^ ^ ^^'XantCcilhw by the establishment of a Native Agent to look after 'If protection were afforded ^ safety and the int erests of trade, or by these merchants being taken Encouragemfint of British trade. under ^ p ro tection of one of the British Agents in Persia, the effect on British trade would be astonishing. . , 3 mi tj c ' These merchants would lay out nearly four times the amount which they do now m trade. The Parsees of Yezd would form companies and firms, establish factories and banking Its future. corporations, and import and export goods of English manufacture for local as well as foreign, consumption to a vastly larger extent than they do now. . , « At present English trade is decidedly at a disadvantage here when compared with that of Russia whose A P S Armenian subjects, whether naturalised or native, carry on extensive English trade as compared with Russian. business in perfect safety and security owing to the protection afforded bv that Government to all its subjects.' . . t. • /-. ir A The pearl fisheries m the Persian Gulf were more produc- Pearl fishery. tive than ^ ur i n g the previous year. BUSHIREJ E - C - R0SS . C ° lm ^ The loth April 1888. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.residency and muscat political agency for 1887-88. 35 APPENDIX A TO PAET III: consisting of the following tabular statistics:— 1. Return of principal articles of export from Busliire during the year 18S7. 2. Return of principal articles of import iuto Bushire duriug the year 1887. 3. Table showing the total value of all articles exported from^ and imported to, .Bushire from and to foreign countries, during the years 1886 and 1887. 4. Return of shipping at the Port of Bushire in the year 1887. 5. Return of British shipping at the Port of Bushire during the year 1887. 6. Return of foreign shipping at the Port of Bushire during the year 1887. 7. Statement showing the quantity of opium exported from Bushire from 1st January to 31st December 1887. 8. Statement showing the total quantity and value of opium exported from Bushire and Bunder Abbas during the years 1878 to 18^7. 9. Contrasted statement showing the value and description of goods exported from Bushire during the years 1883 to 1887. 10. Contrasted statement showing the value and description of goods imported into Bushire during the years 1883 to 1887. 11. Return of principal articles of export from Lingah during the year 1887. 12. Return of principal articles of import into Lingah during the year 1887. 13. Table showing the total value of all articles exported from, and imported to, Lingah from and to foreign countries, during the years 1886 and 1887. 14. Return of shipping at Lingah in the year 1887. 15. Contrasted statement showing the value and description of goods exported from Lingah during the years 1883 to 1887. 16. Contrasted statement showing the value and description of goods imported into Lingah during the years 1883 to 1887. 17. Return of principal articles of export from Bunder Abbas during the year 1887. 18. Return of principal articles of import into Bunder Abbas during the year 1887. 19. Table showing the total value of all articles exported from, and imported to. Bunder Abbas from and to foreign countries, during the years 1886 and 1887. 20. Return of shipping at the Port of Bunder Abbas in the year 1887. 21. Statement showing the quantity of opium exported from Bunder Abbas from the 1st January to the 31st December 1887. 22. Contrasted statement showing the value and description of goods exported from Bunder Abbas during the years 1883 to 1887. 23. Contrasted statement showing the value and description of goods imported into Bunder Abbas during the years 1883 to 1887. 24. Return of principal articles of export from Bahrain during the year 1887. 25. Return of principal articles of import into Bahrain during the year 1887. 26. Table showing total value of all articles exported from, and imported to, Bahrain from and to foreign countries, during the years 1886 and 1887. 27. Return of shipping at the Port of Bahrain in the year 1887. 28. Return of principal articles of export from the Ports of the Arab Coast of the Persian Gulf during the year 1887. 29. Return of principal articles of import into the Ports of the Arab Coast of the Persian Gulf during the year 1887. 30. Table showing the total value of all articles exported from, and imported to, the Ports of the Arab Coast of the Persian Gulf from and to foreign countries, during the years 1886 and 1887. 31. Return of shipping at the Ports of the Arab Coast cf the Persian Gulf in the year 1887. e 2 m m• ''' ' - TABLE No. 5. Return of British Shipping at the Port of Bushire during the year 1S87. DIRECT TRADE IN BRITISH VESSELS FROM AND TO GREAT BRITAIN AND BRITISH COLONIES. ENTERED. CLEARED. Numbeb of Vessels. Tonnage. Value of Cargoes. Number op Vessels. Tonnage. Number of Crews. With Cargoes. In Ballast. Total. With Cargoes. In Ballast. Total. Number of Crews. With Cargoes. In Ballast. Total. With Cargoes. In Ballast. Total. Cargoes. E R 116 8 124 78,383 10,978 89,361 5,686 79,39,810 121 3 124 86,299 3,018 89,317 5,685 *34,59,356 * Excluding R17,72,000, being value of opium exported to Hongkong for China. INDIRECT OR CARRYING TRADE IN BRITISH VESSELS FROM AND TO OTHER COUNTRIES. Countries whence arrived. ENTERED. Countries to which departed. CLEARED. Number op Vessels. Tonnage. Number of Crews. Value of Cargoes. Number of Vessels. Tonnage. Number of Crews. Value of Cargoes. With Cargoes. In Ballast. Total. With Cargoes. In Ballast. Total. With Cargoes. In Ballast. Total. With Cai-goes. In Ballast, Total. Nil ... ... ... ... ... ... Nil ... ... ... ... ... ... ... 0 1-4 01 H to t&gt; H h-1 o w hd O W H O H w w ►d « p3 co (-4 fe! Q cj tr 1 •t J O tr 1 o TAnx.E TSTo. 0. \56 administration report of the pebsian gulf political p art iv.—muscat teade repoet foe the yeae 1887-88. The year under report compares very favourably with the preceding one, the total value of the trade for the year being ^303,080 against | 3,115,290 in 1886-87, showing an increase of $187,790. The imports amounted to $1,862.,395, showing an increase of &lt;8)1,44,585, and the exports to $1,440,685, showing an increase of $43,205 over the figures for the previous year. In the case of imports the principal increase was in rice, coffee, sugar, piece-goods, and kerosine oil from India; and in cotton and salt, from the Persian Gulf and Mekran Coast, whilst in the case of exports the increase occurred principally in dates, fruit, fish, and cotton fabrics. There was a great decrease under the head of Imports from the United States. The customs were farmed by Ratansee Purshatam, a Bhatia merchant, for $110,000. A..S. G, JAYAKAR, Surgeon-Major, In charge of Political Agency, Muscat.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000358.0x00026e_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/V/23/53, No 245</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000358.0x00026e</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/V/23/53, No 245</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>‘Administration report of the Persian Gulf Political Residency and Muscat Political Agency for 1887-88.’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1888/1888</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-10-31T02:22:59</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (34 folios)</extent><extent>The report is arranged into four numbered parts, with lettered appendices containing further reports and statistical data coming after each part. The General Summary is further organised into numbered sections, and further divided into paragraphs which are also numbered, from 1 to 99.</extent><extent>Foliation: There is a foliation sequence, which is circled in pencil, in the top right corner of the recto of each folio. It begins on the first folio, on number 3, and ends on the last folio, on number 36.Pagination: The volume contains an original typed pagination sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Administration Report on the Persian Gulf Residency and Muscat Political Agency (no 245, Foreign Department serial no 20) for the year 1887-88, published by Authority and printed by the Superintendent of Government Printing, Calcutta [Kolkata]. A copy of a letter from Colonel Edward Charles Ross, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf and Her Britannic Majesty’s Consul-General for Fars, to Henry Mortimer Durand, Secretary to the Government of India (Foreign Department), dated 14 June 1888, is included in the report (folio 4), the original of which submitted the report to Government, under the following headings:Part 1 (General Summary), submitted by Ross (folios 5-11), containing numbered summaries of local political affairs, and incidents or events of particular note for: 1) Muscat state; 2) Oman pirate coast; 3) El-Bahrain (referred to as Bahrain in the text); 4) El-Katr [Qatar]; 5) Nejd, El-Hasa [Al-Hasa]; 6) Fars and the Persian Coast, including Shiraz, Bushire and its districts, Lingah [Bandar-e Lengeh] and Bunder Abbas [Bandar-e ʻAbbās]; 7) Persian Arabistan; and 8) Persian Baluchistan. The report also includes summaries for: 9) Climatic observations, recorded by the observatory at Bushire, and 10) British actions against the slave trade. Appendix A contains tabulated meteorological data for the year, supplied by the Bushire observatory.Part 2 (
                           Administration Report of the Muscat Political Agency for the year 1887-88), submitted by A. S. Jayakar, Surgeon Major in Charge of the Political Agency (folios 12-18), containing a summary of affairs at Muscat, under the headings: political affairs, official changes, and slave trade. Appendix A to Part 2 is a sketch of the career of Seyyid Sultan bin Ahmed, the Imam Muscat, written by Colonel Samuel Barrett Miles.Part 3 (
                           Report on the trade of South Persia for the year 1887-88), submitted by Ross and dated 15 April 1888 (folios 18-30). The report comprises a short summary of the year’s trade, with notes on: exports (opium, tobacco, cereals); imports (Manchester [cotton] goods, sugar, metals and rice); shipping; exchange; custom; and notes supplied by Lieutenant Vaughan on the economic state at Yezd [Yazd], where Ross advocates the establishment of a British agent. Appendix A comprises tabulated data on import, exports and revenue, in the Gulf ports of Bushire, Bandar-e Lengeh, Bandar-e ʻAbbās, Bahrain and the Arab (Oman) coast. An index to the trade tables can be found at folio 20.Part 4 (
                           Muscat trade report for the year 1887-88), submitted by Jayakar (folios 30-36), comprising a brief summary of the year’s trade at Muscat, and also containing tabulated data on imports and exports at Muscat (listed by commodity), and the nationality and average tonnage of vessels visiting Muscat.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Agent and Consul, Muscat</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="personal"><namePart>Sayyid Sulṭān bin Aḥmad Āl Bū Sa'īd</namePart></name></subject><name type="personal"><namePart>Samuel Barrett Miles</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Persian Gulf</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Muscat</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Agriculture</topic></subject><subject><topic>Trade (practice)</topic></subject><subject><topic>Meteorological data</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000358.0x00026e#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>