<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000257_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T21:22:33.360Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Telegram En Clair. From !METCALFE, Central India, Indore. To Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain Fo. Nil. i \ Dated 14th T T arch, 1940* Kindly telegraph whether wife entitled to one fare? J2K_3asrah or Karachi when proceeding on leave alone from Gulf• O2- Telegram Sn Clair. From Political, Bahrain. To rETCALFE, Central India, Indore. No. 76 lated 17th March, 1940. ..— 1 - Your telegram fourteenth fare admissible if you proceed on leave within six months of wife.No.761-1 /44 Political Agency, BRhrain. 17th April, 1940. To The Secretary to the Hon f bl6 the Political Resident In the Persian Gulf Bushlre. remorandun. I enclose a charge certificate, in quadruplicate, showing that Captain R. D. Metcalfe has assumed charge of the office of the Publicity Officer, Bahrain, with effect from the forenoon of the 17th April 1940. for Political Agent, ^hrain.No.753-1/44 p o i i W* 1 A ^oncy 9 Bahrain. 17th April, 1940 From Captain K. 1). Metcalfe | Publicity Officer/^ lahraIn . /L -dx. To r : l he 'vccountont 'ienervfl^ Central Kev: nueF., e * D elhi . Sir, I nave the honour to forward herewith a copy or the certificate showing that i took over charge of the post of Publicity Officer in the Pereian Ckilf on the forenoon of 17th April 1940 ana to request you very kindly to issue my salary slip by return Air ail * 2. A copy of irr last Pay Certificate is enclosed. I have the hor.our to be, Your most ohedient secant, 7 c /lAL Publicity Officer, Bahi^ain. fjnfNo.780- Political Agency! Bahrain. 2l8t April, 1940. To Messrs. Qray, Mackenzie &amp; Co.i Ltd., Bahrain. .. Dear Sire, I should be grateful if would issue the following passage tickets and reserve one first class berth ex-Bahrain to Bushire by the slovr mail leaving here on or about the 5th May 1940. 1. One first class ticket with food for Captain R. D. Metcalfe, I.A., 2. ne deck ticket with food for hia servant. 2. The cost of passages will be paid on receipt of your debit note. Yours faithfully, for Political Agent, Bahrain* frT L' BRITISH OVERSEAS AIRWAYS CORPORATION. BAHRAIN ISLANDS PERSIAN GULF | £ 1 - ^ Tele2)Iione : 45 M Telegrams : Flying Bali rain Cotles : Bentley s &amp; I.A.r.A. 8^1/377/3.2 12 th May, 19^0. The Assistant Political Agent, BAHR3E: Dear Sir, GAPTAUT I.'I3TG^iLF3 V/e regret to inform yon that we have 'been unahle to secure a reservation for Captain Metcalfe fnap Barnrein to Alexandria on May 18th, the first available accomrriodation 'begin on 23rd May, due in Alexandria on the evening of Hay 2I|th. We would suggest, therefore, that you apply to the D.C.A., India, for a priority passage, and v/e shall immediately relay this demand to our Principals. I have the honour to 'be Sir, Your Ohedient Servant, 1 • •••• Station Superintendent.Mo. ^T-T- //t/V Poli'ical Agencyi ^ahi'ain, the 14th 1940• To The Station Superintendent, British Overseaa A5rways Corporation, n A H R A I N Dear Slrt .Vlth reference to your telephone conversation with Mr* Metcalfe this morning I enclose herewith his passport No# 22 k 78 and should te grateful If It could be sent to fiaghdad by to-morrow's flying-boat or an endorsement and full visa for travel to Egypt. If Mr. Metcalfe is unable to obtain passage on the flying-boat of the 18th, he will travel by K.L.M* or Air France from Basra. I should be grateful if arrangements could be made to hand the passport to hln at the aerodrome at Habi^aniyah. Yours faithfully, / w y '; &lt;- -; % 1. C , .) 7 i for Political Agent, Bahrain, A ■ i -7/'/? BRITISH OVERSEAS AIRWAYS CORPORATION eleplioue : 43M BAHRAIN ISLANDS PERSIAN GULF (uc^ BAH/-1A03/P.2 The Political Agent, BAHREIN li+th May, 19U0. lelegrains : Flying B.ilirain Codes : Bentley 's &amp; I.A.T.A. Sir, PASSPORT NO.2278 J 4*. /W' n I have the hono\ir th acknowledge receipt of British Indian Passport No # 2278, the property of Captain Metcalf, This passport will 'be sent to Baghdad on the Flying Boat of May 15th, and I will advise my principals there 'by cahle where and when it is to he handed hack to Captain Metcalf, 1 : M-'# ^ I have the honoxub to he Sir, Your Obedient Servant, V^3 STATION SUPERINTENDENT, /'Q'. Political Resident, Bushire Political Agent, Bahrain. 267. .Dated and received the 16th May 1940. Is Letcalfe likely to get passage to Cairo ? fftj t'' —■JiO D /0 .jA7.; THE CUSTOMHOUSE: BAHRAIN: 30th May, 1940,, ,23rd Rabia II., 1359., /-&gt; ^ I find that s.s.^arpeta'v.SSS, arrived here on the 19th May, and discharged ten cases of liquor marked 'PKIPSON 1 which have not yet 'been cleared. These cases appear to 'be addressed to Metcalfe; and I mention this in case you m^y wish to have them cleared for him, as the charges for khanchia etc., are adeeming. To:- H. V^eightman Esquire, I.C.S., The Agency, MANAMAH. /''N (X .f A'No. Political Agency, Prhrein the 1st June L 40, To, Messrs Grey Mackenzie ^Co. Ltd., Brhrein. Dear Sirs, Ten cases liquor marked ,, PH'P30N W arrived here per S.S.Bfrpeta voyage 282 on i9th Mry 1 j 4U, Theae cases arc meant for Captain Metcalfe end I should be grateful if you would issue a delivery order and send it to me per bearer. The bill of lading will be sent to you as soon as Captain Metcalfe arrives. Yours faithfully, * / Assistant Political Agent. kTelegram G.T.C. From , Political Agent, Bahrain. To Political Agent, Kuwait. No. iff Dated 4th June 1940. IMPORTANT. Is' Metcalfe in Kuwait ? If so when is he returning here ? - Political -Telegram GTC. From Political, Kuwait. To Political, Bahrain. No.365 Dated 4th June, 1940. Your telegram No.168. Metcalfe hopes to arrive Bahrain sixth. A. ^ CTelegraphic Addreua ; Aooouirra. All cummuniuationH should be addressed to the Accountant General, Central Revenues. OFFICE OF me ACCOUNTANT GENERAL CENTRAL REVENUES No. aC61-64»889 NEW DELHI, doted the JL. M^' 19/ S W k V WP olosurefl. To T HE ACCOUNTANT GENERAL, CENTRAL REVENUES, The High Coaniasioner for India 9 \ccounta Department, India House y \ldwych # London, W.C. 2« Captain H.D.Metcalfe, I,A. of the Indian Politioal Service* • • • Sir, la continuation of this office letter No«QC51*54-6027 dated the 19th January 1939, Z have the honour to atate that the above named officer made over charge of the office of tfc Uhder Secretary to the Resident for Central India, Indore on diet '&gt;arch 1940 (after-noon) and Joined hie duties as Publicity Officer, Persian Qulf,Bahrain on the forenoon of 17th April 1940* AS he ws entitled to sterling overseas pay during his Joining time pay for the period frofi 1-16th April 19401 you will kindly continue to pay his sterling overseas pay # £*16/- p«ffl* (Pounds fifteen) only from 1st April 1940 onwards to his nominees in Sag land. The expenditure on this account is debitable to lv 35-S.At- Charges in England * High Coooissioner for Indie Sterling Overseas Pay-Non-Voted. J hove. tkf. honour tc bs, &amp;ir, Tour most ebedUnt servmt. &lt;1 .L. Sinha• d istent AceomitlsCV- A/J a cul c t^crtn^ P. (z fe ¥ A. X, C.—8-A. ^ ^ OFFICE OF THE /^-V no,3sijllzp ^/_- a'2&gt;tyu'^i. % the 21 • MAY _ ^ Co-A*.- ^'. 2). Me£cae.fe. ^j^laa-i /^Q ^vc^-^- ^ is informed that under order No. gj-g _, dated 9 - 6 - (Gazette pag e 6 -)/o he is entitled to draw pay and allowances at the monthly rates shown below from the dates specified :— Details of calculation. : &gt; : r • f — Substantive pay Officiating pay Overseas pay fyssa£?LCt ^ . Special pay . From A 4 O o !(&gt;■ u. l(o t*nj(jl j&gt; e. &amp; i' CO*: ctoj*- */. &gt; a&amp; ct (u j /&lt;! O. v &lt;? Lq t/C*. ^ ft'OO Total From qonf^ / /^/. /?• 'x ' (l icrtrj^ f h &lt;y*/- ± jjlh From From a/d- ^frr rj~ V-C^4&gt; (su-£ J ^eA z /l ItSf-frt* Cr ( &lt;m£ / ^:/ © X 'V y^o t/e vc^ 0\s&lt;j&lt;l ir f *- ^r/dz Cv;^., The scale of pay is on may be drawn till the stage *. . Increment accrues every year and, in the absence of instructions to the contrary, this is reached. j [Signature] . • [Designation) A/(t 6i^e./sxj^Q\&amp;i/Lk*j , Notr 1 :—It is particularly requested that this slip may be attached to the first pay hill drawn at these raterf- and that No. may be entered as the audit number at the top of every pay bill. T* / Note 2 :—Deductions of fund subscriptions and recoveries of (Government dues as noted in the last-pay k -'~ '$ certificate should be effected unless otherwise stated. ♦ Here state the stage at which a pause or efficiency bar operates. No Copy forwarded to the Treasury Officer. -for information. He should insert the details of pay given above in any last-pay certificate issued by him in favour of this Government servant. {Signature) (Designation) No Rent Officer Copy forwarded to the Executive Engineer Unit Accountant for information. MFP—274 Audit—(M-519)—l 6.6-37—50,000. [Signature) [Designation)Mo . n^ Politicrl Agency, B^hr- in, th;. ilth June 1940. To, The Secretary to the Honourable The Political Resident in the Persirn Gulf, BUSHIHF, MemorraiU . Reference your printed letter No.27t,-S deted t ILth May 1940. 2. Although His Majesty's Government, .n their telegram No.2752 of 4th Juno 1940, luve sanctioned i House Rent Allowance of Ri. 150/-/- p.m. for the post of Publicity Officer, Persian Gulf, the Accountant-General, Central Revenues, has only authorised me to draw h.lo /-/- p.nu I should therefore be grateful if you would please request the ^.G.C.R. to iswsue a correct salary slip. Publicity Officer, Persian'Gulf. Of ptain.No. Politicel Agency, Bahrtin, the 9th June 1940. To, The Accountant Gencrrl, Central Revenues, NF' With reference to your letter No,0051-54-^1 dcted the 2i3t May 1940, I have the honour to inform you that I arrived at Karachi on 12th Jpril 1940 in the forenoon. Would you therefore kindly authorise me to dra^joining time pay tiom ist April 1940 to 16th Ppril 1940(inclusive)at an early date. I have the honour to b; , Sir, Your most obed cnt servant. rtif (IAL Ca tain, / Publicity Officer,Persian Gull Bahrain.Political Agencr No./Z^yw w Lv ▼ Behrein, the L.:th June 77^ To, Imperial Pirweys, Bahrain. Dear Sirs, iifter travelling by air from Pahr&amp;in tc Alexandria, I returned in a B.O.A.C. aeroplane fro to Basra and then T^esra - Bahrain, '^or these two 1 journeys, I paid full fare i.e., £.8/- and £.14/-/- respectively, without any rebate for either being a ment servant or travelling on a return journey. As you already have a certificate that I Governm nt servant, will you please grant me credit, deductions admissible for the above journeys towards charges for taking me from BdJ^ in to /iexandria. Yours faithfully, - Captain, Publicity Officer,Persi Gulf./K. 'Vt 6CA. gc st-s'uwi o/ 2t s ^ ' &lt;10 OFFICE OP THE A G C**6r*t^ &lt;gt: st -stf./dsz .ae 19 .IIIN./feAO. g .P. ^/y /4&gt; r^gu*. (9 w 6 c . dated Ar ^- is informed that under order No ^ ._, dated (Gazette page ), he is entitled to draw pj^t-ajid allowances at the monthly rates shown below from the dates speeitied :— Details of calculation. Officiating pay Overseas pay Special pay From luj±q (ci ^tr*/ / /5/- Total ± t From /2. .tj-Qo u.it'io fi&gt; itrref From From A The scale of pay is_ (l iov*l +£ tsj* 0^X0 .-0 a* on may be drawn till the stage*. . Increment accrues every year and, in the absence of instructions to the contrary, this .is reached. ^ {signature)- * /j si (Designation) fT$ $ ^ Note 1 :—It is particularly requested that this slip may be attached to the first pay bill drawn at these rates and that No. may be entered as the audit number at the top of every pay bill. /Ai, Note 2 :—Deductions of fund subscriptions and recoveries of Government dues as noted in the last-pay /v£ certificate should be effected unless otherwise stated. ♦ Here state the stage at which a pause or efficiency bar operates. No. &lt; ?&lt;? fZ-feV/- /55J PfyC, frJuU. M * Oa. . Copy forwarded to the TVomuTy Officer » for i for information. He should insert the details of pay given above in any last-pay certificate issued by him in favour of this Crovernment servant. No.. [Signature) &lt;**'•*.) feck. 4m u* j Rent Officer Copy forwarded to the Executive Engineer Il/ U for information. l^/( \ Unit Accountant {Signature) {Designation) MFP—274 Audit—(M-519)—16-6-37—50,000.Telegraphic Address : Accounts. AH communioationa should be ftddreased to the Accountant General, Central Revenues. Enclosurea. OFFICE QF THE ACCOUNTANT GENERAL 7 CENTRAL REVENUES ' uf- NEW DELHI. V' 7 - A'oOO 51-54-1703. dated the IB. JUL. 19 40 Prom To The Jiccountant General,/^ ^ Central Revenues. ( ] Captain R.Metcalfe, Publicity Officer in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain . S 1 r, I have the honour to state that consequent on the creation of the post of the Publicity Offictr for the Persian Gulf and your appointment thereto ^ith effect from the 17th .April 1:940, viith the concurrence of His Majesty's Government, the provisional pay slip issued under this office No.GO 51-54-89i, dattd the 21st May 1940, is hereby amended as below:- * ?roa 17th April 1940. 1# Pay Q Ha.800/- p.m. (Rupees eight hundred only). 2. Special oay ® Rs.200/-p.m. (Rupees lno hundred only). &gt;m&lt; 3. House rent allowance Rg.l50/-p. Subject to the production of usual certificate. (Rupees one hundred and fifty only). 4. Stirling Overseas Pay £15/- Payable in England• (Pounds fifteen only). Less amounts already drawn. /■ The pay authority issued under this office No.GO 51- 54-1^ .^•y dated the 19th June 1940 is hereby confirmed, jVt ^ V\t I have the honour to be, Sir, lour most obedient servant. Signed. (J. L. Sinha), As si sua nt Accoun ts _ 0£fi ct-m / n No.GO 51-54-1704. dated the ^ Copy forwarded to the Political 'igent, Bahrain, for information and necessary action. Assistant Accounts Ofiictr.Politlo^il Agencyi Bahrain* 27th Augsut 1940• To Messrs. Mackinnon ?!ackenzle Ltd. f Karachi . Dear Sirs, A short while ago, Messrs. Gray, Mackenzie Ltd., Bahrain sent to you try slow Gulf mail five packages in my name, marked w To Await Arrival 11 • My present plans are to arrive in Karachi by air on Saturday, September 7th and proceed as soon as possible to Kashmir. Since the following day is a Sunday, when presumably the Customs will be closed. I do not want, if possible, to wait till the Monday, and would therefore be grateful if you would please clear these packages through the Customs. I enclose a bunch of keys and also a sworn affidavit in support of my claim that the contents of the packages should be allowed to pass free of duty. Could your representative meet me at Karachi airport on my arrival, to inform me if the packages have been successfully cleared or not? I want to catch the Karachi - Lahore - Jaramu mail train which leaves Karachi 19.40, travelling first class, in an air conditioned carriage if available, thence by car via Banilal to S^rinagar# My heavy kit will travel with me# If this is also in your line of business, would you please arrange a return rail-cum-road ticket as above for me?. Yours faithfully. Captain, Publicity Officer, Persian Gulf, Bahrain.37 Political Agencyi Bahrain. 27th August 1940. I hereby solemnity affirm that the articles contained in the five packages forwarded by me to ressrs. Fackinnon Mackenzie Ltd.f Karachi are with the following exceptions, articles of clothing apparel belonging to ray wife and myself. The exceptions are (1) the golf clubs, (2) the tennis racket in the bed roll and (3) the cine Kodak camera in rny suit case. The clothing belonging to my wife was all worn by her in India (where she still is) and exported by me to Bahrain last April, on the understanding that my wife, having spent the hot weather in Kashmir, would later Join me in Bahrain. This is now impossible owing to a pending transfer and I am therefore now sending her warm clothes back to her in India. My own clothing was also all exported from India last April and is now being sent on ahead to India, to await my arrival on leave by air. The tennis racket and cine Kodak were also purchased in India, are used and were exported by me in April last. The golf club were purchased in Bahrain but are used and will be re-exported to Bahrain in October when I return from leave.No. 10 ^ -79/76 5^ The Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Tiuli presents his compliments to The Political Agent, Bahrain. The Publicity Officer, Bahrain. IP £ pji and is directed to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents, for information. British Residency and Consulate-Greneral, BUSHIKE. r. / Dated .. 26th A^ttst 19 40. — w Reference to previous correspondence : Bushire Express Letter No.973-79/76 dated the lat August 1940. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Express Letter No.F.209-N/40 dated the 7th August 1940, from the Government of India in the External Affairs Dept Simla. Subject. Publicity Officer for the Persian Gulf.t f } From To GOVERNMENT OF INDIA External Affairs Department EXPRESS LETTER Foreign, Simla The Hon'tie the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. (Repeated to Secretary of State for India, London.) NO.F.209-N/40. Dated the 7th August 1940. Subj ect:-Publicity Officer for the Persian Gulf. Continuation of our express letter No.F # 209- N/40 dated 21st June 1940. 2. The post of Publicity Officer for the Persian Gulf sanctioned in the above mentioned letter is for the duration of the war. The issue of the above has been authorised. (Sd.) V.B. Arte, Under Secretary to the Government of India. hBO. (6*/ Political A/^ncy, Hahrain the 3i^ September, 1940. To, M«83re British Overseas Atn^ayfl Corporjition., B A •{ R A IN. Dear Sire, Captain Metcalfe f s address in Inditi will be s- Care of Postnaster, Na^in Bagh, Srina^r, Kashmir. 2. An exit permit for Captain retcalfe is enclosed. Yours faithfully, OAL Captain, for Political Anent, Bahrain.ERTIFICATE * CERTIFIED that Captain R.D.Metcalfe ie a Government sexvant. Captain, for Political Agent, Bahrain.ii No. 1674-1/44 Political Agency, Bahrain. 7th y«pt«nber 1940. To The Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf f Bushire. Me morandum * Reference your telegram No.T/273 dated 16th August 1940. 2. Captain R. D. Metcalfe handed over to Captain J. p. Howes on the 7th September 1940, in the afternoon arid proceeded on leave. 3. The relevant charge certificate is enclosed. 4. It is requested that the Accountant General| Central Revenues, New Delhi, may be informed accordingly Political ft.gent, Bahrain. k VIGOVERNMENT OF INDIA. Department. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). [N.B.— This is an ORIGINAL message sent by AIR MAIL which provides a meant of communication more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to he trexUed, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To sate t inie and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the ^signature oj ji responsible officer o f the Department.} No. 1884-1/44 Ba ^ a * Daled \xxioucA the7tb Ootober » I 940, 19 8 Tc// From To Captain J.3. Ho^08| ?o itical Officer, Trucial Coast, and Publicity Officer in the Persian Gulf. The Accountant General, Central Revenues f yew Delhi * SUBJECT I ~ SA.IAHY I took over the charge of the duties of the Publicity Officer in the Persian Gulf, on the 7th September 1940 in the afternoon in addition to the duties of the Political Officer, Trucial Coaet, and the relative charge certificate was forwarded to the Hon'ble the Political Hesidert in the Persian Gulf. 2. The salary certificate has not arrived so far. Grateful if it is oent to me by air mail, ji / Captain* i Captain. Political Officer, Trucial Coast and Publicity Officer, Pei^sian Gulf, Bahrain# Copy to i- The Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, with reference to this office Meraorandvcn Ko.1674-1/44 dated 7th September, 1940. . {Siynatwe) S. 44. M FP— 825S&amp;1'—(M -1070)—14-9 34—10,OC0. (Designation)■C/ TtUgrajiMc Address : AccotJNTa. All cotofnuftiCationa should be addressed to the Aoconntant General, Central Revenues. Lnolosures. From OFFICE OF THE ACCOUNTANT GENERAL CENTRAL REVENUES NEW DELHI. No. 0051-54-3120 dated the ft- OCT 1940 T HE ACCOUNTANT GENERAL, CENTRAL REVEN To Capt. R#D. Mcx-Cci-lX 0) Publicity Officer, Persian Gulf, Sir, ^ith reference to the acSvances of pay of Rs.800/- and of travelling allowance of Rs,1460/- (Total Rs.2260/-) grantea to you on the occasion of your transfer from Indore to Bahrain, I have the honour to state that the following au -justmonts have been atade against the advances in question:- I. Advance of pay:* Rs.633-4-0 2 instalment of Rs266-10-0 recovered from your pay bill for the period from 17.4,40 to 31.6.40 paid on 9.6.40. Rs.266-10-0 recovered from your pay bill for June 1940 paid in July 1940. Total amount recovered •• 799-14-0 A sum of R8.-/2/- is still remaining outstanding against you and may kinaly be refunded to Government from your next pay bill under intimation to this office. The advance of Travelling Allowance of Rs.1460/- was refunded in cash in full in June 1940. / have the honour to bt, Sir, ) our most obcdierU $ervant t 3d/- (J.L. Sinha) Asaistant Accounts Officer, Central Revenues.BY A'R J^AIU Telegraphic Address: A ccounts. All communications Bhould be addressed to the Accountant General, Central Revenues. Enclosures. OFFICE OF THE ACCOUNTANT GENERAL CENTRAL REVENUES NEW DELHI. No. GC66-65-vi36b dated the From T he ACCOUNTANT GENERAL, CENTRAL REVENUES, IP To Captain J.E. Howes, Political Officer, Trucial Coast, BAHRAIN, wjfo Sir, J M V /itn. reference to your express letter ^o # 1SS4-1/44, datea the 7th October 1940, 1 have tne honour to state that neither any charge certificate nor any oraers fixing your pay as Publicity Officer, Persian Gulf have so far been received, in the absence oi which this oflicc is not in a position to issue any pay slip in your favour. The Secretary ^ to the Hon'ble the Resident in the Persian Gulf is being re que sted to move in the matter to enaole this oil ice to issue the necessary authority in your favour. jr nil* *fir Jionour to hr. /'our most obedient •. vi . (J .L. Sinha) irai * . ov fcnueB.GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. Department. EXPRESS LETTER (AiR MA1L)» [N.B.—rAts is an ORIGINAL message sent hi/ AIR MAIL which provides a means of C (&gt;mmMntca/&lt;on more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It xt intended to bt treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To sare time and to obviate formalities it in drafted in the form of a telegram. It is uuthenhcated by the signature of a responsible officer o f the Department^ No. 2043-1/44 Dated Bahraim. XTOCX XXJ6X , j aBxaoacia 28th October, 1940. 19 From w T# Captain H«D* Metcalfe, I .A., Political Officer, Truclal Coast# The AccountaAt General, Central Revenues, New Delhi * I Reference correspondence ending with your letter No.GC66-66-3368 dated 16th October 1940 to Captain J.B. Howes, Political Officer, Truclal Coast* N«ith«r Captal * He««* nor I hav« as y«t received any pay and as a result are feeling financial difficulty* I therefore request tnat, provisional salary slips may kindly be issued as soon as possibls by Air Mall* The details are that I proceeded on three weeks leave on full average pay In India from September 2*k 20th to October 11th and was on the usual Joining time from September 7th - 19th and October 12th -23rd• During this period Captain Howes carried out the duties of Publicity Officer Persian Gulf In addition to his own* On 24th October In the forenoon I handed oyei uliarge uf the rv Ffiand took over from jh^: the office of Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Sharjah* My provisional salary slip may kindly be addres ed to Sharjah and Captain Howes* to Bahrain* Political Officer, Truclal Coast* {Signatwe) S. 44. MFP_8?5S&amp;P—(M-i070)—14-9 34—iO.OCO. [Designation)&lt; u^l Office of the Publicity Officer, Persian Gulf, bfchrfiin. 10th Novtmber 1940, Ce^tein J.B.Howes, Publicity Officer, Persian Guif, Bahrain. The Secretly to the Honourable The PoliticEl Resident in the Persien Guif, Busnire. I hrive the honour tc; rffer to my application for ler.va aent Muscat, and to af y thrt the Hcn f ble the Political Resident has informed ar in conversation thet he is not able tc rgree tc my taking ler-ve ex-In:if in the suniier of i k j4U. 2. He hrs, ha^vrr, rxprossei generrl t ^ruvel to^ tLkins: leave in Indi?., rrther th-n recess, b. I therefore request you to cossicer my appliesti for 5 months' leave in Austral it rs withdre^in; end to repfs' it by c months* iecve in Indi? with effect from May ist, i§; or dtte of avciliat,. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your ©est obedient servant. ■ Ci; tt Jtii• Publicity Officer,Persian Gu Copy to:- , \ ^The Political Agent, £ahrf?in f reference telegram N o .2l2 d^ted iOth August ij40.V, - • ■' *Telegraphic Address;- 'Gray' H The poiiticai Agent, Bahrein. (I ncorporated ik' E ngland) 17th November ^^40. Dear Sir, . . ^ ^ 'PHIPSOi^ 11 - 1U C/s liquor arrived, hereper s • s• 'Bc^rpeta' ^8^ on iy/5/4U. ^ We have to draw your kino, attention regarding your personal letter or guarantee on behali' or Captain Metcalfe on the 1st June 1940, covering the above shipment, which has not been released by you although its period of validity expired. v*e shall be glad, ir you will kindly arrange to release the same at your early convenience on product tion of ^ill of wading. Ltd., Agents Ch.Ill'jl —. J MUX 1 Telegraphic Address: A ccounts. All communications should be addressed to the Accountant General. Central Revenues. OFFICE OF THE ACCOUNTANT GENERAL CENTRAL REVENUES NEW DELHI. Enclosures. No. OC 51^54-3964* dated the 15th NoYenber 1940. From To :he accountant general, t central revenues, .ho Captein H. 0« Wetcalf«, I.A., Political Offlaar, Trucial 3 H A R J A 1!. Sir, witii rurerancfe to your exprstia latter No.2043-1/44, dated the 28th October 1940, I have the honour to obearre that the fact of your having proceeded on leave for 3 weeks vas not intirated to thia office preTioualy nor have any order* aanctiuning you laava so far been received. In the absence of xhe aaiie, tnifa office was not In a position to issue any Huthorlty for pnynent of leave salary. In this connsction it uay also be stated that no certificate for the admissibility of It-uve, as required under the rules was obtained by (YltrcZ you fron this office which has not been furnished direct to the Ooverment of India. 3* To enable this office to oa leu late the exact amount of leava anjoyad by you, it is requested that the date of your reaching » the fixed point vis., Karachi while on returning fron leava may pleasi be intimated. 3. Prior to your proceeding on leava you^r ware holding charge aa publicity Officer, Bahrain. In paragraph 3 of your letter it has however been stated that you took over charge, on return from leave, aa Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Sharjah. It is presumed that your headquarters have been changed from Bahrain to Sharjah. Ifcia may pleaaa be conflmed. It is preeumed that your pay will be disbursedI disbursed .• h.retofow by the Ag«rt. Bahrain to • copy of tho authority In raapaet of your laaw aalary «nd P'y will be issued* T have the honour to be. Sir* Your siost obsdisnt servant § g n e d* (J. L. Sinhe) Asaistent Accounts officer. . r. rr;.; 1940 t o. ' ■ - No. GC 51-54-3965, dated the Oopy forwarded to Captain J. B. HoWea, Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Bahrain, In continuation of this office letter N • GC55-85-3368, dated the 15th October 1940 for information. * c »rt ficnte ahowinK the date and hour of handing over charge o If the publicity Of^cer in the Persian Gulf is still awaited. In the absence of special orders fixing extra pay in resect of the period of his duty as Publicity Officer, Bahrain, it is not ; e0 arrange for the payment of any pay and allowances in his favour. (J. L. Sinha) Assistant Accounts Officer. % ^ ni-w ♦ - . 'r l ~Telegraphic Address : A ccounts. AH communications should be addressed to the Accountant General, Central Revenues. OFFICE OF THE ACCOUNTANT GENERAL CENTRAL REVENUES Enclosures. ISo. GC61-54-3978 NEW DELHI. dated the From To Sir, The ACCOUNTANT GENERAL, CENTRAL REVENUES, \1 Capt. R.D. M€tcalfe f Political Officer, Trucial Coast, SHARJAH (Persian Gulf). t.mu - With reference to your express letter No.2043-1/44, dated the 26th November 1940, I have the honour to authorise you to draw your joining time pay ana leave salary at the rates no tea be&amp;owi- A. Joining time pa.y 8.9 .1b40 to 19.9 .1940 (1) Pay ^Hs.1000/- p .m. (Rupees one thousand only) (2) Sterling overseas Pay £15/- p.m. (Pounds fifteen only) - Payable in England. B. Leave salary 20.9.1940 to 10.10.1940. ( Provisionally • pending receipt of the sanction to leave). (1) Leave salary @ fc.923/9/- p.m. (Rupees nine hundred aal twenty three and annas -/9/- only) • (2) Sterling portion of leave sal?ry @ £16/- (Pounds fifteen only) pay ble in England. The joining time pay from the period from 11th October 1940 to the 23rd October 1940 will be authorised on receipt of information regarding the date of your arrival at Karachi vftile returning fi om leave. C. From 24tri October 1940 on war as. Pay te.800/- p.m. Sterling Overseas Pay. £15/- per mensem. Payable in Englcnd. Special pay* &amp;.200/- p.m. H.R. allowance Hs. 100/- p.m. The.i( By Air Mail » ?io.2260-8/2 Political Agency, Hotbrain. 6th December f 1940 To ? essrs. Phipsc n ^ Co Vood Street, Karachi Des.r Sirs, In .ay last you shipped 10 cr sen liquor by s.s. Baipeta to ohe adciresa of Captain R.D. Metcalfe at Bahrain- lit the absence of Captain 1/a tea If e these cases were i»eleased by us on hi^ behalf on a letter of guarantee t-hat the shipping document would be produced by us within a reasonable tine. Captain i.etcalTe iias now informed me that he received no shipping documents from you. Vculd you please send me a bill of lading covering these ten cases to enable me to redeen the letter of (ruarantee. Yours faithfully, for Political /Vgont, %}irainTelegram I.W.C. From Political, Bahrain. To Accounts, New Delhi# No.336 Dated 9th December, 1940. J- ui Reference my Express Letter No.1884 dated 7th October* I request that salary slip may be expedited by air mai 1.BY Alrt MAIL. v The Political Agent, Bahrein, Dear Sir, est. 1883 4 WOOD STREET December, 40. a Ref.Yoar letter^No.2260-8/2 date d 5.12.1940. The Bill of Lading was posted to the address of Capt. R.B.Metcalfe on or about the 5th May 1940. We however enclose a copy of it to enable you to redeem the Letter of Guarantee. We shall be obliged if you will kindly inform us if Capt. Metcalfe is still at Bahrein. We are, Dear Sir, Yours faithfully, Per.Pro.Phipson &amp; Co.jl/bd,I^S No.2325-1/44 Political ^gency, Bahrain. 16th December, 1940• To Tessrs. Gray Mackenzie &amp; Co., Ltd., Bahrain. Dear Sirs, Please refer to your letter No.L/748 dated the 17th November, 1940. 2. I enclose herewith the Bill of Lading covering the 10 cases liquor ex s.s. 'Barpeta' 1 for Captain Metcalfe . ^ho letter of ^^uarantee should now be cancelled. Yours faithfully. for Political Agent, Bahrain. ■K/ (Copy of memorandum No.D,2034'S&amp;0 dated the 11th November 1940 from the Government of India in the External Affairs Department, New Delhi, to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf) SUBJECT: Publication in the Gazette o 4 ' India the dual charge of Gapt. J.B. Howes Reference your endorsement No,1260-79/76 dated the 12th October 1940. 2. Captain Howes, Political Officer, Trucial Coast was appointed to hold the charge of the post of Publicity Officer in the Persian Gulf J .n addition to his own duties consequent upon the grant of leave to Captain T'etcalfe for 3 weeks only. As it^is not customary to notify the appoinl ments of this kind which are for a period of less than one month, it is regretted that your proposal for the publica tion in the Gazette of India of the dual charge held by Captain Howes cannot be accepted. The grant of leave to Captain Metcalfe is however being notified. s No. IS'4- -79/76. British Consulate General, Bushire. Dated the/i^ December 1940. Copy forwarded for information to:- 1. Captain J.B.Hoves, Publicity Officer, Persian Gulf, Bahrain. 2, The Political Agent, Bahrain.Telegraphic Address: •Gray 1 eno 1-an o ) JrS v i Zl 't 1 BAHREIN, 17th December,^ 40, The Political Agent^ Bahrein. Dear ^ir • _ . ooo 10 G/s Liquor ex s .s.Barpeta dte f? i y With reference to your letter No. 2325-1/44 of 16th Instant, we would advise that the enclosed bill of lading is not a Original one,being Duplicate copy of shippers, a jfully signed original bill of lading ^required to enable us to return your letter of guarantee. Yours faithfully, For GRAY, MACKENZIE &amp; CO. ,Ltd. ^nclos : -1. agentsNo. 2369-1/44 Political Agency, Bahrain. 22nd December, 1940. /(/ To Messrs. Gray Tackenzie ^ Go. Ltd., Bahrain* Dear Sirs, y/f' ^ ^ Please refer to your letter No. 1/1092 V dated the 17th December, 1940. 2. The original copy of the 3ill of lading was posted by Messrs. Phipson &lt;5: Co., Karachi in I.feiy last to the address of Captain Metcalfe, but v the latter however has not received it so far. In the circumstances I trust that the duplicate copy, now obtained from the shippers, and forwarded herewith duly signed, will be accepted in lieu of the original. Yours faithfully, for Political Agent, ^hrain^ H; ■ Telegraphic Address:- XttCtKBfiX 1 Gray 1 L/1119 The Political A^ent, Bahre in. /I i»r engi-ano) BAHREIN, 24th Decembe^ 40 ^ear Sir, PHIP3CN KARACHI - 10 c/s Liquor ex s.s^Barpeta* 1 v. 288. * We thank you for your letter of ^2ndl instant enclosing shipper's copy of bill of lading covering the above cargo, 'e regret however this document is insufficient and w ould therefore be glad if you would sign the attached Letter of Guarantee form returning it to us, pending receipt of the Original Bill of Lading. Shipper's copy is enclosed herewith. yours faithfully, For GRAY, MACKENZIE &lt;Sc CO., Ltd., Enclos;-2. T/Ch. AgexxtsTo I he Captain and/or Agents and/or Owners of the S.S, w V ^ ^ ' / Gentlemen, V\e should be obliged by your granting delivery order to OVt\ t in reipect of the undermenlioneil goods without production of Bill of Lading, nnd in consideratiou ol your so doing we undertake lo pay on demand all Freight and'or General and Pai licular werage and/or charges whatsoever thereon, to indemnify you and each of you against all claims and/or demands uhich maybe mnde against you or any of yon in respect of the under- menlioned goods {ind to hold you harmless from any and all consequences that may arise by your granlini; such deliverv order *nd acting thereon, inciuding losses, damages, costs or any otlier expe nse which vou or any of you may sustain or incur by reason ol premises or in anyway relating thereto. We further undertake to hand you I^ill of Lading duly endorsed within two months from date of Ihis'guarantee : and further, ii any proceedings be instituted against you or any of you from lime to time in reaped of the said goods, whether by a holder of Hill of Lading or otherwise, we undertake to provide you witn snflicient funds to defend the same, and to meet any proved claims, and, if called ui on, undertake at anv time whilst the said goods are in our hands to deliver the same to you. We further undertake that the Underwriters of these goods shall be informed of this Indem- nity should a claim in respect ol these goods be made upon them. In all the undertakings and obli- &lt; ations hereunder we bind ourselves jointly and severally. K.P.B. .\larks and No3. Quantity and Contents Shipped by Port of Shipment Port of Discharge, t-OfV- y l ^ o / I i ( W—• s t-A'- V i IV ^ C \a ^ t Bill of Lading dated /r. i ^ u l )A i KD Snii 'PEhs OH Consignees. baKKKHS.Telegraphic Address:- 'mespers' ^r^mu/7y c, (Incorporated ix England) h/ 'ny BAHREIN, 30th DECEMBER^ 40. The Political Agent, _ , 1 Bahrein. '1 1 A A Dear Sir, PHIPSON - 10 c/s Liquor ex s.s .^Barpeta^V .288 KARACHI, ''/ With reference to our letter No of the 24^h instant, we shall be glad if you will send us shipper's copy of the Bill of Lading covering the above, returned to you under cover of our above letter • T^is Bill i-judxii^ will be accepted by us in lieu of the original Bill of Lading already lost intransit. Yours faithfully, For GRAY MAC &amp;C 0. ,Ltd. Agents 3/L No.24 dated 12-5-40 sent to fl/S Gray Mackenzie &amp; Co., Ltd., Bahrain under P.L. No.15-1/44 dated 4-1-41. A V/A'Telegraphic Address:- —M&amp;CMkRS' .Gray '/■ 1/ i ! ( I ncorpowateo W E nguano) f Bahrein. 6th January ^41 The Political Ji^ent, Bahre in# I ill Dear sir, 10 Gases Liquor per s .s .'Barpeta' V»282 « V/ith reference to our letter no-L/1134 of the 30th ultimo, we enclose herewith your Letter of Guarantee in respect of the above cases duly cancelled by us. Yours faithfully, y. yr *k No. Politic&amp;l Agency, Bahrein the 1st June 1940. To, Messrs Grey Mackenzie &amp;Co. Ltd., Bahrain. Dear Sirs, Ten cases liquor marked 'PHTPSON' arrived here per S.S.Barpete voyage 282 on 19th May 1940. These cases are meant for Captain Metcalfe and I should be grateful if you would issue a delivery order and send it to me per bearer. The bill of lading will be sent to you as soon as Captain Metcalfe arrj^es. Yours faithfully. fj nj / VV M y ^ Assistant Political Agent.No.242-E Grovernment of India External Affairs Department. New Delhi, the 6th January 1941. mimmm Captain J.B. Hoves, Political Officer, Trucial Coast, ^as appointed to officiate as Publicity Officer in the Persian Gulf, in addition to his own duties, with effect from the afternoon of the 7th September 1940 to the forenoon of the 24th October 1940. ( 0 d.) O.K. Caroe Secretary to the Government of India. Copy for information to: ^ The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the P- rsian Gulf The Accountant General, Central Revenues, Nas Delhi, with reference to their letter No.GCf:. r )-65-4636 dated # the 12th Decerber 1940. to Hon'ble the Political Resi- delrt^in the Persian Gulf. s By order, etc. (Sd.) Under Secretary to the Government of India. No. ^3 -79/76 Bushire, lb February 1941. % Copy for information to the Political Agent, Bahrain -No. -1/44. Political Agency, Bahrain. 22nd February, 1941. Copy for information to the Publicity Officer, Bahrain.7^ Te le gram From To No. / i' Dated the 15th March 1941. G.T.C. Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Officer, Trucial Coast, Sharjah. / / Please arriveairways Bahrain 28th March / ^ take over from Howes. Political.uojtl- floe of the Publicity Officer, Persian Gulf, Bahrain. lut Dated the April 104-1. 7« ^ r To, The Accountant General, Central Revenues, I'lov/ Delhi, lienor andura, I enclose here^'rlth the Last Pay Certificate of my predecessor, Captain J.B.Howes. He has requested that his leave salary be paid at the Bahrain Treasury. Ijjiy salary slip kindly be sent to my address by Air llall . as the sea imils are slcn? and irregular. Sd/- R.D.Metcalfe. Captain, Publicity Officer, Persian Gulf, Balirain. No. Of 1941. Dated the J/A April 1941. t (o^ Copy for\rarded with conpliinents to the Political Agent, Bahrain, for information and such action as nay be deemed necessary. Captain ^ Publicit^r Or/icer, Persian Gulf, Bahrain.• -' 7 C. A. C.-31B. (App. 8A, Rule 2, C. A. C.) last-pay certificate. Last-pay certificate of... Oerpt cin- J vB ;-Honre«^ 1 v ';•£; of Pnb-llclty'Officer* * In' 'the * •PerslBn- • 'Be^irGi-n proceeding on....i eaV e ^ 0 ** •India 2. He has been paid up to.. Hri(J .. 1 . Tlc . lTrs . ive .. (3 f ..gri. s t--Ma-reh--l-94'l at the following rates :— Particulars. Rate, Substantive Pay ^ 950-0-0 p.m. Special QiEcialing pay 178 200••0—0 p»i!i« jkicLinge-SompcnsatioiL Allowance ^ 150-0-0 p.m. Deductions. lT^i€»-^M4ef»^-^4r4w-*»ri&lt;i^-0rphan Fund ® ^ 25-12-0 per month. 3. He made over charge of the office of.Persian. B8-hp-&amp;in on the.. er noon of...^.th--April---1^4-l^ 4. Recoveries are to be made from the pay of the Government servant as detailed on the reverse. 6. He has been paid leave salary as detailed below. Deductions have been made as noted on the reverse. /-s Period. Rate. Amount. From to at Rs a month. From to at Rs a month. From to at Rs a month. 6. He is entitled to draw the following :— 7. He is also entitled to joining time for days. 8. The details of the income-tax recovered from him up to the date from the beginning of the current year are noted on the reverse. 0. [Signature) 10-4-1941 • {Designation) U Dated at Bahrain 19 . /C * * I' « , for Politrical Agent, Bahrain.k REVERSE. Details of recoveries. Nature of recovery. Amount Rs. To be recovered in instalments. From. From. From. .to. .to. .to. Deductions made from leave salary. on account of ..Rs. on account of Rs. i » on account of Rs. Names of months. April 19 May 19 June 19 - July 19 August 19 September 19 October 19 November 19 December 19 January 19 February 19 March 19 Pay. Gratuity, Fe,. Amount of Inoome- tax reoovored. R emarks. MF?—76 Audit—(M-l5i)—12-T-S8—40,000. L/^-&amp;v A a A. T. c.— 8-A. es OFFICE OF THE ^ &lt;? Cg Tc ^ &gt;'*c &lt;/€ &gt;L U No. &lt;yC5'A 6. /V OeXUc the 19 ^ ^ pu6/ic*.ty , pdsuca*. l /^ &amp; £ yculaju . is informed that under order No. -, dated (Grazette page ), # # 7 ^ vjl cw £J\JKJ i/vs X. C_i ) y ie is entitled to draw pay and allowances at the monthly rates shown below from the dates specified :— Details of calculation. £- From 7 4- From From From ^Substantive pay . . . Officiating pay Overseas pay Special pay .... 3scj / * oo 2vy[ fi i (*JA~0xC CU^, C C Total ci yLrvw- ) 3_--0 /X su-m^ The scale of pay is_ on may be drawn till the stage * Increment accrues every year and, in the absence of instructions to the contrary, this .is reached. (%«»&lt;»«) ( ' s * ) $ ' . [Designation) vl - c c hu^^ja fa / N ote 1 : It is particularly requested that this slip may be attached to the first pay bill drawn at these rates • Zt and that rso. may be entered as the audit number at the top of every pay bill. , N ote 2 : Deductions of fund subscriptions and recoveries of Government dues as noted in the last -pay ' certificate should be effected unless otherwise stated. * Here state the stage at which a pause or efficiency bar operates. No._SuLL-S4- 366- ; Copy forwarded to the Treasury Officer /I ^ /, / . for information. He should insert the details of pay given .above in any last-pay certificate issued by him in favour of this Government servant. [Signature) No.. [Designation) fa . Rent Officer Copy forwarded to the Executive Engineer Unit Accountant cjc* &lt;?■&lt;-«.'&gt; fc- &amp; for information. 'a MFP— 994 Audit— (M-1604)—14-10-39— 60,000. [Signature) [Designation)From - Tne Hobble thc'^SiAWftioal Resident In tn« Persian Gulf, Bushlre# To - Tn« Secretary to tne Gorernaent of Indie, ax tern*1 Afrelrs Oep«rtmentt Simla. Menorandua So. fJS -7«/76, ) Baa hi re, tne May, 1^41. ) SUBJECTi- ^ublioity Ofrioer. irereian Gull', Heference Memorandua llo«D«3474*S/40, dated tne 24th Marcn, 1941, from tne (JoYernrncnt oi Indie in tne i^xterml Affaire Deyfrtraent. 2. Captain J.B* Howes, Publicity Officer, Persian Oulf, nanded over onarge of nie duties to Captain K.i). Metoalfe and proceeded on leave on average pay tor two and a naif montns witn eftect from tne 7tii April, 1941. The relative charge certificate and draft Oasette notifications ere enclosed* for Poll Kesident in tne Persian Gulf. Copy to : iXh^Accountant-Generel, Central Revenues, Uew Delhi. with copy of draft notification. It is presumed that Captain Howes is entitled to the leave granted to him. 2.The Publicity Officer, Persian Gulf, Bahrain, with reference to his endorsement No,l60. dated the 7th April, 1941.i I . Diuyr G^^ETTE MOTiyiOAXlOS 1. Captain J.B. Howes, of the Indian Political Serrice was granted lepre on prerpge pay for two end a half months with effect from tne 7th April, 1941. 2 # Captain H.D. Metcalfe, of the Indian Political Service has been appointed as Publicity Officer, Persian Oulf, Bahrain, with effect from the 7tn April, ly41. n~No. ^35 The Secretary to the Hon' presents his compliments to olitical Resident in the Persian Gulf Captain R.D, Metcalfe, Publicity Officer, Persian Gulf, Bahrain. and is directed to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document^ for guidance with reference to paragraph 2 of the Accountant Ueneral, Central Revenues, iiew Delhi, Letter lio.GC51-54-4^, dated the 7th April, 1941. British Residency and Consulate-Greneral, BUSHIRB. Dated. M . Ma y».. I 9 . 4 . 1 r. Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Demi-Official Letter dated the 7th April, ly41, from Captain A .C. Stewart, Secretary to the hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire to C.J. Pelly, Esquire, I.C.S., c/o The Political Agent, Bahrain. ilAL IT9&gt; COPY. Bushire, the 7th April, 1941, * Dear Pelly, Colonel Prior desires me to remind you that if you draw pay while you are in India^on the language course)you will be liable to payment of Indian Income tax. In order to avoid this he suggests that you arrange to draw it from wherever you draw it now and have it sent by Supply Bill to India, Yours sincerely, Sd, A.C. Stewart, C.J, Pelly, Esquire, I,C.S,, c/o The Political Agent, Bahrain.CONFIDENTIAL. H No. C /214 of 1941. The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to The Political Agent Bahrain. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment British Consulate-General, BIT SHIRE. Dated...2 .4 th..June.. Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Telegram No» T/2C1, dated 24,6.41 from Political Kesiden' at Bahrain to Resident Kaehmir Srinagar. Captain Howes. (jji f „ £ f fTtlagraa I.W.C. Trom Political Resident at Bahrain. 0 Reaident Kaehmir, Urinagar* Ho. T/X99, I w Dated 24th June 1941. W / Your tolaisraffl No* i64 June 22nd* PoXiowlng lor Howeu begins* on expiry of your leave you should return to iiahrsin temporarily as Jhiblioity Olficer. I am informing Foreign to whom you ehould apply for priority air pa^isage* - ESS IBS ITT PERSIA* GULF - 24 /6#Telegram Q. From Political Resident, Bushire To Political Agent, Bahrain. No. 686 Dated and received the 19th June 1941. Metcalfe may proceed on leave forthwith. He must be back by August 15th at latest. f-v Qi. -'h' . TSf, ^Telegram I•W•C. From Resident, Kashmir. To Political Agent, Bahrain. No. 194. Dated and received the 4th July 1941. Howes arriving by air July 13th. Resident Kashmir. //f i t j ?' t Copy sent to 1. The Hon'ble the Political Resident, CaJ^ 'Bahrain, 2. The Publicity Officer, Bahrain, under endtt: Nos: 1269-1/44 and 1270-1/44 datc^d 5th July 1941 respectively.A. T. C.—8.A. OFFICE OF THE r ^ ' D i ^ AJ Jir».4*^57-f5&gt;^77 / SUi%*J^ .tk, A* a 'Le 0 fl 41. i e'. ■. -r/*.££ ■... . .■ K. tc^ fi -j). f ' t-Cppl- j-?,. J. &gt;4. / ^tz ^ /k? (P-c^^i. -*/&lt;&gt; (f h &amp; a is informed that under order No. , dated (Gazette I^ge ), he is entitled to draw pay and allowances at the monthly rates shown below from the dates specified :— Details of calculation. Substantive pay Officiating pay ^Overseas pay •-» Special pay . ........ Total From 8 so £ xoo i 50 o 5' The scale of pay is ' * * ^ From From h~l~ From ^ i r I : lot-l/nl logo t 0 so £2s to^njjif. £ 'xo/'o/ i l, t ' l I A 6 V«^ t kj^jnuuu. eLr.-d^- &gt; u iTVu, on every vear and, in the absence of instructions to the contrary, this may be drawn till the stage *, .is reached. {Signatvre) (Designation)fot.'Z ■ N ote 1 :—It is particularly requested that this slip may be attached to the first pay bill drawn at these rates aud that No._ __ .niay bo entered as the audit number at the top of every pay bill. N ote 2 :—Deductions of fund subscriptions and recoveries of Government dues as noted in the last-pay certificate should be effected unless otherwise stated. •Jlere sj^te the stage at which a pause or efficiency bar operates. Copy forwarded to the T-goft&amp;wy^- Officer for information. He should insert the details of pay given above in any last-pay certificate issued by him in favour of this Government servant. {Signature) {Designation) gpji • j ' ^ a-a- No f A A, . Rent Officer ^ 6-^y h ■' ffy C Copy forwarded to the Exe cutive Engineer Unit Aocountant .for information. {Signature) {Designation) MFP—994 Audit—(M-1604)—14-10-39—(30,000.Telegraphic Address : Accounts. All communioations should be addressed to the Accountant General, Central Revenues. B Y AIR MAIL. OFFICE OF THE ACCOUNTANT GENERAL . , CENTRAL REVENUES new delhi. (1nd1a) No. OG 55-65-2285» dated the 24th J u 1 y&gt; 1941* Enclosures. 'h rBOH v To TFF ACCOUNTANT GENKRAL, r;-: CENTRAL RF.VKNUJ'S (japtain J. B. How«fl, Publicity Officar, Persian Gulf 9 B a h r a i n. Sir, With reference to your Memorandum No,305-Per, dated the 14th Jtily 1941, I have the honour to requeet you kindly to intinfite the actual date of your arrival at the specified station viz., Karachi while returning from leave to enable this office to determine the period of joining tia© admissi ble to you and issue authority for payment of your joining time pny. Tou are, however, entitled to draw at the following monthly rates from 14th JUly 1941 subject to usual deductions Pay • • ^5# 950/— Sterling Overseas Pay. £ 25/- payable in England. g|»cial pay •••• Rs* 200/- House rent allowance. Rs« 150/- mal Rs .1,300/- ♦ £25/- I have the honour to be. Sir, Your meet obedient servant. Signed. -&gt; . V (S, n, Bhattachr rya) ASSISTANT ACCCDNTS OTTTCKR. e • e No. GC 55-65-2286, dated the 24th July 1941. Copy forwarded to the Political Agent, Bahrain, for information and necessary action. (s. h. BHATTACHARYYA A ssistant Aoccum o?ticbi«No.1521-1/44 Political Aganoy, nahmln th« 6th August, 1941. From. To Sir, Th« Political A ^ent, Bah^^ain. The Aeooimtant-Gc'ii^ml Central R«venu«s, New Delhi* h 0*1 I have the honour to refer to your endorsement No.QC-55-65 -2286 dated the 34th July, ^941, and to inform you that Captain J.H.Howes, Publicity Officer in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain, hae in a bill dated the let Auguet, 1941 f (Vr.No* 5 for August, 1941) drawn the following amounts from this Treasury under his own orders as controlling officer Leave salary from 1-7-41 to 6 -7-41 Joining tim« pay from 7-7 -41 to 13- r7 -41 pay from 14-7-41 to 31-7-41 language pay from 26-10-40 to 6 -4-41 and 14-7-41 to 31-7 -41 @ iu*150/- p.m« House rent from 14-7-41 to 31-7-41 @ itt»160/- p.ili* ..•236- 3-0 •259-11-0 Si .667-12-0 is.1388-11-0 as# 37- 1-0 Total [U.^G39- 6-0 I have the horour tc be, Glr, Your moat obedient seivantj for Political Agent, Bahrain. Copy to the Publicity Officer in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain, for information*GKRTIPIKD tiiat Captain J.B* Howes, of the Indian Political Service, atationed in the Persian Gulf aince i93b haa now been transferred f»nd is returning to India permanently. His cojivszta solely of his personal affects which are for hie own use anu not for sale# W\ .for Political .^ent, BBhr£»in»Telegram S. From Captain Howes, Bahrain. To Political, Muscat. No. 286 Dated the loth August 1941. Expect to arrive Tuscat pbout August 22nd. by S.3. 'Suiyang 11 . Political -Metcalfe expected to leave by air for Bahrain on August 18th. - Alban -t, Telegraphic Address : A ccoukts. All communications should be addressed to the Accountant General, Central Revenues. Enoloaures. Frfrn OFFICE OF THE ACCOUNTANT GENERAL CENTRAL REVENUES new delhi. A T o. GC 56-65-2746 dated the To The Accountant General, Central Revenues. Cap t • J' • B • Howes ^ Publicity Officer, Persian Gulf, Bahrain. 5ir, ft Q In continuation of this office endors^nent No.GC 56-65-2657, dated the 13th August 1941, I have the honour to enclose a copy of letter ^0.1521-1/44, dated the 6th August 1941 from the Political Agent, Bahrain which shows that you have already drawn difference of leave-salary and Joining time pay from the Bahrain Agency without waiting for authorities from this office asked for in your letters No.340-Per and 353-Per, dated the 31st tJuly 1941 and 5th August 1941 respective ly. The sum of Hs. 1388-11-0, mentioned in the Political Agent, Bahrain letter, quoted above, represents language pay &amp; Rs.150/- p.m. for the entire period from 24th October 1940 to 31st July 1941 and not for the periods shown therein. Accordingly, you have drawn L r leave-salary for the period of your leave from 22nd * V, ^ April 1941 to 6th July 1941 &amp; Rs.1376/9/- (Rs.1226/9/- previously authorised plus Rs.150/- now drawn) p.m. as the revised rate of your leave-salaiy comes to Rs.1291/4/- (after taking into account the language pay) the amount overdrawn &amp; Rs.84/6/- p.m. for the period of your leave may kindly be refunded to Government by deduction from the net amount of your next pay bill underintimation to this office. 2. The circumstances in which language pay, joining time pay and the difference of leave-salary were drawn without any authority from this office may kindly be stated. In this connection a reference is invited to article 61| Civil Account Code, Volume I. 3. It is not understood how in your letters, quoted in paragraph 1 above, you have asked for authorities for payment of (1) the difference of leave salary and C2) your joining time pay at Muscat and at the same time drawn them from the Bahrain Agency. This may kindly be elucidated 4. Pending receipt of reply to a reference made to the Government of India, JelxtBEnal Affairs Department, you are provisionally authorised to draw language pay @ Rs.lSO/- CHupees one hundred and fifty) p.m. with effect from 1st August 1941 in addition to the emoluments mentioned in this office letter ^o.GC 66-65-2285, dated the 24th July 1941. V 'h / thp hrntur t 9 l 9t y /Sir. Sd.(P.K. Bose) 4 0 Br Copy forwarded to the Political agent, Bahrain, No.GC 55-65-2746, dated the for information and necessary action in continuation of this office endorsement No.GC 55-65-2286, dated the 24th duly 1941. t\s regards his letter, quoted above, it is not understood why the procedure laid down in iirticle 51 Civil account Code, Volume I was not followed. - ^ -'TV.r? vmw wm M.I.M.i Political Agency, Bahrain- 30th August, 1941• The Political Agent, Bahrain- The Accountant General,Central Revenues, New Delhi. I have the honour to refer to your endorsenent No-GC 55-66-2746 dated the 19th Augustj 1941, and to infonn you that Captain J.B. Howes has since been transferred to Muscat. It is requested therefore that the Political Agent, Muscat, may be instructed to effect the necessary recoveries- I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant, for Political Agent, Bahrain--2- / t- Telegraphic Address : A ccounts. All communioations should be addreaaed to the Accountant General, Central Revenues. Encloauree. \ i OFFICE OF THE ACCOUNTANT GENERAL -j ^4? CENTRAL REVENUES V*/ No. Gc51-54-3083 new prom To doled The Accountant General, Central Revenues, Sir, Oapt.R,D f Metcalfe, Publicity Officer, Persian Oulf, Bahrain ^ Hith reference to your letter No.39^-Per, dated the 24th August 1941, T have the honoir to authorise ^ou to drai« vour pay a .i ailovances at the rates bidicatea beloiip:- your pay (1) From the 5th August 1941 to the 19th August 1^41; .Toinlng timii nay ^ Rs. 1050/- per mensem (Purees ont thousand and fi tyj only-f-£25/- payable in England - (Pounds Twenty five; only, (2) From the 2Qth August 1941 onwards , !• Pay ^ Ha.SSO/- per men sen (Ruptes eight hundred and fifty) only. II* Special P&amp;y d Rs.200/- per mensem (Rupees Two hundred) only. r TI« f5terling oversea pay Q £25/- per mensem (Pounds Twenty five) only - payable in £1gland. IV« House rent allowance of Hs. 150/- per - mtsisem (Rupees One hundred ani fifty^ only - subiect to the production of usual certifi jate* fcions. The above payments are suojtct 10 usual deduc- 2. As regards your claim for thehouse rent allow ance (vide para 2 of your letter under reply; during the neriol of your leave, your attention is invited to Auditor General's decision below Supplementary Rule 6.A- ^undame tal Rule and Supplementary Rules 7oluni [-. As the certificate of your returning, on the expiry of the leave, to the sane post from whicn you proceeded on leave was not emoodied in the Governmeut of India Notification No.l05-S dated the 9th Tuly 1941, your claim for the Sime does not appear to be admissible. 3. As regards yuur letter No.390-Per dated the 23rd August 1941 it may be stated that as per records of this of ice you art entitled to sterling overseas pay and leave-salary as indicated belo^;-y ofEYcA^MM^ ,,/# Do tr.-j-. r. - .3 ct \ '«✓ 1 ~'lxL* 'y U (jsntr Msw De-lhi No. From T! GC56-66-3116 Dated th The Aocountc.nt General Central Jtevenues „ ro a Capt* J.B. Howes y l*A* f Political Agent and His Britannic Majeety'e Consul, yVSCnT. Sir ' xn continuation of this office express letter QC66-66-2818, dated the 21st August 1941, returning the Charge Certificate for completion, 1 have the honour to state tiiat the sajse has not yet heen r€ctiy€« toacK duo, thixj kindly be expeoited to enable this office to 1*6^% necessary authority in your favour. In the meantime you may provisionally draw from the date of your taking over charge as Political Agentt Muscat, your pay and allowances at the following rate, less usual fiaarl, deductionsi- Substantive pey. •••••••*• • fecial ^ay - Language pay. . Iw'oTvw Charge allowance. •••••••• Sumptuary allowance. ••••••• ^•1^0/' Authority for the arrears of pay and allowances cue to you will bs issued on receipt back of CI) your Charge Certificate (2) the details of your journey from Bahrain to Muscat (which may kindly be furnished) and Ce3) your last pay certificate from the Political A^ent, Bahruin. X have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant. 5d/ ' (J.L. Sinha) Assistant Accounts Officer • P.T.O z^ J Hi s 4 ;upt ». a A. C.) LAST-PAY CERTIFICATE. La8*-p»y certificate of—Gap-uaijX ofthe...Jettblicitar...0fflee».±Q.tlie..Rer3iaa.fta^.r«.xal» proceeding on... .'tTBOSf 93^........ to.. .P.cOlUcal- Agancy^.. :4iscat ' 2 He has been paid np to..a^.4nol^?4.^3-.o^-.3i&amp; , t-JuILy r '^S«43' at the following rates :— Particulars. Rate . ^ r 950-0-0 PJU Substantive ray ?», oQ0-0-0 rf Special pay * r- 150-0-0 « Laaaguage pay ^ xscix^ « House Rent allowance ♦' Captain J # b. Howes has &lt;3rQ.\m lancuage paj 7 * fron s4-10-4u go .. .aU7^4Q. &amp;15Q/—P^aa^—- i, \ Deductions, \ .Military..• and• •.Orphan ^nd @ Ps26A-/- P»n» deducted for tlip month of July^ 1941» | 3. He made over charge of the office of.*&lt;&amp;ff£t7cr'trt*iiW'5*'jJ l u 1 Itfl'QjftPf I \ on the..foy «-..noon of ...i4tlr -f«gttStrf i94t 4. Eecoveries are to be made from the pay of the Government servant as detailed on the reverse. 5, He has been paid leave ealary as detailed below. Deductions have been made as noted on ^ reverse. Bate. Amount. Period. to at Rs. From at Rs, From «.^...at Rs. ....at Rs a month. 6. He is entitled to draw the following He is also entitled to joining time for days. 8. The details of the income-tax recovered from him up to thfe date from the beginning of the current year are noted on the reverse. {Signature) n f &lt;,Jnf 15th Sep teller, 1941. for Political Agent, Bnhraiiu Dated a t ^ [Designation) P«T#0.No 1805-1/44 The Political Agent, Bahrain, Proseots his compliments to ;— The Political Agent &amp; H«B. TTf s Consul^ Muscat. and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document ( s) &lt;/ '/ The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf Dated 18th Sept mber f 1941 Keference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure Name and Date. Subject Last Pay Gertif icate of Gapta In J.B. Howes, l.P.SNo, 0.0.45-1/44 of 1942 The Political Agent, dilirain, Praseots his complirosnts to ;— Captain H.l.Metcalfe, Under Secretary to the Resident, Eastern States, CALClfrT^ and has the hmoiir to send hitn a copy .of the und»rm3ntioneJ document ( s ) m original, The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf Dated Jb21h-^an ua ry, 1^4 9- . Kefcrence to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure Marne and Date. Subject I Bill No.230/30 from Abdul * oor M.Bastaki, Bahrain, for Rs.39/-■ Telegraphic Address : Accounts. All commuaioations should be addressed to the Accountant General, Central Revenues. aY MR MAIL. ho OFFICE OF THE ACCOUNTANT GENERAL CENTRAL REVENUES NEW DELHI. iVo.GC. 51-54- 7185 1^. dated the ! ■' ' AC 'i ^ i i WXfisT 1. Copy forwarded to the Political ^gent, -^ahrciin in continuation of this otflice endorsement NooGC.61-64-6627 dated the 19th Jjeceni- bee 1941 with the request that Captain Metcalfes charge certi ficate and last pay certificate may kindly be furnished at a very early date* Enclosures. (E. ROYCHC.VDHURY) Assistant accounts Officer. Copy of Express letter NooGA, III /S427 dated the 16th January 1942 from the Accountant ^eneral, Bengal, to the Accountant General, Central Revenues, ^ew ^elhi ^apt£^.n .^etcalfe, late publicity Officer, Bahrain, assumed ci^rge of tfee office of the Under Secretary to the Resident for the Sastern states on the afternoon of the 6th January 1942, The countersigned last pay certificate and the following transfer documents of the officer may kindly be furnished to this off dee immediately to enable this ollice to aithoris e the payment of the officer's pay and allowances:- (1) service statement. (2) ^ain and subsidiary leave accounts, (3) average pay leave account, (4) his passage accounts* -'•he date of his increment in the Indian Political servie may also kindly be stated. 1/[A* ^J t BY AIR MIT.. I No. 5x-j. 1/44 The Political Ageat, Baliraia, Praseats his compliments to :— The Accountant General, Central Revenues, New D e 1 h 1. each and has the hwiojr to send him a copy the utidirmentioned document ( s ) The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf Dated 24th February, 1942 Kaference to previous correspondence His Endorsement No.GC.51-54-7185 dated the 20th 4 Description of Enclosure anuary, 1942 Mame and Date. Subject 1. Last Pay Certificate of Captain R. D. Metcalfe, I.A. 2. Charge Certificate of Captain R. D. Metcalfe, I.A., ///Cop y v Copy of letter No.GC. 51-54-?^ of 14th February, 1942 from the Accountant General, Central Revenieb, New Delhi♦ to the Political Agent, Bahra in. ^ i..poJed ^f o r 0\ f i 17/44 I have the honour to invite a reference (to this Office endor&amp;ement ^To. ^C. 51-54- r7 1^5, lated (20th January, 1942, forwarding a copy of the ^ ^ (Accountant General, n cngal expre^e et t er . ile /3427. dated the ISth . T 8nuary,l 0 42 anJ to :-equebt you kindly to furnieh the charge certificate and .he (last nay certificate of the officer at en early date. 2. In thU connection this Office erdorbemente S8th January,1941, G.C.51-54-l?tB at tent Ion it No.GC51-54-^406, invited to dated the dated 15th Tune r 28th January, 1941, G.C. 51-^4-l^.b, aaxea lotn t uuc /ZjtJ\ i ic/lJ iq4i a9 T Ri-fi4-iefeP T -eip^e^-3'^th-^.Re-i a 4i , 0C.5154- - y// , 41?0 , dated 25th September 1941 and c.C 51-54-tB4? t*a /V f- iv w] dated ?rd January,1942. Replies to the oh^eotione communicated to the Officer 'copies endorsed to you; as above) from time to time have not yet been received. It is therefore requested that you will kindly take steps to furnish necessary replies those objections as the officer has since been transferred under the audit control of the Accountant General, Bengal. It may also be stated if the amo i in + ^ T?e.e/ P /- and Rs.lC/l2/- have since been recovered from the officer. The favour of a very early reply is requested.Will th« GoT«rniwBt of India in the Vjcimrml Affair® DapKrtment kindly refer to their L'onortinduB No* D*4261«*H/4X 9 dated the 13th bept«aber 9 1941 regarding the appointuont of Ifr* Bertram Thomae ae Publloity Officer for the Persian Oulf? a. Zt has been stated in sub-paragraph (b) of Kis Kajssty^s Secretary of 1 . » * ^ • State for India telegran No .loaST, dated the Tth Ba|it«iber 9 1941 that the '« ' * • Tjoeal Allosanoe of £600 por annum shich is to be paid looally is recover- able from the Ministry of Infomation through usual channel® at quarterly intervale beginning from December 31st 9 1941* 3. The o^urgee on account of the Publicity arrangewent in the Persian Oulf as contcnplatsd in the Qo^M'naient of Indiat External affaire Depart* ■ant Kxprese letter Ho. F.209^/40, dated the 10th L&gt;ept&lt;fBbcr 9 1940 are being debited entirely to Hie liajeety^ OoTernaant through the oonthly accounts as they arise from nonth to nonth* 4* It is thus preeumed that the charges on account of ths ubllcity arrangeiaente In the Persian CKilf will continue to be debited to His Kajsety's OovermoBnt as has been done hitherto* In vieVf however 9 of the Instructions oontaxnsd in sub-paragraph (b) of His Isajesty^e secretary of Ctate for India telegraa referred to abowe 9 a doubt has arisen whether the charges 9 in (|uestlon 9 will, in the first lnstancs 9 be debited to the Indian Budget and then recovered quarterly from the Ministry of Inforaation* Ths position raay 9 therefore 9 kindly be elucidated* Sd/- B. Roy Chowdhury. OcTt* of India. Departaent U^Q, A OCR UC \o. JC 09 i 9 date J the No* 00 55-155-7694. Dated the Copy forwarded to the Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Kesldent in the Persian Oulf f Bushire for infomatlon* Ths pay slip in favour of Mr. Bertram Thomas, Publicity Officer, Pereian Oulf, Bushire has not bsen Issued so far as no charge certificate of the officer hae been received* If a pay elip has to bs leeued in favour of the officer in respect of the Local Allowance of £600/- per annum, he may kindly be aeked to expedite I, !nn.a .«nm; 1 . ''''iwiM*' i' 1hie charge certificate at an early date* ifl /u.*7t tr*- No. GC 55-155-7695. Dated the &amp;d/» (B. Roy Chowdhyry) Assistant Account■ Officer* b- 0 Copy, together with a copy of the endorsement, forwarded to the Political Agent, Bahaain, for information and nscessary action* I 1. (B* Roy Chowdhury) Assistant Account* Officer* •i W r//(/ EXPRESS - LETTER* No.441-1/44 From - Political Agent^ Bahrain* To - The Accountant General f Central Revenues, New Delhi Dated 11th March, 1942. Please refer to your endorsement No.GC 66-166-7696 dated the 18th February, 1942. The requisite information was given under this Agency Printed Letter No.327-1/44 dated the 24th February, 1942. for Political Agent, Bahrain.Teleg/dphic Address : Accounts. All communications should be addressed to the Accountant General, Central Revenues. OFFICE OF THE ACCOUNTANT GENERAL Os From CENTRAL REVENUES NEW DELHI. A ' 0 GC56-156-8181. &lt;s&gt; # /1 dated the 'i/js The ACCOUNTANT GENERAL, CENTRAL REVENUES, ^ Enclosures. 3-1 ^ To ! ( Bertram Thomas, £3qr. f Public Helatlons Officer y Persian Quiff Bahrain. sir, p\^ 'z/lth refer once to Po; h Jtical Agentf BaliTi ln eiUlordGCient ho.327~l/44 dated 24# 2.42 forv»arding your charge certificate! I have the honour tc- atate that the date on vwliich yea cseinkoft charge of tl^e poet of the Publicit Officer, poreian &amp;jM t Bahrain has been ehown therein as 10th D«c«hber 1941 (forenoon). Aei no;%'ever, Captain R.B.Metcalfe from wh«m you took charge has been paid upto 10th December lt&gt;41( after noon J and ae the Qovernmbnt of India, SXternal Affairs D^partinent have notifiadCempioyment in the above post ^i-wx effect iroui the forenoon of the lith December 1943 j you 4»re hereby authorised to draw your lecal allowance Q £60/- p.m. with effect from the above date i.e., 11th December 1&amp;41. The#•••/// No. 70. To, Sir, Office of the Public Relations Officer Persian Gulf, Bahrain. Dated the 25th.March 1942. (3? 'The Accountant General, Central Revenues, New Delhi. PERS^ With reference to your GC66-155-8181 dated the 13th March 1942. I have the honour to state that by the terms of my appointment my allowances of £50/- per month date from the day following my arrival In Bahrain, and not from the day Captain Metcalfe handed over. An express ruling governing this charge, which Is entirely debltable to His Majesty's Government, is laid down in Ministry of Information letter E2427 dated 7th August, London. This states expliclty as follows 'While holding this appointment you will receive salary at the rate of £900/- a year, payable monthly, with effect from the date of your embarkation, together with a local allowance of £600/- a year, payable from the day following your arrival in Bahraln n . I arrived in Bahrain on 4th December. My allowances of £50/- per mensem are therefore due to me as from 5th December 1941. Will you kindly acknowledge. I have the honour to be Sir, Your obedient servant 0 ^0^ Public Relations Officer Copy to Political Agent, Bahrain for information.No• 72. Office of the Public Relations Officer Persian Gulf, Bahrain. ^ Dated the 25th March 1942. 6^ To, Asslstant Accounts Officer, Government of India, New Delhi. Sir, Reference your GC55-155-7696 dated 18th February regarding the accounting of allowances due to me as Public Relations Officer in the Persian Gulf. 2. I have no last pay slip to send as my appointment as Public Relations Officer was the first appointment held by me under the Ministry of Information: 3. A charge certificate was sent by Political Agent, Bahrain No.327 dated 24th February, but this has no bearing on the date of my local allowances vide my reply No.70 dated 25th March to your GC55-155-8181 dated 13th March. 4. The sum of £50/- monthly to be drawn locally has been found inadequate and I have cabled I'lnlstry of Information to increase this to £75/-. 7 Public Relations Officer Persian Gulf, Bahrain. Copy to Political Agent, Bahrain for information.J- ' ^ l/£ Office of the Accountant ^ Central Revenuod New DeLbli f'OJ.55-155-83914/ From To jtn ' &gt;&amp;tx*uiit«nt ^ucral r Central Revenues, Sir, Bertram Thomast Ssauire, O.B.S., Public Relations Officer, •&gt;* Persian Gulf, Bahrain. In continuation of this office letter No.GC.55-156-8181, dkted the i3th # liarch 1942, I have the honour to state that it now transpires from your pay bill for December 1941 that you arrived at Bahrain on the oth December 1941 # Under the orders contained in the Secretary of State for India telegram No.10587,dated 7tb Septemoer 1941 you are entitled to draw the Local allowance Q aoO/- D.m. with effect from the day following your arrival at Bahrain i.e. from 6th December 1941. Authority for payment of the ^ocal * allowance issued as per this office letter cited above may, therefore, be treated as modified to that extent. rtVCAL Ai RECEIPT -6'ir, jst ooxidittu vtnte ' —.^-O^fiKHoychowdhury) ^ No. X • 55-155-8^2. dated Copy forwarded to the Political Agent Bahrain in contiirjation of tiiis office endorse lent,•,,.Will tto« Governrcftrvt of India in the External affairs Department kindly refer to this office U «0« note ^o«QC6&amp;- 15o-7693 dated^the 19th February 1942 regarding adjuetment of the oharfiefixaccount of the poet of the PubliciV Officer, Persian Qulf, Bahrain. 2. The sanction for the exteneion of the poet in question is due to expire on 26th February 1948 vide Government of India, External Affaire Department letter Ko«r«8(90}-K/40 dated the 29th November 1940. Necessary sanction for the same beyond 28th Fetruary 1942, if since accorded, may kindly be furnished to this office at an early date for neceseary action. • map, 1942 Office of the Accountant General Central Revenues New Delhi. No.GC66-166-7916. Dated the Copy forwarded to the Secretary to Hobble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bush ire in conti nuation of this office endorsement No,GC55-155-7694 dated the 19th February 1942 for Information and necessary action. Sd/~ (B.Roychowdhury), Assistant Accounts Officer, _ Central Revenues # \ ^ * ■ N0.GC56-156-7917, dated the Copy together with a copy of the endorsement forwarded for information and necessary action to the Political Agent, Bahrain. (Bifeoychowdhury /, Assistant Accounts Officer, Central Revenaes. f/UJ- '7% .Telegraphic Address; Accounts. All communications should be addressed to the Accountant General, Central Revenues, OFFICE OF THE ACCOUNTANT GENERAL CENTRAL REVENUES NEW DELHI. M).ac.ai-64p07i8. dated the From A ♦v The ACCOUNTA^f'GENERAL, CENTRAL REVENUES, ■ Enclosures. t To Qu Hl^i Coaniasioner for Iaiia 9 Aooounta Department, India House* Aldwych, London, W.C.2. r Sub- Capt: 3«D.llotoalfe, I«A« 9 Sir, In continuation of thin office letter No* GC • 51-54-3081,dated the 12tb September 1941 and with reference to the Accountant General, Bengal letter No. r U-III/^604,dated the 5th February 1942 1 have the honour to period 1941 to 10th December 1941 only. ' I4r hon * t' t&gt; r**, if ;d/- (B.Hoyohowdhury) &gt;&lt;• O p. :-oNo. 71/2.-1/44 Political Agency, D. KA, Bahrain. 22na April, 1942. ^' The A.G.C.R,, New Delhi. ^ ^ ' Sir, W I have the honour to refer to your endorsement No .GC. 51-54-8720 of the 51.3.1942 and to invite y a reference to this Office letter No. 550-4/2 of 2b. 5.42 which replied to your letter No.GC 51-52-7632 of 14.2.1942. rJ. M - 2, Your preeumption with regard to the date of handing over of Captain R.D.Metcalfe is correct. . ^ , I have etc. 4 for Political Agent, Bahrain./a 'X Office of the Accountant General, Central Revenues, 0055-165-577. New Delhi. No- dated the From The Accountant General, Central Revenues, To Bertram Thomas, Eeqr., PJublic Relations Officer, Persian Gulf, Bahrain. Sir, With reference to your letter No.82 dated the 1st April 1942 and in continuation of this office letter Ko. cio,'£•£g. the ^th April 1942* I have the honour to authorise you to draw £ 60/- p # m. (Pounds fifty) only from 6th December 1941 to 30th April 1942 - less amount already drawn. Authority issued in your favour as per this office letter No.OC66-166-8181 dated the 13th April 1942 and since modified as per this office letter N0.QC66- 166-8391, dated the 21st March 1942 may kindly be treated as cancelled. 2 # The Ministry of Information has since increased the local allowance payable to you from £ 60/- to £ 76/- with effect from the end of April 1942. You are, therefore hereby authorised to draw the local allowance @ £ 76/- p.m (Pounds seventy five) only from 1st May 1942 - less amount alread|y drawn if any. JW J / 3a/~ ( B#Roy chow dhury ) , f0t0o0No.QC56-l55-578, dated the Copy forwardea to the xolitic^l Agent, Bahrain, for information and necessary action in continuation of this ofiice enaorsement No.GC66-155-8391, dated the 21st March 1942,I KMpyLxBtxjtsimgxam 11 Copy of telegram No.116 dated the 22nd May 1942 from the Ministry of Information, London to Accounts, New Delhi 116 SLiPAX FROM ME^ISTRY CF INFORMATION STOP PLEASE AGAIN INCREASE LOCAL DRAWINGS BERTRAM THOMAS BAHREIN FROM SEVENTY FIVE TO NINETY STERLING MONTHLY COMMENCING END M.iY STOP OORRESPCNi&gt;ING REDUCTION MADE TO BANK HE. ^yrop. Copy of telegram No•9198-112 d^tea the 22nd May 1942 from the Ministry of Information, London, to Accounts, Delhi 9198-112 EMPAX GDNIL EICON HTPCX LTAIT AKREM G T? EV / T NTZEY NDZ^D NGiTOA LBZKH LHA3K. SON EH RDLKH PGSOD NK3TW AJFPTS iiSUiVAFLUT LDAPS i«XNAV AFOGU » a TAXANDUM FROM MINISTRY OF INFORMATION PLEASE ADVANCE FUND RSQUIRED PUBLIC RELATIONS OFFICER PERSIAN GULF WHBf PROCEEDIN3 ON YOUR SUBJECT TO RECONCILIATION AGAINST ^TRAVELLING ACCOUNT ON IHE RETURN AOCOUNTr.NT OPYJ * &lt;* tfh tupiufh-f■ I , OPITCI? OP j SE .'.OOO'JSTANT GENERAL C^TRkL REVENUES DELHI. No. GC.55-155-311&amp; ^ J Dated the | ^ * . : From r i The Accoutrbrdit General, Central Revenues. To Bertram Thomes Esquire, O.B.E., Public Relations Officer. • &gt;&gt; Bahrain, (Persian GoilfJ, Sir &gt; Adverting to this office letter No, GO.5b-155- 5rCdated 30-4-42. I have the honour to stete that at the instance oi the Ministry oi information you were requested^todraw £.7b/- (lis. 1000/-) ?xau from 1-5-42 in the^fefr quoted letter. It now transpires from your pay bill for ^ay 1942 oeid on 1-6-42 at the Bahrain Treasury that you have drawn Rs. 1200/- (as against Rs, 1000/-) as yom pay for May 1942, k mm of Rs. 200/- has thus be^n dra^n in excess. This amount may kindly be refunded from vour next oay bill for credit to the Ministry of information, quoting this letter ar relerence# I have the honour to be, Sir, lour most obedient servant, Sd/-.(B, Roychowdhurv) Assistant Accounts Officer, Central Revenues. BY £ V 1 »i ■ . jx i| ^ ^ ■'■' 0x ; K P \ / No. GO.55 -155-3116 Dated the Copy forwarded to the Political Ac^nt, Bahrain'm coi^tinuation of this office endorsement No, GC.55-155-578 dated 30-4-42. ihe circumstance? in whichothe officer v.as paid his pay pay for I^ay 1942iHs.l20C/- instead of Rs. ICOO/- may kindly be elucidated at an early cate. Assistant^Accounts Officer, Central Revenues.I &lt;- Depositor No. Defence Savings Provident Fund. &gt; i of Nomination when subscriber has a family. lount at my credit in the Defence Savings Provident Fund at the time the members of my family mentioned below in the manner Age of the nominee. Amount or share of accumulations. (This column should be filled in so as to cover the whole amount at credit.) -signature of subscriber. Witness No. 2. Signature of subscriber. ; rTHE POLITICAL AQENC BAHREIN. //wu U.F, A. To The A .G.C.R,, New Delhi. Sir, V/ith reference to your endorsement No. GC. 55-155-&amp;?8-d8^ed 3116 of 25.8.42, -L have the honour to state that the onAX^dymertt of Rs.200/- 'by Mr.Bertram Thomas, O.B.t., Public Relations lriu orc^j-^ejt Officer, Bahrainbeing adjusted by shortp«y»«\t of Local Allowance for September. The c*+i^ight A &gt;JL- r a - rv ie pay bill' is regrefted. I have etc. for Political Agent,Bahrain. or information to Mr.Bertram Thomas, O .B.E.,P ,R,oNo.291 Public Relations Office, Persian Gulf, Bahrain, Dated the 16th September, 1942 To The Treasurer, Political Agency, Bahrain. Memorandum ; Please advance me Rs.340/- against travelling expenses (Letter of Credit) which I shall require to attend an official confer ence at Jerusalem on the 21st instant. ^-1 IV Public Relations Officer in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain,CONFIDENTIAL. No. 1065 -3. hi The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to h J i'' ^ The Political Agent, Bahrain. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document^, with the request that it nay be forwarded to the officer concerned. it British Consulate-Gem'ral, BUSHIRE. Dated. . the, # 19 th # 0 c to be r 1942, Reference to previous correspondence Description of Enclosure. Name and D&gt;«te. Subject. Receipt for Hs.15/- mad Enclosure sent in origi^i P.R.O. in the G.G., Bah dated 8th November, 194^ al to I'r. Bertram Thomas, :^ain, under Endtt.No .1975-1/44 1\ e rat to Mr. Bertram Thonas. h'NTo tt To i j'j British Consulate- General, Bush ire, the / th No vemoer, 1^4^« The political A ^ent, Bahra in. Memo randum. A sum of Rs 3i/4/- has Deen paid oy this office to Messrs jiay Mackenzie k Go. L td. ,3ushir e, towards cost of one first class passage to Bahrain for Mr. B.Thomas. Would you kindly recover this amount and credit i t to this Residency Unofficial account. Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire.Rcocipt Abstract. -r^ Payment lent for separate departments and for receipts and payments. d by^ 1 - ' ) r ^ ^ ^ section intimating adjustment under iount during the month of /^ . . y - 19 lount. Is. a. Date of delivery to the section concerned for adjustment. -V Month's account in which adjusted (To be filled in by the adjusting section). Remarks. v&lt;JL ' } * *■ ' &lt;&gt; &gt;' - ~ r * f I4 No. 29. The Public Relations Officer, Persian Gulf, presents his compliments to : E.B.WakefUed, Esquire, Political Agent, Bahrain, 'He under A^- ffl 'sNo, 50-1/4-4 of 7th January 1943 direct from the Accountant-Genera].. ' New Delhi, and has repied in the sense of the attached letter.(!'o,]) • Office of the Public Relations Officer, Persian Gulf, B ahrain. Date ^ Januar.y--X9-43^- Reference to previous correspondence : His letter No. 50-1/44 of 7th January 194-3. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. of* - - ' C-py Ol Letter No.l dated 2nd January 1943 to the Accountant-General, Central Revenues, New Dei^, with its enclosure from the India Offi Letter No,2 dated 2nd January 1943 to the Assistant Accounts Officer, Accountant-General, Central Re e nues, Ne w Delhi, on the reduced allowance as from January inclusive. ce. Subject. Recovery of Rs,200/- #No.l Dated the 2nd Jenusry, 194 To The Assistant Accounts Officer, Office of the Accountant General, Centre! Revenues, Ner; Delhi. With reference to your GC. 55-157-5369 dated the 17th of December, 1942, and In continuation of your GC; 55-155-3115 of the 25th of August, 1942, in which you print out thiat I drew local allowt^nce of Rs.1200/- in respect of ay liay 1942 salary from Ministry of Information whereas I should have drawn only Rs.1000/-, I have the honour to forward herewith a copy of India Office telegrei® 15B75Zby which authority was given to the increase of my local allowance to Rs.1200/- frnm my pay of Rs. 1500/- with effect from the 1st of 'ay. not th. 1st of J'ine. 2. The misapprehension would appear to have arisen from the following circumstances. I asked London in April for increase of rey local allowance to Rs.1000/- and a little later finding that this was not enough asked that it be amended to Rs.1200/- instead of Rs.1000/-. It would appear that the authority for the Rs.1000/- was Issued to you before my second application had reached London. In fact the allowance of Rs.1000/- never came into effect herc # 3. In these circumstances there has been no local over drawing of R5.200/- in respect of the month of May and so no refund has been necessary. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Copy forwarded toi (BERTRAM THOMAS) Public Relations Officer in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain* The Treasury Officer, Political Agency, Bahrain.Telegram G.T.C. From Retaxandum, London. To Political Agent, Bahrain. No. 15875. Dated the 10th and received the 11th September, 1942 Following for Publicity EMPAX for Bertram Thomas. Your 280 and 121. Reply sent to Accounts, Delhi, May 21st requesting increase of local drawings to £.90/- monthly. Paynents to Bank here reduced to £.35/- from May inclusive accordingly. Repetition of wire to Delhi being arranged.Accountant. - Retaxandum -3' 2- No. 2 Public Relations Office, Persian Gulf, Bahrain. Dated the 2nd January, 194-3• To The Assistant Accounts Officer, Office of the Accountant General, Central Revenues, Nev? Delhi. Sir, In answer to your GC.55-155-551B dated the 24th December 1942, with regard to the reduc tion of my local allowance from £90/- to £60/- I have the honour to request your confirmation that the Y?ords 'commencing from end of January 1943 you should therefore dra?; your Local Allow ance £60/- p.m. (Pounds Sixty) only from 1st February' have reference only to the time of draw ing this local allowance. The readjustment of my pay in London has effect from the beginning of the New Year, that is to say, is applicable from the month of January inclusive . I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, 1 (BERTRAM THOMAS) Public Relations Officer in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain.II No. 47 Dated the 18th January,1943. To The Assistant Accounts Officer, Office of the Accountant General, Central Revenues f New Pelhi. Sir Please cancel my letter No.l of the 2nd of January, 194-3• I have Just received a copy of my Statement of Account from my London Bank for the past year in which it is shown that the equivalent sterling of Hps.200/- was in fact paid into my account by Ministry of Information in respect of my April pay 1942• I regret that this Y/as not known to me when I wrote you on the 2nd of January. I have now given instructions that the Rps.200/- be witheld this month by the Treasurer from my local allowance in accordance with your No.GC .55- 157-5369 of the 17th December, 1942. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, (BERTRAM THOMAS) Public Relations Officer in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain. Copy toi The Treasury Officer,/ Political Agency, Bahrain in continuation of my No.291dated 9th January, addressed to Political Agent, Bahrain.Telegram G.T.C From To No. Britconsul, Heshire Political, Bahrain 607 Dated and received 15.2.43 Has Bertram Thomas returned Britconsul A.P.A. Mr.Bertram Thomas returned yesterday. Telegram informing Bushire has been issuedPUBLIC RELATIONS OFFI^CE'' ' Persian Gulf i 7 7- BAHRAIN 17th July 1948. To, The Treausry Officer, Political Agency, Bahrain. Please advance me a sum of Rs.1,000/-/- (Rupees one thousand only) for expenses in connection with my tour to Cairo to attend a conference. Public Relations Officer, Persian Chalf, Bahrain. * ^&lt;j. /z .2 a fa c^? Political Reeident at iihiraz India Office, London Minister of State 9 Cairo for Miniform Political Agents Bahrain SAVING No. T/455 Dated the 15th August 1945* Bertram Thomas who has taken one months leave on recess asked me to agree to his absence for longer period say six weeks. as he did not get away at all last summer I said I had no objection. - PRIOR - CO^IL^TIAL . Office of the Political Resident in the Persian 0ulf 9 CAUP 3HIRAZ. Dated the 15th August 1943. Copy forwarded, with compliments, to &lt;- The Political Agent, BAHRAIN. 4h*/ V E-0. &amp; S8/7 XXX Political Resident, at Shiraz. Political Agent, Bahrain, Telegram From To No. T/672 Dated 7th received 8th September, 1^43. IMPORTANT Following is repetition of Cairo telegram 10 September 4th begins Following received from Algiers tegins Following for Ryan from Bertram Thomas, propose return by first air opportunity available about September 8th. Ends. ncj - PRIOB - ^3 mz!Telegram: En clair. (I ! / ' s /s &gt;-5' f A-&gt; From: No To: Ministry of Information, Cairo, Publicity, ^Bahrain. Empax 56. Dated 22nd October, 194-3. Received 23rd October. For Bertram Thomas from Mason your letter of 14th to Ryan who is away authority is granted for Captain Dixon to assume office in acting capacity. Public Relations Office ^ 0 ' 1^ • 23rd October, 194-3. Copy forwarded with compliments to Political Agent, Bahrain, for information.m / Certified that we have respectively h&amp;nded over and taken over charge of the office of the THibllc Relatlcma Officer In the Persian Gulf, Bahrain, on the ?3rd October, 1943, afternoon. Rl lIEVEI) OFFICER OfTICEH Public Relations Office in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain. Dated the 23rd October, 1943. Copy forwarded with compliments to: 1. Kiddle East Division, Ministry of Information, Malet Street, London, W.C.I. 2. The Controller, British Ministry of Information, Middle East Services, Cairo. 3. The Accountant General, Central Revenues, New Delhi. 4. The Hon'ble The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. s^ \ The Political Agent, Bahrain, for information and such action as may be considered necessaryWo. i Forwarded. ^Ith complimentb. to the Accountant (itr* ^ Central &gt;vevenue6 9 New Delhi, a^vl the controller. Accounts Dlvm* Ministry of Information, Cairo» C. A. C.-31B. (App. 8A, Rule 2, C. A. C.) LAST-PAY CERTIFICATE. Last-pay certificate of... .^rt.r.W. .. **&lt;*• &gt;., .9-X..«.«!«&gt;. 1°**..,9.^?•«'. 0 -p*^ 0 Tertian Gulf, Bahrain proceeding ^ . Cairo to \ 2. He has been paid up to..^ 1 ..9°*&lt;???•!■ ». at the following rates :— Particulars. Rate, Locfil A^lowance Ra.BOO/- (£,60/-) TTfTTcTa^mg^^y ^TMigg'Coinp'ensatfqB' Mluwanctf Re. 800- o Deductions. 3. He made over charge of the office Bahrain on the ^^SToon of. 4. Recoveries are to be made from the pay of the Government servant as detailed on the reverse. 5. He has been paid leave salary as detailed below. Deductions have been made as noted on the 'W reverse. Period. Rate, Amount. From to at Rs a month. From ....to at Rs a month. , From .* to at Rs ■, a month. 6. He is entitled to draw the following :— 7. He is also entitled to joining time for days. 8. The details of the income-tax recovered from him up to the date from the beginning of the current year are noted on the reverse. Wrf.. is . Political Agency,Bahrain, {Designation) ior Agent, Bahrain. The 3rd November, 1943 # . \ » | ' -r/. Office of the Accountant General 9 Central Revenues New Delhi* No .GC55 -163-3648. dated the To The Secretary to the Kon'ble the Political Eeaident in the Persian Gulf 9 Bushire* t&gt;ir, ^ ^ I hare the honour to invite a reference to the letter No.Nil dated 23rd Uct. , 43 from the •'Public Eelatione officer* 4 in the Persian Gulf Bahrain Uopy endorsed to you} s showing Capt- W.G.Dixon of the Indian Political Service as hsving assumed charge at . i^ahrain as ^Public Relations officer' from Hr .BavtHiam Thomas on the afternoon of 23-10-43 and to request you kindly to furnish urgently the necessary orders conveying sanction to Mr .Dixon's appointment to the above post end the pay and allonence admissibl to hin while holding the post to enable this office to issue pay slip. 2. Prior to his above appointment the officer was Assistant Political Agentt Bahrain. It is presumed that he has since made over charge of the latter post. If so the charge certificate of his making over charge of the said post may please be fur nished to this office by return of Mail. A copy of this Istter is bwing endorsedw* to Mr. uixon and the Politicc.! Agent, '^ahrain also. •/ NOV if I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, 3^/' (B. Roychoudhury) ^ Assistant Accounts Officer* y Public Relation Officer, Persian M o.GC5L-163-3649 , drted ihe Copy forwarded to Captr in I'.G.D'ixon, I.P.S 'iulf, Fahrs-in, for information ■ nd necessary rction. It silica transpires from his charge certificates that he made oyer qs P.' Bahrain on 6-f^-43 (F.If) and took over as \ .P.Bahrain on r '-10-43( &gt; F.- ) . tie he b thus been on j.t.ifor 6-10-43, I'or which he is hereby authorised to d raw joining tine pey ^.1150/- p.ci. (Rupees one thousand one hundred end fifty only}^iR continuation of this office leV^er !:o.0055-163-3900, dated 23-10-43. ll CD. oychoudhury) .Asfie^nt Account a Officer.v. dated the 19th May 1937, I have the honour to intimate that debit for Re. 1-3-0 for this office debit memo-Ko. 481» will be raised against Administrative Officer, 3 R Dn., milrt-. in this office accounts for the month of llarch Final 1937. 1 Jmue the honour to hr % sir Your most obedient servant A.S.K. 29/5 Autt .Wntroller.1. A pay bill may be presented at a District Treasury two days before the last working day of the month by the labour of which the pay is earned. 2. A pay bill may, if desired, be enfaced for payment to a Banker or Agent and submitted for collection through such Panker or Agent; this will obviate the necessity of the officer's attendance in person or by messenger, as payment may then be made direct to the Banker or Agent. 3. When exemption is claimed in respect of any amount paid to an Insurance Company, the original receipt of tho Company for the amount paid or an attested copy thereof should be attached to the pay bill. '1 he receipt will be returned with the cheque. , 4. The period for which a subscription to a Fund is due shoald be specified when it differs from the period for which pay is drawn. 5. The fund deductions of a Covenanted Civil Servant are taken upon bis allowances before deductions on account of Civil Service Provident Fund. 6. The Government of India exercises no supervision over the management of the Hindu Family Annuity Fund, the General Family Pension Fund and the Bengal Christian Family Pension Fund and is in no way responsible for their solvency. 7. In the case of officers entitled to Sterling Overseas Pay, fund deducticns are based on the Rupee Pay plus the rupee equivalent of the Sterling Overseas Pay. 8. When the deduction on account of income-tax shown in the bill includes tax calculated on Sterling Overseas Pay, the details of the calculation, on which the deduction is based, may be given at the foot of the bill or, if there bo no space at the foot, in some other suitable place; the total being brought into the body of the bill in the appropriate plat e and the two entries connected with a letter mark or otherwise. The details should show the sterling amount of the Overseas Pay as also its rupee equivalent _ f Name of Fund. Amount. s. d. I. C S, Family Pension Regu lations— Self . . . . Wife &gt; . Son . . . . Daughter Donation on marriage Interest on ^ ona ^ o n8 Total * I. M. S. Family Pension Regu lations— Wife- Promotion donation. Marriage donation . Excess age donation Disparity donation . Subscription . Son— Donation Subscription . Daughter— Donation Snbs&lt;-ription ■ Unmarried subscription Payments on account of insurance of passage money Interest on passage money premia Total Rs. @ rupee a. Name of Fnnd. Indian Military Widows' and Orphans' Fund— Wife— Excess age donation Disparity donation . Fine for delay in reporting marriage Subscription Interest on arrears . Son's subscription Daughter— Extra donation Subscription . Fine for delay in reporting birth Unmarried subscription Interest on arrears Passage money premium Passage money interest Amount. s. d. Total Rents- Rs. ^ @ rupee Rent of building No. ) . Rent of special services Furniture rent iMeter rent Rent of fans . W ater rate Energy charges Cost of stock materials issued by Division Total -T Signature. N oth 1. —Treasury and Audit Officere should Bee that all oompnlflory deductions Including those for I. 0. S. Provident Fund are duly made and schedules regarding G. P. Fund and I. 0. S. Provident Pnnd, when such schedules are prepared hy the officers themselves, are attached to the pay' bills. N ote 2.—Subscribers to the Sterling Branch should note on the bill and in Fund schedule attached to the bill that the recoveries relate to the Sterling Branch.Certified that we have respectively handed over and taken over charge of the office of the Public Relations Officer in the Persian Oulf f Bahrain, on the 21st December, 1943, afternoon. (ls.. RFXIK D OFFICER RELIEVING 0FT1CBR Public Relations Office in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain. Dated the 21st December, 1943* Copy forwarded, with complinents, toi 1. Middle East Division, Ministry of Information, Malet Street, Lrndon, W.C.I. 2. Tha Controller, British Ministry of Information, lllddle East Services, Cairo. 3. Tht Accountant General, Central Revenues, Hew Delhi. 4. Tha Hobble Tha Political Resident in the Persian Qulf, Bnshlre. 5. The Political Agent, Bahrain, ■►.trr- ]ir -■ - ibw ^twnis tdeMHlxiMMLeaLA«jRy •Please refer to paragraph 257 (iv) of your intelligence Summary No. 24 dated the lat January 1944. ■ 2* Prom a charge report received here i see that Dixon handed over to Hadow as Public Relations ,Officer on the 2l3t December 1943. 3. The original arrangement was that you would take on these duties. unless, however, you issue another charge report notifying all concerned that you have taken over from Hadow it will be difficult for you to draw the allow ance proposed in paragraph 3 of my telegram no * ^483 dated the 24th December 194 3. co •0 May or t Hickinbotham, C.IJE., Political Agent, JS A H R A 1 ^ . O.B.S., A\ RECEIVED \ RHL. °i -17 FEB. 194 V ?&gt; ■A —' CllAUGS CKHTiyiCATE Cortiflod tlmt wr Jiavo respectively handed over and taken over charge of the office of the Public Hclations Officer In the Persian Gulf, Bahrain, on the ^4th December 1P43, forenoon• K$LI3SVST3 OF FICER KISLIiWIHC O^r JC^R Public He lotions &lt; :f'ice in the Persian Gulf, Bnhrf?in# Dated the '-7th FebiAiary 1£44 Copy forwarded, with comol lr«cnts, tos- 1. ricV; 1c- East Division, ?'In is try of Info-^stlon, ^falet street, London, W.C.I* 2. The Con teller, British ministry of Information, Middle .Kast Bervlcee, Cairo. 3. ''ho A^countant-Genoral, Central Revenues, New Delhi. 4. The TTon'hle f he Political HesMent in the Persisn Gulf, Bushlre. 6- I'he Political A rent, Bahi^ain*// / ^ a CHARGE CERTIFICATE. CJ^RTIFIED that we have respectively handed over and taken over charge of the office of the Public Relations Officer In the Persian Gulf, Bahrain, on the 6th July 1944, aftenoon. ) RELIEVED OFFICER 'TsQ. ■ T 3- 1 RELIEVIHO OFFICEH No. 2l. Public Relations Officer, Persian Ciulf, Bahrain. ^ated, (&gt; Jtt July 1944. Copy forwarded, with coiapliments, toi- 1. Ministry of Information, Middle East Division, Malet Street, London, W.C.I. 2. Ihe Controller, British Ministry of Information, Middle East Services, Cairo. The Accountant General, Central Revenues, New Delhi 4. Oie Hon 1 ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bush ire • -^5. Ihe Political Agent, Bahrain.75 '7 . k if t CHARGE CERTTnr..T . CEOTIFIil) that we have respectively handed over and taken over charge of the office of the Public Relations Officer in the Persian Oulf, Bahrain, on the 20th August 1944, afternoon. RELIEVED OFFICER RRUEVINO OFFICER Public Relations Office, Persian Gulf, Bahrain. *o. 379. Dated, 21st August 1944. Copy forwarded, with conpllnents, toi- 1. Ministry of Inforwatlon, Middle East Dlwlslen, Ms let Street, London, W.C.I. 2. The Controller, British Ministry of Infarnation* Middle fast Services, Cairo. 3. The Accountant-General, Central Revenues,Rew Delhi. 4. The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Ould, Bushire. -J 5. The Political Agent, Bahrain.^V v /A- f %' U No. 4406 - 65/35. (gb To BRITISH RESIDENCY AND CONSULATE GENERAL, BUSHIRE. the 9th November, 1945, m he Political Agent, 'Bahrain. ^TEMORANDU! 1 ^ i ,•&gt; • » &gt; i . „ , v- a &lt; a i% ^ ' i js&amp;- ' f V'' Reference your memorandum No. 4444 - 1/44 dated the 24th October, 1945. 7 - ^ , 2. Vith reference to his letter No. GF.51 - 164 - 1911 dated the 17th September, 1945, the Accountant General, Central Revenues, may kindly be informed that the monthly payment of £ 25.0.0 to the Political Agent for Publicity work has been sanctioned by the Ministry of Information, Middle East Division, London, and that these payments are not debitable to the Government of India. He may also be told to raise a debit for these payments against the Department concerned. Secretary tb the Political Resident in the Pers.tari Gulf. G.A.M.No. f)7) H7 From To / POLITICAL AGENCY. BAHRAIN, December, 1946, Lt.Col•A.C. Galloway| O.ii.K., Political Agent, iiahrain. The Accountant General, Central Revenues. New Delhi* • v Slr » ; 1C , 1Q ?, ha T 0 l t ? e ^? lono )J r t0 rafar t0 your letter No. OF 51- Pf'f 17th September, 1946, and to inform you that the monthly payment of £ 25/-( i.e. Es.333/5/-) to the Political Agent, Bahrain, for Publicity work has been sanctioned by the ilinistry of Information, Middle j u. * JT i 011 * ^on^on, and that these payments are not . 5 h 2 ^ernment of India. I therefore request tlwt the debit for these payments may kindly be raised against the Department concerned. I have the honour to be, •Sir, Your most obedient servantj Yt ' Political A^ent, Bahrain. Copy with compliments to the Public Relations Officer, Bahrain, for information.1-4 V- o ' Total carried forward. Total Refonda Net charges of the raooth Ilivisional Accountant. a/S Bo « 'y u i Schedule of Works Expendmtnre, and 72. In all other cases, th« • Fnll nsme of work a'? given in the esttraat«, sbonl l he o.ntored hero In the ca^o of cMh p g 5 P. W. A. Form 68, or in the Schedule of deposit Works, Takavi Works, or Debits to Stock, P. W. A. o name of the Schedule should he given, . « • j * Tk u i. f Onlv such particulars need he entered as are necessary to avoid errors in the posting of charges in Schedule Doc c J Ip the case of Tr nsfer Entry debits the supporting vouchers if exceeding Rs 25 S -noted beloV rach entry, and the amount the petty vouchers being s P e&lt;^ in the col In tho CaSe of lran8fer 1 Credits a referoucc to the Schedule Docket in which the corresponding debit U shown should bo given In the same . W | 1 1p. w a 48 STATEMENT OF RENTS EECOVERABLE IN CASH OR BY DEDUCTION FROM PAY BILLS. [P. W. A. Code, paragraph 256.] P rovince Bfavcu. . Name of Division Name of Canal, etc._ Major Head to he credited 'A c ^ . to If fl Ph 1 Nam® of Building. Vo / •v ^ ^ 'C&lt;. * '-j. L t 0 To be filled in by the Tbeasury Officer. Name, rank and office of occupant, with rates of his pay and allowances, as known to the Divisional Officer. Amount recovered during l, Remarks with date and other particulars of changes in the rates of emoluments shown in column 3. 81 I . , Copy of para 3 of letter NO.AG. 2845/46.1!•!. dated the Ist Vay •46 from the Accountant General India Office Thitehall London to A»G» C«R*» % 'ew Delhi# . ••••••••• v ( 0 EXPENDITURE IN CONNECTION WITH THE PUBLIC RELATIONS OFFICER IN THE PERSIAN GUIF. i au also to inform you tnat vouchers in support of a payment of £30 -i-d made to kessrs cable and Tireless Ltd. in respect of transmi tter nire for February *42 at the Bahrain Broadcasting Ration (Oabl« and tireless reference No.b /28 dated 2nd Uarch *42) are neid at this office. A debit in respect of tnis payment cannot be identified in t ho Outward Account Current schedule and I am to enquire where tne relative debit is to be found. Tne vouchers are enclosed ior perusal and return#\ni OFFICE OF THE A .G.C.R. NEW DELHI, No # Ta/26-8-1415 dated TO The JHoliticaX Agent, Bahrain # mft~ The Director of News and EXtenia?. Services, a# I . R *, New Delhi letter Jio• 10(6;-K/4S-12232 dated 14 # 8 # 46 regarding payment of travelling expenses for nr. B # wayedh and his f^aily for their journey from Bahrain to Delhi (copy enclosed) Kindly arrange to maJce an early payment of fc»1215/- (Ripees one thousand two hundred and fifteen only) to the F.K.O. Bahrain (to who® a copy of this letter is being endorsed) under intimation to this off ice # Debit/o^, the amount when paid may please be included in your monthly account, emoting the Bo. and date of this latter as authority# c E&amp;C 1 No J j T.. y. Sr. I- Date Accounts Officer* •/t25» The maxiraum subscription payable by the subscriber In whole rupees on his pay of Hs. 180A in respect of 31st March 1938 is Rs.28/- per month and not Rs # 30/- per month. The excess payment at Hs. 2a pc month up to date should be adjusted in his next pay bill, quoting this as authority on the bill as well as on the schedule. The Sumptuary allow- r ance of Hs. 100/- is not treated as pay. In all a sum of Rs. 93/- has been recovered in excess from M. Sher Zaman Khan to— wards his ^eneral Provident Fund subscription vide Memo: No. 733, dated the 14th August 1939 from the Audit Officer, Kalat State, to the Wazir-i-Azam, Kalat State,^ (copy enclosed)* Subscription for the months of May to i August 1939 has been recovered at the correct rate of to. x f &amp;; A P.T.O.... /True Copy/ Su Si /vu erintendent S.O. ixi Agency.Q&gt;py of letter wo »10 (6 )' , E /46»12232 dated. 14•S®46 frofl* the Director of ^ewe and iixteriial Services, All India Kadlo f Mew Delhi to the A«G # C« M # Mew Delhi* i have the honour to invite a reference to I. &amp; A. Deptt letter Mo # K # 459 dated 22.4.46 sanctioning payment of travelling expenses for Mr. E.Arrayedh and his family for their journey from jaahrain to Delhi. The amount of Rs.2116/3/- is made up as follows s* 1.382/10/- vide AGCR u.o. M o. T a /26-8-1488 dated 17.10.46. Already paid to P.R«o» Bahrain nHHtuHftimitimii mi* Array®dh To be paid now to Fublic He lations uffr, Bahrain. fis.300/-/- vide our T.A«bill wo. 12(64) paid on 1.10.4i lfacken*ie &amp; Co. Ltd. Advanced to Mrs, Arrayedh 916/-/-) BiU of M/S Grey A 300A/-) - — to be paid to nr. Arrayedh 218/9/- A bill for the net amount of tts. 218/9/- has been made out and presented at your cash counter separately. it is requested that arrangements may kindly be made to pay a sumof Bs # l216/- as shown abo^ to f .R.O. Bahrain und€ under intimation to this office. The expr is debitable to 46- Broadcasting middle iiast ^o ado as ting F.8C3) Allowances, Hono etc.✓Copy of letter wo,AG/4C85/46-M .1. dated 6,6.46 from the Liondoa to the wew tfelhi* Sub:- Expenditure In connection with the Public Relations officer in the rereian Gulf o.A.C, Schedules August 1^45- Debit of ^,22909:9:6 rfith reference to the debit included in the uut ard Account Current schedules for the month of August 1^45 as above, i am to invite your attention to payments in respect of the pay and Allowances of Mr, Ibrahim .Arrayid, according to Voucher i&gt;io«36 of April 45 0*.115 j 2 ) this of:icer left for xnaia with ef.ect from 16th March 1945 and voucher JMo,55 of &amp;ay 45 relates to payment of •^•343:7 o . account of his leave pay for t the period 5th - 30th ^ril 45# in the circumstances i am to enquire (a) where a debit in respect of the ray of Mr ^bra'-im Arrayid for th^ period 1 - 15th March has been or ^ill be raised, r :, Cb) v.hether his emoluments for the period 16th March to 4th April are an. H,m,G , liability ana if so v/.en a debit ma^* be expected. (c ) whether any dejits in respect of him on account of tl.e perioa a^^ter oC/t;.; /^r^p-ril 11 • •a,/ - 'Xp^.ed» jl am also to enquire «.hether Mi , ibrahimArra,. id had any pas^-a^e il^ts in connection ..ith hit journey to India md if so whether any debits in relation thereto maj be .^expected. it would also be appreciate, if you would state whether ^er.sion and le ve contributions in respect of any member of the office staf: a-^ recoverable from H.M.G. and whether all the debit due in respect of publicity allowace, set e.g. voucher im o.31. of June 45 have be n raised.Air mall. NO. loJJc_ 1/44. POLITICAL AGENCY, i-- BAHRAIN, September, 1946. From The Political Agent f Bahrain^ To The Accountant General, Central Revenues, New Delhi. Sir r ajh\ * I have the honour to refer to your letter No.TA.lO« 3/993 dated the 29th July, 1946, and to request that the vouchers in support of payment of £ 30 to Messrs. Cable and Wireless Iitd., sent to you by the Accountant General, London, may please be sent to this office to facilitate proper Identification of the debit. 1 have the honour to be, . Sir, Your most obedient servant. * f( 'tV - Captain, for Political Agent, Bahrain. ma. \NO, 1/44. POLITICAL AGENCY, , BAHRAIN. /yf£ September, 1946. (\\\ ^ To V The Accountant General, Central Revenues, New Delhi . MEMORANDUM: - C ^ f 3. /f ^ Reference your memorandum No.TA/26-8' 1415 dated the 28th August,1946. 2. The sum of Rs.1215/- has been paid to the Public Relations Officer, Bahrain, by this Agency voucher No. 26 of the 15th September, 1946. ' oA Captain, 1 for Political Agent, Bahrain. NMJro No#3031-l/44 # Political Agency, Bahrain, The 16th September, 1946. From The Political Agent, Bahrain. To The Accountant General, Central Revenues, New Delhi. Slrj Subject? Pay md allowances of Mr. Ibrahim Arraved. I have the honour to refer to your letter No.TA/ 10-3-1217 dated the 15th August, 1946, and to furnish the following reply in respect of the questions raised by the Accountant General, London. (a) &amp; (b). A debit for Es.489-3-0 has already been raised by Bahrain Agency Treasury voucher No.36 of 3/45 as under:- (i) Pay from 1 to 15-3-45 @ Ps.450/- p.m. Rs.225/0/ (ii) Leave salary from 16-3-45 to 4-4-45 @ Rs.396/4/- p.m. Es.264/3/ Rs.489/3/. The above amounts are debitable to Foreign Office, London. (c) As Mr. Ibrahim Arrayed joined for duty with the Government of India, Information and Broadcasting Department, New Delhi, from 1-5-1945, no further debit has therefore been raised by this office after that date. 2. Mr. Ibrahim Arrayed had passage rights and hence expenditure in connection with the Travelling Allowance for himself and his family was met by the Government of India, Information and Broadcasting Department. Following amounts were spent by the Public Relations Office in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain:- (i) Advanced to Mr. Arrayed while proceeding to Delhi. Rs. 382-10-0 (ii) a. Advanced to the wife of Mr. Arrayed to meet the cost of railway tickets from Karachi to Delhi - Rs. 300/ - . Paid to Gray Mackenzie &amp; Co., Ltd., Bahrain, being cost of 5 second class tickets (without food) from Bahrain to Karachi - Rs.915/-. Rs. 1215-0-0 The above amounts have been refunded to the Public Relations Office, Bahrain, by Bahrain Agency Treasury voucher No.12 of 12/45 and voucher No.26 of 9/46. 3. No pension and leave of the staff are recoverable All debits due on account of contributions in respect of any from His Majesty's Government, the Publicity Allowance areo - 2 - raised regularly every month in the monthly Cash Account of this office. I have the honour to be&gt; Sir, Your most obedient servant, 0[C/ Captain, for political Agent, Bahrain.&amp; MIDDLE EAST CENTRE FOR ARAB STUDIES, AUSTRIAN HOSPICE, JERUSALEM. 12th September 1946. hi 2r &lt;u: c^i ^(y^- When I was serving as Information Officer (Public Relations Officer) under the Ministry of Information in Bahrein, ^th December 19U1 to 23rd October 1943&gt; I drew all funds to meet M. of I. expenditure through your Agency Treasury, and the usual system was followed whereby the accounts then went through the Accountant General's Department to the Government of India at Delhi, who in turn sent certain figuresto the Ministry of Information in London. I have recently received a letter from the M. of I. auditors raising queries in connexion with certain items of my pay and allowances, and a 1941 travelling expense item, and I am not in a position to answer adequately without a complete list of my drawings in Bahrein. Would you be so good as to arrange for your Treasurer or Accountant to send me a complete list of these? The task is not really so big as it may sound, as one usually drew a lump sum once a month, except for advances when going on tour. Itwould be terribly good of you if you would do ^is, and I only bother you because the items in question, when added together, make up a sizable figure, and unless I can explain them, the auditors may unjustly claim refunds from me. The cause of fogginess in the M. of I. accounts at home arises in part I think from the many channels through which our accounts passed, and in part to the system - a legacy of the early days - /contd.I I i i l%0 \- ~ 1 '• • ^ - 2 - whereby any monies that I drew against M. of !♦ had to be shewn (by your regulations at the time) as an advance to me* This was true of advance for travelling expenses, for instance, which I accounted for on my return. One or two of the supporting claims appear to have gone astray because the sums appear to have been regarded in London as personal advances to me against my pay* I would not bother you by asking for a complete statement shewing dates and drawings, were^ it not necessary. I am addressing this impersonally to P.A. as I do not know for certain who is P.A., or if he is on recess. Colonel Rupert Hay, when he wrote me the other day, I seem to remember, said the P.A. was» or was to be,Colonel Galloway. If so, we shall have Muscat as well as Bahrein in common, and I hope one day you may get a chance of coming to Jerusalem, in which case I should hope to have the pleasure of putting you up. If you ever do come this way would you be good enough to lecture to ray School on the Persian Gulf? I have a group of 20 odd young Officers, quite worth talking to. Geoffrey Prior and Reader Bullard have both broken their journeys when on their way to or from home and stayed with me and lectured here to earlier bunches of students. I am just embarking on a new course with a fresh batch of young men, none of whom know anything about the Gulf. Forgive me for bothering you for the Bahrein list of Ministry of Information disbursements during my time, i.e. Uth December 19U1 to 23rd October 1943* I shall be most grateful if your Accountant can make this list for me and send it at the earliest possible convenient moment, to enable me to deal with the M. of I. auditors queries of so many years ago. Best wishes. The Political Agent, Bahrein. Persian Gulf . 'V-OAAXW y» c ■ ^jyjLD.O. K o .C/1133. The 7th of October t 1946. Dear Colonel, please refer to your letter dated 12th Sepce^ber, 1946, addressed to 'political Agent* 1 h 2. T enclose a statement of your 'drawings 1 * which I hope will give you all the information you desire. Yours sincerely, fm Lieut-Col. Bertraca Thoaas, O.B.S. f Middle Bast Centre for Arab Studies, Austrian Hospice, Jerusalem . NS. P. ^61 I# OFFICE OF THE A.G.C.R.NEW DELHI. NO TA *10'»3/1579 jWated th® To The folitleal Agent, Bahrain* Sir, ^ In forwarding herewith a copy of letter No AG-9936/45 1UI.dated the 22»7-46 from the Accountant General -^ndia Office London. I have tne honour to refer to itemltoe alemd 2 kf youw-CaWi Account for 7/44 in which the amounts of Re 15/3 and He 250/- wore credited by F.R.O. 2 The information ds to in which months accounts giving voucher No and fete in which original payments representing the above refund ware made may kindly be intimated in consultation with the P.R.O.Bfchrain of necessary. Assistant Accounts Officer.&gt; 1 131 OFFICE OF THE A *6 •€•&amp; .NEW DELHI. /b f Copy of the let er No 9936/45-M.I .dated the 22ndJul^l946 .from thr A ndia Office AhlteHall London S*l!f*I«to the Accountant General .Central Revenues New Delhi* Refund of Hr., RJi.Hadow^e share of the cost of petrol for Jtiy 1944 Re 15/3(£ls2s9ft}and'refund of allowance granted to Mr., E .P^lmaida for January -May 1944 Rs 250(£18:15j-) I am directed to refer to the credits on the above account afforded in the schedules of the outward Account current for the month of September 1944 and ti enquire in which schedules of the outward Account current debits in respect of the corresponding expenditure have been or will be raised*NO . i) ^ frb- POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN, 1U' 0ct; c&gt;^Qr,1946. in To The Accountant General, Central Revenues, New Delhi. Sir, I have the honour to refer to your letter No.TA 10-3/1679, dated the 24th September, 1946 and to state that a sun of 39/11/-being cost of petrol (including Ps» 16/3/- of Mr.Hadow's share) was drawn froa the Head 11 C-Travelling' by this Agency Treasury voucher No*32 of the 27th June, 1944. 2. A sum of ks.250/-beirig arrears of increase @ Es # 50/-p.m. granted to IJr.Almeida in accordance with Ministry of Information, Eondon, telegram No. 4, dated the 9th June, 1944 was drawn from Head 'B-Pay of Staff' by this Agency Treasury voucher No.14 of 14th June, 1944. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant. */ ^ ^ ' Captain. / ( for Political Agent, Bahrain. h iyJ Dear Mr. Ranee, MIDDLE EAST CENTRE FOR ARAB STUDIES, AUSTRIAN HOSPICE, JERUSALEM. th December 19U6. r'-' / No 7^0 P.R.O. Bahrein Accounts through G. of I. Treasury. 19U1/43. Q.tfi &gt;cv Thank you very much for your D.0.C/il33 dated 7th October last, sending me a statement of my drawings on M. of I. Account through the Bahrein Treasury, December 19I|.l to October 1943- Will you be so good as to amplify one or two items for me please. (i) Is the list you have sent me a complete list of all payments made during the period in question please? For instance, M* of I. entertainment in Bahrein is not mentioned, how much, if any, was brought to account specifically in M. of I. accounts through you. Entertainment incurred on tours was doubtless brought to account in my travelling claim, but there is no mention in your list of Entertainment incurred in Bahrein itself. Can you kindly elucidate. Jassim Muhammed, who was my chief clerk at the time (he is now I understand political representative on the Trucial coast) would doubtless remember. Similarly 'Advances' made me when proceeding on official tours._ Paragraph 2 refers. J — 2- M. of I. auditors who are winding up M. of I, was accounts in London have lately raised a query on the travelling_allowance paid at Bahrein for my tour'to Cairo (dates include recess in North Africa), and return to Bahrein, 20th July to 27th September 1943. The item which appears in your statement of drawings 30/10/43 Rps.1086/10/8 refers. As you will be aware the practice of your Treasury in Bahrein, vis-a-vis P.R.O.'s tours, was to make an advance to me on the eve of my tour as a Personal Advance, and I accounted for it as olilcial expenditure on return from the tour in the form of travelling allowance claim. The Auditor has brought to^jny notice that an advance is shewn to me on the 18th July on the eve of the tour, of Rps.1000; that the travelling claim of Rps.1086/10/8 claimed at the end of the tour has in this particular instance not been shewn against the advance, but as though it had been paid in cash to me in addition to the advance. This, of course, could scarcely be the case, as it is against normal practice, and your Treasurer would have required me to account for the July advance before making any fresh payment to me, but the fact is that the auditor's book, presumably built up on the vouchers you would send back through the Government of India, shews the double charge: I shall be grateful therefore if you will check up in your Bahrein accounts and confirm that, as was the invariable practice, the travelling allowance must have been offset against the Advance, or else the advance otherwise accounted for. Some clerical omission somewhere would account for it but you will appreciate that three years after the event, serving in other jobs and countries, I have no detailed records with me. Clearly when I drew the next payment from the Treasurer in Bahrein he would have drawn my attention to any outstanding advance unaccounted tor; that there was none I am certain, when I left, ■ti.D.H.Ranee t Esq . /contd.otherwise I should have 'been aware of it, and it would scarcely have escaped the vigilance of both Bahrein Agency and Delhi accountants. The fact that the statement of my spendings you have sent me does not shew this item of Rps.1000 on the 10th July indicates, perhaps, that if it was paid, as it presumably was, it would have been accounted for in the usual way, i.e.* travelling allowance claims. Will you kindly therefore look into these two-items in your book for me and* confirm, to enable me to answer the query. The M.of I. Auditor's suggestion of a double charge for this tour would, if allowed to pass, involve me in a repayment of the advance drawn for and expended on the tour, which would be quite unjust. 3- Reference the item in your list Rps.1238.7.0 23*5^3 Travelling Allowance of P.R.O. 10/3 to 19/U to Saudi Arabia. As this seems a small travelling allowance claim for the journey will you kindly compare its details with the itinerary which, according to my pocket diary, was as follows: 10/3 Bahrein - A1 Khobar 10/3 - 15/3 A1 Khobar (Dhahiran) 15/3* Dhahiran to Mu'Aqala 16/3 Mu'Aqala to Riyadh 16/3 - 20/3 Riyadh 21/3 Rihadh - Uwaimid 22/3 Uwaimid - Duwadimi 23/3 Duwadimi - Dafine 214-/3 Dafine - Wadi Hama 25/3 Wadi Hama - Jedda 25/3 - 28/3 Halt Jedda 29/3 - 2A Ship Jedda to Suez 2/U Suez*- Cairo 2/i| - 18/1| Cairo (conference) 18/1+ - 19/U Cairo - Basra 19/U - 20/Ij. Basra - Bahrein Transport launch halt car car halt halt halt halt halt halt halt ship car halt air Will you please say whether my Travelling Claim covered these entire details. thus:' Launch Car across Arabia (Khobar to Jedda) Halts in Arabia Halts, Jedda Ship fare Jedda to Suez Car fare Suez to Cairo Halts Cairo - Bahrein to Khobar - 10 days - 10 nights (halts) - 3 days - 16 days U. Will you please inform me whether my steamship passage when leaving my M. of I. job in Bahrein by ship for Basra in the last week of October 13k3 was charged to the accounts, or whether I paid it myself. In the statement which you have sent me there is no mention of the sea passage but there is an item on 30.10.Z|6: 'Cost of Air passage and freight on excess luggage Rps. 735/U/O.' What journey is this in respect of please? /contd.5- The auditor draws my attention to a payment of Rps.200 on the 26.10 .14 .3 on transfer to Cairo, for'which he says he can find no off-setting voucher, and in the absence Ox one, which he now calls upon me to refund. There is no n.ei'tiun ot this item in the statement of drawings you have , me and so it vas almost certainly accounted for to meet some specific purpose met locally at the time (e .g. packinp- carpets and furniture and transporting to ship) but if so the voucher has gone astray. Can you kindly elucidate/ 5. Forgive me for writing at such length and putting you to trouble, but you will appreciate the difficulty in aealmg with auditor's queries in winding up the M. of I. three years after leaving the Bahrein post, and I am quite sure I owed nothing at the time of leaving, and faced as I am with their invitation to pay £162 in all out of my own pocket m the absence of vouchers which might easily have gone astray in the war, or as a result of a clerical error or two. B Cxv CUm, ^ Uxx-M H. D. H. Ranee, Esq., The Political Agency, BAHREIN.D .O.HO. sst) -1/44. POLITICAL AGENCT, BAHRAIN, 3 J»riu«ry, 1947. t ^ ^ ,/ ( Please refer to your deial official letter No.BT/64 d«ited the 14th December ? 1946# 2. The following additional inforja^tion is available here;- Your par*Kr*ph 1 (i) During the period in question expenses incurred by the Public Relations Officer on entertainments and gratuities in Bahrain and on tours, in addition to those already included in the list sent with iay previous letter were as follows 28-10-42 iintertaim^ent on tour of P.R.O. - 6s. 42-0-0 29-11-42 Dinner to Dutch released prisoners of War. Rs. 42-13-0 21-2-43 Gratuity to Wall Barkah Ks. 100- 0-0 ' to Sawaig Es. 50- 0-0 ' to Sohar Ks. 100- 0-0 Rations for c«ir -md launch crew Es. 70- 0-0 20-10-43 Expenses incurred on cineiia party at the P.R.O. •s house held on 18-10-43. Ks. 31- 0-0 30-10-43 Expenses incurred on a dinner and cinema party held by the P.R.O. on 20-10-43. Hs. 43-0-0 Your p*raar*ph 2 You drew an advance of &amp;». 1000/- against your tour expenses by Agency Voucher No.32 of July 1943. This advance was repaid by you to Government on the 7th October 1943 *nd h-is been shown on the receipt side in the October C-tsh Account of this Agency. No question of your refunding this amount to Government should therefore arise now. Your para^r^ph 3 . The details of your Travelling allowance bill d*ted the 22nd aky 1943(Agency Voucher No.40 of May 1943) are siailar to the details given by you, and cover all the expenditure incurred on halts, steamer fare, car fares and taxi fare etc. The bill also includes an additional item ' gratuities in Sa^di Arabia'- Rs. 200/-. It does not however cover launch fare from Bahrain to A1 Khobar nor car fare across Arabia( A1 Khobar to Jedda) as, presumably, no such expenses were incurred. Your para^r^ph 4 . No steamship passage from Bahrain to Basra was paid when you left your il.of I. job in Bahrain, and it is believed that your journey was actually arranged through the Navy. The item dated the 30th October 1943 ' cost of air passage and freight on excess luggage- -ks.735/4/- relates to your air passage from Bahrain to Cairo on the 20th July, 1943 to attend the llinistry of Information Conference held in ^airo in July 1943. ThisThis expenditure wiis not included in your original Travelling alio /ance bill Tov the above tour(Agency Voucher No. 15 of 10/43 for Ks. 1086/10/8). Your p^r^^raph 5. An advance of 200/- was paid to you by Agency Voucher l^o. 3o of October 1943 on your transfer to Cairo. It was stated in your Last Pay Certificate that this aaount should be refunded to the Agency. A copy of your Last Pay was sent to the Controller, Accounts Division, iinistry of Inforuation, Cairo. It appears from the books in this office that this amount of ts. 200/- has not yet been refunded to this office, and therefore renains outstanding for adjustaient. Perhaps you would arrange with the Ministry of Information, Cairo, to adjust this anount now. To Lt.Col. Bertram Thomas, O.B.E., Middle East Centre for Arab Studies Austrian Hospice, JERUSALEM.conmixmtlm. No. Secretaty to The Boa-blaj/the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to in original and has the honour to transmit to him a c?opy o^the undermentioned docu ment-^ Tor favour of return with a report in uae coarse. The political Agent Bahrain, British Kesidency $ (jnrmuto;! ar Qan ftrijil , Bahrain, &gt;1118111^. Bated.. .^.0 th.. i) e c ^ 1o e X. .3... 46 « Reference to previous correspondence; Description of Enclosure Name and Date. Subject. L.U• letter i;o.BT/54 dated ae lc ta jecei ber, 1946 from Lr. Bertram Thomas, Miudle Last Centre for Arab btuuies, Austrian Hospice, Jerusalem, to the Hon'ble tne political resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain. Accounts of tae Public Kelations Office, Bahrain i for 1941 - 4: .HO. s fo -1/44. POLITICAL AGEKCI, ^-BAHRAIN, /?*- February, 1947. To The Secretiiry to the Mon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain. MEMORANDUM«- . . I v ' ^ r Reference Residency Printed Letter i . o .3819 9 dated the 26th December, 1946. 2. De^ii official letter No.BT/54, dated the 13th December, 1946 addressed to the iion'ble Lt.Col. ff.R.Iay, C.S.I., by Lt.Col.Bertram ThoiuaS, O.B.^., is returned herewith in original. Despite the last sentence in the first paragraph of iir.Bertram Thomas* letter, he wrote the very next day, 14th December, 1946, to this office requesting the same particulars from Captain Ranee and a reply furnishing the information required by him has already been sent to Jerusalem. In the circumstances, no further report is deemed necessary- 'a '[l. Political Agent, Bahrain. Lwr 10^GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. DEPARTMENT. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). ^3 [N.K, This is an ORWINAL message, sent by AIR MAIL which provides a means_ of communication more. expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is inteiided to he treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of cu telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department. PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY -65/35. Simla ■/XM/i/// 1 /' Bahrain, /2^ February, '''47' POLITICAL, Bahrain y, lM To My printed letter No.3819-66/36, dated the 26th December 1946. Accounts of the Public Relations Oifice, Bahrain, for 1941—43. 2. Grateful for early reply. I = KEPGU = The issue of the above has been authorised for Secretary to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf. No Bahrain Recebt S. 44. MGIPC—S2—842(Gnl)MFP—(6806/M-620)—29-842—25,000. II &lt;6^V . k c y^f7 ■ - ^ /i w- OFFICE OF THE ACCOUNTANT GENERAL CENTRAL REVENUES NEW DELHI. \*h .(0- No. TA 10-3/309S the From U o The ACCOUNTANT GENERAL, CENTRAL REVENUES, r-'- ' .'•&gt;! ncjjn.. .tfhz.l'tk.- The Accountant ' India office, White Hell, London, S^ # l« Subject:- cred t in roapect 01 ti»« reiund of she re of the political Agency of petxrolo'ara Products for 8,9 arid 10/46 # Reference:- Tour No. A.11232/16-MI dated 16.10.'IS. An extract of p^rn I of your letter ouotod above is being forwardod to tno Foliticfal As ent Bahiain and on receipt of th^ reply, requisite iiiforrcation will be furnished# As re^-ird i jiari 2 of your letter under r-jVoroncq, a reference is invited to t lis office letter No. TA 10-3/2037 dated IS.11,46® •/Q S^h (HARMAL: 3ING1I.) No. TA 10-3/3100 L, . A3ST?. ACOOmT3 OF-IOtfR. Copy along with a copy of Para J of India Office Letter No, AG-11252/46-MI dated 16.10.46, forwarded to the Political Agent Ju^rain lor t oriiishing the information at an early date. ' The credit in question were included in his cash accounts for 10,11, and 12/45, i ^ Asstt. Accounts Officer. Kof para 1 • Copy ^of letter No. A.G. 11232/46 MI. dated 16th 0ctobei#46, from the Accountant General, India Officer, White Hall London, SW. I, to the A .G.oR* • New Delhi. Credits in respect of the refund of the share of the political Agency of petroleum products for the months of August, September and October^S. am directed to refer to the credits of Es. 40.15{£3:1:5), fis. 34,93 (£2:11;10) and Rs« 40.? (£3:0:8) afforded in the schedules of ohe 0»A.C* for the months of November *45, December*45 and January*46 respectively on the above account and to request that you will furnish further details stating in which schedules of the O.A.C. debits in respect of the corresponding expenditure have been or will be raised.No . rr&amp; Political Agency, Bahrain. Dated, 6th February, 1947. To The Accountant General, Central Revenue^ MEW DELHI. Memorandum tA Reference your endorsement No.T.a.10-3/3100 d:ted 13th December, 1946, regarding credits in respect of the relund oi the share oi* the Political Agency of the petroleum ' ( i0 ^ ac ^ s 1 or murA ths of August, September and October 1945. '/• ^ its oi Ro.62/2, '-,61/2 and fc, r /9/4/- on account of the cost of petroleum products were raised by Agency voucher os. 21 of October 194$, 10 of Tovember 1945 and 16*of December 4o respectively. These amounts included share of the Political Agency and were credited in 10, 11 and 12/46 by the Public Kelations Office, Bahrain. l{/£ /YA 6j for Political A^ent, Bahrain. / 1 iiu^r yi _ yPublic Relations Office, Persian Gulf,- Bahrain. i^Ai LKxTi^ From Mr. G. W. Jackson, Public Relations Officer in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain. To Director, Information Department, India Office, London. 'O. //jy/ Dated 19th July, 1947. I have taken charge of the office of the Public Relations Officer in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain, with effect from 17th July, 1947, forenoon, on the departure of Mr. C.J. ^elly, O.B.iS., on leave to the United Kingdom. 1 ublic Relations Officer, Persian Gulf, Bahrain. Copy forwarded with compliments to:- 1. xhe Accou t^nt-General, Central Revenue, New Delhi. 2. The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain 3. The Political Agent, Bahrain. &gt;T-, ^0^6^ $ No. I486-S• Persian Gulf Residency, Bahrain, the 12th August 1947^ To ■ 1 I The Political Agent, , Bahrain. Copy to The Public Relations Officer, Persian Gulf, Bahrain. The Accoun tan t-General, Central Revenues, New Delhi. MEMORANDUM. S /w . ?&gt; v -'rujy Referen^^Publio Relations Officer's Express Letter No. 1-119 dated the 31st July 1947. 2. You are hereby authorized to make advances in round sums to the Public Relations Officer, Bahrain. The amounts so advanced should be debited in your accounts to His Majesty's Governments publicity expenditure in the Persian Gulf . Sd. A. C • GA1XOWAY. Political Resident, Persian Gulf. Attested. for Se(p1retary to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf. RHL. No ri u iiio* /—* /3 £ Public Relations Olfice, Persian Gulf, '.Bahrain# Datec 16th November t 1947# C^HT I; IGATjl, Certified that we have respectively handed, over and taken over charge of the office of the Public Relations Office in the Persian Gulf, on the 18th lioveraber, 1947, afternoon, ' / HKLItVKL Oi'FICKR y / 4 }h - RbLIEVI^-OFF ICLR Copy forwarded with compliments to:- • H. .Brook, ii.sq. , Director, Information jepartment, India Office, Whitehall,S.I 2o The Account ant-General, Centrzl Revenues, .New Delhi# 3* The Hon # ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain# The Political ^ent, !3ahrain» . v0 Mo.217I-S PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY ' ^ BAHRAIN , the 17th December, 1947 n I The Political Agent, BAHRAIN v : ' Copy to:- The Public Relations Officer, BAHRAIN MEMORANDUM Reference attached copy of Public Relations Officer's memorandum No.5-158 dated the 28th November, 1947. 2. Please receive from Public Relations Officer and credit to His Majesty's Government the sum of Rs.10,352-9-9 mentioned therein. 3. Please also receive from Public Relations Officer and credit to His Majesty's Government in future any amounts recovered by him from the sale of publications etc. For Secretary to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf 'O?/-&amp; ~ N o.5-158 PUBLIC RELATIONS OFFICE Persian Gulf BAHRAIN Dated 28th November, 1947. The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahraim. Memorandum Reference your memorandum No.l596-S dated 4th September, 1947. 2. The sum of Rs.10,352/9/9 was accummulated over a period of years under sub-head 'Y Receipts .for photographs, films, publications etc.' as follows By balance from sales of publications for the period 5/8/42 to 31/3/46 By sales of publications, photographs and rent of films for the period 1/1/46 to 31/3/47 By sales of publications from 1/4 to 31/8/47 2717 15 3 6775 866 1 6 9 - TOTAL 10352 9 9 'LB' Sd/- C.J. Pelly, Public Relations Officer, Persian Gulf, BAHRAIN,vt&gt; A &gt; U No. 2 - '3 Pulillc Relation# Office, Persian Gulf, Bahrain ». Dated 11th February,.1948 To The Political A4,ent, Bahrain® Memoranaum, O \ 19 1 j* , 0^^ In continuation of my letter No* 2-146 dated 19th October,1947o ^shall !®e •*ateful if an advance of a further sujd of £»375 to meet my expenditure for the quarter let January to 31it March,1948, is made to me# »V Public Relations Officer, v Persian Gulf, ^ Bahrain. Copy forwarded with compliments to:- 1- R.W♦Brock,Ssq», Director,Information Department, India Office,Whitahal1»W♦I» 2- The Accountant General,Central Revenue^New Delhi. 3- The Hon^le the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf^ Bahrain•Telegram From To No, Date IWC. A.G.C.B.5 New De^hi. Political Agent, Bahrain. TA 2191 6th and received the 8th March, 1948. Please telegraph by the 15th ularch approximate amount advanced or to be advanced to the Public Relations Officer, Persian Gulf up to the 31st March. ACCOUNTS.Office of the A.G.C.R. ^ ^ NEW DELHI. Copy of telegram dated the 6th larch 1948 from the A. G.C.R. jNev/ Delhi, to the POLITICAL AGENT BAHB UN (Persian .Gulf) . • • • • Please telegraph 'by 15th ;iarch approximate amount advanced or to be advanced to Public Relation Officer Persian Gulf upto 31st March, No.TA• 3-7/2192 Copy by post forwarded to the Political Igent Bahrain. 2, The information is required by the A.G. Commonwealth Relc'tinns Off 3 ce,London and may be furnished immediatelyoPublic Relations Office t Persian Oulf f Bahrain. Dated 24th Harch, 1946, CH nKGi Cii.HTlflCATL. I Certified tnat w© nave respectively nanded over and taken over charge of the office of the Public Relations Officer in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain, on the 24th iUrch t 1948,forenoon♦ C OFT ic?:* RfcLI-iV XMfy^GfW IC£R Copy forwarded with coriplinjents to:— I* R.W.J5roolc t £s%» t Director, Information Department. C /? rj&gt; IndAa^iiiCi^oc, Uhltehall, S .W.I. 2. The Accountant-General, Central Revenues, New Delhi. % The Hon*ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain, y 4. The Political A^ent, Bahrain. A v1 * Public Halations Office, Persian Gulf, No* 2-SQ Bahrain# Dated 10th June, 1948. W\CA ' ^ v X To . oX\ The Political Agent, Bahrain. SAHRA^ '■ Memorandum, I shall be grateful if an advance of a sum of £.300 t» meet my expenditure f«r the quarter 1st npril to. ^ 30th June,1948, is made t» me. C— . Public Relations Officer, Persian Gulf, Bahrain. Copy forwarded with compliments to:- 1-R.Brock,Ssq..Director, I. iddle Last information Department• Foreign Office, x ' London. 2- His Excellency the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain.I ■ No./fJ7 -1/44. © Political Age' cy, BahraJ n, Dated the 19th June, 1948. To The Public Relations Officer, Persian Gulf, Bahrain. Memorandum. Reference your momorandu- '0.2.59 dated the 10th June 1948. 2. A cheque for £5.4000/- ( equivalent of £ 300/- f) Rs. 13-5-4 per £) on account of your advance for the quarter 1st April to 30th June 1948, is enclosed herewith. 3. Please acknowledge receipt. foik Political Agent, Bahrain. MS,No.l/44. Political Agency, ^ Bahrain, Dated the 4th December,1948, To The Public Relatlois Officer, Bahrain. Memorandum. Reference y&gt;ur nemorandaa 2-118 dated the 27th November, 1948. 7 . \ 2. A cheque for us. 3659-12 -0 ( Rupees three thousand six hundred and fifty nine and ann«-us twelve only'^ being equivalent of £ 276/- is forwarded herewith. It is requested that the attached receipt in duplicate may please^be signed and returned to this office. 1 ^^fo^^litical Agent, Bahrain. i:im Ke. Pub/2-30 'A v Public Relations Office, Bahrain, Persian Gulf. Dated 10th February,1949 To The Political Bahi^ain. S • I/ernoranduBit In continuation of mj letter No•2-116 dated 27th November,1948» 2» I shall be grateful if an advance of a further sum of £» 256 to meet my expenditure for the quarter 1st January to 3121 I. : arch, 1949, is made to me* Public Relations Officer, Bahrain, Persian Gulf. Copy forwarded with compliments to:~ 1 - R.W. Brtck, Esq., Director, Middle East Information Department, Foreign Office, Lond ©n• 2 - His Excellency the Political Reside in the psrsien Gulf, Bahrain.v&lt; if I Public Kolatlons Office, Bahrain, Persian Gulf. No,Pub/1- 7? July n , 1949* cHAiME emirk-m* Certified that we have respectively handed over and taken over charge of the Enbliu Office of the Public Relations Officer In the Per3 lab Gulf, Bahrain on July /, 1949. CT/9. F*. BBLISVED OFFICER HELIiTV ING OFFICER H.Mc.C, Andrew J.A.F. Gethin Copy forwarded, with conplinents, toi- 1. Major General A.J.c. Pollock 5 director. Middle East Information Department. Foreign Office, London. 2.- Accountant, Finance Department,(Information Accounts}, Foreign Office, London, 3. Els Excellency the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain. 4 » Political Agwit, Bahrain. f-a* k'tip , l-hill \ u -3 M 1U' ^ ^ ' ^ U-^ ^. O' '^. ' &lt;9*^ 4 t^' U1 This amount was made to Mr. Thomas directly by the Treasurer as a Personal Advance, and therefore the P.R.O. Is not In a position to state whether It was accounted for y as an official expenditure^, by Mr. Thomas on his return from the tour In question. In the form of travelling allowance claimed, or not, for If It was accounted for, which probably was the case, a copy of the receipt Issued to him by the Treasurer would certainly be available at the Treasury as well as an entry of the recovery would have been made In the Treasury accounts. I am of Mr. Thomas 1 opinion that It could be scarcely the case that the Rs. 1000/- had not been recovered by the Treasurer when the T.A. of Rs. 10^6/10/8 was paid to him, for In a similar occasion at an earlier date a Personal Advance had been made to him when he was proceeding to Cairo via Saudi Arabia on 10/3/43 and was recovered by the Treasurer when the T.A. of Rs. 1238/7 for the Journey was made to him, vide T.A. Bill dated 16th May, 1943, Voucher No. 22. Chalam No. 16 dated 22nd May 1943 was Issued by the Treasury to Mr. Thomas for this payment. As there was no reason why the Personal Advances made to Mr. Thomas by the Treasury should have been recorded In the P.R.O*8 accounts, no such records were made, and therefore the elucidation of the point In question could only be made by the Agency Accountant Para 3. —— , . , . . The details of the T.A. Bill dated 16th May, 1943, based on Mr. Thomas* Travelling Claims for the tour In question, are almost similar to this Itinerary, save for a slight difference In the total of days spent In the tour for which the T.A. Bill shows 41 days, while It Is only 40 days In his Itinerary. His Travelling Claims did not cover launch fare from Bahrain to A1 Khobar nor car fare across Arabia (A1 Khobar to Jedda)i as probably there were no expenses Incurred. Para 4. No steamship passage from Bahrain to Basrah was paid when Mr. Thomas left his M. of I. job In Bahrain. Mr. Rahlm Bukhsh Thinks that Mr. '^homas 1 Journey to Basrah was arrar^ged throughP.R.O. The Navy. The Item dated 30/10/43 'Coat of Mr Passage and freight en excess luggage Rs.735' in our statement, to which Mr, Thomas refers, covers his air passage from Bahrain to Cairo on 20/7/43 to attend the Officers conference held in ' Cairo in July, 1943, (^is item was not included in the original T.A, Bill for the tour. Voucher No. of the Treasury for ), vide T. Bill dated nil, month of July, 1943, Voucher No. of list of payments for October, 1943, Para 5. This is also a Personal Advance which might be elucidated by the Agency Accountant. There is no record for it in the P.R.O.'s accounts. May return to the Agency Accountant pi.? D.1.47. cjljl* * «-•— f? ? A h A. n , 1 Ow 1 fa tyx - fw - l &amp; h 3 ^&lt;^^0 fvu . A V 'vs rtU OCX'. \ ^ ^ ^ OL v. fXo 'SL^v j - \jl fiUO Xa' A rv CWs. • O Uo-vv% Ca &lt; wv ^ cv c«c^U ^ ^ o ■ '• W\ A ^ r ^'</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000257_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1040</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000257</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1040</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 1/44 Publicity Officer, Bahrain'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1940/1949</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-04-01T00:04:34</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (240 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in chronological order from the front to the rear of the file. Circled serial numbers (red for received correspondence; blue/black for issued correspondence) refer to entries in the notes at the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation system in use commences at 1 on the front cover, and continues through to 249 on the last folio before the back cover. The sequence is written in pencil, often underlined, and appears in the top right hand corner of the recto page of each folio. Foliation anomalies: ff. 1, 1A; ff. 24, 24A; ff. 46, 46A; ff. 88, 88A; ff. 153, 153D. The following numbers are omitted from the sequence: 12, 14, 16, 49, 51-59. The following pagination ranges occur: 179-180, 186-187.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file relates to the appointment and service of holders of the post of Publicity Officer in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain (from 1942 known as Public Relations Officer in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain), including Bertram Sidney Thomas (served December 1941 to October 1943).The papers, which include correspondence, telegrams, memoranda, charge certificates (recording the handing-over of duties between officers), notifications, last pay certificates, letter of guarantee for a bill of lading; and other forms and certificates, cover the following topics: travel arrangements; correspondence concerning charge certificates and last pay certificates; appointment and transfer; pay and allowances; advances of pay; attendance at a conference of Publicity Officers in Cairo, Egypt, May 1940; transport of personal effects; recovery of sum paid to servants at Bushire, July 1940; Government of India confirmation of the continuance of the post of Publicity Officer for the duration of the War, August 1940; certificate confirming that the holder was a Government Servant; leave and leave salary; payment of Indian Income Tax; bill from merchant in Bahrain, December 1941; bill for transmitter hire, July 1946; and correspondence between Bertram Thomas and the Political Agency, Bahrain concerning the accounts of his service as Public Relations Officer, Bahrain, December 1946 to January 1947.The Arabic language content of this file consists of the bilingual letterhead of a Bahrain merchant.The correspondence (the main body of papers in the file) is dated 14 March 1940 to 11 July 1949. The closing date in the overall date range is provided by an entry in the notes at the rear of the file.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Public Relations Officer, Persian Gulf, Bahrain</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Publicity Officer, Persian Gulf</namePart></name></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000257#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>