<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00015d_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T18:25:38.443Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">File No. 8/40 Collection No.I I N T ROPUCTORY. r# : In introducing the last issue of this we gave details of important decisions relatang to future '^Id food control which had been taken at the final plenary session of the U.K.O.B’ood and Agricultural Organisation. On 20th June the Combined Food Board was dissolved and is now superseded by the new world food allocating organisation, the International Emergency Food council, ^hi Council consists of nineteen member nations and . the Soviet Union had representatives present v.v meeting. The Argentine Representative present but d^ not vote; he explained that instructions from his Govern had not yet been' received but ^vere expected at any women The Aroerican Secretary of Agriculture, Mr .Clinton P.Anderson has *een t tt p P and under him will i unction a ooiioxaa- ^ of S nine 'nations^ in addition to the ^ited Kingdom^tte United States and Canada, the following S1 . elected to membership of this Central Comnuttee - Argentine, Australia, China, France, India and Denma^. ine election of the Argentine is contingent on h„r * ^ me nib or of Iho 1«S«1 1 *CI. The seventeen Comodity Conmttees of the CorrfciBed Food Board are being taken over intact ^ ^ only the membership of these Committees is sub oct to ona 0 h iS , hlation-^^fact^Le'Filiofto^alre^ recoraaended shouid_ternuh^e on 3^t or earlier if world conditions permit, out ^ its replacement of the Cor^ined Food_Bo a ^ purely for war purposes, yi , vA&amp;er =ohere of influence produce an organisation vath a ^mder^sph^^^^^ Qf and action and thus greatly licf availabilities all important information on food ouppiic^, and requireKehtsiCEREi\LS - 2 - POOD SECTION. 1» Wheat/Flour. . The intreduction of 'bread and flour rationing in Great Britain is a pointer to the fact that the acute shortage throughout the world Is only now beginning to make itself truly felt. This should set an example to all countries of the world to conserve their present supplies to the utmost. In addition it reflects the spirit of one nation to contribute every available ton of grain to avert the coming crisis. This crisis will not develop in the Middle East for another two months, for flour in stock and already on the water mil be sufficient to meet all our commitments up to 31st August on the same basis as that of the past few months. It is therefore now and during the next two months that all M.E.countries should endeavour to conserve their supplies, for after 31st August the supply position becomes uncertain and mil depend entirely on the wheat or flour allocated to the Middle East for loading during the months of July, August and September* As reported in the May Monthly Letter, these loadings may well be drastically reduced, and if in addition, flour is loaded and not wheat, the situation automatically worsens and we will not be able to meet all consumers’ requirements. These hard facts must be faced squarely for there is little doubt that the period ahead will be more difficult than any experienced, during the war years. We therefore most earnestly request all.Middle East countries to co-operate who1eheartedly by the internal collection and use of their local harvests and the maximum use of adulterants. 2. Rice. No improvement in the supply position is envisaged and in consequence no increase in the present allocations is likely for some tine to come. 3. Sugar. We are able to report that the sugar prograrxies' referred to in the last Monthly Letter have been agreed by London; providing no unforeseen difficulties arise, all countries are assured of their supplies until early next year, on the same basis as during past years. Shipments, however, still tend to slip, but stocks in the pool are sufficient to meet any serious emergency thus caused. A-3- 4. FERTILISERS. At a recent meeting held in Washington preliminary estimates of the amounts of chemical fertilisers which may he available for crops to he harvested in 1947j indicate that there may be an increase in the production of all three plant nutrients; on the other hand judging by the requests of countries now before the Fertiliser Committee of the T.E.F.C. there will still be a deficiency of supply over demand; 30/o in the case of nitrogen and some in the case of potash. Substantial increases in nitrogen output would be realised if the nitrogen production capacity in Germany a.nd Japan could be fully employed. Some 400 to 500 thousand tons more nitrogen per annum could also be produced if the full synthesizing capacity of the U.S.Government nitrogen plants were utilized; but before this can be done, additional equipment and additional facilities for converting the raw ammonia to fertiliser material will-have to be installed. In general the fertiliser picture', indicates that supplies will be short in every major producing area in the world. 5. SEED POTATOES. All seed potato requirements have now been submitted to London. At a special meeting recently held in Washington to discuss urgent food problems the impprtant role which potatoes play in the diets of many peoples was stressed; it was advocated that steps should be taken, to make a larger quantity of this foodstuff available for human consumption and the follov/ing recommendations were made:- (a) that governments should give consideration to acquiring the crop and to the control of harvesting! distribution, and consumption; (b) that governments should discourage the harvesting of min crop potatoes before they are fully matured, except in countries producing two or more potato, crops annually; (c) that the use of edible potatoes for alcohol and other industrial purposes should be drastically curtailed and where possible prohibited; (d) that potatoes should only be fed to livestock in cases where it is impossible to make them available for human consumption; (e) that countries Y/hich have surplus potatoes that cannot readily be exported be encouraged to mix potatoes in bread and so ease the grain 'position. 6. TEA. All Middle East countries have now been advised of their individual allocations from India and Ceylon covering the period April, 1946, to March, 1947. It is regretted that in some cases, alloc.: tions have been reduced and although strong representations have been made to London it is unlikely that '.the Tea Committee will be in a position to review the Programme, until September. Should further supplies become.available at that time everyeffort will be made to make good such reductions that it has nov\r been necessary to make./13 -4- 7. COFFEE a As pointed out in last month's issue the Ministry of Food wishes to he advised imuediately the negotiations far the purchase of quantities allocated have been completed. We shall be grateful therefore to have your co-operation and assistance in this matter. 8. OILS AM) FATS. Groundnuts. ^he~ supply position remains unchanged as the Indian Government is still rigidly maintaining the embargo on the export of Groundnuts from India. 9. Sesam e. A small allocation of Sesame Seed to the Middle East has been granted by the Government of India and although insufficient to meet total Middle East requirements it will assist, in the present emergency ;the most necessitous cases. When official approval has been received countries will be notlfieu. 10. Copra &amp; Coconut Oils. We are continually asking London for further information regarding the surplus availability from British East Africa and we are hoping to receive very soon some definite news concerning further shipments to the Middle East. - 11. Soap.. Middle East countries are fully conversant by now with..the serious shortage of oil seeds prevailing throughout the world and the fact that the present urgent need to make use of all supplies for edible purposes reduces the availability of oil for the manufacture of soap. It will greatly assist if manufacturing Countries keep their production of soap to an absolute minimum and all Middle East countries should practise the utmost econoiry in disposing of- their present stocks* MISCELLANEOUS. FOODSTUFFS. 12. Tinned Fish. i . • We are still awaiting, from certain countries, details of their specific requirements of varieties and choice of supply areas. London are urgently awaiting complete details and countries are advised, in their own interests, to forward this information to tis without further d$lay otherwise we cannot accept any responsibility should they be excluded from participating in the forthcoming distribution. Nil returns are required.13« Desiccated Coconut Interested Middle East countries have been advised of a further allocation ex Ceylon and we would remind them tha' orders must be placed for the full quantity before the 1st October, 1946. After this date the Ceylon Authorities reserve the right to re-alloc-te such amounts which have not then been claimed. 14. Dairy Products. It is inportant to note that details of licences issued for supplies from Australia or New Zealand should be cabled to the Dominion Authorities, with a copy to this Mission. Failing such notification to the G-cvernment. of Australia and New Zealand export facilities will be withheld and shipment delayed. We ask for your co-oper' ? tion in this matter.6 - M/JERIALS SECTION. 1. TIMBER. Sone countries appear to 1 oe under the impression that there are only certain approved loading areas for timber* For your information and guidance we would point out that as timber is not subject to allocation you are at liberty to obtain your requirements, within agreed, quotas, from any country in a positlor to supply, other than Germany and Roumania* 2. RUBBER. The Rubber Directorate of the Ministry of Supply have requested that when allocations are made orders should be placed at the earliest opportunity to enable this Mission to forward full details as to import licence number, consignee, consignor,etc 3. TIN. We are still endeavouring to obtain a firm allocation of tin to meet the Middle East second half 1%^ demands* Details should be in our hands in the near future. It has come to our notice that certain Middle East countries are endeavouring'to obtain Tin Metal in excess of their allocation and from loading areas which are not approved. In sich cases the Tin Committee has at our request cancelled these allocations. The only approved loading areas for Tin Metal are the United Kingdom and Belgium, and orders should only be placed within the allocations agreed by this Mission* It is in the interest of Middle East countries to abide by these restrictions for in the long run they vdll receive a much larger percentage of thair actual needs than would otherwise be the case. This Mission is continuously demanding an increased allocation for the Middle East as a whole and if it had not been for our insistence certain countries would not hove received any allocation and others considerably less than that already granted* For your information and guidance the. original allocation for the first half of 1946 amounted to approximately of requirements for the year v/hereas after strong representations had been made by this Mission this was increased to l+Oyo of cctual requirements to be supplied during the first half of the year. We ore hopeful of obtaining the balance of 60fo for supply during the second half 4. TEXTILES. (a) Cotton Yarn ex India* This Mission has now been officially notified that no quar whatsoever of cotton yarn will be made available for the Middle Ea from India during the period July/December,1946. The reason for this has been stated to be the acute shortage of yam to meet India’s internal requirements, (b)' Cotton Piecegoods and Cotton Yam ex Italy, For'the info mat ion of all Middle East countries we would mention that private trade between Italy and the sterling area may now be re-opened subject to the proviso that in all cases trade /commodities-7~ corxiodities which are on the Reserved Commodity List or controlled hy International Committees should be v&amp;thin any allocations made by these corxiittees* Proposed exports to Italy of Short List goods should first be referred to this Mission. This resumption of trade is on a merchant to merchant basis and commercial concerns within the Middle Last are advised to establish immediate contacts with merchants in Italy in order to obtain firm-offers of cotton piecegoods and yam. 5. JUTE /ltD JUTE PRODUCTS. Vie have not yet received from India the allocations of jute products for the second half 1946 and the first half 1947* We are informed that the commodity is still in very short supply and that there is lifcilfc likelihood of an increase in the next period’s allocations. This Mission will do everything in its power to obtain as large a proportion of the available supplies for the Middle East as is x^ossible. 6. HIDES AND LEATHER. Middle East countries will have received our Circular Saving to the effect that hides and le ther have now been removed from the Short List. At a meeting held in Washington on 26th June,1946&gt; the International Hides, Skins and Leather Committee reviewed the present position and agreed to terminate all its activities as from that date. All previous recommendations by the Committee are to be regarded as revoked. This implies complete cessation of international control, allocation and price and reversion to free market. A further statement is expected in the immediate future from London, in which it is anticipated the implications of this cessation of control will be indicated. On -receipt of this information a further circular will be addressed to Middle East countries. 7* COAL AND COKE. (a) Commercial Requirenent s. Shrpnents are being ntaXntained well within programme and there is every possibility that quotas will be shipped^ in full. Please bear in mind the fact that coal and coke are still in extremely short supply and every effort should be made to ensure that these commodities are used only incases where other fuels are unsuitable. 1 Railway Requirements. There is no change Tn the shipping programme to meet the coal requirements of the Middle East railways and supplies are coming forward as and when arranged by the Military Authorities. The tonnage required to carry these cargoes is now charged to the civil ana not the Military shipping programme. (c) Coal Bunk ers. . , n As stated in the May Monthly Letter this Mission has now^assumed responsibility for the programming of coal bunkers for certain Middle East ports. We have already dealt with the requirements of Haifa Port, Famagus1&amp;and Djibouti which ports are the only ones for which we have received any justification for supply. In the case /of- 8 - of Haifa and Famagusta only small quantities have been approved as these two ports are not normal bunkering places but it is necessary to maintain a small stock to meet emergency ,, toppin'?' ,, requirements and to anable vessels arriving v/ith depleted bunkers to move to an approved bunkering depot. If, however, there are any other countrie s who consider that they have certain ports which should hold coal bunker stocks they should immediately furnish a statement of their requirements, names of firms capable of handling this work and justification for supplies. 8, HHWSPRTbT* IlSa countries will have received our Circular Saving advising them that Newsprint has been removed from the Short fist and that they are now at liberty to obtain their requirements of this commodity from any country in a position to supply, 9. TIRES AND TUBES. Advice has been received from the Board of Trade that they have now established allocations of tyres and tubes for the third quarter of 19A6. details will be communicated within the next few days. We are at present negotiating with the British Stores Bisposal Mission regarding the allocation of surplus ¥,D,tyres and tubes. It is anticipated that a very large quantity of these will become available and as soon as details of sizes have been received we will advise the quantities allocated to each country from this source. Quotas are likely to be revised in the light of these allocations. 1°o SU RPLUS W.D.STORES. In our May Monthly Letter we drew attention to the availability of certain surplus cookers which were being offered by the Ministry of Supply, Simla, India. We have now been advised that the quantity is 9? 000 and not 900 and that communications should be addressed to Ministry of Supply Eastern Group Section,Simla, and not to the Disposals Section, •i°, R ELEASE OF W.D.STORES. J.T-C,procedure as established by G-.H.Q. Administrative Instruction No. 61 covering the Emergency Diversion of Service Stocks for Civil End-use has now been abolished. Application for release of W.D.Stores will henceforth be sponsored by the appropriate British Authority in British administered countries and by H.B.M,Diplomatic Missions in independent countries. These requests will then be passed to the British Middle East Office with the necessary certificate of justification who will in turn pass them to the British Stores Disposal Mission* Full instructions as to the new procedure are contained in British Middle East Office Circular Letter No*97 (3^) dated 17th June,1946*PROGRAM-.ES SECTION 1. MIDDLE EAST SHORT LIST.. During the month we were able to notify the decontrol of SL.32 - Newsprint. As this item only was involved, it was not considered necessary to publish an amendment* 2. PROCUREMENT PROGRAM IE. The June Amendment Schedule is in the course of preparation and will he published within the next few days* Tea allocations fibr the period April, 1946, to March, 1947# were notified in our Savingram dated June* The units of measure a,re given in thousands of pounds, whilst in the Procurement Programme these allocations have been calculated ffbr the Middle East in nett metric tons; for propjraix'dng purposes it is necessary to keep measures of weight uniffbrn. We would refer to the information contained in No.73 Circular Saving doted 11th June. Only very small quantities of many of the oils and fats contained under the heading of SL.6. are required in the Middle East and these are used mainly flbr industrial or medicinal purposes. These oils and fats are normally subject to specific allocations by the C*F;B. but, as the tabled requirements are snail we were of the opinion that the procurement of such quantities would not adversely af 1*001 the world supply position. We have therefore obtained London’s agreement that Middle -East countries my proceed with the procurement of quantities tabled in their respective procurement pro gramme s without awaiting specific C.P.B. allocations. This information is conveyed to interested Middle East countries in the Circular Saving mentioned above, together with the supply areas from which supplies of each item are most readily available* If countries have a demand Jfbr any of the items in question and have not tabled a requirement but nevertheless require supplies for essential purposes, they should submit the case to us for consideration in the usual way and should not issue import licences until they have received from us confirmation that a requirement figure has been established in their programme* I mmeeamm■INTRODUCTORY. Indications of the world food production during the year 1546-47 have been given in the third of the series of surveys prepared for the Famine Emergency Committee in Washington. The report stated that present conditions gave promise of a world wheat crop considerably larger than that of the year 1945-46, a near-record crop in prospect in North America, a substantial increase in Europe, North Africa and Turkey, and a bigger acreage in the Southern Hemisphere# These increases in production, however, will be largely offset by a smaller carry-over, particularly in bread grains, thus leaving the Yrorld’s total food supplies gjKv still on an emergency level. Increased quantities of rice are ^ ’ expected but, even so, production will still be far below pre-war average• It will be realised from this report that, although there are prospects of increased supplies during the latter half of this year and in 1947, the critical world food shortage will continue and the incidence of any wide-spread drought in the months immediately ahead might well be even more disastrous than the effect of the drought which developed in 1945 and early 1946. In this connection it is heartening to note that the drought is broken in New Zealand and that the Australian Winter wheat crop has increased by 17%.POOD SECTION. CEREALS. * Wb.e at/llour. As predicted in our June Monthly Letter, the supply of wheat, which continues to cone forward in the form of flour, ie beginning to become precarious, Whilst the meagre supplies now in stock and shipments already on the water are sufficient to meet the consumption requirements of all countries until the end of September, there are signs that the period thereafter will be critical. Loadings during September nay be a negligible figure. It is for this reason that we once again find it necessary to .. request all countries to endeavour, in whatever way possiole, to collect the maximum quantity of wheat from their own harvests. .The period between October to December inclusive is likely to be the climax of the present world shortage in the Middle East and it vd 11 be during this period that countries may have to rely upon their own resources for the Is.rger part of their consumption requirements. In this connection it v/ould .be oi great help to us if each country would review their requirements of imported wheat/flour and report at the earliest possible date .any reductions they are able to accept in their monthly releases ex pool stodks for the months of September, October, November ana December, 2 • R, ic 0 • Although there has been no improvement in the present ^ sup jly situation, it is hoped that we may shortly be in a position to supply all countries with their fourth quarter allocations. 3. Sugar. For the past two or three months we find that the shipments against our loading programmes have been slipping considerably. Due to the fact that we were holding emergency supplies in the pool to offset these delays, no serious consequences arose except in one case. However, loadings are now being brought up to schedule, and it is hoped that within the next five or six weeks* loadings will be coming forward according to programme. h. FERTILISERS. Details of the allocations made by the Fertiliser Committee of the I,E,F,C,of nitrogenous fertilisers to Middle East countries have now been sent to all M.E. Governments and with some exceptions are ap-oroximately 8% of the actual requirements submitted. No details .of delivery are yet known but when these are received countries wall be informed.5. SEED POTATOES. Wc have asked London for confirmtion that the requirements of Middle East countries forU*K. seed potatoes submitted at the beginning of this month vd.ll be met in full by the Ministry of Food and delivered at the required time# As soon as this confirmation is received countries vdll be informed* It is pointed out that the Ministry of Food, London, are the sole exporters of seed potatoes from the U.K* 6* TEA. Strong representations have been made throughout the month regarding the allocation of tea from India and Ceylon to Middle East countries. In our Circular Saving dated 16 th July,1946* v;e informed all countries that they were in a position to supplement their present allocations of Tea from China, Japan and Formosa. A further meeting of the Tea Committee' of the I.E.F.C* took place on 31 st July, 1946, and we shall report any changes in allocations as soon as we receive them, 7. OILS AMD FATS (including Oi l Cake.) There is no prospect whatsoever of any immediate improvement in the supply position of oils and fats. Strenuous efforts hove been made during the month to overcome almost famine conditions in some territories and surplus W.D.ghee and palm oil has helped in a small degree to relieve the position. Small allocations of sesame Seed from India have been notified to those Countries having an established programme, Wc are in communication with London regarding suxoplies of copra and coconut oil from East Africa. 8. THE TED FISH . • At the end of March we circulated a questionnaire regarding tinned fish requirements, and allocations have now been made to those countries who had replied* There seems little point in those countries'who have not replied submitting details at this stage, 9. DESICCATED COCOMJT. Increases in allocations of desiccated coconut from Ceylon have been notified to the countries concerned but attention is again drawn to the fact that any quotas not taken U|3 before 1st October, 1946* may be re-allocated elsewhere by the Controller of Imports, Exports &amp; Exchange, Colombo• 1°. COCOA 'BEAUS♦ During the month details of allocations of cocoa beans and cocoa butter have been advised to interested countries but it should oe clearly understood that cocoa butter can only be imported at tile expense of cocoa beans, in the praportion of 1 ton of butter to 2,5 tons of cocoa beans. 11. CASTOR OIL. Confirmation has now been received that U.K.is unable at present to. permit the export of castor oil,whether medicinal,industrial,sulphonated or unsulphonated. It is suggested that M.S.countries should obtain their supplies from Tripolitania, where an exportable surplus exists. The Indian supply position at present seems uncertain but it is prooable that at q L later date a certain amount may be forthcoming from that source-K- * 12. MIDDLE EAST PROCUREMENT PROGRAMS Details of the allocations of tho iter-is referred to above and of any nmendiuents to tho Middle East Procurement Programme v/ere given in Amendment Schedule No.8 dated 3'lst July, 1946, the relative copies have been despatched. 13. MIDDLE EAST SHORT LIST. The 5th ihiendiaeiit Sdiedule was issued to all countries on the 22nd of the month and confirms the deletion, which had already been advised by Savingran, of newsprint and all items of leather and hides. This Amendment Schedule also includes the item SL.19 - Edible Nuts - which has not been deleted and is no longer subject to control by this Mission. 14. IMPORT LICENSING. We are receiving many details of import licences which have been issued by countries which, although covered by the Procurement Programme, do not conform with allocations, e.g. licences for Cheese from Holland, when a territory has allocations from Australia and New Zealand only. It is important, in respect of all MESL.starred items (except those items of oils required for industrial purposes which were• mentioned in our Circular Saving 73 of 11th June,i946) that licences are only issued in accordance with approved allocations as notified by us end included in the Procurement Programme. We are also receiving instances of replacement licences which do not agree in any detail with the earlier import licence they purport to replace. In some instances queries which we have to raise specifically in order to clarify oup records, have not been answered. We should like to stress the importance of an early response to such queries as it is essential that pur records are kept in line with tho se of countrie s if wo are to avoid confusion arising in respect of the licensing position against programmes* /materials%) f I IviiiTBRIi-iLS SECTION. 1, (a) TBSER. We have received notification from the Chief Controller of Exports that the Government of India, has decided to permit the export of the less durable species of Timber such as Jungle Wood, Mango Wood,etc*-, to th^ extent of 20 / of the quotas -approved by the Middle East Supply Centre for the year 194^* ^ certificcate will be required from the Government of the importing country that the timber is required for essential purposes in the territory* This certificate will have to be submitted by the supplier when making an application for an Indian Export permit* (b) TIMBER MhUFRCTERES AMD PLYWO ODS. The export of a certain quantity of Plywood and miscellaneous Timber manufactures, including La the, Shingles, and Hardwood Floor .mg will also be permitted by the Director General of Industries and Supplies, Nev/Delhi, subject to the approval of each application for Sin export licence by the Office of Industry and Supply* Any import licences issued on India for either Timber or ii...bei manufactures should be within agreed quota* 2. RUBBER. The Rubber Directorate of the'Ministry of Supply has now 'received application for export permits to cover tne cotal allocation approved for Middle East countries for Natural Raw Rubber*‘ This Mission has sent the necessary covering ap^-oval to London and shipment will be made at the first availaole opportunity. 3. tut. No details have, as yet, been received as to the second naif 1946 Tin allocation.• We have, however, requested^the Tin Control denartnent of the Ministry of Supply to obtain this information from the International Committee as soon as possible and, upon receipt, details will be passed to the interested countries* 4* (a) JUTE AND JUTE PRODUCTS EX INDIA., Middle East countries will have received intimation by wliis time of the allocations of Jute and Jute Products for tne perio^ 2nd half 1946. The Governrsent of Indxa have stressed that it mo been found necessary to continue regulation of export on gg basis in order to ensure equitable distribution of tnese cola oditie. which continue to be in short supply. It has further been ooiuv , chiefly due to the uncertainty of crops and rails GhfTnoe’tions establish allocations only on a half-year oasis. T JI° ■ . notified will therefore cover the period ending on 25th Dece.ocr, Uito. notii i .. - a entities for the second period, namely The hone is expressed that qUc.niitj.oe iux o /- first half 1947, wall be intimted early m Decenoer, 19 wj* (b). W.D. Surpluses of certain categories of Ju te Products. The export of the following categories of Jute goods procured from Indian Army surpluses ex-Disposals Directors e con muo permitted outside of quota:- 'a) Sandbags and products therefrom fb) Camouflage series V c) Jute webbings 'd) Jute tents canvas. Ac)- 6 . (c) S^n5b^.r.-s» In the light of prevailing &gt; shortages of Jute Sacks no bring te the notice of all M.E.countries the fact that large quantities of unused sandbags ex Ariiy stocks are coining forward for disposal, particularly in Iraq and India# Countries may wish to consider the advisability of obtaining 'quantities as they become available particularly as procurement thereof vdll not be regrrded as coning within quotas# Contact should be made direct with either the Indian Goverm.ient Disposals Directorate or the British Stores Disposals Officer, Baghdad, copying correspondence to B.S.M. (ivuE.) for information* Sandbags may also be obtained from the United Kingdom through Commercial Channels and those will also be o ut s i de quo t a • SISAL. Countries requiring an allocation of East African Sisal failed to submit details in sufficient time to be considered by the Coiauonwealth Supply Council for the 2nd half 194^ period. Censeouently no allocations have been made to the Middle E~ st area. This Mission has, however, prepared a strong case for an emergency allocation from the Reserve Pool and it is to be hoped that in the. near future tie Council will agree to meet Middle East requirements from this Reserve# We would, however, take this opportunity to dray/ the attention of the various countries to the fact that when a dead-line date is given in our request for information, this is done with the knowledge that a meeting will be held on a certain date and if the information is not received in time for submission to the Controlling Bo 15 ^ for inclusion in their Agenda, countries are liable to lose their chances of obtaining a shard in the available supplies# 6 • COAL AiiD COKE The world coal position has further deteriorated. A reduced export availability from .South Africa is additionally ag ravated by a serious breakdown in the loading appliances at Lourenco . Marques, and attempts to obtain supplies for ‘the Middle East^ from other areas have unfortunately mmt with no success* This Mission is endeavouring to ensure that programmed requirements are forthcoming but in view of two extreme difficulty being experienced in obtaining supplies to meet the needs of this area, countries are strongly Urged to conserve present stocks as much as possible# Coal should only be used when it is impractical to utilise other fuels* 7# TYRES AND TUBES# We have now received a preliminary list of surplus tyres^and ■ tubes. A Circular Savi'ngram is in course of prep'’ration asking countries to submit their requirement of W*D.types and.sizes such as Sand,Runf1ats and Combat. Standard sizes will be allocated in accordance with known requirements#SECRET l/ $ BRITISH SUPPLY MISSION (MIDDLE EAST) o MONTHLY LETTER No. 10. AUGUST, 1946 o S990m/GHQP/120/9-4f»I N T R 0 D U CTO R Y. The British Government has now issued a furtiier white oaper entitled 'Second Review of the '.lorId Pood Shortage.' rt confirms much of what was foretold in the -l-± ::t -; v,: 'T_ t vi co in (ipril, and stresses that the world as a whole is xar from he 'out of the wood' yet, and in fact that strict economy must still oe the order of the day. Broadly speaking, the world situation is now _ re-china its most critical stage with stocks of the 1915-6 crop^ fallingio their lowest level and the new harvest only just beginnn s to move into consumption* In some respects the assessment given in April has worsened, as sh omento to deficit areas including the Uni oe a Kingdom, Continental Europe, and the gar r,ast have fallen Jo. the totals eicpected. Moreover, with depletes, stoats i North America, it '..ill ha difficult to mo into in adequate ship-gnto until the new crops begin to reacn the seaooara in ^ situation has resulted in she raoioninj, 0- g , although throughout the war - hecoming necessary m * v ’ .-gnto in it has been possible by effecting certain economies to .^aint., tteoughout Europe, the low calorie levels m so avoid a mpor disaster, it nmst be steosseu Wt these cannot^ be endured for long at the present low level it-.out . The same general coition ^aila^n so ar^as^^--^^ . hat dependent on the outcome of the world s main harwo,. .. In the cose of oils and fats world supplies have become more stringent and there has been no real improvcmen . _in'total supplies of -eat and sugar. Whilst these conditions prevail, the mddle E^t , , n .-i-i o-r-B-n Ihle food oreduced \.atinn rne must continue co muce uso o.. :.•■ p 1 c ' ni 4 -c-i ro 1 ' qourc’es can Bo area for no improvement in suppxies from outoi - expected.• 2 - POOD SECTION. CEREALS. 1. Wheat and plonr . Owing to the very meagre supplies now .available f*r exoort from all sources of supply, pool stocks ^continue to oe rintained at a precarious level. Against the Middle East wheat llocation for the third quarter, required to rneet consumption neeuo rf all those dependent upon pool stocks for, the fourth qu^roer, vessels continue to load the greater proportion in tne^ oxm oi flour. We must emphasise once again that tins x loux i.* s^ heing supplied against programme on the estaelxsnea oasis o 7' of flour to 100 tons of wheat. As a result of the request msde in t.c Julq edition of this nonthly letter, one or countries pavo nov informed us that they are able to reduce their demanes upon pool stocks during the next two or three uornhs. It a- - e - this that we are aole to iiUiii ,ni ux ^ ^ r-V-scs. requirements for consumption m Occooer, i.^* V^^Vdin^futuro Thereafter, on the basis of present imoriration xw^rain^, futu, loadings, the outlook is as bad as ever and it xs bouna xo be some months before there are any signs of an improvee^. 2. Rice. All allocations of rice for the third quarto: have now been made available and shipped by the Britishjuxnxstxy ' ■ ■ — are not .yet in a. position to release the -* • n n f 1 J- /-&lt;n t --v *1 r '\CW'TP ( of Food Rice Agency. we are ' , uo , ly 00 sition fourth Quarter’s allocations, owing to t—• - g ,s;x. Afurther communication vill be issued early in Sep-conoer, ,h,u it is hoped that supplies vill bo available. 3. Sugar. ^-r At the present time there are no indications 1 n the suooly nituation. However, vesi.eio ux ow any improvement in .a i ^ n r0 vid'n:r no unforeseen. hoy; borlnninc- to load as programed ana, pio\..u h venous lXt0y ° . o11 oii no .-,tions based on tnose ox previouo &gt; yearoanrHtlH ^oLbfnths ahead. *o increase in present allocations, however, can be envisaged. A.-V- 4 -3' SEED POTATOES. Wg h yg been informed that the Mniotry of Pood in London nill endeavour to meet in full the M.E.requirements of seed ootatoes from the II«K* for delivery October 1 946/i'e.rch&gt; i .14 / • Seed potatoes from areas other than the U• K* c.re no longer uno.or mie control of this ? 'lesion and an amendment to this effect \dll be^ included in Ai’-icridment Schedule ho *6 to the middle mast Short Li».» c which will shortly bo despatched to all Ivjiddle East countries. $ 5. TEA. In our Circular Saving dated 14th August,1946, we asked all M.2.countries vhich have an allocation of tea from India to inform the Tea Controller, Calcutta, of the name^s) of the appointed importer(s) and to submit to hia. details of import licences as' and when they arc issued* This: step is necessary owing to the closure of our Liaison Office in Bordbay for unless the Tea Controller receives the requisite informstion, shipments of tea froei In'.da will be delayed. A further opportunity has been given to M.E. countries to supplement their tea allocations ey enabling Jicm to ourchano supplies from Java and from any other terr.dtory otner than IndiaCeylon and British Bast Africa through normal comilercial channels. This concession, effected by the 30 th dept nab nc.v j -O 1 -, only r-'oolies to shipi'ents concession is allowed to continue after that date, an immediate notification vill^ be^issueci, It will be necessary for us to be given full derails^of iiapox licences as and when they Are issued and to be notified oy tne end of Septa, her of the quantities shipped. e 6 , COFFEE. B e1gian C ongo r em Only coffee from Brit id :iins ubjoct to control and : 3 1 Af rica and the we are preparing for early despatch to M.E.countries a detailed account of the procedure to be adopted in ord^r to obtain future supplies iron these sources. 7. OILS AND FATS. Our effo to maintain supplies of oils and fc*ts to M.E. countries b'W oontinuod throuriiout the uotrth. Tee .&gt;qcral supply position robins extreaoly &gt;Ufficuit ana it there is little orospcct of any alleviation oi &gt; thl ArAest, the seAnd h if of 1%7.- The -rid s fate ^ vdiich doveloped after Poarl Harbour ana beouse oven uore .-cate the liberation of Europe rose from:- (a) The heavy aecrease to pre-war. in Eurooean indigenous production cor.: pare d (b) The fact that only liberated Pacific nearly 4Q3 of tho a trickle of supplies and Port.a China region world’s exports. is as yet coming from the which formerly provided /increased—-4- IncrcAsed allocations of sesar'c seed fron India have 'been notified to those li.E.countries having an established procure ent figure and a we shall shortly be sending out the names px UUU.J. o .^XX XJ X &amp; — « ... 4. of the exporters nominated by the Inaian Government m respect of each country. „ Linseed Oil. We have now received advice that Indiajc^ftGx examining the internal supply position, is prepared to resuauc exoorts of small ou;uitities to the M.E. We h'.ve caeled In -ia for confirii-ition of the n~: e S of erXglirXcci ohippors toghe various countries concerned and inxdiatcly. ..o rec.iv^ information we mil notify individual countries of one quantity ^ available to then and the suppliers on aihon orders s...oulo. oe place. C astor Oil. We are advised by C. A.B. ,G.H.Q., that supplies of castor oil are available for export from Eritrea and^/e have asked them to offer supplies to those Middle East countries vno have an established procurement figure for tins commodity. 8. TINIsED EISH. \Jc have inf on .13 d M.E. countries th.- o in v.^ew of a reduction in Service offtake, the Ig.P.c. axe properegto consider requests for further supplies ^oi and sardines. Those countries requiring aogtiouX of either of these types arc advised to submit, details to us without delay* It is unlikely that very f G thev We available and requests mil be forwarded g. gonuon g tne reccived, so speed in preparing and forwaxcahg ae^.ndo m ensure a greater chance of partaking ox ‘;’ lar ^ t„ r ^.. ve availability. In addition, canned ^ “maiVontoUed by the now been deleted from the list of oo^o^W &gt; I.E.P.C.and a corresponding aiHendment to the m.xu.o.L circulated in the next few dmph. % DESICGATED COC ONUT^ Some countries hm-ve not yet acr/rsea us 01 , ■ nllocation of this coii*euity irox. import licences regaxaing oheir mil ^ tion of the M.E. Ceylon and it is ^sih pointed out 1st 0ctoK . r , 1% 6, allocation not covered by e.eport 10 - iruorts. Exports my be re-allocated elseahere by the vontrollm 'Wf'- y, Exchange, Coloiibo,Ceylon. J*fly therefore, be individual allocations ano vhich are^regir^i^ tQ ^ ^ktrhEhohlnphtsr Exports and Exchange.~5- 10 . DRIED FRUIT. Dried fi;s 3 apples } apricots, poaches end pears h a ve nov/ been deleted from the list of dried fruit previously subject to allocation by the International neiorgcncy i ooo Council^ -nd a corresponding aiBoncbx'iit to the hidule L sc Short uiob ■will oe issued in the next few days. The only dried fru.it still remining subject to control are raisins, currants and prunes. MEDDLE LIST PROQUREMEHT PRQGjiallll. Details of further allocations notified to countries durin,'.’ the inonth have oeen incorpointed in Schedule No.9 which was issued on j&gt;1 so ..ugust* individual .iUiiendnent 111 idle Si '.OxiT LIST. The sixth Amendiiont Schedule to is in course of preparation ano will bo few days. In this schedule we Induce in respect of tinned fish, dried fruit, the Middle East Short List despatched within the next tin changes mentioned above coffee and seed potatoes.MATERIAL' SECTION 1. TUBER. After protracted negotiations the Udnistry of Supply have succecdec in closing a contract for the supoly of tinibor from Roumania. This contract is of course subject to ratification by the Roumanian Government. In accordance adth promises nv.de to th 3 Middle East Supply Centre and to this Mission that any timber obtained by the United Kingdom from Roumania -would be shared with the Middle E st a total of 5&gt;000 Standards (approximately 10,000,000 board feet) have been set aside for sale direct to Middle East countries t prices to be ar nged* The sellers are the Ausnit Group, Bucharest and those countries interested in obtaining a share of this timber should contact the suppliers direct at the earliest opportunity. 2. RUBBER. In order to contradict rumours prevalent in the trade xie would draw attention to the fact that Rubber is still subject to Int rnational Commodity control through the International Rubber Committee. 3. TIN. The International Tin Committee has recently requested considerable information to justify the second half tonnage requested by this Mission to ra et the requirements of the Middle- East. This inforr.mtion has been furnished and forwarded to London. We hope to receive a firm allocation in the n.ar future. 4. TMTILES. We are pleased to state that we have now hoard from the Gowmment of India to the effect that the temporary ban imposed on the production of cloth for export to the Middle East' countries expired in August 1946. Please make this information As widely known as possible. 3. JUTE. Some Middle East countries appear to be rather lax in rcsDect of the granting of import licences lor Jute products# Countries have been informed of the allocations nude by the Ooveramnt of India for the period 26th June to 25th December 1946 and, although those quantities will come forward, wo mould strongly advise Governments to insist upon importers obtaining licences oeiorc shioment, otherwise non-essential Jute pro nets may oc imported at the expense of a country’s essential n eds such Cotton p ■ cks, Piessian,etc• lS Jute brasOviiv' to the frjiiino conditions existing, in Incin and the consequent necessity to increase fooo. oroduction it is possible that there, vill be a considerable reduction in the acres :e ulantcd for bute v.ith the result that there v.iil^Dc little likelihood of obtaining any substantial increase^in present allocations and there is no guarantee that chc half 1947 allocations vdll bo any larger, if as large, as the second half year 1946. o. SISAL. We hr ve now receivcd details of sisal oiioc ti ons dor th- reminder of 1946. The quantities are very G ''iuch ,nailer than ,e had hoped but as British 3 .st rfrican Sisal is in extremely short supply M.E.countries leay be nolo to obt in supplies fron Portuguese East .ifrica, Eritr-a.etc. Those types of sisal should be suitable for elondin^ «u a B ritish*' East African variety. Those countries having a ^ procurement figure for this conaodity have been inforriea as o t heir a11oc ation * 7. COAL 'i HD Q O KL. The coal oosition is not? extremely critical and v:o would a vain emphasise the necessity for the most rigorous conservation of stocks. g hnvo orovxcusly ooxntoa out that coal should be used only vhen alternative .aim., of ' - . ~r XI- l .r'Tl f combustion are impracticable. In this connection \rould nontion that there_are few installations that cannot ue coiwerted to oil firing. The supply position is atthe present time ^ so serious that it has been neces-W, in era r to L^e^ ^ --- .-it 1-1 require’- ents of certain ji&amp;dalo Last countu^-, to coaiiro:, tm united States. *&lt;*«*££% ^ raore expensive than the couth au.nc.~u 7^r ^ J * , ^go^tsi'c now has boon supplied to this area, but, of shipping it has been necessary to sup on ^ncan /c.-.u.SECRET BRITISH SUPPLY MISSION (MIDDLE EAST) MONTHLY LETTER No. Confidential. BAHRAIN RECEIPT. f O. .Date. * 4 * 4 * No. 11. SEPTEMBER, 1946 8900m/GHQP/l 20/9-46.INTRODUCTORY. V Since its formation on 20th June the International Emergency Food Council has 'been getting doun to serious uork. The international character of this Council makes it less flexible than its predecessor, the Combined Food Board, but this is compensated by a larger representation of the big supplier and debtor nations throughout the world, which must in the long run prove an advantage. ■ A review-of the world supply and requirements position for bread grains and bread grain substitutes for the twcl'/'e month period 1st July '\9k6, ; to 30th June, 1947&gt; shows a deficit of e.5 to 8.5 million tons. If the requirement figure is compared with the available export surplus of wheat and flour^only, the apparent deficit is 13 to 15 million tons. These figures, however, are onlj 7- an approximation ana more def inite conclusions may be drawn when the following information is received:— (a) The ultimate yield of grain crops in the Argentine and Australia. (b) The world’s rice position. (c) Export possibilities from U.S.S.R.and the normal surplus areas in the Danube basin. (d) Classification of U.N.R.R.A.’s requirements. (e) Confirmation of the validity of all requirements. Stated requirements on the whole are higher than ore-war and this m b C G . 1 ccounted for by the shortage of other foods and the natural tendency to supplement such dciiciencies by cereals. The total requirements of wheat aha suostibutc grains approximate 28 million tons or 34 million if the requirements of U.N.R.R. A.countries are added. The export availability of wheat from the United States is assured as harvesting of winter wheat is practically complete and the harvesting of spring wheat has commenced. In Canada also, given.favourable conditions, present estimates of exportable surplus will be maintained. In the southern hemisphere the outcome is still unpredictable as the critical months of the gro\/ing season are still to be faced. Still more uncertain are the quantities of wheat which should bo available from the normal surplus regions of eastern end south eastern^ Europe. It is not expected that total who at exports incluuing the last named areas will reach a total of 23 million tons, tne figure which was exported by the four main areas during the p^s season. It is also difficult to give any of the amount of coarse grains which will be : use as w.eat substitutes. Much depends on th Argentine and United States of America^ pre^ realistic estimate made avail : ble for e harvest in the ent official estimat indicate a record, crop. /WithWith reference to other coLinoditioc still in short supply, the U•S.Dcpnrtisent of Agriculture have published a \ 70 rld food supplies survey for 1946-1947 in which it is stated that the production of rice end vcyetahlc oils is expected to show an increase, but supplicse&amp;f cseat &gt;ind dairy products will he about the sane as 1 st year and a decline in animl fats is expected. World production of suaar is expected to be 1' ryer than it was last year but the unusually low stock position will leave total supply far short of current deiaand. The picture is not very encouraginy and strict control and equitable distribution of available supplies nust continue until such tine as production at least equals requirements•FO OD SECTION CEREALS. 1 . Who t -Mid Flou r. Wo ore able to report that oufficient flour c.'--ue for;, rd iuto oool r tocks during Sept .- •her to enable us to release in Octeoer the reouired Kiddle S et allocations for c msufiption during Our loading progr for the third ouartor j v-nicn is required to neet consunption roouireuents for the fourin ^ - Quarter , has nov; fallen behind, schedule and it is not ger ,mo;.n whether the balance still to be loaded v/ill, in fact, come ^ form-rd. The pool only consists at present of a bare corking stock and is} therefore, not sufficient to offset any cenoellationi or delays in load! to enforce the Due to this vie must request all count no strictest economy in the use of imported cheat no. flour and to infom us at the earliest Possible ^-tc of any further reductions they arc able to accept in tneir present allocations from the pool. Providing tvo or three reauctions can be effected the saving thus obtained together with a s^nll ^ shipment of flour nov/ on the vrater, v;ould enable us to accunul • ,^e the' amount reouired by the end of next month to meet consimiption needs up to the 31st of December. We have recently suorautoo. - oro^romme to the authorities in London giving our la' amg requirements of vdieat or its equivalent for the foirtn quarter to ineot consumption require, .ents for the first quarocr of 194/. We envisage tint this prograamc vdll be acceptea, out ue -uso repeat that no improvement to present -llocations cm mticipated. be 2. Rice All rice allocations for the fourth quarter have non oeon role -soil '.nfi it is hoped th-t the-.shipnent of these 'grfg V ill shortly oom. nco. Owing to the scarcity of supply o, ot- vldlst '-vaiiahilities for the first qurrtcr of 194/ still r^ixn orohloav- tic’l, no increo.sos to orosent allocations can jo considered. 3* Sugat« Vessels are nov; arriving in the idea. la jv..su ,s ^px o .^ 1 ■ j^d, ^ with the result that uost c -untries have now t^coiwu^uificioo supplies to 1-st until to end “J/Wygy T iLgW, si blo have boon dolivorod in aov nec as .- ^ g_, delays to and cancellations in loading frogxc^-.iCo, _ ; Jr Vrx ^ indication tot supplies -re bceoiiinr; r-iere plentiful. Stoc^ oil the. lor. ding ' roes rro still very low na will oontxnuw «&gt; for some months to co e. A-4 - 4 ~ TEA The Ton Corirdttec of the I.E.?»C.is holding a further iLeetinf' in October to review; the alloc tions 'of ten. r-:i?de by the Co: seittoe t their meeting in July. We ore not optimistic regarding possible increases in allocations rcr.de to M.S.countries. The Com ittee vdll also consider the possibility of extending tire concession v,hereby M.E.countries may supplement their allocations by purchases of tea from sources otherthan India,■Ceylon and British East Africa, it mould be appreciated if countries who have already op ned negotiations for supplies in this category would give us details of expected arrivals. The decisions taken at the forthcoming meeting of the Tea Committee of the I.E.F.C.mail be communicated as soon as they arc received. 5* COFFEE. . ri It van stated in our last Monthly Letter that only coffee from British Sst Africa and the Belgian Con :o remains subject to control and \jq circulated to interested countries the method of procurement for 1947* Any countries who have not yet taken up their 1946 alloc ■ tions arc advised to do so without delay. 6 . OI LS ./TO FA TS. One of the Mission’s greatest difficulties at the present time is caused by the continued and acute shortage of oils and fats. We are doing our utmost to assist countries in obtaining their essential minimum requirements and we fully appr ciato the difficulitics which Middle East Governments arc now facing regarding edible oil and oil for the manufacture of soap. 7/. LI NSEED OIL. Interested M.E.countries have now received a supply of Linseed Oil from India. Details of shippers have also been provided. 11ocations for the established In inn 8 .- SO YA BEANS . In view of some possible previous misunderstanding it is pointed out that Soya Beans, if imported for use as oil-bearing seeds,i.e. for tile production of vegetable oil for edible or industrial purpose must be debited to the importing country * s alloc -1ion of oil-bearing seeds. A9. SO,! 5 « 5 ~ M.E*countries Ir vo no'./ been infer: jed of individual alloc tions of soap from India, ml ye roco^iend tha.t import licences be issued v/itli the least possible delay. It should be possible, v.lth tile arrival of soap supplies from India, for some territories to economise in the use of certain oils used in thelocal uanufacturo of soap, and thus increase the nanufacture of . r.rmarine. 10. ANIMAL OvAnp; to the present dearth of oilcake from, local processing it may be that a shortage of animal feeding stuffs is non being experienced in several M.E.countr.'ieS •■. , nd alloc tions of supplies of oilseed cakes and mixed feeds ' gainst such deficiencies v.ill be extremely difficult. We ivould point out that all '•ninal leeoing stuffs (other than oilseed cakes and mixed feeds), i.e. .acat meal, fisha^e^l,etc., are not subject to control and therefore^ M.E.countries .r-. in a position to offset any deficiencies vlixch cr.y arise by the importation of these do-controlled pro. uctn. &gt; ' ■ h 11. COCOA 5E.; iTS. The Cocoa and Supplies Committee of the I.E.F.C.havo requested inform.tion’regarding present stocks nd 1947 estimated requirements of cocoa beans and coco - ': buster am a circular questionna.ire Ao this effect has seen sent to M.ii• conncrres. 12. DAIEI PR OD IICTS « London have again stressed the importance of caoling to tnc Australian and Non Zealand Governments full details of all import licences issued for the importation of dairy products from those sources. The Australian and Nov; Zealand Governments mil not issue export licences until they have received confirmation from M.m. ^ countries that the corresponding import licences have been issuea. 13. NUTMEG» There is now available for distribution a further quantity of nutmeg from the Windward Islands since the of all M.E.countries have now been fully covered by^ allocations; any country requiring greater quantities oreviously cstirmted is invited to suorait ciet. mils o- 1 - ^ demands for consideration in the light of ^nis o...a..ll a va il ab i 1 i ty. snr. 11 reoixlrement c jvious tian was ;s increased .daition 1- 6 — * 14. TIMED ?ISH. To clfvfce \tq have roocivcd replies from only three oountrij s to the questionnaire despatched at the he ginning of the month offerin~ increased quantities of Canadian cannea hern i.\a ana sardines. If any M.E.country has an additional demand for these items! it is in its interest to send us details at the oarlxest possible date, otherwise there is a grave risk oi thio additional availability being absorbed before demands are roceivee tor consideration. 15 * FuS.P'RQCUPdl MT PROGRAtddE. Details of further allocations or maencb.Tents to tin ividdle East 1%6 Procurement Programme have bean incorporated in Amendment Schedule No. 10 nhich -was issued on 30th September. l£. MIDDLE EAST SHORT LIST. The 7th Amendment Schedule to the M.E.S.L. is in course of preparation and will be issued within the next few days. /E'lTERI./VLS SECTION 1, . / M.E,countries mil Ir.ve received our Saving No, 121 Coolie Circular of tlx- 25 th September, 194^} v/horein xic announced the . renoval of Tinber from the Middle East Short List.. The allocation of Roumanian timber to vhich ve referred in our August letter v/ill not be affected* London has agreed that this allocation of 5? 000 standards vdll be permitted to come forward, to Middle East countries in spite of the fact that timber has now been removed from the Middle East Short mst* It is unfortunate that the contract with the Ausnit Croup is being held up at present because Rourrnnia is insisting on payment in U.S.A.dollars. The Board of Trade -v/ill cooaunicate ■with Comaercial Diplomatic Officers direct through the RAMilT-TAMAR series as soon as they have succeeded in concluding the, Ausnit eo nt ract. 2*.RUBBER. Although this commodity is still subject to International Commodity Control through the International Rubber Committee, it is being removed from the Middle East Short List . Those countries requiring an .allocation of Raw Rubber should, in future, apply direct to the International Rubber Committee in Washington.. British controlled or administered territories should submit their requirements to London through the Crown Agents for the Colonies. The deletion of this commodity from the Middle East Short List will be included in the next Amendment Schedule. 3. TIN. We have received advice from London to the effect that the Tin Committee will be considering alloc tions of this commodity about mid-October. As soon as details hove been received all countries will be informed as to their six re of the Middle Ea.st overall allocation. 4. TEXTILES. In order to dispel rumours that the Government of India was withholding supplies of textiles except in exchange for grain the Commerce Department at New Delhi states that 'As a matter of general policy we are not using cotton piece goo ds as incnc o^ent for purchases of grain in the Middle East countries*'^ Those countries who normally obtain allocations of cotton piecegoods from India are advised to make this information known as widely as possible. /5* (- 8 ~ 5. JOTS. Since Jute 2 nd Jute Products are no Ion ur subject to international control those commodities are bains deleted from the Middle East Short List and vail no longer be 'subject' to control by this Mission. These commodities are, however, still in very short supely uid are subject to allocation by the G-overnaxmt of India. In order to ensure that essential supplies only are imported, individual countries are advised to continue import licence restrictions in respect of the whole range of Jute Products. Relaxation of import licence restrictions may well mean that the alloc tion is -taken up in non—css ntial Jute Products to the detriment of essential supplies. All coiav.ura.cstions regarding the supply of Jute and Jute Products and copies of import licence lists, in duplicate, should be sent in future to the Indian Government Trade Commissioner, Alexandria. In the case of Persia, com.unications and licence lists should be sent to the Indian Government Trade Co a.issioner, Teheran. 6 , SISAL. This is another commodity which, although in world short supply, is boar - --’~-cd from the Middle East Short List. British Eav orsal will still be subject to allocation and details in regard to 1947 requirements should . be addressed to the Raw Materials Division, Bo-- rd of Trade, London. It is suggested that import licensing bo.retained for this commodity. \7e world raention that although only limited supplies of British EaSo ..frican Sisal aru available, M.E.countries may be able to ruginent these supplies with Portuguese East African or Eritrean bisal. 7. COOT Ali COKE. The coal su rply position is still deteriorating and until December at the earliest the United States of America appears to bo the sole source of supply. Although everything possible is being done to ensure tire .arrival of essential supplies to thv V* e Er-^.t we r 1 ' t ' gain emphasise that every cconony me r ^ ‘.n ie use of coal and whenever possible alternative ruels sliould be used.SECRET BRITISH SUPPLY MISSION (MIDDLE EAST) MONTHLY LETTER Ho. 12. OCTOBER, 1946 o 8900m/GHQP/l 20,9-46.1 N T RODUCTORY the first euniversery The 31st October, 1946 P of tne British Supply Mission. A review' of the 3 ns t yenr reveals that much progress has been ande in the del control of coiiL.oditics end ve are now consiciers.bly closer than we were ‘&gt;' e, ' r r - 0 “t 0 return to nonr’-l coo.'jercial practice our first objective. © On the 'food' side, world controls in the main exist only^in so far as basic con. odities are concerned, whilst items on tne 'm to rials' side have been removed from international control except coal, tin, and rubber. The year has also seen the dissolution of the Combined Pooa Board ana the establishment of the International Emergency Ecod Council which_is now the arbiter of world food production^ supply eno. allocation. The I.E.P.C. with its wider sphere cf influence ana action, should continue•its work until world proauction of essential foods at least equals world requirements. In tails connection it is relevant to point out that decisions on availabilities and allocations of foods which are conaunicated by this Mission to Middle East countries are invariably international rulings oy the International Emergency Pood Council and are not the responsibility of any single government• Pood supply prospects for 194 7 are somewhat confusing. Although ve know that the harvest in North America is an all time record, this in itself is not sufficient to ensure plentiful supplies. As Fitzgerald, Secretary General of the I.E.PiC• pointed out in his speech to the Council on the 18th October, 'food supply prospects in the forthcoming year do not v/arr nt undue optimism.' He said there has been too great a. tendency to look at this year’s large production of who at and to overlook the very large decline in wheat stocks. Similarly U.N.R.R.A’s Director General, La Guardia, in his report to the Secretary General of the United Nations General Assembly, stated that the prospect of f.amine in 1947 can be avoided only if the United Nations prepare ■without delay effective plans to meet conditions of urgent need. &lt;fe hesitate to forecast what hie future may hold but one thing is certain, reconstruction and a fair division of hie world’s resources can only succeed by international co-operation and planning. Wh t must be avoided is the tendency to put domestic problems before international affairs. The success of the I.E.P.C• or any other world organisation depends upon the support given to it by member nations. Let us hope that this support will be forthcoming.&amp;- 2 - FOOD SECTION. CERSi\LS. !• Wheat mid Flourc P) Y/e can no\; confirn that the balance of the third quarter’s lor dine requirononts for the Kiddle Seat care forward durin.o; the course of this inonth in the form of uhcat. We are also able to confirm that our loadina requirements submitted to Lone.on for the fourth quarter have been approved andi that, so far, loadings against these roquirerents are kceoin; to scheaule. There is every hope that all countries* requirements can be met for some xiae to come. From present indie tions the bulk of loadings during the next few months v.ill be v.heat. Should r reversion to flour take pl'ce, ample varnin • •.'.dll be given tlirou h the medium of this letter to enable countries to re'-c.aapt their i.ailing programmes* The co-opc .ation of all countries in making the best and utmost use of their local resources has assisted, in no small way, to overcome the cdificulties of the past few months when supplies of wheat and flour v/ere ao uncertain, 1947 may bring; forth a regular flow o f supplies, but it is. doubtful whether there will be any improvement in supplies for stock building or to allow any decrease in the present aeulto ration rates. All countries should, therefore, continue to make the ..rxia.un use of local r~sources during the coi.in venar. 2. Rice, /dl allocations of rico for the fourth quarter continue to be shipped as and when opportunities arise, ft is not yet known what supplies will bo available for the first quarter' of 194/, but it is unlikely' that pry increased -allocations will be authorised. 3• Sugar. Pool stocks came down to a. very low level during the month under review but vessels now pro ramaod and duo'to arrive next month will re-establish the position and offset any future delays or cancellations in loadings. Our low ing requirements for the first half of 1947 have been submitted to London and it is expected that these will be approved. The I.E.F.C has been asked to consider an increase to the overall Middle East sugar allocation for 1947* Such an increase can only be granted if stocks coring under official allocation show an increase over previous figures* In the .meantime, all arrivals of unallocated sugar will continue to be deducted from allocations from official sources. A.3- V) ( J ) At the October nee tin; • of the Ter. Coo ittcc of the I#3»P.Ca v.hcn ■nllocntionc \:c::c review;oo., certain ndjuntoents to rlloc;'ti 'ns wore oa-.’c ana those countries concerned have been notified. It is regretted tlrt exist in;; reserve stocks aero insufficient to meet all the demands received for increased allocations and, although every request was yiven the rest careful consideration, only the most necessitous and justifiable cases could be entertained. The Cor. ittce has reconaonded that the period allowed for negotiating purchase ^including shipment) of tea supplies from sources other than India, Ceylon and British Bast Afric- shall be extended to 31st December,1546. This concession should enable K.E.countries to supplement their allocations. ihy \jc remind Governments that, as oreviously requested, they supply us with full particulars concerninr; purchases made from these free.areas* i.c. details of the import licences issued and, if possible, dates of shipments and expected times of arrival. / Green Tea. We have been advised by the Tea Controller for India that the export of a limited quantity of green tea will be permitted from India, outside I.S.P.C. allocutions already notified. No quotas have been allotted to pTticular countries and tlie tea can bo shipped to any country. Supplies may be obtained through corx:.erci '.l clianncls from tin estates vdshing to export or shippers selected by the:., i.e. the estates may&gt; if they so desire, nominate exporters to handle the expert of green tea on their behalf. The Tea Controller has. promised to supply us vdth a list of the estates holdin/; a quota and, when this information is received, it will bo circularised. In the meantime, we have no objection to a Hid- ; le East country entering into negotiations for the purchase of green tea from India should they know- of an established' exporter• Wo would request that imports be strictly limited to a country*s pre-war consumption figures, 6 . Coffee, During the past month certain M;E.countries have complained of a shortage of coffee owin' to the limited arrivals of co -'fee from Bast Africa. We are doing our best to speed up deliveries from this source of supply. In this connection may we remand M.B.countries that coffee from all other supply areas (excepting Belgian Congo and British E st Africa) is no longer subject to control by this Mission. We understand that supplies can be obtained from Aden and Ethiopia at short notice; also tinned coffee from the U.K. is known to be in plentiful supply. / 7 *-4- ?• Oils Frits» Although oils and fats continue to be in very Si.ort supply, it h s oeen possible to allocate to those countries most in need certain quantities of sesame and copra ■..nich snoulo. ensure nnintcnoncc of the edible oil ration ior several months to come. The Mission is doing its utmost to obtain for M.E.countries their reinimue requirements, but i. r o --Us g emphasize the imp or thneo of preserving these supplies of oils ana fats for edible purposes and not for the manufacture of soap; more especially as the allocations of soap made by U.K. and India should be sufficient to meet H essential requirements of this commodity in most Middle East countries. 8 , Cocoa Beans* _ During the course of the next month ve should be in a position to aavise interested M*E*countries of the I•E*E•&gt;«interim allocation of cocoa beans against total requirements for the year 1946/1947, Middle East Short List. Amendment Schedule ho.7 v/as issued on 14th October. Manufactured products containing sugar, jute and jute products timber and timber products were deleted from the Middle East Short List. Middle East countries are reminded that,althou^ji a product once deleted from the Middle East Short List is no longer subject to any form of control by this Mission, it may still be subject to varying degrees of control by the' Governments of the supplying countries* This is particularly applicable to jute and jute products v.hich mill continue to be subject to export control by the Indian Government* 1'A. Pro cure: ent 3 ro ;ranm * The eleventh Amendment Schedule to the 1946 Procurement Pro. ramme was issued on 31st October, 1946, and copies should now have bo m received by all concerned. The major function of this particular Amendment Schedule was to delete from the various Procurement Programmes those items which, Imvhag been deleted from the Middle East Short List, are no longer subject to quota restrictions or determination of source of supply. /teTERIALS SECTION-5- M/iTSRIALS SECTION. 1. Tin. Countries v.dll no’, r h ve received details of their respective allocations of Tin Metal for the second hr If 1146. This tin i/.ay he obtained fron the United Kin-pdon, Belaiun, Holland or South .frica. It is, houever, still necessary for details of licences to he sent to this Mission as soon as possible after orders have been placed in order that the necessary recoiraxnelation may he sent to the Tin Control Committee in London. 2. Coal and Joke.■ Wo re, ret to state tir t there, is no improvement in the coal supply position and ship-pin;: facilities continue to ho extremely difficult. The termination of the U.S.A. ur.riti;.'iO strikes is re suit in;: in the movement of certain coal c.arpes hut the enomous quantities of poods vhLch have accumulated on the docks \. r ill take some tine to liquidate and until this occurs there is little likelihood of any improvement in the shipping position. The London Coal Committee, in conjunction alth the v/ashin.jton Coal Committee* will endeavour to meet the Middle Cast approved proqrrrise and supplies mill be allocated as and ahan possible. Wc would mention, however, that the Eastern I'fcditorranoan ‘ countries have little hope of obtaining supplies oth--r than from the U.S.A. We are hopeful that the Red Sea countries at least will obtain South African Coal hut there is no assurance that this a/ill be the case. This Mission -./ill continue to pr oSS Middle East claims for co.al supplies hut in .view of the extrciicly critical position, all countries should make ever 5 r effort to reduce consumption of this conaxidity by usinp oil-fuel^ or charcoal whenever possible. In the case ox some^ Mio.cile East countries the use of locally ained lianite should ee e-hcoura.red as a substitute for imported coal. iThe United St’.t's hive re^oit^y t^ken tv« oi^^nifi^ant stops In the -i tter of -.orld food policy. The decision of the U.3•Department ef Apiculture to oeaso the purch se of foods on behalf of forciepi governiacnts after 31st Dece..:bcr is the natural aei uonce to th lifting of price controls. This a-s not imply,ho'.cvor,that intern .ti*n il apouaents for the llecotien of food ore to be ignored,but It docs imply that nations wHJ. enly get as iomh food fron. America os they can afford to pay f^r, probably nt greatly increased prices. It is also cle, r th^t a.-»ny scnll notions particularly those \4w h. ve benefited fro.a U.N.R.R.A.aid '.nu th 'so with nat dollar oxch nge will h ve onsider.blc difAcuity in purch.sing food from the United States. Sir Jhn Byd Orr's plnn for a pemanent or Id ?ood 3o«rd has .also reoeivod n set back ar /oa^rlca is shewing a preference to entrust schcm-L of c'aa.iodity control to the proposed I: nal Trade Organisation to 7.A.O. This attitude is n t n oesaarily unreasonable; the essential is that all oohooco &gt;C ooiaaodity ojntrol should bo brought under supervi iid this perhaps the X«T«0»aan do better r as well an nea.- uth rity. In spite of the fact that the grain hArvento in the United States an 1 ana da are \*cll above average the wo Id position is to some extent discounted by a reduced Australian wheat surplus end th present 0 strike of soft coni ruinern in the United States wllch n co ,1 * b is I '.ti &gt;n of stacks. probability of a continuing ohartage in basic foodstuffs and ancillary iaat rials. In these circumstances the importance that the 2? nations a&lt;ho repro.ent the I.E.F.O. can dcaionstrato t&gt; the world th t effective int:motional cjo- operotion can be nucce: nful. The essence of the prablcm is not whether a world food bo rd is c nrtituted or the International Trade Organisation assumes responsibility in the future, but that neither con succeed unless the nations of the world wholeheartedly and unselfishly ogroo to co—operate in carrying out the responsibilities entrusted to them#FOOD SECTION CBNEALS, 1« llheat rmcl El our» The October loader carrying flour was diverted to Ceylon at the last nioiaent and for a time it appeared that there 4 would be insufficient reserve in the Pool Stocks to meet requireioents in the form of flour. However, a replacement loader cane forward in time to obviate any changes to the prograiTine for at least the majority of Pool Stock consumers. 1/e were also in a position to loan supplies to the Yf,D«to meet an emergency. Supplies against the fourth quarter programme appear to be coming forward as programmed in the form of wheat and although there appears to be no prospect of any improvement in the- supply position, we should be able to supply the requirements of countries dependent on Pool Stocks for some ti me t o cone, Estimates of requirements up to the end of February,1$47&gt; have been sent to London and we hope to receive- confirmation in due course that these have been -agreed. We rust emphasise that future prospects do not yet warrant any reduction of adulteration rates and provided the utmost economy is maintained, we shall be table to meet essential requiret-unts, provided there is no complete breakdown due to the present strike of coal miners in the U.S.A, 2. Pice. The supply position still remains critical and, although we h-ve sent forward estimates of the quantities which will be-required for c nisumption in the Middle E -st during the first hi If of 1947, we have had no conf irma.tion yet that supply is assured; the best that can be expected is the maintenance of supplies during -1947 at the same level as in 1946. 3, Sugar. Although we have been advised that the fourth quarter loaders h ve fallen behind schedule we do not think there mil be sufficient delay to cause a crisis. London has- agreed to recommend to the X.E.F.G* our demands for certain increases in supplies during 1947&gt; until confirmation is received that these recommendations have been agreed by the I.E.F.C.it is prudent not to raise any false hopes,-4- B, Spicos, Advice wp.g s..nt to p 11 H.E*countries in our 130 Circular Coolie S ving to the effect tlr.t qll spices h. ve been deleted from the Kiddle Eest Short List* 9* Cennod Fish* In our 129 Circular Coolie S'ving wo advised all Kiddle Fast countries of changes which hive been notified fro London in connection with types of canned fish still subject control. We have since received further clarification from I.E.F.C.and the position now is that the only types of canned to the fish subject to control are:- Canned Salmon Pilchards Sardines Herrings Slid Brisling Alev/ives Tuna Mackerel Crawfish Groundfish (cod,haddock,liake,cusk, p ollock, sai the, an dlling) Confir. ation to this effect will be included in an Amendment Schedule to the Middle East Short List which will be issued within the next few days, and which supersedes the information given in our 129 Circular Coolie Saving. 1C, Seeds - Fi^ - ld Crop. although the Middle East demand for grass seeds is small we ende vour to keep the Middle East Short List in line with the Reserved Commodity List established by the 1.1?,F,0. There have been two recent aiaendinents to grass seeds, the first at the beginning of October inserting crimson clover, winter vetch, spring vetch, &lt;-nd perennial rye grass, and tie second towards the ond of October deleting winter vetch again, and also Alfalfa and Kentucky Blue Grass* The next amendrx&gt;nt schedule^ to tho Middle East Short List will show only the present position in respect of this item. Middle Bast Shor t List. An Amendment Schedule No*8 was issued at the end of the month under review incorporating the changes mentioned above and this schedule will be in the hands of Middle East countries within the next few days. 1 94*a Procurm ,.nt P rogra mme At the end of the month we incorporated all allocations and amendments which had been wade to the various 1946 Procurement Program into the final 1946 Amendment Schedule to this programme.. This will oe in the hands of M.E*countries within the next few days. .PCS /MATERIALS SECTION-5- m:,erials motion. Tin. Xc io understooa clint ceri?!!! iiidriXc Snst iieporters are endeavouring io olDiam Tin ivieioi from India and/or Hon^ Hon r; out piciu tne* .1 location made 'by tile Xntornational Tin Com 'it tee#' _' The G-oveminent s of the importing countries should h ? ve their attention draim to the fact that any Tin Metal which any arrive - irrespective of source of origin ~ mil he debited to current quotas or taken into consideration by tlx- International Tin Committee when compiling allocations for the next period. A further point which should be mentioned in connection with Tin ivwtal obtained from India or Hong Kong is that this metal is likely to bo of the Chinese refined variety* This particular type of Tin contains a large percentage of impurities, including .arsenic, and is therefore suitable only for industrial purposes and should not be used in connection with' food coirtw iners. Coal and Coke* The coal position continues to deteriorate and the strike, of the- soft coal miners in America, unless settled at an early date, will be r. most serious blow to all countries receiving coal from this source. It would appear that the export of U.S.A.coal has already virtually ceased and for this reason we have rmu-sted London to endeavour to allocate supplies from ..Itemsto sources. There is, however, little likelihood of this happening since it is well known that the United Kingdom is unable to spare any of its own meagre stocks and India and South Africa have indicated that there is little chance of their being able to spare any coal for this part of the world for some considerable time* Coal consuming countries should therefore realise that it is Incumbent upon them to conserve their supplies of coal to the utmost and make use of substitute fuels whenever possible* This Mission will, however, case end wo are hopeful the forthcoming for this area. continue to press the Middle East t so:ee quantities at least will beThe month under review has been notable for the many contradictory statements’ issued concerning the world grain situation. These statements have in the main been misleading because they failed to develop the theme and to explain that the shortages were due to subsidiary factors rather than an actual shortage of grain. There is no doubt that North America has had a phenonmenal harvest, but whether this is sufficient to provide grain for all who are in need is problematical. Again the subsidiary factors of transport and currency ere in themselves fully capable of defeating the primary objective.. Fortunately the American coal strike has been broken and the movement of supplies from the growing areas to seaboard has started again, nevertheless the harm has been done and extraordinary efforts will be required to rectify that. Again with the end of Lend Lease and U.N.R.R.A. the countries who require grain will have to rely on their own resources of gold and dollar exchange for their purchases, unless they can obtain financial resources in the form of a dollar loan. This is one side of the problem; the other side is America’s, for without export purchases, prices cannot maintain their present levels, and a slump in grain in America would result in serious internal repercussions. The prospect of increased supplies of sugar for the Middle East during 1947 also appears to be dwindling. This is not so much due to actual lack of available supplies, but rather to the inability of the big produ'cer countries to maintain control over rationing and price. Without such control the entire system of international allocation is bound to fall down. We do not want to appear unduly pessimistic but should events turn out 'as expected and Middle East countries have to fend for themselves in world markets, wre doubt whether they will do as well as under the system of controlled allocation. The international control of tea also appears to be ■ on the verge of collapse as Geylon and India have expressed their intention to re-open tea auctions on January 1st. The I.E*F.C. have made strong representations to both countries to stay their hand but so far no official information of future policy has been received.2 . FOOD SECTION CEREALS 1, Wheatt and Flour Supplies against the fourth quarter loading programme are coming forward satisfactorily and as far as can be seen at present, the requirements of the various Middle East countries dependent on pool stocks are assured at least up to the middle of 1947. 2. Rice h- We still await, confirmation that the estimates submitted by us on behalf of Middle East countries for provision of rice for consumption during the first half of 1947 have been approved. There are signs that the system of controlled allocatipn of sugar will breakdown during 1947. If this is the case, there is little likelihood that the increases recommended for 1947 will materialise. In the meantime allocations for Pool stocks can be maintained at the same level as before. 4, Tea In our November Monthly Letter, we stated that many references had recently appeared in the_ press of several _ Middle East countries to the effect that' tea auctions were to start again in India and Ceylon on-January 1st which implies that tea will have to be de-controlled when the present Ministry of Food contract has expired, namely 31st March, 1947. We have been informed that the Tea Committee of the International Emergency Food Council is still discussing the future procedure to be adopted in such an event* Immediately we receive any further in'formation, Middle East countries wall be advised. We wish to remind all Middle East countries, who have issued import licences for tea from sources other than India, Ceylon and British East Africa, that they should advise this Mission of the quantities actually received against the licences issued* 5* Coffee This Mission has been advised of the 1947 availability of East African Uganda Native Robusta Coffee and interested countries will be informed as soon as possible. 6, Soap The United Kingdom authorities have informed us that in A &amp; /viewK- &lt; ^ f view of the supply position at home, it has been necessary to effect a 50/a cut in the allocation of soap from the United Kingdom to the Middle East during 1947. The reduced quantity, now available, will be allocated as fairly as possible amongst necessitous Middle East countries who will be advised of their individual allocations in due course. y. Oils and F ats We wish to emphasise that the supply position of Oils and Fats generally still remains most acute. Furthermore, there is no indication that any improvement in the present critical supply position can be anticipated throughout 1947. This Mission wi11 however continue to explore every possible source of supply in an effort to obtain at least the minimum essential requirements of Middle East countries. We have been informed by the Ministry of Food that shipment will be ^effected during -this month of the outstanding allocations of Copra and Coconut Oil from Zanzibar. 8, Canned Fish The amendments included in Middle East Short List Amendment Schedule Number 8 superseded the changes suggested in our 1^9 circular Coolie Saving. The position as shown in the Middle East Short List Amendment Schedule is in accordance with the Reserved Commodity List of the International Emergency Food Council and should be acted upon accordingly. 9» Dairy Produce Recently, we have received several from the United Kingdom authorities and Government Trade Commissioner in out that Australian exporters ar complaints, both from the Australian the Middle East, pointing quoting numbers of import licences supposedly issued by various Middle East countries, but which have not been confirmed to the Australian authorities through the correct channel. Middle East countries are again reminded that details of all import licences issued -or the supply of Dairy Produce from the Southern Dominions must be cabled by the issuing authority to the Australian Government, Csaiberrci, repeatec to this Mission for the advice of the Minis try of Fooc. in the United Kingdom, Unless the Australian authorities receive advice of import licences issued by Middle East countries and receive confirmation from the / Ministry1 —7.. ; Ministry of Food in the United Kingdom, export facilities will not be granted. MIDDLE EAST SHORT As we have received no advice position of controlled commodities List Amendment Schedule was issued December. O LIST of any changes in the no Middle East Short during the month of /5. MATERIALS SECTIONMATERIALS SECTION 1, Tin We have been requested by the International Tin Committee to submit figures for first half 1947 Tin requirements. These figures are to be on the basis of capacity to consume with all controls removed . This is a hopeful sign that the position is easing and whilst there is no indication that full requirements will be met, it at least implies that allocations will be substantially larger than those granted for 1946. A Savingram has been despatched asking for the information required by the International Tin Committee, 2, Coal and Coke The American Coal Strike has now ended and early shipments of much needed supplies appear more promising. Some coal for the Middle East is already moving but as internal stocks in America had been reduced to an extremely low revel, the American Authorities have decreed that only 50/3 of the previously agreed December coal export programme will be permitted to come forward. Since the strike had previously restricted November shipments of coal to approximately 50o of the agreed programme, and owing to the short lapse of time between the cessation of the O.S.A. Maritime strike and the beginning of the coal strike, the total quantities of coal actually exported from America to the Middle East will fall far short of the programme for the second half of 1946. It is hoped that January shipments will show a large improvement over November and December and that this much needed commodity will shortly be shipped in accordance with agreed programmes. All countries should however take note that there are no grounds for undue optimism over future coal supplies and that strict economy should continue to be exercised over the use of this fuel. 5. Jute Products We wish to draw attention to the fact that the Jute Products position is extremely critical and it may be necessary in the very near future for M.E. countries, who are obtaining bagged grain through allocations made by this Missi' to return bags for re-use. The shortage of bags is'seriously /hampering}&gt; A /i*' SECRET BRITISH SUPPLY MISSION (MIDDLE EAST) MONTHLY LETTER No. 15. JANUARY, 1947 © 9458m/GHQP/120/12-46INTRODUCTORY The Preparatory Comaiission on World Pood Proposals, set up by the United Nations Pood &amp; Agricultural Organisation at Its Copenhagen Conference last September, has now submitted its report bo the Director General, Sir John Boyd Orr, for consideration by the r .A.O Executive Committee. The objectives of this Commission wer&lt; to develop and organise production, distribution and utilisation of basic foods, to provide diets on a health standard for the people- of all nations, and to stabilise agricultural orices at levels fair to producers and consumers alike 51 . Tii is a. step in the right direction and gives hope that, in-the years to come, equitable distribution at stabilised prices of the world’s surplus foods will be directed and controlled. At present, despite current food shortages and chronic malnutrition among more than half of the world’s people, unmarketable surpluses of food present the most pressing problem, and emphasise more than anything else the necessity for International co-operation in this, pernaps the most urgent of all fields. Sir John Boyd Orr, in a recent broadcast in Washington, proclaimed his fears of the future when he said ir if Governments do not give their whole hearted co-operation to the world food plan announced by the. Preparatory Commission In Wasnmgton last week - a plan which is for the benefit of the /peoples of the world - there Is no alternative to a third world war 5 ’. The plan is made, and it has every element of success-. The execution and fulfilment depends on the countries and peoples of this earth.’ The future, for better or for worse, is in their hands. o-o-o-o-O-o-o-o-o-4/- 2 FOOD SECTION CEREALS. 1 . Wheat and Wheat F lou r« Supplies in pool stocks are now sufficient to ensure tie needs of the Middle East until the middle of 1947, but this fact^should not taken to mean'.that supplies will be more readily available and that consumption rates can be allowed to increase. .The present favourable position of pool stocks is due to the fact that we are now in the period immediately following the collection of the Northern hemisphere gram harvest and present stocks will probably nave to last almost until the next grain harvest is collected. Conservation of supplies is therefore still necessary. In this connection, attention might be drawn to the recent discussions of the I.E.F.CCereal Sub-Committee in which it was decided that allocations shou^ be made, not only.of wheat, but also^of rye, maize, barley and oats, to meet requiremen s for human consumption and seed. Supplies o thnqp cereals for animal feeding would.be made only from stocks unfit for human consumption or where release of such cereals for animal fG W n !!hp C for make higher grade cereals directly ^variable fo human consumption. 2 . Rice • Arrangements have already been made for ^ nmnlies of rice from Ministry of Food stocks in s^ptTo meet the requirement of those countries lependent on such stocks for January and Pobrua /. (Derangements to release against the March requirements are in hand. Rico remains in extremely critical supply and consumption must continue at the minimum possible level. 3* Sugar . Our efforts to obtain supplies for the Middle East as a whole at a slightly increase rate in 1947 are being continued, but approval lor increases must of course depend on tho ° v y a ^ world supply position and for the moment wo are nneble to confirm that such increases willbe _ authorised. Immediately a ^al decision is given by the I.E.F.C. sugar sub-committee Middle East countries will be informed.3 f) 4, ' Tea* Fulfilment of 1946/47 quotas . At a recent meeting of the I.E.F.C. Tea C'ommittee, held in January 1947, it was confirmed that the Government of India and of Ceylon had stated their intention of fulfilling their undertakings regarding the 1946/47 crops* It is understood that after all quotas' have been met, there will be no residual reserve.- It was also agreed that the period of ship ment for uncontrolled tea extra to quota should be extended to 31st March 1947. 5.‘ Coffee . Interested Middle East countries have been advised of their allocations of Uganda Native Robusta Coffee ex East Africa, and the authorities are advised to inform Nairobi immediately of the official importer nominated to negotiate coffee, as otherwise Nairobi can take no action. Importers are to deal direct with the Hard Offfee Controller and not, with any member of the group working under the Hard Coffee Controller. Importers are not authorised to deal direct with members within the group on the question of allocations. Letters of Credit should be opened In favour Of the Hard Coffee Controller or nominee. East Africa has stated that the proposed shipping programme Is impracticable. Participating countries will bo informed of the revised^ programme as soon as actual availability is ascertained, 6. Soap . During the month we notified Middle East countries of their 1947 soap allocation ex U.K# The fact that these allocations are considerably lower than the supplies made available during 1946 is a reflection on the oils and fats supply- position. The U.K. authorities are notifying manufacturers and exporters in the U.K. that 50/fe of the 1947 allocations may be exported during the first half of the year. Authority to export the b alanc e/-4 balance of tho allocations will be given to exporters at a later date. Oils and Fat s. We cannot over emphasise the serious situation regarding the international supply of Oils and Pats through which the world is now passings This acute shortage is likely to continue for several months to come, a.nd we must ask those Middle East countries whose needs are urgent not to panic in an endeavour to secure supplies, as representations have been made on an extremely high level and the Ministry of Pood are doing their utmost to obtain further supplies through the I.E.F.C. Interested Middle East countries will be advised in duo course of the results of these efforts. In the meantime it may be necessary to curtail the manufacture of soap in certain Middle East countries, In order to maintain the more essential edible oil ration. We urge, therefore, that existing stocks of edible oils should be conserved for the purpose of rationing on an absolute minimum basis. We are in constant touch with East Africa regarding availabilities from that source of supply, and hope shortly to be In a position to advise certain Middle East countries of further shipments of Copra and Coconut Oil. 8. C anned Pish . We quote below in confirmation of the Middle East Amendment Schedule issued at the end of December a paragraph from the minutes of the I.E.F.C. Canned Pish Sub-Committee:- u The Committee agreed that the types of canned fish under allocation should be clearly defined and It was agreed to recommend that the term !! canned fish 1 ’ be deleted from the Reserve Commodity List and the following substituted therefore: Canned Salmon, Herring (including Kippered Snacks), Sild, Brisling, Pilchards, Sardines, Tuna, Mackerel, Al'ewives, Cod and related species and Crawfish. This has the effect of removing all shell fish from the allocation with the exception of Crawfish’ 1 . 9• Dsary Produce . In accordance with our recent communication notifying certain Middle East countries of allocations of Cheese, Butter and Ghee, to be Suoplied from the Southern Dominions during 1947 we / -5 \/ n D VJ ■ we wish to re-iterate that unless the instructions .already given are strictly adhered to, and particulars of import licences forwarded to the respective Governments by one or the other of the channels suggested, supplies will not be forthcoming as export will not be permitted. 10. Dehydrated Vegetables . We have been advised by London that the import of Dehydrated Vegetables into the United Kingdom will be allowed in 1947 through normal commercial channels. Importers will need United Kingdom import licences. 11. Sugar Confectionery . Though this item has been deleted from the Middle East Short List supplies from the United Kingdom remain subject to export control and In our Savingram dated 28th January, we notified various Middle East countries of their allocations of chocolate and sugar confectionery, cocoa and drinking chocolate for supply from the United Kingdom during the first half of 1947. MIDDLE EAST SHORT LIST / No Amendment Schedule was issued during the month of January, but as various items have been deleted from the M.E.S.L, since the last Amendment Schedule was Issued, it Is intended to issue a further Amendment Schedule within the course of the next few days. v Allocations• In view of the numerous requests received from, various Middle East countries lor authority to take up supplies against commercial offers received by them for commodities subject to allocation and for supply from areas other than those from which allocations have been granted to them, we wish to point out that the acceptance of an I.E.P.C. allocation places a definite^obligation on the accepting territory to adhere strictly to the terms of'the allocations (both with regard to quantity and supply sources) and to refrain from taking up any extraneous offers.6 MATERIALS SECTION 1 * Tin, We c.re anxiously awaiting Information regarding Middle East countries' tin requirements. Unless this data is available for presentation to the International Tin Committee for consideration^at their next meeting It may well be tna„ countries will ieopardise their chance of obtaining larger supplies during the first half of 1947 than were received during the same period of 194b, ^e have requested an Increase of 50% on previous quotas but unless this or some other figure Is ^supported b^y requests from the individual countries it io possible 'that the Tin Committee ^may not accept ihe estimate submitted by this Mis si on &lt;&gt; economy in reserves, 2 , Coal mid Coke , Coal is once again moving according to programme but importing countries should bear m mind that it will be some time before tne arrears, which were caused through the U.S.A. Maritime and Coal Strikes, will be shipped in full. it is advisable, therefore, for all Middle East countries importing this fuel to continue to exercise strict its use until, such a time as their ^ are once again in a reasonsole concition. The supul Tr of foundry coke remains extremely difficult but we are hopeful that stocks of this commodity will shortly be arriving from South Africa. In order that our 1947 coal and coke programme be as complete as possible all^countries having a ( requirement should submit details^to tnis his sio at the earliest possible opportunity. requirements actually needed to maintain the ^cono.} of the country, as well as maximum requirements should be shown so that in the event of any improvement in the supply position the London an Washington Coal Committees will be aware of e-cl country's total needs and will be in a position to make allocations accordingly. When submitting ^ 1 information full justification and !£°^ n 6 given and details of any control^over diotributio that may prevail would be of assistance. -.q-o^-o-o—O— o~o—o-o—</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00015d_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/334</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00015d</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/334</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 8/40 British Supply Mission (Middle East) Monthly Letter'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1946/1947</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-08-05T21:11:10</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (74 folios)</extent><extent>The file is arranged chronologically.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 76; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. A previous foliation sequence, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file consists of monthly reports of the British Supply Mission (Middle East) from June 1946 to January 1947. Each report, marked secret, opens with an introductory statement consisting of notes on the global food supply situation, including political developments. The reports are then divided into two sections, with information on the food supply, on the one hand, and that of materials on the other. Each section is broken down into parts relating to a particular food or material type. Many reports also include notes on recent or upcoming changes to the allocation and supply schedules.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>British Supply Mission (Middle East)</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Middle East</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Food supply</topic></subject><subject><topic>Reports</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00015d#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>