<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x00029a_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T10:46:30.553Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Confidential . No. C/112-10/14 i ^. r ? V $ a Tbe Political Ageot, Bahrain, Presents his compliments to: — The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document ( s ) The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf. r/1 v Dated 19th February 1939 Reference to previous correspondence: Des&amp;ription of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Demi-official letter dated Major Frank Holmes, Petroleum Bahrain Unallotted Area. Concessions Limited, Bahrain, to the Political Agent, Bahrain, with enclosure.c3&gt;' 7 / Petroleum Concessions Limited, Bahrain, Persian Gulf. 14th February 1939. My dear Weightman, I enclose herewith 2 copies of the Hawar Islands draft Agreement. Three copies have been sent to the London Office of P.C.L. with a request that one copy be handed to the India Office. I have also sent one copy of the draft to the Adviser. Yours sincerely, Sd/- Frank Holmes. Snclos. 2 copies draft Agreement. H. Weightman, Esq., I.C.3., The Agency, Bahrain.J Tt on the betweei bin Isa of the Empire Exalte&lt; Shaikh powers on his in the whom i being t Govern first pa and P&lt; Compar the Cor assigns of the Ir years &lt; months A Agreen T Shaikh’ known which Islands Islands westeri T to as t Enlargi of Bah produc Area ” purpose by bot3 m Name of ®!|e Herrifal This is an Agreement made at Bahrain on the day of 193 corresponding to the day of 135 between His Highness Shaikh Sir Hamad bin Isa al Khalifah, Knight Commander of the Most Eminent Order of the Indian Empire and Companion of the Most Exalted Order of the Star of India, the Shaikh of Bahrain, in the exercise of his powers as Ruier of the Bahrain Islands, on his own behalf and on behalf of and in the name of his heirs and successors in whom is or shall be vested for the time being the responsibility for the control and Government of the Bahrain State of the first part (hereinafter called 'The Shaikh') and Pelroieum Concessions Limited, a Company registered in Great Britain under the Companies Act. 1929, its successors and assigns (hereinafter called 'The Company') of the second part. In this Agreement all references to years and months shall be to years and months of the Gregorian Calendar. ARTICLE 1. The area to which this Agreement applies is:- The whole of that portion of the Shaikh’s dominions being all those Islands known as the Hawar group of Islands in which is comprised a total of fourteen (14) Islands and the waters between those Islands and the territorial waters on the western side of the main Island of Hawar. t * The above area (hereinafter referred to as the ‘‘Leased Area” ) is shewn on the Enlarged Inland Departmental Government of Bahrain map (scale 1 : 34800) and re produced on the attached map - the “Leased Area being Coloured in Red - which for purposes of identification has been signed by both contracting parties. ^ “C-** 0 (jAl Nt*© j jjj U ^&lt;j A J ^ a! U ^ aLL*)I jj &lt;) Ul&gt;-j Ait j j Aj LJl j j'j-*: J &lt;}y k ~ j 1 Jj' J&gt;_ \c9 a_J 1 jllH ) CS. ^^V^AA-. O'S' jSJ 1 jyIsI UjIL^ (J © 1^9 jlJLl!) ^£j a : 3./ ( ^ . AAA.&gt;- AaAA^A».!I •i© 3'l AiUtl jf _ J/ill olil _ : ^ AasU’^I ij_j^&gt; y o* *3^“^ 3^ ^ ^ o a A»9l 0 Jj s T ^ li-1 a*. 9I jji Aa1&gt;-1a*.)I o'iaI^ Cxy. . Jy 9 * o* (Jj*b aiLaIIi iiUiLit ^ j9%y \A “AiL:i (dh (3 ( ( TiA* j AaI^U’ a AiLuil ^r* AaS^I^ Apca-ji!' &lt;^9 JaW I^aIc ^9j o j &gt;-■— 2 — Any question concerning private property situated within the “ Leased Area ” shall be dealt with in accord ance with ARTICLE ( 15 ) of this Agree ment. ARTICLE 2. The period of this Agreement shall be 15 Calendar years from the date of signature. ARTICLE 3. ( a ) Within nine months from the date of signature of this Agree ment the Company shall commence geological exploration. (b) The Company shall drill for petroleum to the following total aggregate depths and within the following periods of time at such and so many places as the Company may decide (i) 4,000 feet prior to the 4th anniver sary of the date of signature of this Agreement. ( ii ) 12,000 feet prior to the 10 th. anniversary of the date of signature of this Agreement. (iii) 40,000 feet prior to the 20 l;h anniversary of the date of signature of this Agreement. ( c ) The Company shall conduct its operations in a workmanlike manner and by appropriate scientific methods and shall take all reasonable measures to prevent the ingress of water to any petroleum - bearing strata and shall duly close any unproductive holes drilled by it and subsequently abandonded. The Company shall keep the Shaikh informed generally as to the progress and result of its drilling operations but such information shall be treated as confidential. jL:r ilL. aJU'NI ) V® ^ a_Xj 5 s eJU _ dlolil O a a)' I j *jl)| jj- o' (v) jT UNI J j Nl ^jdl jN«i- 4 *) IJI Aldl ^ 1 a 9 i • • ♦ (&gt; ) 4a91a&gt;NI ^3 ^l)| &gt;Aa&gt;» ^&gt;Jt9 \ Y ♦ • • -W AasUjNI ^c. Ua&gt;» (J jJ'-i ^J3 ^ • - ( r ) aJIa’NI *Jl&gt; Jc. yy $j 1: o' a5 ja»»J! d) a!^ 4*11 U» *)l ^A^' J AaAaU* J AaL^ - OUaL &lt;4a 1» I (jl ♦111 J* 9 ” 0^ J ' ^pl ^Jc- ’*&amp;jL\\ j+i~Sj dllS -U&gt; l^il^l ^ ^&gt;**0 j jjc- \a\c 4a^D' 0 ' '-yf’ O^Ujl*H Jt*jCj jARTICLE 5. In calculating Royalty for the purpose of this Agreement account shall not be taken of any Petroleum and its derivatives (hereinafter referred to as “the Substances” used by the Company in its operations or used by the Company’s employees within the Leased Area nor of any water or foreign matter which may be produced with the substances. ARTICLE 6 . On each anniversary of the date of signature of this Agreement the Company shall deliver to the Shaikh a return of the Substances if any on which royalty is payable for the year ended three ( d ) months prior to such anniversary and a statement of the amount of royalty if any due to the Shaikh for such year, and a report of its operations under this Agreement during such year. The Shaikh or his Rep resentative shall have the right to check such returns and statements which, as well as any reports shall be treated as conlidential by the Shaikh with the excep tion of such figures therein as he may be required by law to publish. ARTICLE 7. In consideration of the payments prescribed in Article 4 the Shaikh hereby grants to the Company for the period of this Agreement the exclusive right to explore search for drill for produce win refine transport sell export and otherwise deal with or dispose of the Substances and to do all things necessary for all or any of the above purposes within the Leased Area. ARTICLE 8 . The Company shall not carry on any operation within areas occu pied by or devoted to the purposes of mosques, sacred buildings or graveyards. ARTICLE 9. For the purpose of this Article the date of discovery of oil in commercial quantities shall be the date upon which the Company has completed and tested cut a well or wells capable of producing in accordance with first-class oil practice at least seven hundred ( 700 ) tons of oil a day for a period of thirty consecutive days. ^11 A) I _ * jLill j -Lju)' l r U^J aS'/JI .i_* Jc. £ j\s ^ ^11 Ij l*J &lt;0—11 A) I y A^lc- ^Lll» U Li j ^UJI IjU (j-* * ©Aft ^j^Ai ^ 1)1 . 4I*JI ©Aft ^ O &gt;-j ©Aft y J _ * » » J jU) 4» 1 jl^ft 4&gt; Oli 2 4* A3 ^)1 Ia^U ©j/aI! U* 4j' I _ 4*j LJl »^lil 4a3Ui*N 1 ©Aft ft 4«) I J\ ©i^i! 1 1_j©- 4^.) UrNI ©A_ft ©Aa a5 J J Jj£j '-^v'J il • ^ © • • (•-Jr 0 rirJ.»rj , 1,11 • o Ailalil ^ lftA&gt;-l j! •^C'l ©j/aII 4&gt; l» ^a^*:: _ 4l&lt;»li]| ©illl 1 ajLiII Jl^l . J»Ui!j 4-Ajll 4 : XjN1 j li j\l*&gt; ©illl ©a! jlaJlj 4jl_4*^«ll)l ©ilil ljl&gt;l ^ 1 J 4^3 1 A3 4&gt;-jjJI^;© ^J)- ©Ai ^ . 4JI y.A U y ^1)*• • /! / ths ex] Compa found hereof year, 1 Shaikh Substa the sai which Article of its Shaikh right t and al the re shall b Pi have t for fr? Substa lorries utensil supplie equipir other whatso and it£ operati Substa by the duty a shall { and ge Compa emploj duty i Leased ( of fire; except Shaikh• — — 5 — ARTICLE 10. Within threi months after the expiry of the calendar year in which the Company has declared that oil has been found in commercial quantities ( Article 9 hereof) and of each subsequent calendar year, the Company shall deliver to the Shaikh a statement of the amount of the Substances won saved and exported during the said calendar year and of the royalty which is or might have been payable under Article 4, hereof, together with a report of its operations during the said year. The Shaikh or his representative shall have the right to check such returns and statements, and all such returns and statements and the reports of the Company’s operations shall be treated as confidential by the Shaihk. ARTICLE 11. (a) The Company shall have the right to import water, and drill for fresh water, within the Leased Area the Substances, fuel, machinery, motorcars and lorries, aircraft, equipment, plant, timber, utensils, iron work, building materials, food supplies, medicines, medical supplies, office equipment and household furniture, and other materials, equipment and goods of whatsoever nature required by the Company and its employees for the purpose of its operations hereunder and to export the Substances and articles previously imported by the Company free of customs or export duty and taxes or other charges, but it shall pay on all personal goods, clothing and general merchandise imported by the Company for the personal use of its employees or for resale to them the ordinary duty in force for the time being in the Leased Area lb) The importation by the Company of firearms and other weapons is prohibited, except with the written permission of the Shaikh. Jt*) A) (3 &lt;&gt;! — 0 oil! JUr-y.*? ijll AlJ! *Uai*l •.jU 1 ) g';, j'f y _ iUt o' Ulr a;*. *11^ o j{\ A.JK: b 1 *j JLU ^[*-5 J AlJI l.ll k ^'—' 1 r y' • Aa) ' ^ I . r-j/alUiJI Ob 0 J.J 1 a*^^^ j O'i j Oil t*JI 0 &gt;x_a j O jc-.iii o.Lii • A) o’ AfT^m 3 ^ (') — A) 5 ill i-{[\ Aaklilhdljl j *113j v»L&gt;l jb— : jII 3 ^^3 ^y 9 ^^y^ J y J ^l j ^ y A y ^allj A -o ^3 -I M £_y&gt; &lt;J' C' A 1 ^311 j'-A-al) j ^ AliJI Idl^V 3 j '' aL^I y 3^1 ^&lt;3 ^ 3 ^V 3 y-La:)! ^y*&gt;y j! AiT^irl jlJja)! ^ruji^ jc^X \{jCjy^y^)\ JA dJlS/ 3 jl 1 A**^*.* i a; L*JI^. 11 !y A^^asx-lJI L »*-.! \ { -• ~ 3 l.**-* ^ J jJjLH 3 J- 4 ^- ^'1 ^Ia’I aaLuII A) jUIa»a1—VI a5 jSJ) { &lt; r &gt; ) . o^l VI As^i-oVI y— y — Provided further that aircraft required or the Company’s operations shall only be &gt;perated in accordance with regulations, if my, which may be made by the Govern ment of Bahrain for the operation of air craft generally (b) The Company shall under normal conditions accept and transmit free of charge on its wireless and telegraph in stallations such of the Shaikh s messages as will not interfere with the Company’s business, and in times of national emergency the Shaikh shall have the necessary use free of charge of the Company’s wireless and telegraph installations and railways for governmental purposes. (c) The Company may use harbours constructed by the Government of Bahrain provided that they do not when so doing, impede or interfere with the use of those harbours by the subjects of the Shaikh. The Shaikh’s ships shall have the right to use harbours utilised or constructed by the Company provided that such use in no way hampers the Company or interferes in any way with the safety of its operations of which the Company shall be the sole judge. Any wharves or appurtenances con structed by the Company shall be for its exclusive use. ARTICLE 14. The Company shall have the right to lay down pipelines, roadways and transport facilities and to construct and erect the necessary buildings and machinery required for the transport or passage of crude oil over and in the territ ory covered by the Concession granted by the Shaikh under date 2nd, December, 1925, and over any concession that the Shaikh may grant of a later date than this Agreement provided that it shall not exercise such right in such manner as to interfere with the operations of the Com pany holding that Concession, nor shall such right include the use of the harbour equipment which that Company may construct for its own operations or of the land in the actual occupation of that Company. UlA JUI fUl f &gt;~. IT V.J ^11 jlJaJ! (jl -LjV—) &gt;5 IfJl IS! jl'AoU! J!^M! j X'yj) &gt; ( V ) a a »!^* 1:11 j f ^ j Jr* (jj 4^=»yJJI Jj^' ^1 ^11 J^-j UtJl^ o' ^ . Je\ dJ^J! jl J^JI !i&lt;k N j! y~&gt; % *»$&lt;&gt;■ .. j!^i! •!» J^-! ^ J^j*! j (ji w^! &lt;3^ JL. ^ j! aS” tftdvr j 1 Ji-jd aL aJ&gt; Jj^ y a 5yd'i jfsj ifd,; aS ^ J\ Ic^* !i l &gt;! j’ Aj^» j! A)J j.d\|S J uf . i»*5 A5^d)l aco' r 1 !! i &gt;' il jl Ji:U a, jlkl! Li'j ^3^11 V’.^' ^jjl 3 Ll.SI IfU) J\ Jy r li» Jyj ^ Y ^ j a».:^ ^ * » Q- jlr 'As ^ 3L.:.SI /ZH JU-i jJ- 1 a* Jl. j' X' 1 zj'u... JUz-' lj» J.—iMj \ t [-J Jt| y UUM dll.- V-iir . 0l» ^yz'l dll.'— 8 — ARTICLE 15. (a) The Company shall lave free of cost the unrestricted use and jccupation of and surface rights over all uncultivated lands of the Leased Area which ,he Company may need for the purpose of ts operations and in particular the Company shall have the right to select an area or ireas of land chosen by the Company with 3 xclusive surface rights upon which to erect, killing rigs, pump-stations, oil-refineries storage, terminal, shipping and aircraft facili- ;ies and any other works required for the Company’s operations; and the Company may Duy or lease for such purposes any lands, louses or buildings with the consent of and &gt;n conditions to be arranged with the iroprietors thereof, but the terms of such eurchase or lease shall not be in excess if those ordinarily current in their res pective localities. (b) The Company shall acquire only such lands, houses and buildings as are necessary for its operations under this Agreement. The Company shall inform the Shaikh from time to time of the land, houses and buildings which it requires to occupy for its operations; and land, houses and buildings previously acquired by the Company from the Shaikh but found no longer necessary for its operations shall be returned by the Company to the Shaikh free of cost. ARTICLE 16. (a) The Company shall have the right to purchase at current market rates fuel, water, food, building and constructional materials and other supplies of every kind in connection with its oper ations hereunder. (b) The Company shall employ subjects of the Shaikh as far as possible for all work for which they are suited under the supervision of the Company's skilled employees, but if the local supply of labour should in the judgment of the Company be inadequate or unsuitable the Company shall have the right to import labour, preference being given to labourers from neighbouring Arab countries who will obey the local laws. The Company shall aUo ^ ave the right to import skilled and — A — j LA ^)l Lli / J JjA- A Ujllstf. OLJlal! Jl I ^^ &gt;! Jl^l ;,l . 1 ^ j! j' j' A?j L ^ ^ ^ (J* 4 ^ J • ilLr ^ (v) a&gt; ^ LLVIj rt.JL '1 *.Lr j LjUrN! l^lkr ^ ^Tjl^ jllLLN! jj LLl^N * \ JJ j-j? ^ ^ j f ^jA j! • (Ji ^ UjljJ jj-pseyCT ( 1 ) jiiii •LUj \ jL-Vl &lt;_£/..!) ji tj Cj* &lt;£j jiyij ^LL)! y % O* 1 *-^ 5 j’ (^-») ^'1 ja_j ^c- ^.CLlI l\cj j~&gt;AI LA Ji^n ^ ^yijir isi &lt;Jl*h L ^*11 j^A! . LLA1 yJI.echnical pay to th such wag Company engaged. ART to the Ci property theft, hi damage ai appoint if itself pay all times the Shaik protectini and its en at its ow the accoi: places as ART stances fi for conv weight s determini Shaikh ai of oil am gravity. The stances b technical represent have the and to e: ces may represent ary and of fire ai all exami in such a interfere If upon i such app order th be put ii a reason examinat discovert error sh hearing consideri dar Mon of or fro;.echnical employees. The Company shall jay to the workmen it employs a fair wage, &gt;uch wage to be decided and stated by the Company at the time the workmen are engaged. ARTICLE 17. The Shaikh shall give to the Company and its enmployees and property all protection in his power from theft, highway robbery, assault, wilful damage and destruction,and the Company may appoint in consultation with the Shaikh and itself pay trustworthy guards who shall at all times be subjects of the Shaikh unless the Shaikh permits otherwise to assist in protecting the property of the Company and its employees. The Company shall erect at its own expense suitable buildings for the accommodation of such guards at such places as the Company shall decide. ARTICLE 18. In measuring the Sub stances for purposes of royalty the factor for conversion of the volume of oil into weight shall be such figure as may be determined and agreed upon between the Shaikh and the Company after the discovery of oil and the ascertainment of its specific gravity. The Company shall measure the Sub stances by a method customarily used in good technical practice and the Shaikh by his representative duly authorised by him shall have the right to observe such measuring and to examine and test whatever applian ces may be used for such measuring. Such representative shall comply with all necess ary and usual safeguards for the prevention of fire and other accident; and shall maKe all examinations and tests at such times and in such manner as will cause the minimum of interference with the company’s operations. If upon such examination or testing any such appliance shall be found to be out of order the Company will cause the same to be put in order at its own expense within a rea sonable time, and if upon any such examination aforesaid any error shall be discovered in any such appliance, such error shall - if the Shaikh so decides after bearing the Company’s explanation - be considered to have existed for Three(3)Calen- ^ ar Months previous to the discovery there- or from the last occasion of examining the O' !:£ o' &lt;j &lt;3^ ^ Oj^j j \ a) y + A * I il UU! a*) LJI olll j\a]) old• jj] qOJI •jj'O O '* 1 O' A^yOJI j * A I 1 . • o' p-f; 0*3. (J* ^ ‘ j G' O' \i\cj LcO ' O^T-b^ Ai (Jc. 1 i . 1 ^aaJL&gt;c.Oaj a 5 Ailf t yA AaI I . ^ 'll l&lt; Jj* LO f UNI J .ly II ^1 yl (^13^3 Ail—otl! »^lll J&gt; y£ 3 aJI Jkl) ^j|l 0^1 ' j jj* ^ 03^' o' ^~ A * ^ y i ju&gt; *A&lt;r j^\y o^! yyj aS^di . ^yii o' jyCy AaU'I Uo l»iW aIa.aI-. 1I Ail &gt;11, ' % * I ol. Ji-I l^j Aaa A&gt; j-XL» Ala-^ly ^*—11 OUIy-' A,' ^ l &lt; J aP%£ ' &gt; IjLa (jl y • 3*a— AiiliJI AliyI Jj ‘k -tic- xyjJjII ^ yA&gt; y j&gt;-\ A: A__&gt;' Aj^ jyy oNlA-l^jj OldjN'^'Oli y'1» . ACoilJl^ij J^xll yJuL Jdl^x-o’jll I a) Nl *JO^tl-arol A^.-)! w,r a) I A»J j rt.O)l*lO O' J'*'* 0 ^ 3l.* A' 1^ ylAi 4 j y.—»»tA) &gt;.T y. y Adio^i jj am;— 10 — \ • — ame in case such occasion shall be within uch period of Three Calendar Months and he Royalty shall be adjusted accordingly, f the Company should find it necessary to dter, repair or replace any measuring ippliances it shall give reasonable notice o the Shaikh or his representative to en- tble a representative of the Shaikh to be iresent during such alteration, repair or ^placement. The Company shall keep full and :orrect records of all measurements as iforesaid and the said representative of the &gt;haikh shall have access at all reasonable imes to such records and shall be at iberty to make extracts from them. Such 'ecords shall be treated as confidential by he Shaikh and his representative. ARTICLE 19. (a) The Company shall iave the right at any time after the expiry )f three years from the date of signature )f this Agreement to give the Shaikh six months notice in writing of its intention .o terminate this Agreement and this \greement shall absolutely determine on .he date fixed for such termination in such notice. (b) If such notice be given not later ;han 30 years after the date of such signa- .ure the Company shall be entitled on such ietermination to remove free of all taxes md duties all plant building stores mate rial and property of every sort provided .hat for a period of three months from the receipt of such notice the Shaikh may purchase the same at a price equal to the leplacement value at that date less dep reciation which price shall be agreed or tailing agreement settled under Article 26 hereof. ( r ) If such notice be given later than 30 years after the date of such signature all the property aforesaid shall become the property of the Shaikh free of all cost. • -U L }' ua&gt;_ ^ 4 ] ^ j j&gt;~\ (r') ^ w &gt;■_}£ li ylc-1 1^.li s' * • - s t * jl + 1 ) ^&gt;- 4 ) J Jll jl 4-lr j! ok&gt; ^ j j ^ -X_ll fr % -!&gt;■' 4) oil Ui (j! 4 aa»LU . 4) j q. 1' ! J\s ^U! •A«) ^ 4-9 1 a 1 a-1ft 4 a§L»*^ 1^ ®-tft j 4-3111)^' »JLft 4 Ia» . UftJ (j LU^lb’ *-tft J^^Lc .1 (j! 1^1 ( ^ ) ^3^:11 lift U\c *)1 »J^A ► ^ ^3^ jj?y** i (jj's^lJ 4 -X)NIj ON ''yi Jbl^C. jkf&gt; 4 j I '+^a ' j vwJ^A-ll j ^j- 4 &gt; I 4) ^1) »Ja ► o-tft ^a 4I~a»- ^A-lll 4 C- ILjIa* I jl:l! ^ 1 j dUf-i U dilS J-a4*3^U,*NljCc ^ lS ! iVI j4a!c jiL .4*3 U* Vl a Jft^^^/ j4^*^ v^JUi'll w &gt;. jjC » 02’% j^VI lift ^Lc! 1^1 ( Ij/a'.l I —tft x-3 ft I ^ * . i-* (jj 5 t^i- 4 7x--ar li) 'a»If sequent Agreem cession? underta tain prc to absl interfer interests Pr Article : the Con] or remc of the a cession. AR agrees t obligatio to a Brit to any the Britif of the I Britannh been obi AR the Co.n; of this Shaikh ai deemed i far as majeure, fulfil inea condition the peric the perio For reement insurrect storm, ti fire, eart which tht prevent &lt; ARl genei administr act what as provid No « terms of Shaikh or °f the si If the Shaikh should at any date sub sequent to the date of signature of this Agreement grant to any other parties con cessions or permits as aforesaid the Shaikh undertakes that such concessions shall con tain provisions requiring the holders thereof to abstain from damaging, impeding or interfering with the property, operations and interests of the Company. Provided always that nothing in this Article shall be interpreted as debarring the Company from drilling in, and winning or removing oil from, any and every part of the area covered by this present Con cession. ARTICLE 23. The Shaikh hereby agrees that the Company may transfer the obligations and benefits of this Agreement to a British Company to be called 1 or to any other Company registered within the British Empire, provided that the consent of the Shaikh and the approval of his Britannic Majesty’s Government has first been obtained to such transfer. ARTICLE 24. Failure on the part of the Company to fulfil any of the conditions oi this Agreement shall not give the Shaikh any claim against the Company or be deemed a breach of this Agreement in so far as such failure arises from force majeure, and if through force majeure the fulfilment by the Company of any of the conditions of this Agreement be delayed the period of such delay shall be added to the periods fixed by this Agreement. Force raajeure as used in this Ag reement includes the Act of God, war, insurrection, riot, civil commotion, tide, storm, tidal wave, flood, lightning, explosion, fire, earthquakes and any other happening which the Company could not reasonably prevent or control. ARTICLE 25. The Shaikh shall not hy general or special legislation or by a ^istrative measures or by any other ac l whatever annul this Agreement except as Provided in Article 21. No alteration shall be made in the arn } s °* this Agreement by either the ^ *ikh or the Company except in the event 0 the Shaikh and the Company jointly 3 '.j* ^ J- ^ •Am.) s t' : - !^l.U Jt. O' ^ j J » _ » j' y L )»Ifl*r Cf b- ;:c . oi . Oil' . JJJ jL:^i li* ^ . io'il ill!jJair ^ 1)1 jj ^ J.* j! 4j llai jS\ . 4.) IL j\\ tiJjl ^ 4 ! '}&gt;- j tJ^.9 ijC' ^^aa, ( j!_ jJL*!! j 4*) lj! Si 111 ^ ^Lali 4^9Ur'y , »^* jl.)\ o .aUji 4.9 '.A*N'!9 »^a» || o-Xfr ^ -i»* aj^l_a]| oJUajb j 4i:a'lj jUj J**'l 4 . 9 li»*5ll al! 4*-' -^iy ^Jlll ^ 4&gt;_!j jW!j . j! lj*9i jjX6A (j j j 4^11! eilll ,L &lt;) l; j' A; jol IJLI) pic le-—&gt;■ 4.9U,' *)I ! ^*1) j! xyf' ^-5^^ »^ll- 3 ^ J^Jl Jj* *)1 4.9 lai’N! »-tA Jtf&gt;j j£, ^13 — —\r— greeing that it is desirable in the interests i both parties to make certain alterations eletions or additions to this Agreement. ARTICLE 26. (a) If at any time during he currency of this Agreement any dif- erence or dispute shall arise between the &gt;arties hereto concering the interpretation )r execution hereof, or anything herein ;ontained, or in connection herewith, or ,he rights or liabilites of either party lereunder, the same shall, failing any igreement to settle it in any other way, be referred to two arbitrators, one of whom jhall be chosen by each party, and a 'eferee, who shall be chosen by the arbit rators before proceeding to arbitration. (b) Each party shall nominate its own arbitrator within Sixty days after delivery of a request so to do by the other party failing which its arbitrator may at the request of the other party be designated by the British Political Resident in the Persian Sulf. In the event of the arbitrators failing to agree within Sixty days after being chosen or designated the British Political Resident in the Persian Gulf may appoint a referee at the request of the arbitrators or of either of them. (c) The decision of the arbitrators, or in a case of a difference of opinion between them the decision of the referee, shall be final and binding upon both parties. (d) In giving a decision the arbitrators or the referee shall specify an adequate period of delay during which the party against whom the decision is given shall conform to the decision and that party shall be in default only if that party has failed to conform to the decision prior to the expiry of that period and not otherwise. (e) The place of arbitration shall be such as may be agreed by the parties and in default of agreement shall be London. ARTICLE 27. The Company shall make all payments that become due to the Shaikh under this Agreement into the Shaikh’s ac count with the Eastern Bank Limited Bahrain, and the Bank’s receipt shall be a full discharge for the Company in respect to the payment of the sum stated in the Bank’s receipt. ^ ,J A) i yJUlj 4 -oLJI ©ill' ^1 lli U.'N' ^a j*. Cr* M y y* tf' . yC©*:)l y^i—^ a*^&gt;* (»w&gt; | ^ &gt; .1 _ 1 &gt; AW&gt;- (jls cLll-ii jy ^a (jA*) jp~ ( 3 »_y' j^i .1 Jl3 ji IS'J JtiiU j j .**&gt; u ijy-A y^i»- y . 1 aJL» } (S' y -t.c- ^^-3 (j aIU j j' jl J o' ^ j v ^ : *i. y^y' ^ j** ^ ^ y y**yy ^ ^'( 5 ) ^ —&gt;-U Aaa»Ii&gt; »&gt;Xa I y^t O * y-- lii Jj: jl j'yJI je-jllJ \z\ Ml 1 jAa&amp;A^ yi) li^j^C Mj jlyll .Mi^ijaiidh' jjj-yy ApOJ 1 jiyu y^_ ji AaIp ^ Ja) ^a^^aII ( ^ ) . jxi j I o'^y' ^.A^-Ai ^aOII^-X' — jjA*) Ia-)I ©Mil aasUtMI ©Jl^ ^aOu ^yi oiy^i j&gt; ^Jl j jd jc^ll j ^ 0)1 Jl A^jj n j\a lll*'i j—■© ^^&gt;* 1—11 yuMi jj£j_j . dAlJl yi-a)l J jA-ll jLll» ^ A^y*AA.!l_ 14 —U The Shaikh may from time to time iesignate in writing another Bank or Banks for the purpose of this Article. ARTICLE 28. This Agreement is writ ten in English and translated into Arabic, [f there should at any time be disagreement as to the meaning or interpretation of any clause in this Agreement the English text shall prevail. In witness whereof the parties to this Agreement have set their hands the Day and Year first above written:- Atiil diDtli ia dranoMa (jjchilli Silll \JL&gt; . a.a) ^*11 • -X* y» j\aaaA\ j' J Ijlyl Aifj - A)lj AjlirNI Aa^Ui jJllI \t • ^J^aAaII Aaa»»!Ij j&amp;m Ji uj THE COMPANY aS^jJI THE SHAIKH ^Ca^L)I IN THE PRESENCE OF liUJb IN THE PRESENCE OFfidential . Mo.C/146-10/14 Dated the 5th March 1939. I 9) : ''RE RES' \Mo llX... 1 Date ^ RECO I have lust received a copy of the Secretary of Stated Express Letter No. P.Z.1111/39 dated the 1st March 1939 regard ing the Bahrain Unallotted Area, and as you may perhaps want my comments I am sending them across by the mail leaving to-day. 2. First paragraph of- the Express Letter There would be no harm at all in making the proposed communication about sovereignty over Hawar, provided it is appended to the communication (now apparently to be made) convey ing His Majesty^ Governments approval to a concession for the whole Unallotted Area being given to the Bahrain Petroleum Company. As a separate communication, possibly made in advance of that approval, it might cause apprehension in the Shaikh’s mind. In point of fact all parties fully recognise the position. Second paragraph of the Express Letter I presented a copy (in Arabic) of the Bahrain counter claim to Hawar to the Shaikh of Qatar when I saw him on the 10th January. It would, I suggest, be reasonable to demand his rejoinder before the end of this month, and if you agree perhpas you would telegraph to me the two words 'HAWAR YES'. I will then inform Shaikh Abdullah at once and if I do not receive his rejoinder by, say, the 23rd March, I will go over and try to extract it personally. He may object that the Bahrain Govern ment had much longer for the preparation of their counter claim, but I can give him an adequate reply to such an object ion. Yours sincerely, on'ble Lieutenant-Colonel 3ir Trenchard Fowle, KCIE.,CBE., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire.aM 3679 a (N expens if it hi From To Dated No. Ipolitical Department. H679A INDIA OFFICE, EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). /■^ This is an original message, sent by air mail to save telegiapliic expense * but intended to be treated on receipt with the same expedition as if ft had been telegraphed. It has been drafted as if it were so despatched.) From Secretary of State To Dated No. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf,repeated to Political Agent, Bahrein and Government of India, External Affairs Department. 1st March, 1939. P.Z.1111/39. •S iftHIWE Kfc StDENcf Um ..VU/* mcoucs Confidential. ' Bahrein Unallotted Area. Reference paragraph sf 3 '* y ^ 5 of your express letter of the 14th February, No.C/35 of 1939. It would seem to be neceasary, if His Majesty’s Government were to approve of concession over whole of unallotted area being given to Bahrein Petroleum Company, to warn both the Sheikh and the Company that the question whether the Hawar Islands are included in the concessional area depends on whatever decision is eventually given by His Majesty’s Government regarding the sovereignty over the islands, and that consequently no operations could be commenced in Hawar pending such decision. Do you agree? There is no reason to suppose that this position is not fully understood both by the Sheikh and by the two competing oil companies. In the circumstances, however, it would seem highly desirable that an early decision should be reached on the t # S question of sovereignty over the Hawar Islands. Please , , , , - - / ^ sec my express letter of the 21st July, Ho. P.Z. 4962/38, Latest reference to question in the papers before me occurs in paragraph 4 of your express letter of the 3rd November, No. 544-3 of 1938, in which you stated that you v/ere enquiring from/2 from the Political Agent, Bahrein, whether any reply had 'been received from the Sheikh of '-soar, Ii h^ has not yet replied he might now oc asked uo snomi u his reply within such further short period as you think reasonable. The issue of the above has been authorised.By Air Mail. P.Z. //// 19 tt, R 3o injl INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy has been sent to by Mail. - “ ter l C- * The Foro iftii Secretary, Governmont of-In4ia. The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. 3681( 8 &gt; « 2 -. 2&gt; India Office \\ 1/39 1st March, 1939 Dear Jarrett, \«t^ Under cover of India Office letter lTo*f»Z.1111/39 ? dated the 22nd February ? v;e have sent you the latest papers on the subject of the Bahrein Unallotted Area. You will see from these papers that the rahrein letroleum Company nave refuseo. to hid, except for the whole area including the Hawar Islands. The great superiorit 3 r of their offer over any that Petroleum Concessions Limited can mahe, and the realisation that, if they fail to get what they want, no guarantee against a heavy reduction of future production, and therefore of royalties, will he forthcoming, have moved the Sheikh and his advisers to propose to give the whole of the additional area to the purely American Company. The Political Agent and the Political ^ - ----- —r-~ j-,, ■ ■ ll .»r—— ■ * Resident recommend compliance with the Sheikh’s wishes. 2. We shall he glad of your views. Subject to these it seems to us that in the circumstances it will he best to accept the Sheikh’s proposals, subject however to a caveat as to the sovereignty over the Hawar Islands, which as you know has not - ~ - | yet been decided. I enclose a copy of a letter sent to the Resident/ Jarrett Esq., dmiraltyResident on this point. 1 r c do not appreciate the Bahrein Petroleum Company’s ohjeetion to bidding for all the area l os e lauar ; hut uc cannot oclicvc that it ’w T ould acivanco either the Sheihh's interests or our ov/n to try to dislodge them from this position. You v/ill ohserve that in paragraph 10 of his letter r eightman er.presses the viev; that the grant of a concession for Hawar to Petroleum Concessions Limited under the advice of His Majesty’s Government mould he as disastrous to the prestige and position of His Majesty’s Government as to the Sheihh and his administration. 5. If this view is accepted p t he next step we thinh woul d he to discuss with the Bahrein Petroleum Company our desiderata in the event of the concession being given to them. Ballantyne is aware that we should want to do this. Your letter of the 6th December; I T o. I .06624/30; stated the Uj ) desiderata to he a pre-emption agreement; a satisfactory refinery agreement (both of them in respect of the whole area) and reservation of the right of Petroleum Concessions Limited to erect a refiner:/ at Bahrein. Perhans Starling could advise whether the last is really practicable or necessary ? As regards the other two we ought to state our needs together with/with t draft proparwith the rest of our political desiderata in the form of a draft agreement for discussion with the Company and we v/ill prepare and circulate a tentative draft later. Liay we have your views on the foregoing at an early dat I am writing similarly to byres and Starling. Yours sincerely? (Sgd.) r. PEEL.86/14 Telegram %&lt; From To Mo. 138 Dated 15th M a rch 1939 lolitical Resident, ^uahire* Political Agent, -Bahrain. Hawar • Ye s. If Shaikh does not produce counter claim by end of this month he will be time barred Britconsuljij'U (D • GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. Departmen.. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). B.— This is an ORIOIHAL ,erU by AIR I expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than ^ o&amp;rtok ( ^ • responsible officer of the Department ] Bus hire, n , ,, 16th MarCh ' Datedthe 192»3 of 1939. 39. c bom political Resident, f \C Bushir e. O - Hi8 Majeaty's secretary of State for India, w Xiondon# eoeated secretary to the Sorernment of India, External 4ffairs Department, RSftMSiPaf Hew Delhi. political Agent, Bahrain. (25 3ubj ect t Bahrain Unallotted Area* r'. w ■ Your Bxpress Letter No. P.Z.1111/39, dated the 1st March 1939* I enclose herewith copy of e letter !^o.c/l46-10/l4, dated the &gt;th March 1939, from Political Agent, Bahrain. l. I agree with Political Agent’s views and have telegraphed him •HAYAH Y3S*, adding that if Shaikh Abdullah does not produce his counter alaim by the end of this month he will be time barred. Attested. sd. T .C.Fotfle. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. ^/c for secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. {Signature) s. 44. Designation) .—86/14 Bahrain Unallotted Area. Holmes who returned to Bahrain a fortnight ago has intimated that he wishes to place an offer before Shaikh for Bahrain “waters?. Shaikh has replied through me that as he has already expressed his views (vide his letter enclosed with ray Bxpresa Letter C/91 dated the 12 th February 1939) he does not wish to consider any new offer from Holmes for any part of Unallotted Area. 2 . Letter follows by mail. POLITICAL ACcSUT. Copy sent under F.L.Lo.243-S of 24 / 3/39 to 1 . 0 . and G.of I.ronfidential D.O. No. C/187-10/14 Dated the 25th March 1939. BUS* ’’RE REGENCY - NO,-- . C0NFI0CT7IAL RtfOW Win you please refer to my telegram No. 21 dated the 23rd March 1939 in regard to Holmes* wish to re-open negotiations for a part of the Unallotted Area ? 2. Holmes returned to Bahrain on the 7th March, and there was much speculation as to the object of his visit. After a fortnight*s delay he came to me and said that he wished to place before His Highness an offer for what he calls the ’’waters'. He argued that during the previous negotiations His Highness had told him more than once that he would have an opportunity to make an offer for the waters after the offer for the Hawar Islands had been submitted and considered. In point of fact it is argu able that this is true, but certainly everyone here thought that after Holmes had put in his final offer for Hawar he had finished. However I considered it was impossible, without stirring up a great deal of trouble, to refuse to ascertain His Highness* wishes, which I accordingly did via Belgrave. 3. His Highness and Shaikhs Mohammad, Abdullah and Salman were unanimous that they wished to receive no further offers, and His Highness informed me, both through Belgrave and afterwards personally, that he does not now wish to consider any new offer from Major Holmes, or from any other party, for the whole or for a part of the Unallotted Area. He states that he has expres sed his views to the British Government on the offers already received and he is awaiting their advice on the matter. 4/— jnourable Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Trenchard Fowle, K.C.I.E., C.B.E., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. U si 00- 2 - (K) I think, new 4 . I have communicated this decision to Holmes who will I think, now leave Bahrain, in which case the atmosphere of intrigue and suspicion will lighten considerably. 4 . I have c 5 . I considered, when Holmes approached me on this subject, (a) It might have been misrepresented by Holmes that I for a chance to cry 'obstruction'); (b) It might have caused delay in London in examining the proposals already made by His Highness: and (c) It might well have been extremely embarrassing for His Majesty 1 s Government to have had to give oificial orders one way or the other. The outcome has been as T expected, though I should emphasise that I offered no advice whatsoever to His Highness myself. his new offer for the waters, I have a fairly good idea what they are -- in fact definitely uninteresting. whether I should not obtain official orders before conveying his request to the Shaikh. X decided not to do so for three main reasons : personally was obstructing him. (He is, I believe, looking Yours sincerely, P.S. Although Holmes did not inform me of the terms of ? Iinnf idential No. C/207-10/14 p, »o^ iV#,. Oatc 'confidential records The Political Agent, Bahrain, Presents his compliments to:— 1 -i u/ Phe Honourable Ihe rclilicsl HesidenL in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document ( s ) The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf. Dated 31st March 1939. Reference to previous correspondence: Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. . Letter dated the 28th March 1939 from Major Holmes to Political Agent, Bahrain. Bahrain Unallotted Area. . Letter dated the 28th March from His Highness the Shaikh of Bahrain to Major Holmes.Co nf Ident ijuLt Bahrain, 28th March 1939. ) s Political Agent, Jfehralat. Dear Sir, With reference to my application to make a.n offer for the 'Waters' which in the draft Agreement I designated the 'Shoal Area'. I find it difficult to believe that His Highness is deliberately repudiating all the promises and assurances he repeatedly made at our meetings during the last four months, and there must be some explanation which I feel may be a misunderstanding as to the mean ing and extent of the designation of the waters as the 'Shoal Area'. Actually there is nothing f new f being put to him as the fact that we were at liberty to present an offer for the 'Waters' at some future date - dependent upon settlement of the Hawar Concession - has been accepted by His Highness throughout the Hawar negotiations. In any case and whatever the cause of Kis Highnesses appar ent 'change of front' I feel and I think you will agree that it is only reasonable that as the promises and assurances were made to me personally, I should be given an opportunity of an interview w ? ith His Highness. My Company will expect me to make every effort to reach a clear understanding of His Highnesses intentions as regards the waters by direct contact with His Highness. In these circumstances I am addressing a letter to His Highness asking for an interview as soon as convenient, aid I trust you willjjee your way to facilitate this should His Highness consult you. Before leaving Hi S ^ighness, if he permits, I propose to leave with him a copy of the draft Agreement for the 'Shoal A^ea' (Waters) and an explanatory memorandum both of which His Highness can examine at his pleasur • I think you will agree that the application for the inter view and the presentation of the draft if His Highness wishes to accept it, are both in order and In accordance with my original instructions from my Company which were presumably known and approved by the India Office ? In this connection also I should like to recall to your notice that at my meeting vrith the Hon»ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf at Basrah at which you were present it was made clear that I should be at full liberty to make contacts with His Highness as I considered necessary to explain my Company T s offers. Yours faithfully. Sd/- Frank Holmes. (copy sent to India Office and Govt.of India under P.L. No 0 320-S of 7/4/39, refoour P.L.No.274-3 of 30/3/39, copy of bare PoL.sent to P.A.Bahrain, ref. His P.L.Ho,0/207-10/14 of 31/3/39). /3* Copy of letter dated the 28th March 1939 from His Highness the Shaikh of Bahrain to Major Frank Holmes, Bahrain. After Compliments We thank you for your letter dated 28th March v/hich we have read. Last time when you were here you made an offer for the Hawar Islands and waters around Hawar Islands. We received the offer and gave it our consideration then we forwarded it to the British Government with our opinion about the offer and asked for some advice about the matter. We have not yet received a reply from the British Government to our letter. We do not wish to discuss any offer for another area because we have not decided yet about your offer for Hawar. We are willing however to receive your new draft agreement for the waters and we will examine it but we do not wish to discuss it while the answer from London about your Hawar offer is still unknown to us. Salaams. *\0 J' ' (copy sent to India Office and Govt, of India under P.L. N0.320-S of 7/4/39, ref.our P.L.No.274-3 of 30/3/39, copy of bare P.L.eent to P.A.Bahrain, ref. his P.L.No.0/207-10/14 of 31/3/39).Letter dated the 5th April +f 39 n f n 0 '' R Ma i° r Holmes to Bahrain Unallotted Area - P.C.L’s tne Poiitrcal Agent, Bahrain,! offer for the 'Shoal Area' Bahrain with enclosures# pinutes of a meeting held at in? Advise rate on the 5th Apifil or*3^ ^ ^ L Istj^GP 'ths 5th Adp - !! IQ^Q ■Pr»r\m ^rn • ss SS? B o L?. e S: ls ' t= iz “a;r ••••••••«# Draft Agreement ''The Shoal Area' Bahrain - 1939 _ I have the honour to forward herewith the under- mentioned documents :- r/r't Cne copy of a Draft Agreement f, The Shoal Are^ M Bahrain - 1939. C“ ° OPy °fo“ U t 5gSS.““ &gt; “ Pl “* t ” r y --fondu. Cne copy iSkfof tSo e 5S“p3i: ith Hls Hi8h ' ,ss 2. The Agreement and the memorandum were presented to His Highness in English and Arabic at this meeting on the 5th April. 3. His Highness had previously agreed to examine the Agreement and at this meeting he promised to discuss the Company's offer for the Shoal Area with the Company after a reply had been received from the British Government on the Hawar Concession. 4. The Adviser to the Bahrain Government was present at the meeting and he confirmed that Major Holmes was correct in this interpretation of His Highness's promise.is coverei together Islands a: western This excl inside is map. The to as the Enlarged of Bahrai produced purposes by both i Fur Company piece of 1 area) in Island ( Rights”). are fixe&lt; the sea c line Iron Boundary Post No. just Nort' straight on the N of Longi The scribed a the righ therefror the right the Shoe sand, gra of cost, and cons and maki deemed r on the op winning, Porting ; from Tb Should “Surface Shaikh t] the peaci occupied— 3 — Also all that area is excluded which is covered by the Hawar group of Islands together with the waters bteween those Islands and the territorial waters on the western side of the main Island of Hawar. This excluded area is outlined in red and inside is coloured in yellow on the attached map. The above area (hereinafter referred to as the “Shoal Area” ) is shewn on the Enlarged Inland Departmental Government of Bahrain map (scale 1: 34800) and re produced on the attached map - which for purposes of identification has been signed by both contracting parties. Further. The Shaikh grants to the Company Surface Rights over the rectangular piece of land (about 3 square miles in area ) in the North West corner of Bahrein Island (hereinafter called “ The Surface Rights”). The boundary limits of this area are fixed as follows On the North by the sea coast, on the South by a straight line from the Bahrein Petroleum Company’s Boundary Post No. 25A passing through Post No. 14A to the West coast at a point just North of Badaiya’, on the East by a straight line from Post No. 25A to a point on the North coast about 1/3 mile East of Longitude 50° 30’. The Surface Rights of the area de scribed above do not confer on the Company the right to prospect, drill or win oil therefrom, but the Company is granted the right to use for building purposes on the Shoal Area and Surface Right Area, sand, gravel, stone, clay and limestone free of cost, to erect buildings, dwelling houses and construct stores, drill for fresh water and make such use of the surface as may be deemed necessary by the Company to carry on the operations appertaining to the work of winning, exporting, selling, disposing, trans porting and refining of the crude oil won Sh Oin ia Th0 ^ rea described herein. ou any oil concession covering the «? U . r J ace Rights” area be granted by the 91 the Shaikh undertakes to preserve occupation of the sites already opie or selected by the Company. % j&gt;-r (J 51 ' dlir 4,?-lid *Ld Iwad j jjv oJlAj 0 J 4*9Id) ''d • .5 JjC. jli-1 Jo 4) 4^9U*Ml «if~ 4ilaiil» Jk»:\ c .9l^JljlJ.ll)oMc-'o -iiUiiaudj ^ '4^yC&gt;-j'o- w 54lid^ 4iL»ll ( 4*19^1 ( rtA* ‘-N ) 4 jbMI •jA j: ! l 4*b 4il9 a 2 . l* r^ ^ ^jMl 4j\ c .j.i! •'jiyi tj ji-«i 3y* p ~ ■ A * , . ^ ) (ji jl.A Yo IjZ 4iai ; -XlP j JjaW •Jillll-Uc. Pi \ t l 4ia*)L~j Lvi J ', ( 4 ,^) j-JU-h J' by ^.*•1^ 41i 4)' ^1 A YO 4la4l)l ^a a ^*4.**.^ ja l* f z ^ 0 • Y’ • J^iall -l 3 ^- 4Ja* 11 4ikdl •d &gt; jb \ t ’A jl 3b&gt;-i y ydl y •Uji ^—'' JaJI^JojMI 4ii*L» 49ljjl J 4.1»M J ; L. o^b b'^b J &gt;b j3^' ^b cf J] ^*: J jrJl-ar J 3' bolil ^^-*-11 ^lil v-b J . lif. 0.11 49liJl 4ik:II(*) V this Agreti (b) 5 f signatu first (5) fi shall be n On fir On sec On thi On foe On fif There anniversar l Rupees th English tor saved and the “ Shoal three mon the date o: Rupees whichever (c) ] Coimuercia dance wit! during the period of i then the j become el declaration Rupees th English to (Article 5 whicheverarti ior ths pu shall not 1 its derivati “tha Subst its opsrati employees of any wa' be produc ART! ths date c Company £ of tha Sul is payable months pj statement due to th- report ofi during sii resentativ such ret well as a confidenti tion of si required ART payments hereby c period of right to produce and othe the Sul necessar; purposes AR' carry on pied by mosques, AR Article coramen which thi out a wi accordar least st a day for— 6 — ARTICLE 5. In calculating Royalty lor th 3 purpose of this Agreement account shall not be taken of any Petroleum and its derivatives (hereinafter referred to as “th 3 Substances” used by the Company in its operations or used by the Company’s employees within the Shoal Area nor of any water or foreign matter which may be produced with the substances. ARTICLE 6 . On each anniversary of the date of signature of this Agreement the Company shall deliver to the Shaikh a return of the Substances if any on which royalty is payable for the year ended three ( S ) months prior to such anniversary and a statement of the amount of royalty if any due to the Shaikh for such year, and a report of its operations under this Agreement during such year. The Shaikh or his Rep resentative shall have the right to check such returns and statements which, as well as any reports shall be treated as confidential by the Shaikh with the excep tion of such figures therein as he may be required by law to publish. ARTICLE 7. In consideration of the payments prescribed in Article 4 the Shaikh hereby grants to the Company for the period of this Agreement the exclusive right to explore search for drill for produce win refine transport sell export and otherwise deal with or dispose of the Substances and to do all things necessary for all or any of the above purposes within the Shoal Area. ARTICLE 8 . The Company shall not car ry on any operation within areas occu pied by or devoted to the purposes of mosques, sacred buildings or graveyards. ARTICLE 9. For the purpose of this Article the date of discovery of oil in commercial quantities shall be the date upon which the Company has completed and tested out a We U or wells capable of producing in ac cordance with first-class oil practice at feast seven hundred ( 700 ) tons of oil a day for a period of thirty consecutive days. u — A — ju ■ ya* I _ u* (j 1 pax &gt; 1 -.^ * 11 aiS'j ;&gt;i;ukn wtfyDi y Sr* y J - A-oU! oUl 'S' IJ Lj ]1 cJ! jcdibj ^uU» L&gt;L'j fj* \ j X) j a:J 1 y *a! j'-b'j *' 1 y jlk j** J&gt;-A) y L&gt; — O j'a) y j)**' 0 ol.U!J.II. Ail - aa, U olll UrNI A»&gt;ljfl \-lp~ aJU;NI ••A* y 3 u* A s* y j ji j’ . &lt;jlsJl Aikil (j U*A&gt;-I j' •Ji^A &lt; ' , r ^_i; Mi v; - oltll jl - Al^l . jiljtll j A^-liil ViMlj jl;5^U1 e-U Ai'_wl:'l o'H ^ WJI i jU jriUt O j 1 » J b' . &lt;J'^uy p - f 8 i IeSiARTI the expiry Company found in c hereof) ? year, the Shaikh a i Substances the said Ci which is c Article 4, of its opei Shaikh or right to cl and all si the repor shall be tr ART have the for fresh' Substance! lorries, ai utensils, ii supplies, i equipment other ma whatsoevs and its e operations Substance by the Cc duty and shall pay and genei Company employee duty i n Shoal An &lt; b ) °f firean except w Shaikh.— V — ARTICL &lt;0. Within three months after the expiry of the calendar year in which the Company has declared that oil has been found in commercial quantities ( Article 9 hereof) and of each subsequent calendar year, the Company shall deliver to the Shaikh a statement of the amount of the Substances won saved and exported during the said calendar year and of the royalty which is or might have been payable under Article 4, hereof, together with a report of its operations during the said year. The Shaikh or his representative shall have the right to check such returns and statements, and all such returns and statements and the reports of the Company’s operations shall be treated as confidential by the Shaihk. ARTICL 11. (a) The Company shall have the right to import water, and drill for fresh water within the Leased Area, the Substances, fuel, machinery, motorcars and lorries, aircraft, equipment, plant, timber, utensils, iron work, building materials, food supplies, medicines, medical supplies, office equipment and household furniture, and other materials, equipment and goods of whatsoever nature required by the Company and its employees for the purpose of its operations hereunder and to export the Substances and articles previously imported by the Company free of customs or export duty and taxes or other charges, but it shall pay on all personal goods, clothing and general merchandise imported by the Company for the personal use of its employees or for resale to them the ordinary duty in force for the time being in the Shoal Area and the Surface Rights Area. (b) The importation by the Company firearms and other weapons is prohibited, except with the written permission of the Shaikh. Jt z\ aW j &lt;;i —;;&gt;UI oUJ ) ^ ^ o' aJ l» Aa«* Aj If* ( wlJ! • J h Lj JLU A^.UI * j Jkt! A.^J! A~JI olil y* jiT y ^ . ijf HI cJI oil Ul j j oli ui j juJJI [-* “aS'^I oUU jrjUlJlj J 'a^^lb (I) —;^ ;,UI ULil! ll'j iy ) j ,L:JI ^yj A) jl&gt; ji-l oWy-allj jA r LlioU f lljA aS^IHaJ) if* j* jljll j *^1 UUN j j jXal^ j' p!&gt; l^aJI J* j j J 11 p-j' fib* (Jy*' A, jUIajJI-'JI &gt;1 ^ -M (v) . J* jib u*- 9 — ,nd water as may be necessary for the ‘ffective conduct of its operations hereunder Provided further that aircraft required or the Company’s operations shall only be jperated in accordance with regulations, if m y, which may be made by the Govern- nent of Bahrain for the operation of air craft generally (b) The Company shall under normal conditions accept and transmit free of charge on its wireless and telegraph in stallations such of the Shaikh’s messages as will not interfere with the Company’s business, and in times of national emergency the Shaikh shall have the necessary use free of charge of the Company’s wireless and telegraph installations and railways for governmental purposes. (c) The Company may use harbours constructed by the Government of Bahrain provided that they do not when so doing, impede or interfere with the use of those harbours by the subjects of the Shaikh. The Shaikh’s ships shall have the right to use harbours utilised or constructed by the Company provided that such use in no way hampers the Company or interferes in any way with the safety of its operations of which the Company shall be the sole judge. Any wharves or appurtenances con structed by the Company shall be for its exclusive use. ARTICLE 14. The Company shall have the right to lay down pipelines, roadways and transport facilities and to construct and erect the necessary buildings and machinery required for the transport or passage of crude oil over and in the territ- 01 y covered by the Concession granted by the Shaikh under date 2 nd, December, 1925, 9n over an y concession that the Shaikh 9 r ant of a later date than this Agreement provided that it shall not exercise such right in such manner as to er w ^b the operations of the Com- n y olding that Concession, nor shall ‘ ch right include the use of the harbour construct 1 f Wl “ Ch that Com P an y ma y land ‘ l0r ° Wn 0 P era ti° ns or of the Comn m ac * u&amp; l occupation of that JlnaU ^LJJI liib ^ j 1 ^'1 O'jLLjl (jl Ai ls ^c- J rc.-t IfJl A r U.I !*&gt;! IfikL' ( j ^5' ) (j'V JaiS , 3**1 b LA '3 /vL.'i Jl k* j:ll J Vl.ll Ji^NI J -&lt;,. 1)1 &gt; v ) j b ^ tj**’^ iJ* 1 ’ Jj Lb ^ j 1 ^..11) jLl) oljj’ , V dJ^**.)) J • jl j[\ Ju:~l &lt;.11) (g) . Jb*** - ^ (j c ^J J’SL ,3)1 * 3 '^' j' 3 ^* v y* m, ^ j' y»i' ^ /»i) y 3 &gt;-i‘'' **&gt; y ^ i; 3^ y ^ j — ^-b* 1 ^ L-*' i^b^i ^Jl Ij'U y Ji .0 i JUI Zj\:f Li'j V‘ NI ^ y.:-Sl J)l ^l;VI Jy f lil U!l JJj ^^r• it- ^a—!■&gt; f £ j j-;-H ^ jlr 3 ^..1)1 tj*J li&gt; 3**:^ M j! iLU &lt;/lb Jb^b 3-^^^ 3 ^' aj •jl31 3 l* ;: -'^ 3 ^ l f U jll ^jN! ^1 ^&lt;1 Lih: lylb- . Cls &lt;*111 dib*artk have free ( occupation uncultivatei the Corapai its operatio shall have areas of la exclusive si drilling ri( storage, ter ties and ar Company’s buy or leai houses or on conditi proprietors purchase o of those 01 pective loc (b) T such lands necessary Agreement the Shaikh houses an occupy for and buildi Company longer net returned 1 free of cc ARTI have the market ra constructh of every 1 ations her « v (b) subjects ( f°r all v under the skilled er °f labour Company Company labour, pr from neig °tay the also have— 10 — — \ * ARTICLE 15. (a) The Company shall have free of cost the unrestricted use and occupation of and surface rights over all uncultivated lands of the Shoal Area which the Company may need for the purpose of its operations and in particular the Company shall have the right to select an area or areas of land chosen by the Company with exclusive surface rights upon which to erect, drilling rigs, pump-stations, oil-refineries storage, terminal, shipping and aircraft facili ties and any other works required for the Company’s operations; and the Company may buy or lease for such purposes any lands, houses or buildings with the consent of and on conditions to be arranged with the proprietors thereof, but the terms of such purchase or lease shall not be in excess of those ordinarily current in their res pective localities. (b) The Company shall acquire only such lands, houses and buildings as are necessary for its operations under this Agreement. The Company shall inform the Shaikh from time to time of the land, houses and buildings which it requires to occupy for its operations; and land, houses and buildings previously acquired by the Company from the Shaikh but found no longer necessary for its operations shall be returned by the Company to the Shaikh free of cost. ARTICLE 16. (a) The Company shall have the right to purchase at current market rates fuel, water, food, building and constructional materials and other supplies of every kind in connection with its oper ations hereunder. (b) (b) The Company shall employ subjects of the Shaikh as far as possible I° r all work for which they are suited under the supervision of the Company’s billed employees, but if the local supply of labour should in the judgment of the onipany be inadequate or unsuitable the Company shall have the right to import a °ur, preference being given to labourers from neighbouring Arab countries who will 0 3 y the local laws. The Company shall a ^° ^ ave the right to import skilled and (jf ^ ij Ttic Ui A' jii ^ \i \ jC y' A)i y j JL. A^.9 J&gt;,y jt jyf- N '“-A J # *i . -Ai*&gt; yh tfyut da-* ^ ( v ) i.LrjU^yJl a^sU ‘^1 'oyy y 3 * . »• . y 1 a&gt;« q-jlu *^yj\ ♦ Ll'j ^ y* A&gt;_J^-^j* &lt;J 5 d&gt;'jiyy A.^wdun^l A^Aii^y^r 0 . r -uk:d ji (-) yi J .iSi Ct Jr d^\ jj,J y £r!i ly, ^ LAj^U) ^ilU' Jo*' Jr yj- Jl*' 1 —^ o’ jy.\a yil'j ^ ^&gt;1 . ; : U! yiyJltechnical f pay to the such wage Company i engaged. ARTK to the Cor property a] theft, higl damage and appoint in &lt; itself pay 1 all times 1: the Shaikh irotecting and its emt at its own the accomi places as 1 ARTI stances foi for conve weight shi determiner Shaikh am of oil and gravity. The i stances by technical represents have the i and to exi may represents ary and u of fire an all examin in such m; interferen upon s such appl: order the be put i n reasona examinati discovery orror sha bearing oonsiderei d a r Monti or fron— 11 — technical employees. The Company shall pay to the workmen it employs a fair wage, such wage to be decided and stated by the Company at the time the workmen are engaged. ARTICLE 17. The Shaikh shall give to the Company and its employees and property all protection in his power from theft, highway robbery, assault, wilful damage and destruction,and the Company may appoint in consultation with the Shaikh and itself pay trustworthy guards who shall at all times be subjects of the Shaikh unless the Shaikh permits otherwise to assist in protecting the property of the Company and its employees. The Company shall erect at its own expense suitable buildings for the accommodation of such guards at such places as the Company shall decide. ARTICLE 18. In measuring the Sub stances for purposes of royalty the factor for conversion of the volume of oil into weight shall be such figure as may be determined and agreed upon between the Shaikh and the Company after the discovery of oil and the ascertainment of its specific gravity. The Company shall measure the Sub stances by a method customarily used in good technical practice and the Shaikh by his representative duly authorised by him shall have the right to observe such measuring and to examine and test whatever applian ces may be used for such measuring. Such representative shall comply with all necess ary and usual safeguards for the prevention of fire and other accident; and shall maire all examinations and tests at such times and in such manner as will cause the minimum of interference with the company’s operations. “ u P on such examination or testing any such appliance shall be found to be out of order the Company will cause the same to e P ut in order at its own expense within a reas °nable time, and if upon any such | ® xam ination aforesaid any error shall be ^covered in any such appliance, such j-rror shall - if the Shaikh so decides after earing the Company’s explanation - be | considered to have existed for Three(3)Calen- • ar Months previous to the discovery there- 0r from the last occasion of examining the —- \N — • (J^y*^®****' U-Xip l^dU* ^ &lt;*&gt; LJI oUl • j j ZS. iju* j! } j\aJ1\\j j!i»jO j jj&gt;-\ ‘ J G' l»\cj ^a Li 1 OSC-bf A) la- I jJpLJ villi • A* *\^T. + aa+A ^ . Uj^ir ^11 ^\a^\ *1 yi-! ^l^ll t/Lij All—ob! “oil! JaI; j jy» ^jJ! ^j! jj^! aL 3 a * J' 3 ! ^ ! JLa) A^ jjA) A_a1c ^l! aS^DI ' J'sfl y A*1a!I l«*^ L^lc Aai j1q)1&gt; jl» ^jl-! al» ^^aII AjjX- aLa*!^ O'*! j&gt;X aJ l/**^!-* ^ la* jl o-^^y • l )'***'' 1 AtiU! a&gt; 15^! ^*7 ^&gt;-Nl !-Xft xp *y*&gt; y &lt;s j»-! ^ j!--!! \yyj^^y }U*-OlU*j!^. j 1 ?- •! j&gt;-!j! 1 j« 1 'Xp*a&gt;.j !^! a) N! *ift^cl^a&gt; j! AfT^.UI a) ! A)J IS! Jll! !i* J‘- jli -if W j (r) x* a‘» V jOmaS^JJI ^l-»» I -A*; •tz* j* j* A&gt;lO^! Ji Aaa-T' ^ A.*^*same in c such peric the Royal! If the Cor alter, ref appliance? to the Sh&gt; able a re' present d replacem( The correct r aforesaid Shaikh sb times to liberty to records s the Shaik ART have the i of three of this A( months i to termi Agreemer the date notice. (*») than 30 j ture the determine and dutie rial and that for a receipt c purchase replacem reciation tailing a 26 hereo ( c ) 36 years a ll the p PropertyI game i n case such occasion shall be within such period of Three Calendar Months and the Royalty shall be adjusted accordingly. If the Company should find it necessary to alter, repair or replace any measuring appliances it shall give reasonable notice to the Shaikh or his representative to en able a representative of the Shaikh to be present during such alteration, repair or replacement. The Company shall keep full and correct records of all measurements as aforesaid and the said representative of the Shaikh shall have access at all reasonable times to such records and shall be at liberty to make extracts from them. Such records shall be treated as confidential by the Shaikh and his representative. ARTICLE 19. (a) The Company shall have the right at any time after the expiry of three years from the date of signature of this Agreement to give the Shaikh six months notice in writing of its intention to terminate this Agreement and this Agreement shall absolutely determine on the date fixed for such termination in such notice. (b) If such notice be given not later than 30 years after the date of such signa ture the Company shall be entitled on such determination to remove free of all taxes and duties all plant building stores mate rial and property of every sort provided that for a period of three months from the receipt of such notice the Shaikh may \ purchase the same at a price equal to the replacement value at that date less dep reciation which price shall be agreed or ieihng agreement settled under Article 26 hereof. ( c ) If such notice be given later than 30 years after the date of such signature . a h the property aforesaid shall become the ; Property of the Shaikh free of all cost. ARTICLE 20 . On the expiry of this : ^reement at the end of the period of I ^ ev enty-five Years provided in Article 2 or — \t • JL* • ^' (J Jl*' J ^ , — ' , » . » » oN 1 aJJ-lLJ j li ^ La)) ; - jjNj. jl J* A - ' ^ y /'t **' 1 S'* , a A; ji y JUJ-NI 1 ^.3- (j ji-'p-*- . _ L; * ‘ i ^ j LaI) LJ! j** LL j jjil' j LLLLia^ . A: jA-IaJ j (I) ;iLU Ic- ft.+iy)\ •f -Oyb ‘ -X*) A: L5 qJJ! AJU'bH JlUl y a:- . j/UVI I-X* j i^L-L ^ j/lfrV' &lt; 1 &gt;-X&gt;- (V ) \ y}\ IjlA -XnJ LL ^ ti j J ] d.Uo ^ y&gt; L Xc- *S jj’itj j oL- xi^c ji y&lt;&gt; ^ A)\ ]cf jA'! [fty L^-» o^’ ij*-)' #-X* jj* Al*2&gt;- ^ l r L&gt;L:J a*-*.* ^jL.5 U* J L y . A A L* NI oJfiy^y jlah yW ^ ( a) . J; [aa y KL UL !y yti* y ^ Al-» j ^any extern the movab Company handed Producing such ex pi reasonably ARTI of Article the right 1 to take w: the Compi the Surfac : (o any of the ment with they fall ( [ ' (b) 1 in respect Article 26 Furt Agreemen the rights Limited u December as not 1 with the of the sail Pro 1 Article si the Comp or remo\ of the ar cession. AR] ment sha way the i Parties c( other the tide 5 pn of the Ci injurious; If 1 sequent %eeme cessions— 43 — any extension or renewal of that period all the movable and immovable property of the Company in the Shoal Area shall be handed over to the Shaikh free of cost. Producing wells or borings at the time of such expiry shall be handed over in reasonably good order and repair. ARTICLE 21. Subject to the provisions of Article 24 hereof the Shaikh shall have the right to terminate this Agreement and to take without payment all the property of the Company in the Shoal Area and over the Surface rights area if. (a) The Company shall fail to make any of the payments prescribed in this Agree ment within 6 months of the date on which they fall due, or [ • (b) The Company shall be in default in respect of an arbitration award under Article 26 hereof. Further the rights conferred by this, Agreement are in all respects subject to the rights of the Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited under their lease dated the 2 L :th. December, 1934, and shall be so exercised as not to damage, impede or interfere with the property operations and interests of the said Company under their said lease. Provided always that nothing in this Article shall be interpreted as debarring the Company from drilling in, and winning or removing oil from, any and every part °f the area covered by this present Con cession. ARTICLE 22. Nothing in this Agree ment shall be read as restricting in any wa y the right of the Shaikh to grant to other Portias concessions or permits for materials other than the Substances as delined in Ar ticle 5 provided that the operations and rights °f the Company hereunder are not thereby injuriously affected. If the Shaikh should at any date sub- ^quent to the date of signature of this 9 r eement grant to any other parties con- oossions or permits as aforesaid the Shaikh ix\ji Jbaf y ju&gt; y u itii oil' j O&amp;Clrif jl&gt; yujjj ui u » ' &lt;&lt;Jl^ A) iii-j Adtlj A-.9u.‘Nj •-!&gt; ^ J^ \ma y j (3^:'. &lt;y ytP~ AlLaL* ^ A?l 5 jj O&amp;lL/ Ail ^ j*t}\ O(') 'S' ( v ) oUU'.i* ♦I^A^J* U I*.-*’ ^ . A.*§L».''i' y* - **'^ A«oL~)i Jli- ^ £s* 0 •i. t 9 . N c srt a:- r A J Jlut.' N A^jl*: J**:**•’ jl ^ ^-L ^»j oisdli.c a^iH Jjj *’j . *^ ac ' j a1&lt; ; J ll-' 3 'u^N IU* j. ! aaL:1 ' * 1 ^*3&gt;- Ai .LL jJL-L UviO &gt; j' P A.f ei* • &gt; - . • • ** ji * l r^ a i* J ; Ja-I' A.' ^yr UUNt &gt;T j- / v'j-'Vi .-&gt;» j- - u '- «„L!I x ( .:, •‘f i (.J* : IT^y J ' J '-''3 I^UUundertakes that such concessions shall con tain provisions requiring the holders thereof to abstain from damaging, impeding or interfering with the property, operations and interests of the Company. Provided always that nothing in this Article shall be interpreted as debarring the Company from drilling in, and winning or removing oil from, any and every part of the area covered by this present Con cession. ARTICLE 23. (a) The Shaikh hereby agrees that the Company may transfer the obligat ions and benefits of this Agreement to a British Company to be called or to- any other Company registered within the British Empire, provided that consent of the Shaikh and the approval of Kis Britannic Majesty’s Government has first been obtained to such transfer. (b) If in the opinion of the two Com panies conncerned during the course of development of the ‘ Shoal Area” and the ‘Hawar Islands” Area it becomes clear that some degree of concentration on one area is likely to expedite and facilitate the discovery and production of oil in commer cial quantities in one or both areas then the personnel, supplies, property, services and facilities of whatsoever nature of either Company may be freely placed at each other’s disposal under their own arrangements for convenience of working the defined Areas a whole, whilst maintaining the separate entity of eanh of the Companies. Further the Companies will have the eight to distribute their drilling obligations as they think best over either or both Concession Areas provided always that the total annual drilling footage completed between the two Companies is not less than the aggregate of the drilling obligations ^th which each Company separately under 1 * ,s r espective Agreement must comply. (c) Similarly, provided that the total Annual payments made in any year by the ^°nipanies shall not be less than the ag- 9 re gate of the amounts which each Company se P3rately is bound to pay in that year under its respective Agreement, then the Elective discharge of the said obligations * ^ * I • jii-x ^11 Ailadi u V d . JiJJ 3LL.MI 1i* £JS\ ^ ' olL| oik) j &lt;. *b*l d yiS lil • (v_j) j ^Uc '-^ 1 ^ JbLi- La j j\ uy5k;Ll j \ jU zJ- o* ^ \c^ 4$^' -*:*) ‘Sj-y iib 1 ' • (j - 4 Icjd .;d villi ^ d k 9 d^ 9 ' c^*'ljro U l^A.1 P IjuI d* 1 *^ o' 1^1^ jl &lt;£.As*-! c . V * . , pU»i j&gt;\\ d ■■■*■• • #-x&gt;- d ja &lt;j Jvii k^rv—l vib-idj ( ^ ) ^LU d d' &lt;;-l\ till) d ^ . IflsU'l— 15 — in regard to annual payments may be effected by either one, or jointly by the two Companies, in such proportions as the -discharging Companies may think fit, and for this purpose either of the Companies may take over from the other the sub stances, and may utilize or export the same as if such substances had been produced from its respective defined Area, whilst maintaining the separate entity of each of the Companies. ARTICLE 24. Failure on the part of the Company to fulfil any of the conditions of this Agreement shall not give the Shaikh any claim against the Company or be deemed a breach of this Agreement in so far as such failure arises from force majeure, and if through force majeure the fulfilment by the Company of any of the conditions of this Agreement be delayed the period of such delay shall be added to the periods fixed by this Agreement. Force majeure as used in this Ag reement includes the Act of God, war, insurrection, riot, civil commotion, tide, storm, tidal wave, flood, lightning, explosion, fire, earthquakes and any other happening which the Company could not reasonably prevent or control. ARTICLE 25. The Shaikh shall not by general or special legislation or by [ administrative measures or by any other I act whatever annul this Agreement except as provided in Article 21. No alteration shall be made in the terms of this Agreement by either the Shaikh or the Company except in the event °f the Shaikh and the Company jointly I agreeing that it is desirable in the interests both parties to make certain alterations deletions or additions to this Agreement. ARTICLE 26. (a) If at any time during the currency of this Agreement any dif- ; terence or dispute shall arise between the | Parties hereto concering the interpretation or execution hereof, or anything herein detained, or in connection herewith, or SI — &gt;o— jo j J i£±&gt;H Li 6 ^y U U &gt;y i ^ ^ p Jr .. A -h fLili j -i*’ \^f~ 0 j Jtll ^ A)J^ . l f L^ y ^ r ~^ j P Ai y A^b'jJ-U; j 1 Ml aJUM 1 (jfh j* [-t c J ^ • D J* M aJIaMI ^ u L / ji v 0 - Ai ' ijuMi .i» j 1 j j' J’•v 1 - ,1s 1^1 aJIaM' s* - J All (1 )- jjA^^Ul W9 » * ... t cuir .y- j 1 J 1 V : - x “. J ' 1 oui/jjyxi y |j:16 — —n— |h e rights or liabilites of either party hereunder, the same shall, failing any Agreement to settle it in any other way, be referred to two arbitrators, one of whom shall be chosen by each party, and a referee, who shall be chosen by the arbit rators before proceeding to arbitration. (b) Each party shall nominate its own arbitrator within Sixty days after delivery of a request so to do by the other party failing which its arbitrator may at the request of the other party be designated by the British Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. In the event of the arbitrators failing to agree within Sixty days after being chosen or designated the British Political Resident in the Persian Gulf may appoint a referee at the request of the arbitrators or of either of them. (c) The decision of the arbitrators, or in a case of a difference of opinion between them the decision of the referee, shall be final and binding upon both parties. (d) In giving a decision the arbitrators or the referee shall specify an adequate period of delay during which the party against whom the decision is given shall conform to the decision and that party shall be in default only if that party has failed to conform to the decision prior to the expiry of that period and not otherwise. (el The place of arbitration shall be su ch as may be agreed by the parties and iu default of agreement shall be London. ARTICLE 27. The Company shall make all Payments that become due to the Shaikh under this Agreement into the Shaikh’s ac count with the Eastern Bank Limited Bahrain, an d the Bank’s receipt shall be a full 'fischarge for the Company in respect to tlle Payment of the sum stated in the Bank’s coceipt. The Shaikh may from time to time designate in writing another Bank or ^ a nks for the purpose of this Article. » 1 J.»- j &gt; &lt;/ (v) j ji- SI Ji j* wil» k? ^.IL ♦l_ij &lt;«\»&gt; jii dAI-L ^ j* 1^1 j *11 ^ JUSI j . IaL. a»l j ij* J 02 ^-^' j (j jl ^Xi-I jly jl (^) ja\\ ^c. \c^j ^ ^ j** ^ ^ j ji&gt; ^ a-KO j III! O-U ly-*' O' liA j' jly)l Jiy jl ^ ^y.^lL.1 lil SI l^J .Sl^-xliJiI'dll*' j'yli O' aJc- ^ 0 ^- 0 ,&lt;T ( » ) . o*^ J o/t* 3'^’f O u, .y-' - Ojj ^ ' l ***'' ! UU-SI .i&gt; oUiil J. ^Jl j jd jyO)l dljl J ^0)1 J] A,A dL»l S&gt;oLi' JuSI o/tJ . oJUl 1 j 02 ^' ^ o' &gt;' 3' 02 *' o* C ;^' 1 d^ : ^ J l^j^ j' ^'^. 02 :' ^ ^f) © — n — — NV — ARTICLE 28. This Agreement is writ ten in English and translated into Arabic. If there should at any time be disagreement as to the meaning or interpretation of any clause in this Agreement the English text shall prevail. In witness whereof the parties to this Agreement have set their hands the Day and Year first above written:- aJUtNI j j ol*)l oil 1 j^ Ijl yl 4&gt;lj . J-**! A&gt; ^ *- 1 ^ jli yd! U doiJ w dkacMMs jiCn Ji jt. THE COMPANY THE SHAIKH Cr 11 IN THE PRESENCE OF till jj IN THE PRESENCE OFMemorandum for presentation to His Highness the Huler at a meeting on 5th April 1939 with the object of making clear to His Highness the unusual conditions that are attached to submerged areas in conducting geological examinations, pros pecting and developing. And to point out that methods that are routine on land have to be modified when operating on submerged areas. Also to assure His Highness that the Com pany is desirous of developing the 'Shoal Area' with the least possible delay. Your Highness : After Greetings. 1. I have the honour to bring it to your Highness 1 s notice that during previous meetings v our Highness was good enough to assure me that when the question of the Hawar Islands was settled you would be prepared to consider an offer by my Company for the submerged lands which I propose to refer to as the 'Shoal Area'. 2. A map showing the boundaries of the 'Shoal Area' for which I am applying to Your Highness is attached to the 'Shoal 'Area' draft agreement presented herewith. Your Highness will note that the area is marked on the map in red and is the same as proposed for Petroleum Conces sions Limited in Your Highness’s suggestions for partition in June 1938, less the Hawar Islands Group and its waters. 3. Your Highness will appreciate that prospecting and developing an area - entirely submerged under varying depths of the sea - presents an entirely different problem to that of developing an area on dry solid land. The amount of pre paratory work required to explore and develop a submerged are&amp; and to provide against storms and rough seas, is both costly and extensive. The greater part of the preliminary work on the sub merged lands is in addition to that necessary on dry lands and as a consequence the work takes longer to carry out. 4. Your Highness may be interested to hear that each drilling site entails the erection of a heavy platform upon which/- 2 - which to mount the derrick and the drilling machinery. The platform has to be placed - at least 15 feet above the high tide mark - and be supported on some 50 re-inforced concrete piles, each 40 feet long. The piles have to be driven into the bottom of the sea to a depth of 25 feet. Your Highness will see that much extra work is involved under the conditions described above, therefore a longer time is necessary to achieve results. Initial and annual payments prior to production, should reasonably be smaller to compen sate for the increased cost of development. 5. Terms submitted for consideration (a) Payments The payments considered reasonable in the circumstances are shown in appendix 'A' to this memorandum. They are less than those offered for Hawar for the reasons explained in preceding paragraphs. (b) Commercial production Your Highness will note that in spite of the increased difficulties of production from submerged lands, commercial production has been left at 700 tons (the same as in the Hawar Agreement) with a view to troubling Your Highness with re-discussions as little as possible. (c) Drilling obligations Owing to the abnormal conditions which are encountered on submerged lands, particularly in the initial and 'trxal and error” period, the Company has allowed 5 years (instead of 4 in the Hawar terms) that is an extra year to cope with the first 4000 feet. Y r our Highness will doubtless agree that this is reasonable. Apart from this extra year drilling obligations are the same as those of the Hawar Agreement which we believe were acceptable to Your Highness. (d) Article No. 23 in the draft Your Highness’s attention is drawn to Article No.23 in the draft Agreement, the reasons for possible transfer or/-7 / -3- or amalgamation may be explained briefly as follows Your Highness’s wish and the Company’s aim is to reach commercial production and locate profitable oil fields in the earliest possible time. It may become clear at some stage in the development of the two areas that this result can - in the long run - best be achieved by concentrating more on one area than on the other for a time. The extent of this concentration and its value in expediting oil production on the desired scale xan only be judged as examination and experiment give rise to the more general problems of the best way of exploiting the potential &lt;hil-f ields. I think Your Highness however will understand that a situation can very easily arise in which it would be to the advantage of all concerned if the development of the two areas were controlled as one unit. If this were acted upon it would mean that the Companies’ personnel, supplies, property, services and facilities of whatsoever nature could be freely placed at each Company’s disposal, under their own arrange ments. This would be convenient for working the defined areas as a whole, whilst maintaining the separate entity of each of the Companies. The object is as Your Highness will see to hasten the day oil royalties commence. 6. Although the Hawar Islands if proved, provide a pro mising field, its area is very small and its oil deposits may be quite limited and exhausted in a few years. Hawar plus ”Shoal Area” however offers a much better chance of developing an oil-field capable of yielding oil over a long period and thereby supplying a steady revenue for the State of Bahrain. The combined areas also constitute a field large enough to justify very special attention by my Company even if curtailment or delay on other territories is involved.7. The Surface Rights Area The 'Surface Hights' Area as described in the draft Agreement for the 'Shoal Area' (Article Ho. 1) is a prime necessity as a base from which the activities of the Company can be directed. It would be very difficult - if not impossible - to develop the oil resources of the r, 3hoal Area' without such 'Surface Rights'. I feel sure that Your Highness will appreciate the necessity of the Company being granted such use of the 'Surface Rights' Area which is shown on the attached map, outlined and scored crosswise in red as described above. 8. Should there be any noint which Your Highness requires ' further information, I am always at Your Highness's complete disposal. I have the honour to be, Your Highness's most obedient servant, Hnclos. Appendix 'A' (Particulars of Article No. 4 in the draft Agreement as regards payment).APVMDIX ’’A” Financial Terms for the M Shoal Area M Dr aft Agreement AHTICL3 NC. 4 (a) Initial Payment 30 days after the date of signature of the Agreement (b) On 1st Anniversay of the date of signature On 2nd ' ' ' ' On 3rd f « ' n n On 4th ' ' tt t? On 5th ^ ^ »» Rs 200,000 Rs 100,000 Rs 100,000 Rs 100,000 Rs 100,000 Rs 100,000 Jl Thereafter annually on each subsequent anniversay EITHER Royalty of Rs 3/8 per English ton of 2240 lbs. of petroleum won, saved and exported during the year OR Rs 275,000 whichever shall be the greater. (c) But if the discovery of oil in commercial quantities (i.e. 700 tons of oil a day for a period of 30 consecutive days) be declared at any time during the currency of five (5) years / para (b) hereof_7 then the following annual payments will become effective from the date of such declaration EITHER Rs 3/8 Royalty OR Rs 275,000 whichever shall be the greater sum. oOooiimmary of Meeting at Manamah on the 5th April 1939 bo It) Abbreviations H.H, His Highness the Shaikh M.H. Major Holmes Adv. Adviser. Present Bahrain Government His Highness the Ruler Shaikh Mohammad bin Isa Shaikh Salman bin Hamad Mr. Dalrymple Belgrave. P.C.L . Major F. Holmes Mr. S.V. Packer Mr. Ashraf (Secretary to Major Holmes) M.H. After the usual exchange of courtesies M.H. after asking H.H’s permission presented the Draft Agreement for the Shoal Area, an explanatory memorandum, and a separate Arabic translation of Article 23. Copies of the memorandum and Article 23 were also distributed to Shaikh Mohammad, Shaikh Sulman and Mr. Belgrave for perusal. H.H. H.H. accepted the draft and accompanying memorandum and pointed out that he could not discuss them or say anything in the matter until a reply came from London on the Hawar question and it was settled. H.H. said if M.H. was going home he could perhaps expedite matters in London, and that he H.H. was ten times more anxious even than M.H. for the reply from the British Government. M.H. M.H. pointed out that should a reply come after he had left for London the completion of the Hawar question as far as the Company was concerned could be settled by Mr. Packer. H.H. H.H. agreed that this was satisfactory to him. M.H. M.H. emphasized his Company’s wish to make the Hawar Concession payments as soon as a reply was received from London. H.H. H.H. said immediate payment was of no consequence. M.H. M.H. asked Mr. Belgrave if he could take it that H.H. was ready to discuss the Shoal Area when the Hawar question was settled. Adv. Mr. Belgrave confirmed that this was what H.H. intended to convey to Major Holmes. Note During general conversation H.H. remarked a propos of the lack of results in Qatar that he was sure that any concession area taken up by Major Holmes would produce oil. Sd/- 8rank Holmes.Minutes of a meeting held at the iidviserate on Wednesday 5th ^pril 1939. On 5th April 1939 His Highness Snaikh bir Haaad bin Isa Alkhalifah received Major Frank Holmes who was accompanied by Mr. E. V, Packer y I.d. ,. t and Ashraf . ohtiikhs Mohomed and Sulman and the Mvisar to the Bahrain Government were present. Major Frank Holmes presented His Highness with a draft agreement for the shoal area of Bahrain. His Highness informed Major Holmes that he would give it his consideration but was not prepared to make any decision until he had received a certain communication from His Majesty’s Government in London regarding the Hawar area. iidviser # Bahrain Government. Major Frank HolmesConfidential Hr Sl'^HIRE RESIDENCY. CONFiBEfTRAL RECORDS D.O. No. C/246-1.a/29 Dated the 13th April 1939 4b Cv-v ^ ^ Cx^\_yJ Will you please refer to the correspondence in regard to the Hawar Islands resting with your Express letter No. 192-S dated the 16th March 1939. 2. I was half way across the Qatar Peninsula on my way to see Shaikh Abdullah bin Qasim when I received the news of the Dubai disturbances and had to return at once without seeing the Shaikh. I have however now received a 17 page letter from him on the whole subject, with certain enclosures, the translation of which is not yet fully complete. I will send this across by the next mail together with my comments on the whole case. Yours sincerely, Honourable Lieutenant-Colonel 3 ir Trenchard Fowle, K.C.I.E., C.B.S., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, BushireBritish Residency &amp; Consulate-General, Bushire, the 22nd April 1939* TProm Ihe Hobble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. To His Hajesty f s Secretary of State for India, London. Copy to Secretary to the Government of India, Kxternal Affairs department, Sew Delhi. The Political Agent, Bahrai n. Subject &gt;- Bahrain Oil - Offer by Petroleum Concessions Limited for •Shoal Area.* Memorandum. In continuation of ayrrespondence ending with ray Printed Letter No.320-3 dated the 7th April 1939, I enclose herewith a copy of letter dated the 5th April 1939 from Major F. Holmes of Petroleum Concessions Limited, to the Political Agent, Bahrain, with copy of its enclosures other than the draft agreement mentioned therein. I have received only one oopy ol the agreement from the Political Age lit, Bahrain, a--d suggest that copies for the India Office and the Government of India may be obtained from Petroleum Concessions Limited Head Office at London. 2. As the question of the grant of a concessio * over the entire Unallotted Area is under consideration by His Majesty’s Government, I am not commenting on the present proposals of the Petroleum Cone«asios Limited. Jj-^ Y! * 3d. T. C. Fowls. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. ATTSST&amp;D. /&gt; for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.Confidential (AT § t h &gt;4 ^ / Mr , v / GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. Department. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). —This is an ORIGINAL message sent by AlH MAIL which provides a means of communication more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department ] No. To 39 5* 1 * *3 Buahire, Dated JSm 22nd April 1939. His Majesty's Secretary of State for India # London* Repeated Secretary to the Government of India, iilxternal Affairs Department, Dew Delhi. Political Agent, Bahrain* Subject *- Bahrain Unallotted Area* Reference correspondence ending with my Sxpress Letter I-o*192-3 dated the 16th March 1939* 2* Political Agent, Bahrain, informs me that he has now received the counter claim from the Shaikh of ^atar and is forwarding this to me by next mail with his comments* Sd* T.C.Fowle* Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. S. 44. MFP—104 8 S&amp;P—(M-2042)—17-12»37—20,000. Designation)4 o*,U* A Confidential b No. C/266-1.a/29 From To Political Agency, Bahrain, the 22nd April 1939. E. Weightman, Esquire, I.C.S., Political Agent, Bahrain. hesic^ncy. I No .6..0.P........ Date COMFi[&gt;ENTlAL RECORDS* The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Subiect Ownership of Eawar Islands. Sir, I have the honour to refer to the correspondence on the above subject resting with paragraph 2 of your Express letter No. 192-S dated the 16th March 1939, and to forward herewith a translation of a letter dated the 30th March 1939 from Shaikh Abdullah bin Qasim A1 Thani, Shaikh of Qatar, together with its enclosures, being his rejoinder to the Bahrain Governments counter-claim to the Eawar Islands. 2. The documents in this case are now the following b. U' • ft * 4^ . ' ■ (1) Letter dated the 10th May 1938 from Shaikh Abdullah bin Qasim A1 Thani to me, of which a copy was forwarded to ^ fi.uq - • you with my Express letter No. C/312 dated the 15th May 1938. The substance of this letter was a complaint against ,f the interference and action taken by the Bahrain Government at Hawar, which is a dependency of Qatar 1 ’. (2) Letter dated the 27th May 1938 from Shaikh Abdullah bin Qasim A1 Thani, a translation of which was forwarded to you with my Express letter No. T/3 dated the 3rd June 1938. This letter contained the Shaikh of Qatar's formal claim to sovereignty over the Eawar Islands.- 2 - (3) A preliminary statement, outlining the Bahrain Govern ments counter-claim to the Hawar Islands, a copy of which „ n.U-q * bov3 (4) Letter No, 1972-S.F, dated the 3rd January 1939 from the Adviser to the Bahrain Government, a copy of which, with its enclosures, was forwarded to you with my Express letter —- Ri,b - b. I'M* • No, C/10 dated the 5th January 1939. This letter contained the Bahrain Government 1 s formal counter-claim. -Mi ‘ (5) The rejoinder from the Shaikh of Qatar now forwarded with this letter. I have made certain marginal comments on this. In addition mention should he made of letter No. C/180 dated the 28th April 1936 from the Adviser to the Bahrain Gover- ment, a copy of which was forwarded to you with my predecessor’s - ^.39* ^.$4 . letter No. C/217 dated the 6th Fay 1936. In this letter, which bears reference to the negotiations then proceeding for a con cession covering the Unallotted Area of the Bahrain possessions, the Bahrain Government formally stated their claim to sovereignty. 3. The Shaikh of Qatar’s claim, as set out in document No. 2, is based on the following :- (a) A plain asseveration of sovereignty over this group of islands as over other islands adjacent to Qatar, the coasts, promontories and ’’everything belonging to Qatar”. (b) A formal denial that Bahrain had, until recently, occu pied these islands or exercised jurisdiction in any form therein. (c) A claim that the islands, by virtue of geographical pro pinquity, are an integral part of the Qatar State. In addition to these, in submitting his rejoinder pp (document No. 5) the Shaikh of Qatar has forwarded papers v/hich purport to be statements by persons possessing local knowledge that the Eawar Islands belong not to Bahrain but to the Shaikh of Qatar. The value however of these latter documents is greatly diminished by the fact that the signatures on all of them are was also forwarded with my Express letter just quoted ^ - h• iirj in /-in one handwriting, unsupported by thumb impressions or seals of the alleged signatories. Nor is any description of the alleged signatories given, their place of residence or reason for having special knowledge of the Hawar Islands. There is no suggestion that they are residents, whether temporary or permanent, of Hawar — and indeed there could not be; and to be brief, their testimony is to my mind entirely valueless. 4. A claim for sovereignty based merely on geographical contiguity is, as I understand it, of little practical value save possibly in respect of an unoccupied area of land or an island lying contiguous to or in the territorial waters of the State raising the claim. Were this not so an equally valid claim to the whole of the Qatar Peninsula might presumably be raised by the Saudi Government l In the particular case of the Hawar Islands, or at least of the main Hawar Island, there is sufficient evidence to show that they have been occupied, whe ther temporarily or permanently, for the past 150 odd years. It follows therefore that the fullest consideration must be given to the circumstances attending that occupation, to the nationality of the occupants, the authority they recognise and to evidence of the exercise of direct jurisdiction over them; while geographical propinquity cannot be held by itself to raise any special presumption favourable to Qatar. This I believe to be correct even though at low springs it is possible (as I am informed though I have not verified this by experiment) to wade from the Qatar mainland to a certain point on the main Hawar Island in about three feet of water. 5. The bare assertion of sovereignty made by the Shaikh of Qatar must be devoid of value in the absence of corroboratory evidence. The only evidence offered in this dispute is that produced by the Bahrain Government, which the Shaikh of Qatar in his rejoinder attempts to show to be either false or in capable of bearing the construction put upon it by the Bahrain Government. /■-4- r m) Government. I propose therefore to examine this evidence and make some attempt to estimate its value. Before doing so how ever it may be well to make some brief mention of the earlier history of these islands. 6. (a) In the Persian Gulf Gazeteer, Volume II, page 1513 it is stated that the Dawasir of Zellaq in Bahrain have houses in two places in the island which they use in winter. (Zellaq is a village on the west coast of Bahrain and the Dawasir of that place have lived there for generations). ’ (b) In paragraph 7 of letter No. 207 dated the 4th April 1909 the then Political Agent, Bahrain, stated that on a visit to Hawar he had been told by the Dawasir who were then in resi dence that they, regarded Hawar as their own independent terri tory, the ownership of the island having been awarded to them by the Qadhi of Zubarah more than one hundred years earlier. He adds that the Qadhi at that time was an official of the A1 Khalifah, who were then in possession of Zubarah, and it would seem to follow therefore that Dawasir ownership of Hawar derived directly from the authority of the A1 Khalifah. The Political Agent mentioned a written decision, which however now seems to have disappeared. I might add that on a recent visit bo Eawar I received corroboration of this story, the local Dawasir claim ing that they had possessed more or less independent rights in Hawar since the days when the A1 Khalifah were in Zubarah. That the main island of Hawar has been inhabited for generations is evident from the fact that there are two quite considerable cemeteries in the island. 7. I have myself verified the accuracy of the statement p* made in the Bahrain counter-claim (document No. 4) that there are two villages in the main Hawar Island. These are quite small villages, occupied by about 35 and 20 families respectively, living in houses of the type known as ’ kubara* , i.e. built of unfaced stone and held together with mud and roofed with date palm. These are definitely more permanent constructions than fishermen f s /-fishermens ‘barasties 1 (palm huts) and some at least of them are occupied throughout the year. Hawar suffers from the absence of a permanent water supply, since the cisterns to which reference is made in the Bahrain counter-claim are only full after heavy rain and are subject to loss both from evaporation and from leakage. There was, for instance, heavy rain in Hawar a month ago, filling the cisterns to the brim, but the local people informed me that this water would be exhausted within three months. Water therefore, during much of the year, has to be brought across from Bahrain and this naturally restricts the number of persons remaining there permanently and makes it necessary for them to send their goats (except a few in milk) and their cattle across to Bahrain. Nevertheless a few people do remain there throughout the year, though whether this is equally true of the past I cannot say. 8. The Bahrain Government claim, and the Shaikh of Qatar denies, that there is good grazing for flocks and herds in the Hawar main island. I can state, from personal knowledge, that in this respect the Bahrain Government are right. After good rain the island provides better pasturage than Bahrain itself and even this year, when the rain was very late, there are still to-day between 50 and ICO animals in Hawar. This point is of importance as supporting the Bahrain statement that Eawar is considerably more than a temporary refuge for fishermen. Similarly it is quite true that the gypsum (or ji^ss) which is found in Hawar is excavated under licence from Bahrain. In point of fact on my recent visit to the island the local Dawasir complained that the Bahrain Government were over-free with their licences and that the juss reserves were Ti &gt; 0 being rapidly exhausted. 9. Mention is also made in paragraph 9 of the Bahrain counter-claim of the pearling boats owned by the Dawasir of Hawar. I believe that Hawar owns only four, but these four were /-were drawn up on the beach near the northern village during my visit there last week and they are admittedly registered in Bahrain. Were the Dawasir purely temporary visitors to the island, with their permanent habitations in Zellaq, their pearling boats would not be beached in Hawar. Nor indeed would there even be fishermen there at the present time, since fishing in the surrounding waters is suffering from its sea sonal decline. ^ 10. In their preliminary statement (document No. 3) the Bahrain Government state that the permanent fish traps at Hawar are registered in the Land Department of the Bahrain Government. This is not strictly accurate, since these traps have been under dispute for the past three years between mem bers of the Hawar Dawasir, and clearly registration cannot be effected until their dispute is settled. Nevertheless it is true that the dispute itself is before the Bahrain Sunni Shara Court and I have myself seen part of the record. The mere fact that the claimants to these traps, which have unquestion ably been in existence for several years, should refer their dispute to the Bahrain Government is of importance in indicat ing the exercise of jurisdiction by the Shaikh of Bahrain. Further and more important evidence of the exercise of juris diction by the Shaikh of Bahrain for years past is provided ——— ^ b. i2&gt;L4 */&gt; /*£ * in the two judgments forwarded with the Bahrain counter-claim. These two judgments, dating from some thirty years ago, are of unquestionable authenticity and both of them relate to dis putes in regard to ownership of 'land and sea properties' in Hawar. The Shaikh of Qatar in paragraph 11 of his rejoinder seeks to show that these two judgments are of no evidentiary value since it is, he claims, common for Qadhis of one Moslem country to settle disputes between the subjects of another Moslem country. This statement is of course true up to a point in 'personal' cases, but the Shaikh of Qatar would be the/-the first to deny that a Nejdi Qadhi, for instance, could settle a dispute between two Qatar subjects in respect of landed properties in Doha. 11. It may be acknowledged that owing to the adoption of more regular procedure in Bahrain than in Qatar, the Bahrain Government are in a better position to produce evidence of a judicial nature than is the Shaikh of Qatar. The record of a Bahrain case has for instance been submitted to me showing that processes were issued for the attendance of certain Hawar residents in a Bahrain Court seven years ago (i.e. long before the Zubarah dispute flared up, and before Hawar became of interest from the oil aspect). It would be unfair to make too much of the Shaikh of Qatar r s inability to match this evidence, but it is noteworthy that he does not, and so presumably cannot, claim that he himself has ever decided a dispute in regard to property of any description at Hawar. 12. It may be worth while making reference to the ooint men- tioned in paragraph 13 of the Bahrain counter-claim, in regard J to the rescue at Hawar by Shaikh 1 Isa of Bahrain of a party of Turkish soldiers who were wrecked there. On my recent visit to Hawar I enquired from the older men whether Turkish soldiers had ever landed at Hawar and the story of this wreck was repeat ed to me in considerable circumstantial detail. It is of no great evidentiary value except as indicating that the Shaikhs of Bahrain were in the habit in the past of visiting the island 13. To sum up. The Shaikh of Qatar has produced no evidence whatsoever. He relies solely on an uncorroborated assertion of sovereignty, on geographical propinquity and on the alleged statements of certain unidentified persons. On the Bahrain side there is evidence that the original occupation of Hawar by the Dawasir was effected under the authority of the A1 Khalifah, that the Zellaq Dawasir have frequented these islands L -j for a great number of years, that the courts established by- 8 - W) 1^- the Shaikhs of Bahrain have promulgated decisions in regard to disputes over property there, that questions of ownership of fish traps have been submitted to the decision of the Bahrain Shara Court, that seven years ago Bahrain processes were served in Hawar, that the boats owned by the Dawasir of Hawar are registered in Bahrain and that gypsum or juss is excavated from Hawar under licence from the Bahrain Government. I am not able to state definitely that these Dawasir have for the past 150 years occupied Hawar at all seasons of the year, though those now in residence there claim that this is so • On the other hand the cemeteries, the water cisterns, the ruins of the old fort which I have myself seen and the type of house in use all provide evidence of consistent occupation for at least the greater part of the year. And finally in the absence of any indication of occupation or of the exercise of jurisdic tion by the Shaikh of Qatar, the construction of a police post by the Bahrain Government there some 18 months ago, the build ing of a mosque in the northern village under the orders of His Highness the Shaikh of Bahrain and the efforts made to drive an artesian well constitute, in the light of older history, a valid and proper assumption of constitutional authority on the part of the Bahrain Government. The small barren and uninhabi ted islands and rocky islets which form the complete Hawar group presumably fall to the authority of the Buler estaolish- ing himself in the Hawar main island, particularly since marks have been erected on all of them by the Bahrain Government. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant,Translation of a letter dated the 9th Safar 1358 (30th March 1939) from Shaikh Abdullah bin Qasim A1 Thani, 'Ruler of Qatar, to the Political Agent, Bahrain. After Compliments. Reference your letter No. C/9 dated 5th January 1939 (14-11-1357) enclosing a copy of the Bahrain Government’s ^ b-S'b - . tvG letter about the Hawar Islands. I thank you for the short opportunity which you have afforded me to enable me to examine and investigate what has been written by the Bahrain Govern ment on this matter. Before commenting on the letter I beg to say :- FOREWORD Selfishness and covetousness are two of man’s natural instincts, on which nations have proceeded since times im memorial, and which drive some people after their coveted objects. This is due to some imaginations and fancies, which develop to such an extent as to be ultimately mistaken for facts, which enshroud the minds and affect the hearts and senses. Then he would think that sophistication is one of the laws of selfishness which can legitimately be used to justify his actions when he challenges the rights of others and takes possession of their properties without any real justification. This is what has prompted the Bahrain Govern ment to extract out of sophistry a few weak allegations for use as a ladder on which to ascend to their coveted object. But they should understand that any Government, however tyrannical and powerful they may be and in whatever manner they may stray from the right path, cannot hold on to false pretences for unjustly taking possession of the properties of others if those who will prevent them and compel them to turn to the right path are available. I therefore Request you to reflect on the matter and to subject it to careful examination. I invoke your conscience- 2 - in the investigation of right and justice, to turn your careful attention to the well-balanced and true facts which will reveal the right to you and if you review them carefully by the scales of the mind, as to the present situation of the matter and the requirements of its circumstances and ambigui ties in a manner which conforms with conditions prevalent in these parts, and with the customs which are familiar to its inhabitants• 7/e believe that the might of justice is strongly fixed, over and above the outward appearances of allegations, and cannot be erased by sophistry or be shaken by well-polished allegations. r hen you view the matter from its true phase the facts will be clear to you and all the sophistications, which, with the support of falsehood are intended for satis fying the greed, will crumble down. Right is more deserving of being followed. I submit my comments on the letter of the Bahrain Government. Usual Bnding.r - '&gt;• :iDia ; i vo- Ko coiument 0 comment S ? haikh u H al ? ^° es -claim that belt letachments L ; r ' ese ntatives |ere ^ Hawar. Translation of comments on the statement of the Bahrain Government in the case of Hawar Islands. Submitted by the Huler of Qatar. 1. The Bahrain Government try to find out justification for the action they dared in the Hawar Islands out they fall into confusion about the matter. They lose the point and then have recourse to sophistication and the obliteration 01 facts to which no one, who has the least know ledge of conditions which prevailed in these islandsL in the past, would support them. In studying their memorandum and examining its contents I did not find out that they have put forward even a fraction of the evidence which can be considered as sufficient proof from an indicative point of view, or a proof which can be a likely argument to justify their recent action in islands which form a part of Qatar. All that it contained are some far fetched allegations which are remote from the truth. ^he Bahrain Government deny my statement that they did not occupy those islands except in recent ■^ays, and they allege that they belong to the Bahrain, and that they were inhabited by their subjects for more than a century. Then they recant and contradict their own allegations and support my statement in saying that their military detachment was only recently stationed there. 3. Whoever views this allegation will find it not only illogical but also far away from sensibi lity, and will be surprised by its strangeness and bare-faced contradictory appearance. That islands which are so described by the Bahrain Government, and which they claim as belonging to them and in- haoited by their subjects for over a century, should5 5 3 0 tillages, not towns. The idea that any thing need be done for remote villages is entirely modern [in these parts. remain for so long unoccupied by their military detachment and without any representative, except recently, is an allegation which makes one laugh because of its extraordinary strangeness. It is unnecessary for me to give more instances about the weakness of this allegation, its remoteness from the truth and its illogical foundation, becausejeveryone who has knowledge of logic will not agree with them on this point. 4. Nothing out of the words ,f co-operation” and 'brotherliness' which they put forward to justify the same, could be used as a basis for the foundation of their claim. Because, had the Hawar Islands been as described by the Bah rain Government inhabited by their subjects in a permanent manner, or that it can be described as towns and villages or anything approaching the same, then 'co-operation'- and 'brotherliness' would have not prevented their Government from taking the necessary steps required by the condi tions of towns so described as belonging to them, as it is in all countries of the world. But as the truth is different from that mentioned by the Bahrain Government it becomes necessary that they should justify the actions and liberties which they have taken in a land which does not belong to them by putting forward conclusive proofs which should be logical, agreeable and acceptable to a living conscience. But if they use false allegations and obscure methods for unjustly taking possession of the lands of others then we will not give in. 5. The Bahrain Government describe my statement that the islands are an abode for11 There are houses built of unfaced stone, with mat roofs• Much more • *piere is excellent pasturage after ^ain in the main island. **?here are two established Ullages. -3- fishermen as M a laughable allegation and an untrue description” and they allege that 'they are inhabited villages, established since a long time, with firmly built stone houses, permanent! inhabited, for more than a century, by the sub jects of the Ruler of Bahrain and the subjects of his ancestors with their wives, families, herds and boats'. I am surprised by such con coctions and by the bold denial of the firmly set facts. Even more strange than these con- tradictory remarks, which are apparent in all their allegations, is (the fact) that while they 1 deny my statement that fishermen frequent the is-§ lands yet they recant and confirm it thus 'that shows that the islands are frequented by fishermen who are from among the inhabitants of Hawar Islands'. If the Bahrain Government show their ignorance of the conditions of Hawar in these terms, and to the extent of drawing a hint from my letter that fishermen frequent these islands - and there are no other fishermen than those to whom I referred above - whom they want to use to justify their action. (Then?). The clear fact which nobody can deny is that Hawar Islands are not in any way as des cribed by the Bahrain Government. Because they are islands whose extent is from 4 to 5 square miles approximately at high tide. Moreover they * are barren, without water and unfit as a pastu rage for herds, and was in the past completely without inhabited buildings and by no any way ♦ * can be called villages or anything that approach-J es the meaning of this word, and generally un frequented except by fishermen who come from-4- time to time, or who pull up their fishing boats (for a 'dry' or repairs) temporarily, and to whom reference was made by the luler of Bahrain himself, and who then leave* All people who knew these islands since olden times know nothing besides what we have mentioned. The description given to it by the Bahrain Government, as mentioned above, does not conform with any of the truth either because of their ignorance of those islands or because they want to deny the facts which are known to all, and to rely on sophistication. 6. The Bahrain Government show surprise at my statement that their recent action in Hawar has no justification, and they cover these actions by a robe of falsehood, and then they call their action by a name through which they try to cover the right with a screen of the wrong, and the word 'the cultivation, by a Buler, of part of his domain' is a word which cannot be used in any way. The Bahrain Government have confessed, in their memorandum, that their military detach ment camped on their behalf in the Hawar Islands only in recent days, and have built strongholds, roads, wharves and signposts recently. The confession of the Bahrain Government about their having taken the liberty of taking those actions in the Hawar Islands only in recent days is directly conflicting with their allegation of owning those islands in the past, and with their description that t hey are a part of their State, as it is impossible to conceive that islands which are so described by them, and which they allege are subject to them and form partof their country for more than s. century, should * remain all along these years without a detachment * Why ? ior security and for the administration of .justice and to represent the Huler of Bahrain in those Islands which they bewail as being part of their state, and allege that it consists of villages * There are goats inhabited by people with boats and herds. We also and some cattle. observe, from another point of view, clear con tradictions in the memorandum of the Bahrain Government. A confession by them that the islands are owned by the Ruler of Qatar is about clear, and that is by the fact that some incidents took * p 1 d. ce in one not -uar ofx past, between Qatar and Bahrain, which are recorded in history and in the memories of some living persons, which has shattered relations of ’’brotherliness” and threatened interests more than at present. The fact that the Bahrain Government did not mention * lu would have been} there being any detachment stationed by them more effective to 5 give proof of a } at Hawar Islands under those circumstances, and Qatar detachment } having been there 5 during which time it -/was more necessary to b rinn in the past l } ^ ^ 5 out a detachment than it is now, and for the same reasons which the Bahrain Government now want „ to use as justification for the oresence of i tneir detachment, is conclusive nroof that the t 7 Hawar Islands are owned by the Ruler of Qatar at least since that time and up to the present in which the Bahrain Government now try to use the presence of their recently stationed detach ment as an excuse for taking Hawar Islands. Had the Ruler of Bahrain known anything about this he would have alluded to it in his memorandum which is in our possession. His silence about it is a considerable hint to our ownership of these-6- islands at. that tima and that it i’orms a nart of Qatar up to the present in spite of the recent actions which we are trying to put off by means of understanding. 7. T he following is one of the misleading allegations made 'by the Bahrain Government :— M Why did not Shaikh Abdullah use the right which he claims about the owner ship of the islands. He was up to a year ago ignorant of there being such islands and only now stirred under the impression that they may perhaps contain Oil'. This is a foolish saying. We extend an oppor tunity to the Bahrain Government to cite any instances of any action which they took in the past in Hawar Islands and which we did not challenge; have they taken any action or possession of Hawar Islands in the past, which they claim as their property and part of their state formedof inhabited villages for more than a century, which action will serve as a proof or will give a correct indication of their having owned the islands ? Had we known of any such thing we would have not challenged them when ther wanted to take over the islands now, by using our right against them. The Hawar Island is well known to all the people of Qatar, most of all the Ruler. Can it be logically assumed that a Ruler should be ignorant of a part of his terri tory ? I leave the matter to v our Excellency’s sense of understanding to judge as to who is ignorant of the Hawar Islands. Is it I, who has described it according to the true situa tion, or the Ruler of Bahrain, who has described it as against its natural state and who alleges that it is formed of villages and buildings-7- 81 (te) '.v 1 th permanent mhalDitants^ then* families j herds and ocvatS) and who has 'created a dome out of a grain' ? Unless perhaps the Bahrain Government had 'a revelation in the underground world'. 1 have been twice and the Bahrain des cription is a good deal more accurate than Qatar* s. comment Perhaps an opportunity might occur in ♦ the near future for v our Excellency to visit the Hawar Islands to enatele you personally to see for yourself and ascertain who is the truthful amongst us, so that your judgmertt may ce iormed in the light of true facts* The reason which has prompted us to ask for the prevention of the Bahrain Govern ment from the actions which they took in the Hawar Islands is not greed for the presence oil but to prevent the Bahrain Government from taking a part of Qatar* 8. In article 6 of their memorandum the Bahrain Government ask: To whom do^d the Hawar Islands belong if not to Bahrain ? It would have been better had they asked : To whom does '^atar belong if not to Bahrain ? Whatever can oe said about Hawar can be said about the whole of Qatar, and we ask the Bahrain Government whether the Hawar Islands, from a geographical point of view, comprise of a part of Bahrain completing it from the south or a part of Qatar completiag it from the north ? Cur previous remark, about the indepen dence of Qatar and the recognition of our ruler- ship over it, carries its meaning which, if the Bahrain Government does not perceive, is not latent to those who have knowledge of situations in these oarts*-8- * This is quite true of Shaikh Abdullah bin Qasinu There is one place where ther^ is only about 3 feet of water at low springs. Squally that Qatar is part of Arabia *. 9X © 9, The Bahrain Government try to find out some means of geographical justification for including the Hawar Islands among the number of islands which form Bahrain, but they find nothing more than saying 'The situation of the Hawar Islands is undisputed. Its situa tion is more known to the Rulers and public of Bahrain than to Shaikh Abdullah the Ruler of Qatar, because the Ruler and public of ♦ Bahrain frequent those islands whilst no one of the A1 Thani family had ever set foot over it'. This is a foolish saying which shows the ignorance of its author about geographical situations. The Hawar Islands are not more than a mile from Qatar and it is only separated from Qatar, during high tide, by shallow water from the sea, but during low ebb the short distance between Qatar and Hawar becomes nearly uncovered by sea water and so directly connected as to be about traversable by foot whilst, on the other hand, the Hawar Islands are tens of miles away from Bahrain separated by deep sea which forms the passage of sea communications, and which is the natural boundary between Qatar and Bahrain. The Hawar Islands are considered,f rom a geographical point of view, as a part which completes Qatar from the North Any one who has the least primary knowledge of geography will agree with this. The tracing by the Bahrain Government of the geographical connection of Hawar to Bahrain by saying that the people of Bahrain frequent the islands or by saying that the-9- *i2vidence ? rBahrain subjects living in Hawar. But if they have any cases they come to the Agency Court. Ruler of Bahrain had visited it - assuming that he had visited it once during his life time, although that has yet to be proved -~ is one which will make people laugh at this wonderful geographical knowledge which the Bahrain Government has invented. The alle gation ghat no one of the A1 Thani family has ever set foot on it is refutable. Th* ♦ late Shaikh Qasim has visited it many times and many others of the people of Qatar had visited it. 10. Among the evidence put forward by the Bahrain Government in their memorandum is that the pearl-fishermen of Hawar take their pearl-fishing (account) books from Bahrain, by which means they aim at creating Hawaris, and to take themf or being their subjests. But, do they forget that those to whom they refer as taking pearl-fishing books are * * Bahrainis and not Hawaris ? Moreover pearl fishing books cannot b« taken as proofs; all those who go to Bahrain with the object of pearl-fishing carry such books: the people of Hasa, Nejd and ^atar, who follow the pearl fishing trade in Bahrain, all carry such books at Bahrain, has it also ever occurred to the Bahrain Government to take possession of the lands of their neighbours because their pearl- fishermen carry pearl-fishing books ? This is an argument which the Bahrain Government has found in 'the world of investi gations'. 11. The Bahrain Government frankly admit that the investigations, carried out by them, for old cases referring to Hawar, as is-10- And counter-sealed by the Shaikh of Bahrain. But not about ownership of land and water in a foreign State! Would a ^tar Qadhi settle a dispute about land at Riyadh ? alleged by them, did not result except in the finding of two decisions made by the Sunni Qadhi of Bahrain in respect of a dispute between two persons 28 years ago. This cons titutes all the evidence put forward by the Bahrain Government v/hich they think can be relied upon to satisfy their greed in the Hawar Islands, ''hen we cast an investigating look over these t wo cases we find that the Qadhi of Bahrain did not give the least indi cation about the nationality of the two liti gants. Therefore they are of unknown nationali ty and they may be of any other Arab State. This assumption is strengthened by the fact that disputes arise frequently between Muslims in other countries than their own and they go to the Qadhi of the Shar’a who registers their cases and gives his decision which becomes valid and executable between the two litigants as if it had taken place in their own country and by their own Qadhis, that is because the Islamic Shara f a law is the same on all points and by common consent and can take place in any place where the Shara'a is recognised as if it is one law for all. This is a practice which is confirmed and practised in our state and in Nejd, Oman and other parts of Arabia, thus it is possible for the Qadhis of Hejd to decide between ’Oman subjects, and for the Qadhis of Qatafc to decide between Nejdi subjects and register their cases. This practice was also prevalent in Bahrain until a certain time past. Assuming however, for argument’s sake, that the two persons, betweenThey were not mere disputes about fish traps, but about rights in land and water. Untrue »*here are they ? ^ have myself seen them at Hawar. whom a decision was given, are Bahrain subjects who have fishing traps near Hawar or of those who frequent the islands for this purpose, yet this does not show in any way that the Hawar Islands are owned by the Ruler of Bahrain or that it is subject to him. If we take this argument for granted, then, it would follow that each Government who have subjects in another country can claim that country as belonging to them. This, I believe, is an argument which the Ruler of Bahrain himself will resent if any claim arises about a part of Bahrain in such a way. Any sane and right thinking person will not associate himself with the acceptance of such actions which are irregular and sway from every known law. 12. In the memorandum of the Bahrain Govern ment there was a petition signed by some per sons of the Dawasir, whose number does not exceed twenty, alleging thst they are the sub- i jects of the Bahrain Government, and in which they have put some false allegations. V/e con firm that these persons, who are mentioned in the petition, have no more connections with 5 the Kawar Islands than their feeing as fishermen 5 5 who frequent Hawar In the fishing seasons. .e 5 have many persons who tender evidence that their allegations are false and that they are no more than fishermen as is referred to above. As to their real dwellings and places and their pearl-fishing boats, these all are at Bahrain and its districts as you will find confirmation of this statement in the enclosed documents. In this connection I may mention that a family-12- Queer that they have not done so during all these months. *V&lt;/ho and where are they ? ho, as they are non-existent. This does of ?°unse happen ln some places. of the Dawasir tribe who live at al-Zalaq when they used to frequent Hawar for fishing purposes they were attacked at that place and they put a complaint before my late father Shaikh vasim who heard their complaint and decided against those who have attacked them on the ground that the attack took place in his own territory. This incident is known to some individuals and there was no custom of recording such incidents, as they are dealt with orally we have no record of it, but there are reliable witnesses who will give their evidence about the same. 13. Now that T have put forward my comments on the statement of the Bahrain Government in this matter in which they rely on a few indi viduals of Zalaq who may be of its subjects or it may be that they come to these islands for settlement in winter for fishing, like others, who are the subjects of Saudi Arabia, do. Then, would it occur to the Government bf H.M. King Abdul Aziz to claim the islands be cause some of their subjects lived on them and built dwellings and water reservoirs. In order to know the local situation it would be necessary for Your Excellency to turn your attention to the fact that there is nothing strar^ge about the action of some fishermen by living in an island which belongs to Qatar or any other Government, or that such fishermen are subjects of one Government or the other. This is a widely prevalent custom, and one v/hich is natural and cannot change through change of times or places, and-13- (^) one which is in accordance with relevant con ditions and situations in these parts, and to which the people are accustomed and agree able. The good faith of the Rulers of Arab States, and the exchange of mutual good neigh bourliness, humanity and the love for the well-being of all, coupled with the customs, conditions and situations refereed to above, are all matters which prompt the rulers to | leave the islands free, as long as such islands remain, as I have mentioned above, a refuge in which the aforesaid fishermen settle during winter, for fishing by setting fish traps and nets on the shores of the islands as fish are found there in abundance and are a source of great profit to the fishermen who find it necessary to remain on these deserted islands for a long time and which also necessitates them to build dwellings and water reservoirs as there is no water available on the islands. The rulers of these islands saw no reason for ■ interfering with the affairs of these fishermen because they are caused by the aforesaid con ditions. The above-mentioned conditions and customs are the chief reasons for not depriving I these poor seamen of their means of livelihood, j The rulers also saw’ no reason f or such preven tion since such conditions prevail not only in Hawar but also in most other islands. '. r e ^okhnooniyyah cite as an example the island of Zakhnooniyah a very special figured which is in Saudi Arabian territory near ’Ugair, Com he Turkish venticn of 1913. and which is frequented by the Duwasir and others, as they frequent Hawar, who have set up fishing traps and nets, and raised ap*Which are they ? -14, Saudi dwellings as is in Hawar. In fact the conditions of Hawar are comparatively same as that of Zakhnooniyyah yet the Arabian Government saw no harm f rom the ci? oions mentioned above 5 and that is becau they saw no reason for preventing persons who under such conditions settle on the on- against islands, or for taking any other steps * them. There are a number of islands in ’Oman on the southern side of Qatar, which are in- habited by persons from Qatar who go t o settle there in winter and return in summer, and in which they have built stone houses, v/ater - ese.. v oil's anc mosQues and in which they have set up fish traps and nets. Their houses and traps are there up to this hour; would it then occur to us to claim these islands of our neighbours because some of our subjects go to settle there every year and because they have built houses and set up traps there ? ..puld any one in the world agree with us if we raise the same plea as that of the Puler of Bahrain for claiming the rights of our neighbours only because ocr subjects are in their territory ? Can the settlement of foreigners in other people f s countries be taken as a reason for their country to take possession of the territory in which they settle ? Unless perhaps this is a new in vention which the Bahrain Government wantto put into practice, it would then be a different 1 matter. Would it then occur to the Bahrain Government to send their military detachment 1!™ to Zakhnooniyyah and take possession of it l!| J j■ ni/jjf-15' loo) because some individuals of the Duwasir and others of their subjects frequent it as they frequent Hawar ? Truly this is one of the strangest and most surprising matters. We refer such arguments to any one who has a sound mind and a living conscience and to whoever has knowledge of rules and regulations which are followed in all countries. Mow that I have explained my comments and remarks to Your Excellency as fully xxd as is required by the circumstances of this case, I am confident that His Majesty 1 s Government will stand impartially in this matter and carefully investigate and examine it for real facts from their true aspects, and will be guided by the strength of justice more than arguments and will not be misguided from the light of facts by any reason. 3d/- Abdullah bin Gasim M Thani. Ruler of Gatar. Dated 9th 3afar 1358 (30th March 1939)• • • • Translation of a testimonial of evidence submitted with the Euler of Qatar 1 s letter dated the 30th March 1939. We the undersigned say that we witness in accordance with our knowledge and well established facts that Hawar is subject to Qatar and was never a separate or divided part of it. We also witness and confirm that by no any means did it become subject to Bahrain. The Euler of Bahrain never occu pied it or exercised any authority in it in the past which can be taken as a means for their claim and the taking of action in these islands as they did last year. Hawar was never subject to any except Qatar and that is in accordance to its natural situation. We refute the allegations of the signatories of the petition that Hawar is subject to Bahrain, and we say that it never was. The signatories of the petition are none other than those who frequent Hawar and other islands during the fishing season, and they do not inhabit any place other than Bahrain in a recognised manner: their house, boats and permanent places are there; we confirm this, and we write this testimonial as a proof to the truth, and with the object of tendering whatever true evidence we have. Dated 25th Muharram 1358 (16.3.1939). 1. Ahmed bin 'Isa el-Muhannidi 2. Ali bin 'Isa el-Fuhannidi 3. 3a'ad bin el-Muhannidi (bin Ali) 4. Muhammad bin Omar el-Muhannidi 5. Muhammad bin Abdul Wahab 6. Abdullah bin Ali el-Muhannidi 7. Ahmed bin 'Isa bin Yusuf 8. Abdul’Wahab bin Ali 9. Rashid bin Darweesh 10. Salim bin Darweesh el-Muhannidi 11.. Abdul Rahman bin Rashid 12. Ali bin Muhammad bin Ali 13. Abdulla bin Jasim el-Muhannidi 14. Ghanim bin Shahin el-Muhannidi 15. Abdul Wahab bin Hamad el-Muhannidi 16. Muhammad bin Ali el-Muraikhi^ 17. Hamad bin Hamdan el-Muhannidi^ 18. Jasim bin Rashid el-Muahannidi 19. Ibrahim bin Sa'ad bin Budah 20. Ibrahim bin Abdullah el-Ansari.Translation of a testimonial of evidence submitted with the Huler of Qatar’s letter dated 30th March 1939. We the undersigned according to the best of our knowledge and the firmly established facts take an oath by -od and say that the Hawar Islands were never subject to Bahrain, and the Rulers oi Bahrain never had authority in them, and never took possession or any actions in these islands in the past. We witness and confirm that the Hav/ar Islands are subject to Qatar and inseparably attached to it and owned by its ruler. Whatever different allegations is made is false, and we also confirm that these Islands was not inhabited in the manner which is alle ed, but it was as other islands irequented by fishermen who come to it durirg the -ishing season and leave it in the diving season. •* e ^Iso witness that the allegations made by the signatories of the document in respect to Hawar are false, and if it be true that they are of those who frequent the islands then they cannot be any other than those who temporarily come to the islands for fishing during the time in which they are free of the pearl-fishing season, and we also testify that they live in Bahrain permanently, their boats and im movable properties and places are all there. We write this testimonial for the purpose of stating the facts and for submitting the evidence v/hich we possess about a firm and real matter. Dated 25th Muharram 1358 (16.3.1939) 1. Khalifah bin Mubarak bin Hitmi . 2. Ibrahim bin Nasr 3. Ali bin Sultan bin Ali 4. Shahin el-Asiri 5. Yusuf bin Ahmed el-Sulaiti 6. Muhammad bin Khalifah el-Suwaidi ' 7. Ibrahim bin Abdulla el-Hasawi 8. Khalid bin Ali el-Khulaifi 9. Abdullah bin Khamis el-Khulaifi 10. Muhammad bin Sultan el-Suwadi 11. Muhammad bin Rashid el Ashri 12- Muhammad bin Khalid el-Suwaidi 13. Muhammad bin Mu11a Ibrahim 14. Nasir bin Sultan el-Suwaidi 15. Ahmed bin Ali el-3ulaiti 16. Abdulla bin Mulla Ibrahim 17. Muhammad bin Nasr bin Bakht.translation oi a testimonial of* evidence submitted v;ith Ruler of Qatar*s letter dated the 30th March 1939. the I the undersigned according to my knowledge say that I personally know the following persons each in person 1. Ahmed bin Rashid el-Dousari 2. Yusuf bin Ahmed el-Dousari 3. Ali bin Shahin el-Dousari 4. 3a'ad bin Muhammad el-Dousari 5. 'Isa bin Hasan el-Dousari 6. Sultan bin Ahmed el-Fatam 7• Subah bin Saqur el-Dousari 8. Ahmed bin Shahin el-Dousari 9. Muhanna bin Huzaim el-Dousari 10. Muhammad bin Ahmed bin Shahin el-Dousari These persons are inhabitants of al-Zulaq a district ex island of Awal$ their boats, houses and properties are there. They have no any connection with Hawar other than their being fishermen who come to it during the wishing season and then they leave for their own places at Zalaq, they have nothing at Hawar except shelters which they have set up because of necessity for sheltering them during the fishing season. I state this and confirm it according to my personal knowledge of these persons and I take an oath to the same effect* Dated 25th Muharram 1358 (16-3-1939) 3d/- Muhammad bin Abdulla el-Ghurari.Translation of a testimonial of evidence submitted with the Ruler of Qatar’s letter dated the 30th March 1939 We the undersigned persons t ake an oath by God and say that to the best of our knowledge, and according to firm facts, Hawar island is a part of northern Qatar and was never subject to Bahrain, and that the rulers of Bahrain never exercised authority or took any measures in, or possession of, Hawar islands which can justify their claim or taking possession of these Islands which we testify are an inseparable part of Qaxar, subject to Qatar from every angle of its situation and owned by its ruler. The allegations made by the signa tories of the document respecting Hawar are untrue. If they are really of those who frequent Hawar then they cannot be any other than those fishermen who settle in Hawar and other islands during the winter for fishing when they are free from the pearl fishing season. They are permanently settled in Bahrain, their boats, their houses end immovables are all in Bahrain. write this testimonial for the purpose of stating the facts and for submitting the evidence v/hich we possess about a firm and real matter. Dated 25th Huharram 1358 (15th March 1939) 1. All tin Rashid el-Karma* ee 2 . hbd 11a tin Ha shid el-Manna 1 ee 3. Khalaf tin Hasan el-Banna•ee 4. Abdul Aziz tin Muhammad el-Manna* ee 5. Hasan bin Abdulla el-Helli el-henna*ee 6. riashid tin Abdullah el- ell! e 1-1 arms* ee ?. the sin bin (Cnar el-l anna* ee £. Seyid All tin Muhammad 9* Bayed Husain tin IHhaurad y r - Bay id Abdulla bin Bu hemmed :— -ayid Bssain bin btampan T2. Ba y id He shin bin Bellh IB. 2usain bin All el-l anr-e* ee -A. lb hare ad tin yor? ry- -a If bin Abdul la el - * r anna * ee -T. Abdul atat tin Abdulla el-Hanria*ee yj- rtraniu bin l uharmad el-j t'ne* ee -'Id tin Baif et-; anr^*ee rf • Abdul Heh«n tin * Jba eVhan/^*ee . * Iza a aj- bijeua 1 ee eb-hube 1 e! larur air 3e^ir# * 0*0(?j GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. rionfidantlal Department. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate o/ “ teU3ram - u «&gt;&gt;* &lt;*« a No. 423-S To . Repeated Busnira, M i!smi' the 33th April Jfia Majesty's leeretary or -state for India, London; r he ^ecretary to tne GOT«*r*nment of India n tHa ifijcternal Affair# Department, New JJelni. Politioal figent, Banrain. Reference my *21* Cjwnersnlp of »^ar Islann^. i C\ ''T'\ . 3- Keferenoe correspondence ending with ay impress Letter Uo.192-3, dated the 16th Mar on 1939. 3. I enolose herewith copy of letter Ho.C/266, dated tne a&amp;H April 1939, and enclosures, from the Political Agent, Bahrain, together with the papers mentioned in his paragraph 2 (4). The •th« papers referred to by him have been forwarded previously to t*»« mdia Office and the 8overnaent of India. 3. *eightman* a report ig a very clear statement of tne «*»e and nis summary in paragraph 13 confirms my opinion given in Paragraph 7 of wy impress Letter Ho.423-3, dated tne 25th May 1936, th ♦ Ha^ar belongs to ^aixraic and not to ^atar. should Hie Majest, *rmnent concur in tnis opinion I euggeat tnat I be authorised to «y taeir decision to tne ShaiJchs of Banrain and fiatar. ad.t *o # jpoaXj* Political Resident in tne Persian Gulf. Attested ’•‘•ident 9 ! ary t0 th * Political nt in the Persian Gulf. S, 44 ilFp. (Signature) (Designatim) 985 S&amp;p—(M-1597)—27-11-36—10,000.7471 Wt 23481/1' 215 2000 8.38 INDIA OFFICE, . ■ OLI l I C^L( NXP iR: iiL)D epartm ent EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). (N.D.-—Ihis is an original message, sent by air mail to save telegraphic expense but intended to be treated on receipt with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. It has been drafted as if it were so despatched.) From Secretary of State. To political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Repeated to Political Agent, Bahrein, ana to Government of India, External Dated 25th April, 1939- Department. Rt lSHIRE RESIDENCY. Date. CONFIDENTIAL RECORDS I Your express letter of the 14th February No. c/35 of 1939* Bahrein Unallotted Area. 2. Subject to certain conditions His Majesty f s Government are prepared to approve the Sheikh’s proposal to give concessional rights over the whole of the unallotted area, including the Hawar Islands, to the Bahrein Petroleum Company and the Sheikh may be so informed. 3. The conditions in question are as follows (a) that the inclusion of the Hawar Islands in the concessional area is subject to the eventual decision of His Majesty’s Government in their adjudication of the claims of the Sheikhs of Bahrein and Qatar to sovereignty over the Islands; (b ) that the terms of the agreement between the Company and the Sheikh are approved by His Majesty’s G-ove rnment; and (c) that an agreement is concluded between the Company and His Majesty’s Government to safeguard the latter’s interests.His Majesty’s G-overnment s decision is being 4- communicated informally to the representatives of the two Companies in London, and the desiderata to be embodied in an agreement between the Bahrein Petroleum Company and His Majesty’s Government will be discussed with Mr. Ballantyne in the near future. Copy of a letter addressed to the latter is enclosed. 5 . Copies of the replies of the interested departments to India Office letter No. P. Z. 1111/39 of the 1st March are enclosed for your information. With reference to paragraphs 2-4 of the Admiralty letter of the 31st March I feel no doubt that, after all the protracted negotiations, the Sheikh is fully aware of the relative merits of the offers made by the two Companies and prefers, as stated in his letter of the 6 th February, to safeguard his revenue from the Bahrein Petroleum Company. The issue of the above has been duly authorised.?. 2.1 518/39. FOREIGN OFFICE, 3.7.1. 9th March, 1939. (E 1617/196/91) My lear Peel, Pith reference to your letter to Syres, P.2.1111/39 of the 1st March, regarding the Bahrein Unallotted ^rea, I unite to say that we agree that, in view of the attitude of the Bahrein Petroleum Company, we can only advise the Sheikh to accept their offer, subject to caveat as to the sovereignty over the Hawar Islands. 2. \7e also concur in your proposal to negotiate an agreement with the Bahrein Petroleum Company.regarding our political desiderata. 3 * I am sending a copy of this letter to Jarrett and Starling. Yours ever,P.2.1907/39. PETROLEUM DEPARTMENT (Mi ne s Depart rue nt ), Dean Stanley Street, P.D. 21/9. Part 5 . Millbank, London, S. \7.1. 23 th March, 1939. Dear Peel, &gt; 'r 1. Your letter to Starling P.2.1111/39 of 1st March about the Bahrein Unallotted Area. 2 . I an writing to say that in all the circumstances we agree with the views of the Foreign Office expressed in Baggallay’s letter (E. 1617 / 196 / 91 ) of 9th March. 3. In paragraph 3 of your letter you mention the question wh±ch was raised in Jarrett f s letter of 6 th December (M. 06624/38)? of the reservation of the right to .-.C.L. to erect a refinery in Bahrein. P.C.L. have, of course, under the General Refinery agreement an obligation to erect a refinery somewhere in the Persian Gulf if and when their production in that area reaches half-*a-nillion tons. At the present tine they hold concessions over large areas in Qatar and the Trucial Sheikdoms, and it hardly seems necessary or appropriate to try and insist that, under the Bahrein Petroleum Company's new agreement concerning the Unallotted Area, we should attempt to secure the right for P.C.L. to erect a refinery in Bahrein. The contingency of their needing to erect one there seems rather remote. 4. I have sent copies of this letter to Jarrett and -^yres. Yours sincerely, (0d.) R. N. Quirk. ;Peel, Esq., M .C. , In.-lia Offi Ge , King Charles Street 8 . . 1 •P.Z. 2067/39- Military Branch, M. 01463/39- Admiralty, S.V.1. 31st March, 1939 . Immediate and Confidential , Dear Peel, * In reply to your letter No. P. i. 1111/39 dated March 1st, I am now able to give yoa the views of the Admiralty on the Sheikh of Bahrein's proposal to grant the concession for the whole oi the Unallotted Area, including the Hawar Islands, to the Ba.hrein Petroleum Company# 2. Our first observation is that the financial terms offeree, oy the Company are in substa.nce not so generous as they may appear to be on the surface* as we understand it, the minimum annual royalty which they are offering to guarantee for the next fifteen years is only about half that already derived from present production in Bahrein, so that provided the existing oil field produces for the next fifteen years a.t little more than half its present rate, the Company would be able to make up its guarantee without difficulty, on the existing field. ^s no additional payment is offered other than the initial 400,000 rupees for the new fields, the net effect is that, leaving aside the remote possibility of the failure of their present field (when they might in any case be unable to meet their obligations) they pay nothing, beyond a small sum down, for the rights over the Unallotted ^rea, including the Hawar Islands. 3- Ve recognise that in any event the Sheikh is unlikely to be much influenced by a simple comparison of the cash offers made by the two applicants for the Unallotted Area or portions thereof, since he appears to have always in mind the, probably exaggerated, fear that the Bahrein Petroleum Company,/ ; Peel, Esq. , M. C. , India Office, S. V. 1.2 . Company, in the event of a rebuff, would deliberately cut down their proauction cl oil in Bahrein to the existing minimum royalty figure and supply the balance of refinery requirements from Arabian production* Nevertheless, if you agree with the foregoing analysis of the American Company’s offer, you may consider it desirable, in the Sheikh’s own interest, to make quite certain, through the Resident, that he fully appreciates the position. 4. If, however, it is clear that the Sheikh has made up his mind with h^s eyes open, the Admiralty agree that he should be allowed to grant the concession for the whole area, including the Ha war Islands, to the Bahrein Betroleurn Company. 5» feel, however, that every endeavour should be made to secure the following conditions:- . -LU- rwnurn^ri'Vit- -n a jul-.... (a) That, as you suggest in your letter, a —• caveat should be inserted in the agreement between the Sheikh and the Company in respect to the Sovereignty of the Ha war Islands. (b) That the Company shall enter into a pre-emption ag reement to the effect that in the~event’ of a' state oFnational emergency or war (of which K.M. G-overnment shall be the sole judge) H. M. Government shall have the right of pre-emption of all the oil produced or refined by the Company within the Sheikhdom of Bahrein. (c) That the Company should undertake to give a guarantee to H.Government to refine , in tim e of warT a stipulatecV minimum quant iTy of crude b iTto whaTt ev e r s pe cTf i c a tTont he' AamiraiTy^ s4 r olITd* consider the most suitable for their purposes at the time. 6 . Me assume that the undertaking of the Company in the Agreement as summarised in paragraph 3 l( c) of Veightmom’s express letter No. c/91-10/14 of the 12th February, would be for the refining of the stipulated minimum quantity of Bahrein/3. Bahrein oil o.t_Bahrein L Me consider that this should he made clear. 7. I am sending copies of this letter to Starling and Eyres. Yours sincerely, (sa.) C. G. Garrett.INDIA OFFICE 1.2067/39 \7HITEHaLL, 3.V.1. 24th April, 1939 Dear Mr. Ballantyne, I am authorised to inform you that as a result of the negotiations held early this year the Sheikh of Bahrein has expressed a wish to give a concession over the whole of the unallotted area of his territory to the Bahrein Petroleum Company, and that His Majesty’s Government are causing him to he informed that subject to certain conditions they are prepared to approve his proposal. The conditions in question are as follows - (a) that the inclusion of the Hav/ar Islands in the concessional area is subject to the eventual decision of His Majesty’s Government in their adjudication of the claims of the Sheikhs of Bahrein and Qatar to sovereignty over the Islands; (b) that the terms of the agreement between the Company and the Sheikh are approved by His Majesty’s Government; and (c) that an agreement is concluded between your Company -•nd His Mb.jesty’s Government to cover the safeguarding of/2 . of the interests of government in respect of the old and the new concessions. './e hope in the near future to he able to discuss with you in detail the nature of the agreement referred to under (c) above. Yours sincerely, ( 3 gd.) R. PBEL86/14 Telegram ^ From PolitiOcxl Keeident, Suahire. To Political A^ent, Bahrain* Copy by post to His Majesty’s Secretary of State for India* London* Secretary to the Gorernment of India, External Affairs Department, Simla* Sto'284* Dated the 5th Bay 1939* India Office Express Letter Mo* P.Z*2067 of the 25th April. Bahrain Unallotted Area. Please inform Shaikh accordingly* BRITC03SUL. / 5 • 39Telegram S from OoTernment of India, Kxternal Affairs Department, Hew Delni. Repeated To Heoretary of ‘State for India, London. Political Heaident, tsusnire. No.741 Dated and receired 6th May 1939 Important Per Peel from Metcalfe Reference your telegram Ho.769 of 27th April. Steps to be taken in the Gulf in the event of war. from oil producing wells in the Gulf estates is clearly of / I’M#' f&gt; • ^ • great importance please see paragraphs 14 and 19 of enclosure 3 Lv&lt;C * to Walton and paragraph 12 of tfowle* a note forwarded with b • U“1 * J (/\ dL • your demi-official letter Ho.p.2. 3128/38 of hay 19th 1938. This desideratum appears to be secured by pre-emption clauses in agreements between Companies and His Majesty* s government except at Bahrain where there is no agreement between nis Majesty’s Government and Company. we do not Jcnow result of negotiations between Admiralty and Bahrain petroleum Company referred to in Towle’s note of April 19th 1938 but consider in any case immediate steps should if possible be taken to negotiate an agreement with Coa^pny either through cnaikn or direct which will give us rights of pre-emption and control went copy of which was forwarded under Gibson’s demi-official 193ft / ^ MVfvU* JO \paragraph 19} assumes that even in the absence of such an agreement the Shaikh could in exercise of his sovereign power 2 ^uestioh of ensuring adequate supplies of oil in the event of war on the lines of Muscat pre-emption agree- Nowle in his demi-official note of Januarydirect Company to sell tneir oil to His Majesty^ OoTern- taent* W# Tael some doubt wile trier in th© absence or any claut© in agreement between maikA and Company Uil* could be done without rendering 3haikn liable for damages. we suggest however that matter should be examined urgently with a view to asoert&amp;ining what procedure could be adopted in an emergency to secure oil supplies for gia Majegty*a ^vernment at Bahrain and at the same time to safeguard the legitimate interests of concessionaires. ?owle will no doubt telegraph nis comments. Government of IndiaD.C. No. C/299-10/14 Dated the 5th May 1939* Reference India Office Express letter No. P.Z. 2067/39 dated the 25th April 1939 about the Bahrain Unallotted Area. 2. As the Bahrain Petroleum Company here ha#k received &lt;x f\ loX telegraphic summary of Feel's letter of the 24th April 1939 to Ballantyne (copy enclosed with the Express letter under reference) I considered it essential to inform His Highness immediately of the decision of His Majesty's Government. Ordinarily of course I should have waited for your instructions to do so, but it seemed in the highest degree undesirable to allow the news to reach His Highness and the public in Bahrain generally by the backstair route. I hope you will approve of \ this action. Yours sincerely, honourable Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Trenchard Fowle, K.C.I.E., C.B.E., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire .Confidential JNo#475*3 of 1939. British Heeidency and Consulate General, Bushire, the loth i!ay 1939. To Hie Political Agent, Bahrain. Subject * Bahrain Unallotted Area . Memorandum 10 4' Your letter ao.C/229-10/14, dated the 5th May 1939, crossed my telegram Jio.284 of the same date, in ehich 1 asked you to inform the Shaikh accordingly. ad.T.C,JO#I£ Political resident in the Persian Gulf. Attested 1 Secretary to the lolltioal •eident in the Persian Gulf. . \ \86/14 l©^ Telegram I.W.C. From Secretary of State for India, London. To Political Resident, Bushire. Repeated Political Agent, Bahrain. Copy by mail to Government of India, 'Sxtemal Affairs Department, Simla. No.857. Dated 12th received 13th May, 1939. Important . Petroleum Concessions Limited have let me know informally that they understand that statements are being made in Bahrain to the effect that Shaikh considers recent message from His Majesty f s Government (my Sxpress Letter of 25th April No.P*■j,2067) means that His Majesty’s Government are instructing him to give a concession for whole of Unallott ed Area to Bahrain Company and that but for this he might still consider a different course . 2* If suggestions are in fact being made that His Majesty’s Government have given instructions to Shaikh they are of course based on misapprehension which it would seem desirable to remove. At this end I am informing Petroleum Concessions Limited of fact namely that Shaikh after long negotiations with the two Companies and careful consideration °f all aspects came to the conclusion that Bahrain would be best served by accepting offer of Bahrj* n Petroleum Company f or the whole area (including Ha^ar island). His Highness addressed a considered letter to the Political Agent in this sense informing His Majesty’s Government accordingly while / adding- 2 - lio adding that before making final decision he wished to avail himself of the offer of the advice which at the commencement of the negotiations they had said they would be prepared to offer on their conclusion* nis iiajesty^ Government on receiving thia communication decided there was nolreason to advise Shaikh in any way contrary to his own views arrived at after such careful consideration of his interests* They accordingly informed Hie Highness that on certain conditions in r egard to detail they were prepared to approve of his proposal to give whole of his concession to Banrain Petroleum Company, I® evident from the above that no pressure has been brought to bear on Shaikh and I presume His nighness himself is not under any misapprehension aa to attitude of His Majesty’s Government which as frequently explained has been that he should be left free to decide question in accordance with his views of Bahrain interests, -Secretary of State for India.86/14 ni Telegram From To Repeated Copy sent by air mail to Secretary of state for India* London, Political tfealdent* Sushire. Political Agent* Bahrain. Government of India* tfew iJelhi. NO. 859 Rated 12th received 13th i£ay 1939. Important ay telegram NO.S57 of May 12tn. Information received informally from P.C.L. also includes statement tnat no decision regarding unallotted area would be made by shaikh witaout discussion with and concurrence of his family. I had been under impression that letter of 6th February (?from) Shaikh and his fanily represented his definite conclusion subject only to approval of his Majesty's Government. As you know I have informed both Companies informally that nis Majesty* s Government are prepared to approve Shaikh's proposal. It was desirable so to inform B.P.C. in order that a commencement might be made with consideration of terms of agreement to be made between Company and nit testy's Government with a view to avoiding unneccessary 1 delay. if there is in fact a doubt about shaikh's final decision please inform me by telegraph. It will alto be ieairabls in tiiat case that final decision one way or the ®ther should be reached as soon .s possible. India Office86/14 rtlegram from TO JciO«301 ik J^olltloal iiosldent, ^ushlro • Political Ago at» Bahrain* Dated the 13th May 1939 • important - : A India uffioe telegrams no«857 and 859 of May isth. U) (*) i presume 1 can telegraph India office that Shaikh is under no misapprehension as to attitude of nls majesty’s uovernment ^paragraph 3 1 of telegram no*857) and that there is no doubt that Shaikh's decision • Mil * Is final (telegram no«859)« Mo other points would appear to call for reply* nrltconsul r86/14 3 Political Agent, Banraln. Political Resident, BuaJilre. Secretary of state for India, London. Oorernment of India, Sev Delhi. Dated 13th received 14th May 1939. f .|N India Office telegram isio.857 and telegram Ifo.859 of Hay 12th. 2. neither helgrave nor I nave heard of any statements being made in Bahrain as reported by Petroleum Concessions Limited. &gt; Shaikh of Bahrain is under no misapprehension as to attitude of his Majesty* s Government and there is no question that letter of 6th February signed by shaikh 9 e brothers and eldest son represents their final and definite decision. The message contained in India Office iiUpress Letter ho.p # 3 # 2067 dated 25th April was received by them with great satisfaction and relief. Telegram Prom To Repeated Copy by air mail to No.69 Political86/14 l I If Its Telegram from To Repeated ffo.892 Bated 18th received 19th May 1959 Secretary of State for India* London* Political Resident* Bushire* at Kuwait. Political Agent* Bahrain* / / I // (/r v ^ Reference Political Agent f 8 telegram Vo»69 of May 15th- UHALLOTTED ARSA* I presume that Shaildi will at an early date announce his decision in principle (subject of course to actual negotiation of agreements required) to local representative of the two Companies concerned in recent negotiations* Secretary of State for India*Telegram 3 Prom Political Agent, Bahrain. To Political Resident at Kuwait. Repeated Secretary cf State for India, London Ko*73* Bated and receired 22nd May 1939* India Office telegram No»892 of 13th May. Shai&amp;t is announcing decision by letters to representatives of both Companies today. Political AgentI m % Sfejm INDIA OP?ICE, i.28^/39. Lfiden tial . 7HIT3HALL, LONDON, 3.’/. 1. 19 th lay, 1939 ■ *- }Lcs*sa. f '* Many thanks for your telegram of the 6 th May, No. 741, dealing v/ith the desirability of securing a pre-emption agreement with the Bahrein Petroleum Company to ensure the availability of Bahrein oil in time of emergency. Actually we are in process of discussing this matter with the Company as one of the conditions on which we would be prepared to approve the grant of a concession to them over the unallotted area. Paragraph 1 of Fowie's telegram of the - 1*1 Hi ' h j-ia^y, wu. 297 , refers bo this. Je v/ill of course send you copies of the correspondence which we expect shortly to have with the other interested Departments on this subject. With relerence to paragraph 2 of Powle’s telegram we recently took an opportunity to sound Ballantyne on the possibility of making Hasa oil available for His Majesty’s Government if required in time of war. He promised to think the matter over, but, as he said, much will depend on the JUDrey Metcalfe, ICC IE. , CSI. , MVO. External Affairs Department. circumstances/2 . '2 JO n circumstances prevailing at the time, e,go on Ibn Saul’s attitude to His Majesty’s Government; moreover the position would necessarily he different from that in Bahrein where action by His Majesty’s Government or by the Sheikh (on their advice) in commandeering the Company’s products in time of emergency would not expose the Com -any to damages for failure to execute their current contracts. 3 . As regards paragraph 3 of Howie’s telegram I understand that both the admiralty and the Mr Ministry have been in touch with the Bahrein Petroleum Company on the question of their using Bahrein oil products. I gather that at present Bahrein fuel oil is not considered altogether suitable for naval use. The Bahrein refinery could be modified to produce the high-grade aviation spirit required by the Royal Air Force, but so far the Air Ministry have not been able to Provide funds for this purpose or, by altering their contracts, to assure a market for higu-grade petrol which would justify 1 the Company in themselves providing the capital for the adaptation of the refiriQry. I am sending a co &lt;y of this letter to Powle. Your* •IflOBfGV*By Air Mail. Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy lias been sent to l Tfru ruieryu OLLiutniiiT) hi* e&gt;f hicteM' The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. 3681(®&gt; fc67/39' INDIA OFFICE, TOITEHALL, S.W.1. 3.0th May, 1939. @&gt; I Dear Baggallay, ?ith reference to your letter of the 9th March, No. E.1617/196/91 &gt; regarding the Bahrein Unallotted Area, I enclose for your comments a provisional draft for an agreemenl betv/een the Bahrein retroleum Company and His Majesty’s Government. fe have had a preliminary talk v/ith Ballantyne on this subject. He understand that though the Company will * 2 in the first place negotiate a separate agreement with the Sheikh covering the unallotted area only it may he their intention eventually to have a consolidated concession agreement which would apply to the whole territory. In any case it is of course our intention that the political agreement and its accompanying schedule should apply to the whole area covered by the Company’s concessions. 2. Articles 2, k and 6 of the draft are based on provisions of the 1934 agreement between the Company, and the ^heikh. It seems desirable to have them reaffirmed in an A greem ent with His Majesty’s Government. Article 5 corresponds to the similar provision in the Debai and Sharjah Political/ Jaggallay, Esq. , “reign Office, S. 1 .2 . political Agreements, as we understand that the Company are not altogether satisfied with the terms of Article XVI of their 1934 Agreement. \7e think however that the local authorities v/ill hove to 'be asked what provisions are considered essential in this Article in the light of their j experience. The remaining Articles and the Schedule are cased on provisions in the political agreements relating to ! Kowei t, pi tar, etc. u r e have, however, tentatively added a proviso to the usual form of article 8 and should he glad j to know whether the Admiralty think the addition desirable. | ihe views of the local authorities on this article may also ; be required. The preamble and first article allow for I signature before the new concession is signed and can be amended if the concession is signed first. 3. You will see that we have included as .article 11 the penalty of termination of the Concession Agreement by the , - for any breach of the Political agreement. We had j supposed that this trilateral arrangement which has been [used elsewhere would not be possible in the present case, j -mvo part of the concessional area has already been fully ue/eloped without the Company being a parly to any such arrangement. But we found that Ballantyne himself rather expected/I a 3. expected that some such arrangement would he stipulated by us, and we therefore propose to try to get it accepted by the Company and the Sheikh. I enclose a copy of a letter we are sending him in this connexion. ?ith regard to the enclosure to this letter, we think it desirable to omit in this case the provision for the surrender of the Company’s properties to the Sheikh in the event of termination of the lease which has been embodied in the correspondence relating to other concessions in the Persian Gulf. It would perhaps be asking rather much of the Company to expect it to agree to this, and the termination of the Concession Agreement should afford a quite sufficient penalty by itself. 4* V/e should be glad to have your comments at an early date. I am writing similarly to Starling and Jarrett. Yours sincerely,4./ ?. 2067 / 39 . im H v ihis ^i.greement d.at.ed the day of One Thousand nine hundred and thirty-nine is made between Kis Majesty’s Government in the United Kingdom (hereinafter ^ s 11 s d lii s 1 ia iestv ? s T-ovp 7 * \ r -p • ■ u jOVv.ii.MOr.t } of che one part and the Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited (hereinafter called 'the Company, whion expression shall where the context so admits be deemed to include its successors and/or assignees and snail also be deemed to include any subsidiary Company) of the other part, Whereas Agreements dated the 29th December, 1934 ? and the 3rd June, 1936, the Company has obtained a concession xrom the Sheikh of Bahrein (h erei nafter called a the Sheikh”) over part of his territory and whereas the Company has obtained, or may hereafter obtain, a concession from the Sheikh over the remaining part of his territory the Company has agreed with His Majesty’s Government as follows 1 • ihio agreement shall have effect only in the event of the Company obtaining a concession from the Sheikh in respect of territory other than that covered by the aforesaid agreement of the 29 th December, 1934 . x.* The Company shall be and remain a British Company registered in the British kmpire and shall maintain an Oxlice in Great Britain which shall at all times be in the charge of a British subject who shall be the recognised channel of communication between the Company and His Majesty’s Government. 3. Notwithstanding anything contained in the Agreements between the Company and the Sheikh the obligations and benefits of those agreements shall not be transferred to any other Company without the prior consent in writing of His Majesty’s Gove rnment.12-3 2 . 4. At least, one of the Directors of the Company shall at all timeu, be a British subject, who shall be persona grata to His Majesty's Government. His Section for appointment as Director shall be made in consultatjon with His Majesty's Govemii!tnt and nis salary as director shall be provided by the Company, A reasonable time shall be allowed for the replacement of the British Director in the event of this post falling vacant. y 5* The Company in all except unimportant or routine matters shall deal with the Bahrein Government through a Chief Local Representative in Bahrein, who shall be a British subject. The approval of His Majesty's Government shall be required for the person so designated. He will be ordinarily resident in Bahrein and will-be responsible for the Company's local relations with the Bahrein Government, which shall, except in routine or unimportant matters, be conducted through the Political ,-i.gent in Bahrein. a reasonable time shall be allowed for the replacement of the Chief Local Representative in the' event of the post falling vacant. 6 , As many of the employees of the Company in Bahrein as is consistent with the efficient carrying on of the undertaking shall at all times be British subjects or subjects of the Sheikh. ?. Subject to the terms of its Agreements with the Sheikh the Company undertakes at all times to pay due deference to the v/ishes of the Sheikh and to the advice of the Political Agent and the political Resident in the Persian Gulf. 8 . Notwithstanding anything contained in the Agreements 'between the Company and the Sheikh the Company shall not have the right to use or occupy, and shall not include in the areas selected for the purpose of its operations, any sites which mayl have been selected ty or on behalf of the Sheikh or his Majesty's Government/I Government for defence purposes, for aerodromes, aeroplane or seaplane bases or for wireless and telegraph installations or ions or in connexion with the development of harbours, provided that with the consent of His Majesty’s Government which shall not be unreasonably withheld the Company shall have the right to use for the purposes of its operations such harbours as may be developed by the Sheikh or His Majesty’s Government if there is not reasonable harbour accommodation available elsewhere. Subject to the terms of the agreements with the Sheikh harbours and harbour facilities developed by the Company shall be under its complete and exclusive control,/provided 'that with the consent of the Company which shall not be unreasonably withheld His Majesty’s Government shall have the right to use such harbours and harbour facilities for the purposes of His Majesty’s naval, military or air forces if thei: equirements can not adequately be met elsewhere. and shall be so constructed and operated that their operations shall not interfere with the operations of such wireless, telegraph or telephone installations as may be established by or under the authority of the Sheikh of His Majesty's Government 10. In the event of a state of national emergency or war (of the existence of either of which His Majesty’s Government shall be the sole judge) His Majesty's Government shall have the fight of pre-emption of all the oil produced in Bahrein, in accordance with the terms of the schedule hereto. \S 11 • In the event of notice of termination of the Agreement between the Company and the Sheikh being given by the Sheikh on the ground that the Company has failed to observe any of the terms of the present Agreement between the Company and His f 9. Telegraph, wireless and telephone installations, if any, maintained by the Company shall be of use only in its business Majesty's/11^ 4. Majesty's Government, the arbitration provisions of the said Agreement between the Company and the Sheikh shall apply if the Company considers that notice of termination on such grounds is not justified, and in that event the Sheikh shall not cancel the said Agreement until arbitration takes place in accordance with the said provisions and unless the Companj fails to comply with the award of the arbitrators within the reasonable time which shall be fixed by the arbitrators for so doing.TK-^ SGK^DULj-.] above vf.f erred to P re-empt ion C lause . in the event of a state of national emergency or war (of tne exxatones and duration of which His lujesty’s Qovernnent shall be the sole judge) - (1) His Majesty's Government shall have the right of pre emption of all crude oil gotten under the Concession granted by the Sheikh to the Company and of all the products thereof and snail have tne right to require the Company to the extent of any refining capacity it may have in Bahrein to produce oil fuel that shall comply with the admiralty specifications at the time provided that Bahrein oil be of a suitable kind and quality for this purpose. ( 2 ) Company shall use its utmost endeavours to increase ^o f^r _s r^sonably possiole ’-/ith existing facilities the supply of oil and/or products thereof for the Government to the extent required by the Government. (3) The Company shall with every reasonable expedition and so as to avoid demurrage on the vessel or vessels engaged to convey the same, do its utmost to deliver all oil or products of oil purenased by the Government under their said right of pre-emption in the quantities at the time and in the manner required cy the Government at a convenient place of shipment or at a place of storage in Bahrein to be determined by His ehijesty’s Government. In the event of a vessel employed to ^arry any such oil or products thereof on behalf of His Majesty being detained on demurrage at the port of loading the Company shall pay the amount due for demurrage according to the ^-rms of the charter party and/or the rates of loading previously agreed with the Company unless the delay is due to onuses beyond the control of the Company. any dispute which may/( 5 )/ may arise as to whether the delay is due to causes beyond the control of the Company shall be settled by agreement between His Majesty's Government and the Company, and, in default of such pcc.M euti? 'tlic question shell 'be refemed. to two nrhitmtors, one to 'be chosen by His Majesty’s Government (or the Political Resident) and the other by the Company, with po-er uo up. oint an umpire in case of disagreement, such arbitration to be held in England and to be deemed a reference to arbitration under the provisions of the arbitration Acts 1889 to 1934 (32 and 33 Viet, c.49; 24 and 25 Geo. V c.14) of the Imperial parliament, or any statutory modification or re-enactment tnereof for the time being in force. (4) ihe price to be paid for all oil or products of the refining or treatment of oil taken in pre-emption by His Majesty’s Government shall be either (a) as specified in a separate agreement or (b) if no such agreement shall have been entered into, a fair price for the time being at the point of delivery as the same shall be settled by agreement between His Majesty’s Government and the Company, or in default of such agreement by arbitration in the manner provided by the last Preceding sub-clause. To assist in arriving at a fair price at the point of delivery the Company shall furnish for the confidential information of His Majesty’s Government, if so required, particulars of the quantities, descriptions and prices of Bahrein oil or products sold to other customers and of charters or contracts entered into for carriage and shall exhibit to His Majesty’s Government original or authenticated copies of contracts or charter parties entered into for the s ale and/or carriage of such oil or products.1^ (5) His Majesty^ Government shall be at liberty to take control of. the works, plant and. premises of the Company in Bahrein, and in such event the Company shall conform to and ohey &gt;..*.11 directions issued by or on behalf of His 'lajesty’s Government. Compensation shall be paid to the Company for any loss or damage that may be proved to have been sustained by the Company by reason of the exercise by His Majesty’s Government Ox the powers conferred by this sub-clause. ^uiy such compensation shall be settled by agreement between His Majesty’s Government and the Company or, in default of agreement, by arbitration in the manner provided hy sub clause ( 3 )«INDI.x OFFICE? P.2.2067/39. iuth May, 1939. annf idential . Dear ivi r. Baliantyne , In the course of the discussion here on the 9th May regarding the nature of the agreement which His Majesty’s government would propose to enzer into with the Bahrein Petroleum Company some reference was made to the procedure by which the oheikh would take cognisance of it and provide the necessary ’’sanction” for any hreacn of its provisions. Perhaps I might explain in more detail the nature of the procedure which we have in mind and which has 'been followed in other similar cases, as you may wish to have the information as early as possible. 2. ¥hen the agreement between the Company and His Majesty’s Government is being negotiated the Company would be invited to express their willingness to agree to the arrangements set __ out in the enclosure hereto. dpon their doing so, and concluding the agreement with His Majesty’s Government, the Sheikh would be given a copy of the agreement, informed of the/ 3 a liantyne &gt; Birchin Lane, E.C.3.($) 1^0 2 . t he understandirgreached with the Company (as descrihed in the enclosure), and asked to state in writing that he understands these arrangements and agrees to them# On receipt of his reJ ly the Company would he asked formally to signify their acceptance of the arrangements and thereupon His Majesty’s Government would intimate to the Company and to the Sheikh their approval of the Company’s concession. To complete the picture, the arbitration provisions of the concession agreement are formally made applicable to any case of termination of the concession by the Sheikh under the arrangements described above, as you will see from article 1 i of the enclosed revised provisional draft. 3. Me now propose to consult the interested Departments upon this draft, and hope to be able to address you at an early date. You will note that some amendments have been made in articles 8 and 9 and a more extensive amendment in Article 5, which is now in the form most recently used. Yours sincerely,142) 13! ENCL03UPE. (a) Should any of the terns of the agreement between the Sheikh and the Company be inconsistent or in conflict with the terms of the agreement between the Company and His Majesty’s Government signed in London on the agreement between the Sheikh and the Company will to the ' extent of any such inconsistency or conflict be subordinate to and be controlled by the terms of the agreement between the Company and His Majesty’s Government. (b) If the Company should fail to observe any of the terms of the agreement between the Company and His Majesty's Government signed in London on or if? the alleged failure having been disputed by the Company, the matter has been referred to arbitration under article of the Company's agreement with the ‘Sheikh (which is made applicable to the case by article 11 of the agreement between the Company and His Majesty’s Government) and the Company should not remedy such failure within the reasonable time which should be fixed by the arbitrators for so doing then the Company agrees that the Sheikh will be entitled to terminate the agreement be tween the Company and himself.B y Air ir Mail. P.Z (%) |1&gt; l IL [ BUSHiRE RESID ENCY.! « iV - ? 9. CONFIDENTIAL RECORDS IN DU OFFICE, LONDON. Forwarded with tlie compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office.(M) IlS'- 067/39* 'jriftnt lal . Dear Starling, INDI.. OFFICE, 'HilTEHiILL, S.VM. 30th May, 1939. 'i T ith reference to my letter of to-day, No. P.2. 2067 / 39 , about the negotiation of a political agreement with the ^ ./:&gt;r Bahrein Petroleum Company, I enclose a copy of the preliminary draft of a concession agreement which Ballantyne has forwarded for the consideration of his principals at Bahrein. On a preliminary examination we do not like his method of dealing with the area to be covered by the new concession. V/e have ot received a copy of the map intended to accompany the concession, but we gather that it would exclude from the Sheikh’s ’’present u possessions islands or reefs to which the Saudi Arabian Government or the Sheikh of Qatar has already made, or may make claim. The Sheikh of Bahrein would hardly welcome this distinction between his ’’present * 1 and his ’’future” possessions. It should be possible to devise some more satisfactory definition and we have made a suggestion for this purpose in the enclosed amended copy of &gt; the draft. he have also added an article as suggested in your/ Starling, Esq.., C.B.E. , Petroleum Department (Mines Department), Dean Stanley Street, O • tit • l *(i your letter of the 27th May, 1938, No. P.J5. 21/9, tart 2. ?e would welcome your observations on Ballantyne’s draft and on our suggested amendments. ^s I mentioned in my above- quoted letter we understand that his plan is first to have this concession signed in respect of the unallotted area, and perhaps at a later date to negotiate a single consolidated concession covering all the Company’s rights and obiigationb in Bahrein. I am writing similarly to Baggallay and Jarrett. Yours sincerely(i*D p. 2. 2067/39* D^T 9/5/1939 THIS D 3 D i made between HIS HXCiiiLLHNGY SHAIKH SIR PHH.LJ) BIN SEaIKH ’ IS^ IHHiLIHAH 9 K. C.I.S. 3 C.S.I.j SH.il/Hi OP BuJIRBLIN, of the one tart (in this deed called “the Shaikh”) (acting on the advice of the British Political Resident in the Persian Gulf) and IH BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED of the ctner deed called !, the Company”) And being SUPPLE.ZHe..a &gt; 0 a-^.ease dated the 29th day of December 1934 (in this deed called 'the Lease”) made between the same parties as are p deed whereby certain rights and privileges were ccnferred ..to the Company in consideration of the payment by the Ccntan;- of the royalties and of the observance and performance by the Company of the other obligations more particularly referret t in the Lease And being ^LSO SUPPLEMENT.-EL to the deed da 3rd day of June 1936 and expressed to be stytlemental t Lease (in this deed called “•'the First Supplements- deem between the same parties as are parties to this deem : the Company covenanted that it would proceea to est:. :_t soon as practicable a Refinery at Bahrein and tae a altered in the manner and to the extent sta.ca m : Supplemental Deed WITNESSES as follows:- i^RTICLE 1 .2 . reefs, territorial waters and submerged lands lying and being ? within the boundaries of the area delineated on the Plan attached to this deed and on which the boundaries are shewn as running from to 3 and from 3 to C etc. and in this deed these are called the ’’Shaikh’s present possessions”. (t) Those of the Shaikh’s present possessions which were not at the date of this deed exclusively leased to the Company by the Lease have been called, and are called in this deed, the '’additional area”. (c) additional territories and possessions of the Shaikh which may, after the date of this deed, come under the dominion of the Shaikh or his Successors during the term now unexpired of the period of fifty-five years granted by article 1 of the Lease or any extension of such period are in this deed called the ‘’Shaikh’s future possessions”. ARTICLE 3. The Shaikh and the Company have now agreed (a) that the Company shall pay to the Shaikh four lakhs of Rupees (Rs. 4 , 00 , 000 ) on or before this deed is executed and (b) that the rights and privileges granted by the Shaikh to the Company by the Lease and the First Supplemental Deed shall extend and a PPly to the whole of the Shaikh’s present possessions and the Shaikh’s future possessions and (c) that there snail oe such further modifications, extensions, enlargements and other alterations of and to the Lease and the First Supplemental --ued a s are contained in this deed. f our lakhs of Rupees (Rs. 4*00,000) the receipt of which the ARTICLE 4. The Company has this day paid to the Shaikh the sum of Shaikh hereby acknowledges. xi.R TICLE 5»/ARTICLE 5 . 3. (a) The Shaikh hereby grants to the Company on behalf of himself and his Successors for the term now unexpired of the period of fifty-five years granted by the Lease, the exclusive right to prospect and drill for, extract, treat, refine, manufacture, transport and deal with petroleum products, naptha, natural gasses, tar, asphalt, ozokerite and other bituminous materials within the Shaikh's present possessions and (b) The ohaikh hereby further grants to the Company on behalf of himself and his Successors for the same period the exclusive right to construct and operate refineries and storage tanks within the Shaikh's present possessions and also the right but not the exclusive right to construct, erect and operate pipelines, railways, wharves and jetties, tramways, roads, buildings, machinery and telegraph apparatus of all kinds in any part oi tne Shaikh's present possessions so far UvS necessary for the purpose of its business, and (c) The Shaikh hereby further grants to the Company on behalf of himself and his Successors the like exclusive and non-exclusive rights within the Shaikh's future possessions ns are granted by sub-clauses (a) and (b) of this hrticle for the term then expired of the period of fifty-five years granted oy the .uease and every such grant under this sub-clause (c) shall without further word or action on the part of the then Shaikh come into effect upon every portion of the Shaikh’s future possessions coming under his dominion, and The rights granted by either sub-clauses (a) or (b) or (o) of this Article shall not include the exclusive right to Se H Within the Shaikh's present possessions and the Shaikh's future possessions any products the subject of such rights or °f any one or more of such rights, and (e)/k. (e) The foregoing grants of rights ty the Shaikh and his Successors to the Company shall operate by way of confirmation and enlargement of the grants of rights exietin- under or by virtue of the Lease as altered by the First Supplemental Deed and this deed. .iRTICLlI 6. (a) r The Company will pursue with diligence and without unnecessary delay, geological work within the additional area and the Shaikh’s future possessions, including structure drilling and geophysical work, if necessary, and (b) The Company will drill test wells for oil wherever geological evidence warrants, commencing operations on the first test well not later than two and one-half years from the date of this deed, if a favourable area has been found, and (c) If oil is discovered within the additional area or the Shaikh’s future possessions the Company will continue drilling further wells until oil in commercial quantities, that is of a daily average of 500 tons produced in accordance with good oilfield practice, has been obtained, or until the area is no longer deemed favourable, and (d) IJ^on discovery of oil in commercial quantities the Company shall continue drilling within the productive area until the requirements of good oilfield practice have been met, this obligation however being subject to suspension during such times as the wells then drilled within the additionalarea and the Shaikh’s future possessions are capable of a total daily average of at least 1,000 tons of oil produced in accordance with good oilfield practice. article 7 . The royalty provisions of Article VII of the Lease, as modified by Article (B)-(3) of the First Supplemental Deed, shall as from the ^Late of this deed 7 apply over the whole of the/5. the Shaikh’s present possessions and the Shaikh's future possessions. ARTICLE 8. article VIII of the Lease, as altered by Article (B)-(4) of the First Supplemental Deed shall have force and effect only until ^/Ehe date of this deed 7 and after that date and in place of article VIII of the Lease as altered by article (.o)-(4 / 1 of the First Supplemental Deed the following provisions as to minimum royalties shall apply and be binding on the parties to this deed, namely (a) The minimum royalty payable by the Company to the Shaikh during the period of fifteen years from ^bhe date of this deed/ shall be at the rate of not less than Twelve and one-half lakhs of Rupees (Rs. 12,50?000) per annum which shall be increased to the rate of Seventeen lakhs of Rupees » (Rs. 17&gt;00,000) per annum during so much of the period of fifteen years as shall remain unexpired after (and if) oil in commercial quantities is found within the additional area or the Shaikh’s future possessions and the wells drilled in such additional area and future possessions are capable of producing the /equivalent amount of oil/in accordance with good oilfield practice, and (b) Following the fifteen-year period or any extension ol it and continuing so long as the Lease is in operation? the Company will pay to the Shaikh not less than the rate of One and a half lakhs of Rupees (Rs. 1,50,000) per year in respect of royalties but that sum shall be increased to Three lakhs (Rs. 3 j 00,000) if oil in commercial quantities should have been found within/6. within the additional area or the Shaikh’s future possessions either before or after the fifteen-year period and the wells drilled within such additional area or future possessions are capable of producing the Equivalent amount of oil/ in accordance with good oilfield practice, and (c) The foregoing provisions as to minimum royalties contained in sub-clauses (a) and (b) of this article shall be subject to suspension under the terms of Article 9 of this deed. ARTICLE 9. The following provisions shall as from the /date of this deed/ be substituted for the existing article IV of the Lease, namely:- The Shaikh shall give all the protection in his power to the Company and to its staff and labourers in any part of his territory from thefts, highway robbery, assault, etc. Similarly the Shaikh shall protect all the property of the Company and of its employees which may be exposed to wilful damage or to possible losses by theft. If the Company’s work is delayed by such events as are mentioned in this article or by force majeure either on Bahrain or elsewhere then the period of every such delay shall be added to the period of fifty-five years granted by the Lease and also to the several periods referred to in Article 8 of this deed; neither shall any minimum royalty Be payable in respect of any such delay. 'Force majeure” as used in this deed includes the ;ict of G-od, vis major war, insurrection, riot, civil commotion, tide, storm, tidal wave, flood, lightning, explosion, fire, earthquake, malice or negligence or default of any third party and any other happening (whether solely due to the forces/forces of nature or not) which the Company could not reasonably have foreseen or if it had foreseen, could not reasonably have prevented, averted or controlled. i JIT I OLD 1 0. During the period of fifteen yearp from the J!ate of this deed/ and any extension of that period due to 'delay' as provided for by article 9 of this deed, not less than one- half of the oil processed in the Bahrein Refinery up to a total refinery throughput of 20,000 barrels daily, or, if oil in commercial quantities is found within the additional area or the Shaikh’s future possessions not less than one- half of the oil processed in the Bahrein Refinery up to a total refinery throughput of 25,000 barrels daily, shall be oil produced in the Shaikh’s present possessions and the Shaikh’s future possessions provided the wells drilled in such present and future possessions are capable of producing that much oil in accordance with good oilfield practice and subject to the delay provisions of Article 9 of this deed.HIS EXCELLENCY SHAIKH SIR EXIvLJ) 3I:X SHAIKH ’ISx. _.L KH.,LIPaE, K.C.I.E., c.s.i., siLiiKH op Bahrein - and - THE 3..HREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LBCTIJ DRi'^PT DEED of FURTHER MODIFICATION of Lease dated 29 th December 1934 .P. Z. 2067/39. DR.lFT 9/5/1939- THIS mde ‘between HIS HIQHKEilS KILiLIR.JI? K. C. I.E. , C.3.I. (in this deed called : *the h E E D SHAIKH SIR IL-aiJ) BIN SH^xIIOi ? IS.. .iL ^ SIlvIKN 0? BAHREIN, of the one part Shaikh’ 1 ) (acting on the advice of b.ie mitish political Resident in the Persian Gulf) and THE B. HIRE IN PEiRCLEUivI CO LIP. .NY LIMITED of the other part (in 'this deed called ’’the Company”) And being SUPPLEMENTS to a Lease dated the 29th day of December 1934 (in this deed called ”the Lease ’) made between the same parties as are parties to this deed whereby certain rights and privileges were conferred upon the Company in consideration of . the payment by the Company of the royalties and of the observance and performance by the Company of the other obligations more particularly referred to in the Lease And being ..LSO SUPPLEMENT..L to the deed dated the 3rd day Of June 1936 and expressed to be supplemental to the Lease (in this deed called ’’the Pirst Supplemental Deed”) made between the same parties as are parties to this deed by which the Company covenanted that it would i-^oceed. to establish as soon as practicable a Refinery at Bahrain and the Lease was altered in the manner and to the extent stated in the Pirst Supplemental Deed WITNESSES as follows ARTICLE 1. The Shaikh on his part and the Company on its part have duly observed and performed to date all their several Agreements and obligations of and under the Lease as altered oy the First Supplemental Deed. ARTICLE 2. ( Q ) ^11 the lands, islands, shoals, reefs, territorial waters and submerged lands which are in the possession ofthe Shaikh are referred to in this deed as the Shaikh's territory. it is understood that the extent of the Shaikh's territory shown on the map attached hereto? is subject to any decisions that may be reached by His Majesty's Government in the event of claims being laid to portions of that territory by other Rulers. (b) That part of the Shaikh's territory which was not at the date of this deed exclusively leased to the Company by the Lease is hereinafter referred to as the ’’additional area”. ARTICLE 5 . The Shaikh and the Company have now agreed (a) that the Company shall pay to the Shaikh four lakhs of Rupees (Rs. 4,00,000) on or before this deed is executed and (b) that the rights and privileges granted by the Shaikh to the Company by the Lease and the First Supplemental Deed shall extend and apply to the whole of the Shaikh’s territory and ; c ) that there shall be such further modif ications 5 extensions, enlargements and other alterations of and to the lease and the First Supplemental Deed as are contained in this deed, ARTICLE k . The Company has this day paid to the Shaikh the sum of tour lakhs of Rupees (Rs. 00,000) the receipt of which the Shaikh hereby acknowledges. ( a ) The Shaikh hereby grants to the Company on behalf of himself and his Successors for the term now unexpired of the Period of fifty-five years granted by the Lease, the exclusive righ t to prospect and drill for, extract, treat, refine, ^nufacture, transport and deal with petroleum products,4 h .!■» HI* naptn-., natural gasses, tar, asphalt, ozokerite and other bituminous materials within the Shaikh's territory and (b) The Shaikh hereby further grants to the Company on behalf of himself and his Cuccessors for the same period the•exclusive right to construct and operate refineries and storage tanks within the Shaikh's territory and also the righ„ but not the exclusive right to construct, erect and operate pipelines, railways, wharves and jetties, tramways, roads, buildings, machinery and telegraph apparatus of ail kinds in any part of the Shaikh's territory so far as may be necessary for the purpose of its business, and '' C/ right 8 granted by either sub-clauses (a) or (b) -r (°) ox this article shall not include the exclusive right to sell within the Shaikh's territory any products the subject of such rights or of any one or more of such rights, and ( d &gt; ^ oregoing grants of rights by the Shaikh and his Successors to the Company shall operate by way of confirmation and enlargement of the grants of rights existing under or by virtue of the Lease as altered by the - H irst Supplemental Deed and this deed. i-RTXCLR fi. (‘•) Tne Company will pursue with diligence and without unnecessary delay, geological work within the additional L ' reCl ’ lnclu&lt;iin g structure drilling and geophysical work, if necessary, and ' b ) Tne Company will drill test wells for oil wherever geological evidence warrants, commencing operations on the firSt test wel1 nob l°ter than two and one-half years from datt ' 01 thls deed &gt; lf a favourable area has been found, and (c)/ ,4. Ufk (c) If oil is discovered within the additional area the Company will continue drilling further wells until oil in commercial Quamitiesj that is c.r a daily average of 500 ton^ produce'-', in accoraance with good oilfield practice? has been obtained? or until the area is no longer deemed favourable? and (d) u P°n discovery of oil in commercial quantities the uompany snail continue drilling within tne productive a'^ea until the requirements of good oilfield practice have been met? this obligation however being subject to suspension daring su^h tines as the wells then drilled within the addi t i onu 1 a re a a. re capable of a total daily average of at least 1,000 tons of oil produced in accordance with good oilfield practice. ■uRTICLE The royalty provisions of article VII of the Lease? as modified by Article (B &gt; '-(3) of the First Supplemental Deed? shall as from the ^/Sate of this deed/ 7 apply over the whole of the Shaikh’s territory. . ARTICI;^ _8^ i.rticle VIIl of the Lease? as altered by article (B)- l4) of the First Supplemental Deed shall have force and effect °aly until ^he date of this deed/ and after that date and in place of article VIII of the Lease as altered by Article (B)- \4) of the First Supplemental Deed the following provisions as 1° minimum royalties shall apply and be binding on the parties to this deed? namely ( a ) Tiie riiinimum royalty payable by the Company to the Shaikh during the period' of fifteen years from //he date of this deed/ Siia3 -1 Ue at the rate of not less than Twelve and one-half lakhs ^ u Pees (Rs*12&gt;5Q000) per annum which shall be increased5. to the rate of Seventeen lakhs of ‘Rupees (Rs. 17,00,000) per annum during so much cf the period of fifteen years as shall Ft nut In un^zp., I'^ci as or \ cioo, .uf ) oil in commercial Quantities is 3. ounJ. uishj.n the additional area and the wells drilled in sue;:, acusmonul area are capable of producing the Equivalent amount of oil/ in accordance with good oilfield practice, and (b) Following the fifteen-year period or any extension of it and continuing so long as the Lease is in operation, the Company will pay to the Shaikh not less than the rate of One and a half lakhs of Rupees (Rs* 1,30,000) per year in respect of royalties but that sum shall be increased to Three lakhs (Rs. 3?00,000) if oil in commercial quantities should have been found within the additional area either before or after the fifteen-year period and the wells drilled within such additional area are capable of producing the /equivalent amount of oil/ in accordance with good oilfield \ practice, and (c) The foregoing provisions as to minimum royalties contained in sub-clauses (a) and (b) of this Article shall be subject to suspension under the terms of article 9 of this deed. ARTICLE 9. The following provisions shall as from the /Raze of this deed/ be substituted for the existing article IV of the Lease, namely The Shaikh shall give all the protection in his power to the Company and to its staff and labourers in any part of his territory from thefts, highway robbery, assault, etc. Similarly the Shaikh shall protect all the property of the Company and of its employees which may be exposed to wilful damage or to possible losses by theft.m* 6 If the Company ’g work is delayed by such events as are mentioned in this article, or by .force majeure either on Lease and also to rhe several periods referred to in Article 8 of this deed; neither shall any minimum royalty be payable in respect of any such delay. tide? storm, tidal wave, flood, lightning, explosion, fire, earthquake, malice or negligence or default of any third party and any other happening (whether solely due to the forces of nature or not) which the Company could not reasonably have foreseen or if it had foreseen, could not reasonably have prevented, averted or controlled. .-iRTICLS 10 . During the period of fifteen years from the /date of this deed.7 and any extension of that period due to 'delay 5 ' as provided for by article 9 of this deed, not less than ox e- half of the oil processed in the Bahrein Refinery up to a total refinery throughput of 20,000 barrels daily, or, if oil in commercial quantities is found within the additional a sa not less than one-half of the oil processed in the Bahrein Refinery up to a total refinery throughput of 25»000 barrels daily, shall be oil produced in the Shaikh’s territory provided the wells drilled in the Shaikh’s territory are capable of producing that much oil in accordance with good °ilfield practice and subject to the delay provisions of •article 9 of this deed. Bahrein or elsewhere then the period of every such delay shall be added to the period of fifty-five years granted by the 'Force majeure' as used in this deed includes the ^ct of God, vis major war, insurrection, riot, civil commotionrticle 11. The Company undertake to adopt all reasonable precautions (which shall include the provision of the most modern equipment) to prevent pollution of the coastal waters by oi.l, mud, ot any other fluid or substance which might contaminate tne sea water or shore line.* 0 u» [SI GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, Department. mwFIDfiNTIAL Ho- Si'C. s c^loiiiiii r.ieo^Ds | Date EXPRESS LETTER [IV, B, This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt^ with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched*] From Political Agent, Bahrain, To Political Resident, Bushire.' N °t C/376-10/14 Oaied loth June 103 9. Jubject Bahrain Unallotted Area, Reference India Office Express letter No, P,Z, 2067/39 uated the 25th April 1939 and subsequent telegraphic correspondence, „ Jb. ATS i forward herewith a copy of a letter dated the 5th June 1939 from His Highness the Shaikh of Bahrain forwarding a draft of the proposed agreement for the Additional Area and requesting the approval His Majesty's Government to this draft. I have the following comments to make on the draft lease (a) Preamble it will be observed that the draft is in the form of a deed Su Pplemental to the original Lease of 1934 as amended by the Supple- aental Agreement of the 3rd June 1936 relating to the establisiiment the iefinery. This is due to the anxiety of both parties to complete A s. e. MFp_4oog£p—(M-480)—26-7-34— 2,00,000. u- 2 - 1 m /s&gt; complete an agreement with the least possible delay, since an attempt to prepare at this stage a single document embodying the provisions of the original Lease, of the Refinery Agreement and of the negotiations conducted between the Bahrain Government and the Company in respect of the Additional Area would clearly involve considerable delay. Both parties contemplate that an all-embracing document of this kind shall be negotiated in due course (subject to the approval of His Majesty's Government) but consider that this is a matter which can be taken up at leisure in the course of the next two or three years. this view I am in entire agreement. (b) Article 1 -ms article may have some legal significance which is not apparent to me. To mv mi nr! i+ y mind ^ 13 unnecessary but neverthe less unobj actionable * „ l . ffcf. ~ (c) Articles 2 and'3 oome considerable discussion has been held, and both parties have solicited my personal views, on the question of defining the area to which this Supplemental Deed shall apply. 0f . b0th P arties is ^ame a lease for an area oincident with the existing and future possessions of the 0f 'Strain, and the wording now used seems to provide th6 Sljlli; ' lest mean s of achieving this object. It is to be recog nised that in existing circumstances it is not possible to define eitxier m words or by lines on a map the present dominions of the Shaikh of Bahrain. In the first glace , though there can b e no substantial doubt in regard to Bahrain's rights in the HaWar -~'&amp; up of islands, Lis Majesty's Government have not yet b ® en able t0 da nlare their final decision on the dispute existing between Bahrain and Qatar in respect of these islands. Secondly “ dls P ut e exists between Bahrain and the Saudi Government~in regSrd t0 the two islands, Bain al Kabir and Bain as Saghir, on both /--3- both of which Bahrain Government marks exist at the moment, i^iirdly no accurate survey has yet been made of the voters, shoals and reefs on the east, south and west of Bahrain main island. hile uheretore it would not be impossible to define 'the present dominions', by reference to the names of islands (excluding the Hawar group and the Bainain) and 'their terri torial waters', no substantial advantage could accrue by so doing cit the present stage, the wording now proposed provides for the elasticity necessary for the conduct of negotiations between Saudi Arabia and Bahrain both in respect of the substan tive dispute existing in regard to the Bainain and also for the definition of 'spheres' in the manner suggested by me separately in demi-official correspondence arising from that dispute. It provides also, by its reference to 'future dominions', for the extension of the Bahrain dominions by acquisition of the sea bed in shoal waters by effective occupation in the manner adumbrated in foreign Office Minute of the*22rld April 1938, which formed one of the enclosures to India Office letter Ho. P.z. • (p'rf - p. f(pi . 2904/38 dated the 29th April 1938 to your address. I have - tU-l already indicated Separately the likelihood of intensive explo ration of shoal waters in the next few years and it is clearly desirable that the present lease should be so drafted that the Bahrain State may not be deprived of the benefit of such explo ration conducted by its client, the Bahrain Petroleum Company. In short, since - as the result of last yearns negotiations - ^he ahrain Government are in treaty with a single company for &amp; lease covering the whole of the Bahrain dominions whatever bney may be during the next 55 years, I suggest that the present defi nition is adequate. (d) Article 4 'P' requires little comment. The wording of sub—paragraph ^) does, it is true, serve to extend the term of the original Lease /■maintain /- — / 1— Lease since the period of 55 years counting from the date of the new Deed relates to the Company* s rights within the whole of the Shaikh’s present and future dominions; hut since the normal le^se period is 75 years ? i do not see that any objection need he taken on this score. It will be observed that in sub-paragraph (b) the non exclusive rights granted to the Company are new to include ,? radio and other facilities and apparatus of all kinds except that radio equipment may not be used to transmit messages beyond the limits of the concession. ” Since the sister company in Arabia has a similar right it seems unreason able to refuse it in the Bahrain lease, and the prohibition on radio transmission beyond the limits of the concession serves to protect the interests of Cable and tireless Limited. DUb-paragraph (d) again seems to me to be totally un necessary but unobjectionable. (e) Article 5 j.n this article it will .be observed no provision is made tor maintaining a fixed number of 'strings of tools' in operation either in the present concession or in the Additional Area. Such an obligation was definitely included in the offer made m Mr. Davies* letter of the 12th January 1939 to the Adviser to the Bahrain Government, a copy of which formed item 2 °£_the correspondence forwarded with my Bxoress letter ~o. J. (n'd _ p . / 5 y ^/51 dated the 19th January 1939. It appears however that shortly afterwards the Company withdrew this particular part . -pH 0 oi its offer in a letter of the 6th February 1939 of which I now enclose a copy. By an oversight on the part both of the Company and of the Bahrain Government no copy of this letter ' k,as J orwarded to me at that time and I have only now received in response to an enquiry. I mention this point merely in elucidation, since I ieel convinced that an obligation tosuch /- -5- maintain a lixed number of drills in operation can confer no substantial benefit on the Bahrain Government in ensuring that the company pursues its operations in accordance with good oil field practice; and I have ascertained that the Bahrain Govern ment do in fact appreciate this point. sr h /A' (f) Articles 6 and 7 &lt; provide for the revised minimum royalty figures as negotiated between uhe company and the Bahrain Government, and require no comment. (g) Article 8 also follows the agreement provisionally reached between the parties in their recent negotiations* (h) Article 9 equally reproduces an item in the negotiations already held, but requires some comment. It appears that by local agreement between the Bahrain Government and the Company a. considerable part of the gas produced during the refining pro cess, which is in fact used in the furnaces in t'he hefinery, is converted by mathematical formula into an equivalent amount of oil fuel which, in accordance with the original Lease and the subsequent Refinery Agreement, may be deducted from the royalty paying total of crude oil as ' f oil required for the customary operations of the Company’s installations’’. This of course is a reasonable and economic arrangement to which no objection can be taken; but viewing it in relation to an article prescribing that one half of the oil processed in the Refinery up to a total Refinery throughput of 20,000 (or 25,000) barrels daily shall be Bahrain crude, it may conceivably be Reid that it subjects that share to proportional deduction. On a rough calculation this would cause a deduction of 6 per cent, and it was certainly never intended that the Bahrain share of the Refinery throughput should be subjected to anyreversed /- f'K) - 6 - such reduction. So far as I ajn aware the working arrangement between the Government and the Company, to which I have referred above, cannot legally be described as an essential part of the original Lease or the Refinery Agreement and consequently the Company could not claim a legal right to a deduction on this score. If this view is correct then I see no need to vary the then I suggest that that doubt might be resolved by inserting the words ,r royalty paying' before the v/ord M oil' in line 12 of the English part of this article* There is little doubt that such an insertion would be accepted by the Company, though in return they might propose a second variation in the article by which, in place of the existing stipulation, it would be provided that not less than one half of the amount of oil processed in the ..efinery, up to a total of 20,000 (or 25,000) barrels daily, shall be produced in the Shaikh 1 s present and future dominions. The effect of this would be that while the Shaikh*s royalty rights under the article would be preserved, the Company would be enabled to vary the proportions of Saudi and Bahrain oil being processed in the Refinery as might suit them best seasonally. It has, for example, been explained to me that the Arabian crude produces twice as much first grade kerosene as does the Bahrain crude and almost twice the quantity of diesel oil, while on the other hand the Bahrain crude pro duces a greater proportion of petrol. In view of the heavy seasonal demands of certain Eastern countries for kerosene the Company might at times wish, by increasing the Arabian pro portion of the throughput, to accumulate greater kerosene stocks than they could do economically if tied to a fixed daily pro portion of Bahrain oil passing through the Refinery; at such times the major part of Bahrain production would be exported in the form of crude. At other times the process might be wording of Article 9. ' If t If however a reasonable doubt exists-7- reversed when petrol stocks required to be built up. Any rights conferred on His Majesty's Government by a pre-emption schedule in a separate Political Agreement would not of course be atfected; nor need it be apprehended that such a proposal would indicate an intention on the part of the Company to reduce Bahrain production to the minima negotiated, since in ^ b.ill a letter of the 5th June 1939 Mr. Thornburg, on behalf of the Company, repeats the assurance given last January that while the Company cannot actually guarantee more than the minima negotiated it has every expectation of being able to maintain Bahrain production at a figure approximating to present production. I enclose a copy of this letter herewith. I trust that this explanation is sufficiently clear for appreciation of the points involved. (i) Article 10 requires no comment and is unobjectionable.1 . : ‘ cr**** ^ b* 1 ^ J ° ^ * J «L«Xa OA •fcC-JLftJI) #J,JL&gt;^J| j ^^ LJUO,, ( * i5^J| * ^vX-JJlgpLJ! ^*1! ^ ^JJj f—V 1 *' &lt;Jj I &lt;L&lt;* J^+4^ j ^ •— ‘ — •&gt; u^tj* Ua irljl^■,;U-i &lt;L,Aiio.; 4,.^(iJ' iijjJ \ f lU 4 ^ ^ s^a^gjUjVi #Jla — ^ ^ji A.—. ..&lt; J I. ..i &gt;»U &lt;lL-J U—X, ® ^4 ^JLJI £,yji A.JLJ L p^i»&lt; 41—it ^ ( ' J,VI JLi_JI ' L ^ 1 o» ^Jl o.jl-aU ^ V‘u^ o* 5LL — J jj jjLJI^ L-i^M dj J 0 J&gt; VI al^l jl&gt;J \j — cr^s I* ^ ■** J l—ic ': i ^ ' j, 9 . » \i» Lrr^j V r KC C. t£ou&gt; e^-y made between HIS (HIGHNESS SHAIKH SIR HAMAD BIN SHAIKH ’ ISA AL KHALIFAH, K.C.I.E#, C.S^I.j SHAIKH OF BAHRAIN, cf the one part (in this deed called 'the Shaikh') (acting on the advice of the British Political Resident in the Persian Gulf) and THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED of the other part (in this deed called 'the Company') And being SUPPLEMENTAL to a Lease dated the 29th day of December 1934 (in this deed called 'the Lease') made between the same parties as are parties to this deed whereby certain rights and privileges were conferred upon the Company in consideration of the payment by the Company of the royalties and of the observance and performance by the Company of the other obligations more particularly referred to in the Lease and being ALSO SUPPLEMENTAL to the deed dated the 3rd day of June 1936 and expressed to be supplemental to the Lease (in this deed called 'the First Supplemental Deed') made between the same parties as are parties to this deed by which the Company oonvenanted that it would proceed to establish as soon as practicable a Refinery at Bahrein and the Lease was altered in the manner and to the extent stated in the First Supplemental Deed, WITNESSES as followsse'^ui jr Cl* J&gt;* JL+^ d* n g ! j. .—11 ^Jl 6 I (t) i •!♦-) La I^**r ^ j La Jl&gt;-j ~^ ^ (^f4 # ■ J*-- ! ij j *■&gt;• 5 ^^? j—**V &lt;jXJ oj—«J! ^ JUcCj ^jfL&amp;~- &lt;i « dijLJIj _UiJ!j Jji/vJ I d^J ^1 ,J Wl^l -_SJI jL-„ ji UfUi^ s^uji &gt;^ji ^fc.. t .’« I -La* \i«U .IJ I I ( ^) La j—&gt;*. i_^J I I a^uL' i juJ I 4 j_aj 0^ * Laj I LaJ^^vj iLiJ \j £z ^,1 La \yAM ^ j La a-&gt;2 »tuX- L’l Jg^...U&gt;» 4 —‘i^ »■' ^j-'J^ 4 J a - Ij A ...,, &lt; ..- A.^lj ! ^ (_$ j &gt;-! o X^-^r... &lt;w ^5 Ij ; J ^^ • by the Lease and the First Supplemental Deed shall extend and apply to the whole of the Shaikh^ present and future dominions, and ha :here shall be such further modifioations, extensions, enlarge ments and other alterations of and to the Lease and the First Supplemental Deed as are contained in this deedo c i. L 4 , ( ARTICLE &lt;41 .&lt; (a) The Shaikh hereby grants to the Company on behalf of himself and his Successors for the period of fifty- five years from the date of this deed, the exclusive right to prospect and drill for, extract, treat, refine, manufacture, transport and deal with petroleum products, naphtha, natural tar, asphalt, ozokerite and ‘ other bituminous materials within the {b‘ The Shaikh hereby further grants to the Company on behalf of himself and his Successors for the same period the exclusive right to construct and operate refineries and storage tanks within the Shaikh 8 e present and future dominions and also the right but not the exclusive right to construct, erect and operate wipe lines, railways, wharves, Jetties, boats, tramways, roads, buildings, machinery, telephones, telegraphs, radio and other facilities and(?) J-i* -b^ji jU, 71 J it ^ J g, (&lt;-') 3jL_JI j jt-Mj a U5' J—*■ Jil jjl ( 1) I «1A L; ) ^ ijL** 4^u. lT-^ U —&gt;■ .1 LjJLu, o-A ^1 ioj! 4 ^* t ^ ^ (jS&gt; ^LJu, 4 ju&gt;-lj Ju-u/^l ,» J 0 i^lia-jUl 0 *-&gt;J ■ 4 JLm4 UlL 4a. Article YIH of the Lease, as a by Article B-4 of the First the Company to the Shaikh durliw the period of fifteen years from ' ‘ :ii e date of this deed) shall be Twelve and one-half lakhs of which shall be increased to the rate of Seventeen lakhs of during so much of the period of fifteen years as shall remain quantities is found within the capable of producing in accord ance with good oilfield practice e quantity which would bear a royalty of not less than computation, andAwali, Bahrein Island, February 6, 1939. C.D. Belgrave, Esq., Adviser to the Bahrain Government, Manama, Bahrain• Dear Sir, As one of the terms of my Company 1 s offer for the Unallotted Area, my letter of January 12, 193© contains the following paragraph : 'During the period of one year following the date such Concession is granted, my Company will maintain at least 4 strings of tools in continuous operation within the area covered by the present Lease.' Commencing with the discovery of oil at Bahrain my Company has continuously exceeded the drilling obligations under its present Mining Lease^ During the past year or longer it has maintained four to five strings of tools in operation. «s a result there are now enough producing wells completed that tne ooligation to continue such a rapid development program over the next year would serve no useful purpose and could have no effect on the amount of oil to be pxoduced here. On the other hand, a slower development pro gram will put my Company in a better position to space the wells properly for greater ultimate recovery and to utilize more efficiently the experience gained in drilling. Because a more normal program will not affect Bahrain’s revenue, and will be helpful to my Company in its operations, the Company now wishes to modify its offer of January 12, 1939 to the extent of eliminating the obligation quoted above, ./ill you kindly inform His Highness the Shaikh of Bahrain of this modification. Yours faithfully, Sd/- F. A. Davies. Representative, ihe Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited111 /.wall, Bahrein Island 5th June 1939 C. Dalrymple Belgrave, Esq,, Adviser to the Government^of Bahrain, Bahrain, Dear Sir, In his letter of 12 January 1939 to you, I r. F.A. Davies made certain statements as follows : 'The above mentioned figures are minimum figures and my Company, while it can make no further guarantee, is pleased to assure His Highness that, in the event this Concession is granted, it has every expectation of being able to maintain the production of Bahrain at least at a figure approximating the present production so long as the wells drilled are capable of producing that much oil in accordance with good oilfield practice.' We now isish to assure His Highness that the foregoing statement of expectations still applies. This present statement is made with the thought in mind that our new Deed will shortly be executed in substantially the form submitted to His Highness with my letter of 5 June 1939, and is intended to mean that the foregoing assurances will continue to apply after the new Deed is in effect. Yours sincerely, 3d/- Max W. Thornburg.Confidential* ^ m QOVHRNMENT OP INDIA, Department. [N. B. This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, to .are exjKi.se and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, mth the same expedition as if it had been To sate time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been &gt;S3 m : !!( From To No* The Political Resident, Buahire# The Political Agent, Bahrain* 586-3 of 1939. Dated 22nd June, m ?• Subj ect : Political Agreement with Bahrain Petroleum Company. it Reference India Office Printed Letter ^To. P.Z.2067, dated the 2nd June 1939. 2 . Following are my comments2 Preamble• Article 1. Article 2. Article 3. Article 4. Article 5. u\ S. 6. MF P~785S&amp;P— 2 ,r&gt;, 000 . :?o comment. Rb comment • Jorresponds to Article XIV of 1936 Lease. Stronger than Article XIII of 1936 Lease. Ho comment. This relaxes in favour of the Company, so far as unimportant or routine matters are concerned, the rigid provisions of Article XVI of the 19 36 Lease. India Office think / thatm (i^4v - V ' |'|3 - 2 - Article 6* that the local authorities will have to be asked what provisions are con sidered essential in this Article in the lifc-ht of their experience. I see no objection to this Article. Hepeats Article XVII of Mining Lease. It would be preferable to have the *3* The employees of the Company in Kuwait shall at all times so far as is oonsistent with the efficient carrying on of the undertaking he British subjects or subjects of the Shaikh* With the consent of His Uajesty 9 s Coverusent, which consent shall not be unreasonably withheld» persons of other nationalities may be employed if in the opinion of the Company they are required for the efficient carrying on of the undertaking. Bbtwithstanding anything contained in the Agreement between the Company and the Shaikh f the importation of for eign native labour shall be subject to the approval of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf*l'\ GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. oo^ gB . TO Ai,. Department. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). No. 587-S of 1929 baM ^ lr *A Nelv ueint\ xxxxxx 22nd Juxio, 79 39. T ik From Political xtesideut. To Refer ence xxxxxxxjexx Repeated Buuhire• Hia Majesty's Secretary of State for India, London. The Secretary to the Government of India, External Affairs Department, Simla. The Political A^ent, Bahrain. Subject * Bahrain Additioiial Area draft oonoession. r f Reference India Office Printed Letter ^o.P.2.2C67, dated P .i* 1 the 2nd 19 39. I encloee a copy of Express Letter ?3b.C/376- 10/14, dated the poth June 1939, from the Political Agent, Bahrain, with enclosures• 2* Mr. Ballantyne's draft has been superseded by Mr.Thornburg's draft, ehich varies in several respects from it and which has been accepted by the Shaikh, subject of course to the approval of His ^jesty's Government. It is on this draft therefore on which we ^ave to work. My comments are as follows* Preamble. I agree with Political Agent's views: see also penultimate paragraph of India Office letter 8067, dated the 30th May 19 39, to the Petroleum Department • (Signature) Articles / . / 8/44, (Designation) —M.1 KQ-TX 97 11 Od 1A AAAI'l'o - 2 - ^ticlee 2 and 'Prcserit and future doIQinloaB ,l . It was pointed out in paragraph i of the India Office letter quoted above that the Shaikh of Bahrain was not likely to welcome the distinction between hi a present* and his 'future' possessions. He has however now accented this dis tinction, and the definition pro posed by the Company is, I think, more likely to be acceptable to him than that proposed by the India Office. The use of the Company’s definiti on in no way, of course, affects the position of His Majesty*s Government in regard to the claims of other Rulers or of those of the Shaikh himself. I concur with Political Agent. I concur. I concur. I concur, but Petroleum Department mifc&amp;t like to give an opinion. I concur. I concur. I suggest that the Petroleum Depart ment be asked to give their opinion on this Article. This does not appear in Mr.Ballan- tyne’o draft and waa obviously / inserted Article 4 (a). iw* (o). Article 5. Articles 6 &amp; 7 Article 8. Article 9. Article 10.By Air Mail, P.Z. 19^ INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, — '?• t Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. H ■11 Z,2o94/39 India Office ? Whitehall P 3.V.I. 2 ^nd i.Iay 3 19 39 Resident in the Persian Gulf Ro.423-3 (forwarded under India Office letter Ro. ?.Z.2394/39 dated 10th Hay) regarding the ovmersh i p of the Uavva r Islands. Lord Zetland agrees wit . the view expressed Toy the Political Resident that t hese isla nds belong to the sheikh ofJSahre in and not to the Shelkhlf o atar ; and ho p- oposes subject to the eoncuFrenee of the Secretary of state for - eign Affe-.x s to request the Governiucnt of India if they also concur to instruct the Political Resident accordingly. I am ; 3ir ? Y our oh c di on t 3 or van t (Sgd.) R. PEEL. hicur Secretary of State- -■oreign Office, S. '7.1.i 38X2/196/91 Sir, Y FOREIGN OFFICE. S.W.I. 13th June, 1939. iii I am directed by Viscount Halifax to acknowledge the receipt of your letter P.Z. 2894/39 of the 22nd May regarding the ownership of the Hawar Islands. Lord Halifax concurs in the Marquess of Zetland’s proposal to request the Government of India, if they see no objection, to instruct the Political Resident in the Persian Gull to inform the crheikhs of Bahrein and Qatar that His Majesty’s Government have decided that these islands belong to the Sheikh of Bahrein. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, {SW G.^ “tier Secretary of State, hdia Office.5 f / GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, Department. EXPRESS LETTER [N,B, This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to sore telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be lr&gt; a(ed on receipt, with the same expedition as if it hud been Leb graphed To sare time and formalities id is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] From To Political Agent, Bahrain. ■ p i &lt; • .4 •• r&gt; c r' rr c, * c •&gt;, t \/^l I o. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Camp Bahrain. C/394-10/14* Dated the 30th June 7559. Subject: Political Agreement with the Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited. jT2. Your Express Letter No.586-3, dated the 22nd June 1939, on the above subject. 2. In the course of examining the draft agreement, it has occurred to me that a major obstruction may arise owing to the existence of sales contracts already entered into by the Company ^ _ ?or long periods ahead. ( I have not, of course, made any attempt locally to ascertain what contracts they now have). Such contracts flight contain 'force majeure' clauses to cover non-performance owing to war, but such clauses could not, I imagine, be stretched legally to cover a subsequent agreement with His Majesty*s Govern- flent by which the latter may pre-empt in v/ar-time. If this is so, it will become necessary to approach the problem from a totally different angle — in other words His Majesty's Government must $. e. M’P-iOOS&amp;P (M 480 26-7-34-2.^0,J00. first/tg) 125 2 - first acquire a legal right from the Ruler of Bahrain to take over (in effect) in war time all Bahrain products describable as ,f war material'I am not quite sure what the legal procedure would be, or whether a subsequent formal Political Agreement with the Company would be necessary. Possibly only an understanding would be necessary — that His Majesty's Government on their side would pay fair prices and/or compensation, and the Company on their side would work their concession and Refinery Agreement to capacity limits. 3. If, however, a Political Agreement is still necessary, I have the following comments to make on the present draft. Preamble and Article 1 . Bince the draft concession for the Additional Area has already been submitted to His Majesty’s Government for approval and is likely to be signed before — or simultaneously with — the Political Agreement, the Preamble and Article 1 will presumably be amended as contemplated in the last sentence of paragraph 2 Office letter Ho.P.Z.2067/39, dated the rso ,K 3rd Hay 1939. Article 2 . I suggest there are considerable disadvantages in canalising all communications between His Majesty’s Government and the Company. In existing practice communication on many subjects of mutual importance to His Hajesty f s Government and the Company is initiated between the Company’s Chief Local Representative and the Political Agent in Bahrain. This possesses the advantage that Plis Hajesty's Government can receive, in the initial stages of any such discussion, a report based on local knowledge (c.f. comments under Article 8 below). I suggest therefore that the Article be redrafted to allow communication in Bahrain . Articles 3 and 4. No comments. Article 5./3 - fl / Article 5 In point of i&amp;cu a great deal of routine and unimportant work is already disposed of in direct communication between the Company and the Adviser to the Bahrain Government. I see no need for any special reservations to be made in this article, ihe Political Agent knows everything that goes on, and if he were to find that too liberal an interpretation were taken of the words “'routine or unimportant matters' it would be his business to ste - ih^ and rectify matters. Articles 6 and 7 . No comment. *^ Article 8 . I'he addition to the normal form of this Article is presumably due to an (inaccurate) suggestion by mr. Ballantyne that His majesty* s Ships use the Company*s harbours free of charge. an point of fact the Company has no harbour approach able by any but shallow draft boats and barges. The addition therefore bestows no benefit. Articles 9, 10 and 11 and the Schedule . No comment Political Agent, Bahrain.86/n ft* Telegram Q, Srom Political Resident t Bushire» To GoTernment of India» Simla*. No.368 Dated the 8 th July 1939. India Office letter No.P.Z. 3693 June 16th. Hawar Islands. May I assume that Government of India concur with views of His Majesty's Government ? I should like to inform Shaikh of Bahrain as soon as possible. Britconsul44 . Designation) m confidential , GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. Department. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). [N. . m an OBlGINAL message sent by AlJti MAIL tohich provides a means of cornmunicatwn more expedtltoue than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formahttes it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department ) No. 627-S To Repeated Date 10th July, 19 His Majesty*s Secretary of State for India, London. The Secretary to the Government of India, External Affairs Department, Simla. The Political Agent, Bahrain. Subject t~ Political Agreement with the Bahrain Petroleum Company .Limited. t \ S Reference your Printed Letter No.?.2.2067/1^39 dated the 2nd June 1939, with enclosures. 2. After consultation with the Political Agent, Bahrain, my comments on the draft Political Agreement are as follows. &amp;s follows: Preamble. No comment. Article 1. No comment. Article 2. Political Agent, Bahrain, writes 'I suggest there are considerable disadvantages in canalising all communications between His Majesty's Government and the Company• In exist ing practice communication on many subjects of mutual importance to His Majesty's Government and the Company is initiated between the Company's (Signal ure) chief- 2 - ft m) i «1 Chief Local hepresentative and the Political Agent in Bahrain. Thie poseesees the advantage that Hie Majesty's Government can receive, in the initial stages of any such discussion, a report based on local knowledge (c.f. comments under Article 8 below). I suggest therefore that the Article be redrafted to allow communication in Kai^rain .“ Since the Headquarters of the Cosapany are not in England this Article as worded is necessary but it does not prevent questions being initiated at Bahrain. I am not of opinion that any amendment is necessary. Article 3. No comment. Article 4. No comment. Article 5. Political Agent, Bahrain, writes* 'In point of fact a great deal of routine and unimportant work is already disposed of in direct communication between the Company and the Adviser to the Bahrain Government. I see no need for any special reservations to be made in this Article. The Political .Agent knows everything that goes oa, and if he were to find that too liberal an interpretation were taken of the words 'routine or unimportant matters' it would be his business to step in and rectify matters• w If this reservation were not inserted all business between the Company and the Bahrain Government would have to be conducted through the Political Agent, which would give the latter unnecessary work and lead to delays. Since, as the Political Agent points out, routine work is already disposed of in direct communication between-3- ; . Ky i* % between the Cottipany and the Bahrain Government the reservation merely regularises the position, and I am of opinion that it should be retained. Article 6. This repeats Article XVII of the 1936 Mining heese. It would be preferable to have the stronger wording of Article 3 of the Kuwait political Agreement though it might be difficult to secure this with a wholly American Company. Article 7. No comment. Article 8. Political Agent writes* M The addition to the normal form of this Article is presumably due to an (inaccurate) suggestion by Mr.Ballantyne that His Majesty’s Ships use the Company’s harbours free of charge. In point of fact the Company has no harbour approachable by any but shallow draft boats and barges. The addition therefore bestows no Denefit. M Whether the addition is made on the grounds suggested by the Political Agent or not, it is impossible to say what future developments may occur, and I think it should be retained. Article 9. No comment. Article 10. Political Agent, Bahrain, writes* M In the course of examining the draft agreement, it has occurred to me that a major obstruction may arise owing to the existence of sales contracts already entered into by the Company for loiig periods ahead. (I have not, of course, made any attempt locally to ascertain what contracts they now have). Such contracts might contain 'force majeure' clauses to cover non-performance owing to war,war, but such clauses could not, X imagine, be stretched legally to cover a Subsequent agreement with His Majesty’s Government by which the latter may pre-empt in war-time• If this is so, it will become necessary to approach the problem from a totally different angle - in other words his mjesty’s Government must first acquire a legal right from the Huler of Bahrain to take over (in effect) in war time all Bahrain products describable as «war material” # I am not quite sure what the legal procedure would be, or whether a formal Political Agreement with the Company would be necessary.- Possibly only an understanding would be necessary - that Eis Majesty’s Government on their side would pay fair prices and/or compensation, and the Company on their side would work their concession and Refinery Agreement to capacity limits. M The points raised by the Political Agent would seem to be covered in paragraphs (4) and (5) of the Schedule to this clause, and in any case it seems to me tnat the Company will doubtless safeguard their interests in this matter. Article 11. ko comment. Sd. T. C. Fowle, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.Telegram .Prom To Ho. 978 Secretary to the Government of India, External Affairs Department, Simla. Political Resident, Bushire. Dated and received 10th July 1939. / x Your telegram Ho. 368 of 8th July. Hawar Islands. 2 + Your assumption confirmed. Please see our Express Letter Ho. P.22-H/39 of 1st July.0 /f Confidential. ^0.640-3 of 1939. British Residency &amp; Consulate-General Bushire, the uth July, 1939. From • The Hon 9 hle Sir Trenohard Fovle, KCIB. # CBB., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf To •His Majesty* s Secretary of State for India, The India Office, London. With reference to correspondence ending with your letter -No. l.Z.3693/39, dated the 16th June 1939, to the Government of India, I have the honour to enclose herewith oopy of letters and to the Shaikh of ^atar, 2 despatched these letters after having ascertained from the Government of India that they - p' (&lt;}o concurred in the decision of His Majesty*s Government. I am sending copies of this letter to the Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Department and to the Political Agent, Bahrain. Sir, * I have the honour to be Sir Your most obedient humble servant, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. *sent under Printed letter jmo. 641-3 of the lith July,1939.Confidential . flo.642-3 of 1939. British Realdenoy 4 Conaulate-General, Buahire, the nth July, 1939. f c To Tht Political Agentf Bahrain* SubjjBct: Owner ship of Hawar Islands* MsmorandiuP i In continuation of my Printed Letter No*64i-3, dated the nth July* 1939* I enclose herewith letters for the Shaikhs of Bahrain and (4atar* which please transmit to these Rulers* sd* TaJ.Fowle* Political Resident in the Persian Gulf* Attested * for Sedretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf*/ (RMl IW GCMFIEMTIJII. V BUSH’:n*i l.- v&gt; i.'. &gt;mv-v t-'i-is; a ,M GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, 171 iiIRS Department, EXPRESS LETTER CQNFlQyK/ lAL RL CLT.US [iV, R, T/n's is aw ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt,' with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed, To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] From FCHEIGN, SET-a. \ To BEITCCNSLl, BISEIRZ. / (Copy to - Secretary of State for India, London. A'ow F. 22C-K/39. - Political ilgent, Bahrain* ) Dated / July 2M 9. SUBJECTS* OTanerahip of Eawar IslarhE * hi*®* ^ r Refer oKice India Office letter Ko* P*2*3693/29, da.ted 16th June 1939* 2. Government of India concur ir, tr.o riev? tn&amp;t the Hav^sx islands belong tc Bern: air. ar/i not to Qatar a/n request that you .iill infom the Cl.aikhs concern.ec as proposed* The issue cf the ah eve nas been author isPE THOLE'If COJCESSIOPS I LEI TED, CITY-GATE HOUSE, f f’B/55. PUT SB UR Y SQUARE, LOITDOF, E.C.2. :er Secretary of State for India Whitehall, S.W.l. 1 Sir , 30th Tune, 1939. It is proposed in the near future to replace Hr .ih.V. packer, the Company’s present Manager in Bahrain, ®0 ^r.Frederick ^irthur Bali. _ our consent of Mr .Ball to Bahrain is asked. Mr .Ball is 35 years of age, married, to the posting was educated at the Liverpool Institute, worked for 9 years in all with tne British American Tobacco Company in Egypt and Syria, and has served for the last 7 years with this Company and the Iraq Petroleum Company Limited. Por the last 2k years i-u has been our assistant manager at Jeddah, where we believe his relations, both with the public and with the British and other diplomatic authorities, have been excellent. V/e should, therefore, be very glad to receive your normal approval to the proposed posting. We have , etc . , (Sd.) J. Skliros Por PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LIMITED.1 ,4065/39. I1TDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL, S.W. 1 4th July 1939 Sir, I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to acknowledge the receipt of your letter of the 30th Jy ) 7 / June, llo.pc.26 3/55, regarding the proposed replacement of Mr.3.V.Packer by Mr.F.A.Ball as your Company's Manager at Bahrein, and to inform you that a reply will oe sent thereto as soon as possible. In the meantime I am to ask that you will be good enough to state whether Mr.Ball is a British subject and whether it is proposed that he should succeed Mr.Packer as the Chief Local Representative of Petroleum Development (Qatar) Ltd. for Qatar. I am, Sir, Your ob ed i ent Ser van t, j, p f /'aging Direct or, ' e ^ r °i eurn Concessions Limited, City-Gate House, Finsbury Square, E.C.2.^ 066 / 59. liMDIA OFFICE, Wril TEHALL, S.W.l. 4th July 1939. Dear Eyres, I enclose a copy of correspondence with Petroleum Concessions Lmited regarding a proposal to appoint Mr.F.A.Ball as their Manager in Bahrein in succession to Mr.E.V.Packer. There is no indication that Mr.Ball has had experience of the Oulf and he is therefore presumably unknown personally to the political authorities there. He appears, however, to be known to the Legation at Jedda, and as a first step we should bo grateful if you could make very early enquiries of the Minister about his suitability/ - , from the point of view of His Majesty’s Government for the appointment in Bahrein. It would be helpful if Bullard could reply briefly by telegram. I an sending a copy of this letter and enclosures to Starling and Jarrett. Yours sincerely, fSgd.) j, p QfBSOIw ; 2 yres, Esq., ioreign Office.By Air Mail. P.Z. 10 % c t fBUSHIRE residency! Dsfe CONFiOcNiiAL KECORDr INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, - T&gt; ^, Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office.a- 7-d f ,4023/39. INDIA OIA'ICS; '.'.'llITDHALL ; S. vf. 1 6th Julyj 1939. Dear Baggallay; Nany than),a for your^le^tters _ of the 20th and 21st June, Ilos. 12.4025 and 4026/196/91, about the draft C ° KC —° n f ° r the Bahrein UnallottirT^, relevant draft political agreement. ~~~ 2. ! r. Ballantyne called rerc-titr ^ a recentl y fo ^ an informal talk and I enclose a note of the converget i n-n W- +• ^uuvcioaiion*Witn regard to the subjects covered:- A. Je should be glad to nave the views of the Foreign Office on Ballantyne&gt;s suggestion regarding the area of the concession. 3. With regard to the new draft of thn „„„ uidiu oi the concession I enclose herewith a copy of a letter nit ^ -Ky a letter just J ^geeived from the F°-~ ReSiaent ' 3u ^ ect to the views oTtle Petroleum Department on the comments made by the Political ’2nd June, -closure. Agent on Articles 5 and 9 we are disposed to think that the revised draft concession may be accepted. C * 1 enclose a n °te of provisional comments on the -iay, Bsq. % Office. points/l.H u © 2 . points raised Toy Ballantyne and should he grateftil for any views you may wish to express. Ho doubt the Petroleum Department and Admiralty will he ahle to help in the matter of the objections to the pre-emption clause. 3. I am consulting also Starling and Jarrettj to whom a copy of this letter and enclosures is being sent. Yours sincerely,; (Sgd.) R. PEEL,Bahrein Unall ottar. Area. &lt;g) Hr. Ballantyne , at his request, called on the 26th June tor a furtner talk about the political agreement, etc, it v/as explained to him that in the absence of the views of certain other Departments concerned the draft agreement given to him was still purely provisional. He suggested however that time might be saved if at this stage he could express his views informally. He wished to speak about three matters relating to the nev/ concession. A * —S ax&gt;ea 0 .t.l^S_coneosglCTi &gt; Hr. Ballantyne said his Co...pony wer e specially interested in the question of rights over the shallow waters round Bahrein. He was aware of the dispute as to the ownership of the two small islands west of Bahrein (Bam-al-Kabir and Bain-as-Jaghir) and of the suggestion for dividing the Bahreini and Saudi spheres by a median line. He produced a large chart of the Bahrein archipelago which his Company were in process of completing by their surveys, and pointing to various small islands oast of Bahrein on which the Bahrein Government had put up marks he said that in one view Bahrein had sovereignty over the waters within three rales of each of those islands. Further, if elsewhere in the shallow waters his Company were to erect derricks then he believed Bahrein could claim the ownership of the adjoining waters within a three mile radius. He however intended to put forward a more sweeping view, namely, that the whole of the area between Qatar and Hasa outside the territorial waters of Qatar and Saudi Arabia (in the latter case, east of a median line if one were drawn between Bahrein and the mainland) should be regarded as within the ownership of Bahrein (and so within the area of the Company's concession), on the analogy of claims which he believed were maintained elsewhere that territorial sovereignty could be exercised over all the waters of a gulf even/ f2 . even outside the customary three-mile limit. I said that we should have co consult the Foreign Office 'before we could say whether it is possible to pursue this suggestion. li-f—:Qfl agrec: :icnt. Mr. Ballantyne left v/ith .'-e a copy (attached herewith) of the draft concession as it stood after negotiation with the Sheikh, together with certain correspondence relating thereto. He explained that the last two clauses were additions proposed subsequently to the submission of tne draft to the Sheikh, He pointed out that a.s the result Oj. discussion with the political authorities in Bahrein Arti cle 2 had been modified in a way that he hoped would meet our objections to his original draft. lie also drew attention to the specific reference in Article 4 to radio iacilities* the use of which is confined within the limits of the concession. He said these facilities, to which he assumed His Majesty’s Government would see no objection, were absolutely essential for the geophysical work which the Company would carry out in the additional area. He added that the Company’s representative in Bahrein had tried to have included permission for the use of aircraft, but that the Political Agent and the Bahrein Government had firmly objected to this. fhe Political Agreement . Mr. Ballantyne left the attached memorandum as an informal expression of his comments .th the on the draft. Apart from articles 5 JJX CDO-LUII UJ_ and 10 (wil schedule) to which he saw fundamental objections, he referred to the following Articles Art. 2 . He suggested that instead of “ The recognised channel '* 1 the words should be altered to “a recognised channel ’ 1 so as not to preclude the Company from dealings with the Political Agent as the local representative of His Majesty’s Government. Art. 7. * Mr. Ballantyne was assured that this Article was in a common form as used in other/3. other similar agreements and did not arise out of any previous aspect of the company's relations with the Sheikh and His Majesty's Government; indeed its object might he expressed as a desire that the Company should continue in the future to act towards the Sheikh and His Majesty's Government as they had done in the past, nhen it was emphasised that the whole Article was expressly subject to the terms of the Company's concessions, Mr. .ballantyne did not seem anxious to press his objection. A:o regards Article 3; Mr. Ballantyne's difficulty lay in the v/ords 'the obligations and benefits of^ those agreements.” If they covered,, not merely the formal assignment of the concession to another company, but also any alteration in the existing holdings of the Company's shares (or of the shares of The Standard Oil Co. of California), this was an obligation that the Company could not accept. He said that over two years ago this issue had been discussed with us at the time when the Company was making marketing arrangements with the Texas Corporation, and that it had been found impossible to go beyond an understanding that the Company would give His Majesty's Government an opportunity to express their views before concluding transactions affecting their share holdings. The Company might have to enter into commitments, e.g. by mortgaging shares or operations for the funding of its obligations, a possible result of which might be the passing of shares to interests which were neither British nor American, but the Company could not bind itself in all such cases to obtain beforehand the v/ritten consent of His Majesty's Government.4. \ As regards Article 10 and the schedule 0 . Mr. Ballantyne, with reference to his note on this Article, explained that the serious difficulty which he found in tne re—emotion obligations had not so far occurred to iiis Company hut was inescapaole, and would ecually arise in connexion with mining concessions obtained by Indian Oil obligations had oeen entered into by the Anglo-iranian Oil Co. or in respect of oil concessions in Iraq. I said that tne reason no douot was that Persian and Iraq territory was noc under our control, but that pre-emption obligations in tne same terms had been accepted by the companies operating in che other Arab States of the Gulf, and that similar obligations were imposed by the Government of India. He saia his Company had no desire whatever to avoid meeting His Majesty’s Government’s requirements. There -would be no difficulty in their recognising that His Majesty’s Government or the Sheikh on His Majesty’s Government’s advice, could step in and take the oil when required in an emergency; this would be a case of the application of ’’force majeure” beyond the Company’s control, a contingency for v/hich contracts duly make provision. But if the Company voluntarily accepted pre-emption obligations they would have to disclose them in their contracts and this would completely upset their marketing arrangements. He would be glad to discuss the difficulties with legal Departments concerned v/ho probably knew the answer to his objection. experts. I said that we would first have to ^iocuys the (Intld.) J.P.G.© V&gt;1 DATED 1939 HIS HIG-HMESS SHAIKH SIR HAIvIAD BIN SHAIKH 'ISA AL KHALIPAH, K.C.I.E., C.S.I. , SH-UKH OF BAHREIN - and - THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. DRAFT 1939. DEED OF FURTHER MODIFICATION Of Lease dated 29th December 1934.THIS DEED made between HIS HIGHNESS SHAIKH SIR HAMAD BIN SHAIKH T ISA AL KHALIPAH, K.C.I.E., C. S. I. , SHAIKH CE BAHREIN, of the one part (in this deed called ,f the Shaikh H ) (acting on the advice oi the British Political Resident in the Persian Gulf) and THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED of the other part (in this deed called n the Company”) And being SUPPLEMENTAL to a Lease dated the 29th day of December 1934 (in this deed called 'the Lease') made between the same parties as are parties to this deed whereby certain rights and privileges were conferred upon the Company in consideration of the payment by the Company of the royalties and of the observance and performance by the Company of the other obligations more particularly referred to in the Lease And being ALSO SUPPLEMENTAL to the deed dated the 3rd day of June 1936 and expressed to be supplemental to the Lease (in this deed called 'the First Supplemental Deed') made between the same parties as are parties to this deed by which the Company convenanted that it would proceed to establish .* 0 -soon as practicable a Refinery at Bahrein and the Lease Y/as altered in the manner and to the extent stated in the First Supplemental Deed WITNESSES as follov/s:- ARTICLS 1 . The Shaikh on his part and the Company on its part have performed to dote all their agreements and obligations under the Lease«. i i as altered 'by the First Supplemental Deed. ARTICLE 2 (a) nil landSj islands, shoals, reefs, waters and submerged lands over which the Shaikh now has dominion or which may, after the date of this Deed, come under the dominion of the Shaikh or his successors during the period of fifty-five years from the date of this deed, or any extension of such period are in this deed called the 'Shaikh's present and future dominions'. bThose of the Shaikh’s present dominions which were not at the time of this deed exclusively leased to the Company by the Lease, together with the Shaikh’s future dominions, have been called, and are colled in this Deed, the 'Additional Area'. ARTICLE 5 The Shaikh and the Company have now agreed (a) that the Company shall pay to the Shaikh four lakhs of Rupees (Rs.4,00,000 ) on or before this deed is executed and (b) that the rights and privileges granted by the Shaikh to the Company by the Lease and the First Supplemental Deed shall extend and apply to the whole of the Shaikh’s present andfuture dominions and (c) that there shall he such further modifications, extensions, enlargements and other alterations of and to the Lease and the First Supplemental Deed as are contained in this deed. ARTICLE 4 . (a) The Sheikh hereby grants to the Company on behalf of himself and his Successors for the period of fifty-five years from the date of this deed, the exclusive right to prospect and drill for, extract, treat, refine, manufacture, transport and deal with petroleum products, naphtha, natural gasses, tar, asphalt, ozokerite and other bituminous materials within the Sheikh f s present and future dominions. (b) The Shaikh hereby further grants to the Company on behalf of himself and his Successors for the same period the exclusive right to construct and operate refineries and storage tanks within the Shaikh’s present and future dominions and also the right but not the exclusive right to construct, erect and operate pipelines, railways, wharves, jetties, boats, tramways, roads, buildings, machinery, telephones, telegraphs, radio and other facilities and apparatus of all kinds in any part of the Shaikh’s present and future dominions so far as may be necessary for the purpose of its business except that radio equipment may not be used to transmit~ 4 - messages beyond the limits of the concession; and (c) The rights granted by either subclauses (a) or (b) of this Article shall not include the exclusive right to sell petroleum products within the Shaikh’s present and future dominions, and (d) The foregoing grants of rights by the Shaikh and his successors to the Company shall operate by way of confirmation and enlargement of the grants of rights existing under or by virtue of the Lease as altered by the First Supplemental Deed and this deed. ARTICLE 5 (a) The Company will pursue with diligence and without unnecessary delay, geological work within the additional area, including structure drilling and geophysical work, if necessary, and (b) The Company will drill test wells for oil wherever in its judgment geological evidence warrants, commencing operations on the first test well not later than tv/o and one-half years from the date of this deed, if a favourable area has been found, and (c) If oil is discovered within the additional area the Company will continue drilling further wells until oil in commercial quantities, that is of a daily average of 500 tons for a period of 30 consecutive days produced in accordance with good oilfield practice, has been obtained, or until the area is no longer deemed favourable, and (d) Upon discovery of oil in commercial5 quantities the Company shall continue drilling within the productive area until the requirements of good oilfield practice have been met, this obligation however being subject to suspension during such times as the wells then drilled within the additional area are capable of a total daily average of at least 1,000 tons for a period of 30 consecutive days of oil produced in accordance with good oilfield practice. ARTICLE 6 . The royalty provisions of Article VII of the Lease, as modified by Article (B)-(3) of the First Supplemental Deed, shall as from the (date of this deed) apply over the whole of the Shaikh’s present and future dominions. ARTICLE 7 . After the date of this deed the following provisions as to minimum royalty shall apply, in the place of Article VIII of the Lease, as altered by Article B-4 of the First Supplemental Deed; namely (a) The minimum royalty payable by the Company to the Shaikh during the period of fifteen years from (the date of this deed) shall be at the rate of not less than Twelve and one-half lakhs of Rupees (Rs.12,50,000)per annum which shall he increased to the rate of Seventeen lakhs of Rupees (Rs.17,00,000) per annum during so much of the period of fifteen years as shall remain unexpired after oil in commercial quantities is found within the additional area, and the wells drilled within the Shaikh 1 s present and future dominions are capable of producing in accordance with good oilfield practice the quantity which would hear a royalty of not less than Rs.17,00,000 in any one year of computation, and (h) Following the fifteen year period and continuing so long as the Lease is in operation, the Company will pay to the Shaikh not less than the rate of One and a half lakhs of Rupees (Rs. 1,50,000) per year in respect of royalties hut that sum shall he increased to the rate of Three lakhs (Rs.3,00,000) if oil in commercial quantities should have been found within the additional area either during or after the fifteen-year period and the wells drilled within the Shaikh’s present and future dominions are capable of producing in accordance with' good oilfield practice the quantity, which would hear a royalty of not less than Rs.3,00,000 in any one year of computation, and- 7 ~ (c) The foregoing provisions as to minimum royalties contained in sub-clauses (a) and (b) of this Article shall be subject to suspension under the terms of Article 8 of this deed. ARTICLE 8 . The following provisions shall as from the'(date of this deed) be substituted for the existing Article IV of the Lease, namely:- The Shaikh shall give all the protection in his power to the Company and to its staff and labourers in any part of his territory from thefts, highway robbery, assault, etc. Similarly the Shaikh shall protect all the property of the Company and of its employees which may be exposed to wilful damage or to possible loss by theft. If the Company is delayed in or prevented from carrying on its work or ^ in fulfilling any of its duties or obligations under the Lease as altered by the First Supplemental Deed or this deed by such events as are mentioned in this Article or by force mojcure either within the Shaikh’s present and future dominions or elsewhere, then the Company shall be free from all liability in respect of any such failure or delay and the period of every such delay shall be added to the period of fifty-five years granted by this deed; neither shall any minimum royaltyo — &lt;s&gt;. T 3 C payable in respect of any such delay. ’’Force Ilajeure' 1 ' as used in this deed includes the Act of God ; vis major, war 3 insurrection, riot, civil commotion, tide storm, tidal wave, flood, lightning, explosion, fire, earthquake, malice or negligence or default of any third party and any other happening (whether solely due to the forces of nature or not) which the Company could not reasonably have foreseen or if it had foreseen, ^ould not reasonably have prevented. averted or controlled. ARTICLE 9 . During the period of fifteen years from (the date of this Deed) not less than one-half the oil processed in the Bahrein Refinery up to a total refinery throughput of 20,000 barrels daily, and if oil in commercial quantities found within the Additional Area then not less than one-half the oil processed in the Bahrein Refinery up to a total refinery throughput of 25,000 barrels daily, shall be oil produced in the Shaikh’s present and future dominions, provided tne Wells drilled are capable ox producing that much oil in accordance with good oilfield practice and subject to the delay provisions of Article 3 of this Deed.9 ahticl^ 10 . The Company will not drill on Um Hasan Island nor within the present municipal ■boundaries of Manama and Muharraq as defined in the Lease P nor within 500 yards of the Shaikh 1 s existing hunting lodges ? namely at Howaitha, Amar and A 1 Umattala without j.irst obtaining the permission of the Shaikh or his Successors. It is understood that these areas are included in the area covered by this Deed and that there will be no further payment or consideration for these permissions when granted. ARTICLE 11 . The Lease shall as from the date of this deed be read and construed as if the alterations of and to the Lease and the Hirst Supplemental Deed set out in the foregoing provisions of this deed had been made in the Lease on the date of this Deed and as so altered the Lease and the Hirst Supplemental Deed are hereby ratified and confirmed as valid and binding on the parties thereto for all the purposes thereof. DATED this day of One thousand nine hundred and thirty-nine and executed in three parts all having equal validity.26th tTune P 1969 POUT I CAL ACaiiDKDJTT . &gt;ii NOTES ON HOUGH DNANT GUBHItTED BY H.N. GOVEHIILIENT TO THE BAHREIN PETEOLNUN CONPANY LIMITED POP CON3IDEPAT6 ON. Delete present Recitals and substitute following :- ''The Company having hnowlcdgo of the protection afforded by H.M. Government to and enjoyed by 5 the Sheikh of Bahrain ( here mat tor called '‘‘the Sheikh'') and having by the several Agreements dated the 29th December 1954* the 3rd June 1936 and che 1939* obtained with the prior approval of H.L. Government the several concessions men tioned in such Agreements in regard to petroleum and matters relating to petroleum over the whole of the present and future territories of tne Sheikh and having every desire to submit to the influence of K.M. Government within the confines of such territories* has agreed with K.M. Government* as follows :- !i 2. Delete present Clause 1 . 3. Modify original Clause 2 to accord with the practice of the Company communicating with H.M,Government at Home and Abroad (abroad through the Political Agent and other Representatives) and thus avoid a technical default by failing to communicate through a British Subject in charge of the office in Great Britain. 4. Original Clause 3. ' The import of this is not understood: could it be explained ? .I s 3. Original Clause 4. No objection. P 6 . Original Clause 5. It is suggested that this might be improved by altering it to read as follows 'The Company in all except unimportant or routine matters shall deal with the Bahrain Government through a Chief Local Representative in Bahrain who shall be a British Subject and who shall be the recognised channel2 . of communication betwoon the Company and the Bahrain Government. All communications which that Official may desire on behalf of the Company to address to the Bahrain Government concerning amendments to or interpretations of ; rhe Hining Lease or to any supplements thereof or concerning any other matters of direct concern to H.M. Government; as indicated by H.B.M’s Political Agent; shall be made through H.B.M's Political Agent in Bahrain. Communications with the Bahrain Government relating only to the conduct or regulation of ordinary company operations may be directly between the Chief Local Representative and the Adviser to the Bahrain Government; with copies to the Political Agent. The approval of H.M. Government shall be required for the person so designated. A reasonable time shall be allowed for the replacement of the Chief Local Representative in the event of the post falling vacant. 7. Original Clause 6 requires no comment. 3. Original Clause 7. The real import of this clause is understood to mean that the Company acknowledges the power and position of H.M. Government as the Protector of Bahrain. However, tied in as it is with the power of the Sheikh to terminate the concessions, it would seem to place into the hands of H.M. Government an undue legal power which the Company believes it is not the intention of H.M. Government to acquire. The Company wishes to uphold the position of the Government in Bahrain and assuming that H.M. Government desire to retain the Clause, it is suggested it should be altered to express the undertaking of the Company at all times to pay all proper deference due to the prestige of the Sheikh and to the advice of the Political Agent and the Political Resident in the Persian/ (230 O. Gulf subject always ? of course 5 to the terms of its agreements with the Sheikh. Has this provision grown out of any contrary l.istory during the past few years ? 10. Original Clause 9 seems to he acceptable. 11. Original Clause 10. This, with its schedule 5 seems to overlook the fundamental difficulty with which an operating company is faced in providing for such provision in its marketing contracts. Whilst the terms themselves could be criticised any such criticism must be deferred to the all- important question of whether such terms can properly be imposed upon an operating company having regard to the fact that no buyer from the Company could possibly be asked to submit to a clause in his contract providing for the variation of the terms or termination of the contract to meet an agreed-upon supply of oil and/or loss of control upon the happening of a state o^. emergency proclaimed as such by H.ii. Government. As to the arbitration 3 who would receive notice to arbitration as representing H.M. Government ? 9. Original Clause 8 . is assumed alternative accommodation available elsewhere is within the Sheikh’s domain.@ Comments on Mr. Ballantyne’s notes on the Political Ac^eernent. 1. Presumably this suggestion is in substitution for the 'whereas” paragraph of our preamble, which, along with opr Article 1, was worded to cover the possibility that the political agreement would be signed before the concession* Mr. Ballantyne’s draft seems unobjectionable except for the words 'prior approval' which in one sense are not accurate since approval of the new concession is conditional on the signing of the political agreement. Perhaps 'knowledge' would do in place of 'prior approval'? 2. Agreed. 3* The substitution of 'a' for 'the' before 'recognised channel' suggests that there may be several recognised channels, but there seems no practical objection to the change and the Company are not likely to want to alter their existing; contacts with His Majesty’s Government which work satisfactorily. 4. The Article in our draft was taken from the Koweit Political Agreement. In other political agreements 'obligations and benefits' is omitted. Mr. Ballantyne thinks there could be no objection to the Article with the words 'the obligations and benefits of' omitted; indeed the Article would then only reproduce in other terms the provisions of Article XIII of the 1934 lease (with reference to which, by the way, he would like to have inserted in the Political Agreement 'Such consent shall not be unreasonably withheld' though we had already shown our unwillingness to add these words to Article 2.) But he suggests that this does not carry us as far11. This is for separate consideration. (m &amp; as we might wish, since it does not provide control over share transactions, and that we might wish to have some such provision as 'It is understood hy the Company that any transactions which have as their object or possible result the passing of control over the Company's operations to foreign or other American interests shall not bo effected without prior ascertainment of the views of His Majesty's Government 1 * • o^ y, r 4. -• i n j. c incSu 0 not Ballantyno f s words and represent only a rough draft to show the nature of his suggestion. (Reference should bo made in this connexion to &lt;cr*^ India Office letter P.Z.2544/37 of the 20th April 1937; covering Mr. Clauoon’s note of an interview with Mr. Ballantyne on the 14th April, 1937, and to Admiralty letter of the 25th Hay 1937, Ho. M.02525/37. The subject seems to have been pursued no further in 1937 as no subsequent papers can he traced here). ^* £i_ima facie and subject to the views of the local authorities this substitute for Article 5 seems unobjectionable 8. -he Article 7 of our draft is stock form in our drafts and wo should perhaps insist on it. 9. ihe words 'within the Sheikh’s territories' might be add^d after 11 elsewhere' 1 at the end of both sentences of Article 8.t \ f 7471 Wt 23481/P 215 2000 8.38 INDIA OFFICE, Political Department. xiy &lt;/L » r rATi7\T r r ' 'l EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). (N.B. This is an original message, sent by air mail to save telegraphic expense, but intended to be treated on receipt with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. It has been drafted as if it were so despatched.) From To Dated Repeated to !! No. lot C Secretary of State Political Resident in the Persian G-ulf 4th July, 1939. Political Agent, Bahrein Government or India, External Affairs Department P. Z. 4065/39 gUSHlHE nb.SJ DENriv' No ^P.o.6 Date 11.(2/. CONFIDENTIAL RECORDS Please refer to the correspondence regarding the ownership of the Kanar Islands resting with India Office &gt;/$/ 39, dc letter to the Government of Indio, No.P.Z.3693/! ted / the 16th June, and to the enclosed copy of correspondence / with Petroleum Concessions Limited. N If the Government of India concur in the view of His Majesty’s Government that the Hawar Islands helong to the Sheikh of Bahrein please let me have your views (accompanied by a detailed sketch map) as to the line of division which should he drawn between the territories and territorial waters of Bahrein and of Qatar in the area affected. The issue of the above has been duly authorised.Z. 4065/39. ®) PETROLED!:' CONCESSIOKS LIMITED City-Gate Tiouce C. 26/56 Finsbury Square, London, 2.C.2. 30th June, 1939 The Under Secretary of State for India, Whitehall, S. W. 1. Sir, It is uesir^d to recall certain correspondence which paosed oet\;een the India Office and this Cotnpany in 1936 on the suoject of the allegiance or ownership of the Uawar group of islands situated west - and within the territorial waters - of the Qatar Peninsul evidence at present oefore His Majesty’s Government, it appears to them that ITawar belongs to the Shaikh of Bahrain, and that the burden of disproving his claim would lie on any other potential claimant w . A subsequent letter, dated September 14, from Mr. M. C. Clauson to Mr. S.H.Longrigg calls particular attention to ’’the limited nature' of this decision. It says; 'It is important that the Company should clearly understand that His Majesty’s Government’s position is as stated in the last sentence of that letter' (i.e., Mr. Walton’s letter above-quoted) 'namely, that on the basis of the evidence at present before them it appears to them that Hawar belongs to the Shaikh of Bahrain and that the burden of disproving his claim would lie on any other potential claimant. Perhaps you will be good enough to drop me a line to confirm that the Company appreciate the limited nature of the decision given by His Majesty’s Government in regard to this group of islands'. The 2. A letter No.P.Z.4582/56 of July 14th 1936, from i.r. J. C. walton to Mr. J. Skliros states; 'On the basis of the 'TCnd -Company duly confirmed this. 3. In spite, however, of the provisional, or limited, nature of the ruling under reference, it appears that the Hav/ar group have subsequently come to be treated as de facto Bahrain territory; so much so, that both this Company and another have been encouraged to make offers to the Shaikh of Bahrain for a concession to include the Hawar group. It is reported also that the Bahrain Government have recently conducted a survey, built a police post, and otherwise asserted its authority over the islands. “f. j. t might appear from this that the matter is now finally judged and should not be re-opened. That this is not the view of the Ruler of Qatar appears from the following extract from a letter received yesterday from the Company’s Bahrain Manager; ’’When I had an interview v/ith the Shaikh of Qatar on 13th June the subject of Hawar islands arose. The Shaikh put forward quite confident claims to their ov/nership as obviously part of Qatar. He by no means gave the impression that he is not serious in his claims, which is the view usually put forward by the Political Agent He said that he had written three times to the Political Agent v/ithout reply. Incidentally, the Shaikh of Qatar said that he regarded the Hawar islands as included in our Concession and not for disposal to an American Company”. 5. This attitude by the Shaikh of Qatar is entirely spontaneous and no steps whatsoever have been taken by this Company to produce it. The Company cannot, however, be indifferent to it and cannot but hope that it will lead, at least, to an examination of his claims, to which, at first sight, considerable force is given by the extreme- 3 - propinquity of Iiawar to tho coast of Qatar, and its relatively great distance from Bahrain. 6 * I1: ma y 130 ahded that the original negotiator of the Qatar Concession in 1935, Mr.C.C.Mylles, was and remained under the impression that Hawar formed part of the Concession area. v'/hatover rricay he the final ruling adopted regarding the ownership of Kawar, the Company feels it most desirable that sucn ruling should cover authoritatively and in detail tnc distribution of territorial waters and reefs as between Qatar and Bahrain. Our information from Bahrain is to the effect that representatives of that Government are mapping reefs, etc. in waters immediately adjacent to the Qatar Peninsula and which would appear, under any but altogether exceptional circumstances, to belong to the Ruler of Qatar. The fact that the latter has no British adviser and no Political Agent seems to create a certain danger that the Bahrain State - between which and himself very bad relations exist at present - may be encroaching at his expense: which, in the present case, would also be the expense of the Company. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your obedient servant, (Sgd. ) Managing Director.f INDIA OPPICS, V.'HITEHALL, P.Z. 4065/39. LONDON, S.W. 1. 4th July, 1939. I P.m directed hy the Secretary of State for India to refer to your letter of the 30th June, No. PC. 26/56, and to inform you that statements Ly the Sheikhs of Bahrein and Qatar of their respective claims to ownership of the Hawar Islands have recently keen submitted to His Majesty’s Government and that final orders on the subject are expected to be passed in the near future. It is recognised that in the event of His Majesty's Government deciding that the Islands belong to the Sheikh of Bahrein it will be necessary precisely to define the ■ ' — -- - - line of division between Bahrein and Qatar territories in the neighbourhood. I am, Sir, Your obedient servant, (Sgd.) R. : ‘ e Managing Director, Petroleum Concessions Limited, E.C.2.I 86/14 Telegram From To No.T/125 Political Resident, Bushire, at Shiraz* Political Agent, Bahrain. Dated 22nd July 193 9. India Office Express Letter No.P.Z«4065 of 4th July. Hawar. Please let me have your views with sketch map. Fow le86/14 Telegram Q Political Agent, Bahrain* Political Resident, Bushire at Shiraz. From To No.103. Dated and received 24th July lb39 0 Your telegram No.T/125 and my Express Letter No.C/444 July 22nd. It would be difficult to submit considered proposals without an accurate map, and if there is no objection I would like to await the suggested aerial photograph. Political AgentGOVERNMENT OR INDIA *]r/vj Confidential« _ Department. EXPRESS LETTER B, T/ns is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt,' with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To sa&gt; e time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched.] Reference India Office Express Letter No.P.Z.4065/39, dated the 4th July 1939. No maps or charts exist showing the location of the Hawar Islands with any degree of accuracy. It occurred to me that if the Royal Air Force aircraft were coining this year to Bahrain for training exercises as they did in the summer of 1938 they might be able to make a photographic map of the Hawar Islands and the adjacent coast which v/ould not only be immensely useful for the present purpose, but also extremely valuable in future. As the High Speed Launch now in Bahrain aew provides a means of direct communication with A.h.Q. I made an unofficial enquiry and have been informed that photographs could be taken within the next six ^eeks. A.H.Q. have asked for a map of the area to be covered. From Political Agent, Bahrain To Political Resident, Bushire # » C/444-1.a/29 TktUi 2und July JOS / Hawar Islands S. 6. MFP-400S&amp;P—(M 480)—26-7-34-2,00,000. IT// 2 If you approve of this proposal, I would suggest that an official request now be made to A.R.O. for a small scale photographic mosaic of the area shown in red lines on the enclosed sketch map. This sketch map makes no pretence to accuracy and, I think, indicates a far wider area than actually exists. Could A.H.O. be asked to return the sketch map to me in due course, as I have no spare copies ? Political Agent, Bahraint /v cLi c\ Ref «■ 18 &gt; Preamble Art. 1. Art. 2. Art. 3. Art. 4» Art. 5. Art. 6. Art. ?. Art. 8. Art. 9. Art.10. Art.11. » 1 - y tx. P’ L&gt; Vo • P' X. ( 0 II ^ c4,. 1 y/43 ^ ^&amp; ■ »&lt; / ^ Draft Political Agreement. No comment, do. Corresponds to Art. XIV of 1936 Lease. Stronger than Art. XIII of 1936 Lease. No comment. This relaxes in favour of the Coyso far as unimportant or routine matters are concerned, the rigid provisions of Art* XVI of the 1936 Lease* India Office thin* that the local authorities will have to be asked what provisions are considered essential in this Article in the light of their experience. P.A., Bahrain may be consulted. Repeats Art. XVII of Mining Lease. It would be preferable to have the stronger wording of Art* 3 of the Kuwait Political Agreement though it will be difficult to secure this with a wholly American Coy. No comment. This is for the Services. India Office axe consulting the Admiralty ♦ No comment* Secures pre-emption. Explained in para 3 of India Office letter of 30th May to Foreign Office. - //# - Ref. 19 /Ref « 19 » ft* /iL Draft Concesaion Agreement idxcept for the changes suggested in India Office letter of 30 th May to the Foreign Office, tills is technical and commercial* Mo comment on our part appears to he called Mr* Ballantyne’s draft which we have received from the India Office was *for the consideration* 1 of his princi pals in Bahrain*** The latter have made substantial alterations in it and what we will have to work on now is the Bahrain draf t, of which the Shaikh approves and on which he has formally so^jt the advice of Political Agent has commented in detail* Preamble. India Office are aware of the definition distinguishing between the Shaikh*s'•present** and his “future possessions and have suggested an amended definition* (The Shaikh himself has not objected)* for. 2 . 0 . y. L. n!o ■ C|yifc. | 0 |I4, d • I°| *»| id . intention in drafting the document in the form of a supplementary deed* Article 1* May agree with Political Agent* Art. 2 &amp; 3* The India Office object to aArt* 4*. May agree with Political Agent - Art* 5* Ditto* Art* 6* Mo comments* Art* ?* Ditto. Art* 8* Ditto* Art* 9* It is difficult to follow P*A f s arguments* I cannot see how the *lofcal agreement* regarding gas referred to can effect the proportion of oil processed» which is laid down as one half up to a maximum ( not minimum ! of 20,000 (or 25,000 barrels) a day* The deduction for the purposed of royalty accounting appears to be altogether another question. Similarly it seems to me that the expression l, 20,000 (or 25,000) barrels daily* expresses a max imum and that it does not debar the Coy* from varying as might suit it seasonally the proport ions of Saudi and Bahrain oil processed provided that the proportion of one half Bahrain Oil (up to the stipulated maxi mum of 20,000 or 25,000 barrels) ia maintained in the year's working* If this view is correct the Coy* do not require to make the variation that the P*A. thinks they may claim. / Art* 10*Art* 10* This is not in Ballantyne f 3 draft and has doubtless been inserted at the instance of the Shaikh* ft lol* . /$. /ufA#. &amp;f, /? . bf. ^ „, yX • hz-Xknx?- /o /ssc^z X-L./Se. 'Sis xj. a Arf.a .fiU* -itt}'* { . h 7 0 F.L. /Vo . I°Z. W* i- 1^1^ ■ 'fb^^ X.L.~\&gt;o . 30 /V3? Ref*21* Formal authorisation from the Govt* of India may be awaited ? Ref * 22 * Para 2. The pre-emption schedule appears to cover the points raised by P*A# but this is a point for the Coy* and the Petroleum Dept, to settle and it does not appear necessary for us to raise it* Para 3 (Art*l) /36/14 Para &gt; (Art.l)* We may include this point in our comment to IUM.G* If the concession for the additional area is signed then the words 'or may here inafter obtain'in the Pre amble of the draft Political Agreement and the whole of Article 1 thereof will be rendered unnecessary* (Art*2) The adoption of P.A*s suggestion would mean that ^ ax. J.bid . Mr* Ballantyne would step out of the picture and that all communications between ^ the Coy. and H.M.G. will have to pass through P.A. &amp; P.R. The present arrangement has been working satisfactorily for years and the change suggested by P*A* would in volve a good deal of addit ional work at Bahrain and Bushire. The balance of 4' £jL advantage appears in con tinuing the present system. (Art.5) P.A. agrees with yout comment. (Art.8) While the additional ppowioe confers no benefit at present, it may be useful in the future. We may say so in our comment. After / /S-T- 70 - h jul</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x00029a_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/692</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x00029a</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/692</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'B. 56. Confidential 86/14 - v. BAHRAIN UNALLOTED AREA.'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1939/1939</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-06-09T12:06:45</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (251 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 253; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 6-241; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled, and are located in the same position as the main sequence. A previous foliation sequence, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The volume comprises correspondence between the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf (Trenchard Craven Fowle), the Political Agent at Bahrain (Hugh Weightman), the India Office (Roland Tennyson Peel, John Percival Gibson), the Secretary to the Government of India, External Affairs Department (Sir Aubrey Metcalfe), the Shaikh of Bahrain (Shaikh Ḥamad bin ‘Īsá Āl Khalīfah), Bahrain Petroleum Company (Hamilton R Ballantyne, Fred A Davies, Max W Thornburg), and Petroleum Concessions Limited (Frank Holmes, John Skliros) regarding the Shaikh of Bahrain’s proposal to grant a concession for the whole of the unallotted area, including the Hawar Islands, to the Bahrain Petroleum Company and His Majesty’s Government’s approval of the proposal.Following on from the approval of the proposal to grant a concession to the Bahrain Petroleum Company (BAPCO) the correspondence focuses on discussion around the proposed agreement, to take the form of a deed of modification to BAPCO’s 1934 lease and the political agreement which would accompany the concession. The main areas of discussion including the definition of the area the concession would cover, and the need to include a pre-emption clause in the political agreement. Copies, in Arabic and English, of the draft deed of modification (ff 146-161, 170-180, 218-227) and draft political agreement (ff 133-139) are included in the volume.Also discussed in the volume is the conclusion of the sovereignty question relating to the Hawar Islands following the submission by the Shaikh of Qatar (Shaikh ‘Abdullāh bin Jāsim Āl Thānī) of a response to the counter-claims made by the Shaikh of Bahrain. On reviewing both claims and supporting evidence His Majesty’s Government's final decision was that islands belonged to Bahrain and not Qatar.Also included in the volume are copies of draft concession agreements put forward by Petroleum Concessions Limited including one for the Hawar Islands (ff 8-26) and one for the waters and islands of Bahrain, described as the shoal area (ff 44-65).A series of file notes which were maintained as a record of the correspondence in the volume can be found at folios 242-248</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Bahrain Petroleum Company</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>India Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Petroleum Concessions Limited</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Agent</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Indian Political Service, Secretary to the External Affairs Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>King of Bahrain</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Emir of Qatar</namePart></name></subject><subject><geographic>Hawar Islands</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Bahrain</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Concessions, Oil, Bahrain</topic></subject><subject><topic>Territorial disputes</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x00029a#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>