<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000517.0x00035b_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-20T03:42:12.328Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">( 5 ) 27th April 1943. k.y dear r*Qonnor, ^ ony thanks for your letter of the 26th April end or in copy of t paragraph in the 'Sunday despatch' of 25th April. This stupidly \ inaccurate use of your name is an example of very unintelligent anticipation. I am paasinr on your letter to eel in the India Office. Tours sincerely, (-d.) J.G .Walton. Tir Frederick n*?onnor, CSI., CIE., CVO.d&gt; 56 Glebe Place Chelsea S. W. 3. 3rd May 19^^ Ext. 2246/42 Dear Mr Peel, Many thanks for your letter of th the 20th April and for sending a copy of iny letter about the para in the Sunday Dispatch to the a:propraate authorities in the Home Office. I have also asked my Solic tor to get the paper to publish a dementi which I hope they will do next Sunday. j.here was some delay as my Solicitor hajpens also to be the paper's but he now says he will fix it up. Yours sincerely l.T.Peel Esq, CBE, MC. India Office. \DRAFT LETTER T. Uathew, Esq., Home Office, n S'lp* 1 ^ ^ V !&lt;§&amp;*, hlxtLuJ' M e&gt; ^EXT 2246 1 B ft APf mi 194 3 j ■ , ^ / ^*K I enclose a copy of a letter from Sir Frederick 0 f Connor regarding the ineeiro*c»«t association of his name with the case of the Reverend Basil V/illiams in a recent Sunday paper. Sir Frederick was connected vrith us here in the days when he was the British Envoy ^at Nepal, which is his reason for addressing the India Office now. 9 cCc kH Tkci 1 ^ ir I Imp! sure little that you can U.~ £V»w U&lt; ^ do to rut watturii rirtht. but i t- waJ 1 &gt;tn douht s^tiof^r. hi in tn l-mniv that his nMjartj. ^mv-e-beon. brought to notice in the right quarters. I am writing to tell him that I am paoolng on a oopy of his—letter to ymn &lt;*€*.) H. zxj</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000517.0x00035b_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/816</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000517.0x00035b</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/816</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Ext 2246/43 Sir Frederick O'Connor'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1943/1943</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-05-22T14:00:25</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (6 folios)</extent><extent>The file's contents are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 8; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file comprises correspondence between Roland Peel to Sir William Frederick Travers O’Connor regarding the reference to O’Connor in an issue of the Sunday Dispatch. The Sunday Dispatch relates O'Connor to the case of Reverend Basil Williams. O’Connor asks the India Office to take action over the inaccurate use of his name in the newspaper.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="personal"><namePart>Sir Knight William Frederick Travers O'Connor</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000517.0x00035b#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>