<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0001c5_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T06:32:28.601Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">I ^e&lt;i. , T (y Oo . ^ COM?IDEaTl|L t _ ._Jjdj[]'~. 0f 1915 •' 'cOWiOtMrui fitCOfiDl - ' , camp XVII, ■ -v-——J-. - ! Central Arabia. Froiti, Captain W.H.I. Shalcespear, I,A., political Offjuer on special Duty. TP, The Political Resident in th^ Persian Gulf, BASFAE . 4th January 1915. sir, |,r ■ JJl I In continuation of my letter No 3-7 da tea ?th jjocera- -ber l'll from KuFa..t I have the honour to report that, leaving Kuwait on tne i3th D^ceiRb^r, I AMuJ. Ae.is 'Bin Saud'^' c £.ap on the Sist ijeceinto-'-r 3.014, The A^lr*9 last lettor had led rie to expect hi ; n to be nearer Kuwait, but poor ^razin^ north of 9 the D ah ana and the presence of a large force coiapelled hi .a to o . o ca^ip at Ki;.ufsa ? atom Lat -G. %'&gt;* 5, Long '.3. 35 1 E) and entail- -cl iipon a jcnrriey of .yap nllen. t was received very cordially o, r 'Bin saud' and his hr^ther^ and net nany friends •&gt; ' -■ i' f Vt v i' x ' 2. Crtr ioTi' ''.l.l tica i ^l.tnat' on. it '71.11 he of interest to note- htu that the atMtn.le of eentr?' i.rabl, f*o far as I an guB ge a v. Is tc j iMM .It In t.hle aann, is very eynnathetlc towards C^Tyhu, Great Britain, anta^oni^aic to Gar r-ny and one of hatred coi'iibind \ -ed v /ith a oeni'3 of relief and a hope that at last the rna china- -tiono of the Ox-uonan Government In ITeir! may come to an end. There ia unaffected rejoicing at the British successes in Basreh an.v Guma,. ■■■htle not a trace of fanatical spirit adverse to Great Britain is visible. By far the most potont factor, other than the personal predilections of the Anlr aivl his fa nly. jn A. • producing this favourable result in Fahabi Arabia has been the British Proclamation regarding the Holy Places. I was informed by some who were present that Abdul Aislz 'Bin saud' had the 7; -clamation read out at one of his 'Majlis' in Buraidah when/h @ lar^e number of his notables vere present, conimentine on it as much proof ci Dritisn sincerity and drawln£; comparisons/to our advan- -tage bstv/een tne Govexnaient v .liica, though of another faith, v.x-; pre earocl to bin.*, its ell by such a pioclariiation and one; wiii ch hed ccnti.racily it? Biib^ects, though of its own faith, ana attempted to proclaim a H Jihad' while allying iiBelf to an- -otho:„ ch ietian ovvto:, i cfn s^y vith sjshu ranee that a reli^- -lous war, as hoped lor by t-h© Cwtoman Govermient has no support -trs in Cental '-'Hln scuc.' ii.r^-lf hae already practical -ly imprisoned a Turlils?j o.ericrr in Jiasa, voir, to him to h-Ip train his iico. v. fyr Ihe ^r .j rjid is keeping icur Uleraa at Burai- -dsh i.n what :aay be •l«sciloed ae ho no u.:M: a: ccnflneirent . These iour *'-n aie 01 tnt? »*■ am-li coct, leBi^crte of Baghdad or Kerb^la rnic. wero seuu i;/ rurL..s a luid lo preach a ! Mih.ui'. it will &amp;. evident irom x-o,^ ale re Vaat the ^v R' jzl 1 situation pcllt- -icaiiy throughout 11 Bin Saud 5 territories is as favourable to Great Britain as cau je ;;v.sired. c ;a:np -?iffl t ' ^ n ii? .5.:^. .1 ', lief ore proceeding to deal with 'Bin Saucrs' relations with the i^ri tlsh Gov .rnment it vill be Vvtll to cleai the ground by explaining nis present re- -lations with his neighbours. 'Bin Stud' in eorunon with all oth -ci Arab Chiefs received repeated requests Jro:a the Sublime Porte tc proclaim a 'Jinad' against the Brit _sh # Tin oart as- -signc:' to hia was the protection Odd defence of Basrah and Baghdad from any British advance in Lower Mesopotamia, 'ibn Rashid' was to have joined forces with the Rov.aia (Anaizah), ro ■(.itat, Bani Salchr, Shcrrrat and other western tribes near pp the Fediaz Pailwsy anf cved on the Sinai Tenineula and Egypt, while the Sharif of Mecca, the inrr: Yahyah and the Say id idrisi were to have sr cured the Red Sea littoral and defended the Holy places and other tot .ns aid ports in Yemen and fiedjaz. The plan idscarried for tne same reasons that the attempt to provofc* a ■'■Jihad' has failed the Ottoman Government failed to ta'Ke in- ~to account the irritation its policy for the past five years has reduced in Uraeia, failed to form** that combined action between the tribes would be impossible without some more or3 ^ T Xes^ laitlllf 00^*1 tlOA of tnoix feuds, enraitlejs and jealous- -ies and failed to realise that religious er^nuslacn could not do invoked on the fllmay pretexts it advsnced. The result has been tnat the Chiefs consulted each other before moving and apparently came to the conclusion that it would he lore profit -able to await events thar^tsice up the TurXleh cauLe. 'Bin Baud', the Sharif of Mecca and the Sheilchs of the great Anal- j -zah tribe in Korthcn. i.rabia c.c cided to holo together and re- -main in constant ccnuriunlcation . 'Bin scud' and 'Ibn Rashid' he ving had been on bad terms rince the sunvner and the former,deci -ided xo open hostilities as soon as the season permitted, ap- -prised the Analzah ahalKhs in the jorth of his intentions and o'ot.alnod a x-ronlsa of their su pon liiz$ 'Von Kashid n . 4, Au the same time he informed the Turkish Government •uhct be mi; at feud wlih ' r lbn Kashicx' it was impossible for him j 'oo iiivve Lorth for li.e projection of Mesopotamia, leaving Bejd c :-en to ctinc , unles?- a ia until''Ibn Ra^hid' moved on E&amp;ypt, Laving thus founc: a legitimate excuse for taking no action lixe -1/ to conilict with British intentions in IraK, 'Bin saud' set 1 vbcui nis prepaiatioLS for a campaign against 'ibn Rashld' for thi double purpose of keeping him from any advance Egyptwards j c^.i carrying out his original lan to crush him. 'Ibn Rashid' 4 w r ' \-f' ;/ f&gt; Q « * J 1 x v j wx » Jl j „ .j t/.j. i t, t;.-i3 a io freouant dissensions ofcliOLon nis 11'loss a no no nas not tnt povv&lt;©j to control ohem, f ,i 115 ..o2-i o.: thoi have ootaaily tiansfoned tneir allegiance to 'Bin Si *d N , ''Bin saio ?t naa collected at this camp some socc' to 4of his tovvnsmen, has the vfaole of the Umtair and Aj- -man Be-io-nn trib38 within call and has issued orders for an- -o cher 4000 Do^nsmen to Join nis standards within the next fe^ dsys. His preparations are on a seal© he has not attempted sinew Xvll ( ;) 'Aiofi the Sharif of Mecca at TurKish instigatior mace his incursion into Wa^nam. He will move within the weeK and hooee to flai and crush ■Ibn Hashid' before the end of Jan- -uary, unless one latter has moved westwards, in which case nev plans will have to be mao.e.A ms.:lng matters either easier for uj* or ciore difficult for t )0 Turl-CB bo far as the present war lr&gt; concerned, until h obt'.lnB in that Treaty so:.io v ry no lid guar-nteo of nip .edition v/itn Greet Britain practically ae his Suz- rain. Granted this, he can X) ■ j'- lied upon to use ell his re.Hour cob and iavmoe influ not only -ence in Arabia on our aide/in the prenent war but aft rver-is and to continue 3ft ar its conclusion to have no dealing a v .ith any other Foreign ?ower ••vithout first conunleating alth us. Ho I) _a for Uio earliest possible decision for already his neutral a ition aibaraases him considerably with the Turlca am failing a very early coap ehensiv agreement 1th us he rast in self-defence and to avoid reprisals give eons praoticI areof of his Intentions to side '.1th the Turl^s. There i. no threat implied in this for f bitter hatred of the Turks is al.-oat an obsorei n ;ith Abdul Aaiz but he recognizes that failing Bri- -tisn arotection he ust aa peace eith his en y p.m. at once prove hi *,elf a friend — for him there is no half-way house, I venture to submit that 'Bin Saud' in ef ect z acs far little ore than 'tiat ha a already been conv yea in th&lt; Acting Resident's assurances, if those were leant to a:&gt;piy t: th fu- -turc and re not Halted to the -.resent crisis, ana \f they are int -raret^d liberally and generously, in -^xchance 'Bin Saud' offers to malce hiaioelf a British vassal for coed , The addition to our responsibilities does net a pear heavy:— (a) The Tuiacish menaces from the ^ est and north of :a?aje, though very real to Bin saud, need give ur no anxiety— we have no :r- a son to su pose they ill be ore succesc- -ful in th i future than they have been ithi n the i ; t t a or three decades, while guaranteed fro a attac'a by sea 'Bin saud' will be In a far better position to icet thorn than ?-?as ossible hitherto; hould th y become thr atoning, strong diplomatic re pre r en t a t io ns v/ould probably suffice to prevent any attempt on a scale -ith 'hioh'Bin Saud' could not cope hi .self, (b) We should pro! / be called upon to act as arbit ia: some-hat mor frequently than hitherto b t-en the A .r: j snslXIie along the coast and'3 ln a ^ j ' Ilargely to tno vantage of our own inter cts # On the other hnnd tno ecv^nt^^es so--, i to be concidersble; — {*) Complete control of the Arabian littoral of the PerBian GUlf. (b) Similar corrpi te control of the Anns Traffic. (c) The practicel exclusion of Foreign Powers and influ- -once in Central Arabia , „ '.I (cl) The security Induc^.cl by British Suzerainty and'nin Sam's j t:tron^ control of the BedouiP. tribes will give a groat i-tpetus to tr*:ee through the peroian Gulf -ports, pro- -brbly diverting a nharc of -hat no acres through the Red Sea o tr», (e) The influ nee 'Bin Saud' hae over Mahomedan o -in- -ion in Arabia, an inlfuencc li':eiy to increase a« the Turkish K'-ii-ire brcaicr. up anc- the Khali fate of t-Uffi! 11 the sultan euaationed, will b' - a British asset, (f) 'Bin saud , » n influ-n,ce* rrith all Arab tribes and partio- -ularly --'ith the Northern Anaizah , ith whom our oc- -cupation of I.c er Mesopotamia v /iil bring us in close contact. 10. Kha lif a ts f inl m. Havjrir rcferrc' to the Khalifate of I si 8 n above perha s it i?iil be as well, to explain that we has: little n -ed to f^ar an attempt on the art of 'Bin Baud' or his family to arrogate this title. The Wahabis only acknowledge the first four rChalifs and rr subsequent ones, in a conversation r'.th 'Bin Baud' I gather e that ir.ost Arabs other than ahabis rnd probably also .lost Mah :edans ftr.d their faith in the Khali- -fat' of the sultan s verely shaKe^n by the. circumstences of Abdul Kanld 1 s :er oaition and :,:ahoied He ahad's accession. The Arabs no a anticipate a similar revolution ;lth Mahoraed. Reshad ar&lt;^ Suver ? aha as the rincipals and shouia it cone to pass that the latt r becomes Sultan the opinions I hear expressed indicate that the Khali fate will by the comcion consent of islam revert / ■ / to the descendants of the Prophet's family in 'scca , of whom the re ent head is the Sharif and who I feel sure would com- -mand 'Bin ssud's' support in such an event rather than his an-. ' v CONFIDK- T TIAL. *) No.Of. 5?- of 1915. British Residency and Consulato-Grenoral. Bushire, M-t January 1915. From - Liout-Colonel S.G.Knox, C.I.E., Officer On Spocial iiuty. { In the absence of the Resident). Persian Gulf. To The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, Foreign and Political Department, DELHI . i Sir, I have the honour to forward for the information of the Government of India, a copy of the marginally cited No .S -13 dated 4th January 1915 ,(0 letter on the subject of from Captain Shaicespear to Hesi-j dent. jj 'Bin oaud' and his atti- ! tude towards His Britannic -ajesty's Government. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant, Lieut-Colonel On Special Duty. ( In the absence of the Resident}Telegram. R. Prom Oox Basrah. To Foreign. No. 167-B. Dated 29.1.15. Further communication received from Captain Shake spear datefl 16th January. On that date Bin Saud had 6,000 townsmen own and A3man Umtair Harb tribes of Bedouin with 700 townsmen and a large force of Shamar tribesmen was at some wells 25 miles distant. Bin Saud was expected to move camp 15 miles towards him and then attack. General belief was that a victory for Bin Saud was certain. Oox. ■s&gt; 0 A ^i ■ f ■ I(11) COHFI.'Dl r »I:TIAL NO of Camp XXI, Central Arf-blu. From, | Rtc df-fy- Captain Shakespear* I # A« f | ^ . ' -'7rnT*'^i r=^v lOtN i Political Officer on s^ol'r.I Duty, To, The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, BASRAH . i5th January A 15, With reference to oar a S» of my letter No S-.13 dated the 4tn J .iriu: ry w5 j. a.- . Vo tne li* noiir to re ort thf t th four por- -Bona pant by the Tur IXn a.u tar Titles to pru oh a w Jlhr.fi arrlv -ed In 'Bin 3.0 ua'■' of p on th« iSth Instant. 3, After : y la.^t .ettor lad b on c ! snatched Abdul Aziz 'Bin Saud' consulted le rm to what was to b done v, t uh 11K' e four , awaiting him in Burai^ ah. He sc id th?-t ' s they cer- -talnly carried lett rs from the Porte he vould ha.ve to ree thera . ooner or inter an-, an til h: d :.d sec them ho could not e:&lt;- -aotly ascertain tlieir mission, I agreed that no object ooulrl be us. ved by 1 :aving taem Indefinitely in Buraidah , where they Might find o:por'GUiiity for Intrigue; he accordingly had them summoned to his camp, 'S, On arrival the deoutotion proved to cons'.st of three Ul-ma, waiiabis re si dorr; in Baghdad, who had been fore a by Dja/id P: aha to form the de utation much against their will anr were Instructed to pr ach a 'Jihad'; the f urth a- -bar proved to be Haji Dakar Bey, a Major in the Turkish Army, a Kurd from ioaui district by oirth and an adherent of th' Committoe party in politics; nis duty ostensibly was the instruction of 'Bin 3aud f s' Arabs in the art of mod m ?/ar but his real da si on war that of apy on the other members of the de utation. The depu- - tat ion left iJa^hda i immediatc-ly after the Britl'h occupation ox Basrah and travelled via Da lascus .rid the Hedjaz Hall ay toMedina snu tnenco to x3u :r -idah. They brought with then color of the 'Fatwa' issued by the SheiKh al-i«lam In Ccnrtantinopl enjoining a religious war and were instructed to brin^ about I?eace between ''Bin Saud' and 'Ibn Ranhicl', inducing then to move trelr combined forces against the British troops in Mer- -opotcTiia, i enclose a copy of the rocii; :nt u- on htch in my pre pence and b fore c 'ra^lis' of his headm n 'Bin Saud' Co; ■•-^nted cauftlcaily and particularly on the fact trrt though issued by the supposed head of islam to other Moslems It cid not b ar even the usual i nci neco; sary superscription 'B^sm Allah ar-Rahman ar -Rahim' # The deputation after two days in camp ere dismissed and 1-'ft yesterday on their return to Bur- -aldah and Medina, -Ith the intimation that 'ibn Ha 'hie' havin,- b en located with a large hostile force within t'vo days* march peace betw en the two Arab chiefs war impo risible, 4, It will be of interest to add that the her a of the de utation was say id r 'ahmud Sha'ri Alusi, a weil-^no n Alim of Baghdad. f, Bin Saud w informed ;.ic? that in a private conversation with the sayid the latter ex- ressed bitter condemnation of the TurKs and said that the people of Baghdad would gladly v^ioone freedom fro'. Turkish misrule; ho would gladly hf-vc met --c but the -presence of the Turlcish officer nac.:e any intercourse impose- -ible and he feared reprisals on his fa mily in Ba^hc ad should $ the British troops not have already occupied the city b fore the return of the deputation. 5. A copy of this letter is be ng sent direct to Sir Per- -cy Cox at Basrah and another to the Residency at Bushire, I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most ob client servant. Political Officer on Special Duty.TliLSGiiA: I. Prom - 3ir ?. aox,Basrah. To - Poreigr^DelM. I mo . KG-B,dated the ?Ath February 1915. Your tele ^am 235-D.3. Regarding treaty 31n Baud writes asking either that another Officer be deputed,or onat negotiations / be continued by correspondence direct froin Basrah and not via Kuwait. The posiGion in Oantrai -j-y.bia is this. Bin Saud claims to have altLnauely defeated Bin Rashid, but independont reports are to the effect that both parties lost heavily and each has retired to his headquarters,the for-ner to Buraidan and the latter to Flail. They are hardly likely to indulge in hostili ties again for some tiue to come. I would propose now to send him the draft treaty which was a- aiting despatch through Shake spear, together with Viceroy's letter. In doing so I would advise him to li^n it without d lay and say that as soon as it is completed an officer can to mwk then be a jpu&amp;ed to discuaj details of the second treaty. Even if he will not sign without further dis cussion,wo sha ll hi v ure advantage of Imowing in what direction^ his objections lie before deputing another officer, ^hen the tine comes Colonel Grey or i can go as may be .most convenient at the moment. Cox. &amp; .. /' r iy No 3/Jot 1915. Politioal Agenoy, Kuwait. B'JSHlFif RFS^D^NCY ^ ■p I , r' 1 UV ' I ! jr s///- /^r Lt-Golonel W. G-rey, I. A, , COf .rldln i U l T e S os T ' Politioal Agent, Kuwait, The Politioal Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Dated Kuwait, the 29th June 1914 Sir, Some six weeks ago a party of the Shammar tribe from the S.E^of the desert traot known as the Nafud in N.Central Arabia raided, in Kuwait territory, about four hundred oamels and other property belonging to the inhabitants of Shagra in Nejd. H.E.Sir Mubarak thereupon wrote to Ibn Rashid the Shammar Chief, aooording to the usual Arab custom, asking him, in virtue of the traditional friendship existing between them, to recover the stolen animals etc. 2, A translation of Jbn Rashid f s reply is attached. Besides announcing definitely the political position of the writer and shewing his disinclination to help Sir Mubarak in the matter at issue it confirms the information given in para 7 of my letter No 318 dated the 9th instant regarding the recent fighting be- -tween Ibn Rashid and Bin Sa'ud. There is no doubt whatever that the Shammar would have joined the Turks had they not been other- -wise engaged, and our thanks for their absence hitherto from the ranks of our enemies are due Sir Mubarak who suggested the A policy which kept them employed, and to Bin Sa'ud who carried it out. It is not clear from Ibn Rashid's letter whether or no he ex- -peots early orders from the Turks to take any action on their behalf, but he will before this have received news of the fall oJ Amarah which will presumably affect the views of the Shammar. But as regards ourselves this tribe have now to their account From Toin addition to the death of Captain Shakespear the fact that they have committed robbery on an unusually large soale in the territories of our vassal and ally Shaikh. Sir Mubarak, and should it be considered advisable at some future date to assist Bin Sa'ud to reassert his lawful authority over Hai-i and the surrounding country, we have apparently sufficient reasons foi undertaking to support his cause in a practical manner. 4, Oooies of this letter and its enclosure are being sent to Basrah♦ I have the honour to be Sir, 5 i , Sir, your most obedient servant,, Lt-G.oJ-onel ,y^'7 - Political Agent, Kuwait.From Sa'ud bin Rashid to H.E.Sir Mubarak bin Subah, dated 30th Rajab 1333 (13th June 1915). Aft e r oomp1iment s, I am well by G-Qd's grace, and the letter brought by your •man Saif has arrived. With regard to the oamels and booty whioh you say the Shammar took - I am to hear that, at this X time there is no reason for such an act. Know this, that I follow the Sublime G-overnment and await their orders in everyfek -thing, and I will not take part in any affair whioh threatens the interests of the Sublime G-overnment. You speak of former friendship but you have no^? carried out it's incumbent duties outwardly you are friendly, but inwardly an enemy, the wise yx man is his own advocate, and you know the articles of friend- -ship, and salaam. ■^He -affects not to believe that the raid took place. ^Meaning that Sir Mubarak could convince himself of the truth of the accusation If he wished.views regarding the military plans to be adopted; which oomprise the evacuation of Hofuf by the majority of* Bin Saud's troops, the defehce o± the neighbouring date gardens, and later an attack upon the AJ nan Trom th^ee sides simultaneously, It is to be hoped that Bin Sa'ud will follow this advice which seems to be sound, in view of the numbers of the opposing forces and the im- —pending arrival of support from two directions. His Excellency has no longer any confidence in Bin Sa'ud as a military leader, 4. Referring to Bin Sa'ud's letter to Major Keyes on this subjeci Sir Mubarak informs me that the following statements are untrue, and I have no evidence whatever to support them (1), That the friendship of Bin Sa'ud with the British was the reason for A,bu Dhabi helping the Araif. (2) . That there is friendship between the Ajman and the (3) « That Bin Rashid has sent the Ajman any Turkish money. The Ajman are merely regarded as rebels against Bin Sa 'ad whose authority they ori-^iru.ll-y recognise, S. A copy of this letter is being sent to Basrah and another to the Political Agent, Bahrain, for information. Turks. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, political Agent, Kuwait.9 Telegram en ol• (proper names in R) Prom Cox Kut No.R 216• 6 Kovember 1915 7 From letters intercepted and sent by Bin Saud to Bahrain it is olear that in spite of warning Shaikh Abu Ohabi has been assisting Bin Saud's enemies. Now states that one of Araif named Salman having escaped after a defeat by Bin Saud has fled and will tale refuge with Shaikh Abu Dhabi, We need to secure hia surrender if poss - ible. In what waj? do you think we can best punish Hamdan for his conduct ? Is ship available to sand there T Addressed Trevor,repeated Holland for communis cation to Bin Mendil with reference to Basra No,2745 B, Cox. /t Telegram en cl. (proper names in R) To Cox Kut,repeated Basra departmentally No.69S C, 7/11/15 Your R 316. Ro difficulty about sending ship if situation remains same# Shaikh Abu Dhabi is also reported to have been playing the fool at Shargah recently and threat ©ning to make coalition against ^ Jowasim Shaikhs and I have just sent hira wrning about this. I mentioned to Commodore the other day that no ship had been seen in those parts for a long time and one might go there soon • Trevor .i. ci 1 0 r*3/Iii a J^n • O J- • i^roiti - Cox, Aziziyah. To - Trevor, Bushira. No.R.361. Da t ad 13 bri r e o e i v 9 d 14 th N o v embe r 1915, You 1 693-u. ■viiat punishment can you suggest for (c) : Shaikh Abu Dhabi (Harndan)'as deterrent. Gox. Telegrara. En. ol. From - Trevor, Bushire. To - Gox, Aziziyah. No,1271. Dated 16-11-15. C'S' i Your R.06I. It is difficult to know what punish™art except fine is possible. If Gs -(Shaikh Abu Dhabi 1 s)guest is now with him again, perhaps if 0 =( .haikh A.D.) were obliged to give him up and he were sent to India for deten- would tion this would suffice as it/deal severe blow to Cs (Shaikh A.Dhabi's) prestige. Possibly G (he) might be called upon to contribute towards entertainment of his guest while in India as he is so keen on entertaining the man in spite of warnings, Trevor. tiTele^rarr.. ol. From - O ok, a. T.H. { through Basrah). Io - ire/or, Bushira. l^o .R-433 . uated 18th reoei/ed 19th November 1915. Your telegram 1271^if you can arrange with Commodore for a ship to prooeei there, please write a snorter to Shallqn Ahu 0haBi somewhat on following lines if you agree oallxng attention to his insincere protestations in reply to our re- 3^ Sa~*'s ' monstances and his mischievous interference in 'sfc^r. ai fairs in a way hostile to our friend and to Pritish interest, tell him his conduct is being reported to Government and if he wishes to palliate his conduct he had better hand over refugee to H.k's ship . CoxjuiL. No •Of • 3^3 Of 1915. ritish iieai ienoy and Conaulstte-i eneral, Buahire, 19th No camber 1915. Sir, ih3 ...;iuikh ci* /Vtu iJhabi, iiarndun bin Zaid having in spite of ^/^rnir £: b ani his own protestations to the contrary a^ain r ischie-yotssly i rterf are.l with the affairs of Shaikh Abdul Aziz Mr 'aud, t-'0 r of liejd, and assisted his enemies, Sip '^'eroy Gox has lireoted me to £i/e him a sharp warning. It is probal le that twb relatives of Bin ^aud who are enarrdes of his, ra&lt; ? i Salman and Fahad A1 Araif ha'/e again taken refuse with ...ariar, although he has declared he would never give theiri refuse a^ain, i an therefore in aooordanoe with :.'ir ^eroy 0 ox * e instruction writing u severe letter to the Shaikh of Abu Dhabi and irforning his hir that he has broken his promises to me and abused/position as a :..haiKh ui ier the protection of the British Government, and that such offerees are grave ani must be reported to Government: in the msanwhile if he wishes to palliate hi3 conduct he should forthwith har.d over the refugees if they are with him, it ivcul I carry more weight 1* this letter could be taken down by ore c p Is .:hips If you can spare one ^or the .job. it would show that ve are really in earnest, and it will at the sai-e t i' e five 4^' ar opportunity to send the A1 Arai. away &lt; ^ straight off ]f he is also in earnest. if then a s ip can be detailed for this purpose, I beg that one may : i ordered to proceed, when convenient, with the letter first to Shargah and there take^i on board 'Chan rahadur Aha Commodcre, Persian Gulf, H a hi. , O , * J uno M • at j,. ushire. -Abdul 1iNO. —' Ox' 1 15. British Residency and Consulate-General Bushire, November 1915. ■f 6 To Jhaikh of Abu Dhabi• x am exoeedin ly surprised, to learn x'ro n letters inter cepted by his Honour Bin 3aud and sent to His Honour Sir Percy Cox in Xraq that in. spite ox - .earnings you have received and of your own protestations made in your letter^ dated 25th ■ - been mischievously interfering in ^in jaud's affairs and assist- j • b O Saud, Salman ^1 Araif had fled away with the intention of taking refuge with you. I no.v enquire if you have again given him an , - , out of ruspect for which Bin 'aud does not send a force to crush you. uch oxS-'ences are grave and it is ruy duty bo report , L mean, •vitlx the QOi i: iOdore ox' his . ..aj 3st.-•- ' s ^mps in tiie u-u.^.f to send a s .i to your port with t is letter^ and I l.&lt;ave bo i- .. oj ' yo i that if you .vish to palliate your conduct, and if the aforemen tioned salr-ian Al Araif or any of his relatives are with you, yov l;ad be t ■ yr ad o ver these refugees to the Captain of .. ' ? Ship. I strongly advise you to do this. Thib io what had to be said and may you be preserved. Deputy political ReoiienL,.'ersian jxu ... , ajor,ij l. t&lt; 3 r*» liritinh ii0Gi:i3nc5.' and Oorsulate-Gen^ral, Bus hire, 20 th o/ember , 191^. i'o Khan Bahadur Atlul Latif, Shar f. sih. Jr\ • 0 • S i r t-'jrcy J ox nas learnt with aatonishment trough letters intercept 3d hy Bir Saud, that Shaikh Hamiar 'bin Zaid iq ptlll a:-sis uir^ ^^1 Araif, in nvite or hie protestatiors, further T ^e Q froni ■-'he Bahra-in reports that Sctlman A1 Araif has 'been defeated ar I 'l3'i and is going to Abu Dhabi- by now he is probably there, 1 ha/e. .iccordingly arranged with the CoTnmodore to send a man- of.- -/ar to ai/u ^habi • 7ith a xetter to Shaikh Harodan 9 of* which T annex a copy I'ecc^ mending him if he wishes to palliate his offen ce, re should send the Araif on board the ship. i ha70 arranged vith the Commodore that the ship should call , you au ohargah and take/along to Abu Dhabi, /hen there you can take t^e letter ashore and explain matters to Shaikh Hamdan. Please do your best to make him understand that the matter is most serious. I** he ii i not enjoy Pritish protection Abdul Azi 7 would na73 sent an expedition against him and smashed Mrn, It Is only because he is on friendly ter^s with the Pritish Go/ernment that he loes Aot do this. Cb-rjously the British Go7ernment cannot permit this abuse o^ its protection, by which a protected Shaikh harbours and assists the enemies of the Go/ernment's friends, anc l_2S9 3 a base for their operations. He should therefore hand orer these Araifs. They will not be illtr-mted and will probably lire in comfort somewhere, only thev will not be allowed to intrigue against Bin Saud. if Hamdar. bin Zaid ioes not hand o/er these men, it will be the worse for him. lie has no excuse as he was warned and pro mised not to harbour them. (Sd) A.P.Tr6 7or, Ma jor, Deputy Political Resident, Persian Gul ^.From Lt-Colonel W.G.Grey, I.A., Political Agent, Kuwait. No C 37 of 1915. Political Agency, Kuwait, To The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Dated Kuwait, Koveraber 25th 1^15, Sir, I have the honour to address you in continua tion of my memorandum Mo 34 C dated loth inst. on the suDje&amp;t of the Amir Bin Baud and the Ajman tribe. 2. The two Ajman Shaikhs who are in command of the forces of their tribe now operating against Bin Saud, viz. Shaikh Dhaidan of the Hathailan section '.nd Shaikh I'iiamaiyis of the Sufran section, recently approached Shaikh Salim bin Mubarak with a view to peace. He replied that he had no cower to receive their submission, and that they must ap&gt;ly either to his father Sir Mubarak at Kuwait or to .Din Saud himself, and offered to send a deputation under escort uo whichever of the two they might prefer. After some dis cussion it was decided that Shaikh Dhaidan with a few fol lowers should proceed to Kuwait and there make unconditional surrender, Khamaiyia remaining with Shaikh Salim. 3. The party arrived here on the iJOth inst., and were favourably received by Sir Mubarak who has accepted their submission upon a promise of future good behaviour and oossibly other terms which have not yet been communicated to me. On the Sfmd a messenger arrived from Bin Saud • A requesting Mubarak not to treat ?»ith the Ajman ShaiKS, out it was then too lat# for this request to be considered evenif the Shailui would have considered lt ; w.iich is unlikely, as the feelings of the Aiair in regard to the AJman v *ere believed to 'be ferocious in the extreme, and it was even said that a general massacre of such as fell into his hands would have followed upon a surrender to himself. 4. At the first glance it mi^ht ap ear that this termination of the campaign, however satisfactory from a humanitarian point of view, is a little hard on Bin Baud who, setting aside the loss of his brother 3a * ad, has suffered consider ably more at the hands of the Ajman than they have at his. But it may be urged in reply that without help from Kuwait Bixi Gaud would have been powerless to continue operations after his defeat in the night attack at Hofuf in which iia'ad lost his life, and that the promises of the AJman to liubarak include an undertaking to submit to the authority of the Amir of Nejd and Hassa in whose territory so many of them reside. It is believed that Bin Saud after the first sense of annoyance has passed off may realise that the prospect of help from the AJman in the future outweighs whatever satisfaction he might have derived f^m the extirpation of the two sections who had taken the field against him. 5. ?ihile it is therefore unnecessary for us to do other than approve of the peace which has made, I think we mi^ht A evince our sympathy with the troubles of Bin Saud, and our aesire to help him to . reserve order in the future,by takin L&gt; some notice of the part played by Hamdan bin Zaid A1 Khalifah Shaikh of Abu Dhabi, in connection with this affair. This chief, who is y in common with other Trucial chiefs y in treaty relations with us, has joined in the Intrigue against Bin Saud by supplying or attempting to supply his adversaries with munitions of war and affording an asylum to Sulaiman A1 Araif besides urging the A1 Murrah tribe to su port the Ajman. If I am instructed later to pay another visit to Qatar in connection with the proposed treaty with Shaikh- ' I • — ———Abuull-ii: bin Jasim it ai^ht also be convenient to allow me to ...roceed to Abu Dhabi and. ropressent to ShalU. ir.-adan bin Saif our view of his conduct In thi; atler; and. the oppor tunity :il 711 be taken at the same tiae to inform hi;i that we ^'iould re. ard -ith /rave displeasure any attempt on hie part to encourage a revolt ;&gt;alnst the authority of Shaikh Abdullah f v^atar whose elder brother Kiiallfah is believed to be sup ported by Haiadaii In the attitude of cuoosition to Abdullah which he has adopted. This, course would certainly have the effect of encouraging Shaikh Abdullal* and would I suspect, go soae way ta arcs ovorconiaa ais fear of . ermittin.... British subjects to reside in his territory. C. Copies of this letter Pave been sent to a .srah and Bahralii. 1 have tae honour to be air, yaur .nost obedient servant, Lt-Colonel Political A,,eat, Kuaait.9 - S - 1 to you by W/T. !!• Arrived at Abu Dbabi 1 p.r. or. Saturday 18th Decerber. Tbe Residercy Agent care off, and reported that ti e Sbeil-b l^ad beer loyal to I- i y r rorioe, tl^at Salman and Pabad A1 Araik had sou£ht refuce with hir, but that it had been refused. Consequently I oert ashore to that I shornd be ^ leaded to receive the Sheikh, and he care off at once. On his leaving I fired a salute of £ furs. 1?., At 1C ; . r. yreirl cd ard jrocee -v .ed, to the Northward, arrlvirr off Dibai at 8,5C a.r. l r th December, where I landed the Residency Agent, he haviiu: asked to be iut on Shore there instead of at sl arja. 13. Left a^ain at 9. 11 a.m. and shaped course for Bushire. Sifhted no vessels en rouie. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your obedient Servant, / Lieu t e r. a n t -Co r r. a n d e r in command.iui ti sh Re8idency ^uahire, 22nd December 1915 No•Cf.453 x'roin The Deputy Political Resident ard Acting Consul-General To The Commodore, Persian Gulf Division, Bushire, y.emorandum. i have duly received your Memorandum dated 21st December 1915, forwarding a letter of Proceedings of H.M.S• M Eritomart M at Abu Dhabi, and beg to express my hanks for the assistance you have given in this matter Deputy Political Hesident, and Acting Consul-GeneralCONFIDENTIAL No.Cf. of 1915. British Residency and Consulate-General, Bushire, 26th December 1915. A copy Oj T the undermentioned letters is forwarded to the political Agent, Bahrain, for information, with reference to various reports in letters and diaries regarding the move ments of Salman A1 Araif, and his tal-ring refuse in Abu Dhabi. Taj or. Deputy Political Resident,Persian Gulf, Xt Letter £Jrom Shaikh Handan bin Zaid m dated 15th December 1915, explaining his attitude since receipt of the previoi^s warning re harbouring the A1 Araif, S. Letter No,511 dated 15th December 1915, fro^ Residency Agent to Deputy Political Resident, A&gt; 3. Letter No,512 dated 15th December 1915 from -do- to -do-. 77 SIrom - Residency A^ent, Shargah, To - The political Resident in the Persian iVnlf ^'o o 511 Dated 15th December 1915 .&gt; I beg to report that on the 10th December the man-of- war 'Brito^tart' arrived at Shargah and I went on board and M- saw the Captain who^ji delivered your letter i\io P 3^7 of '^he 20th isiovember 1915 containing copy of 1 your letter to the Shaikh of Abu Dhabi and also the original letter to that Shaikh. I duly understood what you have written therein, on the subject of the assistance given by the Shaikh of Abu Dhabi to the Araifs * I at once left with the man-of-war for Abu Dhabi where I landed aohfturg with the Captain o We met the Shaikh and de« livered the letter to him,and the Captain and I discussed the matter of Araifs with hinu The Shaikh verbally replied that Salman arrived at -Cfee Dhabi via Katazjlixtenduny to stay at Abu Dhabi, but that in view of the warning he had received from the Political Resident in the Persian ^hilf, he did not agree to his stayr He left Abu Dhabi about 25 days before the arrival of the ahip there, embarking on sSe Abu Dhabi boat^ in a place called Radim in order to proceed to the Bedouins in the interior such as Al~Murrah and others,. He did not know his whereabouts after he left up to the time, the man-of-war had arrived „ The Captain then thought it better to leave as he had certain important duties to perform, and that I should re« main at Abu Dhabi for a few days ; perhaps some of the Araifs would come there or I might hear some news about them. Up to the 15th December 1915 no one of the/. Araifs or any news of them arrived at Abu Dhabi „ As Shamal was blowing hard during all the time of my stay, no boats could come by sea and no news was received about them by way of land c I heard from the Shaikh of Abu Dfeabi that after the occupationoccupation oi by tae Amir of Hajd, the Sliaikh has placed IdLiiielr in conraunioption of a Iriendly natm-e with the ii£iir, and ae told me t.^at he Intended to pay a visit to him and conclude treaties with iiim. 'i'-ie iviuir of ilajd Sient aim a verbal message stating that tne interview would take place at Oroaaa. The Shaiku ot abu Dhabi be cane sure iron tuis answer tiiat tlie Aiair .lad enmity wit a iiiia. He was ti'^ref ore, doing I JLs best to oppose trie Arair of' ilajd, but when he received your letter warning .lira not to aitord xiis assistance in any manner calculated to dis please the .fuair ot Ilajd as ae was on terns oi' friends aip wita the Britisix Qovernnent, the Si^aikh stopped iiis intrigues etc. against tae said iunir. ^aese are the statements ot the Shaikh of abu Dhabi to ae. I beg to forward aerev/ita a letter irora tlxe Biiaikh of abu Dhabi to you in reply to your letter on t e subject of % the Araifs.rrom - Keaiden;,y Agent, Sharguh. ro - deputy Political He^ident, , ^e^.l itn Gulf. ^10. 512. Dated 15th December, 1915, X beg to inform yo^j, that, reports received by me ./uj.ie c.o adu Dhabi, state i.hat when the Political Agent Banruin visited Kfttar to d.i««ra the Turkish soldiery at Kata-r, Salmun Araif was a guest of Shaikh Abdullah bin Jawim, Salman had an intention of paying a visit to the Political Agent but Shaikh Abdullah bin Juaim prevented him from doling ro. .Vhen the PoliUcal A^ent left Katar, Salman let t urie place I or r*.bu Biiaoi, -.i-t; ^ac ^Qii Ox &gt;.-1e biiaiKn qj JDhaoi was once present at the meeting of Shaikh isa bin Ali, Chief of Banram, and ne heard Shaikh iea say that he had heard that Salman Arail had left Katar for Abu Dhaoi; that perhaps he incendeo staying at the latter plttce, and that it did n;?t seem advisabi that Salman should, be at Abu Dhabi as he was afxa^a Lnat tne Chie of aou Dhabi would fall in/trouble wi th the jjr i oi sh Go •/eramen t,. ihe man, having neard the statements of the Chi 'f oi Banrain, especially l^ft Bahrain for adu Dhaoi and informed the Chief of that j31ace. Salman Araif was then at Abu Dhabi and when the Chief of that place heard nthe news from his man he informed Salman of it. T-i^y -uou, Jit j. i, best for Salman to leave Abu Dhabi .p ^ , , . 75t€ SUscks AS for .he interior via Radira tojjedouins^Almurah and others. Salman left Abu Dhaoi, apparently ;25 days oefore our arrival at that p^ace. 1 have also heard that , while at aou Dhabi, Salman received 2 letters, on^ from Amir Aodul Aziz Khan bin Saud and another from Abdullah bin jasim. Chief of Katar, the former stating that the outlaw yahd had met with his de 8tinydestiny, that Salman should go to hira, that h' will Bee nothi ig out good : that it wae evident t the kingdom was for hiTi and Salman una. that i t not advisarylf or to fight. If he did not accept this counsel ne would oe ruppr ^esed and would mast witn the came fate lib that of hi;s predecessor, while the letter from shaikh Abdullah Din Jasim to Salman ad/ise^ti him that ne should lis :en to the advice of Amir Aodul Aziz. iJ'ter he received, the 2 letters, Caiman declared that ne was willing to come to ami able terms with the Amir, but chat hi nad no confidence m any recone ilia ion between him and xifnir jiodul ^ziz witnouo a/xeliable .security. These are the r-ports l have obtained about Salman Araif'^ at Abu Dhabi.5) i /' K Confidential. MEMORANDUM. No C 44, dated Kuwait, December 22nd, 1915. To D .C.P.O., Basrah. Copies to Bushire and Bahrain. With reference to my Memorandum No C 40 dated December 3rd on the subject of the Araif and the AJman tribe, I regret to say that the information regarding Salman contained therein was not correct. It seems that the Sabia* seized the few men who were with him and he alone escaped to Qatar. There he requested help from Shaikh Abdullah who refused assistance but offered to intercede for him with Bin Saud. This Salman declined and left for Abu Dhabi where it is ber lieved he still is.i'rorn f' -w O C 3 c.: 1 . Political A^c-riCj, Kuv/a i t. Lt-Colonel ,'3,Grey, I,A. Politic*;.! i : u :ent , Kuwait. The Honours 1)1 o the Political Resident in the -ersian Guir, Busiiii'e, and. C.P.O. , Basrah, mnm miBEm Hg, /{ ^ Q « //. / ^ ccnfikntml sraisr C^- / Dated Kuwait, ^ebraaj , y :nd, l.;l .. i r, I have the honour to refer to my letter No 04^3 dated Mad ultiaio on the subject of Bin oaud and the Ajiaan tribe. The Amir has declined, to acce nt Shaikh Jabir's pro. osal that he should regard hostilities with the Aji.^an as closed, and Jabir has tlierefore ejected thea from Kuwait territorial li.Mits. According to information which I have received they appear to have retired to the Torth West. ■3. I attach a translation of a letter which Shaikh Dhaidan of the AJmaa has written to the '' Turkish Army Commander' through Ajaiai. This letter was riven to me conf .1 dentially by a person who desires that his identity should not be disclosed, but I have every reason to think that it is genuine. 4. From the same source I hear that tne Aj;.ian h. ve .nade ab agreement with Snaikh Jabir whereby he is to allow them to come to Kuwait occasionally to buy provisions and they undertake 1) not to molest anyone in Kuwait territory and (2) To regard as their friends the Awazim, the Duwasir, and some portions of the Jani Khalid even should they meet them out ride Kuwait limits. 5. Copies of this letter and its enclosure are being sent to Bushire. I have the honour to be, Six 1 , ;;our most obeaient servant, A /7 S ^I it-ColonelLgjte y....bitten by S haikh. Phalaay: AI A.' nr.! to the &gt;f Turkish Ar^jL.Colande r n an d ^ent via A.lal^A t date d -vbout 1 Jan u ary , 1 12. A. C» You know ?ind yo will understand. We have been your subjects since the day you tor a Has a, ana y,.u nave rovlded for us since that time. Bin Saud took iiaaa from you and this year :e deter lined to reta]-..e It -which v;e would have ajne had not Bin Subaii hel ed :. J in Saud. alow we are under your orders and these of Ajal i, and if we can have 00 neu and guns from you we will tike I las a by Goc' s hel - ^: a...a we are at your disposal what ever you order. A letter to the sarae effect was sent to Ajaiai at the saiue tinie, the last sentence of which read - T/e are at your als. osal and that uf Bin Raahid. 1 '13as rail o f, I t ' Memo randu ;u The following items of new? oonoeming the Ajaan eto are or interest«, Dhaidan and Kuamaaiyi,. ohe Shaiidia of the Hathailan and Sufraa seotiona of the AJuwn tribe with 4000 and boo followers are at Jilawa. There U evidently friendship between them and Ajami jaho me information oontaineu in ay letter No. 0.3 of Snd February appears to be jor^eot* The Mutalaggaa section or thi.. trxbe (400 fighting men) are wita am Hamad bin Saw-ait or -one iihaffir with whom is also Bin Tawala ShaiKh of the Asjlaa seotion of Lhe Shammar. The^e three are olose friends. aJ man, the remaining member of the Araif hau become re conciled to Bin Paud and is now with him. Bin raud ir at Riadh. Tae Sharif oJ iiecca ia busily engaged in enrolling troop,:;, from the rh-.mmar, Nejd tx-ibes/^His object is unknown here, rjin bhaalan or the Afciza tribe is at Labba 3 days 5 journey Tron Hall. He is on bad terms with Bin Raslaid. copies of tliis Memorandum have been senz to the Deputy poli- -oioal m^e 3ident in the Persian Guir and tio the Political Agent, Bahrein. / Lieut-colonel, * Political Ageno, Kuwait.* ■ -/ — -(COPY). No•5166• Chiei Political orfice, Basra, 30th June 1916, From The Ciiief Political Officer, Basrah, To The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department, Simla* CM v» In compliance with the instructions contained ■ in Foreign Department letter No,312-W, of March 10ih, i nave the honour to forward under separate cover three copies of the Treaty with Bin Saud, with Arabic Transla tion, for ratification by His Excellency the Viceroy» I have, etc., SdA P. Z* Cox, Chief Political Officer&gt;) (COPY). ^ No. 851-W, From Deputy Secretary to the Governraent of India ^ n iv:ie For slgn and Political Department, To The Hon 1 ble Lieutenant-Colonel Sir P.Z. Cox, K.C-S.I^K.C.I.E., ^ ^^litical liesident in the Persian Gulf Dated Simla, the 21st July 1916. Sir, With reference to your letter No.5166, dated the ^ 'Kr 20th June 1916, I ain directed to forward two copies of * One for record in the offir^ r.' , n . . i'? li ?iv c ; e ^ Kesiaeni in 'the Persian Gulf;' ) 0ri£:ln£l Treaty c .nc --.e o^her for delivery to Bin Saud, ) concluded with Bin baud, ituler or Kejd, duly ratified by the Viceroy and Governor General in Council. f oeven printed copies are also enclosed of the same document. I have, etc Sd/- Denys Bray : Deputy Secretary to the Government of IndiaTEEATY. In the Name of God the Merciful and Compassiouate* Preamble, The High British Government on its own part, and Abdul Aziz bin Abrlnr Bahman bin Paml Al-Saud. Euler of Najd, El Hassa, Qatit and Jubail fnl the towns and ports belonging to them, on behalf of himself, his heirs and successors, and tribesmen, being desirous of confirming and strengthens^ the friendly relations which have for a long time existed between the^wo pfrties and with a view to consolidating their respective interests-the British Govem- ment have named and appointed Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Percy Cox K.C S I K.C.I,E., British Eesident in the Persian Gulf, as their Plenipotentiarv to Pafea^Al-Saud. 1)1111)086 WitU Abdu! Aziz bin Abdur Rahman bin Tlle Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Percy Cox and Abdul Aziz bin Abdur Eahman bin Faisal Al-Saud, hereafter known as ' Bin Saud ' have aereed upon and concluded the following Articles: (I ) nn+'f Tlie i B T lt i' Sb i G0T ? I ?, m ? nt 1 (30 actno . wle&lt;3 S e an d admit that Naid, A1 Hasa Qatif and Jubail, and their dependencies and territories, which will be discuss ed and determined hereafter, and their ports on the shores of the Persian Gulf are the countries of Bm Saud and of his fathers before him and do hereby recognise the said Bin Saud as the independent Euler thereof and absolute Chief of their tribes, and after him his sons and descendants bv in. hentance; but the selection of the individual shall be in accordance with the fw 1 i? a v n n t 1 y S Euler) of his successor; but with the proviso that he shall not be a person antagonistic to the British Government ?u anv respect; such as, for example, in regard to the terms mentioned in this Treaty^ (H) In the event of aggression by any Foreign Power on the territories of the Ji m ' 1 ancl . his descendants without reference to the G ° Ter J nme ; lt aild without giving her an opportunity of communicatinn- with Bin Saud and composing the matter, the British Government will aid BiS Saud to such extent and in such a manner as the British Government after rdtunfr^ 118 ^ 111 ^ 001181 ' 161111031 effeCtiVe f0r P ro Meeting hi™ interests (III) Bin Saud hereby agrees and promises to refrain from enterins into anv correspondence, agreement, or treaty, with any foreign Nation or Power and further to give immediate notice to the political authorities of the British tbHro ^terrUonL 1 ^ ^ 0f ^ ^ P6wer to ^ (IV) Bin Saud hereby undertakes that he will absolutely not cede, sell mort. gage, lease, or otherwise dispose of the above territories or any part of [hem or grant concessions within those territories to any Eoreign Power or to subjects of any Foreign Power, without the consent of the 0 BriS Government! And that he will follow her advice unreservedly provided that it he not damaging to bis own interests. 1 ue 1106 (V) Bin Saud hereby undertakes to keep open within his territories, the roads StLflolyPlS i ' Iaee9 ' ^ ' 0 P ro ' ect pilgrims on their passage toTnd- ■ - . ^ '• I F. &amp; P, Dept. Press—No. 1156—19.7-16—60, Bin Saud undertakes, as his fathers did before him, to^ refrain from all agression on, or interference with the territories of Kuwait, Bahrain, and of the Shaikhs of Qatar and the Oman Coast, who are under the protection of the British Government and who have treaty relations with the said Government; and the limits of their territories shall be hereafter determined, (VII) The British Government and Bin Saud agree to conclude a further detailed treaty in regard to matters concerning the two parties. Dated 18th Safar 1334 corresponding to 26th December 1915. (Signed and sealed) ABDUL AZIZ AL-SAUD. P. Z. COX, Lieutenant-Colonelt 'British Resident in the Persian Gulf. (Signed) CHELMSFORD, Viceroy and Governor-General of India* This Treaty was ratified by the Viceroy and Governor-General of India in Council at Simla on the 18th day of July A. D. one thousand nine hundred and sixteen. (Signed) A. H. GEANT, Secretary to the Government of India, Foreign and Political Department*(COPY). ) No. 64 of 1916. Government of India. foreign and Political Cspartraent. ic.r,e. War To night Honourable Austen Chamberlain, iiis Majesty* s Secretary of State for India, oimla, %he 28th July 1916» Sir j ' xUl reference to your telegram, dated the 6th March 1916, we Have the honour to forward herewith copies a treaty concluded with Din Saud, Huler of Nejd, which has been ratified by the Viceroy and Governor -General in Council,- We have, etc,, Sd/- Chelmsford, Sd/- Beauchamp Duff BdA H. H. Craddock, SdA C s H. An Hill, Sd/« C, S, Nair, Sd/- G, IU Lowndes,53/? x Telegram From Foreign,Simla. To Trevor,Bushire. No, 549-S• D, 19 R.20/8/i6» 19 ^ alc03 P oar,s letter from Bin Saud's camp S.16 dated January 19th/ Oox wishss to publish it in Bureau Bulletin extracts from it. Copy said to have been forwarded by you in February 1915 to this department . Letter not traceable. Please send duplicate copy as soon as possible and give Mo. and date of your forwarding letter. , Foreign. Telegram.P. From Trevor,Bushire, To Foreign,Simla, No, 1706, a. 80/8/1 P. Keference your telagram No.549-3 dated 19th August, apparently copy of Shakespearis letter hhkb 3-16 dated January 19th never received in this office. Have wired Cox to send you copy. It xs not clear from record whether copies of Sfeakespear's S~14 and £.-15 were sent on to Foreign Department as they should have been, and I am sending them now. Trevor.c;OX»FxiJu,J l i'IAi J . . No. 3/7 -0. Of 1916. liritlsh nssidanoy and CJonaulata-uanaral, Bushira, 30th August 1916. From Major A. P, rr97or, C # 1 Japuty Political Roeldant, Parsian Gulf. To x.: 2 Hon* bla ...r, A.H.Grant, 0.3.1., 0 ,1.,5. , 1 0j - oeoratary to the Government of India In the foreign ani Political Department, S i m 1 a. Sir, / it- oontlrmation of ray telegram No. 1706 dated SOth August 1916, I have the honour to forward herewith copies of the lace Oartaln W.H.I.Shakespear' a letter No.S.14 dated the 15th January 1915 and No .S.15 dated 16th January 191o, .rich apparently ivera not sent at tirae of receipt. Aa stated In the abo^eraentioned telegram letter No.16 iiited 19th January was neyer received in this Rosidancy. 1 ha/e telegraphed to Sir P.Uox asking him to submit a copy to the Government of India. i I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Major, Deputy Political Resident, Persian Gulftranslation of a letter from Abd El-Aziz Ibn Abd Er-Hplinan Al-l^aisal dated the 20th July 1-ir, to His Honour Sir Percy Cos, His Majesty's Consul General in the 'ersirn Gulf. r n the naine of God the merciful. After Compliinents • Your Friend had the honour to receive your esteemed letter and understood the contents. Rolorrinn; specifically to what you wrote; fi) As re T r !s 0 ' ir fitting with the Al-Murrah tribe vu. your recret that Ibn Rashid was able to k ep his position safe at hail, 1 would inform Your Jon.ur, in that connection, that our n'btinr *th the Al-Murrah was an urgent mattert although, no . U t, it was my interests that '.-ere primarily involved yet these to some extent are connected with the interests . Croat Britain £i'»so. You doubtJ car n-3 aware that the Al-Murrah are allies of the Turks and that the Turks have an alliance with Ibn Rashid and his tribe. It wes the intention of the Al-Hurrbh 'O jjoc-e^ i.o .f ,.rus Kuwait in order to co-onerate with ti c 'i r'.-s and bn Rashid, and had they done so there would certainlv n/ have been some u*toward result either in Iraq or in my direc tion. TV-ir intentions however became evident before the event by reason or their many acti .ties in the direction of Hassa ana • rtif ant', their plundering and marau;lin.~; and I was com pelled to deal -ith them as an enemy firstly, because they had a.^ -ressed on my subjects and secondly, because it wns necer :u.?y to nrevont their Joinin- their allies mentioned above. I appealed to God for assistance and by His help they are now uiilato : an;', are no longer of any importance. And as to ibn Rashid beiiv; able to mrl:, ,aln his position secure at Hail, there is o doubt that the norson who -nve vou this information was en enemy. He was probably one of the foil ov:in^■ following of Ibn Rashirt nhon the sent to you, hoping ' 1 that by reason^ of their activities on your side and their proxinity to you they might fill you -ith .one apprehension so that -ou night accept his denands. But thanks to God, the reverse of this happened and Ibn Rashid became of no innortanc- in your judgnent, as I told you before. And it, is plain that Your Honour yourself fully appreciated the triviality of his following and of his Personality for you have recorded them in your lottor. With reference to A1 Abd and Hail, I sent against then FIT son Tur'i and Faisa * Ibn Pashid with an adeauate force, and ever since you and I parteI at Katif up to now they have boon investing Hail and interrupting its 'nusabilah'. ^Supply cora mnications). There is but a snail number of desert Arabs in trail, but the fact that we wore not able to force an entranc into the town is due, firstly, to the reason that the terrain between ■:aslm and Hail is barren ground where there is no vegetation for camels to eat, (and you know well that nothing can b- one by Arabs without their camels); rnd secondly, because the town is fortified and it was not possible to make successful assault in the absence of effective weapons. We had only our original guns which, as I have told you, are only light ones; pnd moreover, wo had not enough ammunition to enable us to enter into prolonged fighting with Ibn Rashifl and Into war ♦Ith the Turks generally. (ii) T beg to Inform you that you have fulfilled my denands j am' sent ne what was necessary. You have done what was re quired and I an thankful and obliged to Your Honour. (iii) I bog to acknowledge also the receipt of the letter of :ris Excellency the Viceroy awl was very ^lai to receive it. Civ) I confirm what I told you regarding; the exnort of fljoods to hostile coir trios and note that you have nade energe tic arrangements in that con ection. As I said before, the system you have established is no doubt very .-ood # Cv) I note also that you have despatched theTreaty to HisHis ^'xcclloncy the c^rov o r»v. ^ ' 3 A 01 signature and I an thankful and. obliged. Cvx) . ith ro^ar- t® lay relative Ahjaed Ibn Abdulla A1 Tha- Lyan I note t .. t you Imve, soon after the receipt of ny infoma -tlon, sent for him. and that he cane to you. 1 note also fa' you have found nothing in his papers to prove hin -uilty, but ,,aVe arran ® eC - f0r !lls departure for Masqat where lie was to he under detention until you heard from ne and learnt what my wishes Vrer0 *' t0 hls -''ture disposal. As I told you previously I Had fornerly trusted hin but he S ave me no intimation re .ardin, his departure, and told me nothing until ultimately he wrote no . letter wiiich T sent to you together with the Treaty, -'lis hrvinc thus left without reasonand without any warning caused me to suspect him, for you are aware of the nature of the present tine and of the people now-a-days.You are well aware, too, that people do many things which are contrary to their own interests and I was rfr-id that he ni~ht do things of which we should disapprove and which you rould not consider justified on the part of one who is connected with me. I thou-ht It host to explain the facts to you so that in the event of his h„i,i , li ty of any --isconduct, I misfit escape any odium due to the fact of it r : having been committed by one of onr people. V'e have no fear, now would any one fear, that any serious evil would result to hin from his hein. T arrested by Government in connection with his departure without wnrnin,- and without prudence, for the fact is that Great Britain and yourself are noro hind to onr people than we are ourselves in such matters, hut the truth is fat Ibn Thanaiyan has a family in our neigh bourhood and they cane to my father's house and beared him to ask no to write to Your Honour to request you kindly to send hxm back; and my father has asked mo to do this, if he re . turns, Ibn Thanaiyan shall live in my father's house with him, at the capital, Riyadh. I her- 'ou t 7 iererore to send him feack to BahreiA and to Instruct His Majesty's Consul there to send him to Ojalr ort0 ' ntir at! '' t 0 ' !cf! to ''assa soon after his arrival at Eohreln. Believe ne I did not write to you about him for ciny ^opsonal POcisons T r*nT-tr J onlj wanted to safeguard our own 200 nnn0 anl t0 enSUre that ''thing should happen from one of oin people Which might be opposed to the Interests of our Friend Great Britain. ^11) With regard to Ibn RasMd and his correspondence vith Shallch Ibrahim and your relations with him I endorse rrliat Your Honour said, which i &lt;= + t , o + ' , taat all Are a-r-ed that he is an Ignorant and foolhardy youth. As you remarked, his following only amounts to -0' or 300 men. Nevertheless his remaining In the Shamleh Is not expedient. Your pollcv and correspondence with reference to him arrears to me to have been quite appropriate; but there Is no doubt that ibn Pashld Is unable to appreciate and recognise it. „e is absolutely unable to guide his own footsteps, much less lead th- desert Arabs and people of that kind. By his remaining in your neighbour hood and by showing plenty of activity, he evidently thought that he would secure one of two things : either that you would comply with'his demands (but that was Impossible for owing to your diplomacy and capability you inderstand his nosition as you do that of others) or that he would receive some benefits from to •urks. And all the arrangements of the Turks with him hove been badly managed. They complied with his wants to some extent but it would seem that they have given him up as a bad Jo), owing to his nrevious conduct and the way in which he has trifled with them. I duly received the telegraphic news Your Honour sent to Abd el Latif el Handil to Bahrein informing him that your Cavalry with the Dhafir and Ibn Tuwala had attacked and defeated Ibn Radiid. I was very glad to get the news and hope to receive confirmation of it. I pray God that whatever is useful in the Interests of Government may happen. (vill) And you have mentioned also that ibn Tuwalla visited youyou two days a~o and timf -t+ • tj,at ' ls h0 Ped that he will act 1 coyoperation with t o ^ t, o Jhaflr. You nls ■ renarl: that he has inforued you regarding the oneratlon- of . -tions of ny SO n Turkl and riKal -Obayyel against Hail and its vicinity. *oix say that Ibn Tuwalla hones to unite .ith the tribes wlncli adjoin Jiin and + and that you expect that I .ill tell hi ra that -16 may reckon on my support. Sod Tnrk1 ' 1 ^ 1 ' f0 ™ Cl ^ ^ an d pleas jod, he ..11 rlse to hls duties ^ ^ uv.'alla and ny assurance to hi n , j at oncc Tyrot(s ]iim a which I enclose herewith e™ v ' o 1. Your Honour to see. re ^ TW+I., 5&gt;ee # it xt nieots y o,,r approval, kindly send it on - • na him. Tliere is no d011)31 t'lat if Timn 111 « Tuwalla opposes T bn Rashi-i, -e shall draw closer to hln in our relations and shall heir, hin in on . sp nln 111 all circumstances. TU,ralla ^ the AS1 - — to he under our a^s of old and even Ibn Hashid himself. Inshallah the old state of things will be restored. •'ix) You have informed no 'Tim.f +t,. n0 the course of the stru.^le in the European theatres of war aad told me how the aemans am suffering from lack of ammunition and provisions, and how their expectations are being disappointed and that they are suffering heavy losses. v;e pray to God to disappoint their hopes, our Friend Great Britain and her Allies will, wlth God's help and Protection ' tol x 10 yi ctory over them. This s t/ iat is to he 1 &gt;■ o t *■Pr»t-» i ' ' oecause we believe that the Germans 3211 t;!0ir A1UeS n0 0ther intention than to oppress and over-tax the world. Just as they have done in Syria and Baghdad and Constantinople. Without doubt people whose first deeds are of this kind will fail ln their objects. fx) Then you spoke of the situation on the Tigris and at Baghdad and mentioned that the Russian Cavalry were moving in t.uu vicinity vhilst your own victorious Armies on the s were in contact with the Turks some 15 miles from Kut, and that you are awaiting a more favourable season. Inshallah, this will come soon and we shall receive the news of your victory over them\ob them as wg hone. (M) Tl.en vou „ nt „„ „ ten m t]iat ^ '' •' f«. B.,„ n K „ lrlT ^ -4 «... y .„ , wpo lt ^ ^ ' SO ' J '' »» • source of conforl to t'° '1 '• tho ouhlic, t tru , t „ MU som copipleted. rxii) Then you spoke of the Custom Duty char , e(i at ana j-.u rait and said that you were about to conmunlcate with the Political Agents and would inrom ne of the result, r do not douht that you are n ore ooreful of .y lnterests thpn I am myself. fxlll) v 0ll have suggested that I must have heard of the opening of tho Telegraph Office at Behreln and remarked that It vou.. he a moons of quicker co.munication with no. I do not douht that this i s a wise measupe ^ for of t .0 PUT lie. if *8 a proof of the rood policy of the British Government towards her subjects and all of those who are under Iier patronage. (XIV) Your Honour expressed doubt as to whether I should not he lnCOnVeni0nCefl b ' V reacU ^ long letter, on the contrary I was glad of it and gained from it much knowledge of tho things connected with n e and ny affairs and of the progress of the war. 'hen I receive plenty of news fron you I enjoy peace of rind and can safe,guard myself in regard to nunorous interested people : so please let your letters be long, as they are a source of pleasure and utility to me. (xt) i was glad to receive the news regarding the Shatlf of Mecca and to receivo it officially from you. You thought I wight already have got the news, but in any case your connunlcation is the one on which I should depend, i am ln trut.i vory mch pleased at what has happened, firstly, a s it is a knock-out blow for the Turks, and secondly, because I do not wish any Turk to remain or to exist in Arabia. Inshalla this event will be propitious also for my Friend Gr-at Brl^tiin.i 1 soon as was co'pf'Tivi r\- 0 o t ie accuracy of the Sharif's news, ami even before your letter reached ne, I had the intention to ..rite to Your Honour regarding ny position and clrcumtances vis a vis the Sharif and also regarding the questions .hlch affect you In this connection. I reel it Incurihent on .e to state to you, (though vou are -ch hotter infomed in regard to the affair than , t , iat ^ fear , 1S that the Sh - if ^ obtain fro. the British Govern ment an undertaking for his independent control over the H«djaz and the Arabs. Although you yourself probably appreciate ny fears, it is possible that the representative of the British Governnent who is actually conducting negotiations with the Sharif, is not acquainted with the position. As you are aware there has been war between ne and the Sharif for years and his rtesl-n ha* if. -ic s always heon to r^et a footing in nejd and the neighbourhood, both among Bedouins and the townspeople. In fact he has not failed.to interfere in these directions and the Turks were assisting hi n m his pro- ceedings and proyidlne; hi^ ..it, tAe necessary means* It Is essential therefore that Your Honour should draw the attention of Government to the fact that the boundaries between Nejd and the Hedjaz are well-defined and that the tribes of Nejd cannot cor- under the sway of any one. We cannot put »p with or tolerate such an Idea as I have previously e^lalned to you. -•or is not Nejd the land of our forefathers ? Moreover Mecca fron t tf carl' \st tines, up to now had an Independent chief; but It has been an Anirate under the Turkish Governnent. What has pronpted ne to emphasize this to you is that I notice In the official connunique that nentlon is nade of •the Arabs' as if they were a compendious whole. It was incun- hent on ne to explain to you ny views on this point. Further more, the Sharif in his dealings with you is not free fron political guile and knows well how to turn phrases. He ! i i fis . ) oiibt exaggerating matter, li'fiat he want Is to obtain supnort fron you or else that you should exert yourselves with him ln attaining this end. i have therefore ed , ou .,o tant in the event of your agreeing with me you r ' t ' coflTnuni Celt© to tlic ''r*-!■#* ^ ' ^o ,r ernnent what I have said In case my vionc' cMiTr.,,1^1 . Tiews should con-end thenselves to then. Tf however, you do not think as j do , nevor nlnd . I do not ^ ^ lf the Sharif does «*tal„ his independence in this Way * !!Ut the roal P oint ±s that the Turkish Government Uod hi., j annirLitlon, arms and money, and he was leadln them to hope that he would do great things for them in Syria: but when no got all he wanted from them, he rose and declared Ms independence; his motive being thereby to put the Turks in difficulties with the British Goremment and so obtain from them his independence, guaranteed by the German Government. And what your Friend deduces from the facts is that the Shiirif i-: .ot now in any danger from the Turks. The Sharif's position depends upon the people of the Hcdjaz, that is on the iioilouins. Tf they support him, he will not be in any danger from the Turks, but if they abandon him and side with the Turks, then the position of the Sharif i„ the Hedjaz will be worth nothing, what I apprehend is that if the Turks see that the British are helping the Sharif, they will grant him Us independence at once and remain at rest in regard to him, but will turn their attention to him again hereafter. My advice is that you should help the Sherif but only to a partial extent, so that the Turks may still cherish hopes of crushing him and 1=0 also may remain in fear of the Turks. Thus the Turks will be treatly embarrassed in the Hedjaz and this will be an assistance to your business in Iran and elsewhere. In short, as far as I can see, the protraction bf the hostilities between the Sharif and the Turks is a most expo lent course for you. Mv'hope is that you will take these-remarks into deliberate consideration. What you see in ny opinions deserving of apnroval do as youIn the Nam© of God the Merciful. From Abdul Aziz ibn Ahrhi*» d t , ion ^ftdur Ralman al Faisal, ■10 - The Chief Political Officer. Datod the 15th August 1916. After Gonplinento• - tiospatolisci q, l©t.t.0r» to tr . Honour recently; Inshallah you recoivod it and it found you in the best of health, it J some little tine since X roooiV9a any lett9r ^ ^ ^ ^ ' oa rg to me the good news of your victories over the evil do- era. la. always siting for your good news in that connection. ^ t0r ny previous letter to you. I received tram the 77 ^ ; 00051 lett0rS COnVOylnS of his occupation o .locca with the assistance of your runs nn » i ^ you. guns. lie asked no to^ender hin assistance and to unite nysolf wit h hin. I have written bade saying that as regards assistance I will not fail to render it to tll0 utmost of pitt -norrAy a ~ x ^ , %' P'' '1 01 m As to union f? - ! t7T 'h-tr-i T -u uzixon vrizn Him I have remarked that I have no designs on his country, i.e. the Hedjaz and its surroundingss whereas, on the other hand, he, in the past, has been in the habit of interfering with ny tribes and ny territory, alleging that this has been done at the instance of the Turks and thap it was they who were prompting him to do so. I contended that if he naant to be sincere and desired to be united with me and that we should work hand in hand, he should give no an under taking and a solemn promise for the immunity of ny terrirories and my subjocts, and for abstention from trespassing in our limits, or from interference with our subjects. If this reply is m the affirmative and he acts loyally, no effort on my part will, please ^od, be spared to lielp him to the best of my ability. My motive in replying as above is not due to any desire on ny part to ally myself with him, for you are aware of his previous relations with me: but it was due, firstly, to the fact of my al liance with yoursol #es, and secondly, to my hatred of the Turks#• r a ^ ^ anxious to further ^nvfTriv, j.-, So, if he aMWPrs . t my aSSi3t to ox P el ^ ln tha ^irmtivo and aosm ,e S me that he „ no aim other than r^i r ■ 0 1100 to iapoeo on no so that '' ^ ^ ^ If ^ 18 render hlnsolf freo to ^ ^ independence and the natter • ' ' interference with m e. then aft ' ^ b0tWS9n ^ ^ ^ X shall loo. or myself to the be 6 t of my ability. But, if on th fhn Tna + + e contrary* ~ 7our s '' ,k ™' 1 —«««« to o oomsment to 7&lt;jn _ i ^ r ' to ,ou - 10 ' w '» and territories are well fenown; and a fi^ti ^ ' aM a further reference win ba t0 y0U ' when I receive his reply. I also have to inform Your Honour that I have recently loarnt that the A3nan , who was latoly ^ ^ ^ ^ neighbourhood of Zuhniv T&gt; . _ ' haCi ' 0n account of the peace between n lashid and Ibn bubaii, come to an understanding with boti^ those Chiefs, soon after the departure of Xbn Hashid from ^ neighbourhood of his contact with Ibn ^ala and Ibn Swait, to the effect that they should settle in the territories of Ibn Subah. This is not as it should be . I have explained to four J Honour regarding the AJman and their attitude towards me. they are outlaw subjects of nine and the reason of their contumacy was their support by Ibn Subah and their stay at Koweit, and this will certainly cause friction between me and Ibn Subah, for »y subjects are bound to pursue the feud with the Ajman and so am I 0 I have also sent my representative, Abdul Aziz al Rabai, with letters to Ibn Subah and have made the necessary communi cation to him regarding matters at issue betwoen him and me. I Have also instructed my representative aforesaid that if ibn Subah responds to our advice and complies with my wishes, so nuch the more gratifying will it be to me, and I shall regard them as the best of friends and fellow-tribesmen. If, however. I * he•u) ro e jocu.. .1 ..asico, ny nessengor hao been instructed to refer te your Consul at Kowelt; and then, if possible, he will proceed to Basrah to lay the matters before you. But in truth I have said more than enough on this subject. You will understand that did matters concern him and me alone, wo should come to issue in regard to differences of less importance than this; but as your Government is also interested, I am/willing that there snould be any differences between us. People, however, in these clays, while they fail to abide by their friendships or to o uich t - fiends, do not hesitate to^act contrary to the principal©® of religion and good sense. But it is certain that there are matters from which no advantage is to be gained by interference with them. Owing, however, to my regard and friendship for Your Honour, I do not do anything without communicating with you, and I will act v ;ith circumspection, i depend on you in this matter and beg for guidance from Qod, and thence from you. I trust your friend ship w r itn me will be perpetual and hope that I shall receive news of your good health without any intermission, and trust you will acquaint no with the good news of tho victories of your amies® May you be preserved# etc. I . 9/2. III # Chief Political Office, Basrah, 9th Sept. J916 Copy to Political Agent, Koweit. * Bahrain • D.P.R, Buchire. 0 ^ D.S. t-.. § n i \ \ Captain. D. C. P. 0. ft , I ITelegram. y ^ Dailv ' uffifflar y Novmbur 11&gt; From - Cox, Koweit (Radio). : of'state J'^^cf^Cairo^and^Politioal ^Basra ^f'ted Secretary No. T~ffl 58. ^ Dated and received 21st November, 1916. Ibn Saud arrived at Koweit in His Mai^tv' v.- r ^ x . 18 Ma 3esty s ship Juno yesterday evening much pleased and imoressed with v with u-i o m • * , ''pressed with voyage and wit His Majesty's ship. This evening November 2 0th Durbar - place at Shaikh's residence at which Shaikhs of Koweit Durbans composed of principal inhabitants and some Bedouins headmen of Shammar Aslam and Dhafir. After delivery of decora- -tion and a few words from me, three Shaikhs above mentioned vied with each other in expressing their enthusiasm for their attachment to Great Britian. Shaikh of Mohammerah gave the lead with an exceedingly pro-British harangue and was followed by Ibn Saud who gradually warmed to his work and delivered most animated speech in which he cited and dwelt upon the in- -ylquities committed by Turks against other Muslims, said that they were outside all of Isla. and went on to impress his hearers of the complete contrast between our policy and that of Turks viz. that whereas Turks had continually tried to disintegrate the — Arabs and foment their differences we were encouraging them to unite for the common good. He eulogised action of the Sharif and urged obligations oi all true Arabs to participate, Finallv all three Shaikhs swore to work together with us and for us for the achievement of the conimon end. Ihere was much enthusiam and the scene was a most edify- -ing and memorable one, news of which will travel far. Addressed Foreign, repeated Secretary of State, H.Co, Cairo and Political, Basrah, Cox. Y.A.Telegram. R. From Loch, Bahrain. To Political,Basrah. No. 9-0. Dated and received pOth January, 1910, 'V Cox s telegram No. 328-T, January 10th. Bin Saud. Have sold supply bille for £8500 which will enable me to meet January payment. For further payments should I try to seil bills or will you pro ide cash. Former would draw attention to transaction. Loch. ===000=== Telegram. R. From Political, Basrah. To Political Agent, Bahrain. No. 501. Dated 21st January, 1917, t ♦ Your telegram 9-0. Please try to sell bills. If you cannot do so at par let me know. sushis ni&amp;z&lt;s?i. I s&lt;s N ^ . 2-3. r./-? === &gt;«tb §■ ■ Ho - Political. Chief Political Office, Basrah, 21st January, 1917. D. P. R. Buiahl re. Copy forwarded for information. .X \ V Oaptain, Deputy Chief Political Officer. * i bedsNo: ChiQf olitical Office ^asra.lst: Febry; 1917 Hi '' &amp; .0 ,vi&gt; ' 5 i 0-^ ©sdt: Agent, Uhargah, A/C. it is not hidden froE you that *'* 3haikh 'Mul Aziz ibn Oaad Aair of ejd has allied himself to the British cvt. oy a formal treaty and is their friend and cooperator, ibn Saud represents to me that his dependents who have claims against the Peoole of Oman find difficulty in recover- -ing their just rights. 1 wish you to explain to the ShaiJche of the Trucial toast of Oman as above and say that 1 hope they win treat Ibn Gaud's dependent with all consideration in view of his status as an ally of the British Govt, ou yourself also will not fail to use your best endeavours on behalf of such dependents of the Afiiir. ( i Chief ^©3 itical Officer Copy to D.P.fi. u en ire. rf ■r&gt;* v $ * /1 c i a.. j A- 1 / -eo^u -4__ y^'7 'uM Ui. \ \Prom , The Hon' ble Lt.Col.Sir P ,Z .Cox .0 .3 .1. X.G.I.E rolitical Resident and Chief Political Officer To H .j :. the Amir Abdul Aziz bin Abdur Bahman al Faisal. Hakim of Nejd etc . A/c . J. now ta.te jrp the pen to write to Your Excellency on a number of subjects which need communication between us,but in the first place I must express my great - pleasure m hearing via Bahrain firstly that you recover ed fr^m the fever which overtook you on your return journey from --atif .and secondly of your departure from your capital of Riyadh on 24th January (Rabial Awwal Si/th with your troops in the direction of ^asim. 1 hope that before you started you had received the news which 1 asked the Political Agent Bahrain by telegraph to send to the effect that Government had been pleased to accept the recommendations which I made in regard to the assistance to be rendered to Your Excellency in the matter of arms and ammunition and funds . Soon after sending you my letter of 23rd January 1 received your welcome letters of 14th Safar (10th Deer) written from Oqair,and later 1 received those of 22nd Safar (18th December) The letter which you enclosed to the address of His Excellency the v r iceroy of India was duly received and sent on to lndflLa,and 1 thank you very much for the kind reference which you made to your friend and officer) of the Military Administration. As you know,apart from the personal regard which 1 have for Your Excellency,we areare ai. zgme merely the instruments of our Government &amp; endeavour to act as i/ve know they would wish. x wil only deal with one important matter in the body of this letter and that is your own present plans. The other matters which need mention 1 will deal with in separate sheets. As mentioned above jiny last news of your honour's movements is that received from Bahrain to the effect that y ou had left Riyadh for Q^asim, 1 will now tell you what the position is and in able what way we hope you will be to co-operate in our common interests. On the Tigris we have not ceased to make steady pi ogres since you left. There has been continual trench fighting and we have now obtained possession of the junction of the Shatt—al—Gharraf with the Tigris at Kut .This the whole of the right bank of the river from the Hai Junction opposite Kut downwards to Shaikh Saad and so on to Basrah is in our hands. The enemy have retired up river from Kut except those in the Sanniyat position on the left bank who still remain,but now that we have got posses- sion of the river bank behind them up to the Shatt~al~ Hai,their position has become very difficult. Then on the desert side ? as you know,the Railway is running to Nasiriyah and troops and supplies can all pass by rail and it makes us very strong^here. Then South of Khamisiyah our friend Sa'ud as Salih as Subhan who has been joined by the Aslam,Dhafir and Budur and many other Shammarjis holding the ShamiyahV Hail or „ edlna a „ d Ira? Ea Shi . ' ,,0rth '' Sha,i » Ibr l '' ,0Ur bOM ' «. t „ op8 that side'' 1116 ±r0m QaSlm and thre ^— g h lm from ' ' 18 &amp;1S0 a PP^ent from the report ' :r sary s y e d M U h ammad bin Abdullah ^ ufq) that - J are exertlng en d eavour e to get I bn Kashid 'bo mov© 'to tho ' tte MSlst ™» »f their troop. a t Medina. I myself hardly thin 1 - it y ^ Possible that he Jbn Rash id wui d are to leave Hail now as he i iioi/i.as ne is weak and has so many enemies around him but in am; ' m any case it, i s clear]v important to prevent him at this juncture fr ■ • assistance to the Turks a H v ' ^ lur ks anci Your Excellpn^t; -io , . j-oAoeiiency is now m an excellent dor it^ inl ^Ployed and to threaten SO Vle0r0Uelj ^ to leave Hani and .a y eVen t0 COme 0UX t0Wards ^sim to defend, himself against you. If you can act on thpqp ii-n^rv i J-ines and prevent hiin moving towards Medina.while nt tho - at the same^ to our friends on the side endeavour to keep the^ejaz Railway cut n0rth 0f Led - lr,a t):ie Turkish garrison in Medina will completely isolated from assistance and supplies and will have to retire or surrender. This is how your friend sees the matter and it i s hoj.ed that your view of the position will not be differ enti. Any how I shall hope to receive frequent ^ews of your movements via Kuwait and pray God to prosper your r tunee and give you victory. i ii ■ i1 As regards the world war.there have recently been some important developments. li-Lstly. The internal position of Germany has become acute and she'has made proposals for peace.but there were proposals which were not sincere.and only meant that she is now exhausted with fighting and hoped to get an armistic while peace discussions were proceed ing,after which she would be ready to fight again. The result was that the Allied Powers unanimously refused to listen and will not have peace except on the terms tha,t we wish. Lspecially we must insist on a guarantee that Germany shall never be in a position to ma.-ce suhh a war again. In desperation she has now begun to violate all the laws of nations and humanity more than ever,and this has so exasperated the neutral nations that even America has now severed relations with Germany and dismissed the German Ambassador. It looxs as if America would now come into the war .but as yet no hostile act has occurred and it is possible that uermany may offer such apologies and reparation that war will be everted. Any how the Amerloan people and also the Spanish Governrnent who were before quite neutral in their feelings are now entirely in favou.^ of our A1 ied Powers and will give them all possible oo-operation in the way of supplies and ammunitions, So that you wi 1 see that the prospects of the Allies are now very favourable. 1 will now oonolude this long letter with my best regards to Your Excellency and will touch upon the matters nEntioned below on separate sheets.I am leaving to rejoinn the Army Commander almost at once and hope I shall be able to send you good news from there. Please find enclosed a packet which our friend Shaikh Khazal asked me to have sent to you. May you be preserved. P.R . and C,P.0, Lavi,e separat ely . 1. four telegram to the Sherrf i. , epij to ^ mi his letter signing hi.self -King of the Arabi ,. 2 . ifour dependents in Oman . The lamented death of our friend Shaikh Jabir. The question of stoppage of supplies goint, to the enemy . The Emissary Saiyid Muhammad Abdulaah Yamani. despatch of photographs to Your Excel ency . 4 5. FRE1- The tel egram to H.H. the Shpr-i-p ■ oiienf ln reply to his fflBSLag© 'to you „ You asked me whether it was fV.™ h- . aS ±ro m him direct or sent tJar ougJa me . These are the facts . The teleo-rn h -p e I ' ele g r aph from here to Banrain is as you lotow by wireless anri sj-ess and on the wireless system only cypher telec-rams are ^ i tgrams are allowed during the war bo this telegram had to be sent tn m • sent to me m cypher and was sent on to Bahrain in + v. i t ' 0 be decyphered and sent on to Your Excellency. The course « s forced in the cas,, of yoor reply. It .as reeeived b, „ in cypher.and seno on tc High Coramis:. inner ,airo ,ho »onld have ' e cyphered and sent on to its destimation. As regards ihe Sheriff signing himself fMalik el Bilad ad Aiabiyah',your statemanship will 1 know cause y0U t0 agree Wlth me that ' ^ not worth while at this juncture raising this question between yourself and the Sheriff . You can rest completely assured that the title which he usee or does not use has no meaning in refer ence to yourself . The Sheriff has given bs definite assurance that he fully recognises the independence of yourself and your country and you can completely rely on our assuranceaand the terms of our treaty with your honour e 2- Your dependents who have claims in Oman. 1 have written to my Dy .Resident at Bushire and to the Shaikhs of Uman through our Agent on the Oman Coast reminding them af your honour is our friend and ally and that all possible co-operaton is to be afforded to your dependents for the recovery of their just claims.I'You will already have heard ^-p +h j t n.drd of the death after a Sh01 ^ 1]nterriai lIln e S s of 0U r lamented friend Shaikh We are in the hands of God and fate did not all0W hlm t0 Snj ' 0y his P osit iin long. May he rest in iJeUC8 ' Shaillh Salim ha8 needed to the Shaikhship without disturbance and has undertaken to fulfil all ^he obligations and treaties entered into by his father (m ay God rest him) with the British Govt. - Col.Hamilton has already written to your honour about the stoppage of supplies going to the enemy from Kuwait. This is as you will recognise an important and urgent matter .Poor Shaikh Jabir owing to his easy going nature and perhaps owing to his sickness was slack in this matter .but 1 hope Shaikh ualim wiiJ be stronger and that you wilt copperate to the utmost and approve of our not letting any merchandise out of Kuweit pvr'p-rt o-n - w-.-Lt except on passes signed by your Excellency or your Deputies. This is one impor tant way of winning success against the enemy. As regards Syed Muhammad Abdullah Yamani .many thanks to your honour for kindly sending on his latter to you for me to see. According to my information this man was for merly the Agent of Imam Yahyah in Constantinople and formed part of the Turkish mission to Bin Rashid and to Yemen,but thahk God his letter to you shows that his heart was not really with the Turks and iD hope we may feear that on your arrival at Q,asim you were able to stop the mission from going to Yemen and to seize what they were conveying, 6• 1 venture to send you a set of the photographs whichi/vere ^a.^en on the occasion of your visit here they niciy interest your honour , P.R.and C.P.O,Telegram. R. From - Loch, Bahrain. To - Basrah, Repeated Trevor, Bushire. No. 0 . c -G. Dated and received 2nd March 19 Bin Saud has sent Abbas-al-Fala ii onvn-rr - envoy to jrou. Asks for H.M.Ship if no merchant vessel avaiiflhio m available. No steamer expected here m near lucure. Can you arrange passage. Abbas offers congratulations on successes. Addressed Basrah, repeated Bushlre, reference my immediately preceding telegram, h d ivV'L ./ „■ 'Xfv.'.-. .. flc^.A^ •: Z Loch. Signal Message. To - 'Lawrence 11 Bushire. Dated P-3-17. Pe our conversation of yesterday. Another person who wants early passage to Easrah has turned up at Bahrain in shape of envoy from Bin Saud to C.P.O. Understand inconvenient fo you to go over till after next mail. Could you go ^ due Vtxx. When is 'Investigator' due? Perpahs she could go across if you can't. Trevor. Signal Message. To - Trevor. Bushire. Dafied 2-3-17. I am v,iring to D.S.T. now to ask when 'Investigator' may be expected at Bushire. Suggest leaving on Sunday picking up envoy and calling in here to get steam-boat on way up to Basrah if this sMitis fits with investigators' movements. If there is ftny urgency I can leave t nTYi orrow. Lawrence.Telegran. R. From - j.och, Bahrain, To - Trevor, Bushire. Repeated Basrah. No. 0 o_c. Jated and rceivBd. 6t,h M&amp;rch Your telegram 4^C) ^ ' Envoy and Bank man l^-rt R-f-To p _ , . xi- ijan o ..arch 5th for Bushire by dhow to catch mail. Addrossod Bushire, repeated Basrah. Loch, Signal message. To - tt Lawrence*Eushire. Dated 6th March 1917, Just heard from Bahrain in re^ly to my wire saying you could go about 12th that envoy and Bank man left by dhow yesterday ^ f or Bushire to try and catch mail,. Consul General. -2 t rvf Htp npw regime in TurkGy and would 'welconip, the aggressive P 0 ^ ^tigh Agent in one of his ports, and he added if lie recovered ^ fJntish Age.t ^ ^ that our trade ^tu ..nutes Captain Shakespear eould make no other maintain on the . - ^ confined its interests to the coast joinder than t a the Butis^u cla . mstothe or(ierillg of affairs in Central and had nevei chall r we wer e moreover on amicable f ra 1 a ;dth VuS' and a shonld be averse from anything in the nature of terms - 'A^ ottoman Government, but in his comments on the report intrigue against t. pointed out that as the Porte seemed disposed of this n S If Sstment of matters relating to British interests in the to be mtracto'lo ^ ^ .„ noreibn ga . ud ' s attitude. His personal authority Gulf, v e oonld not ■ i „ , vc n f 0 entertain cordial it distant relations h Uh g him The Foreign Office, however, decided that it was in,possible at that time to swerve from our policy of strict non -interference. . , + • . t Two vears later ibn Sa'ud, without the assistance which he had tried to nhtain from US thon-b he was credited throughout Arabia with having secured obtain tiom us, i =&gt; . ted with o U t difficultv the small Turkish garrisons and establXd Wmself'on the coast at Qatif and Ojair. Captain Shakes pear on ht re urn to En-land in June 1914, from a long projected journey across Arabia n the course of which he had visited liiyadh bore witness to the strong ir^onal domination which ibn Sa'ud's vigorous and commanding personality ? i PctnVilishpd and from other reports it was clear that he ^as legaided bevend Ws own fimitier°the coming man. He proved more than a match c : iiipffpotive efforts of the Turks to retake the Hasa; they resorted to diplomacy and opened negotiations with him through Saiyid Talib of B^ra . Earlv in May Tal'at Beg had formulated m private conversation atthe British Embassv the expectations of the Ottoman Government m terms which seemed to his bearers little consonant with actual conditions He proposed to estab lish a strictly delimited frontier between ibn Sa'ud and ibn Rashid, place repre sentatives of the Sultan at Riyadh and at Hail, and rely upon ^ e ^ officials to control without the aid of force the actions of the two Amirs. As for tie Hasa, ibn Sa'ud would be appointed Mntasamf of the province hnt the collection of the customs would remain in Turkish hands and lurkish garrisons would be replaced in tne poits. Nothing was more certain than that ibn Sa'ud appearance on the coast must' ultimately bring him into direct contact with ourselves ^hethe. e ■welcomed it or sought to avoid it; and this anxiety und t % la y accelerated the action of the Porte. But at the moment Turkish fea s ve e groundless. We were concerned wholly with the conclusion of prolonged ne tiations with Constantinople touching interests m Mesopotamia and the bu which were of vital importance, and were less inclined, if possible, than bet for Arabian adventure. We made a friendly offer of 7' 11 ® h nto ^ 1 refused, and when, in April f^l Is the Amir met the British Agent, Colon Grey, outside Kuwait, he was given to understand that we had it eluded a comprehensive agreement with Turkey and could ho^d u hope of support. Ibn Sa'ud was thrown back on his own f. s0 ^ es ', bu ^„f„ lf were considerable, and the secret treaty which was signed in May by m™se and the Wall of Basrah, fell short of lal at Arab Bureau, 8th October 1916. ^(icip^jonS. He accepted the title of Wali and Military Commandant of Najd Avhich was offered to himsel an his descendants as long as they should remain loyal, and engage 0 n ; n Turkish flag, but he was to have charge of the customs, on behalf ot the ut ™ . Government, raise his own levies and provide the garrisons for Qatir an j * Deficiencies in the Najd budget were to be met from the customs, and no re from any local income was to be paid to Constantinople until such time as was a surplus—an eventuality of doubtful occurrence. But while exercisij, his own territories an authority which was in all but the name that o an ^ pendent ruler, his correspondence with foreign Powers was to be con ^ solely through the Porte, and in case of war he was to come to the assis a f O J the Sultan.4 the terms of which were drafted forthwith. They included a guarantee of complete independence on our part and an undertaking on the part of ibn Sa^d that he would have no dealings with other l owers except ^^er re f ere nce to the British Government. He informed Captain Shakespear that he had been in communicaiion with the Sharif and with the heads ot the northern 'Anazah confederation and that they were resolved to stand together. He was iK^ldii^in detention a party of four envoys sent by the Turks to urge him to ioin ibn Hashid in a jihad against us, ^ut after consultat^ SVinl-esnear the Turkish mission was dismissed with the reply that ibn Easlnd s Ws were camped within two days of ibn Sa'ud and that there could now be no Question of peace between them. On January 17th a messenger arrived from Mecca bearing a letter from the Sharif's son'Abdullah wno wrote that the Sharif had been called upon to proclaim the jihad and was temporizing till he heard what line ibn Sa'ud proposed to take. Ibn Sa ud made answer tha he saw no advantage to the Arabs in joining the Ottoman Government and had himself dismissed a Turkish deputation empty-handed. N Upon the reports sent by Captain Shakespear from ibn Sa ud s camp, Sir Percy Cox was authorised to proceed with the negotiations for the treaty, but on January 24th battle was joined between ibn Sa ud and ibn Rashid and Captain Shakespear, unarmed and present only as a spectator, met his death. Ibn Sa'ud's version of the disaster was that he was shot dead by a Shammar rifle -bullet, but this statement is in any case based only on second-band in formation, as it is undisputed that Captain Shakespear had taken up a position in a different part of the field than that where his host was located. Since then various and divergent accounts of what happened have been recited, one of little more value than another, but the balance of evidence soes to show that he was first wounded in the leg and disabled, and soon afterwards killed in the charge of ibn Hashid s cavairy which overwhelmed the flank on which he was posted. In the saave qui pent which ensued it is feared that he was either abandoned or forgotten, but the precise circumstances of his untimely death will probably never be ascertained. Ibn Sa'ud expressed profound regret for the loss of one whom he regarded as a brother, and always refers to him with respect and affection. The action was indecisive; both parties claimed the victory and both were temporarily crippled and forced to retire. It was an unexpected and a somewhat disconcerting result, for ibn Sa'ud^s preparations had been made on an exceptional scale and his forces were said largely to outnumber these of ibn liashid, though he was inferior in cavalry. _ The accounts given by the Arabs attribute his defeat to the treachery of the 'Ajman. Ibn Sa ud s personal courage is beyond question, but he not uncommonly falls short as a tactician, and Mubarak of Kuwait pronounced him to be a poor leader in battle.^ But if he had not dealt ibn Rashid a crushing blow, he had at least put him out of action and prevented him from joining the Turks, as he unquestionably w r ould have done. The intervention of ibn Rashid in the early part of the Mesopotamian campaign might have added considerably to our difficulties. Nevertheless Captain Shakespear's death was a heavy price to pay for the advantage of immobilizing him. The two chiefs held apart without further hostilities till the summer when an agreement dated June 10th w T as concluded between them. Ibn Rashid recognised ibn Sa'ud's claims, except that of overlordship which he could scarcely be expected to acknowledge, and undertook Arab Bureau^herewith enclosed. not ^ ^ ^ treacherous game towards the Turkish Government but to incline towards whichever Government was in alliance with ibn Sa'ud. He confined his own jurisdiction to Hail and its villages and the Shammar tribes, while ibn Sa'ud was acknowledged to hold all Najd from A1 Khahaf to Dawasir. A1 Khahaf is no doubt the Kahafah of Hunter s map, a little north of latitude 27°. In a tribal country the adjustment or frontiers can never be very exact, but it is clear that ibn Rashid renounced all pretensions to the Qasim, a province whose rich oases had frequently changed hands. It is of interest to note that the tribes reckoned as subject to ibn Sa'ud are the Mutair, 'Ataibah, Harb, Bani 'Abdullah, 'Ajman, Murran,agression from foreign Powers. O.i his side ibn Sa ud engaged to liold no ^eorrespondenoe with any foreign Power and to grant no conce^ons to foreigners, to keep open the roads to the Holy Places and to commit no aoyrtssive act on other Shaikhs under our protection. D ' Ibn Sa'ud was unaware of the exceedingly confidential correspondence which we had been carrying on with the Sharif during the winter of 1915-me, but the results to which it led could not hfn o him indifferent. Rulalioiis between the Hijaz and Najd had been dictated by conflicting sentiments. The Shirif had even mere reason than ibn Sa ud to feai the links, but lie was iealous of ibn Sa 'ud 's position as an Arab Chief, and the feeling was reciprocated in Kiyadh. The fluctuating allegiance of the tribes is a rich source of discord in Arabia, and the absence of any defined frontiers enhances the uncertainty of claims and obligations. In 191J the fehant Abdullah, asseitin- that he acted on behalf of the Ottoman Government., marched to the borders of the Qasim for the purpose of re-assertmg an authority which was probably a thin- of the past and must at the best have been shadowy. The tangible results of the raid do not seem to have been more than a re-msistance on the Sharif's suzerainty over the distant sections of the Ataibah, a tribe which had once been under ibn Sa'ud but had largely seceded to the Sharif. 4. smull tribute to Mecca from the Qasim villages was ^ stipulated for by 'Abdullah before his withdrawal, but it is unlikely that it was ever paid. Prom 1913 the Sharif showed strong anti -Turkish proclivities, and before the outbreak of war he and Ibn Sa'ud drew together. They were in correspon dence when Captain Shakespear paid his first- visit to Riyadh m the spring of 1914. In January 1915, they were acting in conceit, and ibn Sa ud told Captain Shakespear that in his view the Khalifate would revert to the family of the Prophet, of which the Sharif was the representative, if it dropped from the hand of the Sultan of Turkey. In TViOvember ]915, Abdullah reappeared in Najd, with what object is not very clear. His own explanation was that he was sent on a mission to ibn Sa'ud, with the further purpose of collecting dues in the Qasim and Sudair. Except for a doubtful suzerainty over wandering sections of the 'Ataibah, the Sharif does not seem in Beduin estimation to have rights in either province, his limits eastwards being some where between Longitude 44° and Longitude 45° at Sha'arah, Duwadmi, Jabal Dhurai and Jabal al Nir. 'Abdullah is not reported ^ to have advanced much beyond Sha'arah : he collected dues from the 'Ataibah, subdued the small allied section of the Buraih (by origin Mutair) and returned to thr Hijaz : but ibn Sa'ud, barely emerged from a perilous contest in the Hasa, not unreason ably regarded the expedition as inopportune and even suspicious. (These sentiments were reflected in his conversations with Sir Percy Cox in December. He reminded the Chief Political Officer that the Wahabis recognized no Khalif after the first four, and was careful to add ^ that if the Sharif should assume the title it would make no difference to his status among other ruling Chiefs.) In June of the following year the Sharif rose in open rebellion against the Turks and declared the independence of the Arabs. Ibn Sa'ud, writing in July to the Chief Political Officer, , ■ „ „ 3 „ acknowledged the receipt from him of Arab Bureau, 2nd August 1916. official news w ith regard to the Hijaz, expressed his satisfaction at the discomfiture of the Turks, but put forward his own apprehensions that the Sharif might proceed to claim authority over parts of Najd, and in support of this fear observed that in declaring the inde pendence of ' the Arabs ' the Sharif appeared to treat them as a compendious whole, an attitude which he regarded w T ith anxiety. In August he wrote again, saying that he had now received a letter from \v*h tw pnn ofu a f iQ-R the Sharif in which the latter announced gus ' ' the occupation of Mecca and asked him for his help. Ibn Sa'ud gave a summary of his reply, and a copy of the original Herewith enclosed. letter 1138 sillce been received. He assured the Sharif that he would render all assistance which was in his pow r er, but asked for a written undertaking that the Sharif would abstain from trespassing in his territory or interfering with his subjects. Ibn Sa'ud went on to ask Sir Percv Cox whether hismmmmammmmrn i j) ^ . i. i * flfi pmild not hope to exercise tlie mfluen.ee over Shaikh W tSat practised and weighty diplomatist ilm Sa ud n hich had 1 before Mubarak's death relations between Ids father ; ™oveoyer for some yeai^ hetore^Mulm Riyadh and the negotiations between himself and the Ottoman Mubarak s attitude du _ 0 , l01 ? Accordmo* to his account the Shaikh had Government in the spring ot 1914 Aceordm to atf r s s c ;nrx 0 s :ri ttJ ^ -d advised iba m April Mubarak c 0 Tirks refusino*, at the same time, to be Sa'ud not to come to tenns ^ i , a ^ Sf 'g 0 indignant was the Amir that he present at his meeting wi 2, . gfakespear that Mubarak should not be con- expressly stipulated with given to the 'Aiman was suited in the negotiations with aml i n pgie ibn Sa'ud Aiab Bureau, stb April 1916. complained of the incidence of the transit dues which had been, from time immemorial, levied in Kuwait wi.ilp ihn Sfl'ud's anxietv as to the ambitions of the Sharif, and h;s growing estrangement fldth KuwaH shoAved that the chiefs allied with ourselves had not from otherTourcra of^he^despatch oi' 'an agent (Muhammad) Taufiq ibn Fara'un of Damascus, for the purpose of buying camels for the Ottoman Government; the emissary was well chosen, for he was a personal friend of ibnSaud and had visited Naid on the same business the previous year. But on this occasion uaa visueu J.iaj tlje Am . r was p resse( i by us to prevent Arab Bureau, 19th September 1916. f r om obtaining camels : he accord- inclv arrested ibn IWun, confiscated WO camels which had been purchased siss- - i.... ^. t Tu1:T—!£ Arab Bureau, herewith enclosed. another attempt to stir up ibn Rashid against us was in the wind. Kushaid ibn Lailah, ibn Bashid's representative at Constantinople, joined him at Hail with a few German and Turkish officers a small body of Turkish soldiers and some guns; accounts varied as to tlie exact comnosition of the mission, but its presence in Hail m some form seemed fairly certain. Ibn Sa'ud had written in September that he wou.d be glad ol a personal interview with the Chief Political Officer to discuss the q u esti on of co-operation with the Sharif or offensive action against ibn Eashid. I n . 0c ™oer he repeated the request urgently, and on all grounds it seemed advisable to accede to it. Sir Percy Cox met him at Ojair on November 11. lbll!5a ™ explained to him his position in detail. He had lost considerably, m ai material, in the fight with ibn Bashid in January 1915. Since then he had been almost continuously in the field, first against the 'Ajman and t en agams Murrah. Most of the normal trade of Najd was with Syria, and the tribes were accustomed to sell their camels to Damascene dealers: the strict bloc vac e Imposed by ibn -Sa'ud—the seizure of ibn Para'un's camels bore witness to its reality—gre\s more and more galling : tbe Najdis grumbled, the tribes wer restless, all asked wherein lay the aivantasre to themselves of their omet s attitude, and it was increasingly difficult for him to keep them m hand. i regard to the Sharif, Sir Percy Cox was able to give ibn Sa'ud the tuiiesT, reassurance. Our treaty with the Amir had been communicated to i. j and when the Sharif announced to us his intention of proclaiming himselt King of the Arabs on November 5, we had insi&amp;ted on a formal admission 11a claimed no jurisdiction over independent rulers. The news of the corona ion at Mecca, had not yet reached Central Arabia and was not discussed. Uurmg conversation with the Chief Political Officer at Basrah ibn Sa'ud maae passing remark about the Sharif's calling himself Sultan but his mm seemed to be set completely at rest, on hearing that his rights were sareguar e by us and that the Sharif bad explicitly denied any design on the indepen en of himself or his compeers. Ibn Sa'ud having expressed to tbe Chief Political Officer at their meetm^ at Ojair his inclination to pay a brief visit to Shaikh Jabir of Kuwait e returning home, the project was cordially encouraged as appearing eminen j .■. fi 10 'Resides this kiiittinEi: together of Arab leaders, the meeting at Kuwait has d reduced certain immediate results. In the first place the extent and nature nf ihn SVnd's share in future hostilities with ibn Eashid, if such should occur, was agreed upon. He undertook to maintain 4,000 men under arms : if ibn Eashid moved in force towards the 'Iraq he would move up parallel with him towards Zubair and join the friendly tribes and a contingent from Kuwait He informed the friendly Shaikhs that he would support them if ibn Eashid threatened to attack them in strength. If, however, ibn Eashid should remain at Hail ibn Sa'ud would harass and attack him as opportunity offered, using the Oasim ^ a base. In view of the strain upon his resources during the last two vears he has been given 3.000 rifles with ammunition, as well as four machire suns and granted a monthly subsidy of £5.000 to cover the expenses he will' incur in maintaining his men in the field. Active co-operation with the Sharif was not considered practicable, but ibn Sa'nd was ready to send one of his sons with some 40 men to Mecca as a sign of good-will, it the Shauf ^ould make a special request for them. Secondlv, a letter was written by ibn Sa'dun, in the name of the three chiefs to 'Aiaimi ibn Sa'dun urging upon him the harm which he d r;in g ' J to the Arab cause by his present attitude, Arab Bureau, herewith enclosed. invitin 0 ' him to enter into communication with them and promising him friendly consideration and an opportunity for honourable submission. Finally, with the co-operation of Shaikh Tabir of Kuwait and the diplo matic skill of the Shaikh of Muhammerah who was throughout of the highest service to the Chief Political Officer the delicate problem raised by the presence of the 'Ajman among the friendly tribes reached a satisfactory solu tion. For the period of the war a truce between ibn Sa'ud and the 'Ajman was agreed upon and instructions were dratted defining the position of the 0 fugitive Shaikhs with respect to all tribes Arab Bureau, herewith enciosei. under our protection. On his return to Basrah, Sir Percy Cox called in the 'Ajman leaders. They had been pro foundly disquieted by the advent of ibn Sa'ud thinking that it augured ill for themselves, but the principal and more courageous headmen met the Chief Political Officer at Zubair and accepted the proposed terms, in return tor which they were promised a monthly allowance similar to that received by the other friendly Shaikhs of the Shamiyah They evinced little doubt that the remaining headmen of the 'Ajman, including the two who were still with 'Ajaimi, would come in as soon as they heard of the happy issue of their own venture. Letters have been written to Fahad Beg ibn Hadhdhal informing him of the Kuwait meeting and inviting him to join the league of Arab chiefs in expelling the Turks. These have been sent through a man from Fahad Begs tents who was in Basrah at tie time of ibn Sa'ud's visit and went to see him at Muhammerah, where he received advice and instruction from Shaik Khaz'al in full measure He was entrusted also with letters from the Shant which have been waiting opportunity of despatch to Fahad Beg, Hachim al Muhaid, 'Ali Sulaiman of the Dulaim and others, and with presents in money to guide Fahad Peg's decision and to encourage the smicable disposition ot the Shaikh of the Dahamshah, Jaza'ibn Mijlad. Communications of the same nature are on their way to 'Athah al Qulal of Kajaf and JViuhammad All Kamunah of Karbala. M Jitll tfoj ' II r Enclosure No. 2. Copy of a translation of an Agreement, dated the 26tli Rajah 1333 {10th June 1915), beticeen Shaikh Abdul Aziz lin Ahdur JRahman al Faisal, Muler cf Najd, and Shaikh Saud bin Abdul Aziz bin 11 ash id &gt; Amir of Hail and Shammar tribe. (Note by bin Sa'ud.— This is a verbatim copy of the paper executed bit ween myself and bin Eashid.) In the Name of God the most Merciful and Compassionate. This is the agreement between me Sa'ud bin Abdul Aziz bin Eashid and Abdul Aziz bin Sa'ud. That is to say. % foiiare. &lt; ' _Thev have in these days sent to me messengers with letters asking that I will amnesty them. But I know that they do net really aim at a truce nor will they make confidence in me, on account of their bad deeds in the past which are not hidden from you. They hope to deceive me and thus attain their purposes, and by wasting time make off to any other place they like. More over thev are ignorant, their knowledge and control being in the hands of Dhaidan and Khumsiyis, who is now with bin Rashid's men and with bin Saedun. The former is their overlord and they do not act without his orders, while the latter is influencing in any way he wishes. I have, however, granted them amnesty, provided they come to the direction of Najd, and provided their Shaikhs come to me. It is probable that they will accept that. My intention is to clear them oS from this direc tion for if they remain on this side, they may cause disturbance in one of the two following ways;— Either they will be at the bidding of bin Rashid and bin Sa'adunatany time they like, or else they will certainly aggress on my tribesmen, who will then be forced to pursue them. As I have mentioned above, it is known to you that operations on this side which arc in youi hands will harm some of the tribes. If therefore you think it better that they should clear off from the side of Zobier and ICuwait, I should find it, too much more convenient as I depend firstly on God and secondly on you, and am acting in pursuance of your orders to me, and secondly because the harm caused by tlieir remaining there Avill be great. Interested people or persons ignorant of the real facts may say to you ; ' I am afraid that if they go they will side with bin llashid or with bin Sa'adun, and then some hostile action on their part may ensue. As regards the possibility of their joining the said individuals they are looked upon as some of their very subjects, and it is only by the previous machinations of bin Ilcishid that they have become so, may God confound them. Therefore I wished now to express to you my thoughts, and there is no doubt that you are more careful on my interests than I am myself. Also your policy must have been w T ell acquainted with their affairs in relation to bin Eashid. I have, to say the truth, stated too much, for which I request you to be so kind as to forgive. May the Creator keep you safe and may He protect you. (Seal.) Dated 22nd ThiUKidah 133d—31st September 1916, N ote .—A solution of this question—the feud between ibn Sa'ud and the 'Ajman—was arrived at the personal meeting of bin Sa'ud with Shaikh of Kuwait and Chief Political Officer at Kuwait on November 21st, 191(5. Details of terms as solution follow. P. z. COX, 26th November 1916. Chief Political Officer, Enclosure No 4. Translation of Utter from Sir Khaz'al Khan, Shaikh of Muhammerah, to- Amir Abdul Aziz ibn Abd-er-Hahman al Faisal al Sa'ud, dated 19th October 1916. In the Name of God, the Compassionate and Merciful. After profound salams: This is to enquire about your august health. As regards ourselves, we are, thanks to God, quite well and happy. While expectant of good news of your success and prosperity, we received with the hand of affection your letter, announcing your well being, and weourselves very fully in cementing the friendly relations of our three families and descendants, for we feel it i s our duty and obhgatron to do so and your man Abdul Aziz ar Eobai will certainly corroborate the regard and accord he has experienced from us. Ind we are pleased to learn from your brother, Shaikh Jabir, that you have a mind to proceed to the place of all, Kuwait. Please God tins good news 'which I was fflad to receive, will take shape, so that, iiishallah, we may meet you happy and in good health, and may be fortunate, to see your countenance. iWXIN Enclosure No. 5. Translation of a letter from Sharif JTussain of Mecca to Abdul Aziz ibn Saud, 6th Zill Qoiada 1334. After compliments. Your Honour's letter of 13th ShawalLas reached me and the contents have been understood, and what you mentioned about the continuance of your good health has pieased me. But as regards your observations, they can only emanate from a man bereft of his reason or of an absent mind. But thank God we are capable of enduring more than this from persons of less amount than you, and this time it is one 0 duty to bear it also from you. But O ! Eather of Turki, it' you believe in God and in the Day of Judgment it is to be denied that you should not busy yourself with what there is no cause for. You see that I am convinced that we are co-partners except in regard to what God has forbidden. This is the right and the truth and there is no mystery behind it. If you realise this and rid yourself of doubt and suspicion (which are not right on the part of people like yourself) this is what is to be expected from the sagacity and perspicacity of persons such as you. Be it otherwise, I shaU realize that God has given you up, and there is no method in His will. But tbe request will demonstrate the truth. At any rate we are waiting to see how you have carried out what we communicated to you in our letter sent to you by Homaidhan, which dealt with the Asaiba and their news. This is what had to be explained and on (?) of the above it has been written. Seal of Sharif. P. S. —Your letter and its enclosure are sent by us enclosed herewith so th^t you may reflect in w T hat you wrote to us in them. As regards what you desired us set forth in the enclosure, if God has dispersed your doubts there is in my opinion no need for it, while if your doubts are still being revived by the intentions of ibn Paraon and people like him, then there is no use in it, for the result in writing in that sense will be that I shall receive from you a letter asking for its cancellation, just as you have asked me now to cancel what you wrote to us in this sense, and which Nasir bin farhun brought to us under your confirmation, and which is in our hands. And God is with us and with you in good fortune. Seal of Sharif of Mecca. Enclosure No. 6. Translation of letter from ihn Sa ud to the Sharif of Mecca, dated loth Shawal 1334=loth August 1916. After presenting you with profound salams, and praying for thee that God may rest on you his blessings always, and after offering our obligatory regardsand respects to you, we be? to ^tatp fW patched to your honour, in which we told vi/wlnt 118 ^ ? lettei ' was des - Your Honour ( ma y God „ y0U wh3t was su ffi™nt, based on its foundation, and the fouSornf .!r 0 ^ S ^ ei ' e ^is Truth. iounaanon ot religion and of the world is And we (may you be pi'eservc'U in fii, r , , correspond about matters of which io^e are nnft. P e , witl1 y ou God, with any intention that there should be anv elfn 5 h 11 18 not ' P Iease But we see that whereas m-inv ,,fangement between us. with you and you belieye what they tellTotraTb ai]d illter ? sted P eo Ple are we are convinced that the real facts will ^ Ci,, 0 ? me su fP Icious of yet of enemies and people in general, which cannot pnd' C01 ' tla 5 t to the gossip with you in a manner which should neither disnlew v' 3 ' an We 1137,3 dealt to you, and we will follow you for better or Cwwl y 110r Cause P^judice After the departure from here at . . Twaiq, the messengers whom we had sent with' 1 ! 6 ' Il ' 1 Homaidhan and bin was thaf they should incite the 'Ain.ah ^ ties lavished gifts 0 on 11 thmn^parthJuUrl^in 1 '^ ^ presents. No doubt from information which has'renchld^® €xa oSerated matters and are pleased (with their experiences) ' 7 But our servants have, undoubtedly annriserl ,.r i i , Turks, at which every Moslem and Anb Ma . i • ? c,0Ile b y the became established and known to me that'their ® e y es f disgust. It Islam and of Moslems and especially Arabs and tTthe ? anEihiIatio11 o f that we should resolve to be sincere to v'rm « J t therefore incumbent any case, so that, iushallah, we may attain our subject andthat r ^ y0U ia found our enemies. Thus we shall not be blamed and } may con ' energies and shall not have cause for regret 1 ' 16 ' ^ Saa11 ^ concentrat iug our 'Omy God, forgave me and my plrenTs^.^ eve ' 1 m tie invocation we say increased last year by brothef Abdulbih 'ail d 6 !)v hi''' 1 /' S , , ? etween us ' which was contumely and his abuse of our reLioLn^ with the Easul (may God bless him) said, ' In the event of arT' that thingmore'than 11 :— 0Uld unders * aild that wo do not mean by these words any- (i) That God may help you and us, that we may co-operate in the question of this religion, and (ii) That we are afraid of what we have seen of the actions of the pre sent Government towards Arabs and towards the mosques, which they have turned into quarters for troops. Their on]y obiect is he destruction of Islam and Moslems. Also when we saw their activities m these expeditions, we were exasperated at it. ^ 0Ur ob j ect was io a ^ain worldly ambitions or achieve our own merests, you are aware of how others are exerting themselves. All that we16 desire we can have, but God refuses that we should prefer our worldly interests to the zeal of Moslems and Arabs, and —• (Hi. That we rest assured in regard to your attitude,^ as we already mentioned, so that we may actually co-operate with you to our utmost power for the benefit of us all. Except on these terms, there can be no permanent understanding between us, especially regarding the question of interference with our tribes and subiects. So we request you to accept what we say and hear with it as advice and that you will perform what we ask in order that, insliallah, the purpose may be achieved and that co-operation may be afforded. This is what was necessary for your information. Please convey our salams to your noble sons, lierej our respected lathei, and oui brotheis and sons salute you. May you be preserved in safety. (Seal.) Dated 13th Shawal 1334. Enclosure No. 7. Translation of a letter dated 24th Dhill Kaj 1334 {22nd October 1916) from Abdul Aziz bin Abdur Rahman al Faisal bin Sd &gt; ud i Huler of Najd, etc., to the Hon'ble Sir 'Percy Cox, Chief Political Officer in Iraq. Previous to this I sent you some letters dated 15th Shawal 1334 (15th August 1916), 10th, 13th and 22nd Dhill Qaadah 133^ (9th, 12th and 21st September 1916) in wdnch I informed you in good time what w T as necessary to be communicated, but I regret to say that I have not received answers to them as yet and am indeed wondering at the non-arrival of replies, for your honour is aware that the continuance of correspondence during such days is a matter of the greatest importance. I therefore hope that the answers are on their way to me. You have already been informed that I have detained bin Faroun in custody and seized the camels he bought for the Turks. I have also made more strict the blockade against trade, and communications generally, with the Turks everywhere in my territory. In opposition to this action of mine, the Turkish Goverment sent to bin Rashid 25 (twenty-five) German and Turkish officers accompanied by guns (cannon), arms, and other necessaries and also about 300 soldiers and bin Ilashid%5 agent in Constantinople, Hashid bin Laila, and two days after arriving in Hail, the aforesaid Rashid proceeded with two German officers and a Turkish officer towards Iraq. Up to date 1 have not got information as to the movement of Bin Rashid and the soldiers mentioned above; but I am watching their movements and surely they will attempt some advance. I would a^so state that I would like to have a conference with you for which I have made up my mind to be in Hassa on the 10th of Muharram 1335 (7th JNTovember 1916). I request you to send an immediate answer as to whether I can have a chance of meeting you at the place you will fix and the time at which you can get leisure or else you will let me know your opinion. According to information I have received about the movement of the troops in Medina, they have given up the idea of marching to Holy Mecca and have fortified Medina with trenches. They have also taken steps to protect the railway and have also kept troops in Medina for defence, and the remaining soldiers whom they wanted to send to Mecca have returned to Syria. This is all I know and only wish the permanance of your friendship and the continuance of the news of your welfare. May God preserve you.i r« '31 that he himself has no intention of interfering. You need therefore have no on this point. It may not be hidden from your Honour that at 3-30 p m to-day our friend Shaikh Jabir will have a majlis at which I shall have the honour to decorate him on behalf of His Majesty the Kmg with the Order of the Star of India, and I trust it will suit you to he present also so that I may have the honour of delivering your own decoration at the same time. May you be preserved. Enclosure No. 10. In the Name of tlie Compassionate and Merciful God. prom Abdul Aziz ibn Abd-er-Eahman A1 Eaisal to the Hon'ble Sir Percy Cox, Political Resident of the Persian Gulf ^may his eminence be lasting). 'After enquiring about the health of your sound disposition, I received, with nleasure vour highly esteemed favour of the 20th November 1916, and ?read it with pleasure and good hope, for it informed me of the arrival of the tele-rams from His Excellency, blis Britannic Majesty s Secretary of State, and also from the High Government of India, which explained their gracious inclination towards your true and sincere friend on his investment with the Eminent Order of the Knight Commander of the Indian Empire, m token to their confidence in my loyalty and helpful attitude to the cause of His Excel lency the Sharif, and my firm agreement with your Great Government. I became extremely pleased with their gracious condescension and His Majesty's high regard. There is no doubt that this is due to your extreme kindness and appreciation of the sincere and loyal. Your Honour stated that His Britannic Majesty's Government, in their dealings with His Excellency the Sharif, were careful to reserve my rights, and that His Excellency the Sharif has no intention to interfere with my country and territories, which are confirmed as under my control since years. I am, anyhow, tranquil thanks to the presence of Great Britain, and the state of affairs*between me and His Excellency the Sharif will be according to your wish, viz., that I should agree with His Excellency, though, thanks to God, my accord with him has been manifested since old times, for His Excel lency is the Eather of Arabs. I am waiting to-day for your presence in the majlis which will be held by His Excellency, my dear brother, Shaikh Jabir: and I'll be honoured by your delivering to me the Eminent Order. Our meeting with our brothers. Shaikh Khaza'al Khan and Shaikh Jabir, is one of the greatest fortunes and pleasures though, thanks to God, we see one soul: and you will, inshallah, see all what will please you in our eternal union &gt; In conclusion, I offer best wishes for your Honour, together with my heartfelt thanks. (Seal.) May you be preserved. 23rd Moharram, 1335. Enclosure No. 11. Translation of letter from Abdul Aziz ihn Ahd-er-Rahman al Faisal to Shaikh Ajaimi al Sa'adotm, dated and despatched on or about 30th November 1916. mlatioti i ^ Ik co After compliments. As regards ourselves, thanks to God, we are quite well and happy, and our affairs are, through the generosity of God, very prosperous and such as would please you.BfotllGI* ! God }in q 'F q r&gt;i I -Jf ^ 4 -s\ 1 instant, in good condition of VeaTth ^ my t0Wn K:un ' ait 0 ' the 22nd meet my honoured brother, Shaikh T T ha PP 1 , I1 . ess - And my ohieet is tn Kuwait) and to renew, inshallah, tLe perpe'tual'a! 1 ] 1 ' 8 Sdooes8 j on (as Shaikh of our heneflt, prestige and happiness and thank, f-n p 0 ^ aad co - 0 Peration for coincided with the presence of our pt L hwi i ^ 1 rov «lence, this our meetino- so that we were greatly pl eas ed. We W fl n'^i + er, . 8hai th Ehaz'al Khan' what will conduce to the honour of ArX ,} de f ermln ed unanimously to do And this your present aUiL ^ eUhanCe t,leir S'^tness^ own interests and those of the Arab ^e senSl' 8 -T- llarmfuI to y o 'r on us to explain to you the portent of it 'for incumbent as one of ourselves, and belong fo one of H,* JiT' . I Mother, are reffarded wish jou prosperity and tranquillity and dia.aitv 1,. + ' ab eIemeu ' s and we ourselves, m regard to every des,v7w 0 ? y J . Ust as we wis1 ' them for reputation of Arabs, honours them, anf weservpsTh • nC ?- Wllich P ro mote S the will not be attained except by meetbi^ 7^ , lgnit y ; aB(i this end co-operation between us all. oS aiid undertakings and sincere characteristic Arabian '^alitws^you wifni 0l I I |' co ?^ dellce in your zeal and promotes the good name of the Arabs and their S( i? aud . grati . fled whatever reputaton. And we all expect from vonr ti oriour ' ari d enhances their meeting with us on this basis, because weZli^ I1?Ur aCCOr ? with us a because such a meeting will have a l^n fi ? ln i ^ our ^-^bian zeal, and auspicious result for ai{ of us. ^efioial and desirable effect and an You should explain to us all fliof i ourselves in your place in regard to all matters an(i P u t you m respect of honour and interests. If thmi ^ 0U concern this is the object Of our desires'; if not, JeshaU be^ wT Pt ^ VieWS ^ abov ™ for we have explained matters to you bv wav nf absolved ^'om responsibility pray to God for a satisfactory and auspfcious result Th' - §ulda n ce and we explained. . We request you to convey onr lln T V s f hat 1)3(1 to be respected friends already referred to saiute you ' mS ers - Hi re, the And may you be preserved safely. ' (Seal) ABDUL AZIZ ibn ABDUH RAHMAN ai, P j IISAL, Dated the 26tli Muharvawi 1335. Enclosure No. 12. Translation of set of instructions to le -Uriajir, bhammar Adam and 'Ajman. With the consent and approval of ibnSa'udand the Shaikhs of Kuwait, Novem her 1916. which on the tribes inter-tribal differences and PntL • f Brl tish Government to sink their Order to coCrat^ with tbp t I 'f• ^ p 8 ' a § reeme nt with one another in Dhafir tribe and tbosp of th t i OTe , rnt ? eut ' 0 n these conditions the a united attitude and should t Tawala ' and the A J™an tribe, should adopt n viotTT- + should abandon differences existing between fhpm ™u h a new to earning the satisfaction of the British Government or nomads 6 'fn t0 ^ ^^ahitants of al iarid, either townsmen nomads, and similarly the people of Aarid are not to raid the 'Ajman. Kuwait tn nl w man slla11 not raid the Arabs dwelling in the Nigrah (i.e., from -sas ass sst-jSLsr*' *• «• - «-* - •««»mmmmBimmn ■■ — 4. All tribes who are subjects of the Amir Abdul Aziz A1 Sa'ud (the near and far), ^ho ply to Kuwait with earaTans, shall be free from molestation both going and coming, even the tribe of Lmtair. 5. Outgoing and incoming caravans of JSajd, '^hich carry away merchan dise from Kuwait to all towns of Isajd shall not be molested. 6. Should any of the'Ajn'an who are with 'Ajaimi start raiding, the friendly 'Ajman shall not allow them to come near them nor help them in any way and shall not mix with them and none of them shall join the raiding parties of the friendly 'Ajman, except those who may come over to live with the latter and become part of them. 7. The tribe of Umtair, both those who are located at their own camping places and those who go on raids from those places are not prohibited from raiding the 'Ajman and vi r e versa. 8. Should the 'Ajman seize any of the Umtair trade caravans exporting goods from Kuwait, they must restore the same completely and if Umtair seize 'Ajman's caravans they must likewise make restoration. 9. None of the friendly 'Ajman shall send any of the goods which they get from Khamisiyah, Zobeir and Kuwait to the 'Ajman who are with Ajaimi. 10. They shall not be friends with enemies of the British Government, such as Ajaimi and the Shammar Aabdah, but shall raid them. 11. So long as the above terms run into force and the 'Ajman adhere to them and remain obedient to the British Government the Amir Abdul Aziz bin Sa'ud will not molest them, and they can rest immune so long as the Government are satisfied with them. jo r Enclosure No. 13. Purport of Chief Political Officer s remarks wJien delivering decorations. I feel greatly favoured by fortune at having the honour on behalf of flis Majesty the King-Emperor and His Excellency the Viceroy, to invest Your Excellency Shaikh Jaber with the Companionship of the Star of India and Your Excellency Ibn Sa'ud with that of the Knighthood of the Indian Empire. I have been commanded when delivering to each of you these decorations in their behalf to express to you at the same time the ajipreciation of His Majesty's Government of the co-operation and accord w 7 hich we have received from your Honours since the beginning of the war. It is a great satisfaction to His Majesty's Government to know from me that you Shaikh Jaber have the firm intention of following in the wise footsteps ot your distinguished father whose statesmanship and length of view made him famous among the Chiefs of the Arab States—while as regards your Honour, al Amir, it has been a matter of much gratification to them to know that the relations between Y r our Excel lency's family have been confirmed and cemented. It is my good fortune to find our tried friend Shaikh Khaza'al here at Kuwait, than w T hom no one has deserved better of the British Government, and'it is a source of great satisfac tion to be able to feel that at this time we are all bent on one common purpose, to which we are quite confident of a successful issue. I beg to offer you my congratulation on your decoration and hope I may be spared to see you win further distinction. 3. G. P. L, Delhi - No. 801 F. &amp; P. D. 6-2-17-10. 541 Wnote on THE 'AQAIL. The Aqail are all men of Naid hnf organization. They are professional neutrals who^ld Tti ^ 0116 tnbe n0r h: ' Ve they any trib '' 1 ' the capacity of merchants financing their own ^ ^ 0 '' th&lt;; clesert ' Aether in 'Aoail and of other merchants an Z ' 1 ^ ^ ^ * ** ' fcI - - zui, ' rti in the towns. 'Aqail or non-'Aqai,. to buy ca.nels and sheep from the tr.L' t I are knowledge of the desert and of (he tribes and the fact th m ; Qnahhcat.ons — who are not .mphcated m ' Arabia, where every tribe is at eumity with its neighbours, it is essential to I , In the 'Aqail who can safely pass from one tribal district to another Th I 1 C ^ men desert tolerably secure, they enable the tribesman to sell his animalsLVto 6 orail such commodities as he needs. In order to preserve their neutral character men of b t k av tt u ' a a -i t ^iitiracter, men of bitj tribes snoh as the Harb or Ata.bah, are not allowed to become 'Aqail on account of .h • • t - The settled popu.at.on of the Oas.m, who are oflar'ious ■mportance as un.ts are best suited for the purposes required, and it is from them chiefly ^ are drawn. Any man of this kind coming up from Najd and engaging in desert traffic or service is recogn.ed as an Aqaili. Some families, like the Bassam, have been 'Aqail for two or three yls ^ 0therS ■ RUmaih ' ^ beCOme » the O' The capitalist class of 'Aqail. generally known as Jammalah, are to a large extent settled in Zubair, Baghdad and Damascus, but thev retain nn Jnf + n . , , ' mey rCta111 an lntinia te connection with their relatives in the Oasim and work in partnership with them. They may even form a network across the desert like ne assam who have a house in Damascus, another in Zubair and many representatives of the I 'i the 0 • lS,n, • a11 Playi '« i' 10 olle h-ds. The chief business of these merchants is camel-buying ; they pay partly in money and partly in goods brought from the towns. They are a so camel owners, bring up their own caravans and buy goods from the towns, supplying them to e interior. It is obvious that this traffic can readily be extended into supplying Syria, or any other par of enemy territory, with goods from the 'Iraq, and the 'Aqail will as gladly supply enemy tribes -ch as the Shammar, as tribes friendly to us. In war time the professional neutral is a suspect.' e movements of Aqail merchants should therefore be watched carefully and reported. The poorer class of 'Aqail. the Zuqurt, are exceedingly numerous, but they are less important •tan the 'Aqail merchants. They will take any job offered to them, irrespective of blockade regulations, but they do not initiate trade. They can be dealt with in connection with the caravans which they accompany. 'Aqail servants and guides who are found with suspect caravans should be given short shrift. A list of the principal 'Aqail families is appended.LIST OF CHIEF 'AQAIL HOUSES. Bait DAKUU.—Originally from the Dawsir. Jarullah. Sulaiman. tztt. m *—- - - -—— - B ait B assam- B . Taminjron, 'Anaizah anA Buraidah. This family forms a pretty complete net over the whole area of 'A 'r at Damascus, Zubair and in the Qasim. They are camel 1 ^ ''' W ' th members and the 'Iraq and traders in that region They do U '' J ' leaders between the Qasim 1 hey do ' ot come up as far as BaRhdad. B ait R awwaf— B. Tamim, come from Buraidah. Jasim, now in Ba g hdad. but wants to move to Basrah, probably finds work short here c: z:':' Damascus ' now in '• 1 ^ --—-^ B ait al ' A ssaf. I think there are representatives in Basrah • u sran , the Baghdad man has recently died leaving sons who are not grown up. weaving sons B ait al K hunaim—5. Tamin from 'Anaizah. Haji 'Abdullah in Baghdad. He used to have some IS camels which he hired out. Is now impoverished; is said to have discontinued desert traffic and does a little trading in Baghdad. B ait ' A li al L ahm— From the B. Khalaid. Ibrahim, in Baghdad, but a very old man. Nasir, in Hit, where he owns a garden. This family is no longer of importance. B ait A bdullah al N ujaidi, in D amascus. Ihe following live with the 'Anizah and have no permanent habitation in any town. Isa Rumaih—He has quite recently become an 'Aqaili. Deals in camels and purveys for the 'Anizah. Muhammad al Madhi abu Rus. Ali ibn Hazza. Other well-known Damascene 'Aqail are Shami al Dhiyab, 'Abdullah Hulaisi and his brother Salih, Ali al Ribdi (from Buraidah) and Daud ibn Sulaiman al Salih. Ibn 'Aqab mentioned by Colonel Leachman is unknown here. Sulaiman al Dakhil had not heard of him. S.G.P.Bd—753—1,187—60—14-12-17.- *JL ■ 0 :yi) -'3/7. Tale-ram From To Eepeated No., Dated R. Political Bushire. Civil Comniasioner, Baghdad. Political Bahrain. 1144. June 10th 1920. Bahrain letter dated June 3rd 149-C. Last para. As far as I know there is no explicit guarantee, but in this particular conection it is interesting to note that in 1901 we helped Shaikh Mubarak stave off Bin Rashld and Turks whose enmity he had incurred by helping Bin Sa'ud family. See page 1087 Gazetteer of Persian Gulf et sea:. Telegram From Tp Ho., Dated R. Political Bushire. Political Bahrain, Hl+C June 10th, 1920. A/ou-^ C Following from Koweit^ Begins Ends.What do you think of this bit of news? Trevor. /* Tel©j egram R. From To Mo., Dated Political Koweit. Political Bakhire, Civil Commissioner. 42-C. June'9th, 1920. It is reported on authority of Abdullah Nafisi who has retur- -ned to Koweit, that Bin Rashid has declared^on Bin Sa^d. Latter has warned Qasim people to be ready but they are un twining to fight side by side with the Ikhwan. Political. Telegram R. From Political Bushire. To Political Baghdad. No., 1146 Dated !^ei June 10th, 1920. Have repeated Koweit telegram No., 42-C to Bahrain and asked him what he thinks of this information. &amp; Trevor. i j I ■ ■B| i - 1 I i a'0 1 i i -t-h 6i/e. Telegram K, . litteal Kowelt* «cree «®r. Civil Coral SS ioner Baghdad. iOlltioal Sushire,,and Political Bahrain, ^0 • J| d''--a lated Jua© £!7t: 1 receive;' 29th 1320. Report h. _lovoa hero on th. authority of nion arrived froa Ihn Tawaah that a large force of Bin Sa 'ua 's men froa Cuaaibah attacked Sharaar a' Shuaihah,75 Biles Horth-Wost of Qusalbah,on June , t .i. Bin i-aBhld » o ran at Adwah tvionty alios East of Hall receive;! pnevious inforcation and told Shualbah people to await attack but to send away their tonts. H© took all his troops to their aseistance and arrived at Shualbah in time to make a counter attack on 3in Sa'ud's force which he routed and pursued for nine mttmm hours,inflict5-ng great loss* It is also reported that,but not believed,people of Buraidah refused to allow the defeated force to enter the town* Political 9f 3- D Tel0gram#Code» From ~ Political, Bahrain. To - Political, Kov /eit. Tep ated Baghdad and Bushite. i No.171, Dated and received 'Oth June 19 20 , four 40-0 not confirmed, here. It is certain however that Bin Saudis standard in charge of his brother has been in Qassim for somt time. Political.i T0legran,Oodo # F toh — Political, Bahrain® To - Civoom, Baghdad® Repeated Political, BuGhire, Ho.l82-C # Dated and received 5th Ju^y 19^0« Bin Saud writing 3:!rd June states certain meribers fanily sick request Harrison visits Riyadh have replied that Harrison in India Wj.ll no u return 3 months have referred matter to you# Quas aib 1 Imovra nothing of siclmosc among family Bin saud he hints doctor possibly required for wounded® As Bin Saud ! s letter is couched in rather urgent 'torms I think it advisable you sent him telegraphic reply. For your information, Br Dame newly arrived from America is here though he ignorant of Arabic# Have said nothing to him yet # Political. ,'T-i .&gt; n .'0 61/6 Telegram From To 53/7. ' R. Political Koweit. Civil Commissioner Baghdad. Repeated. Political Bushire and Bahrain. No., Dated 49-C. July 5th.tree eived 6th)1920. Yesterday Sheikh received letters from Bin Rashid and other Shammar chiefs confirming the news reported in my telegram no.,46- &lt;Terms of alliance offered by Bin Sa'ud to Bin Rashid,which he would not accept were friendship with his friends and war with his 4 enemies, vyhen asked who enemies were envoys said Shereef and Shaikh of Koweit. Shammar are mobilizing against Bin Sa^d. Political .6l/6 &amp; 55/7 Tel ©gre.m, 0 o de &lt;, From - Political, Bahrain. To - Civcora Baghdad, Repeated i/olitical Bushiro- « Koweit* No.18770. Dated and received nth July 1920. Letter from Bin Satid dated 28th June complained of youth- fulness Biii Rashid a-id his inability restrs.in certain section^ Shammar from raiding his subjects. He had been compelled to send his son Saud with strong force to punish raiders. Saud pursued and came up v^ith them six hours from Hail and severely handled them recovering all stolen booty. Bin Saud sends above for the information of trusts also reply to Ha3 questions will be sent him. ' J; 1 t t Political,n—ifcw QONFIDENTT AT., /-3/ v 15^ /7 FOlitioal Agency, Bahrain• r/ ^ Dated the 26th July,l980e TO ihe oivil Cofi2ii £ }3iQ^03« 701 B A Cr H u A D« ^ y — y MEMQKiiNDuM . bui ject; # jhaii-ai iibdullah, O.I.E., the youngest son of Shaikh Isa of. Bahrain, has given me the following inform ation, which X send for what it is worth. The report has also been confirmed by three wall to do travellers from Kuweit ana is to the effect that dhaikh Salem of Koweit has been making secret advances to the Shaikh of Mohammerah, Syed lalab of Busrah and Bin Hasohid, with a view to obtaining their support against Bin Saud. Syed faleb and Shaikh of Mohammerah have promised their support, and as an earnest have sent respectively ten horses and seventy horses (mares and horses) as presents to Shaikh Salem# The nature of the support promised is not stated. Shaikh 3alem has also invited uhari bin Twala to come into Koweit territory and camp in company with Ali bin Khalifah, nephew of Shaikh ^alem, at Itehara as a precaution-* ary measure, uhari bin Twala has agreed to do this* Shaikh Abdullah further states that there are indications that the Shareef of i4ecca. Bin Has chid and Shaikh Salem of Koweit are in communication with one another the general intention being to check Bin Saud 1 3 increasing power, the immadiat© object to prevent him going to Mecca by threats of war and invasion. The above stories appear to be not much more tlan gossip,but, perhaps, are worth report- t lng * VV^ . Major, C.I.E., political Agent, Bahrain. Copy forwarded to :- D.P.H., Bushire. Political Agent,Koweit.1 Np V T\ nn y A * i IAL. Toloaraa (PJ From Political, Kuwait,. To Civooa, Bagliaad. Mo. 6iS G. Dat«a astli. July Jpgtf, Cliari l a Sawalah arrived in Kuwait yestsrday and is tlie gu ®st of Shaifeh Salim, Hs raports tha d«feat of Ibn Sa'ud'a forces by tla# Sliammar in Qaeia about a month a-o, of which I had prsviouBly heard va 0 ue rumours. Sa'ud, Sa'ud's son, fled to Riyadh, Qasis is vary anti-lfchwan. A mesa anew from Hufuf reports great discontent in Hasa, Even Ito Jaluwi blames Ibn Sa'ud for unduly favouring the Ikhwan. The Shaildi has imprisoned the man as an impostor, and promised him a reward if the story ptovjs to be true, and punishment if it Proves to 'b® falat. Addressed Baslidad. Smt hj post to Bualxire and Bahrain, TJ ¥ Ths Deputy Political Resident, Bushiro, The Political Agent, Bahrain. •Political Agency,Kuwait. 28th, July t92o. yjs~ a ~ * o. \ Memoranda'; A copy of the abov® telegram is sent herewith^ -—Major, Political Kuwait. ■ V-.J- ■ - ■ IiFIDENTIAL. Telegram (je.) -64 } From Political, Kuwait. lo Oivoom,'Baghdad, ^ Mo. 71-0. Dac.ea 1st#, August 1920, Reference toy teloeraa «o. oo-G, laragraph X. betters frora Qaaii, dated )utii .uly received here yesterday disprove the .report. There -as not been any fighting since the affair at Shu'aibah in oas middle of June, which latter is confirmed but appears to have oeen a smaller affair than originally reported. Addressed to Baghdad; posted to Bushire and Bahrain. 4' ^V Political Agency, Kuwait. I at, August 1y2u* The Deputy Political Resident, iBushire.^ The Political Agent, Bahrain. US...QRAltD 'Ji,i. A copy of the above telegram is sent herewith. ol.tyuz-t / ^ —— i^ajor, Political Agent, Kuwait,»53/7 ■ Telegram R From Political A^ent,Koweit. Civil Commissioner, Baghdad To No 37-C. August 50th 1920. Dated Local feeling against Shailvh Salim is grov/ing very strong, due to loss of trade through the Quarrel with Bin Sa'ud and to his incapacity as a ruler and his total lack, of tact. The following brief incident has aggravated the matter: Shaikh sent Pidawis to arrest a youth from the influential family of Saqaijwho was guilty of offence. Fidawis v/hile 'bringing him through the street beat him in a brutal and degrading manner before the Shaikh had seen or sentenced him, but when told he commended them. All, including the Saqar family,agree youth deserved punishment-,but object to Fidawis being allowed to take matter into their own hands. I believe much revolutionary talk is going on, all wanting to be rid of Salim, and the majority favouring Ahmad bin Jabir as successor, but a minority wanting Shaikh Hamad. Several -people have independently asked Mylreafe private advice regarding the possibility of getting Salim deposed, last scheme being to offer throne to Ahmad bin Jabir, and then for him and a representative deputation to. visit the Agency and ask us to depose Salim. Llylrea has put them off. I consider Ahmad bin Jabir would ^ a great improvement on Salim as Shaikh, but I presume we must morally back Salim as far as possible. I should be glad of inst- -ructions as to action in case of revolution actually taking place, or in the unlikely event of joint representative deputat- i -ion takxHJ? asking British Government to remove Salim. . Political Koweit,Telegram From To Repeated No. Dated P. Civil Commissioner, Baghdad* Political Bushire, Bu ehire, Foreign Simla, and India Office 10540 London. August 31st received September 2nd 1920. It is no u, ±n my opinion, the custom for us to accord moral support to the £haikh of Koweit against his own towns-people, nor is tnere any treaty to that effect. On the other hand his behaviour,up to the present time, has not been such as to just ify our talking active measures to depose him, either on our own initiative, or at the request of the towns-people. It is our policy to support the d_e fax to ruler, but it is his business to feettle with his own people. Until the receipt of orders from the Government of India y the above principles should guide you actions. You should inform the representative deputatjo n, in the event of this being formed and it visiting the Agency, that the behs.v- iour of the Shaikh has not been such as to justify interference in the matter by the British Government, though it is admitted that it has not been satisfactory. You should inform the Shaikh of the tenour of your reply, (previously having informed the deputation that you intend to do this). At the same time you should urge him to right himself with his own towns-people, and explain to him that his attitude towards us since he became Shaikh of Koweit has not been such as to justify me in recom mending to Government of India that eh should receive our act ive support against his own towns-people. We shall allow matt ers to take their course and restrict interference on our part to the offer of protection to him against physical harm.^ The present quarrel with Bin Sa'ud seems to be largely per sonal, and it that it is 'not impossible that a more satisfactory arrangement, than he is likely to make, in the interests of the principality of Koweit, might be negotiated by his successor. , • v./-\nn^ PDmrnpnts if any, to the same addresses Bushire should, repeat conimwiioto, ^ as this telegram has been directec. Civil Comm- This refers to Koweit telegram no. '7-0.Telegram F. From Political Bushire To Political Baghdad Repeated Political Koweit, Foreign Simla and Foreign Office Your view of the attitude that the Political Agent should t8&gt;e in regard to the dissension between the Shai&gt;h and the towns-people, has my entire support. I have only one suggestion to offer, which is almost to be assumed. The words 'and to protection of British lives and prop erty in the event of disturbances' mig : t well be added to the end of the third paragraph. This refers to Baghdad telegram no,10540 of August 5 1 st. No 1592 London Dated September 2nd 1920 Trevor,I ' Telegram R. ! From Political Agent,Koweit. * * To Political Eushire, Repeated Civil Commissioner, Baghdad. Political Bahrain. No. 94-C. Dated September 7th received 8th 1920. Your telegram No.156?. Report believed here that on Septem ber 1st pirates from Jubail boarded a Koweit pearling boat bel onging to Saqar, while watering at Kamisah, murdered the Nakhuda name Ibn Ubaidan and seized the boat. The rest of the crew .jumped overboard and took refuge in other boats. Also rumoured that a Bahrain boat was boarded a few days before but was not molested when the pirates saw that it was from Bahrain, The Political Agent Bahrain is said to have enauired into the latters case. Political. \ i Telegram Code. From Political To Political Repeated Political Dated September No. 293-C. Koweit telegram no. 94-C. Nothing is known of incident. If story true it would have reached Bahrain which now-a-days seizes upon any story against Ein Sa^d with avidity. Political. ■ M \ ■ ; ■ 'fiift- «i' Telegram B. Froin Political Agent Koweit. To Political Bushire. Repeated Political Bahrain, and Civil Corami~sioner,Baghdad. No. 97-C• Dated September 14th aid received 15th 1920. My telegram No.94-C. Boat in question, a Shuai,has returned to Koweit and crew state that on morning of August 29th while watering at springs in sea. called Ghamisah, a Jolly-boat and a Baoarah approached them, each one from ishk side, and opened fire on them. The Nakhuda was killed and the rest jumped overboard, whereupon the Pirates boarded the Shuai seized, everything including pearls and 1,400 in cash. They promised the crew tr lives if they came on board which they did. They were taken to Jubail and detained there eight days whilst the Governor communicated with Ibn Jilawi. They were then released and all their property returned, except the cash was R s 310 short. I have examined twelve of the crew independently and am satis fied that the story is not fabricated,. Political.-K ^ v ^ f J*-' QOUPIO C'T'i'IAL. No • g-G f Politic tl Ag-^noy, Bahrein ■)at94 the 14th jaDtentber, 1? To i e:S:snf ^StOf^n. . _ H r . f* political Agent, , .Jc^'ej-Xc ao«i*»iJd iaite. K 0 W E IT. ■•enoa your 94-G, rlatQ'l 7th Sopter^bsr, 1920. x havs made very careful enquiries on the aubject, and I think I have run the true facts or the origin of the story to Harth, at last. About Ist Jsptember a Koweit pearling boat, Nakhuda o:ae Abaidan ( this corresponds with the nane of your ran) ouru into -Jubail to ^et water^ with na^iy othet* pearling boats. The spring fron which fresh water is drawn is in the oaa ( we have several such in Bahrein). Whilst a crowd of boats were all trying to get water atonce a fracas arose between Abaidan and the crew of another pearling boat, both of whom wanted to be the first to draw water. In the scriTainage that followed several on both sides were wounded and Abaidan the Hakhuda was killed by a rifle shot. Abaidan though resident in Koweit is a subject of Bin Saud. The question of 'pirates' never came in at all, and the fracas, though happening at a snring actually in the sea off Jubail, is similar to 'rows'* which not infrequently take T )lacs at wells in the desert. Jubail people are, at the beat of it, rouprt Uedouins, not far removed ^rom desert-men. I donot think the Incident neei be looked upon as any thing more than accident. I am proceeding to Jubail myself shortly, and will further inquire into the v story. Fajor, O.I.g* political Agent, Bahrein. V' Copy to; i).p.R, 8ushire\) reference ^oweit's No.94-0 of 0.0. Baghdad) 7th September,1920.'// 5&gt; / 0// / • b R. Political Agent Bahrain. P o I xl. leal Agent Koweit, Poli tical, Bushire, and Civil Commissioner,Baghdad. 207-C. September 13th received 19th 1920. Koweit telegram No.97-0, See my despatch number 303-C in post. Quarrel arose over water Nalrhoda, man Zilfi,Nejd subject of Bin Sa^d. Amir^Tubail dismissed as result of incident. No question of Piracy. Political. Telegram B'rom To Repeated No. Datedv/ «*■' r i) 61/6 and 53/7. Telegram R. trom Politioal Kowelt, TO Politic a1 Baghdad• Pepaatod Political 3a irain and Bushire. T^o. 1B2-C. i-ated a November Kith received 14th 1920* Three Aj/man n' !?ed Naif (cousin of Dhaidan),Abu Kilab and Paqm have separated themselves from Ihaidan and come over to Ibn Subah with their following of one hundred tents their camels and sheep. They have just arrived Koweit end say Abu Thaar (pres- -umably Abdul Azlz-al-Turkl) who is camped with Hhaidan in Sudah asl^ed latter to poison them f but he only made a pretence of trying to do so•Shaikh has just received letter dated October Clet t from Bin Rashid to the effect that-firstly he had successfully raided the Akhwan near Dak-- (?) on the Casim border.Ibn Mudhai- -yan # Hanayah and Fardah who followed up party were defeated. Secondly Ibn Shalan recently tried to take Jauf but Bin Fashid's garrison defeated him with enormous loss capture of two guns and large Quantity of munitions of war also his own mare from which it is thought that he may have been killed. Political. Telegram R. From Political Koweit. To 'igh Commissioner Baghdad. Repeated Political Bahrain and Buahire. Dated November 15th received 14th 1920. So. 193-C. My imnediatly preceding telegram.Names of Ajman shaikhs should Second- , &lt;&gt;&gt; be as follows, -Nahar -al -Mutalaqqimj First -Naif -bin -I !ithlain; r hird Ubaid-bin-Mishhah, and also a fourth Huzaiylm-bln-Laskah. f * Political.I 53/7. • Telegram From To Repeated Ho. Dated R. Political Kowelt. H1 gh C-mmi ss i oner, 3ag 'idad, Political Eushire and Bahrain and Basbah. IBR-C• November P9th received December 2nd 19P0. My immediatly preceding telegram. Report apparently exaggerated It is said that meeting was merely in concert with Shaikh Zubair would nelp to oeara,a(mutilated groups),who had claims in Zubair, Political. .FROM Sonior J-ptrai rr i.aval Officer, Persian Gulf ■-• . j . 'iftiAD', at Basrali. TO High CoaEi.sioner, Baghdad. (Copy oo Bushire, ) DAJH 6th BQV. 1920. KUKBES - I assi-t nt ; received oy ne from an officer assistant surveyor, i i: the port directorate Basrah, by najce EADRI, an ex-Turkish naval lieutenant. ...ho info-ration here/ith was collected by hip at Eoweit when he was there in lEDUSTaY early Hoveitber 1920. Sir, X have die honour to state that on according of the information there are sorce Turkish officers and civilians among bhe Arab tribes ./ho have formerly been in the Mesopotamia area and Kejid in Turkish periods^ I may humbly mention their nusros and career as I know, i. s .j o r Omer l3,xzx son of Araf Pasha es'*'' over nor of Damascus, belonrii G 'to the Young Turks Committee. His duty wa.3 to distribute money to the Tribes and incite them against cne Dritisa government. He was sent to Kejid by the lounG Turks Committee for consultation and settlement with, Ibn Suooud in Inarch 1914, Gol Baha Bey also belongs to the Youno Turks Committee he ,lso proceeded to Mesopotamia in Hay 1914 to incite the Tribes against the British, Cr vilian Sami Dey of Adrianople /ho held an high aosJbts position amors the Young Turks Committee and also the best friend of Taalat / Pasha was appointed as Governor of Kejd April 1914 but ovring to the outbreak of w r couM not proceed there. (Signed) Kadri (A ft /V 'T Ji-e- D », T t— vt.r.s* : U ti. i Captain; Senior maval Officer, Persian Gulf. □52/7. ^ Telegram From n t ■'•o Fepeated No Dated • ^-confirmed reriort says that Bin Sa'ud has sent for Dawish and that latter left his camp South-to est of Safah foC Riyadh on November 21st. Political. r n • Political Koweit. : -igh Commissioner Baghdad. Political Bushire and Bahrain. '&gt;90-0. November roth received December 2nd 1920l/ * S3/&lt;ry Telegram From TO repeated No. Dated Po High Commissioner,Baghdad, iolitical Rent Aoweit. . ^ olltlcal -gent Bahrain and .olitical Bushire. (Mutilated) 0 Decoxiiber ord receiveo 4th 1920. I have assurances fror Bin Sa'ud to the effect that he will not make, an attack or. r.oweit.Ho request for Husalabah as yet has been made to the Shaikh,upon that understanding with Zubair, under the present circumstances x am not prepared to issue virtual prohibition. This refers to your telegram no.ie^-u dated November PPtft 19S0. High C 011 i 3 i ( 1 f r nf) I ^ k- ^ y 55/7 55/57 T0l9frram R • From Hirli ConTnlssloner, ap;hdad. To Political Kowelt. I opoated Political i'ushl ro. No, Dated January 5th received ^th 1981. Your tele.^rarr ^o,5-0 and riunh-ire telegram ' o#21 • I have exaniinod correspondence and agree with esident* Fleaoe warn Shaikn accordingly , and toll hlir? that he is only building up further trouble for himself by a^ain collect -ing a large force at Jahrah, also remind him that it is the Port and people of Koweit that H.M.G.have to consider, and I find it difficult to believe that his lownspeqie are in favour of his present policy# inds. P ersonal ♦ Please inform me what feeling is in P ouoit now as regards Sallift's doings and policy. Cox. Telegram K. (Pty) From Political Koweit. To Political Baghdad. } epeatod Political Bushi re• &lt;-&gt;&gt; J Dafcsi 6&gt; y j, No# 10-C* ^ tour telegram io.iefl-S. I an oomstunloatlng your message to the Fhaikh. Public opinion In Koweit does not seem to be opposed to fal- -im's present policy regarding Jahrah.People do not trust lim Ba'ud 1 s promise that he will not attack .Koweit and they xxa* regard Jahrah as an outpost for its defence. Kesent is of course felt at recent levying of men,but it is against t in Ea'ud rather than Salin. Gome bitterness is aVOg felt against us for not bringing pressure to bear on Bin Sa'uc. hie fooling which was strong at time of battle of Jahrah but died down with arrival of H«K,Ship and aeroplanes,is Increasing again now.S^m people are delighted at rumour of raid by Dawieh nearZubair at? they argue thi b will force \is to brin^: pressure on Bin I hPd hopec? that Shaikh Khazal mi^ht give Salim useful advice,hut or. sounding him I saw greatest ( g{ ) Salim right in employing seceded tribesmen,etc. Political. $ Group omitted. Telegram P. From 11 i gh Co mm j s s io n e r. To Political Kov/eit. Repeated Political bushire. No. 1«B~S. ^ated January A th received Fth 1021 Your telegram Januray fth re jushire (telegram^ 21. Yes,that is position temporarilly; (corrupt * roup) object must h: » to reconcile parties and get them to agree not to harbour each others secessions. Please endeavour to get t-alim to real 12. • .. -ness of his position at present political juncture. It Is contrary to our politics .and wishes that he should get entangled in intrigues with Shereef and Bin Hashid for the. purpo of attacking Bin Ba'ud and he will come up against us in so c?oir as long as he maintains correct relations with -in Sa'ud we cn t give him a good deal of moral support to prevent .in Sa'ud arno^ -ing him. On the other hand if he insists on quarrelling with 131 Cy'ud in the interior we cannot give him effective help and aro only concerned to ^rotect port of Kcweit from attach. If no pgr in his present course our only remedy must be to find a shoAKh who will manage his politics better than ralim does. Fo not male any threat to him from me,but try and reason with him yourscl- the above lines. High Commissioner.P3/57 and 575/?. Telegram F. (Pt.y) Prom Po 1 i ti eel, VoYi el t, 1 gh Co^nl 8?;loner, • ar.bdad. PoUiticp,! Dushire, 21 - C » 10th received 31th January.19S1. Tc Fepeated No. Dated -■'y telegram o• 1 C• On January 9th,very day after visiting me and writing me letter. Shaikh sent for several leading merch- -ants and said he wanted to collect more men to send to Jahrah. They refused and said he had enough there already. However,men are being enrolled on wages today,but have not been sent so far, I said in my telegram o.lft that people were not opposed to Balim's policy; this is still largely the case theoritically, but in practice when it comes to g i-ng or providing men themsel- -ves they are i5»s;xiRi 'beginning to think differently. There is S also section of people who think all available men should be concentrated in Koweit for the defence of the town itself, and that three or four hundred are enough for Jahrah. Few of latter even see large force at Jahrah is a positive danger,being merely challenge to Faisal. It has become 'known too that a lar^re force is contrary to our advice and most think it silly to oprose this. I'eeling against Balim is getting very strong again,and revni- -utionary talk increasing. They realize that he is chief obst- -acle to peace as the whole quarrel is a personal one between kx him and Fin Sa'ud; and whatever be the rights of the case he, is simpler (two corrupt groups). PoliticalI • ^ •&gt; 7 '&gt;■? Tolegram R. From Political, Kuwait. io, Ilign Coraaissioner,Baghdad. Repeated Bushire. No.44/c Dated 12th received 13th February 1921. y immediately preceding telegram. Have Just been saying good-bye to Khazal before going to Basra tomorrow and in course of conversation he said what a good thing it would Salxm w,..ie to sot up council similar to what I had heard was being discussed. From what he said I rather fanc/y he started, idea# He returns to Mohammerah as soon as Tvy arrives. PGlitioal. V %53/7 Telegram R. from High CoirmiBBioner,Baghdad. Poll cal # Kowei t», To Repeated Bushir© # /Vo lif-S , Dated 14th redoived 15th February 1981. ■ Tour 43/C. I agree with reply on lines you suggest but with following modifications of language. Say as deputation is aware it is not normal policy of His Majesty's Governemtn to intervene in internal affairs except in case of some glaring Jilece of raisgovornimWi or to safeguard British subjects and interests but in view of recent difficult situation and its lively importance to interests , of Koweit you are sure you will havemy approval in advif ing Sheikh Salim to xdiiut accede to their rupresentaiions and 8ummon(?) small council of advisers. n —-Telegram Code, Prom - Political, Kuwait t© ao f nis3ion ^J Baghdad. Copy t© Resident, Bushire. No. 471. Dated nth received 12th August 1921. A party of Dhafir who belong to Bin Suwad Raided near lahrah on 7th August and carried off 04 c ^...elo oaring to ixiiv/ait Beduines and about 120 belonging to Ajman.Telegram P. From Political,Kuwait. To Basra and Baghdad. Repeated Resident,Bushire. N0 .142/C Dated 5th. received 6th Septeraber 19E1. Your telegram of the Srd September. Shuaib which is 8 hours west of Jaharah was raided by a party on 20 camels and they captured four herds of camels. The pprty was under the command of Sulbi Alafnan of the Dhafir and Muhammad -wajaan of Shammar and said to be connected with Bin Hadhal• Politi calTelegram R. Froa Political,Kuwait. To High CoiiTiissioner,.Ba ?^L ^ai. Repeated Bushire. N0.I66/C Dated 7th receive# 8th October 19^1. There is much talk in Kuwait about loan of 60,000 dollars, which Sheilrh Ahmesi has just na^e to Bin SauA, which is not first loan since his acession. I think Bin Sau«-, who appears to be more in neesi. of money, will continue to exploit Ahiae^ as long as he can ret anything out of hia, ani that Ahmed, with his absolute faith in Bin Sau$, will ®:o on tryin?; to supply his neeis as lont; as he can raise money. As every one else loolrs on money l^flt to Bin Sautl as lost for ever, this is likely to lead to trouble between Ahmeel ani rest of Subah family - if not with townspeople. Political. Telegram F. From Hi^h Commissioner,Ba*h#ad, To Political,Kuwait, Repeated Bushire. No * 10 2)9-8 Dated. 8th- received 9th October 19S1, With reference to your telegram Ho,166/0, It is an inconvenient but very delicate quest inn and I hare?ly advise your 'oing more than cautiously getting some influential friends of Sheikh Ahmei to try to convince him of, the folly of risking his money in this way. High Ooamissioner.Telegram P • Z^v From Political,Kuwait. To High Ccmmiesioner,Baghdad. Repeated Bushire and Basrah, N0 .114-S. ^ated 16th received 17th July 192£}« A party of Asian Shammar and Dhafir undevjone Nuraan of the latter tribe made an unsuccessful attempt on the 5th July to raid a small number of subjects of the Sheikh of Kuwait who were at Kuwaikib 11 miles N.E, of Jahrah• i Political•r- y: translation of a letter, dated the 2ist Safj.r i3 4 i ( ia th October less ), froDI M.E, th. Shaikh of Kuwait to the Political A^ent, Kuwait. ^fter complimentB. I told you verbally yeeterduy, l? is had bin Zaid al- Kuhailan, a subject of mine living in Kuwait, was , roceedln 0 with a friend of his to the Shaaoar tribe with money and goods, as detailed in the attached list, with which they Intended to buy sheep to bring to Kuwait. On the eth -afar - th rfa*x September) a raiding party of the Sa'id section of the Dhafir under Muhammad bin Salhwi came u,on them at a Place called Lamkh, between Wac-bah and Ansab. and robbed them of all the money and goods mentioned in the list. ' the tribe In question is living under the 'Iraq Government, i think it best to report the matter to you with the request that you will communicate with the proper au^iori- tiea on the subject, and I trust that you will endeavour to__ ^©Ij tii© stolen sytjy r , 0Cov0r , Gci, Usual ending* i^lst of goods stolen from rahad bin Zaid al-Kuhailan of Kuwait by the Sa'id under Muhammad bin Haihan at Lamkh, between Waqbah and Annah, on the 6th Safar 1341 (..?th September 1822): 4ir dollars in cash. Icj Large Water-skins„ 1 Bales of American ^awahi1'Cloth* 4 Bales of 'Mardhuf' Cloth black &amp; 2 red}, 1 dozen Head-cloths, 1 Bag of Coffee, ^mall Water-skins, 6 Buckets, 6 Cow-hides, // 'Su/wU'tQ-S o-f &amp;&gt;iT? lbs, of Cardamom, 2 Riding Camels♦ 1 Pack Camels</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0001c5_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/480</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0001c5</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/480</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 53/7 X (D 54) Kuwait Affairs, Bin Saud (Captain Shakespeare's Deputation)'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1915/1923</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-08-28T09:39:12</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (218 folios)</extent><extent>File is arranged in chronological order, from earliest at beginning of the file to most recent at end.</extent><extent>Foliation: There are two foliation sequences in this file. The most complete sequence, which should be used for referencing, is circled in pencil, in the top right corner of the recto of each folio. It begins on the title page, on number 1, and runs through to the last folio of writing, ending on 208. The following foliation anomalies occur in the file: f.1 is followed by ff.1A-C.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains correspondence regarding relations between the British Government and Abdul Aziz ibn Abdulrahman ibn Faisal Al Saud [‘Abd al-‘Azīz bin ‘Abd al-Raḥmān bin Fayṣal Āl Sa‘ūd (Ibn Saud)]. The correspondence also discusses political developments in Kuwait including the deaths of Shaikh Mubarak Al Sabah (f 76) and Shaikh Jābir Āl Ṣabāḥ (f 138). Other regional rulers including Khaz'al Al Ka'bi, the Shaikh of Mohammerah and Shaikh Ḥamadān bin Zāyid Āl Nahyān, the ruler of Abu Dhabi are also discussed in the correspondence.The file contains a detailed letter (ff 2-10) to Major Percy Cox, British Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, from Captain William Shakespear, former Political Agent in Kuwait (and then acting as Political Officer on Special Duty). The letter discusses Captain Shakespear's recent visit to Ibn Saud and outlines his attitude towards the British Government and lists the advantages of making Ibn Saud "a British vassal for good". The death of Captain Shakespear at the Battle of Jarrab in January 1915 is reported in the file on folio 26.The file contains correspondence between Major Cox and Ibn Saud regarding the development of his relationship with the British Government and Ibn Saud's attitude towards the Ottoman Empire and Germany. The file contains a précis regarding relations of the British Government with Ibn Saud from January 1917. The précis was prepared for the Director of the British Government's Arab Bureau in Cairo by the Bureau's Chief Political Officer in Iraq, it contains copies of a number of relevant letters and agreements between the British and Ibn Saud.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x0001c5#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>