<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00038d_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-18T00:04:26.096Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">D#0#H0* The Tolitical A{^ney, Bahrein \i[£ June 1929. My dear Belgrave, Yesterdays perfonuaiioe in the huharra^ Baladiyeh hc.s oontinoed me of the desirability of introducing a system of provident funds ibr all State and Local fund employees as mxm as possible. At the present moment, neither State nor either of the Municipalities have any control'their ^aployees, '&amp;lq beinj non~pensianable can down tools a:id depart like day labourers should it suit then to do so. I surest that if State policy does not admit of a pension scheme on the lines of other Governments, a rovident fund v/ould aisv^er the purpose equall well* The form I su prest is one that I have introduced i.n several places where I have been stationed, vis: a co tribution of ~/l/~ in the rupee by the em^^loyee and -/~/6 by the State. The proceed is put into a Post Office C. Dalrymple Bel rave Lscmire, Adviser, idirein ./’ovt# Bahrein savingssaving® bank account* which the employee is unable to xiaadle during his service without he permission of the State authorities, and as soon as a useful balance is obtained it is L vested in lost Office Cash certificate*, I think you considered that this oeasure ai(jht first be introduced in the State offices and afterv^ards into the i unici alities* I co .cur in this view, and su ; est timt snould any employee make any difficidty over accepting this innovation ( it nd ;ht ^e intpduced by a decree of His .ncoellency the Shaikh) his inore* raents sight be suspended until he a reed, provided that he was not serving on a contract which recluded such a step* If you wish to send me the conditions you think of imposing on those funds I siiall be very picas- ed to inake any sugjostioiis that occur to no* ihe principal ones should I think be that the employee WDuld not normally be enti led to the State contribu tion unless he completed a term of y ars, say three or five, preferably the lattor and gave six months notice of his resignation and that in the event of his beingconvicted by a properly appointed Criminal Court for any aisueBieanoor or offence n ainst the State he would be only entitled to nothing or to such interest in the total sum of his fund as the State mi, ht decide* ine incroi ants tfiic'i have been rocoia; loaded tor the 3;aladiyeh should be ^ranted subject to their ultimately becoming liable to such a rule. fh-is concession of-/-A&gt; would not of co ree nminally be granted eoccept to individuals permanently in the sen-ice of Government or a Municipality, and the scheme need not he Bade applicable to persons who are on the ver e of retirement. Yours sincerely,— .^ r — - - - ' ^ ^ ^ ^ * Bahra in, Persian Gulf. Dtd, 9th Beby, 1930. Dear Prior. I enclose herewith two copies of the Bahrain Government Provident Fund rules as desired. Yours sincerely, LTHE BAHRAIN GOVEFTBAHT PROYIDEM 1 FUIH). 1. This fund is for the benefit of officials employed in the various deportments of the Government of BJxoain. i The Secretariat and Land Department li Customs and Import Y-.rd iii Wakf Departments iv Education Department. v Municipal Departments vi State Police. and such other persons who may be permitted by the Gov ernment to participate. 2. Participation in the Provident Fund is obligatory upon all officials upon the permanent staff in the ser vice of the Government of Bahrain earning A 50/- Rupees Fifty Only, per mensem or more, excluding allowances. 3. The contribution will be monthly ond will be calcu lated on the monthly rate of each official who will contri bute one anna for each rupee of pay per month, but not including allowances. 4. The Government of Bahrain v/ill contribute one ho If anna for each rupee of pay per month of the incumbent, but not including allowances. 5. The fund wil] be held in trust by the Bahroin Govern ment and will normally be administered by the Adviser. 6. The contributions of each contributor will be de ducted monthly from his pay by the Head of his department and will p^id to the trustee of the Fund who v/ill add to it the contribution of the Government. This joint amount will be lodged in the Indian Post Office Savings Bank, on behalf of each contributor so that the contributions will immediately begin to increase for the contributor.7 7. ''hen the joint contributions accrue to Ks ... the sum will be withdrawn from the Savings Bank and re invested in Indian Post Office Cash Savings certificates to be held by the Trustee on behalf of the contributor, 8. ^t the expiration of the contributor’s service with the Government of Bahrain, these certificates, together with any balance in the Post Office savings bank will be handed over to the contributor as his absolute property, but subject to the following rules, and such further rules as the Government o' Bahrain may think fit to announce. (i) No contributor will be entitled to receive or deal with any of his contributions until he has com pleted four years satisfactory contributory service, but if a contributor is transferred from one depart ment to another his previous contributory service counts. (ii) No contributor will be allowed to deal with his contributions in any way during his service. (iii) If a contributor is invalided out of the Government Service upon the medical certificate of the Government’s Medical Officer, at any time, he will receive the value of his own and the Government’s contributions. (iv) If a con'ributor resigns of his own accord from the Government service before completing four years’ contributory service , he will be entitled to recover his own contributions only. (v) If a contributor resigns of his own accord from the Government service after completing four years contributory service, and upon having given three months’ previous notice, he ’..ill be entitled to re cover the^value of his ov/n contributions together with-3- v/ith the contributions by the Government of Jahrain* (NOTE) Eor this purpose the period spent by a contri butor upon leave, during which he actually drav/s his leave pay (but not leave without pay) is understood to be included in his service. (vi) If a contributor is dismissed from the Government service consequent upon conviction by a court of any criminal offence he will forfeit all benefits, including his own con tributions. (vii) If, as the result of a departmental enquiry, a contributor is dismissed from Government service he will be entitled to receive the value of his own contributions, but not the government’s contributions, (viii) If a contributor dies during his service, the value of his own contributions and also of the contributions by the Government of Bahrain will be paid over to his legal heir. For this purpose each contributor is required to register with the Govern ment of Bahrein the particulars of his legal heirs. (a) The expenses of maintaining the Bahrain Govern ment contributory provident fund will be borne by the Government of Bahrain. xmy moints or disputes as to^ the operation of the fund will be considered by the Adviser whose decision thereon will be final. (ix) Contributors will be required to sign their accounts yearly to show that they are satisfied that the balances and certificates are shown correctly. ************The Adviser states in his D.O. that he has forwarded two copies, whereas we have received only one. May ask him to send another one. sd.M.J.G- 10//2 I have taken the second for Consul Basrah. C.G.P hr v 10// H.C. I wrote to Consiil Basrah hy registered mail sending the rules for Bahrain Government Pension Fund. He has not acknowledged it what was the number of the letter. -- C.G.P. 20/3 P.A. No letter appears to have been sent officially &lt; perhaps it v/as sent D.O. The Adviser in his D.O. dated 9th February says he has sent two copies of these rules but only one copy was sent to this office with your order 'File for information', and no letter appears to have been sent B.J.5 , I submit a note on the subject which 20/3 was in this office.© f ° g Telegram - Code. From - Political, Bahrain, To - Britconsul, Basrah. No. 522 Dated the 20th March 1930. Hope you have received copy Bahrain Provident Fund Pailes and two private letters sent over month ago.* If No. ^Sp/U-e of 1 35 1 Office of {he Adviser to the Government. Bahrain. Dated, 27th J/Thany 1351 27th Octr. j'rom The Financial Adviser to the Government ? Bahrain, Persian To H. B. M f s Political Agent, Bahrain, Persian Gulf. Sir, I have the honour to refer you to the Provident Fund scheme started for the benefit of the permanent employees of the Bahrain Government, which was originally instituted on your suggestion. The total number of the employees amount* to about fifty, and it was decided to invest their contributions as well as the Government contribution in postal cash certificates. It now appears that the postal rule does not allow the purchase by one individual of certificates worth more than Rs 10,000/-. So far we have purchased certi ficates of the value of over Rs 17,000/-, the rule of the Rs 10,000/- limit having been brought to my notice only yesterday. As you are aware, the amount represents the provi dent fund of about fifty employees of the Bahrain State, and© ' ^ and I, as trustee of the fund, invest the joint contributions in uostal cash certificates on their behalf. In view of the fact that these purchases are made by me on behalf of a number of persons, I should be much obliged if you would kindly approach the postal authorities and if possible, obtain their senction to waive,in this case, the restriction of the Rs 10,000/- limit. I have the honour to be Sir, Your Obedient Servant, Financial Adviser to the Government, BahrainC’s. P. P. — L (in) 978—200-12-29 —B. The Agency, Bahrain, Dated—tuv X^Xii ^ovcmbor l 93 S. No. izax. From The Political Agent, BAHRAIN. To The Adviser to the Government of Bahrain, BAHRAIN. LOiiCTiG st«L 1 cgu ior the beiieTjit ui. orupi oy e10 01 the B&amp;hx’G.j.n Gov eminent. be ouviatea by each contributor purchasing his own cash certificates,or by vour purciia.sin^ them on his behalf; tne certificates beim^retained by you for control and safe keeping. xhis would ve the additional advantage that in the event of a contributor leaving the service of the Bahrein Government during your absence,it would be possible for him to cash 1 is certificates without your presence as the officer acting for you could simply hand them over to them. If not already in your possession I suggest that a copy oi the rostax ouiae be purchased lor the information of your office. it appears to me that the difliculty mentioned would I have tne honour to be Sir, _our Most dbedient Servant, / Political Agent, Bahrain.No. of 1360 Office of the Adviser to the Government, Bahrain Dated, 13th Shawal, 13^6' X November 3, 1941, ) His Britannic Majesty 1 s Political Agent, Bahrain. MKMORANDUM :- I should be grateful if it would be possible for you to kindly obtain for the Bahrain Government copies of the Provident Fund rules obtaining in Government departments and Municipalities and Rail ways in India. S.ZThe Manager of Publications, Government of India Central Publication Branch, Civil Lines, Delhi* Memorandum * I shall be grateful if you will send me by V.P.P* one copy each of the following rules. 1* General Provident Fund Hules, Central Services. 2. Contributory Provident Fund Rules (India) 3* Any pther Provident Fund Rules applicable to MunicipalitK^and Railways in India. Iwl - for Poliiibail Agent, Bahrain.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00038d_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1238</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00038d</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1238</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 6/23 Provident Funds for all State and local Fund employees'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1929/1941</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-08-27T18:00:46</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (19 folios)</extent><extent>The file is arranged in chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 21; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 4-18; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains correspondence regarding the establishment of a provident fund for government employees in Bahrain. The correspondence is between the Political Agency in Bahrain and the Adviser to the Government of Bahrain (usually Charles Dalrymple Belgrave). The idea for such a fund is first suggested by Captain Charles Geoffrey Prior, the Political Agent in Bahrain, in June 1929. The papers cover the discussion over the details.Folios 9-11 are the Provident Fund Rules, as set out by the Bahrain Government.Folio 20 is internal office notes.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Pensions</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00038d#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>