<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000419.0x000125_en</identifier><datestamp>2019-01-10T11:44:10.324Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">MICROFILMED DOCUMENT DO NOT ISSUE USE IQR[Clips OF BRITISH FIRMS■» ff ,5 l Masqat the 8th September 1915 From Lieut-Colonel R.A.E.Benn, Political Agent and H.B.M*s Consul Masqat To The Hon'hle The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, SIMLA. Flth reference to your telegram No.434,F,A., dated the 31st August 1915,1 have the honour to forward,herewith,a copy of my letter No.791, dated the 8th September 1915 with a copy of its enclosure which I have addressed to the Assistant Secretary,Political Department.India Office,London,on the subject of the settlement of Haji Abdur Rahim bin Gaffin's account with Messrs,C.H.Laubenburg &amp; Co, of Birmingham. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant * Dated 29 OCT 1915 (Sd) R.A.E.Eenn, Lieut-Colonel Political Agent and R.B.M's Consul,Masqat.© 30PY. British Agency and Consulate. Masqat the 8th September 1915. No.791. Sir, T *ith reference to the correspondence ending with your telegram dated the 21st July 1915 regarding the refund of the deposit of Haji Abdur Rahim bin Jaffir by Messrs. C.H. Laubenburg and Co. of Birmingham, I have the honour to forward,herewith,a copy of Receipt for £226-16-8(Rs.3,402^8-0) paid to Haji Abdur Rahim bin Jaffir in final settlement of his account with that firm, 2. a copy of this letter,with a copy of the enclosure,is being forwarded to the Hon'ble the' Secretary to the Government of India in the foreign and Political Department, I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient humble servant, (Sd) R.A.E.Benn,Lieut.-Colonel, Political Agent and H.B.M’s Consul,Masqat. The Assistant Secretary, Political Department, India Office, Lord on.- &amp; Heceived from the Political Agent anri H.B.M’s Consul,Masqat, the sum of (£226-16-8)*Rs,3,402-8-0 (Three thousani four hundred and two and annas eight only) in final and full settlement of my account with Messrs.C.H.Lautenburg &amp; Co. of Birmingham. (Sd) Ahdur Rahim hin Jaffir, Muscat Agency. The 2nd September 1915. i \ -Sir; With reference to the correspondence ending rith your telegram dated the 21 st July 1915 regarding the refund of the deposit of Haji Abdur T&gt;Mm bin Jaffir by Lessrs. haubonburg and. do. of Birmingham, I hare the honour to for- -rard,herewith,a copy of Receipt for £226-16-8{Rs.3,4^-s-t') paid to Haii Abdur lahim bin Jaffir in final settlement of his account with that firm* p. A copy of this letter,with a copy of the enclosure, is being forwarded to the Eon'bis the Secretary to the Jorcrn- -mont of India in the Foreign and Political Department. I haTO thn honour to bo, Sir; Your most obedient humble servant, Lieut-Ooionol, Political Agent and H.B.I ! s Consul,hasqat. The Assistant Secretary, Political Department, India Office; ijondon®p«C/r- ^ * •eg . ... r-f ■ Telegram. i i Prom - The Political Agent, Maskat, 4 i 35u5 I o 1 r- To - The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign &amp; Political Department, Simla No. 170, dated the 16th (reed. i?th) August 1915. Reference India Office telegram of 21st July and their Memorandum of 16th July, with enclosures, regarding Laubenhurg*s account. Kindly authorise me to pay Jaffer £ 116-13-0 from Maskat Treasury. iTelegram. From - The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign &amp; Political Department, Simla, To - The Political Agent, Maskat« No.4'3//-E.Ao, dated the 31st August 1915. Your telegram dated 16th August, No.170. Laubenhurg*s account. Payment of £ 116-13-0 from Maskat Treasury to Jaffer is sanctioned.... 1% •ill rwr.y w C. H. LAUBENBURG TELECRAMS:- 'laubenburg, Birmingham’’ telephone:- CENTRAL 6 2 5. ^ f-0 'vi/g Copy to India c423 JUL 1915 CODES US ,6. ,R| r r-iTn »■'- g PIT^^ S, UEBER'S, D 4- 4 58.CAMBRIDGE ST + -4 4 4 BIR M I NGH AM 4 4 BENTLEY’S COMPLETE PHRASE, WESTERN UNION TELEGRAPHIC. KENDALLS 12 FIGURE CYPHER* PRIVATE CODES. The Under 3 Sir, July 13th 1915 cf State for India. Volitioal Departuent. :to4S ; India Office. Londen. S. W # O R« P2302/15 L4JUU915 We have the hencr to acknowledge your letter of yesterday, enclosing note by Accountant-General dated July 6th 1915 re the financial Statement in connection with our Stocks of Arms &amp; Ammunition at Muscat which we find quite correct, we have also had a letter this week fro* I-ieut Colonel Benn No 527 dated 11th June to the effect that he cannot accept any claiK of ours on Abdur Rahiia bin Jaffar for shortfalls in the realization of the goods at this end &amp; although it seeas hard on ua that we should have to bear the whole of this serious losSj we accept his Decision. We have also pleasure in accepting your 3 Propositions for the final closing of the whole transaction &amp; in doing so, we beg t© express to your office, the Foreign office, &amp; in particular to Lieut colonel Benn &amp; his Predecessor -Colonel Knox eur hearty Thanks for all the trouble taken on our behalf &amp; kind assistance given to us in this matter. With regard tc the sum of SI.16.0 kindly send same to us imtead \cf tc hr Darlow. ^_ \ We have the honor to be ^ir, your obedient lervantsNo. of 1915. IP 0 ' 1 ' British A-^ency and H.B.M* g Consulate7 With reference to the correspondence ending with your Memo.dated the 14th May 1915 forwarding copies of correspondence regarding the sale of arms and ammunition belonging to Messrs. C.H.Laubenburg &amp; Co.of Birmingham by this office,! have the honour to submit,he-rewith a copy of letter No dated the 11th June ' / 1915 which I have addressed to them on the' subject. I have the honour to be Your most obedient humble servant. Political Agent and H/B.M f s Consul,Masqat The Assista-nt Secretary Political Department, INDIA OFFICE WHITEHALL, London.From To No .i&gt;Y&lt; of 1)15. Brit Isa Agency and d.B.M's v^onsalate. Masqat tao 11th June 1915. Lieut-Colonel R.A.E.Benn, C.I.E., Political Age-nt and Consul, Masqat, Messrs. C.H.Laubenburg &amp; Co., Birminghan, Gentlemen, With reference to paragraph 2 of your letter dated the 7th May 1915 to the address of the India Office,! beg to state that the total of tae various sums renitted to you through the India Office on account of arms and annualthon sold on your behalf by this office is as you state,£832-4-4. £923-4-4 as shewn in paragraph 4 of my letter No.,316 of the 10th April 1915 to your address was a clerical error. 3. With regard to last para-graph of your letter quoted above,your remark that it will probably be necessary to make a further claim on Abdur Rahim bin Jaffir' s deposit is not understood. Had the rifles been allowed to remain for sale in Masqat the price realised would undoubtedly have be$n 1C% abc^ e the full invoice price.The arrangement made by colonel Knox quoted by you was applicable only if the goods were disposed in Masqat. 3. x regret also that I cannot accept any resp- 'isi i li y the condition in waich the rifles reached you f Political Agent and H.B.M*s Consul,Masqat. ;! 11 2 3 or i9!5 F rom Ar^vt' Muskat, 21st June 134. Your telegram of the 19tli June. Laubenburg. 2b/. was paid out oi : 134/. mentioned in paragraph 5 of my Letter Xo. 31b, dated l()th April, addressed to Laubenburg which please see. It is therefore recoverable from Laubenburg to enable me to make up the sum refundable by the firm to Jahr. Amount payable by the firm to you is 118/. Os. 9d. * tvs IQi X llfr '°l / SoFromiUN ^W. DARLOW, Nwer, Merchant and Importer. stereo telegraphic a. cable address: “DARLOW, BEDFORD.” TELEPHONE 56 &amp; 56 A. a m Bedford, ieth June, 1915. &gt;( ^ / aL O The Secret&amp;ry, India Office (Political Dept 7/HITEHALL. £.»V. Re CARTRIDGES from MUSCAT* Confirming the call made hy my representative 6apt. Tetley with reference to the above cartridges consigned too the account of Messrs. C.H. Laubonourg &amp; Co., Birmingham, as arranged with them I have pleasure in enclosing cheque value £118. 9s. ( one hundred and eighteen pounds, nine shillings) in full discharge of all liabilities in connection with these goods. I shall be obliged if you will let me have details of how the amount is arrived at and a receipt for the same, so that I can place the matter before Messrs. Laubenburg. Will you then kindly give instructions that I am allowed to examine these goods and take delivery as required. Thanking you in anticipation, Yours obediently, ... -S. G. P. I.—147 P. A. k H. B M.’a Consul, Muscat. -1 1-3-13. 1,440. fi A. „ i n 1 JO( \ No. 436 Put aw Tdeut-ColonelZR.A&gt;E« Benn, C &gt;I.E&gt;, Political Agent and H. B. M.’s Consul, Muscat, The Agaia'ta n't B ecretary, Political Department, of 191 5 . India Office,Whitehall, LONDON, British Agency and Consulate, Muscat, the l^th Way pjj ^ Sir, With reference to the correspondence ending with your Memo.dated the 16th April 1915 forwarding for ny in— -formation a copy of Messrs .Laubenburg &amp; CO ’ s letter dated the 14th April 1915 to your address!*! have the honour to forward,herewith, a copy of my letter No.455,dated the 15th May 1915,with its enclosures.which I have addressed to Messrs.C.H.Laubenburg &amp; Co on the subject of the disposal of their aims and ammunition. I have the honour to be, Hir, Your most obedient servant, Tieut-Colonel, Political Agent and F.B.M’s Consul.Masqat.From To No. British Agercy and TT .r. T, s Consul ate. Masqat the 36th May 3936. Lieut-Co3onel R.A.S.Eenn, C.I.S., Political Agent and fl.I .M*s Consul, Masqat, Messrs. 0.H.Laubenburg &amp; Co., Birmingham. Qentlemen, Vrfith reference to your letter No.P.396,dated the 26th March 1916 and subsequent correspondence addressed to the mdia Off ice, London, I am glad to know that the complete number of rifles as intimated by this office(734 rifles)has been received by you. I now enclose for your information 3 statements marked A.E.and 0.showing particulars of all sales effected by this office from your stock of rifles and ammuni- -tion deposited in the Masqat Arms Warehouse. 2* You will observe that a total sum of Rs.16,040-1 3- (£1002-14-5)has been realized for you and that a balance of ✓ Rs.1,662-12-0(£110-3-8)now remains with this office. This latter amount as explained in my letter No.316,dated the 10th April 3915 is being utilized to reduce the sum due by you on account of deposit refundable to Abdur Rahim bin Jaffir as has been fully explained in my above quoted letter. Your cheque for £318-9-1^ is awaited when the sum of £276-16-8 will be handed over to Abdur liahim bin Jaffir. 3* As regards the damage alleged to have been caused by careless packing,! beg to state that out of 17 cases of rifles despatched only 4 cases from which sales had been made and which had therefore been opened,were repacked locally. The best carpenters available in Masqat were employed for t' is work,the greatest care was taken and the packing waspersonally superintended by tbe Masqat Varebouse Superintend -ent. Tl^e reraaining 3(3 carses were shipped in tdeir origiml tin-lined cases as received froa you.I regret therefore that I cannot accept any responsibility tor the condition in which tie rifles reached you. I am, Qeiitl emen. Yours faithldil ly, Lieut-Colonel, Political Ag:ent and H.E.M # s Consul,MasqatPolitical Agent and H.B.M's Consul, Masqat,No. 176 E.-A, dated Simla, the 4th May 1916, O From—The Deputy Secretary to the Government of India-in the Fereigp-^nd Political Department, To— L. Robkbtson, Esq., Secretary to the Government of Bombay, Political Depart ment. ^ I am directed to invite a reference to the correspondence ending with your telegram No. 1241 W., dated the 12th February 1915, regarding the transhipment to London per S. S. “ Kaiser-i-Hind ” of 17 cases of rifles, which were consigned to Messrs. Laubenburg &amp; Co. 2. The Political Agent, Maskat, reported that he had personally superin tended the shipment on board the B. I. S. S. “ Yirawa ” at Maskat, and that the 17 cases contained 734 rifles, hut the consignee states that the 17 cases on delivery were found to contain only 681 rifles, viz., 598 long Martinis and 83 Sporting Lee-Enfield Magazine rifles. &amp; 3. I am to enquire whether the consignment was checked in any way at Bombay, and whetter you can throw any light on the shortage of 53 rifles now reported. Telegram P., No. 95 M., dated the 7th (received 8th) May 1915. I rom The Secretary to the Government of Bombay, Political Department, Bombay, To—The Secretary to the Government of India iu the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Simla. Please refer to your telegram No. U5 S., dated the 27th ultimo. Cases of ammunition mentioned therein left Bombay on the 28th April per S. S. ‘•Novara”. Telegram, No. 198 E.-A, dated the 11th May 1915. From-The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, Simla, r ^° r ^‘ le ^ ecre tary to the Government of Bombay, Political Department, Bombay.' nVwa p*? ^ el ^ e f ^th May. Lauhenburg. Consignment has been re- checked and found correct. India, Foreign Secrevarv No |9 Vi, dated lo IY&lt;AV i 9 ioO 1918 Telegram P., No. 445 S., dated the 27th April 1915. From—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, Simla, To—The Secretary to the Government of Bombay, Political Department, Bombay. On the 19th instant per B. I. Steamer “ Barpeta ” 150 cases of ammuni tion were shipped for Bombay at Maskat, addressed to Superintendent, India Store Depot. The date of sailing and name of the vessel taking the consign ment to London should be reported. Telegram, No. 94 E.-A, dated the 6th April 1915. From—The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Poli tical Department, Simla, To—The First Assistant to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Knox s telegram, 260, 29th March. Laubenburg’s ammunition. Sug gestion approved. Please act accordingly. Addressed First Assistant, Bushire ; repeated Political Agent, Maskat.S A No. 317, dat^d Maskat, the 10th April 1915. From— Likutenant-Colonel R. A. E. Benn, C.I.E., Political Agent and His Britannic Majesty's Consul, Maskat, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department. With reference to the correspondence ending with your telegram, No. 94 E.-A, dated the 6th April 1915, I have the honour to forward, herewith, a copy of my letter No. 316, dated the 10th April 1915, with enclosure, which I have addressed to Messrs. Laubenburg &amp; Co. of Birmingham on the subject of the reshipment to England of the balance of their ammunition. 2. A copy of this letter with its enclosures is being forwarded to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Enclosure to Serial No. 127. No. 316, dated Maskat, the 10th April 1915. From— Lieutenant-Colonel R. A. E. Benn, C.I.E., Political Agent and His Britannic Majesty's Consul, Maskat, To— Messes. Laubenbukg &amp; Co., 58, Cambridge Street, Birmingham. I beg to invite a reference to your letter, dated the 22nd January 1915, on the subject of the reshipment to you of the unsold stock of ammunition belonging to you and now remaining in the Maskat State Warehouse. 2. In this connection I would first invite your attention to your letter of the 20th March 1914 to the address of my predecessor Colonel Knox in which a mention was made of a sum of £706-9-2 having been paid to you as deposit by Abdur Rahim bin Jaffir and refundable to him minus a sum of £ 479-12-6 on account of the cost of goods shipped by you to Abdur Rahim bin Jaflir by S. S. “ Turkistan' and not paid for by him. The amount refundable to Abdur Rahim bin Jaffir therefore comes to £ 226-16-3. 3. The arrangements made with your firm by Colonel Knox was that he should first realise your claim by sale of goods ex S. S. “Mashona' and then pay Abdur Rahim bin Jaffir’s claim for refund of the deposit with you. 4. The total sum realised for you by this ofiice by sale of your goods up the 31st December 1914 is £ 922-4-4. This amount has been remitted to and acknowledged by you. This office also has in hand a further sum of £lo4-7-6f on account of sales effected during the months of January and February 1915. We have also the balance stock of your ammunition in the State Warehouse amounting to 150 cases valued approximately at £1,400. 5. I have now been directed by the Government of India to ship these 150 cases of ammunition to the India Office, who will deliver the same to you on payment by you of a sum of £92-9-lJ, arrived at as under:— £ d. Deposit refundable to Abdur Rahim bin Jaffir {vide paragraph 2 above) ... ... ... ... 226 16 8 Deduct balance in band with this office {vide paragraph 4 above) ... ... ... ... ••• 134 7 6f Balance ... 92 9 If 6. In addition to the sum of £92-9-1^, there is also a sum of £26 due by you to this office on account of freight and other charges incurred by this office in connection with the despatch of the ammunition as per bill attached. I shall therefore be obliged if you will include this latter amount in the cheque which you will be good enough to hand to the India Office making a total of £118-9-1J. 7. The 150 cases of ammunition will be despatched by Britisn India S. S. “ Barpeta” sailing hence for Bombay on the 19th April 1915.mi for approximate charge, to le incurred in re,hipping 150 ca,e, ammunition to England. Freight on 150 cases to London Bill of Lading fee ... ••• . Wages of coolies, carpenters, cost of nails Wages of coolies for removing cases from State Warehouse the lighters Hire of lighters and coolies ••• Total Rs. a. P&gt; • •• 297 5 3 1 0 0 • • • 45 4 0 to 20 0 0 • * 15 0 0 378 9 3 * Vis'* Say £26 Any balance remaining unspent will be returned.Copy. ) Prom - The Political Agent, Maskat 10 ^ ::e Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, Simla. NO. 348. Dated the 20th April 1915. Received 21st April 1915. Your telegram dated 6th April, 94-E.A. 150 cases cartridges shinned hy Barneta 19th April, Bombay.17(553. I. 1380. 500.—9/1914. Reference Paper. Political and Secret Department. — as Register No. S. 14834. 191 . Referred to the Secretary, Political and Secret Department, 5th August, 19] 5 (1) With reference to your minute dated 28th July 1915 in the accompanying file, will you be so prood as to obtain sanction to waiving the claim on Messrs. Laubenburg for lipjiterage (13s.9d.) and port rate (£2.18.4) respectively. (2) Will you also inform Mr.Darlow that the cartridges will be at his risk while at the India Store Depot and cannot be kept there indefinitely. (Sd.) H.W.Fry. i D.G. of Stores, y As regards (1) please see attached Minute sanctioned by the Under Secretary of State. It is understood that the Stores Department is taking action in respect to (2). (Sd.) A.Hirtzel. 10.8.15. (1) Noted and returned. (2) A separate reply is being made in regard to the disposal of the cartridges. (Sd.) R.E,Hewlett. 31.8.15.«■ 51' From Viceroy, Sth May 19J5. Foreign Secret, Your telegram of 24th April. Laubenliurg IbO cases of amiiumitioii addressed to Superintendent, India Store Depot, slupped from Bombay on 28tli April per S.S. ‘‘ Novara.1733 From Viceroy, Sth May 19li5. O l f Foreign Secret. Your telegram of 24th April. '-LaalmTliurgr iW cases ol amimmition addressed to Superintendent. India Store Depot, shipped from Bombay on 28th April per S.S. “ Novara.”165 U i r &lt; k * 110 N°. dated Maskat, the 21st March 1915. From— Lieutenant-Colonel R. A. E. Benn, C.I.E., Political Agent and His Britannic Majesty's Consul, Maskat, To—The Hon'ble the Foreign Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department. With reference to the correspondence ending with your telegram A + c -iv ^°- ^2 D.-S.,t dated the 8th March : 1915, I have the honour to forward, here- ^ with, a copy of my letter No. /A, dated 21st March 1915, which I have addressed to the Political Resident in the. Persian Gulf, Bushire, on the subject of the despatch to England of the ammunition belonging to Messrs. Lauben- burg &amp; Co. of Birmingham. No. ^f, dated Maskat, the 21st March 1915. From— Lieutenant-Colonel R. A. E. B//n, C.I.E., Political Agent and His £ y Britannic Majesty's Consul, Maskat, To—The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. I have the honour to invite a reference to the correspondence ending with + c : i eo/\ ' telegram No. 282 1).-S.,J dated the 8th t era o. {a). March 1915, from the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department to your address on the subject of the despatch to England of the ammunition belonging to Messrs. Laubenburg &amp; Co. of Birmingham. 2. In this connection I have the honour to state that, through an oversight, which I much regret, the sum stated in my telegram, No. 179,§ dated the 26th February 1915, to your address and repeated to the Government of India, as being due by Messrs. Laubenburg to Abdur Rahim bin Jaffer on account of refund of deposit, was incorrectly shown as £706-6-0 (the exact sum is £706-9-2). It seems from a letter, dated 20th March 1914, received from Messrs. Laubenburgh &amp; Co., after Colonel Knox’s departure from Maskat, that the deposit of £706-9-2 was placed with the firm by Abdur Rahim bin Jaffer “ as a general guarantee for the due payment of their drafts, for the. § Serial No. 87. In* India, Foreig;i 8 No ''i °- C&gt; ,these woods. Abdur Rahim bin Jailer’s deposit, therefore, must be reduced by £479-12-6, thus leaving a balance of £226-16-8 refundable to him and not £706-9-2 as previously stated. The arrangement made with the firm by Colonel Knox was that he (Colonel Knox) should first realise Messrs. La u hen burg's claims under a later shipment ex S. S. “ Mashona ” from sales and then pay Abdur Rahim bin Jaffer’s claim for deposit. Messrs. Laubenburg &amp; Co. there fore contend that Abdur Rahim bin Jaffer is not entitled to the refund of his deposit until the “ Mashona ” shipment has been realised for them in fuh. v The “ Mashona ” shipment may now be said to have been realised for them in full, as the balance of goods remaining in the Maskat Warehouse, is at the firm’s request, to be reshipped to England. 3. I have now discussed the subject with Ilis Highness the Sultan and have informed His Highness also of the concessions granted to Messrs. Lauben burg &amp; Co. by his late father and reierred to in Colonel Knox’s recent telegram, Serial No. 88. No. 162, dated the 28th February 1915, to the Government of India. Ilis Highness has agreed to waive all his claims. 4. The total sum realizable for Messrs. Laubenburg &amp; Co. under the S. S. “Turkistan” and “Mashona” shipments was £3,937-18-7. Of this sum £ 922-4-4 have already been remitted to the firm up to the end of 1914. We have also a sura of £134-7-6! in hand on account of sales during January and February 1915; and in ammunition, 150 cases valued at £1,400, at £9-6-8 per case. 5r I would now suggest that Colonel Knox’s proposal to detain the ammunition until Messrs. Laubenburg &amp; Co. have remitted the sum of £ 226-16-8 due to Abdur Rahim bin Jaffer, less £ 134-7-6J now in hand, he carried out. If this arrangement is approved by the Government of India, Messrs. Laubenburg &amp; Co. will be asked to send a cheque for £ 92-9-1J when the ammunition will be despatched to England. 6. With reference to the last paragraph of Foreign Department telegram Iso. 282 D.-S., dated the 8th March 1915, Abdur Rahim bin Jaffer has been Serial No. 88 (a). absent from Maskat for some considerable time and he is now said to be in Bombay. I have, therefore, been unable to ascertain whether he would be prepared to accept ammunition in lieu of cash. 7. A copy of this letter is under despatch to the Hon’ble the Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department. Ill Telegram, No. 2G0, dated the 29th March 1915. From—LiEUTBNANT-CoLONKL S. G. Knox, C.I.E., Bushire, To—The Secretary, Foreign and Political Department, Simla. Please refer to Benn’s letter 244, dated 21st March. Laubenburg’s arms. I agree generally but suggest that as sum is small one and ammunition urgently Enclo. to Serial No. 110, needed it might he shipped to India Office to save time who would deliver goods Laubenburg on payment £92 odd, see paragraph b, Benn’s letter. Addressed to Foreign; repeated to Maskat.Telegram P., No. 226-D. S., dated the 22nd February 1915. From—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, Delhi, To—The Political Agent, Maskat. (Repeated to Bushire.) No. 226-D. S. Laubenburg. Eeference your telegram No. 44, dated the 6th instant. The ammunition should be shipped without delay. Eifles have been insured by Laubenburg against war risk on the assumption that the con signments were not insured at Maskat. Please say whether this is correct. Telegram No. 59, dated (and received) the 23rd February 1915. From—The Political Agent, Maskat, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment. Urgent. Your telegram dated 22nd Pebruary, 226-D. S. I propose ship ping the consignment to-morrow’s mail. Please telegraph should it be ad dressed as directed 26th January, 95-D. S., or direct to Laubenberg and Company. Telegram No. 1035-D., dated the 83rd February 1915. From—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, To—The Political Agent, Maskat. Your telegram dated 23rd Pebruary, 59. Consignment should be addressed in accordance with my telegram of 26th January, 95-D. S. Telegram No. 58, dated (and received) the 23rd February 1915. From—The Political Agent, Maskat, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment. Your telegram, 22nd February, 226-D. S. Consignments were not insured at Maskat. Addressed to the Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department and repeated to the Political Eesident in the Persian Gulf. Telegram No. 179, dated the 26th (received 27th) February 1915. Prom —Lieutenant-Colonel R. A. E. Benn, C.I.E., Political Agent, Maskat, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Delhi. Foreign Department telegram dated 22nd February, 226-D. S., Laubenburg’s ammunition. Please refer to appendix G. of enclosure to Maskat letter No. 188, dated 22nd October 1913, to Political Eesident in the Persian Gulf copy of which was sent to Government of India. Under Eule 16 of Arms Warehouse Eegulations a sum of R5,000 and 95 is due by Laubenburg to Sultan of Maskat on account of rent charges from August 1913 up to date. Sultan of Maskat is willing to take ammuni tion in lieu of cash. There is also sum of £706 or E10,590 due by Laubenburg to Abdur Eahim Bin Jaffer on account of deposit paid by latter to Laubenburg. This makes total of R15,692 due by Laubenburg exclusive of certain freight and loading charges on stock to be shipped now. I have only about R 2,000 in hand of Laubenburg’s money on account of goods sold here for them. Number of cases of their ammunition now in stock and ready be shipped is 150 of 2,000 rounds each and is valued at R21,000. I solicitorders whether I should retain R15 3 692 worth of the ammunition. If this is done only 37 boxes instead of 150 will be despatched to Laubenburg. Addressed Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, repeated to Foreign Department. Telegram No. 162, dated the 28th February 1915. From—Lieutenant Colonel S. G. Knox, C.I.E., Bushire, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart, ment, Delhi. Maskat telegram 179, 26th February. Laubenburg ammunition. Maskat telegram 9, 8th January 1914, to Resident confirms my first impression that in view of special position Laubenburg, late Sultan had been inveigled into concessions to them forewent warehouse dues. That claim therefore falls. Secondly. Laubenburg claimed money not goods. I agreed to do my best for them, realise their claim first from sales then pay claim for Jailer’s deposit and any balance was to go to His Highness. I consider latter should forego his claim to balance which was only a kind of set-off against remitted warehouse charges and unlikely to be realised. Fair solution therefore would be for Laubenburg to remit to Consul for payment to Abdur Rahim Jaffer £700 less Rs. 2,000 now in hand to their credit. Until this payment is guaranteed I think that they should not be allowed to remove ammunition. Addressed Delhi; repeated Benn, Maskat. Telegram P., No. D. S.-282, dated the 8th March 1915. From—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, Delhi, To—Leiutenant-Colond S. G. Knox, C.I.E., Officer on Special Duty in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. (Repeated to Maskat.) Please refer to your telegram of the 28th February, 162. Laubenburg. The case is not quite clear to us. Your recommendation is apparently that Sultan should forego all claims. Does he concur in this ? Benn should sound him. M ould £700 worth of ammunition instead of remittance be accepted by Jaffer? 1 “Swiftsure” in Suez Canal, 6th February 1915. No. 233-1462, XIV N. 42. Sir, r ® ference t0 Government of India telegrams Nos. 1917-47 M. of 10th September 1914 and 1917-54 M. of 8th October 1914, I have the honour to forward for the information of His Excellency the Viceroy and Governor ^ ene frL° f I ^? ia in Council the attached report received from the Senior A aval Officer, Persian Gulf, No. 1-15 of 5th January 1915, concerning the valuation and destruction of the dhows in question. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your obedient servant, R. H. PEIRSE, Vice-Admiral, , , Naval Commanderdn-ChieL The Secretary to the Government of India *n the Marine Department.No. 1-15. H. M. S. “Espiegle,” at Kurnah, 6th January 1915. Sir, With reference to your memorandum 1462 XIV N. of 4th September 1914 I have the honour to report that all the dhows which were under detention at Jask have now been destroyed, and a statement showing the approxi mate value of each dhow made by the Officer Commanding Troops at Jask is attached. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your obedient servant, W. NUNN, Captain and Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf Division. The Commander-in-Chief, H. M. Ships and Vessels, East Indies Station. Dhows. No. 1 3) }3 33 33 33 33 33 2 3 4 5 7 9 10 VALUE OF DHOWS AT JASK. Valut. Rs. 275 275 70 . 625 . 275 . 1,300 . 1,875 . '875 No. C.-209, dated Aden, the 3rd March 1915. [Confidential). From—Major General D. G. L. Shaw, Political Resident, Aden, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Pohtica Department. I have the honour to report for the information of the Government of India that His Majesty’s Charge d’Affairs at Adis Abeba having telegraphed to me to supply him 13 carbines and ammunition, I sent to h,m 13 carbines and one box containing 1,120 rounds out of the stock of arms and ammum to Aden from Djibouti in February 1914. The balance of the ^ “ sent to Woolwich by the first available transport. The rifle c^ts ^ despa of which was advised in your telegram No. 58-D, of the 3rd January 1915, have just been received from India.Tolegran. (Oopy) Jron TIig political laskat. To Tlie Secretary to tlie G-ovenEient of India in the Forein and Political Te nrtnent, Delhi. IlOo 8C* Dated the list I .arch 1915* heed, the list harch 191a. Foreign Department telegram 1593 D., lith I larch 3one further explanation was necessary regarding Lauoonhurg affairs. Sultan of Ilaskat also only just returned from tour. Jaffer is in India, heport posted. Aaaroscou, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, repeated Secretary tr, t.Tio rimm-mmant of India, Poreipn S political Dap'Nc 10858/14 *rd addreie Tha Under Searatary of State Foreign Offiee LONDOH foreigh office Ma r ek 17tk/m4 Gertlenen, &gt; Wltfe roferenee to your letter ©f tke lOtk inetant, I a* Aireeted t'y Seeretary Sir E.Grey to exprees kis regret that ke le unable to aeeict you further in the natter of your elain againat All Khan. Ir regard to tke diepeeal ef your eteek at Mueeat, I an to state that His Vajetty's Consul at that plaee reports that ererything possible is being done te facilitate sales. For example, His Higness tke Sultan has foregone all warehouse and eustons dues and special instruetions hare been given to his superintendent to do all is kis power to press the sale of your aras te approved purehasers, whilst the warehouse superintendent tke Consul, &amp; tke elerieal staff of tke Consulate are doing ageney work for your firn gratis, and einee Vr Poole handed ever te His Majesty 9 s Consul ecntrel ever tke arms those belonging to your fir* are offered in tke first instanee to intending purchasers at every enquiry made with regard to ar*s. It is unfortunate that tke rifles do not appear te appeal to buyers as the prises are high a d It is well known that tke arms have bee* in tke warehouse f r r * long time. His Hignees the Suita* has however been speeially requested tc assist in disposing ef the* and to inspeet tke stoeks before placing orders elsewhere* I am, Gentleme*, Yeur most Obedient, humble Servant (Signed) w.Langley*Ho 179 of 1914 BritlBh Agenoy an4 6onoiilato Kvaoat the Slot February 1914. To:- l'os«re C.H*Laubenb\irg &amp; Co. P8 0a»bri4g* Street. BlrMimgluiii. Gertlore» 9 With rofereroo to tha oorreopoatonoo oa41ng with ay latter Ho 1132, 4at od th© 26th HoTonbor 1913 to your a4dr©ae, I ohall b© flad If you will inform me as ta th© fallowing. I umderetand that you dealre me, if peaslble, ta sail the goods ax SS l, haf»hona' row dotainod ir the tfuaaat State Warehouse, Tide enclosures to your latter dated the 11th Sept amber 1915 for the sum/ of £3579.18.9 plus 10j£ profit £357.19.10 total £3937.18.7 and to remit thip sum to you lees £706.9.2 to be paid ta Abdul Rahim Jafar am aeocuirt of deposit. I ash this suestlem because I hare recelyed a letter from Abdur Rahim Jaffar through His Highness the Sultan ir which ha asks for the raturm to him of the B*lading for goods ex SS* Turk!star' and offers in exchange for this Document to be content with the sum of £227.6.8 to be paid to him after the sale of the goods ex SS Mashona As your representative- hr Paolo - was emphatic in his wish that the Bill of Lading for goads as FS'furkistan' should not be handed oyer to Abdur Rahim Jafar until I had realized sufficient money from the sale of these goods to pay you £3251.9.5 I hays refused to deliver the B # lading in guest ion until Abdur Rahim Jafar praduoas a letter from you authorising me to hand it oyer or until the 'kaihena' gecds have been disposed of to an extent suffieient to enable mo to pay you £3231.9.5. But as Abdul Rahim Jafar soars anxious, if I may oo exproso it, to buy tho B* lading in oxehango for £479.26 I am doubtful whether thoro has not been soma mistake and(3£ whether he hae ever paid you for the geoAs ex SS' Tur]ciBtan ,, • I shall be obliged if you will lot Be know whether you 0 accept the figure* £3937.18.7 ae eorreet and inform Me of the exac&gt; aKOunt that I a« to pay Abdur Rahim Jafar therefrom. The balanee naturally will he remitted to you before anything is paid te Abdur Rahim Jafar. Perhape you mould also explain to me why Abdur Rahim Jafar ie e# anxious to get hold of the B* lading for goods ex Turk!star' 0 Ae x understand that he has long age received the goods ex SS* Turkistan' without produetiom cf B*lading or Delivery order, I eannet understand why he should trouble himself to obtain what is to him an • « mppsxtmmtty apparently worthless Deeument. I am shortly handing over to my Bueeessor Lieut Colonel &lt;4 R.A.E.Benn, C.I.E, and am anxious to rlaee all this matter of the 'hashona' goods on as^ clear a footing as possible, so that he may be spared all the unneeessary trouble in disposing of the question. I \9, Gentlemen, Tours Faithfully ( signed) S•G•Knox Fsjor Politisal Agent &amp; H.B.h , s Consul MUSCAT.f r) 1335 From Viceroy, 6th April 1915 Foreign Secret. My telegram of 24th March. Lfeube nlburgi aShnimi^ on. Sultan has waived claims. Benn explains Jaffir’s clarnTTsHo/ Am issuing immediate instructions to ship ammunition to India Office for delivery to Laubenburg after payment of above sum. Papers followMea sr s.C.H• Laubenburp &amp; Co. (^vr^k 'CoV^A- Gentlemen, With reference to your letter of the 20th March 1915, regarding your Maskat stocks of ammunition, I an directed by the S. of S. for India to inform you that the G.of I. were instructed by telegraph on the 20th February that, the cart ridges should be shipped to England as soon as possible. They now report (24th March) that local difficulties have arisen at Maskat, where the 30*Jan.1915 with enclo: Sultan has preferred a claim for Rs.5095 (£339:13:4) on account of charges, while Abdul Rahim Jaffar claims Rs.10590 (£706) for a deposit stated to have been paid to your firm. A full report is being sent by mail, and a further communication will be addressed to you on its receipt. With regard to the 17 cases of rifles referred to in your letter of the 26th March, I am to enclose copy of a report by the Political Agent, Maskat, showing that the full number of rifles (734) were duly packed and shipped at Maskat on the 30th January last. In these circum stances the S.of S. cannot under stand the shortage reported by Mr. Darlow, and can only surmise that some mistake was made in counting the rifles at Bedford. As regards the damage alleged to have been causedcaused by careless packing, a copy of your letter is being forwarded to the G.of I. and the P.A., Ilaskat. I.am to .add that expenditure to the total amount of £8:13:6, as shown in the enclosed statement, has been incurred by this Office in connection with the rifles. You are requested to refund this amount to the Accountant-General, India Office, together with the further sum of £22:6:8, being the total cost of telegrams sent to and from India on your behalf, as indicated in the margin.* A further communi cation will be ma.de to you in due course as to the amount repayable by you for freight from Maskat to Tilbury. (Note by D.G.of Stores) j *To Viceroy,23 Jan.1915. \ From ^To x From To * From J ♦« 2 Q 3 Feb. 15 ' 20 ' 24 M 24 Mar. Refer 'll! If Total at l/8d.= £22:c;: Let f (S-) A. Hirtzel.TELECRAMS:- laubenburc, Birmingham!’ TELEPHONE:- CENTRAL 62 5. C. H. LAUBENBURG &amp; CP + 58,CAMBRIDGE ST ^ 4- - 4- BIRMINGHAM 4 4 J. CODESUSED:- If L A.B.C. 4T? 1 A ST! 1 E DITIO N S, LI E B E P's', yl i BENTLEi'’S COMPLETE PHRASE. WESTERN UNION TELEGRAPHIC, KENOA! LlS 12 FIGURE CYPHETR/v a/t PRIVATE CODES. ’ A•- * I &gt; March 26th* 1915. s. The Under Secretary of State rfor IKD3fX # Political Department, i f ^ . _ 1 1 H /4 Whitehall, 3 ^ - Cpj^i ! r ^' a %cMkjr. Sir, L 0 M D C M, S. W. »• conflm our of the 18th. uTirrnca 20th. inst., and ahall he glad to hear soon that the Cartridges hare been re- shipped* The seventeen cases of Rifles from MU SKAT have been duly delivered to Mr. Darlow of Bedford, who reports to us, that instead of 734 Rifles, as mentioned in your communication of the 17th. ult*, the cases only contained 6S1 Rifles, vial 598 long Martinis, and 83 sporting Lee Infield Magazine Rifles. He also informs us that many of the Martini Rifles are in a very had state with damaged stocks and forends, &amp;e* # which damage has been caused through very careless packing, the nails of the packing cases being driven right into the Butts &amp;*£ the Rifles* Kindly inform the Authorities at MUSKAT of this shortage and ascertain whether they were left behind or perhaps sold at the last moment j also kindly inform them that in order to put the damaged Rifles into proper state, considerable expense will be incurred* Mot having yet received the detailed Account Sales, we cannot tell whether the 681 Rifles art the correct Balance of the unsold portion, and should be obliged if you would obtain fullc. H. LAUBENBURG &amp; CO., B’HAM. PAGE two. To Th« Under Secret Ary of State for IKDIA. (continued) particular* of Sales representing the £827:2:3 remitted us, as early possihls* We have the honour to be, Sir, Your Obedient Servantsput av/ay with. .. From Viceroy, 24tfi March 1915. Foreign Secret. Laubenberg ammunition. Your T , February. Position complicated. Sultan claims charges Rs. 5,095; Jafir Its 10,590 for deposit paid LaubenbeJg; see papers sent weekly U M. 2Jjih March. Political Agent reporting by post. * rTELECRAMS:- ;nburg, Birmingham!’ CENTRAL C. H. LA U B E + + 58.CAMB •f -f B I R M I I ' ^ / ;: -rcIa 20 th tBf 1 ~&gt; X te Under Secretary of state frtr India. loI 11 leal Uernrtr ent. Whitohall. ] iiOr«»on o, f hc__J-p*396 Heferring to our letter of Kefcruary 18th last resecting the return of the Cartridges lying at Muscat. #e trust that you hare cabled out for these to be returned by first direct or indirect steamer. &gt;e would inform you that we hare now sold these Cartridges to Mr f.darlow of Bedford, to whom you recently delirered the ,17 eases of Rifle*. filre Hr Darlow every facility for Aealin* with the Lartrlfljes as he requires them very urgently. ^Te have the honor to lie Sir,put away with War Office, War Office, TM-yi* ■ ■ I i v {) Whitehall, 0162/119 (M.O.5.) 1 1 li/arch, 1915. ^4.Ui Inarch, S.W. 19i5 j The Director of Military Operations presents his compliments to the Under Secretary of State for India, and with reference to his letter , P' of the 17th February, last, would be glad to learn if the consignment of Messrs Lauben burg’s stocks of arms and ammunition has arrived in this country from Muscat.Telegram P., No. D. S.-95, dated the 2Cth Jannary 1915. Prom—The Secretary to the Government ot India in the Foreign and/^olitical Tlnno rfmu-nf ® aL To—The Political Agent, Maskat. (Repeated to Lieutenant-Colonel S. G. Knox, C.I.E., in absence ^ Political Resident Persian Gulf, Bushire.) Laubenburg. Please refer to your telegram No. 303, dated December 7th 1914. You should make arrangements to ship to England as soon as possible by quickest route, stocks which belong to Messrs. Laubenburg. You should satisfy yourself before the vessel leaves harbour that arms, etc., are actually on boardship. Goods should be consigned to Laubenburg, care of Director-General of Stores, India Office, and addressed to Superintendent, India Store Dep6t. All expenses are to be recovered from Laubenburg. Please furnish telegraphic report as to the arrangements which have been made and name of steamer taking consignment. Expenditure statement should, in due course, be submit ted to Government of India. VV1, datedTelegram P., No. 86, dated (and received) the 27th January 1915. From—The Political Agent, Maskat, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, Delhi. Please refer to your telegram No. D. S.-95, dated the 26th January 1915. It is presumed that Laubenburg ammunition, which is in very bad condition, is not required; India, Foreign Gucretae Mo ’ 1 A dated 13 FEB 1915* t fide state- aent ttached* The cases are addressed to The Superintendent India stores Depot, London consigned to Messrs C*H. Laubenburg and Co C/o The Director General of stores, London. O fs They will be transhipped at Bombay by the British India Company to a homeward bound steamer. The Bill of Lading, together with a copy of paragraphs 1 to 4 qf this letter, has been addressed to the Director General of Stores, India Office, London. A duplicate copy of the Bill of Lading is enclosed herewith. 3. I personally superintended the shipment of the rifles and satisfied myself that they were actually on board. 4. The freight to London amounting to Rs. 351.6.3 has been paid by me to Messrs Towell and Co here. A statement of expenditure incurred in connection with the despatch of these rifles and which is recoverable from Messrs. Laubenburg and Co, is being prepared and will be submitted in due course. 5. My telegram No. 303, dated the 7th December 1914 showed that the balance of Messrs. Laubenburg and Co*s stock in hand at Masqat on that date was 759 rifles. x Since that date 25 rifles have been sold to approved purchasers through the Masqat Arms Warehouse, leaving a balance of 734 rifles now despatched. 6. A copy of this letter is under despatch to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, I have, etc., Sd/- R.A.E. Benn, „ , Lieut-Colonel, Political Agent and H.E.M's Consul, Masqat.C. H. LAUBENBURG &amp; C9 TELECRAMS:- “laubenburQ. Birmingham' + ^ 58. CAMBRIDGE ST 4 -f CODES USED:- A.B.C. 4T« a ST“ EDITIONS, LIBBER'S, BENTLEY'S COMPLETE PHRASE, !n Union telegraphic, Lis 1 21FIG U R E CYPHER A TELE PHONEI- CENTRA L 6 2 5. f * BIRMINGHAM + U- Cs 12IFIGURE CYPHER A PRIVATE CODES. i’aroh 5th 1©15 Th© UmLer b©cr©tary of State for India He:- P.396 Political Department. Whitehall. Lord on S. T y. ' ^ir, W© have the honor to acknowledge receipt of your Oommunloation of the 26th ulto, and note that the 17 cases of Rifles were not insured at haelrat against War Risks. We hear that the 6b w Kaiier-i-Hind with the 17'eases on hoard has arrived and Is discharging to day and in view that we have already sold the whole lot to Kr W.Darlow - Gun kaker A Merchant at Bedford, it would save time ( the Rifles being urgently required By kr Darlow) and expense to us, if you would kindly grant Permission for the 17 case# to he forwarded to Bedford direct fro* the Docks instead of to C/0 Director General of Stores - India Office. Fleas© send us the note for shipping expenses that we may send you Rewittanoe. With refird to the Oartriigee at lla.k.t please note that we alao have a buyer for these, an* we trust that you will kinily give early Cable instructions for the. to be returned, unless you have ^Iready done so W© have the honor to Be -Sirtelegrams:- burg, Birmingham’’ C. H. LAUBENBURG &amp; 09 / 58,CAMBRIDGE ST + 4- Put away with. A.B.C. AT* A 5T? EDITIO N S, LI E B ER'S , telephone:- B ENT LEY'S COMPLETE PHRASE, WESTERN UNION TELEGRAPHIC, KENDALLS 12 FIGURE CYPHERA WESTERN UNION TELEGRAPHIC, KEN LUlS 12 FIGURE CYPH ERA 4- -f BIRMI NGH AM 4* 4- | PRIVATE CODES. | PRIVATE CODES. / 1 jO The Under Secretary of State for Indian ’ — ^ Political Departaient. WHITEHALL “ February Ifth 1915 T Sir, RE P 396 In acknowledging receipt of your letter of yeBtor^a^Sj^^' note that 17 cases containing 734 Rifles fro* our stoek at huscat were shipped by the Sk' Kaisar-i-Hind' fro* Boinkay on the 6th inst &amp; that Bills of Lading were posted fro* Lueeat to the Director General of Stores at your office. There were originally 92fl Rifles, so that 1C6 were sold. No doudt we shall shortly receive detailed Account Sales of goods disposed of. Kindly let us know, when the 17 eases dre landed We refret to hear that the Arirunition wae found to be absolutely useless, but vessrs Kynoch wTom we have Just consulted on this matter, gtdte that as the Cartridge* were in 2ird Liwed 'cases d loaded with Cordite, they should be allright, therefore kindly eable out to have the whole lot re- shipped by first available 8tea*er, because if on .rriYAl we should find the ftu.litjr of the .artrldfe. »« had ae stated, we should ash i'oecra Kynoah to tako th»* h*rt A l*i the irrrsi. o-ee we could realize a good sir ty selling the® as old r.tal.\ (!i3 No. j162/119 ( M .0. 5 • ) * vfv P d War Office, Whitehall, S.W. 12th Fshruar^r, 1915, ?hs Secretary, War Office, presents his compli ments to the Under Secretary of State for India, and in continuation of his letter of the 31st January, 1915, would, he glad to receive full details of the consignment ol arms and ammunition which Messrs Lauyenhurg are despatch ing to England from Muskat, as well as the particulars-as to the name of steamer and port of arrival asked for in the above-mentioned letter.BENBURC, BIRMINGHAM. + + 58,CAMBRIDGE ST + + + + BIRMINGHAM 4 4 TELEPHONE:- CENTRAL 62 5. Fefcruarjr Ut 15. 3 9 6 1915 $F£B19ttd Ike U»*et* ^cretary of Stat« for India. Political Department. India Office. London m. ,V, Sir, I.. r. P l y to your letter of the 30th ultimo., ee eanuet u^erstae* that our Ammualtlo. store* 1. the far.house a t Muscat sh.uM h. * ad because all the ease, wore alaellue* an* eo.sequeutly atr an* watertl^kt. Shoul* you refer to the quality In general, we may say that they are uot UoTeruaeut quality, Mt Kysoeh’s ConmareUl quality an* such as hare always been shlype* an* accepte* nt | ^usoat. Tke .303 Cartridges would he useful here and could easily ke sold to Defence Corps for practising purposes. Should the GoTernment of India hy their remarks mean to • OBTey that our Cartridges have kees damaged in some way to sush ****** that they would have to ke thrown into the sea, it would of «ours« ke useless for us to go to the expense of having then returned, and in this ease we should suffer and unmerited and h9 **J 1*9*, kut we can hardly think this, as long as tke Cartridges were stored in the warehouse and the cases unepened.From C. H. LAUBENBURG &amp; CO., B’HAM. PAGE... 2. The Umiler secretary of state for jehr lat ifl. Co«t«l. In any case, if the Anmunitiou, particularly the 160,000 7 mfon Mauser Cartridge,, could he sold to di. Highness the sultan of Muscat or to some oae else, erea at a reduction, we should prefer this, otherwise please hare them returued, unless they are absolutely useless. The loss in this case ought howerer, to he borne by Mr Abdul Rahim Jaffar and u a dji All Khan Moosa Khan, who ordered the Cartridges and who ought to hare paid us for them at the time. i 3 1 ease Jo not hare the shipment of the Rifles delayed on account of the Cartridges as they are rery urgently wanted. *e should feel much obliged if you would kindly SPan t our Mr C.H.Laubenburg a short Interriew for the purpose of discussing this matter* Ye hare the honor to he, sir, Your obedient ^errants.Whitehall, S.W. 51st January 1915. The Secretary, War Office, presents his cornpliments to the Under Secretary of State for India, and with reference to the communication received on the 26th instant regarding Messrs Laubehburg 1 e stocks of arms &amp;c at Muskat, would be glad to be informed in due course of the port of arrival, and the name of the steamer, to enable the necessary arrangements to be made with the Customs Authorities for the r ©_importation of these arms into England.(1377) Telegram -P. From — The Secretary t4 the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, Delhi ; To The Political Agent, Maskat, Maskat, ( Repeated to Resident Bashire ). No. D.S. 124.' Dated the 5th December 1914. With reference to Foreign and Political Department telegram dated 4th instant No. D.S. 121 please also quote prices.. Trie iolltical Arcent, W^Rkot, . The Secretary to the Coverment oT India in the ^orelm find Political department. (Repeated Political Rocldent in the Persian Gulf). HO, 303. Dated ami received the 7th December 1914. A reference if. invited to i'oreim and Political Department teler-rama, .or. D.a. 121 and XIQL D,; .124 dated the 4th and 5th December 1914 re-pectively. Detail of IlritlRh rtock now in Maskat under the heads mentioned is a* foil jws. Pirrlly j rmr:- (1) ,3C3. There are 94 rportinp; Lee Metfordr moKaaine rifles richly engraved, the retail price of which is //$- $-o Re./118 4H&gt;&gt; and Invoice price £ 7-3-6d, also / of the some kind of rifles but not enpraved, the retail jirice is Hs,l02 # and Invoice price £ 6-3-Gd. There are olfio/ringle long rtock Msrtinl Metford riflen, the Retail price is Ms. 36/8/- and Invoice price l 2-1-0. Total 759 rlflee. The above are all from Messrs Laubenberg'e stock and invoice price is from hlr invoice. (2), (3), and (4) Nil. secondly SErmnltion:- (D.3G3. There are 2,04,582 roundr of aniunitlon o: wiiich 1,80,800 rounds ore Laubenberg'*. The balance belongs to anotaei local firm ond is stock solv/iged from cen , Retail pricr of ammunition belonging to L'Ubcnberg^ ntock ir Us. 70 if under 10,000 rounds are taken and us. 6b per thousand round® if over 10,000 rounds are token. (2) and (3) Nil. (4) 1,48,600 roundr of seven mllle metVes for r.vuser rifles, all L ubenberg’s. Retail price is iis. 7o/« per thousand roundr. or Hs. 75 if under 10,000 rounds are taken. Of tawvwvmry snider anifnunition belonging to the deported Ali Musa Khan there are 13^974 rounds. Price per thouBand rounds K s. 100, These have been in stock for a long time.communication to tlipm wiii ^ ^ne.n will be made by the India OfficeJ * J- 4S 1^7 War Office, Whitehall, S.W. 31st December, 1914. The Secre■f'arj 7- o:f the War Office presents his compliments to the Under Secretary of State for India, and hegs to forward for his information a copy of letter No. 0162/119 dated 3l/l2/l4 addressed to the Under Secretary of State, Foreign Office .■ Ifw/yi- /Uft /&gt; t ^ ^ u *£ ^ ^ JUU •■ ^ ^ ^ c ' l^l UfJi Lud fr^-\ iHL [jf^ Cl! F /' rcnn Secretary of State to \ icervy, l^oreigu 1 )epartment, 2nd December 1914. Foreign Secret. Your telegram dated 28th November. Aden. You would also presumably require ample evidence that violation of our frontier was such as could not safely be ignored. Subject to that further proviso your proposal approved. 1 presume von cannot use British stocks, Muscat. Tkrtvv . far U'ct^co^ - JU fir tuj^ • 1II l\Tne Under Secretary of State, India Office. In any further communication on the subject, please quote K „. 79520/14. and address— The Under-Secretary of State, — Foreign Office Foreign Office, London. I,cv December 10 th, 1914. Sir:- Oft \c| |5 ' I am directed by Secretary Sir Edward Grey to transmit to you, herewith, for the Information of the Marquess of Crewe, a copy of a letter from Messrs. C. H. Laubenburg and Company, relative to their goods at present deposited In the Arms Warehouse at Muscat. I am to enquire whether, in view of the correspondence enclosed in your letter of the 4 th instant i P.4618, Lord Crewe considers that these arms would he of any use to the Government of India, and, failing this, whether he would see any objection to their being re shipped to England. &gt; A copy of this letter, with its enclosure, has been sent to the War Office for the information of the Army Council. I am, Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant,copy. (79320) C. H. LAUBENBURG AND COMPANY, 58, CAMBRIDGE STREET, BIH/JNGHAIvl. December 4th, 1914. Sir:- Re No.74786/14. We have the honour to acknowledge receipt of your letter of yesterday enclosing in money order £16. 3. 11. which in addition to 3 . 5. for cost of remittance, making in all . . . .£16. 7. 4. being a further amount realised by the sale of our goods in the Arms Warehouse at Muscat during the last quarter, for which we thank you. We regret that the sum realised has again been so small, and we would venture to inform you, that the fact of having to be without such a large sum as £3,000 about, is pressing very severely upon us in our business, particularly at the present time, when on account of tne War, we are having so many acceptances held up in India, Shanghai and Morocco. In Ine Under Secretary of State, Foreign Office.(&amp;&gt; i In your letter of the 19th August you directed us to address ourselves to the War Office for the purchase of the remainder of our stock of arms and ammunition, but unfortunately we received no reply. This being so, we would ask you to kindly give instructions to the Authorities at Muscat, to reship the goods to us here, because at the present time there is a much larger demand for these rifles &amp;c., than can readily be supplied by the many Civilian Defence Corps, which have been formed all over the country. We have the honour, &amp;c., (Signed) C.H.Laubenburg and Company.—— r*-'- C. H. LAUBENBURG Sc C9 CODES USED:- G^C 4-T' A 5T» EDITIONS, lieber’s. BENTLEY’S COMPLETE PHRASE, WESTERN UNION TELEGRAPHIC, KENDALLS 12 FIGURE CYPHER* PRIVATE CODES. BIRMINGHAM. + 4 58.CAMBRIDGE ST 4 4 TELE PHONEI- CENTRAL 625. 4 4 BIRMI NGHAM 4 Tha Rt Hon, Rov^Ver HtjJi TSi^ The Under Secretary of State for India ! India Office. Downing Street I endor Sir Our Ccldfeo Afert lr F-anei. Stuart irforre ub that ha calm at the India if.ice yesterday in connection with the under- Kentioned matter, and had advised ub to exolain the aame fully to you in the hope that you may see your way towards extending to ue your meet valuable aaeistanee. ..'e have the honor to state for your information that about 2 y 93. r r a^o we shipred to , use at by order of our customers vizi- Hajl Alikhan hoosa Khan a A»dul Rabin Jaffar at v uscat Rifles &amp; Arrurition ( the Rif lee of the 1 arufacture of the Field Rifle Go - R’Kae) as per enclosed 2 Invoices. The Stearer carrying these goods ought under ordinary circuTrstaneee have arrived at Kuscat fully 2 to 5 weeks before E.R.H the sultan's Prohibition care in force, in which case there would have been no difficulty for our custorers to ortafn due Delivery of the goods, but unfortunately th Sultan seized the goods &amp; in eonseqreree our Custcrers refused to pay. In reality the Sultan's Prohibition ought rot to have effected us, for as scon as ve had delivered the goods as Per contract with ou' 0 customers in buscat Harbour ourlaubenburg &amp; CO., b’ham. PAGE...g re6T&gt;oreibility ceased ard tberefora wa annealed to the Sultan to hel^ ue to obtain payirer.t f ott the Oustorers, the none so as we ocinted out to hiir, that ^a held a gnecial ^^arwit f-cm Mu franting ub per®iseion to irrport Fire ArffB X ar-unition into }, uBcat without let or hindrance, which '^arrit had another S yeadfc to run beyond the tiwe of the ^ohiMtion* We believe that this i-'rohifeitioit was for the nurnoBe of etonMrg the illicit Trade that was being done in India 1 we also hrow t that this illicit Trade was chiefly done by French Merchants resident at luscat. Ab far as we are concerned we assure you that we have never had the slightest knowledge of what hecane or the goods after they reached husgat, on the contrary we had always been in the relief that the goods were bought * used by the Traders Tribes in Arabia where there has be-n for nary years ~still is, a legitimate Trade in Fire Arms A Ammunition. '. !r e sold these goods as Merchants irthe same narrer as we sell any other 1 erohandize ir India 4 the East, where we have traded for over 50 years, we have had a lot of correspondence over this matter witv the roreign Office « also had an interview t^ere last December with air waiter Langley, who hae a full knowledge of the whole affair this business ir which we have innocently suffered,has beep a very great lose to us . at the end of the i-terview Sir 'alter Langley aynnathlaed v;it&gt; ue, saying that it was a hard case i heavy covpersation frcir H • V .Gov ernrert• Cur 'd custorers, who probably aiso 3rs ’ r ' olved in the il'icitLAUBENBURG &amp; CO., B’HAM. PAGES rrado,were let off without payine for the goods and we had to stand the Brunt 01 ail the loss. The only concession we have obtained fro* H.l r .Foreign Cffie© has been that they agreed to store the goods for us at Fusoat free oi charge and to instruet R.V.Consul there to sell the goods on our behalf at a profit of XO?i asoye the iryoieed asrounts. Up ti^l now they have sold &lt;5c remitted to us f?41.l6.8, without however having given ua detailed i^artieulars of what the Sales consist of. As per enclosed 2 copies of Invoices to our 2 eustorers the value oi the whole Lot stored with H.M.Consul is:- F3937.1b.7 Less 741.16.8 already soxd, remains:- f3l96.1.11 unsold. New Ir Stuart informs us that it was suggested to hin at the foreign Office that we should apply to the India Cffiae and that probably in order to avoid further loss to us, whi#h is being incurred and also in view oi the present war with Turkey, you might be disposed kindly to make arrangements that what remains of the stock of Rifles &amp; Aiwrunition at luscat, should be taken over by tne Governnent or India. Trusting that you may be able to accord us your valuable aid. we have the honor to beMuse[12 | In any further communica- t bn on this subject, please quote ('PV-j® ^ rt\2 No - 2. »nd address- The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. ^ndia. JZ $ J / ^ lit- ^ Tke l/&gt; “^ecretary of State for Foreign A fairs presents his compliments to the Under-Secretary of State for and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cofn^ 0 f the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, 1 3 , IQ I4 . Reference to previous correspondence: L e tt er ^ ^ Foreign Office if- Ftta if I Description of Inclosure. Name and Date. Subject. oj- c/Jms^TsoJ-' f-c /z (Similar letter sent to Jopy (o.2. (k.5ii00/l4) S' foreign office, June 11th, 1914. r‘ sir:- &lt;/lu4rr%ywo, 3 With reference to yenr despatch No.26, of Jemuary ^let. last, I an directed by Secretary sir E. Grey to Inform you that, after a consideration of the various 64 polni.s in question, yeur letter to Messrs. Laubenburg, which was enclosed therein, has now been forwarded to the firm with an intimation that the question of a guarantee of payment by the Sheikh of Kowelt has been settled by the Sheikh’s decision not to purchase from their stock of arms, while neither His Majesty's Government nor the Government of India can undertake any responsibility for damage to their arms In ware house at Muscat. Messrs. Laubenburg have also been Informed that Sir E. Grey cannot authorize you to take any such action as they wish In connexion with the document signed by Monsieur Elbaz on August 23rd, 1913, as His Majesty's Government cannot take any steps which might be regarded as supporting their claim against the heirs Aeutenant-colonel A. E. Benn, His Majesty's Consul, Muscat.(25200/14) heirs of Veesleurs Ooguyer. You should therefore refrain fron approaching the French Consul at Muscat in the natter, as desired hy Messrs. Laubenburr. I am. Sir, Your most obedient, humble ‘Servant, (fa i *y &gt; .j ■ Sigtied) fK Langley.F 2.7A &lt; 1 - ' 2 In any further communication on the subject, please quote no. 20654/14. and address— The Under secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. W i Foreign Office May 15th, 1914. r ^ Sir:- Q O % +7 &amp; I am directed by Secretary Sir E. Grey to transmit to you herewith, in original, Messrs. Lauhenhurg's re- 68 . 6 . 2 . ceipt for a further sum of Three hundred and sixty eight pounds six shillings and twopence forwarded to them i through this Department by His Majesty’s Consul at Muscat. I am to request that the receipt may be transmit ted to Lieutenant Colonel Benn in due course. I am. Sir, Your most obedient, s humble Servant, !rsd?a 22 MAY 19U Under Secretary of State, India Office. * 18MAY1SU X?,,Messrs, C. H. Laubenburg and Coy. to Foreign Office. 58, Cambridge St. Birmingham, 8 th May 1914 Sir, Nos. 10858/14 and 19497 . i.e have the honour to acknowledge receipt of your letters of the 17th March and the 7th instant, the latter enclosing ten postal money orders for £368-6-2 being a further amount realized by the sale of our goods in the Arms Warehouse at Muscat and in addition the sum of £3,13.10. which has been deducted to cover the cost of remittance. V/e thank you for this remittance and are also grate ful for all the steps you have taken to effect a speedy disposal of all our goods. There is still a balance of £3022 outstanding and we trust that we may soon receive further and larger remittances. We have, &amp;c., (Signed) C. H. Laubenburg 8 c Co.v p p C 7 914 271 Telegram P., No. 253 S., dated the 23rd April 19H. From—The Foreign Secretary, Simla, To-The Political Agent at Maskat (repeated to Political Resident, Bushire). • serial No. 269 . Maskat arms. Please refer to Bushire telegram* No. 487, dated 21st April. We need not consider insurance of any stocks of arms except Laubenburg's for the present. Probably it will only be necessary to insure balance of stock left after conclusion of transaction with Kuwait, if it comes about. Please find out and let us know by wire Towell &amp; Co.’s terms for such insurance. 272 Telegram R., No. 500, dated the 24th (received 25th) April 1914. From—The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire To—The Foreign Secretary, Simla. I have only just realised from your telegram* No. 253 S. of 23rd April • Serial No. 271 . it was intended to insure Laubenburg arms and trust it is not proposed at Gov ernment expense. If Laubenburg does not do bis own insurance, it would seem that His Highness should do it, as he will benefit by sale of balance of arms, after Laubenburg’s claim has been paid off. Arms fairly well looked afier and in safe custody and only damage it would seem necessary to insure against is deterioration. In the circumstances, I consider insurance of Laubenburg’s arms undesirable and difficult. Addressed Government of India; repeated to Maskat. 273 Telegram R., No. 107, dated (and received) the 24th April 1914. From—The Political Agent, Maskat, To—The Foreign Secretary, Simla. Your telegramf No. 253 of 23rd April. Towell and Company are only t s rial No 271 marine insurance agents and regret they cannot undertake our business. May I obtain terms from insurance agents in India or would the Government of India prefer do this themselves. Value of Laubenburg’s stocks according to list under despatch to invoice is as follows : arms Rs. 36,664, ammunition 22,333, total Rs. 58,997, omitting fraction of rupee. Addres;ed Government of India; repeated to Bushire.a r 1 B J 2 o .A 4 266 Telegram, No. 1917—12-M., dated the 17th April 1914, p rom _The Secretary to the Government of India, Marine Department, To—His Excellency the Naval Commander-in-Chief. The continuance of the arms traffic blockade for 6 months during 1914-15 has been sanctioned by the Secretary of State for India, who has, however, asked that a careful watch should be kept on the situation and, if practicable, the blockade be withdrawn sooner. Will Your Excellency kindly furnish the Government of India, by about the 1st June 1914, with your views as regards the possibility of discontinuing the arms traffic operations. mk, '7 n T7T \ P V’Q in OUtnlj 1 AIv i o No 37.Vi, dated 3 1914 QO Q MAV* O' «'• fVIAT (b , *1 I268 Telegram, No. 486, dated the 21st (received 22nd) April 1914. From—The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, To—The Foreign Secretary, Simla. ., „ s My 424* of 9th. Please send list of prices to Kuwait without delay. Addressed Masqat; repeated Foreign. 269 Telegram R , No. 487, dated the 21st (received 22nd) April 1914. From—The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, To —The Foreign Secretary, Simla. f Serial No. 263. Your telegraraf No. 238 S. of 21st April. Much regret delay over this question. I am afraid it m ill be at least three weeks before I receive the Kuwait reply and can report on the subject of Laubenburg arms. Some delay caused by non-receipt of telegraphic sanction solicited in my telegram + No. 424 of 9th April. + Serial No. 238. I imagine also Political, Maskat, is embarrassed by alternatives suggested in last half of my telegram already quoted. If announcement of sanction could he accorded to either alternative, he would be in better position to discuss insurance with To well and Com- § Serial No. 244. p an y. As stated Political’s telegram§ 78 of 11th April, repeated to you, he prefers insurance of only such stocks as remain with him for sale and doubts possibility of insuring all stocks excepj at prohibitive rates. Addressed Government of India; repeated to Maskat.v. 235 Telegram No. 199 S., dated the 8th April 1914. From—The Foreign Secretary, Simla, To—The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire (repeated to the Political Agent, Maskat). Please refer to your telegram,* No. 254, dated the 1st March 1914. • serial No. 148 . Continuation of blockade for six months sanctioned. A careful watch should be kept on the situation and report submitted if the blockade can be withdrawn at an earlier date. 238 Telegram R., No. 424, dated the 9th (received 10th) April 1914. From—The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, To—The Foreign Secretary, Simla. Tour telegram* No. 187 8. Regret delay; but did not understand from terms of your telegram that action was • senai No. 230 . called for by either Maskat or myself. I see no objection to asking the Shaikh of Kuwait but think it likely he and Shaikh of Mohammerah have discussed matter of Laubenburgh’s arms and think that prices high and ammunition defective, I have requested Political, Maskat, to be ready to send lists and prices to Grey at Kuwait, if requirements sale to Kuwait is approved, and would be glad of telegraphic sanction. Regarding insurance, I have no information as to final removal of diffi culties that prevented disposal of stocks t senai No. 1 * 4 . authorised in your telegramf No. 109 D.-S. of 23rd February. If compliance with those orders is likely to be long delayed, I concur and suggest that Political, Maskat, enters into negotiations with To well and Com pany, Maskat, who are Insurance Agents, and report terms of contract before finally signing. If, on the other hand, stocks are likely to be disposed of shortly, it would seem advisable to wait and insure only such stock as will remain in hands of Political, Maskat, for sale, presumably in State warehouse. I would further suggest that Consul at Maskat should ask his French colleague whether he has yet received any orders regarding handing over finallv to us stocks belonging to Louis : Serial No. 176. D., vide your telegram} No. 161 D.S. of 14th March. Political has promised news re insurance, but I send this on to avoid further delay. Addressed Government of India, repeated Maskat.244 Telegram R., No. 78, dated (and received) the 11th April 1914&gt;. From—The political Agent, Maskat, T 0 -_The Foreign Secretary, Simla. Tour telegram,* No. 424. Insurance of stocks purchased by us. While present stocks are stored in private • Serial No. 238. godowns under no protection, it would urobablv he difficult to effect insurance with reliable firm except at prohibitive rates but I can approach Elbaz ns suggested. Your suggestion to wait and insure only such stock as will remain with Political, Maskat, for sale, seems best arrangement. Elbaz informed me a few days ago that Erench Consul had not yet received orders to hand over stocks. List of prices for Grey is ready. Addressed Bushire ; repeated to Foreign.247 Telegram R., No. 439, dated the *lth (received 12th) April 1914. From —The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire To—The Foreign Secretary, Simla. Your telegram* 78. There is surely some mistake. I did not suggest • serial No. 244 . approaching Elbaz and should be cautious , , , , . insuring goods iu any company re commended by him. I suggested Towell and Company. Addressed Maskat; repeated Foreign. 248 Telegram P., No 2U S., dated the 13th April 1914. From—The Foreign Secretary, Simla, To—The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Laubenburg’s arms. Please refer to your telegramf No. 424 of the 9th t Semi No. 138 . instant. Will you kindly report whether Shaikh of Kuwait is willing to purchase arms and ammunition and what terms he offers as regards payment for same Your views are also requested.f 255 No. 984, dated Bushire, the oth (received 14th) April 1914 (Confidential). From— Major S. G. Knox, C.I.E., Offg. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, To—The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreio- n and Political Depaitmcnt. I have the honour to acknowledge the receipt of your letter! No. 988 D. t Seri&amp;i No. 129 . ( i ated Ifcth February 1914., regarding the disposal of the stocks of the British firms engaged in the arms trade with Maskat. 2. The instructions contained in paragraph 2 of despatch:}: from His * SerIal iXo 118 Majesty’s Secretary of State, No. 4 (Secret), dited 23rd January 1914, will bo borne in mind and officers serving in the Persian Gulf havo been informed of the existence of Messrs. Kynoeh’s stocks in England and requested to help British firms when feasible. 3. In regard to the question whether it might he made a condition of Ali Musa’s eventual return to Maskat that he should take delivery of the consignment ordered by him from Messrs. Laubenburg, I have the honour to state that the views of the Political Agent, Maskat, were invited by me on the point. He has embodied them in his letter No. 61, dated 20th* March 1914 (of which a copy is attached) to my address. I agree generally with what the Political Agent, Maskat, says on this subject, and would add that I heard at Maskat shortly before my departure that Ali Khan had written to his friends, possibly out of bravado, to say that he was entirely happy at Bombay and bore no malice against anybody except Bis Highness who, he considered, should have supported him more wholeheartedly. If that is his real attitude of mind, it is doubtful whether pressure, if attempted, would be effective. 4. A further difficulty in the way of exerting pressure on either Ali Musa or Jaffar would be that, apart from any question of oppression, our action would certainly be misunderstood. It is believed by the people of the country that, whatever our diplomatic attitude may be, the British authorities would really be happiest if no arms or ammunition came into Oman at all. I imagine that the popular view; as I have stated it, is not really very far wrong. If now, we exert our influence to force these Arab merchants to take over British stocks, the slander, sedulously circulated by our French and German friends at Maskat, that the only object of the British is to get the trade into their own hands will receive support and affect our reputation injuriously. No. 61, dated the 20th March 1914. From— Lieutenant-Colonel R. A. E. Benn, C.I.E., Political Agent, Maskat, To— Major S. G. Knox, C.I.E., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. I have the honour to acknowledge the receipt of your endorsement No. 640, dated the 1st March 1914, with which you forwarded to me a copy of letter* No. 988 D., dated the 19th ^ • Serial No. 129 . February, from the Deputy Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, with enclosures. As regards the suggestion made in the last paragraph of the despatch! from His Majesty’s Secretary of State for + Serial No. 118 . Indiaj No ^ date(1 2 3rd February 1914, regarding which an expression of my views is asked for, I have tlie honour to state that I am of opinion that it would be an oppressive measuie o ma 'e i a condition of Ali Musa Khan’s eventual return to Maskat that he should tate over the arms and ammunition ordered by him from Messrs. Lau en ur 0 . In five years’ time, when the period of Ali Musa Khan s banishment wi expire, the ammunition would probably be quite worthless, while the arms, to the dampness of the Maskat climate, would, no doubt, have depre ciated in value to an extent which might render them quite unsaleable. As regards the disposal of Messrs. Laubenburg’s stocks, the sales are pro- cceding steadily but well.■/ From Viceroy, \8th January 1914 . recommend [A.] Stocks at T r ffiC ' '* Kirkee Arsenal for disposal to • 1 H 1 ro.fr r, ’ ^ calibre be sent to arms of other calibres and all ammunition^shoidd &lt; ’S e thm Xa '“' 0t i ion : ® under responsible supervision. [B.] Stocks at Muscat : —aml^lhO and ^Tabove 11 f f ,n “ unit ; on . for s»ch weapons, should he treated as in AH) and ( ) above. Most undesirable such weapons and ammunition for which complete security cannot be secured should remain in Persian GuH to arms of other calibres and ammunition at Muscat should be treated as fn A (2) above except such as are to be sold to bond fide purchasers withfn a .vear. 1 ossibly arms of '303 and '450 calibres can'be utilised in some way None of their ammunition can be utilised. Arms of other calibres cannot m, and , . t iere 18 110 'eS'tnnate market for such in India. Possihlv His Majesty s Government may know of some better market. Knox’s thfnkTtW 0f , ,e , n, u rgS v nns 8 , hows difficult y o f (? honest) trade, and he thinks that we should be authorised to destroy.Ibarra. Laubm'hurg to Foreign Office. i°u . y ' - ''' -V. ; v / z'&gt; IF Faro}, 1914 .lefc^enne JJo. 10PAF/14 Fir, We have the honor to acknowledge receipt of your letter of yesterday enclosing chegne fPGP.9.4 being a further amount realined by the sale of our goods in the j, sc act Arms Warehouse up date, for which m thank you. have etc.. O.H.LIn any further communication on the subject, please quoti :t, please quote 11414/14. and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. Put sway with Foreign Office Match 23rd, 1914. i 1 1 ■ SOT Sir:- k 1 19,4 I am directed hy Secretary Sir E. Grey to transmit to you, in original, Messrs. Laubenburg's receipt for a £263.9.4. further sum of Two hundred and sixty three pounds nine s' y shillings and fourpence forwarded to them through this Department hy His Majesty's Consul at Muscat. I am to request that the receipt may be trans mitted to Major Knox in due course. I am. Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant, 25 MAH 1914 Or FiOE. The Under Secretary of State, India Office. n Si MAH 1914draft telegram. J-0. C.c. $ SECRETARY OF STATE TO VICEROY, FOREIGN DEPARTMENT. (Retamilla) C*t^i -X ft Despatched A3 I^acxaoLj 191 ^ cAv&gt;™\ /(ncjo ^ fa\c/n&lt;;C h\ 'Cota k c -it *t cV OfUiLd, fl/l' &lt;k- kilvul' yf &lt;r KU' 'C /U/wiLi fx^Crntr^ 'P. &gt;! m /, fa. ^ ^ - 13969. T i ^of 3 5. 1000.—10/1912. [2429/11.]MM In any further communication on the subject, please quote no. 7877/14. and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. Foreign Office March 9th, 1914 * r - &gt; I am directed hy Secretary Sir E. Grey to trans mit to you herewith copy of a despatch from His Majesty 1 s Consul at Muscat dealing with various questions relating to the disposal of the stock of arms owned by Messrs. Laubenburg at Muscat. As regards the firm's request that Major Knox should communicate to the French Consul the document signed by Monsieur Elbaz on the 23rd August last, Sir E. Grey proposes to reply that it would be con trary to the decision already communicated to the firm for His Majesty's Government to take any action which might be regarded as supporting their claim against the heirs of Monsieur Goguyer. It will be seen that Messrs. Laubenburg enquire in their letter of the 9th January whether His Majesty* s Government or the Government of India * r - &gt; could 16 Under Secretary of State India Office —F Copy to frsdia 13 MAS 1914(7877/14). could guarantee payment by the Sheik of Koweit in the event of their Belling to him. Sir E. Grey would be glad to receive Lord Crewe's views on this point, but he would suggest that such a guarantee would not be desirable. As regards the question of responsibility for the safety of goods stored in the warehouse, Sir E. Grey assumes that this responsibility rests with the Sultan. he would however be glad to learn whether Lord Crewe is of opinion that the question of insuring the goods should be considered. It is proposed, if Lord Crewe concurs in the views expressed above, to send instructions in this sense to Major Knox, and to forward to Messrs. Laubenburg the letter addressed to them by that officer, copy of which is enclosed. I am, Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant,Copy. 7877, 'essrs. BFITISF ACrEMCY AND CONSULATE, MASQAT, OMAN, January 31st, 1914. Gentlemen:- I have the honour to acknowledge the receipt of your letter of the 9th January, 1914, on the sub ject of the disposal of the goods relating to the 'Mashona' shipment. While I admit that the disposal of these goods is difficult and will take a long time, the prospects are not quite so hopeless as your letter implies. The sale of these goods was held up by the necessity of offering them 'en bloc* 1 to the Sheikh of ’'Uhammerah and it was not until his definite re fusal, which reached me only in the beginninp: of Oc tober, that I was able to commence selling them to other approved purchasers under Warehouse Pules. During the quarter ending 31st December, a sum of £60 was remitted to you through the Foreign Office,London, and has probably reached you * ere this and I at pre sent hold to your credit another £33, which with any further sums realised will be remitted to you at the close .H. Laubenburg and Company, Cambridge Street, Birmingham.clos^ of the current Quarter. T have already told you that I was unable to ac cept the offer of the agent of the Sheikh of Kov/elt and my reason for refusing to accept it was the un certainty of recovering payment. As to whether His ’'ajesty's Government, or the India Office, would guarantee payment ! have no instructions whatever. 1 + h regard tc the question of the copy of the document, signed by Monsieur A. Elbaz before the p rench Consul at Masqat, and your request that I should hand it over to the French Consul and at the same time support your claim for recovery, I am re ferring the question to Higher Authority for instruc tions, as T have none at present. Again, with regard to the postscript of your let ter, having nc instructions, I am quite unable to ex press any opinion as to the responsibility of ui s ’’a.lssty' e Government in regard to the safety of the '’'ashona' goods against fire, theft, or pilferage. I have noted what you say about the price of .303 cartridges for machine guns and have further informed the Superintendent of the Masqat Arms Warehouse, His Highness the Sultan occasionally consults in whom matters.matters. Should Hla Highness the. Sultan consult me V on ihs T shall h© glad t»o do what/ I can t»o assist you. T have &amp;c #&gt; (signed) 3.G. Knox, Major, Political Agent and Fis Britannic Majesty's Consul, Masqat.s ~° , ,, ,,,, the score that lie cornu procure guou* »&gt; Jc.J 0 u.i, C u uuu oer.cer at a offered f 0 * sa ’ v]iere The goods wore also offered to Hap Najif-bin-Ghalib, agent of Hie Sheikh of Kovveit. The latter would have been ready to take them on payment of three months’ date after delivery, but I did not feel justihed m accepting his olfci ^ A^erTsmaU’qStity 0 ^ Hie goods have been sold and I hope gradually to disnose of the rest, but, while taking no responsibility beyond the safe custody of the money 5 for which the goods will he sold and its remittance in due course to you and hot the .mods shall not he sold at prices below those quoted by you, I think I should inform you that I shall consider myself fortunate if I am able to remit to you on their account a sum which amounts to very nearly 3,400/. within a year of the date of this letter. ^ , g disposed ot&gt; an d, as you will see from the above, my exneetations in many directions have been disappointed, 1 can give uo opinion whatever as regards the 1,000 Lee-Metford rifles mentioned in the close of your letter of the 3rd October. f„;ti,f, 1 n,. In regard to the sale of the “ Mashona ’’ shipment, I regret to inform you thattho s have heeu refused by Sheikh Khazal ot Mohammerah, to whom they wete Enclosure 2 in No. i. Major Knox to Messrs. Laubenburg and Co. Gentlemen, Muscat, November 26, 1913. I WRITE to acknowledge the recipt of your letter of the 7th November, 1913, regarding the sale of goods ex “ Mashona,” and in reply to say that it appears my letter of °the 20th October, 1913, which answers most of your questions, has crossed your above letter. Q 2. I hope to remit to you by the end of the current quarter a sum ot 21/. Is. M. Yours faithfully, S. G: KNOX. Enclosure 3 in No 1. Messrs. Laubenburg and Co. to Major Knox. Dear Sir, Birmingham, January 9, 1914. WE have the honour to acknowledge due receipt of your letters, dated t e 20th October and 26th November, 1913, and in thanking you for your kind endeavours to dispose of the goods relating to the “Mashona” shipment, we regret that t e prospects of a speedy realisation of the whole lot are so hopeless, and considering tna at the present rate of selling, viz., 21/. 4s. 8c/. worth in about six months, it will ta e about twenty-five to thirty years to dispose of the whole parcel, which is a very serious matter to us. _ With regard to the Sheikh of Koweit’s offer to take the goods on condition tm payment is made three months after delivery, we should be disposed to accept those terms, if there was a certainty of the money being duly paid at the expiration ot thre months, or if His Majesty’s Government or the India Office would guarantee payment. We have not replied sooner to your valued communications, as we a J interview with the Foreign Office in London early in December last, and we arostm correspondence with them in reference to our Muscat affairs. According to a let we have received this morning, they inform us that they are again communicat 5 with the Government of India, and with the British authorities at Muscat, respecting disposal of our stocks and the recovery of the amount due to us from Ali Musa h i ■ who has still to take from us a large quantity of rifles and ammunition contracted with us, that is, the Field Rifle Company. A^j We had also asked the Foreign Office to assist us in the recovery of minimum due to us from M. A. Goguyer (A. Elbaz) for 600 rifles we have in sIn any further communica tion on this subject, please quote *»• ^321 and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London, dia. r The Undersecretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Undersecretary of State for and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cof^ of the under-mentioned paper? Foreign Office, , 1914 . Reference to previous letter: uUam. Description of Inclosure. Jo JJdlAsm Name and Date. Subject. (JMtsrthXsb CLowo Cl2] /7322/14 FOREIGN OFFICE, Febriaiy 24th, 1914. Gentleman: - With rafarance to your letter ol the 6th instant, ruspectlnf 1 : the .piality of certain cartricifsco manufactured by you and now at Muscat, 1 am directed by Secretary Sir E. Ore.' to Inf on i you that he regrets that ha does not see his way to comply with your suggestion that samples of these cartridges should be obtained by HI* Majesty's Representative at Muscat for examination in this country. I am, Oontlei .en, Yonr raObt obedient, hwnble Servant, esar 8« Kynoch and Company, Limited, Lion Works, Witton, Bi rralngbam.7.'22/l4. FOREIGN OFFICE, FobTiary 24th, 1914. Gentlamen: - I an directed by Socretaiy Sir E. Grey to , N, actoiofledge the receipt of your letter of the 5th Inetaiit, In which you en piire as to the result of the communications which have been passing with the Govern ment of India respecting your clairas against All Khan ! oosa Khan and Abdul Rahim Jaffar. I am to inform you that it has now been ascertained that the Government of India do not con sider that it would bo practicable for them to take action locally in support of your claims against these persons. I am. Gentlemen, Your most obedient, tumble Servant, !Big-mi) W, Langley. H. Laubenburg and Company, Cambridge Street, Birmlnrham.I I Draft to F. 0 . I am directed by the Secretary of State for India to acknowledge w w I the receipt of your letters of the 11th February 1914, Nos. 5467 and 567.-, regarding the disposal of o:.e stocks of the Pritish firms engaged in the arms trade with ;Kaskat. With regard to your letter No, 5673, the 1 arquesa of Crewe con curs in the proposal of the Becre- ; tary of State for Foreign Affairs ; to inform Messrs. Kynoch Ltd. that cLt-c? Iul. LL^ he no’Tr in a poni i'‘ oin to comply with their suggestion that samples of their cartridges at haskat should be obtained for examination in this country. With reference to your letter No. 5467, I an to state that iVessrs. Laubenburg r s receipt for £60, in respect of sales during the last quarter of 1913 is being forwarded in original to the Political Agent at Naskat. As regards the firm’s claims against 20 FEB 1914 Ali Nusa and Jaffar, to which reference is made in the 7 nd para. of your letter, I am to say that the papers promised by the Crqvt. X pj - 0 f India by the mail of 15th Jan. last#1 ryi) m f last have been received at this OfLice and were corariunicated to your Department or. the Ind Deb. Special attention is invited to raj or Knox'* telegram to the Govt, of India Mo. 9, dated the '3th January 1914, which was included among them. In the circumstances explains Lord Crewe fears that it would be imprac- 1 ^dv tidable to take further actiorTTocally, in support of I'essrs. Itaubenburg's claims. (si)TJ.MWSS, 1 l uIndia. /,/ it In any further communication on the subject, please quote no. 5467/14. and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. Foreign Office February 11 th, 1914 . i , Sir: - i- * * « MM (h. Cony fo ’'d ! a 20 FEB 1914 Wltn reIerence t0 Foreign Office letter No .3712 of the 4th inStant ' 1 M directed by Secretary Sir E. Grey to iorv; rd to you herewith in original, for transmission to ;hiscat, the receipt from Messrs. Laubenburg for the Sixty pounds received from His Majesty's Consul at Muscat in respect 01 sales oi Messrs. Laubenburg's arms during tne quarter ended December 31st. As regards the question of the recovery of the amounts claimed by the fim from Ali Moosa and Abdul Rahim Jaffar, I am to state that dir D. Grey proposes to await the report sent by mail on January 15th (see your letter of the 16th ultimo) before making any reply to Messrs. Laubenburg on t&amp;is question. I am, Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant, Unde r Secretary of State, India Office. h L 12FEB1S M A 1 HI'QasrS'Lau'banburg to '^trytjJqyxj Office. 5 February 1914 ' Sir ' fL fir in /Ik V h 3712/11 v * Ma t0 ^amlKioz ctuA rm*ir« of your lettera Qf ^ 8 th ultimo and 4th instant, the latter enclosing two postal none,/ orders amounting to Sixty pounds, being the mount received from His Majesty's Consul at lUscat in respect of the sale of Arms and Ammunition from our stock at lUsoat during the quarter ended the Cist Pecmher, for which we thank vou. Trusting to receive soon the result of your comcnications with the Government of India and with the Prttish Authorities at l’’. iso at respecting the disposal of our stocks and the mount due to us from Alt Khan Koosa Khan and Abdul Hahtm Jaffar. We have etc., (Sd. ) C.H.Lauben virg &amp; Co.kynoch, limited, LION V/OIiKS, WITTON, BIRMINGHAM. February 6th, 1914. Sir:- We have the honour to acknowledge the receipt of your letter of the 28th ultimo for which we thank you. With regard to the remarks in the concluding para graph of your letter, we may say that some time ago our Birmingham friends informed us that they had received a 9 complaint from Muscat respecting a certain lot of cartridges, but although both they and we did everything possible to obtain samples of the goods complained of, or to get more particulars, we were unsuccessful. In any case, the complaint was not regarded by our friends as a serious one, and the fact that we continued to do such a large trade, we think, confirms this. If His Majesty's representative at Muscat could obtain and send on to us samples of the cartridges complained of, we think we should be able to prove that the trouble was not due to the caps at all. We are &amp;c.. For Kynoch Limited, (Signed) A.E.Jowett. ® Under Secretary of State, Foreign Office. Secretary.Ub Britannic Majesty 'b consulate. Muroat fie 7fi January 1914. ,26 JAN I9l4j 3 ir, 6 , I .mve t. 1 © aonour iiilora you taat I iav© u ' lL *‘ daar&gt;attC;ied 'to your address two postr.l^ money orders amounting to £60/-(sixty only). ^ Tdis sum represents tie value of arms and ammunition sold under Maskat Ar^s Ware iouse rules during tie quarter ending 31fit December to approved purodasers from tie xs atooks t at present detained in tiat Wareioune and tde property of Messrs Ijaubenburg and ' , o of Birmingian. 3* I Pave the nonour to request you v/ill be so good as to $ay this amount to Messrs Laubenborg &amp; do of Bir- —mingiaa on account of tnis jonsulate and forward to me the firm*s receipt for t:iat amount. A sum of twelve anillings mas been deduct— -ed from the amount realised during tie quarter from tne sale oi' t xese arms to cover cost of remittance and I would request t iat tme firm nay be notified accordingly. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Major, Thiaf :lerk, foreign Office,, London. &lt;11 s Britannic Majesty's Consul,Mus at.51 Telegram P., No. 47-D. S., dated the 6th Jannary 19H ^ T DepartmeS, Delhi, &lt; ^ 0Ternmen * ; »f India in the Foreign and Political To-The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bnshire. {Repeated to Political Agent, Man tat.) be concluded. Will you khuily CMnmnmicatebv We 0011 ? 0Ternmeilt is about to stocks to be purchased should ie disposed ott js^ft%v\, /I* Telegram P., No. 7, dated and received the 7th January 19H. From—The Political Agent, Maskat, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in p • Department, Delhi. m the Forei ^ Political I have sent the following telegram to the British Resident, Bushire — Please refer to telegram No. 47-D. S„ dated 6th instant, from Foreign Department. Perhaps the following remarks may be of me r / Committee here (for ?) selection(s) and destruction, be one naval officer 88684 military officer privately ordered (to) Maskat garrison, and self as Presided As my experience (of) Laubenbnrg’s arms shows me the difficulty of how trade, I think we should be encouraged to destroy. When required for th P purpose (of) destruction, armed launches should be placed at our disposal bv the Senior Naval Officer and as a rule destruction would be by throwino- over board. Main expense, which is difficult to estimate, will be dhow and coolie hire for the conveyance (of) arms from godowns to launches and storage godowns. I think I can arrange for the latter in the godowns under the post master’s and dragoman’s quarters and magazine in Consular escort lines In order to guard, clean, and preserve such arms as are selected for future sale it will be necessary to increase temporarily the strength (of) the Consular guard by an armourer, one Naik, and twelve sepoys, which would suffice, and I can arrange this with the Officer Commanding. We could probably’ clear the French godowns in a fortnight and submit a report in a month showing arms and ammunition reserved for sale. The Officer Commanding troops and the Senior Naval Officer have been consulted by me and they see no difficulty in carrying out the above proposals Ends.-In any further communication on this subjc No. and address— The Under-Secretary of State. Foreign Office Foreign Office, London. '''! January 16th, 1914 . Sir I am directed, by Secretary Sir E. Grey to transmit to you herewith copy of a letter from Messrs. Kynoch respecting the arms trade at Muscat, together with copy of a letter from Colonel Tisdall commenting on the statements made by the firm. The draft of a reply which it is proposed to address to Messrs. Kynoch is also enclosed, and Sir E. Grey would be glad to learn whether the Marquess of Crewe concurs in the terms of this draft. As regards the question of the stocks held by the firm I am to observe that it would probably be desir able to help British firms, as far as possible, to avoid the loss which they may be expected to incur on the arms and ammunition prepared by them for the Muscat market. Sir E. Grey would accordingly suggest, unless Lord Crewe sees any objection, that the local author 1 - UMer Secretary of State fedia Office. 1 ties(1179/14) authorities etould be encouraged, when feasible, to sup ^ lv/ tl exj: ' rtiC * r ulrements from the stocks held by these firmB in England. I am. Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant,Registry No. 1179/14. Draft. jssrs. Kynoch Limited. K (W2-) ^ 0 ., J’anuan' I 91\ Gentlemen:- I am directed by Secretary Sir E. Grey to inform you that he has had under his consideration your letter of y the 22 nd ultimo in which you suggest that the ammunition prepared by you for Messrs Dieu should be taken into account in es timating the value of the stock of arms and ammunition to be purchased from Messrs. Dieu by His Majesty^ Government I am to inform you that you are mistaken in supposing that the rifles held by one of the Birmingham firms have been included in the claim put forward by Messrs. Dieu. Only the stocks held by Messrs. Dieu at Muscat and Jibuti are to be acquired, and His Majesty*s Govern ment would be unable to recognise any further claim which Messrs. Dieu might presentpresent In respect of other stocks; As regards the last paragraph of your letter I am to inform you that the Secretai y of State cannot advocate for you anything in the nature of a monopoly of the trade in arms and ammunition on the Muscat market• The local authorities will however he reminded that you hold a large stock prepared for their requirements.Ms Kocmeut ,s .ha l^n, Hia M „ e ,„, „ ] A^MS traffic. CONFIDENTIAL. [57911] * No. 1. Messrs. Kynoch to Foreign Office.—{Received December 24.) ^ r ’ __ _ TT ~ Lion JJ orks, Witton, Birmingham, December 22, 1913. MUSCAT. At the inteiviews which we have had with you in regard to compensatino* British firms or taking over the stocks which they have not been able to dispose of by means of the new regulations put into force last year, you have stated, and continued in writing, that no British firm shall be recognised or compensated in anv shape or form. In view of this decision we have been obliged to inform Messrs. Dieu &amp; Co.' that we hold them liable for a large quantity of cartridges which are still lying on our premises, and which were specially prepared for them in accordance with an under standing which avc had wdth that firm to always have in process of manufacture sufficient cartridges to meet their requirements. We were surprised to hear, therefore, that the stocks of rifles of one of the Birmingham firms have been included in Messrs. Dieu’s claim, and that this claim has been duly recognised by you, so that they will receive the full cash value for the rifles not taken. Seeing that our arrangement with Messrs. Dieu &amp; Co. was made simultaneously with that ot the Birmingham rifle firm in question, and that for all intents and purposes our positions are identical, w r e take the liberty of asking whether it is not possible for you to admit our claim as well as that of the firm in question, and to add to the claim of Messrs. Dieu the amount which thev are liable to us for the goods undelivered. As regards further orders for cartridges, which we understand wall be given out horn time to time both by the Sultan and the several sheikhs, &amp;c., and which w r e gather will be more or less controlled by you, w r e w r ould take this opportunity of asking whether preference can be given to us for such orders, not only to in some measure compensate us for the loss which avc have sustained through no fault of our oavu, but jdso to relieve us of the large stocks of cartridges which were prepared by us for the mis interested in the Muscat trade, and which they are now unable to take delievry of. We have, &amp;c. (For Messrs. KA T noch, Limited), a: E. JOWETT, Secretary. [1919 aa —3]AKMY INSPECTION DEPARTMENT # ENFIELE LOCK 9 POKTIFRP ENT), MIDDLESEX. 8 th January, 1914. Muscat. In reply to your letter of the 5 th Instant - 57911/13 - transmitting a copy of Messrs. Kynoch's letter of 22 nd December 1913, for observations - I beg to state, in reference to paragraph 5 of Messrs. Kynoch 1 © letter, that Monsieur Dieu’s claim for com pensation was only admitted for the stocks actually held at Muscat and included in the schedule agreed to i I hy the British and French Consuls at Muscat as the property of Monsieur Dieu (see Arms Traffic Confiden tial 43328). In addition, it was recontnended that a further stock held hy Monsieur Dleu at Jibuti, originally con signed to Muscat, should be taken over on the same terns as the stock at Muscat, subject however to delivery end verification at Muscat. At one of the interviews in Paris, Monsieur Dieu stated Secretary of State, Foreign Office.(235) stated that he by the raanulacturera, for PW-nt of rlflea .l reK!y mvTlM ^ ^ x ' Oouin, fo™ ed ^ 0I the 8tccte at ^ but Itoasrs. Kynoch . s aUrmC3 ^ 3 th01r latter ttat pw^t MU be «, tor rul , 8 iB lnc ‘ rrect - M «*r the rifles actually at Muscat art Jibuti were included to Monsieur meu's claim - Messrs, ■'ynoch's content uor in the eucceodlns parafraph Is therefore not supported. re- I would add that Monsieur Dleu read a letter cclvod by him from re as it.. Kynoch Limited resfect.lng a stock of atmuni- ion held by this firm for Monsieur Dleu on a ‘tacit understanding* i.e. net expressly ordered but Ifoneleur Dleu was Informed that the matter would not be entertained and he did not press The poxnt as, presumably, he was under no liability to take delivery. I a*n &amp;c., (Signed) A.L. Tisdall. Lieutenant Colonelbated Q U„. J 9^-^ Date. Under Secretary Secretary oi State Committee Under Secretary Secretary of State Initials. SUBJECT. Copy to. i? - /(, ^ ^ \ \ '&lt;~b FOR; INFORMATION. A / s, I x w yin any further comniun.ra- tion on this subject, please quote No. Jndia. and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. Pk 1 ‘ j 6 \ ! S Z.J The Undersecretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents vnpliments to the Urcxf/A ~ v and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop v) 0 f the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, &lt;y &gt; IQ i &lt; i~' Reference to previous letter: %*U*, (fffis f i'll3 cf Description of Inclosure. Name and Date. Subject. ^ Mfym, if (Similar letter sent to ) ru]678/14 FOREIGN OFFICE January 8th, 1911. Gentlaman:- I am directed by Secretary sir K.Grey to Inform you that he haa hud under hie consideration your letters of the 17th and 18th ultimo respecting the dis posal of your stock of anas at Muscat and other matters relating to your business at that place. I am In tha first placa to observe that you are mistaken in thinking that at the interview which your representative had at this Office on the 3rd ultimo he was informed that the French flms at Muscat / would no longer be allowed to carry on the trade. His Majesty 1 a Government has no power to prevent French or other firms trading with Muscat, provided that the re gulations are observed, nor can they advocate that you should be granted a monopoly of the trade. Sir S.Grey is also unable to entertain the suggestion that a part of the money to be paid to Messrs Gogayer a k^bentourg and Company, 58 * Cambridge Street, Birmingham.——— Ooguyer should be retained in order to settle any suns which my he du© to you from that firm. I am to add that the Secretary of 3tata le again coszsaunleating wiT,h the Oovenxaent of India and ^ith the British authorities at yuacat raapecting the diaposal of your stocks and the recovery of the amount du« to you from All Khan. I m, Gentlemen, Your r«ost obedient, humble Servant, fc: I k.Cji From Political Agent, Maskat, 8th January 1914. (Repeated to Viceroy.) ^ our^ telegram of 7th January. I have no information to explain Ivynochs report. His Highness intends to order arms and ammunition and has been making enquiries, but he has assured me that he has not yet placed any orders. Neither of us knows of anyone else at Maskat who could have sent orders indicated. Arabs dislike ‘vynochs’ ammunition on account of brass caps—they say these cartridges deteriorate rapidly.1 In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote Xo. I/in) and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. £ndi ia. Copy to India 30 JAN 1914 The Undersecretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents co, 'ph'neats to the Undersecretary of State for and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith copvt* of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, ■ , 1914 - Reference to previous letter: Description of Inclosure. Name and Date. Subject. I dFrrw 'IlfK-stCIn any further communication this subject, please quote No. 59/14. r and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Ofilce, bn8(^ at e. London. Sir:- Foreign Office January 6 th, 1914. I ain diracted by Secretary Sir E.Grey to transmit to you herewith copy of a letter from Messrs Kynoch respecting an enquiry received by the firm for a large quantity of ammunition for Muscat. Sir E.Grey proposes to reply that he has no know ledge of this enquiry, and I am to enquire whether the Marquess of Crewe concurs in this answer. I am. Sir,copy- ' (59). r K Y N 0 C H LIMITED, lion works, WITTON, BIRMINGHAM. r p \'\ 31st December, 1913 . Sir:- l.Iuscat,. Referring to the concluding paragraph in our luo^.r of tne &lt;32nd instant, we Peg to inform you that we have just received an enquiry from an outside source for a large quantity of ,303 cartridges, which are said to he destined for Muscat. If this is a legitimate enquiry we have no doubt, having regard to the arrange merit that you have made on the other side, that it is known to you. That being so, would it be possible for you to fall in with our wish - namely, to have all such business for Cartridges passed through us? Pending your reply we are not quoting the firm in question. We have, &amp;c., For Kynoch Limited, (Signed) A. E. Jowett, Secretary. Und9r Secrybary of State, Poi, eign offi ce .In any further communication on this subject, please quote no. 56984/13. and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. Foreign Office December 1913 I am directed by Secretary Sir E. Grey to transmit to you herewith copy of a letter from Messrs. Laubenburg respecting the disposal of their consignments of arms at Muscat, and their relations with lihan, Jaffar and the firms ol Dieu and G-oguyer. I am to observe that the account given in the penulti mate paragraph oi what was said in an interview with the repiesentatives oi the iirm at this Office respecting the trench firms is incorrect, and it is proposed so to inform Messrs. Laubenburg, and at the same time to point out to them that tnere can be no question of His Majesty’s Government advocating a monopoly for them of the arms trade at Muscat. In view, however, of the statements contained in this letter Sir E. Grey would be glad to learn whether in the opinion bnaer Sec retary of State of(56984/15) of the Marquess of Crewe anything can be done to assist Messrs. Lauoenburg in obtaining payment from Khan and Jaffar or to help them in any way in getting rid of their stock waen arms are required by the Sultan of Muscat. I am to add tbet the idea of laying an embargo on any part ol the money which is to be paid to Messrs. Goguyer cannon oe entertained, and dir h. Grey proposes so to into mi Messrs. Laubenburg. I am, Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant,C.H.LAUBENBUBG AND COuPANY, 5«, CAMBRIDGE STREET, BIRMINGHAM. December 17th, 1913. Sir:- Re Muscat. In accordance with the reQuest made to us at the Interview which you kindly granted to us on the 3rd Instant, we have the honour to put before you the various matters discussed, as per enclosed notes, which were drawn up for submitting to you at that Interview. As you expressed your determination not to grant us any compensation, we must abide by your decision, but v/e feel so strongly that the consequences of your action at Muscat fall so heavily and undeservedly upon us instead of upon the real culprits - who actually benefit, instead of being punished - that we humbly ask you to assist us in obtaining at least our rights from Khan, Jaffar, Goguyer and His Highness the Sultan. j Khan has still on order with us 1,500 rifles, each s ./i. with 100 cartridges, which at 40/-. equals £3,000. These he Is in justice bound to take, and although he refuses r Secretary of State Ior Foreign Affairs.2^ refuses to accept delivery of them on account of the ne W 'regulations, he ought, nevertheless, to pay us for them, and as he Is a very wealthy man (we are told worth at luaso £oO,OGO) we think His Majesty's Consul, if in- s: ivc i r A hy ou, could easily force him to discharge his liablli des t/O us witihout» rurbhor (l 0 lo,y. As you uro a or 3 *V 0 hold o. dopooit, rroiu him of £600, which sum was lodged with us as a security for the due fulfilment of his contract, on the understanding that it should be deducted from tho last invoice when the contract was completed. We were, however. Induced by you to allow this £600 to be deducted from the illegally obtained •Turkestan' shipment. Respecting the 'mashona' shipment for Khan and Jaffar amounting to about £3,400 (exclusive of Jaffar's deposit of £700) we have received a letter from His Majesty's Consul at Muscat dated November 26th 1913, saying that, so far, he has only sold goods to the amount of £21. 4. 8. and you will readily understand that at this rate of selling we shall not receive payment In full for 25 to 30 years. The Consul further wrote as follows^ K follows in a letter dated 20th October 1913:- In regard to the sale of the 'inashona' shipment I regret to inxorm you that the goods have been refused by 3heikh Khazal of uiuhaaiereah to whom they were offered for sale On the score that he could procure goods which suited him better at a cheaper rate elsewhere. The goods wars also offered to Haji Najif bin Ghallb, egent of the Sheikh of Koweit. The latter would have been ready to take them on payment at three months' date after delivery, hut I did not feel Justified in accepting his offer, and the negotiations fell through*. With regard to the Sheikh^ statement respecting the goods being too dear, we feel certain that this is contrary to fact, and that he could not possibly obtain rifles and cartridges at prices lower than those charged on our invoice. It is self evident therefore that the refusals to buy the goods are made for the sole purpose I ! pf cutting down the price, and probably in the hope that we shall eventually become so weary of the business that we shall finally let them go at a great sacrifice. We therefore humbly submit to you that you should take over and pay us for this 'Mashona' shipment, not however in the way you have done to the French traders, to whom you have agreed to pay a profit of 30Bo, hot only on the 'Mashona' but even a much later shipment. We2SB We have undertaken to accept a aaall profit of 10^ which Wo will barely cover the very heavy expenses WQ VG Incui red in lawyers' fees, travelling, cabling, exiici other expenses, to say nothing of the interest accruing for 1$ years. We consider that his Highness the Sultan has treated us In a particularly bad manner, for letters which we received from Khan &amp;c., show that he actually prevented them from paying for the 'Turkiston' shipment, although they had the goods and sold them at a great profit. Khan wrote us several times that he could have sold the 'tiashona' shipment in a legal manner to the Sheikh of Kowelt, but that His Majesty's Consul refused to hand him over the goods, because he said they be longed to Louis Dleu and Company. Concerning our connection with Louis Dieu and Company, we think you must all along have been under a misapprehension, and consequently unjustly incensed against us. We would explain that we have never had any business transactions with that firm, nor ever supplied them with any rifles or ammunition for this, or any other market; in fact the^ were our competitors and obtained their supplies from other Birmingham firms. Mr.aS\) Ur.Dieu caina to aoo us about May or June 1912, which was about the time we found out that our customers - Khan a^d Jafj.ur iLc., woie In the habit of obtaining our 0 goods without the Bill of Lading, and without first paying for them. When discussing this matter with Messrs Louis Dieu and Company, they offered to act as our agents and look after our interests and payments, which, having regard to the circumstances then obtain ing, we readily accepted, as It was necessary that we should have some one resident in Muscat to whom we might entrust our Bills of Lading. At our interview with you we mentioned that we (The Field Rifle Company) had obtained, by the assistance / of Hi a Majesty’s Consul, Muscat, and the intervention of the French Consul, a document by which Mr.A.Goguyer (A.Albaz) agreed to pay us an indemnity of £1,050 mini mum for 600 rifles which we had made to his order, and which he refused to teke delivery of when the new regula tions came into force at Muscat. According to this document - copy of which we enclose herewith - it will be seen that Mr.Goguyer promises to pay this minimum sum of £1,050 immediately he received an indemnity in whole oror part, and aa va undorotand that certain payments will shortly he made to him, we would ask you either to kindly forward this document to His Majesty's Consul at Muscat with the request to collect the sum In ques tion for us, or. If paid In Paris, to Goguyer's heirs or legal representatives to collect the same from the lattor there. We have already explained in our previous letters, as also at the Interview with you, that through the action of the late Sultan we have been made to suffer most severely and unjustly, not only by the large sums still outstanding, and the large stocks of finished rifles end material left on our hands, but also by having our trade absolutely ruined. We would also men tion that we still owe to Messrs Kynoch a considerable sum for cartridges supplied by them for the 'iviashona shipment. Irrespective of the large quantity of cartridges contracted for with them, delivery of .hlch 9 has not yet been taken. Fortunately this firm has been most considerate with us, and has been satisfied Aith small monthly payments on account, and so far have refrained from taking action and forcing acceptaccept delivery of the cartridges. It seems certainly very hard that we should be made.to suffer so severely, although we have done nothing illegal, and yet the parties who carried on this ne- farioua and illagal businase, and iiiady vast sums of money by it, should not only go scot free, but should actually benefit by it with your assistance. We really cannot believe that now you have had our case fully explained you will not ao something to help us, either in the way we have suggested, or in any other way you may deem just. • Wu further feel that we have been very badly treated in respect of the order that was placed by Khan last summer with a French firm to supply the Sultan with over a million cartridges, which might? equally /ell have been taken from our toshona shipment. His Highness the late Sultan having completely ignored his ooligauion* to us by virtue of the two special permits he gave us, the present Sultan ought in justice to give us some com pensation for the losses he has infliciea upon us, hich compensation he could well afford out of the handsome which you are paying him, and subsidy of £20,000 per annum.«m&lt;i being entirely in your hanue, u ehoule be e staple rntter lor you to obtain a reaeonable sum by „ w ol compensation for us. At our interview with you, you laid stress upon the fact that the trade in Muscat was not stopped, and that a certain demand for rifles and ammunition would still bo f Oj thcoming. You further mentioned that you would j not suffer any longer the French firms at Muscat to do .his Of}, ‘ nd we therefore venture to submit to you that one way in which you could certainly help and recoup us somewhat for our losses, as well as to give us a chance of clearing our heavy stocks of rifles and parts, as also the cartridges which we ore bound under contract to take from Messrs Kynoch, would be by induc ing His Highness the Sultan to recognise our flra in the future, as the only parties through whom rifles and ammunition for Muscat could be obtained. In conclusion we would say that we came away from ^he interview feeling that you in some degree recognised that our case was a very hard one, and we therefore trust that you will be good enough to do something to assistassist us In one way or another. We have &amp;c., ( ;1 Tied) C.H.Laubonburg and Company.T5oirit8 re ' ‘' for U8 ® at Interview 3rd December 1913. lst * Wh9n 80:1,2 shipments of rifles were seized in 1899 they were directed by the Marquis of saiebury to b c ^ releasenl and we were allowed to re-ship to Juecat. See ou;* letter herewith showing that we were not doing an unlawful trade* 2nd* According to Treaty of Commerce (herewith) made with the Sultan of Muscat in 1894 it states •No articles whatever shall he prohibited from being im ported into or exported from the territories of His Majesty the Sultan &amp;c.' and that for any alteration 12 months notice should he givera* No notice has been given. 3rd. We have hud for a number of years special Permits from His Majesty the Sultan allowing us to import withou' lot cr hindrance Arms and Ammunition into MuBCat. 4th. The last tv/o Permits (herewith) are to C.H. Laubenburg anc Company dated the 9th ^ert ibor 1908 for 6 years and to the Field Hifls Company dated i&gt;hc 5th June 1908 for 6 years, so that according to these Permit, we are stjll at liberty to ship to ftoscat^ An»(^5 £ji(i Anuunltxon until September 9th 1914 end June 1S14, 'without let or hindrance' according to the terns ci the Permits. 5th. Mashona shipment left hero on the ^ ^ cr: ^ 1 before the new Regulations cuixia into force and the Steam Ship 'Maabona* took an excepticnaxly long time to arrive at Muscat and ought to have arrived 1G to 14 hays before the first of September, neither at the time die we know of any new regulations coming into force. 6th. In April 1912 our Mr. Poole had an inter view with His Majesty the Sult&amp;n, when he did not ex press a wore of a Prohibition coming into force short ly; on the contrary, he hoped that our trade would increase. 7th. In your letter of November 26th 1912 you say that you cannot take any responsibility on account of our Permits because it is Vised by the French Consul, that this Vise is simply to prove that the signature is really that of Hir Majesty the Sultan, might have been witnessed by an: other respectable Party. 8th.8th. In your letter of May t;7th 1913 you say with re (sard to the Maehona shipment that 'no favour has been or will be shown to foreign dealers or shippers &amp;c.* yet we know that a few months ago the French Traders hac a very large quantity of Arms ard Aumunition released which they brougnt to their Go- cc'.vns at Muscat and afterwards sold at an encuncus profit. As our goods were not released wo consider a distinct and very valuable favour was shown to the French Traders. 9th. Moreover, we understand that His Majesty's (k)Vermont has taken over the whole of the remaining stocks of the French merchants at Muscat, and paid them at the full value plue 30'' profit. 10th. On the other hand, when in your letter of the 18th July 1913 you informed us that an oppor tunity was iucely to occur to dispoee of the stocks cf Arms and Airmunlt ion held hy us in the warehouses at Muscat anc that it could probably be arranged o sell our stocks, if we were willing to accept a moderate profit and if we agreed to abandon our claims - 156111?: the £' from Jaffar - we agreacl £600 deposit from Khan and £700 to your proposition and asked onlyonly thu moderate profit of 1C??. 11th. Mow considering that the French traders were able to sell a largo lot cf their Impounded stocks at an enormous profit and were paid by His Majesty's Government for all their remaining stocks full value plus 3C?o profit, you can Imagine our surprise at the contents of a letter dated October 20th 1913 from His Majesty*s Consul at Muscat, in which he says that he will consider himself fortunate if he can remit the valuo of our gooes - M&amp;shona shipment - within 12 months from the as.to of his letter. 12th. Now, as British subjects, and considering that we have never dons anything illagol in this business, having always properly declared the ship ments, we feel confident that you will not treat us in a worse manner than foreign subjects, as our claim to compensation is unquestionably much stronger than the claims cf the French Merchants, who, as we have heart at Muscat, are really blamed for any so called illeglt- | imate trade. We would repeat that we have cone our { trade always under special Peraits and openly, and based on Treaty Rights. We also firmly believe tha most, if not all, of our rifles and Ammunition wer for14 th. for a iagitlajL^o trade and destined for Hhaiks rounc Muecat dc. and that there was a legitimate as well as an ^^ -• x c &gt; proved by your own as .veil as the Consul's letters, where he mentions that he cculd aall our stcck either to the Shaik of Koweit or til a Chalk of ^'tchameraii. (Here we would also take exception no your isnorks made in your letter of the 27th May and to the effect- that this business is ^Disgraceful' if carried on by British subjects. We would emphatically state that there are no more loyal subjects to His Majesty The King than ourselves and we would never do anything to aid the King’s enemies). 13th. We would also much prefor to give up al together the making of Rifles and now that our trade has been absolutely ruined by His Majesty's Government at Muscat we submit that you should pay us for the warehouse goods, as well as for the l^nished and un finished goods in stock, made specially under special contract with customers at Muscat and for v/hich wo had £1*500 deposit, which Deposit you made us give up in return for helping us to get our 'Turkeswon shipment Paid.1 -n. 11 rou cannot do this we would ask you to assist us through Hie Majesty's Consul am His Majesty the 'Jultan at ‘Muscat to force noth Jaffar and Khan whom we knew are very wealthy, to discharge am Pay their 1 labilities to us and to pay for the goods that were ordered and which they refused to take after the Regulations cu/ae Into force. It seeiiis most unfair that these customers should be assisted to get out of their liabilities to us and that we should pay the whole of the loss. We also feel that His Majesty the ''Sultan shculc also be made to pay us compensation for breaking his agreement with us. 15th. The //hole affair has caused us a great and undeserved less, to say nothing of heavy charges for travelling - sending Mr. ^cle to Muscat - Lawyers expenses, cablegrams &amp;c. &amp;c. 16th. Respecting your statement in your letter cf the 18th No verier 1912 saying that compensation is not duo to 'British Merchants', we would maintain that it is not u question of compensation to British Mer chants but to a British firm whose principal trade for &amp; number of years has boon with Muscat unoer the full knowledge19 th. Knowledge oi Hie Governnent, and under Special Permits from His Majesty the Sultan of Muscat. In order to obtain tius trade it has necessitated the expend: /u/o o ■ nsiderahle Bums of money by sending representaoives oo ^UDcat anc havmp in readin&amp;ss large stccics which ere not suitable for other imirkets. 17th. i' ,, urthermore i our competitors hero^ who 1 have not done this trade direct with Muscat, but have had their orders and contracts principally from Paris Houses, have boon or will be paid for ail their unexecuted contracts, as otherwise they would take proceedings against their customers, so that these com petitors of ours lose nothing and we are penalized to the extent of having our large 'Mashone' shipment and thd InOO Rifles and many unfinished rifles made for and started on contracts placed by our »Iuscat c tornars. left on our hands without a chance of getting our money from our very veal thy customers, unless you give us your help and make them pay up. 18th. We have never been requested by the British Govarnnant or their Representatives not to ac this business in Arms and Ammunition.j.. • • • If your Malesty's Government will not give us any compensation whatever and assist us in aw way, then we would ask you to arrange that any future orders glv^n out for Anns ana Annunition be given to our Firm, or to compensate us for the less of the Legitimate tx*aao which you admit has always existed* aoth. Liability for cartridges to Kynochs.The Undersecretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Undersecretary of State for JL ^ and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop Lj 0 f the under-mentioned paper, lAAytt. ^a^Co-?-oiAjC. ' Foreign Office, SO • WS ■ / Reference to previous letter: Description of Inclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Cll sf' f . /^fuo — S— i n-^ . m... ■ fas I C. H. LAUBENBURG AND CQ7PAiNY. 58, CAMBRIDGE STREET, BIRMINGHAM. 18th December, 191.'5. Jr » » Sir:- Re 55416/13. We beg to confirm our letter of yesterday and have the honour to acknowledge receipt of youreof the 15th instant, and note the manner in which His Majesty's Consul is disposing of our stocks, and in reply would refer you to our remarks on this matter made in our letter of yesterday* In this letter we mentioned that the sum outstanding for •Mashona* shipment was about ^ £3,400: This however is not quite correct us the 10f£ profit v/e agreed to accept ought to have been added. We enclose a statement shewing that the net amount, after deducting Jaffar's deposit of £700, is j, £3,717.0.4. «lth regard to our clatt on Kton lor payment oj j £i.OOO. being for 1,500 Hlflee eaoh with 100 cartridge.! / nricinal letter from him at 40/- each, we enclose an original in which he ud r&gt; iit8 having dated November 26th 1^1', i this Vthis quantity still to take. This letter may be use ful to mis Majesty’s Consul in case Khan should refuse our claim. We have &amp;c.. (Signed) C.H.Laubenburg and Company.X With reference to your letter P.4551 of the 11th ultimo, respecting the clelm of Messrs Laubehburg in connection with the Muscat Arms Regulations, I am directed by Secretary Sir E.Grey to transmit to you herewith copy of a further letter which has been re ceived from the firm. The representatives of the firm have been invited to call at this Office on Wednesday next to discuss the matters to which they refer. It would however appear from their letter that it has not been found possible to dispose of their stock at Muscat in the manner ori ginally proposed, (see your letter P.3397 of the 22nd August), and Sir E.Grey would be much obliged if iniorma- tion could be obtained as soon as possible as to what has happened with regard to this matter. I am. Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant,C.H. LAUBENBURG AND COMPANY 58, CAMBRIDGE STREET, BIRMINGHAM. Dacember 3rd. 1S13. Reference 51561/13 We have the honour to acknowledge receipt of your letter of the 18th ultimo, and regret to notice the attitude you have taken up with regard to our claim. We have also received a letter from His Majesty's Consul at Muscat, on the matter of disposing of our 'Mashona* shipment which is of an unsatisfactory nature. As we have mentioned in our previous letters that this matter is of Importance and extreme urgency to ub y and as it is difficult to set out in a lettsr the various points, vhich we wish to submit to you f wa should feel obliged if you would grant us an in terview on either Tuesday or Vadnesday next. OTianking you in anticipation of your reply, . (Signed) C.H. Lauhenhurg and Company Under Secretary of State, Foreign Office. 12 1913 We have &amp;c..[12] In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote No. Q f and address— / '~X The Under-Secretary of htafe, Foreign Office, London. 11 COPY TO INDiA | S ECfU- r Ai Y'3 i The Undersecretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Undersecretary of State for t ^ ' and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop of the under-mentioned faper. Foreign Office, WS- RECEIVED^ 29 AUGiyu Reference to previous letter: P* 3 3 'Y l\ a i / 3. Description of Inclosure. INDIA OFI'iCDE. Name and Date. Subject. Cf Oaa^. . 25j, Puff- ~ . /Dp''' , ■ t' 29 ^9® Amwix amai. iUffUt 2$ , 1913. Uontlcnonj- «ith rsfarenco to your letter of tlic 18th. inottnt sspoctin^j tho proposed sale of your stock of arms and trounitiun at uaeat, 1 am directed by secretary uir &amp;» Urey to inform you tket ho ia again corcnunioctinr with iiis i.ajoaty'e Uonaul on the subject. with reasrd to your observation that you understand that the affairs in question will bo nettled in accordance with the contents 01 your letter of the 21at. ultimo, I am to point out tliat there ia nothing in the letters addressed to you from this iepartmait to warrant the assumption that this will nsuoasarily be the oauo. 1 an. Oentlamen, .our most oLa»’ient, ruiiwle servant •»r». baubaabur-j anti co'npnny, ab, -ambridge wtreet, i irmir^piwn.In any further communication on this subject, please quote No. 58418/13. and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. -- Foreign Office 20th. August, 1913. With reference to your letter of the 13th. instant (P.3270) I am directed by Secretary Sir E. Grey to transmit to you herewith for the information of the 1'arquess of Crewe copy of a letter from Lessrs. Laubehburg and Company respecting the disposal of their stocks at I'uscat. Sir E. Grey thinks it might be desirable to point out to the firm that they are not warranted in assuming from the Foreign Office letter of the 14th. copy of which is en closed, that the matter will necessarily be settled on the lines suggested by them, and I am to enquire whether Lord Crewe would wish a communication to this effect to be made to the firm. I am, r REQElVED 20 AUG 1913 h'.LilA OFFICE. Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant, Under Secretary India Office.FOREIGN OFFICE. August 14th, 1913 r- Gentlumon:- With refarer.ce to your letter ol the 2lst ultiinc respecting the proposals made lor the sale of your stock of anus at iiuscat, I am directed by Secretary Sir E.Grey to inform you that a telegram has been re ceived from His luijosty's Consul at Muscat stating that Monsieur Menasche claims that all the British stocks conoicneci to Mossrs Dlsu ond now detained In tlio //nro- houso havo 'beoii accjuirod by Massrs Dlsu* Until this claim is disposed of It will oe very difficult for the Consul to take any further steps in connexion with your stocks, and I m accordingly to suggest that you should telegraph instructions on the subject to your Agents at Muscat as soon as possible* I am &amp;c., (Signed) W.Langley 583r s Laubenburg and Company 58, Cambridge Street, Birmingham.'0 58 r .) ^ Unde 58, CA'.EKIDGE STREET, BIRMINGHAM, loth August,, Sir: - Be No. 3750^/1,3 - We l5 ®K to acknowledge receipt of your letter of the 14th Instant, contents of which we note, and understand that as soon as His Majesty's Consul at Muscat can obtain delivery of the Mashona Shipment, the affairs in question will he settled in accordance with the contents of our letter of the 21st ultimo. On receipt of your letter we communicated at once with Messrs. Louis Dieu and Cie Paris, and you will see by the enclosed. Telegram from them, that they have cabled out to Muscat not to put any obstacle in the way of the Sale of the Stock at the Custom House, Wo therefore trust that we shall soon hear now of a settlement. We have &amp;c., (Signed) C.H.Laubenburg and Company Secretary of State, p °mgn Office.4Lito In any further comtnunica- tion on this subject, please quote AL' • No ajid address— 1 / /3 The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. •rjfij I kJ ^ i / S 13 T/te Undersecretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Under-Secretary of State for and, by direction of the Secretary of % State, transmits herewith cop lAA of the under-mentioned faperS r ysrf7r~fc\ l HP! A ^ Foreign Office, S 1 ' IsEcn 1 ; ■; ai - ■5/ , 1913 . Reference to previous letter : Description of Inclosure. Xame and Date. Subject. CUrv^ flia fF C ~~ , i ku ffSpkfkif letter tetri VIn reply to your favour of the 18th Instant re Muscat, we have the honour to Inform you, that we shall he pleased to agree to your Propositions and dispose of our ' ashona shipment at Invoice price viz:- Khans Shipment - £2031. 3. 9. Jaffars £1548.15. 0. plus a profit IQ?' to he added. This profit will barely cover our loss of Interest and the extraordinary expenses for Travelling, Cables &amp;c., &amp;c., which we have incurred in this connection. With regard to the Deposit, we agree for the £700 to he deducted from the amounts owing by Jaffar being:- £479. 2. 6 for unpaid Turkistan Shipment £.2.20.17. 6 from the Mashona shipment £700. 0. 0. leaving a balance of £1327.17.6 plus IQ?' or as per en* closed statement amounting to £1460.13.3. i'fee Under Secretary of State, Foreign Office.We can however not agree to the Deduction of Khans eposit of £600 because our Terms upon which we ac cepted his orier were:- Delivery C.I.F. Muscat, cash againso jocumants, and for the Deposit to be deducted from the last shipment which is lying in our ware- house consists of IfOO Fifles and 150000 Cart ridges, Nevertheless we would also agree to the said Deposit to be deducted from the Mashona shipment,pro vided that you ca^ collect or secure the amount out standing for our Turkistan shipment viz., £1861.11.0 which he obtained illegally without the production of the Bill of Lading, and that you give rs your assistance in the recovery of the amount for the 1500 Fifles and 150000 Cartridges above mentioned. We enclose statement of amount owing by Khan amounting to £3580.5.11. We note your Femarks with regard to Agency rights of Messrs. Louis Dieu and Company to which we agree. We would further mention that If you could dis- pose to the Sultan of the 1500 .303 Martini Fifles and 150,000 Cartridges above mentioned and '/hich ready packed for delivery, we would be prepared to take 45/- (forty five shillings) each rifle including 100 cart ridgesl) cartridges to each delivered Cif K^uscat We have &amp;c.. (Signed) C.H. Lauhenburg and Company■ This Invoice (Khan's) consists of: 565 .303 Fifles (Martini - so-called .303 Mauser at Muscat) 1b . 303 Lee Metford - Special Pattern Sporting Plfles. 30 Oases each 2000 - .303 Cartridges, equals isoooo.L ;opy v 33898). ¥ V V KYNOGH LBkIITED, UC1I WORKS, BiaHNOHAM . July sand, iyi3. Slr:- Wa have tha honour to ncknowladga the receipt of your letter of the 18th instant informing ue that a certain number of rifles and cartridges are required for Muscat, and that an opportunity is likely to occur to dispose of the stocks now in the bonded warehouse at that place. As you are doubtless aware, we do not direct business with Muscat, so that the stocks to which you refer belong to our customers, who we understand are giving you the information wliich you require. As regards Mr. Louis T)leu, wo have no arrangement Whatever with him. So far as we can make out, the quantities of ammunition which you require are no longer available at Muscat, so that it will probably be- necessary to obtain the additional quantities from this side. In that cose we could supply you from the stocks which, p Under Secretary of State, ^ Foreign Office. ■as you are aware, have been lying here, and which were specially made for that mrket. Oiu Piles for the.303 Cartridges would be 80 /- net, Including packing and delivery c.i.f. Muscat. We have also a small stock of 41,750 Martini Cartridges which were specially made for that market, and which we should very much like to dispose of, as they are unsuitable for any other trade. These we would supply at 70/- net packed and delivered c.i.f. Muscat. ilie cartridges are all ready, so that we could ship inraedlately on receipt of your instructions. Wo take it that the necessary arrangements for payment would be made by you. Y/o shall be pleased to give you any further in- for.iation which you may require. We have, &amp;c., For Kynoch Limited, (Signed) A. Bddison, General Manager.In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote No. and address— •, /3 The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, 4 ^ London. v h The Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Undersecretary of State for ^ and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop lQA of the under-mentioned faperZ Foreign Office, /tUc*. PzjU- /Ay' 1 *' Description of Inclosure. Name and Date. Id Fu^rd FguA. ft) fcuOrtvduWj ft. JUL1913 30 ’V Si T., W r Subject. /'Toffc- - favtuo 21 oiorn&lt;&amp;. Jioly Jfr f 1913. G«ntl&lt;«nttn:- .iith rel*oranoa to rtfoant corroapondonco rospootic^; iha arms trado at ^uaoat t 1 10 directed by aocretary dir orey to iiu* orw you that a tol^r«j*!i imu Lucn received i’ror Hia majesty 1 a vionaul at i uacat atetin^ that an opportunity ia liiioly to occur to diapoa© oi‘ the atochta ot aroa and aimunition held uy you in the warehouao# it ia understood that about One thousand ; auser rillua with about ouven huiidrud thousand rounds o£ aaniunition and about three hundred thousand rounds oi kartini henry aa^uiiition are required# it could probably be arranged that these should be purcliased iron your stocks if you are willing to accept the invoice value plus a moderate prof it t enu ii you are prepared to agree to tills errangoi.ent ,'mcl ^ill inform this kcpartisant of the rate required the necessary instruc tions could be sent to muscat by telegraph# it would how ever j-dsuted#T Copy.'- 1 Gentlemen:- &gt;' 0 Riil&lt;BJ 0 mC 4 . July , 1913, afith reference to recent correspondence respecting the arms tr^cic at I.uscat, i am directed by uecretary iiir a# urey to inform you that a telegram haa been received from iiia ^ajeaty a Consul at i.uBcat stating that an opportunity iii lihely to occur to dispose of the stocks of arms and art iunition held by you in the warehouse* it is understood that about One thousand r euser riiles with about uevon hundred thousand rounds of ammunition and about fhree hundred thousand rounds of kartini Henry ammunition are required. it could probably be arranged that those should be purchased from your stocks if you are willing to accept the invoice value plus a moderate profit, end if -y you ;jre prepared to agree to this arrangement and will inform this bepartment of the rate required the necessary instruc- ns could be sent to uscat by telegraph. it would how- srs. Laubenlmrg, and Company.however not bo possible for bir Urey to intervene in the matter unless it is understood that all claims on the part of yourselves and of kesars. hynooh against Abdul lahim Jafar ajid Ali khan are abandoned, and that the Consul is authorised to ceduct from the purchase money the deposits paid by these tw0 Parti 68 * it would also be necessary for you to deal direct with the agent of Lr. Louis Lieu as regards agency rights, as this point is not one in which the Consul could intervene* ^ similar letter has been addressed to Messrs* K^noch. 1 am, iIn any further communication on this subject, please quote No. 30701/13. and address— The Under-Secretary of State. Foreign Office, 11 ^% ate. Sir:- 2 * y 8 I 9 i5 J Foreign Office July llth, 1913 mh reference to my letter of the 8th. instant I am directed by Secretary Sir E. Grey to transmit to you herewith for the Information of the Marquees of Orewe copy of a letter which It is proposed to address to Messrs. Kynoch and hessrs. Laubenburg respecting the disposal of arms and ammunition at Muscat. Sir E. Grey would be glad to learn whether Lord Crewe concurs in the terms of this draft. I am. yv -07 ^12oUL1 Sir, Your moBt obedient, humble Servant, COPY TO INDIA 1 j SECRETARY’S NT.MT... | &gt; ^ Under Secretary of State, India Office.Regi epprp. epprp. rRegistry No. 30701/13. F. O. % July Draft. ]* c'oP\ TO 1^ I*? 191 f-- ^ SECT TARY’S • | Gentlemen:- With reference to recent correppondence reppecting the arm? trade at MUpcat, I am directed hy Secretary Sir E. Grey to inform you that a tele gram hap teen received, from Hip Majesty *p Consul at ?tipcat ptating that of the stocks of arms and ammunition held hy you in the warehouse. It is understood that about 1,000 Mauser rifles with about 700,000 rounds of ammunition and about 300,'000 rounds of Martini Henry ammunition are required. It could probably be arranged that these should be purchased from your stocks if you are willing to accept the invoice value plus a moderate profit. ]* COpV TO 1 ^ 1*6 1 9 1 f-- 7 fsECRr-TARY’S I 1 andIf you are prepared to agree to thip arrangement and will inform thip Department of the rate required the neceppary inatructionp could he pent to Muscat hy telegraph. It would however not he popsihle for Sir E. Grey to intervene in the matter unless it is understood that all claims on the part * Lauhenhurg of your selves and of Messrs. T . Kynoch against Ahdul Rahim Jafar end Alj Khan are abandoned, and that the Consul is authorised, to deduct from the purchase money the deposits paid hy these two parties. A similar letter has been addressed LgiUbenburg. to Messrs. K ynoch.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000419.0x000125_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/10/398</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000419.0x000125</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/10/398</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>File 2768/1913 'Arms traffic: Muscat warehouse; claims of British firms'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1911/1915</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-10-20T23:52:16</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">fre</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (318 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the inside front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 320; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains letters relating to the sale and shipment of arms and ammunition to Muscat in Oman. The majority of the correspondence is between the British firm of C H Laubenburg and British Political Agent in Muscat. The letters discuss changes to particular shipments of arms and ammunition as well as disputes and claims on payments due to the arms supplier. Other firms included in the correspondence are that of a W Darlow of Bedford, and Kynoch Limited.French correspondence in the file is issued from the French Consul in Muscat, Antoine Goguyer or Algerian Merchant Abraham Elbaz.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>C H Laubenburg and Company</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Arms industry</topic></subject><subject><geographic>Muscat</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Arms traffic</topic></subject><subject><topic>Business records</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000419.0x000125#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>