<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000466.0x000285_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-11T14:29:27.633Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">?1LE No. 26-S/1. © PY v 1940 . The Political Agent, Bahrain, presl«M*9PWiilPrtWfew^to:— ( ^. W., r 328 * u U).L '^/c. The Under Secretary of State for India, i India Office, London. and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document (s) The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf Bated 6th January 1940. Reference to previous correspondence: Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Export Licenses Nc 1409 dated 21st J and 11th August IS un &lt; RECb. POL. DEPt. j WJAN 1940 INDIA OF r !CE s. 1108, 1289, 1290and e,22nd July, 22nd July 39 respectively.^.6 Utfts » No. 2098-8/1. OPt r N The Political Agent, Bahrain, / / u *• f jO - 15 v *' *-fiiii^&gt;«&gt;J ^resciUs hifc-cbmplijaients to:— y&gt; - sc u IV The Under Secretary of State for India, India Office, London. and has the honour to send him jDoqijcxd the undermentioned document (s) The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf Dated— 29th November 1939. Reference to previous correspondence: Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Home Office License No. 1,419 dated the 14th August 1^39, duly countersigned.No. 1131-8/1. / \% ■ U3 r^.'. 443S 1959 . The Political Agent, Bahrain, Presents his compliments to: — rfy Asifk* fu^y(U*£t ^ t \^n (XC± HO. V ^ 1 21 JUL 1959^ J IT The Under Secretary of State for India, India Office, Whitehall, London. and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document ( s ) The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf. Dated 9th July 1939. Reference to pnevious correspondcn.ce: Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject.No. / C /6 C ) -8/1. h, Q/LP -7 D'-tD/ 1938 The Political Agent, Bahrain, Presents his compliments to: — The Under Secretary of State for India, India Office, Whitehall, LONDON. and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document ( s ) The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf. Dated ,14th December, 1938. Reference to previous correspondence: i Description of Enclosure, Name and Date. Subject. Licenses Nos. 750, ^t&gt;2 , 963, 1054 and 1055 dated the bth May, }3th June, and 24th June 1938 respectively. ri * —</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000466.0x000285_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/274</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000466.0x000285</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/274</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>PZ 8457/38 'Bahrain – Drugs – Licences issued'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1938/1940</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-12-22T00:03:02</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (5 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 7; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file consists of covering letters produced to enclose various licences granted in pursuance of the Dangerous Drugs Acts 1920-32. The original export and Home Office licences are not included in the file.The correspondents include: the Political Agent, Bahrain to the Under Secretary of State for India, India Office; and the India Office to the Under Secretary of State, Home Office.The file includes a divider which gives a list of correspondence references contained in the file by year. This is placed at the back of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Export licences</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>District Magistrate, Bahrain</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Drugs</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000466.0x000285#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>