<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x00002e_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-11T17:40:12.848Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">INo.15/C. FIDEKTIAL'. Bolltloatl A^enoy t Ku ;. it, D^ted February iVn , i., l j. To Tho Civil Coninlssioner, 4 B A d TT DAB. ‘ r . Reference attached letter from Bhalth *Abdul ’Aziz as Sa’ud in which he lays claim to 3AL3UL, the place A T here Shai/ch Salim intend;- building a qasr. X• I enclose a traced part-copy of the map which foraed i an annex to the An -Turclsh Agreement of 1 . I', It will be seen from thl that BALBUL is ml thin XT 'AIT territory, tho south ern boundary of which r’Jins by JR3AL TI^TTI^AH to the sea leaving cat paae 8 BALBUL about two and a half miles tr the dorth. Article ?/of the A ,rcement define;? the boundaries of Kuwait as follows:- ’’La 11 ;ne de dpmarc itloh part en lalssant a Koueit les oults d’Es-Safa et ....et.Antaa *x)ur «a'oo\itir a la nor pros de DJbbel-.¥ Mountfm. Cette li;'ne est marquee en vert sur 1 carte annexe© a la preoente coiiyentlpn (annexe V)„ H C. I an 'waiting instructions from you before replying, to the letter. 3. Up to the present Shaikh visitlny the olace and salectin- a the 1 piace and I Intend ^oin^ there the weather permits)to ensure that as stated. Salim has done nothinj beyond site. Re invited mo to see within the next fev days(if the location of the site Is Captain, Political Ajyent,Kuwait..Lett ir. I’ranalition. ^Tdul ’Aziz *&gt;vbdur iahnan il Kaiual ao &gt;a*ud• Captain D.V, 4cCollum., Political Acrer.t, r uwait* Dated 2^th dabi * al Alrhir 1?&gt;^7= lat Aebru ry,1919. deceived 7th February, 1919. From the testimony of all our officials of the port of w al Jubail” it appears that ohaiVh Salim al iubara/ intends making a place for himself within our nroperty at a cpot named 'balbul”. Verily we did not think he would do such a thing as the place is across our boundary. We like to inform you of this as something may occur by his entering within our boundary,which tiTiQ would be/cause of trouble. Ve do not knov what is his r^ son for doing this and truly we are surprised by this sudden ehtry. i^o doubt it will be known to you. The ^uwait-Hasa boundary both in the p^st and present is bnown. If it (i.e. dalim’s intention) is not known to you ve would like to notify you of it and of anything that may occur either now or afterwards. From. To. /W 125501103 7 f&gt;.O 00 Pad 8 . A. J. W. &amp; Co. 1 L 15 Forms/C. 2123 . '0' “ C ” Form (Duplicate). Army Form C. 2123 MESSAGES AND SIGNALS. No. of Message Charges to Pay. Olfice Stamp. £ s. d. Service Instructioni-: Handed in at Office m. Received FROM PLACE&amp; TIME--I I— i -a% / Tel egran. R. Rror . poli’tical . To. Ksili Givoor Baghdad. No. - Dated 24th April, 132Q. Shaith inferred r.e today that by Bin Saud’s ordrers Bin ishf^ir • • SliaiMi of Umtair tribe and a staunch a.thwan building houses and settling with his followers at jariyah which is within his uerri- tory aaa Shai'di requests that you will -kindly stop this and issue such orders as will prevent such encroachr.ents in future aaa Solicit early action be taken as tension between Bin Saud and Shafdi increasing. Tribes of forrrer are murdering travellers and looting caravans in Kuwait territory since last fortnight. Political.IP • 37/3. political Agenjy, Kuwait Dated Idth liay, 1920. To The ^ivil Cominis iloner, Baghdad. Me norandum. Heferenoe your telegram No.5369 dated 4th May,1920. Shaiith Sail a visited ne yesterday expressly in oonneotion with the oooupatijn of Jariyah by Bin ishgair. He states that his relations with Bin Saud are so impaired/that he finus it inpossible to settle the natter without your intervention. He produced in original a letter d^ted 25th P&amp;abi-al-Thani,i337 — 28th January, 1919 from Bin f!aud -nd a copy of his re^ly thereto^ d x, ted 9th Jauaai al Aw a 1337 = 11th February, 1919 reg.braing the Baloul question. Copies of these ^re forw ^-.ed herewith. It will be ooserveu therefrou that there is practically a cxeaa-look between theo. He states that cie^pite all thio, r^nd in ooedience to your orders he na^e friendly representations througli Bin Saud agent and odiers, but that Bin Saud is inflexible and continues to issue secret orders to Akhwan to rttaok and plunder Tjr uwait car vV .ns t.n^ travellers. He also inferoed ae th*t Bin lohg*ir has sent letters to Hil *1 bin Pejhan and ^hanlan bin xMi, the two biggest Kuwait pe &lt;.rl nerchants, and to ^o.ae others x’eq.ae ^ting to leave the country of Kafirs and to oa„e mn settle &gt;t Jariyah which is now naae near to theo. Purther that the interruption on the Kuwait- Zubair telegraph line fro.c 7th to 9th inst j.nt was due to the cutting of the line by TJmtair tricesnen in the vicinity of r a*bia These tribes.aen who -re all Axhwan h-d previously -to-cxed and looted near Janara a caravan of 6C Canels going fron Kuwait to Zubair. ✓ build ^asr at g ilcul he stopped fro.a doing so and begs now that you aay be pleased to order juin aud to stop -.r^n building at by the latter’s aggression The Shaikh states th-t when Government ordered hi.a to J -riyah, giving hi-a at the aa^e ti.te a definition oi the Kuwait boundaries.phe Shaiidi requested aie to make uhiD j ommuatoation io you oy telegraph au his own expense, but !• explained to hi a th .t it was one whioh I could not explain fully by telegraa, and that I v/ould therefore send it by ^ost. He eventually agreed to this but n.3-£ed te to request you to jend a telejraphio reply. He is tenporize I suggest th.*t su oh a reply aay be sent as will paoify him for tne present. auoh peiturbed over this question Ler^t, l/Z poliuoal Agency, Kuwait.MO. /3I -0. political ao&amp;mo Bahrain, the 13th May 1920 • X. 'Zo To hqu. The Oivil Gommisaioner, Baghdad Reference Ruwait f a Memo Bo«2d/c dated l2tf:*2l|iril .1920 &gt; to your addresa copy aent me under your Ho.i309§ dated 29th April Al Khalid Hamoula, tribe Bam Khalid today 15th May 1920 • He atated that 4 daya ago i.e. 9th May Shaikh Salim of Kuwait aent a party of raidera under (according to Bedouin report) Ali bin Khalifa and Ahmad bin Jabir against a body of Mutair Akhwan who were camped at Graiyat wells. This place is probably the same as the Jariyah i.at.28 Long. 48 mentioned in Political Agent Kuwait’s letter. The Mutair Akhwan were under the leadership of ibn SHGaIR a well known Shaikh of that tribe. My informant atated that Shaikh Salim (or ibn Mubarak as he ia called here) claima these wells aa within Kuwait territory and had already warned ibn Shgair to depart - but latter had refused and had started to build a few mud huts preparatory to settling for the hot weather. Aa a result of the raid, my informant stated, all ibn Shgair’a camels had been taken and the settlers had been driven away. Aa regards loss of life nothing definite could be elicited from Shaikh Abdul Aziz. 2. It is eawly to prophesy, but should any of the Mutair have been killed, one may expect to see some counter raiding of Kuwait territory on the part of the Mutair who are fiercely Olannish and will not allow the slight to go unpunished. The Mutair are strong- \ ly Akhwan and are under the notorious Shaikh Faisal ibn Sultan al Darwish. 1920 • I received a visit from Shaikh Abdul Aziz ibn Mijdal of the Copy to:- Political Agent, Bahrain D.P.R., Bushire P.A., Kuwait, yTelegran. Code. Civcom Baghdad. Political Bushire. \ Shaikh Bhaij who is in charge of Shaikh's flag in desert had yesterday witn report tnat on the morning of IJth April Faisal ■Qd Duwish Shaikh of Untair tribe with large number of Akiwan carrying their and Bin Saud f s flags advanced from .Jariyah and attacked Dhaij sho king out Din Din aaa Latter left car., and everything behind and narrowly escaped with some of his men on h©rse&amp;«*t)to Shiaibah aa^ N mber of T &lt;Uwait oribesmen are re orted milled details not received yet aaa Large force from Bin Saud said to&lt;be coming to attacm Kuwait aaa There is panic in town Shaikh has ordered bazaar to be closed for a few days and building wall to defend town and aking other military defensive prepara- tions. Political. 403. '• H.C. I/C Political Agency.Kuwait 20/5/20.Telegr^nl Code. Civoom Baghdad, political Bushire Reference r.y telegram 403. Authentic information not yet received, but it is believed that 1Q0 to 200 sen have been killed by Akhwan and upwards of 3000 car.els N ^of Shai^fh and tribes looted besides large number of sheep tents etc. Awazim were attacked by them on 21st but att-acK was repulsed Town is still being guarded at night Aduressed Baghdad repeated Bushire. polit ical 410 23/5/20MEMORANDUM No S/l£4_. OFFICE OF THE CIVIL COMMISSIONER, BAGHDAD. Political Agent, Kowait• S.G.P.Bd.—8—12—25,000—1-4-19. Tintp 22nd L^ay f _/ 9 ^0 Your 37/C, May 13th. Please inform Shaikh Salim that I have carefully considered the question raised by him with regard to his frontiers. In the light of my information regarding the Upper Akhvan movement generally, I do not see rr^ '/ay to address Binsaud in a latter for the moment, but I will do so as soon as he has replied to a letter which I sent to him on the 10th May, inviting him to a Conference to settle various matters outstanding between himself and Kdnj Hussain. This conference dll I hops take place within the next few months, and I will make it my business to see that the interests of Kowait are adequately represented by a representative chosen by the Shaikh of Kouait and by the Political Agent in person. The time and place o^ this conference cannot be settled at present, but he may rest assured that the matter will not be lost sight of. Acting Lieut. -Colonel. Civil Commissioner I. A. in Mesopotamia. \ G.L.Telegram. Prom. Uo. NO. . Dated Cu • More Kuwait. ? Uivoom Uj&amp;M Ma^i Arrived toda^/ aaa Have seed. Shai ^Salin and given him message contained in your S 154 of 2~' instant, aaa Have gained no fresh information regarding AKHWAN trouble aaa Foresee no serious danger to KUWAIT town aaa Names mentioned in previous wires are on Lorimers laaetteer map aaa Am proceeding BUSHIRF at noon in K.M-S- TRIAD. MORE.Telegram (P). To Civcom, repeated Political Busnire &amp; Bahrain. No 39 G. Dated 2nd. June 1920. Shaikh Salim despatched a letter to Ibn Sa*ud on June 1st about the Jariyah incident. He nas given me a copy and am posting it to you. Precis of letter begins : You are aware that Faisal ad-Duwaisl and the Ikliwan attacked, my son Da*ij &amp; his followers when suspect- li ing no tiling, and killed.&amp; robbed them. I was greatly surprised at this as our two houses are so closely allied by ties of religeon and family, and cannot imagine who can have incited Faisal 4 the Ikhwan to this disgraceful act. Had I not been anxious to save innocent Muslim lives, I would have taken action at the time, but I have been patient, as Faisal &lt;&amp; his followers are your subjects. _lj.i view of our brotherhood &amp; the long-standing alliance between us, I report the matter to you, and I feel confident that it will displease you even more than me, if once you realise the true facts and are not deceived by falsehoods. My request is that you will issue orders to Faisal to return the property and make resti- uution ior the men. If he will not obey your order, I cannot hold you excused and will have to appeal to arms. I send Abdullah as- 3uma.it and 'Abdul 'Aziz al-Hasan to visit you regarding this, and they are authorised to answer you. Bnds. I now estimate the number killed by the Ikhwan at 140. There is little doubt that they killed the wounded. No further Ikhwan move reported. There are numerous unreliable rumours, e.g. a proposed attack on Kuwait on the 'Id. Some people are doubtful of Ibn Sa'ud's pdwer to restrain the Mutair against their will, and this seems to be the sole possible danger, Jork on wall, which is oadiy sited, continues, hull has quite spoilt our aerodrome; will wire when new arrange ment raade.Addressed Civcom, repeated Bushlre and Bahrain. PoliticalTelegram ( P. ) From Oivcom, Baghdad To Political, Kuwait No. 6636. Dated 4th. June 19^0 (Received 5th. June) Reference your telegram No. 39 C., dated 2nd. June 19 2 ^. Remind Shaikh peremptorily that in case of real emergency aero planes, not walls, are Kuwait's fcest protection, and get him to keep landing ground in proper order./ M Telegram ( P. ) Proa Politioal, Kuwait, To Givcom, Baghdad, No. 40 C„ Dated 6th* June I 920 . ^ Reference your telegraa No. 6636 , dated the 4th. June. I-had already addressed the Shaikh and he has ordered the wall to he levelled and reconstructed outside the aerodrome. According to him it will he ready in a few days, hut I fear a more considerable delay is necessary before the ground can he fit to land on. I have inspected Me Gollum l s original landing ground, described as Site B by Lieut. Jones in his report dated Uth. November the pillars intact, no actual digging done and the surface good. The Shaikh promises to keep it clear as a temporary measure, so tliis may be used in the event of its being necessary to send an aeroplane here before the permanent aerodrome be ready again. In this case 1 would like 24 hours notice to enable me to v/hiten the centre of the ground and the pillars.3* Telegram Code. From P.A. Bahrain. To D.P.R.Bushire repeated to C.C.Baghdad. No. 654. Dated 26th and received 27th May, 1920. Mutair-Kuwait incident. Following received from Shaikh Manahi bin Fenir of Bani Khalid whose camp is near Graiyat and may be considered a trustworthy account. Begins:- Some days ago Bin Saud ordered Ibn Salighair of Mutair settle at Raiyat Mutair ase all Akhewan. Salim objected sent Bhaij his commander him Dhaij succeeded capturing Ibn &gt;-» Saughair’s camp. Latter appealed to Faisal for help, Faisal hurried from Nejd by forced march surprised and captured of Graiyat were camped Rishaida section of Avazim Kuwait tribe those were also rounded up by Faisal who carried off all live stock and ten Secahur? Faisal after raid returned Artawcleaving Ibn Saghair in possession of Graiyat. In nutshell Kuwait trod on lior/s tail and caught a Tartar. Here incident only looked upon as raid and counter-raid nothing more. Majority Awazim on perfectly good terms Bin Saud at present grazing with Bani Khalid gassa. Ends. My informant states Graiyat most certainly within Bin Baud’s territory. Addressed Bushire repeated Baghdad. force, Dhaij himself escaped. In the vicinity No. Office of the Civil Commissioner, Baghdad the 27th May, 1920. P.A.Koweit. Copy for information. •yux-Lieut .-Col., I.A., Acting Civil Commissioner in Mesopotamia. A.R.Telesram ( P. ) - Prom Political, Kuwait, To Civcom, Bashdad, IJo • 4 1 0 - Dated ^th. Jiane 1920 In continuation of my telegram No. 40 C., wall on landing -round almost down. Although I :iad impressed on Shaikh verbally and in writin- that the new wall should not be close to aerodrome, yet it is bein- built about tv/elve yards from its boundary and parallel to i^. I presume, however, that provided the actual aerodrome is clear tnis will not really matter. Should a greater distance be imperative kindly wire*33 N0.165-S of 1920. British Reeidency and Consulate-General Bushire, 30th.May 1920. Koweit. A copy of Bahrain confidential memo no.137-C of May 21st 1920 is forwarded^with compliments.with reference to Bahrain confidential memo no.l31-C. By order Lieut Assistant Resident.(COPY) No,.lS7-C POLITICAL AGENCY. Bahrain 21st May 1920. To Memorandum . Reference my n .131-0 dated 13th May 1920 reporting alleged attack by Shaikh Salim of Koweit’s men on ibn Shgair f s Akhuan camp at Garaiyat wells. I have received a later reoort, this time from Shaikh Hallal of the Mutair, to the effect that I the attack was made not by salines people, but by the paramount Shaikh of the Mutair Faisal al Darwish. The above is the more likely version of the two stories. ad/- H.R.P.Dickson, : T ajor, Political Agent, Bahrain To to D.P*R.Bushire.Sxanslation of lottor dated tetb Bamadrm 1398 - 29tli l ay 192C fron the Shaikh of uusralt to Tbn Qa*ud. You have hoard of the evil deed perpetrated by 1'aieal ad/«&gt;I&gt;uwaiBh and the Ildiwau: how he attaoked our .ion Da'1J with hia ■ aervanto and the nelctihourlng tribe a, whiah wore vltli hlra, and kll ed the non and oelcsad the property without justlfioation. They made this attack on thoia while they believed themselves safe as none oould poaslbly have foreseen ouoh a thine, and we wore ere at! surprised at it, Se have always considered that the M Ca’ud and A1 hub ah were one house by religion (&amp;£nan wa nadhhaban) family and honour* Wo were auoh astonished at tills ooeurrenoe and oan not imagin who oan have inoltod Jt'alsal ad-huwaieh and the Xkhwan to perpetrat till a disgraceful act* \ had we not been anxious to save the blood of kuslina and pro- teot Innocent lusliia lives we would have taken effective action at the time* * 1 &gt; ..e kept patient however and exercised forethought as Duwaiuh and hio follov/era arc your subjects* In view of the brotherhood and the long union which has been between us m are reporting the natter to you* os we feel opnfidon that it will displease you even more than it did us if onoe you kno- the real fact of the case* and ore not deceived by uatruo tales, for men of high position have attentive ears. that we hope from your hxcollcnoy is that you will order him to return the property £nd make restitution for the men for the sake of the honour of the two houses and families. If ho does not listen to your »ords and obey your ordern, we oan not excuse you and will have to say •Easbina Allah wa ni’jn al- b'akil* (we depend on God who is the best of helper six (l*e| a do- % claration of war) and the Lord will pardon ua for the Hood of too Kuslimu of tooth aides and will hold hixe guilty who Is the oause* • Af 1 ^ •La Laula wa^uwata Hla Blllahl ll« f All il~adhiia'. have ae« putod our men Atodullrdi as^Lumlt and AtodviUbls al-Basan to visit'3rou Njyardljv^ this vrt th«'r nvc* avt-horlsed to ropl^j to you and xa hBff eonfldoaoc in (Sod and you. V» hope for the oontlnuanoe of lore (frlondahlp) and union . Greetings to your father, hrothero and uma. our son Ahmad and hi a brother a a ad you tiiolr greetings. i “ifD i'elegram uoce. ij'rom JM Political, Bahrein. To n Political, K owe it,, ho. J&gt; 01 **u. Dated VlIi June ltt2G. Political, hov/eit. Letter from Bin Baud daied 25th liay rt ceived today summary as follows. Kuwait affair Bin Baud describes incident accuse Salim of being cause latter’s troops marched ostensibly to attack Qaraiyat dLS o^S reaching tirrnvif rutllatodjl Hammdh which is in Bin Baud*s territory east of Qaraiyat. Qurayat Mutair expecting attack asked Faisal for help latter arrived and greatly Irritated at advance of Daaij engage/him Bin Baud greatly regrets Balia took direct action lo - tsqAilato&amp;) him he should nave done so if ne nad any comr&gt;laint slxx against hut air asks now if he is free to oe dealt with direct with Kuwait or not if as Salim should communicate with nim at once if not then Government should settle matter oefore it jgrows Digger. ■ ' Political.do. U52-C / Political Agency, Bahrain, June IS 20. To The Civil Coirmissioner, Baghdad. idK^OHAiihUia:- In continuation of my telegram ^o. 15 1-C dated 3rd June 1920, 1 beg to forward, herewith enclosed, translation of Bin Baud *6 letter dated 7th Raraadhan 1358 ( 26th ilay 1 ) regarding the Kuwait - vutair affair, for your information. Uajor, C.I.I. Political Agent, Bahrain. Copy to L.P.R., Bus'ire P.A. Kuwait. tt »* (Ity? 'flu- //% yu+ATranslation of a latter dated 7th Ramadhan 1338 ( 3 R 6 th Ma&gt; liUO) from din gaud, Ruler of Rajd, to Major H.R.P.Dickaon, C«1 •£•9 political Agent # Bahrain* after Compllments # The object of writing this friendly letter is to enquire after your health and to say that my condition will please you in every Mfpeot* Mothing has occurred except what I informed your Honour of in my previous letter regarding Bin 8 ubah* Shaik of kuwait and his evil desire to harm my subjects the 'Mutair' who are residing within my boundaries as you may have heard. Bin gubah equipped his troops and alarmed the tribesmen residin in the vicinity of kuwait and determined to fight them. He then advanced to a place called C^aryah and declared war against mys subjects* I have informed your Honour in order that you may communicate with the Civil Conmissioner in Mesopotamia and ask him to 1st me know whether Bin gubah is under the pro tection of the High British Government or not. If he is then I request that his transgression and pointless intrigues may be stopped. If he is not i.e. if he is independent, I request I may be informed; my object is only to prevent any Incident which may cause displeasure. I had requested you to stop him (galem) from his goings on but he £ is determined to con tinue in his evil desires, ghaikh galem ordered the despatch of troops under the Command of Da|J As-Sucah, these arrived together with tribesman who were with him, at 'Al-Hamdh' a plac in mydominions and outside the boundaries of Kuwait. — The inhabitants of Qaryah begged their kinsmen viz., Mutair for help and on the advance of Bin gubah there was a skirmish t and subsequently occurred the trouble; This news displeased our hearts thi4r is their being attacked and consequently fleeing away, i desire to inform your Honour and to state that if Bin gubah has any complaint great or small, he should refer &gt; t it to me, and I shall communicate with the High British Govern ment and ask them to decide between us giving due Justice^3 '&amp;) • \ to a*oh aide* To matters In their present condition 1 fear will result in greate trouble* I request you to inform the Hon'ble Civil Commissioner of the above asking him to expedite a ra^ly with extreme hurry* Usual ending*1^7-C. POLXXICAL AG£MC iiahrain, the 7th June 19*0 To The Civil Conmiseioner, Baghdad• MikMUkAAiUUM Intelll^enoe Mutair-Kulttiit Affair. ’ibi-Al-Aziz al-Quaaibi Bin Saud^ agent in Bahrain has written me the attached letter: 1 gathered from him that the contents are practically a facsimile of a private letter from Bin Baud to himself. The ideas contained are of value I think as they give Bin Baud's point of view aa explained by him to a personal friend* Political Agent, Bahrain Copy: To D.p.R., Bushire• for information P• A* , Kuwait fly? /ti J 9 av. //?Translation of a letter dated ISth Hanadhan 133e(=*5rd June fro* Abdul Aziz bln Hasan duealbl, Agent of Bln Gaud In Bahrain to Major H.R.P.Dickson, C.I.E., Political Agent, B'diraln. After Conpllmente, I beg to Inforn you regarding the real news of the Uutuir and Ibn Subah. j Firstly regarding Waryah (Oaralyat or Jarlyah). This place ir the 'dlrah' and oawplng ground of the Dushan, (family of ai. :1, al Dawaish) *nd the Mutalr from old times, and now It is Inhabited by part of the Mutair who formerly used to Inhabit Al-Hatawifan but who left because of some local lll-f*ellng among them. When Bin Baud entered Hasa recently the Mutair came and asked him to give tnem 'Qaryah', this he did: The place Is not within the borders of Bln Subah, whose boundaries are known to gtart from Al-Sutalhlyah or even further northwards. After the Mutair encamped (under ibn im lair, at ftaryah. Bin Subah sent them a party on camels; but without letters. This party said to Ibn Shaqair the headman,'leave at once ^ or we will attack you.' Ibn Shaqair replied that Bln Subah was not Ml his Chief but that Bin Saud was, and that he would refer the matter to hi« for order®. Bln Subah, on hearing this reply from the leader of hie party was furious and declared war against the whole tribe of Mutair,and f definitely sent them a meesage as follows: 'You Mutair are rr.y eneiriei He then Issued a prohibition against the export of any grains or «txi other commodities to Bin Baud's people, as you have already heard. Bln subah next sent for his men and cousin DalJ and told them to take action against the Mutair and march on to the people of ftaryah. DalJ apparently was the instigator and planner of thie move. Mext DhalJ marched off and encam^pd at Al-Wafra and agai: . rt' er advanced to Al-Jahal. From this place he proceeded to Maqalr where he sent for the tribes of Al-Awazim, Al-Rlehaldah and cetafcn of the Mutair who had long ago settled within the borders of Kuwait. When they arrived he ordered them to Join his for ^ 8 aB he Intended attacking the settlers at Qaryah. To this they replled'we will neither listen to you, nor obey you because we are Bln Gaud's and tha inhabitants of Ciaryah are subjeets of Bin Saudani tha., have done no harm* Later however they agreed to march and startjd southwards* When ain ihaqair heard this news he at once sent for his kinsmen asking their help as he was afraid of Lin Subah for reasons that his women and childreii were with him* He sent a message also to Bin Baud who wrote and s ordered him not to proceed north of qaryah* and that should any one come and attack them at &lt; 4 aryah they should resist by force of arras* Xhe next move in the act was that Bin Sufcah's forces camped at Hamdh about five hours distant from ^,ar&gt;ah and to the southeast of it* From there Dhaij sent out a patrol which met a lAutair patrol from *aryah. There was a fight - The news having reached the respective Headquarter (Dhaij and ibn Bhqair) reinforcements were urgently called for* These coming up Joined battle with each other. We now know that Bin Subah was defeated although we do not know actually what were the casual ties on both sides* As regards the people of ITeJd all were sorry to hear the news,and extremely indignant to hear of the action of Bin Bubah* They also infmmed Lin Baud of this misdeed and he replied telling them that the question did not concern them* Bow the Imam Abdul Aziz has written asking me to inform jfOur Honour and to put two questions 'If Bin Bubah is under i the protection of the High British Government, then the matter can be settled between him and Bin Bubah through His Majesty*s Government* If on the pther hand Bin Bubaii is an independent ruler then he would like to deal direct with him*' The truth of the whole matter is that Bin Baud and the inhabitants of Mejd have nothing against jin Bubah and the people of Auwait, on the contrary they have affection for them, and in like manner the people of Auwait like Bin Baud and the inhabitants of Bejd* Bines however Balim Bin Bubah became Shaikh he has adopted a strangely contrary policy towards Bin Baud which is not hidden from you* Bin Baud has been exercising patients for the sake of your Government no doubt all Government officials are aware * of this change of attitude* Bin Baud has urged me to inform you of this affair for thetha settlement of whioh he is extremely anxious. He wants to know whether he oan settle the matter direct between him and ain ttubah or whether a settlement should be arranged through your Government.4 Telepran Fro 1 ^ - Political, Bahrair. To - Political, Bush1 re. Repeated - Civcom, Baghdad, ifo. ^7. Dated. P4th May \*2C. Your telerram 105? and last sentence; no telegra^ receivec t fro^ Bahgdad. Regarding Kuwait's report as far I can judge s™al] incident has been rragnified into big affair in order to win sympathy for Sale^ and discredit Bin Saud. Mutair under Faisal would never dare move against Kuwait without Bin Baud’s orders. Situation as follows; Graiyat wells marked Jaraiyah on map are claimed by both Kuwait and Bin Saud. In order to control recently surrendered Ajman Bin Saud ordered hutair occupy wells in question. Point is of strategic importance as its occupation prevents encrochment fro™ Kuwait and effectually keeps Ajman under tight rein. Salem objected move and ordered Dhaij drive away Mutair. Latter refused threatened fight if attacked: whether Mutair finally attacked Dhaij without provocation as' alleged not yet known here consider unlikely. Will keep you informed fresh news. Addressed Bushire repeated Baghdad. Political. Copy to; P.A., Kuwait (by posOTelegrar ro From - Political, Bahrain. To - Political, Bunhire. Repeated Civco rr ', Baghdad. No. B54. Dated n «th May Mutair Kuwait incident. Following received from Sahikh Manahi bin Fenir of Bani Khalid whose camp is near GRAIYAT and may he considered trustworthy account begins. Pome days ago Bin Saud ordered ibn SGHAIR of MUTAIR settle at GRAIYAT. MUTAIR are all AKHWAF. Salem objected sent CHAU his commander oust him Dhaij succeeded capturing ibn # Sghair's ca^p. Latter appealed to Faisal for help. Faisal hurried from Aajd by forced march surprised and captured whole Dhaij's force. Dhaij himself escaped. In the vicinity of Graiyat were camped Rishaida section of Awazim Kuwait tribe these were also rounded up by Faisal who carried off all live stock and tent«. Faisal after raid returned ARTATI leaving ibn Shgair in possession Graiyat. In nutshell Kuwait trod on lion 1 s tail and caught a Tartar. Here incident only looked upon as raid and counter raid nothing more. Majority Awazim on perfectly good terms Bin Saud at present grazing with Bani Khalid Hassa. Ends. My informat states Graiyat most certainly within Bin Baud’s territory. Addressed Bushire repeated Baghdad. Political Copy to: P.A., Kuwait (by post)&lt;9 i'/ T^lejrram Fro^ - Political, Bahrain. To - Civcom, Baghdad. So. 342-C. Dated P9th May l^PO. Bin Saud writes dated IBth Way. Corrplains Shaikh of Kuwait ■ been persecuting his ir utair Subjects at QARAIYAH, fails entirely | understand Salim'? strange and uncalled for action, especially latters declaration that, Mutair tribe are to be treated as enemies: If Salim has grievance he, Bin Saud, quite in dark regarding same. He cannot say what i^ at bottom Salim's actions now. He Bin Saud on terms friendship with Kuwait since Mubarrak's days. In spite grave news received he reluctant move. Asks H.M's Government take control and punish wrong doer before affair grows bigger. Letter follows. Political Copy to : D.P.R., Bushire ) by post ) for P.A., Kuwait ) information.Telegram. From - Political Bahrain To - Civil Commissioner t Baghdad No. 142 C Dated and received 29th May 1920 \Lcu~cL ^inoatheod writes 16th ''Ay complains Shaikh of Kuwait been persecuting his Mutair subjects at qaraiyah fails entirely to understand Salim’s strange and uncalled for action especi il Iv latters declaration that Mutair tribe are to be traated as enemies. If Salim has grievance he Birnwho** quite in dark Mubarak’s days. In spite of grave news received he reluctant move. Asks H.M.Government take control and punish wrong doer before affair grows bigger. Letter follows. Telegram. From - Political Bahrain. To - Civil Commissioner,Baghdad. No. 654. Dated 26th and received 28th May 1920. Mutair Kuwait incident.Following received from Shaikh Manahi bin Fenis of Banikhalid whose camp is near Graiyat and may be considered trustworthy account begins. Some days ago Bin Saud ordered ibn Soughair of Mutair settle at Graiyat Mutair are all Akhwan.Salim objected sent Dhaij his commander oust him.Dhaij succeeded,capturing Ibn Saughori’s camp.Latter appealed to Faisal for help. Faisal hurried from Najd by forced march surprised and captured whole Dhaij’s force,Dhaij himself escaped. In the vicinity of Grayat were camped Rishaid section of Awazim Kuwait tribe,these were all rounded up by Faisal who carried off all live stock and tents.Faisal after now. regarding same , He cannot say what is at bottom^Salim^ s action tSSLi on term, friendship with Kuwait since raid uraid returned Artawi leaving Ibn Saghair in possession of Gray!at. In nutshell Kuwait trod on lions tail and caught a tarts Here incident only looked upon as raid and counter raid nothing more. Majority Awaizim on perfectly good terns, i-t-d Binomfry at present grazing with Bani Khalid Hassa en r ^. y informant states Graiyat most certainly with Bin Sand’s territory. Addressed Bushire repeated Baghdad. T/zr. Office of the Civil Commissioner Baghdad,31st May 1920. To By,Political Regident.Bushlre. Political Agent.Kowelt. Political Agent.Bahrain. Copies forwarded for information.- Lieut-Colonel I.A. Ag.Civil Commissioner in Mesopotamia.QuMfrlDJsUa^UL * POLITICAL AGfeiUCY. Buhrain # the 14th June 19£0« To /Vo. ¥S~ ^2'S r £far*. rtZ*’ The Civil Commiealoner # b a G H C A U. MLMui 4 AbLUM « IntalliRenoe * bJ (1) Ae: Aueuit - iiutair Affair* Shaikh Abdullah bin Isa al JChalifah, C*I*E«, informs me that FAISAL al Dawiah has returned to QRAllAT (Jariyah) from Aejd. As a matter of fact shaikh Abdullah reports that Paiaal was met half way to Eiadh by a messenger from bin Saud upon which he returned; (*). On 10th June I asked Abdul Aaiz alAuaaibi whether there was any possible chance of the Mutuir acting against Kuwait i; spite of bin baud’s orderas He laughed at the suggestion and said such a contingency was impossible* The Hutair was one of the moot loyal of bin baud’s tribes and would never move in face of definite orders now received from bin Saud* They will however hang on to « 4 raiyat* (3) . Regarding Hail news; A good many rumours are going about regarding bin Rasohid having denounced the recently ratified treaty between himself and bin Raud. I have not yet received anything worth making a definite report about, as everything one hears here is unreliable* The moot common story is that Bin Rasohid’s family took offence at a recent order of Bin Saud in which the latter informed bin Rasohid that their ,, weJh ,, or 'tisyar' (official safe conduct) would not be recognized in Mejd; and as a result had determined to denounce the recently made treaty* (4) * Mahomed al Saud brother of the Imam is reported to have taken a force to passim about 13 days ago* Another small force under Abdullah al baud another brotheris said to have moved up in the direotion of Kuwait as a pre cautionary measure* The first report is confirmed by al Qusaibi here who says hin gaud^ idea is to prevent the discontented Hail party from intriguing anywhere passim way, hence the demonstration&lt; The second report Al ^uaaibi says is untrue* (5)* uuring the week X sent Bin Baud's two sons a small 'Ravage' rifle a piece with 600 rounds of ammunition, also to Bin Jaloui amir of Hasaa a gold watch and to Ibn Bhalhoob, Bin Baud's private secretary a gold watch. The above gifts being a small tb&gt;FFVf* return for the hospitality shown me whilst in tt&amp;adh'. Political Agent, Bahrain* Copy to: 0*P*M«, Bushire* ?•*., Kuwait• \ Tcle^rani (Code) Fppfi Political, Bahrain, Td Political, Kuwait, No. 173-C. Dated tst (Reed, 2nd.) July 1920# ’'roar telegram 7b70, Private letter to Shaikh of Bahrain fro a Najd so l arcc stated reliable, q^ives following version recent reports 3 ha mar. A’dr.an affair. Begins. About 10th (Tune Ibn Rabian, Shailth Attalbah, attached section Harb and Hu tain tribes at Baidha ITathil, sixty Ale’s west Hail, captured all their canels; losses on both sides approximately 500 . Later, all Harb counter-raided camp Shammer, who recently converted to Ahhwanisn at G-uara (luwarah), twenty miles west lusaibah, Harb raid successful; Shammar Alihwans practically wiped out. Dads. Above confirmed by mainland Bedouin sources. # Bin Sa’ud writing :c fro i Riyadh on 24th June re Kuwait aff ir makes _ no mention anything unusual, present is regular season for Bedouins to ghaszu. My opinion is that little importance need be attached stories fighting which are’obviously only ordinary raids. According . Qusaibi relations between Bin Sa’ud and Bin Rashid friendly. Addressed Baghdad, repeated -Kuwait. For Bushire ’oy post. (/' ly h /V ^Telegram (t«) From Political, Kuwait To Oivoom, Baghdad (Repd. Politicals Bushire &amp; Bahrain. No* 47 0. Dated 4th July 1f20 Reference my telegram No &gt;9 0 of 2nd Juft* 0 Meflsangers arrired back today, accompanied by Nasir ibn Sa’ud al-Parhan with a letter from Ibn 4a , ud. Believe letter to be satisfactory, but have not yet seen it. According to Nafisi they confirm report contained in first part of telegram No. 173-0 from Bahrain but say that after this, about 13th June, Ibn §a , ud , s son Sa'ud did raid Shammar near Shu'aibah, though they do not acknowledge his subsequent defeat* People here still believe the rumour reported in my telegram No 46-0, . ’^ut my opinion is th at, though possibly founded on fact, it is a great exaggeration*V Telegram (?.£ From Political, ' To Civcom, B a g No. 0. Dated 5th July 1^20. liy telegram No. 47 G. I am posting a copy of Ihn 3a 1 ud 1 s letter to Baghdad. It is most dissappointing and seems quite opposed to Clause VI of our treaty of 26th foecember 1915. Precis begins. I did not tell or v/ish Duwaish to attack, but I can not blame him. I am returning some of the loot and am collecting the rest. Uver sinefc you became shaikh you have been constantly worryiiog me; rece] for example by sending your men to JarAyah without letting me Icno.v . \ by forbiddiii^ trade with ^ny ports, etc. If you say the British gave Jariyah to you I know how to talk to them. In the old days there was never any question of boundaries bet7,reen our respective . . families as yours stopped in Kuwait and'mine ran the tribes. It was Mubarak who first started taking ”zakat M , at a time when our power was weak. He conquered Hasa and gave it over to the Turks in return for the M zakat” of the Awazin. Although he took over the Mutair and other* tribes I said nothing. Jhen he died the tribes came back to me of their own accord. It was you who first raised &gt; \ the boundary, question by claiming as your own-this and that tract of land. I advise you to .accept my terms and sign the enclosed paper, as'if you do not I will attack you on the next provocation, dnds. Paper for Shaikh's signature begins: To Ibn Sa'ud. After complements. (As was the case) before God forced these differences betv/een us, there is no difference between ufly and I am to you as were my ancestors. 'Jith regard to the frontiers and tribes I will not encroach on your rights according to the old system. I write this to ease youT'mind and.for the sake of friendship and peace. uwait dad, Repd. Politicals Bushire &amp; BahrainTelegram (?•) From Political, Kuwait To Civcom, Baghdad No* 50 G. . Dated 5th July 1920 Reference my telegrams No. 48 G and No. 49 G. Shaikh is very anxious for advice as to how he should reply to Ibn 3a*ud. He lays great stress on Anglo-Turkisii Agreement. No prospect of honour- - able peace except by our help. You should get copies of Ibn Sa , ud*s and Ibn Rashid* s letters by Friday morning when kindly reply as soon as possible as messengers anxious to get away. %' \ To S Translation of a letter, dated 21st June- 15^0 from Ito Sa^ud to Shaikh Salim al-l.!ubarak as-Subah, ' - , I have received your letter, dated the 12 th ultimo ( 29 th Ivlay and have understood all that you said therein, especially re^ardin^ the attack made by Pawish on Du*aij and your Arabs v. r ho were with him, also your remarks about the past and present union between the two houses of Sa'ucj. and Subah; also that you only left DaWish 'alone, when you were able to punish him, so as to avoid bloodshed amingst Muslins; also what you say about restitution, and that you will not hold me excused should he disobey me. All that you have stated is true. The sood deed from you is not much, and it is only right that I should do what you ask. Thank God there is no one here who can over-rule me, and I am able to. enforce my will with or without anyone else*s / consent, as the good man knows himselfw I, your brother, v/ould like,, however, to explain one or two points regarding which you have written. . As regards Ijawish’s attack: God knows I did not order him to attack, nor did I wish-him to, especially in the way he did. I did, however, know of their gathering and taking defensive measures. But God ohdained the incident in question,! can not say I am sorry that it happened, for reasons which I shall now give. As a matter of fact, I did send men to stop them, but the affair had already taken place. I call God to witness that, from the time I left Kuwait till this moment,.! have always wished well of the people of Kuwait, from the Gubah family itself down to the meanest of the inhabitants, ad is known to both God and aan. As regards the relations between the Subah and S’a*ud families, I can only say in the words of the poet:- ,s If affairs be in the hands of the wise, only good will result; if they be in the hands of the wicked, then evil consequences will be brought on all. This is very true indeed, 0 son of Mubarak, One would never have dreamed that that friction could possibly air is e between the Sa*ud and Subah families, and I can not now understand why it should.' Think yourself what have been and are the causes of this friction, or ask people of understanding who are with you and they will tell you. As to your statement that you left Dav/ish alone for my sake, it was a good thought of yours, as God forbid that the' day ever come when you and I measure our strength together. You know .that when facts are concealed, and the truth is not • known disagreements are sure to arise, so both sides must disclose, all the facts* As regards the events which have* occurred, God know:: I hadno knowledge of br part ip them, nor do I know any outward or 1 inward cause for them other than yourself. Ever since you became Ruler of Kuwait, I do not remember a single month passing in which you have not worried me in some way, and that without any cause. I h ,ve tried to disbelieve reports which are commonly talked about, and^ have absolutely disregarded more obscure rumours. Since the month of Aajab five specific incidents have taken place, which could only appear to be the work of a mischief maker, but you .are not that, of' course; 0 no, you are a very wise,man and on-, of great knowledge! You do evil because you like* ^.t, and you seek it for its own. sake. .(I; You sent a-mounted force to threaten the neoole at Jrriyah -• . without first warning me. ‘ \ a ' (2) .Then Kafisi came here, you‘merely sent me a verbal message by him -* • anci nad not the* -hr* r i t • &lt; (3) ding at ; ~ ^ inscigation, and you sent me no letter or m cssa k* K( k ou t ss ? ed an °^ der in Kuwait prohibiting exports to my ports. * You declared war on the Mutair, \ :ie kear what you have to say about these five ooAnts. ~ tue or iocs and people affected had been no one's children mien, ox course, you could have dealt with,them; but they are my cnildren, and I, yoUr brother, am their ruler, and yet you did not +£ rc ‘ L ?i\ to r;1 ®- as their chief. You are certainly not a man to treat v...s....* .&gt; 1 ...i goou ?o .icy, nor are you one who could say that vqu d’d ^ t lor^fnendshi^ s sake, and whom I could thank for doing it. The reason ui|e 1 lo f t k7aG that uy subjects have bee troubled with doubts, and ' onerc are tnre^ kinds of them : ( 1 ) those who-are afraid. ( 2 ) those wno are the guardians of their religcon and their country,- and ( 3 ) tao '; e ,7ao , llate eval : 1 myself have b:ien sdrt-ly puzzled as to the cause of tnese affairs as there appears to be no r-.a T 1 u:icm^r-. v .s kie;? nothing until Du'aij.' appeared against N the ; anu tney naturally believed the ru.lours which the- ha' hea- son. Tnc people t Ha idh u heard before.‘ ■ 11 6 /v o ; \' 2 ncl what God had ordained took place, for, as la said in holy •*r ; * u Nou^lit that ye devise can ]dc fulfilled unless God I rinse If v/ill it''. You will realise that these events have been Going on for a long tine now, and 1 both (n*eat; and s .all havevfelt their effect. It behoves ,us not to think of greed and satisfying pur own ends, but of how this^ • ever widening - breach, which as you know will har i both of us, can be repaired. Two things are necessary, one now and one later on. The first is that you sign the attached note as a final settlement of the boundary, and other disputes. If you have any claims to'put forwarl I will obey justice, or if you make it your plea that Jariyah lias b 6 en given to you by the British, then leave the matter to them and 'X know how to talk to then. Secondly, you may rest assured that all I have said in this letter is true, as is :y purpose, and' I assure yOu that every foot towards a settlement that you go, I will go a, yard. ; \ . * ^ Regarding your friends ‘Abdullah as-Sumait and *Abdul 1 Aziz al-Hasan, they have given me your-message, and I have explained everything that was necessary to them,, and 'thereis no might or pov;er save in God”. As. touchiiig the restitution, I ai sending two camels, a riding camel and a horse with your friends, and I have sent out men to collect the rest; as soon as our differepees are settled, all you demand will be available - from my own property, if not from yours. I am sending my uncle, Hasir bin Sa*ud, with your deputation, in the hope that he my gain your good will. I pray to settle our autual affairs, and'those of all Muslims, so that ye may come to an agreement arid.be united. ' - &gt; r usual ending. Supplement to the above. After complements. You know that the affairs of this world depend upon two things i the first and highest is the 'Shdri’ah 11 , and the Second is steadfastness of purpose and forethought, as the poet has said:-'“The careful man is he -who’ does nothing until he lias considered N what its result willbtiV- You must realise that it was not I who Started all these quarrels and disputes about boundaries,and subjects,* but that it was you your self wh 6 were responsible for them, though I trust they will now be ~ settled. I want to explain what my own point of view is, and you know best what your own is and whether the two agree. You know that from the very beginning there was never any question about boundaries and subjects between the s Subah and 'Sd’ud fa.lilies, nor was there .ever any misunderstanding between them, the 3ubah stopped '/ in. Kuwait and the Sa'ud controlled the tribes, and there was no friction. Then, when evil days fell on Najd'and the country was split .'into two parts, one under the Turks, the AjPan and others, and the other under Ibn Rashid, people who were discontented at this went to Kuwait, as there was no difference, between the tribes or people, and everything went quietly until the death of Muhammad as-3ubah. After him Mubarak succeeded, and I was^in Kuwait. He started- taking 'zakat u from the tribes, which began to come' in to Kuwait - they used to go one year to him, another to.Ibn Rashid, and another to the,Turks V/hen your ( father occupied Hasa fori me. he paid the Turks / 600 dollars a year for the “zakat“ of the Awazitn. Although the Mutair mne Subai' and others used to come and pay him “zakat“, but I said nothing as it-mvas all in the vray of friendship. When your father died the . .utaut-hi .and the Rashaidah were with me, .and took 'zakat” from them. If things had gone on the same v/ay there would never have been any question of'where our frontier was or whose subjects such and such a tribe was. It was you, in your greed, who started the dispute by N claiming such and such property as-your own. I am not greedy so' why should you be when I an your^friend and-brother. If you can orove your right by the “Shar*”, then I bow before the Shap*, if by the sword then let the sword decide, but if by friendship^then I an the man for friendship.This will show who is obedient and who disobedient. so but do aot stir up strife arid widen the breach, if 70U appeal to&lt;■ .^7 the Shar*, I must win on my evidence, and if to the other alt^rnativ (war) I will not .a^ree as it is cruel and hateful to God and man. Now, -Salim my brother whom I honour, I beg of you to ^ive up your contentions and stop these disputes Which can benefit you neither now hereafter. It is not for my own 5 ain I say this. I an confident that if I am driven to fight for my rights, by the grace of God I shall win. I have nothing' but the best of intentions towards Kuwait and its people, and for you, its ruler, and for your people I wish nothing T^ut peaore. I swear to god that I will be to you as I was,to your father and your brother, and to ,deal with you in the future as I did in the past. But if you refuse to sign this paper, then I am absolved from all' responsibility. If you deal peacably with me I will do the same with you, but if you v/orry me I will talce immediate action, uay God aid us to a settlement. Document for signature. From Salim al-Mubarak as-3ubah to Abdul ‘Aziz bin Abdur Rahman al-Fulsal, After complements. (As was the cas^) before God forced these differences between us,there is no difference -between us, and I am to you as were my ancestors.T/ith regard to the frontiers and the tribes I will not encroach on your rights according to the old system. I write this to ease your mind and for the sake of friendship and neace. m 1....Translation of a letter dated 6th 3hawwai 13-.8 (2;ird June, 1920) from H # E.Shaikh Sir AMul Aziz A1 Faisal As Saud, K.C.I.E., Ruler of Nejd # Hassa and Dependanciea, to lajor H 4 R.P.Dickson, Political Agent, Bahrain. After Cpupil. ignt s I have already informed you of the regretahle incident which recently took place owing to the high handed actions of Bin Subah, Rul^r of Koweit. Recently a deputation from Koweit with letters arrived in Riadh. They have admitted their fault and confessed that they were in the wrong* I have returned the deputation with letters, copies of which I am forwarding enclosed herein for perusal. My object is only to secure peace and tranquility in y territories and tha neighbouring districts, most es pecially those parts which are under the prfcection of my { friends, the British Govern:.ent. I have also sent back with the deputation on# of the A1 Baud family, namely hasir ibn Baud, and I trust that any mistake or ; i sunder standing will be cleared up through his good offices and that relat ions (between Koweit and ourselves) will return to their original condition as used to exist in the times of fche predecessors of both of us. As regards my reference made to His lajesty’s Govt, through your good-self, X have not received any reply up to the present moment. Such delay leads to a state of affairs which is not desirable, and, in :y opinion, might early res It in develop ento of an undesirable and disturbing nature. My f*ar is only due to :.y anxiety to conform with the wishes of His Majesty's Government, otherwise, as far as my own subjects are concerned, I can, God’s grace, k^ep them in control, and the wrong doer can be dsalt with. More especially am I anxious about tht Hajj question as the time has drawn very ear. If an answer is not receiv ed by the mi idle of the our ent month (Ghawwal), the Hajj willTranslation of a letter dated 12th Ramd -an 1338 (29th May 1920) l^om the Shaikh of Kovreit to ihn Jaud* m+mtim m mi.m+mim m You have heard of the evil (L&amp;&amp;X perpetrated hy Talsal ad-IXivraiah and the Ikhwan : how he attacked our son Dai,) with his servants and the neighbouring tribes, which v;ere r/ith him, and Icillod the r ea and aeiaed the pro party without justificatioix* T)iay rm&amp;v till ) attack on them while they ‘believed the aolves safe, as none cpuld possibly have foreseen such a thing, and wo *rero greatly surprised at it* ¥e have always considex*e&amp; that the Al- laud and Al- Subah were one house by religion (dinnn ym mdhliaban) family and honour* We were much astonished at this oo :urrence and oanxiot jbi«aglne who ooul^ hf?,v# incited faisal ad—Duwaish and the Ikhwan to perpetrate this disgraceful uot. Had we not been anxious to save the blood of Hus- li^s and protect innocent Muslim lives we would have taken eff-active action at the time* We kept p&amp;tle&amp;t however and exercised forethought as Duwaiah and his followers arc your subjects* In view of the brotherhood and the long union which has been between uo we c,re reporting the matter to you, as t ve feel conflflwst that it will dla-ploaue you even more tlum it aid ua If ones you toe* the real f&amp;ot of the cnae and are rot deceived hy untrue tnles, for aon of high position have attentive eara. Shat we hope from Tour Excellency ia that you will oxAer hiia tc returri the property and ntOte restitution for the Eer for the sake of the honour of the two houses and families. If he does not listen to your words and obey yohr you orders, we cannot excuse and will have to say 'Kashina Allah wa Niaml Wakll' (Wo depend on God who is the bestof helpers; l.e. a declaration of war) and the Lord will pardon us for the hlood of the Muslima of the both sides t and will hold him guilty who is the cause La Kaula wa la quww&amp;ta ilia Lillah ilAli il a&amp;hiia', We have deputed our raen AMullali As-Junait a■ d AMul Aziz A1 Hasan to visit you regarding this and they are authorised to reply to you a d we have confidence in God and you. We hope for the continuance of love (friendship) and union. Greetings to your father, 'brothers and sons. Our son Ahmad and his brothers send you their greetings.' • After aomullr:«nt3 I have received your letter of the 12th ultimo and have understood what you inti;aated therein* especial ly about the attack of Ad-Duwish* and about Daij and nis men. Also your remartcs about the two houses of As~3aud A A 3 *. 3 ubah being ever united* as also that you have left Ad-Duwish un-punished in order to avoid the blood shed of Muslins and that you expect payment of compensation &amp; would not excuse or forgive me if I failed to exact the penalty from the wrong doers. All these good rem&amp;xfes of yours are appreciated and I feel that I have an obligation towards you towards you a.«id you have every right to expect all this from me. Thank G-od* there is not one who can give me orders, and I am strong enough to enforce my orders with or without his (any body # s) consent. I* your brother*would,however, like to explain to Your Excellency certain matters. As to Ad Duwai 3 h f s attack : God knows that I did not order him to attack* nor did I wish it, especially th j thing that happened. Of course, I knew of their (the Mutair f s) gathering ( in qaraiyah), and their taking defensive measures. ¥hen God ordained the incident in question I was, however* not sorry for reasons I shall now explain. I did, as a matter of fact, despa tori messang era to stop them* but they had already taken action. As regards my own feelings towards Koweit* its Baler and people* I call God to witness that from the time I left Koweit till this moment, I have always meant well by them This is known to God as well as to man. As to the rela tions of As-3aud and As— h* I can only repeat what * • • Translation of a letter dated 4th Shaw al 1338 (21 st June 1920) from Bin 8aud to Shaikh Salim As Subah has( 2 ) has haan said (COUPLET) *If affairs ara taken in hand in the first place hy wisemen.they have only good results: if they are in the hands of the wicked,then evil conse quences ara brought on all concerned'. Oh son of Mubarak, I should never have believed or dream ed that any friction would have taken place between the As-Baud and the As-Subah, I cannot now fathom the causes You,however, should ask yourself what they are, in order that yju may under tand them clearly, or you should ask those of your class who know the causes well. As to your remarks that you left Ad^Duwaiah alone for my sake, I may say that this is what could be expected of you, I trust the time may never com© for our forces to measure strength with each other. Also, may Ckxi keap you safe, you are well aware that if things are Qoncialed and facts are not stated , then ill % •feeling is surely caused, ( The above is sarcastic vein in original Arabic) It is now necessary t at both sides should disclose facts. As regards myself, God knows that I had no knowledge of or connexion with this affair, which God has ordained, nor, as far as I am concerned, did I know of any outward or inward reason to cause same. On the other hand, since you became Huler of Koweit, God knows not a month has passed but I have experienced, worry at your hands, although I gave no cause for niwh a thing. Many were the reports, public property, that reached me but which I tried not to believe, while I may say that others of a more obscure nature I positively refused to entertained. God knows how many these have been. However, certain definite events that have taken place from ’BajaV onwards number five. Such could not have beon brought about except by either a foolish man, or one determined on mischief. Of course, you are not a foolish man, but possess great wisdom (1) You despatched a mounted force to the people of Qaraiyah, without sending me a warning beforehand. (2) Kafiai came to ia« with a varhal masaag* from you YouYou You did not deign even to write a few lines. (3) You sent a party of the ♦lutair* and ’AJimn* (probably meaning settlers of these tribes in Koweit, who acted on behalf of 3alim) who molested the inhabitants of Qaraiyah. Yet you did not inform me in writing or by massenger. (4) You issued a •prohibition order* in Koweit stopping all exports to Bin Baud’s ( ay) ports. (5) You seem to have forgotten that the xutair were my subjects. Kindly inform me. May God save you ( Allah Yusal- liimk)on these five points. What would have happened to those people who were put to serious trouble, if they had had none to protect them; but they have both a protector and a ruler, and he is your brother ( myself). In this you did not treat them with a good policy; you said also that your action was in accordance with religion. You could not, if you think thus, know the good from the bad. Buch methods as yours canSooly result In trouble, y subjects • • suffered in three wO- They were put to (1) personal worry (2) uneasiness (3) They were brought to that state of mind and doubt which ended in inflaming their religious fanaticism to such an extent as to make them ready to turn on any one who provoked or interfered with them* I was myself extremely surprised to hear of this state of affairs and at first was in doubt as to the causes that led to them. Any one, naturally, v/ould wonder what was at the back of these h&amp;Pbenings \ (hrhat are the r^al facts). Of a sudden (my irritate4)P«0Pl« found *BaiJ • marching out against them, he even reached HADTH, and as this action came on top of the many upsetting happenings (above men tioned) they (naturally) believed that DaiJ had come out to attack them. Then followed what God had ordained as He hath said in the Holy Quran (Quotation) 'You cannot form a plan or execute your intention unless God Hinself wills it to be do-ne'.fou will, of course, understand that your unfriandly actions had pone on previously for a long tine, and every one, great and snail, had felt the effect, and they could only he Imputed to the covetousness of the doer In the absence of any conciliatory actions. This la the whole reason why the harmful Incident too’: place and you sufferred a loan. I see no way of bettering mattera than f r you to sign the aoconpanylng dooment as a final settlement. If you have anything to bring forward which I donot Imow of f I rshall be glad to consider It. I may add that aa you have vorbally coramimioatod through A1 Kaflril that tha Qaraiyah ^LUaation be stub nil t ted to the British Govern out # I aay # by all Maana f let it be eo* I shall know how to plead my oausa. X wish to aaoure you tnat all I have staid in the beginning of thin letter is oorre#t and truo # and I ji fully confident tijat in future we ;hall have no trouble with each other, and everything will be aatlafhctorl- ly arranged. N\ tur friends Abdullah As Bur^xit. ai.u Abdul Asil^ bin uasan heve delivered your mes tage to me and I have explained to them all that was necessary* You isay rest assured that I am quite willing to meet your ^3hes in every way, bo may It please God. As regards restitutio' of cavnels and horses —tr^.aTiodfi-yy X have sent out men to go round and collect them. As soon as the points the points at variance are settled, every thing will bo available, both what belongs to you and out of our own property. I am sending with our friends (your deputation) ny uncle T sn8ir bin Saud in the hope of gaining your good will as I am anxious to come to an agreement, fay God put tilings right between us both and prosper Muslims, help His faith and make it glorious. U :• : •• - -A&amp; i'ranalation of thw supplimant to Bin Baud's ITstter dated 4th dhawwal 1338 (21at June,1920) to Shaikh Salim As- Bubah, Huler of koweit. After compliments lou know that the affairs of this world depend upon two things, the first and highest being ahariyah, the second being perseverenoe and forethought, as the poet says:- 'The most careful man is he who does not do anything until he hae fully looked into the consequences of the intended action'• kou, of course, realize that these unfortunate matters which have recently happened and the consequent disputes and struggles about boundaries and subjects have not been started by me at all* lou alone have been the cause though I hope now they are as good as settled and our minds are at peace* Let every one remain within his own boundaries, I say* I would, however, like first to explain to you all I have in mind, and you are best awar&lt; of what you have in your own mind* I donot know if you have different ideas on the subject* ¥ou know that from the day God created As-Saud and As- Bubah, never have they said,'This is our boundary, these are our subjects*• The Ae-Subah confined themselves to loweit while the As-Saud looked after their own affairs,neither party having any doubt or difficulty* In the past when misfortune came upon Kejd it was split up into two parts, one going to the Turks and partly Ajman domination (iiassa) and the other under Bin Rashid* In thosi days any one who found himself pressed upon too hardly or tyriniz* ed over by any of these three took refuge in koweit, because it was all one'Tarifah'(class)• Things went on in this way till Muhammad bin Bubah died. After Mubarak had succeeded to the principality of koweit I was at loweit. He used to give 'Zakah' (pecuniary heip)to those of Morthern and Southern Arabs who used to come down to him* They used to take refuge alternately with him, with Bin Rashid and Turks* When I occupied Hassa your father was still paying ^600/- to the Turks in place of the | V ^% Zakat' of Al-Awazim* lour father used to take the Zakat from the ttutair*3ubia and others, who used to come down to him and we did not object owing to cloae friendship existing between ua« flot long before the death of your father the 'Mutautuhoh' and the w Haahaidah' waited on me and I took Zakat from them. Had things gone on smoothly neither you nor 1 would have said even once in our lives “This is my boundary, and these are my subjects** iou have yourself opened this question and have shown avarice against us your friends, coveting our tribsemon and boundaries, it is you who aay*thia is my possession' I myself have no such ambition against you. X now ask, “Gan you show me ar any right or Justification for your amoitious claims, which are dir jc ted against us, your own kith and kin* Had you had any Sharii (legal) Justification, X should have submitted atonce* Or, if any part of the country had been taken by sword, then the deci sion of sword is inevitably obeyed. Hut if it is, as it surely is, a question of “Amanah' and j^dMwUh' ( a trust and voluntary gift), then it rests with him who gives it,i.e. my-self, to take it back or to leave it ( in the hands of the trustee or the receiver of the gift). 1 now say that if you have any proof or argument you may bring it forward and X shall oe the first to accept and respect the same and will not disregard it in the least. Hut if you have none, than I would beg you not to seek one vainly, firstly in order that you may akoid wrong-doing, and secondly for the sake of our friendship and alliance which you should value. If you have proof of your contention then take it (the disputed land) by all means, otherwise donot try to Jump on things that are not yours and thereby oreat hostilities and estrangements, kou, of course, know that you have to leave all your possessions ( on death). There ia no doubt about this* if we go to a court or arbitration I am sure to win my case as I have best proofs in support of my claims. If otherwise, then 1am not going to accept or agree as that woul&lt;l be injustice which i ie not liked by God or any wise man of any nationality. low, Salim, my brother, on my honour I beg of God and of you to settle up these matters and to give up these contentions which donot promise any immediate or future good to you. I call God ta witness that I am not seeking any personal gain. I know too well that if I fought for wrong 1 shall oertinly be the loser, and if I am driven to fight fqr my rights then by the grace of God I am sure to win. God knows I have no aim against the honour of loweit and its Kuler and people and I wish you all safety. If you agree to what is just and sign this doourte nt which is enclosed herein, I shall be indebted to you and shall try and win your good will in every respect. And I, on my part eolemnly pledge myself to you tiut I shall maintain the same good relations with you as I had with your fat her and brother, and we will jointly work for common good in all matters. If you refuse to seal this document. If you refuse to seal thi3 document and agreement then I am absolved from responsibility. Make peace, I do the same. Wrong me and encroach upon my rights, then I defend myself. May God help us both for good. UoUAL MulHGTHIS TH* HSTTLa M^MT I B4G UF 10UH iLXO:r.L^IOY IS From Salim etc. -ato. To Abdul Aziz etc, etc* After compliments As regards the recent regrettable incidents, they were ordained by God against the will of both of us. They donot alienate us from each other; but on the other hand we are as (good friends) our forefathers were to one another. As regards as our respective bounaaries and subject tribes,these are known to me and I have no right or intention of encroaching on any of them. These are, according to old rules and to be treated and considered as 'Mayanah'(common to both by consent. In accordance with the above (as token thereof) I have written this document with a view to securing a friendly settlement and to set ycur mind at rest, because it is a 'Mayanah' ( common property or interests) and there is no (intention) of ooveting(your proper ty or possession). God is the witness to what I state, may peace and blessings of God be upon Muhammad, his descendants and com panions •mmam Telegram (P.) From ‘Giveom, Baghdad. To Political, Kuwait. No. 8266. Dated^9th. (Received ICth.) July 1920 , Reference telegram ITo. 48 G of 5th# July from Political, Kuwait, and connected papers. Please write a reply to Ion Band’s letter - \ of 20th. Pay, to the effect that I have also heard from Shaikh - ' • Salim on the-suojpct. Re ind him that under Clause VI of his Treaty he is Under an obligation to us that he will not have recourse to other than friendly leans for the settlement .of disputes of this nature, and that should it be necessary he can always.apply* for our good offices in the matter# Addressed Bahrain,- Repeated Kuwait and Bushire# jiu? /rt&gt; y2 /cfll ho9 ; lele^ran (5.) Fron Giveon, Baghdad. To Political, Kuwait. Ho* 7265 - Dated i»th. (Received 10th.). July 1920 . Refer^co your telegran Ho 50 G of July 5th &amp; connected papers. ..1. ITou should point out to Shaikh Salim that the Anglo-*Turkish Convention of Ip 15 v;as not a do on lent to which he was activ ;ly party, and that, in any case 'it was drawn up under very different circunstances at the tine when the Turks were in Hasa* (Corrupt proup) opinion is that its proviislons have been superceded so far as he is concerned by Clause VI of our /i^rcement of '26th, December 1 &gt;*‘O with Ibn Sa*ud. According to this clause the limits of Kuwait territor./ still remain to be determined. * 2’. Lay advice to the Shailda is reply,politely refusing to sipn the document, invoking the friendly^ arbitration of the British Government, and aproeinp not to take any further action regarding Jariyah pending such negotiation (Although you need hot toll him • this, the result of the, negotiation will, in ny opinion, likely restrict his territory to a smaller area than that given by the .Aigdo-Turkisn Convention). g. On the receipt of : u . luest from the Shaikh of Kuwait for our good offices in the latter, I an prepared, with the previous J sanction of hi. n. Goy era lent, to address Ibn 3a 1 ud on the Subject, i . - . - - 'and if possible'arrange a settlement of the affair at a meeting of the principals or their plenipot entiarios. I have already vfarhod nan, Vide iy i .aoliately following telegram. Addressed Kuwait, Repeated Bushirc and BadiraiA. A J j'A /erhk oTelegram (?.) From Political, Kuwait. To Giveon, Ba^idad, Pc?u. Political Bushire Political Bahrain. Ho. 54 G. Dated 10th July If 20 . ' . Bcforeiacc your No 82o5 of ;th July. Shaikh io unwilling to leave things alone at Jariyah, as Ibn Sa*ud makes the acceptance of his torus a condition of return of balance' of loot, and lie#is loath to leave his 'halal' in his hands pending negotiations. He will., persist in regarding the frontier of the Anglo-Turkish Convention as permanent. He talks of going to war with Ibn 3a*ud. I have tried to make hiu see reas 6 n, but all I could get fro i him was a promise to thiifc the natter over and take no rash measures without informing us.TRAHaLATlQH, 2^ °3&gt; Political Agency, Kuwait, ICth. July 19^0. To H.E. Sliaildi Sali:a al-^ulDaralc ac-Subah, Ruler of' Kuwait. After 1 complements. As I infor led your Excellency verbally, The livil Jo .lissiou r tcl^s rae in his telejrau as follows:.- . 1. I aa to remind Y.S. that the .inrslo-Turkish Convention vfas not a document to which Ton Subah v.as an activ party, .if., i drawn up under very different circumstances from the present,when 3a*ud&gt; Rated the g loth. 3afar 133^. 2. His advice to Y.S. is to reply to Ibn 3a‘ud, politely re fusing to sign the paper, invoking the friendly arbitration ox thi British Government, and agreeing not to take any further \ action regarding Jariyah pending such arbitration. 3 . On receipt of a request from Y.2. for our good offices in the matter, he is prepared to address ibn 3a*ud on the subject, between Y.2, and Ibn Sa'ud or your plenipotentiaries. '• .Telegram (P.) Prom Political, Kuwait. To Oivcom, Baghdad, Rcpd. Political, Bushire &amp; Bahrain. No. 5 b C. Dated 13th July Reference my telegram No. 54- 0. Precis of letter from Shaikh dated 12 th inst, which I am sending you by post, begins:- I do not under stand how Anglo-Turkish Convention was superseded but feel confiden' British Government will not allow mi rights to be betrayed. I am extremely grateful for the advice and for the offer of arbitra tion, but I feel that Dawish's action is one that I cannot in honour overlook if Ibn Sa’ud does not order him to make restitution. I have* accordingly v/ritten to lim Sa'ud again and sent envoys with Nasir and will no doubt receive a definite reply. If he does not now order restitution to bo made I shall ask for good offices of Govt. I have refused to sign the paper.Political Acanoy, Kuwait. IV th. Sul? I - To th« Oivil Ooniiaoione®?, BAGHDAD. Ref or sixoo rjy tolofran Ho. 3^ C, clatod tlio 13th July 1920 I anolooe horowith dhalkti Salim 1 a latter of the 12t5i inat in oriGinal, together with a translation. It is in reply to a letter of mine, Ho. pno of the ! th. Inst., In i^iioh I aabodied the rsain referflnoe to your opinion tJiat tlie probable result of nesotiationfl would be that lUa territoiy eeulcl be reetrioted to a aaoller area tJian th t Given by t]xe AnGlo-Tur!d.oh Convention. 1 had a long Interview witlx hin on the i , .\nd care* fully explained the variouo :x&gt;into to him in detail. He ms ^eatOy distreooed over tli© AnGlo*Turkiah Convention, .ind kept repeating over and over again ttat Captain Moflollun }iad shown loin thia frontier on a aap and told him definitely that it was his for all tine. He talked wildly of going to war with Ibn Oa'ud if he would not order Fhiaal ad-Dawiah to nalce restitution, aa, he aoid, he could not in honour leave his ’U-Oal” in hie hands. He said he felt atroixg enough to beat Ibn 3a*ud, and opened his oliirt and allowed ne a wound on iila cheat - prosuaably to ia ress uixin n© that he not frightened of war. As lie was cjuite inoapable of uadmm%m^ reason at the tine, I left hin to think over ; :y letter, whioh he liikl not as yet seen. X saw him again on the 12th. m tixe date on ^hiah he wrote, the letter and he wan than oonalderaWy oalMr and l«ea thlrotliy. fox’ WTX'. He still 2:** harplas on the Anslo-TurXlah CotwanUon, ' points of your telegrao Ho. 7265 , but, of oourae, onitting alla a the p^er, * i that he too was naoot anxloua to return to the old tftate of frlendahlp, nerely ursine; hie to order restitution to he aade for the Jariyah affair, ^ritiiout naJtlns ^-ny reference to a frontier het^reen then* fron hie letter, wao that he thought that, ao ire had repudiated tlie and tliat hio heat ;x&gt;lioy ^aa to try and patch up the quarrel with Ito Ja’ud over the reotiti:tion question, preferring to leave the frontier undecided than to have it decided against hlsu &amp;(% ud will now he acre 'ursious to cone to tons and ; lore lihoiy to ortler taie return of the 'haloT’, because of the reported defeat of hia forces ly Ihn Rashid at Ohd^hah in the ;ii^Ue of June, ahioh, t^eUie^ %me or not is believed here* This hope suqr tare been stresigtlim^ hy a vague rumour of anot^x^* recent defeat near Buraid h, iSxiali I entirely discredit* 'Iho Olr JJdi has issued an order, find had it proolained ty 'dallal , that no one in Kumit is to aention t2xe nane of Ibn aa f ud at all* Uia object is said to be ttat he wlalxea to avoid all chance of n Jours roa^xhing Iba ears that people here are spacing ■'' ' : ::v •• ^ tmtm laiiMi Mi inMI mt flMM took place* but* of course, do not teiov w!iat advice they gave, or to What av.tmt, 1? any, Shaikh SoUa InfluwwM ^ ^ a^io,. Tim .ThaUsfc has not aanUonoa the aubjeot to rae ninoe the The la.iresolon vvSiioh J calnaCL fron thio Interview, aa I think there ia little doubt tiiat he hopes that Ibn Ahn.id bin .T; bir, neltlier of rtwra had been Inside his house for Ian; tine, and that the fomer oimOj aoouaed hln of always t.,v,.-t n c ths adrloe of hla oarvanta and never oonaultins tiie otiier nadbera of tiie A1 'ubah. I understand that a s«neral faaily PeoonoiUation- 3 - Tule&gt; ram* Jlforti* P.A Bahrein. To - Civil Cozaaiooionor, Baghdad. No. 1746. Dated, let. and reed. 2-7-1920. Bln Gaud v/riting under date of June 23rd states that he has received Koweit deputation and has returned them (to) with conciliatory letters hy hand of NAGIK of Bin Baud, copies of w loh he forwards. He complains of great delay on part of Hie LSaJesty 1 s Government in nswer. to his recent letters particularly regard to HAJ j urges iraportance of receiving reply to hie proposals imoediately to avoid serious development s) given latest date for TTNJI Pilgrimage to start as July 18th. Requests imedlate tele* •ruphic reference. Translation of letter posted. Telegrai. P, Prom - C ivil Coiwaisoioper, Baghdad. To - ', of 8. India Office, London. No. 8060. Dated. 5-7-1920. Following telegram from Bahrain dated July 1st crossed your telegr m of July 2nd. 5173 beginss Bin S&amp;ud x x x x x x x x X X X X X X X ends. posted.Translation of a letter, dated 14th. July 1 2 2C # ' iTon t ' hc 31xc;ildi of Kuwait to ITm Sa'ud, ^ | After oonplenioits. I have rcoeived your letter dated the 2tot. June \;&gt;2o t and its Bupplen«nt ; froa Ilaair aa-da’ud, and liave understood ^hat you nean. ReGardinG Dawiah’s attaok, you say tiiat you had not wished it to happen, hut that iBhen it did happen you were not sorry for certain reasons hidden in your heart which you explain in your letter and its supplement. I do not see any reason for hrin£inG in all these events and writing this long explanationj if I an to give reasons and you are to do the same, the explanation will 1 become long and protracted* That happened in the past between us is not hidden, but every tiling is cleaj?* There was no senoe of obligation between us, as we were formerly as it were one body, and, please God, are now* I never mentioned the question of boundaries and subjects in ny letter tfhioh I sent you at the hand of ’Abdullah as-Sunait and ’Abdul 'Asia al-Hasan as this is perfectly clear; my subjects are well known, and ny frontier was fixed by the two Governments, and X hold papers to prove it. I informed you through ny envoys regarding the disgraceful deed which Dawiah and his followers had done, and requested you that the 'halal' should be returned and restitution made for the men who had been unjustly killed, as I felt sure that, in view of our friendship and union, a deed like this woulS displease you even more than it did me, and I am sorry to see tliat you oppose what I ask by putting forward these excuses and false tales. I an sure that the reason you resist the Just claim which I have against you for what Dawish has done is that you have been listening to the lies of envious people who have been trying to cause ill will betwem us. You say that if I do not accept your terms and sign the paper, I must excuse you from making resti tution. tty brother, I am surprised at your saying this, and can hardly believe it, as it is Just what would please our enemies. The question of our subjects and boundaries is understood, and please God, I shall do nothing to harm or displease you, butdisplease you but shall ^uurd our friendship and union# But I have strong reasons to put forward regarding ulxat Dawish nnd his followers have done, and I have done wlmt was right towards you, tuid rqy condition towai*d 3 you iS known, so there is no need for long explanations over such an unworthy ev«sit; as the proverb says 'it is bad to think over the pi^st 1 ’. Regarding the signing of the paper? I mist ask you to think the natter over carefully, and I an sure you wilj- see the right ana benefit of remining as we were in the past# I trust you will abandon the things whioh annoy ne and please our eneniea, end, please God, you will only see a good result which will please you# With reference to Dawish, as I told wou before, I can not take action against hin without letting you know, as he is of no importance, though, by the grace of God, I could in every way. I have receive^ the caaels, riding camel and horse, which you sent with the envoys, and I trust that you will now order the return of the rest of the property# I hope you will not make any objection to this, as it is a thing for which I can not-hold you excused# I am sending you Mubarak bin Half and Hilal with Nasir# Usual ending*io3 TrrJislation of a letter, dated the 17th, July lo-C, from the Shaikh of Kuwait to the Amir ‘Abdullah al- fut*ab ar-Rashid# After oomplem'aita. I have received your letter at the hands of your man ‘Abdullah and his friends, and was much pleased to read what you say about your love and friendship, for which I am very grateful, and I thoroughly appreciate your true and sincere friendship# You say that certain people have envied the friendship which exists between us, and have tried to stir up ill will and spoil our relations, and that the most violent of these is Ibn Sa^dj that he made it one of the conditions of the terms of peace which he offered you that you would break off relations with the Sharif Kusain and with me# You say that when you understood his purpose arid refused, he started attacking your subjects, and that you have, accordingly, sent your men to let me know your true friendship* I most sincerely thank you, and, by the grace of God, the bounds of our true friendship will increase and continue, and, please God, the wish of the envious will not be gratified.% brother, if such be the conduct of Ibn Sa^ud, then may God defend the right# I am well, thanks be to God, and I pray God to give us both prosperity and peace, and that the end % of both of us may be good. By his gracious kindness God will • confound every foe# I am sending you my nan, and your nan, Abdullah, will, no doubt, tell you about everything* I am writing this friendly letter to confirm our friendship, and to offer you my thanks# Usual ending#t JON FID .Nri/U, . NO .^3 -0. t^olitioal Agency* Bahrain# Dated the 25th July*1920• TO The civil Ocuoaiaaicnsr* BAGHDAD. MisJtOitANDuM . Subject* * INTJDDKibflJ^ G^Nii.AA D» Jhaikh Abdullah* G.i.iii.* the youngest son of Dhaikh Isa of Bahrain, has given ne the following inform ation, which 1 send for what it is worth. The report has also been confirm®! by three well to do travellers from Kuweit and is to the effect that Shaikh Salem of Kowait has been making secret advanooa to the Shaikh of jlnhanunerah* Syed Taleb of Susrah and Bin Raschid, with a view to obtaining their support against Sin Baud. 3yed Taleb and Shaikh of Mohammerah have promised their support, and as an earnest have sent respectively ten horses and seventy horses (mares and horses) as presents to dhaikh Salem. The nature of the support promised is not stated. Shaikh Salem has also invited Dhari bin Twala to come into Koweit territory and camp in company with Ali bin Khalifuh, nephew of Shaikh Salem, at iehara as a precaution ary measure, uhari bin 'rwala has agreed to do this. Shaikh Abdullah further states that there are indications that the Shara&amp;f of ^ecca. Bin Raschid and Shaikh Salem of Koweit are in communication with one another the general intention being to check Bin Baud 1 ® increasing power, the imrediate object to prevent him going to iaecca by threats of war and invasion. The above stories appear to be not much more than gossip,but, perhaps, are worth report- ing. ^0,1.... Political agent* Bahrain. Gopy forwarded to D.P.R.* Bushire. political Ag^nt,Koweit. 21/?/2QDated 12tii (Reed. 13tii) August I 920 * Rave received a long, angry letter froa Ibn Sa'ud, dated 28th truly, aclmowledging the message sent in your telegram ho. bob of luth July, he says that in the past he has invariably tried to do the right tiling by H. m. G-ovt., in witness whereof he mentions his letter Of 24th Sha'ban. He accuses the Shailch of Kuwait of having given the P.A # an entirely wrong version Of his letter of 4th Shauwal (21st June), or, if he produced the original at ail, he. is emphatic that it was -altered. He asks that the original may be called for and. compared with the true copy which he sent through Bahrain, he says his ehvoy, nasir, uas returned, and he is indignant at the latters treatment by Shaikh Salim, whom he accuses of p having instigated the people of Kuwait to public - ly insult him - to insult his envoy was equivalent to insulting him. Nasir was kept practically a prisoner, and was prevented from paying an official call on the r.A., which was also an insult. Salim in his reply brought oy Hasir, a copy of which he encloses, refuses the olive branch, so he, Ibn Sa r ud, has severed relations with him. if h.jd.G. consider her interests are affected, let her fix a frontier between Kajd and Kuwait. If, on the other hand, she do not wish to interiere, let her say so. he will welcome .... sword as arbiter, ne asks for an answer one way or the other at once. He would personally liKe to settle the case as he is anxious to prove his friend ship to H.iu.G. He begs that he be not again asked to try and settle the matter direct with Salim, as he is an irresponsible individual overcome with arrogance, as H.M.Gr. must surely nave realised by now. Letter follows bt post. 1 • % Registered Wo. 113. Telegram (P.) itrom Political, Kuwait. To Givcom, Baghdad, Repeated to Pol.,Bahrain &amp; Pol*, Bushire. Wo. 74-C. Dated 13th August I 920 . Reference telegram No. 23b-C from Political, Bahrain. Copy of Ibn oa ud s letter already sent to Baghdad, under cover of my Wo. 51-C of-3th July, which may be compared with Bahrain copy. --- Statement that Wasir was prevented from calling on me is untrue; Salim himself accompanied him and, introduced him to me. Snaikh Salim returned to Kuwait on Wednesday, and, as he v will orobaoly nave discussed the question of. arbitration with the Shaikh of Luham- &lt;aarah, he may be more reasonable. Shall I raise the question agaln?-- / 1Telegram (p.) ' * r \ Prom Political, Kuwait. To Oivcom, Baghdad, depd, Pol # , Buahire Pol., Bahrain. No. 75-0. Bated 14th August I 92 O. The Shaikh has just sent Abdul Latif to tell me that he has this morning received Ibn Sard’s reply to his letter of 12th July, and , . \ * - - - that it just falls short of being a declaration of war. Ibn Sa'ud accused him to his envoy of having sent his own people to impersonate Ibn Rashid*s messengers, referred to in my telegram lio. 49-0 of 5tii July, but, on being appealed to, Nasir acknowledged that they were genuine. Two employes of P.A., Bahrain, were present at the interview, There was -a small raid on 12th August near Subaxhiyah,wiiich ’was at the time considered unimportant, but is now attributed to Ibn Sa'ud's instigation. Abdul hat if says that the Shaikh is now considering his next move, and that he (Abdul iatif) purposes urging him to ask for the good offices of His majesty*s Government at once. He thinks that he will do so now, arid is of opinion that the only thing that might deter him from doing so would be the fear that his action might be attributed by public opinion to fear of Ibn Sa*ud.Telegram (P.) From,Political, Kuwait* To Civcom, Baghdad, Repd. to Pol.,Bushire a Pol.,Bahrain ho* y 6 -c. Dated 15th August I 920 . Reference my telegram ho. 75-0* The Shaikh has just been to see me and has asked for the good offices of .uis a^ajesty’s Government to settle his dispute with Ibn Sa'ud, ne started by saying that, although Ibn Sard’s letter was not an official declaration of war, he did declare war verbally to his envoys in the presence of representatives of the Political Agent of Bahrain, and that he has already started instigating raids. I told him the expurgated gist of Bahrain telegram No. 236 -G, as I ment that he will accbpt our ruling wnatever frontier we allot. I would suggest that both parties be warned by you to restrain their tribes from ail acts of aggression-pending negotiations. had previously done to ’Abdul hatif, and he said that as Ibn Sa’ud says he would prefer that his majesty's Government should settle the case, he (Balim) desires this still more, ne volunteered the state/o') \ Telegram (P.) J’roiii Political, Kuwait. To Give ora, Baghdad, Repd. Pol., Bushire &amp; Pol., Bahrain. ho. 77-C. Dated 16th August Reference telegram Ho. ^43*“G from roliticai, Balirain. A section of the Ajman axso some* of ^he non-Ikhwan kutair have come over and are 4 encamped near Suhaihiyah* nere oneir action is, of course, descrioed as spontaneous, nothing is known here of the raid. Doubtless both sides will now attribute any tribal,raid to the work * of their rival. * !V3l # ♦ &gt; » it \ Telegram Code, From Political , Bahrein. To Political, Kuv/ait. No.260/C. Dated 17th (Reed.18th) August. 1920. . Koweit No. 74/C Binsaud actually said in his letter that Nasir was presented (prevented ?) from paying his respects to you for some days was finally only allowed see you in com pany with Shaikh of. Koweit fullstop Regret my telegram did not make this clear addressed Koweit repeated Baghdad. Political. \</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x00002e_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/5/99</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x00002e</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/5/99</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 5/C Boundary questions: attacks on Ikhwan; dispute between Shaikh Salim and Ibn Sa`ud'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1919/1920</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-11-01T16:02:39</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (114 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the volume.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the last folio with 115; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 5-114; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.A previous foliation sequence, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The volume comprises telegrams, despatches, correspondence, memoranda, and notes from February 1919 to August 1920, mainly relating to boundary questions between Ibn Sa'ud and the Ruler of Kuwait, Shaikh Salim [Shaikh Sālim al-Mubārak Āl Ṣabāḥ], as well as attacks on the Ikhwan and British relations with Ibn Sa'ud.The volume includes an index (folio 115) to topics and people discussed in the file. The principal correspondents in the volume include: the Political Agent, Kuwait (James Carmichael More); the Political Agent, Bahrain (Harold Richard Patrick Dickson); Ibn Sa'ud; the Ruler of Kuwait; and the Civil Commissioner, Baghdad.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Emir of Najd and Hasa</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Desert warfare</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Emir of Kuwait</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Agent and Consul, Muscat</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Iraq</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Baghdad</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Slavery</topic></subject><subject><topic>Colonial administration</topic></subject><subject><topic>Treaties</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x00002e#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>