<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0002d4_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-11-20T12:45:17.236Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">II /a- No.‘3^5’ -81/H* The Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident to the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Political Agent Muscat. and is directed to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents, for information. British Residency and Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated.. M'th March, •PtT 1939 . Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Memorandum from the Director Jiwani Air Station of Civil Aviation in India, No.036-121, dated the 13th February, 1939. (Received with jixternal Affairb Department endorsement No. D. 1058-F/39 , dated the 18th Fe brua ry , 1939.)(k) Copy of memorandum No. 036-121 dated the 13th February 1939, from the Director of Civil Aviation in India, to the Superintending Engineer, Aviation Circle, Central Public Works Department, New Delhi, etc. Jiwani Air Station. Difficulties have arisen in connection with shipments intended for Imperial Airways, Jiwani, or ing to consignment^ being despatched via Ghuk-dur* where they have been held igc up by the Muscat Customs authorities. It is requested that all concerned with shipments to Jiwani will kindly see that they go direct and not via Cwadur. Arrangements have been made with the British Indian Shipping Company to call at Jiwani when the cargo justifies their doing so.6 Telegram - GTC From - Political, Muscat# To - Britagent, Gwadur# No# - 68 t.h&lt;» i P.t.h .TarmtaTV 1940 Please telegraph (1) number ©f (a) Imperial Airways (b) K.JL.M# (c) Air France and (d) Other nationali ties* aeroplanes which landed in Gwadur during the year 1939 aixl (2) names of important persons who passed through Gwadur during this period.INDIA OF'“ICE RtCOnJS MICROFILM</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0002d4_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/6/76</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0002d4</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/6/76</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 2/1 British Consulate Muscat 5201 AVIATION Landing Ground at Gwadur'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1936/1940</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-07-31T22:02:10</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (4 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 6; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains correspondence related to the use of the landing ground at Gwadur (Gwadar).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><geographic>Gwadur</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Civil aviation</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0002d4#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>