<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x00025a_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-13T21:12:43.357Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Translation of letter No.231 aatea the 24th July 1935 from the Residency Agent, Sharjah, to the Political Agent, Bahrain. After Compliments. I beg to enclose a copy of a letter sent to me by Shaikh Said bin Maktum, Ruler of Bibai regarding his discussion with the Bibai Agent ol the Mesopotamia Persia Corporation ana demanding from him expenses incurred on 2000 bags of cement landed by the Japanese steamer Nanku Maru on 8th Rabi Awwal 1353 equivalent to 21st June 1934. 1 also enclose a statement of the expenses for your information, 'ihe original letter ana the statement oi expenses have been forwarded to the Secretary to tne honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gull, Bushire. Usual Ending.Translation of copy of letter dated the 5th Rabi TRani 1354 (6th July 1935; from Shaikh Saia bin Maktum,O.B.E., Ruler of Libai, to tne Resiuency Agent, Snarjah. After Compliments. I beg to in inform you that I aauressed the Agent reagrding the expenses incurred in connection with 2000 bags of cement which arrived by tne Japanese steamer on 3th Raoi Awwal 1353 (21st June 1934). Upto this date the total expenses have come to ks. 12845/-. I am sending to you the enclosed copy and request that you will finely look into the matter. As you know every one wants his o&gt;m•gr j . ^original on file ^o-^/lO)* % extract from letter wo.241 dated the 28th u^ly 1936 from the nesiflency agent, oharjah, to the r 0 litical ^gent, Bahrain. 3. ihen the ohaikh disclosed to the senior x^aval ufficer in the,rersian uulf his claims against the Mesopotamia rersia corporation limited and »»ali ^zaffar bin oulaiman, wali of ^hassab on behalf of the oultan of iviuscat. xhe D e nior naval ufficer told him to report the matter to the nesidency agent, uharjah, who will refer the two cases to you, and that he (the o e nior naval officer; will inform the honourable the Political nesident of these.j-'.O • IC 62 14/167 HI. To —wr» ^urust /f , 1935. ji W ■ ?! I{ (^, / M' Jti The Politioal Agent, Bahrain . rt.\ Memorandum . fe5&gt; reference letter No. 226 datea the 24th July 1935 from the Residency Agent, Bharjah, on the subject of the claim of the Shaikh of Debai against the Mesopotamia Iran Corporation, Limited, for lis. 12,345/- being charges due on 2000 bags of cement landed at Lebai by a Japanese Steamer on the 21st June 1934. 2. I lease report, for the information of the non'ble the Political Resident, what the present position is .NO.269-B/10. Political Agency, Bahrain, the 20th Augsist 1^25 To, The Secretary to the Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, BUSHIEE. ^ \\ / MEMORANDUM. Reference your memorandum No.14/ib7 TIT dntea the 15th August 1935. 2. • The original complaint was sent to you ana only a copy to me. 3. The Agent of the Mesopotamia Iran Corporation Limitea, at Dibai, is under the orders of the Company’s Agent at Bushire. I therefore suggest that you give him a copy of the Shaikh’s complaint for report. 4. I neea hardly point out that this complaint has only been made after compensation has been extracted from the Shaikh on account of looting of lighters belonging to the Mesopotamia Iran Corporation Limited, during May 1934. ’ Captain, Off:;. Political Agent, Bahrain.'V. Translation of letter IJo.294 nateu the ^Ist ^.ugust l^eh from the j ne^idency ^yent, Sharjah, to the Political ^gent Bahrain. ^fter Complimenti i heg to inform you that I am enclosing a letter aatiressed to you by Shailhi Sale bin i!antum,0.3.h., huler of mbai v/hich i hope will be receiver b v . you. I have forwarded its copy to the Secretary to the Honourable toe IV ITranslation of letter dated the 12th Jamad^AWwal 13o4 'i.e. 12th A u ust 1935) from Shai.di Saia cm :,Iaktum,C.Liii., :uler of Libai, to the Political ^gent, Bahrain. 9 \ a. t'M i-^°\ ^fter Compliments. I beg to state that I have so long been waiting for the pass (No Objection Certificate) for the rifles of my brother Jumah bin Maktum but did not receive any reply from you. My brother is constantly making irupuiiies. from me about the same. I, therefore, request, you to give the matter your due attention and send me the pass (No Objection Certificate) concerning the rifles ol my above-mentioned brother. 2. I beg to remind you about the amount due to me by the Company and the Agent and also the amount due to me by Wali Mudhaifar bin Sulaiman. I have previously sent you a letter on this subject but have not so far received any intimation from you with regard to the realisation of the amounts due by the aforesaid persons. I hope you will give your attention to this matter. 3. Further, I may mention that I have previously written to you about Hasan bin Muhammad, a prisoner at Muscat. Every week I get letters from his relatives enquiring from me about the matter. I request that you will kindly let me know how the matter stands. Usual ^nding.'Vc m Z K.-B/10. . The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to;— Thb Secretary to the Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, EUSHIRE- and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document (s). The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf. O' .V _ Dated 27th August 1935 / Reference to previous correspondence : Bahrain sieinoranaum No. 254/V .5 . dated 5th August 1935 ana memorandum No.269-B/10 dated 20th August 1935. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. 1. Copy of translation of lette dated the 12th Jamad Awwal r 1354 (12tnoAugust 1935J frorr the Ruler of Dibai, to the Political Agent, Banrain. Claims against the Mesopotamia Iran Corporation Limitea and against Wali Mudhaffar bin Sulaiman of Khasab.After Compliments, It is not concealed from you that I intend to leave(for Hasa)tomorrow morning. If you have any work and want me to come to you, I am ready to uo so toaav. For information. J On return irom Hasa, if God willing, I will come- — - • OFFICE NOTE. Claim of Dibai against Mespers Spoken to Mespers Agent, Bahrain. He informs me that the only possible person against whom the Shaikh of Dibai can have a claim is the consignee and that, in law, the shipowners, shippers, and agents are only carriers and cease to have any responsibility, even for landing charges, once the cargo has reached its destination. The Bahrain Customs have a rule whereby any unclaimed cargo is sold after six months, by auction, in order to cover landing and storage charges. This confirms the above statement, that the consignee is responsible for landing, wharfage and demurrage charges. 24th September 1935. A.P.A.Bahrain i *n /Mi 6/(o ,~ i N C O R PO RAT I N GI ST E PM E N LYNCH 8»C9 LYNCH BROTHERS, LIP GRAY, MACKENZIE &amp; C9 and GRAY, PAU L &amp; C9 Mesopotamia Persia Corporation, LIMITED. Tele graphic Address:- 'mespers'.’ Codes usedi- Bentley's Complete Phrase Code. Scott's Tenth Edition. The Standard Shipping Code. 5!! 1 Edition. N? GEN/61. DUBAI, aND SEPTEMBERX!? »5, Jenab Sheikh Sayid Bin Makthoom, 0. B. Ruler of Dubai. E. Dear Sir, 2000 Bags Cement Ex s.s. w Nankwa Maru n With reference to your conversation with the undersigned on the subject of the above consignment, we are now informed by ship-owners through their Agents - Messrs, Frank C.Strick &amp; Co. (Basrah Ltd., Basra,- Jphat the shippers have now definitely abandoned the cargo and no liability will be entertained either by the ship-owners or any party associated with them. Kindly note that we have a lien on the cargo to the extent of Bs.210/-/- being landing charges incurred by uM and we shall be glad if you will kindly arrange to remit us the amount when the cargo is finally disposed off by you. Your£ faithf For The Mesopotamia Persia Copy to:letter Nc . D.O. 84 dated tne 12th Septemoer 19*55 from the ttescpctamla Iran Corporatlcn, Ltd*, Busdire Secy Gcpy may oe sent tc P.A. Bahrain with reference tc his memo at page 94. Perhaps P. would like tc take tne file on tour and explain the situation verbally to the Shaikh as opportunity occurs. Please put up in Bahrain if Shaikh of Duoai is there. If not there, put up in Shargah. This file was taken on tour but nc action appei tc have been taken on it. D.O. Nc. 37 dated the 15th October 1935 from the Me sc pc taihl a Iran Co rporation Ltd., Bu shire&gt; nelevent papers may oe sent tc Bahrain. Cclcne: Loch will take up the case with Mespers Agent there, «J. ii • 3 • 19/10/35 Copy tc the Political .Agent Bahrain with reference tc his Memorandum Nc. 269-B/lO dated the 20th August 1935. S.3.A 22/9/35 u .s 25/9/35 A.R Secy May be resubmitted tc P.R S.R.A 17/10/35Copy cf a D. 0. letter Nc . DO/84 dated the 12 th September 1935 from the Mesopotamia Persia Corporation Limited, Bushire to the Secretary tz the Hon*ole the Political resident in the Persian Gulf. i refer to your letter No. fio/ 1753 cf the 31st ultimo, 1 am instructed by my Principals to tell you that the Shaikh cf Duoai has been advised that the main Agents cf tne steamer in Busreh instruct the cargo should be abandoned without any liability whatsoever to the steamer. The cargo therefore is now the property cf the Shaikh and he is at liberty to take any steps he considers necessary to recover his charges against the consignment.Copy cf a D.O. letter Nc. D.0./87 dated tne loth 0ctcheril935 frcm the liescpctamia iraa Ocrpcratlcn Ltd., Bushire to the Secretary to the ncn’ole the Pclitlcal resident In the Persian uulf, Bushire. in continuation of my D. O* letter of the 12th ultimo to you regarding a claim made hy the Shaikh cf Dubai on a shipment cf 2000 Dags cf Cement ex s.s. -Nankwa Maru' landed at tee pert cf IXibai, i have to advise you that the Shaikh cf DuDai has been notified by cur Dubai Agents that the shippers have definitely abandoned the shipment and nc liability will be entertained either oy the ship-cmers cr any party associated with them. The Shaikh i under stand has replied tc cur Agent at Duoai that he is unable tc do anything in this matter, as it has oeen referred tc the Pclitical Department, and that he still insists cn full demurrage and charges. i have oeen asked by the Agent cf the ship owners tc get in touch with the Pclitical Resident tc expedite settlement cf this matter and tc find cut cn what grounds the Shaikh is maintain ing his present attitude, i shall be glad if you would let me have seme news as seen as possible.No. £ 14-167 / V N V r &gt; .... ^ The Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Political ^gent, Bahrain, and is directed to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents. British Residency and Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated k •JanuaTy -1&amp;66 Reference to previous correspondence : Bahrain Letter No. J^-B-10 dated the 20th ^ugust 19S5. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Letter No.L.lu5«5 dated the 8th January 1936 from Messrs.The Mesopotami Iran Corporation, limited, Bushire, to the secretary to the Iolitico.l Resi dent in the i ersian Gulf. Claims against the Meso potamia Iran Corpora tion, Limited, and against the ovmers of the s.s.Nankwa Ma.ru.Copy of letter No*L, 1053 dated Bu.sh.i-re, 8th January 1936 from The Mesopotamia Iran Corporation, Limited, Bushire, to the Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. I refer to the claim made by the oheik of Dubai against the owners of the s.s. n Nankwa Maru' in respect of 2uOG bags Cement landed at L/ubai. In my Demi-Official letter of October 15th I asked that, as the Dheikh has been notified that shippers have abandoned the consignment and that no liability can entertained by the shipowners or any party associated with them, we should receive some advice from you in the matter. I am being pressed by my principals and shall be glad to hear from you as early as possible.Ne. 42-13/10 The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to ‘Ifre Honourable tho rolitierl Hecidont in the reroian Guir 9 ljuchiro. and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document j^). The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf. , DatedM Reference to previous correspondence : Hi shire printed letter No,101/14/107 dated the 14th January 1936. Description of Enclosure. 1 . Name and Date. Copy of letter no.SO-'v'lO dated the 2nd February 1936 to Khan Sahib Husain bin Hasan *Mnad, l n charge current duties of the Residency Agent, Sharjah. Subject. Clain of the R'aler of Dibai against the resopotamla rersia Coiporation Limitedtranslation of letter wo»91 dated the 10th reomary 1936 equivalent to the 16th uhul qa 1 dah 1354 from rJian bahib nusdin bin nasan *Amad, in charge current duties of the nesidency Agent,bharjah, to the political Agent,Bahrain* After compliments, .deference your letter dO*39-B/10 dated the 2nd rebruary 1936* 2* 1 made inquiries from Shaikh sa*id bin Maktum, u*B»Jii* , Buler of ijubai, regarding his claim in connection with the 2000 bags of cement, over which there is trouble between him and the Agent of the Mesopotamia rersia Corporation, and asked him whether the matter was settled or he still claimed the charges* ne replied that after he had sent copy of the account which he claimed on account of the Ardhiyah to the Honourable the political Resident in the Persian Culf, the Agent of the Mesopotamia Persian corporation told him that they(company) were not concerned with the cement and that it was left for the shaikh to dispose of it against the charges, xo this he replied thamvCompany; that the cament did not worth the amount of charges due on it and that he still claimed the charges which v/ere due according to the statement of account which was submitted* 3* ± also made inquiries about the consignee and about the reason for which he did not take delivery of it* • • • i beg to inform you that he was an Iranian by name^/Baqir rakhra originally from cingah who lived in uibai for many years working as trdder and used to go to India sometimes* xhree years ago he went to xehran for a change of climate and there he married the daughter of Malik al-Kuttab. uuring the same visit he al$o purchased 2000 bags of cement from the Japan &amp; Iran company and paid them some earnest money and took a letter from thenuCompany) to the Agent of fhe Mesopotamia Persia corporation at uubai to the effect thathe was to pay the balance price in varans and take over the 2000 bags of cement, xhe said Hajji joaqir went to jjabai and presented the letter to liir.iiandeth, the Agent of the Mesopotamia rersian corporation and expressed his readiness to pay the varans, the balance price of tne cementj in accordance v/ith the terms 01 tne letter ..hich he brought with him and to take over the above mentioned cement, ivtr.&amp;andeth refused to accept the varans from the said najji ^aqir and to deliver the cement to him. ue 4 also refused to accent the letter which iiajji Baqir produced and wrote on it that it was not accepted, there upon najji uaqir went back to the company at xehran and retunred the letter togetTa^r with acertificate which he obtained from the merchants at L/ubai on the subject. ne delivered the papers to thenu comp any; and got back he the money which/paid them as earnest money and cancelled the purchase. usual ending. Copy forwarded to the secretary to the Honourable the political pesident in the Persian culf, mshire*Jib.87- m/IO.-I. Politic*! Agency, Bahrain, thr let arch 1G3G. x'o *-«Bero. raoopotaiia rows .if Corporntien United, riaorah, • Iraq. u. Si Mnr airs, ' The Honourable the Political Aoaldent in the i-ercian Mlf has instructed os to deni with the clair nade by the ohnikh of dibai rj-rinct your Coiporntlon in connoctioii v?ith 0000 bacs of cora nt landoc; at ^bal by the daprencoe otenner a r(nnk;i -iaru“ on tho Slot u-jnc 1034 . I have nade onriuirioc at Dubai and it ooene tlmt the coneiqnoo wao an Ircnim nesaed Ksjji i.aqir Fakhra, ••ho lived for am-- yoaro in Dube.- an a trader. some throe years uro he is flaid to have rrono to Tehran and during hia visit to have bought POOO bags of conmt Iron the ^apan and -iron corapaay, for which ho p id ea nest rionoy. ho took a letter from tho Company to too Agent of your Corporation at •nbni to tho effect that he ('rjji oqir) vm3 to pay the balance of tho price of the Corent in'krona and to take over the 2000 bags of cement. Ka^i Bnqir went to Jubai and presented toe letter to i-r.Kondeto, toon your Agent, and expressed his readiness to pay the balance of too price in krans and to take over toe conant. aandeth roAicod to accept the krone from Hajji »aqir or to deliver too cement to him. no ai 0o roidsed to accept the letter which KaJJi naqii* x&gt;roducGd and vvi'ot.© on it thnt , uiau i/QO not accoptod* aaiji ;iaqir want nek to the ^ •)*&gt;•- -t - „ , -O. ,11 .oiiran and apparently got back the 9mm Mr and Oanccllo theJV) C' 2 ^ v— v /^— A ^ ~A &lt; ^-^0$xy s *&gt; ^3&gt; ev&gt;)^&lt;y &lt; ^22/j it* an slat ion of letter no. 193 dated the 21st arch 1936 from k =? nuoain tin nasan ‘Amd, i n charge current duties of the Kesidencv Agent, bharjah, to the political Agent, Bahrain. After Compliments &gt; v lS3fi. Keference your letter Uo .88-ri/10.-l dated the 1st .-..arc x made enquiries discreetly but could not find that najl Baqlr haS any P ro P e rty in uubai. i have not yet heard about his return to uijbai. usual ending.fij/O- rr I NCORPORATI NG: STEPHEf^ LYNCH &amp; C9 LYNCH BROTH ERS.fP GRAY, MACKENZIE &amp; C9 and GRAY, PAUL 8r C9 The Mesopotamia Persia Corporation LIMITED. Telegraphic Address; 'mespers'.’ Codes used; BentJey's Complete Phrase Code. Scott’s Tenth Edition. The Standard Shipping Code A.B.C.St* Edition. N Bahrein, 29th March, &amp;ENTI.EY s Second. V 0 k The Political Agent, BAHREIN. Dear Sir, As requested in your letter No.87-B/10-l of the 1st instant, we enclose herewith a statement received from Mr. P. S. Kandeth, receipt of which please acknowledge Yoylrs faithfully, Enc.1.2 000 BAGS CE MEN T - KA,TI BAKER PAKHR. DTTBAI. The above forms part of a shipment of 4000 bags cements discharged at Dubai by the s.s.'Nankwa tlaru' in June 1934. Sbmetlme In July of that year I received telegraphic instructions from The Iran Japan Trading Co ( then Persia Japan Trading Co) Teheran to deliver 2000 bags of cement to Haji Baker Fakhr against collection of about His. 8000/- and I advised The Iran Japan Trading Co, that whilst I was willing to collect the amount on their behalf the cement in question could not be delivered until and unless I got the relative Bill of Lading in exchange. Sometime in August Haji Baker Fakhr called on me and informed that he was willing to pay the amount due to I.Japan Trading Co. In Krans. Persian currency was not legal tender in Dubai and in view of the fact that Importation of Krans into Iran was prohibited at that time, not to mention the loss in exchange by converting krans into rupees and rupees into Krans for payment to the I.J.Trading Co,Tehran, I gave Haji Baker Fakhr option of payment either cash in rupees at Dubai or by a Kran D/Draft on Teheran. Haji Baker did not agree to these terms. He went back and for months there was no news of his whereabouts. do not remember whether Haji Baker produced a letter from The I. J.Trading Co, and I wrote on it that I did not accept/btt if I have not accepted such a letter it was for the simple reason that such a letter from a party whose interest in the goods was only the cost thereof was not an authority formas the Steamship Agents’ Representative,to release the cargo without the relative Bill of Lading. I had not received the Bill of Lading and had standing instruction from Head Office that no cargo should be delivered to any %&gt;rty except against the Bill of Lading. f I am not aware of what transpired between Haji Baker Fakhr and The I.J.Trading Co,. In this connection I would add that due to pressure brought to bear on me I came to an arrangement with the Sheikh of Dubai whereby he agreed to accept Ps 300/- In full and final settlement of demurrage plus the usual duty. In the meantime the owners of the goods had abandoned the cargo and the Sheikh was notified accordingly. I should state here that the foregoing Information has been drawn purely from memory and do not vouch for the accuracy of facts in the absence of records. ^P, S. Kandeth. 1 Khorramshahr, 19th March 1936.Extract of letter No.461 dated 11 th July 1-36 from the Residency Agent Sharjah. xxx Regarding the claim of the Ruler of Aibai against the Mesopotamia Iran Corporation limited on account of ce ent. As the Shaikh has already removed and used the cement, in my opinion and subject to your approval he may ultimately be informed that e has no claim against the Ships’ Company. Usual Ending..4 \\ ^ * A* Is) I^J C V^.^X)A 4 % ♦ —•j(^»i,w^j&gt;iii,ii! ) to l L Letter dated the 11th Jamadial Awal 1355 (30.7.36) from Shaikh Sai'd hin Maktum, O.B.E., Ruler of Duhai to Captain Hickinhotham, Political Agent, Bahrain. S After Compliments. ^ ^ I have received your letter dated the 27th Rahial Thani 1355 ( IJ7.Z6) and have understood what you have mentioned about the case of cement. We did not object to this except through the Political Agent, Bahrain, who ordered us to receive the cement on its value and claim for the rest. This is v/ritten for your information. Usual EndingLetter dated the 11th Jamadial Awal 1355 (30.7.56) from Shaikh Sai’d hin Maktum, O.B.E., Ruler of hubai to Captain Hiokinhotham, Political Agent, Bahrain. After Compliments. I have received your letter dated the 27th Rahial Thani 1355 ( /y - ?. ^) have understood what you have nnenoioned about the case of cement. We did not object to this except through the Political Agent, Bahrain, who ordered us to receive the cement on its value and claim for the rest. This is v/ritten for your information. Usual Ending.- INCORPORATING:- STEPHEN LYNCH A C9 LYNCH BROTHERS, L T P GRAY, MACKENZIES, 09 AND GRAY, PAUL 8. C9 Telegraphic Address:- 'mespers'.’ Codes used:- Bentley's Complete Phrase Code. Bentley's Second Phrase Code The Mesopotamia Persia Corporation LIMITED, IN REPLY PLEASE QUOTE N?M/y2^p BAHRAIN, 7 th November /9 36 H. 3. M's Political Agent, BAHRAIN. Dear Si* 4 , We have been advised by our ^e^re^ry at Basrah that the claim from the Sheikh of Dubai for demurrage on 2000 bags Cement ex s.s. M Nankwa Mam' has been referred to you. May we kindly ask you if this is so, or whether the Sheikh's claim has since been withdrawn, as we would like to know the present position. Yours faithfully, (frputy Mona?*No. -B/10-1 Political Agency, Bahrain, tae 18th November,1936 To irfiessrs The Mesopotamia Persia Corporation Limited, BAHRAIN. Dear Sirs, With reference your letter No.L/l320 of 7tn November 1936. 1 beg to inform you as follows On 17th July last the Officiating Political Agent, Captain T. Hic/winbotham, wrote to tne onaikii of Dubai saying tnat he aid not consider tnat the Shaikh hau any claim against the Company T s agent, because ne haa ueeu the cement. On July 30th the Snaikh acknowleugea this letter, ana said that he ,f only objectea through me 'olitical Agent, Bahrain, who ordered him to take tne cement at its value ana claim for the rest.” 2. No furtner correspondence nas passed. Yours iaitnfully, for Political Agent,Bahrain.Shaikh of Debai’s claim for demurrage on cement. $ I spoke to the Honourable the Political Resident on the 19.1,1936 on the above subject. He will tell Mr. Allcard that I am dealing with the case of the Shaikh of Debai’s claim about cement and suggest to him that the matter should be dealt with by the Mesopotamia Persia Corporation in Bahrain. 0 2. What we want to find out is who was the purchaser of the cement and^^ether the Shaikh f s customs rules have 9 any provision for taking over or selling goods after they have lain in his godown for a certain time. am not at all clear that this was not made as a Japanese speculation 4L. UZ\' t**-* u-sj-rfuz** though I was told^by an Indian merchant it was bad . 1 This needs to be cleared up. Then we shall be in a position to judge whether we can tell the Shaikh that he should have sold the stuff as soon as the time was up. 19.1.1936 * 4^ •A » — ~ a - 1 ' hen the shaikh of Idbai came to cahrain in September 1935, the officiating a.P.a. asked him about the name of the consignee and he replied that the cement W as imported by the B.I. Agents at uibai and that he knew of no other consignee. Mr. Jasim who was presentu was then on tour with the p.r.) when the shaikh came to see the P.T.Oufficiating a.P.A. on 6,10«35 he v/as bold that he had no right whatsoever against the Mesopotamia Persia Corporation in Dibai but a^inst t-he consignee and that he could sell or take over the unclaimed cement against his claim* ( 2 ) in reply to a question put to him, the shaikh of uibai said that there were no provisions in his customs rules about unclaimed goods lying in his godown for a certain time* (3) I heard, though not certian^that the goods v/ere actually ordered by an Iranian merchant, who was then trading at uibai,now is living in Iran, but on account of the delay in getting the dill of liading could not take over the goods in time and that later on refused to take over the goods and thus remained unclaimed* i heard that the shaikh of Dibai made this as a counter claim against the Mesopotamia Persia Corporation for having claimed compensation for the goods which were looted from their lighter^ at the rJiaur of uibai. 23.1; 36 P.R. wishes us to ta^e over action on this case. 2. The first thing to do is to gind out who the consignee is and whay he did not taice over his cement. If there is a consignee,then I think that according to commercial custom (we shd checK this point if it arises)m &gt;0 j a. 4 K 25 • 27* it is he against whom the Shaikh shd proceed. If,however, the consignee proves to be the steamer Tine, then the claim would clearly lie against them in their cpppcity of consignee. The Shaikh might then refuse to allow their steamers into his port . Issue letter. / 1.2.36 issued letter imo. 39-3/10 dated the 2 nd re’bi’uary 1936 to .5.Husain bin Hasan *Arnad 5 sharjah. P.L.Ho.101/14/167 dated the 14th January 1S36 from the Secretary to the P.K., 3ushire. k t o A.P.A. claim of tie rculer of i/jbai agaciinst lespers. In oui le oter 1 . 0 . 30-h/ 9 dated 2-2-36 ^at p. 201 *202 v/e asked K.S.Husain to let us know v/hether the Kuler of Dibai still makes this claim. Un receipt of this informat ion we can inform mshire accordingly. May be filed. ^ £ 2/2/36 / dfcyi No sir, we are awaiting reply from K.S.Husain to our letter No.39-3/3. f /P/Q 3/3/36 dti &gt;1 M- ffrlVL ♦ i li.1L 29. Issued P.L.No.42-B/lO dated the 3rd February 1936 to the Honourable the P.R.,Bushire.Letter no.58 dated the 85th January 1236 from K#S I Husain bin Hasan ’Anad, sharjah, to the p.A.Bahra Letter imo. 91 dated 10.2*36 from js. # b.nasain, Sharjah* from the above letter it is clear that the claim of the Shaikh of uibai lies ayainst either the consignee najji Laqir or the japan Iran company and not against the agents of the I do not thinK that we can be as positive as above. We must find out what part the Agent of the Meso potamia^ Persia Corporation played - apparently he refused to hand over the cement. This ,if true, does not sound as if the Corporation were^/merely carriers or the agents of carriers, though possibly it may oe so— ^ ^ 2 . I thinK that the plan most liKely to get the truth is for H.M. to taK.e this file when he goes an tour with P.R. and get a statement from Mr Aandeth and also see if it is possible to get the ship’s manifest from the Dubai customs. He? Claims of virumal valabdas A.P.A. In the circumstances, may be filed till the smallpox epedimic has disappeared. s/2/36 ‘V A*P.A. 13.2.36 22.2.36£}/10 ” |. 33. issued letter i\io.87-jj/ 10.-2 dated the 1st ^arch 1936 to Messrs. Mesopotamia rersia uorporation Ljtd. ,^&gt;asrah. 35. issued letter am o *88-u/ 10.-2 dated the 1st march 1936 to Khan oahib nusain, oharjah. ^ v ' Mr Kandeth is in Basrah. But H.M. shd try to get the manifest out of the Dubai Customs,or a copy of the essential portions relative to the cement. Also any information about Hajji Bagir and the transaction. rs\f action. L *7 • 3. 36 0 looted 7.3.36 in compliance with the above order, ± got the manifest ^attached; through n.b.nusain who gave a receipt for it. fhe P.H. did not land at jjubai and we left immediately after the shaikh had landed* according to n.b.nusain the consigees were the shippers themselves who issued delivery order to the purchaser najji naqir to enable him to receive the goods from the agent of iviespers at lAibai, but for the reasons stated in ii.A's letter jwo. 91 dated 10.2.36(p*30) were not delivered. Hajji Baqir left Dubai for good and has ceased to have any business at mabai. isrs.Se m. riow we seem to be getting nearer the truth. Await reply from Mespers, but put up in any case when P.R. is here. tz. 2f &lt; l\ frjip. 1,1*^ better dated 19th xl a bi al Thanl 1355 (9-7-36) from the Kuler of Dubai. A.P.A. In view of your discussion of the case with the A. A. and the latter’s suggestion (vide his letter No .461 dated nth duly 1936)the Shaikh may be informed by the k.A. that he has no claim against the Co. because he used the cement. 15-7-36. 45 45 . /%&amp;/- /fciA fa - ^ J £&amp; ''I) P.A. Please see your notes on files 3/10 and 3/10 Ijrnarked A and regarding Baler of Dubai's claim on acoount of cement. In view of your note on A I presume you wish to reply to the Ruler of Dubai. Dpa-tt submitted for aoorovaJL. 17-7-36. . a ///7 77 Issued letter No.S80-B/ 10 -! aated 17&gt;7&lt;36 to ^ Duler of Dubai. fromkhfiler^f ‘ Wal 1356 ^-7.36j A.P.A . Submitted please. 54.Q.du. 7jc(tr V.o .</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x00025a_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1867</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x00025a</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1867</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>‘File B/10-I CLAIM OF THE RULER OF DUBAI AGAINST MESPERS’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1935/1936</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-05-12T22:01:01</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (59 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 61; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 50-60; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.A previous foliation sequence, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains enquiry correspondence relating to a claim made in 1935 by Shaikh Said bin Maktum [Shaikh Saʻīd bin Maktūm bin Hasher Āl Maktūm] the Ruler of Dibai [Dubai], principally against the shipping agents Mesopotamia Persia Corporation Limited (also referred to as the Mesopotamia Iran Corporation Limited). The claim concerns the reimbursement of expenses incurred by the Ruler of Dubai, in connection with 2000 bags of unclaimed cement landed at Dubai by the Japanese steam ship
                           Nanku Maru(also spelt
                           Nankwa Maru) on 21 June 1934. The main correspondents are: the Political Agent at Bahrain, the Residency Agent at Sharjah, the Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf at Bushire, Mr P S Kandeth the Dubai representative of the shipping agents, and the Ruler of Dubai. The letters exchanged between the Ruler of Dubai, the Residency Agent and the Political Agent are in English and Arabic. The file also includes: the cargo manifest submitted to Dubai Customs by the
                           Nanku Maruon its arrival in 1934; the statement (in Arabic) of expenses incurred by the Ruler of Dubai on the landed cement, signed by the hammalbashi (chief of the porters’ guild) at Dubai Pier in 1934; and the witness statement made in 1935 by Mr P S Kandeth, regarding the purchase of the cement in 1934 from the Persia Japan Trading Company at Tehran, by the original consignee Haji Baker Fakhr (also spelt Hajji Baquir and Haji Kaber), a Persian subject.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Landing charges</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Emir of Dubai, Āl Maktūm dynasty</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Native Agent, Trucial Coast, Sharjah</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Mesopotamia Persia Corporation Limited</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Dibai</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Cement</topic></subject><subject><topic>Claims</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x00025a#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>