<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100059346669.0x000002_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-07-16T13:47:55.644Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">SECRET POLITICAL DEPARTMENT Dated Telegram Formally acknowledged Initials. Under Secretary Secretary 0f State Committee Under/Secretary. Secretary of State FOR USE BY DEPARTMENTS ONLY. PreviousA */ | [This Document is the of H - „ . « / * '' i ' V ' . — or fll? Britan nio Mafestw^rs^., be ^turned to the For»ei^n Q^ Z'7TI-I -~-^-- Gove ^ m ent. *o&gt;» official \-s (85846/^/34) &gt;: / 7 a FILES ONLY, * 9 ;: . Cypher telegram to Sir P, Cox. (Teheran), Foreign Office, June 13th. 1919. 12„0,p,n„ No, 337. O i*r Your telegram Ho t 360 (of Majr 14th} e (Shiraz ITorth R*ad Guards). The Treasury consent to the continuance of payments not exceeding tomans 7 c 5GO a month on condition that the expend!tat's is cnarged to the fersian Government as an advance out of prospective loan. ¥.111 this arrangement he agreeable to the Persian Government? In replying please state on what date the advances beg.i-n as the India Office in agreeing to accept a moiety made it a condition that the arrangement should he re garded as temporary and limited to a further period of three months* if %J*U’ jIn any further communication on this subject, please quote and address , , The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London, S.W. 1. 4? / 3&gt;3^, 4 ]• -1278 ^ ^-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, presents his compliments to the dp&amp;P LU 9j[^X and, by direction If the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cof of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office. igig Reference to previous correspondence to Letter from Foreic J n 0 ffi ce • Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. o ^ / Sdcj&amp;spLo. 17 UL1913 J (Similar letter sent to \i , 1 L aindexed In any fnrthor oommunication on this subject, please quote no- 74245/W/24. and address, j. not to any person ly name, but to— “ The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W.l, ^ Sir:- ifgn Office May 23rd, 1919. rs.8,500 I » directed by an Odrcen „ t Kedieeton to refer to my letter n-p CObdect.e ‘ r&gt; ' 19th - 8J1 d the Ohnected con-es p „„dence, reepecting t te nKlntemnce Guarde tree, shlrae to the l6 £a ten border “ “ estl ™ tea ooot of tonahs eight ttoeeand flee undred a month, art to transmit to you, herein to be laid before Mr. secretary Montagu, a copy' 01 8 telesra ”’ Ir ” » ls Majesty's Minister at Tehran on the subject. 2. Lord curzon concurs in the view expressed y the Viceroy ox India in his telegram of April isth, as to the maintenance of this force until the South Persia Rifles are finally transferred to the Persian Authorities. ■3. I am therefore to enquire whether Mr. Montagu will agree to the payment of a moiety of the expenditure be Under-Secretary of state, India Office. r. I*- IV- ‘;i P &gt; . - r ^ilt 3 p fe -xt- w V involved. r xinvolved* 4. copies of the correspondence on the subject are being furnished to the Lords Commissioners of His Majesty’s Treasury with a recommendation that a moiety of the expenditure should be met out of Imperial Revenues. I am, Sir, &lt; e &lt; Your most obedient humble Servant,INDEX 5 ? n ' » FILES ONLY. Decyptier. Sir P. Cox (Teheran). my 14th, 1919. D. 5.40 p.m. 14th May, 1919. R. 4.20 p.m. 15th Way. 1919. No. 360. Your telegram No. 105. Please see Government of India’s telegram No. 433 of April 13th to Secretary of State for India. His Majesty’s Consul at Shiraz reports that position is now very (? group omitted) as F.F. has advanced two months pay and will not advance more without assurance of repayment. i \ &gt; tv*indexed 1 1 A ^ *• - f -*--W ■ * f'V ^ ,. . y t% J o Secret. 1C17. Our tele^rnri of loth Arril. I^Qx'wh Hoad Ctaards. Hots on reports t r -..at Farmer. Fnrm^ ;-,3 paid force for 2 months but of his om pochet but aeolines to advance more without ^ssursnce of x-’epaTment. _ie reco:;:,lends that if psyraerit c.annot be guaranteed until settlement of South Persian Rifles/ ques wion . ..e may oe author!set to rroimi-se to yenay ijarm.an wnatever .ias been and will be hereafter spent v. I &lt;J' Hi t. u3 ^ i limit until the receipt of final orders. road highly s at i s f ac • I o ry, Pm h far 1 has completely. Disbandment of road guards robberies. Re support Rotson in this should be g rateful. for anything tha.t can be done to expedite- transfer of South Persian Fdfl.es to Governor---enera!.' Re Vue only budgeted continuance of Indian expend!‘hare on this up to the end of June, and should be most unvilling to exceed amount allotted Vr this purpose. Addressed to Secretary of- State and repeated to ene: It, IJku A'-'O Ip' LI ilDecyphor. Sir P. Cox (Teheran ). May 14th 1919. D. 5.40. p , 14tli Iday 1919, H. 4,20.p.m. 15th May 1919, No , 360. v\\ Your telegram No. 105. Please see Government of India's telegram No. 433 of April 13th to Secretary of state for India. Hiar Majesty's Consul at Shiraz reports that position is now very (? group otpited) as P.F. has advanced two months pay and will not advance more without assurance of repayment. »•••*« • • . A'if Ciar.Og rTAffRy: -ii.* x- *Oa.i ;iceroy, FotgI^li Ds’D^rtcienv Sated lota April, 1919. (Heed* 14th April, 1919.) ueexeo. Your teiegroji of 28th Febn?.^r ,t / 1 igt* Payment to Farman Farm for protection north road. Consul, Shiraz, in reporting th-f results are oawasfac wory ;mA t oat Govemor-G-eneral represents present unusual good order along the rood Trill raoHlv -- v degene rise n uen are not paid, recorimends the conwinuaice of payments until South Persia Rifles are Handed over to Governor-General. These vievrs are supported by Cox and have our concurrence. Charge has no a »,• w c exceeded oCOO tomans and Consul does not anv-ucipa/Ge is will go beyond 7500. Unsstisfactor^r nature of t-'.ese tuf'-ngchj doles emphasises desirability of very early settlement on main South Persia Rifles question, in connection with which Go^/ernor-General ’s success -on this small scale is very relevant. Aidressed to Secretary of State and renested toIn any further communication , 1 _• on this sujr^ec^, ^plea^^uo^e ^ No. • and address, not to any person by name, but to— “ The Pndcr-Secretary of State,” POREIGN OeFICE Foreign Office, London, S.W.l. s , fi tfe^ary 19th 1919. Urgent. s 9 j Sir, Ts. 10 , 000 .. Ts. 8,500, With reference to my letter of the 23 rd ultimo t ^ ireCted ’ Dy E&amp;rl Curzon Kedieston to transmit J ° y ° U h0rein ’ t0 ’ De lald before Mr. Secretary 'ontagu, a copy of a telegram from His Majesty's Ministe r in Teheran regarding the situation in Shiraz. 2. Lord Curaon has recelvod the smctimi of the Treasury to accept a moiety of the sum of Teh thousand Tomans if Mr. ''ohtasu .ill accept a similar moiety as a charge on Indian revenues. With regard to the question of the mainten ance of North Road Guard from Shiraz to the Ispahan oorder at the estimated cost of Sight thousand, five hundred lomans a month, His Lordship will be Slad to learn Mr. Montagu's views on the subject in view or the fact that the Government of India The Under Secretary of State India Office.T 't 0 Minute Pape .. . j 5 ^) Telegram P., No. 178-248-G., dated the Juth (received 11th) September 1»18. I 1 ioti} Sir Percy Sykes, Shiraz, To_The Ch.et of the General Staff, Simla (repeated Minister, Tehran) Clear line. Your 7196]-M. O. 1, September 9th rounds of ammuSn to f ruzabi * d « July, I lent him 200 rifles and 20,000 several hundred riflest WaS f SUb9 ®1 uentl y ^isoovered that Kawam had several Hundred rifles m reserve from those which were given him in 1916 from South PerliTHi/ ^ Ar f bS ° Ver 250 ritles whicb were collected restorer The trib^mf and “ uti “ e ers of which only 13 have been restoreo. Ihe tribesmen and village Tufangchis in Ears are well armed and w en lighting against us they produced plenty of ammunition. Before con- dering any turther loan of rifles, Consul was asked to get back those which ammunition toEar™ “p alS ° those oollected ^ bim. To sell further rifles and are ten i mes the P 1 ar “ a w ° uld me M simply arm traffic as the local prices are ten times the Government sale prices and Barman Farma’s subordinates The riflas which are loaned are damaged and are unpaid and untrustworthy neglected and unfit for subsequent military use. In everv case the ammuni tion would be shown as expended. The rifles and especially the ammunition * Transposition. given, loaned or sold to Persian regulars* m » . . fall into the hands of tribesmen and Tufangchis eventually, and become both a menace to British interests and a danger to our troops. The Southern Road will presumably be taken over bv me and I shall be prepared to take over the Northern Road again in December. (f) Omission. ln ^ he meantime I see no extra ( f ) for putting into Persian hands any more — rifles or ammunition. Telegram P., No. 93, dated the 13th (received 14th) September 1918. From—His Majesty's Consul, Shiraz, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Simla (repeated to Tehran, 170, Bushire and Ispahan). A scheme for road guards for Northern Road from Shiraz to borders of Ispahan has been submitted by Governor-General providing for a total force of 66T men including footmen, cavalry commanders and establishment, doctors, inspectors, writers, &amp;c,, complete. Monthly total cost is tomans 8,484 and length of road is over 200 miles. Governor-General guarantees that he can adequately guard the road and escort posts and caravans with tb^s force except in case of concerted rising of great tribes of which, in near future, I trust there is no prospect. The scheme has been carefully gone into by me and satisfied myself it is as economical and should he as efficient as is possible for such a force. It errs if anything on side on economy as some secorts of road appear to me to be too lightly guarded. Governor-General is being advised to begin without delay laying out posts according to his scheme. Cost of first month will probably be about 3,000, second month 105 and third month according to full estimate. 0^ (VW^C_ tfcc (r/TvC Kny ►wwtcX U-K) Co tu 4 0—| • K 1 1 iTelegram P., No. 95, dated the 19th (received 21st) September 1918. From—His Britannic Majesty's Consul, Shiraz, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Simla (repeated to Tehran, 173). If the control of northern road is to be assumed by Sykes in December and southern road earlier, continuance of Governor-General's scheme which as reported in my telegram, 93, would take three months to get into working order is not worth while in my opinion. His Highness is therefore being advised by me to discontinue his preparations which were in train. The Tufangchis which he has already collected he can post at one or two places on the road where robberies are of frequent occurrence, Colonel ■J/Villiams, on return of Abadeh relief column, can continue to guard the rest of road. These men will be supplemented by Governor-General’s Tufangchis as stated above and should be sufficient to prevent serious troubli on road for ^iterval before South Persia ^iifles , control is re-established. Information quoted in Sykes’telegram, 179—24S-G., regarding Governor-General's scheme to raise bogus trouble on southern road is not credited by me personally. Por recovery of rifles taken by Arabs from South Persia Rifles posts I am pressing the Kawam. Those lent to him and to Kashgais are now in use by latter at present engaged in operations against forces of Soulat. This refers to your telegram, No. 2029-S. Telegram P., No. 158, dated the 21st (received 22nd) September 1918. From—His Britannic Majesty's Charge d'Affaires and Special Commissioner, Tehran, Persia, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Simla. Reference correspondence ending with Shiraz telegram, No. 173, Septem ber 19th. ' v &gt; I think that it would be prudent to let Governor-General have the small amount of arms asked for, if the Government of India do not consider that Sykes' anticipations in the direction of taking over northern and southern roads are likely to be realised. Telegram P., No. 98, dated the 22nd (received 23rd) September 1918. From—His Britannic Majesty's Ctfnsul, Shiraz, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Depart ment, Simla (repeated to Tehran, 178). That control of northern road should revert to Sykes without interval under Governor-General is the natural sequence of above telegram. sc h eme w as adopted latter was ready to accept full responsibility for safety of traffic. As road will be guarded by Tufangchis appointed by South Persia Rifles in interval between now and resumption of control by South Persia Rifles, it would not be fair in my opinion to put responsibility on. Governor-General. Sykes is also willing to temporarily resume control with Tufangchis now on road and His Highness who assures me that he will i^ive every assistance in his power, is willing to place control in his hands. I hese road guards, however, it should be thoroughly understood, should not interfere in any way with internal direction of country. S\ kes should, therefore, I recommend, again at once take over control making, pending more permanent arrangements, such arrangements as he considers necessary. ° This refers t o my telegram, 95, September 19th.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100059346669.0x000002_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/10/577/3</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100059346669.0x000002</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/10/577/3</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>File 4612/1915 Pt 3 'Persia: maintenance of north road guards; payments to Farman Farma'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1919/1919</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-04-30T09:58:35</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 item (24 folios)</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This part comprises telegrams, despatches, correspondence, memoranda, and notes, relating to the payments to the Governor of Fars, Farman Farma [ʿAbd-al-Ḥosayn Mīrzā Farmānfarmā] for the maintenance of the North Road guards.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100059346669.0x000002#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>