<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x0002cb_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-18T07:13:03.020Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">mm RELATED FILES PUBLIC RECORDS ACT, 1958 (See paragraphs 24, I to 24, 4 of Part D of Digest of Office Procedure) When the officer dealing with this file considers that it is unlikely to be used again, or when the file is automatically closed at the end of a three-year cycle, the Higher Executive Officer (or Officer of higher rank) responsible for the subject should recommend in the appropriate space on the back cover of the file whether the file should be destroyed after a prescribed period or preserved. If he is unable to form a firm view, one of the spaces for “Consider at First/Second Review” should be signed: where this is done, a note must be placed on top of the file as the last paper giving reasons for deferring a decision. CROSS REFERENCED UNDER PRECEDENTS NOTED UNDERStatement of Farrasli Audullah (AbDud ) . On 1.3*36 mtq Loch was returning Irom Jabai and driving the- car. When about sunset hrs ho 011 * s car reached in front oi the .American School for ooys where two roads meet, a taxi swiftly came out the western turning ol the road and wanted to go towards east. Mrs Loch's car was bound to north, as this taxi came out of the corner, Mrs Loch blew the horn and turned her car towards the right and the taxi stopped quite close to the car. Had Mrs Loch not turned her car to the right the taxi would have collided with it. Mrs Loch drove to tne Agency and the taxi was following. The taxi driver did not blow the horn as he was going to taxe Uie turning but he blew it simultaneously with Mrs Loch. I did not see the driver. But Muhammad Ahmad, Agency driver, saw him and says that his name is Ghulum bin Muhammad and his Ho.91. Abdullah. * Recorded before me this 15th day of March, 1936.© D.O.Jfo.ll0/V.O. Datoc, 17th farch 1S36, ) ^ dear nelgrave, yj * i enclose a copy of a statement regarding a taxi 3 which nearly collided with the Agency car* as the a grieved car was nine and no danage was done, I should prefer that no case should he brought against the driver of the taxi, but I should be grateful if he could be warned* 8* (Shulun bin ^harried lo said to bo r. rersian bom in Bahrain. Yours oincerel-. 0 * Dalrynple x&gt;eIgrave, n»squ ire, Adviser to the Bahrain v/ovemnent.* jjahrain.D.0 # Ho*3l2«E/3 Political Agency* Bahrain* the 14th August*1936. Pear Steele, I have received several complaints from foreign residents in Bahrain about the w 8crimalaging ,, at the issue of ice at the Baladlah* and have received one charge brought by the police against a foreign subject. 2. Although any interference by me in the running of the Bahrain police would be improper* the Interests of foreigners are the special concern of the Agency. I therefore made it my business to go to the Baladlah and see the conditions under which ice is issued. 3. I regret that I came to the conclusion that the police charge of 'jostling” against Muhammad bin Abdullah Zaid could not be entertained without charging similarly half of Bahrain 2 4. It also seemed to me th f t it might be possible to avoid complaints by the police and charges by the police in the future if same sort of aliening system could be arranged* say by making the crowd line up In single file along a few chandals on stands. 5. Would you kindly give the matter your considera tion ? I am sure you will agree with me that this sort of friction is all to the bad. W.B. Steele Esquire* Acting Commandant of Police* BAHRAIN.[ 0 GOVERNMENT OF BAHRAIN. POLICE DEPARTMENT. D. 0 Bahrain, nated: Au^ist,lh36 28th J/Awal,1355 Siank you for your D.O. in connection v/ith che ice distributed by the Baladyia* SoEie trouble is generally experienced during August, at the ice aepot.oue to a shortage of ice and consequent scrambles, 5/6 policemen and eight nature are on duty and a chandle barrier already exists, I have observed that the police are very patient with the crowd, as they should be, but certain foreignafs, notably Persians, are inclirfd to take advantage of this. However, the new ice plant, (one ton and one ton storage capacity) started yesterday, and to-day two shops are functioning, and in each case four persons will be admitted only f at a time r through the barrier. One Kavildar and live police will regulate each shop and eight naturs. There always will be, however, the man Lieut.JIB .Howes, H.B.M*s Assistant Political Ag B ahrain. ^ ;ent,73 GOVERNMENT OF BAHRAIN. PQjjl'Jili I'iOl’lUij MO bor ibrivin^ juicenses Persons wishing to renew their driving licenses may apply either in writing or in person to- the Police office at Matiamah Port between the hours of 6,30 and 8,30 a,m, or 3.30 and 6.30 p.m. daily. The renewal fee must accompany the application, for wnich a receipt will be given. ho person is allowed to urive a car unless he or she is in actual possession of a license, 'wuich should be carried on the person or in the car when driving* It will assist the police and avoid delay if applications for renewal are sent in before the date of the exf Possession of a receipt for fees paid will not necessarily prevent a driver be in a license. POLICE DEPARTMENT. Bidh&amp;Ih. toTed . 30th. ^ust.1936 12th J/’Ihatd,1355 PF/32/55 piry of the old licenses CAfV. 7*1 Fpom, Tlie Clerk-in-charge,Naval Base,Jnfair. Date, 19 th. Sept ember 1956 Nov / To, The H.B.M*s Polical Agent,Bahrain. Submitted. Last evening at 6.15 taxi No.206 entered Jufair NavO. Base without permission with some women,as these instan ces are occuring too often the matter is therefore brought to your notice for such action as you deem necessary. Clerk-in-charge Naval Base Jufair Copy submitted to The Senior Naval Officer,Persian GulfVNo. }Uj'/ 0- Political Agency, Bahrain, tne 23rd September,1935. The Acting Commandant of Police, Bahrain. llemo rang urn . I enclose a. copy oi' report from the 01 erf in- charge, Naval Base, Jut’air for favour of necessary action. lor Offg. Political Agent, Bahrain.GOVERNMENT OF BAHRAIN. POLICE DEPARTMENT. KO.PF/39/55 Bahrain. Dated: .oepteuibe^lDSS 26th J/Thani, 1355 H.B.M's Political Agent, ' ' £! /‘» Baiiraiii* Memo ran dum:- Re Omar Ishaq, deceased. At about 10.30 a.m, on Saturday, 29th August,1936 Omar Ishaq, deceased, was working on a Ford car in the garage of Haji Khalil Kanoo and had opened tne bonnet on the rig.it juuMediate- ly on opening it, flames issued and the deceased caught fire. It is stated by a witness that de ceased tried to extinguish the flames by means of waste and suffered several burns in consequence. On the cry of fire the police rail to the garage from the adjacent police station ana met the de ceased at the door of the garage where they ex tinguished his clothes and took him to the Victoria Memorial Hospital for treatment. He aied at 1305 p.m, on 2nd September,1936 (see the enclosed medi cal certificate). At the time of the occurance (fire) there were three other people present, Aimed Ali Kanoo, who was standing near the bonnet of the car, Haji Ahmed Hasan, and His assistant Moosa Essa Hasawi, the latter two persons were working on a bus wiliin six feet of tne Cent fheir statements are attached. Hie car was cold, but petrol was being used to clean it, and a small tin of petrol .was standing on the running board on the left hand side, Hie re appears to be no evidenceGOVERNMENT OF BAHRAIN. POLICE DEPARTMENT. nQ.PF/39/55 13- 9- 36 26- 6— 55 of a deliberate attempt to cause fire,but it seems very probably that the outburst was caused by a careless act, such as throwing down a lighted match, or a ciga rette end near the car* It appears that persons were in the habit of smoking in the garage at all times. There was no warning sign, or notice displayed (such as 'no Smoking'), or any fire appliance of any description in the garage. In my opinion there should have been both. The carpenter Haji hhmed Hasan seems to know a 6 ood deal more about the case than he will aisclose.Report @n the death ©f Omar Bin Ishaq Bastaki Irani. The deceased was brought t© hospital at 11 a.m. ©n the 29th August 1936. He had been involved in a petrol fire and was suffering from severe and extensive bums of the abdomen, chest, back, both arms including hands and fingers, neck and face. He was also suffering from severe shock. He was treated for four days but succumbed through shock, exhaustion and slight toxaemia. The burnt areas were doing as well as could be expected. He expired at 1305 p.m. on 2nd September 1936. D.T.M., Medical Officer-in-Charge, Victoria Memorial Hospital, Bahrain. The Acting Commandant, State Police, Bahrain.No- 3 ( V' O- p oIitical Agency, Bahrain, the 18th September, 193b. The Acting Commandant, State Police, Bahrain. Memorandum . deference your letter No.PF/39/bb dated the 13th. September 1936 (26th Jamadial lhani,13bb). I do not gather from your letter whether the police intend taking any further action m the matter. Would you please inform me ? for Offg. Political Agent, BahrainA.P.A. No reply lias been received to letter No.3bb/V.O. dated tiae 18tn September, 1936 from tne Acting Commandant, so far. May a reminder be issued please? / 1.10.3b. ^■u i 1 V ITo ihe Political Agent, Bahrain Complainant Saleh bin Sharidah subject of Bahrain residing at Mohara^ Accused Abdul Aziz Bu fhalid bin Si f doon, subject of Kuwait, 1 oeg to state that my nephew Ali bin Habib useci to go witii the accused for diving as a puller. Unfortunately he fell sick. He asked the Makhoda to bring him to shore but the Aaknoda reiusec. to do so. he died in the sea and was brought to land as dead. We did not know what was the reason of his sickness on account of which he died. ' When we washes his deadbody some blood came out of his mouth. 1 hope that the Government will do the needful according to justice. Hated 18th Jamadail Thani 1354. ' 5th September 1936. a .To, Makarraq Dispensary, Dated 6th.SeptemDer 1966. ,4l&gt; H.B.M's Political Agent, Bahrain. Sir, Kef:Your memo.dated 5 th.Sept ember 1956,regarding case of Ali bin Eabib. I beg to state,that no detailed Post-mortem examination of the internal organs,could be held,as no such proceedure is in vogue locally.My conclusions were arrived at,only,by an external examination of the body. From the external appearence of the body and the general c physique,the diseased seemed to have been in the enjoyment of perfect health just before his death. He complained of severe pain in the region of the heart, which,in my opinion,must have had a sudden seizure proving fatal immediately.A severe and fatal attack of Angina Pec toris, Syncope or Complete Heart-Block often proves fatal in spite of best and immediate medical attention. In this case the attack must have proved fatal too quick- for treatment to be of any avail. I beg to remain, Sir, Yours obediently, In charge Maharraq Dispensary.I \ GOVERNMENT OF BAHRAIN. POLICE DEPARTMENT. UO.FP/SS/bS Bahrain. Dated;- 51st Au^ast, 1956 15th j/?iiany 1555 H.B.M’s Political Agent, Bahrain. Memorandum I return herewith Warrant to Search the house of one Mukhtar, Irani and have to state that the search i duly carried out on 50th August, 1956, without incident. Commananu, srare policeNo. t&amp;&gt; &amp; / f(&gt; of 1356 Offiqe of the Adviser to the Government, -Bahrain Gated, Muharram 29, 1356 April 10, 193 1 ?. H. B. M f s Political -^gent, Bahrain. Memorandum:- I forward herewith copy of a Police Order on cases relating to the Bahrain Petroleum Company, for your information. I 27 Ufa H.The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to The Commandant ol Police, Bahrain. and has the honour to send him ^S^W^he for favour of disposal. m original undermentioned document rsA. The Agency, BAHHAIN, Persian Gulp. Dated... Ipth..April _ 1937 Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Petition datea 4th Safar 13 bin T Abdullah al Hammad and two Saudi subjects, applym 56 (lb. 4.37) from Muliammad T Ali bin Muiiammad al Hammao, g for a job.^ ^ copy- Translation. To, The Political Agent, j^ahrain ^e, Muhammad bin ihimad al Hammad and T Ali bin Muhammad al Hammad, beg to state that we are from Najd. We came to Bahrain in order to earn for our living. We were serving in the Hedjaz m the Army-Artillery section. We are now submitting this petition with a request that you will very kindly grant us employment m the Army at Bahrain if you think fit for which we shall be very grateful to you. Tne decision rests with you. Bated 4th Safar 1356 (15.4.37) Sd. Muhammaa bin ’Abdullah al Hammad, and, T Ali bin Muhammad al Hammaa. I.A. PI. speak on this. B.T.- 15/4 Forward, to O.G.Police. B.T.-15/4£ ( 3 - Ho* 239/V.O. Political Agency^ Bahrain, the 29th June 1937* To The Adviser to the Bahrain Government, B A H R A X H* Memorandum * Vhile trying case Ho* 114 of 1937 Rais Police vs Ahmad bin Habib, for an offence under Section 377 read with Section 511 of the Indian Penal Code, it has c orae to my notice that the Police did not produce the accused be fore a Magistrate for seven days. I should be grateful if in the ease of foreign subjects the provisions of Sec tions 60 and 61 of the Criminal Procedure Code may be care fully observed in future cases* 3d/- T. Hickinbotham. Captain, Political Agent, Bahrain* _—RECOMMENDATION 1 FOR DISPOSAL RECOMMENDATION SIGNATURE DATE DESTROY AT FIRST REVIEW (i.e. within 5 years) DESTROY AT SECOND REVIEW (i.e. after 25 years) PRESERVE CONSIDER AT FIRST REVIEW CONSIDER AT SECOND REVIEWRECOMMENDATION 1 FOR DISPOSAL RECOMMENDATION DESTROY AT FIRST REVIEW SIGNATURE DATE (i.e. within 5 years) DESTROY AT SECOND REVIEW (i.e. after 25 years) PRESERVE CONSIDER AT FIRST REVIEW CONSIDER AT SECOND REVIEW</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x0002cb_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1980</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x0002cb</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1980</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'[Un-numbered file] Police cases'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1936/1937</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-07-11T22:06:36</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (34 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 36; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 2-35; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains correspondence in the form of petitions, reports and statements, related to police cases in Bahrain. Cases of note include the renewal of driving licences, and the distribution of ice by the Baladyia (Municipality).The main correspondence is between the Bahrain Political Agency, and the Adviser to the Bahrain Government (Charles Dalrymple Belgrave).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Physical examination</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Adviser to the Government of Bahrain</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Petitions</topic></subject><subject><topic>Criminal investigation</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x0002cb#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>