<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000291_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T21:54:04.475Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">n Daar Dr. Dame, * I should be interested if you would give me 80^6 information as to how your new European ard at the Mission hospital is going to be run. I should like to know roughly what sort of fees would be charged on European patients, men or women, who use the hospital, apart from the medi cal feeSyand what arrangements would be ade for cases who are being attended by the Government Doctor. It is possible in the future, if finances permit, that the Government will employ its own lady doctor, a project that has been under consi deration for several years in which case it might be advisable for her European patients to receive hospital treatment, a similar position might arise in the cose of patients of the agency Surgeon who now acts also as the Bahrain Government doctor, /hat will happen in these cases/ I had meant to write to you before on this subject but have been rather busy owing to the anniversary celebrations. Yours faithfully, \n \ u \ Dr. L. ?. Dame, .D.. Mason Memorial Hospital, Bahrain. V1 GOVERNMENT OF BAHRAIN. D.0//O73 - h Bahrain, February ^,1934 iV . Dr| /U | Dear Colonel Loch, Regarding the question of the new ward which is being built by the American Mission and for which they were given a small piece of ground by the Bahrain Government. Dr. Dame has shown me the agreement between the Bahrain Petroleum Company and the Mission. It shows very clearly that though the Bahrain Petroleum Company is pro viding the money for the building and giving all the equipment, the building and all that is in it are the absolute property of the Mission and the Bahrain Petroleum Company have no authority to make regulations regard ing the use of the ward. It is expressly mentioned in the agreement that the ward besides being for the use of the Europeans and ximericans 'emplJyet~by the Bahrain Petroleum Company, is for the use of all other Europeans and Americans in Bahrain. It does however say that the employees of the Bahrain Petroleum Company shall have preference. I asked Dame for an explanation of this preference, but he said he did not think the question would occur as the accomodation was sufficient for six people or eight in an emergency. 7 . %v S 'X &lt; V-' - 2 - Regarding the question of other doctors than the Mission putting their patients in the hospital he said that they would admit petients into the hospital to be treated there by other doctors provided that the doctors were properly qualified. I enclose copies of two letters from Dr. Dame. Yours sincerely, Lieut. Colonel G-. Loch, H. B. M*s Political Agent. Bahrain. i rsCopy of letter from Qr. L. P. Dame, dated, Bahrain, Feb. 9, 1934 to Mr. C.D.Belgrave. It just occured to me to remind you that in the pest few years we have taken care of seaman Skeet TT Collins TT Cat ham Mrs. Steele Mrs. Meikle A meohanic from Bin Saoud T s Air Port in Darein An Engineer from a B.I.steamer A Britisher from Zobeir and Busrah who was looking for a job here Major Holmes Mrs. Hendry, and others, when we really had no proper faci lities for European patients. In fact we have never turned a patient away and when necessary turned our own home into a nursing home. Now that we shall have facilities for such needs, there need be no doubt but that every person who wishes a place in the pro posed nursing home will be accomodated.Copy of letter dated Feby. 6, 1934, from Dr. L. ?. Dame, to Mr. C. D. Belgrade. Thank you for your letter of Feb. 5th. its you know the new Nursing Home is primarily for the American and European staff and their families of the Bahrain Petroleum Company. Aside from that we had not made any plans for an extensive European clientele but to have a place for the occasional patient such as we have had now and then. It is not the usual custom for doctors who are not on the staff of a hospital to have patients in that hospital. My medical friends at home can only have patients in the hospital where they are on the staff. This is for very evident reasons. Every hospital is jealous of its rating and reputation and cannot afford to have men of a lower standard than they wish to maintain on the staff. Let me atonce state that if you should become ill — which Cod forbid — and wished to have Dr. Holmes take care of you in the Nursing Home you would be granted that privilege But for us now to commit ourselves for the next twentyfive years more or less that every doctor, male or female, who comes to Bahrain should be granted the opportunity of taking his or her patients to the Nursing Home^is more than we can promise at present.We are here to serve this oomnunity to the best of our ability and we hope not to fall short in that. In this particular instance therefore we would rather not commit our selves unreservedly. Much will depend on the individual, his qualifications as a doctor, and to some extent his country of origin, — be it Europe, ^meriEca, Syria , Egypt or what. I should be glad to come and see you some time soon to talk this matter over more fully. I expect to leave for gutter Friday afternoon or eveningPROGRAM c~\ of the CEREMONY of the OFFICIAL OPENING of the American Mission Nursing Bungalow Tuesday Jan. 15, 1955. 5:15 P.M. Chairman Rev. G. D. Van Peursem The Official Opening by Lt. Col Loch Entrance into Bungalow Words in behalf of the Bahrain Petroleum C Mr. F. Davies Words in behalf of the American Mission Dr. L. P. Dame Dedicatory Prayer Rev. G. D. Van Peursem Tea &amp; Inspection of the Bungalow.* ■ '• ■I To the European Community of Bahrain Dear • Va 'vvum) A-Ov •• The Ame ssion Hospital Bahrain Island, Persia May 6, 1 We understand that there has been some discussion about the charges in the European Nursing Bungalow. Unfounded rumors of excessive charges have come to our attention. In accordance with arrangements and agreements made with Chief Medical Officer H.M.S. Shoreham and with the Bahrain Petroleum Company we have decided upon the following as our basic charges for members of the European Community of Bahrain who do ei-^come under the above arrangements. The food charge is determined by the Bahrain Petroleum Company inasmuch as all food arrangements are made by them. The Nursing item cowers such things as light, heat, refri geration^ laundry etc. Special ex$ra charges will be made 6or operations, laboratory examinations and special treatments according to their nature. Physicians fees Food Nursing Rs. 7 per person per day. Rs. 8 per person per day. Rs. 4 per person per day. Total Rs. 19 per person per day Sincerely yours, (J) * hJ • For the American Mission Hospitalsssion Hospital Bahrain Island, Persian GuLFj u ]_y 4^ 19^ ^ To the European Community of Bahrain: Dear In accordance to a letter just received from Mr. E. A. Skinner, manager of Bahrain Petroleum Company Ltd., I have been informed that the charge for food in the Nursing Bungalow will be 60 cents per meal or approximately Rs. 5- 0—0 per day. The total charge per day will then be Rs. 16 per day instead of Rs. 19 per day as indicated in my last notice. Sincerely yours. UV w M'.-Dtj—* for the A mericam Mission Hospitals jif- AmThe Bahrein petroleum Company limited His Britannic Majesty*s Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir: The Bahrein Petroleum Company is building a Class I Hospital in the New Camp and during this year will build Class II and Class III annexes which will be run in conjunction with the Class I Hospital. This me^ns that by the end of 1937 the Company will handle medical care and hospitalization for all classes of its Employees and that present arrangements with the Port Doctor and the Mission will be discontinued. This brings up the question of what shall be done with the European Nursing Home donated to the Mission by the Company ^nd a discussion with you on the subject is indicated which we will thank you to arrange at your convenience. Yours very truly, /I G. N. R. SMITH Chief Local Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITEDCONFIDENTIAL. D.O. No* 1135 / 2/9 D?; ted the 11th May 1937. My dear Belgrave, A V jT ¥ Will/you please refer to your demi-official letter Jr No* 1073-5*F dated the 18th February 1934 in which you mention an agreement between the Bahrain Petroleum Com pany and the Mission* I shall be grateful if I can see this agreement if you have a copy In your possession. 2* On the 4th of this month Doctor Storm and Mr. van Peursem called to see me about the Mission Hospital nd they apparently were exercised in their minds regarding the possibility of an agreement, written or verbal, re garding tne retention of the building in which the Bmi- rain Petroleum Company employees were housed for the ex clusive accommodation of the Europeans. I told them that I would look up the records but I knew of no verbal under taking. I have examined my records but can find no trace of an agreement other than the one noted above* There may be some undertaking in connection with the gift of land from His Highness about which I have no information. It would seem that the Mission are being given the present accommodation reserved for Europeans and the Bahrain Petro leum Company employees and that they contemplate using the accommodation for high class Asiatic patients. I am assur ed by Doctor Storm that they would reserve two or three- beds in some part of the Mission for the exclusive use of Buropeans/- C. Dairyuipie Belgrave, Esquire, C.B.L., Adviser to the Bahrain Government, BahrainEui’opekns and also that a scale of fees vail be instituted which would conform es far as possible witri the financial resources of the patients concerned# 6# I talcing the matter up with Colonel Fowle because although the Mission have stated that they will have beds available for Europeans and the Bahrain Petroleum Company have also said that if they have accommodation available they will not be unwilling to admit Europeans from the civilian community, I consider that as far as the official civilians, both European and Anglo-Indian, are concerned Ca&gt; {(ul m accommodation must not only be available but should be/re served for their exclusive use in case of necessity* 4. The question of accommodation for riavai Eatings and Royal Air Force personnel must also be considered, and al though it is possible that in uhe event of a Squadron coming to Bahrain the Air Authorities will make medical arrange ments for their own men which would probably include accom modation for Havel Ratings, it will be some four or five years before this happens and In the mean time we must clearly have some sort of hospit&gt;^i accommodation ready in case of necessity* 5# With regard to the non-official civilians, an ever increasing community, I feel that although perhaps there is no actual obligation to provide medical facilities we shouli be wrong in not making every effort to afford relief in case of sickness and I shall be glad if I may have your views on this point. Has this problem been considered in connection with any meaicsi scheme that the Bahrain Govern ment may be contemplating? Yours sincerely,' D.O. He.1221. , . The 20th Hay 1937. i \ A Captain Hie ■:inbothan has asked n@ to tell you that he is very sorry he cannot settle the question of t he nursing home with you before :*r* Skinner leaves - as he has to leave at mid-day to -ay for Sharjah.\m If V- 1 1 / D. 0. 369/SF. Bahrain, May 19, 1937. ''•w. Dear Hiekinbotham, f N 1 Reference your D.O. Mo. 1133-2/9 dated llth lay 1937. 2. I saw the agreement between the Bahrain petroleum Company, Limited and the American Mission in Dr. Dame ! s house in 1934. I have no copy of it and I cannot now recollect the wording of the part referring to patients other than Bahrain p Petroleum Company patients, but my letter D.O.1073 was written before I had seen the agreement. I am quite sure that it was clearly specified that the Mur sing Home could be used by the European popula tion besides employees of the Bahrain Petroleum Company. I suggest that the Mission or the Bahrain Petroleum Company should be a'sked to show us a copy of the agreement or that part of it referring to v* patients other than the Bahrain. Petroleum Company. ^ 3. The only correspondence I have y referring to the matter is my letter No. D.O. 1017 dated February 5, 1934 to Dr. Dame copy of which I enclose and a long letter from him dated February 6, 1934, mostly about other medical matters out of which I give two extracts referring to the Nursing Home. 'As you know the new Nursing Home is primarily for rhe Americanand European staff and their families of the Bahrain Petroleum Company. Aside from that we had not made any plans for an extensive European clientele but to have a place for an occasional patient such as we have had now and then. \ /1-3- wm—mmmmmmm imM —— !t It is not the usual custom for doctors who are not on the staff of a hospital to have patients in that hospital. My medical friends at hpme can only have patients in the hospital where they are on the staff. This is for very evident reasons. Every hospital is jealous 01 its rating and reputation and cannot afford to have men of a lower standard than they wish to maintain on the staff. 'Let me at once state that if you should become ill - which God forbid - and wished to have Dr. Holmes take care of you in the Nursing Home you could be granted that privilege. But for us now to commit our selves for the next twenty-five years more or less that every doctor, male or female, who comes to Bahrain should be granted the opportunity of taking his or her patients to the Nursing Home is more than we can promise at present. 'We are here to serve this community to the best of our ability and we hope npt to fall short in that. In this particular instance therefore we would rather not commit ourselves unreservedly. Much will depend on the individual, his qualifications as a doctor, and to some extent his country of origin - be it Europe^ America, Syria Egypt or what. I should be glad to come and see you some time soon to talk this matter over more fully. ” 'As regards charges in the European Nursing Home, the charge for an obstetrical case including all medical and nursing service but excluding room and board will be as ^ou/-. Other charges have not yet been decided upon but will probably approximate the rates ior similar services in India, copy of which I enclose.' ^ V I also enclose copy of .-another note from Dr. Dame dated February 9, 1.934. 4. I think myself that an arrangement for accomodation in the Bahrain Petroleum Company’s hospital for European non-Bapco patients would be more appreciated and far more valuable than an arrangement for beds in any part of the Mission Hospital.5. Regarding the Bahrain Government hospital which is to be built; it is not at present proposed to build a European ward though this may perhaps materialise some day. Yours sincerely, Captain T. Hickinbotham, I.A., Political Agent, Bahrain.Copy. F\ D.O. 1017/S.F, Bahrain, February 5, 1934. Bear Dr. Dame, I should be interested if you would give^ me some information as to now your new European Ward at the Mission hospital is going to be run. I should like to know roughly what sort of fees would be charged on European patients, men or women, who use the hospital, apart from the medical fees and what arrangements would be made for cases who are being attended by the Government doctor. It is possible in the future, if finances permit, that the Government will employ its own lady doctor, a project that has been under consideration for several years in which case it might be advisable for her European patients to receive hospital treat ment, a similar position might arise in the case of patients of the Agency Surgeon who now aets also as &gt; the Bahrain Government doctor. What vail happen in these cases? I had meant to write to you before on this subject but have been rather busy ov/ing to the anniversary celebrations. Yours faithfully, Sd/ 6. Dalrymple Belgrave. Dr. L.P.Dame, M.D., Mason Memorial Hospital, Bahrain.Bahrain, February 9, 1934, Dear Belgrave, It iust occurred to me to remind you that in the past few years we have taken care of Seaman Sheet, ,f Collins, ' Gatham, Mrs. Steele, Mrs, Meikle, A mechanic from Bin Saoud^ airport in Darein, An Engineer from a B.I, steamer, A Britisher from Zobeir and Busrah who was looking for a job Bahrain- here, Major Holmes, Mrs, Hendry, and others, when we really had no proper facilities for European patients. In fact we have never turned a patient away, and where necessary turned our own home in to a nursing home. Now that we shall have facilities for such needs, there need be no doubt but that every person who wishes a place in the proposed nursing home will be accomodated. Yours sincerely, Sd/ L. P. Dame.. 0 • No * 1264-3/iJ Dated the S7th May 1337, dear Smith, \ T/ V K Will you piefc.de refer to your letter Ho. PA-155 of the 1st April 1^3? concerning the new hospital vmic'a the Bahrain Petroleum Company is building at the label* g* There is nov, a certain amount of doubt as to whet is going to happen to the Luropeun Hursing Tome whicu tlie Company very kindly uoiiated to the Mission# ancl I should, oe very ..retelul if you could let me have a • 'Opy oi the- ment between the Company and the Alter teen Mission concerning the transfer of the hospital over to then:..* Tne reason why I should like to cnis is that we are not quit© certdn whether it was clearly specified t.as t tne Cursing dome could be used, oy th# Auropean population besides toe employees 01 the Bahrain Petroleum Company. Accordingly once we get this definitely settled up we shall knew now wu ^ta.no wi.tn ta^ rhifsliig home as regards the n©w cnnaitlons, since due Mission, as you fc.r^ a&gt;are, are contemplating using the accommodation I'iow maue vacant by the transfer ,ot the Ba.hru^.n Pe ^roleuii eom- pahy employees to the new ho spit si, xor to© care of h.*,g*i class Asi&amp;tuc patients* The problem, tlxeref &gt;1 e, arises as to whe ther we are in any wt «ihbuL-o - u; -; - :'o..-. ,,, .. use of the European, Angle-Indi an end official eoamities two ox 4 three beus in cn© revised version of tiie Sux*sing uorne* 3. If you would very kindly, therefore, let me see the exact wording of the Agre©ment# -* should tnen be in a position to go xnto Kj io case more t&gt;ikOrougn^-y* A* v* • ii* cisuth, Is Quire, Chief bocal Hepresentutive, The Bahrain Petroleum Company limited, Bahrain* yours sincerely,■ — ?!??SSI r !D.O. No - ,71 tz6 Assistant The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to:- C. Dalrymple Belgrave, Esquire, C.B*E., Adviser to the Bahrain Government, Bahrain, J 7 -l ' Mi and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document (s). The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulp. Dated... . May .1937.. Reference to previous correspondence Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Demi-official letter No. 1264-2/9 dated the 27th M*': r 1937 to the Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, Bahrain. Subject. Transfer of the European Nursing Home to the Mission by the Bahrain Petroleum Company. 1—THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED / -I Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf May 30, 1937 PA-225. His Britannic Majesty , s Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir: . t-i-.r *r * , ^ S Please refer to your D.O.No.1264-2/9 of May 27th regarding the donation of the Nursing Home to the Mission by The Bahrein Petroleum Company limited. We are enclosing a copy of the original agreement of January 22, 1934 as requested. When Bapco decided to build their own hospital, Mr. Skinner mentioned to Colonel Loch that the company would like to cut off entirely from the Mission and that the Mission would probably want to run the Nursing Home for high class Asiatics. On Aoril 1. 1937 our letter No. PA-155 was written and as a result there Ls a conference at the Agency on April 28th at which were present Colonel 0. Loch, Captain T. Hickinbotham and Mr. E. A. Skinner. The memorandum covering this conference is enclosed. It is apparent that the Mission will not be able to operate the Nursing Home for Europeans without outside assistance. Sincerely yours. C. W. R. SMITH Chief Local Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITEDCOPY. i THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. January 22, 1934. Dr. L.P.Dame, The American Mission Hospitals, Manama, Bahrein. Dear Sir: The following will alter the terns under which you and your staff take care of the Bahrein Petroleum Company’s employees, as set forth in my letter of January 9, 1932:- 1. From January 1, 1934, the monthly retainer paid to the American Mission Hospitals, will be Rs. 400/-/- instead of Rs.200/-/-. This will cover all medical attention to Class I and Class II employees and their families 2. Will include medicines used. 3. Will afford these employees and their families the facilities of the American Mission Hospitals and medical staff. 4. Will cover visits necessary to our various houses in Manama or to the camp at Jebel Dukhan. 5. It is understood that during Dr. Dame’s absence either the other members of the American Missionary staff or D r. Holmes will care for our employees and their families. It is agreed that if the American Mission Hospitals will import a first class American nurse, the Company will raise the above retainer Rs.250/- which would make a total amount of Rs.650 monthly, provided that such nurse will always be 'on call” to take care of European and American employees in the Nursing Home being built for that purpose. It is understood that the amount of Rs.650 monthly is for an indefinite period. If at any time it is not satisfactory because of exceptional services rendered, an additional amount may be charged by mutual agreement. If the above terms are satisfactory to you, please sign two copies of this letter in the space designated below, and return to this Office. The terms as listed above are satisfactory to me. Yours very truly, A SKINNER, Manager, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LTD, 3. P. DAME, AMERICAN MISSION HOSPITALS. Note:- Class I employees - Europeans and Americans. Class II ” - All other imported employees,mostly Indian &amp; IraqiBAHREIN, April 28, 1957 #• „ir THE BAHREIN PETROLEDM COMPANY LIMITED i NURSING HOME DONATED TO MISSION BY BAPGO Discussion with - Colonel G* Loch Captain T* Hickinbotham Mr. E. A. Skinner When the building and equipment were donated to the Mission, it was understood by the Political Agent, Dr. Dame and Mr. Skinner that it would be run for Europeans only. Bapco are now installing their own hospital facilities. It will be impossible for the Mission, without assistance, to maintain this Nursing Home for Europeans. While Bapco are willing to take Manama residents temporarily they are not willing to obligate themselves to do this indefinitely because the Manama population is growing and will continue to grow. With the number of European residents at present, which will soon be augmented by the Residency personnel and additional R.A.E. people, Bapco facilities would be inadequate. Colonel Loch appreciated the Company’s offer to take care of Mwnwmw residents temporarily (it is suggested that the rates be nominal) but at the same time stated that Bapco had no obligation whatever to take care of outsiders now that they are running an independent hospital. Several solutions of the problem were mentioned and Captain Hickinbotham stated that he would take up the matter with the Political Resident so that Menamfl Europeans will have independent hospital acc ommodations•30 # f On June the 1st I had a discussion with Dr.Storm concerning the future of the European Nursing Home, The point J_n question v/as the hospital accommodation for those members of the European community, the Anglo- Indian official community and possibly the Royal Air Force and. Navy who might fall ill in Bahrain and ^ind themselves without any form of hospital accommodation ready for them owing to the fact that since the Bahrain Petroleum Company have removed their entire hospitali sation to the Jabal there are now no beds ready in case of emergency for the above-named category. Dr. Storm was most willing to help and the only difficulty appear ed to be that the Mission Hospital are somewhat diffi- dent about mahing out any rigorous form of contract as this has been found occasionally in the past to be a little difficult for various reasons. We agreed, how ever, that there was no reason whatsoever why an under standing in writing should not be made between the Agency and the Mission concerning the welfare of the at present unprovided for community. The Nursing Home, I gather, is now meant for the use of the native patients but Dr. Storm told me that they have separate accommo dation in which they could always be sure of having three beds read,/ for any European invalid. The main difficul ties concerning this were that he did not want to be bound down by a rigid contract because, for example, as he is the only European member of the staff there would be no doctor of his class to look after an Euro pean in those short periods of his absence such as his tour and leave. He felt that if a contract was made the Mission would feel bound to arrange to have some doctor always ready at hand to tend for any hypothetical case. Similarly/-IASM **' 1 ■■■MM V\ [ 3 ' Similarly over the question of cooking for Europeans he w' icl that they would be prepared to do this out of their Gv.n kitchen with suitable charges of course and we agreed that should there be an epidemic when the number of patients would put an exceesive strain upon the cooking arrangements given the Mission no doubt some assistance could be/temporarily from the Agency or possibly some other establishment. We Dotn agreed tnat it was desirable to have this understanding put down in writing not because of any difficulties which eight arise in the present but because it would obviate so many difficulties and misunderstandings in the future. Possibly the understanding might be formulated on a basis such as this:- i,The Mission Hospital are prepared to have three separate beds ready at any time for the reception of any invalid from the European, official Anglo- Indian, Naval and Royal Air Force communities. •it is understood that should the number of patients place too greaw a strain upon the cooking arrange ments of the Mission then outside help will be given from the Agency or elsewhere. 3.It is again understood that the Mission are in no way bound to have an European doctor permanently to hand for the service of these invalids and should by ill chance any one fall sickduring the absence of, for example. Dr.Storm himself, then some other arrangement must be made for their medical attendance. 4,It is understood that a scale of fees will be pre pared which is commensurate with the class and wealth of the patient concerned. 5.This measure it is hoped is only to be a temporary one/-one until such time as, 'for example, Bahrain Government decide to add a 'ing to their proposed hospital for Europeans,etcetera patients or until there is a hospital installed for use of the British services 1 hich might he extended to look after also the European commu nity. Once a general understanding on this sort of basis hao been arrived at which without being contractually binding nevertheless ensures that there will always be accommodation for at least three of the Euro%an, etcetera community, the various problems in connection with the medical welfare of the community will have gone a long way towards a solution. 'Dictated on 2nd June 1937.Ho. 1409-2/9 Foliticel Agency, Bahrein, the Slst June 19?7. To The Chief ho cal Representative, •The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, 3 .a il n .a I h i Dear Sir, yj&gt; ' Pleise refer to your letter Ho. PA-155 atted the 1st April 10S7. 2, At the altcaseion that was held I gathered tnat the Bahrain Petroleum Company would be prepared to aceom- «od&amp;te Europeans other than their own employees in their hospital should the necessity arise and should they have sufficient accommodation available. I have discussed the matter since then vilh the representatives of the Mission Hospital and with Colonel hooney, the Residency surgeon, Bushlro* I uxiderstand that the Mission JOS- oitai are prepared in emergency to accommodate Europeans but Colonvl Rooney has point-.d out to me that In ..is opinion the principal reason for sending persons to tne hospital is so that they may oc well looked atcr ana pro- ■ i 7 ■. i JL r S ■ ■ cl U *■ Cl at therefore, in ills opinion, I should anuc-..vour to come to sobs ^rrangck'ent with your Company as, although the stand ird of nursing in the Mission Hos pital is no doubt very high, it could not be considered to be us nigh as that in a hospital which has a European nursing staff. I will be gr; teful if you would let m: sn-r-v whether you c. n confirm the st-tement which I under stood to have been made at the discussion referred to above. Yours faithfully, Civ Capt£ in, Political Agent, Bahrain*THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, June 29, 1937. No.PA-298. His Britannic Majesty’s political Agent, Bahrein, Dear Sir, In reference to your letter No.1409-2/9 dated t -225 June 21, 1937, I wish to refer further to our letter PA and the mirnoran^um which was attached covering the discus sion. 'While Banco are willing to take Manana residents temporarily, they are not willing to obligate themselves to do this indefinitely ”. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited can possibly accommodate the Manama residents, but reserves the right to consider each case individually in accordance with The Bahrein Petroleum Company’s position at the time. Yours very truly, / G. W. R. SMITH, Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED./n ,&lt;f ’ No.1493-2/9. Political Agency, Bahrain, the 2nd July 1937# To The Chief Local Representative, The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited, Bahrain* Dear Sir, With reference to your letter No* PA-298 dated the 29th June 1937, I should like to thank you for your assistance in this matt-r which has been greatly appreciated* Yours faithfully,No. ' 8° 7~ /o Of 1361 Office of the Adviser to the Government, Bahrain Dated, Ramadhan 19, 1361 September 30, 1942 H. B. M's Political Agent, Bahrain. Memorandum: - Ar I enclose, for your informa-tion, copies ol corres-y pondence with the State Engineer, Bahrain,and State Medical Officer regarding the hot water supply at the Government Hospital. The hospital has been continuously used by British forces for sorae weeks and we have had large numbers of in-patients as well as out-patients. The new European Ward opens tomorrow and the number ot in-patients will increase. The State Medical Officer contends that s ould the hospital be used for wound cases the prevision of an adequate hot water supply is essential. At present cases of this tyre have not occurred but if there appears to ce a nossibilitv of the Bahrain Government Hospital becoming a Base Hospital I think the question of obtaining replace ments for the boiler might be reconsidered. Adviser to the Government.13S Copy of a memorandum No ,Sl!I0/8/61 dated 26th May 1942 from the State Engineer, Bahrain, to the State Medical Officer, Bahrain. I strongly recommed duplicating your large Beeston Boiler, i.e. the sections only, tanks, etc., are not required. The cost today would be approximately im. 1,100/- d.d. Bahrain, . Owing to the very high calorific value of the z ocal fuel, and our operating difficulties, a spare is necessary. This would enable us to isolate a boiler once a month for inspection and cleaning. If you agree I will order the section; delivery should be affected (circumstances permitting) in six to eight months.5 ? -V. Copy of a memorandum No.4/7/71 datod B8th l' ^ from the State Medical Officer, Bahrain, to the b a Ehgineer, Bahrain, Re: duplicating of Beeston Boiler for the Bahrain Government Hospital, I certainly agree. Will you very kindly ask the Adviser for sanction? I presume the out-patient hoiler is too small to use for reserve purposes. Thank you very much. S.Z,Copy of memorandum No. AGB/43/61 dated 30th May, 1942, from the State Engineer, Bahrain, to the Adviser to the Government, Bahrain, enclosed is a letter from Dr. Snow in connection with the large heating boiler at the Hospital. Dr. Snow agrees to the proposition, so may the purchase be sanctioned, please? Demands for hot water, particularly during the winter months will increase (R.A.F. Ward etc.) and the small dispensary boiler is not of sufficient capacity to deal with the whole supply.Copy of memorandum No.1006-10 dated 4th June 1942 from the Adviser to the Government, Bahrain, to tne State Engineer, Bahrain (copy to the State Medical Officer, Bahrain). , Reference your memorandum No. AGB/43/61 dated 30th kay, 1942, as it appears that a large heating boiler at the hopital is necessary I agree to attempt being made to obtain it, it will be debitable against Medical Budget of 1362.» Copy of memorandum No. 1630.10 dated 8th September 1942, from the Adviser to the Government, Bahrain, to the State Engineer, Bahrain (copy to the State Medical Officer, Bahrain). 42 Reference your memorandum No.AGB/84/61 dated 24th Shaaban, 1361. I do not consider that a new boiler can be classified as 'essential to the war effort'. It would be possible to run the hospital without a hot water supply as is done in quite a lot of hospitals i.e. The Berout University Hospital. We have been asked to reduce require ments of shipping space to the absolute minimum and the test is now to be whether or not the cargo is 'essential to the war effort'. In this case it is not absolutely essential. 3.Z.Copy 0 f memorandum No. 17-2/61 dated 10th September 1942 from the State Medical Officer, Jaui ain, the Adviser to the Government, Bahrain,(copy to the State Engineer, Bahrain). Hot water supply in the Bahrain Go 1 //^ Hospital as 'essential to the war eifoi_t . with reference to your memorandum of . ove iqao +n the state Engineer re; future up-keep of the above water supply, the argument not only centres round^its use for war ^but its necessity during peace time, n h °spltel without continual hot ’water, immediately assumes^ secondary standard not only because of the diminished hygiene of Itaff and patients, but mainly through lack of its vital function combating wound sepsis. During war-time wo hp pn ha need 'and if this ever became an important Bo.se Hospital hot water would be of absolute prime importance in wound treatment, and lack of it would seriously affect the mortality of Septic cases. The question theraiorehl think hinges on the ultimate us or this Hospital .Yar.\ Ho,C/i,Sl£, Political Agency, s46 Vm / 1 Bab.rain ? the 6th October To The Adviser to the Goveif^'iontj Bahrain, Heferenee your memorandum Ho* ID07-10 dated oOth September 1942, received in r.y office on Ott; 0«-UV.:«r 1»42. I shall he interested to receive fren tirae -fee time statistics of oui~patienti and in-patients fr’on tiie British force® who have boon tTo^toO. at the Govcr^no-nt Hospital# I tliink it essential tnot the Hoonital should he ©quipped to he used as a iJase Hospital Xx necessity arises, so that wound cases can be given the best, possible treatment# I suggest therefore, that you should go 'for ward with the scheme to provide another boiler# bfC f Political Agent, Baiirain. - RaJ ? o •\ x r it/u Ttio Adviser to the Bahrain Government presents ills complir-iertts to:- His Britannic Majesty’s Political Bahrain. and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned note for information. Adviser’s Office, Manama, Bahr ain.. HO. ^ Dated, tune 28, 1943 Description of enclosure T T ane and date Subject■mHi ■■■ n 3 r \ n ^ £v3 Note on a meeting held at the Advisecrate on the afternoon of June SSnd to discuss hospital facilities for European civilian patients in Bahrain, Those present were: Mr. C. Dalrymple Belgrave, Dr. R.H.B. Snow, Dr. W,H. Siborm, Dr, I.M.A, Doeg, Dr. E. Barney and Miss N.M, Harbottle. Dr. P.W, Harrison was away from Bahrain. The Adviser told those present that he had called the meeting 'because the care of European civilian oases in the Government Hospital row presented a difficult problem® Two private wards existed in the Mens Hospital and also in the Womens Hospital. Those in the Mens Hospital were almost always full, being occupied by Naval, Army and Air Ebrce officers. In both hospitals adequate nursing staff to deal with European oases did not exist, the Indian women nurses in the “Womens Hospital were fully occupied with local patients and the R.A.F. nursing sisters on the Mens side worked only in the service wards. During the last year about a dozen European civilian patients had been admitted, these included members of merchant ships crews and patients from other stations in the Gulf. In the past Awali hospital took in some cases from Manama but owing to the expected arrival of several hundreds of additional Bahrain Petroleum Company employees, in a month or two, the Awali hospital could not be depended upon to have beds available for non Company patients during the next twelve months. The whole question Md therefore become somewhat urgent. During the discussion that followed it appeared that no alternative hospital for European civilian patients existed in Manama. The Mission Hospital annex which used to be used as a European nursing home was now used for Indian and Arab patients and no regular facilities existed there for dealing with Europeans.Tiie possibility of opening a European nursing home was discussed 0 It was suggested that one of the flats in the Gro^rernment Hospital would he entirely suitable for such a purpose having the advantage of being adjacent to operation theatres, X-Ray room and the existing European kitchen and provided with hot and cold water, European sanitation etc* This flat could contain two single bed wards and one two bed ward. Additional European nursing staff would be essential. Such an arrangement would entail building new quarters for the doctor or matron who vacated the flat and provision of quarters for the extra staff. It was pointed out that the hospital belonged to the Bahrain Government, an Arab Government, and that the exclusive use of a part of it by the non Government European community would probably not meet ■yyi-fch approval. It might be possible to have a sped al ward run on different lines to the rest of the hospital where the fees would be such as to make it unlikely that any but a very few Arab patioats would wish to make use of it. The two service wards in the Mens Hospital were a war time measure, part of the costs of construction had been met by the R.A.F. Authorities who also supplied the European nursing stafj^ The provision of these wards was approved by His Highness The Shaikh as a contribution towards the war effort. The wards in which European civilian patients have been accommodated in the two hospitals are not suf ficiently separated from other parts of the hospital to entirely obviate the possibilities of cross infec tion neither has separate staff been available for nursing European patients.V V *&gt; V, • dtb The suggestion that there should he a small European nursing home close to the G-overnment Hospital was discussed. Such an institution would have the use of all the pa hospital facilities such as X-Ray, theatres etc., for which the usual fees would he paid. Future hospital requirements in Bahrain were considered, both immediate and post war. It was assumed that the personnel at the Naval Base would, not decrease and that the staff of the Petroleum Concessions Limited might increase. No information was available about future R.A.F. plans in Hoharraq especially whether or not any form of hospital was contemplated there. It was agreed that there was need for some kind of nursing home, run ©f on the lines of a cottage hospital^ in Bahrain especially if the Navy continued to depend upon local hospital resources after the war. Such an institution might be valuable not only to people in Bahrain but to Europeans in other Gulf stations. While considering whether such a scheme would be financially supported by the © various firms and institutions in Bahrain it was pointed out that firms, if they contributed, would probably wish any such **■» scheme to include provision for itoep-easi staff. The possibility of two rates of fees was examined, the meeting was informed that the Mission Hospital Annexe was now being frequently used by this class of patients but the Mission had no financial arrangement with any of the firms for regular medical attendance etc.- 4 - The great difficulty &lt;*f putting up any building during the war was emphasised and the impossibility of obtaining fittings etc. It was suggested that there were two problems to consider; that of the immediate future which had become pressing because the Awali hospital could no longer be depended upon to take in non Company patients and that of the future, after the a war. It was finally agreed that the European firms should be approached as to their views on the desirability of considering a scheme for a European nursing home in Bahrain. S.Z.MHMi n l Acting Acfviser to the Bahrain Government presents his compliments to ; His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrain. and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned documents, for information. Adviser s Office, No Manamah, Bahrain. Dated January 15, 1946. Description of enclosure. Name and date Subject. Reference to previous correspondence :—nsiMi ,yi; tUII J k, &amp; GOVERNMENT OF BAHRAIN. MEDICAL DEPARTMENT. •m A THE BAHHAIH GOVERNMENT NURSING HOME. m The Services* Inpatient War Scheme 1942 — 1946 in the Bahrain Government Hospital will terminate January 15th: 1946. From this date European civilian inpatients can he admitted. Until the full nursing home scheme is established, the existing regime as provided for the Services will continue under a Bahrain Government Hospital staff. The situation will be revised every six months until con- -ditions are stable and full provision can be made for all needs. Present accommodation will be:~ For Men. A general ward of 12 beds. One private ward. For Women. One private ward in the Women’s Hospital* Fees. A charge of Rs.17/8 a day will be made for each private w§rd, and Rs.15/- a day for the general ward. These are inclusive charges covering all overhead costs, food, laundry, and all treatment except , Operations, Confinements, X4.Rays and special Laboratory tests* It is hoped that all patients will make allowances for im- -perfections in the present temporary arrangements. The women’s ward i*sr£&gt;t ideal,and the nursing staff will be mainly non-European. European doctors will however be directly responsible for their patients,and similarly a Matron and Sisters for the supervision of the nursing. Late 1 5 M. 1945 The/Adviser to the Bahrain Government. MRT&lt;No.1492-2/9 Political Agency, Bahrain, The 13th May, 1946. To The Officer in charge, Cable &lt;&amp; Wireless Limited, Bahrain. Dear Sir, With reference to your letter No.2A/64 dated the 25th April, 1946, the question of further equipping the Victoria Memorial Hospital is s ill under consideration, but it is agreed that in the present circumstances you would be well advised to make use of the European ward in the Bahrain Government Hospital. 2. It is by no means certain that Dr. Steele will be leaving Bahrain this year and so the question of appointing a successor to him has not yet arisen. Yours faithfully, for Political Agent, Bahrain.MRT S. M. 0., BAHRAIN The Nursing Home inpatients are at present averaging two patients a day in the winter, and probably six in the hot weather* One European doctor and three Indian doctors are adequately caring tor them* From time to time consultants are called in* The existing routine is therefore at present satisfactory* Most Manama business firms have appro^hed me about inpatient facilities for their European staff* Messers: B.O.A.C* have also raised the question of their Anglo-Indian staff who can be admitted here to other private wards but with difficulty, owing to a waiting list for them* I am willing to undertake to fulfill their requests, or any other, but I have pointed out that I would be reluctant if it would embarrass relationships as regards the long standing Committments which many firms have with the Agency Surgeons*copy of a letter No, 3044/CA dated the 29th March, 1946, from Air Vice Marshal Strafford, I am desired by Sir Geoffrey to ask you to convey a suitable expression of thanks to His Highness and the officials Bahrain Re:e it No..S3.^.Date■■■■■■■■ Fron Air Vice Marshal &gt;i. C« , ■■■■■■■■■■■■■■■ CB. t33FG . 'V A.ir He a dqu a r te r s, Royal Air Puree, Iraq Command. Reference : 30UU/GA 29th. March, 1946. ^ . I would like to record our thanks for the many klndneoosB and the help which your representatives have extended to the R, A.F. in the Bahrein ut .t' Hospi tal mid to our Nuroing Sisters at the Government Rest Bouse* I would he grateful ’if you would have conveyed to His Highness the Shaikh of Bahrein a personal message convey 4 ng my thanks for his kindness and generosity in providing accommodation for the R* . personnel in the State Hospital and for the nursing Sisters at the^Government Rest House# This has been a valuable contribution to the allied war effort and the as latanee of His Highnes' the Shaildi of Bahrein in this connection has been much appreciated. My Principal nodical Of: .leer visited Bahrein in early December, 194:3? and made certain arrangements with the concurrence of the Political Agent, and since the 15th# of January the Service patients have been moved into Station Sick Quarters, Muharraq. I would, also like to take this opportunity of mentioning with gratitude the great assistance that Dr# R. Snow has been to the R.A.F. Medical Officers and Nursing Bisters, and the help Mrs# Belgrave has always given to our Nursing Sisters. I Sir Geoffrey Prior, / The Hon. the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bu shire. \ A Copy to The Political Agent, Bahrein, ^ s 6&gt; I $ ?D* 0* No*1563-2/9 19th May 9 1946. r- My dear Belgrave, I have been asked by Air Vice Marshal S.C. Strafford 9 C.B., C.B.ii., D.F.C., Air Officer Commanding, R.A.F .9 Iraq Command, to convey his grateful thanks to Dr. H. Snow for the great assistance rendered by him to the R.A.F. Medical Officers and Nursing Sisters throughout their stay in Bahrain* Air Vice Marshal Strafford also writes to thank Mrs* Belgrave for the help she has so consistently given to the R.A.F. Nursing Sisters during their time here. 2 . I should be grateful if you would kindly convey these messages to Dr. Snow and Mrs. Belgrave. Yours sincerely, C. Dalrymple Belgrave, Esq., C.B.E*, Adviser to the Government of Bahrain, Bahrain* CJ, Translation of letter dated 21st Jamad Al-Thani ) 1365 (22nd May, 194-6) from His Highness the Ruler of Bahrain to the Political Agent, Bahrain*. ' \h \ * y I have received your kind’^Tiffter No.69-2/9 dated 20th May, 194-6, (19th Jamad Al-Thani, 1365) and am pleased to learn of your good health and happiness. You have kindly said that the Air Vice Marshal S.C. Strafford, Officer Commanding R.A.F., Iraq Command, has asked you to convey his sincere thanks to me for my assistance during the war years in providing accommodation in the Hospital, and for the attendance! of the doctors and nurses. Your Excellency, we considered it our duty towards our dear freiend the Great British Government and as loyal friends it tr incumbent on us to give our assistance. We pray to God that we may all tread in the path of righteousness and receive His benefits. I request you to convey to -few my sincere thanks for his kind appreciation and ~wishr*fafe jP*' fa* health and prosperity. We request from God His lasting friendship and the strengthening of our relations and friendship with His Majesty the King of Great Britain and kis Government.Tha Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to :&lt; The Hobble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf 9 Bushire, and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentiond document^ Thb Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf Date 30th -1946.. Reference to previous correspondence: Demi-official letter No.1651-13/3*3#17 dated the 24th Aprils 1946 from Mr* C*J* Pelly* O.B.E.j I*C*S** to Lt* Col* A*C* Galloway, O.B*E*, Political,A^ent, Bahrain. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject, Translation of letter jdated 21st Jamad Al-Thani f 1365 (22nd May, 1946) from His Highness the Ruler of Bahrain, to the Political Agent, j Bahrain.to afsli^es^e SlK ’bSh, to the Political Agent, Bahrain. ^ j I have received your kind letter No.69-2/9 dated 20th May, 1946, Cl9th Jamad Al-Thani, 1365) and am pleased to learn of your good health and happiness, You have kindly said that the Air Vice Marshal S.C. Strafford, Officer Commanding R.A.F., Iraq Command, has asked you to convey his sincere thanks to me for my assistance during the war years in providing accommodation in the Hospital, and for the attendance of the doctors and nurses. Your Excellency, we considered it our duty towards our dear friend the Great British Government and as loyal friends it was incumbent on us to give our assistance. We pray to God that we may all tread in the path of righteousness and receive i^s benefits. I request you to convey to Air Vice Marshal Strafford my sincere thanks for his kind appreciation and my wishes for his health and prosperity. We request from God His lasting friendship and the strengthening of our relations and friendship with His Majesty the King of Great Britain and his Government. c “AV?- GOVERNMENT OF BAHRAIN. MEDICAL DEPARTMENT. 13 JUNE 1946 Daring the next six months the present system will remain unchanged* H/ An extra change will however have to be made for Penicillin owing to its present cost, and the monthly air freight rates# y Messersi dray Mackenzie Ltd&gt;# ^ Messerss 3« 0# A# 0* Ltd;. .Messers: Cable &amp; Wireless Ltdj. ^ Messers: A# 1# 0. C# (S.l.) Ltd;« Messers: Eastern Bank Ltd;* Messerst Imperial Bank of Iran Ltd;# Messers: P* C« L# Ltd;# r the Adviser to the Bahrain Government# Sssim *- H.S.K's Folitia&amp;I Agent, Bahrein. MHT.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000291_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1066</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000291</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1066</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 2/9 European Wards in Bahrain'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1934/1946</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-09-10T16:30:20</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (63 folios)</extent><extent>The papers in the file are arranged chronologically.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 65; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 2-64; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled, and are located in the same position as the main sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains correspondence between the Adviser to the Government of Bahrain, the Political Agent at Bahrain, the American Mission Hospital, and Bahrain Petroleum Company (BAPCO). The correspondence regards the transfer of the European Nursing Home to the American Mission; the opening in January 1935 of the American Mission Nursing Bungalow; the BAPCO hospital; and fees and care for European civilians in hospital in Bahrain.Copies of correspondence between the State Medical Officer and the State Engineer at Bahrain are also included in the file.The file contains some correspondence in Arabic and English, with the Ruler of Bahrain, Shaikh Salmān bin Ḥamad Āl Khalīfa.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>King of Bahrain</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Adviser to the Government of Bahrain</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>American Mission Hospital, Bahrain</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Bahrain Petroleum Company</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Hospitals</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000291#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>