<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0002fc_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T22:54:05.434Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">No. 1%^ -4/4 To © Po 1 it ic a 1 /.gency, B&amp;hrain, The 19th Augubt,1943. I The Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, BUSH IRE. MEMORANDUM. X enclose herewith, in duplicate, the budget estimates for this Agency for the year 1944-45 for Political Agent, Bahrain0. A. C. 19-A. (See Article 186-A, C. A. C., Vol. t) Department or Office, political Agency, Bahrain. Statement of details of provision proposed for pay of Officers for the year 19^4 -19 45 Noth 1.—Voted and Non-voted items should be separately shown. Note 2.—In the case of temporary establishments, authority under which they are entertained should be quoted. Note 3.—Numbers and amount of provision should agree with the entries in the estimate form. Note 4. —Names need not be given in the case of officers whose names are omitted from pay bills. Dated of MFP—996 Audit—(M-1606)—6-11-39—25,000. 19 Signature of Officer Designation of Officer-g 0 . /&lt;&gt;3 L C. A. C. 19-A, (See Article 18S-A, C. A. C., Vot I.) K- iDec X - ^ r ■■. to rgfcfc« Department or Office. Officers Po 1 it 1ca 1 Ag ency, Bahrain, Statement of details of provision proposed for pay of for the year 19 ^ ,-19, ^ . Note 1.—Voted and Non-voted items should be separately shown. Note 2.—In the case of temporary establishments, authority under which they are entertained should be quoted. Note 3.—Numbers and amount of provision should agree with the entries in the estimate form. Note 4.—Names need not be given in the case of officers whose names are omitted from pay bills. Dated f S C of ^0^ MFP—996 Audit—&lt;M-1606)-^6-11-39—25,000. 19^. Signature of Officer Designation of Officer / ^ Oc ffL r 0 Ifr.lr'o al Agent, BAHRAIN.-* CONDITIONS. 1. The Company or any Telegraph Company or Government Telegraph Administration, by whom this telegram is or would in the ordinary course of the telegraphic service be forwarded, may decline to forward such telegram althou~ 1 ' it has been received for that purpose ; but in such case the amount paid fo* transmission will be refunded to the sender at his request. 2. Neither the Company nor any Telegraph Company, or Government Telegraph Administration, by whom this telegram is or would in the ordinary course of the telegraphic service be forwarded, nor any of their respective officers or servants shall be liable to make compensation for any loss, injury or damage arising or resulting from non-transmission or non-delivery of the telegram, or delayer error or omission in the transmission or delivery thereof, through whatever cause such non-transmission, non-delivery, delay, error, or omission shall have occurred even though occasioned by the neglect or default of such Company or Administration or any officer or servant in their employ. 3. This telegram shall be forwarded in accordance with the provisions of Vie International Telegraph Regulations and the provisions of such Regulations shall be deemed to be binding between the sender and this or any Telegraph Company or Government Telegraph Administration by whom this telegram is or would in the ordinary course of the telegraphic service be forwarded. 4. The above mentioned conditions also apply to telegrams tendered to or delivered by the Company by telephone, over a private line, or by any other means whatsoever. NOTE.—Code words used in the text of telegrams must not contain more than 5 letters. The use of accented letters is not permitted in code words. By International Regulations, the sender of a telegram is obliged to produce the code from which the text or part of the text in code has been compiled if requested by the office of origin. * If figures and groups of figures, including commercial marks containing figures and letters, are used in code telegrams directed to extra-European destinations, their number, reckoned in accordance with the Rules for charging, must not exceed one half of the number of chargeable words in the text and signature. Full information respecting code telegrams may be obtained from any of the Company’s Branches.No. 1463.: . . 7 * / . 4 A The Secretary to the Hoti’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to / The Political. Agent, Bahrain.^ The Political Agent, Kuwait. His Majesty’s Consul, Kerman. o 4 5 6 7 is Majesty’s Consul, Msn&amp;ar iADhr.j His Majesty’s Consul. Khorramshahr• His Majesty’s Consul-General, Ahwaz. is Majesty* s Consul, shiraz. and is directed to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents. British Residency and Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated Reference to previous correspondence: Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Copy of relevant extra for 194^ ,ct from Budget Bstiriates - 45 . ■' r, sa '.O . /TOTAL - BAflRAIH. y st:ph head . C T ‘XRG''’S 0 1 ACCOUNT ON DIPLOl -T.C ' &gt; CONH j Ar C.’/ T :VICA:S II r AN: _ A All;. j . 2 . Pay of IstaUlishments: U i;ec'ica] ests.Ul 1.shment. : .U. Allowances, Honoraria, etc. (TT) i ori /:•'e t 1;; o t jw -1-e i| p% 4,400 y ravcO 11 n' ; al l.o'i c.nce. Dearness allowance. B.5. Other Charges. 'Cota] . y 2,500 Hor^ital contjnr’encies and raeciicai ecuinment. ^ 1,600TO PREVENT MISTAKES ATTENTION IS CALLED TO THE IMPORTANCE OF LEGIBLE WRITING. Printed in England. J»ly. 1942 (50,000 pads.) CABLE AND WIRELESS (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND.) LIMITED No. Charge. OFFICE STAMP AND DATE. Clerk’s Name, No. and Circuit and Time forwarded. Offici?' “(OW- &lt; Instrucoons ItiAir &lt;/ \m0ua£&gt;' w I Instructions a 1 Time to be Words | Signalled. To Name Address BRIT C ONSUL BUSHIRE Actual expenditure upto 50th Septembe r Pay of Oil leers 21578 Ls tab lib Line nt 11168 Sumptuary allowance 1071 House rent 1815 Travelling allowance 6546 Dearness allowance 6619 Launch grant 4582 Central Contract - grant 817 Post and Telegrams 19816 Office allowance 9462 T61a1 Bahrain 83474 stop Special war expenditure Of f icers 5540 Establis hment 9269 - House rent 2475 Travelling allowance 2731 Dearness allowance 4490 Cont ingeneies 8513 Total 33018' stop' Dubai Hospital establi shmen t 2165 Dearness allowance 994 Hospital contingencies 346 Total 3505 POLIT iC AL raMMt Mat Mt ik*n a «y b« tof«a|d«d MbjMt to Mo contfitiom oriotod oa tack «t MU Iona ky •kick I (free to M boaak. Signa' :e of Sender. Address (Not to be telegraphed) Telephone No BAHRAIN] - ® P,T.O. i -x &lt;■ ’TT ^ \CONDITIONS. 1 . The Company or any Telegraph Company or Government Telegraph Administration, by whom this telegram is or would in the ordinary course of the telegraphic service be forwarded, may decline to forward such telegram although it has been received for that purpose ; but in such case the amount paid for transmission will be refunded to the sender at his request. 2 . Neither the Company nor any Telegraph Company, or Government Telegraph Administration, by whom this telegram is or would in the ordinary course of the telegraphic service be forwarded, nor any of their respective officers or servants shall be liable to make compensation for any loss, injury or damage arising or resulting from non-transmission or non-delivery of the telegram, or delay or error or omission in the transmission or delivery thereof, through whatever cause such non-transmission, non-delivery, delay, error, or omission shall have occurred even though occasioned by the neglect or default of such Company or Administration or any officer or servant in their employ. 3. This telegram shall be forwarded in accordance with the provisions of the International Telegraph Regulations and the provisions of such Regulations shall be deemed to be binding between the sender and this or any Telegraph Company or Government Telegraph Administration by whom this telegram is or would in the ordinary course of the telegraphic service be forwarded. 4. The above mentioned conditions also apply to telegrams tendered to or delivered by the Company by telephone, over a private line, or by any other means whatsoever. NOTE.—Code words used in the text of telegrams must not contain more than 5 letters. The use of accented letters is not permitted in code words. By International Regulations, the sender of a telegram is obliged to produce the code from which the text or part of the text in code has been compiled if requested by the office of origin. If figures and groups of figures, including commercial marks containing figures and letters, are used in code telegrams directed tc extra-European destinations, their number, reckoned in accordance with the Rules for charging, must not exceed one half of the number of chargeable words in the text and signature. Full information respecting code telegrams may be obtained from any of the Company's Branches.No.c&amp;C^ -4/4 POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN 4th October, 1944. Forwaraed, with complimentb ,to the Oecretary to the Hon'blt the Political Rebident in the Persian Gull, Bus hire for Political Agent,Bahrain.( No. 1843-77/8. ' 7 ' U BHIXIBK m&amp;JjMtim iHD TS OtmJIA® mBKil.g ^/7. Dated E7th Jiane, 1944. To # The Bonowatle the Political Resident in the Persian Oolt $ itohire. The Under Secretary to the Ooverrment of India, Ji&amp;ternal Affairs Department, MLMiM* sir. With reference to External Affairs Department latter Bo. 1036^44 dated the 15th April 1944, 1 have the honour to request Umt an annual alloteont of &amp;• 50C/* may Aindly he made to meet the cost of priced publications required for the use of this Besideacy and offices suhordinat© thereto. The amount may he allocated as helow s- Busiilre. ... 20Q/- Political Agent* toeoat. « IOC/- Politioal Agent, Bahrain. » e&lt;v- Political Agent, Kuwait. M 3C/- Consul, Bandar Abbas. II SC/- Consul, Kerman. m 8Q/- Consul, Khorramshahr. m 60/- Total. I have the honour to he, Sir, Your most obedient servant. ' y Copy to ;■ I: : I She Political Agent, Muscat. The Political Agent, Bahraini The Political -Agent, Kuwait. His Majesty*© Consul, Bandar Ahhas. His Majesty *b Consul, Keman. Hi© Majesty’s Consul, ^orramshahr. H,&gt; &gt; v It » r L NO. 3AS3. POLITICAL AGENCY BAHRAIN, IHtNOVEMBER,1944 J v/ To The Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire . MEMORANDUM *•- I enclose herewith the statement of anticipated excesses and savings in the budget grants of this Agency for the year 1944-45, Political Agent, Bahrain, 7Bakraia Receipt Dated 2nd January, 1945 5 r^ i To The Political ngent, Juscat. The Political Agent, Bahrain The Political Agent, Kuwait. His Majesty's Consul, KKorramshahr. His Majesty's Consul, Kerman. Eis Majesty's Consul, Bandar iibhas. memorandum . A statement is enclosed showing the modifications made in your Budget estimates for 1944-45. 2. In submitting your proposals for the final financial review it may Be assumed,^unless intimation is sent to the contrary, that the additional funds which the Government of India have Been ashed to provide have actually Been provided. Secrete Ltical Resident in the Persian Gulf.« Telegram G.T.C. ( \ From Political Agent, Bahrain. To Political Resident, Bushire. No. 76 Bated 5th February 1945. fi) Fin-il financial reuleu. Following are excesses Allowance honoraria 2470 * Launch grant, 1800 Office' allowance. 2500 Establishment 1590 Allowances honoraria 2870 Other Charges 500 2. Following are savingst- Pay of officers 295 Medical establishment 45 Allowances honoraria 1000 Other charges 500 Pay of officers 1640 -POLITICAL- AMO.NO. 4/4 To POLITICAL AGENCY 5 _ BAHRAIN, SX February, 1945 The Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire * M emorandum :- I enclose herewith the statement of final excesses and savings in the Budget grants of this Agency for the year 1944-45. , for Political Agent, Bahrain.■A.JL NO. 5~£Jl~ 4/4 POLITICAL AGiSNCY, BAHRAIN, / b/U February, 1945• To The Political Officer, Trucial Coast, n Shariah* Memorandum :- A grant of Rs. 1800/-(one thousand and eight hundred) only for the financial year ending the 31st March, 1945, has been provided for the Ford truck held by you* 2. It is anticipated that there will be no saving on this fund by the end of the current financial year. ’A for Political Agent, Bahrain*' . ■- Received the sum of Ps.300/- (Rupees three hundred only) as detailed on the reverse. His Majesty ty $ s Vice- Consul, Bushire . i Bushire, The January, 1945,Telegram From To No. Dated G.T.C. Political, Bahrain. Britconsul, Bushire. 125 The 25th February, 1945. My telegram 76 February 5th. Please provide, Rs.300 half 600 more under C-3 allowances etc., on account of book debit of language reward to Hadow. PoliticalTelegram From To No. Dated G.T.C. Political Agent, Bahrain. Britconsul, Bushire. 145 v 6th March, 1945. Reference my telegram 76 of February 5th. Anticipate saving of fis.7100 half 14200 under Posts &amp; telegraphs charges. =P0LITICAL= AMOn &amp; No.274*0130 griDish Agency, bharjah* Oated the 1st April 1945* TO The political Agent, Bahrain. memorandum. Reference your memorandum No* 552-4/4 dated che loth February 1945. the disposal of the sum of is.1800 alio teed for che Ford rrucS. for the financial year ending the 31st iarch 1945, and shall be grateful if you will kindly remit die amounc to me. . It is requested that a similar amount e sanctioned for the next financial year. 2 I forward herewith a statement showingNO. 4/4 To POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRAIN, April, 1945. Vt, The Political Officer, -Tmcial Coast, Sharjah# 11&gt; rvP ' Memorandum:- Reference Sharjah memorandum No#274#0l3C dated the 1st April, 1945 forwarding a statement snowing the disposal of £s» 1800/- allotted for Sharjah Ford Truck. 2# Receipts of payees in each case may please be sent to me for forwarding them to the Accountant General, Central Revenues, New Delhi, with the monthly cash account# 3. Government of India have been requested to sanction a similar grant foi 1 the current financial year 1945-46# for Political Agent, Vwt Bahrain# cJwA'Enclosures to Voucher No. 59 of March 1945 of the Political Agency, Bahrain. The Accountant General, Central Revenues, New Delhi.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0002fc_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1125</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0002fc</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1125</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 4/4 VI Budget Estimates for 1944-45'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1943/1945</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-09-17T12:01:34</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (38 folios)</extent><extent>The correspondence is arranged in chronological order from the front to the back of the file and terminates with a set of notes at folios 37-39. Circled serial numbers in ink, which occur throughout the file (red for incoming, blue/black for outgoing correspondence), refer to entries in the notes.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1 and terminates at the last folio with 39; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains the statement of budget estimates for the Political Agency, Bahrain for the financial year 1944-45, and associated financial statements and correspondence.The correspondence is mainly between the Political Agency, Bahrain and the Political Residency in the Persian Gulf. There is also some correspondence with British officials in the Trucial Coast.The budget estimates cover expenditure on pay of officers, pay of establishment, allowances and honoraria, secret expenditure, and other charges. Also included are detailed pay statements; statements of 'K-Special War Charges'; statements of actual expenditure for the first six months of the financial years 1943-44 and 1944-45; statement of anticipated excesses and savings for the year 1944-45; and statement showing modifications in the budget appropriations for the year 1944-45. The correspondence consists of covering letters, and correspondence concerning particular items of expenditure.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Expenditure</topic></subject><subject><topic>Budgets</topic></subject><subject><topic>Food prices</topic></subject><subject><topic>Funds</topic></subject><subject><topic>Fees</topic></subject><subject><topic>Motor vehicles</topic></subject><subject><topic>Cost of living</topic></subject><subject><topic>Air force personnel</topic></subject><subject><topic>Army</topic></subject><subject><topic>Travel allowances</topic></subject><subject><topic>Coffee</topic></subject><subject><topic>Hospitality</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0002fc#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>