<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0003bb_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T11:19:27.910Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">TET.FnPAF. FROJT. Reoldent. F.K.H. Triad. TO, Political Kuv;ait. FO. T. Dated 27/7/2.V. &lt;2c.recd. 2&lt;*/7/2V. please inform sheiich Ahmed that provided he cooperates loyaly with R.M.O. at present juncture, they will make every effort to secure for him an honourable settlement in his dispute with Bin Baud with regard to Kuwait trace etc. Please ask sheikh to formulate proposals that will be acceptable to him. F.M.O. will examine proposals and consider posibility ipproaching pin Baud, with a view to securing his icceptance. If you and sheikh Ahmed wish, I nil come Kuwait ^fter my present tour to discuss matter with you and Sheikh before forwarding proposals, ends.DRAFT CONFIDENTIAL. FO. 4.4d. Dated 21^/7/29. F.E. A.C. etc. In continuation of the convex-bat ion which r had with Your Excellency this morning, I send you as promised an \rabic translation of the telegram which I received from the Honble. the political Resident yesterday, regarding settlement of outstanuing quest- ions between Y. E. and Ris Majesty King I bn saud. tfsual ending.&amp; y V CO^IDEDIIIAL .- 2(0.451» 4- © political Agenoy, Kuwait. Dated the lPt August 1929. pro® TO Lieutenant-colonel H.R.P.DioiCFon, C«I«E»» Politioal Agent, Kuwait. The Hon'hle the Politioal Repident in the Persian Calf, BUPhire. Kuwait relations with Bin Baud. Sir, in reply to your telegram No.T.9 dated 27th July 1939 : I tiave the honour to report that I have personally seen His Bxoellenoy the Ruler and explained the substance of your te legram to him. 2. He is now engaged in formulating proposals that wil be acceptable to him, vis-a-vis Bin Ssud, and these when ready will be submitted to you by post. Needles p to say Hip Excel lency reiterates his earnest desire and willingness to co-ope rate loyally with His Majesty’s Government at tne present Juncture and in particular to do all in his power to deny supplies to the Hessa insurgents. 3. in the meantime, as I have had the opportunity of discussing the question of the relations between Kuwait and Nejd with His Exoellenoy on many occasions lately, and from alx angles, I venture to submit below some of the oonslusions I have arrived at, as well as some of the principAA causes which have led to the estrangement of relations between these two states, in doing this I realise that I am largely giving the Kuwait point of view, as explained to me by the ShaiKh, but tnen I presume this is what is required if we are to get at the rco + of the trouble. 4 . i desire especially to lay stress on the fact that both the Ruler of Kuwait and his people honestly believe they have been unjustly treated by both His Majesty’s Government a:by Bln S&amp;ud. They have got It firaly fixed in their heads that because Bin Baud was a big and strong person ana one lively to give trouble v His ilejesty's Government sacrificed the interests of their small principality on more than one occasion, oy fa vouring gin Baud to the detriment of Kuwait, in particular th believe that in order to get Bin Baud to agree to the present 'iraq-Hejd boundary line at the ojair conference of 1922, His Majesty's Government unbeknown to the Shaikh of Kuwait presented Bin Baud with a large slice of Kuwait's southern territory,thus depriving them, the Buler and people of Kuwait, at one blow not only of that portion of Hassa and north-east Nejd territory which Shaikh MubaraK had acquired and consolidated in agreement with the Turks and Bin Haschid, but also depriving them of their sole line of defence, the!powerful tribes of gutair, Aiwa, (al-Dooshan), Ajman and Awazim, whose habitat lay in the ter ritory in question, and who had to go with the 'lopped off territory**. 5. The above point of view, and the fact that the Shaikh of Kuwcit in no way desires to ta&amp;e up an aggressive attitude but rather takes up the attitude of one fighting for his very existence, may be of assistance to you in putting the matter before His Majesty's Government. 6. The actual causes of the dispute between Nejd *nd Kuwait, may be divided under two heads. (a) The arbitrary fixing of the present Kuwait southern boundary at the cjair Conference of 1922 as mentioned in paragraph 4 above when the Ruler of Kuwait was not present to fight his own battles, even though his adversary Bin Baud was there, the natural result being the present emasoulatea con dition of Kuwait state. (b) The Blockage of giiw&amp;it by Bin Baud and the consequent present state of ruin which Kuwait finds herself in. 7. As regards (a) I do not propose saying much, beyond the fact thnt His sxoellenoy the Ruler and all persons of any standing in Kuwait stoutly maintain that the southern boundary/ -3- of iOiwftit, in she ikh Mubarak *p tiuie etartad from Dobat Balbul on ti» see (80 mile? Bouth of the prepent boundary, and pepping through Nta , Jariye al-Sifla (included), Jariya el-Ilya (inolud- # ed), Wabra (inoluded), Safa (included^ met the Batin at Hafar (excluded). From thip point the line turned North-BaPt end Joined the prepent South-leat corner of Kuwait boundaiy at Urn el-Hemir. ThiB southern area enclosed the whole of the Ajman tribal area and that of the Muteir Aiwa (Dooshan). In this connection it may not be amiss to mention that Safwan, jahara end Subaihiyah are all considered to belong to the Mutair Aiwa still. As regards the Awasim, their habitat was further north from ^usur to al-gooda (al-Makhta) i.e. the strip along the sea to Bast of Subahiyah, Wafra and Bamadh. The contention also of the Ruler of Kuwait is that this southern boundary line was approved of by the Turkish authorities when they were masters of Hasps and it was only in Shaikh Salim’s day that Bin Baud started making claims against Kuwait, and then only because of a personal feud between the two men, which ended in Shaikh Salim building a fort at Balbul which threatened jubaii (ainsin). 8. it iB interesting to recall that Bin Saud at the Ojair Conference never laid claim to any part of Kuwait ter ritory as far as I recollect (I was present on the occasion), he claimed instead to be the chief of all the 'Badia' i.e. bedouin tribes of Arabia, and as such where Kuwait wap con cerned he demanded that the AJman, gutair and Awasim should be considered to come under his control. The first two of these tribes had alreaay been pursuaded to Join him through the Akhwan movement, so, as Bin saud said, they were his already. As for the Awasim, these had been forced to go down to Hasse Just before Shaikh Selim’p death, by Bin gaud’s threat of attack and deptruction, but had not become Akhwan end if allowed would return to their Kuwait allegiance. Over the question of this tribe much heated argument took place, and speaking from memory I think that Bin Saud agreed to allow it to return to . Kuweit if it chose to do so of its own free will. It never did; Bin Saud saw to that. d. According to His Excellency the Shaikh, he was faoed^lwith 'a fait aooompli H on the return of Six Percy Cox from Gj*ir f the latter only then informing him that nip Southern province had gone to Qih Baud together with the Mutair and AJuan, and that hip boundaries for the future were to be as they exist today, fhe ghaiich relates how he protested to Sir per ay Cox, and getting no change remarked M I suppose you have given my territories to Bin Saud because he ip the stronger and has the big sword'. Sir per&lt;y Cox laughed and repl led, 'Yes v but someday things may change and then you will be able to regain what you have lost and more'. This is of course Shaikh Ahmad's story, and he tells it as an amusing reminicenoe and adds 'the sword conquers today in spite of anything you anglish say'. Ig* 1 trust it will be realized that I am quoting Shaikh Ahmad's point of view above entirely and have consulted no files or books of reference. The point I wish to oake is that with the transfer of the Awazim, Mutair *nd Ajman, Kuwait has been rendered absolutely defenceless. These tribes know her every weakness and her^well, and as Akhwan under Bin gaud have grown to look upon the walls of Kuwait as the llttlt of their sway, (and Bin gaud has encouraged and fostered this idea to the best of his power). 11. This brings one to a still more interesting point and one which oonoerns us closely at the present moment: I refer to the policy of getting the Shaiadi of Kuwait to invest in a fleet of light lorries armed with Lewis duns for his defence. Though the Shaikh has expressed his readiness to ao the needful, he has confided to me that he has no faith at all in the scheme, for he knows that ftp own Kuwait townsmen who will nave to man the oers will never make fighters, and as he admitted sadly to me recently, 'not 50 oars manned by my townsmen will be of the slightest use if attacked by the Akhwans. All they will be able to do will be to police my territories and deal with petty raids'.personally I fear ghainh Ahmad is not far wrong in his estimate of the 'riffraff' whom he oalls his 'fidawi' forces. I cannot see the car scheme becoming a success until he either gets one of the above tribes beck, or imports European or Indian mercenaries to man his armed cars. The immense prestige which the desert A^hwan have today vis-a-vis the townsmen of Araoia has only to be seen to be understood. It can only be compared to the Afridi cf the-6- @ * frontier and the Calcutta Babu. 12. as regards (b) the Blooxade. Bight years ago the Customs reoeiyts for the port of gu^ait amounted to over A 6 laos per annum, this with an uniform charge of 4 ^ ad valorem oustom cUty e foday these have dropped to di la laos, and Kuwait is on the verge of ruin, with empty bazaars and shops, and an air of desolation everywhere. Yhat has saved the town from going under altogether, has been the pearl trade, though this is far from being in a healthy condition. Bin Baud's polioy of BlooKade, a seemingly cruel and unnecessary aot, which Kuwait has been too weak to resist has been and is the oause of this state of affairs, lb. The story is as follows After his suooess at Bahrain, when Bin Baud won his victory seven years ago in the matter of transit dues, he turn ed his attention to Kuwait, and in the reign of the present Euler wrote him a letter and pointed out that he was in need of more money and had decided it was time to tax goods going into Nejd from Kuwait. He therefore proposed to the Euler three alternatives to enable aim to accomplish this end. These were eitner (a) that a custom official of his be allowed to open an office at the exit gate of the city and collect revenue from cara vans leaving for Nsjd (whether tribal or 'Hathar') or (b)tha t Shaikh Ahmad should appoint such official, and sena the taxings to Risth. or (o)ti^t Shaikh Ahmad should send him Bin Baud a lump sum annually, equivalent to what was considered a fair revenue (sum not fixed). 14. shaikh Ahmad declined to entertain any of the three above alternatives on the grounds that in the eyes of the Arab world, it would be tantamount of his becoming a 'vassal' of Bin Bauds. He maintained the attitude that Bin Baud snoula adopt the ordinary metaoas as understood by the nations of world ana place Customs posts on the frontier line. He there—fore made on© following oounter proposals to aBPiBt Bln gaud, tdough ae ne pays ne felt in no way bound to do thisjai ;~ (a) Bin gaud to build a line of ouetoos poets anywhere along the frontier he pleased, and if thee# was a question of water difficulty, suon posts oould be ereoted a short distance inside the frontier line, e.g. Subahiysn. He jdhaiich Ahoea to give full facilities for the rationing of suoh posts from Auwait town. (b) The “manifest' system to be adopted on all goods going to Hejd; i.e. every ca ravan to be given a statement of the gooas it exported, a second oopy being retained in Kuwait by the Ruler and a third oopy owing sent to Bin gaud Monthly This system would insure that any caravan that attempted to evade a customs post on the frontier would be caught on arrival at Nejd and be made to pay full custom duty as well as fine . (o) ghould Bin gaud desire it, the yolitioal Agent, Kuwait, oould countersign evezy out-going manifest as well. (d) The ghaiKh of Kuwait for his part to assist oy every means in his power the levying of 2iJcat on any of Bln gaud f s trices should they be grazing in Kuwait territory &lt;?nd allowing,if necessary, Bin gaud's off ioLais themselves to woric with his men for the purpose. 15. To trie ghaiich's proposals Bin gaud turned a deaf ear, his only reply being that they were unacceptable, ana therefore he was reluctantly compelled to forbid by force all Intercourse between Kuwait and Hejd, either by his merchants or his tribes- i men, or by Kuwait meronants ana tribes,asn. in other words he besieged Kuwait and has continued to do so for the past 7 years. iin the beginning he wbb content to hpve so called bodies of l &lt;4 ^ +•.-i a-t' cmmmAY* « r&gt;H tu 4 r»+■. q ^ the Shaiidi of Kuwait to his icnees, he adopted in the laat four yearB nor© forcible netuodB in the shape of letting loope Aichw&amp;n raiderB and Bedouinp oaapqhereding ap police und'^r hip officials into Kuwait territory, to prey on all and sundry: in faot to raid anything they could find, up to the actual walls of Kuwait. This move resulted in aany people, subjects of the Shaiich, being Killed ana thousands of sheep ta&amp;en. The wretoned ghaiith Ahmad whilst refusing to admit defeat and supported by hip Kuwaitis sitting behind their great walls has continuously protested to Bin Baud against these acts of war. Bin Baud as often has apologized for his officials 1 and tribes 1 misdeeds but has never punished or restrained any of his people. Bhai&amp;h Ahmad as in the days of the Saxon* and Danes has tried at times to buy off Bin Saud f p polioe parties by supplying them with free rations in the hopes that they would go. They have only come in greeter numbers. IB. The notorious Amir of Hassa, Bin Jaloui, has been in charge of operations from the beginning and later sent his son I*had to conduct matters on the spot. This youth has been responsible for some outrageous aots and until nemesis over took him recently was growing more and more impudent in his methods. It is said that he was on his way to oooupy Jahara for good and oonduot the blockade from inside Kuwait territory when he was billed in Basse recently, one crime of Bin jaloui’s which did more than anything else to stiffen the resistenoe of the Shaikh of Kuwaiti people was the cold blooded murder of 2 Nejdis who were handed over oy Stoikh Ahmad on a promise of safe oonduot to Bin Jaloui and a fair trial. The crime I understand was that they had brought 3 camels across the border into Kuweit. As soon as the Nejdis were handed over, they haa their throats out irom ear to eer by a negro slave a few yards outside the main gate of oho oity. Eho nogro shouting out (it is said),*thus shallmy master t«aoh you, o people of ifiiw&amp;it, Uiat ills boundary e*tends up to your veiy wallB*. Tdip incident happened 4 years ago. 17. Throughout the above blooiced# or ae^toe. Bin Baud has been astute enough to keep up a seemingly friendly cor respondence with ShaiKh Ahmaa, in mat particular has he always denied responsibility for any Akhiran raids and damage, though these very raiders who are today in revolt against Bin Baud, one and all will admit that they received direct orders to act as they did on every occasion from Bin Baud himself, not even through his Governor, Bin Jaloui. (I myself asked the Akhwsn leaders Jteisal al-Shiblan, H«am al-HethAain and al-puqm this very question recently and all admitted it was so). 18. in oonolus ion from a long talk which I had yester day with She ixda Ahmaa, I gather the proposals which he is now formulating will ta*e the following line, I thin* his demands are moderate;- (a) There must be complete freedom of trade between the people of Nejd and KUwait, this to apply to towns men as well as tribesmen. In other words the siegfe or blockade to cease. (b) No parties of Bin Saud or Bin Jaloui, tribal or regular forces, to be allowed to cross the frontier at any time. (o) Bin Baud to have as many customs posts on the frontier as he choeees. (d) The manifest system mo aome into force. (e) Reciprocal arrangements for surrender ing criminals to be set up. (f) Small matters of disagreement to be settled between both Rulers direct. If these cannot be adjusted, both sides to agree to refer them to His Majesty 1 * Government for decision. (g) If possible Kuwait southern boundary to be rectified, so as to bring at1 er p t one of the big three tribes who onoe belonged to Kuw*it.under Kuwait oontrol once acre. This &amp;a an act of delated juPtioe and to give Kuwait a derenoe toroe. guoh « -r . tribe it ^o^eible to be the Ajaan, the Awazim being too unwarlike. 19. it jaay be asked what guarantee hap the 3h*i&lt;th of Kuwait that with the removal of the blooitade trade will revive and Kuwait return to her former prosperity. The answer is that provided din gaud doe? not impose a prohibitive duty, her loPt trade will return for the following reasons;- (a) Kuwait has no pea Journey by dhow f as is the oase at Ojair, -^atif and Jubail. (b) Caravan leaders f ind superb grazing at jahara for their tired oamels after their long Journey up to the ooapt and oan afford to give them a month’s rept before the return Journey. At ojalr. &lt;4&amp;tif and jubail ohe grazing is praotioelly nil. (o) It is no common thing f or a tfejd caravan to lose 4&lt;j/fc of its camels at these latter ports, whilst in the north there is no loss at all, and where actual camels are ownea by the merchants of AJeJd as they almost always are, this is a serious matter. (d) At Hoffuf in the South Bin jaloui has made it a rule to seize merchants* camels Just in frcn gejd or flefrftr , and force them to make one trip at least in conveying Bin spud’s government 'stores” from the ooapt up to Rie th, (sukhra system). (e) Iiast but more ii%ortant than all the above points put together is the faot that very good 'credit' is given by the merchant? of Kuweit,® and this point alone tends and always will i tend to attract merchants of t^asia, Hail and lower Hejd to the detriment of other ports on the Bast Cost ana the towns of Mecca and• U_ (^) ''i Meaina in the W«st- Thie credit ByBtera has on to he seen to be believed. It iP no/oooamon feBtuxe Tor a aierohent to oome to Kuwait with £ 100 in hie pooioet, and to purohape £ 600 worth of rice and piece good?*. He pope when he liicep, and no interest is charged. Today Nejd owes the merchants of Kuweit many thousands of pounds dating from the period before the bloo^de. .repayment is very slowly being made and only lapt wees I no- tioed that a men nf/_tNwtlwT sent Bt 7,000/- via jubail to Kuwait in Pettlement of a debt 7 years old. 2q* We now oome to the question as to what customs Bin Saud oan charge on goods entering Nejd vie fQiwait, without upsetting the trade via Bahrain too muoh. Today the dues charged are as follows (a) Goods via Kuweit have to pay Kuwait sea Customs plus 2^ land export duty, both of whioh go to Shali&amp;h of Kuweit. Total 6*&gt;. Goods via oJ»i^ have to pay to Bahrain and 7$ to Bin Baud et Ojair. Totel 9^. If therefore Bin Baud were to impose a 7% duty on Kuwait goods entering Hejd, I am of opinion this would be a reasonable tax, even though the total cUty on goods entering ftejd via Kuwait would rise to 12^, as opposed to 9i^ via Bahrain and ojair. It Is possible however, that even at this figure the trade via Bahrain would suffer and be diverted to Kuwait, so great is the popularity of Kuwait compared with other ports. If this turned out to be so, tiie balanoe could probably be struoK fairly evenly if the duty were raised to K# on goods via Kuwait. I Know ^asim merchants are prepared to go to this figure but not more. Thet is to say a total of 16$.21. of oourse, we shnll neve to de*l with the opposition of the gre»t houf^e of el-&lt;4op»ioi of B^hTnin ^nci Ha bps # ana private BsnicerB to Bin Baud. This firm farms the oustoais of OJ»ir, (^atif and Jubail eveiy year, end caaitep a very good thing out of it. l‘heir polioy has teen to Kill Kuwait ana without l doubt it has largely been at their Inst&amp;noe tnat Kuwait has been blooKaded for bo long. Under tne proposal mentioned in para graph Bo above, l thin* at least one third of tne trade whioh goes via B&amp;nr&amp;in now wouxu be diverted to Kuwait. How are the ^osaibl family going to meet tnis loss. I oan myself see no way out of it, than for Bin Baud to olose down tne farm and talce direct customs revenue himself, or, asK the ^osaibi family to taice up the Kuwait farm as well, a suggestion so full of dif ficulties as to be impracticable. Af things ere, the chief opposition without doubt to a settlement of the Kuwsit-Bin Baud question is going to come from this powerful business men house of al-^osaibi, and it were well that His ifrtjesfcy’s Government be warned what to expect * from tne start. Bin Baud, I fancy, is very greatly in debt, financially ana morally to the ^osaibi family, and the pressure tney will be able to bring will be of no mean oraer. 1 nave tne honour to be, Bir# Your most obeaient servant, ! Lieut-col., Political Agent, Kuwait.TELEGRAM. FROM Brlurgent, Jeddah. TO, political Kuwait. NO, 16401 Dated x/b/29. My telegram July 30th, gave resume version of Kings speech To Ataibah Chiefs at Duwu^ami in which he said he proposed send army to attack AJman on Aug.6th. Foreign Office letter June 13th states code in Question is being sent you. Please Inform me whwn received.61/14 iv. Telegram From to Repet&amp; No 163 R. Agent D’jedda. / j Foreign Office ^OSBS9k 114, Jagdad.Jerusalem.Bushire. Koweit. 163. (copifes l)y post to Cairo# Aden^aAnd Oovt of India ) Dated 31st July 1929. According to account published here speech delivered 'by King t:&gt; chiefs of Ataibah trile who had been summoned to meet him at Duwadami on his way to Riyadh, King, after upbraiding them for being in part disloyal and after jassing judgment on them stated that he wished to annihilate the Ajman tribes, that he proposed to send an army against them on August 6th. All persons who have wavered in their allegiance but no*/ profess loyalty are to take part. Absence of anyone with out a proper excuse wilj'he punishable by death dy by arrest of his army and confiscation of his arms and horses. iea Agent. Repeated to political Resident ’’Triad ' Bushireradio. under No 737^ ffi 3 ' i-obt copy to Political Agent, Kuwait reference this office telegram No. 749, dated 3rd August 1929. By order, for secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Bushire, 4th August 1929.IJranp lotion. - ftl-jebir »P-Suto6h,c&amp;.I., C.I*£. , fiuler of KUWf» it. - Colonel a.R.i'.Uio-cFon, ^olitio»l Agent at Kuwait. - ^7th safer lo4d (Srd August 192d). After greetings end ooupliaentp eto* 9 Witii the bend of affeotion, I duly reoeived your letter Ho*449 dated 2£nd Safer (29th July 1229), Inoluolng tranFlAtion of e telegraoi (I./9 dated 27th July 1929) reoeived by you froa the hon*ble the ji j olitloel He^ icxent in trie per^ian Qulf. X nave netea the contents, and have understood what His gKoellenoy desired to ooxtvey. X also ear gre teful for the o*re and attention anion His Sxcellenoy has shown to iue his friend. 1 therefore tnan£ the xiign nr it is n Govern xient for its favour and .cindne^a, ana desire you to oonvey ay gratitude and thanks to tae Hon'ole one rolitioaX He ixent in the jper^lan Gulf. As for my elf I ea the loyal friend of His Majesty^ Governaent • As regards ay brother Bin Saud, you joiow wy well that there is no real enalty (Khasama) between hi a »na ay self in anything, And X trust tnere never will be. Xhe good relations existing between us are of a permanent nature, ana wnere he is concerned 1 shall by God # s will, enaeavour with all the influ- enoe and power at my disposal to loyally oarry out tne wishes of His majesty's Government, not only in uamtLxm# word out by deed. nevertheless 1 would request you to inform the Hon'ble the ^olitioal Hesioent of all the happenings that have befallen Kuwait ( at tne hands of Bin Saud), of the gloo^ae of my territories, of the continual raids (gharat) of am Baud's A&amp;owan, ana the Atteoits by his regular forces (3*ria) and all within the boundaries of Kuwait, and one and all being acts yrom To Dated- 4 *- of* oruel perpeoution on ay Fubjeot* or Kuwait oontrazy to wll law? and my right*. I would further *pk you to mwKe report on the peizure of the good^ exported for poor Bedouin^ tribe*, whether were t**en A out by their subjects or by the subjects of my or other states. Ail thi?* and more is due to the strictness of (Bin Baud**) blo- Oiiecie of KU^eit, and to the eotivities of his forces near y city, jo such an£ exte^lt has traae between Bejd and Kuwait been interfered with tnet my revenue ha* : been reduced from its former figure by 7 q#. This too hes been brought about by Bin gaud’s siege operations which have been going on without interruption from the year 1340 ( ) to the present time. jnere oan be no aoubt that suoh methods (of liih gaud) bring grief to pure affection, and displease the best friendship. fhe present request of His Majesty’s government that I should put forward the proposals whioh l deem suitable (for solving the KUwait-Nejd dispute) has given me veiy great satis faction, and will further bring joy and happiness to aany. Nor oan there be any doubt that thi** is due to the Kiindne^p and generosity felt by His Majesty's Government for their friend. It is of o ourse thine able that 1 should go against tne orders of His Majesty’s Government in anything that is desired or approved of. fo revert again to the ettao^s of the AKhwan end regular forces (of bin 3 »ud), 1 have corn these with patience, ana have oomplainea to Bin Baud on every single occasion that th‘y happened, but i regret to say that no restitution of my own stolen property, or tt**t of any of my ;-ubjeots has been made *f yet. Moreover I have been doing 9 «x utmost to meet Bin S*ud in every single request that he has put forward or that would give him satisfaction. Nor can nor will he deny what I say. Unfortunately I have received nothing in return to give me or my people pleasure. AS regards Kuwait generally, we have not sufficient force or strength to defend our-elves from these continuous attaoKS, seeigg that our tribes and defenders were t«^en away from us, when Sir peroy go* reduced the territories and bounds-boundaries or Kuwait, how oould they reoein with us seeing that they no longer had suffioient rooa to graze their oaaels end fXooKa, whilst the constant fear of Bln Baud 9 * attacks hastened their going over to the other side. Hsd the territories of Kuwait today been as before and our tribes oeen with us we should not have lap or tuned His ^Je^ty , s (Jovern-aent, but would have defended our own borders f and carried out any orders, that His Jajesty 9 s Governaent had cared to in^ose wltnout in anyway asking for or expecting help. As things are, we oan do nothing for we have no power to defend ourselves, whatever^therefore tnat^the ooverniient sees fit to decide, must be accepted. hr X am no^ putting forward to four Honour three state ments, the first includes one number of raids and attacks made by gin 3aud 9 s A&lt;dw»n within the boundaries of Kuwait and the number of Kuweit suojeots Killed, ana the amount of pro- perty stolen. j?hs Second gives- the number of raid* made by Bin baud 1 * Regular froops {% Saria), also within Kuwait boundaries with \ property seized etc. i?he third gives in detail my proposals ana demands vis-a-vis Bih Baud ana whioh you have requested me to furnish. Whatever action His iaajesty’s Government deoides to t*Ke or whatever line it approver of, th^t will be tne right ana propitious one* (Healed). Ahmed ai-jabir as-Bubah.propOBwle to HiP fixo^llenoy ui^b of i£u»ait vin-A-viB a.M. wii« King of Nejd, A idj&amp;z otc. All trade t»otw#en KUwalt ^nd aejd iaoludiag aedouin tr»d« to be free. a. If H. , 4 . King bin S*ud demirep to ImiJOPe a duty on goods leaving :&lt;uwAlt, in obsrg* of his pabjeotP, to Nejd pnri to dip Bedouin ■pribep, we pgree to hip plaotng ou^'ton^ yoPts ell Along our frontier, should there be diffioulty BDout water, we agree to the posts oeing placed at the following watering places in; 146 our ooundariep, namely fha ailat / iUrKi, fhajiilat Uai I^aaiyir I'ha ailat tiana^iah Al jfci^ai. Betions for tne posts to be supplied froaa Kuwait without delay, and without tax oeing levied. 3. I (the Ruler of Kuwait) promise to send by eaoh A air of caravan a *:aBnifePt' containing a list of all goodP exported and at the end of every aonth to submit copies of all asnifests ipcued to the King direct. Should there be found any difference at des tination, AX* H. d. the King will be able to punish the responsible Asair of the caravan. 4. All raiders and regular troops of Bin Saud to be for bidden entry into the territory of Kuwait. 5. If any of Bin Sand** tribe? enter Kuweit (for gracing purposes) ana the King desires to te&lt;e 2iicat from them, I agree that it oe done (ana by his officials). d. criminals such as murderers and robbers, Should they taxe refuge in N«Jct from Kuwait territory, or visa versa, to oe handed over, if surrender demanded. 7. if King Bin Baud should have any fault to find deserving of correspondence, he snould address me direct, and at the time ol complaint, and we will do our best to meet hi? wiFhes. Should agreement not be oome to between us, then the faots to be reported to His Majesty*? Governaent: I will raise no oojeotion. B. Uhe territory of Kuwait used to be wide and large during the lifetime of my grandfather Sbaith kub*rSiC and our tribesCOMFIDEHTIti-i . W No.464. political Agency, Kuwait. Bated tne 8 th NuguPt 1929. From Lieutenant-colonel H.R.p.DiokPon, politloal Agent, Kuwait. ; To The Hon'ble the lolitioal Reticent in the peraian QKilf, Burhire. ^ Subject;- DuwiPh'e letter to Aair Baud. Sir, • x have the honour xo refer you to ujy telegram No.428 dated I the 15th July 1929 and previous correspondence. ▲ rather curious incident has resulted which, I thin* is worth reporting. Shaikh Ahmad saw me two days ago and remindt&amp;a me of Faisal ad-Duwish’s letter to Aiair Saud, told ae that at the time he felt grave doubts as to the genuineness of the missive, in particular he suspected the (a) inordinate length (b) the expression that he the Ruler of Kuwait was a chicken. He had therefore mentioned the whole matter to Hillal al liutairi who, as you know, never loses touch with his old tribe the Mutair. He had also shown him the copy of Faisal’s letter which I had presented to him, Shaikh Ahmad. Hillal who at the time supported shaikh Ahmaa in his views, it seems wrote to ad- puwish and taxed him with the matter. The latter has replied swearing as big an oath as he can (by his religion and by his wives honour and his own) that he never used the expression ■chicken' at all, and that his only letter to Amir Saua was in reply to one received, and was a short statement only of why he left Artawiyeh, nothing more. Faisal ad-Duwish aaded lat the letter complained of was an obvious forgery and especially sf his opponents were in possession of his seal (taken, as reported, at Sabilla). J*isal asked Hillal al Mutairi to inform both Shaikh Ahmad and the colonel Dickson of thi answer of nis. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant, ^ ^ Llsut-Col. , S political Agent, Kuwait.Telegram From Political Resident| Bustiire* To H.M*s• Secretary of State for the Colonies 9 London, No* 23 British Agent, K Q Lepeated Britis Dated 3rd August 1929 neforence letter dated 23/12/1347 (corr- -esx&gt;onding to 6 th June 1929) purporting to have been addressed to Bin Baud by Faisal bin Dawish, whioh aocoinpanied letter of 16th June from Fuad Hamza to British Agent, Jeddah* The Shaikh of Kuwait declares that Ibn Baud obtained Faisal bin Dawish^s seal after the battle of r&gt;abilla. The style and wording of the letter lead in question coupled with this fact iaat the Shaikh of Kuwait to suppose that the letter is a forgery* was mentioned incidentally by the Akhwan leaders who • '^t oiitical Agent Kuwait on 13th July ( see my telegram No. 22 of 20th July). That Bin Baud had taken Faisal's seal Post copy sent to the rolitical Agent at for information only. ST)/ C.C.J. Barrett, Lieut,-Colonel, Political Kesident in the Persian Gulf. Attested: far Secretary to the Political Kesident in the Persian Gulf. Bushire, 3rd August 1929.~ZM Confident ial. ^ no. 6 of 1929. .British residency and Consulate-General, mishire , 3rd August 1929. A copy of the undermentioned paper is forwarded to the Political Agent, Kuwait, for favour of coioinents after consultation with the Shaikh of Kuwait. iiy Order, for Secretary to the .Political Kesident in the .Persian Gulf. Letter tio. S.O. 1475, dated the 25th July, 1929, from H.E. the high Commissioner for Iraq, Baghdad.0 '54' Copy of letter Ho. S.0.1475, dated 25th Julji 1929, from His Excellency the High Comiuissioner for iraci, Haglidad, to the Hon’ble the Political Kesident in the nersian Gulf, Hushire. dated the 12th of July, 1929, concerning air action in Kuwait territory. best for bringing the Royal Air Eorce promptly to the help of the Shaikh of Kuwait if he should need it to expel Hajdi insurgents who come, without his consent, into his territory. next move into Kuwait for grazing, that raiders from Hajd may attack them as they did during the early months of this year, thus necessitating once again taking advantage of the authorisa tion given by the Shaikh of Kuwait (vide Kuwait's telegram no. 459/S., dated the 30th of September, 1928, to you;. in such circumstances intelligence of the raiders' movements night reach Zubair or Sufwan before Kuwait and unless action was taken at once it would be difficult to protect the threatened ira^i tribes or punish the raiders. A wait for a reference to Kuwait would probably rob the Royal Air Force of their opportunity. 1 have the honour to refer to your telegram no. 664 •1 agree that the procedure proposed by you is the 3. It is possible however, when the Iraq desert tribesTKLROPAM. FROM. Resident, Bushire. TO. political Kuwait, po # 7 . Dated &amp; reed. 12/&amp;/2V. You may send mere intelligence reports to Baghdad, but all telegrams and letters referring or discussing questions of policy such as Bheikhs views, should be sent- to me alone. Bearing in mind these general directions, use your own discretion in cases of urgency.3 ^ TO. ReHident Rushire. FROM Pol i t .1 ca 1 Kuwa 1 1 . NO. 469. Date(U2/o/a9. J!y telegrara No. 42b dated ibth July. Sheikh’s messengers have returned with letters for sheikh and myself. In letter to sheikh R.S. full of protestations friend ship, assures Sheikh his spiritual home is Kuwait, apologises for flag incident, thanks sheikh for valuable help in stopping supplies to rebels, offers send him troops by land and sea to assist him repel any attempt rebels to cross border. In letter to me B.S. reports his arrival Riath reiterates his pleasure my appointment Kuwait especially at present juncture. Urges me continue blockade rebels, ana above all to prevent them crossing Kuwait frontier. Finally proposes a regular exchange Ideas by means letters to combat enemy moves. Translation by post. po]itical.Telegram (c). prom - Political, Kuwait. To - Resident, Bush ire. Higticoma, Baghdad. No.466. Dated 12th August 1929. Al Duwish who till recently hiding vicinity t^araa and al- Kaoa near Daifa on 2nd August made rapid move across 13o miles \ waterless deseirt and on 4th August struck large concentration Sbei and sh Sahool tribes supported by detachment 130 Bin Baud's regulars at (^aya near Artawiyeh. Attack entirely successful and camp numbering 400 tents taken. Bin Baud's detachment destroyed, other losses both sides insignificant as Duwish s orders were to spare all who surrendered. Above may be considered correct news. Possible next points attack either Haiiar Ajibba or Hafar al Atz south east ^aya. political. Telegram (c). prom - political, Kuwait. T© - Special, Basrah. NO.467. Dated 12th August 1929 . -Al Duwish has struck al—^aya and captured concentration of 400 tents Sbei and Sahool, destroying detachment 130 Bin Saud's regular troops which camped with them. Attack waa took place 4th August and was complete surprise. Above may be accepted as correct newe. Suggest your watching Hafar Ajibba or Hafar al Atz south east ^aya f cr next fetroke. Polit ical.No.468. political Agency, Kuwait. Dated the 12th August ld29. prom Lieutenant-Colonel H.R.p.DioicPGn # C .1 - B. , politioal Agent, Kuwait. To The Hon 1 ole the politioal aesihent in the perpian Gulf, Buphire. paipal al-DuwiPh’p raid on the Sfcei and Sahool at (^aya. Sir, In continuation of my telegram No*466 dated 12th Augu?t 1929, I have the honour to forward the following fuller details of this insurgent Puooess which in my opinion is liicely to have a far reaching effect on those tribes and groups of Bedouin who are still sitting on the fence. H«B.Shaikh Ahmad received intimation of the engagement this morning (12th August 1929) in the shape of a short note from Faisal al Duwish giving the hare facts as stated in my telegram. A Salutoha from Nejd however also arrived at the same time who stated that he had fallen An with the raid ing party a day before the attaoic, and had been forced to gc with it being only released after the effair was over. The Salubba f P tale, which ShaLth Ahmad considers reliable ( he Knows the man who has a family at Kuwait) is as follows and is given in the form of paragraphs below (a) Al Duwian left al i^araa ana al Haba south of Safa, where he had been in hiding more or less, on the 2nd August. His force numbered about 8000 oamelmen (this I consider an exageration) with 25 q horses. (b) . There being no water between Qjaraa and (^»ya which is pronounced QAIYBH by the Arabs, he decided to do the 130 milep by a two-day 'Dash'.- 2 - 'v (o) At (^y» were located. 400 tents of the Sbei and school tribes supported by e aetaohjaent (SIREIA) of 13 q of Bln Saud^ regular troops. (d) The ettr oJc oaoae as a oonplete surprise, and not much of a fight was put up by any one. (e) Thousands of sheep were taicen and much loot though no oaaels were captured as these i»d all gone a day r p journey away to graze. (f) Two important Sbei and Sahool shaiichs were ^illwd though not oore than 40 of the ranic and file: bat the nen of Biu Saud f p detachment were nearly all jellied. (g) Before the actual attack was launched, Faisal al-Duwish had called all his leaders together, and had enjoined on them the necessity of ceasing from their old methods of billing wholesale. He bade them to accept the surrender of any man who threw down his rifle in to&amp;en of submission, and ordered them to harm no woman or child. (h) After the battle al-Duwish fed all his cap tives, and ordered any who wished to depart, he also detailed parties to drive back to tyiraa his last camp a large prop ort ion of the sheep taken, though the teller of the story gave it as his opinion that pro bably only half would ever arrive, owing to lack of water and the intense heat. (i) Al-Duwish next sent out patrols in the direc tion of Ajibba and Hafar al Atz, at both of which places Bin Baud has forces. (j) Three boxes of ammunition intact were taken from the detachment as well as many rifles and a saddle bag full of money. (' t ^) He far al Atz Ip situated to the South iDast of &lt;^aya. I have the honour to be, Sir, four most obeaient servant, Lieut-col., Political Agent, Kuwait.From iro.471. CuNgIDJMlIAo. polltloal Agency, Kuwait. Dated tde 12td Augup t 1*23. Lieutenant-Colonel H.R.p.DioKFon, C politioel Agent, Kuwait. Tde Hon’ble tde Political Repident in tde Persian Qulf, Bupdire. Intelligence. Sir, in continuation of my telegram tfo.469 dated 12td August 1329, tde following eomewdat intereeting information wap given me by Sbai*d Admad's cdief meseenger who left Riath on tde 1st August end reached Kuwait on the nigdt of tde lotd/llt d August« .file p*'rty baci oon.Pi. 3 bed of four trusty henodmen of AAe SneiKd Ahmad including tne chief mepsenger who is locally renowned for speaKing out dip mind. (a) The party reached Riatd 7 days before Bin g*ud arrived there. They were seized by r *' * H Bre id M at Refar al Batin on their way south, but were released at tde intervention of one of gin s»ud f s officers. (d) on dip arrival, Bin S*ud was Kind to them, cut continually telKed 'big' of what he was going to d) at the end of 'Rabia al Awal - (25td of August) with tde insurgents in Ha sea. (o). Tne party found a vast gathering of Soutnem Bedouin at Riatd and tneee Bin Saud was feeding freely with food and gifts. He also was disbursing arms and ammunition in qu*ntitj»u. They w*r. BtruoK witn toe fact tl* t t:lere were ver y rew important aaaiithB In Riath. * g tnose they saw or heard of tfere ibn Shuqpij- 2 - Mish«ri a 1-MUFfllyiF (Brath), Naif ibn ii^ziad, yaipal al-DuwlFd’F protege at Artawiyeh nne^e tc^ree latter Bin gaud wap keeping more or le^p under restraint, their following having been ordered to return home. (d) Bin Baud told uy informant that Baud hie Borl ( Abu S^^ein) had gone to BaFsa for a lo da ye' tour, (flinoe confirmed by telegram from Baud to the Shaikh of Kuwait dated loth August 1929). gy infor* ant ooula not say if gaud was going to replace Abdul Aziz al-amrKi as Commander of Troops in Has»a , or was merely going to visit Bin tfaloui and report on his condition. (®) All the members of the Baud family were with the King except fiaiFal his ron. ( O No Ataiba 3te Uhe were seen with sin Baud* wy informant could not understand the absenoe of these. (s) Uy informants opinion wap tmt Bin Baud was making olear preparations for a Beaouin oampaigr 'ga L u^ . wne re oels, but all depended on whether Auaioa chiefs would play 'straight'. ( a ) Bin SaudS information regarding rebels appeared poor; for instance he had no iaee when tiey the messengers, left on Isfc August ti»t ^isal al- D uwxr-a ma left Bassa for an unknown destination, end only on 2nd August when they were a aay out of Riath did express messengers pass them going North to warn everyone that al-Duwish was on the war path, (i) On their return Journey to Kuwait the party crossed the traces of Duwish^ raiders. These were ner vy - a ell marked and led south. Numbers were estimated at two or three thousand. (J) Aoting on the previous instructions of Shall of Kuwait, the chief oesseager asiced Bin Seud in Riet if he would accept the surrender or the insurgents if he, Shaiida Ahmed, oculd arrange suoh. Bin Baud hadgiven him a de^initly negative reply. (*) Similarly under orderp the chief messenger had upbraided Bin Baud for hie continuous harsh and unfriendly treatment of Kuwait and demanded in the name of H Alieh' to Know whrt ShaiKh Ahmad had ever done to him, except return good for evil, din gaud had pretended to weep, and tod sworn that StoiKh Ahmad was his dearest friend, and he looked upon Kuwait as his birthplace, and though only one woman rema ined alive in KUwait city he would honour her above all women, so highly did he regard shaikh Ahmad, the town, its people etc.etc. (1) Bin S«ud f 8 last instructions to the chief messenger were to tell shaikh Ahmad to fend all furtner letters by sea via oj*ir. X have trie honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant, f /v^&gt; - Liaut-col., political Agent, Kuwait.conyiflmmL. No.470. Folitlo»l Ag9noy t Kuwait. Dated tJ^e l3thAuguBfc 1329. Jproca Lieutenant ^colonel H^R-F-DioicFon, political Agent, Kuwait. To The Hon*tele the .Political RePident in the Persian Gulf, BuPhire. Sir, In continuation of coy telegram No.469 dated 12th August 1929, i have the honour to forward Sagli^h tranalation of H.M.King A bdul Aaiz al-gaud^ letter No.13/3477 to xy eddrepa dated 23rd Safer 1348 (£oth July 1929). The Arabic original ia not very eapy to tranala te,but frcoa the laPt paragraph it would appear ttet the King desi- r#B that i should start a regular correspondence with him regarding reoel movements etc. with a view to an exchange of ideas. As the King 1 ? letter has come under official oover, I should be glad to know how I should act in the matter. To my mind the King either wishes me to write him an occasional private letter giving him news, of rebels etc., much as Shaikh Ahmed doen, or he finds himself so out of touch with affairs in general in his eastern province, ttet he hopes to use me as a sort of 'la is on officer' between himself and His H^Jesty 1 * Government much as I used to be when at Bahrain in 1919-20 and the present letter is his first move. I have the honour to be, Sir your most obedient servant Political Agent, Kuwait.TRAflSjuAfxUjj. proin - Abdul Aziz bin Abdiir B^hman al-paipal. To - Li#utenpnt-Colonel H.R.p .DiakPon C . I , political Agent, Kuwait. No.'13/3477. Dated, Kingdom of Rijaz, Najd &amp; Dependencie? , the 23rd Safer 1348 (30th July 1^29.) After cOJQplimeats . Vie have already Beat to four Bxoellenoy a letter from HaJau, and now seeing that the mepsenger of our brother Aiimad al-jaoir ip about to leave for Kuw &amp; it we desire to send this letoer with him to firstly to give you information of our arrival at Riyadh, the capital of our country, by the Or^oe of God, in hap^iaeps and health, secondly to arrange that future correspondence may p pass regularly between us. We have already informed you in our letter, which we sent from Hajaz, of the great pleasure we felt at your coming to Kuwait as political Agent representing the British Government, and also for being fo olose to our country at suoh a time as this, when the interests of both Pides are fo at sta*e, and when it is so necessary to taKe steps with mutual assistance to reAove these ills which ruin the welfare of our country, as well as the welfare of those countries which the British Govern ment has taken upon itself to defend (t.e. Kuwait and f iraq). Doubtless you are aware of the negotiations whioh teve taken place already between us and the British Government, and of the agreement that wa 3 arrived at with regard to thope rebels from among our subjects, who are in the neighbourhood of Kuwait and whom we have punished and intend again to punish shortly, for tneir past aggression on Kuwait and t iraq. we are sure that Your Excellent will watch and taare steps always to privent any supplies, food, or ammunition going over to t iem, and especially will not allow them individually or in Parties, to ^ee.v refuge in Kuwait territory, because these two points are among the most important whioh the British Government has promised to us in our efforts to deal with these evil people.t FROB-I. Rush Ire. TO political Kuwait, np,806. Dated &amp; reed. 13/8/29. your telegram yo. 4t9. Do not reply Bin Baud till I have received s ecre ^ &lt;i ’ r 'j of state for the Colonies orders. 3o\ U :Telegrain(c) prom - political, Kuwait. To - Resident, Bushire. Repeated to Higkooma, Baghdad; Special,Basrah. No.474. Dated 14th August 1929. Kuwait Di ar y NO.14 paragraph 108. Ajman under Khalid bin Mohammed met and defeated detachment of Bin Saud south of Nta, 5th August killing 26 men and capturing 28 camels. Above reliable. Addressed Bushire repeated Baghdad and special Basrah. Political.Tola&amp;ram P. u&gt; a fr * political lieiiluent, BusUir Baoratary oT Gtate for the Colonies, Tondon, 25. British A^ent, Jeddah, repeated _ ?74 ,lenoi oD- ,r^yernmeht of India, Simla, ' Luted 9th August 1929. The Shaikh of i^uwait • s requests are as 2 . follows:- ^ 1. Kejd ana Kuwait should t*** reatriutiuiis, . Iol Bitud way, place customs posts on the frontier lino and also, if required By difficult- -Ijb of water supply t , at th?imi_l_^t3 A1 iliqai, .1 anaqish and Turki urn Uqdair, Monthly manifest of all goods exported will he sent hy Shaikh of Kuwait. mtry into Kuwait territory forbidden to Bin Baud’s raiders and troops. Bin Baud’s officials to enjoy the right of collecting zakat from Nejd tribes even in Kuwait territory. 3. 4. ■ 5. 6 . 7. 8 . Mutual surrender of criminals. All complaints to be addressed direct to the Shaikh of Kuwait. If no agreement is/ reached case should he referred to K.l’s. ^ovornment. Return to allegiance of Kuwait of Kutair, AJman and /wazim trihes. Of these requests the last is a thorny question. Despatch, with copy to Baghdad, follows hy next air mail. The foregoing refers to your telegram of 26th July. igmfldtnUfci. British Msoiden^ and Cons Bui.hire, eth Aui^uot 19S9 4 2 hsv 9 Uis honour to refer to your teitfpraa of the 80th July 1929 authorising nr to inform the rhaiJch of Kuwait that, i^orided he oo«operates loyally with His J.ajesty'e Oovemswrit 9 they will nsitr ereiy effort to eeeure an honourable settlenent for bin in his dispute with Ills Majesty the King of najd. The V«r t at /.;i wd.t has now or- warded me a letter, dated 27th liafar 1348 (3rd Au^uet 1929}, from Hie T’&gt;eellen«y Uw tUuiiich, slilcii i enclose in translation, in which he ibrnulates the proposale which will be uceestable to him (I'tatersunt 3}. He iiae also forwarded Statemeht 1 which gives a liet of the raide that have been Made by Uie Akhwan Into Kuwait during hie reign together with casualties inflicted on Kuwait subjecte anc j^o^erty carried off, and another statement Bo. 2 ehowlng the activities of Bin Baud's own forces within Kuwait territory. Before presenting hie proposals to the tuiUcal Absent tiie riiaiith re iterated his earnest desire ana willingness t© co operate loyally with His Hapesty'e Uovermjtrt — his UAMmr'% nB:Qm?TAmr of irrATB won **hb cownmn, QOUmiAL ornCK, 10 f THKBT, urnm*. present^ 8 • pr&lt;*o«Tit juncture anti in j^ikTticulajr to n© nil in hi a powsr to deny nuppllea to thm Unci* insurgent •• J ghmikh Ahmad of Kuwait's iro^ooaia propounded in hia Statomnt 5 on thm idioio appear to mo to uo reasonable 9 though tin**© or otiarm oT a aimilnr nature iiave boon oonolatently rajo«tad by Min Baud in the iumt. Thera ia no ouoh diffaranca bataaan Judicial elandarrio in Kuwait and «ajd aa to render proposal mo* 6 undeoirable • iTapoaal Mo • 8 wtiich run© dire ally con trary to Bin Haud'a policy ie aure imwever to meet at first with a direct refusal and it will be difficult to get Bin Baud to con©icier it. £•/ Bin 8 amd would like to dain all the Bedouin tribee / inoiuciint u.ot,e in allegianc# to ti e Iraq uov- ernaentaH hi© subject®. Me doe a not liice fixed boundariea aitiier between hiMself and Iraq or hiMaalf end Kuwait. Thie hu» alwaya been hi© claim and it wad mida umoiatakably clear «iien Min : aub *© mvi ccmmtindad by Abdulla bin Adwah under the ©upnwm coBmimd of Min Jllawi obtained the surrender of two m^d merchant a who had been guilty of bringing three emncla acrooa the border into Kuwait end had taxer i refuge in Kuwait town. A negro alaire of Min dilawl promptly out Uie throata of theoe unfortunate® at Ui« gate of Kuwait exclaiming in a loud tone l 'Thu® ahull my master 'teach you* oh people of Kuwait* that hi© boundary 'extende up ta your eery wallaf This incident appeara aa Mo. 6 in Statement 8 . The Bhaikh of Kuwait himaelf mould also be happy ta do wi thout boundariea in Uie desert* and in 1981* before the Uqair Conference* admitted to najor Here that no frontier was neoesaury between hi® territory and Majd {jtolitieul Agent* Kuwait's Mo. \ I61-C** 4 ** 7 . 5 ^ oiaii idi AhM«(t would now llkir ti»« throw JUiwult triboo to be reiunted to hin. It lo an intereotii% that nfwan, l^ara. and tlubaihi/a, wft&amp;ioh are oltuatod well within ttw ^rooent farty-wile rwllifan boumlar/ of Kuwait p ar« etill aeRoidered to belong to Uw nutair Aiwa. In order to attain tlkta object ntmikh haiuad han augmented to olonel Plakaon t hie v t»litioal A^or t $ prwaiaiably bwoauoo houmiarioo now appear to be neoewaarj though lie wae willing to diapenwe with then in 1 ^ 81 1 that the boundary of Kuwait elu&gt;uld atari fron hohat Bulbul and ^ee through ttta, 4ariya al &gt;ifla # Jariya al Ilya. mbra. dUTa to nett the Batin at nafar (eneiuded)* Theee aire the bo aidariee deewrlbed in the Anglos urkieii Conwentlon of 1815 . on which all the hoi kite of Kuwait hare laid etreea. the Uomrent ion no 1 raiii'ifcd oik wnu ^uuee .iJcr Uy ' 8* jailing return of the ttutair Aiwa, which in wore than he wait really expect, the Shaikh aeKc for the return of the Ajnan or the Awaalsa. preferably Ute forxa* er. idu&gt; hare a reputation for bravery and who are always restive under Bin baud's control. irhs Awanln on the other hand are not regarded as a noble tribe. the Bedouin will not intexmsrry with Data freely am look down on than as poor spirited. they oan. however, on oeoaeione aa&lt;|uit thesmelves ns well as any Arab tribe as was shown when Oie Ajmm attaoked then at Al Bit ha in June 1880 . 8* *?im halkh lias told Colonel lok^n th^t he no faith in hie townoaen to protest hie territory fron serious raids. All 2 &amp;e would sxpeot item to us is S»Hwe work acid the repelling of petty raids. He *e- oepted the proposal to man armoured oars with his *ub~ Jests (esc my telegram Ho. 18 ) as a ^ijg allsr , but no Kuwaiti would over have the sour age to stand up to the Akhwan . swing to Ute prestige of the desert vkhwan xam to-a ay» w t««4oy Ui« town dweller. Tim :)m,Xkh urges thut the only reel resMitiy is Um retui , ii of one or wore of his tribes. 1 oonsioer it would be * wuste of tlM sad trouble to stteiipt to perouode bin :;aud to allow tbs Kutair and Ajwali, of wliow he is afraid 9 to return to the allegiance of the Al Htabah of Kuwait. The Awasin however are distinctly a Kuwait tribe and it la possible that he way counter*t. to their return to their old allegiance. Although the prestige of the Akhwan is great, the events of this year Bust have dons a great deal to destroy that religious ferocity on which it rested, and even the \wasia supported by Kuwait** towed ears triiould aot a. a rtiicid for Kuwait against all but raids on a grand soale. l i append a rough shstsh nap prepared bp Cel* odel Tsicboon showingthe range of tlie nutair Aiwa, Ajaas and Awasin. | | 1 an not aware whether youwouid be willing to re-open wLtli Bin 3 aud the question of boundariee, which night give rise to oounter-elains on the Iraq frontier. It will be seen that Uie AwasiM ran*3* e*tend a down the coast of tite 'ereiiui Gulf through the neutral sons ana for some miles into what is recognised as sajd territ ory. It would probably suffice if Bin r&gt;aud nerely aetanewledged then to be a Kuwait tribe end renounced &lt;ul rights over ttei. rhis question of the rstvms of a tribe to his allegiance is important as, although in wise of the anticipated os 1 lapse of the fanatical AKhwen Movement 1 attach greater weight Uuun the Shaikh hinself to the iMportimee of hia anwd care as a protection, Kuwait Is at present largely defenceless. However much sin Baud may tie himself by paper agreements about Outturns, he will always in the future be able to stop trade again by launching raids into Kuwait territory. it is clearly sin .'taud*s policy, wltenever he thinks it is in illsTelegram (c). Prom - Political, KUwait. To - Besident, susiiire. Repeated Higiiooma, Baghdad and S peoial ,B&amp;sraii. Ho.478. Dated 16th August 1929. Shaikh reports express messenger arrived this morning from Ajman headquarters bringing news that 200 Ajman raiders on 8th August intercepted baggage of Saud, King^ son, at Abu Jiffan important strategical point 7 q U hles east Riath and destroyed it and entire escort. Raiders then overtook Baud's car .convoy in heart of Dahana, and captured fourteen motor cars in night attack. Two cars escaped and got through to Hoffuf containing King's son, Saud al Arafa and Suleiman al Arafa. * ‘ Jhaikh who considers information reliable has had news confirmed by friend in Bahrain. Addressed Bushire repeated High Commissioner for 'Iraq and Special Basrah. political Telegram (c). Prom - Political, Kuwait. To - Resident, Bushire. Repeated Highcona, Baghdad. No. 479. Dated 16th August 1929. Reference my 466 of 12th August. Confirmed that after Duwishls attack, Ifcn Mashur, al Rufadi, and obeid al Humaid detached themselves and proceeded Ataiba country. t party raided outskirts Zilfi en route. Obeid al Humaid is person connected King's court Baghdad. Unconfirmed report has it that Duwish has summoned Ajman shaikhs meet him at Mahairiyeh due west Nta. Addressed Bushire repeated Baghdad. Pol itical.Telegram (c). prom - Political, Kuwait. To - political, Balarain. Repeated Resident, Bushire. No.482. Dated 17th August 1929. Shaikh anxious to prevent Al Ribai confidential agent of Bin Saud now at Bahrain from coming to Kuwait, says he posses| definite information that man intends starting subversive movement against himself among local populace. Can you prevent his sailing in tactful way, and without letling it be known request comes from Shaikh. Addressed Bahrain repeated Bushire. Political. Telegram (c)* prom - political, Bahrain. To - political, Kuwait. Repeated, Bushire. No.998. Dated 18th received 19th August 1929. Your 482 dated 17th August. Al Ribai has already boarded Bankura bounded for Kuwait. Addressed Kuwait repeated Bushire. political.Telegram (c) . prom - political, Kuwait. To - Resident, Bushire. Repeated Highcoma, Baghdad. No.481. Dated 17th August 1929. Letter arrived from Duwish to Shaiidi last night informing latter that he had returned to Tawal Janubi which is rectangle formed by wells Safa, ^araa, Haba, wabra. He reports Bin Baud's detachment retired if*om Hafar Ats, states al Dahaina not I bn Mashur led party sent to Ataiba as reported yesterday. My opinion Duwish will now either strike al Awazim or at Biu Baud's shammar and Dhafir camped Neutral Zone. Braih at Hafar in latter contingency will probably join him. Addressed to Bushire repeated to Baghdad. political.D.O. .K0.4fa3. Very confidential. The Agency f KUWAIT. iw/b/iiii. My dear I was dining with sheikh Ahmad last night, and after dinner he took me aside and told me the following. He was convinced, he said, that King F&amp;isal was in the closest touch with the insurgents and was incouraging them. That of the many Agents the King had sent down to Kuwait, one in particular known in the telegraph office as ”Kohomed bln Ibrahim” was ecpedally active. This person sent regular telegraphic and written information to the Kings confidential Ataiba pecetary 'Abdullah al Mizfir', (who represented him at the OJair Conference of 1922,^) j personally suspect that the said Mohomed bin Ibrahim is none other than ’’Tifullah Saleh jr.B.' but have yet to prove it!!! The Sheikh went on to say that A 1 Puwish failing to get any change from H.M.G. when he made his recent requests through himself the sheikh of Kuwait and me, had now decided to try his luck with the High Commissioner Baghdad, to this end he had recently nont the notcrioue A li ghuarlbat to Baghdad armed with hie net elgnet ring, with inatructlone to have the necessary letter prepared in suitable language, and sealed there for presentation to Kle Excellency the High Commissioner. The letter would take the form of a prayer that he A 1 Puwish who with his tribe were free born men struggling for their liberty against a tyrant, should not be treated by H.M.Goutcasts and slaves In rebellion against a R.M.G. as master. But as the British loved liberty so H.M.G. should look upon their efforts to free themselves from Bin Bauds bondage with sympathy; that he Al puwish dia not ask for aaBistance from H.M.G. but merely for neutrality; that It was his gawlehi right to expect this, for neither he nor his people were criminals. That any harm they had done to Iraq and the English was under orders. That as neutrals H.M.G. shoula not sto.j food and necessities of life going to their women and chil^ -dren etc. The letter when ready, said sheikh Ahmad, would he thought oe present-* to the High commissioner through King Faisal, who sympathised with, If he was not the originator of the idea. This morning I confirmed the sheikhs statement re telegrams going to Abdullah bin Miz,fir, from the postmaster, who reported that many had been sent lately. I also manageu to lay hands on one of Mohomed al Ibrahim s receipts, which was found in Mullah Saleh's office and which I enclose. The poatmaster said he would shew me all telegrams sent if I would ask him to do so in writing. This I do not propose doing. Sheikh is annoyed with King Faisals intrigues here to say the least of it. yours sincerely,Telegram (c). Prom - political, Kuwait. To - Resident, Busdire. Repeated Highcoma, Baghdad. No.485. Dated 19th August 1929. W NO* 481 of 17th August. Shaiidi reports this morning that Dawish arrived at iiaiar al Batin in force last Friday object to carry Braih along with dii^, and attack sbammar and Dhafir in Neutral Zone. Latter bearing arrival retired hurriedly former into 'Iraq latter todays Hail. My opinion Dawish will return to his base, taking Braih with him. Addressed to Bushire repeated to Baghdad. political.Telegram (c). From - political, Kuwait. To - Resident, Bushire. No.486. Dated 19td August 19B9. Ibn Mashur acting for Dawisii has written Shaikh asking if Akhwan camels may graze Subaihiyah, he guarantees on behalf Akhwan to withdraw them on first sign advance by Bin Saud. Shaikh has given negative reply. Political.Telegram (c) . Prom - Resident, Qushire. To - Highcoma, Baghdad Repeated to Kuwait. No. 825. Dated and received 20th August 1929. Kuwait*s telegram 16th August No.478. Bahrain confirm AJman burnt five motor cars belonging to Amir Saud which were stuoic in Dahana. They killed all drivers and fought engagement with Baud's men killing 25 of them. Addressed to High commissioner for 'Iraq, Baghdad repeated to Kuwait. Resident.Ttlcgram Tran Political rtuonlr*. H.U 4 b* Kecr^tary of ^tutc for tho Colonieo, London, no* 87. copy to- High Couwifioloner for Iraq* mgiauwl, Ho. 807. H.K's. Agent, Jeftiluh, Mo. 807. (Jiy lUr MftlX.j Bated 13th August 1^29. warwly profeBoing friendship. His Majesty asHures ihaikh his spiritual ho»e is Kuwait, thanks hi* for denying supplies to rebels, offers to send hi* by sea and land forces to assist hi* in repelling rebels, uf»d apologises for flag incident. Agsat, rickoon(shoia he has w*tpreviouslyJ, expressing pleasur at his appolntxaent, at preeent juncture, to Kuwait, urging hira to blockade and above all prevent rebels fro* crossing into Kuwait territory, and proposes regular exchange of ideas by wans of letters to combat rebel novenent*. and Hie Majesty (who are personally known to each other )T 1 think it would be better that Hickson should wi*c me con- « tents of messages he proposes oeming for your formal ap*rova before he despat dies any replies. Kven though Messages may purport to be private letters between friends, Hickson now holds official position as i*&gt;litic*a Agent at Kuwaiti Hin Baud if it suits hi* will try to hold Hie Majesty** Gowrn- rent responsible for anything Dickson nay have said, while repudiating anything which way not be to fcls liking. British Agent at Jeddah. I have accordingly told Dickson not to return any answer till your orders have been received, by ms. Bin Baud has sent rsjyfty to the toiler of Kuwait His Majesty has also written to the i J olltieal 7)o you approve exchange of letters between Hickson Ibn Baud *ay aloo attempt to short-circuit ?,h* yoregoing refers to *y telegram of 17th July 1989 Mo. 21. Dost copy sent to the -Political A^eni^at flCiAstvtiA/r f xttctfa' for information only. SD/ G.G..T. PAD r,f T^ rn &gt; Lieut.-Colonel, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.-TKIVFGIAM'. PROK, Resident pushire. TO. Dickson, c/o political Kuwait. NO. fc24. Dated l^/b/2y reed. 2U/fc/^w. Will be grateful for your advice in following matter. It is proposed establish service light aeroplanes connecting Bahrein with Airways service. In 1927. Bin Baud on advice pin jilawi turned down similar proposal as likely exacerbate tribal feeling aroused by Iraq frontier posts. Shortly F.F.O. will be asking Ibn saud for settlement various controversial matters connected with last two years raids. (Following questions now arise.) (a) would Bin Baud now be likely reverse his refusal of two years ago. (b) It was suggested if proposal went through Qusaibi that it might be acceptable to B.S. Cc) supposing Qusaibi agreed make proposal, woulci his being used arouse jealousy in other authorities. Cd) Would his Intervention be likely succeed. ((e) would project have better chance success If deferred till next spring, thus giving local situation time to improve. W« are anxious to avoid taking *ny step which may prejudice obtaining Bin Bauds consent establish regular and permanent British Air Service with fixed landing grounds on Rasa coast when time comes. Make your observations as full as possible, senciing leaves In next few dt-tys. by post if one« - '■ ' , ($) T t r’Olltioal ASKlty, KU*«lt. D.O.NO. Uj i Oat«n the Oitad Augwt 19^J. 1|W jLo. , K in reply to your telegr*a ho.394 of 19th August. It p^e-a? to a# th* matter ra»olT«p It elf into two Ispuas (p) Whether Alrwpyp o»n arrange to run etrplght through froa Kuwait to B A txrPin f pULPpenPing with any eaergenoy landing groundP en route, ’ t \ . V' a » %»; K- . *: iv or (b) whetner they aupt hove puoh eaergenoy l^naing grounds arranged t cr and Ip id out before th*y o n start their pervloe# B. If Airways oan agree to (e). the oape Ip greatly *1 .am plified, &lt;^nd I see no reason why witn the improved engines of to-d^y and with specially large petrol tan/Oi fitted tney should not dlsoard the Idea eltogetner of energenoy grounds. rney t do not have any between gushlre and Lingah that I /enow of, and the distance as the orow flies is only gao miles (say 300 flying miles) between guwalt ana geneae, s mere nothing. If they oould deoiae definitely on this oourse then the Bilers of Kuwait and Bahrain would be the only person^ whose permission need be asxed and this only a? a oourtesy measure. Bin gaud's permission need not in my opinion, be aSstea at all t for aeroplanes to fly aown his oo*st-line, providea tney v remained outline the three mile limit* 3• If on the other h nd Airways insist on (b) being neoessary, tnen the natter becomes far more diAfioult, for tne simple reason that (a) one not on y will h^ve to square b^&gt;a gaud, a very pig headed person, but (b) there exist no villages or towns nips along the whole coast of f|as*a exoept Juba 11 and ^atif where any form of control may be said to o^lst. The two above mentioned places do however possess Amirs, To liieutenfnt-Co^nai c .C .J.aarrett, C* r '•I«,C«I*E*, goa'ble political ivesiaent in the perrian Oulf, Bus air e-a- (t|&gt; 'll 4. How if you loo«c nt tnw aAy, if ^na Juowll 4o And 80 r«0p«otivwly from BAhrain oouid bw nadrn ufw of, provided ground condition^ ^ere PuitAoie, out wn»t of tdm wild p treton oetween Jubsil And tne Kuwait ooraer. do viliAgep exiPt and oertainiy taere ip never any control, eitder now or at One beet of ti.aep. In tniF area on*y AJtan, Awaaim an d B**mt -Thalia oedouinr roam, and tdeae are diffioult fol&lt; to tAO&lt;Cle a Iwayp , 6. An emergency ground oouid probably oe fixed up at Subalhiyeh on ,^u wA lt border, though X have not ween the t ground. 6 fhe beat solution would be for Airwaye to deoide on Subaihiyeh (or Shaiba), Jubail and ^tif ab emergency landing grounda, and neglect the long a tret oh Juba 11 Subalhiyeh (17o mllea) • 6. Having aecided on thla and .mowmg how horrioiy aupplclouB Bln Saud ia of aqy Qovemaent move, however innoo nt. I Bhoul d get (^oBalbl to oe approached oy Alrwaya direct, with the re^ueat tnnt. he act a a their agent in the matter and on tnelr oehalf open the uueBtion with oin Baud, (^oaalol muat etphaaige the fact that tne or it ip h government and Boyal Air force are not in tne picture at all, anu tnat the new air-line will oe to serve fearl verohanta 1 interests solely. He should point out his. Bin Baud's per mis a ion, is only sought for aaohines to fly along the ooapt line, and possibly land at Jubail or (^atlf should accident or forced landing be necessary. Should ^osalbl consider tost din Baud would prefer that machines actually call at ^tlf or Jubail as a regular measure, he oouid be allowed his discreet tlon to suggest such course. 7. X thin* th ^t (^osaibl who seems more than anyone nnxlous to get tn» line established, oouid persuade Bin Saud to agree to all Airways demands. He must however tao*le Bln Baud personally anu not write. X again emphasise that neither the political Agent, Bahrain, and oerta inly not His Majesty's government (though Jeddah) ehould figure in the business at all. Let (^osaibl do it ell in his ©apacity asi ® -13 —ti— Agent r or Airways, m purely oooMMroUl oonoern. Art^rwardp *n«n n* tv* a* got Bin daud to agree, eijgtle ter up oould oe drawn laJ**-* up by Airways ana (^opa tutt»na Mbwn all A* ready H1 p MaJePty*p Qovernaent oould be oalied In to wltnepp the doouaent or do- ounentp, in the InterePt of Airwayp. 8* ^eaeuoer tn -1 if onoe din Saud geta It Into hip head that HI* Urgapty'p Oovernaent Ip behind the Poheae, he Ip oa- pable 1»ot ppolllng all, po fearful and PUPplolou* Ip he of fancied British intriguep agalnpt his* Bln Baud too Ip parbloularly difficult *hen yoiitioal offloere tao«le hla about anything. I ^cnow thlP froa experience. ** alpo ha* another characteriPtio, and clever aan though he Ip, he Ip eaPlly perauadea to follow a particular line of thougut or Idea by sen juqz wno put round hla, and theae in aoPt oapee are anti- gr ItlPh. 8. finally taking your actual ^uePtlone aeriatia my anawerp are ae foilowa;- (a) Bin Baud eight be peraueded to rewerwe hie refuaal of 8 yea re ago if approached cleverly and not by Hi* MejePty'p Oovemeent direct. He turned down Royal Air force propopalp / nor thing of leperiai Airwayp, (b)rhe beat chance of getting Bln Baud to aooept to day ip f I thln^c, to put up the propoeals through %Q*a icl. (o) fhe Baling uee of ^oaalbl would not arouee Jealouay in other authoritiea certainly not in the elndP of anyone in xuw»lt. After all having got our pc heme through we can alwaye clip i^oealbl'e winge. (d) ^oealol'p Intervention would be Bore lively to puooeed than anyone elee'p. fhe family la persona grata with Bin Baud and both Abdul Amis and eepe- daily Abdul Bahian have the neoeeeary way with then, and can over perpuade Bln Baud if they llKe. (e)I tnin* project would have better chance of puooepe if deferred till next pprlng, but 1 should be in clined to get Air**y* to approach the (^opalblIFTODIATE. TEX^ETtRAH. (m) * FRPH. Political Kuwait. TO. (1) High coma Baghdad, (3) Resident Bushire. No. 4bb. Dated ^2/b/29. I^.8t night Ibn Mashur with ten men arrived eight miles from city, asked for Interview on important matter. I visited him at &amp;a.m. today. Ibn Mtshur requests immediate permission visi^^dad, he has been deputed by Akhwan leaders as their envoy, to lay their case before K.M.R., as they convinced H.M.O. does not know true facts of their struggle for liberty. jbn W.hur .l.M. l~v. b, c»r for Bb.r.1. Sblurdb, .bbMbS, dealreo »..ur.nc. h. »» bl. ..rv»b, .111 nob he interferred with en route. Would be very grateful urgent telegraphic reply as to whether I can issue necessary travel permits, as have promised Ibn Mashur an answer by Friday night. Addressed Righcoma, repeated Resident. political.Telegram (c). From - Political, Kuwait. To - Resident, susdire. Repeated to Higdcoma, Baghdad. No.489. Dated 22nd August 1929. Your 825 and my 488 today's date. Commander of party which destroyed oars with Ibn Masbur. He assured me that fourteen cars burnt these be captured in following order four in one place, six in another, 'three in third and one by itself. Addressed to Bushire repeated to Baghdad. political 489., Telegram (c). prom - political, Kuwait. * To - Resident, sushire. Repeated to Higdcoma, Baghdad No.490. Dated the 22nd August 1929. My 485 of* 19th August. Ibn Mashur told me that Aichwan were under ibn Rashidan and al-puqm’s son not Duwish. party afterwards raided Shaimaar south Bir Ansab and took 600 camels. Added al-Duwish due Hafar today. Addressed to BU- s hire repeated to Baghdad. political.TELEGRAM. URGENT. FROM. po]Itlcal Kuwait. TO. Reoident Rushire. mo. 4d2. Rated 23/b/29. Your ^31. Reply posted yesterday, should reacji you Sunday, Following is summary my opinion. Firstly. B.S. might be persuaded reverse his previous refusal if approached cleverly, and certainly not by FT.M.G. direct. To this end Airways in their capacity as commersial concern might commence negotiations direct with B.S. through Qosaibi. FT.U.O. to approve every step but keep entirely in background, commercial side of scheme to be empha siz.ed by Qosaibi all through. Secondly. Consider best chance success of scheme through Qosaibi who I understand thoroughly in favour idea. Thirdly. Employment O.oaaibl need not arrouse jealously. Fourthly. Qasalbi family 'peraona 6 rttn» with Bln S^ud and more likely succeed than any one else. Fithly. Project would have better chance success if def erred till spring but should be inclined get Air* ways to approach Qaaaibi confidentially now, and let latter decide whether the time is propitious or not. Sixthly. Whole difficulty to my mind lies in whether Airways insist emergency landing grounds in RS-ssa, or not. If not and I fail to see necessity myself there is no reason to approach B.S. ut all. jf they do and R.S. Is not amenable to Airways reque&amp;s as put forward by Qusuibi, then solution lies in providing Flying Boat servoce.TELEGRAM. FROH. ReBident Ruahlre. •pO politicfa.1 Kuwait. ^ro. ^31 pated &amp; reed. 22/8/20, please reply urgently by telegram to my telegram po. &amp;24 August 10th. proposed Air service Bahrain. TELEGRAM. FROM. Resident Bush ire. TO. Political Kuwait, pated &lt;* reed 23/6/29. jiro # ^3 9 As Colonial Office were pressing for reply, I had to answer their enquiry without waiting your repl^ toFROM Resident Rushire. TO Political Kuwait. FO. S33. Rated 22/b/29. I have referred your telegram Fo. 488 to secretary of state for Colonies, with recommendation that permission be refused. TELEGRAM. FROM. Righcoma Baghdad. TO political Kuwait. no. Addressed to Bushire repeated Kuwait. Secretary of state for Colonies 28y. Reference colofli 1 -! Office 245. j agree that Jbn Mashur should be refused permission come Baghdad and should be ordered quit Kuwait at once, presume you will give necessary orders Kuwait.TELEGRAM. IMMEDIATE! FROM. Resident Bushire. TO. Political Kuwait. NO. 634. Dated and reed. 23/&amp;/2V. Addressed. Kuwait, repeated Baghdad, your telegram No. 4fa6, secretary of State for Colonies directs that permission requested by Ibn Mashur should be categorically refused, and that he should be ordered quit Kuwait Territory at once Please Inform him accordin^lw.COKPIDENTIAL. Political Agent, Kuwait. H.E.Shaikh Ahmad al-jabir as-Subah, C.S.I. ,C.I.E., Ruler of Kuwait. Dated the 18th Rabia I, 1848 (23rd August 1929). IMMEDIAT E. After Compliments. Yesterday when I visited ibn M a shur, he requested permission to proceed to Baghdad and se the High Commissionei I told him I could not give him this permission myself, but would ask the High commissioner and the Resident in the Persian Gulf for orders, and would let him have a reply by tonight. I have now to inform Your Excellency that I have this morning received the following reply from His Majesty's Government to whom the mat er was referred. 'Secretary of State for Colonies, London, directs that permission requested by Ibn Mashur should be categorically refused and that he should be ordered to quit Kuwait ter ritory at once'. I shall be greatly obliged if Your Excellency will transmit the exact wording of the message as received by me tolbn Mashur before this evening, an d would ask that you order him to leave Kuwait territory at once. I send also letter from myself to Ibn Mashur which I would ask you to kindly send out to him with your letter. Usual Ending. Let•er. Erom - To No.493.-(ri) 2 H' From - political Agent, Kuwait. To - Shaikh parhan ihn Mashur. No. Nil. Dated 18th Rabia I, 1848 (23rd August 1929). After compliments. As promised by me to you yesterday, Ii referred your request to proceed to Baghdad, to His Majesty's Government I have now to inform you that a reply has come, saying that your request is refused and you are forbidden to go to Baghdad. Also that you should leave Kuwait territory immediately you receive this. This is what had to be said. Usual ending.No.199. XiriDDA, July 30, 1929. Lir, 1th reAreaM to my ti.legrv.ai No.114 of to-4. y iu,U, 1 iuve the honour to enoloae the tranal tlon of th a * ;0Ch * “ ”***« iu toe Um el ,ura, which the King ie aV ted to h. ve addressed to the chiefs of the Atalb. h tribe who had boon ammsoned to meet him Wuldahi on hla ».gr to jUyadh. as you will remmber, at the time of the King** departure from Meoou for N,jd t it w 8 expected that he ^ midht have trouble on the » y with the Atulbeh tribe, but owing to the elaborate ;r cuustlons taken by him and no doubt also to tn* arrive of news of the defeat of the .gm&amp;n tribe, hla journey through the doubtful area appear to have been ucoompliehed without incident. 3. In his s.jeeoh Ibn “aud does hot mlnoe matters, i partioulariy when he reminds his alienee of the d.y when wltn band oi iorty men he attacked and defeated them, •nd ahen he te-lls them ttiat his jwople are their taaat-.rs &lt; ^ dl soeudantn oi tiielr masters by right of tho aword. •are there not a number of you* he says ‘upon whose fathers’ and grandfathers’ neoks my aworo and ay fathers’ and &amp;r -mi.fathers* swords nu-de play*. *• it the atalbap tribe are now prepared to hel him;., in carrying on the government of which they reap tac benefits and km nimself nes wo bear tne worries and itlsin-pa, well and good. If not he will wash his hands 01 lheffi , Ud the&gt; * ** understand tnat he will deal ta rdly wiUi tiiem. o# HdBi i4uJeti t/* i X*iii0ip4uL Ol‘ o tiit8 ^or i'orel&amp;n Its.&amp;• Ibn Baud on his ^art profeaaes to roady to hear any coai laint and to attend to it, if need he tafcine action against himself, his sms, his brothers or his emirs. He also oalls upon the chiefs to tre t their men well nd to de l justly ift them, and he declares an amnesty in the case of 11 those who departed from his allegiance hut haYe now return© to the fold. annihilate the Ajman tribe iund roposes to send army ; gainst th ® on August 6th, all backsliders who have now returned to the true religion are to be present. If &lt;ny one is absent without a proper excuse the ;.enalty is death or the amreet of hie rmjj and the confiscation of his . rms nd horses, 7, Apparently &lt;n official note was t of the rooee. lugs and signed by witnesses, b. No det ila have reached me of the judgment passed by Ibn Baud on the leaders of the tribes which is referred to in his apeeoh, 9, Cftpies of this des atoh and its enclosure h-ve be n j ddressed to His Majesty's High Commissioners for hgy t, Palestine and Ira&lt;i, the Government of India in the Foreign end Political ’department, the clitic 1 te; idents at Aden, Bushir^ and Bahrein , nd the . olitical ^gent at ko eit. Finally he states th.t he wi hes to highest respeot. 2 have the honour to be with the Your most obedient, humble Servant, W,L.BOND,Speech of His Majesty the King. The Kin^ after thanicing God sai&amp;i I promised to meet you in this place (Al Buwadami) and I know well that you can he classified under three headings: one part I am sure is very religious and faithful to its country ^nd Government. The second ...art is afollower of every troublesome leader, and the third, which 1 thank God is the sxiL.llest of the three, is the mo: t trouble some. I wnht on pilgrimage directly &lt; fter Sibilla and I iiad. not time enough to ascertain wno are the good nd who c.re the had among you, because after the people of ^ibilla were badly defeated, everybody was afraid and everyone gave evidence of obedience. I was thus unable to know who was honest and who was false in his pretence. God nas always been with me v.nd has always revealed to me those vho wish to h^rm their religion, king and country. The ingratitude of the AJwan , nd those who followed them was a testimony against those who wish ill to their religion and country, and showed them up, and showed their sympathy with the backsliders and debauchees, so that they became known to the Moslems. My recour e to God and my adherence to the Mohammedan tanots and my following of tlu Moslem sheikhs and Ulemas, all prevent me from losing my self- control, and I therefore before continuing my speech mt: wish to show you the legal veraiot issued by the Moslem Ulemas against the backsliders and also the lives advioe given by them in this matter, so that he who / lives openly and that h. who dies dies open**Then His Majesty ordered that the legal verdict should he read. It was heard with tears, solemnity and revenence, all asking for pardon. His Majesty then proceeded with his speech. You people of Nejd (I do not mean hy the people of Hejd those who have made a covenant with the word of (k&gt;d, but those who may belong to those backsliders or debauchees or those who may he ve asaoci ted with them or agreed to their ideas) you all know that we are your m sters end descend&amp;fcts of your masters and that, by the will of God and the word 'unity* and tne sword we ere your Kings* We were kind to the we^k ^nd respectful to the old umong you, and so you became rich after being poor and high after being low. Then the devil blew in your nose nd you thought accordingly th^t you had to interfere in the Government's work ,-nd to give orders whicn you h d no j owers conferred on you to give. So things went from bad to worse and I was forced to put an end to it. I sent people to w\ rn you, but with no result. Then o me the d y of Bibilla ana according to God's wish it was the sword th,t was to give 4he final Judgment. \ v Now you people of Nejd, if you wish to help me in carrying on this government of which you re«.p the benefits and of which I have th bear the worries and mishaps, this will be good for you, but if you wish to help our enemies, I shall wash my hands of you and you will see wh-t strict measures I shall take against you. I am sure you have not forgotten that day when I attacked you with my forty men. You were under the leadership of Ibn el Bashid who had a large numbernumber of men and soldiers, with the Arabs and the Turks bi.eKing him und supplying him with &lt; rms, ^uns anu money* There was the Hej&amp;s Government also helping him. You have not forgotten wu.t 1 did to him with that 3 nit.* 11 b**nd of men, hut God at last helped me, so that I killed the shepherd tnd ruled the flook. las any one of you who helped me that day done any favour to me*’ iro, none of you did me any favour. G d only did me favour An that day. iiAe there not a number of you upon whose fathers' v..nd gr. ntifathers* nooks iny sword and that of my father and grandfatners made lay, and this for your disobedience and for your aelpint, the backsliders. Yourpeople of Kejd, I h.;Vo promised God tnree thingsi lirst, to summon the ^eople to believe in the unity of God and make use of the :&gt;haria in giving judgment, secondly, to kill the insloent with the sword, thirdly, to reward those who do good ana to unish the; evil-doers., and equally l w&lt;nt three things from you; lirst, if any of you is ill tre tod or lias any com laint to offer he should tell me, and oarsed by he who conceals hos complaint. I promise you before God that 1 am prej ared to look into every complaint and to take the necessary action even if against myself, my sons, my Brother or my amirs. secondly, you leaders of tae tribe, 1 order you that, should you receive any benefits or oliarity foom me, your men should sh^re la it with you. You should treat tnem well ^nd not ^unish them or let anybody P uni oh them when the punishment is not in accordance with the Mohammedan Sharia.Thirdly f I want all of you es eoi&amp;lly those who helped me in m&lt; ny urt vious or recent h&lt; penings and those who hel ed tiie haokaliders hut have now retuinea to tne fold, to _romise me first to advise any baokslider or disobedient man that if he returns to the fold, he will be *;iven safety md security, I be does not, &amp;ill him, and let the Mohammedans he well rid of him. iwlso note tuat I want to annihilate these Ajm^n and aa*e an end of them, and that by the will of God, I shall send an army on the fir t of Babi el ivw&amp;l iAugust ath) and I shall not allow ny one of those who helped the baoJtsliders and have now returned to the true relition to be i bsent. If any one ol them is absent without a proper excuse, eitnet #ill liim and let the Mohammedans be rid of him or arrest his &lt; ray nd oonfinoate his arms end horses. The Kin£ afterwards pardoned those who returnfid to the true w y of religion and gr nted safet and security to all of them. All this was noted down in a paper whioh fter being read by the clerk was signed by; heikh Moh mmod Ibn Abe el i-atif. hheixh Omar ibn Abd el h«itif. abdullah ibn Abd el : aliab ibn Sahem as witnesses. Ole leaders who attended the speech and to whom this Speech was deliver d were: bheikli Omar Ibn Abd er Rahim.n Ibn Rabean. Jlxeiich aihgan BuJ&amp;d Ibn Hamid (brother of Sult n Bin Bujad now prisoner.) Jiheikh ^uaJil hi Haidal» hheikh halt n Abu el Ala. ^ heikh Kh led Ibn Game. All ohi fs of tne different sections of the At loah tribe,p. Secretary of State for the Colonies, London. political Resident, Bushire. Groyeminent of India, Siicla. High Commissioner, Baghdad, !fo 239 iiated lath reed 19th August 1929. Your telegram of 15th Juno ho 14. Departments interested have considered in the light of the recommendations made by you, air Gilbert Clayton, the Air Officer tfomanding in Iraq., and the Government ci' India, ttie oeat means oi 'Obtaining ihn Gaua’s consent to the proposed s eariing service, including establishment ana use of emergency landing grounds on Aasa Coast, i without whicn it is improbaole Imperial Airways would wish to unueroane service;• There has been general desire to promote service, out the : following criticisms, on which we should like to have your observations before arriving at decision, have been directed against putting the project forward at the present time and through ^usalhi as intermediary. (1) Ibn Baud turned down in September 1927 a sinlil.r proposal on the strength of an adverse report from the Loir of Hasa, wno deprecated the proposed flights in views of tribal feeling, already much disturbed at rumoured establishment of military posts near the Iraq, frontier. The posts are still a highly controversial issue and the brioal situation in North Eastern Nejd very unsettled. Further, His la tJ esty'8 Government will shortly oe asking I bn Gaud ior settlement of several important and contentious questions such as restoration of luot by Gojdi to Iraqi tribesmen, I bn Baud/* efforts to seduce Iraq.! tribesmen to bejdi Telegram From To Repeatedallegiance, raiding and counter raiding on the Trans*-®) Jordan frontier etcetera, Is there any reason to suppose that Ihn Saud, with or without consulting the Emir, would now he disposed to reverse x^evious adverse decision?. (2) Supply of British Air Craft and 1 ilots to the HeJaz is still problematical. *e hope however that it will be realised. Its effect should be considerable. Would not Ibn Saud be likely to regard British flights over, and landing grounds in Hasa territory more favourably al ter he was - * assured of supply of Air Craft from British sources, in which case the landing grounds might be of practical value to him?. (3) Even if Qusaibi (whose pjfst record incidentally is none too good ~ cf. ©ur unfortunate experiences in 1923 - and by whose use the jealousy of other local authorities might surely be provoked) submitted proposal, to Ibn Baud it must neverthlecs, as at present proposed, appear as emanating from His I'ajesty’s Government through yourself. In view of Ion’s own request t; Sir Gilbert llaytjn in August 1928 that all co. munications to him from His Majesty’s Government shou d be made through Jeddah and of categorical instructions issued accordingly to His Majesty’s Agent at Jeddah on ipril lich last 7 &gt;*ight not this be prejudicial ?. On the other hand in present circumstances a formal request through Uis Majesty’s Agent at Jeddah might court refusal. (4) Would not the project have a greater chance of success if it was deferred until, say, next leaning season, thereby affording time for the situation to improve for the possible supply of British Air Craft to Ibn Saud and perhaps for a heprosentative of Imperial Airways to negotiate locally, thereby emphasising the commercial and non-political character of the proposed service. e are anxious / you will realise, to avoid taking any step which might increase our difficultieswhe^ the time domes to obtain Ibn Sand's consent to the establishment of a regular and permanent British air seririce along the Persian Gulf with fixed landing grounds etc on the coast of Easa. Secretary of htate f r Colonies. Post copy for information only to the PelitiCfU. Agent, Bahrain Kuwait.^ fid/* C # 0 .,t ^^jj^^rett, Lieut-Col., political Resident in the Persian Gulf* Attested. for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Buenir*, Z\*t Autfit&amp;t 1GS9.bl /20 ( io'm \CP Telegram From To Repeated P. Political Resident, Bushire. Secretary of State for ttie Colonies, London. No 29. Government of India, Simla. No 337. Latoci 23rd August 1929 (1) Ibn Jiia^d, ttie Amir ©f Kasa who advised against the proposed flights in 1927 has resigned his posl^roken in health. He has been succeeded hy Amir Sand. The latter, I hope, will he more progressive. Tho provocation to tribal feeling in the matter of the military posts soill remains hut owing to Dawish*s rebellion the situation has altered considerably. In spite of tho existence of tne posts the tribesmen whose hostility was alleged to he the cause of* Bin Sana’s refusal have sought our aid. Bin Gaud as well, who went so far as to authorise the Royal Air Force to bomo his own tribes in Nejd territory has sought and obtained substantial supports in arms and ammunition and even more valuable moral support vis a vis Kuwait. Though I ©annot giveoa definite opinion as to Bin Gaud’s attitude I consider the omons favourable. (2) I agree that flights along the Hasa coast would probably be regarded by Bin Gaud more favourably^f the project to supply British aircraft and pilots 'to Hejaz materialised. It is possible that advised by his newly appointed representative in Teheran he may wish to impose some restrictions on the lines of tue Persian Reglement pour L^viation. (3) To the hot headed Abdulla husaibi who was temporarily in charge of the firm, were dye to * ^ tue unfortunate experinces of 1923. V.lti the help of ^ head of V e ^j^mjittian Bahadur *bdul Aziz usaibi,Page 2. A a person of a very different stamp^they were put rigtt. I here is something mhat in what you say about jealousy but I believe owing to their position as financial \o\ creditors the ^usaihis have immense influence with Bin Baud. The family has not been approaohed hy me in any way hut I think they might he disposed to help, as Ahdul niman^ a member of the family^ speeiaify chartered an * aeroplalrtt' from Basrah to Banrain in August 1927 and r akes frequent use oi the .-iasrah ;airo service. / bdulla Uoaibi joined witn other Bahrain merchants in an attempt to hire an aeroplane for the Mecca pilgrimage. Owing to failure to a^ree as to price and term the scheme fell through. I do not think unuue importance should he attached to Bin Baud•a request to Sir Gilbert Slayton that all communications should he made though Jeddah. , hen I was Political Agent Bahrein I received direct communications from Bln Baud on trifling matters connected with &gt;amrain, also, as you will see from my telegram Mo 27 of August lota, Bin Baud wishes to open direct private communication with Dickson of Kuwait. I tuink that ^usaihi might he sounded through the adviser to the Bahrein Government or better still one of the Bahrain Sheikhs^ and not through the Political Agent,to see if he would take up t e subject on behalf oi Imperial Airways and the Bahrain Government without appearing too openly in the matter. I myself do not favour approaching Bin Gaud hy a multitude of roads and think that all official communications should he made through Jedaah, hut think we might in this instance attempt the iuaaihi route in the manner stated aoove. I dont think much harm will have been done if Qusaibi fails. I am inclined to agree. September 23rd marks the close of the official diving season thoughPage 5 io *5 \o^ P 0arl buyers stay on atout a fortnight or three wee^s i longer* ore then half the present season is therefore over. Beferenee is to Colonial Office telegram of August loth. Resident. Pofit oopy to the Political Agent, information only. Bahrain t f Pr Kuv/p i t. v &lt;Sd/. C.C, j .Barrett. Lieut-Col• Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Attested. for Secretary to the Political in the Persia.r: Gulf. 2 b /^. ResidentBushire, 25th August 1929. 61/14 Telegram P To From Political Resident, Bushire. Secretary of State for the Colonies London. No 28. Repeated High Commissioner, Baghdad. No 832 Bated 22nd August 1929. Immed iat e On Thursday morning (22nd August), politiaal Agent at Kuwait interviewed Ihn liashur at Pashur’s statement he has 'been deputed hy leaders of the /khwan to lay their case before His Majesty’s High Commissioner at Baghdad for His Majesty’s Government’s information. Ibn Mashur asks for permission to proceed, on tiie 24th of August, without molestation to Baghdad. I recommend that permission he categorially refused and he should be ordered to quit Kuwait territory immediately as bin Mashur has a had record ■ and is one of the cnief rebels against His Majesty King Bin Saua. Copy by post Is forwarded to the Political Agent at Kuwait f®r Information only. ST)/ C.C..T. Barrel t, Lieut.-Colonel, latters urgent request near Kuwait. According to Resident Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Attested: Resident, Persian Gulf.Bushire, 25th August 1929. ii' 61/14 (1^) Telegram From P* Secretary or ;iiiat 8 for the Coloni.ea T.ondon. Political Hooidont, Bubhli*e. • epeatod High Ootomi sal oner, Baghdad. Mo 245. Dated 22nd reed 23 August 1929. Im medi ate. Tlu t yeritiission re^ueated hy Bin Bashur should he categorically refused and that he should he ordered to yuit Kuwait territory at one© is sgreed to by me. Foregoing refers to your telegram No 2J of 22nd August 1929. Secretary of State for the Colonies. XK Copy by powt is forwarded to the Political Agent at Kuwait f©r Information only. ST)/ C.C.J. Barrett, Lieut.-Colonel, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Attested: for Secretary to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf.ccMffUDimriAL . HO.600. political Agonoyt i&amp;iwait. Dated the 26th August 1929. V From To Lieutenant-Colonel H.R.p.DioiCRon, political Agent, Kuwait. The Hon*Ole the political Resident in the Persian Quit, Bashire. Ihn Meshur 1 * visit. * Sir, I have the honour,in continuation of my telegram No.488 dated the 22nd August 1929,to give some details of my con versation with Shaiich Iterhan ibn Mashur which may be found of interest. 2 . I shall not dwell on the main request of Ion Bashur to visit Baghdad Excellency the High Commissioner. This has already been dealt with by telegram. 6 . Ibn nashur camped at Fort Mishrif, or ^psr Surra as it is also known, some 8 miles south of Kuwait. He had oo a e in, he said, via Shaiba, the last village of the (^usur group. 4. He was accompanied by 15 armed men who all wore ^ne large white turban over red kaffiyahs. Ibn Mashur himself carried a sword. 5. The conversation was held in the pr©Fence C) ^ She irt.i Abdullah .W»bir, the Shftiith of Kuwait's right tend mn nd Comiiwader of ijroopa. 6 . The Aldwen Leader appeared to be about 40 yeprs old end j tell. »nd though spe.King for the moat pert in one oej ■ dialeot, he oooeaionelly broke into the Oa-ae.-oue petoia. He greeted ae in friendly meaner end after the ueuax go xpli.nents , oeme to the point of his viait nemely hie desire to proceed to Baghdad. When I asKed him what ha wanted to go tnere for, he replied, 'To explain to the 'kandub ee Semi', our/ diffi- , oultiww position. We are victorious toaay, and aa suoh we consider it a suitable time to reiterate our promises of friendship withths English and to rs-assure His M^Jst ty’saovernaent that we AictwsnS? will not again attaoic the ' Iraq or Kuwait tribeB'. Ha added tiaat the Aichwan leaders bad Bent him ap their envoy realising that though all went well today with them, in the long run, the man with the long purpe and reeouroep would win. When that time oeme they the jkKhwan now in arm? i p gainst Bin Baud intended to 'Hajir 1 ! They oould never endure to live under Bin Baud again. The Ajmen ,MUtair Jita iha and other elementB now fighting against Bin Baud would , he said, leave d their homes for good and BeeK other oountriee. X here interJeote and said, 'Suoh talic is foolish, how oan Puoh a tribe as the AJman possibly leave their homes and gracing grounds in HaPBa'. He quioidy replied,'They went to Semawa for two yearB onoe and oan easily go for more'. 7 . ibn Mashur went on to say, that he hoped to get from Baghdad an apsuranoe that the A**Xiwan would be allowed to enter 1 Iraq and settle down there. They would prove good soldiers and defenders of her border. Failing assistance from 1 Iraq he intended proceeding to Damascus and asking the French if they would aooept them, for 'H*Jir H out of Bin Baud’s dominions they g. I bn Mashur next burpt into the usual violent Akhwan tirade a^inst Bin Baud, quoting instance after instance of his supposed lying, breaking of his plighted word and treaohery. He seemed visibly affected ^hen referring to his women *nd child- fighting he said it was by a trick. Firstly he had given out that in a great victory in Hassa he Bin Baud had ora&gt; a©a Ajman and Mutair and slain all their She iKhs, l ^ assisting actively. Secondly he had promised to re?lease ion Humaid as soon as his daughter 'Watha' oame to Riath and claimed him. The first turned out to be in every way false news, and when the l&amp;y 'Watha' arrived and begged for her fatnei s release some days after Bin Baud’s return to his capital, he ourtly refused to see her or carry out his promise and dismissed her an d party to their homes in very summary fashion. As a matter of faot, he I bn naphur was of opinion that Ibn Humaid no longer lived, and Ataiba were beginning to believe this too. would. r.n whom, h. said. Bln S&amp;ud .till h*ld in dur»noe at Shaaihs, 9. «h«i I *PKed how Bin 8 «ud got through to Riath without £ i-3- He »1bo thouglit the arrival of &amp;1 Daiaaina and obeid al Huaaid in the wept would start trouble again. 1 q. ibn Mpflhur desoribed the reoent raid on ^ya t whioh was a real suooess. only Id of Bin gaud’s detaohiaent had escaped. Al DuwiPh , s strength was 25oG then according to roll call figures. Great oai'e was ta.ien that the reyul. e inflicted on t;he AKhwan oy the Awazim in wap no ^ repeated. Their plans had been joade extra carefully in consequence H, j]ae narration of the cutting up of the iiotor convoy bet ween Abu Jiff an and Hoffuf was left to mo named al Athaixtv. The i latter who had oomaended the actual raiding party stated that 14 cars were destroyed, end gave a oonneoted account of tneir capture and bunking which, he said, took place at four different places in the Dahana . His account rang true and was given in detail. 12. Ibn MBshur thei showed me a bunch of letters and cypher telegrams (figure and letter) addressed to sin Baud from Faisal and other heads of departments in Mecca. These, he said, had been captured from ^osaibi^ messengers coming up from the coast. 13. B*^ ore 1 elosed the interview, Ibn gashur esKed after Mr. philby and Joyce pasha and appeared disappointed when I told him the latter was not in Baghdad now. 14. Though I had been warned that ion Mashur was more fanatiod. than the r^t, X found tnis not so. There was a lot of the 'Hathari' humour about him and he several times saw a jo^e nd laughed naturally. He struck me as having more brains than trie VlStT average Bedouin and probably the^to Baghdad idea emanated from him. 15. in confirmation of reports I had received from elsewhere Ibn MaPbur told me that Bin Baud had individually written to all Akhwan Si»ikhs recently urging them to come back to him wien all would be forgiven and buri\ied. These letters were couched in lan guage and persuasiveness that only Bin Saudinew how to employ, said Ibn Mashur. So far the A*diwan had refu* ed to listen to r: e ' yrer? voice. 16. on my return t o Kuwait and after I had sent out to Ibn Mashur and told him in writing he oould not proceed to Baghdad and must quit Kuwait territory at once, he sent in his secretary one Abdul Aziss of fa of to ask if I could arrange a safe conduct for him to Nuri al Shaalan. I replied verbally to the messenger * &lt;CONFIDENTIAL. No. 499. Folitioal Aganoy, Kuwait. De-ted the 26th August 1929. prom Li«ut«a»nt-Colon#I H.R.F.Dioicson, C.I«E.» political Agent, Kuwait. To The Hon*hie the political Resident in the Persian Oulf, sushire. Al Duwish's efforts to win over the Braih. Sir, | in centinuation of ny telegram No.498 dated 26th August 1929. I have the honour to submit herewith fuller details regarding al-Duwish’fl visit to Haffar. 2, a oo or ding to His s^oellency She iich Ahmaa who oh&amp;aiued his news from a special man whom he had sent for the puivose, al-Duwish arrived at Heifer on 22nd August ^nd on the same day the Braih shaiichs Iton Ashwan and I bn Munaihim arrived baoK from a visit to Bin gaud at Riath. The latter f s news from there was that Bin Baud had collected a large force of ^ahtan Dawasir and Southern tribes with the idee of moving them into out news of a big Ataiba raid against the^htan left at home, caused him to send bao* the Dawasir and qeltan to o a^l Lne situation. 3. Bin Baud had also, according to them, ordered ibn l&amp;»»d to r.aein .t AjibUa only If tie felt e*fe, otherwise tie should retire on Hail. 4 . fo theoi, toe Brelti 3t»ito», Ibn Sato i»d given orders bti»t tnsy should retire froca toe exposed position of Hefffar .1 B»tin, end aove soatii Art&amp;wiyeti. Bin 8 »ud b*d exbreoteu 'an oetli on to* Kor&lt;=-n' that they would not yl&amp;y him f&amp;lBe. 6 . on hearing tniB last, report el-Duwish had uptorfeidea thaa, the Brelh generally, for being foole. 'Eleven times 11.8 Bin Baud broiten hip promis.P to you, do you not consider it time you broke your one enu only oath to him. you ere Brain end Muteiris firpt, afterward? Nejdis. No* is your/ time toone of the other oourpes todey, you will not he allowed to ait on the fence any longer M . By auch and Biailar arguments al- Duwiflh, it seems, prevailed on Ibn Ashwan and Ibn MUnaihia to agree to throw in their lot with the insurgents. nearly ended in a fraoaB, when Azaiyiz ibn Faisal al-Duwish, fearing lest the Braih were about to refuse his father’s offer, suddenly broke in and shouted ' ware not my father present, by Ood, I would lop your heeds off with my own hand, You Cowards!*' &gt; gl-Duwish, however, roundxy rebuiced his son and made immediately as* pardon. He subsequently also forced him to go to the in sulted chieftains* cents end appease their anger oy gifts.and Apologies. 7. At the end of tne proceedings al-Duwish novtng extracted. the necessary assurances of alliance, returned to Safa in the 9/ According to 3 h*i*h Ahmad, not onxy rntny of the Bin Saud’s Shammat? who were camped in tne Neutral ione, but ©l^o 6 . According to the Shaikh's messenger, the negooiatlons •pawal Janubi. Tnere he said he would await the arrival of Ibn Ashwan and Ibn Munaihim. 8 . His son Asaiyiz he sent off with 1000 men of Ifcil not improbaoly tiie objective being Adibbe ibn M'saad. mo^t of the Suwait group of Dhafir, have moved into 'Iraq, example Hautush al-suwait who is now at Chabda. This last may or ioay not be correct news. The portion about puwish and Ibn Ashwan, the Shaikh considers, reliable. I have the honour to b e, Sir, Your mo ft obedieit servant, Lieut-Col., political Agent, KuwaitTelegram (c). Prom - Political, Kuwait. To - Hesident, Busiiire. Repeated to Highcoma, Baghdad. No.498. Dated the 26th August 1929. My 49o of 22nd August. Shaikh informs me that I bn Ashwan and Ibn Munaihim arrived Haffar from Riath same day as Duwish. pormer stated Braih ordered retire at once to Artawiyeh by Bin Saud, but Duwish made powerful appeal and extracted promise ttet they would throw in their lot with rebels. Duwish then returned Safa, shaikh adds it still uncertain how Braih will act. Adores^ ed to Bushire repeate to Bigh Commissioner for Iraq, Baghdad. political.Telegram (c)- From - politloal, Kuwait. To - Resident, Bushire. Repeated to Highooma ,Baghdad* special,Basrah. No.SQl. Dated 29th August 192 9. IMMEDIATE^ My No. 498 of* 26th August. It has now been definitely ascertained that whole of Braih concentration at Hafar have thrown in their lot with insurgents. Main body with leaders arrived Safa and are proceeding Hamudh-wafra area via Wabrah and Jariyah al Sifli. owing to scarcity water southern route camels it seems were sent via jahra. These arrived yesterday. Shaikh on hearing news immediately sent orders that they should quit Kuwait territory via Sha«|/depres ion. Defection this important group is likely Dave serious repercussions everywhere. Addressed to Resident in the persian Gulf repeated to High^ commissioner for 'Iraq and Special, g^srah. polit ical.THKEDIATK. ?■: GFAr. TETiRGRAM. TO. (D Resident Bushire t 2 ) FTighooma Baghdad FROM. Political Kuwait MO. 502 Rated 29/8/29. Kxprer &gt;8 messenger Just in from sub&amp;ihlyeh, reports that Buwish's wife accompanied by wom*n and ©hilaren &amp; old men of Mutair and Rashaida, have suddenly crossed into Kuwait territory with large numbers camels, and have camped Subaihiyeti and other wells immediate vicinity, rruwish’s head slave who in charge states that scarcity camel fodder has compelled them move from namudk, and that they intend leaving Subaihiyeh as soon as puwish tells them where to go. Sheikh Kuwait has sent AbthUlah bin jabir to issue immediate warning that unless everyone across border by noon Sunday there will be trouble. Sheikh thinks move is deliberate plan of Duwish who reported to be at Arak with his fighting strength, to see whether we will bomb women and children crossing border alone. At present sheikh is awaiting Abdullahs return. If his report shews situation as bad as messenger maKes out, shall either proceed subaihiyeh myself or shall recommend bombing in which case consider camels only should be attacked ana not tents, and these only for short period. There is of course a connection between above incident and Braihb move into Itassa, vide my immediately proceeding telegram. Addressed Resident, repeated Klg^ Coma. political 502.IMMEDIATE. TEIiECrRAM. FROM Political Kuwait. TO. (l). Resident Bushire. Righcoma Baghdad. Fo. 5^4. Dated 30/a/a*. Just returned. Duwish has promised me on word of honour to quit Kuwait territory Sunday at dawn, taking all rebel forces women children and camels. Report follows. political.jgOHFIDMTIAL No. 505 . Political Agency, Kuwait. Dated tlie Jlst Anguat 1929 Prom Lieutenant-colonel HoH.P.Dickson, C.I.E., Political Agent, Kuwait. The Eon'ble the Political Eesident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Akhwan forces at Subaihiyeh. s Sir, In continuation of my telegram No .505 of JOtn August, I have the honour to report that I left Kuwait at 5 by car for Warah a prominent hill a few miles north of Subai- hiyeh. At 2 p.m. I had previously in consultation with His Excellency the Shaikh, sent Abdullah bln Jablr with 2 cars to A1 Duwish»s camp with instructions to bring al- Duwish at all costs to meet me . Time would thus be saved as I wanted the heurJ| to get off my above telegram to you. As I was about to leave I was joined by Shaikh Ahmad, who had previously said he would not come as he did not desire it to be reported to Bin Saud that he the Shaikh had held communication with the arch—rebel leader. As an after thought, he said , he had decided to come, both because if the seriousness of the situation, and as a personal guard to myself. As regards any future accusation that might come from Bin Saud he thought my presence with him would be enough to disprove of any suggestion of evil intention. His Excellency was extremely upset at the sudden appearance of the rebel forces inside his border. The move had been made very secretly, and the last news that had reached Kuwait was that Duwish was in the Tawal Janubi. Thefact tkat tliey had all their women and children with them made the Shaikh particularly anxious about the situation. 'At all costs we must save these from being bombed', he kept on saying. 'Both for you English, and my sakes. If there should be a wholesale killing of women the results will be deplorable'. The Shaikh had still another amxiety - this was that if we took air action, the Akhwan in desperation might swoop down on Kuwait and Jah&amp;ra and cause incalculable damage. Their whole strength was at subaihiyeh and all theij leaders were present. Though I had not reported it in my telegram Ho. 505, the Akhwan leaders had talked very big to Abdullah al Jabir, the previous night. 'Let the English bomb us we do not care, it will serve to show us one more enemy and we shall know what to do', they had said, and 'If our women are killed then we shall move north taking Jahsra and Safwan ©n route and proceed via the Euphrates to Syria, in spl£e of the English'. Such and other un necessary talk, which I had not considered it worth while to telegraph, had been conveyed to shaikh Ahmad and was distinctly worrying him. At fl&amp;ra as the road got sandy we waited to see if al—Duwish would turn up. H© arrived at 5*50 p.m., and it was a smart piece of work on Abdullah bin Jabir^s part, for the Akhwan feared treachery, and made every effort to pre vent their leader seeing me. with al-Euwiah came his 5 son©, (excluding Ae&amp;lyl* who left Hafar to raid Lena 7 days ago), al-Fuqm, Z&amp;b Sahman and three other Ajman Shaikhs. In appearance ai-puwish was short with broad shoulders. He had a distinct stoop and a very big head. The point how ever that struck me was his long ugly nose and rather pro truding teeth. His beard was straggly and trained into a point about 9 iuches below his chin. As usual all the members of the party wore white turbans and carried swords and Turkish Mauser carbines.On the whole my interview was a pleasant one, and the Akhwan leaders seemed a merry lot of rascals, friendly and willing to talk. I saw not the slightest sign of any anxiety as to the results of their fight with Bin Saud. One of al-lruwish's remarks to me and which showed how the wind was blowing was, 'we have cleared northern Nejd of Bin Sand’s forces, and we have done the British a good turn by sending baok to ’Iraq some of her recalcitrant tribes like Snammar and Dhafir. We must now deal with Awaslm, those fools who will not take a hint, we wish to detach them from Bin Saud, and if they will not come by kindness, we shall have to worry them by sending snipers at night and shooting up their camps. This will bring them to their senses, we do not wish to kill them. They are not worth it'. After the usual prediiminary salaams etc., I got His Excellency Shaikh Ahmad to open the ball, and he did it extremely well. The gist of what he said was he summed up in the words 'Why Faisal, when Colonel Dickson and I had given you a dosen different warnings not to enter Kuwait under pain of being bombed, you promptly go against our warnings and sneltering yourselves under your women’s skirts invite destruction'. Al-Duwish’s reply was rather typleal and was delivered with a broad smile. 'Oh Ahmad!' he said, ' firstly let me assure you that I knew nothing of our women and oamels entering your territory, as you call it, we were returning from our raids, and my 'Abd' foolishly and against all arders brought all our oamels and women and set them down at Subaihiyeh. Se condly t I am a man, enshaliah, and as such do not believe the English will bomb women and children, and people who have no i quarrel with them.Thirdly . when I saw the harm hy ay •Afcd*, T realised that nothing could he done, so I accepted the inevid&amp;ble and joined the women, hut the 'Abd 11 shall he punished. Fourthly . You talk about a boundary, and Subaihiyeh being in Kuwait, iiy answer is have you told the Hakuma that Subaihiyeh is the ancestral home of the Mutair Aiwa, and of us the Dooshan in particular, also that we the Mu/tair and Ajman are your fighting tribes and have been since the world began. If not you had better do so quickly. We certainly have been enticed away under the name of Religion by Bin Saud but we have no further use for him and as erring children, we now wish to return to our old homes and be under our old Holers. fifthly , we have no quarrel with the Hakuma, and have already told her that she need have no fear from us. Our words are those of true Mussalmin and we do not lie. Since we gave our word, has f Iraq or Kuwait seen anything but peace on her frontiers. Sixthly . We require nothing but water and gracing for our camels which cannot find enough to eat or drink in North Hassa. At Hazmxdh there is a famine said all grac ing has finished. Here round Subaihiyeh there is plenty for all. Our idea is to leave our camels and women here and issue forth into Nejd once more to carry on our fight.I tiien joined in tlie wordy battle, and brought all Oovera- ment’s arguments to bear. The chief point I stressed was that we had given our word to Bin Saud, with whom it was our policy to be on friendly terms, and as aijiuch we could not breah our word. They the Ahhwan surely did not wish us to be breakers of words, the very thing that they were never tired of accusing Bin Baud of (the hit told). This and much more I talked about till close on sunset. I then produced your telegram NO.057, giving extract from Beuters about their impeding destruction and defeat. This I believe did the trick. They were furious. I pressed the point, and said Bin Baud and all the world were laughing at them for entering Kuwait, as men frightened and in the last extremity of despair and fear. Duwish apparently could not stand any more, but suddenly exclaimed 'fala’hi we have heard enough, I shall leave Sunday at dawn for Wafra, the Awasim’s grasing grounds X shall take, and we shall en shall ah have food, we will show the Hakuma if we are about to surrender to Bin Baud or not*. I said, “Will you give me your *kalam sharaf* to this”. He replied , M Yea, you have ay »kalam sharaf 1 , * I shall depart on Sunday at dawn.* The sun dramatically then set and Faisal himself got up and said it was time for prayer. After leading it and with Shaikh Ahmad behind him, he at the end, and still kneeling turned round and faced the kneelers, and addressed Shaikh Ahmad, and said, *0h Ahmad, do not fear, you have ny word! I should move tomorrow morning, but the Akhwan camels are scattered.They shall be collected all tomorrow Saturday and at dawn on Sunday I shall lead the way back to wafra. It will take time for the rest to follow, give them the whole of Sunday for our following is a big one'. The party then broke up, f and we returned to Kuwait by d .15 p.m. Al-Duwish 1 s part ing words to me were 'You must visit us and see what beau- tlful horses we have*, j ^ tae to U-.tf. sil '» Your most obedient servant.COMFT.Di:ijTIAL. NO. Political Agoncy, Kuwait. Dated the &gt;lst Auguut 1929* The undementioned translation of a letter is forwarded, witn coaplincnts, to the Hon^le the political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, for information. Li out-Colonel, . political Agent, Kuwait. Translation of a letter No.p06 dated the 31st August 1929 , from the political Agent, Kuwait to His Excellency the Ruler of Kuwait, Kuwait.Translation of a letter Ho*50b dated the Jlst Aiigust 1929, from tne Political Agent, Kuwait to His Excellency Sfcaikii Ahmad al-Jabir as-Subah, C#S*I«,C 8 I«E., Euler of Kuwait. ))))))) After Compliments. I am writing to express to Your Excellency my deep appreciation and grateful tiianks for the great assistance you gave me in our 3oint endeavours to get the Akhwan to move out of Kuwait territory yesterday. The work we were engaged on was one requiring great tact and careful hand ling, and I feel sure that had not Your Excellency been with me, I should not have succeeded in accomplishing anything alone. we That/were successful, and have obtained al-Duwish's ** promis eto move out of Kuwait territory with his women children, flocks and camels on Sunday next at dawn is a great victory for wmoderate' methods. I thank God Almi ghty tnat we were able to accomplish our ends peacefully. That success was due to G*od first, and afterwards to Your Excellency's persuasive powers is very clear to me. I should also like Your Excellency to thank Shaikh Abdullah al-Jabir for all he did. His work was most valuable. Last night 1 telegraphed to Bushire and Baghdad in forming them of what Your Excellency had accomplished, and this morning I received a telegram from the Hon'ble the political Kesident in the Persian Gulf thanking us both. Usual Ending.TELFXTRAH. IMPORTANT. \Vt FROM. Resident B'UBhire. TO political Kuwait. HO. ^4. Dated ai/a/2e reed. your telegram, ITo. &amp;04. Secretary of ptate for colonies directs that before air action taken if Duwish does not quit Kuwait territory full consideration should be given possibility employing other means, e.g. armoured cars, to induce women and children to leave and to prevent their drawing on Kuwaiu for supplies. If action by air proves necessary, all precaution should be taken to avoid bombing innocent tribesmen, women and children. I hope paisal will have left tomorrow, and no action will be necesaary, but in case he proves obdurate, your suggestions are awaited. August 31st.Telegram (C) From - Political, Kuwait. To - Resident, RusJiire. Repeated Higkcoma, Baghdad. No.&gt;00. Dated 2nd September iy^&gt;. Your telegram dated &gt;ist August No.064. Duwish kept his word left Sunday at dawn. Remainder Akhwan slowly following. Shaikh anticipates complete evacuation Kuwait territory Wednesday night. Shaikh 1 s patrols are with Akhwan hurrying on process but progress bound to be slow owing large number-non combatants, baggage and camels. Addressed to Resident in the Persian Gulf, repeated to High Commissioner for 'Iraq.. Political.TELEGRAM. IMMEDIATE?. TO. Resident Bushire. ■^ROM. Political Euwait. NO.^lO. Dated 2/9/20. PERSONAL. Hav» Just seen four aeroplanes flying high, and apparently £oin£ towards Subaihiyeh. X have not been informed of any such intended move, and have purposely avoided asking for any aeroplane reconnaissance. At this delicate moaent when I have just brought about peaceful! evacuation at personal risk such action on part air CTommand criminal. However high they fly Duwish will think I have broken my word and they have come to bomb while his people mc*y easily open fire. Could you protest very strongly to B^gbaad. I must be consulted before Air Force act like this and risk spoiling everything. political.Telegram (C). From - Political, Kuwait. To - Resident, Bush-ire. No.211. - 'TU Dated 2nd September 1 ^ 2 ^. IMMMIATE^. personal. My !?10. Received two messages from planes flying over Subaihiyeh reporting Akhwan in full retreat. Planes n made two visits flying 1^00 feet and 000 feet above Akhwa ca*-ips. Between visits they landed Kuwait and as I came aerodrome hottest part of day flew away without deigning wait for me. I am still entirely in dark about whole affair, and trust you will protest most vigourously at cavalier way I been treated both by Baghdad and by mechines themselves. The one crowning mercy is that % machines were not fired on and all my labours of past week undone. As it is my face has been successfully blackened seeing that I told Duwish he would see no aeroplanes provided he kept his word. Political.—No.191i July 20, 1929 Sir, I Tiave the honour to report that Ihn Saud has taken another important step towards establishing the r ahhabi religious influence at Mecca to the esclusion of that of all other sects. assumption of _-ower Ibn Saud made drastic reductions in the number of Imams of each of the four Sunni sects who had for generations led the daily prayers at the holy mosque in Mecca. His next mea; $ire was to allow one Imam only for each sect, the four Imams talcing iturns during the day in leading the five different prayers, th&lt; Imam of the Hanbali sect, to which the ahliaois claim to belong, doing oO at two of the sessions. 3. Ibn Saud has now abolished this system and has dismissed the Imams, retaining only the hahhabi Imam and appointing one other of the same sect, ooth Egyptians, who now in turn lead all the prayers. 4. Hitherto also a separate part of the mosque (musallah) has been reserved to each sect for its devotions, ''ifn. the dismissal of the Imams these musahhals automatically cease to exist c.nd all prayers are now read from one part of the mosque only. 5. Although, under the system existing latterly, all four sects of the Sunnis have had perforce to accustom themselves to praying axL&amp;Rr indifferently under the leadership of their own Iman or of that of It will be remembered th. t soon after his the His Majesty’s Principal Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.the other sects whose turn it happened to oe to lead the prayer, the non?Hanhali sects have done so in the comforting knowledge that they were still represented at the Mosque and that, as explained above, they had once a day an opportunity of following their own Imam# 6. Ibn Saud's action may have serious repercu sions in the Mohammedan world, if it becomes generally known and is exploited, and it is not too much to imagine that the Pilgri age might also be affected. 7. I am sending copies of this despatch to Mis 'ajesty’s High Commissioners for : gypt, Iraq, and Palestine, the Secretary to the Government of India in the foreign and Political Department, the Political resident, Bushire and the political Resident, *-i.den. I have the honour to be with the highest i respect, sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant, W.L.BOND#JED BA# Attguut 10, 1929 # i ir, Id ay d.ea &amp;toh Jio # 191 of the 20th ultimo I had the honour to report that Ifcn * au&amp; had dlsmiaaed the three non-H^nbali Imans, or # as one may say» the three non-Y ahhabi In.a ms, trou the holy Mosque in Mecot*, leaving: only two ahuaM Imams to lead the daily prayers^ 2 # It has apparently fcoen lound neoesnary now on ractioal grounds to increase the numoer of X&amp;ams from t v ?o to live* i’he throe additional imams have chosen fron among the residents of Hecoa« They formerly belonged to one or other of the non- t ahhabi soota, hut they are all now converts to the Tahhabi doctrines, and, like the otiier two Imams, lead t*:e prayers according to the Kanhali fora of ^ womship* Jione of them has had any previous connexion with the Moaque. Two of Mum are Indians, young men of no religious atamlint, and one of these wae, until his elevation, a bookseller in Mecca* Z 0 The arpointments as made are not of a kind to eonailiata public opinion. If anything they are likely to have the opposite effect. 4* I m aending copies of this despatch to K-M.High womisirt. loner a far ^gypt, Iraq and Palestine, the Crovormaont of India in the Eoreign and Political Department, the Politioal Residents at Bushire and Aden, and the lolitioal Agent at 'oweit. X have the honour to he with tho highest / NO. ^ 06 # reopsetf air i Tour moat obedient, humble Servant, Els Majeety*a Principal secretary # r, # n of tt,te for foreign affairs.No. 49 of 1919 British Bosidenoy and Consulate-General, Bushire, 27th August 1929. Sir, 1 hare the honour to forward herewith a oopy of a letter from the Folitioal Agent, Kuwait, Ho. 43 r , Agent*s telegram No. 43d, dated 19th August, to which he refers, was enclosed with my letter No. 43, dated 22nd August. 2. The oontinued embassies to Kuwait and the attempt to send Ibn Kashur to Baghdad show that the « Akhwan are realising their unenviable situation, fnless they can rouse the Ataibah ^isal al Dawish ib bound to be defeated. In that event Iraq, or Kuwait must expeot a mass immigration of the Ajman or Mutair Aiwa accompanied by their women and children. 3. It is for the decision of His Majesty’s ftuauac Government what action should be taken in such an event. The Boyal Air Force have orders to exclude refugees flying from I bn baud's army, but presumably these orders apply to the fighting men, especially Faisal bin Dawish and his chief followers. It will be impossible to take air action against women and child -ren, and unless some measures are devised His Majesty’s Government will lay themselves open to Ibn Saud*8 reproaches. 4 * etary of State for the Colonies, Colonial office, Downing Street, London, S.w.i. dated 20th August 1929 A copy of the Political4 In the meantime, as Colonel Diekson’s letter shows, a large movement of the insurgents* herds across the Kuwait border into Buhaihiyah may he expected* Copies of this letter and of its enclosure are being sent to the Crovernment of India, His tecell- -ency the High Commissioner for Iraq, and His Majesty’s Agent and Consul at Jeddah. I have the honour to be, 3ir, Your most obedient servant, r% C.J.Barrbtt Lieut-Col*, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf Copy to the Political Agent, Kuwait Attested. '’(jvv for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.Telegram P. Prom Political Eesident, Busnire To Secretary of State for tie Colonies. London. No 30. repeated Oovernmontollf India, Simla. High Commissioner, Baghdad. o 844. Da tad 26 tii August 1929 Paragraph (1) requires modification as it is now reported that I bn Jiluwi having partially ree verea in ealth is continuing as Amir while his son Jaud bin Jiluwi is actt&gt;aily doing tie work. Bahrein reports that within a month a change of mix is expected to occur. Reference is to my oelegram of August 23rd Resident ^ A Kuwai t Post copy sent fcd the Political Agent Bejrrain for information only. / Attested : SD/ C.C.J. Barrett, Lieut.-Colonel, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. for Secretary to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf. Bushire, 27th August 1929.Confidential. Ho, 384-S. of 1929. British Kesidency and Consulate-Cieneral, Bushire, 28th August 1929. A copy of the under-mentioned paper is forwarded to the Political Agent at Bahrain information. Political Agent at Kuwait/ By Order, for Secretary to the Political Kesiaent in the Persian Gulf. Telegram Ho. 2889«*n. of 26th August 1929 from t in? Government of India in the foreign ano Political Department, Tiraia.Telegra ? J'roin To Kepeateu ?• Govorment of India, Simla. Secretary of state for India, London Political cQsideot, : us..ire. High Coraruissi jner, Baghdad . NO 2689-S. hated 26t.. reed 27th August 1929. On the whole, as the season is so far adva iced, Gtovamaient of India agree that we should play ior safety &lt; nd defer approaching Ion Baud until it i. seen how British assistance to him over aircraft pans out. deference is to political Kesident’s telegra.. No 29 of ugust 23rd. ForeignI ^3 vuf 30or8tai*&gt; of otat© for th© Joloni©s 9 Lon&lt;ij Jolitioal iiesiduntt Bujhir©. High omaiiosionor, Bag: clatt. No 2o0. i)ht©u tSist August 1^29* Impor t avit , If yai8ml-al-r&gt;awish does not leav© } owoit . aasuiriQ that bei’ox*© any air action is tak©n full consideration will be given to the possibility of using other means (©•g. &amp;i*;av&gt;ur9Gl oars) to induce the women and c ildron to Quit Kuwait territory and to ©t&gt;p them iroa drawini supplies from Kuwait# rvery possible precaution should be taken to avoid bombing innocent tfi ^sniei^women anu ohilure ix air action proves necessary Kefere ice is to your telegram Nos 33 to 35 oi 50th and 31st August# # ^eoretar., oi Jtate for ti e 'olonieo 1 i Post copy to the Political Agent at Kuwait for information. SD/ G.C.J. Barrett, Lt.-Colonel, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Attested: for Secretary to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf. Bushire, 1st September 1929.CQIIF ID INITIAL No.509. Political Agency, Kuwait. Dated the 2nd September 1929 Prom Lieutenant-colonel HoH.P.Dickson, C.I.Eo, Political Agent, Kuwait. To The iion^le the political Eesident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Sir, Reference your D.O* dated 20th August asking for a defination of Bin Saud's regular forces. I have the honour to report that Bin Saud divids his armed forces into the following classes (a) Regulars. (b) Akhwan. (c) Aar aba. 2. Taking (a). These,so called ’*Regulars’; are nothing more or less than his rt Pidawi” troops. They receive regular monthly pay, but wear no special uni form. Most of them are of the rt hathar H class as opposed to the 'Badia”. This does not mean to say they are townsmen necessarily, for you will always find men from different tribes employed as Fidawis. A good example of the type recruited,are the Shaikh of Kuwait pidawi forces stationed at Jahara. perhaps the best English name that could be given them, would be ' paid Mercenaries ”» for They are for the most part chosen ibusm their reliability, and carry out the direct orders of Bin Saud's Amirs etc., whereas under category (b) (c) the individual fighter carries out his Shaikh's orders first. The garrisons of the 'Kuts' or forts which dominateKail, Hoffuf, Mubawaz and Qatir for instance consist oi tKese so called , 'Regular ,, troops, licssa^es to tribal leaders otiier towns and tae guarding of prisoiiers and collecting of zifcat etc is entrusted to tiiese per sons. They go under tbe naine of M Sir^iyall ,, (singular) and 'Sar^aya' (plural) o Tiie Ai^dwan effect £o dispise them and call tdem «Hatharis M . Tde Atdwan (b) on tde otder iiand were brought into being by Bin Baud to fight his battles and win them in the name of Religion. As Badouins they would never have boon reliable, as Ahhwan and inflamed by ”the pin” they became well right invinciole. They may be likened to Cromwell* s”Iron sides'* or the G-er.ian 'Strom Troops'. por the rest these fanatics are too well knowi^ uo need further description. Suffice to say, when they attack, they have a regular drill which consists of dismounting from their camels and horses, and advancing shoulder to shoulder infantry fashion, and in several lines. Their boast is that they never run nor are tempted to sheer out of the fight as ordinary Bedouins do when on houseback. If an ”Akhu« is slain his place is im mediately taken by another. There is no pause in the forward progress, or so their drill has it. Their motto is 'move swiftly and secretly to your objective, when there, attack on foot'. A regular reserve is always maintained in rear to rainforce where necessary. Sucn manoeuvres as dawn attacks, night attacks, flank and rear attacks, eoc. etc., are regularly understood and practiced. The Akhwan look upon themselves as the elect of Ood and the creme de la creme of Bin Baud’s troops. For this reason ihioy feel confident of ultimate success in their rebellion against Bin Baud. Theirs may belikened to a antiny of 3in Sard’s pretorian :&gt;iard rather than a retellion. The Athwaa despise (a) the sarraya and (h) tlie Aarab. 4. The ,, Aarad M are the ordinary Ba J dia or Bedouin allies of Bin Baud, and a certain amount of them usually accompany the Akhwan on a G-hassu. por instance when al-Dnwish made his recent march across 150 miles of waterless desert and struck at the she! and Sahool at Oaiyeh, he was accompa nied by a number of AOman 'Aarab'. These were used as scouts patrols etc. and when the final attack was launched, skirmished ahead. The Akhwan were the heavy infantry and main^-stay of the at tack. They also formed the lieserve. jt should be realized that not every iTu-oairi or Ajmi is an Akhwan: only those of uhem who feel that way, ooin the ranks of the elect. I have the honour to be, Sir, your most obedient seivant, (A Lieut-Colonel, political Agent, Kuwait.Telegram . FRO}!. Resident Bushire TO. Political Kuwait. FO. fc6Jb Bated and reed. 2/^/3^. Addressed Baghdad, repeated Kuwait. political Agent Kuwait reports seeing four aeroplanes flying high and apparently going towards subaihiyeh. He has not asked for air action, and protests strongly agaJ.nst what may be considered by Buwish as breach faith on his part, when he had secured Akhwan evacuation by peacefull means. X support Dicksons protest very strongly, and must request that to avoid possible deplorable consequences my telegram ob* July k 2 th should be strictly carried out. An air reconnaisance at this stage is likely to be misunderstood. telegram FROM. Resident Bushire. rpo. political Kuwait. no. avi Dated and reed. 3/^/2$, y“our telegram No. hil. Two strong protests despatched.relegrarn FROM. Highcoma. Baghdad. TO. Y Political Kuwait. NO. nil Dated and reed. &amp;/*/**• Addressed Bushire, repeated Kuwait. Air Officer Commanding Iraq sending reconnaisance down to Subaihiyeh today to ascertain Duwishs movements. Note. 'Hbove reed. 3.45pm, after Reconnaisance had come and gone. Aeroplanes passed over Kuwait at 1^.30 p.m returned 3.45p.m.\&amp;1&gt; TELEGRAM. TO. (IResldent Huohire. ^) Rigl'icoma Baghdad. FROM. Political Kuwait FO. Dated 3/0/29. Baghdads 264 reed. 5.45p.m. after reconnaieance had come and gone. Addressed Bushire, repd. Baghdad. telegram. FROM Political Kuwait. TO. Resident Bushire. NO. Sw eated 3/0/29. V7 511. Aero 4 no. A.311 recapitulating news given yesterday ends by saying 'bombs dropped nil, s.a.a. fired nil,' proving that machines were out for blood had they been chrittCnged, this they obviously invited by flying at ft. / political.0 \Q* TETjETtHAM FROM. Resident Bushire. TO, political Kuwait. NO. Dated and reed. 3/U/aw. My telegram Mo.iSCS. secretary of State. See.* no objection to proposed exchange letters between rrickson and Ibn Saud, subject to proviso that contents of messages to His Majesty are reported to me by telegraph and terms proposed replys are similarly reported, for ajjproval before despatch. Copies of all correspondence actually exchanged shoula be sent to me. please wire terms your reply Bin saud.Telegram (C). From - Political, Kuwait To - Resident, Bushire No. Jplb Dated 4th September i^^V* IMMEDIATE- Iviy telegram of 2nd September Ho.i?Ob, At 4 p.m. today evacuation Akhwan complete except for few odd tents which will be gone dawn tomorrow. To hasten movement Duwish issued order from Wafrah that any Akhwan left Kuwait territory after tonight would be raided by him. Political.con f i dei:t i al • 10 . 517 . Political Agency, Kuwait, Dated tiie 5th Septenbor 192 ^. From To Lieutenant—Colonel H.H»P*Dickson, C.I.B.# political Agent, Kuwait. Tlie non’blc the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Rushire. Sir, in continuation of ny telegrams Hos.510, 511 and 512 of 2 nd September 1929, I have the honour to enclose copies of three wireless messages 'A','©', 'C* sent by ^our machines while actually reconnoitering over Subaihiyeh. These were intended for Baghdad via Shaiba and copies were immediately wired me here. I also attach copy of a fourth message 'D' which recapitulates the work of the day and was despatched from Shaiba at 0.20 p.m. to Baghdad wit.^ coj&gt;y to me. 2 . You will notice that the name Jariyah lias been used in several instances* This place does not exist and ap parently steps have not been taken to have the name deleted from R.A.F. maps, vide my despatch No.594 A dated 20 th June 1929 and last paragraph. 5. The motor car mentioned in messages 'S ’ 1 and !, D ! ' be longed to His Excellency the Shaikh of Kuwait. It brought out a special party of six selected men, who at my suggest ion were sent out to hurry on the laggards and 'beat up n those not getting a propcr'move on.' It being recollected that al-Duwish himself with his principal chiefs had already loft on Sunday morning at dawn. 4 . For your information, the wells on which the Akhwan were actually camped on were:Al Tawil SubailiiyeJi Al Sub eh Shinaiti Arfigiyeh (on border line) 5. As I have already given my views on the sending of the air reconnftisauce in question in my telegrams referred to at the head of this despatch, I do not propose to make any further remarks on the subject here. The effect however of the incident on His Excellency the Shaikh was unfortunate and is given below. 6. On my return from the aerodrome where I had failed to meet the Commander of the Reconnaissance (as reported by wire) I proceeded straight to the Shaikh*s official residence in the Town, to explain that I was entirely unaware of the intention to send aeroplanes. I found him in a state of great agitation, and before I was allowed to say anything he started upbraiding me for having 'let him down' and not told him I was sending for aeroplanes. When I told him I knew nothing of the whole business, he expressed great astonishment, and asked how it was they could come without ray knowledge or permission, who re presented His Majesty's Government in Kuwait. He then turned to what was his and my immediate anxiety. We had seen 4 machines go in the direction of Subaihiyeh but only 5 had been seen to land on the aerodrome and fly away again and apparently in great hurry* Everyone was saying, he said, that they had heard the explosion of bombs, and he greatly feared a disaster, and that the Akhwan who were in a surly mood at havingbeen made to move had opened fire, and had shot down a plane. As I was trying to reassure the agitated man that 'B' telegram had distinctly said there was no firing, and that I sincerely hoped all was well, a messenger rushed in bringing nessage 'C', which clearlyindicated that all was well and machines were leaving for Shaihah (they never came near Kuwait on return journey). X immediately read it out to the Shaihh, and I have never seen a man so relieved. He kept on repeating 'Thank G-od, Thank God, I never believed the Akhwan could have restrained themselves, with the Duwish of all men not present'. He obviously was in a high 7 nervous state, for he then asked me why he had been treated like this? He had always understood he said that his permission was to be asked, before any machines landed at Kuwait. lie v/ould never refuse such permission of course, he added, but it was his right to expect to be asked if only as a matter of courtesy, and he hoped I would remind the autho rities in Baghdad that he would like to be informed in future if any aeroi^lonns desired to visit Kuwait whether they were Government machines or those of Imperial Airways. He referred again and again to the 'extraordinary tact lessness' as he called it, of the H.A*F* ut their rusning in, when he and I were engaged in the delicate business of getting a disturbed hornets nest quietly out of his dominions. The Akhwan were in mood to sting anyone who came near them, he said, and for aeroplanes to swoop down to 1500 feet and 800 feet range and stay there taking notes, was as if they were deliberately trying to provoke a hostile response in order that they could get an excuse ('hajja') to bomb. 'Where', added Shaikh Ahmad, 'in the world, would you have found anyone in the position that the Akhwan were in, and expectuA them not to ppenVfl&amp; fire. They could not but have believed that they were coming to bomb. I managed to calm His Excellency down before I left, and I am sure he did not mean half oi what he said. Ho doubt his excitement had got the better of him for the-4— (£9 for the moment for the fear that perhaps two British officers had been hilled had upset him very greatly and added to the(natural) indignation he felt at being 'lef down' . ^' ^ I liave reported the above at length as it is of interest to know that others as well as niyself were anxious and felt at the tine that a serious blunder had been made. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant. W * Lieut-Colonel, political Agent, Kuwait. le.S-dl^V c -^ (aT 'Tte-'iTelegram Eli CLAJE © Baghdadi number. From - Lock Four,Basraii (SiiuAiLali Rly). To - political, Kuwait. Words 75* Dated and received 2nd September 1929* Time of Issue 1.4-0 p.m. Clear Line. Following received froa air craft. Hr.4 reference your A 200 2/9 following at SubaiHiyeh. 600 tents including 50 white ones scattered among them. Approxi mate 5000 6000 animals going south west and more leaving camp. Descended to 1500 feet, positive sign of hurried preparation for departure. Camels donkey and sheep now hurrying S.W. some animals with tents etc. on backs. Air Craft not fired on. Lock Four. Telegram ffli CLAIR . From £ Lock Four, Basrah (Shuaibah Rly^. To - political, Kuwait. Words 8o. Dated and received 2nd jpagBcxi Sept.|i929. Time of Issue 2.55 P* m » Clear Line. Following received from Air Craft. Hr. b. One covered 5 seater car stopped at Jariyah about 4-0 people gave it send off car now proceeding S.E. by E. 120 degree Jariyah. Hr. 7 reference my Hr. b car now going South and about 6 miles North of Subaihyah Hr.8 Lock Four Ok. returning Shuaibah. Evacuation still taicing place at SubailiyaH Jariyah. Flew down to 000 feet but no firing seen or heard. Lock Four.and about 200 animals moving S.W. by W.E Misash Telegram BN CLAIR From To Lock, Basrah. (Shuaibah Bly) political, Kuwait* Words 52. Dated and received gnd September 1929* Time of Issue 2*45 p.m. Clear Line. Following received from Air Craft Ur. 11. Ho signs of further evacuation taking place. About 400 tents left Subaihiyeh. Am leaving area now and returning Kuwait and Shuaibah. Telegram EH CLAIR. From - Aero 4, Basrah (Shuaibah Ely). To - political, Kuwait. Ho. A-Jll. Dated and received 2nd September 1929* Clear Line. Your A-200 2/9 Lock Drummond Sheen Monk left Shuaibah 0820 £llT returned 1229 GMT. Reconnoitred Subaihiyak area, subaihiyak. 250 black tents and 20 white tents. Appromimately 2000 to 6000 animals going South west and extending up to 6 miles in that direction others prepared to leave and were seen later on the move with tents etc on backs of animals going S.E# After this first move movements appeared normal but groups of men seen gathered round large 9 pole tent, pecended to 800 feet but air craft was not fired pn. jariyah. 100 tents four white Time of Issue 8.20 P*ni120 tents 12 white about 5000 animals round wells no movement or signs or evacuation at this place. Un marked well 5 miles E&amp;st of Warah. 50 tents and four ♦ white no movements of animals. 1026 G-MT Jariyah. Covered five scater touring car stopped here about 50 men gathered round car which afterwards proceeded South towards STubaiyah. Left area 1200 hrs. G-MT no further signs of evacuation Air Craft were not engaged Bombs dropped nil. S*A.A. fired nil. Aero 461/14 P. Political Resident, Bushire. iii^L Oommissiooer, Baghdad. Political Agent, Kuwait. Bated 2nd September 1629. Immed iate. Pour aeroplanes flying high and apparently going towards Sudaihiyah have heen reported by Political Agent Kuwait. Political Agent has not )s k ed for air action and he protests strongly against Wi;at may be considered by Bawish as breach of faith on his part when hy peaceful means he had secured Akhwan evacuation. Bickson’s protest very strongly supported hy me and I must request that to avoid possibly deplorable consequences the procedure laid in mjf telegrain No 664 of 12th July should he strictly adhered to. n tnis stage a me&gt; e aerial reconnaissance is likely to be misunderstood. Bestdent. Post copy to the Political Agent, Kuwait. Telegram Prom To Repeated No 366. SB/ C.C.J. Barrett, Lieut.-Colone1, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Attested: for Secretary to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf. Bushire, 9th September 1929.'elegra^ i • From political Tieaident, Bushire, To High Coirmiasi &gt;ner f Baghdad. ::o d?2. Dated 3rd .Jaiteiiber 1929. Ttiat tae pJanes were not fired on and tde whole of lickson's effete spoilt hy tt is precipitate action ia extramely lucky. s it is^DicixSon considers his face has oeen blaokon/ad as he told Dawiah that if t.e kept his word he would see no aeDplanes. At the present Juncture personal ihfluence of &lt;iokson has been ^nesti/cahle value and you will agree with me that any action likely t &gt; decrease it is most unfortunate. Your telegram No 2i4 was received by him after the aeroplanes had returned 11* )m reoonnaissano© and thus he hhd no opportunity of stopping ti eifc. • hen tuey alighted f r s)iOrt time at Kuwait he triad to reach the aeroplanes but tie reports f^ew off ignoring him. Reference is to your telegram No 2i4of 2nd September. .Resident. .”oat copy to: The Political Agent at Kuwait 0 Rd/ C.C.J. Barrett, Lieut.-Colonel, Political Kesicient in the Peraian Cull*. Attested for Recr^xary to the Political Pecicent, Persian Gulf. Buohire, 3rd September 1929.British residency and ConsulaterCJeneral, Bushire, 3rd September 1929. Prom The Hon’ble Lt.-Col. C.C.J. Barrett, C.S.I., C.I.K., With reference to your letter of the 31st August 1929 I enclose an open letter addressed to His Excellency Shaikh Ahmad, which I shall be glad if you will read and, if you aee no objection, deliver to him. I have had much pleasure in bringing your own skilful conduct in this and preceding affairs to the notice of His Majesty’s Secretary of State for the Colonies and the Government of India. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf To The Political Agent at Kuwait Sir 1 have the honour to be Sir Your most obedient servant l.t. -Colonel Political Resident in the Persian Gulf vTelegram Code tTQm Political neeideat Dushire To Seoretaxy of atata for the Colonies London* Ho.37 ■Dated the and September 1929* hy imiaediately preoeedlng telegram* X wieh to oring to notice agarfrar^^e Colonel Liciceon** mi tiring hither to eucessful efforts throughout the heat of summer, to make the shaikh of Kuwait carry out his promises to Ais Majesty* ®oTermaont. - lUSlLJWT - *#* ■Post copy sent to: l The Political Agent at Kuwait. SB/ C.C.JTo Barrett, Lieut.-Colonel, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Attested: for Secretary to the Political Resident, Persian.Gulf. Buohire, 4th September 19S9.Telegram (C)# prom - Resident, Bushire. To - political, Kuwait. N0.8S1. # Dated and received 6th September 1929- Secretary of state for Colonies have asked me to convey to you an expression of his appreciation of your efforts which have been maintained in circumstances of considerable difficulties and physical discomfort and « to congratulate you upon the success of your personal intervention with Faisal al Dawish which averted a serious and embarrassing situation. I have much pleasure in complying. Resident. Telegram (C). i From - political, Kuwait. To - Resident, Bushire. Ho. 522 . Dated the 7th September 1929* Your 861. Deeply grateful encouraging message. PoliticalTelegram H. FRO!!, political Kuwait. TO. Resident Bushire. FO. 523. Rated ?/9/29. Tour B?0. propose replying to Bin Baud as follows. Firstly Than* him for letter. Secondly. Inform him that I an. fully aware of correspondence which has recently passed between him and R.M.G. with regard rebels. Thirdly. That sheikh of Kuwait and I constant in our efforts prevent supplies reaching rebels, and forbidding movement across border. Fourthly. Inform him of Jbn Rashur visit, and puwish^s arrival at pubaihlyeh, and of their summary ejectior; Fithly. Bay I shall always be glad exchange views as to best way deal with present problem, as well as other matters connected with his and puwaits interests. political 523.Telegram (C) From To political, Kuwait Resident, Bushire No.. Dated yth September Shaikh’s man in from V7afra reports that (X) Duwish and majority Akhwan leaders there. {2) Ibn Ashwan with Breih at Hajira. (^) Duv/ish probably moving south towards Riath as result news that Ataiba have defeated Bin Saud’s forces Qassim. Latter news not confirmed other sources, politicalTelegram (c). From To political, Kuwait Special, Basrah. No. Bated the / J©th September l^^y* Your letter dated yth September. (1) All rebels left Kuwait territory evening 4th. (2) Duwish with majority leelders \7afra. Ibn Ashwan with Breih vicinity Kajira. (4) No news at all of Azaiyiz beyond Bedouin report that he reached Hazil. (5) Shaikh says no foundation report that Abdullah with Awazin, situation unchanged there. (6) Letter from Duwish received yesterday says he probably moving south direction Riath as result news that Ataiba defeated Bin Saud’s forces Qassim. No news this defeat other sources. Political.ns /?2 Confidential. Ho. 417-S. of 1929. British Resident and Consulate-General, Bub hire, 9th September 1929. A copy of the undermentioned paper is forwarded to the Political Agent at Kuwait for information. By Order, for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Telegram Ho. 80, dated 26th July 1929, from the Foreign Office, London, to the British Agent and Consul at Jeddah, regarding the meeting between the Political Agent, Kuwait; the Shaikh of Kuwait and rebel JNajd leaders. (Received under Colonial Office letter dated the 22nd August 1929.;/ CONFIDENTIAL N Not to be publishr i witbcmt previous '• . x of H. M ? s Govei nuK nt &gt; Copy. N ——' NO DISrHIBUJICy. fE.3725/2322/91) Paraphrase Telegram to lir. Bond. (Jeddah). foreign Office. 26th July, 1929. 6.45 p.m. No. 80. fieference Bushire telegram of July 20th No. 22 to Colonial Office repeated to you regarding the meeting between the Political Agent at Koweit, Sheikh of Koweit, and rebel Nejd leaders* As it is possible that a garbled account of meeting may reach Ibn Saud from other sources, substance of Bushire telegram should be communicated to Hejaz Soyemment as soon as possible.oOMBIDENTIAh. No. -S. of 19P9. Br.ltiBh Kesj denoy and consulate-(renerp.1, Bushire, septenber 19?9. TO The Political A^ent, Kuwait• MEMORAN DUM. Before forwarding your letter No. 517 of 5th September to the Secretary of State for the Colonies, with copy to Government of India and Baghdad, I crossed out the word 'natural” in the 3rd line of page 4. Royal Air Force, and have insisted that you mist be informed before planes are sent over Kuwait territory, and I think it is sufficient to inform the Baghdad authorities of tne shaikhs feelings without again underlining the fact that we agree with them. I have already protested against the actionof the Lieut-Col., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.TELEGRAM. M. FROM. Britagerit Jeddah. TO, Zusacari Kuwait. NO. 1*15 Dated 1Q/U/22 k reed. 11/&amp;/2W. Addreoaed to F'oreign Office telegram No. 130 repeated Kuwait, Bushire, Jerusalem, Baghdad 1B5. copies by post to Cairo and Govt. of India. persistent rumours to which I am inclined give credence tend confirm opinion held in jreddah and Mecca that political arid financial situation in Hedjaz and Nejd is becoming steadily worse. The Ataibah are giving serious trouble, jt is confirmed from various sources that they have been robbing lorries containing arms and cash which were b«Ia^ sent to Riyadh and have been committing other acts of aggression. It is further reported a strong punitive expedition \ sent against them has been defeated near Turaba. Governor Jeddah has recieved Instructions from Mecca to prevent sale foodstuffs to Arabs of this tribe, and to exercise a strict control sale to other visiting tribes. On Medina side the Beni Amr of Nejd parb tribe have tltfcown off their allegiance and there are frequent reports of raids and robberies in that and In Kenaklya territories. New and severe measures are being taken to bleed Rcdjaz tribes of men and money, and there is general discontent. It is estimated that about Bedouins have been concentrated at Taif, and sent to Medina and Nejh. situation although unsatisfactory is to a large extent natural result of period suspense through which country is passing In anticipation definiute solution by battle, of situation vis a vis the A^h wa n.TELEGRAM. M. FROM. Agent Jeddah. TO. Political Kuwait. NO. 1&amp;6. pated 11/9/29. reed 12/9/29. Addressed to Foreign Office telegram Nt&gt;. 13x. Repeated Baghdad, Kuwait,Bushlre lb6. j/[y telegram No. 1^^. Further note recleved from Acting Minister for poneign Affairs states, interview of rebel leaders with political Representative Kuwait, and fact their return in safety has created a bad impression and has given rise to rumours that His Majestys Government have changed their attitude, and are not carrying out their undertakings. He hopes Instructions will be Issued for arrest such persons in future, and their deportation to Redjaz Government for trial and punishment . Copy note leaves by bag today. Agent 1.3111.Telegram V From To Political .esidant, Bi33iiir3« Secretajry of otate for Colonies, London, Fo 41* vepoated (Jovernment of India, Simla. High Commissioner, Baghdad. &lt;$023 High Commissioner, Jerusaie/m. British Agent,Jeddah* 90 B. i&gt;n meptomher 9th unconfii^ed report was leceived in J uwait that Id. Baud’s I’ire as in asim wore defeated tne ; tal ah. . etorenco is to Jeddah telegram to Foreign Office No 130. osldent. PoRt copy for information to The Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, The Political Agent, Kuwait, J The Political Agent, Bahrain, The Political Agent, Muecat, 8d/- C.C.J.Barrett. Lieut-Col•, Political Hepd dent in the Persian Gulf. Attested. 7 for Secretary to the Political ReAdent in the Pereian Gulf. Bushire, 11th September 19B9.Telegram jf. FROM Political Kuwait. TO Resident Bushire. FTo. Datedl2/k»/i!»). fry 523. presume you will wire nxs me as soon as suggested letter to Bln Baud approved. Anxious get letter off by next Sundays down mall Bahrain. political.mEMORANDTTM . Your telegram No. 5?,6, dated 9th September 1929. such purely news telegrams should be repeated to Baghdad. The delay involved in repetition from Bushire affords the Air Officer commanding in * Iraq an additional reason for posting a Special, service Officer at Kuwait.Confidential Mo. ^$3 -S of 1929. British Residency and Consulate-General, Bushire, I'X September 1929. A copy of the under-mentioned paper is forwarded to the Political Agent 'at Kuwait for information. By Order, fcr Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Coramunication flo, 171 of 5th July 1929 from E.M f s. Agent and Consul at Jeddah to the Foreign Office, London*, (with enclosure^. (Received under Colonial Office iedtte r dated the 22nd August 1929. J riqo Cop&gt; ♦ (E 3617/2322/91) NO. 171 . HI 8 Majesty's Agent and Consul at Jedda presents hie compliments to His Majesty's i-rincipal secretary of Ctate for Foreign Affairs and has tne honour to transmit to him the undermentioned do cuments. British Agency, d edda. duly S, 192J. Reference to previous correspondence. Jedda . .L. no. 102 of 21.6.29 and Jedda telegram No.104 of b.7.29. Note from the hejae Acting Minister for Foreign Affairs. NO. 14.3.6 Of 24.6.29. Leakage of supplies from Kowelt to the Ajman.his Excellency H.B.M. Agent and Consul, Jedda. 1 have the honour to acknowledge the receipt of your letter ho. 1097/33/139 of 14*1.1348 (21.6.29) concerning certain cooperative measures on the part of the Pritish Government against some of his Majesty’s subjects wno are being pursued. The hejaz Government appreciate the British Government’s friendly attitude whicn has come as a fresh proof of the best of the mutual and friendly sympathy existing between the two countries. As regards the hejaz Government’s request that the British Government should consent to tne pursuit of fugitives from hejazi forces, it originally rests on a desire to destroy tne disaffected persons and to deprive them of any opportunity of committing freen offences. how that the British Government have undertaken to do this both in Koweil and in Iraq, this is all that was requested. With reference to your statement in paragraph 4 of your note regarding the hheikh of Koweit’s denial of tne allegations of his having given assistance, the hejaz Government believe, as I have had the pleasure of expressing, both verbally and in writing,0, writing, to Nt. Jakine, that tne sheikh does not intend to injure the hejaz Government, nor does he intentionally do harm to them, and they accept the assurances forwarded to them on this point. The information received by the nejaz entirely GovernmentJailB to show that any of the Awazira and tne loyal Akhwan have taken any action of the kind mentioned in paragraph 4 cf your Note under reference, stating that the sheikh of Ko&gt; eit believes in its occurrence, especially since there is enmity ox old standing between Awazim and tne /vjman, -which is so well known tnat it leaves no room for doubt about tne impossibility of one party’s helping the otner. ihe Hejaz Government would however be very grateful if the oheikh could give the names of some of these persons and the approximate dates of their movements in this connexion. In case it is proved to have actually happened this will help considerably in discovering tne facts which you were good enough to say that the British Government are anxious to determine. It remains for me to mention one more point in connexion with this subject. This concerns what you mentioned in paragraph 2 of your letter, regarding the cooperation of British forces with the forces of the sheikh of Koweit, for this indicates, if 1 am not mistaken, that the measures about to be taken will be confined to the prevention of the use of Koweit territories for unlawful activities. You will realise, however, that the benefit of this will not be complete unless measures are taken to place obstacles in their path wherever they may be, whether in KoAeit or in hejdl territory. 1 request you thereforetherefore to draw the British Government's attention to the fact that the question will naturally be solved when their reply to the rest of the suggestions contained in my last letter to which you refer is received. with the nlghest respects. KJAO nhtthA. Acting Minister for foreign Affairs.Telegram (^C). From - political, Kuwait. To - Resident, Bushire. Repeated, Special, Basrah. IJO.^^K. Dated I'dth September iy2y. Reference paragraph G my IJo.4y^. Fugitive who has arrived Jahara confirms report already received another source that Azaiyiz raiders numbering ^00 reached Lauq_a 100 miles north hail where they carried out successful surprise. . On return journey they were intercepted by I bn M^aad's forces in great strength at Um er Rudhumma and completely defeated # Those who escaped were Faisal al Shiblan who with 100 men had gone south previous to fight and Azaiyiz himself who cut his way through with about 00 picked men. Addressed to Bushire repeated Special , Basrah. Above telegraphed to Bin saud by Nafisi. Political.I Telegram CC) To prom Resident, Bushire. Political, Kuwait. Uo. ^14. Dated and received l4tli September 1^2^. Baiirain telegram No.ilOO, i^th September begins. Saud's forces over rebels. First ‘/00 men under Dutiaiwah Ataibi killed last week, second bOO of Dawisli f s men under Uzaiyiz ad Dawish killed by Ibn Muaeed to last man after cutting of their retreat towards Kuwait a few days ago. Ibn Gaud has written to yusaibi he will wash lie jd with sword as patience and forebearance have failed to correct rebels. Ends. gusaibi claims two fresh victories won by Ibn ResidentTelegram M From Resident Bushire. To Political Kuwait, No. 909. Dated and reed. 13/9/29. Your telegram No. 323. Secretary of state for the Colonies concurs in reply proposed.SOmPEHTIAL . no. • prom political Agency, Kuwait. Dated the 15 th September 1929# Lieutenant-colonel H.R.P.Dickson, Political Agent, Kuwait, To i • Tlie ^onible the political Resident in the Persian dulf, hushire* i Sir, x In accordance with orders passed in your telegram No .909 dated IJth September 1929* I have the honour to forward translation of my letter to his Majesty the Mng of ned^az,NeJd and Dependencies for your information. In addition to the above letter I also sent a short private note to His iiajcsty, giving the news of Sir Gilbert Clayton^ sudden and regretable death. I have the honour to bo. Sir, lour most obedient servant. (vT ' * Lieut-Coionel, political Agent, A U wait.CONFIDENTIAL. From - Lieutenant-CoIonel H.H.P.Dickson, C.I.E., political Agent, Kuwait. To - His Majesty al Imam ADdul Azis Din ADdu± Hahman Din Faisal as-Saud, K.C.I.E., King of the Hedjaz and of Najd and Dependencies. N0.53J. Dated the 14th September 1929* Your Majesty! After greetings &amp;c. I have the honour to acknowledge Your Majesty*s letter No.13/3477 dated the 23rd Safar 1^45 and to express my sincere thanks to ^onr majesty for the very friendly sentiments which it contained. I have further to inform Your Majesty that in a propitious hour I also received your private and personal letter written from the Hedjaz sometime previously in which Your Majesty was g&lt;fcod enough to express pleasure at my being appointed to Kuwait as the representative of His Majesty*s Government. I was much gratified at this expression of Your Majesty* s sincerity of heart and it showed very clearly that Your Majesty remembered the days when I had the honour *f being your guest at Haffhff as well as the many friendly and intimate conversations which we had together then^ 2. Whilst I desire/* to offer Your Majesty full apology for not having replied to your letter earlier, I should like to say that the delay in doing so has been due solely to the fact, that it became necessary for me to re fer the letter itself, as well as certain other points re ferred to in it to His Majesty’s This all took Time. 3. In addressing Yo^-i* Majesty now I wish first of all to say that I am fully aware of the correspondence which has passed between Your Majesty and T, is- 2 - Hie Majesty* s G-overnment witJa regard to those rebels from among your subjects who have their concentrations in the neighbourhood of Kuwait. 4. I should also like to make it abundently clear to Your Majesty that the Respected of All, and Your Majesty 1 good friend His Excellency the Shaikh of Kuwait,together with myself have been constant in our efforts to prevent supplies in the shape of food, ammunition etc. reaching the rebels from the very beginning of these troubles, nor axe we in any way lessening our efforts at the present moment. 5* As regards the crossing of any of the Ajm&amp;njMutair or Ibn Masliur's rebel tribesmen into Kuwait territory,Your Majesty may rest assured that not only do none of the above mentioned Bedouins attempt to cross the border openly but their leaders from Faisal al puwish downwards have received several stern warnings both from Shaikh Ahmad and myself both in writing and verbally that should any of the Akhwan in their efforts to escape endeavour to take refuge in Kuwait territory they will be Immediately ejected, and by bombing if necessary 0 That a certain amount of food gets out to the rebels secretly is probably true, but with the tight control on the export of all foodstuffs that the Shaikh has imposed, such secret dealing^ I would ask you to believe, has been reduced to a minimum. 6. It may interest Your Majesty to learn that on the 17th Eabi I, 1546 (as22nd August 1929 ) Ibn Mashur sent in a message asking for permission to proceed to Baghdad under safe conduct and interview His Excellency the High Commis sioner. as he was not allowed to come closer than Qasr Mishrif, I saw him there and conveyed his request to His Majesty’s government. The reply I received was that Ibn Mashur»s request was to be categorically refused, and that he must quit Kuwait territory at once. I conveyed the message to ibn Mashur and he was forthwith ejected on loth Bafci I, 1J4&amp; 2jjrd August 1929 ). With Ibn Mashur wereten men. 7 # A still more important incident and one which I •fcjiiiLk proves more than anything else the friends Ap and good will His Excellency the Shaikh of Kuwait feels for Your Majesty, and also shows the careful watch which H^s Majesty* s Government is keeping on this matter^ occurred on the 24th Rati I* 154b (*= 29^ August 1929 )* On that day Shaikh Ahmads patrols on the southern border reported that Faisal al buwishls family accompanied by all the women and children of the Mutair and ashaida vv large numbers of camels under the charge ol al v. .s- o head slave had crossed the border and had camped at Su- baihiyeh under the plea that water and 'asirub** was very scarce round hamudh and Wafra. The same evening and while His Excellency the Ruler of -^uifait was mak-uig arrangemoiits to eject them, came the further news that Faisal al Luv/iSii himself with all the Akhwan leaders had also arrived at Subaihiyeh* ^’hey were iiimediately followed by ail the aJ man with several thousand of their women, old—.len and children. On the morning of the 25 th ^aoi, (=50kh August) as the situation was critical and as it was undesirable that we should bomb the Akhwan women and children of whom there were several thousands present, I decided to go to Subaihiyeh myself and warn al huwish that he must leave at once otherwise His majesty’s Government could not hold itself responsible for the consequences. Accompanied by His Excellency the Shaikh ^ met raisal al Duwish and ot,her JC* Akhwan leaders at War a, and I thank God that our mission was successful. That we were able to Induce the Akliwan to leave without our having to haxm their women and children was due first to Sod, secondly to the splendid support which Shaikh Abmad gave me. As it was buwish left by dawn on Sunday 2?th Rabil (= 1st September) with all his people and not a single Akhwan man, woman or camel remained at-4- Xe&gt;o Subaihiyeh or in Kuwait territory by the evening of tke 1st Babi II, 1J40 (= 4tJi September 1929 . Q. Finally I should like to take this opportunity of assuring Your ^ unchanged feeling of respect and to say that I shall be glad at all times to exchange views with Y 0 ^ Majesty my means of letters, as to the best way of dealing with the present problem, as well as other matters connected with Your Majesty’s and Kuwait interests* This is what had to be said &amp;• &amp;• Usual ending. Lieut-Colonel, political Agent, Kuwait*@ zee' no .554 COnFIDENTIAL. Political Agency, Kuwait. Dated the 16th September 1929 prom Lieutenant-colonel H.R*p.Dickson, C*I.E#, political Agent, Kuwait. To Sir, The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian ^ulf, Bushire. V. jn reply to your No.J9t&gt;-S dated 5rd September 1929# I have the honour to state that I duly delivered your letter to His Excellency the shaikh of Kuwait and enclose his reply which was sent in an open cover, together with a translation of same which for convenience I haye had made. 2. I should like to add that His Excellency was gratified in the extreme with your message, which came just at the right time. If I may venture to say so, it is n pats on the back' of this nature that are so valuable and which do more than anything else to assist the political Officers in local charge, to keep matters moving in a friendly and amicable spirit. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, I*i eut-Colonel, political Agent, Kuwait.-id? Translation of a letter Prom - H.E. Shaikh Ahmd al-Jabir as-Subah, C*S«I. ,C.I.E*, Euler of Kuwait. To - The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bashire. Dated 11th Rabi Ii f 1J4&amp; (= l^th September 1929). After compliments. With the hand of sincere!ty I took your esteemed letter No.C/257 dated the Jrd September 1929 which I have read with pleasure and thanks for your kindness and good wishes towards your sincere friend. I also gratefully thank the beloved of all Lieut enant Colonel Dickson for keeping you informed of matters which have brought gratification to Your Excellency and secured Your Excellency's satisfaction in regard to our persuasion of Faisal bin Sultan ad-Duwish, and getting him to quit the territories of K-uwait as desired by Your Excellency. Furthermore I wish to add that I also shall con tinue as always to do my best in any matter that may bring pleasure to you and lead to His Majesty' the Glorious King's Government being satisfied with me. I ask God Almighty to grand me assistance in so doing by faithful services, I repeat my many grafeful thanks to Your Excellency and ask your constant good office* Usual Ending. .CONFIDENTIAL No .557 Political Agency, Kuwait. Dated 18th September 1^29• prom Lieutenant-Coionej. H.ii.p.Dickson, C.l#E., political Agent, Kuwait. To TLe Eon*Lie tEe political Besident in tiie persian Gulf, Busliire. Situation in Hassa and Nejd Sir Reference your telegram ro. 914 dated 14tn September 1929 quoting al-Qosaibi’s claim in Bahrain tiiat (a) Aaaiyiz with 600 of al-Duwish^s men had been destroyed to a man by Ibn M’saad. (b) That al-Duhaina the insurgent leader sent by al- Duwish to yassim had been killed with 700 men. I have the honour to say that 1 think al-Qosaibi in his anxiety to give out good news, has exageratedjAatf&amp;a*. This is a mistake and will only haim his master’s cause when the full facts become known. 2. as regards (a) please see my H 0.956 12th Septem ber. prom the last remark it will be seen that al-Qosaibi got his news from jtL-Nafisi of this Town, who coloured his news to the extent that he reported“no survivors” at all. Actually, here in Kuwait we have not yet received a correct account of the engagement, so the true tale of Azaiziz's defeat is not known. One thing is known however, it is that (a) the original force numbered 500 ; (b) en route to Lauqa, 100 men were sent back in charge of two large bodies of raided camels. (c) Paisal al-Shiblan»s detachment numbered about 80 , and 100 survivors have definitely returned to Wafra.This leaves 520 with Azaiziz unaccounted-2- ■% personally I am of opinion tliat Azaizi* did not escape and that iie witli 520 men were killed, 7/e siiall hear the truth no doufct in a few days. I bn M’saad^ success was the result of clever work, and he brought off his coup by filling up certain wells, and denying the water of Um er Rudhumma to a weary and very thirsty force as represented by Azaiziz raiders. These fought to get to the water but failed* 5 . As regards (b). The news here is that al-RgMiacfc Duhaina is veiy much alive and is creating a lot of trouble but as this comes from insurgent sources, it must be accepted with caution. Bin saud himself says nothing about his death in a long letter dated 20th August which Shaikh Ahmad received by last up mail (12ih September 1929 ). This letter was a particularly friendly one and a precis of it is given in the following paragraphs. (a) . He thanked the s&amp;ai&amp;b. of Kuwait for so kindly entertaining Abdur Rahman Qosaibi and for the messages sent him by that individual. (b) . He hoped before long to personally arrange a meeting with £is 'brother' the shaikh of Kuwait. He would arrange the date later. (Shaikh Ahmad knows nothing about this meeting). (c) . He would long ago have se^t out on his expe dition to punish the insurgents, but the heat was too great. (d) . The people of Ue^d proper and Qassim had recently refused to provide troops, where with to attack the Akhw&amp;n in Uassa, their excuse being that the country was so disturbed in their midst that he Rih Saud must first settle the trouble at home before asking them to move to a distance. (e) . That al-Duhaina sent by Faisal al-Duwish was-5- ( 2**\ T^lo creating a lot of trouble in.Q&amp;ssim, but he had several forces engaged in trying to bring him to action, including a force sent from Hejaz by his son Faisal, until this person was 'settled tt there could be no more north. (f). That his troops had indeed surprised al-Duhaine l once and taken many camels, but the man him self was still at large and creating much mischief. 4 . heading between the lines, it would seem that Bin Saud is too concerned with affairs nearer home to feel strong enough to start on an expedition against the northern insurgents yet. Shaikh Ahmad states there undoubtedly is serious trouble in and passim and reads Bin Saud’s letter as confirming this. At the same time, says Shaikh Ahmad, Bih Saud must if he is to save his kingdom, make one big effort to taokle al-Duwish, in the next month or two. 5. The various rumours from Mecca, London and else where that Bin Saud^ forces were coverging on the rebels &amp;c are so much 'moonshine^ and will only be quoted by the rebels as examples of the stupid lies with which Bin Saud is trying to bloster up his cause. . 6 . The actual position of Bin Saud*s forces today is follows:- (a) . The 'Awassim/ tribe are at Mulaija (8 miles North of Nta) under Mubarak Ibn Drai and Ibn Jami. They are assisted by contingents of Bani Khali d ; al-]lanassir, Bani Hajir, Q ah tan and Sahool -(all small). Also by a detachment of 2^0/J00 of Bin Saud f s regulars (sarraya). The whole force numbers about 2500 and is hampered by the iln-numberable women and children of the Awazim. (b) . There is nothing at haffar &amp;1 Atz though themammLamamatm fy C Oil FIL' Eli TIAL . IJOn 5 • From political Agency, Kuwait. Dated the loth September 1929 Lieutenant-GoIonel H.iUp*Dickson, G.I.h., Political Agent, Kuwait. To The Hon*tie the Political Resident in the Persian dulf, Bushire. Pres-ence of political Undesirables irom ’ Ira^ in Kuwait. Sir, I have the honour to report that on Sunday last l^th September 1929, His Excellency Shaihh Ahmad called on me, and complained formally of the presence of the following persons who had arrived from Baghdad on 15 th September (a) Faihan bin Ajailan of the Ataiba. (b) MUtrak bin Hejlah of the Ataiba. (c) Aid al Dehainah of the Ataiba. (d) All bin Faleh abu Shuaribat of the Mutair. (a) and (b) are according to Shaikh Ahmad refugee Ataiba leaders residing at tne court of the Amir Abdullah of Trans-Jordan, and came via Baghdad to Kuwait. (®) is believed to be a brother of the rebel leader now in arms against Bin Gaud in qaesim, and acts as courier between Baghdad and Kuwait vide Special service Officer Basrah’s report I/Bs/1 Part IV (d) for period ending 11th September 1929 . (d) Is the we31 known Itutair refugee of Baghdad who has on several occasions visited Kuwait before, and proceeded secretly to the rebel camp* in tnis connection please see Diaries No.11 paragraph 70, Ro.lJ paragraph 96 . i;o 0 14 paragraph 102 and Kc .15 paragraph lib (b ) 0 His Excellency stated that (a) and (b) mentioned 2.above, on arrival attempted to engage a motor car to take tiiem to Aafra and visit kaisal al Buwisli. As lie nad however forbidden all commonications with the rebels the necessary car was nnobtained and the persons came and petitioned him for a car. He refused their reguest — of course. J. His Excellency further stated that he has been aware that for some time past there have been certain movements of mysterious emisaries between Kuwait and Baghdad, but he has not complained officially because such persons have come armed with regular certificates of Identity issued by the Baghdad authorities, 4. Seeing however that there can be no longer any doubt that these persons are acting as 'go between' between persons in *irag and the rebels, His Excellency has desided that the time has come to take action. What has persuaded him to move more than anything else has been the presence in Kuwait of Baud’s confidential agent Abdul Aziz al Rubai for the last three weeks, and the fact that this person has more than hinted that tne Shaikh would do well to prevent suen people visit ing Kuwait as in duty bound he had to repots movements of suspicious persons to his master. As His Excellency said to me, rt I have enough accusations of my own from Bin Eaud torefute n without bringing on my head the ciiarge that 1 am enejuraging well known refugees from Bin Saud's Grovernment in ‘Irag in their intrigues with the hebels/ 5 . What His Excellency now asks is that if you see no objection , His Excellency the high Commissioner may be approached with tho reguest that the individuals named above, be watched and refused further permission to visit Kuwait, and tnat ail police officers in ’Irag-5- (ifr. be warned not to issue Certifioatea of Identity to tlie^ without previous reference to Kuwait. He farther suggests tnat a list be kept of such undesirables in His Excellency the High comniissioner*s office and that as occasion arises the names of suspicious persons may be added on receipt of a telegram from k this office. 6 . Finally Hie Excellency says he would have acted before, but for his anxiety not to offend possibly import ant persons in 'Iraq.* He feels however that his position is becoming so difficult that he must not allow such XKxyp scruples to stand in the way any longer* As regards the persons already in Kuwait, His Ex cellency proposes to get rid of them as soon as possible. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Lieut-Col., political Agent, Kuwait.COUJTIDEKTIAL Ho. $k0. Political Agency, Kuwait, Dated the 19 th Septeater 19^9 From Lieutenant-Colonel Dickson, C.I.E#, political Agent, Kuwait, To Tlie Hon , ‘ble the political Resident in the Persian (rolf, Rushire ,&gt; possible rt Mass entry of Insurgents into Kuwait, Sir, In reply to your demi-official N0.425-S dated loth September 1929 . Your question is indeed a dif ficult one and has engaged my attention for sometime past, I have also discussed the possibility on several occasions with His Excellency the Ruler, who finds it equally difficult of solution, 2, In the first place, Bin Saud would appear to have been too astute for us once more. He must have known when he asked that refugee rebels should be kept out of 'Iraq, and Kuwait territories, that women and children would accompany such rebels to the pro portion of 4 to 1; h® therefore may be said to have deliberately deceived His Majesty's Oovernment, On the other hand His Majesty's Government obviously understood by the term 'rebels'* and 'refugee forces 1 *, that fighting formations were meant, and they conse quently agreed to keep these out by air action. It is unconceivable, I think, that Eis Majesty's Government would have promised to bomb large numbers of non-com batants to please Bin Saud if they had known the twue facts.5. As I understand tilings here and tiie sliaiJtii agrees with this view, the forces in rebellion against Bin Baud will never send their women and camels alone across the border, and remain fighting themselves till the last. This might be expected in the case of civilized persons but not of Bedouins. The Bedouin notoriously fights twice as well,if he has his women and children with him. The latter give him great moral \ encouragement f so much is thfeSso that their leaders themselves would never agree to the move, let alone the rank and file, we may rule therefore a cross ing of the frontier en masse by women children alone, /hat happened at subaihiyeh the other day was in no case a running away or attempt to take refuge. It was a question only of water and grazing shortage in fact a typical 'try on» or bluff, as was seen the manfolk followed the women at once. If there is going to be any crossing of the border I am convinced it will be by all the Akhwan forces together, either as the result of immediate severe pre sure or as the result of a decisive beating in the field. 4. just as Bin Baud deceived us into giving^ a promise, by implying that only fighting men would have to be dealt with, so I think we have a loop-hole of escape and are entitled now to say to him 'we understood from you that it was men we were to bomb and kept out by force, you never explained to us that every fight ing person would be accompanied by 4 or 5 women and children. 5. Things being as they are, and on the assumption that armed men will be inextricably mixed up with women etc. we have two ways of meeting the situation. (a) By civilized methods. (b) By Tribal ditto-5- ?») * n Under (A) we can say to Bin Baud that we agree to intern a force of rebels only, after forcing tiiem to disarm,, We can then place thw whole force so interned in a selected area, till the end of hostilities and the] negotiate for their surrender and return to their country when the rebellion is finally quashed, if Bin Baud does not require them back we must settle them in our own territories, an unlikely contingency. Whilst interned we must be responsible that the in ternees are not attached or molested by the many tribes who owe them a grudge. Therefore the area they must be placed in should be well away from the frontier and one easily controlled and guarded. If we cannot guarantee the refugees safety in every way we must not disarm them. 6 . under (b) the tribal rule is as follows. If one tribe fleeing from its enemies takes refuge with another tribe and makes rt Dakhala’ f , the Euler of the country or shaikh of the tribe, whose protect ion is sought is bound to (a) first negotiate with the pursuers for an amicable settlement. (b) Failing that he must mobilize his tribe and defend the fugitives. (c) Or if he feels he cannot help in any way he must give due warning to the refugees, and must move himself out of his own territory to a distant part, in no case can he eject the refugees by force or hand them over to punishment by their enemies, under the above analogy (and Bin Saud knows these rules, quite well), Iraq and Kuwait, even though the Akhwan refugees have been opposed to them in war previously, cannot refuse them 'dakhala', and havinggranted H dakliala ,t they must proceed to negotiate as best they can with Bin Saud for their final repatria tion. in no case may they allow the refugees to raid back against their pursuer (in this case Bin Saud) from the fru-an* territory where they have made “Dakliala”. And in no case can any particular |3 member of the refugee party be handed over to apease the wrath of the pursuer. 8 . It will be seen from the above that (a) the civilized method is really an improvement on the old tribal law, and probably has been evolved from it. 9 . My own opinion is that we should apply (a) the civilized method, to the problem and insist on the principle of internment. In the case of Kuwait I should transfer the whole force of refugees into the rectangle east of the Safwan Jahara road (i.e. that bounded by Um Qasr Safwan, Jahara,Sabiya). The leaders such as Duwish, Ibn Hathlain, Ibn Mashnr &amp;c. &amp;c., I should place on Falaika Island out of iaarmsway and as hostages for the good behaviour of their followers. As the Shaikh of Kuwait could not protect them from serious raids, I should not disarm thejd internees. Bubiyan Island would have been an ideal spot for them, had thefr been water, but there is not In the case of ’Iraq.. I should transfer the refugees en bloc across the river Euphrates, and place them in the area enclosed by the Shatt ragftYwfe al-K4&gt;r and Hor Hussainiyeh on the north and east the Diwaniyeh-Buwaitha-Samawa railroad on the North west, and by the Euphrates on the South as far as al Bat ha. This area has plenty of water and grazing in it and for once in a while the Dhafir could beprevented from going tliere in the armnmer. in the case of ‘Iraq, also, I should not attempt &amp; disarmament as to let the refugees protect themselves would be better than for us to have to protect them. Their insurgent leaders coaid be kept at Duwaniyeh or Basriyeh under surveillance and as hostages. As regards the camels. I suggest that both the 1 Iraq, and Kuwait Governments give out that no camel claims will be entertained by their own lationals against the refugees until such time as negotiations are complete for returning the refugees to their own countries. In these negotiations a clause could be inserted whereby all camels bearing the tribal marks of either ’Iraq or Kuwait tribes should be handed over before the tribe *x be allowed to leave and vice versa all camels claimed by the refugees as being in the be hands of ’Iraq or Kuwait tribes to also/handed back. 10. The question of blood guiltiness of both sides to be officially declared as H imm Dum' i.e. forgotten. It being remembered that the attacks of the Akhwan represented the attacks of Bin Baud’s regular troops, and were done to order. 11. Finally Should the highly improbable happen, and Bin Baud’s armies get between the rebel fighting forces and their encampments, then and then only, we expect to see an influx of ^non-combatants with their camels across the border. Should this occur, we may take it for granted Kuwait will be selected,as the rebels not only are in the immediate proximity now but both the Ajman and Mu.tair as well as Kashaida, look upon the Shaikh of Kuwait as their old overlord, and one must likely to be able to protect tiiem. In such an event I advocate their all beingtaken charge of by Kuwait and placed round Jahara area and on the coast north of the bay of Kuwait* 12. This letter has I fear been written in a hurry to catch the mail steamer, and I apologize for the disconnected way it has been put up. The views expressed in are mainly my own opinions, formed from private talks I have had with the Ruler and other leading Arabs. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Lieut-Coi., Political Agent, ^SiwaitCOHFIDEHTIAL KO. 558 . Political AGGncy,'Kuwait. Dated the 19 th September 1929 . To The Hon»ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Memorandum Reference your 420-S dated 10th September 1929* telegram R 0.526 dated 9 th September 1929 that I had not informed any one else of the news it contained. Actually to save money I sent you a short edition only. I sent another telegram No .527 to the Special Service Officer, Basrah, on the same day containing fuller details - see copy attached. You could not have known this and I am sorry I mislead you. I shall not err again in this respect. I am afraid 1 gave you cause to assume from my - * Lieut-Col., political Agent, Kuwait,1-1^ Telegram (C) v From - Political. Kuwait To Resident, BuShire Repeated Highcoma, Bagiidad; Special,-Basrali. No.^42. Dated ^ist 'September iv^y. # Uy of Isth September. Firstly .Confirmed tiiat Faisal ai Shiblan and Ibn Ashwan‘s sou returned ;7afra I'/th September with many shammar camels each having brought off successful raid near blail and Shaaib*^ secondly .Still no definite news of Azaiyis. Thirdly. Duwish moved to Arak on 10th. Has given out that he marching on Ilaariyeh with Ajman immediately. After dealing with Awazim at Rta he with Mutair will carry war into llejd proper, leaving Ajman in control Hassa. liutair women and camels remain yafra Politleal ILO.tj: 95^ is registered as 950 in P.A f s register.2 2 -S' British Kesidency and Conaulate-General, Bushire, 7th September 1929. A copy of the underrmentioned papers is forwarded to the Political Agent at Kuwait for favour of his remarks. By Order, Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. 1. Letter from H.E. the High Commissioner for Iraq, Baghdad, Ho. S.O. 1742, dated bth September 1929. 2. Letter to H.M’s. Secretary of State for the Colonies, Ho. 53, dated 7th September 1929, without enclosures. 3. Letter to Government of India, Ho. 410-S. of 7th Septemb' 1929 h-o , *-4yConfident Itil Mo • 410-S. of 192 9* British Hesidency and Conoulute-General # Buuliirc f 7th rJe^tember 1929. From To The Hon ♦hie Lt.-Col. C.C.J. Barrett, Political Bcaiderit in Uie Persiun Gulf, The foreign Secretary to the GoYemnent of India, Simla. ; Letter from H.K. the Hi^h CoRnniBaioner : for Iraq, Mo. 0.0.1742, d/ 5-9-1929.: Letter to H.B’b. Secretary for the : Colonies, Ho. 53, d/ 7-9-1929, with J enclosures. : Sir, I have the honour to forward for the information of the Goirerniaerit of India a copy of the correspondence noted in the margin regarding an aeroplane recon naissance over i Subaihiya carried out by the Hoyal Air Force in Iraq in connection with Faisal ad Dawish's recent intrusion into Kuwait territory reported in correspondence ending with this office endorsement Mo. 396-8., dated the 31st August 1929. I have the honour to be , Sir, Your most obedient servant. SI)/ C.C.J. Barrett, Lt.-Colonel, ’Political 'esident in the Persian Gulf.Secret The R e si h eu ey. ( i 4 'o. S* 0 « 1/42. Ra^ndad# jiated otii Septe .oer 1929. f SlC, Sir, I have the honour to refer to your tele^ranu Noa* 866 and 872 dated 2nd a*id 5rd of September, 1j 29, reB x .ectivexy . j eiidaiae here v/j. tn u copy of a letter from the Air officer Coromandint; on the subject ol tii.e reconnaiseance sent oy hi » to Suo&amp;ihiyah ox* the 2 ixa ixistaut, wnicn fully explaiiiS tne reasons for his uctioxx. I entiruxy e.,uorae tne viuwo of tue Air officer CoxamaiAdi^ ax.d, in view especially of the ai ue .tioxi of uie serious te^sioxx created iii 'ira^ t,.e grave uiaturca^xceB w.iic*x are taxing place in Palestine, 1 leit also unat it was esseiii/i .1 to clear up tne situation on tne southern ii^*rtier fr xitier uv; it H txxe Aimwa.* hod still uee , fou.-d in Ituwait tnxxatiiy territory, it would probably have bee.* necess r v countermand reixiforceraenta whicn v;e e lixider crd ra to proceed to Palestixie. 3. I am very conscious of the admirable meaner ixi which Lieutexiant Colonel Diqhaon has dealt with a ver^ delicate situatioxi and of the desirability of doing nothixxg which might decrease Ms personal infiuexxce. At the same time, i cannot see that 'xxis face has been blackened', or tnat axi. ciiarge .16 oreacn of faith can be brou^nt against hixi uy u -^hisax-ei-jawisn, or aiiyoxie else. You will remember tnao Lieutenaxib - coloxiei hiensoa states, in M*' ( t«le«ram So S04 of iOth August, that j-aiaal- vel*jawlsh had ^ivea his w ra of honour to leave u baldly an on Sunday Slot Au^no , wiffc all lhe re . Ej foroea, women, ehlldrea and caiela. The . ir racodiiaissa »ce did not proceed to Suoainiya . u...i „ the next mornin.^ towarus noon, so t.utl u2 . @ 7^* /^N (if) Faisal-el-DawiSii was still tnere v/iie.* it arrived it was he who had brokea his w rd raid not Lieu ten: .*t Colonel Dickson, ' ^• I would add that, in Ira^, it is not re.am.x., reasonable to expect any ^reat consideration for Palsal-er-Dawish and his companions or miy UiiCOnfiri-iQd i eliance on tneir promises* Iraq has a heav v , alia as yet unsettled, account a^ai^st tuem for past massacres and heavy losses in pinp^rilnn property a;id flocxs and, not uniiaturally, rejarus a larje proportion of the her as for whicn they are so sj&amp; solicitous as the stolen property of Iraq tribes. I n °y e that tnis despatch and tiie letter of the Air Officer 0ontnandin^ will adequately explain tne urgent situation which de.iai.ded i imediate uctlo** ana 1 ^ rt ' no ti/Be for the prior reference to y u wmcijis, and will continue to oe, the rule in s c cases. conclusion, i aesire to associate n^seif with tne Air officer Commanding in his express!o,; - regret that difficulty or annoyance should iiave oeen caused to you or to the Politic^ Agent at iuwait 1 am sending a copy of txxia despatch to tue Secretary of State for ta. colojiies. 1 have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant (S^d) Gilbert vll^iy ton. !Xxiere were therefore S&gt;,000 xae.,, under a noted leader, witxiiu lour or even three a aye march of the vital port oi o.asruh and it waa therefore essential, from the point oi view of Iraq, to Know what Dawieh was doing, ihe position was further complicated by the fact t.at reinforcements were under orders for Palestine, if Dawish was not going to go, still more if he was o . t..c aove Northwards, it would have teen essential to stop these reinforcements at onoe and this might have reacted seriously on the events in Palestine, so there was not only Iraq out Palestine ana Transjordan to be considered ine previous reputation of Dawish is not as to justiij us in attaching muon importance to ais word of honour and I consider mat I should not nave been iuliixiing my responsi oility wi th regard to the uefenoe oi Iraq if j nad sat still and hoped for the beat. action was right does not prevent me from regretting t it caused annoyance or difficulties to the icliticni Agent Kuwait or the Political Resident Bush!re. R* Srooke-'p opiuoa. Air Vice-Mar Biial, Air Officer Commeaidi^, Iraq Comma-id.Britieh Feoitieiicy uii&lt;3i ConBulaiit-KfCtierjil # JJtiohirir, 7th Bajptmabrr X9R9. No&gt; 53. Schedule« Sir. With reference to letter Wo. S«0, 1748* dated the bth September 1989, from Hio Kaccellendy the Coomieeioner for Iraq to my addreoe, copy of which hue been forwarded direct to you, 1 liave the honour to forward for the information of Hie Ka^eety’e Government a copy of my reply to Kie K*eelleney t&gt;.e Hi^h Conmitteione; for Iraq, Ho. 409-S. of to-day*H date, togetlier with aopy of connected correepondence enumerated in the attaclved schedule. 2. Copy of thie letter and of its enclosures is being forwarded to tiie Governnent of India. I iuive the honour to be. Sir. * Yom* most obedient, humble servant. Siy' C.C*J. Barrett, LiOut•-Colonel, 'olitical Beoident in the 'eruUxn Gulf.No. 409-3. of 1929. British Eoaiuency ana Conaulate-Gonoral, BusLire, 7th 3&lt;*pt&lt;*i»her 1929. Sir, I have the honour to aoknowleOgo receipt of your letter No. 3.0. 1742, dated 5th Jopiesfiber 1929. 2. tty point of view is that as Chief i olltloal Bepresentative in the Persian Oulf I, acting through olitioal \,:ent at &lt; uwait, an responsible to the Government of India and H.M # s. Secretary of State for the Colonies for events in Kuwait. So long as the situation can be controlled by peaceful means it is the duty of the Political Agent and myself to oonti^o It. ^hen we JOun find the position getting beyond our control It la our duty to call in the military, here represented by the Royal Air Force in •Iraq,. once we havo called in military asslst- -ance control passes out of our vivilian hands till the situation has do an restored to the normal. 5. In this particular case the situation had almost reached the stage when control would have been transferred to the military out thanks to the prompt measures taken by Colonel Dickson this stage was not reached. Although a warning was issued no request for military assistance was made. Bueh being the case it was unfortunate that without previous consult- -ation the Air officer Commanding took the risk of upsetting all the political measures of the 3 olitioal Agent at Kuwait. 4. We are all anxious to carry out the policy of His Axcellenoy ^ je High Commissioner for ’Iraq, Baghdad. ■ Lof Ri&amp; Majesty’s Government, which is to oxclude ths Akhwan rebels from Kuwait. Thera has merely been a slight mlaundarsbanding &amp;» to the bast nouns of achieving this end. I am sincerely grateful to Mr Robert srooke Popham and yourself for the aenti*- -rnents ajcpreasea at the conclusion of y ur letters and T can assure you that I am anxious only to co- -operate wholo heartedly with the Uoyal Air Force. This incidentt which fortunately had no untoward result, shows how necessary is the free exchange of information between departments. You did the political Agent and myself the favour of informing us by telegram that reconnoitring planes were being despatched to gubaihiya. Had this information been sent before instead of after the anroplancs had left all chance of an unfortunate Incident would have been avoided. 5. An argument with the Arabs as to whether Colonel Dickson’s or Faisal bin D&amp;wish’a face had been blackened by an encounter at Gubalhlya is a subject which obviously should be avoided. To get the best results &amp; British officer’s word should be above suspicion. I hold no brief for Faisal bin Dawish, quite the reverse, but I must point out that he left at dawn on Fulday according to hia word and his followers were on the move immediately afterwards The danger was from the action of hot-heads among them these followers. If some of xlunui had fired on the planes, these, which appear to have been carrying bombs, would no doubt have retaliated and not only would all the good results of the political action have been wasted but the very result of delaying . reinforcementsreinrorcemants for lalsBtino, whtoh the Air c ffioor Ouioiaanuing was wishing to avoid, would have bean brought about. 6 . I am in complete sympathy with the Air Officer OoiiiiBanding*s desire to clear up the situation, especially in view of the call made by Xalestine on the Boyal Air Force in 'Irag, about which I was not previously cognisant, but, in my view, Colonel Dickson, who has shown himself to be in close touch with the movements of the rebels, aould be trusted to report whether Faisal bin Dawlsh had kept tils word. In fact I received his Ho. 508, reporting that Dawish had gone, some time before his 510, stating that he had seen aeroplanes, about which he had no information, flying towaras Subaihlya and asking that a protest be made as he had purposely avoided asking for any areo- -plane reconnaissance. 7. The Political Agent, Kuwait, already lias Instructions to give all Information direct to you. If the Air officer Commanding so desires I am prepared to authorise him to communicate direct with any offloor of the Royal Air Force he may name but I request that, to assist that cooperation of lUvlal and iillt&amp;ry which is obviously so desirable, the lolltloal Agent, Kuwait, may be Informed beforehand of any flights over Kuwait territory in sufficient time to enable him to protest if necessary. Ite will naturally make no objection except for vary strong reasons. A copy of this despatch is being sent to His lajesty’s Secretary of abate for the Colonies and to the Oovernment of India. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servan Dd/- G.C.J.Barrett. Lleut-Col,, lolltloal &lt;evident in the ] arsian Gulf.30.231. JTf.EDAt \ e t.icater Mr, 2 h&amp;ire the honour to refer to ray telegr m of today’s di te nd Moo to my des?.atvih Ho.2£4 of the 3rd inat, nt in whloh 2 tmoioeed tra nslation of a note reoelved from Vv noting Minister lor Iroreiaa Affairs oxMnmmlOi ting the offioir 1 th'n^s of the tfej* a uovermnent for the motion ta&amp;en by Mie Majesty’s Ooverntient as reported in your tel gr&amp;w !Jo.e? of the 20th ultimo and ftialtire telegr m to the Colonial or io# lo.ar of ymy ^eth. •-• wn h ve the honour to enoloae trans* Xation of a second note received from the acting Sinister for foreign Aft airs la re. oect of the sane action. It is of r ther different t nor. fhe good- vill of ^ia ^nj©sty t s GoV6mnent . nd its deaire to coo er&amp;te wit i the hejass Oevemusent a • pears to ; heikh .iuad, ;vparently on neoond t.-ouf to he considerably less mamifeat t&gt;ian inilo tm in ia first note, ue now sUtos indotd that the visit of the rebel leaders to doreit territory and their interview i&amp;t:i the elitiaM He re tentative eouled with tie faot that taey were Ml owed to retain in . afety has oau^edaa very bad impression amd has el^^n rise to rumours t.-at His f » aoverument not carrying out their obligations. t:; « he trusts Uiat instructions will V given to the responsible authorities in future to arrest stiob peroona end to h nd %iwm over to toe He jam His Majesty's . rlnoi al SeoroWy of i tate for foreign iff aira.~U*\ no. i 4 / 3/40 29.3*1346. ( 3.9.29; h is xoellerioy i.-B. . Agent and oonsul the goodwill and the desire to /'■v co-operate with his Majesty*a Oovrrment asniidsteA Dy the iriendljr jiritisu OoTernaent 9 by tneir refusing on two occasions to listen to the rebels against whom i.is Majesty tne King has sent the necessary forces in order to punish thorn for their hostile action towards the neighbouring countries, have had the beet of effects ana impressions on my acvernmcntg is hritannic * ajesty’s Govi rnment, as reported in four xoeiienoy*s two notes «o.1477/33/160 ol duly 27th, 1929, and *0.1747/33/19? of ..ugust 27th, 19; 9 , in pursuanee of wiiion orders were given for actio t to be teucen against tiie rebels, is evidence of firra friendship, and His Majesty's obernjaent welcome it with taanks and a sense of obligation. communicate my Government's thanks officially to His Britannia Majesty's Governiacnt for tne honourable position which they took up. 11 . t the hi gut? s t r« . u u ts • 1 'ae resolute course adopted by 1 mi directed therefore to *tfhB HivHAA oting Minister for ioreign AffairsTelegram. M. From. BritAgent Jeddah. To Zusacari Kuwait. No. 192. Dated 21/9/29 reed. 22/9/29. Addressed Foreigm Office Telegram No.139, repeated Kuwait Bushire Jerusalem, Baghdad, Simla 192, copies by post to Cairo, Aden. My telegram No.130. Government Officials in conversation talk of sucess punitive expedition. I am informed on good authority though that punitive force has been defeated at ^ady Subai, a little north of Khurma, and that large proportion has deserted. Strong rumours that well known Wahabi leader Khalid bln Lowai the Commander expedition has withdrawn to Khurma, and that Taraba, place mentioned paragraph two of my telegram referred to is now in hands rebel tribes added to facts that two caravans have been attacked on north Mecca^ Taif road and a number of cars sent from Taif to Riyadh with supplies have been obliged return via Medina, tend confirm rumour defeat. I also learn from same source that situation at WehJ and A1 Ula is giving cause for disquietude. Certain of the Ashraf leaders are said to be at bottom present troubles.prom Political, Kuwait, To Resident, Busliire. Repeated to Higiicoma, Baghdad; Special, hasrah. No.54&gt;&gt;. Dated P4th September i^^^. Shaikh says it may be taken as certain now that Azaiyiz with approximately men were killed after inflicting equally heave losses on their opponents. Addressed to Resident in the Persian Gulf repeated to High Commissioner for 'Iraq, and Special, Basrah. political.SECRET •H-') political Agency, Kuwait. Dated tJie 24tii September 1^29. from Lieutenant-colonel H*R*P.Dickson, C.I.E., Political Agent, Kuwait. To The Hon*bl© the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Intelligence - situation in Hassa &amp; Hejd. Sir, In continuation of my No.5&gt;7 dated loth September 1929 and my telegram Ho.542 dated 21st September 1929 , I have the honour to report a very interesting conversa *4 tion with Shaikh Hillal al ifutairi which I had yester day the 2Jrd September 1929 . This individual as you know resides in Kuwait and is probably the wealthiest man in the Persian Gulf to day. He maintains, at all times, the closest touch with Nejd, and more particularly with Faisal al Duwish and Ibn Ashwan the two most important Rebel Leaders. With the foimer because of a life long friendship between them, and with the latter because Ibn Ashwan is the head of Shaikh Hillal f s own tribe the Uutair (Braieh) 2. Shaikh Hillal al Mutairi’s knowledge of affairs in Central Arabia generally, and especially his know ledge of Desert politics and the things that the great Bedouin tribes are thinking of and discussing, is in my opinion unique, and being a man of 70 years old with mind still active and strong, whatever he has to say is usually tempered with Judgement and common sense. 5« In politics Shaikh Hillal is a Ifutairi tribes men first, secondly a Kuwaiti pearl merchant and loyal- 2 - aubject of the ai Sutah, Lastly he is, and always has been an anti-Bin Saudite and as such his sympa thies are entirely with the Rebels. Being however, as I said above a man of long views and clear pers- the Shatt al-Arab on 21st September 1929 where incidentally he received on l 6 th September 1929 as visitors Mutrij ibn Hijaa (Ataiba) and Rihan ibn Marwi (Mutairi) both resident in Transjordan. These individuals according to the Special Service Officer Basrah’s report No.l/BS/1 dated 17th September 1929 paragraph (a) brought letters from Abdullah al Misfir, who holds an important position in the palace at [ Baghdad. Thetw would appear to be a connection between the visit of these men and items of news mentioned in paragraph 6 below. imparted the following information which is given below in the form of sub-paragraphs. (a) Azaiyiz the son of al Duwish was un- doubtedly hilled at urn el Rudhumma but with h im not more than 2^0 men. The incident is looked upon as a regrettable incident and will in no way affect the plans of al Duwish. (b) Al Duwish had mobilized the Ajman and Uutair and was at the moment of writing moving South against the Awazim. Al Duwish had deliberately allowed the Awazim to hear of his movements in order to convey the impression that he intended pective, his appreciations of situations are nearly always sound. 4 Shaikh Hillal arrived from his estates on In his conversation with me Shaikh Hillal-5- © attacking them any&amp;ay now. They, the Awazim, with their allies and Bin Saud’s regulars (Sarraya) in all afcout 2^00 strong had formed a camp surrounded fcy tranches and defensive posts North-East by East of Nta and were to all intents and purposes awaiting the coming attack. (e) Duwish’s plan however was not to attack at all. Having got the Awazim concentrated with all their camels and sheep in a small area, he was going to surround them by a ring of camps distant four to five miles away, and force them either to come out of their trenches and attack him, or surrender. The large number of camels and sheep with the Awazim was their weakness, and would help force an£ early desision* These required to be grazed and as soon as they quitted camp, Faisals plan was that they should be attacked and rounded up. The superior strength of the Akhwan forces would enable them to adopt these tactics. (d) Al Duwish hoped for a complete surrender in a matter of 4 to 5 days by these methods; the only danger being that the Awazim would w tumble ,, to the plan before the door was closed to them, and would escape south to the Qatif or Huffuf oasis. (e) There was little chance of the Awazim moving over to the Akhwan side voluntarily as did the Braih, as theirs was a tribe originally subject to the Ajman, whom Bin Baud had fwxww freed from bondage and giventho status of an independant trite. Inci dentally tnis was iiow Bin Saud tiad won the Awaziia over to his side from their former allegiance to Kuwait. The Aw&amp;zim would lose their freedom once more if they threw in their lot with the rebels now and would again have to pay ’’iLhawa'* to their old lords the A^man. (f) Having accomplished his object of either forcing the Awazim to surrender or compel ling them to retire south, al Duwish’s next move would be to leave the Ajman masters in Hassa, and move with all his Mutair forces to Artawiyeh. Here he would establish his base and striking South West would seize the Sudair and Washm provinces and cut off Hiath from the rich province of Qassim. (g) The operation would not be difficult as Bin saud definitely had no troops (regular or tribal) in the field except the Awazim k their allies, &amp; the force under Ibn M*saad at Ajibba. There was nothing at all at Hafar al Atz or Awania (South of Nta) as reported in defferent quarters so per- sistantly. (h) As regards Qassim itself, the rebel leader^ al Dahaina was definitely alive &amp; well, and going from success to success. He had already established relations with the townspeople of Anaiza and was receiving all the supplies he required from that quarter.(1) Recent letters from al RJiaina to al Duwisli were repoarted tliat all was going well witii hia in Qassim, in spite of a temporary set back caused by tne report spread by Bin Saud tnat Hassa and Ktivait bad been taben over by tbe English, and that the Afchwan attached in rear were in extremis. This report for a short time had created some thing of consternation in the ranks of the Ataiba insurgents, but the truth was now known. (j) It was perfectly true that Bin Saud had possession of all the towns in iiassa, Nejd and Qassim today, but as far as Qassim was concerned this would not help him much as the inhabitants would be compelled to come to terms with the rebels who had it in their power to ruin all agriculture, gardens etc lying outside the town areas. As everywhere irrigation was by 'lift' from wells and as camels were the means used, these only had to be driven off by the Akhwan and all ir rigation would come to a standstill. Al Juwish was perfectly aware of this fact, &amp; once at Artawiyeh he intended to force Qassim to declare for him by means of this form of pressure. 6 . sdaiEh Hillal next confided to me the following which he described as ' most 8 eorot ,&gt; refusing to divulge the source he had got it from. He added that he could not definitely assure me, that what he said would 'come off' or turn out to be true, but that he believed that something on the lines of what is described below was being planned and would be attempted.- 6 - 1 -SZ- (a) (D) (c) s Tiie ini'o mat ion lie imparted was Tliat King Hassain would siiortly come to Baghdad from Gypurs for liis healtJi. That nuri al Shaalan and the ItUalla, would shortly start hostilities against Bin Sand and attack Jauf. That shaiumar Jarha under Ajil al Tarwar were arranging fox' a general move South of all Shammar elements in r Iraq, with a view of recover hail for the ar-Raschid family. That fehough all members of this family were state prisoners in Riath, there remained junior member of the family at large to whom it was intended to offer the cnieftainahip temporarily, (who this is is not clear). (d) That several prominent Shammar Shaihns were already at Baghdad arranging details of the above plot, and that the recent movements of messengers between Baghdad and al-Buwisn^ headfuarters were all to do with this plan. (e) Finally that Duwish had agreed to get into touch with loyal shammar elements still in Nejd and try and win them over also. 7 . i have given the above in detail, for coming from a of Hillal al Mutairi*s calibre, it is worth taking note of. As far as the information given in paragraph 5 goes, I personally believe Hillal al Jutairi nas given me correct news which he has received direct from al- Duwish and his agent in yassim. The report about al Rahaina’s successes nas been confirmed by the shaikh of Kuwait also and I think we may assume things are not going too well with Bin Baud in Hejd, though the report that Bin Baud cannotleave Riatii, siiouJLd be accepted with reserve. As regard* the 'very secret” news given in para graph 6 * I prefer to mahe no comments, though it is not improbable that skereefian elements wherever found will endeavour to further any plan that will embarrass Bin saud. I have the honour to be, i Sir, Your most obedient servant. Lieut-Colonel, political Agent, Kuwait@ effort soon, lie feared a serials of now enemies would arise and join Duwish against him. When I asked who these were, shaikh AhJaad replied that he had had it from Ali al Shuwairhat when he passed through a few days ago, that King Faisal had secretly sent for all the Shaamar refugee Shaikhs to Baghdad - vide Kuwait Diary No,l? paragraph I 56 - including Ajil al Yawar (Shammar Jarfca) and Agah ihn Ajil (Shammar Abda), and had called them cowards for not rising against Biu Saud and Making themselves masters of Hail, that the time was now ripe for action and if they did not move they deserved to he slaves for ali time. That when the Shammar shaikhs excused themselves pleading their fear of al-Duwish, he the King had said, 'Have no fear, I have arranged things with al-Duwish (*lat khafun Duwish andhi*)”• They then replied that they would not move till the cold weather set in and that if in the meantime Bin Saud did not htfing about a change in the situation, they the Shammar would act and throw in their lot with the in surgents. 5 . His Excellency said he had not paid much at tention to the above as he thought rather libellous story, at the time, but that it had now been corroborated by Hillal al Mutairi, in rather remarkable fashion . Shaikh Ahmad then proceeded to tell me exactly what Hillal had reported to me as 'most secret* information, (vide paragraph 6 of my No.54b). 6 . From the above there would appear some reason to suppose that al-Duwish is in touch with the Sheer- ifian party and is making efforts through them to get Shammar and Anaze to come in as allies by offering them Hail and Jauf respectively. 7. His Excellency shaikh Ahmad is, it would seemSean,i&gt;f tiie above opinion also, but is obviously cautious about stating bis views. He made one curious remark to me, which is worth recording. 'Remember al-Duwish is a great politician', he said, 'there is no question 0 f pin behind this rebellion; what puwish is playing for is the downfall of the house of baud and the rise of himself al-Duwish in -Bin gaud^ place, with success his horizon has become widened and now he hopes to become master of Nejd, and in the process does not oare if the Hljaz returns to the Shereefian family or Hail to Bin Easchid' • 6 . it must not of course be forgotten that the Shaiiih of Kuwait is among the anti-Bin Saudites. I have the honour to be, l</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0003bb_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/5/32</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0003bb</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/5/32</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>File [10/4] British relations with Ibn Sa`ud: activities of Faisal Al Duwish</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1929/1929</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-07-07T22:29:54</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (260 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 262; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 4-260; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains correspondence related to the British Government's relationship with Ibn Sa'ud [‘Abd al-‘Azīz bin ‘Abd al-Raḥmān bin Fayṣal Āl Sa‘ūd]. Specifically, the correspondence concerns hostilities between the forces of Ibn Sa'ud and the Ikhwan during the rebellion led by Faisal al-Duwaish [Faysal al-Duwaysh], the possibility of Ikhwan members entering Kuwaiti territory with their followers and tensions between Ibn Sa'ud and Kuwait.Much of the correspondence in the file is between British officials at the Political Agency in Kuwait, the Political Residency in Bushire, the High Commission in Iraq and the British Agency in Jeddah, but the file also contains copies of letters, in Arabic with English translations, from Ibn Sa'ud and the Ruler of Kuwait, Shaikh Ahmad al-Jaber al-Sabah.In addition to correspondence, the file contains the following:an English translation of a speech given by Ibn Sa'ud that was published in the Meccan newspaper
                              Umm al-Qurain July 1929 (folios 96-99).an account of a visit made to Kuwait by al-Duwaish in August 1929 written by the Political Agent in Kuwait, Major Harold Richard Patrick Dickson (folios 121-125);details of how Ibn Sa'ud established Wahhabi dominance at the
                              Masjid al-HaramMosque in Mecca (folios 140-142);a breakdown of the structure and tactics of Ibn Sa'ud's military forces (folios 151-153);an account of an interview between Dickson and Hilal al-Mutairi in Kuwait in September 1929 in which al-Mutairi claimed that King Faisal [Faysal] of Iraq was plotting with members of the Al Shammar tribe to support the Ikhwan rebellion against Ibn Sa'ud (folios 251-257).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>British Agent and Consul General, Jeddah</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="personal"><namePart>Fayṣal bin Sulṭān al-Dawīsh</namePart></name></subject><subject><topic>Ikhwan revolt (1927-1930)</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0003bb#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>