<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000602.0x0001ad_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-20T09:20:03.988Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">IAW-'- me XED In anj further communication on this subject, please quote No. £■ and address —not to any person oy r^ame^ but to-^ / “ The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. 1. r\p.z'~ | 2905 t ! 1935 J /etc THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his m. compliments to and, by direction of the Secretary of State transmits herewith cop-ci^ of the undermentioned paper.-r # &gt; i ^ / Foreign Office, i ( 1 , i93 -c 7&gt; Reference to previous correspondence : c^fo tfzrzfZ.. Description of 'Enclosure. '7/7 '*V'rV7/ L&gt; ' Name and Date. Subject. -as /Y° (£&gt; . &amp;cUZ£ /S’ 14—6130 10950(2) Simitar letter sent to 'tfy boy ~yK^t&gt; nf .y/ Sir, With refejsnce to your despu-toh Wo* 109 (£ 1417/ 13455/9^) of iwarch 7ti last, I have the honour to furnish the following o'bscr'v itions on the status of the Mesopotamia Persia Corporation, uimited. 2 0 The Corpoiition -ms registered in Iraq on July 3rd, 1919, under the provisions of the Companies Proclama tion issued on Juno hid, 1919, by the General Officer Commanding His Britamic Majesty's Forces in Mesopotamia. This proclamation, tie terns of which are still in force, made applicable, to companies formed in Iraq, the provisions of the Indian Companies .uCt of 1913. The registered office of the Corporation is at Basra. I understand that the Corporation is also registered in Persia in accordance with the Persian Companies law. 3. as originally constituted, the Corporation comprised the following firms, all of which were registered British companies:- Stephen Ly ich &amp; Company, Lynch Brot icrs, Limited, Gray, Maokansie &amp; Company and Gray, Paul Se Company. Of these firms, only Lynch Brothers Limited are now in existence,/ The Right Honourable Sir John Simon, G.C.S.I., K.C.V.Uo, etc etc etc*existence, but the capital of the Corporation is still held in its entirety &gt;&gt;y British subjects. 4* The business of the Corporation in Iraq consists mainly of purchasing raqi producewhich is then consigned to one or other of th ir principals in the United Kingdom - Messrs. Lynch Brother;., Limited, and Messrs. Gray, Lawes, Limited - by whom it ; s sold on commission. They also act as distributors of Un ted Kingdom manufactures and are, in addition, agents of t e British India Steam Navigation Company, the i- 1 . &amp; 0* team Navigation Company, the Euphrates &amp; Tigris Steam Naviga* ion Company, and Imperial Airways, all of which are register d in Great Britain. 5. Under the previsions of the Indian Companies Act (which, as shown abov v is now part of the law of Iraq) any company incorporated &lt;utside Iraq and having a place of business in Iraq must be registered there. The Iraqi Courts have held that a fore: gn company is deemed to have a place of business in Iraq w enever it has a branch expressly so styled or has, in Ira: , a representative authorized to act for tho Company as a &lt;isclosed principal. Consequently the shipping companies mertioned above have all been registered in Iraq in compliance with the law, the penalties against nen-registration bein^ heavy* 6 e . Yfhile, r ther&lt;fore, the Mesopotamia Persia Ccrpcraticn may not b&lt; legally constituted as a British company, their interests, on the other hand, are entirely British, and on the o&lt; casions when they have applied to this Embassy for supptrt, they have done so purely v/ith a view to protect those interests. Their protests against the assessment for taj ation of the British India Steam Navigation/e&lt;P ^ Navigation Oompany anc of Messrs,, G„ &amp; jJ. Norton; and their request for guidance in respect of the navigation rights of the Euphrates &amp; Tigris Ste&amp;ui Navigation Company are oases in point* Ca these occasions the right of His Majesty*s Representative to afford support to the Corporation has never been questioned by the Iraqi Government and I would suggest that there are. in the circumstances, good reasons for continuing some suoh measure of support as fas hitherto been accorded to the Corporation* 7o I consider t ic.t it would he a mistake to allow the impression to gain ground that His Majesty’s Government have withdrawn their sipport from the Corporation. It vonId probably bo difficult in practice to give support to British companies like the Euphrates &amp; Tigris Steam Navigation Company wit lout maintaining close relations with the local corporation that represents them here. 8* I do not, of course, wish to depart from the principle that only such companies as are British registered ai^o legally entitled to British diplomatic support. I understand, however, that His Majesty’s Government in the United Kingdom have at times countenanced a departure from this rule and that it is sometimes allowable, in deciding on the measure of aasi itance to be given to any given company, to attach some weight to its connexions and the situs of its capital holding, and not to regard the sikge social as the sole criterion. 9. I venture to suggest, subject to your concurrence, that the measure of assistance to bo given to the Mesopotamia Persia Corporation should be determined after consideration of/s C of tbs merits of each particular oa^e, and that no general injunction should be .aid down which would prevent Hie Majesty’s ifimbassy fro i assisting the Corporation irrespective of the oiroivnstao.oes * 10 ^ I am send in.; a copy of this? despatch to His Majesty s Minister at Tehran,, I have, etc» ? ( ?gi u ) ARCHIBALD CLARK KERB «0 COPY. (ID /o 5 / 0 (E 145/136/95) Mo. 755/E . (3^~/5/34) .. ./•... ..... British Embassy, Bagdad. 27th .December, 1934. ir. With reference to my despatch No. 650/E of November 6 th last, I gather from semi-official correspondence from your Department that the agitation against the freight rates on Iraqi exports which attained some prominence in Basra last Autumn has given rise to the impression that merchants who endeavoured to use British shipping were prevented from doing so by force. 2. I have made the necessary enquiries both in Bagdad and Basra on this point but can find no evidence in support of this allegation. A certain amount of moral suasion was, no doubt, exercised by those who considered Lhat they had a grievance, but I cannot find that these limits were ever exceeded in the endeavours made to secure a reduction in the rates charged by the British India Bteam Navigation Company and other British Companies. 3. While it appears to be true that the British India Company suffered to the extent of £1,000 as a result of the attempted boycott, I am given to understand that the methods of retaliation used by them (~fhich injeluded a general reduction in the price fetched by Iraqi dates in Bombay) have not been without effect and may give pause in future to those who contemplate similar action against them. 4./ The Right Honourable Sir John Simon, G.C.S.I., K.C.V.O., etc., etc* , etc.4. There is also an impression that Iraqi export merchants are being subsidized by the Iraqi Government so that they may induce ships of other Companies to compete with the British India and other British Companies. I am reliably informed, however, that all that has happened so far is that Abdul Jabbar has been given a repayable advance of ID.7,500 by the Iraqi Government to enable him to recondition his river fleet, and that his British competitors on the Tigris and Euphrates are not averse from this step. 5 . It is likely that the British India Steam Navigation Company will come to an early agreement with their competitors on the whole question of freight rates. 6 . I am sending a copy of this despatch to the Department of Overseas Trade. I have, etc., (Signed) F.H. Humphrys.fv DEXED In any further communication on this subject- please quote immunication on this subject- please quote No. \T -\tCyfe \lofc -lVi . ' to any person by name, but to— and address— not, “The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. X. am / 1 J n /&gt;ti THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith copvfi^o of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, , 1935 Reference to previous correspondence : ^ 0 Description of Enclosure.(Q&gt; copy Wo.698 (6/91/34) (lT~7696/662/93) TQ &gt; b \ r. Sir, I have the honour to report, with reference to your despatch No.779 (E 6583/662/93) of 12th November, that the Iraqi Government have now notified the agents of the British India Steam Navigation Company that the mail subsidy received by the Company for services rendered to the Indian Government is not liable to Iraqi Income Tax. 2. The income tax assessment made upon the Company is being adjusted accordingly and no further action on the part of the Board of Inland Revenue is necessary. I have, etc., (Sgd) P.H. Humphrys. British Embassy, Bagdad* ■ 11th December, 1934. The Right Honourable Sir John Simon, G.C.S.I., K.C.V.O., etc. , etc., etc.In anj further communication on this subject, please quote . no. t usi.'fc'fvi, and address —not to any person by name, but tlo— “The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. 1. rv. z: iresents his THE Under-Secretary of State for I jFore ijgof Affa irs compliments to and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith copvju* of the under-mentioned paper. 3) Foreign Office, X.\ , 193ly . v|5-f? Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. V\.V\ pEHOLOSURE 1' + ~ - f LETTER 1 NO ' 62 io7hECt3» fmom . AMD ffiCR-t I k . . . W 1 Similar letter sent to 14 —6130 10292 (2)THIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY’S GOVERNMENT ._il JU ^ i'./.. EASTERN (Iraq). i 7823 June 11, 1934. CONFIDENTIAL. l 19 34 Section 3. [E 3838/3838/93] No. 1. Mr. Ogilvie-Forbes to Sir John Simon.—(Received June 11.) (No. 302.) Sir, Bagdad, May 30, 1934. I HAVE the honour to inform you that the Iraqi Ministry of Finance have addressed to the Mesopotamia Persia Corporation (Limited) (presumably as agents of the Euphrates and Tigris Steam Navigation Company) a request for a copy of the permit granted by the Ottoman Government allowing the latter company the right to operate a steamship service on the River Tigris. 2 . The corporation have referred the request to their principals in London, and have informed the Ministry of Finance in this sense. 3 . I have the honour to enclose a memorandum dealing with the history of British navigation rights on the Tigris and the Euphrates compiled from such records as are available at this Embassy. From this memorandum it will be seen that no permit appears ever to have been held by the Euphrates and Tigris Steam Navigation Company or by their predecessors, Messrs. Lynch and Co. 4. There can be no doubt that the request of the Ministry of Finance has its origin in questions recently raised in Parliament and by the press concerning the participation of British companies in the river transport system of Iraq. This agitation was instigated by one Abdul Jabbar Khedery, an Iraqi competitor of the Euphrates and Tigris Steam Navigation Company, who was perturbed by a proposal of the customs authorities which, if carried into effect, might have deprived him of part of his share of the river traffic. Hitherto the Customs Administration have permitted off-loading at Basra and the transfer from ocean steamers direct to river steamers, for dutying at Bagdad, of cargo on through manifests to Bagdad; and also cargo on transhipment manifests for Bagdad for which ocean bills of lading were issued to Basra only. “ Through ” manifests were issued in respect of the steamers of the Euphrates and Tigris Steam Navigation Company only, and Abdul Jabbar’s share of the traffic consisted of the cargo manifested to Basra for transhipment to Bagdad. 5. Recently the Customs Administration gave consideration to ways and means of reducing the abnormal congestion existing on the customs wharves at Bagdad, and envisaged, amongst other remedies, the withdrawal of the facilities hitherto accorded to merchants for the dutying at Bagdad of cargo shipped to Basra on transhipment manifests. This would have entailed the discharge of such cargo at Basra, with consequent higher handling charges, and would seriously have affected the interests of Abdul Jabbar, while leaving those of the British company relatively untouched. 6 . The British companies are averse from antagonising Iraqi concerns, and I understand that Messrs. Strick, Scott and Co. and the Hansa Line, the principal ocean shippers concerned, have now agreed to the issue of through bills of lading to Bagdad by Abdul Jabbar's steamers equally with those of the British company in respect of river transport. Thus the disadvantages under which Abdul Jabbar has hitherto worked, and of which he feared an aggravation, have been removed, and a further manifestation of nationalist feelings in this connexion is probably unlikely. During the past' few weeks there have been suggestions put forward designed to induce the Iraqi Government to give some financial assistance to Abdul Jabbar. As, however, he now stands to lose nothing, it is possible that the last has been heard of this proposal. 7. I am sending a copy of this despatch and its enclosure to the Department of Overseas Trade. I have, &amp;c. G. OGILVIE-FORBES. [131 1—3]2 Enclosure in No. 1 . Right of the Euphrates and Tigris Steam Navigation Company to Operate a Service of Steamers on the Tigris. THE history of British navigation rights on the Tigris and Euphrates, and of the disputes with the Ottoman Government incidental thereto, goes back well over 100 years. The earliest reference to these rights is contained in a treaty of 1661 between Great Britain and Turkey, containing the following clauses :— “ IV. All English ships or vessels, small or great, shall and may at any any time safely and securely come and harbour in any of the ports and seas of our dominions, and likewise may thence depart at their leisure, without detention or hindrance of any man.” AA. JA. ^ TV* TV TV TV TV “ XXII. The English nation and all those that come under the banner of their vessels, small and great, shall and may navigate, traffic, buy, sell and abide in all parts of our dominions .... and their ships and vessels may come safely and securely to anchor at all times, and traffic at all times in every part of our dominions.” In 1798 a British agent of the East India Company was permanently located at Bagdad, and there must have been considerable traffic between Basra and Bagdad to necessitate the establishment of such an agency. The river traffic was, it appears, carried on by means of country boats owned or hired by the East India Company and by British merchant vessels flying the British flag. In 1834 the Sublime Porte issued a firman, at the instance of His Majesty’s Government, granting premission to “ the British Government ” to navigate by turn two steamboats on the River Euphrates “ for the purposes of facilitating commerce.” This firman subsequently gave rise to a long series of misunder standings, generally deliberate on the part of the Ottoman Government, which caused the right of British vessels to navigate the Tigris and Euphrates to be continually called in question. In actual fact, the two steamers to which the firman referred were not engaged in commerce, but were carrying out survey work on the Euphrates on behalf of His Majesty’s Government; and the rights conferred by treaty and acquired by usage were not affected in any way by the terms of the firman. In 1841 a second firman was obtained. This recited the terms of the previous firman and guaranteed the protection of the commandant of the two steamers when in the execution of his duties. (The original of this firman is believed to be at the British Embassy in Constantinople.) The fact that the name of the commandant was Lynch subsequently gave rise to much confusion, and enabled the Turkish authorities to argue that the navigation rights of the Euphrates and Tigris Company (Lynch and Co.) derived from this firman, and were consequently confined to the Euphrates. In 1845 a dispute arose between the Turkish authorities at Bagdad and the British representative as to the liability to taxation, other than the usual import and export dues, of British vessels navigating the Tigris. The Vali of Bagdad questioned, incidentally, the right of British vessels to navigate the Tigris at all except under special firman. The matter was taken up at Constantinople, and in April 1846 the British Ambassador obtained a Vizirial letter addressed to the Pasha of Bagdad, which dealt chiefly with the question of taxation, but which recognised imlicitly the navigation rights of British vessels on the interior waters of the country. The terms of this letter were confirmed by further Vizirial letters of 1861 and i862. It was in 1864 that the Ottoman Government first based their objection to British commercial navigation of the rivers on the terms of the two firmans of 1834 and 1841, which in reality applied only to British Government vessels. For some reason this contention was allowed to pass unquestioned, and it was not until 1883 that anyone thought it worth while to traverse it. The same ill-founded argument was adduced time after time whenever the question of replacing a vessel of the Euphrates and Tigris Company arose.3 In 1875 controversy arose over the right of the Euphrates and Tigris Company to tow barges on the Tigris. The Ottoman Government again relied on the wording of the inapplicable firmans of 1834 and 1841. The then Political Agent was instructed to report on the whole question, and the following main conclusions were reached by him : — ( 1 ) That the British Government has under the firmans of 1834 and 1841, which have been confirmed by the Vizirial letters of January 1861 and July 1862, the right, subject to certain special conditions, to navigate the River Euphrates with two steamers, “ for the purposes of trade.” ( 2 ) That under the arrangements of 1846, also confirmed in the Vizirial letters of 1861 and 1862, British merchants are at liberty to navigate the Tigris and the Euphrates under the British flag and without any restriction as to the number or description of the vessels employed, subject to the payment of the stipulated dues. (3) That the Euphrates and Tigris Steam Navigation Company, represented by Lynch and Co., have no firman granting them an exclusive privilege to navigate the Tigris with two, and only two, steamers. Their rights really depend on the arrangement of 1846, and so far are neither greater nor less than those that may be claimed by any British merchant. The Political Agent also quoted, in support of his conclusion numbered ( 2 ) above, article 8 of the treaty of 1861, which permitted the import and export of merchandise in British vessels equally with Ottoman vessels, whatever the place of origin or destination of the goods concerned. In 1883 trouble again arose over the request of Lynch and Co. to be allowed to replace an old steamer by a new one. The Ottoman authorities again relied on the firmans of 1834 and 1841, asserting on this occasion that British vessels were entitled to navigate the Euphrates only, and going so far as to prevent the sailing of Lynch’s boats. Pressure was brought to bear on the Sublime Porte by the Ambassador at Constantinople, and eventually all restrictions on navigation were removed, the Ottoman Government yielding apparently to the clearly expressed view of His Majesty’s Government that the firmans of 1834 and 1841 had nothing whatever to do with the rights of navigation of British merchant vessels, which derived from usage, from the Vizirial letters of 1846, 1861 and 1862, and from treaty stipulations; but they refrained from admitting as much definitely and in writing, and the survival of the old argument is apparent in the terms of an agreement concluded just before the outbreak of the Great War. In 1913 Lord Inchcape negotiated a concession with Hakki Pasha, the authorised representative of the Ottoman Government, for the exclusive right of navigation of the Tigris and Euphrates and of all navigable waters connected therewith. The concessionnaire was to form an Ottoman company within a specified time. An appendix to the concession provided that it should not come into force until after ratification by the British and Ottoman Governments of a declaration on the same subject signed by Sir Edward Grey and Hakki Pasha in London on the 29th July, 1913. This declaration was never ratified, and consequently the concession never entered into force. In article 4 of the concession it is stipulated that nothing in the concession shall in any way impair the liberties then enjoyed by Messrs. Lynch or their nominees with respect to navigation on the Rivers Tigris and Euphrates, these liberties being quoted in a schedule attached to the concession, reading :— “ (A) Two steamers flying the British flag shall continue to navigate the Rivers Tigris and Euphrates, and to participate in the general right of navigation on the Shatt-el-Arab. “ (B) One steamer flying the British flag shall be held in reserve to replace either of the aforesaid steamers during disablement. “ (C) The two steamers actually plying shall be at liberty as heretofore to tow two barges each. “ (D) One steamer placed under the direction of Messrs. Lynch or their nominees, but flying the Turkish flag when outside the port, shall be at liberty to navigate concurrently with the two steamers specified above, and likewise to tow barges.”These provisos are reproduced in the declaration signed by Sir Edward Grey and Hakki Pasha. It is curious that the Foreign Secretary should have consented to admit in this way, by implication, the Turkish point of view, hitherto held to be completely erroneous, that the number of vessels maintained in the Mesopotamian rivers was subject to limitation. No doubt it was felt that the grant of the concession justified an admission of the truth of what was manifestly false, but of the falsity of which it would have taken several years to convince the Turkish Government. After the war no question of the navigation rights of foreign vessels on the Mesopotamian rivers arose, although no definite declaration appears to have been made throwing them open to international traffic. Lord Inchcape raised the question of the validity of his concession, consequent upon rumours of restrictive measures by the Iraqi Government in 1924, and was informed that, for • the reason given above, it could not be considered as being, or ever having been, in force; but that His Majesty’s Government would have no objection to his applying to the Iraqi Government for a new concession on the lines of that of 1913. He did not, however, take any action in the matter. The Euphrates and Tigris Steam Navigation Company at present operate, at certain seasons of the year, as many as thirteen steamers on the River Tigris. It would therefore be unwise for them, as successors of Lynch and Co., to rely on the admission in the schedule to the concession above mentioned that Lynch and Co. had long enjoyed the right to employ two steamers on the Tigris, even if that argument were held to have any force, which is at least doubtful. They could plead usage, and the terms of the Vizirial letters of 1846, 1861 and 1862, but it was held at the time that such Vizirial letters were not binding for any indefinite period of time and could be revoked at will; and the Iraqi Govern ment, as successors of the Ottoman Government, could therefore presumably take such action, and usage alone would not operate to prevent the Iraqi Government enacting a cabotage law, in the absence of any contrary undertaking by the Iraqi State. One is therefore forced to the conclusion that the only useful course of action open to the Euphrates and Tigris Steam Navigation Company, to safeguard their interests in the event of the enactment of some nationalistic measure by the Iraqi Government, would be to constitute themselves an Iraqi company. It is improbable that they will be willing to do this except as a last \ resource, but it might be well for them to bear in mind that the growth of I nationalism in Iraq may later make the constitution of an Iraqi company with ( British shareholders a more difficult matter than it is at present. Bagdad, May 23, 1934. C. A. W. W.('D n C0£^. (E 6237/3836/ 23) i'jo. 564. (326/16/34) jritisu Sabas, ^a b dad. £4til September, 1934. Sir, In continuation of despatcii uo. 505 of ^ugust £9tli last, regarding tne right of the Euphrates and Tigris Steam Navigation Company to navigate tne rivers Tigris and Euphrates, I have the honour to transmit to you herewith a copy of the letter which the local manager of the Mesopotamia Persia Corporation has addressed to the Iraqi Director-General of Commerce, in reply to his request to be furnished with copies of the Turkish Vizerial letters of 1646, 1661 and 1662. 2. The letter to the Director-General was drafted in consultation with His majesty T s Embassy, after tne Managing Director had obtained the approval of the Head Office of the Company in London to a reply in the proposed terms. 3. I am sending a copy of this despatch to the Department of Overseas Trade. I have, etc., (Signed) George Ogilvie-Forbes. The Right Honourable Sir John Simon, G.C.S.I., K.C.V.O., etc ., etc., etc.■■■ Enclosure in iiagdad Lespatcn no. 564 of E4/9/34. E/^W42. Translation. Ibtii September, 1934. Lear Sir, With, further reference to your letter No. 544£ of the 25th ultimo, I am now instructed by the E.&amp; T.S.N.Go.Ltd., London, to advise you that as the Vizerial Letters of 1846, 1861 and 166L referred to, are a part of the British Diplomatic Records, it is not within the competence of the Company to submit copies to your Ministry. the necessary application should be made, through the usual, diplomatic channels, to the Foreign Office in London. It is therefore suggested that, if you so desire, Lours faithfully, (Signed) J.L. BnTTSY. Director. To The Director-General of Commerce and Income-Tax, Ministry of Finance, Bagdad .nication on this subject, please quote E. ViOiSiy'i’wlsV^ y person by nathe, but to— In any further communication on this subject, please quote /'''v No. and address —not to any “The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. 1. T / 19 .. J 53^ h/~ ^ THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to T ». X S 4 &gt;Teu*» — t ■ 1 and, by direction of the Secretary of State,ILPA..,j5PP^it ( 377 / 3 / 34 ) c-ir, Bug'iuudU 6 th 1934# I hare the tujnour to Invito a reference to ny daayataii Mo* 6 66 /k of Boptoahor 20th on tte ou^^oot of tho local pi*ese osuajp-algn against allogod excessive frolgiit ratos on export® of Xra^l produce* 2* 7he retaliatory action taken by the British India t-teaai Navigation coiapaay in reducing their rates for the carriage of Iraqi produce to Indian Porta to Ha*5/«» f aa against the rate of lie*a/- fixed by the .astern uteaw Navig ation Coiaj/any of i^oabay in agreement with Abdul Jabber iihcdalry has ao far had little effect, ainoe local ahippers have I adhered to their undertaking to ship by the last mentioned aoifcpany f a steaucra* In a further effort to break the oppos ition the British company is now accepting Iraqi produce for carriage to India without pre-payment of fixed freight, consignments ao shipped being sold to the beat advantage on I the Indian market and freight recovered from the proceeds of |sale* 3* the Minister of Finance, Yusuf Beg uhanim, is reported to have stated in the course of an interview given during his reeenfc visit to Basrah, that the Cabinet were giving serious attention to what is described aa *th© problem of exorbitant shipping rates, which is the principal concern of date producers', and to have said that three possible solutions presented themselves - the establishment of an Iraqi Navigation Company which would acquire a number of ateamere; the creation of a company which would charter foreign The Bight honourable Dir John -Jlmon, 0*0* * I., k. 0.7*0., etc* • etc* • etc* /vessels3 vaanala at raa&amp;onafele ratea; or tiio conati tut I on of a body to act aa interaodtary between shipping companies and ahlppere with a view to eacuring that freight® were flaced at a fair lewel* 4* I an aendlng a copy of tala despatch to the *iepajrt~ aent of i rerseaa Trade* I have the honour t© be with the highest respect, hir, Your most obedient, humble Servant, Slsne*) Q. QGILVIE FOR'/FScation on this subject, please quote In any further communication on this subject, please No. and address —not to any person by name, but to- “The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. 7588 THE Under-Secretary of State for foreign Affa-frs—^resents his compliments to — u. and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop\SL/» of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, \\ , 193\* . Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. Jf? 'pd-' •' /ft' Name and Date. Subject. 14—6x30 10292(2) OJu-JcLTHIS DOCUMENT IS THE PROPERTY OF HIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY’S GOVERNMENT CONFIDENTIAL. (14505) [E 6501/5462/93] Memorandum by Mr. T. G. McNie, of the Iraqi Ministry of Economics and Communications, on the History of Steam Navigation in the Middle East.—(Communicated by His Majesty's Embassy at Bagdad, October 1934.) [ In continuation of Foreign Office Memorandum No. 10207, Confidential, of April 24, 1913, respecting the navigation of the Tigris and Euphrates.] IN spite of the remoteness and inaccessibility of Iraq from the birthplace of steam navigation, the Rivers Euphrates and Tigris saw the first steamers only seventeen years after the Comet, the first successful commercial steam vessel, had been launched on the Clyde. This early contact was due to the enterprise of the British Government in trying to find, by means of steam navigation, a shorter route to India than that round the Cape when they decided to place steamers on the Euphrates to run from Berijah near Aleppo to the Shatt-el-Arab. It could not have been by chance that the Euphrates was selected, as there was an English trading station at Aleppo in Queen Elizabeth’s time, which owned over 300 vessels on that river, whether safinas or shakturs (see Note 1 ) is not known, and this trading station was used for the transmission of goods from the Far East as well as from Arabia. It is mentioned by Shakespeare in one of his plays : “ My husband’s to Aleppo gone, captain of the Tiger,' and there is actually a record of the journey of two London merchants to Tripoli aboard the Tyger, on their way to Aleppo, Bagdad and Ormuz. In 1835 an expedition was formed and named after its commander. Colonel Chesney, “ The Chesney Expedition.” This new venture started from England in February aboard the sailing ship George Canning, which carried as part of its cargo two paddle steamers in plates and framework, as well as the seventy-five members of the expedition, which consisted of naval ratings, marines and artillerymen. The George Canning landed the expedition at the mouth of the River Orontes in the Gulf of Sardia on the Syrian coast (Note 2), on the 12 th March of the same year, and Colonel Chesney was faced with the difficult task of transporting two steamers, in sections, with all their machinery, from the Mediterranean to the Euphrates, a distance of over 180 miles, with little or no roads, and very inadequate transport facilities. This, however, was accomplished safely, though many anxious days were experienced with the boilers and engines, which could not be dismantled into easily handled packages. As an instance, it is said that it took 104 oxen with fifty-two drivers to haul the boiler of the Tigris, which was the smaller of the two vessels. On reaching the Euphrates, a base was established 2J miles below Berijek and called Port William (Note 3), after the then reigning monarch of Great Britain, and the work of assembling the two steamers was begun. The vessels were reassembled and launched, and called the Euphrates and the Tigris, and they started their first voyage on the 16th March, 1836, almost a year from the date of landing. Considering the difficulties of transport, of establishing a port, and the backwardness of the country in which they were working, this in itself was a remarkable feat. These two steamers were built by John Laird of Liverpool in 1834, the Euphrates being 103 feet long by 19 feet beam, and the Tigris 70 feet long by 16 feet beam, and had engines of 50 and 20 horse-power, respectively. The Tigris had a very short existence, as she was sunk during a violent squall on the 21st May, only two months after starting the downward trip. The squall was so great that the two vessels lost touch with each other for a time, and 7670 [10822] B2 then almost collided, but the waves were so high and the visibility so poor, that the Euphrates could render no assistance to the smaller vessel. The whole of the cash carried by the expedition and a large part of the instruments and stores were lost with the Tigris, and the position of the wreck could not be immediately located. This unfortunate disaster occurred at Werdi, about 90 miles above Ana, and twenty members of the crew were drowned, including Lieutenant Cockburn of the Royal Artillery, and Lieutenant Lynch of the 26th Bengal Native Infantry, who was a brother of the second-in-command, Lieutenant Henry Blosse Lynch. The remnant of the expedition carried on in the Euphrates and made a survey of the River Euphrates to Kurna; they arrived at Basra on the 19th June, 1836, and then proceeded to Bushire to refit. On the 25th July, repairs having been completed, the Euphrates was towed from Bushire to the Shatt-el-Arab by the Elphinstone, and then proceeded under her own steam up that estuary to Kut-el-Frangi, the modern Margil (Note 4 ), which was then the home of the Basra Political Agency. Later, with Colonel Chesney and Lieutenant H. B. Lynch on board, she steamed up the Tigris to Bagdad (Note 5), arriving there on the 30th August, 1836, the first steamship to be seen in front of that historic city. She left again for Mohammerah on the 5th September. Some time after this she sailed from Mohammerah, bound for Port William, carrying an Indian mail for Europe, but only got as far as Lam-Lam, 140 miles upstream, when a serious accident befell her machinery, and she had to drift back all the way to her starting place for repair. These repairs were carried out by the help of the Indian naval steamer, the Hugh Lindsay (Note 6 ), the first steamship to enter the Persian Gulf (Note 7). This accident, together with the disaster to the Tigris, helped to a great extent to discourage the home authorities, and it was acknowledged that the Isthmus and Red Sea route, though longer, would be cheaper and safer than the Euphrates route, and in consequence, in January 1837, the expedition was broken up and the surviving vessel, the Euphrates, was handed over to the Honourable East India Company. The expedition had failed, but it had served a purpose. It had introduced steamships and steam-driven machinery to a little-known country, and brought that country to the notice of people who were one day to see the possibilities of using these modern inventions on its rivers for the benefit of its people. An attempt was made by Lieutenant H. B. Lynch to reach Mosul in 1837, but the Euphrates only got as far as Nimrod at the function of the Tigris and the Greater Zab (Note 8 ). The East India Company were still playing with the idea of utilising steam navigation on the Euphrates and Tigris, and sent out Commander Hawkins to take charge of the vessel and make another trip up river. In March 1838 the Euphrates steamed up the river as far as Hit, but great difficulty was experienced in passing the marshes on its lower courses, and an adverse report resulted. In 1838 Lieutenant Lynch again took the Euphrates up the same river from Kurna (Note 9) to above Fallujah, and, steaming down the Saklawiyah and Khirr Canals (Note 10 ), crossed the desert from the Euphrates to the Tigris a memorable voyage, and one not to be equalled until 1912. After crossing the desert, Lieutenant Lynch made another attempt in his vessel to reach MosuT but he had to return after reaching Kut Abdullah, about 20 miles from his o- 0 al. In June 1839, in order to furnish proper surveys of the Tigris and Euphrates, the Last India Company sent out via the Cape three other iron steam vessels These thiee vessels, named the A. ssyria, the Nimrod and the Nitocris, were shipped in framework on the sailing vessel Urania, and they arrived in Basra on the 22 nd December, 1839. Here they were immediately put together at Kut-el-Frangi, or Margil, and finished in April 1840, and'from that date until 1842 the steam flotilla on the two rivers consisted of Euphrates, Nimrod, Assyria and Nitocris. ’ ’ ^ The Euphrates had very little artillery, but the new steamers each carried six swivel guns and a large gun, mounted fore and aft. The activities of these four vessels were well known, and a complete navigable survey of the Rivers Tigris and Euphrates was accomplished. The chief performance of the flotilla was a trip up the Euphrates in the Nitocris and Nimrod in 1841 by Lieutenant C. D. Campbell, assisted by Lieutenant Felix Jones€ 3 They left Basra on the 1 st April, and reached Meskena on the 31st May, and the little Nimrod, under Campbell, got as far as Beles, which was considered a very remarkable feat. During the downward trip the Nimrod struck a snag or rock and was sunk, but she was raised and refloated, and Kurna was reached about the end of May 1842. The only result of this remarkable voyage, unfortunately, was clearly to demonstrate that the navigation of the River Euphrates was impracticable. In 1837 Captain Estcourt of the Chesney Expedition had reached Ahwaz in the steamer Euphrates, and reported on its possibilities. Therefore, in 1841, the Assyria, under Lieutenant Selby, navigated the Karun (Note 11 ), and also its tributaries the Gorgar and the biz, as far as Shuster and Kut Bandar, as well as the Bahmanshir channel, from Mohammerah to the sea. An account of several voyages performed by Mr. Layard the eminent archaeologist, in the Assyria, on both the Karun and the Tigris, is mentioned in his early adventures. All this was of great service to the countries concerned, in spite of obstacles and objections put in the way by Turks, Russians and Persians. The general outcome of the Chesney Expedition and of over twenty years of labour on the part of the Indian naval officers, who continued its work, was that Iraq had been converted from a terra incognita into a country perfectly well understood in its main features, and with certain important districts outlined in great detail. After the survey was completed and no further work could be found for the four vessels, the Euphrates, the Nimrod and the Assyria were withdrawn in 1842, and taken in tow to Bombay by the East India^ Company steamer Semiramis, the Euphrates on the 13th May, the Nimrod on the 29th June, and the Assyria on the 10 th August. The Nitocris remained on the two rivers under the command of Lieutenant Felix Jones, who succeeded Captain H. B. Lynch in 1843, and in 1846 he made an attempt in her reach Mosul, but only got as far as Tekrit, 142 miles above Bagdad. On the 16th May, 1846, the Nitocris was taken to Bombay for repairs and overhaul, and she returned to Bagdad in 1847, still under the command of Lieutenant Felix Jones. During the time she was away for repairs there was a rumour that she would not be returned or replaced, and the local merchants were seriously perturbed and petitioned for her to be sent back or replaced, as they declared that the presence of a British gunboat on the Tigris was very necessary for safe navigation. The Nitocris was particularly useful in 1849, when, in consequence of tribal wars, all locally owned navigation was stopped, though British-owned vessels were permitted to pass freely up and down the Tigris. In 1850, however, she was reported unserviceable, and in 1852 was so crippled by defective boilers that even had the Resident approved she could not have been prudently sent on any service where she might be required to come into action. At length in 1852 after a delay caused by the Burmese war. the Comet, a by no means new but otherwise suitable vessel, was refitted and sent out to Iraq to take the place of the Nitocris, which was broken up in Bagdad in the same year. The Comet was an old vessel of the Indian navy which had been built in 1838 and had taken part in the Sind operations in 1843. It does not appear that she was named after Henry Bell’s famous steamer on the Clyde as the Indian navy possessed at this time a whole galaxy of astronomical bodies including a Planet y a Satellite and a Meteor. Those six early vessels, the Euphrates, the Tigris, the Assyria, the Nimrod, the Nitocris, and the Comet were the real pioneers of steam navigation in Iraq. The Hugh Lindsay, as far as can be ascertained, did not return after effecting repairs to the Euphrates m 1836 and neither did the Semiramis, after its visit in 1842 to tow the Euphrates, Nimrod and the Assyria to Bombay, until its return during the Persian campaign. About this time the Turkish Government began to see possibilities in the use of steam vessels which could ply independently of wind or current. Here was an instrument to their hands to collect taxes or to overawe the unruly, a force that could be sent off without any delay and without the high costs of moving troops and baggage. In 1850-51, therefore, the Turkish Government started the Oman Ottoman Shipping Company, and their first two steamers were the Baghdadi and Basrawi, which were built in Belgium and sent out to Iraq in sections. Two more from the same firm, the Alans and the Naus, came out in 1854. [10822] b 24 Basra, about 1854, was visited by some of the new British steam frigates, very much larger vessels than any of the others. They were stationed in the Shatt-el-Arab at different periods during the Crimea War in order to demonstrate against the Persians, who were inclined to favour the Russian cause, and so visits were paid by the Auckland, the Ajdala and the Akbar, the Akbar pro ceeding up the estuary as far as Kurna. . ^ The Shatt was to have another influx of steamers in 1857 when the Persian war was drawing to a close and Sir J. Outram, the general in command, arrived before Mohammerah with the steam frigates Ferooz, Assays, Semiramis, Ajdala and Victoria of the Indian navy. They were assisted by the river gunboats, Assyria and Planet, and also by the Bagdad Political Agency vessel, Comet. This was the second visit to Iraq of the vessels Assyria and Semiramis, the Semiramis having come out in 1842 to tow the Assyria and her sister ships, Nimrod and Euphrates, to Bombay. The Comet especially distinguished herself in a dash to Ahwaz with the Assyria and Planet, under Commander Rennie. With the 78th Highlanders aboard they completed the rout of the Persians without loss to themselves and the campaign came to an end. About 1856 the Oman Ottoman Company began to have trouble with their steamers, as those who had control lacked the business qualities and experience necessary for running vessels. The boats were badly managed and did not run to time, and the Wali of that time, Kozlukly Mohd. Rashid Pasha, applied to the East India Company for the loan of an officer to put in charge of their vessels; Captain A. C. Holland, of the Comet, was appointed to the command of the Baghdadi and he was the captain of the first Turkish steamer in Iraq. Single- handed he could do very little, as his complaints went unheeded, and those in authority over him did their best to work against him instead of with him for the benefit of the company, so things went from bad to worse, and the merchants were again obliged to go back to their old way of working with mahelas. At this period a wealthy Bagdad merchant, Joseph Ezra Abraham Goorjy, made a great effort to establish some steamers on the Tigris under the charge of Captain Holland, but the Turkish authorities, unwilling to proclaim their own failure, would not grant him the necessary permit. In 1862 the firm of Lynch and Co., brothers of Lieutenant H. B. Lynch of the Chesney Expedition, through the good offices of Colonel R. Taylor, the Resident Agent at that time, got permission to run steamers on the Tigris, and com missioned the City of London, which had been built on the Thames by J. and A. Rennie and Co. and sent out round the Cape in a sailing ship in plates and angles. In the following year, 1863, during the administration of Namyk Pasha, three more steam vessels were ordered from Belgium for the Oman Ottoman Company, named the Phrat, Mosul and the Resafah. They did not, however, arrive at Basra until 1869. In 1865 Lynch Brothers had placed another steamer on the run. This was the Dejla, built in London by the same firm that built the London, and these two vessels carried the mails to connect up with the British India Steam Navigation Company, which had opened a service to Basra in 1863 (Note 12 ). Lynch Brothers were now strongly established. In 1871 the Oman Company brought out two more vessels which were built at Trieste. They were called the Telafar and the Maskena, and had engines of 50 b.h.p. The Maskena was a sort of freak ship. She had four paddle wheels and was sent out in plates and angles to Maskena on the Upper Euphrates. Here she was launched and for a time she plied between Maskena and Saklawiyah above Fallujah. In 1864 the Comet was reported unserviceable, and a relief ship called the Satellite was sent out from Bombay to relieve her, but whether she arrived or was lost en route is not known as no record can be found, but she does not seem to have plied as a Residency vessel on the Tigris and the Comet was not relieved until 1884. Prior to 1869 the Oman Ottoman Company’s vessels were used purely for Government purposes, such as the transport of troops, carrying of despatches and the subjection of tribes, but, subsequent to that year, they were devoted mainly to the carrying of cargo and passengers with the avowed intention of runningrs 5 Lynch s steamers off the river. The running of the river steamers proved a great benefit to the merchants, who no longer had to wait until convoys of mahelas were formed for mutual protection, and the thirty to fifty days spent in tracking local boats up and down the river was reduced to some six or eight. The payment of tolls to the sheikhs on the river, wherever they touched or banked in for the night, was also abolished and theft of goods by robbers reduced to a minimum. The Lynch boats became exceedingly popular for many reasons other than speed and reliability. They towed and carried a great deal of cargo, which was neither broached on the way or lost in the godowns, and their passengers were not called upon to pay their fares twice nor were they otherwise imposed upon. They sailed regularly and to time and, as they ran in conjunction with the British India Company, Bagdad, enjoyed, for the first time, the great advantage of an outward and inward weekly mail service. Under the first firman the British Government were allowed to have twp vessels on the Euphrates and Tigris, but when Lynch’s were granted permission i for a steamer service, Constantinople apparently purposely confused the political I vessel with those of Lynch Brothers, and persisted in stating from time to time that the concession was only for twowessels and not for three. Right up to the outbreak of the Great War. therefore, Lynch Brothers were liable, at any time, to have their vessels stopped and a guard put on them. The reasons given were varied and childish. Sometimes it was because the firman stated steamers only were allowed and not steamers and barges, although there is little difference between towing cargo and carrying it. Sometimes it was a definition of “ duba ' (barge). An iron barge was a “ duba,” and there was no mention of dubas in the articles and though they might tow mahelas they were not, on any account, allowed to tow dubas. This attitude on the part of the Turkish Government almost suggested that they wanted to restrict trade instead of increase it in the interior, and although Lynch applied to run vessels north of Bagdad to Samarrah it was not allowed. Whenever Lynch’s vessels were laid up, however, the Oman Ottoman freights were increased and the people responsible for the embargo were amongst the most disgusted, as there was more cargo to hand than both companies could conveniently carry. The country was still in an unruly state, even round and close to the principal towns, and in 1872 the British India mail steamer Cashmere was boarded and looted at Basra by a gang of armed robbers, practically under the guns of a Turkish war vessel. The thieves got away with property to the value of 42,000 rupees and killed a fireman and wounded the chief engineer, the chief officer and thirteen of the crew. Strong remonstrances made by the British Government resulted in most of the loot being recovered, and all the thieves with one or two exceptions were caught; several were hanged and the rest imprisoned. The incident of the Cashmere described above brought the Sheikh of Mohammerah to assist the authorities in the recovery of the loot and the apprehension of the culprits, and it was through his efforts that most of the booty was recaptured. In gratitude, the British India Company gave orders that I thereafter all their ships should fire a salute in the sheikh’s honour as they passed his palace at Mohammerah. This practice was continued until in recent years he/ was removed at the order of the Shah to Tehran. On one occasion this practice again nearly led to an international incident. Apparently, by accident or on purpose, someone had placed a cricket ball in the small mortar on a British India ship that was approaching Mohammerah. This was undetected, and when the round was fired the projectile fell startlingly near the sentry on guard at the sheikh’s palace. It took quite a lot of explaining by both the company and the British Government before his Excellency was pacified. In 1874 His Majesty’s steam frigate Philomel paid a visit to the port and went up the estuary as far as Kurna. In 1876 the Lynch steamer Dejla was sunk and totally lost through running on to the wreck of sunken mahela in Bagdadiyah Reach below Suwairah, where the wreck can still be seen in the low-water season. In 1878 Lynch and Co. put a new steamer into commission called the Blosse Lynch, named after the elder brother, and she was followed by the Kalifah in 1880 and by the Medjidiyah in 1881. Life on the Tigris in those days could be exciting. In 1874 a lion and two6 or three lionesses had been shot from the deck of the Lynch steamer Dejla by Captain Clements, who reported that one of the lionesses had sprung into the water and attempted to board the vessel. On the 8 th July, 1880, the new Lynch steamer Khalifah was attacked by x\rabs at Seay for near Ezra's Tomb. The marauders tried to board her and failing this kept up an incessant rifle fire and killed a quartermaster and a ^ passenger before the vessel got out of range. The captain, Mr. Clements, and chief engineer. Mr. Cole, were both badly wounded. The perpetrators of this outrage were never brought to justice, though several expeditions were sent against them by the Turkish Government. In 1879 the Oman vessel Telafar caught fire in the Shatt-el-Arab and was completely gutted. As it was considered too expensive to have her repaired and refitted she was never used again. The Oman Ottoman Company were not very fortunate in the running of their vessels, due to the want of proper supervision and properly trained officers and engineers, and to the practice of having their repairs done by local blacksmiths instead of in a properly organised workship ; consequently many of their vessels fell into disrepair and were often out of action for many months. For instance, the Baghdadi lay at Amarah for two months in 1882, and the Mosul was laid up at Basra from August 1882 until June 1883, a period of ten months. The Resafah was under repair for a year, and after 1883 the Rasrawi was no longer employed, all due to neglect and chicanery on the part of those responsible. In 1882 it was found absolutely necessary to replace the Residency vessel, the Comet, which had, since her exciting adventure up the Karun during the Persian war in 185/, led a useful, worthy, but uneventful existence as a carrier of despatches and mails, surveillance and protection of British trade and shipping, surveying and observation work and in maintaining friendly relations with the tribes on the rivers. After forty-four years of service she had to be laid away, but she had a respite, as the new vessel building at Bombay was not ready and Lynch s City of London was chartered to run on the rivers in the meantime as the Residency gunboat. It was a short-lived charter though, as when the City of London was proceeding to Bagdad she ran on a sand-bank at the mouth of the bweib River near Kurna, broke her back and was totally lost. Later it was found that the new vessel constructed was too large for use on Tigris and consequently a new vessel had to be built, but it was not ready until 1884. On its arrival the old Comet was broken up at South Gate (Note 13) in the same year. The new C omet was a vessel 125 feet long by 25 feet beam, drawing 3 feet of water and having a speed of 9 knots; her crew consisted of 1 officer, 4 warrant officers, 35 petty officers and men, and her armament was two • 45-in. 5-barrel Nor den felt guns. This Comet was not a lucky vessel, and her first commander, Captain Havelin. died in his bath at Ctesiphon on her first trip to Bagdad. The inconvenience of having no captain, however, did not deter Mr. Plowden, the British Resident at that time, from projecting a trip to Mosul, and in April 1885 (far too late in the year) a start was made. The gunner, a man named Nelson, was placed in command. Fahamah was reached the first day and after a prolonged halt of fifteen days they arrived within 10 miles of the Adhaim. After two more days they made Tikrit and two days later they ran aground about 10 miles below Baiji. Many attempts were made to refloat her, but they proved fruitless. ^ Mr. Plowden had therefore to return to Bagdad by Killick (Note 14) and the Comet remained hard and fast for almost a year until April 1886 when - she was got off by her new commander, Captain Downs, and, on the top of a biz rise, reached Bagdad in twenty-four hours. In 1894 the Comet, under Lieutenant Elwell Sutton made a trip up the river as tar as Samarah, but she did little of note, except the customary duties, until the outbreak of the Great War. In 1890 Bagdad was to have it first shipbuilder; he was a local blacksmith- mechanic named Joseph Haluta, and in the years between 1890 and 1895 he built the hulls of five vessels, the Dejla, the Hamidi or Nasrat, the Musoodi the harawadi ^and the Othmanli. \\ ith one exception, the engines for his boats were purchased abroad but the plates and angles were bought in the local market. Ine Dejla and the Hamidi were the first two screw vessels to belong to the country with the exception of Lynch’s steam launch and Mackenzie Gray’s Arab which came out in 1874 and 1884 respectively. The Masoodi and the Sarawadir 7 ,&amp;L were stern-wheelers, but the Othmanli was a paddle boat, her paddle shafts having originally been used on the old Comet. It was a remarkable feat, as Haluta was an illiterate man and could not make a drawing or plan, but laid out his plate and frames apparently by eye. It seems likely, though, that he must have had some assistance, as his stern-wheelers, 4 ^ as well as his screw vessels, were the first in the country and it is known that he bought his vertical engine (probably out of Lynch’s old launch) for the Hamidi from Abdullah, one of the engineers of the old Comet. These vessels ran for a time between Bagdad and Samarah on the pilgrim trade, and then the Dejla was sold to Abdul Jabbar-el-Khedhery, who ran it between Basra and Bagdad until it was laid up in 1929. The Hamidi eventually ran between Basra and Mohammerah as the Mudheiffery, but it sank near Salchiyah in 1923. The Masoodi also went to Basra, but sunk through neglect at Sarajah Creek. The Sarawadi, like the others, went to Basra, and is still running between || there and Mohammerah as the Mudheiffery. The Othmanli, Haluta’s largest vessel, had the shortest life, as she sunk at the Bagdad customs wharf in flood time after a trip to Samarah in 1906. In 1892 the firm of Lynch Brothers put a new steamer, the Malamir, on the river, and her first year was marked by a rebellion against the Turkish Govern ment of the Abu-Mohammed tribe. This tribe lived on the river and were responsible for the attack on the Khalifah in 1880 and for attacks on local and Turkish vessels in 1878, when on one occasion nine people were murdered. The tribe rose under Sheikh Zaidan, and several boats were plundered between Qalat Saleh and Kurna. The steamer Mosul was also fired on and prevented from passing through the disturbed area, though, on the same occasion, British vessels were allowed to proceed unmolested. About 1896 the Meskena, with a cargo of wool aboard, caught fire at Basra, and, being completely gutted, was left to corrode at Margil. In 1902 two Turkish gunboats arrived at Basra, the Kiled-el-Bahr and the Zohaf. In 1904 the old Oman Ottoman Company was purchased by the Senniye Department of the Ottoman Government, and they brought out in the same year the Barhaniyah and the Hamidiyah. These two steamers were built on the Clyde and sent out in plates and angles and reassembled at Basra under the supervision of Mr. Graham, their superintendent engineer. In 1908 the Turkish Government sent out to the Shatt-el-Arab the cruiser Marmaris, and in the following year Lynch Brothers put their large twin-screw steamer on the river. This was the J ulnar, which was later to distinguish itself in the war. In 1910 Asfar had a steamer called the Etoile de V Orient, and in 1912 the Senniye Department brought out their largest vessels, the Basrah and the Baghdad, which were fine double-engined, four-cylinder boats, 212 feet long and of 60 feet beam. Wonkhaus had started by now, and in 1912 they brought out the large / screw tug the Pioneer and two steam launches, the Tekrit and the Samarah. ( Two fast Thorneycroft river gunboats next made their appearance on the rivers for the Turkish Government, but, as far as can be found out, they had no names given them, but were called the “ offspring of the .Marmaris.” They must, however, have had some distinguishing number or colour. In 1912 the municipality instituted a ferry service between Karradah and Bagdad, and had two small steamers on that run called the Birinji and Ikinji. It could not have been a great success, as in 1912 the Ikinji crossed to the Euphrates by way of the Khirr and Saklawiyah canals in order to work on the construction of the Hindiyah Barrage, and the hull was still there up till a few years ago. The Birinji was sunk below Nasiriyah in 1914. At the outbreak of the Turko-Italian war in 1911 the Zohaf was sent from Basra to assist the Turkish navy in the Mediterranean, but she was captured by the Italians in the Red Sea. Before the Great War broke out in 1914 it was known that the Turks favoured the Germans, and the British cruiser Espiegle arrived in the Shatt-el-Arab to protect British interests, and on the 7th October a curious message in Turkish and Arabic was received aboard which read : “ Please voumma leave the Shatt before twenty-four hours ”; of this no notice was taken, and another message was received on the 13th which gave them eight days, after which force of arms was threatened. The Espiegle, however, remained until all ships had cleared and until war was declared between Britain and Turkey on the 31st. On the outbreak of war all Lynch's steamers with the exception of the Khalifah escaped capture, and the Medjidiyah, convoyed by the Comet, conveyed some hundreds of British refugees to Mohammerah. The presence of the Comet at Mohammerah after the outbreak of war was strongly objected to by the Turks. They demanded that she should be forced to leave Persian waters, and with the idea of giving her a warm reception all down the Shatt-el-Arab as soon as she appeared, they lined the banks of the estuary with artillery. The surveys done by her predecessors had, however, borne fruit, and the Bahmanshir Channel (Note 15), which was .parallel to the Shatt and connects Mohammerah to the sea, was sounded and found to be sufficient for her draught. Accordingly, one day, well screened by date-palms and quite unsuspected by the Turks, the Comet steamed down the back channel to join the British Expeditionary Force, and the chagrined Turks, who were still looking over their gun sights, were politely informed by the Persians that their demands had been complied wdth. The Comet from now on had a brief but glorious existence, and was in action continuously from Kurna to Amarah, and it was on her that General Townsend steamed ahead of his forces and bluffed the Turkish Commander of Amarah into a surrender, though he was 50 miles ahead of his troops and had only twenty-two Europeans aboard besides himself. She was also at the first battle of Kut, and Lieutenant-Commander Cookson, who was aboard her, was killed in a gallant enterprise for which his name was honoured by a posthumous V.C. The Comet, along with the Firefly, the Shaitan, the Shushan and the Sumana, took part in the advance to Ctesiphon, and in the retreat the Firefly ran aground at Aziziyah. The Comet, going to her assistance, came under heavy shell fire from both river banks and had to be abandoned aground and in flames, though the crew of both vessels escaped in the boats and were rescued by the Sumana. It is a curious fact that Mr. Tom Dexter, late dragoman of the Residency, was an engineer on board of her when she first came out from Bombay, and his son, Henry T. Dexter, was an engineer on her when she was shelled and destroyed. Of the Turkish war vessels, the Marmaris was sunk by the Espiegle at Kurna; one of its ‘ ‘ children ’' was sunk at Basra, the other was captured at Nasiriyah and is now the Tilda of the Basra Port Authority. The KUed-el-Bahr was sunk in the Shatt-el-Arab along with the old Baghdadi, the A Ians, the Ftoile de VOrient and a German ship called the Echatana, to provide an obstruction to the advance of the British war vessels. The Mosul was captured by Townsend in the first advance, and, after having run for some time between Basra and Sheikh Saad, was sunk at the mouth of the Chahala in order to divert the river as much as possible into the main channel. The Basrah was captured at Aziziyah, and after being run for some time was sent to Britain in 1919, but being in bad condition it did not get further than Malta or Gibraltar. Of the Wonkhaus tugs, the Pioneer, was captured at Aziziyah in General Maude’s advance, where she was acting as a gunboat, and was used by the British until 1919, when she was released and is still running on the Tigris under the Iraq flag. The other two were sunk, the Samarah by gunfire near Nasiriyah, and the Tikrit by the Turks in order to avoid capture by the British when they caught up with her near Shergat. The 'early Naus had corroded and rotted at Basra long before the war, and the Phrat and the Resafah were sunk to block the Euphrates Channel at Asawi Bend below Nasiriyah to prevent the passage of the British expeditionary vessels. The Barhaniyah and the Hamidiyah were blown up by the Turks to avoid capture, the first at Baiji and the Hamidiyah at Fatah. The Khalifah was recaptured at Aziziyah and is still in running order, as is also the Malamir. The Blosse Lynch was only broken up in 1926 and the Medjidiyah in 1928. The Julnar was the vessel which made the famous attempt to break the boom defending Kut in order to reach Townsend with food and ammunition, but the9 *Vf boom being made of chain and wire rope laid at an angle, the Julnar ran herself into the bank where she was captured, with all her crew who remained alive. She was under the charge of Commander Firman and Lieutenant-Commander Cowley. Firman was killed and Cowley murdered by General Nured Din of the Turkish Army, but both received post-humously the V.C. for their gallantry. The Senniye steamer Baghdad, being one of the newest and most powerful vessels with the Turks, managed to reach Mosul where she was captured, and was the first steamer in history to reach there, though there had been repeated attempts made by British Residency vessels since 1837. These being of small power could not stem the current. earners in Persia. We have already seen that Ahwaz had been visited in 1837 by the steamer Euphrates under Captain Estcount, in 1841 by Lieutenant Selby in the Assyria and in 1857 by the Comet and the Planet. In 1882 the Persians decided to try steam navigation for themselves, although their rivers did not lend themselves to navigation as easily as the Euphrates and Tigris, and in 1882 the Sheikh of Mohammerah had a small steamer plying called the Karun. In 1885 after the Karun River had been opened for navigation by order of the Shah, the firms of Grey, Mackenzie and Lynch despatched the Arab and the Blosse Lynch respectively to ply to Ahwaz. Later the Blosse Lynch was replaced by a stern-wheeler called the Shushan, a vessel of 150 feet and drawing only 2^ feet of water. In 1889 the Shah placed on the river the screw steamers Persepolis and Susa, which had been ordered from Germany in 1885. These last were found to be unsuitable and the PersepoUs was withdrawn and made a Gulf gunboat. In 1890, for diplomatic reasons, the Shushan was presented as a gift to the Shah and was run between Ahwaz and Basra, while the Susa maintained the connexion between Shuster and Ahwaz. Naval activities died a natural death in Persia, as far as the Gulf and the Karun were concerned, as, except for the running of the Imperial Customs vessel Mazaffri in 1902, no other vessels appear to have been brought out before the Great War. Bushire also had its little share of steamboat history, as it had, in 1872, an old Indian navy vessel called the Berenice, supplied for the use of the British Resident Sir Felix Jones, who had been responsible for a lot of survey work in Iraq in the early days. After 1876 Bushire was without a vessel until 1887, when the Lawrence was sent out by the Royal Indian Marine. The Lawrence was a fairly large vessel of 900 gross tons, 1,277 h.p., a speed of 12 knots and a crew of 90 men. She did yeoman service in the Gulf in British interests, and was serviceable enough to join the British expedition to Kurna when war broke out in 1914. The names of the steamers to visit the country and to belong to the country are given in order :— 1836 Tigris Sunk at Werdi 1836. 1836 Euphrates Returned to India 1842. 1836 Hugh Lindsay ... On a visit up the Gulf. 1840 A ssyria ... On a visit up the Gulf 1842. 1840 Nimrod ... On a visit up the Gulf 1842. 1840 Nitocris ... Broken up at Bagdad 1852. 1842 Semiramis Towed the Euphrates, the Assyria and Nimrod to India 1842. 1850-51 Baghdadi Sunk in the Shatt-el-Arab 1914. 1850-51 Basrawi ... Neglected and allowed to break up at Um Dejaj Creek, Basra. 1852 Comet Broken up at Bagdad 1884. 1854 A Ians Sunk in the Shatt-el-Arab 1914. 1854 Naus Corroded and sunk, Basra 1880. ) 1854 A uckland ...' 1854 Ajdala ... &gt; Steam frigates on dutv in the Persian Gulf. 1854 Akhar ... ... ^ ) [10822]10 1857 1857 1857 1857 1857 1857 1862 1862 1864 1865 1869 1869 1869 1871 1871 1874 1874 1878 1880 1881 1884 1885 1886 1892 1890-95 1890-95 1890-95 1890-95 1890-95 1904 1904 1908 1909 1910 1912 1912 1912 1912-13 1912-13 1912-13 Ferooz ... ... 1 A ssaye .. Semiramis Victoria .. A ssyria .. Planet British India Steam Navigation steamers ! Out with the Persian expedition in 1857 |* returned to India on signing of peace. and City of London., Satellite Dejla Mosul Sunk at Sweib, near Kurna, 1881. No information. Sunk at Bagdadiyah Reach 1876. Captured by the British and sunk at Amarah 1917. | Sunk in Euphrates below Nasiriyah 1914. Burnt out between Basra and Kurna 1879. Burnt out at Basra 1890. Lynch’s steam launch. Philomel ... At Kurna on duty. Broken up 1926. Still in running order, but laid up. Broken up 1928. Sunk at Aziziyah in 1915. Sunk 1900. Frat Re sa fah T elafar M eskena Blosse Lynch Khali fah Medjidiyah 2nd Comet Arab Shushan Malamir Dejla Hamidi or Nasrat Massoodi Sarawadi Othmanli Barhaniyah Hamidiyah M armaris J ulnar ... Etoile de V Orient Thorneycroft gunboats Birinji . Ekinji . Baghdad Basrah Pioneer , Samarah Tekrit Still running. Still running. Scrapped 1929. Sunk near Salachiyah 1923. Sunk at Sarajah. Running in the Mudheiffery. Sunk at Customs’ Wharf, Bagdad, 1906. Sunk at Tekrit 1917. Sunk at Tekrit 1917. Sunk at Kurna 1914. Sunk at Tekrit 1917. Captured and sunk by Turks 1914. One sunk at Basra 1914, the other the launch Tilda. Sunk below Nasiriyah 1914. At Hindiyah barrage 1926. Captured at Mosul 1917. Captured at Aziziyah 1917. Still running. Sunk at Nasiriyah 1914. Sunk at Shergat 1917. port The crew of the first British vessels were mostly Europeans, and some of them married and settled in the country, and their descendants still live in Bagdad. It is told that in the early days when the pay of the crew of the Turkish gunboats (which was nearly always in arrears) was very long overdue, they would detach and sell some of the wooden paddle floats, with the result that when orders to sail arrived, they were unable to do so, and had to make a report of an imaginarv breakdown to machinery in order to get money to replace the wooden paddle floats. An interesting relic was discovered in a home in Bagdad recently; it was the ship’s bell of the second Comet, which was set on fire and sunk by shell fire at Aziziyah by the Turks during Townsend’s retreat from Ctesiphon, and it is hoped that a suitable home may be found for it in some British museum in the near future. THOMAS G. McNIE, M.I.Mar.E. * » 't, &gt;Notes. Gafinas are long, narrow, wooden sailing vessels about 50 feet by 9 feet by 3 feet and propelled by a single sail. Shakturs are flat-bottomed rectangular vessels about 30 feet by 8 feet by 4 feet. They travel in pairs, tied together for stability. Ihe George Canning had to lie out about three-quarters of a mile from shore and all the packages and stores had to be landed by a hawser. Port William was over 1,000 miles from the Persian Gulf. Margil is the port for Basra. Bagdad is 560 miles from the sea. The Hugh Lindsay was an Hon. East India Company vessel. There was another steamer in the Indian Ocean about the same time called the Forbes, built at Calcutta in 1834, but she was not a success. The Zab is 260 miles above Bagdad. Kurna is at the junction of the Tigris and Euphrates. The Saklawiyah and Khirr Canals cross the desert from the Euphrates to the Tigris near Bagdad, their combined length is about 55 miles. The Karun is the main river of Persia and flows into the Shatt-el-Arab at Mohammerah, a little below Basra on the left bank. The first British India Steam Navigation vessels were as follows :— Arabia (built 1863). Euphrates (built 1863). Busheer (built 1864). Cashmere (built 1864). Bagdad (built 1871). They were all Clyde-built. The South Gate of Bagdad. A killick is a large raft buoyed up with the inflated skins of animals, and have been in use on the Tigris for thousands of years. The Bahmanshir Channel is a narrow branch of the Shatt-el-Arab which runs from Mohammerah, behind Abadan Island, to the sea.pi In any further communication on this subject, please quote * No. ^ and address —not to any person by name, but to— “The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London FT Cz7 ., s.yv. i. 7341 THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop&lt;-^ of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, , 193^. Reference to previous correspondence ■ r&gt; 0 / V* Description of Enclosure.COPY (E 6485/3838/92) NO .582 . (3^2/18/34) British Embassy, Bagdad. 6th October, 1934. airr^' 4 * Sir, * jc ^’' ,fith reference to my despatch No.564 of September /24 th last, I have the honour to transmit to you herewith a translation of a note from the Iraqi Ministry of foreign Affairs requesting copies of the /izerial letters issued by the Porte in the years 1846, 1861 and 1862 granting rights of navigation on the rivers Tigris and Euphrates by British steamships. I have replied to the Ministry that their note has been referred to your Department. 2. In this connexion I would draw yOur attention to my despatch No.302 of May 30th. I have a suspicion that this information is required, not only for taxation purposes, but also to challenge the entire right of navigation. 3. I am sending a copy of this despatch to the Department of Overseas Trade. I have, etc., (Sd.) George Ogilvie Porbes The Bight Honourable Sir John Simon, Gr*C*S.I*, K«G*/*0., etc • , etc ., etc.@ II ENCLOSUKH IH BAGiiAD DESPATCH No. 582 of 6/10/34 tr~ 7338. t 4 4 Thef Ministry for Foreign Affairs present their compliments to His Britannic Majesty’s Embassy, Bagdad, and have the honour to state that the Mesopotamia Persia Corporation Limited, Bagdad, say that the Tigris and Euphrates rivers have been opened for British cargo and passenger steamers since 1846, as a result of negotiations which took place between the Ottoman Government and Sir Stratford Canning, then British Ambassador at Constantinople, and that the Euphrates and Tigris Navigation Company Limited, London, enjoy the right of navigation in the above mentioned two rivers by virtue of ministerial letters issued in 1846, 1861 and 186E and now kept at the British Foreign Office. *as these letters are needed for perusal by the 1 Iraci Departments concerned, the Ministry request the kind intervention of the esteemed Embassy for copies thereof to be obtained and transmitted to the Ministry as early as possiole. In awaiting a reply the Ministry avail themselves of this opportunity to express their highest consideration and esteem. Ministry for foreign Affairs, Bagdad, 29th September, 1934.FOhKXON OFFICE, S.llf.l. 734 1 L (h 8486/333 8 / 93 ) 29th November, 1934o ith rsi’crence to Mr. Ogilvi© P’orbes^ despatch No. 58b 3 ( 3f^/18/84) of the 6th October I trerssit to Your KxcQllero.y the ? ccoiop^nying copies of translations of the Turkish Vlserlf 1 letters .issued in the years 1346, 1861 end 1662 to th» Vali of Bfgdad in regord to the right of nrvigstion of the Suphrriee »ru5 Tigris by British vessels. 2&lt;&gt; I em ftdvieed thf-t tiis Irr.qi Government could legitimet&lt; ly clrim thei, in virtue of Article 189 of the Treaty of Lausanne, they er*3 entitled to receive fro® the Turkish Government certified cooi.g,. of tiicsc documents. In these circumstances, and es X consider tnat no ueoiful purpose would be served by postponing oompllance u:l ih l oo Irac i Government’s request of t) 5 29th Depi^iber, I s)Bll be glad, if, unless you see serious objection, you nill furnish -hem with copies of these letters. In doing so, you should expl; in to the Iraqi Government that tj.s firmans of 1334 ana 1841, to vhich reference is made in the letters of ifcOl mo 1P82, co'icernef the right of His Majesty’s Oovcrnmert themselves to maintain two vessels on the Euphrates, and had no beari?ig on the general right of navigation ir the Kuphrates and Tigris, which ms secured to private British vessels by usage and treaty. 3. Copies of trrnslf ii u s of the two firmans of 1354 and 1641 are * U,o ^ncloeef. Should the Iraqi Government at p lete * stage His Excellency h ie utenant~J ol on a 1 etc., ote. ? etc., Bagdad.Vizierial Letter to the Pasha of Bagdad, January 15, 1861 (3 Re jeh f 1277.) (Translation) The British Embassy having recently made certain communications for the purpose of obtaining a renewal of the orders which were sent concerning the British steamers and boats authorised by His Majesty to ply on the rivers Tigris and Euphrates, it has appeared from the register that, permission having on a former occasion been applied for by it to station two steamers on the River Euphrates at Bagdad and to run them by turns, for the purpose of facilitating trade, two firmans, dated respectively the end of Shahan 1250, (1834), and the beginning of Rejeb 1257 (1842), X were addressed to the late Governor-General of Bagdad, Ali Riza Pasha, authorising the permanent station of two steamers on that river, providing it were proved and established that the advantages resulting therefrom would be mutual, and that no sort of inconvenience would ensue therefrom. Further, that in virtue of a report received respecting the dues payable by vessels and boats navigating the Euphrates and Tigris, and in conformity with the request of the British Embassy for vizierial instructions, on the ground that British merchant- vessels might trade in those two rivers after payment of the fixed clues according to treaty, and considering that the transport of goods from one point on those two rivers to another, without going out to sea, is, in fact, internal trade, and that under such circumstances vessels, under whatsoever flag it may be, must pay the same dues as Ottoman vessels or boats * This should be 'in the Government of, u x This should be 1841, see p. 9 of the Chronological Table.n boats, and that British vessels, whether coming loaded from ^ abroad and entering one of those two rivers with their cargoes, or issuing therefrom to the sea laden with Ottoman produce, and bound for foreign countries, after having paid the dues payable on their cargo, according to the treaty and tariff, are only liable to the payment of 'palamar aktchesi’' (l.e. right of mooring), or cable money, on entering or leaving the Tigris or Euphrates, like all other foreign ships coming to other parts of the Ottoman Empire. For these reasons, on the 6th Rebiul- akhir, 1262 (1846), instructions were sent to Bagdad directing, as above, that the same dues should he levied on British merchant-vessels engaged in internal trade as on boats belonging to Ottoman subjects, and that after the custom house duties payable on their cargoes shall have been levied on merchant- ships of the same nation, either coming from abroad or going abroad, a sum of 5 piastres cable money should be levied, and that nothing over and above that should be exacted. You will be so good as to act according to the above rules. (Sealed) MEKEMKD 3 Rejab, 1277 (January 15, 1861).Firman issued to Pasha of Bagdad, August i9(B9i 0 184:1 (1st Decade of Rejeb, 1257) c •4 ' (Tp^slation)« A command to ray Visier, All iy.3a Pasha, actual Gouvernor- General of Bagdad, Busaoxah, and Shehr-i-Zar, whose glory endurel The question of a grant of permission on the part of my august Government for the stationing 0 . 1 . two steam-vessels on the River Euphrates in (the Government oi Bagdad by the Government of England, and their alternate plying for the purpose of facilitating commerce, having been formerly mooted and requested by the embassy of the said Government resident in ray capital; anu my &lt; ilX and pleasure for the granting of such permission having been signified for such stationing of the said two steamers on the said river and their alternate plying, provided that, as was stated, mutual advantages should result, and no inconvenience be caused thereby, austtst rescripts were issued, addressed separately to thee, the said Governor-General, and again separately, addressed to the requisite parties on the right and left banks of the said river; and furthermore, as the commander of the said steamers, the Englishman named Captain LenJ (Lynch), having lately oorae to my capital, has now •| returned to that region (of Bagdad, or the Euphrates), «1 it has been requested, in an official note by the embassy of the said Government, that an august rescript be again issued for the necessary assistance and requisite personal consideration to the aforesaid (commander) in the due performance of his service. It has been / ascertainedascertained by reference to th ' records that aura at « rescripts were so issued fror my Imperial Chancery, and therefore my exalted will arid pleasure was attached thereto, for the execution in accordance therewith* In consequence, my Imperial Majestic Sovereign command in the matter has issued and emanated in honour, according to the henign tenour of which the present august rescript has now again been issued and accorded« Wherefore, when the matter shall become known to thy sagacity, though ahalt take due care and exert judgment for the plying of the said steamers as heretofore, and for the execution of the necessary assistance and requisite personal consideration to the aforesaid commander in the due performance of his service First decade of Hajeb, 125 v .In any further communication on this subject, please quote No. C S and iddress— no/ to any person by name, but to— “The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. I. • &gt; ) 03G THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to ( \^ and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith copvfi^ of the under-mentioned paper. |7) lilt Foreign Office, \V'V 3to o , 193 i, . -ft Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. f V ' L - Subject. EiXt-OS’JRE id V/EwCLY L-7 No. 4 7 2 2 NOV 1934 FROM 8ECRETARV, POLITICAL SECRET DEPT. INDIA OFFICE 1R AND 15 N0V1934 j # J Similar letter se7it to 14—6130 10292 (2) fcjPR. -T.K0*779 (ft 6683/^62/9?;) jm , r a v.io 52th Hovewber, iQZA* ^ith reference to v r© Of tlvle ‘oi'hea 1 deepatch t ; Oo670 (6/65/34) of the 2r\d October» I transmit to Your ftxcellency the accoiapanyinf? cooy of a letter from the Board of Inland ■Revenue eta ting that, in the absence of further Information, the noard are unable to advise ref?;arcHny the liability of the British InrHa 'team TJavlgatlon Oomoany 7,imited to Ir*aqi Income tax in reBrent of the mall subsidy received by them from the Government of India© 2© I shall he glad if you *111 endeavour to obtain and forward to me the information required by the B ^ird In order that the ratter may he further examined© I am, with great truth and re spec t p Your r.xceilency’s obedient Servant, ('or the Secretary of r ’tate) His Kxoellency ftieutenant=Colonel rir ’’rands humphrys, O©C 0 '! c c r01 c ro n 0 v c 0 0 * etCo f eto 0f etc©. Bag da d 0X.».2QaO/l/3.4, ^ [The above number and letter should be quoted in any reply, addressed to— The Secretary, Inland Revenue, Somerset House, London, W.C.2, with the word .T&amp;XS.S.... in the - “ s *hand corner of the envelopt Sir, f * j- 3 XjU k'l y ' R /03I INIiAND REVENUE,! •'3 4 1 S0MERSETL.Jl0USE, LONDON, W.C.2. [icU- L_ „. ■ 4 26th October, 1934. Iraq - Income Tax , 'In '/w'hj J ) n , I am directed by the Board of Inland Revenue to r sfer to the letter (e. 6354/662/93) sent to you by the Foreign Office on 24th October and to transmit to you the enclosed copy of the Board’s reply to the corresponding letter sent to them. 'm*'*'' I am, Sir, The Secretary, India Office, Whitehall, S.W.l.■■■ r COPY &gt; 4 Any further communication should be addressed to :— The Secretary, 1 INLAND REVENUE, /• Somerset House, London, W.C.2, quoting the following reference :— Taxest Inland Revenue, LONDON, W.C.2. T.202C/1/34* 26th October, 1934. Sir Iraq - Income Tax* With reference to your letter of the 24th October, (E.6354/662/93) enclosing correspondence from H.M. Representative in Bagdad regarding the liability of British shipping companies to Iraq income tax, I am directed by the Board of Inland Revenue to state that the information regarding the mail subsidy paid by the Indian government to the British India Steam Navigation Company Limited is not sufficient to enable the Board to give any advice on the matter. It is presumed that the question arising is whether the subsidy is part of u the full sum receivable ••• on account of the earnings of passengers, mails, live stock and goods shipped in Iraq If that is so it is essential to consider on what terms the subsidy is paid and how the amount included in 'the full sum receivable has been computed. If it is desired to pursue the question information on these points should be obtained. of Trade, India Office, Treasury, and Department of Overseas Trade. Copies of this letter are being sent to the Board I am, etc The Under Secretary of State Foreign Office, Downing Street, S.W.l.COPY 1934 J {E 6354/662/95) *1° Kq -_VO,_ (6/e 5/34) 3757 . i n Y 0 -- 11 ' despatch ho» 606 (E 5646/662/93) of Septemher 5th, you instructed me to represent to the Irani Government Tax Law in such a way as to relieve British shipping corapanie from the payment of a b,j tax on their gross freights, £« j have no?/ the honour to inform you that a compromise has been arrived at between the Iraqi Government and the agent of the shipping companies in their dispute as to the inoxcencu of this tax. The Irani income tax authorities have agreed to allow the deduction from the total gross freight, on which assessment for the tax is made, of the proportion of freight pale to on-carriers and of transhipment charges included in through rates of freight. On their side 6 uhe shipping companies have cutpo eb to withdraw thei 1 contention that agent booking commissions and port and other charges should also be deducted from the gross earnings on which they are assesse This compromise solution of the dispute has been accepted by the desirability of interpreting or emending the Iru^i income The Bight Honourable Sir J ohn Simon 9 0.0 *3 etc* , etc. t K.C./.O(s5) Messrs. ?.C. St rick &amp; Company on behalf of the Strick Line, and by the Mesopotamia Persia Corporation on behalf of the companies which they represent s the British India and Ellerman Bncknall Steam Navigation Companies and the Lloyd- Triestino group. The companies profess themselves satisfied with this arrangement and I do not, therefore, propose to take any further action in the matter. 3. I regret, however, to report that another dispute appears to be impending between the Iraqi taxation authorities and the shipping companies in regard to their liability to pay tax on subsidies received for carrying mails to and from the Persian Gulf. Tnis difficulty is stated to have arisen as the result of a ’'clerical error’ 1 on the pert ox the British India Company, and ^ enclose a copy of a letter from the Head Office of the Mesopotamia Persia Corporation at Basra to their Bagdad Manager on the subject. I should be grateful to receive your observations on this new development and to learn whether I am authorised to make representations to the Iraqi Government, in the event of their insisting upon the inclusion of mail subsidies in the assessment of the taxable earnings of shipping companies. I have, etc., (Sd.) George Ogilvie-Porbes.@) ir Norn BaSKEH. BO/IT. ENCTiOSUKE IH BAOBAB BESP^TCH No. 570 of 2/10/34 26th September, 1934 l!y dear Battey I raq XTico me Tax - Ocean Steamship Companies* v/itii reference to jour letter DO/IT of £let instant, yon say advise waidof the Embassy that the Ooean Steamship Go’s for which we act as Agents, i«e» the B#I«, a* &amp; B«, Lloyd Triestino, have accepted without question the assessment to Iraq Income Tax, based on the figure of 5 ;.b on freight collections, after deducting oncarrying freight and transhipraent charges• You may be interested to Know that I am having correspondence it present with the Taxation Authoritisci regarding the assessment B in the case of the B«I *, or the amount paid by the Indian Government to the Company as mail subsidy. The Managing Agents, in submitting Statements of Earnings first of ail, inoxuded in the earnings the ^mounts allocated by them to the Voyage A/cs of fast gulf steamers in respect of the mail subsidy* In a recent letter received from them they now state that, in their opinion, such earning should not be assessable, in view of the fact that the contract for the carriage of mails is made with the Indian Government, and that payment in terms of the agreement is received in India* It does /appear J*L* Battey, Esq., BAGED Ah.appear that there is something to be said for their contention that no part of the mail subsidy accrues in fraq, but I very much doubt if the Taxation Authorities will give way on this point* M&amp;nagin*? Agents state that in rendering the Warnings Statement, the allocation of the mail subsidy was included therein as a result of a clerical error. Had the amount not been shown by them, the question might never have been raised by the Taxation Authorities, but as you will appreciate the figures, once having been disclosed, are no., lively to be lost sight of by the .ssessor. Yours sincerely. {Sd«) L.M# taring.^ INDEX** 1 In any further communication on this subject, please quote and address —not to any person by name, but to— “The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. 1. V 7 507 THE Under-Secretary of State for Fo(rQg,d) Affairs) presents his compliments to and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith copv of the under-mentioned paper.) Foreign Office, 193 1 ^4- Refere7ice to previous correspondence Descriptio?i of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. s-sr ^ LC) | ENCLOSURE IN WEEKLY LETTER NO. 42 18 OCT 1934 FROM SECRETARY, P0UT1CAL AND | 6E0RET DEPT. INDIA QFFK tfCOPY. ^ BRITISH EMBASSY, (C 5462/5462/93) No. 468. (377/1/34) Sir, I have the honour to report that there has been considerable agitation of late in the local Press on the subject of freight rates for Iraqi produce from Basrah to British and Continental ports. The shipping lines concerned (the British India, Strick and the Hansa Lines) propose to s d increase their charges for the carriage of grain to 27/6 per ton as compared with a maximum charge during the last s s s grain season of 25/-, and for dates from 30/- to 35/-. 2. The agitation, which has its origin in Basrah, is led by a well-known grain merchant named Hasham al Khadhery who, in conjunction with other members of the same family, especially Abdul Jabbar al Khadhery, owner of several river steamers, is proposing to establish an Iraqi Steamship Company with the object of exporting Iraq produce at lower rates. At the moment they are contemplating the constitu tion of an Iraqi Shipping Company, the shares in which would be held by Iraqis only. It is proposed to raise 1.1.50,000 by this means, the cost of a share being Fils 750, and to secure from the Government a further sum of I.T.50,000 as a t loan. I understand that so far very little support for the scheme has been forthcoming from the trading community in Basrah. The Right Honourable Sir John Simon, G.C.S.I., K.C.V.O.,3. It has also heen suggested, with a view to challenging the attitude of the regular steamship lines, that Swedish and Japanese Shipping Companies should be invited to call at Basrah to take Iraqi produce. As regards the Swedish ships, it is stated that Swedish ship owners are in negotiation with the Persian Government for the grant of a monopoly for the carriage to Mohammerah of railway material, and that the ships so employed would therefore be available for the Basrah trade. It is also known that a local firm of Shipping Agents is in communica tion with a Japanese Steamship Company with a vie?f to obtaining their Agency. 4. I understand that Messrs. Stricks have been in communication with the Iraqi Legation in London on the subject of the alleged excessive freights which it is proposed to introduce, and that their contention is that, owing to the increased demand for space from Basrah and the falling off in the imports into Iraq of material for the oil concessionary companies, they find themselves in the position of having to send vessels to Basrah in ballast, and that they must recoup themselves for the lack of outward freight by slightly higher charges on Iraqi exports. 5. There seems to be little justification for the indignation shown by grain and date merchants. As regards the latter, it is to be noted that the three principal date packers in Basrah, Messrs. Hills Brothers, The African and Eastern (Near East) Limited, and Messrs. Andrew r eir and Company, the first being American and the second two British concerns, v/ho represent one-third of the whole date-packing industry of the country and who finance three-fourths of it, have /4 (g) have made no complaints; while Abdul Jabbar al Khadhery, who has already been mentioned as one of the instigators of the agitation, has himself increased the rate for river transport by his vessels from p ils 275 to Fils 50®, probably on the same grounds as are urged by Fessrs. Stride for the increase of ocean freight rates. 6* There is little doubt that any attempt to run Iraqi steamships in competition with the regular lines would end in financial disaster for all concerned, quite apart from the fact that it would prove impossible to effect insurance of shipments by such vessels. The intrusion of Japanese shipping offers better prospects for the malcontents, but they overlook the fact that the grain and date trade is a seasonal one in which promptness of delivery is an essential factor, and that the great experience of the regular shipping lines in this respect can'be acquired by new-comers to the trade only at the cost of much time and money. It is probable that the agitation will die down in due course, as do most agitations in this country, without any useful ^ purpose having been attained. 7. I am sending a copy of this despatch to the Department of Overseas Trade. I have, etc (Sgd. ) GEORGE OGILVIE-FORBESA J&amp;S&amp;g, (377/8/54) \ BiF, 1th F©fei*ence to isy despatch Ho* 46d of August 13th on the subject of the local px^s® campaign against alleged excessive freight rate® on exports of Iraqi produce f I have the honour to report that Abdul Jabber al ihsderi 9 the owner of a small fleet of river steamer®, and the only competitor in river traffic of the Euphrates and Tigris Steam navigation Company, is stated to have made arrangement® with the Eastern Steam navigation Company of Bombay for the despatch to Basra of three steamers a month, at intervals of ten days, during the next four months, and that he has induced 53 Basra merchants to sign an agreement binding themselves to export grain and dates by these steamers to Karachi and Bombay at the rate of a rupees (600 file) per ton delivered at docks at either of those ports* 2* The British India Bteaa Navigation Company, which ha® hitherto enjoyed a monopoly of the traffic which Abdul Jabbar lUnederl is now intent on capturing, has responded to this move by cutting its rate® from as. 10 to 12 (Fils 750 to 900) to As. 5 (Fils 375). I am informed by tho Company's local agents that the new rate shows a definite loss to the Company. The wisdom of the Company’s action The Aight Honourable Sir John Simon, G.C.S.I., i .C.v.o*, etc., etc., titc. seemsCD bo to tm open to doubt, einoe it can only be interpreted locally as proof that the rates hitherto in fox*ce were excessive, and will no doubt be adduced si r a argu ment in favour of the formation of an Iraqi Shipping Comp any* Probably the British India Steaa Navigation Company oontesaplate this eventuality with equanimity, relying on the almost inevitable failure of such a company to strengthen their position in the long run* It remains to be seen whether Abdul Jabber al Khederi haa ao far commitfeed himself, vis—h—via the ^astern Steam Navigation Company, as to involve himself and his adherents in financial loss* If so, he will no doubt divert the loan about to be mentioned from its original purpose to reimbursement of such losses* 3 # Abdul Jabber si /Jiederi is reported to have obtained an advance of I*D« 7,500, with a promise of a further sum of the same amount, from the Iraqi Govern ment, under the provisions of the Law for the encourage ment of Industries, for the purpose of enabling him to compete with the .Euphrates and Tigris Bteam Navigation Company in river traffic. ^here n&amp;miB to be little justification for such a loan now that, as reported in paragraph 6 of my despatch No* 50&amp; of ay 30th, through bills of lading from British and Continental ports to Bagdad are being issued by his steamers equally with those of the British Company* he appears, however, to possess considerable personal influence, possioly derived from the clamorous press support he receives or instigates for his schemes; and the insatiable naturenature of hia appetite is shown fcy his recent eialia to import garden pus&amp;pa (exempt from Customs dues as being agricultural machinery) for use on hie river craft, lie has so far failed in this attempt at Basra* but is now pressing the matter in Bagdad# Should he succeed in carrying his point# the Euphrates and Tigris 3team Navigation Company will# I understand* present a claim for refund of duty paid by them in the past in respect of imports of similar machinery. 4. I am sending a copy of this despatch to the Department of Overseas Trade. 1 have the honour to be with the highest respect* Sir* Your most obedient* humble servant, (Signed) 0. OHMLVIE F0R3£S1 In any further communication on this subject, please quote No- t- ss V^Vo 'W'oX and address —not to any person by name, but to— “The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. i. THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign^ Affairs compliments to and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith copVJUa of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, V * 193 Lv* ^ Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. ^ N&gt;Sh * ENCL 03 UR|E NO. 3 7 FROM BE 8 E 0 RE’ Subject. v ^-c&gt;®vv s si. in v/ee;:ly le.iER 13 SEP 1934 _ . ■-'.-n ^ \ 1 A M n OaETARV, -iEP ‘' jJt r DEPT. INDIA OFFICE Similar letter sent to 14—6130 10292 (2) ' -- V_Ow -.(XjT^ ~ P. z. 5757 FOKSION omCK, • 5th Sentenher, 1934. (K SS46/668/93) t ! 9 3 4 31 r V?ith rercrenc® to Sir Francis Hvuim..rys' despatch ho. 860 (6/P1/84) of the 10th May, I transait to you tha accompanying copy of « letter f -o® the Board of Inland Ht'Yonuo In regca-d to the HaMUty of uhliwlng ooatpanies to tvi\ \ i incomo tax® So I request that* unless you see ofejection, you will endeavour to aeeure the &amp;eeeptanc© by the Ireql author 1 tie b of the Interpretation of Article 51a of the Iraqi Income Tax Law, 192?* suggested In the concluding sentences of p&amp;ragraph 4 of the letter from the Board or Inland Revenue* or* failing this, that you will emdeavour to persuade the Iraqi ciovernment to amend the Inooao Tax law on the lines suggested in paragraph 5 of the Board’^ letter* I ssi, with great truth Sir Your obedient Servant* (For the Secretary of state) &lt;h A. £&gt;• Ogllvle- Forbes, Ksq, etCo * etc , Ksq* , C.l* , etc*2291, Wt. 16213/7530. 3000. 8/33. Wy.P.C. 613. indexed Any reply to this letter should be addressed to— “the secretary, Board of Trade, Great George Street, Westminster, S.W.l, and the following reference number quoted:— 5639^“ L..1934„J (cA OF TRADE, I Great George Street, M.11442/34. reet, Tpk , S.W.l. l* 1st Sejt ember, 1934 Westminster, 1 / / Ihe Board of Trade present their compliments to The Secretary of State for India in Council and beg to transmit herewith for information copy of a letter of to-day’s date which they have caused to be addressed to The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London, S-W.l. ENCLOSURE IN WEEKLY LETTER NO. 3 6 6 SEP 1934 FROM SECRETARY, POLITICAL AND SECRET DEPT. INDIA OFFICE Reference to previous correspondence (if any):—1 \ z. Telegrams—“ SHIPMINDER, PARL, LONDON TelephQrt o—WHITEHALL 5140 Ext. 5639 subject should be addressed to:— The Assistant Secretary, Any further communication on this and the following number quoted :■ E.11442/34 Mercantile Marine Department (address as opposite) Merca^'iQ^ Marini| Department, Board of Trade, Great George Street, Westminster, S.W.l. COPY Sir 1st SaDtember, 1934 I am directed by tha Board of Trade to refer to your letter of 16th August, 1934, (£.5169/662/93), transmitting copies of correspondence with His Majesty^ Charge d*Affaires at Bagdad and the Board of Inland Revenue concerning the liability of British shipping companies to Iraqi income tax. In reply I am to state that the Board concur in the .secretary 0 f Stated proposal to instruct His Majesty’s Charge d’Affaires at Bagdad to approach the Iraqi authorities in the sense suggested by the Board of Inland Revenue in their letter to your department of the 10th August, a copy of which was enclosed in your letter under reply. Copies of this letter have been sent to the /Treasury The Under-Secretary of State Foreign Office, London, S.K.l.mmm —mmmrnk. Treasury, India Office, Board of Inland Revenue, and the Department of Overseas Trade. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your obedient Servant, (Signed) W. CARTER. L&amp; Notes. Register No. P. z 5330/34. SECRET. Minute Paper. POLITICAL DEPARTMENT Dated 193 . Rec. Date. Initials. SUBJECT. To Under Secretary SecretaryState... Committee Under Secretary Secretary of State— Jo, f. o/. &amp; 1/K^i Iraq. Effect of new Income Tax Law on British Shipping. Copy of to SEEN POLiTICAL COMMITTEE. 3 SEP Previous papers ;~ FOR INFORMATION. Please see P.^. 1287/34 where it is reported that the British Chamher of Commerce at Basra complained that the new law (Article 29,which adds to the original law a new Article No.5lA, flagged) is not a tax on income hut a tax on turnover. Sir F. Humphrys observed that although the Companies criticised the law, they proposed no alternative £b rmula to place before the Iraqi Government, and said that he would communicate further with the Chamber of Commerce on the subject. 77^,Correspondence is suomitted below, from which it will be seen that the Chamber of Commerce/ 2730 1000 4.342. Commerce propose that certain items should he excluded from the 'gross freights' on which income tax is chargeable. The Board of Inland Revenue, who have been approached by the Foreign Office,suggest that it might be possible to persuade the Iraq.! Government to accept an interpretation of this new law which excludes two of the items mentioned by the British Chamber of Commerce at Basra, namely 'on-carrying' freights and customs charges. Alternatively, should this course prove unfruitful they suggest that the Iraqi Government might be asked to amend the law in order to exclude from its operation the items 'on-carrying' freights and customs charges, on the ground that 5 per cent, of the full sum receivable, including these items, is an excessive estimate of profit. Subject to the concurrence of the Board of Trade (which can, I think, in this instance be presumed) the Foreign Office propose instructing His Majesty's Charge d’affaires at Baghdad to act on these lines. v Secretary, E.&amp; 0. Department, Secretary, Financial Department, For information and any observations. * Ce&lt;: —&gt; ■z/r 5EEN rtOUTICAL COMMIT' 1 B&amp;» 3 sep mi rf/Lc T. Seen, thank you. Prima facie I think that Somerset House might have given a stronger lead; hut the law is so crude that any amelioration would he welcome, and ■oerhans even what they nronose is too much to hone for.In further communidj&amp;ion on this subject, ptease quote voX^itjqlUziqfy and address —not to any person by nMu, but to— “The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. X. CO] THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his pliments to Xj JfatT jfrf J vA transmits herewith cop \/ and, by direction of the Secretary of State, of the under-mentioned paper.1 I •m K 616©/*68/M fo B or^nt, 0*nCK 8^0 lo X6th August # 1934* Sir, ifith rsfsrenoe to Forslgn Oific© letter i?©* K 1031/66S/93 of the 83rd February, X am directed by Secretary olr tTohn Siaon to transmit to you, to be laid before the Board of Trade, the aecoopanylng copies of correspondence with Hie Majesty's Charg4 d 1 Affaires at Bagdad and the Board of Inland Revenue in regard to the liability of ©hioring coiananies to Iraqi ineotae ta*c B 0 The Secretary of State proposes* subject to the concurrence of the Board of Trade, to instruct His Majesty*s ChargA A’Affaires at Bagdad to endeavour to secure the aeoeptanoe by the Iraqi authorities of the interpretation of Article 51A or the Iraqi Income Tax Law, 1927 suggested in the concluding sentences of paragraph 4 of the letter of the 10th August froai the Board of Inland Revenue, or alternatively to persuade them to aacnd the Incose Tax Law on the lines suggested in paragraph 8 of the Board*s letter, 5, Copies of this letter ere being sent to the Treasury, India Office, TJepartaent of Overseas Trade and Board of Inland -evenae, I a&amp;, Sir, Your obedient Servant, The Secretary to the Board of Trade, (SUnod) C. F. A. WARNER.Copy (E 3376/6613/93) NOft 260o ( 6/531/34) Begdado 10th May, 1934&lt;&gt; British Embaasyp Sir With reference to paragraph 9 of my despatch No© 68 of February 1st, I have the honour to transmit to you herewith copy of correspondence with the British Chamber of Commerce ©t Basrah concerning the liability of shipping companies to Iraqi income tax© 2o X shall be grateful to learn at your earliest convenience whether, and if so, upon what grounds, I should now approach the Iraqi Government on the subject of Article 29 of the Iraqi Income Tax Lew of 1933© I have, etc©, (Sgdo) F.H. Rumphrys The Right Honourable Sir John Simon, G.C.S.I., K.C.V.O., etc*Enclosure in Bagdad despatch Ho© 260 of 10&lt;&gt;5 o 34d dD 70 (6/6/54) British Embassy p Bag-3ado 7th Februaryp 1954, Sir* I am directed by Ms Excellency the Ambassador to acknowledge the receipt of your letter of January 26th lestp which he received from His Majesty’s Consul p Basra 5 regarding the recent amendment to the Iraqi Income Tax Law which provides that Iraqi income tax shell be assessed on the full sum. received in Iraq by shipping agents on account of the freight of goods consigned abroado 2c His Excellency requests that he ray be informed what* in the opinion of the Chamber* would be e suitable amendment to Article 51-A of the Income Tax Low to meet the objection described in your lettero The Income tax legislation has from its inception made profits on such business liable to income tax and if the matter is to be taken up with the Iraqi Government it will be necessary to recommend to them an alter native formula to that which now governs the assessmentc The expression in the article under reference is;- ,f (l) The profits chargeable to tax shell be deemed to be an amount equivalent to five per centum of the full sum receivable by the owner or charterer on account of the earnings of passengers* mails* live stock and goods shipped in Iraq* provided that for this purpose shipped in Irfeq shall not include the transhipment of cargo brought to. Iraq” \ and the expression 'Grose freights' in your letter is not mentionedo 3o His Excellency will also be glad to receive confirmation \ that ilie not desired to challenge the rate of 5°J as the basis of assessment of profltc I am p etc** (Sgd„) O.H. BATEMAN.■■■■■■■ I &lt;JT) 7/ Enclosure in Bagdad despatch NOo SoO of 10o5o54 0 BRITISH CHAMBER OF COMMERCE, BA SR A Ho Office of the Secretary,, Post Box NOo la 20th April* 1934o Sir* At a recent meeting of my Chamber* I have been directed to reply to your letter No, 192 of the 12th of February 1934* which has so far remained unanswered owing to the subject matter thereof receiving the attention of my Chamber., With reference to the letter Ro 0 6/6/34 of the ?th of February from His Majesty’s Embassy* Baghdad* my Chamber have instructed me to suggest that Article NOo 51A of the Iraq Income Tax Law may be so amended as to provide for the deduction of the undermentioned items from the ’’gross freights' earned by Shipping Companies operating with ’Iraq and which constitute actual outlays and/or payments which have to be made by them* and can* therefore* not be considered 'Earnings' in any sense of the word:- a. Booking commissions and Agents’ chargeso bo Oncerrying freights on through cargo to ports other than those served directly by the Companieso Co Transhipment chargeso do Port Dues and charges o eo Customs Chargeso In as far as the rate of 6^ as a basis of assessment of the nett profit of the Companies is concerned* my Chamber consider that it would not be desirable to challenge thiSo My Chamber would appreciate your passing on these views* together with your recommendations to His Majesty’s Embassy* Baghdado I have* etc.* (Egd)o ? ? Honorary Cecretaryo His Britannic Majesty’s Consul* Basrahm n V COPY (E 5169/662/93) T,2020/1/34 INLAND REVUTOFi, SOMERSET HOUSE, LONDON, W.C. 2. 10th August, 1934. Sir, XraQ - Income Tax - shipping . The I em directed 'by the Board of Inland Revemie to refer to your letter of the 3lfct May, 1934, (E 3376/662/93) and previoue oorreepondence regarding the charge of Iraq income tax on British shipping companies. Under the Iraq Income Tax Law, 1927, ae amended, a shipping company, not resident in Iraq hut carrying on 'business there, is liable to the tax in respect of the profits derived from that business as being M income which accrues in or is derived from Iraq* (Article 5). Under Article 51A (inserted in the law by Article 29 of the Third Amending Law, No. 60 of 1933) the profits so derived are to be *deemed to be an amount equivalent to five per centum of the full sum receivable by the owner or charterer on account of the earnings of passengers, mails, live stock and goods shipped in Iraq M The profits which may be shown by the accounts of the company are to be ignored. The questions for discussion are whether under the Law certain sums can be excluded from the gross sums receivable by the shipping company in respect of freight etc. as not being part of the 'full sum receivable on account of the earnings of * and whether, if these sums cannot be excluded, the Iraq Government should be moved so/ Under Secretary of State, Foreign Office.80 to amend the lair at to permit these exclusions. Under United Kingdom Income Tax law there is no provision such as Article 51A prescribing an artificial measure of the profits of shipping companies, and the Board have no experience in dealing with chargee made on such a basis. Where the Income Tax liability of a foreign shipping company requires to be ascertained an attempt is made to ascertain the profit actually made in the United Kingdom. Expenses such as those shown in the letter from the British Chamber of Commerce, Basrah, dated 20th April, 1934, would all be deducted in arriving at the company^ profit, and no question would arise as to their inclusion or exclusion from a figure of gross freights. No attempt would be made to charge income tax on any profits of the “on-carrying” companies which might be deemed to be included in the “on-carrying” freights. Little guidance can therefore be obtained from a consideration of United Kingdom Income Tax practice. As regards the interpretation of Article 51A of the Income Tax Law, 1927, the Board find it impossible to attach any clear meaning to the words “of the earnings” which are quite inappropriate in the phrase “the full sum receivable ••• on account of the earnings of passengers ... shipped in Iraq”. It may perhaps be possible to put forward the interpretation of the Article which seems to be suggested by the British Chamber of Commerce, Baerah, viz. that certain amounts included in the gross receipts of the shipping companies could not be regarded as ”earnings” and ought therefore to be excluded from the “full sum receivable ... on account of the earnings”. The Board suggest however, that this interpretation should be applied only to the “on-carrying” freights and the customschargee referred to at and 'e' of the letter. Theee may perhaps be regarded ae amounte which the shipping company will pay over to third parties on account of the shipper, but the other items (’'a”, M c M , and M d M ) seem to be rather expenses payable by the shipping company out of its own share of the freights. Iraq Governratnt perhaps an amendment of the law might be asked for to exclude the ”on-carrying'* freights and customs charges from the 'full sum receivable ...' on the ground that 5 per cent, on the full sum receivable without deduction for these amounts is an excessive estimate of profit. (The Board note that the Chamber of Commerce do not desire to challenge the rate of 5 per cent; such information as the Board have available indicates that for several years past Britith shipping companies engaged in international trade have on the average made considerable losses, and that only a few companies have made any profit as computed for United Kingdom Income Tax purposes.) 1 am, &lt;tc. (Signed) A. HKLBON.I vt-'-r. 9 Hi INDEXED Tn any further communication on this subject, please quote No - nd address — not to any person bu name, but^to— ’ # ‘The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. 1. THE Under-Secretary of State for I ^oreigjiQA ffiaiirs pi esents his compliments to XJLt and, by direction of the Secretary of State, /i/ transmits herewith cop of the under-mentioned paper. 2 Foreign Office, , 193W . V y Reference to previous correspondence : OcE i-v i Description of E?iclosure. Name and Date. Subject. 14—6130 9785 ( 2 ) 6 .f ^.' v xCopy (E 3080/662/93) A’O. 221 . / British ^.mbsesy, 1954, Bagdad. 25th /iprilt 19; ? 4. Sir t I havs the honour to transmit herewith for your Information a copy of a further law amending the Iraq Income Tax Law in the shape of ©n amendment to the third amending law. 2. The effect of the law is to bind the Finance Authorities unconditionally to refer to the Court of Cassation for decision, on the requisition of an assessed person, any point of law arising out of a decision by an Appeal Committee. The paragraph which hie been superseded only ade it incumbent upon the Finance Authorities to make such e reference if the request was made within tan days after the decision had been notified by the Appeal Committee, and was accompanied by I*I). 5 as security for Court Fees. I have, etc., (For His Majesty's Ambassador) (Sgd.) George Ogilvie-Forbes. The Fight Honourable t ir tl ohn Simon, O.C• . 1 •, .C.t. 0*, etc., etc., etc. *KN010SURK IK BAdDAD DESPATCH* No. 221 of 26/4/34. (Published in A1 Waqatyl’ A1 ’Iraqi 12th April, 1934)• L aw No. 19 of 1934 Amending the Third Amendment to the Income Tax Law No. 60 of 1933. We King of ’Iraq, With the approval of the Senate and the Chamber of Deputies, do hereby order the enactment of the following law:- Article i * Clause (2) of Article 44 of the Income Tax Law as amended by Article 24 of the Third Amendment to the Income Tax Law No. 60 of 1933, shell be substituted by the following clause H (2) The Finance Authorities shall be bound to refer such point of lew to the Court of Cassation Ar ticle 2 . This law shall come into force frorr the date of coming into force of the Third Amendment to the Income Tax Law No. 60 of 1933. Article 3 » The Minister of Finance is charged with the execution of this lew. Done at Bagdad this 6th day of Dhul Hijjah, 1362, and the 22nd day of March, 1934. GHAZI. Neji A1 Suwaidi, Jamil A1 Madfai, Minister of Finance Prime Minister•t f' In any further communication on this subject, please quote No - ? \ ■vV^ and -address —not to any person by name, but to— “The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. 1. T\ m ' f - I - — -.Mr I Hlii Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to VX^&lt;W ^ VAJLo. and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop njlo of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, \ . , 193hr p.' 4 Li; Reference to previous correspondence : e 'ScX.t-v Description of Enclosure. L&lt;M /o Name and Date. Subject. W.^ “ENCLOSURE imrrETI—“' ■ I ’&lt; ' No. 9 f MAR. 1934 FH®M SECRETARY, POLITICAL AND SECRET DEPT. INDIA OFFICE ^ c l-a^e 0 . 0 \ 14—6130 9508 ( 2 ) Similar letter sent 1° ^ ^ \ % cr\ TCOPY (E 5690/4392/93) (129/31/33) ■■■■ I BRITISH ElvIB/vSSY, | ^ A BAGDAD. 14th September, 1933. go (ID Dear Department, Your letter E 4392/4392/93 of 17-8-1933 about the new Iraq.! Income Tax Law. We have at last succeeded in obtaining a translation of the new. Law, which was passed by parliament at its last Session, was published in the Arabic edition of the ’Iraqi Government Gazette on August 17th, and came into effect on September 3rd last. It is a long law of 33 articles and introduces extensive amendments to the already widely amended original law. We are still examining the effect of them and a report on the subject will be submitted officially as soon as this is completed. The taxation on air transport companies, referred to in the enclosure to your letter, is described in the attached extract from the new Law, which orders that/ the taxable income of sea vessels or aircraft shall normally be five percent of the total receipts derived from traffic originating in ’Iraq. This formula is new, but, theoretically, it does not involve the imposition of fresh taxation upon air and sea transport companies. Under the original Income Tax Law, ’Iraqi income tax is leviable upon all income which accrues in, is derived from, or is received in, ’Iraq. Imperial Airways, Limited and all transport companies, have always been liable to pay tax upon the income they derive from ’Iraq. Spasmodic 0 attempts to assess such profits have in fact beem made by the/ Eastern Department, Foreign Office, S.W.l.-zy the f Iraqi Government: there has been correspondence with shipping companies arising out of the attempts, hut without any satisfactory result* Subject to the fairness of the percentage, regarding which we are not yet in a position to offer any comment, a definite formula to govern assessment should be more convenient, both to the Government and the Companies concerned than the undefined liability hitherto existing. We were not consulted by the ’Iraqi Government regarding the contents of the amending Law, but, in the light of the factors described in this letter, we do not think that we would be justified in protesting to the ’Iraqi Government against the inclusion of the formula. Yours ever, CHANCERY.CfD di Extract from the Draft Income Tax Third Amendment Law, 1933 (as published in the V/aqayi ’ A1 'Iraqiyah No. 1286 dated 17th August, 1933). Article 1 . This article points out that the law under amendment is the Income Tax Law No. 52 of 1927 as amended by Law No. 51 of 1930 and Law No. 73 of 1931. X X X X X Article 29 . Adds a new article (No. 51-A) as under to the Income Tax Law:- ' Article 51-A . The following provisions shall apply to the assessment and collection of tax in the case of owners and hirers of large sea vessels or aircraft coming into any port in Iraq or engaged in traffic in ’Iraq where the owners or hirers of such vessels or aircraft are persons not resident in ’Iraq. (l) The taxable income shall be deemed to consist of 5% of the total amount receivable by the owner or hirer of a vessel or an aircraft on account of passengers, mails, animals (domestic or agricultural) and goods taken on board in ’Iraq; provided that the term ’’taken on board in ’Iraq” for the purpose of this article shall not include the transfer of cargo brought into ’Iraq from one vessel or aircraft to another vessel or aircraft. (2) In cases where the vessel or aircraft coming into ’Iraq has no agent in ’Iraq, the captain of the vessel/vessel or the pilot of the aircraft, as the case may he, shall he deemed to he the agent of the owner or hirer thereof. (3) In case of delay exceeding three months in the payment of the tax imposed on any person engaged in shipping or air transport work or on a vessel or aircraft hirer, the Finance Authorities (regardless of whether the tax was assessed on the person concerned directly or in the name of another person) may, in addition to the powers vested in them under this law in regard to the levying and collection of tax, address to the Director General of Customs and Excise, or any other person authorised to issue departure permits, a certificate (?warrant) stating the name, or names, of such person or persons and the facts concerning the tax the payment of which is delayed; and upon receipt of such certificate in respect of such person he (? the Director General of Customs and Excise or other person authorised to issue departure permits) shall disallow the departure from any port in ’Iraq of any vessel or aircraft owned (wholly or in part) or hired by such person until the tax shall have been paid. (4) The holding up of a vessel or an aircraft under the provisions of this article shall not exempt its owner or hirer, or both, from the payment of Port Dues and any other charges for the period during which the vessel or aircraft is held up. (5) If the Minister of Finance is of opinion that the arrival (? in ’Iraq) of a certain vessel or aircraft(&amp;&gt;) ‘SH aircraft was (only) incidental, and that such vessel or aircraft is unlikely to repeat the visit and that other vessels or aircraft 'belonging to the same person owning such certain vessel or aircraft are (also) unlikely to come into ’Iraq, he may order that no tax shall he claimed or levied from such vessels or aircraft. An order so given by the Minister of Finance shall exempt such vessels (? vessel) or aircraft from liability to tax under this law in respect of such (? incidental) visit. The Minister of Finance may, however, cancel such exempting order in respect of a second or more visits by a vessel or aircraft belonging to or hired by the same person”. X X X X X XCOPY (E 6276/4392/93) FOREION OFFICE, S.W.l. 1st November, 1933• Sir, In my note No. E 5830/4483/93 of October 23rd I had the honour to enclose a translation of the passage of the new Iraqi Income Tax Amendment Law concerning the taxation of aviation and shipping companies operating in Iraq, and stated that, pending its further examination. His Majesty^ Government in the United Kingdom had made no representations to the Iraqi Government in the matter. I added that, should His Eajesty T s Government decide to make such representations, I would not fail to bear in mind the desire of the Netherlands Government to be associated therewith. 2. I now have the honour to inform you that, after careful examination of the new provision. His Majesty^ Government have reached the conclusion that this provision of the New Iraqi law is not of a nature to justify representations to the Iraqi Government. In these circumstances His Majesty’s Government propose to take no further action in the matter. I have, etc., (For the Secretary of State ) (Sgd) G. W. FENNEL. Jonkheer E. de Marees van Swinderen, G.C.Y.O., etc., etc., etcig% OQT’T (K 10FX/66E/9®) No« 69» 16/8/M) British ’ tabassy. l0t February, X9£4* 3lr. In paragraph 4 of my despatch JO# 59c of September 14th last, X commented upon article £9 of the new Iraqi Income Tax Law, the text of which was transmitted to the Fasterm Department in a ae^i-official letter of the same oJp*' date &lt; *tu It9/Zl/%Z)* £ m Thi» Article, as you are aware, aaoea^es the chargeable inoois«f of shipping and aircraft companiea on the baaie of 5 ' of the gross freight in respect of goods shipped in Iraq# at the present rate of taxation this means that the actofil amount payable to the Iraqi Government by aircraft and shipping companies is 9 of &amp;? of their gross outward freights from Iraq# In both of the above mentioned oommuni cat ions the opinion was expressed that the question whether or not this provision of the new law is objectionable will depend upon the answer to the question whether 5 of the gross freights is a fair and reasonable basis for computing the chargeable income derived in Iraq by the companies concerned* 2m The Dutch Minister in London was Informed in your letter of November 1st last that His K*jt*ty f » Government hod reached the conclusion that the provisions of the new law in this respect were not of a nature to Justify representations to the Iraqi Government# The Netherlands Government are, of course, oemoernetf with the new tax only in so far as it affects the Dutch (F#L#H* ) air line, and I &amp;m aware from a conversation which I held In Bagdad in December /wi th The Fight Honourable Sir John Simon, 0#C#J#X** E#C#Y# &gt;•* etc*, etc., etc*&lt;fD v with th€* Dutch Minister in { ?«hran that hi© OerrtriMint ex^ertaln hope that the decision of HI® Majesty*© Owrnaint In thl© matter 1® not final. For the moment, however, I understand that ©o far nt» the aircraft oorspanle® are concerned (l»i&gt;eriai Mrways and ) the eueotlon 1© not urgent, since they have surmounted the difficulty ‘by the simple expedient of oddinff to their pcuMMtxtgtr fare© and freight rates more than Is* necessary to recoup any loss they may sustain by reason of the incidence of the new tax. 4, Ths position of ©hipping companies, however, is different, and I have for 8 one time been expectin to hear complaints from them regarding the new tax. This has now come la the form of the attached letter addressed to me by the British Chamber of Ocsnsirce In Basra. ^fee Brltich sompanlss affected arc the British India Line Copenting with the Mesopotamia and Twrsia Corporation) and Messrs. si trick and Company, but the German Minister has informed my First secretary that the German Han©a line are ready to associate themselves with the British companies. 5. Ton will observe that the upohot of the east mode cat by the Chamber of Coatmsrae is that, in the special elrcumstansss of their trade from this country, the tax us now compute 1 .! and levied is a tax not on income but on turnover, and that computation on the basis of -prosa freight 1© 1 neon 5 table because it res ilte la u t-ix oc pro!its ; uic iosseSj alike. ©. ?hey also point e t that owing to the transhipment® which are necesssry to .ret goods fIraq to oth*r parte- of the world, the gross freights charged by the shipping companies operating from Basra include many charges that have to be paid over to other companies. Yet the chargeable income for /purposes thsp:iy ^oscb taxation oamirnttA on th« 'bae.18 of %K« fuXX mornt oHargid In Iraq lrroop«otlT« of the faot that much of It ia e apt nil tare and not ixMHMMi* for example* when the Mesopotamia Persia Corporation chip a cargo Of dates from Basra to Hew York on which the ?pcom freight is {oay) thirty »hillin;-8 # probably some twenty to twenty-five sjhllXin *© of this amount in paid away in freights to other companlta and transhipment at Bsabay* Harahurr (or London) ,and perhaps other @ntrepote* :&lt; Tet the Corporation are called upon to pay tsac on the basis that 5 of thirty shillings represents their profit* 7* For the moment X agrat that the actual amount of t&amp;r&amp;t!on which the shipping companies are called upon to pay cannot be regarded m excessive,, la&amp;smnah tus it only amounts to is. penny in the pound* But in these days every penny counts, and no-one can foretell If &lt;tad when the Iraqi Government may feel constraint to raise the rate of taxation* It might, of course,. b« argue a that there is nothing to prevent the shipping sompanies from follow!np the example set by the /aircraft companies and. that they oaa oaapensate themselv^s for their losses by adding a certain amount to their freights* There are,, however, disadvantages in this# Complaints against the high freight# in the ersian Gulf are tilready loud, and in any ease it would be inadvisable to take steps at the present time which would h.'ive the effect of increasing the cost of Iraqi goods to foreign consumers* Howrer, it may well be that In the near future freight ratos in the Gulf may have to be reduced owing to the first appearance of a subeldised Italian line which will shortly begin operations In the TeraIon Gulf* 8. These figures are, of course, hypothetical and are given only m an ilxuctrat ion*8. You will ob&amp;*rv* %h&amp;t auth &gt;a^h th# oonnpiml«« OTltiol^ tht ba»i© of a«M»oia»n« introauooS im the new fimenainr law, th* ? do not ouggeat nnj other sjethod of oo^nputatl on which would appeal to them ae being more reasonable* Unite®, however, eom- alternative formula Is put forward h? the ®oap«mle® concerned, I fear that the Iraqi Government will not willingly oha.n#;e the present extern, 9, ^ 1 m therefore com?mn!aating further with the ChmMr of Commerce on this mibject, and will forward their observations in due course• I have, etc*. (Sgd• ) F# IU Hump hr ye* mtmmWCLO$?;r^ Ii4 BA01V4D DfSPAtCa# C 0 ? T ) go. 66 Of Bim^E ai'-M:)’ :t oj 1 Ovwic?., UlS'lAE# omoo of tht secretary I oat .Box ko. I. ECth January # IU34 Tour ?:xoolXeaoy # Iraq Xnoone f ?ax re latinos to ShlprdUK Comr-anieo# I tons Veen directeti Vy thf member® of ay Chamber to place before Tour excellency the foll0wlzif 9 regard Inf the aeeteeaent of Income fax relating to Shipping Co»pa dcs # Income fax Law of 19£$ publlebed In the Iraq, dovermient Oasette Ho. 1286 dated l?th Amgaet 19S2. In tblo 1 ?aw Tour tCxcelleney will note that income fax is aeeeeeei on of the gross outward freights. At the outset I would mention that my Chamber considers this new X»w is not what may be termed on Income Tax, but is a direct tax on the turnover of shipping Companies Irrespective of whether the Companies chew a profit or a lose on their business relating to Iraq. Whilst we shipping Companies &amp;gr«*u untcr protest, to this form of as^eesnent, my Chamber would point out that freights earned by the Company trading from Iran. Shipping Companies from here, in order to facilitate trad# and help export* of the country, issue through Bills of Lading to various ports at which they do not call but to will oh the m amended in the provisions of Article 20 of the Third the term *CB08D fimiZJtS* should be applicable to the gross His Excellency Sir Brand* Humphry*, 5»C#U«$., O.D.V.o/f ocd * Hie 'irltan io Majesty’s ambassador, Baghdad.As an foaAe art on-«»rri«S 1&gt;y other stesasahip Oompanlta. txaraple, to aaslat in the export of dates to as many ports as possible, through Si Us of Lading «•« 3aarah T '° erery port in the world. m&amp; the oargo Is transalpped at TarioM places «.n routs such as jombss. i'ort :air. London, HaaSare and the Continsnt. and the goods are forwards* by etoa-aere sailing at these ports but not touching irno. in oarrylng out thee# tranehlj*«ntB the Stsawshlp Companies from Basro not bensflt in aaf way, ths oncarrylng frslght Xielnf liatwdlately paid orer to the on-oarryln- Company, Is, therefore, oontended that there Is no ground for holding that the total sums rsoelred la irag ore id ant leal wit&gt;s the 'S'XOiv X whioh are to serve under Article oik as a basis of Income *?a* Assessment In Iraq, ja the meantime, ’’t»&gt;iBvehip Agents have reoslved from the Dirsotor Osneral of ;evenM issessmsnt Hotioes dated the 11th January, ashesBlog Chlppin-’ Qwnpanlee on the basin of gross freights inaiadin* on-oarrying freights, stating that notice of appeal suet be lodged within days of above date. liy Ohafiber, therefore, solicits Yo’ir ®SSalUnay*S kind asaietanae to take this matter up on their behalf a# my Chamber considers, for reasons mentioned above, that it is a tax,on alleged Income, part of whioh is not received by the Shipping Companies oarrying the goods from Basrah. I have, etc., (sga) t i i y Honorary secretary, Bh® British Chamber of corameroe. ■esrah^jINDEXED In any further communication on this subject, please quote , ,, No ‘ ^ I H- 3x i R. g ana address —not to any person by name, but £o— The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign 0®ce, London; S.W. 1. 0^ M THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his mpliments to ^ and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop^e* of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, 0.1^. 0^. , 193 J . Reference to previous correspondence :COPY (E 5686/439?/93) British Embassy Bagdad. s *— 14th September, 1933. Sir I have the honour to report that the ’Iraqi Government have passed a Third .Amendment Law to the Income Tax Law, which introduces a number of important changes into the machinery for the collection of ’Iraqi income tax. 2. The new law has been published in the Arabic edition of the Government Gazette, and its provisions are made retroactive to the beginning of the present financial year. It has not yet been published in English, but an English edition is under preparation. Owing to the very large number of alterations made to the original law since it was passed in 192T, the Ministry of Finance have decided, I am informed, to publish a complete and revised edition of the law as amended, copies of which will be sent to you as soon as they are obtainable. 3. The new amending law comprises thirty three lengthy articles and, in order to save time and to avoid the constant necessity for cross- reference, I have had the attached note prepared summarising it article by article, from which the principal changes made can easily be seen. No The Right Honourable Sir John Simon, G.C.S.I., etc., etc., etc. K.C.V.O. ,, S'* Qq- No variation is made in the rate of tax. There are two important new principles introduced, one of which is the adoption of a method of fixed assessment for members of the professional and trading classes according to their income, which is to be assessed by committees appointed in the large towns for this purpose. This method is probably better suited to ’Iraq than the normal method of obtaining a detailed statement of income, and pursuing the usual formalities of assessment, for these classes. The change has been in contemplation for some time, and the Minister of Finance has been empowered by law since 1^ 6 to call upon tradesmen, merchants and profess.onal men to register themselves for taxation purposes. 4. The chargeable income of shipping and aircraft companies entering the sea and air ports of ’Iraq, will be computed on the basis of 6$ of the amounts receivable from traffic originating in ’Iraq. Such companies have been liable to pay tax on their profits since the original law was passed, but the ’Iraqi Government have met with considerable difficulty in their attempts to assess the profits, and the agents of shipping companies have been called upon to provide voluminous details of the trading oi their principals. The expedient now introduced attempts to define this liability and, provided that the rate of 5$. is not excessive (which, prima facie,'be a matter of convenience both to the companies concerned and to the Government. The Finance authorities are given powers to detain in ’Iraq, ships, aircraft, and persons who delay in satisfying the demands for payment of income tax made upon them, and it is to be hoped that these provisions will not be enforced by the Finance authorities in a narrow minded spirit. 5. The privilege of exemption from tax for the first ID. 160, and the payment of two-thirds tax for the second ID. 160, is now withdrawn from residents abroad and the profits of companies. 6. I am sending a copy of this despatch to the Department of Overseas Trade. I have, etc., (Sd. ) F.H.HUMPHRY'S.^ : -OPY (EncloBtiire in Bagdad Despatch No. 693 of 14.9.1933.) Third Income Tax Amendment Law . ^ (As published in the Arabic edition of the 'Iraqi Government Gazette on 17.8.1933). Articl e 1. Drafting only. Articl e 2. Repeals the definition of appellate authority Article 3. Article 4. Article 6. Article 6. Provides for special treatment to be given to dividends paid to non-residents under a new article ordering deduction of tax at source. Drafting amendments. The exemption from tax granted to military and civil personnel of His Majesty's Government is now limited to ’’subjects of the British Government'. This will bring within the operation of the law Assyrians. Probably not of importance as there are few employees of the Royal Air Force, not British, who are in receipt of ID. 160 per annum, which is the taxable limit. Drafting mainly. Tax at full rate, without rebate, is now chargeable on residents abroad and companies. Provides for deduction of tax at source on all dividends and interest payable to persons abroad. Article 7. Orders the collection of tax upon pensions paid to pensioned employees to be made by the employer in the same way as deductions are made from salaries. (See Article 13). Article 8Article 14 Drafting amendments* Article 8« Article 9, Article 10&lt; Article 11* Article 12. Article 15* Redrafts the instructions covering the liability of agents to supply information regarding the income of their principals* Empowers the Finance authorities to call upon hotel keepers and householders to give the names of residents in their houses* Empowers the Finance authorities to demand from Bankers particulars of dividends or interest from Bonds or shares paid By them and the names of the payees. Empowers the Finance authorities to call upon all tradesmen and professional men in any specified district to register their names and ■business addresses at the Income Tax Office in that district. This power already rests tn the Minister of Finance under a law of 1926, which is repealed By a later article in this law. Bedrafts the instructions regarding the suBmission of returns of income, more clearly defining the responsibility of the 'chargeable person' and the Finance authorities. The ultimate liability remains upon the chargeable person, wh* is legally responsible for declaring his liability to income tax. Makes employers responsible for reporting any pensions paid to pensioned employees. (See Article 7).Article 2Q. Article 16. Article 16. Articl e 17. Article 18 . Article 19. Introduces a new device into the machinery of income tax assessment. The Finance authorities are authorised to set up Assessment Committees throughout the country to undertake assessments in cases in which the normal method of assessment is not followed. These committees are to consist of an official President, one official member and two non-official members, all to be nominated by the Minister of Finance. Provides that these Committees shall classify tradesmen, merchants and professional men into categories constituted according to their estimated annual income and lays down rules to govern the powers of the Committees. A fixed rate of tax is laid down for each category: the rates correspond approximately to the normal income tax payable upon the assessed income. Machinery is provided in Article 11 for the compulsory registration of tradesmen, etc. The procedure provides a simple method of taxing the ’’non-employee professional and trading class 1 ’ without the formality of intricate assessment. The classification is subject to appeal. Drafting amendments. Gives powers to Assessment Committees to revise classifications with three years retro active effect. Amends the regulations regarding notice of assessment in order to cover the notice of classification introduced by Articles 15 and 16,&lt;@&gt; &lt;f-) Article 20&gt; Amends the regulations regarding objections to assessment for the same reason. Article 21 . Amends the machinery, for lodging and hearing appeals for the same reason. An additional clause is inserted providing that an appeal against assessment shall he accompanied by a deposit of half the amount of the assessed tax provided that it shall not exceed £60. Brings into one article the regulations for the establishment and procedure of General Appeal Cornmiittee. No alterations of substance are made. Article 23 . Hepeals the articles absorbed by the preceding omnibus article.. Article 82* Article 24. Article 26. Article 26. Article 27* Amplifies the regulations governing the reference to the Court of Cassation of a point of la*, including payment of a deposit of ID.5 by the appellant. No change in procedure is involved. Redrafts the provisions for the payment of court fees arising out of a reference to the Court of Cassation on a point of la*. Drafting amendment only. ■» Drafting amendment only. Articl e 28 . Reduces the surtax penalty for delay in payment from 10$ to 5$ and reduces the second period of grace from 46 days to 81 daye. Provides thatArticle 34 , &lt;&amp;c&gt; that if the demand note allows for payment in instalments and any instalment is not paid within 14 days from the date on which it is due the instalment arrangement shall he cancelled and the whole balance remaining due shall he payable immediately. and aircraft companies coming into Iraq ports shall be deemed to consist of 8$ of the total income receivable on account of traffic originating in ’Iraq. The Finance authorities are given power to iold up air craft or vessels of any company which does not pay the assessed tax within three months of being assessed. upon the Police to detain any person in Iraq whom they suspect is about to leave f Iraq without paying all the tax for which he is assessed. the changes made in the law by the earlier articles. merchants, professional men and tradesmen which has been practically a dead letter since it became law in 1926, and the provisions of which are now covered by the contents of Article 11 of this law. 16 days after the date of its publication in the Official Gazette, i.e. is effective from 1st September, 1933, and that the new regulations shall have effect from 1st April, 1933. Article 29. Provides that the taxable income of steamship Article 30. Gives the Finance authorities power to call Article 31 . Redrafts the penalty clauses conformably to Article 32 . Repeals the existing law for the registration of Article 33 . Provides that the law shall come into forcePUT P , * ^ \ f % « W &lt; * i ♦ SECRET COPY EXTRACT FROM I1TTELLIQEIICE REPORT IK).l dated the 7th of January, 1931 . CQUHCIL OF MIKISTERS x 1, At a meeting held on December 22nd, the Council passed a resolution adopting a draft law amending the Income Tax Law which had the effect of increasing by one-half the tax for the year of assessment ending 31st March, 1931, and of raising the rate to 9^ for the year of assessment 1931-32. The High Commissioner requested Fis Majesty to withhold approval of this resolution in so far as it referred to the assessment of 1931-32, as he considered that the rate of 9^ was too high and unjustified by any figures that had been produced. The clpaft law was, however, submitted to Parliament and passed although Kis Majesty stated that he had not approved the resolution. In the circumstances the High Commissioner urged His Majesty to return the draft law to Parliament for reconsideration. His Majesty replied, however, that such a course would involve resignation of the Cabinet; in the circumstances while recognising the fcr ce of the High Commissioner^ advice he had decided to sign the law on the understanding that if His Majesty’s Government subsequently desired that it should be amended he would take the necessary steps to ensure that the required amendments were introduced. 2. At the same meeting, the Council approved a draft law for the reduction of pensions and pension gratuities on a sliding scale of 5^ to 8$, the reduction to operate until the end of March, 1931, only. x x X.03 5. At the same meeting, the Council approved a reduction in salaries and allowances payable to officials and employees of the State and municipalities other than those engaged on contracts. The reductions vary from 5$ on salaries and allowances not exceeding Rs*lOO/- a month to 8$ on amounts exceeding Rs.200/- a month. This reduction is to operate until the end of March, 1931, only. XX x 18. Meeting of 29th December. X XX The Salaries Tax Law. There was then a heated debate on the Salaries Tax Law which was lately passed by both Houses, but did not meet with the approval of His Majesty King Faisal. In explaining the reasons for the return of the Law to Parliament , the Prime Minister said, in his communication to the President, that the Law had not been passed by His Majesty, because it was thought that it contained certain provisions which, in principle, were considered to be contrary to the provisions of article 11 of the Anglo-Iraq Treaty. Salman Effendi Al Barrak said that the return to Parliament of the Law meant beyond doubt that it was the clear wish of His Majesty that Parliament should 'shelve' the Law for certain unavoidable reasons. He aslced the House to consider the Law as a thing of the past, supporting him, the Minister of Finance said that even the Government had considered it necessary to 'shelve' the Law, particularly in view of the fact that two substitute bills had been drafted and presented to Parliament for no purpose other than that of devising some means whereby appreciable cuts on the expenditure side of the budget could be effected at/104 at a time when trade was so seriously depressed. Yasih Pasha Al Hashimi then bitterly criticised the Government for having given effect to the Law before it had been definitely approved by His Majesty King Faisal. Yasin Pasha also complained of the manner in which certain bills were treated by the Government as dead letters, while other bills were enacted with undue haste. The Minister of Finance replied that whenever a mistake was committed it was always better to rectify it before proceeding any further. Thabit Beg f Abdulnur also defended tbe Government, and refuted the allegations made by Yasin Pasha. The law was then T, shelved' f and considered as repealed by Parliament at the proposal of Salman Barrak Effendi. Draft Law Amending the Income Tax Law. At this point, the Minister of Finance asked the House to treat the draft Law Amending the Income Tax Law as an urgent matter. The bill was passed after a short discussion. The House also discussed as an urgent matter and finally passed a draft Law for the Reduction, of Pensions and Service Gratuities at rates varying from 5 to 8$, which is to remain in force from 1st Kovember, 1930, to 31st March, 1931. Ibrahim Effendi al Wa T idh, in supporting the measure, said that the Government, in submitting the present bills, had been prompted by a desire to alleviate the burden caused by the present trade depression. He proposed at the same time that both Senators and Deputies should not lag behind in demonstrating their sympathy with the taxpayers and those suffering from the effects of the present, unprecedented crisis, and should forego a reasonable percentage of their allowance for the benefit of the public. He urged his colleagues to accept a reduction in their allowances to the extent of 6 per ceit. r 4 Supporting/Supporting his proposal, the Minister of Finance said that although the hill did not specifically include Senators and Deputies, the matter having been left entirely to their patriotism, he would appreciate any gesture in this direction. He added that although monarchs are usually exempted from any such measures, yet His Majesty King Faisal had been graciously pleased to contribute towards the public funds ten per cent of the amount of the Civil List. Doctor Faiq Shakir seconded the proposal of Ibrahim Effendi al Wa’idh, which was carried by an overwhelming majority. X X X Parliament. The senate. 38. Meeting of 29th December, 1930 . xx x The Vice President announced the receipt from the Lower House of a communication reporting that the latter has at the request of the government adopted a resolution shelving the Salaries and Allowances Tax Law; whereupon the Minister of Finance explained the reasons for this action, as expounded by him in the Chamber of Deputies. After Asif Al ^asim Agha had expressed surprise at the Government's failure to discover at some earlier stage that certain clauses of the bill were inconsistent with certain treaty obligations, the government proposal to shelve the bill was adopted. The House then passed as an urgent measure without discussion the draft Law Amending the Income Tax Law, which, it was explained by the Minister of Finance/{Ob ■■■■■■■■■■ Finance, represented one of two substitutes for the draft Salaries and Allowances Tax law above mentioned. The second of the two substitutes for the shelved draft Salaries and Allowances Tax Law, namely the draft Law for Reduction of Pensions and service Gratuities, was then passed as an urgent measure with little discussion. x X Xlitio7 Tgm.No.552, d/-16.11.30. INTERNAL 342 As has been stated in a previous paragraph the new Anglo-^raq Treaty was passed through both Houses of Parliament on November 16th, by large majorities, It is worth recording in view of the Press campaign that is being waged against the treaty in England on behalf of the non-Tfoslem minorities that all the parliamentary representatives of those minorities voted for ratification. Of the Kurdish representatives only one voted with the opposition. The debate on the treaty was taken without previous warning and was attended by no manifestations of excitement in Baghdad. The opposition newspapers continue to repeat monotonously their arguments against the treaty and maintain that the present Chamber of Deputies is not representative of the people of ’Iraq, One nev/spaper has been suppressed for vilifying Rustam Beg Haidar, the new Minister of Finance, but continues to appear under another name(R5563) Wt 17789/2334 10,000(2) 12/29 II JC S? Cp 112 i* Am Communications on this subject should bo addressed to— The Under Secretary of State, Colonial Office, London, S.W.l, and the following number quoted :— 6/ Subject: ft'U v fa ^ ^ iql Reference to 'previous correspondence M.^1 0-r Letter the Colonial Office of the \o / Transmitted by direction of the Secretary of State for the Colonies. A copy has also been sent to the E.NC OSUili 7 IN K z4 y; tKIV ItMLb 22 JAN. 1931 A Y POLITIC**- A*0 t | pi C£PT : J bDIA OFFICE GotoiiTaT^Office, Downing Street, 35 19 ^.(TIT) 78154 /31. P. z. (326 1931 PARAPHRASE telegram from the Secretary of State for the Colonf eg to the High Commissioner of Iraq* (Sent 7 p.in 0 12th January 1931), No.13. His Majesty’s Government approve the action which you have taken regarding Income Tax as reported in the last paragraph of your telegram No*622 of 31st of Deo ember. It is presumed that the Iraq Government have deoiled to abandon the Salaries Tax Law.PARAPHRASE telegram to the Secretary of (Dated 13th January State for the Colonies. 1931. Received, Colonial Office, 3*47 p 0 m,» 13th January 1931). Ho*25. Reference your telegram No.13 of 12th January. The position is now that the salaries law has been abandoned and that the Income Tax Law has received Royal Assent and was promulgated without amendment on 8th January. King Paisal explained that if he had accepted my advice the Cabinet would have resigned. He promised however that if Kis Majesty f 8 Government took exception to the Law after a full examination of the figures and financial situation he would arrange for it to be amended as desired. X am sending a full report by Air Mail this week.T please quote any further comr No. and address—«&lt;?/ to any person by ndme, but to— “The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. I. compliments to tin iu^dth- JiLtSjJbo^ an ^ &gt; direction of th^ Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop |£1 of the under-mentioned paper. Foreigri Office, 1931 .Extract from Iraq Intelligence Report No.25 dated the 10th of December, 1930. x x x x x The Draft Salaries and Allowances Tax Law passed the third reading by 15 votes to 1, after a debate of some length,much on the lines of the debate on this bill in the Lower Chamber. The Opposition speakers were Maiilud Pasha Mukhlis, Haji Hasan al Shabout Asif al Qasim Agha and Fakhri al Jamil, who approved of the measure as a whole, as a necessary evil, but objected to the exemption of British officials. x x x x x The Draft Salaries and Allowances Tax Law then came before the House, and at the request of the Minister of Finance it was discussed as urgent matter and passed through the final stages. The debate on this draft law was long and stormy and centred mainly on the exemption of the salaries of British officials - as unconstitutional and against Article 11 of the Organic Law - and the remedying of the financial and economic crisis, with the desirability of a higher rate of tax on salaries of above Rs.1,000 per mensem and the exemption of salaries under Rs.100 per mensem as a quite subsidiary issue. In the course of the debate anti-British attacks were made not only against the comparatively high rates of pay of British officials, but also against their alleged callous lack of sympathy with 'Iraq in its present crisis. The anti-British speeches were not directed against British officials only, but also against British companies operating in 'Iraq, whose alleged lack of sympathy was the sole subject of a 3 minutes debate on the Law for Fuel Oil Advances to cultivators, which came under discussion later. Towards the end of the debate, when abuse of the British reached/ttS (ft?) reached its most violent point, Rustam Beg Haidar rose and expressed regret that u hot-headedness n should reach such undesirable limits and should end in such ridiculous and uncalled- for attacks on the British, who were only in ‘Iraq for a short time and should be treated generously. It was most derogatory to the reputation of the country that so shortly after the conclusion of the new Treaty of Alliance and friendship such unworthy utterances should be made. He wished the friendship implied by the treaty to find expression not only on paper but also in good cooperation between the ‘Iraqis and British. The bearing of the draft on the economic crisis was dwelt on at length by Yasin Pasha al Hashimi who read from notes. Begal points in the debate. The Opposition maintained that: The law under discussion was (a) against Article 11 of the Organic Law, because in exempting British officials, it exempted a class of tax-payers; and (b) against Article 92 of ihe Organic Law because it affected the allowances of Deputies and Senators. In regard to the latter point a slight verbal amendment was adopted so as to avoid contravention of the Organic Law. In regard to (a) Government speakers thought otherwise and pointed to the exemptions in the Income Tax Law as precedent. Nobody questioned the constitutional legality of the exemption of the salaries of the High Commissioner's staff from the operation of this law. Some maintained that employees of commercial concerns should be included in the law. Amendments adopted. The law finally passed through the final stage almost unanimously with the following amendments: £a) In the exemption clause regarding British officials, the wording was amended to read “Anglo-British Officials' instead of 'British Officials'. This it was explained, was intended to make/tUo make the exemption cover only the English and not other British subjects. (b) Another amendment carried brought Port, Railways, Awqaf, Amanat al ’Asimah, Water Board and Municipal Officials within the reach of the law. (c) A third amendment exempted the following: The first 15 rupees of pension allowances not exceeding Rs.30 per mensem. The first 15 rupees of the pay of soldiers, policemen, and prison guards. Ration and Fodder allowances payable to members of the police and the army. The salaries of servants of places of worship under the Department of Awqaf and Charitable Allowances received by the poor from Municipalities. x x x x x 366. In regard to the Salaries and Allowances Tax Law (paragraph 363), the amendments introduced by the Minister of Finance in the Chamber including the Port of Basrah and the Railways within the scope of the Law involved its application to about 600 indian officials serving on contracts. This amendment was never referred to the Council of Ministers and consequently the High Commissioner had no opportunity of expressing his views upon it. Moreover the Minister of Finance had previously assured the High Commissioner that the Port and Railways would not be affected. In the circumstances the High Commissioner, who had from the beginning advised the ’Iraq Government that the application of the law to any officials serving on definite contracts was inequitable, had no option but to request the Regent to withhold the Royal Assent to the law. King '^li however acting under pressure from the Cabinet disregarded the High Comiuissioner ’ s request and gave the Royal Assent. His Majesty apologised for this on the following day and tried to make out that his endorsement was due to a misunderstanding. The High Commissioner protested to King Faisal on the latter's return from Cyprus and it was arranged that the law should not be published pending receipt of the views of His Majestyte Government. x x X Xr B 12 Communications on this subje should be addressed to— The Unhek Secretaky of State, | Colonial Office, * London, S.W.l, and the foliawing number quoted :— /- I) 0 rr V 'i‘ Trt ‘ b- Reference to previous correspondence: it*- from Letter the Colonial Office of the fu tjh Transmitted by direction of the Secretary of State for the Colonies. A copy has also been sent to the(5^ K^i 78154/30. I&gt; L . i Q-i ! 1 19 31 ~N \ 8 January 1 Sir, I ara directed by Lord ^assfield to refer to tne telegram from tne nigh Commissioner for Iraq To, 624 a copy of wiiich was transmitted to tne f?eSary' C |itn the letter from inis Department of tne 1st of January, numbered as above, reporting the passage through the Iraq Parliament of a hill to increase the income tax in iraan Mr. 2. -abject to the concurrence of The Lords Secretary, Henderson Co ruesioners of the Treasury, Lord nassfield irojoees to inform Sir ¥. humphrys that = is ajesty’s Governrtient approve tne action taat he has ta en, as reported in tne last paragraph of nia tele^ra i under reference, and to add that it is presumed taat tue iraq Jovernment nave decided to abandon tne Salaries and allowances Tax Law which formed the subject of correspondence with tae ireasury ending with Colonial ff , , f .of-January. ;:o. 76471/30. uffice letter of tue 2iJn&lt;i of ..ftce iter, 'o.78471/30. THE UNDER SECRETARY OF STATE, FOREIGN OFFICE. THE CEC I'i , 'Y, TRSaS jHY.78025/SO. DOWHIHG STHEST, 3rd January 1931. COBFII) CKTIAI . Sir, I am directed by -^ord Passfield to refer to the letter from this Department of the 13th of September numbered as above, with which were enclosed copies of the printed Record of Proceedings of Meetings of the British and Iraqi Delegations concerning the new Anglo-Iraq Treaty, and to transmit to you herewith three copies of an addendum sheet to be inserted at the end of the copies of the printed Record enclosed with the letter from the Colonial Office under reference. I am &amp;c• f Sd. ) J.S. .Plood. The Under Secretary of State, India Office.(2378 C) 50 12'30 (fatT) i'j.i At a subsequent private meeting between the Prime Minister and Sir Francis Humphrys, the latter put forward an alternative draft Note as follows :— “ In view of the close friendship and alliance between our two countries the ‘Iraq Government will normally engage British subjects when in need of the services of foreign officials. Such officials will be selected after consultation between our two Governments. It is understood that this shall not prejudice the freedom of the ‘Iraq Government to engage non-British foreign officials for posts for which suitable British subjects are not available. “ Nothing in the Treaty shall affect the validity of the contracts concluded and in existence between the ‘Iraq Government and British officials.” This was accepted by the Prime Minister after a prolonged discussion and it was agreed that the Treaty with Annexure and Notes should be prepared in English and Arabic for signature on the 30th June. Major Young undertook to check the Arabic translation, and the English and Arabic versions were signed by Nuri Pasha and Sir Francis Humphrys as arranged, in the presence of King Ali, who was acting as Regent, and all the members of the two delegations on the 30th June.1-2.3 fT^) PaRAPHPw^SE TELEGRAM from the T Iigh Coirmi aeioner for Iraq to the Secretary of state for the ColonieSo Dated 31st December,, 1930c Received in the Colonial Office at 2o55 pcirio * 31st Dooember c IMPORTANT o Noo 622.-. The income Tax Amendment Bill ?rae rushed through both homsaa of Iraq parliament on 29th December, Bill is an on dig eat 3d measure unsupported by any reliable dat^- and the Government Btiflod all discussion of its in ^ne chaaiboro rt provides ior increase of o 0 .-.’vi' C'csi?. t whie year ’ v vo which I liave not raised objection) and tor aext year it raises tho flat rate .-.x uii e6 to v per cent,, the first 2 9 000 Rupees of rnoe-ue being exempt and next 2 P 000 Rupees being subject to 6 per cent tax* Exemption limit is at present 4*000 Rupeeso New rates are to ':e applied to ”1931 - 32 and subsequent years” c I advised the Iraq Goverrunent not to exceed following limits (1) first 2,000 Rupees exempt (2) next 2*000 at present rats (3 C 6 per cent) (3) flat rate at double present rates (7c 2 par cent)« fhe above limits are approximately estimated to produce 14 Lakhs next year as against 5 Lakhs at present* that is an increase of 180 per* cent while new rates provided for in Bill are estimated \n produce 20 Lakhs* an increase of 300 per cento I also advise (d) that the operation of Bill should 0(2 -eetricte.d to ihe firnncial year 1931/1932 since it wa&amp; designed merely as uaergency measure.The Iraq Government have behaved throughout in a reprehensible manner and I think that the new Bill is aimed at foreign residents and Companies* is a panic measure which has not been based on or justified by any reliable figures and prima facie is unfair and unreasonablec I have accordingly advised King paisal to return the Bill to Parliament for amendments This would enable Parliament to nass immediately a Bill providing for an increase in the tax for this year of 50 per cent and would mean that the Income Ta-x Bill fox’ next, year would be introduced after Budget estimates and figures regarding the tax had been carefully scrutinised and the effect any new rate proposed in the Bill had been discussed with me and communicated to His Majesty’s Government for approvalHI COPY. NO.M95 P z. l: 59 1 Q i I Secr^tart^ ^Y.tJ^Counci 1 o f Mini st ?2^ Baghdad. 29th Novemher, 1930. Enclosure to despatch 1197 High Comini sooner for Iraq dated 4.12.3p. To:- Tne Secretary to H. 1 ?. the High Commissioner for f Iraq t Baghdad. I foivard to you herewith copy of draft Salaries and Allowances Tax Law in the form in which it was passed Ly the Chambers of Senate and Deputies (Stfd.) ’Abdul Qadir Rashid, Secretary to the ouncil of Ministers.ivzr. c q / ■ oy . 1 Draft Salaries and Allowanc [es TAX.-’Law 'vp A Article 1. Tiiis law shall be called Salaries and Allowances Tax Law No* of 1930. Article 2. A tax will be imposed on salaries and allowances payable from the general revenue®, and from the revenue® of *A®lttah, i unicipalitie® and at r Boards, and which will fail due to be p;\id with effect from 1st ! ! ov&lt;»mb?r 1930. Article 3 . The word 'salaries* includes the salaries of ^inieters, permanent and temporary official®, offic r® and employee® whose salaries are debited to salaries or oth^r votes of the general budget or the budgets of the Department of Bailways. Port, Awqaf, Amanat al ’Asimah, inicipalities and ater Board®, together with pensions, pension gratuities and salaries of Khairat al Ludawarah . Article 4. (a) The word 'allowances* includes the Privy Purse,^and allowances f special services, t eth r with the allowances, wages, and gratuities which are paid to various addresses against the carrying out of special duties (it does not include theVarious kinds of travelling and transport allowances). This tax shall be collected from Senators and Deputit® in proportion to the allowances payable to th^m. (b) Allowances are considered as a part of the salaries as far as Article 5 of this law is concerned. Article 5. The tax will be collected in accordance with the following rates:** (a) One anna on each rupee of salaries and allowances not exceeding Ks .100 p .m * (b) Salaries and allowance® exceeding Rs.100 p.m. but not exceeding Rs.3C0 p.m. - one anna on each rupee of the firstcf. / Sijiju ® first hundred rupees, and one anna and a half on each rupee exceeding that amount . (c) Salaries and allowances exceeding Re. 500 p.m. - cne anna on each rupee of the first hundred rupees, one anna aid a half on each rupee of the second and third hundred rupees, and two annse on each rupee exceeding that (the latter) amount. \ Article 6 . This tax does not apply to: (a) Salaries of Angl o-British officials engaged on contracts . (b) The first 15 rupees of the salaries of pensioners whose salaries do not exceed Rs.30. (c) The first 16 rupees of the salaries of soldiers, policemen, and prison guards. (d) Ration and fodder allowances payable to police and army individuals . (e) Salaries officials « n employees of mosques and places of worship belonging to the Directorate-General of Awqaf. (f) Salaries of needy persons, paid by Municipal ties. Article 7. The provision of this low dll cease to operate at the end of the financial year 1951. Arti le 6 . The Sinister of finance is charged with the execution of this law.78471/30. 1930 from tha Tacretary of State for tho Colcniag to the Commissioner of Iraq. (Sant 4.0 p.m. 12th December 1930). No. 472 . Reference your telegram No.590 of the 6th of December. The Iraq Government may be informed that, provided that the Salaries and Allowances Tax Law is abandoned,, His Llajesty’s Government would not object to their making provision for the additional revenue desired to be produced by means of an increase of the general income tax in a fair and reasonable manner and a small reduction in the salaries of low paid officials who are not serving upon contracts. You should in communicating' the above to the Iraq Government, make it clear that His Majesty's Government are in full sympathy with their desire to raise additional revenue, and have intervened only because the measure contemplated by the Government of ;raq to that end seemed to them to constitute a serious breach of moral obligation, and to b^contrary to the Iraq Constitution. The alternative means His Majesty's Government now propose would be free from these objections and would equally serve the purpose which tho Government of Iraq have in view.\ £ ^ lift PARAFHHASK TSL^QRAM from the Hig£i Commissioner for Iraq to the Secretary of State for the Colon!es„ Dated 6th December 0 (Received, Colonial Office, 5 C 55 a»nn, 7th December, 1930). IMPORTANT. No* 590 c Reference your telegram No c 464 of 5th December regarding the Salaries Tax Law. Notwithstanding my oral and written request to the contrary the Regent signed this Law which had been passed by both Houses, on the day previous to that on which King Feisal returned from Cyprus. I took the first opportunity after the King's return to protest strongly against this proceeding. King Faisal admitted that a mistake had been made and stated that if he had been in Baghdad himself he would have refused to sign it. At the same time the Law had now been through all stages and he did not see what could be done. I informed him that I was * still awaiting your reply to my telegram No.575 and said that 1 must insist upon the publication of the Law being deferred pending its receirt. He agreed to this but warned me repeatedly that if H.M.Government raised objections to the Law as passed, the Cabinet would inevitably resign. I reserved further comment on the merits A of the Law until I had received that reply from H.M.Government and on that occasion confined myself to protesting against the procedure which had been adopted by Minister of Finance and King Ali« The present position is that the Law will not cane into force until the elapse of fifteen days after its publication in the Official Gazette which cannot be postponed beyond the 15th December at the latest. The Law will then if publi shed have retrospective % effectT 'wn, \HO effect as from the 1st of November and deductions from the salaries for the month of November have already been made in anticipation of its enactment, the amounts deducted being held on deposit pending the coming into force of the Law, 2 I fully discussed with the British Advisers to-day the position arising out of your telegram No.464 and so far as it is possible for me to judge the Cabinet mil resign n they Ire pressed to introduce ^amending Law fraa the pr0p ° 88 tax all officials servi£*f%ey will probably retort, in reply to the argument that discrimination against other than British officials is a breach of Article 11 of the 1922 Treaty, by suggesting that British Officals should be included as well, rc wouio. apt— from your telegram that this course would be open to the same ■ - objection vis. a flagrant breach of moral obligation and definitely ' opposed to the letter and the spirit of Article eleven of Iraq Constitution. I should refuse, therefore, to accept it. The only solution which I can see and which is recormiended by the majority of . Advisers is that I should be given authority to inform the Government of Iraq that H.M.Government would raise no 003 action to the aban donment of the Law and tc a corresponding economy being effected 1 by raising the Income Tax. The actual increase in the rate of income tax which would effect this result has not yet been calculated exactly but it is thought that an increase from the existing Wh to something sfe under \%together with a reduction of the figure of income below which the tax is not leviable from Rupees ^OOO to 2,000 a year plus a cut in the salaries of officials who receive less than Rupees 2,000 per annum would result in approximately the same revenue as that expected from the Salaries Tax Lav as it now stands. The only other alternative which any Adviser couldwas that the Govermient of Iraq should be pressed to exclude all officials serving under contract from the operation of the Law and that they should at the same time be invited to open negotiations for the revision of the conditions of their contracts. This suggestion was negatived by the majority cf Advisers and in my opinion is open to insuperable objections. Firstly the Government of Iraq would find great difficulty in inducing Parliament to accept an undefined future economy 2 negotiations for which would certainly drag themselves out over a long period; secondly it is doubtful whether this alt. 3 mative would not involve a revision of the British officials agreement for the period from the present time until 1932; thirdly the concurrence of all foreign contract officials would have to be obtained and in the meantime they would a.gain 00 come a target for universal attack and the Iraq Government would be encouraged to concentrate on a reduction of their numbers to an undesirable extent. After full consideration I seek authority to inform the Government of Iraq that if they find themselves unable to emend the Law by excluding from its operations all officials under contract, IL Mo Government would have no objection to an increase of the general income tax in a fair and reasonable manner, and also a small cut in the salaries of low paid officials to such an extent as will be necessary to bring in the seme revenues as would have been secured by Salaries Tax Law as passed by Parliament. I should be very glad io have an early reply to this telegram in view of the fact that the Law only awaits publication to come into force, and that publication cannot be deferred beyond the end of next week.Lr'jL'/fe Reference to previous correspondence: er from ^ ie Colonial Office of the 'J/ Transmitted by direction of the Secretary of State for the Colonies. A copy lias also been sent to the Colonial Office, Downing Street, 19*^0 . i (E5563) Wt 17789/2334 10,000(2) 12/29 H &amp; Sp Gp 11278471/30. PARAPHRASE TELEGRAM from the Secretary of State for the Colonies to the High Commissioner for Iraq. (Sent 10.45 p.m e , 4th December, 1930). IMPORTANT No.464c Reference your telegram No.575 of 28th November There cen be no doubt, while the application of the proposed tax to officials serving on contract might not be an actual breach of contract in the sense that it could be the basis of action in Court,that it would be a flagrant breach of moral obligation. It is the strong opinion of HoM.Government that not only British but all officials who are under contract should be exempted. The term 'Anglo-British' is, in any case, unknown in official terminology and if it has any meaning at all, it might held to exclude Scottish and Irish of ticiais. Moreover there wculo. at any rato bo an appearance of conflict with Article 11 of 1922 treaty if only British officials were to be exempted from payment of the tax. This is an important point since the compatibility of Iraqi legisla tion with that Article is watched jealously at Geneva by certain foreigi Powers, whc mi$rt discover way of taking up the question on grounds of general principle even though in practice none of 'choir nationals was affected. Criticism by the Permanent Mandates Commission would also be liable to be provoked by any appearance of conflict with Article 11. You can rely on H.M.Government 1 s support in resisting any attempt to apply the tax to officials on contract. VideVide also Article 11 of the Constitution of Iraq Tmch appears to establish tha principle of equality of taxation and to prohibit any tax being levied on one special class onxy* Tfi- '.-rjJ't. law, which would involve tha tax being icaprosed on civil servants only, seems definitely opposed to 'the letter and spirit of this Article. It mi^t be possible to meet this difficulty by recasting the draft iaw in 8uoh fora ae to provide not for a tax on salaries but for a reduction of salary in the case of all officials -ao ere net serving under contract.78471/30. rs Arising out of our conference this afternoon, I enclose the draft of a telegram to Baghdad about the proposed tax on salaries. I shall be glad to know, with the least possible delay, whether the India Office concur in the draft. TN m-uiM-i Ltlltrt n'6. ^ \\w&amp;m 12 DEC 1930 MfT. INDIA mijot G.H.G. Anderson Esq., D.S.O.,M.C.(Ts5s r\ i&gt;\im ro; cciicuniv^ci OF rCRSIG:.- cffic;. UOa office.' MD TEL/BHAii (OVPUER) HIGHCOMA BAGHDAD* No. Your tolegram No.575* ohilo application of proposed tax to officials serving on contract might not be tctual breach of contract in sense that it could be basis of action in Court, yet there can he no doubt that it would be flagrant broach of moral obligation, ana are strongly of opinion that not only British but all officials who are under contract should be exempted. In any case term 'Anrlo-Bri! irh' is unknown in official terminology and if it means caything at 11 might be held to exclud'exclude Scottish and drieh officials* Moreover there would be at any rate ;n appearance of conflict with Article 11 pf 1922 Treaty if Lriiirii officials / wfj ® only were exempted from You can rely on suppor: of t.l'.G. in resisting any atteript to apply tax to 0 f f i c i a. 1 s on c on t r a c. t. See also Article 11 of Iraq Constitution which appears to entaMish principle of equality of taxation and to prohibit Ijiny tax on one . mcial class only# Draft la-, which wonli # involve imposition of tax or civil servants only, seems definitely opposed to letter ana spirit of Inis Article. This difficulty might possibly be ret by recast in. draft lav. in -such ferr- as to provide not for tax on salaries but -fft* reduction of salary in case of all o-f*fuials not sorvin- on contract*Communications on this subject should be addressed to— ?HE Under Secretary of State, Colonial Office, London, S.W.l. and the following 7 347 4/30 . / . ^ Number quoted: «. — — ' /’ ~ / Downing Street, S30 l * December , i9$j . ^ s* ( 3*0 1.oCci Sir, I am directed by Lord Passfield to refer to the telegram from the Hlgn Commissioner for Iraq no. 575 ot the 28th of November, a copy of which was sent to the India Office under cover of the letter from this Department of the 29th of Lovember, numbered as above, and to transmit to you herewith, to be laid before Mr.Secretary Benn, a copy of the draft Salaries and Allowances Tax Law which is referred to in the telegram under reference and also a copy of a letter on this subject which was addressed to His Majesty King Faisal's Private Secretary by direction of the High Commissioner. 2. Lord Passfield proposes to call a conference to be held in tne Conference Room at the Coxonial Oiiice at 4 p.m.on the 3rd of December, in order to consider Wiiat reply should be returned to the High Commissioner's telegram, and he would be glad if arrangements could be made for a 'THE UNDER SECRETARY OF STATE, INDIA OFFICE. representativeDraft Salaries and Allowances Tax Law of 1930 Article 1 . This law shall be called 'Salaries and Allowances Tax Law of 1930 ,! . Article Z . A tax will be im )Osed on salaries and allowances payable from the general revenues and which will fall due to be paid with eifect irom 1st hove ber, 1930. Article 3 . The word 'salaries' includes the salaries of Ministers, permanent and temporary officials, oificers, and employees whose salaries are deoited to salaries or other votes of the general budget, together with pensions, pension gratuities and salaries of Khairat al-Mudawarah. article 4. (a) The word 'allowances' includes the rivy urse, Senators and Deputies allowances and allowances of special services, together with the allowances, wages and gratuities which are paid to various addresses against the carrying out oi special duties (it does not include the various kinds of travelling and transport allowances). (b) Allowances are considered as a part of the salaries as far as Article 5 of this law is concerned. Article b . The tax will be collected in accordance with the following rates (a) One anna on each rupee of salaries and allowances not exceeding Be.100 p.m. (b; Salaries and allowances exceeding bs.100 p.m., but not exceeding Rs. 300 p.m. - one anna on each rupee of the first hundred rupees and one annaand a half on each rupee exceeding that amount. One anna on each rupee of the fir t hundred rupees, one snna and a half on each rupee oi the second and third hundred rupees, and two annas on each rupee exceeding that (the latter) amount. article 6 . (a) This tax dees not apply to the salaries of British offic ale engaged on contracts. Article 7 . The provision of this law will cease to operate at the end of the financial year 1S31. Article 8. (c) Salaries and allowances exceeding Ks. 300 p.m. (bj This tax does not apply to the salaries and allowances of soldiers and policemen. The Minister of finance is charged with the ,, execution of this law.Secretariat of the High Commissioner for ’Iraq, Copy. Cufl^D^mAL. Ho. B.0.211. t5H Baghdad. 14th November, 1930. Ly dear ’Abdullah Hffendi, Heierence my letter Mo. h.0.206 dated the 12th November, 1J3G, regarding the resolutions passed by the Council of Linisters at their meeting held on 6th November last, I am directed to inform you that His Excellency the High Commissioner, while he would have preferred the omission from Article 6 of the draft Salaries and Allowances Tax Law of the word 'British', has satisfied himself that the article as drafted violates no constitutional principle. His Excellency does not, therefore, wish His Majesty’s approval of resolution No. 1 to be further delayed. His Excellency desires r.-e to point out, however, that it will of course be open to any foreigner serving the ’Iraq Government on contract and feeling himself aggrieved by the operation of this law, to move his Government to make diplomatic representations to the ’Iraq Government on his behalf. Yours sincerely, (Signed) B.S.k.STUBGiiS. ’Abdullah Effendi al Hai, Private Secretary to H.L.King Faisal, Baghdad. Copy to; The Secretary to the Counoil of tinistera.12b Communications on this subject should be affdressed to— The Under Secretary of State, Colonial Office, London, S.W.l, and the following/.umber quoted :— /Zk _ ®&gt; J / Reference to previous ^correspondence: to Letter y rom die Colonial Office of the 'll Transmitted by direction of the Secretary of State for the Colonies. A copy has also been sent to the A Colonial Office, Downing Street, 19 )®. ENCLOSURE IN WEEKLY LETTER Ho. 4 9 4 DEC mo no* ^-GvITAKY, Pa^lTiOAL AMD U.uur r*fT. INDIA OFFICE L (R5563) Wt 17789/2334 10,000(2) 12/29 HAS? Gp 112 V P$ &lt;5^ &lt;k 4 1 P 83i6 1930 . ParaT)hr&amp;s« Telegram frm the High Commi.a^ioner ior Iraq to the Secretary of State for the Colonieiio Dat 9d 28th November e I930o (Received Colonial Office 7*20 pom. 28th Novembers 1930c} Important® No® 575o PleaB© see my despatch of November 14th Noa l 0 il8 in which was encloecd a draft salaries and allowance® tax law 0 Although I advised that the word 'Britiflh* should be omitted from Clauee da I did not insist on its omiaaion but informed ihe King that I understood that th&amp; ^Britieh H inciudsd all Britieh SubjeotJic With regard to the remaining Foreign Officials on contract which con slot of a few iSgynt lfcns and Syrians,, I mado it UmS a diplornatio protest migit be invited® I expressed the»® views personally to th* King and the Minister of Finance but the latter proposed and carried, without reference to the Council of Ministers and therefore without giving me an opportunity for making further comments an amendment in the Chamber yesterday making the -^aw anplioable to other Departments including Port and Railways which contain hundreds of Indians on contract® He also accepted an amendment substituting for the word ‘♦British* in Clause 6 a the tern 'Anglo-Bri fciah% thereby making it clear tnat the Law will apply to British Indian Officials, In the meantime it occurs to me that the compromise of ^British* may oe regarded as inconsistent with Article 11 of the Treaty of 1922 0 The subsequent amendments made by Parliament further involve discrimin4ion against the British which the Government of India will presumably resent® I have therefore asked tie Regent, unless an amendment can be mad# in the Senate extended to all Officials on contracts,, to- 1 ' ■ 1 to withhold his consent to ths Bill until X am able to let him knew that His Majesty* n Govemment d®si re to inciat uoon it«? amendment in aiiy way e Should it bo held .•hat di©cri»iinato3fy treatment i® contrary to Articlo il of the Iv'^J Treaty tha Iraq Got may ooxmtv? by proposing to extend the app3,ioation of ths Law to British Offioiais algOo This would ba opposed vehemently by British Officials on both legal and moral grounds® 2 should be glad to reoelwe your inetructionsae early as may be possible whether the application cf the Law to Officials *41 '^ontxaot oonstituteo a breach of ^uch Contract and if not (B) whether X may count on your support in refusing to acquiesce in ITS application to any class of 0Fr202d&amp; on Contract® 2 have not bean able to trace any record that the High Comissioner has ever before called upon the King to withhold bis assent to a Law after it© passage through P&amp;rliamsnto Baring the debate in Parliament moreover the exemption of British officials from the tax arousegfetrong hostile comment&amp;&lt;&gt; This question may therefore assume &amp;r exaggerated importance and x request a very early reply to this telegram®TREATY SERIES No. 17 (1925). TREATY OF ALLIANCE BETWEEN GREAT BRITAIN AND IRAK, Signed at Bagdad, October 10, 1922; AND Protocol to Treaty of Alliance between Great Britain and Irak of October 10, 1922, Signed at Bagdad, April 30, 1923; TOGETHER WITH Agreements subsidiary to the Treaty of Alliance between Great Britain and Irak of October 10, 1922, Signed at Bagdad, March 25, 1924. [Ratifications exchanged at Bagdad, December 19, 1924.j Presented by the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs to Parliament by Command of His Majesty. LONDON : PRINTED &amp; PUBLISHED BY HIS MAJESTY’S STATIONERY OFFICE. To be purchased directly from H.M. STATIONERY OFFICE at the following addresses : Adastral House, Kingsway, London, W.C.2; 28, Abingdon Street, London, S.W.l; York Street, Manchester; 1, St. Andrew’s Crescent, Cardiff; or 120, George Street, Edinburgh; or through any Bookseller. 1925 Price 9d. Net. Cmd. 2370.Treaty between His Britannic Majesty and His Majesty the King of Irak. Signed at Bagdad, October 10, 192*2. [Ratifications exchanged at Bagdad, December 19, 1924.] His Britannic Majesty of the one part, and His Majesty the King of Irak of the other part; Whereas His Britannic Majesty has recognised Feisal Ibn Hussein as constitutional King of Irak; and Whereas His Majesty the King of Irak considers that it is to the interests of Irak and will conduce to its rapid advancement that he should conclude a treaty with His Britannic Majesty on the basis of alliance; and Whereas His Britannic Majesty is satisfied that the relations between himself and His Majesty the King of Irak can now be better defined by such a treaty of alliance than by any other means : For this purpose the High Contracting Parties have appointed as their plenipotentiaries :— His Majesty the King of the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland and of the British Dominions beyond the Seas, Emperor of India : Sir Percy Zachariah Cox, G.C.M.G., G.C.I.E., K.C.S.I., High Commissioner and Consul-General of His Britannic Majesty in Irak; His Majesty the King of Irak : His Highness Sir Saiyid ‘Abd-ur-Rahman, G.B.E., Prime Minister and Naqib-al-Ashraf, Bagdad; Who, having communicated their full powers, found in good and due order, have agreed as follows :— Article 1. At the request of His Majesty the King of Irak, Plis Britannic Majesty undertakes subject to the provisions of this treaty to provide the State of Irak with such advice and assistance as may be required during the period of the present treaty, without prejudice to her national sovereignty. His Britannic Majesty shall be represented in Irak by a High Commissioner and Consul-General assisted by the necessary staff. 2693 W t. 20942/328 500 1/26 F.O.P. [140201 B 2Article 2. His Majesty the King of Irak undertakes that for the period of the present treaty no gazetted official of other than Irak nationality shall be appointed in Irak without the concurrence of His Britannic Majesty. A separate agreement shall regulate the numbers and con ditions of employment of British officials so appointed in the Irak Government. Article 3. His Majesty the King of Irak agrees to frame an Organic Law for presentation to the Constituent Assembly of Irak and to give effect to the said law, which shall contain nothing contrary to the provisions of the present treaty and shall take account of the rights, wishes and interests of all populations inhabiting Irak. This Organic Law shall ensure to all complete freedom of conscience and the free exercise of all forms of worship, subject only to the maintenance of public order and morals. It shall provide that no discrimination of any kind shall be made between the inhabitants of Irak on the ground of race, religion or language, and shall secure that the right of each community to maintain its own schools for the education of its own membeis in its own language, while conforming to such educational requirements of a general nature as the Government of Irak may impose, shall not be denied or impaired. It shall prescribe the con stitutional procedure, whether legislative or executive, by which decisions will be taken on all matters of importance, including those involving questions of fiscal, financial and military policy. Article 4. Without prejudice to the provisions of articles 17 and 18 of this treaty, His Majesty the King of Irak agrees to be guided by the advice of His Britannic Majesty tendered through the High Commis sioner on all important matters affecting the international and financial obligations and interests of His Britannic Majesty for the whole penod of this treaty. His Majesty the King of Irak will fully consult the High Commissioner on what is conducive to a sound financial and fiscal policy and will ensure the stability and good organisation of the finances of the Irak Government so long as that Government is under financial obligations to the Government of His Britannic Majesty. Article 5. .nib iviajesty me Amg ot Irak shall have the right of representa- tion m London and in such other capitals and places as may be agreed upon by the High Contracting Parties. Where His Majesty the King of Irak is not represented he agrees to entrust the protection of Irak nationals to His Britannic Majesty. His Majesty the King of Irak shall himself issue exequaturs to representatives of foreign Powers m Irak after His Britannic Majesty has agreed to their appointment.5 ( Article 6. His Britannic Majesty undertakes to use his good offices to secure the admission of Irak to membership of the League of Nations as soon as possible. Article 7. His Britannic Majesty undertakes to provide such support and assistance to the armed forces of His Majesty the King of Irak as may ^A-om time to time be agreed by the High Contracting Parties. A separate agreement regulating the extent and conditions of such support and assistance shall be concluded between the High Con tracting Parties and communicated to the Council of the League of Nations. Article 8. No territory in Irak shall be ceded or leased or in any way placed under the control of any foreign Power; this shall not prevent His Majesty the King of Irak from making such arrangements as may be necessary for the accommodation of foreign representatives and for the fulfilment of the provisions of the preceding article. Article 9. His Majesty the King of Irak undertakes that he will accept and give effect to such reasonable provisions as His Britannic Majesty may consider necessary in judicial matters to safeguard the interests of foreigners in consequence of the non-application of the immunities and privileges enjoyed by them under capitulation or usage. These provisions shall be embodied in a separate agreement, which shall be communicated to the Council of the League of Nations. Article 10. The High Contracting Parties agree to conclude separate agree ments to secure the execution of any treaties, agreements or under takings which His Britannic Majesty is under obligation to see carried out in respect of Irak. His Majesty the King of Irak undertakes to bring in any legislation necessary to ensure the execution of these agreements. Such agreements shall be communicated to the Council of the League of Nations. Article 11. There shall be no discrimination in Irak against the nationals of any State, member of the League of Nations, or of any State to wffiich His Britannic Majesty has agreed by treaty that the same rights should be ensured as it would enjoy if it were a member of the said League (including companies incorporated under the laws of such State), as compared with British nationals or those of any foreign State in matters concerning taxation, commerce or navigation, the exercise of industries or professions, or in the treatment of merchant vessels or civil aircraft. Nor shall there be any discrimination in Irak against goods originating in or destined for any of the said States. There shall be freedom of transit under equitable conditions across Irak territory.Article 12. No measure shall be taken in Irak to obstruct or interfere with missionary enterprise or to discriminate against any missionary on the ground of his religious belief or nationality, provided that such enterprise is not prejudicial to public order and good government. Article 13. His Majesty the King of Irak undertakes to co-operate, in so far as social, religious and other conditions may permit, in the execution of any common policy adopted by the League of Nations for prevent ing and combating disease, including diseases of plants and animals. Article 14. His Majesty the King of Irak undertakes to secure the enactment, within twelve months of the coming into force of this treaty, and to ensure the execution of a Law of Antiquities based on the rules annexed to article 421 of the Treaty of Peace signed at Sevres on the 10th August, 1920. This law shall replace the former Ottoman Law of Antiquities, and shall ensure equality of treatment in the matter of archaeological research to the nationals of all States members of the League of Nations, and of any State to which His Britannic Majesty has agreed by treaty that the same rights should be ensured as it would enjoy if it were a member of the said League. Article 15. A separate agreement shall regulate the financial relations between the High Contracting Parties. It shall provide, on the one hand, for the transfer by His Britannic Majesty’s Government to the Government of Irak of such works of public utility as may be agreed upon and for the rendering by His Britannic Majesty’s Government of such financial assistance as may from time to time be considered necessary for Irak, and, on the other hand, for the progressive liquidation by the Government of Irak of all liabilities thus incurred. Such agreement shall be communicated to the Council of the League of Nations. Article 16. So far as is consistent with his international obligations His Britannic Majesty undertakes to place no obstacle in the way of the association of the State of Irak for customs or other purposes with such neighbouring Arab States as may desire it. Article 17. An}’ difference that may arise between the High Contracting Parties as to the interpretation of the provisions of this treaty shall be referred to the Permanent Court of International Justice provided for by article 14 of the Covenant of the League of Nations. In such case, should there be any discrepancy between the English and Arabic texts of this treaty, the English shall be taken as the authori tative version.US 7 Article 18. This treaty shall come into force as soon as it has been ratified by the High Contracting Parties after its acceptance by the Con stituent Assembly, and shall remain in force for twenty years, at the end of which period the situation shall be examined, and if the High Contracting Parties are of opinion that the treaty is no longer required shall be terminated. Termination shall be subject to confirma- aon by the League of Nations unless before that date article 6 of this treaty has come into effect, in which case notice of termination shall be communicated to the Council of the League of Nations. Nothing shall prevent the High Contracting Parties from reviewing from time to time the provisions of this treaty, and those of the separate agreements arising out of articles 7, 10 and 15, with a view to any revision wdiich may seem desirable in the circumstances then existing, and anv modification which may be agreed upon b^ the High Contracting Parties shall be communicated to the Council of the League of Nations. The ratifications shall be exchanged at Bagdad. The present treaty has been drawn up in English and Arabic. One copy in each language will remain deposited in the archives of the Irak Government, and one copy in each language in those of the Government of His Britannic Majesty. In witness of which the respective plenipotentiaries have signed the present treaty and have affixed thereto their seals. Done at Bagdad in duplicate this tenth day of October, one thousand nine hundred and twenty-two of the Christian era, corresponding with the nineteenth day of SaTar, one thousand three hundred and forty-one, Hijrah. J P. z. COX, His Britannic Majesty’s High Commissioner in Irak. ‘ABD-UR-RAHMAN, Naqib-al-Ashraf of Bagdad and Prime Minister of the Irak Government.X No. 2. Protocol to the Treaty of Alliance between Great Britain and Irak of October 10, 1922. Signed at Bagdad, April 30, 1923. [Ratifications exchanged at Bagdad, December 19, 1924.] We, the undersigned plenipotentiaries of His Britannic Majesty and of His Majesty the King of Irak respectively, having been duly authorised, met together this 30th day of April, 1923, corresponding to the 14th Ramazan, 1341, in order to sign the following protocol to the treaty of alliance concluded between their Majesties aforesaid on the 10th October, 1922, corresponding to 19th Sa'far, 1341, Hijrah, subject to ratification. PROTOCOL. It is understood between the High Contracting Parties that, notwithstanding the provisions of article 18, the present treaty shall terminate upon Iiak becoming a member of the League of Nations and in any case not later than four years from the ratification of peace with Turkey. Nothing in this protocol shall prevent a fresh agreement from being concluded with a view to regulate the subse quent relations between the High Contracting Parties; and negotia tions foi that object shall be entered into between them before the expiration of the above period. In witness of which the respective plenipotentiaries have affixed their signatures thereto. Done at Bagdad in duplicate this 30th day of April, 1923, of the Christian era, corresponding with the 14th day of Ramazan, 1341, Hijrah. P. Z. COX, His Britannic Majesty’s High Commissioner in Irak. ABDUL MUHSIN AL SA'ADUN, Prime Minister of the Irak Government. i *9 No. 3. British Officials Agreement made under Article 2 of the Treaty of Alliance between Great Britain and Irak of October 10, 1922. Signed at Bagdad, March 25, 1924. [Ratifications exchanged at Bagdad, December 19, 1924.] We, the undersigned plenipotentiaries of His Britannic Majesty and of His Majesty the King of Irak respectively, having been duly authorised, met together this 25th day of March, 1924, corresponding to the 19th day of Sha‘ban, 1342, in order to sign the following agreement subsidiary to article 2 of the treaty of alliance concluded between their Majesties aforesaid on the 10th day of October, 1922, corresponding to the 19th day of Sa‘far, 1341, Hijrah, subject to ratification. THE AGREEMENT. Whereas a treaty of alliance between His Britannic Majesty and His Majesty the King of Irak was signed at Bagdad on the 10th da} 7 of October, 1922, corresponding with the 19th day of Sa'far, 1341, Hijrah, and a protocol to the said treaty was signed at Bagdad on the 30th day of April, 1923, corresponding with the 14th day of Ramazan, 1341, Hijrah; and Whereas by article 2 of the said treaty His Majesty the King of Irak undertakes that for the period of the same treaty no gazetted official of other than Irak nationality shall be appointed in Irak with out the concurrence of His Britannic Majesty; and Whereas by the same article it is provided that a separate agree ment regulating the numbers and conditions of employment of British officials so appointed in the Irak Government shall be con cluded between the High Contracting Parties : Now therefore it is agreed as follows :— Article 1. The Irak Government agrees to appoint a British official approved by the High Commissioner as and when it may be requested to do so to any of the posts enumerated in schedule I hereto annexed. Article 2. The Irak Government agrees that any British official appointed to serve the Irak Government in any of the posts reserved under article 1 of this agreement or in any of the posts enumerated in schedule II shall be given a contract on the pay and grading pre scribed for it in the said schedule and embodying the terms and10 conditions of service set forth in schedule III, save and except that British officers seconded or appointed to serve under the Ministry of Defence of the Irak Government shall be given contracts on the pay and grading prescribed in schedule IV and embodying the terms and conditions of service prescribed in schedule IV. Article 3. Subject to the provisions of article 2 of the treaty of alliand# nothing in this agreement shall prevent the Irak Government from engaging British technical or scientific experts or British clerical and subordinate staff on special contracts. Article 4. The Irak Government undertakes that the obligations accepted by them under any contract of employment signed and issued in accordance with this agreement prior to the termination of the treaty of alliance, including the payment of contributions to the provident fund as prescribed in schedule III of this agreement, shall continue m force during the continuance of such contract and on its termina tion, notwithstanding the prior termination of the said treaty of alliance. Article 5. I oi the pin pose of contracts of employment entered into before the termination of the treaty of alliance but continuing in force after such termination as provided in article 4 of this agreement, a revision of such clauses in schedules III and IV of this agreement as contain a reference to His Britannic Majesty’s High Commissioner or to the Disciplinary Board constituted under clause 17 of schedule III shall be undertaken in connection with the negotiations for the con clusion of a fresh agreement between the High Contracting Parties provided for in the protocol to the treaty of alliance. Article 6. All British officials appointed to posts in the Irak Government under the terms of this agreement shall be in the service of the Irak Government and responsible to that Government and not to the High Commissioner. SCHEDULE I. Advisers to the Ministries of Interior, Finance, Justice, Defence and Communications and Works. Directors or Inspectors-General of Irrigation, Public Works, Agriculture, Tapu, Surveys and Veterinary Services. Director or Assistant Director of Audit, Inspectors-General of Police, Posts and Telegraphs, Health, Education, Customs and Excise. President of Court of Appeal.11 SCHEDULE II. Grade I. Advisers to Ministries of Interior, Finance and Justice. Pay Es. 2,500—100—8,500, provided that these rates may be exceeded if the Irak Government is unable to P^tain suitable officials except on a higher rate of pay. Grade II. (i.) Adviser to the Ministry of Communications and Works. President of the Court of Appeal. Inspector-General of Posts and Telegraphs. Inspector-General of Police. Inspector-General of Health. Inspector-General of Education. Inspector-General of Customs and Excise. Director of Irrigation. Director of Public Works. Director of Audit. Director of Agriculture. Assistant Adviser to the Ministry of the Interior. Assistant Adviser to the Ministry of Finance. Eevenue Secretary to the Ministry of Finance. Pay Es. 1,800—100—2,800. Note.—( i.) This post may be on special short-term contract ex-grade, or may be combined with the post of Director of Irrigation or Public Works, whichever of the two is senior. If so combined or on ordinary contract, the starting pay will be Es. 2.200. Grade III. Senior Administrative Inspectors. Senior Finance Inspectors. Senior Police Inspectors. Deputy Inspector-General, C.I.D. (i.) Judges, Court of First Instance Secretary to the Ministry of Communications and Works. Director of Tapu. Director of Veterinary Services. Superintending Engineers. ( Health Specialists. .. J Directors of Hospitals and Institutes. ( n *) 1 Chief Medical Officers in Mosul and Kirkuk. { Medical Officers of Health in Bagdad and Basrah. p ay Es. 1,500—75—1,800—100—2,800. Note.— (i.) If appointed without knowledge of Arabic and local legal experience, to start at Es. 1.350 and be on probation for two years.■Mi Vi 12 (ii.) If allowed to take private practice, to start at Rs. 1,200, and, in the case of future appointments of Health Specialists, if they are allowed to take private practice, they may be placed in another Grade. Grade IV (a). Collectors of Customs. Director of Surveys. Chief Agricultural Research Officer. Chief Agricultural Inspector. Executive Engineers, P.W.D. Electrical Specialist. Government Architect. Executive Engineers, Irrigation. Inspector of Posts. Senior Executive Engineer, Telegraphs. Inspectors of Education. Qualified Medical Officers not in Grade III. Pay Rs. 1,200—75—1,800. Grade IV (b). (i.) Junior Administrative Inspectors. Junior Finance Inspectors. Junior Police Inspectors (1st class). Junior Executive Engineers, Telegraphs. Agricultural Officers. (ii.) Deputy Collectors of Customs. Assistant Director of Public Health (Personnel and Accounts Section). Pay Rs. 900—50—1,200—75—1,800. Note. —(i.) Increments of Rs. 75 throughout. (ii.) Not to rise beyond Rs. 1.500 in this grade unless they pass a departmental test qualifying them for post of Collector and no such post is vacant. Grade V. Assistant Collectors of Customs. Assistant Irrigation Officers. Assistant Engineers, P.W.D. Junior Police Inspectors (2nd class). Survey Officers. Other Officials in Departments of Posts and Telegraphs. Veterinary Officers. Superintendent of Medical Stores. Pay Rs. 800—50—1,800. General Note. (i.) An official already in the service of the Irak Government, who is appointed to any post mentioned in this schedule and similar in■ (T66) IB grade to that in which he is serving at the time of such appointment, shall be placed in the grade prescribed for the post at such a point as will give him a total salary not less than the salary which he is drawing at the time of signing the new contract. In calculating such salary regard shall be had to the number of months which he has served towards the new increment due under his old contract. (ii.) Junior Administrative Inspectors shall be placed at such a ppint in Grade IV as shall give them the salary nearest (either above or below) to their present salary plus Rs. ‘200. their position as regards increments being taken into account as above. (iii.) In order to enable them to meet the extra expense which will be involved by the payment of rent, lighting and conservancy charges, married officers (other than Junior Administrative Inspec tors) stationed in Bagdad, Basra or Mosul, and drawing pay at the rate of less than Rs. 1.500 per mensem, shall be granted a personal allowance, to be absorbed in future increments, of Rs. 150 or such portion of Rs. 150 as shall together with their salary amount to Rs. 1.500 per mensem in all. SCHEDULE III. Regulations relating to the Service of British Officials in Irak. Period of Service. 1.—(1.) Every official whom it is desired to employ in the Irak Government will be required to enter into an agreement to serve the Irak Government for a definite period, to be specified in his agree ment, of five, ten or fifteen years. (2.) Such period of service will commence on the date on which he embarks to take up his appointment, or in the case of an official already serving in Irak, on a date to be fixed in his contract, and shall not be considered to be interrupted by any local, sick or ordinary leave granted in accordance with these regulations. (3.) Except in the case of officials who before the commencement of such period of service have served not less than one year in the Irak Government and whose retention in the posts in which they are specialised has been asked for by the Irak Government, the first year (or, in the case of officials referred to in Note (i) under Grade III in schedule II, the first two years) of such period of service shall be probationary and the official’s contract may be terminated at the end of the first or second year, as the case may be, by three months’ notice in writing, and when such notice is given the High Commis sioner shall be given an opportunity to give his opinion regarding the official concerned. On such termination of his contract, the official shall be entitled to any leave or leave gratuity which he has earned and a free passage to England for himself. He shall receive from the Provident Fund only the amount of such contributions as he has made hitherto.Salary. 2- (i.) Ihe salary of an official, together with the increment to it, will be that provided for his office in schedule II, provided that— (a.) In the case of officials already serving under the Irak Govern ment and (b) in the case of new appointments of officials with special experience or qualifications, the initial salary of an official may be fixed by his contract at a point in the grade of his office higher than the initial salary of the grade. Half Salary during Voyage on Appointment. (ii.) On being appointed an official will be entitled to half salary from the date of his embarkation to take up his new appointment to the date of his arrival in Irak and to full salary from the date of his arrival in Irak. (hi.) For the purpose of this and the succeeding regulations the term ‘ * salary ’ ’ means the salary attached to the office held by the official and does not include a personal allowance or other payment made to the official. The term emoluments means and includes all payments made to an official including salary and allowances of every kind. Currency of Payment in Irak. (!•) Subject to clause 16 of these regulations, emoluments paid in Irak will be paid in rupees. (2.) An official, on giving three months’ notice, shall have the option of drawing one-third of his salary in London at the fixed convexsion rate of Rs. 15 to £T, or in the event of the currency being altered at the par rate of exchange. An official who shall have availed himself of this option may, by giving three months’ notice, cancel the arrangement and draw’his salary in rupees in Irak. Passages of Officials. 4- A. (1.) An official will, on first appointment, be allowed a free fii'st-class passage out to Irak subject to his executing an agree ment under which he will be bound to refund the cost thereof in the event of his relinquishing the appointment within three years from the date of his arrival in Irak in order to take up other employment in Irak, or within one year from the date of such arrival for any other reason than bodily or mental infirmity. (2.) He will also, on the termination of his service, be allowed a fiee passage to England : provided that if the Government terminate his conti act under clause 18 of these x'egulations for misconduct or insuboi dination, ox the officxal himself tex’imnates it fox* any x'eason other than bodily or mental infirmity, the allowance of this passage shall be at the discretion of the Disciplinary Board constituted under clause 17. (8.) During the currency of his agreement an official will be further allowed a free passage from Irak to England and back, once■■■ (f6l) itS 15 if his contract is for five years’ service, twice if it is for ten years’ service, and three times if it is for fifteen years’ service. (4.) The Government may provide the passage allowed under this regulation on any ship of a recognised line which carries first-class passengers between England and Irak. If the official elects to pro ceed by a different route, he shall receive the actual cost of the passage chosen by him or the value of the passage chosen by Govern- ent, whichever is less. 0 Wives of British Officials. B.—(1.) The wife of an official already married at the commence ment of his contract shall be allowed two free first-class single passages either way between England and Irak when the contract of the official is for five years’ service, three such passages when the contract is for ten years’, and four such passages w 7 hen it is for fifteen years’ service. (2.) When the official marries during the period of his contract, his wife shall be allowed two free single passages either way for the next five years remaining to be served by the official under his con tract at the time of the marriage, and one free single passage either w 7 ay for every subsequent five years remaining to be served. A period of less than five years shall not be taken into consideration in deciding to what free passage a wife may be entitled under these regulations. (3.) Passages allowed to wives shall be provided under the same conditions as those allowed to officials under 4 (A) of these regulations. Quarters. 5. In the case of an official occupying a house which is the pro perty of the Government, an official who is occupying a house by himself shall pay rent at the rate of 8 per cent, of his salary, and an official who is sharing a house with another official shall pay rent at the rate of 4 per cent, of his salary provided that the pay ment made by the official or officials occupying the house shall in no case exceed a fair rent for the house calculated on the basis of the actual rents of privately-owned houses in the locality. Rent will be paid on the same principle by officials occupying houses which are not the property of the Government, provided that the payment made by the official or officials occupying the house shall in no case exceed the actual rent of the house. Should such pay ment be less than the rent of the house, then, in order to assist the official in paying the balance of the rent, the Government shall give such officials an allowance in aid as follows :— In Basrah and Bagdad : Married officials not exceeding 12 per cent, of their salary. Unmarried officials not exceeding 6 per cent, of their salary. In other stations : Married officials not exceeding 8 per cent, of their salary. Unmarried officials not exceeding 4 per cent, of their salary.These allowances in aid shall be subject to revision every year in accordance with the actual fluctuations of rents. For the purposes of this clause the term “salary” shall be deemed to include personal allowance, if any. Equipment of Quarters. 6. The Government shall, if possible, equip all Government houses occupied by officials with such electric lights, fans and watqfcs as may be recommended by the Directorate of Health Services. Local Leave. 7. An official may at the discretion of the Government be allowed local leave not exceeding 21 days in each calendar year. Such leave shall not be cumulative, and shall not be combined with ordinary leave. Ordinary Leave. 8. —(i.) An official will earn ordinary leave at the rate of one day’s leave for every five days of effective service. No leave other than local leave shall count as effective service. (ii.) Ordinary leave shall be cumulative. (iii.) Subject to the exigencies of the service, an official may be granted the ordinary leave due to him at any time he desires, and may claim the right to take the leave due to him if under a fifteen years’ contract three times; if under a ten years’ contract, twice; and if under a five years’ contract, once. (iv.) An official on the expiry of his service, or on the termination of his contract by the Government for any reason other than insub ordination or misconduct, shall receive a gratuity in respect of ordinary leave which is due to him and which owing to the exigencies of the service he has been unable to take. This gratuity shall be calculated at the rate of one day’s leave allowance for every day of leave due subject to maximum of nine months. (v.) When on ordinary leave an official shall be entitled to full salary. Sick Leave. 9. —(i.) Short periods of absence from duty owing to sickness not exceeding ten consecutive days will be allowed in Irak on full salary. Any absence extending beyond that period will be counted as sick leave. (h.) The aggregate amount of sick leave which an official may be allowed shall be as follows :— If he is on a five years’ contract ... ... 1 year. If he is on a ten years’ contract ... ... 2 years. If he is on a fifteen years’ contract... ... 8 years. (iii.) If these aggregate amounts are exceeded the Government shall have the option of terminating the contract without compen sation. (iv.) On each occasion of taking sick leave an official shall receive full salary for a period up to six months and thereafter such leave as17 is due to him up to a further six months. If no leave or insufficient lea\e is due to him to cover the second six months lie may complete the period by additional sick leave on half-pay. At the end of this period of twelve months the Government shall have the right to terminate without compensation the service of an official who is on a five years contract, and in other cases, i.e., if the official is on more than five years’ contract, a medical board shall assemble, and, if it is ''•msidered that the official is unlikely to be fit to return to duty «/ithin the limits laid down in sub-clause (2) above, Government shall have the right to terminate the contract without compensation. (v.) Nothing in this clause shall in any w r ay modify the obligations of the Irak Government to pay an officer of the Imperial forces or Indian army on return from his employment until he is fit for duty in the Imperial or Indian establishment as the case may be, subject to the maximum period of sick leave with full pay of his substantive rank provided in the regulations of the service concerned. Medical Attendance. 10. In Irak an official will be entitled to free medical treatment, but this privilege shall not extend to his familv. Compensation in case of Termination by Government. 11. In the case of an official whose services are terminated by Government other than for reasons stated in clauses 1, sub-clause (3), 9, 14 and 18, Government shall pay into the Provident Fund on his behalf, and he shall receive from that fund, in addition to the sum already due to him therefrom, a sum equal to the combined contribu tions of Government and the official which would have fallen due in respect of the balance of his contract. Special Compensation for Death, d'c., due to Docal Disturbances, (Ac. 12. Special compensation, which shall not be less favourable in the case of an officer of the Imperial forces or Indian army than that to which he would be entitled under the regulations of his parent service, under rules to be laid down hereafter, will be granted in the case of death, injury or loss of property, &amp;c., due to war or local dis turbances, or in the case of permanent disability certified by a medical board to have arisen out of the special circumstances of his employ ment. In the case of loss of property, no compensation will be paid unless it can be reasonably showm that it was impossible to insure such property or that insurance could only have been effected at an exorbitant premium. In any case compensation will be paid only in' respect of articles considered necessary and indispensable, and the Government will take no responsibility for the loss, theft, ordestruc- « tion of valuables, such as jewellery, works of art, &amp;c. Provident Fund. 13. A Provident Fund shall be instituted to which Government and the officials shall contribute as follows :— (i.) Every official shall contribute to the Provident Fund monthlv by the deduction from his salary bill of one-twelfth of his pay. [14020] ' ’ c18 (ii.) The Government shall contribute monthly in respect of each official a sum equal to twice the official’s contribution during the preceding month. (iii.) Sums deducted on this account from the salary bills of officials, together with the sums due from Government, shall be transmitted monthly to such person or persons as may be appointed Treasurer of the fund by His Britannic Majesty’s Government, and the fund will be administered by trustees approved, and in aceordang| with rules laid down by His Britannic Majesty’s Government. (iv.) Every official, except officials on whose behalf the Govern ment has paid or accepted liability for pension contribution up to the date of commencement of service under the new conditions, shall contribute to the fund in respect of service between the 11th Novem ber, 1920, and the date on which these conditions of service become applicable to him a sum equal to one-twelfth of his aggregate pay during such period. (v.) Government shall contribute a like amount to that con tributed by the official in respect of pre-contract service referred to in sub-clause (iv). (vi.) In the case of officials who are lent or transferred to the Irak Government by other Governments and who continue to qualify for the pension payable by their parent service on condition that their pension contributions continue to be paid, such pension contributions (except in so far as they are payable by the official himself under the rules of his parent service) shall continue to be paid by the Irak Government. The first five sub-clauses of this clause shall not apply in the case of such officials. Languages. 14. An official will be required to comply with the provisions of such regulations relating to language examinations as may be drawn up by a Disciplinary Board constituted under clause 17 of this schedule and approved by the High Commissioner. Such regulations may provide for the stoppage of promotion in the event of failure to pass an examination prescribed as compulsory, and may further provide for termination of the official’s contract without compensation in the event of repeated failures. Travelling Allowances : Acting Allowances. 15. Travelling and transport allowances within Irak and acting allowances shall be admissible in accordance with rules applicable to local officials. Currency. 10. In the event of the currency being altered, the rupee emolu ments shall thereafter be payable in the new currency at the current rate of exchange except as provided in clause 8 (2) of this schedule,19 Discipline. 17. Officials will, for the purposes of discipline, be under th&lt;' supervision of a Board composed as follows :— President : The Prime Minister. Members: A representative of his Excellency the High Commissioner, three Ministers and three senior British officials nominated by His Majesty the King. The findings of the Board shall be subject to the approval of His Majesty the King. Before such approval is given, his Excellency the High Commissioner shall he given an opportunity of expressing his opinion on such findings. Termination for Insubordination, dtc. 18. The Government has the right, subject to the approval of the Disciplinary Board as constituted under clause 17, to terminate without compensation the services of an official who has been guilty of misconduct and insubordination, and to receive back from the Provident Fund the whole or part, as may be decided by the said Board, of the amount contributed by Government to his credit in the Provident Fund. Termination of Contract by Official. 19. An official will be entitled to terminate his contract during its currency by giving six months’ notice in writing to the head of his Department, but should he do so it shall be put before the Disci plinary Board as constituted under clause 17 to decide in the circum stances whether he should receive his free passage home, any or all of the leave due to him, or more than half only of the amount stand ing to his credit in the Provident Fund at the time of his resignation. 20. In the case of any seconded officer of the Imperial forces or Indian army, if, on the termination of his contract otherwise than under clauses 18 and 19, he cannot be absorbed within the authorised establishment, the Irak Government shall be liable for his pay and allowances at normal British rates for the period during which he is awaiting absorption. Arbitration. 21. If any question arises under the agreement entered into by an official whether as regards its interpretation or in any other respect, it shall be referred to the Disciplinary Board, whose decision, after the approval of His Majesty the King as provided in clause 17. shall be final.r X 20 SCHEDULE IY. Regulations relating to the Service ok British Officers EMPLOYED UNDER THE MINISTRY OF DEFENCE OF THE IRAK Government. Period of Service. 1. —(1.) An officer will be required on appointment to enter ii^&amp; an agreement to serve the Irak Government for a period of three years, extendable, if both parties agree and, in the case of an officer of the Imperial forces or Indian army, subject to the approval of His Britannic Majesty’s Government or the Government of India, as the case may be, to five, seven and ten years by successive renewals. (2.) Such period of service will commence on the date on which he embarks to take up his appointment, or in the case of an officer already serving in Irak on a date to be fixed in his contract, and shall not be considered to be interrupted by any local, sick or ordinary leave granted in accordance with these regulations. Salary. 2. —(1.) The salary of an officer together with the increment attached to it will be that provided for his office in the table of grades annexed to this schedule. Half Salary daring Voyage on Appointment. (2.) An officer proceeding to Irak to take up an appointment under the Government of Irak will be entitled to the full pay of his Irak appointment from the date of arrival in Irak and for the period from the date of embarkation to the date of his arrival in Irak, (a) if an officer of the Imperial forces, to half-pay of his Irak appointment or to his British regimental pay (without allowances) of his substan tive rank, whichever is the greater; (b) if an officer of the Indian army, to half the pay of his Irak appointment or to the pay of his substantive rank without staff pay if proceeding from India to Irak, or if not so proceeding the British regimental pay of his substantive rank, whichever is the greater; (c) in all other cases to half the pay of his Irak appointment. Currency of Payment in Irak. * 3. —(1.) Subject to clause 10 of these regulations, emoluments paid in Irak will be paid in rupees. (2.) An officer, on giving three months’ notice, shall have the • option of drawing one-third of his salary in London at the fixed conversion rate of Rs. 15 to LI, or, in the event of the currency being altered, at the par rate of exchange. An officer who shall have availed himself of this option may, by giving three months’ notice, cancel the arrangement and draw his salary in rupees in Irak.(' 70 ) ((&amp; 21 Passages o/ Officers. 4. —A (1.) An officer will, on first appointment, be allowed a free first-class passage out to Irak subject to his executing an agree ment under which he will be bound to refund the cost thereof in the event of his relinquishing the appointment within three years from the date of his arrival in Irak tn order to take up other employment in Irak, or within one year from date of such arrival for any other * ^Sason except bodily or mental infirmity. (2.) He will also on the termination of his service be allowed a free first-class passage to England; provided that, if the Government terminates his service under clause 18 of these regulations for mis conduct or insubordination, or if the officer terminates it for any other reason than bodily or mental infirmity, the allowance of this passage shall be at the discretion of the Government. (8.) During the currency of his agreement an officer will be further allowed a free return first-class passage from Irak to England and back, once on a three or five years’ contract and once again if the contract is extended beyond five years. If an officer who has already taken the free return passage or passages to England granted under this sub-clause or who is not entitled to any such free return passage, is sent to England on the ground of ill-health, a similar free return passage to England and back shall be granted to him. (4.) The Government may provide the passage allowed under this regulation on any ship of a recognised line which carries first- class passengers between England and Irak or on a British Govern ment transport. If the officer elects to proceed by a different route, line or class, or to a destination other than the United Kingdom, he shall receive the actual cost of the passage he takes or the value of (he passage allowed under this regulation, whichever is the less. Wives of Officers. B (1.) The wife of an officer already married at the commence ment of his contract shall be allowed two free first-class single passages either way between England and Irak if the officer’s contract is for three or five years’ service and one further single passage if the officer’s contract is extended beyond five years. (2.) When the officer marries during the period of his contract, the wife shall be allowed two free first-class single passages either « way if and when the officer’s contract is extended. (8.) Passages allowed to wives shall be provided under the same conditions as those allowed to officers under 4 A of these regulations. Quarters. 5. In the case of an officer occupying a house which is the pro perty of the Government, rent will be charged on the following principle :— An office)' who is occupying a house by himself shall pay rent at the rate of 8 per cent, of his salary and an officer who is sharing a [14020] nhouse with another officer shall pay rent at the rate of 4 per cent, of his salary, provided that the payment made by the officer or officers occupying the house shall in no case exceed a fair rent for the house calculated on the basis of the actual rents of privately-owned houses in the locality. Kent will be paid on the same principle by officers occupying houses which are not the property of the Government, provided that the payment made by the officer or officers occupying the house shall in no case exceed the actual rent of the house. Shoi^L such payment be less than the rent of the house, then, in order W assist the officer in paying the balance of the rent, the Government shall give such officers an allowance in aid as follows :— In Basrah and Bagdad — Married officers, not exceeding 12 per cent, of their salary. Unmarried officers, not exceeding 6 per cent, of their salary. In other stations — Married officers, not exceeding 8 per cent, of their salary. Unmarried officers, not exceeding 4 per cent, of their salary. These allowances in aid shall be subject to revision every year in accordance with the actual fluctuation of rents. Equipment of Quarters. 0. The Government shall, if possible, equip all Government houses occupied by officers with such electric light, fans and water as may be recommended by the Directorate of Health Services. Local Leave. 7. An officer may, at the discretion of the Government, be allowed local leave not exceeding 21 days in each calendar year. Such leave shall not be cumulative and shall not be combined with ordinary leave. When on local leave an officer shall be entitled to full salary. Ordinary Leave. 8. —(1.) An officer shall earn one day’s ordinary leave for each five days of effective service. No leave other than 'local leave shall count as effective service. The period spent on voyages other than on first appointment shall be reckoned as ordinary leave. (2.) Ordinary leave shall l&gt;e cumulative. (3.) Subject to the exigencies of the service, an officer may be granted ordinary leave at any time and may claim the right to take such leave as may be due to him— In a three years’ contract—Once. In a five years’ contract—Once. In a seven years’ contract—Twice. In a ten years’ contract—Twice. (4.) When on ordinary leave an officer shall be entitled to full salary.28 (TtF) (5.) An officer on the expiry of his period of service, or on the termination of his contract by the Government for any reason other than insubordination or misconduct, shall receive pay in lieu of any ordinary leave which is due to him and which owing to the exigencies of the service he has been unable to take. The amount so issued shall not in any case exceed nine months’ salary. 9. —(1.) Short periods of absence from duty owing to sickness, ^)t exceeding ten consecutive days, will be allowed in Irak on full salary. Any such absence extending beyond that period will be counted as sick leave. (2.) The aggregate amount of sick leave which an officer may be allowed on a three years’ contract shall be eight months. (8.) If this aggregate amount is exceeded the Government shall have the right of terminating the contract without further notice. (4.) On each occasion of taking sick leave an officer shall receive full salary for a period up to four months and, thereafter, such leave as is due to him up to a further four months. If no leave or insuffi cient leave is due to him to cover the second four months he may complete the period by additional sick leave on half-pay. At the end of this period of eight months the Government shall have the right to terminate his contract without further notice or compensation. (5.) If his original contract or his contract as extended under clause 1 hereof exceeds three years, he shall come under the regula tions as to sick leave laid down for civilian officials under clause 9 of schedule III. (6.) Nothing in this clause shall in any way modify the obligations of the Irak Government to pay an officer of the Imperial forces or Indian army on return from his employment until he is fit for duty in the Imperial or Indian establishment, as the case may be, subject to the maximum period of sick leave with full pay of his substantive rank and allowances as ordinarily issuable as provided in the regula tions of the service concerned. Medical Attendance. 10. In Irak an officer will be entitled to free medical treatment, but this privilege shall not extend to his family. Termination of Contract by Government. 11. In cases other than those provided for in clauses 9, 14 and 18. the Government shall have the right to terminate an officer’s contract on giving him three months’ notice in writing. Such notice shall only be given with the consent of the senior British officer attached to the Ministry of Defence. 11a. Where an officer of the Imperial forces or Indian army cannot be absorbed within the authorised establishment on termina tion of his service under the Irak Government, that Government shall be liable for his pay and allowances under the regulations of the service concerned for the period during which he is awaiting absorption.X V 24 Special Compensation for Death, &lt;£’c., due to Local Disturbances, tfec. 12. Special compensation, which shall not be less favourable in the case of an officer of the Imperial forces or Indian army than that to which he would be entitled under the regulations of his parent service, will be granted under rules to be laid down hereafter by agreement between the High Contracting Parties in the case of death, injury and loss of property, &amp;c., due to war or local distu^ bailees, or in the case of permanent disability certified by a medic^ board to have arisen out of the circumstances of his employment. In the case of loss of property, no compensation will be paid unless it can be reasonably shown that it was impossible to insure such property, or that insurance could only have been effected at an exorbitant premium. In any case compensation will be paid only in respect of articles considered necessary and indispensable and the Government will take no responsibility for the loss, theft or destruction of valuables, such as jewellery, works of art, &amp;c. Gratuity. 18. On the expiry or termination of his contract, except under clauses 14 and 18, an officer shall be entitled in addition to any sums payable under clause 8 (5) to a gratuity of one month s pay at the rate he is then drawing for every completed year of service, fractions of a year to be reckoned at the rate of one day's pay for twelve days service. In the case of officers who are lent or transferred to the Irak Government by other Governments and who would continue to qualify for the pension payable by their parent service on condition that their pension contributions continue to be paid, such pension contri butions (except in so far as they are payable by the officer himself under the rules of his parent service shall continue to be paid by the Irak Government. Such officers will not be eligible for payment of a gratuity under this clause. Lanyuages. 14. An officer will be required to comply with the provisions of such regulations relating to language examinations as may be drawn up by the Ministry of Defence and approved by the High Commissioner. Such regulations may provide for the stoppage of promotion in the Irak service in the event of failure to pass any examination prescribed as compulsory and may further provide for the termination of the officer’s contract without compensation in the event of repeated failures. Travelling Allowances. Acting Allowances. 15. Travelling and transport allowances within Irak and acting allowances shall be admissible in accordance with rules applicable to local officers.no 25 Currency. 16. In the event of the currency being altered the rupee emolu ments shall thereafter be payable in the new currency at the current rate of exchange, except as provided in clause 8 (2) of this schedule. Discipline. ^ 17. Officers will for the purpose of discipline be under the senior British officer employed under the Ministry of Defence, who will himself for disciplinary purposes be under the High Commissioner. Termination for Insubordination, dec. 18. The Government has the right, subject to the concurrence of the High Commissioner, to terminate without compensation the services of an officer who has been guilty of insubordination or misconduct. Termination of Contract by Officer. 19. An officer will be entitled to terminate his contract on giving three months’ notice in writing to the Minister of Defence, but in that case he will not be entitled to a free passage home unless he has com pleted at least eighteen months’ service in the country since joining or since his last return from leave. He will be entitled to receive the gratuity due to him under clause 18, but not to any leave or gratuity in lieu of leave. A rbitration. 20. If any question arises under the agreement entered into by an officer, whether as regards its meaning or in any other respect, It shall be referred to the High Commissioner, whose decision shall be final. GRADES. Grade I. Adviser or Under-Secretary of State to the Ministry of Defence :— Rs. Pay 2,500—100—8,500 Grade II. Senior officers, whether in headquarters or liaison officers, with a rank not lower than that of Major, except in the case of officers already employed in such senior posts :— Rs. 1,500—75—1,800 1,800—100—2,300 PayGrade III. Junior (A‘wan) officers :— Rs. Pay 900—50—1,200 1,200—75—1,800 If the officer under grade III holds the rank of Captain, his salary shall commence at Rs. 1,200, and if he holds the rank of full Lieu tenant or has more than seven years’ service to his credit, his salary shall commence at Rs. 1,000. General Note. (i.) An officer already in the service of the Irak Government who is appointed to any post mentioned in this schedule and similar in grade to that in which he is serving at the time of such appointment shall be placed in the grade prescribed for the post at such a point as will give him a total salary not less than the salary which he is draw ing at the time of signing the new contract. In calculating such salary regard shall be had to the number of months which he has served towards the new increment due under his old contract. (ii.) In order to enable them to meet the extra expense which will be involved by payment of rent, lighting and conservancy charges, married officers stationed in Bagdad, Basrah or Mosul, and drawing pay at the rate of less than Rs. 1,500 per mensem shall be granted a personal allowance, to be absorbed in future increments, of Rs. 150, or such portion of Rs. 150 as shall bring their salary up to Rs. 1,500 per mensem. In witness of which the respective plenipotentiaries have affixed their signatures thereto. Done at Bagdad in duplicate this 25th day of March, 1924, of the Christian era, corresponding with the 19th day of Sha‘ban, 1842, Hijrah. H. DOBBS, His Britannic Majesty's High Commissioner jot Irak. JA'FAR AL ‘ASKART. Prime Minister of the Irak Government.wmm “T ill 27 No. 4 Military Agreement made under Article 7 of the Treaty of Alliance between Great Britain and Irak of October 10, 1922. [Ratifications exchanged at Bagdad, December 19, 1924. j We, the undersigned plenipotentiaries of His Britannic Majesty and of His Majesty the King of Irak respectively, having been duly authorised, met together this 25th day of March, 1924, corresponding to the 19th day of Sha'ban, 1842, in order to sign the following agree ment subsidiary to article 7 of the treaty of alliance concluded between Their Majesties aforesaid on the 10th day of October, 1922. corresponding to the 19th day of Sa‘far, 1841, Hijrah, subject to ratification. Whereas a treaty of alliance between His Britannic Majesty and His Majesty the King of Irak was signed at Bagdad on the 10th day of October, 1922. corresponding with the 19th day of Sa‘far, 1841, ilijrah, and a protocol to the same treaty was signed at Bagdad on the 30th day of April, 1923, corresponding with the 14th day )f Ramazan, 1341, Hijrah; and Whereas by article 7 of the said treaty His Britannic Majesty undertakes to provide such support and assistance to the armed forces of His Majesty the King of Irak as may from time to time be agreed by the High Contracting Parties; and Whereas by the same article it is provided that a separate agree ment regulating the extent and conditions of such support and assist ance shall be concluded between the High Contracting Parties and communicated to the Council of the League of Nations; and Whereas by article 18 of the same treaty it is provided that nothing shall prevent the High Contracting Parties from reviewing from time to time the provisions of the separate agreement referred to above with a view to any revision which may seem desirable in the circumstances then existing, any modifications which may be agreed upon by the High Contracting Parties being communicated to the Council of the .League of Nations : Now therefore it is agreed as follows :— The two Governments hereby recognise the principle that the Government of Irak shall at the earliest possible date, provided it shall not be later than four years from the date of the conclusion of Signed at Bagdad, March 25, 1924. THE AGREEMENT Article 1X . 1 1 28 this agreement, accept full responsibility both for the maintenance of internal order and for the defence of Irak from external aggression. With this end in view, it is agreed that the material support and assistance now being rendered by llis Britannic Majesty s Govern ment to the Government of Irak shall he progressively reduced with all possible expedition. Article 2. ,— v Such support and assistance as may for a time be provided by t^ Government of His Britannic Majesty shall take the form of the presence in Irak either of an Imperial garrison or of local forces main tained by His Britannic Majesty’s Government and of the granting of facilities in the following matters, the cost of which will he met by the Irak Government :— 1. Military and aeronautical instruction of Irak officers in the United Kingdom so far as this may he possible. 2. The provision in sufficient quantities of arms, ammunition. equipment and aeroplanes of the latest available pattern for the Irak army. B. The provision of British officials whenever they may he required by the Irak Government within the period of the Treaty. Such support and asisstance shall in no case take the form of a contribution by His Britannic Majesty’s Government to the cost of the Irak army or other local forces maintained and controlled by the Government of Irak, and similarly the Government of Irak shall not contribute to the cost of the Imperial garrison or forces maintained and controlled by llis Britannic Majesty’s Government. Article 8. So long as the presence of an Imperial garrison or the mainten ance of local forces under the control of His Britannic Majesty s Government is necessary in order to assist the Government of Irak in attaining the full responsibility accepted in principle under article 1 of this agreement, the following provisions shall regulate the military relations to be maintained between the two Governments in Irak. Article 4. The Irak Government undertake to devote not less than 25 per cent, of the annual revenue of Irak as defined in article 4 of the separate agreement regulating the financial relations between the two Governments, to the maintenance of the regular army and other local forces controlled by them, and in so far as their financial capacity permits, progressively to increase the strength of their permanent regular army of various arms in accordance with the programme prescribed in the schedule hereto annexed and to form a reserve army. The British Government shall equip the units of these forces, as and when they are completed, in accordance with the pro visions of article 2 of this agreement.T?^ 172- 29 Article 5. The strength and composition of the Imperial garrison and of the local forces under the control of His Britannic Majesty’s Government • shall be reviewed each year with a view to the progressive reduction provided for in article 3 of the financial agreement referred to in the preceding article. , ^ Article 6. The Irak army shall, subject to the provisions of the Irak Consti tutional Law, be commanded by His Majesty the King of Irak. The Officer Commanding the British Forces in Irak shall not intervene in matters relating to the Irak army except as provided in articles 7 and 9 of this agreement. Article 7. The Irak Government undertake to grant the Officer Commanding the British Forces in Irak authority to carry out such inspections of the Irak army and other local forces as he may consider necessary in order that he may test their efficiency and to submit to His Majesty the King of Irak, through the High Commissioner, his recommenda tions as to such steps as he considers necessary for their improve ment, and they agree to give full consideration to the wishes of the High Commissioner regarding the movements and disposition of the Irak army, and to provide such protection for aerodromes and land ing grounds as the High Commissioner, at the instance of the Air Officer Commanding, may require. The Irak Government shall not be entitled to assistance from His Britannic Majesty’s Govern ment as contemplated in article 8 should they fail to give effect to any recommendation of the High Commissioner regarding the movements and disposition of the Irak army given in virtue of this article. Article 8. The Irak army shall only be employed in the interests of Irak and the two Governments hereby agree that neither Government shall undertake any military operations for the maintenance of internal order or of the defence of Irak from external aggression without previous consultation and agreement with the other Govern ment. The Irak Government shall not be entitled to the assistance of any forces maintained or controlled by His Britannic Majesty’s Government against or for the suppression of any external aggres sion or any civil disturbance or armed rising, which shall, in the « opinion of the High Commissioner, have been provoked or occa sioned by action taken or policy pursued by the Irak Government contrary to the advice or express wishes of His Britannic Majesty’s , Government. Article 9. In the event of operations being undertaken in which forces main tained or controlled by His Britannic Majesty’s Government are to take part, the command of the combined forces shall, subject to any special arrangement which may be accepted by both parties, be vested in a British military commander selected for the purpose. [14020] EV, 30 Article 10. The Irak Government undertake to recognise and. if necessary, to secure by legislation or otherwise, the following powers and immunities for any armed forces maintained or controlled by His Britannic Majesty’s Government in Irak, such armed forces to be regarded as including civilian officials and Indian public followers attached to and inhabitants of Irak serving with the air and military forces :— ■ (a.) The right to require from the Irak Government such action according to law as may be necessary in the detection and arrest of persons accused of offences committed against such armed forces or any members thereof and to secure the trial of persons so accused. It is understood that the right to secure the trial of such accused persons shall include the right to secure their trial by a British Judge of the Irak Courts or by a Special Court composed of two British Judges of the Irak Courts and one Iraki Judge. Appeals either from the Ordinary Courts or from the Special Court shall lie to the Irak Court of Appeal, which shall in such cases have a majority of British Judges. Trial before the Special Court shall only take place in circumstances which are certified in writing by the High Commissioner and the Air Officer Commanding to be of such exceptional urgency or importance as to render trial by the Ordinary Courts undesirable. Such certificate may specify the date and place of assembly of the Court, in which event members of the Court shall proceed if necessary by air with such despatch as is needful for the Court to assemble at such date and place. (b.) The right to exercise over all members of the said forces the control and jurisdiction provided by the British, Indian or other military law, to which the members of such forces are subject. (c.) The right voluntarily to enlist inhabitants of Irak under the A rim and Air Force Acts or otherwise, it being understood that the Irak Government undertakes for its part when called upon by the Air Officer Commanding or any person authoiised by him in that behalf, to give all the assistance necessary to effect such enlistment and to remove as far as possible causes tending to prevent such enlistment. (d.) Immunity from arrest, search, imprisonment or trial by the ei\il power in Irak in respect of criminal offences for all emoiled and enlisted members of the said forces : provided that inhabitants of Irak being members of such forces shall be ordinarily subject to the jurisdiction of the Irak Courts and shall onl\ enjoy such immunity in respect of acts certi fied by the High Commissioner or the Air Officer Com manding to be done in the performance of military or other official duties. Nothing in this sub-clause shall prevent t e forcible detention by the civil power of anv member ofr v 31 the said forces who has just committed, or is in the act of committing an offence which involves danger to life. If the member so arrested is not an inhabitant of Irak, he shall be forthwith handed over to the Air Force or Military authorities. (e.) Immunity from civil process in respect of any act done or omission or default made in good faith by any member of such forces when acting in performance of his military or official duties; the certificate of the High Commissioner or Air Officer Commanding that an act or omission or default was done or made in good faith in performance of such duties to be conclusive. The immunity provided by this sub-clause shall not debar persons who have incurred material damage on account of the said acts or omissions or defaults from claiming compensation otherwise than by civil process. (/.) All such immunities and privileges in respect of civil process as are granted by the Air Force Act, the Army Act. and the Indian Army Act to persons subject to such Acts, and immunity from imprisonment on the order of a Civil Court in respect of any civil action tried by such court. Article 11. The Irak Government undertake to introduce legislation providing for the arrest and punishment of any person who is acting or con spiring in such a way as to endanger or obstruct the said armed forces or attempting or conspiring to cause mutiny or disaffection among the said forces, or to bring the said forces into hatred or contempt, and to take action according to law against any person who is certified by the High Commissioner to be to the best of his belief so acting, attempting or conspiring, and in the case of persons of other than Irak nationality so acting, attempting or conspiring or being likely so to act, attempt or conspire, to take such preventive steps according to law as the High Commissioner may consider desirable and practicable. Article 12. The Irak Government agree that, in the event of the said forces undertaking military operations in Irak for the purpose of assisting the Irak Government to repel external aggression or to suppress civil commotion, the King of Irak will, on the request of the High Com missioner, proclaim martial law in all such parts of Irak as may be affected by such aggression or commotion, and entrust its administra tion to the Air Officer Commanding or such other officer or officers as the Air Officer Commanding may appoint, and will further secure the passing of the necessary measure of indemnification for all acts done by the armed forces under martial law upon the subsequent re-establishment of civil government. Article 13. The Irak Government undertake to provide every facility for the movement of His Britannic Majesty’s forces (including the use of [14020] ’ E 2wireless telegraph and land-line telegraphic and telephonic services and the right to lay land-lines), and for the carriage and storage of fuel and supplies for such forces on the roads, railways and water ways and in the ports of Irak. Article 14. The Irak Government undertake to recognise and to secure licence or legislation the right of His Britannic Majesty’s forces to establish and work at the expense of His Britannic Majesty’s Government a system of wireless telegraphs for the transmission and reception of external and internal messages on British Government service. No payment either by way of charge or compensation for loss of traffic shall be made to the Irak Government in respect of such messages. His Britannic Majesty s Government undertake that no messages other than on British Government service shall be transmitted by the said system except by agreement with the Irak Government, which agreement shall provide for compensation for loss of such traffic by the Irak Government’s Department of Posts and Telegraphs unless such messages are transmitted at the request of the Irak Govern ment, in which case His Britannic Majesty’s Government shall be entitled to payment for the transmission of such messages. Any compensation which may be due to the Irak Government shall be in the form of a reduction of the debt due by the Irak Government in respect of the telegraph system transferred to it by His Britannic Majesty’s Government. Article 15. The Irak Government undertake at all times on the request of the High Commissioner so to restrict the working and method of trans mission of the wireless telegraph station at Basrah and so to define its wave-length as to obviate interference with British Government stations, and further undertake, in the event of an emergency arising, to hand over the said station on the request of the High Commissioner to His Britannic Majesty’s forces for the transmission ot messages on the service of His Britannic Majesty’s Government, subject to the payment of compensation for the loss of other traffic. urthermore, the Irak Government agree that the above under takings shall hold good notwithstanding the disposal of the wireless telegiaph station at Basrah by sale or otherwise and that, in the event of their deciding to discontinue the use of the station, three months ^ notice of such intention shall be given to His Britannic Majesty s Government, who shall be given an opportunity of taking over the station before dismantlement, and of operating it for the remainder of the period of the treaty. The terms of this article shall apply equally to anv other per- manent wireless telegraph installation which may be established by the Irak Government during the period of this agreementPrime Minister of the Irak Government. Tt?) 88 SCHEDULE. Programme of Expansion. 1924- 25.—1 Pack Battery. 2 Battalions Infantry. 1 Company Engineers. First Line Transport for all existing units. || Expansion of Bagdad Training Centre, including initiation of a Cadets’ College. 1925- 26.—Air Unit to be initiated as recommended by Air Head quarters, subject to satisfactory progress being made in the strength and efficiency of the local ground forces in Irak. 2 Pack Batteries. 1 Cavalry Regiment. 3 Infantry Battalions. 2 Transport Companies. 1 Field Ambulance. Ammunition Column. Formation of Infantry Training Depots. Formation of Artillery and Cavalry Depots. 1926- 27.—2 Field Batteries. 3 Infantry Battalions. 1 Company Engineers. 1 Skeleton Company Engineers. 1 Signal Company. 1 Field Ambulance. 1927- 28.—1 Field Battery. 1 Pack Battery. 3 Infantry Battalions. 2 Transport Companies. 1 Field Ambulance. In witness of which the respective plenipotentiaries have affixed their signatures thereto. Done at Bagdad in duplicate this 25th day of March, 1924, of the Christian era, corresponding with the 19th day of Sha‘ban, 1342, Hijrah. H. DOBBS, His Britannic Majesty’s High Commissioner for Irak. TATAR AL ‘ASKARI,34 No. 5. Judicial Agreement made under Article 9 of the Treaty of Alliance between Great Britain and Irak of October 10, 1922. Signed at Bagdad, March *25, 1924. \ [Ratifications exchanged at Bagdad, December 19, 1924.] We, the undersigned plenipotentiaries of His Britannic Majesty and of His Majesty the King of Irak respectively, having been duly authorised, met together this 25th day of March, 1924, corresponding to the 19th day of Sha'ban. 1342, in order to sign the following agree ment subsidiary to article 9 of the treaty of alliance concluded between Their Majesties aforesaid on the 10th day of October, 1922, corresponding to the 19th day of Sa‘far, 1341, Hijrah, subject to ratification. THE AGREEMENT. W hereas a treaty of alliance between His Britannic Majesty and His Majesty the King of Irak was signed at Bagdad on the 10th of October, 1922, corresponding with the 19th day of Sa‘far, 1341, Hijrah, and a protocol to the same treaty was signed at Bagdad on the 30th day of April, 1923, corresponding with the 14th day of Ramazan. 1341, Hijrah; and Whereas by article 9 of the said treaty His Majesty the King of Irak undertakes that he will accept and give effect to such reasonable provisions as His Britannic Majesty may consider necessary in judicial matters to safeguard the interests of foreigners in conse quence of the non-application of the immunities and privileges enjoyed by them under capitulation or usage, and that such pro visions shall be embodied in a separate agreement which shall be communicated to the Council of the League of Nations : Now therefore it is agreed as follows :— Article 1. The expression “foreigners” means the nationals of any Euro pean or American State which formerly benefited by capitulations in Turkey and did not renounce the same by an agreement signed before the 24th July, 1923, and of any Asiatic State which is now permanently represented on the Council of the League of Nations, and includes corporations constituted under the laws of such States, and leligious oi charitable bodies or institutions whollv or mainly composed of nationals of such States. Nothing in this article shall prevent the conclusion by His Majesty the King of Irak in agreement with His Britannic Majesty of a special convention with any State providing for the extension of the benefitsof this agreement to nationals and persons enjoying the protection of that State or for the non-application of this agreement to nationals of that State. Article 2. His Majesty the King of Irak undertakes to employ British legal experts in the Courts and to grant them judicial powers under the laws of Irak and that the procedure now observed in the Courts in Regard to the investigation of offences and the trial of cases and Either matters in which foreigners are concerned shall continue and be put into force by law, that is to say— {a.) That foreigners accused of an offence (other than a contra vention) which is within the jurisdiction of a Magistrate may claim to be tried by a British Magistrate. (b.) That foreigners accused of an offence which is beyond the jurisdiction of a Magistrate may claim that the interroga tion during the preliminary investigation shall be under taken and that the orders as to their release on bail and as to their committal for trial shall be made by a British Magistrate. (c.) That foreigners committed for trial may claim that their trial shall be held before a Court which includes at least one British Judge, who shall preside. (d.) That in civil actions over 750 rupees in value, foreigners who are parties to the cause may claim that the final judgment in a Court of First Instance shall be given, and that appeals or applications for revisions shall be heard by a Court pre sided over by a British Judge and composed so as to include one British Judge in a Court of three or less than three, two British Judges in a Court of four or five, and three British Judges in a Court of more than five. (e.) That in criminal cases foreigners may claim that their appeal or application for revision shall be heard by a Court pre sided over by a British Judge and composed as prescribed by the preceding .paragraph, or if all the parties joining in such appeal or application are foreigners and agree to that course, by a British Judge sitting alone. (/.) A foreigner who is a party to the proceedings and has not sufficient knowledge of Arabic to understand them may claim that all proceedings shall be translated in English and the Magistrate shall so order if he considers the claim to be well grounded. (&lt;/.) That in the towns of Bagdad and Basrah and their environs and in all other places where a British Judge or Magistrate having jurisdiction for that purpose is available the house of a foreigner shall not be entered by any judicial or administrative authority except on a warrant issued by a British Judge or Magistrate. Where no British Judge or Magistrate is available as above and in all cases where the police are by law allowed to enter houses with out search warrant, the house of a foreigner shall not be enteredPrime Minister of the Irak Government. 3G without a report of such entry being immediately made to the nearest British Judge or Magistrate. Article 3. His Majesty the King of Irak undertakes that every law affecting the jurisdiction, constitution or procedure of Courts or the appoint ment and discharge of Judges shall, before being presented to the legislature, be submitted in draft to the High Commissioner for views and advice on such of its provisions as concern the interest of foreigners. Article 4. In matters relating to the personal status of foreigners or in other matters of a civil and commercial nature in which it is customary by international usage to apply the law of another country, such law shall be applied in manner to be prescribed by law. Without pre judice to the provisions of any law relating to the jurisdiction of religious courts, or to such powers of Consuls in regard to the admin istration of estates of their nationals as may be recognised under agreements concluded by the Government of Irak, cases relating to the personal status of foreigners will be dealt with by the Civil Court, subject to the conditions of this agreement. In questions of marriage, divorce, maintenance, dowry, guardianship of infants and succession of movable property, the President of the Court hearing the case, or, in case of appeal or revision, the President of the Court of Appeal and Revision hearing the case, may invite the Consul or representa tive of the Consulate of the foreigner concerned to sit as an expert for the purpose of advising upon the personal law concerned. Article 5. • 11 is Majesty the King of Irak agrees to submit beforehand to the High Commissioner for his concurrence the appointment of all British Presidents and members of Courts of Appeal and Revision as well as the termination of the appointment of any British Judge or Magistrate. Article 6. I he provisions of this agreement shall remain in force for the period of the treaty and shall cease to have effect after the expiration of that period. In \\ itness of which the respective plenipotentiaries have affixed their signatures thereto. Done at Bagdad in duplicate this 25th day of March, 1924, of the Christian era, corresponding with the- 19th day of Sha'ban, 1342, Hijrah. H. DOBBS, His Britannic Majesty's High Commissioner for Irak. JATAR AL ‘ASKARI,37 No. 6. Financial Agreement made under Article 15 of the Treaty of Alliance between Great Britain and Irak of October 10, 1922. Signed at Bagdad, March 25, 1924. [Ratifications exchanged at Bagdad, December 19, 1924.] We, the undersigned plenipotentiaries of His Britannic Majesty aaid of His Majesty the King of Irak respectively, having been duly authorised, met together this 25th day of March, 1924, corresponding to the 19th day of Sha‘ban, 1342, in order to sign the following agree ment subsidiary to article 15 of the treaty of alliance concluded between Their Majesties aforesaid on the 10th day of October, 1922, corresponding to the 19th day of Sa'far, 1341, Hijrah, subject to ratification. THE AGREEMENT. Whereas a treaty of alliance between His Britannic Majesty and His Majesty the King of Irak was signed at Bagdad on the 10th day of October, 1922, corresponding with the 19th day of Sa‘far, 1341, Hijrah, and a protocol to the same treaty was signed at Bagdad on the 30th day of April, 1923, corresponding with the 14th day of Bamazan, 1341, Hijrah; and Whereas by article 15 of the said treaty it is provided that a separate agreement shall regulate the financial relations between the High Contracting Parties, which shall provide, on the one hand, for the transfer by His Britannic Majesty’s Government to the Govern ment of Irak of such works of public utility as may be agreed upon, and for the rendering by His Britannic Majesty’s Government of such financial assistance as may from time to time be considered necessary for Irak, and, on the other hand, for the progressive liqui dation by the Government of Irak of all liabilities thus incurred, and that such agreement shall be communicated to the Council of the League of Nations; and Whereas by article 4 of the same treaty His Majesty the King of Irak undertakes that he will fully consult the High Commissioner on what is conducive to a sound financial and fiscal policy, and will ensure the stability and good organisation of the finances of the Irak Government so long as that Government is under financial obligations to the Government of His Britannic Majesty; and Whereas by article 18 of the same treaty it is provided that nothing shall prevent the High Contracting Parties from reviewing from time to time the provisions of the separate agreement referred to above with a view to any revision which may seem desirable in theX 38 circumstances then existing, any modifications which may be agreed upon by the High Contracting Parties being communicated to the Council of the League of Nations : Now therefore it is agreed as follows :— Article 1. The two Governments hereby recognise the principle that the entire cost of the civil administration of Irak shall be borne on revenues, and that the Government of Irak shall, at the earliest possible date, accept full financial responsibility for the maintenance of internal order, and for the defence of Irak from external aggression. Article 2. Such financial assistance as may for a time be provided by the Go\ ernment of His Britannic Majesty shall take the form of the main tenance in Irak, at the expense of His Britannic Majesty’s Govern ment, of an Imperial garrison or of local forces controlled by His Britannic Majesty’s Government, but shall in no case take the form of a contribution by His Britannic Majesty’s Government to the cost of the Irak army or local forces maintained and controlled by the Government of Irak. Article 3. I he financial assistance to be provided for the aforesaid purposes shall be progressively reduced as His Britannic Majesty’s Govern ment may determine in each financial year, and shall ’in any case terminate within a period not exceeding four years from the date of the ratification of peace with Turkey. Article 4. I he Government of Irak undertake to devote not less than 25 per cent, of the revenues of Irak towards the cost of the defence and security of Irak. lor the purpose of this article the revenue of Irak shall be legalded as the gross receipts in all cases under each head of revenue service with the exception of the commercial services, other than Posts, Telegraphs and Telephones, of which the net revenues shall be included. Article 5. His Biitannic Majesty s Government agree to the transfer to the Government of Irak, and the Government of Irak agree to accept the transfer, of the undermentioned works of public utility at the valuation shown against each of the works specified : Irrigation Roads Bridges Posts, Telegraphs and Telephones Total ... Rs. • 62,12,040 3,20,000 11,17,500 17,60,000 94,09,54039 ' ? '3) Article 6. The Government of Irak accept the liability to repay to His Britannic Majesty’s Government the full value of the works specified in the preceding article, representing a total sum of Rs. 94,09,540. Article 7. The sum of Rs. 94,09,540 shall constitute a debt to be repaid by ^^ans of a terminable annuity, calculated so as to repay the capital sum, with interest at 5 per cent, per annum, within twenty years from the conclusion of this agreement. The Government of Irak further agree that, if from any cause the whole or part of the annuity payable in any year shall remain unpaid at the close of that year, the amount so outstanding shall be added to the total debt and converted into an annuity terminable within twenty years from the conclusion of this agreement, with interest at 5 per cent, per annum. The annuity payments required under this article shall be a first charge on the general revenues of Irak and no prior charge shall be set up without the consent of His Britannic Majesty’s Government. Article 8. His Britannic Majesty’s Government hereby transfer to the Government of Irak as from the 1st day of April. 1923, and for a period not exceeding four years from the ratification of the treaty of alliance, the management and administration of the Irak railway system, which shall remain the property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government, and the Government of Irak hereby accept the respon sibility for administering and managing the said system. So long as the railways are administered and managed by the Irak Government, all receipts of the Irak railways will be kept separate from the general revenues of Irak and will be used solely for meeting (a) current expen diture of the railway, and (5) in so far as there may be any surplus of receipts over such current expenditure, the cost of further capital works undertaken with the approval of the High Commissioner or the payment of interest on money borrowed for the purpose of such capital works. So long as the railways are administered or managed by the Government of Irak, His Britannic Majesty’s Government will do everything in their power to obtain for that Government any advice or assistance which they may require, the cost of such advice or assistance being charged as a part of the current expenses of the railways. His Britannic Majesty’s Government will not sell the railways to any private purchaser within the period of four years from the ratification of the treaty except with the concurrence of the Irak Government, which shall not be unreasonably withheld, and the Irak Government shall not within the same period lease the railways to any private lessee without the concurrence of His Britannic Majesty’s Government. In the event of the Government of Irak desiring within the said period to acquire the ownership of the railways, whether for the purpose of selling or leasing them to any private purchaser or lessee or otherwise, His Britannic Majesty’s Government shall state the terms upon which they will be preparedto transfer such ownership, and the transfer shall be made upon terms to be mutually agreed. In default of agreement as to such terms, the matter shall be referred to three arbitrators, of whom one shall be appointed by His Britannic Majesty’s Government and one by the Government of Irak. The third arbitrator shall be chosen by the other two arbitrators by agreement, or failing such agreement, by the President of the Permanent Court of International Justice. The arbitrators shall take into consideration the expenses incurpfi4 by His Britannic Majesty’s Government in the construction, equ\ ment and maintenance of the railways and the past, actual and pro spective value of the railways to the Government and people of Irak, and shall decide what payment ought to be made by the Government of Irak to His Britannic Majesty’s Government for the transfer of ownership, and in what manner and at what dates, having regard to the general financial resources and liabilities of Irak, such payment ought to be made. His Britannic Majesty’s Government and the Government of Irak undertake to accept and to give effect to the decision of the arbitrators. His Britannic Majesty's Government and the Government of Irak agree that on the expiry of the period of four years from the ratification of the treaty of alliance the ownership of the railway system shall in default of prior sale or transfer be forthwith trans ferred to the Irak Government on terms to be mutually agreed, or failing such agreement, to be decided by arbitration as hereinbefore provided. Article 9. The Government of Irak agree not to dispose by sale or in any other manner of any of the works specified in articles 5, 6, 7 and 8 without the prior consent of His Britannic Majesty’s Government, until such time as repayment of the value of all the said works has been completed. Should any of the said works be so disposed of with the concurrence of His Britannic Majesty’s Government, the out standing debt to His Britannic Majesty’s Government in respect of the work or works so disposed of shall simultaneously be liquidated by the Irak Government. The negotiations for such disposal shall be conducted by the High Commissioner and shall be subject to the approval of His Britannic Majesty’s Government. Article 10. His Britannic Majesty’s Government and the Government of Irak agree that the Port of Basrah shall be transferred to a Port Trust, and that the conditions of this transfer shall be dealt with separately and shall include the following :— 1. Port receipts and expenditure shall be excluded from Irak General Accounts, and a Port Trust shall he set up with the authority of the Irak Government, and subject to the approval of His Britannic Majesty’s Government, to administer the port. ‘2. The valuation of Its. 72.19,000 shall be treated as a debt of the Port Trust to His Britannic Majesty’s Government.0% 6$o) ° f f? % 41 The terms and conditions on which the Port Trust shall operate shall be subject to the approval of His Britannic Majesty’s Government, and shall be dealt with by separate arrangement in consultation with the Government of Irak, who hereby agree to facilitate the negotiations for the establishment of the Port Trust, and to secure the position in Irak of the said Port Trust by such legislation as may ^ be necessary. Article 11. 1. The Government of Irak agree that all lands and buildings, the property of the Irak Government now in the occupation of His Britannic Majesty’s Government for military and other purposes, shall remain in the undisturbed occupation of His Britannic Majesty’s Government until such time as they are no longer required : provided that after the termination of the Anglo-Irak Treaty and subject to the provisions of any further treaty or agreement which may be concluded in pursuance of the protocol to the said treaty, His Britannic Majesty’s Government shall not retain such land or buildings for a period longer than may be reasonably necessary for the sale or disposal of any buildings or works, the property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government, situate thereon. 2. The Irak Government agree to transfer to His Britannic Majesty’s Government, free of charge, waste Government land required for military and other purposes by His Britannic Majesty’s Government, and such land as well as the buildings thereon, or to be erected thereon, shall remain the property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government for so long as such land and buildings are required by His Britannic Majesty’s Government, provided that after the termination of the Anglo-Irak Treaty, and subject to the provisions of any .further treaty or agreement which mav be con cluded in pursuance of the protocol to the said treaty, His Britannic Majesty’s Government shall not require the transfer of any further waste Government land for military purposes, and shall not retain any such land already so transferred for military purposes for a period longer than may be reasonably necessary for the disposal of such land and the buildings thereon as provided in sub-clause 5 of this article. 8. Privately-owned land or buildings required at any time before the termination of the Anglo-Irak Treaty by His Britannic Majesty s Government for military and other purposes shall at the lequest of His Britannic Majesty’s Government be acquired or leased by the Irak Government under such Expropriation Law as may from time to time be in force, and the Irak Government shall receive the purchase price or rental from His Britannic Majesty s Government. The Irak Government agree to promulgate such legislation as may be necessary for the compulsory acquisition or leasing of any privately-owned land or buildings required by His Britannic Majesty’s Government for military and other purposes, and any such legislation shall, in the case of land compulsorily leased on behalf of His Britannic Majesty’s Government, empower HisBritannic Majesty’s Government on or before the expiration of such lease to remove any works or buildings erected on such land by His Britannic Majesty’s Government, and shall further provide that, where the land or building is to be acquired or leased on behalf of His Britannic Majesty’s Government, a representative of His Britannic Majesty’s Government to be selected by the High Com missioner shall serve in any Assessment Board constituted under such laws. As regards privately-owned land of which ownershi]^^ acquired under this sub-clause by His Britannic Majesty’s Govern ment for military purposes, the Irak Government shall have the right, at the termination of the treaty, to purchase by agreement or arbitration the land and the buildings thereon. As regards privately-owned land of which the leasehold is obtained under this sub-clause by His Britannic Majesty’s Government for military pur poses, the period of the lease shall be for the period of the treaty, but shall be extended after the termination of the treaty at the request of His Britannic Majesty’s Government for such time as may be reasonably necessary to enable His Britannic Majesty’s Govern ment to dispose of the buildings thereon, 4, The Irak Government shall place no obstacle in the way of His Britannic Majesty’s Government purchasing by agreement privately-owned land or buildings, 5. His Britannic Majesty’s Government shall have full power to sell land acquired by them prior to the conclusion of this agreement, and to be acquired under paragraphs 3 and 4 of this article, together with the buildings thereon, and to appropriate for their own use the proceeds of such sale, if at any time such land is no longer required by His Britannic Majesty’s Government. His Britannic Majesty’s Government shall have full power to dispose of land, together with the buildings thereon, transferred to them under paragraph 2 of this article, subject to payment to the Government of Irak of the sale or rental value of the site, such value to be determined, where possible, by reference to the market value of similar land in the neighbourhood or by agreement between the two Governments. Article 12. The Irak Government undertake that, notwithstanding the termination of the treaty of alliance, the financial obligations accepted by them in articles 5—11 of this agreement shall continue in force until repayment of all sums due by them to His Britannic Majesty’s Government under this agreement has been completed, and shall be faithfully fulfilled. They further agree that until the completion of such repayment no prior charge on the general revenues of Irak shall be created in order to secure a loan or for any similar purpose without the prior consent of His Britannic Majesty’s Government. Such consent shall not be withheld if His Britannic Majesty’s Government are satisfied that the object for which such prior charge is to be created is one which will tend to secure the sound financial development of Irak, and will not impair the capacity of the Irak Government to discharge their liabilities to His Britannic Majesty’s Government.43 CiD Article 13. The ordinary expenses of civil government and administration and the salaries and expenses of the High Commissioner and his staff will be borne entirely by the Government of Irak. His Britannic Majesty’s Government will invite Parliament to make a contribution amounting to half of the expenditure approved by the Secretary of Sftate upon salaries and other expenses of the High Commissioner and staff. The Government of Irak will provide quarters for the accommodation of members of the staff of the High Commissioner subject to the payment of reasonable rent by the officers concerned. Article 14. 1. The Government of Irak agree that the following articles shall be exempt from customs duties on import or export:— (a.) All articles for the personal use of the High Commissioner. (b.) All articles for the official use of the High Commissioner and his staff and of the Imperial and other forces or services maintained in Irak at the expense of His Britannic Majesty’s Government, all articles imported by or con signed to the Navy, Army and Air Force Institute or any other official canteen for His Britannic Majesty’s forces, and all personal effects introduced on arrival in Irak by members of the High Commissioner’s staff and of such forces or services : provided that if any articles imported or introduced under this exemption are disposed of to other parties than those entitled to this exemption, the customs duty then in force shall be paid by the person, service, force or institute making such disposal. (c.) All imported articles addressed to individual members or recognised messes of His Britannic Majesty’s forces on production of a certificate that they are for the use of the individual or mess concerned. (d.) All articles exported by members of His Britannic Majesty’s forces on production of a certificate that they are not exported for sale. 2. Duty shall be paid on all articles not imported directly by the authorities, forces and services detailed above, but the Irak Govern ment agree to grant a rebate of the duty so paid on production of a certificate from a competent authority that the articles on which duty has been paid have been delivered to and received for the official use of the High Commissioner and his staff and of the Imperial and other forces maintained in Irak at the expense of His Britannic Majesty’s Government. Article 15. The Government of Irak agree not to levy any tax on the forces or services of His Britannic Majesty’s* Government in respect of offices, buildings, land or premises occupied by such forces or services for official purposes.Article 16. The Government of Irak undertake to provide for the due pay ment of all sums which may be payable to officials of British nationality in the employment of the Irak Government in accordance with the provisions of the terms of the contracts of those officials, and this undertaking shall continue in force during the continuance and on the termination of such contracts. Article 17. The Government of Irak recognise their liability to meet as they fall due all sums or charges in respect of the Ottoman Public Debt which may be assigned to the Government of Irak under the Treaty of Peace with Turkey. Article 18. The forces and services of His Britannic Majesty’s Government, including the Navy, Army and Air Force Institute or any other official canteen of His Britannic Majesty’s forces, shall pay at most-favoured rates for all services rendered by Departments of the Irak Govern ment. Article 19. His Britannic Majesty’s Government agree to contribute towards the cost of upkeep and maintenance of roads and bridges used for traffic by His Britannic Majesty’s forces. The expenses incurred by His Britannic Majesty’s Government on public roads and bridges shall be taken into account in assessing such contribution. In witness of which the respective plenipotentiaries have affixed their signatures thereto. Done at Bagdad in duplicate this 25th day of March, 1924, of the Christian era, corresponding with the 19th day of Sha'ban, 1342, Hijrah. H. DOBBS, His Britannic Majesty's High Commissioner for Irak. TATAR AL ‘ASKARI, Prime Minister of the Irak Government.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000602.0x0001ad_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/2886</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000602.0x0001ad</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/2886</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 17/24 ‘Iraq. Internal. New Iraqi Income Tax Law. Effect on British aircraft and shipping.’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1930/1935</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-09-12T22:48:43</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">fre</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (182 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the inside front cover with 1, and terminates at the last folio with 182; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 2-182; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains papers mostly relating to the following: the objections of HM Government to Article 6 of the draft Iraq Salaries and Allowances Tax Law of 1930; and the liability of British aircraft and shipping companies operating in Iraq to income tax under Article 29 of the Iraq Income Tax Third Amendment Law of 1933 (these papers mainly concern shipping companies).The file also includes papers relating to matters including: the right of the Euphrates Tigris Steam Navigation Company to navigate the rivers Tigris and Euphrates; alleged excessive freight rates on Iraqi exports; and the status of the Mesopotamia Persia Corporation Limited.The papers largely consist of India Office minute papers, and correspondence and copy correspondence between the following: the India Office and the Colonial Office; the Foreign Office and the Colonial Office; the High Commissioner for Iraq and the Secretary of State for the Colonies; and HM Ambassador to Iraq (HM Representative at Baghdad) (with enclosures) and the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs.The file includes three documents in French: copies of Vizierial letters of 2 April 1846 and 20 June 1862, and a copy of a firman issued on 29 December 1834.The file includes a divider, which gives a list of correspondence references contained in the file by year. This is placed at the back of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Shipping companies</topic></subject><subject><topic>Taxation legislation</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Colonial Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>High Commissioner, Iraq</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Euphrates and Tigris Steam Navigation Company</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Mesopotamia Persia Corporation Limited</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Ambassador to Iraq</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Tigris River</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Euphrates River</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Taxation</topic></subject><subject><topic>Civil aircraft</topic></subject><subject><topic>Income tax</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000602.0x0001ad#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>