<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000466.0x00023d_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-20T02:59:49.408Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">DEPARTMENT OF COMMERCE. GOVERNMENT OP INDIA. No.o06-i;.II (15)/37. -imla, Uhe 2Vth July 1937. from J ttd auhib A.H.Puri, B.A., LL.E., ?[ AaaiBtant Becrat&amp;ry to the dove: To Tho /lag Officer CoBinanding, Royal Indian Nary, Bombay* Subject:- Set&amp;bliabsent of a li^it on Kubber Island* Sir, reference to the oorreepondence ending «ith your letter No. rG/£120 # dated the Bth June 19^7 9 on the above subject, I am directed to oonvey the sanction of the Central Governm ent to the establialiment of a li^it on rubber V Island in the Persian Gulf at an estioated initial cost of fe. 9,13d/* (Rupees nine thousand, one hundred and thirty four) and a recurring cost of approximately fe* 2,050/- (Rupees two thousand and fifty) per annum. 2. The Central Government agree that if a spare flasher of the same type and burner capacity as the original one can be obtained from the Basra Bart Directorate*s stock, it need not be purchased for the light on Kubber Island. It may, however, be observed that there it no likelihood of a •pare flasher deteriorating if original and spare are both ueed alternately to keep them in working order, as is customary in such cases* A 3* 1 to add that in his letter No* 2/ » dated the 2nd July 1935, the Port Director, Basra, stated that the range of the proposed lig$it would be 12 miles in olear weather with the height of observer at 30 feet* is Commerce.the usual practice xa to calculate the range with the height of observer at 15 feet, the range of the proposed li^it would work out to 10«5 miles, but should be advertised as 10 miles* I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, A.N.Puri. Assistant Secretary to the Government of India. SSL,Copy of a letter No. PG/2120, dated the 8th June 1937, from the Flag Officer Commanding, Royal Indian Navy, Bombay, to the Secretary to the Grovemment of India, Depart ment of Commerce, Simla. Subjects- Establishment of a li^it on Rubber Island. With reference to Commerce Department letter No.6-P&amp;L(18)/ 36,of 8th January 1937, I have the honour to state that a very definite majority of Shipping Companies are in favour of the establishment of the ligjat. 2. Taking into consideration thc.t the ships of four large Companies regularly trade to Kuwait, that the port is frequently used by H.M. Ships, and that there is every indication of an increase in shipping owing to the advent of oil, the Port Director, Basra, is definitely of opinion that ar light should be established on Rubber Island. I entirely agree with this view. 3. As regards para. 2 of the Comnerce Department letter under reference, I do not consider that a spare flasher for Rubber Island Beacon will be necessary. The flasher should be serviceable for, at least, 7 years and a spare one would deteriorate if kept in stores unused. In the event of a total breakdown, or during periodical overhauls, a spare flasher can be issued on loan from the Basra Port Directorate’s stock as is now done in the case of the Muscat li$it.* Co Py of a No. 6-P&amp;L (18)/36, dated the 8t 1937, from the Asaiatant Secretary to the Government of Department of Commerce. New Delhi, to the Flag Officer Royal Indian Navy, Bomoay. Subject:• Establishment of a light at Kubber Island. Yith reference to your letter No.PG/3970, dated the 24th November 1936, on the above subject, I am directed to say that the Government of India observe that although the proposal to establish a li^it at Kubber Island, in the approaches to Kuwait, is supported by a majority of the members of the various shipping concerns, it does not find favour with Messrs. Mackinnon Mackenzie and Company, whose ships f/ftwi the bulk of tonnage entering and leaving Kuwait annually. The Port Director, Basrah, is also extremely doubtful whether the amount of shipping justifies the installation of the light at present. In these circumstances the Government of India feel unable to sanction the proposal on the information available and would be glad to know whether you have any special reasons for recommending the establishment of the light in spite of the opposition of Messrs. Mackinnon Mackenzie and Company and the Port Director, Basrah. 2. In this connection I an also to say that the Engineer - in-Chief, Li^ithouse Department, observes that only the^flasner has been allo.ved for in the estimate of the cost of the proposed light and suggests that in order to prevent any prolonged stoppage of the light during repairs and/ or overhauls a spare flasher should be provided. I am accordingly to request that this point also may be examined and a revised estimate submitted to the Government of India, if necessary. h January India. Commanding,Copy of a letter No* PG/3970, dated the 24th November 195^, from the Flag Officer Commanding, Royal Indian Navy, Bombay, to the Secretary to the Government cf India, Commerce Department, New Delhi* Subject:- Establishment of a light at Kubber Island* I have the honour to forward for the consideration of the Commerce Department a copy of letter No*2/5202/306, dated 2nd July 1935 from the Port Siewxrcre, Busra, on the above subject* The proposal was placed before the Advisory Committee at its meeting held on 10th December 1935 and it was resolved that it should be circulated to the Members to enable them to ascertain the views of the concerns they represented* Replies received from the Members axe forwarded herewith.lt will be seen therefrom that the majority of the Members are in favour of the establishment of a lig^it at Kubber Island.r No.2 Headquarters, Port Directorate, Basrah, ’Iraq* Date 2nd July 19o5* The Flag Officer Conmanding, Royal Indian Naiy, Bombay* Sir, I have the honour to forward herewith for your information a copy of a letter received from the ikster of Messrs. F.C.Strick &amp; Go's s.s. 'Grorjistan' with reference to the establishment of a light on Kubber Island* There is no doubt that a light established on this island, as suggested by the master, would be of valuable assistance to vessels making the Port of Kuwait at night, but I am extremely doubtful whether the amount of shipping justifies it* I suggest that the views of the Shipping Companies be obtained in this connection. The coat of this li^it would be approximately fc*9134/- making up as follows, excluding maintenance charges, which would amount to approximately fe* 2050/- per annum including hire of the Li^it Tender. (a) One i\o*LVFA*500 M/M lantern fitted for Sunvalve Control, 360° Dioptric lens and KLS 130 flasher (2 x 2o) 50 litre cluster burner set to 0*5 plus 4.5 equal to 5 (1/10). £ 1 ho#Vs • 10 type Sunvalve. 6 Nos. fully charged A.50 type D.A. Gas Cylinders. 1 No. fiveway coupling block with type Vt-90 Stop valve and pressure gpuge. 3 Nos. type F.490 Cylinder clamps for a*50 Cylinders. 3 Nos* Accumulator pads for A.50 cylinders. 40 feet 8 a/m copper covered steel tubing. 10 Nos. F.10 unions. £• . 215- 0-0 25- 0-0 200 - 0-0 3“ 0»0 1 - 2-6 0-16 -0 4-13 *4 460-17 $ With insurance and shipping charges say £471-0-0 qy Rs. 6280—0—0m 5 ® Brou^it forward Rs # 6280-0-0 Making cement concrete block base o^xB 1 top 6'j&amp;' and height 3 ft. Iron work for structuro (15 feet ni^hj. Holding down bolts. Add for oontingencfcs . Rs. 319-0-0 205-0-0 SQr&amp;sS, fe. 554-0-0 fe* 5.Q~ftiQ Hire of Li^it Tender 3 days for con veyance am attendance during erection. Total. • • • • 604-0-0 2260-0-0 St, 9134-0-0 Maintenance Charges of light per annum as follows: Recharging 0 Nos. D.A. Gas cylinders 0 &amp;♦ 5u/-'each. Rs, 400-0-0 Paints, burners, etc. 150-0-0 Hire of light Tender 2 days. 1500-0-0 The height of Ka^ber Island above H.W. 8 ft. Height of concrete Plinth. 3 ft. Height i 1 * 011 structure from base to burner. 16 ft. Height of light above H.W. Height of observer say 30 feet. 27 fast 2050-0-0 This will give the li^at a range of approximately 12 miles in clear weather.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000466.0x00023d_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/234</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000466.0x00023d</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/234</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>PZ 5547/37 'Persian Gulf:– Establishment of a Light on Kubber Island'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1937/1937</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-09-29T19:55:16</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (7 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 9; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 2-8; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file consists of correspondence concerning the establishment of a light for shipping on Kubber Island [Jazīrat Kubbar]. The material is predominantly copy correspondence dating from 2 July 1935 to 8 June 1937.Correspondents include: the Port Director and Director General of Navigation, Basrah; the Government of India; and the Flag Officer Commanding, Royal Indian Navy, Bombay.The file includes a divider, which gives a list of correspondence references contained in the file by year. This is placed at the back of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><geographic>Kubber Island</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Lights</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of India</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Indian Navy, Commander-in-Chief</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Port Director and Director-General of Navigation, Basra</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Shipping</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000466.0x00023d#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>