<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000555.0x0002eb_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-20T08:30:54.966Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">' tv :- dr . f * -COPY (E 7464/6386/34) No. 641/9/36 . Dear Department, British Legation, Tehran. 13th November, 1936. f l r'&gt; r~ r ^ 'LJ f i- } v&gt; / Your despatch No. 442 (E 6654/6386/34) of the 29th October enclosing a copy of the Senior Naval Officer’s report to us of the refusal of an Iranian Amnieh N.C.O. to obey the regulations of the British India Company when a passenger in their S.S. Bankura. 2 # This incident was mentioned orally to Ansarie Head of our Department at the Ministry of Foreign Affairs, on the 23rd October. He was asked to try to get the Ministry of War to ensure that all subordinates were told that the Company’s regulations in such matters must be observed. He agreed that the regulations were reasonable, and said that he would take the matter up with the Ministry of War. We hope that there will be no repetition of the refusal to give up arms. Yours &amp;c., Chancery. The Eastern Department, The Foreign Office, London, S.W.l.ANY FURTHER COMMUNICATION BHOUtO BE ADDRESSED TO- THE BECRITABY OF THE ADMIRALTY LONDON. 8.W.I. A THE FOLLOWING LETTER A NUMBER SHOULD HE QUOTED:- M.04808/36. TELEPHONE NUMBERI- iT EHAU 9000. ^ . Admiralty, London, S.W.i. ^ 36. FORM A. SECRET. Sir, I a^i commanded 'by My Lords Commissioners of the Admiralty to transmit, for the information of the Secretary of State for India in Council, a copy of a report from the Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, concerning the conduct of certain Iranian passengers in the s.s. BANKURA. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, The Under Secretary of State, INDIA OFFICE, S.W.I. HPJ, © Subject ... e.s. BANKURA - Conduct of certain Iranian Passengers. Prom The Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, H.M.S. SHOREHAM at Bahrain. Date Path September, 1936. No.506/1. To His Britannic Majesty’s Minister, Tehran. Copy to:-i The 'CSmr^Bnde^r-in-Chief, East Indies. • ! (No ^10/506) f / ‘W* ; / The attached report from H.M.S. BIDEPORD regarding the conduct of certain Iranian passengers in s.s. BANKURA, is forwarded for such action as you consider necessary. (Sgd.) V.S. BUTLER. CAPTAIN. SENIOR NAVAL OFFICER, PERSIAN GULF. The Commaander-in-Chief, East Indies. ) Stamp. 6 Oct., 1936. ) •iSECRET. Prom ... The Commanding Officer, H.M.S. BIDEFORD at Khor Kuwai. Date ... 24th September, 1936. No.2676/7. To The Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf. S.S. BANKURA - MISBEHAVIOUR OP IRANIAN PASSENGERS. When we intercepted the s.s. BANKURA for mails and provisions off the Quoins on her way to Bunder Abbas from Muscat on 24th September, 1936, the Master (Captain John W. Milne) came on board and reported to me in the following sense. 2. While at Charbar on 2Pnd September on his present run the following were among the Iranian passengers who embarked there for Bunder Abbas Mahomed Dorrani Gurbani, Corporal, Persian Road Police. Mohamed Reza, Private ,, ,, ,, Mohamed All , Private, ,, ,, ,, who had in their custody, two prisoners accused of theft. 3. The Corporal stated he was going to take the prisoners to Teheran. 4. These police were all armed with rifles, and it was ascertained that these were loaded. 6. In accordance with the British India Steam Navigation Company’s orders the Chief Officer requested the Corporal to hand over his firearms for custody while on board, and told him they would be restored before the party landed at Bunder Abbas. The Corporal refused to do this. 6. The Chief Officer then brought the Corporal before the Master, who personally ordered him to hand over the rifles for custody. The Corporal again refused, saying that he would only surrender his arms if ordered to do so by one of hie own officers. 7. The ship had already left Charbar for Muscat. At Muscat the British Consul was in recess, and there was no Iranian Consul, but the B.I. Agent there again explained to these pdicemen that they should give up their rifles in accordance with the Company’s regulations. This had no effect.8. So at the time when the Master reoorted to me the Iranian Police in hie ship were still walking about with loaded rifles in defiance of his orders. 9. The Master stated he did not want to risk a brawl by- ordering his own officers and men to disarm these policemen. As the Master said he anticipated no trouble whatever from the policemen if left to themselves, I decided not to send over an armed party to disarm them, and the Master preferred that no action of this kind should be taken. 10. The Master’s object in making the report is to have the Iranian authorities’ attention drawn to this flagrant act on the part of their officials in order that it may not be repeated. 11. The Master also informed me that he considers it most humiliating that he should be defied like this, especially as the Iranian Authorities are continually harassing the B.I. Mail Steamers with petty regulations and fining the Masters for disregard of Regulations which have never been published. 12. I told the Master that I would report the matter through Service channels together with his request that some action may be taken with the Iranian Government to prevent a repetition. (Signed) DOUGLAS FISHER. CAPTAIN. Senior Naval Persian 25 Officer, Gulf Division. Sep., 1936. ) Stamp. )■MM ' ^ MSSSAGE. To : Tehran Repeated to S.N.O Kerman. SECRET. » From : Britconaul, Buahire. (63/704). Addressed to Tehran, Repeated to S.N.O., Kerman. Master B.I.S.N. Cos. BANKURA informs me that Iranian non commissioned officer and two soldiers escort to two prisoners refused to give their arms into his charge on coming on hoard in accordance with regulations of Company, which are ordinarily observed. They embarked at Charbar and disembarked Bander Abbas. 2. At Muscat Master consulted the Captain of H.M.S. BIDEFORD but they decided that case did not necessitate disarming by naval party. I understand Captain of H.M.S. BIDEFORD is reporting to Senior Naval Officer. 3. Corporal’s attitude was that he had no orders from hie officer and case may, I gather, be regarded as merely obtuseness on his part. 4. At the same time subject to S.N.O. I would suggest that Iranian Government might be asked to warn the military authorities to see that in such cases subordinates observe Company’s Regulations, as it is undesirable that authority of Master of Ship especially in places like the Persian Gulf should be so slighted. T.O.R. 1730/5th Oct.36. (63/704). P.R.P.G.0 \ PS. iVi kJ O Cr bhCELT. Fr ; )o:- C. in G. Lnst Indies. [ IN. Date:- 7 . 10 . 36 . Heed:- 1415 . J Naval Cypner (u). addressed A(jLiiralty ? I'epetited S .N* 0 .Persian Gulf. 930. H.ivi. S.IIDLFOIiD intercepted British Ship Bankura on (? 24th September) off Quoins. Master reported one corporal and two privates Persian Road police had embarked at ^harbnr witn two prisoners hound for Bunder xihas. Police had loaded rifles which they refase to deliver up despite orders of master and request of British Indian Agent Muscat. At request of the master no action was taken to disarm these men. Master asked that attention of Iranian authorities should he drawn to the flagrant breach of orders on the part of their officials. Minister Teheran has been informed. Full report follows by air mail. 1146/7/10. Note:- D e layed for repetition of corrupt groups. 1st Lord. J o &gt; • J . r.a Or J.l . a r S c T, 4tit d . I. D.C.N.S. a.C.N.G. Civil J. rrd pari .G^c• Secretary. Naval SeC. P.A..S. (S) O.D.2. D. N. 1.2. D. of p .‘I 1 el egre 11 Sn Cla i r From Director, Persian Gulf Division, Karachi Political Resident, Bushire. To Dn ted P/149/2302. 21st (Received 22nd) July 1930. Report for week ending 19th instant® Reference last week f s report* It is not true that L ir Rbdi son of Din Uohamed is captured. Tlie Officer Gommanding Troops at Charter has just returned from Dashtyari District v/ith 200 rifles which he has collected from Din Hohamed 1 s tribes men. The fact that the Persian strength in Dashtyari District is only 60 men at Charbar and 6 at ^wetter :l shows that Baluchi opposition is not a serious factor and that the Persian authority is well established. Kir Burke t and Ilurad son of Ilustafe Khan, when proceed ing to Ghoshki, were fired on by a Tahrzai village. This led to fighting in which 14 men of Taharzais were killed and 4 .killed and 4 wounded on the other side. It is reported that Kir Burkat is taking action against the Tab^rzais. The area ITorth and West of Jask is more disturbed and the Persians do not appear to have In the Jask District Abdullah Khan son of much authority therei s AVSmn COCTID^TIAL^ No* 311-3 of 1930. i n c, Forwarded to tlie Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, for information, with reference to this office endorsement No* 259-S*, dated the 21st June 1930. By order. Sd/- J* Groning, for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Bushirei The 2nd July 1930. Subject;- Arrest of Din Mohammed of Dashtyari. Telegram No. P. 149/229, dated 1st July 1930, from the Director, Persian Gulf Section, Indo-European Telegraph Department, Karachi*Telegram D. T. From D. P* Gr. Karachi♦ To Political Resident, Bushire* No* P. 149/229. Dated 1st reed* 2nd July 1930. Report for week ending 28th instant. Mir Din Mohamed^ tribesmen are still at Pulan under his son Mir Abdi, About 25 rifles have been brought in by Dilawar Khana cousin of Din Mohamed. It is said that the Persians offered to release Din Mohamed provided Dashtyari district is completely disarmed and all rifles handed in. Din Mohamed # s family has taken refuge at Gwadur with the concurrence of the Muscat Authorities. D. P. G.2 Jo. 259-S of 1930. 29jul 1930 Forwarded to the Government of India in the* Foreign and Political Depart.ient, for infor mation. 2. Copies of the enclosures are being sent to His -&gt; -- Majesty’s Minister at Tehran. - —\ ’ . \ t, o ' 7 Q ' 0 ,_J By order, Sd/- J.Cronning, for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Bushires The 21st June 1930. Subject;- Arrest and proposed despatch of Din Mohammed of Dashtyari in British India ship from Charbar to Bushire. List of Papers. 1 . Telegram dated 16th June 1930 from Director, Persian Gulf Section, Indo-European Telegraph Department, Karachi• 2. Telegram No. 617 dated 17th June 1930 to ditto (with copy of letter No. 14535/28 dated the 11th (S.202/202/34) January 1929 f from the Foreign Office). 3. Telegram No. P.149/2295 from Director, Indo European Telegra^Department to assistant Political Officer, Panjgur, dated 19th June 1930. 4. Extract from D.T. from Clerk-in-Charge, Charbar, to Clerk-in-Charge , Bushire, dated 21st June 1930. enclosure IN INDIA. FOREIGN SECRETARY’S Letter No S.3 M. Bat lit JUL.1930 Re0 28 JUL1930Telegram I.W.C. (X.T.) ^rom D.P.G, Karachi To Political Resident, Bushire Words 108 « Dated and received 16th June 1930* Charbar reports that Din Mohamed and his relatives have been arrested by the Persians and are prisoners in Charbar fort. Clerk in Charge states definitely that Persians intend to embark Din Mohamed for Bushire forcibly in s.s. 'Barjora” due Charbar 11 a.m. to norrow Tuesday morning. Charbar is in Quarantine and only mails are dropped on upward journey. There is no embargo on booking passengers at Charbar for other Persian Ports. Clerk in Charge Charbar expects Baluchis will resist and will cut our telegraph lines if Din Mohamed is embarked on British ship and suggests that Barjora proceed straight to Muscat and drop mails there. I do not attach great importance to this threat. British India Steam Navigation Agents do not wish to offend Persians but will order Barjora proceed to Muscat Direct if orders are received from Government. I do not consider that any special action is necessary but would be glad of your views as to embarkation of Persian Military prisoners on British snig) which will call at intermediate port of Muscat. Din Mohamed has always been very friendly with the British Government and has much assisted this department. D.P.GTelegram i’rom I. W.C Political Resident c/o A.S. Bushire. To D.P.G. Karachi. No. 617 Dated 17th June 1930• Immedia te. Your 108 of 16th June. Board of Trade advised Chamber of Shipping of United Kingdom that British Shipping Companies should be advised not to accept on board any Persian Guard with prisoners as passengers and that when armed Persian soldiers are embarked they should be deprived of their arms and ammunition while on board as passengers. Please communicate this privately to Clerk in Charge, Charbar, v/ho will bring the matter to the notice of Captain of mail steamer. Resident c/o ^.Smm Copy, (K. 202 / 202 / 34 ) M. 14535 / 28 . Foreign Office, 11 th January, 1929 to in/r ijrom you Sir, I am directed by the Board of Trade that their attention has beer: drawn to the fact that, at the request of the Persian Government, certain British ships in the Persian Gulf carry armed troops guarding prisoners from one Persian port to another. The Senior Naval Officer of the Persian Gulf Division has recommended that British Shipping Companies should be advised not to accept on board their ships any Persian guard with prisoners as passen gers, and that when armed Persian soldiers, or any other individuals with arms are embarked, they should be deprived of their arms and ammunition while on board as passengers. I am to request that you will bring this to the notice of the Shipping Companies principally concerned. I am, etc, Sd/- G.B.Baker. T e General Manager, Chamber of Shipping of the United Kingdom, 28 , St. Ma ry Axe , B • C • o #Telegram D.T. From D.P.G. , Karachi. To Assistant Political Officer, Panjgur. Repeated Political Resident, Bushire. ITo. P-149/229 5. Bated 19th (received 20th) June 1930. as result of arrest by Persians of Sirdar Bin Mohammed of Bashtiari it is reported that his tribesmen are collecting and intend crossing into British territory probably near Saman Kaur. Further information will be supplied if and when possible. B. p. G.Extract from D.T. Prom Clerk in Charge Ch&amp;rbctr to Clerk in Charge Bushire dated 21 st June 1930* xxx x x x x Prom information I have been able to collect it appears they are going to keep him here until he collects all the a-rms in Dashtyiari and pays his debts after that he will most probably be sent to Teheran. x x x x x</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000555.0x0002eb_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/2209</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000555.0x0002eb</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/2209</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 7/40 'Persia: carrying of arms by Persian authorities while escorting prisoners on British boats'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1930/1936</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-09-27T22:52:10</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (23 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in rough chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 23; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Correspondence regarding British India Steamship Navigation Company regulations that armed Persian [Iranian] Officers should give up their weapons when transporting prisoners on vessels flying the British flag.The correspondence dated 1930 concerns the arrest of Sirdar Din Mohamed of Dashtyari [Dashtīārī], and his transport from Charbar [Chabahar] to Bushire [Bandar Būshehr], escorted by armed officers. It includes details of attempts by the Persian Government to disarm the tribes in Dashtyari, and British concerns that Baluchi tribes would destroy local telegraph lines in retaliation. The file contains communications received from the Board of Trade, the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, the Senior Naval Officer Commanding in the Persian Gulf, and the Director of the Persian Gulf Section of the Indo-European Telegraph Department.The correspondence dated 1936 concerns an incident where Persian Road Police escorting prisoners from Charbar to Bunder Abas [Bandar Abbas] refused repeated instructions that they give up their weapons and ammunition to the ship's crew. The Commanding Officer of the HMS
                           Bidefordsubmits a formal complaint to the Persian authorities.The file includes a divider which gives a list of correspondence references contained in the file by year. This is found at the end of the correspondence (folio 2).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Transportation of prisoners</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Senior Naval Officer in the Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Indo-European Telegraph Department, Persian Gulf Section, Director</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Persia</geographic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000555.0x0002eb#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>