<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000884.0x0001b7_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T12:57:32.002Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">SECRET. m t PERSIAN GULF GAZETTEER. PART 1. w- HISTORICAL AND POLITICAL MATERIALS. PRECIS ON ARMS TRADE IN THE PERSIAN GULF,SECRET, 4 PERSIAN GULF GAZETTEER. PART I. HISTORICAL AND POLITICAL MATERIALS. .-.J , PRECIS ON ARMS TRADE IN THE PERSIAN GULF.1 CONTENTS. 9—10 u 12 l 2 Paragraphs. Questions affecting the Arms Trade, 1883—1887 ... ... 1—3 Amendment of the Indian Arms Act, XI of 1878 ... ... 4 _8 Suspected trade in Arms between Bander Abbas and the Frontier otcLt6S| looo • • • ### The Traffic in arms on the Mekran Coast, 1890 Prohibition by the Sultan of Maskat of the arms trade at Gwadur, 9* ••• ••• ,,, Application by the Bombay Government for a license to tranship cartridges, 1892 ... ^ 1 Representation by the Consul-General at Zanzibar regarding the arms trade with Maskat, 1892 ... 14 ^ The possibility of checking the arms traffic discussed, 1892 ... 16—18 Importations to Maskat from Zanzibar, 1892 ... ... jg License issued by the Bombay Government for the export of certain arms to Baghdad, 1891. Issue of a notification for future guidance ... Seizure of Arms at Bushire by the Persian authorities. The British Kesident asked to interfere, 1893 Reported large consignments of arms for the Sultan of Maskat and the Chief of Abuthabi, 1893. Measures taken to prevent tran shipment at Bombay The trade in arms at Maskat. Representations by the Persian (jovernment that arms for Oman should not go vid Persian Ports i8 95 ... ... ... ' 20 21—22 23 29 30 3» The Bombay Government grant a license for shipment of percussion caps to Bushire, 1895 ... ... ... ... 2 5 Major Sadler's report on the Maskat arms traffic, 1886 ... 27 Arms traffic at Maskat, 1896 ... ... t 2 g The Commissioner in Sind authorised to issue export licenses, 1896 The ultimate destination of arms shipped to the Persian Gulf dis cussed. Measures for the suppression of the trade, 1897 The Sultan of Maskat requests sanction to an increase of 2| per cent, on the import duties on arms and ammunition, 1897 The Secretary of State enquires regarding the importation of arms into Afghanistan, 1897 ... ... Examination of surrendered arms on the North-West Frontier. 18 ,8 Arms trade in Bahrein. Agreement with the Sheikh for the suppres sion of the trade, 1898 ... ... &gt; 35 (i) The Sultan of Maskat joins the British and Persian Governments in the endeavour to put a stop to the arms trade ... ... • (J) Seizure of the S. S. Baluchistan in Maskat territorial waters I '9' ... ... Decision of the Sultan's Court regarding the legality of the seizure of arms on the S. S. Baluchistan, 1898 24—25 32—33 34 36 ... 37 The arms traffic in the Persian Gulf previous to the seizure of the o. o. naluchistan reviewed, 1898 . Claim for compensation by the Sultan of Maskat on account of alleged losses sustained by his customs—not allowed, 1898 ... 30 Rifles imported vid the Persian Gulf found on the North-West frontier, 1898 The danger through wholesale importation of arms into Persia Representation of Messrs. Fracis, Times &amp; Co. regarding recent seizure of their arms. 1808 a C927FD 9 « 40 41—42ii |, : m 1 r Rules and Regulations for the Registration of arms and ammunition at Maskat Leakage of Government Ammunition from Her Majesty's Ships, i&amp;99 Rules and Regulations for the Registration of Arms and Ammunition at Maskat amended, 1899 Report on the attachment of arms at Bahrein in January, 1898 The Sultan of Maskat's claim for compensation discussed and nega tived, 1899 ... Arrival at Maskat of Monsieur Goguyer, 1899 The powers of the Board of Customs regarding munition* of war referred to legal opinion, 1899 ... ... Letter from the Persian Ministry for Foreign Affairs prohibiting the importation of Arms, dated the 6th Shaban (3rd July 1881) ... Importation of arms from Maskat to the Italian Protectorate on the Benadir Coast, 1899 Major Pagan's views on the necessity of winning the Sultan of Maskat over to our side in order to deal effectively with the arms traffic, 1899 Suggested concession to the Sultan of Maskat, 1899 ••• Captain Cox's report on the arms traffic at Maskat, 1899 The right of seizure discussed with the Legislative Department, 1 99 ••• ••• ... ... ... The Sultan receives the arms confiscated from the Baluchistan, ^90® ••• .•• ... ... ... Revival of Notification No. 1560 of the 1st October, 1880 1 he Sultan of Maskat's position as regards certain claims with which he was threatened for seizures on the Baluchistan, l 9oo (1) The Sheikh of Bahrein restores confiscated arms to Messrs. Fracis, Times &amp; Co., 1900 Agreement with the Sheikh of Koweit prohibiting the arms traffic, May 1900 Agreement with Maskat as to the ownership of confiscated arms, l 9oo Interpretation of our agreement with Persia, regarding the owner ship of confiscated arms, 1901 The case of the seizure of the S. S. Hathor referred to legal 0 P inion — — ... ... ... Fracis, Times &amp; Co., V. Meade. Judgment, May 1901 Seizure by the Turkish authorities of arms destined for Katar, Feb ruary 1901 The arms trade between the Persian Gulf and the North-West Frontier, 1901 The difficulty of dealing with the Arms trade at Maskat owing to the French and American Treaties ••• ••• Transhipment of small parcels of arms and ammunition intended for personal use. Notification, 1902 I he question of approaching the French Government regardine the Maskat arms traffic, 1002 ' ^ ••• •••., .«» Landing of a cargo of arms and ammunition at Hasina, a small port near Lingah. Sources from which the Arab and Baharlao tribes obtain their supplies of armSi 1903 Measures taken for the suppression of the arms traffic between Oman and the Somali Coast Paragraphs. 44 45 46 47 48 49 50 51—53 53 54 55 56 57 58—59 60 61 63 63—64 65 66—68 69 70 71 73—75 76 77 78—82 83 84—85••• 111 / Paragraphs. The rights of search by men-of-war defined, 1903 ... 86—88 Arms traffic between the Persian Gulf and the North-West Frontier of India, 1903-1904 ... ... ... _ 89 _ go Trade in arms and ammunition between Sur and Somaliland. Pro posed appointment of a British Agent at Sur, 1904 ... 91—94 Traffic m arms between Maskat and Koweit. Intention of M. Goguyer to establish a branch of his business at Koweit, 1904 95—96 Despatch to the Secretary of State on recent phases of the arms traffic, 1904 ... ... ... ••• ••• ••• y/ Amendment of the rule in respect to the traffic in arms and am- mumtion at ports on the seaboard of Persia, the Persian Gulf, Baluchistan and Gwadur, 1903 ... t t 98—102 Proposed removal of restrictions requiring British subjects at Maskat to submit weekly statements to the Political Agent of the importation and sale by them of arms and ammunition, 1904. 103^^^/ The right of the Persian Customs authorities to interfere with ves sels carrying arms and ammunition for other than Persian / Ports, 1904. .,106 The Arms Traffic at Koweitt / d &amp; / Instructions to Naval Officers in the Persian Gulf with reference to the Arms Traffic. ^ - cPREFACE. * In submitting this precis on ' the Arms Trade in the Persian Gulf,' I wish to point out that my reason for treating matters in connection therewith at somewhat great length, was to facilitate the work of the officer compiling the Persian Gulf Gazetteer, by saving him the trouble of constantly referring to the recorded collections. The yth November } /po^. C. H. GABRIEL, Lieut,Questions affecting the Arms Trade, 1883—1887. 1. In February, 1883, news was received that a telegram had passed through Aleppo, advising the shipment from Paris of 80,000 Remington cartridges for Basrah and offering to supply as many more with the necessary rifles by another maker. Later, in May, the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf reported that the 80,000 cartridges were for His Royal Highness the Zil-es-Sultan and were intended for 80 Remington rifles purchased by that Prince. 2. In November, 1884, the Secretary of State requested the Government of India to afford facilities for the transhipment of certain ammunition purchased by the Zil-es-Sultan for importation into Persia. 3. In April, 1887, the Persian Government Agent at Jask raised the question as to the right of the telegraph officials to land their private guns and ammunition, and in this connection Her Majesty's Charge d'Affaircs, Tehran, pointed out that special permits were always required for the importation of guns. Amendment of the Indian Arms Act, XI of 1878. 4. In March, 1888, the Bombay Government represented the difficulty they were continually experiencing through being asked to grant export licenses for ammunition or arms other than cannon to Maskat. It was pointed out that rule 6 of the rules issued under the Arms Act, 1878; dealt with the export of certain arms and ammunition by sea at seven ports and for no other ports, and further that this rule seemed to deal only with British ports of import and not to touch the case of export from British port to port beyond the jurisdiction of the Government of India. It was further shown that for exports by sea there appeared to be no rule or limitation provided by the Government of India, and that our jurisdiction was exhausted once the vessel had left our shores although existing in full force before the arms are exported. This being the case, the Bombay Government were of opinion that it was worth consideration whether the Government of India should not impose some restriction on export to Maskat and other places in the Gulf by requiring the Political Officers there to give a permit to import. 5. In reply, the Government of India expressed the opinion that it was not necessary at present to impose any special restriction, but that it would probably be sufficient that a copy of every license issued for the conveyance of arms to Maskat, should be communicated to the Polifical Agent at that place, who would be instructed to ascertain, as far as possible, the ultimate destination of all such consignments and to report to the Government of India if he had reason to believe that importation to Native States in India was practised to any serious extent. 6. Following on this representation, the Bombay Government in May, 1888, stated that the Agent of the British India Steam Navigation Company, Bombay, had applied for a license to tranship for Bahrein, for sale, a consignment of 72 cases containing arms and ammunition which had arrived from Zanzibar; the Government of India were requested to pass orders in the case, and also a5 to whether all applications for export of arms and ammunition to the Gulf should be referred for sanction to India. Acting on the advice of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, the Government of India replied that the license to transmit arms to Bahrein might be refused, and in reply to the further point raised, the Bombay Government were informed that applications of the nature mentioned need not ordinarily be referred for the orders of the Government of India, but that each case might be dealt with by the Government of Bombay in communication with the Resident in the Persian Gulf, the action taken being reported to the Foreign Department for information. 7. In answer to enquiries made by the Agents to the British India Steam Navigation Company, the Government of India informed them that the license C927FD Awas refused in the exercise of the discretionary powers vested in the Governor- General in Council by the Arms Act, and not in virtue of any treaty with the Chief of Bahrein. 8. In October, 1888, the following notification issued from the Home Depart ment :— 'Notwithstanding anything in rule 6 of the Indian Arms Act, XI of 1878— {a) a license to export ammunition or military stores, or to export arms other than cannon or than such rifles as come within the operation of rule 5 of those rules, from the port of Calcutta, Madras, Bombay, Rangoon, Calicut, Karachi, or Aden to any port in a Native State in India, or to any port in foreign territory except a port on the coast of Arabia or Africa, may be granted by the Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department or by any officer specially empowered in this behalf by the Governor General in Council; and (/5) a license to export ammunition or military stores, or to export arms other than cannon or than such rifles as aforesaid, from the port of Aden to any port on the coast of Arabia or Africa may, under the authority of the Govern ment of India certified to by the Secretary in the Foreign Department, be granted by the Political Resident at Aden. Suspected trade in Arms between Bander Abbas and the Frontier States, 1888. 9. In November, 1888, it having been suggested that facilities existed for the surreptitious importation of rifles at Gwadur and Bander Abbas for despatch to Afghanistan and Independent Frontier States, Sir Robert Sandeman was asked to make cautious enquiries on the subject. In replying, Sir Robert Sandeman in January, 1889, expressed the opinion that the trade in arms should be carefully watched and discouraged, and also that there was no doubt that it existed to an even greater extent than was supposed, and that under present conditions, once arms and ammunition were landed at Gwadur, there was nothing to prevent their finding their way into Afghanistan. 10. As the result of further enquiries, it transpired that the traffic was very Pro., October 1904, Nos. 136—146. unimportant. However, it was thought desir- . . a t&gt;le not to lose sight of the subject, and with this in view, the Agent to the Governor-General in Baluchistan was asked to instruct the Political Agent in South-Eastern Baluchistan to make confidential enquiries from time to time, and more especially during the winter tour along the coast, and to report anything that might discover. The Traffic in arms on the Mekran Coast, 1890. 11. In December, 1890, the Agent to the Governor-General in Baluchistan Pro., Secret E., February 1891, Nos. re P° r ^ ed that 21 containing rifles 252—258. sent b y Messrs. Ruzie &amp; Co., to Messrs. Busbar Bundally &amp; Co., other Khojah merchants of Gwadur, had been stopped at Karachi, and that a few other cases from Maskat had been stopped at Gwadur. Instructions were asked for as to the course to pursue and especially as to general instructions about the trade in fire arms along the coast. In discussing the subject it was observefl that in 1888 it had been decided that there were no special reasons for restricting the trade in arms with Maskat and that Gwadur belonged to Maskat. In the same year in the discussion about the new Commercial Treaty with Maskat, Colonel Ross' opinion had been accepted that arms need not be referred to in the treaty and that ' the matter might be left to be dealt with should occasion arise.' In this connection it was noted that importation of arms into Maskat itself and their importation into the Maskat dependency of Gwadur were on somewhat different footings as in the latter case we had an interest in preventing arms bein^ sent up to the Perso-Kalat border, where boundary quarrels might be troublesome This was pointed out to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, who was asked^ ? e ! 0,ta ' ^ Maskat 10 !ssue for the use of His Highness' troops stationed'Ther^r When Collector 1 waslnformed 6 that the^ 0f , Enfield 'A' d ^ained at Karaehi, the refused. WaS mtormed that the .transhipment license for Gwadur should be Prohibition by the Sultan of Maskat of the arms trade at Gwadur. I89I. ' 12. In March, 1891, the case having been represented to the Sultan of Pro., Secret E., May 1891, Nos. 9 — Maskat, His Highness issued an order J4 - * prohibiting the import of arms or ammuni- therefrom. tl0n lnt0 G,vadur territory, or their removal Application by the Bombay Government for a license to tranship cartridges, 1892. 13- In April, 1892, the Bombay Government reported that the British India Pro., Secret E., July 1893, Nos. 264 mi P an y ^ applied for a license to —'68. tranship 102,000 cartridges for Falia on case was urgent, the Government of India might' refCT to^hJfpf ^ at, r aS the ment or might see reason to let it pass at once Persian Govern- Bombay Government were accordingly directed to ascertain whether the con! signor or consignee had got permission from the Persian authorities. Representation by the Consul-General at Zanzibar regarding the arms trade with Maskat, 1892, 14. In a telegram received from the Secretary of State, dated the 22nd Pro., External A., September 1892. I f9 2 &gt; it was stated that the Consul- Nos. 63—83. Ueneral^ at Zanzibar had reported that b t » S .hipprf Maskat, arms under the eighth article of the Brussels Conference Act. It was believed ^h^ many of these arms returned to Africa, and in view of this it was asked whether the Sultan of Maskat would prohibit re-exportation. 15. Tne Resident m the Persian Gulf who was asked to report on the matter stated that no re-exportation had taken place from Maskat, but M-th 30 ?' I 6 ' ': e - eX P 0rted fro ™ Sur - and added that the Sultan of Maskat had issued a notification prohibiting re-exportation. Mayl^V'^^ 0 ^ COmmUniCated t0 the SeCretary of State on the 4 th The possibility of checking the arms traffic discussed, 1892. 16. The Secretary of State in his Political despatch No. 23, dated the 14th April, in forwarding a copy of correspondence from the Foreign Office, requested that any suggestions the Government of India might have to offer, in view of the possibility of checking the traffic, should be forwarded to his Lordship for com munication to the Foreign Office. F The Resident, Persian Gulf, who was asked to report on this despatch rlfrh J ! r \^ f r adm!tt e d that unusually Urge consignments of arms had jreached Maskat of late, forwarded to British Indian subjects and chiefly imported4 in the Sultan of Zanzibar's own steamers. Large quantities of these arms had been sold to people belonging to Bahrein, Koweit, and other Gulf. ports on the Arab coast, who had shipped them to their respective ports. The Sultan of Maskat asserted that no arms found their way back to Africa in Gulf dhows, but Colonel Talbot was not inclined to place much reliance on what the Sultan said in this respect. 17. The Sultan was averse to Her Majesty's ships searching dhows carrying his colors, and as under Article VII of the new Treaty with Maskat the 'importa tion of arms could not be prevented, any further prohibition must, in Colonel Talbot's opinion, be enforced at Zanzibar, should the Sultan's proclamation prove insufficient. Colonel Talbot suggested that in theory it might be possible to prevent this smuggling by inviting the Sultan of Maskat, the Trucial Chiefs, and Bahrein to adhere to the principles of the Brussels Conference. 18. In accordance with the views expressed by the Political Agent, Maskat, and the Resident in the Persian Gulf, the Secretary of State was informed on the 23rd August, 1892, that the apprehensions of Her Majesty's Agent and Consul-General at Zanzibar were regarded as not borne out by the facts, and that this opinion was based upon the present great demand for firearms in the Gulf Ports, and considered that as long as that demand continued, no danger was likely to arise from the importation of arms to Maskat, or from their accumula tion there. It was suggested that since the importation of arms could not be prevented at Maskat, any further measures for checking the trade should be taken, if possible, at Zanzibar. Importations to Maskat from Zanzibar, 1892. 19. On the 7th August, 1892, the Political Agent, Maskat, reported, for information, that the Sultan of Zanzibar's Pro., External A., October 1892, Nos. steamer ^Swordsman ' had arrived there 41 43 ' on the 24th ultimo with 13 cases contain- ing 367 firearms, consigned to a Khoja British subject at Maskat. License issued by the Bombay Government for the export of certain arms to Baghdad, 1891. Issue of a notification tor future guidance. 20. On the 14th December, 1891, the Bombay Government Intimated that they had issued a license for the export Pro. External A., December 1892, Baghdad of certain arms and ammuni- Nos. 31—39. t j on consigned to the Russian Consulate at that place. In stating that In the present case the license had been granted free of charge and without the usual permit, the Instructions of the Government of India as to the procedure to be followed in future similar cases, were solicited, it being pointed out that while the issue of licenses within the political jurisdiction of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf was authorised, the case of export to a port in Turkish Arabia was not provided for. The Resident In Turkish Arabia — to whom the matter was referred — stated that he saw no objection to the issue of such licenses provided that the guns were sporting shot guns and not intended for sale, but for the private use of the exporter. As a result, the following notification issued :— Notification. ' In exercise of the powers conferred by clause [a) of the additional rule under the Indian Arms Act (XI of 1878), published in the Notification by the Government of India in No. 4217-I., dated Simla, the i0Lh November the Home Department, No. 19050! the 15th Sep- 1S92. tember 1902, the Governor-General in Council is pleased specially to empower the Secretary to the Government of Bombay, in the Political Department, to grant licenses to export, by sea, sporting shot guns, machinery for manufac turing ammunition for the same (including machines for loading and recapping cartridges), cartridge cases, and percussion caps, not ' tended for sale or for military purposes, but for the private use of the consignee, to ports v thin the political jurisdiction of the Political Resident in Turkish Arabia.'Seizure of Arms at Bushire by the Persian authorities. The British Resident asked to interfere, 1893. 21. In December, 1893, the Agent of Messrs. David Sassoon &amp; Co., at Bushire, asked for the good offices of the Pro, External A., March ^94, Nos. Resident in the Persian Gulf with a view to obtaining the release of 17 cases of arms and ammunition which had been sent from London consigned to Messrs. Towell &amp; Co., of Maskat, but which had been seized at Bushire under orders of the Sadr-i-Azam of Persia. The Resident proposed replying that he saw no sufficient grounds to interfere in the case. It was remarked that the Persian authorities were no doubt justified in their action, for they were probably aware that ther£ was no real control over arms imported into Maskat once they left the importer's hands and that such arms were bought by the Maskat shopkeepers and smuggled into the zone of the Brussels Act. 22. The question as to whether some means could not be adopted to check the trade in arms at Maskat was again discussed, and it was remarked that there was little doubt that arms and ammunition imported into Maskat were smuggled from there into Yemen and on to the East Coast of Africa. The control at present exercised by the Government of India was limited to consignments of arms which entered Maskat after transhipment from British Indiaover direct shipments, which must be considerable as the duty thereon was said to form the Sultan's principal source of revenue, we had no control. It was noticed that the German Government had issued a prohibition against the importation of arms, etc., into the Persian Gulf region for fear of their being smugged within the zone of the Brus sels Act. It was remarked, however, that should we issue a similar prohibition, the trade would not be checked to any material extent and we should advantage the trade of France, Holland and America who had treaty engagements with the Sultan under which they were guaranteed the benefit of the most-favoured-nation clause. It was decided that taking into consideration the fact that pending the receipt of instructions from the*Home Government, we were not moving in the matter of applying to the Gulf, the General Act of the Brussels Conference, we might for the present confine ourselves to simply approving of the Political Resi dent s proposal not to interfere to recover from the Persian authorities the. arms intended for Maskat. Reported large consignments of arms for the Sultan of Maskat and the Chief of Abu Dhabi, 1893. Measures taken to prevent tran shipment at Bombay. 23. In October, 1893, the Consul-General at Bushire addressed the customs t , 0 . r- , o officials at Bombay with reference to a 466-472 rch 1894^ ^ os . Frenchman called Captain Chapny who had been trading for some years in a specu lative fashion in the Persian Gulf. It was reported that Chapny had ordered some 4,000 rifles for Maskat and the chief of Abu Dhabi and that he had received a large sum for them as an advance. The arms and ammunition were to be brought from France to Bombay*and there transhipped in Chapny's steamer ' Esther' for conveyance to Maskat and the Persian Gulf. In January, 1894, the Collector of Customs, Bombay, informed the Consul- General at Bushire that a case containing 27 rifles had been seized by the Preventive Department. That it was misdescribed as hardware and intended for transhipment to Bushire, and that it might possibly belong to Chapny's consign ment of arms. The trade in arms at Maskat. Representations by the Persian Gov ernment that arms for Oman should not go vi^ Persian Ports, 1895. 24. In February, 1895, the Political Agent, Maskat, referring to his previously Pro., External A., August 1895. Nos. Gxp re ssed opinion that the transhipment 15—jq, of arms for Maskat being stopped at Zanzibar, the trade would continue through 2963 b6 other channels, said that It now appeared that arms^ and ammunition were conveyed to Maskat from Bushire and also direct from England on orders sent home from Bushire. 25. In April of the same year, the Sadr-i-Azam addressed Sir Mortimer Durand, pointing out that arms were imported from time to time as merchandize into the interior of the country through the ports, and that when any officials of the Persian Government got to know of the fact, the owners pretended that the arms were destined for the district of Oman. Under these circumstances, it was requested that the necessary orders might be given to the responsible persons to import firearms, intended for Oman, to that place by sea, without entering the ports of the Persian Gulf in order that they might not be interfered with by the Persian authorities. The Government of India replying to Sir M. Durand, said that it rested with the Persian Government to ^ adopt any measures which might be considered necessary in respect to the introduction of arms through Persian ports. Further, that the Government of India would prefer to avoid any action which might tend, directly or indirectly, to stimulate the trade in arms with Oman, and did not propose to move in the matter. The Bombay Government grant a license for shipment of percussion caps to Bushire, 1895. 26. In September, 1895. the Bombay Government reported for information ^ ^ . 0 that a license had been granted after due No T g erna '' c 0 er 1 95» en q U iry and with the sanction of the Political 0 ' 1 4 ' Resident in the Persian Gulf, to a Persian subject, Haji Muhamed Tuckey,* to enable him to ship 24 lakhs of percussion caps to Bushire for sale there. Major Sadler's report on the Maskat arms traffic, 1886. 27. In March, 1896, Major Sadler furnished his report on the importation „ , . . , o c m of arms an d ammunition into Maskat. , EKternal A. June .896, No S . 44-46. Colonel Wilson, Resident in the Gulf, in commenting on this report, pointed out how brisk a trade in arms there was through Maskat and that it was evidently general throughout the Gulf, and on the increase. At Bushire it had been very active, all Persian protestations of a desire to check it, notwithstanding. It was directly to the advantage of the Local Governor, who on the Persian system bought his office, including the customs revenues, and who was therefore not at' all likely to hinder so lucrative a trade. It was also rumoured that the Residency Agent at Bahrein was—perhaps through his connection with Messrs. Francis, Times &amp; Co. (of London and Bushire) whose agent he had been—the leading man in the trade at Bahrein, Colonel Wilson further observed that the Turks ought to be most concerned at the state of the arms trade, for they would find their troops at Hasa, etc., confronted by Arab tribes much better armed than themselves. At Bahrein too the position would be more serious should it again be threatened. The position at Maskat was also serious, for in the event of another revolt the Sultan's enemies would be even more formidable than on the last occasion, when they were better armed than their partisan. In conclusion, Colonel Wilson strongly advocated a re arrangement by the Sultan of his foreign engagements so as to exclude this stream of arms into his country. It was felt, however, that His Highness would, with his usual perversity, prefer to keep his revenue from the importation of arms. Arms traffic at Maskat, 1896. 28. In April, 1896, the India Office forwarded a copy of a. letter from the Secret E., July 1896, Nos. 266—268. Consul-General at Hamburg stating that orders had been placed with a local firm for the supply of some 20,000 repeating rifles for the Sultan of Maskat(&amp; 7 In July, 1S96, news was received from Zanzibar regarding an attempt made e ^ . . o ^ xt by Arabs, proceeding: to Maskat, to Secret E., August .8 9 5, Nos. 70-7., s ^ uggle on ^ board tli |&gt; 3^ s _ Avoc ^ „ a large number of guns, possibly intended to assist rebels in Maskat. The Commissioner in Sind authorised to issue export licenses, 1896. 29. The Bombay Government, writing in September 1896, drew attention External A., November I1896, Nos. to the fact that while the District 57—59- Magistrate, Karachi, could under rule 6 of the rules framed under the Indian Arms Act, 1878, grant licenses for exports to certain specified ports, the Commissioner in Sind was not authorised to issue any export licenses under the Act. As a consequence, all applications for the export of arms, etc., by sea from Karachi to Bushire and Maskat, and other ports in the Persian Gulf and in Turkish Arabia had to be referred to the Bombay Government. As a result of this representation, the Government of India issued the necessary notification authorising the Commissioner in Sind to issue the export licenses. The ultimate destination of arms shipped to the Persian Gulf discussed. Measures for the suppression of the trade, 1897. 30. In January, 1897, ^ Intelligence Branch in forwarding an extract from c . r? a . o vr the Quarterly Return of important war Secret E., August .897, Nos. 23-35- ^ and ^ Naval Stores shipped to Foreign Ports from the United Kingdom,' enquired as to the ultimate destina tion of the arms and ammunition shipped to Bushire and Maskat. The Resident in the Persian Gulf who was asked to supply the requisite information replied that of the shipments to Maskat and Bahrein 'a large part, in the case of Martini-Henry rifles, was destined for Bushire, whence these rifles were distributed to the surrounding Persian districts, to other Persian ports, to Persian Arabistan whence some doubtless crossed the Turkish frontier, and to Koweit for Turkish Arabia. The weapons classed as'* guns,' probably included Enfield rifles, and were said mostly to go to Hadramant and thence into Arabia ; some also found their way to the Pirate Coast and to Mekran and Persian Baluchistan. It was estimated that of the Martini-Henry rifles, about 60 per cent, found their ultimate destination in Persian territory, 25 per cent, in Turkish territory, and the rest in Arabia. Of the Enfield rifles and other weapons 50 per cent, were estimated as going into inland Arabia, 20 per cent, to Oman, 10 per cent, to El Hasa, Katr and Koweit and ao per cent to Mekran and South-Eastern Persia. It was noted that there were apparently no means of checking or effectively preventing the arms and ammunition trade carried on in the Gulf ports. So far back as 1880, Sir Mortimer Durand had noted that it seemed very questionable whether the efforts then made to check it would not have the effect of driving it into foreign vessels which would not touch at Indian ports. But, apart from this opinion, there existed actual difficulties in the way of stopping the trade in arms, etc., in the Persian Gulf. The local Turkish and Persian officials would be required to actively support any preventive measures that might be introduced ; while the assistance of the Trucial Chiefs, as well as of the Chief of Bahrein and the Sultan of Maskat, in this direction, would also have to be reckoned upon. Maskat was said to be the centre of the trade; and the treaty concluded with the Sultan by Great Britain in 1891 precluded all interference w r ith trade generally. America, France and Holland also had treaties with Maskat, which gave them the right to sell arms and ammunition freely. If, therefore, any check on imports of these articles was to be effectively exercised, the provisions of those treaties must first be amended, or the provisions of the Brussels Conference Act be made applicable to Maskat. The Sultan of Maskat requests sanction to an increase of 2i per cent, on the import duties on arms and ammunition, 1897. 31. In April, 1897, the Political Agent, Maskat, reported that the Sultan had asked for sanction to an increase of 2| per cent, on the import-duty on arms \8 and ammunition, but that he was not prepared to recommend an assent to the request, unless the assent of other powers admitted of such increase being of general application, so that the interests of British manufacturers and merchants should not exclusively suffer. The matter was referred to the Secretary of State* with * Despatch No. 116 of 1897. the rem: ; rk His Highness the Sultan Pro. No. 34 ibid. appeared to incline rather to make a profit from the trade than to desire to put it down. The Sultan gave, it is true, as a reason for wishing to, raise the import duty on arms, the consideration that ' the continued import in large quantities of arms and ammunition is likely to cause serious trouble to ourselves,' but an addition of 2^ per cent, to the duty was not likely to act as a deterrent. The Secretary of State was further informed that although India was not, perhaps, directly interested from a military point of view, Imperial interests were involved in questions which might arise from the trade. • A large proportion of the arms trade of Zanzibar appeared to have been diverted to Maskat about the year 1892, and Maskat had for some time been the principal port of entry for consignments of arms sent to the Gulf and the Oman coast. The Secretary of State enquires regarding the importation of arms into Afghanistan, 1897. 32. In October, 1897, the Secretary of State informed the Government of Secret F,, June 18981 Nos. 251— 346. i n dia that it had been reported that on previous occasions the importation of arms into Afghanistan had been conducted through Persia. It was also said that a large cargo of Mauser rifles was likely to be sent nominally to Hongkong, but really to Bunder Abbas. This information was telegraphed to Colonel Meade who was asked to furnish his remarks thereon. In accordance with later instructions received from the t Pro. No. 266. Secretary of State, Colonel Meade was directed! to observe extreme caution in making enquiries, so as to prevent the operators taking alarm. The Resident in the Persian Gulf telegraphing on the 22nd October 1897 X Pro, No. 267. said | that it did not appear that arms were taken via Bushire to Afghanistan, but it was known that large quantities constantly consigned to Maskat were carried by native boats to Bunder Abbas, whence their ultimate destination was unknown, but that the British Agent at Lingah would enquire secretly and report. Colonel Meade recommended that the Resident at Aden should be advised to watch cargoes of arms transhipped for the Persian Gulf, and to send particulars by telegraph, it was further suggested that the Persian Government should be urged strictly to enforce the existing orders against the importation of arms into Persia, on the ground that danger would follow to trade and internal tranquillity if it were not checked. Pro. No. 269. The Resident at Aden was in structed in accordance with Colonel Meade's recommendations. 33. On the 25th October 1897, the Secretary of State telegraphed that owing to the fact that he was making enquiries into the alleged arms traffic, it was desirable that the local officers should do nothing further at present. The Aden and Persian Gulf authorities were informed accordingly. Examination of surrendered arms on the North-West Frontier, 1898. 34. The following extract from a despatch to the Secretary of State (No, 78 Pro, No. 323. P* 1 898) regarding the results of theexam- ...... , ination of rifled arms and ammunition surrendered by the tribesmen on the North-West Frontier, is of interest in connec- tion with the trade via the Persian Gulf:— ''We forward also four reports by the Ordnance Department on small-arms ammunition taken from the tribes on the North-West Frontier. The great majority of cartridges and / .. r - . ... ; I ' ■9 cartridge cases recovered are of service make. None have been found of /the special form to which our attention had been particularly drawn in connection with the Persian Gulf trade.' Arms trade in Bahrein. Agreement with the Sheikh for the suppression of the trade, 1898. 35. In Secret Despatch No. 6, dated the 18th March 1898, the Secretary Secret E,, July 1898, Nos. 432-469. of State intim , ated that His Excellency's report as to the arrangements made with the Chief of Bahrein for the suppression of the arms trade and the measures taken in consequence was awaited. In requesting the Resident in the Persian Gulf to arrange quickly with the Sheikh, it* was pointed out that the position at * Pro. No. 457. Bahrein was not complicated, as at . , Maskat, by treaty engagements with other powers. What was required from the Bahrein Sheikh was a simple and unconditional agreement to prohibit all import and export of arms into or from that island. Colonel Meade telegraphedf on the 3rd May 1898 that the Sheikh had t Pro. No. 459. signed the agreement prohibiting un conditionally imports and exports of arms. Copies of the agreement and of a proclamation and notification giving it effect and making it generally known were afterwards received. The following is a translation of the Proclamation dated 30th April, 1898:— Be it known to all who see this that British and Persian vessels of war have permission to search vessels, carrying their and our flags in Bahrein territorial waters, and to confiscate all arms and ammunition (weapons of war) in them, if those arms and ammunition are intended for Indian or Persian ports or the islands of Bahrein. Bahrein vessels, found in Indian and Persian waters by British and Persian vessels of war, suspected to contain arms and ammunition for Indian and Persian ports, and the islands of Bahrein, are liable to be searched by the said vessels and all such arms and ammunition found in them will be confiscated as property of the State.' The notification was as follows ' Be it known to all who see this, that whereas we have already forbidden the sale ot arms and ammunition to our subjects in the Island of Bahrein by our notification,dated 13th Safar 1313, January 1896, and whereas there is roason to think that, notwithstanding our pro hibition, many arms and much ammunition are imported into Bahrein for the purpose of being exported therefrom to British Indian and Persian ports, where such importation is prohi bited, and whereas we have resolved to do all that lies in our power to assist the British and Persian Governments in putting a stop to this illegal traffic, we hereby declare that from the date of this notification the importation of arms and ammunition into the islands of Bahrein, and the exportation of the same therefrom, Is absolutely prohibited. All arms and ammunition in future imported into the islands of Bahrein or exported therefrom will be seized and confiscated as property of the State.' The agreement was as follows :— ' I agree to absolutely prohibit the importation of arms into Bahrein territory or ex portation therefrom, and, to enforce this, I have issued a notification and proclamation to all concerned.' At the instance of the Secretary of State, Colonel Meade was asked to expedite a full report as to the actual treatment of arms seized at Bahrein and as to the disposal of any others placed there previous to the arrangement with the Sheikh. (1) The Sultan of Maskat joins the British and Persian Governments in tjie endeavour to put a stop to the arms trade. (2) Seizure of the S. S. 'Baluchistan' in Maskat territorial waters, 1898. 35. On the 25th January, 1898, Sir A. Hardinge received information from Secret E., July 1898, Nos. 326-431. ^ e « ty ,' S C0I, ( SU l; G T e . ral u in J BuSh ^ _ that the Sultan of Maskat had agreed to join the British and Persian Governments in putting an end to the traffic in arms. With this object, the Sultan published a warning to his people informing C957FD10 them that the trade in arms was illegal, and that all arms found would be con fiscated. A similar warning was given to British subjects in Maskat. The Sultan further gave a written permission to British and Persian vessels of war to seize in Maskat waters British, Persian and Maskat vessels with arms consigned to British and Persian ports ; also to seize Maskat vessels in British and Persian waters and to confiscate the arms found on board. In December, 1897, Sir A. Hardinge had, in accordance with instructions received from the London Foreign Office, requested the Commanders of Her Majesty's ships in the Persian Gulf, through the Resident at Bushire, to do their utmost to intercept and seize in Persian waters the S. S. *' Baluchistan,' which was known to have shipments of arms on board,—warning was also conveyed of the attempt that would probably be made to divert the whole cargo of arms to Maskat. The conclusion of the agreement with the Government of Maskat permitted action to be taken by Her Majesty's ships in the waters of Maskat, and the M Baluchistan ' was seized on the 24th January 1898 by H. M. S. ' Lapwing ' near Maskat, and the cargo of arms was landed and made over to the British Consul pending instruc tions as to their disposal. It was thought that the seizure of arms on board the S. S. ' Baluchistan' together with the seizure already made at Bushire, would strike a most effective blow at the traffic of arms in the Persian Gulf. In speaking with regard to the arms question in Bushire, the Consul-General stated that there were undoubtedly still large numbers of arms which had been secreted by British and native firms, but that it would be extremely difficult to obtain information as to where they had been hidden. Sir A. Hardinge stated that the feeling in Bushire during the recent seizures ran so high that it would be desirable before any further seizures were made^ that a gunboat should be present in the harbour while search was being made. The Firman Firma, who, as Governor of Fars and the Gulf ports, farmed the revenues of the customs, had placed every possible obstruction in the way of the seizure of arms, and—said Sir A. Hardinge—had endeavoured to bribe the ministers to cease their opposition to the importation of arms, but without success. His Highness, who undoubtedly had made large profits by the importation of arms, at this time announced to the Persian Government that he had given up the farming of the customs of the Southern Ports. Decision of the Sultan's Court regarding the legality of the seizure of arms on the S. S. 14 Baluchistan,' 1898. 37. On the 16th April, 1898, the Resident in the Persian Gulf reported that Pro. No. 353. t ^ e Sultan of Maskat had held a terri torial Court to adjudicate on the legality of the seizure of arms ex S. S. ' Baluchistan.' Further that His Highness had confirmed the decision of the Court, and considered that the capture of the arms was lawful, although the port of destination had been changed from Bushire t« Maskat. His reasons for this view were set forth in his decision, which was as follows :— « Whereas this day the 15th April, 1898, we, that is to sav, I, Saeed-bin-Muhammad, the Wazeer of His Highness the Sultan of Maskat, and I, Badr-bin-Seif, held a court by the order of His Highness Sayyid Feysal-bin-Turki, Sultan of Maskat, for enquiring into the circumstances under which certain arms and ammunition ex S. S. ' Baluchistan 'of Swansea No. 104951 were seized by the British man-of-war ' Lapwing ' on the 24th January, 1898 near this port in the territorial waters of His Highness the Sultan of Maskat, and whereas' we have examined Lieutenant Commander G. Carr, R.N. (C.M.G.), Commander of the ' Lapwing,' and heard his evidence on solemn affirmation and have examined the bills of lading, manifests, and papers and telegrams which the above mentioned commander pro duced, we find after a full enquiry and deliberation as follows :— (1) That the said arms and ammunition ex S.S, ' Baluchistan' were seized by the British man-of-war ' Lapwing.' (2) That the seizure was in every respect legal and in accordance with the permis sion given by His Highness the Sultan to British men-of-war at the request of the British and Persian Governments. (3) That those arms and ammunition were intended for Persian ports.II (4) That the alteration in the port marks of destination oh the cases took place (wa? carried out) during the stay of the S. S. Baluchistan ' at Port Said on or about the 6th January 1898, with the intention of misleading as to the true destination of these cases ; but such alteration did not confer any immunity on them from seizure in accordance with the above-mentioned permission. (5) That the arms and ammunition are the very ones mentioned in the original manifest which is attached to this decision. Major C. G. F. Fagan, Her Britannic Majesty's Consul, was present in Court on behalf of the British Government. I, Feysal bin Turki, Sultan of Maskat, having carefully considered this decision of my High Court approve of it and agree with it. In witness whereof I have put my signa ture and seal to it.' FEYSAL bin TURKI bin SAEED. SAEED bin SULTAN. The Arms traffic in the Persian Gulf previous to the seizure of the S. S. Baluchistan ' reviewed, 1898. 38. The following memorandum written by Sir William Lee-Warner and dated from the India Office on the 3rd June, 1898 is of interest as showing the trend of events leading up to the seizure of the S. S. ' Baluchistan.' The Trade in Arms in the Persian Gulf, Persian Prohibitions. —On the 3rd July, 1881, the Persian Government notified to the British and other Foreign Governments that the trade in arms and ammunition with Persian ports was prohibited. ' Importers,' writes Colonel Meadefcm 2 3nd March, 1898,' were well aware of this.' The British Minister observed that we had at all times applied to the Persian authorities to prevent Afghanistan obtaining munitions of war through Persia, and therefore he had raised no objection to the prohibition. Nevertheless, owing to the weakness of the central authority, and to the sale of the offices of Governor and Customs Collector, the traffic continued, and importers made secret arrangements with the local officials to evade the law. In 1895 the Persian authorities seized a large consignment of arms in Bushire, and in the following year a special preventive officer was appointed by the Persian Government to enforce the prohibition against the traffic. On the other hand, certain British traders, who had landed in 1895 at Bushire some arms from the S. S. ' Zulu,' alleged to have been overcarried by mistake, appealed to the British Government against their confiscation by the Persians, and obtained the restitution of their goods. The consular reports also, year by year, noticed the increasing trade in arms with Persia in terms which, if they referred to the prohibition, seemed to treat it as nominal only. In 1897, however, events occurred which brought to the front the danger to Persia and the Government of India arising from the neglect to enforce the law, and on the 1st December 1897, the British Resident at Busnire was informed that the Persian Government had already authorised the Malik-ut-Tujjar to seize any arms he could find at Bushire which had been illicitly imported. On the 18th December, 1897, the Sadr Azam addressed the British Legation referring to the prohibitive laws and expressing satisfaction at the prospect of concerted action. The Persian Govern ment announced its determination to enforce the law rigidly, and caused a com munication to be made to the Sultan of Maskat inviting his co-operation It also accepted an offer of the British Government to assist it by searching British vessels believed to be engaged in the illicit traffic, and by seizing any arms or ammunition found on them in Persian water which might be on their way to Persian ports, and be owned by British or Persian subjects. The Sultan of Maskat readily promised his aid, and extended the prohibition against importa tion into Persia or British India to Maskat territory and its waters ; and on the 13th January, 1898, His Highness issued a notification declaring that arms or ammunition destined for Persia or British India and found in Maskat waters would be confiscated. At various dates in December the premises of certain merchants In Bushire were visited by Persian officers in the presence of British13 consular officers, and stores and farms, etc., were seized. The S. S. ' Tresco ' arrived at Bushire on the 25th December, 1897, and a few arms were also seized on board her, and the same operation was repeated on the arrival of the ' Baluchis tan ' in that port on the 1st February, 1898. Previously to this the ' Baluchis tan ' had been stopped on January 24th in Maskat waters by H. M. S. ' Lapwing' which acted under the proclamation of the 13th January, 1898, and on the 15th April, 1898, a court appointed by the Sultan found that the arms and ammunition seized on board were intended for Persian ports although the marks on the case had been fraudulently altered at Port Said on or about the 6th January, 1898, and it decreed that they were therefore justly confiscated. The owners of the S. S. ' Baluchistan ' must have expected the fate which they provoked. They also owned the S. S. ' Turkistan ' which had carried in February and in July of 1897 a quantity of arms to the Gulf, and the S. S. ' Arabistan ' which had sailed in September, 1897, with several cases of arms and ammunition. It is inconceivable that they were not aware of the restric tions and dangers of the trade. In fact on the 23rd of December, four days before the ' Baluchistan ' sailed from Marseilles, and long before it reached Port Said, or Jibuti, they wrote to the Foreign Office referring to the orders given by the Persian Government, and asking Lord Salisbury ' to give such instruc tions as will enable our steamer to have protection in this matter.' They admitted that the Resident had informed their agent 'the arms are liable to be seized and confiscated in Persian waters.' On the 34th December they were asked by the Foreign Office to give certain detailed Information as to the consignee's names and other particulars. This, however, was an inconvenient request with which they did not comply, and on the 13th January their omis sion was referred to in these terms ' In the absence of that information there is nothing to show that the shippers and exporters were not at the time of exportation alive to the risks which they have incurred by engaging in a trade which is contrary to Persian law and regulations. British interests. —It is convenient here to summarise some of the reasons which induced the British Government to come to an agreement with the Persian Government and to assist it in enforcing the Persian regulations. 1. For some years past it had been evident that Maskat was becoming a centre of trade in arms and ammunition, and the Sultan was anxious to stop its growth as dangerous to his own position. Rebellions against his authority in Dhofar and at Matha had proved that the tribesmen were armed, and the British Government had given advice and even lent its active aid in restoring the Sultan's authority. It was at first proposed to put a heavy tax on the importa tion of arms, but the Maskat Treaties of commerce of 21st September 1833, with the United States of 19th March 1891, with Great Britain of 17th November 1844, with France, and the rights of other most favoured nations were found to be opposed to this solution. The alternative of prohibiting the export of arms to the Gulf from Great Britain was considered and rejected. There seemed then no other course open save that of stopping the trade with Persia and India through Maskat, and this course, after a discussion of some months, was finally proposed to the Foreign Office on the 1st December, 1897, the very day on which the agent of the Persian Government informed the Resi dent at Bushire of the orders which he had independently received from the Per sian authorities to make a seizure of arms. 2. Amongst other events which served to call attention to British interests in the matter were several piratical attacks on British Indian vessels trading with the Gulf and Shatt-ul-Arab. In the case of the '* Hariposa ' and more recently in that of the ' Kahanposa,' which was attacked on the 2nd December, 1897, near Saihan Point, the fatal use of firearms and our failure to secure satisfaction for the piracies convinced Government that steps must be taken to protect British commerce by dealing with this question. There were precedents for such action, because in 1892 the Sultan of Maskat had, in the interests of Germany, been induced to prohibit the re-exportation of arms from Maskat for the coasts of Africa and in the previous year their exportation to Gwadur was also prohibited. Now, British interests in the Gulf are bound up with peace, because we have a network of Indian treaties with the tribes for what is called theu Maritime Truce.' Of recent years, at Koweit and Bahrein, and at Zobara in the El Katr Peninsula, there have been grave disturbances requiring our inter vention, and in each case the position was aggravated by the arms traffic. 3. In Persia itself British interests had suffered from attacks upon the telegraph system of the Indo-European Telegraph Company, which the Persian Government and the local Chiefs are bound to protect under agreements with the Government of India. Sevaral lawless incidents culminated in the murder of Mr. Graves in December, 1897, and the increase of these attacks was attri buted to the army of the robbers and tribes in Southern Persia. Even at Bushire itself the Residency was not free from danger, while the roads into the interior were often unsafe. 4. Beyond the borders of Persia and in Baluchistan itself, a survey party was attacked on the 9th January, 1898, and it became necessary to land a force of sailors and British Indian troops in order to protect the servants of the Indian Government. 5. It was also ascertained that arms were being imported into Afghanistan through Bunder Abbas, Charbar and other ports opposite Maskat, and it was alleged and feared that the tribes in revolt on the Indian frontier were obtaining ammunition and arms from the Persia Gulf. In support of this last ascertion, it was proved that Afghan emissaries were awaiting the arrival of the ' Baluchistan ' at Maskat, and 20 packets of Martini-Henri ammunition, with paper showing that it was made in Belgium, were found at Pasni in Mir Suka's house in February last. It is worthy of note that the Belgian manufacturers of rifles obtained last year from the British Government contractors the exact measure ments of the British Martini-Henry rifle, so as to ensure that the British ammuni tion would fit the rifles ; obviously those who ordered the rifles expected to get access to British cartridges. Certain caravans have also lately started for the British Indian frontier from the Baluchistan coast with cases supposed to con tain arms transported from Maskat, and steps have been taken to follow them up. The only doubt which has been thrown on the supply of these rifles and ammunition to the tribes arises from the fact that amongst the arms surrendered by the tribes none corresponded to the arms known to have been sent to Maskat. But the value of this evidence is discounted by the fact that the tribes have surrendered their worthless, stolen, or specially made up arms, and no rifles have been captured in the field, because rifles as well as the bodies of the slain are removed by the tribesmen. Information obtained in England shows that the importers in the Gulf ordered arms on account of the tribes, and it is note worthy that the Belgian manufacturers took pains, after the outbreck of the dis turbances in 1897, t0 erase all marks on the rifles and cartridge cases sent out by them for the Gulf. Methods of the Trade. —The methods of the trade lend weight to the suspicion that the arms were known to be liable to seizure and were wanted for no proper purpose. Secrecy has been the rule in the last two years. Arms have been shipped or transhipped at the last moment in order to take advantage of con fusion or hurry. In some cases the intention to ship at London has been altered in view of the vigilance of the customs, and the cases have been shipped at Manchester instead. Although the exporters have in many instances received full payment before shipment, the bills of lading have even in these cases shown no names of consignees. Clearly in such cases the names were omitted by design, as the bills did not pass through a bank, and there was no need to adopt the vague generality ' to order.' In a recent case, a false name of consignee, namely ' Gopalji Walji,' was entered as the consignee, and repudiated by the said Gopalji on arrival. Even the name of the exporter has been changed at the last moment in order to divert attention, as Spencer was put in place of Carling &amp; Co. The arms have been entered on bills of lading as ' hardware,' and when on one occasion a true copy of the bill of lading was called for, the shippers inserted ' merchandise' for ' hardware' which would have been a less inaccurate description, and when the bill was challenged, they wrote that it was made out ' from memory.' The cases themselves bear marks only C937FD*4 and no address Even these marks and the destination are altered on board, either at Port Said or at sea. The shippers undertake to land not merely at the port originally named, but at another port in the Gulf as desired, and the desire of the consignee is signified at the last moment, and even at a port on the way to the Gulf. The practice of the trade has been carefully watched of late, and the main impression produced by the inquiries is the endevour to obscure the destination and the names of the recipients of the arms. Some firras of repute have given up the trade, and the firms which take most part in it have Indians or Persians as partners. At the port of receipt the trade is largely in the hands of those, e.g., Malcolm &amp; Co. of Bushire, or Gopalji Walji of Maskat, who have secured a contract for the collection of the customs. Where the importer is not also collector, he secures the goodwill of the cus toms authorities by payment of a bribe in the shape of a special ad valorem duty. The receipts from these duties are not entered in the customs receipt. The English firms have agents at Maskat or in the Gulf, whose proceedings are in accord with the whole spirit of secrecy that pervaded the trade. Finally the arms sent out are chiefly of Belgian make, and the greatest care has of late been taken to remove all marks from them. Our policy for the future.—\ have shown that despite the representations of Maskat, and the customs regulations of Persia, an illicit traffic of arms, chiefly of Belgian make, has been carried on by a few British firms in a secret manner with the Gulf, and that it is inimical to British interests. As to its extent, its registered value rose from Rs. 13,120 in 1892-93 to Rs. 23,87,195 in 1896 -97, and when lately the operations of search and seizure were conducted at Bushire, Maskat and Bahrein, some two and a half million rounds of ammunition, and nearly 16,000 rifles were seized. Our interests in the Gulf are to preserve peace and order for commerce, and in Persian territory we desire to maintain communications and open out trade routes. In Baluchistan we are more directly responsible for order, and it is important that Afghan and Pathan tribes should not have access to an unlimited supply of arms. We must therefore continue to assist our allies in suppressing the illicit traffic in arms, and it is necessary that no favour should be shown by them to foreign merchants. We have a right to expect that Persia will uniformly exert itself to confiscate arms imported by any nation contrary to its regulations. As regards the British importers, whose arms have been seized, no intervention on their behalf will be justified unless they can prove in the Consular Courts that the arms seized were not intended for Persian or Britieh territory, or if so intended were being sent under permission duly received from responsible authority. The trade is at present almost entirely suspended, and its revival would be unfair upon Persia and Maskat as well as opposed to our own interests.' Claim for compensation by the Sultan of Maskat on account of al leged losses sustained by his customs—not allowed, 1898. 39. In July, 1898, we find the Sultan of Maskat preferring a claim on ac- ^ 0 count of the loss of income from customs beoret E., March 1899, Nos. 13 -1 • sustained by him in consequence of the permission given by him to Her Majesty's vessels of war to seize arms and ammunition in his territorial waters. The claim was not allowed however, it being clearly shown to be unwarranted by His Excellency the Viceroy who wrote ' The claim for compensation seems to me almost ridiculous. What are the facts ? The Sultan sells his customs for ^1,40,000. Suddenly he hears of the combined action of the British and Persian Governments re arms and of the intention of the shippers to evade seizure by altering the destination of their arms to Maskat. He accordingly cancels his contract and makes another which promises him $30,000 more, an increase which he thinks he will derive from the policy of the British Government. Subsequently the British Gov ernment in pursuance of the same policy seize the cargo of the u Baluchistan ' (with his permission given in return for no promise or quid pro quo) in Maskat waters. He now has to cancel his second contract, and to take $1,45)000 from the former in consequence of the reduced expectations of the latter. Then he is left $5,000 the better for the arms policy of the British Government (*.&lt;?., the difference between the $1,40,000 of the first con tract and the $&gt;i,45 j 0 0 0 of the third).15 Even had the arms not been seized, it is very doubtful whether as they were in transit, he could have claimed any cnstoms dues on them at all. If he is already the gainer of $5,000 by our action, and further there is a chance (which I suppose there is) of his getting something out of the value of the confiscated arms, why should we give him anything at all ? ' Rifles imported via the Persian Gulf found on the North-West Frontier, 1898. 40. In December, 1898, it was reported that Captain Roos-Keppel had Secret F., March 1899, Nos. 178—301. purchased from tribesmen in Kurram two Martini-Henry rifles of the type imported in the Persian Gulf, and that the man from whom he had purchased them said he could get numbers more from the tribesmen. The danger through wholesale importation of arms into Persia. 41. Sir Mortimer Durand, writing to the Foreign Office on the 1st June, Secret E., March 1899, Nos. 261—563. i8 9 8 » said— ' There can be no doubt whatever that the wholesale importation of arms of precision into Persia is dangerous to the peace of the country, and consequently injurious to our trade, and it may in time prove to be a difficulty with which the Persian Government will find it has not the power to cope. I think the Sadr-i-Azam should be supported in taking stringent measures to put an end to the import, and that the firms which have suffered from the con fiscation of their illicit cargoes should be left to bear the loss. It is true that the import has been allowed to go on in spite of the prohibition; but the firms concerned seem to have known quite well that they were doing what they had no right to do. They chose to run the risk, and have doubtless made large profits. There is no serious hardship in their now being left to suffer some loss/' 42. Replying to a question asked in the House of Commons, Mr. Curzon Pro. No. 299, ibid. stated that the prohibition of the import of arms into Persia could only be the act of the Persian Government. In the case of the other Governments possessing territories on or in the neighbourhood of the Persian Gulf, viz., the Government of India and the Turkish Government, a similar prohibition existed ; whilst it was also being enforced in their own territories by the Sultan of Maskat and the Sheikh of Bahrein. Further, that special inquiries had been made as to whether the prohibition enacted by the Persian Government was being equally enforced against arms of other than British origin, and that it was found that the prohibi tion was universal and that the import of foreign, no less than of British arms, has ceased. Representation of Messrs. Fracis, Times &amp; Co. regarding recent seizures of their arms, 1898. 43. Messrs. Fracis, Times &amp; Co. had for some time been in lengthy Pro. No. 308, ibid. correspondence with the Secretary of btate lor India with reference to the seizure of certain cases of arms and ammunition exported by them to the Persian Gulf. The Secretary of State writing to the Foreign Office on the 9th August, 1898, and referring to the seizure of arms at Bahrein, regarding which Messrs. Fracis, Times &amp; Co. had written :—''It appears that recently arms and ammunition belonging to us of the value of upwards of 2,000 sterling have been seized and confiscated by the British Consul at Bahrein,' said ' The true facts appear to be these. In 1896 Messrs. Fracis, Times asked the Assistant Resident at Bushire to give them a letter of introduction to the Chief of Bahrein for com mercial purposes. Thereupon they were required to give an assurance that they did not intend to deal in arms there, an assurance which must at least have reminded them of thei6 Persian prohibition. They, however, evaded this difficulty by entering into negotiations with a merchant named Agha Muhammad Rahim, who was also employed as a British news agent at Bahrein. This man had obtained from the Sheikh's Vizier a concession of a mono poly of the local trade in arms, which the Chief had previously given to his Vizier, and he, in his turn, now made it over to Messrs. Fracis, Times. Last year Messrs. Fracis, Times fell out with Agha Muhammad Rahim, and also with native merchants or buniahs. Civil pro ceedings were in due course instituted by Agha Muhammad against Messrs. Fracis, Times which are still pending, and then the Sheikh, quite independently of any action taken, or any advice given by the British Resident, took possession in January last of the stock of arms and ammunition stored up by Messrs, Fracis, Times at Bahrein. It was not until the end of April last that the firm took the obvious and proper course of submitting their protest against the Chief's action to the Resident, and the matter is still under consider ation, The inquiry will throw light upon the proceeding of the British news-agent in this matter, which at first sight seems to require modification. ' The main conclusion indicated by these facts is that the British consular authorities in the Gulf were not aware of and were not responsible for the seizure complained of; and that Messrs. Fracis, Times' losses at Bahrein are entirely distinct from the other seizures to which this statement refers. Their claim to restitution depends on the result of the legal proceedings referred to and upon further inquiry into the circumstances. ***** In conclusion, the following general remarks regarding British interests in the suppression of the arms trade were made:— ' Messrs. Fracis, Times, in their statement, dated yth March, 1898, mention 3,800 rifles, besides ammunition, seized in their godowns in Bushire, arms and ammunition of the value of ^12,000 sterling seized at their depot on Bahrein, and £700 worth of arms seized on board the 'Baluchistan,' independently of a stock of arms at Maskat which they value at ,£9,000. If these operations of a single firm of Parsee and British partners represent at all the magnitude of the trade in Belgian and British arms which other firms are conduct ing, the matter becomes one cf most serious importance. In the first place, such a traffic is endangering legitimate British trade in other commodities with the interior. Serious complaints have been received of the insecurity of the trade routes in Persia, especially in Southern Persia. Her Majesty's Minister at Tehran, in his letter of the 27th June last, repeats the opinion expressed by his predecessor in these terms ;—' There can be no doubt whatever that the wholesale importation of arms of precision into Persia is dangerous to the peace of the country, and consequently injurious to our trade.' ' From other parts of the Gulf the same injury to trader is reported. In the case of the piratical attack on the sailing vessel ' Kalianpasa,' committed on the 2nd of December near Saiban Point in the Shatt-el-Arab river, the crew were killed by firearms. This outrage is not the only one of a similar character, and in April last the Assistant Political Agent at Basra reported that Hasan Khyun intended to interfere with the steamers of the Euphrates and Tigris Steam Navigation Company plying on the river. Then again, on the Arab Coast, the intervention of the Indian Government to uphold the Sultan of Maskat's authority has been more than once exercised of late years, and the arming of the rebels is felt by His Highness to constitute an element of danger to the Sultan's rule. The attack upon the British survey party in Baluchistan and the murder of Mr. Graves on the Persian side of the border, which followed the perpetration of several attacks upon the persons and property of British subjects in the employ of the Indo-European Telegraph Department, illustrate a condition of affairs which must be seriously aggravated by allow ing an illicit traffic in arms to continue. In this connection attention is invited to my letter suggesting the need for systematic enforcement by the Persian Government of its regulations against all importers and thus who are taking part in the prohibited traffic in arms. Lastly, there is the danger felt in 1880, when only caps, smooth bore guns, and even flintlocks were being carried through Persian ports into Afghanistan. It was ascer tained by special enquiry that Baluch and Afghan Agents were, during the late frontier disturbances, sent down to Maskat to await the arrival of the S, S. 1 Tresco ' and 1 Balu chistan.' The makers in Belgium, who have supplied Messrs. Fracis, Times and others with Martini-Henry rifles, procured last year from England the exact dimensions of the chambers of the rifles used by the Indian Government; and although Messrs. Fracis Times &amp; Co. state that the market is glutted, the traffic attained its highest dimensions last year, when the Indian frontier was most disturbed. Several cases of the identical cartridges which were exported from Manchester, but made in Belgium were found in February last in the house of Mir Suka in Pasni, and Afghan caravans were in April last awaiting in the neighbourhood of Bander Abbas the expected consignments. Unfortunate ly the tribesmen on the frontier almost invariably succeed in carrying off the arms of those who fall in battle, and it is not to be expected that the arms which they surrender at leisure should be their best weapons. But sufficient information has already been obtained to show that the opinion expressed in July, 1880, by the Government of India, that ' the^7 control of the export of this ammunition to the Persian littoral has become a matter of special political and military importance,' has lost none of its force, and the single fact that the Island of Bahrein under British protection should have been silently used as a depot for arms of precision emphasises the need for increased vigilance in the future.' Rules and Regulations for the Registration of arms and ammuni tion at Maskat. 44. Whereas it is necessary to the due observance of articles 6, 7, 13 and 18 of the Treaty of Friendship, Commerce and Navigation, Pro. No. 471, ibid. concluded at Maskat on the lyth March, 1891, between Her Majesty the Queen of Great Britain and Ireland, Empress of India, and His Highness Seyyid Feysul-bin-Turki, Sultan of Maskat, and for the peace, order and good government of Her Majesty's subjects, being within the dominions of the Sultan of Maskat, his heirs and successors to know accurately what arms and ammunition are possessed in or imported into or sold within the said dominions of Her Majesty's subjects. Now, therefore, Her Majesty's Consul at Maskat, in exercise of the power and autho rity vested in him by article I of the Maskat Order in Council, dated the 4th November 1867, has made the following Rules and Regulations for the registration of arms and am munition by Her Majesty's subjects, within the said dominions, and hereby give notice that the said Rules and Regulations shall, in the absence of any notification to the con trary, come into force on and after the completion of one calendar month from this date I. Every subject of Her Majesty who now are hereafter has or becomes possessed of any arms or ammunition in the dominions of the Sultan of Maskat or who imports any arms or ammunition into the said dominions, shall, without unreasonable delay, furnish to Her Majesty's Consul at Maskat a true and complete list and description of all such arms and ammunition. Such lists and descriptions shall be in such form as the said Consul may, from time to time, require. II. Every subject of Her Majesty who sells or otherwise parts with any arms or ammuni tion in the dominions of the Sultan of Maskat, shall without an unreasonable delay, furnish to Her Majesty's Consul at Maskat a true and correct statement showing the number of arms or amount of ammunition sold or parted with and the name and address of the person or persons to whom the said arms and ammunition have been transferred. Such statements shall be in such-form as the said Consul may, from time to time, require. III. Her Majesty's Consul shall be the sole judge as to what constitutes unreasonable delay in furnishing such list and description or such statement as aforesaid. IV. Any subject of Her Majesty who fails or unreasonably delays to give such true and complete list and description or to furnish such true and correct statement as aforesaid, shall be liable, on conviction, before Her Majesty's Consul at Maskat, to a fine not exceed ing 500 dollars or imprisonment for a term not exceeding 3 calendar months. British Consulate, Maskat, (Sd.) C. G. F. FAGAN, The 24th September 1898. ) Her Britannic Majestys Consult MasJcat. Leakage of Government Ammunition from Her Majesty's Ships, 1899, 45. It having transpired, in connection with the seizure of a quantity of Government ammunition in the Maskat o~8i8 SeCret ^' Marcl1 NoS, bazaar, that leakage has taken place from 790 1 * some of Her Majesty's ships in the Persian Gulf by way of interpreters, the Government of India writing under date the 6th Pro No 817 March 1899, pointed out to the Naval Commander-in-Chief, that in view of the efforts being made to prevent the importation of modern arms and ammunition G927FDi8 into the countries adjacent to India, the Government of India trusted that His Excellency would cause such measures to be adopted as would prevent the issue of the ammunition from Her Majesty's ships to any person in the Persian Gulf unable to produce the written authority of the Resident to possess such ammunition. Acting on this intimation, the Admiral issued stringent orders to prevent Pro., Secret E., May 1899, No. 96. the ppssibility of such irregularities occur ring in future. Rules and Regulations for the Registration of Arms and Ammuni tion at Maskat amended, 1899, 46. It was found in practice that British subjects were able to evade the Pro., Secret E., June 1899, Nos. 3— 6. existing ^ rules and regulations for the . _ registration of arms and ammunition at Maskat by appointing Arab subjects as their sub-agents for the sale of arms. The same procedure was adopted by all the principal dealers in arms, with the result tnat the regulations became absolutely inoperative. Writing to the Secretary of State on the 7th April, 1899, the Political Agent, Maskat, submitted an amended draft of the rules and regulations, in supersession of those already sanctioned. The proposed amendments are printed below in italics : I. Every subject of Her Majesty, who either on his own behalf or in the capacity of Agent for any other person or firm now or hereafter ; has or become possessed of any arms or ammunition in the dominions of the Sultan of Maskat or who imports any arms or ammunition into the said dominions or who is concerned _ directly or indirectly in such importation, shall without unreasonable delay furnish to Her Majesty's Consul at Maskat a true and complete list and description of all such arms and ammunition, provided always that no owner, or master, or agent of a vessel in which arms or ammunition is imported into the said dominions, shall, by reason of such importation he deemed to be directly or indirectly concerned in the importation of such arms or ammunition for the purposes of these rules and regulations. frnm?- UCh f llSt .- anddeS - CriptionSshallbeinsuch form as the saId Consul may, irom time to time, require. II. Every subject of Her Majesty who sells or otherwise parts with any arms or ammunition in the dominions of the Sultan of Maskat, or who benefits dtr Jcul delavfurnlshto^ Her^M a \ afor .f a \ d ' shal1 . without unreasonable delay, turnish to Her Majesty s Consul at Maskat a true and correct statement s owing the number of arms or amount of ammunition sold or parted with and the name and address of the person or persons to whom the said arms or ammumtion have been transferred, such statements shall be in such form ™ the said Consul may, from time to time, require. Her Majesty's Consul shall be the sole hirlo-P oe u ^ reasonable delay in furnishing such list Id 1 deSriptio 0 o^^th Tat mfnt 'a' aforesaid and of the liability or otherwise under the J. statement as ./ Her Majesty's subjects to fMthfsLe re ^ lahms Report on the attachment of arms at Bahrein in January, 1898. 47- Regarding the attachment of arms at Bahrein, in January, 1898, Colonel Secret E,, July 1899, Nos. 94—248. Meade forwarded the following memo randum in November, 1898. ^ No, 129 in Secret E,, July 1899, Nos. 94-248. r claims of Messrs. Fracis, Times are set forth in their letters noted in the margin.19 2. The firm asserts that they have a case against the British Government as the Sheikh was really acting under the direction of the British authorities. 3. To clearly understand the position of affairs at Bahrein, in connection with the concession granted by the Sheikh and its withdrawal as well as the attachment of the stores of arms and ammunition at that place, I would, in the first place, invite aperusal of the accompanying letters and statements, a list of which is attached. 4&gt; From these as well as from previous correspondence between the Government of Narrative of recent events at Bahrein which led India and the Resident in the Persian Gulf it b 0 ^hVsheikT' forim P ortationofarms g ranted will be seen that in 1895 there was much danger y 6 e ' to Sheikh Esa and his subjects, as well as to the numerous British Indian subjects and proteges at Bahrein, from an attack which was contemplated by Sheikh Jasim-bin-Thani, whose head-quarters were on the neighbouring Arab cost. The troubles were ended by the destruction at Zobara by Her Majesty's gunboats the Sphinx and the Figeon of a number of buggalows which were to have been employed in attacking Bahrein, which was undoubtedly saved from a hostile invasion by the intervention of the British. 5. I am told that at that time there were not 100 rifles in Bhrein, and after th e Small number of arms in Bahrein in 1895. incident was over the Sheikh apparently wishe^ to get some for his own protection. 6. To do this in the cheapest way for himself, he granted a concession to his Vizier Abdur Rahman, permitting him to import arms and ammunition under certriu conditions : the Vizier, in return, to supply the Sheikh annually with 30 rifles and 6,000 rounds of ammunition. In the concession it is stipulated that arms are not to be sold at Bahrein or on the neighbouring Arab coast, and it is also stated that it is liable to be cancelled on the death of the Vizier, or whenever he wishes to return it to the Sheikh. 7. The Vizier, who could not, presumably, work the concession himself immediately The Virier immediately hands over the conces- handed it over to Agha Mohamed Rahim, a sion to Agha Mohan.ed Rahim, the news -agent at merchant in Bahrein, who, some sixty vears be- Bai.e.n to the Bnt.sh Res .dene,. had obtained nationality &gt;; ' 8. Mohamed Rahim is of Arab descent, but his family have for many years been caiuji jdl - l Persian subjects, and have been connected with Position of Agha Mohamed Rahim, news-agent fi,„ -r -f- u ^ o at Bahrein. the British bovernment. He acts as our news agent, and channel of communication with the Sheikh of Bahrein, and is supposed to look after British interests there. He has the reputa tion of being a well-to-do merchant, and it would, I may say, at once be difficult to get a man of his position to carry on the dirties he performs on^the pay of the post, Rs. 100 per mensem if he is not allowed to trade. Mohamed Rahim and his predecessors, no doubt, have only held it because it gave them prestige, and assisted them in their private commercial u nder- takings. The Agent's dual possession is undoubtedly an unsatisfactory arrangement, and advantage has been taken of it by Messrs. Fracis, Times to assert that they were dealing with the British representative at Bahrein when they obtained the concession, and again that the British representative had induced the Sheikh to act as he did, when in reality Mohamed Rahim was acting in his private capacity as a private individual. It will, however, be difficult to get a trustworthy agent of this class, or one who will ,17 . not use the influence, the position gives him to Opinion hat a regular Europeon representative u; „ • i. t j t , • , , . , is very desirable for Bahrein and the Arab coast. torucv d his ow n interest, and I certainly think we ought to have an Englishman as our re presentative for Bahrein and the Arab coast. 9. Mohamed Rahim having obtained the concession from the Vizier, entered into _ -, , j L , arrangements with the firm of Messrs. Fracis Aefha Mohamed Rahim hands on on the conces- Tim** Pr rv uu i, i • t , , sioo to Messes. Fracis, Times, &amp; Co. r imes &amp; , Co :' wlth whom he previously had business relations. 10. The firm then started bringing arms to Bahrein, from which pkee they were sold to traders from various parts of the Gulf. Traffic in arms how carried on. Agha Mohamed Rahim was made the Bahrein agent of the firm, and was to get half the profits. It is over the amount of these profits that the parties have fallen out. That it is over the number of guns, qtc., sold and the prices realized. A^ha Mohamed, Rahim was assisted in the sales by his nephew Mahomed Khalil ; and Fracis, Times were also represented by employes of their own, who appear to have watched the sales on their behalf and sometimes to have sold the rifles themselves. n. Payments were made as a rule direct to Mohamed Rahim, except where ' Arms sometimes paid for at BosWre, but deli- Mr. Fraeis at Bushire gave delivery orders to ▼ered at Bahrein and then smuggled into Persia. purchasers ; that is it sometimes suit the firm to take money at Bushire but not to deliver the weapons there. In such cases the guns were handed over at Bahrein by the agent on receipt of the delivery order, and there is little doubt that the arrangement was20 employed to evade the prohibition against the importation of arms Into Persia whenever the Persian officials gave rise to difficulties. Mohamed Rabim has stated that they were taken to Taheri, Lingah, Bunder Abbas, and other places in Persia. 13. The concession for importing into Baherin was a profitable part of the arms traffic carried on by Messrs. Fracis, Times, who Derot at Bahrein very profitable to Messrs. are said b Mohamed Khalil to have sold about Fracis. limes &amp; Co. , -a , r&gt; i. • i 0,000 rifles at Bahrein alone, at an average rate of Rs. loo each, or some 6 lakhs of rupees altogether. 13. When the amount of the traffic came to his knowledge the Sheikh appears to have taken alarm, and as he heard that the concession- coming tato k ?herta«. ara tI,e nUmb ' gUnS aries were evading a condition in the concession to the effect that no sales were to be made to people at Bahrein itself, or at Katar, on the Arab Coast, it seems that he told the Vizier to stop the importation. 14. Sheikh Esa's apprehensions appear to me reasonable. His position at Bahrein 0 . . ., has always been more or less precarious, and The Sheikh s apprehensions seem reasonable. . 0 , fi-iri 1 t in 1095—to the events ot which 1 have already referred—he would certainly have been destroyed but for our assistance. Arming his enemies is therefore a very serious matter for him, and he was justified in trying to curtail the importation of arms, which might be used against himself and his family. 15. The correspondence between Agha Mohamed Rahim and Messrs. Fracis, Times, clearly shows that the latter were aware, long cu M tl s . rs \ Fr f- c5s ' &amp; f C I 0, ffi kn - ew of the before the arms were attached, that the Sheikh Sheikh s obiections to the great traffic in arms. . . , • . n . , was raising objections, and in one letter they refer to the termination of the concession by the Vizier's death, and say that in no other way can it be ended, showing I think that the question of terminating the con cession had been raised. Mohamed Rahim and his nephew have declared on solemn affirmation that its conditions were clearly explained and understood by Mr. Fracis, and that they themselves understood when they received it that it was liable to be withdrawn. 16. The Sheikh seems to have thought that he had the right to do so through his Vizier, and to have exercised that right in conse- Sheikh Esa appears to have thought he had the ce of his dread that o{ th h tight to cancel the concession. ^ 1 • 1 i , , , were coming to Bahrein would be employed against himself. 17. The Vizier in April, 1897, told Mohamed Rahim that he must stop importing . . . „ . arms for four months, after which further orders wonW be issned, and he subsequently demand- ed back the concession. Mr. Fracis was duly informed of this, and it is clear, as I have already shown, that he knew for some time of the Sheikh's objections to the traffic, and had even on one occasion told Mohamed Rahim to threaten the Sheikh that he would report him to the British Consulate if he tried to evade his obligations. 18. It is necessarv here to refer to the con- Knowledge of the British Regidency at Bushire nect i 0n 0 f t hi s Residencv with the arms traffir of the arms traffic going on at Bahrein. necciun 01 mis x \esiaency witn me arms traffic to Bahrein. In January, 1896, that is, about six months after granting the concession to his Vizier, the Sheik issued an order prohibiting the importation of arms to Bahrein under a penalty of a fine of 25 per cent, of he value of the goods brought in. I have little doubt that the Sheikh issued this prohibition at the request of the concessionaires, viz., Mohamed Rahim and Mr. Fracis with the object of keeping the trade exclusively in their own hands. When it first came to my notice, however, in October 1897, I did not understand its object, as I was not aware that Mr. Fracis and the agent held a concession, and I at once called upon the agent for an explanation. This was in October 1897, and it is possible that my inquiries caused Mohamed Rahim to turn round and try to stop the traffic in which he had taken such a prominent part, and it is possible also that the seizures of arms at Bahrein and Maskat may have encouraged Sheikh Esa to attach the arms at Bahrein j but beyond this I am certain that no directions were sent to the Seikh from the Residency or advice given him about the arms traffic, and he acted on his own initiative. 19. As regard the letter to Mr. Fracis from the First Assistant Resident in July 1896, . _ . , , _ o c a lt appears that Mr. Fracis about the middle st l' s h/n.',er slw'it 7 I j g of iSgb-that is, several months after the con- cession was given—made an application for our , good offices with the Sheikh, to this the letter from the First Assistant is a reply. Agha Mohamed Rahim has stated that he never saw or heard of this letter, and it is possible that Mr. Fracis may have kept it to himself, fearing that if it came to our Agent's know ledge he might object to act for them at Bahrein.21 Messrs. Fracis, Times question the right of the Assistant Resident to tell them not to deal in arms, and further ssert that the letter in question was really the work of Mr. J, C. Gaskin, the Extra Assistant Resident and Vice-Consul, who signed it The original order on the application, which in my office is in Mr. Ducat's handwriting, and the draft of the letter written on the order is in the writing of the head clerk. Mr. Fracis, it will be seen, also complaints that his firm was not so favourably treated in this matter as others, who were not warned against dealing in arms when they asktd for our good offices. I believe this is correct, but it is, I think, likely that independent information against the firm of Messrs, Fracis, Times, who were well known to be largely engaged m the arms traffic, and objections, after the Zobara affairs, to the importation of arms to Bahrein and the Arab Coast were the reasons why Mr. Ducat treated them differently to other firms, and made a special stipulation about the trade in arms when writing to Mr. Fracis. Mr. Fracis asserts that it was done because Mr. Gaskin was interested in the other firms and was opposed to his own. I do not know that there is any real ground for this assertion, and the statement made to me by Mr. Gaskin, in my opinion goes to disprove it, as neither he nor Mr. Sequeira, the other uncovenanted Assistant, appear to have taken any steps to bring the evasion of theobjeciton made in Vir. Ducat's letter to the notice of my prede cessor, Colonel Wilson. If Mr. Gaskin was really hostile to the firm of Messrs. Fracis, Times it is not clear why he allowed them to go on importing arms to Bahrein in spite of the letter of the 7th JulyJ which he said to have inspired. 20. Apart from the question of the reason for Mr. Ducat's special warning to Messrs. Some of the Residency staff knew that Messrs. Fracis, 1 imes, it is clear that some members of Fracil, Times &amp; Co. were importing arms with the the Residency were undoubtedly aware of what ^!onr 0,OUtaBe ' tinS ' &gt; ' te °' Mr ' Uu&lt;:at ' s I&gt;IJ ' was going on, and knew of the connection bet- ween Mr. Fracis and Agha Mohamed Rahim. I cannot, however, think that it had ever been brought to the notice of my predecessor, Colonel F. A. Wilson, or of his First Assisstant, and until that is established, I consider the Residency cannot be said to have been cognisant of the fact that which the First Assistant had requested them not to engage in. As far as I personally am responsible, I am able to say that I took the matter in hand as soon as I got to know of it, and heard nothing from my predecessor when I took over charge which would lead me to think that he was cognisant of the real state of affairs at Bahrein. 21. The Sheikh attached the arms in January while I was at Maskat and the Mekran The Sheikh attached the arms in lanuary 1898. Coast. 1 he fact was mentioned bv Mohamed Account of myown visit to Bahrein in February. Rahim in a letter to his nephew, who was then at Bushire, and he informed Mr. Fracis and Gaskin, who told my First Assistant, Mr. Prideaux. The latter reported the matter by a telegram, which I received at Jask on the 28th January I arrived at Bahrein on the 4th February, and I saw the Sheikh on board the Lawrence the same afternoon. I landed the next day, and inspected the godowns where the arms were stored in the morning ; I thought at first of putting the Residency seals on the doors of the godowns, as we had done at Bushire, but soon found that there were serious objections to my doing so, as a thorough examination of the arms, which was absolutely necessary, if I sealed the doors, would take several days, and, moreover, it was impossible for me to arrange for their safe custody. 1 told the Sheikh, therefore, that as he had attached the arms he must remain responsible for them till the question of the jus tification of his action was settled. I am confident that the Government will approve of my action, which was, I believe, the only course open to me at all the time. 22. Though I had nothing to do with the attachment of the arms, there were reasons The British authorities had nothing to do with against their release until the question of the the attachment of the arms. Sheikh's justification for his action and the ap peal of Messrs. Fracis, Times against it had been fully investigated, and as I had gone to Bahrein chiefly to ask the Sheikh to agree to measures for stopping the arms traffic, I could not at the same time have pressed him to set free a large quantity, which he maintained he had a right to confiscate, until I received the orders of Government. Mr. Fracis has referred to my not again landing, and to the delay there occurred in giving him my memorandum. This was due to the state of the weather, which prevented my again visiting Bahrein. The weather only moderated in the evening of the 7th. when an agent from Mr. Fracis came off, to whom the paper was given. Mr. Fracis, though warned that delay in submitting his appeal against the attachment of his arms would act prejudicially to his own interests, did not address me till April last. His contention that his claim lies not against Sheikh but against the British Government appeared inadmissible, and 1 informed him, in reply, that this was my opinion, sending him at the same time copies of the letters I had received from the Sheikh and Agha Mahomed Rahim. His reply to this letter reached me at Shiraz late in September, and I took up, the further inquiry immediately on my return to Bushire, after the arrival of Agha Mohamed Rahim and his nephew, who were summoned from Bahrein, 23. I found on my return that Mr. Fracis had written to my First Assistant, asking for information regarding the case between himself and Agha Mohamed Rahim, and C927FD22 also the complaints made by the Banians at Bahrein. Mahomed Rahim gave me to understand, in April last, that he was about to bring a suit against the firm, and I was under the impression, when I wrote my report from Shiraz in July, that this had been done Mohamed Rahim has informed me, however, that what he meant was that he wished the settlement of the accounts between him and the firm for sale of arms at Bahrein, as well as other transactions here and at Basrah, submitted to an ' Ijlas,' or Commercial Court, under the supervision of the Residency. There is a civil suit between the parties going on in the Turkish Courts at Basrah, and it is probable that the Agent was referring to it when he spoke to me in April. The complaint brought by the syndicate of Banians at Bahrein was against Agha Mohamed Rahim, and not directly against Messrs. Fracis, Times. They stated that the agent was bringing in goods belonging to Mr. Fracis at the privileged rate allowed to himself, and that they were suffering loss in consequence. 24. 1 would, in conclusion, offer the following observations, for the information of Government, and to assist in the final eneral observations. disposal of the arms attached by the Sheikh, and of the claim for compensation advanced by Messrs. Fracis, Times. Mv views are the result of a consideration of the evidence now before me, and they 'may be modified, if I obtain more later on. They will not, further, prejudice any judicial inquiry I may be called on to hold. It appears to me that the Sheikh gave the concession with the object of getting a few arms for himself, without realizing how it would be used or what it would lead to. The condition (1) allowing the Vizier to return the concession, and (2) forbidden the sale of arms in Bahrein and on the Arab Coast were, I think, inserted to enable the Sheikh to stop the traffic if it became dangerous. From a political point of view, he was, I consider, justified in endeavouring to recall the concession when he found what was going on, and I am also of opinion that it was liable to be withdrawn. On this point, however, legal advice will no doubt be necessary, and we ought alsi to obtain further proofs of the fact that arms were purchased from the concessionaires by persons living in places where sales were forbidden in the concession. This can only be done on the spot ; and I will, if so desired, visit Bahrein and the Arab Coast shortly and collect evidence. I will also, at the same time, obtain an explanation from the Sheikh as to the apparent discrepancy between the reasons he has given to me for his attachment of the arms and that contained in his letter to Mr. Fracis. As I have said, I think this can be explained ; but I will reserve a final opinion till I have questioned Sheikh Esa himself. 1 he translation of the Concession was made in my office. I am sending a copy of the Arabic original, and would suggest that it may be carefully scrutinized by an expert, and that a true translation may be sent to me, if the one I have is found incorrect. The Sheikh was no doubt encouraged to proceed against the arms traffic to Bahrein by the knowledge that the British Government disapproved of it, and had assisted in the confiscation of arms elsewhere. It is also possible that Messrs. Fracis I imes &amp; Co., might have found means to make the Sheikh withdraw his opposition if he had not known that we would support him. ' Granting these possibilities, however, the fact remains that the Sheikh wished to withdraw the concession long before the British Government moved in the matter of the arms traffic, and that his granting the concession, his desire to stop the traffic, and finally his attachment of the arms, were his own acts, without any advice or oromotini on part of the British authorities. Whatever share Agha Mohamed Rahim took in these transactions was as a private individual, and not as a British Agent at Bahrein The question of a robbery, or theft, of the arms has not been lost sight of, but will be duly investigated when the general question is settled ; and I think that the arms them selves should be surveyed by an expert as soon as convenient-first, to establish thrfr ongm when many will, I thmk. be found to be of Belgian manufacture; and, second to check them and see .f any determrat,on or damage has really occurred since they were attached. It will then have to be decided what should be done with the arms t Hn tw think it is desirable that they should be left at Bahrein indefinitely, or until the question disposed ot tr betWeen the fir,n and A g ha Mohamed Rahim, are finally These matters involve inquiries which may take some tim^ anrl movr oi * 1 C^V? alpr0 rt in ^i. andI / 0Ubti£it is sate t0 ,eave such a 'tock of arms at'a place like Bahrein, which might, under certain eventualities, such as the death of the nrp sent Sheikh, etc., become the scene of trouble and disorder Ir, , be possible to guard the arms and they might pass into the hands nf employ them against ourselves, for we'are b'onnd'To prTect'onr d to maintain peace and order in the place. J Bahrein, and /23 I venture, therefore, to suggest that the arms should be handed back to the firm, on the condition that they remove them from the Gulf, and do not attempt to sell them there, or, if it is considered that the firm are not entitled to have them back, that we should bring them to Bushire or remove them to British India. In offering this opinion, I would point out that, although Mr. Fracis was wel 1 aware of the conditions in the concession, and though the firm appear to have carried on the traffic as a speculation pure and simple for their own profit, without any regard for the wishes of the Sheikh or consideration of the danger to which they were exposing him and his family, as well as the inhabitants of Bahrein, by selling indiscriminately, the cir cumstances under which the traffic was started render it doubtful, if we should permit the entire confiscation of the property of a British firm by a Ruler like the She'ikh of Bahrein. M. J. Meade. The Sultan of Maskat's claim for compensation discussed and negatived, 1899, 48. Early in 1899 the Sultan of Maskat put in a claim for compensation for Secret E. ^ oss st ^ te ^ had sustained in conse- Pro. Nos. 309—310, July 1800. quence of his co-operation with Her Majes- 3 9 3 ' } 99 \ ty's Government in the suppression of the arms traffic and more especially in the case of the seizure of the S. S. ' Balu chistan.' The claim was based upon the fact that a short time previously the Sultan had farmed the customs for $140,000; then thinking that the customs would derive benefit from the policy of the British Government, he took the action of re-selling the contract during its period of currency for $170,000, in order to get the expected profit himself. Subsequently the British Government, in pursuance of the same policy, seized the cargo of the ' Baluchistan ' in Maskat waters. Thereupon, the custom's farmer, being disappointed in his expectation, induced the Sultan to take $145,000 or $25,000 less than the price of the re-sale, and agreed that the duty on further consignments of arms arriving by other ships after the ' Baluchistan ' should be taken by the Sultan. The view taken by the Government of India was that, having regard to the finding of the local court of enquiry, and to Article 6 of the Treaty of 1891, it was very doubtful whether the Sultan or the customs contractor could have claimed customs dues upon the arms in the ' Baluchistan,' even had they not been seized, as the goods were in transit. Further, that not only did the Sultan apparently suffer no loss by the confiscation of arms which were intended for Persia, but, on the contrary, had gained $5,000 by the action of the British Government. Also that the Sultan could, under the revised contract, take duty cn consignments of arms in any ships arriving after the ' Baluchistan,' and in addition there was the chance of his getting a moiety of the value of the con fiscated cargo. Under these circumstances, the Government of India were unable to admit that a claim for compensation had been established, and the Sultan was informed accordingly. Arrival at Maskat of Monsieur Goguyer, 1899. 49. Writing on the 10th April, 1899, Major Fagan reported further parti- culars regarding the recent arrival at Secret E., July 1899, Nos. 370-457- Maskat of the two French subjects—Mon sieur Antouin Goguyer and his assistant. It transpired that Monsieur Goguyer had visited the principal British Indian traders in the place and had endeavoured to persuade them to give him orders for arms and ammunition of any description they might require. He had pointed out that by placing their orders with him, they would escape all the risks at present attending the arms traffic in consequence of the action of the British authorities, and he undertook to accept all risks of seizure and to send the arms in dhows flying the French flag to any port in the Persian Gulf, asking in return that any trader placing an order with him should at the same time deposit one per cent, of the purchase money in advance and should undertake to give him 2^- per cent, of the profits.24 The powers of the Board of Customs regarding munitions of war referred to legal opinion, 1599. 50. In March 1899 the opinion of the law officers of the Crown was taken on the question whether section 139 of the Customs Consolidation Act, 1876 (39 and 40 Vict., cap. 36), empowered the Board of Customs to require, under penalty, names of suppliers and consignees of arms, ammunitions, and munitions of war; the case as laid before the law officers was as follows :— This case is put on the following points:— In December 1897, t ^ e India Office and the Foreign Office expressed a wish to the Board of Customs through the Treasury that, in consequence of large exportation of arms, ammunition, and munitions of war to ports in the Persian Gulf, information could be obtained of the sailing and destination of all ships carrying such cargoes to that part of the world, the object being to facilitate the measures which Her Majesty's Government were adopting in those seas in order to check this illicit traffic. Besides the supply of information which the Board at once agreed to furnish, and took steps accordingly, it was pressed upon them also to take if they possibly could do so, measures not only to have and to impart knowledge of the departure of the various consignments, but also to closely examine, check, and, if that were legal, to detain them, and especially to find out, if possible, the real suppliers of the goods, and the real consignees. The Board of Customs were obliged to reply that they could supply with these requests to a certain extent only, and that the law they administered would not allow of all that was wished for being done. In order to explain the question at issue it is necessary, at this point, to set out what the law in this respect is. Dutiable goods, which, of course, are never exported, except from bond and goods receiving a drawback of duty, are not exported from the United Kingdom without the putting in, before they are laden of certain documents, which constitute the ' Entries ' outwards of the goods ; and any shipment not in accordance with those entries would be prevented. This, however, is not the case generally as to /ree goods, which all arms and ammunitions are. Free goods are laden without any previous ' Entry,' and, although all goods about to be exported may, at any time, be examined, in practice, unless there is any special reason for care or suspicion, free goods are laden and exported without any check on them at all. While this, however, is so, as to the goods themselves, they do not leave the country altogether unnoticed. For the purpose of trade returns, and statistics, it is provided that the exporter of free goods shall (under liability to a penalty) Section n of Customs and Inland render, within six days after the final Revenue Act, 1881 (44 and 45 Vict. c. clearance of the ship, a full description of 12). the goods he has exported, by a document called a ' Specification,' and these specifications are liable to be tested with the manifest of all the cargo in his ship which has, within the same time, to be rendered by the Master or his Agent. Such is the general law as to free goods ; and the Board of Customs pointed out that, under it, they could do nothing to prevent the sailing of the goods. There are, however, exceptions to this absence of provision as to free goods. 39 and 40 Vict., c, 35. section 139 of the Customs Consolida- tion Act, 1876, it is provided that, as to all articles which are 'explosive' within the Explosives Acts, there shall be pre- entry of them, under penalty in the event of this not being complied with before lading on board the ship. As regards 'ammunition,' a portion of the articles to which the care of the Foreign and India Offices was directed, and which are ' explosives,' this pro vision met a large part of their requirements, but it did not do so at all as to another most material part, viz., arms, in relation to which a most important case had arisen of large quantities of arms shipped to Bushire in the Persian Gulf. The section, however, in question (section 139) contains a provision going further than explosives. It contains a power for the Board, by order under their hands, to apply the pre-entry provisions, beyond explosives, to any goods where the Board are satisfied that ' the public interests rendered such a course expedient;' and it was pointed out that the Board would readily make such an25 order as to arms, if the Treasury so directed. This suggestion was approved of by the controlling authorities, and an order to that effect was made, and issued on the 36th February 1898, applying to :— Cannon, machine guns, and other ordnance. Muskets, rifles, revolvers, and small arms of other sorts. Other firearms. Swords, cutlasses, bayonets, and other arms not being firearms Torpedoes, shells, and shot, not containing explosives. (These articles, if charged, have to be entered as explosives.) Parts of any of the above are to be entered as such under the appropriate heading. For the convenience of Counsel the portion of section 139 relating to this is here copied : 0 The Commissioner of Customs may, by order urider their hanrls, require due entry and clearance before shipment, and in such manner as they may direct, of any goods intended for exportation or carriage coastwise, or being satisfied that the public interests render such course expedient, and if upon such entry the goods shall not be found to correspond with the particulars contained therein, they may be detained until the cause be explained to the satisfaction of the Commissioners of Customs, they may thereupon restore the same on such terms as they may see fit.' The order thus made did not achieve all that the Foreign Office and India Office had expressed a wish for. It did not authorise detention of arms, etc., provided the pre-entry requirements were complied with; and the Board of Customs pointed out that detention in itself could be effected only by a Proclamation or Order in Council, under section 8 of the Customs and Inland Revenue Act, 1879; but the circumstances were considered to be scarcely of sufficient gravity to call for this strong measure. Then, again, the request for accurate information as to the real suppliers of the goods, and the real consignees, was left in a doubtful state, and this is the point on which the opinion of the law officers is sought. This information is regarded as of the greatest importance by the India Office, and they have strongly urged on the Customs the acquisition of it, if possible. It is the opinion of the Board of Customs (and I have so advised them) that they have not a clear legal position to absolutely demand this information ; and the question is whether this opinion is right or not. The India Office, while not wishing to withdraw any doubt on the Customs view, have expressed a wish to have the superior opinion of the law officers. In order to understand the question, some explanation must be given as to the Customs decuments or ' Entries, ' and as to the use made of them. 1 he forms of these documents are given in the Schedule to the Customs Consolida tion Act, 1876, and it will be seen, upon examining them, they are very carefully complied, requiring from the person rendering them only just so much information as is necessary for the revenue, and other public purpose. For instance, in the report of the ship and of the cargo, thereof under section 50, there is a provision that the name of the consignee shall be given ; that is to say, the person who stands as such in the bills of lading from which the report is made up by the master. This statement, the name of the importing consignee, is desirable in these documents, because this general report by the master of the contents of his ship, each consignee of any item of cargo has to make 'entry ' of that item of cargo sepa rately. The general statement by the master can, by this means, be checked against the particular statements by each consignee, and if there is any omission the report facilitates inquiry as to why due ' entry ' has not been made. Here, therefore, a certain amount of what may be considered, in a way, a trade secret, is to be made known to the Board of Customs ; but in no other form in the Schedule is there any provision for diving into such private facts. Of course, any documents put in either as to an import or as to an export must naturally be signed, and the person signing it must, in some way, assume the character of an importer or exporter; but it is provided in every form that there is no absolute necessity, even here, for the name of the importer or the exporter transpiring, because all these documents may be signed by agents ; and with the exception of this statement as regards the importer and exporter, or, as it may be, his agent, the forms are merely descriptive of the articles of commerce C927FD26 themselves, and with no information as the source of supply, or the individuals for whom they are destined. With r-fgard to most of these forms, it is provided in the Act that they may be modified in such manner as the Commissioners may, from time to time, think fic, and this is, no doubt, a very wide provision. At the same time it has always been doubted whether a modification of any of the forms, so as to introduce an element of information which seems to have been studiously omitted in them all, and which would be raising a very large question of inquisitorial action into the movement of trade, would be a modification within the meaning of the power given for this purpose. Then there is this point to be mentioned. In connection with the Customs Service there is an insurance office for those who are in the service called the ' Customs Fund ' and for many years prior to 1880 the Directors of this Society published a daily journal called the ' Bill of Entry,' in which they gave parti culars, in London, and at some of the larger outports, of all consignments inwards and outwards each day. This journal is largely bought in the commer cial world, and has an extension and profitable circulation, in giving the parti culars in this journal of the imports and exports this Society were in the habit of stating (so far as they could be learnt from the entries) the names of the importers and of the exporters of goods. Frequently these names were of very little value, as they were only the names of importing and exporting agents ; but the names were given for what they were worth. In the year 1880, it was decided that this publication (which was producing a profit of about ;£ 10,000 annually, a sum produced by making use of documents obtained at the public expenses and by public officials) ought no longer to be used as a source of profit for an Insurance Society, but that the profit, whatever it might be, ought to go into the Public Exchequer. The publication, therefore, was, by order of the Treasury, transferred from the Society to the' Satistical Office of the Customs, with a certain amount of compensation to the officials who had been engaged in the work in the service of the Society. When this transfer was made, the question was raised by trader whether it would not be right to ask for the suppression altogether in this publication of the names (whether agent or not) ot exporters. It was considered that it was oamaging to traders to have secrets of who were exporting goods and where they were going to, made public ; and after a considerable inquiry by a Depart mental Committee, it was decided that these facts in the publication should be for the future omitted. Of course, there is a considerable difference between stating names in a public journa , and requiring the statement of them on Customs documents • but in this case the requirement, if it were made, would be one, not for the purpose ot assisting the Customs in any matter connected with the revenue but for transmission to anrther department of the Government in order that some check and watch might be placed upon the doings of the particular people whose names would be thus extracted. It has been thought right to point out the above trend of idea throughout the Customs documents and publications as to how far these kinds of secrets are to be required and to be made known. There would, no doubt, be a areat deal to be said as to the strong reasons of high state why in the present insfance the information should be obtained and imparted ; but, on the other hand, it has to be considered, on the part of the Board of Customs, whether they can make a requirement as to which, .f it should not be complied with, they would be power ess to enforce it, and as to which it is doubtful whether they could lay their Wer on any provision by which they could make a refusal into Court. So far, of course, as obtaining a signature of a nominal exnorter on the entry which is put m, this no doubt, could be done, and is done and such information, so far it goes, could be made known to the India Office This however, would by no means supply all that is wanted, and would be little to rely It should be pointed out that, although in nearly every other instance where an entry or report whatever it may be, is required under the Customs Act -There is a form provided in the bchedule, there is, as it happens, no form prodded with regard to section ■ 39, and so, therefore, it might possibly be held haf as regaros an entry under that secfon, the Board have a perfectly free hand27 and could in relation to goods held to be of such importance, make rec|uirements which were not thought necessary in ordinary cases; but when I asked whether a form under this section could be made thus stringent. I said that 1 thought it was exceedingly doubtful, but that possibly it might be justified under the words in regard to •' public interests, ' on the ground, that is to say, that if public interests were strong enough to render an order necessary at all, they would be strong enough to render inquisitorial action also justifiable. Upon this opinion the Board thought it undesirable to put the requirement of the names of suppliers and consignees into the form of entry which they directed to be used, but they instructed their Collectors to try, as far as possible, to get all such information in this respect as regards any consignment as they possibly could, and that when they made a return of a consignment (which in each case they were instructed to do) to the Board for transmission to the India Office, they should fill the particulars in this respect, so far as they had been able to obtain them. In a great many instances the Collectors, by their industry and influence, have been able to supply these particulars, but in a recent case an entry havin^ been put in, signed by an agent for the exporters, a refusal has been made to furnish information as to the suppliers of the goods, and information, also as to the persons or authorities for whom they may be intended. The goods con sisted of large supplies of arms and ammunition, and were going to Bushire on the Persian Gulf. The objection to give the iniormation is couched in these words:— ' We really cannot understand for what statistical purpose these are required, and as this disclosure regarding our business appears to us unwarranted and most unusual we shall feel obliged by your informing us upon what authority you make the request. As a matter of principle, we strongly object to supply to anybody the names of our suppliers and customers for any goods, and we must respectfully decline to do so in this instance unless you can refer us to an Act of Parliament which lays this obligation upon us ' There is only one more point to mention, but to which it is necessary to call the attention of the law officers. Besides the Customs documents which have been referred to, there are, of course, the documents which pass between the traders themselves, as, for instance, invoices and bills of lading. Here a^ain even with these documents before an inquirer, it would not be certain^ having regard to the number of purchases which take place merely on commission from and by middlemen, that the names of the real suppliers of goods and the real consignees of goods, would be discoverable; but, nevertheless, access to these documents would go a long way towards knowledge of the inner history of transactions, and where there is access to these documents available to the Board of Customs it might be argued that they have a right to demand in their forms any facts which the trading documents available to them micrht be expected to disclose. With regard to these trading documents, there is access to them by the Board of Customs prescribed in two sections of the Customs Act; that is to say in section 65 as to the entries of goods inwards, and in section 'i 1 of the Cus toms and Inland Revenue Act, 1881, in relation to the specifications as to free goods, which have to be rendered within six days after the final clearance of the ship. It has sometimes been urg^d, that the access to these documents provided for in these two instances establishes a general footing that they may always be demanded bv the Commissioners of Customs whenever they think fit. I have not, however, so thought myself. It seems to me that this, being an inquisito rial power, must be read very strictly, and confined simply to those instances in regard to which the Act specially lays it down ; and as regards goods exported there is a very good reason why it is provided in relation to the specifications for free goods and not in regard to any verification of the entry of dutiable or drawback goods ; because as regards specifications for free goods they f-is stated earlier in this case) are not rendered until the ship and the goods have departed, and when there is no power to test the information by examination of the goods themselves. Upon the above the Law Officers are asked to kindly state whether or not they think that, under section 139 of the Customs Act f the Board have a power28 to modify the form of entry which they have so far prescribed for the purpose of There is a general provision, under that section, and to put into that entry section 131 of the Customs Act, that any also a requirement that the true name goods for which entry before shipment shall be given of the supplier of the goods is required, and which are shipped, exported, and the true name also of the wit out due clearance, shall be forfeited, consignee at the port of destination to whom the ^oods are about to be consigned, and to require that such statements shall be truly made, and in the event of their not being made, or being made in such a way as to give reasonable ground for believing that they are untrue, to take action for the detention of the goods until the requirements are thoroughly and truly complied with, or the ultimate forfeiture of the goods. Letter from the Persian Ministry for Foreign Affairs prohibiting the Importation of Arms, dated the 6th Shaban (3rd July 1881). 5i-Since the right of purchasing arms and munitions of war abroad, and intro ducing the same into Persia, belongs to the Persian Government who exercise it through their specially appointed officials, and if thj^ absolute right were not exclusively confined to the Government and everybody who thought fit to do so were allowed to purchase such articles and introduce them into the country, this great governmental privilege would become obsolete, and considerable evils would result to the Shah. Therefore His Majesty the Shah has issued stringent orders that no one shall import arms of any descriptian whatsoever into this coat - try from abroad, and any person in whose possession arms of foreign makers aie found will be liable to have them confiscated by Government. By His Majesty's orders the above is communicated to Your Excellency in order that you may bring it to the knowledge of British merchants and subjects so that, being informed of it, they may be careful to avoid trading in these pro hibited goods, and so that no injury may result to them from ignorance of the present Regulation. (S eal of MIRZA FAUD KHAN, Persian Minister for Forein Affairs) (Official seal of Persian Governmeat.) Registered and seen in the Persian Foreign Office, This is a true copy of the original document. 10th Shaval, 1316 (21st February 1899). (Seal of MUSHIR ed DOWLEH, Minister for Foreign Affairs. The copy is a true copy of the original document. 10th Shaval, 1316 (21st February 1899). These are to certify that the foregoing is a true and faithful translation of its original in the Persian language existing in the archives of His Majesty's Lega tion at Tehran. Dated at Her Majesty's Legation at Tehran, this 24th day of February 1899. H. P, PI COT, Lieutenant-Colonel, Oriental Secretary* 52. The opinion of the Law Officers was thus stated :— ' We are of opinion that the Board have not power to require these further particulars. The power under section 139 is merely to order before shipment entry with such particulars as would ordinarly be made after shipment. The provision that the entry is to be ' in such manner as they may direct ' does not confer the power to require such further parti culars, any rrore than the similar words in section no of the same Act, or section n of the Act of 1881 which now takes its place.'29 The India Office in expressing the special acknowledgments of Lord George Hamilton for the full and clear information contained in the case laid before the Law Officers by the Board of Customs, further stated that— ' It is clear that as the law stands, very little control can be exercised in the country Over the trade in arms and ammunition to the Persian Gulf.' The Secretary of State for India in a Despatch (Secret No. 15), dated 28th April 1899, forwarded, for the information of the Government of India, a copy of a letter from the Admiralty, dated 17th April, drawing special attention to the very large shipments of arms and ammunition to the region of the Persian Gulf during the last four months. It was mentioned that in consequence of the standing of the law at home, it was impossible to compel the disclosure of the names of supplies and consignees of arms shipped from English ports, and that therefore little effective control could be exercised on the trade. Lord George Hamilton went on to say that the consequences of this large trade in arms and ammunition deserved anxious consideration. So long as large quantities of arms and ammuni tion reached Oman and the Persian Gulf and were disposed of by whatever means, there would be the probabilitity of their passing into the hands of the population of the southern provinces of Persia, this at the same time increasing the disorder and insecurity of those provinces and decreasing the power of the Persian authorities to cope with the evil. There would also be the risk of a portion of the traffic reaching Afghanistan, and passing into the hands of the turbulent tribes of the North-West Frontier of the Punjab, or with the dominions of the Khan of Kelat, thereby aggravating the difficulties of the Indian Government in the task of preserving peace on the frontier and peace and order in the territory of Baluchistan. For checking the traffic which might tend to produce these consequences, it appeared that Her Majesty's Government must at present mainly depend on the co-operation of the Persian Government, on the willingness of the local authorities to carry out the instructions of that Government, and on their power to make those orders effective. Importation of Arms from Maskat to the Italian Protectorate on the Benadir Coast, 1899. 53. In April 1899, the British Consul-General at Zanzibar wrote stating that Secret E., November .899, Nos. 37- J 1 ? 6 'if 1 ' 13 ' Consul-General had informed 40&gt; him that a considerable quantity of arms and ammunition had recently been imported into the Italian Protectorate on the Benadir Coast, but that he could not give any particulars as to the description or number of rifles imported, but' he said he had been informed by a Somali, who had confessed to participating in the traffic that they had come in dhows from Maskat and Jibuti, but more specially from Maskat. The Consul at Zanzibar had informed his Italian colleague that the trade in arms and ammunition between Africa and Oman was one which His Majesty's Agents in both countries had always done their best to stop, but that although he felt confident that any attempt at their exportation from the port of Maskat would be defeated by the vigilance exercised there by British cruisers and officials, it was very probable that the trade might be carried on with some of the smaller ports in Southern Arabia, over which it was impossible to maintain any adequate surveillance. In replying to this letter, Major Fagan said that he gathered that there was a misapprehension as to the nature of orders issued to British officials of war in Maskat waters regarding the arms traffic. The instructions were to seize any arms or ammunition (found on vessels flying the British, Persian or Maskat flags) destined for Persia or British India, but that no authority existed for interfering with any arms traffic that might exist between Maskat and any portion of Africa. Further in a Despatch No. 216, dated the 2nd November 1899, we informed the Secretary of State that— ' ' There is ground|for believing that the apprehensions of the Italian Consul -General are not altogether unfounded, and that a traffic in arms is actually carried on between the smaller ports of the Sultanate and tha African Coast. Wc are now making endeavours C927FD30 to secure the active assistance of His Highness the Sultan in checking the arms traffic in the Persian Gulf, and should these efforts be successful, it may be possible to take similar steps with regard to the traffic between Maskat and the African coast.' Major Pagan's views on the necessity of winning the Slutan of Maskat over to our side in order to deal effectively with the Arms traffic, 1899. 54. The Political Agent, Maskat, in submitting his views regarding the Secret E, November 1899, Nos. in a y ms at and &gt;m thence to 205—255. opposite coast, briefly reviewed the situa tion. Referring to the seizure of the ' Baluch istan, ' Major Fagan said that there was no doubt that the Sultan scarcely realized, before this capture of the arms was effected, what the result of the agree ment to which he had become a party would be and this is amply verified both by the remark that he made when he heard of the seizure which was duly reported to you and by the efforts which he made to evade the obligations under which he had placed himself to hold a court to adjudicate as to the legality of the seizure. There is equally little doubt that his objection was, and still is, simply due to his knowledge of the fact that any interference with, or checking of the arms traffic means loss of revenue to himself, more especially since the law of prohibitions which has been put into force in Persia renders it necessary that arms intended for Persian ports should be landed at Maskat (where they pay duty) to be ultimately smuggled into Persia as opportunity offers. Major Fagan further stated that from the very first His Highness had done his utmost to nullify his agreement of January 1898 :— (1) by encouraging, by every means in his power, the importation of arms ; (2) by giving purchases of small quantities of arms, passes showing that the arms purchased are for Sohar or some other ports in His Highness' dominions, notwithstanding that he is fully aware that the arms are really intended for Persia ; (3) by refusing to condemn arms seized by us even though the evidence as to their evident destination is as complete as circumstances permit. ' It is obvious, therefore,' wrote Major Fagan, ' that if this traffic is to be put a stop to, it can only be done by winning over the Sultan to our side. Money is what he is in need of and if he is to be persuaded at all it will only be done by the agency of the rupees. If my views are accepted, I would respectfully suggest that in the first place His Highness should be given a lump sum of Rs. 26,250 for the permission accorded to the Government whereby they were enabled to seize the arms on the ' Baluchistan,' and that, secondly, a percentage should be promised him on the value of any arms seized in badans or native craft in His Highness'waters and found by His Highness' Court to be bound for Persia. I have suggested the payment of a percentage rather than a fixed monthly sum because I think we would be more certain of His Highness' active assistance of the amount we give him depended on the successful results of his co-operation. The seizure of a few native craft with arms on board for Persia and the confiscation of their cargo of arms, would, I feel convinced, be attended with excellent results. It would be immaterial whether the arms so captured were of British or foreign importation because they are purchased by natives before they leave Maskat, and therefore complications arising from foreign ownership would not be encountered unless French proteges at Sur and other places, took up the trade, which at present is not the case. . ' I am not aware whether the Sultan would be ready to co-operate with us on these terms. He is sharp enough to see that although such a procedure would be at first very profitable it would never theless result in the slaughter of the goose which lay the golden egg, but it is quite certain that without his3i co-operation we can do nothing ; but with it the traffic will soon cease to be lucrative.' With reference to the above representation, the Political Resident in'the Persian Gulf was informed on the 7th October 1899, that while the Government of India were not prepared to reconsider their previous decision not to pay the Sultan a lump sum on account of compensation for losses, at the same time it was recog nised that success in preventing the smuggling of arms from Maskat to the Persian Coast must largely depend upon the Sultan's cordial co-operation in the measures which might be adopted, and that it was advisable to enlist his sympathy and assistance by giving him a direct interest in the results. Further, that whatever the decision might be, regarding the seizure of arms of the ' Baluchistan,' the Government of India would not be unwilling to recognise the Sultan's right to a predominant share in the disposition and value of all arms which through his co-operation might be seized in Maskat waters while in course of being smuggled in native vessels across to the Persian or Makran Coast, Suggested concession to the Sultan of Maskat, 1899. 55. In a despatch No. 206, dated the 26th October 3899, the Government of India recommended for the favourable consideration of Her Majesty's Govern ment that, if it should be decided not to interfere on behalf of the traders whose arms were seized by the Sultan's order, the Sultan should be allowed to keep the arms, or to receive the value of them. I Captain Cox's report on the arms traffic at Maskat, 1899. 56. Under date the 14th November 1899 Captain Cox forwarded a report o . T- A M . regarding the traffic in arms and ammunition Secret E., Apr.I .900, Nos. .07-14.. J Mas f at From iti it app e ar ed that for the five months ending with the 31st October 1899, the total arms sold was 3i79 2 by the British subjects reporting their sales. The manner of distribution of these munitions after arrival in Maskat was, roughly speaking, as follows :— (a) 5 per cent, is not re-exported, but'comes into use in Maskat and the immediate interior. (b) 40 per cent, goes to the Pirate Coast and Koweit. (c) 30 per cent, is divided between Lingah, Mashur and Hindian, {d) 20 per cent, goes to Bunder Abbas. From these estimates it will be seen that over 90 per cent, of the arms left Maskat again by sea. They appeared to be exported principally indriblets ; hardly a dhow leaving the port without a few. In many cases they were covered by passes under the seal and signature of the Sultan, setting forth that they were consigned to subjects at Sohar and that neighbourhood (between Maskat and- Cape Mussen- dum). Others were no doubt smuggled without passes ; generally, it was believed, n bales of dry limes or bundles of date mats. Captain Cox further stated that he had been informed that previous to the seizure of arms from the ' Baluchistan' parties of Afghans and other Pathans used to pay periodical visits to Maskat and make extensive purchases ; they had now ceased to visit Maskat, but had turned their attentions to Bunder Abbas instead. Those munitions which went to the Pirate Coast were for the most part taken up by the tribes of the Hinterland, from whom the demand appeared to be strong and constant; the chief depot for the distribution of them on that coast was said to be Ajwan, a small port near Shargah. From this report it became evident that if a British Consul were located at Bunder Abbas, we should be in a better position to get the Persian Government to prevent the smuggling of arms to that place. It was also thought that many of the dhows found their way to Gwadur,32 The right of seizure discussed with the Legislative Department, 1899. 57. In connection with the seizure of arms being conveyed from Maskat to Persia or other ports, the seizure might be— (i) from Maskat vessels in Maskat territorial waters. Arms so seized would clearly belong to the Sultan. (n) from Maskat vessels outside of Maskat territorial waters, i.e. t anywhere between the Coast of Oman and Persia. The second proclama tion of the Saltan of 13th January 1898 gave to British vessels the power of search and confiscation in such cases. The Legislative Department were asked to advice whether, as a matter of law, the arms so confiscated were equally the property of the Sultan with those mentioned under (i). F The question was also asked that supposing the arms to be carried in a vessel flying a Persian flag, whose property in view of the proclamations would they be, {a) if seized by a British vessel in Maskat territorial waters, {b) if seized, outside those limits, anywhere between the two Coasts ? The opinion of the Legislative Department was as follows:— 1. Arms seized in Maskat vessels in Maskat waters, —The Sultan allows the seizure and we have not agreed to give him the arms. In strict law, we might keep them; but the Sultan has evidently a strong claim to them. We ought to agree either to give him the arms (or compensation, if admissible) or to submit the matter to a Maskat Court. If the point is put to it, the court will probably adjudge the arms to the Sultan. 2. Arms seized in Maskat vessels outside of Maskat Same answer generally as to question 1. If the seizure is in Persian waters, I do not think we are bouud to give the arms to Persia, but Persia will probably think we are. We ought perhaps to make some compensation for making the seizure in the Shah's territorial waters. » 3. Arms seized in Persian ships— {a) In Maskat 'waters, -We can only seize them under the authority given in the Sadr-i-Azam s letter, and we have bound ourselves to hand them over to Persia. We have not bound ourselves to com pensate the Sultan of Maskat for loss of customs duty (if the goods are distined for one of his ports) or for violating the peace of his territorial waters, but he has a strong claim to compensate on both grounds. ^ We might ask Persia to pay the compensation, or we might treat it as a charge on the property handed over: but Persia may contend that this is not in the agreement. (3) Outside Maskat waters. We must hand the arms over to Persia, and Maskat has a claim to compensation for loss of customs if they were for a Maskat port, but not so strong a claim as in case («). I append a few general observations on the legal aspects of the case. It seems to me that the present situation is not satisfactory, and that we should endeavour to make our position stronger, as opportunities may occur. If in time of peace a British officer, acting on the orders of his Government, seizes a Maskat ship and confiscates the cargo, the owner has no le^al remedy • he must apply to the Sultan to protect him. The Sultan has told his subjects that he is co-operating m the suppression of the traffic in arms, and that he will not protect them if they engage in that traffic. The property in the goods seized passes in the first instance to the Govern ment which orders the seizure j the manner in which they are to be disposed of must be settled by diplomatic agreement. We have hitherto declined to give the Sultan any general assurance tha we will give him the arms we seize ; each case, therefore, must be settled as itarises.33 What the Sultan may fairly claim, it is not easy to say. If we were framing an agreement we might offer him :— (1) Arms belonging to Maskat subjects or a money compensation, if it Is) thought unsafe to give him the arms. (2) In the case of goods destined for Maskat which would have paid customs duty there, compensation for loss of duty. (3) In the case of arms seized in Maskat waters, some payment in acknow ledgment of the Sultan's rights. The Sultan may possibly claim arms belonging to Persian or British ownersj seized in Maskat waters, and adjudged by a Maskat Court to be duly confiscated ; but this claim is very questionable. If the owners are Persian subjects, the arms may be claimed by the Shah under the loosely expressed agreement we have with him. If they are British subjects, the question will be taken to an English Court, as in the case of the ' Baluchistan '. In that case the plaintiff failed, because the title to the arms was held to be resjudtcaia, having been decided by a Maskat Court, composed of the Prime Minister and the Commander-in- Chief. It is unsatisfactory, both from tbe legal and from the political point of view, that British officers seizing the property of British subjects, should have to rely on the judgment of a Maskat or Persian tribunal. It may be observed that, while we rely on the Maskat judgment, we hesitated to give effect to it. The Court means to decide in favour of the Sultan, yet we delayed giving up the arms. But for this convenient Court and its judgment, it may be doubted whether the Maskat law, as embodied in the notification and proclamation, would have supplied us with a defence. It must be remembered that the territorial waters of a State are not part of its territory. They are a part of the sea, over which the state has rights. Mariners of other nations retain their rights of innocent passage ; and when a British merchant ship is exercising this right, it is not clear that a British officer may seize her cargo because she is contravening the law of Maskat. We have no right to execute Maskat law, except such right as the Sultan confers on us, and an English Court may hold that the British Gov ernment cannot, by making itself the agent of a foreign power, acquire an arbi trary power over British subjects and their property. The same considerations apply to a seizure in Persian territorial waters. The Sadr-i-Azam says we may search vessels ' trading in the Persian Gulf.' His letter is probably a sufficient authority to stop a Persian ship, anywhere in the Gulf and to confiscate arms belonging to Persian owners. But it does not enable us to seize arms of British owners on the high seas ; and if we seize such arms in Persian waters, we are not safe unless we refer the matter to the Persian Court, and place the usual arguments before the judges. The ' Baluchistan ' case shows that our present operations have not yet a sufficient legal basis. We seem to require (1) Agreements with Maskat and Persia, conceding the right to search vessels and confiscate arms, and providing for the manner in which the arms are to be disposed of, and (2) an Imperial Act, forbidding this traffic to British subjects, and empowering our officers to seize arms and ammunition. This would have been a proper case for a joint note in this Department. But I have taken the liberty of going beyond the limits of the reference, and my colleagues prefer to note separately on the questions referred.' The Sultan receives the arms confiscated from the ' Baluchistan, 1900. 58. In a despatch No. 33/ dated the 1st March 1900, the Government of India advised the Secretary of State that orders had been issued for the delivery to His Highness the Sultan of the cases of arms and ammunition, the property of British subjects, which were seized on board the S. S. ' Baluchistan ' by H. M. S. ' Lapwing.' C997FD34 59. As an illustration of the great cunning displayed in the arm trade from ^ t Maskat, Captain Cox referred two distinct Enclosure to No. 137. cases in which dhows had slipped away from port taking advantage of the temporary absence of a warship from Maskat. Revival of Notification No. 1560 of the 1st October 1880. 60. The Secretary of State in a recent despatch had raised the question of * Secret, November .880, Nos. « the advisibility ofreviving the order con- (i 7 — 3 o). tamed in Notification* No. 1060, dated the 1st October 1880, by which arms brought into an Indian port and declared under manifest to be consignments without transhipment to a port on the Persian Gulf were removed from exemption from the provisions of section 6 of the Arms Act. The main reasons for the cancella tion of the Notification would seem to have been that as the direct route from England to Persia via Maskat was open for the importation of arms into Persia, it was no use putting obstacles in the way of importation via an Indian port. Circumstances, however, had now changed. There was no doubt that arms osten- sibily destined for Persia found their way to tribes on the frontier and into Makran, and the measures recently taken by us in concert with the Persian Government to enforce the prohibition (which had technically been in existence since 1881) against importation into Persia had removed any necessity that there might have been for protecting the British India Steam Navigation Company, or any other company trading with Persia via Karachi, from unfair competition with other companies dealing with Persian port direct. As the resuscitation of the old notification would merely have the desirable effect of putting a further obstacle in the way of what was now styled an illicit trade, it was again brought into force by the publication of the following li Notification. —By the Government of India, Home Department. In exercise of the powers conferred by section 37 of the Indian Arms Act, 1878 (XI of 1878), the Governor- General in Council is pleased to cancel the Notification by the Government of India in the Home Department, No. 361, dated the 8th March 1883, and in modification of the orders published in the notification in the same Department No. 1572, dated the 29th August 1879, to declare that arms, ammunition and warlike stores brought into an Indian port, and declared under manifest to be consignments without transhipment to any port on the sea board of the Persian Gulf, shall, until further orders, be liable to the prohibition and direc tions contained in section 6 of the said Act/' The Sultan of Maskat's position as regards certain claims with which he was threatened for seizures on the ' Baluchistan,' 1900. 61. Regarding the handing over to the Sultan of the arms seized on the Secret E., August 1900, Nos. 81— ga. the Resident in the Persian Gulf writing on the 16th July 1900, asked for instructions in respect to certain claims with which the Sultan was threatened in connection with the arms. In reply the position was thus briefly explained ' The Government asserts that the arms, etc., were seized by them under the authority and on behalf of the Sultan, and that the decision of his Court of Law absolved them from any liability for damages. If their plea is upheld, no claim for damages can be, either against the Sultan, or against the Government. If it is upset, a claim for damages will be against the Government who made the seizures, not against the Sultan to whom Govern ment handed over the arms which had been illegally seized.' (I) The Sheikh of Bahrein restores confiscated arm to Messrs. Fracis, Times &amp; Co., 1900. 62. On the 29th April 1900, Captain Kemball reported the intention of the Secret^E., July 1900, Nos. 165—177. Sheikh of Bahrein to dispense with any _ . . . further enquiry into the matter of the con fiscation at Bahrein of the arms and ammunition belonging to Messrs. Fracis Times &amp; Co., and to make them over to the firm. Captain Kemball suggested35 that the arms should be given back to the firm on the understanding that they should be taken out of the Gulf. y It was further suggested that as it was likely that Messrs. Fracis, Times &amp; Co. would endeavour to sell their arms, if released from Bahrein, at Koweit, an omcer should be sent to Koweit to enquire into the arms trade there with a view to some arrangement being made with the Chief. In discussion it was shown that we could not prevent the Sheikh from hand- * Secret E., July 1898, Nos. 432 —469, over arms to Messrs. Fracis, Times No. 464. if he desired to do so : the agreement * , . „ , . b y which he bound himself to prohibit the importation of arms into Bahrein or exportation thereform was entered into by him three months after the seizure of the arms, and could hardly be regarded as binding him to prevent the exportation of arms which he had been forcibly detain ed ;, r ? m L a date an ! erio y t0 the prohibition. We were at liberty to advise the Sheikh, however, that, having regard to that argument and to the actual terms of the concession granted to Messrs. Fracis Times in which it was stipulated that the concessionaire ' should not sell guns to the people of Bahrein. Katr and the Arab Coast, he would be well advised to hand over the arms to Messrs. Fracis limes only on condition that they promised to abide by the terms of the original concession. This would prevent the latter from disposing of the arms anywhere in the Oulf, for if they attemped to land them on the Persian Coast we could seize them in virtue of our agreement with Persia. Agreement with the Sheikh of Koweit prohibiting the arms traffic May 1900. ' 63. The Government of India conveyed sanction to the Bahrein chief restor ing athis descretion the arms to Messrs. Fracis, Times &amp; Co., subject to the above stated condition and on the 26th May 1900 the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf Teported that as theTesult of his visit to Koweit he had concluded an agree ment with the Sheikh absolutely prohibiting the trade in arms. The agreement and jiotification were as follows :— Agreement by Sheikh Muharak-hin-Sahah^ Chief of Koweit. 11 I agree to absolutely prohibit the importation of arms into Koweit or exportation thercform, and to enforce this 1 have issued a notification and proclamation to all concern ed.'' Notification 'by Sheikh Mubarak-bin-Sab ah, Chief of Kowe it. ' Be it known to all who see this that, whereas it has become known to us that the traffic in arms in British India is prohibited, we have, therefore, decided to do all that his in our power to assist the British and Persian Gorernments in putting a stop to his illegal traffic, and we hereby declare that from the date of his notification the importation of arms and ammunition into Koweit and the territory under my control and the exportation of the same are absolutely prohibited. All arms and ammunition imported into any, ports of Koweit territory or exported thereform in future will be seized and confiscated.' Proclamation from Sheikh Mubarak-bin* Sab ah, Chief of Koweit. ' Be it known to all who see this that British and Persian vessels of war have permis sion to search vessels carrying their and our flags in Roweit territorial waters, and to confiscate all arms and ammunition in them, if these arms and ammunition are intended for Indian or Persian or Koweit ports. Koweit vessels found in Indian and Persian waters by British and Persian waters by British and Persian vessels of war suspected to contain arms and ammunition for Indian, Persian and Koweit ports are liable to be searched by the said vessels, and all such arms and ammunition found in them will be confiscated.' 64. In connection with his proclamation, the Political Resident wrote that he had taken no steps to make it known, as it had to be considered that Koweit vessels fly the Turkish flag, and although it might be presumed that there would be no objection to British or Persian vessels of war searching vessels under the Turkish flag in India and Persian waters, the search of vessels carrying the Turkish flag within Koweit waters by our ships might prove a source of em barrassment if it came to the knowledge of the Turkish authorities.36 In reply the Government of India informed the Resident in the Persian Gulf that in view of the embarrassment which might arise from the slarch of vessels carrying the Turkish flag, whether in Koweit or in British or Persian waters, no action should be taken in the way of search or seizure of Koweit vessels unless or until instruction should be received from the Secretary of State for India, to whom a reference had been made. The Secretary of State in a telegram, dated the 16th August 1900, notified that Her Majesty's Government approved of the advice given to Bahrein and of the proceedings regarding Koweit, on the understanding that no effect would be given by British authorities, without special permission, to the Koweit proclama tion of 24th May. Agreement with Maskat as to the ownership of confiscated arms, 1900. 65. In despatch No. loo, dated the 26th July 1900, the Government of India Secret E., August .900, Nos. .91- ^ addressing the Secretary of State ob- 20l served that under the terms of the Sultan s proclamation, dated the 13th January 1898, and in the absence of any words of limitation, the permission to confiscate, which had been conferred by the Sultan on British and Persian vessels might perhaps be construed to mean that the confiscating Government was entitled to take for its own benefit arms and ammunition seized in pursuance of that proclamation. Unless this interpretation of the agreement with the Sultan could be accepted, the Government of India thought that the agreement should be revised. Both the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf and the Political Agent at Maskat were of opinion that any concession, whereby all such seizures would become the sole property of the Sultan, was unnecessarily liberal and would involve undesirable risks. After consultation with the local officers, the Government of India there fore recommended that the following stipulations should be emboflied in a revised agreement:— 1. In the case of arms and ammunition belonging to Maskat subjects, which may be seized by British vessels in course of exportation from Maskat in the Sultan's territorial waters, two-thirds of the arms and ammunition will be given to the Sultan or may be purchased from him as may be arranged, the remaining one-third being retained by the British Government (for prize money and expenses). 2. Arms and ammunition belonging to Maskat subjects, which may be seized outside Maskat territorial waters, will be held at the disposal of the confiscating Government. 3. The Sultan will receive compensation at the rate of 5 per cent,, on die insured value of the goods, for loss of customs duty in- the case of arms and ammunition, the property of other than Maskat subjects, destined for Maskat, which would have paid duty had they not been seized. 4. In the case of arms and ammunition seized on Persian, Bahrein or Koweit vessels in Maskat territorial waters, the Sultan will receive some money payment in acknowledgment of his rights. 5. Except as provided in clause (1) above, all arms and ammunition, seized in virtue of this agreement, will be the property of the con fiscating Government. Interpretation of our agreement with Persia, regarding the ownership ot confiscated arms, 1901. 66. With reference to the terms of our agreement with the Persian Govern ment regarding the ownership of arms and ammunition seized on Persian vessels . within Maskat or Persian territorial waters or upon the high seas ; it appeared, ' , * Ti/T X-T a * » j from the text of the letter* written by the * Enclosure in Mr. Hardmafe's des- ^ T\/r tu j* i ^ i ,1 patch to the Marquess of Salisbury, No. a , pj r o ^ dated the 3, dated the 5th January 1898. lotn Uecemjer 1097, that all arms the importation of which into Persia was37 hibited, must be handed over to the Persian Government when they have been seized by British vessels or vessels trading in the Persian Gulf, whether within or beyond Maskat territorial waters, and whether belonging to British, Persian, or Maskat subjects.^ The Persian Government might conceivably take advantage of the loose wording of this agreement to enforce embarrassing claims. Sugges tions for revising this agreement, in which a clause similar to clause (0 above, were therefore made. 67. Two further questions were also submitted for the Secretary of State's instructions. The first question was whether the issue of a general notification by the Sultan of Maskat to the effect that 'all persons wising to export arms by sea from one part of Maskat territory to another must provide themselves with passes for such arms,' could be described as restriction of export inconsistent with treaty obligations. Having regard to the terms of Article II of the French Treaty with Maskat of 1844, and to the view expressed in Secretary of State's telegram, dated the 17th December 1897, the Government of India were disposed to think that such a notification would, under present conditions, be inadvisable. It was thought, however, that no objection could be raised to the Sultan's issu ing a warning to his subjects to the effect that any vessel conveying arms and ammunition from one part of Maskat territory to another, or from Maskat to any port on the Arab coast, was liable to search by British or Persian men-of-war on the suspicion of the arms being intended for Persian ports, and that the masters o£ such vessels should, therefore, provide themselves with passes from the Sultan covering the export of such arms and ammunition. The second question was whether, in the absence of any special agreement with the Persian Government, British vessels were at liberty, in virtue of our agreements with Persia and Maskat, to search vessels bearing the Turkish flag which might be suspected of carrying arms destined for Persian or Indian ports^ whether in Maskat, Persian or Indian territorial waters. The Government of India in submitting these questions remarked that owing to a recent decision in the Court of Appeal, the position of affairs in relation to the arms traffic in the Persian Gulf had been somewhat altered, and that, there fore, it might possibly not be convenient to Her Majesty's Government to issue any general instructions with a view to strengthening the legal position of our local officers in regard to the prohibition of that traffic, until the judgment of the Court of Appeal had been referred to a higher tribunal. The difficulties experienced by local officers were, however, serious, and it was considered that no effectual check could be secured, unless and until Her Majesty's Government were in a position not only to pass an Imperial Act pro hibiting the traffic in arms with ports on the Gulf of Oman and in the Persian Gulf, but also to induce the Governments of other powers to take similar measures. 68. In replying* to this despatch, the Secretary of State on the 9th * Secret E., February 1901, Pro. No. N . ov ® m ber 1900, in commenting on the five i 7 2. stipulations proposed to be embodied in a. revised agreement with the Sultan of Maskat, stated that it was desirable to await the judgment of the House of Lords in the case of Fracis, Times &amp; Co., v. Captain Carr, R. N., before taking any steps in the direction of revision. Apart from this it was considered a preferable arrangement that arms seized by the British authorities under powers derived from the Government of Maskat should be handed over to the Government on whose behalf and within whose jurisdiction they were seized. The Secretary of State was of opinion that it would be necessary to come to an arrangement with the Turkish Government before British vessels could search ships carrying the Turkish flag, and that at present there did not seem to be any pressing necessity for taking action in that direction. The case of the seizure of the S. S. ' Hathor ' referred to legal opinion. 69. In connection with the seizure by the Belgian customs officials of a Secret E,. March i 9 oNos. 1-43. consignment of arms found on board the British steamer Hathoi; at Bushire. in C927FD '38 which the man suspected of importing the arms said that he was a native of Koweit, the question of legal seizure and liability of the ship was referred to the law officers of the Crown who replied as follows :— ' We were honoured with Your Lordship's commands signified in Sir Thomas Sanderson's letter of the 27th ultimo, transmitting to us the papers noted in the accompanying list, relating to a case of importation by the British ship Hathor of arms into Bushire in contravention of the Persian law. Sir Thomas Sanderson, after reciting the facts of the case, requested that we would take the papers into our consideration, and favour Your Lordship with our opinion on the following points :— (1) Whether the master of the Hathor was amenable to Persian law ? (2) Whether the Persian law should not form the subject of a Queen's Regulation or Regulations under Article 49 of the Persian Coasts and Islands Orders in Council of 30th December 1889, and under Article 290 of the Persia (Inland) Order of the same date, so as to enable infringements of its provisions to be punished in Her Majesty's Consular Court when such infringements were committed by British subjects ? (3) Whether the Persian authorities had any right to detain the ship on her return to Bushire failing the payment of the fine by the master or charterers ? (4) Whether the Persian law of 1st January 1900 could be enforced under Article 233 of the Persia (Inland) Order containing general provisions for criminal authority and procedure, taken in connection with Article 10 of the Persian Coasts and Islands Order with respect to smuggling (see Mr. Spring- Rice's telegram No. 85, 14th November, paper B)? (5) Whether the master could be prosecuted in a British port on the charge of the arms not having been included in the ship's manifest (see Mr. Spring- Rice's telegram No. 89, paper F)? ♦ (6) Whether the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf (who was also Her Majesty's Consul-General) could compel the master's return to Bushire (see Mr. Spring-Rice's telegram No. 89, paper F)? (7) Whether Persia could claim jurisdiction over the master under Article 7 of the Treaty between Persia and Russia of 22nd February 1828 (paper S) (see Mr. Spring-Rice's telegram No. 93, paper I)? (8) If the answer to the preceding question should be in the negative, whether the master could be tried by Her Majesty's Consul-General under Article 10 of the Persian Coasts and Islands order respecting smuggling, and Article 57 of the same order conferring the powers of a Justice of the Peace on Her Majesty's Consul-General (see Mr. Spring-Rice's telegram No. 93, paper I)? (9) Whether in our opinion any other, and if so, what general instructions might advantageously be given to Colonel Kemball and Mr. Spring-Rice res pectively, in regard to this case ? (10) What reply should in our opinion be returned to Messrs. Bucknall Brother's letter of 26th November? In obedience to Your Lordship's commands we have taken the papers submitted to us into consideration, and have the honour to report— (1) That in our opinion the master of the Hathar is not amenable to Persian law. The importation of arms into Persia is not an offence under the laws of England, and as the Persian Law of 1st January 1900 has not been made appli cable to British subjects, the^master has not been guilty of an offence cognisable in the British Courts in Persia. To acquiesce in his being tried by a ^Persian Court would be an abandonment of the position hitherto asserted that British subjects should be tried in Persia by a British Court, and is, we submit, most unadvisable. (2) We think it would be advisable that the Persian Law of 1st January 1900 should be made applicable to British subjects. This may be effected by39 Regulations under the order in Council as to Inland Persia (Article 290). As regards the Coast and Islands Order, owing to the different wording of Article 49&gt; this cannot be effected by regulations, and if it could the penalty would be only Rs. 100. Under these circumstances probably the best course would be to pass an Order in Council dealing with the point as regards all parts of Persia. (3) the ship has not been detained at Bushire this question does not arise. (4) The answer to this question is in the negative, as the importation of arms is contrary to prohibition, and could not be held to constitute the offence of smuggling as defined by Article 10. (5) We do not think that under the circumstances stated any prosecution would lie against the master of the Hathor. (6) No. (?) Such jurisdiction could not be claimed by Persia under the Article in the treaty referred to. That treaty is not binding upon Her Majesty's Gov ernment and the most-favoured-nation clause in the Treaty of Paris could not curtail the rights of Her Majesty's Government. (8) As stated in the answer to the fourth question, the facts would not support a charge of smuggling. (9) ^ We think Colonel Kemball and Mr, Spring-Rice should be instructed to explain to the Persian authorities the reason why proceedings have not been instituted, and the intention of Her Majesty's Government forthwith to aoply the Persian law of 1st January 1900 to British subjects. 1 (10) It is now unnecessary, as the ship has not been detained, to consider the reply to Messrs. Bucknall's letter.' Fracis, Times and Company—V.—Meade.—Judgment May J901. , 7®* ^ July Messrs. Fracis Times and Companv commenced an action for damages against Colonel Meade, Resident in the' Persian Gulf in respect of the seizure of certain of their arms and ammunition in the Persian Gulf at the end of 1897 and early in 1898. Mr. Justice Bigham delivered judgment on the a2nd May 1901 and summed up in the following words 'The defendent—I refer now both to what took place at Bushire and to what took place at Bahrein—in my opinion acted not only with great discretion and great ability but also with the strictest regard to the requirements of the law. He never heard of the claim now made against him personally in this action until he returned home in the summer of rgoo. It was then stated by the plaintiff; it was stated after vain attempts had been made to obtain relief from the British Government in respect of the same seizures and it is indeed nothing more than another attempt in the same direction. There must be judgment for the defendant with costs. Seizure by the Turkish authorities of arms^destinedlfor Katr, Feb ruary 1901. 71. In February, 1901, the Consul at Basra reported that the ' Hodeida' « .brought to Basra a considerable Secret E., June 1901. Pro. No. 80. consignment of Martini rifles and ammu nition, which were seized by the Turkish gunboat ' Zohaf' from a Persian sailing vessel off the coast of Katr. The number of rifles was 250 and the rounds of ammunition 12000. The rifles and cartridges were destined for Yasem-bin-Thani, the Sheikli of Katr, who protested vigorously against their confiscation, asserting that in the then unsettled state of the country he was forced to arm for self-protection. The arms were stated to have been brought from Maskat.4° The arms trade between the Persian Gulf and the North-West Frontier, 1901. 72. The following extra'ct from the Meshed Confidential Diary for the Secret E.| November 1901, Nos. 58— week ending the 2nd August 1901 is 60. worthy 01 note as showing the trade in arms existing between Bunder Abbas and the Afghan Frontier. ' Eleven Martini-Henri rifles and over 1 ,000 rounds of ammunition have been captured by the Customs Department at Karez, from information I was able to supply to them. This makes 26 rifles and a large quantity of ammunition, captured from one caravan from Bunder Abbas. All of these arms would probably have found their way to our frontier. A full report will shortly be submitted to the Government of India, giving details of how these rifles are brought from Maskat to Bunder Abbas, or a small place on the Persian coast from which place the Afghan traders, who go to Bunder Abbas, bring them to Meshed from where they are sent to Afghanistan and the Indian border.' 17 , 1 a a -i ^ 73* further discussion of the question External A., April 1002, Nos. 61—68. r r: j- • r 1 ^ y ' of arms finding their way from the Persian No. 17 of 1902. Gulf to the North-West Frontier, the Secretary of State was addressed on the 23rd January 1 902, as follows 'In previous despatches we have expressed the opinion that arms and ammunition imported into Maskat and the Persian Gulf ports reach the tribesmen on our North- Western Frontier. During the course of the blockade of the Mahsud-Waziri tribe, and the punitive operations which we have been and are still carrying out against them we have obtained convincing proof that this is the case. ' In reporting on the proceedings of the punitive column despatched from Jandola during the first week in December, Mr. Merk, Commissioner on Special Duty, states that on the body of one Jan Khan, son of the principal Mahsuc Malik, who was killed, were found a revoler marked 'made for Fracis, Times and Compay, London'; also Martini-Henry cartridges bearing the initials F. T.C., which we presume to be the mark of the same firm. Mr. Merk adds that he has seen cartridges similarly marked in the possession of Darwcsh Khel tribesmen during the past year ; and the Commandant of the Dera Ismail Khan Border Military Police reports that among the arms deposited this winter as usual by Powindahs on entering British territory, there are 15 Martini-Henry rifles evidently imported from the Persian Gulf. We send for your Lordship's inspection a cartridge, bearing the F. T. C. mark, which was used by one of a gang of Mahusd raiders, who were surprised by our troops between Sarwekai and Girni during the past summer. ' Major E. W. Maconochy, Assistant Quarter Master General, Intelligence Branch, who has been on tour in the Gomal and Tochi, writes that, while at Sarwekai early in December he took the opportunity of inspecting the bandoliers of some of the Darwesh Khel who were there, and that of four men selected at random, three possessed solid drawn Martini- Henry cartridges bearing the mark F. T. C, The Political Officer at Wana told him that be could procure 5,000 such cartridges in a week from local men. The Waziris all &lt;5poke of these cartridges as coming from Meshed. ' 74. Captain Bowring, Assistant Commissioner at Dera Ismail Khar, in Secret E, December .902, Nos.. i. ^mitting a report on the Persian Gulf rifle trade, and the B. L. ammunition in use among the Mahsuds said that the principal person who obtained rifles for sale to the Powindahs was one Haji Amin, a resident of Bunder Abbas. He had two or three shops for rifles, none of which, however, were in that town. His son -in-law, agents and shops, were located in Maskat. His direct interme diary with the trade was a prominent citizen in that town, a Bilochi by tribe. The rifles were imported by ships sailing by way of the Cape. These ships had had to proceed secretly during the last two years owing to watch set on this trade. The principal traders of Khorasan were of the Mian Khel, Dotanni and Maji tribes of Powindahs. At the time of the Powindah exodus from British territory in April and May, members (not the same every year) of these tribes proceed to- Karachi where they take ship to Bunder Abbas. These men made arrange ments for camels and boxes to proceed also to that town. On arrival they paid Haji Amin at the rate of Rs. 40 to Rs. 50 per rifle, each with 100 rounds (formerly the number of rounds had been 400 per rifle).4* after this, Haji Amin sent word to Mdskat, where the required number of rifles and amount of ammunition was shipped on board native vessels to be taken off. Formerly the rifles In boxes were placed under planks, now, however, that vessels were searched by gunboats it was stated that the rifles were done up in lead cases, and an arrangement of rings and chains was fixed to the bottom of the boats. If, therefore, a gunboat was sighted, the boxes hooked to the chains were let over the side until the vessel had been searched. The vessel with the rifles then proceeded to some out of-the-way place near Bunder Abbas, which had been notified, and the rifles were taken off into the jungle or secret hiding place. On netvs being received at Bunder Abbas of their safe arrival, the retail Powindah purchaser proceeded with his camels and boxes accompanied by one of Haji Amin's men to the spot. The latter having handed over the rifles, immediately made higiself scarce. The Powindahs then started off towards Meshed and proceeded^ that place to Seistan and Quetta or there abouts, whence thay made for Khorasan vid the wild hills of Baluchistan. During this journey, they would travel by night along the road and by day lie concealed in favourable spots off the road. On arrival, the rifles were sold at variable prices, the better class fetched about Rs. 180 when sold to Powindahs, where as the inferior fetch only Rs. 70 80. There appeared, however, to be only one price for every kind at Bander Abbas. The cartridges which seemed to be the commonest among the Mahsuds were Nos 1, *, 10, 12 and 5 and it was concluded thai Nos. 5, 10 and 12 were those cartridges of which 100 were given with every rifle brought up from Bunder Abbas direction. 75. Writing under date the 25th August 1901, the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf in commenting upon a report by the Political Agent, Maskat, on the subject of the arms trade in the Persian Gulf, gave his opinion that most of the arms imported into Maskat found their way into Persia, where the demand was naturally the greatest. It was practically impossible for the Persian Customs authorities to check the traffic. ' In course of time'— said Colonel Kemball— ' they may be able to put a stop to the importation of arms into the larger ports, but I do not see how they are ever going to prevent dhows running into the numerous small places along the extensive line of coast. I have heard on good authority that even now dhows find no difficulty in bringing small consignments to places within a few miles of Bushire. Colonel K em ball thought that it was practically impossible that the traffic in arms carried on as it was by native sailing craft could ever be put a stop to in the Persian Gulf so long as an active demand existed and purchasers were willing to give remunerative price. There was some talk about the intention of the Persian Government to purchase two small gunboats for the purpose of patrolling the Persian Coast of the Gulf, but it was doubted even if these gunboats were procured and kept in^working order, whether any effectual check on the trade would result. The difficulty of dealing with the Arms trade at Maskat owing to the French and American Treaties. 76. In connection with a suggestion that the French Government might be approached diplomatically with a view to a revision of the existing treaties with Maskat so as to admit of the Sultan's prohibiting the importation of arms, it was thought that the French Government were not likely to agree to an actual prohibi tion by the Sultan of the import of arms into his dominions. Both the French and American Treaties provided that import of all kinds of merchandise into Maskat was to be entirely free, and the French Treaty provided that there should be no pro- h ibi'ior ei'her ri import or of export of any article. The Treaty with the Nether lands simply provided for the most-favoured-nation treatment. There was no limitation of the effect of these Treaties similar to that in Article 23 of the English Treaty, and they must remain in force until terminated by mutual consent. C927FD) 43 If therefore, the Sultan was to be induced to prohibit the import and export of arms to and from Mask at, it would be necessary to obtain the consent of the French and United States Governments to the revision of their treaties, ihere might be difficulty in persuading France to fall in with our views, since in 1897, when the Sultan proposed to raise the import duty on arms from 5 to 7a per cent, the French Government refused to consent to the change on the ground that it involved a modification of the tariff presented by the Treaty of 1844. Transhipment of small parcels of arms and ammunition intended for personal use.—Notification, 1902. 77. In regard to the transhipment of small parcels of arms and ammunition for personal use the following Notification issued dated the 31st July 1902 N otification.— By the Government of India in the Home Department. In exercise of the powers conferred by section 27 of the Indian Arms Act, 1878 (XI of 1878), the Governor General in Council is pleased to direct that the following proviso be added to the Notification of the Government of India in the Home Department, No. 9^7» dated the 13th April I9 00 j namely. ' Provided that nothing in this Notification shall be deemed to apply to small parcels of arms or ammunition in respect of which the Persian Consul-General in London has certified in writing that permission has been granted by the Persian Government for their importation into Persia, and that they are intended in good faith for the private and per sonal use of the consignee.' In forwarding a copy of this Notification to the India Office, the Govern- mant of India requested that the Persian Consul-General might be instructed to state, in the certificates issued by him, that permission had been^granted by the Persian Government for the importation of the arms and ammunition into Persia, and that they were intended in good faith for the private and personal use of the consignee. The question of approaching the French Government regarding the Maskat arms traffic, 1902. 78. On the 1 ith October 1902, the Political Agent, Maskat, in reporting „ , * T - ,-(■ certain remarks made by the French Consul Secret , . arc 1903, os. . re g arc li n g the arms traffic in which the latter had enquired—' are there no means by which this trade can be stopped ? ' asked whether the opportunity could not now be taken to come to an arrange ment on the subject with the French Government. The Secretary of State was addressed on the subject in Despatch No. 9 of 1903. It was pointed out that Mons. Lorance stated that he was prepared to support any proposal which might be made for the prohibition of the importation of arms into Maskat, and he expressed the opinion that the French Government would probably co-operate towards this end with the other Powers concerned. Without attaching undue importance to these utterances, His Majesty's Govern- ^ ... ment were invited to consider whether * af P i atC r X ' negotiations might not now be instituted ternal), dated the 9th January 1902. . &amp; 1 j * • j- . j ' in the manner already* indicated. 79. The opinions of Commander Kemp, Senior Officer in Persian Gulf, on the Arms Traffic were embodied in a report dated the nth September 1902, which was as follows ; — ' Very little can be done in the way of suppressing the traffic, while the existing treaties between Great Britain and Maskat and the French and Maskat remain in their present form. Our Treaty of 1891, with Maskat states that no prohibition is to be placed on any imports or exports (not excepting Arms and Ammunition), and the French have a similar Treaty. If we use active measures to suppress the trade carried on by our own subjects, then Y/e drive it all into the hands of foreigners without reducing in it the least and also lose the little control we have of it at present. By agreement of 1898 between Great Britain, Persia and Maskat, vessels flying these flags can be searched within territorial waters if suspected of smuggling arms into43 Persia. Dhows very seldom take a cargo of arms, but carry what can conveniently be stowed away in the other cargo. If arms are fouud on board a dhow in Maskat, the difficulty of proving their destina tion is immense, and owing to the configuration of the coast line, the same holds good at sea. A dhow may be bound for the Private coast where there is no prohibition, but still find it convenient to drop arms at various places on the Persian coast, and if bound for the Persian coast with arms on board she conveniently alters her destination for some port on the Arab coast. * The purchaser either proceeds by mail to Maskat or sends an Agent, he then makes his purchases, arranges for the arms to be shipped and where they will be received, and returns by mail in time to arrange for their re- Vide Captain Bowing's statement on page . ception, Haji Cassim* is a well-known mer chant of Bunder Abbas, and, as he is a man of means, the Persian authorities can deal with him effectually. He is not known to be specially interested in the traffic. He is agent for the Mogal line and other steamers. The precautions of rings and chains and lead cases seem unnecessary. The greatest difficulty the searches has to overcome is the political and legal 'aspect of the case. A dhow's cargo might be carefuly examined, and even if arms are found the difficulty of proving her destination for a prohibited port is almost insuperable. Arms are brought to Maskat by steamers trading regularly between the United Kingdom and Maskat, and are landed at the Custom House in the same way as other trade goods. There are shops for their reception at Muttra as well as Maskat. Ships are seldom taken to examine dhows for arms before leaving Maskat owing to the difficulty of proving illicit destination. Dhows have no clearance papers. The traffic goes on all the year round. By agreement with the Sultan of Maskat and Persia, we have power to search dhows flying his or the Persian flag, and should we strictly enforce this right, the dhows would probably fly some other flag. There is no reason to suppose that the traffic is carried on particularly under the French flag.' 80. Writing on the 17th November 1903, Lieutenant-Colonel Kemball a . . ,1 »-r-&gt; . 1 t reported that information had reached Agreement with the Trucial Chiefs. 1 • ^ 1 • , , , &amp; him that the trade in arms between Maskat and the Arab Coast was increasing. El Katr was the place to which the arms and ammunition were chiefly taken, but reports had recently come in that con signments had been brought by sailing vessels into Shargah, Debai, and Abu Dhabi. It was said that the arms were taken out of Maskat under permits for places in Maskat territory. Colonel Kemball pointed out that he would endeavour to arrange with the Trucial Chiefs that the importation of arms should be put a stop to, but with regard to importations into Katr, no arrange ment was possible, and, in order to prevent the traffic our men-of-war would have to be left freedom of action in the matter of searching all native craft under the Arab or British flags, and confiscating any cargoes of arms irrespective of their destination. 81. On the 8th December 1902, Colonel Kemball reported that he had visited the various Trucial Chiefs and had obtained agreements from them in accordance with which they had promised to prohibit the importation into their respective territories, and the exportation therefrom of arms and ammunition. With regard to Debai, the Chief had asked that he might be permitted to import arms and ammunition into Debai for his own use ; no objection was seen to this and a letter to this effect was given to him. We, the undersigned Trucial Chiefs, agree to absolutely prohibit the importa- tion of arms for sale into our respective e ' territories or the exportation there from and to enforce this we have issued a Notification to all concerned. MAKTOOM- bin -HASHAR (Debai). SAGAR- bin -KHALED (Shargah). RASHID- bin -AHMAD (Um-el-Kowain). ABDUL AZIZ- bin -HAMAID (Ajwan). ZACED- bin -KHALIFAH (Abu Dhabi).44 Signed and sealed in my presence by the above mentioned Trucial Chiefs on board the R. 1. M. S. Lawrence on the 2^th, 35th and 26th November 1902. (Signed) C. A. KEMBALL, Lieutenant-Colonel, Officiating Political Resident, Persian Gulf. Notification. Be it known to all that whereas it has become known to us that the traffic in arms in British India is prohibited, and as we are of opinion that the traffic, if continued, is likely to be prejudicial to the interests of our territories, we have, therefore, decided to do all that lies in our power to put a stop to this illegal traffic, and we hereby declare that from the date of this notification the importation of arms and ammunition into our respective territories and the exportation of the same are absolutely prohibited. All arms and ammunition so imported or exported in future will be seized and confiscated. From Lieutenant Colonel Kemball, Officiating Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. After compliments,—-With reference to the agreement into which you have entered Debai prohibiting the traffic of arms at Ajwan I write to inform you that upon your repre- Um-el-Kowaio Abu Dhabi senting the matter to me you will be permitted to import c.rms and ammunition yourself in such quantities as you consider advisable for the protection of your own territories.' 82. Major Cox also issued a notification at Maskat and reported that the Sultan had issued a similar notification to his subjects : — Notification. Dated Maskat, the yth December 1904, Whereas the Sheikhs of the Pirate Coast, namely Abu Thabi, Debai, Shargah, Ras-el-Khamia, Um-el-Kowain and Ajwan have notified a prohibition against the importation of arms and ammunition into their respective territories this is to warn all British and British-protected subjects that any arms orammuni- tion that may be found in process of export to the abovementioned territories will be liable to confisaation. (Sd.) P. Z. COX, Major, His Britannic Majesty's Consul, Maskat, Landing of a cargo of arms and ammunition at Hasina^ a small port near Lingah. Sources from which the Arab and Baharlao tribes obtain their supplies of arms, 1903, 83. The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf writing on the 21st July Secret e., October 1903, Nos. 42—46. '9 0 3» reported that he had recently receiv- ...... , ed . a letter from the Agent at Lingah, informing him that a cargo of 400 Martini-Henry rifles, with some revolvers and ammunition, had been landed about the middle of May at a place called Hasina a small port not far from Lingah. The Agent had been asked to make enquiries as to the destination of these arms. His report is interesting as showing one of the sources from which the Arab and Baharloo tribes obtain their arms. I have made enquiries from which it appears that some of the residents of Lar and Gerash who are by profession traders, come to Lingah and buy there bills in dollars on Maskat for arge sums. Their business relates to buying rifles, and for that purpose they go personally to Maskat. After buying arms they ship them in sailing vessels v hich land them at the bhib Kuh pQris 1 he.r principal object is to sell arms to the Boharlao and Arab tribes who live round about Shiraz, m the dependencies of La-, and at Gerash and Jehroom. Whenever the Chiefs of Shib Kuh and the Khans of Lar and the subordinate districts want them, they sell to them also, as their business is trade, but their chief object45 is to sell to the tribes. Four months ago these Laris and Gerashis had brought in Maskat rifles, revolvers, and cartridges to the value of about $80,000, and it was from this lot that they had landed these rifles and cartridges {mentioned in Agent's previous report). They do not always land them (the arms and ammunition) at one port only. They take into consideration the exigencies of the time and the friendship of the Chief of Shib Kuh with the Khans of Lar.' Measures taken for the suppression of the arms traffic between Oman and the Somali Coast. 84. In a secret despatch No. 23, dated the 2Sth August 1903 the Secretary Secret E., January 1904, Nos. 531 —543. re ^ err ' I J=? t0 subject of the jo. tramc in arms which was believed to exist between Ornan and the Somali Coast, said that the Sultan of Maskat should be moved to issue a notification declaring illegal the exportation of arms and am munition to the portions of the African coast and islands, including Socotra, ymg to the north of Cape Guardafui which are under the British Protectorate, and authorising the seizure of such arms and ammunition in Maskat territorial' waters and in Maskat dhows on the high seas. . . Telegraphing later, the Secretary of State said that the Sultan should be invited to issue notification extending the prohibitions to the Italian Protectorate, also to empower the British and Italian ships of war to deal with suspected Mas kat dhows in territorial waters and on high seas. 85. On the 20th October 1903, Major Cox forwarded a copy of the notifica tion issued by the Sultan. Notificatiom. To all whom it may concern. Be it known that, in pursuance of an understanding come to by the Govern ments of Great Britain and Italy, the importation of arms and warlike stores to those portions of the African Coast and islands (including Socotra) lying to the north of Ras Aseer (i.e., Cape Guardafui), which are under the British^ Protec torate, and also to those pans ot the African Coast, which are under the Italian Protectorate, has been prohibited. Accordingly, at the request of the British Government pursuant to her understanding with the Government of Italy, I hereby notify the said prohibi tion. Be it, therefore, known that any native craft transporting arms or warlike stores to the localities in question will incur the risk of confiscation, and that I have granted the authority to British men-of-war to search, on my behalf, vessels which there is season to suspect in this connection in Maskat and Oman' waters, and similarly to search Maskat crafts on the high seas if reason exists for suspecting them. Furthermore, I hereby grant authority to Italian ships of war also to search suspected Maskat vessels either in territorial waters or on the high seas. Maskat ; j The ijth October igoj, ) The rights of search by men-of-war defined, 1903. 86. Commander Kemp addressing the Political Resident in the Persian Secret E., April 1904, Nos. 89-03. , Gulf on the I0 ^ h Au g us t 1903, asked that he might be informed on the followinsf points:— &amp; 1. Whether all vessels (with the exception of those under French and 1 urkish colours) may be searched by His Majesty's ships), both C937FD T45 on the high seas, as well as within all the territorial waters of the Gulf, with the exception of those territorial waters belonging to T urkey. 2, In the events of one or more of His Majesty's ships being specially detailed for this duty, whether all vessels (not steamers) should be indiscriminately searched, or only those against whom special suspicion is directed, or when special information has been obtained from the various Political Officers and Agents stationed in the Gulf ? observing that indiscriminate searching would probably cause much inconvenience to honest traders. 3. In the event of a capture being made, what course should be adopted by His Majesty's ships with regard to the captured vessel, her crew, cargo and arms, having regard to the place where the cap ture was made and the place to which the captured vessel belongs ? 87. Lieutenant-Colonel Kemball embodied his views in a memorandum which he submitted for the approval of the Government of India :— ' On the high seas British ships-of-war can only search vessels* under British Only sailing boats are meant. Persian and Maskat flags. 1 hey can do this in virture of the special agreements which we have entered into with the Shah of Persia and the Sultan of Maskat. Maskat vessels it is understood fly the ordinary red Arab flag, and in view of our general position in the Persian Gulf and of the agreements which have been entered into with the Sheikhs of Bahrein and Koweitithe search of all vessels under the Arab flag would probably be free from objection. Within Persian territorial waters, British, Persian and Maskat vessels can certainly be searched by our men-of-war and probably too there would be no objection to the search of ail vessels flying Arab colours. The same remark applies to Maskat territorial waters, but arms found on board could only be confiscated if the Sultan decide in such cases as may be referable to these Courts, that the arms are intended for places where the traffic has been prohibited. Within the territorial waters of Bahrein, Koweit and the Trucial Chiefs there would probably be no objection to the search of vessels under the Persian and Arab flags. Legally I believe vessels under any flags could be searched within these territorial waters, on the authority delegated by the ruler of the State to the British ship-of-war. I do not consider that indiscriminate search of all vessels, on the high seas at any rate, would be justifiable, though His Majesty's ships-of-war would be entitled to search an vessels under the British, Persian, and Arab flags upon reasonable presumption existing that such vessels contained arms and ammunition destined for places where the prohibition CXlStSa With regard to the disposal of captured cargoes it has'been decided that seizures in 1-ersian territorial waters, or upon the high seas in the case of Persian vessels o-o in entirety to the Persian Government, and that seizures in Maskat waters or on Maskat vessels upon the high seas go to the Sultan of Maskat. _ I he same ruling might also bfe held to apply to Bahrein, Koweit and the Trucial Chiefs, but in these cases I am doubtful whether such action would be politically expedient or necessary at any rate in cases of seizure upon the high seas. Such seizures, must iusti- fiably, in my opinion, be retained for the benefit of His Majesty's ships or delivered over to His Majesty s Government. In the case of a capture made within Persian waters or upon the high seas, the captured vessel, her crew and cargo, if the Persian, should be handed over for disposal to the Persian authorities at the nearest port where a proper Cus toms Administration exists. In the case of a British vessel within Persian territorial waters, such vessels should be made over to the nearest British Consular authority, who will proceed with regard to it in accordance with law. Other vessels captured within Per sian territorial waters are, I presume, amenable to Persian jurisdiction. The same remarks mutatis mutandis apply, I think, to vessels upon the high seas or within Maskat territorial waters. In the case of Koweit, Bahrein or Arab Coast vessels captured on the high seas, the vessels might at the discretion of His Majesty's Commander be set free after the contra- and cargo has been seized. I his m'ght also be done in case of Persian or Maskat vessels captured upon the high seas. It rright be found difficult for capturing ship to take the captured vessel to the country of its origin.47 88. The Government of India accepted the above views subject onlv to the following reservations :— ^ th* h' T he ex,stl I n ? Britls h law apparently does not authorise the search of a British ship on carrvine- th^Rrit «?h'fl k' t0 reStriCt SearCbeS ' SO far aS co — veLels British ships g 0a g seas ' to natlve craft onl y. and not to attempt to search The objections which exist to any indiscriminate interference with vessels on the hiah seas, apply also in the case of territorial waters, where the right of search should not be exercised except when there is reason to apprehend an infection of the local law. Special caution is necessary in the case of a merchant vessel carrying the flag of any European Arms traffic between the Persian Gulf and the North-West Frcntier of India, 1903--1904. 89. With regard to the alleged trade in arms from the Persian Gulf via Secret E., April 1904, Nos. 267—286. Mesh ed to the North-West Frontier, , ' Captain Smyth's report, dated Quetta. 21st March 1903, is of interest:— ^ &gt; ' The best informed man on the Frontier, Muhammad P afiq Khan, for many vears Native Political at Chaman, firmly maintains that Meshed is a regular receiving hous'e for arms and ammunition, which arrive there from the Persian Gulf, are stored in Bast (sanctuary), and exported thence in large and small quantities into Afghanistan and across the south-west part of Afghanistan to the tribes on our North-West Frontier • a few finding their way down through Seistan to Baluchistan and the Sarhad. When in Meshed I took considerable interest in the question, personally conductincr investigations in the bazaar, etc., and in looking up the previous correspondence and reports in the Meshed Agency, I soon convinced myself that previous reports as to the non existence of the traffic were altogether unreliable, and that the place was full of smuggled rifles and ammunition, principally Birmingham made Martini-Henry rifles ; they are for sale by hundreds, at a low price, not much over Rs. 100 each. 1 had 200 Martinis counted by a reliable agent. As a rule, 100 rounds of ammunition was supplied gratis with each rifle. Colonel Whyte started cautious enquiries among the Persian officials. The result was startling: the Passport Officers infermed us privately that the arms traffic existed, and also that the Russian officials connived at it, and that at certain, or rather uncertain, times large consignments of smuggled arms were despatched by the Russian authorities' to the Russian Consul in Seistan—M. Miller. This trade in smuggled arms has existed for years, but I am of opinion that it is much restricted now on account of better customs supervision. I could not now quote the number of rifles per annum that have passed through Meshed. It must have been laro-e a year or two ago. Probably the rifles mostly come from near Bunder Abbas via Kerman to Meshed. Some may have come from Bushire. I should imagine that practically none of these rifles come^ along the Seistan-Nushki routes, but that most of them pass from some point north of Seistan via the Helmand and Registan desert. Perhaps some pass through Baluchistan via Kharan and Kalat; such arms would probably go direct from the Gulf, and not ^ Meshed, which, however, seems to have been a great market for these goods.' At all events, the trade has existed, and probably many rifles were sold direct to the Afghans of Herat, Juwain, etc., and the trade cannot have ceased altogether, though, perhaps, the Russians have organised it a little.' 90. In January 1904 the Consul-General at Marseilles reported that one Secret E. ; April 1904, Nos. 307—313. case &gt; supposed to contain boots for Bushire to be shipped on the 31st December at» Marseilles per ' Shahritan ' chartered by Messrs. Bucknall Brothers, was accident ally found to contain revolvers. The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf was instructed to inform the cus toms, but not to disclose the source of information. Trade in arms and ammunition between Sur and Somaliland. Pro posed appointment of a British Agent at Sur, 1904. 91. Major Cox, Political Agent at Maskat, writing to the Consul-General at Secret E., May 1904, Nos. 39—47. Berbera on the 3rd August i9 0 3t informed him that one of the dhow-owners at Sur holding French papers had lately purchased from French and Russian dealers in48 Maskat a large quantity of rifles (about 500) with ammunition in proportion and had taken them with him to Sur. It was possible that these munitions were intended by the purchaser and his fellows of the French flag for subsequent export to Somaliland when their dhows proceeded on their post- monsoon voyages to the Gulf of Aden, with cargoes of dates. Major Cox further stated that he had reason to believe that the purchase money was made up of subscriptions from various dhow-owners. 93. On the 23rd July 1903, the Admiral, East Indian Station, informed Enclo. No. ! to Pro. No. 42. Ma i or C . ox ^ '? ha ^ be f n •■eP OTted on good native authority that rrom 3,000 to 4,000 rifles and ammunition had been landed on the Italian Somaliland coast about 3 months ago from Maskat, and were now at a village two days' march inland from Boreida, and that it was said that they were consigned to the Sultan Othman Mahmud, who was selling them to the tribes and Mulla, with the latter of whom he was in league. 93. In drawing the attention of the Government of India to this report, Major Cox pointed out that seeing His Majesty's ships could not interfere with dhows under the French flag on the high seas, it was difficult to devise any effective measures for preventing the arms reaching their destination except the close and vigilant patrolling of Sultan Othman Mahmud's coast. Referring to his previous recommendation for the appointment of a British Agent at Sur, Major Cox said that if a trade in smuggled arms between that post and the Mullah's adherents was proved to exist, the fact seemed to afford a lively argument in favour of such a measure. 94. Regarding the appointment of a British Agent at Sur, the Government of India doubted whether there was now more need for the appointment than there had been previously, in fact seeing that the Sultan now had his steamer in which he could move freely up and down the coast, and that additional gun boats were now to be available, thus diminishing the difficulty of the Political Agent's visiting Sur when occasion arose, the need seemed to have become less. In any case, it seemed inadvisable to send an Agent to this centre of French influence, until the question of Anglo-French relations at Maskat had been settled one way or the other. Traffic in arms between Maskat and Koweit. Intention of M. Goguyer to establish a branch of his business at Koweit, 1904. 95. The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf telegraphing on the 28th Secret E Mav iqo 4 Nos 48-60 January '904 said that Captain Grey had ' y 9 ' informed him that the British India Steamer ' CMndwara' had sailed from Maskat on the 26th January with 500 rifles for Koweit; the arms had been shipped secretly, and the ship's Agent, Goguyer, was a passenger on the steamer. Colonel Kemball stated that he was informing Sheikh Mobarek that he was expected to enforce the prohibition with regard to the consignment. It was understood that the Sheikh was the only person who could legally enforce the prohibition, and therefore, the seizure of the consign ment had better be left to him. Colonel Kemball was instructed* that he could not seize the consignment *p m tiw in a British harbour or on the high seas, ro. o. 49) ^ consignment should be seized by the Sheikh as soon as clear proof existed of the intention to land. If possible arrangements should be made for a man-ot-war to watch the proceedings at Koweit, aud the Consuls at Muhammerah and Basrah should be informed in case the arms should be carried on. 96. On the 18th February 1904, Colonel Kemball telegraphed that it had been reported that the ' Gulistan ' which Pro. No. 52. i e f t Maskat on the 16th February, had taken arms of unknown quantity for Mons. Goguyer at Koweit. Further that private information from Basrah had stated that 1,000 rifles and 300,000 cartridges49 were on their way from Paris to be transhipped to Aden for Goguyer. Colonel Kemball had reason to believe that Mubarek had some understanding with Goguyer, and it seemed useless telling him to confiscate the consignment, while seizure by us in Koweit harbour, was not permissible. The previous consign ment referred to per S S. ' Chindwara' was not taken to Koweit, having been put off again at Maskat before the ship sailed. Colonel Kemball was informed in reply that he or one of his assistants should visit Koweit and personally ascertain the facts from Mubarek, warning him against intrigue with Goguyer and reminding him of his agreement of May 1900 declaring the importation of arms illegal and e npowering British ships-of- war to search vessels in his territorial waters. Despatch to the Secretary ef State on recent phases of the arms traffic, 1904. 97. The recent phases of the arms traffic formed the subject of a Despatch Pro. No. 60. (^ To - 7^ of I 9 0 4) t0 the Secretary of State, dated the 31st March 190^ :— (1) From the Officiating Political Resident in 'We have the honour to forward a copy of the Persian Gulf, No. 39, dated the 19th February the marginally noted correspondence reeardine 1904, with enclosure. 1 • . r , r . 5 ,. 0 the shipment of arms and ammunition from Mas- (2) From the Officiating Political Resident in kat to Koweit. the Persian Gulf, No. 48, dated the 24th February 1904, with enclosure. t • j. • • • „ d i-*- 1 d -j . i. • strict criticism to which our proceedings (3) rom the Officiating Political Resident in „ £1.1 c o r. 1 i - . rt the Persian Gulf, No. 62, dated the 4th March ^ ' Case of the S. S. Baluchistan &gt;904' were subsequently subjected in British Courts (4) From the Officiating Political Resident in an( ! claims which have been ad- the Persian Gulf. No. 69, dated the nth March danced by the German Government in connec- tion with the seizure, indicate the necessity of omitting no precaution to ensure the technical correctness of our action, and in considering the ptesent reports we have examined the question of our rights in seizing and confiscating arms in the territorial waters of Maskat. 1 he poA er of confiscation conferred by the Sultan s proclamation of the 13th January 1898 Cop y ^rwarded with Secret despatch No. 86 relates only to arms and ammunition which are (External), d„ed 5th July ,900^ intended Indian or ^ arc also the property of Brjtish, Persian, or Maskat subjects, and we thus have no special rights in the case of arms consigned to a port in other territory, such as Koweit, or where the warlike munition are the property of a subject of any power not mentioned in the proclamation. In view of the agreements for the prohibition of traffic in arms and ammunition which we hold from the Sheikh of Koweit and Bahrein and from the Trucial Chiefs, and having regard to the opinion expressed by Sir Nicolas O'Conor in his despatch to Lord Lans- downe No. 759, dated the 16th November 1903, that for the purposes of the present case we might treat as illegal the introduction of arms into any part ot the Ottoman dominions, we think it advisable that the terms of the Maskat proclamation of 1808 should be revised by substituting for the words ' Indian or Persian ports' the phrase ' Indian Persian, or Turkish ports, or for the territories of the Sheikh of Bahrein, the Sheikh of Koweit, or of the Trucial Chiefs, and further, that the words ' and if thev are the pro perty of British, Persian, or Maskat subjects' should be omitted. The wording of the Sultan's proclamation of 1898 follows the phraseologv of the instructions of His Majesty s Government conveyed in Lord George Hamilton's telegram dated the 21st December 1897, and it would, therefore, be necessary in any case to refe^ the matter for your orders before addressing the Sultan of Maskat on the subject. Since we propose the addition of the words ' Turkish ports,' it will, no doubt, also be desirable to refer to Sir Nicolas C) Conor. There is, however, another and most important aspect of the case. Even if our powers of search in Maskat territorial waters can be enlarged in the manner suggested there will still be the difficulty that boats carrying arms mav clear from Maskat for ports in the territories of the Sultan of Maskat, where the traffic is not prohibited, and thence sail for Koweit, or some other port, as appears to have been the case in the present instance. This will necessitate the adoption of measures for searching arrivals in Koweit itself. Sheikh Mubarak, in conversation with Colonel Kemball, has recognized our right to do this under the proclamation of 24th May 1900, but obviously a seizure of arms in Koweit harbour by a British ship acting under the authority of the arrangement with the Sheikh would almost certainly, if the vessel carrying the arms were a foreign ship or even a British steamer, raise the whole question of the status of the Sheikh. In the present C927FD M5° caie we were compelled by the urgency of the matter to authorise Colonel Kemball to search for the arms said to have been sent to Koweit, but, before directing our officers to take such action generally, we desire, in accordance with the instructions contained in the flegram of nth August 1900 from your predecessor, to refer the matter for the opinion of His Majesty's Government as to the course which it is advisable to adopt. The present position of affairs in which Mons. Goguyer apparently intends to establish a branch of his business at Koweit which seems likely to become an intrepot for the arms trade^ is emi nently unsatisfactory. In view of recent declarations on the subject of the status of Koweit His Majesty's Government may possibly be willing now to authorise seizure of arms under the proclamation. If, however, it is held to be undesirable to assert our predominant interests so openly, perhaps the Turkish Government, who are vitally interested in checking the trade in arms in Northern Arabia, may agree to our searching all vessels in Koweit waters with out prejudice to the question of the authority under which the right is exercised, or to our exercising such a right of search in Turkish territorial waters in the Persian Gulf outside the Shatt-el-Arab without referring specially to Kor eit. Some such arrangement would probably make our position in the matter secure against all objcectors. We are advised that it would not be necessary to make over arms seized in territorial waters of an Arab Chief under our sole protectorate to the Chief, so that the difficulties anticipated by Colonel Kemball would not necessarily arise. Arrangements are in progress for opening a British Post Office at Koweit in charge of an Indian Assistant'Surgeon, and, as soon as this has been done, we propose to dispense with the services of our present agent. As long as Mons. Goguyer remains at Koweit, it will be necessary to arrange for frequent visits of a Political Officer and ship of war to that place, and it may be hoped that these overt signs of our interest in his proceedings will induce Sheikh Mubarak to adopt a more satisfactory attitude on the subject of this arms traffic than he did on the occasion of his last interview with Lieutenant-Colonel Kemball. The attention of Major Cox, who will shortly succeed Lieutenant-Colonel Kemball on the departure of the latter on leave, will be specially drawn to the necessity for consolidating our influence at Koweit.' Amendment of the rules in respect to the traffic in arms and ammu nition at ports on the seaboard of Persia, the Persian Gulf, Baluchistan and Gwadur, 1903. 98. Under date the 27th April 1903, the British India Steam Navigation , . xt co Company submitted for consideration the External A., May 1904, Nos. 168-171. fo ll 0 „i n g enqu i ry ' Whether arras, ammunition and warlike stores shipped at Bombay under permits from the Commissioner of Police for ports in the Persian Gulf, should not be allowed free transmit in mail and other steamers calling at Karachi, and the Company exempted from the necessity of procuring licenses from the Karachi Magistrate under Home Department Notification No. 967 of 13th April 1900, which we hold applies to steamers from foreign ports and not to vessels from Indian ports carrying goods, the export of which has already been licensed by the proper Government of India official at the port of shipment.' 99. The Government of Bombay on the 1st June 1903 pointed out that in accordance with Home Department Notification No. 967, dated the 13th April 1900, arms, etc., brought into an Indian port and declared under manifest to be consignments without transhipment to any port on the seaboard of the Persian Gulf must be covered by a license. It was the practice in the Bombay Customs House to treat Maskat, for the purpose of this notification, as a port on the seaboard of the Persian Gulf and to require licenses in the case of arms consigned without transhipment to that port. But a strict interpretation of the notification did not warrant this procedure, as Maskat is not in the Persian Gulf. As it was doubtless the intention of the Government of India to extend the restriction to Maskat and other ports adjacent to the Persian Gulf, the Governor in Council suggested that the notification be amended so as to include all ports on the Mekran coast and on the eastern and southern coasts of Arabia. 100. In reply the Government of India observed that in view of French treaty rights to demand the free admission into Oman of merchandise of all kinds, it had hitherto been found impracticable to suppress the arms traffic with Maskat, and so long as present conditions were maintained in this respect, the Government of India considered it inexpedient to place restrictions on British5* trade in arms In that quarter. In the case of the remaining portions of the east' ern and southern coasts of Arabia (other than Oman and the coast of the Persian Gulf proper), the Government of India were unaware of the existence of any importation of arms from India, and, so far therefore, as concerned Arabia, they doubted the need for any amendment of the notification. With regard to the Mekran coast, however, the Government of India agreed with the Bombay Gov ernment and^ with a view to give effect to their suggestion, they proposed to issue the notification below. For convenience sake the draft purported to cancel the notifications of 1900 and 1902 and to incorporate so much of these as was still required. 1 lot. In enclosing a copy of the question put by the British India Steam Navigation Company (see above^, for information, it was observed that under existing rules the reply to the enquiry made by the Company must be in the affirmative, that is to say, that arms consigned from Bombay to the Persian Gulf in vessels touching at Karachi, were subject at that port to the restrictions imposed by section 6 of the Indian Arms Act, 1878, aud clause 6 of the rules under section 17 thereof, even though a license may have been issued in due form under those rules permitting their export from Bombay to the Persian Gulf. The Government of India were inclined to consider that the requirements of the rules in this respect were unnecessarily onerous, and that an exemption might be granted in the case of arms, etc., consigned to any port in the Persian Gulf or on • the seaboard of Persia, Baluchistan, or Gwadur, which had been exported from a port in British India under a license duly granted at that port and in transit In any intermediate port in British India. 102, The following notification Issued Notification.— By the Government of India, Home Department. In exercise of the powers conferred by section 27 of the Indian Act, 1878 (XI of 1878), the Governor-General in Council is pleased to cancel the notifica tions of the Government of India in the Home Department, cited on the margin, and to direct that the following additions be made to the like Notification No. 1572, dated the 29th August 1879, namely:— (1) After the word ' Africa' the words ' and provided that such port be not on the sea-board of Persia, the Persian Gulf, Baluchistan or Gwadur,' shall be added. (2) At the end the following paragraph shall be added The Governor- General in Council is further pleased to exempt from the prohibi tions and directions contained in section 6 of the said Act:— (a) small parcels of arms or apimunition in respect of which the Persian Consul-General in London has certified in writing that permis sion has been granted by the Persian Government for their importation into Persia and that they are intended in good faith for the service and personal use of the consignee; and (b) arms, ammunition and military stores consigned to any port in the Persian Gulf or on the seaboard, of Persia, Baluchistan or Gwadur which have been exported from a port in British India under a license duly granted at that port and are in transit in any intermediate port in British India. Proposed removal of raaitrictions requiring British subjects at Mas- kat to submit weekly statements to the Political Agent of the importation and sale by them of arms and ammunition, 1904. ///% Writing on the 7th June 1904, the Political Agent at Maskat again raised the question as to the advisability of dis- Secret e., September 1904, os. 239 241. continuing the practice by which merchants were compelled to submit weekly statements of their arms transactions. Captain „ - Grey pointed * out that it was largely Enclosure to Pro. 0. 239. owing to their having to do this that foreigncompetition had assumed such a formidable aspect, and that having once gained a sufficiently profitable footing with their arms traffic to insure themselves against loss, they might seriously threaten our trade in other directions. It was further shown that the regulations in great measure failed in their object, owing to the introduction of brokers, whereby the name of the real purchaser did not appear in the transaction. The Secretary of State was addressed ro. o, 240 i n » Despatch No. 156, dated the 18th August 1904:— ' We have the honour to refer to your telegram, dated the 3rd November 1903, directing that, until the views of the French Government had been ascertained on the points raised in our Secret despatch No. 112, dated the 30th July 1903, relative to the suppression of the arms traffic and the expulsion of Mons. Goguyer from Maskat, no action should be taken in connection with the matter dealt with in paragraph 6 of the same des patch as to the cancellation of the rules issued in 1898 requiring British subjects at Maskat to submit weekly statements to the Political Agent of the importation and sale by them of arms and ammunition. 2. We now forward a further reference from the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, in which he again invites attention to the disabilities which the existing regulations impose upon our traders. We agree with Captain Grey that it is very desirable, so long as the trade continues, to secure its remaining, as far as possible, in the hands of British sub jects ; and if there appears to be no probability of the early conclusion of any agreement with the French Government, for the suppression of the arms traffic at Maskat, or for the ex pulsion of Mons. Goguyer, we recommend that, pending the issue of orders on the sub ject dealt with in paragraphs 1 to 5 of our Secret despatch No. 112, dated the 30th July 1903, the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, may be permitted to suspend the restric tions in question.' The right of the Persian Customs authorities to interfere with vessels ^ carrying arms and ammunition for other than Persian ports, 1904. //^vt In August 1904, correspondence passed between the Minister at Tehran and the Resident in the Persian Gulf, regarding certain arms which had been dis covered in the luggage of some passengers bound for Koweit in the S. S. ' Kangra' in May 1904. Major Cox informed Sir Arthur Hardinge that he did not consider that the Belgian Customs Department should be permitted to search the baggage of steamer passengers not booked to Persian Ports, much less to seize arms not so consigned or destined. With regard to the dhow traffic. Major Cox thought that the question was more difficult. Any dhow with arms on board, once she has passed the Quoins into the Persian Gulf proper, is carrying contraband, but there might be occasions when small presents of arms could legitimately pass between one Sheikh and another. As far as Basrah dhows were concerned, the Turks professed to make their own arrangements for checking the illicit import of arms. The officials of the Persian Customs Administration, already had powers which enabled them to harass non-Persian dhows, many of them British protected, to a considerable extent, and the Resident therefore, thought that it would be a dangerous additional weapon in their hands for worrying native craft, were we to admit any right on their part to search dhows and to seize as contraband arms or other goods not clearly destined for Persia. The Arms traffic at Koweit. /^.In the diary of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, under heading Koweit, the 8th August 1904, the following was recorded :— ' It is believed that either Sheikh Mubarek or his son has an arrangement with Mons* Goguyer by which the latter imports arms and ammunition, and the former takes delivery thereof. The British India Steam Navigation Company's S. S. ' Henzada' is said to have brought last week 12 cases of arms and ammunition which were taken delivery of by the Sheikh.' /^Under date the 18th August, a further delivery of arms to the Sheikh was recorded, and on the 22nd August 1904:— ' Five Basrah merchants have come here to buy arms probably to sell to Basrah people, as Haji Monnir's death has caused a great sensation, and there is a demand for firearms for personal protection.'53 Instructions to Naval Officers in the Persian Gulf with reference to the Arms Traffic. /^The Admiralty in addressing the Naval Commander-in-Chief, East India Station, on 23rd June 1904, relative to the searching of British ships suspected of trafficking in arms in contravention of Article 8 of the General Act of the Brussels Conference, informed him that the Brussels Act did not itself confer any powers of search or detention for the enforcement of the Article referred to. This being so, His Majesty's ships have therefore, no authority to search or detain suspected vessels apart from the powers conferred upon them within British territorial waters under local regulations, or in the territorial waters of the Italian Protectorate and in Persian and Maskat waters in virtue of the special arrangement made with the Governments of these countries respectively. The Admiral was also informed that the telegraphic information sent to him from time to time with regard to vessels leaving England with consignments pf arms and ammunition, was intended for use in the event of their trafficking within the Territorial waters above mentioned, and not with a view to any action being taken in regard to these vessels on the High Seas. -v v . tb if 1 ■■l' £ dj8i 9H; ts —1 f. v i istf^vA bfiss &amp;nt nc ■■&gt;■■■ . ■ ;• ' hTKO rL j- t: y Q. C. tfcsn Biliala —Kc, C027 t) iO-ll-Cd, 30- C927FD</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000884.0x0001b7_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/20/C237</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000884.0x0001b7</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/20/C237</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>‘Persian Gulf gazetteer. Part 1. Historical and political materials. Précis on arms trade in the Persian Gulf.’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1904/1904</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-10-10T14:43:31</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (31 folios)</extent><extent>The contents of the précis are arranged in rough chronological order, and organised under a number of subheadings, with each paragraph numbered from 1 to 108. There is a contents page at the front of the volume (ff.5-6) which lists the subheadings with their corresponding paragraph numbers.</extent><extent>Foliation: The foliation sequence commences at the front cover and terminates at the inside back cover; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.Pagination: The volume also contains an original printed pagination sequence, with page numbers located top and centre of each page.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The volume, stamped ‘Secret’ on the front cover and frontispiece, is part 1 (historical and political materials) of a précis the arms trade in the Persian Gulf, covering the years 1883 to 1904. It was prepared by Lieutenant Cecil Hamilton Gabriel of the Indian Army, and published in 1904 by the Government of India Foreign Department, Simla, India.The précis comprises copies of correspondence relating to: the nature and extent of the arms traffic between various parts and ports of the Gulf and the wider Indian Ocean region: chiefly in and around Maskat [Muscat], but also on the Mekran [Makran] coast, the route between Zanzibar and Maskat, Bahrein [Bahrain], Koweit [Kuwait], Oman and Somaliland [Somalia], and between the Persian Gulf and the northwest frontier [Afghanistan]; reports of the seizure or surrender of arms, or vessels carrying arms, including the seizure of the SS
                           Baluchistanin 1898, and arms traded by the company Fracis, Times &amp; Co.; agreements between the British Government and local rulers for the suppression of the arms trade; the issue of licenses for the export of arms; arms traffic in the Gulf, in relation to French, Italian, Persian and Turkish Governments; instructions for naval officers in the Persian Gulf in relation to the arms traffic.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>HMIS Baluchistan, minesweeper</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Fracis, Times and Company, Arms traders</namePart></name></subject><name type="personal"><namePart>Cecil Hamilton Gabriel</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Zanzibar</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Bahrain</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Makran Coast</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Muscat</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Arms control</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000884.0x0001b7#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>