<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100059346669.0x000003_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-07-16T13:47:55.644Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">&gt;293) (138619/W/34) FI LES ONT.Y , Cypher telegram to Sir P.Cox, (Teheran) 5 Poie^gn Office, October 22nd e 1919» 9^0 e p 0 m,,. No.561, 5^ Your despatch No. 75 (of May 18th) Farman Parma. Your telegram No.460 (of July 4th) and connected telegrams have been carefully considered. In view of the large sums we have given to this family during the war and particularly in view of the first instalment out of the loan (see your telegram No.546 (of August 15th)) of which Prince Pirouz must have received a considerable snare 9 I see no reason why we should now be called upon to acquit ourselves of any further 'debt of obligation”, / You should therefore make it clear to Farman Parma that, though we recognise and fully appreciate his loyalty to us during the war, it is quite out of the question to give him a lease of property,in Mesopotamia as suggested or a further subsidy in cash. If Prince Firouz raises the question here he A will be given a similar reply. to In'” ^ fV * DOCUment is the P-orenty of Hi. R^„.— b« ^turned t«, the Fo^ei^^ n«„„ jf I»cJWaiesty»s Government. ilStj^equiped fon official usa.l FILES ONLY Lecypher, Sir P, Cox (Teheran), 8th September 1919, P. 3 p.m, 8th September 1919, H,' 11,15 a,m. 10th Ho. 609• 0 : 0 : 0 : 0 : 0 : 0 : 0 : 0 : 0:0 Your telegram Ho, 328, Consul at Shiraz asks for renewal of subsidy of tomans 11 r 000 a month for some time longer, I support this application on following grounds. Part of amount consists of office allowance of (?F^F of tomans 2,000 a month promised by us to him when he agreed to go to Shiraz in 1916 and cannot well be stopped till we are prepared to inform him that his further retention of post is indifferent to us. Remainder tomans 9,000 a month is cost of private (group undecypherable)s and establishment and of administrative expenses in excess of sums authorised by Persian Government. FJ\ asserts that local revenues are insufficient to meet expenditure already authorised by Persian Government yet Persian Government is opposed to granting any subsidy to Pars, I think therefore it is (?expedient) to continue our subsidy a little longer in order to avoid risk of friction and premature (?resignation of) F.F. (10,9 8-4)&amp; 118143/W/34) 1 '’*' &gt;»'■«, ; 3 2 O 1919 The Acting Under Secretary of state for Foreign Affairs presents his cornpliments to the Under Secretary of State for India and in reply to his letter of the 19th instant (No.P.4490), relating the obligations of His Majesty’s Government to the Farman Farma, is directed by Earl Curzon of Kedleston to transmit here* in, to be laid before Mx.Secretary Montagu, the draft of a telegram which Lord Curzon proposes / with Mr. Montagu's concurrence^© address to His Majesty's Minister at Tehran on this subject and on that of the monthly subsidy which His Lordship proposes to termi nate. 2. A similar letter is being addressed to the Treasury.11814W34 iif r. Cox, Ho* iTfM. Amxk&amp;t 1919. Despatched i nwmiM,. M. Yuur deapai^i Mo. 75 of !8ih |^r« ilraifit of loiid iii Mesopotamia is .not practical©. 1 d® oonaidc-ring ^ith India office the question of a payment of aoney in complete seiilardent sad I think 13.5,000 would be ample* actual »u. is of coarse not finally decided on but I cannot go abo?e this and it is intended to end our subsidies to hiss altogether I consider the time-has come to dis continue the monthly payments of tomans ' 11*OUU* whole miter.indexed In any further communication on the subject, please quote tfo- 1Q0978/W/34. and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. Sir; - L+on £15,000 y 21st, 1919. $ &amp; m 1 Wi-on reference to theletter from this Department 110,85517 of +jhe 16th ul ™ end to previous correspon- cence, I pan directed by Earl curaon of Kedleston to transmit to you, herein, to be laid before Mr. Secretary Montagu, copies of correspondence, as marked in the margin, relating to the claims of prince Parman Parma, at present Governor-General of Pars, ypon His Majesty's Government and to the extent of the obligations Oj. His Majesty's Government to him. I am to draw attention to the final paragraph' of Sir p. cox' despatch, No.75 of May 18th last end transmit m you, herein, a copy of a memorandum, drawn up in this Department, suggesting that a final settlement of this claim might be reached either by the payment to His Highness of a sum of Fifteen thousand pounds or by the apportionment to him of some estate or property in Mesopotamia. I am to request you to .‘furnish me with Mr.Montagu's considered views on these alternative proposals, and in tue event of his being in favour of the payment of a sum of Fifteen thousand pounds to state whether he is prepared to accept a moiety of the expenditure involved. I am, Sir, Your most obedient humble Servant,Copy. ( 108006 .) PERSIA. n 4 , ! ''T . 1 if: . 1 S19 military. Decypher. Sir 0. Marling (Teheran). June 16th 1918 D. 12.30. p.m. R. 8.45.p.m. No.549. June 16th 1918. My telegram No,512, of June 6. His Majesty's Consul at Shiraz telegraphs that Farman Farma has made following request in writing:- A. his Majesty's Government will pay him compensation at the rate of £40,000 a year for losses sustained owing to non-collection of revenue affected by last three years from estates belonging to him and his five elder sons. Will guarantee them that revenue so long as troubles continue. G. Will guarantee lives, honour and free enjoyment of property to himself and his family. D. But in the event of his having to flee the country and of loss of his estates His Majesty's Government I wii.l grant him property in British territory and provide income equal to that lost. S. That such income be paid to him during his own , * life and to his sons afterwards. It would be unprofitable to examine re-opening of demands in detail and only question is what is it worth while to pay Farman Farma. Personally I think that his services i / r j ; 41 i.i i $ * si(18.6. 8/4)* services to us have been very great in the past and I agree with His Majesty's Consul that with some guarantee as he requests he would be able and willing to do much more, ye cannot expect him to burn his boats for us. I would suggest following. 1. £lt,000 down in respect of A* Tomans 3,000 a month so long as he remains Governor of Fars, •3. Tomans 3,000 a month to his family in Teheran of which Tomans 1,000 to Firuz. 4. £40,000 a year in case of exile of which £10,000 to Firuz. The proposals are greater than my earlier recom mendations which Treasury considered excessive (your telegram No.259 of May 13) but I feel bound to submit them as Farman Fanna's services to us at present moment are of such great importance and it seems to me we cannot rightly expect him to risk his whole position unless we guarantee him very substantially. I should be glad of an early reply.(108963.) PERSIA, MILITARY. Decypher. Sir 0. Marling (Teheran). 18th June 1918. D. 8.45 a.m. 18th June 1918. R. 8 a.m. 19th No.562. URGENT - My telegram 549 of June 16. Following from Consul at Shiraz. Begins, Farman Fanna makes following remarks on your suggestions. His principal point is that question in paragraph VI of my telegram No.Ill has not been touched as regards Capital represented by his properties i.e. no question of property of equal value to those he loses will be provided for him. For the rest he considers suggestions inadequate (as represented by 2 and 3 of your telegram under reply). He cannot remain another week Governor General of Fars recognised by Persian Government if he*openly sides with us and if he does not declare for us he gets nothing more from us. I do not consider present is the time for haggling over money - if his assistance is desired I consider we must agree generally to proposals made by him and formulated by me in my above mentioned telegram. If I can give him written guarantee that we accept those conditions generally, details to be decided later, he will come forward immediately and if not he cannot help us as we want. (? He is already) cursed in Pulpits- and his soldiers are maltreated in the streets. I strongly urge his proposals being accepted without discussion. Ends. (19.6. 3-4)(108943.) PERSIA A. military. Cypher telegram to Sir C. Marling (Teheran) Foreign Office, June 2ord, 1918, 5*45. p.m. No*336. Urp;ent. Your telegrams Nos. 549 and 562 (of June 16th and 18th respectively, Farman Farma*) Eastern Committee have had under consideration demands put forward by Farman Farma and the suggestions made by you and His Majesty's Consul at Shiraz on the subject. The Committee are unable without further data to decide the question of compensation for the alleged loss of revenues from his estates during the last three years. It is not clear to them for what reason his mere absence in . Fars should have rendered impossible the collection of revenue from his estates situated, presumably, near the capital and in other parts of Persia, and I should, there fore be glad, to receive your observations on this point. From your telegrams it appears that you consider that there is very material benefit to be gained by the retentioi of Farman Farma on our side, and in these circumstances His Majesty’s Government are prepared to make to Farman Farma a total allowance of Tornans 6,000 per mensem for him and his family so long as he remains (a) Governor-General of Fars (b) friendly to us and (c) for the duration of the war. If Farman Farma’s estates are confiscated owing to his friendly relations with His Majesty’s Government or if His Highness be driven into exile for the same reason. His Majesty’s Government will consider the payment to him of an adequate allowance.v copy. (85617/W/34) Cypher telegram to Sir p. Cox (Teheran) 15th June, 1919 # Foreign Office, 15th June, 1919. 1,45 p.m, NO. 340. Your despatch No. 75 (of May 18th). Please supply me if possiole with particulars of all sums paid to Farraan Farina at Shiraz which can properly be considered to be a subsidy from us as l distinct from Administrative Expenditure eventually recoverable from the Persian Government also telegraph what amount has been paid to the family rat Teheran since Farman Farraa took up his duties at Shiraz. This information is necessary for decision on the subject.s .4 copy. (100978) Decypher. Sir p. Cox (Tehran) 4th July, 1919 , D. 11.00. a.ra. 4th July, 1919. H. 11.30 a.m. 10th July, 1919. No. 460. Your tele grain No. 340, of 15th June. Suras paid to Governor-General Shiraz as a subsidy not recoverable from Persian Government amounted up to September 20th, 1918 to Tomans 2(21)000 (221000) as advised in ray despatch No 79 December 2nd, 1918 and since ?October 21st to about Tomans 12,000 a month. (? These) subsidies although not recoverable from Persian Government were for purposes of administrative expenditure approved by His Majesty’s Consul at Shiraz. They included certain allowances to Farman (Farm)-a. Thus in addition to his official salary of Tomans 2,000 a month paid out of advances recoverable from Persian Government he claimed Tomans 1,000 a month extra allowance which Persian Government disallowed but Miich has been paid him (as well as) (gr. undec.) (?further special) allowance of Tomans 2,000 a month approved by His Majesty’s Government out of above-mentioned ?future 4 copy. (100978) l recoverablerecoverable subsidy. These payments have been made monthly since July 1916. faecret, Payrents to his famiiy in Tehran consist of a monthly payment of Tomans 2,000 from resources at disposal of His Majesty's Minister.copy. (108006/13) 08963/18) .340 Of th June. 85617 ) ,\A Please refer to Sir C. Marling’s telegram No* 549 of 16th June, 1918* The proposal therein is to give Farman Farma: 1* £15,000 down to compensate him for alleged losses and 2« Tomans 3,000 a month as long as he remains Governor of Fars, 3. Tomans 3,000 a month to his family in Tehran* In Foreign Office telegram No. 336 of 23rd June, 1918, authority was given to pay Farman Farma 6,000 Tomans a month for him and his family so long as he remains (a) Governor of Fars, (b) friendly to us, (c) for the duration of the war. This arrangement was not carried out, but we asked Sir P. Cox to give particulars of all sums paid to Farman Farma which can properly be con- # side red as subsidy as distinct from administrative expenditure eventually recoverable from the Persian Government. His reply (herein) shows that the sums paid are as follows: up to Sept. 20, 1918 (see 19340) Tomans 221,657 Oct. 1918 to July 1919, about Tomans 12,000 a month. July 1916 to July 1919 Tomans 2,0 Firuz Mirza at Tehran,The subsidy of Tomans 12,000 a month is dealt with on paper 97921. in applying for it originally in January 1918, sir c. Marling said:- 'Of this sura xoraans 11,000 a month is required to meet personal allowance and other necessary expenditure of Governor General which Persian Governiflent will not recognise.' -P* Cox now says that 'these subsidies although not recoverable from the Persian Govern ment were for purposes of administrative expendi ture approved by H.M. Consul at Shiraz.' But as Tomans 1,000 a month was an extra personal allowance, I have taken that sum and the Tomans 2,000 a month paid in Tehran to his family and calculated them as follows:- Tomans 1,000 a month. Paid to Pan a an Parma as a personal allowance out of the sum of Tomans 12,000 a month paid for adminis trative purposes July 1918 - July 1919. 12 months Tomans 2,000 a month. Paid to Nosret ed Dowleh at Tehran for the Farman Parma's family - July 1918 - July 1919. 12 months Tomans. 12,000 24.000 Tomans 36,000 Authorised by F # 0* telegram No* 336 of 23rd June, 1918, Tomans 6.000 a month, July 1918 - July 1919, Tomans 72,000, Balance due to Farman Farraa Tomans 36,000 or £14,400 at the rate of Kran 25 « £1,I append a copy of my memorandum on the subsidy of Tomans 12,000 a month for convenience of'reference. G. P. 0. 15th July.n 9813/18) '1756/18) 71549/18) 88147/13 ) 15276/19) 0868/19) 4625) Recent history ot Pa man Parma* s subsidy of 12,000 Tomans a month. 1. On loth January, 1918, sir c. Marling asked for allocation ot Tomans 17,000 a month for Pars: adding that 'of this sura Tomans 11,000 a month is required to meet personal allowance and other iiecessary expenditure of Governor General which Persian Government will not recognise.** On 22nd April, 1918, Sir C. Marling applied for a new allocation of Tomans 12,000 a month for further 6 months and said 'this sum virtually represents personal allowance and other necessary expenditui’e of Parraan Parma which Persian Government will not recognise but which we cannot discontinue in present circumstances, H 3 0 On October 11th, 1918, Sir P. Cox asked for the sanction of Tomans 12,000 a month to be renewed for six months for the same reasons as those given by his predecessor in No.2. The renewal was authorised for three months. 4„ On 26th January, 1919, Sir P. Cox asked for a renrwal for 3 months. This was agreed to on 27th Pebruary for three months from January 23rd to April 23rd. 5. On April 26th Sir P. Cox asked for another renewal for three months 'as expenses continue whilst revenue returns have scarcely begun.' The renewal was authorised on 7th June until 22nd July 'or conclusion of peace which ever is earlier. (Initialled) G.P.C. 15th July,[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government. ! PERSIA. [June 7.] CONFIDENTIAL. Section 2. J5617] No. 1 . Sir P. Cox to Earl Curzon.—(Received June 7.) Tehran, (No. 75.) My Lord, I HAVE the honour to refer to the correspondence ending with Foreign Office telegram No. 336 dated the 23rd June, 1918, on the subject of the claims of his Highness Prince Farman Farma and his family upon His Majesty’s Government and the extent of our obligations to them. It appears from the record that Sir Charles Marling felt that the response of His Majesty’s Government to the recommendations made in his telegram No. 549 of the 16th June, 1918, fell so far short of what he considered would satisfy his Highness or could advisedly be communicated to him by this legation that he decided to take no action upon it; and there the matter stood when I assumed charge of this legation. I understood from my predecessor that he contemplated making personal representations on arrival in England. His Highness Firuz Mirza Nusret-ed-Dowleh approached me on the subject soon after I arrived, and at first I was able to put him off with the argument that the situation had changed so much as to make the matter less urgent, and it would be better to see the result of Sir Charles Marling’s representations to the Foreign Office. Recently, however, both he and his father have returned to the attack, and as we must sooner or later give them a reply, I do not think there is any object to be gained by fencing with the matter further. Father and son consider that they have received assurances in principle, and that it is only a question of their being defined. They base their claim to this extent on Sir Charles Marling’s letter to the Farman Farma of the 3rd November, 1915, of which I attach a copy.* The precise losses for which the family claim consideration are embodied in the following paragraphs :— 1. As regards their properties situate in Azerbaijan, mostly in Maragha, on the border of Soujbulak and Kurdistan, most of their villages have been in the Russo- Turkish fighting zone, and have been bombarded and laid waste by both parties and subsequently overrun by disbanded troops. Nearly all houses and other buildings have been gutted or destroyed by the removal of all woodwork. All live-stock, both for agricultural use and for breeding purposes, have been looted or consumed. They estimate that the cost of repairing the damage would be not less than 500,000 tomans, and the loss of revenue suffered, 250,000 tomans. 2 . Properties at Assadabad on the Kermanshah-Hamadan road. These have not suffered so much in the way of destruction, but both Turks and Russians were in possession of the tract and lived on it, paying for part of what they took in worthless paper money. They claim losses in this area of 200,000 tomans. They of course do not expect us to refund them these losses, but they urge that, in view of the undoubted and unwavering services they have rendered to us in difficult times, it is incumbent on us, now that we are in a position to do so, to see that they obtain prompt reparation. His Highness the Farman Farma has recently put forward the suggestion that if we retain control of Mesopotamia we • should recompense them without inflicting undue burden on ourselves by granting the family, on lease, a tract of Saniyeh property in Mesopotamia. I mention the suggestion in case it should be considered to form a possible method of solution. As regards the title of the family to our assistance, Sir Charles Marling is better able to speak from personal experience than I am, but I certainly think that we do owe them a very great debt of obligation, and that we are bound to acquit ourselves of it in some measure and in some form. I can only submit the facts of the case for the wise consideration of His Majesty’s Government. I have, &amp;c. P. z. COX. SirO. Marling 1 to Farman Farina, November 3, 1915. [2903 p—2]INDEXED A. / 33io j 191 EMM 2*2&amp; «&gt;PcynhfT. Sir ?. Cot? (Tehran) July 4th, 1919 . 11. 30. a. w. July 4th. 1919, . 11,3‘ .a.ra, July 10th. 1919. Xo. 460. Tour telegram Ho. 340. Su ** paid t0 Governor-General Shiraa as a subsidy net reooTer--.:-le from Persian Government amounted mi to September 80th, 191 a to Tomans 2 ( 21)000 { 221000 ) as advised in my despatch &gt;fo, 79 December 2 nd. 1918 and sines TOotober 21 st. to about Tomans 12,000 a month. (i Them) subsidies although not recoverable from Persian Government were for pumosea of administrative expenditure approved by His Majesty’s Consul at Shiras. They included certain allowansee to Tarman (fan).a, ihus in addition to hi &lt;• official salary of Tomans 2,000 “ mortth aala out of advances recoverable from Persian Govern-' went he claimed Tomans 1,000 a month extra allowance which Pereiaa Government disallowed but which has been paid him (as well as) (&lt;?r. undeo.) (? further special) allowance of Tomans 8,000 a month approved by Hie Majesty's Government rat of above-mentioned Tfuture recoverable subsidy. These payment* have bean mad&lt;? monthly alnct July 1916# or^ta ‘ayments to hin family in Tehran consist of a monthly payment of Toman a 3* GOO from re sou res a at disposal of His Majesty's Minister, KjOI 18 SEP 1919^■ l (e5Ci?/rf/34) *, 1 « / ^ - rV O^LY. Cjrpher telegram to Sir IV^Oox (Teheran) June IBth, 1919 Foreign ^mco, June 15th, 1919, 1,45 p.m. llo. 340, Hour despatch .No, ?5 (of .May IPth), I Plaaee au : ;&gt;ply .ie if noDr4hle with partioulars of all ! ®'*iaa paid , wo Farnian Farstta at -j'airaa 'which can properly bo considered to be a subsidy from us as distinct from Adainistratiro iirpondi tuto eventually recoverable from the Poroimn Govorroacnt also telegraph wh&amp;t amount has been paid j to the family at Teheran since Far man F&amp;rma took up his •'duties at Shir a*, Xhia information is neceaomry for decision an the subject. - 1 . 1 . h cep 1CIn anj further cmiununication on this subject, please cwote No. and address The Under-Se/^etary of State, Foreign OfSce, London, S.W. 1. The Undersecretary of State for Foreign^ffyirs presents his compliments to the /^hjsbr and, by direction of the Secretary of State, thmsmits herewith cof of the under-mentioned paper. IQIQ Reference to previous correspondence Letter Foreign Officetima, it in incumbent on us, now that m are in*f&amp; poeition to do «o # to see Uiat tnoy ootain prompt r^ration. Hi. ^ . n^ss-tha Farman ?ama haa recently put forward the auction that if wo retain control of ’%«opotama we should reco^mens# tho?t without inflicting undue burden on oura&amp;lt/e* by granting the family on lease attract of Saniyth property in llitopotemia I mention the Mg jf tion in ii ^hoild im conaiderod to form a possible method of eolation. ns Mgardw Hi# Utt# of the tmilf I# #mr ###1# ^ r linpf is better able to enoak from personal ex perience than I am. but I certainly think that w do owe them a very great debt of obligation am v wi^ S«r&gt;\*&lt;. r Kkj«-4LVU&gt;vt quit ourselves oT^TPIn^ome^ that m are bound to ac- i can only submit the facts of the lor the wis# consideration of*His Majesty*s fiovern- m^n t. 7 / I nave the honour to ue # witli Uie lugh^et respect, : y Lord, . Your Lordship * s most obedien t, burnt 1 c Servant,, V- I. rrh^DSCument is the Property of His B ritannic Maiesty's Govern m « nt . and shoul d Foreign Office if not required for official use.1 g cwjp ’ ■' ■ / *•;, ./ '* f * ■ « ^ W *i —■ (^\£) ^ X-C/U^y' £EBm- HrfWr (1089655.) ! J. MILITARY. Cypher te! . Llarli^r (leheran) Rutqikii June 2?rd. 1918, 5 C 45 p. m, No. 338 # Urgent , Your telegrams Npe, 549 and 562 (^f June 16th and 18th respectively f Farpan Farma«) Eastern Committee have had under consideration demands put forward by Farmar F^rma end the suggestions made by you and His Majesty ‘ s Consul at Shiran on the subject* The Committee are unable without further data to decide the question of compensation for the alleged loss of revenues from his estates during the last three years* It is not clear to them for what reason his mere absence in Fars should have rendered impossible the collection of revenue from his estates situated, presumably, near the capital and in other parts of Persia, and I should, there* tore, be glad to receive your observations on this point. From your telegrams it appears that you consider that there is very material benefit to be gained by the retention of Furman Forma, on our side, and in these cir* cumstances His Majesty ! s Government are prepared to make toFThis Pocumeirt foe &gt;f¥lce if ticrf required for off cial use.] .it • ’ ■ h tif-m if H jy* ’ } ] Q ! I -m' \ O x ' — IESSSJAjl. (108968.) % Cypher telegri’n to Sir- C. (lehjeran) Foreign Office, June 2?rd, 1618, 5.45 p. ni No. 336. Urgent . Your telegrams N0 b, 549 and 562 (fii June 16th and 18th respectively, Farpian Farma,) Eastern Coranittee have had under consideration demands put forward by Farinas Fpma and the suggestions made by you and His Majesty's Consul at Shiraz on the subject. Ihe Comittoe are unable without further data to decide the question of compensation for the alleged loss of revenues from his estates during the last three years. It is not clear to them for what reason his mere absence in Pars should have rendered impossible the collection of revenue from his estates situated, presumably, near the capital and in other parts of Persia, and I should, there fore, be glad to receive your observations on this point From your telegrams it appears that you consider that there is vmy piaterlal benefit to be gamed by the retention of Far-man Forma, on our side, and in these cir cumstances His Matty's Government are prepared to maketo Forman Farma a tonal allowance of Tomans 6,000 per men sera for him and his family so long as .he remains (a) Governor- General of Pars, (h) friendly to us, and (c) for the dura tion of the war. If Farman Farma r s estates are confiscated owing to his friendly relations with His Majesty’s Government or if His Highness he driven into exile for the same reason, ills MajestyHs Government will consider the payment to him of an adequate allowance.■'■pan» immediate and onfidential ■A n 4$ a ' 44 4 . VV 41. y t ;' 1 \ V Wa j ( /°$t 8 f W. f 1918 .) 3 if ‘ Reference .-—Letter Foreign O.fice. The Undersecretary of State for Foreign A fairs presents his compliments to the Undersecretary of State for India, and is directed by the Secretary of State to transmit the accompanying cofiies of ^ telegram , as marked m the Foreign Office, - ■L - '''&gt; w- PE \5Ja hl LIx^gy De cypher, Sir 0, Marling. (Teheran), June 18th,1918, Do 8 t 'b.a.m. 12* 25cP,m June 18111,1918 NOv 564. Shiraz situation J cal Plj lD In view of Consul’s opinion as to urgent necessity to give Far man Farm and Kavam assurances on their own terms I should he glad to receive authority to instruct him to give wrimen promise to than effect at once (16,6. 8/4).rThfs Document is the - His be retunned to the Foreign and shouldf ——!i-^2£-r23fej_ft&gt;rofflciai ..^~r~ MILITAs Decypher, sir C. h-Rrllrig*-(rvheran% ,iath ju.ie- lcjs D• o,45 h, n, ISih a.m. 19th June 191S V, ; T 0 . 562 T'acw aaaaaaaa^»aaaaaa^aa ..$S£ltV£o My telegram 549. Following from Consul at shiras. Begins. Farman Farma .nakes following remarks on your suggestions. T fis principal point is that question in paragraph VI &gt;f my telegram -o. Ill has not been toucheo as i £'. 00.1 els Capital represented by his properties i.e. no question of property of equal value to those he loses will be provided, for him. j For the rest he considers suggestions inadequate a ( as ^Presented by 2 and 3 of your telegram under reply). ! T ~ Ie cw-ot renain another week Governor General of pars 1 recognised by Persian Government if he openly sides with us and if he does not declare for us he gets nothing more iron us. I do not consider present is the time for aaggxina over money ~ if his assistance is desired 1 consider ye must agree generally to pro no sals made by nun and. formulated by me in my above mentioned telegram, y -1 can give him written guarantee that we accent vnose conditions generally, details to be decided later, ne will come forward immediately and if not he cannot neip us as vn want.(? TT e is already) cursed in pulpits and a 1 s sol 01 or s ar e :m 1 tr e a ted 1 n th e- stre e t s. .. I s tr 0 np 1 y in;ge his nr 0 nosa 1 s be 1 1 ig accented w it3^• • discussion. Ends. (IS.6. 8-4)[This Document iis the Pr-oyvertv of; r H«s-vailt -wtlsit. Ofliae if not yecguired fo be returned to th : ti I/iJijlTAHY ’s ©O De cypher Sir c. Marling, (Teheran), June 16thji918 I), 12*30,p*rru Rc 3*45^,111, June l£th 0 1918. No, 549 My tele gr am Nca 5}3, His Majesty f s Consul at Shiraz telegraphs that Par man Parma hac made following request in v^riting:- His Majesty’s Government will pay him compensa tion at the rate of £40&gt;000 a year for losses sustained owing to non** collect ion of revenue affected by last three years from estates belonging to him and his eider sons, B* Will guarantee them that revenue so long as troubles continue c Co Will guarantee lives,honour and free enjoyment of property to himself and his family. Do But in the event of his having to flee the country and of loss of his estates His Majesty’s Govern ment will grant him property in British territory and provide income equal to that lost* E, That such income be paid to him during his own life and to his sons afterwards c 9 services! \ PERSIA EaBMI DecyiDher. Sir C, Marling (Teheran). 6th June 1918, D, 5 p s m e 6th p, 8 ajn, 8th no „ 512 6 (K). June 1918 Copy to ItnilSL A A »•* A A. A. A «V A A A A &lt;•'&gt; A i J &gt; A »*, A A My teleginarn no , 413 parraan Parma has asked -Consul if on successful conclusion of war we will guarantee him in writing position of prince of Southern Pe rs ia tributary to Persia hut practically independent. This he urges would ensure peaceful and well managed Southern Persia entirely under our control. I am replying to His Majesty 5 s Consul that proposal amounts to what will he piece of shameless duplicity which I am sure His Majesty*s Government do not contemplate hut that if he thinks flat refusal would he too discouraging he may inform Farman Faina that if ever events should force unon us some such solution of question of Southern Persia 1 would endeavour to get l-LH. appointed. It is evident that recent developments in Shiraz have made Farman parraa anxious about future and I would heg favourable consideration (group unaecynherahle) propo sals.. o , c 8-4) 111 Hr ! iigtogJtogument is the Property of His Britannic Majes ty’s Governfl$tTan&lt;J^ should be returned to the Foreign Office when done with' unless ‘ for official use.] required N (W- r y 1 iiv; jrVr i ecyphtsr. Sir c. Marling, (Teheran), 1913. D. 2.'50ep e m, May 15tli e 191; * P • 1 o • P 0 in. No.413. Your telegram No.259. Allowances I suggest are modest compared with tnose which Germans are paying their friends e.g. Nizam Es Sultaneh who the Persian Minister for Foreign Affaire informed me gets Turkish £30,000. a month out of which however he has to pay the Persian refugees while in addition he had been guaranteed sum very largely in excess of their value m cos 3 his property here was confiscated. However aie question of allowances has not been raised of l-&lt;.oe c*na i± iiuuueh’s (iimprove) as seems likely, very likcuy will not be alluded to again. I should like however to make the gift to Piruz who has been of the greatest service to us since Parman Parma went to Pars„_ ^ ' L ' *' —V - MitSI 4 Cypher telegram to Sir C* ferllng (Teheran) No. 259. In view of present situation in Pars 3 it appears un necessary to come to any immediate decision on the subject^ though I cannot disguise from you the fact that I consider it extremely improbable that the Treasury would he prepared to entertain any scale of allowances such as you suggest. Unless, therefore, you consider that the matter is of im perative urgency. J hope the mutter may he left in abeyance for the presentsa •;UL V [This Document is the Property ot Hi s Britannic Mail. should be returned to the Foreign OHi cc wh^r^T for official use.'! ^nmeat, and unles PERSIA. ^ &gt; o AlIUlARY. (66694). Cypher Telegram to Sir 0. Marling (Teheran) Foreign Office, April 27th. 1918. 6,30.p,m. !\io. 224. * *• Your telegram No. 309 (of 15tH;^iftff Barman f Farma). Discussion of question raised in your telegram No. 158 (of 27th. February) was adjourned as it seemed unlikely that matter would require early decision. I presume that the eventuality which His Highness has in mind is his possible recall by Persian Govern ment in event of their deciding to throw in their lot with the enemy and the consequent seizure of his pro perties. T agree tnat it is desirable to give necessary support to anyone who has committed himself to our cause and worked with us as has Farman Farma. I should therefore be glad to learn your views as to what guarantee His Highness would seek and what com pensation we should be justified in promising to him and his family in the contingency in question. , \any urgency cut if information 'received from Kasvin see my telegram Ho* .156.of today has any foundation in fact it would be well to take them into consideration at once. My earlier information Ms been to tho effect (group undecypherable] Jangali movement in this- direction was contemplated ior two montM or more but it is possible that B*M» agents who must have in mind possibility of movement on our part- from Bagdad have induced Kuchih Khan to forestall ns by a coup with Bolshevih assistance before the last Russian troops have left. Addressed go Foreign Office No, 158, repeated to Sir ?. Cox and Government of India,</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100059346669.0x000003_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/10/577/2</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100059346669.0x000003</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/10/577/2</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>File 4612/1915 Pt 2 'Persia: personal claims of Farman Farma upon HMG; proposed payment of a lump sum'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1918/1919</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2018-04-30T09:52:48</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 item (64 folios)</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This part contains telegrams, despatches, correspondence, memoranda, and notes concerning the personal claims of the Governor of Fars, Farman Farma [ʿAbd-al-Ḥosayn Mīrzā Farmānfarmā] upon HM Government and the proposed payment of a lump sum.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100059346669.0x000003#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>