<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000151_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-11T10:37:52.528Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">j- ■ £ i 1 ri |v IF o. 37 Political Agency, Bahrain, tksrp SMCY- 1 ' Dated the 11th January 1931 From Oai^tain 0. G-. Prior, I.A., Political Agent, Bahrain To The Hon'hle the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire Dir, I have the honour to forward for your information a copy of a letter I have received from the Adviser to the Government of Bahrain, j-'rima lacie there seems no doubt that within the three mile limit that Bahrain Government are entitled to levy such dues as they may wish, subject only to treaty limitations, and I feel quite certain that the Persian ]-overnment does not allow transhipment for foreign countries to take place within its waters without the levy of duty. Before considering the matter further, I would be glad oO oe informed what the practice of the Persian Government in the matter is, and what rules, if any, they have to -ovem such transact ions. I have the honour to be, Sir, lour most obedient servant. Political Agent, Bahraina/ Gop/ of letter No.955/3 dated the ISth Raja'b, 1349, from the Aoviser to the Government, Bahrain, to H.B.M's Political Agent, Bahrain:- Re: Transliipmeiit of Qarv:o . I have the honour to refer to some previous correspondence on the above subject between /ourself and the Director of Customs and the Acting ^dtiser of which the last letter was your No.T/ll of 11th August 1928 from Shiraz. Since then the question seems to have been deferred. Recently it has been re-considered by me and the Director of Customs. Before the re-or^anisation of 1923, transhipment of cargo at sea within the port took place unrestrictedly because there was no efficient means of controlling it from the shore. Owing to the reticent improvements in the amenities of the Port it is considered that the Transhipment at sea has increased; and such transhipment is nearly ssmsxai always ci cargo intended for, and coming from, the same mainland ports at present served by the regular RS cargo. I propose that the transhipment of cargo at sea within the Port should be under the control of the Port, and that some dues should be paid on it in return for the use of the Port. It is therefore suggested that the cargo for hj. el ui an Ports should be treated in the same way as ordinary RLi cargo and ilxport cargo, but on cargo for other ports tue lull 5/o should be deposited, this being refundable upon production oi the usual proof of landing witnin sixty days.1/ I Confidential. Ho.72-S of 1931. British Residency &amp; Consulate-General, Bushire, the 24th February 1931, From - The Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf To - The Political Agent, Bahrain. \ V Sir, ^ith reference to your letter Ho.37/7/4, dated the 11th January 1931, I am desired to inform you that Bushire customs levy a fee of 9 shahis per package whether directly transhipped to another vessel or landed and subsequently re-shipped. A transhipment manifest is required. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant, \ Gapt., Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.Telegram Oo0.e ■^rom Prior, Isfahan. Re siden t, Busiiire To No: Nil Dated. 22nd received 23rd 3eptemper, 1931. Following from Adviser begins:- Propose subject to no Political objection charging 2 per cent customs dues i.e re-exportjdue on cargo not landed 'but transhipped within Port to Native Graft for Poreign Ports. Matter is urgent heavy transhipment occurred Banimra and unless stopped urgently otata will suffer severe Pinaneial losses finds. I consider ^tate can do what it pleases within ( ? ) subject to treaty restrictions. Wholesale Evasion re-export dues will involve serious loss to State Prior.17/' Uls Telt^rcua G»T.C» Prom Political Resident, BusMi® To Political j^gsrt, Bahrain. Ho 503. Dated the E7th September i93i !&gt; /I f4/&gt;f Re-export dues* Matter has been discussed with po litical Agent and it is regretted that owing to shaikh isa's undertaking giyen to jtsin saud no duty is leviable on cargo transhipped at sea, political Agent will re-open the matter on retarn from India. •RSSIESHT-1st October 1931. No: 04/ 185 To. 1, The Commissioner In sinff* Political -eoartment Karachi. 2, The director of Customs. Bahrein. 3. The Secretary, Central Board of Revenue, Simla, Subject:- Bahrien Trale . Sir, y As desired by the Committee, of ray chamber, I have the honour to enclose herewith a copy of representation jral members on the above sjibject, which It will be noted that the Bahrein trade which has ever since remained in the ands of British subjects is now seriously threaten end as a result of a new a -ran gam en t near Bahrein, It is thus Quite obvious that the nort 0° Bahrein will soon cease to be distributing centre, as it has ever C since been for A J air an places beyond, for reason o' diffe- -rence of about ofx annas eleven per ba • in handlinjT charges, duty Etc: on goods, if taken direct to Ajair instead of through Bahrein, Side by side it may ultimately orove to be preju- - dicial to the inte ests of the ■■riuish shipping as well if the trade passess to a non-British subject. In tuis connection it may also be mentioned that the inte ests of Bahrein customs, which is under the ritish supervision, are also radically effected. In the circumstances I have the honour to xsspcxx request that will be ^leased to tslce such ste-os as are deemed fit to ntotect th- trade fromKarachi to Bahrein. X have the honour^ Sir, Your most obe-iinet HOflOUBARYtOSFIDBHTlAL . Ho. 673-3 of 1931. British Residency &amp; Consulate-General, Bushire, the 10th October 1931, To The Political Agent, Bahrain . Heferance this office telegram JSo.503, dated 27th September 1931, and petition dated 3rd October 1931 to your address from certain exporters from Karachi to Bahrain. Resident your views on the question mentioned above. MEaORAMBllM . Transhipment dues at Bahrain . 2. Please submit to the Hon'ble the Political By Order, for Secretary to the Political Resident f , in the Persian Gulf,^ confidential. H o.729-S of 1931. British Residency &amp; Consulate-General, Bushire, the 3rd November 1931* from • The ilon'ble Lt.Colonel H.V.Biscoe, I.A., v Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, To • The Commissioner in Sind, Karachi, With reference to your endorsement Io,{)-1401«G, dated the 16th October 1931, forwarding a copy of a letter from the Honorary Secretary, the Buyers and Shippers Chamber, Karacil, regarding Bahrain trade, and asking for my remarks thereon, I have the honour to state that there is no new arrangement for shipment to Ojair* For the last 10 years the arrangement has been that goods intended for the dominions of His Majesty King Ibn Saud should pay 2 percent duty if landed at Bahrain and subsequently transhipped within a period of 20 days, and no duty if transhipped straight into dhows in the harbour for conreyance to the mainland. Sometimes one procedure is adopted and sometimes the other as may be moat convenient, The Honorary Secretary states that this arrangement would be ultimately prejudicial to the Interests of British shipping. It is not clear how this can be the case or how British shipping can be in any way affected, for the goods will in any case be brought up to Bahrain as hitherto by British India steamers. I may mention that .lb •oS'' that Bahrain is not a British port as the writer seems to imagine, and the arrangement is one arrived at between two independent Arab rulers, and it will therefore be difficult to bring about any modification in the existing procedure, which, as I have already pointed out, has been in force for 10 years. I have the honour to be. Sir Your most obedient servant. It, Col on el Political Resident in the Persian Gulf* mfide: sistant ,sh Residency &amp; Consulate-General Copy forwarded to the Political Agent, Bahrain, for information■24 C's. P. P.—L (in) 126—500-4-31 / Nn C/118. From The Agency, Bahrain, ^ l T w ' ? rjn^rf the P,8t.h Governbp.r 193I-. l-lv V 1 Ij**- i&amp;QnUS The Political Agent, BAHRAIN. To The Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Sir, i 1 ' / I have the honour to refer to jo#r letter No:673-S dated the 10th October 1931 and to your letter to the Commissioner in Sind and to enclose a copj, of mj letter to Messrs Llackinnon, Mackenzie u Co., at 3o baj, tcgether with a copy of their reply . to me which shows that they have now decided to cease the practice of overside delivery. 2. Upon reaching Karachi in October I Liaediately visited Messrs Mackinnon,Mackenzie u Oompany who had originally sanctioned the overside delivery and discussed the matter with them. They did not know that I «had seen-privately the Mesopotamia Persia Corporation's letter to them and were at fist disposed to create difficulties. Ofcourse.the loss of cargo was a serious consider ation but finally thev a Teed that if the Bahrain Government t/ v QJ guaranteed to reduce their 'khanchiya' charges they would recommend to Bombay.with whom the decision lay,that no more cargo should be booked for .oversice delivery. I then wrote to Messrs Mackinnon,Mackenzie co Company at Bombay. • 3. On ray return the Indian merchants waiteS upon me and again put forward their grievance. I told them that i had done all t at I could and advised them to renew their applications to Bombay and not to Marachi.who had not the power to decide the matter. 4. Messrs Mackinnon.Mackenzie c.Company at Bo-bay then wired to the Mesopotamia Persia Corporation that the same shipper had offered them 5000 bags on the sole condition that the, guaranteedc&gt;7 2. overside delivery,and that failing it he would ship by other lines in future. Their Manager discussed the matter with me and a reply was sent that this could only 'be bluff and that with the winter storms at hand he would be bound to shin by the British India Steam Navigation Company's steamers. Messrs acldnnok,Ilackenzie £ Company then wrote saying that they would discontinue overside deliveries. 5. The news gave great satisfaction both to the Bahrain Government and the Indian merchants and it is to be hoped that the matter will rest there. I had been nervous that the extra T khanchiya T would provoke some such 'affaire' but in the face of the Financial Adviser's and I'irector of Customs' insistence had not seen my way to force my view upon them. Both are now, however,converted to this view. The question is a complicated one and our whole action regarding the He Export concession has appeared to me ultra vires from the very start. This must, however,be discussed another time and with fuller treatment. I have the honour to be Sir. Your Host Obedient Servant, Political Agent, Bahrain.14 No:K/l4* Karachi. Dated the 17th0^tober 1931. from: - The Political Agent, Bahrain at KARACHI. To:- Vessrs ifackinnon Mackenzie &amp; Co., Ballard Estate..Bombay. Sirs, I have the honour to refer to the question of ■ o-rereide deliveries at Bahrain of goods manifested for Ojair and other mainland ports. 2. The Mesopotamia Persia Corporation have,I believe, given you the facts of the case from their point of view,and your Karachi branch have also informed you how they are affected as shippers. 1 understand that you have temporarily suspended these shipments,but in case further preasure is brought upon you to resume them,l think it advisable to show J how the Bahrain State will be affected and the possible repercussions upon your interests. S. The Bahrain State depend on their Customs revenue for 90% of their revenue,and in their straitened circumstances the slightest reduction is a most serious matter. The arrangement of overside delivery by the British India Steam navigation Company causes a loss of ad valorem on the whole amount transhipped and these amounts we have to wake good somehow,a probable alternative being the levy of Port dues and increased customs fines for packages short delivered. At present the Shipping Companies pay no dues whatsoever, though they benefit substantially by the facilities provided ! and are able to clear their veAiels far more quickly than was formerly the case. You are probably aware of the instance of a certain rice steamer before the War which was delayed for 66 days,and it is only the improved administration2. and facilities that have made such incidents a thing of the past. The levy of port dues at Bahrein would probably form an awkward precedent,and one which the Persian Government might desire to follow though the facilities they provide are everywhere negligible. 4. Jfrom the express letter received today from the Hon*ble the Political Resident I find that the Indian merchants at Bahrain have appealed both to him and to my locum tenens regarding the overside deliveries,pointing out that the practice would Involve the ruin of their mainland buisness. As you are probably aware,their branches on the mainland were closed by order of the Kedjas-Nejd Government a few years ago,and they are obliged to maintain Arab agents to handle their business there. This they do at present by selling their imports to an Arab firm at Bahrain while the goods are in Customs charge,the consignment being subsequently re-exported by the Arab firm to its agents on the mainland. Should the arrangement fail they can always import the con signment (almost invariably rice) into Bahrain and so get theij money back. If.however,anyone is allowed overside delivery, the Indian importer is completely out out.as he has no branch on the mainland to handle consignments and is obliged to sell his goods for anything that is offered. As a representative of the Indian Government any loss of business to Indian subjects is naturally a matter of concern to me,and I feil sure that if a profit is to be made.you yourselves would prefer that an Indian firm rather than a Hejdi firm should make it. 5. The Mesopotamia Persia Corporation have represented their case to you and shown the loss that overside deliveries will involve for them.but of course there is the question of the loss of cargo to the British indian Steam navigation Coy to be considered. I have discussed the matter with the Manager of your Karachi Branch.and it appears that he con sidered that the British India Steam navigation Company were3. losing oargo to country craft who compensated for the irregular sailing toy greater economy of rates and complete avoidance of Bahrain dues,and he mentioned that the Arato shipper who had first applied for the orerside delivery stated that the rates had recently toeen enhanced. This is to some extent true. The Customs dues for re-export cargo continue at 2^ ad Talorem.the figure for the past 10 years (they were formerly 6^ and no re-export concession was allowed) ( tout the 'khanchia*,a demurrage charge.has.since this summer been leriable after three days and not after 10 days as before,and so if a consignment were to be held up in Bahrain for a day or two by rough weather it would become liable to this three days kbanchia which is roughly about 1| to on bag cargo. 6. After my interview with your Karachi Branch I immediately communicated with the financial Adviser at Bahrain and asked him whether,if you would cease overside deliveries lie would be prepared to remove the three days khanchia on re export cargo,in other words to revert to the former practice and leave the rates as they had been before. He has just replied agreeing to this and so I trust you will see your way to meeting the wishes of the Bahrain Government arid refrain from allowing overside delivery. The advantage of it can only lit best be/temporary for regulations could be devised to defeat such delivery within territorial waters,though time would be lost and difficulties would ajrise. Of course, the Bahrain Government cannot protest at anything that takes place outside territorial waters,but these stretch a long way,and 1 feel certain that the delays to the steamer which carried arms and ammunition for the Hedjas-Hajd Government two years ago,(which lead to some correspondence at the time) will make any repetition of overside delivery outside territorial waters most unlikely. 7. 1 am returning to Bahrain tomorrow and will be glad toVI 4. to give you any further Information that you raqulra* . I hare the honour to be air. Your l£ost Obedient Servant* Political Agent« Bahrain at Karaohi.Oopy of letter dated 5th November 1931,Uo:2310,from Messrs Mackimion,lIackenzie LGo.,Bombay,to the Political Agent,Bahrain. OVERSIDE DELIVERIES AT BAHRAIN OF GOODS MANIFESTED TO OJAIH aND OTEER LJUNLAND PORTS. We have the honour to acknowledge receipt of your letter No:K/l4- dated the- 17th Ultimo and which was written to us prior to your departure from Karachi. The particulars you furnished were very helpful to us and we are much obliged for all the trouble you 'have taken ! in the same connection. We have now definitely decided to refrain from hooking : cargo from Karachi to Ojair,and other mainland ports,and our Agents at Karachi have he en instructed accordingly. We have also written to the Company's Agents at Bahrain in the same connection./ f ■ 7^1 2- • i tf' Ko.C.35 of 1931. Office of the Political Resident in the P«rrsian Gulf, s. 8. 'CHAKLA', SIB, 14th December 1931, from « The Hon'ble Lt.Colonel H.V.Biscoe,I.A., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, fo - The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, Hew i ^elhi. Sir, p • I have the honour to invite a reference to the correspondence ending with letter lo.SSl-S of 23rd September 1920 from the Deputy Political Resident, Persian Gulf, to the Government of India, foreign and Political Department, dealing with the question of the levy of customs dues by the Bahrain State on goods intended for the territories of His Majesty King Ibn Saud. Under the orders then issued the rate of duty levied on goods landed at Bahrain and transhipped within 20 days to the mainland was reduced to 2^, while no duty at all was leviable on goods transhipped at sea which were not put ashore. The fact that no duty was leviable on goods transhipped at sea evoked a very vigorous protest from Shaikh Isa at the time and has always been a sore point with the Bahrain Government. 2. During last summer seme large consignments of rice were sent to Bahrain and transhipped straight to the mainland thus evading all customs dues. The Adviser to the Bahrain Government therefore addressed the Political Agent on the subj'ecr and stated that owing to recent improvements in the amenities of ...**2~ I ... of the port, transhipment at sea had increased and that some dues should be paid on such goods in return for the use of the port. The matter was referred lay the Political Agent to the Residency, and as Captain Prior was then coming down from Ispahan to Bushire, the opportunity was taken to point out to that under the orders of 1920 the State was pre cluded from making any charge on transhipment goods, 3, i may mention that not only was the transhipment of goods a loss to the State but also to the large Indian mercantile community of Bahrain, who were deprired of the middlemen*s profits, and they made representations on the subject through their head offices to the Commissioner in Sind and the Buyers and Shippers Chamber at Karachi. From Bushire Captain Prior proceeded to Karachi, and while there took up the matter of transhipment cargo with the British India Agents, and I have just received a letter from him in which he informs me that they have agreed to refuse to accept cargo for overside delivery in return for reduction of demurrage charges by the Bahrain State, which was formerly leviable after 3 days, but which will in future be leviable only after 10. 44 It seems not improbable that this arrangement will evoke Tigerous complaints from Arab merchants to Ibn Baud who may be moved to protest regarding it, since, while it does not break the letter of the previous agreement, it could I think be held to infringe the spirit. I am therefore reporting the matter for the information of the Government of India, but unless His Majesty's Minister at Jeddah has reasons to urge to the contrary I would suggest that we should wait and see whether Ibn Saud moves in the matter.I am sending a copy of this despatch, to His 1 Cv* Majesty^ Minister at Jeddah and to His Majesty's Secretary of State for India. I have the honour t o be. Sir, Your most obedient servant, ^ Lt. Colonel, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Copy forwarded to the Political Agent, Bahrain, with reference to his Ho.G/118 of 28th llovember 1931. Confidential Assistant. . - - - -( \\ nonfidentlal » Ko.lOO-S of 1932. British Residency &amp; Consulate-General, Buahire, the 18th February 1932. A copy of Jeddah despatch ^o.l4 t dated the I 18th January 1932, to the Ooverniaent of India is forwarded herewith for information. Jl p 2. In this connection please refer to Bahrain a . m meraorandum So.235-0, dated the 9th August 1920 to the Wm Deputy Political Resident, Eushire. We have not got on our records a copy of the Political Agent's letter to Ihn ■b y ' t Sa'ud referred to in the latter* s reply of 12th z.il s^adah 1338 (28/7/20). Please forward an Arabic copy and translation thereof. By Order. 1 „ for Secretary to the Political Resident t in the Persian Gulf, The Political Agent, Bahrain.C's P. P.—L (III) 129—500-4-31. no, op 193 -v-. The Political Agency, Bahrain, Dated the 6th. March To The Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident * Please refer to your Memorandum Wo:100-S dated the 18th February 1932. I forward herewith English and Arabic copies of letter dated 14th July 1920,No:C/l96,from the Political Agent,Bahrain,to Bin Sa T ud,to which the latter^ letter of the 12th Dhil Qa.^ha 1338 was a reply. MEMORANDUM. the Persian Gulf BUSHIRE Political Agent Bahrain.No:C/l96. Political Agencj, Bahrain, the 14th July lit* To, • His Highness Abdul Aziz bin Faisal al Rahmas al Saud. Sultan of Nejd and its Dependencies. After Compliments. I have the honour to inform jfour Excellency that I have now received Government's orders on the subject of customs duty charged in Bahrain on transit goods which are sent from India and other foreign ports via Bahrain consigned to merchants on the mainland. Hitherto Shaikh Isa has been charging duty on the above kind of goods,namely,k^ the same rate as is charged on ordinary imports. On Your Excellency's representation which I duly submitted to Government,the matter has been fully considered by them amd it is deciaed that in accordance with International rules generally accepted only 2/o duty will be charged on transit goods consigned to the mainland provided that these are removed from the Bahrain customs house within 20 days.from date of landing. If goods are taken from steamers direct into lighters which proceed to the mainland without touching Bahrain, no duty will be charged by the Huler of Bahrain. This order applies to the whole coast of Hasa and Qatar but does not apply to goods going to Oman as these usually go via Dubai. Usual Ending. (Sd).H.R.P.Dickson, Political Agent,Bahrain.132/ To Telegram B. 'A7 From Foi'eign and Foliti cal department, uewUelhi To Political Kesident, ±iushire . Repeated H.M's. Secretary of state for india, London. H.M's. Minister, jeddah. Uo. 764. Dated ll.th a&amp;xxii(received 12th March 1932. Xour letter of 14th December 1931, jno . G.35. Bail rain dues on goods in transit. the Secretary of State for xndiaanfi H.M's. Minister at Jeddah copy of letter sent by the x-olitical Agent at Bahrain to ibn Saud which was acknowledged by the latter in his letter dated 88th July 1920 — copy of ibn Saud 's letter was received with your letter of the 23rd ,/o2&gt;September 1920, wo. 281-S. -3. The Government of xndia are inclined to think &amp; that trior's agrement with the British india Agents at Karachi which, so far as they are aware, he had no authority to make, infringes spirit of 1920 arrangement and ought to be cancelled whether ibn Saud protests or not. But in view of possible consequence of cancellation locally and of possible developments in the event of negotiations with Xbn Saud on Gulf questions supervening they would be glad to haveyour views before making recommendations to this effect to his Majesty's govern ment . 2 Please forward to the Government of mdia foreign J? tbfzE X J? R E S S L IS T; TER. J'rom-Resident, Bushire. To -Foreign, New Delhi. Repeated to-Secretary of atatefor India, London. H.M's. Minister, Jeddah. Ho. 158-3. of 1932. Dated Bushire, 15th March 1932. ' 4 Your telegreat Ho. 764, dated 11th March 1932. Bahrain dues on goods in transit. 2» As desired I forward herewith a copy of the letter sent by the Political Agent at Bahrain to Ibn Saud dated 14th July 1920. It will be seen that he was given a definite undertaking that no duty would he levied on goods transhipped in^to lighters and taken stiaoK direct to the mainland. 3» Captain Prior had no authority to make the arrangements reported in ray letter Ho. G-35 of the 14th December 1931: he presumably assumed that it was a matter of internal administration, and did not realise its wider aspect, and only reported the matter after the arrangement had been concluded. 4. As regards cancelling the arrangement whether Ibn Saud protests or not, I would suggest that this is a matter in which it would be best to be guided by the opinion of Sir Andrew Ryan, after he has received the copy of the Political Agent's letter to Ibn Saud. As regards the local consequences of cancella tion, I understand that very little advantage has ; been taken of this concession till recently, though it has beer in force for eleven years, some months ago one or two largi sh-2- largish consignments arrived for overside delivery, and the state feared lest their customs revenue might be adversely affected. If direct transhipment was adopted as a regular practice and on a large scale it would undoubtedly affect the revenues of the state appreciably, and this at a time of special financial difficulty when the state is faced with a large deficit. Moreover it would, as pointed out in my letter Ho, G-35 of the 14th December, hit the Indian mercantile community, who are also passing through difficult times. 60 As far as I am aware no particular negotiations are impenaing with Ibn Saud regarding Gulf questions, and from this point of view I see no objection to can cellation. ^other hand Ibn Saud has not yet protested,, and the matter was not mentioned at Hasa, though I had long discussions with His Majesty's Secretary on many questions connected with Bahrain. 8. To sum up: (i) Cancellation would adversely affect the revenues of Bahrain at a time of peculiar difficulty if it resulted in a large increase in direct transhipment. /iH\ J!* Y!0111 d llit tlie Indian mercantile communityhard. ($ii) lu wouldj I think! give rise to a good deal of resentment. These transit dues which were forced on Bahrain have always been a sore point, (iv) Ibn Baud has not yet protested, anl actually the British India steam Navigation Company or any other shipping company are perfectly entitled to refuse to accept goods fbr over side delivery; and the B. I, have by no josh moans/-3- 1) means got a monopoly of Bahrain trade. The Hsn sa Line in particular bring large consignments of goods to Bahrain, (v) On the other hand if His Majesty's Minister at Jeddah considers that it infringes the spirit of the agreement, and that on -wider grounds it should he cancelled. I think his views should he accepted# (SGD) H% V. BISCOB, Lieut.-Col., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. ir~ 'Ai ( /] Ax Attested: for Hh &amp; kjc Secretary 1 0 the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.; 664 /316/86 P. Z '1 .34 /■•» »■ I»ff OFFICE - :: S.¥.l. 9 ? 2 SSipd February, 1932, Sir, -K* # iitii reference to your letter Mo, i' j ,2, ii?0/S^ of the IStfa JfaBuary, J itm directed by uecrettery 31r John ^iaon, to tr&amp;.nefflit to you the necompteByinjg copy of &amp; despatch from His M(4«»ty f b Minister at Jedda in regfcrd to the levy by the Bahrein State of Ctistoas dues on goods intended for the territories of King Ibh Btrnd, S. It will be observed that in paragraph 2 of hie deaottch Wo. 14 of .Tenuery 19th to the Government of India, sir a * Ryan states that he la unaware of the nature of the agreement on this subject which ap ears to have been reached with King Ibn •iaud in , %9W» Ho details of this agreement, other than those contained in the correspondence ending with your letter Ko. P. 7931 of the 5th Hoveiaber 1930, appear to be avuilafcle in this ©apartment. I am accordingly to request that further information om to the nature of the etgreeaent may, if possible, be furnished to this -department. Sir John Alison would also be glad to learn whether secretary air Uamuel Koare considers that the arrangement now made by the political Agent at Bahrein for the refusal of facilities for the overside delivery of goods at Bahrein could reasonably be head to infringe any rights accorded to King Ibn Baud under any such agreement. 3, kcopy of this letter is being sent to -the Colonial Office. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, ter ieeretary of t^te La (-ffice.uk E X T H A E T. / (Received under i.O. p.l. jno. j ^.Z. 1909/32, dated 1st Ap ri I 1938. E. 1353/782/91. J*)HKlGjN UJjmGK, 'o. W * 1. 24th March 1932. Sir, * * * * 4. Sir John Simon presumes that, before final instructions are sent to Lieutenant-Colonel Biscoe in the matter, the Secretary of State for mdia •will consider whether the porposed increase in the Uafrain customs duties could be considered to be an infraction of the 1920 Agreement with King ibn Saud regarding .Bahrain duties on goods destined for Uejd, which formed the subject of India Office letter .wo. 1589/32 of the 12th March. * * * * I am. Sir, iCour obedient servant. J. /&lt;# t * *• * * SD/ G. W» Kendel.^0 .1079/123/8. ul till \/wr 1 HIS Majesty's Charg^ d'Affaires at Jedda presents his compliments to 'tlie Poli'tical Resident in 'the Persian Gulfj and has the honour to transmit British...he.gabi.QXl.f .wm* documents. \ tz v : HIOuRDS .AP.J?i.X...9.tfeji..., 193.8.. {M y Reference to previous Bushire express letter No.l58-S of 15/3/32 to Govt, of India. Description of E Name and Date. Subject. ?o Foreign Office, )espatch No. 168 of 9/4/32. Bahrain transit dues. opy to New Delhi under P.L.No. 65 of 9/4/32. 3479 5898 (2)u m»%m* mm Slr f / f to !fo»l&amp;S-6 of %he ■ IM IMNil the s-olitloml MMMI ti Ml MiMl Mf to th« 'mmtm3eoreta3?y to the Oovernzient of reu^rding 3«hrain transit du#», I haw the honour to eutHalt ti»o following appreciation of the pocitloat 2# IE January 1920 Baa domaMod orallyt through the Politieal Agent at Uahroln, ttxat ^C^fttoaw Kegulations «s uMerstood In civilli&amp;ed countrtee he enforoed In B«hrain M « 0, After consideration of the matter hy the oo^ermeat of India* colonel Dickson replied in July in writing, that »in eocordsnce with Xntcrnaticmsl rule® generelly accepted only B % duty would he charged on transit good® • « • • • Xf goods were taken from ateamere direct into lighter® whiob proeeeded to the jselnland without toucMag Bahrain, no duty would he Merged 11 , 4, There was thue magreeamt, hut a conoeseiou, to Ihn in the nane of internatioual uisage# 5. The Bahrain state, however, hm recently agreed to grant an extension of free demurrage 3,d@^0 to 10 on goods carried in Britioh India ships, in consideration the British India Company*© refueisg to accept cargo for overside delivery at Bahrain into dhone plying to the mainland# % thio official agrewent, aadc with one of the two chief ©hipping companies to the mutual advantage of the cosspaoy and of aahrainl merchants, the Bahrain State ha® In effect prejudiced the 1980 conceasion Hie Majesty's i^incipel Secrete^ of a tat# for Foreiga Affairs*si cheque, the duty on the shortage will b© collected at the last customs office from which the traneportiag ship sailed^ If the transit goods ape found to he different from those shorn to the customs declaration, they will be treated as contraband# .ikr.'^iliiCl.e. C-arts, aniisals and. other iseans of transport used for carrying goods and passengers across the frontiers are exempted froa customs dues on condition that they are returned within six months#r Qonfidential* No:0 / . T ^Pi^gy;.J ■ Political Agency, Vfii &gt;e 'i ^ i Bahrain, the 14th May 1932. TTsIt' (Ai&gt;\s i i'rom:- The Political Agent, Bahrain. To:- The Hon r ole the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bush ire. Sir, I have the honour to refer to G-overnment of India telegram No:764 dated the 11th March 1932 and to say that since my action has been 'brought to the notice of the Secretary of State and H.B.ll^s Minister at Jeddah,! may ; perhaps,'be allowed to offer some explanation,the more so since I believe I can show that the suggestion that I concluded a formal agreement with the British India Steam Navigation Company is misleading. 2. I„\was in Isfahan when the question of overside deliveries was first raised by the G-overnment of Bahrain,who proposed to levy the full 2^ rate of Re Export duty on the cargo transhipped at sea by the S.S 'Bahkura' due at Bahrain towards the end of September. I discussed the matter with the officiating Political Resident and the Bahrain Government were informed from Bushire that the orders of Government precluded this,but they took up the matter EEgsr energetically with the Agents of the Company and telegraphed to me again on my arrival at Karachi. The Hindu shippers at Bahrain and Karachi also made representations to myself,the Hon'ble the Political Resident and the Director General of Commerical Intelligence and Statistics,Calcutta. 3. The shipping for overside delivery had taken place from t Karachi,and as a result of the energetic proests of the Mesopotamia Persia Corporation at Bahrain,Messrs Mackinnon, Mackenzie &amp; Company had stopped the practice,having only given overside delivery from two steamers. I saw their Karachi2. Manager and found that he had already decided to accept no further cargo of this nature for the time 'being. I did not make this point clear in my letter No:0/ll8 dated the 28th November 1931. He stated,however,he had been told 'by the shipper that the A additional dues at Bahrain made it profitable to ship by country craft direct,and so short circuit Bahrain and all its dues,and that they could not afford to lose cargo to sailing craft. 4. He referred,ofcourse,to the extra khanchiyah or demurrage charge levied last year,•which added some to the Bahrain dues, as and whose application I had objected to at the time/being likely 5 to divert trade. I offered to ask the Bahrain Government to remove this khanchiyah,and so to revert to the former position of Re Export cargo. He said this would facilitate matters and the Bahrain Government agreed to it. 5. The Karachi Manager informed me,however,that he was unable to settle matters of policy without a reference to Bombay and that though he hh ± personally did not intend to accept any more such cargo he was referring to Bombay,and advised me to sr write to them too. As the question had not been definitely settled,it seemed advisable to write to Bombay and place the point of view of the Bahrain Government and the Hindu merchants (who had also made energetic protests) before them. I pointed out that the Bahrain Government had foregone the extra khanchiyah and reverted to the former position and also said that the State could not afford to lose the revenue and would certainly make it up by other means,if they lost it by overside delivery. 6. I do not think it can be said that this was an 'agreement' nor that I exceeded my duty in taking up a matter which vitally affected the Bahrain Government,the Hindu Merchants and the Mesopotamia Persia Oorporation. It is a purely commercial matter in whieh the British India Steam Naviation Company have pleased themselves,as they are entitled to do. Unless they are afraid that they are going to lose cargo to sailing craft,they will never agree to give overside delivery^ as this leads to endless difficulties and in the sole instance in which it hasS. ^ occurred during my tour of duty here,excluding last year, (when arms were shipped from India for the Nejd Government) sad the steamer was delayed for 24 hours. Even last year they §id not give overside delivery for consignmeats of less than lOOObags owing to these very difficulties. The Government of India will realize from this that the natter is not quite so simple as it appears. 7. I wish to say that I had no knowledge of the letter written by Colonel Dickson to His Majesty Kiiig Bin Saud stating that no duty would be charged on goods transhipped direct at sea. The war and lack of staff had reduced the igency office work to chaos and in 1922 all confidential files of earlier date were closed and new ones opened,and I regret to say that I have never found time to read these old ones. On receiving the reference from the Bushire Residency,however,I managed to trace the file and have now read it with useful results. I was aware;that the reduction of transit dues to had been forced on Shaikh Isa in the teeth of the strongest opposition ; but it now appears quite clear that our sole motive appears to have been to placate Bin Saud at the expense of this unfortunate State. At one place I find the Political Resident infoming the Shaikh that 'in accordance with international practice no charge should be levied on goods in transit' while Shaikh Isa pathetically replies 'he is certain that there are also things in his favour in international practice,if he only knew of them'. That he is not far wrong is disclosed by the example of Iraq where 1$&gt; is charged upon all goods at the present moment, 8. I have discovered one valuable fact from the Political-' - Agent T s letter No:G/228 to the Residency dated the 3rd August 1920. He states 'no cargo is ever at present transhipped from steamers at sea and taken direct to the mainland. There is no prospect of such a thing happening in the future as far as I can see,seeing that the Landing Company,also a British India Steam Navigation Company's concern,is interested in landing all&amp; 4. cargo at Bahrain. They would lose heavily if cargo were put direct into lighters for the mainland. Hence the British India Steam Navigation Company may be counted upon to distinctly discourage transfer of cargo. Shaikh Isa therefore stands to lose nothing 'by Government's order as far as it concerns steamers transferringjia^J'. It mil be seen that though bound by treaty to pfotect interests we actually were instrumental in fetteriag its liberty in advance. 9. It should be mentioned at this point that the Anglo Persian Oil Company's steamer,the S.S 'Khuzistan' now regularly discharges oil here for the mainland by direct transhipment,and in accord ance with Government's orders no charges are levied upon this. The Bahrain Government wished to protest against this,but I pointed out to them that the steamer had a very small draught and could easily stand into some place on the Hasa coast if they applied the Be Export duties,and that this would create an undesirably precedent. Also they do not bing a very large quantity of cargo and the loss to the State is not great. With the British India Steam Navigation Company,however,it is very iizfiszExiEs difierent and since it is to the interest of both the British India Steam Navigation Company,the Bahrain Government- and the Hindu merchants not to allow overside delivery, I most strongly urge that they should not be pressed to do so. If the Nejd Government considered they had a grievance they would long ago have raised the matter,and the fact of their not having done so clearly shows that they realize the British India Steam Navigation Company are within their rights in refusing overside delivery if it does not suit them. 10. I notice that His Majesty's Minister at Jeddah is to be called upon to say whether the spirit of the 1920 arrangement has been infringed or not. Surely this State^w^standsto lose heavily should have some say in the matter,and it is surely wrong that no mention of it should be mde to them? Do not the rovernment of India feel tnat the time has come to cease calling upon Bahrain to make sacrifices to benefit our relations with5. Bin Saud. This vicarious generosity has cost the G-overmnent of Bahrain over ten lakhs since the institution of the arrangement, or roughly 10fo of their income. What would the Government of India and the Indian public say if it was known that His Majesty's Government,while charged with the protection of their interests,had obliged them for political reasons to surrender lOfo of their revenues in favour of a foreign power? It will be recalled that the Kimberley Gotten 3xcise Duties were conceived in something of this spirit,and I believe that there is no Enactment that His Majesty's Government would sooner have to seen undone,or one which has done more/damage our presti/ge in India. 11. The reduction of the transit dues from 5;o to 2/a caused bitterness at the time,and though this has now died down,it will be instantly revived if the Bahrain State are to be called upon to make further sacrifices,particularly at such a time as the present. The Araba are quite intelligent enough to know exactly what motives inspire our action and they will realise that fre are helping the strong against the weak,and the less fr^ndly against the friend. I have heard it suggested that Bahrain is deeply indebted to us. Our contact with it has certainly contributed to its prosperity,but I cannot recall any action that has not been taken in our own interests as much as in those of Bahrain,nor any action that has caused us to be out of pocket. It will be remembered that when the two platoons of Indian infantry were sent here in 1926 the State were called upon to pay for their expenses to the last penny. Further,the State have granted unhesitatingly facilities for aviation for Twhich we have unsuccessfully offered very large sums elsewhere. The Bahrain Arabs are among the few peoples I know who are genuinely friendly towards us,and it would be a tragedy if we were to jeopardise their friendship to benefit a State whose friendship exists only in name. 12. It must not be lost sight of that the Hindu merchants are vitally affected since their mainland -brff trade will ben 6 ruined if overside delivery 'becomes a practice. They have mch 'better means of ventilating their grievances than the Bahrain G-overnment and will make full use of them,and this should be ± taken into account. 13. In conclusion,! trust that my contention that the matter is a purely commercial one may 'be accepted. If the British India Steam Navigation Company are forced 'by commercial reasons to grant overside delivery., the Bahrain G-overnment will have to 'bow to the inevitable and take such steps as they deem fit to restore the lost revenue. I beg,however,that the Government of India will not of their own motion bring pressure to bear upon the British India Steam Navigation Company to give such delivery. I have the honour to be Sir, Your Most Obedient Servant, Political Agent Bahrain.COMJlIEliTlAI.. H0.347-S of 1932. Britisii Be8id®ney Gonsulate-Gemral, Bushire, the 1st June 1932. The Hon'hle Lt.Colonel H.¥«Bisooe,I.A.» Jtjlitical Resident in the Persian Gulf, ) The Foreign Secretary to the GoYernment of India, S i^ m 1 a. Sir, I have the honour to invite a reference to despatch / »o»168 of the 9th April 1932 from His Majesty's Charge d*Affaires at Jedda, regarding Bahrain transit dues, and to forward for the information of the Government of India a copy of a letter received from the Political Agen t» Bali rain &gt; on the subject• 2. With the first portion of Captain JPrior's letter I am in general agreement, namely, that this is primarily a cojanercial matter, and that we cannot compel the British India Steam Mavigation Company to grant overside delivery if the, do not wish to do so. Their local Agents, the Mesopotamia Persia Corporation, are naturally strongly opposed to it since they are also landing contractors. The Hindu merchants in Bahrain are also opposed to it, and it is, I think, undoubtedly a trouble some arrangement for the shipping company. Their only fear seems to have 'been that they might lose cargo to dhows. It is primarily a matter for them to decide whether it is in their interests to give overside delivery or not. From « To-2- 3, ^fith the latter part of Captain trior's letter I am afraid that I am not altogether in agreement, and I think he has weakened his case by straining his argument. He contends that by compelling the Bahrain State in the interests of our relations with Ibn Saud to reduce the dues on goods in transit from 5&gt; to we have sacrificed the revenues of the State to suit our own interests. Hiatever our motives may have been it is the universal practice to charge less on goods in transit than on goods imported for consumption in the country. j »cjd, 'Iraq., India, and Great Britain all give concessions to transit cargo, and I see no reason why the Bahrain State should not do the same. Ibn Saud was on strong ground in asking that some concession should be made to him in this respect. 4. 'ihether it was necessary to make the further concession that goods transhipped direct should pay no duty at all is open to argument, but anyhow hitherto very little advantage has been taken of this privilege. Mr. Hope Grill considers that Ibn Saud could contend that we have circum vented this concession, but I am inclined to doubt whether it is a live issue at the present moment. Had it been, surely Ibn Saud would have raised the question when I saw him at Hasa, but it was never mentioned, neither has it been mentioned since, and Ibn Saud is not slow in bringing for ward any grievances that he may have. Hiile, if for political reasons it was considered desirable to cancel the arrangement entered into between the Bahrain Government and the British India Steam navigation Company, the latter would probably be ready to meet the wiehes of the Government of India, there is obviously no means of compelling them to do .. •.3- do so, and the ansner to Xbn Saud would be that the Stoao- ship Company in their own interests do not deiire to give overside delivery. In these circumstances J would suggest, subject to any views that sir Andrew Ryan may express, that it is unnecessary to raise the question at the present juncture. I am sending a copy of this despatch to His x Majesty's Secretary of State for India and to His Majesty's Minister at Jedda# I have the honour to he, Sir, ■ / Your most obedient servant. STEP , f Mr i &gt;oliti J. ty.Colonel, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. iilrf X'dkJL AS 3 I* • XQX-wtLl'&amp;BOi ums ifdxiuiu^tx Ag Bu ^ f J^aiu feci it« A. -71.19/212. Telegram E.27. From Government ot India, Simla. To Political Hesident, Bushire. No. 1320. Dated and received 2nd June 1932. Beference Jeddah despatch No, 168 dated 9th April to Foreign Office, Bahrain transit dues. Government of India would 'be glad of your views. FOBEIGN.Extract from Baiirain Diary No. 11, dated 16th. June 1932 (for the period 1st to ibth June 1932) * * * * * * * * * * * 227. A proclaiaafion has been issued 'by the Baiirain Government authorising the Director of Customs to collect Harbour dues of Rs. 10/- from all foreign craft entering the Port of Baiirain. These dues have been collected from launches in the past and are no?/ extended to all craft except bona fide pearling boats and tawwasha boats, vvho have been exempted from the payment of this tax, while boats bringing stones and juss are to pay Re. l/- only.19/212 Telegram From To E 30. H.M*s Minister, Jedaa.. Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, London. No. 91. Bepeated to Political Eesident, Bushire. Ho. 116. Dated 24tb received 25tli June 1932. Political Besident's despatch No. 347~S dated 1st June sent to India, copy to India Office. Acting Minister for Foreign Affairs protested strongly yesterday against alleged action of Bahrain authorities in insisting, some days ago, on landing rice cargo for Hejaz Government after it had 'been unloaded direct from steamer into dhow sent to receive it. Ihn Saud asks for urgent steps to repair action which he considers a violation of Dickson's letter of July 14th 1920. / By an1^12. Telegram B..30 Political Resident, BusMre. To Political Agent, Bahrein. No 561. Bated 25th June 1932. Following from Minister, Jedda 'beginsActing Minister for Foreign Affairs .... Dickson's letter of July 14th 1920'* Ends. Please report facts briefly 'by telegraja. DEMI-OgPIOIAL . Suggest you send me despatch 'by next mail on general question on lines discussed, and meanwhile Bahrein Government should refrain from steps calculated to give grounds for furtKer protest. Resident./ A (o ^ 19/212 Telegram E 30. Prom Political Agent, Bahrein. To Political Sesident, Bushire. No 102 Bated 25th received 26th June 1932. Your telegram No 361. Goods arrived with hill of lading marked for * Bahrain in transit Ojair* and since steamer Gom- -pamy gave no prior notification of transhipment, goods were dealt with as ordinary cargo. Bequest for remission of customs dues was made hy Qatif customs director on the grounds that con- -signment was for personal use of King. Since similar request for 40,000 hags was made two years ago and re- -fused State was unahle was-unahle to accept proposal. BEMI-OPPIGIAL . Arrangements are heing made as suggested hy you. Political.19/212 # Telegram S .SO Itom Political Eesident, Bushire. To H.M*s Minister, Jedda*,.. 366. Repeated to Secretary of State Colonies, London. 6 Copy 'by post to Government of India, Foreign &amp; Political Department, Simla. Dated 27th June 1932. ! Tour telegram Ho 116 to me of 24th June. 2. G-oods which consisted'of consignment of rice arrived with hill of lading marked 'Bahrain in trans- -it Ojair*, and since steamship company gave no prior notification of transhipment, goods were dealt with as ' ordinary cargo. 3. Later, Director of Customs, Qatif, made request for remission of customs dues on 17000 hags of rice on ground that consignment was for personal use of King. Similar request for 40,000 hags was made in 1930 and refused ( vide my telegram No.T.96 of 25th July). u|u*a.t Similar^was given on present occasion. State is per- -fectly ready and frequently does exempt goods which are for personal use of King or household, hut consign- -ments on this scale are obviously not. ^ Sheikh discussed matter with me last week at Bahrain and told me that question had again suddenly become acute. Bahrain Government are making representationsit representationsjon tilie suTDject wliicti I liop© to fopwapd. l)y air mail of 7titi July. Meanwliile I tiavG advisod State that pending settlement no obstacles should he placed in way of overside delivery and also informed local steamship agents that 1 saw no ohjection to their giving overside delivery if they wished to do so. Matter therefore Vs now entirely one for settlement between shippers and steamship company. Resident.19/212 \ Telegram H. 27 S'rom Secretary of State for India, London. To Political Resident, Bustiire. No. 1737 Dated 27th received 23th June 1932. Please telegraph your observations on Jeddah telegram of June 24th to Foreign Office, repeated to you as No.116, repeating that telegram and your reply to Government of India in case they have any observations. Secretary of State for India.I J 1 I ■19/212 To Telegraph From R 27. Political Resident, Bushire. Secretary of State for India, London No 370 Dated 23th June 1932 Tour telegram of 27ttL June, No. 1737. My observations contained in my tele- -gram No.6 of 27th June to Colonial Office are heing repeated to India with Jedda telegram refferad to. Resident.19/212 Telegram 11.30. To From Political Hesident, Bushire. Government of India, Foreign &amp; Political Department, Simla. # No. 371 Dated 23th June 1932. Li k Following is repetition of Jeddah telegram of 24th June. Begins;- ( Insert distri- -hntion and text of Jedda telegram No 116 of 24/6/32 ). of tfune 27th. Begins:- ( Inser- Ihution and text of Bushire telegram No 366 of 27^th June.) Ends. Foregoing telegraphed to you at request of India Office in case you have any observations. ends. Following is rep( '''' of my reply ResidentI I 1 1 ■v , 7/ No. 0/104 of i93 1 P olitical A gency, B ahrein, Dated the 26th June 19^ .. THE POLITICAL AGENT, l( T© The H on t ble the Political -te si den t i n the Persian G-ulf. , 3ushire. Sir, I have the honour to forward a letter received from His Sxcellency Shaildi Hamad to your address regarding transhipment dues in Bahrain harbour. You will notice that he states his intention of denouncing that part of Shaikh Isa ? s letter v/hich allowed Bti-ig transhipment within Bahrain territorial waters. The letter on which His Majesty Bin Saud relies is Major Dickson T s letter No:196-G dated the 14th June 1920. 2. It will 'be useful in the first place if i summarise the correspondence that led up to the institution of the 2$ HS duty. Throughout this despatch I will refer to the 2,0 duty as the He Export or EE duty,and to the cargo directly taken from steamer to 'boat or from boat to 'boat as tranship ment cargo. Arabs do not use the term HS but usually speak of tranship cargo £§3? tnat which pays 2^,presumably because the transhipment has hardly ever occurred. 3. Till 1S13 Shaikh Isa used to charge 5% on all cargo but he then reduced it to 2^ on all cargo destined for the mainland but discharged at Bahrain. In 1916,on the excuse that the war had greatly reduced his customs he increased this to 5)^, this enhanced rate finally leading to a protest from Bin Saud demanding a return to the old 2-^ rate or rauxier the remission of all dues except arthiyah or ground tax. His protest and a summary of the matter as it then stood was sent to the Hon'ble the Political Hegident by the2. W 'V • t Political Agent in Ms letter No;58-G dated the 28th February 1S20. l 1 he Political Agent expressed the opinion that strictly speaking Bahrain should not charge anything on transit cargo as it was contrary to international . practice. To this the Political Resident replied on the ^Oth.March in his telegram No:553 that there was no recognised scale of duty on transit or transhipment cargo, and that most countries charged some duty 'based on the principle of not kiiling the goose that laid the golden eggs. This point is of interest ani I will return to it later. 4. In his Memorandum No:72-G dated the 10th March 1920 L the Political Agent reported to the Residency that an intervieviT Shaikh Isa had said that on no account would he reduce his duty from 5^ to in order to please Bin Saud. lie apparently felt that his honour was involved,and said that when he had to reduce his duty for transit cargo in 1913 from 5^ to 2$ he had done so of his own free will in order to attract trade. When he had achieved his object he. again raised it to and he said that he would not reduce it again unless forced to do so 'by the Resident. The Political Agent recommended that he should be pressed to reduce his rate to 2-1$ but made no mention of free transhipment at sea. £ ^ ' 5. In his letter No:112-C dated the 27th April to the ■ f ^7 political Resident the Political Agent first mentions free transhipment at sea. The matter is now complicated by ^£ suggestions from the Oivil Commissioner at Baghdad that Bahrain should be allowed to increase its customs to the Persian scale and so recoup itself for concessions to Bin Saud,but the Resident opposed the suggestion of giving Bahrain more revenue on the grounds that the administration was so rotten that there was no guarantee that any of it would be spent on harbour improvements. The Oivil 5% ( ^ 0Iimi i ss i 0rier ^ Baghdad in his telegram No:5256 dated the-lb- 3. 24tii May 1920 si^ested that the rate of HE duty should 'be 2 or 2t/o and that nothing should he charged on direct tran shipment. This is the first mention that I can trace of a 2$duty. 6. The matter now moved rapidly. The Government of India apparently agreed to a 2^ EE Export duty and to free tran shipment at sea,and Shaikh Isa was instructed accordingly, Bin Saud and the Ruler of Qatar 'being simultaneously informed of the new concession. The reason given to Shaikh Isa by the Resident was that his former practice was T not in accordance with existing international law T . In his covering letter,the Political Agent informed Shaikh Isa inter alia *• j that T 'In other words,Your Excellency may possibly shortly be invited to raise the Bahrain Customs tariff to the extent of that fixed by the Persian Government. Should this take place lour Excellency may expect to receive a greatly increased revenue from your customs. Such an increase will no doubt be half as much again or possibly double your existing revenues', p v. Shaikh Isa received the news badly and immediately asked to be allowed to return to the old rate he had previously refused to concede. Shaikh Isa apparently also asked that the free transhipment at sea should not be forced on him. The Political igent discussed these points in his % forwarding letter No:228 of the 3rd August 1920. The Resident informed Shaikh Isa that the orders of Government must be obeyed,and sent three letters to him with his letter No:253-S of 28th August 1920 to the Political Agent. The , ^ ^ first told him that he must carry out the orders of Govern ment without demur,and the third warned him against mischief maters. The second is of the greatest importance for I nov/ find in its penultimate paragraph that he informs Sha&amp;k Isa that the free transhipment at sea is only intended to apply f o to goods that come by steamer. If Shaikh Isa had not been in his dotage he WDuld have produced this letter long ago and the difficulty of country craft discharging cargo directi 4. into other country craft and escaping customs dues would never have arisen. Since it is manifestly unfair that the State should 'be ignorant of an important letter like this owing to Shaikh Isa's incapacity,! propose to give a copy of it to the Adviser unless you instruqt me by telegram to refrain from doing so, I 8. Shaikh Isa yielded 'before the unrelenting pressure of the Resident and finally accepted the terms,though with an ill grace. Shortly afterwards another question arose. Hitherto,by private arrangement,he had allowed baled goods to pass for ^in Saud's territory unopened at a charge of Rs.15/- per bale. This was to obviate the difficulty of rebaling goods that had been packed under pressure,and since it was calculated that ah average bale was worth not less than Rs.1,000/- the arrangement was to Sin Saud T s benefit. Shaikh Isa now ordered,however,that such goods should be opened to assess their value and collected. The Resident declined to intervene,but the matter was finally settled locally by Rs.20/- being accepted instead of Rs.15/- and the bales were allowed to pass as before. 9. I now come to His Excellency Shaikh Hamad's letter. It may be broadly summed up as saying that though all avail- able economies have been made the State is in sore need of money,and since he can no longer afford to give free tran shipment, which,moreover he considers an infringement of his sovemgn rights,he intends to cancel the clause of Shaikh Isa's letter which allo¥/ed it. 10. This action has been precipitated by two things. During this spring,retum freights by country craft (mostly from Kuwait) from Karachi to Bahrain fell to unprecedently low rates. The British India Steam Navigation Company were unable to reduce their rates to meet this and consequently a number of booms,some containing as much as a thousand sacks of rice came to Bahrain and transhipped their cargo to smaller craft from Jubail and Ojair without paying a penny to the Bahrain5. Government. The second point is that news has been received that a Karachi shipper offered the British India Steam Navigation Company 35,000 'bags of rice on the sole condition that they will alloi/ him overside delivery,i.e enable him to secure free transhipment. The conjunction of these two factors has much alarmed the Bahrain Government j and the merchants since they see their entrepot trade 'being conducted under their noses and in their port without the Government 'being able to obtain revenue from it or the merchants their trade. I should mention,that for a variety of reasons it is,practically speaking,only possible for Nejd and Hasa merchants to profit by this direct traffic, and the Bahrain merchants though liable to the competition of others in the home market find themselves shut out of . the trade of the mainland. 11. Since Shaikh Isa T s letter prescribed no time limit and since it was not a formal treaty but a private arrange ment and since he received no compensating advantage,it is clearly open to the sen to rescind a concession granted by the father. Bahrain,as we have frequently stated,is an Independent Irab State and has a perfect right to levy such dues and make such arraiigements in its territorial waters as may seem good to it. As I have mentioned above,the Resident himself stated that the usual practice of States was to take what could be taken without killing the goose that lays the golden eggs 12. When the concession was originally forced upon Shaikh Isa,much play Y/as made of the argument that other ports such as Bombay charged nothiing for transhipment. What is done elsewhere is of little value^in a place like the Persian Gulf,which is a law unto itself,but apart from this the argument is fallacious for the transhipment referred to in these ports is that of cargo on a through manifest for onward transmission by another steamer port. Bahrain is A strictly speaking the destination of transhipment cargo here,for the mainland ports cannot 'by any stretch of imagination be called steamer ports mr do the merchants who ship the cargo live there. 13. The Port of London and other great ports grant cheap transit facilities 'because it suits their policy to do so, and if they did^not rival ports should soon 'take their entrep3t trade from them, -'-'he situation here is entirely different. The Hasa and Nejd merchants who import on a A large scale do not live in their own countryjlDut prefer to conduct their business from the peace and security of Bahrain. They take full advantage of the facilities of the port,send their children free to Bahrain schools,use Bahrain hospitals and enjoy the protection of the Bahrain State forces. . Since the Customs dues provide almost the sole source of revenue in the State it is only reasonable to expect that they should be expected to contribute something to them. It should be remembered that no port dues exist here except on launches and unless Customs dues are paid the transhipment traffic does not pay a penny. 14. As the Shaikh says in his letter conditions have changed since Shaikh Isa signed his letter. Transhipment from steamers was unknown,and he could not have foreseen A 3 (though we should have foreseen for him) that as much as 35,000 bags of rice at a time might desire to make use of this loophole. It is clear that transhipment from country craft to country craft did exist (Political Agent's letter No:228-C dated the 3rd August 1920 to the Political Resident) but on the other hand it is equally clear that Shaikh Isa used to collect5, j on all goods transhipped. a c 15. In view of the Resident's assurance to Shaikh Isa that the free transhipment only applied to goods transhipped from steamers to country craft I presume that I may inform the Shaikh immediately that he is at liberty to charge the full S/o on cargo transhipped from one country craft to another without any farther delay,and this will only leave11 V. the question of steamer transhipment. 16. It must 'be quite clear that once transhipment from steamers is alloY/ed on the scale contemplated,it is only a question of months before the entire entrepot trade is con ducted in this way,the local and Hindu merchants 'being deprived of their share,although their Nejdi and Hasawi competitors in Bahrain will be able to compete in the Bahrain market as heretofore. Exactly why the advantage to be gained by free-transhipment from steamers was not realised and utilized earlier,! cannot say,but I believe that the answer lay in the reluctance of the British India Steam Navigation Company to allow it. They will always prefer to have their cargo landed by their agents in Bahrain,and but for the recent competition of country craft would never agree to any other proceaure. Nowthat in the terms of Oolonel Trevor T s letter,country craft is not allowed free tranship ment, they will not have this competition to fear to the same extent and will be less ready to grant it. 17. Bin Saud appears to be mder the impression that he has a grievance as regards Bahrain,whereas the local opinion is that we have fostered his interests and those of his merchants rather than those of Bahrain, '..'hen,after the war,permits for the export of rice were hard to obtain,we made the Qusaibis T fortune by granting them permits where others had to go Y /ithout,and then the RE Export concession was first introduced it was restricted to Nejd and Hasa merchants, thereby giving them a 3, j advantage over the Bahrain merchant desiring to trade with the mainland. 18. Under what obligations are we to Bin Saud that his interests must prevail every time? It seems to me that when it suits him he is allowed to quote T international practice* and that when it does not suit him he is allowed to plead 'the requirement of his country'. He is allowed to blockade Kuwait in time of peace and expel Hindu merchants like criminals from his shores because they ventured to compete //8. with Ms merchants,and this time no word is heard of inter national practice. If the Government of India decided to expel Japanese merchants from Bombay because they were found to be doing good business,the Japanese Government would probably consider it an act of war. 19. Again,I have just discovered that while his subjects in Bahrain are all treated on perfect equality with Bahrainis and pay identically the same taxes,he on the other hand levies a higher rate of tax from Bahrain subjects on their date gardens there than that paid by his subjects,the difference being some 18/o. It be clearly seen that his policy is based entirely on self interest and expediency and that any mention of international practice is a blind. 20. it should be clearly realised that free transhipment on a large scale will still further retard the raising of the rCuwait blockade. The port that is being used as a substitute for Kuwait is Jubail,and if Bin Saud is able to take his supplies there without any payment of dues at all at Bahrain,he will obviously prefer to use that port and will maintain the full rigour of his blockade against Kuwait. Jubail itself is impracticable for steamers,and he can only therefore approach it free of charge by means of such a concession at Bahrain. 21. Jhe Bahrain G -ovemment have made drastic economies but there is obviously a limit to this,for unlike their nei^ghfeours they have a more or less civilised Government to maintain. They have made immense improvements in the last few years,so much so that they are attracting immigrants from all over the Gulf. Their administration cannot,however, iae maintained for nothing,and if thwarted in this matter of transhipment dues they will probably recompense themselves by levying drastic port dues,which they would be perfectly entitled to do. I need hardly say that this v/ould be most unv/elcome go the British India Steam Navigation Oompany and if,as might easily happen,the Persians were to hear t4.it9. and imitate them the result would 'be most unfortunate.for them. The Bahrain Government have sunk a great deal of money in the port and appointed a British Customs Director and Port Officer and 'they are entitled to an adequate return for their outlay^apart from any consideration of revenue. 22. The Bahrain Government must,however,'be careful to avoid killing the goose ; which would not he so very difficulty for with adequate buoying and piers Has Tanurah could he turned into a port that would take a great deal of trade away from Bahrain. Whether they could persuade steamers to go there or not is another matter,hut I 'believe that it could he done. I do not consider that they are likely to do this as long as the EE Sport duty is maintained as low as 2 ( j and I do not think that the withdrawal of the transhipment concession will he sufficient to incite them to develop^ Ras Tanurah. At the present moment,there is little doubt that they could not afford it. ! 23. I am advising Shaikh Hamad that he should await a reply S from you before denouncing Shaikh Isa's letter since it was based on the orders of the G-overnmait of India. I consider: ; (а). Since the arrangement is based on a letter and nipt on a treaty or formal undertaking he can abrogate it at will,the more particularly since he received no quid pro quo and conditions nave changed. (б)- Bahrain is an independent State and entitled to do what it pleases in territorial waters. The tran shipment traffic must be controlled even if only to prevent smuggling. Since there are often 50 or more ships in harbour this cannot be done without expense. (c). International practice means nothing in these primitive countries,and is only used oy Bin Saud as ammunition against us and not as a guide to be followed. Bahrain is sui generis for no^where else that I am aware of do leading merchants of one country live in and transact their country 1 s trade from--another 24. I request therefore,that His Majesty King Bin Saud maybe informed that the Bahrain G-ovemment regret that they are obliged to discontinue the free transhipment concession since it will dislocate the trade of their country. It might be mentioned to him that the old rate of RS duty was 2'4o but that we secured its reduction to 2;o for him.10 25. Pinally I request that I may be allov/ed to inform the Bahrain Government that they may put a stop to free transhipment from country craft to country craft forthwith and that they may levy Zjo duty upon it. Strictly speaking they are still entitled to charge on it. This is covered 'by Colonel Trevor's letter and does not form part of Major Dickson T s letter to His Majesty Bin Saud which only prescribed free transhipment for goods transhipped from steamer to country craft. It would 'be inequitable to withhold this information from them since it is only due to the fact that Y/e dealing with a Shaikh in his dotage that the knowledge was not made use of 'before. I have the honour to be Sir, Your Most Obedient Servant, Political Agent Bahrain.From Hamad bin Isa Al-Khal: To The Hon t ble Lt. Col. 2 After compliments. It is not hidden from Ezoellency that the finanei of Bahrain, during the last has been very weak, and You have frequently advised us our expenditure and to look channels of increasing the : A few years ago, our revenui almost 12^- lacs. Last yea] under 8 lacs. Yet the neec country and the Government ] diminished. Although last reduced the Civil List by 1C stopped paying very large pg which we received ourself be n lso effected many economies expenditure was greater than This year, 1351, again we ha greater economies, we have i pay of all our Government sd 10^, We released our Poliibe and we have effected economi heading in our headings of e but the position is still cr Political Reside42?' From Hamad bin Isa Al-Khalifah. s t SJ? %l &lt;■ t To The Hon'ble Lt. Gol. Sir H. V. Biscoe, K.B.E., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. cS^' (J * After compliments. It is not hidden from Your Excellency that the financial condition of Bahrain, during the last two years has been very weak, and Your Excellency have frequently advised us to reduce our expenditure and to look for new channels of increasing the revenue. A few years ago, our revenues were almost IS-^- lacs. Last year it was under 8 lacs. Yet the needs of the country and the Government have not diminished. Although last year we reduced the Civil List by 1C$ and we stopped paying very large payments which we received ourself before and ®lso effected many economies, still our expenditure was greater than our revenue. This year, 1351, again we have made greater economies, we have reduced the pay of all our Government servants by 10$, We released our Polite Officer and we have effected economies in every heading in our headings of expenditure; but the position is still critical.-s- Your Excellency obtaine mission from the High Gove increase the Customs tax u imports from 5^ to 7-|$, al tax was decided upon by tr ago between us and the Hig for this we are very thank tunately owing to the con which is affecting our peo; of luxuries has much dimin: GoTernment will obtain but from this extra tax. In times of need we see] advice from the High Gover; nobody but Allah and the &amp; help us, and so now in thii financial danger we reques the High Government in a m is of great importance to i effects our prosperity and and we earnestly hope that obtain this assistance. About 12 years ago, the requested Shaikh Isa that assist His Majesty King Ibi friend and brother, who wa of the High Government, thi-2- 1 &lt; 9 ' 7^ Q ^ ' Z. - V- Jl L^llj^jj C ^y ^Ma^ ^UL ^ ^ ^ U- Lo ^ , requested Shaikh Isa that in order to ' • ' rf,A- '^ ^ —, t^----- fl, I^» assist His Majesty King Ibn Saoud, our friend and brother, who was also the friend ~- ^ I ' of the High Government, that there should ' Your Excellency obtained for us per mission from the High Government to increase the Customs tax upon certain luxury imports from 5^ to 7-|^, although the Customs tax was decided upon by treaty many years ago between us and the High Government, and for this we are very thankful. But unfor tunately owing to the condition of finance which is affecting our people, the import of luxuries has much diminished, and the Government will obtain but little profit from this extra tax. In times of need we seek help and advice from the High Government, as nobody but Allah and the Government can help us, and so now in this time of financial danger we request the help of the High Government in a matter which is of great importance to us and which effects our prosperity and our trade and we earnestly hope that we shall obtain this assistance. About 12 years ago, the High Governmentshould be a reduction in on goods imported through his country, on which form duty was paid, i.e., 5^. V agreed to this request of Government and he reduced to 2^. From this action a very great loss to the r( Bahrain, as Your Excellency but of this we do not speal remind Your Excellency thai King Ibn Saoud asked only f tion of Zjtfoand he obtainec tion of 3/C, that is, more t for. Shaikh Isa made anot sion to His Majesty King lb please the High Government, permitted the exporting of piece goods from Bahrain wi opened, contrary to Customs ill this help which ke rend' to the request of the High I we received nothing in retu: we said nothing. At the arrangement was made in wrii Shaikh Isa and the Hon^le i that if the goods should be from boat to boat on the see not take Customs duty,, and i that we wish to discuss withshould be a reduction in the Customs on goods imported through Bahrain for his country, on which formerly full duty was paid, i.e., 5^. Shaikh Isa agreed to this request of the High Government and he reduced the amount to 2^. From this action there was a very great loss to the revenue of Bahrain, as Your Excellency is aware, but of this we do not speak. We remind Your Excellency that His Majesty King Ibn Saoud asked only for a reduc tion of 2-0,and he obtained a reduc tion of 3$?, that is, more than he asked for. Shaikh Isa made another conces sion to His Majesty King Ibn Saoud, to please the High Government, for, he permitted the exporting of bales and piece goods from Bahrain without being opened, contrary to Customs rules and for ill this help which fae rendered acceding to the request of the High Government, we received nothing in return, and yet we said nothing. At the same time an arrangement was made in writing between Shaikh Isa and the Hon'ble the Resident, that if the goods should be transhipped from boat to boat on the sea, he would not take Customs duty,, and it is this matter that we wish to discuss with Your Excellency now. \-4- We would point out to 1 that this written arrangen prescribe any time limit.f ment. Conditions have very greatly since that ti what is fitting at that ti today. Neither did we be arrangement made 12 years that time intended to perm the Government of Bahrain At the time that the above written it was not the cus fer cargo from one boat to the water within the boundi Bahrain, and when Shaikh Ij he did not think that such would happen, because all for the ports of His Majes - used to enter Bahrain firs- it was sent to the ports oj and it was only because of Shaikh Isa agreed to the r( High Government. And now we intend to all mentioned in Shaikh Isa^ 1 Hon T ble the Political Resid refers to the direct transl boat to boat within the bou our country, because we nov-4- JCs&gt;- (J1 We would point out to Your Excellency that this written arrangement did not prescribe any time limit.for the arrange ment. Conditions have changed in Bahrain b very greatly since that time and now, and what is fitting at that time is not fitting today. Neither did we believe that the arrangement made 12 years ago was at that time intended to permanently bind 1 the Government of Bahrain for ever after. At the time that the above letter was written it was not the custom to trans fer cargo from one boat to another in the water within the boundaries of Bahrain, and when Shaikh Isa was asked he did not think that such a thing would happen, because all cargo imported for the ports of His Majesty Ibn Saoud used to enter Bahrain first, and then it was sent to the ports of the King 'and it was only because of this that Shaikh Isa agreed to the request of the High Government. And now we intend to alter the clause mentioned in Shaikh Isa^ letter to the Hon^le the Political Resident which refers to the direct transhipment from boat to boat within the boundaries of our country, because we now see that it » • * 0* * } J u{ &lt;S^X&gt; /&lt; ci*&gt;^ a-VJoi&lt;54^ ^-5- it is harmful to us and to c During the last three mon thing has ocurred against ou Sailing boats of large size ^d Iraq, have entered our ha loaded with cargo and have d goods into other boats in th our boundaries and the boats the goods to foreign ports. trade has been carried on wi whatever of Customs or anyth we consider that this is not they use our port for unload: they must pay Customs duty i, be treated as is treated R.E, the cargo should land on the and then be reshipped as usuj last three months we have los Rs 16,000/- of Customs duty tl action of these boats^and no i is intended to do this by stei grea' This practice is also dan^ because it makes it possible entry of goods into Bahrain for we have no knowledge or over these goods, and we do r. where these goods go to, and are and what they contain. islands in our country and in there are harbours, and cargo at any of these places, and i^ ] 3yVjj Ui brL^ ^ U-J \^JcjJ&gt;JsJ&gt;^J],y^\ ■*Jc&gt;- J! ' ' l ' it is harmful to us and to our country. ' ^ During the last three months a new S m ~ y * thing has ocurred against our trade. CsC*^ £&gt;* Sailing boats of large size from India %d Iraq haye entered our harbours loaded with cargo and have discharged their | ' ♦ goods into other boats in the sea within *^ our boundaries and the boats have carried the goods to foreign ports. Yet this » . ' ' ^ trade has been carried on with no payment whatever of Customs or anything else, and J £^^3 j we consider that this is not right. If \ , ' they use our port for unloading the cargo they must pay Customs duty i.e., 2$ and sf &lt;?[ a Jo. U* .it . 'i » a a be treated as is treated R.E. cargo, i.e., the cargo should land on the Bahrain pier % 1^1 'i a and then be reshipped as usual. In the 11 last three months we have lost about »j| .• - '* Rs 16,000/- of Customs duty through the • cjJ action of these boats.,and now that « is intended to do this by steamer the loss willb^L?^^^ ' tT ■ 11113 praaioe is also dan8erous ^ , because it makes it possible for the ^ ^ J entry of goods into Bahrain by smuggling for we have no knov/ledge or authority over these goods, and we do not know * ^ | where these goods go to, and what they are and what they contain. We have six . It-' islands in our country and in every island there are harbours, and cargo can be landed at any of these places, and it is generally .j) r-6-'- *-6- generally known that much c Bahrain by smuggling method, it is our right to control exports within our boundarii subjects are amazed that we to do this. In countries i this practice is forbidden, are also being injured becai merchants who live in our cc importing goods for the com Majesty Ibn Saoud through Ba paying Customs duty in Bahrs own merchants have to pay Ci they cannot compete with the merchants in the trade in tt His Majesty Ibn Saoud, nor c them as our hands are paralj writing which made the arrar. subject. In the interests of our c revenue and trade we have de this arrangement, that is, d ment from boat to boat withi We do not ask to take Gustoni boundaries, but we have deci 2^ on goods directly transhi to boat within our boundarie May you be preserved and-6- || generally known that much cargo enters Bahrain by smuggling methods. Also it is our right to control imports and exports within our boundaries and our subjects are amazed that we are not able to do this. In countries such as Iraci this practice is forbidden# Our merchants are also being injured because the merchants who live in our country are importing goods for the country of His Majesty Ibn Saoud through Bahrain without paying Customs duty in Bahrain, but our own merchants have to pay Customs and so they cannot compete witn the foreign merchants in the trade in the country of His Majesty Ibn Saoud, nor can we help them as our hands are paralysed by the writing which made the arrangement on the subject. In the interests of our country and 'revenue and trade we have decided to cancel this arrangement, that is, direct tranship ment from boat to boat within our fronuiers. We do not ask to take Customs outside our boundaries, but we have decided to xake 2^ on goods directly transhipped from boat to boat within our boundaries. May you be preserved and Salaams. s K . - ^ 1 la. ■ • • foreign \ /\ \ a M i » l crjr^J, z &gt; t «' n »JU *• i i . / r.. . . - . » m * » 'l ~ ♦ \m0S m m » \ cHi' ca J i t; . \ v. a.. i uAIR MAIL . Conf idential. Mo.436-3 of 1932. British Residency &amp; Consulate- General, Busblre, the 29th June 1932. Sir, In continuation of nay telegram lo,6 addressed to His majesty's Secretary of State for the Colonies (Ho, 366 to His Majesty's Minister, Jedda) of the 27th June 1932, regarding transhipment cargo at Bahrain, I hare the honour to forward herewith for the information of His I. -*'■ \ Majesty's Government copy of a despatch received from the \v Political Agent, Bahrain, and of a letter addressed to me by Shaikh Hamad bin Isa, Deputy Ruler of Bahrain* 2. I had hoped that the question of this tranship ment cargo, in respect of which a concession was made to Ibn Saud many years ago of which very little advantage had been taken, would not become acute. I visited Bahrain for a day, however, about 10 days ago on my way back from Shargah, and Shaikh Hamad came to see me, and at once raised the question of transhipment cargo. 3. the concession granted to Ibn Saud was two fold and is contained in Colonel Dickson's letter iSo. C-196 of 14th July 1920, in which it was laid down that i future only 2 per cent duty would be charged on transit goods consigned to the mainland provided these were removed ... ssty 's Secretary of State for India, The India Office, London.. -2- v. removed from tlie Bahrain Customs House within 20 days frcm date of landing, and secondly, that if goods were taken from steamers direct into lighters which proceeded to the mainland without touching at Bahrain, no duty would be charged# 4, In respect of the first concession which deals with what is known as RS-Export (R.E.)cargo, no difficulty has arisen# Extensive use has been made of this concession and large quantities of goods are disembarked at Bahrain and subsequently taken over by dhow to the lejd coast, and the arrangement works satisfactorily. 5. Hitherto, however, practically no advantage has been taken of the second concession, namely, that of direct transhij ment at sea, without payment of any dues at all. It is an exceedingly inconvenient arrangement for the shipping company since it is difficult to check the goods on the steamer, and secondly their own Agents at Bahrain are also landing contractors and they are naturally averse from losing their landing fees* Latterly, however, a large number of dhows belonging to Kuwait and other places, have brought up extensive consignments of rice to Bahrain and they have been transhipped direct into lighters and taken straight to the Arab coast, the Bahrain Government being in ignorance of the fact that the concession of free transhipment did not extend to goods arriving in native craft# It seems to me improbabli that this will recur till next spring# These dhows load dates about September and carry them to India, Aden and other places, formally they bring back timber, and a certain amount of miscellaneous goods, but this year, probably owing to the slackness of trade, they have been unable to obtain their ..• \-a* their normal freights, and' therefore have loaded rice and brought them up at very low rates to Bahrain. There is no doubt however that the concession does not extend to natire craft. Firstly, in Golonel Dickson's letter to Ibn Saud it is specifically laid down that no duty will be charged if goods are taken from steamers direct into lighters: secondly, when the concession was first imposed on the Bahrain (Jovernment, the then Deputy Political Resident, Colonel Trevor, under the authority of the Civil Commissioner, Baghdad, addressed a lettei to Shaikh Isa, and informed him definitely that this rule was only intended to apply to goods manifested for Hasa, Hejd and ^atar, and brought by steamers. A copy of this letter was forwarded to the Government of India under Bushire letter Ho.281-3 of 23rd September 1920. It is clear, therefore, that the Bahrain Government are entitled to charge 2 per cent duty on goods brought by dhow, and that Ibn Saud cannot claim free transit on such goods. 6. There remains, however, the question of goods brought by steamer,regarding which the local Agent of the Go. British India Steam ^avigation^ showed me certain correspond ence that he had toad with the Bombay and Karachi Agents. In this they stated that they were being asked to accept consignments of rice provided overside delivery was given and that while the Company did not like this arrangement, at the present time when freight was very scarce they did not feel justified in refusing it, I informed the local Agent Mr# Russet, that if the Company chose to take goods for overside delivery they were of course entirely at liberty to do so. 7. It will be seen that Shaikh Hamad announces that he proposes to revoke thin latter concession, and, for reasons which ....fi|0 -4- which I now give, I think there is much to be said icr his contention. When this concession was forced on Shaikh Isa, there was, practically speaking, no administration of any kind in Bahrain and the Bahrain Government had provided no landing or port facilities of any kind. In these circumstances there was no particular reason why shipping using the port of Bahrain should pay anything more than they would if they used any other sheltered bay in the Persian Gulf; such money ^ was received went into Shaikh Isa 1 ® pocket and he there fore deserved no particular consideration. This state of affairs, however, has now radically changed# The Bahrain (Jovernment have provided wharves, lights, beacons, etc., and it seems only fair that shipping utilizing the facilities of the port should contribute towards its cost, as they do in all civilized ports. At present the Bahrain State levy no port dues. The outer buoys are maintained by the Basrah Conservancy Board, acting on behalf of the Government of India, and for them ships are charged, but some lights have also been provided by the Bahrain Government. It would seem only fair therefore that the Bahrain Government should either be allowed to charge 2 per cent customs duty on all goods brought into their port, or should be entitled to charge port dues. As Shaikh Hamad in his letter points out this agreement was presumably not intended to bind che State xor ever and as the Government of India pointed out in another connection, it is generally understood that treaties for the denunciation of which no provision is made hold good rebus sic stft n tibUB . In the present case circumstances have radically changed, further the Bahrain Government must in . ••-5- in any case zeroise oustoms supervision over the tran 8 hlpment of tills cargo, as otlierirlse the way would be open for extensive smuggling. The only really satisfactory method of preventing this is for the goods to he landed at Bahrain and subsequently re-exported. 8, 1 have In connection with the proposal to grant tariff autonomy to the State of Bahrain pointed out the serious financial difficulties in which the State is at present Involved. If the practice of overside delivery becomes universal for all goods destined for Kejd it is calculated that the State will lose 25 per cent of its customs revenue - a contingency which I should view with the utmost dismay, and which would, I think. Involve the State in such serious diffieulties that His sJaoesty's sovernment or the Government of India would be compelled to come to its assistance as they have done in the case of Muscat. 9. On the other hand, the suggestion that the State should charge port dues would impose a heaTy burden on the shipping interests concerned, the chief of which is the British India Steam lafigation Go3#any, who would haTe to pay so much per ton on all their ships entering the port. I believe that they are at present making very little profit out of their slow mail service, and any additional charge would be very unwelcome. further, it would probably increase the price of the necessities of life to the inhabitants of Bahrain, many of whom are nowadays on the brink of starvation. I would therefore urge that representations should be made to the Hejaz Government on this subject and that the circumstances should be explained to • • •-6- to them, particular emphasis being laid on the fact that since the concession was made conditions have radically clmnged and that the Bahrain GoTernment iaare simk considerable sums in the development of their port while at the same time charging no port dues: that it is only fair that shipping utilising the port with its present facilities should pay something for these facilities, and that there are two alternatives, either the abolition of the right of free transhipment, or the levy of port dues, which the Bahrain State are clearly entitled to impose if they see fit; the latter would in the long run probably involve higher freight rates from Bombay which would not be in the interests of the Hejaz Government or the people of Hejd and that in these circumstances His Majesty^ Govern ment trust that the Hejaz-Hejd Government will agree to tne discontinuance of the privilege of direct transhipment — a privilege of which actually they have hitherto seldom availed themselves. It might be added that His Majesty's Government are confident that the Shaikh of Bahrain will as an act of courtesy continue to waive in the future as in the past, all duty on goods for the personal use of His Majesty the Li.ng and his household* I must apologise if this despatch is somewhat disjointed# I did not expect to be able to send it off till next weeks I however received Gaptain Prior*® despatch yesterday, and can just catch today's air mail# As tne matter is one of great urgency I have thought it preferable to submit my views at once in possibly a somewhat crude form rather than delay a week. \ I am sending a copy of this despatch to His Maj esty' s • • • . , ■ ■ ■ . . '• ■ • V , ^ V ' \ : . ^ \ • iii.'20 c -7- X Majesty^ Minister at Jedda and to the Government of India. J hare the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient, humble servant. ^ JiTfy * folitical Kesident in the Persian Gulf. ATTESTED . Confidential Assistant. Copy forwarded to the Political Agent, Bahrain. v ^ y 0 Ur ^ Bu^C h . ^19/212 Telegram B 30. Prom H.M*s Minister,Jedda. To Political -Resident, Bushire. No. 1.32. Eepeated to Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, London. No. 105. Dated 30th June received 1st July 1932. 4(5 Your telegram No 366. I am not clear as to reply to 'be given to Minister for Foreign Affairs. Can I say that form of 'bill of lading necessitated landing, from point of view of regulations, or must 1 ascrihe landing simply to unwillingness of shipping company to contract overside delivery? And am I right in assuming that transit duty i)utlnot import duty must now 'be paid once goods have 'been landed, for either reason ? r I have to meet allegation that it was authorities who insisted on landing after rice had 'been unloaded overside into dhows from inland. Minister for Foreign Affairs admitted that rice was for distribution to trihes. Ryan. tf- hmy19/ 212 A Telegram B 30. From Political Hesident, BusMre, To Political Agent, Bahrain. No 377 -^ated 1st July 1932. A'' Following from Jedda, 'begins:- •* I am not clear dislsri'bution to tri'bes ends. PresumaMy allegation is not correct. Resident.-j I ITelegram E 30, ^rom Political Agent, Bahrain. To Political Eesicient, Bushire. No 109 Dated 2nd received 3rd July 1932. Your telegram No 377. Bill of lading was in form for re export cargo and steamer company did not give previous notice of intended overside delivery so goods were landed in usual way. Transit duty was payable 'but Bahrain Government have waived payment of duties. Eice was handled 'by landing company lighters only^ so allegation is unfounded. Political. o19/212 fl Telegram S. 30. Jrom Political Eesident, Bustiire. To 11.1*3 Minister, Jedda, Bepeated to Secretary of State for India, London. Copy 'by air to Government of India, -foreign &amp; Political Department, Simla, [wvwfru Cw/ 7 ^W h M4• j No 385 n- Dated 4th July 1932. o^a / Your telegram No 105 to Secretary of State for foreign Affairs. Following from Political Agent, Bahrain, 'begins:- 11 Bill of lading was..... ...allegation is unfounded.* Ends. Resident. \ Wtr /1 vtIf ''IT 4 (i Confidential D.0.No:G/U0. Political Agency, Bahrain,the 3rd July 1S32. Regarding the consignment of 17,500 bags of rice Y/hich they wished to tranship at sea for Bin Saud. 2. The Bahrain C-overnment finally decided to allow half the consignmsit or some 8,800 sacks through free as a concession and told Muhammd al Tawwil T s envoys that this might be done. Some 2,500 sacks were landed fe** the first consignment and though they should have paid 2^ duty they have been included in the free 8,800 and Bin Saud only have hamali charges to pay. Muhammad al Tawwil T s envoys were q_uite satisfied vdth this. 3. 0fcourse,if Bin Saud applies to tranship the remaining half free of charge the State will presumably have to give way but I hope something will have been decided by then. In this case,ofcourse,the application was through Muhammad al Tawwil and was sent direct to Shaikh Hamad and the Adviser,which he had no business to . , 4. At our last meeting Shaikh Hamad was particularly ' He started on a line that I very much dislike, ''Bin Saud the great king,king of the Arabs,great expenditure in supporting I slam, our duty to help him'. I cut in and asked if Bin Saud was king of Yemen,Trans-Jordan,Kuwait, Iraq_ or Bahrain. Abdulla smiled at this but asked Shaikh Hamad if he wished to help Bin Saud by mining Bahrain. He then became a little more reasonable. 5. The fact is that he does not really understand the Hi] question and while one minute he says that every thing passing through territorial waters should pay full duty and that ruin is in sight if it does . Inot,the next minute he would like Saud have all A his imports free of all charges. He does not seem to see that the tiro are incompatible. HonBble Lt Gol.Sir Hugh V.Biscoe.^K.B.S., Political Resident in the Persian G-ulf, Bush ire.is requested that in any fu ^ on this subject the under-r* number may he quoted, ssed to— e Under Secretary of State fc 793 i# 0 Political Department, India Office, Lcmd 5.3104/32 Transit dues at Bahrein, air With reference to the Government of India's telegram to.764 of the 11th March on the subject of transit dues at Bahrein I am directed 'by the Secretary of State to request that he may he furnished with the vieirs of the O-overnaent of India regarding the whole question, in the light of Jedda despatch Mo.158 of April 9th (a copy of which was sent direct to His Excellency the Viceroy and to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf) and of the despatch io.154 dated 24th May from the Foreign Office to Jedda, a copy of which was enclosed in my weekly letter of the 2nd June. 2. A copy of this letter, together with a copy of Foreign Office despatch Ho.154 is 'being sent to the Politic 1 Resident in the Persian Gulf. I am, oir. Your obedient Servant, /but (Sd.) J. G. WALTON. eign Secretary to the Government of India, Foreign &amp; Political department liimla..3104/32. 266/25). FOREIGN OFFICE, S.W.I. 24th May, 1932. Sir, / With reference to your despatch No. 168 of the 9th April, I have to inform you that, in the course of a general discussion of minor outstanding questions on the 11th May, Fuad Bey Hamza, Acting Minister for Foreign Affairs of the Hejaz-Nejd, raised the question of transit dues at Bahrein. Government had some time ago asked His Majesty's Government to arrange that certain goods destined for King Ahdul Azle personally or for the use of the Hejaz-Nejd Government should 'be exempt from transit dues at Bahrein. This request had heen refused and the Hejaz-Nejd Government were consequently endeavouring to develop a port of their own at Ras Tanura. Should they succeed in this project, Bahrein would probably lose he- vily as a result of having refused the small concession which had been asked for and the grant of which would have been greatly appreciated at the time. Fuad Bey Hamza was informed that the matter would be examined. 3* The request which Fuad Bey Hamza had in mind may have been that which Sir Andrew Ryan reported in his telegram No.108 of July 15th, 1930 as having been made by k Liyb the Hejaz-Nejd Government in connection with the importation through Bahrein of a consignment of rice from Karachi. It will be remembered (see Sir Andrew Ryan's telegram No.128 of August 6th, 1930) that the King's request for a Fuad Bey Hamza explained that the Hejaz-Nejd waiver » Gill, Esq., stc. etc. etc. Jedda.waiver of transit dues on that occasion could not be acceded to. But that request was made so long ago that Fuad Bey may have had some other motive in referring to the matter and it seems possible that what he actually had in mind was the new system instituted last year and dealt with in your despatch under reference under which British India Agents will no longer accept goods for 'overside delivery' at Bahrein so that all goods shipped to Bahrein for the mainland are now liable to pay transit dues in Bahrein port. Should this oe the case, Fuad Bey Hamsa's remarks may possibly h-ve been meant to indicate that King Abdul Aziz does not propose to protest against the new system, but merely intends to endeavour to make himself independent of Bahrein by developing a rival port of his own at Has Tanura. I am, with great truth, Sir, Your obedient Servant, (Por the Secretary of State) (Sd.) G.W.Rendel.'BY AIR MAIL ' OHFIISITTIAL. l^ll i-r &gt; .v Ho. I 1 . 132-11/32. [-0 \v( n A copy of the undermentioned paper is forwarded to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf for information with reference to his telegram ]fo . 371, dated the 28th June 1932. By order, etc,, assistant Secretary to the Government of India, ^ • Foreign and Political Department, SIMLA. The 4th July 1932. Telegram to the Secretary of State for India, London, Ho. 1506 dated 4th July 1932.iW Telegram lo. 1506,-«• Dated 4th July 1932. Prom ..... FOREIGN, SIMLA. To Secretary of State for India, London. Reference Bushire telegram dated the 23th June Ho. 371. Bahrein transit duties. Government of India will furnish their views on whole question as requested in your letter of 9th June when they receive communication referred to in paragraph 4 of Biscoe's telegram. We endorse his advice to Bahrein Go vernmen t.8US^2fl HE Si DEN ' Tin s it pi '• ^ m ,^\ ^ Rr^riD£NiiAl BfcuuHdS. I' { ^ Confidential . D.0.No:0/ll7. VPolitical Agency, Bahrain,the 10th July 1932. A**/ xlease refer to your despatch to the Secretary of State regarding the overside delivery question. 2. I enclose copies of two letters from Bin Jiluwi and Muhammad al Tawwil regarding the concession allowed by the Bahrain G-ovemment. You will see from Bin Jiluwi's letter that he apparently accepts the payment of the 2 / o duty on the remainder of the consignment and it does not look as though Bin Saud were going to ask for the duty to 'be remitted. 3. Do you not think in the circumstances that G-overnment might 'be pressed a little more strongly isc the State cancelling Shaikh Isa T s concession? I notice your despatch mentions the question of ri ' q retaliatory port dues. I am afraid that if the Iledjaz G-overnment are asked to choose 'between'overside delivery ^ ^ &gt; and port dues and not overside delivery and no port dues, they will certainly choose the former. e should 'be very sorry to have to carry out our threat aad it would hit the B .I very badly and they would probably cancel the weekly call and revert to the fortnightly down call if any expenses were occasioned to their steamers. 5 Hon'bleLt Col .Sir Hugh V.Biscoe. ,K.B.E. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Budiire.« i Translation of letter No 195 dated 26th. Safar (30.6.32. ) from AMulla bin Jilwi , Amir of Hasa addressea to His Excellency Shaikh Hamad bin Isa al Khalifa, Deputy Huler, Bahrain. After compliments. With our inquiry about your health - we hope you are quite well. We, by the grace of God, are in a happy condition in all respects for which we thank Him. We have received your kind letter natea 21st. Safar 1351 which has given us pleasure to know that you are enjoying good health and other tilings mentioned have duly been noted. Brother , you have mentioned regarding rice that our condition and yours are same ana so our mutual help as well and that what concerns the king concerns all. We have no uoubt in your icincness. May not God deprive us of your existance. Landing of rice from the steamer to the boat will be better for us than landing on the pier but if you consider otherwise , your decision is paramount. Rice which arrives later and for which there is no permission may be countea from the steamer to the boat a. •'* 1 11'iiinfT'''rif-mjniniijifiniirino^ ^ and tax collecteo., as its landing on the pier and thence removal to the boat vill cause tie lay and trouole to us-, ihis is Mtsdbcxs our desire and Uod willing your consideration will be full of olessings.. This is what is to be said, compliments to father Shaikh Hamad ( Isa ? ), your brothers, Salman and his brothers. Here Saood and his brothers send theii compliments, ivlaij God preserve you. Usual Indigg. h.k1 Translation of letter No. 2 dated 25th. Safar 1351 (29.6.32 ) from Muhamad Tawil , Inspector Oenersl of Customs and Director of Revenue , Hasa and its dependen cies, addressea to His Excellency Shaikh Hamad bin Isa al Khalifa , Deputy Ruler, Bahrain. After co ipliments. Our prayer to G-od that you be in a perfect health and happiness. »«e are in receipt of your letter dated 21st instant in connection witn 880w bags of rice out of the original consignment lor His Majesty the King. We thank you for your kindness and we as well as His Majesty hope this in you. It is not hidden from you that this rice is specially in the name of His Majesty for distribution mong the tribes as usual and we are thankful to you for what you have done to assist and give facility to us in the matter. We hope that you will issue you orcier to the authority concerned to allow our agent to take delivery of the rice from the steamer direct to the baats which have been fixeu to carry the cargo to our pier. as_the landing of the cargo at the Bahrain pier will^expenses for porterage and landing charges which will be of no profit to the Government of Bahrain. You will not agree that there willfee be such a loss on the cargo without any profit to both the sides. Your decision is paramouM. Usual Ending. H.l«1 f &lt; ?m v |r« Confldeotial* B .0.JI..48». a of »S2. Th( R „ ld , noyt Bu«hlr« t the iStto aidLy i952# With reforenee to w&amp;deep at oh Bo, 436-S of th« 20th June, » copy of which waa forwarded to you under my printed letter «o.45?-S of the same date, regard ing Bahrain traneit duee # X forwftrd herewith for your informaticm a ©opy af a letter addressed toy Bin JiXuwi to Shaikh Hamad of Bahrain, from whieh yon will see that he apparently aceepte the payment of the 2 per cent duty on the remainder of the consign ment, even though it is transhipped direct into lighters. I do not know if the Me|a# people will regard themselves as in any way ^ound lay Bin Jilu^s offer hut send the letter to you in case it should he of assistance. I m sending a copy of this letter together with its enclosure to miton. Sir Andrew Hyan,, * s Kinister, I s. i i a* J c ' 7 /1^Ma- Telegram To fiepeated to From R 27 Government ot India, Foreign &amp; Political Department, Simla. Secretary of State for India, London. H.M*s Ministers Jefida. Politioal Resident, -Bushire. Ho. 1644 i^ated 23rd received 24ttL July 1932. / Biscoe's despatch No. 436-3 of 29ttL June and ijrevious correspondence. Bahrain transit dues. us important. (a) Arrangement of 1920 was forced on Sheikh in somewhat questionable exercise of suzerainty and without any consideration 'being received 'by Bahrain from *Ihn Saud. On political grounds tnerefore we douht whether we should 'be justified in insisting on continuing arrangement against Sheikh's expressed wishes and we are not clear how we can in practice enforce such^i decision. 'e have recently recommen- -ded grant of fiscal autonomy to Bahrain and now to deny him right to exercise this limited measure of sovereignty within.: his own port would 'be wholly inconsistent with that recommendation. (h) In taking decision of 19 20 Government of India had in view interests of Bahrain itself since they feared that Sheikh Isa*s insistence on excessive transit dues would kill transit trade, whereas smaller charges... 2 Following considerations appear tocharges would increase Ms iDcome. Situation has now changed and it seems clear that if free transhipment is permitted there is grave danger of Bahrain losing large portion of their income although they have in the meantime invested capital in improving their port. (c). Although inteirnational practice established 'by Barcelona Convention does not permit duty on goods in transit it allows levy of dues to defray expenses of administration and supervision. We can therefore find no Justification in international custom for entirely free transhipment within territorial waters whether from steamers or dhows. 3. Conclusion is that we must acquiesce in withdrawal 'by Sheikh of transhipment concession and explain position to ♦Ihn Saud on the lines suggested in paragraph 9 of Resident's despatch. Should 'Ibn Saud decline to accept explanation, we think imposition of port dues, to which he can have no valid objection, should he further considered in spite of administrative objections pointed out hy Eesident. Foreign. o Confidentail Assistant.OMIDSmAL. jM Ho. F.131-H/32. A copy of the undenwentioned paper is forwarded to the Hon'ole the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, for information, with reference to his endorsement No, 454-3 of -Oy 1932, dated the 6th July 1932. 'w -ftSjOENC Of:. . Assistaxit Secretary to the Governiiient of India. gn and Political Department, Simla, e July Letter from the Colonial Office to theii?©reign Office* No. 98005/32 dated the 27th June 1932. (With 1 3.0.)\\\^ 98005/32; 27 til June 1932. Sir, I am directed by Secretary Sir Philip Gunliffe Lister to refer to your letter No. B.2349/266/25 of the 26tli of May enclosing, for his observations, a copy of correspondence with His Majesty's Representative at Jeddan regarding tne Bahrein transit dues. 2. It is observed from India Office letter Ho. PZ.3i04/ 32 of tiie 9th of June that the Secretary of State for India has asked for the views of the Government of India on this question, and Sir Philip Gunliffe-Lister would prefer to await the hcjoyt. views of that Government jss?making any observations on this subject. 3. A copy of this letter is being sent to the India Office. I am, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Sd/- G. G. R. Williams. Under Secretary, foreign Office, True Gopy, ^^^SuperTn t enden t, Issue Branch, Foreign and Political Department,/316/25) /13S/11. My George, Jp I^ your official deupatoh Mo»154 {^ ES4f/E&amp;&amp;/E5) of ay 24, rucordlftf a dlscutttaion with ^ad ramaa about ^ runs it dues at Bahrain:- I take it that this la for my information only and calls for no action or eonrasnt here. I may say, however, that In my opinion Fuad was almost certainly referring to tho refusal in 1^30 to waive transit duoe on rico for Ibn Sa'tft's troops# He has too food a memory to h forgotten that end I think that, if he had had the irior arrt&gt;nfoment in mind, he would have referred to it eirpllcltly, t itill ha^e a divided mind about the rrior arranpa- raent. v .hen I diecuasbd it at home with Chrietophor arnor, I leant to thy flew th t it involved no clear breach of the ander- takiaf given to ibn 3a'M in l^SO and might therefor® be allowed to stand until ha contastad it, it ha ahoald think, fit to do m* I still think that view tonabia, hat there may he a ca^a for reeonsidaring the matter on the grounds that (a) The queation can be argued both ways; (b) Fuaa has now manifaated Interest in one aspect of Bahrain transit dues and to should ©scape all possibility of reasoaable reproach by c iiieelllnf the Prior arr ngeaent} , \&gt; (c) The Government of India did not themselves seam to be very keen on upholSing irior. Handel, , 'oreign office. ■ :e m nrFHffgf? n m v. COVERING LETTER DATED ?1 . -o o Hi C0?V w l F P Y AIR mail IHITISH GAT I OK, J i) £i£x Ml JAl. June24th,I am not in favour of making aaj? concession to Iteo sa 'M ae rogarde duos on good® landed at Baliraiii for tranafeipmont to mm,so long as fe@ does wo little to accommodate ae in other directions. I cannot eea that thare la any International objection to the transit daea being levied in a port of which as© is made. I do not personally understand the reference to «International rales generally accepted' in the letter ^hlch Dickson wrote to him on 5aly 14, 1980. ! / A Ur 0 Yours ever, ^ (Signed) ANDiEW OTAN.\vO 13/1/9* MiBistpy of Foreign Affairs, Bait * al Awml, 15&amp;1. 8th July, 1933, JMtto iUidr®^ Hyan s aister ©tc» t Jedda. Your sse#U»0F, / ' I have received Your iixoelleucy'8 Mote Ho•115 of July 5th 1932 (1st Jsiaoi * al Amml 1351). I thank you for the coiacmaloaticm you have mde ooaceraiisg the jaaimer in which the supplies received at the port of Bahrain for our Govemaoat have 'mm treated. 'itm iiaportant thing at present in the view of Goverment is that orders say he given for the execution of the terms of the letter sddressaed to His Majesty .-y Lord the King by Colonel Dickson on 'behalf of the British Oovomiaent on 37th DM 1 ! ai;Jja WM Ko#535/192 and we requost that the British Qoveraaent should t&amp;ktsuch preosutionary aeaaui'es as will avoid any breech of the promise given by the British dovernaent in the above~iaentioned letter# With highest respects, (Qgd) YClouf Ytstn* for Minister for Foreign Affair®.1 V 1 Board of Trade, (Commercial Relatla e£d Treaty Dept), C.R.T.4744/32. ' S.W.I. 16th August 1932. Dear Laitliwaite, Your letter of the 8th August (P.Z.4526/32) about duties on goods transhipped at Bahrein en route from the mainland has been handed to me on my return from leave. On general grounds we doubt whether there could be any objection to the levy of a duty at the rate of 2% on goods transhipped in ports or harbours of Bahrein. We can think of no valid ground on which an exemption could legitimately be claimed on behalfi of goods which happen to be transhipped from steamers, and the duty seems to us a perfectly legitimate and cotemon-sense method of obtaining revenue, particularly as no- 1 port dues or similar charges are levied. I am sending copies of this letter t o Warner of the Foreign Office and James of the Colonial Office. Yours sincerely, •Laithwaite Esq (Sd) T.G.Jenkins.[SI I INDIA STEAM NAVIGATION Co., I/in. ( INCORPOKATED i N ENGLAND. ) idress:- ons.' BOMBAY, lst Se P teml3e ^ 93 2 . (Post Box No. 122.) ^ v 1 The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, British Residency &amp; Consulate-General, ^ Bu shire • Sir, v We have the honour to refer you to the correspondence which was exchanged with the Political Agent at Bahrein in October 1931 on the question of overside delivery at Bahrein of goods manifested for Ojair and other mainland ports. Since then the position has become very acute and merchants are now in sisting on receiving ex Company's steamers, outside the port limits of Bahrein, their goods intended for the maiiAand. If we do not grant this concession we will definitely lo^e a very substantial source of earnings to the Company. Part of this source has already been lost but indications definitely point to our suffering to an eyen greater extent. As we have no doubt you are aware, we are at all times anxious to conform to the wishes of yourself and the Political Department in the Gulf and also to assist^as far as possible^he Government of Bahrein. On the other hand, conditions have now reached a stage when,if we continue to neglect the trade for OJair and other mainland ports the result will be the introduction of oppositioii vessels in the Gulf which will not only appropriate the trade to mainland ports in proximity to Bahrein but will also compete with this Company's steamers to and from other Persian Gulf ports. Ihen we make this statement we do so in the full V knowledge that shippers have the intention of approaching other Steamship services if we do not assist them.-2- We accordingly feel sure you will appreciate the serious position in which we are placed, namely, if we maintain our present policy of refusing to accept cargo other than for discharge at Bahrein we shall add considerably to the loss that is at present being sustained by this Company in maintaining their steamer services on the Persian Gulf. On the other hand, if we meet the wishes of merchants and obtain their support by giving overside delivery into their own boats outside Bahrein^we shall ) in all probability be causing disappointment to the Shaik of Bahrein, with whom we have always endeavoured to maintain the most friendly relations. Giving full consideration to these two aspects of the situation we have reluctantly come to the conclusion that our future policy must be to cater for the trade to the mainland ports and it is our intention to land cargo into consignees own boats outside the port limits of Bahrein. Before, however, fulfilling our intentions we shall be pleased to hear from you, preferably by telegram, whether there are any sound and cogent reasons why we should not act as we propose above. ■* In the meantime pending your advices, rather than allow merchants to make other arrangements we have agreed to charge a specially low rate which will enable them to handle their cargo via Bahrein but which arrangements are of such a nature that it would not be possible^from an economical point of view^for the Company to continue on this basis for any considerable time. This will explain what might otherwise appear to be an argument against our present attitude,as merchants, we believe, are sending forward considerable quanti ties under these temporary arrangements. As you have no doubt observed, the tendency at the-3- present time is for small ports to spring up and to cater for trade which ,in former years^was served by main ports and to combat this tendency would, we maintain, have dis astrous results. As an example of this point we would instance the Kathiawar ports between Bombay and Karachi. These ports have received no encouragement from the Shipping Companies until it was observed that in spite of the luke- waim attitude adopted towards them these ports were in creasing in importance and had to receive equal considera tion to that of the main ports such as Bombay and Karachi. Trusting to receive an early reply from you in view of the importance to this Company of this question. We have the honour to be, Sir, Your obedient servants, Agents. /%&gt;Tc leg raja G.T.C. Ke si dent, jjUsliire rx ' c Political a-exit, Bahrain c/o Pestmaster, Karachi - No 553. Dated the 9th September 1932 . Banr:-- in Transit dues. t ^ r.rltier. India steam navigation 30. jjombc in letter to mt da-tea the ist Septembe^ state that ior economic reasons they will reluctantly be compelled to accept cargo for overside delivery outside port limits of Bahrain. i-lease interviev. naracM agents who are ' probably aware of proposa^and without committing yourselr in any to them telegraph your views. -hssilsitt-tt/vt V PR1VATS The Residency# Buahire, lOtb September 1932 I enclose your pr irate and personal information a copy of a ^ letter dated let September from Messrs* Mackinnon Mackenzie &amp; Co., Bombay* &lt; , DmBeltsrare, Esq,, Bahrain.v^- 131 CONFIDENTIAL. &gt;r - No. 642-S# of 1932, The Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Political Agent, Bahrain. and is directed to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document/ v . g a copy has been sent imivately to Mr« Belgrave to T n facilitate reference- y A\\ ■ fTV\l — - IP ' ^ • British Residency and Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. /-A' iV 1.^ Dated, ■ ^ (Reference to previous correspondence ; This office telegram No, 553, dated 9th September 1932. Description Name and Date. Letter dated 1st September 1932 from Messrs. Mack inn on Mackenzie, Bombay. Subject. Bahrain Transit dues.v 19/212. Telegram G.T.C. From Political Resident, Bushire. To Political Agent, Bahrain, c/o Postmeater, Karachi. No. 558. Dated 12th September 1932. Ily telegram No. 553. Bahrain transit dues. If your views make a long telegram please seik send them by next air mail instead. RESIDENT.mmmm isMM {23Wl2%/2o}, Attgait lf3g. to# . ...w&gt; $ it v - , wmmm ^ Witli TOfermo© to ajr deapatoli Ho*291 of July 10 and previous correajKsndenco relative to tranait duos at Bahrain, I tor© tho honour to fammuft ooploe of a lottor ana enclosup© tmmtUe lato Sir fiueh Blaooo vhioh roaohed so on July at. You ^)h Will doUbtlesa take into aocount Hkb T Jiluwl*® letter when con- alderlnc wfcat attitude ahould l»e taken up vla-l-vla of Ibn Ja*^ J In the light &amp;fSir Itugjb's deepatch Io«436 i of June 39 to the India Of floe and, tn® views hy trie aovemiaeat of India in the i?oreisn and ^olltioal iiepartment' © telegram to tiie India Offioo of July BS. The late ffolitiaal lesident seeuc to have- thought that I sight still he diaeueaiag the matter her© hut I have in faot had no further com»unication regarding it with the Hejasi aovemaont sinoe receiving tit© note encloaed in my deepatoh under referenoe# 4# A b iiheylch Itaaf 'fSaln*® original ooiaiurj.cation to as was oralj I cannot ho certain whether he had definitely in aind the question of exeaption frojs dues as a corollary to that of overside delivery* I 6&amp;mm&amp;d this to he the mxm shoiad he mmmfa&amp;tsurprised to find that hie aovomaaent coneidered th€ tormT que a ti on iiwatorial as Ihn Jlluvi appears to have done# In any ease it wuld he ueelee® for ae to pursue the question until Hie Maleaty* a Oovomaent have taken a decision on the pro posal in the telegram from the Govemaent of India referred to ahove# 3# I as sending copies of this despatch to Bushir® and Siala# I have the lionour to he with tho high©at respect, @lr 9 Your most obedient, ■® ^5®style Principal Secretary aushle servant, 1 stat ® for Foreign t %ffairs# I A„/&lt;// CONFIDENTIAL . No. 676-S. of St± 1932. Copy forwarded to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department with reference to Jedda Printed Letter Ho, 106, dated 6th August 1932. By order, 'a f or Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. British Residency &amp; Consulate-General, 17th September 1932- Bushire Subject Bahrain Transit dues, List of /v Letter Ho. 487-S, dated 13th July 1932, from Sir Hugh Bxsooe to Sir Andrew Ryan, with enclosure.\C,\%[ 9 IU CONFIDENTIAL . Ko:C/l58. Office of the Political Agent,Bahrain, Sind Club,Karachi,the 13th September 1932. i! V From: - To: - The Political Agent, BAHBAIH. BU SHtRE RED iD^Y. /f/ o.,, C.VS-^'-'- t' OOWilliHTIAUEIlOTO The Hon^le the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf., BUSHIRB. Sir, 3r I have the honour to refer to your telegram Mo:553 dated the 9th September 1932 and to say that I interviewed the Karachi Agents who raised the matter of their own aucord.and y v showed me a copy of the Bombay Agents letter to you. They said that in view of the threatened competition they would be obliged to accept cargo for overside delivery outside harbour limits although they would be most reluctant to do so. It appears that one Muhammad al Marzuk went to Bombay and interviewed Mr.Hadow and threatened to ship by opposition lines or to send cargo by country craft if they refused to grant him overside delivery outside port limits. 2. The Agent showed me a letter from their Bahrain Agents reporting the visit of the Pagervick which stated that the State was contemplating taking steps against shippers who engaged in this traffic and enquired what these steps were. He stated that he understood that the State could not prevent overside delivery taking place outside territorial waters. I replied that the State had considered the possibility of refusing these foreign steamers permission to come to Bahrain and also the repatriation of merchants who insisted on conducting their business in this fashion, 3. The Agent said that they fully realised the difficulty they would experience in giving overside delivery outside port limits and that they would not do so unless they were they were forced to do it. He seemed to consider the competition of country craft of littlef 2, &lt;/V&lt; - of little danger since they could only proceed there in fair weather and their rates were low owing to unnatural circumstances, I said that the 2,% duty which their transhipments now paid would discourage them. He apxjeared to doubt that the steps suggested were practicable. I stated that the view in Bahrain was that the interests of the State and the British India Steam Navigation 3- Company were identical and that delivery outside port limits would be equally inimical to both,and with this he agreed. 4. It will be seen that the villan in the piece is Muhammad j al Marzuk of Karachi who acts principally for Muhammad al Tawwil, through Abdul Aziz al Bass am in Bahrain. This man had some 7,500 I out of the 30,000 packages the S'agervick brought up and the steamer took them direct to the Mainland. If the visi^ts of this steamer of similar ones to Bahrain were stopped,or if they were not allowed to land cargo there ? Marzuk would not be able to find enough cargo to fill a steamer himself and would be obliged to ship by the British India Steam Navigation Company,who,if they had not the threat of this line,would not agree to give him overside delivery. The State refused to allow the Russians to send steamers to Bahrain and there is nothing to prevent them from disallowing the visits of any other vessel they found harmful to their interests, / 5, In this connection I should mention,that^one of the partners of Dhamanmal Ishardas visited me after the passage of the Pagervick,! asked him why he had allowed the ship to go to the Mainland when it was contrary to Bahrain interests and in the long run,his and those of all the other Indian merchants. He said that they had now realised this but that the space had been available on the ship,andjais Agents had not considered this when they accepted Marzuk's cargo. He said that they did not intend to accept such cargo in future.and that if I wished he would not charter these steamers again, I replied that I could not express a wish in what was really a matter of business. It would appear that Dhamanmal Ishardas is not likely to raise any difficulty if these steamers are stopped and no one else has sufficient3. financial strength to charter a steamer by himself. 6. If the State finds a Hejdi merchant in Bahrain conducting his business in such a way as to cause definite loss of revenue &lt; or of trade,there would he nothing to prevent them repatriating men. Bin Saud expelled the entire Hindu population of Qati£ without a word of protest from us,and would not be able to protest against similar action on the part of the Bahrain Govern ment. 7. The State feel very strongly regarding the evasion of their dues by onerside delivery and will fight it by every means in their power. If we oppose them in what they may conceive to 1 be legitimate steps to protect their interests,we shall be doing ourselves no good,and,in the long run,damaging British Indian interests. The matter is not a simple one,however,and I hope to discuss it with you on my forthcoming visit. I have the honour to be Sir, Your Most Obedient Servant, Political Agent, Bahrain at Karachi. \Confidential * Ho. 687-S of 1932. British Residency and Consulate-General, BusMre, SOtto. Septemlaer 1932. ;c J'rom The Hon • hie Lieut •-Colonel T.C.W. Fowle, .Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, To The foreign Secretary to the Government of India, Simla. Bahrain Transit Sues . xv 0 Sir, I have the honour to refer to Government of India telegram Bo. 1644 of the 23rd July 1932 to the India Office and connected correspondence on the above subject. 2. whether the Bahrain State can abrogate the Transit Dues Agreement with His Majesty Ibn Saud seems to depend on whether the so-called agreement was really an 'agreementor Merely a •♦concession 41 . In ordinary law for a contract, or agreement, to be binding there must be a 'consideration' given or received on both sides and it is arguable that the same holds good in international law. The Bahrain State certainly received no consideration Ibn Saud in the matter: on the contrary the State has been the loser. It seems obvious therefore that the arrangement come to was a concession on the part of the State which it can with draw, local circumstances having altered. If this view is correct would itjnot be possible for the communication to His Majesty Ibn Saud to be of a more categorical nature than/,%'A - 2 - than that outlined in paragraph 9 of air Hugh Biscoe's letter Mo. 436-8, dated the tCjt 1932, to the India Office (copy forwarded to India and Jedda under Ho. 437 -s), and concurred in 'by the Qovernment of India in paragraph 3 of their telegram under reference? If the agreement in question was in reality no 'agreement tt , tout merely a con cession, could not rbn Baud 'be informed that, owing to changed circumstances, which of course would be carefully explained, the Bahrain State regretted that they could no longer continue it, and that in future 2 per cent, dues will toe charged on goods delivered overside? There would thus toe no question of Iton gaud's refusal, and— provided that the Bahrain State has a right to levy these dues (which it would seem to have according to the Board of Trade letter Ho. C.R.T.4744/32, dated the 16th August 1932, copy forwarded to the Government of India and Bushire under India Office printed letter Ho. j?.Z .4991/32, dated 20th August 1932)- r -there wi 11 toe no question of the State having to impose port dues, the otojections against which are detailed in paragraph 9 of Sir Hugh Biscoe's letter already quoted# Iton Saud will doutotless toe dis gruntled, tout matters have now reached a pass where it seems to me we have to choose toetween offending His Majesty, and staving off ruin for Bahrain. The financial condition of the latter is already, without any question of the loss of transit dues, causing me no little anxiety. The State depends for its prosperity almost entirely on the pearl trade, which at present is at a very low etoto: catches of the last few seasons have toeen poor, and even when pearls are found there is little market for them, nor is the market likely to improve for some years. The State gets toy far the greater part of its revenue from ad valorem customs dues, and not only has the toulk of trade decreased, tout likewise the price of commodities imported. Iiast/ml Last yeai^s 'budget, (the Bahrain financial year runs from May to April)^ recsiTed since Sir Hugh Biscoe wrote his despatch of 29th June, did not balance, and unless an un expected change for the better occurs the State will very soon be reduced to the dangerous expedient of living on its capital—a small reserve which it has built up in more prosperous times. If to this critical state of affairs is added the loss of its transit dues the State will be brought an appreciable step nearer to bankruptcy, and His Majesty's Government or the Government of India may well—as pointed out by Sir Hugh Biscoe in paragraph 8 of his letter already quoted—be forced to come to its financial assistance as they have already had to do in the case of Muscat. 3» So much with regard to the Ibn Saud aspect of the question. As will be seen, however, from the copy of a letter dated 1st September 1932 from the British India Steam lavi- gation Company, Bombay, which I enclose, there has now arisen another and perhaps even more serious complication. On receipt of this letter I telegraphed the .Political Agent, Bahrain, now on recess in Karachi, to get into touch with the British India Compady's Agent there, who would doubtless be au fait with the matter, talk it over with him, and let me have both their views. I enclose a copy of Captain Prior's reply. 4. The situation is that the British India Company, faced by competitors who threaten to practice overside delivery outside Bahrain waters, state that they will reluctant ly be compelled to adopt the same practice themselves unless I can produce any sound and cogent reasons why they should not do so. The Company do not fear the competition of natiwe craft (vide paragraph 3 of Captain Prior's letter, » which aspect is also dealt with in paragraph 5 of Sir Hugh Biscoe's depsAtch of 29th June): it is the competition repre- sen ted/- 4 - aented toy such vessels as S.S. w FagerTioJc M — mentioned toy- Captain Prior—which is the danger. 5» The ^agervidc^, a Norwegian Tes^%, was, I gather from Gaptain Prior's letter, chartered toy the Indian firm of Dhamanraal Ishardas of Bshrain, and the owner of the cargo which was taken to the mainland is one Mnhaaaaad al Marzuk, #10 acts principally for Muhammad al Tawwil, Iton Saud'3 Customs Director at Hasa. It will toe otoserved that one of the partners of Dhamaimal Ishardas and Company has informed Gaptain Prior that cargo to the Mainland will not toe accepted in future, and if uhamanmal Ishardas and Company continue this policy, this source of •cmpetition to the British India Company will at least toe remored. 6« fhe danger, however, still remains of steamers of the #, Fagervick rt class coming to Bahrain and giving overside delivery outside Bahrain waters. (Overside delivery from such steamers within Bahrain waters can toe charged the 2 percent, dues.) With reference to this danger Captain JPrior suggests the possibility of the State refus ing such, foreign steamers permission to come into Bahrain waters, or at any rate to unload cargo there. As there is not enough cargo for the mainland only to fill a steamer, such vessels would toe compelled to call at Bahrain to unload the 'balance of their cargo, and they would not toe allowed to do this toy the State if they had practised overside delivery outside Bahrain waters. (At least that is how I understand Captain i^ior's arguaent.). It seems to me that such action might toe successful in removing the competition of overside delivery outside Bahrain waters, which is the main danger driving the British India Company towards adopting such measures themselves. Captain Prior points out that the State refused Russian vessels pe mission/- 5 - lU 'l permission to call at Bahrain, and presumably they nave equal right to extend this refusal to other vessels, retaliation in the way of shipping restrictions heing, I believe, a legitimate weapon in the hands of any Govern ment. Such vessels might not always he foreign ones: a steamer belonging to an Indian Company might also toe chartered, hut—though this might raise protests in Indian circles-*! think the Bahrain State would he on strong ground in applying the restriction to Indian vessels also. The restriction, it must he remembered, would not be an absolute one: it would merely be a measure of self-protection. Any vessel that did not practice overside delivery outside Bahrain waters would be welcome at Bahrain. Captain Prior's further suggestion of the possibility of the 'repatriation' —a euphemism for expulsion— of merchants who conducted their business on objectionable lines (paragraph of his letter) I cannot fully endorse. Bahraini merchants the Bahrain {Jovemment could presumably deal with, as they thought expedient , though even they might find it difficult to punish their subjects for practising lawful trade, how ever much this trade might run counter to the financial interests of the State, But it is more than likely that some of the 'offenders* would be either foreigners or Indians, both of whom by the Bahrain Order in Council come under the jurisdiction of the Political Agent, who can deport them only for certain specified offences. In other words, it would be legitimate to take action against the trading, but not against the persons of the traders. 7. With regard to the letter from the British India Company referred to above, I enclose a copy of my reply, which is to the effect that I trust that they may be able to 'wait and see* before taking the steps they contemplate. I understand their anxiety not to lose trade, especially in these/- 6 - these difficult times for shipping companies, tout it is import ant that they should be dissuaded—if possible—from taking any precipitate action. Once they comraenoe over side delivery an impetus will he given to this undesirable practice *hioh it may be very difficult to stop. It is equally naoepeary^for the Bahrain State, and ourselves, to consider the matter of overside delivery outside Bahrain waters carefully before committing ourselves to definite steps for putting an end to this practice, fending, there fore, a consultatiHn with Captain Prior, isho arrives here on the ISth October, (I will also obtain the views of the Financial Adviser, Bahrain,), I should lilce my views ex pressed in paragraph 6 above, on Captain Prior's suggestion as to retaliatory measures, to be considered as tentative. I have, however, given them now so that the matter might come under the consideration of His Majesty's Government as soon as possible* * On the other hand my views expressed in paragraph 2 as to the nature of the communication to be addressed to His Majesty Ibn Saud, provided that the State has the right to impose the 2 per cent# dues on overside delivery within Bahrain waters without having recourse to port dues, may be taken as considered ones. 8. To sum up. The Bahrain State is faced with serious financial difficulties, and if to these is added the loss of its transit dues, in order to stave off the bankruptcy of the State, His Majesty's Oovernment or the Indian Government may sooner or later have to step in and assist the State as they did in the case of Muscat. By a concession which the State, wome twelve years ago, under considerable pressure from us, gave His Majesty Ibn Saud, it is now threatened with the loss of these dues. I am of opinion that His Majesty should be informed that, owing to changed circumstances, the State is now regretfully com- pelied/I £1 m y m compelled to cancel this concession* A further complica- tion, however, has now arisen* The British India Company, forced 'by competitors viho threaten overside delivery out side Bahrain waters, state that they will reluctantly be compelled to adopt the same practice themselves unless strong reasons can he produced why they should not do so. Certain action to deal with the threatened competition has 'been suggested 'by the JPolitical Agent, Bahrain* In as far as his proposals are directed against the methods of trade, and not against the persons of the traders, these proposals have my tentative concurrence. With regard to the letter from the British India Company, I have sent them a reply which I trust will have the effect of prevent ing them from taking precipitate action until I have had an opportunity to consult further the iPolitical Agent, Bahrain, who is visiting Bushire shortly, and until His Majesty's Government have had time to give the matter their consideration. i am sending copies of this despatch to His Majesty's Secretary of State for India and His Majesty's Minuter at Jedda. I have the honour to he, Sir. Your most obedient servant, i.t • -Colone 1, iPolitical Resident in the Persian Gulf. ^Sent under printed letter no. 688- h , dated 20-9-1952. Copy forwarded to the #oliti..al Agent, Bahrain for information. By urder. Confidential Assistant.Confidential. British Hesidenoy and Gonauiate-General BusMre, the 20th September 1952. Mo. 702-8. L Subject ; OTeraide i^eliTery at Balrirain Gentlemen, Please refer to your Private letter of the 1st September 1932. X quite appreciate your position, and — your anxiety—especially in these difficult days for mercantile marine—not to lose such trade as may be available. I also note with thanks your remarks as to your desire to co••operate with the Political Resident, and your reluctance to take any steps which would be detrimental to the trade of Bahrain. g. Your letter has had my careful attention. Immediately on its receipt I telegraphed Captain Prior, Political Agent, Bahrain, who is on recess in JKarachi, to get into touch with your Agent there, discuss the matter with him, and let me have a report, #iiGh i have now received. You are no doubt also in receipt of a communica tion from your Karachi Agent on the subject. 3, The situation as I understand it is as follows. Your Company does not fear the competition country craft. There remains that represented by steamers of the 'fagervick' class./ srs, Mackinnon Mackenzie &amp; Co., &amp;t8, The British India Steam navigation Pany, Limited, *&gt;ay f- 2 - class. This competition is of two kinds; (a) direct transport of cargo to the Mainland, (b) overside delivery outside Bahrain waters. With regard to (a). It is possible that such voyages may cease. It is, however, (b) which is causing your Company most anxiety, and which may force it to employ reluctantly similar methods, i.e. overside delivery outside Bahrain waters. It is possible that the Bahrain State may be able to take certain retaliatory measures against any of your eompetitors using such methods wbich will prevent their continuing this practice. If this were the case the danger you most fear would be eliminated. 4. Captain iPrior is arriving here on the 12th October, and I will then go further into the matter with him. I have also reported the whole situation, which is a complicated one raising many serious issues, for the consideration of His Majesty's Government and the Indian Government. In the me an time I trust you will see your way to postponing the grave step of accepting cargo for overside delivery outside Bahrain waters. Such a step would undoubtedly be a serious blow to the financial prosperity of Bahrain, and the prosperity and interests of that State are in the long run identaoal with those of your Company. Yours faithfully, it .-Colonel, .Political Besident in the -Persian Gulf.rhe Residenoyy Buahire, 2iBt September 1932. In r»©ent correapondence on the subject of Bamrain transit dues Captain Frier mentioned that S.S* 'FagerviclC 4 , of the national Steaoship Line of Ionrey # apparently chartered by DhaiaatKaal Ishardae# had taken 7500 packages*out of a total cargo of 30000 packages* direct to the mainland- Will yon please let us know when this took place, what part of the sieinland the cargo was landed at, and any other relevant details* t..c / e vf E-hadur Abdul Haiy Slhashmi, Indian / ssistant, Political Agency, Bahrain.,^1 private. The Hfitucienoy, Buahire, the 24th aeptember FXeaue refer to ray private letter of he iOth iie^tember. Prior i» coming up here on tine 12th October to diacuas the raatter. What are your views? If the fi* 1*8. coupe titers couid be prevented fro® in- dulging in overeide delivery outaide Bahrain »atera, B.I. theiaaelvea would not toe forced to do ao. it i C. Belgrave, Kaq., Baia'ain.investigation of the proposals of the Sheikh of Bahrein, to avoid any charge of ill faith. But at the same time the &amp;' • arguments adduced in Sir Hu -h Biscoe's Despatch of »29th June ^and the Government of India's telegram of 23rd July, to which reference is made above, will doubtless carry great weight more particularly in the difficult financial conditions at present confronting the State of Bahrein. 4, ©le cjiestion has already been very closely examined in the correspondence referred to above; the arguments on both sides have been thoroughly canvassed, and it is not proposed to recapitulate them in any detail. Suffice it to say that in the light of the discussion the Secretary of State finds himself in complete agreement with the views of Sir Hugh Biscoe and of the Government of j.nu.ia, and suggests that we must acquiesce in the withdrawal by the Sheikh of the concession of free transhipment, explaining . w the position to Ibn Saud on the lines suggested in paragraph 9 of Sir Hugh Biscoe's Despatch of 29th June. He agrees also that in the event of its proving impossible to satisfy the King of the Hedjaa and Hejd by an explanation oi this nature, it would be necessary, despite the objections to such action, to consider without further delay the inrpositicn of port dues by the Sheikh of Bahrein. But his strong feeling, which will he trusts be shared by the Secretary of State for the Colonies, is that both on grounds of equity and on wider political grounds, the right solution of uhis question is the modification of the arrangements of 1920 so far as they refer to transhipment free oi charge. It is relevant in this connection that, in the lirst place, the arrangements of 1920 did not extend to any cargo save that transhipped frcsn steamers into lighters or native cra^t, that until quite recently no advantage, for practical purposes, appears/Itv appears to have been taken of than; and that the effect of withdrawal would not so far as can be judged be of substantial importance to the Government of the Hejaz and Nejd. In the second place, while it would no doubt be possible to bring some pressure to bear upon the British India Company with a view to their reconsidering their reluctance to accept cargo for transhipment overside at Bahrein, the case for such pressure is not a strong one, and there is in any event considerable risk that action of this nature might lead to criticism in the Inaian legislative bodies as the result of representations frcm the Hindu merchants of Bahrein. 5, A copy of this letter has beam sent to the Foreign Office and to the Board of Trade, I an, Sir, Your cbedient Servant, (Sd.) J. C. WALTON,i'-V \ \A CONFIDENTIAL , No. 734-S of 1932. The Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Political Agent, Bahrain, and is directed to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document/ * British Residency and Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. 'A vV o- 'l 1 ' )ated... .iQ.t Reference to previous correspondence : Bushire endorse™nt no- 687-B of 20th beptember 1932 Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. .A India Office printed letter No. P. Z.5133/32 of no date, with enclosures.(as markedj. Bahrain Transit hues.i*Vi y y V i | R0 mmo^y.J Political Agenoy, /T'^ Bahrain, the 1st October 1932, !AL HEOOH Please refer to your B.C. of the 21st idem . The ^agerrick' arrived here on the 3rd August oiid,after discharging the 'bulk of her cargo at this port,left for Cjair on the 6tli taking 4900 hags rice and 1000 hags sugar. She returned here on the 8th after discharging the 5S00 packages referred to at Ojair and left lor haracii c.ie Sai ;ie u . This consignment was imported 'by iiOdul xj.ziz oin Ali «.l Bassar.ij a Tejdi merchant trading in ahrain^ and despatched from Karachi through his shipping agent L-uhammaa -.arzook Kuwait i. The owner of the cargo, Abdul Aziz A1 iassam, it woild appear, arranged for a local pilot to enaole uie uapuJLi t-o take the steamer to Cjair. ming Jsquire, feidency, tUuiIIfl-lJ 19/212 (hi-UuutJ ^ ^ / VUy Z^' ) Kxtract from iiahrain JJiary l^/^dated 2nd uctober 1932, for the period 16th to 30th aeptexaber 1932. * * * * * MlSCB LLAJNEOUS. 368. A consignment of 12,000 bags of Calcutta rice and 600 'bags sugar arrived £xsl for King xbn baud by axb. 'Grmara' and S.b. 'uundee' on the 21st and 26th aepteraber respectively, xhe usual transhipment duty has been paid on these consignments. The delivery of the sugar ex the a. '•Dundee' was taken outside port limits. * * * * *C 4 Q x Confidential . No;C/165. Office of the Political Agent,Bahrain. c/o Post Master,Karachi. 1st October 1932. y^-' • ■ ^ From:- BUSHIRF ^EBtQSNCY. An lb The Political Agent,Bahrain, 3 l ~ at Karachi. '-~rrn~ OONFIOE^iiAL HEflOROa, Tor- Sir, The Hon'hie the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf..Bushire. I have the honour to refer to your letter No:6&amp;7-S dated the 20th September 1932 to the Government of India regarding Bahrain transit dues. 2, I pointed out jto the late Sir Hugh Biscoe in my B.O. /()-&gt; No;C/117 dated the 10th July 1932 that the Hedjaz-ITejd Government had accepted the situation and this view has since been confirmed 'by a private letter I have just received from the Adviser. According to this they are making a further very large shipment of rice and sugar and are paying the 2%transit dues without quest ion, kuhammad al Tawwil having been ordered to arrange this with Shaikh Hamad and the Bahrain Government. It is clear,therefore, that the communication to His Majesty King Bin Saud might very well he of a more categorical nature, 3. As regards the view expressed in the conclusion of paragraph 6 of the above mentioned letter,! venture to since suggest that/the Government of India made no protest at the expulsion of the Hindu community from Qatif it would he difficult to explain to the Bahrain State why persons conducting operations ruinous to their trade should he allowed to take shelter at Bahrain, Every State is at liberty to withdraw permission to reside from foreign nationals with or without assigning a reason,and I believe a caseA Iin a case of this nature has recently he en brought to your notice at Bushire. I have the honour to 'be Sir 3 ' Your Most Obedient Servant, P A' ^ At ly t Political Agent, Bahrain at Karachi.19/21E Telegram Prom E 27. To Political Resident, Basliire. Government of India, Foreign &amp; Political Department, Simla. Repeated to Secretary of State for India, London. H.M'S Minister, ledda. Mo. 621 Bated 7t]i OctolDer 1932. My despatcb. Ho. 687-3 of 20tli Septtfealier, paragraph 2. Bahrain transit dues. Political Agent reports that usual transhipment duty has 'been paid on large consignments for I'bn Saud delivered oversi&lt;ie ooth within and without port limits at end of September. Payment is apparently in accordance with arrangement suggested in Ihn Jiluwi s letter of SOth June (see my printed letter No.676-3 of 17th September) . In circumstances I now suggest it is preferable to let well alone and hold up proposed communication to Hedjaz Government until that Government reverts to question. Post copy forwarded to the Political Agent, -oanrain, for information. By Order, Resident o Confidential AssistantM 19/212 Telegram Prom E 27 Government of India, Foreign &amp; Political Department, Simla. Secretary of State for India, London. Political Resident, Bushire. To Repeated to No. 2267 Dated 10th received 11th Ootoher 1932. ■^ushire telegram No. 631 of October 7th Bahrain transit dues. 2. We agree in the circumstances now explained it will 'be better to avoid raising matter with Hedjaz Government. Foreign. 0 Post copy forwarded to the Political Agent, Bahrain, for information. By order. Confidential Assistant. 7 ^ J-O-F-A. r&gt; 1 hoi/j*-, / V'A^J *po N&gt; Bahrain. Dear Colonel Pov;le» 8th October 1932. Before I recieved your letters of 10th and 24th September i the subject of direct transhipment at sea I had been shown a copy ' Mackinnon Mackenzie's letter to you by Russell, the B.I. agent i Bahrain and we discussed the matter together. It is difficult to make any helpful suggestions as the Government ■ Bahrain can do nothing outside its territorial waters a.nd the itter is no longer an internal one.. Since your letter I think the itter has changed, for the worse, then it was only a matter of the .rect transhipment at sea, now the B.I, themselves are threatening to ;nd steamers to the mainland. If small steamers and native craft could be compelled not to give :rect transhipment at sea the B.I. would not have felt forced to do &gt;. Uow Russell tells me that Mazook the Arab merchant of iiarachi, who 3 the B.I.'s biggest shipper, is threatening the B.I, that he is )ing to arrange for a small steamer to carry his cargo between India id Ras Tanoura or other mainland ports direct. The B.I, who are actual/*/ )sing money on the Gulf run at present are so alarmed at this threat iat they are prepared to send a boat there ti emselves. Mazook tells them that great numbers of native craft are plying jtween India, Karachi, and Bahrain and the mainland ports, cutting ray their trade, he also tells them that most of the cargo he ships &gt; Bahrain eventually goes to the mainland, I think much of this rgument is bluff. Possibly a great many native craft sail from irachi with cargo said to be for -Bahrain,or for the mainland, but a sry few of them actually arrive at their alleged destination. They reep up the coast to Persia, or to the ports near the frontier. In Karachi native crafts declaring for mainland ports are not ;quired to produce landing certificates from the ports to which their irgo is declared; if this could be done 1 think the whole matter Lght be affected and the argument which Mazook uses to force the B.I. )uld not hold water. 1 am f inding out at this end how much of his nports really go to the mainland. The Bahrain Government will, now, gladly allow direct overside jlivery within the p»rt provided that the duty is paid, I think lis fact is not sufficently known to the shippers in Bombay and irachi. We should lose pier fees etc etc but in comparison to the £ this is not of importance. It is generally believed that a great deal ©f the earg® which is »nt to the mainland is smuggled across to Persiaj I am told that now ; is even worth smuggling rice across, not only tea and sugar. I think something could bRBa.££KKi«A be effected by making things Lightly unpleasant for the people in Bahrain, all foreigners, who aie : the bottom of this new trade. They are the Bassam family, Mejais, id Mustapha bin Abdul Latif, a Persian, whu used to be Managing Lrector of a small Gulf shipping company which was swamped by the B.I me of these people are popular, Kanoo and the j^ozaibis aislike all ; them and Shaikh Hamed is very indignant with them, he realises ti.at lere is a danger of a large proportion of our already depleted revenu^ Lipping away and all through the actions of people who have livea i his country for many years and grown rich on ^xaciing hex6#(f ! vP / I'll ■ fvvVV^ Tele gram Code. / ^ From Political Agent, Bahrain (on recess) To Political, Bakrain. Ho. .i 1 : Dated jO October 193S. following for Adviser^ begins. Marzuk came to see me on sailing and said he was pressing Mackinnons for reply regarding overside delivery. He asked lae if way out could not be found. He said he would agree to pay net duty provided he was allowed direct transhipment and not obliged a%^d cargo and ipuld drop question chartering special steamer. Consignments to be not less than 3000 bags both rice and sugar. He assured me Mackinnons would accept gladly despite loss of landing charges. This I believe is fact. Failing this he threatened ship direct to Ojair avoiding Bahrain altogether by 500 ton steamer and showed me telegram offering him space. Only drawback appears possible diversion sugar trade but if this occurred concession could be limited to normal Hejd requirements. It should be borne in mind other merchants may also apply for same facilities. Unless Bahrain Oovermaent sees objection I recommend this as best solution for all. Please telegraph if I should advise Resident accordingly. Minimum consignment might be 4000 bags or prAviso added that concession only applies genuine Nejd cargo. - Prior.fa Telegram Code. tf • &gt; ft . . trh ' wiv) yrom Political, Bahrain. /L Political Agent, Steamship Varsova, Hen J am Hadio* Ho. 1072. Bated loth (received) 11th October 1932. Follwing from Adviser^ begins: Agree to your suggestion as best under all circumstances, for time being preferably 4000 bags and genuine Nejd cargo marked RE. Knds. • Political./?&gt; Confidentic! . Office of the Political Agent, Bahrah, Gamp Bushire, Dated tiie IStJa October 1S32. The Political Agent, Bahrain, at Bushire. The Hon* ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Sir, I have the honour to say that on my departure from Karachi for Bushire, Mohammed Marzuk, a Karachi merchant principally interested in the overside delivery, came to me on the steamer and said that he was pressing Messrs. Mackimon Mackenzie &amp; Go, for a reply regarding the matter. 2. He asked me if a way out could not be found and said that he would agree to pay a net 2 per cent duty, provid ed he was allowed direct transhipment and not obliged to land cargo, and if this was arranged he would drop the question of chartering a special steamer - a threat he had held out to the British India Steam Navigation Gompany if he was not given overside delivery outside Bahrain territorial waters# 3, in the course of the discussion he said that he would undertake to send full consignments of not less than 3000 bags at a time of both rice and sugar and he assured me that Messrs# Mackinnon Mackenzie &amp; Co. would accept gladly despite the loss of landing charges. This, I bej-ieve, is ci fact. . • • Pr om To|7^ fact. Failing this be threatened to ship direct to Cgair, avoiding Bahrain altogether, by a small 500 ton steamer, and showed me a telegram from a certain firm offering him space. 4 # I told him that I would represent this to the Bahrain Government, and that I hoped that some solution could be found on these lines, and upon the steamer leaving I immediately telegraphed the gist of the above to the Adviser, pointing out certain drawbacks, one of which is a pose-Vie diversion of the sugar trade which, however, could be counter ed by limiting the concession to normal Hejdi requirements. I also pointed out to him that other merchants might also apply for the same facility. Nevertheless I recommended this solution to him and asked him for the views of the Bahrain Government. He has replied to me that the State considered this the best solution from the present impasse, but. that they wished that the minimum, consignment to be 4000 bags, and added that the concession could only apply to genuine I.ejdi cargo and that it must be marked n E.E. w 0 5. I suggest therefore that messrs .lackinnon Mackenzie &amp; Co. may be asked to inform Mohammed Marz.uk that the State will allow him direct transhipment in Bahrain waters provided (l) that he pays a net 2 per cent duty, (2) that his consign ments are not less than 4000 bags of rice or sugar and (3} that the consignments are genuine Hejdi cargo. Messrs.^.ackuror Mackenzie &amp; Co 0 I feel sure will be delighted at this solution as it removes the threat of opposition steamers and although they will lose in landing charges ( the landing Company at Bahrain being a subsidiary of the British India Steam Naviga tion Company) wxii still this loss will be far less than what they would lose if rival steamers were to be introduced-3- on this runo I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant, Capto, Political Agent, Bahrain.■.... , .J ■nonfidentlal# H0 .776 -S of 1932. British Residency &amp; Consulate-G-eneral, Bushire, 14th October 1932. Oyeraide deliTerv at Bahrain , Dear Sirs, Please refer to my telegram lo # 660, of today's date, communicated to you through the G ot erranent of Bombay. interested in the question of overside delivery, interviewed Captain Prior, the Political Agent, Bahrain,(who has just been on a visit to me here)at Karachi on 9th October. After dis cussion he stated that if he were allowed overside delivery he would pay a net 2 per cent transhipment charge, would under•• take to ship consignments of not less than 3000 bags at a time and would refrain from chartering special vessels for carrying cargo direct from the mainland# On consultation the Bahrain Government have intimated that they consider this the best solution out of the present impasse provided that the concession is limited to genuine lejdi cargo, marked ' R.l. % and shipped in consignments of not less than 4000 bags at a time. 4, It seems to me that this is the most satisfactory 2 Mohammed Marzuk, the Karachi shipper principally solution of the question that can be arrived at in the interests of Maekinnon Mackenzie &amp; Co.Lxd., Agents, British India Steam lavigation Co.Ltd., B £ m b a-2- of all parties conoerned. T&amp;e Bahrain cioTernment, while losing a certain amount of rerenue in the way of pier charges, etc., retain their main source of revenue from such cargo, i.e., the 2per cent transhipment dutyj the British India Steam H&amp;Tigation Company, while losing some income from landing charges,(in which I understand they are interested), retain, without fear of competition, their isain source of profit, the carrying trade; and the shippers obtain their chief requirement, overside delivery. 5. Xwould surest therefore tnat Mohammed Ilarzuk ( and any other shippers mho offer cargo fear overside delivery) may be informed by you of the conditions on which the Bahrain Government are prepared to grant the concession within Bahrain waters. If the minimum of 4000 bags required by the Bahrain Sovernment is likely to prove unacceptable to shippers I dare say that the Bahrain Government might reduce the minimum to 3000 bags. If difficulties arise on this point please inform me» Agency. Yours faithfully * under P.L.No.777-3 of 14/10/32. political Resident in the Persian Gulf Copy forwarded to the Political , Bahrain, for information. By Order Confidenti-xaBAdtantnoafidential, Ml nl U0.778-S of 1932. British. Residency &amp; Consulate-General# Bushire, 14th October 1932. from - The Hon*ble Lt.-Colonel T.C.Fowle, C.B.E., o'' &gt; Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, To - The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, Hew Delhi* Bahrain Transit dues * / \ v \K Sir, / In continuation of nay letter 5o # 687 -s, dated 20th All September 1932, I hare the honour to forward herewith a copy of ' a letter Bo,776-S, dated the 14th October 1932, which I have addressed to the British India Steam navigation Company,Bombay, on the subject of overside delivery, I am hopeful that the Company will accept the suggestion made therein, which offers a practical solution of this difficult question, and one, moreover which will strengthen the hand of His Majesty's Government should the Hedjaz Government recede from their recent attitude, report- ^ ed in aay telegram Ho*631, dated 7th October 1932* x I am sending a copy of this letter, and of its enclosure, to His Majesty's Secretary of State for India and y His Majesty 1 s Minister, Jedda. 3I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant. y i Lt*-Colonel, if Political Resident in the Persian Gulfi, P.T.O.G.R.T. 47 44/32 Dear Lalthwaite Many thanks for your letter of yesterday (P.Z.5133/32) about the so-called transit duties at Bahrein. When I spoke to you earlier about the matter I did say that it was doubtful whether the Transit Convention really applied to these dues, and on that there were two points (1) whether the goods were in transit within the meaning of the Convention, and (2) whether, if so, the dues themselves could he considered to he transit dues. of the fact that it is usually in our interest to interpret the Transit Convention as widely as possible we should not wish to contest the Foreign Office view, which apparently is that goods transhipped at Bahrein are in transit within the meaning of the Convention. The real point is the second one, that is whether these dues are 'special dues in respect of transit' within the meaning of the opening words of Article III of the Statute annexed to the Convention. On this point feel quite confident that the answer is in the negative. a country shall not place impediments in the way of goods vtiich have to cross its territories in getting from one country to another. The aues which are allowed to be levied are those 'intended solely to defray expenses of supervision and administration entailed by such transit.' This, as you will see, ma&amp;es no mention of such expenses as the upkeep of ports. It was intended to deal solely The first point may be open to doubt, but in view The Transit Convention is intended to secure that with/ La ithwaite, Esq/;.&gt;v IS I with thefprovision of services for Hie purpose of securing that goods, which had paid no customs duties because they were in transit, actually left the country at the other end of the journey and did not remain within the country itself. Glearly, therefore, it was contemplated that dues necessary for the upkeep of ports and similar expenses would he charged in addition. charged is intended to defray the expenses of the port. No country can claim that its goods shall have the use of a port in another country and shall make no contribution to the expenses of that port, and it seems to us therefore that no country can claim that goods which have to 'be imported through Bahrein should escape all charges in Bahrein. For the reasons which you explained it would he inequitahle and unsatisfactory to charge port dues on the tonnage of the vessels carrying the goods, as is done in most other countries. The alternative is to charge dues upon the goods themselves, and it seems to us that dues so charged, so long as they are reasonable in amount and hear some relation to the cost of upkeep of the port, are port dues in fact whatever they may he in name and fall entirely outside the scope of the Transit Convention. made sure that the dues shall he called by some name which did not suggest that they were in fact transit dues. As we understand the matter, this transhipment Perhaps some difficulty might be avoided if you I am sending copies of this letter to Rendel and Williams Yours, etc. (3d.) T.G. JENKINS.1^ P *Z.5133/52. INDIA OEPIGE, WHITEHALL, 3.W* !• 25tri August 1932. \ ** \ Dear Jenkins, You will have seen the Foreign Office letter of 23rci August, No. E.4157/316/25, ahout transit dues at Bail re in. I saw the Financial Adviser to-day and ascertained from him that the dues at Bahrein are, in fact, substantially he low the amount required to defray the expense of supervision and administration. But in any case, if we rightly understood our discussion with you the other day, the view of the Board of Trade is that nothing that occurs in connection with cargo at Bahrein, whether it he transhipment overside or landing and reshipment at the wharf, falls properly within the definition of transit. The point is not of much importance in the circumstances, hut I should he glad if you would confirm the correctness of my assumption. Meanwhile, we are writing officially to the Colonial Office supporting the proposals of the Political Resident and the Government of Inaia on the general question. I am sending copies of this letter to Rendel and Williams. Yours, etc. (Sd.) J.G. LAITHWAITE. • oenKins, Esq., m.u., Board of Trade, Great George Street, 3.W. 1. Jenkins, Esq., M.O.,CONFIDENTIAL . ^ No. 785-S Of IQ*? The Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Political Agent, Bahrain, and is directed to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents. British Eesidency and Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. /m , v ■ i7th. .U9.to be.?,. 19 $2. N f Reference to previous correspondence ; Bushire printed letter Ho. 734-B, dated 1st uctobe. 'L Description of Encl ^32. x. 6y Name and Date. 1. Letter No. P. Z.5133/32. dated 25th August 1932, from the India uffi to the Board of i 'rade, London. 2, Letter Ho. C.K.Y.4744/32, dated 26th August 1932, from the Board of Trade to the India Offi Subject. Bahrain Transit Lues. (Received under India Office endorsenent Ho. P.I,5135/3^, of no date.)Ilk' 1 ' |V&gt; Forwarded, with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office, for the information of the Political Resident, Bushire. India Office, Whitehall, London, S.*W. 1. Got&gt;y sent to ^ U.i' , inn&gt;r}~7 : -1^0 | lPOiElOK OFFICK, S.' .1. | 4829 /^16/25) * 12th October, 1932# j :■$ dear Laithwait®# You. are# I think waiting to l*sam out views on your official letter i.2.6138 /32 of the 19th September to the Colonial Office about the propoeefl annulment of the concession made by the Sheikh of Bahrein to Ibn Sand in 19go, exenpting from transit flues goods which are cestined for Ihn Saud* s dominiona and are transshipped at Bahrein direct from the oteamer into lifters or dhows without being landed# V'e see from the semi-official correspondence between you and Jenkins of the Board of -rade that the possible ' international' difficulty under the Barcelona Convention is disposed of. After careful consideration of the arguments advanced by Biscoe in his despatch of ^7 Jane 29th, of which you sent us a copy m /our ^&lt;5 P.2.4082/38 of the 8th July, and by the Oovernaent L/g&gt; India in their telegran of the 2Srd uly (youi ^ P.2.44&amp;3/58 of 2Bth July), « are prepared to acquiesce r^' in/ Lai thwai te 9 &lt; sg#// x/ ia the proposal that the Sheikh should now he allowed to withdraw the concession. We have» however, two points to raise# e think that it would he inappropriate toaak Ihn Saud to agree to the discontinuance of the privilege, as suggested in para graph 9 of Biscoe* s despatch, since this would imply that we to re not confident of our position and felt hound to ask Ihn Baud's consent* If such consent were refused the situation wight hecoiae embarrassing* s woul- therefore prefer to notify to Ihn Baud the discontinuance of the con cession as a decision taken in the plenitude of the rights of the Sheikh of Bahrein; and we think it would prohahly he preferable not to mention the alternative of imposing port dues* The withdrawal of the concession and the proposed explanations will imply, to some extent at least, a confir- mation of the remainder of the arrangement made in 1920s that is to say that they will imply that the dues to he | charged henceforward on all goods in transit at Bahrein land destined for Ihn Saud's dominions (except those for ihn | baud's personal requirements) shall remain at two per cent* 1 i understood, when I raised this point with you the other day,/flay, that it would» in the opinion of the India Office, he met hgr instructing the Political Resident not to permit the Sheikh to raise this transit due above two per cent, and that you were confident that the condition which is 'being aade in agreeing temporarily to grant the Sheikh tariff autonomy - viz*that he must give the Political Resident four months' notice of any proposed change in his tariff - will place the Political Resident in a position to carry out such instructions* Ve should be glad to have confita rnation of this and to know that you are prepared to instruct Powle accordingly* instruct Hope Gill to make a written communication to the Saudi Oove rument on the lines proposed above. On hearing from you that you agree, we will I am sending copies of this letter to Blaster and to Jenkins* Tours ever.Telegram From G.T.G. Political, Bahrein. Gapt. Prior, Bushire To Unnuinbered Dated and received 27th Octoher 1952 IMPORIAHT . 'Ahniedi'' flying British flag arrived to day Thtirsday and was permitted to land Bahrain cargo provided 2^ duty was paid on Ojair cargo. Oaptain states OJair cargo has no concern with Bahreii and that duty is payable 'by consignee. He requests assistance. Three passengers for Bahrein were per- -ffiitted to land. Please telegraph instructions. iroliticalIMj'CRTAKT / i have consultea K.sident, ne is of opinion tnat matter nsould seem prixaaril^- one toratate to settle but would like to give Ufcv tam what assistance iie can. i imve pointed out to him thAt consignees or their agents live m iscJarain ana He suggests tnat these eonsignees fflight give state a letter oi guarantee to pa^ tixe two per cent dues proviaed matter was put to arbitration of political Agent later, ^ain point from UaptMn's point of view would seem for ship to unload ner cargo as soon as possible and con tinue her voyage. -PRIOR- -fffWj'/f/l/Z. itle^ram a.T.C. ■ br0 ' i Uaptain jfrior, ijushire. 10 political Agency, jj hrain. Unnumbered. iJattd tiie 28th uctooer a 332.19/212 Telegram From Political, Bahrein. Capt.Prior, Busliire a.T.o To Unnumbered. -^ated and received 29th October 1932. IMPOBTAHT. ^ State informed Captain of Ahmedi and consignee that it will allow discharge if Z% dues on Ojair cargo lodged in Bank provisionally in the name of the i?oliti- -cal Agent; Captain to 'be Agent using Bahrain landing Company. * Ends. Following from Adviser:- PoliticalConfidential Office of the Political Agent Bahrain, Gamp, Bushire. Dated the 29th October 1932 10 - From The Political Agent Bahrain, at Bushire To The Hon t ble the Political Resident in the Persian (Julf. Bushir e. Sir, I have the honour to refer to the correspondence enclosed with Bushire Residency endorsement Ho.809-S, dated the 26th October 1932, regarding Bahrain Transit dues. possible 'international' difficulty that may arise under the Barcelona Convention, I taJce this opportunity to point out that since the State is not a party to this Convention and has not even heard of it, it has no bearing whatsoever upon Bahrain and its affairs, I may perhaps be permitted to record here my surprise that whereas Ibn Saud is allowed a perfectly free hand to do whatever he thinks best in the interests of his State, the moment the Government of Bahrain show a desire to assert themselves their way is barred by a formidable barrier of international conventions, I have mentioned elsewhere that when Shaikh Isa was informed in 1920 that his transit duty was illegal according to international practice ( now curiously enough found to be legal after all ) he pathetically observed that '' he was sure that there was something in his favour in international practice if only he knew of it'. 2, Since considerable attention has been devoted to the-2- \ I 3. I notice from a statement in this letter that the Foreign Office are prepared to acquiesce in the Shaikh's with drawal of this concession. Are they aware that the Bahrain Government have already withdrawn it and consider the matter settled ? It is therefore quite inappropriate to attempt to secure Ibn Saud's concurrence to its withdrawal and he must be notified of a fait accompli . Since he has apparently already accepted the situation a detailed explanation appears out of place. As regards the imposition of Port dues. have come to the considered opinion that this is quite impracticable and will if necessary give detailed reasons which will, I think, prove unan swerable. 4, Finally I notice the view expressed that the withdrawal of the concession will confirm the remainder of the 1920 arrange ment. This is quite untenable. What has happened is that the State is now being granted customs autonomy and that this is to be exercised subject to a four months* notice to the Political Resident. This in no way prejudices their existing treaty right to charge up to 5 per cent on all classes of merchandise, and they can charge any transit duty they please provided they do not exceed that figure. Actually, they would be ill advised to exceed the 2 per cent duty now levied and have no intention of doing so. Circumstances may change, however, and the State must be left full scope to protect its interests in whatever method the situation of the period dictates. 5. I presume I am in order in referring to demi-official letters since this appears to be the only form the correspondence has taken. 1 have the honour to be. Your servant Gapt., Bahrain.lSjf212 Telegram E 27 Political Resident, -^ushire. Political Agent, Bahrein. No. 713 i&gt;ated 1st Bovember 1932. V / v Your letter of 13tb, September, No.0/158 paragraph 2. Bahrein Government should not without prior reference to me issue notice refusing steamers who earry cargo to mainland permission to discharge c cargo at Bahrein. Eesident.11^ 3 * • • # • aoKFimmiAL , liO» BSS'- .5 of IViSSS# British, ^ecidency onsulate-General» Buahire, tiie 2»d lio?ember 1932# from - The iion'ble Jut..Colonel T.C.Fowle, i olit ical -eaident in the PerBian ^olf, to - The Foreign ieoretary to the 'Government of Indl&amp;y Hew -&gt;elhi • BivHriAlS TICAHSIT JUBS. Sir, I have the honoor to refer to i-'orelgu Office letter lo. K.4829/316/2&amp;# dated iEth October 195Et to the India Office IreoeiTed under cover of India Office Printed Letter P. (,,$225/32) on the subject mentioned fbove. g # j note that the Foreign Office consider that it «ould be inappropriate to m *Maje.ty Ibn Saud to agree to the discontinuance of the concession and would prefer aerely to notify Hi® Majesty of its discontinuance by the Shaikh of Bahrain* »ith this view 1 agree, in fact I advocated it in paragraph £ of my despatch Ko.687.ii, dated 20th September 1932. I suggest further that any comimnica- tion which may eventually be made to His majesty Ibn should contain no mention of the possible iiaposition of port dues, against which alternative there are practical difficulties.— 2— 3. I might add that the foregoing does not affect the suggestion contained in my telegram IIo»631, dated 7th October 1932, that owing to recent developments the proposed communica tion to the Government of Saudian Arabia may be held up until that Government reverts to the question. I am sending copies of this letter to His Majesty's * Secretary of State for India and His Majesty's Minister, * Sedda* ♦sent under P.L. No.834-S of 2/11/32. I have the honour to be, Sir, Tour most obedient servant. \v li. Lt.-Colonel, ^ Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, I v ■ Copy forwarded to the Political Agent, Bahrain, for informa tion. c By Order, r Confidential Assistant \ v \v V . X- • \ 'N 1 '19/212 IS u % f Telegram Prom To So. 172 Bated 2iid received 3rd Novem'ber 1932. S 27 Political Agent, Bahrein. Political Resident, Bushire. Captain of 'AHMBDI* informed Adviser that Lieut-Commander Phirby, Royal IndianMarine ('bro- -ther of well-knoTKn adventurer) now port official Bombay, who formerly entered Ojair harhour himself, personally supplied him with special plans in Bombay (not Admiralty charts). Ship also carried 'buoys for 'buoying entrance. Since developement of OJair can only he at expense of Bahrein and detrimental to Bahrein and British interests,cannot understand his venturing such action without your knowledge. Doubtless his brother instigated this. Political.19/2 IS Telegram From To No. 1539 Datied 3rcL received 4tli NoveDi'ber 1932. Political Agent, Bahrein, Political Resident, Busblre. ^iT 0 'AHMADI* has unloaded at Bas Tanura. Despatch follows. Political. Telegram From To No. 1144 ■^ated and received 4th November 1932. G.T.O. Political Agent, Bahrein. Political Resident, Bushire. v Your No. 723. No. No cargo landed here. It is now 'being shipped 'back from Bas Tanura and State will turn a 'blind eye. Political.,1^ .0 66111 i dent ial . No:0/175. Political Agency, Bahrain,the 5th November 193E. QingNCY . J The Political Agent, Bahrain. from:- e To:- The Hon T ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.,Bushire. C!i ir I have the honour to forward for your information a copy of a letter I have received from the Adviser to the Bahrain Government regarding the S.S 'JJamadi'. This vessel unloaded her cargo at Has Tanurah and is now believed to have proceeded to Ojair,possibly to load dates. I understand that the cargo originally destined for Bahrain has either been disposed of on the Mainland or is being broiAght back in dhows to Bahrain. 2. The Ship left Bahrain before I arrived and I cannot, therefore,give any account of what occurred,but the facts are clearly set out in the Adviser's letter. I was surprised that the State did not accept the Captain's offer to pay the duty but apparently he got no further than making the offer and subsequently withdrew it. At no time did the ^tate place any obstacle in the way of the steamer leaving Bahrain,their attitude simply being that no cargo might be landed here. 3. I was surprised to find on arrival,,the intensity of the feeling the visit of this Ship has aroused and the action of the Shaikh's Government has been warmly applauded by all the leading merchants,who clearly saw in the opening of such a ±x traffic the ruin of thei^ country. His Excellency Shaildi Hamad is satisfied with the action taken for the present,but vail no doubt consider other means if this action should be found to be insufficient for its purpose. 4. At the instance of the Bahrain Government a telegram hasa been sent to Messrs Maokinnmi MackenzCompany through the local Agents of the British India Steam Navigation Company to discover whether lluharjnad al Marzuk has accepted the terms offered him hy the State,which were outlined in your letter - ■ ^ ^ ^ Iio:776-S of the 14th October 1932. A reply is still awaited * 1 ill and I am,therefore,unable to say exactly what the situation is regarding this proposal. I understood from Shaikh Muhammad that this man was recently charged before a British Indian OouT*t with smuggling silver dollars into India in boxes of dates. This fact,if true,is of interest. 5. In preventing the visits of steamers who will inevitably destroy the Bahrain entrepot trade,the Bahrain Government are protecting not only their own interests,but also British interests and those of the British India Steam Navigation . Company. It is to our interests that trade should be concen trated in these islands and any diversion of it to Ojair or Has Tanurah,where we have no representative and Hindus cannot aU*, trade,would be a blow to our position. ^As has been point out elsewhere if the State T s finances collapse,we shall be expected to come to the rescue. The British India Steam Navigation Company are at present in a weak position since their mail contract obliges them to adhere to a schedule,ano. visit a number of ports (Jask,Charbar,Henjam,Lingeh) which a^-e a dead loss to them. If My means of rival steamers of small tonnage the Nejd G-overnment could fo^ce them to visit Has Tanurah not only would a deadly blow be st^ucic at Banrain, out the Company would be obliged to spend at least one or mo-e days at an additional port and so have great difficulty in maintain ing the present service which only gives steamers five days in harbour at the terminal 6. In r^ga^d tothe instructions contained m your telegram i^^To:^ of the 1st November 1932,1 venture to point out that the State has already issued its proclamation and that it would be impossible for than to withdraw it now and any such suggest ion/ -3- suggestion ¥/ould be very ill received. It is mifortiHiate that the State did not give longer notice of its intentions but they are well within their rights and legally their position is unassailable. On the Persian coas^ customs officials constantly strike whole shipments from ships mani fests and refuse permission for their landing on the grounds that some monopoly law is infringed,with the result that the steamer is obliged to carry them all the way back to the port of origin. Adecxuate notice is seldom,if ever,given of these enactments and protest is inva^iatly ineffective. You are probably aware that bills of lading contain clauses which protect Shipping Companies from It he acts of Princes and ■Rulers''. I understand that no vessel similar to the Ahmadi is on its way to Bahrain and a similar incident will not arise again as all shippers are well informed of the Bahrain Govern ments embargo,and will male their arrangements accordingly. I have the honour to be Sir, lour Most Obedient Servant, Political Agent, Bahrain.Ho. of 1351 ofiice of the Adviser to the Government. Bahrain. Dated. End, Rajab. 1351 Slst Ootr. 1952. from The Financial Adviser to the Government, Bahrain, To H. B. 1*8 Political Agent Bahrain. Sir, I have the honour to acquaint you with the facts leading up to and connected with the stay of s.s. 'ihrnedi^, belonging to the Eastern Navi gation Company, in Bahrain. I understand that® the Company and the consignees are making an ofxicial complaint to you alleging that the ship was delayed in the Port by the Government of Bahrain. X. Owing mainly to outside conditions over which the State has no control the iinancial position ox this State is now very grave. Recently however the trade and the revenue of Bahrain has been threatened by a new and vary serious danger, which if n ot prevented will reduce the revenue by perhaps one third. ^ Certain foreigners, Hindus, iersians ana Najdis, who have for many years enjoyed the ireedom and security of Bahrain and have grown rich from tradingtrading in Bahrain, have recently combined together to charter small steamships from India which they bring into the harbour of Bahrain. These steamers carry cargo for Bahrain and for the mainland port of Ojair. Until now Bahrain has been the entrepot of the mainland and all cargo for the mainland entering Bahrain pays Z% Customs duty, whether transhipped directly, within the port, or landed and re-exported. £ Some two months ago a small stermer, s.s. 'Feger^ick' of the National Steamship Company came to Bahrain where she discharged cargo and then carried the remainder of her cargo to Ojair. She was chartered by Messrs. Dham nmal Isardas, a Hindu firm, resident and trading in Bahrain. Owing to various circumstances the Govt, did not on this occasion take any action, but the danger of further incidents of this kind was tully appreciated. The Government also learnt that if small steamships continued to run direct from India to the mainland, calling at Bahrain en-route where they lighten themselves by discharging cargo to enable them more easily to navigate the course to OJaii, there might be a possibility of the British .india oteam Navigation Company sending their ships direct to the mainland ports. This would entirely destroy Bahrain's position as the entrepot of the malniand. i The Government is aw^re that it cannot prevent or control ships which are going direct from India to mainland ports but it intends to discourage this practice by every possible means in the case of steamers whichwhioh first call at Bahrain on their way to the mainland, or which visit Bahrain after discharging cargo at mainland ports. The State strongly resents the action of these foreign merchants who in this way are attempting to evade the payment of the duty and as an indication of its disapproval, such steamers, unless they pay the duty,, will be afforded no f cilitles whatever and will not be allowed to land cargo in Bahrain. 7. ifter lengthy discussions with his brothers, his eldest son and myself, on the subjects I have mentioned above, H. E. Shaikh Hamad decided on 20th October to publish a proclamation (No. 28 of 1351) forbidding any one to become . gent of an jlir or Shipping company, with out the permission of the Government, also forbidding persons to load or unload cargo or passengers in Bahrain waters without permission. The proclamation was issued on 24th October. According to a bazaar rumour s.s. ft . hme ii n was proceeding to Bahrain with cargo 1 or Bahrain and the mainland. I Various merchants in Bahrain were approached by the astern Steam navigation Company and invited to accept the Agency including Messrs. Dhamanmal Isardas, Yousuf bin jhmed Kanoo, Mustafah bin Abdul-Latif, but they all refused. Finally Messrs. Mohomed Abdul-Aziz ll-Ajaji k Bros, applied to the Government for permission to accept the Agency. Permission was refused, ij. On 27th October s.s. * hmedi' arrived. Ahout one third of her cargo was for Bahrain and about two thirds for Ojair, the Bahrain consignees were Messrs. lishendas Haridas and Messrs. lustafah bin Abdul-Latif, the first a Hindu, the second a Persian firm; the Ojair cargo-4- oargo according to the manifest was in the name of Abdul i zi; u hi al-Bassam, a Najdi merchant. All three live and trade in Bahrain. In accordance with the decision arrived at, the Director of Customs was instructed to inform the Captain of the ship that 2% duty should be paid on the Ojeir cargo failing which no cargo would be allowed to be discharged in Bahrain. II The captain refused to pay but suggested paying a co resoonding amount to be called 'bottom duty' but this suggestion was not accepted. He landed and called on me, and then lodged a complaint at the Agency. He then called on the consignees. On 28th a report on the cargo was prepared by the Director of Customs from which it appeared that the duty on the Ojair cargo was approximately Bs 8,112/-. On the same day, the Captain wrote a letter protesting against Government's prohibition to land Bahrain cargo, and applying to act as his own Agent• ^ On 29th, I had several interviews with the Captain and wrote to him suggesting that the amount of duty claimed should be provisionally lodged in Eastern Bank, in the name of H. B. M f s : olitical ..gent, who would deal with the matter on his return. 1 copy of the letter was sent to the Ojair consignee, Abdul Aziz iili Al-Bassam with a covering letter asking him to acquaint the Government if the money was lodged on which the Bahrain cargo could be discharged. m Abdul Aziz Ali al -Bassam reulied that the cargo lor Ojair was not his but belonged to the shippers.l ^' lie was informed that it was immaterial by whom the money was lodged and as soon as it was deposited the Bahrain oargo oould be landed. He replied that he would wire to the owner of the cargo and inform Government on receipt of reply. me 1 1 • On 30th the Captain informed/by letter that he had orders to proceed to Ojair with all the cargo. He enquired whether the Bahrain Government objected to his leaving and was informed that neither now nor at any time did the 3 hrain Government object to his le ving the iort. In the same letter he stated that tae 'Representative of Ojair' had arrived and was prepared to pay the deposit in the name of King Ibn Saoud. (6- On 30th, Shaikh Mohomed al-rTawil arrived from Hassa and, I understand, made a personal protest to M. K. Sheikh Hamad at the boat being held up. (&lt; \ Today I have heard that the boat is proceeding to Res Tanura where she will discharge her Ojair cargo. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your Obedi nt Servant, .dviser to the Government.{ITISII INDIA STEAM NAVIGATION Co., LTD. 4 ( INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND. ) BOMBAY, 26th Octol)®-1 93 tyhic Address:- ( p ost Box N o. 122.) I ackinnons.' The Politioal Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrein. . Sir, Overside delivery at Bahrein. ¥e have the honour to acknowledge receipt of and thank you for your Confidential letters ]Joa.702/S and 776/S of 20th ultimo and 14th instant, in connection with the overside delivery of cargo at Bahrein. This matter is at present under correspondence with this Company's Managing Agents in Calcutta, and we shall write you fully shortly. Ve have the honour to be. Sir, Your obedient servants, P 4 CO. JJ in0iniBU8Hi^ r RE8IDiNCY._ Teler&lt;-«m:- I.w.0. / No:- 182. 'TSfiiHl: Dated:- 12-11-1932. F^ors:- Politic 0 ! To:- Gomniissioiie^ in Siiid.K. o ^chi. Grateful if ynu could post following to kackinnons .Bombay,with, oopy to I^ckiniions JvPr^chi. Begins- lours letter 7th Koveraber to Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. 'Ghsrtering ST )eci«l vessels' 1 -'ofe^ed to steamers only as State has no check on movements of country c^aft proceeding direct. If limit 4000 b^gs c-e^tes difficulty Stste will agree to smaller amount convenient to you. Q nnf ident i-'i-l . No:0/183. Political Agency Bahrain,the 13th November 1932 Oopy forwarded to:- The Secretary to the tn&lt; i oeu'coaiv /■ Hon'ble the Political Resident in tVip. Persian Gulf.Bushi' 'in the Persian ^df,Bushire. for information with reference tc/Messrs kackinnon, Mackenzie &amp; Go's letter of vd Vth 'ovembe- 1932 to the address of the Hon'hle the Political Resident,with copy to this Agency. Political Agent, Bahrain..■ ' ■ - , : - • •/.M {ITISII INDIA STEAM NAVIGATION Co., l/n&gt;. ( INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND. ) pqmRAY 193 2 . f aphic Address:— ( post Box No. 122.) ' C, ^' NS ' BY AIR MAIL. ilYATB AKD COHgniSlITIAI.. Tlie Hon'tie T '' :ie jPolitical Resident in the Persian Gulf, Britisli Residency, &amp; Consulate-General, Vj ? v &gt; ^ . r BU8HIRE ftESOSNCY^ \ Sir» Hit /f OOHHOiHTiAi- l OTOaXDB DELIVERY AT BAHREIN, ~~ We have the honour to refer to yoxir letters H ob . 70S-S and 776-8 of 20th Septeaber and 14th October last reepeetively, acknowledged in our letter of 26th ultimo ^ In the first of your above mentioned letter®you stated your understanding of the position to be that this Company did not fear country craft competition. This hardly represents the pre sent state of affairs and while the following reiflarks may be ua- necessary in view of your later advices we set them out for your information. Oj . The competition which is being experienced from country craft between all ports of call on this Company's Persian Guli Services is most serious. These crafts manned by a few men are under no obligation to conform to Government rules, their upkeep la practically negligible, ami they pay little in the way of dues at ports of call* In these days when they can find, no lucrative employment in fishing, etc., the crews are willing to accept cargoes at rates which grant them a bare living and are naturally exploited by shipper®. Against this competition the British India Company has to reduce rates of freight to, in many cases, a level below economic working point. In the case of certain commodities the Company are unable to compete at all. These boats also land cargoes at points where the Company cannot do so. for various reasons, and are an ever increasing menace. u It will therefore be seen that country craft opposition cannot be lightly dismissed and is as serious as the opposition-2- of the smaller SteaaiBhip Companies, and if we are faced with the grant by the latter of delivery of mainland cargo either direct at mainland ports or outside Bahrein Territorial water limits you will realize how serious the Company^ position ■becomes. There is no doubt that this matter has arisen through the increasing charges levied on cargo by the Bahrein Govern ment. These charges have reached such a level that they have driven cargoes along cheaper avenues. We ^in Bombay, are faced with the same problem. In Bombay there are all facilities for handling cargo, good docks, etc. These facilities have to be paid for but, with the fall in values, cargoes have been directed to ports e.g., in Kathiawar, inhere, while few faci lities exist, charges are negligible. / You also informed us that the Bahrein State may be atle to take certain retaliatory measures against tkose of our competitors shipping direct to the mainland or granting over side delivery outside Bahrein Territorial waters. We must say that me are doubtful to what extent retaliatory measures such as those indicated will assist this Company. The number of smaller Steamship lines today is such that the exclusion 01 one from any trading benefits will bring forward another. The principaa shippers interested in the Hejd trade are Messrs El- marzook and S .A.Bassam and if they are determined to ship to the mainland direct they will find means of doing so. To our mind the better method of retaining the traffic for carriage via Bahrein is to win over these shippers. 1 Here we would refer to your letter of 14th ultimo, in which you set forth the conditions under which the Bahrein Government are prepared to grant overside delivery of csxgo intended for mainland ports. We repeat these conditions in abstract Consighments Zll TS^e^an^OOO-3- &gt; ,(e Consignments must be marked W R.E H , termf^li^te^rged 6 ' 60 * 6hil&gt;ment6 t 41636 2^ transhipment dues on the value of cargo and must refrain from, (a) chartering special vessels for carrying cargo direct to the mainland and (b) taking delivery of cargo overside outside Bahrein Territorial s?ater^, ^ There is one of the conditions above to which we wish to draw your attention viz 'Shippers agreeing to effect shipments under these terms must fefrain from chartering special vessels.« We take it that, in framing this condition, the Bahrein Government had in mind not only such vessels as the Q»nd intended to 'Ahmedi'^'Pagervik M but also^include country craft. We shall, however, be obliged if you will advise us the exact meaning to be applied to the word 'special vessels'. q . You will realise from our previous remarks that country craft competition is a serious matter to this Company and, if shippers interested could be persuaded to confine their cargo to this Company's vessels, it would be greatly to the advantage of the Bahrein Government as well as to the Company. I p Por some time the Bahrein Government have permitted direct transhipment from one country boat to another in Terri torial waters at a transhipment charge of 2^ on the value of the goods transferred. It seems to us that some inducement should be offered shippers by regular Steamship Companies to confine their shipments by these Companies, especially as the condi tions set out above demand minimum shipments of 4,000 bags. Such a stipulation is not made in the case of country craft and we therefore suggest that the Bahrein Government might consider a charge of ad valorem only on shipments by regular Steam ship Lines against 2^ in the case of country craft. \ v &gt; yjf e feel sure you will realise that it is essential to keep the transhipment charge as low as possible in an endeavour-4- % l '\ to persuade shippers iat.eres'ted In csirgoes for th.e mainland to ship all their cargo via Bahrein. \ f lr.We would advise that we hive made no suggestion on the above lines to shippers but are doing our utzoost to persuade them to accept tjie terms as laid down atoove. Mr.Bassam, whom we have interviewed here, is, we heliev«, considering the conditions favourably and is referring to his Karachi and Bahrein Agents; Mr.Blmarzook is being inter viewed by the Company^ Karachi Agents and we shall be in a position to advise you the result of these negotiations later. ^ In conclusion, we have to thank you for the consideration you have shown in regard to the interests of this Company. We would again assure you that it is our desire to work in co-operation with you on all matters within your sphere of action and we trust that an agreement^satis factory to all concerned will be reached as a result of your efforts. We have the honour to be. Sir, Your obedient servants. JMasC AGENTS ,; '■*19/212 Telegram Iton E 30 • H.M*s Charge d 1 Affaires, Jedda. Secretary of State for foreign Affairs, London. No. 208. To Eepeated to Government of India, Poreign and Political Government of India's telegram No 2267 to India Office. Sandi-Ara'b Government have now raised issue of Bahrain dues on has is of incident of November 1st when British ship apparently had to unload cargo on mainland. Despatch follows. Department, Mew Delhi. No. 40. Political Eesident, Busrhire, No. 266 Dated 19th received 20th November 1932. Charge d*Affaires o'/'* ,11 a 91? from J)iary ^o. dated 19th .woveia'ber 19,52, ■ rora the Political Agent, liahrain. ★ Ar * ^ ^ NKJT) NEW S. (,445). it is reported that Muhammad al 'rawwil, the Director of Custoais at (^atif, is building a customs shed at Has Tan our a and that arrangements have been made to call there monthly \vj th direct cargo for the Mainland. This is considered to be bluff. (446.) Reference paragraph 495 of hiary uo. 20 of 1932. The .Bahrain cargo overcarried by the B.S. 'Ahmadi' has been landed at Ha-s Tanoura and it is underotaod that the uejd authorities have undertaken not to levy any customs dues on it and that ±5 ail rain consignees will be allowed to tranship it to Bali rain on payment of porterage only. A large quantity of this cargo has since reached Bahrain. f447). The S.S. 'Ahmadi' is reported to have arrived on the 14th November at Has Tanoura from Basra, to load 10,000 bags of dates. This cargo would normally have been shipped at Bahrain. * * * * * ****** * *o Gonfiaential . No :G/ I. Political Agency, Baiirain, the Soth November 1932 Wa/ i r~n/ I iiaiira i'rom, [ OONH ial The Political Bahrain. To The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.,Bushire. Sir In continuation of my letter No:C/l75 dated the 15th November 1932 I have the honour to say that the affair of the S.S 'Ahmedi' appears to have settled itself. Upon the refusal of the Bahrain Government to allow it to discharge Bahrain cargo in Bahrain,it took this cargo to Ras Tanoura,whence it was either taken to -atif or stored at Ras Tanoura. Muhammad al Tawwil,the Director of Customs for the Hasa ports,gave every facility for this and made no charge wkatever on goods that were landed,the idea being,ofcourse,to encourage such shipments in the future. Some of the merchants concerned disposed of their Banrain cargo on the mainland and others brought it to Bahrain,where they were allowed to bring it in as a special case on payment of the ordinary Customs dues. 2. The action of the State appears to have had an excellent effect. The idea appeared to have got abroad that the Bahrain Government were powerless to retaliate against anyone who injured their traae or to ta/^e oteps to defend themselves, as a result of their resolute action,however,it appears timt all iuea has been given up of sending such shipments in future, and,Abdul Aziz al Bassam, the Baiirain agent of Muhammad al ikarzuk oi Karachi,has apparently been authorised to arrange fortranshipment in lialirain waters upon payment of the EE duty of in future. This, of course, arises out ol the ne-otiauions set on foot a month ago and,if,as appears, i.-uhamcid al niarzuk has decided to give up his attempts u o one ijanrain dues tne matter has achieved a most fortunate conclusion. ine action of these shippers in sending cargo direct to Nejd waters was very strongly resented hy the whole body of public opinion in Bahrain. The bulk of the merchants realised q,uite clearly that the growth of the Mainland ports would cause them great difficulties ana tney were insistent in their demands that the Bahrain Government should do something to protect them. The Bahrain Government in addition,I believe,are reducing their khanchiya and other charges to facilitate the re-export of cargo and render any further attempts at direct shipment unlikely. I have the honour to be Sir, Your ilost Obedient Servant, (|y ' Political Agent, Bahrain.'1l Mo. 885-8 of 1952. Britisli Residency and Consulate-General, Bus hire , 30tli lovem ber 1952. From The Hon 1 hie Lieut,-Colonel T.C. fowle , Political Resident in the JPersian Gulf, To The Foreign Secretary to the Oovemment of India, Hew Delhi. Sir, With reference to correspondence ending -with r telegram Ho. 206 (Ho. 40 to the Government of India), dated 19th Hovember 1932, from His Majesty^ Minister, Jedda, to His Majesty's Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, I have the honour to suTamit the following report on the recent visit of the British steamship ••Ahmedi' t© Bahrain and the circumstances which resulted in its discharging its cargo on the mainland of Arabia. 2. On the 25th October last, Captain i ?rior, the iPoliti cal Agent, Bahrain, who had visited Bushire to confer with me on various matters, received a telegram from the Financial Adviser, Bahrain State, that the Shaikh of Bahrain had issued a proclamation on the 24th October forbidding any person to accept the local agency of shipping Sompanies with out the previous permission of the Statej that the steamship «Ahmed1 M was due on 27th October with 4000 packages for Bahrain and 7000 for Ojair, on the mainland of Arabia, and that the State refused permission for any cargo to be landed at Bahrain from the vessel.- 2 - After consulting me. Captain jprior at my request leplie^ that the State's action had been noted t and that I suggested toiat the state would be in a stronger position ii it permitted the cargo consigned to Bahrain to be landed provided a charge of 2 per cent, was paid on the cargo consigned to Ojair. 4 « The 'Ahmedi M duly arrived on 27th October, and on learning the attitude of the Bahrain government the captain of the vessel applied to the Political Agent, Bahrain, for assistance, representing that the Bahrain Gov ernment had no concern with the cargo consigned to OJairj the duty on which was payable by the consignees. Captain Prior, however, pointed out to i me that the consignees, or their agents, of the cargo consigned to Ojair lived at Bahrain. 5. The matter was urgent, there was no time to enter into lengthy arguments, especially by telegram, into the merits of the State's decision, and the main object for the moment was to enable the * Ahmedi 14 to discharge her cargo for Bahrain with the least possible delay, and continue her voyage. I suggested, therefore, as a compromise that the Bahrain Govermeut should permit the cargo for Bahrain to be discharged if the consignees of the cargo for Ojair gave the State a letter ojf guarantee to pay the 2 per cent, charges, on the understanding that the matter would be put to the arbitration of the Political Agent later. This suggestion was communicated by Captain Prior to the Bahrain Government and on the 29th October the Financial Adviser, Bahrain State, informed Captain Prior that the Bahrain Government had informed the captain of the 'Ahmedi' that it would permit the discharge of the cargo consigned to Bahrain provided the 2 per cent. charge/8./ charge ©n the cargo consigned to Ojair was lodged in the Eastern Bank, Bahrain, provisionally in the name of the Political Agent, the captain of the vessel to act as agentpf the line, using the Bahrain Landing Company (a subsidiary of the British India Company) for discharging the cargo for Bahrain. This latter proviso was presumably in order that the letter of their proclamation of 24th October might be carried out. Captain Prior then left for Bahrain, and on his arrival there informed me that the 'Ahmedi* had left Bahrain before his arrival without discharging any cargo, ^ which it carried to Has Tanura, on the mainland, and dis charged there. 6, On the 1st lovember i telegraphed to the Political Agent, Bahrain, that the Bahrain Government should not with out prior reference to me issue a notification refusing steamers, which carry cargo to the mainland, permission to discharge cargo at Bahrain* The case of the M Ahmedi' was an isolated one and the compromise suggested by me (vide paragraph 5 above) was in order to avoid delay to the steamer without binding the State in any way. The Bahrain Government proclamation of 24th October (a summary of which is given in paragraph 7 of letter Ho. 673/3, dated 31st October 1932, from the Financial Adviser, Bahrain, copy enclosed) did not in itself offer ground for protest by either shipping interests or the Saudi Arab Government. A general notification, however, on the lines of the first sentence of this paragraph might, in my opinion, have furnished ground for protest, and this 1 was anxious to prevent. 7. Since drafting the above I have received a letter from the Political Agent, Bahrain,—So. G/204, dated 26th Movember 1932,—a copy of which I enclose, reporting the method of disposal of the Bahrain cargo landed at Has Tanura.- 4 - jV'i ®* ouc±i are the facts connected with the recent visit of the 'Ahmedi' to Balirain. I shall coraroent on them further on receipt of copy of the despatch promised in the Jedda telegram referred to in paragraph 1 above. I am seeding copies of this despatch to His (X) Majesty^ Secretary of state for India and Mis Majesty's &lt; jP Minister t Jedda« I have the honour to he, 'L sir. ' 5four most obedient servant, _5L Lieut.-Colonel, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. // Copy forwarded to the Political Agent, .Bahrain, for information. order. 1 nt Confidential Assistant,COPY SENT TO. H ah n. - mr. Oils {{iff5^ OONFtDlNTiAl REQOflO^ FOSKIOI? CPPICK, ^ SoWolo 4th Kovealserj 1932 0 SI* 8 ! fi^ )C ?lth reference to India Oftie© letters P.S.6098/38 of y. the 8th October anfl ^.S D 6179/32 of the 11th October, I aa directed by Se«?&gt;retary Sir John Simon to inform you that he concurs in the opinion of the Goveraiaent of India and the Political Resident in the Persian Oulf that the question of the payment of transit duty at Bahrein on good© destined for the dominion® of King Ibn 8aud and transhipped off Bahrein dl rect into lighters without landing should not in present circuia stance a be taken up with the Oovemiacnt Baudi Arabia „ ana that the contemplated communication should not be isade to Kins Ibn Saud regnrding the proposed withdrawal of the so-oolXed 1920 concession® 8e The secretary of State understands» as a result of semi -official discussion with meters of the India Office, that Secretarr &amp;smmllioare is prepare^ to accept this view® 8 0 A eo &gt;y of this letter is being sent to the Ool®ni®l Office. ^ I m* Sirs Yqup obedient Ber^e^ti) (Sii.) W. RENDEL. I&amp;ep-Secretary Stat© P OlTice. Copy sent to Batirain under P.L.No. 896-S dated 2nd December 1932. IC^'00NFID2HTIAL, il M No, 0-44 of 1932, Office of the Political lesident in the Persian Gulf, Gajap, Bahrain, dated 10th Decembe- 1932. Subject Bahrain transit t^-ade. Sir, I have the hdiou' 1 * to ^efe 1 * to co^^spondence ending with my despatch No* 885-S, of 30th lovemhe^ 1932j tojthe Government of India on the above subject. 2. You will ^emember that we discussed this matter with Mr, Belg'-ave, the Financial Advise^ to the Bahrain State, during my present visit to Bahrain. By far the g^eate^* part of the revenue of the State is derived from customs dues, and of these dues a conside^ble fraction is represented by transit dues taken on goods destined fo~ the mainland, i.e. Saudi Arabia, The question of the concession in the matter of transit dues given to His Majesty Ibn Saud by the late Shaikh Isa was dealt with in my despatch Ho, 687-S, of 20th Sept- - ember 1932, to the Government of India, and this aspect has been solved by the decision of H, M's. Government to inform Ibn Saud that the concession is definitely at an end ( vide Foreign Office letter Ho. 3.4829/316/^5 of 12th October 1932, to the India Office, copy sent to you unde- this office P.L. No. 809 -3 of 26th Octobe- 1932;. Transit dues, therefo-e, on goods delivered overside f&gt;-om steamers in Bahrain wate-s will have to be paid. (Ove-- -side delivery from dhow to dhow was never covered by the concession) The Political Agent, Bahrain, ■ 1 yp^ j ^ concession)• This decision has not been cosuaunicated I 1 Ihn J and fo' v * the reasons given in my t ele^ara^o i* 6th October 1932 to the Gove^ment of India, with which the Government of India and H.M's, Government concurred ^jv (vide Government of India telegram Ho. 2267, of 10th October ^1932, and foreign Office letter of 4th November 1932 to India Office). If, howeve w , the Saudi Arabian Govem- -ment '^aise the question this decision will presumably be communicated to them. 3. -Another threat has, however, arisen to Bahndn^s transit trade, which takes various fo w ms. (a) - Small, Specially chartered, steamers may carry cargo''both lor Bahrain and the mainland, unload the farmer at Bahrain, and takS the latter on to Saudi Arabia, thus evading the'transit dues ( 'Ahmedi* case, my despatch to Government of'India No. 885-S of 36th November 1932. and 'FagerVick' case, my- despatch No. 687-8 of 20th September 1932 to Government of India). (b) 0^ sueth steamers may give overside delivery outside Bahrain waters and thus fon;e the British* In^ia Steam Navigation Oompanv to follow suit ipara- -graph 3 of my despatch Ko. oo7-S). , ( q )Or these steamers may make dire'ct voyages to the mainland without calling at Bahrain at, all. (d) Or country cmft (dhows)'may infulge in any ' combination of activities under (a), (b) and (0) vide S-itish India Steam Ilavlotion company's letter of 7th November 1932 to me (copy attached,. 4 # With regard to (a). •■*0 opinion, and Mr. Belgrave agreed, that muxns — #iile as an isolated instance — the action of the State in regard to the 'Ahmedi' could be justified, (Mohammed Marzuk, for instance, the principil shipper of the mainland cargo in the 'Ahmedi 1 , deliberately broke the agreement with Captain i^ior mentioned tjK i n m y despatch to the Government of India, Ho. of h 14th Qotober 1932), this action could not be adopted as a general policy. H, therefore, another vessel in , h similar circumstances wishes to land cargo at at some time in the future, it will have to be allowed to do ?o. Phis \I3 ihis will not involTe much 'loss of face'' on the part of the State, as the notice it has issued in this connection, see •- w • paragraph 7 of Financial Advisees letter to Captain Prior, ilo. 676/3 of 31st October 1932, merely '••eiterates the general and theoretical ^i ^ht, which presumably eve^y Goy- -ernment possesses, of controlling the unloading of ca^go in its own waters. 5» With ^egard to (b), (c) and (d) we we^e agreed that P^ima facie it was difficult to see what political or adrain- -ist^ative action the State could take, and Mr, Belg^ave was inclined to conou»* in this opinion. The only line for the State to pursue would seem to be, somehow o^ other, to make it woHh while for the traders concerned to use Bahrain as a transit poH. There a^e some suggest- -ions to this effect in the British India Steam Navigat- -ion* Company 1 s letter to me of 7th November. I would be grateful if you would discuss the matter with Mr, Belg^aye and let me have your views in dug oourse. I have the honour to be, t Sir, low most obedient servant, Lieut-Col., Political le si dent in the Persian Gulf.Ic^nA india offi whitehall, 454 1^1 Me Under Secretary of Stat Political Department, India Office, London, S. W. 1. london, s.w. 1. 7 A700/3? 77] Mth November 1932 ■noom Sir I am airected by the Secretary of State for India to acknowledge receipt of your letter of the 4th November, No. ^•5285/316/25, on the subject of the Bahrein transit uues, ana to say that he concurs In the course of action taerein suggested by sir John Simon. 2. A copy of this letter is being sent to the Colonial Office, I am, Sir Your obedient Servant (Sd.) J.c. Walton Codv forwarded to til© PoliticalAgent, Bahrain w . -rv T n-1 it ^ /1 O /^O under P.L.N0.914-S of 16/12/32 p e Under Secretary FOREIGNzyj/j. PfESIDKNCV. bn vi &amp;rr Oil* j , OOKfl^VTiAL «£00fi0S. ] fc.«r ^7 , p + £ ran foo^ 0 '^ le ' t ' tei&gt; ^ 0 * wll dated 9th. bhaban v Ln, uec, 1932 ; fVom nis excellency ohaikh namad bin isa ai Knalira, ueputy Kuler, rsahrain addressed to jjieut.. uolonel i'• C• w♦ rowle, Political rtesident in the Persian Gulf. After Compliments, ± beg to inform iour Jiixcellency that on 24th. tjaraadi al Awal 1351 (24th, uctober 1932 a proclamation was issued by the tjovernment of cahrain under wo. 28 in connection with transhipment of cargo and it was mentioned in article 2 in the said proclamation that nobody is allowed to tranship cargo from one boat to another or from the steamer to another boat, within the popt limits -tftrtrf- of rsahrain without getting a permission from the acup-t. x'o-day two boats arrived from casra with cargo and transhipped the loads to three boats belonging to c^atif within the port limits of Bahrain near the shore. This is prohibited and they had no permission to do so. consequently the Port Officer was asked to arrest them, xhe owners of the cargo are foreigners and they are living in Bahrain. Since this sort of practice is harmful to our country i beg your excellency''s assistance to put a stop to this and to punish those persons who have done this, usual ending. n.H $0,915-3 of 1932. British Residency &amp; Consulate-General, Bushire, the 16th December 1932. 3' A copy of the undermentioned paper is forwarded to the Political Agent, Bahrain, for information and dis cussion with His Excellency the Shaikh. . By Order. / ^ for necretary to the Political Resident in . the Persian Gulf. f}. 4-^' Translation of letter JSo. flil dated 9th Shaban (8th December 1932) from His Excellency Shaikh Hamad bin Isa al Khalifa, Deputy Ruler, Bahrain, addressed to Lieut. Colonel T.C.W.Fowle, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. ' / ■ itl/ift Telegram g.t.c. ^ 1 ^ Politics 1 Kesiaent, isusiiire# Political Agent, isahrain, lo 856. Dated the 2ist December i952. lext of saudi Governinent 1 s protest in regard to ••Anaiedi' incident has now been received, Saudi aoverximent enquires ^a) attitade of uritish (ioverninent in regard to inciaent. what arrangements can be made in near future to avoid recurrence. ic) what permanent arrangement can be rnacie for mutually satisfactory settlement of transit dues question. ele,rer.te ^ A pr esume .oanrain (iovern- ment agrees with our views contained in paragraph 4 ol my letter of 10th December no 0»^4. &gt;— 5, 1 propose suggesting that with reference to both (bj and (c) niskajesty's ciovernment should ask jaaudi Government to send representative for ins- tance / Muhammad Tawwil^to jsahrain to discuss question with jsahrain Government with a view to amicable settle ment. 4. Please let me have ypur views by next mail after consulting Bahrain Government. -RhiSiDi^T-X t4 glTISII INDIA STEAM NAVIGATION Co., LTD. ( INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND. ) jgy gATg &amp; COH FIDBITTIAL paphic Address:— MACKINNONS. v AIR MAIL The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, British Residency, Bushire. S 1 r, We have the honour to confirm our telegram date readings* 'Anxiously await reply our private Confidential letter 7th November especially regarding transit &lt; ♦ duty.* I Th® only reply which we have received with regard to the points raised in our Private and Confidential letter of 7th ultimo :.s in respect of the interpretation placed on the words 'chartering special vessels 11 conveyed to us in a telegram received from the Political Agent, Bahrein, dated 12th November last, despatched through the Commissioner in Sind. * iV P' * ■ &gt; We are very anxious to learn whether it has been possible to persuade the Bfthrein Government to concede some concession to the Ocean Lines over that granted to the small craft and accept transit iuty of 1 percent in the case of the former vessels, especially in rtew of the fact that the Bahrein Government stipulate for shipments Jf not less than 4000 bags per steamer whether shipped on account of Mie or more merchants. When Captain Prior passed through Bombay recently we had the pleasure of an interview with him, during which he advised us that the B&amp;hrein Government would be agreeable to grant the concession of pay- Bent of transit duty on cargo for the mainland whether this cargo is transhipped in territorial waters direct from an Ocean steamer to country craft for the mainland or whether it is landed in Bahrein and Iftter transferred to the mainland. In the latter case, while merchants Kmld originally pay the ordinary Bahrein dues, they would receive a refund on the cargo shipped to the mainland, leaving the nett amount Payable to the Bahrein Government on this class of cargo at an amount bivalent to the transit duty on the c.i.f. value. BQMBAY J 19th D6cemben Q3 2. 1 1/7 \2. V Z7| We shall be glad to learn whether this concession will be allowed to the merchants. We have the honour to be, Sir, Your obedient Servants, Agents. jents * 1 ill \ Copy forwarded to Political Agent, Bahrain, under Bushire P.L. No. 965-S, dated 27th December 1932.Telegram G.T.G. J 1rciH political Agent, joaJarain, r - Lo Political resident, ±iushire. J^o ii48. Dated the ii9th anu received tne 30th December 193S Your telegram 861 23rd December, Following is text of telegram from British maia a team navigation uompany, ijombay, to their Bahrain agents. Begins, 'is jsahrain Government prepared to graxit concession pay ment of transit duties on mainland cargo ooth shipped direct from ocean vessel to country craft ior oirect shipment ana on cargo landed at jjahrain for transference to mainland, later.' Ends. Bahrain Government ia considering various measures for making Bahrain a port attrac tive to steamer transit trade, but 1 think tnat it woula be unwise to announce concession as it woula remove from our hands bargain counter at meeting with aaudi representative, suggest tiiat you should inform jsntisn mdia steam navigation Uom^an^ confidentially of position and that 1 should d do so local agent teil^him that you are explaining X 11 to iiombay. jrleaee telegraph reply. -POLITICAL-u v GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, D bpaktmrnt. \Jf k&gt; express letter so despatched.] ' ^««i/ From Political Resident, Bushire. 6 To Political Agent, Bahrain, A^, 977-S of 1932. Dated 31st December Your telegram of 29th December, No.248. 2, Concession cf overside delivery in Bahrain waters on payment of transit dues and subject to certain conditions has already been agreed to by Bahrain Government and B.I. Company have been so in formed in paragraphs 2 and 3 of my letter 776 -s of 14th October. 3, Concession of payment of transit dues only on cargo landed at Bahrain and re-exported within 20 days to mainland has been enjoyed since 1920 and is nothing new. ' • ■ ' • • ■ I . \ \ ■' 4, In the circumstances I do not think that to inform I. Company in sense of paragraphs 2 and 3 above would deprive Bahrain M 'C K 1&gt; - llWsJ&amp;t —(0-1254)—24-8-31—1,00.000.1 \ V u1 -2- Under Secretary to the Political i Resident in the Persian Gulf. Bahrain Government of bargaining counter vis a vis Saudi Arab u-overnnient. (Overside delivery has already been p- (j granted in respect of cargo referred to in Ibn Jifuwi's letter of 30th June to Shaikh Hamad. See also my telegram to the Government of India, No.631 of 7th October). You may there fore reply t9 B. I» Company and inform local Agents as suggested above. 5. You may also inform them of any customs relaxations which the Bahrain Government are now prepared to make, except any general reduction in the present two per cent transit dues (if the Bahrain Government do contemplate such reduction)^ N which is a bargaining counter vis a vis the Saudi Arab Government. T. C. Fowle, Lt.-Colonel, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. ATTESTED.[CfhH^ Confidential 110 .978 -3 of 1932. British esidency &amp; Consulate-General Bushire, the Slst December 193S. f Dear Sirs, I am directed by the Honourable the Political Resident to request that you will kindly number the para graphs of your letters to him in order to facilitate reference - particularly by telegram - to separate points dealt with in different paragraphs. Political Resident was sent by you to the Political Agent, Bahrain, but there was no indication on the copy sent to this office that this had been done. It would expedite the disposal of references on the subject of Bahrain Transit Dues if you invariably sent copy to the Political Agent, Bahrain, of your communications to the Political Resident, and indicated the distribution. I am sending a copy of this letter to the Political Agent, Bahrain. 2 Copy of your letter dated 7th Hovember to the Yours faithfully. Under Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Messrs.Mackinnon Mackenzie &amp; Bo.Ltd., Agents,The British India Steam Navigation Company Limited B oi m b £■ . ■Cl/u J&amp;.ls/i &amp;&gt;. TL- V&amp;Vvv toZ. % &amp;O Jl ^) ^ tZs/~«^. 1 j -^2- . C - cma&lt; T-lf i z- y/JL-i*-- TpoJx*^ f? Ut? ^//&gt;/f!l / ^ ^ J' .c: r .-- P«R . Frankly I donU see that to answer the Bil. in the iffirmative (subject to mainfnance of present time limit'of 20 days for re-exporting mainland cargo, vide Sir Hugh Biscoe's letter 729-S of 3rd Kovember 1931) is any concession at all (except as regards tne limit of 3000 bags fixed by the Bahrain Government), or deprivation of a bargaining counter. In either case (i.e. over-side delivery or re-export) the Bahrain Government will get the transhipment duty, whldh 1= all 1 1 7 a ilMV S ^ 0 ^ In this connection see your letter 77b- v 14th October 1932 to the B.%. and para 3 of the B.I. j 4/x / '/ letter of 19th December. As regards the action suggested by the P.A. you have informed the B .I. in your telegram 860 7 of 23rd December,that the Bahrain Government are consider- 4@g their proposals. fX 4- PA ^ A? W- s f W&gt;' '</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000151_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/364</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000151</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/364</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 19/212 I (C 41) Bahrain Transit Trade'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1931/1932</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2013-12-01T00:00:35</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (271 folios)</extent><extent>File is arranged in chronological order, from earliest at beginning of the file to most recent at end.</extent><extent>A bound correspondence volume. Foliation is circled in pencil, in the top right corner of each folio. It begins on the first folio after the front cover, on number 1A, and runs through to 271, ending on the inside of the back cover.Anomalies: ff.1A-F; f.23A; f.31A; f.39A; f.44A; f.93A; f.97A; f.137A; 221A; f.230A (stored in an envelope on the reverse of f.230).</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains correspondence between various British officials and Shaikh Hamad bin Isa Al Khalifa regarding the transshipment of cargo at the port in Bahrain. Specifically, the correspondence discusses Bahrain's right to levy transit dues from Saudi Arabia on cargo transshipped at sea and cargo entering the port at Bahrain (from Saudi Arabia).The agreement that the British had pressured Shaikh Isa bin Ali Al Khalifa to make with Bin Saud in 1920 (regarding transit levies) is discussed in detail as are the attitude and actions of Bin Saud.The file also includes correspondence with the British India Steam Navigation Co. Ltd. and correspondence regarding a ship named the
                           Ahmedithat was barred from entering the port in Bahrain.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>British India Steam Navigation Company Limited</namePart></name></subject><name type="personal"><namePart>James Orton</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="personal"><namePart>Francis Warden</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="personal"><namePart>Hugh Weightman</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="family"><namePart>Āl Sa'ūd (Family)</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="family"><namePart>Āl Khalīfah (Family)</namePart></name></subject><subject><geographic>Bahrain</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Būshehr</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Customs administration</topic></subject><subject><topic>Foreign relations</topic></subject><subject><topic>National Economy</topic></subject><subject><topic>Religious conflicts</topic></subject><subject><topic>Rights of states</topic></subject><subject><topic>Arab nationalism</topic></subject><subject><topic>Social reform</topic></subject><subject><topic>Economic reform</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000151#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>