<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000166_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T18:28:35.503Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">■ Confidential* British Agency, Sharjah, Dated, the 7th June 1947. No.581.1115 To The Political Agent Bahrain Memorandum. I forward herewith a translation of a letter dated the 15th Rajah 1366(4.6.1947)addressed to me by Abdullah bin Ali al Sani T , a Kuwait subject at present residing in Dubai, which is self-explanatory. stayed a few days as the guest of Shaikh Shakhbut. While there, he applied for and obtained permission from the Shaikh to collect and export birds dung from Abu Dhabi islands. He also spoke^to the Shaikh about the possibility of granting him a concession to prospect for red oxide on his islands, but the Shaikh did not give him a definite promise that he will do so. He then approached me saying that before actively entering into negotiations with the Shaikh he wanted to know whether we had any objection to his doing so. 6 3. This man, who styles himself as a concessionnair and monopolist, is a bankrupt, of bad reputation and has no ostensible means of living. His object apparently is to obtain a concession on paper from the Shaikh of Abu Dhabi granting him the sole right to prospect for red oxide and then sell it at profit to any company that may like to take it. t understand he has been in communication with some Bahrain merchants such as K.B.Abdul Aziz al Qusaibi and Haji Khalil al Muayyad to whom he declared that he will shortly obtain the concession and enquired if they desired to be partners with him. His object, I should not doubt, is to get money from them on the account of the so-called This man recently visited Abu Dhabi where he&amp; - 2 - concession snd swallow it. Before leaving Abu Dhabi he composed a poem in praise of Shaikh Shakhbut to which he gave as wide publicity as he could in Dubai and Sharjah. There was nothing objectionable in the poem from the political point of view. 4. T shall be grateful for your orders on the subject. -Translation of letter dated 15th Rajab 1366(4*6*1947) fro© Abdullah bin Ali al Sani* , to the Residency Agent, Sharjah. After Compliments. I write to inform you that shaikh Shakhbut bin Sultan, Ruler of Abu Dhabi, has authorised me to negotiate for red oxide belonging to him on Dalmah and Sir Beni Yas islands. A* I fully understand that such a concession cannot be offered to any company without first informing the Residency Agent, Trucial Coast, I deemed it desirable to let you know about it and obtain your views on the subject. I realize that it will not be possible to make such an offer to anv but to a British company and, should the company that | holds a concession from Shaikh Sultan bin Saijr (Ruler of Sharjah) desire to take over this concession, X will have no objection to arrive at an agreement with them. I would also like to inform you that it is over * 50 years that my father had settled and carried out business in Dubai and therefore it would not look strange for me to take up such an enterprise. Usual Ending.No.c/713 political Agency, Bahrain, The 20th of June, 1947 To The Secretary to the Hon’hlo the political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain Sub j ec t;- Red Oxide Concession Nun ting Enclosed is a translation of a letter from Abdullah bin Ali al Sani* to the Residency Agent, Sharjah. Abu Dhabi to collect aid export guano from the Abu Dhabi islands. He introduced the question of getting a con cession to prospect for red oxide, but got no definite reply from the Shaikh. lie then approached the Residency Agent asking him whether the British Government had any objection to nis entering into negotiations with the Shaikh. 3. The writer of the letter is a bankrupt, of bad reputation, and has no ostensible means of living. His idea is to obtain the concession and then to hawk it around looking for the highest bid. It is suggested that the fact that interest is being displayed in red oxide possibilities in the Abu Dhabi islands be brought to the notice of the Golden Valley Ochre &amp; Oxide Company, Limited, and inquiry be made from them as to whether they are interested. if they are not, Abdullah bin Ali al Sani’ would be informed that unless he produces satisfactory evidence that he has sufficient capital to work any concession granted to him his proposal to take up such a concession cannot be approved. 2 The writer obtained permission from the Shaikh of 3d./- C.J. PELLY political Agent, Bahrain for Assistant political Agent Bahrain. NS.'•'-‘■SttiSUT X- v On 0*'- V No. 1406-S The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Political Agent, Bahrain , and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the under mentioned document(s) Persian Gulf Residency, Bahrain. Dated the 30th July, 1947 Reference to previous correspondence. Bahrain Agency Memorirndum No. 0/713 dated 20th J une, 1947. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date Residency Express Letter No. 1251-S dated the 28th June, 1947. India Office, London Express Letter No. Ext. 1514/47 dated the 23rd July, 1947. ,v\ 7 V\ 3°' A\oa r Subject Red Oxide Deposits in the Abu Dhabi Islands. nfideatial. ; receipt. ' ^ ✓ • •Date A ? . t, ) ML.© ' EXPRESS LETTER From Political Resident, Persian Gulf, Bahrain. To H.M’s Secretary of State for India London. No. 1251-S Dated the 28th June, 1947. Copy is enclosed of Bahrain memorandum No . C/713 dated the 20th June, 1947. 2. Grateful if enquiries could be made from the Golden Valley Ochre and Oxide Company Limited as to whether they are interested. If they are, it may be possible to arrange for their representative to visit these Islands next cold weather. 3. The Golden Valley Ochre and Oxide Company may be interested to know that there is now competition in this field for Consul-General, Bus ire, has received an enquiry from the Standard Tar and Asphalt Company, Lahore, recently. Sd/ A.C. Galloway, Political Resident, Persian Gulf. Attested Sd/ J.Croning, for Secretary to the Political Resident, Persian ^ulf ML.1 EXPRESS LETTER From Secretary of State for India, To Political Resident, Persian Gulf. Dated 23rd July, 1947. No. Ext 1514/47 r Reference your Exjjress Letter No. 1251-S of 28th June, 1947. Red Oxide deposits in the Abu Dhabi islands. i 2. ^atter has been taken up with Golden Valley Ochre and Oxide Company as proposed by you, and copy of their reply is forwarded herewith. Issue of the above has been duly authorised. Sd/ E.P. Donaldson. Copied ML,Ext 1514/19 The Golden Valley Ochre &amp; Oxide (Colours) Co*. Ltd Wick, Bristol. July 16th, 1947. NSK/LA F. Harrison, Esq., India Office, Whitehall, London, S.W.l. Dear Eir, enquiring whether we are interested in obtaining Red Oxide from certain further islands in the Persian Gulf, i.e. the islands of DALMAH and SUR BENI YAS belonging to the Shaikh of Abu Dhabi. We are certainly still very much interested in obtaining.further Red Oxide and will arrange for the Expedition / we are again sending out this Autumn to examine the possibilities of obtaining Red Oxide from these two islands, although the Signer hen he stayed in the Persian Gulf and visited the Shaikh of Abu Dhabi, did not get the impression there was Red Oxide deposits on these two islands. However, the matter will be carefully investigated by one of our Engineers in the Autumn. V'' We thank you for your letter of the 15th July I am, Y our s f ai thf ul 1y, 3d/ The Golden Valley Ochre &amp; Oxide (Colours Co. Ltd, _ . . / Director. Copie d ML. • ' ' :Confidential . British Agency, Sharjah. No# 1243#J115 Dated 20th December, 1947. To, The Political Agent, Bahrain. Mjb^iUBiihDUk . I enclose a copy of a letter dated the 14th December, 1947 from Mr. E.Innes Pocock in Abu Musa. 2. There is no correspondence here advising me of the Comp any .ts intention to prospect for Keh Oxide of Iron on Sir Beni Yas and Dalmah Islands. If, however, there is no political objection to his doing so, X suggest that a letter of introduction and good offices be sent fiom this office to Shaikh Shakhbut explaining Mr. pocock 1 s status and the intentions of his Company, that Mr. Pocock be advised to seek permission to prospect direct from Shai&amp;h Shakhbut. 4 # 1 understand CoBim&amp;nder Bayldon himself negotiated the Company r s present concession with the Shaikh of Sharjah. Political Officer,Trucial Confidential. Coa6t &gt; sh 6 r J 6ii * BAHRAIN RECEIPT. N a../Jr/. D a t e... $ X S'x: V GOLDKM VAMjEY OCHRE &amp; OXIEE (colours; CO.LTD. To, Bu Musa Island. 14th December ,47. The Political Cf'iieer, Trucial Coast, DHarjah. Dear Sir, Sub.iect.t- fair beni Yes end Dain.ai. XelaiiGS. I have been instructed to prospect for Red Oxide of iron on ihe Islands of i&gt;ir Beni Yas and Dalmah. I understand that you have already been advised of our intention from England,and that it is now merely a question of local arrangements. \ I should be obliged therefore if you would kindly make the necessary ari'angements with the Shaikh ttf Abu Dhabi to enable me to proceed with the work at the earliest opportunity. fours faithfully, t»a./- E.Innes Pocock. (Mining Engineer;(Ta ) n\ CONFIDENT TAT,. No. 0/ 14# The POLITICAL AGENCY BAHRAIN. 4th January 194 8 * to; The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliment: The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bahrain, and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document(s) # There are no papers in this Agency concerning the ' Company’s intention to prospect on Sir Beni yas or Dalmah islands, hj May Mr. Poeoek be given the letter of introduction suggested by the political officer, Prueial Coast? REFERENCE TO PREVIOUS CORRESPONDENCE; Description c&gt;f Enclosure. NAME &amp; DATE. ' ' ' SUBJECT. /Memorandum No, 1243.1115 dated the 20th December, 1947, from the Political Officer, True.Lai Coast, Sharjah, to the political Agent, Bahrain, with enclosure. Red Oxide. ‘ 1 ® NS.CONFIDENTIAL No.49-3 PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY BAHRAIN, the 7th January 194^ The, Political Agent, BAHRAIN MEMORANDUM Reference your Printed Letter No.C/14 dated the 4th January, 1948. 2. The Golden Valley Ochre and Oxide (Colour: Company, Limited informed His Majesty’s Government in July, 1947, that they were interested in Dalmah and Sir Beni Yas Islands and would depute one of their engineers to examine them in the autumn. Mr. Pocock being given a letter of in1^duction ; to the Shaikh of Abu Dhabi as suggested. 3 . The Political Resident has no objection to For Secretary to the Political Resident, Persian Gulf. 'LB'No. C/72. Political Agency, Bahrain. The 15th January, 1943. To The political Officer, Trucial Coast, MEMORANDUM. Reference your Memorandum No.1243.1115, dated the 20th December, 1947. 2. Che Hon’ble the political Resident has no objection to the action proposed in paragraph 3 of your memorandum under reference. 3. I enclose a copy of Residency printed Letter No.1406-3 dated the 30th July, 1947, and its enclosures for your file. Sd./- C.J. PELLY ♦ political Agent, Bahrain. ATTESTED . for Assistant political Agent, Bahrain.C o Nf t Qt vr //?£- . Tuun PLiwiAi'i GuLi 1 KLbXDLiMCY, OiM i)UAhD ii.T. NKAhChUG. 5th Peee her, li&gt; *9. I enclose herewith a note of imor action given to me by Pocock , who is -v/orl- ing the red oxide depo sits on Bu Musa and Sir bu Na’ir islands on be:iaii of the Golden Valley Ochre and Oxide Company. lie t-, ■ e that ’ n ‘ : 1 ' - Shainh of Abu rhabi for a concession io.t Arzanan island which contains oood deposits of red oxide, but that tne -shainh had siada the ii&amp;poai i] *&gt;e ^ ; ,100. i wM&amp;k i - t: v of the sale proceeds. The Shaikh had reiiarreu to him that he had been cheated by petroleum Conces sions Limited and tin t he did not intend to be ue- oriveu of his rights a,,ain. Pococn tola i e tnat so rur as he knows Arzanah is tne only one oi tne numerous Abu Dhabi islands wnich contains i eo. oxide. Indian and Kuwaiti firms are also competing for &amp; concession there. He hopes shortly to ins pect Tanb and Nabiyu Tanb though tne reports hitherto received regarding the presence o, i e-a oxide in t-.ese islands have been unfavourable. {rj . . T.E. Rogers, Esq., ^ Foreign Office, London. I am sending a copy of this letter to the British Middle East office.i 5th December, - i'iOTE HEGOHDED BY ThK POLITICAL bhbl- DEixT Oh RED OXIDE OBT^lhED i^EO^ Eli iuUSA iE4D bin EU hE’IR. The Golden Vi 1 .ey Ochre and Oxide Co : pany have already obtained EG,000 tons of red oxide from Bu ’-fuse, and Sir bu Na ’ir islands. Their target for this year is 8,000 tons and they hope to be able to obtain 5,000 tons a year iortne remaining 7 years of their concession•</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000166_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/895</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000166</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/895</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File No. 40/5. ABU DHABI RED OXIDE.'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1947/1949</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-06-18T15:50:51</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (20 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>The main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminated at the inside back cover with 20; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 1-19; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled, and are located in the same position as the main sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file discusses possible concessions for red oxide on Dalmah [Dalmā] and Sir Beni Yas [Şīr Banī Yās] Islands, which were under the jurisdiction of the Shaikh of Abu Dhabi (Shaikh Shakhbūt bin Sulṭān bin Zāyid Āl Nahyān).Included in the file is correspondence between the India Office and the Golden Valley Ochre and Oxide Company, which already holds red oxide concessions in the Persian Gulf, regarding its continued interest in expanding its concessions in the region, and making arrangements for its mining engineer at Bu Musa [Abū Mūsā] island, Eric Innes Pocock, to visit the islands and assess their potential.A series of file notes which were maintained as a record of the correspondence in the volume can be found at folios 18-19.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Golden Valley Ochre and Oxide Company Ltd</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Dalmah Island</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Sir Beni Yas</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Ferric oxide</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000166#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>