<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100045805361.0x000003_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-11T14:51:35.201Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><identifier>81055/vdc_100045805361.0x000003_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>Add MS 14056, ff 19r-123v</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100045805361.0x000003</url><physicalLocation>British Library: Oriental Manuscripts</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>Add MS 14056, ff 19r-123v</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Kitāb fī ‘ilm al-bayṭarah كتاب في علم البيطرة</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1466/1466</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-03-31T22:44:02</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>Ff. 19r-123v</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Treatise on horses compiled from the works of the Mamluk Amīr al-Sayfī Yashbak al-Faqīh al-Malikī al-Ashrafī (السيفي يشبك الفقيه الملكي الأشرفي, fl. ca 1450) and Abū Bakr al-Bayṭār (أبو بكر البيطار, for both of these names see title page, f. 19v, transcribed below). The second named authority is likely to be Abū Bakr al-Bayṭār ibn Badr al-Dīn al-Nāṣirī (أبو بكر البيطار بن بدر الدين الناصري; d. 1340/41), known as Ibn al-Mundhir (ابن المنذر), chief veterinary surgeon during the third reign of the Mamluk sultan al-Nāṣir Muḥammad Ibn Qalāwūn (الناصر محمد بن قلاوون, third reign 1310-41), author of
                           Kāmil al-ṣinā‘atayn fī al-bayṭarah wa-al-zardaqah(كامل الصناعتين في البيطارة والزردقة) also known as
                           al-Nāṣirī(الناصري). Against this assumption is the fact that the title page claims that the Abū Bakr al-Bayṭār mentioned composed his work while in the service of Sulṭān al-Malik al-Ashraf Barsbāy (بخدمه للسلطان المالكي الملك الأشرف برسباي, reg.1421-22, see f. 19v, lines 9-10).The copy was completed on Sunday 2 Dhū al-Qa‘dah 870/15 June 1466 by Muḥammad Nāṣir al-Dīn ibn al-Majlis al-‘Ālī al-Sayfī Burdbak al-Muḥammadī Ra’s Nawbat al-Nuwab al-Ẓāhirī (محمد ناصر الدين بن المجلس العالي السيفي بردبك المحمدي رأس نوبة الـنوب [؟] الظاهري, see colophon, f. 123v, transcribed below).The title page (f. 19r) gives the full title as follows:كتاب في علم البيطرةوتربية الخيل والمهارة وعلاجهموأدبهم وشيء من فن الفروسيةمما عنى بجمع ذلك الأستاذ المفننالجناب السيفي يشبك الفقيه الملكي الأشرفيعامله الله بلطفه الخفي آمينوفيه مجموع آخر يشتمل على صفة الخيولاللتي تربى وعيوبها وخواصها ومنافعهامن تأليف الأستاذ الشاطر أبو بكر البيطار بخدمهللسلطان المالكي الملك الأشرف برسباييعمده الله برحمته وما صُنف في هذا الفن مثله أبدًاBook Concerning the Science of Hippiatrics,Raising Horses and Foals, Their Treatmentand Training, and Something of the Equestrian Artfrom what was collected by that diverse masterthe Honourable al-Sayfī Yashbak al-Faqīh al-Malikī al-Ashrafī,(May God recompense him with His hidden subtlety, Amen!)containing another collection comprising the description of horsesraised, their faults, characteristics and benefits[taken] from the work of the skilful master Abū Bakr al-Bayṭār in the serviceof the regal Sulṭān al-Malik al-Ashraf Barsbāy(may God support him with his mercy). Never was such a work written on this art.Begins (f. 19v, lines 2-7):الحمد لله الذي علا بعزته على البرياتوبنا بقدرته السبع السموات وزينها بالنجومالطالعات وخلق النور والظلماتوهو الذي مد الأرض وجعل فيها رواسيوأنهارًا ومن كل الثمرات اتقن ما صنعوأحكم ما انتدع ووضع ما شاء ورفعEnds (f. 123v, lines 4-8):... و ينفع منهأيضًا أول ما يظهر أن يدهن بسمن مسخن وثنفع منه أيضًا أنيوضع عليه مرهم مما وصفنا للورم والخراج وتقود الدابة قليلًاقليلًا ولا تحمل عليها في السير ولا تتعب فإنها تكون سريعة البرزوالله أعلم وأحكم ...Colophon (f. 123v, lines 8ff, text not laid out in lines):تمت كتاب البيطرة بحمد الله وعونه على يد الفقيرإلى الله تعالى محمد ناصر الدين بن المجلس العالى السيفي بردبك المحمديرأس نوبة الـنوب (؟) الظاهرييا رب اغفر لكاتبه ولقاربهولمستمعيه ولجميع المسلمين آمينغفر الله تعالى لكاتبها ولقاربها ...والمنتفع بها ولمن دعا لكاتبها بالمغفرة ولجميع المسلمينأجمعين آمينوكان الفراغ من نسخها في يوم الأحدالمبارك ثاني شهر ذي القعدة الحرامسنة سبعين وثمانماية وحسب الله تعالىوصلى الله على سيدنا محمد وآلهوصحبه وسلم تسليمًا كثيرًا والحمد لله تعالىحسب الله تعالى ونعم الوكيلوإذا رأيت عيبًا فسد الخللا (!) فجل من لا عيب فيه وغلاالخط يبقى زمانًا بعد كاتبه وكاتب الخط تحت الأرض مدفون</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Veterinary medicine -- Early works to 1800</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100045805361.0x000003#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>