<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000117_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T09:53:17.177Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">g(fi i ^ The Political i-^ency, Kuwait. 8th February, 1949 1 D.O. No. 0/18 Dear air Rupert, Will 122/3/49 dated S8th January, 1949. 2. I think you are correct in your assumption that the Oil Company has consistently failed to comply v/ith Article 4 of the Political Agreement. This failure is partly due to the Company^ fear of offending the Shaikh, but against this it is not too much to say that on the appointment of a new G-eneral Manager, the Shaikh'makes it perfectly clear to that jjjerson that he expects all matters concerning the Company to be brought to him direct, and not through the Political iigent. It is impossible for us to insist on the operation of the Article in question so long as the Shaikh continues to bully the Oil Company in this manner and the Oil Company continues to stand for it. 3. I am sure that in the early days of the Oil Company's operation the Company avoided consulting the Political iigent on problems concerning the Company as a matter of Company policy. bcott was quite jittery about it, though Jordan, I am'glad to say, is better and does occasionally discuss cases. This policy often brings the Company into consi derable difficulty, but so long as they continue in their masochistic attitude it does not seem to me that we can take the lead in getting them out of the situation in which they now find themselves. 4. another point is that the Chief Local ^ Representative himself is an appointee of the ; Sheikh and only holds office at the Shaikh's * pleasure. We cannot expect any business which is likely to cut across the'Shaikh 1 s supposed interests to be pressed by a Chief Local Representative. I think the Oil Company are fully aware that the time has about come to terminate the services of the ^ present Chief Local Representative on account of age. When they have found a suitable man to replace him, it is possible that they will consider revising their policy and conforming to the Political Agreement. Yours sincerely, Political Resident ? Persian Gulf Residency, Bahrain.D.O.No.C/19 (b/2). The Political Agency. Kuwait. The 8th February, '49. Dear Sir Rupert, Will you please refer to correspondence ending with ray telegram No.C/24 dated 23rd November, 1948? 2. I shall be grateful to know if any advance has been made in the appointment of the Chief Local Repre sentative for Aminco. The Sheikh's Representative of the Cprapany writes on Kuwait G-overnraent note-paper asking for visas for Kuwait fpr employees of the Company. This shows that they are still sending out employees from the States to Kuwait, and does not presage any immediate departure from Kuwait in spite of the fact that the Company have no territory in which to operate. +a1so there is considerable amount of talk about the Sheikh's having granted them a piece of land on which to build offices and staff quarters on hhe spare land outside the boundary fence of Dasman. The Sheikh informs me that he has agreed to no such site, though I cannot be certain that this is a fully accurate statement. Sheikh's present a __ ween the Kuwait Oil Company and the Agency, that after the appointment of a Chief Local Representative we should find it hard indeed to make the Company conf orm to the Agreement. Whether or not we should endeavour to is not of immediate importance, what I require is an officially appointed person with whom I can deal in case of need and who by .agreement is bound to work through me in certain matters. 3 . I venture Yours sincerely H.E. Sir Rupert Hay,KCIJii. ,CSI., Political Resident, Persian Gulf Residency, Bahrain.(S' ■ - v 9 Telegram O.T.P. From Political, Kuwait./ To Prodrome, Bahrain (Please pass to Political Resident) Tel. No. C/24. Dated the 23rd November, 1948. 4** Your telegram No. 39. 2. I think we should insist on the Political iigreement being brought into operation forthwith and have a Chief Local Representative since the Company are already commencing operations and it is at this stage that matters of great political importance arise c.f. my telegram No. C/26. as reg ards Morris there is very little choice but I think it is up to the Company to suggest a name vide Clause b. We could agree to Morris if he is suggested in a temporary capacity without prejudice to any later appointment. 3. Your paragraph 2. I have discussed matter with Morris who either has not the information to give or refrains from imparting it. However, I suggest we need not pursue the matter for a while because of the hitch in the Company’s baudi negotations. = GALLOWAY — TMThe Political ii^ency Kuwait. C/39(b/16) Pebruary, 1949. Reference paragraph four of my letter No. C/18 dated 8th February, 1949. 2. I hear that the bhaikh sent for Dickaon a few days a^;o and after lon^j and lengthy talks on the weather the bhaikh informed Dickson that the Company had written to him saying that they proposed to retire him on his next birthday. The bhaikh said that he had replied saying that he was fully satisfied with Dickson's work and did not want a change. 3* I have no official intimation of the above conversation. D. bir Rupert Hay, KCl^., Col., Political Resident, Persian Gulf Residency, Bahrain.■i The Political ii^ancy, Kuwait. 28th February, 1949. (S' 0 / 40 ( 5 / 16 ) Kefaranee my letter No. (J/39 dated 26th February, 1949. 2. The Shaikh informed me yesterday that he had agreed to a further exteiision of one year to Dickson's appointment as Chief Local Kepresentative. H.L. 6iv V.K. Hay, KCIK., CSI., l^litical Resident, Persian Gulf Residency, Balirain. * TM♦ Code. Prodrome, Bahrain. Political, Kuwait. CON HDKN UAL i Kuwait Receipt f Ne 7^ Dated A&amp; 2 • tf9 Telegram From To Tel. No. 53. Dated and received 28th February, 1949. CONFIDENTIAL. £ ^ Your letter No. 0/19(5/2) dated 8th February. 2. If yousee *o objectioa please tace question of appointment of Chief Local Representative with AMINCO with head of their Kuwait Office in accordance with Foreign Office telegram No. 330 dated December 10th. If I remember rightly I gave you a copy of this for necessary action when I was at Kuwait in December. HAY5/16 Telegram O.^.P. From Political, Kuwait. To Prodrome, Bahrain. Tel. No. 53. Dated 7th March, 1949. Your telegram No. 53. I have no copy of Foreign Office telegram No. 330 but have now taken action. 2. Company were considering employment of a lawyer as Chief Local Representative but now wish to introduce Dr. William Lind Morris as Chief Local Representative. I suggest His Majesty 1 s Government’s approval may be conveyed. GALLOWAYmm Telegram O.^.P. From Prodrome, Bahraia. To Political, Kuwait. Tel. No. 66. Dated and received 10th March, 1949 Your telegram No. 53. Foreign Office telegram No. 3030 authorized me to convey unofficial approval to appoint Morris in a temporary capacity. Please convey approval accordingly if you consider ( raut ) case but if you thinK formal approval necessary please refer to me again. = HAY =Telegram From O.T.P. Political, Kuwait Prod rorae , Ba h ra i r . To Tel. No. 69. Dated 20th March, 1949. Your telegram No. 66. Morris is actiag im a temporary capacity; but I think: formal approval is desirable to accord with clause 5 of the Political Agreement. GALLOWAYTelegram 'M* 1 Cypher ' To FO 127 Repeated Saving No 7 to Kuwait. From PR Bahrain Tel No 127 Dated 23 Mar 49 Confidential. Addressedto Foreign Office Tel No 127 repeated saving to Kuwait. Ydur Tel No 330 of 1948. AMINCO have asked that MORRIS should he accepted as Chief Local Representative. Under Article 5 of the Political Agreement HMO’s approval is necessary and it appears i&gt;referable that this should be officially conveyed. May this be done ? HAY,telegram Code From Prodrome, Bahrein lo Political, Kuwait No. 93 Bated and received the 4th April, 1949. Oonficential . My telegram No. Office. Please convey His Majesty’s Govern- raenti’s* official approval of appointment of Morris as Aminco’s Chief Local Hepresentative. 127 to foreign DREDGENo. M/38(5/16) A pril 5, 1949 Sir With reference to our recent conver sation on the subject of the appointment of a °hief Local Representative for the American Independent Oil Company, I have the honour to convey to you His Majesty’s Government’s approval of your appointment in this capacity in fulfilment of Article 5 of the Political Agreement between His Majesty’s Government and the American Independent Oil Company. Your obedient servant Dr. William L Morris At INC0, Kuwait .SAVING TO Code R Confidential FROM FOREIGN OFFICE TO BAHREIN No. 162 26th March, 19H9. D.5. 0 p.m. 28th March, 1949. Repeated to Kuwait No.2 Saving C ONFIDENTIAL Addressed to Bahrein telegram No, 162 26th March , repeated for information saving to Kuwait. &gt; q Your telegram No. 127'ldated 23rd March; 1949]. [ Appointment of Morris as Aminco Chief Local Representative ^ You may convey official approval. [Copy sent to Middle East Secretariat]. CO A ^7 S'. v B B BCONFIDENTIAL. PE HSIAN GULF RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN. (122/26/49) 2nd May, 1949 . Please refer to my semi-official letter 5(122/21/49) of the 19th April which may have reached you unnumbered. It refer- * red to your let-Ger(E 2963/1531/91) of the 18th Marcfe about the question of security in the Kuwait Oil Company’s installations. 2. I have for some time bean perturbed by the failure of the Kuwait Oil Company to comply with the provisions of Article 4 of their Political Agreement which amongst other things adversely affects our influence over the Sheikh. As he can get almost anything he wants by applying direct to the oil company we have nothing to bargain with when we want something out of him such as the appointment of British advisers. 3. The first desideration is to get rid of the present Chief Local Representative, Dickson. He is now 68 and the company have for several years been trying to get rid of him but the °heikh, whose nominee he is, will not agree. The Sheikh on the 27th February informed Galloway that he had agreed - to Dickson’s appointment being extended for a further year. He is entirely in the Sheikh’s pocket, and para 7 of Audsley’s report on his visit to Kuwait gives us ample grounds for in sisting on his removal. I would call particular attention to the attitude he adopted in conversation with Audley over the proposal that 'Che company should have its own security force - a matter in which he should have supported the company’s policy ( if they have any ) and not that of the Sheikh. He was U appointed by the Sheikh under Article 6(a) of the Commercial Agreement between the Sheikh and the Company, and the Sheikh will naturally try to retain him as long as possible as he is his man and he will have no say in the appointment of his successor. There is nothing in the Political Agreement or elsewhere providing for the removal of a Chief Local Represen tative once appointed but I am of the opinion that if we were to inform both the company and the Sheikh that Dickson was persona non grata and that we refused to have any further dealings with him, the company would be compelled to recommend somebody in his place, and the Sheikh though he would no doubt ^ resist as long as possible would be forced to accept the posi- tion. ^ /£ fvU Sf/H (erf*? 4. As soon as a new Chief Local Representative has been appointed the company should be informed in writing that we expect them in future to comply strictly with Article 4 of the Political Agreement and we should tell the Sheikh, who has copies of the Agreement, that we are doing this. As pointed out in my letter ( 122/3/49) of the 28th January, a copy of which formed an enclosure to my letter under reference, the SheiKh is not compelled by the Commercial Agreement to sonduct his relations with the company through the Political Agent but chis does not affect the situation very seriously and provided the company have to reply to him through us we shall hold the whip hand. 5. ^ith regard to the presence of Kuwait police within the Kuwait Oil Company’s camps, the company have only themselves to thank for the position that has been reached. I regard it as/ B.A.B. Burrows, Esq., Foreign Office, London.as most unsatisfactory but once the company have acquiesced in their presence I cannot see that we have any right to order the Sheikh to remove them. Southwell’s screed is a miserable effort to wriggle out of the false position in which he now finds himself and shows a complete misunderstanding regarding jurisdiction. The Kuwait police can only deal with persons subject to the Sheikh’s jurisdiction, and their Commandant, Jabir al Ahmed has recently been forced to admit that he was wrong in arresting and fining a Pakistani for assaulting an Arab. The company’s police are required for dealing with persons subject to the Political Agent’s jurisdiction and should continue to perform this function whatever state of training and efficiency the State Police arrive at. Southwell’s last paragraph is typical of the attitude of the company’s management towards any approach to the Sheikh through the Political Agent - which as I have already indicated is a matter we must do our best to put right. 6. It may interest you to knww that recently when a fracas occured in the desert at some distance from Ahmedi the State Police immediately applied to the company for transport to take them to the scene of action and'intended to leave the camp entirely unprotected. Jordan mentioned this case to show that the arms discussed in my letter (122/24/49) of the 29th April were still required in spite of the presence of Kuwait police in the company’s camp. 7. Would you kindly let me know if action may be taKen on the lines proposed in paras 3 and 4 ? 8- I am sending a copy of this letter to Jackson. sd. W.R.Hay. ( Reed, under Residency Complimentary slip 122/26/49 )122/3/49 PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY, BAHRAIN 28th January, 1949. Dear Galloway, Please refer to your semi-official letter No. 0/6(31/13) of the 20th January. 2. I agree with the action you have so far ta^en. I consider we must resist to the best of our abilit/y any endeavour on the part of the Sheikh to station his own guards inside the Kuwait Oil Company’s camp. 3. As I mentioned to you at Kuwait, this case has brought to my notice the unsatisfactory position which appears to exist as in respect of communications between the Oil Company and the Sheikh. In Article 4 of the Political Agreement with the Company it is laid down that the Chief Local Representative will be responsible for the Company’s local relations with the Kuwait authorities and these local relations shall always be conducted through the Political Agent except as regards routine commercial business. The Sheikh, on the other hand, vide Article 6(a) and (b) of his Commercial Agreement with the Company, does not appear to be bound to conduct his relations with the Company through the Political Agent, although it is to be inferred that all business ordinarily will be conducted by his Official Representative with the Chief Local Represent ative. The position is much less satisfactory and much less well-defined than it is in Bahrain. 4. So far as I am aware, though I may be wrong in this, the Company have consistently failed to comply with Article 4 of the Political Agreement largely for fear of offending the Sheikh and we have with equal consistence failed to insist upon their compliance. If I am right in this supposition,would you kindly let me know if there is anything we can or should do now to put matters on a proper footing ? Yours ever, sd. W.R. Hay. Lt.Col. A.C. Galloway,CIS., QBE., Political Agent, Kuwait.C°fy far fOBlISB OFF1CS. S.tf.l. 18th Jurie, 19U9* (S 6632/1531/91) s — Avlfing out of the ratter« referred to iu your letter Ho. { 123 /^ 6 A 9 &gt; of the 2 nd May, 1949, «ad ei^eeguent dleroeetone whieh X had with you end «)ach&gt;&gt; o in the Oulf, X oohed Southwell of the Kuweit Oil wwpengr to cell the other day# 2. X told him thet Hie Hejeety’s OcYemment 1 a objectivoo in interceti;^ the’ selreB in the ielatioue heween the Oil Coi pany end the Sheith were as follows:- (i) The avoidance of political troubles so that the Corpany cem operate at its naxisauci effectiveness ^ through the eheonee of friction* (it) To eneure that the btate^ eff ire develop on proper lines, ew sin with the object )f avoidii^g political difficulties which might react on the affective*iee© of the Coqpeny** operation©. (ill) To eneure that our rirhte es regard© Jurisdiction were aintained. Thie requirement had been e phaeiced by the recent fining of a Pakistani by the State authorities when they had no Jurisdiction to do so. For the above reneojia end because there had been e tendency recently for the clauses of the Political A reement governing the relatione between the Compaiiy end the Sheikh not to be adhered to, it was desirable that there ehouid be e rotun to the position laid down by tiie Af reorient. Thie might nsean that there would be temporary diffic ulty over bringing the Shei h late lliie but we were eatiefied that there would be adventure in tills course in the long run. 3 . Southwell maintained that the Co paray had u©t in fact by«*puo 0 ed the Political Agent and that J Lt had all along been Mftfr inteatlon end^jpraatioe to keep thOLPcllHcSUAf:ent i^eraed of ti^n^otiori?J|stween the Shei'di end the Co. -puny la which the Political cat wee likely to be interertodu A difficulty, I however, wrfc that tSTwordEg of U*© Political a. reement I left core doubt a© to the kind of subject© on which it II would bo neeeseery for the Co pany to reply to any approach fro . the Sheikh through the Political Agent. | The Conpaiiy would be grateful for a closer definition ' of ©ueh eubjecte. Southwell also made the point that it would be necessary to point out to the Sheikh that Hie Majesty*e Government were now going to Insist on the letter of the Political Agreement being followed. X a reed that thie was 00 and c neider thut the best hleutenant-Coloi-el Sir Rupert liny, K.C.X. h, C.S.X., way/* • •way to do this lo that oa the iiext occaeioa whoa the Ceciimny have to reply to the tihoixh on a non routine sublet whlcsh ehou d properly be conveyed through the Political Agent 9 the latter ahould take the opportunity of pointing out to the £$helkb that in eo iiifoming him he let acting in accordance with the terras of the Political Afreet neat* 4* houthwell also nade the point that If Hie Ha jc sty*8 Oovemraent were to reassert their rights in Kuwait to ehaiiDol co. is an:icetiox4i fro® the Ootr?pany on certain subjects through them, the Sheikh might tend to counteract this by using his Kepresentotive in London, Kesip, to ca^Eaunleate with the Company in l^ondon, which he was fully entitled to do« If this were to happen, Southwell assured me, the Coqpany would c ntlnue their present practice of keepiiig us li^forsied of ©p roaches made to ther^ by Ker*®, end t Is would in proetlce osiount to consultation if any appropriate point arcs©. Southwell added that It we© the Conpany•s policy to keep in tho clooest poesible t uch with us, and he instanced his calls at the Foreign Office for ooiioulfetion both before and after hie visit to Kuwait earlier this year* 5* ?he only outstemdlng point rerasins for us to attempt son© defi itioa of the kind of subject on which we should insist that the CoTj^mny 1 # reply to on approach of the hhelkh or luitiutivo of their own should be chaiuielled throw;h us* Though the general Intention of the wwrdl.ig of the Political Agreenant is cletr, theio will iio doubt often be border»line oases between .urely routine ooi as^rcial natters and ox*es in which these is a political aspect or general aspect with which we should concern ourselves* li seems to me that a definition, which Southwaii ...shed, might be aecorapanied by a few examples to illustrate our point, ahould be attempted by you in the first place from your knowledge of the various raatters which have called for discussions between the Sheikh and the Cozipaay in recent years, and I shall be glad if *j you will let us have your views. 6* I am writing a separate letter about Dickson. y&lt;&gt;u ^ Sincerely V v (B.A.B. Burrows.)PERSONAL &amp; CONFIDENTIAL. 16th July, 1949. |^0)w r?' ,v ' |U It seems unlikely now that I shall have an opportunity of discussing Burrows’ letter E 6632/1531/91 of the 18th June about the Kuwait Oil Company’s observance of the Political Agree ment and the question of Dickson's successor, vide my letter 122/35/49 of the 2nd July. Would you kindly forward your comments on Burrows' letter to Jakins with a copy direct to Burrows ? 2. Can you think of a suitable successor for Dickson ? The only man I can think of is Jogi^ Crichton. He is on a temporary job at present at Bangkok. He has I think most of the quali ties required for the job and his lack of pre vious acquaintance of the Gulf and its personali ties will not altogether a disadvantage. /v G.N. Jackson, Esq., M.3.E., Political Agent, Kuwait.No .C/196 ($/&amp;) ■ THE POLITICAL AGEfiCY Ktn.'ATT., 96th July, 1949. Plesnc refer to Sir Rupert Hay’s letter No. 322/37/49 dated the 16th July, 1949* asking re to send you r.y corjue^ts on Burrows 1 letter No.6632/1531/91 of t^e 18th June. 2. Before attempting to define vhat cases should he channelled through ns we should first decide what are the fundamental adtnlrlstrati yc responsibilities or the Kuwait Covernr-ent and to what extent those responsibilities should be modified by the special requirements of the Kuwait Oil Company, We should also try to differentiate .between expenditure that should properly be a charge or the State revenues and expenditure that should be met from the Shaikh’s privy purse. This should not be as difficult as at first right might appear because the oil royalties have hitherto been made over to the Finarce Bepartrent of t v e Kuwait Government. 3. T v e standards c r administration of the Kuwait Government affect ■he work of the Kuwait Oil Company more or less directly In every branch of governmental ectlvlt'*, if only because sc many of the Kuwait Oil Comrany's employees live in the town of Kuwait. There is a tendency when standards of administration rerain low and the operations of oil companies are seriously affected by the deficiencies, for cil coisrsnies them selves actively to help to raise standards. The e is no objection at all to the Kuwait Oil Company’s putting their technical resources elf the disposal of the Kuwait Government, provided the Kuwait Government reet a rea sonable share of the expenditure and provided f ey do not postpone every improvement in the hope that the Kuwait Oil Company will eventually, in 4 heir own interest, undertake it for them, it should be our function to decide what are fair charges on the Kuwait - Government f s administration, what should be charges on the Shaikh’s privy purse, and to wret extent the Kuwait Oil Company should pay for the!^ own special require ments. This we can do only if these subjects are chann elled t hr pug h 11 s . 4. I wil1 take as examples esses *het have actually arisen since I took over here Arrll. Sir Burert Hay will be* able to tide! more. r first example is that of the water supply ... own. The Kuwait Dll Comp a y are interested in the *va1 ntenanco of adequate supplies heemse their The for Kuwait labour/.••••. H.G. Jakins, Esq., Political Resident, Persian Gulf, BAHRAIN.mmrn—mmmmmmmmmm tin : 2 : labour fo^ce cannot rerrain in the town without sufficient water* They alsu know that if the cirrly arrange ents for the town were at ary tir** - to break down the Kuwait Govern .Tent would immediately tr*n to them for help: and human oud nol.tti&lt;al consideratfonr would rake it inros?lble for thor* to reins© :it* Krov*’ r r, this they have, I understand, sot asido oil store ye capacity to keep a 10 days* reserve of water to root just such an enerponey* Such \ ©serves rh.oulo r cro nrcnerly ho roc.in- tavned by the Kuwait Governrent therscives, and if the Kuwait Oil Conuany arc asked to build the tanks they should at least be built at the Kuwait Covernrent*s expense. / 6. The spcooci example concerns the Kuwait Police. With the original purpose, I understa d, c ' preventing cutt’-raks of fire the Kuwait Oil Company organized a watch and ward service for work inside their camns* In the course of tire it exceeded its original functions snd became to all Intents and purposes ~ ~rivote ^olice force. Control of it h?s nrw been assumed by the Kuwait Government who have absorbed it into +v f ir regrrlar police f(•‘rco. The Kuwait Oil Company are, however, still paying the personnel. The Shaikh is bound to give the Company r.r-d its employees protection (Articles 3 p 10 of the should : think it the outset this can the new Quarantine Service. This had to be expanded to deal with f'^e increased number of ships calling here Tor the Kin alt ni l. Company. It nr3 organ- ir.ed by us in consultation with the Kuwait Govcrnrent. Control rests with ns but. the Kuweit Government are meetinp the cost of the service. rid Corjrerolei Agreement)} hut regular police bo a ch to on the revenues of the State, * is fair to say that had we been consulted from it might h^ve been arranged that way. Against be cited 7. Tr'O cases have also come to Ir.w as aoulied by subjects- certain to persons injured involving or- legal jurisdiction my notice. According to Islamic the Kuwait Tribunals to Kuwait sums are to be rrid as conrnna tion in accidents^b:' &gt; bosc held to be jk/s- resoonsib.le for the accidents. When British subjects or rrotecT.ed persons ere injured by Kuwait subjects they can claim eompensetior by proceeding in accordance with para (5) of Article 64 of the Kuwait O^cler in Council of 1949. Kuwait subjects can sue British sub jects for ConnerRation under pera (X) of the sane Article. The Political Agent is repriired by Article 89 to recognize and apply certain local customs. The Kuwait Oil Company usually settle claims out of court by ray'ng comrensatlon without rcit'ng to be sued for it. When tliev wish to recover corpensrtlon for their British protected employees injured by Xnv.aitis the 3 r do however. Early in asked the Kuwait Oil Company to double the rates of compensation. The Kuwait Oil Conrany are reported to be considering this demand; but have not consulted the Polit^ial Agent. If the Kuwait Oil Company agree to these new rates it v;ill be difficult for other British subjects to vegist them. Matters affecting the applica tion of the lav/ to all British subjects, whether employees of the Kuwait Oil Company or not, should net be dealt with % i“ A' ^ . ~hJS +■ ^ #«* Agent*s Court. have recourse to the Political Mai'ch the Shaikh's Offlcirl Pepresontative by the/....s 3 s by the Kuwait Oil Company direct with the Shaikh as jf they were routine comnercial business. The other case involving our letral jurisdiction arose out of tho control of liquor. Certain British subjects and protected persons are allowed by agreement with the Shaikh to drink alcoholic liruor in Kuwait, which is otherwise ^ry*. These privileges were not easily secured and th&amp;y were granted subject to certain conditions. The Political .Agent is responsible for seeing that these conditions are observed, and he can, if necessary enforce these conditions ageinft persons subject to his jurisdiction bv having recourse to Article 3° o' the Kuwait Ord^r in Council, the issue of a King’s ?,egulat J on under Article 8Mb), further to define the law on this noint is under consideration. The Km^dt Oii Company, however, have also been permitted by the Shaikh to import liquor. To which British subjects and protected persons they should ^transfer it is n question in which the Political Agent is Interested because ultimately he is responsible for protecting the privileges this ratter of all persons siibject to his jurisdiction, and also for seeing that the agreerent with the Shaikh is observed. Early t&gt;ls year the Km fit Oil Company referred direct to the Shaikh one tion of whether or not certain British protected persons ernloyed by them should be given Honor imported by the Company*. 8. Questions affecting labour and conditions ox' work can be quoted as further instances. The Shaikh recently instructed tho Company to dispense ps soon as possible v-ith li e services of their Iraqi artisans. A considerable number have al-eady been dirchargod. Accor- dl^g to Article 3 of the r ol1.tioal Agreement the consent of the Political Resident was rem-ired fo v their engage- ment. The wholesale dismissal of artisans of a particu lar country, one of Kuwrit’s neighbours, is likely to have repercussions on Km ait’s external relations*, end v.e should be consulted. Mr. Audsley’s report (paragraph 15) disposed that Indians employed by the Kuwait Oil Company had been denied by the Shaikh the right of free associa tion for joint cpnsulation with the manegeirent. It should be the function c the Political Agent to try to see that our views prevail in such ratters. Indeed, ary question affecting the real value of wages or the conditions work of the Company’s labour force is one in which the Political Apert is interested .if or ly because by imp-oving conditions of work v/e can do ro much tc combat co.- 'unisr* The Shaikh has not shown himself particularly enlightened in ♦Ms respect and we cernct a'ford tc have important and far-reaching questions of this nature nego tiated direct between the Company Finn the Shaikh. 9. The Kuwait Oil Company, I underrtand, do a good deal of work: for the Shaikh himrel^ such as the supply of water for his Palace, t v e laairtenmce of his air-conditioners, cars, yachts, etc., not all of which is paid for. I see no objection to their arranging direct to do private services of tc*ts na tu. e - the A*; eri cer Xnhf rt nq^pt Oi l Coi:.ns.ny’s be-^tavi'j : ir will probably rake it neccssar*’ for the Kuwait Oil Company to do r&gt;ore and more for the Shaikh but such free services should rot bo extended to governmental activHies such as road-bunding, town rater supplies, etc. \ \ If/...If t^ese latter ouestions are channelled through the Political Afent, he should be able to see that work done or the Kuwait Governront is raid for * 10. ; I am sending a copy of this letter to Burrows * r cNo.C/196 (S/M) • THE POLITICAL AGENCY KUWAIT, 26th July, 1949. Plea no refer to the second rerdprarh of Sir Rupert Hay*s letter No.122/37/49 of the 16th July, 1949 2 . If a knowledge of trabic 1 considered to be an important qualification p or this po^t, Perhaps J.B. Hov;es would be suitable. He is a fo^^pr Indian Political Service officer with 7 years experience In the Persian Gulf. He is an interpreter in Arabic. He was a candidate for the Foreign Service but withdrew his name before the interviews. The Appointments Board set up to deal with the Indian Services would, however, have his record. 3. He was employed by the Iraq Petroleum Company in Basra until a month or two ago; but resigned because, I understand, he was not employed in a post that offered scope for his capacities. This is a much more Important post than he hrd with the Iraq Petroleum Company and he might consider it. H.G. Jakins, Ksq., Political Resident, Persian Gulf, BAHRAIN.No. i-y54(5/16) ' / ' His Majesty’s Political Agent at Kuwait presents his compliments to P*A«B« BUPPOWS , Esq. , and has the honour to transmit to him the under-mentioned documents. British. .. Poli t.l C a 1.. Agency t • Kuwait Reference to previous correspondence: .&amp;&amp;th.. July..., Residency letter No, 132/37/49 July 16 Description of Enclosure. 194.9... , 1949 Name and Date. Copy of let tel 1 No. C/195(5/16T of 26th July, 1949, to H.G. Jakins, Esq., Political Resident Persian Gulf, Bahrai Subject. Relation betv/een the Sheikh of Kuwait and the Kuwait Oil Co,, 3479a 35437 (8)CtNFID&amp;ftTIAL (122/46/49) PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY BAHRAIN 9 1st September, 1949. Please refer to Jackson’s semi-official letter No. C/196(5/16)^of the 25th July about the extent to which the Kuwait Cil Company should be required to conduct their business with the Shaikh through the Chief Local Representative and the Political Agent. 2. I concur generally in Jackson’s suggestions and have nothing to add to them except that I consider that all correspondence regarding the interpretation of the company's concession or any amendments it may be desired to make in it should be conducted by the company with the Shaikh through the prescribed channels. For instance, I understand that the company require a reply from the Shaikh to their claim/t that all the Kuwait islands includ- ^ L ing Qaru Kubbar and Umm al Maradin are covered by their ^ t concession, c.f. Foreign Office despatch No. 38(£.6434/ * 1531/91) of the 27th May and its enclosures, twarrnrrit^ed * and I would suggest that a request for such a reply should be made through Dickson and the Political Agent. The Political Agent might perhaps take the opportunity of explaining to the Shaikh either orally or in writing at his discretion that this is the correct procedure under the Political Agreement and that it is proposed to follow it in future in all matters which are not 'routine commercial business'. 3. With regard to the selection of a successor for Dickson, Jackson has suggested Major J.B. Howes, C.B.E., a former Indian Political Service Officer with 7 years experience in the Persian Gulf and an excellent knowledge of Arabic, though I am not quite sure myself that he is of the type required. If! feel inclined myself to recommend Lt. Col. J. Crichton, C.I.E., who acted for a short time as Foreign Secretary to the Government of India and is at present employed temporarily by the Foreign Office at Bangkok. I have given his name to Southwell. 4. I hope we shall be able to arrange for Dickson to be replaced at any rate not later than February 1951 and if possible earlier. Dickson was nominated by the Shaikh under Article 6 of the company’s concession and there appears to be no provision either in the concession or the Political Agreement for his removal. Presumably, however, if we were to inform both the Shaikh and the company that on account of his age we no longer considered him suitable for the appoint ment, we would in the end get our way though we might en counter some resistence from the Shaikh. The next Chief Local Representative will have to be approved by us and the Shaikh is entitled to no say in his appointment. 5. I am sending a copy of this letter to Jackson. B.A.B. Burrows, Esq., Foreign Lffice, London.The Political Agency, Kuwait. No. (5/16) September, 1949. &lt;■ Dear Dir iiupert, Please refer to the enclosures to your compliraentary slips Nos. 122/45/49 and 191/5/49 dated the 1st September and the 8th September 1949 respectively. 2 The Sheikh’s alleged stipulation in the third paragraph of the Middle East Secretariat’s letter n that he must be informed of donations of this nature and has asaied that grants for educational purposes should go towards the maintenance of the Kuwait Educational Centre for Boys in Cairo' is another instance of what happens when the Kuwait Oil Company do not confine their direct dealings with the Sheikh to routine commercial business. Yours ever, 4 X H.E. Sir Rupert Hay, KCIB., CSI., Political Resident, Persian Gulf Residency, Bahrain.G.ft. Jackson, ksq. , , The Political Kuwait. WITH THE COMPLIMENTS (i HIS OF MAJESTY’S POLITICAL RESIDENCY BAHREIN, Persian gulf. 29 th October 19^9 37433—5The Persian Gulf Residency, Bahrain. 122/49/49 29th October, 1949. Please refer to my letter 122/45/49 of the 1st beptember about the channel of correspondence between the Kuwait Oil Company and the Shaikh. I enclose herewith a copy of a note I recorded after my recent visit to Kuwait. 2. Troutbeck has told me that the reduction of Noonan's post at the B.k.h.0, is under consid eration. If his services are dispensed with there he would in my opinion make an excellent Chief Local xiepresentative for the Kuwait Oil Company subject to his being fit enough to stand the climate. 3. I am sending a copy of this letter to J ackson. —/ Hs' /f. //#/ B.A.B. Burrows, msq. , The Foreign Office, London. S.W.1.COPY I understand that the Kuwait Oil Company are now endeavouring to comply with the clause in their Political Agreement which requires them to conduct their correspondence with the Shaikh through the Chief Local Representative and the Political Agent except in routine commercial matters. Mr. Jordan told me he was anxious on his own account to put matters in this respect on a proper footing. What is now required is guidance from the Political Agent to tne Company^ management regarding the subjects which should be dealt with through him both generally and as occasion arises. (w.a. hay)(E 12788/1532/91) FOREIGN OFFICE, S. 1. Uth November, 1049 CONFIDENTIAL Your letter 122/ij.5/49 of the 1st September about relations between the Sheikh of Kuwait and the Kuwait Oil Company. We have been discussing this question with Southwell. The delay has been mainly due to til Oil Company, difficulty of pinning him do™ to anything definite. The delay has been mainly due to the /i^ve Southwell the gist of Jackson* s letter 0/195(5/16) of the 25th July. He was rather indignant a, the extent of the charges against the company for dealing direct with the Sheikh on matters which they should have handled through the Political Agent. in several cases he produced what seemed to us at first sight to be good evidence that the political Agent had been kept well in the picture on various occasions, the implication of course being th^ u i we had wanted to we could at any time have arranged to convey the company^ point of view to the Sheikh ourselves and that if we allov/ed the company to go on dealing with him direct, we had only ourselves to blame. I must confess that I got the impression that in certain cases at least, the apparent lack of contact recorded by Jackson was due largely to the changes in the Political'' Agent during the time in which the Company has been in operation and to the lack of records in our files of conversations at Kuwait between the Political Agent and representatives of the company - due no doubt to undent- staffing and the press of other business. However this may be our chief anxiety is of course to see that these matters are handled in the right way in Southwell suggest s, that another part of' the difficulty has been that various branches of the comoany deal direct with the Sheikh’s administration instead of dealing through the chief local representative. That is to say, the latter with the best will in the world~could not keep the Political Agent closely informed of all the company s dealings with the Sheikh because he himself was not in a position to know about them. Southwell wishes for his own sake to make a change in this practice and to lay down that all dealings between the comoany and the local administration must be carried out through the chief local representative. This will give the latter a full picture of what is going on and will enable him to keep the Political Agent much better informed, and they ought then to be able to decide between them which matters con be dealt with direct by the company and which should be channeled^ through the Political Agent. Southwell left with me at our last conversation a memorandum of which I enclose a copy, setting out the principles on which the procedure Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Rupert Hay, K.C.I.E., BAHRAIN. /should C. S. I. ,should work* I have told him that at first sight this seems a suitable statement, provided that it is made clear to the Political Agent and the company’s representatives that the two examples given are illustrative rather than exhaustive and that a great deal of discretion must be left to those on the spot to decide between them which procedure should be used. Before this arrangement is finally brought into operation I am waiting to have a further talk v/ith Southwell about the timing. I think he would prefer that we should simply tell the Sheikh lf out of the blue ,? that this procedure is to be followed in the future in accordance with the Political Agreement. We have always thought it would be best that we should wait until there was a definite issue on which the company ought clearly to communicate to the Sheikh through the Political Agent and that the latter should then communicate the company’s views on this particular issue and at the same time explain that he was doing so in virtue of the Political Agreement which it was intended to observe strictly in the future. Southwell is now considering whether there is a current issue which it would be suitable to use in this manner. Southwell indicated to me that relations between the Sheikh and the Company were not so good as they had been, partly he thought because of some cases of faulty approach by the company’s representatives and partly because the company w e now beginning to send in bills for -work carried out for the Sheikh when the latter no doubt expected them to do it free and when he was still receiving various free services from Ai-OTQQ. Southwell also foresaw further difficulty arising from the approaching completion of the removal of the company’s offices, etc., out of Kuwait town to Ahmadi, This would considerably reduce the amount of money which Kuwait merchants and contractors would be aking out of the company for transport, etc., and would no doubt increase the demands of the population for a larger share in the royalties. Southwell also gave as his view that events in Qatar had caused a profound impression in Kuwait and that this, coupled with the difficulties referred to above, might be making the Sheikh of Kuwait more ready to seek outside advice. (This coincides closely with the view expressed by Smile Bustard about whom I am writing to jrou separately. I do not know whether he and Southwell have been in contact and if so whose original idea it was.) I asked Southwell if he meant that he thought we might now be able to succeed in having a British adviser appointed. He said he thought the conditions were much more favourable for this than they had been for a considerable time but that it might be better not bo try at the beginning to appoint a full-blown adviser with control over finance, etc., but to start with a more technical appointment, e.g. for town planning.If a suitable British expert could be appointed for some such purpose as this and was able to prove of real benefit to the Sheikh and to Kuwait without trespassing on the prerogatives of the Sheikh or the Subah family, this would be extremely useful in itself and might also pave the way for the acceptance of British advice on a larger scale. I shall be very glad of your views on Southwell’s remarks and particularly on the last paragraph. I am sure you will agree that we must look for every possible opportunity of getting the Sheikh to accept British advice of all kinds. If it is true that he is running into internal di ficulties this may well be a suitable moment for us to broach the subject with him again. I am sending a copy of this letter to Jackson at Kuv/ait. . A. B. Burrows)COPY (E 12788/153V91) MEMORANDUM THE KU ,vIT vJL CO;:. ..UT t S LJ^O X RELATIONS AT KUWAIT The Company is most anxious to arrive at a modus operandi for the conduct of its local relations at Kuwait which will be entirely satisfactory to H.M. Government and yet protect the Company from any suggestion bf discourtesy to the Ruler* The Ruler has the right to address the Company direct on all matters affecting his relations with the Company irrespective of their importance or of the degree to which H.M. Government may be interested* The Company under its Agreement with H.M. Government dated 5th March 1934* is required to conduct its local relations through the Political Agent except as regards routine commercial business* It will always be difficult to state any convenient hard and fast definition which clearly distinguishes between matters affecting local relations which should be conducted through the Political Agent, and matters which can be regarded as routine commercial business* It is felt, however, that this distinction can be made clearer by recording the more important subjects of current interest ?/hose nature requires that they be referred to the Kuwait authorities through the Political Agent. These are:- (a) major public works which include measures for the improvement of water supplies; (b) administrative matters of major importance including police measures for the safety of the Company 1 s operations* It is the wish of H.M. Government that any communication on such matters from the Company to the Kuwait authorities should be transmitted through the Political Agent and the Company is being instructed accordingly.' In matters of lesser importance, the maintenance of close liaison between the Company’s Chief Local Representative in Kuwait and the Political Agent should make it possible for appropriate decisions to be taken as each case arises* 19 th October, 1949AMERICAN iNDEPENBENT Oil, COMPANY Kuwa 1.1, T-c i n i am .Giil-f November* X9^'9 /O If His Britannic Majesty^ Political Agent Kuwait Dear Sir: This will ?? cl vise His Majesty 1 s Crovernment that Mr. James Mac Pherson, who arrived in Kuwait on November 1?, has assumed the position of Resident Vice President and General Manager of this company's local facilities on that date. In view of the impending transfer of the undersigned to other duties, the approval of His Majesty's G-overnment is repuested for the designation by this company of Mr. Mac Pherson as Chief Local Representative. Yours very truly, William L. Morris4o No.11/174(6/16) Political Agency, Kuwait. November 21, 1949. Sir, I have to acknowledge the receipt of your letter of November 19 which is receiving attention. Yours faithfully, H.G. Jakins. Dr. William L. Morris, American Independent Oil Company, Kuwait.telegram From To ■Repeated OTP Political, Kuwait Prodrome Bahrain j0 (£ r\ [ ^ Prodrome London (for iuformation) (telno 105) No. 264 Dated Lhe 22nd November, 1949 Foreign Office telno 162. James McPherson arrived here on November 17 and assumed position of Resident Vice President and General Manager of American Independent ^il Company. 2. Company has now applied for approval of His Majesty’s Government to his designation as Chief Local Hepresentative in accordanee with terms of paragraph 5 of the Political Agreement. JAKINSPERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY BAHRAIN,' 12th November, 1949. (122/52/49) ■i? , &gt;/. Uj I should be grateful for your early comments on Burrows' letter E 12788/1531/91 of the 4th November which was copied to Jackson, about relations between the Shaikh of Kuv/ait and the Kuwait Cil Company. I enclose a copy of a letter I have written to Felly, as Bahrain experience should assist us in laying down the principles to be followed in Kuwait. H. G. Jakins, Esq., Political Agent, Kuwait.W m**r' m PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY BAHRAIN, 12th November, 1949. CONFIDENTIAL (122/51/49) As you probably know, some of our troubles in Kuwait have been due to the fact that the Kuwait Cil Company have not been dealing with the Shaikh through the Chief Local Representative and the Political Agent as they are bound to do under their Political Agreement except as regards routine commercial business. I enclose a copy of a memorandum prepared by Southwell for the guidance of the local manager setting out the principles on which the procedure should work. I have been asked for my comments and shall of course consult the Political Agent, Kuwait. I should, however, be grateful if you could kindly let me have a note showing how the procedure works in Bahrain. The only correspondence passed by the Bahrain Petroleum Company through the Chief Local Representative and the Political Agent to the Shaikh which I have seen during recent months has, if I remember rightly, been concerned with sea-bed matters. Can you give examples of other subjects which have been dealt with in this manner? Apart from formal correspondence, are the company in the habit of discussing direct with the Shaikh or his officers without your being present matters which do not fall under the head of routine commerdial business? 2. I am sending a copy of this letter to Jakins and would be grateful if you would copy your reply to him. C.J. Pelly, Esq., C.B.E Political Agent, Bahrain.THE WM11 CIL COi.:PAI■ Y 1 S _LtCAL K: LATIU b AI. KUWAIT The Company is most anxious to arrive at a modus operand! for the conduct of its local relations at Kuwait which will be entirely satisfactory to H.M, Government and yet proteet the Company from any suggestion of dis courtesy to the Ruler. The Ruler has the right to address the Company direct on all matters affecting his relations with the Company irrespective of their importance or of the degree to which H.M. Government may be interested. The Company under its Agreement with H.M. Government dated 5th March 1934, is required to conduct its local relations through the political Agent except as regards routine commercial business. It will always be difficult to state any convenient hard and fast definition which clearly distinguishes between matters affecting local relations which should be conducted through the Political Agent, and matters which can be regarded as routine commercial business. It is felt, however, that this distinction can be made clearer by recording the more important subjects of current interests whose nature requires that they be referred to the Kuwait authorities through the Political Agent. These arej- (a) major public works which include measures for the improvement of water supplies; (b) administrative matters of major importance including police measures for the safety of the Company^ operations. It is the wish of H.M. Government that any communication on such matters from the Company to the Kuwait authorities should be transmitted through the Political Agent and the Company is being instructed accordingly. In matters of lesser importance, the maintenance of close liaison between the Company's Chiel Local Representative in Kuwait and the Political Agent should make it possible for appropriate decisions to be taken as each case arises. 19th October, 1949To Political, Kuwait No. P96 Dated the ?9th received the 30th Never her, 1949 Your telegrar No. ?64. Mis liajesty's Governrrent i approve. HAY.—&lt;•« No.M/177(5/16) Politjc?l Agency, Kuweit. v Neverber 30, 1949. 3) Sir, V/ith reference to try letter No ? ! ;/174(5/16) of Noverrber PI address ed to Dr. Willi air L. Morris I am instructed to convey to you the approval of His Majesty^ Government to your appoint! ent as Chief Local Representative of the American Independent Oil Company in Kuwait. Yours faithfully, H.G. Jakins. Mr. J. MacPherson, American Indenendent Oil Kuwait. Corpany,Confidential . No. 0/279(5/16) Political Agency, Kuwait. December 1. A349. Dear Sir Rupert, Your letter No. 1PP/5P/49 of November IP. \ 1 feel it a little premature for me to express much in the way of views on Burrows* letter to you No. E ir788/1531/91 of' November 4 except to agree that changes in the Political Agent in Kuwait and inadequate staffing of this post have contributed largely to past confusion. Geographical considerations have also played their part. Oil men, particularly in the open ing of a new field, are always in a hurry to achieve their immediate aims - which are not necessarily ours — and the distance of thirty miles that separates us here is an undoubted obstacle. 3. In my first contacts with him Jordan expressed eagerness to keep me in the picture and suggested pay ing a monthly call on me to talk things over. If we can get him into the way of discussing corpany matters with freedom - to which he seems inclined - it will be of great advantage. The opening of an Agency office in ~ina al Ahmadi, which I have suggested, should heln us to keep our ear much closer to the ground. The questior of staff does however remain an over-riding consideration. If the Political Agent is tied to desk and court whatever arrangements may be made as a result of discussions with Southwell will be abortive. I hope the Department will not lose sight of the bearing of this question of staff on Kuwait policy. I entirely agree that if the company were to canalize their dealings with the Sheikh to the Chief n/V Local Representative risk of mistaken action would be much reduced and correction of past practices made easier. I notice that in the past there has been some criticism of the present chief local representative on various scores including that of his being ' the Sheikh's nan '. Jackson, I believe I am correct in saying, regarded Dickson as an the whole being a good thing and my own immediate, and admittedly brief, impression is not unfavourable. I think that if Dickson were given formal instructions, in my presence, of the company's intentions with regard to relations with the Sheikh his collaboration should be assured. He has the Sheikh's confidence and that is no mean asset narticularly if we want to tighten things up. A new isn with a change of policy might well upset the Sheikh. If there is any doubt about Dickson I should say it lies in his effectiveness and not in his probity. It is obvious that there should be a complete tie-un H.E. Sir Rupert Hay, KCIE., CSI., Political Resident, Persian Gulf, Bahrain.that ~ 2 - tie-up between ourselves and the company before present ing a M definite issue n to the Sheikh* And having once agreed on future procedure the company must ensure that their various branches are ready to, and do, auply it* 6. I doubt whether the ' population *’ will make demands for a larger share in the royalties* The company is now about to start consolidating its position but its policy as explained to me by Jordan is to see that reductions in staff fall on foreigners rather than on Kuwaitis* Individual contractors may feel the draught but they have done well and will doubtless launch out elsewhere. Aminco in the Neutral Zone claim that until they strike oil their out goings will be kept to the lowest possible level - they are for instance undertaking no housing programme at all, even their mess-rooms will be mobile. 7. I gather that the Sheikh himself - but no one else - was a little shaken over events in Qatar which were popularly interpreted as having arisen out of the Ruler’s meanness and his reluctance to meet demands for a more equitable distribution of revenue. The Sheikh here is mean but the purse-strings are held by Abdulla Salim not the Sheikh and the minor Sheikhs are not badly treated as they were in Qatar. 8. With regard to the appointment of an Adviser I think we should hasten slowly. In the course of conver sation with the Sheikh I referred to the impending arrival of our financial man. Although I was careful to use the expression n economic assistant M I thought the Sheikh looked at me very suspiciously and he said ' I suppose .| he is to spend his time going up and down the gulf n . On the other hand I am told that feeling in the town is that the changes in and additions to the staff at the Agency portend changes in the state. It seems to me that this feeling should be encouraged so that the appoint ment of an Adviser imposes itself rather than is imposed. If, too, the minor sheikhs continue to overspend their allowances ( I understand they are all very much in debt ) the Treasury might welcome an Adviser to bear the brunt of their displeasure. So that altogether the next two or three months should put the question of the adviser into much blearer perspective and us in a much better position to decide when to press for the appointment. 9. I agrtee that it would be an admirable idea to get the Sheikh to accept a town planner. But there already exists a vague plan - at least buildings are being pulled down and streets widened. The Sheikhs, too, are scrambling to lay their hands on various sites so that on the whole I don’t think the prospects of their accepting a town planner are very bright. 10. I myself do not see/the deciding of which questions should go through the Agency and which not presents any great difficulty. What constitutes routine commercial business should be clear enough and it should notnot be necessary to define specifically, for instance, that police measures are not routine corrercisl business But as I wrote above if the comany were to canalise its local relations v;ith the Sheikh through the Chief Local Representative it should not be difficult for the latter to agree with the Political Agent on which questions should be handled direct and which through ±he Agency, ► H. I m sending a copy of this note to Felly, Yours sincerely, E.G.Jakins,,Confidential Political Agency, No.C/R-545 Bahrain, 23rd November, 1949 Dear Sir Rupert In reply to your letter No.122/51/49 of the 12th November, 1949, I enclose herewith a memorandum showing how the Bahrain Petroleum Company conducts its correspondence with the local authorities. 2. I have not come across instances where the Company has discussed matters which do not fall under the head of routine commercial business with the Shaikh or his officers without my being present. I refer of course to formal discussion. There have been occasions which either the Shaikh or someone has told me about when the Shaikh has asked the Company in formally why it does not extend or hasten its operations; that sort of discussion has never been very serious nor very frequent. 3. As requested by you I am forwarding a copy of this letter and its enclosure to Jakins. Yours sincerely, Sgd. C.J. Felly. Excellency Sir Rupert Hay, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Political Resident, Persian Gulf.MEMORANDUM. The Bahrain Petroleum Company^ local relations. The Clause in the Political Agreement between His Majesty's Government and the Oil Company, by which the latter is required to conduct its local relations through the Political Agent except as re ards routine business, is fairly closely observed in Bahrein; although here, as in Kuwait, the terms of the clause have never been the subject of close definition. I would divide correspondence between the oil company and the local authorities into three categories: (1) Important matters with a political aspect, e.g., concerning the concession areas, the company*s Annual Report, and Royalty Payments. Such correspondence is invariably conducted through the Political Agent. (2) Less important matters which nevertheless have a bearing on the relations of the company with the local government, e.g., the reservation of sites for company work, the drilling of water wells by the company at the request of the local government and all correspondence with the Adviserate. Copies of such correspondence are invariably sent to the Political Agent. (3) Matters of routine correspondence (not neces sarily of a commercial nature) between the company and the local government. These wx usually comprise of correspondence about the registration of the company’s motor vehicles and the like. Such correspondence is conducted between the Company and the local authority concerned - in the case specified with the Bahrain Police.No - F/157(5/16) Confidential. His Majesty's Political Agent at Kuwait presents his compliments to dhc Eastern Dept. , and has the honour to transmit to tyiSris the undermentioned documents. , ^ v tf} British Pol-it ioa-1 • Agency-, Kuwait. S4-. Deo etaber.-XO, , 194.9... Reference to previous correspondence: Residency telno D04 Decembers to Kuwait Description of Enclosure. 3479a 35437 (8)w tx] n Clair i ,11.088/1538/9. FROk lOHEION OF FIC E TO BAliliUll^ No. 722. 26th November, 194-9. D: 7.1-5 p.ru.26th November,191-9. Repeated Saving to: Kuwait No, 7. Addresse d to Bahrein tele grain No. 722 of 26th N ovember, repeated for information Saving to Kuwait. 27 . Your telegram No, 551- [of 21-th November: Approval of kacpherson as Chief Local Representative of American Independent Oil Company]. Yes. [Copy sent to kiddle East Secretariat] mu *fKINDIA OFFICE LIBRARY and RECORDS Photocopying record Ref. No. SSL: , ICR ? Date Name Process No. of exposures 1 2 3 4 5 6 REFER T O THE SPECIALIS1 CONCERNED</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000117_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/5/268</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000117</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/5/268</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 5/16 Chief Local Representative for KOC and Aminco; relations between companies and Shaikh'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1949/1949</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-07-17T16:48:04</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (56 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence for this description commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 58; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. A previous foliation sequence, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains papers discussing the relationship between the Kuwait Oil Company, the British Political Agency in Kuwait, and the Kuwaiti Government. In particular, the papers discuss the concern by British authorities about the extent of their influence at the Kuwait Oil Company, and the extent to which the Ruler of Kuwait's authority applies to some of the Company's peripheral operations. Other papers discuss the removal and appointment of personnel in order to indirectly ensure a minimum of British influence at the Company. The latter half of the file includes papers that discuss the dismissal of Iraqi artisans at the Company, and the political repercussions of changing labour practices.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Kuwait Oil Company</namePart></name></subject><subject><topic>Petroleum industry</topic></subject><subject><topic>Labour relations</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x000117#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>