<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000182_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T05:30:43.864Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">3D/«b Telegram Q From Secretary of State for India, London. To Political Resident, Bushire. No.lObb, Dated and received 10th June 1938. *■ - ^5 Your telegram No.241 of 10th June. Copies sent to Bushire as desired. Secretary of State for India35/86 Te le gram ^ From Political Resident, -csushire. To His iiajesty's Secretary of State for India, London. No.242, Dated the 11th June 1938• I presume copies of draft Muscat treaty have been sent to -Bahrain as requested and not to Bushire as stated in your telegram ^0.1086 of the 10th June ? l]J&amp;r , 38.EBniynii i ,&gt; 35/86 Telegram Fronf Political He si dent, iiushire. To Secretary to the Goveriiment of India, JSxternal Affairs Bepartment, Simla. Hepeated to il.M's Secretary of State for India, London. Oovy by post Political Agent, Muscat. 1*0.248 Bated 13th June 1938. Demi-official . Metcalfe from Jb'owle. Your telegram -'0 . 934 of 11th June. In the circumstances best course will be for me to get translation done by my Inter- -preter. Signature copies can later be prepared in London or by Government of India after check by them# .tfowle• Copy sent to Muscat under jP«L..No. 370-S of 13.6.38By Air Mail. p.z. loiiT iV K Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy has been sent to by Mail. - -Sear I (jl5Y&gt;\ Id ?- ^ Wv-JLw p. L Ihe The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. 4963 2000 7.36 r yCANADA COMMONWEAL NEW ZEALAN UNION OF S IRELAND SOUTHERN PJ Circular d /To 1 &amp; 57 (to all)mmtm P,Z. 3198/38. Enclosure in Dominions Office Covering Letter No.T.576/19 dated 5th May, 1938. CANADA COMMONWEALTH OP AUSTRALIA NEW ZEALAND UNION OP SOUTH AFRICA IRELAND SOUTHERN RHODESIA. Circular despatch E.No.lO. Downing Street, 5th May, 19 38. /To 1 &amp; 5/ (to all) Sir, My Lord, With reference to my Circular despatch E.No.33 of the 10th September, 1937, and to my despatch No. 1 ^ of to-day^ date, I have the honour to state that, on the occasion of the renewal for a further year from the 11th February, 1938, of the Muscat Commercial Treaty of 1891, the Sultan expressed his unwillingness to agree to any further renewal after the 11th February, 1939. Advantage was accordingly taken of His Highness f s recent visit to this country to discuss with him informally the terms of a new treaty to take its place. A copy is enclosed of the draft treaty which has now been sent to His Highness as a result of the discussions. This draft is subject to further consideration on both sides, but, subject to this, it is hoped that the negotiations may be resumed with His Highness in July after his return to Muscat and that they will be concluded in time for the new treaty to be signed there during that month. I have, etc., (Sgd.) MALCOLM MAC DONALD. (p v 0- L , 7 1 -P.Z. 3199/38, 1 \ Enclosure in Dominions Office Covering Letter Ho.T*-76/18 dated 5th ay, 1338. \NAgA p. 1 '7 • ^ELAKD 3. 61. Downing Street. 5th May, 1958- Sir, 268 41 With reference to my despatch No.-=^- or the 13th July, 1937, I have the honour to transmit a copy 11.37. / of the English text of a document signed by the Sultan of Muscat and hy the Political Agent at auocat prolonging the Muscat Commercial Treaty of 1391 or a further period of one year from the 11th February, 1958. 2. This despatich is being sent to Canada 1 T o.1 t &gt;7 and Ireland No. 61. I have, etc., (Sgd.) MALCOLM MAC DONALD.Confidential G-overnment of India, ixternal .affairs Department* / 0 EXPHSSS LSTTiilR. (AIR IMIL). To The Secretary of State for India, London. Repeated Political Resident, Buahire. . -A Demi-officii]. ^ Keference your demi-official letter No.P.Z.2976/38 dated 28th April 19o8 # we have the following comments to make on the latest iraft of the Treaty:- ^T^cle 2-fcr^yaph (1,) - This Article provides for reciprocal freedom in respect of commerce and navigation. We understand that ordinarily such provision is held not to include participation in coasting trade. It is perhaps undesirable that there should be any ^uch limitation in the present case, nhether expressed or implied, is it is presumed that no Muscat vessels take part in the Indian Joasting trade whereas British and Indian vessels possibly take part in the Miscat coasting trade. We should be grateful, however, for ^owle's views on this point, 4rt4cXQ ^-Paragraph (7) - We should be glad to receive Fowle's confirmation that the charges referred to are of long standing, c.f. •aragraph 3 of Peel^ demi-official letter under reference, before / ' .ccepting the provisions of this clause. ' M h 77 (3) /- 2 - 1 1 /1 ^ticle 34 - /e would suggest the insertion of the words 'at seaport towns^ after the word 'reside*' in the third line of this Irticle. In this connection please see our demi-official No.1349-0, dated the 16th of April 1924. Though it is unlikely that the Sultan would wish to appoint a Consul at the headquarters of the Government of India and although the proviso requiring approval of the places at ?/hich ^onsul6 should reside might give us grounds for refusing for such a demand if made, it seems desirable to take the opportunity of clarifying the position by entirely preventing such a demands For 'whose nationals they may be' at the end of this Article we would suggest 'whose national he may be'. (^) Article 16 - The expression 'crime or a serious offence' seems too vague. It is presumably based on the old Treaty, vide Article 14, in which the expression was 'crime or serious offence punishable by lav/'. We would suggest that the Political Resident might attempt to find a more precise phrase in his forthcoming discussions with the Sultaiu 2» It is possible but unlikely that we may have a few more comments to make. If so^ we will inform you by telegram. The issue of the above has been authorised. Deputy Secretary to the Qovernment of India. M* 't X.—nil Demi-01 licial letter to I .D. 7akely, Esquire, Secretary, Political Department, India Office, London, 3.17.1, No.l349-a., dated the 16th April 1924. • i n Flease refer to the correspondence ending with the telegram from r is Excellency the Viceroy in the Foreign and Political Department, dated the 13th September 1923, No.1128-3., regarding the application made by the Italian G-overnment for the issue of an exequatur to an Italian Consul at Delhi. This application His Kajesty's Government were able to refuse, because the provisions of the Anglo-Italian Treaty of Commerce of 1883 were made applicable to India under a Convention (dated 15th June 1914) which itself restricts the appointment of Consular officers to seaport towns. 2, The examination of the Italian application has led the G-overnment of India to consider the position which would have to be taken up in the event of similar applications from other Powers, and to take note how far it is possible at the present day to adhere to the rule, referred to in the beginning of the telegram cited in the previous paragraph, under which Consuls in India (other than the Consul-General for Afghanistan) are confined to the seaports. The Commercial Treaties affecting India have now been scrutinised and it is thought that the conclusions arrived at may be of interest to the Secretary of State. 3. Under the Treaties concluded on the 16th February 1866, 21st November 1848 and 9th December 1856, respectively, Columbia, Liberia and Morocco possess unrestricted freedom to appoint Consular officers in any of the territories. Dominions and settlements of Great Britain. The Government of India would consequently be unable to resist a claim put forward by any of these countries lor the locaijion of Consular officers ...-2- officers at inland to'vns. Such a claim, however, is perhaps not likely oe made ana oer se this inability is not a matter of imporuance, ine same applies also to Muscat who under the treaty of 19th March 1891 possesses the ri,-ht to appoint Consular Officers in the territories of G-reat Britain wherever the interests of commerce may require the presence of such officers', 4. The rights of these unimportant Powers are based on the express provisions of their respective treaties. There is no otner rower, so far as the examination conducted by the Government of India, has revealed, which enjoys the sane ri.'-^ht ^being restricted to Burma and subject to mutual consent gives no cause ..or anxiety. But there is one Power that has a plenary and indefensible right, in virtue of the most-favoured-nation clause which finds a place in her treaty with Great Britain. That Power is P ersi a. The treaty concluded with Persia on 4th March 1857 became applicable to India immediately it was concluded, and Article IX provides that 'the high contracting parties engage that in the establishment and recognition of Consuls-General, Consuls each shall be placed in the dominions of the others on the footing of the most-favoured-nation'. Afghanistan having availed herself of her treaty rights to appoint a Consular representative at the headquarters of the Grovernment of India, a Persian claim to make a similar appoint ment could not, in the opinion of the C-overnment of India, be resisted. 5. The Persian frovernment are believed, on the strength of certain observations made by the present Persian Consul- General, to cherish some intention of seeking to put their right into exercise. 6. So far as the Grovernment of India are aware, Persia is the only Power that has most-favoured-nation rights in respect of the establishment and recognition of Consular officers as-3- contrasted 1 7ith 'facilities, privileged exemptions and immunities of every kind ' granted to them, and for that reason as well as because the enjoyment of the right to appoint Donsuls in Inoia in other cases, has been restricted by agreement, the appointment of Persian Consuls to inland towns in India need not lead to the admission of other foreign Consuls. I am to ask that this view may be confirmed./) A h* 3» r/^ Telegram From To Secretary to the Government of India External Affairs Bepartmentt Simla• ' Secretary of State for India, -London. Political K e si dent, isu shire • Repeated to ^o«936 I&gt;ated and received 12th June 1938. k / r reference paragraph 2 of foreign Express Letter ^0.^.63-^/38 dated 8th June. Muscat Treaty. We have no further comments. foreign.-&lt;£ iwwiwsssssie.iB^jasffl 3^6 Telegram From To Repeated Q Political Resident, Bu^i ire, on S.S.Varsova. Secretary to the Governne nt of India, External Affairs Department, Simla. His Majesty's Secretary of State for India, India Office, London, Copy by post to Political Agent, Muscat. No.T/131. Dated the 16th June 1938. /M Demi-official Fowle to Metcalfe. Your telegram No.946 of June 14th. My Interpreter whom I have with me is already engaged in translation. This being so I hardly think that Siddiq Hassan^ services are necessary FOWLE, ? a. p,L. M*. j 'ifTele gram ^ ^om H.M. Secretary of State for mdia, Loridon. To Governnient of India, External Affaire Depart* inent, Simla. Repeated Political Resident, i3ushire« Ho.1100 Dated 14th June received 15th June 1938^ j\ \ KM r ' following for Metcalfe from Peel. / My telegram ^0.1076 of June 8th« lauscat Treaty following is gist of Watts* comments. JJtill record follows by mail beginss ixticles l and 19 . He thinks it mould have unfortunate effect locally if subjects of Aden Protectorate and Zanzibar are deprived of benefits of British jurisdiction and is of opinion that Sultan if pressed will give way. His real interest is in subjects of Persian Gulf Sheikdoms. Article 4 . Should remain as drafted and no attempt made to press for equality of treatment as regards immovable property. Article 5 (3). In the light of difficulty experienced in the past owing to demaMs made at Muscat and Muttra for additional duty on goods which had already paid duty at some other Sultanate port, following addition suggested •there shall be no variation of customs dues in any of the ports of the Sultanate and goods once landed and duty paid thereon shall not be liable to re-assessment of duty*. Article 5 (4)(b) and (6) * Suggest that periods of 1 month and 3 months will hit merchants rather severely should be increased to 3 months and 6 months respectively. Article 6 (2) /Article 6 {2)* As drafted sub-paragraph ^2) will lead to endless trouble exactly as was experienced in the past ovei interpretation of phrase 'ready lDoneylDarket• ,, in old treaty• He would therefore press for its omission and araendment oi sub-paragraph (3) to provide that Xariff Board shall fix values for Customs purposes in all cases# He thinks Sultan would accept this. Article 6 (4&gt; « Doubts whether experts will ever agree on choice of umpire and suggests addition should be made to provide for solution in case of impasse. Article iN'o. 13 ^1) (iv). Last sentence object- -ionable on ground that it will enable Muscat State or unscrupulous persons ( by fraudulently including a Muscati national ) to take an administration or personal status case out of the hands of the consular authorities. SECRETARY OP STATE FOR HID I A. oc^jr D&gt; ■Telegram Q From His Majesty^ Secretary of State for India, London. To Governmeit of India, External Affairs Depart ment, Simla, Repeated Political Resident, Bushire, Copy by post to Political Agent, Muscat, No.1126. Dated the 17th and receivedthe ISth June 1938, Following for Metcalfe from Peel. s j* fj ~// / J Reference Fowle ! s letter No.300-S of May 28th and paragraph 3 of GovenSnt of India telegram No.926 of June 8th. Muscat Treaty. 2. Foreign Office areinclinedto think that it would be a mistake to endeavour to persuade the Sultan to concede favours which are not enjoyed by British Consular Officers elsewhere and that generally speaking our demands should be kept within limits of what our own practice regards as reasonable except where very special local conditions point something wider. As regards (a) in Fowle 1 s proposed letter to Sultan, Foreign Office point^ out that while 'free entry for all personal requirements' may be of advantage in saving government from having to compensate Consul for high cost of living, this could not be a valid reason for claiming Customs exemption and if conceded by Sultan would undoubtedly lead to similar concession for Muscati Consul. As regards (b) Foreign Office consider that there is fair groundground for asking that Consul and staff should not be deprived of enjoyment of commodities which for reasons of climate and national habit they could not forego without discomfort and possible prejudice to their health and well being and that they should therefore be permitted to import such goods in reasonable quantities without restriction. As regards (c) Foreign Office point out that in the United Kingdom,^foreign Consular Officers are not entitled to exemption from municipal taxation and except as regards income tax on their official salaries from state taxation also. SECRETARY OF STATE FOR INDIA t■J--- JLllllJH ik I s '■ I S p'/ p ^ ^A!C Y J &gt; S' . jf Ir eu^n^ ! Dato.**:!.:?' | '''confidential RECORDS I J p. Z.4044/38 lu^ INDIA OFFICE, V/HITEHALL, S.W.I. 14th June, 1938 c n / In response to your telegram of the 10th June, No. 241, I enclose herewith four spare copies of the latest draft of the Muscat Treaty. I take the opportunity to inform you of another drafting amendment which will he required if the amendments desired 'by the Sultan in Articles 1 and 19 (as noted in the margin of the draft) are accepted, in whole or in part. In this event there should he inserted in line 6 of Article 19(l) after the word 'protectorates', the words 'or to any of the States under his protection'. A copy of this letter is 'being sent to the Government of India. | i', U ~i Hon'hle Lt.Gol. Sir T.O.W.Fowle, K.G.I.E., G.B.E., c /o The Political Agent, Bahrein.By Air Mail. P.Z. V.)U. If 0 0; 'c^«.»'n r T prrr^ir^.-r^j./^Y ^ Dato..+.?.:.+.:..lt. j COM K3S!frirRa»RB3 'i ,r&gt; INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, / ^ Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy has been sent to by ^'g M ail - 4963 2000 7.36 The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.^HMUasJ S: 0 Reference ' &gt;7 . ! o r tide 1 (ii). The Sultan in the course of several conversations with me on the subject of the jurisdiction of nationals other than those defined in the 1891 treaty mentioned that he intended to press for jurisdiction over the subjects of the Persian Gulf Sheikhdoms on which he said he felt rather strongly. The procedure hitherto followed in Muscat has been somewhat variable. In numerous instances sub jects of the Persian Gulf Sheikhdoms have been sent to the Agency for trial but perhaps more often they have been tried in the Muscat Government Courts without reference to the Agency. In none of these conver sations with me did the Sultan claim jurisdiction over the subjects of the iiden Protectorate and Zanzibar. I think in the present instance this is merely a ''try on' 1 of his and in my opinion should be resisted. The Sultan never objected in the past (as of course he could not do under the terms of the 1891 treaty) to subjects of the Indian States being considered as British Subjects and it seems to me that since Zanzibar and the Aden Protectorate States are apparently in precisely similar positions to those of the Indian States that the nationals of the former should be accorded the same privilege of protection and jurisdiction over them as those of the Indian States. I think it would have an unfortunate effect in Muscat locally if people who are 3 after all? genuine British protected persons should be deprived 0° the benefits of British jurisdiction5 and my opinion is that the 3ultan ? if pressed? would drop ais claim for jurisdiction over the subjects of these States. Article 1/ L ricle 1 (iv) The above remarks will of course apply to the Sirticle 19. marginal notes of Article 1 (iv) and of Article 19. r ft ^ icle The alteration in this Article compared with the corresponding one in the old treaty is^ i think ? an excellent one in particular respect to the necessity of would-be travellers notifying the local authorities oi their intended movements in outlying parts of the Sultanate? and of failure to do so 'being at their own risk. ■ cle The effect of the first part of this Article, that f I' ^ is to say regarding conditions under which immovable property may be acquired5 will I consider result inevitably in frequent restrictions and obstacles being imposed upon British nationals. The Sultan P I know? feels strongly upon this question and imagines that British subjects have for sometime past been acquiring too much valuable property in his dominions and thereby automatically freeing themselves from any form of control by the Muscat State authorities and for that reason I do not think it will be of much use to press for complete equality in this respect with Muscati subjects as has been done as regards movable property. The latter is really the important one because British interests in Muscat are almost entirely concerned with tradej import and export, and the concession obtained from the Sultan as mentioned in the latter part of this Article I consider a very advantageous and real one since they have been put on the same footing with the netionals of the Sultan himself. It seems to me? therefore? that the Article might well be left to stand in its present form and no attempt made to press for/.. Wtfflu* A //5 \ / 3. for full equality of treatment with the Sultan nationals as regards irnmova'ble property. Lcle 5(3). During my time in Muscat I have had considerable trouble with the question of additional customs duty being levied at Muscat and Muttra on goods which have already paid duty at some port in the Sultanate where they had first been landed. The grounds for this demand put forward by the Director of Customs was that incorrect duty had been assessed at the first port. This procedure leads to serious inconvenience to merchants and of course many abuses. If at all possible ? I think it would be most advantageous to have some sort of addition made to this section whereby it would be clearly laid down that goods once landed and duty there on paid no further question of the amount paid on them at whatever port they may have been landed should be allowed to be brought up ? and I would suggest some sort of clause as the following ? which I think might meet the case - 'there shall be no variation of the customs U dues in any of the Ports of the Sultanate and goods ''once landed and the duty thereon paid shall not be 'liable to re-assessment of duty 15 . This Clause., or an addition somewhat on these lines, thought it might appear surprising in a Treaty with another Country ? would, I think5 not be objected to by the Sultan and it would have the very real advantage of saving what I feel ? from experience5 will be endless disputes and arguments on this particular point \!^ - - , I ile 5(4)(b) The period of one month will, in my opinion, hit merchants rather severely and at least three months should be allowed for the purpose. Article 5/■ 4. le 5 (6). My remarks regarding article 5 (4) ('b) also apply to tills article. In this case I think three months inadeg L uate and at least six months should 'be allowed. le S (2). This Clause I am afraid will lead to endless I ■ ! 1 trouble exactly as in the past was experienced over the interpretation of that unfortunate phrase ''Tieady money market'' in the old Treaty. mentioned in Sub Paragraph (3) of Article 6 provision has been made for the appointment of a Tariff Board and I would strongly urge that an attempt be made to delete altogether Sub- Paragraph (2) and interpose in Sub-Paragraph (3) some form of expression by which the Sultan undertakes to fix values for customs purposes solely and entirely by means of this Tariff Board. All British Indian Merchants with whom I have discussed this point were unanimous in welcoming such an institution and the Sultan himself from time to time has stated to me that the idea in principle was quite acceptable to him 9 and I think there is a good chance ? if he were pressed, to his agreeing to have all values fixed by the Board. le 6 (4) I would suggest that some sort of Clause as the following should be added to this sub-article - Should the experts be unable to agree as to the 'choice of an Umpire the decision o' p the Custom House Si Authorities shall be final 1 * I suggest this in the light of my experience in numerous cases which have occured where disputes have arisen between British subjects and the Muscat Customs Authorities. The experts who would be chosen by the two parties under this paragraph would, I am convinced, never be able te agree on any one Umpire in view of the fact that/immunity from any form of interference from Muscat Government Officials. I think the Safeguards to he laid down in the proposed confidential letter to the Sultan should provide ample safeguards in this matter. My experience is that the Omani Laws generally speaking are no more severe or onerous in their effect than the laws of British India hitherto made a .piicable to British nationals in Muscat.36/86 Telegram G,T,C. From Political Resident, busnxx-e, id , t&gt;. vary ova. To PoiiLicax, Masc&lt;xL* No.T/141. Dated the 20th June 1938, Please make local enquiries and telegrapla me c/o Post Master Karachi names and addresses of some three Indian merchants now in Karachi who have previously been in Muscat doing import business. I wish to consult them as to Muscat Customs matters. RESIDENT. 20.6.'3^.. —Telegram Q From Political Resident, Bushire, at Karachi, To Secretary to the Government of India, External Affsi rs Department, Simla, No. T/146 Dated the 24th June 1938. Muscat Treaty. Please telegraph what Customs exemptions if any are allowed by Government of India to foreign Consuls (a) de carriere (b) not de carriere. 2. Reference Article 11. In addition to insertion of words 'at seaport towns' do you see any objection to deletion of words 'and the places at which they reside ' ? '3. Deletion of these words would give (a) Sultan right to appoint Consul at any seaport ^own in India, to which Government of India would presumably not object, and (b) wuld deprive him of right to insist at any time in the future that our . Consul should reside at any seaport town other than Muscat. 4 # (b) is unlikely but if deletion were not made would be possible. FOWLE. 24.6. 1 38.T jyrnft letter from His Highneaa tue Hultan of Muscat and Oman to the Hobble the Political Resiaeiit in the Persian Gulf, .ith relerence to tne coiiveraat ion wriicn we had yesterday, I am pleased to confirm A# that the following ^oocis shall be exempted from payment of customs duess (i)goods imported for the official use of His Majesty's Consulate. (ii)good8 imported for his personal use by His Majesty *8 Consul. B. That any prohibition or restriction imposed on the importation of goods into Oftani territory shall not apply to tne goods mentioned in paragraph A (i) and (ii) ab ov e f tUut c** n-t y-uUt.36^86 Telegram Q yroni Government of India, External Affairs Department, Simla. To Secretary of State for India, London. Repeated Political Resident, Bushire, at Karachi. Copy by post Political Agent, Muscat. No.1053. Dated the 29th and received the 30th June 1938. / Following for Peel from Metcalfe. / Your telegram No.1148 of June 22nd. Muscat Treaty. Articles 1 and 19,2(1), 6(3) and 6(4). We agree. 3* Articles 6(4)(b) and 5(6) - We consider that Sultan should be pressed to accept Watts 1 suggestions. 4. Article 6(2). We would suggest that fairest basis for fixing values of goods for Customs assessment purposes would be the wholesale market price less duty and any generally recognised trage discounts and that this principle should if possible be laid down in Treaty to enable Muscat Customs Officers to decide valuations of particular articles which may not be included in Tariff Board valuations. 6. Article 13(1)(4). We are inclined to agree with your views but are examining matter further and will telegraph again if necessary. 6. Article 16. We accept suggested amendment but do not press for it if Sultan raises difficulties. 7. We would suggest that Fowle unless he has any further comments to make b© authorised immediately to discuss alterationsalterations proposed with Sultan at Karachi, ''i % «/ 8. We have no coiranents to make in alterations suggested in your telegram No.1076 of June 8th. GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. /I ■ l7 -y kfl- W ^ £/*'■ , io i hS- A-36/86 Telegram From To Repeated Q Secretary of State for India, London, Political Resident, Bushire, at Karachi. Government of India, External Affairs Department, Simla, Copy by mail Political Agent, Muscat* No.1200. Dated the 30th June and received the 1st July B 38. / ,^3 Fowle from Peel, / / Reference my telegrams No.1076 of June 8th and 1148 of June 22nd and Ji/etcalfe's telegram No. 1063 of June 2Sth. Unless you have any further comments please discuss proposed alterations with Sultan including amended Article 6(2) on lines desired by Government of India and report results. Reference Government of India No.1060 of June 29th Consular privilegeV Please proceed on lines indicated therein unless you see any objection / / / / 40 SECRET® Y OF STATE FOR INDIA. ,.^S8.Draft letter from His Highness the Sultan of Muscat and Oman to the Hobble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, With reference to the conversation which we had on the 1st July 1938| I am pleased to confirm A. that the following Joods shall be exempted from payment of customs dues : (i)goods imported for the official use of His Majesty^ Consulate, (ii)goods imported for his personal use by His Majesty's Consul. B. That any prohibition or restriction imposed on the importation of goods into Omani territory will not apjhly to alcoholic liquors and tobaocoi and arms to the extent of two guns| two rifles and two pistols or revolvers and ammunition therefori imported by His Majesty's Consul for his personal use.b Telegram Q From Political Resident, Bushire. To Government of India, External Affairs Department, Simla. No.T/163. Dated the 2nd July 1938• Paragraph 4 of your telegram No•1056 of June 29th, Sultan wishes to retain present wording of Article 11, He quite realises that retention of words 'and the places at which they reside' would give Government of India right to refuse residence of his Consuls at any particular place. In regard to matter 3 7 raised in paragraph 3(b) of my telegram No«T/146 of 24th June, he is prepared to let us have a letter giving our Consul the right to reside 4t Muscat. 2. This proposal meets our point of view and I trust that Government of India will concur. FOWLE. P.L C l^o r d . 7. ^kh Telegram From To Repeated Q Political Resident, Bushire, at Karachi, Secretary of State for India, London. Government of India, External Affairs Depart- ment, Simla. No.T/166. Dated the 3rd July 1938. s! Muscat Treaty. Grateful for as early reply as possible to my telegrams in order 'before I leave Karachi on 10th July to have finished and accepted by Sultan (so far as the Arabic goes) complete Arabic text of Treaty. This can then be finally checked by His Majesty's Government and Government of India. FOWLE. ^\1 Vlj 1361/58 Board of Trade, Great George Jtreet, London, 20th June, 1938 Dear Symon, ^ P o &gt; Draft Anr.'lo-Muscat Treaty « I* Following on our telephone conversation, we have cor^idered the points raised by '/atts in his letter to Gibson of 11th June, We have only the following observations to make (and even as regards most of these points I think that you are more concerned than we are);- A rticle 5 (3) . Would not the intention be more clearly brought out if Watts* clause (which I gather would be an addition at the end of the present paragraph) were amended to read: 'There shall be no variation of the Customs duties as between different ports of the Sultanate, and when goods have once been landed at any such port and the duty thereon has been paid, the goods shall not be liable to re-assessment of duty at the same or any other port'• Article 6(2) . Our interest is of course slight compared with India*s, but we are disposed to feel, as regards watts' proposal, that it is desirable to fix a uniform basis of valuation, whetaer there is a Tariff Board or not. Otherwise what is there to ore vent the Tariff Board from valuing different articles on different bases? Moreover, a valuation list which covered everything would be impossibly long. Surely some principle will need to be laid down to enable Customs officers to decide on the valuation of particular articles wAieh may not be included in the Tariff Board 1 s valuations, without having to hold the goods up until the Board can be called to ether to fix a valuation. You/ •B, Symon Ksq..r You will remern'ber that paragraph 2 of this article was the result of lengthy discussions in the London negotiations, and i should doubt i' ; tne Sultan could be induced to arrec to any substantial amendment of it, if it is kept. Article 6(4) . Watts' suggestion would snea to put the Muscat Customs in the position of always having their way in the last resort, and it would seen preferable to say e.r. 'should the experts be unable to agree as to the choice of an umpire, the uirrpire shall be chosen by agreement between the consular officer of His Majesty and the Omani Customs aut orities at We have also considered the letter of 8th June from the External Affairs Department of the Government of India, sent me under your reference P.L,4151/38. Only one point in this interests us, viz# the suggestion that such a provision as Article 2, paragraph 1, is ordinarily held not to include participation in coasting trade. Vie do not know on what grounds this suggestion is made - in our treaties, where the coasting trade is to be excepted from the national treatment revisions, we always regard a specific exception as necessary for the purpose# Article 3(3) of the present draft Treat.,; , ives British shipping full national treatment and no e ception is made for coasting trade. Therefore the object apparently desired by the Government of India is, we think, already secured. the port of importation 1 ' Yours sincerely, Sd. R.J. Shackle&gt;60/38 £4 Poreien Office, J.w.l, .1/305/91) 2 lst j une ]_9 rr - o - My dear Gibson, # r J&lt; siM ' With reference to India Office letter ...a.4151/38 of the 17th June and previous correspondence on the subject of the draft of the new Muscat Treaty the follovvinc: are our observations* ^ ^' /f&gt;-1 cjc, re e a rd to the amendments set out in India Office telegram Ho•1076 of 8th June to the Government of India (India Office letter,2.3994/58 of 11th June) and in Peel's letter P#2.4044/38 of 14th June to Powle, v/e have no coriiments. With reference to Watts' comments set out in India Office telegram No.1100 of 14th June to the Government of India (India Office letter P.2.4135/38 of 15th June) I send you herewith a minute 'by Beckett which represents our views. As regards the comments set out in Government of / /c India Express letter P.63-N/tl8 ^of 8th June (Indie Office letter P.2,4151/38 of 17th June) I attach another minute by Beckett, In view of the urp;ency of the matter we have not had time to consult our Treaty Department who may ossibly have comments to make on matters of form. If such proves to be the case we will address you again later. Yours sincerely, Sd. T.V. Brenan Gibson EsqIf ' ■■I4360/38 it 611/305/91) The first comment of the Government of India is I think raieconceivetl. Article 2 (1) has nothing to clo with the coasting trade, hut the relevant article is Article 3(3) which provides that in all that relates to navigation and uhe treatment o shipping, the Sultan undertalees to treat British vessels not less favourably in any respect than Omani vessels and the vessels of any foreign country and therefore covers the coasting trade. I think the suggestion in rticle 11 is quite unnecessary. As regards Article 16, I do not really think any amendment of the provision is required, but if any amendment is made it should be to insert the words 'punishable under the law applied by the consular authorities of His Majesty with penalties not exceeding •*. (BdO Beckett 21st June, 1958.50/38 J:'7 *7 | 5/305/91) As regards Articles 1 and 19, I agree with Major ?/att * s suggestions, but would point out that the care for striking out Zanzibar from the exceptions is str ?v;er than that for striking out the Aden protectorate. As regards Article 5 (3) I have not in ; to say except that the words ^Sultan*8 territories'' sho Id 'be substituted for M Sultanate' As regards Articles 5 (4) (b) and 6 I have no observations. As regards Article 6 (2) I am not sure that Major Watts is right, but the point is primarily for the Board of Trade. It seems to me, however, that Article 6 (3) provides that the Tariff Board fixes the actual valuations and all that Article 6 (2) does is to give some indication as to the principle the Tariff Board should follow in doing this. As regards Article 6 (4), what Major Watts actually proposes is that a sentence should be added that if the experts were unable to agree as to the choice of an umpire the decision of the customs house authorities shall be final. I do not think this will do because this will lar.e it certain that there never will be any agreement as to the choice of an umpire. I would sug est saying 'In the event o taeir being unable to agree on the choice of an umpire, the umpire shall be chosen by the consular authorities of His Hajesty and the Sultan.' As regards Article 13 (1) (iv) I think l.ajor Watts is wrong here because he thinks that the section requires the case to be referred to the Moslem religious court apparently without option should any other party to the proceedings/proceedings be a national of the Sultan. But that is not what the section says. It says 'when the person whose status is in question is a Moslem', and that is quite a different thing from sayin any other party to the proceedings. I do not think any amendment is required. (bd.) w .E. Beckett. 21st June, 1958.Telegram Q Frcm Government of India, External Affairs Depart ment, Simla, To Political Resident, Bushire, at Karachi. No,1081. Dated and received the 4th July 1938, Your telegram No.T/163 of July 2nd. Muscat Treaty Article 11. We concur. GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. U. \V 0 . CI LV 6'. XZ s J35/86 Telegram From Q Government of India, External Affairs Depart- ment, Simla. To Secretary of State for India, London, Repeated Political Resident, Bushire, at Karachi Copy by post to Political Agent, Muscat. No.1082. Dated the received the 4th July 1938. % L t 1 Fowled telegram No.T/160 July 1st. Muscat Treaty Article 2(1). We would agree to suggestion made by Powie m paragraph 2 if it is acceptable to His Majesty's Government. GCVERNMENT OF INDIA. Telegram From To Repeated Copy by post No.1083. Q Government of India, External Affairs Departs ment, Simla. Secretary of State for India, London. Political Resident, Bushire, at Karachi. Political Agent, Muscat. Dated and received the 4th July 193£. Fowle's telegram No.T/162 July 2nd. Muscat Treaty Article 16. We concur. GOVERNMENT OF INDIA#7 Telegram Q From Political Resident, Bushire, at Karachi. To Secretary of State for India, London, Repeated Government of India, External Affairs Depart- ment, Simla• Copy by post Political Agent, Muscat. No.T/169. Dated the6th July 1938. 4$ Paragraph 6 of your telegram No.1219 July 5th. Muscat Treaty. (a) Both drafting amendments have been accepted by Sultan. (b) In subsequent correspondence Government of India have accepted present dradTt. (o;),. Confirmed that these charges are of long standing, FOWLS. p .u.■WWII III IE* 36/86 Telegram Q From Government of India, External Affairs Department, Simla. To Secretary of State for India, London. Repeated Political Resident, Bushire, at Karachi Copy by post to Political Agent, Ma scat. No.1091. Dated the 6th and received the 7th July 1938. r. # . r &gt; ^ / 1 Fovi/le's telegram No.T/161 of July 2nd, Muscat Treaty paragraph 2 to paragraph 5. We agree subject to acceptance by His Majesty's Government. GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. 7.7.'38./ u ' Telegram Q, 5Tom Secretary of state for India, London. To Political Resident, Bushire. Repeated Government of India, Simla. Copy by mail to Political Agent, Muscat. Uo. 1232 Dated 6th July received 7th July 1938. IMPORTANT Muscat Treaty, 2# Your telegram lJo .T/l58 of June 30th and Government of India telegr'am of July 1st No. 1071. His Majesty's Government accept compromises referred to in paragraphs 3 and 4 of your telegram following consequen tial alterations will be required in draft (a) In Article l(ii) insert marginally noted amend ment of Sultan subject to substitution after 'Ras al Khaimah' of following words 'and Kalba and, for the purposes of Articles 13, 14 and 15, nationals of States of the Aden Protectorate and nationals of Zanzibar of Omani origin who own property in Oman M . (1?) in Articles l(iii), l(iv) and 19 (1), Aioh do not affect question jurisdiction, insert Sultan's j . ,D / ^ aziiendments subject to omission of words 'the Aden Protectorate and Zanzibar' and insertion of 'and** before w Kalba H . (c) In Article 19(i) after 'protectorates M insert 'or to any of the States under his protection'. ' Your telegram lTo.T/169 of July 6th and paragraph/'2 — - paragraph 6(b) of my telegram of July 5th 110.1219. It seems desirable to make drafting amendment suggested by Government of India viz. to read at the end of Article •♦whose national he may be'. India Office35/86 li telegram jrom % Government of India, External Affairs Department, Simla. To Secretary of State for India, London. Repeated Political Resident, Bushire, at Karachi Copy by post to Political Agent, Muscat. UO.1106 Bated and received 7th July 1938. Muscat Treaty. Reference paragraph (c) of Powle^s telegram 1T0.T/169 of July 6th. 2. We accept provisions of Article 5(7). Government of IndiaD • , Translation. {i Dated Karachi, 8th JEjaadi-al- Awwal^ 1357. (7th July 1933). from - The Sultan of Muscat and Oman. To - Lieut.-Colonel Sir Trenchard Fowle, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. After Compliments. r I have received Your Honour^ letter N0.425-C dated Karachi the 5th July, 1938, which I read with pleasure and understood what you wrote. I confirm my agreement with what you have written therein. Your sincere friend, 3d. Said bin Taimur.iWyjiMifc iW» i m i 11 mi ■' £, - Translation • . ■— —— Bated Karachi Qth Jaxaadi al kmjal 1557. (7th July 1938) J'roia — H.H• the Sultan of Muscat and Oia.an« To - Lieut.-Colonel 3ir Trenchard Fowle, political Resident in the Persian Gulf. a -n After compliments. n g-K With reference to Article 11 of the new treaty between myself and my friend His Brit annic Majesty's Governments I confirm with much pleasure whet I informed you of in the course of our conversation, namely that Hie Britannic Majesty's Consul has the ri^ht to reside in the capital of our country Muscat. Your sincere friend, 3d. Said bin Taimur.Translation Dated Karachi 8th Jamadi al Awwal, 1357. (7th July 1958) From - H.H. the Sultan of Muscat and uaan. To - LieutColonel Sir Trenchard Fowle, political Resident in the Persian Gulf. After Gompliments. With reference to the conversation which took place between myself and Your Honour on 1st July, 1938, in connection with the new treaty between myself and my friend H.B.M. G-overnment, with much pleasure I confirmi (a) the goods mentioned below shall be exempt from Customs dues:- (1) the goods imported for the specific use of H .M. Consulate in Muscat. (2) the goods imported for the personal use of H.M, Consul. (b) The prohibition and restriction which may be imposed upon imports into the Oman territory shall not apply to alcoholic drink, and tobacco, and arms to the limit of two guns, and two rifles, and two pistols (or revolvers) and the ammunition for the same imported for the personal use of H .M. Consul. In this connection, however, I may mention that Customs regulations should be observed on the importation of any of the aforementioned require ment. Your sincere friend, Sd.Said bin Taimur—I-B. Translation. laaaoMmmM • Dated ICarachi 10th Jamadi al Awwal 1357 {9th Tuly 1938}. From - H«H. the lultan of Muscat and Oaan. To - Lieut•-Colonel Sir Trenohard i^owle, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. After Compliaienta. - ^ 91 • I had the pleasure of receiTing Your Honour's letter N0.447-G, dated Karachi 8th July 1938, which I read and understood, and I confirm my agreement with what you mentioned in the second paragraph of your said letter. I also accept the Arabic translation of the draft of the naw treaty as its correct translation. In this connection I express ray thanks for, and appreciation of, the valuable help which you rendered to rie in London and here in the course of our treaty conversations, and I hope that, through your meduim, the conclusion of the treaty will meet the wishes of both the contracting parties in view of the benefits which it confers on each. Usual Tending. Your sincere friend, Sd. Said bin Tairnur,To Repeated From Telegram Q Political Resident, Bushire, at Karachi Secretary of State for India, London. Government of India, External Affairs Department, Simla, Copy by post to Political Agent, Muscat, No.T/175, Dated the yth July 1938. Muscat Treaty. Discussion with Sultan concluded. Full report will be sent from Bushire, FOVvLE.GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. Department. EXPRESS LETTER (AIRMAIL). rv n —This is an ORIGINAL message sent by AIM MAIL which provides a means ofeonmunicatwn more ' expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to b? treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. Tu save time and to obviate jormaliiies it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department ] No ' 390-3 Dated 1! *Mt iT *'the n M 3 e lhi' 15th July 38 xxxxxxxx J T f From - Political Resident, Bushire. To - His Maje3ty f s Secretary of state for India, London. Ropeated Tlie Secretary to the Governraent of India in the Sxternal Affairs apartment. Reference y — Simla. xmkx SS e The political Agent, Muscat* Muscat Treaty ^ • Reference correspondence ending with my telegram H o .t/175 of 9th July 1938. I arrived at Karachi on the 23rd June and left on the 10th July. The Sultan did the same. During this Period I saw His Highness almost daily* As I had antic ipated when I suggested visiting Karachi, there were a number of minor points, and one or two major ones, which had to be settled by discussion before the draft Treaty could assume its final form. I found His Highness in good health and, as usual, in amiable mood. . &amp; | \ % I enclose herewith the following documents. A. Letter No.c/447, dated 8th July 1938, from me to ^ His Highness, with enclosure, setting forth the changes agreed on at Karachi and asking for His (Sign Highn# „, Designation)Ivtt to iCcut a. -2- Higtmess's acceptance of the Arabic translation. ^ A » / J a jn * * ***&amp; * Translation of His Higimess's reply to A, dated 10th jamadi al Awwal 1357 (9th July 1958) confirming thes^ changes. k Letter No.C/425, dated bth July 1938, from me to His Highness, relating to Article 7 (Lighting and Buoying). ^ - Translation of His Highness 1 s reply to C, dated 8th Jaoaadi al Awwal 1S57 ( ?th July 1938), accepting the conditions mentioned therein. A p i\ * t '' Translation of letter fr6m His Highness to me, dated 8th Jamadi al Awwal 1357 (7th July 1938), relating to Article 11, and giving His Majesty's Consul the right to reside at Muscat. Arabic translation, as approved by Sultan, oi the draft Treaty and of the draft confidential letter referring to Article 15. ^ . Translation of letter from His Highness to me, dated 8th Jamadi al Awwal 1357 (7th July 1938) regarding privileges of His Majesty* s Consul. A'lM • 4, Reference letters A and B. In the forme- I asked (para 2) His Highness to confirm the changes agreed on, I mentioned (para 3) that the present draft was still subject to the final and formal acceptance of His Majesty's Government and the Government of India, and I requested (para 4; rlis Highnesses acceptance of the Arabic translation of the drrft Treaty, m his reply (3) His Highness accepted the whole of ay letter. 5. ^^ Hote forming the enclosure to A gives the changes agreed on in Karachi between His Highness and myself, after reference to His Majesty^ Government and the Govern ment of India. 6 /5, I have the f oil owing further comments to offer. Article 1 (ii), ( iii), (ivl . The juridical and commercial atatus of nationals of the States of the Aden protectorate and Zanzibar -waa the most important point I had to discusa with His Highness, and one to which hie attached considerable weight. The reasons for the Sultan 's jf' ' M o « attitude were given in paragraphs 3 and 4 of my telegram Ho.T/iSS, dated 30th June 1938, and seemed to me to deserve consideration. The compromise finally come to, |fv ^ vide paragraph 2 of India Office telegram &gt;10 .1232, dated 6th July 1938, appears to me a reasonable one. Article 1 (v). Drafting amendment. Ho comment a. Article 2 ( l) « The question of the participation of British and Indian vessels in the Muscat coasting trade ^ h .! o raised in Government of India Sxpress Letter Ho.5 1 .63-K/38, dated 8th June 1938, was disposed of in paragraph 5 of India Office telegram Ko.1148, dated 22nd June 1938, and was therefore not raised with the Sultan. The amendment suggested by His Highness regard ing the entry of nationals of His Majesty into Muscat territory was accepted by His Majesty f s G-overnment in Paragraph 3 of India Office telegram No, 1219, dated 5th July 1938. Article 5 (3). See paragraph 5 of India Office telegram Ho. 1219, dated 5th July 1938, and Government of K'T / Ko. India telegram Ho.1091, dated 6th July 1938. The position I is as explained in paragraph 1 of my telegraii No.T/l61, dated 2nd July 1938, and does net differ, I imagine, from that in other countries. If a subordinate Customs official Makes a wrong assessment I presume that the universal practice/practice is that a superior can re-assess. This being so, I did not feel that we were on strong grounds in asking for preferential treatment in iiuscat. Moreover if the - ' suggestion in paragraph 3 of India Office telegraia Ho» 1148, dated 22nd June 1958, had been adopted it seemed to me that a mercnant would b^ve been stopped from appealing to the head customB office in Muscat in case of over- assessment - a right which Xfcs he possesses under the pres ent draft • In addition, and this applies also to Article 6 (2) and 6(4), I was influenced by the reasons I ■ »■ *&gt; given in paragraph 2 of my telegram Ho,T/l61, dated the 2nd July 1938. Article 5(4) (b) . Ko comments see para- graph 5 of India Office telegram Ko.1219, dated 5th July 1938, and Crovernment of India telegram Ho» 1C91, dated 6th July 1938. Article 5 (6). 3ame remarks as above. \rticle 6(2). Ho change. See remarks in paragraph 4 of my telegram Ho.T/ldl, dated 2nd July 1938. My views accepted by His Uajesty^s Jovernment, vide paragraph 5 of India Office telegrtim So. 1219, da^ed 5th July 1938, and Government of India, vide their tele- gram Uo.l09l, dated 6th July 19b8, Article 6 (4). No change. The Sultan 7 s ^-k 'a- attitude as given in paragraph 5 of my telegram Ko.T/161, dated and July 1958, seemed to me reasonable. There will be a certain amount of automatic pressure on both Parties i.e. the merchants and the Muscat Customs to come to a settlement. The former will wish to clear their goods/gooda before the period of four monthG allowed under j^tiole 5 (6); the latter will desire to collect their customs duties as soon as possible. His Majesty's Government finally agreed to there being no change, vide paragraph 5 of India Office telegram lTo.1219, dated 5th J^ily 1933, as did the Government of India, vide their tale grain NO.1091, dated 6th July 1938. Article 7, See letters C find D. (vide paragraph 3(b) of India Office telegram Ho. 1076, dated v \ A i i , W ■ Vf 1 ] 8tli June 1958. Re the assurance asked for by Sultan, His Highness♦ s point of view is apparently that unless the Persian Gulf duos are reduced shipping will not be willing to pay the dues levied by his Government. article 11. In paragraph 1(3) of Government of India Express Letter to 1^.63-^/58, dated 8th June 1938, it was suggested that the words ^at seaport towns' should be inserted after the word^reside n in the third line of this Article in order to prevent a demand by the Sultan for the appointment of his Consul at the headquarters of the Government of India. I suggested, vide my telegram Ho# T/146, dated 24th June 1938, to the Government of India, that the words rt ana the places at which they reside 11 should also be deleted, in order to deprive the Sultan of the right to insist at any time in the future that our Consul should reside at any seaport town other than Muscat. Co this the Government of India agreed in paragraph 4 of their K . If if telegram No. 1056, dated J&gt;9th June 1953. On the changes being suggested to the sultan he stated (vide my telegram ^ K • ^ V ^•T/ldS, dated 2nd July 1938, to the Government of India) ^hat he wished to retain the present wording of the Article, quite/realising that the retention of the words «and the places at which they reside' would give the Government of India the right to refuse residence of his Consuls at any particular place. He h?(.s written letter (S) giving His Majesty^ Consul the right to reside at Muscat. \rticle 13 (l), mendment suggested in para- ' ' A m , h . I c !' { graph S(c) of India Office telegram No.1076, dated 8th June 1938, accepted by Sultan. article 13 (l) (iv). 3ee correspondence end- • ^ b,(« ing with paragraph 2 of India Office telegraia ¥o .l219, dated bth July 195B. Our amendment accepted by His Highne s s. Article 16. This is not an Article which is important from our point of view, and if the ultan had raised strong objections to it in London we Mere prepared to omit it. The suggestion made in paragraph 5 of India Office telegram no . 1143, dated 22nd June 1938, was made to the Sultan but was not agreeable to him. The final result was the omission of, the Aords M ora serious offence*', vide paragraph 4 of India Office telegram Ho. 1219, dated N K /. C 5th July 1938. /j? tide 19 (1). Sultan accepted the drafting amendment suggested in India Office letter Ho.P.Z.4044/38, dated 14th June 1938. j-- - Insertion referred t o in paragraph 2(b) of fi *'v India Office telegram No.1232, dated 6th July 1938, made. j\rticle 23 (2). Insertion referred to in - ^ A.T^ p s Paragraph 3(d) of India Office telegram No. 1076, dated 8th June 1938, made. 7 ' He the translation (F). As you are aware, vide paragraph 4 of my letter H0.245-S of 14th May 1938, K J b I the/the translation of the treaty of 1891 caused a good deal of trouble and delay, and on this occasion also was not iavoid of difficulty, Tide correspondence ending with my telegram Ho,T/lSl of 16th June 1958, The translation of w Interpreter, Kh&amp;Jk Sahib Mirza Ali, vfas shown to the Sultan, who had some alterations to suggest. Fortunately His Highness*3 own Secretary, Khan Bahadur Anraad bin 3iu3iflJ3Biad shubaili, was with him at iiaracni anu. j\han Bahadur Saiyid Siddiq Hasan also came to Karachi on ten days 1 leave, and was good enough together with Xhan Bahadur Ahmad bin Muhammad shubaili and Khan Sahib Mirza Ali t o f orm a translating Goiamittee of three. Their results were daily submitted to the Sultan, who took considerable trouble in satisfying himself of the correctness of the translation# The result has been that the translation nas been done quickly, correctly and economically, fend unless there are any serious errors I trust that it will be accepted by His Majesty 1 s .rovernment and the Government of India in its present form (see paragraph 8(b) below). 8, What now remainc to be done appears to be as follows. (a) for His Majesty's Government and the Government of India to approve finally of the text of the present draft, (b) for arrangements to be made - I suggest in London- for the Arabic text to be checked, (c) f or the Sngli sh and ATab i c t ext s to be prepared for signature^ (d) for the treaty to be signed. I suggest that tnis could/oould be done by my viaiting Muscat in October when I return from leave. As far as the Sultan is concerned he Is quite agreeable to this. Reference letter Gr# This letter is not strictly bound up 7ith the treaty and there is no refer ence in it to the treaty. In Yiew however of the fact that the question arose in correspondence connected with the treaty it may be conyenient to deal with it here. 'he Foreign Office gave their views, vide India Office telegram Ho. 1126 of 17th June 1938, and the Government of India theirs in their telegram Ho. 1060 of 29th June 193^. In further correspondence with the government of India, the latter stated that they were prepared to give certain reciprocal privileges which are set forth in letter G. The net result is we have secured privileges for our Consul at Muscat which the Government of India are pre pared, if necessary, to give to a Muscat! Consul in India, though at this stage the Sultan gave no indication that he would ask for such privileges. Incidentally there was no question of persuading the Sultan against his will to accord these privileges? he accorded them readily# 3d. T.C. FOVLS political Resident in the Persian Gulf. ATTESTED ^'(fC for Secretary to the political Heaident in the Persian Gulf.Tele gram From Secretary to the Government of india, External Affairs Department, iiimla Repeated Ho. 1146. To Political He si dent, Jbuahire# Secretary of State for India, London. Dated and received the 16th July 1938. Jr 1 1») Your telegram iMO.T/l66 of July 3rd. Muscat Treaty. translator here and subject to the concurrence of His Majesty's Government Government of -India would prefer that Arabic text on completion should be sent to His Majesty*s Government for final check and preparation of signature copies. Owing to lack of official Arabic QOYISRUCSHT O? Il^DLA P. a . {\L.35/86 / i Tele gram From To tl.k'a Secretary of State for India. London. Secretary to the troverninent of mdia, External Affairs i^epartrcent, Simla# Political Resident, ^uahire. Repeated to Ho.1296 Dated 20th received 2lst July 1938. ^ fv July. iour telegram no. 1146 of 15th Arab translation of Muscat Treaty. Ho objection to check etc. here. Secretary of otate for India. ?.L. (i.Telegram fr cm 35/86 Government of India, External Affairs Department, Simla. To Secretary of State for India, London. Repeated Political Resident, Bushire ^t Karachi. Political Agent, Muscat. flo. 1368. Dated 27t]i received 2&amp;tlci August 1938. treaty make* , -/'A A fit* Your telegram Ho. 1492 of August 26th. MUSCAT Government of India have no observations to Mp t.L. - PORSIGN. \ \ cTGOVERNMENT OP INDIA. Department. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). 1 [N.B.— This is an OHIO IN AL message sent by AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department.] Office of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, No* To c/699 Date Camp, Karachi^ 3rd September 1^38. The Secretary to the Government of India, External Affairs Department, Simla. 1938. Your telegram No.1368 dated the 27th August Muscat Treaty. 2. Grateful for post copy of India Office telegram No.1492 of the 26th August referred to, which I have not ■ received. Sd. H. Weightman. Offg. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. p Secretary to tl: for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. {Signature) (Designation)P.2. ^C&lt;'y ' ' 19 J/ INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, p.! i^ HIRE . HEG'P-NCY. ;» Date ' CONFINEMTIAL F.2C3nC3 J Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy has been sent to i^r' ■t) The Political Resident in the PersianGulI ^963 2000 7.36I vM Lc Cypher telegram from Secretary of State lor 11^1.a. to G-overnment of India? jjXternal^Afibirs Department, dated S6th. ^uga-st, . F (No. of words 27) X 1492 Addressed to Governmont of Indie, copy by post to Political Resident in the Persian Gulf and 10 iho Political iAgen ! -, r.Aucica ^• Reference political Resident's Express letuer Ho. 890rS of 15th July. Muscat Treaty. / Ifave you any observations to 0^1 or on revised ill :■- -.-i •-x- IKDIA OTA/ICE P. Z. 6004/38 I'/iilTEriALij 9 S . ... 1. . 27th August ? 1938. Dr. Ar'berTYp our Assistant Librarian., has 'been good enough to check the Arabic translation of the Muscat Treaty and I enclose a list of the passages where substantial discrepancies occur as between the English original and the draft Arabic translation. This list v does not include a rather large number of passages where it v .ould be desirable, either on grammatical grounds or in the interests of exact clarity- to make minor./ ? ( / . ■ emendations in the Arabic. As, in your covering letter, you expressed the hope that, unless there were any serious errors, the Arabic text should be accepted in its present form, we should be glad if you would let us know whether you consider that the points dealt with in Arberry's note are of sufficient importance to warrant further reference to the Sultan before the signature copies are prepared. 9 K t ! A copy of the draft Treaty, as amended in the light of your discussions at Karachi, is enclosed. 2. i also enclose a copy of a letter from the Boara of/ Sl r Trenchard Powle, KCIE. , CBE. , C/o Lloyds Bank, Ltd., Cox &amp; King's Branch, , 6, Pall Mall, M U l ' S. W. 1, isthV- of Trade in regard to the interpretation of Article 12 (8). May we have your opinion as to which amendment should he accepted. I assume that this amendment in itself might safely he made without reference to the Sultan particularly if the second alternative is used. Yours sincerely, (Sgd.) R.sM' Article 1 (ii) the marginal addendum 'except nationals.in Oman' is omitted in the Arabic draft. This omission may be supplied as follows, subject to con firmation as to the correct spelling of the names of the places in Arabic t Ll io .r j^ul, - o^^iLlI j ^ J„YI ^;LJI (iii) the marginal addendum 'except Koweit...and Kalba' is omitted. This omission may be supplied as follows, provisionally:- ' ' (iv) the marginal addendum 'except Koweit...and Zanzibar' is omitted. This omission may be supplied as follows, provisionally Article 4 . The opening phrase reads literally, in the Arabic, 'It shall be permitted to nationals of His Majesty resident in the territories of the Sultan...' The discrepancy can be remedied by omitting the word (which should incidentally have been ). In rendering the phrase 'any other legal manner', the adjective ier^ has been used, which suggests reference to the Sharia law. To avoid this restrictive implication, the word can be used. The phrase 'to possess the same' has been omitted. This may be supplied thus: J-* Article 5 (4) (a) The phrase 'the foreign place of destination' has been rendered 'the place'. The following would be an exact translation:Article 6 (3) The following is the literal version of the Arabic: 'All the goods on which duty is to be levied shall be fi-ed according to the price of their market...' The following would be a more exact version of the text:- U-J^ ^.UJI Article 9 (3) The word 'excep1k)ns ,, has been rendered in the singular. It should be translated by (3) (d) The Arabic reads 'for the protection of animals or trees'. The word s^LJI should be substituted for ^Lr2f) Article 13 (3) The phrase 'to the owner, Captain, Agent of the ship or aircraft' is rendered 'to their owner [sc. the owner of the goods], the Captain or Agent of the ship or aircraft...' Is this the intention of the English? Article 19 (1) The marginal addendum 'except Koweit...and Kalba' is omitted. This omission may be supplied as follows, provisionally:- .a JOI ^-&gt;7 Article 30 (1) The phrase 'any Member of the British Commonwealth of Nations' has been rendered 'any of the English Dominions'. To bring this phrase into line with the satisfactory rendering of 'British Commonwealth of Nations' in Article 1 (iii) , the following translation would be more suitable:-Article 31 (1) The Arabic rendering of this section reads, literally; 'So long as the provisions of the present Treaty are not applicable in any territory referred to in Articles 19 and 20, by virtue of accession under Article 20 or by notice of extension under Article 19, goods produced or manufactured in the territories of the Sultan will be accorded treatment as favourable as that accorded to goods produced or manufactured in any other foreign country', [The rest of the section has been omitted in the Arabic draft,] A full translation of the section would be;- &gt;1 r-oU) ^ HI ijuoLJi 0 LU-JI J ,1 J^L.' )i i jLlI Axl-f 8 i/l ^ zV*r ^ ) '3 Xs 9 JuJ\ ^1 Jyo^l Article 22 (1) The phrase 'the proper interpretation of the English or Arabic text of one or other of the Treaty stipulations' has been rendered by 'the translation of the text of the English or the Arabic or the one or the other'. A correct rendering would be;- t i\j&amp; l_*J 1 -by&lt;3^ / N - , A— c. . /^C ^Ox/ 4 ' cC-o. P-k.^.ofCs-^,6004/ 38 BOAHD OF TRADE 5 Great George Street ? S.W.I. I 2bth Augustp 1958 Dear Symon;, I was talking to you on the telephone this evening ahout Article 12(2) of the Muscat Treaty. In order to get round the difficulty of the interpretat ion of the word w owner 5 ' in the sixteenth line of Article 12(2) - i.e. whether owner of the cargo or owner of the ship is meant - and also the difficulty of what is meant by the word ^goods' 1 in the thirteenth line of Article 12(2) - i.e. whether this includes mparts of a ship'' we would like to introduce a fairly substantial amendment into the Article. After the words u they shall further take every possible care that' 1 in Article 12(2) we should like the sentence to continue U such vessel and all parts thereof and all furniture and appurten ances belonging thereto ? and all goods and merchandise saved therefrom3 including any which may have been cast into the sea? or the proceeds thereof ? if sold-, as well as all papers found on board such stranded or wrecked vessel? shall be given up to the owners of such vesselj goodSj merchandise^ &amp;c, } or to their agents when claimed by them or to the British Consul . If it is too late for such a substantial amendment to be incorporated into the Treaty ? we would ? as a last resox o t ? be content with the substitution for the words ''the owner, captain, agent of the ship or aircraft ? or British Consul; subject always to rights of salvage' 1 '' of the words n their owners^ the accredited representatives of such owners y or British Consul subject always to rights of salvage''. I hope this is clear. Yours sincerely 5 Sd. R.B. Tippetts Symon Esq. (K' cv- ■ y.Office of the Political Resident in the Pers ian Gulf, Carop, Karachi, T^Q.ffOcC/Sig, Dfited the bth September, 1938 # tic The India Office have aent me a copy of Peel's demi- official letter Ho, P.2.6004/38, dated the 27th August 1938, to you, regarding the Muscat Treaty. Will you please let rae know if you want me to take any action here before your return ? I see that you had an idea of signing the Treaty with the Sultan in Muscat in October, and if this is to be possible, these outstanding points must necessarily be settled before your return. As the Sultan has a copy of the draft Treaty in Arabic I do not see how amendments are to be inserted in the signature copies without a prior refer ence to him; this is paurt ioularly the case in regard to Article 12 (2) where a substantial amendment is proposed. 2« I might point out also that the marginal addendum to Article 1 ( ir) should be similar to that to Articles l (iii) and 19 (i),l.e. «except Kuwait and Kalba' and not 'except Kuwait and Zanzibar 11 . 3, x am returning to Bahrain next ondfey, so • einc _ you will reply to me there. ' ■ '■. I • ' /■ / 1 hope you are enjoying your leave. ' &gt; ( / , : ■ , ^ Yours sincerely, : J': Th « Hon' ble Trenchard Fowle, KCI^* t OB^., c /o Messrs.Lloyds Bank Ltd., 6 Pall Mall, LOKDOH. f/ c ( cUfv-i Co-/ fit •No .F.63-N/38. A copy of the undermentioned paper is fonmrded to the Hon T ble the Political Resident in the Persian G-ulf, for information, with reference to his Sxpress Letter Mo. C/599, dated the 3rd September 1938. By order, etc., t .sUt ' ' \ssistant Secretary to the Government of India. External Affairs Department, Simla, the / ^ September 1938. —— /t ^ Telegram'from the Secretary of State for India, London, No. 1492, dated the 26th August 1938. jA / ^ ? r r ) ^ -J ^ ) ft **.4^ c-f-y f3b' / p fc' f'! Telegram 'Q' From H.M. Secretary of State for India, London* To Political Resident (at Bahrain)# Repeated Political Agent, Muscat# Copy by post to Government of India, Simla# No. 1631 Dated 23rd received 24th September 1938# Following for Weightman from Gibson# Your demi-official letter to Fowle No#0/612, September 5th# MUSCAT TREATY# Fowle agrees that Sultan must be consulted regarding suggested emendations of Arabic translation and proposed amendment of Article 12 (2)# We should therefore be glad if you would instruct Watts to approach Sultan accordingly# If possible Sultan should be persuaded to accept larger amendment to Article 12 (2)# Alteration in text of Articles 1 Ciii) and Civ) and 19 (i) should of courae be identical as you point out# - RETAXANDUM -c/o LlDycis Sank ^td, 6 Pall Mall, S.W.I. 31st August 1953. Gould you please refer to your letter No.?.2.6004/38, dated the 27th August, on the subject of the Muscat Treaty. 2 with regard to Arberry *s corrections in the Arabic translation. I certainly think that a further reference should be made to the Sultan. I suggest that the corrections be sent up to Weightrnan, with instructions to ask Vatts to go through them with His Highness and get the latter* s approval. As His Highness kindly vetted the translation Watts should of course make his approach a tactful one. 3. yith regard to the Board of Trade amendment. I am also definitely of the opinion that they should ue relerred to His Highness. I have no reason to suppose that tae latter will make any objection, but if we alter anything without his consent, even If he finally approve^ Ox iv, I am afraid he will get the impression that we have done something if not behind his back, at any rate over his head, and will be somewhat huffed. 4. These references will of course take a little time, but we have till February for signature, so there is no hurry, it will be far better to have a little del-y now in the matter of the final signature, rather than to run the risk of trying to alter the signature copies once tne latter have been made out. I am sorry to inflict ay handwriting upon you, but I am at the moment 'hiberniating' far removed, I am glact cq say, from typewriters and such like. Yours si ncerely, sd. T.C.Fowle. •T .Peel 51s q, ,M0. , Th, 2 India Office, London.5^ QOHFIMTIAL* GOVEKNiilENT OP INDIA, D epartment, EXPRESS LETTER [M&lt; ^ an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to sare telegraphic expense and undue me of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the satne expedition as if it had been telegraphed* To sai e tune and Jui tuai dies U is worded and tiiyutd as if it had u&amp;m so despatched % ] Office of the Political Heal dent in the Pers ian Gulf, Gamp. BAHRA T K. F rom • Officiating Political Resident in the Persian (iulf 9 / 'i f f To - The Political Agent y Muscat. Mo. C/696 of 1938. Dated 25th September, [ys 8. Subjects Muscat Treaty. . — — Reference correspondence ending witn India Office telegram 10.1631, dated the 23rd September iy3ti,(repeated to you). 2. Please approach Sultan as soon as possible regarding (a) suggested emendations of Arabic translation and (b) amendment of Article 12 (2). as regards (a). The English text of the draft treaty used in the discussions at Karachi is identical with that forwarded to you under India Office Printed Letter No.P.Z.2976, dated the 30tn April 1938. a note of the changes agreed on in Karacni was forviarded J. n% t0 you under Sir Trenchard Fowled Express Letter Mo.390-S, dated 15th July 1938. The Sultan has a copy of the same English with the cfc&amp;nges agreed on in Karachi entered thereon. He haB ^so a copy of the Note mentioned above and a copy of the Arabic 2*' 'translation/ mfp-501 s&amp;p—(m.820)—23-7-36—300,000.-2- translation incorporating these changes, as you have not got a copy of the Arabic translation tne best plan would be lor you to work on the English text and the Arabic translation held by the Sultan. The former should be checked with tne Note enclosed with Sir Trenchard Fowle's express letter of ibth July 19-38 and the Arabic translation should then be checked in the light f.lU of Mr.Ar berry's Note {copy of which was forwarded to you at p /u ^ Ziarat under Residency Printed Letter Ko,c/652 f dated the lt&gt;th September 1938). The marginal addendum to Article 1 ( iv) should be identical with that to Articles 1 (iii) and 19 (i). It is possible that some of the omissions which occur in the India Office copy of the translation do not occur in the Sultan's copy for the latter was prepared first and checked by the Sultan himself, and the copies for the India Office, the CTOvernment of India and Bushire were then made from it. The instances of faulty translation will of course occur in tne Sultan^ copy. 4. As regards (b). The Sultan's agreement to tne proposed amendment and his acceptance of tne Arabic translation oi tne amended Article (which should be prepared in Muscat) should be obtained in writing. sd. H. Weightman. Officiating political Resident in the Ptrs ian ^ulf. Attested 4 L' A-V ^or Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian GullVi 5 A: i 1 i— - INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL, LONDON ? S. ¥. 1 . P.Z.6599/3o. 28th September, 1938. Ivly dear Powle, Would you kindly refer to your demi-official letter I mo . C/102 ^01' the 23rd February about the modification of the Muscat Tariff ? vi ' ' :r ' b , f&gt; ' - 2. If the substituted letter is not yet to hand we should be glad if a further effort could be made to obtain it from the Sultan. 3* Incidentally the Foreign Office will require a certified copy of the Arabic text for transmission? with a translation? to the French Government. k* I am sending a copy of this letter to V/atts. Yours sincerely, on 'ble Lt. -Col, Sir T.Q.J, Fowle ? / n rn , &gt;C.I.S. , C.B .E. ? 0 ille Agency ? &gt; Bahrein. 1 (j I tCOKFOfflTIAL. GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, Depariment, Ki) ' y EXPRESS LE B.—This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to he treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To me time and formalities it is worded aud siyned as if it had been so despatched.] From To Political Resident, Bushire at Kuwait. Political Agent, Muscat# Ho. C/743. Daied Vth October IWB*. ■A Sub.lect; Muscat Tariff. 0 / /•/ Reference India Office letter No^ 6599/38, dated the 28th September 1938, copy sent to you direct. Z. Please take action accordingly. Sd. T.C. Fowle, Political Resident in the Persian G-ulf • ATTESTED ^or Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf# s. 6. MFP—501 S&amp;P—(M.820)—23-7-36—300, 000. 1 J ■ vlTelegram Q,. Itom political Resident, at Kuwait To political Agent, Muscat Copy by mail to Secretary of State for India, London, and Grovernment of India, External Affairs Department, Simla. Ho.T/fe04 # Dated tiie 16tli October, 1938 # India Office telegram No^lSGO October 14th, MIS CAT TREATY. Please inform Sultan accordingly. ./ / / Res identGOVERNMENT OF INDIA. Department. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL), V R —This is an ORIGINAL message sent by AIR MAIL which, provides a means of communication more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to he treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had heen telegraphed. To s.tve time and to ohvtaie formlities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated hy the signature of a mponsiile officer of the Department.] i\ m No. G /13S Po Bated T the 18th Ooto'ber 19 38. J Political Resident, Bushire. SubjectMuscat Tre^ tZ h Refereuce^' express letter No.C/96 of 25th September 1938. I forward herewith ^ copy of a letter Ho.C/137 dated 11th October 38 from me to His Highness the Sultan and of his reply thereto th October 1938. As will be seen from the Sultan's letter he agrees the first of the alternative amendments suggested to Article 12(8) the Draft Treaty and to the Arabic translations of the amendments ;reed upon between you and His Highness at Karachi in July 1933 with ie modifications as detailed in my above mentioned letter to the Sultan. The Sultan 's assertion that the word l^as no r.-otrictiv- digious meaning as stated by Mr .Arberry appears to be supported bj le Dictionary ( Badger 's) but this Agency Munshi declares that the itter's interpretation is that of all Islamic countries and is correct, never the point does not appear a very important one and since tl man has committed himself, in our exchange of letters, to accept the eaning of this word as including all forms ox law, it may etained. ■5 +i nn to iudse tlrie Sultan's suggested So far as I am in a position to juag ilternatiye word of not suitable# '• inetruotions 'oontaln.d 1„ p.r.^.ph 5 of jour .loo. ,«o..4 Letter to make the marginal addendum^^Articles l(IIl), ( ) identical S. 44. (Designation) MFP—1048 S &amp;P—(11-2042)— 1 7- 1 2-37—20,000.iSS 11 Article 1 &gt; (ii) the marginal addenduiB 'except nationals .o. in OInan ,, is^ omitted in the Arabic draft. This omission may be supplied as follows, subject to confir mation as to the correct spelling of the names of the places in Arabic 5» | 6 II IT j\y^\ j fa yjl ^ ♦ j hy Ju*ji (iii) the marginal addendum 'except iioweit , and Kalba' 1 is omitted® » This omission may be supplied as follows, provisionallys- j ) ofi J y ^l^ykJUl y ^ U ^Civ) the marginal addendum 'except ivoweit ••• and Kalba is omitted. This omission may be supplied as follwos, provisionallys- j ufij J ^jis» LJ ^^iauUt y ^ ^ ♦ j&amp; &gt;m j j j Article 4 . The opening phrase reads literally, in the ^rabic, 'It shall be permitted to nationals of His Majesty resident^ in the territories of the Sultan . The discrepancy can be remedied by omitting the word Cwhich should incidentally have been )• In rendering the phrase 'any other legal manner', the adjectiv%%•*#■*■£ has been used, which suggests reference to the Sharia law. To avoid this restrictive implication, tne word ur' can be usedo The phrase 'to possess the same' has been omittedo Ihis may be supplied thuss Li Article 5 (4) Ca) The phrase 'the foreign place of destination' has been rendered 'the place'. The following would be an exact translation0^ .««SESW*ee3Ml ■ o : -2«- Article 6 (2) The follwing is the literal version of the ^rabic; 'All the goods on which duty is to be levied shall be fixed according to the price of their market The following would be a more exact version of the texts A rticle 9 . (3) The word 'exceptions' has been rendered in the singular. It should be translated by •yti; \ (3) (d) The lirabic reads 'for the protection of animals or trees'. The wordc# u&gt; should be substituted for^tpwAVI 11 ■ ■ ■ ■ •• Article 19 (l) The marginal addendum 'except Kuwait 4^, and Kalba is omitted^ This omission may be supplied as followsj provisionally•' fly J U* 4 J ^ ^ • **6^ jy*-) 3 Article 20 Cl) The nhrase 'any Member of the British Commonwealth of Nations' has been rendered n any of the English Dominions • To bring this phrase into linewiththe^^ ing of 'British Commonwealth of Nations in ticle 1 (i J, the following translation would be more suitable•- ♦ ^ (jfi* 'i '•The ^rabic rendering of this section reads literally; 'So long as the provisions of the present Treaty are not applicable in any territory referred to in Articles 19 and 20 9 by virtue of accession under Article 20 or by notice of extension under article 19j goods produced or manufactured in the territories of the oultan will be accorded treatment as favourable as that accorded to goods produced or manufac tured in any other foreign country'. (The rest of the sectior has been omitted in the ^rabic draft). A full translation of the section would bej- ijjfC ^ T* j M if iJl1 ^ pi J U jl T • a V-UJI iyushjl JJ-nS M 2^UJI 2g) ^ iiyUwejl uf &gt;5JI dill J ^ iy-J! y sOt 2(1 ^ iyunUI y ^5 iJl ^ Article 22 (l) The phaase 'the proper interpretation of the English or Arabic text of one or other of the Treaty stipulations has been rendered by H the translation of the text of the Knglish or the Arabic ot the one or the other • A correct rendering v/ould be5- * 2A*LwJ( O-V ^us^ 1 .J 1 jc-i ^y** WSs jmCSM' • Translation of a letter dated 17th. Shaban 1357 (12th October 1938) from His Highness Saiyid Said bin Taimur, Sultan of Muscat and Oman to Major R.P.Watts, H.B.M's Consul, Muscat* \ I .After compliments. I have received your letter No.0/137 dated 11th October 1938 and understand all you mention therein# I confirm that you have fully understood siafe what I agreed to in the matter mentioned in your letter quoted above* Usual Ending# V Ill ii uGOVERNMENT OF INDIA. Oonfidential. ' Department. EXPRESS LETTER (MR MAlU ^-Thisitan ORiaiNA^ sent by AIR MAIL which provides a wansTof communication rnort expeditious than the ordinary mail and ts cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to le treated, MP'dition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formahhe* it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature- of a responsible officer of the Department.] ^ - J No. 555-3 of 1938» gu ahirc, the 4th November, 7538. fft vtom - Political Resident, Bushire. To - secretary of State for India, London. Repeated Secretary to the Gorermnent of India, Bxtemal Affairs Department, Hew Delhi. Political Agent, Muscat# aubjeott Muscat Treaty, With refer«ice to correspondence ending with India Office telegram Uo.1631. dated the 23rd September 1938, I enclose a copy of an isxpreas Letter Ho#c/138, dated the 12th October 1938, from the Political Agent, Muscat, from which it will be seen that His Highness has agreed to the proposed amendments in the Arabic and English texts with the exception of, in the Arabic only, (a) the translation of the word legal in Article 4 in the phrase 'auy other legal mannerIt will be seen that the adjective CS^ Preferred by Hie Highness to the adjective &lt;3^^ • 1 agree *ith His Highness that 3ms no restriction in meaning to a religious implication* It is true that Shariah can have a meaning of religious law but in a Moslem State such as Muscat there is no other law and therefore the word ^Shariah 11 covers all law whether r ®ligiou3, civil or criminal. Legal in Article 4 should therefore be translated in accordance with the Sultan^ suggestion. (Signature) (*)/ (Designation)I * F -2- (b) With regard to the further suggestioas of His Highness on the Arabic te-xt of \rticie 1 (ii), (iii), ( iv) ^ is always referred to as and should be so translated, anc is not given the article, which should therefore be omitted. The translation of Kalba by is undesirable as lixaiting Kalba to Khor Kalba, the Sultan's suggestion should therefore be adopted, that is to say the plain word Kalba, without the article, used. 2. In the 'gn ^liah of Major Jatts 1 letter to His Highness one or two clerical errors (underlined in red) have crept in. These however may be ignored as they are insignificant, and the correct wording as suggested by you used in the fair copy, f 3. In continuation of my Printed Letter No,499-S of the 2oth October 1938 1 enclose copy of the letters exchanged between the Political Agent P Muscat, and the Sultan, relative to the amendment of Article 19 (1) of the Treaty. 4. 7xth the incorporation of the above amendments the signature copies may now be prepared, and despatched t o me as early as possible. At the same time it is requested that an instrument delegating all plenary powers in regard to the signing of the Treaty may be granted, and formrded. these should be sent to Baurain by air to save time and I can pick them up there on my way to Muscat. sd. r f.C.Fowle. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. At tested . Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.1 ■ '11 35/iOi, 35/86 and Town Telegram G.T From Political Agen1 9 Muscat To Political Resident, iiu shire Ho. 1292 Dated and received 4th I ov ember 1938. For information. Sultan informed me today that he proposes to leave for Dhofar between December 7th and December 15th and return to Muscat about middle of January 1939• Poli tical /ft. Sit-s ' iP. Z. 6079/1938, 109/21 UNION OF iOUT 'UICa, iO'.:TH .FRIO... hOQ3a, TR ilfCr. .R O . . . , LONDO:, .0.2. 1 bth .utjast, 193^. lily dear Secretary of State, Acting on the instructions of my Qov:rn;rient, I have the honour to invite your attentio to Jr. McDonald's ^ f -7 despatcu ni No. 10 of the 5tii lay, 193Q» and to offer the following observations witn regard to the sabject matter thereof. His Majesty^ aovern eat in the Union of :0a .h frica have perased the draft treaty betv,\,.c . tiie iJnitod ia^dom and Muscat and wish to draw attention to several articles thereof, viz. Articles 1, 13-15&gt; 2'J and 2';, '..'hicu, accordiiig to their view, constitute a departure fro the aadorou din,, arrived at, in 197? rc.5ardini tne rcs active s^here action of the several Gove n Lents of His iajesty in 1 act of nationals and the interests of nationals ox each l..i ■oi of the 0ommonweal th. It will be rcmeabered tiiit iu ...U) coromon cause then that the mere fact of a person bein^ a British subject does not entitle any Member of ^ae Commonwealth of Nations to treat him as its national a ad exercise in regard to him the jurisdiction and i aic oi aib which any Government ordinarily exercises in rota-ect oi persons who are its nationals. His Majesty * s Government in the Jnio.a -jeiiH-s -'^.-oa^ii '.l^ for regulating the treaty relations which taey ui^n ^0 exi^o between the Union and any other country, and for stipulating benefits for sach of His Majesty's subjects as are nationals of the Union, feel that in the draft Treaty in sjuesLion this aspect of the case did not receive due attention, in as/ Sight Honourable Lord Stanley, P.O., M. P. » . secretary of State for iommion iiiiaiio, Domi ni ons Off ice.2. as the articles referred to above pur ort to affect als ; His Majesty 's subjects who are nationals of the Union, ships and aircraft registered in the Union and goods of Union origin imported into J.as cat, and, farther, contains n .'71 ! » ^ ^ H ' ^ f r t ■ , r an accession clause (article 20) which, although usual in multilateral treaties intenoed ^o be of general ujplLci.tion, is very rare in bilateral a : :ree :ients, and, within t e British .mpire, canie int .- use at a ti le the United ... :do.a was seized of the power and the responsibility, to regulate, at least formally, the relations betwe ;n Its colonies and foreign countries. If, with respect to the acces. ion clause, other Members of the G o fiua. on w e a It h would lilce the old practice to continue, the Union G-overnment would not raise any luruher objection than the above to its raaintenance in the irL.cU4 , but&gt; in regard to the other articles, they i eel uha^ something should be done in order to obviate what one; ieel would be an encroachment, on the part of His ..viajest,/ - Government in the United Kingdom, upon a iield oi a-- b-on legitimately falling within the scope of the autaon u- of His Majesty 1 s Govern tent in the Union. As the draft submitted now stands, the treaty ie one exclusively between the United Kingdom and Muscat. Article 19 shows that it is not intended to apply e^n b the colonies and dependencies of the United Kingdo.a, .nless rendered applicable to such territories by further special action. This being the case, all encroachment coulw., it is submitted, be avoided by confining the Treaty to Jntisn subjects, wh &gt; are nationals of the United Kingdom, oi «re connected with territories subject to the jurisdict.LO.; of His I.lajesty 's (Jovernaent in the united Kingdoa, and to ships and aircraft registered in the United .ingdoa or m territories subject to the jurisdiction of His Maje^y 's Ctove rnment/II 'm 3. Government in the United Kingdom. Tovision co.ild then be made in the accession clause for the apj.lication of the clauses of the treaty to s.icu of His Majesty 1 s subjects as are under the- jurisdiction, an.I such ships and aircraft as are registered in tue territory, of the iierriber of the Commonwealth who accedes to the Treaty. nny .e iber of the British Com lonwealth of Nations who wishes to enjoy Ux benefits of the Treaty could then accede theretj, so ^..:.;,t the necessity for making .rovisions such as t _ose c ned in Article 21 would full away. It woulu 'be much appreciated by my &gt;ovornaent If tiie Government of the United kingdom c .-ula see their wa clear to reconsider the ten-xs of the draft Treaty in the lijht of the above observa11 ond» witu a viev/ to relieving them of the embarrass in,; positiOii in which tiiey have been olaced 'by the provisions now appearing thereia. The difficulties arising from the use of Uoo wide terras necessitating restrictive provisos, as well as the continuance of a practice which nas becoae obsolete, v /oald thus be duly provided against. tielieve me, Yours sincerely, (Sgd. G. T. te Water.■f : .7066/36 j^nclosu.. © ia Dominions Oi 1 !. ico covo'' &gt; i' , ^. ^, ■ note elated 14th October ? 19 3o. DOLIIITIulTS OPliTCE, S .'7.1. 14th Octoher ? 19 „ My dear High Cor.ini ssioner ? j. The questions dealt with in your letter of the 16th August to the Secretary of State regarding; the draft Treaty 'between the United Kingdoin. and huscat have 'been car efullv considered 'by the competent Departments of His Majesty's Government in the United riingdonip and I am now in a position to communicate to you the views of His Majesty's Government on the points raised. i. The Articles of the draft Treaty to which His Hajesty 1 s Government in the Union have called attention fall into two ! 'Ul ... • ^ \■ ' ^ ) categories ? namely ? Articles 1', 20'and 21, which are general provisions of a type which it has 'been customary for many years past to include in general Commercial Treaties negotiated on ^— •; -1^© •• ■'.* ' f 'behalf of the United Kingdom, and Articles 1. ? 14 and 15 which relate to the securing of special extra-territorial rights in the territories of the Sultan of Muscat; and it will be convenient to deal separately with these two categories. £ , As stated above, the Articles in the first category follow existing practice in regard to the draft ng of Commercial Treaties. This practice is based on the recommendations contained in a Heport of the Drafting Committee of the Inter- Imperial Relations Committee of the Imperial Conference of 1^50 which were accepted by the representatives of the G-overnments then present 3 exceot those of tile Irish ./roe State; a copy ox 'the Report of the Committee is annexed for convenience ox reference. Since that time His Majesty's g-overnment m the United Kingdom have included provisions based on the recommend ations of the Report in all their draft Commercial xreatics; T fc pr . recent/ • Ja-cer ? Esq.2. recent examples may 'be t ound in the Commercial Treaty with Siani; signed on the 23rd November, 1937 (Treaty Series No.33 (1938) - Cmd. 5731) and the Commercial Treaty with the French and Tangier Zones of Morocco signed on the 18th July last (Cmd. 5823). As nothing occurred during the Imperial Conference of 1937 to suggest that the recommendations of 19 30 should he departed from, His Majesty's Government in the United Kingdom have felt bound, in the absence of an indication that a change is desired by all the Governments concerned, to adhere to the practice recommended in 19 30. I should add, as regards the proposed Treaty with Muscat, that, as the terms of the draft have now been agreed with the Sultan of Muscat, and as the conclusion of a new Treaty is urgently required in replacement of the existing Treaty which is shortly due to expire, we feel that it would be impracticable to suspend the final conclusion of the proposed Treaty pending consultation between the Governments concerned; we should not, of course, wish to suggest that this would preclude such consultation as to the inclusion of provisions of this character in future Commercial Treaties. The provisions of the draft Treaty with Muscat relating ljjh*- ' *■¥ ' v- • / t 5 &gt; ■ ' ' to extra-territorial jurisdiction (i.e. Articles 13, 14 and 15) stand on a somewhat different footing. In the first place, however, it may be pointed out that the provisions oi the new Treaty do not invo3-ve any change m this respect, but are designed substantially to maintain existing rights. Moreover, in the case of a small country like Muscat where the native courts are extremely primitive and the local laws unsuitable in many respects for application to persons of European origin and wnere there is no institution such as the Mixed Courts in ^gypt a.b an alternative, the right of recourse to a Court maintained b^ tn^ United Kingdom and the application of the law of British mdia rather/ a mm I M a# - m/ F'M rather than local law must ? it is thought 5 'be considered as indisputable a 'benefit, as are any of the other rights proposed to he obtained for British subjects generally under other provisions of the Treaty. The discussions which took place at the time of the Imperial Conference? 1937 ? and subsequently5 regarding the application of extra-territorial jurisdiction, were understood 'by His Majesty's Government in the United Kingdom to he related to the exercise of jurisdiction when olotained 'by treaty and not to the question of treaty provisions. They would consequently 'be more relevant to the later stage? namely? the issue of Orders in Council for the exercise of rights secured 'by treaty. The United Kingdom Government do not v/ish to dissent from the view * that in general the exercise of extra-territorial jurisdiction in foreign countries in respect of British subjects belonging to the Union of South Africa must be regarded as exercised with the consent of His Majesty's Government in the Union; they would be quite willing? if the Union Government should so desire? that the Order in Council v/hich will eventually require to be passed for the exercise of such jurisdiction should be expressed to be passed at the reouest and with the consent of the linion u-overn- ment? or? alternatively? if that course were preferred? that the Union authorities should themselves make the necessary cu-r'ange- ments for passing the Order required in respec 0 oi British subjects belonging to the Union. We feel? however? biiat one Union Government may well consider that Muscat? 07 reason 01. iukj special position? can properly be treated as standing m a different position from other foreign countries where extra territorial jurisdiction is or has been until receriol^ enjoyed-, such as China? Egypt and Morocco. Legally and technically? Muscat is an independent State and his Majesty o Lro .^eiin the United Kingdom do not exercise jurisdiction there over foreigners/A foreigners in general. In practice ? however ? owing to the influence exercised there through the Government of India and the political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Muscat stands in a special position which has considerable resemblance to that of a British protected State. In the case of British protected states - as for example the Persian Gulf Sheikhdoms of Koweit and Bahrein - it is assumed th^t His I.Iajesty's Government in the Union would not think of questioning the right of His Majesty's Government in the United Kingdom to exercise juris diction over the rights of persons belonging to the Union as over other classes of British subjects? and other non-natives such as United States citizens or French nationals. Having regard to the special position of Muscatj it is thought that the Union Government may feel it preferable to adopt a similar attitude to the exercise of extra-territorial jurisdiction in Muscat and not to regard it as necessary to indicate by one or other of the means outlined above that authority in the territory concerned over British subjects belonging to the Union is exercised on the advice of Ills Majesty's Government in the Union. An early expression of the views of the Union Government on the question of the Order in Council for cae continued exercise of extra-territorial jurisdiction ox iuuscat would be appreciated j as we should like to proceeo. as soon as possible with the drafting of the necessary Order. The necessity for bringing the new Treaty into xorce next February and the time required for the various legal formalities would make it very desirable to put this in hand at the latest by the middle of December ? and 3 if we have not heard further from the Union Government by then; we trust that we may assume that they concur in a draft being prepared on the basis suggested above. Yours sincerely 5 Sd. Devonshire.}7^/39 •i**' - —s * ,2.7066/38. DO MINIONS OF FICI ±j 3 O 'ITtT 1 o » V V . J. . 14th October, 1938 Dear Scallan, ^ ^ The Secretary of State's letter of today's date replies co the liigh Cornrnissioner 1 s letter of the 16th August on the subject of the draft Commercial Treaty with Muscat. There are two points not dealt with in the Secretary of State's letter which I have 'been asked to mention to you informally, l . ? You v/ill see that in paragraph 5 of the Secretary of State's letter he refers to the question of consultation with the other G-overnments of the British Commonwealth concerned. i/Ve have not included in the letter any suggestion as to the mode of consultation as we assume that, if the Union Government wish to pursue the matter ? they might prefer to undertake such consultation themselves. We should, of course ? 'be quite willing to do so if the Union Government desired. ^ r r,% In paragraph 5 of the Secretary of State 's letter, the question of consultation as to the use of ohe provisions in question in future Commercial Treaties is also mentioned, I ought to say that there are several other Commercial Treaties now in contemplation, one drafts of which include provisions of :ne K ind in question, e.g. with Chile , and Colombia ? negotiations for v/liich have already begun, as the Union Government have been informed. I have been asked to say that, while we do not vvish to prejudice the general question, we feel that it might oe rather embarrassing for us if the suggestion w^xe made Scallan, Esa. that/35/86 Telegram Jrom To Repeated Copy by mail to % Secretary of sitate for India, londoii. 1oli tical He aident, Bushire• Political ^gent, Muscat. Governmeat of India, -uew I)eIhi • Ho. 1979 Dated 17th received 18th -overaber 1938. l MaiiWa a ^ . » .^j Your Express Letter of November 4th H0.555-S. MUSCviT TH^ a TY. I am informed that Arabic translations of Articles 12 and 19 enclosed with Political Agents ✓ b. iS^ letter of October 12th differ considerably j.nd not only in respect of amended •oassages from ^rabic translation enclosed with your Kxpiress Letter of July 15th and are open to i . criticism. further 1 understand that^translation oi remain ing articles even when corrected in accordance with your letter of November 4th still contains several errors mainly grammatical and perhaps due to clerical mistakes but which it is undesirable to retain in a state document. Owiu^ to difficulty of telegraphing corrections it is proposed if you see no objection to send both to you and to political Agent, Muscat, by next Saturday's air mail a copy of com plete Arabic text embodying and indicating corrections thought necessary. translator will keep corrections down to minimum which he considers really necessary. Jhou^h in other circumstances he would have wished to suggest more extensive changes. On receipt of revised translation Political Agent could consult Sultan again and telegraph briefly whether and with what exceptions the changes are agreed to. Secretary of State for India.35/101 and 35/86 / Telegram From To ^0.365 Dated the 18th November 1938• I oil tical nQsideiitf Bushlre • i oli tical Agent, Muscat# S-' 1 114 p \1' . ^ /t /t' MvJLnanedlately preceding telegram and your telegram No#1292 of iMovember 4th« 2» The treaty In signature form should be with us towards the end of December* Could Sultan postpone his visit to Jhofar until first half of January when 1 would vieit Muscat for signature ? If he agrees to this he would be free to stay at Dhofar as long as he likes. If he goes in December he will have be back for signature of treaty by mid-January as present treaty expires in February# 3. tleaee telegraph Sultan*s decision. Britconsul to ; '-k I/ 35/lCl &amp; 55/66 Telegram ^ From Political Age lit, ^uccat# To lolitical iiesideiit, iiushire. l.o. 170 • Jated and received 2C.th - overnber 1938. Your telegram ^ 0.363 of 16th lovernber. Sultan regrets he calicot postpone his departure He gives an assurance that he will back in Muscat by middle of January as he has no desire to re ma in longer in DnOi&lt;AK* POIITIJa L/ . ^ Telegram ^ ■^'rom Political Resident, Jiushire. To Political Age r. t, Mu scat. Ho.36S. Dated the 2ist November 1956. j My telegram ^0.362 dated the 16th November. Matter must be settled by you with Sultan before latter leaves for Dhofar. I lease keep me informed of progress. BRITCOISIJX. . ■ly .w 'j Mi3679A INDIA OFFICE, POLITICAL Department. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). f r (N.B. Ttiis is an ongiDtil messagG, sGnt oy air rnail to save telGgraplii^ expense, but intended to bo treated on receipt with, the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. It has been drafted as if it were so despatched.) ic From Secretary of State. Government of India, External Affairs Department, Repeated to Political Resident in the Persian Gulf and to the Political 15th November, 1938. To Dated No. P. Z. 7585/38. RESIDENCY . •••• 'cONFiDENfiAL RECORDS ^ P Muscat Treaty. Please see references to Article 7 in Political Resident's express letter of the 15th - -■ July No.390-S ? and enclosures thereto. Sultan's request for written assurance to effect that Persian Gulf . A Lighting and Buoying Committee will reduce their total- dues in proportion to reduction in their present expenses 'brought ahout by arrangement under (a) of draft letter. Board of Trade for their part see no objection, while pointing out that Government of India are the authority to reduce the dues, acting on the advice of the Committee. Are you prepared to authorise Political Resident to give desired assurance? The issue of the above has been duly authorised. J P. QIBSONfsp 3679A INDIA OFFICE, FFICE. S^j^Co ■ POLITICAL (EXT) I H Department. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). (N.B.— This is an original message, sent by air mail to save telegraphic expense, but intended to be treated on receipt with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. It has been drafted as if it were so despatched.) From Secretary of State, political Resident in the Persian Gulf^ rp, pOJ-lTjlUa-L IttJti JLU-dJ. U XU OUC JT C i O -L ciii VTUJ-X* 10 Repeated, with enclosures, to Political Agent, Muscat. without Arabic enclosures, to Government of India, Dated ^gth November, 1938. External Affairs Department* No. P. Z.7662/38 •t' i% b ' BUSHIRE RESIDENCY. DatQ...'?rJ l'!/•*?.. CONFIDENTIAL RECORDS Reference my telegram of the 17th Noveniber, No. 1979* Muscat Treaty. I enclose copy of the Arabic text which it is proposed, subject to your views and with the 3ultan T s concurrence!, to adopt in preparation of signature copies. It embodies certain corrections in the text which has already b^en agreed upon with the Sultan (including revised text of Articles 12 and 19 enclosed with —- * your express letter of the 4th November, No. 555-S)• These corrections, which are understood to be self-oxplanatory, are considered essential for grammatical or other reasons# If you see no objection please consult Sultan and telegraph His Highness^ views. 2« You villi observe that translator has inserted in Arabic your name and designation in the preamble ana your name in the signature clause. If any corrections are required here please indicate them. Certain minor changes have also been maoe in the English text which however v/ill presumably not require to be mentioned to the Sultan. Apart from improvements in punctuation these arc - (a) In Article l(ii)» lines 2 and 8, omit 'the term'^ -3 Repetition of these words is avoided in sub- sect 10ns (i)(iii) and (iv) of the Article* L.&gt; ? |&lt;? Af('b) In Article 13(3)., line 2^ substitute 'nor 51 for 'or 11 • (c) The following corrections are required in the list of amendments enclosed with your letter to the Sultan of the 8th July 0 .- i ^ &gt; (i) Article 2(l), 19th line. The amendment should 'be - Before 11 shall' insert 51 they'• (ii) Article 11. The pnrase to he substituted should 'be 'v/hosenational he may be'. (iii)Article 13(1). The amendment should read 'subject to any right of appeal which His Majesty may provide'. This correction involves a change in the Arabic text also; which has 'been made in the enclosed copy. r A corrected copy of the English text is enclosed. 4. You will note that in English text your signature will precede that of Sultan. This is due to fact that treaty will 'be printed for signature in a form which v/ill not permit space for the signatures side oy side. This also applies to signature copies in Arabic. There would 'be no objection in principle to oultan s signature preceding yours in the Arab ic copies, out bnio would involve reversal of order of names in the pieamole and the signature clause of the Arabic text. This could no doubt be arranged, if you think it desirable, but as Arabic translation accepted b3 r Sultan follows j^ngli^h text he will presumably not object to ordei of sign^tur also following that of the English copies. The issue of the above has been duly authorised-F sew^SSS#-'--* - '■ ^ ^ ■X ft '■—Oct-ib! i ' i ' :—i /' r/^-r — j ■ His Majesty The Kino: of Great Britain, Ireland and the British Dominions beyond the Seas, Emperor of India, and Sultan Saiyid Said bin Taimur bin Faisal, Sr. It an of Muscat and Oman and Dependencies, Desiring to confirm and strengthen the friendly relations which new subsist between them and to promote and extend their c o rnme r c i a 1 relations b y the conclusion of a new treaty to replace the Treaty of Friendship, Commerce and Favigation signed at [Juscat on the 19th March, 1891, wnich terminates on trie 11th Feoruaiy, l.-'oJ^ Have accordingly appointed as their plenipotentiaries;— His Hadesty The King of Great Britain, Ireland and the British Dominions beyond the Seas, I^peror of India (hereinafter referred to as H-s Majesty): For Great Britain ana rTorbhej.n Ireland: ^ we.cae, jjtot. Cal. Sift ^ vor India: _ ^ „ rjX/= Si. F ^ u FolUli.al&gt;- «' 6v'f ; The/\ V Article 1 » For the purposes of the present Treaty ~ (i) The terra r 'territories of His Majesty' or '''territories of the one (or the other) High Contracting Party' in relation to His Majesty shall mean the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Northern Ireland and India? and any territories to which the present Treaty applies 'by reason of extensions under Article 19 or accessions under Article 20; and the term u territories of the Sultan* or u territories of the one (or the other) Hi^h Contracting Party' in relation to the Sultan shall mean Oman and its Dependencies. (ii) The term 'nationals of His Majesty' or t-feo torn 'nationals of the one (or the other) High Contracting Party in relation to His Majesty snail mean all subjects of His Majesty and all persons under His protection? wherever domiciled^ Bxcept nationals of Koweit, Bahrein, Qatar, A'du Dhabi, Dit&gt;ai, Sliarjah, Ajwan, Umm -al Qfi'.vain, Has-al-Khaimah and Kalba and, for _ _r&gt; a -v-i h* i p i p ^ 131 14- an d 15- the purposes oi Ax iicieo ^ -i -p v,^ of the Aden nationals of tne Protectorate and nationals of Zanzibar of Omani origin who own property in 0man &gt; and the term 'nationals of the Snltan' or Wl ,. 0 'nationals of the one (or the other) High Contracting Party' m relation -.n moan all the Sultan 's to the Sultan shall mean a-i- , o-« p vpr domiciled. i ; ox the subjects? whore vol aum-i purposes/purposes of Articles 2, 5 ? 4, 5, 6, 13, 14 and 15^ the word t5 nationals' shall be ueeried to j/nclude corporate 'bodies created under the law of the territories of the High Contracting Party concerned. ( iii) 1'he tern 'British vessels' 1 or 'vessels of one (or trie other) High Contracting Party' in relation to His Majesty shall mean all ships registered under the law of any part of the British Commonwealth of nations, including any territory under the sovereignty, protections suzerainty or mandate of His Majesty except K. owe it, Bahrein ? Qatar 5 Abu Dhabi ? D^baij Sharjah? Ajman, Umm-^1- Qa wa i n ? H a s - a 1 - Kh a i ma h and Ka lb a ^ and the A term 'Omani vessels' or ''vessels of one (or the other) High Contracting Party' in relation to the Sultan shall mean all ships registered by the Omani Crovernment and entitled to fly the flag of the Sultan. (iv) The term 'British aircraft 1 * or 'aircraft of one (or the other) High Contracting Party' in relation to His Majesty shall mean all aircraft registered under the law of any part 01 the British Commonwealth of Nations ? u n--irier the sovereignty, including any territory unaci protection, suzerainty or mandate of Kis Majesty except ICowcit, Bahrein, Q^tai , A Dhabi&gt; Dihai, Saarjah, Ajman, uram-to- qawain, Ras. al- Khaimah and Kalha; and the term tt q 'i c i'it 01 one \ 01 'Omani aircraft' or axxeiaib the other) High contracting Party xa relation/tr % ^ &gt;• relation to the Sultan shall mean all aircraft registered 'by the Omani Government. (v) The term 'foreign country 11 shall mean in relation to His Majesty any country or territory not under the sovereignty, protection ? suzerainty or mandate of His Majesty, and, in relation to the Sultan, any country or territory not 'being a part of the territories of the Sultan.% U- Article 2 . (i) ihcro shall 'be perfect freedor.i of commerce and navigation 'between the c err iter ies of the High Contracting Parties, o-jacn .ulgii Contracting Party shall allow the nationals of the other to enter ail 'oortSp creeks and rivers with their vessels and cargoes &lt;, also to travel? reside and pursue commerce and trade5 whether wholesale or retail, in his territories provided, as regards nationals of the Sultan, that they satisfy and observe the conditions and regulations applicable in the territory of His Majesty in question to the entry, travel, residence and departure of all foreigners, and provided that nationals of His Majesty satisfy and observe the conditions applic able in the territories of the Sultan in regard to the entry of foreigners and that^ in proceeding from the place where they reside in the territories of tne Sultan to another place in his territories where for eign subjects do not already reside^ thoy shall, before doing so, notify in writing the local Omani authorities of the place- where they reside, and such authorities shall inform them whether the intended om -i +■ o'hi for them to travel destination is suitable xOx t -' . 4- 0 f (-I t - authorities in Guestioii. to or not; 11 ^no auuuuxa.u ■ aid nationals in writing that notify the said ir the intended des tination i « nnnill itable, ana the s i d n a t i o n a 3- s p e r s. t s in travelling they should to their destination, 01 &gt; g_ 2. au t n or i t i ^ o 0 -p fail to notify the i-oc their intended movemenu o , they will -procoeu/Article 5 , (1) ax i o n al s o i' E i s 1.1 ijl j e s t y s hal 1 enjoy throughout the territories of the Ooi-L tan v/i tn j . es ject to coinmerce^ shipping and the exercise of trade all the rights, privileges, immunities, aovantages and protection, of whatsoever nature, enjoyea by the nationals of the Sultan or the nationals of any other f o r e ign c o untry. (£) They shall not be liable to taxes, duties, imposts, restrictions or obligations of any description whatever, other or more onerous than those xo which the nationals of the Sultan or the nationals of any other foreign country are subjected. (3) In all that relates to navigation and the treatment of shipping, the Sultan undertakes xo t reat British vessels not less favourably in any respect than Omani vessels or tne vessels of any other foreign country. The provisions of this Article relating to vessels apply also to the passengers and cargoes carried therein.Art! olc _4. l^axioiitils of His Majesty ohall u u ^ a ^ -i fc t - a i.1 t ae 'territoric s of th e Suxt an to rare or to acquire, by gift, purchase, intestate succession, v/ill, or any other legal manner, land, houses, and property of every description, vaie tuer liiovaole or inniiOvaDlc, to possess tne saae, eid i roe 1 y to aispose thereof by sale, barter, donation or otherwise on the same conaitions in respect of immovable property as are or may be established with regard to the nationals of the most favoured foreign country and in respect of movable property as are or may be established with regard to the nationals of the Sultan or the nationals of the most favoured foreign country.11 ^ Articl e _5. 'v i ) r t i c 1 e s o p ocTuc ed or manof a ctured in the territories of His Majesty imported into the territories of the Sultan, from whatever place arriving, shall not 'be tillo j e c i,ij d i, o du t i e s or cha rge s othe r or nigher tnan those paid 03.1 the lilce articles ^rodaced or manufactured in any other foreign country. (2) I\'0 other or higher duties or charges shall he imposed in the territories of the .Saltan on the exportation of any article to the territories of His Majesty than such as are payable on the exportation of the like article to any other foreign country. ( 3 ) Til e i mp o r t du ties 1 e vi ah 1 e in the territories of the jiiltan on goods produced or manufactured in the territories of His Majesty and on goods imported by nationals of His Majesty shall be paid at the port or other _:lace in the Sultan's territories where the goods are first importedj and on payment thereof such goods shall thereafter be exempt vithin the said territories from ail other Customs duties. (i^.)Customs duties shall not be levied in the territories of the jultan on goods produced or manufactured in the territories of His Majesty or imported by nationals of His Majesty in the following cases, namely:- (a)/1. o Article 5 (continued) . (a) On gooas v/hich, being destined and manifested for a foreign country, are transnipped from one vessel or aircraft to another in any of the ports or airports of the Sultan or which have been for this purpose provisionally landed and deposited in any of the Sultan's custom houses to await the arrival of a vessel or aircraft in which to be reshipped abroad; but goods so landed shall only be exempted if the consignee or his agent shall have, on the arrival of the vessel or aircraft, handed over the said gooas to be kept unaer customs seal, ana declared them as landed for transhipment, designating at the same time the foreign place of destination, and if within a period not exceeding three months after their first landing the said gooas are actually shipped for the said foreign country as originally declared and without having in the interval changed owners, and if all customs charges are paid before they are reshipped, (b) On goods which, not being destined and manifested tor the territories of the Sultan,have been inadvertently landed, provided that ^ ._ n t in the custody of such gooas are left m w tj-je customs authorities and are ,,i n ati on abroad . • TOT cl U-Oo L/X x v- reshipp^ 1 J - 01 tyi thin/ Hi' ; ■Articl — xrJL-il ( continued). vv 1 'i hi n t \7o .mcnthnL of b e i ng g q i ani ; 111Co g ciXx c u s uOi fi s cii c.r* £'.' e s thu g-oodo are re shipped. (c) On coal, fuel and oil, Naval and. Air .force provisions and stores and littings, the property of His Majesty, .10.e a, and are paid before landed in the territories of the Sultan foi ohe use oi the ships of His Majesty' Naval Forces and the aircraft of Jfis Air Forces^ duty shall, however, be payable if any of the goods thus exempted are sola or otherwise disposed of in the local markers. ( dj On gooas transhipped or landed pending the repair of damage caused to the vessel or aircraft by stress of iveather or disasters at sea or in the ai r, provided t he o argo s o aisc harged shall be left in the custody of the customs author i 11o s and be r e shi ppe a abroad v/ithin a period of three niontiis from the date of the original landing and that all customs charges have do en pai a. (5) In the cases referred to in •paragraph (4) above customs ioimiali ties in respect of landing, examination, clearance and shipment of goods are to be observed. (6) All goods remaining uncleared in the Sultan's customs houGos_ after four months from trie date of inicii. original/ ■ 'M ■ Hga .'■rMr il; s3..l ± ojs loiiie duties 1 ©viable -i.ii the territories cf the Sultan ah all be paid in cash and net in icind. (c) The value of the goods on whioh dutjr is to be levied shall be xixed according to their market orice following the normal usage of trade in Mi scat• (3 ) '1'he Sultan 1 s Governnient shall have the right to fix the valuations for customs purposes of any descriptions of goods for any period^provided such valuations are fixed by a tariff board appointed by the Sultan consisting of equal numbers of the Sultan's nat ionals and nat io nals of His MaJesty representing the merchant community and presided over by the Director of the Sul t a j . i ! s Cu 31 o m s. (4) In the event of any dispute arising between a national of His majesty and the Customs House Authorities regarding the value of any goods, this shall be determined by reference to two experteacn j-yai tj nominating one^ and tne valut oO ascertained shall be decisive. Should however these experts not be able to agree ? they shall choose an umpire, who-se decision is to be consiacred ■; ; -v-s;'Art ic le 7. The Sultan's Government has the right to charge all vessels entering any of the ports in the Sultan's dominions with shipping ? tonnage? or harbour dues^to 'be administered under the control of a special board appointed by the Sultan for the improvement of the harbour and construction and maintenance of lighthousesp etcetera. f'-ng .rticle 8. Internal duties? taxes or fees levied \. r ithin the territories of either high Contracting Party for the benefit of the State, or of organs of local or municipal government, on or in connection 'with goods produced or manufactured in the territories of the other Party, shall not he other or greater than the duties, taxes or fees levied in similar circumstances on or in connection with goods of national or any other origin.(1; vto pr ohi b i t i on or restrict! on sh:iii be- imposed or maintained on the importation into the territories of one Saltan of any article ? from './natever place arriving, produced or manuf-actured in oliu territories of His Majesty v/iiich shall not equally extend to the importation of the like articles produced or manufactured in any other foreign country. (2) No prohibition or restriction shall be imposed or maintained on the exportation of any article from the territories of the Sultan to the territories of His Majesty v/hich shall not equally extend to the exportation of the lixe articles to any other foreign country. (3) Exceptions to the general rule laid aown in the foregoing paragraphs may be made only in the case of (a} prohibitions or restrictions imooscd in the incerests ol puo—ic sec an ty I (b) prohibitions or restrictions regarding traffic in arms, ammunition and implements of war,, or, in exceptional circumstances, all Ouher mi lit a r y sup i' 1 i e s ; (c)/Art icle 9 (continuod) (c) prohibitions or restrictions imposed tor the protection of public health: (d) prohibiti ns or restrictions imposed for the protection of animals or plants, includiny protection against diseases, degeneration or extinction? as well as measures talc en against harmful seeds, plants and c ■. n imals •Article 11 , ijj.ther of the two High. Contracting .arties may appoint consuls to reside in the territories of the other? subject to the consent and approval of the other as regards the persons so appointed and the places at 'which they reside. Such consuls shall at all tiuies he accorded in the country in which they reside treatment and privileges not less favourable taan consuls of the most favoured foreign country. Bach of the High Contracting Parties further agrees to permit his ovm nationals to he appointed to Consular Offices by the other Contracting Party? provided always that the uerson so appointed shall not oegin to act without the previous approbation of the High Contracting Party twhosc national ho may be..Art icle_ _1 o. (1) Trie Consular authorities of Majesty in t-o torriteMpn ev? the. Saltan ii.ncij.xj.qitljjecc go afty ripjht of av/ooal wliicb. His Hajosty may provide, try and determine (1) all criminal charges against nationals of His Majesty; (ii) all civil suits in which nationals of His L-ajesty are defendants; (jii) all 'bankruptcy cases in which the hanmrupt or the person whom it is sought to make 'bankrupt is a national of His Majesty; (iv) all proceedings connected with administration of the estate of a deceased national of His Majesty: a (v)yui c i ue st ions of persona 1 status where the person whose status is in question is a national of His Majesty, always provided that where such person is a Moslem the Consular authorities may remit the case for decision 'by a Moslem religious court of the Sultan on such conditions as they may determine and shall so remit the case if any other party to the proceedings is a national of the Suiten. (2) All criminal or civil cases in which a national of His Majesty is complainant or plaintiff and the accused or defendant is a iintional of the Sultan or a national of a third country shall to triod and determined toy the courts ol the/Article 1-3 (con tel.) tne Sultan. xhe national of His Majesty shall have a right of appeal to the Sultan, in accordance with the procedure prescribed in the Omani courts, against any decision given against him. in any such case if the Consul of His Majesty shall so request. If the Sultan should 'be absent the appellant may, if he so desires, ask that his appeal may he heard 'by the Sultan's representative. (3) H national of His Majesty shall not 'be arrested his property seized, nor his house, office, warehouse or other premises occupied by him entered and searched without his consent, by an officer of the Sultan save under an order signed by the Consul of His Majesty and any national of His Majesty arrested and any property of a national of His Majesty seised shall be placed in the custody of the Consul of His Majesty: always provided that, in case of necessity lor the prevention of breeches of the peace or a breach of a law or regulation of the Sultan which has been made applicable to nationals of His Majesty under Article 15, the authorities of the Sultan may without such an order arrest a national of His Majesty or take charge of his property or enter and search his house, office, warehouse or other premises occupied by him, but in this case the proceedinr -a shall be/*&lt;■ 4iiicle__ 14 In the exercise of their renpcoctive juriscl.ictions under paragraphs (1) and (2) of Article 13, the authorities of the Sultan and the dW-ular authorities of His Majesty shall afford every possible aid and faci111y ior satisfaction of the rightful claims of the nationals of one High Contracting Party against nationals of the other.The Consular authorities of His majesty v/ill5 at the request of the bultan ? appljr in the exercise of their jurisdiction under Article 13 all laws and regulations of the Sultan which it is desirable to apply ^ nationals of His Majesty in the territories of the Sultan, including5 in particular? laws and regulations imposing taxation or duties and police and municipal regulations» : ;'SL • ■ ■-—I—.iTat...onals of the t\7o High Contracting arties shall, T/ithin the territories of each other, enjoy freedom of conscience and religious toleration, the free and public exercise of all forms of religion, provided that such exercise does not vound or outrage the religious susceptibilities of the country in v/hich it is proposed to be practised, and the right to build edifices for religious worship in places specified for the purpose by local authorities. Nothing shall be done by either High Contracting '.arty that may disturb existing place s of vrorsh ip belonging t o nat i ona1s of the othe r.Article 1 9. (1) His Majesty may through his Consular' Officer at Muscat give notice of his desire that the present Treaty shall extend to any of his colonies s overseas territories or protectorates ? or to any mandated territory in respect of which the mandate is exercised 'by his Government in the United Kingdom P or to any of the States under his protection ? except Koweit ? Bahrein ? Qatar, Ahu Dhabi P c • i D$bai s Shar j ah5 A jman p Umm al Qav/ain ? Sas- A al-Khaimah and Kalha ? and the Treaty shall 'be extended to any territory specified in such notice as from the date thereof. (2) After the expiry of a period of tv/o years from the coming into force of the present Treaty^ either High Contracting Party may, 'by giving twelve months' notice ? terminate the application of the present Treaty to any territory to which it has 'been extended under the provisions of the preceding paragraph.i '■■■■ A rtiolo P. o (1) T P-G iI^ gh C o nt ra c t i ng iWbies agroe that Hie Majesty majy cy notification given through aoccde to the present Treaty in re spec o oi any Mernber o'£ the British Commonv/ealth of Nations v.-hose Government may desire that such accession should 'be effected. Any such accession shall take effect as from the date of notification thereof. (2) After the expiry of a period of tvo years from the coming into force of the present Treaty either High Contracting Party may, 'by giving twelve months' notice, terminate the Treaty as regards any country in respect of :-.hich notification of accession has been given under paragraph (l) of this Article. (3) Any notification made under paragraph (l) of this Article may include any dependency or mandated territory administered 'by the Government of the country in respect of which notification of accession is given and any notice given under paragraph (2) oi' this i -ircicle oiiall be applicable to any sucn dependency or mandated territory v.iiich was included in such notification ox accession. his Consular Officer at Muscatr *- - ' Article 22. U) Trie present Treaty has 'been executed in quadruplicate, two copies tjcxn &amp; written m English and two in Arabic. These are understood to te '&gt;1 similar import and signification; m trie erent, however, of doubt herealter arising as to the proper interpretation of the English or Arabic text of one or other of the Treaty stipulations, the English text shall be considered decisive.. v 2) ihc present Treaty shall be ratified, and ratifications shall be exchanged at ^Muscatit shall come into force on the 11th day of February, 1939 if ratifications have been exchanged before that date, or if they have not then been exchanged on the date of exchange of ratification;(1) The present treaty shall re;wain rorce for a period of 12 years i roiii tae date of its entry into force. Unless one of the High Contracting Parties shall have given to the other notice of termination one year before the expiry of this period, the present treaty shall renain in force until the expiry of one year from the date on which such notice shall have heen given. (2) A notice given under this Article sijodLl uiot afXect the ©/ xrati■ i gm? the Treaty a.s. 'bet'-men tiie torritoricts of the Sultan and any country or territory in respect of vhich notification of accession has 'been given under Article 20. It shall however apply to any territory to which notification of extension has heen given un de r Article 19» I n wi trie s s whe reef. . ^ : h! 1 / on 'behalf of His Majesty the King of Great Britain, Ireland and tne hribisn Dominions 'beyond the Seas, Emperor of India, and Sultan Saiyid Said bin Taimur 'bin Faisal, Sultan of Muscat and Oman and Dependencies, on his own hehalf,Ar t 1 c i a 23 (continued) have signed the saroe and affixed thereto their respective seals. I)one at Vus cat, this ^ay of 193 , corresponding to the of the year Hejira. Sreat Britain and Northern Ireland Sultan of Muscat and Oman and Dependencies. IndiaWith reference to Article 15 ? I desire to place on recoi d bne procedux'e which has 'been agreed on for the operation of this article. 1. If the Sultan desires that any law or regulation shall he made applicable to nationals of His Majesty, he will communicate a copy thereof to the Consul of His Majesty. The consul will post a copy of the law or regulation in his office and the law or regulation shall 'become applicahle to nationals of His Majesty one month after the date on which it is posted. It is, however, understood that at the request of the Sultan in case of urgency a shorter period shall 'be adopted. 2. (1) In the case of legislation imposing taxes or duties and of municipal or police regulations, the consul will always post the laws or regulations within two weeks of the receipt of the request from the oultan ( or within a shorter period in special cases of urgency) unless the laws or regulations are in conflict with Articles 2, 3, 4, 5, 8 or 10 of the present Treaty. (ii) In the case of legislation imposing customs duties, unless the law or regulation is in conflict with Articles 3, 5 or 6 of the present Treaty, the consul will post the law or regulation immediately upon receipt ox the request from the Sultan and the law or regulation shall 'become applicable to nationals of His Majesty within such period as the Sultan may direct. (iii) The same procedure as in suh-paragrapii (l) above will apply in the case of all other laws and regulations, unless in any particular case the consul of His Majesty submits to the Sultan serious reasons for the modification/modification of the lav/s or regulations to render them sui caol g for application to nationals of His Majesty or reasons v/liy such application is unnecessary. In the event o.c tue consul submitting such reasons the Sultan will consider the matter 3 and, if he does not see fit to accept the suggestions of the consul, will request that the question of the application of the law or regulation in question should 'be immediately referred to His Majesty's Government in the United Kingdom.35/86 P. L#No # P. z* 29 76, d/-30.4.38 (which was tne one usea iu Vol, A. 77 p.99. Karachi), alao tne .Note of tne changes made, wnicn was Ibid.p # 83 # sent to nim under Sir Trencnard Fowle's X.L,No.390-S, d/- p.128, 15.7,38, He has not got a copy of the Arabic text. rne Sultan nas tne same Snglign text, with tne corrections entered tnerein, as well as a copy of tne translation. It is quite possible tnat some or all of tne omissions wnicn occur in our copy of tne translation do not occur in tne Sultans, for tnat was prepared first and cnecKed by tne Sultan nimself, and tne copies for 1.0. and G.of I. and Bushire were tnen made from it. The instances or faulty translation will of course occur in tne Sultan's text as well. The best plan, tnerefore, would De for Major Watts to work on tne English text and Arabic translation neid oy tne Sultan. The former snould first be checKed with tne iMOte of changes (A. 77, p. 83} and tne Arabic translation s no aid tnen be cnecked in the lignt of Mr.Arberry' s Note. Instructions to Major 'fatts may issue by post, explaining tne above? 1-9 ye £ •'-v fk. ft. /4' v3 SQ V'/ H(Maa- *- L - tio- ct • '2/'/ i f Z 7 /. -- &lt;zf tz/. ^ zr/'o/^ '&gt; ■ 3 ?. - f /t (j This is satisfactory, especially tile Sultan's acceptance of tne larger amendment to Article 12 (2), Copy of PUC ma5 r be forwarded to India Office and Govt,of India withtne following comment. (a) The recommendation in Political Agents para- 3 may be concurred in. (b) There are two clerical errors (omission of ''al 1' before 'papers'* in the 19tn line of Article 12 (2), and substitution of 'of' for 'in' in the 3rd line of Article 12 (5), and some omissions in punctuation in tne same Article as set forth in Major Watts* letter No.0/137 d/-ll. 10.38 to the sultan, but these can be correctly inserted in tiie signature copies without reference to tne Sultan.. (c) Signature copies may now be prepared. (d) Also Instrument of full powers for you to sign Treaty. J- SScct«C ■*. ^ , 55^.5, e ^ i u[ii|5^ U&gt; ^ ci^cx, O^'c c . — / 3</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000182_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/1/413</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000182</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/1/413</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Muscat Treaty'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1938/1938</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-09-18T15:12:16</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (255 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged chronologically from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the system of foliation in use is the sequence of numbers written in pencil in the top right hand corner of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Correspondence relating to negotiation of Muscat Treaty in 1938. The Muscat Commercial Treaty 1891 had been renewed every year but in 1938 Sultan Said bin Taimur stated that he was not prepared to renew it further. Correspondence relates to the negotiations over a new treaty, the clauses and their wordings.Discussions in the correspondence included:Issue of appointment of Consular Officers to inland towns.Whether the treaty could be translated into classical or modern Arabic.Jurisdiction of nationals other than those defined in the 1891 treaty.Customs duties.Importation of items such as alcoholic liquors and tobacco by His Majesty's Consul for his personal use.Arrangements for obtaining Sultan's signature in Muscat or Dhofar.Includes side-by-side Arabic and English translations of draft clauses as well as a copy of the Arabic and English text proposed for the treaty. The final treaty was composed of 23 articles covering: nationals; aircraft; internal duties and taxes; prohibitions on imports; appointment of Consuls; assistance of vessels in distress; freedom of conscience and religious toleration; procedures for termination of the treaty; the equivalence of the Arabic and English version of the text of the treaty but where dispute English text was considered decisive; length of treaty. Also includes a confidential letter relating to Article 15. Correspondents include: Said bin Taimur [Sa‘īd bin Taymūr], Sultan of Muscat; Sir Trenchard Craven William Fowle, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf; Rutherford Berriman Tippetts, Board of Trade, London; India Office, Whitehall, London; Political Agent, Muscat.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Treaties</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000193.0x000182#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>