<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0000d8_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-11T18:49:36.722Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">COUJ* IDEJSTIAL fio. 26- S of 1932 British Residency &amp; Consulate-General, Bushire, the 20th January 1932. From The Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political submit in triplicate your Administration Report for the year 1931 as soon as possible, and in any event to reach Bushire not later than the 1st of March to enable the Hon'ble the PolitiCcil Resident to submit the full report for the sphere of the Residency before the 31st March. Resident in the Persian Gulf To The Political Agent Bahrain Sir, I am directed to request that you will kindly I hare the honour to be. Sir, Your obedient servant. Captain, Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.C’s. P. P.—L (in) 126—500-4-31. O) No. The Agency, Bahrain, Dated the 27th February *93 2 From n &lt;\(&gt; r\ v 1 rC To The Political Agent, BAHRAIN, The Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. % Sir, i have uie houoor to Forward herewith,in triplicate,my Annual heport on ine administration of the Ban rain islands. i nave the honour to be Sir, Your Most Obedient Servant, 'olitlcal Bahrain.3 1 i. dm ini 61 rat ion Report of the Bahrain Agency for the year 1931 • FKBSOMKL . Captain C*G.’rior iield ciiar^c of the j.^ncy tnroughout tne year. Khan Bahadur Saiyid Siddiq Hasan helu charge of tiie auties of Indian Assistant until the 14th April wuen he left for India being succeedeu by Khan Bahadur Abdul Haiy. Saiyid Cidui proceeued to andahar ffhere he had been transferred as British Consul. hs cad an exceptional knovleoge of ^ruoiCjmc his transfer -vas a great loss to the g^ency,for ue &lt;rfs taucu likeo ana reS|jectec both by ti*e ohaikhs and the leaning ^ercliatits. A^h TIL Al KalALIFA FA.ii.Y. ohaikh Hamad has been on oxcellent terns m.tn tiie Agency throughout the year,ana with tne return of Dr.Holmes nis health improved, lie agreed to a lJ.v cut in the Al Khalifa family allowances,but made no attempt to reauce his personal expenaiture and is now in financial difficulties. He has little sense of vaj.ues and gave unnecessarily large presents to his many visitors during tuo year. Hxs xcellency is of too generous a disposition fnd these sell invited visitors,who are almost all neighbouring ahaiiihs,havo no object in coming other than lining their pockets, ior in these parts the host is expected to give ms guests presents rno tip their servants l&amp;visnly. 3iiaikh Hamao cannot be made to raaliee that the he giveo to these people,the more will come to Bahrain, if taken to task,ilia Excellency will say that he ooes it to serve the oritish Government by demonstrating to his neighbours toe wealth ana Happiness he enjoys in the snadow of iiis Majesty's Governnent. shaikh Abdulla bin j.sa is apparently genuinely interested in his portfolio of ^auction,but snows e tendency to pass on the more disagreeable problems to the Adviser for disposal, lie tookhis usuiii hunting trips to the raninlnad, seeking bustsras ana beauin brides with e^uai zeal. ohsikh MtUmawad bin is&amp; proceeded to India for the sake of hia health at the close of the /ear# Ilia real object in fcoing was to save mone/,since he gets free tickets froa the British India Steam Navigation Compen/ and he finds lx* can live cheaper in Bombay than Bahrain. An improvement in the Manama Municipal it/ is always noticeable when hi® brother,Shaikh Abdulla,takes over his duties es Trecicent. shaikh Salman has done good work on the Bahrein Court and is the only member ol his family who is not afraia of hara work, ihe .^shrain Court are handicapped a tendency on the part of ohaifch Hamad to revise their cruers men tney give decisions unfavourable to prominent men,but with tte death of shaikh is&amp; and the accession of shaikh Hamau,Shaikh SaLaau»s position will become much stron^-er. Shaikh Salman is on excellent terms with the ngency. Shaikh haehid bin Muhammad is President of tm Jajlis al Urfi,or Com: ercxal Court,end also the hiving Court, a® has little influence,but has done quite well. shaikh kubarak bin Hamad shows uro.iise qJl the Lower danrain Court and has done well, ne lias not much character,but is the meet intelligent of tne Shaikh’s sons,and now that he has been provided witn glasses he is making most praiseworthy efforts to remedy his lack of education. 'in. .-olitioal Agent's efforts to persuade Shaikh harad to see that his two youngest sons,Caij and Aimd,receiTed some eoucation did not «eet with auoh success,but a local man has bean found to teach them two morning a week, it was suggested that turee mornings a week would be more useful,but His excellency felt this woulu be too wrest a strain for his lenjamin.Baij. (ir.heigrave proceeded on leave on tne 12th ,*ril ana returae- on the 23th October. Luring his absence Captain n arke acted3 . him. he was accorded &amp;d enthusiastic reception on his return, and tne Shaikh seeraea ^isa to have him back. The Jitatw is fortunate to have Hr.Bolgravd. he is likod by tne people ^ho realise that his work benefits them and he shows marked courage is oorsbatting niids on *»ne Bahrain finances froru whatever source. Captain 'arke acted for hr.Belgrave during tiie latter’s absence on leava,i» addition to dis own duties as Commandant of Police. He may best be described as having a fourth form brain on a field officer’s figure,ana he showed himself a poor substitute for Br.Belgmve. ue has not the courage of the latter in resisting rains on the ! t«te Treasury and is apt to ingratiate himself by increasing tne Civil List or attempting to do so. The Political Agent drew his attention to the fact that tne plrdtoon or so of Punjabi sepoys in his charge were getting steadily slacker,ana he replied ti*&amp;t he iiad noticea it too. He suiaefchat naively attributed it to the absence on leave of the Indian officer. Iur.de Grenier discharged his humcrua duties with his usual zeal, lie is not popular with a section of the merchants,indeed no nonest Director of Customs could ever be really popular,but His Excellency realises that he would h*ve much less money to spend if it were not for ,Mr.ae Grenier’s untiring efforts, and supports him. BAiduv IL i yh iOv,. Under tnis heading are grouped all tne forces of law ana order,consisting of tne Indian Armed ioiice,tLe local police, (or Lrsnch r oiice as they ere celled) enc the datura of night watchmen. The latter are an irregular bocy who do not wear uniform or perform any unila,out nre anaed with long Lee Lnfieia rifles. The nature are posteu at Badaiya,ilanaaa and Muharraq only. The strength of these bouies is given below.Masai4 . Indian Police,all ranks including clerk. {♦‘ollowerbjUiilorij^iatry etc., &gt;;rab Police,inciaUing four vijd&amp;go f ids^is and clerk. Nature. ‘jhe Bahrain Government have been training; local men to replace the Indians as the ag reements of the letter expire,and propose to substitute loc*?! men for tliefi remainder during 1932, since they can now be obtained in sufficient numbers. The Indians are relatively expensive and know little Arabic or Persian; they do not thrive in i:Jahrain ? 8S the climate seems as * trying to them as it is to Europeans. The recruits are mostly of negroid extraction since tne Arab objects to unilorra or discipline,but the Amirs on the mainland rely to a large extent on a. uimilnr type of man,and there is no reason why they should not do well. t LOOaivallv * i Sunni-Sdiah relations have deen good,and trie younger generation appear to have little religious animosity to other sects. Shaikh Abdulla and Shaikh AH bin Hasan continue to be trie Shiah siaddia. He former is an alert and intelligent man and bott! ere on very good terms with the Agency* The Sunni .^adhis are the] three Abdul La life and they are not on over goon terms with either the Bahrain Government or ti»a agency. They have so far defied all attempts to pHce the Sunni 'aqfs on a proper footing, but the policy of the State is to allow them to reauce them to greater chaos than they are already in before taking definite action in the matter. By some unhappy ever eight in the office of the High Co iaissioner at Begudaci, the prohibition against the return of Hhaikh Khalef was overlooked ana he was given a visa for Bfihrrin His return caused great alarm to the Lheih Qauhis,since he has strength on 1-1-31 71 6 £e!) Strength on 31-12-31. 50 o 43 50 235 221.5. iiwaense influenccjand tnej wore pacified witn uifiicuit/* The rolitical Agent warned 'Inaikii Khalaf tnat he would be returned to ira i if he gate further trouble# His ixoellenc/ at first his raina with Chirac t is tic wtsaknoss,anu asked the political Agent to agrt;e to aio regaining parmauently in ^hrain. in spite of his past record for ni&amp;ohief iwkiQg 9 it sooaied to the Political agent that it should be possible to prevent him giving trouble if he was allowed to stay,and ne did not care , to incur the odiua of opposing his return if tne Shaikii desireu him tc remain,so he refrained fro® opposing the suggestion# Shaikh Khalaf iis&gt;s ?ged very much in the last four years,but Id ‘men live a long Ui.a in bahraiu. he however,begun to show signs of the cloven hoof# There has been little serious crime end there hsve bt,en no affray took place between Persians anc Somalis at .uharraq# The subject matter 1 the dispute was a difference of dpinion between a Persian baker and b Pomeli customer regarding a penny loaf. Fortunately the bomtiis were heavily outnumbered or several The incident sho&gt;vo tnat nuhruin still possesses the elements of aiscoru. On the ECth Uay,i.bijor iioliaefa and five American employees of the Bahrain letroleuu Company arrived,anu were followed later by another five. About a tnousana tons of equipment followed by successive steamers,and drilling staitea in October,His excellency fhaikh Hamac working the drill for its first few blows. The rig quivered unuer tue impacts and Lis hxcellency glanced at it and The ^or ^nixation of the oil company is remarkable# Of the immense quantities of stores required,nothing was mislaid and determined only to alio# ^im a brief visit to Bsnrain but changed gang muroers or decoities# On the 4th of Lay,however,a serious people would have oeen killed sad ns it was a dozen were injured. said 'the machine is uruniL'. everything arrived on time.6* iVith the exception oi* iSajor Holmes, all the operating staff are Amoricans^nd the rig hanas are moatlv Iraqi, inf act except for tho Cikhs in the Fower i.ouse,ali art non , ! 5ritisii subjects, lajor Holies annoahced on his arrival iiiat they woulu eiaplo/ some 4oO men,but this figure has never oeen refcneu,and as soon as the camp was complete Ina nuiiiuer was rouucea to soue 30 or 90. rs lith the exception of Uiu hlssen huts which were made in England •diich tnoy are disoatisfied with,all tneir require ments from machinery to load pencils eeen importeu from the tfoited rtatos^nd thic influx has h&amp;u a ueciueu effect of introducing goods of American manufacture into the uazaer. it is sn interesting point that in sipto of tneir enthusiesm for things made in the dniteo htatos of America tuey have not fnf:de any rapprochement witn tho Arabian Mission,ano there is little love lost between them. The canp is fitted with everything that practical comfort could ougyest,and refrigerators,electric light and heaters,full length bsths and hot and cola showers ana water borne sanitation C* ni. are apparently sine qua non on 1 location 1 ,tnough they woulu be considered luxuries by most officials in India. The American employees tnat have been sent have so far proved tc be of a good type,ana have given little trouble, occasionally (none are teetollaers; one retires to his querter; and drinks hinself into a state of coma,but this is done in the privacy of their camp,ana no harm is aone. AliThCLxk ■ I Shniku hamau has naa great success with his well at KharzexLui,but has so far only been able to utilize a fraction of the water. As was notea last too much water is being wasted and Major Holies st* tes tlat the head of water,formerly 24 feet,is now only 17. He considers tne spring# in the sea should be blocked end all iurtner urilling stopped. #nen funus permit,it would pay the State to import a qualified engineer to advise them regaruing their policy with Artesian wells. 17. The work of the agriculturist has been restricted b the paucity of funds for experinents,but he has been occupieo on elementary Thaikh Hamad’s estates ana has given/instruction in some of tue schools, he also supervioea some experiments with cotton on land belonging to the ^usaibis,and the British ^rowing association reported that the samples sunt thera were of excellent quality. This was particularly interesting in view of the fact that it was planted too late in the season. Until cotton can be grown on a larger scale it will aot be very profitable,and local landowners have been unwilling to embark on a crop which ©hoT/s such a poor return at present world prices. The Government cannot now spare the funds for encouraging them or providing tiiO ginning rinchiiiery that is required. Totie progress is being rnad© with market garuuning, but the taste for vegetables grows slowly. The price of Bahrain dates fell below that at which Bf sra could oo landed in Bahrain and rent receipts were accord ingly very poor. His Excellency lost over half of his private income owing to this,but rents are invariably tixac very high, and it idonly in tne best years tiiat the full ‘Biuounte can be recovered. Tne Customs revenue amounted to Iia«5,09,000/-. The decline in ooranodity prices bei% w mainly responsible for this. M0K1C1PALIT 1KS. Botn Municipalities cio good work ena there is much friendly rivalry between them. Both nsve met declining revenues by cuts in their expenses,8nc though no large wori^s have been undertaken a good standard of general working has been laaintained. A tendency on the part of the i/anana Municipality to consider itself a State Council has been checked. The Muh&amp;rra* bazaar has been lit with electric lights and its sea road completed. J1 ——A consioerfcble emount of roed wmening iia8 ta^en place,sna at the suggestion of the Political Agent,* parallel road to tae .anataa See head is being constructed which will open up tne whole area,now served by wreteneu lanes. The doctrine tnat the roads should precede building development created some astonishment,but is now well established. The Political &gt;igent was asked to arbitrate in the question of the huge area of land claimed by the Cusaibis behind the Mission Hospital. A most unhealthy swamp had grown up here,and now that the boundaries have been fixed (the award gave the .jusnibis a fifth of what they claimed) the Municipality are drying the land by pumping. Gramophones, hitherto iwaoral and banned^are now in coffee 3 liApg,taough their records are strictly censored at the time cf import. It is interesting to hear that, while German (Arabic; records are found to be very immoral,His Master’s Voice records are comparatively pure. The fnara’a Courts still refuse to accept tne eviconce of gramophone sellers.as such men must obviously oe immoral# • It is the general view that the age is getting much more immoral,and one frequently hears that immorality is on the increase since men can no longer kill off erring female relations Liquor seems to be finding its way into the towns in spite of all attempts of the Police to check it,end as elsewhere, prohibition seems to have bred bootlegging. I*uikii.O liuhi-Jj . Owing to shortage of tunas no works of any importance were unaertaium,but tne new .narantiuu buiiaings were completed. ElUCATUN. The number of seboois in existence on the 1st January end Ox. 01st December is the same in 1501 none hi ving been abolished or opened curing tne year, 'mere ere two girls schools and six boys school s.-lanama Sunni ana xisk Shiah,Huiisrra j Sunni,headSunni,Bafa f Sunni,al Kaamis Shiah. No: of taacbers on 1-1-1931. Mo of Sehosiers on 31-13-1931. Of Sale. Female. the total for both 26 6 sexes ana on both 27 8 , dates,15 are foreigners No: of students No: of stuaents on 1-1-1931. on 31-12-1931- .Sales. 500 560 | Fera&amp;les. 157 176 Education is free,and except in a lew cases even paper, pencils are provided free of charge. English is now taught only in the two top fora* of the schools. Since the pruning of tne Educational 6ouncil tne schools have bear running cowparativaly smoothly,though tne Ehiah school in Ifamm has ccapsretively ftw students in coiap&amp;Eison to its capacity. I A religious teacher in a juanaiaa Sunni schOsjl began to give trouble in July,but the end of the scnooi year was at hand and his services were aispe;ised with during tue no^idays. The American f'iaaion aaintcin a boys school ana a girls school. The former had a maximum cnroimunt of 149 witn an average attenaance of 54,anu the latter 115 ana 33. The girls school is a vety go ahead affair,and does a great ueal of good. The girls play tennis ana go for picnics,both unheard of liberties for Arab asdua maidens,and if any improvement is effected in the position of women in Bahrain it will be mainly through the agency of Ars. lame's school, ihe more conservative Arabs do not approve of girls learning to write as they say they could then send messages to their lovers. TRADE . The year proved even worse for the r earling industry than 1930,and but for a persistant demand from India for the cheaper grades of pearls,the trace of Bahrein would have come to astandstill. This surprising dera^nu from India is thought to be (ji cue to money that could not be spent on better textiles owing to the boycott being expenued in pearls, another view being tuat * pearls are an essential part of certain religious ceremonies among Hinfius,and still another view,that in a world of fluctuating values some felt pearls were a good investment. Itoth catcher and prices were poor,though prices did not fall below the very low figures of the preceding year. Next year, there is little doubt that many fewer boats will set out for then is no longer the capital to finance them. It is estimated that two-thirds of the pearling capital in Bahrain has disappeared into the sea in the last three years,and men who had a capital of ten or fifteen lakhs have nothing left except pearls for which there nre no purchasers. u Bad though the state of trade is in ‘Bahrain there is some comfort to be found in the reflection that our neighbours are worse off,for iatif and Qatar are to ail intents and purposes ruined. A cause of the comparative prosperity of Bahrain is to be found in the fact that Gulf capitalists have steauily been moving their capital over ana establishing their headquarters here for some years past. This is true both of the , rab and r ersian coasts,and is a great tribute to the administration of Bahrein. There is little doubt tuat its good oraer,security, bankjwireless and shipping facilities act as lodestones,and both Nejdi and ersisn merchants anu shaikne nave been moving tneir valuables to its gilt-edged shores. ihe total value of the trade amounted to ^s.17, as compared with He• 253,00,4£G/-uuring the preceding year. The total value of imports amounted to hs.^104,61,880/- as against Hs.160,37,490/- the preceding year. The exports emountec to Ils. 66,58,340/- os against hs.^,26,29,960/- for the preceding year. Iliu figures of export are not accurate since few of the pearls exported are declared et their proper value if declared at all.li. (£) ^KDOSTiar . It is pleasent to have to record the birth of a new industry in Bahrain. Khalil Kanoo,ancL one Faik i.uhaffi,^ ^/rian,entered into a partnership to produce tiles and were given a uonopily for two v years to encourage them. They have produced sojae 7J f OOO of excellent quality and fully equal to the dest that Basra produces but liave found some difficulty in disposing of tnem. The partnership has broken up,Falk Auham describing nis late partner as 'a frienuly thief', if times were normal they would have none very well. i a ■ There lias been a smrked interest in football durii^j the past year and the rolitics.1 Agent took a tern to sra for three days. GiUPPIMi . The total num ter ol aotor lauuc^ea plying uire on 31st December 53. Of these o were bui.t ciurix^; tae year. 33 hailing vessels were built in Bahrain uurlng the year as compared with 55 built the preceding yea.r. 110 British Ships, 1 j Geritian ana 1 Norwegian entered ana cleared the fort of Bahrain as compared with 123 British snips and 11 German snips that cabled during the preceeding year. ;,arly in November the British India Steam Navigation Company decided to allow their down steamers to make a weekly call at Bahrain instead of fortnightly. This hss been a welcome change and is much appreciated by the local mercantile community. Geven accidents took place at sea,within Port limits, during the year and in three cases loss of life occurred,once whe; a coolie was killed while cargo was being discharged from the 1.5 Bankura on the iJth April,and on two otner occasions when men were swept overDoard and drowned,one of these accidents occurring on a lancing company’s lighter. The nancing Coapahy have worked at a loss throughout the year and have had several boats bauly damaged in the heavy stums at the close of the year.Li. LLSCTiilC UGhT . /‘t ■ lh« ©lectrio ligUt rias been extenGeci to i-lunarre over head wire as i&amp;r as the deep channel and thereafter by submarine cable,the polis for the overhead wires being plc-cea on piers that will later oe incorporateu in the ; anaraa-,;uhe rreq sea road f 'Ihe concern which belongs partly to the State and partly to the Municipalities,is paying its way but not making sufficient as yet to meet MaprMiaiaau depreciation charges. Mr*ii«iLSteel* had taken the place of air.F.V.Jordan ana ass been engaged as a full time State servant, he was formerly an employee of Messrs Gallanoer^ Cable cnc Construction Company he also fulfils the duties of State Lingineer. Several visits were paid to Bahrain b 7 His i^ajosty’s Hhips stationea in the ersian Gulf ana on the 16th Leceixber the d.M.S ^Emerald” arrived on a 4 days visit. While she was in port a fetal accident occurred when F/ht r.lleinneaan,who was giving demonstrfitions in the ship's f, flycatcuer ,f of machine ^nning targets on the water,lost flying speed,stallee and crashed alongsiae the ship, he was buried next day with full military honours and a huge following of Arabs accompanied tne body to the grave. it was particularly unfortunate that the accident should have occurred ss the Emerald were giving a party to the notables of Bahrain to demonstrate the various activities of the vessel. hQYnh AIR FOBCK. , There is little that is new to record regarding the hoyal Air loroe. They appear to have given up their ^hor Lupin moorings,indeed tr.e Khor is too small for such big vessels as the langoon8,and are now concentrated in lior Haliya. Jn one occasion a sea plane accompanied two iiangoons ana tiiey were a mooring A violent storm arose but the oad Iiangoon was able to ride it out et its om anchor,thereby proving that the holding ground is good. The Political Agent undertook several flights aceompanyLm. i - —■—- 1 ^. ^ a flight to ..asira island in .lax. 'ihe brother of tins ^haikb of lias al ytiaimeh W5v8 flown to Bohrain for medical treatment and flown oack again after a week f t stay. His Excellency Shaikh Ahmad al Jabir paid iiis first visit of the year to Bahrain in a flying boat. BhiTHE lETKIiEt Vu » wr* T ... .B.j alkor of ine .esopotamis ercin uorporation Limited who hsa been unwell for some ti,/;e was relieved by feir. J. Rus sell 1 ro rn Bun de r A bb ? s ^ vw c&amp;fr Mr.E.Harden of the Eastern bank limited was relieved by Tr.t.Kaa in September. Xhe Bank decided to build new nremises on the sea roau at a cost of .is.?5|SJ0/-. The builciixig- is being built by an iropi contractor from ruiniorccc concrete,the first occasion on which this material has been employed in ilanrain. it will be very interesting to see the fate of the cement,aioce tne Sahrain air ana water nave hitherto undemined the best that can be produced. ihe Anglo ursian Oil Oomprjjy became increasingly unpopular throughout the year owing to thio much higher rates Bsked for petrol ana lore sene here as compared with those obtaining on the T 'ersian Coast. The ^rabs feel they are being ileecec by this Company,wild have cone to a regional agreement with their competitors and prevent other stocks coming in. in April the Imperial l- Internation Communications Company took the place of the indo European Telegraph Department, it is believed that they will modernize the equipment which is out of Q£l ttfti # The 8.3 ’’Marlfty' chartered by the Bombay firm of hanchodlal Parahotamuas of Bombay made a trip up the Gulf ana caused some plana to tne Britisn India Steam Navigation Company. POST OFFICE . During the year S,5uw registered letters were received and it,v)8U aespatenet as compared with letters received and14 (s) I 4,037 cesisateiied lact year. 4,071 parcels were received and 267 despatched iM I s. 13,636/4/- worth of otsc.ps wore sold. Cash certificates worth lie.So,2*3/6/- were sold and certificates worth 1.2.13,760/6 were uiucuergcc. Oritiah Postal Orders to tae value of ii.733/3/u wore sold and i;o. 11/15 paid, llavim^a Bank deposi ts s.'.;ouatcd to .is .46,833/— r.nc .io.iey orders for Hs. 1,30,475/5/5 were issued nna Rs.3,333/7/4 paid. On the 1st Soveaber tne 'oat office aovod tc its new quarters. The noon for estra a 00 Q'n.i udation in the Agei cy haying been ktmtti/ felt^ro^caals wore auoaittod during the early pert oi the yo* r invo6.vi.rg the altorriti. 0.11 of t\fo big ccll^ rootas to aake a new loGt fiffiee, ide proposal was sanctioned,and a new post ixiice was r rovidee at a cost of ha*. ,uJ0/-,a work lor which the pre-war estimate had been he#7,000/-* Assistant Surgeon h.doines hay remained in cna.rge throughout, tne year* The total number of cases treated during the year,compared with the preyloun year,^exe:- 1330. 1931. Outuour patients. 5,153 12,070 inuoor patients. 357 . 244 riajor and minor operations# 435 1,033 l*r holme a awnruud the A&amp;iuur-i-lUnd medal in the Birthday honours to wie great satiuiaction oi.’ his many friends in hbnraiu# lilu work nas been invaluabde,ano tno very large increase in outdoor patients ai.n operations in idol is the best testimony to lu^ efficiuncy with wnioh no o^ycharged his duties, the increase fate m&amp;.xi-kj.y at»*ojug tan ^anama »»o.ioti,a class that have hitherto noc uo^ievuv. m nos^4.Uiis,and ^ho will not even visit tao uornea f y hospital at tne eLyyiou. o4,B-io jutuoor patxunts ?a.o hi/ rauoor patients were treatec at tae oea f s hospital of the American .Pi as ion during tiie year ana 41d tiajor ana minor operations were perforfaed. hr.L.?.Lamremained in char^ of thin aospital tnrou, r nout u e /ear,except for a. period of three months when he proceeded on leave to the United Staters. She women’s hospital had 7,:54 outdoor patients and 169 indoor patients on coffapared with 8,3 j 6 outdoor patients and 25b indoor patients treated during 1930. 61 tmjor and minor operations were performed as a ;aiiiLt 1^5 for the proceeding year. Dr.lifxany hold clierge throughout the year except for a tiiree month’s rocssr in xnuia. UDiOkL. the total number of civil suits instituted washblO as compared with 1967 in 1 ,h&gt;0 aoti tne number if criminal suits 360 ps compared vuth 360. Ihe bjtal nu/iber of petitions registered uurii^; the ye^ir was ^,705 unu insolvency cases 12. xhe extra clerk applied foi* last year i^as been sanctioned, and it m-a been possible to speed up the work of the vernacular office. VISITS F 00Y limtiNT J /bjCIllS. The Hoa’ble rt Col.F.Y.Biscoe, Political Resident in the Ikrsisn Gulf,accompanied by Captain P.C*/]. ban,Under Secretary, ana fir. jjasoelles cf the Teherrn legetion arrived on the 3rd and left on the 6th Februerv# m Air Vice archal G.Ludlov-Hewi11,A.ir Officer Commanding, Iraq, Command,rrrivori on the ^3th (• ehrurry and left for Muscat the following day* Other visitors toex ksnsx were the Shaikhs of Kuwait (two visits and Dubai and st?r. Shaikh Muhammad al Hurm of Gaobandi also paid a visit to Bahrain on his way to Fnd from Hesa,and naked the 'oliucai Agent if he could sell him any rifles. The request, needless to say,was refuaod. His Highness 1 rince Ahmad Tauniu,a granuson of His imperial iajesty the iate Sultan Abaul Aziz of Turkey acconpaniec by Jemal asha,a Syrian officer of the olo Turkish army ana now in the service of Bin 'and also paid a visit. The latter slat.that he had been on a mission to India to discover the reasons for tne falling off in the nunber of Indio/; hajjis,but both were probably loo kin, oi t for nocey and vK?re grateful for the tip whicl Shaihh H&amp;rad gave them. disreputable Austrian named fraz and his wife also paid Bahrain i visit vith the intention of proceeding on the Haj overlrnu. they wore some four memths late or eight months early for ihxs,ann their pretensions to being converts to Islam were not if.nun seriously as the man seemua to know little of his new religion,ana replies to queries tnai ne aia not holu with any &gt; par tic ufs r sect, but Islam generally, as they xived by begging, tue hesiaency were as tec to prevent such persons being given visas m future,ana orders were issue a to prevent a recurrence oi such visits, u number oi destitute inaian hajjis also arriveci ana ,veio repatriated at consiaerabfe expense. On an average turee requests for repatriation or monetary assistance were received by ine Political Agent uaily,and it ss impossible to help any save a fraction oi the most distressing cases. N £ J p . Under the iron lirnd of Bin SaudjHasa end hey,a prouuced little in the w- y of interest anrin:’ tiro pf at , ear. din .tiluwi, fa A fceevy hoiKied governor of e -red to hvve regained his former ibilitv r.nc overa ge the effects of the stroke he suffered after bearing the news cl his Buii.VaLecrs ueath^ in battle tire year before, he is a patriarchal .jovenior of Uxe ola school and is held in wholesome awe b the bedouing'no the Ojair-Hasa road was consequently safe throug*hout the year** The excessive taxation cou;heu with the baa pearling season and poor date market ruined the 'atif oasis,and what little trade there *as mostly vent to wubail,- port in which the Qusaibis ar^e largely interested. Thsw is of now creation and owes its rise to the Kuwait blockade but consists of little more than two rows ol houses and a Customs house rod small pier.Muhamjtfc a bin Suwailliia,tae j^ir of ^atif,wh o liad shown hitfstfltf to be thoroupniy frieuul/ to tuc ^jea^y,was dismissed towards the close of the year,ueiu^ limuiy succeeded by Abdul itwhan bin rjituralien, hiero v/as no recrudescence of the Bnluiia trouble at oat if 8 no no persecution of genuine A Bahrainis.* the m tioruUity ^roolem is one tnat is much better left to solve itself locally and a ,modus '/iYt.-udi has been found. more seems to oe an emtoasron of eifeudi-ism and bureau- cratio control m nin Jauu l s eastern ^ rovincus, -nci luhaaimad al law11,the omnipotent oustoms director of hasu^uas usurped much power ionuer±y vosoea in tut Aiaiis. a j&gt;u ; nig Ccurt has now been sec up in fat if modelled on tao one at Bahrain, and if it is properly run it will be another benefit that Bahrain has on enforcud/its neighbours,lor the ,atar divers nave demanded aivin?: books ana proper accounts ou ine lines of those their Bahndn brethren enjoy. hi nee almost evtryont wuhia t«o nunersu. .uiies must now come to Bahrain if ne is to obtain a loan si finarce himself ^ it will be seen tiiat Bahrain is playing* an increasing part in the economic liio oi uie forsian buxf,anu such business is done on tne terns of the Bahrain morchants. The question of waiving re-expoxc dues for goods destined for Bin hud was not raised again,Out it is not believed that the be jd Government will rest content v;itn tne present situation and they have already enquired the price oi buoys, with a view to .naking fas Tanura a port. Ihey have faiiec so far to find wa cer tnere,but there is nothing* to prevent its being piped from 10 miles away. lith the exception of the Vmir of bat if and a grudging recognition by fin filuwi,the policy of the iNejd officials seenu to ho to i vore the . ^ency ,and none ever visit it though they frequently come to Bahrain on.business. Though fanaticism has diminished.the Onristian is not persona grate in the Hass,and a Kejdi fresh from his native wilds will avoid shaking the19'. rjnlliteci hnnd of the Politics.! .vrrent even in Shaikh Hamad's J iT}a f ilis,or will fcxtt;na tvvo ilrif^ers like a duchess st a garden party. By the close of the year aLfiost every town of inkportance _ | in Ne.id and Jiasa nad been fitted with wireless. The plants are supnlied by tne British Marconi Company. 3m ed The Political ^yent stated last y^ar iaat he cid not ’ iCi concur in tne view tuat Bin o&amp;ud dispensing ui tue services oi the use ibis 7 ei’ that tiiey were under eclipse. On the contrary tneir power nas waxed rather than waned,and xs. tuey nave been steacily buying property tilrcughout tee year, despite very he? vy losses in me o&amp;nl.ruptcy oi Iiabib Bosenthal. In fact,one nay sa. that they appear a inert tne owed only firm in BauraiH with any ready ijioney leit,tiiougji/some ] Jo, 000 oy a in oaud • wile ii u.^iicntly liCnis tiiac this ^ monarch will '^o banni’upt’ inis icea arises trom applying 1 tnc westexm rule oi thucib 10 ? person to w om it in no way I applies, for il »i.e is uimbie to pa^ *iis cievvi tuis,Tin naud will simply retire to tne interior leaving inem disconsolate oh his borders* ihe - .,'usaibis sy neve to wait a long time for their money,but there is little feai ut- 11 repudiate his obligations to them. Beioro proceeding on recess Lno iGj.iticsi. iigent v/arned Abaui iciz yusaibi against further acts of ression such as ^ those wnich nad marked the last two summers,ana none occurred, pne relations of the ngenoj with Lie hss.ibis are officially ^ most cordial,but they can haraly oe ignorant of Lie fact that Ki U . it is onlyforce L.at prevents them doing as tney please in Banrain. T.,e Political \gent paid two visits to nta^ in the past year and was well received by Shaikh Abdulla bin Jasim. The' 5 -. n (g) Shaikh has little pov/er over the more uiurui/ of his kinsmen, ana villages on tilt* northern diores oi Lne peninsula pa/ little attention to him. » delations were not improveu ..non,at the ciose oi the /ear the .political l «vus joh^oo to autacii ao-io poaixs belorn;irn ’ to a relative who iida boon sucu o fc two i eisian merchants in the »i.gnt|cy Court, ihe bxin 1 ^ ouais large!/ in oearl 3 himself,and after den/mg ieignanti/ that ^e Court had any right to toubg them,once t—c case has been settieu amicably anti the pearls returnee, to i-onah,no himself sent them to ioiiiba/ for sale to meet uis own claims. v n act amounting to piracy and another in which a wrecked Persian ahow' was lo(btea occurrea on the northern shores of Qatar,ana neither nad been settled satisfactorily at toe close of the year• ihe Shaikh T s weakness in these guarters ma/ be the cause of iroubit; in the future# 'me .aaouer is uein^ taken no by the Political Agent on his next visit to L»ohah. Qatar nas been much more severely affecteo by the depression tiian Bahrain,ana the bulk oi the inhabitants are on the verge of aestitution. in fact slave owners are finding difficulty in feeding their property. SOVIET . IP slaves .vure runnumitted auring the course of the year lue steos taken to crevent tlie traffic in women from lalabar appear to nave been successful, one woman complained that she had been divorced ai^a had no.v he re. to go, but an arab on v.he .gency verandah was struc-k by her charm mn oiiered to marry her at once, hlie .■vgency,in a now role ot match maker, warmly-' sec once tiie proposal ,anu the naupo pair were sent to the Qaahi^s forthwith, rne wlaiabaris present a ciifiiculty in tiiat scarcely anyone knows their language,ana though the Agency with its present stall habitually conducts official T/v business in five languages, or even at a pincn,yet la la bar i is an obstacle to be surmounted with difficulty.27 ) (2 i&amp;iVJ • J.U 3 j r ms unusually nut but tiie rainfall was much greater than usual being 5-1 inches. iiea?.y rain tailing in rebruary an a ovary uy'staur rooiu in toe i^ency leaked save one. ihe oareli av s almost, f coiuyleto failure arm ti is raised the temperature in vune. ^ jiUjiV*. j.. • lor the first time in tue last three years,the Staff of the Agency was sufficient for its bare needs,and the extra vernacular office clerk asked for was sanctioned in April. ‘the work in the Inglish office is now practically up to date, and the &lt;rration of cases in the vernacular office reduced from nearly two months to two weeks, in tue latter an improved filing pud regictrat.on system has oeen instituted,and if a party brings a erro which is always given them it is possible to trace a case in a. minute or two. Since the agency Courts are expectec to ‘'unction in *radic, ersian or ilnausi.ani,a larger staff is rennired tha \ aigiit [ else\hmre Tbe^uffTcleri^ V.ith the ofd strff the worn oi tae iingiish office was always hopelessly in an cars, tae grade ^eport oeiiig' at one time over s year Isle, it m to ue hoped these delays will not recur. It should bo noted that Bahrain _s a clearing ground for many do rtment s e ud c t i v i ti os ci i oi ; L i cn auu o i rec tlyj^ to the work of the gency. fne payment of the i*oyal *ir force Kest house 5\aff a id their penorci supervision,tue payment of Upper lir )bservers and pensioners,rupee payments anu storage of tosha kbanr for the residency,anu certain telegram accounts of His Ie jesty*s 5hips are only some of the moim recent additions to the xxxKac^ate clerical /orb,each small in itself but in the ag.gre -ate totalling considerable atuount oi work not usually falling to koliticai Offices. Bahrain,formerly an out of the way pearling Lown,oecomes every day more and more ixxaxtxcd the centre of tne Gulf,and22 4 21 . tne European population ii&amp;s doublea in ti..e last timse ytars. Ihis lias a repercussion on sucn matters as entertaining anu the uresent sumptuary allowance is quite inadequate lor the purpose,whatever it my'have seen when originally lixeu 23 years ago. This poxnt was represented before, though unsuccess^! fully aiiu is being represented again, it should ue reiueiuDereu that ..rabs also expect some entertainment,but at present,though frequently accepting their invitations,the Political -gent is forced by circumstances to made little or no return. ihe year lias been a quiet one,and generally satisfactory except for the disastrous pearling situation. British prestige is high,and tne innabitants are still surprisingly grateful for the material beneiits tney enjoy as a xesult of of hritish intervention in these islands, -oong ,iay they continue to feel this gratitude for it is a quality that is tae ;*iore wolcoiae on account of its rarity* Political Agent,Bahrain.1 (£) Confidential. D.0.No:C/46. Political Agency, Bahrain, the 14th jviarch 1932 Lear Gastrell, I am sending two additions to my Annual ^port and would be very glad if you could have them pasted as addenda to the three copies that 1 forwarded to you. I have sent them in triplicate ana they could be cut up for convenient insertion. The firet should come after 'Trade' ana the second after 'British Interests'. Any confidential letters requiring my -inwioointe attention should be sent to me in Karachi. Yours Sincerely, Gao tain K.H.Gastrell Secretary to the hobble . The Political “esident ptain L.h.Gastrell Secretary to the hobble . The Political ‘esiden in the Persian U ulf, Bushire.ICONFIDENTIAL No.26-3 of 1933 British Residency Sc Consulate-General Bushire, 6th January 1933 To The Political Agent, Muscat. The Political Agent, Bahrain.^ The Political Agent, Kuwait. H.B.M. *8 Consul, Kerman. *8 Consul, Bandar Abbas* I am directed to request that you will kindly submit in triplicate your Administration Report for the year 1932 as seen as possible, and in an&gt; event to reach Bushire not later than the 1st of March, to enable the Hon*ble the Political Resident to submit the full report for the sphere of the Residency before the 31st March. for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Sir I hrTe the honour to be \Victoria Memorial Hospital, Bahrein,Persian Gulf. 15th:January 1933. Bear Sir, I forward the following information,asked for am your letter No:11,P12«1.33. Number of Outdoor patients... 14614 9 t 9 9 Indoor ,, 278 Number of Major operations. 33 f t 9 9 HiV9r ,, 676 The following are the figures for Malaria during the past five years. 1928 1123 29 1685. 30 2474. 31, 3137. 32 2828. The arerage nuraher of cases of Malaria,from 1922 to 1926 was 822. In 1927 the number rose to 1997. These figures do not include the cases that have come under notice in Gallali,Hed,## Hala Naimr an d Maharrak. Yours sincerely, C——■ &gt;No: PA/HL/ TliE CUSTOlMOUSi:. BAHRAIN: 15th January, 1933., 19th Ramdhan, 1351.,■ H.B.M’s Political Agent, BAHRaIN: Memorandum :- In reference to your No:C.13 of 12-1-33., I have to report:- (a) Number of launches built in Bahrain, equipped with new engines, registered in Bahrain during 1932. . . . NIL. Cld launches brought here from other ports, and registered in Bahrain, during 1932, 4 * Old engines fitted into newly-built Bahrain launches, and registered in Bahrain: 6 . T ^ Launches sold to foreign ports, during 1932. 3. New Bahrain motor launches: ..... (b) On 31st December, 1932: Number of launches registered for passenger traffic: Number registered for cargo and passengers? Number registered for cargo and tawwasha, Number registered for Tawwasha, Number registered for private use only, Total:- 22 . 22 . 6 . 12 . 2 . 64. STEAMERS Entry &amp; Clearance: Year ended 31st December, 1931., BRITISH: B.I.S.N.Coy Ltd: 83 Strick Line, I? • British Tanker 11* City Line 4- Ellerman &amp; Bucknall £ • GERMAN: Hansa Line. NORVteGIAN: National Steamship Coy T o t a 1:- Year ended 31st December, 1932: BRITISH: B.I.S.N.Coy Ltd., Strick Line, British Tanker, City Line, . . . . Bombay Steam Navigation Coy,. . GERMAN: Hansa Line: NORWEGIAN: National Steamship Coy. . .. T o t a 107. 18. 16. 9. 1 :- 117. 11 . 2 . 130. 151. 11 . 3. Ter: The above figures do not include any warships, or Light-tender, or Cable-ship. and PORT OFFICER. BAHRAIN.xio: ^ . Political Agency, Bahrain,the ^bth January llbo. To, The Director of Custoias, Baixrain. Memorandu m. With reference to your Memorandum No:PA/HL/l5/44o dated the 15th January 1955,it is requested that you will kinaly supply me with the follo-ving information in respect of the trade of Bahrain for the year 1932. Value. Imports. Exports. (a) General Merchencize. (b) Pearls. (c ; Specie &amp; Gold Coins. It is not possible to ascertain these figures from my records ; as the monthly Statement for December 1932 has not f &amp; yet oeen received. jK 2. It is also requested that you will kinaly state what the Customs revenue for the period 1st January to gj 31st December 1932 amounted to. /jt Political A^ent,Banrain.URGENT REMINDER. 'rom To THE POLITICAL AGENT, The Director jif_£ustoms, Bahrain. Bahrain. iO. • Bahrain, dated the ILth February ^3 2* MEMORANDUM. I have to draw your early attention to this office letter No. 40 ated 25th January 1 93 0, regarding Customs revenue £ Trade fi :: ureand o request that its reply may be expedited. Lieut Colonel Political Agent, Bahrain.Confidential. Political Agency, Bahrain,the Zna March 193b. No:0/88. From:- Liejit Colonel Gordon Loch, I.A*, Political Agent, Bahrain. To:- The Hon T ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Sir, I have the honour to forward,in triplicate,my Annual Report on the Administration of the Bahrain Islands. B. I am indebted to my predecessor,Captain C.G.Prior, for the greater portion of this report. I have the honour to be Sir, Your Most Obedient Servant, V.-administration report of the oehrain agency for the year 1932. 28th November wnen he was relieved by .uieut Colonel Goraon noch. latrine of his nouse and was brought round with difficulty by hr.Lame. The close of the year saw His Excellency appreciably weaker,and tnere is little doubt his end is not a lady of exceptional character,who has been his mainstay,^ also ill,apparently with some heart complaint. excellent terms with the Agency tnroughout the year. *iis grant from the revenues of the Etate ^anu that of ail the nl Khalifah a 10 per cent cut throughout the year and since he made little attempt to economise his private finances nave fallen into some cunfusion. His estates,hov/ever,fortunately brought m more than in 1931 as the date crop was more profitable,or his indebtedness would be greater than it is- 5 , Shaikh muhammad bin Isa Al Khalifah caused some surprise by extending his visit to an Austrian eye specialist in Vienna to ~o to England. Shaikh Hpnad was somewhat nettled that the ilrst intimation ne received of the visit to England should have come from outsiders,and also possibly ielt that these extended tours ill concerted with Shaikh Muhammad’s pleas of poverty. Shaikh Muhammad wrote tnat he was extending 1 . Captain C.G.Prior held charge of the agency until 2- Khan Bahaaur Abdul Haiy al Hashirai held charge oi the V cost of Indian Assistant throughout the year. iar otf- (Note. He died on the 9th Lecember 1932). His wife, Shaikh hamaa bin Isa ill Khaliiah has been on(5 his viait to see iiis i^ajesty tne King, and dad the Honour of being presented to his ..lajeaty at a Garden '.''arty at bucjcin^ham Palace. Lieut Colonel Gordon ^och accompanieu him to interpret at the request of the Indie Office. He was very pleased with his reception in England. His son,L&amp;shid,one of the less unpromising Al Khalifah uiea m October. suspected of creating trouble so as to gain kudos by settling it, was finally seen in his true colours ever the agitation regarding the na fs in February, he was well aware of the trouble that was brewing in iuharraq, and did not warn the Ruler or the Adviser of what was Happening, - lien the trouble cane to an head he niu nothing to check it,and on one occasion when Sh&amp;iidi Hamad sent him out to talk over some malcontents all he could say to them was T ana tfiakum’ or f I am with you f . Chen paying the 1 La al pi f-rt n. u ] 1 r tltt? Pnliticml taxed Him with this and Shaikh of tne incitement caused by a gross insult offered to him by tne uivers. is by far the most useful of Shaikh Hamad’s sons. This is very iortunate as he is likely to be the Heir, he has shown signs of bein^r more able to assert himself anu is less afraid of his w relations than he used to be. he is on excellent terms with the Agency. 8, Shaikhs Mubarak bin Hamad ana Abdullah bin Hamad went on the Eajj via India on tne H2nd February ana returnee overiana on the 13th May. They found the overland trip something of an ordeal,but were well satisfied with Bin Sa'ud »s reception of them. The more observant Abdullah had noticed many signs of the financial stringency of the Bedjaz. 6 . Shaikh Abdullah bin Isa a! Khalifah,who nan long been 7. s; haikh Salman bin Hamad Al Khaiifah has done Shaikh La’ij continued his career as the spoilt chila3. &amp; of tne family,find,it is believed,is still spared tne rigours of an education. Ahmad, his younger brotner,a well naimerea intelligent lad,has had a teacher engaged for him but it is not imown what progress he has made. 10. Shaikh Bashid bin huhaimaad a! Khalifah aid good work as ^resident of the Majlis al Urfi. ^ B Anrji i h S T A . 11. wlr.C.I .Belgrave proceeded to hnglana on leave on urgent private affairs on the 7th August and returned on the 10th September by air. 12. jr.Aeigrave showed his usual determination in repulsing attacks on the State Treasury,and showed much personal courage during the divers 1 riot, he had handled tne police,in addition to his other duties,with ability,and has been very successful in bringing to a successful issue a number of illicit liquor cases,gaining much credit for the administration by so doing. He also discovered and broke up a number of boys’ brothels in ^uharraq. 13. Oaptain L.5.Parke proceeded on short leave to India on the 22nd January and left Bahrain for good on the 15th April, he had become more and more perfunctory in the discharge of his duties and the reduction of this post has been a very useful economy. 14. j'r.C.G.L de Grenier was at his post throughout the year and was entrusted with certain of ^r.helgrave’s functions during the latier’s absence on short leave,though he was not appointed Acting' adviser. He,however,showed a decided leaning towards exceeding his instructions, he gave tne agency great assistance m dealing with traae enquiries. ' BaHKAlh POilGB . lb. It is convenient to consider under this head all the forces of law and order in Bahrain. These consist of the remnants of the Indian armed Police,the local Police (who are4. (§) beir^ trained to replace them] ana the Nature or Night-watchmen. The latter are an irregular body who ao not wear unixcrm,or perform any drills,ana are armed witn long Lee ^nfiela rifles. They are posted at Lanamah anu Luharraq. The strength of these bodies is given below:- Strength on l-i-3iS. Strength on 31-12- 1932 Indian Police • • « 50 11 Followers • • • 0 8 Arab Police • • # bo 118 Naturs * • • 121 120 15. Almost all the inaians were allowed to return to India in September and October on completion of their agreements. few men were engaged in their place,but they are principally usea as Instructors,or to relieve the men under training of guard duties. The new Arab recruits,mostly of Negroid extraction, have made an excellent start,and there seems no reason why they should not become as smart as Negro troops elsewhere,since they seem to have a natural love of drill. Partly owing to the hard times dozens of men offer themselves for enlistment,but a very high percentage are rejected for inferior physique. Now that the initial difficulty of obtaining men has been over come it should be easy for the State to find tneir retirements locally, since men constantly bring their frienus icr enlistment,as tne Indian solaier does in India. ^ LOCAL AFFAIRS . 17. lio Sunni-Shiah quarrels arose uuring the year,ana the wuharrem celebrations passea off without incident. The educated Persians are rapidly losing all interest in religion,but the ^rabs are more conservative. 18. Shaikh Abuullah bin nxunammad halih ana Shaikh Ali bin Husain al Nusa 1 continue to be on gooaxterms with the Agency,and both supported the Government curing the agitation against a proclamation aesigneu to secure honest aisposal of inheritances.The bunrii t aoiiis are still the three Abdul jjatifs and are not on good terms eitner with the Agency or the Bahrain Government# Their decisions are far from impartial,and there is growing dis-satisfaction of their administration of the Sunni V/a^is# Their attitude over the agitation mentioned above was unsatis factory. 19. The Financial adviser considers that Shaikh. Khalaf has been making mischief amongst the Baharna,but no instance of it came to the Political Agent T s notice. Luring the latter part of the year the oia man returned to Uraq to fetch a wife. But for the fact tnat old men ao not appear to uie m Bahrain, the view might be ventured that ne would not trouble anyone for long. 20. Inheritance Proclamation Agitation , ihe uauram Government aecided at the ena of January to issue a proclamation, the gist of which was that a stricter control would be kept over properties left by deceased persons and inat steps would be taken to protect the interests of widows and orphans. The proclamation also provided lor the calling for accounts from executors by tne Courts,and stated tnat no one would be allowed to deal with an estate before obtaining the sanction of a Court. This last provision was objected to as interested persons are usually able to divide up a deceased’s moveables before the case comes before ?. &amp;uhi,'ond this proclamation was speciiioaiiy designed to prevent ouch action. The Bon’bie the lolitical Resident was m the vicinity snd the malcontents remained quiet intentionally or otherwise until he Lod ieit dahram jiiu. tht- matter then CGiue to a neud. The agitation started in wiUhairaq ana Hiaa ana had undoubtedly been in existence soi^e time before anything was heard of it owing to meiiicient police arrange ments. Shaikh Abdullah bin isa Al iaialifah was undoubtedly well aware of what was going on,but took no useful action,and later snowed some sympathy with the agitators. Tne proclamation wasmisrepresented in every possible way,one rumour being that no dead might be buried without the Government’s permission. The trouble then spread to Janamah and the bazaars were closed tram the ( Jth to the 11th February. Unfortunately Shaikh iiaaad was due to pay his la visit to iJuharra^ and an early settlement had to be made. The Adviser askea the Political agent to reissue a similar Agency proclamation of 1931 to show Bahrain subjects that the idea was not a ne* one,and that foreigners were liable to similar regulations. This was done, but it proved to be an unfortunate step, excitement then prevailed amongst the foreign community as well as the Bahrainis and large bodies of Persian swarmed over from huharra^. The Political Agent held a prolongea meeting with their leaaers and, after he had succeeded in separating the Persians from the Arabs,was able to pacify them by slightly mouifying the pro clamation though not in any essential feature. Uhaikh Hamad had in the meantime exhibited characteristic weakness xor although he met the first deputation that went to meet him at hakhir with firmness,he threw away the advantage he had gained by asking them at tue end ’What do you want me to do?’ He sent a confiaential messenger in at night to ask if the Bahrain Government proclamation should not be secretly removed in the night,to which the Political Agent objected. On the night of the 10th February,however,unknown persons removed it and the Agency proclamation and the Shaikh accepted the fait accompli. As a result of this agitation the friends of the Government harmed themselves and the Government itself suffered a severe setback. Fortunately they recovered all their lost prestige in the firm handling of the divers’ riot. There is little doubt that the Hunni &gt;cdiis were in full syrapathy with the agitation. 21. Diver s’ idot . Un the 25th day a divers’ agitation^5 7 . for increased salaf came to a head when some ringleaders arrested* The salaf had been fixed at Hs*30/~ for uivers ana Rs*25/- fc*r haulers,an uncomfortably lo% figure,but all that the industry could afford after three baa years. Certain men had busied themselves in stirring up taeir fellow divers to refuse these terns (althougn representatives of the divers uad been present when the usual meeting to fix the rates had been held) ana net with a ready response from the more turbulent section of foreign civer3,a motley crowd of blacks,domalis,Hadhramautis and wild men from tne interior of the Arab Coast generally* Shaikh Abdullah warned the Adviser that there were signs of trouble at Sukarraq and on the 25th certain ring-leaders were arrested. Next day the trouble commenced with dramatic sudden ness. bnaikh Abdullah and the jimir had come over to , anamaix to discuss the matter with the Adviser, and were on their way back to ;,iuharraq,'vhen tne adviser received news that a very large body of men na^d landed on the -ijanajuah-^iuiiarraq causeway and were coming to his office, apparently they maae for the Police Station,for before the Adviser had reached it they had wrecked it and rescued a ring-leader imprisoned the day beiore. The Political Agent proceeded to ioin the Adviser as early as possible and met him at the Police station,which was found to have a door and two windows burst in, the glass being in fragments On the way to the Police Station the Political Agent drove through a section of the mob and had occasion to notice their ugly temper. The adviser had sent up to the Fort for the available Indian Police,and he and the Political Agent proceeded there to expedite matters. Some thirty men were hastily armed and a passing lorry commandeered and the little force returned to the Police station to find a rabble of some 1,500 divers armed with clubs,sticks and crowbars,evidently in a state of considerable cxc'tement,while a crowd of about a thousand looked on from the8 * &amp; houses and other coigns of vantage. ! ihe Adviser wished to use the Police to protect the bazaar, but the ol it leal r »gent advised him to disperse the mob,pointing out that they had a flank which could be turned. It was decided to attack them,and the Indian Police (who had instructions not to fire without orders) opened out ana advanced against the right ilauk of the mob. For a few minutes the Police made uo headway and it looked as though they would have to fire or use the bayonet,but then the divers began to give way,alarmed possibly by the firing of the ftaturs, which was controlled with difficulty. The Police now began to drive the mob along the sea road anu. into the sea,being reiniorced as they went by naturs,Shaikhs* retainers,Agency farrashec and others,and folioved by the lorry. 'The mob were finally all driven into the sea,then some four feet u.eep,snd many made their way to a»uharr&amp;A in passing sailing boats. The Adviser followed them in three launches with all available police but no further disorders occurred there and the nob dispersed quietly to their homes. One sepoy was wounded,two divers killed,probably by shots from the naturs and three or four injured,but not a single shot was firea by the inaian Police,whose behaviour throughout was aomirable. Shaikh Hamad,for once in his life,dealt firmly with the guilty,the fact being tnat his temper was quickened by the insult that the divers had levelled at his brother,Abdullah# Apparently f?s Shaikh Abdullah was returning to 'dollarra \ he met two boat loads of divers sailing over and ordered them back. The canaiule, however,merely scoffed at him and lilting up their clothing shook their membra virilia at him,ana the high wind carried them past before he could co anything# xiiis is the most oltensive insult in Arab countries and the usually mild Shaikh namad observed to nis Chamberlain that had anyone done that to Kim he wouxd have ? 0ut him down,no matter who he was,or where he was'. It was fortunate indeed that the trouble was settled with so little loss of life,and good came out of evil,for theBahrain Government regained at one stroke,not only aii the prestige they haa lost over tne inheritance proclamation and more,but the divers,who had succesbrull./ raiseu their saiai's by disorders in the two previous years,learned a lesson that should not easily be forgotten. OIL GONG lb! I ON . L2. The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited struck oil on the 1st June and before shutting oft The well obttdned a tlov of 70 Tons a day. There is little doubt tnat they would have obtained an even greater flow had they gone aeeper,but as their concession stands at present,it uiu not pay them to do so. 23. The rig was dismantled anu re-erected come two miles away on 8 fresh site where drilling commenced on the 1st August. A second rig has been brought from America and ass seen erected on yet a third site. The second well has reached a depth of over 1,500 feet and traces of oil have been found. 24. The Fields juanager is to move into y&amp;namah and there is little doubt that the Company are beginning to exert a consider able local influence. This will undoubtedly increase with their operations and their experience of Bahrain,and combined with the Arabian Mission,they represent a most unfortunate intrusion of foreign influence into Bahrain. 25. The Company engage all their Indian personnel in T Iraq or locally,and have not given them formal agreements, iipart, moreover,from some British Inman mechanics and clerks,the Company have no British personnel whatsoever,if Liajor Holmes be excepted. They have already exerted some influence on trace and a number of American lines of goods have made their appearence, despite the adverse rate of exchange. ^ AhTuSigN WLLLG . 26. Aater is still being wasted in incredible quantities and Bahrain’s more valuable asset is being frittered away as though it was inexhaustible. Towards the ehu of tne year iVlajorHolmes,the pioneer of artesian wells in Bahrain t addressed a Ion:; letter to Shaikh Hamad pointing out the danger of squanuer- mg so valuable an asset and stating that certain artesian wells have no 1 ' tapped the lowest water holding strata* Shaikh H^mad has oronised to take action but will re uire to be pressed to deal with me matter thoroughly as he himself and many of his relations are the worst offenders. A number of wells nave been drilled very cheaply,at prices that do not admit of proper lining and water is being lost m immense uantities unuer the ground as well as running to waste in the sea. AGFiCUhiU-B. 27. fi e A riculturist proceeaea on leave on the k&amp;th nU^;ust,Nmd xus return is unlikely until finances improve. His work uas shown some results,however,and not only have*excellent cotton crops been raiseu,bu'c a very good start has been mane with iruit cultivation, and some excellent oranges have been grown. As the person responsible for his engagement,the Political .vjxnt vieied his departure *ith regret,but there is little ccubt that he has done good considering the exiguous means at Lie disposal. The Tusaibis are now the principal exponents of improved fanning, and the remark of Abaul Aziz to the Political agent on the dawn of new ideas is worth repeating * The Tirol year he used manure,he said,it was given to him free, the second, he hid to pay ama.il price for it,but this year,now that its value has be~n discovered, he had had to pay a stiff price for it. The yuan ibis action in cleaning u., their oate gardens ;ind getting rid of useless trees had been observed by their neighbours -ith interest and will undoubtedly be followed. 23. iue ante harvest was better than last year,ana prices on the whole were higher. C U S l 0 M o . 29. The Customs revenue amounted to Ls.6,14,594/-. The decline in commodity prices was principally responsible for this decline.30. The Bahrain Government introduced s Vi per cent duty on luxuries in place oi the former 5 per cent trom the 6th hay ann later rai&amp;ea this to 10 per cent with a lb per cent duty on liquor and tobacco on the 31st lecember. Bionic iPAbmas . 31. Both iiunicipalities do ^ood work, though tneir means become more and more straitened. 32. Both municipalities,particularly that of M&amp;n&amp;mah,have able Secretaries,and only lack of funds prevents more rapid development. An effort was made to prevent the hanamah sea front oeinp used as a latrine,but much still remains to be done in his matter. 33. A road 1ms been made inland,parallel to the Manarnah sec road,at the instance of Captain Prior,and its value has already been perceived. 34. Both Municipalities still continue to interest them selves in.many natters suite beyond their purview,but little harm is done tmC they provide useful safety valves,and on the whole do their work very well. 35. Tne hanamah municipal Gardens now have the nucleus of a zoo,including a dejected vulture,who is popularly believed to be an eagleJ 36. The hananah Municipality imlvec the price of ice ana sold a far larger quantity than the year before to the great benefit of the public. They will only purchase ice in the hottest weather,however,and a shamal will stop all demand for a day or two,though with better times a taste for it will undoubtedly develop. V5creem T is now a good Arabic word. / ruBLic 37. Owing to financial stringency no Tories ol any magnitude were carried out this year. ^ JOa x 10x&lt; . 33. hix boys T schools ana two girls 1 schools were inexistence on tne 1st January. On the ^nd October when the schools reopened after the sumner vacations the ilanamah Ounni and Shiah boys- schools were amalkaiaateu. it was learea at one time that this umalgamation would lead to an agitation by the hhiahs but nothing untoward happened. 39. t&gt;o0 ocys and 173 girls were on the rolls on the 1st January and Odd boys and girls on the rolls on the 31st , scember. 1 h t, i) 40. The pearl trade ended the year with a 25 per cent to 20 per cent improvement,improved prices compensating for a disappointing yields had the decline of the three preceeding years continued half the Islands would h?ve gone bankrupt, but the close of the year lound nen willing to lend again and a more cheertul note prevailed. The big buyers maintain that there has been no e uuvalent rise in the Luropean market,but as buyers it is not in their interest tc think otherwise. There is little doubt that the exceptionally calm autumn greatly helped the K&amp;dua,or closing season,and many divers are said to have acne much better during this period,when they can dive with whom they please,than in the iiain season or Tghaus- when they must dive for their nakiiudaiis. It will be some time before their earnings are transformed into increased imports,but benefit to trade should come- 41, in this successful radda,Bahrain seems to have benefitted more than nor neighbours,as the mainland boats,who will not go out to deep water once the main season is over have little good to report. 42. The total value of trade amounted to hs. 169,82,270/'- as compared with Es*171,20,220/- in the preceeding year. The total value oi imports cuiiounwcu to hs• lUD,82, /io/— as against Hs.104,61,830/- and the exports to hs.do,99,560/- as against hs.56,58,240/- for the preceeding year. The figures of exports are not accurate since few of the pearls exported are aeclarealb. at their proper value,ami taose carried on the person are not i declared at all. The I'i^ures for specie also are not reliable. INDUSTRY . 43. The tile industry closed down,being unable to dispose &gt;j£ accumulated stocks. The tiles are good and very cneap,but the times are against the purchase of anything but necessities. 44. Ahmad bin Yusuf lakhrup^ith the encourngetient of tne • Agency,iuis opened a den is agency anu nas sola e Ainor ana two Coiley saloons. The springing of tne latter is an immense improvement on tne ola model,ana if only touring models were available tie would co much setter. The more expensive meads nave no sale r t present. 45. The interest m football continues to increase and some of the young *1 Khalifah join in tne game. Cricket also has some devotees,principally Inaiens or young men educated in India. 10.Vi .•-1; CdllrluC . 40. The total number of launches plying for nire on the list beeember was 03. 47. Sixteen sailing vessels were built during the year as compared with thirty-two built curing 1931. 43. One hundred and Fifty-one British chips,eleven German and three Norwegian entered ana cxearou the Port of Bahrain as compared with One hundred and seventeen British Ships, eleven German ships ana two Norwegian snips that entered and cleared the Port of Bahrain during 1931. 49. a launch belonging to the Shaikh of Tibbin which was returning there with merchandise.caught lire on the Both august on the pearl banks not far from Bahrain,and was completely destroyed,fortunately without loss of life. The engine was a German one supplied by j;usuf Fakhra,ana ^uc inoiuent is not likely to enhance their sales.14 . | •J L? 50. The r .us??ibis sold a big; launch to His Majesty Bin Sa^d and it successfully made the voyage to ^edJah,reaching huscat in four days from Bahrain. 61. The year was notable for the auvent of three special steamers,the ’iarly’ on the 27th January,the U^agervick’ on the 27th April and the ? AlMQvli ’ on tne 27th October. The two last named carried direct cargo for mainland ports,and the •AHmedi* was refused permission to discharge any cargo at Bahrain es she declined to guarantee that the mainland cargo would pay the customary two per cent transit duty. 52. The competition of tnese steamers v/itn the nritish India 5 team navigation company juimited is a ¥ery serious matter for the Gulf. The reguiar mail service,first oi ail monthly ana then fortnightly anc. weekly has been the creation of the Gulf trade as we Know it now,and ships such as these intruders which carry cargo Ior possibly the two best ports only cause great loss to the British India hteam navigation Company limited at a time when they can ill axiom it. ny their mail contract the Company are obliged to call at a numoer of t.orts which no longer have any trace worth mentioning,and they are thereby handicapped in dealing with these competitors / j TV v&lt;t% i 53 . .c 'Cnaonde' arrived in on the 20th February,being Dreceeued by n party on the 7th February to cnrty cut a survey. Ti.ey finally left on the loth ay not having altogether completed their work. They were delayed by storms,January bavin! been exceptionally calm and the ether months correspondingly stormy. 54 . Yho Haval CoroMindor-in-Chief of the fiast Indies S.ai&amp;dron,His excellency Hear Admiral E.Dunbar-Nasmith^/.C.jC.B., in ii.M.h 'Hawkins” paid a visit to Bahrain on tne 17th Becemher. lie xeit on tne Both nece.'f.oer. 55 . The Senior Naval Officer in the Persian Gulf in 11. .S ’’Tried' snei. other of His Majesty’s Snips paid visits to I iflb. Bahrain during the /ear. HOYaL ;ilh FOiiOja. . b6. The Flying Boats of ^03 (F.BJ S^uauron R.a.F paid frequent visits to Bahrain during the year. A Rangoon made a lorced landing at Jinn&amp;h Island on the loth January,and another made a forced landing on the loth September. Tne Flying Boats have been extremely fortunate so far in having made forced landings either m or very near sneltered water,for landing in a rou-n sea would speedily end their careers. The Political agent made a number of flights,once spending naif an hour over the atar eninsula at an elevation of uneer an nmarea feet, searching for landing grounds,an uncomfortable experience in a flying boat. y /viATioa . b7. imperial Airways aecideti to transfer tneir line to the Arab Coast ana the first flignt *as due to pass tarough Bahrain on the oth October. The iirst aeroplane,iianno,uuly arrived but sank into the treacherous surface of tne 0 Hainan aerodrome and only freed itself next day after tremendous efforts. Imperial Airways had been warned of the surface of this aerodrome,but unaccountably paid no heed,nor aid they send a Haimibal pilot to invest! rate until a fortnight before the tirst aeroplane was due.. When this pilot came,he pronounced the aerodrome as unsuitable,but his recommendations were ignored with this untoward result. The Company then obtained permission from the State to use the Muharraq aerodrome,but by the ena of the year ueitner had the location of a permanent aerodrome being the decided,nor had the Company completed/e ;nipping of their Rest House. U 1 giullSH IKTaKiSTS . 5a. .Russell ot tlie Mesopotamia Persia Corporation limited neia cnarge tiiroui;nout the year. The Landing Company,15. the property ol ttie British India Gtesra Navigation Company Limited but run by ihis iirm,lost throughout the year,tne visits of the ^arly’ and f Pagervick f (neither ol whom utilized their services) causing adaitional loss. The Lanuing Company,like the *uail L'ervice,are a vital necessity lor Bahrain, since they ana they alone possess craft large enough to handle very omjty cargo,and cr^ws prepared to take their coats out in ooisterous weather. 53. iir.L.u&amp;m held charge of the ^astern Bank throughout the year. The new premises were opened on the ^cra June and represent a new era in Bahrain building, being constructed oi sfceel rnd reinforced concrete. GO. Complaints against the unduly high rates charged by the Anglo ersian Gil Company Limited lor petrol continue to be made, iiajji A. F. Williamson and ilr.Luard visited Behrain during the year,and Mr. Fy lies passed through Bahrain after securing an exploration concession xrom the Ghaikh of atar. iQdi wii-iCi* . 61. Luring the year 3,307 registered letters were received ana 3,2Ul despatched as compared with 3 ,duo registered letters received ana 3,ucu despatched during the previous year. 3,30? parcels were received ana 371 aespatcned and Rs. 12 ,164/2/- worth of stamps were sold. Cash Certmc&amp;tes worm Rs. 18,080/12/- were sold and Certificates worth iis.7,028/9/6 were discharged. British Postal Orders to the value of hs.9b2/l/6 were sold ana Ks.ol/lo/b paid. Savings Bank deposits amounted to Ks. 41, 347/lb/3 and ^oney orders lor Rs* 1,21,142/6/o were issuea ana iiS.b,626/4/6 paid. articles despatched by the nest bound nir Pail weighed ob*960 kilograrmnes and by the Last bound Air Mail 29*000 kilo grammes. 62. ir.Bashiruddin was replaced in October by Ur.'.afar Husain,wno was formerly at Bahrain. Mr.Bashiruddin suflered ifrom a mi id form of religious mania and caused considerable annoyance to the public and the Agency and finally,it is believed to the Postal hepartaent itself# m £» 1 0 A h • 63* Assistant Surgeon H#Hoiaes neld charge throughout the year and aid excellent work, it is interesting to note that Bahama women,the most ignorant ana bigoted inhabitants of the Islana 8 ,come to ];r.Holmes’ hospital more readily than to the American Mission omen’s nospit&amp;l. 64. The total number of cases treated during the year, compared with the previous year,were:- 1931. 1932. Outdoor patients ... 13,070 14,bl4 indoor patients ... 244 273 Major and Minor Operations ... 1,033 709 65. 32,3?o outaoor patients and 337 inaoor patients were treated at the Pen’s Hospital of the American mission during the year and 515 Major and Minor operations were performed. 66 . Dr.L.P.Dame proceeded to Tail* on the 20th Liay to attend a favorite wife of Bin Sa’ud’s,returning on the 2nd August. The then proceeded tu India on two months recess. Ir.Thoms from Basrah neld charge of the Hospital during hr. Dame’s absence on tne mainland. The Mission doctors are always ready to leave their Hospfctals for indefinite periods and it necessary close them to attend cases in the interior. 67. The aoraen’s nospital ol tne American Mission treated 16,606 outdoor patients and 303 indoor patients during ibf32. y 4 Major ana Minor operations were performed. Mrs (Dr) Haenggi held charge throughout the year. 63 . a serious matter is the great increase of malaria, the number of cases being lour times as many as those in 1926, which has resulted from the boring of artesian wells and the breeding iacilities afforded to mosquitoes in the waste water. Mequres to comoat this evil are being concerted.13. JLHICIaL . 69. The tot^al number of Civil suits instituted was 2,471 compared witn 2,310 in 1931,ana the total number of Criminal suits 44b as compared with 360. The total number of petitions registered during the /ear amounted to 2,969 and Insolvency cases to 9. VISITS OF OCYrMilbiMT OFFICIALS ANh OTKhRS . 70. The Kon f bie Lieut Colonel Sir Hugh 3iscoe,K.i5.L., Political hesident in the Persian Gulf,paid an official visit to Bahrain on the 3rd January accompanied by hr.Baggallay of the Teheran Legation* He again visited Bahrain for varying periods on the 20th January,20th ^arch (accompaniea by His Britannic Majesty’s Minister at Teheran, Mr.Hoare),12th April, 3rd blay ana 20th June. His death on the 19th July was much lamented by ail the inhabitants of Bahrain,who felt they had lost a sincere friend, ^hen the number of these visits is considered,many m rough/ weather ana some in most unpleasant heat,it will be realised aow Sir Hugh hastened his end by his devotion to duty. 71. The Hon’ble Lieut Colonel T.C...'.Fowle,C.B.E.,Political hesident in the Persian Gulf,also visited Bahrain oil an official visit from the bth to 12th Lee ember, accompanied by Mr. J.Croning, U • B.E.,Und er Secre tary. 72. Sir Philip Sassoon,Under Secretary of State for Air, passed through Bahrain m January. lie was to hsve spent a night here,out receiving an unfavourable weather report postponed his arrival a day and only halted for an hour or so. He was much struck by the relative cleanliness of ^anaaiaii f as compared with Baghdad. 73* other visitors ■■vere the ohsiich of KuvaitjWho sccomp* anieh Sir Hugh Siscoe in January,a soaewhat etabarrassing visit. V4. iiousieur Georges Cassin,French Consul at Buahire, arrivea on the lyth of iiarch and left on the both.19. '.Gi: L 75. :v!r.K.S.Twitchell,an American Prospector,believed to be in tne pay of Crane,the American bathroom millionaire,arrived from Hasa on the 7th January. 7d. ‘ihe number of Indian beggars has somewhat reduced,and J no disreputable Europeans visiteu liehrain curing the year, thereby showing tiiat the Passport restrictions have borne fruit. 1 oA T UIiI AHAiUA . 77. The outstanding point of interest was the iion T ble Lieut Colonel Sir Hugh Hiscoe*s visit to Bin Sa T ua at Hofuf, accompanied by the Political .ngent, dap tain G.G.Prior,and Lieut Colonel li.H.P.Hickson,C.I.o.,Political ^igent,Kuwait. The visit was interesting,the apparent friendliness of Bix^a T ua contrasting with the sour looks of nis loilowers. The party left Kofuf on a characteristic note of savagery,seeing,a hand and foot of two men mailed over tne town gate as they went out. The men had been caught stealing camelsjand owed their lives to the clemency of Bin Sa ? ud,Bin Jiluwi,the redoubtable Amir of Hasa,having wished to put them to death. 78. The Amir Mansur,a thirteen year old son of Bin Sa^d, visited Bahrain on the 14th January for medical treatment. 79. Muhammad al Tawwil rented the ilesa Customs lor eleven lakhs in January,but was unable to secure this figure ana was obliged to ask for it to be reduced. TP^e Province,more especially Qatif,has been reduced to destitution by the impositions of Bin Sa’ud.who has killed the goose that laid the golden eggs with remarkable skill. But for the preveryrtion oi the emigration of women,the bulk of the population would have fled to Bahrain long- ago. 80. Abdul Aziz usaibi went on Haj j in February,his purpose being to extract some money from Bin Sa'ud. in this he failed, and the usaibis have ceased to import for him, the work now being done by Muhammad al Tawwil ana the payments made iron the Hasa Customs. The enormous sum of money thus tied up with Bin Sa f ud20 . y weakened them,and thou^^h their influence in i Bahrain is still very strong they are much more easily handled than before. Abdullah usaibi has permitted himself some most violent reraarks about nis Monarch,which will doubtless reach the Royal ears. 81. L-essrs Boucicault and GaXder employees oi the Marconi Company arrived on the 26th April and paid one or two other visits to Bahrain. They had experienced great amicuity with their h’ajdi personnel,and mentioned the incident of a simple private of the line who had oeen promoted mechanic for meritor ious behaviour. They erected stations at Jubaii and .atif bringing the number in Bin 2aMid’s dominions to eighteen. 82. Muhammad al Tawwil studiously avoided the agency on his visits to Bahrain,as do almost all hajdi officials,but visited the Ilon’ble the -'olitical Resident on one occasion on board a Mail Steamer. Bin Sa’ud had apparently tacitly accepted the claim oi the Bahrain Government to two per cent transhipment dues on all cargo passing through Bahrain waters,for Muhammad al Tawwil was instructed to pay (3rd September) on a consignment oi 12,000 bags oi rice and 600 bags of sugar that came through for the mainland,but later m conjunction with Muhammad al u&amp;rzuk oi Karachi,he arranged for tiie ’Ahmedi ? to taice some 2G,000 bags ol rice airect to the mainland. I'de Hahrain Govern ment declined to allow this steamer to land Bahrain cargo,winch was over carried 1*0 the mfcxnl&amp;nd. Tawwil,with an eye no doubt to iuture snipments allowed it to be stored tree and brought back to Bahrain without payment of any duty,and is said to have erected a Customs shed at Mas Tan?urah,and to have offered merchants free transhipments should they aring other consignments there. 83. Bahrain is a liaboth’s vineyard for the King of Sa’udi Arabia ( A T a R. 84. The Political Agent paid several visits to atar,twobeiiu., m connection with an emergency aerohroiac near Dohah. The Shaikh had agreeu to tnis,subject to being granted an aauitional measure of protection,but when nis wisn was acceded to he then produced otner reasons lor being unable to grant it* ^iitical Agent successfully closed the cases which had causea trouble with the Ghaikh at the end of the pi eceeuing y ear,and pleasant relations v/itn the ohaikh were restored. V Gh^VGHT * So. Twenty slaves w^re nianumitted during the year,employ ment being iound lor some m the Bahrain Police. Ho thing of interest occiuTeb. m this connection during the vear. S?. The rainfall amounted to 2*70 inches,the year being somewhat cooler than its predecessor. The most striking features were an exceptionally calm January and autumn,the latter being very favourable to the raddah. 38. The year ended with a more optimistic note than 1931 owing to the improvement in the local pearl market,and the Bahrain Government,having won back in the divers 1 riot the prestige they had lost ever the agitations of lebruary,concluded the year in a stronger position than they have hitherto enjoyed, despite their financial difficulties. 89. The year has on the whole been more s&amp;tisfactory than 1931 ana the inhaDitfJits of Bahrain arc possibly even better disposed to the Agency than before. His Excellency Ghaikh hamad bm isa al Kualifah is a loyal friend to His Majesty’s Government and deserves well ol them. Lieut Colonel. Foiltical Agent,Bahrain.A to No:C/612-8/8. Political Agency, Bahrain,the £3rd Leceraber 1938. To, The Adviser to the Bahrain Government, Bahrain. Memorandum . Aould you kindly let me have the following inlormation lor use in compiling the Annual Administration Report of the Bahrain Agency,lor the calendar year ending the 31st December 1933:- 1. Police . Strength on 1-1-1933. 31-13-1933. Indian Police. Arab Police. Followers. Total. Naturs . Manamah. Muharraq i Total. A snort note on the Police and on Law and Order in general. Number of schools in existence on 1-1-1933. Number of schools openea during the year. Number of schools closed during the year. ENumber ol students on the rolls on 1-1-1933. Number or students on the rolls on 31 - 13 - 1933 . Number ol teachers on the 1st January 1933. Number of teachers on the 31st December 1933. A short note on education. 4* Pearling; Industry . A short note. 5. Municipalitie s. A short note. 6. It would be convenient if you would let me have the information by the end of January 1934. Lieut-Colonel. Political Agent,Bahrain.No:C/613-8/8. Political Agency, Bahrain,the 23rd Lecember 1933. The Lirector of Customs Bahrain. Memorandum Would you kindly supply me with the following intormation,i or use in compiling the Annual Administration d Report oi the Bahrain Agency,lor the calendar year enaing the 31st Lecember 1933;- (a) Number of launches built m Bahrain during 1333. (b) Total number of launches plying lor hire on the 31st December 1933. (c) Number of Pearling craft registered in 1933 as compared with 1932. (a) Number of:- and other Ships that entered and cleared the Port of Bahrain during the years which ended on the 31st December 1932 and 1933 (separately). (e) Customs revenue for the period 1st January to 31st December 1933 as compared with the revenue lor the same period of the previous year. (f) Gross value of the trade of Bahrain for the year 1933 under the following heads (g) Total value of transhipped cargo and customs revenue thereon for the years 1932 and 1933. (hj A brief report on accidents within port limits. 2. it would be convenient if you would let me have the information by the end of January 1934. British German imports. Exports. General Merchandize. Pearls. Specie. Total. Lieut-Colonel. Political Agent.,Bahrain.:.0.No:C/6l4-e/b. iecember 1933. nOuld you kindly let me toTe tiie lollG^in^ inicrmalion,tor use in compiling t&amp;e /innual Administration Report ot me Bahrain Agency,regarding the working oi your (a; Ruaber ol out-aoor patients treats^. (b) dumber ot in-door patiente troatec. (cj Number of major operations perioraed. (d; Number of minor operations perionaed. (•) A snort note on any epidemics that may have come to your notice. (f) anything else of special interest. 2. 1 should also be grateful it you would let me have any Iigure8,ffhich may be easily available,bearing on the spread of malaria and venereal disease. 3. It would be convenient if you would let me have the information by the end of January 1934. hospital/s during the calendar year ending the 31st Lecember 1933:- Yours sincerely, Victorial Slemorial Hospital Bahrain.No. 0 f 1352 Office of the adviser to the Government, Bahrain. Dated, Ranadhan 20, 1352 January 6, 1934. H. B. M T s Political Agent, Bahrain. Memorandum:- P Pith reference to your memorandum No.C/612-8/8 dated December 23, 1933, my last annual report dealt with part of the period under review, but as we work according to the Arabic calendar the reports overlap. Police. Strength on 1-1-33 31-12- Indian Police 11 4 Arab Police 118 138 Followers 8 8 Total - 137 150 During the year an experiment has been made by sending four of the Bahrain police for a nine months course of training with the 10th Baluch Regiment at Karachi. Some N.C.Os and men of the same battalion have been sent as instructors for the police in Bahrain. The result of this arrangement has been extremely successful. The Police in addition to their normal duties have taken part in an unusual amount of ceremonial drill, guards of honour etc., during the year.the Police posts in Hedd, ^uharra^, and Sakhir as well as the guards in Manamah have been maintained. Lately the }olice have taken over daytime control of t.ie Manama a bazaar where owing to increased motor traiiic etc it was found necessary to post police on point duty. This arrangement has made it possible to effect a reduction in the Manamah Naturs. The strength of the Naturs at present is as follows:- 1-1-33 Strength on ^ 31-12-33. Manamah llaturs 77 67 Maharaq 1L turs 43 43 120 i i 1 O 1 1 r-H 1 1 rH | About 40 policemen are available for daily parades and for any emergency that might occur. The Police force, which is now composed entirely of locally enlisted men, mostly Bahrain subjects, is more popular with the people and more effective for police work than when it consisted of Indians. Law and Orde r. In spite of hard times and unemployment there have been an unusually small number of serious crimes although there is an increase in petty thieving and pickpocketing. One case of attempted murder was tried by the Bahrain Court during the year. There is an increase in the number of liquor cases and the habit of drinking liquor is spreading. The vigilance of the authorities and the severity of punishments has caused owners of illicit stills to take most careful precautions to conceal theirliiGir trcde. In three recent cases the persons who liquor were servants of meuibers of the Ruling Familj/. HIii cat ion . Schools. boys. Girls. No. of schools in existence on 1-1-33 5 2 Schools closed during the year — Schools opened during the year — Total number of schools 5 2 on 31-12-33. boys girls Number of students on the rolls on 1-1-33 — 623 190 Number of students on the rolls on 31-12-33 — 629 198 Number of teachers on 1-1-33 27 Number of teachers on 31-12-33 27 At-the beginning of the new term, after the diving season, the number of foreign teachers was reduced. The work of the schools is progressing favourably. Boys who pass out of the schools are now grantet leaving certificates after passing an examination and no candidates for any vacancies in government offices are accepted without these certificates. Students from other schools may take the government school examination on payment of a fee. ^n independent school in Manamah managed by a Bahrain Shia was started about a year ago and is doing well. The Persian school has recently enlarged its building. Pearling. It has not ye^t been possible toto summarise the accounts of the diving clerks in orler to ascertain the value of the catch, as is done every year. ^'rom all accounts the catch was poor in quantity and quality and the market was stagnant. Most of the nakhudas sold their pearls to the merchants but the merchants in many cases were unable to find buyers. Only Mr. Pack and Mohomed Ali Zainal visited Bahrain from Europe. The advances at the beginning and end of the season were the same as last year. They were accepted without comment. jxt the usual meeting after the diving season the merchants stated that they would have liked to suggest a reduction but if this were done it might nro- voke trouble among the divers. Increasing numbers of divers worked on the Khammas system instead of the Selafieh system. Several leading pearl merchants have sug gested the advisability of considering the closing of the pearl banks for a season. This would benefit those who hold stocks of pearls frompast seasons but the divers themselves would be out of work. Such a suggestion is impracticable unless the whole diving industry of the Sulf co operated. Municipalities. Both municipalities are handicapped by shrinkage of revenue and little £ has been done except the usual routing work of town cleaning and some small improvements in widening narrow places in the bazaars and roads.Th© portion or tho sos road from Mnharra^ to the deep channel has been completed. The vvopk was supervised by the ?!uharraq municipality and the funds were provided from TT Thilth’ f with tne permission and approval of the executors of the ,? Thilth Tt adviser to the Government., 5 of 1934 Lear Sir, . . ^ Victoria Memorial Hospital, 14th: January 1934. A 1 * Ref: your letter D.C.No:C/614-8/8. D/28th: Decemherl934 The following are the figures fromt the Annual Beturn of sick for this hospital for the year 1933. No: of Out-door patients 14902. ,, /sv ,, ,, ........ 229- No: of operations.. ••••••.. .. 979. A mild epidemic of Mupps occurred during the year. The following are the figures for Malaria for the past three years. 1931...... 3137. 1932......2828. 1933 3696. Yours sincerely. Lt:Cil: Gordon Loch, H.B.M’s Political Agent.£.0.No:C/36-8/8. Political Agency, Bahrain,tne ^nd January 1934. Bear Br.Holmes, ’Aillyou kindly reler to your demi- ol'licial letter No:5 dated the 14th January 1934 iorwardmg certain statistics of work none m the Victoria Memorial Hospital during the year 1933. 3. Would you please let me know how many of the 979 operations perlormeu were minor and how many major operationsV 3. I would be glad if you would send me a short note on the spread ol venereal disease,as 1 understand that it has been on the increase in the past few years and 1 should like to know to what e tent it is so and to what it may be attributed. ¥ours sincerely, r Dr*R.Holmes, IM.B, Victoria Memorial Hospital, Bahrain.C01fJTD3NTIAL ?rom 2 1 / uAiU iv&gt;j4 w&gt;' No 30-S 0 f 1934 NriMsh Residency and Consulate-General, 'ifihire the SOth January 1934, The Secretary to tie Hon f ble the Political Resident In tie Persian Gulf. fo ^he Political Agent, Bahrain. The Political Agent, Kuwait, his Majesty’s Consul, Kerman. His Majesty’s Consul, Bandar Abbas. Administration Rpnort for the year 193 3 Si r, I am directed to request that you will kindly submit in triplicate your Administration Report for the year 1933 as soon as possible, and in any event to reach Bushire not later than the 1st of March, to enable the Hon’ble the Political Resident to submit the full report for the sphere of the Residency before the 31st March. j i tof I 934 * Dear Sir, / Ref: your D.0.No:C/36-8/8. No; of )Jajor operations.• , # , Minor t t 908. There does not appear to have been any very marked increase of venereal disease during the past few years, as shown by the returns of this hospital. -The following are the figures for the past six years. Gonorrhoea. Syphilis. 1926. 124. 162. 1927. 183. 187. | 1928. 151. 143. 1929. 84. 257. 1930. 87. 207. 1931. 120. 154. 1932. 91. 215. 1933. 108. 279. thousands of young men arrive to take part in pearl diving. Sea ports,and places with large floating populations always have a high incidence of venereal disease,and fahrain is no exception. As the locals consider venereal disease of small importance,the above figures are only a fraction of those infected yearly. Yours sincerely i Col: Gordon Loch, H.B.M’s Political Agent,HgPQRT OF THE MARION WELLS THQI^S HOSPITAL. 1933 There were a number of changes in the hospital staff this year* Dr* Tiffany who was married last year went home with her husband in June* Her furlough, really began in April but she kept up some of her hospital work until June* Mrs* Van Peursem returned from furlough in February and began almost at once to take over some of the hospital workj taking over full responsibility with the beginning of Dr* Tiffany's furlough* Our Indian nurses who had served us faithfully for five years left in February and two new nurses came two weeks after their departure* Two more nurses came in August. Miss Te Winkle of Madanapelle helped us get all four and we are very grateful to her untiring efforts in our behalf. When in July the King of Sa # udi-Arabia asked for womens medical help in Riadh we were hard pressed to know what to do. If Mrs. Van Peursem and one nurse went to Nejd only one nurse (and a new one) would be left. We felt sure however that Dr. Harrison who was to bring the other two nurses with him from India would respond to bur request and fill in at least part of the interval at Bahrain. So it was decided accordingly. It was really thrilling to know that Central Arabia was also beckoning for women doctors and nurses. Dr. Harrison made his first trip to Riadh sixteen years ago. Since then our men doctors have made four more trips there y but now women were to have a turn also and we really believe that this first call will be followed by others. Mrs. Van Peursem writes: The work among the women in Riadh was as much of a social interest as it was of health value for them. Inour visits with the women we did concentrate on health talks, hygiene and infant care. Religion, especially comparative religion was frequently brought up by the more intelligent. V/e had many opportunities to testify to the superiority of Christianity as the only 'Way to Salvation.' The patient for whom we had been called, a wife of the King one other lady of the royal household and four slaves were operated on during our stay. The ladies received every attention possible and as good nursing care as conditions would permit. However, the four slaves, who had to be in a small room at the men^ hospital, receiving a minimum of nursing made a more rapid recovery than their more favoured owners. Nurse Grace and I dividing our nursing duties between us often had fourteen hours days. i Whenever and wherever we visited the circle of women present soon turned into a small dispensary. Several of the royal ladies received regular treatments and after these were given as if by a signal relatives with children, slaves and their little ones would appear by dozens needing quinine, mixtures, eye-drops, ointments etc. Hypodermic injections are very much a la mode in Hiadh and all kinds of miracles are expected of them. We treated approximately twenty-five patients (women and children) per day; many of these patients receiving but one treatment. The application of Spanish fly plaster threaten ed to out-popularize the ancient custom of branding. We hope that as more humane remedies displace their crude branding etc. that also their false beliefs, superstitions, slavery and concubi nage may be dispersed by the Great Physician who loves them.” The work in Bahrain has followed the usual lines with some increase in every line of work except obstetrics. The orphanage begun by Dr. Tiffany is a particularly fine piece of work. It is a touching sight to see the five babies sleeping-3- sleeping in their lovely white cots. There are also five older children and Bertis who is in the C.M.S. home at Nasik, Inaia, rhe blind boy, Abud, has been sent to the Home and School lor the Blind, in Jeruselenu rhe orphans constitute an added burden and responsibility. Financially they are a liability. 1‘hey take up the whole children * s ward and recently an adjoining room has been set asj.de for the older children and the care-takers. (The main care-taker is Urn Miriam who was baptised last Easter.) This means so much less hospital space. Healthy children should not be in a hospital at all but until we have a separate building for an orphanage the present arrangement must be continued. Mrs. Van Peursem also began classes in midwifery. Six enrolled and the class met twelve time when it was temporarily halted by the Nejd tour. The Manama Municipality secured one of our former nurses to open a small dispensary and to take care of obstetrical cases. We are on the best of terms with her and have offered her our help at any time. Our Christian community is gradually increasing in numbers and influence through such efforts. A small circular garden in front of the hospital building gives promise of adding much beauty to the yard. Staff prayers are held every morning and later morning prayers in the dispensary. Many of the patients and their friends attend the Sunday morning chapel service. The greatest need we have is far a suitable building to house the orphans. Their number will no doubt increase. STATISTICS. Hew patients •••••••• 5480 Total treatments.•*•• 20978 P.T.ONo:C/Vb-tf/tt. Political Agency, Panram, tile 7th February 19b4. To, Tne Lirector of Customs, Bahrain. Memorandum . \ 'V ^ould you Kindly send me,as soon as you 1 conveniently can,your reply to my Memorandum No:C/fal3 dated tne ^brd BecemDer lydo regarding mtormation tor the Annual Administration Report. Lieut-Colonel, Political Agent, Ban ram.THE CUSTOMHOUSE. ' - BAHRAIN. ' n. /ut / 7 th February, 195 A., No ?k/hh/JrJ 22nd Shawal, 1^52., H.B.M's Political Agent, BAHRAIN. MEMORANDUM :- y i 3&gt; In reference to your No=0/615-8/8 of the 25-12-55., I have to report:- (a) Number of motor launches built in Bahrain during the year \93}: NIL. Add: Motor launches brought here from foreign ports, and registered as Bahrain craft t. Sailing craft converted in motor launch by fitting new engine: 1. Number of new sailing craft built in Bahrain during 1923. . . 17. / Sailing craft built in Bahrain sold to a foreign port: . . .1. (b) Number of motor launches plying for hire on 3 1st Deer 1922**,,&gt; 42. ' ' ' ' H n tawwasha n n n ,....14. n n ,1 ' for private use 2 . This does not include the Political Agent's steam launch nor his motor launch. (c) Licensed Pearling craft during 1932: (l) Rehewals 282, (2) New licenses. 75. . . 438. Licensed Pearling craft during 1933: (l) Renewals 262, (2) New Licenses... 74, . . 426. (d) Number of steamships entered and cleared during year 1952: Would you please refer to my PA/HL/l5/443 of 15 th January, 1955. Number of steamships entered and cleared during year ended 51/12/22:- BRITIS Hi B.I.S.N.Coy Ltd: .... 105. Strick Line: .... 2 p. British Tanker Coy Ltd. . . — GERMAN : Hansa Line ..•*•• Total :- ^52* (Not including warships, or light-tender). (e) Customs Revenue from all sources: Tear i ^ v. Q ,r»niiA fl+flmoa for Government Licenses) (f) ^rtr^of-r^ year ,5- «ouia you please refer to my PA/SF/25/488 of 14th February 1955. t8i Exports.: Value of the trade for the year 1955- a, . 79 - 60 ,110/- Ra:56,45,750/- General Merchandise. . * / 5 ^ 37 ^ 740 /- Pearle (stated value) il.9l’.68o/- 25.44.610/- Spe0ie Totals:- ~ 91.94.500/^ These figures are collated from my monthly trade reports. 1032’ 1955? (g) Transhipment cargo: baton s duty. Valuei_Cust®e_^ty: Re =25,59,0007- Re:90,780/- (h) No accident by eea of any ^^^rncXV^a.^^ 9 ^ PVHL/S^^^-J-^-^ whiih reported an accident with loss of life at sea between Qatif and Bahrain. ^ 1 // /&lt; OF CUSTOMS, and PORT OFFICER. BAHRAIN.(% i o. *\ ?&amp;*\ iTS Confidential . No:C/143-8/8. Political Agency, Bahrain,the 35th February 1934. From:- To:- Lieut-Colonel Cordon Loch,I.A., Political Agent, Bahrain. The Honourable the Political Resident m the Persian Gull, Bushire. I have the honour to refer to your Circular Letter No:30-S dated the 30th January 1934 and to say that it is regretted that pressure of work has pre cluded my being able to complete the annual Admin istration Report for the year 1933 but it is hoped to send it by the next mail. I have the honour to be Sir, Your most obedient servant,0 Political Agency, Bahrain,the hth ^arch 1934. &amp;U) Coniident ial . No:C/173-8/«. From:- Lieut-Coionel Goraon Loch,I.A., Political Agent, Bahrain. To: - Tne Honourable the Political Resident in tne Persian Gulf, Bushire. Sir, I have the honour to forward,in triplicate, my Annual Report on the administration of the Bahrain Islands. I have the honour to be Sir, Your most obedient servant, Lieut-Coionel, Political Agent, Bahrain.nummistratioG r.eport ol* the Bahrain ,gency lor tne year ( a ^* 'olitical .iHent . (!;• Lieutenant-Colonel Gordon Loch held charge of the iigency until tne Uth /ipril,when he proceeaea to Bushire to oiiiciate lor tne Political I.esiucnt,Knho was proceeuing to ingland on deputation, curing his absence,till the ii3rd May, the inaian itSoistant,Lhan oahaaur ’Abdul Laiy al hashixi, olliciateu as Political iigent. viij. on tne ^Ith July Lieutenant-Colonel Gordon noch again proceeded to dushire handing over cnar^e oi the Agency to oaptain h.H.Gaatrell. i.ieutenant-Colonel Loch returned iron Bushire on the 1st Auvember and took charge ol the Agehcy iron Captain Gostreii. iriaian Assistant . Khan Bahadur ’Abaul Haiy al Lashimi held charge ol the post ol Indian Assistant throughout the year. (i). His Excellency Ohaikh lianad bin Use Al Khalirah,C.S.l has been on excellent terms with the Agency throughout tne year. On the 9th February he was presented a Khantan Iron His excellency the Viceroy oi India by the Honourable the Political Lesicent in the I ersian Puli at a ^arbar held to celebrate his accession to the huiership oi Bahrain. His excellency LhaiKh Hamad has been accorded a personal salutes! eleven guns. On the 9th lecember His ^xceliency Shaixh Hamad bin Use Kiiaiifan proceeued to Kuwait in h.i.S inorenam on a visit t. excellency lHaiidi Lir ,iniaad Din Jatur,K.C.l.,0. . 1.,Isule/ Kuwait. He returned on tiie IDtn leceober.well please- witic(**)• ^ nigixX oi tlie 3ni/4tii June a son, 1 isa,was boro to Shaikh oaliaan,tne huier’s eldest son* r j.iie event causec such rejoicing ana news oi it wes receivea with noticeable interest b/ the v haikh oi v^atar and the Rulers of the iracial Coast* (iiij* On the idhnd November the -&lt;idow of His excellency shaikh Oir f Isa bin ? Ali Al Kh&amp;lifah left by sea for Mecca,where it is supposed tnat she will resiae* it is said that she took with her a considerable amount of gold. (iv). shaikh Muhammad bin f lsa Al khalifah marnec a young daughter of his brother-in-law, T Abaullah bin : aia,on the 13th July, his former ;.ife aieo in 1333. (v). Lihaikh ? ;)bauliah bin ’Isa Al Anal if ah has been on good terms with the Agency. (vi). Shaikh Jalman bin iieaad t d Khalifah is on eAceilent terms with the Agency and is doing well on the Bauram Courts. A son was born to hii; on the night of the 3rd/4th June. (vilj. hhaikh feshia oin Muhanaad Al Khalilah has done gooa work as resident of the . ajlis al f L T rfi. 3. BAHRAIN AUh . (i). Mr.C.D.Belgr&amp;ve held charge of the appointment of Financial Acviser ana Commandant of Police throughout the year. (li). Mr.C.C.L de Grenier,Lirector of Customs ana Fort Jfficer,proceeded to India on short leave on the 13th July and returned on the 13th November. (in). Hr. a.B.S teele held charge of the appointment oi State kngmeer throughout the year. (iv). Hr.^.Bevjr of essrs hinney Murray ana Company, Chartered Accountants,3aghaad,amveu on the loth arch out an audit of the Bahrain uoveroment accounts lor 13F 4. ^O^iCA * The forces of law and order in Bahrain consisPolice ana i^autrs or mgtit-watchmen. The latter are an irregular body,who do not wear unitorm or peri'crm any drill but are armed with long Lee untield ritles. (it)« -he Armec lolice nave posts in HidajL’unarxa^ ana L&amp;Jchir ana supply guaids m ^anamah. in aduition to tneir normal duties, the police took part in ceremonial parades and provided guaras-oi- honour on a number oi occasions. Their appearance invariably strikes visitors as excellent. The Nature are stationed in ..'nnamah and Tuharra&lt;i. (iii). The strength of these bodies is given below:- Strength on 1-1-1030. strength on 31-lk-iy33. Indian Police. 11 4 Local Tolice. 113 13d Followers. 3 6 Aaturs. 1ZQ 110 35V 26u (iT). The replacement ot Indian Police by Local men has now been successfully completed, the four Inmans who now remain being Instructors. Pour Arab Non-Commissioned Officers were sent ior training with the 10th Laluch Hegiment at Karachi,ana when they return they will be used as instructors and will replace the Indians now employed. (v;. The Bahrain Government have also aske. for the services of a Lon-Coamissionec Ofiicer ot the Indian oiice to instruct the Armec roiice in lathi drill. b. LX ah .v i i AlU,.. (i;. Tnere have been no agitations or ounni Oh^ah quarrels during the year and in spite of nara times ana unemployment there has been an unusually small number ot serious crimes,though there has been an increase in petty thieving and pick-pocketting. lily. The annk habit tens to spread ana there has been an ncrease in the number ot liquor cases, xhe vigilance oi the4. Polled and the seventy ot the punishments me tea out to olienders has had a salutary ei’lect and owners of illicit stills take the most caretul precautions to conceal their apparatus and wares. (ill). On the eve ol the 1st January 1033 a girl aged 16 years was murdered (though custom would condone the act) by her uncles in circumstances of exceptional brutality for unchastity. Ihe men then tied to ^atar where they are still at large. (iv). )n the 10th January a Ivajdi stabbec a Bahrain subject over a few annas. The case was tried by the Political A^ent, who sentenced the ksjdi to death. The sentence was coniimec by tae Governor General-m-Council and the man was executed m Bahrain on the morning of tne 10th April. on c^Coknioa . (i). The Bahrain Tetroleum Company Limited have sunit live wells into the oil bearing stratum and ere contemplating shipping oil at the rate of seven hundred tons a day from the middle of 1034. (ii). The Company have introduce^ a number of Bntian subjects among their personnel and the ligures stand:- Hritish subjects. Americans. Bahrainis. Others U Class I . Superior 3tafi Class II . 19 lerical. Camp. itrtisans Class III. — _rvants. Semi-skilled labour. Unskilled.»it Ai a vie# to controlling tlxe water supply the rJahram Gorernment issuea a notice in ::arch rorbiciLing the boring of ne.v wells witnout sanction and ordering that no ?aore wells should be borea in the towns of r&amp;n&amp;B&amp;h f Muharra^, Hidd and Galali, &lt;vhere the waste water had already become a uanger to public health, orders were also given for the provision of suitable valves to prevent water being wasted ana for the casing of all bores. Certain initial anc annual fees have been laid down and provision has been made for inspection by a Government ollioial. AGhL/ lili . (i). The experiMientai orange trees have again borne excellent fruit ana when and if more funds become available, it should be possible to develop this branch of agriculture. (iij. A quantity of ’mes^uit’ seeds ( a thorny ^aicn growing tree suitable for firewood) were obtained from iera Ismail Khan by the courtesy of tfr.B.J .Gould,Resident in Aaziristan; and both seeds and seedlings have been given to His Excellency ChaiJch hamad bin T isa Al Khalifah and to certain local individuals interested in agriculture. It was hopeo that if the experiment was successful large areas might be planted with them in oraer to avoid dependence on f Gman and the 'ersian Coast for supplies of firewood. As,however,an oil industry is developing in Bahrain, there is not perhaps the same necessity,as there was in the past,for securing an home-grown supply of firewooa. (iii). An endeavour has been maae by one firm (A 6c &amp; Tatim) with an Indian agriculturist in partnership,to start a vegetable garden for English ana Indian vegetables. The experiment was unsuccess!ul as the land was too exposed to the high winds which prevail m Bahrain.■6 . ft ». CU3TGM3 , (i). Tile Customs revenue amountec to Rs.b,£&gt;3,393/- as against R8«6,14,b94/- ooilected during the previous year* ihe decline in commodity prices is chiefly responsible for this decline. (ii). a he circumstances attendant on the visit of a ship, the S.S. ^hmedi,to has lanurah in October 1933 raiseu with the oa 1 udi Arab Government the question of the levy ol transit dues on cargo transhipped at Bahrain for ports on the m&amp;inlanu.. endeavours are being made to bring about a settlement of this dispute on terms agreeable to both countries. In tne meantime cargo for the mainland is being transhipped from steamer to lighter on payment of two per cent duty only* 10. (i). Falling revenues have prevented tne two Municipalities of Manaaah ana Fuharraq from doing anything beyond the usual routine work of town cleaning ana small improvements in road widening in the bazaars and elsewhere* (ii). In Muh&amp;rra l a causeway has been constructed as far as the drep water of the channel between Muharraq and lanamah. The funds were provideu from the ’tiiilth’ by the permission of the executors and the work was supervised by the kuharra^ iiunicipal- ity. 11. PUBLIC r.QUZ . Owing to financial stringency no works of any magnitude were carried out. 13. h XATION * (i/* Cix boys schools and two girls schools were in existence on the 1st January* ho schools were opened or closed during the year. (ii). On the 1st January six hundred and twenty-three boysaiui one huaureu ano ninety girls were on the roils and on the 31st December six hundred and twenty-nine boys and one hundred and ninety-eij/ht girls* ihere were twenty-seven teachers employed throughout the year. (HI)* ^oys who pass out of 'overnment schools are now given School heaving Certificates and no candidate for a vacancy in the Bahrain Government ofiices is acce ten,unless he has a certificate, r tudents of other schools are allowed to taKe the Government school examination on payment of a fee. (ivj. xhe Persian school has recently been enlarged. (v&gt;. A school in .anamah started a year ago by a Bahraini hhi’&amp;h is aoing well. (i). It has not yet been possible to summarize the accounts of the living Clerks in order to ascertain the value of the catch, from all accounts however,the catch was poor in quality and quantity ana the market was stagnant, ivlost of the nakhuonhs sold their pearls to merchants but tne latter were unable to find buyers. (ii). Geveral leading r e&amp;rl erchants have suggested the advisability of considering the closing of the pearl banks for a season. r ihis would benefit those who hold pearls Irom past seasons but if adopted would mean that divers would be out of work. The suggestion is^m any case,impracticable uiuess the pearls and m one case a salutary punisnment was inflicted, in &gt; view of the adverse eiiect that tne introduction of cuiturec pearls would have on the pearl trade,tne Barirain Govemiaent issued M) whole diving industry m the Gulf co-operated. (ni). Attempts are being maae to introduce Japanese cuitureu a notice laying down severe penalties lor tnose indulging in tnis nefarious practice and other rulers of the ^rab Littoral nave beefijn asxea to co-operate m the matter.tf. Uv;« total value ol trade afflouiited to Re.lb,6'/^,400/- as compsrea with Re. 16,9*2,*70/- in ly^. Tht total value ol imports amounted to Rs.y, 194,300/- as against Rs.10, bb*,VlG/- ana exports to Rs.6,676,100/- as a^inst Rs.6,399,660/- in 193^. V v;. oargo vaiueu at Ks.3,639,000/- was transhipped at Bahrain ior the aminland and other porta as compared witn cargo valued at Rs.3,103,360/- transhipped m 1933. ‘^viy. ihe ligures ol exports are not accurate since lew ol the pearls exported are declared at their proper value,and those carried by exporters in person are not declared at ail. r ihe figures tor specie are also unreliable. 14. nMMM- Hil. lb. ATHLETICS . interest in football (soccer) continues to increase and there are now seven football clubs m Bahrain. The Bahrain Sports Club,which is the oldest institution of its kind in Bahrain,plays hockey and cricket (and to a lesser degree football) and has two tennis courts. (li). There is one Golf Club in Lanamah and another at The Bahrain 'etroleum Company Limited T s camp. IS- Ml (i). The total number ol lauhcues plyiiv tor hire on the 31st lecember *as HI ty-seven as against sixty-two on the corresponding hate of the previous year. (ii;. Four hunhred ana tnirty-six pearling craft were licensee curing the year as against four hundred and titty-eight licensee m 1932. (ill). Seventeen new sailing vessels were built as compared with sixteen built curing 1932. One selling vessel was converted (9)— 9. into a launch and one was sold. (iv). One hundred and Torty-two British Ships and ten German Ships entered and cleared the Port oi Saiirain curing the year under review as compared with One hundrec and filty-one British S hips,eleven German ! hips and three Norwegian ihips that entered ana cleared the Port during the previous year. (vj. On the 31 st Lecember the S.S Hegistan of the Stnch Line of steamers ran aground about live miles north-west of the outer buoy,while entering the Bahrain harbour. She was lightered anu refloated the following day. ho aam&amp;ge was none. (vi). His Majesty Xing Bin Sa’ua purchased a launch in Bahrain from ’All bin Sa^ar al Jalahaimah for PiS.4,bOG/-. (vil). The S.S Fagervich of the National Steamship Company ol Norway proceeded to has ianurah direct in September which a cargo ol rice for the mainland. She did not call at Bahrain. (vili). The Has 'arwan beacon was dtmolisneu early in the year and a re-miorceu concrete pillar was erected in its place. Jn the 19th ^&amp;y an automatic white flashing light was placed on the pillar but,as it was in direct line with the Customs’ mast light from the Lest Spit buoy anchorage it was hardy visible to craft making the port at night,and the colour was changed to rea on the 31st October. 17. ■ i.GYAL KA7Y . (i). Th. Senior Naval Omcer,Persian Gull division,in H.M.S 'inad and later in H.a.S Gdorenam anu otiiers of His JfAj.stjr’i Snips ot the Persian Gulf division paid frequent visits to i-ahrEin||, during the year. f (ii). Lnterprise of the Fourth Cruiser Squadron arrived | r 1 f m on the 12th and left on the 14th April. She was to nave left on the 15th April but put out earlier on account of heavy seas (iii). II., .5 Luncan and Uie First Hestroyer ilotilla.accompanif -H (K hi10 . by the Senior Neval Officer,Persian Gulf Division,in H.J.S Shoreham,arrives on the Vth October ana left lor basrah on the ihe usual courtesies were exchanged and the visit was the occasion of a combined parade of Landing Parties irom the Hotiiia and the Laiirain Armed -olice. Ihe salute was taJcen by ills excellency Shaikh liamad bin ’Isa Al 'haliiah# Ihe moral cifect ei trie visit oi the Flotilla has been excellent. Ihe Arab population of the ersian Gulf has noteu our atrexigth ana mioraifition irom a number oi sources tenus to show that the visit oi the rlotiila has resulted in British Shipping being treated with more respect and less petty obstruction on the Persian Coast than has been the case for some time. vivj. Lis excellency the «av&amp;l Commandtr-in-Chiel,^&amp;st inuies Squadron,Vice-Aumiral v.h.Dunbar-Itesmith,V.C.,C.B.,in H.aUS Hawkins,paid Bahrain a visit from the Gth to 10th November. (t). li.M.S Colombo of the fourth Cruiser Squadron was at Bahrain from the 17th to Ulst lecember. HOYaL AIL FQECc. . (i). Flying Boats of Ho:&lt;203 (F.B) Squadron,Royal Air Force, paid frequent visits to Bahrain and Aapiti aeroplanes of ^0:84 Squadron,Royal Air Force,came on a number of occasions. (ii). A Rangoon Flying Boat made a forced landing at Pa^s al Biayah on the B4th July and a napiti aeroplane sank through the surface of the Aanam&amp;h lanaing ground on the 2bIn July ana broke a propeller. The machines left without incident in both cases alter repairs had been affected. (ni). In June the Political Agent returnee m &amp; Rangoon Flying Boat from Sharjah alter a tour oi the Irucial Coast in H.M.S Fowey. On the Vth August he again visitec Sharjah by Flying Boat. (H)11 . 13. AVIATION . (i). Imperial Airways United nave continued to use tne landing ground at Auharrai.as it was iounu tnat tfie landing ground was too sol't for heavy aeroplanes ol the Hannibal type* (ii). wm the 31st Bareli imperial Airways* east bound aeroplane, ?&lt;nno,Emae a iorceu landing at Jubail owing to bad visibility. He was,however,rendered assistance by tde local people and arrived at Bauram on tde ioilowing day. Uii;» xbe amount oi mails,both to anu from Bchrain,carrieci by air shows a steady increase. Uv). ^r.dceurice Wilson,a Bntisn aviator,landec,without permission,at £uharra* in his Moth GaBJC on the 31st May. As tne crucial Coast is not open to private lliers he was not allowed to leave Bahrain until he gave an undertaking that he would not proceec to Sharjah. He lelt to return to Basrah on the ioliowing morning,but it was later heard that he had iiown direct to /wadur• In justice to hiia it should be added that that the strength of the wind against him would have prevented his reaching 1! Basrah. 20 • BRITISH mmms . (i). Mr.J.Russell ol the Mesopotamia r ersia Corporation limited held charge throughout the year. Ihe Mesopotamia Persia Corporation Limited are also agents in Bahrain for Imperial Airways Limited. (ii). Mr.L.Ham held charge of the ..astern Bank Limited throughout tne year. (in). Messrs A.H.T.Chishoi*,A.C.S&amp;mp$on,A.F. aliiamson and R.H.i-.rnoia of the angle-Persian Oil Company Limited,passed through^ BcdirRin frequently on their way to Lohah m connection with o negotiations with the Shaikh of ' star. (IZj.f lii&amp;e i'd. (iv;. ,.ajor ; rank (.olmes resigneo Ms appointment of CMel jl Local Representative,The Sakraxn Petroleum Company Limited,and ! left for tne United Kingdom on tde 21st September. ilr.i.A. :| Skinner,the Company's Fields Manager,is acting as Chief Local Representative* ho. port on ick . \i). k,urin£ the year three thousand nine hundred and filty- one TG istereu letters were receiveu ana tnree tncmshnd one hundred and thrrty-iour despatched as comparec with three thousand nine hundred and seven registereu letters received and three thousand two hundred and one despatched during the previous year. Three thousand eight hunured ana twenty-eight parcels were received and two hundred arid thirty-four despatched ana stamps worth Rs. 1^,0223/14/- were sola as compared with Hs. 13 , 164/3 worth oi stamps sold the previous year. ( 11 ). Cash Certificates worth Ra.34,733/13/- were sold and ^ertilicates worth Rs.11,134/13/6 were discharged. British p ostal Orders to the value of fis. 1,369/7/6 were sold and Rs.133/6/- paid. Savings hank deposits amounted to Rs.46,330/1/4 and konay Orders for hs.l0b,20&amp;/l/6 were issued and Rs.6,017/6/- p&amp;id. (ili). Articles despatched by the east and west bound air mails weighed 3l7*o4 kilogrammes,as compared with 64*% kilo grammes in 1933. (iv). ostal communication with the mainland via Bahrain was established with eflect from the 1st July and registered and unregistered articles are accepted for Buraidan,Hail,Hoiuf,Jubail i Wat if, Riyadh and ’Gqair. Mails are exchanged weekly. (?). Indian Postage Htam,&gt;s surcharged ^Bahrain” were issued for sale to the public witu eflect from the loth August. His 'ajesty the king was graciously pleased to accept a set of the new stamps,which were presentee to him for his collection of13. postage stamps by His excellency Lhaixii Hamad bin f isa a! stamps aaa axl j. otters emanating from Bahrain are treated as unstampan by the Persian Postal authorities. ivi). mr .Zat&amp;r Husain Held charge of the Post Olfice throughout the year. 21. EPICAL . (i;. Assistant Surgeon P.Holmes,I.M.L,has heia charge extremely bigoted) visiting the Hospital lor treatment has greatly increased in the past few years. malaria cases numbered three thousand six hundred and ninety-six as compared with two thousand eight hundred and twenty-eight cases in 1932. (iii). ihe spread of malaria is ascribed to the breeding from the artesian wells ana by tne increased amount of wa standing about in houses now that the supply oi water is Steps ere being ta&amp;en to combat this development. (i). nr.L.-.Lame,:,I.I.,held charge throughout the year except for short periods wnen he visited the mainland. Khalilah ihe Persian authorities refuse to recognise the new throughout the year. He is very popular with the local inhabit ants and the number oi patients 'notably Bahrani women,who are 1 • Victo ria memorial Hospital . (ii). Vhe total number of cases treated curing’1932 ana 1933 were:- Outdoor patients. 14,614 14,902 indoor patients. 244 229 Total. 14,356 15,131 sfejor ana Minor operations. 709 979 grounds for mosquitoes which have been provided by the overflow 2. Hospitals of the American V-isaion .ito- Uij. Lr Thoms joinea the Hospital on the Hth March. He proceeheu on recess to India on the 6th July ana returned on the 1st October. aiij. flr• ft.P.Harrison arrived iroa Muscat on the 6th August and leit on the lyth September. U*)* Ir.M.N.Tillany (now Mrs.W.H.Haenggi) lel*t for the dnitec States of America on the bth June. (vj. in the men’s hospital 47,987 cases were treated curing the year as compared with 32,376 cases in 1332. In the women’s hospital 20,376 cases were treated as compareu with 16,606 cases m j 3«32. 622 indoor patients were treated in the women’s hospital ana 303 in the men’s hospital. There were 74 obstetrical cases ana 838 major ana minor operations were performed. ikialana accounted for thirty-five per cent of the cases treated. (vi;. On the l7tn April Lr.L. .Lame,accompanist: by ^rs.Oame, left for Eofuf at the request of ’Abdullah bin Jiluwi,the ’^mir of Hasa. They returnee on the bth Llay. (vii). Dr*A.A.Thoms ana tne Leverend G.L.Van Feursea proceeded to Larin on the 3th May and returnee on the Hth. (vui). In July His majesty King Bin Sa’ud asiteu lor medical help for women and a party consisting of Lr and Mrs.Dame, Mrs.Van Peur8em,Iiss G.Davis and five compounders ana servants left for Riyadh on the 26th July. The patient for whom they had been called was a ife of the King ana another laay of tne » i Poy&amp;l household. The party returned to Bahrain on the 24th October, vhile in Riyadh they performed 130 operations,treated 3,267 cases ana receivea 221 out-calls. JUDICIAL . The total number of Civil Suits institute^ was one thousand nine hundred ana forty-one as compared with two thousand four (lb;(16) and seventy-one institutea during 193k: end tne total number of criminal suits ms four dundreo and seventy- two as compared witd four hundred anu forty-five for the previous year. (iij. The total number of petitions registered amounteu to two thousana three hundred and fifty-three arm insolvency cases to four. (ill). On® murder case was tried in wdicn tde accused was a subject oi oVudi Arabia. He was lound guilty and sentenced to death, lue sentence was confirmed by the Governor General- in-Council and the execution was carried out in Bahrain. (iv). The decrease m the number of Civil Suits instituted is due to the prevailing depression. 23* mils JT GGYuh^Nl OI-riCLiuS (i). f ihe iionoureble Lieutenant-Colonel T.C.^.Fowle,C.B.h., rulitical resident in the Persian Gulf,visited iiahram on the wth F ebruary and landed for tae day on the IBth March. He again visited bahram from the 11th November to the 2Gth. ( 11 ). Air Commouore A.L.Cunningham,C.B.,Chief of tne Stall, British Forces in ’Iraq,arrived on the 3th February. (iii). Colonel J.F.Turner,I.S.O.,director of . orxs in the Air xiinistry,visited Bahrain on the 23rd ^sreh. (iv). Air-Vice Marshall C.$.3urnett,C.B.,C.3.B.,D.S.O., Air Oflicer Commanding,British Forces in Ura-i,arrived on tne 9th May. He again vxsitea Bahrain on the 24th September and 16th November. (v). Her excellency Udy Aillingaon passed through by Imperial Airways f west bound aeroplane on the Ibth June. She was met at the aerodrome by the Political Agent. (vi). Captain (now rlajor) C.G.Prior,lately Political Agent, Bahrain,passed through bj the east bound aeroplane on the 6th June. (vii). Major J.J.Rooney, I.M.S. f Heaidency Burgeon,Busnire,arrives on a visit of inspection on the 2nd August. (viiij. Kajor C.K.U.Breaner,iI.C. .Political Agent,Muscat, erriveu on the Sth floreaber to aeet the ilonoursble the Political resident. vix;. Captain l;.]s.fiallaoe,K.C.,Cinl Lord of the Admralt/, passeu through on the west touna aeroplane on the loth November. lie wfcs met at the aerodrome by the Political Agent. • v xy. Mr. B.C.H.Cross,Area A;anager,Near i&amp;st Area,Imperial Airways Limited,arrived on the 17th January and leit on the *Gth. vxij. Mr.a.h.Lomb&amp;rai (a citizen ol the dnited States oi* America;,8 director or The Bahrain etroieum Company Limitec, arnveu on the Mnd March. vXii). Mr. d.??.wanson,Chairman oi* the. ..astern and General Syndicate Limiteo,arrived on the Mnd -iarch. (xiii). His Excellency Shaikh dir Ahmad bin Jabir,K.C.I.^., • wa• X•,itUler ot [.uvyait,arrived on the 20th June anu leit on the 1st July. (xiv} • Shaikh sultan bin Sa^arjBuler of Lfcarjah,arrived on the 29th October and left on the 1st November. *4- 3A y BOX (i). Hasa nac been further drained of its resources by the imposition of a numoer of forced loans ana taxation lias reduced the people to a dreadful state of misery. A number of people have fled to Bahrain, smuggling their women out dresseu as men. (n). Muhammad lawil paid a visit of courtesy to the Political Agent,but no business was discusseo. (iiij. The events in 'Asir have been watched with interest, but there seems to be a general feeling tnat an outbreak of war 'between grabs’* would be most unfortunate. 25 • aatab . (i). ihe Political Agent visited *at&amp;r in K.M.S Fowey in (IV)hhmHH 17. June. The usit mg pureljr ol a priTate aeslgnea tQ renew an old friendahip and no business was aiscussed. The opportunity was,lioweTer, taken of bringing home to tne ^haiim (who had refused the Angio-^eraian Oil Company Limited permission to use s wireless set) the uses of wireless telegraphy,by arranging for him to listen to his own message of congratulation to his Lxcelienoy ‘haiKh Hamaa bin 'Isa Al Khalifah on the birth of a grand-son being transmit tea, and for tne reply to be delivered to him two or three hours later. On the next visit oi representatives of the Anglo-Persian Oil Company Limited, permission was accorded to them to use their wireless. v ii;. On the J&amp;th August Lhaihh 'Abdullah bin ^asia al TtaaA.1, I-uler ol Qatar, left for iioful en route to Illy a ah on a summons from his Majesty King 2in Sa'uu. He returned to Dohah on the . 2Vth L'epteaber. 26. SL-VoRY . f eventeen slaves were manumittec during the year as compared witn twenty :;.anumi tied during 1932. ^ i i. iLi . (i)• liie year 1933 was exceptionally cool ana high winds blew practically throughout the summer. (ii). On the 1st April a violent,though short,atorm with a wind speed ot tfQ to iib miles an hour passed over Bahrain causing considerable damage. A number oi reed huts were swept away and trees uprooted, 'art oi the wooden roofing oi a large verandah oi the Hospital was carnec away and depositee on the other side ci* the building. Hail stones measuring about an men and an half in circumference fell ana a slight earthiiuaice was felt. (iii). The total rsinfall for the year amounted to 1*44 inches. Cr-xj HhiUi « A more cheerful feeling prevailed in the Suq than there (l*) MJj15 . &lt;!£) Was in 1 ‘ !3ii,due t0 a lar s e extent to the nopes of benefits from oil. .ue saa.nistmtiTe position of the Bahrain Severn- VWv ment was stronger,thtm.* the financial situation continued to give ground lor anxiety,though the prospects of oil develop ment became brighter as the year wore on. /? uieut-Coionel f Political Agent,Bahrain.nV r-.C.No:0/239»B/8. Political iVgencj, Banrain,the Hbtn March 1934. Lear Boctor Lame, 1 - el urn, with many tnanics,tne reports, enclosed in your letter dated the &amp;ia February 1934, on the Lancn „ells lhorns hospital and tiie I'ason Memorial Hospital lor me year 1933. I have read them with great interest,the more so as 1 can irom my own experience contrast conditions now with those of the past. Yours sincerely, /i lr.L.P.Lame,i*i.L., Bahrain.iiOministratiori Report tnr 193^, n V'r CO CO .Ko:l. .No:2. S.No:3. S.No:4. F.A. Drafts to:- Adviser, director of Customs, Dr.Holmes. Dr.Dame, submitted for approval please. Memorandum «o:C/ol2 at ^S-liJ-lSSb to iiaviser,Baiirain Govt. Memorandum No:C/513 of 33-12-1933 to Lirector of Customs. ' setter Iw:C/614 of 28tb Eecember 1933 to Lrs.Lame and Holmes. ; ■!** i xi/iemoranaum No:923-9A of G-l-1934 from Adviser,Banrain Covt. P.A . '?ay await replies from Director of Customs and the 11.Os of the 2 Hospitals. ^Y&lt;- I S.No:5. | D.O No:5 of 14-1-1934 from Dr.Holmes,Victoria Memorial Hospital 1) . The M.O does not say how many of the 979 operations performed by him during the year were minor operations and how many major operations. 2) . No mention is made of the spread of venereal disease. 3) . Draft submitted for approval. IllS.No:61 S.No:7. S.No:8. Letter No:C/36 of 22rad January 1934 to Er.R.Holmes. Secretary’s Circular letter No:30-S of 20th January 1934. P.A . Statistics are being collected and are due by the 21st January 1934 from the Director of Customs and the Mission Hospital. 2. May file? / D.0.No:7 of 24th January 1934 from Er.R.Holmes. P.A. File? SJo:9. Letter dated 2-1-1934 from Dr.Dame,Mission Hospital,Bahrain. ^ 3 . No reply nas yet Deen receivea irom tne Director of Customs. . Draft reminder submitted for approval please. r A / [,'M S.No:10. Memorandum No:C/?5 of ?-2-1934 to Director 01 Customs. S.No:ll. Memo No:PA/HL/12/b21 of V-2-34 from Director ol Customs.(2) r Confic ential . NosC/^S-e/S. To, I IS Politics! Agency, « Bahrain, the If^th January 1935* The Adviser to the Bahrain Governrrent, Bahrain* Memorandum ** Would yoUjkindly let me have the following information i or use in compiling the Annual Administration Report of the Bahrain Agency, for the calendar year ending the 31st December 1934:- 2 * Police. Strength on 1-1-1934. 31-12-1934. laturs Indian Police, i^rab Police. Followers. !• Manamah. Muharraq. • •••••• • ••••••• Total. A short note on Police and on law and Order in general. i nucation . Number of schools in existence on 1-1-1934. Number of Schools opened during the year. Number of Schools closed during the year. Total. Number of students on the rolls on 1-1-1934. Nu ber of students on the rolls on 31-12-1934. Number of teachers on the 1st January 1934. Number of teachers on the 31st December 1934. short note on education.mmmssaasaasmama^mm 2 . 3. Pearling Industry . A short note. 4 * Ijinicl^alities . A short note. 5. Agriculture. A short note. The i-lectr lc Departir^nt . A short note. It ’jvould be convenient if you v.ould let me nave the information by the end of January 1935(tUD No:C/26-8/8 Pol tical Agency, Bahrain, the 12th January 1335 To, The D:rector of Customs Bahrain j.3:,.or:-nQum Vould you kindly supply me wUh the following Lnformat: for use in compiling the /annual Administration Report of the •Banr&lt;u_n agency, for uhe calendar year ending the 31st December (a) number of launches built .n Bahrain dur ng 1334. (b) total number of launches plying for hire on the 31st December 1834. (c) number of pearling craft registered in 1834 es compared with 1933. (d) number of:- and other Ships that entered end cleared the Port of Bahrain during the years which ended on the 31st December 1933 and 1334 (separately). (e) . Customs revenue for the per od 1st January to 31st December 1334 as compared with the revenue for the same period of the previous year. (f) Gross value of the trade of Bahrain for the year 1S34 under the following heads (g) total value of transhipped cargo and customs revenue thereon for the years 1933 and 1934. (h) a brief report on accidents within port limits. 2. It would be convenient if you would let me have the information by the end of January 1335. British, German, Japanese Italian imports. i xports General Merchandise Pearls. Specie. Total -eut-Coionel, Pol t-Cal Agent, Bahrain.D.O. &gt;oIC/27-8/8# January 137 , 5 . IjM:- v V^). Number of out-door p&amp;tients treated, (b). Number of in-door patients treated, ‘vc). Number of ^Jor operations performed. (d) . Number of minor operations performed. (e) , A short note on any epidemics that say hare come- to your notice. * x l;. Anything else of special interest* 2. I should also lye grateful if you would let sie have ^ny figures* Vv 'nich siay be easily available* bearing on the spread of malaria and venereal disease. 3. It vvouid be convenient if you would It t sue have the infer rat Ion by the end of January 1375.*7 of 1353 Office of the Adviser to the Government, Bahrain. Dated, Shawaal 25, 1353 January 30,1935. H. B. M f s Political Agent, Bahrain. Memorandum:- With reference to your memorandum No. C/25-8/8 dated 12th January 1935 in connec tion with information for compiling the Annual Administration Report of the Bahrain Agency, I am giving below the required particulars.— 1. Police. Strength on 1- -1-1934 31- -12-1934 Indian Police 11 4 Arab Police 118 146 Followers 8 8 137 158 Naturs, 67 Manamah 77 Maharaq 43 42 120 109 During the summer the death ocurred of Haji «bulman bin Jasim, the Police Officer. Haji Sulman had served in the Police from the time that they were originally organised. He was a Shia Bahraani, a capable and loyalloyal officer, his skill in investigating criminal cases was remarkable. It was entirely owing to him that the gang of Arabs,who carried out the Sitrah murders and the attempt on Shaikh Hamad’s life, were finally rounded up and convicted. An instructor in lathi drill was borrowed from the Karachi Police and a course of instruction was carried out dur ing the year. The usual police posts have been main tained, owing to the double service of aero planes the police post at Hedd is kept more busy than before. The question of increas ing the number of men stationed at Hedd is under consideration. About 40 men are now available for daily parades at the Fort. Hundreds of applications are received every month from men wishing to enlist as policemen. Law and order. One case of murder took place in Muharraq towards the end of the year. The victim was a prostitute. An armed attack was made on a house in the village of Zing, about a mile from the Fort and an old man was robbed and severely beaten. He died some weeks later. The attack was carried out by several men who were armed with rifles. Money and gold ornaments were stolen. There is reason to believe that the men were Kassawis. A number of prosecutions were made inin liquor cases but in spite of the efforts of the government to suppress the manufacture ana sale of liquor the habit is increasing. It is partly due to the number of highly paid Iraqis who are employed by the Bahrain Petroleum Company, who can pay heavy prices for illicitly manufactured liquor. 2. Education. No. of schools in exis tence on 1-1-34 Schools opened during the year Schools closed during the year 7 Total 7 No. of students on the rolls on 1-1-34 827 No. of students on the rolls on 31-12-34 963 No. of teachers on 1-1-34 27 No. of teachers on 31-12-34 30 There has been some changes in the teachers in the Manamah and Maharaq schools as certain masters did not return after the holidays, having obtained posts in Syria. During the year the scout system was introduced into the Manamah and Maharaq schools. One of the new masters has some experience in this work in Syria. The Shia community during the end of the year, approached the government on the question of education. They stated that the Shia boys were debarred from using the-4- the Manamah school which used to be entirely Shia. ihis is not the case, all government schools are open to students of any sect and in the Manamah boys school there are two Shia teachers. The work of education has run smoothly during the year and there have been no disturbances. 3. Pearling . The state of the pearling industry is worse than last year. There was a decrease of about 100 in the number of boats which went to the banks during the last season. The catch was small and the market was very bad. Only one foreign buyer of importance visited Bahrain and no important sales were state made in Europe. Locally the present/of the market is ascribed to the cultured pearl industry. It has taken the Bahrain pearl dealers several years to realise what harm is done to their trade by the cultured pearl industry. Figures of last year’s catch are not yet available. As the production of cultured pearls increases and improves yearly I see no prospect of improvement in the Bahrain pearl trade. The rt Tesqaam TT was settled at the usual meeting at a rate which is lower than any previous year, Rs 20/- for a diver and Rs 15/- for a puller. The mer chants and nakhudas declared that they had not got the money with which to make a larger advance. The announcement was received without any comment.4. Municipalities. No outstanding work has been done by the municipalities during the year, except the roofing with corrugated iron of one of the Man amah bazaars. Both municipalities are suffering from lack of funds. The Manamah council was’dissolved in January and the members had exceeded the term of their appointment. 5. Agriculture. Nothing to report. 6. Electric Department . The department has continued to progress as far as the production and sale of units are concerned. Approximately 17000 more units were sold in 1934 than 1933. At the end of 1933,414 different houses were con nected while at the end. of 1934,527 houses were connected. The scale of charges remains the same. Wiring of premises was continued by the department, the rate being about the same as in 1933. During the months April - October, the price was reduced by approximately Rs 6/- per point as an experiment, the result was a big loss. During the year a telephone line was run to the landing ground of Imperial Airways at Muharraq and a small exchange installed in that city. This section of the depart ment is not self supporting and the price per instrument hired has been reduced fromVictoria Memorial Hospital, jE*0*l/35 • &amp; Bahrain, the T8th: J&amp;nuary 1935* Dear Sir, Herewith the figures asked for in your B.O.Fo:C/27-8/8* Number of out-door patients..... 16472. Number of in-door patients 334. Number of major operations .21. Number of minor operations........855. Small-pox occurred in epidemic for in M&amp;harraq and Kanammeh. Venereal diseases during the year.322. Venereal Disease during 1933. 297. Malaria during tne year..... 4456. Malaria during 1933. 3696. Yours sincerelyfar Letters have issued 1 who give us inforrnati Dr Dame’s reply has the drafting of the past Repprts (which too long). On the eonsult me verbally A.P.A. o the various officials and others on for the Administration Report, cjome. Will you Kindly taKe over eport on the general lines of •tfere perhaps on the side of being more political matters , please Jefore drafting. 2 9 j 1 • -5 d ffx. kU~. / TUtvu' ^ ^ 4 — yv- oJ a • *1' CU^i 1^53 ^d^ctiu. v^LviT. LD.O.KoiC/412. 20th July 1935 |C|V I return with ssany thanks your copy of the Report for 1^34 on the Mission Hospitals, vhich was sent to Colonel -och on the S4th January 1^35. ihe delay in returning it has been due to your long absence froci Bahrain* 4 ^ Dr • • P • Case , M • D •, Arabian Mission, Bahrain.- 6 - from Hs 150/- to Rs 125/-. The municipal ice plant was operated as usual by this department. The wireless station of Messrs. Cables and Wireless, Ltd., has been connected to the local supply during the year. 10 Kw. is connected but the load is intermittent. . Adviser to the Government.sbbbbhhhhhhHMHI r Confidentisl . NoIC/289. Political Agency, Bahrain, the 2nd May 1935. Fromt- Captain G.a.Cole, I.A., Officiating Political Agent, Bahrain. Toi- The honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Sir, I have the honour to forward in quadruplicate the Annual Administration Report of the Bahrain Agency for the</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0000d8_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/297</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0000d8</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/297</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>File 8/8 1931-34 Bahrain Agency Administration Reports and Related Papers</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1932/1935</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-08-05T21:09:31</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (151 folios)</extent><extent>The volume is arranged chronologically.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the inside of the front cover, and terminates at the inside back cover; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is also present in parallel between ff 6-148; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled, and can be found in the same position as the main sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The volume contains correspondence relating to the collation and submission of the annual Administration Report of the Bahrain Political Agency, as well as the reports themselves.Present within the volume are the reports for the years 1931-1934. Each report contains a prose statement and sometimes statistics on all or most of the following subjects: Personnel; Ruler of Bahrain and the Al Khalifa Family; Local Government Officials; Bahrain State; Bahrain Police; Local Affairs; Oil Concession; Artesian Wells; Agriculture; Customs; Municipalities; Public Works; Education; Trade; Industry; Athletics; Boat Building and Shipping; Electric Light/Electric Department; Royal Navy; Royal Air Force; Aviation; British Interests; Post Office; Medical; Judicial; Visits of Government (British) Officials; Movement of Foreigners; Visits of Arab Notables; Nejd (from 1932, Saudi Arabia); The Qusaibis; Qatar; Slavery; Climate; General. Each subject comes under its own sub-heading. Each report is signed by the officiating Political Agent at the time of submission to the Political Resident at Bushire.Preceding each report is correspondence between the Political Agent and the institutions and offices that provided reports and statistics for the final Administration Report. These include: Charles Belgrave, Advisor to the Government of Bahrain; the Director of Customs and Port Officer; the Head Munshi; the Postmaster; and doctors and other employees of the American Mission Hospitals (men's and women's) and the Victoria Memorial Hospital.There are internal office notes following some reports, concerning their collation and submission.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Victoria Memorial Hospital, Bahrain</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>American Mission Hospital, Bahrain</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Director of Customs and Port Officer</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="personal"><namePart>Sir Knight Charles Dalrymple Belgrave</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Colonial administration</topic></subject><subject><topic>Health services</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x0000d8#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>