<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x00024e_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T11:59:36.657Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">*** -■ U U* , J,, Y^y'g Document is thr property of H is Majesty's Secretary of State for India. SECRET. 7 Germany and the Middle East. I circulate to the Tabinet a report of a lecture by Dr. Paul Rohrbach, taken Irom Llie Ilarnhnrger '^reindeiihlatt of ord December. Dr. Ilohr})tich writes on the Middle East with authority. He was one of the first Germans to interest himself in Persian affairs. A. C. -Mh December J915. 1 rRW M AXY's POSITION IN THE WORLD, BV Dr. PaUL UOHRBACII. { Lecture in the Hamburg Volksheim, printed in Hamburger Fremdenblatt, 3rd December 1915. The writer comments on the stale-mate in Europe, and points out how the situation has now been altered to the advantage of Germany by the opening of a way to the Middle East and especially to the Suez Canal, with all the dangers therein involved for England. Taking Germany's three opponents—England, Russia, and United States of America—he observes that they have unlimited space for the expansion of their population, whereas Germany has none. Moreover, these three empires are economically self- sufficient, which Germany can never be. u If the war is to bring in nothing ' to Germany, if the course of the world is to be resumed in 1916 at the 44 point at which it left off in 191 I, it is easy to foresee Germany's future : ' she will grow slowly, while her enemies grow rapidly, and she will become ' more and more dependent upon them.'' She must, therefore, make herself self-sufficient in respect of the supply of raw material. ' This cannot ' be attained by annexation. The large and thinly populated regions of ' Livland and Courland might serve for a time, but not permanently. The ' possibility of a future for Germany lies in the East, in Asia Minor, Syria, ' Mesopotamia, Palestine. These regions must be opened by railways and ' capital, and this can only be done for Turkey by German help. In the ' neighbourhood of Nineveh, traversed by the Bagdad Railway, lies one of ' the greatest oil-tields in the world ; in the bosom of the Taurus are mighty ' deposits of copper and other metals. The plains of Babylon can be made ' one of the greatest cotton- and wheat-producing regions in the world, and ' in Mesopotamia millions of sheep can pasture. There we have most of ' the raw materials side by side. Let us suppose that the present war- 41 alliance between Germany, Austria-Hungary, Bulgaria, and Turkey, ' becomes a permanent economic combine—Germany as a great industrial 14 State, Austria-Hungary as an industrial State in the making, Bulgaria as ' an agricultural state, and Asiatic 'Turkey as the richest producer of raw ' material in the world. We cannot copy the gigantic form of our rivals— 14 for that purpose we came too late in the partition of the world. Our ' position is difficult, and calls for intellectual, political, and national S.S. 422.' exertions to enable us to maintain it. What we have to do is to create a ' form ot political and economic industry on a grand scale, i.e., a permanent 41 political and economic alliance with our present confederates. Then we 14 should have, even in a future war, all necessary raw materials—by means ' of the Bagdad Railway- without the enemy being able to hinder us. 44 There is another thing. One of our most important objects in the war is the freedom of the seas. We might secure it if our fleet were as strong as Britain's. But that requires time, and much, much money. There is another possibility of securing the freedom of the seas againsl England, viz., if we can tind, somewhere in the world, a point from which wo can apply sensible pressure to Kngiand. 1 hal point lie.s on the Sue/ Canal. If Turkey completeb the railway to the immediate neighbourhood ot Egypt, and makes good military posts in the neighbourhood of the Canal, then we have such a point of pressure against England, and can compel her to yield at any time. With such a point on the Suez Canal, and an economic alliance with the other Central Powers, Germany, in spite of her unfavourable position in the heart of Europe, can permanently maintain herself against her more powerful rivals.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x00024e_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/18/B221</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x00024e</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/18/B221</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Germany and the Middle East'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1915/1915</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-10-10T12:13:31</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 folio</extent><extent>Foliation: The foliation commences and concludes on folio 6, as it is part of a larger physical volume. These numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional former foliation sequence is also present in the volume; these numbers are also written in pencil, are not circled, and can be found in the same position as the main sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This printed memorandum, by Joseph Austen Chamberlain, contains a report of a lecture 'Germany and the Middle East', by Dr Paul Rohrbach given at the Hamberg Volksheim which was printed in
                           Hamburger Fremdenblatt, 3 December 1915.The report discusses Rohrbach's opinions on the current situation in Europe and how Germany now had an advantage following the opening up of routes to the Middle East and the Suez Canal through the provision of railways and money to Turkey. The lecture also focused on Germany's need for raw materials, how access to the Middle East can provide them with oil, minerals, cotton and wheat, and the potential future economic benefits posed by the war-time alliance of Germany, Austria-Hungary, Bulgaria and Turkey. The lecture concludes with the suggestion that as Germany cannot compete with Britain in its Naval strength it could use the Suez Canal as a point of pressure to try to secure access to the sea and its own position in the heart of Europe.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Secretary of State for India, United Kingdom</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Hamburger Fremdenblatt, Newspaper</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="personal"><namePart>Paul Rohrbach</namePart></name></subject><subject><geographic>Germany</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Suez Canal</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Turkey</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Middle East</geographic></subject><subject><topic>First World War (1914-1918)</topic></subject><subject><topic>Trade (practice)</topic></subject><subject><topic>International relations</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x00024e#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>