<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100027268955.0x000002_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-18T16:28:25.707Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">V • * ' -&lt; Copy. Protectorates and Spheres of Influence not forming Territories of Her Britannic Majesty . i. Afghanistan and its dependencies. 2* Kalat and its dependencies, 3 . Kashm i r and i ts dependenc i es . 4. Nepal and Bhutan, 5. Native State s in India, several hundreds in number, 6. Trans-Salween Shan States, 7. Tribal territory on the North West and North East frontiers of India within the influence of the Govt, of India, but not yet incorporate into British InclicL. 8. Bahrein and the Trucial Chiefs of the Persian Gulf. 9. Arab Chief ships in the neighbourhood of Aden and on the Arabian Coast as far as Oman, 10. Somali Coast. 11. Socotra, 12. Laccadive Islands. UForeign Office to India Office. Sept ember 9th,1895 . Sir, J am directed by the Marquess of Salisbury to transmit to you, to be laid before Lord George Hamilton, the accompanying translation of a note from the German Ambassador at this Court, requesting the German Government may be supplied with a list of the British protectorates and Spheres of Influence which are excluded from the operation of the Extra dition Treaty between Great Britain and Germany of May 5th, 1894. I am to request that Lord Salisbury may be furnished with a list of the British Protectorates and Spheres of Influence under the administration of of the India Office which are not 'Territories of Her Britannic Majesty' within the meaning of the Treaty. ^ similar letter has been addressed to dn 1 nnial Office. I am, etc*, (Sd) Francis Bertie.Oopp. Sr Tv elation. Count Hatzfeldt to Marquess of Salisbury. German Embassy, London, August 24th, 1805. My Lord, The Treaty of May 5th, 1894, extending the Anglo^Germm Extradition Treaty of May 14th 1872, applies, so far as this country is concerned, only to the United Kingdom of Great Britain and Ireland, and to the Colonies and Foreign Possessions of Her Britannic Majesty, and not to the British Protectorates and Spheres of pnflnxmre. x This fact has given rise to doubts on the part of the Imperial Government as to which of the British territories, particularly in Africa and Asia, come under the provisions of the new Treaty. I should be much obliged if Your Lordship u&gt;ould. furnish me with a list of the territories which are excepted from its application. I have, etc., (Sd) Hatzfeldt.(9936.) PERSIAN COAST AND ISLANDS. RULES OF COURT. Tlie following Rules of Court made by His Britannic Majesty’s Consul-General for Fars and tlie Coasts and Islands of tire Persian Gulf, sanctioned By tire Governor- General of India in Council, and approved by the Secretary of State acting with the concurrence of the Treasury, are published for general information. Bushire, October 20, 1911. P. Z. COX, Lieutenant-Colonel, His Britannic Majesty’s Consul-General. Rules of Court under Article 49 (1) of “ The Persian Coast and Islands Order in Council, 1907.” Fees. 1. THE fees in the table hereto annexed are to be levied in respect of proceedings in, or processes issued out of, any Court established under “ The Persian Coast and Islands Order in Council, 1907,” in place of the fees prescribed by the Rule, dated the 27th July, 1908, issued under the aforesaid Order. 2. All judicial fees and fines levied by the Courts established under the Order, as well as fees for the registration of British subjects enjoined by the said Order, shall be collected by means of Indian revenue and Court-fee stamps. These stamps, which are supplied by His Majesty’s Indian Government through the Karachi Stamps Depot, shall be affixed, on receipt of the amount which they represent, to the document for which the fee is charged, or, where there is no document, to a receipt. The stamps shall be affixed close to the officer’s signature, but where this is impracticable they may be affixed on the top left-hand corner of the document. They shall be cancelled at once by punching out the figurehead so as to leave the amount designated on the stamp untouched, and also by writing the date in distinct figures on each stamp thus—10-7-08. The use of a date stamp for this purpose will not comply with the instructions. 3. The stamps shall not be disposed of to the public uncancelled. 4. Uncancelled stamps shall not be accepted by a Court officer in discharge of fees ; any stamps thus offered shall be returned to the tenderer. 5. The Court officer shall, with the exception provided in clause (6), require all fees to be paid in advance and before the stamps are cancelled. 6. In case of attendance out of Court, or of commissions, the fees need not necessarily be paid in advance, but when paid a receipt shall be given by the Court [742] Bofficer, attached to his account or separate, bearing fee stamps to the value of the sum received for such attendance or commissions. If an additional charge is made for expenses, a separate receipt, not stamped, shall be given for the sums received on that account. 7. These Rules shall come into operation on the 20th day of October, 1911, and may be cited “ The Persian Coast and Islands Rules of Court, 1911.” P. Z. COX, Lieutenant-Colonel, His Britannic Majesty's Consul-General. Sanctioned by the Governor-General in Council: a. w. mcmahon, Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department. Approved : E. GREY, His Majesty's Principal Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs. FEE TABLE (PERSIAN COAST AND ISLANDS). Service. 1. For service of summons, petition, answer, motion paper, notice, warrant, decree, order, or other document on a party, witness, juror, assessor, or other person under any branch whatever of the civil jurisdiction :— Within 1 mile (English) of Court Beyond, for every further complete mile Bs. a. 2 0 0 12 Decision of Questions without Formal Suit. 2. On summons for issue or special case 3. On issue or special case ... 4. On hearing 15 0 7 8 15 0 Summary Procedure for Administration of Property of Deceased Persons. 5. On summons ... 6. On order Summary Orders before Suit. 7. On application for order... 8. On recognizance ... ... .... 9. On order Bankruptcy and Liquidation by Arrangement or Composition. 10. On declaration by a debtor of inability to pay his debts ... ‘ ... 11. On debtor’s summons 12. On bankruptcy petition ... 13. On petition for arrangement or composition... 7 8 7 8 3 12 3 12 3 12 75 0 15 0 P- 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 0 03 D c 14. On order for adjudication 15. On meeting or adjournment of meeting Bs. a. p. ... 15 0 0 ... 15 0 0 16. On special resolution presented to the Begistrar for registration 17. On extraordinary resolution presented to the registration ... Begistrar for 18. On order of discharge 19. On notice to creditors, each 20. On preparing advertisement 21. On execution of warrant 22. On keeping possession, per diem 23. On inventory, per diem ... per cent, on the gross amount of the assets not exceeding a total fee of 3,000 rupees, per cent, on the gross amount of composition not exceeding a total fee of 3,000. ... 30 0 o 0 ... 0 3 0 3 12 0 ... 15 0 0 hr 1 8 0 5 0 0 Pi obate and Administration. 24. On application for probate or administration 25. On oath, for every executor and administrator and surety 26. On every security 27. On probate or administration 28. Where the Court appoints as administrator an officer of the Court 29. On filing account 30. On passing account 15 7 15 The like sum as was payable in England for stamp duty under section 27 of the Act 44 Viet., cap. 12, in like cases. In addition to the foregoing, 1 per cent, on the value of the estate and effects. ...700 ... 15 0 0 Ordinary Suits. On Summons or Petition. On Hearing. 31. In every suit of any kind whatever other than such as are 3 annas in the rupee, not exceed- before specified ing a total of 375 rupees, but in no case less than 2 rupees. Bs. a. p. I Bs. a. p. 15 0 0 ! 15 0 0 Note.— Where any of His Majesty’s Courts in that portion of the Coast and Islands of the Persian Gulf and Gulf of ’Oman which is within the,dominions of the Shah of Persia or any Judge or duly authorised officer thereof shall be satisfied that estate duty under “ The Finance Act, 1894” (57 and 58 Viet., cap. 30), or under “The Finance Act, 1896,” or any Acts amending the same, has been paid in the United Kingdom in respect of property situate at any place within the jurisdiction of such Court passing on the death of the deceased person, represen tation of whose estate and effects shall have been granted out of such Court, it shall be lawful for such Court to repay to the legal personal representative or representatives the amount paid by him or them to such Court in respect of that property on obtaining probate or administration under section 27 of this table. 32. Where judicial relief or assistance is sought, but not the recovery of money 33. On every summons, motion, application or demand, taken out, made, or filed (not particularly charged)... 34. On every rule ... 35. On every decree or order (not particularly charged) ... 36. On motion for new trial after trial with a jury ... [742 i 3 12 7 8 2 0 15 0 B 2 0 0 0 04 37. On order for adjournment of hearing rendered necessary by default of either party (to be paid by that party) 38. On every warrant of execution against goods— For less than 750 rupees For 750 rupees or upwards ... 39. For keeping possession, per diem ... Ks. a. p. 5 10 0 3 15 7 12 0 8 Appeal to Supreme Consular Court. 40. On motion for leave to appeal 41. On every security 42. On order for leave to appeal 7 8 0 7 8 0 15 0 0 43. On appeal against adjudication of bankruptcy 44. On appeal against allowance, suspension, or refusal of order of discharge in bankruptcy 45. On appeal where judicial relief or assistance is sought but not the recovery of money 46. On any appeal other than such as are before specified \ On Petition or Motion. On Hearing. Es. a. P- Es. a. P 75 0 0 30 0 0 75 0 0 30 0 0 30 0 0 30 0 0 per cent, on amount involved, not exceeding a total fee of 375 rupees. Appeal to His Majesty’s Council. 47. On motion for leave to appeal 48. On every security 49. On order for leave to appeal 50. On record of appeal (including expense of transmission) Miscellaneous. ... 30 0 0 ... 30 0 0 ... 75 0 0 Such sum as the Court directs. 51. On taxation of any hill of costs, for every ten folios, from each party to the taxation 3 12 0 52. On every deposition taken before trial ... ... ... ... ... 7 8 0 53. On balance of estates of deceased persons paid into Court otherwise than in a suit | 54. On deposit or registration of bill of sale, will, deed of partnership, or other document 55. On notice of bill of sale filed 56. For taking inventory, per diem 57. For protest of a bill of exchange and copy ... 58. For noting a bill of exchange 59. For copy of such notation 60. For taking an affidavit ... 61. For every exhibit 62. For drawing a will:— If not exceeding 200 word§ . If exceeding that number, for every subsequent 100 words or fraction thereof 63. For filing any document whatever 64. For certifying signature or seal 65. For attendance at a sale :— At request of parties interested or of local authorities, if absent less than two hours At request of parties interested, for each additional hour or fraction thereof, Eupees 7:8:0, with a maximum per day of 24 per cent, on amount. 15 0 0 15 0 0 15 9 0 15 0 0 3 12 0 2 0 0 3 12 0 2 0 0 15 0 0 3 12 0 3 12 0 3 12 0 30 0 0 0 6066. On reference to the archives 67. For certified copy of document in the archives:— For first 100 words For every further 100 words 68. For preparing contracts between travellers and persons in their employment or other persons 69. For certified copy of such documents:— For first 100 words For every further 100 words 70. For an official certified translation of any document:— For first 100 words For every further 100 words 71. For communication between two Consular Courts 72. For communication in writing to a foreign Consulate or to local authority 73. For attendance of Consular officer at local office or tribunal:— Where amount involved is— Ks. a. p. 2 0 0 2 0 0 0 12 0 7 8 0 2 0 0 0 12 0 7 8 0 3 12 0 7 8 0 7 8 0 Under 3,750 rupees 3,750 rupees, and under 7,500 rupees 7,500 rupees, and under 15,000 rupees 15,000 rupees and upwards 74. For attendance of interpreter at Consular Court, if required by a party in a suit ...780 ... 15 0 0 ... 30 0 0 | per cent, on amount involved, not exceeding a total fee of 750 rupees. Such sum as the Court directs, not exceeding 45 rupees per diem. Criminal Matters. 75. On every summons or warrant, unless specially directed by the Court to be issued 76. On hearing in summary case 77. On warrant of commitment 78. On recognizance 79. For service of notice on each juror or assessor 80. On trial with a jury 81. On record of sentence on a trial with a jury 2 0 0 2 0 0 1 0 0 0 12 0 2 0 0 7 8 0 7 8 0FO* IcjXt /f % c : o Simla * .. The/November 1911. .'• 2^. h*. J A y /Iw // 7. jTj. ^ / * /, -0 ry dear Hirtzel, Please refer to the despatch from His Majesty’s Secretary of State for India Ho. 73 Political, dated the 75th August 1911, regarding the issue of revised Rules of Court with Table of fees, under the Persian . Coast and Islands Order in Council, 1907. Three copies of the Rules were sent to the Political Resident in the Persian Oulf in accordance with the instructions contained in the above mentioned despatch. Colonel Cox has now reported that he has submitted, duly completed, one copy of the Rules to the London Foreign Office. Will you kindly arrange—arrange for the supply of 20 copies of the final issue of the Buies in question for the use of the Foreign Department. To Sir F. A. Hirtzel, K. G. B # , Secretary, Political Department, India Office, London.India Office, London, 25th August 1911. Political, No. 73. To His Excellency the Right Honourable the Governor General of India in Council. My Lord, With reference to the letter of Persian Gulf. Revised Rides of Court under Persian Coast and Islands, Order in Council, 1907. Coast and Islands Order in Council, / ^Letter of India Office to Foreign Office, dated 24tli April 1911. Letter of Foreign Office to India Office, dated 31st May 1911. Letter of India Office to Foreign Office, dated 21st June 1911. Letter of Foreign Office to India Office, dated 31st July 1911 (with three enclosnree in original.) your Excellency’s Government in the Foreign Department, No. 31, dated the 30th March 1911, enclosing a draft of Revised Rules of Court, with Table of Fees, under the Persian 1907, I transmit copy of correspon dence'^' with the Foreign Office on the subject, and request that action may be taken as desired in para graph 2 of the Foreign Office letter of the 31st July 1911, should Your Excellency see no objection to the steps proposed. I have the honour to be, My Lord, Your Lordship’s most obedient humble Servant, (Signed) Crewe. 11548. I. 1691.11548. A 2 ENCLOSURES. Enclosure No. 1. India Office to Foreign Office. India Office, Sir, 24tli April 1911. With reference to the letter of this Office, dated the 9th September 1910, as to the revision of the Rule of Court submitted by His Majesty’s Consul-General at Bushire for the sanction of the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs under Section 49 (1) of the Persian Coast and Islands Order in Council 1907, I am directed to enclose copy of a letter from the Government of India on the subject. The Secretary of State for India would be glad to receive the observations of Sir E. Grey as to the reply to be returned. I have, &amp;c., The Under Secretary of State, R. Ritchie. Foreign Office. Enclosure No. 2. Foreign Office to India Office. No. 15,418. Foreign Office, Sir, 31st May 1911. I am directed by Secretary Sir E. Grey to acknowledge the receipt of your letter of the 24th ultimo respecting the Revised Rule of Court to cover the table of fees proposed under the “ Persian Coast and Islands Order in Council, 1907.” I am to state that Sir E. Grey proposes, with the concurrence of Viscount Morley of Blackburn, to approve the issue of the rules of Court enclosed in your letter under reply. I am, &amp;c., The Under Secretary of State W. Langley. for India. Sir, Enclosure No. 3. India Office to Foreign Office. India Office, 21st June 1911. In reply to your letter No. 15,418, dated the 31st May 1911, I am directed to say that the Secretary of State for India in Council concurs in the proposal of the Secretary of State for F oreign Affairs to approve the issue of the revised Rule of .Court, enclosed in my lettei of the 24th April last, with table of fees under the Persian Coast and Islands Oidei in Council, 1907. I am, &amp;c., The Under Secretary of State, E. Ritchie. Foreign Office.Enclosure No. 4. Foreign Office to India Office. Sir No. 24,539. Foreign Office, 31st July 1911. With reference to your letter of the 21st idtimo approving the proposal to issue certain revised Rules of Court under the Persian Coast and Islands Order in Council, 1907, I am directed by Secretary Sir E. Grey to transmit to you herewith, to be laid before the Secretary of State for India in Council, three white copies of the Rules in question, which have been signed by Sir E. Grey. I am to request that the Earl of Crewe will take the necessary steps to obtain the signature of the Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department in the place indicated for that purpose on page 2, and that His Lordship will request the Government of India, when that has been done, to forward the three white copies direct to His Majesty’s Consul-General at Bushire, to whom the necessary instructions as to signing them and inserting the date will be sent by this Department. The Under Secretary of State for India. I am, &amp;c., W. Langley.&amp; m In any further communication on this subject, please quote No. 24539/11. and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. Sir:- (wi A Foreign Office July 31st, 1911. aP &gt; With reference to your letter of the 21st ultimo approving the proposal to issue certain revised Rules of Court under the Persian Coast and Islands Order in Council, 1907, I am directed by Secretary Sir E. Grey to transmit to you, herewith, to be laid before the Secretary of State g for India in Council, three white copies of the Rules in question, which have been signed by Sir E. Grey. I am to request that the Earl of Crewe will take the necessary steps to obtain the signature of the Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department in the place indicated for that purpose on page 2, and that His Lordship will request the Government of India, when that has been done, to forward the three white copies direct to His Majesty’s Consul General at Bushire, to whom the necessary instructions as to signing them and inserting the The Under Secretary of State, India Offic(24539/11) the date will De sen “ by this Department. I am, Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant,Iii any further communication on this subject, please quote no. 15418/11. and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, Sir:- May 31 1911. ' M I am directed by Secretary Sir E. Grey to acknowledge the receipt of your letter of the 24th ultimo respecting the Revised Rule of Court to cover the Table of fees pro posed under the “Persian Coast and Islands Order in Council, 1907% I am to state that Sir E. Grey proposes, with the concurrence of Viscount Morley of Blackburn, to approve the issue of the rules of Court enclosed in your letter under reply. I am, O ■? y» ull ,i Ingi+P Sir: - With reference to the letter of this Office dated the 9th September, 1910, as to the revision of the Rule of Court submitted by His Majesty’s Consul-Geheral at Bushire for the sanction of the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs under section 49 (l) of the Persian Coast and Islands Order in Council 1907, I am directed to enclose copy of a letter from the Government of India on the subject. The Secretary of State for India would be glad to receive the observations of Sir E. Grey as to the reply to be returned. I have &amp;c., (Signed) R. Ritchie. | e Under Secretary of State, foreign Office. '-9 ^ \ o. p n.: a. &gt; -1911. I f-&lt;7 j O POET WILLIAM. FOREIGN DEPARTMENT. GENERAL. NO. 31, DATED THE 30TH MARCH 1911. (Copy.) Revised Rule of Court to cover the Table of Pees proposed under the “ Persian Coast and Islands Order in Council, 1907.” S. G. P. I.—3966 F. D.—25-3-1913.-14.No. 31 of 1911. GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. FOREIGN DEPARTMENT. general. To The Eight Hon’ble VISCOUNT MOELEY of ELACKBUEN, O.M., Eis Majesty’s Secretary of State for India. My Lord, Port William, the 30th March 1911. ^ efer f^ ce to Y our Lordship’s Political despatch No. 91 dated the 9th September 1910, we have the honour to forward, for the consideration of His Majesty s Government a copy of a letter No. 3300, dated the 17th December 1910, from our Political Resident in the Persian Gulf requesting to be enlightened as to the precise nature of the revision advocated by His Majesty s Principal Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs in the Rule of Court wiih Table of Fees, submitted for his sanction by His Majesty’s Consul-General at Bushire under Section 49(1) of the “Persian Coast and Islands Order Council, 1907. m 2. The Law Officers to the Goyernment of India are in doubt as to the precise meaning that can be given to the instructions contained in Your Lordship’s despatch. If objection has been raised to the inclusion in the Eule of Court, paragraphs (1) to (5) submitted by His Majesty’s Consul-General, Bushire, of details regulating the manner, etc., in which fees are to he levied’ then it would seem that the rule cannot be revised as suggested by His Majesty’s Principal Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, because the details as given would appear to be necessary by the decision to credit the fees collected to the Indian Exchequer. We submit a draft of the revised Eule of Court in accordance with the instructions as at present understood, and request that more precise instructions as to the revision and adaption desired may kindly be furnished by Your Lordship if the draft should not be suitable. We have the honour to he, My Lord, Your Lordship’s most obedient, humble servants, (Signed) HAEDINGE of PENSHUEST. „ O’M. CEEAGH. „ GUY FLEETWOOD WILSON. „ J. L. JENKINS. „ li. W. CAELYLK „ S. H. BUTLEE. „ S. A. IMAM. „ W. H CLAEK.Enclosure 1. No. 3300 ; dated Bushire, the 17th December 1910. From— Lieutenant-Colonel P. Z. Cox, C.S.I., C.I.E., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, To—The Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department. I have the honour to refer to the correspondence enclosed with Eoreign Department letter No. 2189* G., dated 26th October, in which I am desired to submit a revised Eule of Court to cover the Table of Eees proposed under the Persian Coast and Islands Order in Council, 1907. 2. It seems to me possible that there may be some misunderstanding. In any case an examination of the papers leaves me in doubt as to precisely the direction in which revision is required. I therefore venture to ask the Govern ment of India if they can enlighten me on this point. 3. I am desired, in revising the Pule of Court, to adapt it to the Persia Judicial Eees Order in Council, 1898; hut that Order is an Amendment to the Persia Order in Council, 1889, which is not applicable to the Persian Coast and Islands, where the Order of 1907 applies. I do not see therefore how the present Pule can he adapted to the former Amendment Order. 4. Again the text of the Pule as submitted by me was based as far as the preamble is concerned on the wording of the Rule of 28th December D99, sanctioned in Eoreign Department letter No. 152-E.A, dated 17th January 1900, and approved by the Secretary of State for Eoreign Affairs in Eoreign Office Despatch No. 3, dated 9th April 1900. The details as to the manner of levy given in paragraphs (1), (2), (3), (4) and (5) after the preamble were rendered necessary by the decision to credit the fees collected to the Indian Exchequer and have no parallel under the Persia Order in Council to which they could he adapted. Trusting that I am not troubling Government with this reference need lessly. Enclosure 2. (Draft.) PEPSIAN COAST AND ISLANDS. RULES OF COURT. The following Pules of Court, made by His Britannic Majesty’s Consul- General for Ears and the Coasts and Islands of the Persian Gulf, sanctioned by the Governor-General of India in Council, and approved by the Secretary of State acting with the concurrence of the Treasury, are published for general information. Bushiee ; The 1911. Sis Britannic Majesty’'s Consul- General. Rules of Couet undee Aeticle 49 (1) of “ the Peesian Coast and Islands Oedee in Council, 1907.^ Fees. 1. The fees in the table hereto annexed are to he levied in respect of proceedings in, or processes issued out of, any Court established under “ The 30r56 F. D.Persian Coast and Islands Order in Council, 1907 ” in place of the fees prescribed by the Pule, dated the 27th July 1908, issued under the aforesaid Older. 2 All iudicial fees and fines levied by the Courts established under the Order as well as fees for the registration of British subjects enjoined by the Paid Order shall be collected by means of Indian Revenue and Court-fee stamps. These stamps, which are supplied by His Majesty’s Indian Government through the Karachi Stamps Depit, shall be affixed on receipt of the amount which they represent, to the document for which the fee is charged, or where there • s no document, to a receipt. The stamps shall be affixed close to the officer s sienature but where this is impracticable they may be affixed on the top left- E comer of the document. They shall be cancelled at once by punching out the figurehead so as to leave the amount designated on the stamp untouched and also by writing the date in distinct figures on each stamp, thus 10-7-08. The use of a date stamp for this purpose will not comply with the instructions. 3. The stamps shall not be disposed of to the public uncancelled. 4. Uncancelled stamps shall not be accepted by a Court officer m discharge of fees ; any stamps thus offered shall be returned to the tenderer. 5. The Court officer shall, with the exception provided in clause (6), require all fees to be paid in advance and before the stamps are cancelled. 6 In case of attendance out of Court, or of commissions, the fees need not necessarily be paid in advance, but when paid a receipt shall be given by the Court officer, attached to his account or separate, hearing fee stamps to the value of the sum received for such attendance or commissions. It an additional charge is made for expenses, a separate receipt, not stamped, shall be given tor the sums received on that account. 7. These Hules shall come into operation on the ^ayof 1911, and mav be cited “ The Persian Coast and Islands Buies of Court, 1911. His Britannic Majesty's Consul- General. Sanctioned by the Governor-General in Council. Approved. Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign Department. His Majesty's Frincipal Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs. Pee Table (Persian Coast and Islands). Service. 1. Por service of summons, petition, answer, motion paper, notice, warrant, decree, order or other document on a party, witness, juror, assessor,^ or other person under any branch whatever of the civil jurisdiction Bs. a. P- Within one mile (English) of Court ..... 2 0 0 Beyond, for every further complete mile .... 0 12 0 Decision of Questions without formal Suit. Rs. a. p- 2. On summons for issue or special case .... 15 0 0 3. On issue or special case ...... 7 8 0 4. On hearing ........ 15 0 03 Summary Procedure for Administration of Property of Deceased Persons. 5. On summons 6. On order . Rs. a. p. 15 0 0 15 0 0 Summary Orders before Suit. 7. On application for order .... 8. On recognizance ..... 9. On order ...... Rs. a. p. 7 8 0 7 8 0 3 12 0 Bankruptcy and Liquidation by Arrangement or Composition. 10. On declaration by a debtor of inability to pay bis debts 11. On debtor's summons ..... 12. On bankruptcy petition ..... 13. On petition for arrangement or composition 14. On order for adjudication ..... 15. On meeting or adjournment of meeting 16. On special resolution presented to the Registrar for registration. Rs. a. P- 3 12 0 3 12 0 75 0 0 15 0 0 15 0 0 15 0 0 cent, on the gross amount of the assets not exceeding a total fee of Rs. 3,000. 17. On extraordinary resolution presented to the Regis trar for registration. 5 per cent, on the gross amount of composition not exceeding a total fee of Rs. 3,000. 18. On order of discharge 19. On notice to creditors, each 20. On preparing advertisement 21. On execution of warrant 22. On keeping possession, per diem 23. On inventory, per diem Rs. a. p. 30 0 0 0 3 0 3 12 0 15 0 0 7 8 0 5 0 0 Probate and Administration. 24. On application for probate or administration . 25. On oath, for every executor and administrator and surety. 26. On every security 27. On probate or administration . . . • Rs. a. p. 15 0 0 7 8 0 15 0 0 The like sum as was pay able in England for stamp duty under sec tion 27 of the Act 44 Viet., Cap. 12, in like cases. 28. Where the Court appoints as administrator an officer of the Court. In addition to the fore going, 1 per cent, on the value of the estate and effects. 29. On filing account 30. On passing account Rs. a. p. 7 0 0 15 0 04 Ordinary suits. 31, J n evory suit of any kind wliatcvGr otliGr than sucli as are before specified. 32 . Where judicial relief or assistance is sought^ but not the recovery of money. On summons or petition. On hearing. 3 annas in 3 annas in the rupee not exceed- the rupee not exceed- ing a total of Rs. 375 ing a total of Rs. 375 but in no but in no case less case less than Rs. 2. than Rs. 2. Rs. a. p. Rs. a. p. 15 0 0 15 0 0 Note. Where any of His Majesty’s Courts in that portion of the Coast and Islands of the Persian Gulf and Gulf of ’Oman which is within the dominions of the Shah of Persia or any Judge or duly authorised officer thereof shall be satisfied that estate duty under the “ Finance Act, 1894 ” (57 and 58 Viet., Cap. 30), or under the « Finance Act, 1896,” or any Acts amending the same, has been paid in the United Kingdom in respect of property situate at any place within the jurisdiction of such Court passing on the death of the deceased person, representation of whose estate and effects shall have been granted out of such Court, it shall be lawful for such Court to repay to the legal personal representative or representatives the amount paid by him or them to such Court in respect of that property on obtaining probate or administration under section 27 of this table. Rs. a. p. 33. On every summons, motion, application or demand, 3 12 0 taken' out, made, or filed (not particularly charged). 34. On every rule ....... 35. On every decree or order (not particularly charged) . 36. On motion for new trial after trial with a jury 37. On order for adjournment of hearing rendered neces sary by default of either party (to be paid by that party.) 38. On every warrant of execution against goods — For less than Rs. 750 . . , . , For Rs. 750 or upwards . . . . 39. For keeping possession, per diem . . 7 8 0 2 0 0 15 0 0 5 10 0 3 12 0 15 0 0 7 8 0 Appeal to Supreme Consular Court. i Rs. a. p. 40. On motion for leave to appeal 41. On every security 42. On order for leave to appeal 7 8 0 15 0 43. On appeal against adjudication of bankruptcy 44. On appeal against allowance, suspension or refusal of order of discharge in bankruptcy^ 45. On appeal where judicial relief or assistance is sought but not the recovery of money. 46. On any appeal other than such as are before specified. On petition or motion. On hearing. Rs. a. p. Rs. a. p. 75 0 0 75 0 0 30 0 0 30 0 0 30 0 0 30 0 0 ^ per cent, on amount in volved not exceeding a total fee of Rs. 375. i per cent, on amount in volved not exceeding a total fee of Rs. 375.5 47. 48. 49. 50 . 51. 52. 53. 54. 55. 56. 57. 58. 59. 60. 61. 62. 63. 64. 65. 66 . 67. 68 . 69. 70. 71. 72. Appeal to His Majesty’s Council. On motion for leave to appeal .... On every security ...... On order for leave to appeal .... On record of appeal (including expense of transmis sion.) Rs. a. p. 30 0 0 . 30 0 0 75 0 0 Such sum as the Court directs. Miscellaneous. On taxation of any hill of costs, for every ten folios, from each party to the taxation. On every deposition taken before trial.... On balance of estates of deceased persons paid into Court *) otherwise than in a suit . . . . . j' On deposit or registration of bill of sale, will, deed of partnership, or other document .... On notice of bill of sale filed ..... For taking inventory, per diem . . r . For protest of a bill of exchange and copy . For noting a bill of exchange . . . , . For copy of such notation ..... For taking an affidavit ...... For every exhibit . . ..... For drawing a will:— If not exceeding 200 words ..... If exceeding that number, for every subsequent 100 words or fraction thereof ..... For filing any document whatever .... For certifying signature or seal , . . For attendance at a sale :— At request of parties interested or of local authorities, if absent less than two hours .... At request of parties interested, for each additional hour or fraction thereof Rs. 7-8 with a maximum per day of . . . . . . . On reference to the archives ..... For certified copy of document in the archives:— For first 100 words ...... For every further 100 words .... For preparing contracts between travellers and persons in their employment or other persons For certified copy of such documents : — For first 100 words . ..... For every further 100 words .... For an official certified translation of any document For first 100 words ...... For every further 100 words .... For communication between two Consular Courts For communication in writing to a Foreign Consulate nr to local authority Rs. a. p. 3 12 0 7 n 15 15 15 15 3 2 3 2 8 0 per cent, on amount. 0 0 0 0 12 0 12 0 15 0 0 3 12 0 3 12 0 3 12 0 30 0 0 60 0 0 2 0 0 2 0 0 0 12 0 7 8 0 2 0 0 0 12 0 7 8 0 3 12 0 7 8 0 7 8 01910 ^st)b u-v* t K’ c l FOREIGN OFFICE, Q (18559/10) Sir I am directed by Secretary Sir E. Grey to ac knowledge the receipt of your letter of the 24th ul timo, respecting the application to the Persian Coast and Islands of the Indian Limitation Act 1908. I am to state for the information of Viscount Morley that Sir E. Grey concurs in the proposal that the Government of India shall he authorized to issue the necessary Order under Article 7 (3), Part II, of the 'Persian Coast and Islands Order in Council 1907^ applying the Act with effect from the 1st. August 1910. The Under Secretary of State, f I am Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant 10 a.m. '\XNo. 56 op 1910. f GOVERNMENT OP INDIA. FOREIGN DEPARTMENT. GENERAL. © x’O The Right Hon’ble VISCOUNT MORLEY of BLACKBURN, O.M., Mis Majesty's Secretary of State for India. My Lord, We have the honour to refer to the correspondence ending with Your Lordship’s predecessor’s Political despatch, No. 24, dated the 4th March 1904 regarding the application of the Indian Limitation Act, 1877 (XV of 1877) to the Persian Coast and Islands. This Act has been repealed by Act IX of 1908, and our Political Resident in the Persian Gulf recommends that the latter he now extended to the said territories. 2. We support the recommendation and shall be glad if Your Lordship will communicate to us the necessary order, under Article 7 (3), Part II, of “The Persian Coast and Islands Order in Council, 1907 . We suggest that the order should have effect from the 1st August 1910. Simla ; the 14th April 1 1910. We have the honour to he, My Lord, Your Lordship’s most obedient, humble servants, /SIMLA. FOREIGN department. GENEMJ.Ii. No. 56, dates the 14th Apiiil, 1910. Letter to Eis Majesty’s Secretary of State for India. ri Application o£ Act IX of 1908, repealing the ^ tatl0n Aot ' 1877 (XV of 1877), to the Persian Coast and Islands. Foreign Office Press—No. 34—1M-10 3o.His Majesty's Secretary of State for India. Foet William, the 28th January 1904. Sir, With reference to Lord George Hamilton’s despatch No. 82 (Political), No. 2810E..A., dated the 4th December 1903. dated the 18th September 1903, W6 have the honour to forward, for your inform ation, a copy of a Notification which has been issued in the Gazette of India, applying the Indian Limitation Act, 1877 (XV of 1877), to the Persian Coast and Islands. 2. It will he noticed that Lord George Hamilton authorised the applica tion of the Act with effect from the 1st October 1903. The despatch, however, did not reach us until after that date, and, as we did not consider it safe to bring such an Act into operation retrospectively, we directed that the order should have effect from the 1st January 1904. We trust our proceedings will meet with your approval. We have the honour to be, Sir, Tour most obedient, humble servants,1904. FORT WILLIAM. ^cmEiGnsr depa-Htmehstt. EXTERNAL. Enclosure of a letter to Sis Majesty’s Secretary of State for India, No. dated the 28th January 1904.GOVERNMENT OE INDIA. FO REJIG-1ST RERA.RTMElsrT. NOTIFICATION. Dated Fort William, the 4th December 1903. In exercise of the power conferred by section 7, snb-section (3) of the Persian Coast and Islands Order in Council, 1889, and with the previous consent of His Majesty’s Secretary of State for India, the Governor-General in Council is pleased to direct that the Indian Limitation Act, 1877 (XV of 1877), shall he applicable to the Persian Coast and Islands on and with effect from the 1st January 1904. L, W. DANE, Secretary to the Government of India.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100027268955.0x000002_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/10/28/2</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100027268955.0x000002</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/10/28/2</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>File 791/1904 Pt 2 'Orders-in-Council: Persian Coast and Islands; application of the Indian Limitation Act to Persian Coast and Islands; revision of rules of court with Table of Fees'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1904/1911</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-12-10T12:36:26</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 item (34 folios)</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Part 2 contains the revised Rules of Court to cover the Table of Fees proposed under the 1907 Persian Coast and Islands Order in Council (folios 119-122). It also contains correspondence between the India Office and the Foreign Office on the application of the 1908 Indian Limitation Act to the Persian Coast and Islands.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100027268955.0x000002#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>