<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000200_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T19:54:14.697Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">t NOT TO BE ISSUED REFER READER TO IOR SiEQ (iqai NOT FOR DIRECT PHOTOCOPYING COPIES MAY BE ORDERED FROM yFile No.lO/l-XIV. * OILS AND MINERALS. Bahrain Oil Concession. P.C. on J0/1-XIII. cub sequent corresDondence on 10/3-XV. From 1.9.56 to 1.5.37.V' /(!// Telegrara Code From Political, Bahrain To Hickinbotham iind Club, Karachi, Ho* 294 Dated 5th September 1936. Cardwell President of the United States Steel Company wishes to visit Bahrain Petroleun Company any objection to grant of visa. Political. -i- e 1 egr am Co de From Hickinbotham, Karachi A0 Political Sahrain * ^ated 6th September 1936. .hen and why is he corning, -liat is his Company.'V- lelegram Code From Political, Bahrain To iickiribotham, liarachi 0 .302 -Jated 7th September 1936. yf Your telegram 5th September Cardwell. As soon as he gets a visa. See products which he has sold to Bahrain Petroleum Company. ill Steel -lanufacturing Company Bnited States America Telegram rom Hi ck inbo tham, Karachi 10 Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain « r o. Bated 8th September 1933. Your telegram Bo.302. issue.CONFIDENTIAL. No. fj /ll? of 1936, \ 3 &lt;x The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to It, Eia Majesty's Secretary of State for India, London. 2. The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, Simla. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document (s). Office of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Camp, SHIRAN. Dated. 13th- August ' 1-9361 Reference to previous correspondence: Description o Name and Date. 1. Letter H o.g /374-10 /1 of 7th August 1936 from the Political Agent, Bahrain, to the Acting Adviser to th^ Bahrain Government,Bahrain. 2. Letter Ho.PA-605 of the 4th August 1936 from the Chief Local Hepresentative, The Bahra n Petroleum Company, Bahrain, to the Political Agent, Bahrain, C opy f or vard ed , w it h c om Agent, Bahrain, for inf Printed letter ITo.C/St? Subject. Bahrain Petroleum Company - Gauging and Royalty• pliments, to the Political Drraation. 'Reference his 5-10/1 of 7th August 1936. y i y«. fer By Air Mail p.z. ^cjG i! .10S6 o. j&gt; ' i A &amp; (, h ' &gt; J INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, 12 SEP Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy has been sent to by Ah Mail. - --Se^u, PdJ^Jl The Foreiga\ Secretary, (government of India. The Political Resident iA the Persian Gulf. 3681Oop'T By Air Mail. i . AO 11 !'! :L.S%6cfj 19 &lt;n INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, 12 SEP 1956 Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy has been sent to by^Mail The Foreign Secretary, GMrer^ment of India. The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. 3681P.21. 5669/36. THE MHEEIN Pii'PHOLEUk COMtAFI LTD, 11, BIHGHIN LANE, LONDON, So 0.3. 5th August, 1936. Dear Mr. Olauson, , \ In liis letter to me of the 14th July (P.4961/36) Mr. Yfalton asks if I would tell jou what the final arrangement is that is come to between the Texas Corporation and the Standard Oil Company of California concerning the share control of The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited. I am instructed that the share capital of The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited has been increased by 500 shares and that such shares have been subscribed for in cash by the Texas Corporation. The Texas Corporation is a company having limited liability registered under the laws of Delaware, United Sxates of America, The Board of The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited has been increased or is being increased to seven, namely, Mi. James A» Moffett, Yice President of the Standard Oil Company of California will be Chairman of the Board, Mr. Howard M. Herron, one of the foreign sales executives of the Texas Corporation will be President and Chief Operating Executive; the remainder of the Board, in addition to Mr. H. Aldous Aylen, will be Mr. Joseph V. Murray, foreign sales executive of the Texas Corporation, Mr. William Kunstadter, foreign sales auditor of the Texas Corporation, Mr. Max Thornburg, from the manufacturing department/♦ 2. department of the Standard Oil Company of California and Mr. Richard H. Morrison, from the producing department of the Standard Oil Company of California, The new ofxices of The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited are at 142 East 43rd Street, Few York City. A Company called California Texas Oil Company Limited has been organised in the Bahamas with a capital of $1,000,000. This capital has been subscribed for in cash by The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited. This company will have offices at the same address as the Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited. The California Texas Oil Company Limited will, I believe, own the shares of the Texas marketing Companies within the marketing area^ in other words, it will be the company that will control marketing and own the goodwill of the business and, with the goodwill of the business, trade marks and such like. You will appreciate that in saying this, the organisation of marketing is in its infancy and there may oe changes before it is settled in a definite basic form. X await instructions concerning the reply to be made to Mr. Walton's letter referred to above. Yours sincerely, S g d. H o H. BALLANTYifB . ■ j' J -Clauson Esq., India Office, Whitehall, S.W.i.By Air Mail. ; i 1 v 7, A ft. -'/v INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, II 12 SEP 1956 Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy lias been seat to by ^Mail. 3681 Persian Gulf,P.z. 5831/36. THE BAHREIN iETROLSlK COMPANY LIMITED. 11, BIRCHIN LANE, LONDON, E.G. 3. 10th August 1936• / Dear Mr.Clauson, ^ Further to my letter to you of the 5th Augtist dealing with the first part of Mr, vvalton's letter to me of the 14th July, (P.Z.4961/36^ an4 to which your acknowledgment of the 7th August, (P 4 Z.5^69/36) refers, I enclose herewith a copy of a Memorandum just received in London from San Francisco which amplifies the information contained in my said letter. Yours, &amp;c., (Sgd.) H.R. BALLANTYNE. '• Clauson Esq., :ndia Office, Whitehall, s.'J. 1. closure.(M MEMORANDUM . SAN FRANCISCO, CALIFORNIA. July SO, 1936. Note on Bahrein^ In further explanation of the acquisition 'by The Texas Corporation of one-half interest in The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited: This expansion in the structure of the Bahrein Compan, is for the purpose of enabling Standard Oil Company of California, and The Texas Corporation, to bring together the interdependent factors of crude supplies, and finished product outlets. In this manner, the crude oil production available through the Bahrein concession, and the refinery now under construction by the Bahrein Company, will become the sources of both raw and finished petroleum supplies for the markets already established by certain sales subsidiaries, viz: The Texas Company fAustralasia) Ltd. The Texas Company (China^ Ltd. The Texas Company (India) Ltd. The Texas Company (Philippine Islands) Inc. The Texas Company (Soth Africa) Ltd. formerly owned by The Texas Corporation, but now owned by the California Texas Oil Company, Limited, subsidiary of The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited. Activities of these sales subsidiaries extend from Arabia and East and South Africa eastward to India, China, Netherlands East Indies, Philippine Islands, and Australasia. Present plans of expansion of sales facilities include a marine fuel oil terminal at Colombo, Ceylon (to be built by Ceylon Petroleum Cdmpany Limited), and a similar terminal at Suez (to be constructed by a company yet to be formed). A/I&lt; 2. A refinery capable of running ajpproximately 10,000 'barrels per day of crude oil is nearing completion on Bahrein Island, and plans are already under way to increase the capacity of this refinery to 20,000 'barrels per day. It is contemplated that the completed refinery will he in operation about the middle of 1937. For the period prior to completion of the Bahrein refinery, petroleum supplies for sales requirements in this area will be furnished by The Texas Corporation and Standard Oil Company of California, from United States sources. The directors of The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited are: H. A. Aylen J.A.Moffett, Jr.) (nominated by R.H.Morrison ) (Standard Oil Company Max Thornburg ) (of California. H.M.Herron ) (nominated by J.V.Murray ) (The Texas Corporation. A.E.Thayer ) ( Administrative offices are located in the Chrysler Building, 142-E, 43d Street, New York City,1 , GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. Department. rtonf identlal« EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). I'')- [n.b.- This is an ORIGINAL message sent hy AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more expeditions than the ordinary mait and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended tb he treated 9 on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had heen telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated hy the signature of a responsible officer o f the Department.'] No. 713.3 of W. Jimmttelhi* 25rd eptomber ' '66i To XX irom - Political Besident, wmmm. To - Secretary of State for India, Loudoia. Reference xxxxxxxxx ( ^Zt/i He, eated Gorernaxent of India, Siiala, / Political Agent, Bahrain. . ? /i l!ficl.)««re to your Frluted Letter P.,;.,5321/1936 September 12th 1©36. Heoonst Itution the Behralfi Petroleum Company Limited, I see that the Bahrain Petroleum Caiapa^y's adaaiaistratlTe offices are located in the Ohrysler Building, lew York City, I preeuMe that the Oompany is still registered lis ^mda ? sd, Ci.Locn, Lieut.-Colon el, off ici« ti ngPel it leal Ident in the Persian Gulf, Atteated . / 7 - fiar Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. s. 44. {Signature) (Designation)CONFIDENTIAL , j^o. 728-S of 19 6 The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to The political Agent, Bahrain, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment j^// British Consulate-General, BUS HIRE. % [) atec j 26th September 1936, V -&gt; • m T- Reference to previous correspondence ; ; ' Residency Printed letter No,1973-3 of 23rd December 1933. Description o Name and Date. Express letter No.^. 101-N/ 36 dated the 7th September 1936 from the Government of India to the India Office. Subject. Buoying arrangements at BAHRAIN.'1 deceived under Government of India endorsement No.F. 101-11/36 dated the 9th September 1936). Copy of Express Letter Ho.F,iOl-N/36, dated Simla the 7th September 1936, from Additional Deputy Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and political Department, to the Secretary of State for India# London. Your telegram 1995 of 3rd JUly 1936, Buoying arrangenents at Bahrein* Cost of replacing Hun Cantuoy by light buoy estimated at £• 152, per annum, recurring, including attendant and g»s; and £.350, non-recurring, including purchase of buoy and moorings. Buoy to be replac d is probably Buoy Ho. 2 or No. 3 installed at cost of Company last year; vide your telegram No.3180, dated 22nd December 1933. G. of I. wil be glad to receive assurance that Company will pay recurring and non-recurring cost involved in present proposal.THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED No«PA-685 Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, September 30, 1936. His Britannic Majesty's Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir: I take pleasure in handing you herexvith ten copies of 'Abstract of Accounts for the first half of 1936, of 0il Measured Under Lease between His Excellency the Shaikh of Bahrein and the Company dated 29th December 1934, Delivered in Accordance with Article Yll thereof and Statement of Royalties Due for the first Half of 1936 n , and would request that you transmit the requisite number of copies to His Excellency Shaikh Sir Hamad bin Isa al Khalifah £.0.1.1., C.S.I. fill you kindly request the Financial Adviser to sign the three copies on which provision is made for his signature and return them to the Company. I enclose the Company's cheque No.0252 drawn on the Eastern Bank Limited, Bahrein, in favour of the Financial Adviser, in the amount of rupees Six lakhs ninety two thousand two hundred twenty two, annas ten, pies five only (Rs.692,222-10-5) being Total Net Royalties Due to His Excellency Shaikh Sir Hamad' bin Isa al Khalifah, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Ruler of Bahrein, for the period January 1, 1936 to July 1, 1936, as detailed on enclosed Abstract and statement for the first Half of 1936. Arrangements have been made for the Eastern Bank Ltd. to credit the Government Account as of today. Will you kindly request the Financial Advisor to make and forward to the Company a receipt in^uintuplicate acknowledging this payment. Yours very truly. Enclos: G. W. R. Smith Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANT LIMITED. I A*No.0/425 -10 /1. political Agency, Bahrain, the 8th October 19S6* Fro® Captain T,iilckinboth&amp;B, X.A* Officiating Political Agent, Bahrein. to The Acting Adviser to the Bahrain Governsent, B A H R A I K . Sir, I have the honour to enclose four copies of 'Abstract of accounts for the first half of 1036 of oil measured under tne Mining .Uease between His Lxcellency Shaikh Sir Hamad bin 'Isa A1 Khalifah and The Bahrain Petroleum Company limited, dated the 29th December IBM'. The Company'3 cheque Ho.0252 for ^.698,882-10-5 in settlement of the royalty for tni-e period was handed to you on the 1st October 1956 by Mr. J.i&gt;. Hov.es, Assist- nt Politic..! A.srnt, 2* It is requested th t you will kindly sign and r^ turn three copies of the 'Abstract of Accounts 11 for transmission to the Chief tioca I Reppeseata tire, and &amp; receipt In qulntuplicate acitnowiedgiag the payment. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant. Captain, Offg. Political Bahralr.By Air Mail. tf/o' 19 / J INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, 50 SEP 1956 Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy has been sent to cL^-o L &gt; fe Mail - The Foreigm^ecretary, Government of Ind ia. The PoliticalNaesidem in theN^ersian Gulf. 4963 2000 7.36GONFIDENTLIL . P.Z. 7000/36 BAHREIN OIL . Mr. Ballantyne called on Septemloer 2i4-th, and raised two points in connection with the marketing of Bahrein oil. He said that the Company were hoping to market some of their oil in the Phillipine Islands and another part in Indo-Ghina. These were 5 so far as he knew? the only territories in which difficulties might arise in regard to preferential duties. He understood from his principals in San Pranoieco that for oil products going into French or Phillipine territory it would make a difference whether the shipment was from British territory or not since there was in both cases a preferential tariff for British goods. I informed Mr. Ballantyne that for the purpose of section 21 of the Import Duties Act 1932 the Bahrein islands are regarded as 'territory under His Majesty's protection' and therefore that Bahrein products imported into this country receive the 'benefit of the preferential tariff duties applied to Empire goods. Presumably this fact would he accepted hy the Phillipine and Indo-Chinese customs authorities as entitling Bahrein Oil to British preferential tariff. Mr. Ballantyne agreed that this was probably so and that he might tackle the matter on those lines. He went on to refer in the same connection to the question how certificates of origin should be obtained for shipments of Bahrein oil which might be imported into foreign territories. His principals in San Francisco had suggested that an arrangement might be made whereby employees of the Bahrein Petroleum Company would be made Honorary Vice-consuls for e.g. Prance etc., and that in that capacity2. they should issue certificates of origin for use in the countries to which the oil was heing shipped. I informed Mr. Ballantyne that this was quite out of the question as the Sheikh of Bahrein was by treaty debarred from receiving representatives of any Governments other than His Majesty's Government. His Majesty's Government would certainly not allow any infringement of their treaty rights in this connection. 1that so far as I knew there would he no difficulty in such certificates heing issued hy the Political Agent and my impression was that this procedure was already normal in Bahrein. I promised to consult Colonel Fowls and/or Mr. Belgrade, and let Mr. Ballantyne know whether my presumption was correct, Mr. Ballantyne agreed that prima facie such an arrangement would he quite suitable. All that was wanted was definite proof of origin for the purposes of the customs authorities the importing country. M.J. GLAU30N. India Office, 28th September, 1936.INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, 7OCT 1936 Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy has been sent to by A h Mail. 1963 2000 7.36 TVir Fnrn' -n Mrrrntniiyj r&gt;f Tnrlio The Political th' Prrrinin ^nlf..T- ' ■« 3. . 7000/3 6. I HI) IA OFFICE , WHITEHALL, S.W.I. 3rd October 193 6. nn ridential . Dear Mr.Ballantyne f You raised the other day the question of the issue of certificates of origin in respect of oil shipments from Bahrein to foreign countries. You said that the idea, had been mooted of the Bahrein Company's employees being appointed honorary vice-consuls by certain foreign powers with a view to such certification. I explained (for your confidential information) that His Majesty's Government would certainly not allow any infringement of their treaty rights whereby no representative of any foreign power may be established in Bahrein, and I premised to ask Colonel Powle for his views on the solution which seemed to me to be the right one, namely, that the Political Agent should issue any certificates which might be required. I have now consulted Colonel Powle, who agrees that the Political Agent is a suitable authority for issuing certificates of origin (I understand he has already done so on occasions). .R.Ballantyne, Esq., 11, Birchin Lane, E.C.3.7 c f 2. I believe that Certificates of Origin are frequently issued by the Director of Customs, Bahrein Government, but presumably that is not quite what you require. Yours sincerely, (Sgd.) WS- J- CLAUSOM— ■ —By Air Mail. P.Z. (cOLSlJ 19^. | U | I HI f ^ fe. ^ f INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, 3-( 54. Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy has been sent to by Mail. - -^Sea^ fdXJCuLsJb . The Foreig^Secretary, Gove^iment of I ndia. The PoliticaJsResident in the X^rsian Gulf. 4963 2000 7,36l! INDIA OFFICEj WHITEHALL, S,¥f,l p.z. 6942/36. 1st October1936 My dear Seal, Ballantyne, of the Bahrein Petroleum Companyj called on me the other day with a view to discovering whether the Admiralty might be disposed to entertain favourably a suggestion that they should survey part of the Persian Gulf off the Arabian coast North of Bahrein. He brought the enclosed map to illustrate what he wanted. He referred to the fact that when he was away recently^, Hamilton, of the Standard Oil, had come to see me about this question and that 1 had sent him on to the Hydrographic Department of the Admiralty. I remember Hamilton did mention the matter and that I did suggest he should go on to the Admiralty; but I was under the impression at the time that what he was going to speak about was the navigation of the waters actually adjoining Bahrein (i.e. a matter affecting the Bahrein Petroleum Company), it appears that what he really had in mind, and what he discussed with your Hydrographic Department r ' 9 A.Seal, Esq was , Admiralty, S.W.I2. was the surveying of the waters off the Saudi Arabian coast (for the purposes of the California Arabian Company), with a view to the shipment of oil from some point such as Ras Tanurah. As you will see from the enclosed map, which I understand was given to Hamilton by the Admiralty and is based on Admiralty Charts, the California Arabian Company are considering making arrangements for shipping the oil extracted in their Hasa Concession direct by tanker from one of several points on the Coast. This is obviously likely to develop the port at Bas Tanurah, which will no doubt prove to be the most convenient shipp^ing place, and I asked Ballantyne whether it would not be more convenient for the California Arabian Company to pipe their oil to Bahrein (they are, of course, already proposing to pipe crude oil across to the Bahrein Befinery for refining), and ship it from Bahrein with the Bahrein Petroleum Company's oil. H0 said that he did not think this was feasible since, if, as he imagined, there were good deep water channels up to the Arabian coast, it would obviously be the most economical arrangement to bring tankers in there. Moreover, they had the king's obvious wishes to bear in mind. Also, it would suit the Company to be able to take their stores, plant, etc., direct to the Arabian coast without passing- through/73 3, through. Bahrein if they could. The immediate point on which Ballantyne wanted our advice was whether, if he went along to the Admiralty, they would be likely to entertain favourably a suggestion that a survey should be made of certain selected areas off the Arabian coast at the Company's expense. Ho gathered from Hamilton's report of his conversation with the Hydrographic Department that there should be no difficulty about this. Obviously v /e do not want to do anything to encourage the development of a Saudi Arabian port. On the other hand, presumably, if the Admiralty refused to do the work, the Company would be qui'ce able to get some other surveying vessel to go and do it. If the work is to be done at all perhaps it is preierable that it should be done by His Majesty's Government. Subject bo any observations which Rondel (to whom I am sending a copy of this letter) may have to offer, 1 would piopose to toll Ballantyne, if you agree, that he can go and see the Hydrographic Department and that they will give him such assistance in the matter as the surveying programme in the Gulf permits. Presumably Ibn Saud's iormal approval would have to be obtained for any surveying/2 if 4. surveying within territorial waters if such is required. Yours sincerely., ^gd.) m . j.DURRANI'S PRESS CUTTINGS St. Andrew's House, 32 to. 34 Holborn Viaduct, and 3 St. Andrew Street, Holborn Circus, E.C.I. Telepho ne; CENTRAL 3149 (Two Lines). Cutting from the m r Dated September IQS 6 Address of Journal BAHREIN OIL PRODUCTION Due to the fact that all production figures for Bahrein are the private property of the Sheik of the Island, such information is not made public regu larly. However, we understand that the output for the first six months of this year amounted to about 1,533,000 barrels, or more than the total production for 1935 (1,264,809 barrels). I*P .z. f is INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, 17 SEP 1956 Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. sent to by ^ Mail. - Sea The Foreign Secretary, government of India. The Political Resident iAthe Persian Gulf 4963 2000 7»36SCI jis made between His Excellency Shaikh Sir Hamad bin Shaikh 'Isa A1 Khalifah, K.C.I.E., C.S .I., Shaikh of Bahrain, of the one part (hereinafter called 'the Shaikh') (acting on the advice of the British Political Resi dent in the Persian Gulf) and The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited of the other part (hereinafter called 'the Company') and SUPPLEMENTAL to the Lease dated the twenty-ninth day of December one thousand nine hundred and thirty-four (hereinafter called 'the Lease') made between the same parties as are parties hereto whereby the grants and privileges respectively therein more particularly referred to were conferred upon the Com pany in consideration of the payment by the Company of the royalties and the obser vance and performance by the Company of the other obligations more particularly referred to therein, WITNESSES that pursuant to the agreement come to between the parties hereto and for the considera tions hereinafter appearing. (A) The Company shall proceed to establish as soon as practicable a refinery at Bahrain. (B) The Lease shall be modified in manner following, that is to say:— (1) The word 'the' appearing before the word 'pipe-line' in the third para graph of Article I of the Lease shall be deleted and in the place thereof there shall be inserted the word 'each', and (2) The following shall be substituted for the existing Article III of the Lease, that is to say :— 'Article III. The Company, its operations and 'everything now or hereafter belong- 'ing to or controlled by it or used by 'it or intended for its use or benefit 'shall at all times throughout the 'term of this lease be completely 'exempt from all taxes, duties, 'charges, dues, fees and other impo- 'sitions of whatever nature, origin or 'kind, excepting always (a) the 'rovalties provided for by Articles 'VII and VIII hereof, and (b) duties 'on articles for the personal require- 'ments of the employees of the2 'Company, and (c) the taxation J 'imported crude oil (or the prodnoH 'thereof) sold for consumption j! 'Bahrain, and (d) the followj 'specific existing taxes :— State Taxes :— (i) (ii) (iii) (iv) (v) Customs charges for services or facilities accorded:— (i) Hamali fees (payment to porters), (ii) Khanchiyah (rent for occu pying Customs sheds if the goods are left for more thai a certain period), (iii) Crane fees (for use of Customs cranes), (iv) Certificate and amendment fees (charged for alterations and amendments on Customs documents). Municipal Taxes:— (i) House Tax, (ii) Shop, stall and market Tax, (iii) Cart Tax, and (3) Article VII of the Lease sub paragraph (a) shall be modified by the addition after the word 'territories' bi^ within the parentheses of the following words namely:—'other than the 01 used in connection with the refining of imported oils' and (4) The figure '75,000' where ij respectively appears in Articles IV and VIII of the Lease shall be deleted aw the figure '150,000' shall be inserted!® the place thereof. (C) The Lease shall henceforth ^ read and construed as if the modifications set out in Clause (B)—(1), (2), (3) and (4) of this Deed had been made in the Lea se on the fourteenth day of November one Motor vehicle tax, Boat registration fees, on launches and sailing boats Motor driving licenses, Fish trap registrations, Stamped paper and lease forms;3 thousand nine hundred and thirty-five and as so modified the Lease is hereby ratified and confirmed. Dated this third day of June One thousand nine hundred and thirty-six and executed in three parts all having equal validity. His Excellency The Shaikh of Bahrain. (SEAL.) Before me (Signed) T. HICKINBOTH AM 3/6/36 H. B. M's. Political Agent, Bahrain. The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited. By (Signed) E. A. SKINNER. By (Signed) G. W. R. SMITH.Dated 3rd June, 1936. I r ^ ) His Excellency Shaikh Sir Hahi bin Shaikh 'Isa Al Khalifah k.c.i.e., c.s.l, Shaikh of Bahrain — and — The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited. [Copy] Dccb of i^xibtflcatlon o! Ifi dated 29th December, 1934. electric law press ltd., deed a general law pRiN TeF! l on^ '7 INDIA OFFICE, Mio ■3,£ © 3679a Political Department. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). (N.B.—This is an original message, sent by air mail to save telegraphic expense, but intended to be treated on receipt with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. It has been drafted as if it were so despatched.) From Secretary of State for India, Political Resident, Persian Gulf; Repeated to: Government of India, Foreign &amp; Political Dept.j Dated 14th Oct. 1936. Political Agent, Bahrein. No. P. Z. 7111/36. \ Your Express Letter dated 23rd •, No«713-S of 1936. Reconstruction of the Bahrein Petroleum Company, Your presumption is correct. There has heen no alteration in relevant Articles of the Lease of 29th December 1934• The issue of the above has been daly authorise^ (Sg4) M. J. CLAUSON fBy Air Mail. Rz Wavs' - if vS\ v /y V T 1 INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, 17 OCT 1936 Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy lias been seat to by A h Mail. 1 i The Foreign Secretary, Govei\pment of In dia. The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. 4963 2000 7-36INDIA OFFICE, | S. 7275/36. TOTEHALL , S.W .I. 13tli Octo'ber, 19 Dear Mr. Ballantyne, I v/rite to thank you for your letter of the 9th Octo'ber about the employment of British subjects by the Company, and to say that I am submitting it for consideration. Yours sincerely, (Sgd.) M. J, GLAUSOM • R. Ballantyne, Esq., Bahrein Petroleum Company, 11, Birchin Lane,' E. C.3.ul .7275/36. THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED, 11, Birchin Lane, London, E.C.3* 9th OctolDer, /f r ^i Dear Mr. Clauson, I refer to your letter to me p. 2. 5382/36 of August Hi-th concerning the employment of British Subjects at Bahrein. The Company understands that the criticisms in such letter are hased upon its Roster of Employees as of the 1st April 1936 and that such criticisms have reference only to the 'permanent' staff of Class I employees. The figures you quote in paragraph 2 of your letter include drillers, there 'being 29 of these men among the UY Americans you refer to. The number of drillers employed by the Bahrein Petroleum Company must from time to time depend upon the current drilling programme in Bahrein. This programme has throughout the short period of the Company's development been very heavy, and recently it has been very much extended to deal with the anticipated demands of the refinery that is being constructed on Bahrein Island. It is for this reason that a number of additional drillers were sent to Bahrein this year. It is not anticipated that this strenuous drilling programme will be conuinue-a much longer. Upon its cessation most of the 29 -x iliers will leave Bahrein - perhaps only 3 or U will remain ■tor normal operations. Furthermore, there are 6 British men who have been employed as apprentiees to he trained as Refinery Operators. they were sent out during the period nf „ 0 period ox construction 01 a&lt;3 - di tional experience, their nanpo - 1 aailles appear under that heading/heading (see page 6 of the Roster). These men are 'permanent' employees. From the foregoing there emerge two facts, the first heing that the drillers cannot 'be regarded as members of the 'permanent' staff of the Company excepting, perhaps, those engaged in the normal progress of drilling after the extraordinary drilling programme has been completed. The second fact is the number of employees shewn as 'permanent staff' on the 1st April 1936 cannot be regarded as being aiore than 22 American Subjects v/hereas the British personnel numbered 31? comprising 25 shewn on page and the last 6 men shewn on page 6 of the Roster of 1st April 1936. It might be added that when the present drilling programme is completed it will probably be found unnecessary to retain the services in Bahrein of the Drilling Superinoenaent. The number of Drilling Foremen will probably then be reduced to one. I? or your information the Company would say that satisfactory British drillers are very difficult to find; in cjiy e v en w, the demands made upon the Company to develop the oil resources of Bahrein and to refine oil there have luade it impossible for the Company to risk the drilling P-ogiamme going wrong so Standard Oil Company men with considerable drilling experience have been selected in practically all cases. flight I now refer you to the Roster as of 1st July 1936? F-Ou Uiio Report it appears that the Class I 'permanent -tcui includes 51 British as against 28 Americans (excluding Oj.the 25 drillers who will probably be leaving Bahrein the present extraordinary drilling programme has been ^pleted), moreover, of this group of Americans four are skilled/3. skilled Refinery Operators who are expected to leave Bahrein at the end of 1Sj7 ea-iter tney have trained a sufficient number of British employees for the posts. The Company hopes that the foregoing information Y . 7 ill dispel the uneasiness you refer to in your letter under reply and Yfnich has no doubt arisen through a misunderstanding of the real facts of the case. .Despite its almost continuous heavy programme of work since trie commencement of its operations in Bahrein, the Company has consistently endeavoured, to increase the ratio of British to American permanent employees and as much care as possible has been taken to provide in the present refinery construction programme for the employment of permanent British employees. Yours sincerely, (Sd) H.R. BALLARTYHE. M.J. Clausen, Esq., -j- ndia Office, Whitehall, S.W.I.By Air Mail. P.z. y^, 195^. V U INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, /V 7 . Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy has been sent to by AH Mail. - ^ Se^ V ^ I I The Foreign Secretary, Government o f India. The Political Resident in tl^e Persian Gulf. 4963 2000 7.36CONFIDENTIAL. No. 760-S of 1936, U 1 '^TAjfO The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Political Agent, Bahrain, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document (s), British Consulate-Greneral, BITS HI RE. Dated ^ .9.9^ .9 b .f .. I? 3 6 • Reference to previous correspondence: Description of Name and Date. Subject. 1. Extract from Shiraz Diary No«8 for the month of August 1936. Housing arrangements at Shiraz for employees of the Bahrain Petroleum Company, Bahrain. 2. Extract from shiraz Diary No.9 for the month of September 1936. 4;io Extract from Shiraz Diary Uo«8 for the month of August 1936# x x x X X X xxxxxxxx 2. Travellera , s X X X X X b. Several parties of Americans from the Bahrain Petroleum Company have passed through shiraz on their way to Isfahan. The Company tried to rent a garden here for a sunroer rest house but the negotiations fell through because the Governor General's family happened to be living in it and he would not let the owner sign a contract• X X X X X XX X X X XExtract from Shiraz Diary No.9 for the month of September 1936. X X X x X X x X X X x Bahrain Oil Company . Negotiations between the Company and Mr.Sarkiea of Shiraz are in train with a v iew to the renting by the Company of a garden and house in Shiraz (see paragraph 2 b. of the diary for August 1936) belonging to Mr.Sarkies for use as summer rest- house for the Company's staff. X X X X X X XXX XXXCONFIDENTIAL. No. 0/453-10/1. The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to:— lue Acting Adviser to the Bahrain Goverruaeat, B a H H A I and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document (s). 2 Ipt. -—&gt; r' ^ 1 The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf. Dated...,I'&gt;th c to I Vi r. ^ •1 ^ V.v' • Reference to previous correspondence: Name and Date. Subject. !• S Priated copies of Deed of modlfiCLtioa of Lease dated Baiirain Petroleum Company Limited, 1 photostat copy of Deed of mociificotioa or Lease- a... Led • ^tii. i/ccemb r • do ~T he B ahrein petroleum C ompany limited Bahrein Island, Persian N 0cPA-7£4 Gulf, His [Britannic Me Jest 7*0 Iblitical A :ent, Bahrein., &amp; Door Sir: , ^ l K ^ r .o ; y lott-r 'To .PiX-3-i9 of 9, 1936, PlensQ refer regarding the load resenrsd for the Refinery Layout under the rights grcnted in Articles I und II of the Mining Lsase, dated D jcerher i9 p 1934, cOToring Refinery Installation, pipe line and road rights-of-nvay, aM reservation for four drilling ells: ffe are enclosing seven copies of the corrected nap and seven copies of the corrected description of the area reserved for the Sefineryo Please note on your copy of the description and map: (1) The eighth course is described as: / V It 1020,0 feet as corrected in the copy attached it ia: N 21014* S feet (2) The twelfth course is described ast y S l^S* W 1060e0 feet / as corrected in the copy attached it is: S 1«&gt;45 # W 1060 0 feet ^ Will you kindly acknowledge receipt of these corrections. &amp; Tours very truly, o. w. R 0 a^nr. Chief Local Representative, *ncls: THE BAHREIN PETROLEn! CaiPAITy LETTZDNo•C/478- 10/lm Political Agency, Bahrain, the ISth November 1936. To The Chief Local itepresentative, Trie Bahrain Petroleum Lioited, B i. xi it £ I 1^ . Dear air, I acknowledge v.ith thanks the receipt of seven copies of the corrected Bap and seven copies of tin corrected description of the area reserved for the Refinery, which were forwarded under cover of your letter No.?/.-724 dated the 7th November 1936. ij*. r Yours faithfully. a For Politic:1 Agent, Bahrain.P.A. Reference our conversation. I was talking last night to Sheikhs Abdulle bin Hamad, DaiJ bin Hamad, and Khalifa bin Mohamed at Sakhir. They remarked on the annoyance caused by the Presence of one of the Oil Coy's oil burning flares within about 600 yards (by my estimate) of the Sheikh's Qasr. The smell was certainly troublesome. All remarked that Sheikh Mr Hamad would not say any thing about it,'even were it at the door of the Qasr.' 2* I submit that the C.L.R. mey be asked by the expenditure of a few hundred yards of Dining to remove this unnecessary annoyance to H.E. 7(11. '//- ^ L if' t r? ir V No. 900/20. of 1355 Office of the Adviser to the Government, Bahrain. Dated, Sha , baan 30, 1355 November''!^. 1936 irom 0. Dalrymple^eTgrave, Esquire, C.B.E., Adviser to the Government of Bahrain. Bahrain. To His Britannic Majesty^ Political Agent, Bahrain. Sir, k 'JA' I have th^lhonour to acknowledge receipt of your No. G/425-10/1 dated 8th October 1936, for warding an 'Abstract of accounts for the first half of 1936 of oil measured under the Mining Lease between His Excellency Shaikh Sir Hamad bin Isa A1 Khalifah, K.G.I.E., G.S.I., and the Bahrain Petroleum Gompany Limited dated the E9th December 1934' and a cheque for Rs 692,222-10-5 in settlement of the royalty account for the first half of 1936. 2. I return herewith three copies of the 'Abstract of accounts' signed by me on behalf of the Bahrain Government and also enclose a receipt in quintuplicate for the above amount. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, Adviser to the Government. End os.-8^ By A h * Mail. J. I p.z. ^ W INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, **mBSS£ agwfl^. % ,L- L^~ y*, V ; - - yamfepri ' Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy has been sent to - Ifjiljk The Foreign Secretary, Government of India. The Political K^sident in^he Persian Gulf. 4963 2000 7.36 JINDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL, S.W.I. p. 2. 7275/3 6. . ^y 19th October 1936. / W K'^ Dear Starling, f Would you kindly refer to your letter of the 25th s July, i-'.jj .21/5, and to the letter from the Bahrein Petroleum Company Ltd. dated the 9th October, of which a ^ copy was sent to you on the 14th October, Ho. P. Z. 7275/36 on the subject of the employment of British subjects by the Company at ii -ahrein. I enclose herewith copy of a letter r \ 11 * f r 0111 ' the o 11 iciating Political Agent, Bahrein, dated 28th ^ W I T ^ August, forwarding a roster c/f employees as on 1st July 1936, together with the roster itself (for return in due course). 'iH y ou kindly let us have any observations which you may wish to offer on Mr.Ballantyne' s letter. I notice that he deals in detail with the drillers but does not seen to mention the question of senior employees to which you rex erred in jour letter oi the 25th July. We ought ,perhaps, to/ marling, Esq., ^etroleum Department, Mines Department.Ir* to go back to him on this. I am sending copy of this letter to Brenan and Seal. Yours sincerely,V By Air Mail il INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, 18 W 5!&lt; 2Sl&lt;' Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy has been sent to CL^-otj by Mail. - ^ S ea. ti L 7 In U| The Foreign Secretary, Government of India. The Politicah Resident in the Persian Gulf 4963 2000 7,36p.Z. 7954/36. H. 04737/36. COKFl DiH' TIA L Admiral byj ' aii weiiall ? S.V/.i 6til November, 1936. ioy dear Glaus on In reply to your let concerning the enquiry of the Bahrein Petroleum Company whether the Admiralty might be willing to survey part of the coast of the i-ersian Gulf north of Bahrein, we should like to offer the following observations. It is certainly undesirable that an oil port should be developed in Saudi-Arabian territory at Has Tanurah; he have al?/ays hoped that any oil found in the Hasa concession would be piped to Bahrein for refining' and shipment, so that Bahrein would become the central oil port for oil found anywhere on the Arabian coast. Consequently it seems advisable to do all that we reasonably can to discourage the Company from developing Has Tanurah. On the other hand, as you point out, we do not want surveying in this part of the world to be undertaken by any other government. It is known, however, that both the UoS. Coast and Geodetic survey and the Hydrographic Ofiice are engaged on very full programmes of work, and since their nearest surveying ship is in the Philippine Islands it is unlikely that they would detail a vessel to undertake this work. The commitments for surveying of our own xlydrographic Department are such that it would be difficult to justify any departure from the programme already mapped out and approved by the Board, and although the — a. „ i^.W.l. area/area here discussed is in close proximity to one v /hich will be surveyed in the near future to meet Naval Staff requirements, there is little prospect that a ship will be available to extend the work so as to include Has Tanurah and the coast to the northward. So far as Has Tanurah is concerned, the survey of 1922 shows a least depth of 19 feet in the entrance; spring tides rise about 6 feet, and the bottom is probably sand overlying dead coral; a considerable amount of dredging would be necessary before the harbour could be made use of by heavy draught vessels, but it is difficult to stress the lack of prospect of a deep water port at this place because it has distinct possibilities. It w'ould ox course be possible for the California- Arabian Standard Oil Company to charter a suitable vessel and carry out their own surveying work, but this would be a costly undertaking though possibly not so expensive as would be the case if they had to pay for the work to be done by one of our own ships. This we estimate 9-t about ££0,000^; and we should certainly feel that we were justified in charging the Company for any work of this nature v/hich './e do ior them and which is not definitely required by the Navy. In any case, no work in this area could jDossibly be undertaken before October, 1937. I am sending a copy of this letter to Eendel at the Foreign Office. Yours sincerely, Sgd. E'.A. Seal.Biffin * dj c is :1 Ko•C/504-10/1• Political Agency, Bahrain, the S6th November 19S6. From Lieutenant-Colonel Gordon Loch, C.I.E., Political Agent, Bahrain* IO :i The Adviser to the Bahrain Govemisent, B A H R 1 I Sir, K' ^ In continuation of my letter Mo.C/SS-lO/l dsted the /• 15th January^.'936, I have the honour to forward a copy of a letter Ko«PA-7S4 dated the 7th November 1336 with a copy of the corrected map and a copy of the corrected description of the area reserved for the Refinery, 2* It is requested that the corrections nay be checked and that. If there is no objection to them, they nay be noted on your copy of the description and map. S» It is further requested that you will kindly acknowledge the receipt of these corrections. I have the honour to be. Sir, \ Your most obedient servant. Lieut-Colonel, i Political Agent, Bahrain.No•C/505- 10/1. Political Agency, Bahrain, the 26th November 19S6• To The ^hief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, B A H R A l H. ^ Dear Sir, With reference to your letter No.?A-683 dated the 50th September 1926, I beg to return three copies of the 'Abstract of accounts for the first half of 1036' duly signed by the Adviser on behalf of the Bahrain Government together with a receipt (in quintuplicate) for nett royalties i.mounting to i8,6,92,822-10-5. Yours faithfully. 4. For Political Agent, Bahr in,a ■ I 7 ) By Air Mail. ndgf NQ-X—;- / U, 2 7 MOV., r ; - x: INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, (^Z • // - 17^. Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy has been sent to by Mail. - ■Seiw ^ V The Foreign Secretary, Go\ The Political Resident in 1 I . Persian Gulf. 4963 2000 7.36 I J22£Y. (c 7428/39/17). Ho. 1333 0 (920/1/36). J \ Q / U His Majesty's Representative at Paris presents his corapliraents to the Secretary of State for Foreign Affair's and has the honour to transmit to him the under-mentioned documents. British Kmbassy, Peris. 19th October, 1936. e scrip lion of Enclosure Fame and Date Subject xtract from the 'Journal Official 0 of 16th October, 1936. Decree as to French customs treatment of certain Biincrai oils from, 'iahrain./ / V DU 1! Cuttin Dated t Addres t I 1 Mr. Nix w pany in tl Bahrein Is Bahrein Is In Bah sugary lim tion of We is &gt; roducti countered the crest o thickness o The we feet which producing the upper ] outfits are i to the top strata are i in the sug; obtained. When t string of 6, hole is thei liner set op to keep the ing into th( These v under well is little gas is the one Bahrein cru oil did con no difficulty 10,000-barre] last July. Because was not les iX * past wi ena^igh well rels of cru( has been slo will be kep probably the 1937. Last Jai with hydroc gallons to 1 and many c been treated This has he' As this : running nea island, it is the flanks o encountered is the princi 420 are being air-conditioned. Older houses ar with ceiling fans. Large rooms and high c characteristic of these homes and they are fur furniture imported from the United States am comfortable living quarters. The natives live section of the central camp. About 200 whi employed at this time in positions of respon; it is probable this number will be increased within the next year as the extent of the opera Not long ago two new 12-inch lines were la four miles from the shore to serve as loading steamers taking on cargo in the bay. Jhe serve for handling the ' black and white pro pressed by Mr. Nix, and he went on to explaii line handles the crude oil, while the white refinery products, gasoline, kerosene and sm These two new 12-inch lines are m addition to 12-inch line laid some time ago aM used ^ before the refinery was completed to nil the ling the oil away from the island. To empty the tankers of bilge water twc meter lines extend from shore to anchorage. Sm be used to handle crude or refinery produ shore if necessary, but they are laid priman bilge water which cannot be dumped ov of the fishing interest operating 'l^e bay Gulf There are many pearl fisheries off the and also in the bay in which Bahrein Island) The balance of the pipe-lme system for ha oil on the island consists of five stations wi force the oil to the storage tanks at refinery or minal. These pump stations are located a &lt; nal field storage tank batteries and the located wherever possible, at some point bel( head level to assist in delivering the g as and separators located near the storage tanks, stated goes into the fuel distributing systeir. into the tanks. JARROW TUBE WORKS. Jarrow, Novemb Sir John Jarvis, MP., ended a two-days row and Tyneside co-day. He saw the new tube works building, ' old boiler shop at Palmers' works, with his various contractors, with a view to an nnme 1. the alterations and reconditioning of the seems to be admirably adapted for its purpc 'There seems no doubt that this new in speeded up in every way and that the wor nroduction next spring. At the labour exc quired whether facilities could be given for training of prospective employees, as the woi ITS entirely different draraeter from an ously carried out in the north of England the shipbuilding work, he said, he had had a the building of several ships, and he was la posals that day before Tyne shipbuilders m something would result. Times. Work begins this week by contractors on works. The first stage of 'the work consists the large boiler shop on the site,, and found, prepared for the heavy foundry machinery v installed. It is hoped that an increasing nu will be employed in the near future. Roa to be remade, and railway tracks s'trengthem J6 /jpL&amp;eiLr^ DURRANI'S PRESS CUTTINGS St. Andrew's House, 32 to 34 Holborn Viaduct, and 3 St. Andrew Street, Holborn Circus, E.C.I. OAUDCIM IQI AWFl Telepho ne: CENTRAL 3149 (Two Lines ). 13/\O IVE j 1 iN U Cutting from the ^ SJ.f.ixT?. ie ' Oil and Gas Journal.' Dated November 1936 ^ 1 Address of Journal rr 419 I 1 Mr. Nix was petroleum engineer for the California com pany in the Yates field, West Texas, before he went to Bahrein Island about three years ago. He is to return to Bahrein Island in December. In Bahrein Island, he said, the oil is found in a soft sugary limestone very similar to the Brown lime forma tion^ of West Texas and south-eastern New Mexico which is roductive of oil. The formation in Bahrein is en countered at about 2,300 feet below the surface, and on the crest of the structure, a dome-shaped anticline. The thickness of the producing horizon is about 325 feet. DRILLING METHOD. The wells are drilled using spudders for the first 1,500 feet which is mostly limestone of Eocene age, while the producing lime formation is of Cretaceous age. When the upper portion of the hole has been completed rotary outfits are moved in and the intervening formations down to the top of the producing limestone are drilled. These strata are mostly shales and some shale breaks are found in the sugary limestone from which the production is obtained. When the top of the producing formation is reached a string of 6i-in. casing is set and firmly cemented. The hole is then drilled in with 6-in. bit and 4|-in. perforated liner set opposite the producing section. This is necessary to keep the crumbling lime and the soft shales from wash ing into the hole. These wells usually come in flowing at varying rates under well head pressures of about 475 lb. per sq. in. There is little gas with the oil and no hydrogen sulphide. This is the one marked distinction between West Texas and Bahrein crude, according to Mr. Nix, who added Bahrein oil did contain an appreciable quantity of sulphur but no difficulty had been experienced in handling it at the 10,000-barrel refinery erected on the island and completed last July. Because of the daily demand for this refinery there was not less than six wells drilling at all times during flj^v'past winter and early spring. Now that there are ena 1 igh wells completed to provide as much as 20,000 bar rels of crude daily, if needed, the drilling programme has been slowed down and only about three strings of tools will be kept busy the balance of this year and this is probably the rate at which new wells will be drilled during 1937. Last January several of the older wells were treated with hydrochloric acid and responded nicely. From 500 gallons to 1,000 gallons of acid were used per treatment and many of the more recently drilled wells have also been treated with acid when drilling has been completed. This has helped them some. As this structure is a distinct anticline with the crest running nearly north and south, or the long axis of the island, it is known that water is to be encountered down the flanks of the structure. Bottom water may also be encountered if the holes are drilled too deep. As this water is the principal energy available for driving the oil into the wells care is taken to prevent drilling into it either down flank or in the bottom of the hole. One interesting piece of equipment has been devised by the engineering department for use in testing these wells. It is an oil and gas separator mounted upon a truck and the connections provided to take gas and oil from the lease pipe line running from the well to the storage tanks. Regardless of the distance between well and tanks the wells are tested in the same manner. At some convenient point on the line leading away from the well connection is made through a section of rotary hose of relatively small diameter with the pipes mounted on the bed of the wagon. In these pipes an oil meter of the Bassler type and a Westcott type gas orifice meter is placed so all gas and oil passing through this tester may be recorded. The oil and gas separator is operated against about 75 lb. pressure and when the gas and oil from the well has been measured it is passed back into the pipe line and delivered into the stock tank. This is a system which prevents the loss of any gas or oil and still permits the wells to be tested at any time. The wells when completed are also interesting as the drilling derrick is removed and a wooden platform built over all well-head connections excepting a short section of pipe extending above the platform. The gate valve with the pressure gauge mounted on the upper end of the flow string is placed there merely to control flow to the top of this string of pipe. If opened, the pressure may be read on the gauge. If it is desired to run bottom-hole recording instru ments the valve is closed and the gauge is removed and in its place a lubricator is screwed to the top of the flow string and the valve then opened to run the instrument. All other well-head connections are below the platform because it has been found this is a very satisfactory means of sheltering them from the heat of the summer sun and from sand storms. LIVING CONDITIONS. Bahrein Island climate is extremely hot in the summer. The air is humid because of the proximity of the sea. The winters are mild but the total annual precipitation is not more than 3 inches. Water for domestic and industrial purposes is secured from large fresh-water springs and from artesian wells drilled near the coast line. Gas from the oil and gas separators serves as fuel for the homes and offices. Elec tric light is supplied from a central generating plant. The houses are built with wide covered porches extending around the four sides of the building. This serves as shade and through the centre of the house is a wide corridor, usually placed to permit the prevailing north wind to blow through the interior of the house. The buildings are built with a wooden framework with studs so arranged as to permit the placing of large thin slabs of a peculiar sort of limestone between studs. These limestone studs are about 2 inches thick and the material is so tough it can be quarried near the coast and transported without difficulty. When in place the joints are filled with a quick-set gypsum of local origin and then the whole outside of the structure is stuccoed with this same quick-set gyp plaster. The houses when completed have a very neat appearance and the more modern ones420 OIL NEWS. are being air-conditioned. Older houses are furnished with ceiling fans. Large rooms and high ceilings are characteristic of these homes and they are furnished with furniture imported from the United States and are really comfortable living quarters. The natives live in another section of the central camp. About 200 white men are employed at this time in positions of responsibility, and it is probable this number will be increased 50 per cent., within the next year as the extent of the operations justify. Not long ago two new 12-inch lines were laid out about four miles from the shore to serve as loading systems for steamers taking on cargo in the bay. These two lines serve for handling the ' black and white ' products as ex pressed by Mr. Nix, and he went on to explain ' the black line handles the crude oil, while the white line handles refinery products, gasoline, kerosene and similar fluids.' These two' new 12-inch lines are in addition to the original 12-inch line laid some time ago, and used continuously before the refinery was completed to fill the vessels hand ling the oil away from the island. To empty the tankers of bilge water two 8-inch dia meter lines extend from shore to anchorage. These lines can be used to handle crude or refinery products from the shore if necessary, but they are laid primarily to handle bilge water which cannot be dumped overboard because of the fishing interest operating in the bay and Persian Gulf. There are many pearl fisheries off the Arabian coast and also in the bay in which Bahrein Island is located. The balance of the pipe-line system for handling crude oil on the island consists of five stations with pumps to force the oil to the storage tanks at refinery or loading ter minal. These pump stations are located at the five princi pal field storage tank batteries and the batteries are located, wherever possible, at some point below the well head level to assist in delivering the gas and oil into the separators located near the storage tanks. The gas, as stated, goes into the fuel distributing system and the oil into the tanks. JARROW TUBE WORKS. Jarrow, November 19, 1936. Sir John Jarvis, M.P., ended a two-days' visit to Jar- row and Tyneside to-day. He saw the new tube works building, which is the old boiler shop at Palmers' works, with his engineer and various contractors, with a view to an immediate start with the alterations and reconditioning of the building. 'It seems to be admirably adapted for its purpose,' he said. 'There seems no doubt that this new industry will be speeded up in every way and that the works will be under production next spring.' At the labour exchange he in quired whether facilities could be given for the technical training of prospective employees, as the work to be done is of an entirely different character from anything previ ously carried out in the north of England. Referring to the shipbuilding work, he said, he had had an inquiry for the building of several ships, and he was laying the pro posals that day before Tyne shipbuilders in the hope that something would result.—'Times.' Work begins this week by contractors on the new tube works. The first stage of the work consists of repairs to the large boiler shop on the site,, and foundations will be prepared for the heavy foundry machinery which is to be installed. It is hoped that an increasing number of men will be employed in the near future. Roads will have to be remade, and railway tracks s'trengthened and relaid. MANAGING PRIVATE COMPANIES. Fourth Edition of Mr. Bome\ ^ook. This manual for the use of directors and secretaries of private companies has reached its fourth edition, whict is published to-day by Jordan and Sons, Ltd., 116, Chancery Lane, London. The book is recognised as a concise anq trustworthy guide. Mr. Stanley Borrie, the author, is ^ solicitor 1 ; and he first explains the restrictions imposed upon private companies and their counterbalancing privi leges. The incorporation of such companies is next deall with; but the most important part of the book is the ex planation of the duties of directors and officers of such companies. One feels sure that if this book were carefully perused by those concerned fewer risks would be run and the courts would be troubled a great deal less than is the case. PETTERS. Aircraft Industries Corporation, Ltd., have purchased the controlling interest in the Ordinary shares of Petters, Ltd., and five new directors have been elected to the board of that company. Sir Ernest W. Petter continues as chairman of the company, and all other directors remain with the exception of Mr. G. B. Petter, who desires to retire from business and has accordingly resigned. Petters, Ltd., manufacture oil engines and own 50 per cent, of the capital of Westland Aircraft, Ltd. The issued capital is £312,500 divided into 200,000 Preference and 112,500 Ordinary £1 shares. Aircraft Industries Corporation was formed in Octo ber, 1935, as a finance company. It was associated with the issues of capital in Craven Brothers (Manchester), Ltd., and British Marine Aircraft, Ltd., made earlier this year. ORDER To the Publisher, 193. 'OIL NEWS' 70-74, London Road, Elephant and Castle, London, -M V Please send ' Oil News ' as follows for one year:— Name Address Terms: 17s. 6d. per year inland or £1 abroad (post free). (Payable in Advance.)oil news. e furnished ceilings are nished with i are really in another te men are Ability, and 50 per cent.. :ions justify, id out about systems for e two lines ducts as ex- i ' the black line handles dlar fluids. the original continuously r essels hand- ) 8-inch dia- These lines cts from the y to handle )ard because and Persian .rabian coast s located, ndling crude th pumps to ' loading ter- 5' five princi- )atteries are dw the well- oil into the The gas, as i and the oil MANAGING PRIVATE UOMPANIES. Fourth Edition of Mr. b#rie's Book. This manual for the use of directors and secretaries of private companies has reached its fourth edition, which is published to-day by Jordan and Sons, Ltd., 116, Chancery Lane, London. The book is recognised as a concise anc trustworthy guide. Mr. Stanley Borrie, the author, is f solicitor 1 ; and he first explains the restrictions imposed upon private companies and their counterbalancing privi leges. The incorporation of such companies is next deall with; but the most important part of the book is the ex planation of the duties' of directors and officers of such companies. One feels sure that if this book were carefully perused by those concerned fewer risks would be run and the courts would be troubled a great deal less than is the case. PETTERS. Aircraft Industries Corporation, Ltd., have purchased the controlling interest in the Ordinary shares of Fetters, Ltd., and five new directors have been elected to the board of that company. Sir Ernest W. Fetter continues as chairman of the company, and all other directors remain with the exception of Mr. G. B. Fetter, who desires' to retire from business and has accordingly resigned. Fetters, Ltd., manufacture oil engines and own 50 per cent, of the capital of Westland Aircraft, Ltd. The issued capital isf £312,500 divided into 200,000 Preference and 112,500 Ordinary £1 shares. Aircraft Industries Corporation was formed in Octo ber, 1935, as 1 a finance company. It was associated with the issues of capital in Craven Brothers (Manchester), Ltd., and British Marine Aircraft, Ltd., made earlier this year. er 19, 1936. visit to Jar- which is the engineer and ate start with ailding. 'It )se,' he said, istry will be will be under hange he in- the technical 'k to be done ything previ- Referring to n inquiry for ying the pro- -he hope that the new tube of repairs to itions will be /hich is to be mber of men ds will have 3d and relaid. ORDER FORM. To the Publisher, .193.. &lt;&lt; OIL NEWS' 70-74, London Road, Elephant and Castle, London, Sf t. Please send ' Oil News ' as follows for one year:— Name Address Terms: 17s. 6d. per year inland or £1 abroad (post free). (Payable in Advance.)DURRANI St. Andrew 's and 3 St. Ar Teleph Cutting from tl Dated Novembe Address of Joui ail rtuuiuo. - — — or 18.3 per cent. The following table shows the fli in thousands of net tons, in the past 15 years::— Southward. Northward. Year. Laden. In ballast. Laden. In ball 1920 141 365 529 14 1921 109 762 813 2 1922 153 985 1,196 36 1923 137 1,131 1,256 43 1924 157 1,250 1,348 77 1925 173 1,580 1,601 68 1926 168 1,707 1,802 41 1927 183 1,763 1,919 54 1928 170 1,995 2,095 91 1929 175 2,286 2,399 78 1930 211 2,381 2,500 126 1931 198 2,263 1,955 146 1932 299 2,264 2,182 162 1933 374 2,570 2,746 165 1934 344 2,630 2,843 128 1935 414 2,024 2,378 44 NEW TRADE CURRENTS. The share of tanker tonnage in the total tra Canal rose from 6 per cent, in 1920 to 19.1 pe 1933; it then fell to 18.7 per cent, in 1934 and 14.^ in 1935. During the latter year, however, laden the southward direction showed an increase of 7 or 20.3 per cent. Russia accounted for 288,000 tons as in 1934, and Roumania for 16,000 tons only, 45,000 tons. The increase is wholly ascribe( European countries. The new trade currents developed: shipments from the West Indies accounted for 48,000 net registered tons used fo fuel oil; oil shipments from Italy to East Afric; 28,000 tons. In the northward direction tank shipping ] decreased in 1935 by 465,000 net tons, or 16.6 pei same percentage as the corresponding weight 1 the commodity. The decrease in shipments fro and from the Dutch East Indies is no doubt to Iraq competition, but also to the fact that figures were abnormally high. TRADE REGIONS. The variations according to trade regions shown in the following table (laden or in balla sands of net tons):— To or from: 1935. 1934. Abadan 3,851 4,721 Dutch East Indies 347 629 Far Eastern Asia 206 197 Suez refinery 145 77 British India 125 227 Others and 'for orders' ... 186 94 Totals 4,860 5,945 The Far-Eastern trade consisted only of shi]c Russian Black Sea ports, chiefly for Siberia and increase under the ' others' heading is ascri pally to shipments from Bahrein and to Rec Bahrein gave employment for seven tankers, 37,000 tons, as against one of 8,000 tons in 1934. The tonnage of tankers tinually increased, in post -Wc momentarily decreased as upward move was resumed _n Tn 1 Q.^n thprp w; tb November 5, 1936. PUBLISHERS' AND ( ' Oil News' is publishec Latest time for receiving mat1 Wednesday. Subscription; 17s. 6d. per y (post free). Payable in advance Editorial and Publishing O Elephant and Castle, London, S Telephone: Hop 1106 (3 line Advertisements— Rates upt address or to recognised advert our Scale of Charges. Readers who are not subscr order with their newsagent or weekly supply of 'Oil News,' to obtain it. Back numbers of 'Oil Ne each, or post free 7d. In Scotland ' Oil News' i bookstalls of Messrs. John Men; Graham and Company, and fror Company, Royal Exchange Plac( NEW ELECTRODE FOR WE CHROME S - Steels known as 4-6 per ceri / are rapidly gaining acceptance resistance to crude-oil corrosion pressures, can now be successful electrode just announced by t pany, of Cleveland, Ohio. 'Chromeweld 4-6' electrode of the valuable properties of These steels possess a resistance to ten times that of ordinary s oxidation at 1,000 deg. F., three trode contains the essential ela provides weld metal possessing strength and other qualities ess per cent, chromium steels. Sue electrode, can be soft anneale similar to those of mild carbon dered suitable for equipment v is applied during fabrication. 'Chromeweld 4-6' deposits welding procedure and fully anr followed by slow cooling in the cooled from 1200 deg., possess ap characteristics: Tensile strength sq. in.; yield point 35,000 lb. to ■ tility of 35 per cent, to 40 per ce duction in area 65 per cent, tc (Brinell) 130 to 140. If stress re physical properties of the 'Chr approximately as follows; Tens 90,000 lb. per sq. in.; yield point sq. in.; ductility of 24 per cent. 1 in 2 in.; reduction in area 60 per hardness (Brinell) 155 to 175. Applications in which the n available the simplicity and ecor(jL| W 1(£&gt; 354 DURRANrS PRESS CUTTINGS St. Andrew's House, 32 to 34 Holborn Viaduct, and 3 St. Andrew Street, Hoiborn Circus, E.C.I, Telephone: CENTRAL 3149 (Two Lines). November 5, 1936. Dated November ... Address of Journal. Cutting from the . % The tonnage of tankers .Vr. .&gt;A»., tinually increased, in post-w^ momentarily decreased as tl upward move was resumed : all records. In 1935 there wj or 18.3 per cent. The following table shows the fluctuations, in thousands of net tons, in the past 15 years:— Southward. Northward. Year. Laden. In ballast. Laden. In ballast. Total. 1920 141 365 529 14 1,049 1921 109 762 813 2 1,686 1922 153 985 1,196 36 2,370 1923 137 1,131 1,256 43 2,567 1924 157 1,250 1,348 77 2,832 1925 173 1,580 1,601 68 3,422 1926 168 1,707 1,802 41 3,718 1927 183 1,763 1,919 54 3,919 1928 170 1,995 2,095 91 4,351 1929 175 2,286 2,399 78 4,938 1930 211 2,381 2,500 126 5,218 1931 198 2,263 1,955 146 4,562 1932 299 2,264 2,182 162 4,907 1933 374 2,570 2,746 165 5,855 1934 344 2,630 2,843 128 5,945 1935 414 2,024 2,378 44 4,860 NEW TRADE CURRENTS. The share of tanker tonnage in the total traffic of the Canal rose from 6 per cent, in 1920 to 19.1 per cent, in 1933; it then fell to 18.7 per cent, in 1934 and 14.8 per cent, in 1935. During the latter year, however, laden tankers in the southward direction showed an increase of 70,000 tons, or 20.3 per cent. Russia accounted for 288,000 tons, the same as in 1934, and Roumania for 16,000 tons only, instead of 45,000 tons. The increase is wholly ascribed to non- European countries. The new trade currents were thus developed: shipments from the West Indies to Suez accounted for 48,000 net registered tons used for carrying fuel oil; oil shipments from Italy to East Africa required 28,000 tons. In the northward direction tank shipping with cargo decreased in 1935 by 465,000 net tons, or 16.6 per cent., the same percentage as the corresponding weight tonnage of the commodity. The decrease in shipments from Abadan and from the Dutch East Indies is no doubt partly due to Iraq competition, but also to the fact that the 1934 figures were abnormally high. TRADE REGIONS. The variations according to trade regions in 1935 is shown in the following table (laden or in ballast, in thou sands of net tons):— To or from: 1935. 1934. Difference. Abadan 3,851 4,721 -870 Dutch East Indies 347 629 -282 Far Eastern Asia 206 197 + 9 Suez refinery 145 77 + 68 British India 125 227 -102 Others and 'for orders' ... 186 94 + 92 NAL. WijoJ-a ■521,000 tons against 11,000 tons in 1936 Totals 4,860 5,945 -1,085 The Far-Eastern trade consisted only of shipments from Russian Black Sea ports, chiefly for Siberia and Japan. The increase under the ' others' heading is ascribed princi pally to shipments from Bahrein and to Red Sea ports. Bahrein gave employment for seven tankers, aggregating 37,000 tons, as against one of 8,000 tons in 1934. Shipments TONALITIES. • the allocation of tankers accord- nag-WHs-as lomnvs (thousands of net tons):— Fla g- 1934. 1935. Difference. British 4,373 3,758. -615 Norwegian 931 823 -108 Italian 30 70 + 40 Dutch 202 64 -138 Swedish 78 44 _ 34 French 240 42 -198 Russian 16 38 + 22 Danish 34 14 _ 20 German 33 5 _ 28 Others 8 2-6 Totals i... 5,945 4,860 -1,085 The British flag accounted for 77 per cent, of the total in 1935, an increase of 4 per cent, over 1934, despite the fact that it shared to the extent of 55.8 per cent, the total decrease of 1,085,000 net tons, and that the number of tran sits declined from 883 to 789. The British Tanker Company, Ltd., accounted for 590 transits and 2,995,000 net tons, a decrease of 92 transits and 504,000 tons. This company, during the same year had no fewer than 33 calls at Tripoli or Haifa, aggregating 177,000 tons. A similar diversion is noticed as regards the French company Association Petro- liere, which figures out it four ships and 14,000 tons, as compared with 240,000 tons in 1934. The average individual net tonnage of tankers in 1935 was 4,874, a decrease of 242 tons compared with 1934. As regards laden ships only, the comparison between net tonnage and cargo weight was as follows:— 1934. 1935. Average net tonnage (net. reg. t.) 5,131 4,935 „ „ cargo (metric tons) 9,233 8,860 The ratio: cargo to net tonnage thus remained prac tically unchanged at about 1.80. For the first eight months of 1936 it has improved to 1.82, the average cargo being 8,969 tons and the average net registered tonnage 4,939. ORIGIN OF CARGOES. According to origin, the average ratio of cargo to net tonnage varied as follows:— 1934. 1935. From. bo 0) O) tuO fH CO ■M ^ or « CC £ O al bi gj cu tuo 5H eg c oa. bo 55 ca OJ 0 si 0 Oi 0) zs 0 a» Russia 5,759 10,156 1.76 5,755 10,391 1.81 Roumania 4,130 6,869 1.66 4,038 6,885 1.71 Curagao — — — 5,951 10,620 1.78 Abadan 5,053 9,190 1.82 5,052 9,181 1.82 Dutch E. Indies 6,090 10,746 1.76 6,023 10,465 1.74 Bahrein — — — 5,408 10,134 1.87 Thus, in the outward trade, Russia is the origin corres ponding to the highest loading co-efficient, tankers with fuel oil from Curagao coming next. During the first eight months of 1936 these co-efficients improved to 1.85 for Russia, 1.87 for Curagao and 1.93 for Bahrein. The net tonnage record for 1935 is held by the Nor wegian tanker ' Thorhild ' of 8,656 tons net register. She was on her maiden trip with a large cargo of 14,526 tons oil from Batoum bound for Vladivostok.November 5, 1936. oil news. 153 PUBLISHERS' AND OTHER NOTICES. ' Oil News' is published on Thursday morning. Latest time for receiving matter for insertion, noon on Wednesday. Subscription: 17s. 6d. per year inland and £1 abroad (post free). Payable in advance. Editorial and Publishing Offices: 70-74, London Road, Elephant and Castle, London, S.E.I. Telephone: Hop 1106 (3 lines). Advertisements. —Rates upon application to above address or to recognised advertising agents, who all have our Scale of Charges. Readers who are not subscribers must place a definite order with their newsagent or railway bookstall for the weekly supply of 'Oil News,' otherwise they will fail to obtain it. Oil News' may be had at 6d. Back numbers of each, or post free 7d. In Scotland ' Oil News' may be purchased at the bookstalls of Messrs. John Menzies, and of Messrs. Robert Graham and Company, and from Messrs. W. Porteous and Company, Royal Exchange Place, Glasgow. NEW ELECTRODE FOR WELDING 4-6 PER CENT. CHROME STEELS. Steels known as 4-6 per cent, chromium steels, which are rapidly gaming acceptance in applications requiring resistance to crude-oil corrosion at high temperatures and pressures, can now be successfully welded by use of a new electrode just announced by the Lincoln Electric Com pany, of Cleveland, Ohio. 'Chromeweld 4-6' electrode permits full development of the valuable properties of the low-chromium steels. These steels possess a resistance to sulphide corrosion four to ten times that of ordinary steel and a resistance to oxidation at 1,000 deg. F., three times as great. The elec trode contains the essential element of molybdenum and provides weld metal possessing the necessary high creep strength and other qualities essential for welding the 4-6 per cent, chromium steels.. Such steels, welded with the electrode, can be soft annealed to physical properties similar to those of mild carbon steel, and, therefore, ren dered suitable for equipment where severe cold-working is applied during fabrication. 'Chromeweld 4-6' deposits, produced with proper welding procedure and fully annealed at 1550-1600 deg. F., followed by slow cooling in the annealing furnace, or air cooled from 1200 deg., possess approximately the following characteristics: Tensile strength 65,000 lb. to 70,000 lb. per sq. in.; yield point 35,000 lb. to 40,000 lb. per sq. in.; duc tility of 35 per cent, to 40 per cent, elongation in 2 in.; re duction in area 65 per cent, to 75 per cent.; hardness (Brinell) 130 to 140. If stress relieved at 1400 deg. F., the physical properties of the 'Chromeweld 4-6' deposit are approximately as follows: Tensile strength 80,000 lb. to 90,000 lb. per sq. in.; yield point 55,000 lb. to 65,000 lb. per sq. in.; ductility of 24 per cent, to 30 per cent, elongation in 2 in.; reduction in area 60 per cent, to 70 per cent.; and hardness (Brinell) 155 to 175. Applications in which the new electrode now makes available the simplicity and economy of arc welded fabri cation include: Furnace tubing, cracking stills, hot oil transfer lines, heat exchangers, bubble tower caps, return bends, valves, superheater headers and other similar ap plications. 'Chromeweld 4-6' is a coated electrode and is made in three sizes—i in., ^ in., and in. NEWS FROM THE OIL FIELDS. Anglo-Ecuadorian. Production for October, 20,667 tons. Comment: 1,243 tons up. Anglo-Egyptian. Production for week ended October 30, 3,281 tons (previous week, 3,293 tons). . . Comment: 12 tons down. Apex (Trinidad). Production for October, 47,270 tons; deliveries, 44,250 tons. | Comment: Production, 670 tons up; deliveries, 4,420 tons down. British Controlled. Production for week ended October 31: Venezuela, 19,862 barrels; Trinidad, 28,525 barrels; total output, 48,387 barrels. 1 Comment: 3,133 barrels down. Lobitos. Production for October, 26,483 tons. Comment: 2 tons. down. Mexican Eagle. Production for week ended October 24, 179,000 barrels (previ ous week, 453,000 barrels). Comment: 274,000 barrels down. Phoenix Oil and Transport. Gross production of group for October, 72,272 tons (againJ 77,864 tons in September). Comment: 5,592 tons down. Trinidad Consolidated Oilfields. Well No. 17 has been brought into production and is proving the most important so far drilled in the Oropuche field. After producing 1,000 barrels per day for a few days it is now flowing at 1,200 barrels per day under the highest pressure so far experi-j enced in that field. Production for October, 33,000 barrels. Comment: 7,000 barrels up. Trinidad Leaseholds. Produced during October, 43,301 tons; purchased during Octo ber from other companies, 68,354 tons. Comment: Production, 1,993 tons down; purchases, 158 tons up. United British Oilfields of Trinidad. Production for week ended November 2, 4,120 tons (previous, week, 3,990 tons). Comment: 130 tons up. Venezuelan Oil Concessions. Production for week ended October 31: Bolivar district, 780,690 barrels (previous week, 754,423 barrels); Maracaibo district, z4,b barrels (previous week, '25„153 tkarrels)J total, 805 ,384 barre (previous week, 779,576 barrels). Well L.S. 362 at Lagunmas been brought in, producing 390 barrels per day through a 2-1 flow-plug. Well L.B. 1 has been completed at a depth of • and after producing at average rate of 900 barrels per day tnr sj a f-inch flow-plug with 350 lb. pressure during a ser * es l ° , pr0 tests, has been closed in. This well is situated at Bacnaq near the shore of Lake Maracaibo, about 12 miles soutn-ea w present Lagunillas field. J m Comment: Bolivar district, 26,267 barrels up: Maracaibo trict, 459 barrels down.OIL NEWS. io3 OTHER NOTICES. i on Thursday morning. :er for insertion, noon on ear inland and £1 abroad cation include: Furnace tubing, cracking stills, hot oil transfer lines, heat exchangers, bubble tower caps, return bends, valves, superheater headers and other similar ap. plications. 'Chromeweld 4-6' is a coated electrode and is made in three sizes—4 in., ^ in., and in. ffices: 70-74, London Road, .E.l. s). on application to above ising agents, who all have ibers must place a definite railway bookstall for the otherwise they will fail )ws' may be had at 6d. may be purchased at the des, and of Messrs. Robert n Messrs. W. Porteous and 3, Glasgow. LDING 4-6 PER CENT. FEELS. t. chromium steels, which in applications requiring at high temperatures and ly welded by use of a new he Lincoln Electric Com- permits full development the low-chromium steels, to sulphide corrosion four teel and a resistance to times as great. The elec- ment of molybdenum and the necessary high creep ential for welding the 4-6 h steels, welded with the ;d to physical properties steel, and, therefore, ren- rhere severe cold-working , produced with proper &gt;ealed at 1550-1600 deg. F., annealing furnace, or air proximately the following 65,000 lb. to 70,000 lb. per 40,000 lb. per sq. in.; duc- nt. elongation in 2 in.; re- i 75 per cent.; hardness lieved at 1400 deg. F., the omeweld 4-6' deposit are ile strength 80,000 lb. to 55,000 lb. to 65,000 lb. per :o 30 per cent, elongation cent, to 70 per cent.; and iew electrode now makes lomy of arc welded fabri- NEWS FROM THE OIL FIELDS. Anglo-Ecuadorian. Production for October, 20,667 tons. Comment: 1,243 tons up. Anglo-Egyptian. Production for week ended October 30, 3,281 tons (previous week, 3,293 tons). •- - Comment: 12 tons down. Apex (Trinidad). Production for October, 47,270 tons; deliveries, 44,250 tons. Comment: Production, 670 tons up; deliveries, 4,420 tons down. British Controlled. Production for week ended October 31: Venezuela, 19,862 barrels; Trinidad, 28,525 barrels; total output, 48,387 barrels. Comment: 3,133 barrels down. Lobitos. Production for October, 26,483 tons. Comment: 2 tons, down. Mexican Eagle. Production for week ended October 24, 179,000 barrels (previ ous week, 453,000 barrels). Comment: 274,000 barrels down. Phoenix Oil and Transport. Gross production of group for October, 72,272 tons (against 77,864 tons in September). Comment: 5,592 tons down. Trinidad Consolidated Oilfields. Well No. 17 has been brought into production and is proving the most important so far drilled in the Oropuche field. After producing 1,000 barrels per day for a few days it is now flowing at 1,200 barrels per day under the highest pressure so far experi enced in that field. Production for October, 33,000 barrels. Comment: 7,000 barrels up. Trinidad Leaseholds. Produced during October, 43,301 tons; purchased during Octo ber from other companies, 68,354 tons. Comment: Production, 1,993 tons down; purchases, 158 tons up. United British Oilfields of Trinidad. Production for week ended November 2, 4,120 tons (previous week, 3,990 tons). Comment: 130 tons up. Venezuelan Oil Concessions. Production for week ended October 31: Bolivar district, 780,690 barrels (previous week, 754,423 barrels); Maracaibo district, 24,694 barrels (previous week, '25„153 Uarrels)^ total, 805,384 barrels (previous week, 779,576 barrels). Well L.S. 362 at Lagunillas has been brought in, producing 390 barrels per day through a 2- incn flow-plug. Well L.B. 1 has been completed at a depth of 4,640 •» and after producing at average rate of 900 barrels per day tnrougn a f-inch flow-plug with 350 lb. pressure during a series of snon tests, has been closed in. This well is situated at Bachaque ' near the shore of Lake Maracaibo, about 12 miles south-eas present Lagunillas field. Comment: Bolivar district, 26,267 barrels up; Maracaibo dis trict, 459 barrels down.&gt; THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED iss. J hrein Island, Persian Gulf, ^ . e; ^ 936c Wo oPA-751 His Britannic Majesty's political Agent s Ba^ein. , ^ V' Dsar Sir; || ^ v please refer to my letter llooPA-349 of January 9, 1926. regarding the land resenred for the Refinery Layout tmder th© rights granted in Articles I and II of the Mining Le«,se 2 dated December 29. 1934 s cohering aefinery Installation, Pipe Line and Roads Rights-of-way, and re serration for four drilling wells; /e now find it necessary to raake application for additional refinery reservation and I am enclosing herewith seven copies of a new reap which not only shows the present refinery inetallation, pipe line and road rights-of-?ay and Reservation for water wells but also the land which we should like to further reserve, / 'I am also attaching a complete description which shows all the land reserved and how it closes on all sides, which description supersedes all others sent you to date. &gt; The area near Malamlr known as Parcel Wo o 2, now includes all wells drilled in that loeationo Three of the wells are being used for refinery water supply 0 The fourth is used by the villagers as part of their domestic water supply. The fifth •?:ell is capped off c. A revised description of this area is attached, ^ The added area tc the -south-west o the present reservation equals 26-3 acres, and shall hereinafter be referred to as Parcel No,4. This area includes a one cultivated property shown as a 'Piilni Grard*2?J f ', and fo** ! hleb we are arranging purchase. The balance is uncultivated land, apparently net privately oTOed. &gt; A 100 foot wide strip shown on the attached sketch, hereinafter referred to as Parcel Ko c 5 8 is for a bio re direct road from the refinery to the Si^ra Pier^ which will b© used extensively in shipping coke, package goods 8 etc-, This road crosses the Sitra Channel at its shallowest part. This eressing when built, will be designed to regard the ebb and flow of the tide at. thii point- I Also shown on the attashed sketch is a '-CO foot wide strip from the marsh land east of the refinery to tj.de water hereinafter referred to as Parcel No06; This is for a drainage ditoh to drain off excess w^ter from the marsho Yours very truly 9 Incls: GoW.Ro SMITH. Chief Local Representative f THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY, LIMITED® BSSi J?1 f\M PASCAL ONS. Reservat ioa for Refinery at Jebel Hisal- Beginning at a point 27,414 feet Korth and 18,570 feet last ol Triangulation Station Number One (located on the summit of jebel Dukhan) thence South 37 0 59 s West 415 feet to Point called station 5 thence North 48 0 4£« West 245 feet to point called station 6 thence North 24 0 08» West 296 feet to point called station 7 thence North 8 o 30« West 320 feet to point called station 8 thence North 74017« East 265 feet to point called station 9 thence North 16 0 S4 8 East 810 feet to point called station 10 thence North 78 0 33 ! East 410 feet to point called station 11 thence North 21 0 14» East 927.1 feet to point called station 12 thence North 60 o 00' East 2760 feet to a point hereinafter referred to as Point 'A n o thence approximately South 35 0 19» East 2394 feet 9 more or less to a point called Station 18, thence South 60 o 00« West 1110 feet to Point called station 19 thence South 1 0 45 9 West 1060 feet to point called station 20 thence south 60 o 00 J West 2940 feet to pointcalled Station 1 thence North 21 0 38 J . West 690 feet to point called station 2 thence Korth 21 0 56 9 West 390 feet to point called station 3 thence North 45 0 36* West 630 feet to the point of beginning called Triangulation station 14^ The above described boundaries enclose an area of about 300 acres®PARC EL T V/0. RESERVATION FOR VfATER 'JELLS NEAR MALAKTR, Beginning at a point 34 s 032 feet North and 2S s 314 feet E^st of Triangulation Station One (located on the summit of Jebel Dukhan) thence Enst 1100 feet thence South 1761 ^feet to a point on the northeasterly line of Parcel Three5 thence South 42 o 50 , West 54306 feet along the North boundary of Parcel Three; thence North 47 o 10 , West 916ol feetj thence North 1600 feet, more or less to the point of heginnin*?o The ahove described boundaries enclose an area of about 48,1 acresoPARCEL THREE e RESERVATION FOR PIPE LINES TO 3ITRA AND mTSR WELLS. Description of the centerline of an eighty foot wide strip of land 0 lying equally on either side of the line hereinafter described^ and extending from the Refinery to Sitra Loading Terminalo Said centerline is more particularly described as followss Beginning at a point in the Northeasterly boundary line of parcel One,, the Refinery Reservation hereinbefore described, distant Southeasterly thereon 925o9 feet from Point 'A', as described in parcel One 5 thence North 42 o 50 J East» 5687o98 feet to a point hereinafter referred to as point and from which a prominent corner in a long stone wall marking the Easterly line of the village of Malamir bears approximately North 58 0 83' West 2074 feet£, more or less? thence North 41 o 30« East 3757 feet 5 thence approximately North 26 0 16 9 West„ 60 feet s more or lesa to a point in the Southeasterly line of Sitra Loading Terminal, from which point the center of an existing steel tank known as Number 85-3 bears North 4 0 28 s East 185 feetoPAHGSL FOUR* HSSSnVATIOM FOH R^F H' iAT XTBIiX HISAI. Beginning at a point called Station I of Parcel i«To.One located at the South-ITast boundary corner of parcel Tfo.One# Tbance Kortii '60°00* SfLst 2940 feet to Station 20 of parcel One thence North l c 45' East 1060 feet to station 19 of Parcel One thence North 60 o 00' East 1110 feet to station 18 of Parcel one thence South East 2117.11 feet to point called station 21 thence Soutn SO^O' West 1189•124 feet to point called station 22 thence south 30 o 00« East 1800 feet to point called Station 23 thence South 60 o 00 4 West 2208 feet to point called Station 24 thence North 46 o 00 5 West 1170 feet to point called Station 25 thence North 79 o 30 t ^fest 638 feet to point called Station 26 thence North 43 o 08 , West 420 feet to point called Station 27 thence South 82 0 31» West 230 feet to point called station 28 thence North 30 o 32* West 370 f^et to point called station 29 thence South 72 0 39* West 522o35 feet to point called station 30 thence North 5 o 30* West 534^,44 feet to the point of beginning,. The above described boundaries enclose an area of about 263 acres«Ht, PARCEL FIV3. STRIP OJJ LAM) FOR A. M0R3 DIRiiCT ROAD FROM REFINSRY TO SITRA PIER. Description of the centerline of a 100 foot wide strip of land lying equally on either side of the line hereinafter described and extending from Parcel 3 to the sitra Pier® Said centerline is more particularly described as follows ; Beginnins -t a point on the centerline of parcel Three wox 111 42 o 50« East 1695o4 feat from the Sastem boundary of Parcel one 5 thence North 70 o 55' East 6188 0 3 feet; thence North 82 0 54 # East 955 feet more or less to face of Sitra pier.PARCEL SIX .. RESERVATION FOR OUTI^T DITCH AT J EHEL HIS^X . Description of the centerline at a 100 foot wide strip of land lying equally on either side of the line hereinafter described and extending from the Refinery Reservation Parcel Four to a point at the end of said centerline more particularly described as follows g Beginning at a point in the Southeasterly Boundsry Line of parcel Four, the Refinery Reservation hereinbefore described, distant Southwesterly thereon 278o28 feet from point 31 as described in parcel Four j thence South 60 o 57 5 East 3600 feet, more or less, to a point joining the Tide Watero The above described strip of land contains an area of about 8o3 acreso3679A INDIA OFFICE, (^ 1 H Political Department. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). (N.B.—This is an original message, sent by air mail to save telegraphic expense, but intended to be treated on receipt with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. It has been drafted as if it were so despatched.) From Secretary of State for India, ^ Political Resident in the Persian Gulf; Repeated to: Government of India, Foreign Political Dept. Dated 8.12.36. Political Agent, Bahrein. No. P.Z. Your Express Letter of the 19th November, No.C/223 of Tanurah has heen followed up 'by the Company, who are clearly determined to develop a port if it is economically practicable. Minutes of a meeting held on November 17th in the Hydrographer's room at the Admiralty are enclosed for information# The issue of the above has been authorised* 7 1936, Mr,Ballantyne's enquiry about the approaches to Ras CSgd.) M. J. OLAUSCN?*1 p.2. 8562/36. DRA.FT MINUTES OP MEETING AT the ADMIRALTY BETWEEN REPRESENTATIVES OP THE ADMIRALTY, INDIA OPPICE, AND THE CALIFORNIA ARABIAN STANDARD OIL COMPANY. A meeting was held on 17th November in the Hydrographer's room to discuss the possibility of an Admiralty survey of the coast of Arabia, with a view to discovering whether a deep water harbour could be constructed at Ras Tanurah. The following were present: Rear Admiral J.A. Edgell (^rdrographer). Mr. e. A.Seal ( m) Mr.J.H.Peck (m) mr.m. J.Clauson (India Office) Mr.R.Lebkicher ) California Arabian Standard Mr.H.R.Ballantyne) Oil Company. Mr.Lebkicher stated that he wished to discover whether the Admiralty would be willing to survey the area concerned in order to find whether a deep water channel existed to any possible site for a port on the mainland, e.g. Ras Tanurah. The California Arabian Standard Oil Company were at present taking preliminary soundings of a rough and ready nature but it was explained that the prospects of there being a useful channel,could only be ascertained by a thorough survey with proper equipment. This the Admiralty could not undertake at present, but it was suggested that if the California Arabian Standard Oil Company could procure the equipment, it might be possible to obtain the services of a. retired naval officer who was a hydrographic surveyor for the work. The Company were anxious that any charts that they compiled might be acceptable for general use by all shipping that used the port they hoped to develop. The. Hydrographer stated that charts compiled under such conditions would be so used. /V 2. It was agreed that nothing further could he done until the details of the preliminary survey work; already carried out hy the California Arabian Standard Oil Company engineers were known. The Hydrographer agreed to examine the original surveys already completed., with a view to determining the amount of work which would he necessary before a safe channel could he properly defined.No* C/558-10/1. Political Agency, Bahrain, the 22nd December 1936 V From Lieutenant-Colonel Gordon Loch, C.I.E., Political Agent, Bahrain. fo The Adviser to the Bahrain Government, Bahrain Sir, ^ ^7 In continuation of my letter Ho. 0/25-10/1 dated the 15th January 1936, I have the honour to say that the Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Fetroleusi Company Limited, has sent me a blue print show- the in^/land which the Company has reserved under the rights granted in Artieleal and II of the Mining Lease dated the 29th December 1934 to cover (i) the refinery installation. (ii) the pipe line and road rights of way, (iii) the reservation for water wells and also certain further land which they now wish to reserve. necessary to make application for additional refinery reservation, and a copy is enclosed of the blue print and also of a complete description which shows all the land reserved and the boundaries on all sides. This com prehensive description is intended to supersede all others sent to you up to date. 3. The area near Malamir known as Parcel Ho. now includes all wells drilled in that location. Three of the wells are being used for refinery water supply. The fourth is used by the villagers as part of their domestic water supply. The fifth well is capped off. A revised description of this area is attached. It will be observed that the Company find it4, the added area to the southwest of the present reservation equals 263 acres, snddiall hereinafter be « referred to as Parcel Mo. 4« This area Includes some cultivated property shown as a 'Palm Garden'', and for t ■. v A. '' w '' „ l; 4 which we'arranging purchase• The balance is uncultivated land, apparently not privately owned. ■ 5 # A 100 foot wide strip shown on the attached sketch, hereinafter referred to as Parcel Ho. 6, is for a sore direct road from the refinery to the Sitra Pier, which will be used extensively in shipping coke, package goods, et cetera. This road crosses the Sitra Channel at its shallowest part. This crossing when built will be designed to regard the ebb and flow of the tide at this point. 6, Also shown on the attached sketch is a 100 foot wide strip from the marsh land east of the refinery to tide water hereinafter referred to as Parcel No. 6. This is for a drainage ditch to drain off excess water from the marsh. 7, It is requested that you will kindly inform me (a) whether the Bahrain Government accept the proposal for reserving further land and (b) whether they accept as correct the comprehensive description of all the land reserved. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, / Lieutenant-Colo®] Political Agent, Bahrain.CONFIDENTIAL. ^ C/S60-10/1. The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to:— 1 # The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gul Bushire. 2» His Majesty^ Secretary of State for India, London* 3. The Fore in Secretary to the Government of India, Mew Delhi. and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document (s). The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian G-xjle. Dated. •Sfind-PewenbeT *1936 • Reference to previou^corre|p9p^nce'r , Bahrain printed letter No- C/26-10/1 dated the 15th January 1936 • Description 1. 2. Name and Date. 1, f jfnr o Letter Ho. PA-761 dated the 5th Detler.iber 1936 from the Chief local llepreeentative The Bahrain Petroleum Company Idmited. Letter !: f o. C/568-10/1 date the 22nd December 1936 to the Adviser to the Bahrain Government. a Subject, Bahrain c ii of Land. - Reservation77 Cmifidential . Political Agency, No. C/17-lO/l . Bahrain, the 9th January iSJ57, From To Lieutenant-Colonel, Gordon ioch, C.I.E,, Political i ,cnt, Bahrain, the Honourable the political Resident in the„ Pe Jf ian lialf . •Ba shire. Use of vireless telegraphy by ships in the Ba hrain harbour. Sir, refer to the I have the honour to refer to the correspondent /' ending 1th ay printed letter No. C/514-10/1 dated the 15th fey 1954. S. I have received a colSlaint from th«- Officer- in-Chi-rge Cable and Wireiess aiaitod, Bahri.in, that on the 2Znd Moveiaber 1936 at 1533 G«M.f• on a wave length of 36 metres the Danish steamship Henning Marsk used her wireless installation while lying in Bahrain harbour (off Si trail) and sent the following message# Message No. 1 Henning Karsfc^ to OXZ (Lungby Radio in Denmark) words 13 dated time 1505 (addressed to Msrsk KM). 'Ankom Sandag ISorgen Bunkers 175 Forventer Afsealing l4ndag eftermiddag - Heimlnglfersk.« KBH is the sign for Copenhagen, the operator on duty heard 4^ OXZ acknoivledgli receipt^of the above message at 1545 on 36 aetres. 3» the Officer-in-Charge had arranged on that date to coiaamicate with their Cable Ship Lady Denison Pender at 15S0 b,M»T» on the same waWe length but was unable to effect contact owing to interference from the Henning/Henning Henning Ml - rsic, which as stated above was working traffic in the Bahrain harbour. to have been contrwy to the International Telegraph Heguiations. tne attention of the oinirs of the S.S. Henning Marsk the breach of the regulations committed by cheir vessel# I do not know whether sny disciplinary action or the recovery of the cost of the for Cable and wireless .Liffii.t&lt;::d possible. B. I further -suggest that the Bahrain Petro leu® Company I»laited be asked to warn all tankers or other ships coming to Bahrain on their business that t use of wireless telegraphy by ships in the Bahrain territorial waters is not perrrdtted. 4 the action of the S.S. Henning Ifersk appears 5 I recommend that steps be taken to bring to I have the honour to be Sir You: »st obedient servant. Lt,-Colonel5 Political Agent, Bahrain.an the bahrein petroleum company limited 2 A I Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, Ho. PA-10 - January 4, 193?. '■■v '■■■'•;&gt; .. His Britannic Majesty»s Political Agent, Bahrein, Dear Sir: We are sending you herewith three cloth mounted copies of the aerial map of Bahrein, which we have just received from our San Francisco Office. Will you kindly forward one copy to His Excellency Sheikh Sir Hamad bin Essa al Khalifah, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., and one copy to the Financial Adviser to the Government of Bahrein. The third copy is for you. Yours very truly. G. W. R. SMITH, Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED, End: Y.(IT 0 GOVERNMENT OF BAHRAIN. LAND DEPARTMENT. Ko: 1 Z 1^1 o f 1355, Bahra in, Shaw/a 1, 1356 v ki anuary, 1937 To H. B. M'S Political Agent, Bahrain. Sir &gt; I havj&gt; the honour to acknowledge your letter Kb: C/5^8-10/1 dated the 22nd December 1936. 2. lb will take sometime to ascertain whether there are any claims from private individuals to ground within the area mentioned in your letter. It will be necessary for the Land Department to issue proclamations in the usual way before the area can be registered. I have the honour to be, Your most obedient servant, Adviser, Government of Bahrain.(i i, i ] 1 DURRANI'S PRESS CUTTINGS St. Andrew's House, 32 to 34 Holborn Viaduct, and 3 St. Andrew Street, Holborn Circus, E.C.I. Telephone: CENTRAL 3149 (Two Lines). Cutting from the Dated December 1936 Address of Journal and refining operations on tip 7°? dvilU ^ ni Eastern Saudi AraW* ' '-l' 1 of Bah ^ ^ o&amp;ce of the company visitmg the London w 1 \) &gt;Decemb er 10, 1936. a PROGRESS ON Potential Over DURRAI St. Andre and 3 St. Tel Dated Dece Address of J /) o 450 Cutting fron A deep test, No. 52, deeper, started in the he field by California-Texas low 1,300 feet in about carried to basement rock, will test showings of oil the regular pay horizon and probably around 3,000 feet, or deeper. The con reducing wells with a rated .potential of barrels daily, based on open-flow tests 01 tubing on others and small chokes on oi determined, however, that Bahrein Islam ducing ud to 35,000 barrels of oil in 24 he only 54 lb. from starting closed-in press the period. The pressure calculations a readings at approximately 1,100 feet dc REFINERY. Although the California-Texas consd on its 10,000-barrel refinery on the noi the island is not complete, the compar contract for construction to double caps original 10,000-barrel capacity of the refi all products are being removed to other facilities for finishing. In prepara throughput, and also to attain some de producing practice, the company is maki storage capacity. Producing intervals ; by accessibility of boats for moving the . channels. n n ^ i In developing Bahrein Island, Cal Company is observing 3,000-foot spacin; about one well to each 170 acres. The is encountered at about 1,850 feet and pletion depth around 2,150 feet. Due covery in the producing lime and so.~~^-——- classified as Eocene, the actual pay thickness has not been accurately determined. EXPORT. Rising importance of the Arabian coast as a petroleum producer has been strikingly shown by Bahrein s ance this year as an oil exporter of approximately l,75u,uU barrels during /the first six months. Extension of exploration work into undrilled portions of the Arabian coast of the Persian Gulf is indicated tor the near future in addition to work now well advanced m Kowait and on the Arabian mainland due west of Bahrein Island. The last of a series of moves by the Iraq Petro leum Company is signalised by the formation of a ne ^ subsidiary, Petroleum Developments (Trucial Coast) with a capital of £100,000 in 100 a A' shares and 100,000 ' B shares with par of £1 each. The new company is an offshoot of Petroleum ^ or |' cessions, the Iraq Petroleum Company's exploration and development unit. It will exploit concessions obtained by the Iraq company at various places along the Trucial Coast, which runs from Bahrein and Qatar along the southern shore of the Persian Guilf to the Strait of Ormuz. Negotiations for the concessions involved have been under way for 18 months. Two-year options over the prin cipal areas have been obtained by representatives of the Anglo-Iranian Oil Company for the Iraq company. Some of the optioned areas have been converted into full con- : cession agreements by the negotiators of Petroleum Con cessions and it is expected that the remainder will shortly be handled in a similar manner. The areas involved, from ANSWERS TO CO The inquiry coupon to be filled in. If the reply is to be sent b must be enclosed. Readers are particularly ' Personal ' letters intended fo OIL (8786).—The setback in ( occurred last week is one ol pen from time to time. It of leading shares. As for sel write us again in six months' K. K. (8787).—Authorised capi Trinidad is £400,000 in l,000,0i BELLONA (8788).—What war in one direction it makes u certainly not sell Burmah on a declaration of war, for thi Z. (8789).—Both Kern River ai OILFIELD (8790).—The inforn in detail in ' Applied Geoi South Kensington, 2s. COAL ROY The Secretary for Mines i Executive of the Mineworkers' 3 which had called, at his invitat hear any views which they mi| ing the proposed legislation 1 royalties. After an informal technical problems which will when the executive had had tin they would furnish their views1&amp;^&gt; riprsmb er 10, 1936. PROGRESS ON BAHREIN ISLAND. Potential Over 250,000 Barrels Daily. A deep test, No. 52, equipped to drill to 8.000 feet or . pr started in the heart of the Bahrein Island proven fIT hv California -Texas Oil Company, Ltd., is drilling be- f 1 S00 feet in about 18-inch and conceivably may be l0W p H to basement rock. No. 51, near No. 52, now drilling, felt showings of oil encountered in flank wells below the regular pay horizon and probably will be carried to /rTrf ^ 000 feet or deeper. The company now has 35 SdniTelL with a rated potential of mora than 250,000 barrels daily, based on open-flow tests on some wells, open Eg on others and small chokes on others. It has been determined, however, that Bahrein Island is capable of pro- JnciL uo to 35,000 barrels of oil in 24 hours with a drop of nnlv 54 lb from starting closed-in pressure to the end of thp neriod. The pressure calculations are based on bomb readings at approximately 1,100 feet datum. REFINERY. Although the California-Texas construction programme nn its 10 000-barrel refinery on the north-eastern side of the island is not complete, the company has already let contract for construction to double capacny. Part of t original 10,000-barrel capacity of the refinery is m use, but all products are being removed to other affiliated refining facilities for finishing. In preparation for capaci y throughput, and also to attain some degree of consistent oroducing practice, the company is making additions to its storage capacity. Producing intervals are now governed by accessibility of boats for moving the oil into consuming C ^ a In developing Bahrein Island, California-Texas Oil Company is observing 3,000-foot spacing, or a pattern o about one well to each 170 acres. The producing horizon is encountered at about 1,850 feet and the average com pletion denth around 2,150 feet. Due to poor core re covery in 'the producing lime and soapstone horizons, classified as Eocene, the actual pay thickness has not been accurately determined. EXPORT. Rising importance of the Arabian coast as a peti oleum producer has been strikingly shown by Bahrein s ance this year as an oil exporter of approximately l,75u,UU barrels during ^the first six months. Extension of exploration work into undrilled portions of the Arabian coast of the Persian Gulf is indicated for the near future in addition to work now well advanced m Kowait and on the Arabian mainland due west of Bahrein Island. The last of a series of moves by the Iraq Petro leum Company is signalised by the formation of a new subsidiary, Petroleum Developments (Trucial Coast) with a capital of £100,000 in 100 'A' shares and 100,000 ' B ' shares with par of £1 each. The new company is an offshoot of Petroleum Con cessions, the Iraq Petroleum Company's exploration and development unit. It will exploit concessions obtained by the Iraq company at various places along the Trucial Coast, which runs from Bahrein and Qatar along the southern shore of the Persian Guilf to the Strait of Ormuz. Negotiations for the concessions involved have been under way for 18 months. Two-year options over the prin cipal areas have been obtained by representatives of the Anglo-Iranian Oil Company for the Iraq company. Some of the optioned areas have been converted into full con cession agreements by the negotiators of Petroleum Con cessions and it is expected that the remainder will shortly be handled in a similar manner. The areas involved, from 449 FOR A QUICK START FROM COLD . .. run your car on 10 NAI 1 BENZOLE L MIXTURE The spirit of STARTABILITY STARTABILITY is the special virtue of National Benzole, the motor spirit that corned from British coal. Run your car on National Benzole Mixture and you will get not only the easy starting from cold that Benzole gives, but also extra power, and quicker acceleration. The fastest spirit motorists National Benzole Co. Ltd.,Wellington House, Buckingham Gate, London,s.w.i (The distributing organisation owned and entirely controlled by the producers o* British Benzole) west to east, are: Abu Dhabi, Diabai, Sharjah Ummul- Qawain, and Ras-al-Khaimah.—'Oil and Gas Journal.\Qk&amp; 10^ Decemb er 1(X 1936 PROGRESS Potential Over DURRAMT'S PRESS CUTTINGS 449 ON St. Andrew's House, 32 to 34 Holborn Viaduct, and 3 St. Andrew Street, Hotborn Circus, E.C.I. Telephone; CENTRAL 3149 (Two Lines). Cutting from the o.vC ruw?. Dated December 1936 Address of Journal A deep test, No. 52, deeper, started in the he field by California-Texas low 1,300 feet in about carried to basement rock. i! 1 Regular 0 pa^honzon Tnd probably will be carried to iSnnn feet or deeroer. The company now has 35 Producing wells with a rated potential of more than 250,000 barrels daily, based on open-flow tests on some wells, open tubing on others and small chokes on others. It has been determined, however, that Bahrein Island is capable of pro ducing ud to 35,000 barrels of oil in 24 hours with a drop of only 54 lb. from starting closed-in pressure to the end of the period. The pressure calculations are based on bomb readings at approximately 1,100 feet datum. REFINERY. Although the California-Texas construction programme on its 10 000-barrel refinery on the north-eastern s i de 0 * the island is not complete, the company has already let contract for construction to double capacity. Part ot the original 10,000-barrel capacity of the refinery is m use, but all products are being removed to other affiliated refining facilities for finishing. In preparation for capacity throughput, and also to attain some degree of consistent nroducing practice, the company is making additions to its storage capacity. Producing intervals are now governed by accessibility of boats for moving the oil into consuming channels. ^ ^ . m rvi In developing Bahrein Island, California-Texas Oil Company is observing 3,000-foot spacing, or a pattern of about one well to each 170 acres. The producing horizon is encountered at about 1,850 feet and the average com pletion depth around 2,150 feet. Due to poor core re covery in the producing lime and soapstone horizons, classified as Eocene, the actual pay thickness has not been accurately determined. EXPORT. Rising importance of the Arabian coast as a petroleum producer has been strikingly shown by Bahrein's appear ance this year as an oil exporter of approximately 1,750,000 barrels during ^the first six months. Extension of exploration work into undrilled portions of the Arabian coast of the Persian Gulf is indicated for the near future in addition to work now well advanced in Kowait and on the Arabian mainland due west of Bahrein Island. The last of a series of moves by the Iraq Petro leum Company is signalised by the formation of a new subsidiary, Petroleum Developments (Trucial Coast) with a capital of £100,000 in 100 'A' shares and 100,000 a B' shares with par of £1 each. The new company is an offshoot of Petroleum Con cessions, the Iraq Petroleum Company's exploration and development unit. It will exploit concessions obtained by the Iraq company at various places along the Trucial Coast, which runs from Bahrein and Qatar along the southern shore of the Persian Guilf to the Strait of Ormuz. Negotiations for the concessions involved have been under way for 18 months. Two-year options over the prin cipal areas have been obtained by representatives of the I Anglo-Iranian Oil Company for the Iraq company. Some of the optioned areas have been converted into full con cession agreements by the negotiators of Petroleum Con cessions and it is expected that the remainder will shortly e ^Hdled in a similar manner. The areas involved, from ICK START D r on l (0 ! BENZOLE ■ MIXTURE 0^ r The spirit of STARTAB1LITY j . STARTABILITY is the special virtue of National Benzole, the motor spirit that comes^ ^ from British coal. Run your car on National Benzole Mixture and you will get not only the easy starting from cold that Benzole gives, but also extra power, and iililfc quicker acceleration. The fastest spirit motorists ^ National Benzole Co. Ltd.,Wellington House, Buckingham Gate, London ,s.w .i (The distributing organisation owned and entirely controlled by the producers o* British Benzole) west to east, are: Abu Dhabi, Diabai, Sharjah Ummul- Qawain, and Ras-al-Khaimah.—'Oil and Gas Journal.'o i 450 OIL NEWS. December 10 ANSWERS TO CORRESPONDENTS. The inquiry coupon to be found elsewhere must be filled in. If the reply is to be sent by post a fee of five shillings must be enclosed. Readers are particularly requested not to mark as ' Personal ' letters intended for the Editor. OIL (8786).—The setback in oil shares generally which occurred last week is one of similar events which hap pen from time to time. It should not disturb holders of leading shares. As for selling your holding, you may write us again in six months' time. K. K. (8787).—Authorised capital of Premier Oilfields of Trinidad is £400,000 in 1,000,000 5s. shares all of one class. BELLONA (8788).—What war fakes from the oil industry in one direction it makes up in another. We should certainly not sell Burmah on a war-scare rumour, or on a declaration of war, for that matter. Z. (8789).—Both Kern River and Phoenix should be held. OILFIELD (8790).—The information you require is given in detail in ' Applied Geophysics,' Science Museum, South Kensington, 2s. COAL ROYALTIES. The Secretary for Mines received last Thursday the Executive of the Mineworkers' Federation of Great Britain, which had called, at his invitation, in order that he might hear any views which they might wish to express regard ing the proposed legislation for the unification of coal royalties. After an informal discussion of some of the technical problems which will arise, it was agreed that, when the executive had had time to consider them further, they would furnish their views to the Secretary for Mines. SUEZ CANAL OIL TRAFFIC. Oil cargoes having used the Suez Canal in Sect ber, compare as follows with corresponding figure thousands of metric tons):— Sept., Aug. Sept. 1936 1936 1935 Fuel oil 165 65 135 ^ Petrol 157 155 77 Kerosene 48 14 | Diesel oil and gas oil 29 21 49 Crude 20 69 41 ^ Miscellaneous 7 1 2 Total Northward ... 426 325 310 Total Southward 24 63 73 M'' The decrease in the southward trade is ascribed chiefly to the absence of shipments from Russia and Curagao which accounted for, respectively, 8,000 tons and 11,000 in September last year. Russia sent only 21,000 tons, as compared with 42,000 tons. In the homeward direction there is an increase of no less than 37.4 per cent, over last year. Abadan sent 384,000' tons, an increase of 92,000 tons, including 70,000 tons for petrol which accounted for 140,000 tons. The Dutch East Indies sent 21,000 tons instead of 10,000 tons. BahreiiL- appears for 9,000 tons fuel oil, as compared with nil in September, 1935. One notes a cargo of 12,000 tons fuel oil sent back from Massaouah to Italy. Tankers using the Canal aggregated 430,000 tons net- register, as against 431,000 tons in August, and 400,000 tons in September, 1935. This included 186,000 tons in ballast, as against, respectively, 219,000 tons and 195,000 tons. THREEPENCE WEEKLY on Sale EVERY THURSDAY MORNING ENSURE YOUR COPY by placing an ADVANCE ORDER with your Newsagent or Bookstall to RESERVE YOU A COPY OF E very issue IF YOU PREFER WE WILL POST direct to your address. Subscription Rates W6 at Home per annum Abroad Quarterly rates, proportionate. Subscription Form on another page Address: Subscription Dept., ' OIL NEWS,' 70-74, London Road, Elephant and Castle, London, S.E.I . Also 'PETROLEUM WORLD' (monthly) Home and Abroad, 12/- per annum.OIL NEWS. December 10, 1930 R RESPONDENTS. 1 found elsewhere must be y post a fee of five shillings requested not to mark as r the Editor. shares generally which ; similar events which hap- should not disturb holders ling your holding, you may time. tal of Premier Oilfields of 30 5s. shares all of one class. takes from the oil industry p in another. We should a war-scare rumour, or on it matter. id Phoenix should be held. lation you require is given Dhysics,' Science Museum, ALTIES. 'eceived last Thursday the federation of Great Britain, ion, in order that he might ^ht wish to express regard- or the unification of coal discussion of some of the arise, it was agreed that, ie to consider them further, to the Secretary for Mines. SUEZ CANAL OIL TRAFFIC. Oil cargoes having used the Suez Canal in Spnt ber, compare as follows with corresoonding fienrT^V^ thousands of metric tons):— s W Sept., 1936 Fuel oil Petrol 157 Kerosene ... 48 Diesel oil and gas oil ... 29 Crude 20 Miscellaneous 7 Aug. Sept. 1936 1935 65 135 155 77 14 15 21 40 69 41 1 2 325 310 63 73 Total Northward ... 426 Total Southward 24 _ ^ ^ iiaue is ascribed chiefly to the absence of shipments from Russia and Curacao which accounted for, respectively, 8,000 tons and 11,000 tons ' in September last year. Russia sent only 21,000 tons as compared with 42,000 tons. In the homeward direction there is an increase of no less than 37.4 per cent, over last year. Abadan sent 384 000' tons, an increase of 92,000 tons, including 70,000 tons for petrol which accounted for 140,000 tons. The Dutch East Indies sent 21,000 tons instead of 10,000 tons. Bahrein- appears for 9,000 tons fuel oil, as compared with nil in September, 1935. One notes a cargo of 12,000 tons fuel oil sent back from Massaouah to Italy. Tankers using the Canal aggregated 430,000 tons net register, as against 431,000 tons in August, and 400,000 tons in September, 1935. This included 186,000 tons in ballast, as against, respectively, 219,000 tons and 195,000 tons. p. THREEPENCE WEEKLY Oil new on Sale EVERY THURSDAY MORNING ENSURE YOUR COPY by placing an ADVANCE ORDER with your Newsagent or Bookstall to RESERVE YOU A COPY OF Every issue IF YOU PREFER WE WILL POST direct to your address. Subscription Rates 17'6 lO 7 - at Home |,er annu,,, Abroad Quarterly rates, proportionate. Subscription Form on another page Address: Subscription Dept., ' OIL NEWS,' 70-74, London Road, Elephant and Castle, London, S.E.I. Also 'PETROLEUM WORLD' (monthly) Home and Abroad, 12/- per annum. —- P,( llh r'4 /of D,O.N o, D.7783»N/36, Foreign and Political Department, received by sir John Bwart from a friend in the United States of America it is stated that the iiahrain Petroleum Company are opening a hospital at Bahrain for vtilch tfcey are obtaining the services of Dr. Poth and his wife, who is also a doctor and uses her maiden name Dr. Ho be rt son. The wife is an eye specialist and Dr. Poth is described as a brilliant man, surgeon and P.H.D. as well as M.D. Both are about 30 years of age and are graduate of John Hopfcins Medical School, Maryland. Yours sincerely, Sd. W.R. Hay. New Delhi, the 30*1936. S f + a ^Pital at Bahrain by the jiahrain Petroleum Company. * I am desired to infom you that in a private let.ter Tiie Hon• ble Lieutenant-Colonel T.C. v.Powle, CBS., Political Hesldent in Persian Gulf, Bushire. \^ « A js] \ i 9 JAM 1937 Translation of letter dated the 5th Ihul Qa'dah 1355(18.1 from H.E.Shaikh Sir Hamad bin 'Isa al Khalifah,K,C.I.E. C.S.T., Ruler of Bahrain, to the Political Agent, Bahrain. After Compliments. ■■ O' 1 had much pleasure of receiving your kind letter No.C/51 dated 16th January 1957 equivalent to 3rd Dhul Qadah 1355 and noted what was mentioned 'by you. In particular your sending to me a copy of an aerial map of Bahrain sent to you by the Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited. I thank you for it and wish you always good health and the continuance of pleasure Usual ending. r(r^ No .C/76 -10/1. Poiiticai Agency, Bahrain, the 27th January 1937. To The Qiief iiocai Ke pre sent at ive , The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, B A ii li A I K. pi Dear Sir, I write^ar^acknowledge with thanks the receipt of yoar letter No.PA-10 dated the 4th January 1927 and three cloth mounted copies of an aerial map of Bahrain# S* One copy has been sent to His Excellency Shaikh Sir Hamad bin *Isa ^ Khaiifah, K.C.I.I;., C.S .I., who has askec me to convey his thanks to the Company for it. Yours faithfully. Captain, c 'C For Political Agent, Bahrain.I'Yk GOVERNMENT OF BAHRAIN. ^^7 //^. L.D./1355. lin, ^^.Thulqada, 1355. 2,/ January, 1937. To H. 3. M'S. Political Agent Bahrain. Sir Reference your letter ^0:0/604-10/1 dated the 26th Foveniber 1936. There is no objection to the corrections in question which have been duly noted in the original description. Apparently the new plan is not corrected to corres pond to the description. The eighth course is exactly the same length as in the original plan, while it should have been 92 .9 feet shorter. This will change to some extent the position of all the succeeding courses. I have the honour to be Sir your most obedient servant Adviser, Government of Bahrain Y.Confidential* - / /3 Bb GOVERXMEXT OF INDIA, — Department, EXPRESS LETTER [N, B -TJm is an OltlGIhAL MESSAGE, post expense and undue use of th receipt^ with the same expeddion saie time a&gt;&gt;d formalities it a.d SO (A/OSJp(XtL-il/(iCi % ^ F p.om political Agant, Bahrain. To Political Resident, Bushire. ^ C/63-10/1. 22nd January 7 Bahrain Oil. After dinner on the 18th January 1937 I had a talk with Mr. H.M. Herron, President of the Bahrain Petroleum Company and one of the foreign sales executives of the Texas Corporation, in which he gave me the following information. 2. I asked him about the life of the Bahrain field, explaining that I did ecfbecause we had to advise the Shaikh about TiOney matters and I did not want to see the revenue from oil used on expenditure which it might not be possible to keep up later on. The Bahrain Petroleiap Company estimate _ the amount of oil available at present at one hundred 5 s e * * ^f-^oos&amp;p—(M.480^-26-7-34-2,00,000. J million/ ^ / • ;'f\ ? 'C million barrels. They arf, hov/ever, arraying to bore to 8000 feet in order to find out whether there are any lower oil bearing horizons. If no further oil is found, they expect to be pumping in 1939 and estimate the life of the field at fifteen to twenty years. Mr. Herron, however, qualified the statement by saying that it was the most difficult thing in the world to estimate oil below ground. If they found deeper oil, it might raise the life to fifty or even one hundred years. 3. This information emphasises the need for the Ba rain Government to conserve their revenue from 4 oil (see my letter No. C/490 dated the 17th November 1936). 4. Mr. Herron told me that they were up to now disappointed over the oil in Jabal Dhahran, but were trying elsewhere. If oil was found, they would like to pipe it to Bahrain, or if in small quantities ahip it in barges, but he did not know how the 3a•udi Arab Government would look at the proposal. He asited me if the proposal would be well received in Bahrain and I said that I thought that it would. 5. Mr. Herron states that by the time the Hefinery is finished the Bahrain I^troleum Company will have incurred expenditure on the field of some where between two and two and an half million Sterling. 6. Though his appearance has something of benevolence in it, I understand that Mr. Herron is the movin spirit of the Texas Corporation and is said to be extremely clever and full of drive, and swallows up likely oil-bearing territory wherever he/- 3 - //2 ; 0 he can git it. Lieut.-Colonel, Political Agent, Bahrain.lompany limited Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, No. PA-51 January 20, 1937, His Britannic Majesty's Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir: I am sending herewith two bound sets of Tank Tables as supplied to The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited by Messrs. B. &amp; R. Redwood of London. May I request you to transmit one set to the Financial Adviser to the Bahrein Governmand and the other to 1 the state Engineer of the Bahrein Government Yours very truly G. W. R. SMITH, Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITEDNo. / / 2vl~^ c ' of 1355 Office of xhe Adviser to the Government, Bahrain. Dated, Dil Qaad 13. 1355 January 24, 1937 H.B.M's Political Agent, Bahrain. O Memorandum: - I acknowledge with thanks receipt of an aerial map of Bahrain sent to you by the Chief Local Representative, the Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, forwarded with your memorandum No. C/51~10/l dated 16th January 1937. Mould it possible to obtain another copy? ^ Adviser to the Government. Copy to Land Department.-fin % NO,71.3 1937. ritisn Kesidency &amp;consulate-weneral, BuaHire, tne lt&gt;tn January 1937. To Tne Political Agent, Banrain. Subject : use of wireless telegrapny by snips in tne Banrain narbour. Memorandum . / . Reference your letter iio.C/17-10/1, dated tne 9tn January 1937. 2. According to Article 13 of tne international Telecommunication Convention, Madrid, 1932, tne correct procedure is for tne w/T station in question, in tiiis case, Bahrain, to report to tne Manager, Persian uulf, wno will inform nis Administration, i.e. tne Posts and Telegraphs Department of the (iovernment of India. 3. With reference to your paragraph 6 you should warn the Chief Local Representative of tne Bahrd. n Petro]e um Company accordingly, Basing your warning on your letter No.c/502-10/l.V^Il, dated tne 9tn May 1934. ' {4 (, sd. T.G.Jfowle, Lieut.-uolonel. Political Resident in tne Persian uulf. Att est ed. for Secretary to tne Political Resident in the Persian trulf. i(iBy Air M ail. p.z. '\ , K&amp;MjLj/ffjlr-r -x\v- r /i \ 9\i /r« \ wWliF^ INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, a5'/' Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. The Foreign Secretary, Government of India. The Political Reeident in t^e Persian Gulf. 4963 2000 7.36imtA OFFICE, p.,. 467/37, WHITSHALI, e.W.l. J anuary, 1957. atimail. iy dear Fowl©, /lei Enclosed le a oopy of a letter from Starlimj ith / 1957. / regarding the deatlnatlon of Oil suipiients fro® Bahrein. / On the assumption that the desired Information is available, we should be glad it arrangements could be made to comply with the wishes of the Petroleum Department, t an sending a copy of this letter (with enclosure) to Loch. Tours sincerely, (8gd.) M. J, OLAUSON I Hon'ble Lt, -^ol. C. FOwle, C.fl.E, , fipltlsh Consulste, Bushlre.k I 467/37. PETROLEUM DEPARTMENT, (MINES DEPARTMENT), P D, 21/6. DEAN STANLEY STREET, * * MILLBANK, LONDON, S.W.I. 20th January, 1937, L L •' 9 * ^ h Jy ' Dear Clauson, ■ 1 (/ p T/T ^ Before 1st July last, when the method of assessing royalties payable by the Bahrein Petroleum Company, Limited, was altered we were able, from the information on the Marine Delivery Tickets which were forwarded by the Political Agent, to obtain from Lloyds List the destination of each cargo of oil shipped from Bahrein. Under the present system, in which Refinery Delivery Tickets are furnished, we get information about the production of oil, but we cannot ascertain the destination of the exports. In connection with the arrangements made with the Political Agent to furnish Certificates of Origin in respect of oil shipments from Bahrein, I assume that he or the Bahrein Customs will have information about the destination of the cargoes. We are anxious to keep in touch with the movements of Bahrein oil and I should be glad if you could make some arrangement with the Political Agent by which we can have monthly from 1st July last, and regularly in future, particulars of the nature and quantities of oil products exported under country of destination. ^ 8 °2l E8&lt;1 * » Yours sincerely, ftUeS?!: S.W.I. S8d - F - c - stariing -V CONFIDENTIAL | j / V- yNo. 165—S of 1937. .'■if--'''' ^^^ritish Hedency and Consulate General, syvv BuShire, the 4th February 1937. m- : \v ' ^-;v - .. - - : - v.'' ; ' To The Political Agent, Bahrain, v'' Copy to H.M's Secretary of State for India, India Office, London. MEMORANDA f f( ^ India Office letter'' No. P.Z. 467/37, dated 22nd January 1937. 2. Please arrange to comply with the request of the Petroleum Department, and forward the information direct to the India Office with copy to the Government of India and myself. Monthly returns would be a convenient form. 3. 'The arrangements' referred to in paragraph 3 of Petroleum Department's letter of the 20th January are those mentioned in Mr.Clauson's letter to Mr.Ballantyne, No. ^Z. 7000/36, dated 3rd October 1936, copy sent to you direct. Sd. T.C.FOWLE, , Lieut.-Colonel, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. ATTESTED for Secretary to the Political I resident in the Persian Gulf./ Confiaentlal . No. C/87-10/1. Political Agency, Bahrain, the 2nd February 1937, Tha Mhief ^ocaj. Representative, Tlie Bahrain Petroleum Company limited, Bahrain. Dear Sir, I have received a complaint from the Officer- in-Charge, Cable and Wireless Limited, Bahrain, that on the 22nd November 1936 at 1538 G.M.T. on a v.ave length of 36 metres the Danish Steamship Henning Marsk used her wireless installation while lying in Bahrain Harbour (off Sitrah). Tne follov.ing message was sent : Message No. 1 Henning Marsk to OXZ (Lugby Radio in Denmark ) words 12 dated time 1505 (addressed to Mersk KBH) which read 'Ankom Sandag Morgen Bunkers 175 Forventer Afsejling Mandag eftermiddag - HenningMarsk.' KBH is the sign for Copenhagen. In this connection may I invite your attention to my letter No. C/50S-10/1 dated the 3th May 1934. ^ C VIN Y.ould you please warn all tankers or other ships coming to Baiirain that use of v»ireless telegraphy by ships in the Bahrain territorial waters is not permitted. Y&gt;urs faithfully. &lt; ^ Captainj ior Political Agent, Bahrain.11' 1^/ NO.C/88-10/1. Political Agency, Bahrain, tiie 2nd February 1937. To Ihe Qiief Iiocai Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, B A fl H A I N . Dear bir, h 6 ^ yS II Please refer to the correspondence ending with my letter No• C/5^&gt;'»10/1 dated the 16th January 1937, • 1 -- # ' riie Bahrain Government state that there is no object.or to the corrections in question which have been noted in the p &gt; original description. They PQ lnf out that apparently the plan is not corrected to correspond to the description. The eighth course is exactly the same length as in the original plan, ihile it should have been 92,9 feet shorter. This will change to some extent tne position of all the succeeding courses. Yours faithfully, Captain, For Political Agent, Bahrain,No»^/83'»10/l« Poiiticai Agency, Bahrain, the 2nd February 1.337. To The Adviser to the Bahrain Government, Memorandam . T vk O bound seta or iank lables as supplied' to the Bahrain Petroleum ^ompany Limited by Messrs B. &amp; R. Redwood of London are enclosed, with the request that you retain one set ana pass the other to the wtate Engineer to the Bahrain Government. 2. Please acknowledge receipt. Captain, For Political Agent, Bahrain.INo.C/90-10/1t Political Banrain, the Snd February 1937. To The Chief ijocal Representative, The Bahrain Petraleam Company Limited, 3 A il R I M . Dear bir, I acknowledge with many thaaks the receipt o''f tv.o sets of Tank Tables forwar ed wiCh your letter No.PA-SI dated trie 20th January 1937^ which have been transmitted to the Adviser and the btate Engineer to the Bahrain Government respectively* Yours faithfully, — ' Captain, For Political A*ent, Bahrain,vcy .VTUk So.C/al-10 /i. PoiltIcai Agency, Bahrain, the 2nd February 1937. To The Chief ijocai he pre s en t at ive, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, bahraim . Dear blr, 1*111 With refe^ehce to the correspondence ending with my letter Bo.0/76-10/1 dated the 27th January 1937, the Bahrain Government enquire whether you would be so good as to give them one more copy of aerial map of Bahrain. Yours faithfully. Captain, For Political Agent, Bahrain. II | I Comldentlal, Mo. C/96-10/ lw Political Agency, Bahrain, the 2rd February iBg?. The Officer-in-Charge, Cable and V/lrexe-ss Limited, Bahrain. Dear Sir. A fa Please refer to ^our i/i dated the 9th Deceaiber 1936. • It is presumed that in accordance with Article 13 oi the International Teleconuifunication Convention, Madrid, 1932, you have reported the occurrence to the Manager, Persian Guif. : for Political Agent, Bahrain. Captain,I An extract from The 'Iraq Times of the 3rd February 1937. The California and i'exas Oil Company is reckoning on spending £750,000 for the first year or two placing petrol from Bahrain on the Indian market. This statement was made by Mr. Howard M. Herron, President of the Company, who has arrived in Bombay from Bahrain. The new refinery at Bahrain is expected to be in operation in August with an output of 12,500 barrels of petrol daily (this will be in addition to the present export of crude oil, estimated at 300,000 barrels monthly). Arrangements for selling petrol throughout India have already been completed in conjunction with the Texas Company of India, Limited, which has been marketing lubricating oils in India for some years.| . -U ' CONFIDENTIAL. No. I2b-B of 1937. The Hon'ble the Political Eesident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to 1. His Majesty^ Secretary of State for India, London. 2. The Poreign Secretary to tfte Governrnent of India, New Delhi. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents /^/ j M British Comulate-General, BTTSHIRE. Dated ..XQ. 3 .7.• Reference to previous correspondence: Description o Name and Date. tiff 35xpresa letter No.g/65-10/1 dated the 22nd January 1937 from the Political Agent, Bahrain. Subject. mm mit oil Copy forwarded, with com Agent, Bahrsa. n, 1 o aliments, to the Political information.X /(/ DURRANI'S PRESS CU tTIMGS St. Andrew's House, 32 to 34 Holborn Viaduct, and 3 St. Andrew Street, Holborn Circus, E.C.I. Telephone; CENTRAL 3149 (Two Lines). Morning Post 15 Tudor Street, E.C.4. Cutting from issue dated J BAHREIN OIL FOR INDIA (From Our Own Correspondent) BOMBAY, Jan. 25. The California and Texas Oil Company is reckoning on spending a crore of rupees (£750,000) for the first year or two plac- ing petrol from Bahrein (Persian Gulf) on the Indian market. This statement was made by Mr. Howard M. Herron, President of the Company, who has now arrived in Bom bay from Bahrein. A new refinery at Bahrein is expected to be in operation in August with an output of 12,500 barrels of petrol daily Arrangements for selling petrol throughout India have already been completed in conjunction with the Texas Company of India, Ltd., which has been marketing lubricating oils in this country for some years.The Bahrein Petroleum Company limited hi No. PA-70 Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, v V ' February 10, 1937 l V till. I^ (A X }1 , His Britannic Majesty's Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir: II Reference your letter No. G/91-10/1 dated February 2, 1937, inquiring whether w6 could spare one more copy of the aerial map of Bahrein: Although we do not have any extra copies of this map in our file, we are forwarding your request to our principals and will advise you in due course. Yours very truly. G. W. R. SMITH, Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED.The Bahrein Petroleum Company limited No. PA-73 Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, February 11, 1937. His Britannic Majesty's Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir; A Reference your confidential letter No. c /87-10/l of 2nd February, 1937, relative to the complaint received by your office from The Cable &amp; Wireless Limited, Bahrein, that the Danish Tankship 'Henning Maersk' used her wireless while lying in Bahrein Haroor (off Sitra) on 22nd November, 1936: The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited wish me to inform you that they are again taking steps to warn all tankers or other ships coming to Bahrein that use of wireless telegraphy by ships while lying in anchorage in this port is not permitted. Yours very truly. G. 1. R. SMITH, Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED..wTIAk* Ilo.^/x77-10/l# Political Agency, Bahrain, the Snd March 19S7, To The Adviser to the Bahrain u overnment, , ^ JS^mrancug, Reference your mefflorandua No.1207-20 dated the 84th January 13?7, The Chief Local Representative of the Bahrain Petroleum Company iiijait*- d, to whom the matter was referred, informs me that the Company have no extra copies of the map, but that they are forwarding m request for one spare copy to their principals. Captain, For Political Agent, Bahrain,No•C/17S-10/1• Political Agency, Bahrain, the 5th March 1937. •Io The Director of Customs and Port Officer, 3i.HEi-.IBi. Memoranoum, Reference your laeajorandum Ho•PA/HI./31/4S7 dated tne 17th February 1-337, 2. I should be most grateful if,in addition to the information you have so kindly supplied, you could give me further particulars as to the nature and quantity of the various shipments* e Captain, For Political Agent, Bahrain.to believe that this advance may be resumed. * That is why the independence of the small Central European countries is of vital interest to Great Britain. That is why the British Government, who have made no secret of anti-Bolshevist feelings, have decided to support the French-Russian- Little-Entente alliance against Germany. The more so as Russia is bound by her pre-occupation with Germany in the West and Japan in the East, and is thus rendered harmless from the British point of view. Russia is isolated to-day by a row 01 buffer States from the three neighbouring Great Powers—from Germany oy Poland and Lithuania, from the Indian Empire by Afghanistan and Tibet, and from Japan by Manchukuo and Northern China. Germany is isolated from Asia by the small Central European and Balkan States British policy will undoubtedly strive to maintain this state of affairs as long as possible by peaceful methods, but in the case of a war also by armed intervention. This can be learned by listening to the military experts. . ^ ^ And it shows why a war m Central Europe must inevitably become a world war. ■ DURRANI 'S PRESS CUTTINGS St. Andrew's House, 32 to 34 Hoiborn Viaduot, and 3 St. Andrew Street, Hoi born Circus, E.C.I. Telephone: CENTRAL 3149 (Two Linbs). Evening Standard 47 Shoe Lane, E.C .4. ^ Cutting from issue dated OIL IS THE KEY TO BRITAIN'S INTEREST IN THE DANUBE 1 Germany's Bagdad Dream Not Yet Forgotten From Our Vienna Correspondent JJESPITE the shadows cast on world peace by the Spanish civil war, the colonial expansion of Italy in Africa, and the war preparations in the Far East, Central Europe still enjoys the melancholy privilege of being the principal danger spot in Europe. According to recent statistics of the League of Nations, the regular armies of the European countries have increased from 3,600,000 to 4,800,000 during the last five years. In 1914 the European armies totalled 4.600,000 men. In the Central European countries, how ever, a great number of well-equipped semi- military formations supplement the regular armies. Therefore it can be fairly stated that in Central Europe the number of potential combatants has been doubled in compari son with the years preceding the Great War GENERALS IN COMMAND AGAIN Increasing tension and the formation of military alliances have led to a feverish diplomatic activity. Dictators, monarchs, premiers and foreign ministers are travelling more than ever before, but are revealing almost nothing to the public. It is generally assumed that 18 years after the most devastating war in history, a period has once more arrived when generals have the word. Many Britons may ask why the fate of Austria, Czechoslovakia and other small Danubian countries is causing so much excitement in the Foreign Ministries of the Powers. An interesting answer can be found by studying the lectures and treatises of Cen tral European military experts like the Austrian Minister of Interior, Col. Edmund Glaise von Horstenau, who represented the Austrian General Staff at German head quarters during the war and is now said to be representing the German General btalt and the Pan-German idea within the Aus trian Government, or Col. Emanuel Mora- vec professor of the Military College in Prague, who is a representative of the French-Russian-Little Entente alliance. INDEPENDENCE—AND WHY From a military point of view, it seems to the Viennese that none of the European countries is more interested in the ques tion of control in the Danube basin than is Great Britain. , For Britain, it is essential that me Danube countries should remain indepen dent, and that neither Russia nor Germany shall win domination in this part ot me British Dominions are scattered round the world At present Britain safeguards at sea her connections between the British Isles and the Empire. But modern strategy has to take account not only of fleets and armies but also of air forces. Airplanes have revolutionised the technique of war, much as horses revolu tionised warfare in ancient times. Introduction of horses meant the ' motorisation' of armies of old. The ' fuel' for horses grew on the steppes. The armies of nomadic peoples, therefore, operated chiefly in areas with good pastur age. The vast plains of Asia, Russia and of the Hungarian part of the Danube Basin were an excellent basis and supply of 'fuel' for Mongolian cavalry HAMBURG TO BASRA What these plains were for the mounted armies of ancient and medieval times, the oil fields of Rumania, Irak and Persia are to-day for the armies of the air. Airplanes can be fuelled amply, even without any complicated refineries, at the spots where oil is found or at airfields located along the oillines. On the so-called 'transversal' Euro pean-Asian axis, which measures 4000 kilo metres from Hamburg to Basra on the Persian Gulf, there are the two most powerful air bases of the old world—the oil fields of Rumania and Mosul. The Rumanian oilfield is 1300 kilometres distant from the great German air bases. The Mosul field is 1800 kilometres distant from the Rumanian bases From Mosul it is only about 800 kilo metres to Basra. British interests require the Russians to ne occupied in the West as well as in the East, in order that they should be unable to attempt an expansion to the South, where they are immediate neighbours of Rumania, and are not far from Mosul On the other hand. Great Britain opposes German expansion in Central Europe, because by an Austro-German union or the overthrow of Czechoslovakia, the Germans would be within 300 kilometres of the Rumanian oilfields. The Berlin-Bagdad plans of pre-war Germany for an advance along the 'trans versal Eurasian axis ' were held up by the Great War for more than 20 years. British military experts, however, seemCONFIDENTIAL. // No. 195-3 of 1937. The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to 1. The foreign Secretary to the Government of India, New Delhi. 2. The Political Agent, Bahrain -V and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents (£$. 3^ British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated...12.th..5 , «hr.u^.cy..lii37. Reference to previous correspondence y India Office Printed letter No.7756/36 of 4th November 1936. Description o Name and Date. Political Resident's telegram No,198 of 12th February 1937. Subject. Bahrain Additional Area Oil Negotiations. 1 v(H GOVERNMENT OF BAHRAIN. : / 0 0 j /6./L.D./1355. Bahrain, ^nulhaj , 1355. m\ 2-MAR. 1937 J /. ^ March, To His Britannic Ivlajesty's Political Agent, Bahrain. /h' Reference your letter Kb:C/558-10/l. dated the 22nd December 1936, the period, of the prodlamation, 30 days, has now expired and no claims have been received regarding the areas in question, the pieces can therefore be reserved for the Company. They will be registered as part of the Company's area in the Land Department. The Elan is dated 15th Thul Qada, 1355. I have the honour to be, Sir, your most obedient servant, V Adviser, Government of Bahrain.9 ■ % ■ ..I The Bahrein Petroleum Company limited His Britannic Majesty^ Political Agent Manama, Bahrein Island Dear Sir: An oil concession covering the so-called Additional Area, comprising all of the territories under the dominion of His Excellency, the Shaikh of Bahrein (including territorial waters), other than those embraced in the present Mining Lease held by my Company, has been the subject of discussion and negotiations on a number of occasions between His Excellency, acting through his Advisers, and my Company, The last negotiations on this subject were conducted in London during the period between July and October of last year through Mr. C. Dalrymple Belgrave, on behalf of the Shaikh, and Mr. H. R. Ballantyne on behalf of the Company. During most of that period His Excellency was in England and the negotiations were carried on, of course, with the knowledge and consent of the Shaikh and His Majesty^ Government. As no final agreement was reached before Mr. Belgrave♦ s departure from England, it was understood that negotiations were to be continued here in Bahrein, and as I have mentioned to you in several interviews during the past few months, my Company are desirous of re suming such negotiations. The position of ray Company in this matter has been explained fully to His Excellency the Shaikh through his Advisers. My Company believe that for many reasons they are entitled to preferential treat ment in respect of the whole of the Additional Area. His Excellency has recognized that my Company are entitled to this preferential treat ment, At the beginning of the negotiations in London last summer, he assured the Company that he wishes them to have the rest of his ter ritory to deal with. I need not remind His Excellency that when others declined to take the risk of prospecting for oil here in Bahrein, my Company accepted that risk and have been successful in developing oil in commercial quan- rJ^ 68 ' 'k* 16 result that today Bahrein is again enjoying prosperity. e Company have fulfilled all of their obligations and have incurred a ieavy investment in their developments here - developments carried on at a much more rapid pace than required by the Company^ obligations under the present concession. These developments include not only com- P e e facilities of a producing oil field but a modern refinery now in J*™** 0tCQin P ;LQtion » the opening of a seaway to within three miles 'itra, and the installation of five submarine loading lines. Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf f I V ouoiH3 H. B. M.'s P. A. - 2 - March 4, 1937. May I also remind His Excellency that in addition to ful filling loyally all of their obligations, my Company as far back as 1933, in deference to the wishes of His Excellency and his Advisers, suspended their then existing application for a concession over the Additional Area, a step which lost the Company the services of a valu able adviser on local affairs. My Company are reluctant to believe that the Shaikh wishes to disregard his previous recognition of the preferential treatment to which t&amp; Company are entitled. Nevertheless, if the Company must con tinue to bargain for the Additional Area, they are prepared to do so, and should this be necessary the Company believe they are justified in assuming that, at the very least, they will be afforded equal oppor tunities, with respect to any competitors, as to the manner and extent of such bargaining. In other words, my Company, having already done so much for Bahrein, should have an opportunity of fair bargaining with any others who may appear interested in acquiring the Additional Area, The Company cannot believe that they are faced with the juxtaposition of a rival concern who would appear to have no claim whatever to be con sidered in preference to the Company, I am sending you this letter in triplicate in order to facilitate your bringing it to the notice of the Shaikh and his Advisers, My Company would appreciate it very much if you would arrange to do this as soon as possible so that negotiations may be resumed without further delay, and I hope, with successful results. I am also sending two copies of this letter to Mr, Ballantyne in London, Yours very truly. Resident Manager THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED turn j JCONFIDENTIAL. No. G/181-10/1. The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to :■ The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, at Bahrain, and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document (s). Hi The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian G-tjlf. Dated.... .g.th. .Mavoh. .1937 „. if i Reference to previ|us correspondence: / Bushire printed letter No. 195-3 dated 12th February 1937, Description o Name and Date. m &gt;/ 4 J ' Letter dated 4th March 1937 from the Resident Manager, The ^Bahrein Fttr.ileum Company Limited, Bahrain* J U ^ jt- \ ^ Subject. Ba lira in Oil - Additional area.('A' The Bahrein petroleum company limited Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, No.FA-109 March 5, 1937. His Britannic Majesty's Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir: Please refer to your letter Wo.C/88 -io /l regarding a discrepancy in our maps as submitted for refinery reservation, parcels 1 to 6 inclusive: We have again checked all our surveys and computations and find them to be correct. We also find that the map in our file is correct and agrees with the computations. It would, there fore, appear that through some oversight one of the old and incorrect maps was furnished you with our last request. The accompanying three prints are correct and identical with those in our file. In order to identify this map further we have noted on it that this print supersedes all others to date. This should clear up all confusion with regard to this matter. Yours very truly. a. W. R. SMITH Chief Local Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLSTM COMPANY LIMITSDTelegram 'From H.M(s. Secretary of State for Inaia, Lonaoa, Government ol India, Foreign and Political Department, New Delhi, lor Political Resident. Repeated Political Agent, Bahrain. No. 802. Dated Sth (received 9th ) March 1957. four telegram of 7th Ma,rch No. T-ll. Additional ^re&lt;j&lt;. I agree. - iietaxandum. y handed to the U.S. to P-.i-}ik g nfi dt.-nti.frtX. Ho* 0/196- Political v., gency, Bahrain, the 13th March 19S7 The Ac:viser to the Bahrain Government, B A H ft A I M mo-:uaum: Reference year letter No. 31.7/12/LD dated the gist January 19S7# |/ IM ' 2# The Chief Local Representative, Bahraia Petroleum Company, states onat he has -gain checked all his surveys and computations and inds them to oe correct. . iow- ever, thinks that through some oversight one of the old and incorrect maps was furnished and I forward a correct map (now enclosed) vailch supersedes t,lx others and should, thinks, clear up all confusion. 2. It is requested that the ccompanying map may be checked. Captain, For Political /.gent, BahrainNo. C/197-10/1 Political Bahrain, the li oh March 195'J To The Chief Local .Representative, The Bahrain Pi trolcua Company Iiimited, ia ^ ti it jj 1 JM , Dear Sir, / With reference to your letter No. PA- 751 dated the 5th jDeceaioer 1936, the Government issued on th -.8th January 1957 th usual notice (calling upon any person who may have any claim in connection vdtii a trans fer of land to notify it within GO days) in respect of this additional reservation of land for the Company* s refinery area, 2. The period of thirty days has xpired and the Bahrain Government state that no claims were received and that the pieces oi land required by your Company «ill be registered as part of their area in the Land Department of the Bahrcin Government. Yours faithfully, Qc ^ Captain, For Political Agent, Bahrain., S D f 'Vs } 86/14 fnlegrnn Q *** Froffi Secretary of State for India, Lonaon. To Political R cb iaent, at Bahrain. Copy toy air mail to Government Of India, Hew Delhi. No.^54 TXited 5th March received 6th Mr^ch 193''. AW Tom 1 ' telegrara ^To. 1^8 of ^ebrnary 12th. I agree that in all tne circnnr tancess Shaikh ■would probably be &gt;vi8e to gi^e Tip the inea of dividing unallotted area and to let whole area be corapetea for by both companies but I consider this is for him to decide in his ov/n time on the basis oi information which Belgrave has given to him regarding attitude of companies and I do not think we should press him to take any cec is ion, If however -Shaikh asks for advice I agree that he should be given it on the lines you suggest. 2, Your paragraph Ko.' 7 . I agree as to of channel^negotiaMons. If Bahrain Petroleum Company are pressing to continue negotiations I suggest Loch should merely inform Shaika arm at same time communicate to him decision regarding channel which of course follows logically on procedure adopted in London. 31CRlfARY OF ST A* 3 701 (Copy given to ?.Bahrain) k */*' fm § ^CONFIDENTIAL. LA' ■; 1 J /ri No. C/24 of 1937. 'W ' r The Hon ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to 1. His Tajesty's Secretary of State for India, London. 2. The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, Mew Delhi. 3. The Political Agent, Bahrain. / and has the honour to transmit to him a copj of the undermentioned documents (s). 1 Office of the Political Resident in the Persian (lulf, lamp, Bahra in. mhs \ Dated... . Ma-r-e-h- Reference to previous correspondence Bjt' : jS I. J h Description o Name and Date. Subject, A ^ (l)&amp; Oonly, a ^ I !• Letter dated 4tli Marcii 1937 from the Resident Manager, The Banrain Petroleum Company Ltd., Bahrain. Bahrain Oil - Additional area. o(2) (3) only. 2. Political Resident♦ s telegram No.T/ll ®f 7th March 19. s/ :C Telegram Q. From Political Agent, Bahrain. To Government of India, Foreign and Political Department, Few Delhi. No. 66. Dated 16th March 1937. Loch to Fowle. hi«1 May I take action on Secretary of State for India's telegram ITo. 802 March 8th. Additional Area? If so please telegraph one word ACTION. - Political.X \ r: Copy. . I 5 ' . P-A. I understand from an ordinary source that ZUBARAH, the ownership of which remained unsettled since the battle 0 f zubarah which was fought about 70 years ago, is going to be the subject matter of a tensible feeling between the A1 Khaiifahs and A1 Thani. A1 Khalifahs think that the %Fae . tract belongs to Bahrain whereas on account of favourable physical situation of the place, A1 Thani thinks that it is a part of Qatar territory. Since the land is unpopulated it remained without being attractive to any side so far. But owing to the development of petroleum, Zubarah has become a place of interest and Shaikh Hamad bin Qasem A1 Thani has started populating ±t the tract with Qatat subjects in order to ensure the Ksdt claim of ownership of the land. M.H.-13-3-37. A.C.S.-13-3. Copy ofj^ Oil File.pi No. C/216/10-1 The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to:—- The Advisor5 Bahrain lovernnrlit5 IMirain. and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document (s). The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gcli 1 . Dated................. .f. Reference to previous correspondence : Description o Name and Date. Subject, v Letter 1*0,0/215/10-1 dated 19tli n-arch 1937 to His Excellency Shaikh Sir Henad bin ' Isa A3. iQialifah, K.C.I.rf. C»3, X« . i^ular 01,' i Tt&gt;n'7 t» - 5 Hulor oi' Balirain ialiPftin hi'alticnal Area.Uo. C/S17-10/1 Political Agency, Bahrain, the 19th Mrrch 19S7. The Resident Manager, She Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, B A H B A I N. Dear Sir A? With reference to your let:er dated the 4th March 1957, I writ© to inform you that there is no objection to your Company carrying on negotiations direct with the Adviser to the Bahrain GoTernment for an oil concession covering the Bahrain additional area, that is to say, 'all the territory under the dominion of His Excellency Shaikh Sir Hamad bin *Isa Al Khalifah, (including territorial \?aters) ? other than that which was selected by your Company under the terms of their present concession, provided that the Political Agent is kept fully and without delay informed by you of all that takes place, v S. A similar comEinication has been made to Petroleum Concessions Limited. 3* I have informed the Bahrain Government of the above comaainication. Yours faithfully. Lieut-Colonel, Political Agent, Bahrain,Political Agency, Bahrain, the 13th March 1337 Ho. C/218-10/1 The Manager, Petroleum Concessions Limited, BAHRAIN - Dear Sir, With reference to Mr, Longrigg*s letter'No. P.C.26/197 dated the 29th October 1338, I write to inform you that there is no objection to your Company carrying on negotiations with the Adviser to the Bahrain Government for an oil concession covering the Bahrain additional area, that is to say, all the territory under the dominion of His Excellency Shaikh Sir Hamad bin 'Isa A1 Khalifah, K.C.I.E., G.S.I., (including territorial waters), other than that area which was selected by The Bahrain Petroleum Company under the terms of their present concession, provided that the Political Agent is kept fully and without delay informed by you of all that ttikes place. S. A simiiar communication has been made to The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited. S# I have informed the Bahrain Government of the above conmunication. Yours faithfully. Lieut-Colonel, Political Agent, Bahrain.The Town Clerk (Mr, F. J. opar- read a letter from the Federation of Ratepayers' Associations strenuously opposing the present scheme as a luxury one, and urging that the provision of a public abattoir and a sanatorium foi tuberculosis were of more consequence than the provision of amusements ana luxuries for trippers. , ^ Councillor C. F. Langmaid asked as the provision of a swimming pool in tne Lumps Fort scheme was one of tne principal points of contention whether that point could be considered apart from the remainder of the scheme. The Lord Mayor (who is Chairman the Beach, Piers and Publicity Com mittee), said he did not see fit to with draw that part of it. Councillor Langmaid then moved an amendment referring the consideration of the scheme to the special meeting the Council to be held sh o rtl y ^ £° n ' sider the finance estimates for He pointed out that there was a net loss of £4,115 on the Hilsea pool last year and he could not conceive that a pool near the seafront would be a paying proposition. He also urged the Council to consider the scheme in relation to the present financial situation. Highly Speculative Councillor H. G. Cook seconded and described the scheme as highly specula tive, depending on weather conditions. The Council should say what the rate should be and limit the various com mittees accordingly. Councillor A. J. Pearson, supporting the amendment, estimated the cost of schemes under consideration by the Council in the region of £2,750,000, and most of them were social necessities. He was'in favour of all those schemes, but he thought the Finance Committee should map out a plan of priority spread ing over a period of five, six, or seven scheme wortny 01 WgmmgggtM th City. If the Council did not accepy^ scheme what would they do bu the 1 They might lay out a an \ would remind the ^ d ^ Council would IV area of 14 acres and the ooun of . t soon spend £100,000, an , cin jy would be non -revenue P r ?^ c Xe scheme This was a bold comprehensi and there had been no criticism except on financial matters. adv an- He believed ^^the defeTopment of tage to the people as the aeveiop d Southsea Common had been- H e a the Council to consider the s iik e broad, sportsmanlike and ^s^^rt manner; if they refused it Lumps might become nothing more th an some , thing to jeer at. Sir esti- Finance Committee had P ut th ^ The mates on the lowest possible basis. Th Finance Committee was soing throug the capital expenditure already shadowed and passed the Counci , and he was sure that the Council would not oppose any scheme which they con sidered necessary, even if it meant an increased rate. He urged the Council to go on with the Lumps Fort scheme. Only the Deputy Lord Mayor, Alder man Rice, and Councillors Langmam, Wright, Juniper and Cook voted for the amendment, which was lost by 43 votes to six, and the division on the Finance Committee's recommendation was carried by 34 votes to 14. For: Aldermen Billing, Sir Harold Pink, Porter, Perkins, Dashwood, Corbin, Bosworth Wright, Councillors Allaway, Lewis, Blake, Pugsley, Andrews, Harri son, Stapleford, Whiting, Kille, Mrs Ramsden, E. Jones, Willson, Clifton, Lane, Seal, Collins, J. Privett, Pearson, Prince, Fookes, Prewer. O'Rorke, Pratt, Clements, Johnson, Wallis, and Gill. Against: Alderman Rice, Councillors Lay, Langmaid, Mahoney, West, Shar- Wrie-ht. Juniper, Cook, Griffiths,-—— —-— ^ DURRANI'S PRESS CUTTINGS St. Andrew's House, 32 to 34 Holborn Viaduct, and 3 St. Andrew Street, Holborn Circus, E.C.I. Telephone; CENTRAL 3149 (Two Lines). Cutting f^om the . Dated February j^rO. 1937 Address of Journal. CITY OPINION ON BAHREIN DEVELOPMENTS Position Facing California Standard and Texas (From Our City w T he importance which Bahrein developments are assuming as a possible disturbance to the Balance of Power ' in the international oil industry is shown by the inclusion of a special chapter on this subject in the latest ' Eeference Book of Oil Market Com panies,' issued annually by a leading firm of London Stock Exchange jobbers in oil shares. It will be recalled that Sir John Cargill, Bart., chairman of tlie Biirmali Oil Conipany, lias refeired at more than one of the company's annual meetings to the threat of large new oil imports into India and spoke last year particularly of new sources of production in the East. He reiterated the Burmah Company's justifiable view that indigenous produc tion has the first call on the India market, and sug'- o-ested that any threat to the maintenance of this market might force Burmah production into export, ^ 1 •uaAiS ^ou P 0 - 10 ^' 8 '' f im* M o,o M , a -OOT? t 'aonpojd o! '(0^Ai.id) mi aauaxsio^I an 'ANVdwoD no vNuaawwoD ^ ■ Z - 3 -IA'Ml '8U-9U ,S » U83 V Au?d«o 3 '-pn 'snog ^uepjo! P 3 H ddn S e SNOLLVHXSIOHH AMVdWOO A\HNI ^uiaq^ jo uot^u^dxa euios 9A^ 1 im o^'oi sbu ux P^ abs Suxaq X ? s: uL^7^l i JO , 0 , n v ,,^, jo^ ooo;osi g ™ J 0Il g T Ba gsaooid uoi^uaSojpAH uiB^uxniff -P' 0^ uodn pasBq SS ® 00J Tr •; i , nD o.id oifi uo enu0A0.i jo Xo-x^d jo suo L000 0 |J 1 0xp^H ssox 0^ S0UTK -ioj Axxn ,p nr -qooj n« 0a. U01U TO'I ^ ox 6X80^ ^ u[&lt;)t i Av xuoaj AXFnxu0A0 0Xq^ . p e A o,id U00q 'UOl^UUOJUl ejl 0STAVJ01IXO IO 88000118 X0X XOVI 08no H oqt PPIDURRANI'S PRESS CUTTINGS St. Andrew's House, 32 to 34 Holborn Viaduct, and' 3 St. Andrew Street, Holborn Circus, E.C.I. Telephone: CENTRAL 3149 ( Two Lines). Cutting fr™ the — Dated February 2 ,0. Address of Journal 1937 CITY OPINION ON BAHREIN DEVELOPMENTS /} vVW Position Facing California Standard and Texas {From Our City Correspondent) 'n\v The importance which Bahrein developments are assuming as a possible disturbance to the ' Balance of Power '' in the international oil industry is shown by the inclusion of a special chapter on this subject in the latest &lt;£ Eeference Book of Oil Market Com panies,' issued annually by a leading firm of London Stock Exchange jobbers in oil shares. It will be recalled that Sir John Cargill, Bart., chairman of the Burmah Oil Company, has referred at more than one of the company's annual meetings to the threat of large new oil imports into India, and spoke last year particularly of new sources of production in the East. He reiterated the Burmah Company's justifiable view that indigenous produc tion has the first call on the India market, and sug gested that any threat to the maintenance of this market might force Burmah production into export, with corresponding disturbance to other markets. It was evident at the time that Bahrein was the new field to which Sir John referred. Our Stock Exchange friends have returned to the subject because they believe the further progress of Bahrein exploitation, and the possibilities opened up thereby, are becoming a general topic of conversation among oil shareholders—particularly, of course, those in the Burmah Company itself. This belief is undoubtedly justified as far as the more substantial and far-sighted investors in oil com panies are concerned, and Bahrein i^ an even more important topic for those actually engaged in inter national oil trade. The position, as summarised in the Eeference Book, may therefore be quoted in full, and is as follows : — ' (1) The groups controlling the Bahrein field con sist of the Standard Oil Company of California and the Texas Corporation, both of whom control very important interests in the United States, which, in the aggregate, are substantially more valuable than their interests in Bahrein. These companies have had exnerience in the oil industry over a great many years, and it is, therefore, not likely that their policy in Bahrein will be such as to react against their enormous interests in the United States. They no doubt fully realise the futility of trying to force unwanted oil upon the market. 44 (2) The company controlling the production and distribution of the Bahrein production is an amalgamation of producing fields in Bahrein, originally owned by the Standard Oil Company of California, and the marketing organisation in the Orient, originally owned by the Texas Corporation. (3) Caltex, the company in question, therefore already has an outlet for substantial quantities of petroleum products, and although it is true that these outlets in the past have been supplied from the United States, in a great many cases they can be more economically supplied from Bahrein. ^ (4) Consumption is rapidly increasing in the United States. The Standard Oil Cbmpany of Cali fornia and the Texas Corporation are two of the biggest producers and distributors in the United States. There is little or no surplus apparent in the United States, so that reasonably firm conditions exist there. These companies might take a very serious risk of weakening or destroying these satis factory conditions in the United States if, by unduly forcing Bahrein oil upon the market, they create a competitive condition seriously detrimental to all those companies operating in the Orient. It would appear that if such conditions were forced upon the market their effect would be felt also in the United States, and Caltex would have to weigh up the ad vantage of increasing production in Bahrein with the danger to the existing structure in the United States. ' (5) Should the foregoing not be the effect of intense competition in the Eastern markets, it can hardly be assumed that for any length of time the parents of the Caltex Company would look with favour upon selling oil at low prices in the Orient which could be as easily sold elsewhere at better prices.' The authors of this summary of the situation disclaim any attempt at prophecy, but place the facts of the case, as they see them, before the public as an assistance in the formation of conclusions as to likely developments in the Eastern markets. They point out that, without careful study, the subject is one providing material which can easily be misused. Needless to say, the position, as outlined in the Reference Book, is put forward merely as a Stock Exchange view, for the use of investors. The firm producing it, however, is exceptionally well informed on oil matters, and, in view of its business, must have wide and influential connections in the industry. These considerations invest the chapter on Bahrein with an interest which it might not possess if it came from a less important quarter.supply it. . . Mr. Hardie : Is it not a fact that the technical in formation is there, and that its commercial value has been determined? Otherwise the I.C.I. men are all fools. But they are not. Mr. Hardie asked the Secretary for Mines the loss of revenue on the production of 150,000 tons of petrol at Billingham hydrogenation process based upon the 8d. per gallon on imported petrol? Capt. Crookshank: Assuming approximately 300 gallons of motor spirit to the ton, the import tax of 8d. a gallon on 150,000 tons of imported motor spirit would realise about &lt;£1,500,000. Mr. Hftrdie : Does the Minister realise from the figures he has given that for every miner taken on to' produce coal, for every shilling Avhich is thus being saved in unemployment pay, 12s. has to go to the i.o.i. ? That is what those figures mean, and why cannot we have some explanation of them? NEW COMPANY REGISTRATIONS Supplied by Messrs. Jordan &amp; Sons, Ltd., Company Registration Agents, 116-118, Chancery Lane, W.C.2. COMMERFINA OIL COMPANY, LTD. Registered February 10th (private), to produce, import refine, and distribute petroleum and its products. Nominal capital: £100. Directors and registered offices not given. -rrtDURRANI'S PRESS CUTTINGI St. Andrew's House, 32 to 34 Holborn Viaduct, and 3 St. Andrew Street, Holborn Cireus, E.C.l. Telephone; CENTRAL 3149 (Two Lines). Great Britain and the East 1 i/o Strand, W.C .2. Cutting from issue dated. \!o^ reat Britain and the East^ February 11, 1937. U M &gt; Selections from 'Oriente Moderno' , herewith institute a summary of a selection from notable Italian monthly contemporary m the organ of L'Instituto per L'Oriente, founded ncourage a scientific study of the culture, politics economics of the Muslim world, he Journal, reminiscent of the war-time British •ial' Review of the Foreign Press,' is composed of e parts. Part I consists of an article; Part II ews by selected cuttings, the grand lines of the tical situation and provides verbatim texts of docu- its; Part III consists of carefully selected passages ti the Italian, English, French and vernacular Press. •rgia. art 1 of the current issue constitutes a close study he still-bom Constitution of Democratic Georgia, a je that, prior to its absorption by the U.S.S.R., had finned its Social Democratic Constitution (February 1921) and had applied for admission to the League Nations (1920). ine article is written by the Presi- t of the Institution, SE. cav. di. GR: CR: Amedeo innini, Senatore. le summarises the history of Georgia—always a sage-way between Asia and Europe, always a small te seeking outside support from nearby strong inies. In ancient times. Christian and Western of Iture, she leant upon Byzantium. Then upon :hodox Russia. Of her vassaldom to Russia he tes: ' It does not merely signify Russian expansion- ambitions. To Russian security Georgian defence s contingent. An independent Georgia was an in- Bcient buffer State and a menace to Russian safety.' The Russo-Georgian Treaty of 1783 gave the country onomy. But in 1801 she was annexed, to suffer the issitudes of a frontier province and to dream of ependence and Socialism, more particularly after 50, when national sentiment awoke. From 1890 wards Marxist tendencies were discernible. In 1905 ^olution was repressed. Ine Great War brought hope. German troops were i oured as an offset to the Turks. Georgia- gained 'ependence by the Act of May 15, 1918. She was l Pped of part of her territories by the Russo-Turkisn jaty of Brest-Litovsk, 1918. The Allied victory wred Georgian frontiers. British troops were sub- wted for German. There was talk of a British, even a n Italian mandate. The Act of Independence was ^'ned (March 12, 1919) and Georgia recognised ■Ptember 13) de jure by some Powers, by psrs. ^ Congress for Palestine at Delhi. (' Al-Fath,' No. 526. 3 /12/36.) On the initiative of the Association of the Ulama of Delhi, was held in that city (November 6-9) a Pan-Indian Congress for Palestine; 250 delegates; speeches broadcast; 20,000 at the opening ceremony; special provisions for Muslims; Shaikh Sulaiman an Nadwi elected President. The Mufti Kifayatullah, President of the Association of the Ulama, spoke on Palestine, its sanctity to Muslims and the wrong-doings of England. The resolutions passed included support for Palestine Arabs; appeal to England to avoid disturbance throughout Islam; protest against barbarous repressions, demolition of houses, aerial bombard ment, and so on; an appeal for a Palestine similar in status to Iraq and Syria; denunciation of the Balfour Declaration and British Imperialism in Palestine; an appeal to Indian League of Nations repre sentatives to obtain abolition of the Mandate, and a similar appeal to all Muslim countries to agitate with England and the League to abolish the Balfour Declaration, as being incompatible with Art. XXII of the Covenant; an appeal to intelligent Jews to reflect that British policy rebounded on themselves; in the next world War the enemies of England would treat Jews as they had been treated in Germany; appre ciation of the conduct of the Christian Arabs in Palestine; abstention from the Coronation, and non-co-operation in military matters was recommended. Catholic Mission to Iranian Azerbaijan. ' VOsservatore Romana.' 19/12/36.) An account is detailed of the visit of M. Alcide Marma, Apostolic Delegate in Iran to Azerbaijan. Rizaiyyeh (Urmia) is described as the most important Chaldean centre of all Iran, the seat of an Archbishop with eight priests and three Lazarite Fathers; some seventy villages inhabited wholly or in part by Catholics, forty-two provided with chapels. The Cathedral and relevant building were destroyed during massacres (1918). At Rizaiyyeh is the only Priests' College in Iran (Curator P. Franssen). Khusrawa also suffered from the massacres of 1918, and the earthquake of 1930 destroyed the Church buildings. At Patanur the whole population of 250, excluding two Muslim families, are Catholic. Here the Church was also destroyed (1930). At Tabriz there are a Lazarite missionary and Sisters of Charity. The Catholic population there consists of 260 Armenians and 250 Chaldeans. Catholic Church at Teheran. (' Le Journal de Teheran.' 30/ll/36.&gt; A Catholic Church, constructed at the expense of the Italian Govern ment was opened at Teheran in the presence of the Iranian Minister of Public Instruction and the Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs. Afghanistan. (' II Messaggero.' 11/12/36.) On December 3 the Italian Minister at Kabul, Commr. Pietro Quaroni, presented to the King of Afghanistan his credentials in the name of His Majesty the King of Italy and Emperor of Ethiopia. Oil and Gold inSaoudi Arabia. 26/12/36.) Shaikh Abdullah as-Sulaiman al-Hamdan, Minister of Finance m Saoudi Arabia, has said that the American Standard Oil of California, which has the concession for the petroliferous zone m the territory ot Hasa on the Persian Gulf, has dug new wells and started the construc tion of an oil-pipe which will carry the ojl to a new port near Al-Qatit. It is hoped that the company will soon commence production, which is calculated to give 500 tons of oil every 24 hours. The other company. Petroleum Concessions, Ltd., which recently re ceived a concession for oil research in the western part of the Kingdom ot Saoudi Arabia, has now sent two technical missions to make geological studies of the assigned area—one southward towards Sabwa, Jizan, and the Farasan Islands, the other northwards towards Dhaba, Wejh, and Muweilah. • r f An American syndicate, which enjoys the concession tor me exti ac tion of minerals, has found two veins of gold. The one is found in the locality of Al-Mahd, already worked in ancient days, 400 kms from Jidda. A road has been constructed to that place at a cost of £10,U0U, and it is thought that the lack of water will be obviated, which done, development will begin. The other vein is found near Wejh. Among many other items of interest are included notices of. Arabia. Bd giq l^ 111 os qoiqAv stuaiqojd jo uoijnps oq; ui B0]s'n^ P ^ 11130 ' 'P^PP^ v 2 P U13 P 9 ll u fl UOIUQ Uiouo-n 9A12l l P[no3 yfoqj 11 'ssApsuiQqi SUOUIB SJU31UOSUBJ.ib ^ 103119 runr»A» ' - ,^tti T^ccwTHrvo ^T/Cno BA\pq PIHom. sau^unoo UB^^a ^q; i^q; odoq oq; passaidxo ^l^o^ ^ Punoi ln ^ 11 -^ '^Ijun avou oqi ut o^dppj^d o; Eiu^qtv M ^ mooj ;Bq; psdoq os[^ *11^ ■ IO J 30uo uio^qoid 'saujunoo omj aqi uasMjsq suoijB[ndod J 1 u[ ' SBM jo A jbmx am jo s^nooaqi oj 3n P ^ U ' ° 'uos^i aqx puE Xa^mx uaaAvpq jaqDJBq aqi jo 3ui/Unq qj i ■teVnxui WIBiJuaiod e psq B^Sina m,- ■ - J^K a JL DURRANT'S press cuttings' Tal6t ' hon e: CENTRAL 3149 (Two Likes ). Great Britain and the East 170 Strand, W.C .2. Cutting from issue dated.. AM VJ Mr? /reat Britain and the EasU February 11, 1937. Selections from 'Oriente Moderno' «;&lt;. herewith institute a summary of a selectron from ■ notable Italian monthly contemporary I the organ of L'lnstituto per L'Oriente, founded nrnuraae a scientific study of the culture, politics fl economics of the Muslim world. V Journal, reminiscent of the war-time British H •• Review of the Foreign Press,' is composed of L parts. Part I consists of an article; Part II L W s by selected cuttings, the grand lines of the jitical situation and provides verbatim texts of docu- L. p ar t III consists of carefully selected passages to the Italian, English, French and vernacular Press. jorgia. Part 1 of the current issue constitutes a close study tte still-bom Constitution of Democratic Georgia, a jte that, prior to its absorption by the U.S.S.R., had prmed its Social Democratic Constitution (February 1921) and had applied for admission to the League Nations (1920). ine article is written by the Presi- at of the Institution, SE. cav. di. GR: CR; Amedeo lannini, Senatore. He summarises the history of Georgia—always a issage-way between Asia and Europe, always a small ate seeking outside support from nearby strong mies. In ancient times. Christian and Western of Mture, she leant upon Byzantium. Then upon jthodox Russia. Of her vassaldom to Russia he [ites: ' It does not merely signify Russian expansion- t ambitions. To Russian security Georgian defence as contingent. An independent Georgia was an in- fficient buffer State and a menace to Russian safety.' The Russo-Georgian Treaty of 1783 gave the country itonomy. But in 1801 she was annexed, to suffer the eissitudes of a frontier province and to dream of dependence and Socialism, more particularly after pO, when national sentiment awoke. From 1890 wards Marxist tendencies were discernible. In 1905 ■volution was repressed. The Great War brought hope. German troops were Irhoured as an offset to the Turks. Georgia- gained dependence by the Act of May 15, 1918. She was nppedof part of her territories by the Russo-Turkisn reat y Of Brest-Litovsk, 1918. The Allied victory stored Georgian frontiers. British troops were sub- [tuted for German. There was talk of a British, even an Italian mandate. The Act of Independence was ''tinned (March 12, 1919) and Georgia recognised cptember 13) de jure by some Powers, de by During 1919 resistance was successful against Turk, oishevik and White Russian. In 1920, the Soviet, 0CC[i ' 1 ' ec ' Baku, menaced Georgia, who, defend- 1 herself, had her Sovereignty and Independence wgnised by the U.S.S.R. by the Treaty of May 7. ereupon, the Soviet established at Tiflis a numerous ne a ccn ' le l' or propaganda and espionage. t • ^'R being already installed in Armenia _ ember, 1920), Tiflis was attacked from all sides ^succumbed after a fortnight, reverting to a position ssaiage to its northern neighbour (April, 1921). p a e rt ^ ast in General. Naiioaaii . Sectlorl I- ' The East in General.' after referring to native which u/ . i niove ments in Algeria and Morocco, deals with two matters we 'ere summarise: — Congress for Palestine at Delhi. (' Al-Fath,' No. 526. 3/12/36.) On the initiative of the Association of the Ulama of Delhi, was held in that city (November 6-9) a Pan-Indian Congress for Palestine; 250 delegates; speeches broadcast; 20,000 at the opening ceremony; special provisions for Muslims; Shaikh Sulaiman an Nadwi elected President. The Mufti Kifayatullah, President of the Association of the Ulama, spoke on Palestine, its sanctity to Muslims and the wrong-doings of England. The resolutions passed included support for Palestine Arabs; appeal to England to* avoid disturbance throughout Islam; protest against barbarous repressions, demolition of houses, aerial bombard ment, and so on; an appeal for a Palestine similar in status to Iraq and Syria; denunciation of the Balfour Declaration and British Imperialism in Palestine; an appeal to Indian League of Nations repre sentatives to obtain abolition of the Mandate, and a similar appeal to all Muslim countries to agitate with England and the League to abolish the Balfour Declaration, as being incompatible with Art. XXII of the Covenant; an appeal to intelligent Jews to reflect that British policy rebounded on themselves; in the next world War the enemies of England would treat Jews as they had been treated in Germany; appre ciation of the conduct of the Christian Arabs in Palestine; abstention from the Coronation, and non-co-operation in military matters was recommended. Catholic Mission to Iranian Azerbaijan. ' UOsservatore Romana.' 19/12/36.) An account is detailed of the visit of M. Alcide Marina, Apostolic Delegate in Iran to Azerbaijan. Rizaiyyeh (Urmia) is described as the most important Chaldean centre of all Iran, the seat of an Archbishop with eight priests and three Lazarite Fathers; some seventy villages inhabited wholly or in part by Catholics, forty-two provided with chapels. The Cathedral and relevant building were destroyed during massacres (1918). At Rizaiyyeh is the only Priests' College in Iran (Curator P. Franssen). Khusrawa also suffered from the massacres of 1918, and the earthquake of 1930 destroyed the Church buildings. At Patanur the whole population of 250, excluding two Muslim families^ are Catholic. Here the Church was also destroyed (1930). At Tabriz there are a Lazarite missionary and Sisters of Charity. The Catholic population there consists of 260 Armenians and 250 Chaldeans. Catholic Church at Teheran. (' Le Journal de Teheran.' 30/11/36.) A Catholic Church, constructed at the expense of the Italian Govern ment, was opened at Teheran in the presence of the Iranian Minister of Public Instruction and the Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs. Afghanistan. ('II Messaggero.' 11/12/36.) On December 3 the Italian Minister at Kabul, Commr. Pietro Quaroni, presented to the King of Afghanistan his credentials in the name of His Majesty the King of Italy and Emperor of Ethiopia. Oil and Gold in Saoudi Arabia. (' Al Muqattam.' 26/12/36.) Shaikh Abdullah as-Sulaiman al-Hamdan, Minister of Finance in Saoudi Arabia, has said that the American: Standard Oil of California, which has the concession for the petroliferous zone in the territory of Hasa on the Persian Gulf, has dug new wells and started the construc tion of an oil-pipe whi ch wi ll carry the oil to a new port near Al-QatiL It is hoped that the company will soon commence production, which is calculated to give 500 tons of oil every 24 hours. The other company. Petroleum Concessions, Ltd., which recently re ceived a concession for oil research in the western part of the Kingdom of Saoudi Arabia, has now sent two technical missions to make geological s studies of the assigned area—one southward towards Sabwa, Jizan r j and the Farasan Islands, the other northwards towards Dhaba, Wejh r | and Muweilah. • r ^ An American syndicate, which enjoys the concession tor the extiac tion of minerals, has found two veins of gold. The one is found in the locality of Al-Mahd, already worked in ancient days, 400 kms. from Jidda. A road has been constructed to that place at a cost of £10,000, and it is thought that the lack of water will be obviated, which done, development will begin. The other vein is found near Wejh. Among many other items of interest are included notices of: — Arabia. .. , . , t * 1. A letter from Mazih al-Muayyad al-'azm, fnend of the Imam ot the Yaman, to the Egyptian ' Al-ayyam' denying rumours, re con ditions in the Yaman, spread from Aden by unknown persons'through the medium of the English Press.—' Al-Ayyam ' of Damascus. 4/12/36. 2 xhe journey of Mustafa Wasfi Bey, from Sana to Syria, accom panied by the doctor appointed to the new hospital of Sana, Hashim al-Husaini, of Tripoli, in Syria:—' Al-Ayyam ' of Damascus. 4/12/36. 3. An Arab complaint against Aden Schools for bad teaching, necessitating sending children abroad, and hoping that the Governor, Sir Bernard Reilly, will provide Syrian or Egyptian teachers instead of 'useless' Indians.— 'Al-Fath,' Cairo. No. 526. 3/12/36. 4 The return to Cairo of the Mission of the Egyptian Universities from the Yaman and the Hadhramaut. They were welcomed, Europeans being under suspicion of ulterior motives. Al-Ahram, Cairo. 7/11/36. TT urkcv A notice of the work of the Italian Archaeological Mission in Anatolia round aboutNigde, Kastamuni, and Gok Su Tash Kopm and along the Great Roman military road from Tyan to the Cilician Gates sea.— Italian Press. 18/11/36.m jj put ::0 pop mm Ifcproc psk] lies of ■ak leterr ass B Greece was, inTis^opkdon^^u^ between Turkey and *™ M »-«i rfSUiirarfi fesa,- .., a,, .ui'iri^iflnmng pnd have finished mi — ^ problem once for all. He also hoped that room would be fourm Albania to participate in the new Balkan unity. Finally, Sir Ed war Boyle expressed the hope that the Balkan countries would effect economic arrangements among themselves, if they could not have a Customs Union. ' United and at peace,' he added, ' they can play a big 1 m the solution of problems which so far have baffled mankind.186 THE PETROLEUM TIMES February 6, 1937 Growing Importance of Near and Middle East Oil Intense Activity to Secure Territory for Exploitation—International Co-operation Great Feature of Operations A seeming race for potential oil territory is developing throughout the world. In this history is repeating itself. 4t an earlier stage of the petroleum industry's develop ment it formed a well-defined phase. Then came a period when the international oil groups presumably possessed all the oil-bearing territory they then could handle, or perhaps, to put it more accurately, when their efforts were nerforce concentrated mainly on. a fight for markets to provide outlets for the oil then in sight. The day of any degree of partnership—even if only bygentlemen's agreements '—had not then arrived. With the uses and demand for oil ever growing, the days of over-abundant oil wealth are passing, despite the great oil areas already fully and partially tested but not yet in full exploitation. Directorates must think not of next year, but of ; the next decade and beyond. Proved reserves of oil may decline but slowly, and much known rich oil-bearing land may remain to be exploited, but the chances of discovering any vast new fields gradually diminish. In most of the older developed areas the greatest hope for the future must lie in drilling to depths even now the rarity, and beyond. Here the skill of the metallurgist and the equipment manufacturer must play an even greater part than the advanced tech nique of the production engineer—whose work is now^ recognised as implying the co-operation of experts in many branches of science. So it comes about that once again there is a definite urge to secure territory, apparently even when the latter but a minor chance of proving oil-bearing. More geologists and geophysicists are employed to-day examin ing the structures than at any previous period. No where is this urge more spectacular than in the Near and Middle East, and it is timely to describe briefly the current position so far as it can be ascertained—for much is still withheld. The accompanying map has undergone revision of international significance since the last one was specially drawn for this journal and published in the Petroleum Times of February 22nd, 1936. Doubtless it will not be long before further con cession areas will have to be filled in, particularly, it is suggested, in Egypt and Turkey. In fact, this proved the case after the map had just been prepared and this article drafted. Factors of the Moment Several factors are of outstanding importance, apart from that of the vast areas being taken under concession whose oil wealth has yet to be revealed. In some cases preliminary survey has yet to j)rqve it is worth detailed investigation. These factors are the established major importance of Bahrein and the change in the international set-up brought about by the co-operative development between the Texas Corporation and the Standard Oil Company of California through the medium of the California Texas Oil Company, Ltd.; the purchase of the Italian share of Mosul Oil Fields, Ltd., by Shell ' interests, the Anglo- Iranian, Near East Development Corporation (S.O.N.J, and Socony-Vacuum) and the Compagnie Fran^aise des 0 ??i ta !; pumn 1 Jn the foreground is KI pump station, 4 r the bungalows to the left being staff quarters and Wells 38 and 39 tn 1 V 5 ^ C L Iltre . statlon ^ ant * the tank farm to the right. In centre distance is the stabilisation plant, with and th l topping plant to right. Hanjira degassing station is on the hills at left edge and main company r bungalows, offices, stores, etc., lie at right edge, just below the hills )February 6, 1937 THE PETROLEUM TIMES FOSTER WHEELER CRUDE OIL STABILIZATION PLANT AT KIRKUK. The Plant Actually Processes THE TOTAL PRODUCTION FROM THE IRAQ OILFIELDS And is capable of handling 3% OF THE ENTIRE WORLD PRODUCTION OF CRUDE OIL IT REDUCES THE VAPOUR PRESSURE from 80 lbs. to 5 lbs. REID. HYDROGEN SULPHIDE CONTENT from 0.4% to 0.0008%. Thus MINIMISING WEATHER &amp; CORROSION DURIN Telephone; HOL. 2527-8-9 ID. FOSTER WHEELER L ALDWYCH HOUSE • • • ALDWYGH, W-02 Associated Companies FOSTER WHEELER CORPORATION, U.S.A. FOSTER WHEELER LTD., CANADA, FOSTER WHEELER' S.A., FRANC innprcTar&gt;&lt;1ir&gt;cr onA190 drilling was very active at one time and vast sums of money were expended—and lost. Whether modern technique will prove some of these areas to be truly commercial yielding, time alone can tell. If the new Mining Law does not definitely favour such wildcatting, then they will probably never receive the full test which modern technique alone can oive. Western Arabia Since the last review Petroleum Concessions, Ltd., has registered Petroleum Development (Western Arabia), Ltd., to take over the large concession obtained from Ibn Sa'ud extending along the Hejaz coast for a uniform depth of about 60 miles from the north down to the Farsan Islands. The immediate area surrounding the Holy City of Mecca is naturally excluded. A party is now at work carrying out preliminary geological investi gation to decide which areas are worth immediate and detailed work. The Mediterranean Coast Asphalt and bituminous limestone have periodically been mined and still are, to a small extent, at several points along the Mediterranean coastal zone, where, it may be mentioned, both the Standard of New Jersey and the Pearson groups were preparing to drill test wells at the outbreak of war in 1914. Mining licences formerly held by the Iraq Petroleum have recently changed nominal titleships, Petroleum Concessions, Ltd., taking over those in Palestine and Petroleum Concessions (Syria and Lebanon), Ltd., those in the countries indicated by the title. It is also under stood that a small concession held by the late D. A. Sutherland, of London, in the Dead Sea area is still valid. Palestine, like Egypt, is a country in which revised mining regulations have long been awaited. A year or so ago attention was drawn to this delay on several occasions in the British Parliament, but no reference has been made now for some time past, and the present position is not clear. Numerous geological surveys have been con ducted over Palestine in the past, and the position is now being reviewed and the most likely areas chosen for eventual drilling. Turkey not Behind Although reports have appeared from time to time of foreign drilling parties at work in Turkey, the position at the moment is that no large concessions have so far been granted to the international oil groups. Instead, the Turkish Government itself has set up an organisation— Institute of Mining Research and Prospecting (M.T.A.)— which is carrying out a certain amount of drilling as well as researches in the results of old test wells and reports of surface oil indications and some general geological investigations. Although this programme has been proceeding about a couple of years, little detail has been published. Drilling has been announced at Mardin, Adana and Murefte, quite an extensive gas flow being encountered in the latter area whose commercial signifi cance has yet to be determined. However, the Government is not alone in its interest in the oil possibilities of Turkey, for it is reported that one or two important concerns—not allied—have been February 6, 1937 investigating the question. So it is possible that Turkey yet may be the scene of large concessions similar to those now commonplace over the rest of the Near and Middle East oil map On this question of foreign participation the Minister of Public Works has recently announced ' the new Turkish Republic realised the need and the advantages of employing foreign capital for the develop ment of the country, and thus welcomed any investment from abroad which would assume all rights and duties thereof.' A very recent Biitish company registration which may or may not effect further changes on the map is Anatolian Oilfields, Ltd., formed ' to acquire and develop oilfields and other rights.' Mosul Concession Obscure As already mentioned, the position in regard to Mosul would appear to be now in a period of transition following the acquisition of the Italian share of Mosul Oil Fields, Ltd. (holding company for B.O.D., Ltd.), by Mosul Holdings, Ltd. Details of field development have always been a matter of some mystery, and since the recent transaction no news has been issued. About a year ago reports of strong flows of lighter crude were reported from deeper drilling at Qaiyarah and that an increased potentiality for the arsa had been proved. Production, it is under stood, is being held to operating fuel requirements pend ing a decision as to the means of transport to the coast. Meanwhile drilling is being systematically conducted. At the same time, however, the heavy asphaltic crude is being exploited for the manufacture of road materials in the reconstructed refinery. It is reported, though, that its operation is held only on a short-term contract and that this may later be assigned to a domestic company, the recently formed Iraq Corporation, Ltd., whose directors include men of great influence in their country. Undoubtedly the advent of Iraq Petroleum as a large shareholder must alter the situation radically, in more senses than one. It is possible that it may lead to a revision of the more onerous terms of the B.O.D. con cession as a prelude to increased oil exploitation. The original concession terms have all along been held to be a stumbling block, inasmuch as when oil export begins, 20 per cent, of all crude produced may be taken by the Government and a royalty of 4s. gold per ton paid on the remainder, subject to a maximum of £200,000. This applies for the first 20 years. Again, exemption from internal taxation can only be obtained by payment of a lump sum of £15,000 per million for the first four million tons of crude, and £20,000 for each subsequent million. Iraq Petroleum at Full Flow The position at the Kirkuk field is now so well known as to need no comment. It has long been regarded as one of the world's models of unit development, ranking with the Anglo-Iranian company's properties in this respect. Output has for some time been almost up to the 4,000,000 -barre^ per annum capacity of the pipeline to Haifa and Tripoli, although less than 50 wells have been drilled, an appreciable proportion of which are capped. t THE PETROLEUM TIMES I, February 6, 1937 THE PETROLEUM TIMES 187 Petroles, which major oil groups, together with a small participation by C. S. Gulbenkian, formed for their purposes a company called Mosul Holdings, Ltd.; and finally, the widely international aspect of the con cession holders in general. The same group have also formed Petroleum Concessions, Ltd., which in turn has several subsidiaries engaged in active exploration work in the Near and Middle East. International Co-operation This latter feature is the outstanding difference in comparing the conditions which surrounded the acquisi tion of concessions in the earlier days of the industry and the present phase. In the current phase—which may be termed one of ' planning for the future '—there is co-operation to a degree unprecedented over such a vast total area, a situation differing greatly from past history. Not only does it speak volumes for the wisdom of our oil leaders, but it means that the world will gain, and Nature's irreplaceable bounty will not be hastily produced nor wastefully consumed without thought for the morrow. In this, there is at least compensation for the fact that Iraqi oil would not have been forced on the world so rapidly but for the insistence of French policy, leading eventually to production which has been respon sible for Bahrein development and perhaps other major fields to come. The vast influence wielded by the international oil powers which figure in this picture is worth pondering over. They can but be mentioned briefly—pages could be written on the details—but the significance is in- There is no need to dwell on the predominating posi tion so long held in Southern Iran by the Anglo-Iranian Oil Company, behind which is the weight of the Burmah Oil Company and the British Government. The same is true of the Khanaquin territory. In Kuwait the ' Anglo-Iranian ' is associated in equal partnership with the Gulf Oil Corporation, the latter's only exploitation interest so far in the Near and Middle East. It not long ago disposed of its interests in the Iraq Petroleum Company and on the Island of Bahrein. In Iran a new factor complicates the international set-up through details coming to hand as these lines are written of the grant of a large concession—eventually to be fixed at 100,000 square miles—in East and North east Iran to the Amiranian Oil Company, newly formed subsidiary of the Seaboard Oil Company of Delaware. It is worth noting that The Texas Corporation holds a 33| per cent, interest in Seaboard. Afghanistan, too, now comes into, the picture for the first time by the concession of practically the whoie country under consideration to another Seaboard subsi diary, the Inland Exploration Company. Turning to Iraq, the international set-up is far more complex and as yet not wholly clear. There are two concessions. The composition of that held by Iraq Petroleum Company, Ltd., alone is well known, 95 per cent, being held equally between the ' Anglo-Iranian ' (British Government), Royal Dutch-Shell, Cie Fran^aise des Petroles (partly French Government) and by American oil interests (now consisting of Standard of New Jersey and Socony-Vacuum—the latter comprising Standard of New York and Vacuum Oil). As to the second Iraq concession, that held by B.O.D., which is controlled by Mosul Oil Fields, Ltd., the position is at the moment far from clear by reason of Mosul Holdings, Ltd.'s recent purchase of the Italian holding and the litigation which has for some time been pending as to the ownership of certain blocks of shares held under option by a Dutch subsidiary of a German steel group. On this may depend the question as to who really holds the controlling share. However, we shall not be surprised to find this matter settled or adjusted before long, and without actually having recourse to the courts. But it must not be forgotten that at least one independent British firm holds a share interest in Mosul Oil Fields, Ltd. The other international grouping—destined to become a far more important factor yet—concerns the develop ment of Bahrein Island and Eastern Saudi Arabia. Into this aspect of the picture come two groups not represented elsewhere so far, the Standard Oil Company of California and The Texas Corporation. The Position in Egypt Let us range sketchily over the accompanying map, noting the main features of the present position. To consider Egypt first. Of the two best commercial fields ever found, Gemsah has long since been flooded with water, while at Hurghada, the only one now exploited, the rate of production is slowly following its inevitable decline. All attempts to prove extensions have been abortive. For a long time Anglo-Egyptian Oilfields, Ltd., the concession holder of the Hurghada field, has been awaiting the release of new mining regulations in order that it may prospect actively further afield, and is re ported to have surveyed various areas in the Western Deseit and along the Red Sea Coast, for which claims have been filed with the Government. The unreasonable delay of the Egyptian Government in promulgating its long-considered new Mining Law has been doing its nationals a disservice by delaying several large-scale programmes of oil prospecting. It is a sad commentary that, because of this delay, Anglo-Egyptian Oilfields should have been forced to transfer to another country part of its activity to aim to supplement Egypt's falling oil production. The company is under stood to be associated with the oil search now being prosecuted in the northern areas of Trinidad, where secure and equitable oil mining regulations are in force. News comes to hand since this was written that the Government is now considering the grant of a three-year exploration permit over an area—still unrevealed of some 4,000 square kilometres, believed to be located on the Red Sea coast south of the Hurghada field. The question is to all intents and purposes settled. I At Towila Island test drilling has been suspended for some years. While a very heavy asphaltic oil was at one time exploited at Abu Durbar, it is believed this has now ceased. Too much significance need not be given to reported discoveries of oil along the Red Sea coasts and islands—that at Abu Zenima was a recent example. Surface indications of oil exist and shows of oil, even small supplies, have been found in innumerable areas, for ^In, *aceasj Hiioffi]1937 THE PETROLEUM TIMES 187 i. I )h major oil groups, together with a small by C. S. Gulbenkian, formed for their )mpany called Mosul Holdings, Ltd.; and widely international aspect of the con- ^s in general. The same group have also ieum Concessions, Ltd., which in turn has liaries engaged in active exploration work id Middle East. Co-operation feature is the outstanding difference in 3 conditions which surrounded the acquisi- ssions in the earlier days of the industry mt phase. In the current phase—which d one of ' planning for the future '—there n to a degree unprecedented over such a ja, a situation differing greatly from past iocs it speak volumes for the wisdom ers, but it means that the world will gain, irreplaceable bounty will not be hastily wastefully consumed without thought for In this, there is at least compensation for fraqi oil would not have been forced on the lly but for the insistence of French policy, ually to production which has beenrespon- ein development and perhaps other major nfluence wielded by the international oil figure in this picture is worth pondering 3an but be mentioned briefly—pages could i the details—but the significance is in- need to dwell on the predominating posi- eld in Southern Iran by the Anglo-Iranian behind which is the weight of the Burmah and the British Government. The same is lanaquin territory. )he ' Anglo-Iranian ' is associated in equal ith the Gulf Oil Corporation, the latter's ion interest so far in the Near and Middle )ng ago disposed of its interests in the Iraq mpany and on the Island of Bahrein, new factor complicates the international h details coming to hand as these lines are grant of a large concession—eventually to 00.000 square miles—in East and North- ae Amiranian Oil Company, newly formed the Seaboard Oil Company of Delaware, ^ting that The Texas Corporation holds a aterest in Seaboard. 1, too, now comes into the picture for the the concession of practically the whole r consideration to another Seaboard subsi- and Exploration Company. Iraq, the international set-up is far more as yet not wholly clear. There are two The composition of that held by Iraq mpany, Ltd., alone is well known, 95 per )ld equally between the ' Anglo-Iranian ' r'nment). Royal Dutch-Shell, Cie Fran^aise (partly French Government) and by interests (now consisting of Standard of New Jersey and Socony-Vacuum—the latter comprising Standard of New York and Vacuum Oil). As to the second Iraq concession, that held by B.O D which is controlled by Mosul Oil Fields, Ltd., the position is at the moment far from clear by reason of Mosul Holdings, Ltd.'s recent purchase of the Italian holding and the litigation which has for some time been pending as to the ownership of certain blocks of shares held under option by a Dutch subsidiary of a German steel group. On this may depend the question as to who really holds the controlling share. However, we shall not be surprised to find this matter settled or adjusted before long, and without actually having recourse to the courts. But it must not be forgotten that at least one independent British firm holds a. share interest in Mosul Oil Fields Ltd. The other international grouping—destined to become a far more important factor yet—concerns the develop ment of Bahrein Island and Eastern Saudi Arabia. Into this aspect of the picture come two groups not represented elsewhere so far, the Standard Oil Company of California and The Texas Corporation. The Position in Egypt Let us range sketchily over the accompanying map, noting the main features of the present position. To consider Eg3^pt first. Of the two best commercial fields ever found, Gemsah has long since been flooded with water, while at Hurghada, the only one now exploited, the rate of production is slowly following its inevitable decline. All attempts to prove extensions have been abortive. For a long time Anglo-Egyptian Oilfields, Ltd., the concession holder of the Hurghada field, has been awaiting the release of new mining regulations in order that it may prospect actively further afield, and is re ported to have surveyed various areas in the Western Deseit and along the Red Sea Coast, for which claims have been filed with the Government. The unreasonable delay of the Egyptian Government in promulgating its long-considered new Mining Law has been doing its nationals a disservice by delaying several large-scale programmes of oil prospecting. It is a sad commentary that, because of this delay, Anglo-Egyptian Oilfields should have been forced to transfer to another country part of its activity to aim to supplement Egypt's falling oil production. The company is under stood to be associated with the oil search now being prosecuted in the northern areas of Trinidad, where secure and equitable oil mining regulations are in force. News comes to hand since this was written that the Government is now considering the grant of a three-year exploration permit over an area—still unrevealed of some 4,000 square kilometres, believed to be located on the Red Sea coast south of the Hurghada field. The question is to all intents and purposes settled. At Towila Island test drilling has been suspended for some years. While a very heavy asphaltic oil was at one time exploited at Abu Durbar, it is believed this has now ceased. Too much significance need not be given to reported discoveries of oil along the Red Sea coasts and islands—that at Abu Zenima was a recent example. Surface indications of oil exist and shows of oil, even small supplies, have been found in innumerable areas, for }i • i nnetxranrlmtr ad fiais] 1February 6, 1937 THE PETROLEUM TIMES 191 ltd, I a 0 great is the quantity of oil flowing from the Kirkuk I that relatively few wells are needed to keep the le H flSO-mile 12|-in. pipeline working to full capacity. l '' Petroleum 's output last year, with a total of Vt 0L 35O tons, shows a rise of 336,350 tons over 1935, %4hile shipments,at 3,933,200 tons are higher by 484,000 .&lt; An glo -Iranian' Always Prospecting «% 4t the established ' Anglo-Iranian ' fields of Masjid-i- MSulaiman, Haft Kel, Naft-i-Shah and Naft Khanah 1^1 crude oil is not merely produced ; it is brought to the surface with more regard to scientific principles than in ^ probably any other area anywhere. These areas have for M years been the centre of unrivalled large-scale field t u research. Meanwhile the company's production con- tinues to mount up, being 7,489,000 tons for the first I' 11 months of 1936, against 7,459,000 tons for the whole of in 1935. But outside the producing fields at numerous points the company is for ever carrying out test drilling with the idea of establishing reserve areas for the future. It is believed, however, that testing activities on Qishm ' 1 Island have ceased, wti The or igi na i concession in south and south-west Iran m covered some 400,000 square miles, but it will be re mem- leil0 lbered that this was halved in 1932 and must be reduced .o a final 100,000 square miles by the end of 1938. While the company may construct such pipelines as it ianOI requires and may determine their position, it is clear lafepfrom the revised concession terms that there is no barrier SfiMoi to other companies obtaining oil rights over the areas attijgiven up, and presumably they would be able to lay a iS inWpipeline through ' Anglo-Iranian ' territory if required. flMThus there would j^et appear possibilities of further development in the south and south-w T estern Iranian AnWareas. New American Factor in Iran liDg, In Elsewhere in this issue will be found the outline of the ^loJjterms of a concession, eventually to be chosen as 100,000 square miles from the Provinces of Mazanderan and ^ pjKhorassan by the Seaboard Oil Company of Delaware, . with which The Texas Corporation is associated. A new ^lli American factor thus looms on the horizon, about which p, it is too early yet to comment. It can be indicated with . certainty, however, that it denotes the forthcoming call a vast range of equipment and supplies of all kinds ^Iffrom manufacturers. | # Wildcatting at Kuwait A|]: Nothing has been revealed officially by the ' Anglo- rS a , Iranian ' as to the results of their joint venture with the s ^ ^ Gulf Oil Corporation in the Kuwait Petroleum Company the neutral territory of Kuwait. No 1 Bahrah has ^ been reported as around 6,000 ft., but secrecy is main- W ^ Gained as to the indications of commercial oil supplies. irein of Outstanding Importance to the British Empire a Bahrein's importance as a vast new oil reservoir is now ; ,gfcerally accepted, following five years' intensive deve rier 1 ' 1 lopment. Although the full potentialities of the field ^ave not yet been ascertained, especially at depth, it is already believed to be accepted as good for some 250,000 barrels daily. Shipments during 1936 are reported as averaging 10,000 barrels daily from such of the 40 pro ducing wells as have not been capped, an output which will be raised appreciably when the 25,000 barrel per day refinery now under construction is completed. This is expected to be some time in July. Constructional work has been impeded by the difficulty in procuring the large amount of skilled labour required and of getting them to accept the housing and general conditions of the island. With this refinery in use, total production for the current year is scheduled at 6,000,000 barrels, as compared with an estimated output of 3,600,000 barrels for 1936. This joint enterprise of the Standard of California and The Texas Corporation represented by California Texas Oil Company has an importance to British Empire oil supplies not yet thoroughly appreciated. In support of this one can quote the fact that not only does u The Statesman's Yearbook ' show Bahrein as part of the British Empire, but so does the Imperial Institute in its latest oil-production figures included in the annual ££ Statistical Summary.' This being accepted. Empire crude output must become a far more appreciable total in the course of time. Whether this assertion meets general acceptation or not, there can be no denial of the fact that the Bahrein field is the only one whose protection can be absolutely secured by the British Navy. It is worth noting that the island is becoming an important naval base, and it is also reported that it is destined to become one of the chief seadromes in the East. The India Office takes great interest in Bahrein affairs. Several years ago the Gulf Oil Corporation offered this concession to the Iraq Petroleum, which declined to take the property over or develop it. Less than five years ago it was purchased and rapidly developed by Standard of California. It is proving to be a ' gold mine,' as oil is said to be produced there and delivered at seaboard at lower cost than anywhere else in the world. The quality of the crude is about the same as that of Iraq and Iran. Saudi Arabia a Further Source Moreover, along the coast opposite and adjacent to Bahrein lies the seat of another oilfield whose importance has already been proved by California Arabian Standard Oil Company, but not its extent. On what is known as the El Hasa concession there are two main testing areas in Eastern Saudi f Arabia at the moment—Dammam, opposite Bahrjein ,#nd El' Alat/25 miles northwards on the Damma^xstructure. On this dome rich crude in strong flow has been struck, Dammam Np. .2 yielding at the rate of 3,800 barrels of 53 gravity (0.77) crude in 24 hours from a depth of 2,152 ft. Other wells have also proved productive, but efforts are being concentrated on testing the various structures rather than on obtaining yield. No information has been revealed as to the results of the wildcat on the El' Alat dome. It is not yet known what is to be done with Dammam crude. The present centre of production being only about eight miles to the coast, and from there to Bahrein only a gap of 20 miles or so of comparatively shallow water, there is obviously no need to consider theDURRANI'S PRESS CUTTINGS St. Andrew 's Mnnso QO OH « . IS CUTT x£&amp; February 6, 1937 Andrew's House, 32 to 34 Holborn Viaduct, and 3 St. Andrew Street, Holborn Circus, E.C.I. CENTRAL 3149 (Two Lines). Telephone: 193 Cutting from the creation of a major refinery on the believed the concession terms cal] f supply local needs. Gated February ..... The shaded section on our map . of Eastern Saudi Arabia ; it is gener»j^^^©MiWimL^ the concession covers all this area, but some reports limit it to 56,000 square miles. This survey must not close without brief mention of the two remaining Arabian concessions about which practically nothing is known beyond their existence. Both these are Petroleum Concessions' subsidiaries, one being Petroleum Development (Qatar), Ltd., and the other Petroleum Development (Trucial Coast), Ltd. Both were previous u Anglo-Iranian' options and are now being geologically surveyed in a preliminary way. Will Afghanistan Rise to Oil Fame ? Mainly because of its comparative inaccessibility Afghanistan has hitherto been neglected by the petro leum industry, although there are believed to be possi bilities of rich oil deposits in the Hari Rud valley. This country now enters the oil picture of the Near and Middle East for the first time, and should the concession recently granted to a subsidiary of Seaboard be ratified at Kabul, early exploration and perhaps exploitation may be expected; but many millions of pounds will have to be expended before crude is brought to deep w r ater. Much will depend upon the quality and quantity of the crude produced by the initial test wells. Extensive drilling operations and the construction of a pipeline by the Inland Exploration Company, Sea board's other new subsidiary, will involve many serious problems. Transportation of supplies for American and European workers will be no mean matter. Afghanistan is one of the few countries where the Mohammedan way of living continues uninterrupted by Western develop ments, although exploitation of oil on an extensive scale is bound to make some changes, especially if the country becomes wealthy from oil revenues. At present the Afghans strongly resist modernisation because of its resultant taxation that would interfere with their nomad life. Oil men who take part in the petroleum develop ment in Afghanistan will find most of the tribesmen friendly and courteous provided their customs and religion are very carefully respected. It is well to remember that the importation and use of alcohol in any form is strictly forbidden. The nominal ruler of the country is H.M. Mohamed Zahir Shah ; but his uncle, H.R.H. Sirdar Mohamed Hashim Khan, the Prime Minister, is the real ruler. He 18 52 years of age, has held his present position since ^ ail d has enjoyed wide experience in European ^ountries. As we write, His Royal Highness is the guest m ^ on don of the British Government, and will shortlv return to Kabul. While no details of the concession terms are yet [ reve aled, it is certain they will be in line with those Ranted in neighbouring territories. No modern ruler is , n t 0 the possibilities of the oil seeker as a revenue | Fovi er. Who knows but what Afghanistan will rise 8 rength this way, as Iran and Iraq did ? Dof 0 conc ^ u( ^ e an - a ll too brief survey of a vast 611 ia area the possible world oil centre of the .v 1937 may be coming into its the American fields are nains a number of areas tion of Arabia open to ——, x— — _ v _ ^juthern portion, which contains lands considered favourable for prospecting. It is hard to conceive any territory too remote to be opened up by the modern oilfield engineer when the world wants the oil. Meanwhile, it is satisfactory that develop ment is mostly in strong and wise hands.February 6, 1937 THE PETROLEUM TIMES 193 creation of a major refinery on the mainland, though it is believed the concession terms call for a small plant to supply local needs. The shaded section on our map is the probable extent of Eastern Saudi Arabia ; it is generally understood that the concession covers all this area, but some reports limit it to 56,000 square miles. This survey must not close without brief mention of the two remaining Arabian concessions about which practically nothing is known beyond their existence. a Both these are Petroleum Concessions' subsidiaries, one being Petroleum Development (Qatar), Ltd., and the other Petroleum Development (Trucial Coast), Ltd. Both were previous Anglo-Iranian' options and are now being geologically surveyed in a preliminary way. Will Afghanistan Rise to Oil Fame ? Mainly because of its comparative inaccessibility Afghanistan has hitherto been neglected by the petro leum industry, although there are believed to be possi bilities of rich oil deposits in the Hari Rud valley. This country now enters the oil picture of the Near and Middle East for the first time, and should the concession recently granted to a subsidiary of Seaboard be ratified at Kabul, early exploration and perhaps exploitation may be expected; but many millions of pounds will have to be expended before crude is brought to deep w^ater. Much will depend upon the quality and quantity of the crude produced by the initial test wells. Extensive drilling operations and the construction of a pipeline by the Inland Exploration Company, Sea board's other new subsidiary, will involve many serious problems. Transportation of supplies for American and European workers will be no mean matter. Afghanistan is one of the few countries where the Mohammedan way of living continues uninterrupted by Western develop ments, although exploitation of oil on an extensive scale is bound to make some changes, especially if the country becomes wealthy from oil revenues. At present the Afghans strongly resist modernisation because of its resultant taxation that would interfere with their nomad life. Oil men who take part in the petroleum develop ment in Afghanistan will find most of the tribesmen friendly and courteous provided their customs and religion are very carefully respected. It is well to remember that the importation and use of alcohol in any form is strictly forbidden. The nominal ruler of the countrv is H.M. Mohamed Zahir Shah; but his uncle, H.R.H. Sirdar Mohamed Hashim Khan, the Prime Minister, is the real ruler. He is 52 years of age, has held his present position since and has enjoyed wide experience in European countries. As we write, His Royal Highness is the guest ln London, of the British Government, and will shortlv return to Kabul. While no details of the concession terms are yet revealed, it is certain they will be in line with those Ranted in neighbouring territories. No modern ruler is itjr 'ri^ 0 ^ le P 08S ^fr^ es ^he oil seeker as a revenue L! 0 ! 1 er ' ^ knows but what Afghanistan will rise s rength this way, as Iran and Iraq did ? Dof 0 conc ^ u( ^ e ari a ll too brief survey of a vast 11 ial area the possible world oil centre of the future. Who knows but that it may be oommg into its full vigour of development when the American e on the wane ? For there still remains a number of a covering an appreciable proportion of Ara ia 0 P el * concession, particularly the southern portion, w 1(3 contains lands considered favourable for prospec ing. It is hard to conceive any territory too remote o e opened up by the modern oilfield engineer when t e wor wants the oil. Meanwhile, it is satisfactory that eve op ment is mostly in strong and wise hands.194 THE PETROLEUM TIMES PUTTING BRITISH LUBRICATING OIL TRADE ON SOUND BASIS Yorkshire Meeting Follows Example of London and Manchester A very successful meeting, attended by about 120 firms in the Yorkshire and Midland areas, was held in Leeds last week. E. B. Irwin, M.B.B. (president of the National Lubricating Oil and Grease Federa tion) presided, and was supported by i „ February 6, 1937 to the three representatives of the Federation me tioned above—and also to H. Holliday (Vacuum fn Company, Ltd.)—for their untiring efforts and hard work in the interests of all British lubricating oil distributors. Prior to the meeting, Mr. Vicker presided at a lunch which he kindly gave at tip Hotel Metropole to about 80 of those' attending the meeting. BRITISH PROTECTION OF PERSIAN GULF STATES The Arab states of Koweit, Bahrein, Qatar and the Trucial Coast are in treaty relations with the British Government, under which they enjoy, in varying degrees. His Majesty's protection, said'tie Under-Secretary of State for India this week in the House of Commons y answering a question as to the number of treaty engagements under which the British Government have undertaken liabilities in which they agreed to supply armed forces to protect the territories of the Arab rulers of the Persian Gulf. OIL INDUSTRIES CLUB The tenth annual dinner of the Oil Industries Club will be held at the Dorchester Hotel, Park Lane, London, on Monday, March 8th. Capt. H. C. F. Crookshank, M.P., Secretary for Mines, has accepted the Club's invitation to be present, and will propose the toast of ' The Petroleum Industry/' to which Frederick Godber (managing director of ' Shell ' Transport and Trading and a vice- president of the Club) will reply. ' PETROLEUM TIMES M —37 YEARS BACK From the Issue of February 10th, 1900 Weather Controls Production .—More favour able weather having intervened advantage has been taken of it to push development operations, the result being that an unusual number of new wells have been brought in from the older American fields. Things have not been quite so favourable in Ohio and Indiana, though it is expected that the further advance in crude will encourage operators to greater efforts. TIN PLATE MARKET Norton Owen &amp; Co., of 6, Great Winchester Street, London, E.C. 2, report under date Fobruar} 3rd, 1937, as under; — The position of Steel Bars has become even more acute, some makers finding extreme difficulty 111 covering for the orders they already have on their books. This being the case, they naturally are no anxious to sell, and where quotations are made are asking up to Is. 6d. premium over the minimum basis price. Prices may be called 21s. 3d. basis for expor and 20s. 10Jd. basis f.o.r. for home trade.His Britannic Majesty's Political Agent, Bahrein. Herewith are seven copies of the Annual Report covering operations of The Bahrein Petroleum Company limited during the year 1936, Will you kindly transmit one copy to His Excellency Sheikh Sir Hamad bin Isa Al-Khalifah, K.C.I.E,, C.S.X. Yours very truly. End: G. W. R. SMITH, Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN PETROLSDM COMPANY LIMITED1936 AKNUAL HSPOBT . This report. s r&amp;lcii coT«rs operations on Bahrein Island of the o^v-v^in Petroltur, ?o , I &gt;d , du-.nns the year 3 '36 Includes t ahulations abovdng the status of all. wells, of buildings either constructed or in ♦ka course of construction, and a summary which shows the nationalities 0 f t-iff Coapany^s personnel in BahreiUo There is attached a print of tba CoE.pany's map of Bahrein Island on which, are shown locations of wells ari the Companr'e furious facilities including CSactps. Refinery Pipe Lines and T Vt ' P Stations ^ -''d ihere are also Shown enough tope graph!, eel contours to indicate the pngitioi of Jebel Dukhano The infoitoation is given as of 51 st Dsc eriber 1936 BUILDIUGS, s,-.. 5» of the bai 1 dings in the Old Cas© were ufcandoned or disraantl^a and isoved t&gt; y-.ew '-cations but the majority are ati. I being used bo house the cone tract! i n r-ien vfoo are in Bahrein to assist in th-s ai^ding a R«f4i«ry. Ofasiruetica of buildings is being continued in th« Rfcw r^tp, to jir07.de ad: if its housing Acc -oamodations for the personnel ifcich w'.ll even- wially be K! -yai red for tn» opsrations of the Cospanye j.t ic In' that a large proportion of the houses are to be air conditioned and z.i&amp;t a hospital and a combination theater and school building are being constructed&lt;, DRILLIK'3 During the year the drilling program was accelerated e resultir in the aon^latior of 21 producing walla» Likewise enlargement of the Company c s facilities necessitated increasing the water supply and therefore number of ■water walls were drilled Sae tabulation -ittaa *ii x ruction during 1936 far oxcaeded tlr-t of 1935 or of sny quantities of CTude oil were shipped froEi the In addition considerable c^ade oil ^ In order o deliver the crude oil to the Refinery and Sitra it was necessary to -larg. rl gathering sy tsm by the addition of three t! Hefiuerf/ . as oommenced late in 193? The ' at hich time it had a capacity of approzimately 10,000 barrels per day. Before the corgpletion of the first unit, howererj it was decided to .rzii'va;id add iraclring stiUc atd other auxlli&lt;= of a Kirge namber of spe-iial conetrurticn i:ien and thn import at -..on of a I k--?. .;f £;■•..?ci&amp;l eeuipruer.'': '^en oofl?&gt;leti?3. the wfs.nsry v-ill ■ I contain th&lt; following major unitsj crude skills, .racking stills, v ] - - . 'i- , it . . treating plant, laboratory, loading system and necessary tankage, The accompanying map shows the outlines of the Refirory Heserva ticn tankage therein designed for the reception of crude oil from the i field, but not refinery pump stations or pipelines as these facilities :• ^subject to re-arraiigement from t;- ue to time ;;s practice demands The refiner^r Cffine ar-d --rr tni 1,11 arc included in the tabulationTELEGRAMS : ^ONCESS. BAHREIN NS LIMITED BAHREIN G.C.M.G. (Chairman ' D.S.C. (French) Sverly Arms'ian) m' men) CONFIDENTlAX S3rd March, 1937. PERSIAN GULF BENTLEY'S SECOND PHRASE To H.B.M's Political Agent, Bahrain. Sir, We have the honohr to acknowledge receipt of your letter No.C/218-10/1 dated the 19th March, 1937. We are forwarding copies of this letter to our London principals from whom we shall receive further instructions of which we will inform you in due course. lie have the honour to be Sir, Your most obedient servants, For &amp; on behalf of PETROLEUM C0NCE^40NS LIMITED, MkNA-GER.The Bahrein Petroleum company limited Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, March 27, 1937, Wo. FA-14S. ELs Britannic Majesty's Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir, U ( I take pleasure in handing you herewith ten copies of 'Abstract of Accounts for the second half of 1936, of Oil [Measured Under Lease between His Excellency the Shaikh of Bahrein and the Company dated 29th December 1934, Delivered in Accordance with Article 711 thereof and Statement of Royalties Due for the second half of 1936', and would request that you transmit the requisite number of copies to His Excellency Shaikh Sir Hamad bin Isa al Khalifah K.C.I.E., C.S.I. Will you kindly request the financial Adviser to sign the three copies on which provision is made for his signature and return them to the Company. I enclose the Company's cheque No.0496 drawn on the Eastern Bank Limited, Bahrein, in favour of the Financial Adviser, in the amount of Rupees Fourteen lakhs fifty eight thousand eight hundred eighty seven, annas four, pies nine only (Rs. 14,58,887-4-9) being Total Net Royalties Due to His Excellency Shaikh Sir Hamad bin Isa al Khalifah, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., Ruler of Bahrein, for the period July 1, 1936 to January 1, 1937, as detailed on enclosed Abstract and Statement for the second half of 1936. Will you kindly request the Financial Adviser to make and forward to the Company a receipt in quintuplicate acknowledging this payment. Yours very truly, lj G. W. R. SMITH, 1Chief Local Representative, * r »&gt;. ^ v THE BAHREIN PSTROLSDM COMPANY LIMITED. L End: ✓\JU^ ^ 1f p 1 B.O. Ho. 68/20. Bahrain, March 27, 1937 Dear Colonel Loch, The enclosed note from Skinner which was written on my suggestion describes the points which were mentioned during our conversation on Thursday 25th regarding the additional area. The meeting was short as Skinner came late and I had an early engagement that day. Lieutenant Colonel Gordon Loch, G.I.I., ii .B .m's Political Agent, Bahrain. Yours sincerely./jo The Bahrein Petroleum Company limited Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf d No.PA-141 p£ ' March 25, 1937. His Britennic Majesty's Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir: 4' Reference your letter No.C/217-10/l of March 19, 1937, in which you advised that it is satisfactory for the Company to carry on negotiations direct with the Adviser to the Bahrein Governraent for an Oil.Concession covering the Bahrein Additional Area provided that you ere kept fully and without delay infoimed of all thet take place: The Adviser and I h*d our first discussion this morning. This discussion was entirely preliminary and general and consisted: 1. In reviewing the statements made in my letter to you of March 4th which set forth the position of my Company and gave reasons for maintaining that they -re entitled to a preferential right in respect of the whole of the Additional Area. Mr. Belgrave stated that His Excellency Sheikh Sir Hamad bin Issa al Khalifah, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., would like to divide the Additional Area between my Company and The Petroleum Concessions Limited to which I replied that ray Company is only interested in the whole of the Additional Area. 3. No definite terms of agreement were discussed but I pointed out that inasmuch as Hawar Islands are not interesting geologically, as they appeared to be last Fall, the Additional Area has not the same value as it appeared to have at that time. Nothing else of importance \vas discussed. Yours very truly. Countersigned: E. A. SKIKNER ( Resident Manager THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED C. BALRYMPLE BELGR^VS Adviser to Bahrein Government cc Mr. C. Dalrymple Belgrave thk |U4CONFIDENTIAL. No. C/235-10/1 The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to:— The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire ? and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document (s). T he A gbnct, BAHEAIN, P ersian G dle. Dated Ma-reh* • i&amp;S7 v • Reference to previous correspondence : Description o Name and Date. Subject. 1 H ^ 4' Letter NoI PA-141 d:ted the 25th March 1957 from the Resi dent Manager, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, Bahrain, to the Political Agent, Bahrain. Additional Area. bHo. 0/229 -10 /1 Political Agency, Bahrein, the 21st March 1927 From Lieutenant-Colonel Gordon Loch, C.I.E#, Political Agent, Bahrain. The Adviser to the Bahrain Government, Bahrain Sir, h I have the honour to enclose faur copies of 'Abstract of Accounts for the second half year of 1926 of oil measured under the Lease between His Excellency the Shaikh of Bahrain and the Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited dated the 29th December 1924, delivered in accordance with Article VII there of n together with the Company* s cheque Ko. 0496 dated the 26th March 1927 for Rs. 14,58,887-4-9 in settlement of the Royalty for the period stated above. 2. It is requested that you will kindly sign and return three copies of the 'Abstract of Accounts' for transmission to the Chief Local Representative and a receipt in quintupli- cate acknowledging the payment. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant. Captain, For Political igent, BahrainNo. C/240-10/1 Political Bahrain, the 51st March 1957. From Lieutenant-Colonel Gordon Political Agent, Bahrain, To The Adviser to the Bahrain Government, Bahrain. Slr ' V, v1 v I have the honour to enclose a copy of the Annual Report of the Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, for the information of His Excellency Shaikh Sir Hamad bin ♦Isa ( al Khalifah, K.C.I.L., C.S.I. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant. Captain, For Political Agent, Bahrain. I#o cii p is«X # £ # pCONFIDENTIAL. ( au Ng. C/241-10/1 The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to:— 1• The Honourabie the Politic-1 Resident in the Persitn Gulf, Bushire# g* Ills sty f 3 C&lt; cret of State for Indie, Indii Office, itondon. 3# The Foreign Secretary to the Gov^. rn^cnt of In-: l New Delhi and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document (s). A copy' of the Report hi. s been tr. r nsmitted to the ; nvlse to the Brhr' ln jovrmm nt r^r inforr;,--tion of His Excel iency Shaikh Sir Haoud tain , Isa al Khf.lifi.h,K.C.I.; ,,C. ,1 The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gdlf. Dated ............................ Reference to previous correspondence : Description o Name and Date. Subject. /nnu.'.i Report of the Comjiiny 1u, ■ nr in.CONFIDENTIAL. / ir No. C/ 242 -10 /1 The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to Vx 1. The Honour.; bit the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushlre. • His ^jesty* s Cecrst- ry of Sti to for Iridic., India Office, London. Sm The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, New Delhi, v. f\ I * and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document (s). I ;• A copy of the enclosure tqfgctner with the cheque ' fro®, the Company have ben forwarded to the the Bahrain Governrnent, ^-hriTfu''''''— T he A gency, BAHRAIN, P bksian G olf. Dated.. &amp; is.t., ..rch • -1, ••••.• , Reference to previous correspondence : Description o Name and Date. better Hoi PA^142 . ted the 27th March 19S7 the Chief Local Bepr sentailve. The Bah- r in Petroleum Company Limited^ Bahr.-.in, to the Politic: 1 agent Bahrain. Subject. Bi.hrtin Oil - accounts for the s- cond h; 1 of the year 1956 of oil rsea sured under the lining .uthe Bahrein Petroleum company limited L i &gt;7 / Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf z- no»PA- 156 April 2, 1937. His Britannic Majesty*s Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir: o.^ / The Adviser and I had our second discussion regarding the Additional Area this morning in which I made the following offer: that, if His Highness Sheikh Sir Hamad bin Issa al Khalifah, K.C.I.E., C.S.I., will grant to The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited a Concession covering all of his pos sessions including the territorial waters and Hawar Islands, such Concession to be under all of the terms of the existing lease between His Highness and The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited, 1. My Company will guarantee to pursue, with diligence and without unnecessary delay, geological work including structure drilling and geophysical work if these are necessary; 2. To drill a test well if a favourable Area is found; 3. To pay His Highness Rs. 100,000 cash and Rs.300,000/- when Oil has been discovered in commercial quantities (this subject to final approval of the Company Heed Office). Also discussed (in the event Oil is discovered in commercial quantities) were questions of Drilling Obligation and increase in the present Minimum Royalty. These matters are being developed with my principals. The Adviser raised the question as to 'Hie meaning of 'caranercial quantities' and it was pointed out that so many factors enter into the determination of this that anything more definite cannot be stipulated; it is a term customarily used in Oil Concession Agreements. Nothing else of importance was discussed. Pn countersigned : „ Yours very tnJy. ■ S.A. SEENHER . c. DALRYMPLE: BELGR/JTE Resident Manager Adviser to Bahrein Government. THE BAHREIN RETROlto COMPANY LIMITED cc C. Dalrymple Belgrave II . V\M\ D.O. No. 126/EI/9-A. Bahrain, 4tli April 1937. k rt ^(u Dear Colonel Loch, iith reference to the question of oil gauging which I mentioned when the Hon'ble the Political Resident was here last. It will shortly become impossible for Steele to do all the gauging required by the Government and by the Bahrain Petroleum Company as well as his other work. The Bahrain Petroleum Company are pre pared to pay us £500. a year and would I believe pay a little more, if we undertake to do their gauging as well as our own. In any case our own gauging necessitates a visit every other day taking about hours. This work must be carried out by a European with one or two Indian gangers working under him. In my opinion the most satisfactory plan is for the Bahrain Govermaent to take on a young Englishman to do oil gauging and to assist in general engineering and building work under the State Engineer. I mentioned this to Hobble the Political Resident, but when he comes next week I should like to have an opportunity of discussing the frf. rJ ^O L CI H-2- the matter with hiia with Steele present who can more easily explain the matter of gauging etc. I am told by the Bahrain Petroleum Company that the refinery work will start in full swing in July. Yours sincerely, Lieut. Colonel Gordon Loch, C.I.I., H.B.M ! s Political Agent, Bahrain.The Bahrein Petroleum Company limited Wo. PA-171. His Britannic Majesty , s Political Bahrein. Dear Sir: Island, Persian Gulf 13, 1937. The Adviser and I had our third discussion regarding the Additional Area this morning. Mr. L. N. Hamilton was also present The offer which I made during my second discussion with the Adviser and which is set forth in my letter No. PA-156 of April 2nd to you ' was amplified and extended during this morning's discussion so that the offer now embraces the following points: that, if His Highness Sheikh Sir Hamed bin Issa al Khalifah, iC.C.I.E., u.S.I., will grant to The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited an oil concession covering the Additional Area, that is to say all of the territory under the dominion of His Highness (including territorial waters), other than that which has been selected by my Company under the terms of the present Mining Laase, such con cession to be under the terms and conditions of the present Mining Lease except as to the following obligations which my Company is prepared to undertake with respect to the Additional Area: 1. % Company will pursue, with diligence and without unnecessary delay, geological work including structure drilling and geophysical work if necessary; 2. If a favorable area is found my Company will drill a test well and if sufficient oil should be discovered to justify my Company in drilling further wells, such drilling will be continued until oil in commercial quantities has been obtained, or until the area is no longer deemed a favorable one. ? 3. % Company will pay His Highness Rs. 100,000 upon the granting of such concession and a further sum of Rs. 300,000 upon the discovery of oil in commercial quantities. In view of our previous discussion about the meaning of the term 'coramercial quantities' I suggested, for the further assurance of His Highness, that my Company would be prepared to accept a provision stating in effect that as soon as a well, or wells, had been drilled capable of producing, in accordance with good oil field practice, a daily average of a fixed Sf j amount, say 500 tons, of oil, it would be deemed that oil has been found in commercial quantities. i, m Jwv** ' 'k' v ■4* Upon, the discovery of oil in commercial quantities my Company will continue drilling with at least one string of tools until a sufficient number of wells have been drixled within the productive area to meet the require ments of good oil field practice, it being understood, however, that this obligation may be suspended during such time as the wells then drilled are capable of a' total daily average production of at least 1000 tons of oil; 5. Commencing with the date of discovery of oil in commercial quantities the royalties received by His Highness shall not be less than at the rate of Rs.50,000 each year. The above offer relates to all of the Additional Area, but in view of His Highness's insistence upon reserving the use of the Island of Emm al Nassam it is understood that the Company may not drill upon that island without first obtaining the consent of His Highness. The form of the concession, of course, will be subject to the approval of the parties concerned. Yours very truly S. A. SKINNER Resident Ifeinager THE BAHREIN PSTROLEDM COMPANY LIMTSD Countersi aned : 0. DALRYMPIE BSLGRAVS Adviser to Bahrein Government cc; Mr. C. Dalrymple Belgrave.CONFIDENTIAL. No ' C/283-10/1 The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to;—^ The Honourable Vxo Political looidont in the Persia 'lilf, Cr»j.p ' In.hrain 9 and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document (s). The Agency, BAHEAIN, Persian Gulf. Eeference to previous correspondence : rf/ Bahrain printed lott-rl'::o. G/035-10/1 daied the Gist E-rch 1937. Description of Name and Date. 1* Letter Ho.PA/156 dated the 2nd April 1937 from the He- si dent Manager, The Bahrain Petroleum Conpnny Limited. 2. Letter No.PA/171 dated the 13th April 1937 from the Resident Uanaier, llie Bahi^a Petroleum Cocpany United. oft Subject. Brain Additional Area. in/ -&gt;0CONFIDENTIAL. No. C/86 of 1937. The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to 1, His Sajeaty'e Secretary of State for India, London. 2. The Foreign fleeretary to the Government of India, Hew Delhi. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents (s). I 1 !937 Office of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Gamp, Bahrain. Dated... * St^?. . A^r il &gt; &gt; 193?. I; Reference to previous correspondence: Political Resident's Printed letter No.C/43 of 7th April 1937. Description o Name and Date. 1. letter I o .PA-155 dated the 2nd April 1937 from the Resident Manager, The Bahaain Petroleum Company Ltd. ,Bahrai n, to the Political Agent, Bahrain. 2. Letter ^o.PA-171 of the 13th April 193 7 from the Resident Manager, The Bahrain Petroleum c omi» ny Ltd. ,Banrgi n, to the Political Agent, Bahrain. i J Copy forwarded, wi th comp Agent, Bahrain, for info Printed letter Ho. Apr il Subject. B ahrain on, - Additional Area. ijiments,to the Political mat ion, reference his G/2B3-10/1 of 15 thr? 1 CONFIDENTIAL No. C/4Q 1937# 1-0 5 The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Grulf presents his compliments to 1 0 His Majesty 1 s Secretary of State for India, London. 2. Tiie Foreign Secretary to tne Government of India, Uew Delni. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document h 1 (' Office of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, s.s.Bamora, at Bandar Shahpur. Dated .Tt.h.AP.ril,..1.937, Reference to previous correspondence: Residency Printed letter lio.294 -S of 25th llarch 1937. f I Description o Name and Date. /J fj ' F 1 4 ! Letter Ho.PA-141 dated the 25th March 1937 from tne Resident Manager, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Ltd., Bahrain, to the Political Agent, Bahrain, 1 G/235- 10/I tne Subject. Bahrain Oil - Additional Area, sQopy forwarded, witn coniplimeJjtsj to i&gt;irie Political | Agent, Bahrain, reterence his Printed letter xio. 31st March 1937.The Bahrein petroleum Company Limited iy^&lt; 7* J*?y B ahrein I sland, P ersian G ulf No. PA-165 April 10, 1937. His Britannic Majesty^ Political Agent, Bahrein. /a Dear Sir: We find it desirable to erect a small testing laboratory near our sea line terminal anchorage in Sitra harbor. Ship loading requires frequent testing of the delivered oil at the end of the line and our present nearest available equipment for this purpose is at the Refinery which entails from 3/4 to one hour delay while transporting the samples from the ship. We propose to make a rock fill island of approximately 35 feet by 40 feet dimension upon which we can erect a 12 feet by 16 feet corrugated iron and wood frame shelter for the laboratory. This installation will be 3,900 feet shoreward from our anchorage and where the water will be about 6 feet at low tide^and is shown in red crayon on the accompanying blue print. shipping. This location will not in any way interfere with Though we are certain that this installation will in no way interfere with other interests we ask your approval before proceeding with the work# Yours very truly, I G. W. R. SMITH Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN PSTROLEOM COMPANY LIMITED IWii No. ^-e&gt; of 1356 Office of v the Adviser to the Government, Bahrain, Dated, Maharam 30, 1356 April 11, 1937 From To C. Dalrymple Belgrave, Esquire, G.b.E., Adviser to the Government of Bahrain, Bahrain. His Britannic Majesty's Political iigent, Bahrain. Sir, p'T I have the honour to acknowledge receipt of your No. G/SS^-lO/l dated 31st March 1937 forward ing 'Abstract of accounts for the second half year of 1936 of oil measured under the lease between His Highness the Shaikh of Bahrain and the Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited dated 29th December 1934' and a cheque for Ss 14,58,887/4/9 in settlement of the Royalty account for the second half of 1936. I return herewith three copies of the 'Abstract of accounts' signed by me on behalf of the Bahrain Government and also enclose a receipt in quintuplicate for the above amount. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant. Adviser to the Government. Eho:- J • VAn extract from The 'Iraq Times dated the 25th March 1937. 'The Petroleum Times' says: Despite a decline in the last quarterly output of the year, crude oil production at Bahrain for 1926 was considerably higher, at 4,645,000 barrels, than some of the estimates which have appeared. Quarterly figures of output were: January ~ March, 699,000 barrels; April - June, 929,000 barrels; July - September, 1,768,000 barrels; and October - December, 1,249,000 barrels. Last year's figure is a nearly fourfold increase on the 1935 output of 1,265,000 barrels, and is extra ordinary, compared with 285,000 barrels in 1934 and 31,000 barrels in 1933. m('V-f DURRANFS PRESS CUTTINGS St. Andrew's House, 32 to 34 Holpiqpi Viaduct, and 1 3 St. Andrew Street, Holborn Circus, E.C.I. Telephone; CENTRAL 3149 (Two Line Cutting from the ♦ (.* 1937 Dated March Address of Journal RISE IN BAHREIN CRUDE OIL OUTPUT Despite a decline in the last quarterly output of the year, crude-oil production at Bahrein for 1936 was considerably higher, at 4,645,000 barrels, than some of the estimates which have appeared. Quar terly figures of output were: January-March, 699,000 barrels; April-June, 929,000 barrels; July- September, 1,768,000 barrels; and October- December, 1,249,000 barrels. Last year's figure is a nearly fourfold increase on the 1935 output of i.Si^yOO barrels , and is extraordinary, compared with 285,000 barrels in 1934 and 31,000 barrels in 1933. Lv ''y^. ^ Vti! :Bi ' irIt If No, C/297-10/1 Poiifcicai Bahrain, the 21st ^prli 1937 To The Chief i^ocai Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, I ; j ii jj X i'i» Mth reference to your letter Mo. PA-142 dated the 27th March 1957, I return three copies of the 'Abstract of Accounts' duly signed by the Adviser to the Bahrain Government, end also en close a receipt in quintuplicate for the sum of Dear Sir, lis • 14,58,687-4-9 Yours faithfully for Political Agent, BahrainNo. C/313-10/1 Political Agency, Bahrainj the 24 April 19S7 From Lieutenant-Colonel Gordon Loch, C.I.t,, Political Agent, Bahrain# To Ihe Aaviser to the Bahrain Governnient, B A fl H A I N. Sir, I hcve the honour to inform you that the Chief Local Representative, Xhe Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited states that the Company find it desirable to erect a small testing laboratory near their sea line terminal anchorage in Sitrah a. He explains that ship loading requires frequent testing of the delivered oil at th. end of the line, and the Company's present nearest available equipment for this purpose is Lt the Refinery, which entails from three-fourths to one hour's de lay while transporting the samples from the ship. To obviate this, the Company propose to make a rock fill island of approxi mately 25 feet by 40 feet dimension upon which they can erect a 12 feet by 16 feet corrugated iron and wood frame shelter for the laboratory, this installation will be 2,900 feet shoreward from the Company's anchorage and where trie water will be about 6 feet at low tide, and.is indicated in red crayon on the accompanying blue'print. The Company do not think that this location will in any way interfere with shipping or other interests. 2. Would you kindly let me know whether the Bahrain Govern ment have any objection to the installation. harbour I have the honour to be. OXX | Your most obtdient servant. Sir ^re. ^ Blue print. Lieut-Colonel, Political Agent, Bahrain. return requested.TELEGRAMS : PETCONCESS, BAHREIN PETROLEUM C ORS: Cadman. G.C.M.G. (Chairman) i C.B.E. P.S.O., D.S.C. (French) ' C B E. Kbenkian* (formerly Armenian) P Kessler (Dutch) if 'oyd i rench) jeidel (U'S.A.) Sellers iros CODES : BENTLEY'S SECOND PHRASE NCESSIONS LIMITED BAHREIN PERSIAN GULF 26th, April 1937. To His Britannic Majesty's Political Agent, BAHRAIN. Sir, I send herewith a copy of the Bahrain 1957 Draft Agreement which is being discussed with Mr.Belgrave at 10 |i.mo today. The emendations and additions embodied in this Draft are those made by the London Office of Petroleum Concessions Limited. I am, Sir, Your obedient servant. End: it 1. copy Bahrain Draft 1937. gWy {/r ?&gt; k OA If w* X,' ,K »Lit No. C/S16-10/1 Political Agency, Bahrain, the 26th April i9S7. To jor Frimk Holmes, Petroleum Concessions Limited, BAHRAIN. Dear tir. A? Reference your letter dated the 26th April 1927 ■ • lill you please send us urgently a second copy of the Bahrain Draft 1957 Agreement for immediate transmis sion to the Honourable the Political Resident in the Per sian Gulf. Yours faithfully. (S]c for Political Agent, Bahrain.l/l aential. From No. Ji-u/39 Bahrain, 19th April 1937. Dated, 2 i Am m I* Vi Sib, C. Dalrymple Belgrave, Esquire, C.B.E., Adviser to the Government of Bahrain, Bahrain, Persian Gulf. t , iisguire, Petroleum Concessions, Ltd., Bahrain. . u 1 on sl I have th^honour to acimowledge your letter No. PC1/SA413/272 dated 18th iipril 1937, informing me that ^ajor Frank Holmes, the Company^ repre sentative in the Persian Gulf will be reopening negotiations with the liahrain Government very shortly with regard to the Bahrain unallotted area. I think that it is advisable to inform you that a lengthy delay in opening negotiations is undesirable I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant. Adviser to the Government. Copy to H.B.l's Political Agent, Bahrain.comummKL. Bat ed •vll No.c/88 of 1937. the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Camp, Bahrain, the 16th April, 1937, To The Political Agent, B ahrain. Subject! Bahrain Additional Area oil negotiations. Memorandum . Printed letter No.C-86, dated the 15th April 1937 on the above subject. 2. In order to save time in future please send copies of Mr. Skinner's reports direct to the India Office and Government of India. sd. T.C.Powle, Lieut.-Colonel. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. / Att est ed. for aecretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. y, m i[&lt;(S f fji ^ ^*)/ On the morning of the 19th April Mr. Packer came to see me at his request. He informed me that his Company had given orders to M«.1or Holm es to approach the Bahrain Government in regard to the Additional Area. He promised to send me a copy of the letter. 2. He informed me that the geologists expect to be back in Dubai or Sharjah about the end of April and would like then to see Jabal Faiyah. I told him that I had dis cussed the matter with the lesident and that we were of opinion that it would be necessary to warn the Shaikh that if he could not make arrangements for the geologists who go out we should have to consider some other arrangements. An Express Letter to the Residency Agent is issuing by this air mail. 3. Mr. Packer kindly said that he would let me have reports on; (a) the yearns work in Qatar and the Trucial Coast (not technical just brief results) and also (b) a report on the proposed movements of the different parties, who are shortly to be withdrawn for the hot weather. 4. Mr. Packer told me that at a dance at the Bahrain PofT.,-^1 Q i 1 IT1 Club, Mr .Hamilton had persist^itly asked him for the address of a Syrian named Modujgaaa 1 who had worked a great deal for the Petroleum Concessions Limited at tMr. Packer asked me how I thought 4^ that a Syrian would be regarded on the Trucial Coast. I said that as regards the individual he would probably be regarded as a stranger and would have to prove himself a decent fellow before people would trust him and secondly that I did not know what the views of His Majesty's Governr ment would be towards having a French subject in that part of the world. A 19-4-37.Bv Air Mail. p.z. 2mj wi] INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy has been sent to by Mail. - Sea L / ^ ^ hp a** 4963 2000 7.36 Tl/e ^d^igp/^cretarfj^G^v^mm^toflndia. Pcu^cal Regfdent In the Pers^jj^Gulf. jJljL fyUjXi^Xa-v 0 htdia office VraiTEHALL, S.vT.l. p.Z. 2503/57 p jlst A p ril&gt; 1937. A ir Mail C onfidential My dear Fowle, /f |3 1 With reference to your t-elegram No. 19 8 of the 12th February and connected correspondence, you may caie to know that Lewisohn of Petroleum Concessions Limited dropped a remark to me the other day to the effect that the Company had now decided not to press for the additional area on the main Bahrein Islands, 'but to confine themselves to endeavouring to secure the territorial waters (presumably including the small 'territorial islands') and the Hawar group. I gathered that they were instructing their local people accordingly, I am sending a copy of this letter to Loch. Yours sincerely, (Sgd.) Ml. J. OLAUSOW Hon'ble Lieutenant Colonel T.C.W. Fowle, C.B.E., Consulate General, Bushire./ i n 1 No. Bahrain, ' Dated, 17ttL Safar, 1356. April 28, 1937. From C, Bak-jmple Belgrave, Esquire, C.B.E., Advise^to, 'the Government of Bahrain, W Bahrain, Persian Gulf. To SIK, Lieut-Colonel Gordon Lock, C.I.E., H. B. 1*3 Political Bahrain, Persian Gulf. a f T tave the honour to refer to your letter Mo. C/sfS-lQ/l dated 24th April 1937 and to inform you that the Bahrain Government have no objection to the erection, by the Bahrain Petroleum Company, Limited, of a small testing laboratory near their sea line terminal anchorage in Sitrah harbour. 2. Tbe Blue print is returned herewith as requested, I have the i^iour to be, Sir, Your Most Obedient Servant. Adviser to the Government. v End. 1. f\ n iU t&gt;l \ ' r. 1^ i } '&gt; LTELEGRAMS : PETCONCESS, BAHREIN IECTORS : John Cadman, G.C.M.G. (Chairman) Agnew, C.B.E. Cayrol, D.S.O., D.S.C. (French) fraser, C.B.E. S.Gulbenkian (formerly Armenian) LA. Kessler (Dutch) John B. Lloyd Meny (French) .Seidel (U.S.A.) (V, Sellers kliros PETROLEUM CODES ; BENTLEY'S SECOND PHRASE SSIONS LIMITED r\ \\ } BAHREIN PERSIAN GULF 28th, April 1957. 1^ iM' To n, U His Britannic Majesty's Political Agent, Balirain. Sir, Please refer to my letter of April 26th 1957. I send herewith a copy of the notes of a meeting held at the Customs House on 26th April at which the Bahrain Draft Concession 1957 was presented to Mr. Belgrave and discussed with him, There is also a note of a conversation Mr 0 Belgrave this morning. I am. Sir, Your obedient servant.-E- • ♦ ♦ A form of compromise was aissyss©d, viz. - that the island should be included la the eonoessloa area with the reservation that ao work should take place witbout the specific approval of the Ruler. It wa® brought to notice tbut it ms desirable to pro-ride against the contingency tbet the Suler or bis successors faight change their point of view regarding Us Nisan in which case the Company holding the concession would have no protection against possible opposing interests unless some such coaproralse was included In the agreement. Kr.Belgr&amp;re agreed to raise the question of Vm Fiaan aptin with H. E» the Ruler with a view to obtaining either limited rights to drill (which Mr .Bel ^rave thought unlikely) or at least protection for the Company getting the concession against future complications (described above). 3, Mr.Belgrave accepted all the other tainor umend- ments and additions of the latest draft. He however considered that It would be advisable in all the circumstances at present to reduce the minimum of 2000 Tons in the clause dealing with oil in conaaerclal quantities. Mo,1or Holmes agreed to cable London suggest lag a mlnimam of 650 Tons per day for 30 consecutive days. 4. Mr.Belgrave raised the question of the Company's commitiieats in the event of the Company being desirous of giving up the concession during the first 6 years. • Major Holmes shewed him thatthis was provided for in terms which should be satisfactory to the Buler in the Concession agreement and Mr.Selgrave agreed. 5. In reply to a question by Ma .lor Holmes Mr.Belgrave stated that he considered that he would need about a wee: (not longer) to consult H.H. the Buler k get his decisions. 6, Major Eolaes intimated that he expected to return to Sharjah (&amp;. Dubai) on May 2nd. The undersigned agree that the above suMaary covers the essential matters discussed at the above meeting. SignatureADDENDUM NO.l 28/4/37. Reference paragraph 3, 'oil in commercial quantities' - As a result of a telegram from Petroleum Concessions Limited, London Major Holmes and Mr.Dalrymple Belgrave re-discussed this point and it was finally agreed that Major Holmes would re commend to London a minimum of 1000 Tons and Mr.Belgrave agreed to put this offer to H.H. the Ruler. The undersigned agree that the above addendum covers the essential points of the con versation of the 28th April. Signature Signature ignatureCUSTOMS DEPARTMENT. Ho FA/a$h/y.lir:. . . . f 3 OMAR. 1937 H.B .M' s Political Agenl BAHRAIN: 30th March, 1937., 18th Muhurr-um, 1356. ffiMORMDUM:# In reference to your No.C/179-10/1 of the 5-3-37., might I venture to suggest that the particulars sought are to be found in my fortnightly shipping reports, — (A- .J | ''I ( k / OF , and PORT OFFICER. BAHRAIN:</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000200_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/401</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000200</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/401</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 10/1 XIV Bahrain Oil Concession'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1936/1937</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-02-25T12:10:11</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">ara</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (270 folios)</extent><extent>The documents in the volume are arranged in chronological order. There is an index at the end of the volume, (folios 227-240). The index is arranged chronologically and refers to documents within the volume; it gives brief description of the correspondence with a reference number, which refers back to that correspondence in the volume.</extent><extent>The foliation commences on the 4th sheet and terminates at the 4th sheet from the back of the volume; numbering is written in pencil, from folio 226 circled, and can be found in the top right corner of the recto. The numbering starts with 1a, 1b and 1c; 2; 3a, 3b and 3c; 4-37; 38a, 38b, 38c, 38d, 38e, 38f and 38g; 39-63 (64 is omitted); 65-73; 74A and 75B; 76A and 76B; 77-82; 83A and 83B; 84-105; 106A and 106B; 107-112; 113A, 113B, 113C and 113D; 114-119; 120a, 120b and 120c; 121-161; 162A and 162B; 163A and 163B; 164A and 164B; 165A and 165B; 166A and 166B; 167-170; 171A and 171B; 172-240; and then it ends with 241A and 241B, which are the last numbers given to the volume.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The volume contains minutes of meetings at Office of the Secretary of State for India in London, correspondence and telegrams between the Political Agent in Bahrain, the Political Resident in Bushire, the Financial Adviser to the Government in Bahrain, Charles Dalrymple Belgrave, and representatives of the Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited (BAPCO) on the acquisition by Texas Corporation and Standard Oil Company of California of the share control of BAPCO.The volume includes:abstracts of accounts of oil measured during 1936 and 'Statement on Royalty' for 1936 (ff. 21, 188);copy in English and Arabic of the deed of modification of the 1934 Lease, agreed on 3 June 1936 between Sheikh of Bahrain 'Isa al Khalifah and BAPCO, on the opening of a refinery and on the exemption from State, Municipal and custom taxes for BAPCO (ff. 38c- 38f);'1936 Annual Report' including 'Status of Bahrein [sic] Wells as of December 31, 1936' (ff. 173-184);There are newspaper cuttings on oil in the Gulf and several maps within the volume:'Proposed Reservation for Refinery, Water Wells and Lines to Sitra' (3 copies, ff. 54, 85,146);Area Map Refinery to Ship's anchorage Bahrain (f. 207);'General Map of Bahrein [sic] Island' (f. 241b).There are some letters and documents in Arabic.There is an index at the end of the volume (folios 227-240).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Arabian American Oil Company</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Adviser to the Government of Bahrain</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Bahrain Petroleum Company</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Bahrain Political Agency, Confidential Office</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Secretary of State for India and Burma, United Kingdom</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Secretary of State for India, United Kingdom</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>King of Bahrain</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Bahrain Political Agency</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">creator</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Agent</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">creator</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="personal"><namePart>King of Saudi Arabia Sa'ūd bin 'Abd al-'Azīz Āl Sa'ūd</namePart></name></subject><subject><topic>Petroleum industry</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000200#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>