<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000094_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-12T02:16:58.224Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">ml' Cover for Enclosures in Weekly Letter No. dated from Secretary, Political and Secret Department, India Office, to Secretary, Foreign and Political Department, Government of India, INDIAN STATESo uuany further communication on . : Ws s'^' ct, please quote No.K 8326/1320/291. and address, r 7 Ij A&gt;H HI not to any person by name, but to- “The Under-Secretary of State,’' Foreign Office. London, S.W. i. Foreign Office S.W. 1. 18th February, 1938. Sir, hf With reference to India Office letter P.Z.94/38 of the 22nd January, regarding the provision of a new motor launch for the Political Agent at Koweit, I am directed by Mr. Secretary Eden to state, for the information of the Secretary of State for India, that sanction has been obtained for the charge to Imperial revenues of a moiety of the increased expenditure of 1,600 rupees over the original estimate for the launch and that Mr. Eden agrees that this expenditure may now be incurred. I am, Sir, Your obedient Servant, COPY SENT 'V nn MAf* u&gt; lA* a i The Under Secretary of State, India Office. 10 FELjn/DIA. FILEf-^ 3 ^f- : .94 49 Iword^j 3 Q / {k4/, &amp; 30. PS C 0 0 E . 0 g T B L B 0 R A M . From (COPIES CIRCULATED) Dated Government of India, External Affairs Dept,, to Secretary of State for India. Received New Delhi, 4th Jan.1936. 4th Jan. 1938, 2~45 p.m. If §4* Reference India Office telegram 'fXLf No, 114 (si c, ? 390) , February 4th, 1937, and Bushire express letter No.2320/33/25 of 27th November, 1937, copy sent to you direct. New motor launch for Kcweito Government of India agree to increase of Rs:1600 over the original estimate. Concurrence of Hia Majesty's Government to bear moiety of the increased cost may kindly be intimated by telegraph.9 FILE r GOVERNMENT OF INDIA] P.Z. 7976 Department. , 1937 j j EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MXILT r ...... -- -.... ' ^ ' ’ laan R ''Ik AL message eentby AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more ' ~~ /\ txpe. » tons than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be treated, Cr on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been leleraphed. To save time and to obviate * * Jorma iti&amp;&gt; tt ts drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department ] •&gt; L/ /33/25 Bat pc! B ^ re % Dated *M?%eihi' the ^ * kov ember. 19 37 * To Foreign, Kew Delhi. Hi &amp; Iteforenc© Dm correspondence ending with Oovernment of India, Foreign and Political DepartBient Express Letter Ho. f.267-a/ 36, dated 12th February, 1937, regarding new launch for Kuwait. 2. political Agent now reports anticipated excess expenditure of fis. 1,600 over sanctioned amount of Es. 11,000/- for following reasons j - (1) The actual cost of Thorny croft engine c.i.f Kuwait amounts to Es. 7,930 as compared witn fcs. 7,302 estimated in 1936. The rise in the manufacturer^ price since the estimate was made is connected with the rise in the price of iron and steel. ( 2 ) The actual cost of construction of hull, including decking, lavatory, bedding of engine, fenders sails etc. will be Es. 4,436/- as compared with Es. 3,890/- previously estimated. The excess is mainly due to subsequent rise in price of Malabar teak wood from !U 15/- to fc. 20 per plank ( 20 *x !•* 1 ») and in wages of carpenters from fc. 3 /. to Es. 5/- per diem in consequence of hesvy demand created by construc tion of the Kuwait Oil Company’s new camp at Maqua. ^3) .An extra amount 01 Es. 250/— is required for minor essential items such as electric fittings which were not included in the origins BEd). POL DEPT, KJfDECBBa INDIA OFFICE {Signature) e Stine te./ ■ S. 44* {Designation)-*** *^liu~ -2 e atimate • 3. Request sanction to extre expenditure of Rs. 1,600/ may be communicated by telegram. 4. Additional provision to meet the expenditure involved in the current year *ill be required. 5. A copy of this communication is being sent to His Majesty's secretary of State for India, as it vill be neces sary to ask His Majesty's Government to accept a moiety of the excels expenditure. R3SIDEKT - The issue of the above has been authorised. Se ere to the Political Resident In the Persian Gulf.PI In any further communication on this subject, please quote No. K 1426/1^26/291. and address, not to any person by name, but to— “ The Under-Secretary of State,” Foreign Office, London, S.W. i. r P. Z. 943 Foreign Office. ' S.W. 1. V 937 j 6 tli Fetruary, 1937. 1 p&lt;I Sir, / '' V 1 / With reference to India Office letter P.2*8515/36 heckA^' To pssTt, 'aToJV I9B5 ;937 of the 21st December last regarding the provision of a new motor launch for the Political Agent at Koweib, I am directed hy Mr* Secretary Eden to inform you that sanction has been obtained for the payment, as a charge to Imperial funds, of a moiety of the cost of the new motor launch, estimated at about 11,000 rupees. I am, flrfc sir » Your obedient Servant, [AaJ' ' ^ • i ' J yL RECd. P3L r 9 FEB 1937 INDIA O Or,- C E| The Under-Secretary of State, India Office. / 93J siGOVERNMENT OF INDIA. Foreign and Political Department. 1937 EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). [N.B .—This is an ORIGINAL message sentby AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more India Office letter P*Z#8515/36, dated 21st December 1936 regarding new motor launch Kuwait. Political Resident has asked for telegraphic sanction to put work in hand as early as possible as present launch is reported unseaworthy. No expenditure will be incurred before 1937-38. expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to treated^ on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been teleraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department.] No. F.267-A/36 xxxx New Delin' the 3.0 ^ January 19 37 Dated To Secretary of State for India, London The issue of the above has been authorised L for Foreign Secretary to the Government of India to U? , {Signature) 3 0-JAN1337, INDIA OFFICE [Designation)indexed Prom The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, To The Under Secretary of State for India, Political Department, India Office. Dated New Delhi, the //^ovemher 1936. Subject: - Provision of a new motor launch for the Political Agent, Kuwait. / i /vo' I &gt; v Sir, I am directed to refer to the letter from the Hon‘hie the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, No.C/183 of 1936 dated the 30th September 1936, a copy of which was sent to the India Office with the Foreign Secretary r s weekly letter No.189 M, dated the 15th October 1936, and to state that hie &gt;- ———■ Government of India consider it desirable to replace the existing launch which is unreliable and unseaworthy by a now motor launch as early as possible. It is therefore r uO u. es ted that His Majesty r s Government may/moved to agree to the proposed construction locally of a new motor launch at a cost approxi mately of Rs.11,000/- and to bear a moiety of the expenditure for which provision will be made in the budget for 1937-38. The sale proceeds of the old launch will be credited to the Government of India and His Majesty's Government in moieties. be I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant, for Foreign Secretary to the Government of India.» A13 MAIL. MO.'V' 103 of • ia * ~- ifftc« of Political rtcoiocnt in the Per* inn Gulf, Camp, '-'unalt. Dated the 30th September, IGJ'i. Gulf* . The yoreign Secretary to the Ooyernraent cf India, 1 nave the honour to refer to uty teietrao Ho. 642 dated the 16th 8ept«ber 1336 reoonwend iat the ceaetr uot u&gt;n in *&lt;Uwait of a new motor launch for the Political Agent, Kuwait. 8. in the correspondence ending with their Memorandum So .31-333-trat• dated the 10th January 1923 the Oorernment of India sanctioned the purchase of a seoofidbnnd motor i-unen for the Pelitioal Agent, Kuwait, at acoet of aa.6000/- 'his launch waf built by Heaere. Beasley &amp; Kemp in 1917 and was used by the Mesopotamia 'ixpeditionary Joroe till it aas purchased for the Political Agent, Kuwait, in 1922. It has been in use for eome 19 years in hare conditions, a;*i n s become unreliable and unoeaworthy. A copy i# enclose ox a surrey hy Lloyds' Agents at Basrah. I would only u du to; t to my o*n knowledge the Irunoh i» dan^erou* end whenerer there ie any sea running the Political Agent has to toorro* one of the Shaikh* s l&amp;unohes, lie for example at aay arrival on aay present visit. It is undejimuie that the political Agent should be placed in auch a position. The need for a launch tec been Rccepted in the past. Simla. Subject: provision of a new motor launch for the Political Agent, Kuwait. Sir, but / 3.-2- but is nos even greater, osing to the development of the ruwait Oil Coras* ny 1 ® field whioh necessitates frequent visits of the Political Agent to the northern shore of the Kuwait bay and the Khor Subiyah ares and owing to the aetlvltlea of the 9 Iraqi customs launches in Kuwait waters* 4* The Political Agent, Kuwait, proposes that he should be provided with a locally built 9 dhow 9 launch and estimates the cost (baaed on actual experience In Tfehrcd n) at Ra*ll,192/~, of which detaila are given in the attached statement* 5* a Thorny croft engine has been selected, as experience ha a shown them to oe suitable end it la understood that the Kuwait Oil Company are going to use Thornyoroft engines, so that it will be possible to have the benefit of expert help at hand in case of difficulty and of spares being available on the spot* 6. I strongly support the Political Agent's proposal in the light of the experience which I have gained at Bahrain (a) in carrying out the alterations (amounting virtually to reconstruction owing to her rotten condition) to the Bahrain a Agency launch ‘•Felix Jones*, which converted her into «n J admirable sea-boat, * see the correspondence ending withal letter No.7.566 -a/ 33 dated the 7th ( December 1933 from the Government of \ Indie in the foreign end Political ' In capable of going out Department almost any see: . . - - - —- 1 . and also (b) in the course of the construction of a dhow-launch for Rear Admiral J.V.Creagh, the late Senior Naval Officer, in which he would have travelled to fnglend but for the Italo-Ateyssinian hostilities. These craft have proved themselves a success in local conditions and are especially well suited to use by an Arab crew* 7. I accordingly have the honour to request that the Government of India may be pleased to authorise the construction locally /locally of a launch for the Political Agent, Kuwait, at a coot of la. 11,000/- anci to make the necooaory ^roTiaion in the ensuing year*a budget. 8. It is hoped that It will be possible to obtain a few hunired rupees by the sale of the old launch at 'Saerah. I hfcYe the honour to be. Sir, Yoi\r noot obedient eervant, sd, G.Loch. Lieut ••Colonel. officiating Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.LLOYD’S AGENCY Copy, BASRAH. CERTIFICATE No. 95 . Baarah, Slot Sept ember , 1 93 6 . He $ The Mesopotamia Persia Corporation,Ltd. t LLOYD’S AGENTS IN PERSIAN GULF, haviiig on the 16th day of September 1936 been requested by the Political Agent, Kuwait, to survey and report on the motor launch 'KOvyEIT* HEREBY CERTIFY That we appointed Mr,J.G,B.Fuller as our Surveyor. That the enclosed is his Report. That we believe confidence may be placed in same. That the coat of this Certificate, including the Surveyor’s fees of £.4/4/0 (Four Guineas) is £.6/6/0 (Six Guineas), which has been paid to us by the applicant for the survey. That the following expenses incurred by us in connection with the survey have also been paid to us by the above applicant Transport to Koweit and return Pass per t fee ... ... Late fee for passport ... Telegram charge ... I.D.6-700 • 0-682. 0-480. 0-090. I.D.6-952 THE MESOPOTAMIA PERSIA CORPORATION,LTD. LLOYD’S AGENTS IN PERSIAN GULF.Copy, Certificate No, 95, ■Basrah, 21st September 19 36, On 20th September 1936 I proceeded to Koweit to examine and survey the Motor Launch 'KOCSIT' belonging to the Political Department, and the following is icy report HULL , The copper sheathing in patched and torn condition especially round after quarters where wooden hull beneath is rotted in places giving no grip to the nails for the copper I sheathing. The inside ribs or wooden frames are broken and rotted away from aft. up to the engine space. The wooden box carrying the stern tube rotten in places. The cabin sides and wooden awning are in wa ped and shruken condition, the tonguing anxi grooving splintered away in many places. ENGINE. GARDNER - FOUR CYLINDTffl . The working rts of the engine are being badly worn including the gear box wheels; there is very little compression in the cylinders due to wear. The insulation on the armatures of the two magnetos is badly perished causing numerous shorts and the magnetos practically useless# Fufel and water tanks are badly corroded. RSCOMXTNUATION . In ny opinion the launch is unseawortby. The engine is more than 20 years old, and has been out of production by the manufacturers for msgay years, making it very difficult and expensive to obtain any spare parts#Particulars of boat for Political Agent, Kuwait• Hull , (a) Locally constructed built 45* keel, beam 14*6* very heavy built of one inch teak planks and selected local wood ribs Rs. 2600. (b) Wages of carpenters, wooden planks, copper nails and other miscellaneous expenses for decking, lavatory and bedding of engine. Provision of fenders, sails, anchors, ropes etc. .. ' 1290, Engine . Thorny croft 55 H.P. 6 -Cyl inder poppet valve type R.I)/ 6 , outfit A.B.C. reversing gear 2k to 1, to use paraffin, delivery at Kuwait including cost of installation, •••• * 730,2. Total ,,, Ra. 11,192/- *******27 INDIA OFFICE, WHITEHALL, S. 7.1. 14th December, 1922. Sir, In reply to your letter of the 18th October 1922, / No.3127-533-Est., regarding the replacement of the steam launch 'Lewis Pelly' at Koweit by a motor launch, I am directed to say that the Secretary of State for India confirms the action of the Government of India in sanctioning the purchase of a motor launch at a cost of Rs.6000 initial and an annual grant of Rs .2500 for upkeep. I am, etc. (Sd) L.D. WAKELY. P.4455/22. O The Under Secretary to the Government of India, Foreign and Political Department.7 3 ./ # P-4455/22. -■ No. 3127-533-Est. Prom The Under Secretary to the Government of India, in the Foreign and Political Department, To His Majesty 1 s Under Secretary of State for India, London. Dated Simla, the 18th October 1922. Replacement of the steam launch 'Lewis Pelly' at Koweit 'by a motor launch. Sir, I am directed to refer to the telegram from the Government of India to His Majesty’s Secretary of State for India, No.1170-E.B., dated the 14th March 1906 and subsequent correspondence regarding the provision of a launch for Koweit. 2. Conditions have changed and it is no longer essential for the Political Agent to visit the islands and adjacent coasts of Koweit and it is sufficient for him to have at his disposal a good harbour launch. The present steam launch the 'Lewis Pelly”, is expensive to maintain and unsuitable for harbour work. In pursuance of their policy of retrenchment the Government of India therefore suggested to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf that it might be economical to substitute an open harbour launch for the 'Lewis Pelly' and directed that the 'Lewis Pelly' should be towed to Bombay for sale, as it was impossible to dispose of her locally. The 'Lewis Pelly' left the Persian Gulf for Bombay on the 20th May 1922.3« The Political Resident at Bushire recommended the purchase from the Disposals Authorities at Basrah of a motor launch M.T. 6 *, as specified in the margin, at a cost of Rs«5000/-. A further initial sum of Rs.1000/- was required ”' 777 “ to cover the cost of overhauling Built hy Beasley and Kemp in 1917 ) length 5V &gt; Beam 10*4’' Depth 4*6” and also an annual grant of (light 36”) Speed 8.5 knots. ) Hull - Wood carvel, copper sheathed.) Rs*2500 for upkeep. The annual grant Engines - 4 cylinder, single screw, Manchester Gardner Motor Co. 50 horsepower. Rune on petrol. Consumption 125 gallons per 24 hours ’’Lewis Pelly' is to he sold, it is expected that it will he possible to meet the above charges from savings in this grant. In future years there will he an annual saving of Rs.8500 on the cost of upkeep. 4- As the offer of the motor launch was open for a limited period only, the Government of India instructed the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf to purchase it on the terras stated and I am to request that the action of the Government of India may he confirmed. I have, etc. (Sd) P.G. LOCH. Under Secretary to the Government of India. for the upkeep of the ’’Lewis Pelly” is Rs.11000/- and, as theP.z. 587/34 Extract from letter of proceedings, H.M.S.'BIDEFORD'. Period:- 12 th October - 25th October 1933. BASIDU AND BAHRAIN. 10. Arrived Bahrain at 1045 on 24th October. It was found that the engine of 'FELIX JONES' would not start, due to a fractured casting to the Water Service Pump. Ship* s Artificers were able to make good the defect and Launch was turned over to the Political Agent A.M. 25th OctoberV € v flbk Copy of letter liro.22&amp;0» dated the 1st UoYember 1933, from the Hon*tie the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, to the Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, Hew Delhi, ^ 1 M 1 ^ 0 fj \ ‘ I have the honour to refer to your letter Ho,F,277-A/31, dated the ISth May 19 33 in which sanction was accorded to the disposal of the launched 'John Lambert' and 'Felix Jones', 2, I have issued orders to the Political Agent, Bahrain to dispose of the 'John Lambert', through a local broker for the best price that he can get, 3, The Political Agent has represented that it is essential to provide a new launch for Bahrain in place of the 'John Lambert' and contemplated recommending the possession of a launch something on the lines of, but rather larger, than the motor dhow recently built for this Residency. 4, During his recent tour to the Trucial Coast, however, Lieut-Colonel Loch inspected the 'Felix Jones' at Basidu, and consulted the Senior Haval Officer and others about her. As a result he is prepared to take her for Bahrain in place of asking for a new launch and to endeavour to run her on the existing launch grant. He cannot, naturally be sure that the arrange ment will prove a success, but, after consulting with the Senior Haval Officer and other officers, he believes that by certain snail alterations, the cost of which will be met from the existing launch grant, which can be done by a boat^builder in Bahrain, he can so improve ENCL03UF: IN her sea-going qualities as to meet the requirements of [185 Bahrain. 7 EC. j l27lhC. 3 ......2 ;~ 5. I trust that the Govermaent of India will approve of this arrangement, as if successful, it will obviate the expense of purchasing a new launch. 6. The Senior Haval Officer, Persian Gulf has an opportunity of arranging to ^ow the *Pelix Jones'* to Bahrain shortly and I have, therefore, asked him to do so in anticipation of the approval of the Government of India, as the cost of transport by a steamer of Messers P. C. Strik Ltd., would, I understand, be fis.750/-* 2Ho*5** 366-A/33 From The AdaliDeput^y Secretary to tile Goveraiaect of laii* in the Foreign and Political Department# The Hon*hie the Political Heaident in the Persian Gulf* Delhi# the December 1932, Subjecti- Launch for Bahrain. Sir, With reference to your letter So.2250# dated the let SoTember 1933# I am directed to aay that the Government of India approve of your proposals regarding the 'Felix Jones' being sent to Bahrain and run, as far as possible, on the existing launch grant, the cost of the neceseary alterations also being met from that grant. I have the honour to be, Sir# Your most obedient servant, Sd. V. Harahari Rao, Addlt Deputy Secretary to the Government of India,(^S \ M dexed 9 r 1933 Copy of a memorandum Uo. 589 of 1953, dated the 19th I,'arch 1933, from the Kon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, to the Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, ITew Delhi. Sale of Launches ’’John Lambert' and 'Felix Jones'. Reference this Resiaency memorandum L'o. 372, 2. The Political Agent Bahrain reports that neither Imperial Airways Limited nor tne Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited are desirous of purchasing either of the launches.p.z. 1815 / 1933 . Extract from areport of proceedings of ih-Ohief, East Indies. ^ * BAIIKAIN . 17 th - 20t h Dece mb er, 1952 . x xx 6c During the visit the Commander-in-Chief and the Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, were the guests of Colonel Loch, the Political Agent, who was extremely helpful in organising everything connected with the visit. In order to assist in the maintenance of British prestige in this important centre of the Gulf, it is very desirable that the Political Agent should be provided with a suitable motor boat in which to visit ships at the anchor age. His arrival in a very dirty looking shore boat, flying a British flag, is as painful to him as to those upon whom he has to call, X XX27 @ MuC(^ J Copy of a Memorlmdum No, 372, dated Bushlre', ^ the 18th February 1933. Ao» .the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf to the Foreign Secretary to the Government of India,to New Delhi. Sale of Launches 'John Lambert' and 'Felix Jones'. Reference Government of India memorandum No. F. 277-A/31, dated the 31st January 1933. The Political Agent, Bahrain, was asked to institute necessary enquiries in the matter and a reply from him is awaited. Some delay is inevitable as the Cairo and London offices of the Imperial Airways were to be addressed in the matter.in the foreign and Political Department* To - The Hon 1 die the Political Resident in the Persian Gull* Memorandum Ro.F.277- J A/3i« Sale of launches 'John Lambert' ana 'Felix Jones'* Reference /our mepor&amp;nuum Ko*F*1722 9 uated the he is unable to assist in the disposal of the launches* The Director of Contracts* Army headquarters* who was also consulted* states that he can only assist in the disposal of the vessels if tney could oe orought to any of the Indian Ports* it is understoou that they aie not sea-going crafts* and consequently they cannot be economically brought to the Indian Coast* he* however suggests that the imperial Airways* Bahiem* may be interested in the purchase of tne launches* Please thereiore institute necessary enquiries ana intimate result in due course* 25th August 1952. v '^ 2* The Director* ao; The Director* Aoy&amp;l Indian Marine * states that Sd. V. Narahari Rao Under Secretary to the Government of India* I MOLOSUHt \r FOREIGN SECP5 r A - r\ r ■ i l :)&lt;■ '* I OCT ^ l i ' 103 2 1 From — The Under Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, To — The Hon , hle the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Memorandum H0.F.277-A/31. Dated Simla, the 5th August 1932. Sale of the launch •John Lambert*. Reference memorandum from the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department tto.F.277-A/ ^ 31 , dated the 7th June 1932. The Government of India will be glad to know whether any suitable offer has been received for the •John Lambert*. Sd. V. Harahari Rao, Under Secretary to the Government of India. ' III ENCLOSURE IN INDIA FOREIGN SECRETARY’S Letter No a 2.9 m. i Dated ,1; SEP. 1938 Received c 0C1. 1952tfrom The Hon*ole the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf* To The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, S i m 1 a . Memorandum Mo*17^2. Dated Bushire, the 25th August 1952* Sal© of&gt; launch ‘•John Lambert 11 * Reference Foreign and Political Department memorandum Mo.277-A/31 dated the 5th August 1932. Following advertisements inserted in the Iraq and Karachi newspapers regarding the sale of the^steam launch 'John Lambert M enquiries were received from private firms in Karachi and from the High Commissioner, Baghdad on behalf of the Iraqi Government, calling for further particulars about the vessel. The particulars were duly furnished and the Iraqi Government have replied that the vessel is not suitable for tne purpose for which they require it* It is very unlikely that I shall be able to sell the “John Lambert' or even the 'Felix Jones', the motor cabin cruiser at Bandar Abbas and I would therefore suggest that the Director, Royal Indian Marinemay be asked if he can assist in regard to their disposal. Sd. E. H. Gastrell* for Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.i a % ^ . fc k'-- A 780 1 ,^ CQpY 3 J* 1 A Copy of s memorandum No • 1008, dated Bush ire the 13th May 19 32, from the Hon* ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, to the Foreign Secretary to the Govern ment of India, Simla. Sale of launch 'John Lambert” . 133 / Reference your memorandum No.F.277-A/31, dated, New Delhi, the 10th February 1932. In addition to the 'John Lambert” the Political Agent, Bahrain, h e a small motor launch which is adequate for ship to shore work. He can hire a larger and sea- goin^, craft should it be necessary for him to tour. He will not therefore be seriously inconvemdenoed if the '♦John Lambe rt” is disposed of.from- Th« Under i*ecr«tary to the aoYernment of Indie in the Shreign «nd Political 'jepartnaentf To - The Hon*hie the Political fteeident in the Persian Gulf* femora ndun %&gt;. f*277-A/3i* Gated Simla, the June 1932. &gt; dal« of the l«unoh 'John ■Laatert'. Reference corre epondenoe ending with your memo re ndum So. 1008, dated the 13th *y 1932. 2. The Qowerniaent of India are pleased toauthorlee m you to adYertiee the eale of the launch •John L• 2 abert ,, in the newspepere of *Xraq and Karachi *♦ Sd. V. Narahari Ffeo* Under ^feoretery to the GoY^rnraent of Indie.r I&gt; 7. -1 X X1 I O U I r\ i a it innft Gopyj of a mefydyandiiin Ho. 164, dated Bushire, the £5rd January 1932, from the Hon»ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf to the Poreien Secretary to the Government of India, Hew Delhi, bale of Launch ** John Lambert' 1 . H/c 7'f/ 3 ^ I « ’7 ^ yf. Reference correspondence ending with Government of V ~-c. 4^ India, foreign and Political Department memorandum Ho: 277-A/31, dated the 10th November 1931. In order to meet with the wishes of the Government of India for economy, the Political Agent, Bahrain, was directed to place the above vessel on a care and main tenance basis with a reduced crew. During his recent visit to Bahrain -colonel Biscoe discussed the question of the launch and it Vvas dgreeo. that it should be sold. Before, however, sealing her it will be necessary to send her to Abadan for dockinr and this cannot be done till after the winter is over as she will have to be towed. In the meantime I request that Government c- India w iH be pleased to authorise me to advertise the sale of the above vessel in the newspapers of ’Iraq and Karachi. 'V? UUObUrtt w INDIA FOREIGN SECB -va' Letter No 2l&gt; M. Dated 11 FEB. 1332 ✓W. rrn 1070C\ I A II 4/\r7ftk 1'rott--— IJnd«r ? ecret^ry to tlv» Go^ernaont oi India in th« Foreign and Political ^epartm^ntt To The Hon*hie the Political fleeidcnt in the Persian Gulf* Memorandum So* K.£77 -a/!M* j.pt Dated K«* .ielhi, thf 10 Xchruary 193J ♦ Subjects* tale of launch * John Lambert** Heference your memorandum Ho* 164, dated the 2Zrd January 1952* 2* The Goternraent of India will be glad to h&amp;w* a detailed account of the arrangement propoeed for the future, in regard to a launch for the Agency* hie it not quite clear from the correspondence. Ld/-. Y. Uarahari Rao. Dnder Secretary to the Corernment of Indiaft Copy of an extract from memorandum No# 1553» dated :u Bush ire, 26 th July 1931, from the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, to the foreign Secretary to the Government of India, Simla# Reference correspondence ending with my telegram No. 400, dated the 14th July 1931 • 5. Bundar Abbas - Launch Grant - The grant originally in the current years estimates, and owing to the launch having recently been overhauled, it will be possible to reduce the grant permanently to Rs. 11,000 for the next few years. The launch has been considered by competent Naval Authorities to be unsafe for voyages in an open sea and it is moreover more expensive to run than modern vessels of its size and speed. It would, therefore, be in the long run economical to replace the launch by a motor dhow which would combine seaworthiness and cheap running. I would, therefore, recommend that the 'Felix Jones' 03 so^d if a reasonable price be obtained, and arrangements made to supply the Consul with a motor dhow trie cost of inhich would be about Rs. 7,500 and the recurring charges for its running and maintenance Rs. 6,030 per a nnum. x X X- X x Bahrein - Launch Grant - The fixed grant under this head was Rs. 16,000 but has been reduced to Rs. 14,000 in the current years* estimates; I have now further reduced this figure to Rs. 9,000 for the next and ensuing years Reduction in the Expenditure of the Central GO’vernment. ... • • x X X sanctioned was Rs. 15,000. It has been reduced to Rs.13,000 subjectrv r\ i * n *t\rrn, subject to the Government of India’s acceptance of the proposals which I give below. As the present steam launch 'John Lambert' is very expensive to maintain, I would suggest that it should be sold as soon as possible. In its place I propose to send to Bahrein the motor launch 'Percy Cox' which has been refitted and is suitable for harbour work. The sale of this vessel was ordered by the Government ^of^ndia vide their memorandum No. 58(3)-A/29# dated trie Ijrh uod rj A 1930, but it is presumed that the intention of the Government of India will be met by the proposed transfer, For tours to the Arab Coast which the Political Agent is occasionally called upon to make, it will be necessary for him to hire a local vessel, and I have provided Rs. 3,000 for this purpose. But this can only be regarded as a temporary arrange ment and as soon as funds are available, the 'Percy Cox' should be replaced by a motor dhow which will serve both purposes and at the sane time be cheap to maintain. 2E :Copy of a memorandum Uo* 2013» dated Buahire* the Hon* ble the 27th September* 19 31* from the^/Political Resident in the Persian Gulf* to the Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, Si#LU • Reference my memorandum No* 1553* dated the 26th July 19 31, para 7. 2. Political Agent, Bahrein, informs me that he does not consider that the 'Percy Cox' is sufficiently seaworthy for Bahrein waters during the winter months* I am therefore advertising her for sale and will address you further if any suitable offer is received.Telegram Iitt&gt;*523* dated 9 th-Orecd^i^th) October 1931* From « . . Political Resident, Bushire. To • • • • Polindia, Simla • IMPORTANT, Your telegram of 6th October 1068-A# By abolition of Indian personnel in Escorts in Persian Gulf about Ha. 15,000/- can be (group omitted) saved. This is under consideration vide my letter of 6th October Ho. 2070. Abolition of launch at Bunder Abbaa would sav« Rs. 11,000/- . Rs. 4,000/- will be surrendered under othe heads that is Rs. 30,000 in all. Does this meet your approval?Telegram Ho. 6(Simla camp) dated the 20th October 1931. From « • • Foreign, Simla* To ... • Political, Bushire. Your telegram of October 15th 535. Proposal in your telegram October 9th 528 approved. Ho further action regarding establishment.m From- The Under Lieoretery to the Uore rii jent of India in the foreign and l*'olitieaL ^epertm^Rt# To - The Hon* hie the ?oiitioal Heaident in the Persian Gulf* e «io ran dura &amp;o. ¥*211 « ted few Delhi* ihe/oZ / iber l#§i,i _ ^UDCheg at Bahrein and i undajr AbtMe . Reference oorreepocdenoe ending with Government of India Foreign and Political ^epartxaent telegram Ho* 6(iii/ala Ga.'np)» dated the 20tn Oetoh^r 19 31* 2* It ie preeumed that the proposal for the replacement of the launch at Bunder /ihhaa by a motor dhow at a oo at of ia. 7»500 la to be re^rcted ae oanoalled* Pieaee confina« 3* The Goverrr»nt of India have no objection to the sale of the steam launches “Percy Cox' and 'fellx Jones* provided eui table of fere are received* Sd • V • Na raha ri Ra© • Under secretary to the Government of India*DRAFT TELEGRAM PUT AWAY WITH itn. SECRETARY OF STATE VICEROY, FOREIGN AND POLITICAL DEPARTMENT. Sic* “I- Pcdici __ fyroH^ ^ 'C\ i a ft i J rr rv la any furtKer couununication on this subject, please quote r&gt;No. K 1460/1460/234 and address— not to any person by name, but to— The Under-Secretary of State.’’ Foreign Office, London, S.W. 1. Sir, Foreign Office. » S.W.l. 3rd Fe bruary, 1930. ' 6 FEB 1°^ With reference to India Office letter INDEXED h d /, the proposed replacement of the Bushire Residency Motor Launch by a combined motor and sailing dhow, I am directed by Mr. Secretary Henderson to state, for the information of the Secretary of State for India, that sanction has been obtained from the Lords Commissioners of His Majesty^ Treasury for the charge to Imperial Funds of a moiety of the cost involved in the purchase and maintenance of the dhow in question. I am, No .P 7875/2! the 30th December last regarding The Under-Secretary of State, India OfficePUT AWAY MTfl Ho. F.56(3)-A/29. From 2 9 JAN 193® V/ The Foreign secretary to the Government of India, To The Under Secretary of State for India, London. L»~ Dated Hew Delhi, the *7 ^January 1930. Replacement of the Persian Gulf Kotor launch 'Percy Cox' by a. combined motor and sailing dhow. Sir, In continuation of the letter from the Government of India, Foreign and Political Department Ho.F.58(3)-A/29, dated the 20th Hovember 1929, I am directed to inform you that the Hon*ble the Political Resident in tne Persian Gulf has since reported that the combined motor and sailing dhow, if sanctioned, will not be ready for‘delivery till the beginning of the next financial year. It will not therefore, be necessary to meet the expenditure by reappropriation during the current official year, as was previously contemplated, and arrangements are accordingly being made to provide necessary funds in the budget for 1930-31. I have the honour to be. for Foreign Secretary to the Government of India. 7 (with 2 spare copies)Minute Paper. Department. 7^ (&gt; ( v^^C U' ^ ^ (f i^USt^x n i‘ r . F 7705 1 1929 •{ &lt; £ k^^cCc^, — , . , s /- f &amp;bcc&amp; ^ [‘ U^asa '- 7 ^ (^ vv ^ ^ ^ r&gt; 3tJ ^ Xn?»- ,r ~l~. \ Mi ,ru^ , /* /z O'd^oSaJ^ PoOro ^ t r^aSoi ^ f 1 - 5 r w ^ ^ ,3..A,* J7v ^ i .*«. « *’ Z7 ^f T***' • 4“ '“'V li lr*j&amp;/ ' ^ . ■ ^ 4/*&gt; ^ « 'knnT 7^ ^ rtf&gt;cu^&gt; , ^ i A+r^/'^y ‘ , . it P &gt; t, /vO/ /A n.i/v’ « /•‘W/^ ^ ^ ^ V(i **'V ^ 1 ^7 - * , V W ^ ^ i ‘ . ^ .i •'--y ^ (^ ( cwU ' , „ /k ^ ii^cU* ' . A^v.^ t ,. i/ ^v &lt;^V A/ ^ Aro/^Z-^ f 1 / / • /^ ^T^vZeS • ^ ^ A AW W - ^ V 7-^3 7^ Jl, ^ 'J l, #- - il^ ^ ^ ^ ^ r ^ ^ ^ ^ ^ tiu /.W k 4 Sec .^ ^ /— ^ L / kr ^ jf - ‘h • * u. 4 , jisjio *** ^ ^ r . U-^+A &lt;tJ ' . . , •/ ,J, f ^‘^ e f-„ f p^.^4, n -'~iZ , Z~7fZ - &amp; 1 /. ■ a w/ ^ / ~ w A' /CXA Z^ . ., /3^/c^ ^ • ^ ^ r, ' /i ^ Cc^LX^ j ^ ^ ^ ^ Cv^^~ct , ^ F_o. * . /Kv^W p^d^* , ^ 7 CjVf&lt;*l vW 7 *-^ Jr ^ I'M ^T /A/l lU^^j/c ir~ jp* ^ r r CV^. z£-« L/ i{ ^ /i, /wA ^ A A ^U^WU-nt ^ TiU C*k/u Z'f * y7&gt; ^ ^ i, ^ t^W ^ ~vv^S 2c Z-rkC^ A/UcW ^ Ac. ^*vv«^/ ^-^7 A: —*«&lt; - t^ 74 a ' V 3818a 5000 S.2!) &gt;Prom i B! «f\ To v • ^ / •’j *:X Eo.P.58(3)-V29* The Poreign Secretary to the Goveminent of India» The Under Secretary of State for India* L o n d o n .» Dated ITew Delhi, the ' November 1929, Replacement of the Persian Gulf Motor launch 'Percy Cox' by a combined motor and sailing dhow. Sir, I am directed to forward a copy of the marginally noted letter from the'HorT’tie the PoliTroal Resident in the ^correspondence Pprsian Gulf. Ho.284, dated 2nd February 1929. 1.; : Telegram to -do- -do- K 0 . 233 -A, dated 15th July 1929. )resa»din S Tele^raci from -do- -do- Ho.692, dated 20th j uly 1929. i + *• Letter'f r om -do- -do- no. 1990 . dated 51st August 1929. )replacement of the Persian Gulf Motor launch 'Percy Cox',which is reported to be unseaworthy and unsafe in even a moderately heavy sea^ ty a combined motor and sailing dhow. The Government of India strongly support the Resident's proposal, which is both reasonable and economical. 2. The cost of the proposed Dhow is reported to ce Rs.7,500/- (rupees seven thousand and five hundred; and the annual running expenses are estimated at the same figure. The expenditure is divisible between His Majesty's Government and the Government of India, and it is proposed to meet it during the current year by re-appropriation from within the sanctioned budget of the Persian Gulf. I am to request that the orders of the Secretary of State on the proposal may be communica'ted by telegrapu. 9 Ofo m v} I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant. (With 2 spare copies.) for Foreign Secretary to the Government of India.From To No.234 of 1929. BRITISH RESIDENCY AND CON SUL ATE-GENERAL. Busliire, the 2nd February 1929. The Hobble Sir Frederick Johnston, K.C.I.S. , C.3.I.» Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, The Foreign Secretary to the Governiiient of India, Foreign and Political Department, New Delhi. Residency launch n Percy Cox” Sir, I have the honour to address you on the subject of the 'Percy Cox” which is the name given to the liotor Launch in charge of this Residency* 2. The 'Percy Cox' was purchased in 1923 from the Disposals Board, Basrah as a second |\pnd tug for Rs.4,50C/- cut her condition was found to be so bad on arrival here, that a further stem of Rs. 1535/3/- had to be spent on her to make her move, so that her total cost may be taken at Rs.6035/3/-. was , , 3. In 1925 it/xxBiibt found she needed a complete overnaul again and she was sent to Basrah, a further sum of Rs.2335/10/- being spent on her. 4. A S no facilities exist at Bushire for docking or over hauling, nothing has been done in the last three and half years, except giving her an annual repaint and attending to petty repairs. * 5. The condition of the 'Percy Cox' today is bad, and among other defects the following may be mentioned;- (a) her two large magnetos are worn out and require to Ce rep lac ed. (fc) her reversing gear will not function at all, and cannot be repaired here, (c) She requires a new fly wheel, (a) TootIv owing to the fact that several large sheets of her ' heavy ' ondar water copper plating -have fallen off, she leaks and has lost her stability. 6. Recently the Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, after a trip in her gave it as his opinion that apart from the above defects, ■defects, which in themselves constituted a danger, the 'Pertfy was distinctly unsafe in even a moderately heavy sea, and that ner stability was so bad that nothing short of cutting down ^■6^* top hamper, consisting of a wooden cabin for passengers and engine room staff, would render her sea-worthy or fit to go out to mail steamers. These anchor seven miles from the shore, and during the winter ^.nd right up to June, gales are the order of the day, with resulting heavy seas. 7. To have the ’’Percy Cox” properly overhaul^ed would probably cost between Hs.3000/- and 4000/-, and she will have to be sent to Basrah for at least 3 months, and it would probably be more economical to sell her for what she will fetch. 8. Actually for all purposes at Bushire, especially with the unfavourable weather conditions that prevail here, a ’’ combined motor a nd sailing dhow ? is probably the most suitable. These have been introduced into the Gulf fairly recently, and are large, safe and superb vessels in a heavy sea. Bahrein where weather conditions are similar has adopted this type of craft for all landing work, and other ports are rapidly following suit. The cost of a good motor dhow would be approximately Rs.7500/- complete. I have, etc•, Sd. P.W.Johnston, Political Resident, Persian Gulf.r* Telegram No.238-A, dated 15th July 1929. From ... Foreign, Simla, To ••• Political Resident, Bushire. Your No.284 February 2nd. Residency launch Percy Gox. Please wire whether the expenditure involved can be met within your budget grants if necessary by reappropriation. Present financial stringency renders this very necessary. Also please wire full details of probable running expenses of combined motor and sailing dhow compared with those of Percy Gox and how much sale of Percy Gox is estimated to fetch. Telegram Uo.692, dated and received 20th July 1929. From ... Political Resident, Bushire, To ... Foreign, -Simla. Your telegram L T o.238~A July 15th expenditure roughly estimated at Rs.7,500 can probably be met by reappropriation. Collection of details of costs will take some time.Wo.1990 of 1929. British Residency and Consulate General. Bushire, the 31st August 1929. The Hon*hie It. -Col. C.C. J.Barrett, C.S.I., C.I.E., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India in the Foreign and Political Department, Simla. Residency Launch 'Percy Cox ? Sir, ,Vi th reference to Foreign and Political Department telegram ho .23S-A, dated the 15th July 1929 and my telegram in reply dated the 20th idem, Wo.692, I have the honour to confirm that the expenditure, estimated at Rs.7,500, on the acquisition of a combined motor-sailing dhow if incurred during the current year, can be met by reappropriation. The details of the running and maintenance expenses of such a dhow are as follows:- Crew. Engine Driver (Indian) ... jjingine Assistant and Cleaner (Lo cal,,. .... Seacunny (local) ...». 2 deck Khalasis (local) ••• @ Rs.35/- each. @ Rs.150 p.ra. @ Rs.40 p.m. © Rs.50 p.m. @ Rs.70 p.m. Total Rs.310 p.m. = Rs.3,720 per annum. Fuel and oil. The dhow will be fitted with a Kelvin sleeve valve engine starting on petrol and running on Kero sine oil. Assuming the dhow will run on an average of 30 consumption of petrol and oil will be Petrol 30 gallons @ 1/2/- per gallon . Kero sine oil 90 gallons -/14/- n Mobil oil 6 gallons' 2/4/- per gallon. Total Rs. 126 p.m. hours a month the Rs.33-12-0 Rs.78-12-0 Rs.13- 8-0 = 1,512 per annum Mi scellaneousMi scellaneous . Cost of cotton waste» engine spares* rigging fish oil, livery to crew, flags etc. and ^ Rs . 2j50 o pe r annum, rep airs. Total per annum * Rs.? »752 which allowing ior economies may he reduced to Rs.7 ,500 in round figures. The motor launch 'Percy Cox' is not likely to fetch anything in Bushire and would, therefore, have to he sent up to ILohammerau or Basrah for disposal. Bei^ es^tially a river craft she will probably find a purchaser there but i do not think the price will be more than Rs.3,000/-. i have sent the necessary particulars about her build and present condition to His Britannic majesty’s Vice Consul, lio hammer ah and asked him to obtain offers for her. 1 shall report to Government on receiving further information. I have, et£., 3d. C .G • J►Barrett, Political Resident in</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000094_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/3586</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000094</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/3586</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 29/29 'Consulate Launches: Bushire, Bahrein, Bunder Abbas, Koweit, Muscat'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1929/1938</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-06-15T11:33:30</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (62 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence for this description commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 64; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file concerns motor boats and launches for the Persian Gulf Residency and Agencies.The file covers:replacement of the Bushire Residency Motor Launch by a combined motor and sailing dhow, in 1930expenditure for launches at the Bundar Abbas and Bahrain agencies, sale of old launchesnew motor launch for the Kuwait Agency.The file is composed of correspondence between the Political Residency in the Persian Gulf, Foreign Office, the India Office, the Government of India, and Lloyd's Agency at Basrah.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Government of India</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Persian Gulf Political Residency</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Diplomatic service</topic></subject><subject><topic>Consular services</topic></subject><subject><topic>Launches</topic></subject><subject><topic>British</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x000094#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>