<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000419.0x0001fe_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-20T02:34:46.368Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">21517 Minn To Under Se Secretary Committe Under Se Secretary Previous.1 [ 15 a ] Immediate and Confidential. f&gt; r\ r\ 4 22 o 1917' (tV. i CU 0 ■ Wgiy.) Reference :— Letter Foreign Office : The Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Under-Secretary of State for India, and is directed by the Secretary of State to transmit the accompanying copies of ^ telegram , . as marked in the Foreign Office, &gt; I 9 I 7* (Similar letter sent toCIRCUL,a,il) TO lilE KI T G- Aid Vmij C.iDIiBit / J De cypher. Lord Bertie. (Paris). May 2 4th, 1917 . D. 4.30*p.in. May 24th,1917, K. 8.0.a.in. Ifn^ 25th f 1917. No. 474. (H). if- Your telegram Ho. 1243 May 12th. A&gt;* French Government reply in a lengthy Note, oi which text goes to London hy hag to-night, to request His Majesty's Government xor vdthdrav/al oi the French Military Missions to the Hodjas. French Gov-.r:inent lay stress on importance to France, as great Flussulmun power, of maintenance of sovereignty of the Shereef and of the defence of Mecca hut declare their readiness if His Majesty’s Government can give them an assurance that all measures (?have been) (? taken) against a Turkish attack on Mecca, to consider possibility oi reducing the French Military Mission although immediate recall oi the whole Mission does not yet seem possible. French Government in that case would he prepared to recall Colonel Bremond with whom they are very well pleased hut whose rani: would he too high for a reduced Mission and to leave Lieutenant Colonel Cadi. They con sider His Majesty's Government have been (misinformed as to?) sentiments oi the members oi the French Fission and as to views entertained hy Monsieur Picot.X CIRCULATED TO THE KING AMD THE WAR CABINET* Decypher. Sir in Wiiig^te (Cairo) Nay 27th,1917 D, 2.35 p.ra* R. 7,30 p*m. Mi-y 27th. 1917. No. 560 please reier to my telegram No. 469 of April 27th. French Minister informs me that an Algerian notable named cherchali has arrived in Cciro on a Mission from French Government to nedjaz when he will support the chief of French Mission (Colonel Bramend) in his dealings with the Gr;-&gt;nd shereef in Question concerning French pilgrim interests and other matters such as '’prohibition of export of hides” (see my telegram No. 320 March 24th), 'modification of customs rSgime and operations of the Ottoman Bank at Jeddah.' There are matters in which interference by French Military Mission in Hedjaz; has already been deprecated, and I am apprehensive that presence (at Meecah?) of Cherchali may defeat the object we hoped to achieve by withdrawal of BX6mond T s Mission. What it the present position as regards the latter’ Mission (your telegram No. 1243 of May 12th to Paris)? see my telegram No. 123 of February 8th, I strongly recommend alteration in the designation of the British ' ■ J “ 3 ion be made without further delay and that Colonel -on be formally appointed head of his Mission with jorary rank of Brigadier General.0 OEOVILMED TO THE KIHC- M&gt; HE «W! «*»» D ecW.«r o£ Wlwr* «« =&gt;« *• D. 1.55 P.K1. Miiy 8tha91 7. R, 7.15 p.m. No. 497. Secret^ Following lor Graham Iron Sykes Ho. 23, ’oegins:- ! am convinced alter carelul study of situation at v/ej and Jeddah that the sooner French Military Mission is removed from Hedjaz the tetter. French officials are without exception anti-Arab and only seive to promote dissension and (group undecypherable) grow worse and worse. Their line is to crab British operations to Arabs, throw cold water on all Arab actions;and make light of the King to (two groups undecypherabie) both. They do not attempt to disguise that they desire nrab^ failure. Without assistance I do not believe picot will be strong mough to carry the day although he has mad representations to Paris. I suggest therefore that His Majesty’s Government make representations that French military mission in Hedjaz has now fulfilled its purpose, French contingent having absorbed troops at Suez and that it should be brought to an end. I xmd my chief difficulty in improving feeling between Arab and French due to deliberately perverse attitude and policy followed by colonel Bremond and his staff which is in no way ! minimised by Monsieur picot' s advent. (Enas). see my telegram No. 368 in this connection. (21517 I 1500 2000 11/16 Register No. Put away with.„l^ Minute Paper. im a ^.Secret Department, -) It Previous Papers :—Ary isos ; • i Ci rculated to Tne Kla;-: a ad »^r Oafrineu Decypucr of uele..u , ar.i Iron Sir R.'Jingate (Cairo), iipril 27th. 1917. D. d.20 p.n. April 27th.1917. — ^ ^ R. 12.10 r.n. April 28th.1917. |Copy 00 . 469 . Present .moment seais opportune to review quection of French military mission and make clear our position vis-a-vis- of Ruler of hedjaz and other chiefs in the districts which lie in “independent nrabia' whicli it is proposed to recognise in area 13. as defined in hykes - licet agreement. It is in my opinion of vital import ance t.ut all those territories (exclusive of Frown*'- are-) wiiicn lie to tne south of line dividing area n. from area 13 . should eo under British influences only, and ter ,3 of your telegram ilo.339 April 7th 1916 to oir hniaaiahon appeared to admit of no other inter- nrstation. Subsequent indications however coupled with manner in which Colonel Bremand has in J erpreted his instructions while at Jeduah lead me to conclude that ait *eugn spirit of agrenjeat is tnat our influence in /irauian peninsula is inramount. te actual text read in y a coancet i.au with map is capable of misinterpretation to oui in u u x imeut * 1 jiold it to oe vital tnat British influence alone should hold t:io field south of dividing line bwtcen urouti a. a. aaci I cousidor taia point should be made 2 MAY 1917]’ 3rmudu absolutely clear witn French Government before joint ..iission now in Ligypt proceeds further in its negotiations, if 11 eiicn uovemnenu t»‘.nce action in the sense of monsieur Heat's reca.ineuuutiou as notified to you in bxr xauric dykes telegram l&lt;o.!^ of to-day situation as i egai ds iiedjaz will be safeguarded but I would rjrefer a more definite understanding as regards other paramount cniefs in the area under consideration than that con tained in mragraph 11 Sf Oykes-l icot agreement. This woulci stiengthen our position in the event of possible ii^ficuitics with Italy in regard to Idrissi or questior Vv tfi French regarding Gheikh Said. ^ Au&amp; {tuz (H/ /t'vfcx tCjfa h r ‘ 1C } (fa 'fa. /(At.} SJ- l^. (trtc — I 3 ® IWE a Decypher^ Sir Mark Sykes (Cairo) April 27th- 1917 D- 12-5-p-m- April 27th- 1917 H- 9-45-p-n- April 23th- 1917 No- 16 Following for Sir !?- Graham- &gt;—— ' In (?conversation) with Monsieur Picot last night he told me he would endeavour to get French Government (?to) bring French Military Mission in Hedjaz to an pent that they regarded Hedjaz as in (?British) sphere of interest stipulating however for certain rights in regard to supervision of French Moslem, pilgrim, traffic. This l regard as very satisfactory and desire to mention that this frame of mind (?has) been greatly in duced by efforts of Captain George Lloyd- end and of their own notion inform. His Majesty's Govern-a &lt;cv ^iles only . Cypher telegram to sir H. McMahon (Cairo) Foreign Office. April S7th. 1916. 7 p No. 339. (D). P ‘ n April. ZlT meH0S - 284 “ 4 ^ Present position is as follows:- HiS Majesty ' s Gov ™nt and French Government decided tlici't subiect tn Pn r ~cr: ;rr area bounded by sea , 131 ^ Haifa to o P ° lnt 15 ” llc3 north of KU1 .’ 1 ' e ' ulJ ' mir ' on v;e3t l&gt;y line from Tiberias to ffon Kill! I 1 ” 8 Dam3 °“ S ' H0 '' 3 • * U ™-’ Kilns through Birijih and Amadia to Persian frontle- on north by li„ e following Ia„„„ , Irontier Persian frontier. UrUn “““ BU11S 10 Palestine west of Jordan to be International Alfa and Acre to be British with 16 mile hinter land and railway right through International area. Vilayets of Bagdad and Basra to be British if hi M ajesty's Government so desire. Remaining area within above limits to be Independ Basra dT 6 by 11118 '»erlas through ” Ferdi to KOI. Northern half to be French sphere of economic and political half British. interest and southern Monsieur Ploot then proceeded to Petrograd to negotiate with Russian Government. Sir M. Syh.s went to &lt; o'E)VEfP ~&gt;s. advi s e MAY 1917)advise Sir G. Buchanan. Russian Minister for Foreign Affairs objected to French area as outlined. Eventually Franco-Russian difficulty was adjusted as follows:- British area unchanged; International area unchanged; French sphere of interest unchanged but of French area district lying between Persian frontier and line from Bitlis through Sert to Zakhu became Russian in exchange for similar area between Kharput, Sivas and Kaisariyeh. Only outstanding question is status of French concessions in Russian area. Russians intend to regard their area as Russian territory. Reason of these alter ations are explained in ray telegram No. 287 (of 14th April). French intend probably to set up Armenian state including cities of Adana, Sis Zeitun, Sivas, Kharput, Diarbekir. French additions do.not include any large Ottoman population, Armenians, Kurds and Circassian settlers forming bulk of inhabitants. Moreover Sivas has always been included in Armenian reform schemes for six vilayets. Your reference to elimination of Turkish nation is not clear. Vilayets of Brusa, Smyrna, Angora, Konia, Kastamuni and Fskeshehr are untouched by Agreements in question. Owing to new arrangement it is believed that fundamental divergence between Arabs and French regarding Syrian littoral may be now adjusted. Representatives of Ottoman liberals and anti- Coramittee party are now in Paris and have approached Bis Majesty’s(TP) 4 ^ 4 Majesty’s Government and doubtless also French Government. His Majesty’s Government consider it dangerous to have any dealings with them. They should be told that if and when they come into power they should address themselves to Russian Government upon whom Turkish Government wantonly made war by treacher ous attack: but that so long as they are powerless it is useless to discuss matters. I am informing French Govern ment of attitude adopted by His Majesty’s Government. Representatives of Maronite party in Paris are actively in touch with French Government and may be issuing pro-French propaganda in United States of America and South America wherever there are large settlements of Syrians. Monsieur Picot will not be here for ten days at least. On his arrival I will inform you of precise position of Allies in regard to the situation.n 3 ■C This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government, ’ and should be returned, to, the Foreign Office when done with unless /, ' 331 ^ required tor official use.] Up V 1 ' 1 -V- V . . ' L © Tv'ITVVAUi.i ’ - A-nrii 4th. D. 2.20 p. mo R. B.50 p. m. 368. Apl April 4th. r i P 41 ; *-'! &gt; / yo-Ar -teiagT^m 325 ? Very confiden'ticd* ! am well aware tha^ Colonel Dromond*-s activities have frequently extended beyond the scope of his military mission and the chief reason I have hitherto - refrained from representing this strongly is that they have been so signally barren of result. Shereef has repeatedly and in writing affxim^d his desire to negotiate with France or other Allied power only through us and his attitude of a-nnsed * Av** suspicion has been shovm in his invariable polite and r ^ comittal replies to Colonel Eramondts offers and 1 ^ W^T^ : suggestions of which the King has kept Wilson fully informed. In the event of the Turks evacuating Medina I in tended to press for the withdrawal of the French Mili tary Mission and it is a matter for appreciation whether this should not be arranged vtoen or before Colonel Br&amp;iond himself is absorbed in Monsieur Picof s Mission. If required a French liaison officer could then be attached to Colonel Wilson's staff at Jeddah. It is true that the King's demands have sometimes exceeded our capacity to supply but with few and re latively unimportant exceptions our failure has been due to articles required (e. g. 2 batteries of modem . 0 . f. guns) not being available locally or from London. KingKing is now pressing for an increase to his monthly suteidy and additional monies and food stuffs for the supply of Northern tribes* On tftese subjects I shall telegraph to you as soon as I receive parti culars from Hedjaz on Which I can base a recomnendation It is possible l may have to ask French to transfer their wireless set now at Suez to Yenbo,. for which place no British wireless la available.? ^ cument is tho Property of His Britannic Majesty s Government , should be returned to the Foreign Office when with unless rnH fr\r nttinial I We are strongly d..^. re eating to French Governnent export of loides, the latter on the ground that being a non-military question it appears to be outside province .of a head ox a military mission,. Meanwhile I will await your observations on the two alternative courses suggested in my above mentioned telegram. (6(3635/17) Cypher telegram to dir 1?. Wingate, (Cairo), Your telegram No.344 (of March 29th.) lias crossed my telegram No.325 of the same date. provision of wireless, or representations regardingo mm In any further communica- n on this subject, please quote r n on this s &gt;. W. 0 U 0 ll / 1917 , i address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. 1332 i917 1^7 mfidential. THE Under -Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Fnder-Secretary of State for India, and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith copv^o of the nnder-meutioned papery , Foreign Office, A- fb I &gt; 1917. j* CifyrtJ Reference to previous correspondence : Letter Foreign Office: ^ 7^ l D- o to— • --- — iKO. 1.64012/17. 4 - \y r A 1332 917 SBEION Off10E, March 30th, 1917 Your Excellency:- I have the honour to acknowledge receipt of Your Excellency's Note of the 15th instant informing me of the desire expressed by the King of the Hedjaz to be provided with wireless telegraph apparatus for communication between i»iecca, Babegh and Jeddah and to state that, in the opinion of Kis Majesty's Government, the proposal appears open to serious objections. The establishment of wireless installa tions would place the Fedjaz in direct telegr*--ptiio communication with Constantinople and other enemy centres and would render it possible a&lt;a- the Turkish and German wireless news to ae received. The danger presented by such a state of affairs is evident and would render necessary a strict and constant control of both the installations and operators which, under existing conditions, it would be by no means easy to enforce. In these circumstances His Majesty's Government strongly deprecate the propostil and con sider that King Hussein's application should not be entertained. I have the honour to be, with the highest consideration^ igxcellency's most obedient, humble servant. His Excellency Monsieur Cnmbon, &amp;c., ibc., •[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government , and should be returned to the Foreign Office when don e with unless required for official use.j (VJ. 64012/17). r egyp: 1332 Cypher telef-ram tc Sir R. Vingate (Cairo) Foreign Office, I.iarch 29th, 1917. 8.30.p.n. Nc. 325, ^ I 7 , , « o • • Varv Gcnl*ici 3 Htj l.aI^— C£!±) I am somewhat perturbed by activities manifested by Colonel 3r4mond, who appears to be rapidly assuming the function of intermediary between King Hussein and the Allied Powers. , Apart from question of the Ottoman Dank, His Majesty s Government have recently been approached by French Government regarding export of hides from the Hedjaz, increase of Customs duties, and alleged application from the Shcrif for a wireless installation to connect Rabegh, Jeddah and Mecca, I think that Colonel Wilson should take an early opportunity of endeavouring to ascertain from King Hussein the facts regarding his recent dealings vrith Colonel 3r&lt;5mcnd and of impressing upon His Lordship the desirability of making his applications through one channel only and that. British. Alternatively instructions might be given to the British officers in the Hedjaz to show greater promptitude in anticipating His Lordship s wishes. Please telegraph your observations.in any further comm ion on this subject, please &lt;o. W. s /( 2 - o 6 ind address— The Under-Secretary of Foreign Office, London. Confidentiala in any further communica- ion on this subject, please quote io. w. 6 (, l O £ IW7. tnd address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, V London. r Confidential. 1330 I i '917 THE Under - Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Under-Secretary of State for India, and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop of the under-mentioned paperS &lt; Foreign Office, -2, I , 1917. 6 '■pie. 56206) rt i .la'] ■ r.vn t - VI r 1330 ! 917 Le Ministre de France au Gaire a fait connaitre au Gouvernement franfais que l T on songerait dans 1 T entourage du Grand Ch§rif a Clever de 10 a 11 /o les droits de douane. D T autre part, ces droits sont maintenant perqus d’apres la valeur des marcliandises cot^es a Djeddah et sans tenir corapte conxne precedemment des factures authentifi§es par les consuls. Mo Defrance a telegraphic au Colonel Eremond de thcher de faire comprendre au ^rand Gherif que dans son propre interet et dans celui'du commerce en Arahie il serait tres dCsirahle que des modifications ne fussent pas apportCes brusquement,et sans entente prealahle avec les Gouvernements amis^aux reglements et tarifs douaniers et de lui conseiller en consequence de ne pas changer le tarif douanier Ctahli par lui-mCme il 5 y a quelque temps. Le Gouvernement franfais a approuve ces instruc tions et i T Ambassadeur de France a Cte charge de demander a Monsieur ^alfour si le Gouvernement hritannique jugerait opportun une intervention semilable du Colonel Gilson aupres du Grand Cherif sous forme de conseils amicaux analogues a ceux que le colonel BrCrpond a CtC charge de lui donner. M. Paul Gambon saisit cette occasion, etc. iimbassade de France a Londres, 13 Mars 1917,I[This Docume^tv is the Prope rty ot His Britan nic Majesty’s Government, . OHKt and shomd be returned to the Foreign Office when done with., unless required for official use.] Dccyphe.. Sir K. V-ing, te (otdro) i.i, rch &lt;39t,h. 1917. 1312 i9i 7 D. 11.35 ti.r.i. K. 11.30 p.m. Licirch J9tl..l917. NO. 344., ' Bccrot. The following rectrd of recent activiUes of colonel Branond Chiof of French Li lit ary Mission in Kodjoz is sup- lied privately from a Vv.iy r liable sourco at Mecca* 1. Frc;nch rH' : ain approachod Slieroef about French b.-nk ic? JOdda* Shereuf said he was unable to countenance any banicing operations in liodjaz at present* French askod Shored to purchase wireless set from them for £6,000 payment after agreement. Shereef refused* 3* Fr-mch pressed six times that new Arab, coinage be minted in Franco and guarentood to give better t^nns them .any other country. a noncommittal reply was . given on behalf of Shereef. 4. Fr .nch offered to build li(.lit railway Jedda to Mecca a.f once o‘l after war. Gaereef replied time not arrived to consider development of this nature.MinuteI ^ br In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote /I917&gt; D No. * ■ l I *b() 6 and address — The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. 4 1257 , I 7 E Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Under-Secretary of State for India, and, by direction # of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop^^ of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, Q, 7 , 1917. Letter Foreign Office Reference to previous correspondence : : o. fa Go//‘g'} Description of Enclosure. ( C )War Office, Whitehall, S.W. 22nd March, 1917 57 / J [ The Director of Military Intelligence presents his compliments to the Under Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs and with reference to his letter No. W.56860/17 of the 20th instant, enclosing a note from the French Amhassador relative to the erection of wireless stations in the Hejaz, hegs to state that he is of opinion that it is most undesirable that any wireless stations should 'be put up in that country ax, the present time. Major-General Sir George Macdonibgh considers that there are several distinct objections, which need not be specified, to the proposal put forward and ventures to hope that everything possible will be done to induce the French Government to withdraw their suggestion.In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote No. W. I'W- and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. THE Under - Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Under-Secretary of State for India, and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop*-*'* of the under-mentioned paper, ^ r/gV ixi-t ^ Foreign Office, InasrtA O-O., 1917. r— Reference to jo/evious correspondence : Letter ^ om Foreign Office: Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. • LOifC^ ^ t ’ /U ( 21 MAR \ &gt; v r tV ’ (Similar letter sent to (fa £&gt; jfwivLrtj ■ )In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote No. W. 4-off 5* / 1917 , and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. 1000 i iSIZ.- THE Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Under-Secretary of State for India, and, by direction * of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, 72W ^ ’ 1917 - X Reference to previous correspondence : to Letter ? Foreign Office : from 0 Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. S-iL R.. 0 ( c ) (Similar letter sent tocopy. (40845) Private. THE RESIDENCY, CAIRO. 1000 ID 17 11th February, 1917. Dear Mr. Balfour:- I am sending this hy the hand of Captain George Lloyd, M.P., who is fully posted with my views on the important issue raised in the attached letter from Colonel lilson ('Pilgrimage Officer' at Jeddah) and cognate questions. There is, I fear, an impression in London that we have been unduly 'exclusive' in our dealings with our French Allies in the Hedjaz. Lloyd as the result of a prolonged stay at Jeddah, and some first-hand experience of our Allies' activities in the Hedjaz, will supply you with information which will enable you to correct this impression and will call your attention to certain aspects of the local situation with v/hich we have had to deal. I cannot but agree that our Allies have given some grounds for the suspicion that they are prepared to sacrifice the success of the Hedjaz revolt (and forgo the great political benefits that v/ill accrue therefrom) in the belief that this success, directly or indirectly, might militate against the full realization of their territorial aims in Syria. We ' ' The Right Honourable Arthur James Balfour, O.M., M.P., &amp;c., &amp;c., &amp;c.We, on our part, have loyally observed the policy* of 'hands off' in matters Syrian and neither overtly nor covertly have we encouraged Arab Moslem aspirations towards the region specifically excluded from the area of Arab irredentism by the Sykes-Picot agreement. So far as Colonel Wilson and others can ascertain, our attitude in this matter is appreciated by the Sherif, and the latter has shewn a good disposition to respect the obligations our Alliance with the French impose upon us. We have always been at pains to make him believe that our policy and that of the French are, and will remain, closely co-ordinatedI the evidence V/e have obtained from first-hand and reliable sources tends to prove that Colonel Br&amp;nond, in conversation with the Arab leaders, has not scrupled to convey to them a contrary impression. I recognize the supreme importance of doing nothing liable to raise difficulties with the French here or elsewhere: and it is on this account that I am sending Lloyd post-haste to London where, to Judge by indications in recent telegrams, the French Ambassador is concerning himself very intimately with Hedjaz affairs - whether at the direction of the guai d’Orsay or merely on information supplied from the French Minister here I must leave it to you to Judge. in any case I feel you should be fully informed of a situation which, unless carefully handler, might develop injuriously to'the movement for the independ ence of the chiefs of (Peninsular) Arabia - a movement whichCAIRO. 10th February, 1917. My dear General:- Now that the coast towns as far north as Moweilah are occupied by ijherifian troops and arrange ments are being made by Emirs Abdullah and Faisal to try and keep railway eomnunications between Medina and Syria permanently cut (which may possibly bring about the fall of Medina in the next two or three months) it is worth while considering the possible developments northwards in the near future, particularly as to how our relations with France may be affected, and it, therefore, would appear to be most desirable to lay dov/n some broad lines as to our future policy. My personal relations with Colonel Br&amp;mond are, as far as I am aware, most cordial. He visits me two or three times a week and generally remains at least one and a half hours. As I have informed you from time to time he has frequently been most frank in stating that he was not at all anxious for Medina to fall and gave me the impression that the rapid and complete success of the I Arab revolt was not entirely desirable in his eyes. He has also stated more than once that France would have practically nothing to fear from a collapse of the revolt. ItIt is, I think obvious that his fear is that the fall of Medina in the near future, leading as it probably v/ould to a revolt of the Druses and Northern tribes, would create difficulties for the French in Syria, whereas if Medina held out until the end of the war or for say six months from now, the French occupa tion of Syria would be greatly facilitated. Assuming that the French Government take the view I have attributed to Bremond, it appears most desirable from every point of view for our policy to be generally defined and broad lines laid down on which to work, it being, I think, necessary for us to give the French no grounds for supposing that we are encouraging or actively assisting the Pan-Arab Syrian ideal in opposition to them; it was with this idea in view that a final limit of 30,000 rifles was fixed which will only aim the tribes as far north as the Hauran. The Sykes-Picot agreement was roughly to the effect that the Hejaz is our pigeon and dyria that of the French. I understand that until recently Br&amp;nond had no knowledge of this agreement, which may be the reason for his endeavouring to get French influence into the Hejaz as he undoubtedly is, acting presumably under instructions of his Government. The letter which he sent in Octooer to Colonel Cadi at Mecca, urging him to get Sherif Abdulla to telegraph direct to Paris begging for a French Bank to be established at Jeddah as soon as possible is perhaps the most significant of his efforts. AsAs I reported to you at the time, this letter was Immediately read to me down the telephone by Abdulla and a copy was sent to you with a report on the whole subject. The Sherif, or Puad El Khatib, told me at Jeddah that Br&amp;mond had stated he was acting in consultation with me in the matter. I have never exchanged a word with Brfemond about the establishment of any Bank at Jeddah. As you will doubtless remember, Brftmond, in his letter to Cadi, stated that it would be to the latter’s advantage if he was successful in getting the telegram sent and it appears obvious that the French attach very great importance to getting a French Bank, or one with predominant French interests, established at Jeddah, if successful it is not difficult to realise that it would only be a question of time before French influence would be predominant in the Hejaz. In my humble opinion it is essential, with our very large Moslem interests, that the only European influence in the Hedjaz should and must be with us. I attach an extract from an official secret report from Lawrence giving’ an account of an interview Br&amp;nond had with Faisal, I have no reason to doubt the main facts as recorded chiefly because I - knowing Faisal - cannot believe that he would make up such a story. I am beginning to think that the r rencli are Jealous of our Influence and relations with the Sherif andand did not expect that the Arab movement would be such a success as it bids fair to be. The French are ; doubtless apprehensive lest the successes in Sinai and in the Hejaz, due either to British action or British support and direction, will have the effect of increasing British prestige in Syria, where the majority of the population is already pro-British rather than pro-French. In view of the paramount importance of eliminating all possible causes of distrust or suspicion on the part of our allies, it would seem essential that someone fully acquainted with your views and also those of the G. in G. should be sent on Mission to England as soon as possible in order to explain the situation to K.M.G. in a more complete and comprehensive manner than is possible by despatch or telegram. I venture to suggest that George Lloyd would be a most suitable man for this Mission, as he has not only studied the Arab question in general, but has been with me for some weeks at Jeddah and thus has first hand knowledge of the local situation and of French activities in the Hejaz. Very sincerely yours, (Signed) C. Wilson.I Colonel Wilson. Following story was told me by Feisul in con fidence. I hope you will respect the condition. It seems to me rather illuminating talk. I made notes as he told me. 'When I went to Rabegh Colonel Brfemond asked me to visit him on the Haj. I thought I would not go, but Colonel Wilson said 'Subhan Allah', why on earth not? - so I went. I met the Colonel Brfemond and Cadi, and we complimented one another on the honour and pleasure mutually felt. After enough of this, to test my ground, I made a short speech in honour of France. This was well received:- and so I developed the idea gradually, saying I was assured that France, the mother of manners, the banner of liberty, the refuge of the oppressed, the creator and patron of the ideal of nationality, must be looking with all her sympathy and hope tov/ards the first struggles of the Arab people, after six centuries of Turkish tyranny, to win for themselves a little of the joy and freedom of Western Europe. The history of France had been an inspiration for us, and I was glad to find myself in communion with the great current of French feeling, fighting beside them and for them in a Holy War against the coramon enemy. My father, I knew, agreed with me. I hoped that Colonel Brfemond felt glad that the Arab leaders had realised that the Arabs, in their humble way, were helping to secure for France the coveted provinces of Alsace and Lorraine, just as France at Verdun was confirming Arabia for the Arabs.I said that the Arabs were doing their best, but that they were an old and broken people, lacking all modern developments and appliances, and v/ithout con fidence in themselves, or innate encouragement, except in the blood of their martyrs, who had died in Damascus for the race. I said how glad I was to welcome them; representatives of France, to a port now freed by Arab hands from its Turkish burden, and begged that they would make me party to their plans and intentions so that I could help them as far as lay in me. While say ing this I saw their faces become parti coloured and i their eyes confused. As I was not listening to their v/ords (all compliments) but watching their faces for undercurrents of feeling;, I determined to draw them a little further. I said that the conmon aim and purpose of the allies Imposed on them mutual confidence, and . unity of purpose and effort in the face of the enemy, if ultimate victory was to be achieved. As they said 'Yes' only I said that the Arabs were doing their share in fighting the Turks in contact with them on the north and south and could do no more at the moment. Indeed, that we were much in need of help, in spite of the liberality of Great Britain, which had been to us a verj# fountain of benefits, and had given us all that it could spare, generously, trustingly, without establish ing conditions or seeking for controls. Great Britain by trusting us has laid on us a debt of gratitude w'hich can only be met by frank co-operation with her in future, and our acknowledgment that we owe to her all that we have and are. Hov/everHowever it was no disparagement to England to say that further assistance would be most welcome, and if on the same open terns, would lay us under the same obligations. « They said that I must remember that the firmness and strength of the present bonds between the allies did not blind them to the knowledge that these alliances were only temporary and that between England and France, England and Russia, lay such deep and rooted seeds of discord that no permanent friendship could be looked for. Further that no one of the allies could have any business of main importance in the hands of another. For this reason France had to have her direct relations with everything in the world v/hich concerned her interests, and they had come there that day to push France and her point of view. I said that of course treaties were made and unmade and not in the west only - but that between Great Britain and the Arabs were unwritten bonds of mutual understanding which had probably as strong an influence as the innate sympathy of a civilised man for the success of a small and oppressed people. Hie permanent tie of state to state could only be community of ideas and sentiment, as any based on interest alone was necessarily teiminate. However I am no politician (ray father will tell you all these things and more), but a soldier, entrusted by ray father with the Conmand of his Northern Armies, and as such I could only assure them of ray fixed intention to play fair to the allies who showed that they too subordinated political considerationsI considerations to the vital and inmediate need of defeating the Turks. If we weigh and balance now, because we look too far into future political difficulties of success, we will have our throats cut in the present. The Arabs are fighting for their life, and the liberty of their race, not for territorial ambitions. I then said that from the point of view of securing the direct profit of France - crushing Turkey - might I ask them again what military help they thought themselves able to afford us? They detailed to me the guns and personnel they were supplying, and I thanked them as fully as I could. They next said they intended to land them at Yenbo, with a view to their being associated particularly v/ith the successes of our Northern forces, and for the same purpose they wished to attach to my staff tv/o or three officers to be with me and assist me in the field. On the first point I expressed the gratification I would feel personally at their going anywhere they v/ished: but I must remind them that though Yenbo lay in my district yet my father must be consulted, and I hoped that they would take the opinion of Colonel V.'ilson, whom we trust. On the second point I said that my operations took place in the interior, and they must have realised the unfortunate jealousy of the people at any sign of foreign activity: the point would have to be referred to my father. They interrupted that I had already had an English officer in my camp - and I said that I could not discuss details of my present staff with them. ftould they please apply to Mecca direct?1 1 © I then wrote to ray father that I did not require the assistance of a French contingent, and that the French wanted to make terms with the Arab movement, before they assisted it seriously. I suggested that if the price was high we leave the question of accepting the offer till we found it necessary. (Initialled) G. E. L.copy r~ ' NO. W.36361/17* xt£i - ' : icaoelXtOKa. tuoY .••noaiSi* FQRKZCOi OFF It , I 83 R Feoruary -45^4, lj?17« v £ • '“7 i y iNi^ f A&amp;y:- I hfife the honour to acknowledge the receipt of Your 'Excellency’s Memorandum of the 6th instant, relative to the desire expressed to Colonel Brfoond hy the King of the Hedjaz for the empliyment of certain French Moslem doctors, in which Your Excellency was so good as to enquire whether l is Maiesty's oovemment were of opinion that this application on ti e part of King hussein ~o*SC! 9x ( J aohtti'.o om sei I£iw J rt0?ut$X9VQC *' Bhould be encouraged. His Government cannot out feel 'some surprise that such a request Should have come froi!i King Hussein, ar it apnearr ^ oe in direct '' contradiction with his frequently expressed desire to avoid all foreign interference in or intrusion into the Hedjaz, and they are strongly of opinion that the assistance afforded to His Highness should, as hitherto, he limited tx&gt; his essential military and political requirements. As Your' Excellency is aware/ the new Arab State is being subjected to continuous and watchful criticisffl *rom many sections dt Moslem opinion, and It would be undesirable to furnish any grounds for suspicion (total; His Excellency Monsieur cambon* &amp;c., &amp;c. • Ac*. i*; .1 S*' In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote No. W. /'W, and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. !&gt; . o 3 8 i 9 i / THE Under-Secretar}' - of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Under-Secretary of State for India, and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office f rm . i9i7- MCi ttiK Reference to previous correspondence: Letter Foreign Office: I ^ j T / ) Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Cony to India ll %r / tJla/nd.. (Similar letter sent to &lt; C ) 2 1 26FEB J 917 ) DEP^ •)^A^TeltgrMi from Viceroy, Por#i«i Department, Dated 26th February, 1917, Received at India Office,- 7 a.m, (27th) Seeret, Your secret telegram of the 15th instant, Hedjaz. Difficulty is experienced in meeting demand for Mesopotamia but every effort will be made to provide a few Moslem doctors if necessary. Addressed to the Secretary of State and repeated to Cairo,'■53C This Document is the Property ot His Britannic Majesty’s Government, and should be returned to the Foreign Office when done with unless required tor official use.] is ( 3540 - 7 / 7 ) j V rn J.' ~ . # I-OLITICaT, . Decypfter of telej.u.i from Sir H.wingate (Cairo). February 14Lii.l917. S. 1.55 p.m. Feoi-u-ry 14th. K. 4.15 r.b. No,155. / Your tele^ran No.153. Medical men'oer of military mission is studying question and we anticipate no difficulty in providing requisite Moslem medical personnel. I do not consider it likely t-u-t anercef will require or is anxious to obtain,doctors 1'rou elsewhere.'Sv* ,Cj Ay [This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty's GovernmOTit, and should be returned to the Foreign Office when done with unless required for official use.] C ~ ft^) ?&gt;2 c ( /”* o r r (ido fv: FILICS. ONLY ^ecypli^r. Sir H* Wingate (Cairo) February 10th* 1915® D* 8«55 p.m, February 10th&lt;»1917# Fu 8 February llth„1917o NO® 130e Your telegram No® French Minisuei has to-day applied for permission, no previous application having been made c Despatch of amount in question has been authorized® / / /v . i&amp;y 7 ^- i?1^’ 5.- In any further communication on the subject, please quote no. W.28859/17. and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. o r Foreign Office ebruary 12th, 1917. Sir:- I am directed hy Mr. Secretary Balfour to trans mit to you, herewith, to he laid before Mr. Secretary Chamberlain, a copy of a Note from the French Ambassador, relative to the desire expressed by the King of the Hedjaz to engage certain Mussulman doctors from the French colonies in Northern Africa. Mr. Balfour considers that in view of the great political influence which can be exercised by doctors in circumstances such as those maintaining in the Hedjaz, it would be desirable that doctors should also be sent from Kgypt or India, to represent British interests, as against those despatched from French Moslem colonies. Mr. Balfour is consulting His Majesty T s High i i o Commissioner for Egypt in the matter, and he would in the meanwhile be glad to receive Mr. Chamberlain’s observations in so far as the matter affects the Government of India. I am, Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant, tc rr»dia /s The Under Secretary of State, India Office.6^’ In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote No. W. ^ % JW1, and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. (jonfid&amp;H'f'Uik r 600 5 / i 7 THE Under-Secretar}?' of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Under-Secretary of State for India, and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop of the under-mentioned papery . Foreign Office, S' .. 1917. Reference to previous correspondence: Letter from Foreign Office: ^ , Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject.( This Document is the Property ot His Britannic Majesty’s Government, and should be returned to the Foreign Office when done with unless required tor offic ial use.] building by French Gcvernraenb in A;j ecca). French Ambassador has represented tint Lgyptian Government are opposing ^despatch of 123 thousand francs in gold representing price of the building purchased by the French Government at mecca to serve as a hostel for French Llcslem pilgrims, and has expressed hope that necessary authorisation for this payment may be given Without delay. I fear we cannot refuse and I am therefore in forming French limbassadcr that Egyptian Government are being urged to authorize the payment though we have only recently requested them to curtail all expert of gold from Egypt. Please approach Egyptian Government accordingly. \ ;'i / j (28165/17). Cypher telegram to 3ir li . 1/ingate (Cairo) Foreign Office, February 7th, 125.7. 7.p.m No. 110,'■ ''I' 1 '- ■ ■— copy PORKIQM OFFICE, February 7th, 1917 jlo. W.28165/17 Immediate. Your Excellency:- With reference to the Your Excellency was good enough to comnunicate to me on the 3rd Instant, relative to the desire of the French Government to purchase a building I have the honour to state that I have requested His Majesty's High conroissioner for Egypt to urge the Egyptian Government to give the necessary authorisation for this payment to be made. I would explain that the difficulties which have been encountered by Colonel Brtoond in the matter are due to the fact that Hit Majesty's Government had only recently requecoefi the Egyptian Government to curtail all exports of gold from Egypt. I have the honour to be, with the highest consideration. Your Excellency's most obedient, humble servant. His Excellency Monsieur •, Gambon, &amp;c.,.6? 0- V, VW [This Document is the Property o! His Britannic Majesty's Government/ ^&gt;S5 \ and should be returned to the Foreign Offic e when done with unless required for official use.] (24614/1?}r Cypher Telegram, to air Vim-nto (0 &gt;iro) Foreign Gifioe. February 3rd, 1917, 7,0,v*n t No, 83, YoUr tela^ran :w r 865 (o'? October 9th, French I-*iscio:i to the Sherii), French Governrcent hove enquired whether we confirm information which they hive received to the effect that Colonel Jilcon oshod for, end. obtained fror* 1 . the Sherif, the original of the Presidents letter, I propose to reply the: Colonel hi}son never asked for or obtained the original of this fetter, although we understand that a copy was sent him by the Sherif, It is not quite clear, however, from the terras of your above-mentioned telegram whether such a reply would be correct.In any further communica tion on this subject, please quole No. W. £ / l | A 916 arvl aHdre»i&gt; — The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, Txmd on. .... -^ o ut a ^ ' p ] 15197 2 . The Under-Secretarv 'ftf -SiaU-for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Under-Secretary of State for ^ rl ^ — and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop 7 - of the under-mentioned paper ^ Foreign Office, ^ ^ , i 9 i6. Reference to Letter to correspondence , For arm Otfice : from fA Description of inclosure. Name and Date. Subject. P^opy of despatch sent by bag In the 3#S.Arabia . 5197 ho 2 9 6 The Residency, Cairo. November 2nd 1916 My U&gt;r&lt;l with reference to my tele^rniw No 865 of the 9th ultimo, 1 have the honour to forward to you hersfe* t with copy of a translation of the letter addressed by the I reside a of the French Repub lie to the Grand sherif. the Sharif’s reply , but a member of his Staff , Ihuhi Effendi read it through and a sunrary of its contents ia herewith attached . Colonel T’ileon was un&amp;ole to obtain copy of X have the hon ur to oe I y i-ord with the highest respect Your Lore ship's ' dpi obedient humble servant &lt; sifred } ; c‘ ahon Viscount Grey of rT allodon K,G. etc., etc., etc.(m Thfi following translation is from tha Arabic copy of tha E&lt;)nt by th* Pr«pidant of th^ IVanch Republic to tb.« Crand fherif of acca. Prom Raymond u oin care, the President of the Prench Republic, to H.R. Hussein r.bn A1 i, the Hherif and ilmir of ^ecca PI okarram. His Lordship the Grand Sherif and Noble Ingenious friend. (I send you) salaams, the perfume of which will be diffused in all directions and respect tne fragrance of whose perfume will soread to all horizons, e have indeed been informed of the crimes which the leaders of Constantinople Government have committed and the evils which they have practiced : all of which has led Your Highness to demand the rights of independence of Your illustrious ancestors. We ourselves greatly praise your magnificent efforts since we have amongst our subjects millions of i osi erne who ere living under the laws of the just Preach Republic, believing that their efforts will once for all free the two Holy Islamic Cities from tb® yoke of the neople of unlimited ambition: end that our Loslem true subjects may be enabled at a later date through Jfour Highness’s endeavours to make the Holy Pilgrimage. It is needless to remind Your ingenious Highness of the stumbling blocks placed by the Union Go^^rnment to prevent the Pilgri ie from completing their ceremonies and also of the actions committed by the emoloye-cs of the Young Turks: of their evil deeds and ill-treatment of the nil grime on their return: accordingly we have chosen an ambassador to the noble presence of your Highness, namely the sincere ana learned Abdel trader Bin Cabrit to present Your Highness2 - on our 'h^holf our congratulations and endeavoure, who will explain to Your Highnase our intentions towards facilitating mautare concerning the pilgrims of our Islamic countries and all to lighten the troubles oi the way. /ind indeed we consider it very important to guarantee to out Moslem subjects every comfort and we shall do our best so thai they shall fulful their holy pilgrimaged duties with all ease and convenience. For they have proved by their courage and endeavours their sincerity to us at the present time. Ahae 1 ^ader £1 Gabrit ^ ; i]l meet you and hear from you your wishes which we hone you will make clear to him as though you w*re stating to a true friend of Your Noble Fighnese. He will be accompanied by some respectable notables of Algiers, Africa, Tunis and the Far V'eet. There are baid Ahmed bukkareeje of the Ulema of Fas: baid -arallwi Bin ohamed Agha from Gahal El Nazour of Algiers: .aid Yustapha K1 bharshall teacher of i.,ohamedan Theology in the school of Algiers; 8aid El bhatby El Cghby, Commandant of the Nawahi of Tunis; bald Abdou ICani, the chief Judge of French V, r est Africa V/e have entrustea our representative to present to Your highness on our behalf our prayers to grant Your Highness long lif* and,perfect health and that victory will ever be the ally of your protected troops. the most fragrant tree and the sanctified ohamedan essence from the beginning to the end according to his wishes. The .ission contains also El bald El Arabi, Sheikh of the Notables of Tunis. M Translated by Said Emil Bayat, Consul General of France, Secretary and Translator of the French Govt. Paris. And we conclude our letter by demanding of the bounty of the All Giving Cod to guide the branch of ist September, 1916.I wan unabl« to g^t a copy of th*? r^ply, NOT aB opportunities did not permit but I have read it through and I can cummariBe it in the following 1 . His Highness salaam and thanks. &lt;i. His Highness pleasure of meeting th* ..oslero French j^iesion. 3. That he war very glad to keep the oelem Oi ficere who c??ine with the ission and that h«* will appoint them in hie v .'ar Office. 4. He hopee that the French Government will not fail to assist him in time of need. 5. lie hopes that the members of the lesion would bring him the good news about the Pilgrimage and comfortabil ity ol all pilgrims for which the bherif’c Oovernment Aid its best. ( s igne d) • H .Ruhi. Jeaoah • jetober 2jtn, I'ylS.In any further communica tion on this subject, please quo*e No. W. *2 3 3 / O / Ul t) A»16 ^ J and address— The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, I&gt;ond on. r r&gt; H 5196 ■- V7 I The Under-Secretarv of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Undersecretary of State for ( “ ” ’ and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith copvz^o of the under-mentioned paper Foreign Office, f 2 Lf , ‘9 jd Reference to prevporfs correspondence to Letter , Foreign Office: from v Description of Inc Insure. Name and Date. u d/( cV ' 3 &lt;1 0 Subject. 'TIL LDuplicate of deapateh eent in bag,which wae lost in PaO 'Araoia* CAIRO. ;ovemocr lst # 1^16 %0- l p uy Lord, I have the honour to forward to you here* with translation of a telegraphic despatch 1 address* ed to the Grand sherif on October 31st, congratulating iiim on the arrangementB made an successful accot/ip* lishaent of Uie Pilgrim^#* i i^ive sent copies of this despatch to Lord Chelmsford and Gir Keginald llngate T have the honour to be with the higiiest respect, y Lord, Your Lordship**? most obedient humble servant, The Viscount Grey of Failodon, K *(. etc, etc, etc,.Letter telegraphed en clalr to tne Grand f herlfof of . ecca. After compllmentB. i have the honour to congratulate Your highness; with the greateet heartinese end sincerety upon the excellence of the arrangements made by your Government both at Jeddah, on the road to Mecca, and at Mecca itself with its Holy Places for the com fort and safety of the pilgrims in general, and es pecially those from Egypt and India. The Egyptian pilgrims have just returned in safety, and it is fran them 1 learn of the care and trouble Vigen oy Your Highness on their behalf. The precautions from the point of view of public health, the efficiency of the police supervision, and the moderation of (In prices charged fee trans port and general accomodation have not failed to receive most favourable comment from all sides and ,vl 1 1 aaruredly give proof in all those countries ^rom which the pilgrims come of the nobility of Your Highness' intentions, as also of the stability of your rule. In conclusion I congratulate Your Highness upon the results achieved and express my pleasure at the good augury of able and prudent administration in the future.rjst!_ Document to the Property of His Britannic Majesty^ Government, (5$ and should be returned to the Foreign Office when done with unless required for official use.] fflhLa ONLY._ De cypher. Sir H. Kci.inl-.on (Cairo) November 14th, 1916 D. 1.40 p.m. November 14th, 1916., R. C.45 p.va. November 14th. 1916,, i\C . 100 6 r fcf'SV'V) Your telegram no. 846. \ French mission and pilgrims must have reachec homo by now. Need communique be rurther delated. ewoM^^r[T his Document Is the Property o! His Britannic Majesty’s Government, a nd should be returned to the Foreign Office when done with unless required tor official use.] ^ j i £ w J* 9 (230336/16)« m./B OKLY. C^her teler^rcirn to .oir H» McIMion, (fciro), Foreign Office, Noveniber 27tin 1916, 0.15«p&lt;,m. 110.928. ✓ ■JJy telegrum . Io .981. Please telegraph your announcement, or substance of it, to Batavia, Tripoli, Tunis, Algiers, and Ta:igier, and send us copies in Arabic for use elsewhere.In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote »,w. 2/3«7'/ t and address— / The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, Ixrndon. jt &gt; Hf- U ^ 1916 Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his comflvnents to the Undersecretary of State for and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop \jLa of the under-mentioned paper Foreign Office, , lylb Reference to previous correspondence to Letter , Foreiqrr Ollice: from y M Description of Inclosure. Name and l)ate. Subjeei. ^ 'fat rxxfx V c d. d. a Similar letter sent toCopy. | N.I.D./0.L.4578 (213871) o d, 6 H' !y i6 The Director of the Intelligence Division presents his compliments to the Under Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs and hegs to forward herewith for his infoimation a copy of a telegram, which has been received from the French Admiralty. Admiralty War Staff, Intelligence Division, October 24th, 1916.COPY OF TELEGRAM From:- Marine, Paris. Date. 23.10.16. To:- Admiralty. French Cruiser 'POTHUAU' has been sent from Djibantil to Jeddah in response to a request made to the Arabian Political Mission by the Shireef Abdullah, son of the Grand Shireef of Mecca, for permission to visit a French warship. The 'POTHUAU' will remain for a few days only at Jeddah and will return to Djibantil as soon as her mission is accomplished.[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government, and should be returned to the Foreign Office when done with unless y , required for official use. i' r 4352 9 iG FILES ONLY. Decypher, Sir H. Ivid/iahon (Cairo) October 21st, D. 7,55.p a m, H # 2,50,p o m, No. 92b. October 21st, 1916, Copy to ’r'-'j a } zjo Ddr 1916 1 I J Your tele.^ram No. 846„ I had anticipated the instructions contained in your first paragraph at the request of the French Mnister. The communique to fthe press with regard to the pilgrimage see your telegram 'o. 830, is however being prepared for publication later if desired.fThis Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty's Government, and should be returned the Foreign Office when done with unless required for official use/] ' Vft ,'vr *n. *yr ~ ■ i j4352 j --- - • i [ I9i6 j . PlleB only,. Cypher 'telegram to blr hj.ici.ianon (Cairo). Foreign Office. October 20th.l916. -7.40 p.m. No. 846. UrgeirL . French Government regard it as essential that there should be no mention whatever in French oi Allied press of return of pilgrims who went from Morocco, Algeria and Tunis and that any information which could even indirectly give to the enemy a clue as to their itinerary or date of sailing should oe withheld. French Minister in Cairo has been instructed to mention matter to you. In the circumstances you should defer action on my telegram No. 830 (of 17th October) pending furt^hor instruct/ions 0 ^ VCf&gt;vj to tnhiai ■ | QjbOcV.isn&lt;jIn any furl non on this subj W. 2 c and address — The Under-Se ForeignIn any further cominunrca- tion on this subject, please quote No. W. X&amp; ^ ! O \ '&gt; and address — The Under-Secretary &lt;T State, Foreign Office, London. © The Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Undersecretary of State for ^ and, by direction of the Secretary &lt; of State, transmits herewith cop &lt;J^&gt; of the under-mentioned paper T' -. * . copy to Foreign Office, \ 191 ICopy. No.406. (205701) P 43 52 I PARI , 19 !6 October 11th, 1916 My Lord:- I have the honour to transmit to Your Lordship herewith, the text of the Bill which has been laid before the Chamber of Deputies by the French Government, for the opening of a credit of three million five hundred thousand francs for the expenses of the French civil and military mission to the Bhereef of Mecca. I have, &amp;c., (Signed) Bertie of Thame. The Viscount Grey of Pallodon, P.C., K.G., &amp;C •y &amp;C •f &amp;C • 3 [21 OCT 1916VLe President de la R6publique fran^aise Decrete : Le projet de loi doat la tenear suit sera pr6sente la Ghambre des Deputes par le President du Conseil, Ministre des Affaires etran- g&amp;res, et par ie Ministre des Finances, qui sont charg6s d’en exposer les motifs et d’en soutenir la discussion : Article unique. . II est ouvert an Ministre des Affaires etrangeres, au titre de Texercice 1916, en [addition aux credits provisoires alloues pour les d6penses du budget general pir les lois des 29 decernbre 1915 30 mars et 30 juin 1916 et par des lois sp6ciales un cr6dit de trois millions cinq cent mille francs (3.500.000 fr.), qji sera inscrit k un chapitre nouveau du budget deson Departement portant le n° 29 ter et intitule : « Mission en Arable ». Fait k Paris, le 17 septembre 1916. Par le President de la Republique : Le Pr6sident du Conseil, Ministre des Affaires Strangeres, Signe. : R. POINCARE. Sigwi : ARISTIDE BRIAND. Le Mioistre des Finances, Signe : A. RIBOT. •mm A h \\MinnIn any further communica tion on this subject, please quote . w. Zo i Lf. No and address — The Under-SeCretary of State, Foreign Office, I^ondon. 'O x f' Tf&lt;53 - h cL i ' ^ 6 fhe Under-Secretary of state for 'Foreign Affairs presents his compivnents to the Under-Secret ary of State for 3 — and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop of the under-mentioned paper Foreign Office, C 13 1 /9J0 Kef ere nee to previous correspondence: Uf* Letter , Lore tan Oljice from J ^ Description of tnclosure. er sent toCopy. Ho.104. (201214) © A-IlA i e h s. 16 September 28th, 1916. {y&gt;^) I,ly Lord: - L With reference to my despatch Ko.93 of the 4th September last relative to the conveyance of a party of Mobanmedan pilgrims to Llecca at the cost of the Algerian Government, I have the honour to report that the number of persons who were eventually induced to undertake the Journey, apparently as the result of some pressure on the part of the Officers of the administration, did not amount to more than three hundred. The reasons to which is ascribed the un willingness of- the Arabs to make the pilgrimage on such favourable terms are, firstly, the presence of enemy submarines in the Mediterranean, secondly, the fact that two separate bodies of Mohanmedans are fight ing one another in the fcedjaz, and, thirdly, that Medina being at present occupied by the Turks, a visit to the tomb of the prophet would be impracticable. I have, &amp;c., (Signed) Basil S. Cave. The Right Honourable Viscount Grey of Fallodon, K.G., &amp;c., &amp;c •, &amp;c.t [This Document is the Property o! His Britannic Majesty’s Government, a nd should be returned to the Foreign Office when done with unless required lor official use/ lc Following from Wilson, Jeddah, to Arab Bureau night tliat French Mission brought a letter for Sheresf from French Republic intimating friendly feelings of France towards Arabs and new Arabian Empire, enquiring and reporting as to safety of pilgrimage etc, and ask wanted to consult me and take advice of His Majesty's Government as to four his reply to French Government's letter should take, I replied I would inform Your Excellency but without fuller details of what letter contained it would be somewhat difficult to advise, Abdulla with Shereef's permission is sending me French and Arab copy of letter by special messenger on the receipt of which I shall send text or gist. Your Excellency's reply (it sic) should reach me the morning of October Tth* at latest so as to enable Shereef to write his reply before the festivities finished. EGYP Tt Decypher. Sir H, McMahon (Eamleh) October 9th, 1S16* Cairo, No, 233, October 3rd, begins: Secret. Abdulla Bey told me by telephone last ing for Shereef's ideas and intentions; that mission was leaving after completion of pilgrimage and ShereefShereef also asked my advice as to what presents he should make to Mission in return for those brought by the latter; I am dealing with this. Addressed to Arab Bureau for High Commissii. ( oner 0 Repeated to Sirdar', Ends, 2. Following from Arab Bureau, Cairo to Wilson, Jeddah, October 7th, Begins: 'Your telegram No, 233, As gist of letter re ferred to has not been received High Commissioner cannot do more than advise Shereef to send a guarded cut friendly reply of a non-committal nature. Addressed to Wilson, repeated to Sirdar'. Ends, 3 r Following from Wilson, Jeddah to Arab BurBau, No, 262, begins: 'Your telegram of October 7th, Letter not sent by Shereef, have suggested reply of this nature. Addressed to Arab Bureau, repeated to Sirdar', Ends,r [This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty ' s GoTernment, jig and should be retorned to the Foreign Office when d^fle with anlesa reqnired for official age. I 1 ^ i O v —TTU uTCIT' .95502/16) •. ‘ rphei' telegram to Lord Bortie (Paris). _ Foreign Office. October 2nd.1916. S.o^ i No.2170. (D). Colonel Bremond has expressed to Colonel dilson hope that French Government will send European officers to accompany batteries which French are lending to Shereef and to proceed with them inland. Colonel Wilson expressed his apprehension which French Colonel premised to telegraph to Laris. Consensus of opinion on part of all our most experienced officials is against employment oi Christians and Your Excellency should lionJi Government that His majesty's Government would strengry deprecate such action as likely to affect the situation unfavourably and express earnest hope that batteries and ammunition may be sent without personnel. F.ereoted to Sir KokCrmihon ho. 7SI* oflW' 6 )In any further commumca- tion on this subject, please quote Aid) So . w. I ^ I C and address — The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, London. 56 The Undersecretary of S Foretgti A (fairs presents his compliments to the Undersecretary of State for 9 ) -— and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith. copL^^ of the under-meutionect paper Foreign Office, Reference to preznony^eofrespondeiice to Letter f rom Office: Description of tnclosure. 4 .Copy. 1M0.93. (181437) A L G I S R 3, September 4th, 1916. Ivly Lord: - I have the honour to report that by an official announcement inserted in the local news papers the Government General of Algeria have offered to send a party of Arabs on a pilgrimage to liecca. All passage and food expenses as far as Jeddah, and from that port back to Algiers, are to be paid by Government. I have, &amp;c., (Signed) Basil S. Cave. The Right Honourable Viscount Grey of Fallodon, K.G., &amp;c., &amp;c., &amp;c.Os In any further communica tion on this subject, please quote No. W. 3 A and address— ' The Under-Secretary of State, Foreign Office, I^ondon. P 3931 \ V 12 The Undersecretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Undersecretary of State for Jlxfi t and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop of the under-mentioned paper Foreign Office, J2 , lyib Reference to previous correspondence: Utter ^ rom Foreign Office: ~J I U / Description of Inclosure. Name and Date. Subject. h\ c /n t\. 2/S dllxl' % t* OyjL , (*, 2e8EP18tS^ Stmihrr Rttei sent to ti\rThis Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government and should be returned to the Foreign Office when done with umess required for official use.] --•'■'Decypher* Sit K* KcEohon* (Cairo) September No.. 794.. Yorr telegram No. 744. No .further news received from Hedjaz. I am afraid as regards present crisis which can hardly continue more than two or three weeks any assistance that French Government can give is un likely to arrive in time to he of use. Naval Commander-in-Chief is arranging to increase temporarily number of warships on Hedjaz coast and their assistance if need arises may oe of vital import ance in encouraging Arabs and in preventing Turks advancing along coast to Rabegh should latter break through the hills* Main essential is to keep up spirit of Arabs and tor this reason I still urge sending a flight or even half flight of aeroplanes so urgently requested by Shereef. Moral effect of seaplanes now there reported very great but their range is very small. . If aeropla are available I am confident we can find sa-.e base o. coast on which their use would be conditional* Addressed to Foreign Office. Bent to India and EGYPT MILITARY 13. 8.30.p*m. September 17+11,1916., R.12*30.p.m. September 18th,1916*. Sirdar No. 794,Mintrthis Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty^ GoTernment and shoqld be retorned to the Foreign Office when done with unless required for offloial use. Dec, pnor Gi: Do Do 8-5 p.mo 10 c 7 CIO ill o IicDDDon (1-a.nleh), September 15thol91So September 15thol91So September lotli, 191-3^ NOc 785o French Minister informs me that French fission Military and Civil, will leave Suez September 17th for Jeddah whence Lioslem members proceed to Meccan Col. Bremont a:id his French officers appear to intend to remain considerable time at Jeddah* Addressed to Foreign Office, sent to India and Sirdar hOo 785c[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Gover nment and should be returned to the Foreign Office when done with u nless required for official use. r U -rivpn ^ ^ r MILITjU^Y . Cypher Tele-ran to Sir M, McMahon (llanleh) foreign Office, Septenher 14th f 1916 r 10rGrp P nr jl'I Or 7 4fc4 • Your telegr.an ilOr On Septenhor 2;-icl r posal to send Sudanese then oy British troops 773 r War Connittee considered pro- troons to liedjaz and replace from Egypt and wore decidedly of opinion that latter could not he sparedr his decision would equally apply /O sending British troops to HedjaZr I cannot hold out any hope tha of military authorities, which appear to no t objections on mili tary grounds to be well-founded, can be overcone r But this being so we cannot object and nust facilitate assistance which the French nay be able to send, if and when such is forthcoming*[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty^ Gove rnment, ^ and should be returned to the Foreign Office when done wit h unless required for official use;] Colonel V/ilson arrived yesterday* After discussion with him and a long conference with Commander-in-chief, Egypt and Naval Commander~in- Personal discussion with Colonel Wilson results in following appreciation* Situation in Hedjaz has developed to a point at which an immediate decision is necessary r Turks have brought Ali Haidar, their newly ap pointed Shereef with (gr, undec*) and holy carpet to Medina and are determined to try and break through along Sultaneh Road viS, Rabegh to Mecca in tine for pilgrimage r Shereef Faisal is opposing them on Sultaneh Road which is their only practicable route and Shereef Ali is operating on their left flank and rear* Faisal has declared to Wilson that his forces are beginning to doubt reality of British support and states unless they receive moral backing of trained troops at Rabegh they will lose heart and give way to a really determin ed advance on Rabegh where Shereef has large quan'oi- De^yphar* Sirril^-Mcllahon (Ramleh) September 13th r 1916 D? 12ro0fP*m. a R, 8* 50c. Pent, Seplember 13th., 1916 NOo 778 Chief at which Colonel Wilson assisted I addressed fol lowing memorandum to Commander-^in-Chief^ 'M emoran dum 11 »quantities of supplies and nunitions of war on which Turks are reckoning for their further advance to lieccar On the other hand Faisal maintains (and 'fil^on is of the same opinion) that visible sign of British support, and feeling of security afforded by presence of trained troops at Paoegh would so put heart into his Arabs as to enable his and Ali’s force to hold up Turk force and sever their all vital communication with Medina# Turks would be correspondingly discouraged and to them time is now a factor of vital importance unless they are to fail completely* If Turks succeed not only will our pilgrimage be seriously endangered but the whole Arab mdvement will run grave risk of collapse * Re-capture of Mecca, apart from grave damage which will ensue to our prest ige throughout Moslem world will open the whole of Arabia to Turk's and give them tree access to Eastern shores of Red Sea* Situation in Abyssinia and Somaliland Protectorate will also be affected seriously, thus jeopardising the whole military and political situation East of Suez,- Arab revolt has barred Turkish expansion down and across Red Sea which recent information now proves to have been their aim, and at a time when every available man is required in main theatres of war it is essential to maintain this barrier r Moreover we are morally committed to support Shereef and we shall certainly be held in a large mens-measure responsible tor liis failurer Arg'jr.^e^ts in favour of tlnrcat against railway tron Akaba still bolds good but recent developments at Med ina have caused that operation to take second place to L-mediate ^^.d dn^ect support of Faisal by a British force at Babeghr I fully appreciate political and religious objec tions to landing British (Government) troops in hedjaz and capital which hostile propagandists will make of such action, especially in India, but it is a ratter for His Hajesty’s Government to decide whether this would not be preferable to very serious situation which might result from total collapse of Arab movement, which it must be remembered has sympathy if not actual support of majority cf Arab races. After very careful consideration I am of opinion we should offer Shereef to send an infantry brigade to Habegh to give Faisal that moral support which he so urgently demands and, if Shereef accepts, troops should be sent without delay. It should be clearly pointed out that no advance will be made beyond Haoegh in a iy circumstances that a brigade absolute maximum nd that it will be withdrawn immediately present crisis is over, r therefore ask that subject to approval of Consul one brigade of Infantry, one Company of Engineers two batteries of Artillery, one Field Ambulance, and half Sl r ‘ F, Wingate 5 a aero .'lanes be held in readiness jO proceed to Rabegh at earliest possible date, Mahometan troops would be preferable to British if available but presenceprese : ic3 of Huropea'i of ficers and nechanic troops neces sary for a’v sued force na.kes distinction of less value and importance P If we do not send troops I knov/ French. Crover-'ment is ready to otter to send French Moslem, troops to Hedjaz and this I greatly deprecate, as it will rob us of very great political advantages which Shereef’s suc cess will hereafter give us c Moreover they could hardly arrive in time to be of use r Since writing abo^e 1 have received a telegram from Shereet with an urgent request for three battalj ons r 1 am aware how difficult wjde scope of your 'task in a Sg^pt and incessant calls upon you make it tor you to afford more than that material assistance which you have ungrudgingly given up to date, but I beg that you win submit question to War Office with such observations which you may soe tit to make v r There is every hop ; that Arabs will take advantage of precarious position of Turkish force and attain desir ed success by their own efforts but it seems imperatively necessary to provide moral support to ensure this and avoid wide-spread consequences of a reverse* French assistance in troops, even if in time to be of use, which 1 greatly doubt, would entail nnny in convenient c onsequencesr Addressed to Foreign Office, sent to India and Sirdar Wo* 7'7B r[This Pocament ig tha Property of His Britannic Gow^rnment, and should be returned to the Foreign Office when done with unless required for offieial use.] EGYPT, 2 / $&gt;4A\ (181672/16). Cypher Telegram to sir H, McMahon (Romleh) Foreign Office, September 13th. 1916. T.O.p.m, NOr 736 r Please see telegram from General Officer Cornmnding to Chief of Imperial General staff of September 6th, No, 1002, French Government have given official assurance that strict instructions have been given to Colonel Bremond that he is to act in complete accord with the British Authorities in Cairo, to render all possible facilities and not to intervene in internal administra tion of new Arab State nor in any questions affecting the political status of territories on the Red Sea lit toral, I understand moreover that French are prepared to supply personnel, equipment and ammunition for a field battery,.a mountain battery and 8 machine gun. sections, as well as company of engineers, the personnel of a railway and telegraph section and sufficient officers and non-commissioned officers to enable Sherif to organ ise locally 2 Infantry Battalions and 4 Squadrons of Cavalry, Personnel in above cases to be Moslem, Ih view of importance of rendering early assistance to Sherif in matter of guns I have invited French Gover nment to proceed at once with training and despatch of above units..)fc In any farther comraanica- Ijg ob this rabject, please quote The Under-Secretary of State Foreign Office, London. ^ ^ B 14 SEP 1916 12] The Undersecretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Under-Secret ary of State for A and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, iqi6. Reference to previous correspondence: Letter Foreign Office: -7^3 32 Name and Date. No / 7 (Similar letter sent to Description of Inclosure. Subject. iff' &gt;L f\d^CC^ Cr^Copy. No. 158. (177828) TANGIER, i 29 th Aiigust, 1916 ^ a 4 I - ! v . ~ ~ My Lord:- I am informed by my French Colleague that Sid Ben Ghabrit, an Algerian, who was formerly Interpreter at the French Legation at Tangier, but, since the establishment of the Protectorate, has been employed at the Residency, is to be sent to Mecca at the head of a delegation of Algerians and Tunisians to compliment the Grand ohereef on the declaration of his independence. There was, at first, some question of sending Moors with the deputation, but General Lyautey dis approved of this course as being likely to give rise to dissatisfaction in this country. The Moors have never recognised the Caliphate of the Sultan of Turkey, as they regard their own Sultan as the n Emir el Mumenin’ 1 or ft Prince of the True Believers’*, and say their prayers in his name only. I have, etc., (Signed) Herbert E. White* Viscount Grey of Fallodon, K.G # , &amp;c., &amp;c., &amp;cr Immediate and Confidential. '5 b S 6 19 i 6 Ike Under-Secretary of State for Foreign A fairs presents his compliments to the Under-Secretary of State for India, and is directed by the Secretary of State to transmit the accompanying copies of telegram , as marked in the. KsF margin. |M0' 1 Foreign Office, Scjfi^Lcux.'frCs/ ~J ^ igrd. (Reference :• )[This Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government, a nd should be returned to n the Foreign Office when done with unless required for official use.] I/JLI 'fABY -, Decypher„ Lord Bertie (Pnris) Septeraber 5th, 1916. conversation that one of Algerians in the mission is a fully trained artillery officer in French army and has been in command of battery at the front. French hope that Shereef will keep him as permanent instructor and organ!aer. D. 11.32 p.ns. September 5th, 1915. B, 10.40 a.nio September 6th, 1916 ooeooo»f&gt;o«oIn any farther comraomca- &amp; ob thi* snbject, please quote The Under-Secretary of State Foreign Office, London. f'' I *j b o The Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Undersecretary of State for A v*/c^ — and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, ~dtf\JdL y , 1916 . Reference to previous correspondence to Letter , Foreiqn Office from * “ Description of Inclosure. Name and Date. Jt* h*. /^7 i.n. Subject. Mrno tx&gt; y f\ s&lt; { n 8 sir (Similar letter sent to! T 0* 3.97# The residency, Humleh, Egypt. August 24th. 1916. The .M 1 U My Lord, With reference to my telegram No.719, of the 23rd instant, I have the honour to en close herewith copies of two Notes Verbales, dated August 21st, which were hrnded to me by the French Minister. The one calls my attention to the forth coming Missions from the French Government to the Grand Lherif; the other informs me of the prospective arrival at Jeddah of the French pilgrimage to lecca. * I have the honour to be. My Lord, with the highest respect. Your Lordship's rost obedient, humble Servant, (Signed) A. H. M° MAHON Viscount Grey of Fsllodon, K.G., etc. etc. etc. etc.' &gt; This Docnment is the Property of His Britannic Majesty's Qoyernment, and should be returned to the Foreign Office when done with nnless required for official nse.] f p ^ ci 4 S 4 [ ; 916 EGYPT . ' . ESii&amp;Cjaj.Qf Decypher. Sir H.. Mci/iahon (hainleh) August 29th. 1916.. D. 9.20 p,m... August 29th.19.16. li. 10.30 a.m,. August 30th. 1916. No.- 735. Your telegram No. 699. . I will act accordingly. French Minister has now written informing me that as mission are taking presents and 'subsides' of great value it is indispensable that Shereef himself should take the necessary steps to arrange transport and safety of party and itaggage, and that it is equally fitting that he should send a worthy representative to Jeddah to command guards of convey and take full responsibility for all that is intended for Shereef. He asks me to communicate all this to the Shereef. I propose to do so. ■ Confidential. I have thought it advisable in conversation to-day to mention to the French Minister that although mission is political in contra-distinction to religious qua Khalifate it might do Shereef great harm and frustrate our efforts to the contrary if mission was advertised as one of official nature from the Government of France, a Christian power. . It would be better to let it be ■•known /v \ 'ft \ ♦ Of; ’ 3 qJKJ.- tTV * fc -* - AiiGu'n as a congrat/Ulatory mission from Moslem portioii ^ of tlie French Lmpire, and v*nich comes '.ith the approval and assistance of sympathetic French Government* French Minister said he could bring this aspect of the question to the notice of his Government.t 14 la Any farther communica- tiofi or this subject, please quote no w. 167191 /1916 tnd address— The Under-Secretary of State Foreign Office, London. @ (S&gt; P, *&gt; hL The Under-Secretary of State for Foreign Adairs presents his^ compliments to the UNDER SECRETARY OF STATE FOR IaDIA and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transtmts herewith copy of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, September 2nd , 1916 . - Reference to previous correspondence L etter ffjS&amp; Foreign Office: P. 3372 of September 1st, 1916. Description of Inclosure. Name and Date. Subject. To French Ambassador, September 1st, 1916. Crw l ^ * M French Mission to the Shreef of Mecca. / (Similar letter sent to’ 1671.0/16) Copy. *1% Koreif n C r ice, .,©nte wr 1st, Your .xcelloncy:- monsieur de leuriau war, eo fpod as to communi cate to ie on the 4th ultimo a proposal of the French Government to se/Ki a military and political nisrion to the Grand oereef of ;ecoa. , i the ccllency that jlia 3 ajesty Government consider that such a mission, and the military arid financial as sistance which it will afford to the Shereef, will be of considerable utility, and they have accordingly instructed it lajeaty *» lii^.h Commisrioner for {yoi to render it every assistance in his po-^er Ji&lt;i to place Colonel Br 6 mond in relations with the military authorities i ( yot. Instructions will also be sent to His ajesty’s Consul at Jeddah to facilitate the journey of the mission as far an possible, to inform the Shereef of its inoendin^; arrival and to request him to make the necesrary arririf eaents for its reception. 1 would, however, t ke tfatw occasion to surest, for the consideration of Your nxcellency*s Covern- nent, that if tiie mission is announce • as one of an official nature fro^ the i ronch Govemnent, a Chris tian Power, to the Chereef, it hi react unfavour ably on the latter’s position amorv oslens, and that ds .xceliency Ofcueur Paul Cambon, G.C.V.G*(W.152849/16) UU t* 3-vMa ^ y .CUuj. fCf/i r j Secret. i Foreign Office, August 21st, 1916, &amp; i 6 Sir:- 7^ With reference to the Note from the French Charg6 d’Affaires of the 4th«instant, relative to the proposal of the French Government to send a political and military mission to the Grand Sherif, I am directed by Viscount Grey of Fallodon to state that Lieutenant-Colonel Sir Mark Sykes has recently discussed this matter with representa tives of the French Embassy* It appears from this conversation that the proposed mission would not be political in the sense of interfe rence, or even examination of the Sheriffs administration in the Hedjaz or on its littoral, and that its object would be to show Moslem French citizens and the Sherif that the French Government were favourable to the Sheriffs absolute independence, and were desirous to facilitate the pilgri mage, to ensure the comfort of pilgrims from French ter ritory and to afford the Sherif such assistance in arras and money as right be conveyed to him through a purely Mos lem channel. Lord Grey considers that His Majesty’s Government should not discourage this mission, which, besides provi ding the Sherif with additional financial and military assistance, will go far to disabuse native opinion of the impression that the Sherif is a mere nominee of His Ma jesty’s Government, and he would, therefore, propose, if Mr. Secretary Chamberlain sees no objection, to address to / The Under Secretary of State for India. o ' / USW. 15&lt; to the French Charge d 1 Affaires the Note, of which a draft is enclosed herein for Mr. Chamberlain’s con- cur rence. I am, Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant, 9 French Charge DRAFT. yW. 152849/15 DRAFT . 'K French Charge d*Affaires. / Foreign Office, August 1916, Sir;- I have the honour to acknowledge the re ceipt of your Note of the 4th instant, in which you were good enough to communicate to me the intention of your Government to send a military and political mission to the Grand Sherif. I have the honour to state in reply that His Majesty’s Government consider that this mission, and the military and financial as sistance which it will afford to the Sherif, will be of considerable utility, and that they will be happy to instruct His Majesty’s High Commissioner for Egypt and His Majes ty’s Consul at Jeddah to render every as sistance to the members of the mission and to the French Officer who will be sent to Egypt to superintend its movements.*1(^3 In any farther commumca- tjc on thi* subject, please quote «o.w. IS ZV+cj/ iodaddr&lt; The Under-Secretary of State fereign Office, - London. 16 . i] The Undersecretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Undersecretary of State for /LA, / ' and, by direction of the Secretary of State, transmits herewith cop-us of the under-mentioned paper. Foreign Office, J 2 j , 1916 . tc QwccUol. 'I i (buA^U/d\ Reference to previous correspondence to Letter from Forei 9 n Office: Description of Inclosure. Name and Date. Ji —y Subject. 28 AUG 1915 V- ) / (Similar letter sent to 3-^^ DTL . —This Doonment is the Property of Hia Britannic Wajtaty’g Oovarnment, and should be ratorned to the Foreign Office whan done with unisss required for official use.l (167191/16)„ Cypher Tolegrain to Sir H, McMahon (Rnrnleh) Foreign Office, August 28th„ 1916 0 7 &lt; .30.p,w. No. 699. Your telegran No. 719 (of 23rd. August), You should give French Mission every assistance and put Colonel Brernond in touch with military authori ties as desired. Colonel Wilson at Jeddah should also be instructed to facilitate journey of Mission, and to inform Cher if of its impending arrival and ask that necessary ar rangements may be made. Confident ial. Colonel Wilson should not describe mission as a 'political' one, I understand unofficially that French Minister's Note to you goes beyond intentions of French Government, which were merely to mark clearly fact that Mission was not concerned with Ques tion of Khalifate in any way.Immediate and ^Confidential. t his andwmsssm Immediate and Confidential. tL The Undersecretary of State for Foreign Affairs presents his compliments to the Undersecretary op State for India, and ts directed by the Secretary of State to transmit the accompanying copies of telegram , as marked in the margin. Foreign Office, , iqi6. (Reference :— [ 15 a ] 25AU6191C; X ' V; ) /rThis Document is the Property of His Britannic Majesty’s Government and should be returned to the Foreign Office whe n done with unless required for official use.) . iVULITARY Decypher. Hr H. McMahon (Rarnleh) August 23rd,, 1916. D. 12.20 p.ra. August 23rd.1916, R. 1 p.ra. August 24th,1916. No. 719. Urgent. My telegram No. 693. French Mission to Sheriff. French Minister has handed me a note verhale on following sense. Mission which French Government have decided to send to Sheriff of Mecca is entirely p&amp;litical and has nothing of (Treligious) nature about it: it is sent by president of the Republic to Sheriff as head of a Moslem Community which has detached itself from the Ottoman Emoire. The fact is emphasized that this mission has nothing to do with question of Khalifate in which French Government has decided not to interfere, and will not discuss it even should question arise. Object of Mission is to get into touch with Chief who will in future be responsible for the Holy places, and to settle with him pilgrim question which con cerns (? all) French and Moslem subjects. Moslems alone will represent French Government in this mission. 22, AUG 1 PM' MissionMission will consist of two divisions:- 1. , A civil delegation beaded by Ben Ghimburit who is director of the protocol to Sultan of (?Morocco) and an official of French Foreign Office. Delegation will aJ.se include a Moroccan, son of Sherifian Grand Vizier, two Tunisian and two Algerian notables, and possibly one of political leaders of French West Africa. 2. A military delegation, itself composed of two groups a and b. (a) composed of 4 Moslem officers of?) French Regiment accompanied by their Moslem orderlies. (b) which is to (Tremain) in Egypt, composed of Lieut-Colonel Bredus, another officer not yet (?appoint- ed), an interpreter,, two soldier secretaries three orderlies. This military delegation (2) will leave Marseilles on August 23rd for Alexandria where it will be Joined later by civil delegation; latter being due to leave Marseilles on September 6th. '.The two delegations will sail from Alexandria for Mecca on French cruiser 'd'Estree'.- Military Mission is meant to discuss with Sheriff, in agreement with British Military Authorities extent and nature of military assistance which cou.id be given to Arab revolt. This military assistance is apable of being especially useful in view of exis tence of Moslem units. Colonel Bredus, while not himself proceeding to Arabia will also direct the political mission, and he will have to decide where he mustmust make his headquarters in order test to fulfil his duties* He has ? teen (?instructed):- lo To put himself in touch with British military authorities (? especially) (?as to) his own definite quartersj eventual establishment of a base, movements of personnel of (? group) (?etc) and only to act in complete agreement with those authoritieso S* S«, i; Sto Francis d 1 Assisi' will be placed at the disposal of the military mission and is due at Port Sudan on (? g-gptember 10th) * French Minister has been instructed to ask High Commissioner to help him to carry out the above (?arrangements) and he begs him to inform Sheriff of the coming of the mission and to request him to (?take charge of) his representatives to the mission on its arrival at Jeddah and to provide transport and sufficient escort to ensure the safe arrival at Mecca of the members of the mission and the contributions ('subsides') and presents which they are conveying* He also asks High Commissioner to bring the above to the notice of the military authorities and to put Colonel Bredus into touch with them, in order that arrangements may eventually be made for the establish ment of his quarters in Egypt (? or at) some place on the Red sea Coast as he may think besto With reference to French pilgrimage in a further notenote verbal© French Minister informs me that pilgrimag arranged by French Government will consist of about 600 Moslems from Algeria, Tunis and Morocco® Pilgrims will travel on Messageries steamer 'OrenoQu.e” due at Port Said about September 16th and at Jeddah about September 20th® He asks me to inform the Sheriff of these arrangements in order that the latter may be able to take the necessary steps to ensure transport of pilgrims from Jeddah to Mecca and back and their safety on the way® French Minister understands that the Question of mission has been discussed between French and British Governments., I would be glad to receive instructions® Addressed to Foreign Office ? sent to India, Sirdar No® 719ofThifl Dooament is the Property of His Britannic Majesty's GoyernmaBt, and shonld be returned to the Foreign Office whoa- done with unless n 4 - required for official use. IGYPTJ xJ I '' ISKT^TARY . Jecypher. Sir H. McMahon (Cairo) August 13th, 1916 , Do 8.30 p f m, August 13th, 1916, E No. 689 11.45 a 0 m. August 14th, 1916, Arab revolt, (?August 12th) tollowiqg received from H.M.S, 'hardinge' begins, Shereef 0 f Ya^bo requests following message may be passed to Shereef 0 f Mecca, ;i Thursday A,gust 3rd army of Said All fought -fks near Gadir Nabek, battle lasted about 28 hours. Beni Palin ' Beni ^en assisted Said All who draw enemy to mountains and the rest to Gadir Rabek t*he fanner having no water or food, It is said that the Turks lost heavily; Said All captured an officer and some soldiers, mules (? and) arn]S ' LatGr messaee state ® that Um-lej surrendered to Said Ghacib Ibn Bedawi brother of Mahommet Ali; all Juheimahs are ready and expecting rifles and ammunition messenger has arrived from Faisal saying the ibrks nave been surrounded in mountains'. Message ends, Sain Ali iS doubtless Shereef Ali son of Shereef of Mecca, (? Position of) Gadir Rabek not yet ascertained it is presumably in neighbourhood of Medina where Faisal and All have been jointly, operating. Although above news is encouraging it indicates i A' r' i /'Vf tii at/n-s that Medina garrison is operating ovteide of Medina aid it is very necessary to do whatever we can to enco'.rag-e Arab Tribes into more energetic offensive against them. Most effective, safest and in the end cheapest way o f ooing this would be to further enhance the ef'.ect ot our recent success in Sinai by a demonstration against Railway from Alcaba. General Murray is. care- tuily considering this action with naval authorities. His latest intelligence intonation shows that Akaba' has been more strongly fortified than was anticipated. Addressed to Foreign Office, sent to India, Aden, Sirdar No. 689.This -tho Property of His Britannic Maja8ty ? » O-OY^rntwant, ^and h» ratiayped to the Foreign Office when ^otra with nnlssji (n^ l^qiiiired (or offioial asa.l r' ITrYPT T ■ T T rrn \ zjv i iXXJ±i : ill- * Dccypher Sir H. I icl.In.hon (PtaraLeh) Avsivst 14th. 1916. D. 9.40 -n.n. Auyu^'t 14th.1916. R. 12.15 p,.rn. Au n v rt 15th.1916 No. 693 , Vrf»' ..’ .aa ^ Arab revolt. French Ivlnistcr in;!on;iS ne that his Government propose to send a small Mssion comoosed of renre- sentatives of lloslems of Morocco, Tunis and Algiers to Hed,~ias to congratulate Shorecf of Mecca. iF understand that fission will also arrange at Jeddah for reception of some 500 selected pilgrims of good status vhon French Government proTjose to send from above countries for coming pilgrimage. French Minister thinlcs that his Government are addre-sin: 1 : His Majesty^ Govermcnt on the subjects I told him incidentally that moment was perhaps unfavourable for such a fission. I do not think that we can oppose the idea but it indicates desire of French Government to establish direct relations 1th Shereof and perhaps have a (say ?) in Hodjas affairs. Former(\12) v _y Porraor is inevitable in vievj of French interests in North Arabia but any step in latter direction (outside previous consular representation at Jeddah) should I think be discouraged from toe outset-on the part of France or any other po f,r er* Addressed to Foreign Office, sent to India, Aden, Sirdah number 5S3. ——</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000419.0x0001fe_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/10/615</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000419.0x0001fe</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/10/615</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>File P 3372/1916 Pt 1 'Arab Revolt: the French Mission. French Designs in Hedjaz'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1916/1917</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-05-05T11:27:37</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">fre</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (178 folios)</extent><extent>The subject 3372 (Pt 1 Arab Revolt, and Pt 2 Arabia) consists of two volumes, IOR/L/PS/10/615-616. The volumes are divided into two parts, with each part comprising one volume.The papers are arranged in chronological order from the rear to the front of the volume.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the first folio with 1 and terminates at the last folio with 178; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.The foliation sequence does not include the front and back covers, nor does it include the leading and ending flyleaves.A previous foliation sequence, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The volume contains correspondence, and India Office Secret Department minute papers, mostly relating to French policy regarding the Hedjaz [Hejaz or Hijaz]. This correspondence largely consists of: copies of telegrams between the Foreign Office and the British High Commissioner of Egypt (Sir Arthur Henry McMahon, followed by Sir Francis Reginald Wingate); and copies of correspondence between the Foreign Office and the French Ambassador to the United Kingdom (letters from the French Ambassador are in French). It also includes some correspondence between the India Office and the Foreign Office.The volume includes correspondence concerning: the proposed French civil and military mission to the Sherif [Sharif, also spelled Shereef in the correspondence] of Mecca, Hussein ibn Ali al-Hashimi; the proposed pilgrimage to Mecca of Muslims from Algeria, Tunis and Morocco, arranged by the French Government; correspondence regarding the reported requests of King Hussein for the employment of Muslim doctors from French colonies in North Africa in the Hedjaz, and for a wireless telegraph installation in the Hedjaz to connect Rabegh [Rabigh], Jeddah and Mecca; and the British desire for the withdrawal of the French Military Mission to the Hedjaz.The volume includes a divider which gives the subject number, the year the subject file was opened, the subject heading, and a list of correspondence references by year. This is placed at the back of the correspondence.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Doctors</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>King of Hejaz</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>High Commissioner, Egypt</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>French Embassy, London</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Hedjaz</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Mecca</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Arab Revolt (1916-1918)</topic></subject><subject><topic>Wireless telegraphy</topic></subject><subject><topic>Muslim pilgrims and pilgrimages</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000419.0x0001fe#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>