<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000348_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T23:31:01.199Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">mmmm GOVERNMENT OF PAKISTAN MINISTRY OF COMMUNICATIONS (Communications Division). NOTIFICATION. Dated 30-4-48. % V ,* e - i ' \ No - Av-20(3)/48—In exercise of the powers conferred by clause icL° f sul J' Sect J 10 1 n of Section 6 of the Indian Aircraft Act 1J34 as adapted by the Pakistan (Adaptation of Existing Pakistan Laws) Order, 1947, the Central Government being of the opinion that it is m the interests of public safety so to do, is pleased to order that no aircraft, other than aircraft engaged in a scheduled air transport service shall make flights into, or in transit across the territory of Pakistan save in accordance with the following conditions which shall be observed by every person incharge of such aircraft or otherwise assisting in the flight thereof, viz, (1) Every such aircraft shall, immediately upon entry into 1 akistan, and without a prior landing elsewhere in Pakistan, be flown to and landed at (a) If the entry is from the West, Karachi Airport or Karachi Marine Airport (Korangi Creek). (b) If the entry is from the East, Dacca (Tezgaon) or Chittagong Aerodrome. (c) If the aircraft is flying from India to West Pakistan, Lahore Aerodrome or Karachi Airpott. (d) If the entry is from India into Eastern Pakistan, Dacca (Tezgaon Aerodrome). (2) The aircraft, after such landing, shall not proceed further unless the pilot has obtained a clearance certificate in writing from an officer duly authorized by the Central Govt, in this behalf. Provided that the Central Government may by general or special order exempt any aircraft or class of aircraft generally or for any specified flight from the provisions of this order. Provided further that nothing herein shall affect manner the requirements as specified from time to time Government of Pakistan in regard to health. in any by the Sd/- M. H. Zuberi. Deputy Secretary to the Government of Pakistan■ i. s • GOVERNMENT OF PAKISTAN NOTICE TO AIRMEN No. 11 of 1948 REGULATIONS CONCERNING THE FLIGHT OF AIRCRAFT TO OR ACROSS PAKISTAN. (I. 14-24/48) Attention is invited to the Government of Pakistan, Ministry of Communications Notification No. A. V. 20 {3)/48, dated the 30th April 1948, reproduced overleaf, promulgating regulations concern ing the flight of aircraft to or across Pakistan. Karachi: The 29th May 1948. J. P. JEFFCOCK. Director General of Civil Aviation. Pakistan Printing Works, Karachi —400—29-5-48.3 . From, To No. D 352-0/48 S ? ciretary to GovQ rnraent of Pakistan. Ministry of Foreign ./Iffairs and Commonwealth Relation •n he Colonial Secretary, Singapore. H1 s Britanic Majesty r s Consul-General, o tt^ _ . , Saigon. b. His Britannic Majesty f s Consul-General, m, . Bataila. . ^ on ^ke Political Resident in the Persian dulf, Bahrain. ft t ” 9 Political Agent. Bahrain(Mth one spare copy) 6 . The Counsellor British Embassy, Bagdad. o* m!j e Counsellor British Embassy, Jedda. a. ihe 1st Secretary Embassy of Pakistan in Burma, -• Rangoon. 9. His Majesty»s Consul General, Basra Dated Karachi the 25 September 1948 Sir, Airmen' No H enc l°? e . her oin a copy of'Nbtice to - d.t.Ahflot ^ 1 AV.20(3,/48 Communications, Government of li:L ^ 101: ry oi 1. Singapore 2 . Saigon 3. Batavia. 4. &amp; 5 S herjab and Bahrain 6 . Dhahran 7„&amp; 8 Basra 9 Rangoon, I have the honour to be, o Sir, Your most obedient servant, fr^ 0 4.^ (S f Lal Shah) or Secretary to the Government of Pakistan. 'M» 173/48 :.H 1 - ^ ^ (S.Lal S hah) for Seoretary to the Government of Pakistan, &gt;wm CONFIDENTIAL No.C/L-167. * THE POLITICAL AGENCY, BAHRA ■ If, Dated the , s # Tlgt October The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments p The station Superintendent, British Overseas Airways Corporation, Bahrain, and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document(s) - &gt; * HEFEHENUu to PHcVIOUS C Oitxt-.SPONDENCE i DtiSCHiPTIOM- OF ijHCLOain.': REGULATIONS CONCERNIt.G 1HE FLIGHT OF AIRCRAFT TO OR ACROSS PAKISTANINDIA OFFICE RECORDS ■l microfilm</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000348_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/537</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000348</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/537</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>‘File 13/33 Notices to airmen issued by the Government of Pakistan’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1948/1948</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-04-03T00:08:20</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (5 folios)</extent><extent>The file’s contents are arranged in approximate chronological order, from the earliest item at the front to the latest at the end. The file notes at the end of the file (f 6) mirror the chronological arrangement.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence commences at the front cover and terminates at the back cover; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains a copy of ‘Regulations concerning the Flight of Aircraft to or across Pakistan’, published by the Government of Pakistan in Karachi, 29 May 1948 (f 3), which draws attention to a notification on its reverse, issued by the Government of Pakistan Ministry of Communications, dated 30 April 1948 (f 3v), signed by H M Zuberi, stipulating the conditions under which aircraft should fly across Pakistan, and the circumstances under which aircraft should be obliged to land at one of the country’s airports. The remaining item of note in the file is a covering letter for the regulations, from the Secretary to the Government of Pakistan, dated 25 September 1948 (f 2, with duplicate on f 4), with a list of recipients.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><geographic>Pakistan</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Karachi</geographic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x000348#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>