<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000881.0x0000d9_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-05-23T13:48:25.117Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">mi PiiitSlAN GULP iihSIDiiNCY, BAHxiAlN, 17th September, 1949. Dear Burrows, Hart, the United States Consul- General at Dhahran recently asked me a number of questions about the concession obtained by Weightman for the Qatar sea-bed and enquired whether the agreement was regarded as secret. It was clear that he was anxious to obtain a copy of it. I replied that we usually kept oil concessions secret, not ior political considerations, but in the interests of the concessionaires. 2* Would you kindly let me know whether there is any objection to my showing Hart Weightman's concession or giving him a copy ol it, and whether it will be in order for me to let him know the details of any further oil concessions that may be granted. In the case of Weightman f s concession the State Department could presumably obtain a copy from the Superior Oil Company of America if they so wished. Yours ever, W.K. Hay. •i*”* a« ii# Burrows, j^sq. , The foreign Office, iionuoa, s.w.l. (D■MUMl • COPY (£11762/1271/91) COMIDI^TIAL FOxiEIGN OFFICE, S # W.l. 5th October, 1949. Dear itupert, Will you. please refer to your letter ftc. 5/2p2/49 of the 17 th September about the desire of the United States Consul-General, Dhahran, to find out details oi the Qatar sea-bed concession? I am afraid you will have to tell Hart that all oil concessions are regarded by His Majesty^ Government as confidential to the parties and to His Majesty •s Government and that it is not possible for us to reveal the terms of the Qatar sea-bed or any other oil concession. It is, as you say, up to Hart to approach the State Department and for the latter to obtain a copy from the Superior Oil Company if they can, though of course it is by no means certain that the Company would wish to reveal the terms of the concession to the State Department. Yours ever, BEHNaHD BUdHOWS. Lieutenant Colonel, Sir rtupert Hay, K.C.I.E. , C.S.I., Bahrein.jlQNFJPf.NTIA!,. HO.I9/IV6/49. The Political Agency, Muscat August 31, 1949. D«ar Residency, Will you please refer te your letter He.5/236/49 ef the I3th August about sea-bed rights. 2. Se far as ee can see, the Persian definition ef Territerial Waters ean hare ne effect en the interests ef the Sultanate ef Muscat and Onan, particularly as ne pearling is carried on here. 3. leu say be Interested te knew with reference te your Complimentary Slip No.5/187/49 ef the 2nd July that there has been ne reaction as a result ef the Sultan being banded a cepy ef the Persian BUI, and the Minister fer Foreign Affairs confirms that His Highness shows no signs sf taking any action ever sea-bed rights at the sesest. Tours ever.CCNFIDEIvTIAL. (5/2S6/49) persiat; gclf residency, BAHRAIN, 13th August, 1948. Dear Agency, We enclose herewith a copy of a letter from the Foreign Office which deals with the recent Persian Bill on the subject of sea-bed rights, and we should be grateful for your comments. The Tehran dispatch referred to enclosed a copy of this bill, which we have already transmitted to you under cover of our -5/199/49 of 16th July. The mention of the Persian definition of Territorial waters refers to the claim made In a Persian Law of the 15th July, 1934, in which Territorial waters are defined as extending six nautical miles from the extreme low-water mark. The Political Agency, Muscat. /%rCONFIDENTIAL. Copy of letter (£.7398/1271/51) of tile 5th August, 194G, from Mr« T«£. Rogers of the Foreign uflice, London, to Mr. H.G. Jakins, Acting Political Resident, ;3ahrain. ' ill you please refer to Tehran Despatch No. 216(G75/81/49) of 14th June on the subject of Persian sea-bed rights* The only point in the craft Bill which the legal Advisers have questioned is whether the pearling rights of any of our States are affected. I imagine net, unless some of our States send pearl divers to beds within the territorial waters (according to the Persian definition) of a Persian Island, but we shall be grateful if you would check this point* (SGD). T.e. ROGEHfr.11 wm * - (5/195A9) 12th July, 1949. Dear Agency, We enclose for your information a copy of the official translation of the recent Saudi Arabian proclamation regard ing Seabed and Subsoil rights and the decree defining territorial waters. Yours ever, RESIDENCY. 1 1 -******************************************************** 1 . 2 . RCXAL SAUDI ARABIAN GCVERNMENT ! i i i lioyel PronounceirAent concerning the policy of the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia with respect to the subsoil and sea Bed areas in the Persian Gulf contiguous to the coasts of the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia. Royal Decree {*0.6/6/4/3711 concern ing the territorial waters of the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia. (Cmro A1 Kora Supplement No. 1263 of 29/5/1S49). ! I I i I *:&gt;|* ***************************************************** 1 1 I I I I I I I I I I I I 1 I I i 1 I I I i I lrcyal mummommt concaralrtg the policy of the KlTigaoit* ol‘ i&gt;Audii Arabia elth respect to the Subsoil a&amp;U sea bed of areas In the Persian Gulf contiguous to the coasts of the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia ¥ e, Abdul Aziz I bn Abdul Kah&amp;ar* a ! Faisal Al ba'udy King of the Kingdom of oaudl Arabia y AFTER rellatiC# on God Almighty, being aware of the need for the greater utilisation of the world*s natural resources which are the bounty of God f arid of the desirability of giving encouragement to efforts to discover and make available such resources, KSCttiimxHG that by GodU Providence valuable resources may underlie parts of the Persian Gulf off tne coasts of Saudi Arabia, and that modern technology by the grace of God makes it increasingly practicable to utilise these resources, ArPhEClAXXNG that recognised Jurisdiction over such resources is required in the interest of their conservation and prudent utilisation when anu as development is undertaken, DESK UK) that the exercise of Jurisdiction over such re~ sources by the contiguous nation is reasonable and Just, since the effectiveness of measures to utilise or conserve these resources would be contingent upon cooperation and protection from the shore and since self•protection compels the coastal nation to keep close watch over activities off its shores which are of a nature necessary for the utilisation of these resources, and that various other nations now exercise jurisdiction over the subsoil and sea bed of areas contiguous to their coasts, PECLAKE the following policy of the Kingdom of baud! Arabia with respect to the subsoil and sea bed of areas of the Persian Gulf contiguous to the coasts of our Kingdomi The subsoil****.T^ k - 2 - The subsoil and sea bed of those areas of the Persian Gulf seaward from the coastal sea of Saudi Arabia but contiguous to its coasts are declared to appertain to the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia and to be subject to its jurisdiction and control. The boundaries of such areas , Uc/v^v^-v^U-l will be determined in accordance withTbther states ^ having jurisdiction and control over the subsoil and sea bed of adjoining areas. The character as high seas of the waters of such areas, the right to the free and unimpeded navigation of such waters and the air space above those waters, fishing rights in such waters, and the traditional freedom of pearling by the people of the Gulf are in no way affected. This Pronouncement is made for the information and guidance of all whom it may concern. ' May the Faithful always put their trust in God. PRCMULGATKD in our Palace at Riyadh on the 1st day of the month of Shaaban of the year of the Hegira 1368, corresponding to 88th day of May 1949. (SIGNED) ABDUL AZIZ(b) • • • • pppp ROYAL DECREE Wo. 6/5/4/3711 concerning the territorial waters of the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia. (Onun A1 Kora Supplement N0.126S of 29/5/1949) .(3 We Abdul Aziz Ibn Abdul Rahman A1 Faisal Sau^, King of the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia, After reliance on God almighty and in view of our desire to define the territorial waters of the Kingdom, have Decreed as Follows: Article 1. For the purposes of this Decree, (a) The term ‘nautical mile* is the equivalent of meters; (b) The term ‘bay* includes any inlet, lagoon or other arm of the sea; (c) The term ‘island 1 includes any islet, reef, rock, bar or permanent artificial structure not submerged at lowest low tide; (d) The term * shoal 1 denotes an area covered by shallow water, a part of which is not submerged at lowest low tide; and (e) The term ‘coast* refers to the coasts of the Red Sea, the Gulf of Aqaba, and the Persian Gulf. Article 2. The territorial waters of the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia, as well as the air space above and the soil and sub soil beneath them, are under the soverignty of the Kingdom, subject to the provisions of international law as to the innocent passage of vessels of other nations through the coastal sea. Article 3* The territorial waters of the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia embrace both the inland waters and the coastal sea of the Kingdom. Article 4. The inland waters of the Kingdom include: (a) the waters of the bays along the coasts of the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia;(oj trie waters above and Xand?rard from any shoaX no more tnan twelve nautical miles from the main land or from a Saudi Arabian island; (c) the waters between the mainland and a Saudi Arabian island not more than twelve nautical miles from the mainland; and (d) the waters between Saudi Arabian islands not farther apart than twelve nautical miles. Article 5. The coastal sea of the Kingdom of oaudi Arabia Lies outside the inland waters of the Kingdom and extends seaward for a distance of six nautical miles. Article 6. The following are established as the base lines from which the coastal sea of the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia is measured: (a) where the shore of the mainland or an island is fully exposed to the open sea, the lowest low water mark on the shore; (b) Where a bay confronts the open sea, lines drawn from headland to headland across the mouth of the bay; (c) where a shoal is situated not more than twelve nautical miles from the mainland or from a Saudi Arabian island, lines drawn from the mainland or the island and along the outer edge of the shoal; (d) where a port or harbor confronts the open sea, lines drwan along the seaward side of the outermost works of the port or horbor and between such works; (e) where an island is not more than twelve nautical miles from the mainland, lines drawn from the mainland and along the outer shores of the island; (f) where there is an island group which may be connected by lines not more than twelve nautical miles long, of which the island nearest to the mainland, is not more....is not more than twelve nautical miles from the mainland, lines drawn from the mainland and along the outer shores of all the islands of the group if the islands from a chain, or along the outer shores of theoutermost islands of the group if the islands do not form a chain; and (g) where there is an island group which may be connected by lines not more than twelve nautical miles long, of which the nearest island to the mainland is more than twelve nautical miles from the mainland, lines drawn along the outer shores of 411 the islands of the group if the islands form a chain, or along the outer shores of the outermost islands of the group if the islands do not form a chain. Article 7* If the measurement of the territorial waters in accordance with the provisions of this Decree leaves an area of high sea wholly surrounded by territorial waters and extending not more than twelve nautical miles in any direction, such area shall form part of the territorial waters. The same rule shall apply to a pronounced pocket of high sea which may be wholly enclosed by drawing a singly striaght line not more than twelve nautical miles long. Article 8. If the inland waters described in Article 4, or if the coastal sea measured from the base-lines fixed by Article 6 of this Decree be overlapped by the waters of anotherState, boundaries will be deteririned by our Government in agreement with the State concerned in accordance with equitable principles. Article 8. Mth a view to assuring compliance with the laws of the Kingdom relating to security, navigation, and fiscal matters, maritime surveillance may be exercised in a contiguous zone outside the coastal sea, extending for a further...(*?&gt; . H - 4 - for a further distance of six nautical miles and measured from the base-lines of the coastal sea, provided however that nothing in this Article shall be deemed to apply to the rights of the Kingdom with respect to fis&amp;ing. Article 10. Cur Ministers of Foreign Affairs and of Finance are charged with the execution of this Decree. Article 11. This Decree will come into effect as from the date of its publication in the official gazette. Promulgated in our Palace at Riyadh on the 1st day of the month of bhaaban of the year of the Hegira 1368, corresponding to the 28th day of May 1949. (3GD) ABDUL ALIZROYAL SAUDI ARABIAN GOVERNMENT Royal Pronouncement concerning the policy of the King dom of Saudi Arabia with respect to the subsoil and sea-bed of areas in the Persian Gulf contiguous to the coasts of the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia. Royal Decree No.6/5/4/3711 concerning the territorial waters of the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia. (Omm al Kora Supplement No.1263 of 29/5/1949)ROYAL PRONOUNCEMENT. concerning the policy of the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia with respect to the Subsoil and Sea-bed of areas in the Persian Gulf contiguous to the coasts of the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia. WE, Abdul Aziz Ibn Abdul Rahman A1 Faisal A1 Sa'Ud, King of the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia, AFTER reliance on God Almighty, being aware of the need for the greater utilization of the world*s natural resources which are the bounty of God, and of the desirability of giving encouragement to efforts to discover and make available such resources, RECOGNISING that by God*s Providence valuable resources may underlie parts of the Persian Gulf off the coasts of Saudi Arabia, and that modern technology by the grace of God makes it increasingly practicable to utilise these resources, APPRECIATING that recognised jurisdiction over such resour ces is required in the interest of their conservation and pru dent utilisation when and as development is undertaken, DEEMING that the exercise of jurisdiction over such resour ces by the contiguous nation is reasonable and just, since the effectiveness of measures to utilise or conserve these resources would be contingent upon co-operation and protection from the shore and since self-protection compels the coastal nation to keep close watch over activities off its shores which are of a nature necessary for the utilisation of these resources, and CONSIDERING that various other nations now exercise juris diction over the subsoil and sea-bed of areas of the Persian Gulf contiguous to the coasts of Our Kingdom: The subsoil and sea-bed of those areas of the Persian Gulf seaward from the coastal sea of Saudi Arabia but contiguous to its coasts are declared to appertain to the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia and to be subject to its jurisdiction and control. The boundaries of such areas will be determined in accordance with equitable principles by Our Government in agreement with other states having jurisdiction and control over the subsoil and /sea-bedsea-bed of adjoining areas. The character as high seas of the waters of such areas, the right to the free and unimpeded navi gation of such waters and the air space above those waters, fishing rights in such waters, and the traditional freedom of pearling by the peoples of the Gulf are in no way affected. This Pronouncement is made for the information and guidance of all whom it may concern. May the Faithful always put their trust in God. PROMULGATED in our Palace at Riyadh on the 1st day of the month of Shaaban of the year of the Hegira 1368, corresponding to 28th day of May 1949. (Signed) ABDUL AZIZ.I a ROYAL DECREE NO. 6/5/4/3711. concerning the territorial waters of the King dom of Saudi Arabia. (Omm al Kora Supplement No.1263 of 29/5/1949). WE Abdul Aziz Ibn Abdul Rahman Al Faisal Sa^d, King of the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia, After reliance on God Almighty and in view of our desire to define the territorial waters of the Kingdom, have Decreed as Follows: Article 1. For the purposes of this Decree, (a) The term 'nautical mile' is the equivalent of 18 2 meters; (b) The term 'bay' includes any inlet, lagoon or other arm of the sea; (c) The term 'island' includes any islet, reef, rock, bar or permanent artificial structure not submerged at lowest low tide; (d) The term 'shoal' denotes an area covered by shallow water, a part of which is not submerged at lowest low tide; and (e) The term 'coast' refers to the coasts of the Red Sea, the Gulf of Aqaba, and the Persian Gulf. Article 2. The territorial waters of the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia, as well as the air space above and the soil and subsoil beneath them, are under the sovereignty of the kingdom, subject to the provisions of inter national law as to the innocent passage of vessels of other nations through the coastal sea. Article 3. The territorial waters of the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia embrace both the inland waters and the coastal sea of the Kingdom. Article 4. The inland waters of the Kingdom include: (a) the waters of the bays along the coasts of the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia; (b) the waters above and landward from any shoal no more than twelve nautical miles from the mainland or from a /Saudi \ &lt;= f J2 Saudi Arabian island; (c) the waters between the mainland and a Saudi Arabian island not more than twelve nautical miles from the mainland; and (d) the waters between Saudi Arabian islands not farther apart than twelve nautical miles. Article 5. The coastal sea of the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia lies outside the inland waters of the Kindom and ex tends seaward for a distance of six nautical miles. Article 6. The following are established as the base-lines from which the coastal sea of the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia is measured: (a) where the shore of the mainland or an island is fully exposed to the open sea, the lowest low-water mark on the shore; (b) where a bay confronts the open sea, lines drawn from headland to headland across the mouth of the bay; (c) where a shoal is situated not more than twelve nautical miles from the mainland or from a Saudi Arabian island, lined drawn from the mainland or the island and along the outer edge of the shoal; (d) where a port or harbour confronts the open sea, lines drawn along the seaward side of the outermost works of the port or harbour and between such works; (e) where an island is not more than twelve nautical miles from the mainland; lines drawn from the mainland and along the outer shores of the island; (f) where there is an island group which may be connected by lines not more than twelve nautical miles long, of which the island nearest to the mainland is not more than twelve nautical miles from the mainland, lines drawn from the mainland and along the outer shores of all the islands of the group if the islands form a chain, or along the outer shores of the outermost islands of the group if the islands do not form a chain; and /(g)- 3 - (g) where there is an island group which may be connected by lines not more than twelve nautical miles long, of which the island nearest to the mainland is more than twelve nautical miles from the mainland, lines drawn along the outer shores of all the islands of the group if the islands form a chain, or along the outer shores of the outermost islands of the group if the islands do not form a chain. Article 7. If the measurement of the territorial waters in accordance with the provisions of this Decree leaves an area of high sea wholly surrounded by territorial waters and extending not more than twelve nautical miles in any direction, such area shall form part of the territorial waters. The same rule shall apply to a pronounced pocket of high sea which may be wholly enclosed by drawing a single straight line not more than twelve nautical miles long. Article 8. If the inland waters described in Article 4, or if the coastal sea measured from the base-lines fixed by Article 6 of this Decree be overlapped by the waters of another State, boundaries will be determined by Our Government in agreement with the State concerned in accordance with equitable principles. Article 9. With a view to assuring compliance with the laws of the Kingdom relating to security, navigation, and fiscal matters, maritime surveillance may be exercised in a contiguous zone outside the coastal sea, extending for a further distance of six nautical miles and mea sured from the base-lines of the coastal sea, provided however that nothing in this Article shall be deemed to apply to the rights of the Kingdom with respect to fishing. Article 10. Our Ministers of Foreign Affairs and Finance are charged with the execution of this Decree. Article 11. This Decree will come into effect as from the date of its publication in the official gazette. /PromulgatedPromulgated in our Palace at Riyadh on the 1st day of the month of Shaaban of the year of the Hegira 1368, correspon ding to the 28th day of May 1949. (Signed) ABDUL AZIZCQBfIDffillAL Mo. 2X6(075/81/49) British Embassy, TEHRAN. 14th June, 1949* Sir, With reference to my telegram No*419 of the 23rd May, I have the honour to transmit to you herewith a translation of a Bill presented by the Minister of Finance to the Majlis on the 19th May to authorise the Persian Government to assert rights of ownership in respect of any natural resources under the floor of the sea in the Persian Gulf, The text of the Bill is pre ceded by a statement by the Minister of Finance explaining its purpose. 2, You will observe that the draft Bill covers sub stantially the same ground as the proclamations issued by the Saudi Arabian Government and the rulers in the Gulf States under the protection of His Majesty's Government. I understand that this is because the Ministry of Finance were informed of the substance of the Saudi-Arabian proclamation in advance by Mr. Max Thornburg, of Overseas Consultants Incorporated. 3# The Law of the IJth July 1934 referred to in Article 4 of the Draft Bill as remaining in full force, defines the extent of Persian territorial waters as extending 6-miles, or for certain purposes 12-miles, from the low-water mark. A translation was enclosed in Sir R. Hoare's despatch No.320 of 1934. 4. I am sending copies of this despatch to His Majesty's Ambassadors at Washington, Bagdad and Jedda; to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, and to the British Middle Bast Office, Cairo. I have the honour to be, with the highest respect, Sir, Your most obedient, humble Servant, Sd/- J.H. LE ROUGETEL. The Right-Honourable Ernest Bevin, M.P., His Majesty's Principal Secretary of State for Foreign ikflairs, The Foreign Office, London, S.W.l.r THE PERSIAN GULF RESIDENCY BAHRAIN (5/182/40) 28th June, 1949. I think we nrobably ought to let the Sultan of Muscat have a copy of the Persian bill' about the sea bed, a cory of which was for -arded to the Foreign Office under Teheran despatch fto.216 (of the 14th J une). He may as a result with to issue a proclamation hirn- self about the continental shelf of the &amp;ulf of Oman, but I see no objection to this. A real continental shelf exists and I do not think any difficulty is likely to arise about boundaries excert that the lateral boundaries of the small oortion of the shelf apnertaining to the Sheikhdom of Kalba may have to be determined some time. 2. I think we might also pass copies of the bill to the Sheikhs of Bahrain and Ku''ait. Do }rou agree? Sd/- . 7 .R. HAY. B.A.B. Bu^ov r s, Esq., The Foreign O^ice, LONDON./ confidential N o.216(075/81/49) Sir, British Embassy, TEHERAN. 14th June, 1949 Jith reference to my teleeram No.419 of the 23rd May, I have the nonour to transmit to you herewith a trans lation ^of a Bm presented by the Minister of Finance to the Majlis on the 19th May to authorise the Persian Government to assert rights of ownership in respect of any natural^resources under the floor of the sea in the Persian juIi. The text of the Bill is preceded by a statement by th minister of Finance*explaining its pur-nose. e 2. You will observe that the draft Bin covers substantially the same ground as the proclamations issued by the Saudi Arabian Government and the rulers in the Gulf States under the protection of His Majesty’s Government. I understand that this is because the Ministry of Finance ' T ere informed of the substance of the Saudi-Arabian proclamation in advance by Mr. Max Thornburg, of Overseas Consultants Incorporated. 3. The law of the 15th July 1934 referred to in Article 4 of the Draft Bill as remaining in full force, defines the extent of Persian territorial waters as extending 6 miles, or for certain purposes 12 miles, from the low-water mark. A translation was enclosed in Sir Hoare’s despatch No.320 of 1934. 4. I am sending copies of this despatch to His Majesty’s Ambassadors at Washington, Bagdad and Jedda$ to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, and to the British Middle East Office, Cairo. I have the honour to be, with the highest respect, Sir, Your ^ost obedient, humble Servant, Sgd/- J.H. LE ^OUGHT EL. The Right-Honourable Ernest Bovin, M.P., His Majesty’s Principal Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, The Foreign Office, London, S. .7.1.TFXT OF BILL INTRODUCED IN FAJLIS BY FINISTFP OF FINANCE, 19th May, 1949: The National Assembly, The importfnce of natural resources on the sea bed and under the sea-bed in the neighbourhood of Persian territory necessitates that the Persian Government should take the necessary steps to safe guard its rights in T&gt;esrect of such resources, and in addition to the law o^ the 24th Tir 1313 (15th July 1934) concerning the territorial waters of Persia it is necessary that, owin to the inter national regulations vf ich have be°n recently imposed regarding natural resources and especially oil resources in the continental shelf of countries, the Government of Persian on the continental shelf of whose coasts there are important natural resources, should lay down new regulations and proclaim its rights of ownership in respect of these resources. I therefore, submit the attached bill and request its approval. Article 1 The natural resources existing on the sea-bed and under the sea-bed up to the limits of the con tinental shelf of the Persian coasts in the Persian Gulf and the Sea of Oman belong to the Persian Government. Article 2 Should the continental shelf of Persia extend to th^ 5 coasts of another country or be in common with another neighbouring country the limits of the interested countries in respect of natural resources on the continental shelf will be fixed between the interested Governemnts on a fair basis. Article 3 This law shall nto make any change in the position regarding non-territorial waters on the continental shelf and the right of free navigation in the said waters shall remain valid. Article 4 No alteration is made in the regulations of the law of 24th Tir 1313 (15th July 1934) and it shall remain valid. MINISTER OF MINISTER OF PRIME FINANCE FOREIGN AFlAlRS MINISTERan) FROll RESIDENCY BAHRAIN TO FOREIGN OFFICE LONDON Sir R.Hay Telno 320 2Pth June, 1049, Repeated:- Tehran telno 25 Vashihgton No.17 Saving British Middle East Office No.22 Saving Baghdad No.12 Saving Jeddah No.11 Saving SECRET Addressed to Foreign Office telno 320 of June 2Pth repeated ^or information to Tehran and Saving to Washington, British Middle East 0^f 4 ce, Baghdad and Jeddah. My telegram 297 The Sultan has written rrivately to the Political Agent saying that ^or various reasons he does not see his ' r ay to issue the nroclamation. He suggests instead that he should write to him officially referring to proclama tion already issued and claiming the same rights for Muscat He asks if this will be sufficient. 2. Political Agent attributes his attitude to his general unwillingness to act exactly as requested and to his fear of compromising his independence by annearing to act under our dictation in concert with the othwr Gulf States. For reasons stated in the last sentence of my tele gram under reference I do not think it matters much what the Sultan does and I suggest we should inform h^'m that he can.do as he wishes but that if h° does not issue a procla mation we may have difficulty in supporting his claims should another newer show interest in the avea of the sea bed concerned. - Hay -TELE FROM F. 0. TO BAHRAIN T^L NO 411 DATED 30/6/49 RECVD. 1/7/49 Confidential. •Addressed to Bahrain telno 411 June 30th repeated for info to Tehran and Saving to Washington Cairo BMEO Baghdad &amp; Jedd Your telno 297. Unnecessary commitments are to be avoided and I a m not anxious to give the Sultan the assurance you suggest when it seems at present likely that Iran will take action in line with that of our protected states and will leave open the possibility of an agreed settlement of the boundaries. It is also true that the sea- v ed off'the oultan* s coast /ithin the Gulf rrorer is in very deep rate'’ while outside the Gulf the distances between the Iranian coasts and those of the Sultan are so great and the water between them so de^n that friction is unlikely. If you agree I r ould prefer you simply (gp/undec) scout his fe^s of trouble from Ir?n ^or reasons given below.y&lt;r ) By safe hand. c £2$T*%i (40/27/48). Persian Gulf Residency, Bahrain. 20th uctooer, 1948. $4~JU t art Will you please refer to correspondence ending with my P.L. No. B/221 (86/62) - K/100 (86/62) - d/bO (86/62) of the 8th July, about the continental shelf. 2. Following the development of a technique whereby the oil deposits lying beneath the bed of the sea may be exploited, the Government of the United States in 1945 made a formal proclamation of jurisdiction over the natural resources of the continental shelf of the United States. While our views and those of the United States, have generally been easily reconciled in matters concerning Units of oil concessions on land, according to established international practice, the introduct ion of an entirely new element into the whole conception of territorial and maritime rights, has rendered essential a clearer definition of national jurisdiction with regard to the seabed in those parts of the world in which national interests, particularly those of the United Kingdom and United States, might tend to conflict. Such areas are the West Indies and the Persian Gulf. 3. It has therefore been decided by Governments of United Kingdom and United States that a definition in general terms of the jurisdiction over the continental shelf claimed by the various Persian Gulf states should be made at an early opportun ity in order to place on a regular and agreed basis any future sea-bed drilling which may be undertaken in the near future by Ull Companies operating in the Persian Gulf, and to prevent premature claims to the sea-bed ofx' the shore of the Persian Gulf States by other powers. 4. It has been agreed by ourselves and the United States that in the near future, the Governments of Saudi Arabia and the Persian Gulf Sheikhdoms and of the Sultanate of Muscat sjiould be given copies of a draft declaration kx* on the lines of that at Appendix 'A', with the request that they should study them but treat them as strictly confidential for a period of time not exceeding about three weeks in order to allow time for all rulers to be informed of the action which we are proposing to take, and in order to give the Governments of the United Kingdom and the United States, time to warn the Iraq and Persian Governments of the action which they have taken and the reason for it. After the expiry of this period, the termination of which will be notified to all rulers (during which time, the Iraq and Persian Governments will have been approached), the Persian Gulf Shaikhdoms and . uscat will be at liberty to publish the prodl&amp;mation if they so desire. 5. The exact form of the declaration is not yet final, but it is expected to be similar to that attached. The final text will be sent to you when received from the Foreign office, together with final instructions regarding date of / communication R.E. Ellison, Esq., Political Agent, Muscat.communication to the Shaikhs or the Sultan* 6* You will note that whilst the 'Median Line' may be fairly easily determined, there has been no hard and fast definition of the boundaries between the individual states on the Western and Southern sides of the Persian Gulf; these, like the land frontier, remaining to be determined at a later date in many cases. 7. In the case of Muscat, the present declaration takes into consideration only that part of liuscat territory which lies in the Persian Gulf, as opposed to the Gulf of Oman, and does not prejudice the Sultan's right in the sea-bed of the Gulf of Oman or the Arabian Sea. The United States' State Department may possibly make a separate approach to the Sultan, in addition to that made by the Political Agent, Muscat, by virtue of the long standing treaty relations of Muscat and the United States, or, alternatively may request us to inform the Sultan that our own approach is made in their name also. Instructions on this point are being sought from the Foreign Office. 8. If there is any point in this letter or its enclosure which appears to you to require clarification, Vlease inform me as soon as possible, if necessary by telegram.Secret. It UF DRAFT DLCLATIuN .^GAHDXrK; iH-ghD OIL DhPuSITS. •‘Whereas it has become technically possible to utilize the natural resources of the sea-bed and subsoil beneath the shallow seas, n Whereas it is desirable In the interests of protection, conservation, and orderly development that the exploitation of such resources should be properly controlled, Whereas it is just that the sea-bed and subsoil extending to a reasonable distance from the coasts should appertain to and be controlled by the maritime state to which it is adjacent, Whereas the right of the maritime state to exercise its control over the natural resources of the sea-bed and subsoil adjacent to its coasts has been established in international practice by the action of other states, Now therefore, we the (Shaikh, Sultan etc.) of in pursuance of all the powers enabled us in that behalf, are pleased to proclaim, and it is hereby proclaimed, as follows f• The «•••••••»• of •••••••••• hereby declares that the sea-bed and subsoil lying beneath the high seas of the Persian Gulf contiguous to the territorial waters of the •••••••••• of and within the area defined below appertain to the of •••••••••• and are subject to its exclusive jurisdiction and control. The area is that bounded by (A) To the South and North by the outer limits of the territorial sea and a line extending lengthwise in the centre of the said Gulf (hereinafter called the Median line) and (B) To the Bast and West by lines extending from the Eastern and Western limits of the territorial waters of the •••••••••• of ••.••••••• to meet the Median line, which lines are subsequently to be more precisely defined in agreement with the rulers or Governments of the adjacent states in accordance with equitable principles. Nothing In this proclamation shall be deemed to affect tha sovereignty over the islands or the status of the sea-bed and subsoil beneath any territorial waters or to prejudice Persian Gulf right in the sea-bed or subsoil of the waters elsewhere than in the Persian Gulf. Nothing in this proclamation shall be deemed to affect the air or character as high seas of the waters of the Persian Gulf above the sea-bed and outside the limits of territorial waters. 4. Nothing In this proclamation shall be deemed to affect any fishing or pearling rights.’M’PAD Telegram From To No.122. Prodrome, Bahrain Political, Jw?uscat Dated I2th, received I3th Jiay, 1949. X// Secret. Your telegram No.117. JHH.r M n /V^ Please inform Sultan that it is entirely for him to Idecide whether or not to issue a Proclamation. With resrad to hie s a request for official hacking (your telegram No.113) Foreign Office dc not wish us to give him any kind of assurance. If he ?returns to the Icbar^e you should inform 7him that it seems at present likely that Iran will take action in line with that ?cf our protected States and will Ifectve open possibility of an agreed settlement of boundaries thereby scouting his fears of trouble from that source. I am sending you a copy °* a introduced in the Iranian Majlis for communication to him. If he pursues his suggestion to write to you officially claiming rights over sea-bed you can at your discretion inform him that there is no ejection to this but it will not have effect of a public proclamation.Telegram 'M' (Pad) From Political, Tfescat To Prodrome, Bahrain No.117. . Dated the 24th June, 1949* PRIORITY. telegram No.II3. Off-shore oil. oultan has written to me privately to say that for various reasons he does not see his way to Issue proclamation but suggested writing to me officially referring to proclamations already issued and claiming same rights for Muscat. He ado® asks if this will suffice. 2. I think his reasons are probably (l,) his general unwillingness to act exactlv as requested; he likes to make small changes. (2) fear of compromising his independence by appearing to act at our dictation in concert with Gulf Shaikhs. (3) impossibility of getting adequate translation made locally. To issue proclamation in l£nglish would emphasize our part in the matter. 3. I should be grateful for instructions. EllisonV laMBR (Extract from a personal letter dated the 23rd June, 1949 from Kis Highness the Sultan of Muscat and Oman to Mr# R#E# Ellison, Political Agent, Muscat)# ’’Since I saw you I have been considering the matter and I regret to say that for various reasons I do not see my way to make the proclamation in the suggested form but I* am prepared to write an official letter addressed to the Consul saying something like this:~ rt We are given to understand that the Arab States in Persian Gulf have proclaimed their right to the sea-beds and subsoil lying beneath high seas of the Persian Gulf etc# etc. Therefore as our territories extend to the inside of the Persian Gulf we also claim the same rights and whenever the matter comes for consideration we hope that Muscat will be included in this matter”# Then I see the necessary phrases from the suggested proclamation and add it to my letter. I hope this will serve the purpose. If you agree I shall draft a letter and send to you for any addition or alteration and for good English” - ;■ A f /6£i' «?y- a .'M'lfcd Telegram From To No.II3 Political, Muscat Prodrome, Ealirain. Dated tbe,l6th June, 1949* Sultan is studying text of proclamation I gave him and will I hope issue it shortly. He enquired however what would happen if another power (e.g. Persia) encroached on his little corner since he is not in the protected position of the Trucial States. May I say that in that unlikely event he will have our official backing ? MB. Ellisonw ppp» m {l) llhereas it Is desirable to give encouragement to any efforts which will bring about greater utilisation of worlds natural re source st (b) Whereas waluable resources rasjr under lie parts of the Persia] Gull off coasts of -”--~-end it is be cosing increasingly practicable to utilise such submerged resources) (c) Whereas it is desirable in the interests of protection conservation and orderly development that exploitation of such resources should be properly controlled! (d) Whereas it is just that sea-bed and subsoil extending to s reasonable distance of the coast should appertain and be coxxtrollsdB by the littoral State to which it is adjacent* (e) Whereas ri^ht of littoral group to exercise its control ewer natural resources of see-bed and subsoil adjacent to it's coasts has been sstablished in International practice by action of other States! (f) Now therefore we the ......^of ••...••••....in pursuance ©f all powers enebling us in that behalf are pleased to proclaim end it is hereby precis imed as foiluvras The •••••••••••••••cf......« v .... ### .hereby declare sea -beds and subsoil lying beneath high seas of the Persian Gulf contiguous to the hnit or j.a 1 w£t eri; of**.......*........ and extending seawards t o bound&amp;rlss to be determined more precisely as occasion may arise on equitable principles byof***.**,.......*after consulting with reigbbovrirg States* appertain to...••..••• .them and..............and are subject to Its exclusive jurisdiction and control. Ncthing in this proclamation shall be deemed tc affect the sovereignity over islands or states of sea-bed and subsoil beneath any territorial skiers* or to prejudice the rights cf•...of......in sea-bed eg subsoil or waters contiguous to its territorial waters elsewhere than in the Persian Gulf. Nothing in this proclamation shall be deemed to affect the character as high seas cf waters of the Persian Gulf sieve the sca~b«&lt;d and outside limits of territorial waters or status of air space above the waters cf the Persian Gulf outside territcriAl mterfc or fishing and traditional pearling rights in such waters., M*Pad Political, Muscat Prodrome, Bahrain, Telegram From To No.104, Dated the I2th June, 1949. IHHKDJATE. Your telegram No.102. Your telegram No.63 April let was received partially corrupt. Please check and repeat in your paragraph I all between protection of” and 'that exploitation” and in paragraph 4 from ”deemed to” to ”high seas”. Ellison Telegram hM^ad ^ ro ® Prodrome,.Bahrain. Political, Muscat No.105. Dated and received I3th June, 1949. IMMEDIATE . ^ Your telegram No.104. Following is repetition requested. ”Protection of ?conservation and orderly development^and) that exploitation”. ’’Deemed to affect the character as high seas” Hay * f.Telegram From To No.IQ2 Dated Ilth, received I2th June, 1949. QiO / 7 Pad (M) Prodrome, Bahrain Political, Muscat !&lt;/ • Secret* telegram No*70. Saudi Arabia has issued proclamation and Iran lias a Bill before the ?Majlis on the subject of the sea bed* I have received instruction that Gulf Rulers should now be advised to issue their Proclamation and Bahrain one has already been issued* If you see no objection please endeavour to persuade Sultan to issue his Proclamation within (mut) fortnight* I understand from Woods-Ballard that he has no objection to doing so and that he has accepted Draft contained in my telegram No.63* If however he wishes to make any important alterations in the Draft I should like to be consulted before it issues. 2* I have been instructed by the Foreign Office that Rulers should be advised that boundary of territorial waters is 3 repeat 3 nautical miles fi*om low ?water * 7I f you see no objection please advise ?Sultan that this is the definition of territorial waters ^accented by Eis Majesty’s Government» ■ 3# There is no (raut) Arabic translation of Proclamation and I leave it to you whether to decide fco make a translation in your office or to leave it to Sultan to make his own translation. In either case please do your best to make sure that (mut) is correctly translated and send me both English and Arabic copjes of the Proclamation as eventually issued*tele 'M' CYPHER from P.R. BAHREIN TO F.O. TEL NO 167 RPTD. WASHINGTON TEL NO 2 DATED 18/4/49 Secret. Addressed to F.O. telno 167 of April 18th repeated Washington. Your telno 161 was not seen by me before my visit to Dhofar and nothing has yet been said to Sultan about off-shore oil. In view of your telegram 164 I am taking it that nothing is to be said to him about concurrence of U.S. Govt in draft proclamation vide your telegram 11576 of 1948 to Washington and para 4 of W r ashing ton telno 5077 of 1948 to you.COPY L f j&gt;) / A TELE 'M' CYPHER y FROM F.O TO P.R. BAHRAIN TEL NO 186 DATED 8/4 RECVD. 10/4/49 Immedlate. Secret. Addressed to Bahrain telno 186 of April 8th and to Kuwait. Bahrain telno 139 and Kuwait telno 29. It is true that Shaikhs other than the Shaikh of Bahrain have assumed that they are free to grant concessions and our attitude has supported this assumption. Now however that claims of KOC and IPC have received such legal support that they carnot be dismissed as frivolous and in any case seem likely to be pressed to arbitration it is incumbent upon us to acquiiiit the Shaikhs accordingly. This should take the form of an incidental refe rence rather than a formal warning as we are anxious to main tain a neutral position. Now that the issue of the proclama tions is in sight and some at least of the Shaikhs are no doubt anxious to commit themselves a word of advice would be both proper and salutory. Action of the Shaikh of Abu Dhabi (Bahrain tel no 149) emphasizes the risks of the Sheikhs getting into trouble through our tacit agreement that they are free to grant sea-bed concessions. You should therefore take an immedia te opportunity to speak to such Shaikhs as have been spoken to by the companies (to our knowledge Kuwait and Abu Dhabi) and an early opportunity of informing the other Shaikhs.TELE 'M' FROM F.O. f.t beTorf 9d od f&gt;i dl ^ TO P.R. BAHRAIN huts to! ri^uone s.TiIj- merfd evt-; TEL NO.151 b oJnt i^Jne o^ - rfalw [Qw 1 e v swor' ') Xu ori ?. do Iriw sno £J 3 r IMMEDIATE. SECRET. Addressed Bahrain telno 151 of March 24th repeated for information to Tehran Baghdad Washington Jedda BMEO and Kuwait. Your telno 125 not repeated, Off shore oil. Unless you see objection the following action should be taken. (1) Kuwait Bahrain and Qatar to be ( ,, told n ommitted”) confiden tially now that the Saudis are expected to act shortly that the Govt, wil] be advised when to issue their proclamations. This should be three days after the issue of the Saudi proclamation. I am separately instructing HM Ambassador Baghdad to speak to the Iraqis as soon as the Ambassador Jedda has firm information of the date on which the Saudis will act. Should the Ambassa dor Jedda fail to obtain the information the timing of the approach to the Iraqis might have to be reviewed. (2) You may now speak to Bahrain Petroleum Co. (mytel 107) (3) Sultan of Muscat may be informed generally of developments when you see him at Dhofar. (4) Other Gulf states to be informed confidentially after the Saudis have issued their proclamation and told that they will be advised later when to issue their proclamations. I would welcome your suggestions for a staggered programme. 2. The proclamations will not be in the form you suggest which applied to the Median line scheme now in suspense. You will have seen from mytel 150 to Jedda and from para 1 of mytel 3078 to Washington that Ambassador Jedda is expected to telegraph the text of the Saudi proclamation some days before it is issued. A proclamation has also been prepared here and will be telegra phed to you at the end of the week. It may require some modi fication in the light of the Saudi text. If all goes well you should be able to give the three rulers a text at the latest on the day the Saudis issue their proclamation. This should /give' 45 ) }/ SECRET The Political Agent Muscat 40/54/49 ) With reference to F.O. telno 247 of 23/10/48 sent to you in C.S.40/33/88 With the compliments of the Political Resident. Residency, Ba^' ain, Persian Gulf.’K* (Pad) Telogram From Prod.rone, Bahrain To Political, I.hiscat, h T o.70. Dated the 2Bth, received 29th April, 1949* Secret. Off Shore Oil. In accordance with instructions I have received from Foreign Office please take the first opportunity of putting the Sultan in the picture and refrain from mentioning United States participation in the proposals. Kay MB.Telegram ‘M 1 (Pad) N. From Prodrome, Bahrain To Political, I^scat No.63. Dated 1st, received 2nd i^pril, 1949. IMMEDIATE. Begins• 'QX^s, • / /Z r d* - Jfrf Secret. Following.from Foreign Office telegram No.161• telegram No. 151• Following is text of a draft proclamation which you should arrange to translate and hold ready for communication to Rulers. It may be necessary to modify text inplaces in u ^ \ light of draft proclamation to be issued by Saudis. Begins. I. (a) Wherea^l it is desirable to give encouragement to any 'Vj \ efforts which will bring about greater utilization of worlds natural resources: (b) whereas valuable resources may under lie parts of the Persian Gulf off coasts of and it is becoming increasingly practicable to utilize such submerged resources : (c) whereas it is desirable in the interests of of such : vcy wnereas it is aesiracie m tne interesi (? CouterVhtion ) ^ . of'(mut) and orderdj(muj/) that exploitation protection resources should be properly controlled s (d) whereas it is just that sea-bed and subsoil extending to a reasonable distance of the coast should appertain and be controlled by the littoral State to which it is adjacent : (e) whereas right of a littoral group to exercise its control over natural resources been of sea-bed and subsoil adjacent to it ; 1 s coasts hasZestablished in International practice by action of other States : (f) now therefore we the ~ - of - - - in pursuance of all powers enabling us in that behalf are pleased to proclaim and it is hereby proclaimed as follows : 2. The ~ - of - ~ - hereby declare sea-beds and subsoil lying beneath high seas of the Persian Gulf contiguous to the territorial waters of - - - and extending seaward to boundaries to be determined more precisely as occasion may arise on equitable principles by - - - of - - - after consulting with neighbouring States, appertain to - - - them/ 2 . and - - - and are subject to its exclusive jurisdiction and control# 3# Nothing in this proclamation shall be deemed to affect the sovereignity over islands or states of sea-bed and subsoil beneath any territorial waters# 4# Nothing in this proclamation shall be deemed to affect (mutj as high seas of waters of the Persian Gulf above the sea-bed and outside limits of territorial waters or status of air space above the v/aters of the Persian Gulf outside territorial waters or I fishing and traditional pearling rights in such water3 ,, . Ends# NOTE# (i) In the case of Muscat following words would require to be added in Clause 3* Begins# M or to prejudice the rights of - - - of - - - in sea-bed or subsoil or waters contiguous to its territorial waters elsewhere than in the Persian Gulf, (ii) Numbering and lettering of paragraphs in text have been adopted to facilitate reference in correspondence and should be omitted from final proclamation 11 . Ends, You should not take antion until you receive further instructions, -Dredge- MB,PERSIAN GULF RESIDr-m^, BAHRAIN. SECRET 26th February, 1949. (6/14/49) Please refer to Foreign Office telegram 348 a copy of which was forwarded to you under our complimentary slip 40/11X/48 of the 29th December on the subject of off-shore oil. I forward herewith an extract from Foreign Office tele gram 82. Weightman is associated with the Superior Oil Com pany and will presumably soon be returning here shortly and it is probable that representatives of other companies inte rested in off-shore oil will also put in an appearance. 2. Would you kindly therefore explain the situation to the talers with whom you are concerned on the lines desi red by the Foreign Office. It is not yet necessary to commu nicate to them the draft proclamation forwarded with my S.C. letter 40/27/48. An approach has already been made to the Shaikh of Kuwait and 1 enclose a copy of Foreign Office tele gram No.226 dealing with this subject to indicate the lines on which you should proceed. I consider that action should be taken at once vis-A-vis the Shaikh of Bahrain and as soon as possible vis-A-vis the Shaikhs of -^atar and Abu Dhabi. The other Trucial Coast Shaikhs can be dealt with at greater leisure but it is important that the situation should be ex plained to them before they are approached by any oil company representative. 3. The position will need rather careful explaining to the Shaikhs and 1 consider it preferable that this should be done orally at the present stage. 4. If there is any point on which you require further instnuctions please let me know at once. (Signed) F . HAY. C.J. Felly, Esq., O.B.E., Political Agent, Bahrain.M Cypher. Foreign Office, London. Political Resident, Bahrain, Telegram No. 52 Dated 7/2 received 9/2/49 SECRET. Addressed Washington telegram No. 1522 of February 7th repeated for information to Tehran, Bahdad, Bahrain, Jeddah and BMEC. My telegram 910. United States Embassy here have informed us that State Department are considering whether they should give advice to Saudi Arabian Government on the fallowing lines by the end of this week. (1) They might explain the Turman declaration and the application of its principles to the sea bed of the Persian Gulf. (2) They might suggest the issue of a proclamation by the Saudi Arabian Government in terms of a draft prepared by Aramco declaring the Jurisdic* tion arid control of that Government over the submerged areas of the Persian Gulf extending seaward beyond territorial waters, the Saudi Arabian boundaries to be determined as occasion arises on equitable principles by the Saudi Arabian Government in agreement with the States having jurisdiction over adjoining submerged areas. XXX xxxxxTelegram EN M Cypher. Foreign Oflice, London. Political Resident, Bahrain. From To Telegram No. 82. Dated 22/2 received 24/2/49. SECRET. •Addressed to Bahrain telegram No. 82 of February 22nd repeated for information to Washington, Tehran, Baghdad, Jedda and British Middle East Office, Cairo. My telegram 1522 to Washingtom. I am taking up with State Department the proposals outlined in the first paragraph of my telegram under reference which have now been approved by His Majesty*s Government as a general basis for dealing with this matter. 2. I understand that State Department have informed the Superior Oil Company that they have no objection to the latter entering into negotiations about the sea bed oil with the Persian Gulf States. It seems likely that the State Department must have given this permission with the proviso that this was as far as they were concerned, since they were not in a position to authorise American Cil Companies to negotiate with rulers under our protection and open to our advice in this matter. However as the Superior and other American companies presumably now*consider themselves authorised to pursue enquiries regarding concessions for the sea bed, I consider we would no longer be justified in prohibiting British companies from at least tdking with the Shaikhs about possible terms particularly Shaikhs in the areas where pressure exists i.e. Kuwait and Qatar. 3. You should therefore inform the Shaikhs accordingly making it clear that they should not commit themselves and that our advice about the timing of the proclamations will follow. Proclamations by the States other than Kuwait and Bahrain who may require to make proclamations early, may be spaced over a period, being made as and when seems necessary in consultation with us. You should in any case avoid giving the impression that the proposals referred to in the first paragraph above have been finalised.Telegram ? From Foreign Office, London. To Political Resident, Bahrain. Telegram No. 255 Dated 2nd received 3rd November, 1948. SECRET . Addressed to Washington telegram No. 11823 of November 2nd. Repeated for information to Jedaah, Bahrain, Baghdad, Tehran. Jeddah telegram No. 356. In circumstances as now reported by Jeauah, it seems clear that unless we are definitely to favour the interests of an American company at the expense of a British, we can no longer restrain Weightman from approaching the Shaikh of Kuwait. Subject, therefore, to the views of the Political Resident, we do not feel that we can refuse Weightman facilities to visit Kuwait though we do not propcs e that he should be given any special assistance and after he has arrived in Kuwait he will have to make his own approach presumably through the Shaikh's Secretary. Before he goes, we would also propose that the Political Agent should tell the Shaikh that since we know the oil companies are most interested in gaining the concessions to exploit the oil believed to exist beneath the sea bed, we have been giving consideration to the means whereby the Rulers of the Gulf States could extend their jurisdiction over the sea bed in order to open the way for development of any oil and hope very shortly to be able to inform him of our views. In the meantime, should he be approached by any oil company we hope that he will ensure that all conversations which may ensue will be entirely secret and noncomirittal since premature disclosure may adversely affect his interests. We should be glad if you would explain the position as stated above and in Jeddah telegram No. 356 to the State Department.mmmamgm W - r FOREIGN OFFICE. Addressed to Foreign Oflice No.444 of 6th Nov. SECRET. Following from Hay. Bertram Thomas is coming to Bahrain about November 12th and intends to visit Trucial Coast to renew his acquaintance with Shaikhs. I have asked him not to mention sea-bed oil. 2. Noonan has today received Nutall’s letter of October 21st in which he is asked to render assistance to Thomas. 3. Please telegraph to me at Bahrain nature of assistance which should be given to him and whether he should be permitted to mention to Rulers desire of his company to obtain sea-bed concession. (True Copy) i- Telegram ' M ' From Foreign Office, London. To Political Resident, Bahrain. No. 277 Dated 9th received 10th November 1948. IMMEDIATE. Secret, Your telegram No, 444 Bertram Thomas may be given the bag and telegraph facilities and facilities to move about freely. He should nbt otherwise be given any special assistance which is not offered to representatives of other Companies. 2, He should not repeat not discuss sea-bed concessions with Trucial Shaikhs: but see my immediately preceding telegram regarding Kuwait. (True Copy)</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000881.0x0000d9_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/6/442</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000881.0x0000d9</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/6/442</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'14/6 Vol I OFF SHORE OIL'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1948/1949</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-10-23T22:59:24</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (56 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in rough chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 58; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. A previous foliation sequence, which is also circled, has been superseded and therefore crossed out.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The volume comprises telegrams, despatches, correspondence, memoranda, and notes, relating to offshore oil and the definition of territorial waters in the Persian Gulf.The discussion in the volume relates to the following issues:A Saudi proclamation regarding seabed and subsoil rights and decree defining territorial watersA Persian Government draft Bill on seabed rights (folio 27)A draft declaration (folio 38) of the Muscat government and other Arab coast rulers.Further discussion (ff 31-33) surrounds the concern of the Governments of the United Kingdom and the United States to establish agreed jurisdiction to allow seabed drilling by oil companies on an agreed basis and prevent claims by other powers.Also discussed (ff 56-57) is the visit by Bertram Thomas to the Trucial Coast in November 1948 as a representative of an oil company.Included (ff 9-22) in the file are copies of the 'Royal Pronouncement concerning the policy of the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia with respect to the subsoil and sea Bed areas in the Persian Gulf contiguous to the coasts of the Kingdom of Saudi Arabia'.The file features the following principal correspondents: the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf (William Rupert Hay); the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, London (Ernest Bevin); an official of the Foreign Office (Sir Bernard Alexander Brocas Burrows) the Political Agent, Muscat (Randall Erskine Ellison); HM Ambassador to Iran (Sir John Helier Le Rougetel).</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Ocean floor</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Ambassador to Iran</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>United States Consul General, Dhahran</namePart></name></subject><subject><geographic>Oman</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Saudi Arabia</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Petroleum industry</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000881.0x0000d9#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>