<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x0002f7_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T12:01:58.737Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">P. 2023/19. B 317 Mesopotamia : Future Constitution. Letter from Li cut.-Colonel A. T. Wilson, Civil Commissioner, Baghdacl, dated tith Ar/ril 1010. Sir, In reply to your telegram of 14tli February asking for proposals for the future adminis tration of Iraq, f have the honour to enclose a copy of my circular memorandum of 20th February to Political Officers, together with a copy of the draft reply sent to them for their opinion, and of the replies received other than those of a purely affirmative nature. '2. It will be seen that the consensus of opinion is in favour of provincial councils as 1 Annex to enclosure No. 4. outlined in the dialt telegram, 1 and i would propose . , p tt - • , . ^ ve e ^ ec ^ to this portion of the scheme on receipt ol the instructions of His Majesty's Government, subject to an alteration in the number of provinces to live or six as suggested by Lieut.-Colonel Howell. 8. The consensus of opinion is against the appointment of Arab Governors for the leading towns at present, and 1 propose to defer action in this matter for the present. 4. In existing ciicumstances it is not possible to submit more specific proposals than those contained in the enclosed correspondence. They have been framed on the most liberal basis compatible with the maintenance during the next few stormy years of public order, and I trust that His Majesty s Government will see, as 1 do, in the reception accorded to these proposals by responsible political officers in Mesopotamia a satisfactorv indication of the spirit in which the problem is being dealt with on the spot. 5. They represent in my view and in that of my stall' the limit to which we can safely o - q at present, i.e., the maximum for which local opinion is prepared and of which local persomrel is capable. 0 Few Asiatic States can show a greater variety of race and faith, of economic conditions and of mode of life than are to be found within the limits of Mesopotamia ; few, if anv, have such a long frontier compared to population, or have more turbulent neighbours.' 7. These considerations indicate the need for caution, but do not diminish the necessitv Joi ])iogiossi\e measuies, t^he demand lor which will increase as communications improve. cS 1 he existence in Egypt of a very complete Arab facade, with a Sultan, Ministers a Legislative Assembly, and an Arabicised Administration has not prevented trouble there It is I venture to think, a legitimate deduction thai modest beginnings and steady progress on i x ia linos olroi bettoi piospects than stagnation within the limits of a fixed constitution however liberally conceived in the first instance. 0. II these proposals are accepted in principle, I recommend that steps be taken to ascertain whether Sir P. Oox can be spared from his present post and is willing to return to Haghdad as High Commissioner in September or October next. The announcement of his return m this capacity would give general satisfaction to the public in Mesopotamia. 10. If this despatch with enclosures is printed 1 would ask that I may be favoured with oO copies. 1 have sent a copy to the Government of India. I am, &amp;c.. The Secretary of State A. T. W ilsox , Lieut-Colonel, Jor India. Acting Civil Commissioner in Mesopotamia. Enclosure No. 1. Telegram from Civil Commissioner, Baghdad, to Secretary of State for India, No. 9095, dated liith November 191cS. {Repeated to Government of India and High Commissioner, Cairo.) Apart from the tribal organisation in Mesopotamia which it has been our policy consistently to maintain and develop, the municipalities of the principal towns were almost the only indigenous institutions which afforded the ' local population an opportunitv of partaking in the management of their public affairs.' These municipalities are now emerging from financial stringency, due in first instance to departure ol lurkish officials and removal of municipal funds and records followed by prolonged period of war conditions, and necessity on military grounds for maintainino- sanitation, (Xrc., at a lev^l previously undreamed of, but now generally appreciated Thev are now financially in a fairly sound condition. ' \\ ith approval of General Officer Commanding-in-Chief, 1 am instituting, with elfect from 1st Jamiary, both at Pasrah and Baghdad, Municipal Councils on lines evolved bv Lieut.- Oolonel Howell, I.U.S., Military Governor, Baghdad, in consultation with the principal notables or Baghdad. s 30 100 4; 19 aThese Councils will consist partly of nominated and partly of elected members, and will enjoy considerable financial powers in respect of municipal revenues, viz., Rs. 5,000 for a single payment and up to Rs. 150 a month for recurring payments, subject in both instances to the existence of budget provision. The President, Vice-President, and Secretary will for the present be oflicials. Copies of constitution and rules are being posted to you and to India. Similar municipal councils where they do not already exist will be set up in other towns, but the general level of education and civilisation being there lower, with more restricted powers and under somewhat closer tutelage. Enclosure No. 2. Telegram from Civil Commissioner, Baghdad, to Secretary of State jar India, No. Ot)lU),. dated lOth November 1918. {Repeated to Government of India and High Commissioner, Cairo.) To secure the full benefit of co-operation by tribal leaders and large landowners m the administration of these territories I am reviving forthwith, with the approval of the General Officer Commanding-in-Chief, the institution of Divisional Councils, which already existed in somewhat nebulous form in Turkish times. These are quite distinct from the Municipal Councils mentioned in my immediately preceding telegram, but are intended to perform similar functions for rural districts. They will, however, at first be purely advisory. In several Divisions informal councils of this nature have already come into being and are very popular. It is now proposed to give them more definite shape and more formal status, for which a demand has already appeared. They will consist of not more than twelve members, all of whom will, for the present, be nominated by the Divisional Political Officer, and they will hold meetings at regular intervals. The present administrative Divisions are a continuance of the Turkish system, modified in accordance with local and tribal sentiment. They form administrative units of convenient size, each coherent and homogeneous. They are not too numerous to be dealt with direct from Baghdad, from which they are all easily accessible. This close touch is much appreciated by Shaikhs. The constitution of a future advisory or legislative assembly for the whole of Mesopo tamia, when the time is ripe, will be much facilitated by the development of these bodies, and of the Municipal Councils, from which representative delegates can be chosen. The resuscitation of these Divisional Councils has been for some time under consideration and was to have been matured more at leisure. In view, however, of the terms of the Anglo- French declaration published on the 8th November, it has seemed expedient to hasten the inception of these developments which are assured of general support locally, and to give local publicity forthwith to our intentions. Action on these lines will, 1 hope, serve to show the public, both here and elsewhere, that our policy in Mesopotamia is being shaped, as far as possible, in conformity with pronounce ments in Europe. Enclosure No. 3. Telegram from Civil Commissioner, Jjaglidad, to Secretary of State for India, No. 9G97, dated lOth November 1918. {Uepeated to Government of India.) My immediately preceding telegrams. Application will be made b3 T post in due course for the formal approval of Government to the delegation to Municipal Councils of the financial powers referred to. Enclosure No. 4. Circular Memorandum, dated 2()t1i February 1919, from Civil Commissioner, Baghdad, to Political Officers in charge of Divisions.* (Immediate and Secret.) In continuation of my Memorandum No. 27190 of 30th November, I enclose herewith a copy of further correspondence regarding Self-Determination ending with a telegram dated 14th February, 2 received from Secretary of State for - Not reprmtec. India, and 1 am glad to have this opportunity of transmitting the appreciation of His Majesty's Government to the officers who were actually responsible for executing a task which His Majesty's Government justly describe as delicate. 1 Mosul, Sulaimaniyah, Kirkuk, Khanikin, Samarrah, Dair-Us-Zor, Ramadi, Hillah, Diwaniyah, Najaf, Baghdad, Baqubah, Kut, Amarah, Qurnah, Nasiriyeh, Basrah.&lt;§) Q O 2. I enclose a draft reply to the above telegram ; an immediate decision is called for, and I should be glad to know by telegraph, at the earliest possible moment, whether the views expressed therein have your general support and concurrence. An affirmative reply may be conveniently indicated by telegraphing the single word 'Constitution.' T shall also be glad of yonr matured views by post on the general questions raised therein, and in this connection 1 forward an interesting memorandum on this subject by the Judicial Secretary,' with whose views 1 am in general sympathy. , . 1 also attach a note on the subject by Major- - Not reprinted. General Sir P. Cox, written in April 1918, 1 when in London. A. T. Wilson , Lieut.-Colonel, Indian Army, Olhciating Civil Commissioner. Annex. Draft Reply to Secretary of States telegram of lith February 1919. {Embodying Civil Commissioners Proposals.) Your telegram of 14th February. In considering question 1 make the following assumptions: — (1) There will be no Arab Amir but a British High Commissioner. (2) Mosul Wilayat and Dair-us-Zor will be included in 'Iraq, as also those portions of Kurdistan which are now part of Mosul Wilayat, and which are not included in the future Armenian State, i e., the whole of the basin of the Greater Zab. This is necessary in order to admit of inclusion of Assyrians. (3) British control, however expressed in words, will be effective in practice, and will be ensured by retention of adequate military and air forces distributed with due regard to their ability to aid civil power in the maintenance of order. (4) Adequate British financial support for the Iraq State in its early stages, firstly, by loan secured on revenue, secondly, by allowing Civil Administration to take over surplus military assets, such as railways, bridges, docks, electric plant. See., at a low valuation. This country has during the war been equipped and administered in some respects ou a scale beyond our powers to maintain iu time of peace. Only by taking over such assets at a very low valuation and running them as cheaply as possible can we avoid financial instability and consequent political embarrassments. Having postulated the above, 1 submit the following proposals (1) 'Iraq to be ruled by a High Commissioner, having under him four Commissioners controlling provinces as follows ;— (i) Basrah, including the former Basrah W ilayat minus Kut. (ii) Baghdad, including former Baghdad Wilayat minus the Euphrates Districts. (iii) Euphrates, including the Euphrates Districts from Anah to Samarrah inclusive and the Holy Places. (iv) Mosul, including the whole Mosul Wilayat and such areas to the North of Mosul Wilayat as are not included in the new Armenian State. Koughly speaking, the boundary of the latter North of .Mosul should be the waterhead between Lake Van and the Greater Zab. This will place the Assyrians in 'Iraq as they wish. The grant of some form of autonomy to the Kurds of Kurdistan had better be left to our initiative and not laid down in the Peace Conference if this can be avoided. If, however, Kurdistan be given separate status there will be five provinces. (2) The Divisional Councils mentioned in my telegram of 10th November, 9696, to be made full use of as advisory and deliberative, but not as legislative, bodies. They will be none the less influential. Experience shows that elective bodies are unsuited to present conditions. „ , . . , (3) Provincial Councils to be formed in each of the above provinces from members selected of their own choice by the Divisional Councils. The latter are nominated bodies. 1 am of opinion that the legitimate demand for, active participation in actual government and administration can best be met, not by creating central legislative or deliberative Councils, but by giving carefully selected Arabs of good birth and education belonging to 'Iraq by birth from the very outset positions of executive and administrative responsibility. I have visited Aleppo, and am under no illusions as to what this involves. There will be difficulties and loss of efficiency, but we must accept this as the necessary concomitant of our policy, and as a stage in the evolution of an Arab State. This policy cannot be applied to districts in near future. The tribes would not accept Baghdad officials, and the latter are unwilling to face a lengthy period of exile from home, and are not at present fit for responsible district work from any point of view. In pursuance of this policy, I should be prepared to instal selected Arab officers as Governors of Baghdad, Basrah, and Amarah, with a specially chosen British official of ability and character as Municipal Commissioner and Adviser to the Governor, in which dual capacity he could control finances and mitigate inevitable inefficiency in early stages.4 1 am fully alive to tlie imperfections of and inadequacy of the above proposals. They are framed in the conviction that it is only by introducing Arabs into the actual work of the Administration from the very start that we can hope to enlist their cordial co-operation, or prevent a system growing up which will be too elaborate for them to work successfully. The problem before us, like many others arising out of our position in the Oriental world, is in a large measure insoluble. Political discontent, always with us, will increase ; the appetite of the Arab Nationalists will grow, and they will grudge it they be not satisfied. These diiliculties are inherent in the otherwise favourable position which our armies have Avon for us in the East, and we must not be deterred thereby. The change from a Military to a partly Arabicised Civil Administration will make large demands on the patience of the military authorities and on the loyalty and patriotism of the British Staff of the Civil Administration and of allied Departments, but I am satisfied that the policy I have outlined is not only right, but also expedient. It has been framed in consultation with the most experienced oflicers on my Staff, on whom the responsibility of giving effect to it will fall. I am authorised by them to assure Government that it will have their whole-hearted if cautious support, and I can wish for no better guarantee than this of its introduction into Mesopotamia under favourable auspices. E nclosure Ko. Note by Revenue and Financial Secretary, Baghdad, 2lst Fehruary 1919. Reference your draft telegram which you showed to me this morning. 1 do not know whether you want comment from me before you start for Egypt, but if so, here it is :— As regards your proposed division of the country into Provinces,— (1) Your first Province is the old Basrah Vilayet for the abolition of which you showed conclusive reasons five months ago. Is it not rather too soon to suggest its revival ? (2) The Provinces have no co-operative entity or communion of sentiment. They are at present purely artificial creations, and it seems more probable that they will develop into realities if, so far as possible, their borders are marked out in accordance with natural lines. As regards Mosul and Kurdistan, I have nothing to say in this connection, but as regards the Provinces of Iraq T would suggest that the better division would be into five (а) Basrah with special responsibility in connection with the adjoining territories of Koweit and Mohammerah, (б) The Lower Tigris from Kurnah to Aziziyah. (c) Baghdad and the Upper Tigris with Baqubah and Khaniqin included, this being the area in which the ma jority of landed estates owned by Baghdad is are situated. (d) The Lower Euphrates from Suq to Samawah. (e) The Upper Euphrates with headquarters at ilillah to which Anah, Ramadi and Dair-us-Zor could be attached. Each of these would, [ think, have more chance of developing some community of sentiment than the areas named by you. As regards the more important part of the proposals, I take it that your object is— (1) to do something now which will show that the status of the Arab is not one of subordination ; (2) to give to the Arab a share in the auministration which will at least not look smaller than it really is ; and (3) to educate him in time to take a real share. After discussion with Bonham-Carter and Balfour it seems to me that the best way of realising these objects is to appoint Arab Ministers to be the nominal heads of four or five of the main departments, to give the provincial and perhaps some of the divisional com missioners Arab Assistants or Deputies, and to develop the class of D.A.P.O. This would, 1 think, be more appreciated and less obnoxious than your four proposed Arab Governors for the leading towns, especially if you mean to import Arabs from outside to hold these positions. It is precisely in the four leading towns, especially Basrah, that the British and military element is strongest, and that the chances of disastrous friction arising from the appointment of the Arab Governor are greatest. If, however, you hold to it that the experiment must be made in the large towns, let the Arab Governor be something more like a Mayor (with a Corporation attached), and let all his executive orders to British officers issue through the Municipal Commissioner, who would himself be a British officer. Finally, I think that in making concessions to the Baghdadis' reluctance to take up positions outside Baghdad, we are stooping unworthily ; the reluctance rests^ mainly on a recollection of a state of things which is now past and gone, and will, 1 am convinced, rapidly disappear if we do not pander to it. E. B. H owell, Lieut -Col., Revenue and Financial Secretary.- (3 5 ENCLOsruE No. 0. Kote by Revenue and Financial Secretary, Liaghdwl, 27//*. February 1919. (Secret and confidential.) i • i i In replacement of my earlier note, 1 beg yon to accept tbe attached, which has been prepared after more mature consideration. E. B. Howell, Lieut-Col., Revenue and Financial Secretary. Annex. As to the four postulates, 1 have no remarks to offer. With regard to the proposals :— (1) Provinces and Provincial Councils. I adhere to my suggestion that our lines of division should be natural boundary lines, as follows;— (1) Basrah; (2) Tigris, Amarah to Diyalah mouth; (3) Euphrates; (4) and (5) as proposed. As this organisation is likely to be expensive and we have no ollicers senior enough to be Commissioners, nor have any areas local organic unity, 1 suggest that this step be left until demand awakes, the divisional and municipal councils being meanwhile developed. If we have three sets of councils, no first-class men will sit on all three, or if the}' - do they will become professional busy-bodies. (2) Arab Town Governors. Provided that— (1) the Arab Town Governor be a man of the town, not an importation from Syria ; (2) he be chosen by nomination for two years ; (3) he be given a council (also in part at least nominated), in whose name he shall act; . , . . . . . , (4) where necessarv, the Governor and Councils decisions issue through the British officer attached to him— 1 agree. The period of office should be two years and the salary liberal. (3) I withdraw my provisional acceptance of Judicial Secretary's proposals with regard to Ministers. I think, however, that a native of the country should be appointed as assistant to Judicial Secretary, Director of Education, Revenue Secretary, perhaps also Finance. Waqfs might be manned as far as possible by natives, but under an English head for the present. A council is desirable. (4) I suggest the omission of the last four paragraphs of the draft. (Sd.) E. B. Howell, Lieut.-Col., 27th February 1919. Revenue and Financial Secretary. P S—j a j so advocate the immediate employment of 20 or 30 selected natives of the country as D.A.P.O.s, to be attached to Ihvisional ihstnet OlficBis, in aieas deemed suitable for this purpose (i.e., generally areas away from the Euphrates). As these tiain on thej can he used as A.P.O.s in selected areas. Enclosure No. 7. Note by Military Governor and Political OjJicer, Baghdad, 24t// February 1919. (Secret.) . n • 1 have discussed this question in considerable detail with the following : Mr. Bonham-Carter, Lieut.-Colonel E. B. Howell, Major Gordon, the Naqib, Abdel Rahman Eff. Jamil Zada, Abdel Majid Beg Shawi. On the four 'assumptions' which head your telegram I have no comment to offer, and I also concur with your three ' proposals.' As you know, I was inclined to accept your Arab ' Hakims ' for the four towns when we just spoke on the subject, and Major Gordon and I, when we started working out details, formulated a scheme b} 7 which such an otlicial could be fitted into the local Administration of Baghda^en to Bonham-Carter and Lieut.-Colonel Howell, and found them opposed to my detailed suggestions. They will doubtless represent their own views, and 1 only mention them here in connection with what follows.6 T understand their objections to be : — (1) Impossibility of finding men who conld run an administration so closely involved as is that of Baghdad with Military and Technical Departments which will continue to be run by Englishmen. (2) The difficulty of getting British officers to serve immediately under a native. I think on this point we were rather at cross purposes over terms, and you would reply by saying that it was always your intention that the ' Hakim ' should work and issue orders through his adviser. In view of the native opinions, mentioned hereafter, the point is not of great importance. In speaking to the natives named I also discussed IMr, Bonham-( 1 arter's suggestion of putting native Ministers for Justice, Revenue, c^c., with British advisers. In talking over the question 1 was careful to put the various points without bias, and 1 interviewed the Naqib separately from the other two. 1 may summarise their views as follows :— (1) All were very much in favour of your proposed Provincial and Divisional Councils. All were strongly against any form of election. They said* they simply would not face the sort of thing we have been through lately in Baghdad, and that the elective principle must wait some years before introduction into Iraq. They added that il we adopted the elective principle we should get none of the sort of men we wanted to oiler themselves for election. (2) All were against an executive Hakim el Beled in Baghdad, but accepted as good my alternative suggestion that the Hakim el Beled should be President of the Mijliss Idara, which would have a British secretary who would do the work involved in executing the orders of the Hakim and Council. This is only a modification in degree on your original proposal. The Naqib stipulated that the Council must be a body with real powers and not a dummy. t t • The other two added that the Hakim should be daily in office and have his staff of clerks, &amp;c. I think myself that the thing can be worked on these lines, and that, for the men we are likely to get to start with, they are the best. (3) As regards Mr. Bonham-Carter's suggestions for native Ministers and a wider participation by natives generally, the Naqib ruled it out on the grounds of lack of suitable men. (Incidentally he broke oft' into a tirade against the Jews.) Abdel Majid Beg Shawi said roundly what they wanted was British officials with Arab advisers throughout, not the reverse. He would add an Arab adviser to all officials down to A.P.O.s. The idea of importing Baghdadis now in Syria into Baghdad appeared to be unpopular with all the three spoken to. It would be easy to find many natives who would demand a much greater native parti cipation from the very beginning than 1 have indicated here. 1 have no doubt, however, that the men I have spoken to represent a very large body of the more sober-opinion, and that they go rather further than the Christians and Jews will altogether like. The scheme which I should advocate may be summarised as follows:— (1) British High Commissioner (Hakim el Ali) with British Secretaries (Nazir) for Revenue, Justice, &amp;c. (2) Four Commissioners (Hakim) in charge of Provinces (Vilayet). In the Provincial Councils (Mejliss Vilayet^ members elected by Divisional Councils. (3) Deputy Commissioners (Hakim el Qadha) in charge of Divisions. In the Divisional Councils (Mejliss Qadha) members selected by Government. (4) Deputy Assistant Commissioners (Naib Hakim el Qadha) in charge of Districts (Merkaz). (5) In the case of Baghdad, Mosul, Basra and Amara (also possibly Hilla, Kerbela and Najaf) a native Municipal Commissioner (Hakim el Beled) as President of Mejliss Idara Beladiya (Municipal Administrative Council) with a British official as Secretary, who would be responsible for the routine work envolved in executing the orders of the Mejliss. ((3) All the British officials in paragraphs I to 1 inclusive to be given native advisers (Mashawer, not Mustashar) as men become available. (7) New legislation to be by Ordinance by the High Commissioner in Council. Council to be composed of the Secretaries and their advisers. (8) The younger men among the advisers would in a few r years be suitable for posts as Deputy Assistant Commissioners (paragraph 4). (Sd.) 1. C. C. B alfour, IAent.-Colonel, Military Governor and Political Officer, Baghdad.Enclosure No. 8. Note hy Political Officer, Sulaimaniyah, in rcrjard to the political status of Kurdistan. There is strong feeling in Kurdistan wliicli may he called national, but whicli is better described as ' clannish.' It expresses itself in a desire to preserve its own language, traditions and customs, and keep out aliens whether they be Armenians, Arabs or Mosulis' There is, curiously enough, little ^r no antipathy to Nestorians and Chaldeans, in fact, nearly all the tribal chiefs with whom I came in contact were anxious to have their Nestorian tenants back as being the mainstay of their material prosperity. The Jeln was al\vays referred to as a Kurd of the same race and stock as themselves. As far as racial feeling is concerned, there would be no difficulties in repatriating the Jelu through the Rowanduz area. But to the Armenian as a neighbour, and the Arab or Mosul! as an official, there exists a very rooted objection. What strikes one most in Kurdistan is the purely Kurdish atmosphere which prevails an atmosphere which seems so virile and healthy as to be able to choke and smother any foreign culture transplanted to Kurdish soil. Ninety-nine per cent of the population speak only Kurdish, wear an exclusively Kurdish dress, and in scarcely a single respect have allowed themselves to be influenced or affected by the Turkish occupation and administration of their country. For the last four months 1 have been engaged in liquidating the remnants of the late Turkish (iovernment in Kurdistan. The ease with which the Turkish official has made his exit reminds one of the process of shaking a tree overburdened with more than ripe fruit. With the scrapping of the old administrative machinery one might have expected some degree of breakdown in the domestic life of the community. Such, however, was singularly absent, which is explained above in great part by the fact that the Kurd with his strongly developed national characteristics and idiosyncrasies was in a position to supply an immediate sense of communal interest and solidarity sufficient to afford an antidote to their predatory instincts. With this feeling in existence the question that confronts us is whether Ave should develop it on its own lines, or ignore it, and administer the country as a part and parcel of the 'Iraq State.. From what 1 have seen of Kurdistan I am unhesitatingly in favour of the former alternative, and 1 feel sure that all officers who have had actual administrative experience in Kurdistan will share my views. Tn this connection, it might be pointed out that the appoint ment of Shaikh Mahmud as British Agent in Southern Kurdistan gave rise to a certain amount of misapprehension, which expressed itself in petitions to come under direct tribal administra tion. The issues were thus confused. Subsequently when it became clear that to all intents and purposes British Political Officers had the direction of affairs in their own hands, the apprehension of the people died away. It is quite true that the Kurd would prefer the rule of the Political Officer to that of Shaikh Mahmud, but it is equally true that the Kurd would far prefer to be under a Political Officer with a purely Kurdish orientation than to one living in an atmosphere of Arab influence and ideas. This brings me to the crux of the matter, namely, that Kurdistan should seek its inspiration in administration, education, and material progress and development, from a purelv Kurdish centre or centres, and that the present administrative boundaries should be readjusted so as to include in Kurdistan all predominatingly Kurdish areas. 1 have not yet had the opportunity of studying this question except in Southern and Central Kurdistan, but as far as those areas are concerned the solution which naturally presents itself is that Sulaimaniyah should be the administrative centre of a Wilayat to include Neri, Rowanduz, and possibly Aqra, frbil, Kirkuk, Kifri, and Khaniqin. Without any first-hand knowledge it is with some diffidence that 1 venture to express any opinion in regard to Mosul, but prima facie it would be seen that Mosul by its geo graphical position would naturally lend itself to forming the administrative centre of those parts of Central Kurdistan inhabited by Christians or a mixed Kurd-Christian population. Western Kurdistan would thus be left to form a separate Wilayat with administrative centre at Diarbekr and separated from South Kurdistan by a wedge of the Mosul Wilayat. an arrangement which politically would seem to have certain advantages. If the above proposals were adopted, the advantages of the Kurdish confederacy in the way of enlisting the sympathies of the people and conciliating national aspirations, would be obtained, while at the same time the disadvantages of unduly exalting a man like Shaikh Mahmud would be avoided. The political authority at Sulaimaniyah would be in a position to decide what areas would safely and with profit be administered under the tribal system, what measure of local autonomy and in what limits it would be possible to afford the men of commanding influence such as Shaikh Mahmud, the Shaikh of Barzan and Saiyid Taha. If the general principle of considering Kurdistan as a separate political entity be agreed to, it follows as a corollary that the northern boundary of the Diarbekr Wilayat should be an ethnographical one. E. W. C. Noel, Major. Political Officer, Sulaimaniyah.8 Enclosure No. 9. Note hij Political Officer, Najaf, '2~ W l Fehruanj 11)19. (Socvct.) I can only express views I have formed on my experience in Middle Euphrates, \ lews naturally coloured by fairly intimate acquaintance with the city of Najaf. ^ It may he taken, therefore, that I deal exclusively with the problems that in my opinion will face the Commissioner of the Middle Euphrates under the scheme outlined in the dralt not issued telegram of 20th February. There are several outstanding features about this region as compared to the rest (if Iraq : — (1) It is entirely Shiah. (2) It contains the two Holiest Cities of the Shiahs. (3) It is inhabited largely by settled Arabs. (4) It is the richest part of Iraq and does, and will, produce the largest revenue. From (1) it follows that the introduction of Turkish (Sunnij Law, the centre of which will be Baghdad, will be neither successful nor acceptable and that Sunni officials will not be a success. From (2) it follows that this part of the world must always be a centre of intrigue, largely connected with Persian affairs. Form (3) it is probable that the authority of the Sheikh will become less and less apparent and that rule through him will be ineffective and not desired by the people themselves. From (4) it follows that the administration must be experienced. To control the Middle Euphrates with its Persian element, its holy cities, which are veritable sounding boards of commerce and politics, its settled population and its great potential wealth, only one thing is necessary, the certainty of a strong Government. It is assumed that this is a certainty and that its centre will be Baghdad. Now it is educated Baghdad that reacts badly on the Euphrates. Educated Persia does not matter once the status of Iraq is determined. Persia and Baghdad are unlikely to combine. The question then is, how can we best train the people of this tract along lines of which they themselves approve, not opposed to but uninfluenced by the half-Hedged intelligence of Baghdad. The answer seems to be in the greatest possible decentralisation from Baghdad, in making the provincial unit of the Commissioner really effective, and above all in the encouragement and recognition of the Shiah Priesthood and of Shiah Shara Law. Such action would not, I think, encourage Sunni versus Shiah tendencies. The knowledge of a strong Government in Baghdad is a sufficiently strong deterrent, but it would bind the Euphrates district together, and would be the only possible means of checking the pernicious Baghdad influence—in fact, this check would be automatic. The people do not want Baghdad influence, which is and will remain largely Sunni. They are proud of Baghdad as the Great City and capital of Iraq and will acknowledge it as the seat of ultimate power, but it should not go further. Baghdad should be the centre of power, and the moral force of a strong Government in Baghdad, with, as far as possible, a self-contained Government on the Euphrates, would ensure rapid development. To bring this into effect, 1 would— (1) Emancipate all schools from Baghdad control except in financial matters. There should be a Director of Education for the Euphrates responsible in no way to the Director of Education at Baghdad except financially. A large Sheikhs' College should be established as soon as possible, preferably not at Hillah. ,(2) Definitely place the Sunni Shara Court in a subordinate position, i.e.. regard it as the Court of the Alien Sect. Encourage the decision of the Shiah Shara and make Najaf a Court of Appeal. (3) Very carefully examine the present Administration of Civil Police to see if it could be modified so as to permit of its administration entirely for the present by British officers on lines not conflicting with Shiah Law. As regards the other points in the Memorandum :— Divisional and Provisional Councils. —These should begin at once. On the Divisional Councils the towns should be well represented, but should not outnumber the tribal represen tatives. The latter should be Sheikhs, who then should become advisory instead of, as in some cases at present, executive. Arah Governors. —For the present impossible owing to the backwardness of the Shiahs. They should not be given even the opportunity of accepting a Sunni ; it will create trouble later, if now now.0 HniploymcnL of Avah Personnel. —Should begin as soon us possible, though very few will be available for some years, owing to the reasons given above. The success of this personnel will again depend largely on the amount of decentralisation. I.e., whether we have the money to start a training college in the Euphrates area. I entirely agree with the proposals of Mr. Bonham-Carter in paragraph fi of his Memorandum. As regards paragraph 7, 1 am averse to it, owing to the diversity of race and creed, and owing to my firm belief that decentralisation is the solution with only central centres for foreign policy and finance. 1 consider it should be our aim in the Middle Euphrates to back the Shiah, try and give him the idea that he is not opposed and an alien, and that he has a future. He then will develop fast and possibly along the right lines. He is more prone to intrigue than the Sunni, and so in his backward state is peculiarly vulnerable to the crude nationalism of the Baghdadi ; and out of sheer stupidity will intrigue, though he will later confess he was a fool, and that it was against his interests. Give him by decentralisation a chance to learn what his own interests are, and he will go far, 1 therefore strongly advocate the formation of a local capital, but not at Hillah. which is too Sunni and near Baghdad, with law courts, schools, &amp;c. ; toe recognition of the Shiah Shara ; the full and immediate use of divisional and provincial councils ; and the appointment of no Arab oflicials from Baghdad. Every endeavour at the same -time should be made to interest the local notables in admini stration, and Arab local personnel should be taken on as far as they become fit through education, and the highest posts therein open to them. li. E. Win gate, 24th February 1919. • Political Officer, Najaf. Enci^si re No. 10. Teleyram from Political Officer, Basra (Major A. S. Meek), 2nd March 1911). 1 am unable to offer any matured opinion on your S. 11. Paragraph 1 of your proposals and idea of divisional and provincial council have my general concurrence. 1 do not agree as to Arab Governor for Basra on ground that people themselves desire a just and impartial head. We have here no question of political parties as affecting this subject, but of social factions. No man who could be appointed could give public satisfaction, could be free from intrigues of these social factions and from nepotism. In Basra we might successfully elect both divisional and municipal councils on some modified system of election or provide proportion of nominated members with fully elected members. Bift municipality and division should be in charge of British officer. Let there be a definite undertaking, which shall be rigorously respected, as to introduction of national government within a fixed and short period of years, but do not let us be pushed now into scheme which may prove harmful to the objects which Government have in view. Feel myself too ill equipped to make definite statements and regret my inability to produce fuller reply. Enclosure No. 11. Note hy Political Officer, Mosul, 26th February 1919. 1 telegraphed my agreement with the views expressed in the draft telegram, but I would bring forward certain points, which have occurred to me after discussion with my officers. 1. Presumably intentionally, but in our opinion certainly wisely, the policy you have outlined only commits Government to the inclusion of Arabs in civil administration to a small degree, and even then with practically no executive powers. A Divisional Council is to have advisory and deliberative powers only. A Provincial Council is to enjoy considerable powers, but not legislative. 1 hold that a ' Council ' can have no executive powers, and can be only advisory or legislative. The one appointment which is to be filled presumably in the near future is that of a town Governor. 2. It is our opinion that Arabs can with advantage bo appointed to departments such as Waqf, and in the Courts of Justice ; when it comes to appointments necessitating administra tion of law and order and immediate control of the inhabitants of the country, the position becomes extraordinarily difficult. Speaking from my own knowledge of Mesopotamia, I only know two Arabs fit to exert direct control, and neither of these are natives of Iraq. The officers 1 have consulted know of none. In the Soudan the officials are found from seconded officers of the Egyptian Army. Here we have not this class to draw from. The average ' Arab ' officer is generally a Baghdadi or «i Kerkukli ; the former is of low birth, and the latter a soldier of fortune. This latter class is S 30 c10 found iii tlio Mosul Gendarmerie, and is, as a rule, very satisfactory, but only under strict supervision. Speaking of Mosul, the upper classes are, almost without exception, incapable, weak and idle; they will sit in a council admirably where they have nothing to do but talk. When it comes to work, they do not hesitate to admit they are not ready to act. Baghdad, doubtless, is the same. 3. Fhe Judicial Secretary*in his note advocates the appointment of Arabs as Assistant, Political Oflicers at an early date. It is our opinion that, seeing that an Assistant Political Officer is the official who is nearest to the people, he therefore should be a man in whom the people must have complete confidence ; for this reason alone it is obvious, though regrettable, that it would be unwise to give an Arab this appointment G. E. L eachman, Lieut.-Col., Political Officer, Mosul. E xclosure No. 12. Note by Political Officer, Kirkuk, 27th February 1919. (Immediate and secret.) An officer conscious of the crudest inexperience must put forward views upon these subjects only upon definite invitation, and with the greatest diffidence. Mr. Bonham-Carter makes the points :— (1) That the gradual replacement of an initial British bureaucracy is highly difficult. -) 1 hat Iiaq-born oilicials suitable for our uso exist and that such use is desirable in responsible posts. '3) That the headquartei-s administration should assume an Arab form, modelled approximately upon the Egyptian. As regards above point (2), some such sequence as the following is suggested:— (a) l T se of purely Arab subordinate staff, including Mudirs. Such is already in force. {h} Appointment of Arabs as Governors of areas (within the district) larger than tlio Nabizal, whether urban, tribal, or non-tribal. By no means all districts afford such areas. (c) hree use of Arabs as personal assistants to Political Officers or Assistant Political Officers (pay not less than Rs. 400, with corresponding dignity). This official to tour widely as Political Officer's deputy on all subjects. At this stage his lurther education becomes acutely necessary, he must learn efficient (i.e. our) office routine, accounts, filing ; he must be habituated to the use of Englisli- spealung subordinates. If he can acquire English, all the better ; he should be assisted to travel in Egypt or Europe under the most favourable conditions, lie should become not incapable of dealing with military authorities direct {d) Appointment of Arabs as Assistant Political Officer, District, conducting eorre- spondence on European lines, assisted by properly trained personal stalf Pay, Ac., of British Assistant Political Officer. (e) Prom this point, appointment to any work for which Headquarters may select him ^ not excluding Political Officer or Commissioner. if) Baghdad Headquarters Departments to contain each at least one Arab Assistant Secretary (Finance, Revenue, Justice, &amp;c.). Such official (who would have passed through stage (c)) to do the real work of his position. I he above stages represent the possible appointments open to men now present and the system involved might well be fully working within three years. Further, Municipalities. —These, on present lines, to be allowed to dispense with all controls and sanctions eojcepf such unwritten and unofficial guidance as the character of the neaie&amp;t Bntisli lolitical nfficer might render implicit. Large questions of taxation &amp;c in the larger Valadiyahs would be subject to the control of the Revenue Ministry. Technical Sermces—Perforce to remain as now in British hands, but Arabs to be criven exact equality of opportunity according to their merits, and assisted to acquire such merit • t t ! ' e J' ltu, ' e - l' 1 ^ ie country, the part playable by natives of the country has been fairlv indicated by the progressive stages (a)—(/). Every use to be made of the Councils detailed in your draft reply to the Secretarv of otate. At Baghdad, a Council with stated powers liable to growth to be formed English and Arab members sitting together. The Provincial Councils, heads of the greater municipalities the Headquarteis Departments, to be represented; under the Presidency of the High Com- rmssKmer. I o sit for definite short sessions, and to pass measures requiring only the sanction of the High Commissioner and of His Majesty's Government. l 8 wv ti 1 me 1 t0 c l ues ^ on ^ r - Bonham-Carter's first point, that the British bureaucracv can with difficulty be replaced. Surely this bureaucracy need not sit enthroned and remote.11 as it has in India. Arab ollicials (many with mncli experience) will not be frightened by a moderately 'complicated' system; and it is altogether to be deprecated that it should become a shade moie complicated than efficiency demands. Secondly, from the outset, there are to be no appointments for which Arabs are ineligible. Thirdly (though it is no matter for dogmatism) the Arab may well be thought a more promising substitute for the British officer than either Indian or Cypriot. It is submitted, therefore, that the Arab official may well be the gradual and unlimited sharer of our bureaucracy. And to this there is no limit. For instance, if we find and train the right men, there is no reason why the British Revenue Secretary with Arab assistant should not become the Arab Revenue Secretary with British Adviser—and in all fact and sincerity, and in every branch and post. S. H. Longkigg, Captain, Political Officer, Kirkuk Division E nclosure No. 13. Note htj Political Officer, Hamadi, 3rd March 1919. (Secret.) In my opinion the proposals put forward in your draft telegram provide the framework on which an administration suitable to this country can be built up. The general expression of opinion in this Division is that the idea of an Arab State is pleasant; but it is impossible to imagine such a State, which, at the present time, would not be a bad copy of the Turkish administration, and therefore if would be better for things to continue as they are. This is the expression of the moment, but personal aspiration will soon appear and will have to be met. At present the great difficulty is to obtain anyone of sufficient ability to nndertake any work entailing executive responsibility. The inhabitants of the various small municipalities have little interest beyond their own town, and there is certainly no one among them capable of exercising any authority on the surrounding tribes, and it will be some time before any of the inhabitants ol the town do more than aspire to managing their own municipal affairs. This, however, is to be encouraged. The Sheikhs have not yet learnt to control their own tribes, and until they have learnt to do this they cannot be expected to control anyone else. At first there may be some difficulty in forming a Divisional Council owing to the distance separating the various centres of the Division, and the unwillingness of the leading men to travel any distance on any but their own business. District Councils, however, could be set up which could be consulted by the district officers and the Political Officer when on tour. As the inhabitants begin to realise that their interests extend beyond the limits of the area in which they live, a Divisional Council could be established. Finally, as Arabs of any ability are discovered, work entailing executive and administrative responsibility will be ready at hand. L. M. Yetts, Captain, Political Officer, Ramadi. Enclosure No. 14. Xote hy Political Officer, Amarah, March 1910. (Confidential.) 1. I am in general agreement with the views expressed in your draft telegram. 2. I think Arab Assistant Political Officers might be introduced, but not till the Political Officer is satisfied he has found suitable men whom the Shaikhs would tolerate. The tribes want direct rule of the British. They do not want Arabs; and the townsmen are content that we should keep direct control of the tribes. 3. I disagree altogether with Divisional Councils, though I see no harm in a monthly Majlis of Shaikhs. 1. I am in favour of Municipal Councils. These are necessary. ^ T agree with Provincial Councils. 6. I totally disagree with Arab Governors, and with the designation ' Governor.' On tWjyither hand, 1 agree with the appointment of a good Pais with a capable Municipal Adviser.7. I feel, perhaps igiiorantly, that Kurdistan should be a separate province. Kurds are alien to Arabs. 8. It may be well to remember that the Arabs were never happy until the Turks had left Mosul. This implies a vivid consciousness of the close relationship of Mosul with the 'Iraq. R. Ma it us, Captain, Political Officer, Amarah. Enclosure No. 15. Note by Political Officer, Amarah, Qth March 1919. To-day I took the opinion of the Amarah Majlis on the question of a Rais. They were unanimously and decidedly of opinion that a British officer should always be Rais and not an inhabitant of Amarah. R. Marks, Captain, Political 0Hicer.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x0002f7_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/18/B317</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x0002f7</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/18/B317</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Mesopotamia: Future Constitution'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1919/1919</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-09-19T10:50:51</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (6 folios)</extent><extent>Foliation: The foliation sequence for this file commences at folio 31, and terminates at folio 36, as it is part of a larger physical volume; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is also present in parallel between folios 7-153; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled, and can be found in the same position as the main sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This printed report consists of a letter from Lieutenant-Colonel Arnold Talbot Wilson, Civil Commissioner, Baghdad, dated 6 April 1919, to the Secretary of State for India, concerning the future constitution of Mesopotamia. There are also fifteen enclosures, some accompanied by appendices. These enclosures and appendices consist of telegrams, notes, a circular memorandum and draft reply by Wilson and others, including E B Howell, Revenue and Financial Secretary, Baghdad; F C C Balfour, Military Governor and Political Officer, Baghdad; Edward William Charles Noel, Political Officer, Sulaimaniyah [Sulaymānīyah]; Ronald E Wingate, Political Office, Najaf [al-Najaf]; Gerard Evelyn Leachman, Political Officer, Mosul; Stephen Hemsley Longrigg, Political Office, Kirkuk; L M Yetts, Political Officer, Ramadi [al-Ramādī]; and R Marrs, Political Office, Amarah [Amārah].</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Civil Commissioner, Mesopotamia</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Mesopotamia</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Constitutions</topic></subject><subject><topic>Colonial administration</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x0002f7#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>