<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0001c2_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T10:24:12.635Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">fbe T/r PART II. Kawer?Wat 4 PERSIAN GULF GAZETTEER. GEOGRAPHICAL AND DESCRIPTIVE MATERIALS- SECTION III. CENTRAL ARABIA Notes Pages. i and ii SUB-S^TIONS. A. —Central Arabia, South op Wadi Rummah B. —Central Arabia, North op Wadi Rummah Pages. ... 1 to 25 26 to 58CONFIDENTIAL, PART II. PERSIAF GULF GAZETTEER. GEOGRAPHICAL AND DESCRIPTIVE MATERIALS- SECTION III. CENTRAL ARABIA. Notes Pages. i and ii Sub-sections. Pages. 1 to 25 A.—Central Arabia, South of Wadi Rummah R.—Central Arabia, North of Wadi Rummah • •• 26 to 68KOTES. I principal authorities are given at pages 1 and 2G, at the commence ment of subsections A and J3. Of those mentioned only Nos. 2, 5, 12, 15, 17, 18, 20 and 24 of the first list are incorporated in subsection A, and Nos. 5, 6, 9, 10, 13, 15, 16 and 22 of the second list in subsection B. II officers making further inquiries will facilitate the compilation of the Gazetteer if they will, as in the other sections, give all names in Arabic charac ter and send up fresh information according to the following numbered syllabus:— Tracts and Districts. (1) Boundaries. (2) Subdivisions. (3) Physical geography. (I) Climate and seasons. (5) Communications, vit. — [a) Boutes. (&amp;) Distances. (c) Stages. [d) Supplies. {e) Transport. (6) Trade, viz. — {a) Products. (fi) Internal trade. (c) Imports. (d) Exports. (e) Commercial centres. (/) Coinage. (g) Weights. {h) Measures. Mountains, (1) Position. (6) (2) General direction and configuration. (7) (3) Elevation. (8) (4) Height and names of peaks. (9) (5) Snowline. (10) ( 11 ) Valleys. (1) Position. (4) (2) Extent and direction. (5) (3) Slope, surface and general character. (6) (7) (7) Population, viz .— (a) Number. (b) Races and tribes. (c) Character. (d) Religion. (&lt;?) Mode of life. (/) Occupations. (g) Language. G) Customs. (i) Fighting strength. (;) Arms. (8) Administration— (a) Police and army. (£) Criminal justice. (e) Civil justice. (d) Land revenue. (e) Taxes. (/) Officials. G) Relations of civil and religious authorities. G) Geneology and personal details of ruling or leading families. Spurs and offshoots. Geology. Vegetation and animals. Population. Routes and passes. Valleys and lines of drainage. Climate. Tributary valleys. Resources. Population.Inhabited Places. (1) Position geographically and politically. (2) Character of site and general description of place. (3) Defences. (4) Number of population. (5) Tribes, religions and occupations. (1) Position. (2) Shape and extent. (3) Surface and general character. (4) Resources. (1) Origin and political faction, (2) Subdivisions. (3) Numbers and habitat. (4) Character and appearance. (5) Religion. (6) Mode of life. Simla ; Jdth November 1904. (6) Industries, markets and trade. (7) Resources in water, food, forage and transport. (8) Local shrines. (9) Religious, charitable and educational institutions. (10) Administration and government. (11) Historical facts. Islands. (5) Population. (6) Mainland to which belonging (where doubtful). (7) Administration. Tribes. (7) Occupations. (8) Language. (9) Customs. (10) Fighting strength, (11) Arms. (12) Government and political matters. J. G. LOBJMER.2 AAMAU (AL).—According to Palgrave, a predatory and ultra-fanatical tribe inhabiting the Wadi Dowasir, the most contemptible of all the Arabs.^ AAREDH.—Central district of Nejd, containing Dereyyah and Riadh, the former and present capitals. Its northern boundary passes between Horeymelab and Sedoos. It is traversed from north-west to south-east by the Wadi Hanifa and the greater part seems to consist of downs or highlands. Pelly says that the Aaredh hills commence from Mahmel, forming^ its eastern entrance, and come down on the eastern side of the Wadi Hanifa, increasing m breadth as they go. They are cut transversely from side to side, from the Shaab plain to Sedoos, by Wadi Wattar. The grass of the Aaredh hills is pre served for the summer and autumn; in winter the pastoral tribes frequent lower grounds. (See also Wattar). The people are of a restless and warlike disposition and poor; in 1862 seven-eighths of them were strict Wahabis. I he district is of the highest political importance. Population was estimated at 22,000 in 1820 and at 12,000 in 1865. Revenue in 1865 (according to Pelly) was $ 50,000, partly in kind, and number of fighting men 1,200. Palgrave (1862) made the population 110,000, the military muster 6,000 and tbe revenue $ 5,000. AAYELI.—Village in Aflaj district. AEIF,—Halting place 140 miles south-south-west of Aneyza on route to Mecca. It lies in hollow ground encompassed by low basaltic mountains and has a well. AELAJ.—District of Nejd, intervening between Aaredh in the centre and Wadi Dowasir on the extreme south-west; or, according to Pelly, a section of the Wadi Dowasir which is watered byAt the end next Riadh it is separated by a watershed from the Wadi Hanifa. The slope of the district appeared to Palgrave to he to the south-west, but Hogarth gives grounds for doubt ing the correctness of his opinion. Palgrave found that the gardens and palm- groves of Meshallah in north Aflaj, though extensive, were thinly set, and the wells far from copious. There was cotton and white millet. Retween Meshalleh and Kharfa, chief town of Aflaj, road ran most of the way a gorge of some depth ; on either side above were excellent pastures and flocks in plenty ; below a few palm-groves and huts. Population was more sparse than in Yemamah or even Sedeyr. Hospitality was meagre at Kharfa ; and a want of sociability and coarseness of manners were observable, resembling those of the adjoining Dowasir. Aflaj, Palgrave considered, was a barren and savage district and its people resembled the inhabitants of Aaredh except in being influenced more by religious and less by political motives. Population in 1820 was esti mated at 13,000 ; Palgrave in 1862 put it at 14,000, fighting strength at 1,200 and revenue at $ 2,000; Pelly in 1865 made population 2,000, fighting strength 300 and revenue $ 7,000, partly in kind. The main places are Kharfah, Siah, Leyta, Raudha and Biddea. The inhabitants are said to he Dowasir. [An informant of Doughty’s affirmed Aflaj to he in Jehel Toweik, 6 clays from Riadh ; it contained, he said, 4 good palm settlements, but the way was rugged and without villages. This is irreconcileable with Palgrave’s account, who says he reached Kharfa, the chief place in Aflaj, in two days from Riadh.] AIOONEAT. Place § of the way from Shakra to Aneyza, where Sadlier, in 1819, found a walled enclosure, sheltering 10 to 15 families, also grounds cultivated to a considerable extent and well supplied with water. There was a lake of rain-water with grass growing on its borders. AJMAN,—Tribe enumerated by Ross among those of Nejd. He calls them Kahtanic and enumerates 8 sections. Ross reckoned Hasa a province of Nejd; can then the Ejman of Section II, sub-seetion D, be meant ? Palo-rave also mentions Ajman Bedouins, numbering 6,000, in Central Arabia. A LEY I.-—I here is said to he a village of this name in Aaredh, inhabited by a colony of Kurumyah Shammar from the north. AMARIAH.—Mentioned by Ross as a village of Aredh.3 AMER (BENI).— Nejd dynasty who had their capital at Eyanah. ANEYZA Town. (1) Situated in the district of Kaseem, of which it is the chief towni about 150 miles south-east of Hail, 10 or 11 mBes south or south-west of Boreyda and perhaps 200 miles north-west of Riadh ; it lies 5 or 6 miles south from right hank of Wadi Rammah. Distance from Koweit is 17 marches. Sadlier regarded it as tne geographical, political and commercial centre of Arabia. It then (1819) maintained direct communication with Basra, Koweit, Katif, Hasa and Dereyya and was conveniently placed with regard to Medina and the Red Sea. Doughty remarks that it is half w ay between Basra and Mecca, distance about 400 miles from each, and is regarded by its own citizens as tbe centre of the peninsula. It lies almost in the straight line, and not far from midway, between the capitals of Riadh and Hail. Its political position is fluctuat- j n o*. In 1863 it revolted unsuccessfully against the Wahabis of whose dominions it previously formed part. In 1367, in the dismemberment of the Wahabi State, Aneyza secured its independence, which it preserved till 1892, when it was reduced by the Amir of Hail. In the time of its independence (1880) the following villages w ere subject to Aneyza or enjoyed autonomy under its protection, Eyarieh, Owshazieh, Auhellan, Wadi, Raudhan, Ashbibiah, Senanah and Rass. (2) Sadlier says Aneyzah lies in a valley : Doughty describes it as occupying a loamy bothmi, underlain by sandstone rock, in the midst of theNefud; elevation is 2,750 feet. According to Doughty it is a walled oasis rather than a town, the outermost wall enclosing ihe date plantations and cultivated lands and having nothing beyond it but the sands of the Nefud. There is an open space called the Gaa, but whether within or without the town is not clear. Huber says that the appearance of the place from the north is imposing : he took a good half hour to traverse the gardens and outlying quarters on tins side. Guarmani remarks that Aneyzah is divided into 7 quarters which might he regarded as villages, Adeliah, Umm Akmar, Mesookof, Gish, Kadar, Kabb and Gossea. Doughty says there are three principal wards, each of which has a separate banner in time of war. Doughty observed here more aged men than anywhere else in his travels; he found the principal diseases to be cataract, rheum (catarrh ?), oasis fever and enlarged spleen. The houses, even that of Zamil the Amir, were of clay but pleasant and clean. In the town-lands wheat was grown, year after year in the same ground, and the crops were dense but light : the only manures were loam and the dung of the well-yard camels. The fields w ? ere levelled and embanked for irrigation from wells, and the date-trees stood in channels which were flushed once or twice daily. Most of the small landowners were burdened with debt and could not irrigate their lands sufficiently. Stone for well-building and gate posts is quarried at Mergab-er-Rafa and salt for the town is dug at Zighreybia. North of the town is the Wadi Rummah and to the south-east, at some distance, very barren hills covered with loose stones. (3) According to Nolde there are an inner and an outer wall and the space between the two, 2 to 3 kilometres in breadth, is filled with gardens and plantations : both walls have towers and are 10 to 12 metres thick. Palgrave and Guarmani both speak of the outer wall surrounding the date plantations as very massive, but Doughty calls it a thin shell with many wide breaches. Guarmani mentions about 50 isolated towers defending the date plantations. Doughty remarks that the place could not be taken by famine as the date plantations are within the walls, wdiich also enclose numerous wells. (4) Guarmani puts population at 15,000, Huber, at 18,000 to 20,000. Doughty estimates the able-bodied male inhabitants at only 1,200 and says the place had doubled in size in the 15 years preceding his visit Nolde (1893) makes the population 35,000, and Aneyza larger than any other place in Nejd except Howtah. (5) Doughty says Aneyza was founded by Sbeya colonists from Aaredh to whom were added Beni Khalid refugees from Jannah on the dcstiuction of the latter ; in another place he seems to imply that the hulk of the population are Beni Temim. In his time the people were well-clad and had a free bearing. The poor resembled the Bedouins and wore the kei chief and head-cord ; the richer classes w ore the fez and threw loosely over lf ° ° ,Q ' T M eli-to do persons dressed in black mantles of* ligl t sometimes an embroidered collar. Persons of good birth it a Irak gay kero wmrsted uef. havingcimed long rods brought from Mecca. The women were not visible in the day but went out to visit one another between twilight and the last prayer The popular religion (Wahabiism) carried more weight than law or government, and half the people were Wahabis. Yet “ Wahabi ” was used as a term of abuse to ill-natured fellows. The Beni Temim citizens seemed to Doughty to be indus trious and fairly intelligent but somewhat soured by their Wahabi religion. (6) Friday is the market day, as well as that of public prayer which all and sundry residing in the oasis attend. The largest fortune in Aneyza in Doughty’s day was valued at £21,000, and there were 15 merchants of substance doing business abroad; some of them had representatives at Basra and Jidda. Usury was common and agriculturists and even Bedouins of the neighbourhood were burdened with debt. The cash rate of interest was 15 per cent, and the rate in kind 50 per cent, at harvest prices. There were small shops in the outlying quarters selling onions, eggs, iron nails, salt, German matches, girdle-bread and milk. On Fridays veiled women sold in the mejlis chickens, or milk-skins and water-skins tanned and prepared by themselves. Metal-workers were armourers, tinkers, coppersmiths and goldsmiths ; workers in wood turned bowls and made locks, the frames of camel-saddles and wheels for wells; the carpenters were poor having few tools. There were stone-hewers (who seldom lived more than 3 or 4 years at the trade), well steyners and sinkers of wells, workers in marble, manufacturers of coffee-mortars, also house-builders and pargeters. Other trades were those of seamster and seamstress, embroiderer and sandal-maker. The gold and silver smiths of Aneyza are renowned for filigree and thread work and some who have settled at Mecca are said to excel all their competitors there. In the bazaars are sold clothing, drugs (including English medicines, such even as codliver oil), camel-medicines, sugar-loaves, spices, Syrian soap from Medina and coffee of the Mecca caravans. Husbandry, camel and horse-dealing are among the respectable occupations. There is no horse-breeding at Aneyza, but horses are collected from the Bedouins in winter and got into condition for export to India. Aneyza horses are mostly from the Beni Kahtan; there are fewer horses, but better ones, than in the Boreyda market. (7) There is an abundant supply of water from wells; common food, Yemen coffee and clothing from the Gulf are cheap, dates are very good and are sold by weight at 30 lbs. for a dollar. Grain is dear. There is only one well of perfectly fresh water ; wells at the edge of the Nefud yield fresher water than those lower down in the Gaa. Corn grows better on the brackish ground. (8) (9) In 1880 there were 15 mosques, incluiing the Jama in the public square, and 4 schools, 1 of which was for girls. (10) Before the captme of the place by the Amir of Hail in 1892, Aneyza was governed by its own Amir Zarnil ; Doughty (l^Ts) considered him a constitutional ruler who deferred to some extent to his mejlis or council; Huber seems to have found him more arbitrary. At the time of Doughty’s visit capital punishment had not been inflicted for 15 years. Common offences and theft were punished with a beating ; cutting off of the hand for theft was not practised, but hardened felons were expelled the township. In case of a military expedition the lists for service were made up by the Emir, only the better-off classes who owned drome daries being required to serve. Ihose named must send their camels with hack-iiders but might give a personal substitute. The poorer classes remained at home as a guard for the town. An expedition of this sort in 1878 included 20 mares, 200 dromedaries and 400 men. In such emergencies the morning market was discontinued and no butchers’ meat killed, all shops except small general shops being closed by order. In foreign warfare the town carried 3 banners representing the 3 main wards ; in civil strife 5 or 6. Sadlier noted the importance of the town with regard to the Aneyza, Muteyr, Beni Khalid Ateyha, Harb and Misroo tribes. In 1878 the Meteyr and Ateyba were friendly to the town and the Kahtan were hostile. 3 AOOItEZ.—Place two marches south-east or east-south-east of Shakrat. In 1819 it had a burj in the corner of a square-walled enclosure. Around it was a very flat and barren plain covered with gravel, extending north-west and south-east, and bounded on the north-east by rugged, mouldering hills. AliJA. Mentioned by Boss as a tribe of JNbjdwith 7 main sub-divisions.&amp;5 ASHBIBIAIL—Village, ruinous in 1880, dependent on Aneyza and about 9 miles south of that town. AS1M.—Mentioned by Ross as a Kahtanite tribe of Nejd. ATALA (JEBEL and THENEEYAT).—Mountain range lying east of the highest plateau of Sedeyr. It bounds the view from the plateau on that side t to north-west and south the plateau commands an extensive view of lower plateaux and of plains. The road from Mejmaa to Dereyyah traverses these highlands by a pass called Theneeyat Atala ; the highest point is 15 or 20 miles south-east of Thomeyr. ATEYBA.—Called also Ateybis and Ateyban. (1) They are of the Muthur stock. (2) Felly divides them into 3 sections and Doughty into 33 fendies. Guarmani mentions a section called Kuga. (3) Felly (1865) estimated them at 1,400 (? men), Doughty (1878) at 6,000 and Foss (1880) at “ formerly ” 4,000. They occupy the vast wilderness, 300 miles in extent, between Kaseem and the Mecca country. It consists of sandy plains, with the best of desert pastures and isolated bergs of granite and basalt. They have villages and palms in the Harrat Terraa about 100 miles north of Mecca, among lavas so sharp that only donkeys can pass them. The Wadi Fummah is their limit on the north. (4) They are honourable, hospitable not inclined to treachery, and better fighters even than the Kahtan; they are more stable of mind than most Bedouins. Doughty calls them one of the greatest Arabian tribes. (5) In religion they are moderate, not fanatical. (6) They are Bedouins and have few fixed settle ments or none, and wander dispersed through tbeir vast domains. (7) They tend sheep and cattle and raid freely, especially across the Wadi Fummah to the north. In Guarmani’s time they had the best horses among the Bedouins. (8) (9) (10) Guarmani (1863) remarked that continual wars had reduced them to 700 riders. Doughty apparently reckoned their horsemen at some 800 in 1878. ^11) (12) They were originally subjects of the Wahabi Chief and according to Felly (1865) paid him annual tribute worth $ 12,000. In the civil war in Nejd they espoused the cause of Abdullah against Saud and aided by the treachery of the Kahtan defeated Saud when he attempted to subdue them. Up to 1878 they were consistent enemies of the Amir of Hail and had successfully resisted the endeavours of the Turks to take tribute from them. ATTHAF.—Good village, in a valley which passes from north of Aflaj vid. Howtah to Kharj. AU HELL AN.—Deserted site with palms, one or two hours* distance south-west of Aneyza on the Khabara road. It is the rendezvous and starting point of Aneyza caravans for Mecca, and there are said to be ancient caves hewn in the sandstone rock. AUN.—Line of lulls running north-west and south-east, and forming the western boundary of the Ormah district. Further north the same hills are called Temameh. There is also village of same name in neighbourhood of Dereyyah. AWAZEM.-—An outcast tribe on the desert borders of Yemama who hav@ a religion of their own. AYATHAT.—Village in Wadi Dowasir. BAJEEB.—Stage with wells, 4 marches west-south-west of Fass on route to Medina. BAKOOM.—Mentioned by Boss as an Adnnnite tribe of Neid Can these be the Begoum of Taraba whom Brydges mentions as shewing determined hostility to the Turks; or the Bagoom in whose country Doughty locates Jehel Hatthon and who, he says, have settlements between Tayif and Wadi BABRUD.—Village of 30 houses, south of Shakra on the way to Mecca. 1 ? m TE w T- P T? Vin c 0r ^ Dfoyya. apparently no othei . than the bed or the Wadi Hamfa which divided the town into two parts. BATINA.—Bee Shaab. (C905FD) B6 BEDITA. Fourth of S places on route from Biadh to Wadi Bisha. B EG AH.—Halting place about 3 marches north-west of Dereyya wit wells, one of which, contained good water m 18iy. BENBAN.—Village in Aaredh district. BE RATH.— Tribe of 800 who in 1865 paid an annual revenue of P.OOU to the Wahabi. # BIDBEA or BIDEEA.—Village in Aflaj district. BISHAH.—Village in Wadi Shakran. ■RTSHA (WAI)!).—Valley mentioned by Doughty, coming down from Asir (ia which direction ?) and losing itself in sand. There are vdlages through out tt at feud with one another : its course is many journeys. Bedoums are Behi Uklib and Sharan. It is 12 dromedary journeys from Riadh. •rt^TTA A rKELAAT).—Principal place of Korah district, about 40 miles beyond W^adi Dowasir. Is this same as last, and is it really in Central Arabia, not in Yemen or the Hijaz ? BORRUD. Small village between Shakra and Aneyza, 1 march from former and 4 marches from latter, BUBBAN (GAH-UL) .— Halting-place about 2 marches north of Manfoohah. There is sometimes a stream of rain-water here called Mfooz-ul- Bubban. BUREYA.—Kahtanic tribe of Nejd ; Ross mentions 27 sub divisions. BURRA (KUSSUR-UL).—Ruined village, in 1819, with a few wells and date trees but no inhabitants. Site is midway between Dereyya and Shakra about 2| marches from each, west by north of the former and east- south-east of the latter. DAHNA.—According to Felly, is a sandy desert tract extending north west and south-east between Nejd and the Persian Gulf. The route from Koweit to Riadh crosses it in two marches where its breadth is about 50 miles This part consisted in Felly’s time of seven great parallel sand ridges and two smaller intermediate ones, running north-west by west and south-east by east and separated from one another by plains. The ridges varied from |- of a mile to 1^ camels hours, and the plains from to 7 miles, in width. The sand was light red or reddish orange. Where the subsoil of the plains was uncovered, it was found to consist of light clay, pebbles and debris of sand stone. There was some vegetation, and antelope, hares, bustard, snakes, lizards and beetles were seen. The Dahna is said to end near Jabul Yebreen in Yemama, but towards its southern extremity it is called the Nefud ; in the opposite direction it is said to bend round the north-east extremity of Jebel Tovveik and continue to Jauf. Pelly crossed the southern or Nefud port’Oii on his way from Riadh to Ojair. He found it of more confused configuration than the north portion, cones and domes of many shapes taking the place of parallel ridges. The breadth on this route was two marches and apparently somewhat less than 60 miles. The sand here was of a very red or orange colour and owing to the view being shut in on all sides the route was kept with great difficulty. Pelly considered the passage of this portion could not be made by a party of Europeans in the hot weather without fatal consequences to some. Towards the western margin there were many steep ascents from west to east followed by almost perpendicular descents from east to west down which the camels slid bodily. Further towards the centre the sand w T as firmer and scattered with brushwood. Near the centre, patches of soil protruded with dark coloured stones. The sandhills, beyond this point, passed from the form of emin ences and hollows to that of long rollers, and finally to that of steps. The going ceased to he heavy and the country was sprinkled with vegetation. The Nefud was bounded on the east by a well-defined valley separating it from the hills of Sumaan. Wallin notes that the name is locally pronounced Dahana. DAKHLAH.—Village in Sedeyr district. DAL AM.—Village in Yemama district. Is this same as Dillum below ?7 DAM.—Village in Wadi Dowasir. DEREYYA.—Once an important town of the Aaredh district. ^ Most ■writers speak'of it as the former Wahabi capital, but Felly states that it was only temporarily so, during the trouble between the Wahabis and the lurks preceding P its capture by the Turks in 1818. It stood in the Wadi Hanifa a few hours’ distance above Riadh and the *ame below Eyanah, and consisted ot 5 quarters or villages named Ghasibeh, Ture&gt;f, Tarfiyeh, Sabi and Kosseereyn, tbe last being an outlying suburb surrounded by gardens. Brydges’ map gives also a detached suburb or village of Bedjairi on the south side of the town. The town was divided into two parts by the Wadi Hanifa, called apparently at this point Eaten. The descriptions given of the site by Mengin, Sadlier, Palo-rave and Felly are so obscure and conflicting that no satisfactory result can^be deduced from them : it is not even clear whether the course of the Wadi Hanifa through the place is north and south or east and west. The gardens of Dereyyah, which produce apricots, figs, grapes, vine, dates, pomegranates and citrons were devastated in 1818 ; but in 1862 were again flourishing under the care of a small but fanatical colony of gardeners. As late as 1865 the ruins of good houses of more than one storey were visible. Tbe immense date-groves are now formed by the people of Eiman. From Felly’s description it is clear that the country immediately to the north of Dereyyah consists of open downs. Sadlier says that to the north a range of hills is seen running apparently to tbe north-east (? Jebel Toweik); while on the west is an extensive range with a north-west and south-east direction (? Jebel Khour of Brydges’ map). DHORAMA.—Flace in Washam district, which the Turks pillaged and from which they advanced on Dereyya in 1818. Before this Dhorama had plantations and‘the inhabitants lived by agriculture selling their surplus pro duce at Dereyyah and to the caravans of the Persian Haj. It stands on an affluent of Wadi Hanifa. DILLUM.—Village in a valley which runs from north of Aflaj via How- tah to Kharj. DJEBREEN.—Flace located by Palgraye in eastern portion of Jehel Toweik, on direct route from Kateef to Sedeyr. He makes it lie north-west of Oweysit and connects the two by a route running through Wadi Soley. DOADAMY.—Desert village of the Beni Zeyd on route from Sbakra to Mecca. DOAS (BENI).—Tribe from whom, according to Felly, the Wahabi government originally seized Riadh to make it their capital. DOORUMBAH.---Mentioned by Sadlier as a village in the neighbourhood of Dereyya. DOWASTR.—Tribe. Felly estimated them at 1,600 persons, and their annual contribution to the Nejd treasury at $ 12,000, chiefly in kind. He came across them at two places in the Nefud between Riadh and Ojair. Ross des cribes them as of Kahtanic descent, and names 110 sections. The inhabitants of Aflaj district are Dowasir. DOWASIR (WADI).—Felly estimated the population of this valley at 10,000, fighting strength at 1,000 and annual revenue obtained by the Wahabis at $ 16,000, chiefly in kind. The valley extends from a point 15 or 20 miles south of Kharfa in Aflaj for 10 days’ journey (200 miles ?) in a south-west direc tion. It is a long, monotonous, sandy depression enclosed between Jebel Toweik on the north and the Dahna (? Nefud) on the south. There is water in wells throughout its length : it is not certain which end is the higher. Palm groves are said to extend for 3 dromedary journeys almost without interval. In habitants are A1 Aamar and Khodeyreeyah (mulattos). Palgrave describes them as fanatical, predatory and contemptible; an informant of Doughty said they were hospitable, but that adjoining villages were frequently at feud. The villages, mainly of palm-leaf huts and straggling, are Hammam, Shotibba, Soleyil, Tammerra, Dam, Loghf (3 hamlets), Earaah, Showyg and Ayathat. Near Wadi Dowasir is the lava-field known as Harrat-al-Hamra.8 PIT SHAN.—See Muteyr. . , , . L T V I AN—Place between Eiyanah and Dereyya whose inhabitants farm the immense palm plantations of those now all but deserted places. EIYANAH —Ruined town of the Aaredh district, in Wadi Hanifa a few hours above Pereyva. Under the Beni Amer dynasty it was the capital of Neid and here Wahabi doctrines are said to have been first preached by Muhammad ibn Abdul Wahab. The ruins (in 1805) lay in detached groups occupying the entire bottom of the valley on either side of a gravelly torrent bed the valley being however only a few hundred yards wide. Retaining walls of hewn limestone without cement confined the stream, and continued at intervals for 2 miles ; these supported platforms on which the houses formerly stood. The immense date-groves are now farmed by the inhabitants of Eiman. There are also fig trees. ERK.—Place at the lower end of Wadi Taraba, not far from Shalsra in the Washam district. Here flood water collects after rain, forming a lake at which the Bedouins encamp. ERZA.—Village in neighbourhood of Pereyya. ETHELLY.—Some out-lying granges near Rass. EYARIEH.—Ruined and possibly pre-Islamitic town of the Beni Temim, lying on the right bank of the Wadi Rummah about 5 or 6 miles due north of Aneyza. People of Aneyza obtain loam from the site as a top-dressing for their fields. EARAAH (1).—Town or village in the district of Washam. PARAAH (2).—Town or village in the Wadi Dowasir. EAROOK (WADI).—A great valley, running north and south and separating the Pahna on the west from the Moghazi range of Hasa on the east. It contains a labyrinth of sandhills and the passage across it, which is hardly less difficult than that of the Pahna, occupied Palgrave from noon till sunset. In 1862 it was infested by A1 Morra and Manasir marauders. Its length is undetermined, also the direction of its slope. Its identity with the plain or wind-channel crossed by Felly between the Nefud and Sumaan seems doubtful; if it is not the same. Wadi Earook does not extend far north of the point where Palgrave crossed it. EERRA.—Eirst of 8 places lying on route from Riadh to Wadi Bisha. Is this same as Earaah (2) above ? EEYTHA.—Village in Wadi Sirr, 3 marches from Aneyza and 2 from Shakra, between them. GARANIAH.—Pistrict between Aaredh and Hazm-er-Rajee with a popu lation of 7,000, fighting strength of 2,000 and revenue (in 1895) of $ 6,000. GERYEN.—Place in Washam district. GHASIBEH.—See under Pereyya. This quarter was situated close to a hill and was defended in 1818 by a strong fort. GHAT.—Village in Sedeyr district, on east side of gorge up which road leads from Zulfa to Majmaa, and on the Zulfa side of the watershed. It stands under a white cliff and has a copious spring. There are fig-trees and pome granates, and date-palms equal to those of Kaseem. The houses and gardens stand in rows, one above another, on the mountain side. GOAYIEH.—Desert village of the Beni Zeyd on route from Riadh to Mecca. Doughty shows it about 60 miles south of Shakra. HAPPA.—Sixth of 8 places on route from Riadh to Wadi Bisha. HAIEYRAH (1).—Town or village in Sedeyr district. HAEEYRAH (2).—-Town or village in Aaredh district. . sc l^ are fort in Sedeyr a short distance from Toweym on the road to Riadh. J9 HAJAIl.—The northern part of Sumaan extending to Suk-esh-Sliuyukh is so called. HAJIA or GARAT-AL-HA.JAJ.—Hill with ruins between Shakra and Thormada, said to have been a place of pilgrimage before Islam. HAJIR (BENI).—Tribe of about 500 persons, with 10 sections enumer ated by Ross. They contributed annually the value of $ 3,000 to the ISejd treasury about 1865. HAJNOWWY.—Outlying grange of Rass, outside bed of Wadi Rummah and about abreast of Khabara. HALWAH.—'Town or village of Yemama district. HAMMAM.—Village in Wadi Dowasir. HAMMR.—Ceventh of 8 places on route from Riadh to Wadi Bisha. HANIFA (WADI).—This important valley drains the district of Aaredh, traverses Aaredh and enters Yemama ; its subsequent course is unknown. Rising apparently in the Jcbel Toweik bills, it leaves them at a point marked by a conspicuous bluff west of Sedoos. Prom this point it runs in a curve (which is the hollow side?) to the ruined town of Eiyanah, having low hills (? Jebel Khour) on its right bank between it and Jebel Toweik, and on its left bank a raised plateau extending from Sedoos to Eiyanah. The northern approach to this upper basin is commanded by Horeymela, the western by Shakra and the southern by Kharfa. Sedoos and Horeymela appear to be situated in tributary wadis, the latter being at the head of the ivadi in which it stands. At Eiyanah the valley is only a few hundred yards wide and the torrent bed in the centre is gravelly. Sadlier found the bed sandy from Eiyanah (Oineeah) to Dereyya. Erom Eiyanah the valley runs for about half a day’s journey to Malka, first east by south, then south, then east by south and finally east-south-east. At Malka it forks, the main channel running south to Dereyya and thence to Riadh; the smaller channel starts in an easterly direction and, according to Palgrave, also leads to Riadh. Belly calls the smaller branch a “ tributary,” which is a term inconsistent with his own description. At the point of bifurcation are a rest-house, a well, and a garden containing figs and citrons. Down to this point the character of the valley is fairly uniform, having an average width of a few hundred yards and flat-topped scarps on either bank alternating with low slopes. The immediately adjacent crests are never more than 200 feet high. Deer and partridges abound along its course. Floods are said to rise 7 or 8 feet. Erom Dereyya down to Riadh the Wadi appears to be, in places at least, a scarped and contracted ravine rather than an open valley. At Riadh it seems, from Palgrave’s account, to continue eastwards after passing Mmfoohah. Inhabited places in its upper basin are Horeymela, and Sedoos, and in the valley itself Eiyanah, Jebeyly, Eiman, then several hamlets prettily situated among groups of trees and filling up the entire breadth of the valley, then Malka, Riadh and possibly Manfooha. If Sadlier went from Manfooha to Dereyya by this valley, its course below Dereyya is first east and then south to Manfooha. This valley is tbe main seat of political power in Central Arabia and has always contained tbe capital of Nejd (Eiyanah, Dereyya, Riadb). It is evidently well watered, fruitful and populous audits palm groves are luxuriant, especially those adjoining the ruins of Eiyanah and Dereyya. Palgrave says an older name was Wadi Moseylamah. The question of the lower course of this valley is one of the unsolved problems of Arabian geography. Hogarth is obviously inclined to identify it with the “ Wadi Aftan ” of the ancients and to take one of tbe estuaries between Katar and Abu Dhabi, mentioned by Miles in a report, as its mouth. HATTHON (JEBEL).—Mountainous mass in the country of the Bakoom tribe, about 100 miles north-east of Mecca. On its east side is Taraba and in the same neighbourhood Wadi Taraba takes its rise. HARARA.—Town or village in the Aflaj district. HAREEK (1).—A subdivision of the district of Yemama and the southern most in Nejd. The inhabitants are dusky, and Belly does not credit them with any fighting men. Shortly before descending from Jebel Toweik on his route to Hofhuf, Palgrave caught a distant view of Hareek. It lay south of C905ED C10 his point of observation and was separated from Jebel Toweik by a strip of desert. It contained a ragged and isolated range of bids, seemingly granitic, apparently 60 miles in length from east to west. It is a hot, neb tract and apparently an integral part of the Wadi Hamfa country. Hogarth thinks it natural to assume that the oasis of Hareek has some hydrographic connection with the Wadi Yabrin. (See Section II, subjection A.) He says that the political predominence enjoyed by Yemama and Kharj m the middle ages has now passed to Hareek and its capital How tab. HAKEEK (2).—A town or village of the Yemama district. HAEKA.—Village in the Hereyya neighbourhood, one of those which assisted Dereyyah with supplies during the first part of the siege in 1818. The Turks took it and left a detachment there. HARHAT-AL-HAMRA.— See Wadi Dowasir. HAYER. A town or village in the Aaredh district inhabited by Sbeya. HAZZAM.—Tract extending south-south-west of Afif, traversed for 2J days by route from Aneyza to Mecca. HAZM-ER-RAJEE.—Place situated 72 camel hours from Riadh and 176 from Koweit. It is separated from Aaredh by a district called Garaniah. HERREYIK.—Place in Washam district. HOOLAH.—A town of Sedeyr district, about l a day’s march north of Horeymela on route to Mejmaa. In 1862 it was a large, busy, flourishing place and one that had improved under Wahabi rule owing to cessation of local feuds and influx of wealth into central districts of Nejd. Its proximity to Shakra and the Washam road contributed to its prosperity. The inhabitants were diligent agriculturists as well as active traders, and the country around was planted and tilled to a notable distance. It w T as defended by towered walls of sun-dried brick with some unhewn stone. HOREYMELAH.—Town, birth-place of the founder of Wahabi sect. Palgrave places it in Sedeyr, Ross in Aaredh: it is almost on border between the two? It is northern key to Central Nejd and in 18S2 there was a large fort built by the Egyptians, on rising ground inside the town. Horeymelah is surrounded by palm-trees, and blocks funnel-shaped end of a gorge which extends northwards for J a day*8 journey. Slope of gorge not specified in which direction. Palgrave estimated population at 10,000. Horeymela is 9 camel or 3 dromedary journeys from Aneyza, and 3 or 2 respectively from Riadh. HORMAH.—A town or village in Sedeyr district. HOWTAH (1). —Place in Sedeyr a short distance south of Jelajel. The people were said in 1865 to have been converted from idolatry only 40 years before, and still to preserve inviolate certain sculptured caverns which formed the temples of the old religion of Howtah. HOWTAH (2).—Treated by Pelly as a district with a revenue (in 1865) of $ 20,000, population of 8,000 and fighting strength of 500. According to him it lies due south of Sedoos and Dereyya. According to Palgrave, Ross and Doughty, Howtah is a town ; Palgrave calls it the capital of Hareek, while Doughty says it is as large as Aneyza and inhabited by Beni Temim. Nolde found the Sheikh of Howtah a man of high consideration with the Wahabi Amir, and estimated the population at 35,000. HUSSEEAII.—Plain or tableland one march west of Eiyanah. It is hounded by mouldering hills. The road from Eiyanah crosses a ridge or range of hills, and on the west there is again a rugged descent leading to a wide plain. There is good water in wells at Husseeah. Shakra lies 3 marches to the north west. IMAMEH.—Place in the neighbourhood of Dereyya but not of much importance in 1819. Does Sadliermean Yemama ? JANNAH.—Ruined settlement, about 1 mile north-west of Aneyzah ; belonged to Jannah section of Beni Khalid.11 JELAJEL.—-Considerable fown in Sedeyr, on tbe 'west side of the road f rom Mejraaa to Toweym and about 20 miles from each. It had in 1862 an unusual extent of palm groves and irrigation around it, maintained by a flowing stream which came down from a point on the Mejmaa road, distant 4 or 6 hours to the north-east. The buildings and defences were ordinary. JIRZAWEAII.—Halting place with wells, about 3 marches west-south west of Hass on the route to Medina. On the east side are rocky bare hills, apparently an independent range though of no considerable elevation, which the route from Hass crosses. JENEYAH.—Village in the Wadi Shakran. JENUBIAH.—Town or village of Sedeyr district. JEREYEA.—Place in Washam district. JERRIH (WADI).—Main affluent from south-east of Wadi Rummah, supposed to join it about 75 miles east-south-east of Aneyza, It rises in Shiffa. JIBLAN.—Tribe of Nejd connected with the Beni Lam. KAHTAN.—Tribe. (1) Kahtanic tribe from Yemen. They say their original home was at the mountain of Tor in Asir and claim descent from the prophet Hud. (2) Boss names 62 sections. Belly only divides them into Kahtan: and Kahtan-el-Jamb. Boss (1879) remarked that they still mustered 6,000 men. Belly (1865) apparently estimated them at 7,000 (? men) viz. 6,000 Kahtan and 1,000 Kahtan-el-Jamb. (4) They are a southern tribe and their limits not known ; but some of them wander as far north as Washam and they are occasionally seen in Sedeyr and even at Hail in Jebel Shammar. Belly met a few between Ormah and Sedoos. Khabara is said to be a Kahtan settle ment. (1) Balgrave describes those he met as small and slender, of almost Indian type. Their voices were low and their deportment gentler than that of the northern Bedouins. He considered them inferior in build and energy to the Muteyr, Ajman and Ateyba. Doughty however calls them nearly the best in arms among the nomads, but not such good fighters as the Ateyba. Their treachery in war seems well established. They are ill-natured and many reports to their disadvantage are current e.g. that they eat the flesh of their slain enemies, that they murder smokers and that their own dead are thrown to the birds without burial. The word Kahtani is also used in Nejd as a term of abuse, indicating their unpopularity. (5) They are fanatics in religion to an extreme degree. (6) They are fairly rich in cattle and horses. (7) (8) Their speech resembles that of Nejd but is perhaps more eloquent and full. (9) ( 11 ) ( 12 ) In 1861 they were under the influence of Hiadh owin 0 * to their nearness to the centres of Wahabi power, but their loyalty was apparent only. In 1878 they intruded close to Aneyza and raided the Muteyr but suffered a severe defeat near Jebel Dokany, 50 miles south-south-east of Aneyza, from the Muteyr and people of Aneyza. . KASEEM (SOUTHERN).—This district, lying in the north-west of Nejd, is divided by Wadi Rummah into two parts, a northern and a southern; the latter only falls to be described in this sub-section. (1) On the north-west, Southern Kaseem is bounded by Wadi Rummah ; on the north-east, by the district of Washam, of which the frontier villages are Zulfah and Mudhnib; on the south-east, by the district of IVasham from which it is separated by the Nefuds of Shakika and Sirr; and on the south-west, by the margin of the igneous country,^ which begins immediately south of Hass and runs for some distance in the direction of Shakra. Some however reckon the villno-eg of Miskeh and Therrieh, which lie 45 miles south-west of Rass, to belong to Kaseem. At Thoreyih, a few miles further in the same direction, there is still a Kaseem element m the population. (2) The chief towns of Southern Kaseem are Aneyza and Rass and the villages include Eiyarieh, Auhellan, Ashbibiah, Owshazieh (all deserted) and Wadi, Raudhan and Shenana (all inhabited). (3) Hie land ialis to the north or north-west, average elevation is about 2,750 feet and rocks are sandstone. Soil is grit-sand and villages, though green, are scattered among the Isefud. \v ater level is close to the surface; but the water is generally12 slightly salt. The soil is loam in the low grounds and in these spots the wells and plantations are found. (4) The air of the Kaseem desert is sometimes stagnant and sultry. From April to June the weather is warm with overcast skies and, on some days, light rain. Barley is harvested in the end of April. (5) Many routes intersect in Kaseem. The paths from the east to the Holy Cities and from the south to Jebel Shammar intersect at Ayun. Doughty (II. 467) mentions 3 routes from Kaseem to Mecca, the Herb es-Sultany, the mid dle Derb and the Derb Wadi Sbeiya; of these the first is the easiest and furthest to the north, while the third is the southernmost and most difficult. Those adjoin ing are almost within sight of one another. (6) Grapes are abundant : Kaseem dates are sold in Jebel Shammar 100 miles distant, and in some years Kaseem dates and corn reach Medina. Dates are valued by weight. Spanish crowns form the currency. The people are mostly carriers plying to Mecca, Medina, Jebel Shammar, Baghdad, Basrah, Koweit and the Wahabi country : £ of them are calculated to depend on this profession. (7) Country is populous the estimate (Huber’s) being 23,920 in 1880. The fixed inhabitants are styled Kusman and are of Beni Temim descent. The pastures were disputed between the Muteyr and Kahtan Bedouins (1878), and the Ateyba adjoined on the south west. The villagers of Kaseem resemble town Arabs; they are prudent and not given to hospitality, but adventurous. On the whole they may be described as industrious and civilised. The women wear sleeves so loose as occasionally to expose the person from the armpit to the knee. The Kusman were well repre sented among the labourers on the Suez Canal Works. In Palgrave’s time only a minority were Wahabis, and he thought ^ of them had no religion at all. Doughty found them comparatively tolerant as a consequence of intercourse with abroad. Well-sinking is understood, which it is not at Teima or at any place between Teima and Kasim. (8) The political position of Southern Kaseem has undergone great fluctuations ; in 1862 it was subject to the Wahabis, in 1878 independent under the Amir of Aneyza, and in 1892, it was conquered by the Amir of Jebel Shammar. Revenue paid to the Wahabis was $70,000 in 1865. The only villagers of Nejd who now take service with the Turks as Ageylis are those of Kaseem. All Kaseem villages have watch towers, necessitated by the flatness and insecurity of the country. KASSAB.—Place in Washam district. KHAL (JEBEL).—Conical, flat-topped hill of black basalt, 10 marches from Aneyzah on route to Mecca and reckoned half-way. KHALID (BENI).—Tribe, the most powerful in Nejd before the Waha bis, but now much diminished in numbers and influence. They are still nume rous in Aneyza and are more like Bedouins than the Beni Temim yet are of the same main stock, that of Muthur. Doughty mentions a section called Jannah. KHARPA.—Chief town of Aflaj district, stands on a sandy palm- sprinkled plain two days by camel south-west or south-south-west of Kiadh. Palgrave estimated the population at 8,000 ; he found water abundant and gardens better than elsewhere in Aflaj. The Khodeyreeyah or mulattoes almost equalled the white population in number and like pure negroes frequently wore notliing but a waist cloth. Hospitality was meagre and a want of soci ability and coarseness of manners was observable. Kharfa is the key of Central Nejd on the south. KHAltJ.—Called by Doughty Khark. Some authorities describe it as a town, others as a district. According to the latter view it is either a tract forming part of the larger district of Yemama, which also includes Hareek, or else a district in itself of which Yemama is the chief town. According to the former view it is a town, either near Saleemiah or identical with it. A valley rising north of Aflaj descends to Howtah and from Howtah to Kharj. Jebel Toweik stretches away from the upper basin of the Wadi Hanifa towards Kharj. Palgrave says that the country about Kharj is the most fertile in Yemama and the paradise of Nejd. Cotton is more frequent than else where in Nejd and the people are gentler and more amiable than in Aaredh. KHARJ EE.—-Mentioned by Sadlier as a village south of Dereyya. Is Kharj meant ?KHA1UEH.—Referred to by Sadlier as a place near Saleemiab. Is this Kharj above ? laiODEYREEYAH.—According to Palgrave, is the name given in Central Arabia to Arabs having African blood. KHORMAH.—Village in Wadi Sabey. KHOTA.—-Mentioned by Sadlier as a village south Dereyya. Can he refer to Howtah ? KHUBRAH.—Lake with annual cultivation on its banks mentioned by Sadlier as a short distance south of Mudhnib. KONSOLIEH.—Village in Wadi Sabey. KORA.—According to Palgrave, a large but thinly peopled district, half desert, to the south-west of Wadi Dowasir. Its chief place is Kelaat Bishaa. KUSMAN.—See Kaseem {7). LAD AM.—Village in Wadi Dowasir. LAKEYYAT.—Patch of green soil and cluster of wells in Jebel Toweik, on route from Riadh to Ojair, about one march short of the point where the road begins to descend to the Dahna. LEYLA.—Third of S places on route from Riadh to Wadi Bisha. LEYTA.—Village in Aflaj. LOGHF.—Name of 3 hamlets in Wadi Dowasir. MAATEELAH.—Village in Wadi Dowasir. MAHMEL.—Plain in Aaredh, west of and lower than Sedoos, forming, as it were, a recess in the east flank of the Toweik range. It is crossed, ap parently from east to west, by the Sedoos valley and has, in that direction, a breadth of 15 to £0 miles. There are villages at the west end of the plain under the foot of the Toweik range. Does this plain drain to the Wadi Hanifa ? MAJMAA.—Town in Sedeyr, formerly capital of the province and, in 1862, still a place of considerable importance. Stands on a small eminence in middle of a broad shallow valley, surrounded by luxuriant gardens and trees. Walls were 30 feet high at time of Palgrave’s visit and large square fort in centre commanded town. Outside walls was very deep trench partly full of water. Plantations were all outside wnlls. Majmaa is separated from Jelajel by rising ground and less than a day’s march, perhaps 20 miles. There is a route north-east by east from Majmaa to Wabreh. MALKA—Small village in Aaredh district, on the Wadi Hanifa at the point where it divides into two branches. Here were (in 1862) a rest-house, well and garden. Palgrave says it is 8 leagues from Riadh, and Mengin that it is 2 from Dereyyah. Name means “junction.” MANEOOOA.—Town of Aaredh district, apparently in the Wadi Hanifa, about 10 miles south-east of Dereyya. In 1819, it had about 2,000 families, part of the population of Dereyya having, after its destruction, taken refuge here. There were some good two-storeyed houses of mud and stone with flat roofs. Town was surrounded by extensive date-plantations and well supplied with water from deep wells. Water-melons, musk-melons, peaches, figs, brinjals, onions, spinach, clover and straw were obtainable, but the fruit was not of good quality. Cotton vras found and udieat, barley and maize had formerly been extensively grown. Palgrave says Manfooha stands higher than Riadh and is healthier but not so defensible. Sadlier makes Manfooha only 1 mile south of Riadh : Palgrave makes the distance over 4 hours’ journey. Manfooha originally belonged to the Yemama district. • MARAT.—Village of Washam district. MASEL.—Village in Wadi Thalith. MAWEEAH (JEBEL).—Hill 6 marches west, by south of Rass and 2 marches east by north of Henakiyeh. Here first engagement took place bet ween Turks and Wahabis in 1818. Is this Moww an of Doughty’s map ? C905FD Dwmmm u MELHAM.—Village of Aaredh district. MENASEER.—Mentioned by Pelly (1865) as a Bedouin tribe in Nejd of 400 persons paying an annual contribution, chiefly in kind, of $ 2,000 to the Nejd treasury. Are these the Manasir of section II sub-section A ? MESALEEKH.—Tribe of which the founder of Wahabiism was born a member at Horeymelah. Are any of them still settled in Nejd ? MESHALLAH.—Large village in Aflaj district, about ^ a day’s journey from Kharfa on the route to Riadh. Population in 1862 were poor and gardens and palm groves thin though extensive. Cotton and white millet were grown. Skirts were longer and the knife at girdle more common. Name means “ stripping-place.” MESHEAIB (JEBEL UMM).—-Mountain about 100 miles south-south west of Aneyza on route to Mecca. Highest point on route is near here; Doughty made it 4,575 feet. MESTEWWY.—Name of a Nefud immediately north of Skakra. MIRIAH.—Village, ruined in 1819, near Surumdah. MISKEH.—Village placed by Doughty about 70 miles south-west of Aneyza. It has some 50 houses and grows corn; no palms ; same mixed popula tion as Therrieh. MOHALLAT-AL-HATATA.—Village or town in Wadi Dowasir. MORRAH (AL).—Kahtanie tribe of whom, according to Pelly, there were 600 in Nejd in 1865, paying the value of $ 3,000 annually to the Wahabi government. Ross names 8 sections. Are these the same as in section II sub section B.* MOSEYLAMAH (WADI).—See under Wadi Hanifa. MUDHNIB.—Town of Sedeyr district, a few hours south-east of Aneyza towards Jebel Toweik. Marble blocks of which coffee-mortars are made are. quarried in this neighbourhood. Sadlier (1819) found Mudhuib an open vil lage, with abundant supply of rather bitter water in wells ; its date-plantations and cultivated ground were extensive. MUSAJIDEE.—District of which Ormah forms a division. MUSH ASH BATIN-UL-AOORHAH.—Halting place 5 marches west- south-west of Rass on way to Medina. MUTEYR.—Bedouin tribe vulgarly called Umteyr. Lady Blunt says they are also called Dushan, but perhaps this is only Guarmani’s Duscian section. (1) Of the stock of Muthur. (2) Guarmani divides them into Eluah and Breh. Eluah include Duscian, Gheblan, Saaba, Megealda, Gaimat, Aragbe and Baraasa ; Breh include Sarran, Merehat, Berisan, Usiama, Dikakin, Abeirat, Uled Abbad and Beni Abdella. Ross names 24 sections but there is little agreement between his and Guarmani’s nomenclature. (3) Pelly rated them at 1,200 (? men) and Guarmani estimated their horsemen at 2,500. Doughty estimates them at 5,000 souls, next in number to the Ateyba, and gives them a range of 600 miles from Harrat-el-Kisshub nearly to Koweit and Basra. They inhabit plains east of Aneyza as far as the valleys south-east of Ghafeh. They are found also about Miskeh, Therriyeh, Thoreyih and Jebel Shaba on south west borders of Kaseem. Prom Pelly it would appear they summer near Riadh and range chiefly between Riadh and Koweit with Jahara, Zobeir and the Shatt-el-Arab for their limits. According to Doughty they were originally Ahl Jibli and come from the great Harra between the Haramein where some of the tribe are still found. (4) Those Doughty met seemed inhospitable. They resembled ordinary Bedouins, (5) Doughty thought them not fanatical and Palgrave describes them as impatient of the Wahabi religion but reduced (1862) to outward conformity. (6) (7) They are comparatively rich in flocks and herds. Their camels are generally black; none are dun. (8) They speak the ordinary nomad Arabic. (9) (10) See (3) above. (11) (12) According to Palgrave were once tyrants of north-east Nejd but succumbed to the Wahabis. In 1863 they were still tributary to the15 Wahabis, paying the value of $16,000 annually in taxes and were steady enemies of the Harb and Heteym and of the Amir of Jebel khammar. In 1878 they visited Hail from time to time with presents and were friendly, though not subject, to the Amir. They were then hostile to Boreyda and allied with Aneyza. With the last they made a successful foray on Kahtan in 1878. MUTTA.—Small hamlet with cultivation and wells of water, in 1819, one march south south-west of Rass. NAAJAN’.—Town or village in Yemama district. This is probably the Najan which Doughty mentions as a good village, lying in a valley that runs from north of Aflaj via Howtah to Kharj. NAAM.—Town or village in Yemama district. NEFUD.-—Por the Nefud between Riadh and Hofhuf, see under Dahna. In the north the district of Kasim consists mainly of Nefud. The Kaseem Nefudis intersected by Wadi Rummah but its bed is hardly discernible except by greater firmness of sand. Sand itself is not deep, in places, and water-level is high. Limits are undetermined except on west, where this Nefud ends just beyond Rass. Routes connecting places in Kaseem Nefud are generally hollow. The Aneyza people sometimes go and camp in Nefud for change of air. Nefuds called Mestewwy and Sirr occur in Washan district. See also Sub-section B. NEJD.—May be defined roughly as the highlands of Central Arabia (1) In the widest sense it includes the whole space from Jebel Shammar to the southern desert and from Jebel Toweik to the western Derb-el-Haj. The true boundaries are hard to fix. Guarmani and Doughty include Jebel Sham- mar in Nejd ; or, as Guarmani says, “ among the 7 Nejds.” Palgrave consi dered Jebel Shammar a mere appendage ; Felly and Ross excluded it politically. The difficulty arises from a confusion between geographical and political boundaries. In the present precis, which is purely geographical, the following boundaries are assumed : on the north the Wadi Rummah, on the east the Dahna, on the south the impassable desert, on the west an imaginary line starting from the source of the Wadi Rummah so as to run immediately east of Henakiyeh and thence to Jebel Hatthon. (2) The principal districts are, according to Palgrave, Aaredh, Yemama, Hareek, Aflaj, Wadi Dowasir, Seleyyel, W'asham, Sedeyr, Kastem, Hasa and Kateef. Pelly gives Kaseem, Washam, Sedeyr, Aaredh, Yemama (including Kharj and Hareek), Howtah, Aflaj, Selayel, Wadi Dowasir, Hasa, Kateef, Ojair and Garaniah. Ross’s list runs Hasa, Sedeyr, Washam, Aaredh, Yemama (including Kharj and Hareek), Kaseem, Aflaj, Wadi Dowasir, Wadi Sabey, Wadi Shakran and Wadi Thalith. Of the above Hasa, Katif and Ojair never belonged geographically to Nejd and there is now no political connection either. Of the remainder Sedeyr, Kaseem, Washam, Aaredh, Yemama and Aflaj undoubtedly belong to Nejd both geographically and politically. Howtah, if it is a separate district and not included (as Hareek and Kharj probably should be) in Yemama, may also be regarded as a part of Nejd. Wadi Dowasir and Seleyyel formed part of the Wahabi Dominions in 1865 and may be provisionally regarded as belonging to political if not to geogra phical Nejd. Nothing is known of Garaniah mentioned by Pelly, nor of Wadis Sabey, Shakran and Thalith, mentioned by Ross. Palgrave also divides Nejd into Upper and Lower Nejd (el Ala and el Owta). (3) Geologically Nejd is a tract which, protected from the prevailing winds by the lavas that reach from 21° to 28° north along the western side of the peninsula, has not been buried by the shift ing sand and converted into Nefud. The limestone is generally exposed but here and there, especially in depressions, are strips and intervals of sand. The leading features of Nejd are Jebel Toweik and Wadi Hanifa (q q.v.). Accord ing to Doughty, mean altitude of Nejd desert is about 4,000 feet. According to Palgrave, the area of pasture lands is almost equal to that of arable lands and absolute desert combined. Further details of configuration will be found under the names of the districts and in the articles on Toweik and Hanifa. (1) See articles on districts. Snow falls occasionally, and in winter of 1875- 76 (?) lay for 3 days, causing much mortality among camels. (5) Sadlier, Palgrave, Pelly and Doughty have described the routes by which they travelled and Pelly in Appendix X of his report gives a synopsis of distances from Riadh.10 Pal o’rave from native information gives in addition, tlie following routes : (i) Hiadh to Nejran, via Kharfa, Wadi Dowasir (10 days in extent), Kora (? 2 davs in extent), Wadi Seleyyel (3 days in extent), Nejran (reached in 2 days from Seleyyel) ; (ii) Riadh to Mecca via Wadi Hanifa and Shakra ; (m) Shakra to Aneyza ; (iv) Riadh to Zulfa and thence to Zobeir, Jebel Shammar or Kaseem. Articles on these places also contain references to communications, especially that on Kaseem. (6) The products of Nejd are chiefly pastoral, among the principal being ghi and wool. Horses are largely bred by the Bedouin tribes and are collected for exportation chiefly in Kaseem, at Aneyza and Boreyda. These are the “ Aneyza horses ” of the Bombay stables and are sent via Koweit. Camels are abundant and those of the southern tribes are commonly blackish and smaller in stature than those of the northern divas. Northern tribes prefer larger dun-coloured camels which, they say, are better tempered and more tractable. Cattle are commoner in the south than in the north and are most in the Yemma district; they are small limbed and all have humps. There are no buffaloes. Sheep are numerous and those of the Harb tribe are mostly black ; all are broad-tailed and their wool is fine ; they fetch a high, but not highest, price in the Damas cus market and are exported in other directions also. Palgrave thought Nejd might supply half the Ottoman Empire with wool and mutton. Kaseem dates are exported to Hail and in some seasons to Mecca, while ghi is sent from Riadh to Hofhuf and from Boreyda and Aneyza to Mecca. There is usually no surplus of corn, but when the price is high in the Holy Cities some goes from Kaseem. Game are partridges, quail, sandgrouse, pigeon, bustard and ga zelle; wild boar are common in the mountains. Palgrave says there are no gnats mosquitoes, fleas or snakes and very few flies. Among foreign imports noticed by Doughty are clothing from Persian Gulf and English medicines. The weights, measures and currency of Riadh are described by Pelly in Appendix IX of his report. (7) Pelly remarks on the impossibility of forming a close esti mate of the population : from the nature of the country it is sparse, except in certain localities. Excluding Hasa, Katif and Ojair, Pelly’s estimate is 81,000 of a settled population and 18,300 Bedouins; Palgrave’s, with the same deduc tions, 959,000 and 76,500 Doughty says there are less than 60,000 males among the Bedouins. Pelly’s figures appear not to include women or children. The people may be divided into settled tribes and nomads, but even townsmen are of pure Bedouin descent and recognise their connection with their still wandering brethren of the s &gt;me name. The only tribes of non-Bedouin des cent are also non-Arab and of inferior status, such as the Sanis (artificers) and the Sulaba. The classifications by Doughty and Ross of the Arab tribes seem inconsistent. Doughty apparently divides the descendants of Modhar into two branches, those of the line of Elyas and those of the line of Keys. The only representatives of Elyas mentioned by him as found in Nejd are Beni Temim. Erom his account it would seem that the representatives of Keys in Nejd are the Ateyba, the Sbeya, and 5 tribes whom he groups together as belonging to a section called Yam, viz., the A1 Morrah, Beni Khalid, Ajman, Beni Hajir and Shamir. He also mentions the Muteyr as descended from Modhar but does not specify the line to which they belong. As Doughty calls the Mutevr and the Beni Temim Ishmaelites, it must be assumed that all descendants of Modhar are non-Kahtanic. f lhis does not agree with Ross’s accouut in which the Ajman, A1 Morrah and Beni Hajir, besides the Bureya, Asim, and Dowasir (not apparently classified by Doughty) are Kahtanic. The Bakoom and Sabe- yaa are non-Kahtanic in Ross’s view. From Palgrave’s account of the tribes of Nejd it is impossible (with 2 exceptions) to understand which he considered to be Kahtanic and which not; he insists principallv on the unlikeness of the Beni Temim to the others and the Beni Temim he distinctly calls Nezar, i.e., non-Kah,tanic. In his account of the Dahna he calls the A1 Morrah Kahtanic, agreeing with Ross. Palgrave makes the Beni Temim predominate in the south ern districts of Aaielh, Aflaj, Femama and Dowasir and peoples the northern districts of Sedeyr, Kaseem and Washam with other tribes of whom he aiyes no clear account. From Doughty s account passim, it must, on the contrary, be inferred that the Beni Temim are exceedingly strong in Kaseem. Negroes are iound in all paits of Nejd. those in the north are all slaves. In the south they17 are more numerous and many are free. They are common at Kiadh, still more common at Manfooha and Saleemiah, and swarm inHareek and Wadi Dowasir. In some place negroes and mulattos (called Khodeyreeyah) amount to ^ or ^ of the population. Smoking in private is tolerated throughout Nejd except in what remains of the Wahabi dominions and among ultra-fanatical tribes such as the Kahtan. Games are not played and gambling is unknown. The people are fresh in their devotion as if adherents of a new religion. Half- castes (Arab and African) are not allowed to marry Arab women. The law of inheritance among the Wahabis is that of the Koran : a man cannot devise more than ^ of his estate by will; the priesthood appropriate ^; a widow without children gets and a widow with children her issue receiving Villagers and townsmen are lean and tall; with somewhat remarkable eyes and long flat or hollow faces. They are generally of unhealthy appearance. In mind they are active and in disposition more magnanimous than the sedentary population of Hejaz; in warlike qualities they compare not unfavourably with the Bedouins. About one person out of three is more or less blind. They are lovers of coffee made over a charcoal-fire, kindled in a clay hearth that is whitened with gypsum, and blown with smith’s bellows. Their towns are defended by clay w^alls and the towers are shaped like light houses. They consider their language to be purer than that of Syria, Egypt, the Hejaz or Mesopotamia, but admit that it has departed from the standard of the Koran. Einal N in nouns is pronounced indistinctly. The Bedouins are dispersed, over the country for 9 months of the year in small ferjan (nomad villages), each ferij consisting of families more or less connected by blood ; in the height of summer tha ferjan collect together and form large standing menzils at the principal watering places of each dira. The Bedouins, except the Sebaa and Muteyr, place a cross with red cloth at the doo * of a tent where circumcision is about to be performed, and friends send sheep a* presents on such occasions : the sheep is tied by a string to the person of the child about to he circumcised. This practice is common to the Sulaba. The Bedouin women cover their faces from the mouth down, wear a silver ring in the right nostril, and have a braided forelock hanging over the temple. °(8) The greater part of Nejd has, since the time of the W r ahabis, been subject to their government. The Wahabis in 1865 generally collected their revenue in kind and in horses, except in the districts of Hasa, which no larger pertain to Nejd. The Amir used to send a man once a year to receive tribute from each tribe, or the tribute was brought to Riadh by the chief or his deputy. The Amir in leturn gave the chief one or more Hasa abbas. Palgrave (1862) assessed the revenue of the Wahabi provinces (without Hasa and Katif) at $ 163,000 ; Belly (1865) at $ 402,000 including $ 114,000 from the Bedouins.^ Balgrave’s estimate of the Wahabi military muster from the same districts is 40,300 ; Belly’s is only 6,900, but this figure can hardly include the Bedouins whose adult males (?) he puts at 18,300. OJMAN-ER= RAKHM.—Occurs in Belly’s table of Bedouin tribes. Num- AAA the T e as 1 ’ 20( ? ( ? adult males ) aad annual tribute to Riadh as $ o,UUO. Is this same as Ajman above? OODAH.—Town or village in Sedeyr. , n ORMAH.—Piain in the district of Musajidee, roughly IJ days’ journey in breadth ; bounded on the north-east by the Dahna and on the south-west by Temameh hills. On the north it is said to reach 4 or 5 hours beyond Zulfah and on the south to sink into the east confines of Yemama. A dry water- couvse intersects the plain, which, rising in the Temameh hills and running from 1° nort ^ easfc / s ^ V 11 the Here is a usual halting place on th. routes fiom KoweR and Hofhuf to Riadh, which appear to unite at this point, Riadh lying about 2 marches to the south-west. Sadlier describes i C ° Vered i ^ lth St ° neS and very barren : h e experienced heavy ram at this place and the camp was inundated by the drainage of higher 0n t h e dr y hanks of the torrent mentioned are two sets of wells called Ormah and Ormayeh the former being to eastward of latter. At Ormayeh lelly found a grass plat, and copse of stunted mimosa bushes, the first trees since Koweit : on the road he had seen neither hut nor fowl, and scarcely C905BD18 a goat. Ihe plain generally is broken up into low flat or conical hillocks, with flat intervening hollows, ea^h valley having a gully or dry torrent bed, down the middle of its entire length. ORMAYEH.—See Ormah above. OSHEYJIR.— Place in Washam district whence came great Bessam family of Aneyza. OTHEYTHIA.—Place in Washam district. OWEYSIT.—-Group of wells, situated in a circular depression with tracks yesembling trenches leading into it from every side, at the foot of the east ernmost ridge of Jebel Toweik and about ^ a day from the westernmost and of the south Dahna or Nefud. Here converge the Ilareek route from the south ; the Yemama route from the west; a mountain track, which follows Jebel Toweik from a point on the Koweit-Central Arabian route, from the north ; the Djebreen road from the north-west; and the Hasa road from the west. The wells are a dozen or more and the water clear and good ; it is so abundant that the w r ells sometimes overflow forming a small lake at the bottom of the depres sion. There is no other watering-place between here and Hasa. Name is diminutive of Ausat, meaning “ centre ” and refers to central position of wells with regard to communications. OWSHAZIEH.—Ruined site 3 hours east of Aneyza (Doughty, 1878). OWSEIAZIEH (RAUDHAN EL).—Village of 100 inhabitants about 7 miles east of Aneyza (Huber, 1880). Is this the same as the last ? OWSHEYEY.—Place in Washam district, between which and Thormada is the Garat Owsheyfia or Et Teyry, said to have been a place of pilgrimage before Islam. QUARREEN.—(Kowarein ?) Village hours south-east of Shakra, on south side of route from Thormada. RAPA (MERGAB-ER).—Long high platform of sandstone rock, imme diately to east of Aneyza, used as a quarry for the town. RAP1YA—See Pass. RAML-AL-KHALI.—One of Bedouin names for great southern desert. n g r e a t palm village in Wadi Sabey, or possibly in a separate valley of its own name. x ^ r ^ i S A i NI i Y ^ (WADty—A valley containing the village of Raniya. It i doubtful whether this valley is distinct from Wadi Sabey or identical with it. t I ,a ' ms ''ith a few cultivators, Ivins in a ba of right bank of Wadi Rummah, a little south of Eyarieh. RASS.—It is uncertain whether this town lies north or south of Wac Rummah, and consequently whether it should appear in this suh-section orth next. On the one hand Doughty connects it with the principality of Boreydi and in a note states that it ,es north of Wadi Rummah. On the other hot Doughty and Huber show it to the south of Wadi Rummah iu their maps an Huber associates it with Aneyza rather than Boreyda. The evidence for southerly position seems to preponderate. Sadlier makes it 121 hours’ marc W stnnp, 0 rt-' “/i 'VTa' Pal S ra y e was ‘old that it possessed a circle of stand in, stones like that at Ayun. It is only a few miles from Khabara and i t le last settlement, in this direction, of Kaseem ; immediately bevond it be&lt;'in the granitic and basaltic region which stretches to Mecca It lies in h path of many caravans and most of the inhabitants are themselves caravaner rmpiflatfon'at S OW ) 15 f ^^ Huber roughly estimated tli largest, Rueydha, is a town ; the second, Bafyaf ifa vUnge wR^a Wgh watc ^wa^W ’’ 5 iTl 1 ^’ ' the Smallest Hajnowwy Ethelly, etc. ^ ° 11135 SranSeS &gt; Called Vmm Ti y el RAUDHA (1).—Village in Aflaj.19 BAUDHA (2).—A considerable town in Sedeyr surrounded by palm- groves and irrigation. It lies on tbe east side of the route from Tovveym to Moreymelah, about one hour’s distance south of Jelajel. BAUDHA (3).—Small village in Wadi Hanifa, a short distance below Eiyanah, Here Moseylamah was slain in battle with Khalid-ibn-Walid. BAUDHAN.—Village of 12D inhabitants, on the right bank of Wadi Bummah, upon one route from Aneyza to Boreyda. BEMAH.—Place with seven very deep wells in 1819. The place is im portant, as if the wells were filled up the route passing this way from^ Wab to Biadh would, in Sadlier’s opinion, become impassable. At Sadlier’s visit 2,000 families of the Subeeyh Bedouins were encamped here. BIADH (1).—The Wahabi capital. (1) Situated on the Wadi Hanifa in district of Aaredh. Appendix VIII of Felly’s Beport gives the distance of Riadh from various places. Palgrave makes it 1 hours west of Manfooha, Sadlier 1 mile north. (2) Stands on plateau at no great distance from the left bank of the Wadi Hanifa. It is a neat and considerable town but w ithout pretention to beauty. In suburbs are extensive date groves, especially on w est and south, and there are several cultivated enclosures. Palgrave’s plan shows high ground to the north, broken ground to the north-east and gardens on the other sides. He places the main gate in tbe east w^all of the town and shows the chief street as lead ing thence west into the public square in the centre of the town. He divides the town into four quarters all mBeting upon the square, viz., a north-east quarter, low-lying and not healthy, with high houses and straight streets of medium width, containing the palaces of the Royal family, state officials and rich proprietors ; a north-west quarter, inhabited by Bedouins and other strangers, equivocal characters and a few zelators, with the best and the worst houses in the town ; a south-west quarter, with open streets and healthy air, where most of the religious element and the descendants of the founder of Wahabiism live ; and a south-east quarter called Hazik (“ the crowded !&gt; ), that of peasants and the lower classes, low-lying, not healthy and on the whole the worst built and kept of any. Houses are of sundried brick. Tow ? n has many wells : those for irrigation outside the walls are 47 feet deep. (3) There is a fort in the mid dle of the town dominating the whole. Town is surrounded by walls 20 to 30 feet high with a deep trench outside. Colvill (1863) gives population as 5,000 Nolde (1893) as 8,000 to 12,000. (5)—(8) No definite information. (9) There are a large Jamia mosque and about 30 ordinary mosques. (10) Head quarters of Wahabi government. Palgrave’s and Felly's accounts are probably out of date so far as government is concerned. [“ Biadh ' is the plural of Raudha, which means not only a garden but a natural moist hollow where vegetation grows.]. BISH1Y.—Hamlet in Wadi Sirr. BOB AL-KHALI.—The great southern desert is so called, but in Nejd it is generally spoken of as Yemama. BOBBA.—Small village between Thormada and Horeymela, one march from former and two marches from latter. BUEYDHA.—Village on route from Riadh to Mecca. RUMLAH —Mentioned by Sadlier as village in vicinity of Dereyya. SABEY (WADI).—Mentioned by Ross as a district of Nejd containing Khormah, Baniya, Taraba and other villages. This seems to be the Wadi Sbeyaa of Doughty, in which he places Khormah, Konsolieh and perhaps Baniya, but not apparently Taraba. SADIIC.—A small town of Sedeyr district, about midway on the route between Thomeyrand Horeymelah. SAERA.—Village in Aaredh but close to the Aflaj boundary, on the route from Riadh to Kharfa, about one day’s journey from each. In 1862 numbered 60 houses, some of palm-branches and thatch.20 SAHABAH —Mentioned by Felly as a Bedouin tribe of 200 (? men) pay ing the value of $2,000 a year to the Wahabi government. SAHL.—See under Dereyya. SAHMIAH.—Mentioned by Sad Her as a village south of Dereyya. SAHOOL.—A Bedouin tribe of of mixed descent. Ross mentions 8 sec tions. Felly estimates their number at 600 (? men) and their annual contri bution to the Riadh treasury at $ 8,000. SALEEMIAET.—Large fortified village in Yemama district, once capital of Yemama and residence oi Daas family. It is also called Kharj and so is the district surrounding it. Palgrave makes it, apparently, rather more than a day's march from Riadh. Is this the Sallummiah of Doughty, a good village lying in a valley that comes down from north of Aflai by wav of Howtah to Kharj ? SBEYA.—Tribe of Nejd, both nomad and settled, founders of Aneyzah, Bukerieh, Helalieh and other Kaseem oases. Some are still in Aaredh, their village being Hayer. SEBAA—Bedouin tribe of Nejd, estimated by Felly at 800 (? men) paying the value of $ 6,000 a year to the Wahabi. Are these same as Sbeva above ? J SEDEYR. The north-east district of Nejd, stated by Palgrave to be the largest and by Felly to be one of the most settled and populated. (1) Bounda ries appear to be Nefud on the north ; the district of Was ham on the west; the district of Aaredh (the last town of Sedeyr in this direction being Horeymelah) on the south ; on the east the boundary is indeterminate. (2) Principal towns and villages are Dakhlah, Jelajel, Hafeyrah, Jenubiah, Ghat, Hormah, Yabroon, Hoolah, Majmaa, Oodah, Raudha, Toweym, Thomeyr, Zulfah and Sadik. ( 3 ) The district is a chalky down land with thin grass and thinner tree-clumps, yet containing arable marl and sufficient water in the bottoms of a labyrinth of steep sided valleys. Its streams run but little way above ground before being spent in irrigation or re-absorbed into their calcareous beds; but wells need nowhere be sunk above 12 or 15 feet to tap a copious supply. The plateau rises in general elevation towards the south and its summit is well clad with herbage and abounds in game. The eastern part of the district appears to be plain at a lower level than the rest. Sedeyr seems to be in reality not so mountainous as described by Falgrave, but a rolling country with sparse settlements in its hollows, mostly looking west and south. Felly would apparently make the whole of Sedeyr a plain lying on the east of the Toweik range. (4) Falgrave (in October) found the air cool and bracing. (5) One route from Hail to Riadh traverses the district throughout its length. A route runs from Sedeyr to the Wuriya ^ district (see below) crossing the Dahna for 2 days and the Sumaan for 3, in all 5 days without water. Another route leads direct from Majmaa in Sedeyr to the W T abreh wells, crossing masses of rugged sandstone hills towards its east end. (6)—(7) The inhabitants of Sedeyr are physically superior to those of the other districts of Nejed. There are many old and honourable families among them. The inhabitants are genuine Wahabis but their political attachment to Riadh was not strong in 1862. (8} The district was ruled in 1862^ by a Wahabi governor from Aaredh with his^ seat at Toweym. Formerly it was ruled by an indigenous family whose home was at Majmaa [Sedeyr is said to be diminutive of sidr, name of a tree which is abundant there.] SEDOOS—Small town or group of hamlets, the most northerly in Aaredh, situated apparently in a valley of its own which begins at Horev- m-lah, passes Sedoos, traverses the Mahmel plain (a. v.) and nerhans imL the Wadi Hanifa. Doughty heard that Sedoos was itself in the Wadi Hamfa 10 marches from Aneyza and two from Riadh: dromedaries can do the whole distance in o days, the stages being Wadi Sirr, Shakra, Horeymela, Sedoos and Riadh. Felly says the hamlets are pleasant and neat, jotted down m a valley, round a small fort. Numerous detached date-groves and enclosed5&gt;1 patches of cultivation brighten the neighbourhood. From the suburbs of the fort there is a view westwards across the plain of Mahmel to the loftier ranges of Toweik. Near the fort is a mound formed of the debris of what may have been considerable buildings, and on the mound stands an elegant column of hewn stone, shaft still some 20 feet high and apparently non-Muham madan. (See Sketch with Felly’s report.) A dry torrent-bed divides the valley. The people were civil and quiet, but seemed very poor, and had the dingy unwholesome look which belongs to a manufacturing rathei than an agri cultural population. Cattle were few and in bad condition. There isa beautiful flow of fresh water and numerous wells for irrigation. Sedoos may be describ ed as a valley-oasis. To the east is a plateau 300 feet above Sedoos, strewn with fragments of sandstone and crossed by the route toRiadh: the ascent from Sedoos is narrow but not difficult. By dromedary Sedoos can be reached in 4 days from Aneyza; camels take 10. SEE.—Locality with fresh water springs in district of Kharj. The nearest of the springs is one full day’s march from Etiadh. Here the blood horses of the Wahabi Amir used to be sent for grazing. Is this same as Seyeh below ? SELEYYEL (WADI).—One of the most distant of the Wahabi districts lying to the south-west, 3 days’ journey beyond Wadi Dowasir and 2 days short of Wadi Nejran. Said to be a wretched district full of sandhills and with little water. Felly however assigns to it a population of 4,000, including 500 fighting men, and places the annnal revenue paid to the Wahabis at $ 7,000. SELLA..—Fifth of 8 places on route from Riah to Wadi Bisha. SEYEH.—Good village in a valley that runs from north of Aflaj vid Howtah to Kharj. SHAAB.—Fart of the plateau lying between the Temameh hills on the north-east and the Toweik and Aaredh hills on the south-west. Plateau is called Shaab where the route from Koweit to Riadh crosses it. Further north it takes the name of Batina and immediately below IWeik, in the extreme north it is called Sedeyr. SHAARA.—Desert village on route from Shakra to Mecca; inhabitants are Beni Zeyd. Doughty shows it about 65 miles south-south-west of Shakra. SHAKEYKAH.—Village in Wadi Shakran. SHAKRA.—Capital of the Washam district, stands in a low situation on a plain, completely commanded by two hills. It is 4 camel and 2 dromedary journeys from Aneyza vid Wadi Sirr. Previous to 1818 it was considered the strongest place in the country and in Palgrave’s time it was still the key of central Nejd on the w r est. When Sadlier saw it, it had a good mosque and market place, and the date plantations around the tow n w 7 ere very extensive and plentifully supplied with delicious water from very deep wells. The direct route from Boreyda to Riadh runs through Shakra. Hogarth seems to think that it stands on Wadi Hanifa or one of its affluents and (following Nolde) estimates the inhabitants roughly at 10,000. Doughty notes that the people are Beni Zeyd and Suedda ; he calls the town a good one and places it two dromedary journeys east of Aneyza. North of the town are the Nefudsof Mestewwy and of Wadi es-Sirr and south a Nefud containing spring of Engell. SHAKRAN (WADI).—Ross makes this a district of Nejd containing the villages of Bisha, Shakeykah and Jeneyah, but gives no clue to its situation. SHARAN.—Bedouin tribe of Wadi Bisha. SHEBRAMY.—See Shebrum. To which tribe do these Bedouins belong ? SHEBRUM.—Bottom with acacia trees near head of Wadi Jerrir on route from Aneyza to Mecca. Bedouins here are Shebramy. SHEMASIAH.—Village with 250 inhabitants on south bank of Wadi Rummah, but connected with Boreyda in 1880. SHENANA.—Village of perhaps 200 inhabitants, 5 hours from Khabara and about 25 miles south-west of Aneyza.52 SHUT A.—Desert tract about Afif on route from Aneyza to Mecca. Some say it extends from Rass to Afif. others that it reaches 1 day north-east and 2 days south-west of Afif: some that it is same as Hazzam. QTTTisr atvy —Rass. Is this same as Shenaua preceding . SHUJJER.—An old Tillage nearShakrain Washam. SHOTIB A.—Village in Wadi Dowasir. SHOWYG.-—Village in Wadi Bowasir. SIAH.—Village in Aflaj. SIHH. Last of 8 places on route from Riadh to Wadi Bisha. SIRR (AIEOON-AS).—Halting place with wells, two marches west of Shakra, most of the way lying through red sandhills. In 1819 there was an extensive lake of rain-water here. SIRR (WADI-ES).—Valley in Washam, north of Shakra. It contains springs and the hamlets of Feytha, Rishiy, Torrofiy and Ayn-es-Sweyna, also Owsheyeyn with tw r o garats, vestiges of the Beni Hilal. Doughty says it drains merely into a depression. SITARAH.—Town or village in Aflaj district. SOKHN.—Village on route from Riadh to Mecca. SOLEY (WADI).—A long valley of which one end is near Yabroon in Jebel Athalah and the other between Hareek and Yemama. It has few wells and none but small and unimportant villages. It is not clear in which direction Palgrave thought it sloped. Hogarth seems to connect it with the Hanifa system, and if he is right it would fall from north to south. SOLEYIL.—Village in Wadi Dowasir. SOODAN —Pelly found some tents of this tribe near the Wabreh _ wells. According to the same authority they are subordinate to or connected with the Ojrnan and have their summer quarters in Sumaan ; they rarely visit the Wahabi capital, hut wander on the sea-shore. 8UBEYAA.—Nejd tribe, Adnanic, of whom Ross mentions 11 sub-divisions. Is this same as Sbeya above ? SXJEDDA.—Tribe composing part of population of Shakra : Kahtanic. SULABA.—See Selaib, section II, sub-section E. SULEY L.—Second of 8 places on route from Riadh to Wadi Bisha. SUMAAN.—District lying immediately east of the Dahna and extending further north than the Dahna : under the name of Hajar in the north, where it is covered with boulders, some of them large and black, it is said to extend to Suk-esh-Shuyukh. Southw ards it extends at least as far as the direct route from Riadh to Hofhuf. Sumaan is entered (on the route from Koweit to Riadh) from the Wuriya district and is at first a region of confused earth and low flat-topped sandstone hills with intermediate scourings from the winter rainwater. The valleys are winding and flat, brightened here and there in spring by some grass, wild flowers and brushwood. The hills become higher and more entangled further on. Here are the celebrated wells, cross-roads and camping-ground of Wabreh. Beyond Wabreh the Sumaan again becomes more open; the hills being less confused, and the valleys broader, and flat- bottomed, lying generally, in winding fashion, about north and south. The side hills become low, flat-topped, and frequently ribanded near their bases with brick colour. In some instances, where the hills are conical, the summits of the cones are brick-colour, 'then follows a barren and glaring tract, after which is entered a second ramification of valleys, but the aspect of the country is now milder. Next the ground becomes more broken and confused, with patches of green grass and brushwood and, finally, in a distance of about 8 hours, the country opens out into plains and the hills subside into gentle undulations of sandstone and sandstone flakes. The total breadth of the Sumaan on the Koweit- Wabreh-Riadh route is 3 marches or nearly SO miles. Where the route bet ween Riadb and Hofhuf crosses it, about 14i0 miles further to the south-east, it presents cliffs 50 to 100 feet high on the side next the Nefud. In the middle,23 hereabouts the surface consists of hare, unbroken, horizon-bounded downs, strevvn with gravel and small broken stones, affording no fodder for camels nor material for fuel. In spring there are a good many wild flowers m Sumaan and also wild parslev. Sour sorrel, said to have been introduced by the lurks grows plentifully. The common brushwood of the country is a kind of wild myrtle. SUIUJMDAH or SURMUDDAII.—Village parsed by Sadlier about 1 march south-east of Shakra on way from Dereyya. There wore somc .nha ),- tants, in spite of the walls having been recently razed by the Turks, and the dale groves were visible from a great distance. There was considerable culti vation in the neighbourhood and several wells, but the water was not good. Is this identical with Thormada below ? SWEYNA (AIN-ES).—Small village in Wadi Sirr. TAME YU. —See Thomeyr. TAMMEEiRA.—Village in Wadi Downsir. TAUABA. Village in the Whdi Sahey. Is this not the same ^as the Taraha of Brydges, a place of the Bakoom tribe, 'here the Southern Wahabis concentrated against the Turks? Is it not also the Turraba of Doughty, situated on the south side of Jebel liatthon ? TARABA (WADI).—A valley containing Bakoom Bedouins and villages which beginning near Taraba, runs down to Erk not far from Shakra in Washam. There,* after rain, its waters form a standing lake beside which the Bedouins encamp. TEMAMEII Range of hills running north-west and south-east, forming the western boundary of the Ormah plain and the watershed between it and the Shaab plain. Altitude is less than 1,000 feet above adjacent Ormah plain. Ihe road from Ormah to Sedoos leads through a remarkable gap in this range. THALITH (WADI).—District of Nejd containing village of Masel. No clue to its locality, etc. THERRIEH.—Village, about TO miles south-west of Aneyza, through which caravans from Aneyza to Mecca sometimes pass. It is a few miles south of Miskeh and has less than 50 houses and no palms, but grows corn. Inhabitants are mixed Kusman, Bedouins and negroes. THEYDICH.—Place one march from Horeymela on route to Shakra. THOMEYB.—Straggling and dilapidated township on route from Majmaa to Horeymela, one march south of Toweym, THOREYE.—Mentioned by Ross as a town or village of Aaredh. THOBEYIII.—Village in Jebel Shaba, west of Therrieh, with same mixed population. THORMADA.—Called by Doughty Thermidda. A populous town in Washam district, one march *from Shakra. Is this the same as Surumdah above ? TIYEH (EMM).—See Bass. TOEYM.—Hamlet to north-west of Shakra. TORROEY.—Hamlet in Wadi Sirr. TOWEIK (JEBEL).—The precise application of this name is doubtful and disputed, but it includes at least the most elevated portions of Nejd. Pelly alone mentions 3 uses of the term, (i) To describe the higher and more westerly ranges of the hills which extend south from Zulfah to Howtah and thence east (?) to Kharj; these, says Pelly, constitute Toweik proper, (ii) To indicate, besides the higher ranges already mentioned, all the hill land west ward and southward of the Wadi Hanifa, comprising the lower ranges down to the edge of the 'Wadi; in this sense the eastern boundary of Toweikis, accordin'; to Pelly, first tl.e Wadi Hanita, north of that the plain of Mah- mel and still further north the Sedeyr district, (ui) As the name of the whole hilly country of Nejd from Howtah round hy IChare], Riadh, Shaah and so up to Zulfah, Kaseem and Washam; so considered Aredh is asubdivison of Toweik, and Toweik, is synonymous with Nejd or the highlands of Central Arabia. Pelly leaves the western limits of loweik entirely undefined^ Pal- grave calls Jebel Toweik a wide and flat plain or rather plateau lying in the form of a crescent and appears to consider that the districts of bedej r, Aaredh and Washam are situated upon Toweik and forrn respectively its north*east, central and south-west segments, the last being continued between the Wadi Dowasir on the south and the pilgrim route from Nejd on the north, Kaseem, according to Pal grave, is no part of Toweik but is enclosed in the hollow of its crescent. (His map, however, places Whskam where his book locates Kaseem). The following particulars also are taken from Pal grave’s account. Average elevation is 1,000 to 2,000 feet above the plain and not more than 3,000 ''above the sea. Loftiest ledges are in Sedeyr ; centre and south-west are lower. Mostly calcareous formation, but to oast and south are peaks of granite. (Doughty mentions, but does not locate, a lava field called Hairat-al-Saudeh in Jebel Toweik). The extreme verge is generally abrupt and takes a bold rise of 500 or 600 feet in chalky cliffs from the plain ; above this is a table land followed by a second step upwards of 300 or 100 feet and occasionally by a third. High grounds have good pasture, which lasts through the year, but the greater the”elevation the less the fertility and the drier the soil. There are a few sidr, markh and talk trees ; water apparently scarce. Plateau is intersected by maze of valleys, in which are concentrated all population and fertility of Nejd; almost all.have steep and some have precipitous banks. The slope of most of these valleys is from east to west. Toweik water is seldom brackish but often tastes of iron. Iron and copper occur. Climate of north part of range in Sedeyr is extremely healthy, atmosphere dry and people distinguished by ruddy complexion and good physique. Towards the southern and lower end the air is more relaxing and the people more slender and sallow. Palgrave speaks of the last ridge of Toweik on the east descending suddenly into the I)ahna, from which it is clear that his Toweik corresponds with the widest of Pelly’s definitions. Pelly prefers to call all the hills east of Wadi Hanifa the hills of Aaredh [ Toweik is taken by Palgrave to be the diminutive of towk, a “garland” or “twist”; and to refer to the complicated structure of the range.] TOWEYM.—Large town in Sedeyr district on route between Majmaa and Horeymela, 1 march south of former and 2 marches north of latter. Palgrave 'reckoned 12,000 to 15,000 inhabitants. Not well irrigated and stands very high, being on 2nd step of Toweik plateau. In 1862 Toweym was capital of district and seat of Wahabi governor. Houses were compactly built, gene rally in two storeys, sometimes in three, streets were mere lanes, market-place unusually large and situated near circumference instead of in middle of town. Gates were guarded by day and closed by night ; walls were in tolerably good repair and surrounded with a deep outer trench destitute of water. EH DAS —Wells in a wide gravelly plain dotted with barren mouldering hills, 2 marches south-west of Pass on route to Medina. EKLIB (BENI).—Bedouin tribe in Wadi Bisha. VITAILAN.—Plateau about 6 hours east of the plain of Ormah on the route from Itiadh to Hofhuf, from which the Nefud is visible. The country is open with a series of shallow depressions. WABREH.—Halting place in a valley in the Sumaan. It is a main central camping-ground for the tribes on their way to and from the coast. There are upwards of 100 wells within a space of about 400 yards square; but only a few were in good repair in 1865. The wells are cut *3 or 4 fathom deep through sandstone rock. M &gt;ny roads converge here, including a route from Majmaa and a direct route from Riadh. There were remains of a small hill fort near the place in 1865.25 WADI.—Village with population of 500 on the right bank of Wadi Rummah about 5 miles north of Aneyza. Inhabitants are cultivators of Aneyza who look after the date plantations of the Wadi: in the off-season many of them live in the town. Water hereabouts is only 6 feet below the surface. WASH AM—The westernmost district of Nejd, except Kaseem, with an estimated population of 8,000, fighting strength of 400 and revenue of $ 12,000 in i865, Principal places are Shakra (the capital), Dhorama, Paraah, Hareek, Marat, Wasbeykar, Owsbeyfy and Thormada. Doughty mentions also Shujjer, Otheythia, Geryen, Kassab, Herreyik, Jereyfa, Osheyj- jir and Toeym. Palgrave says the people are quiet and unwarlike, the com mercial spirit predominating; but they were in 1862 Wahabis. Best Bombay Arab horses used (1878) to come from Shakra in Was ham. Doughty says Washam is a plain country, thus making it probable that Palgrave’s mnp is more correct than his book (see under Jebel Toweik). The Morrah, Kahtan and other Bedouins of the south wander as far north as Washam in summer. Does Washam drain to the Wadi Rummah or to Wadi Hanifa ? WASHEYKAR.—Town or village in district of Washam. WASIT.—Small village and oasis about midway between Boreyda and Majmaa, about 2 marches north-east of the former and 1 march south-west of Zulfah. It is surrounded by Nefud and stands on the borders of Kaseem, Sedeyr and Washam without belonging to any one of them. There are melons and dates, but inferior to those of Kaseem. Name refers to central position of village with reference to 3 districts. WATTAR—Deepish, well defined valley in Aaredh district. It cuts transversely for a distance of about 7 hours’ march through what Pelly calls the Aaredh hills, connecting the Shaab plain with Sedoos and thence leading down into Mahmel. Range pierced thus is highest at about 5 hours from east end of valley and same point is also watershed between Shaab and Sedoos. About 3 hours’ from east end is running stream with small patch of cultivation, some date trees and small fort, all of these being the first of their kind passed on the route from Koweit to Sedoos. In places the scarps of the valley lay bare horizontal strata of sandstone. WURIYA,—District lying on the north-east side of the Sumaan on the route from Koweit to Riadh. It is separated from the district of Shuo- further to the north by the sandhills of Redaif. Wuriya is a sort of thresh^ hold to Sumaan, that is to say, the ground gradually becomes more broken up into patches than it is further north and strewed with pebbles and mounds of earth and sandstone. YABROON.—Town in Jebel Atbala in Sedeyr district, once of import ance but now dwindled to a mere village. An occasional fair is held here and the place marks the northern intersection of Wadi Soley and Jebel Toweik Is this the same as Djebreen above ? YEM AM A.—Apparently the most southerly district of Nejd, treated bv Pelly and Ross as including Kharj and Hareek. Population in 1863 was 6 000 revenue $ 30,000 and there were no fighting men. In 1862 Yemama minus Hareek was essentially Wahabi and devoted to the ruling family, but fanati cism was not so strong as in Aaredh. Hareek was less loyal to the Wahabi princes, but had been partially gained over by them. Prom Pelly it would seem that there is a town of Yeraama as well as a district, and that it is situated in Kharj, and that Kharj (? without Hareek) is also spoken of as Yemama The ancient district of Yemama is said to have included Uasa under the latter's old name of Hapar. There are said to be running streams in Yemama and a “Sierra of Yemama ’* is mentioned. Manfooha once belonged to Yemama. Ross o-ives the chief towns and villages as Dalam, Naajan, Saleemiah, Zameykhah, Hareek Halwab, Howtah and Naam. On present data it is impossible to fix the rela tive significations of the terms Yemama, Hareek and Kharj. YEMANA.—Good village in a valley which runs from north of Aflai via Howtah to Kharj. Is Yemama town meant ? hPVH9VI 26 ZAMEYKHAH.—Town or village of Yemama district. ZAMIL (AARAB).—Poor Muteyr and Ateyba tribesmen, united under the protection of Zamil, Amir of Aneyza, were so called in 1878. They kept sbeep and goats of their own in the Nefud and acted as herdsmen of the well and caravan camel of the oasis-dwellers. Similarly the townsmen of Aneyza were then called Zuamil from the name of their Amir. ^ ZEYD (BENI).—Tribe composing part of population of Shakra (Kali- tanic). These are also found at Shaara, Doadamy and Goayieh. They are taunted with being of Sulabi descent. ZIGHREYBIAH.—Place with corn cultivation on or near Wadi Rummah about 10 hours from Aneyza, direction uncertain. ZUAMIL.—See Zamil. ZULEAH.—Town in Sedeyr district, near the north extremity ofJebel Toweik, but situated in the plain. In 1862 Zulfah did not belong to either Kaseem, Washam or Sedeyr, but was Wahabi in sympathy and under Wahabi government. Lighting men at that time were 600. It is depot of southern trade from Sedeyr, Aaredh and Washam and inhabitants are merchants and travellers, going as far abroad as Basra and Koweit. Town is key of central Nejd from north. It is a principal halting place for pilgrim cararavans from Basra to Mecca. There is a direct route from Zulfah to Legait (see section 1L subsection E),B- Central Arabia, North of Wadi Rummah. NOTES. The chief authorities for this sub-section are the following; those which contain useful maps are indicated by an asterisk 1. Niebuhr’s “Description de 1’Arable,” 1774, page 297. 2. Burckbardt’s “Notes on Bedouins and Wahabys” 1833, \olume II. 3. Ritter’s “Die Erdkunde,” 1846, Volume XIII, pages 333-44-8. 4. Chesney’s “ Expedition for the Survey of the Rivers Euphrates and Tigris, 1850, Volume I, pages, 627—8, . „ . * 5 . Wallin’s “ Notes taken on a Journey through Part of Northern Arabia, in the Journal of the Royal Geographical Society, 1851. pages 330-339, *6. Wallin’s “ Narrative of a Journey from Cairo to Medina and Mecca, by Suez, Araba, Tawila, A1 Jauf, Jubbe, Hail and Nejd in 1845,” in the journal of the Royal Geo graphical Society, 1854, pages 136-207. 7. Palgrave’s “Notes on a Journey through the Interior of Arabia,” in the Proceedings of the Royaf Geographical Society, 1863-64, pages 63-64. *8. Palgrave’s “ Observations made in Central, Eastern and Southern Arabia, in the Journal of the Royal Geographical Society, 1864, pages 113-125. * 9. Palgrave’s “ Narrative of a Year’s Journey through Central and Eastern Arabia,” 1865, Volume I, pages 21—238. * 10 . Guarmani’s “Itineraire de Jerusalem au Neged Septentrional,” in the Bulletin de la Societe de Geographic, 1865, pages 201-291, 365-423 and 486-515. 11. Ross’s “ Memoir on Nejd,” with 3 Appendices, in the Persian Gulf Administration Report, 1879-80, pages 5-6. *12. W. S. Blunt’s “ Visit to Jebel Shammar,” in the Proceedings of the Royal Geo graphical Society, 1880, pages 81—-102. *13. Lady A. Blunt’s “Pilgrimage to Nejd,” 1881, Volume I, pages 84—273 and Volume II, pages 1—95. *14. Doughty’s “Travels in North-West Arabia and Nejd,” in the Proceedings of the Royal Geographical Society, 1884, pages 386-390. * 15 . Huber’s “Voyage dans 1’Arabie Centrale, 1878-82,” ft Societe de Geographies 1884, pages 317-363 and 4 &gt;8—514; 1885, pages 92—125 and 139-148. *16. Doughty’s “Travels in Arabia Deserta,” 1888, Volume I, pages 284—300 and 520-566 and Volume II, pages 1—76 and 227—330. *17. Huber’s “Journal d’un Voyage en Arabia, 1883-84 ”, 1891, pages 42—316 and 488—735. Contains a valuable Atlas. 18. Curzon’s “Persia” 1892, Volume II, pages 461-2. 19. Nolde’s “Reise nach Innerarabien ”, 1895, pages 8—77. 20. Zwemer’s “Arabia”, 1900, pages 151-2. 21. Forder’s “ With the Arabs in Tent and Town,” 1902, pages 121-167. *22. Hogarth’s “Penetration of Arabia”, 1904, pages 242-294. 23. Government Records, Bushire Residency Diaries and Persian Gulf Administration Reports.of Hail, 100 yards wide at the mouth hut contracting to 26 or 30. The hills which surround it are inaccessible from the outside. In this system of valleys are included 10 small villages, Kena, Weibar, Anabeita, Saka, Hasna, Maa, Ghedhian, Haiet, Remidh and Alia. Altogether there are about 950 inhabitants, but some are only there in the date season. Elevation is 280 feet above Hail. Akda is one of the oldest possessions of the Ibn Kashid family and is looked upon by them as an asylum in case of a Turkish invasion A wall 10 feet high and 3 feet thick, with an opening 6 feet wide at its south end, bars the approach through the gorge. The various valleys are overhung by naked granite crags. An arsenal of the Amir was in 1880 in the village of Haiet and the palms of that village were his private property. The valleys have granite floors covered with 12 to 15 feet of gravel, which retains the w T ater and makes it unnecessary to water the palms from wells. There are said to be 70,000 palms of which about | belonged in 1880 to the Amir, § to the fixed inhabitants and the remainder to Shammar Bedouins; the owners of the last camp beside them from May to September^ some of the family remaining in the desert with the flocks and herds. This mountain bay looks east and is very hot in summer. Guarmani makes the place 1J hours from Hail and gives it 400 inhabitants. AKEILA.—Small village with 16 inhabitants, 1£ hours south-south-west of Kaf, stands on elevated ground among marshes. Huber casts doubt on the existence of this village, mentioned by Guarmani. ALAJ.—See Jan A amir. ALEIDAN.—A division of the Wilad Ali. They had in 1863 about 150 horsemen and 2,500 musketeers on dromedaries and inhabited the valleys be tween Teima and Kheybar. They are divided into Eukara and Toala. ALIA.—See Akda. ALI (BENI).— A division of the Mosruh section of the Harb (q.v.). Though accounted kafirs they are often very religious. Some of them pitch their tents in a circle and keep their animals in the middle, which is un usual among Bedouins of Central Arabia. ALI (WILAD).— A division of the Beni Wahab, living in the south of the Nefud, east of Teima. Doughty estimates £ of them, or 1,600, to be under Hail. He divides those in the south into these fendies : Toala (the most nu merous), Allay da (fendy of the Sheikhs), Thueyba, Taifat, Umshitta, Mraikhan, Jabbara, Erbevlat and Khalid. Huber makes them Lidian, Mesaad, Sened, Mereikhan, Rekab, Ateifat, Mesetah, Teluh, Khalid, Rebeilat, Demjan, Tooalaah, Meshref, Kheil, Dhooeyba, and Sheraabah. ALTAMIAH.—Hamlet with cultivation 6 miles north-west of Shemasiak only 10 inhabitants. ALA.—According to Doughty, a good village in the Amir of HaiTs dominions. AM ARB AT.—Section of the Anezah adjoining the Shammar in the neigh bourhood of Mahamiyeh and Batn. ANABEITAH.—See Akda. ANEZAH.— Great Bedouin tribe. (1) Called Wailyin, as descended from Wail. Adnanic. Original seat was a little north of Mecca between W r adis Bummah and Humth. (2) Main divisions in the south appear to be Eukara, Wilad Ali, Wilad Suleiman and Bishr, but Huber gives Beni Wahab as a main division including Eukara and Wilad Ali. In the north are Jellas (or Kalas?) and Ruwalla. Wallin seems to regard Kalas and Ruwalla as one, and mentions sub-sections called Naif and Shaalan, which live in Hauran but visit neighbourhood of Jauf Aamir and Shatik to pasture their herds of light-grey camels: they even go as far south as Kaseem. Doughty mentions a Moahib section, partly or wholly domiciled among the Billis ; also an Ibn Mujallad section in Kaseem. (3) Doughty estimates the whole tribe at 25,000 souls and the area of their dir a at 15,000 square miles, stretching from Medina to North Syria. Bedouins round Teima C905FD II80 are mostly Anessah. Klieybar is patrimony of Anezali tribe and they own date plantations there. Southern Anezah collect at Kheyhar during date Felly estimated Aneyza in Central Arabia at only 600 (. male adults). (4) Features of northern Anezali are Syrian, frequently Jewish.. ou neza i ar worst-natured of all tribes except Kahtan. (5), (6j Anezah tents are high and wife’s apartment is on (? proper) left. (7) Some Anezah families associate them- selves with Heteym, but do not intermarry with them. (8) (9) f ^ ? ot ’ like many tribes of Central Arabia, set up cross covered with red cloth before tent-door where circumcision is taking place. (10) (11) (l 2 ) Aneza ^ were constant enemies of Amir of Hail, in 1865 they paid 4,000 a yeai, chiefly in kind, to the Wahabi Amir. Shammar respect Anezah, though gene* rally their enemies, as next to themselves in nobility of descent and character. ARBYIYYAH (KASR).— Ruined village with palm-plantation and corn cultivation, less than two miles north of Jehel Samra. It is part of old Hail. ARKAB (TIMM).—See Samra. ARMAL.—Section of Shammar inhabiting Juhbeh and Kena villages. ARNEN (JEBEL).—Range which, commencing at east end of Sahl Beni Helal runs north-east, then east, then south-east, and joins IVlisma, enclosing with it an amphitheatre called bein-el-Karnein, and overlooking the gieat plain of Ghebal from the north. Apparently same as Doughty’s Irnan, which is sandstone ridge with wild goats. ASEFAT.—See Esheka. ASEEEBY.—See Esheka. ASHERAWAT (KASR EL.) or KASR.—Village about 8 hours south west of Kefar. Population 250 to 300 persons. Wells said to he 180 feet deep. Inhabitants are Beni Temim. ASHIB.—See Jauf. ASKHA.—Village mentioned by Palgrave as near Boreyda. Is this same as Esheka ? ATEIFAT.—See Wilad Ali. ATIER.—Village, two hours south-south-west of Jauf. ATREFIAH.—Village, ^ way between Ain Ibn Feyd and Boreyda, for merly prosperous with fine old palm-erove, but ruined by the drying up of most of the wells about 1876. In 1880 it was reduced to 60 inhabitants. Only one well of drinkable water remained. Inhabitants lived by selling firewood and melons at Boreyda. ATWA.—Well 300 feet deep In Nefud on eastern route from Hail to Najaf. It is 28 hours north-east of Hail. AUF.—Section of Harb tribe; reputed robbers, especially of pilgrims; in reality only one of their subdivisions, the Lahebba, are predatory. AWAJI.—Leading sub-division of the Bishr. Their dim extends from south of the Nefud to Kaseem. Doughty describes them as somewhat violent- dealing and always inhospitable. AYUN.—Town or large-village. (1) Situated iu Northern Kaseem about 10 hours south-east of Kuwara and 7 hours north-west of Boreyda. (2) It lies in a depression in a southern hay of the sandstone hills, Jebel Sara. Length is nearly three miles and breadth f to 1 mile. Palms are among best in Kaseem. One hour west of Ayun in same basin is great palm-grove of Ghaf, which it takes 25 mi nutes to traverse at a trot. On the west of the place is an enormous and growing sanddune,kept hack by a mud-wall of which theheight must constantly be increas ed. (3) In 1862 there was a strong and large fort and in 1880 two lofty watch- towers. (4) Population has been variously estimated, 10,000 (Palgrave), 400 to 500 (Doughty), 2,500 (Huber). Huber says Ayun is the most populous place between Hail and Boreyda. (5) Inhabitants are Missennid of Shammar descent.31 They are small, ugly and thin with hollow eyes and projecting cheekbones. They wear red kefiah without akal, like Wahabis. (6) Water is very abundant and drinkable, but not always very good. (8) (9) 10). The place was in 1878 and 1880 dependent on Boreyda. Routes from Holy Cities on east and Jebel Shammar on north meet here. There are Himyaritic inscriptions on the rooks at the entrance of the Ayun basin on the north-west side. BAH I RAT.— Village mentioned by Guarmani, as dependant on Jauf and situated in same valley of an hour north-north-west of Khadhma. BAITHA NETHIL.—Great watering-place, disputed between Bishr and Shammar tribes, about 80 miles south-west of Hail on one route to Kheybar; water is brackish. BATIN.—See Wadi Rummah. BATEEN.—Plain in which Hail stands, between the range of Ajja and Selma. BATN.—Depression surrounded by cliffs about half way from Hail to Najaf. It is a full day’s journey in extent from south to north and is neutral ground between the Shammar and Anezah. Huber’s account is difficult to compare with Lady Blunt’s; but from it the inference may be drawn that Batn is bounded on the north (?) by a scarp 150 feet high, difficult of ascent from the south and called Jal-el-Batn. This scarp is said to run for 100 miles north west and south-east ; ^ of it being west of Derb Zobeideh and rest east. BEDAN.—Or Bedieh. Village inhabited by 400 Shammar. It lies 5 hours west-north-west of Mukak. BEJAIDA on BEJAIJA.—Sub-tribe of Bishr. BEKAA.—Very ancient town, a halting-place of the Persian Haj, 80 miles east-norih-east of Hail. Guarmani makes population 1,000, Huber 400. Site is picturesque, in an immense basin of whitish sandstone. Village is divided into two groups of dwellings, Seheby ou the east and Weimy on the west. Between is a very small but ancient hamlet formerly called Hammam or Mereikeh, now Sher- ky. Near by is a small village called Keseifa, without palms, and a little fur ther off one called Kueian. Middle of basin is covered with thick layer of a very bitter salt. Water, generally bad and brackish, is found at 24 to 30 feet (Lady Blunt says 45) ; level does not vary. Only well yielding passable water is one in Weimy called Samhah; the water is bluish and milky. Seheby and Weimy have each large kasr built of stone blocks and mortar without lime ; there are towers at the angles. Dwellings within are wretched. Palms are fine and produce a good kind of date; com and barley are planted every year. Lady Blunt estimates the circuit of the palm groves at 4 or 5 miles and says name of town had been recently changed, at the time of her visit, to Tayhetism. BELLEZIEH.— Small corn settlement without palms, lying about 15 miles south of the south end of Jebel Selma. BENHANIAH.—Village situated in the triangle formed by Aneyza* Boreyda and Raudha. BENIEH.*—High and extensive plain of fine sand with protruding rocks, forming the commencement of the Nefud and the first barrier on the route from Jauf to Hail. BERZAN.—See Eeyd and Hail. BIDDA.—Small but permanent village somewhere in the Hail princi pality, with palm trees. BISHR.—A leading division of the Aneyza. (2) Leading sub-division is Awaji; there are others called Wilad Sleyman and Bejaida. Doughty names 13 fendies. (3) Of this tribe about 3,000 are subject to Hail. They extend from the south border of the Nefud to Kaseem, on the south-west of the Shammar. Baitba Nethil is in their country and is disputed with the Shammar. They are among the32 Aneyza owners of Kheybar, one of the three Tillages there being named after them Jeriat Bishr. The pasture of their dir a is good, but abundant water is rare and at a deep leyel. (4) The nomad portion are robust and resemble northern Bedouins; these have their clothes from Irak and wear a worsted headbad, fold upon fold like a turban. The tribe are renowned raiders, (o), (6), (7) borne are Ageylies in Turkish provinces. (8) (11) (12) In 1863 they were consistent pnpmips of Hail. BOREYDA.—Town. (1) Situated in Nefud of Kaseem, on left bank of Wadi Rummah, 10 or 11 miles north or north-east of Aneyza. (2) Nefud sand round Boreyda is not deep, but appears to be gradually increasing from the west. Underneath is a bluish white clay, a sedimentary deposit, and m some places three strata of sandstone from three to six feet thick are encountered within 30 feet of the ground surface. Palm-groves and cultivation all lie on side ol town next Wadi Rummah. On north (?) side is a dark wood of ethel trees on a high sand dune. Palgrave describes the outline of the town as an oval. “ 18 0 clay, and two-storeyed houses are not uncommon. Elevation about 2,500 leet. (3) Defences consist of clay-walls containing chopped, straw. Huber says they are 12 feet high and have square and round turrets at intervals rising 6 feet hi 'he r than the walls. Doughty says walls are only 2 feet thick and were built in^lSTS. There is a spacious but low fort and high watch-tower in north-east quarter. (4) Huber estimated population at 10,000 ; Doughty at less than 5,000, or with suburbs at 6,000. (5) Eormer authority makes people Anezah, latter says Beni Temim. There are many Gtalla slaves, especially in following of Amir. (6) Great commercial centre, but activity is at its height only during 4 months which follow date-harvest. Nomads then resort here to buy dates, corn, rice and cloth and sometimes 1,000 of their tents are pitched outside the walls. At other times of the year f of the shops are shut. Boreyda is celebrated for its horse market. Horses come mostly from the Muteyr and animals are more numerous than in the Aneyzah market, but not so good. There are richer men here than at Hail. There are many prosperous camel masters who carry corn in Mesopo tamia, bring clothes and term to Nejd and take ghi to Mecca and in some years dates and corn to Medina. (7) Water is dull and brackish. Huber makes wells 15 to 30 feet deep ; Doughty 42 to 48 feet. The wells are lined with dry masonry. Water level rises after floods in Wadi Rummah. (b) There are 4 schools and 6 mosques, including the Jamia which has a high square minaret. (9) (10) The town was originally called Shamas and stood 2 miles further north. It is a great civil township, more advanced than Hail in having saleswomen and cookshops. It is semi-independent (1880) of Jebel Shammar. Dependent villages are Ayun, Khabara and Hass; also Bukerieh and Helalieh pay ^ pro duce as tribute, corn by measure and dates by weight. There are no subject Bedouins. BUKERIEH.—Oasis village, with palms and high watchtower, about 30 miles south-west of Boreyda and 12 miles north of Khabara. People are well to do camel owners who trade to the Bedouins. They pay tribute (1878) to Boreyda. DAEIR.—Bedouin tribe, hostile to Amir of Jebel Shammar (1863) and infesting the district between Jauf and Jubbeh; found also on the eastern confines of the Nefud about Lina. In Guarmani’s time they w'ere divided into Said, Areif, Ab Edraa, Naalim, Eeluh and Messamir ; had 1800 horsemen and 3,000 musketeers ; and occupied northern borders of Jebel Shammar, between the Shammar, and the Bishr, from Suk-esh-Shuyukh to near Sekaka. Are those same as Doughty’s Thuffir, friendly tribe sometimes at Hail, but settled towards Shekh-ash-Slmyukh and Zobeir in Turkish Arabia ? DAHNA.—According to Wallin, the main stock of the Nefud extending between Jauf and the Persian Gulf. See sub-section A. DAKKY.—Portion of the Nefud, forming a plain that extends 5 hours north-north-east from Jadhamiya and is bounded on the north-east by Jebel Keisy. DAT.—Village on borders of Kaseem, a few hours east or north-east of Aneyza.33 DELHEMI.1T. See Jauf. The Shammari Governor has a strong fort here (1880). DELLAMIEH.—Halting place with water between Rass and Jebel Sak. DEMJAN.—See Wilad All. DERBEH (WADI-ED).— Village dependent on Jauf, in the sarae valley 25 minutes’ distance north of Khadhma. At foot of solitary conical bill called Sabba, north-east of Marid. Inhabitants vTere (184o) 8 families of Derbeh and Menahi. HJAAFAR.— According to Palgrave, a branch of the Skammar. DJOON.— Village of 20 or 30 houses, most westerly appendage of Jauf. DORR AH.—Village near Jauf on road to Sekakah. DRAAE A granite range, more or less connecting Jebel Selma on the north-east with the Harrah on the south-west. Its summits are 10 hours east-south east of Jebel Misma. DRELHA.— Tribe met with by Huber at Hail and in camp 5 hours west of Abbassiek. DUIRAH.—Village, a short distance west or south-west of Boreyda. DZUWEIBA.—See Wilad Ali. EKDER. Village mentioned by Guarmani as dromedary hours east by south of Kaf, separated from it by hills and having 150 inhabitants. Huber casts doubt on its existence. ENKA (JEBEL). —Range, separating Haulat on west from Sahl Beni Helal on east and enclosing latter on its south-west side. ERBAH.—Ruined village with springs, near sandstone hills, a few miles south-east of Teiina. ESHEK A.— Village of Northern Kaseem about 7 miles north-west of Borey da, situated in a depression 9 miles long. It has 200 houses and about 1,000 inhabitants. Water level is at 12 to 18 feet below surface, hut in 1880 supply was diminishing and was undrinkable except in 4 hamlets. Besides main village there are six hamlets named Rafiya, Itari, Gua, Asefat, Asefeby and Khab. ETERA or ITHERI.—Small oasis and stone-built village, in Wadi Sirhan 6 miles or 2 hours east-south-east of Kaf, and divided from it by hills. There is spring and one grove of 400 palms. Huber makes houses 20 and population 100, Guarmani 300. Water only 8 feet below surface. ETHNAN (HARRAT).—Name of a lava-field about } of the way from Kheybar to Hail and forming the north-east third of Harrat Kheybar. It is in Noamsy Heteym country and has a volcanic peak, Jebel Ethnan, from which steam is said still to issue. EYD—According to Palgrave a branch of the Shammar. EURN.—See Hark. EEJIR.—See Eukara. EELUH.—Portion of the Nefud lying between Mujian on the north and Aalem-es-Saad on the south. The crossing occupies 3 hours. This is the worst part of the Nefud, consisting of valleys and scarped hills; it is difficult to pre serve the true direction and the work is very tiring. There are numerous deep fnljes. EERADESSA.—See Heteym. EETET (JEBEL).—Isolated chain of granite hills 16 miles south-east of Hail, but only extending 20 miles north and south. R,oad from Hail to Eeyd crosses it at a point where there is a small spring called Aduah. EEYD.—Small town (in former times large and famous and a station on the Darh-al-Haj from Kufa), about 55 miles east-south-east of Hail and some 6 C 905 FD JMIHIHBHjl 34 miles east of northern end of Jebel Selma. All travellers between Jebel Sham- mar and Kaseem pass through Feyd. Huber gives population as only 2fi0 persons, against Wallin’s 150 families. About ^ are Beni Temim. It stands partly on a sandy hillock 60 or 70 feet high in a wide valley, and partly in the valley. Feyd consists of the village properly so called (only a few houses) and of the following hamlets, which are scattered over a distance of 2 or 3 miles : Ain, Hamra, Abu Shakerah, Seneien, Ghezeizeh, Hueimel, Ghatar, Maleik and Berzan. All these have palm-groves and scattered among them are about 10 •wells. Desert around Feyd is called Aba-ehKrush. Feyd stands upon sand 15 to 30 feet thick under which are about 6 feet of- very hard black basalt. Beneath the basalt is very good water but it was diminishing in 1880. Sand stone appears at intervals immediately east of Feyd, and about 600 yards south of hamlet of Ain is a hill of black lava with ruins called Kherash. A few miles south-west of the town is Jebel Kefail, about 200 feet high, the remains of an ancient crater. FITTIJ (JEBEL).—Low broken line of hills by which Sahilat-el-Kham- mashieh is bounded on east-two leagues east of Hail. FUAR A.—Watering place near Wadi Rummah, one march east of Semira. There are wells and spring, cornfields and Aasr of a Mustajidda villager. Here the Beni Ali are taxed by agents of the Amir of Jebel Shammar. FUEYLIK.—A great plain, open in all directions, and free from hills and hillocks. It lies east of Kaseem and south of Jebel Sara and its extent is about 30 miles. FUKARA.—(Singular, Fejir). Bedouin tribe. (1) Doughty and Huber agree in stating that they with the WYlad Ali form the Beni Wahab branch of the Anezah. Guarmani makes them a section of the Aleidan and the Aleidan a subdivision of the Wilad Ali. It seems that the name Fukara, originally ap plied only to a small sept of the tribe now so called; this may in part account for the confusion. (2) Huber divides the Fukara into 9 sections ; Mebarek, Miefekah, Hejur, Lhemaalah, Sohban, JVteghasib, Feraain, Hueikem and Jemaat. Doughty gives 8 divisions of which only 8 correspond with Huber’s • Salih, Moghassib, Zuara, Hamdan, Hejur, Ainat, Sgoor and Khamala, the last being a plebeian fendy which has grown to be almost ^ the tribe. (3) The Fukara are the furthest north of the Ahl Jibli or Southern Bedouins. Their dira lies between Teima on north andMedain Salih on south and extends as far east as Kheybar and Jebel Birrd. Part of it lies west of Syrian pilgrim route Fukara have 200 tents and are about 800 souls. (4) (5) Somewhat fanatical in religion. (6) Ihey live partly on dates, and the Sheikhs have mud houses at Kheybar. They eat hedgehog and fox and their w r omen go unveiled, (7) They live in Bedouin manner. Doughty estimated capital value of their cattle tents and whole property at £17,000. Fukara make querns of sandstone’which they sell m the autumn fair at Kheybar. (9) Fukara lisp the terminal conso nants. (9)~(1J)(12). In 1878 whole tribe had submitted to Amir of Hail and paid althogether 8400 (? per annum) at rate of 1 crown per 5 camels or 30 cattle. Ihey were on bad terms with Moahib who in contempt called them Fuggera. GARAL.—Beni Temim village of 500 inhabitants. Gazal below ? Is this misprint for GARRAA. Walled village in Kaseem, about 12 miles west of Borevda It has well grown palms and high clay watch-tower on a rock above village.' Elevation is 2,800 feet. Water is brackish, population of oasis about '300 Sub- ject to Boreyda. Is this same as Keraa below ? C , P-^A.-Abandoned village, 13 miles north-east of Jauf on route to oekaka. There are springs and wells. GAZAL.—Place 9 hours south by east of Mukak, 5 hours north-norlh-east of Seleimy, 7 hours north-west of Raudha, 6 hours south of Kasr, 8 hours south- south-east of Kefar. This seems to be same as Ghazala below. . GERA^ L—Village dependent on Jauf and situated in sam© vallcv, 20 minutes south-west of Khadhma.35 GIAWA.— Village 1-J Lours north-west of Khadhma (Jauf) on route to Sekaka. GISAN MEJELLY.—Plain extending northwards from Ilail to Tual Ali, peak near borders of Nefud, and to Jebel Jildiyyah. GHADHUWAK.—Small hamlet, 9 miles south-west of Mustajidda. GHAFECH or GHAFEH or GHAEET.—Place of 2,000 inhabitants, 28 hours south-east of Hail and 10 hours north-north-west of Kuwara, a halting place on route to Aneyza. Is Kehafa meant ? GHAEEL.—District between Selma hills and Kaseem. GHA.LGHAL.—Valley in Jebel Ajja near its north end, coming out near Lakita. It lias numerous tributaries and all are full of palms which grow without artificial watering and belong to nomads. GHAMER.—Village at south-east corner of Jebel Ajja. Its palms are in the hills and flourish on the water of the subsoil. There are tanks but no wells. Near by is a small hill of the same name. GHARB.—-See Jauf. GHAT.—Straggling village with a dozen wells, mentioned bv Palerave between Ayun and Boreyda. J &amp; a GHATAR.—See Feyd. 1 GHAZALA.—Village with 80 inhabitants in 18S0, consisting of 2 large hamlets. It is about 12 miles west of Mustajidda and 19 hours fast camel W 9 nA°^ h ’ WeSt °r f H m 1 . * In 1 1845 was one of t,le la i*ger villages of the Jebel, had 200 Shammar families and was surrounded by a wall of sundried bricks. GHEBAH—Great sandy plain extending south to the Harra, Jauf Wilad Suleiman and Draaf; east to frontiers of Jebel Sliammar ; and north to Misma and sands of Nefud. It is about 4 hours m extent from west to east. In another place Guarmani appears to call the same plain Ghelal. GHEDHIAN.—See Akda. GHEMEISAH.—Hamlet, with palms and cultivation of barley 4 miles south-east of Kehafa. Water is better than at Kehafa; only 25 inhabitants. 1 GHEZEIZAH.—See Eeyd. GHUITI—Village adjoining Jauf Aamir. Inhabited nrincioallr hv nmar workmen from Jubbeh. It lie, east-soutb-east of Kbadhma ^ soutb^t S' ^-mar, about 50 miles south- aud the place was inhabited only 3 months in tbe^velr™ f |1 20 f lnl ! ab . lta “ ts &gt; werej feet square aud 36 feet deep, sunk in hjd earth Palt ^ 00 “ HAIET (1).—See Akda. '°i 0 ' Hanmib^Tlmost'hidden'in^ 5eft^ofIhe^ar a t sou ^' eas * : ^ bet 7 en Kbl/b^t Mustajbida^ and maraud Med ma lt iTefnearhldoW, “p ° n T r °^ ,e between Jebel Sham- inhabitants, negroes bulSellf on ita a °rth side. It has SOD of 3 quarters. Wadi Saafan Ashreif th ? n Kheybar, and consists and 3rd stands on hillock alsocalled Kes^i^ Ti'V ar S est - 2nd smallest 3 springs called Shelall Sefdrly^^Tbu S^an ^ W f red }? north-west and yield toffethpr ^ j ’ trst 2 are to north- is on west and gives 8 litres a second Water of'all g' 1011 ^ ^ C ^ 1 - ed Aly) Subject to Amir of Hail and navs 4 rlatA ^ i f , all A 3 , s P r ings is drinkable. villagers- own share hut there is no govern^iXutenfa arf LgwefbuTtith36 an increasing Arab strain through frequent marriages with poor Bedouin women of .Teheyna andHeteym tribes; they have a high reputation for hospitality. I he Ibn Muiallad, Aneyza Bedouins of Kaseem, owned some of the palm vall eys hereabout, but were driven out by the Amir who appropriate! the groves. I lie ruins of old Haiet are on the plain of the Harra. Climate is feverish. Dates are abundant and, though not very good, better than those of Rheybar. Best kinds grown are gesb 3 berny, fresy and kelb. Surplus dates are bought by Heteym, Harb and Shammar. Corn, barley and maize are cultivated, but there are no cattle or beasts of burden. HAIL.—Capital of Jebel Shammar province. (1) It lies nearly 400 miles east-south-east of Basra and Koweit, 350 north-west of Riadh, 500 north- north-east of Mecca (to which caravans march in 15 long stages, the route y ar y' ing according to water but generally lying through Semira or Mustajidda) 300 north-east of Medina and about 600 south-east of Jerusalem. (2) Rather a town than an oasis, though the quarters on the south and west^ are open, and palms so abundant as largely to conceal the houses. Hail lies in a low nat valley running from east to west and called ’Wadi Hail; town is^ about 1 hour in circuit. At about 1 hour’s distance to west is Jebel Ajja, and immediately to north and east of town is Jebel Samra ; the two are connected by basaltic ridge with maximum height of 300 feet, which screens Hail from north and is crossed by pass 60 feet high. -Wadi Hail, after passing north side of town, runs out through a gap in Jebel Samra north-east of the town. East of the town is a tepid spring of brackish water and this is original site of Hail; there is no other spring in vicinity. Town is not imposing, only large building being Kasr or Amir’s palace, built of clay and whitened with gypsum ; but the green gardens surrounded by pink walls have a picturesque appearance. Most houses have 2 storeys and rooms, though few, are large and commodious. They are lighted only by doorways and by unglazed openings in walls just below ceilings. AU have detached coffee-rooms either standing in an orchard or facing one. Ground belonging to a house is surrounded by a boundary wall. Building materials are sun-dried bricks of small size and beams of palp or ithel. There are 12 quarters; Berzan, Lubda, Jabara, Jerad, Lagdeida, Semah, Abid, Rheneka, Warbaiaah, Seweyfly (an outlying village beyond Jebel Samra), Khereim and Mtfeidha. Lubda in 1815 contained the chief street. The main place is the Meshab about 150 yards long and 25 broad. One side of it is formed by the Kasr, large part of which is 40 feet high; on other is row of makhzans, where Amir’s guests are accommodated.^ Blan of Hail will be found in Palgrave I. 139, plan of part of town adjoining Kasr in Doughty I. 587 and plan of environs in Doughty I. 615. (3) The Amir’s quarter and that of suk are walled and their gates are kept closed at night; rest are open. Walls are only about 10 feet high. (4) In 1845 there were 210 houses. Palgrave estimated 20,000 to 22,000 inhabi tants, Guarmani 7,500, Doughty only 3,000 and Huber 15,000. (5) Population is mainly Shammar, but very heterogeneous. The wood and hay gatherers are Kusman ; there are a good many Gallas ; and most tradesmen are strangers from abroad. People may be divided into agriculturists, tradesmen, men-at- arms and household slaves, last being comparatively few. People are of slender build and all classes and both sexes wear the plaited leathern waistband (hagga). Rood is universally served on the floor. According to Guarmani the morals of Hail are exceedingly lax, including what are practically temporary marriages, etc. (6) There are about 130 shops all held and hired of the Amir. Shopkeepers are mostly wandering tradesmen from Irak, Kaseem and Medina. Rood is exposed for sale in open markets, contrary to custom of Jauf and north country, and pumpkins, dates and female ornaments are sold by veiled women. Length of main suk is about 200 yards. Butchers’ trade is not held in estimation. Artificers are few, and belong to smiths’ caste. There are women-embroiderers in silk and metal thread, but only in a small way. Wooden bowls are turned and camel-saddles built. There are a few house-builders and carpenters, almost destitute of tools ; also pargeters in gypsum. The largest capitals in the town do not exceed £300. (7) Water is easily reached by wells within the town limits, but, except in the Ma-es-Sama well, it is salty or bitter. (8) (9) There are 4 common schools.■37 ClO'i Hail is probably of late foundation and has risen to importance only through being*the residence of the ruling family. The Am.r entertains about 180 guests per day at an annual expense of perhaps b l,oUU. HAIL (WADI).—Lises close to Jebel Ajja about 40 miles south-west of Hail and runs north-east passing close to Hail, which is on its right ban . continues for about 55 miles in the same north-east direction and is finally lost in a depression at Haserah, not joining Wadi Rummah as was formerly supposed. HATAR1 According to Wallin the whole tract between the Dahna and Irak is so called. It is a hard stony tract ; it 8&lt; surface presents an unvarying succession of broad ridges, like waves, alternating with gravelly plains, with out a single hill or other prominent object above the undulating level, to relieve the monotory or serve as a landmark. The route from Jebel Sham mar across this tract to Meshed Ali runs due north. Huber describes Hajara as a desert of calcareous stone, extending from the Nefud on south-west to Jal-el-Batn on north-east and as running 4 days north-west and 3 days south-east of Derb Zobeideh; he describes it as very uniform and absolutely dry and sterile. HALEYFA. Outlying village somewhere in Jebel Shammar desert. HAMAH Plain lying east of Wadi Sirban and north of Jauf; a portion also intervenes between Jauf and the Nefud. Height of last mentioned part is 2 220 feet; it is absolutely level and bare of vegetation, a flat black expanse of eravellv soil covered with small round pebbles. Guarmam appears to call the part immediately north of Jauf Hamemiyeh. Huber treats the Hamad as svnonymous with the great Syrian desert and makes it contain Wadian Portion abutting on Wadi Sirhan below Kaf is an immense stony plateau, with white calcareous outcrops of remarkable shape and a little further south it contains Jebel Misma (2). IT A MEM l YEH.— See Hamad and compare Jal-el-Jauf and Sekaka. HAMRA.—See Peyd. H AMUHIA H.—Depression in Northern Kaseem, about 40 miles east bv south of Kehafa and 2 hours north by west of Kusaiba. It was found abandoned in 1880, having formerly consisted of 6 hamlets. There were no palms but corn and barley were occasionally sown by Arab nomads. HANEIDHIL.— Small place east of Boreyda, between it and Wadi Rummah. HARB.— Great Arab tribe. (1) They are of Kahtanic origin. (2) Guar- mani divides them into Beni Ali, Auf and Beni-es-Sefer. Doughty gives the main sub-divisions as two only, Beni Salem and Mosruh, the latter including the Beni Ali and apparently the Auf ; he does not mention tlm Beni-es-Sefer. Guarmani treats the Mosruh as distinct from Tlarb and divides them into Maimun and Meranhe. The Beni Salem are divided by Doughty into 18 and the Mosruh into 16 sub-sections, all of which he names. The Hazim sub-sec tion of the Beni Salem are probably not really Harb and are sometimes ranked as Sulaba. Doughty mentions also on Oreymat sept which does^ not appear in his general classification. Eurn is a sub-division of the Beni Ali. (3) Belly estimated the Harb at 1,000 (?men) while Guarmani assigned to them 1,000 fight ing men and Doughty reckoned 2,000 persons as subject to the Amir of Hail alone. Part inhabit the Hejaz in the basin of the Wadi Humth between Mecca and Medina, some being nomads and others villagers ; others live above Medina between the Wadis Humtb and Rummah. North-north-east of the Harb are the Hetevm, but the Harb sometimes intrude as far east as Therrieh and Miskeh, the Beni Ali section, apparently, lying furthest to the north and east. Wadi Rummah divides them frornthe Ateyba on the south. Their country in Central Arabia is a flat wilderness with bergs of basalt and grey-red granite. (4) Many of them are of extremely dark or almost black complexion, but their features are true Arab. The women have sometimes silver nose-rings. The Lahebba sept of the Auf are professional robbers, chiefly of pilgrim caravans. Doughty found the Beni Salem honest, kindly, hospitable and well-dressed for38 m—.« w-rlS^* £?&lt;£ io's/'sSSy S SS pwror HiliI. Iivb witli ' ll !' fI uVa-nJi-wu* and oll.nra ‘ pithless day-sleepers (o) Some of the Bern Ah were ult a religious were ut f able tQ say t i ieir prayers 0 and'ah 1! did^not some Mig^ibmirhoods th™Harb n sheep e are allied themselves ^Xn^878'part ^'ttem 6 were^subjec? to taxath)n 0r by ^ tiJ t0 be ' at Semira for revenue and military purposes. TTATt-RAT KHEYBAK.—Great lava region, about 130 miles long with bread“ 5 40 miTes! running south-west and north-east. Kheyhar is situated in it towards its west end and Haiet lies m a cleft on its south side. HASEB.AH.—Place with about 30 wells, 35 miles east-north-east of Hail, aitnated ina scarcely perceptible depression where the Wadi Hail loses itself. Soil is clayey and water occurs at 18 to 21 feet below surface. These wells are quickly exhausted by large caravans. HASIA. Village about 4 miles north-west of Jauf-el-Aamir with 50 inhabitants. HASNA.—See Akda. . , ^ * HAULAT.—Plain on route from Teima to Hail, commencing about five hours south-east of Teima. It. is covered with sandy hills and rocks, the latter being calcareous from north-west to south, and basaltic from south to east. Between north-west and east plain is entirely sandy owing to neighbour, hood of Nefud. There is no water. Plain is two hours across from north-west to south-east. &gt; . HAWAZIM Small tribe living intermingled with Sherarat m neighbour- hood of Sekaka.’ Wallin believed them to be a remnant of a formerly powerful tribe which was also called Adwan. He found them despised and poor and robbed of almost all their animals by raiding parties of Shammar. HAZEL Halting place with wells on direct route between Jauf-el-Aamir and Shebeikah on Herb Zobeideh. If this is the Hazil passed through by Wallin it is also on the eastern route from Hail to Najaf and the wells are 120 feet deep, lined with stone. HEBESHY (JEBEL).—Long black mountain of basalt skirting north side of route from Semira to Boreyda about ten miles east of Semira. HEBUB.—See Jauf. HEEEINA.—Village of 20 inhabitants f of a mile north-east of Hefenab. HEEENAH.—Village ten miles east-south-east (or east-north-east ?) of Laudha ; 50 inhabitants. HEIANIAH.—Small hamlet with 10 Sulaba inhabitants and 5 wells, three or four days’ march north of Hail in the Nefud, towards Jauf-el-Aamir. HEJJUR (JEBEL).—Mountain group of granite and trap, about 40 miles north of Kheyhar, inhabited by Wilad Ali, Bishr and (by permission of the other two) Heteym. Part of the range, at least, drains towards the Ked Sea. HELAL (BENI).—Tribe said to have inhabited northern Nejd in former days regarding whom there are many traditions. HELAL (SAHL BENI).—Plain not far from Teima, traversed on route to Hail. It is bounded on west by mountains Enka and Helwan, on north by Nefudandon east by Jebel Arnen. It is sandy and waterless, though crossed by many torrent beds ; in the centre are fantastic masses of black prismatic basalt. It is 9^ hours across from north-west to south-east. HELAL (ROAD OE BENI).—Track across Nefud from Jauf to Hail is so styled. It is also called Khali.39 V &amp; HEL ALIEH.—Village about four miles north of Khabara ; is ancient Sbeya colony and apparently subject to Boreyda. *HELWAN (JEBEL).— One day’s journey east of Teima. This range is divided on the south from Enka by a gorge (through which one route from Teima to Hail passes) and from here it runs north-east to the ISetua. HENAKIEH.— Called Haieniah by many Bedouins. Village of 100 in habitants in the Nefud 14 hours north by west of Lakita. Is this same as Heianiah above ? # . . . HETEYM. Plural, Heteyman. Tribe. (1) Their origin is uncertain and probably alien. They are ‘connected with the Sherarat and are not regarded as Bedouins. (2) Doughty mentions these sections; Jbn Barrak, Ibn Jelladan, Ibn Dammuk (taunted with being Sulaba). Ibn Simra (or Thiabba), Modhabara, Feradissa, Ibn Hayzan, Khiarat, boarasy and Gabid. Huber mentions also Ibn Balerak, Mehimezat and Awamerah. There are also Eehjat, a small and very poor Heteym kindred, almost out- castes and clients of the Eukara ; somewhat similar are the Bedowna section who supolv the Haj with hay. The Ibn Simra are about K hey bar, and the Noamsy in Harrat Ethnan. Ibn Simra section contains 8 sub-divisions with common name of Adzeibah. Sueyder is a sub-division of Ibn Simra. The Auazim (? Hawazim) are Heteym. Many poor Anezah and Harb families live among Hetevm but without intermarriage. The midland Heteym are Beni Rashid. Poor Hetevm women sometimes marry negroes. (3) Doughty reckons ™idland Heteym at 600 beiU or 2,000 souls, of whom 1,600 are subject to Amir of Hail. Guarmani allowed 3,500 musketeers to the whole tribe. They are a widely distributed race being found towards Koweit on the one side and in the Tehama on both sides of Jidda on the other. The dira of those in Central Arabia is a triangle between the Harrat Kheybar, Kaseem and the Ilarb country ; they inhabit the Harrat Kheybar itself from Kheybar to Haiet and are found in Nefud, on Jebei Hejjur and between Wadis Humth and Rummah. (4) The word Heteym is used as a reproach and Heteym are ranked with Sulaha below all Arab Bedouin tribes. They are less cheerful, frank, dignified and honourable than the Bedouins, also less civil to guests. The men are more robust and the women more beautiful than among the Bedouins. Men are good fighters, well armed and often good shots. Coffee drinking is hardly seen among them. They are distinguished from Bedouins by their long blue shirts. (6) (6) They had only 20 mares in 1863 and in 1878 were still almost without horses, but their dromedaries have always been among the best, only excelled perhaps by those of the Sherarat. The Heteym are inferior only to the Sulaba as hunters and sometimes kill ostriches. Some sections make cheeses of sheep and goats’ milk and sell them at Kheyhar. Men’s side in their tents is on (? proper) left. (7) (9) (10) See (3) above (11) Better armed than most Bedouins. (12) See (3) above. They generally pay khua to all from whom they have anything to fear, which accounts for their comparatively thriv ing condition. Some near Kheybar pay taxes both to Amir of Hail and to Turks. HOW AZIN.—Tribe said by Palgrave to be in part the ancestors of present inhabitants of Jauf-el-Aamir, the other elements being Tai and Bekr. HOWEYSIN.—Poor tribe, despised by Bedouins and much on a par with Sulaha. The Blunts met with them in Nefud north of Hail. HUEIMEL.—See Eeyd. HTJEEIR.—Hamlet short distance north-west (? north-east) of Mukak. HUILAN.—Village in Northern Kaseem about 2| miles south-west of Boreyda. It is about 1J- mile south-east of Khab and its gardens extend nearly 2 miles. It lies in a hollow in Nefud and though surrounded by sand its soil is not sandy. HUSSENI.—See Jauf*el*Aamir. HUWEIT on HO WEYAT.—According to Huber a village of 70 inhabitants in the Harrat Kheybar about 20 miles south of Haiet. Doughty calls it a palm- hamlet of 40 houses in the border of the Kheybar Harra, one journey from Haiet on way to Medina.40 reached by the Blunts after inarch north-west of Lakita. of 'sand ^but has irrigated, un walled fields of barley. IGNEH.—Eirst village of Jebel Shammar passage of Nefud from Jauf, apparently about 1 Small-village on edge There is a large well. 1THERI.—See Etera. JADHAM 1 YEH.—Village of 100 inhabitants, 12 miles north-north-east of Hail. Hates from 1830. JAUE-EL-AAMIB.—Chief northern town in Amir of Jebel Shammar’s dominions. (1) It is entirely surrounded by deserts and lies about 350 miles in a straight line south-west of Baghdad, 250 north-west of Hail and 300 south east of Damascus. It lies 2 hours from north border of Nefud and about 6 marches north by east of Teima (only one through the Nefud), the following being the stages: Daha, Jeyn (or Sfan), Towil, Areyj (in Nefud), Thulla Helwan and Ubbeyt. (2) Elevation is about 1850 feet above sea. Jauf lies in a dead flat depression, of circular or oval form with maximum diameter of 3 miles, running north-west and south-east. Walls of depression are sand stone hills, the Jal-el-Jauf, supporting a plain about 500 feet higher than that of Jauf. Circular form is broken on west by limestone spur which projects from encircling heights and subsides by degrees into centre of plain. The soil of the valley is a crusty and sterile sand with patches, here and there, of clay where water collects and leaves salt behind when it dries. Hain however is rare. Town forms a curve, hollow towards south-west. For f of its length it runs from west-north-west to east-south-east and then turns to run north-west and south-east. Wallin describes it as almost a semi-circle. Its length is somewhat over 2 miles and breadth less than •| mile, the latter being greatest at the point where it changes direction. The orchards and palm-groves, which are continuous, mostly stand away from the town between it and the west side of valley, but at no great distance from walls. ’The water level is not very low but accounts of travellers entirely disagree as to distance. The town consists of quarters, which are really separate villages each encompassed by a wall; there is some discre pancy between the accounts of different observers as to the number and names of these. The following is a list from north-west to south-east drawn up after a comparison of different accounts; Husseni, Gharh (or AinUmm Saleh), Zarai, Kaaid, Hera (or Deraa Marid), Dirat Kattah, Selman (here occurs the more southward bend) Hebub (or Habbuh), Saaidan, Hahebin, Alaj, Zogba,Khadhma, Delhamieh, the last being a ruin. Wallin only gives 7 quarters but his Gharb includes Husseni, Ain Umm Saleh and Kaaid, his Saidiyin includes Selman, Habub and possibly others; moreover he excludes Saaidan from Jauf proper. Huber gives 15 quarters but includes Wadi-ed-Derbeh and Keratin which is seems preferable to treat as separate villages. Huber mentions a quarter Ashib, not referred to by any other authority and Wadi, a quarter 2 miles north-east of Marid. The following points may be noted about these quarters. (Wallin’s) Gharb is perhaps the most recent part of the town. Ain Umm Saleh was a ruin in 1880, the former inhabitants were Ruwalla Bedouins. Dera is the most ancient quarter and to it belongs the Marid castle, originally of hewn stone but coarse in construction, situated on a hill a short distance to the south-west, and connected with this quarter by a wall. Dirat Kattab is the broadest part of the town. Saidiyin or Sarra is treated by Wallin as including Selman, while Hebub is regarded as distinct from Saidiyin by Huber, who says it possesses a strong tower called Kesair and was in former days at feud with Dera, a statement which agrees with that of Wallin. Selman is about the middle of the town. Saaidan resembles the independent village of Ghutti and adjoins it. Rahebin was found ed by Beni Temin but is now inhabited by Syrian immigrants. Khadhma is inhabited by Sirhan Bedouins and Mutawalladin. Delhemieh was destroyed in 1838. Each quarter or village is separately walled and the houses within are irregularly placed and interspersed with small orchards and deep pits from which earth has been taken. Most houses have a detached coffee-room. Building material is sundried brick. In same valley with Jauf lie villages of Gerani, Ghutti, Bahirat, V adi-ed-Derbeh and Keratin. (3) Besides village walls and the old castle of Marid already mentioned there is a square fort built by the41 Amir of Hnil about 1866. It stands on rising ground (where ?) and has walls 40 feet high, towers both round and square some 20 feet higher than the walls, loopholes and machicoulis. (4) Population was estimated by Qaarmani at 6,000, by Huber at 12,000 souls. Town can muster 1,200 matchlocks. (5) Principal tribes are Shammar of theHamoolet Almunasibeh section, Ruwalla (Anezah) and Sirhan (Bedouins) in (Wallin’s) Gharb; people from Shakra and Karant in Dera- Saidiyin, Umar, Abbas and Salman (from Syria) and Haboob (Bedouins) in Sarra ; Syrians from Ruheiba in Saidiyin ; people of Tafila in Alaj ; Bedouins of Wadi Sirhan and Mutawalladin in Khadbma. Saaidan apparently consists or negroes. Beni Lam are also mentioned as found at Jauf. The people generally travel little and seldom leave their oasis except to visit HaU or make the pil grimage to Mecca. (6) Travelling Syrian merchants do business at Jaut. Jaut artificers have great reputation throughout north-west Arabia for work m metal and marble; they make coffee-mortars and pestles. Sandals, camel saddles and brown abbas of light texture are manufactured ; also coarse iron work. Bedouin trade which 'was formerly with Ruwalla, is now (since domination of Hail began) chiefly with Sherarat; the latter bring in wool, butter and milk and purchase dates blue and white calico, abbas, camal-saddles and tanned hides : trade is chiefly carried on by barter. Poor Jaufis go every year to Hauran to labour for Druses. Salt is exported to Syria from neighbourhood of Jauf. (7) There are springs, wells and tanks, but last are not of much value owing to infre quency of rain ; water is generally insipid and often actually had-tasting. Best wells are in Khadhma. The dates of Janf are of the finest sort and there are some 15 varieties. Jauf does not produce enough corn for home consumption and imports grain through Bedouins. The corn grown is sown between trees in the orchards. Vegetables are raised in small quantities ; fi^s, apricots, peaches, oranges and grapes are grown, but not largely. Pome granates do not thrive. There are some cattle and they are used to raise water for irrigation. There are practically no horses or donkeys and very few camels, jauf is dependent on Bedouins for carriage. (8) Jauf is under Hail and a governor, deputy-governor and about 6 soldiers are stationed here on behalf of the Amir. The Amir owns some of the palm-groves as his private property. JAUP (JAL-EL).—Sandstone chain which surrounds valley of Jauf el- Aamir. Height is uniform aad about 500 feet above bottom of valley. These hills descend with steep and rugged walls, partly covered with sand, towards the valley, but merge insensibly on the other side into sands of desert. Descent into Jauf from side next Hail occupies | an hour. To north-east above the chain rises a terrace called Hammamiat, and on north-west a defile called Faaw traverses the Jal-el-Jauf with the road to Syria. On west side of valley circular arrangement of Jal-el-Jauf is interrupted by solitary peaks, jutting out with an equal height from the chain and joining another lower mountain of limestone, which, gradually declining, slopes down towards the centre of the valley, and vanishes in the sand. On the last slope of this calcareous mountain lies Jauf town. Old castle of Mark! stands on a precipice of this limestone hill in the centre of the semi-circle formed by the town, facing full north and overlooking it. JAUE WILAT) SULEMAN.—Large and deep valley about 10 hours east-south-east of Mismah, hidden at foot of Draaf hills. It contains 12 wells of drinkable water dug by the Wilad Suleman and Bishr, who alone have rights of pasture here. JEDEIDA.—Place where principal chief of Harb resided in 1863. JEFEIEA.—Village about 9 miles south-west of Mukak, with palms- Guarmani made population 600, Doughty 5 or 6 families and Huber 100 souls. JEMAYMEH (BIRKET). —Station with a reservoir of Zobeideh, elevation above sea 1,730 feet, about 15 miles south of the Batn on route from Hail to Najaf. JILDIYYEH (JEBEL).—Solitary mountain, a full day’s journey west- north-west of Hail, frequently named as rendezvous for Amir’s military ex peditions. This hill lies beyond granitic tract, in sandstone, and though district consists of stony desert it has better pasture than granitic region to south.42 JUA.—See Esheka. JUBBEH.—Village in the Nefud, about 50 miles from nearest point on its southern border. It is about 80 miles west-north-west of Hail and 170 miles (50 hours) south-south-east of Jauf-el-Aamir. (2) Situated in extensive open plain of elliptical form with hard and stony soil. Wallin describes plain as measuring 10 miles from east to west and rather more from north to south ; Huber makes it 5 miles long from east to west and 3 miles broad from north to south. This plain is surrounded by very low sandstone hills almost undistin- guishable from Nefud ; on north they are somewhat higher. Village stands at north end of plain about 1 mile from Jebel Musliman which is to west-north-west of plain and faces Jebel Ghawta on east-south-east. Jubbeh is divided into 5 suks of which 4 lie in a line from east to west, viz., Tureif, Selal, Hamaleh and Kelab, while a 5th, Mujaalat, is separate and a little distance to south. Houses are of clay hut larger and more comfortable than at Jauf-el-Aamir, inferior however to those of Kaf and Itheri. (3) Surrounded by battlemented walls, but there is no fort. (4) Population has been estimated by Wallin, Guarmani, the Blunts and Huber respectively at 170 families, 950 souls, 80 houses and 800 souls. (5) Inhabitants are Armal, reckoned one of noblest and greatest of Shammar divi sions. They are weak and sickly however, disease is common amongst them, and they are not popular in Jebel Shammar, being reputed unsociable and avaricious. Jubbeh, adjoining best grazing in Nefud and there being no other water near, is always much frequented by nomads and in date-season as many as 150 Bedouin tents may be seen here of Ruwalla, Shammar, Bishr, Sherarat and Hawazim. (6) There are orchards of ordinary fruits and vines ; and here ithel trees are first seen on journey from north. Most necessaries are brought from Hail, inclusive, according to Huber, of grain ; but Wallin says people grow enough wheat, millet and oats for own consumption and import rice only, from Irak, by Bedouin carriers. (7) Dates are grown in some quantity, but they are small and poor. There are about 40 wells with water at 36 to 45 feet ; it is insipid but better than at Jauf-el-Aamir. (8) In Guarmani’s time water-rights for Nefud journey were collected here at rate of $1 from travellers going south and $2 from those going north; merchants had to throw in a cloth-shirt as well. KAAID.—See Jauf-el-Aamir. KAF.—Called also Dirat el Bababe. Principal village in Wadi Sirhan, about 160 miles south-south-east of Damascus and 200 miles (64 hours) north-west of Jauf-el-Aamir. Basaltic and sandstone chains form a crescent around it (on which side ?) and it stands on the margin (which ?) of salt marshes. Ten minutes north of village is hill, about 250 feet high called Saidi with remains of a fort ; hill is composed of black volcanic blocks. Village is small but flourishing, with battlemented towers and walls. In appearance it resembles Jauf-el-Aamir and villages of Jebel Shammar, but clay of which houses are built is lighter coloured. In 1877 there were 16 houses and 70 or 80 palms ; in I860 houses were 17 and palms 450. The village in 1877 acknowledged the Amir of Hail and paid tribute of £4 annually. Inhabitants estimated by Guarmani at 250 were only 90 in 1877 and 1880. Adjoining villages in Wadi Sirhan are Akeile, Gati, Ekder, Uscevuasce and Etera accord^ ing to Guarmani; but Huber questions their existence and Guarmani did not see them. Chief resources are palms and manufacture of salt, taken away by Bedouins, who smuggle some of it into Syria. Ttie salt comes from a hill 3 miles south of Kaf ; it is purified oy crystallisation and becomes very white but retains a bitter taste. It seldom rains here and summer is hotter than at Jauf-el-Aamir. Houses are clean outside, dirty within. People wear Bedouin costume ; none of them can read or write and many suffer from ophthalmia. KARA.—-Village 20 miles east-north east of Jauf-el-Aamir ; commanded on north by rocky mound with a ruin. Palms are good. The Blunts counted only 70 or 80 houses ; Huber makes the population 1,000. Ruwalla camp about here. Guarmani placed it J way between Jauf-el-Aamir and Sekaka and gave it 1,500 inhabitants. KASEEM (NORTHERN).—District bounded on south and east by Wadi Rummah and on north and west apparently by granitic region which encloses41 KHAB (1).—Village aloout 2 miles west-soutli-west of Boreyda in the second Nefud valley from that town. It runs north and south for over 2 miles and contains magnificent plantations. KHAB (2).—See Esheka. KHABABA.—Town in Northern Kaseem, subject to Boreyda and 32 miles south-west of that place. It is an ancient Kahtan colony.. Ilouse-build- ing is rude and there are long dull streets of half ruinous clay cottages. Site has no natural amenity and town is surrounded by clay wall. Public place is about an acre in extent, and in middle of it rises watch-tower. Many of people are cameleers, the majority are agriculturists. They are dull, ungracious and inhospitable. Friday market is held in public square. Town may comprise COO houses, rather less than Bass. KHADHMA.—See Jauf-el-Aamir. KHALID.—See Wilad Ali. KHALID (BENI).—Lady Blunt calls them a branch of the Beni Lam (?) and says Ketherin are one of their sub-divisions. According to Doughty the Beni Khalid (along with the A1 Morrah, Ajman, Beni Hajirand Shamir) belong to the Yam, a group descended from Keys, and now-a-days wander in the north towards Koweit, their original seat having been in Hasa. See sub-section A and section II sub-section D. KHAMMASHIEH (SAHILAT-EL).—Long plain in which Hail stands, bounded on the east by Jebel Eittij. KH ABB AM.—“Wide sandstone mountain platform, elevation 5,400 feet, dropping steeply eastwards to the sandy plain about Abbassieh. It lies some 20 miles north of Harrat Ethnan and the same south of Jebel Irnan. KHASHABAH (UMM-EL).—Group of 4 large hamlets about 6 miles south-east of Kehafah, abandoned owing to drying up of wells. Soil is good in rainy winters. Kehafah people sow barley here. KHATAB.—Village about 5 miles south of Boreyda on route to Aneyza. KHATTA.—Plain lying on north side of Jebel Keisy between two Nefuds. It is 7 hours from south-west to north-east and near centre is very deep well called Bir Tayyem. In summer this land is inhabited by Sulaba. KHATJLAH—See Haulat. KHEIL.—See Wilad Ali. KHEBABA—.See Mukak. KHBEYMA.—-Great palm plantation of the Amir of Hail, north-east of Hail town, watered by springs. ^ KHUDDBA or KHADHRA.—Group of 14 wells about 110 miles east-north- east of Hml on pilgrim route from Persia, and about 24 miles south of Birket Ashaar. W ells are 70 feet deep, and water has unpleasant smell which disappears on exposure to air. KSEBA.-Oasis with excellent water and small fort about H hours to south-south-east of Kaf. There are serpents and “ wild bulls.*’ i (UMM-EL).—Village with palms situated in the Nefud at bottom of an enormous/^ of red sand, 40 miles north-north-west of Hail In 1845 it was new and had 10 families. In 1880 population was 30. KUSAIBA.—Village in Northern Kaseem 60 miles east of Eeyd and 50 north-w r est of Boreyda, situated in a natural basin with sides about 100 feet high along western wall of which it extends far about 2J miles. Large parts of it are deserted. Dates are reputed finest in Kaseem and water is abundant and of constant level. There is a small artesian well of warm water. The ordinary wells are uncertain, frequently failing or turning salt and making it necessary to dig new ones. Climate is said to vary but little and fever45 and mosquitoes prevail throughout the year. People are weak, thin and small and have a drawn and emaciated appearance. Pal grave (1862) calls it a small hamlet; Huber (1880) estimates population at 3,000. KUSAIR.—Village about 12 miles west of Mustajidda. It consists of 3 hamlets standing 700 to 800 yards apart. Water at one of these is un drinkable; the sweet water is found at 75 feet. There are 30 inhabitants. KUWARA.—Village, 10 hours south-south-west of Kehafa and 12 hours north-north-west of Ayun, the last village of Kaseem towards Hail. Situated in a hollow and consists of 8 plantations scattered at 700 to 1,100 y a ^n s apait, over a space of 3 miles square. Palms are poor and yield scarce. There are only 4 wells of which water is drinkable. People are descendants of Tai and very poor. Palgrave (1862) mentioned a large village and Guarmani (1863) 2,000 inhabitants, but Huber only found 12 houses and 120 inhabitants. LAKITA.—Village 14 miles north by east of Hail and opposite, at dia- tance of several miles, exit of Wadi Ghalghal near north-east extremity of Jebel Ajja. It is 14 hours south-south-east of Henakieh, 4 hours east-south east of Kena, and 1 hour north-west of Wakid. It is a fine village, standing on a plain between mountains with excellent palmgroves and orchards owned by Amir of Hail. Palgrave speaks of 400 houses and 2,400 inhabitants, Guarmani of 1,500 inhabitants; Huber’s estimate is 500 inhabitants, agreeing with Wallin’s of 120 families. LEINA or LINA.—Locality lying 30 miles or one day’s march due east of Asheihebat on the Herb Zobeideh {q.v.). Kufa pilgrims pass through Leina and it is much frequented as a camping place on account of its celebrated wells. These according to Huber are about 300 in number with depth of 80 feet and sunk through hard white rook : Wallin says the water is near the surface. Water is good, but not what Arabs call “ sweet.” LEZAM.—See Mukak. LEZRAM.—Village of 300 inhabitants, | an hour south-east of Mukak. Can this be same as last ? LIDIAN.—See Wilad Ali. LUKA.—Halting place with wells on direct route from Jauf-el-Aamir to Sheheikah on Herb Zobeideh. MAA.—See Akda. MAGOOA.—Collection of deep and perennial wells where Palgrave found Sberarat encampment of 200 tents ; apparently in Wadi Sirhan about one full march north-west of Jauf-el-Amir. MAHAMIYEH.—Elinty plain, elevation 1,460 feet, on route from Hail to Najaf. It commences at the north end of Batn about 90 miles south of Najaf and extends north for some 10 miles. With Batn it forms neutral ground be tween Shammar and Anezah. There is a considerable growth of grass after rain. Mahamiyeh may perhaps be identified with the plateau between Huber’s Jal Batn and Jal Waksat. If so it contains the birkets of Akaba and Athamin (see Herb Zobeideh) and well preserved remains of the side walls of the Herb Zobeideh, in places 6 feet high. MA KHAOOL.—Hamlet in Jebel Shammar territory; position undeter mined. MALEIK.-See Eeyd. MARIH.—Ancient castle at Jauf-el-Amir (q.v.) forming nucleus of the place. See also Jal-el-Jauf. MASHREPAH.—See Mukak. MATHUIL—Strip of Nefud, here only 6 miles broad, immediately north of Trobah. MEHASH,—Plantation of 50 palm trees, 6 inhabitants, water at 60 feet, 13 miles west by north of Mustajidda and adjoining south-east corner of Jebel Ajja. CC05PH L46 MEN IP. The cliffs of Jebel Ajja on the side next, and at part nearest, to Hail are so named. Akda lies in this portion. MEREIKHAN.—See Wilad Ali. MEET A AD (IBN).—Bedouin tribe found about Moghair. MESAAD.—See Wilad Ali. MESHETAH.—See Wilad Ali. MESHREE.—See Wilad Ali. METELAH (JEBEL).—Small range running north and south about 6 dromedary hours west of Mukak. It is in Shammar dira and forms west boundary of Jebel Shammar. Well, known as Bir-el-Metela, 7-i houre west- north-west of Mukak, lies at its north extremity. METNAH.—See Mukak. MISMA (JEBEL).—(1) Long sandstone range, direction east and west, about midway between Abbassieh and south end of Jebel Ajja. Salt is found in this neighbourhood, sometimes an inch thick, and is taken to Hail. MISMA (JEBEL).—(2) Chain of hills starting from Wadi Sirhan about 40 miles east-south-east of Kaf and running north-east into the Hamad. MOGHAIR (ABU).—Mountainous block with elevation of perhaps 5,000 feet between Jebels Kharram and Irnan. MOOJIAN.—Portion of theNefud immediately north of that called Eeluh. According to Huber takes its name from long white hill which runs east and west and divides it from Eeluh. Guarmani describes it as a high barrier of very fine sand covered with desert vegetation, which is leafless except in winter ; hut adds that it gives its name to a tract north of it, SJ hours broad, which separates it from Benieh. MUEISEN.—Village north-east of Jauf-el-Aamir on route to Sekaka. Guarmani makes it dromedary hours from Jauf, Huber ^ way to Sekaka. MUKAK.—Spelt by Doughty Mogug. Town. (1) About 45 miles west- south-west in a direct line from Hail ; a good dromedary makes the journey in one day. (2) It lies at foot of a prominent peak which juts out from w r est flank of Jebel Ajja and is about 1 mile from entrance of Ria-es-Self pass to Hail. Site is unhealthy and fever prevails from autumn till early summer. There are 10 plantations with the names and populations following : Adrub (100), Lezam (50), Mashrefah (60), Serhany (50), Kheraba (90), Salamy (30), Metnah (20), Seleil (50), Senud (20) and Shuweima (30). The walls of the houses are built of earth in layers with some cores of sundried bricks laid crosswise. The ground water is lukewarm and fetid, (o)—(4) Wallin reckoned over 220 families in 1S45 and Guarmani 2,000 inhabitants in 1863. In 1870 about % of the inhabitants perished by cholera and Huber in 1880 estimated population at 520. (5) People are Shammar; in 1863 there were 5 families of Beni Khalid. (6)—(7) Dates are grown, but they are scaly, dry and of bad flavour. (8) (9) (10) In years when the rabia is on west side of Jebel Ajja, the Amir’s mares and horses are sent to graze about here. MUSLIMAN (JEBEL).—See Umm-es*Selman. MUSTAJIDDA.—Large Beni Temim village, about 65 miles south by west of Hail. Wallin estimated poputation at 200 families, Guarmani at 1,800 inhabitants and Huber, who says it has declined, at not more than 800. The Amir of Hail’s pilgrim caravans generally proceed by either Mustajidda or Semira and thence east of the Harrat Kisshub to Mecca. NEBBAJAH.—See Thejjajah. NEBKIAH.—Pronounced Nebtsiab. Hamlet of 35 inhabitants, 25 miles north-east of Boreyda, with a stony desert on its south side. NEEUD.—The general word in northern and eastern Arabia for a desert ; and the name, particularly, of the desert, also called Ramal A ali crossed by47 travellers between Jauf and Hail. The boundarie s and extent of this desert are not definitely ascertained. The west limit runs from Jebel Helwan, 8 hours east of Teima, to the Wadi Sirhan and thence (according to Wallin) to a point 2 days south or south-east of Damascus. On this side it must be non con tinuous if, as reported by Doughty, of 6 days’ journey from Teima to Jauf only 1 day lies in the Nefud. Wallin says this side is bounded by a range of hills 100 to 200 feet high. On the south it runs from Helwan past the north extremity of Jebel Ajja, but does not apparently anywhere touch that range. Its south border is 1 hour from Dmm-el-Kulban on road to Lakita where it meets granite. On the east it is irregular and broken into strips, one of which is believed to form a continuous connection between the body of the great Nefud and the Dahna desert between Central Arabia and the Persian Gulf (see sub-section E). Immediately north of Trobah the Nefud is a strip only 6 miles broad and is called Mathur. On the north its limits are unknown except that at the east end it is bounded by Hajara and at the west almost reaches the edge of the Jauf-el-Amir depression. Various portions are known under special names. Several of these are described under Benieh, Dahna, Dhebeib-el-Kebir, Eeluh and Moojian. Its surface does not appear to vary greatly in level; it is questionable whether a variation of more than 150 feet exists on the track between Jauf Amir and Hail, but the southern portion, upon this line, is somewhat higher than the northern. The Nefud throughout consists of bright red sand which is almost crimson when damp ; this sand is somewhat coarse, but absolutely pure and does not vary either in colour or consistency from one place to another. It is generally agreed that the north-west part, towards Jauf, has the most broken and irre gular surface. According to Wallin the ridges and valleys here have no gen eral direction ; the same traveller describes the south part towards Hail as con sisting of open concave plains, with sandhills less in height but of greater circuit than those in the north, interrupted here and there by sandstone ridges. On the east according to Wallin the Nefud falls into low sand ridges branching out from the higher western portions and enclosing between every two of them flat but long valleys which descend eastwards. The principal known landmarks are the Jebels luwal, Aalem-es-Saad and Umm-es-Selman and the chief wells, those of Sekik and Jubbeh. The most remarkable features are the fvljes, depressions of semi-oval shape resembling the prints of a gigantic horse- hoof. The toe of the depression points to the north-west and on the plain above there is generally a hillock of lighter-coloured sand adjoining the south or south-west side of the fulj. Th fuljes range from 1 acre to 200 acres in area and their walls slope internally at an angle of 50° to 60° with the horizon. Their average diameter is perhaps 000 to 100 yards and depth 150 to 250 feet. In some a firm bottom of clay, or a calcareous, ciuartzy or flinty stratum is exposed at the deepest point. These hollows in spite of the instability of their steep sandy sides appear to remain constant in shape and size from year to year and even generation to generation. None of them retain water after a fall of rain. It has been observed that they lie in irregular strings or chains from west to east. The phenomenon of these/w/yes is not yet fully explained, two of the largest, between Aalem-es-Saad and Jubbeh, are called Ayun Kefiah and Eeidha. Another feature of the JNefud is the large ridges which traverse it from east to west: 3 or 4 of these from 30 to 60 feet high are crossed between Jauf Amir and Jubbeh. After rain, which is not frequent but sometimes heavy, pools are formed and continue for some time in parts of the Nefud. In January there is sometimes a white frost in the early morning. Be douins deny the occurrence of high winds: the prevailing wind is from the west. The only well known route in the Nefud is that between Jauf Amir and Hail, which has been followed by 6 European travellers. The average time taken by these was 75 hours of actual travelling, the longest being 87| and the shortest 49^- hours. The distance can be performed in 3 days without difficulty on a good dromedary. The track is merely a camel path about 1 foot broad and in the more exposed parts it is often obliterated by wind, camel-droppings alone remaining to mark the way. It is seldom clear except between Aalem-es-Saad and Jubbeh. The chief points on this route are the wells of Sekik and the villages of Jubbeh and Umm-el-Kutbani a is a a48 already mentioned. Routes crossing or skirting the east end of the Nefud, conducting from Hail to Najaf, have been described by Wallin and Huber. Huber found the Nefud on this side to be narrow and to consist merely of sandhills separated by pebbly valleys. Wallin, whose course lay further west than Huber’s, appears to have spent 3 days in the Nefud. The last ridge crossed by him before reaching the firm ground of Hajara was called Dahna. There is also a route from Jauf-el-Amir to Irak which runs by Hazel and Luka to Shebeikah on the Persian Haj road, but it is uncertain how far this lies in the Nefud. There is abundant desert vegetation in the Nefud and only the want of watering places prevent its being permanently inhabited. The grazing is excellent and when winter rains have made sojourn possible the Bedouins repair to the Nefud with all their flocks and herds. North of Aalem-es-Saad the principal plant is the ghada which yields splendid firewood and charcoal; south of that point it is the yerta, which, when leafless, resembles a thickly matted vine. The commonest plant is udr, with stiff green leaves and brownish yellow 7 flow r ers. There is also nossi, a good kind of camel grass, and hamar, a blue, prickly^ plant w'hich is good forage for horses. Animals are wolves, “ wild cattle,” hares, lizards, snakes (believed to include cobra and horned viper) ; birds are buzzard, kestrel, grey shrike, linnet, wren, desert lark, wheat-ear and an occasional crow; there are also flies, dragonflies and small butterflies. The Ruwalia and Sherarat frequent the north Nefud, the Bishr and Shammar the south, and the Shammar, Muntafik and Dhafir the east, in winter and spring; in summer these Bedouins withdraw to settled countries, the three last mentioned to Mesopotamia, and the Soluba remain in exclusive possession; two Shammar sections in the part near Trobah are the Abtah and Tuman. NOAMSY.—See Heteym. OREYMAT.—See Harb. OTHEYM.—Small village in Jebal Shammar dominions. Unplaced. RAEIYA.—See Eshekah. BAHEB1N.—See Jauf-el-Amir. RARY.—See Esheka. RAU 1)HA.(1) Or Rauth. Village of Kaseem 5 miles west of Ayun. Huber attributed to it great importance and a population of 1,500, but Doughty round only 50 houses. There are palm groves. KAUDHA. (2) Village of 150 inhabitants, 15 miles east of Boreyda, with palmgroyes belonging to family of Amir of Boreyda and imposing clay Imsr constructed by Ibrahim Abu Nehanna. r o j RAUDHA.—(3) Village of tin's name is mentioned by Wallin who places it ? a day north of Mustajidda and gives it 200 families, and by Guarmani who makes the position 6 hours north-east of Mustajidda and the population 2,000 souls. Is this the same as Baudha mentioned by Doughty, a good sized villam; at southextreimty of Jehel Selma, and as a Raudha mentioned by Huber which dhas ?“ 63 1,000 iulmbita “ ts ; or ar « ^ese yet other Rau- EEBEILAT.—See Wilad Ali. REKAB,—See Wilad Ali. REKEIAII.— Fine kasr 20 miles north-east of Borevda- in 1SS0 it eontntn odonly ruins inhabited by 5 cultivators. has a magni&amp;ent opening 78 feet square and depth of 7n feet of which about 30 feet throne'll sand and earth and remainder in sandstone rock. In good years water rises 45 and even 60 feet, corn, barley and maize are cultivated by irrigation from tlfis 1860 &amp; S ° mel ° nS ' llaCe was foullded b y Gahanna, Amir of Boreyda, about REMIDH.— Bee Akda. ROSEH (WADI).—.Valley in which are situated the Birkets of Zobeideh It appears to rise not far Irom the Birket Ashaar and passing Birkets Abdallah* bbiehayad and Jemaymeb to reach the Batn depression after a court of 2049 miles. Name is derived from a plant which grows in it, and is much Prized as pasture for both camels and horses. The tanks are of concrete, now as hard as granite and with a tine polish. Largest is 64 yards by 37 and about 12 feet deep. Fall of valley from its head to Eatn seems to he nearly 500 feet. ItUMMAH (WADI).—Called Ermek by Huber. The principal water- wav of North Arabia, if not of all Arabia. It rises in the Harrat Kheybar about 50 miles east of Kheybar and is believed to reach the Euphrates jalley near Zobeir. Its total length is “40 camel-marches ” or between 400 and 500 miles. Its source appears to be at eastern foot of Jebel Abiadh in the Harrat Kheybar, one of the summits of a range of the Harrat which runs north and south, the principal points being, in order from north to south, Gheinat, Gheneim, Ras-el-Abiadh, La Kebir, Remahah and Aaker. Of these Gheneim also sends down a wadi which joins that of Rummah about 30 miles feither^ east. Ihc source of Rummah is about 40 miles west-south-west of Haiet and its elevation about 6,000 feet. Huber gives the following affluents : Wadi Makhid (left bank) at 50 miles from source; Wadi Kabed (left bank) at /0 miles, Wadi IVIebehel (left bank) at bO miles ; W T adi Rekob (right bank) at fffl miles ; Wadi Ash Abah (left bank) at 114 miles ; Wadi Jadakk (right bank) at 140 ; Wadi Tsadek (right bank) at 185 ; W r adi Tsalabut (left bank) at 190 ; Wadi Garib (right bank) at 232. Makhid (called by Doughty Mukheyat) comes down from the Harrat Kheybcr ; so does Kahed, at the head of which Thurgbud stands. Huber places the desert of Zerb on the upper course of Makhid, and that of Kalankuah bet. ween Kaled and Mebehel ; the former is exceedingly barren and monotonous. Ash Abah appears to drain the district, Shaaba and is perhaps the same word ; it leaves Ghazala and Mustajidda not far from its left bank. Tsalabut is shown ns draining the country between Eeyd and Kaseem. Doughty shews no tributaries except Makhid, that coming down from Thurgbud and one from the south, Wadi Jerrir, which he says is by far the greatest of the feeders of W 7 adi Rummah. He makes it join Rummah from the south 30 miles west of Jebel Abanat at a place Hemelliy, from which Jerrir may be conjectured to be the same as Gureir, shown by Huber as a tributary of Tsadek. Doughty passes the source of Wadi Jerrir 50 miles south west of Aneyza on route to Mecca. Between the Tsalabut and Garib conflu ences Wadi Rummah passes between the Abanat mountains which are 45 miles south-west of Aneyza. After receiving the Garib, Wadi Rummah turns north east passing Rass on its right (?) bank, Khabara on its left, Aneyza on ifs right and Boreyda on its left. About 60 miles below Aneyza is Thueyrat, a great natural dam formed by sand-dunes From Thueyrat to Zobeir Wadi is called Batin and little is known of its course ; except that Hafr (see Secrion II, sub section E) is situated upon it, that it is route of north caravans and that there are a few wells with little water. Erom its source to Rass, general direction of Wadi Rummah is due east, but Doughty and Huber agree that it describes somewhat of a curve to the north between these points. Erom Rass its course, so far as known, is north-east. Above Kaseem it runs through uninhabited country. The Wadi banks are often of clay and gravel and the bed is sometimes three miles across from cliff to cliff. In Nefud plain of Kaseem, Wadi is hardly discernible by an unpractised eye. The arable lands of Rass and Khabara lie in the Wadi bed ; those of Khabara extend for a length of 5 miles. Rass has its palm-groves on the high banks. Between Boreyda and Aneyza the valley is full of palm plan tations ; one is a mile broad, water is only 5 to 10 feet below surface here, but it is brackish and fever is prevalent in the plantations which are tended by negroes. There is much good loam in the middle of the valley, but it cannot he tilled on a&lt; count of the saltness of the subsoil water. Soil is white with subakha, but desert bushes and tamarisks grow. These outlying plantations (which belong to Aneyza) are ancient, but they are the first to suffer in time of war ; consequently old trees are seldom found in them. The village here, called Wadi, is mainly temporary and is at its full size only in date harvest. Floods do not occur more than twice or thrice in a century and the Wadi, even in flood, can be crossed by camel-riders except where the torrent is confined. The last great flood was about 18 :8 when the waters pent up by the Thueyrat dam washed back to Aneyza and formed a lake of about 200 square miles which remained for 2 yeais and attracted many water-fowl not seen before in South Arabia.—50 RU WALL A.—Great sab-tribe of the Anezah in tbe north. Their dira appears to extend from tbe Nefud in the south to the Hauran in the north and from Wadi Sirhan on the west to the route between Hail and Najaf on the east. On the last mentioned side the plains of Batn and Mahamiyehare neutral ground between them and the Shammar. They are said to be more nearly related to the Bishr and Jellas than to the other sub-tribes of the Anezah. Their horses are smaller and spears shorter than tho^e of the Shammar. SAAIDAN.—In 1845 was only a palm plantation watered by a well and belonging to a negro family residing in Khadhma quarter of Jauf-el-Amir. In 1'80 Huber treated it as a quarter of Jauf and noted it was inhabited almost entirely by Shammar from Jubbeh. SAAIDIN.—Or Saidiyin. See Jauf-el-Amir. SABAAN.—According to Wallin, a small hamlet with running water at very foot of Jebel Selma, exactly half way between Hail and Feyd Bedouin families occasionally settle here, to cultivate dates and corn. SAERA.—Village 2 days’ march south-south-east of Hail, 25 inhabitants. Corn cultivation'but no palms. Wells are brackish and bitter. SAKAH.—See Akda. SALAMY.—See Mukak. SALEM (AIN UMM).—See Jauf-el-Amir. SALEM (BENI).—One of the main divisions of the Harb. Doughty subdivides them into 18 fendies. Those he met were, for Bedouins, gentle, honest and hospitable. SAMRA (JEBEL).—Or Samra Hail. Twin mountain of plutonic basalt, close to Hail town on its north and east sides. Wadi Hail passes out between the two hills on its way north-east. Samra can he seen 25 miles to southward ; western hill is lower of two ; eastern is called Umm Arkab and is 500 feet above plain. “ Samra” means “ any rusty black berg of bard stone in the desert.” SAR A (JEBEL).—Low sandstone range which skirts north side of road from Boreyda to Semira for over 30 miles fram Boreyda. Beyond Raudha the road leads across a flat portion of it. Raudha lies in a bay on the south side of the range. SEBAA.—A consider able sub-tribe of the Aneyza, said to be from Hasa where some of their kindred are still settled ; at a later period they occupied the country upon the Wadi Rummah between Kheybar and Kaseem ; now they are Bedouins of the Syrian desert. One of their subdivisions is the Moahib (q. v.). Sebaa are generally short men with long spears. SEE A AN.—Village of 500 inhabitants, at extreme south end of Jebel Selma; 2 days’ march from Hail according to Huber, 12 hours south-east of Hail, according to Guarmani. Is this the same as Sabaan above ? SEBAIH.—Village one or two miles south of Boreyda. SEBAM.—Village of Beni Temim with 2,000 inhabitants (Guarmani). Is this mistake for Sebaan above, which Guarmani calls Seban ? SEHARA.—Village with 50 inhabitants, 5 miles north-west of Jauf-el- Aamir. SEKAKA.—Town, 20 miles north-east of Jauf-el-Aamir, at foot of Hama- miah hills. It lies in a broad hollow, somewhat broken np by sandhills and protruding rocks and surrounded by sandstone cliff. The surface soil is nearly pure sand. Town is irregularly built and not continuously walled. There are many detached houses and gardens. The 4 are Dm ran, Sulieyan, Hirkan and Feyad. Ancient citadel named Zaabal, on hill 100 feet high, dominates town. Water is abundant and nearer surface than at Jauf even. Estimates of population are W T allm 400 families, Guarmani 10,000 persons, Lady Blunt 700 houses, Huber 8,000 persons. Place appears to be increasing at expensemm51 of others in neighbourhood. Palm gardens are twice as extensive as those of Jauf. There is well beaten track between Sekaka and Jauf. In lb45 secondary and tertiary syphilis were prevalent. SELEIMY —According to Guarmani, Beni Temim village of 400 mlmbi- tants, dromedary hours north-north-west of Mustajidda. Huber makes it a small village of three plantations with few palms, 15 wells of which 1 sweet, and only 30 inhabitants ; he places it 13 miles south of Mustajidda. Can the two mean the same village ? SELF (RIA-ES).—Pass through a cleft 18 miles long in Jebel Ajja, con ducting from Mukak on the west side to Kefar on the east. The ascent from west is steep and rugged, and before the crest is reached, a cold spring of water is met with, falling from a cliff ; highest point is 5,100 feet. At middle of pass granite recedes on north side and there are low domes of plutonic basalt. SELLEM.—Bedouins mentioned by Lady Blunt between Hail and Najaf. SELMA (JEBEL).— Range of granitic mountains, parallel to Jebel Ajja and about 40 to 50 miles further east. It is lower than Ajja and about 20 miles shorter, reaching equally far south, but no further north than Hail. There are well-marked craters exhibiting gravel-conglomerate, basalt, granite and red basaltic schist. Route from Hail to Feyd crosses the range by a road which in places is narrow, difficult and, for camels, even dangerous. SELMA (WADI).—Mentioned by Quarmani in connection with Jebel Selma, but not otherwise described. SELMAN.—See Jauf-el-Amir. SELMAN (UMM-ES.)—Or Musliman. Remarkable hill about 1 mile west of village of Jubbeh. It is extremely steep on east and perpendicular on west; height above plain is about 1,200 feet. Summit is narrow and from it top of the higher Aalem-es-Saad is visible. SAMIRA.—Small but ancient town about 70 miles south of Hail, not far from south end of Jebel Selma. It consists of one large kasr with clay towers and 2 smaller ones, area of whole site is less than 2 acres. Inhabitants are Beni Temim of Shubaramy section. Huber puts population at 400, Doughty at only 100 in 30 houses. Water is abundant and only 7 feet below surface. There are no palms but good crops of wheat and barley. Harb I3e- douins assemble here to be taxed by Amir of Hail. SENED.—See Wilad Ali. SENEIEN.—See Eeyd. SENI7D.—See Mukak. SERHANY.—See Mukak. SERIF.—Valley, 5 miles long and one mile broad, which runs north and south at a distance 20 miles north-east of Boreyda. In it are 3 kasrs, con taining some miserable huts. Water is at 7 to 19 feet. The place belongs to Sulaba from other side of Wadi Rummah who come at times, especially after rainy winters, to cultivate barley, maize and even corn. SEWEYFLY.—Village north of Hail, 2 miles beyond Jebel Samra, covers part of the former site of Hail. It is still reckoned one of the wards of Hail town. The village had almost ceased to exist prior to 1878 in consequence of an e\ i lemic. SHAABA.—Desert plain of gritty sand surrounded by trap and basalt hillocks, about 60 miles south-west of Hail and 20 miles west of Mustajidda. It drains to Wadi Rummah. SHAKARA (ABU).—See Feyd. SEAKIK (WADI) (1).—Valley in Nefud, crossed at about 40 miles from Jauf-el-Amir on way to Hail. It runs north-east and south-west; breadth about 1 mile ; depth below surrounling Nefud 120 to 150 feet. It is veryrugged; in places rock comes to surface, in places there are flints, in places sand. It seems to drain a large area of Nefud and to supply wells of Zhery and Sakik. Wells called Sakik are variously stated to number 2, 4 and b; there are 2 close together at the usual watering place; 2 more are 3 or 4 miles distant up and down valley. They have stone parapet, and opening about 3 feet wdde, but diameter increases lower down. They are roughly cut in rock, except uppermost 20 feet which are built with dry hewn stone, lotal -depth is variously stated at from 120 to 225 feet. They stand in a plain of hard and saline soil. Water never entirely fails and is generally sweet but Huber at his visit found it fetid. Nomads collect here in large numbers es pecially in end of summer ; they are Ruwalla, Shammar and Sherarat. The wells are reckoned 12 to 14 hours from Jauf. SHAKIK (WADI) (2).—Valley about 12 miles long which, running from south-west to north-east, loses itself in the hollow containing the wells of Haserah. There is brushwood for fuel and water remains in hollows of the rock for a month after rain. What is the relation between Wadi Hail and Wadi Sekik ? Both come from the same direction and end in the Haserah de pression ? Huber appears to distinguish them in his written account and to confound them in his map. SHAMMAR.—Tribe (1) Kahtanic or Yemeni tribe but regarded by Doughty as of mixed descent. They were one of latest to emigrate from Yemen and obtained their present territory by expelling the tribes of Tai and Keis towards Mesopotamia. (2) Their principal divisions according to Wallin are Abteh and Jaafar, the Sheikhs belonging to former of these. Wallin also mentions branches called Suweid (famed for their excellent butter), Sinjareb, Aslam, Tooman and Armal. The Shammar of Teima are divided into Ali and Hamdeh. Subdivisions called Abtah (Abdeh above?) and Tuman camp about Trobah. Ross gives subdivisions as Saleylat, Singhiara, Esslem, Abdel and Dagheret and Huber also shows Singary (Singhiara ?) in his map about Umm-el- Kulban and mentions Sinjariah (probably the same) to east of wells of Abbassiah. Guarmani mentions a Tuala section; and Doughty one called Kuruniyah, inhabit ing a village called Aleyi in Aaredh in Nejd. (3) Only estimate of numbers is Doughty's of hardly 2,000 souls for Bedouin portion south of Nefud. Sham- mar are widely dispersed, large proportion being in Mesopotamia, among these Zakarit near Kerbela and Sufook. Their principal towns and villages are Hail, Mukak, Lakita, Jubbeh, Jefeifa, Tuweia, Kena, Wakid, Bedan, Wasita, Akda, Lezram, Henakieb andTeyma; and between Hail and Misma on the west only Shammar Bedouins are found. Their western divas are full of basaltic and grey-red granite hills and, having many water-holes, the Shammar Bedouins live more dispersed than those of some other tribes. Their north-east border with Aneyza is 90 miles south of Najnf. (4) Wallin describes them as one of the most vigorous and youthful tribes of Arabia. The men are generally tall and wear brown abbas. In face they are distinct from the Anezah. They regard themselves as, and in Huber’s opinion are, the noblest of the Arabia. They are hospitable. (5) (6) Tribe is partly nomad and partly settled in town and vil lages. Individuals constantly emigrate, always in direction of Baghdad. In tents of Shammar Bedouins wife’s apartment is on (? proper) left. (7) (8) (9) They do not follow custom of some tribes who erect cross, covered with red clotlj, at door of tent where circumcision is taking place. (101 (11) (12) There is a natural hostility between Shammar and Anezah and, in particular, no love lost between Shammar and Bishr. SHAMMAR (JEBEL).—Great principality of North Central Arabia, named from the mountain ranges of Ajja and Selma and from the dominant tribe inhabiting their neighbourhood. (1) I he boundaries of the Sham mar state are liable to fluctuation but are, roughly, as follow : on the north the Ruwalla, Northern Shaminar and ThufAr (DafiV ?) marches (these tribes are not subject to Hail) ; on south-east, dominions of Boreyda (last place in Jebel Shammar in tins direction is Kehafa) ; on south-west a point about 100 miles from Medina (Kheybar is excluded); on west Syrian pilgrim route and further limit of Sherarat country between Jebel Sherra and Wadi Sirhan. Doughty makes extent of country 90 leagues north and south and 170 leagues53 east and west. Guarmani calls .Tebel Shammar, in Arab parlance tbe northern- mncf “nP flio spvon Hmds. ” Wallin remarks on its central and commanding graphical not political 0 -- * _ . ,, viz., from Kasr-as-Snleimy (Sulaimy ?) in the south-wesc toJadhamiya in the north-east, and breadth from Jubbeh to Kehafah about same. v 2) Adminis trative subdivisions, if any exist, are not known. The Nefud breaks the Amir s dominions into two large natural blocks, a northern and a southern. TJougnty enumerates 5 good desert towns, Sekaka, Jauf-el-Aamir, Hail, Kefai and loima , and mentions Kasr, Mukak, Aly, Musta-jidda, Eeyd, itaudha, Semira and Haiet as good villages, and Jefeyfa, Agella, Gussa, Biddia, Haleyfa, Ihurghuu, Makhaul and Otheym as instances of hamlets varying from 10 persons to -0 houses ; in all, he says, some 30 oases. The Bedouins tributary to the Amir he reckons as 800 Fejir, 1,000 Wilad Ali in south, 3,000 or less Bishr in south, J,000 northern Harb, hardly 2,000 southern Shammar, 1,500 midland Ileteym and 2,500 Sherarat. (3) The main features of the Amir’s territory north of Nefud are described under Wadi Sirhan and Jauf-el-Aamir. Ihe Nefud is dealt with under its own name. Bemainder is chiefly granitic and^ basaltic plateau with mean elevation of about 4,000 feet, rising in the north into two high ranges of Ajja and Selma (q.q.v.) and studded almost everywhere with smaller ranges and hills. One of the principal sub-ranges is Draaf which connects Jebel Selma and the Harrat Kheybar. On the north-west, however, extending from Jebel Ajja to Teima is a wide region of sandstone. South of this, in ex treme west, are lavas and elevated mass of Harrat Kheybar, hardly if at all inferior in height to Ajja. On north sands of Nefud are in direct contact with granites of Ajja and on east and south they pass through transition of sand stone into eastern Nefud and sandy plain of Kaseem. On south-west granite continues unbrokenly to Mecca far beyond Shammar boundary to Mecca itself. Generally speaking, sand plains seem to be gaining on granite mountains and burying them, especially in the region between Jebel Ajja and Harrat Kheyber. Greater portion, including whole of south of this igneous region, is drained by Wadi Rummah (q v.). Drainage of Hail plain from Kefar north-eastwards flows into Haseiah basin to north-east and is apparently absorbed, never reaching Wadi llummah. Water, at least in plain between Aj ja and Selma, is general ly brackish and tepid, hut soft and healthy. (4) Climate is salubrious. (5) Wallin, Palgrave, Guarmani, Doughty, Lady Blunt and Huber have described a number of routes, especially that from Syria ma Jauf-el-Aamir and the Nefud to Hail; that'from Hail to Boreyda; and various routes between Hail and Kheybar (7 days by dromedary) and Hail andNajaf. With regard to routes between Jebel Shammar and Irak, Wallin notes that there are two; the more direct and safer lies north-north-east by north and is ill-supplied with water and more fatiguing for small parties; this is the route followed by corn and rice caravans from Mes opotamia and Wallin himself travelled by it The other at first runs more easterly and then parallel to the direct route; water is plentiful but way is apt to he beset by Bedouins. This latter is a section of the Mashhad Ali to Mecca route. (6) Date palms are abundant and other fruit-trees grow, but are scarce owing to difficulties of irrigation. Gourds of uncommon size, pumpkins and melons of different kinds are raised and kept in great quantities for winter consump tion. Wheat, millet and maize are grown and clover for horses ; the corn partly on irrigated, partly on unirrigated lands. Local grain is sufficient in good years and fetches higher price than that imported, which comes from Najaf and Kerbela, the two principal granaries of Jebel Shammar. There are excellent oats, used for making bread. Tame animals are horses, more numer ous than anywhere else in North Arabia, and possessed in smaller or greater number by all wealthier men ; camels, good but inferior to those of Oman and Dust Nejd ; oxen, few and poor; numerous sheep and goats; donkeys often white, used for short journeys between inhabited places; dogs, few and kept at a distance for religious reasons ; some fowls ; cats. Wild animals and birds are panther, leopard, wolf, hyaena, jackal, fox, “wild bull,” gazelle, wild goat, antelope, hare, wabar, large rats and lizards, ostriches. The women of Jobol bhammar weave coarse cloth and striped and coarse-carpets are made; there are no other industries. Bedlurs are always on the move throughout the54 1 country with the wares of Nejd, Irak and Hejaz The country is as yet two and money lenders. (7) Inhabitants are mainly Shammar latter are from usury and Beni Temim skilful and diligent (Sebaa ?) from Nejd cum fern co are not to mention various places, tiocs and this money lenuers. yt) Aimauu/aiita are former are enterprising both in trade and war, agriculturists and do little else. Muteyr and Subey also live intermingled with Shammar; on the cir- found Harb, Heteym, Bishr, Beni Wahab, and Sherarat; negroes, chiefly in the west&gt; and Sulaba and flan azim m There is much intercourse between town and country popula- fact has strengthened national life and unity. Caravans are ran chiefly by townspeople who hire camels from Bedouins and give their own in charge to Bedouins to be tended. The townsmen are superior in courage and skill in arms to the Bedouins and constitute the chief military strength of the state. Some townspeople in spring wander in the desert with their horses, camels and sheep and most Bedouin families per contra own plantations in Ajja and Selma hills. Shammar villages are all surround ed with mud walls and flanked with towers ; they have vast palm plan tations and rise out of plains of sand hetween the mountains. In religion people are Sunnis but fanatical, not tolerating Jews or Christians.^ Na tional banner is green with red edges and device in white of naked scimitar with the words, below, ' God and Muhammad ” and “ Muhammad is the prophet of God.” Wahabiism is not now a power in the land, but in some families the moustaches are shaved and smoking discountenanced. Beading and writing are common, hut literary men are few. Both men and women have the power of extempore composition in verse. Men wear a long garment of white cloth and a brown, black or black-and-white striped alba, kefiah and sandals. Dress of women is blue chemise, black crape veil and black or brown abba wbicli covers them from head to foot, Guarmani makes total population of Jebel Shammnr (? south of Nefud only) 75,000 persons, of whom 33,000 fixed in villagesjand rest nomads. Doughty makes town population 13,000, village population 7,000 and tributary nomads 14,000 ; in all 34,000 and this estimate includes dominions' north of Nefud. Huber makes the settled population of the whole of the Amir’s territory 55,470 souls, distributed in 49 inhabited villages. (8) Political and commercial connection is with Mesopotamia, not Syria, the routes to the former being shorter and easier. Mesopotamia is the nearest and cheapest source of food supply for Jcbel Shammar in bad years and its best market for sale of camels. Large caravans go between the two 4 times a year, and individuals are on the way almost daily. It is remarked that, though population of Hail town is hetero geneous to a degree, there are almost no Syrians. Nucleus of Amir’s fighting force consists of a body guard of rajaj'il variously estimated at 600,8 00 and 1,000 distinguished by brown cloaks, red and blue kefiyahs and silver-hilted words; these are voluntarily enlisted now (formerly they were slaves mounted on the Amir’s own mares) from people o£ country, deserters from Turks, freedmen, etc., most of them live at their homes and get no pay or rations except on service. Besides these, Doughty estimates Amir to have at call 2,000 fighting men from settled villages, mostly mounted on dromedaries but not all furnished with fire arms ; of these only about £ could he mustered for a particular expe dition. He could also raise about 1,300 nomads with dromedaries and 2 out of 3 with firearms ; of these 800 to 900 would be Shammar, Bishr, Harib and Heteym, 250 Beni Wahab, unreliable, from his distant borders; and 200 Sherarat, at heart disloyal. Bedouin contingent generally are not trusted and inhabitants of more remote villages must many of them remain to defend their homes. Bevenue, in the case of settled villages in the north is assessed by palms and sheep 4 Kurush (? yearly) for each date tree, those under 7 years being exempt. ^ At Jauf el-Aamir and Sekaka Turkish coin is accepted; elsewhere payment is made in kind (?). Lady Blunt estimates income from such revenue at £60,000 a year and further receipts from pilgrim caravans at £20,000 to 30,000. Doughty mentions tax on corn and dates at Teima, working out at £1 per head per annum ; among Bukara taxation was at rate of £1 per 8 or 10 persons. §60 was levied on every camel load of Hameydv tobacco brought into Hail. The Amir has large private property and all confiscations are in his favour. Doughty estimated his annual total revenue at £40,000, of which hardly ^ derived from the nomads. One of his chief expenses55 is hospitality ; he entertains about 200 guests daily, gives clothes to the poor and presents to richer strangers from a distance Doughty works out Jus ordinary annual expenditure at £12,000 and extraordinary at £1,000, the latter on gunpowder, military expeditions and political bribes. Among the last are sums paid at Mecca and Medina with the view of securing outlying possessions from the Turks. Theft is almost unknown in Amir’s dominions, Muhammadan penalty of cutting off hand being enforced. SHAYBEH. Halting place of Persian pilgrim caravans 90 miles east- north-east of Hail. At this point old Haj route through Boreyda and present one through Hail meet. There are 30 or 40 wells, 15 to 20 feet deep, of very salt and bitter 3 water ; they stand in a large, hare space, with hills of white sand to north of them. SHEHIEH.—Hamlet in Northern Kascem about 5 miles north-west of Buherieh and over 30 south-west of Boreyda. SHEIHIAH.— Village mentioned by Huber as 12 miles west of Boreyda. Is this same as last ? SHELEIL.—See Mukak. SHEBAABAH.—See Wilad Ali. SHEBABAT.—Tribe, (1) Not reckoned Bedouins by the Arabs ; they are connected with Heteym. (2) Wallin gives sub divisions as Fuleihan, Dhubain, Hulasa, Azzam and Suleim. Lady Blunt mentions Hueymreh, Helesseh, Khayali and Shemalat, of which only one agrees with Wallin’s classification. Guarmani’s classification is : Dcbain, Hlese, Azzam and Flehan. Doughty mentions a despised section called Sweyfiy who are foragers of knot grass for pilgrim caravans. (3) Their headquarters are in Wadi Sirhan whence they spread in one direction to Jebel Sherra and in other to Nefud. Their dira is one of sandstone hills and Doughty gives Maan, Tebuk and Jauf as approximately its extreme points. One of principal summer stations of Sherarat is Ubbeyt between Teima and Jauf. Tribe are about 2,509 per sons. Guarmani estimated their horsemen at 20 and their fighting strength at 4,000 men of whom 2,500 had firearms. (4) In popular estimation Sherarat are ranked below all Arab Bedouins hut above Heteym and Sulaba;they are sometimes however taunted with being Sulaha. They are described as dirty and almost naked, hut the men are strong and handsome and the women hold with an innocent freedom in presence of other sex. A good many are of fair complexion and blond. Those coming in to trade at Teima appeared to Doughty lean and ragged, with quiet and dejected manners. (5), (6) They come to Jauf-el-Aamir at harvest time and exchange cattle, wool, butter, cheese, rice brought from abroad and even milk for dates, mats, tent- cloth, pack-sacks, abbas and blue or white calico. (7) They keep no horses hut have best dromedaries in West Arabia. Sheraris are light and swift and Amir of Hail mounts his rajajil on them. With the Heteym, the Sherarat are next best hunters to Sulaha. (8) (11) (12). They have no common chief of their own, hut render obedience and tribute to Amir of Hail. They regard Jauf-el-Aamir as their own proper town hut d^al also with Teima. These are the only towns with which they are in contact ; they have no other markets for their wool and camels. SHETAWI—Place with 600 palms, nourished by subsoil water, 8 miles north-north-west of Mustajidda and 4 miles east of Mehash. Belongs to Esleh (?) Arabs who sometimes come in winter to plant corn and in summer to gather dates. There is a small hill of same name near Shetawi. SHOTB.—Remarkable deep cleft containing trees, passed on one route from Hail to Kheybar. It. begins in sandstone rock and is believed to traverse Harrat Kheyher from north to south and join Wadi Rummah via Wadi Mukheyat. SHU BAR AMY —See Semira. SHUKKUK.—Unwalled village with sweet water, about 8 miles west of Boreyda, on edge of desert and close under south side of Jebel Sara near its east extremity.56 SHUWEIMA.-Sce Mukak. SINJARIAH—See Sbammar (tribe). SIRHAN (WADI).—Long sinuous tract of depressed ground, rather tban valley, commencing about 2 days’ march soutli of Damascus and extending to a point 1 day’s march north-west of Jauf, making total length about 200 miles. According to Wallin it divides into two branches which encircle Jauf- el-Aamir and ioin Nefud General direction is north-west and south-east. At Itheri breadth is 12 miles and level is about 400 below that of Hamad which borders it on east. Lowest country between Hauran and Jauf appears to he in neighbourhood of Itheri and Kaf where Wadi is about 1,800 feet above sea. Descriptions of its course and surface are somewhat confusing. Huber divides it into the following sections from Kaf to Jauf: Hasotah, Nebay, Kasayem, Jerawi and Walma. The first contains salt marshes, difficult for camels, and for some miles its surface is covered with a layer of dazzling white salt j this agrees with Guarmani’s account. Hasota contains the very salt wells of Melkhat. Prom Kaf to Nebay, surface is sandy and vegetation abundant; but south of this the Wadi grows gradually more sterile, stony and monotonous. In the Jerawi section vegetation ceases altogether and is replaced by sand and gravel. Guai* mani says that north of the wells of Weisit (which he places rather nearer to Kaf than to Jauf-el-Aamir) the ground is sandy and surface level; but south of that point it is more broken. The north part belongs to the Ruwalla, the centre and south to the Sherarat. The principal villages are Kaf and Itheri and Huber questions the existence of the others enumerated by Guarmani near Kaf, vis , Akeila, Gotti, Ekder and Uscevasce. Guarmani’s estimate of settled population is thus 1,065 persons ; Huber’s only 190. There appear to be differ ent routes along the valley following different series of wells; thus Guar- mani’s stages between Kaf and Jauf are Breda, Kseba, Abu Terifian, Adeimat, Meheder, °Weisit, Mueisari, Nebach, Sceba, Yescece, Nebsce, Gerani and Scegar ; the portion between Mueisari and Gerani was infested, in his day, by Bishr raiders : Lady Blunt’s stages are Itheri, Shajbeh, Kuraghiz, Mahiyeh, Maazreh, Shaybeh, Kasr and Jerawi. Huber’s stages are Melkhat, Jedeir-el- Mazer, Meisery, Jedeir, Kasayem and Jerawi. On east, valley is bounded by edge of Hamad, on west by basaltic hills and sand-hills. SULABA.—See Section II, sub-section E. SULEIMAN (WILAD).—A section of the Bishr, inhabiting south part of Nefud east of Teima and Jauf Wilad Suleman, which is a great and broad valley running east-north-east and west-south-west along north edge of Harrat Kheyber; their territory is bounded on the east by Draaf. Guarmani says they have 200 horsemen and 2,500 musketeers mounted on dromedaries, and enumerates their sections as follows: Anage, Msehem, Mertad, Selimat, Gadaure, Shemlan, Sehul, Kemeshia and Bcjiaideh. SULE1MY (KASR-AS).—Small village, mentioned by Wallin, about 5 days from Hail and 6 from Medina on the Harb border, containing about 10 families. Is this Kasr above with distance exaggerated and population under estimated ? or Seleimy ? or neither ? SUNNAA.—Singular, Sani. A menial caste of smiths, everywhere distributed among the Arabs in Central Arabia. They are more skilful as mechanics than the Sulaba. Arabs do not intermarry with them. TAAMIR (BENI).—Ancient tribe which preceded the Beni Temim in Jebel Shammar and dwelt on lower course of Wadi Rummah. Palgrave seems to indicate that survivors are still found near south end of Jebel Selma. TABEH.—Beni Temim village of 250 inhabitants in Jebel Selma, 6 hours west-north-west of Peyd and 4 hours east-south-east of Sabaan. TAI.—Mountains. The ranges Ajja and Selma are sometimes so named. TEIMA.—Town on west frontier of Amir of Jebel Shammar’s dominions. It is about 210 miles almost due west of Hail. (2) It is surrounded by extre mely barren, undulating desert, with rock cropping up and sprinkled with iron stone shingle. Wallin says it stands on a mass of crystalline limestone, but little elevated above ^surrounding country : Doughty on contrary desoabeji57 site as a shallow, loamy flood-hottom. Height above sea 3,400 feet. Wallin says the only cultivable parts are sand-patehes which have encroached on the rock. Town consists of 3 main parts : Haddaj, the main and central village and 2 detached portions called Shark and Gharb. (See plan in Doughty I, 287.) Doughty says there are 3 mk* and 15 small haraU ; Huber that there are 60 plantations/ Town looks like one immense palm-grove. Few houses stand on streets or lanes, but in plantations belonging to owners ; they are of clay and most have 2 storeys. Each of the 3 wards is walled externally and the interior consists of a labyrinth of shady lanes. According to Huber there are 60 separate plantations. On west at less than 1 mile are rums of an ancient town nclud- ing remains of columns. Fever is unknown at Taima. (3) There is now no general wall enclosing all 3 quarters such as apparently existed in 1863. (4) Population was estimated at i00 families m 1,000 per- sons (including 20 horsemen and 150 matchlock men) in 1863 and 1,500 persons in 1880. (5) Population is entirely Shammar ; according to VY ailin ot the Ali and Hamdeh sections, according to Doughty of the Aushez section. Their speech is that of the Shammar, though they are far removed m distance from their native dira, and like their kinsmen they are tall and ready of tongue. They go havefoot but are well dressed in clothing from Irak and their women are unveiled. They are shallow-minded without foresight or reflection. Neighbouring Bedouins are Anezah, viz., Fukara, Wikid Ali, Wilad Suleman and^ Bishr. There are no beggars or destitute in Teima. (6) There is no public market or shop ; buying and selling are carried on in private houses. Camels and dates are the current coin ; there is a little silver, mostly Turkish, in circulation, but it mostly goes to Hail iu payment of Government revenue. Special sleeping carpets called eJcims are manufactured here ; they are of black wool with coloured edges and fringes. Landed property is of high value in Teima, owing to security of water-supply, which never fails. (7) The dates, including the halwa variety, are the best in North Arabia, except a few grown specially at Hail and Jauf-el-Aamir. Some of the palms adjoining the Haddaj well are 90 feet high and said to be 200 years old. Vines, figs, peaches, and pomegranates, introduced from Damascus flourish. Wheat, barley and very fine oats are grown, but not in sufficient quantities to satisfy local demand ; also millet, duksa and tobacco. Wheat and barley are reaped in first week of April. There are a few cattle and poul try in plenty. Water is abundant, clear and agreeable to drink. The main well called Haddai (public in name, but really in the hands of some of the more influential families who charge the others for its use) is on an enormous scale and perhaps the most celebrated object at Teima. The mouth has 4 unequal sides and is about 50 feet in diameter. The sides vary as much as 16 feet in level at the top ; where the side is of mean elevation, depth of well (to bottom) is about 40 feet. Water has a rise and fall of about 10 feet. No less than 48 camels are continually employed in raising water and there are 60 draw-wheel frames. Bulk of plantations are irrigated from Haddaj. (8) (9) There is mosque in each quarter and harat. (10) Teima is the westernmost frontier town of Jebel Shammar, to which it can hardly be said to belong geo graphically. It is a colony, supposed to he 200 years old, of the Shammar. It is a market town of the Sherarat who get dates here in exchange for sheep and butter ; Buwalla also come, but not every year. In 1878 Amir of HaiFs resident here was an African freedman and the revenue paid by the town was $ 4,000 a year. The ruins near Teima are of black basaltic stone and there are inscriptions in archaic Nabathean and Aramaean characters. TELUH.—See Wilad Ali. TEMIM (BENI),—Tribe said to have succeeded the Beni Taamir in North Central Arabia and to have immigrated from Howtah in the south, which they still possess. The villages of Kefar, Mustajidda, Haudha, Sebam, Bekaa, Kasr, Garal, Seleimy and Tabe in the Amir of Hail’s dominion are Beni Temim and \ of the village of Eeyd ; also the whole of Boreyda in Kaseem north of West Hummah and \ of Aneyza south of it. The Kusman generally have much Beni Temim blood. The Beni Temim are all skilful and diligent agriculturists, seldom engaging in either trade or war. They are more robust physically than the Bedouins around them ; they have a spirit of industry and a good plain58 understanding ; but they are heavy, dull, mean and inhospitable. They are more religious than their neighbours and frequent Mecca as much as pos sible. Those of Aneyza are somewhat soured in temper by their Wahabi religion. There is no account of their subdivisions or numbers. One section is mentioned called Shubaramy. TERBIAH.— Kasr with 2 wells and 10 inhabitants in the Nefud, | a day east of Heianiah. TERIFIAN (ABU).—Oasis in Wadi Sirhan, frequented by snakes and “ wild cattle,” some miles south of Kaf. TERMUS —Stony desert of disintegrated sandstone between Kusaiba, Kuwara and Kehafah. THOLE A.—Ancient village on west border of Kaseem, some miles north west of Bukerieh. THUEYRAT.—See Wadi Rummah. THUEEIR.—See Hafir. THURGHUH.—Small palm-hamlet with only 8 inhabitants on west edge of Harrat Kheybar, at head of Wadi Kahed, tributary of Wadi Rummah. It is 30 miles north of Haiet; has palms, corn and barley, also well with water at 6 feet; inhabitants are Heteym. TOOALAA.—See Wilad Ali. TUARIN.—Heserted valley in Jebel Ajja at its north-east end, at one time of some importance ; it contains Himyaritic inscriptions and ancient drawings. It is about 35 geographical miles in length from its source in south west to its mouth at north-east. It contains some water. TUMAN.—See Shammar tribe. TUWIYA.—Or Tuwail. Village in Nefud, 60 miles west-north-west of Hail. Guarm mi made population 500 ; Huber gives in oue place 80, in another 120 inhabitants. TROBAH.—Square fortlet, with wells 20 feet high, corner towers, and a few men in garrison for the Amir of Hail; stands on Hail to Najaf route, 2 days’ march east-north-east of Hail. Surroundings are extraordinarily arid, stony desert with patches of sand. Subsoil is a conglomerate quartz, flints and calcareous stones. TUALA.—Section of the Shammar. UBBEYT.—A principal summer station of the Sherarat, with a ruined site, between Teima and Jauf. Water is almost at surface. UHHIM.—Unplaced hamlet, in Amir ofjlail’s dominions. UHWE.—Small hamlet where Shammar Bedouins cultivate corn, 7 hours east-north-east from Sabaan. USCEVUASCE.—Village of 200 inhabitants mentioned by Guarmani as a short distance to the west of Kaf ; Huber questions its existence. UTA.—Village passed by Lady Blunt on way from Lakita to Hail, I mile to left of road. WADI.—See Jauf-el-Aamir. WAUIAN.—Large depressed area in the Hamad, north of Nefud and east of Jauf-el-Aamir. It is more than 120 miles long and runs south-west and north-east. It contains good pasturage. WAHAB (rsENI).—Term including several subdivisions of the great Anezah tribe. To the Beni Wahab certainly belong the Fukara (800 persons), and the Wilad Ali (3,200 persons)^ Their women go unveiled; as borderers they are not devoted, to Amir of Hail and pay his taxes unwillingly ; they obtain their dates at Kheybar. Their boundary on east is with Abreit tribe. Some59 authorities include the Bishr, Jellas and Ruwalla sections of the Anezah in the Beni Wahab. WAHABI (BENI).— Artificial tribe made up by Amir of Hail out of Sherarat, Sharamar and others with a slave for his own for their chief. ^ The Blunts fell in with 'some of them at the southernmost Birket of Zobeideh. They take care of the Amir’s mares and camels. WAKID. Also Wasid and Wajid. Village 1 mile from Lakita on route to Hail and 9 miles north-east of Hail. It lies on an open flat between moun tains. Population 150 persons. WAKSAT (JAL).—Bidge less than 100 feet high crossing Derb Zobeideh at north of Mahemiyeh (?). It runs north-west and south-east, and has length of about 40 miles. WASEITA.—Small village with about 50 inhabitants about 2 miles south west of Hail. WASIT.—Suburb of Hail on north side separated from the town by Wadi Hail and some cultivation. It was deserted in 1878, having lost 800 persons by plague a few years previously. It is not quite clear that Wasit and Waseita are different places. Guarmani has an “ TJsseta ”, •£ an hour west of Hail with population of 400, which partially corresponds with either. WATHAL.—(?) Spelt by Huber Outsal. Village, 3 full hours west-north west of Esheka and separated from it by a sandy desert through which sand stone rock protrudes everywhere. WEIBAB.—Largest village in Akda(^. v.), about 300 inhabitants. WEI SIT.—Well, in Wadi Sirhan rather less than half-way from Kaf to Jauf, is hidden among hillocks of sand covered with brushwood. It had 4 openings in 1863, and about 20 stunted palms grew near by. ZEYLUL (HAEIBAT).—Small settlement between, Gussa and Agella. ZHEBY.—Wells 2 hours’ east of wells of Sakik. ZILLAJ (DERB).—Route leading up Kharram from west and rising from 4,500 to 5,400 feet above sea level. ZOBEIDEH (DEBB AND BIBKETS).—Route of Persian Haj, from Najaf as far as the Nefud, on the way to Hail is so styled. At intervals there are traces of walls on both sides of the road and birkets or water reservoirs, some very large and in excellent preservation, occur at varying distances. The principal birkets from south to north between the Nefuds and the north end of the Mahamiyeh plain are apparently Ashak, Ashabah, laser ibn Atiah, Asheihebat, Zebala, Jemaymeh and Adhafiry ; the last is a group of 3, south central and north, bearing the same name (Huber). Lady Blunt for the same section names the birkets of Ashaar, Abdallah, Shiehayad (Asheihebat ?) and Jemaymeh. That of Ashak measures nearly 300 feet by 200 and is about 30 feet deep. At Ashabat are remains of about 100 small houses built of hewn stone; immediately north of this station the side walls of road are well preserv ed. At Asheihebat are 2 birkets, 1 round and 1 square, also ruins of considerable buildings. At Zebala are 5 great wells and considerable ruins. At Jemaymeh is a fine square birket with sides 100 feet long and depth of about 13 feet. If the plateau intervening between the Jal Batn and Jal Waksat of Huber corres ponds with Lady Blunt’s Mahamiyeh the birkets of Akabah and Athamin also fall within this section. The former and more southerly of these last is adjoin ed by 3 magnificently constructed wells, now dry, and was one of the most important stations on the route. G. C. Pm« dmla.-No. C-905 F. D,—18-11-04.-80.-C. G.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0001c2_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/5/367</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0001c2</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/5/367</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Persian Gulf Gazetteer, Part II: Geographical and descriptive materials, Section III: Central Arabia.'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1904/1904</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-02-14T01:33:52</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (125 folios)</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The volume, marked confidential, is
                           Persian Gulf Gazetteer, Part II: Geographical and descriptive materials, Section III: Central Arabia, compiled by John Gordon Lorimer, and includes the printing statement 'G. C. Press Simla - No. C-905 F. D. - 18.11.04 - 80 - C. G.'. The volume begins with notes from the author, dated 14 November 1904, and is then divided into two subsections, as follows:A - Central Arabia, South of Wadi RummahB - Central Arabia, North of Wadi RummahEach subsection, organised alphabetically by name, contains a variety of geographic information, including towns and villages, districts, physical geography, tribes and tribal sub-sections, wells, and forts.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><geographic>Arabian Peninsula</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Human geography</topic></subject><subject><topic>Physical geography</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0001c2#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>