<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00009e_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-17T17:03:30.412Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">MICROFILMED DOCUMENT DO NOT PHOTOCOPY USE IOR NEGTo:- The Political -A^ent* Bahrein. l£ No. 136/33/4/R. Headquarters. 3ind Area. iCaraolti. 9 Oct Oder 1940. 12, lv. ^ S' Subject:- Medical Examination xor Itmer^encv Qomniisejons . Sir, The attached rules for Medical Examination of Candidates for Emergency Commissions islll in future be adhered to, and are in supersession of any other orders issued on this subject. I have the honour to be Sir, Your obedient servant. m , J.F. 9/10. D.A.A. &amp; Maj or. Sind Areain Rules under which the Medical Examination of Applicants for ^mer^ency Commission in His Majesty’s Land Forces axe to oe conducted. ATEGORY. (A) Fit for general ser ice anywhere in the world . Medical Examination in accordance with instructions ^iven in Ret&gt;ulations for the Medical Services of the Arqpy 1933, Appendix II. Candidates will oe accepted according to these standards and the certificate will state fitness for service in any part of the world. (B) Fit for service m India or outside Administrative Border in immediate defence of India. Examination will ice as for rt A ,l # Each candidate must possess tne same degree of general ihysical fitness, yet certain localised defects which are no bar to the fficient performance of the duties of this category may be accepted- iach case being considered on its merits. The certificate of fitness 111 include the statement that the candidate is free from any obvious. Infinite organic disease. (C) Fit for work of a sedentary nature in India. Examination ill be on the general lines of that given in Appendix II, The candidate ill be certified free from any obvious definite organic disease likely o cause inef l iciency, death or invalidment. (D) Fit for office work such as Cenorship. A general examination to ensure that the candidate has general ood health and that his eyesight is sufficiently good for the duties o be performed. NOTE ; In the case of all categories evidence of any diseased condition or abnormality will be noted on the record of examination for future reference.THE BAHREIN PETROL! ,EtjM COMPANY LIMITED A w a 1 i, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, NO. PA-197 October 20, 1940 H. B. M’s. Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir, Dr. B.S. Chowdhury has passed me a letter for forwarding to you on the subject of A.R.P. I am attaching this letter together with copies of two earlier letters on the same subject, for whatever action you may deem desirable. Yours very truly, R.* A. KENNEDY Chief Local Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED( 3 ) Refinery, October 18th, 1940 The Rouble,His Brittanic Majesty*s Political Agent, Bahrein. THRU: THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Dear Sir, May I request you to kindly refer to my letter dated the June 12th, 1940, a copy of which is enclosed for ready reference and your reply thereto communicated to me by the Company^ Chief Local Representative in his letter dated the June 20th, 1940^ CL copy of which is also enclosed for ready reference * ^ ments in Aviation, the mobility and striking range of Aircraft in War time, also on account Of the developments in Aeroplane Carriers, even the geographical position of Bahrein has not been sufficient to help and we have been very lucky that even without A.R.P. measures our Refinery has been saved and there have been no casualties. scheme for the defence of Local Civil population, the Refinery and Awali has got to prepared and worked out and since in India I have attended a Course of Instructions in Air Raid Precautions, my services as an Hon*y Air Warden are at your disposal. / It is evident now that owing to the remarkable develop- Under the present circumstances, a definite comprehensive Yours respectfully, Dr. B.S. Chowdhury, Awali.THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Awali, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. June 20th 1940. Dr. B. S. Chaudhury, Awali. Dear Sir, Referring to your letter to H.B.M v s Political Agent with regard to A.R.P. we quote below an excerpt from his letter acknowledging receipt : 'Would you be good enough to tell Dr. Chaudhury that I much appreciate his letter, but that owing to the geographical position of Bahrein Air Raid Precautions are not considered necessary in present circumstances. Should there b# any radical change in the war situation inrolving possible danger from air raids in this area I shall not forget Dr. Chaudhury’s offer of assistance.' Yours very truly, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Sd/- J.S.BLACKBahrein Island, Awali Camp, June 13, 1940. The Hon f ble His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. Dear Sir, With reference to my letter dated the 18th March 1940, regarding A.R.P. measures in Bahrein forwarded by the Company’s Personnel Manager to your goodself, I take this opportunity to invite your personal attention to the fact that with the recent developments, Bahrein which might have been considered in the past as being immune from an air attacK, no longer appears so. Under the circumstances the only defence which is open to civil papulation is passive defence i.e. precautions and pre parations, designed to give the enemy as vague and uncertain a target as possible and to minimise the effects on any bombs that may be dropped. These preparations must be made and practised in time of peace and cannot be hurriedly improvised at the spur of the moment. In the interest of the civilian population in Bahrein, I think there is the immediate necessity of practising ’’Black Out' on a certain date throughout the Island specially at the Aivali and Refinery and the effect to be watched by Civil and Military Air Craft. If the local Government feels interested in this, I can submit a comprehensive scheme for practising 'Black Out” and the preliminary measures regarding restrictions for the street and exterior lighting, vehicle and interior lights. Further, with the permission of the Bahrein Petroleum Company, of which I am an employee, apart from my ordinary duties I beg to offer my services as an Honorary Air Warden or in any other capacity that I may be considered fit for. Yours faithfully, Dr. B.S. CHOWDEURY, Awali Camp. cc: Mr. J. S. Black, Dr. R. A. Kennedy, for favour of information.No.C/820-12/19 Political Agency, Bahrain, the 26th October 1940 To The Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited Please refer to your letter No.PA-197 dated the 20th October 1940. 2. Would you kindly tell Dr. Chowdhury that I very much appreciate the offer of his services and that his special qualifications for A.R.P. work will be borne in mind ? Bahrain Dear Sir, Yours faithfully, for Politica, / A Agent, Bahrainid. lbs % Telegram Q India Office, London, Political Agent, Bahrain 6549 From To No Dated and received the 25th October 1940 Your better dated the 31st August No.C/687-12/19. Day. Air Ministry enquire (a) actual age (b) whether you consider him to have a reasonable educational standard (including knowledge of elementary mathematics) and ability to reach this standard after further instruction and (c) whether he is really keen to fly and fight in air. Please telegraph reply. Betaxandum w&gt; &lt;,0° 6 -'// ' If / ^ I i::--...-' - n-- /■ ' / THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Awali, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, CON- 663. 2 r ! ^ 27th October, 1940. His Britannic Majesty*s Political Agent, BAHREIN. Bear Sir, I am, as reguested, arranging for Mr. K. S. Bay to call on you. If Mr. Bay is being considered for His Majesty*s Forces, I must inform you that he cannot, owing to the present emergency, be spared by the Company for several weeks. Yours very truly, Chief Lochl Representative. THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED.Telegram Q From Political Agent, Bahrain. To India Office, London No. 394 Dated 29th October 1940 Your telegram No.6549 dated the 25th October. Bahrain Petroleum Company cannot spare Day at present. Will telegraph when he can be spared. PoliticalCONFIDENTIAL. No. C/390 of 1940* The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to 1, The Political Agent, Bahrain. / 2. The Political Agent, Kuwait, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE, Camp,Bahrain. Dated... pc tpber .1940 . Reference to previous correspondence : Residency Printed Letter No.640-3 of 15th Tehran telegram No.28 Circular of 12th October 1940* \ n' V u Volunteers for R.A.F.Savingrara R.35. From H*M.Minister, Tehran. To Political Resident, Bushire . No.28 Circular. Dated 12th received 19th October 1940. Following from Foreign office telegram No.199 Circular of 9th October. My Circular telegram 181 paragraph 1* Telegraphic reports may now be resumed in all these cases. Full report should continue to be sent by despatch if candidate is asked to proceed. Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs. -BULIARD.THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Awali, I ■ Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, E8th October, 1940. CONFIDENTIAL CON-667 H.B.M*s Political Agent, The Agency, Bahrein, Dear Sir, I enclose an application by Mr. Simpson for a commission in the Indian Army and a certificate of medical fitness. Yours truly, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY, LTD. Enel 2Awali, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. October 26th, 1940. The Chief Local Representative, The Bahrein Petroleum Company, Ltd., Awali, Bahrein Island, PERSIAN GULF. Dear Sir, I hereby make application for an emergency Commission in the Indian Army for the duration of the war and would be grateful if you would pass this application to the proper Authorities. My Agreement with this Company expires on November 19, 1940, but I would prefer to stay here until the end of November. Yours truly,PRINTED IN MEMORANDUM To JAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED BAHREIN ISLAND, PERSIAN GULF B. P. 9 (200-75 \ B ate 28th October 79 4 WHOM IT MAY CONCERN ♦ I have examined MR, D. A, G-. SIMPSON and find him fit for service with His Majesty’s Forces in any part of the world.Confidential flo. C/854-12/19 Political Agency, Bahrain, the 29th October 1940 To The Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, B A il R A I L Dear Sir, L , h Reference your letter Ro. CO^-667 dated the 28th October 1940. 2. Will you please let me know whether in the present circumstances the Company are prepared to dispense with the services of Mr. y Simpson, and if so when he can be relieved? Yours faithfully, for Political Agent, Bahrain \To:- The Adjutant General Army Headquarters N ew. Delhi No 186/38/3/R. Headquarters Sind Area.. Karachi 17 October 1940. is t Subject;- Egjgjgency Conunisslo n In His Ma.lestvts Indian T.an d An application for Emergency Commission in His Majesty's Indian Land Forces has been received from Mr.R„H. Goody. Bahrain.. ^ yv my request he has been interviewed by the Political Agent Bahrain, a copy of the report is enclosed.. 3. 4. I also enclose a copy of Mr. R.H. Goody's Will you please let me know whether a. . Mr.. R.H. Goody can be sent to Delhi for the next Central Interview. b. . Whether his fare from Bahrain will be paid. Brigadier.. Commander, Sind Area. aakram. Copy to Political. Agent^with the remarks that it is regretted that at present no use San be made of Mr.L.t. AlmefdaT^vice 7 {IaA^- J.F. 'T7/10. L«~GOVERNMENT OF INDI* gxternal Affairs Depa i EXPRESS LETTER . . From Foreign, New Delhi. The Political Agent, Bahrain.^ (Repeated Bntconsul, Bushire) No .D • 5807-N/40. Dated the ^ October 1940. Utilization of the services of British employees of the Bahrain Petroleum Company. Reference your express letter No.C/695/i&lt;/xv, dated 3rd September 1940. 2. The Oovemment of India do not require the services of Mr. Firth at present. The issue of the above has been authorised. Additional Deputy Secretary to tne Government of India.No.C/852-12/19* Political Agency, Bahrain, the 4th November 1940. To The Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, BAHRAIN Reference correspondence resting with your « letter No.CON-622 dated the 5th September 1940 regarding Mr. Firth. 2. V»ould you please inform Mr. Firth that the Government of India regret that they do not require his services at present. . Yours faithfully. / /( for Political Agent, Bahrain. H 2 -o No.C/853-12/19 Political Agency Bahrain, the 4th November 1940 To The Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain retroleum Company Limited, Reference your letter No.PA-165, dated the 3rd October 1940. 2 . Would you please inform Mr. L.C. Almeida, - one of your employees who applied for an Smergency Commission in the Indian Army, - that the Military Authorities in India regret that at present no use can be made of his services. BAHRAIN Dear Sir Yours faithfully, for Political Agent, BahrainBahrain, November 4, 1940. H.B.m* s Political Agent, Bahrain - Persian Gulf. Dear Sir, I wish to offer my services for enlistment with the r, 0rdnanee Mechanical Engineers” and present herewith the following particulars of myself. My present position with the Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited will terminate on November 26, 1940 and it is anticipated that I shall be leaving Bahrain on the steamer 'Silver Java”, sailing on November 18, 1940 proximo, my return passage to Victoria Canada, having been made available by the above Company. It is expected that this steamer will reach Bombay during the last week of November. Until leaving Bahrain my address will be Box No. 175, Awali, Bahrain. It is hoped that a reply to this letter may be received before leaving Bahrain, but in the event of this becoming impossible, I shall endeavour to contact the Commanding Ordnance Officer at Bombay while the steamer is at that port. I must request that this application be viewed in the light of service in India or some other locality habi table by a wife, should I marry during Service. Name Age Born Parents Education Davis, Trevor Crombie Maitland 23 years Victoria, B.C., Canada, August 3, 1917. Father : British, born in England Mother : British by marriage; b. U.S. citizen. Degree of Applied Science, in Chemical Engineering, from the University of British Columbia, and studies pre requisite to University enrolment.- 2 - Employment Oil Refinery engineering and operation in United States and Bahrain. Health Bahrain Petroleum Company* s medical certificate or copy thereof to be presented when available. Military Training One month with Local Defence Corps. I shall be grateful if this information may be con veyed to the appropriate authorities. Yours very truly,( 2 %) Telegram Q Political Agent, Bahrain, Government of India, New Delhi 401 From To No Dated 5th November 1940 Your Express letter No.D.4332~N/40 dated the 31st July 2. Application for enlistment as Ordnance Mechanical Engineer received from T.M. Davis, British, age 23, single, holds degree in Applied Science, Chemical Engineering; expert enced in oil refinery engineering and operation in United States and Bahrain; has worked for a month in the Local Volunteer Defence Force. Medically fit. Prefers service in locality habitable by a wife should he marry while in service. 3. Contract with Bahrain Petroleum Company expires 26th November and expects to leave here 18th November. 4. Request early instructions. PoliticalTHE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED e,**' CONFIDENTIAL CON-673 Awali, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, October 31st, 1940. His Britannic Majesty's political Agent, BAHRAIN. Dear Sir, D. A.G. SIMPSON * In reply to your letter No. C/834 - 12/19 of October 29th, 1940. Mr. Simpson's contract with the Company expires on November 19th, 1940, and so far as the Company is con cerned he is free to do as he likes after that date. Yours very truly, R. A. KENNEliT; Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED./ Sin r*4/k i a* si \ GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. Department. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). [N .'hiAL message sent by AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to be^ trea e 9 on receipt, with the same expedition os if it had been telegraphed. To save time ana to oovtm e formalities it is drafted in the ferm of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a rp.siifinsihl.fi. ntHre.r of th.fi. Tjfi'nn.rf.WhP.ntI y 1/7 t'*' «&gt; I \JO) (/ 014/ oww VIOZr J W ! ir\ responsible officer of the Department.'] No Bahrain, * C/874-12/19 Dated the XXSBBCSC^ 11th November 19 40 To Foreign, New Delhi# Reference Express letter No# D.4332-N/40 dated 31st July 1940. X9C 2. I have received application for Emergency Commission in the Indian Army from Mr. D.A.G# Simpson, a British employee of the Bahrain Petroleum Company. His age is 28 and he has passed the Lower School Certificate, completed a Commercial Course and is at present employed in office routine connected with housing arrangements and personnel. He has no technical qualifications and no military experience. His contract with the Company expires on the 19th November and he is willing to take up any appointment which the Army authorities may give him. 3. He is polite and well-mannered and appears suitable for employment in administrative work but I do not consider him suitable for a regimental commission. I request instructions by telegram. Political Agent, Bahrain.£ j ^__ 51 3 9 / 40 . A.109981/40 / M.5.B, AI R lyj;KIsTRY Dept • ■c J « J • Adastral House, Kingsway, W.C.2. 14th September 1940, Dear Peel, Thank you for your letter oi the 6th September reference PZ.4793/40 enclosing copy of a telegram from ^he Political Resident in the Persian _ G-ulf, regarding Mr. Chandler 1 s applica tion for service in the Royal Air \ Force. I am afraid that a B.Sc. in oil engineering and refinery is no~G a qualification that we could use, so perhaps you will be good enough to inform the Political Resident accordingly, and request him to thank Mr. Chandler a.or the offer of his services. Yours sincerely, (SIGHED) P.H.SHONE. R.T.Peel Esq., India Office, Whitehall,CONFIDENTIAL. No - C/462 of 1940. P//?- The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to 1 . The Political Agent, Bahrain. 2. The Political Agent, Kuwait, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu mentj^. for information. H British Consulate-General, \ __ BTJSHIRE. Camp, Bahrain. Dated 12th November, 194C. ~~ ! Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date Tehran Telegram No.29 Saving of 25th October 1940. Subject. Volunteers for R.A.P.Telegram No.29 Saving. .British Legation, , Tehran. 25th October,1940 To: .oritconsul, Bushire. Following from Foreign Office, telegram No.208 Circular My telegram Circular no'. 40 of July 9th. upper age limit for experienced pilots for operational flying duties and candidates for entry into pilot training has been raised to 30 plus (i.ecandidates must be under 31). That for other air crew duties is still 32 plus. Ends. of 20th October, 1940 Bullard.1.&amp;.-J 9 s * t^jn /-ir* Telegram Q. From Government of India, Mew Delhi. To Political Agent, Bahrain. No. 4440 Dated and received the 13th November ID4C Your telegram No.401 dated November 5th. T.M.Davis. 2. Unless further and much fuller particulars can be given it is regretted that we cannot consider v/hether his services can be utilised as Ordnance Mechanical Engineer. Foreigniio. C/885-1S3/19 political Agency, Bahrain, 16th November 194U To The Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain petroleum Co*, Ltd., B A H K A I N Dear Lir, A reply from liovernment of India has been received regarding the request of Mr, T.M, Davis for Military service. It is requested that if there is no objection he may kindly be asked to call at this office as soon as possible. Yours faithfully. political Agent, Bahraini By Ai UaM- ^ y Air Mail. P.Z.„ - J * te jwk. v-'X'' INDIA OFFICE, LONDON, a3r Forwarded with the compliments of the Secretary, Political Department, India Office. A copy has been sent to l..*T^$sSuL&lt;5« a . by Mail^( ^ Lfe ° The Foreign Secretary, Government al India. The Political Resident in the Persian. Gulf. (11807) Wt.27899/P.287 2,000 9/39 A.&lt;fe BJV'.Ltd. dp.685'h India Office f iiitehall. q m bj « ft- * P.f iSGS/ 40 * 11th September X040, y Sir, g / v' I am directed by the Secretary of State for/India to forward, to be laid before the Secretary of otate for foreign /^Tairc, a copy of two iiomoranda from the Political Resident in the Persia;? Gulf, forwarding the text of Regulations Nos. 2 and 3 of 1940 which provide for control over the departure of male European British subjecta from Bahrein and Koweit and were issued by him, under authority from the Secretary of State for India, on the 29th July as a matter of urgency under the Persian Gulf States (Emergency) Order in Council, 1939# a cop'r of ' the previous correspondence 4 ^-exchanged with the Political Resident on the subject has already been sent to your Department (vide India Office printed letter Ho# P#2.4051/40, dated the 30th July, and connected papers)* I am to request that if the decretory of State for Foreign ,vffairs concurs in the action taken, the appropriate steps may be taken i*he Under Secretary of State, Foreign Office, S # W.1# —^ p *■ &lt;4 J herewith 42 copies or ^cn Regulation together with 5 conies for the file© of your d*r&gt;»rtneni# though the Regulations h^ve alrssdy been issued as urgent the Political Resident my prefer to substitute printed copies when he announces the approval of the Secretory of 3 taie* 1 em 9 Sir, four obedient Servant the Under-decret«ry of Indio Office#P. ^ 4862 / 40 . India Office, litehall, l* 11th September I'-^u# € I am directed bv the secretary of State for India to forward, to be laid before the Secretary of otate for foreign iJTfairs, a copy of two memoranda from the political ReeidenV in the Ferala.n Gulf, forwarding the text of Regulations Nos. 2 and 3 of 1940 which provide for control over the departure of male European British subjects from Bahrein and Koweit and were issued by him, under authority from the secretary of State for India, on the 29th July as a matter of urgency under the Persian Gulf tates (Emergency) Order in Council, 193V. a cop/ of the previous correspondence i^xehanged with the Political Resident on the subject has already been sent to your Department (vide India Office printed letter l o. P. 2.4061/40, dated the 50th July, and connected papers). I am to request that if the secretary of State for Foreign Affairs concurs in the action taken, the appropriate steps may be taken O^he Under Secretary of State, by/ Foreign Office, . .1. An r- K f&lt;693/191/91' FORK! r&gt;H 1-.^ ,■ . I*.. » c3 *^ri x* ,1940 I fcith reference to your l«tt#r of 11th 5epte her (P.2 forw»r^inf? the text of Persian Gulf Begwlptions Hos.P an&lt;? S of mo, I mo. directs hy Viscount Halifax to inform you, for the Infarction of the Secretary of Stute for In&lt;ila# that he approves these Regulation®* 2m 1 mo to tr^nanlt to you herewith 42 cooleo of each Regulation together with 5 eoniea for the files of your &lt;?e^»rtnent. though the Regulations heve p! ready b^en issued as urgent the Political Kesldcsit uwiy prefer to substitute printed copies when he announces the approval of the Secretary of StntS* 1 mm 9 i i r, Tour obedient Servant &lt; ^xfJU^j QomULiu^ the Undei—3ecret?try of State, Indie Office.BAHREIN. NOTICE. Che following Regulation made by the Political Resident in the ian Gulf and hereby declared to be urgent is published for general 'matiom C. G. PRIOR, Political Pesident in the Persian Gulf. Bahrein, July 29, 1940. Regulation made under the Persian Gulf States (Emergency) Order in Council, 1939. No. 2 of 1940. This Regulation shall apply in the territory of the Shaikh of Bahrein, shall be applicable to all male European British subjects therein. 2. A male European British subject residing in Bahrein shall not eed from within ihe boundaries of that territoiy to a destination ide it, except with the leave of the Political Resident. 3. Any person failing to comply with an order made in pursuance his Regulation shall be liable to a penalty of impnsonment which extend to six months or to a fine extending to Rs. 1,000/- or to both. 1. The powers conferred on the Political Resident by Article 2 of Regulation maybe exercised in Bahrein by the Political Agent. Bahrein, Jidy 29, 1940. C. G. PRIOR, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. 11183 21810—1H. B. M.* s Political Agent, The Political Agency, Manama, Bahrein. Awali, Bahrein, Wovem.bsr 18th, 1940 w tx, -Ov &amp; \ Dear Sir. With reference to /ur conversation of this morning, I present herewith the following information, in amplification_of of my letter of 'November 4th, 1940. I shall be most grateful if you will be so kind as to forward this reformation to the appropri ate authorities. Education: St Michael’s School, Victoria, .0., school) Oak Bay High School, Victoria, course Junior Matriculation and university 1925-1930 (a nrivate 1930-1933 leading to entrance. 1933- 1934 Oak Bay High School, special course in Chemistry and Physics, through the kindness of the Principal who holds degrees in these subjects. 1934 - 1 Q 35 Victoria College, Victoria, B.C. general course equivalent to the first year of The University of British Columbia, ith which trie college is affiliated. 1935- 1 Q 39 The University of British Columbia, Vancouver, p. .C., course leading to degree of Bachelor of Applied Science in Chemical engineering, the total course requiring five years. Uhe scope of this course is out 1 ined below. The first three years are devoted to general engineering, vvitn greatest stress being laid upon the ap ; lication of mathematics and physics in the solution of problems of Civil and Mechanics! Engin eering, the mathematics being studied concurrently. oonslderaole importance is placed upon thermodynamics in i os me..e aspects in connection with heat engines. A small amount of analyt ical chemistry is given also draughting and ele entary design. The major theme of these years is praccical engineering* A monch^s course in surveying is given at the end of the second and third y 0 gQ^g # The fourth year is the first year oi s nciaiization, n .a. is devoted to advanced courses in analytical chemistry, geology, ana organic chemistry, and also hydraulics, metallur g, stasis cics, physical chemistry and theoretical physics in_connection with atomic structure and behaviour. I received u.ira place in our class of fifteen, in the examinations of this year. The final year is devoted to advanced uhermooynamics, in connection with gas behaviour, and the P-V-T deviations, uno also with determination of reaction equilibria, and electrochemical phenomena. Also studied are problems in fluid^flow and heat urans- fer, d ffusional processes, industrial stoicnometry, aistillatio and evaporation, filtration etc. Theoretical chemisury, , mainly to its thermo dynamic phases, industrial chemistry and elec ro- 2 - smistry, end f .rt er study of organic chemistry. The major item the fifth year was, however, the thesis occupying some seven or hours a day. In my case this was in connection with the design 1 construction of glass equipment for the separation of the higher :ty acids, 1th the object of isolating and measuring t: e physical rerties of stearic acid, and distearyl ketone and later the pure Irocarbon to be prepared by its reduction. Actually this was not lished in the time at my disposal. Prior to graduation I was contacted by the Standard Oil Coir any oz Lifomia, for service with The Bahrein Petroleum Company limited, 1 I accented this position rather than return to pursue post-graduate idies. Immediately folio ing graduation I ent to San Francisco 3 re I was employed for two months in the engineering office of the uidard company and given minor engineering problems. Folio ing this vas transferred to the Stan.ard refinery, at Richmond, Calif., where time was scent in learning the practical side to the various phases refinery operation, during the next six months. I left the Standard npany, in January, to come to Bahrein in accordance .it the original ierstanding. During my time in Bahrein, I have been operating refining equipment a regular operator, hile doing this I have gained first hand :erience in most of the practical asrects of rrocess industry, and re learned such matters as pipe-fitting, operation and repair of itrollinz instrrrents, purr os, compressors, to, the general c* re o. lioment of various types, including lines and vessels for service high temperatures and pressures. :e oi erating nractices in an industr; 'here the slightest errors r result in 'fires or explosions, is yet I have had no administrative nerience other than directing a ore', of natives. I have resigned from The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited, at the l of ni ie months’ service as a result cf t 1 e fact that this er. ire riod has been devoted to -cork o: suer a nature g .z 1 r den men with no previous technical training, and that tne rate of rancer e it of British technical staff in Bahrein t ositions equii , technical knowledge is too si w for me to consider continued, non- chnical service at the salary rate which it is the company’s policy maintain. For reasons best known to themselves, twe cowcany have -lined to become committed to any suggestions which might provide solution to this problem, leaving no alternative to resignation rn their services, hy salary at the date of resignation was f 1 fJ. 3. n r ps reasonable to exrect an increase uo , — n ^ anzary 9 v-■ g i^ cr qw salaam , ho ever, s ii...- — ema. n -•.. i— i i^nu qvi e a lasting solution to the problem. In vie of the fact that 3 iw: eclate future promises to be satisfactory w w is - 'sps u, „ thp't my value as a source of foreign i come, W3 fcae jiG .-ire t^ar fort, is less t- an it would be ere I irectly engaged in the oroduct- i of materials for the prosecution of this 7/ar. ^ . w steamer, SS’Bloei fontein’, ill reach omoa; at owe rad ox y z : str . or shortly before t en, and I take the liberty oi s ^ re.- . at a renl' or other com imication be sent to me in care e 10 , Bombay*. In any event I shall en: eavour to contact the Commanding 5 inanee icer in that city. .. , . , I anolo-mise for the iengt of this letJery wit cr^s u oi»at i ^ 3 vide the desired information. Yo 1 irs very tru_L 3 /, - - ' r, revor C. . .visGOVERNMENT OF INDIA Department. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). Confidential [N.B. —This is an ORIGINAL message sent ly AIR MAIL which provides a means of communieation more expeditious than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended to he treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the ^Department.] Political Agency, To External Affair department Government of India Hew Delhi Mmmtxsik Reference your 4 telegram Ho. 4440 dated the 13th November 1940 on the subject of Mr. T. M. Davis^ 1 application for enlistment as an Ordnance Mechanical Engineer. I now enclose a letter dated^November 18th from Mr. Davis which contains full details of his qualifications and e xperience. It is requested that the decision of the Government of India may please be communicated to Mr. Davis at the following address as he is leaving for India today C/o The Eastern Bank Bombay Political Agent, BahrainDR* B. S. CHOWDHDRY Awali Camp, November 17, 1940. The PERSONAL ASSISTANT to KIS BRITANNIC MAJESTY f S POLITICAL AGENT, Bahrein. l ■ Dear Sir, I have an appointment with H.B.M'a Political Agent and shall/ call at your Office on Wednesday the 20th instant at 9.00 A.M. I shall be thankful if you will please lay the. relevant papers and correspondence if ^ny, in connection with the following:- Referring to A.R.F. Measures in Bahrein. If any detailed scheme of A.R.P. Measures in hand? Air Raid signal for the civilian population outside Awali and Refinery? location of First-Aid posts? Organising a few A.R.P. workers and arranging to give them training in A.R.P. work ? Adequacy and efficiency of Fire Brigade ? TTiether any necessity of creating a civilian honorary appointment as an Air Warden ? Organising Indian Wing of the local Defence Volunteer Corps { Land as well as Naval ) ? Bahrein Broadcasting Station, its scope and whether extension of scope towards propaganda work desirable ? IV Regarding my two applications addressed to the Admiralty and Air l^inistry, london. V Miscellaneous. \ I hope the date and time will be convenient to His Britannic Majesty*s Political Agent. Yours faithfully, I (a) (b) (0) (d) 1 (e) (f) II III B.S. CHO/BHURY Copy to: Br.R.A. Kennedy for information. 0 ? L i y/,Av/ali Bahrein, November 10th, l*:-40 B. v ' ,r . 1 s Political Agent, The Political Agency, /!. /'UM c ! /fr X( Manama, Bahrein. ar Sir. It has ,just been brought to my attention that a grave 3 understanding exists between Che Bahrein Petroleum Company limited l myself, regarding an opinion which has been erroneously attributed yourself. I take this op ortunity to ex ress my most sincere regret .uable time should have been wasted in a matter so obviously absurd. In the course of a conversation with the personnel department, 1 itioned having recently called at the Political Agency, to discuss 'airs of a personal nature. Later in the conversation I mentioned that ^ad been advised against accepting return passage to Canada without )le provision being made for incidental expenses, towever, I took .ns to ensure that this advice should not be attributed to you, and ;er reiterated that my interview with you was concerning purely 'sonal matters. It is evident that this unfortunate and false conclusic 'sisted in the mind of the personnel de artment, resulting in their itacting you for verification of an opinion of w/hich it was never presented that you were the author. I must confess my surprise that i personnel department should have acted without at least requesting amplification of my remark before doing so. I am anxiously awaiting advice from the Commanding Ordnance Officer at this misunderstanding should have occurred, and that your Bombay, regarding my offer of service. Faithfully yours. (TREVOR DAVIS)C/908-12/19 No. The Political Agent, Bahrain, Presents his compliments to:— The Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, Bahrain XXX and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document ( s ) for information. The agency, BAHRAIN Persian Gulf. t the 23rd November 1940 Dated Reference to previous correspondence: Description df Enclosure. Name and Date. Letter dated the i.Oth November’ 1940 from Mr. T. x,6 Subject. W Davis, Bapco.,Telegram From To No • Dated Q Political Agent, Bahrain. Government of India, hew Delhi. 421 27th November 1940. D.E. Scott, late employee of Saudi Arabia Mining Syndicate leaving for Bombay on 3.S. Barala en route to United Kingdom to take up Military service. Requests passage on troop ship from Bombay. He will call for orders at Embarkation Commandant’s office on arrival at Bombay. POLITICALTelegram 'Q' No From To Government of India, New Delhi Political Agent, Bahrain. 4731 Dated 30th November Received 1st December 1940 \x° Your telegram No. 421 November 27th. D.E. Scott. Personnel of Defence Services only are entitled to passages by troop carrying ships. Even if Scott is proceeding to United Kingdom on military duty no passage by troop carrying ship is available. Foreign -THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Awali, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, 1-700. 3rd December, 1940. X4 7 3 Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, THE IN. ar Sir, k 2- In August of this year we released one of r nurses, Miss. Henninghem, for service with the 1.1.M.N.S. in India Because we thought we could iff our hospital satisfactorily with the remaining r ,v ree nurses. v ^ * j 2' Since then we have, as you know, made % ^ rangements to hosp ital ise, members of the various aed forces who are in Bahrein or who call here, is has increased the work of the hospital very isiderably. For example, last month 54% of the •patients and 10,^ of the out-patients were personnel the Navy and Army. In addition to this one of the remaining 'ses cannot renew her contract when it expires next nth. In the circumstances we have made enquiries out the possibility of getting Miss. Henninghem back, are informed that if you will write to the Matron Chief, New Delhi, explaining the circumstances and :ing it clear that if Miss. Henninghem cannot be .eased to us we shall have to reduce our services to 3 fighting forces, which we are reluctant to do, the tron in Chief may permit Miss Henninghem to return here, effect, if Miss Henninghem returns her work here will of considerable National importance; if she does not jurn we shall have to make - for at least some months - evere retrenchment in our assistance to the Armed •ces. I will be very much obliged if you will putC0N-700. 3rd December, 1940 - 2 - the matter to the Matron in Chief and ask if Miss Henninghem may he returned to us not later than the middle of January next. THE Yours very truly, — Chief Local Representative BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED.No. C/953-12/19 Political Agency, Bahrain, the 9th December 1940 To The Matron in Chief, O.A.I.M.N.S., New Delhi. . j Memorandum I have received a communication from the Bahrain * Petroleum Company stating that in August this year they released one of their nurses, Miss Henninghem, for ser vice with you. At that time her services could be spared without decreasing the efficiency of the hospital. Recently hov/ever owing to the loss of one of the remaining nurses the Company find that they will have to reduce the number of patients they can deal with unless they can obtain another nurse. They would like to get back Miss Henninghem if this is possible and as the hospital caters for the per sonnel of the Royal Navy it is hoped that it will be possible to send back Miss Henninghem so as to avoid any curtailment in the work of the hospital. Cl Political Agent, BahrainI Li!' c *N9rl06/ 38/3 /r. M 1 t ^ Headquarters Sind Area. i Karachi. 21st November 194 0 i Toj- Mr. R. H. Goody, Bahrein Petroleum Co; Ltd., f Bahrein . P f I Subjects- £ffl.er.M.eucy Coamlasion in His M ajesty's Indian T.anrf Forre s Dear Sir, Army Headquarters have intimated that you will be permitted to appear at a Central Interview at Delhi for selection for an Officer Cadetehip in His Majesty*s Indian Land Forces. 2* The present series of interviews will end on 18th Dec *40 but a new series will start during January 1941. 3. Will you please wire at once:- a) whether you will be able to attend the present interview at Delhi, or will appear in January 1941. b) whether you are applying for a Technical Commission.(Details attached.) 4# Please complete the attached forms and despatch as early as possible. 5. On arrival at Karachi you should report at Headquarters Sind Area for an interview with the Area Commander. 6* Please obtain a receipt for your fare from BAHRAIN to KARACHI. On arrival in India this amount will be refunded to you. 7. You will be issued with a railway warrant from Karachi to Delhi. Yours faithfully. Major. D..A. A^ &amp; Q.M.G. , vSind Area. political Agent, Bahrein. Copy toj-Telegram ' 0 ' From Political Agent, Bahrain. To Government of India, New Delhi No. 4-S? Dated 14th December 1940. For Weightman. R.N.Kirby of the Bahrain Petroleum Company has resigned and is proceeding to Bombay on S.S. /arela leaving here 17th. He is aged and is anxious to offer his services to the military authorities in any capacity, Ke is a British subject and a very decent gentlemanly man well-known to this Agency and entirely suitable for commissioned rank. Has long practical experience of oil engineering but knows no languages. If he c annot get service in India he proposes to proceed to South Africa with same object. I am sorry for short notice but Kirby only informed us today of his ; decision to join up. Anything you can do will be much appreciated by him. I have asked him to report to Embarkation authorities on arrival Bombay, and am informing them with regard his arrival. - Political -No. C/970-12/19 Political Agency, Bahrain, the 15th December 1940. To The Embarkation Commandant, BOMBAY Memorandum Mr. R.N. Kirby, a British subject, who recently resigned from the Bahrain Petroleum Company in order to offer himself for military service is proceeding to Bombay by the 3.S. T, Varel« n which should arrive on or about the 22nd December. A reference has been made to the Government of India in order if possible to secure for Mr. Kirby a commission in the Indian Army and they have been informed that Mr. Kirby will present himself to you on arrival at Bombay. Mr. Kirby who is well-known to this Agency is willing to join up in any capacity and if unsuccessful in obtaining a commission I should be grateful for any assistance and advice which you could give him while he is in Bombay in order to help him to enlist in the Army in any other capacity.Dated the 15th December 1940 The Embarkation Commandant, BOMBAY The bearer of this letter Is Mr. B*N. Kirby whose intended arrival at Bombay by the 3.5. ’’Varela* on or about the 22nd December has been reported to you in my memorandum No. C/970-12/19 dated the 15th December 1940. Political Agent, Bahrain.S) No. C/978-12/19 Political Agency, Bahrain, 16th December 1940 To Mr. R.H. Goody, c/o Mrs. E. Goody, British Families Hospital, KARACHI Memorandum Reference your letter dated the 14th December 1940. 2. Your application forms are sent herewith. Please acknowledge receipt. for Poli/tical Agent, Bahrain.t U&gt; /i IsOt} rnMPSDt &amp;*** ^ 4T1 Office of Senior Naval Officer 5 Persian Gulf, H,II. Naval Base, Bahrain, 13th December, 1940, No,191. Sir, T&gt; f I have the honour to inform you that as a result of increased services nou being carried out by the Naval h/T Station at Bahrain, I have been instructed trr the Commander-in- chief, East Indies Station to endeavour to engage 4 ladies as a Coding Staff. The ladies must be British and European and they are required, if employed, to certify that their parents are or Yfere when they died, British subjects. The intention is that 2 should irork from 0800 to 1400 and the other Z from 1400 to 2000. In the first place I propose they should be paid £8 per month. From the point of view of transport arrangements it would be preferable if sufficient volunteers for this work were available in Manama. I should be most grateful, therefore, if you Y/ould approach the local residents and ascertain if any ladies would be willing to do this work. If there are any with typing experience they would be invaluable in the organisation. You. may like to inform them that if volunteers are not obtained locally it will be necessary to obtain Naval ratings from elsewhere, so that, in fact, their volunteering Trill release men for more active employment. The Political Agent The Agency, Bahrain. £Confidential D.O.Ko.C/968 Political Agancy, Bahrain, the 15th December 1940♦ Th® Sanior Maval Officer, Persian Gulf, is desirous of engaging the services of four ladies for certain work in his office. The ladies must be British and uropaan and they are required, if employed, to certify that their parents are or %ere vhen they died, British subjects. The intention is that two should work from 0800 hours to 1400 hours and the other two from 1400 hours to 2000 hours. The salary offered is £ 8 a month. Prom the point of view of transport arrangements it would be preferable if sufficient volunteers for this work were available in b&amp;nama. Typing experience will be a valuable asset. Any offers of service will be welcome as they will release men for more active employment elsewhere. 8* I would be grateful if you would kindly ascertain from amongst your staff as to whether any ladies are willing to offfer thair services on the above terms and if so kindly forward to me their names together with the information required about their parents* 3. Would you kindly treat this as confidential ? Yours sincerely, Dalrymple Belgrave,Esq.,CBE, Adviser W.R. Smith, Esq., Gray Mackenzie &amp; Co . Gahan, Esq., Cable and Wireless hM.C. Dobbs, Esq., B.O.A.C. [.A. Gunn, Esq., Eastern Bank S.H. Lermitte, ,Esq. , P.C.L. e«PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LTD. BAHRAIN PERSIAN GULF. 15th December 1940 T&gt; CLJtA- ( In reply to your D.0* No* C/966 of to-day*s date I regret to say that all the married members of our staff are grass widowers. 2* I have noted your remarks re the confidential nature of your abovementioned letter* Yours sincerely, Major R*Gr.Alban, The Agency, Bahrain*CQPl ^ 1 RS TO BE ADDRESSED TO TERN BANK LIM ITED. LEGRAPHIC ADDRESS: EASTERTIDE. (Ihr (ta^trrn r«ank.Wtutttrh. (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND.) D««r Alban, \ / H With rafaranct to your confidential lettar D*0. N6*0/968 of tha 15th instant, I regret that none af ny rbaff know any ladle* who would bO able to do tha work mentioned therein* a.G.E.W. ALBAN, POLITICAL AGENT, BAHRAIN.m) w Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co. Ltd. (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND) BRAN C H EEL S : :AD OFFICE: DEN HALL STREET, DND0N,E.C.3. 5RAPHIC ADDRESS: GRAY. ;ODES USED: ''S COMPLETE PHRASE. 5 SECOND PHRASE CODE. BUSREH. AM ARAH. KUT. KHORAMSHAHR AHWAZ (for BAN DAR-SHAHPOUR) BUSH I RE. RAS TANURA. BUNDER-ABBAS. LINGAH. BAHREIN. KOWEIT. DUBAI. SHARJAH. MUSCAT. IN REPLY PLEASE QUOTE No DO/124. fo* fa Bahrein, 15th December, 19 40. CONFIDENTIAL A With reference to your confidential letter No. DO.C/968 of trie 15th instant, I nave to advise that Mrs. Leared, the wife of a member of our staff, is willing to offer her services for the terms mentioned. Mrs.Leared has had a certain amount of typing experience, and her parents are both British subjects. I regret, we nave no further applicants suit able. Yours sincerely, Major R. G. Alban, O.B.E., H.B.M.’s Political Agent, BAHREIN.BRITISH OVERSEAS AIRWAYS CORPORATION. BAHRAIN ISLANDS PERSIAN GULF &gt;y4 © 43M Telegrams : Flying Balirain Coties : Bentley^s &amp; I.A T.A. BAH/l/1 886/P. 3 H.B.M. The Political Agent, BAHREIN CONFIDENTIAL 16th December, 1940. t €*C go/ r. Thank you for your letter of 15 th December Nr. D.O.No. 0/968. I am sorry to say that neither of the wives of our staff here will he ahle to help the Senior Naval Officer as neither of them have had any office experience at all, and are unable to type or take short hand; MiaT.A.Millard, too, is very much occupied with looking after her three small children. I am sorry that we shall be able to be of no assistance. Yours sincerely.&amp; onfidential D.O. No. C/979 Dated the 16th December 1940 \ The Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, is desirous of engaging the services of four laides for certain work in his office. The ladies must be British and European and they are required, if employed, to certify that their parents are or v/ere when they died, British subjects. The intention is that two should work from 0800 hours to 1400 hours and the other two from 1400 hours to 2000 hours. The salary offered is £ 8 a month. Typing experience will be a valuable asset. Any offers of service will be welcome as they will release men for more active employment elsewhere. 2 . I would be grateful if you would kindly ascertain from amongst the Company^ staff as to whether any ladies are willing to offer their services on the above terms and if so kindly forward to me their names together with the information required about their parents. 3. Would you kindly treat this as confidential ? Yours sincerely, r. R. A. Kennedy, The Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, B A IT R A I Nhrain Government. Bahrain, Persian Gulf. December 16, 1940» Dear Alban, I am sorry not to have replied to your D.0* C/968 dated 15th December 1940, before now, but some of the ladies concerned took a long time to consider the matter* Mrs. Snow will work until the end of April when she is going to India. Mrs. I’urber will work but preferably in the morning. Mrs. Steele will work but preferably in the morning. Mrs. deGrenier will work if not enough ladies are forthcoming. All four can type a little and fulfill the conditions of your letter. I assume that transport will be arranged by the Naval .authority as none of these laaies have cars. Yours sincerely, Major R.G.E.Vu .Alban, O.B.E., H.b.M|s Political Agent, Bahrain.No. C/ 984 Political Agency, Bahrain, the 18th December 1940 f Sir, I have the honour to refer to your letter No. 191 dated the 13th December 1940 and to say that the following replies have been received from Manama*- U. j \ (1) Mrs. Leared, wife of a member of the s taff of Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co., Limited. Mrs. Leared has had a certain amount of typing experience and her parents are both British subjects. (2) Mrs. Snow will work until the end of April when she is going to India. (3) Mrs. Furber will work but preferably in the morning. ' (4) Mrs. Steele will work but preferably in the morning. (5) Mrs. de Grenier will work if not enough ladies are forthcoming. 2. The last four can type a little and fulfill the conditions of your letter. 3. It is assumed that transport will be arranged by you as none of these ladies have cars. I have t he honour to be Sir Your most obedient servant T olitical Agent, Bahrain P.S. Replies from Awali will nior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, Bahrain iDated 19th December 1940* The Embarkation Commandant, , BOMBAY The bearer of this letter is Mr. D.A.G. Simpson, formerly a British employee of the Bahrain Petroleum Company, who is proceeding to India to join His Majesty’s Forces. His application for an Emergency Commission was sent to the Government of India on the 11th November 1940 and the Government of India have b een asked to communicate their decision on his application to you. Political Agent, Bahrain.Telegram X From Political Agent, Bahrain. To Government 5f India, New Delhi No. 464 Dated 19th December 1940 * My express letter No. C/874 dated 11th November. O « Simpson arrives Bombay by S.S. Barpeta about 2nd January and has been instructed to r eport to Embarkation Commandant, - Political -;^5 44. GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. Department. EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL). -This is an ORIGINAL message sent by AIR MAIL which provides a means of communicahon more 'expeditious than the ordinary moil and is cheaper than the telegraph. Itu mten e nhninte on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time an ■ T ’ ’ - - ■-i n is authenticated by the signature of a formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram, responsible officer o f the Department.'] Bahrain, C/29 - 12/19 Dated Simtex. the 11th January 19 41' The Matron in Chief, Q.A.1 •¥ «N«S•, New Delhi. -H r Reference memorandum No C about Miss Henninghem. Kindly expedite reply. C/953 dated the 9th December U - Political Agent, Bahrain.— 1 THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED \. Awali, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, January 10, 1941. PA-313 His Britannic Majesty^ Political Agent, The Agency, BAHRAIN. Dear Sir, The Bahrein Petroleum Company has offered employ ment to Mr. Archibald Watt, a British subject at present in India. Watt is an experienced Refinery Operator and as we are rather short of operators, and men with previous experience are hard to find, the Company is anxious to have Watt come to Bahrein as soon as possible. Our Bombay Agents inform us that although the National service committee have recommended to the Military Authorities that Watt be permitted to leave India, such per mission has not yet been granted. If you could telegraph to Army Headquarters Delhi recommending Watt's immediate release it would be much appreciated. At the present moment Watt is employed by Caltex (India) Ltd. and they are agree able to his transfer to this Company. Yours truly, Acting Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED.From Telegram ”Q n Political Agent, Bahrain. To Government of India, New Delhi No. 23 Dated 13th January 1941. Bahrain Petroleum Company are desirous of procuring the services of Archibald Watt, British subject, at present employed by Caltex, Bombay. They understand that although the National Service Committee have recommended to Military Authorities that Watt might be allowed to leave India, permission has not yet been received. Becommend early orders be issued as Watt is urgently required by Company. PoliticalD.O. No. C/33 - 12/19 The 13th January 1941. / V) I would be grateful for an early reply to ajy letter No* C/979 dated the 16th Decociber 1940 to Kennedy about lady volunteers for work in the Naval Base* Youra sincerely, y.K* Lipp, Esq*, a v, a b i *PARTICULARS OF CARRIER OF MR. R. N. ANDERSON Educated at Royal High School, Edinburgh, obtaining Leaving Certificate of Scottish Board of Education. Trained as Motor Engineer with Messrs. Rossleigh Ltd., Shangwick Place, Edinburgh. Joined Royal Army Service Corps as Driver on 1st September 1951. Served in Egypt from 4th January 1954 till 50th October 1958. Army qualifications - 1st Class Certificate of Education and Driver-Mechanic Class I (remustered). Employed by Iraq Petroleum Company, as Maintenance Mechanic from 18th March 1938 to date.Telegram 'O' From Political Agent, Bahrain To Government of India, New Delhi No Dated 18th January 1941 B.N. Anderson of Petroleum Concessions Limited ^atar whose contract expires very shortly has applied for military service. He would prefer General Duties Branch, Royal Air Goirce. Educated Royal High School Edinburgh. Obtained Leaving Certificate of Scottish Board of Education. Trained motor engineer with Messrs Rossleigh Edinburgh. Served with Royal Army Service Corps as driver on 1st September 1931. Served in Egypt 4th January 1934 to 30th October 1938. Army qualifications first class certificate of e ducation and driver mechanic class I (remustered). Employed by Iraq Petroleum Company as maintenance mechanic from 18th March 1938 to date. U'y* Mould appear to be/Suitable for commission in technical line. He is due to leave in about a week and requests early reply. - Political -k# THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED \ * Awali, Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf. January 16th, 1941. CON-724 Major B.G-.E.W, Alban, His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, The Agency, BAHRAIN. A \X I have for acknowledgement your letter D.O. No. C/33 - 12/19 dated January 13th, 1941. Prior to his departure on short leave Kennedy had made some enquiries around the Camp hut apparently without any success. I am having these enquiries con tinued and hope to he in a position to advise you the result in the course of the next few days. Yours very truly^^N // • Acting Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN EETROLEM COMPANY LIMITED.4 CONFIDENTIAL. N 0 . 28-S of 1941. \-i ®) {&amp;) -vr The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to 1 . The Political Agent• Bahrain# 2® The Political Agent» Kuwait* and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docement//). with the request that any references should in the first place be made to him* British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated .1 ? n . U ®. r ?.. »hran Savingram No* 35f dated te 27th December 1941* VOLUNTEERS FOR FREE FRENCH SERVICES.y r$r 79/65 DEGYPHER INTER. 8. Savingram No. 35. British legation. Tehran. 27th December 1940. To:~ Britconsul. Bushire. Following extract from Foreign Office telegram No. 232 Circular of 20th December, 1940. Begins. All persona presenting themselves to you as volunteers for service under General de Gaulle, Save those covered by paragraph (i) above, should be dealt with as under: (4) You should first obtain name of volunteer, check his statement, wherever possible, particulars including name, age, rank and service in Trench armed forces or rating in mercantile marine and any special technical qualifications including experience in colonial or other State bervice, or in (gr:mutd) ing map (gr:mutd) or other experience of possible value. Also (gr:mutd) health and fitness to serve in any climate. (5) You should note for your own quidance and may as necessary inform volunteer that: (a) The lowest limit for volunteers for fighting services is 55 for officers and 40 for iion-commissioned officers and men. There is no age limit for merchant service or Civil posts so long as volunteer is physically fit and otherwise qualified to fulfil his duties. (b) Civil posts in Free French Services are limited in number and volunteers are most^likely to be accepted for such posts unless paooiitg special qualifications or previous experience, especially if volunteer is within limits of military age given above. (c) Volunteers for tank corps must be prepared to serve in infantry until a vacancy occurs •^d) Volunteers will only be accepted directly for Air Force if they are already skilled aircraft maintenance mechanics or qualified pilots with a minimum of 250 flying hours on service or commercial types* (e) Other volunteers for Air Force must be ready to serve unconditionally in free French Navy or army, their subsequent transfer to air force depending later on opinions of their suitability, training facilities and requirements* (f) Officers and non Commissioned Officers will only be accepted by General de Gauli£ * n ranks which they have previously held in French Navy, Army or Air Force or on reserve* ITomotion subsequent to joining will be at will of General de Gaulle. (g) Volunteers will not normally be accepted unless they are physically fit to serve in any climate and willing to do so* (6*) fhe question whether persons joining the free French Forces may be allowed to send remittances to their families abroad is now under consideration and further instructions will be given to you as soon as a decision has been reached* Meanwhile enquiries should be answered on lines of warning that it must toot be assumed that such remittances can be allowed nor that family allowances will be payable to families outside sterling area. (7) If any doubt regarding military qualifications i claimed by volunteers or on any other technical military question involved, you should consult appropriate British Service Attache to H. M. (grsmutd^ in your country of residence, or advise to Governor of Colony in which you reside. Define such qualified British Officer hardly igr:mut&lt; available consult, you are at lib«rty to refer lgr:mutd) to me. BUXIAHDNO ENQUIRY RESPECTING THIS TELEGRAM CAN BE ATTENDED TO WITHOUT PRODUCTION OF THIS COPY, Sept. 1938. (12339 Pads.) CABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED. (incorporated in England) ^ m ; Clerk’s Name. 4 n Time Received. KN258/V NEWDELHISUB 22/21 22 01 KR BG POLITICAL AGENT BAHRAIN Mbo YOUR C/ 953-1 2/19 DECEMBER NINTH TO RELEASE MISS ENNINGHEM FROM ARMY REQUIRES WAR OFFICE SANCTION ETTER FOLLOWS , , AG - Lx*. MARK YOUR REPLY ‘2%a Jm/ie?UaCZTelegram ,, 0 ,, From Government of India, New Delh To Political Agent, Bahrain. No. 327 Dated 23rd January 1941 ^our telegram No. 23 January 13th. Orders issued on January 8th for grant of exit permit to Watt, Foreign -No. C/85 - 12/19 Political Agency, Bahrain, the 26th January 1941 To The Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, BAHRAIN Dear Sir, Please refer to your letter No. PA-313 dated the 10th January 1941 regarding Mr. Archibald Watt. 2. I understand from the Government of India that orders have been issued on the 8th instant for the grant of an exit permit to Mr* Watt to enable him to leave India. You may therefore expect Mr. V/att in Bahrain fairly soon. Yours faithfully, L \ Political Agent, BahrainTelegram From Q. Government of India, New Delhi. To Political Agent, Bahrain. No. 394. Dated 26th received the 27th January 1941. Your telegram No.25 of January 18th. Anderson over age for flying duties. Air Head quarters prepared consider him for enlistment in Hoyal Air Force as tradesman but cannot offer definite appointment without interview. If he touches India on his way home he should report for interview to Air Force Recruiting Officer care of Aircraft Depot, Drigh Road, or care of Technical Recruiting Officer, Esplanade Maidan, Fort, Bombay. These officers have been instructed to show him terms and condi- tionsof service in Royal Air Force and to submit a report to Air Headquarters as to his suitability or otherwise for enlistment as t radesman or in any other capacity. No expenses will be paid in connection with interview. Foreign.D.O. No. C/98 - 12/19 The 29th January 1941. Reference our conversation this morning. I forward herewith a copy of a telegram received from the (Government of India about Anderson. V. 'acker, Ksq., Manager, etroleum Concessi ns Ltd*, Yours sincerely, LNo.C/105-12/19 Politicrl Agency, Bahrain, the 30th January 1941. To The Chief Local Representative The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited BAHRAIN Dear Sir, W- Please refer to your letter No. C0N-700 dated the 3rd December 1940 regarding Miss Henr.inghem. 2. I have had a reply from the Adjutant General in India to the effect that Piss Henninghem, being a member of the Reserve, has been embodied within the establishment of the Q.A.I.M.N.3. in India under orders from the v.'ar Office. The ouestion of her release from the service can only be considered by that office on a specific request being made by iss Henninghem herself to that effect. 3. I would suggest, therefore, that Miss Kenninghen should apply herself for release in the first instance. General on the subject in the hope that he will relent. Yours faithfully Political Agent, Bahrain. Hb p.s I have however w ritten again to the AdjutantCONFIDENTIAL. vi i The Hon ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Political A^ent, The Political Agent, Kuwait, Bahrain, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docement (/£). British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated...* ;? %v % Reference to previous correspondence : ,! 8 ? ^ Resiaency P,L* Bo. 28-8 dated 11th January 1941, Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Tehran Saving Bo, 5 dated 17th January 1941, to Political Resident, Bushire, Subject. VOLUNTEERS FOR FREE FRENCH SERVICES.ftp. b-Saving, British Legation, Tehran, 17th January 1941 v Decypher M«59» To- Britconsul, Bushire. .7 Reference ioy telegram ho* 35 - Saving of 27th December* Following additional ?paragraphs may be usefuls instructions also apply to persons of other x French nationality except British subjects. Such persons should not actively be encouraged to enlist but if any apply and have high qualifications their cases should be referred to London. Applications of Allied nationality cannot be accepted unless their Government agree. - BULLARD - AVliL 6/2/41CONFIDENTIAL . No. 137-3 of 1941 The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Political Agent, Bahrain. The Political Agent, Kuwait. v/ and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document (/). 0 British Consulate-General, BUSHIRB. Dated..4th.?.ehruary .1941 Name and Date. Subject. Tehran f s Circular Saving ft 0.6 dated 13th January 1941. British Volunteers for armed forces.CIRCULAR SABING No. British Legation Tehran. 18th January 1941. Britconsul following Circular telegram Uo. 1 Saving dated 25th December 1940 has been received from the foreign office; Volunteers . Delays have occurred in certain cases owing to nationality difficulties, e.g. U) where applicant has or had one paren , o alien nationality, [2) cases of dual nationaiity, and 13) pe s of second generation born abroad who are not British subjects. Position as regards acceptability of persons in above categories 4s as follows.- A. Royal Davy. Standard requirement is that candidate must be British born son of British born parents. Exceptions to^ this rule are that men may be accepted for '‘noitilities only engagements, la) if they themselves are the Bri tish ^rn sons of parents who were naturalised prior to beptomoer id) if they are aliens or the children of aliens or ii }^ eir parents were naturalised on or alter September 28th, 9b I enemy aliens being in all cases debarred), provided that they have some special qualiiications for naval service. Persons not fulfilling the standard requirement are necessarily subjected to some delay but this can be gr&lt;ja xy shortened if certificate is furnished by diplomatic or consular representative to the effect that so far as can be ascertained no security objection to the candidate’s acceptance exists. Acceptance for Royal havy is no longer confined to persons with qualifications required by my circular telegram of 9th July and suitable candidates will now be accepted -or all branches of the hoyal Mavy and Royal Marines. B. Army, ho objection is seen to the acce p tance of per - sons with one alien parent lincluding aliens and dual nationals) provided that consular officers or military attaches are able to give assurances in writing that they are reliable, lull names of such applicants should be cabled to the var Office IA.G. 10) to ascertain whether they may be accepted. Duals and aliens of pure British descent may be despatched to this country immediately, provided that similar written assurance can be given. Applicants should carry passports and the number oi the passport should oe referred to in the assurance. A declaration m writing should also be obtained t rom each applicant that he^^^ understandsand is prepared to accept the penalties to which he^p-^ renders him&amp;elf liable by enlisting in the British forces, especially if already under any obligation ior service in the forces of the country from wnich he comes. 0. Royal Air Eorce . Requires suitable candidates froki ail three categories lsee my circular telegram No. 199 (to consular officers) No. 52 lof 10th October.) - BULLARD\ l ^ \ A it i a ivi ; EXPRESS LETTER. &amp; From The Adjutant General in India The Political Agent, To Bahrain. Subject s- S ister Miss D.L.HENNINGHEM, A.I.M.T1,o.(R) Release from the service of Release from the service of /&lt; No.Z-22902/5/D.M.S. New Delhi, 7 ^ February 1941. % Reference your Express Letter No.C/106-12/19, dated the 30th January 1941. On receipt of an application from Miss Henninghem signifying her desire to return to Bahrain, the approval of the War Office to her release from the service will be obtained by telegram. for Adjutant General in India. / y(1 No GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. External Affairs Department. Dated New Delhi,the iv February 1941- A copy of the undermentioned papers is forwarded lo the Political Asent, Bahrain, for information, with reference to the correspondence ending with his telegram No.464, dated the 19th December 1940. 1. Express letter from Army Headquarters, India (A.G^. Branch) to Headquarters, Bombay District, No.B/65928/A.G.2(d), dated the olst December 1940. 2. Memorandum from Headquarters, Bombay District, to the Army Headquarters, India(A.G*8. Branch) No.51800/107/A, dated the 6th January 1941. By order, etc., Assistant Secre■ - ' _ ' ' - * ' Copy of an Express Letter No# B/6592£/4.Gr. 2(d) dated the 31st December 1940 from the Adjutant General in India, irmy Headquarters, India id.iutant General f s Branch, New Delhi, to the Head quarters, Bombay D istricw Notification has been received that a Mr. D.i.G* Simpson is due to arrive at Bombay from Bahrain by S.S. *Barpeta* about the 2nd of January 1941. Mr. Simpson will be accepted only as a B.Q.R. If, therefore he is prepared to enlist into the ranks, will you please take the necessary action accordingly, and inform all concerned# Copy of a memorandum No. 51800/107/i, dated Bombay the 6th January, 1941, from the Commander, Bombay District to the Arm Headquarters, India, Adjutant General’s Branch, NEW DELH I. ENLISTLIMT- B.O.R.S . Reference your No. B./65928/i.G.2(d) datec the 31st December, 1940. Mr. D.i#G. SIMPSCN reported to these Headquarters on the 6th January 1941 and was inform -ed that he would be accepted as a B.O.R. He is not prepared to enlist in the ranks, and expressed his intention of leaving India for England on the next ship.Telegram From To No. Dated Inter. Political Agent, Bahrain. Commander, Bombay District. 1st March 1941. P Your telegram No.581/A dated the 27th February. Nothing known against V/alker who is said by Bahrain Petroleum Company 'to be quite suitable for commission Petroleum Company Development do not recommend ' Anderson.' I have seen latter who is quite unsuitable for Commission of rank- Political/\/7? MAiZ- EXPRESS LETTER From The Adjutant General in India* To The Political Agent, Bahrain. V* v ? K No.Z-22902/6/D.M.S. | \ ^ New Delhi, ^ March 1941. Reference correspondence ending with this office Express Letter No.Z-22902/5/D.M.S., dated the 7th February 1941. It is regretted that owing to exigencies of service the War Office have not approved the termination of the embodied service of Sister Miss D.L.Heninghem, Q.A.I.M.N.S. (Reserve). for Adjutant General in IndiaNo. C/270 - 12/19 Political Agency, Bahrain, 23rd March 1941 To The Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, B A H R A I N Reference correspo __ th my Printed Letter No. C/149 dated the 17th February 1941. v 2. It is regretted that owing to exigencies of service the War Office have not approved of the termination of the embodied service of Sister Miss D.L. Henninghem. Yours faithfully, for Political Agent, BahrainExtra at from letter No. P/&gt;-452 dated the 5th April 1941 from the Chief Local Rep resentative, The Bahrain Batroleum Company Limited, to the Political Agent, Bahrain. Would ou kindly issue Exit Permits to enable the following British employees of this Company to leave Bahrein : **** **** **** Mr. L.W. Murphy : Refinery Operator, who is due to leave about the middle April for South Africa by tanker, thence to United Kingdom. The Company would like to have Mr. Murphy return to Bahrein but he insists upon proceeding to England.THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Awali Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, April 13, 1941 PA -461 His Britannic Majesty's Political Agent, Bahrein. Bear Sir, Some of our' men who recently returned from leave in India report that they had great difficulty in obtaining exit permits there. The authorities in India seemed to think that these men should have had official evidence that they were employed here on work of national importance. Do you think it will he possible for you to issue to men going on leave some document that will facilitate their re turn? Chief Local Bepresentative THE BAHHELT PETBOIBTM COITPANY LTD.ifidential No.C/348-12/19 Political Agency, Bahrain, the 21st April 1941. To The Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, Bahrain. \ \&gt; Dear Sir, Please refer to your letter No.PA-461 dated 13th April 1941- 2. As you know we already issue a certificate in the form attached to personnel proceeding on short leave to the United Kingdom. Similar certificates can be obtained from the Agency by persons proceeding on leave to India. These should facilitate their return to Bahrain. Yours faithfully, for Political Agent, Bahrain-29/13„ Political Agency, Bahrain (Persian Gulf) Dated CERTIFICATE Mr, , an employee of The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, Bahrain, is proceeding on short leave to the United Kingdom, He is due to return to duty with the Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, Bahrain, on expiry of his leave, and it Is requested that he be permitted to proceed from the United Kingdom accordingly. Political Agent, Bahrain.l-tt .tlx / &amp; Telegram Q. From Political Resident, Rushire. Political Agent, Bahrain No. 303 ^ated and received the 36th April 1941. Can you say when Royal Air Force are likely to release Nrs. Leaned ? I understood Coates was not returning to Bahrain.Telegram From To K T o. 92 Q. Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Resident, Bushire. Dated the 28th April 1941. t Your telegram No. 303 Mrs Beared may be released in about month's time. Coates' return unknown. PoliticalTelegram Q From Political Resident, Bushire. To Political Agent, Bahrain. No. 307 Dated and received the 28th April 194 -l.. &gt;c My telegram No. 303 dated April 26th. Beared is very anxious that his wife should (word omitted ’’join”?) him by next mail and points out that she only remained behind to enable Coates to get away. p lease telegraph when she will be released. 9 3 C/b- -v ' ■■■ , Jr 1 . sh . 0Telegram From 0 . To No. 96 Dated the Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Resident, Bushire. 29th April 1941. v Your telegram No. 307 I have already replied to your telegram No.303 and have again asked A.L.O. Chadwick to get a relief for Mrs. Beared at once. Will wire result. PoliticalTelegram From To Repeated No. 320 Q • Political Resident, Bashirs. Air Officer Commanding, ’Iraq. Political Agent, Bahrain. Dated and received the 30th April 1941. Beared is anxious about his wife who is Air Liaison Officer, Bahrain’s cypher officer. When Beared came to Bushire Coates assured him before departure that there would be no diffi culty about her release and he left her there on that understanding. As there is danger that her Persian visa may expire and passage is avail able about May 8th he requests that she may be relieved by then.Telegram 'O' From To No. Dated Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Resident, Bushire. i0 l 4th May 1941 eA Your telegram No. 320 to A.O.C. 2. Chadwick assures me that Mrs. Leared can be released at once and can go on the next steamer. Political -CONFIDENTIAL. No. 232-S of 19 41 The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to 1. i'he Political Agent, Bahrain. 2. The political Agent, Kuwait. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docement (/). British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated, 21st April, 1941. / Reference to previous correspondence : /V Residency P.L.No. 28-S dated 11th January, 1941, --'A Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. British Legation Tehran^ Circular Saving ram No. 14, dated 11th March 1941. RECRUITS FOR FREE FRENCH FORCES .British Legation, Tehran. 11th March, 1941. o, 14 Girc ular Saving . DSGY PHEH M. 39. Following from Foreign Office 31 of 7th CIRCUIAR. Instances hrve been brought to my notice th?t British officials overseas ?are discouraging recruits for Free French Forces (gr.mutd.) General de Gaulle Majesty's Government to neIp him as much as possible in this es in other matters. It is therefore essential that all suitable volunteers should be treated sympathetically and should receive maximum assistance within limits of my telegram Circular ? ?who urgently needs recruits and it is the policy of His Inform ell concerned under your authority. - BULLARD -Telegram S. From Political Resident, Bushire To Political Agent, Bahrain No. 402 Dp ted and received the 9th May 1941. 0 Your telegram No.107 dated May 4th. It is believed next steamerjafter TT Sui Sang” is lf Baraia”aue Bahrain about May 14th. As there may be no passenger steamer for some time after that, please confirm Mrs beared can catch it . o v ^ ^ JLa~ ', 'Snf^ #* Z: 7^4 CL£o y&amp;La-12/19 Telegram ’’S' From Political Agent, Bahrain. To Political Resident, Bushire No. 127 Dated 10th May 1941. il* /I Your telegram No. 402. There is nothing to prevent Mrs. Leared from catching next steamer on 14th but she tells me she has written her husband by last mail that she wishes to go to India instead. A.L.O. informed her some time ago that she was no longer required by him. - Political -March 10, 1941 From: Guy Clifford, C/o The Bahrein Petroleum Co .Ltd., Bahrein Island, Barsian Gulf. To: H.B.M.’s Political Agent, Bahrein. Subject:- KECRUIIMBNT Sir, I have the honour to approach you concerning recruitmant for the Empire Ifer Effort and to say that I am anxious to make the maximum use of my training and experience. To this end, I should like my qualifications to be examined from time to time against the requirements of the Services in case my training and experience can be put to more effective use than at present. 2 . I shall apprecia te it, therefore, if this can be treated as a Formal Application for a Commission in any of the fitting services in India or elsewhere, or alternatively^for a post in the Government of India in a Civil capacityJ and if this application can be registered for review from time to time as requirements demand. 2. Particulars of my qualifications are a tt a died. 4 , I am at present employed by the Bahrein Petroleum Company Ltd., and am in charge of petroleum exports (both as to quantity and quality) from Bahrein. Mjr salary is Rs.800/-/- month, plus Living Allowance and free Married Quarters. 5 . In this position I do not feel fully exercised, and believe that, with minor changes and without employing any further European labour, my employers could dispense with my services without material loss of efficiency? so that I would be available for employment in connection with the 'Hinpire War Effort. I have the honour to be.PARTICUIAR3 OF EXPaRIENCS &amp;. TEUINIKG Neme:- GKiy Clifford 35 years. Married: No children. Educated at:- Sutton Valence School, Kent (Passed London Metric) City of London College (for Examinations of Chartered Institute of Secretaries). London. - Royal Economic Society, London. - Institute of Petroleum, London. Wide Practical and Business experience in Aviation, Diesel and Furnace Fuels, as well as in Aviation, Industrial and Marine Lubricants. I 'Hie Sir John Cass $ i Technical Institute,! London Petroleum Technology Battersea Polytechnic, \ London I Qualifications:- Member - Chartered Institute of Secretaries12/19 Telegram 'Q” From To Repeated No. Dated Political Agent, Bahrain. Government of India, Simla Political Resident, Bushire. 162 19th May 1941 British subject resident of Trinidad and certain Canadians all employed in Bahrain Petroleum Company wish to know whether they will be conscripted either in their own countries or in South Africa or Australia en route if they leave employ of Bahrain Petroleum Company and return to their homes. Gratefbl for material for reply. - PoliticalTelegram Q. From To Repeated No. 2347 Dated and receivedthe 21st May 1941. Government of India, Simla. Political Resident, Bushire Political Agent, Bahrain. t- Bahrain telegram No.152 dated May 19th. If it is thought essential to pursue this enquiry it should be addressed to India Office. ForeignBRITISH OVERSEAS AIRWAYS CORPORATION. BAHRAIN ISLANDS PERSIAN GULF jne : Telegrams: “ Flyiug ” Baliraln Codes : Bentley s &amp; I.A.T.A. BAH/1/273/S.2 26th May, 1941. H.B.M. Political Agent, BAHREIN Thank you for your letter of 25 th May reference D.O.No.C/506. I am afraid that all the Corporation’s European employees^ are most strictly prohibited from joining any other organisation without the previous agreement of the Corporation and, before seeking permission, I should have to know to what ’ extent the staff would be involved, and whether their services would be required outside Bahrein. In any case, as all our staff have to be on 2k hour call, regular attendance at a course of training is almost impossible for them.Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co.Ltd. (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND) HEAD OFFICE: iADENHALL STREET. LONDON,E.C.3. EGRAPHIC ADDRESS: GRAY. CODES USED: cy'S COMPLETE PHRASE. ;Y'S SECOND PHRASE CODE. BRANCHES: BUSRE H. AM ARAH. KUT. KHORAMSMAHR AHWAZ (for BAN DAR-SHAH POU R) BUSH IRE. RAS TANURA. BUNDER-ABBAS. LINGAH. BAHREIN. KOYVEIT. DUBAI. SHARJAH. MUSCAT. IN REPLY PLEASE QUOTE No. P/6X. Bahrein, 2 6 th May, 1941. Dear I have to acknowledge receipt of your confidential letter D0/C/506 of the 25th instant, and regret that I have no one under my control who can be spared to accept temporary R.N.V.R. commissions. Yours sincerely, Major k. q. Alban, bcUixCjlh .The Bahrein petroleum company limited Awali, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, 27th May, 1941. CON-824. Major R. G. Alhan, His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, BAHREIN. Dear Major Alhan, \ Refer to your letter D.O. No. C/506. Confirming my conversation with you of the 26th May on the subject of the Senior Naval Officer’s letter, we find it impossible to release any of our men for Naval enlistment. Although we have a few men that might be willing to accept temporary commissions, it would hamper our operations if we were to let them go as our staff is at its minimum. M. H. Lipp. THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED.D.Q. no. C/516 Dated the 27th Hay 1941 «ith regard to the British subject from Trinidad and the 4 Canadians who ?/ere enquiring regarding their chances of escaping conscription if they left the Com pany’s service, I have received a reply that the Govern ment of India have no information on the subject, I h t ,ve told Mr, O’Connor this and explained that if he leaves the Company’s service he must take his chance of being conscripted. / 2. I would suggest that Canadians and other# who apply to you might also be informed accordingly' as It may discourage them from attempting to leave your service Yours sincerely, v ! U. H, Lipp, Esq*, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, Bahrain.if-lflential NO. C/521-12/19 I Political Agency f Bahrain, the 27th May 1941* To The Naval Officer in Charge, Naval Base, Bahrain. Memorandum iieference telegram No* 0854 z dated 23rd May 1941 from the Senior Naval Offier. , 2* A circular was issued to all offices in Bahrain but it is regretted that no applications for B*N*V.R* commissions have been received. L. Political Agent, Bahrain.THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Awali Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, May 29, 1941 V ION-825 Sis Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir, &lt;2 I thank you for your letter D.O. No. C/516 about Danadians and conscription. While agreeing that to leave the matter vague as you suggest may discourage men from attempting to leave us, tie feel that we should if possible have accurate information about the application of the Indian Conscription Act, and /vould be very much obliged if you will persue the question. very truly, Chief Local Representative TH2 BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LTD. lit J (OsK,- -- . : |l / c 'fcPrl't^ydL ([ t' /v J ' | -^1Telegram Q From Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Resident, Bushire To No. 175 Dated the 31st May 1941. 0 Your telegram No. 405 22nd May. &lt; The Company were informed accordingly but jr* * | ’i o they have requested information regarding conscription in India as it would apply to ps Canadian and other personnel of the company touching at Indian ports on their way to their homes. Politicalr* Copy of a iBomorandum No.8Vl/i»4l, dafod the 15*,h Fobruary 194X from *ho Military ittaoha, tahran to Army Haad-iuartara, India, New Delhi. f* ~ Subjects- Britiah volumeera for Aratsd Force a. oneul* ' ** ert wait •6U4 6th ^urum*y 1941. “Th^re is aow flood of men leafii^ this area whieh if unoomrolied would be lively to swamp 4he army organisation in India* the total number of BritisJa realeaasd by ♦lie Company last year was 200 and they left in driblets of 3 or 4 at a ti^ae Tor several destinations bu^ mostly for the li*K. There *my possibly be another 200 this year* •Moreover every m,n leavi and recommended for &amp; coai potential officers) takes witn him jirmy i signed either here or at iChorr^shahr in accordame with an arrai^eMnt. mde last October between Pat fission and the Military Mission at 2* Lis^s of all British subjects in Khusist&amp;n have been prepared, together with particulars of their special qualifications for nafion&amp;l service* 3* In order to assist, m however in givim the best possible advice to mn 9 who are r^ow being released by the Company, who are ansioue to do their bit, am who come to the Consulate, (1) where can their services be best used, and (2) where can they do beat for themselves and their families* •Are ma wanted ia India or ^sypt or Hem more than at home? If so, what categories IT particular? MimaditsumxxMKzxxmixg fhst about xhi wives who can drive cars, type, nurse? Any job for them? And Children? Karriag/s allowamcs? hat arc the pyepsprospects of a connsission within a reasonable time? Sexember that uom of these ./ten are givir^ up good jobs in a reserved occupation and that,- all are payi% their way* Jhat about a man of 3k an expert driller am rigger who ms handled native labour here and in met Africa Tor 15 years? Is he to goto India with little chance of civil eapiey&amp;ent and join up in the ranks? Or should he try Kgypt or Kenya where he would probably be of the* utmost use In drilling for water? Builders? Chemists? Accountants? Men with German wives? •Anything which would assist, us in giving helpful advice is what $s need* At present we know nothing • officially • about service in the mat which is precisely what mu from here are best fitted for. fe don f t even iuidw whether Habbaniya could find a use for an t* RAF pilot* •We wish to send these xen off with the conviction that they are wanted, that they are goir^ in the right direction and that tom thought has been given to their personal problems*# / to Ho *F #49(3)~ */41. the Secretary to the aovernaent of India in the External Affairs Departnsnt. His Britannic Majesty's Envoy Extraordinary arid Minister-Plenipot.ent.iary at the Court, of Iran, Tehran, Dated Hew Delhi,the 7th April 1941. Subjecti-Iritieh volunteers for arxed forces in IMSir, - S'- reference +,o your Klliteary A^eche'e -*.aararidua to Arav headquarter ■ in India, So.:fi/l/194i, dated t.be l&amp;tii February 1941, I am directed to e+.ate that the fioferniient of Indie are prepared to accept any nitaber of suitable British personnel for military employment in India either ea officers oi q+imt tanka aco&gt;rdim fo ♦he aducaf i^oal and Jiidioai 8+anaaras 3i %fan iiidifxaualg co^asernati arjd irr^spuc^iva of their present, occupation. Candidates should how?tar be of pure British decent, should rat base vises of enemy origin and giiouid noid eerfificufes *,o th&amp; affacf fh®ir loyally aM its integrity has been serifled by a British Consular Iflicer. i’ersons vrtn special qualifications vill be acceptsd, as far as possible, for appropriate posts* Oa an aseraue 50 cadets per month can oe taken into officers Training sshoois oo-aemii^ from *he let ay 1M1. A brief note (iitii^ an outline af-tr* aersioee in the Indian urmy and Air force is enclosed. It also makes clear that employ sent is obtainable in the Royal Indian fiaty a«i the Department of Supply for those she are technically Qualified. ) 3. 1 m +9 r^qum* that caiididafe® wifh f«chnical qualificat ions mo wish afecur# t^pioyaacnt on account of ♦hour H-chuical abiiify my bo aavia&amp;d +o e#M ♦heir parficuiara on ♦ he preoeribed for:na (five copies enclosed} to Aray Headuuartere at an aarly dafo* £ach application should m accompanied by a certificate that 4 he cam Ida* e ia above suspicion ard should beiur /he personal observations of a Consular Officer whether the candidate is considered suitable for employ^eot as an officer or other rank* 4. Tb* re is m aecemsiodation in ti^e Officers , training School for wives or families and cheap aeo&amp;ia&amp;d&amp;iion is some- tiiaes difficolt to find in the vicinity* If they oom to India, families will have to be boarded elsewhere in India* ^ives of candidates if qualified .ay naxmlly axpeat to find employment in India as nurses and governesses» and cierical appoint aent,» carry!,&amp;*100/- per menaen and above arci also open * i them if t-ey posaesi secretarial ability •the term* ai*d coniitions of service in inch posts are shortly to be issued and a copy will be forwarded to you in due course* b. I am to state that the probable data of arrival of each oarmd&amp;*e should be reported to the {tavernsat of India in advame in order to enable theca to wake-the neceasary rrrar#te- ment.g for the reception and Journey of the individual concerned* 6* In conclusion I as to say that while the Goveram#nt of imia are willii^ to employ all suitable candidates avairajie, *hey would prefer that applicationa from mn who are unsuitable for the posty for which they apply should be discoursed* I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient, servant, Sd/- 8*d*M. Baker, j for Secretary to the Govern^* t of India*CODES : BENTLEY’S SECONC 14 $ iOLEUM DEVELOPMENT (QATAR) LIMITED' Mr. W. Barnfield - Age 31. Qualifications First Mate Board of Trade Certificate of Competency. Ships Officer from June 1926 to November 1937. Inspector of Rivercraft at Abadan for Anglo- Iranian Oil Co. Ltd. from June 1938 to November 1939. Ships Officer in charge of launches for Petroleum Development (Qatar) Ltd., Bahrain, from February 1940 to date. The Company is prepared to release Mr. Barnfield immediately, and we shall be pleased to receive your instruc tions as to the procedure now to be followed by Mr.Barnfield. BAHREIN PDQ/SAC/2479 To H.B.M. , s Political Agent Bahrain. PERSIAN GULF 5th June, 1941. Dear Sir, V temporary commission in the R.N.V.R, 1941. Reference your D.O.No.C/506 dated the 25th of May The undermentioned gentleman wishes to accept a Yours faithfully, For &amp; on behalf of PETROLEUM DEVELOPMENT (QATAR) LIMITED c.c. to Mr. Barnfield ACMNo.C/558-12/19 Political Agency, Bahrein, the 8th June 1941. To The Naval Officer in Charge, Naval Base, Bahrain. Memorandum. Further to my memorandum No.C/521 dated the 27th May 1941, I have now received an application for a temporary commission in the R.N.V.R. The following are the particu lars Mr♦ W. Barnf1eId . at present employed by Petroleum Concessions Limited. The Company are prepared to release him immediately. A^e - 31. Qua1ific a tions First Mate Board of Trade Certificate of Competency. Ships Officer from T une 1926 to November 1937. Inspector of Rivereraft at Abadan for Anglo-Iranian Oil Company Limited, from June 1938 to November 1939. Ships Officer in charge of launches for Petroleum Development (Qatar) Limited, Bahrain, from February 1940 to date. Political Agent, BahrainI v( a. THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Awali, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, CON-847. 15th June, 1941. Exit Permit Mr. E. L. Johnson. His Britannic Majesty*s Political Agent, BAHREIN. Dear Sir, Mr. P. L. Johnson has resigned from our service, his reason 'being that he was concerned about the availability of transportation. We tried to assure him that to date we have no reason to suspect a curtailment or serious interruption in trans-Atlantic or trans-Pacific accommodations, but he felt that he still wished to leave. During a later interview, Johnson was asked whether he planned to withdraw his resignation, but he stated that he did not. ; Je are accordingly arranging a passage for him by a suitable boat leaving Bombay early in July. Johnson*s departure has left us in a somewhat close position as regards manpower and we are of the opinion that he could have contributed his share to the war effort as well here as in any other part of the Empire. He has been requested to call on you for an Exit Permit. Yours^yery truly, M. H. Lipp. Jhief Local Peuresentative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. ^ p/t 0 At* &lt; 52 — £ a^. Ci&gt; Cw ^ •rrmfidential O- No. C/611 Political Agency, Bahrain, the 16th June 1941 To The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf Bushire Memorandum I enclose a copy of a letter No. CON-847 dated the 16th June 1941 from the Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, regarding one Mr. F.L. Johnson. 2. The General Manager informed me privately that Mr. Johnson is a Canadian subject and is employed in the Refinery. His reasons for resignation are entirely frivolous and he merely hopes to be able to get back to his country and secure better employment there. There are some more Canadians who are waiting to do the same thing if they see that Mr. Johnson succeeds in reaching Canada without being taken up for military service on the way. If these men leave, the Company will be in an awkward position and their activities are likely to be hampered just at a time when oil is urgently required* r he Company are arranging a passage for this man by a suitable boat leaving Bombay early in July and if this man could be taken up for military service in India instead of being allowed to proceed to his home we shall probably hear no 3. A further communication will follow as soon as the name of the ship on which Mr. Johnson is sailing from Bahrain - to Bombay is known. more from the others. L Political Agent, Bahrain12/19 Telegram 'Q' Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Resident, Bushire. Government of India, Simla. 214 18th June 1941 Mr. F. Brown, British nationality, operator in Bahrain Petroleum Company, leaving by air for Karachi tomorrow catching next City Line sailing for United Kingdom. His contract is terminated and he refuses to renew. Company fear exodus of employees if this man and other similar cases are allowed to reach destination without being conscripted. From To Repeated No. Dated - Political -T No, 1-2/40-II-RP. From The Director-General, Indian Medical Service, To His Brittanic Majesty's Political Agent Bahrain. New Delhi, the. 194 1. With reference to your endorsement dated the 19th April 941 forwarding an application from Dr. P.3. Bajwa, In-charge atar Gamp, Bahrein, I have the honour to say that under the xisting rules Dr. Bajwa is not eligible for appointment to an mergency Commission in the I.M.3. If he has, however, passed he L.C.P.3. examination from one of the recognized medical schools n India and is willing to be considered for appointment to the mergency Branch of the I.M.D., he may be asked to complete the nclosed application form and submit it to this office along with he necessary documents through the proper channel. A copy of the erms and conditions of recruitment to the Emergency Branch of lie I.M.D. , is also enclosed for his reference. I have the honour to be Sir, Your obedient servant. Major, I.M.S for Director General I.M.SjK. 3 ';.ND CONDITlCrS 0? . Indian gcRuroaHTTO t h ■I-'V : v v ;;'. • ariSROSHCY BR..NQI OF TH3 .SSKT ,NT SUROECNS). w . » pULBUIllSU by him or by the Provincial if: iccrs. ^,11 :rpplicr.nt will normally be summoned ministr-tivo Medical Officer of the Pro * )plied 5en rapproved Imini£trativc Ledicel Cffieers. r interview by the a dnistr txvo meaicai umcor or tne province or •ej. m which he io residing he *oay also be called for an interview r the Dir actor ucnerr.l. Indian *uedioel Service at his discretion* * ndidatcs called up for interview- and medical examination will be ititled to the unaermentlened travelling allowances* Tr n vollin« lowance for a journey vVill b V. v X C » oifclc as for a ic cheapest practical route, irrespective of the me iurney is pjcrfcreied^ If ^nv iv»rf. nr n innmmr io rrant tite ccst_ cf the . exchanged shalL be Hg journey performed by I - v 3thods by which the any part or a journey is pebfermed on a 1 . ; - railway or steamer ticket for which the warrant eeducted fran the travelling allowance admissible:- (a), see one class single fare for a journey performed by rail, *aiid ■-L mileage at the rate.of annas four a mile for journeys performed by road, from the ordinary place cf residence to place of interview or medical examination and return* ib) li second class single fare, exclusive of the cost of meals, for '' a journey performed- by steamer* a r m. - 0. — ~ .;. T v -J.. ■» ' .t; i.. • (c) If la journey is performed by rail or steamer by a class lower than the secona class.. U fare by the class in which tho journey is performed* Gd) Daily allowance for halts in excess of 24 hours at the rate, of Rs.4/~ for each completed 24 hours* Half the rate for broken.' periods in excess of 12 hours* - 1 V.T i i o : - r .-■■■ . m • - - 1 ' . :Excoption — The rate of daily allowance will be Rs*6/~ ih e 4 ; .Calcutta: ahd Rs*5/^ in Bembay, Karachi, Poena and Madras* A candid at em. ill be required to execute a declaration in the escribed form (copy attached)* He will be on probation for a period cf ree months during which he'will undergo a course of training; and if und unsuitable will be discharged from the service* If he completes tfsfactorily the period of probation he will be retained, for the ' ration of the war'and for so- long thereafter as the State shall quire his services^ • ■ r ; ~ -du.* ~■ ' _. , • ( . • L Qualifications for a p pointment *- An applicant must: (i) be a male British subject, of Indian domicile or descent, whose ther (if alive) is a British subject cr a subject of a State in India (if dead) was at the tide cf his death, either a British subject or a •bject of a State in India'or a person in the permanent service of the own or a person who had retired from that service, or a ruler or a bject of a State in India: Provided- that for a male. British subject the requirements cf this le may he* otherwis'e waived by the Government of India if they arc tisfied that their observance would occasion exceptional hardship ana e candidate'^is' : so closely connected by ancestry or upbringing with • s Majesty ! s Dominions as to justify special treatment; (ii) -haVo parsed lHe. ; LoSoM^F* -or L1I1* cr an equivalent examination on one cf: the-recognised medical schools in Ind ia; (iii) not have attained his 35th birthday at the date of appointment: Provided that this age limit may be waived at the discretion of Director Generaln Indian Medical Service*-3- ®cu a Hi': Leave.- /.n emergency Sub-issistant Surgeon my be granted 30 dsvc erjil pay leave in each year of army service if con?atLns cerm-t =,n^ 'Wi'V® ^^9 'taken. If leave is not taken during service it may be ibc^uuulated and granted before release from amv servinn ?i,„® jipulated and granted before release from army service, at Lo rate of 'lays per completed year of army service or for broken uoriods at the ,fi of one day for every 11 dnvn of r„ . p ° rl ? as at tne_ cixmj oux v jluu ur ior oroKon DorioHq qt e of one day for every 11 days of service subject to a P maximnn of 120 .*M* ? asual 1 ° ave and leave on medical certificate at 3/4th mv win ho itH-isoiblc as for regular military Sub-dss is uant Surgeons. FuSl pay leave 'tificatef aValled ° f ln llou or codbinod witii leav^ on nelical applicabli Travelling: conccssionse ^ ■1' I (a) On appointiient a cancliaate will be granted a railway warrant for ysyance of hn.iself from his home to the station to which he is posted veyance for family will not be admissible. posnecu jiiiio.-it) lifter appointment an emergency 3ub—dssistant Surgeon will be ^ itled to conveyance under the rules in Passage Regulations (India) d A xh a ^ ly to a Pf^nent military Sub-Assistant Surgeon in the relulnr ftaikre. When granted leave on medical certificate he will however ^ ^SIcafBoard! 66 COnveyance to any P lace in India recommended by !he Pensions and gratuities (i) E^Isi.pnSo*-* Disability and family pensions and gratuities will nil inadmissible at the same rates and under the same rules as are applica CDKlitipermanent ana regular military Sub-Assistant Surgeons. ' JEjiit .... (ii) Gratuity.- On discharge from the service an emergency Sub- istant Surgeon will be eligible for a gratuity at the rate of one ii s pay for each complete year of qualifying service* Broken periods . be taken into account at the rate of one day J s pay for every 12 davd’ fiGGc The gratuity will be based on the rate of pay drawn at the time ^ m'eleas e&lt;&gt; iefasl Mote.' For purposes of this clause the term 'pay B will include the rOverE* Q^l^ents taken into account in calculating invalid gratuities of 30 niliicl permanent and regular Sub-lssistant Surgeons* Sub-lssistant Surgeon appointed to the permanent cadre w illfri ir Y rar will not 5 however, receive any gratuity but will be allowed ruent!' i0Un ' t hls war ser¥lce f° r promotion and pensiono ^ Termina tion of service *-- The services of an emergency Sub—dssistan ifl*M% eon be terminated normally at any time after the war is over, but e d services shall, at any time be liable to be dispensed with in the ■t^f any misconduct on his part, of which misconduct the Government , ] * 1 }^ be the sole judges and if his services are so dispensed wit] Jll^nall. automatically forfeii. the gratuity specified in paragraph 9 Go On demobilization he will not be liable to serve in the Indian r cal Department Sub-Assistant Surgeon Reserve*Instructions to Candidates rogarding the filling up and submission of Applications lor appointment to the Emergency Branch of the Indian Medical Department (oub-Assistant Surgeons). 1* You should iead these instructions carefully before filling*un the prescribed application forme ^ 2. |he application form must be filled up in your own handwriting. It sh 9 uld, after completions be su bmitted imm^di^tel y to th e Adm^nis^n^mY^—il-h-dhal Qffhner of th ; ^__hh.Qvince in which vou are residing rust of tne Administrative Medical Officers empowered to deal with such applications is reproduced below:- The Surgeon General with Ihe Surgeon General with The Surgeon General with The Inspector General of Ihe Inspector General The Inspector General The Inspector General The Inspector General The Inspector General The Director of Health The Director of Health .a. The The The Chief Chief Chief Medical Medical Medical Officer Officer Officer The Administrative Medical the Government of Madras,' Madras, tne Government of Bombay, Bombay, the Government of Bengal, Calcutt Civil Hospitals, Bihar, Patna. Civil Hospitals 3 U.P., Lucknow* Civil Hospitals, Punjab, Lahore. Civil Hospitals, Assam, Shillong. Civil Hospitals, C.P., Nagpur. Civil Hospitals, N.7.F.P., Peshav/ar. and Inspector General of Prisons, Orissa, Cuttack, cervices and Inspector General of Prisons, _ , . Sind, Karachi. # Baluchistan, Quetta, in Central India, Indore. Delhio Officer. Rajputana, Udaipur. of of of of of The Residency Surgeon, Mysore, Bangalore 3. &gt; In order that your application may receive consideration immediately, you are advised to submit complete documents required under item lb of the Application Form either in original or copies thereof /“IitItI* 'L'v* r r*. 4—f- hi 4 * -P 4 A *1 J ^ ~ ' *! _ i dul by attested oy a ese documents, by a gazetted officer» Applications which are not accompanied duly attesoed, iip_ will not be considered. If the date of birth other than your actual date affidavit executed before a Y birth. given in the Matriculation Certificate is pf birth, you are advised to submit an + Class magistrate about the correct dat&lt; Is L If you are in Government service, you should send your application through the proper official channel, 3. &gt; You should hold yourself in readiness to present• yourself for in interview and medical examination before the Administrative Medical Officer of the Province in which you are residing. For the journey to 3e undertaken for this purpose, you will be entitled to travelling ulov/ance as indicated in paragraph 1 cf the terms and conditions. 5* In case you change your address you should ensure that any communications sent to you at the address given in your application tfe promptly redirected to you at your new address. At the same time r ou should keep the Deputy Director General, Indian Medical Service, few Delhi informed of any change in your address as also the Administra tive Medical Officer till the time of your interview with him. It may be added for your information that recruitment to the Permanent cadre of the Sub-Assistant Surgeons Branch of the Indian fedical Department and the Sub-Assistant Surgeon I.M.D. Reserve have feen suspended for the duration of the war. A If you are found knowingly to have furnished any particulars which ire false or to have suppressed material information, you will be disqualified, and if appointed, will be liable to dismissal.- 2 - lOv What is your' : (a) Gommunity... k v i b) Ro ligion c) Gas to * 11. Modical Institutions at bondod:- Namo of School, Gollogo* otc* Date of ontorihgk Dat.o of loavj it Namo of Examination passed and your position in tho list of qualifi^xi candidates. (If^you obtained any distinction in any sub j act, giv^. dot ad la.) 13* fiaVD you boon omployod anyovlioro after obtaining your &lt; medical qua lification? If “so, give full details of all appointments hold o.g.whoro employod, for how long, nature of duties allotted to you, otc. mu 14* Have you undergone any special training in any -subject? If so give full particulars. and Wary and s “ 15. Tho following documents muse bo s'ldmittod with this application-; (a) Birth certificate (an attested copy from tho Matriculation n tho School Leaving Gertificato or an affidavit ex^Aut r&gt; d bde a 1st Glass Magistrate 'will bo accopted as a satisfactory pr of ago.} _ . ■•■e- _ - (b) iin at to© ted copy of tho Educational certificate or diploma a proof of having passed the .requisite standard. of professions examination. (c) Attost d copies of at least two certificates of character o: which on ^should be. from tho- Principal of^tho Institution^ the candidate' last studied and the other-from a rospons person not being a mombor of th^ candidate^ own family.. to- effect that he is of regular and s toady habits and is lik'd if appointed, to prove Yn every respect creditable to th n Modical Department. ^ ( Note;- Gopies of^documents^m^ntioned above should be attested by a i gazetted officer. Applications which are not accompanied by th n s3 c merits,, duly attested, will not be considered. ISTTf select d, are you propered to join duty at any time at short notice,say 10 days. ^ IV. What &lt; is the' name' of th^ railway station from which you would require a travelling warrant for joining duty, if selected.-3- BBv/ I ON TO BE BIG-NED BY THE CANDID iTE. I hereby declare that the statements in this application arc true to the best of my knowledge and belief and that I am a A § r: !'i : !' s l 1 su bject domiciled in Tn J ia doIicil6d U ii eC Rnr°L Eur0pean or lndian Ascent ( domiciled in Burma. ( (c) a ruler or a subject of a State in India. Tate. Signature. gtrikb''out the tvvo items winUFI do not pcdv the one v^hich applies to you. PP 7 t IB ’ i I o you and retain only FOR CANDID/tTES dtREiDY IN EMPLOYMENT (GOVERNMENT OR PRIVATE). ( To be endorsed by the employer). he character and conduct of .the. candidate, so far'as*! ■am'awarer^e*’ atisfactory and when and if ha-is._.appointed his releasr will oe eed to. Signature of employer ^tion ) instated 18.*****•••••••••• •............ om (f | is Designation. ■ . • s ' li»f' i tali' REMARKS OF THE CIVIL ADMINISTRATIVE MEDICAL OFFICER- drf I 1 ’ ' f v i Im , / 1 !&gt; , 3! I : SMERG-ENCY CADRE OF THE INDIAN MEDICAL DEPARTMENT (SUB-ASSISTANT SURGEON BRANCH)* £.0^1. OF DECLARATION . Is the undersigneds hereby promise and declare that if 1 am appointed to the Emergency Cadre of the Indian Medical Department (Sub-Assistant Surgeon Branch) I will serve and be faithful to His Majesty the King Emperor of India, His Heirs and Successors, as a sub—assistant surgeon so long as my services may be required or until my resignation is accepted, and that I will go wherever I am ordered by land. sea or air* and obey all commands of officers set over me« I am aware that 1 shall be subject to the Indian Army Act during the period of my service. Signature of candidate* The above declaration was signed by Mr* o * » . o «&gt; in my presence* IPli u • * • • • » • «» e Signature of a Commissioned Medical Officer (I J/LS* or R*jUM.C*) Designation &amp; it':*? i iCERTIFICATE OF PHYSICAL FITNESS. (The candidate should be examined free bv an officer of the I.M.3. or the R.A.M.C.). ••• I do hereby certify that I have examined , a candidate for appointment to the emergency branch of the Indian Medical Department (Sub- Assistant Surgeon) and cannot discover that he has any disease, constitutional affection, or bodily infirmity, except as noted below. I do/do not consider this a dis qualification for his appointment as a military sub-assistant surgeon. His age is, according to his own statement years, and by appearance about years. He was last vaccinated (or protected from smallpox) in 19 Vision: Chest? maximum minimum Height: Weight: Details of diseases, etc Signature and Designation of Examining Officer. , ' I *No. C/631 i o rv' im/ Political Agency, Bahrain, the 19th June 1941. To Dr. P. S. Bajwa, C// ° Petroleum Development (Qatar) Limited, Qatar. Memorandum Reference your application for an emersencv coznmission in the Indian Medical Service. y 2. A copy of letter No. 1-2/40-II-RP dated the 26th May 1941 from the Director General Indian Medical Service, together with its enclosures, is forwarded for your information. L - i Political Agent, Bahrain.No C/643 Political Agency, Bahrain, the 23rd June 1941. To The Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, has presumably already left Bahrain, I would be grateful if you could kindly let me have answers to the following questions as early as possible i. Nationality ii. Age iii. Educational qualifications with full particulars iv. Has he knowledge of any of the following : (a) Administrative work in any large industrial firm (b) Textiles (c) Explosives (d) Oils, Paints and Chemicals (e) Timber (f) Leather v. Whether, in your opinion, his general education, character and personality make Mu fit for a commission. £ A U R A I H Dear Sir with reference to the case of It. F. who Yours faitlifully, Political Agent, BahrainThe Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited e, v ,\ 6 PA-552 His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, The Agency, BAHRAIN. Bear Sir, Awali, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. June 25th, 1941. Mr* ff. BROWN « ATS A™ Nationality Education: BRITISH Age: 35 years Experience: cth!;N S i Sec ? ndar y School. Intermediate School leaving certificate. Evening classes “ N e N Stry ana . Metallur gy for several years aiter leaving school. f r Q^?f.+°n ked i n our Refinery for 2i years as a Shift Operator on the Cracking Plants. His worA was^ satisfactory, hut he would not, in our opinion, ever qualify as a foreman. Brown’s previous experience, so far as we know, has heen: 7 years with Lanarkshire Steel Coy. as an Analytical and Metallurgical Chemist. (See references attachedX^J^ ei years with I.C.I. as a Chemist. 2 years with Ford Motor Co., Dagenham, as We attach copies of'the references Brown presented ‘iginally applied for a position with this'*Company. ab regards Question V., we do not feel that we are qualified to judge as to whether or not Browii would he a suitable person for a commission. when heConfidential tfo. C/668 Political Agency, Bahrain, the 26th June 1941. To The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Camp Bahrain. Subject Hr. F.L. Johnson Uemorandnin In continuation of my memorandum No. C/611 dated the 16th June 1941. 2. I forward herewith details regarding Mr. Johnson together with his qualifications, with the remark that he appears to b e of a type suitable to receive a commission Political Agent, BahrainNames JOHNSON FBEDSBICK LLOYD Nationality Canadian Born Sth October 1916 Unmarried Father 1 s name and next of kin F.F, Johnson SI', Duggan Avenue, Toranto - Ontario Qualifications s Educations- B,A• Sc. Toronto University Specialised in Chemical Engineering Experience:- Oil Refineries Foreign Languages NilConfidential No. C/669 Political Agency, Bahrain, the 26th June 1941. To The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Camp Bahrain. Mr. F. Brown Memorandum In continuation of my telegram No. 18th June 1941. 214 dated the 2. I enclose herewith details of qualifications of the above individual as supplied ay the Chief Local Representa tive, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited. 3. As the individual in question has already left Bahrain it is not possible to express an opinion as to his suitability or otherwise for a commission. Political Agent, BahrainBROWN Lt Nationality: Age Education; Experience: British 35 years 4 years Secondary School. Intermediate •School Leaving Certificate. livening classes in Chemistry and Metallurgy for several years after leaving school. Bi own worked in Bahrain Petroleum Company 1 a Pefinory for 2 :r years as a Shift Operator on the Cracking Plants. His work was satisfactory, but he would not* in the Company* a opinion f ever qualify as a Foreman. Brown 1 © previous experience, as far as is known, has been ; 7 years with Lanarkshire oteel Coy. as an Analytical and Metallurgical Chemist. years with I.C.X. an a Chemist 2 years with Ford ^otor C, 5 Dagenham, as a ro g j.s .3 , Xlpp y^uite frankly that man are attr&amp;oted by bitter wages now available In States or Janada and he has applied to his Principals to be allowed to pay bonuses as added ixiducement to personnel whether British* American or Canadian* since Government of India attach importance to continued working of Company X trust they will be able to take action desired* Company are in great straits for suitable personnel and have obtained none from the British Isles for many months past* s a * C.G.-rior, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf* Attested* for ceoretary to the Political resident in the Persian Gulf*Jj!!|J * I# r t APPSHDXX* Agt 35 yra* Single yrankBrown • ^ BritieH. Military training - Kone f eo far ae ie known* Arrived Bahrain - January 19# 1939* Refinery operator* Left • June aiet, i94i.* Keaeon for leaving - Had completed contract and wished to return to Ragland to see his family* settlement • Vacation &amp; Travel Time* iassage hooked to U.K* R*S»:)AY * Age 29 yre* carried* 'BriTiTh • Military training • In Bahrain only* Welder* Arrived Bahrain Left * Keaeon Settlement • April 19,1939. • June 18 th, 194^* - Oontract tefminated by Coy* - Vacation &amp; Travel Time, Passage furniehed to Bombay, afcd Travel allowance given for remainder of journey* Age 24 yre* Single F*L»Johnson * Canadian. Military training - Bone eo far as ie known* Refinery operator Arrived Bahrain Left * Reason settlement - November 14 th, 1939* - Due to leave sometime next month* • Has resigned » no reason given, except that he was afraid there might be no transportation available later on* » Hone made yet, but has been advised Company will grant him absolute minimum passage to H*Y* . * by air for Karachi in hope of aatohing City Line vessel for United Kingdom on or about 21st/22nd June • 41 on B.l.steamer ADKIA for Bombay but possibly disembarking at Karachi* Apparently spenuing leave in India*CONFIDENTIAL. No. C/227 vx ftp: \ £l' U W ; ' *‘1 , u *a| The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to The Political Agent, Bahrain. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment (*). for action on paragraph 2 of Government of India telegram forwarded herewith. Office of the Political Reaid in the Persian Gulf, Gamp, BAHRAIN. Dated, 28th June 1941. RAfprp.nn.A fn nrAvinns A.nrrAsnrmrlAnnA t St P' Bahrain telegram No.175 dated the 1st June 1941. Description of Enclosure, Name and Date. • ncaxuciiaoj/ tc xcgA cud inu. * ? 04 dated the 8th June 1941. \ Conscription of Canadian and 2. Government of India telegram No.3166 dated the 26th June 1941.Telegram q From Political Resident, Bushire To Government of India, Simla. Ho.604 • Dated the 8 th June 1941. ; Your telegram Ho*2347 of 21st May. Bahrain Oil Company had enquired whether Canadian and other British employees touching at Indian ports on their way home would be liable for conscription in India. Glad to know what reply should be given. BRITCOHSULTftltgraxii From To Ho# 3166• Dated 26th % Government of India, Simla. Political Heaident at Bahrain. received ^7th June 1941. Your telegram 604 oX June ath. Qompmj be informed that European British eubje^ta between ages of 18 and 50 including those in transit are liable to be oonearipted in India. 3, For your information# In practice employees of company touching at Indian ports on their way to home would not ordinarily be called up# * FGRBIGH - i Aim 2fci/ 6«The Lanarkshire Steel Co. Limited. Lanarkshire Steel Works, Motherwell. 14th March 1933. TO WHOM IT MAY CONCERN This to certify that Frank Brown was employed for seven years as Assistant Chemist (Analytical) with the Lanarkshire Steel Coy. Ltd., during which period he has acquired a sound practical knowledge of the sampling and analysis of Steel Works Materials, raw and finished. Ms conduct was at all times very good and he gave every satisfaction in the execution of his duties. THE LANARKSHIRE STEEL CO.LTD. W.Gr.CAMERON ChemistThe Lanarkshire Steel Co* Ltd., Motherwell. 25th February 1930. To Whom It Hay Concern I have pleasure in testifying to the good character and ability of Mr. Frank Brown who has been employed as a Metallurgical Chemist with the Lanarkshire Steel Co.,Ltd., for a period of almost seven years. During this time he has acquired a sound practical knowledge of the sampling and analysis of Steel Works Materials, raw and finished, inclusive of Ferrous and Ifon-Ferrous Alloys, slags. Refractories etc. He has proved himself to be an accuarate, reliable chemist and his work was always of a very high standard. I wish him all success in the future. The Lanarkshire Steel Co.Ltd. W. C. CAMERON. Chief ChemistMause of Law, Carluke, Lanarkshire. 9th November 1936. I hereby certify that X have know Mr. Frank Brown for ten years and have fomed a vexy high opinion of him. He is most intelligent and capable in every way, a sober trustworthy worker, of a pleasant disposition and obliging, and eager to give satisfaction. He is a member of my Church, and is much respected in and around this district. I have evexy confidence in recommending Mr. Frank Brown to any employer who requires his services. I will be pleased to answer any enquiries regarding him. I wish him evexy success. Neild Anderson Minister of LawCuratehill, Law, Carluke. 25th February, 1930. ! T 1 i :} \|S iv I IfflM This certifies that I have know Mr* Frank Brown Hillside Cottage, Law, Carluke, all his lifetime. He is a young man of excellent character. He is steady, industrious and thoroughly trustworthy and I hat!e*no hesitation in recomending him for any situation he may make application. (Signed) James Patterson Justice of the Peace, For the County of Lanark.Dalziel Technical School Motherwell. COH 24th February 1930. Hi* B «(B0^ 4 . I ?, Iay Ca P acit y as Lecturer and Demonstrator in Chemistry and Metallurgy at Dalziel Technical School, Motherwell I have been, for a number of years, in constant contact vxith Mr. Frank Brown, Carluke, who is studying at that school. 1 Lave, therefore, much pleasure in stating mv opinion of his character and abilities. has received an excellent grounding in Chemistry and Metallurgy, while at the same time, he has had cood experience in all steel works analysis, including alloys, fuels and refractories etc., Mr. Brown is industrious and mmi enthusiastic in the carrying out of his work and quickly masters any new material. He has proved himself a careful and correct worker. Over the period I have known him, I have been foming an increasing opinion of his capabilities and have no hesitation in recommending him to any work for which his experience qualifies him. I shall be pleased to hear of his future success. Alexander Me .Donald. B.Sc. a.R.T.C. A.I.C.nfM dent ial No.C/677-12/19 Political Agency, Bahrain, the 29th June 1941. ashepj TiW jjj o eiJii liiie)! BTOfli a iteJisaj [ishens To The Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, Bahrain. Dear Sir, 0 \ the 29th May 1941. . 2. I have now received information that European British subjects betv/een the ages of 18 and 50 including those in transit are liable to be conscripted in India. Yours faithfully, L. Political Agent, Bahrain.Telegram Q. From Political Agent, Bahrain To Government of India, Simla. Copy to Political Besident, at Bahrain No. 218 Dated the 29th June 1941. Resident's Express letter No.C/220 dated 25th June. 2 , July for Singapore Exodus of Bahrain Petroleum Company employees. Johnson leaving here by air on or-about 13th Hope he can be conscripted. PoliticalQ. Government of India, Simla. Political Resident, at Bahrain. Political Agent, Bahrain. Dated 9th received 10th July 1941 . ■ Reference your Express letter No.C/220 dated June 25th. Conscription of Bahrain Petroleum Company Employees. Brown left India day after he arrived before action could be taken to conscript him. Orders issued for conscription of Johnson on arrival and Day when traced. Telegram From To Repeated No. 3451 ForeignCONFIDENTIAL . No. C/285 of 1^41. \ t I ^ / ' mm y /f'p^ The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Political Agent, Bahrain, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document • British Consulate-General, JOTSfflQXK Camp Bahrain. Dated... IQth. July.. 1 &amp; 4 J.% Reference to previous correspondence: Residency Express Letter No. C/220, dated 25.6.41. Description of Enclosure. Telegram No. 3451, dated ^th July 1941 from Government of India to Political Resident. Conscription of Bahrain Petroleum Company’s employees • | _ , • ( -i! cTeXigrara ?roro To Hepeated Government of India, Simla. Political Reeident at Bahrain. Political Agent, Bahrain. No. 3451. Dated 9th received 10th July 1941. Reference your Express Letter No. C/22Q June 25th. Conscription of Bahrain Petroleum Company 9 s employees. Brotm left India day after lie arrived before notion could he taken to conscript him. Orders issued for conscription of Johnson on arrival and Bay when traced. - FOREIGN - AVM 10/7.Telegram From To Copy to No* 230* Dated Your telegram No. 3451 dated 9th July. 2. Johnson left Bahrain by air K.L.M. yesterday. He is said to be making a prolonged stay at Sydney. nntt Political Agent, Bahrain. Government of India, Simla Political Resident, Bushire. 12th July 1941. - Political No.C/743-12/19. Political Agency, Bahrain, the 12th July 1941. A copy of the above telegram is forwarded, with compliments, to The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire.DtO. No* C/745 Dated the I2th July 1941. I have received information to say that Messrs* Johnson and Day are being or have already been conscripted in India. Tours sincerely* u H. Lipp* Ssq., Chief Local Representative* The Bahrain Petroleum Co.* Ltd#*Telegram 'S' From To No. Dated Political Agent, Bahrain. Political Resident, Bushire. 244 20. th July 1941 A' Your Express Letter No. C/220 dated 25th June. 2, T ). m . 0*Connor employee of Bapco sailing on tanker H Inge Maersk' for Durban en route to Trinidad on termina tion of contract. - Political -THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Awali Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, 19th July, 1941. PA-590. lajor B. 0. Alban, His Britannic Majesty's Political Agent, BAHREIN. Bear Major Alban, The “Inge Maersk H is due to sail for Durban on the afternoon of Saturday, July 19th, 1941. It will take this boat from 16 to 18 days to reach its destination. For your information, Mr. W. E. Jeffries and Mr. V. S. Wild, Bapco Employees, are going to Durban for leave and are returning to Bahrein. Mr. D. T. O'Connor, a Trinidadian with a British passport, is leaving our employ and is on the same boat. I believe you are entirely familiar with Mr. O'Connor's case. He arrived here this February and broke his contract with us in order to return to either Trinidad or the United States. M. H. Lipp. Chief Local Bepresentative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPiNY LIMITED.Telegram ”Q M From Political Agent, Bahrain. To Political Resident, Bushire. No. 24-7 Dated 2ist July 1941 Manager Bahrain Petroleum Company reports that G.M. McDonald, British subject, left on three months leave on June 9th for Cape Town on definite understanding that he will return to duty in Bahrain. He now cables that he intends to proceed to Bngland for family reasons. Company regard this as deliberate breach of faith to avoid serving in Bahrain and request that if possible he may be conscripted in South Africa. His address is care of Caltex Office, Cape Town. Political -vfMrigntial No.C/784-12/19. Political Agency, Bahrain, the 22nd July 1941. To The Hon ! ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Camp, Shiraz. Memorandum Reference telegram No. 1941 from the Government of India, forwarded under your Printed letter No.C/285 dated the 10th July 1941. 2 . It is learned that Johnson was taken out of his plane in India and conscripted for military service. 3. This news has spread amongst the Bahrain Petroleum Company employees and the effect is said to be good. 4. It remains to be seen whether any further personnel will attempt to leave. Political Agent, Bahrain.Telegram From S. At Shiraz. Political Resident, To Political Agent, Bahrain* No. T/297 Dated 21st received 22nd July 1941. V .ivr Your telegram Mo. 244 July 20tli. ^ 0 ^ Please see paragraph No. 3 of enclosure to my Printed letter No.C/277 dated June 28th. Even if tanker is calling at an Indian port indivi dual is not likely to be conscripted, taking no action. Prior. I am therefore5 THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Awali, Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf, ^ 21st July, 1941. PA-599. His Britannic Majesty's BAHREIN. Dear Sir, / / We have just received the following cable from South Africa - ' G. A. MacDonald a^s us advise you he is returning England family reasons w This will confirm my telephone conversation to-day. This man left here with the firm understanding that he was returning to Bahrein and is due back here from leave on 9th November, 1941. Will you please handle this case and see what can be done to have this man return, otherwise we may have to restrict vacations to South Africa if men continue to go there and then on to England. Yours very truly, M. H. Lipp. Chief Local Representative. THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED.Telegram From u . ?Y/ 1 • i / Telegram Q. From Poliuical Pesid.en'ti^ Shiraz* T° Political Agent, Bahrain. No. T/313. Dated 23rd received 24th July 1941. &gt; c. i 19 I fe /&gt; • A' »J U$i«l . * i\ C O Your telegram No. 247 July 22nd. Action in South Africa requested would involve reference to Union Government through His Majesty's Government. I do not consider this is justified in the present case or in few similar ones that may arise. Prior. J 1THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Awali, Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf. 30th July, 1941. PA-617. His Britannic 2€ajesty*s Political Agent, BAHREIN. Dear Sir, Please refer to my letter No. PA-599 regarding George McDonald who left South Africa for England after he had promised to return for a further contract. We now have a cable from South Africa advising us that L. R. Miles, who left Bahrein on 3rd My 1941 for leave in South Africa on the understanding that he would be returning, has also taken advantage of the Company and gone direct to England. I would like to have rec^ommendations from you as to what steps can be taken where these men, evidently with malice aforethought, make the trip to South Africa with the intention of proceeding to England. We have put these men on tankers as a special concession, making full settlement with them here before they left. In the future we may be obliged to restrict our vacations to South Africa as evidently some of our men are not playing the gam* with us. This is the third case of this kind that has happened. A man should give us 90 days notice if he is not returning. men going on vacation but will pay them their salaries monthly through our Caltex offices in the country the employee is vacationing. Do you think a cable to London advising the proper authorities there that these men have left us without notice would have any effect and so have a more stabilizing influence on the men and give them to ^ under stand that they cannot run off without proper notice. In the future we may not give full settlement to We would app: Chief Local nepreser&amp;aTuve. THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED e cases.rm^fidential No •C/807-12/19• Political Agency, Bahrain, the 2nd August 1941, To The Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited Bahrain. Dear Sir, Please refer to your letter No, PA-617 dated the 30th July 1941. with current Agency affairs, Major Alban only recently left. , I am therefore obliged to ask you for clarification of certain points, before I refer the case for his opinion. 2. Am I correct in assuming that the individuals in question were not merely on leave; but had actually completed their contract with the Company ? Is it also correct that they had not signed a fresh contract; but were under a gentle mans agreement to return and sign a fresh contract on their arrival ? In this case, it might be Major Albans view that with whom this type of agreement may safely be concluded. 3. As regards the 'economic sanctions' which you propose: I do not fufcly understand the detailed procedure which you have in mind, but presume it would not involve a breach of ment between yourselves and men going to South Africa, for the I must apologise for not being yet fully in touch the Company have the best opportunities for judging individuals contract on the part of the Company. It is possible, h6wever, that Major Alban would see no objection to a voluntary agree- retention of a portion of their salary in deposit, in return for the grant of a tanker passage, the deposit to be forfeited /-- 2 - forfeited on their failure to discharge specified obligations May I know your views on this ? 4* 1 do no ^ think that a telegram to His Majesty’s Government in these cases woufcd have great effect. Men are liable to national service in England, whatever their behaviour abroad may have been; and if the sole object of these men is to reach the United Kingdom, I doubt whether the fear of conscription there will influence them in the way, for example, that conscription in India would do. 5. I presume that I am correct in thinking that, even if a breach of contract has been committed, the Company would not consider it worth while to engage litigation in England to protect themselves ? Yours faithfully, IM' for Political Agent, Bahrain.THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Awali, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. August 2nd, 1941. co:irirc!iTL.i: PA.621 His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, The Agency, BAHREIN. Pear Sir, The subject employee, who has elected to return to the U.K. upon his completion of a 30-month foreign Service Agreement is scheduled to sail on the next B.I. 'boat to Karachi. He plans to proceed via City Line steamer Karachi to the' U.K. Present scheduling indicates that he will have a stop-over in Karachi of approximately 4 days. The above information is supplied you for any action necessary in this type of case. Yours very truly, GAK:B.The Bahrein Petroleum Company limited n Awali, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. 4th August, 1941. PA-626. BAHREIN. His Britannic Majesty's Political Agent. T3ATTDT7TW 0 ' Dear Sir, Bahrein, I would like to have your advice if it would 'be possible to approach the Political Resident along the lines suggested, i.e. having all visas for British subjects leaving Bahrein carrying an endorsement that they are not to proceed to the Uni ted Kingdom from India or South Africa without having ratification from the proper authorities in Bahrein. new contracts 'before departing from Bahrein on long leave and will route them through India and will only use a tanker if and when other transportation is unavailable. This will 'be on rare occasions. It is out of our jurisdiction to compel employees after completing a contract to re-sign 'before leaving. If an employee does not intend to return or feels that he does not wish to sign a new contract in Bahrein, we will notify you in these specific cases. They will all 'be routed through India. have convinced me that a cable to London to the authorities there will make little difference and it will be much better to handle it through the Political Agent or Political Resident We will also ask all of our employees to sign As for the last paragraph of my letter PA-617, you M. H. Lipp. Chief Local Representative. THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED*J (U t-r ; } P rnnfidemi al No . C/814-12/19 Asst • The/Political Agent, Bahrain, Presents his compliments to: The Political Agent, Bahrain and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document ( s ) for favour of such action as he may think desirable. 2 , Mr. Boyle is proceeding to Karachi by the 3.3. 'Adria” leaving Bahrain on the 7th August 1941. The; agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf. Dated _6.th .August Reference to previous correspondence: Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Letter No. PA.621 dated 2nd August 1941 from Chief Locll Representative, Bahrain Pe troleum Company Limited. Subject. Mr. J. G. Boyle i&gt;^ HTelegram 'S' From Political Agent, Bahrain, at Karachi To Political Resident, Bushire. No. T/5 Dated 8th August 1941 Bapco report departure of Mr. J.G. Boyle on completion of contract by S.S. Adria on 7th inst for Karachi en route to United Kingdom by City Line. Suggest conscription on arrival. - Alban -rnnfidentiaft t^jY' D.O.No•C/816-12/19. Dated the 9th August 1941. ‘1 ; ! 1 A | | I enclose copies of the marginally-noted corres pondence which I have had with Lipp on the subject of ) the leakage of key personnel ti 1, Letter No.PA-617 datedSCth July f *91 ) 1941 from Chief Local Hepres'enta- ) from the Bahrain Petroleum live, Bahrain Petroleum Company. ) Company through men v/ho go 2, Letter No.C/807 dated 2nd Mgust ) 1941 from Publicity Officer, Bah- ) to South Africa on leave, and rain * / Q ^ ^ ) fail to honour a verbal under- 3, Letter No.PA-626 dated 4tn August ) from Chief Local Representative, ) standing to return for a Bahrain Petroleum Company, ) Ml.' . ) fresh contract, 2. I have made it clear to Lipp that certain steps should be taken by the Company itself, and I hope that I have correctly interpreted your views regarding this point, 3. We should, however, as I think you will agree, do ■ what we can on our part to help a Company, whose produc tion is of importance to us in the present state of world affairs. As you know, the Resident has given his fajor R.G.E.W. Alban, O.B.E., opinion.... Political Agent, Bahrain, at Karachi, mtsopinion that action through Fis Majesty's 'Government and Government of Union of South Africa is not justified. I suggest, however, that we may endorse the passports of employees 01 the Bahrain Petroleum Company whom they regard as 'key men', with some remark such as 'Should net be permitted to leave for United Kingdom without reference to Political Agent, Bahrain'. X have insisted to Lipp that before we can justify ourselves in doing this (on the assumption that P.R. will agree), it is essential that the employees in question should sign a fresh contract \vith the Company^ as a verbal agreement would be insufficient grounds for restricting their movements. Yours sincerely,The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited Awali, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. 11th August, 1941. Confidential. PA-633. His Britannic Majesty’s Political BAHREIN. Agent, Dear Sir, Mr. F. L. Johnson left our employment without completing his full contract and was nicked up in India where he was sent to an Officers Training Camp. Attached is a copy of Mr. Johnson’s letter to a friend of his in Bahrein stating that ”It seems that the Political Agent had wired to the military authorities at Karachi telling them what time I would arrive at the airport and recommended my conscription. As nice a piece of underhand work as I have ever had the misfortune to witness M . here that he would undoubtedly be conscripted in India as we had received information from the Political Agent, according to your letter C/677 of June 29th, 1941 - quote M I have now received information that European British subjects between the ages of 18 and 50 including those in transit are liable to be conscripted in India”. We also received a cable through our New York Office from Johnson’s father asking us to do what we could to withhold conscription before Johnson left Bahrein. A copy of this cable and our reply is attached. thoroughly aware that he might be conscripted in India and therefore we do not see how he could claim any underhand work on the part of the Government or the Company, as this is not a true fact. The whole matter of the conscription of Canadians in India has again been brought to our attention by several Johnson was specifically told before he left From this evidence you can see that Johnson wasPA-633. - 2 - 11th August, 1941 of our stable Canadian employees and they would like to have further clarificatigzf of the matter. On May 27th 1941 in your letter 0-516 you wrote to us on the position of Canadians and in our reply Con-325 of 29th May, 1941 we asked for further clarification. In your reply letter of June 29th, 1941 - No. C-677 - you stated, quote*'- M I have b t now received information that European British subjects between the ages of 18 and 50 including those in transit are liable to be conscripted in India” - unquote. These Canadians have called on us and again asked us under what clause in the Indian Emergency Act can a citizen of Canada be conscripted in India. These men were told that as far as the Company was concerned we had to abide by the ruling of the British Government as we were a British Company and could only take such matters through the proper sources, which is the Political Agent in Bahrein. They asked us for further clarification on this matter by writing to our Attorneys in New York who in turn should write to the Canadian Government. Temoin, that they should make an appointment with you and further clarify the situation if they so desire, as we were in no position to write to our Attorneys on this matter or deal directly with the Canadian Government; that our only course of dealing with such matters was directly with the Political Agent in Bahrein. do so, we would appreciate further clarification of the Conscription Act pertaining to Canadians. We recommended to these men, namely Sutton and For our information, if you are in a position to Yours verv trulv. M. H. Lipp. Chief Local [Representative. THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LBHTED.Dear Carl, Officers* Training School Belgaum, India. July 27th/41. C, G, ^ell, it was a good idea while it lastprl * c-ni ruy r Unfortunately for me, I didn't quite make it ~ So uni pc*- n fv home 1 m J an * jrllht 4 uick like, it looks as if yours truly will h^cne a'hit i of e t t ^° Ver in the gears of the Indian.army. Just call me lootenant aM I am writing this so that you fellows 'har.ir ?hG- t, ■ know what you are up against if you get any ideas wl11 skip home through India. iThen the plane got' into Karachi Ind i went^tr. the customs house to get ay luggage examined they were waitinetor me* It seems that the political agent had wired to the military anthnh??Go at Karachi, telling them what time I would arrive at the ai/port^ aG ^ recommended my conscription. As nice a piece of underhand wo^k as I tovg ever had the misfortune to witness. If that cable had not hlen sent there is no doubt but that I should have been allowed to proceed ,r I am feeling bitter about the whole affair so I am hoping that none nr 7 you Will attempt what Idid. ' oplng l ' nat none of All the righ'/S which a Canadian citizen has at home are nTmamr+i forfeited when he gets to India and the fact that'there is no conlcrirtioS at home or the fact that you are in transit means nothing to the millta™ ithorities here. The law reads 'Any British subject is liable to con? scnption no matter from what part of the Empire he comes' and believe me, you have to have a mighty good story to get around it. Obviously mine was not good enough. ' J ’ I had a te/iihle time in Karachi. T had to 'be interviewed 'by „ . . , t t t ox d iC . J - 11 ^iracni. i naa to be interviewed by l ?~ army officials and it was four days before 1 knew definitely H|t I was not going to be allowed to go. After that I was conscribted and sent here for a four months' course. EEI here took me four d.ays. Bel gaum is about two hundred miles south of Bombay. There is no coastal railroad from Karachi so that upd to cover half of Ind ia to get there - I went by way of Lahore, Delhi and believe it or not, good old Poona. In fact I slept in the station at Poona one night after missing a connection. It's a great life sometimes. The life at this training school is not too bad although the strenuous routine of physical training and rifle drill etc, is just about ailing me after the comparatively lazy life of Bahrein. On the other land, it should do me a lot of good physically. All this has been a great blow to my marriage mans. There is i possibility though that I will get a commission in the ordinance Corps id be put in a munitions plant. If this materializes I will try to get lelen out here. The unfortunate part of it is that those things that I sent home \ my box for some of the fellows there at Bahrein will not be delivered rnless there is some means by which I can have my father claim the box. )therwise it will just lie there in bond until I get home to claim it lyself. Tell Harvey Clare that I am sorry that I will not be able to trrange for those flowers for his girl friend and that I will return his loney to him at Bahrein. I would be very glad if you fellows would write to me here and .et me know how everything is going at Bahrein. I sure would appreciate it f you would do this and I promise to answer everybody. Perhaps you would &gt;e interested in what life in the Indian army is like. If you are writing, the new handle is Officer-Cadet P.L. Johnson .nd the address is on the letter head. Say hello for me to Homo, Bene, Jim, George, Harvey, Pap, Keith .nd all the rest, Sincerely, (sgnd ) Lloyd..D.0:No.C/828-12/19, ■Opted the 14th August 1941, which I have received from Llpp on the subject of the conscription of Canadians In India. \ I understand that the General Clauses Act contains a section to the effect that the word 'European 11 includes American and’’Australian' if there is nothing repugnant in the context. But our copy of the Act is old and un amended, and does not contain this definition. Thdre is a definition of European British Subject in Section 4 (i) of the Criminal Procedure Code; but it might be held that this only refers to the purposes of the Code itself, 3, Can you possibly ascertain the position from some legal pundit in Karachi, jor B, G, Alban, O.B.E., Political Agent, Bahrain, at Karachi. and let me know the answer ? Yours sincerely,Telegram Q1 From Political Agent, Bahrain, at Karachi. To Political, Bahrain. No. T/ll Dated and receivedthe 14th August 1941. Please get copy of Foreign telegram No. 4224 August 13th about Day from Political Resident and make necessary enquiries from Lipp , informing Political Resident and me or result and repeating to Foreign. Alban'A Telegrctm • l Q ( w From Government of India, Simla. To Political, Bahrain. Repeated Political Resident at Bahrain. No. 4224. Dated 13th received 14th August 1941. yf' Reference Foreign telegram N 0 . 3451 of July 9th. 2. Day has arrived with his wife and has been selected for an emergency commission subject to your confirmation that he is of unimpeachable character. Presume that his wife is not of foreign origin. - FOREIGN -rnnfide nti 8,1 No .C/834-12/19 Political Agency, Bahrain, the 17th August 1941, To The Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, Bahrain. Dear Sir, Please refer to my demi-official letter No.C/745 dated the 12th JUly 1941. 2. I have received information that Day is under con sideration for an emergency commission, but the authorities in India wish to have confirmation that he is of unimpeachable character. I should be grateful if you would give me your assessment. 3. I presume that his wife is not of foreign origin ? Yours very truly, for Political Agent, Bahrain. 1 ,1 u Awali Bahrain. 13 August 1941 H.B.M ! s. Political Agent, h Bahrain. Dear Sir, l On 31 July 1940 I sent an application to join the R.A.P. to you. the Bahrein Petroleum Co. subsequently decided not to release me. At the beginning of November next the Company will no longer require me and I want to apply again to join the R.A.P. I wduldbe grateful if you could let me know whether you will forward my applica/tion. information you could give me about service in the R.A.P. for British subjects in the East. I would be indebted to you for any Yours truly, (R.CHANDLER)Confidential No•C/844-12/19• Political Agency, Bahrain, the 19th August 1941 . To The Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, Bahrain• . I 4 l m Dear Sir, / Reference your letter No # Con-623 dated the 5th September 1940 regarding Mr. R. Chandler 1 s enlistment in ^ His Majesty^ Forces. i^&lt;&gt;&amp; I have now received a further application from Chandler for service in the Royal Air Force, and should be glad to know whether the Company will, as he states, be able to dispense with his services after October 1941. Yours faithfully, v*- for Political Agent, Bahrain.THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED /'-N Awali, Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf. No. PA-643. August 18, 1941. P Q ■n/'v j- * Ci * XJXXJL . Eis Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir, Please refer to jrour letter As far as we know Day is of We do not know whether Mrs. No. C/834-12/19, good character. Day is of foreign origin or not. Yours very truly, T\»T TJ T TT3p Chief Local Representative TEE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY, LIMITED.Telegram From Q • Political Agent, Bahrain Government of India, Simla. Copy by hand to Political Resident at Bahrain. No. 295 Dated the 22nd August 1941. Your telegram No. 4424 dated August 13th 2. Confirmed that Day is of good character, not known whether his v/ife is of foreign origin PoliticalTHE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Awali, Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf. 20th August, 1941. PA-651. His Britannic Majesty's Political Agent BAHKEIN. ' - 0 &gt; Dear Sir, Referring to your letter Ro. C/844-12/19 of the 19th inst., IKr. R. Chandler completes his contract with us in October, 1941. He has then fulfilled his obligations with us. Chandler is a chemist of outstanding ability and has proved to be most useful to our organization. ¥e would like to have him remain on a second contract but have no means of insisting on him re-signing unless he wishes to do so of his own free will. Yours very truly, M. H. Lipp. Chief Local Representative. THE BAHREIN EETROLETJM COMPANY LIMITED.No,C/854-12/19. Political Agency, Bahrain, the 25th August 1941. To Mr. R, Chandler, C/o i'he Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, Bahrain. Dear Sir, Reference your letter dated the 13th August 1941 on x,he subject of application for service in the Royal Air Force. 2 . Your application will, if you so desire it, be forward ed to the authorities concerned, provided you are free to leave the island# 3. Information relating to service in the Royal Air Force for British subjects in the East is contained in this Agency notice dated 27th July 1940 and its enclosures. Yours faithfully, for Political Agent, Bahrain.cn / rnnftdential Ko. K/17 Office of the Political Agent, Bahrain, Camp Karachi, the 15th August 1S41 Proa Major R.G.E.W. Alban, O.B.E,, Political Agent, Bahrain, To The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Camp Bahrain. Sir, I have the honour to refer to the question of key personnel of the Bahrain Petroleum Company who (a) insist , on leaving the Company* s service on completion of their con tracts or (b) proceed on leave earned during the contract with the implied intention of returning to take up a fresh contract or ( c ) proceed on leave during the period of their contracts and then depart for their home country without notice instead of returning to duty. 2* As the war progresses skilled personnel become scarcer and these defections cause increasing concern to the Bahrain Petroleum Company*s authorities who have plainly warned that if they continue to lose such men production will have to be decreased# 3 . The General Manager has now reported that two more key personnel who were on leave in South Africa on completion of their contracts and on the clear understanding that they would return to take up fresh contracts, have left for England instead of returning to Bahrain# He requests that some arrangements may be made to prevent or discourage ouch 4 /- occurrences#7 ^ u ;jrv;K ' nt we have no means of preventing British subjects from leaving Bahrain and the only means of discouraging attempts at evasion of further service on the part of personnel is the threat of conscription in India. T:i rt i - m vns 0 f preventing men on leave in South Africa, for example, from departing for the United Kingdom for good. It is true that those men who have completed their contracts (and these are the most frequent cases) have the right to quit, out as the General Manager has already pointed out the time v.ill om /vnen, if defections continue unrestricted, the management will have to call on His Majesty*s Government to provide skilled replacements as an alternative to closing I down the works. 5. It is suggested that the situation would be suffi ciently met if this Agency were authorised to endorse on the passports of such individuals leaving Bahrain some such remark as * Should not be permitted to leave for United Kingdom ■ Canada etc., without reference to the Political Agent, Bahrain”, the Coj^any on their part to ensure that such per- sons have signed a fresh contract before leaving the Island. 6. As regards those employees who either refuse to sign a new contract or who do not intend to return, the Company have intimated that they will route them to destinations through India and at the same time will inform this Agency. They can then be conscripted on arrival in India as heretofore. I have the honour to be Sir Your most obedient servant L Political Agent, Bahrain(L. &gt; 2 \^ Confidential Political Agent, Bahrain, D*0. No. K/18 Camp Karachi, the 15th August 1941, —Cl/a-f tioiArCd A' Reference your dewi-offIcial letter No. C/816 dated the 9th Augu&amp;t 1941 about leakage of key personnel r from the Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited.l ^ \ ^ 2. I send you herewith a letter &gt;o the Political Resident on the subject. Will you please read it and if it is complete, forward it to the Political Resident ? If I have omitted anything however please return it by air with your comments. Yours sincerely. m (k )tain J.B. Howes, M.B.^*., Political Agency, Bahrain.CONFIDENTIAL. 455-ii oi 1U41. r\ \ The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian compliments to Gulf presents his PolltiGal Agent, Bahrain* and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docemenj/j^). Irilisli vJor Britisli Uonsulate-General, BUS HI RE. 9th August 1941. Dated Reference to previous correspondence : Residency Printed Juetter flo.C/ 285 , dated the 10 th July 1941. Ill ■ .ir 5 . Description of Enclosure, Name and Date. Subject. Political Resident 1 s telegram ^o. 783, dated 9th August 1941, CONSCRIPT ION OP J.G. BOYhE79/65 iC.'v A ^ r\ 4 ^ r • 4 a w Telegram From To Ho. 783 Dated 9th August 1941. Political Resident,Buahire. Oovernraent of Xndia, aimla. if) Your telegram iio. 3451 July 9th. b ollowing is repetition of telegram flo.T/3 August 8th from Political Agent, Bahrain, begins. Bahrain Petroleum Company report departure of Mr. J.ti. Boyle on completion of contract by s.s. Adria on August 7th for Karachi en route for United Kingdom by City Line. Suggest conecription on arrival. Bnds. - BRITCOKSUL - R.K.T. 9 / 8 .Confidential Office of the Political Agent, Bahrain, Camp Karachi, the 20th August 1341 So. K/23 To The Honourable the political Resident in the Persian dulf. Camp Bahrain. Memorandum A copy of the marginally noted letter from the stter So. PA-633 dated the 11th August \ Chief Local Representative. Hi with enclosures \ 9 The Bahrain Petroleum Com pany Limited, on tne subject of conscription of Canadian subjects in India is forwarded herewith. 2. As will be seen, as a result of the conscription of Mr* F*L. Johnson, lately of The Bahrain Petroleum Company, some Canadian employees of the Company are querying the conscription of Canadian subjects in India. These Canadians have of course © right to know whether they are liable to service when in India and this they dc know now after hearing about Johnson. It therefore appears that these men intend to challenge the legality of the action of the Military Authorities in India in conscripting Canadian subjects, 3 . I would be grateful for instructions as to what reply I should give these men should they seek an interview. Political Agent, BahrainfWidential No#0/862-12/19• V Political Agency, Bahrain, the 28th August 1941 To The Naval Officer in Charge, Naval Base, Bahrain. Memorandum ^ ^! &gt; Reference my memorandum No# C/558 dated the 8th June 1941 regarding the application of Mr. W. Barnfield for a temporary commission in the R.N.V.R. 2# Mr. Barnfield is anxious to know the result of his application and I would be grateful to know what reply may be given to him. nM. for Political Agent, Bahrain.SNTIAL No. C/443 of 1941. Office of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Camp Bahrain. Dated the 9th September 1941 . To The Political Agent, BAHRAIN. SUBJECTKey Personnel of Bahrain Petroleum Company. ME MORAN DUM . Cj^'_ Reference your letter No. K/17, dated 15th August 1941, copy is enclosed of my telegram No. T/607 of today’s date to His Majesty’s Secretary of State for India. °. Reference paragraph 4 of your letter ouoted above. Powers to prevent the departure from Bahrain of male European British subjects exist in King’s Regulation No. 2 of 1940, dated 29th July 1940, (copy.forwarded to you under Residency Printed Letter No. 554-S, dated 30th July 1940). It is agreed, however, (vide India Office telegram No. 4220, dated 27th July 1940, and connected correspondence) that their use would not be justified in the case of men whose contracts had expired, and in the case of others they would have to be exercised judiciously in order to prevent'* trouble locally. Sd. C.G.Prior ■ : * M - ,, A-ttested. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. for^Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. (A ll k' ONFI P'S NT I AL ^ 1 &gt;&lt;-T\ f: } {%') / _ ^ v * To No. C/444 of 1941. Office of the Political Eesident in the Persian Gulf, Camp Bahrain. Dated the 9th September 1941. The Political Agent, Bahrain. Copy to The Secretary to the Government of India, External Affairs Department, Simla, with copy of Memorandum referred to. SUBJECT Conscription in India of Canadian employees of Bahrain Petroleum Company. MEMORANDUM 'V 0 Reference your Memorandum No. K/ 23 , dated 20 th August 1941. 2. There is no reason to suppose that the action taken by the Government of India is illegal, and in any case the point is no concern of ours. Canadians who consult you should be informed that any persons aggrieved by the action of the Government of India have a legal remedy, and are at liberty to pursue it in courts in British India, if so advised. Signed C.G.Prior Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Attested. for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.I' I) ■A H, O/o GUY CLIFT CUB, YHE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED, A w » 1 i # ftthrein Island, B9rsi«n Gulf. ept«abor 6, 1941. A I H HAIL Hie Senretwpy, Department of Induetries and iAbour. GoTemment of India, DELHI. Dear Sir, I am taking the liberty of addressing myself to you with tha object of tendering my services to The Government of India. My contractual obligations to my present employers cease during October 1941, end I am most anxious that my energies should be more directly used in furtherance of the Empire mr Effort. For this reason, I am, of course, willing to serve in a civil capacity or in any one of H.M. Armed Forces, wherever I could be of most use. I do not know whether, in addressing this letter to you, I am acting correctly, but I am sure that if I am in error you will know the Department to which it should have been sent, and shall feel extremely obliged if you will kindly forward a copy (enclosed) to the correct destination. ?br your information, should the Government of India not be interested in this application, I propose to tender my services to the R. I. N. Attached please find schedule of my qualifications.(2t?J SCHEDULE RELATING TO QUALIFX CAT IONS OF GUY CLIFFORD, m. in:&gt;t. PETROLEUM. F,R. KCON.r, AGE MARRIhD EDUCATED SMPLOYERE SALARY HEALTH EKPERIEHCE 56 ( 301,11 ^ndon, 1905 - both parents English). No children (Wife English). ^utton Valence School 1916/81. School Certificate - London Matriculation. City of London College (for Exane. of The Chartered Inst, of Secretaries). Cass Technical Institute and Battersea Polytechnic - Conaplete courses in Petroleum Technology - both practical and theoretical. Tho Bahrein Petroleum Company Ltd. (pr&gt;st 6 years) I/C Petroleum Shipping. Rs.1,000 p.m. plus living allowance and free bungalow. Sound - Height 6* 0' Weight 11 st. 1 lb. 'fide business and practical experience in the petroleum industry - including the refining, transportation, specifications, and sale of crude oil and its products, including lubricants, petrols, kerosenes, diesel and furnace oils. GC/trwKarachi, 19th September 1941 Many tnanKs lor your letter of September llth» 2# Aa &gt;ou Knowi^the production of petroleum etc« is a key industry of the war ana Government are definitely opposed to allowing key men of the Bahrain Petroleum Company to leave for service elsewhere* I assume that you have con sulted Mr* Iiipp over this master a no tne Company will have no difficulty in filling your place* lf f however, there is a difficulty In finding a replacement^then I certainly think that your services are more valuable with the Company than elsewhere* Anyhow I hope you will let me know how matters stand after wnich I will see whether I can help. With best regards. Yours sincerely, Clifford, Esq., c/o Xhe Bahrain petroleum Company Limited, Bahrain.Bahrain. .5 September 1941. &gt;*, His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrain. near Sir, y/? With reference to your letter of 25 August 1941, I would like you to forward my application to join the R.A.P. in any part &lt;?f the world in categories (b) or (c) y I Q vf V isA, £ of your Notice of 27 July 1940. Name: Richa.rd Chandler. Bate of birth: 27 July 1913. Education: B.Sc. Oil Engineering and Refining, Birmingham University. I sent a Medical Certificate with my application to you of 31 July 1940. h l nj\ iiif Yours truly,Telegram 'q?! From Political Agent,Bahrain, at Karachi India Office, London T/33 26th September 1941 To No Dated In continuation of my telegram No. 333 dated 10th September 1940. 2. R. Chandler whose contract irith the Bahrain Petroleum Company expires early November has again applied for service in Royal Air Force, section (b) or (c) of Foreign Office Circular No. 40 of 1940, in any part of the world. 3. Request instructions. - Alban - /THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Awali, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf. 21st Septeiaber, 1941. PA-685. His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, BAHREIN. t Dear Sir, Please refer to our letters CON-825 and PA-633 dealing with, the forced enlistment of Canadians while passing through India on their way to Canada. Attached is a letter we have received from Mr. P. L. Johnson, one of our employees who quit 'before his contract had expired and who was conscripted in India If Johnson’s case is authentic, it looks as if all Canadians are entitled to depart directly to their homes in Canada after completion of their contracts, or on giving us notice of 90 days which we have stipulated they must do in their contracts. Prom the evidence presented in Johnson’s letter are you now in a position to give us a definite ruling in the case of Canadians leaving our employment. Yours very truly, -v??, // M. H. Lipp. Chief Local Bepresentative. THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. Attachment.Officer Cadet's Training Unit Q,*V.O. Madras Sappers &amp; Miners Bangalore, India September 9, 1941 9 Personnel Manager, Bahrein Petroleum Company, Bahrein Island, P.G, Dear Sir, I have cabled you this morning requesting that you re hook my passage to Toronto, Canada from Calcutta. Following my conscription into the Indian army, while intransit through India in July, I protested to the Canadian Government, still believing that such a detention was irregular. They in turn contacted the Indian Government with the result that orders came from Simla yesterday saying that I was to be discharged from the army, granted an exit permit to leave the country and furnished with railway transportation to Calcutta in order that I might continue my journey to Canada. I ask that you arrange this passage as soon as possible because I must pay my own living expenses from the date of my dis charge from the army and as I have incurred considerable expense already, find myself none too flush. My claim against the Indian Government for this expense is valid enough, but there is little hope of recovering the money before I leave. I understand from KLM f s Karachi agents that £..35 of the fare from Karachi to Singapore was not refunded. Whether I enter this as part of my claim rests entirely with you, so please let me know about it. I hope that my experience here in India will clear up, once and for all, the question which I know to be bothering my fellow countrymen in Bahrein. Yours very truly, s/ F. L. Johnson P.S. - I have permission to remain here in Bangalore until my passage is arranged, provided it does not take too You can get in touch with me at the above address. For ca e purposes, the address, c/o Sappers, Bangalore, is sufficient. F • I. • J *nrmfldential No. K/75 Office of the Karachi, Political Agent, Bahrain, the 89th September 1941. To Ihw Hono arable the Political Resident in the Persian Guif, Bushire• Memorandum Reference correspondence ending with your memoraaiu* Ho * C/444 c;,, ’ ted the £th Scptenl-er 1941 regarding conscrip- tion in India of Canadian subjects in transit. , - Be I enclose e copy of letter No. PA-685 dated the 81st S*.pteiabe; lr41 from the Chief Bocal Representative, ^ha Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, cith enclosure. 3. in view of the fact that Canadian subjects are apparently not being conscripted in India and the suggestion regarding detention of British subjects in South Africa (vide ay memorandum No. E/17 dated the loth August 1941) has not been fount possible, it appears that only British subjects who may pass through India will be conscripted. 4. I should be grateful to know whether the Company are to be informed accordingly. c* In view of the fact that Company personnel are con tinually leaving the service, it is hoped that your sugges tion (vice paragraph 2 of your telegram No. T/607 dated the 3th September 1341) regarding permission for the Company to replace such personnel with Americans may be approved at an early date. political Agent, Bahrain.GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, Department, v LETTE [iV. V.— This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to sate telegraphic expense and undue use of the but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To TdesZched] f0rmahhes U is warded aild si d«ed as if it had been From TRe Political Resident, Bushire. To The Political Agent, Bahrain ^ Repeated The Secretary to the orovernment of India, External Affairs Department, Simla. No. 3*S * Dated September 19 4/ly Subject i- Application from Dr.K.L.George, M.B.B.S. for an emergency com* mission. Copy is enclosed of Government of India Express Getter Bo.D.3?9b-B/41 dated the 20th August 1941. 2. Please furnish report required direct to the Govermaent of India repeating me. Sd. C.G.Prior. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Attested. Po^Becretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. S. 6. MFP—501 S&amp;p—(M- 820)—23-7-36—300,000.til AiRUAlij. GUVERHMiiNT Oi?' INDIA. External Affairs Department. HiXPR^33 DBTTER . yrom foreign, 3imia. To Kesident, TJahrain. ^0.0.3795-^/41. Dated the 20th August 1941. Application Irom Dr.K.L.George, M.B.B.S. for an emergency Commission. Application has oeen received from Dr.K.L. George, G.A.3.O.G., Bahrain, for an Emergency Commission in the i*M.3• it is requested that a report on his character, etc., during his time at Bahrain may kindly be furnished to the Government of India as soon as possible. 13SUE ON THE ABOVE HAS BEEN AUTHORISED. SD. h.A.G.ERi. Under secretary to the government of India.D*0*No *0/936-12/19. Dated the 4th October 1941. Dr. K.L. George, M.B.B.S*, who is working with you, I understand, has applied for a commission in the I would be grateful if you could let me have your confidential views about his suitability and also about his character and work during his stay with you. Yours sincerely, F* W. Ohliger, Esquire, California Arabian Standard Oil Coy., Ltd., i Dhahran, Saudi Arabia.■v CONFIDENTIAL . No. oT 1941 ,.( 2 - 0- u \0 UL. The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Political Agent, Bahrain, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document (§9* British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. * YA -jjy Air ma il becret. uwVOSRIM M&amp;JNIT u# xM DIA. External Affairs Department jj'rom jjorei^n, aunla To uritconsul, isahrain. jjio.D.930*V/(o)/4l. i^ated the 28th August 1941* xour telegram j*o.Y83, dated 9th August 1941 mr.J.u.boyle was interviewed on arrival at Karachi by Military Headquarters, oind Area, and was found medically unfit for military service; it was, moreover, found impossible to utilise his services in any other manner, military or civil. ne has therefore been granted an exit permit to leave India. The issue of the above had been authorised sd. L.A.ii.l'ry under secretary to the government of india,No.C/943-12/19. Political Agency, Bahrain, 5th October B41. To The Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, Bahrain. Dear Sir, Reference your letter No. PA-621 dated the 2nd August 1941 regarding Mr. J. G. Boyle. 2. Mr. Boyle has been found medically unfit for military service and he has therefore been granted an Exit Permit to leave India. Yours faithfully, t , Political Agent, Bahrain.DO/SAC/2641 4th October, 1941 Dear cffltyfr CiMwi W. Stiff, our Diesel mechanic in Qatar, who has had three or four years in the Persian Gulf, wishes to terminate his services with this Company and return to England, As he is a specialist it will be difficult for us to replace him in these days but we cannot retain him against his own inclinations. He is 34 years of age and, presumably, on return to England, will be liable to be called up. The story, however, has been given considerable cre dence in oil company circles here that people in his position are conscripted for military or Government service on arrival in India and get no farther. If this is the case, Stiff would prefer to remain in Qatar. The position now is that if this story can be substan tiated by any responsible authority we can probably retain Stiff*s services. As previously explained, we should have considerable difficulty in finding a replacement although it would hardly be correct to state that he is absolutely indis pensable. If you have anything definite on the procedure in such cases on arrival in India it would be of great assistance to us in explaining the circumstances to Stiff. Yours sincerely Major R. G. Alban, H. B. M.*s Political Agent, Bahrain. /D.0*No*C/941-12/19, O a ted the 5th October 1941* Reference your letter Ho.DO/SAC/2641 dated the 4th October 1941 regarding Mr. W* Stiff. 2 m I have received intimation that European British subjects between the ages of 18 and 50, including those in transit, are liable to be conscripted in India. British subjects who have been proceeding to their homes from Bahrain via India have already beer* conscripted in several cases* Youra s incerely. E. V. Packer, Esquire, Petroleum Concessions Limited, Bahrain.Telegram r From P To C TT o. 350 Dated the 5th October 1941. hr. 9. Chandler, British subject, of Bahrain Petr- lean 'ompnny, v/ho has applied for service in the is leaving Bahrain for India by air on 6 th Octobe on completion of contract. He is anxious to serve in B.A.P. in any part of the world. TT is address will be care of Thomas Cook p c Cons, T'arachi, for some days. t Politic- 1 t L Cp. i. *&gt;) .Dated Simla, the 2&lt;?/£_September 1941. gUBJECT: Conscription in India of Canadian employees of the Bahrain P’etroleum Company. P. Reference your memorandum to the Political Agent, Bahrain, No.C/444 of 1941, dated the 9th September 1941. 2. Although the action taken against Mr. Johnson was entirely legal the Government of India have since telegraphed to the Secretary of State for India enquiring whether His Majesty's Government consider that the National Service (European British Subjects) Act, 1940, should be emended in the interests of Imperial solidarity so as to exclude persons bom naturalised or domiciled in the Dominions. 3. The Canadian Government have represented that Mr. Johnson could be usefully employed in Canada and orders for his discharge from military service in India have been issued. 4. This is for your information only. Under Secretary to the Government of India. Copy to the Political Agent, Bahrain, for information^ for Assistant Secrets dia. 3d. L.A.C.Fiy By order, etc..r nnfidential D .0 .No .C/948-.12/19, Dated the ?th October 1941. 1 enclose herewith a letter from Johnson pouring out his grievances against me. The statement that my cable (No. 218 dated 29th June) said that he was a 'British subject’' is of course a lie and in any case the Government of India took action on your Express letter No. C/220 dated the 25th June 1941, in which he is clearly stated to be a Canadian. It is a pity that he managed to escape from service in India. He has of course been writing to his Canadian friends here in a somewhat similar strain. * Yours sincerely, Hon'ble Lieutenant Colonel C. G. Prior, Political Heaident in the Persian Gulf, Buahire.1 ■ No.P.2. Sir, 4 &amp;** CONFIDENTIAL. Office of Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, Basfcah. 8 th September, 1941. I have the honour to refer to your No.c/682 12/19 dated 28th August, 1941, and to inform you that the application vras forwarded to the Commander-in-Chief, East Indies Station. He has been asked if a reply can now be given. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your obedient Servant Ia. COMMODORE 7 The Political Agent, The Agency, Bahrain.Office of Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, Basrah, 26th September, 1941. ¥ temporary Royal 13aval Volunteer Reserve commission, 2 , Admiralty approval has been sought, however, for the local entiy of suitable civilians as Ordinary Seamen (Hostilities Only) with a view to their obtaining commissions through service. If and when this approval is given I will inform you in order that Mr.Bamfield may be given the opportunity of entry. In the meantime the Commander—in—Chief wishes to thank Mr.Bamfield for his offer of service. I have the honour to be, Sir, £ ' r / COMMODORE The Political Agent The Agency, BAHRAIN.No. C/980 To Political Agency, Bahrain, the 14th October 1941 The Manager, Petroleum Concessions Limited, BAHRAIN * \ i Dear Sir, Please refer to your letter No. PDQ/SAC/2479 dated the 5th June 1941. 2. I enclose herewith a copy of a letter from the . Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, for the information of Mr. Barnfield. /. /./ Yours f aithfully, j U* / 4 political Agent, Bahrain.Dhahran, Saudi Arabia October 9, 1941 fcrajor R» G» Alban, 0« B» E« His Brittanic Majesty's Political Agent Bahrein Island Persian Gulf Dear Sir: 1941. Dr. George, except for a home leave in India last spring, has been with us since December 1939* His work and record with us have been very satisfactory. I have your letter to me dated 4th October Yours truly F. T A. OHLIGERGOVERNMENT OF INDIA, Department. EXPRESS LETTER qonfldmtlal [iY, B,—TMs is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save lime and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] From Political Agent f Bahrain. To Foreign 9 Simla • Repeated Political Resident, Bushire. C/986- 12/19. 16th October 1941 iftk &gt; Application of Or . K.L. George* for an Emergency Cocxnigslon. Reference your Express letter Kb* D*3795-H/41 dated the 20th August 1941* The Manager of the California Arabian Standard Oil Com pany, with whom Dr. 1C. L. George has been employed since December 1939, reports that his work and record with the Company have been very satisfactory* S. 6. M PP—1206 S&amp;P—(M i 723}—4-2-36—200,000. Political Agent, Bahrain.The Bahrein petroleum Company Limited Confidential. PA-736. Awali, Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf. 15th October, 1941. Major R. G. Alban, His Britannic Majesty's Political Agent, BAHREIN. CWam t4Tf TlM h ■ ^ vw Dear Major Alban, Mr. Jameson, Managing Director from London of the Anglo-Iranian Oil Company, passed through here yesterday on his way to Abadan. I had a discussion with him regarding British staff employees working in Abadan and Bahrein. He advised me that he expects before long the British Government may take a definite step, through the Indian Government, to protect them from losing their British staff operators. Mr. Jameson also stated that if he is short handed on men they are willing to return anyone to Abadan who has left, if he so demands. In other words it looks as if there will be some form of conscription of labour for Abadan. Would such an order also affect us in Bahrein if enforced for Abadan? I believe negotiations are now under way or will shortly be taken up through the India Office in Delhi. Yours very truly, '7^/ // M. H. Lipp. General Manager. THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED.Confidential No.C/994-12/19 Political Agency, Bahrain, 20th October 1941. To The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire« Memorandum yf Reference correspondence ending with your memorandum Ho .0/443 dated the 9th September 1941, I enclose the copy of a letter from the Chief Local Representative, the Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited. 2. The Company are most anxious that the same steps as are contemplated in the case of Abadan may be taken in their case also to protect them from losing their British staff operators. 3. I would be grateful to be informed of the reply to be given. L. Political Agent, Bahrain.Telegram From Q* To India Office, London. Political Agent, Bahrain. No. 13158. Dated 19th received 20th October 1941. \ Your telegram No. T/33 September 26th. Air Ministry are prepared to accept Chandler for pilot training provided you are entirely satis fied that he is (b) not yet within six months of the age of 31 (c) still of highest standard of medical fitness; his vision particularly should be perfect, i.e., 6/6 each eye and colour vision normal in all respects. 2. If so please provide him with cost of passage to Headquarters, Air Training Corps, Salisbury, Southern Bodesia as soon as convenient after release from his employment, reporting date of departure and Training Corps may be notified. Subject to his passing Selection Board in Rhodesia and to medical fitness he will t hen be attested and placed under training. He would be well advised to brush up his knowledge of elementary mathematics. (a) a man of courage, determination and person ality , probable date of arrival at Salisbury so that AirI I (* Telegram From To No. 388 Q. Political Agent, Bahrain. India Office, London. Dated the 21st October 1941. v our telegram No. 13158 October 19th. Chandler left Bahrain for United Kingdom on October 6th address unknown. PoliticalTelegram From r - 3. Secretary of State for India, London. To Political Hesident in the Persian Gulf Repeated Political Agent, Bahrain Copy by post to Government of India, Hew Delhi. Ho.13233 Dated and received the 21st October 1941. Your telegram Ho. T/607 September 9th. Staff of Bahrain Petroleum Company. After discussion with Ballantyne and Petroleum Department 1 agree with your views in paragraph Ho.2 and only remedy seems to be that which you suggest in paragraph Ho.3, though Company might be encouraged to explore possibility of recruitment from Dominion sources e.g., South Africa or Australia. Presumably loss of British personnel will be offset to some extent by contraction of production at Bahrain due to policy of obtaining oil from less distant sources owing to tanker shortage. KetaxandumGOVERNMENT OF INDIA, Department, EXPRESS LETTER an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic L * * expense and undue use of the wires, but intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] i V 2 - ?ROM Political Agent, Bahrain To Political Resident, Camp, Bahrain. •/ O' r / \ Vflb c/1042-12/19. Dated gth November 1941./?^ Reference telegram No. 13233 dated 21st October 1941 from Secretary of State for India to you repeated to me. 2. I discussed the matter with Mr. Lipp, the General Manager, who was not optimistic about being able to recruit Americans or Dominion subjects. Americans were getting high salaries at home and were unwilling to come to the Gulf where they would be away from their wives. Company already has a number of Canadians. 3. Lipp said that it was not strictly correct to say that loss of British personnel was offset by contraction in production as nearly reduced production still required^full number of operators. In addition he had received notice from his principals that he must be ready to resume full production at any time. 4. Allowing for normal wastage there was sutficient staff A / ms S. 6. MPP—1-J06 S&amp;P—(M-1723}—4-2-36—200,000.«• 2 *» available 'to run for a*t least* four montths^ provided no key men were lost. Manager suggested some form of compulsory service for key men* vide my memorandum No, C/ 994 dated 20th October, I suggest that any measures for conservation of key staff introduced for Anglo Iranian Oil Company might also be made to apply here, u Political Agent, BdirainCONFIDENTIAL . No. 117-S ol' 1941. The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Secretary to the Uovernment of India, External Affairs Department, n&amp;w Delhi, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document (s). 2. The question is included in the list for discussion during the Resident’s forthcoming visit to Delhi, British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated 2drd October, 1941,v\.4^ w ' THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED Awali, Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf, OctolDer 26th, 1941. PA-752 His Britannic Majesty's Political Agent, The Agency, BASRAIN. Dear Sir, The above-named is a British employee of this Company who has been in our service since December 1936 as a Pipefitter. Mr. Robertson will be leaving Bahrein on or about November 10th, travelling to Australia by air. He will not be returning to Bahrein. We have informed him that he must call on you and obtain permission to leave the Island. Yours very truly, // M. H. LIPP, Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LIMITED. TE:B.BENTLEY’S SECOND PHRASE TROLEUM DEVELOPMENT (QATAR) LIMITED directors ! Lfificr CRUWIRtf.^: C. LESH-JONES, J. B. a. Kessler I BAHREIN PERSIAN GULF PDft/SAC/2659 15th Ootober&gt; To H.B,M. 1 s Political Agent, Bahrain. Dear Sir, REPATRIATION TO ENGLAND - MR.W.STTFTT Mr. W. Stiff, Diesel mechanical engineer employed by us in qatar is proceeding to England about the end of October on termination of services. There are special circumstances in his case which make us very anxious to facilitate in every way his return to England. He has been four years away from his family and extended his original agreement by an addi tional year under pressure from the Company at a time when his departure would have caused some dislocation to our drilling operations in Qatar. His wife’s health has been a source of anxiety to him and the Company feels in view of all the circumstances, that he is entitled to’ expectthe Company to make some effort to assist in his repatriation. It may be added that there is no reason to doubt that his services will be quickly utilized in England on important war work. We shall be very grateful indeed for any action you can suggest to ensure as far as possible that he will not be detained in India and conscripted for war work there. A' Yours faithfully, For &amp; on behalf of PETROLEUM DEVELOPMENT (QATAR) LIMITED MANAGER I/OCOPY PDQ/SAC/2650 CONFIDENTIAL llth October, W. Stiff, Esq., qatar. Dear Sir, RENEWAL OF AGREEIvlEL 'TT When Mr. Griffiths passed through last time the ques tion of your renewal was raised. We understand that the situation is that, if there is a reasonable chance of your being allowed to proceed to England, you are desirous of terminating your service with the Company. If, on the other hand, you are practically certain to be conscripted in India on arrival there, you would prefer to continue in the Company’s service in Qatar. To enable you to judge your chances and come to a decision we have consulted various authorities with the following result The Political Agent confirms that he has received an intimation that European British subjects between the ages of 18 and 50 including those in transit are liable to be conscripted in India. Many such cases have already occurred. Campbell, Gray Mackenzie &amp; Co., who arranges passages, supports this statement and brought it to our notice that it was found necessary to furnish his predecessor, Smith, with a letter from the Political Agent explaining his status and that he would be returning to Bahrain. British Overseas Airways Corporation also bage now issued a circular that all British subjects of military age travelling to India en route to England or the Dominions will in all probability be detained in India and sent for military training. They point out that several cases have occurred^ recently and employees proceeding to India should be supplied with an official letter stating that they are returning to Bahrain where their work is highly important. Will you please notify us as early as possible of your decision ? Your agreement expires on the 3rd January, 1942, and, as it takes from six weeks to two months to reach England, it willjbe necessary for us to make early passage arrangements. Yours pfaithfully, For &amp; on behalf of PETROLEUM DEVELOPMENT (QATAR) LIMITED X F. Packer. managerGOVERKnIENT OP INDIA, ——. Dbpartmbnt, [A’. B—Tkis is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save IdegraMc expense and undue use of the unres, ^intended to be trJLd,Z reievpt, mth the same tapedtiton as if it had been telegraphed. To so 'LpZh^ 1 Me * U “ aud Signed a* */£ had bee. From Political Agent, Bahrain, to Foreign, C/1034 Few Delhi Dated 4th November 1941 m , A copy of letter No, PDO/SAC/2650 doted the 11th October 1941 from the Manager, Petroleum Development (Qatar) Limited is forwarded herewith. In view of the circumstances it is recommended that Mr. Stiff might be allowed to proceed to the United Kingdom on compassionate grounds. If the Government of India agree, it is requested that the authorities at Karachi and Bombay may kindly be informed accordingly, 2. Mr, Stiff will be leaving Bahrain as soon as a passage can be arranged for him, which is likely to be in about three weeks* time, L. Political Agent, Bahrain4 th Nov ember 1941 This is to certify that V . Stiff is an employee of Petroleum Development (^atar) Limited, proceeding to the United Kingdom on termination of contract* u H.B.B/Us Political Agent, Bahrain. No.C/1071-12/19- Political Agency, Bahrain, 13th November 1941. To Mr. Syed Sher Shah, C/o the California Arabian Standard Oil Company, A1 Khobar. Dear Sir, Reference your letter dated the 3rd November. 1 shall be glad if you will call at this Agency when convenient to you. Yours faithfully, J&amp;(. Political Agent, Bahrain.PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LTD. BAH R AIN PERSIAN GULF. DO /SAC/2709 15th November, 1941 Dear ' rV / Reference your note dated the 14th of November regarding Barnfield. The Company have no objection to releasing Barnfield for service in the Royal Naval Voluntary Reserve. Yours sincerely, Major R.G.Alban, O.B.E., H.B.M.*s Political Agent Bahrain.Political Agency, Bahrain, the 14th November 1941. Colonel Hay and I went over to -atar on a visit yester day on the P.C.L. launch '’Ghazal'* On the way I was talking with Barnfield who is in charge of her and who is much dis appointed that his application for an R.N.V.R. commission was not accepted# He is a very decent young man and has experience oi river work at Abadan amongst other things. The Company are willing, I believe, to let him go and he feels that the work he is on at present (running a launch between Balirain and Qatar) is not helping the war at all. He has a sufficient knowledge of Arabic and Persian. T hope you will not mind my mentioning this case, which is none of my affair of course, but it struck me that you might be needing someone with these qualifications. I attach some details about Barnfield. Yours sincerely, IM/. A AIbe Hon ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to His Majesty's secretary of state for India, Pondon* The Secretary to the Government of India, External Affaire Department, lew Delhi* and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document^). Office of the iolitioal He eluent in the Persian Gulf, Camp# BAHRAXH* Dated..*?**? November i94i&lt; Reference to previous correspondeoce: Telegram Ho. 13233 dated the 2iet October, 1941, from Hie Majesty's secretary of State for India, london# Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. ■) S3 Express letter Ho.C/lC42*lV 19 dated 6th November, 1941, from the Political Agent, Bahrain* p ^ C lO Copy forwarded with complime; Bahrain with reference to hi 0/1042-12/19 dated 6th Hovem Recruitment of Americans or Dominion subjects* ht he e to The Political Agent, v/ Express Letter No. r, 1941.6- f $ $ The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Political Agent, Bahrain. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document(s). British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Camp Bahr ain. Dated. £.Q th, NpYemher ,4941. Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Government of India letter F0.D.5378-N/41, dated the 15th November 1941, with enclosure. Regulation to prevent the departure from Persia of the personnel of the A.I.O.C. and the Imperial Bank of Iran.2 . * SECRET 9330 ‘ Telegram XX No,957 dated 3th(reed 9th) November 1941 T.0.0, 4,25 4 m H-'l f t,o.r. 6.15 P :S: From.Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs London T°, 9f ee Jiis Majesty’s Minister Tehran, (Repeated Government of India No,14215 Baghdad No.1138) V E XPRESS _ ^ Your telegram No,1023 Secret, Proposal now under urgent considerst,ion is that a regulation shall be made by Order in Council under Emergency Powere(Defence)Acts 19^9-1940 under which departure of personnel in Persia of Anglo-Persian Oil Company and Imperial .Bank can be prohibited under penalties enforcible in Courts of United Kirgdom for disobedience. Text of draft regulation is given in my immediately iallowing telegram. Please telegraph immediately your comments. Text is being discussed here.simuTtaneously with represent- atives of Company and Bank, Co Regulation applies to Persia but can be extended to other : countries such as Iraq by Secretary of State, It is proposed to delegate to you power to specify undertakings in Persia whose employees will be affected but that you should inform me before spec.ii ixig un.d ei* tan irjgs in ado.it i on tc Anglo 'Persian and Imperial oanK « ^ also proposed tc delegate to you power to apply regul- ■ ation to employees of specified undertakings-. This means that ■ou will hawe to issue a formal order under regulation specifying categories of employees of British nationality ,to whom Order is applied or else mention them be name. If your Order specifies categories} c u wn i ch is perhaps preferable alternative', Anglo-Per si an Oil Company and Bank should not only furnish you with descriptions of categories ko/o also with list of names in each category, and you should make them responsible for seeing that each individual concerned is personally notified. You will have to take steps to ensure that your orders specifying undertakings and employees are brought to9330 knowledge of Company and persons affected in a manner which r‘ ^ easily susceptible of proof in Court. 3. mien as result cf your orders Regulation becomes appli Cab to certain employees they are forbidden to leave their without .your consent, but it is, stated that you shall not withh }o ar conseno ^Jinless you are satisfied that company is willing ^ offer them terms of employment which you consider reasinable y are in this way made responses le for seeing that employees «-.o ar retained as result of your orders receive reasonable terns am! power to let them leave Persia is means by which you can bring pressure on Companies to grant reasonable terms of employment Employees detained by your orders should know that they can appeal to you as regards conditions of employment. Naturally you will » keo? m Fbrsia ay y employee whom Company are not. anxious to Mail lutof . totiae \m liate o Penalty for disobedience to your orders under Regulation j not specified in this particular Regulation bufwill have to m\ following note is brought to attention of those concerned 'any p 6I who on returning to the United Ki.^dom is convicted of having left his employment in contravention of this Regulation will under ^ Regulaoion 32a) of Defence (General) Regulations 1939 be liabie, o 1 ™ summary conviction to imprisonment for a term not exceedirg three ^ ° r t0 &amp; fln6 n0t ^ihg one hundred pounds or to both a*% imprisonment and such fine, or on conviction on indictment to ^ ment for a term not exceeding two years nr +n c- , Hlk n • , ^ 3 e d.is or oo a fine not exceeding 11 ^ five hundred pounds or to both such , ' Wk^ h imprisonment and such fine'. ,,r, U N ' (3) F - s - J -s. a.d.s. P.S.V. &amp;. 0 ,S^CRST £!-&gt;; 0 Telegran 22 No.998 dated(and reed) 8th November 1941. T.0.0. 04.25 T.O.R. 6.15 ^ ron * ♦Secretary 01 State for Foreign. Affairs London* To....Ills Majesty*s 1 Inister Tehran (repeated Government of India No. 14216 Bajidad No. 1139) i y immediately preceeding tele^am. Following is text of draft Regulation. Any person to whom this Regulation applies who is in employment of persons carrying on any essential undertaking shall whether or not he is bound by contract to do so* continued in employment of those persons in such capacity as they may from time to time specify* unless Secretary of State or some person acting with authority of Secretary of State consents to his leaving that employment provided consent under this Regulation to a person leaving his employment shall not be refused* unless Secretary of State or, as the cafje may be, the person acting with his authority is satisfied that employees are willing to continue employment on reasonable terms. t^P(oyiYS 2. The persons to whom this Regulation applies are british subjects or British protected persons to whom the Regulation is applied by a direction of Secretary of State or some person acting with authority of Secretary of State, being’ person employed in Persia orin any such other foreign country or territory, in which for time being His Majesty has no jurisdiction, as may be specified in an order of Secretary of State 3. In this Regulation the expression essential undertaking means any undertaking specified in any order of Secretary ox bt&amp;te as an undertaking the carrying of which appears to Secretary oi State to be essential for prosecution of war. ’■h '.BRANCH F.3. J.3. A.B.3. P.3.Y.GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, Department, LETTER Confidential [l\b % This is an OV TOT'S AL ME SR AG IS, sent by •post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, bat intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To sate time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched.] From Political Agent, Bahrain. Te Political Resident, v Camp Bahrain. C/1101 • 12/19 20th November 1941 Reference Your Printed Letter No. C/582 dated the 20th November 1941. 2. I have discussed the matter with Mr. Lipp, General Manager of the Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, who is the person primarily concerned. 3. He considers that a regulation on the lines mentioned would be of value to the Company inasmuch as employees feel that they are not taking their share in the war* This causes a certain instability of mind which the proposed regulation could go far towards remedying. He observes, however, that the Company allows employees who wish to do so to spend their leaves in South Africa. Some of these men on the expiry of their leave have suddenly decided nbt to return to Bahrain and have either obtained employment in South Africa or proceeded s - 6 * thence /- MFP—1206 SAP—(M-l 723)—4-2 36—200,000,thence to the United Kingdom, It appears that those who contravene the regulation in this way can only he punished on arrival in the United Kingdom. Those who remain in South Africa will escape until such time as they proceed 1939 may have expired, vide Section 11 (3). This prospect will, we think, act as a sufficient deterrent in such caeee. 4# The Company also employs a certain number of Cana dian subjects and one or two cases have occurred of these men leaving the Company’s service on frivolous pretexts in order to return to Canada. It appears that the proposed regulation will not remedy matters as far as Canadian sub jects are concerned. 5. As regards Indian employees of the Company, it is will be any need to enforce the proposed regulation against them. Should however the necessity arise they can pre 6. In the case of British employees who force the Convoany to discharge them by deliberately slackening in their work it would be best if these were conscripted &lt;*n passing through India as heretofore since service in India is unpopular whereas they would not mind being conscripted in the United Kingdom. 7. It is recommended therefore that the regulation may be applied to Bahrain and also to Qatar where Petroleum Development (Qatar) Limited have an oil camp employing a few Europeans and Indians. / j , to the United Kingdom and they will then be subject to punishment even though the Emergency Powers (Defence) Act not anticipated that, under present circumstances, there sumably be proceeded against under the Defence Regulations of India. L Political Agent, BahrainUl A I Sir, Office of Senior Naval Officer, Persian Gulf, Basrah. 16th November, 1941. t0 refer to n 3 r letter No.?? of ?6th QiE+* u inform you that the Commander—in-Chief. East Indies Station has now been authorised to enter 'Hostilities On^ raSngs? forwarbed^orVh^ f 6 ^ wishes his name to be vl' h £ try and -- f 30 f or which branch of the Navy h ^u l’v v^ 1 1 ^Egest he should discuss this matter Ta»a Af^tl Va ” ( f-icer-m-Oharge, Bahrain with a view to getting some idea of the requirements of the various branches. ^ I have the honour to be. Sir, Political Agent, The Agency, BAHRAIN. Your okJ3dient Servant, G0MQ3X)HE i 1No. C/1113-12/19 The Political Agent, Bahrain, Presents his compliments to :— The Manager, Petroleum Concessions Limited, Bahrain* and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document (/§/) for the imormation o~ Mr* Barnfield, with the suggestion that he might discuss the matter over with the Naval Officer- in Charge, Naval Base, Bahrain. The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf Dated _23r IJ.qv ember. 1941. Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure Name and Date. Letter No.22 dated the 16tt November 1941 from the Senior Naval Officer, Per sian Gulf, Basra. Subject Application of Mr. Barnfield for an R.N.V.R. commission.D.CU No. C/684 of 1941 Office of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf # Camp Bahrain. ^ 23rd November 1941. My dear Weightman &gt; Please refer to your demi-official letter No. D.6378-N/41 dated the 15th November 1941* 2. While I have been in Bahrain Lipp, the General Manager of the Bahrain Petroleum Company * has several times mentioned to me the necessity of applying some kind of conscription to his British employees. Alban has now consulted him regarding the proposals contained in the enclosures to your letter* under reference and he agrees that the regulation described will meet the needs of the case if applied to Bahrain. He considers that such a regulation would be of value to the Company as their employees feel that they are not taking their due share in the war. This causes a certain restlessness which the regulation would go far towards remedying. 3. There are about twenty Canadians employed by the Company who will not be covered by the proposed regulation Though one or two cases have occurred of Canadians leaving the Company’s service on frivolous pretexts I do not con sider it necessary to endeavour to obtain the consent of the Canadian Government to the regulation being extended to cover their subjects. 4. The Company allow employees who wish to do so to spend their leaves in South Africa. Some of these men on the expiry of their leave have suddenly decided not to /- eightman, esquire, I.C.S., Additional Secretary to the Government of India in the External Affairs Departmentj New Delhi.(-2F * Ol J - 2 - to return to Bahrain and have either obtained employment in 3outh Africa or proceeded thence to the United Kingdom, It appears that those who contravene the regulation in this way can only be punished on arrival in the United Kingdom, Those who remain in South Africa will escape until such time as they proceed to the United Kingdom and they will then be subject to punishment even though the Bmergeney Powers (defence) Act 1939 may have expired, vide Section 11 (3)* r is prospect will, it is considered, act as a sufficient deterrent in such cases. I 1 * ■ - ' . . W p, 5. It is not considered that there will be any need to enforce the proposed regulation against British Indian sub jects. They could in any case presumably be proceeded gainst under the Indian Defence Regulations on their arrival in that country. 6. It will still be necessary to conscript in India British employees who force the Company to discharge them i i by deliberate slackness or misbehaviour. 7. In the light of the above remarks I recommend that the regulation be applied at the earliest possible date to Bahrain to cover the employees of the Bahrain Petroleum Com pany and also to ''star to cover those of Petroleum Concessions Limited and that the powers described in paragraph 2 of telegram No. 997 dated the 8th November 1941 from the Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs be delegated to the Political Resident. It is unlikely that it will be necessary to specify any undertakings other than the Bahrain Petroleum Company and Petroleum Concessions Limited. 8. Please inform me by telegram whether the Government of India approve my proposals and are making recommendations to His Majesty’s Government accordingly in order that I may ask Alban to prepare the necessary categories and T-r-c&gt;'rw obtain lists of names for the undertakings concerned. 9 /-9. The Manager of Petroleum Conceasions Limited haa not yet been consulted, but I am asking Alban to have a talk with him at an early date and I do not think that he will raise any objection* Yours sincerely,//- VI Vp- No.P.O.??. \ ^ i If |f . Office of Senior Nava?. Officer, Persian Gulf, Basra. 24th November, 1941. £tw i, # 3, ' Thank you fo^your letter of 14th Novenber. I am sorry that the Comi ander—in-Ohief was unab?.e to offer a commission to Bamfield, but I recent^ wrote and told you that if he wished to do so he could enter as a rating with a view to obtaining a commission through service. This is a new scheme started on this station and is I presume to be the normal method of obtaining a commission in the future. It probably sounds less attractive but you will appreciate that this is the only way of obtaining a commission at home in these days. Major R«G*Alban, The Political Agent, The Agency, BAHRAIN.COPY inte ?I^^, witl1 Lieut - Co^rn- Baines at 11.30 A.M. on 26/11/41: Lieut. C/Omm. Baines decidsd that he would wait to see the result of the correspondence between the P.A. and the S.JNl.o. Should nothing come of this correspondence, he would write to the S.N.O reporting on the interview and suggesting that perhaps I may be given a commission R.N.R. Lieut, uomm. baines was going to speak to the P.A. by telephone on the matter. (Sgd.) V/. Barnfield 26/11/41. Cpd/SPA.CONFIDENTIAL. tl' D.O. No. C/587 of 1941. M Tlie Hon ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to Major R.G.Alban, O.B.E., Political Agent, Bahrain, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document^. British Consulate-General, BITSHIRE. Camp, Kuwait• Dated .November 1941 - Reference to previous correspondence: #' &gt;' ; V Bahrain Express Letter Ro .C/llOl-12/19, dated the 20th November 1941 i M 'f ^’/// J 1 O' Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Letter Ro*C/584 of 23rd November 1941 to the Govern* ment of India, External Affairs Department, New Delhi. Application of some kind of conscription to British employees of the Bahrain Petroleum Company and Petroleum Concessions Limited. V % y( fflce ot 'bhc i’oliticnl etii tint In the Persian Guif, D.O. KC. C/584 Of 1941 ‘ ^^“‘Swi^sr 1941. Ify deer Welghtman, rieaee r&lt;?fer %c your de^i-offieial letter Ho. D.637B-N/41 dated th.e 15th Kcverrher 1941. 8. hile I have seen in Bahrein Lipp, the General Manager of the Bahrein PetroleiMi Cmmny f hee several tlffiea mentioned to me the necessity of applying some kind of conscription to hla British oieploye^e. Alban hae now consulted him regarding the proposals contained in the enclomirea to your letter under* reference and he agrees that the regulation described will aest the needs of the case if applied to Ttahrain. He considers that »uch 8 regulation rould be of veins Co the Company as their employees ftil that they are not taking their due share in the war* This e&amp;uses a obtain restlessness which the r^^ulatlon would go fer towards remedying* 3. There are about twenty Canadians employed by the Company who will not be covered by the proposed regulation Though one or two cases have occurred of Canadians leaving the Co&amp;pany 9 a service on frivolous pretexts I do not con sider it necessary to endeavour to obtain the consent of the Canadian Ctoveroment to the regulation being extended to cover their subjects. 4. The Company allow employees who wish to do so to spend their leaves in outh Africa. Horn of these ssen on the expiry of their leave have suddeiOy decided not to /• ^tightmsn. Esquire« C.X.&amp;. f l.C. &gt; #f Additional Secretary to the Government of India in the TExternal Affairs department, Hew Wslhi*to roturn to Bahrain and hav« aUhor obtained omployaont in -outh Africa or proceadotl thonco to th« n n it«d Kingdom. It rs that thoao who contravene the regulation in this way can only be punished on arrival in the United } ingdom. ***** ****** in South Africa will eeeepe until such tl&amp;e a a thoy proceed to the United Kingdom and they will then be subject to punishment even t!iou«^h the iser ency Powers { ^fence &lt; Act 1939 aey have expired* vide ’action 11 (3) • This prospect will, it is considered, act as a sufficient deterx-ent in such cases* '• Vv u ' h * \ d \&gt; It is not co?ieider*d that there will be any neod to enforce t)ie proposed regulation against British Indian sub jects. They could in any case presumably be proceeded against under the Indian nefetjee r egulations on thsir arrival In that country. 6. It will still be necessary to conscript in India British employees who force the Company to discharge them by deliberate slackness or misbehaviour. | 7* In ths light of the shove remark® X recocs^end that the regulation be applied at the earliest possible date to Bahrain to cover the employees of the Bahrain Petroleum Com pany ©j*3 also to Tatar to cover those of etroleum Concessions Limitsd and that ths powsrs described in paragraph 2 of telegram Ho. 997 dated the BtV Povember 1941 from the Secretary of state for Foreign Affairs be delegated to the Political Resident. It is unlikely that it will be necessary to specify any undertakings other than the ahroili Petroleum Company and Petroleum Concessions Limited. Bm Please inform me by telegram whether the Government of India approve my proposals and are making recommendations to His Majesty's Government accordingly in order that I amy ask Alban to prepare the necessary categories and obtain lists of names 4or the undertakings concerned.- 3 • 9. The Manager of Petroleum Concessions Limited has not yet been consulted, but 1 am asking Alban to have a talk with him at an early date and I do not think that he will raise any objection* Yours sincerely, ad* W.H.Hay*Confidential D#0«No. 0/1156-12/19 Dated the 11th December 1941 There is under consideration a scheme for the application of some kind of conscription to British employees of the Bahrain Petroleum Company in order to give the manage ment some hold over their employees and prevent them from leaving the service on any pretext. It is also intended to meet a certain feeling on the part of the employees that they are not taking their due share in the war effort, I think the idea originally started with the Anglo-Iranian Cil Company at Abadan who either have or are going to have a similar measure applied to them. Although you have no great number of employees in ^atar it might be as well to take advantage of the present opportunity to get the measure applied to Datar at the same time as it can do no harm and would on the other hand be of considerable advantage should the war go on for a long time and the operations of the Company be increased, 2, I should be very grateful if you would consider the matter and let me know whether you have any objection to the application of the measure as far as you are concerned Yours sincerely* Packer * ruSQ,* iSanager f Petroleum Concessions Limited* Bahrain,QOf ERNM^nIT of I ndi a • External Affairs Department PRESS LETTER- :eW) . PJ r From To Foreign, New Delhi, Political Agent, Bahrain. .9172-^/41. Dated the November 1941. facilities to Mr. Stiff to proceed to — - the United Kingdom. *_* Reference your express letter Ho .C/1034, dated the 4th November 1941. 2. Government of India agree to allow Mr. Stiff to proceed to the United Kihgdom. The authorities concerned have been informed. THE ISSUE OF THE ABOVE HAS BEEN AUTHORISED, Under Secretary to the Government of India. Copy, with a copy of the express letter under reply and its enclosure, is forwarded for information to the Hon* ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Pi^li ■no. c/iid3 Political Agency, B&amp;nrcin, tne P?nd December 1941 To Tne Manager, Petroleum Development (Qatar) Limited, B A H K A I n Dear Sir, &lt;Ti ^ c— PleaSc refer to your letter Lo. PDC/ SAC/26o9 dated the 15th October 1941* Government of India have agreed to allow Mr# Stiff to proceed to the United Kingdom and have informed tne authorities concerned# Yours faitnfuliy, u Political Agent, Bahrain.PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LTD. BAHRAIN PERSIAN GULF. doA* 30 / 2761 Dear CONFIDENTIAL 22nd December, 1941 * With reference to your D.O. No . C/2256-12/19 dated the 11th December 1941. I am afraid this is a question which must be referred to our London principals direct or through our General Manager in the Near East (Haifa). 1 am sure they will not approve of local Managers giving views which might influence the local ► representatives of H.B.M. f s Government in advocating or bring ing into force any local form of conscription. As you know our parent Company is the Iraq Petroleum Company operating in Iraq, Palestine, Transjordan and Syria including also various subsidiaries under different names. All these locations and subsidiaries come under the Iraq Petroleum Company, Ltd., London, for all the ’’essentials” of administration. All employees are liable to inter-Company transfers at short notice and I feel that, should they be con sulted, our principals would think it most desirable that any form of conscription introduced by the British Government should apply equally to all our areas and locations. Without knowledge of the particulars of the conscription scheme to which you refer it is difficult for me to offer any unofficial comments on the advantages and disadvantages of conscription as applied to Qatar. At present, the situation there seems quite satisfactory as regards the British and American staff. In this connection, however, I should like to bring it to your notice that if any conscription is brought into force it could be applied also with advantage to Indian staff, clerical and artizan particularly - at least to the extent of requiring them to fulfil their contract periods. At present under the Protector of Emigrants’ form of agreement they can always give one month’s notice of termination and satisfactory replacements in these days are very difficult indeed to arrange. An air raid or an agitation for war bonuses might easily lead to a general exodus. Yours sincerely, Major R.G.Alban, O.B.B., H.B.M.’s Political Agent, Bahrain.1 \ CONFIDENTIAL. No. 161-a of 1941. The Hon ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf compliments to Major K,G. Alban, Political A^ent, Bahrain, and^has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document (s). British Consulate-General, BUS HI RE. o Name and Date. External .Affairs Department let ter fi o.D. 5840-11/41, dated the &lt;Jnd December 1941 and enclosures. Dated.. tn December 1941. Reference to previous correspondence : P Residency Printed better ho.G/587 , dated r 1 the 26th November, 1941. Description of Enclosure Subject. Proposed regulation to prevent departure of persons carrying on essential unaer- talcmgs. 111(2 B y Air Mail. Gonfidential. 4 Jr External Affairs Department, flew Delhi. fne 2nd December, 1941. D.Q.NO.D.5840-N/41- bUBJiiiGT ; Regulation to prevent departure from Persia of the personnel of the Anglo- Iranian Oil Company and the Imperial Bank. i'/iy dear Hay, In continuation of my demi-official letter flo.5378-fl/41, dated the 14th flovenber 1941, 1 am desired to forward a copy of the marginally cited 1. Telegram from the Secretary of State for j foreign Affairs, flo.1052, dated the 19th { flovember 1941. 2. Telegram from His Majesty's Minister, | Tehran, flo.1203, dated the 24th flovember * 1941. { 3. Telegram from His Majesty's Secretary of } State for 1‘oreign Affairs, flo.1094, j dated the 27 th .November 1941. I 4. Telegram from His Majesty's Secretary of { State for foreign Affairs, IIo.l09b, { dated the 27th November 1941. j telegrams. Yours sincerely, sd.H. Weight man • The Hon'ble Lieutenant-Col on el Y,'.R. Hay, C . 1. L. Political Resident m the Persian uulf.secret . ■ Telegrani AX. No .1052 dated 19th ^recd. 21st) November 1941. IT.0.0. 2-15 p.m.) (T.O.R. 7.0 a*m.; From ... Secretary of state for Foreign Affairs, London. To ... His Majesty’s Minister, Tehran. (Repeated to Government of India No.14871 Baghdad No.1174;. company and bank it has been decided to abandon proposal that formal order to be made by you under regulation should either specify categories of employees or mention them by name. Order will instead apply to every British subject and British protected person or bank in Persia/. 2. Company and bank have jointly prepared a draft letter which if you agree you should address to their general Managers in Persia. 1 will telegraph you text of this craft. This letter will be sent by you after urder in Council has been issued and General Managers will be responsible for making copies and bringing a copy personally to notice of each British subject or British protected person in their employment who will be required to sign an acknowledgement for transmission to you in following terms: 'X hereby acknowledge having received a copy of His Majesty’s Ministers letter dated .•.•••••. together with a copy of regulation No 3. Meanwhile urder in Council is being held up pending the receipt of your observations. Please expedite your reply. N. branch f.s. J.S. P.S.V.SjSCF&amp;T. Tele&amp;rctfn -KX Lo*1203 dated 24th ^recd* 25th) Noveniber 1941 T.O.O. 20.10 hrs. 1VO.R. 7.15 hrs. I’rora ... Bullard Tehran. (Repeated to foreign, liew Delhi and Baghdad Po.985) Your telegram Bo.1052. Beheme described in your 7 / telegram 997 and 998 is admirable except that it was found difficult to devise comprehensive categories. Bow that this objection is removed by proposal in para. 1 of your above mentioned telegram I think order in Council should To • • • foreign office, London / be issued at once B. BR. i?’S. JS. ADS. PSV. &amp; 0 IMS(11)nOKFID^TlAL. Telegram H. ^o. 1094 dated. &lt;J7th ^reod. 28th; November 1941. T.O.O. 00.5b hrs. T.O.H. 07.00 hrs. ij‘rom To • •• Secretary ot 8tate for Jj'oreigri Affairs, London ... H.M's Minister, Tehran. (Repeated to Government of Incia No. 15257 and Baghdad No.1195.; ^our telegram No.1203. An Order in Council has been made today November 27th m terms of my telegram No.998. Secretary of State has also today made an order under said Orders in Council. Latter is numbered 58 A C of Defence lGeneral) Regulations. You should nov* at once make a formal Order in terms set out m ray immediately following telegram and cause copies of your Order to be sent to Anglo-Persian Oil Company and Imperial Bank with a request that your Order should be posted prominently in their offices. You should at the same time send them letters in terms set out in my telegram No.10^ and request them to circulate copies of letter to employees affected and to obtain their receipts in accordance with my telegram No.1052. c \ 'I* u- N. BR. PS. JS. ADS. USF. PSV. &amp; 0 Dili. DMO. 1M3(13;Confidential. T.O.O. 01.00 - T.O.R. 16.5b i&gt;‘rom To Minister, Tehran (Repeated liovernraent of India 15258 - Baghdad No.1196J My named lately preceding telegram. Text of order is as follows; Whereas His Majesty’s Secretary of Hate for foreign Affairs by an urder made on November 27th 1941 No.58-AC of Defence (General) Regulations made by Order in Council dated November 27th 1941 has ordered ; tl) that Anglo-Persian oil Company and imperial Bank of Persia are undertakings carrying of which is essential for prosecution of war. ^2) that II.Li’s Minister, Tehran or in his absence any person who with his authority may be acting generally on R.M’s Minister’s behalf is authorised to direct to what persons whom said Regulation applies leaving their employment and to satisfy himself that when he refuses consent to a person leaving his employment, emplo re willing to continue employment on reasonable terms. Now 1 Sir Reader Bullard, H. M. Minister, Tehran do hereby direct that all British subjects and all British protected persons who are in employment in Persia of Anglo- Persian Oil Company or of imperial Bank of Persia are persons to whom said Regulation N0.58-AC of Defence ^General) Regulations apply. aforesaid Regulation shall apply and to consent persons to 4 BR. M.S. J.B. ADS. US. PSV. &amp; 0. DMO. DM! * n.::.TELEGRAMS: PETCONCESS, BAHREIN CODES: BENTLEY’S SECOND PHRASE PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LIMITED RS: ^-Q.C.M.G. ~^€hairmm) D.S.O., D.S.C. (French) 'C.B.E. enkian (formerly Armenian) gssler (Dutch) fef.) P/GM.1/2775 BAHREIN PERSIAN GULF ^ONFIDSNTIAL 7til January, 1942. To H.B.M. f s Political Asent, Bahrain. Dear Sir / re ^ erer ^ ce correspondence commendne: with vour letter No. D.O.C/1156-12/19 dated the 11th of afc ember 1941. t V ~ e ?nJo J eGeiveci the following reply dated the 5th of January 1942 from our Managing Director in England : - 'From Skliros To Packer YOUR TELEGRAM 482 PROPOSED SCHEME TO QkTAE BUT WE DO NOT PRESS FOR IT' Yours faithfully, For &amp; on behalf of PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LIMITED ACM MANAGERTranslation of telegram No.48 2 addressed to Patch, Kingshead, Horsfeamsussex v in Bentleys Second Phrase Code. Political enquiring Company’s attitude views British Government scheme designed assist management retain British employees considered indispensable continuance oil operations Fullstop Understand similar scheme impending or already introduced Abadan and under consideration Bahrain Petroleum Company Fullstop Scheme provides for consideration eaeh case on merits by British Government local representative and penalties for unauthorised deserting of post provided Government satisfied employees existing conditions of service or terms for renewals of agreements are reasonable equitable Fullstop please telegraph reply PackerTelegram &lt; From To No. 17 Political Agent, Bahrain Political Pesident, Pushire Dated the 8th January 1942. v our demi-official letter No. C/584 dated 23rd November to Weightman paragraph 9. 2 . Petroleum Concessions Limited have no objaction. PoliticalIV ? ■ The i„ n ^ |®5I? ta ry^° the Government of India the external Affairs Department, The Political Agent, Bahrain* Memorandum No.F.27(54)-S/41. Dated New Delhi,the December 1941* Subject;- Antecedents of Dr. P.V. Kurian^ M.B.B.S. Medical Officer, California Arabian ’ btandard Oil Company, Bahrain. * i • x Dr * • p *Y* ^ian, M.B.B.S. Medical Officer, California Arabian standard Oil Company, Bahrain, has applied for an Emergency Commission in the Indian Medical Service. It is requested that the Grovernment of India may kindly be informed whether he has come to adverse notice in any wav durine his stay in Bahrain. J ^ Under Secretary to the Government of India. %idential No. C/33 Political Agency, Bahrain, the 10th January, 1942 To The Resident Manager, California Arabian Standard Oil Company, D H A H R A N Dear Sir, I shall be grateful if you can give me any information you have regarding the character, reliability, etc., of Dr. P.V. Kurian, an employee of your Company, and in particular whether he has come to adverse notice in any way. Yours faithfully Political Agent, BahrainCONFIDENTIAL. No. 173-d of 1941. ^ Hi ■ V . 1 V ' The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Political Agent, Kuwait, The Political Agent, Bahrain, and^has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned document British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated..^.^.^.©?.©. 1 ?)?©?*. 1941. Reference to previous correspondence : Residency Printed Letter .No.C/587 of dated the 26th .November 1941. 1941, Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Telegram Ho.7171, dated the 16th December 1941, from the Government of India, Hew Delhi. Proposed regulation to prevent departure of persons carrying on essential undertakings.tioveminent of India, New Delhi. India Office, London. Political Resident, Bushire. Telegram. From To Repeated No. 7171. Dated 16th received l$th December 1941„ Foreign Office telegram 1095 of 27th p^T N ov erab e r. 2. 1 i»i Political Resident recommends that regulation, text of which is given in Foreign Office telegram 998 ol 8th November, should be applieo to Bahrain and Qatar to cover British employees of Bahrain Petroleum Company and Petroleum Concessions Limited and that powers described in Foreign office telegram 997^^ of 8th November should be delegated to him. We support his recommendation regarding application of regulation to Bahrain and Qatar and request that he be authorised * to take action on the lines of your telegrams 1094 and 1095 of 27th November* 3. There are 20 Canadian British subjects in Bahrain. Political Resident, we think rightly, does not suggest obtaining Canadian Government’s consent to application of regulation to these and we recommend local solution should be sought by executive instructions.v California Arabian standard oil company Dhahran, Saudi Arabia January 13 , 1942 DR. P. y. KURTAN Major R. G. Alban, 0.0.E. His Brittanic Majesty's Political Ayent Bahrein Island Dear Major Alban: ^ your letter to me dated 10th January 194^. Dr. Kurian, except for the period October I 939 to July 1940 during wnich he returned to India, has been with us since December 1936. His work and record with us have been verv satis factory. O T&gt; I assume your enquiry is prompted by reason of his application for assignment in the Indian Army Medical Service. Dr* Kurian is a good mar and I do not wish to hinder either his advancement or service to his country. Currently however he and Dr. George are our only Indian doctors and I accordingly would be reluctant to lose them and particularly Dr. Kurian pending the arrival of a replacement from India. Enquiries with regard to available replacement material, made to our recruiting agent in Bombay some months ago, so far have produced no result. Yours truly, F. 1. OHLIGERGOVERNMENT of INDIA, ~~ Department. [iV^. D, This is an ORIGINAL MERRAOv * t, expense and undue use of the wires tele( J™vh™ receipt, with the same expedition as it \ l f ^ nded f he tre ^&lt; on save time and formalities ^ i ^ bem graphed. To so despatched,] oraed and signed as if it had been Confidential From Political /'gent, Bahrain. To No* C/74 'oreign, New Delhi. Dated 15th January m 1942 Antecedents of Dr. P.V. Kurian, M.B.B.S. Reference your memorandum No. F. 27 (54) - E/41 dated the 13th December 1941. 2. Dr. Kurian has an excellent record of service with the California Arabian Standard Oil Company, with whom he has been since 1936, except for a short spell of leave. Nothing adverse is known about him. The Company do not wish to lose him before they can recruit a replacement from India. Sd/~ R. G. Alban Political Agent, Bahrain. Attested. / W- . Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain ' ii M PP—400S&amp;P—(M-480)—26-7-34—2,00,000.GQNF ID&amp;MTIAL ^&gt;0.110.50-5. The Residency, Bush ire, 15th January 1942. 1^^ '5 Please refer to correspondence ending with your telegram No.17 dated 8th January 1942. 2 . I forward herewith a copy of Curtis* demi- official letter No 6086-11/41 dated 20th I)ecember 1941.. Will you please discuss the point raised in paragraph 2 tentatively with Lipp and let me know the result as soon as possible. 3. With regard to paragraph 3, if some form of industrial conscription is applied to ordinary British subjects and to American subjects it will hardly seem Reasonable to exclude Canadians. They would, however, presumably be covered at any rate in name by the term w British subjects** in the proposed regulation though it contains no sanction to be applied against them unless they happen to set foot in the United Kingdom. This as is suggested in Curtis* letter may perhaps suffice for the time being. Do you agree?rO»» Political Agent,Bahrain, Political Resident,Bushire. 49 18th January 1942. v 0 ur demi-official letter No.30-3, January 13th. Enclosure not received. Please send by next mail. Telegram From To No. Dated Politicalr ^ V 0 ’ The Bahrein Petroleum Company Limited OOl'TS’r^NTTAT, PA-922 n v / Awali, ^ Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, His Britannic Maiestv*^ Political Agent, “ 3AHRAIH. January 24th, 1942. Dr. K. S. JOLLY Hear Sir, ¥r T o]r is tj0 confirm our conversation with ation submitter 5 ‘hi- thp nS -h° n ^ le su ^J e ct of the resign- 1 ,. 4^ P r ^sent time we can ill afford to vit^ to ou^o^pv rr ‘ and we c ^sider him Z 1 * ^u U ?P era iions and therefore essential to war needs, ns he is the Indian Doctor in charge of Indian and Local Staff; he also carries out dispensary wor..„, first aid and routine physical examinations. ■ _ _ _ . he should like to retain the services of .r. Jolly in our organization, hut if it should he impossible to withhold him from military duty altogether ve request that sufficient time he allowed us to obtain a replacement from India. Yours very truly, M. H. LLP^, Chief Local Representative, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LL YTED, AA:BTELEGRAMS: PETCONCESS, BAHREIN CODES: BENTLEY'S SECOND PH PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LIMITED With reference to corr __„ence ending with our No.F/CM.1/2775 dated the 7th January, 1942. If it is in order, we shall be pleased if we can be informed of the situation subsequent to our above-mentioned memo, and if the measures under consideration are to be applied to our companies or not. The Company chiefly affected is Petroleum Development (Qatar) Limited. enkian (formerly Armenian) .ssler (Dutch) BAHREIN PERSIAN GULF fes.) P/CM. 1/2802 CONFIDENTIAL 24th January, 1942. H. B. M. f s Political Agent Bahrain. nA * 5 Dear Sir Tours faithfully, For &amp; on behalf of PETROLEUM CONCESSIONS LIMITED EPA. MANAGER. kyl. &gt;u|&lt;lUvConfidential No. C/122 Political Agency, Bahrain, the 26th January 1942 To The Manager, Petroleum Concessions Limited B A H R A I N Dear Sir Please refer to your letter No. P/CM. 1/2802, dated the 24th January 1942. 2. The matter is still under the consideration of His Majesty's Government, but you will be informed immediately if, as seems probable, the measures con templated are applied to your employees. Yours faithfully, Political Agent, Bahrain1 -aJ* No. C/124 Political Agency, Bahrain, the 28th January 1942. To The Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, BAHRA I N Dear Sir, Please refer to your letter No. PA-922 of the 24th June 1942. 2. I regret that it is not possible, as the law stands at present, to detain Dr. Jolly for service here. 3. You have also asked, in the alternative, that his departure should be delayed until you can obtain a suitable relief. Whilst I appreciate the reasons which have led you to prefer this request, no representa- ) . ‘ £ / f \ tion on the subject to the Director-General, Indian Medical Service, India, would be likely to achieve the object desired, and I am therefore faking no fur ther action. ■’ / ■ / Yours faithfully, ; . . ‘ S .'V- 1 K \ Political Agent, Bahrain. i V/ .jr ,# 3 ' // T\ \ Ho» 95-S of 1942, British Residency &amp; Consulate-General, Bushire, 2.1st January 1942* To The Political Ag&amp;nt, Barirain* IOSvDRAKDIM . / Reference your telegram Ho.49 dated the 18 th January 1942. # 2* The enclosure to Resiaency demi-official letter Np.30-S dated the loth January 1942 is forwarded herewith. The oversight is regretted. Sd. W.R.Hay. Political Resiuent in the Persian Gulf. ATTESTED . i ^ For Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.external AFFAIRS DEPARTMENTt Vtw Delhi| Tile Decetaber '41* S T (^-O,t),6086^/41, fleaae refer to your demi-official letter No^c/584, dated the 2: rd of November 1941, to Wel^tman. f . v 2. A« you will have seen fro® Foreign tfaegram No.7171, dete^i 16U* December, we have aaked that British subjects in Brhr-in ©nd Qatar should be brought under the Eegulatloa as a. lies to British subjects In Persia* Now that the T3hlted States of America are in the war, it woulu be well to enquire from the Bahrain Petroleum Company whether they ^ro^oce to take any action in respect of their American employees. It eeexae improbable that anything of this nature will work smoothly in Bahrain if there is discrimination between the different classes o^ , the Company’s servants, and if the Americena are not subject to at leest some sort of control. How such control can be legally exercised over American citizans in foreign territory sucli as Bahrain may be a problem of some complexity both for theiu hnd for os, but at least the local llanagez** might put the case to XNABrJUHUE in Baghdad. ■ g i -• In view of paragraph 2 of your demi-official letter under reference, it has net been the ugh 1 advisable to approach Canadian Government whom «e know to be sensitive on the eonsc vi * t icn/. • • 1. T. O.to conscription issue* ^ubject^abt’ His Majesty * 3 Govennaent** views on this point it seems possible that the best course will be to assume loesJUy that the Canadians will legally accept the position, If they do notf and it seems necessary to take some positive action to bring them into line) you will no doubt address us again j dome, thing would seem to depend on the attitude of the Company In respect of its American employees* nnU-944 Yours sincerely, 3d/- G.C.3.Curtis. To The Hon # ble Lieutenant Colonel r . W.H.Hhy, Foliucfl Resident in the Persian Gulf* UaL/l l, B. ^ !.E.rs I Dear Sir&gt; ID ^ C0DD62 ecclosing to lir. D. ittacii: 1v\ &amp; -oO r 'mil ' tin itly, ilit t/in The Bahrein petroleum Company Limited Awali, Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, 31st January, 1942. CONFIDENTIAL CON-944 E. B. Wakefield, Esq., I.C.S., H.B.M*s Political Agent, The Agency, Bahrein. Dear Sir, In furtherance of bur conversation this morning in connection with our personnel question, I am now enclosing copy of a cable which we are to-day despatching to Mr. D. J. Hanna, New York, Vice-President of The Bahrein Petroleum Company Ltd., Yours very truly, THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMP M. H. Lipp Chief Local Representative. •TD. , Attach: 1The Bahrein Petroleum ComDany Ltd., Awali f 31st January, 1942. CONFIDENTIAL DONALD HANNA BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY, NEW YORK. UNDERSTAND CONo^RIPlION ABADAN ARRANOED THROUGH BRITISH AUTHORITIES IRAN v/ITII LONDON STOP UNCERTAIN OF APPLICATION BUT BELIEVE SHORT AND LONG LEAVES DISCONTINUED DURATION STOP SUMMARIZIHI SITUATION FOLLOWING DISCUSSIONS POLITICAL AGENT STOP 01B2 INDIA OFFICE CONSIDERS PRODUCING AND MANUFACTURING OPERATION THIS VICIICITY ESSENTIAL TO TOTAL WAR EFFORT BUT POLITICAL AGENT FEELS THAT TO AVOID UNDUE DISCRIMINATION MEASURES SHOULD BE TAKEN BY COMPANY TO ENSURE THAT PRESENT QUOTA AFRICAN AND CANADIAN EMPLOYEES NOW BAHREIN CAN BE MAINTAINED STOP POLITICAL AGENT HAS NO MEANS TO LEGISLATE FOR AMERICANS OR IMPOSE PENALTIES AGAIIBT CANADIAI^IS STOP TOO POLITICAL AGENT SUGGESTS APPROACH KNABEN3HUB AS TO WHAT MEASURES COULD BE TAKEN TO ENSURE THAT PRESENT QUOTA AMERICANS WILL BE MAINTAINED BUT HAVE NOT DONE SO AS BELIEVE YOU BEST POSITION JUDGE STOP AMERICAN CASOC EMPLOYEES SHOULD BE TREATED SAME AS AMERICANS BAHREIN UNDER AJTY ENFORCED REGULilTIONS OTHERWISE DI3SOTI0N WILL RESULT AS EXCHANGE PERSONNEL CERTAIN CATEGORIES NOW COMMON PRACTICE AND WE DEPENDENT THEIR CRUDE SUPPLY STOP, THREE IN PAST HAVE DONE EVERYTHING POSSIBLE REDUCE AMERICANS Td' MINIMUM IN KEEPING WITH ARTICLE SEVENTEEN LEASE STOP NOV/ APPEARS AUTHORITIES WILLING TEMPORARILY 'WAIVE THIS PROVISION AND ACCEPT AMERICANS IN VIEW DIFFICULTY OBTAINING BRITISH STOP FOUR YOU ^ SHOULD S3 POSITION 1SV.INTAIN PRK3SNT QUOTA. AMERICANS CA1UDIANS k A3 CONFIDEirr AUTH0RITI33 WILL DO KYEHCTIINC POSSIBLE RETAIN ORREPLACE BRITISH IF YOU GUARANTEE AIJD DEMONSTRATE ABILITY REPLACE AMERICANS CANADIANS STOP IF UNABLE MAINTAIN PRESENT RATIO BRITISH AND BECOMES NECESSARY INCREASE RATIO AMERICANS OR CANADIANS FOR UNSKILLED POSITIONS WOULD PRSFBR LATTER AS giTSS MORE COMPARABLE WITH BRITISH STOP FITS PREFER AVOID TBIHJ CONSCRIPTION MEASURES IF AVOIDABLE BY GUARANTEE OF VOLUNTARY RBPIAGEM3 NTS AMERICAIE3 AND CANADIANS STOP IN EVENT VOLUNTARY JUS FLAG II^XITS CANNOT BE GUARANTEED YOU SHOULD DETERMINE ATTITUDE AMERICAN AND CANADIAN GOVERNMENTS POLICY REGARDING CONSCRIPTION STOi- FOR HEALTH REASONS SHORT AND LONG LEAVES SHOULD BE CONTINUED ALL EMPLOYEES UNDER ANY CONDITIONS LONG A3 TRANSPOiXTATION AVAILABLE STOP SIX TOTAL ALL STAFF INCLUDING AND THOSE ENROUTE/ON LEAVE 207 STRENGTH 183 AMERICANS 38 ENROUTE 4 NAIySLY WP ANDERSON OKSEFE SIRJBAT FLETCHER BRITISH 141 ON LEAVE 15 CANADIANS 28 ON LEAVE 1 MANILA 4 STOP EXPECT TO LOSE APRIL TO SEPTEMBER SIX AMERICA* EIGHT BRITISH FOUR CANADIANS BUT V/ITH RECRUITMENTS ORDERED SHOULD HAVE SUFFICIENT REPLACEMENTS 1942 UNLESS EXPANSION PROGRAMS REQUIRE ADDITIONAL MEN STOP ADVISE LIPFConfidential Political Agency, Bahrairij the Bnd 1942 D* 0. No« C/139 Jill you please refer to your confidential derai- official latter No. 30-3 dates the 13th January 1942 ? 2. I air: afraid that I find one aspect of this case some what confusing. In paragraph 2 of his demi-official letter -''T ^ • $ No. D.ovi86-N/41 dated the 20 th Dec ember 1941, Curtis ssvs i ''He have asked that British subjects in Bahrain and Qatar should be brought under the same Regulation as applies to British subjects in Persia**, and the observations in para graph 3 of his letter are based on the assumption that the proposed Regulation will apply to British subjects in Bahrain and Qatar. In fact, however, the Government of India, in their telegram to the India Office No. 7171 dated the 16th December 1941, did not ask for the issue of a Regulation applicable to British subjects in Bahrain and Qatar; they asked for the issue of a Regulation to cover British employees of the Bahrain Petroleum Company and Petroleum Concessions Limited: and the term 'British employees' demonstrably does not, and cannot, include Canadian employees of those Oil Companies (c.f. paragraph 3 of your confidential demi-official letter to Weightman No. C/584 dated the 23rd November 1941 and paragraph 3 of Government of India telegram to the India ^ Q Q n— , Office No. 7171 dated the 16th December 1941). It follows, therefore, that if a Regulation is issued in the terms asked for /- HoiPble Lieutenant-Colonel W. R. Hay, C. I. E., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Dushira .m * 2 for by uhe Goverrmient of India, that Regulation will not effect Canadian employees of the Oil Companies operating in Bahrain and Qatar any more than it will affect -\nierican and Indian employees of those Companies• 3. Assuming, however, that the proposed Regulation is jnade applic3bj.e to British subjects who are employed by the Oil Companies operatiiig in Bahrain anti Qatar, the poBition will apparently be as follows (i; European British subjects will be liable to local industrial conscription, the penalty for breach of the terms of the Regulation being enforceable on the offender* s return to the United Kingdom. (ii) Canadian British subjects will be liable to local industrial conscription, but the penalty for breach of the terms of the Regulation will not, in practice, be enforce able. (ill) British subjects from India will be liable to local industrial conscription, but whether they can, in practice, bs punished for breach of the Regulation is obscure. (iv) British protected persons (e.g. subjects of Indian States) will not be liable to local industrial conscription. (v) American subjects will not be liable to local industrial conscription. jp ^ i 3 4. In paragraph 3 of his letter of 20th December 1941 Curtis observes* ’*it seems possible that the best course will be to assume locally that the Canadians will legally accept the position 11 . I wish this course were possible. Unfortunately it is not. The Canadian employees of the Bahrain Petroleum Company are acutely conscious of their national status as Canadians. They would resent any legis lation affecting them personally which had not received the approval /-3 approval of the Canadian Government; and if they discovered, as they would et once, that no penalty vtas attached to the breach by ck the proposed ;&gt;emulation, they would take every possible opportunity of contravening it. 1 should perhaps add that my appreoh tion of the attitude likely to be adopted in this respect by locally employed Canadians was originally based on the deductions which I made after reading certain records in this Agency, but hss been inde- pdxioeTi 2 aq €iaph«a'ti.c-^XXy ^ conjfirmed by Lipp • 5. I am convinced, therefore, that any attempt to enforce against t,he Caiinciiazis employed in Bahrain s Regulation which had net full legal and constitutional sanction would be doomed to failure* ;.t the same time I fully agree with view, expressed both by yourself and Curtis, that discrimina tion between different classes of the Company’ 3 servants should be avoided to the maximum extent possible. Lipp considers, and I agree with bim, that the best plan is for him to secure, or attempt to secure, a guarantee from his principals in New York that every American or Canadian employee leaving Bahrain will be replaced by another American or Canadian as the case may be. If this guarantee cannot be given, Lipp will take up v.itn his principals in New York the question of industrial conscription for 'meric an employees of the Company in Bahrain and, if he were success ful in this latter attempt, the question of dealing with the Canadians would be greatly simplified. I enclose a copy of a cable which Lipp has now sent to Mr. Banna in New York. He does not think that any advantage would be gained by addressing, at the present stagey the hroerican Minister in Baghdad. 6 . Priina facie the granting of the guarantee sought by Lipp would not go very far towards eliminating the element of discrimination in the treatment accorded to British, Canadian and American employees of tho Company..tut noffl*? discrimination is inQvit»ab.la sine 3 it. is occa sioned, net oy conditions in Bahrain, but by conditions existing in to© homo countries of XU# nationals concerned* Full industrial conscription exists already in &lt;!r«at Britain; it doe 3 not exist, in Caned? or the United f’tates* A European oritish subject cannot return home now* s Canadian or a citizen of the United States can. These difference? c- r 0 well recognised here, an.i Lip'o* c proposal ha 3 the aCivauiuage that the treatment acc led to the various nationals in Bahrain would not bo substantially different from tha treatment that they would receive in their home countries. It also has the advantage of maintaining the present ratio of British, American and Canadian employees• 7. There remains the question of Indian employees of the two Oil Companies, several hundred in number. Lipp would like his control over the Indian employees of the Bahrain Petroleum Company strengthened, and I am definitely of opinion that the proposed Regulation should, if possi ble, be made applicable to them. If the term 'British employees' is used in the Regulation, Indians will not be covered by it. If the term 'British subjects' is used, Indians from British India will be covered by it but not Indians from Native States. It will be necessary therefore if it is decided to apply the Regulation to Indian employees of the two Companies, to use ^ne terra 'British subjects and British protected persons'. I am, however, uncertain what penalty could be imposed on a British Indian subject, or Indian Protected person, for a breach of the Regulation since such person could not be ^ Y **07 apprehended in the Tjnited Kingdom (vide paragraph 4 of secret telegram Bo. 997 dated the 8th November 1941 from the Foreign Office, London, to His Majesty*s Minister, Tehran). It scans desirable that provision should be made /-- 5 - made for the punishment of Indian offenders either in India or in Bahrain, accordim? as they are apprehended in India or Bahrain. But what legal form this orovlsion should assume is not * matter in respect of which I am in a position to make suggestions. The Minister at Tehran might perhaps be able to say how the Regulation applied wo Iran -*.£*• enioreed agsxnst Indians* o. I will keep you informed of developments in the situation at this end; but, irrespective of the results of Lipp* s negotiations with New v ork, I think that industrial conscription for European British subjects employed in Bahrain and Qatar should be delayed no longer, 9* I am sending to Weightmsn by Air Mail a copy of this letter (with enclosure) and of your letter to which it is a reply. ( ^ ^ Vours sincerely, dC' cf HiNo. gcnf icient.-is, , C/141 Ths Political Agcut, Uahraio, Prasaats his compliments to : I * H. Weightman, Esquire, C.I.E., i. C . S ., ’ J c in “ ,ecretar y to the Government of India, External Affairs Department, Hew Delhi. and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document ( s ) The Agency, BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf Dated _ £nd February 1942 Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure Name and Date. Subject t 7 )emi-official letter Lie. 30-S dated ihe 13th January 1942 from the Hon f b]e the Political Resident in the Persia! ?ulf to the Political Agent, Bahrain, Demi-official letter No. C/139 dated the 2nd February 1942 from the Political ^gent, Bahrain, to the Hon’ble the Political Hesider. t in the Persian julf, v,ith enclosure. 7 on scription of labourP.A. T3 of the Bi and it v/ of contn not leav the same spared b the syst mature d B tracts h see page holding they wou their pr A we may r on leaveHtlild!^ ui leoum-ui^ to employment here. For correspondence on the whole question^ Please see pages 35, 41, 71, 88, 93 - 95, ICO - 109, 116 - 118, 12§, 132, 133, 136, 144, 156 - 158, 161 etc. hft- C.L.R. has teen to see me. He says that there are six Coy employees whose contracts are ab out to expire. 3 of these men are not wanted by the Coy. and can go. The other 3 however are key men and the Coy. wants to keep them impossible. They insist on going however and want to get employ ment in the U.K.• , „ . ^ We have no authorit y to prevent them going from here and they appear to be unamenable^to persuasion. C.L.R. suggests that if are told that &amp;e told that they would be taken up in India and“not allowed to go to England this might incline them ' W1 4-u u ~ n-r&gt; n rr -5 c not. SO BV oi &amp;U o maia and not axxoweu yu gy ^ ^^twe to renew their contracts «i ttl the Coy as pa y is not so a|tractivl &gt; ( &lt; ) P.A. Reference your note. There was a loud demand from the British personnel -- * V of the Bapco to be allowed to voltinteer for the services 1 and it was considered essential to introduce some sort of control by which those occupying key positions could not leave the Company's service prematurely while at the same time allowing some of them, who could be easily spared by the Company, to volunteer. The real value of the system is therefore 'only to prevent wholesale pre mature departures'. But we cannot do anything with those whose con tracts have expired and who refuse re-engagement (please see pages 156, 157 and 161) even though they may he holding key positions beyond impressing upon them that they would be serving their country best by staying in their present positions. As regards employees proceeding on local leave, we may refuse 'permits' for them to go out of Bahrain on leave unless they give a guarantee of returning to employment here. For correspondence on the whole question^ Please see pages 35, 41, 71, 88, 93 - 95, 100 ^09, 116 - 118, 12§, 132 ’ 133 ’ 136 ’ 144 ’ 166 A/a n - 158, 161 etc. (AaA ^0 \ i/i I c L.R. has been to see me. He says that there are six Coy employees whose contracts are ab- / , of thele men are not wanted by the Coy. and can 0Ut ^ ' Aowever Ire key men and the Coy. wants to keep them Ihef Illist on going however and want to get employ- no Author it y to prevent them going from here and they Luear to be unamenable to persuasion. r^T R eufurests that if ate told that they would be taken lAdil’ald^nlt allowed to go to England this ffii fVot so^Atfeive to renew their contracts «i t h the Coy as pa y is not so a | &gt;T 0 _In India as in U.£. • We canhot do this however without authority. In the meanti I told C.L.R, that I would try to persuade the men to atlvl if the Coy. wished. u 011 &gt; As regards their being taken up in India, possibly the G of r l may agree to us informing the men that they will be tak«n utT’ in India and not allowed to go to England or elsewhere ahn»?* they insist on leaving the Coy. ^e,should The Coy. are not at all hopeful of being able to get renla^o from anywhere. y aceme |U fit Ev k * (/^ A \tixA- ^ *.• ^ (-If C. l.. X?. r^^/=&gt;co . /ftk ^ A v / ^ 0^4 (U. L* As'^w© Se'^. &lt;xCkr/nA sju- L Vvc r / f 301 - 3 ’'&gt;V -^2.:/ 1 S . G Jl jiP^ 10 n of i hon-p ‘o? sometime past, the Bahrain Petroleum Com pany’s employees have shown restiveness and desire to leave the Company's service on various pretexts. There is danger of the Company losing key men and of running short of personnel in general to point where production will be interfered with. To orevent this exodus it has oeen proposed, and TT is Majesty’s Government have agreed to introduce a measure in Bahrain and Oatar whereby British employees of the Cil Companies will not be aole to leave the service without the consent of the Political Resident, J-he measure may be brought in any day now and the correspondence should be carefully studied.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00009e_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/749</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00009e</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/749</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>‘File 28/57 II Volunteers for national service’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1930/1942</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-10-08T21:17:20</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 volume (351 folios)</extent><extent>The volume’s contents are arranged in approximate chronological order, from the earliest item at the front to the latest at the end. The file notes at the end of the volume (ff 323-353) mirror the chronological arrangement.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence commences at the inside front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 357; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 6-278; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled, and are located in the same position as the main sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The volume comprises applications made by individuals in Bahrain (chiefly employees of the Bahrain Petroleum Company, BAPCO) for emergency commission to the military forces, and correspondence concerning official policy towards volunteers for military duty, and proposals for the introduction in Bahrain and Qatar of conscription for military duty. The file is a direct chronological continuation of ‘File 28/57 I Volunteers for national service’ (IOR/R/15/2/748). The principal correspondents in the file are: the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf (Lieutenant-Colonel Charles Geoffrey Prior; Lieutenant-Colonel William Rupert Hay); the Political Agent at Bahrain (Hugh Weightman; Major Reginald George Evelin William Alban); the Chief Local Representative of the Bahrain Petroleum Company (BAPCO) (Ward P Anderson; Milton H Lipp).The volume includes:correspondence throughout between the Political Agent at Bahrain and BAPCO representatives, concerning individuals who have applied for military service, including: individuals’ contractual obligations and the importance of their work to BAPCO, education and employment references, suitability for military service, medical certificates, exit permits, arrangements for passage out of Bahrain;correspondence related to efforts to secure the return to Bahrain from India of a Miss Henninghem, a nurse previously employed by BAPCO, in consequence of the BAPCO hospital starting to admit members of the armed forces (ff 48-49, ff 86-88, ff 99-100);correspondence relating to efforts to secure the services of four British or European women to work as coding staff at the naval wireless transmission office in Bahrain, including enquiries made by the Political Agency to various British organisations and expatriates in Bahrain, asking after the availability of any possible candidates (ff 58-68);correspondence and papers relating to enquiries into the conscription of former BAPCO employees (and others) who are British subjects (including British Canadian and Trinidadian) in India, upon their departure from Bahrain, under the Indian National Service Act (f 118, f 128, ff 133-142, f 175, ff 198-202), and associated correspondence concerning: the difficulties faced by BAPCO in retaining Canadian employees who would prefer to return to work in Canada (ff 164-165); BAPCO employees who take leave in South Africa, only to inform BAPCO that they have no intention of returning to Bahrain (f 189, ff 196-197); queries over the legality of applying the Indian National Service Act to British Canadians (f 217, ff 229-230, ff 242-242); Government proposals, supported by BAPCO, to introduce conscription in Bahrain for work considered essential to the war effort, including oil production, eventually enshrined as Defence Regulation No. 2 of 1942, under the Persian Gulf States (Emergency) Order in Council (1939) (ff 271-272, ff 275-277, ff 282-285, ff 290-322);correspondence relating to the recruitment of Royal Naval Volunteer Reserves (RNVR) at Bahrain, including enquiries made by the Political Agency to various organisations in Bahrain, asking after the availability of any possible candidates (ff 121-127, f 129, ff 143-144).While the earliest piece of correspondence in the volume is dated 24 February 1930 (a school reference submitted by a BAPCO employee, f 174), the volume commences with correspondence dated from October 1940.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Bahrain Petroleum Company, Chief Local Representative</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Military recruitment</topic></subject><subject><topic>National service</topic></subject><subject><topic>Persian Gulf States (emergency) Order in Council (1939)</topic></subject><subject><topic>Petroleum industry</topic></subject><subject><topic>Recruitment</topic></subject><subject><topic>Second World War (1939-1945)</topic></subject><subject><topic>Conscription</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000241.0x00009e#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>