<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0000df_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-07-09T11:52:27.611Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">Ho. 298 (E 4084/3091/34) FOREIGN OFFICE, S.W.l. 10th August, 1937, Sir, With reference to your despatch No. 180 (419/4/37) of the 18th May last regarding the protection of Norwegian interests hy His Majesty’s Consul-General at Bushire, I transmit to you herewith a copy of a note received by His Majesty’s Minister at Oslo from the Norwegian Minister for Foreign Affairs on this subject. 2. I have noted the observations contained in your despatch under reference and I agree that it is unnecessary to take any further action in regard to the Persian Government. I shall accordingly be glad if you will inform Colonel Fowle that he and his successors are authorised to take charge of Norv/egian interests at Bushire until further notice, I am, with great truth and regard, Sir, Your obedient Servant, (For Lord Halifax) Seymour, Esq,, C.M.G., C.V.O. etc., etc*, etc* Tehran.THa uOYaL NOk«£GIAN MINICTiiY OF FOREIGN AFFAIiiS, Jnr.12435/37. Oslo, 8th July, 1937. Monsieur la Ministre, In a note of the 3rd instant you were so good as to enquire whether the Norwegian Government wished that Norwegian consular interests at Sushire should be in the charge of the British Consul-General and his successors at the post until further notice. 1 have the honour to inform you in this connection that the Norwegian Government would be very grateful if the British Consul-General would be willing to undertake this service subject to the approval of His Majesty's Government. I avail, etc. (Signed) HALVDAN KOHI. Sir Cecil former, X.C.M.G., British Legation, Oslo.jo.laiQ Tna/i/ay) V '7 /i ''5 'I 4 • D i 19 b/ C) 13th ray,1937. Sir, Hie Conaul«a«nariil at Buahire raoeatly informed *te by tole^raph that he had betm requested by the honorary Norwegian Coneul-oeneral at Tehran to arrange faoiiitiea with the loeal authorities for a ^ome^ian 'Trade Commissioner who was on a visit to tfushire. colonel Fowl# added that he was unoertain whether Hie Majesty's ( oneulate- General was still in charge of Norwegian interests and requested iay instructions. * , ^ l • arehives of Hie j ujeety * &amp; Legation show that the oco^taion when this question oame under review was ^ ia i l re ^ to ai ‘ enquiry by His . peaty's minister at Oslo,the Norwegian Government stated that they would be i&amp;rateful if Colonel {afterwards rir Hugh) Biscoe (then His majesty’s Conoul-^neral at sushire) \fould act as i orwegian &lt;* 100 - onsul there as his predecessor had done (see Consular apartment’s letter to the Chancery (jc 1842/&amp;34; of Uay 8th 1930)* in 1932 51r Hugh Biaooe died and rir Reginald Hoare informed the then Norwegian Consul-neneral here,adding that pending the appointment of a sucoeasor, Lieutenant-colonel Fowls would have charge of the oost. jt would appear,however„that when coionel Fowle was appointed to be His Majesty’s Consul-General,no enquiry was ever aa r to the i orwegian Goverimeitt to ascertain whether they desired that he should act as honorary Korwegian vice- The Consul. mr does the wording of the Norwegian Government* request in 1930 that sir Hugh niaooe should loo* after /Norwegian Bight Honourable, Anthony Men ., oto*, etc#, etc., Td£ .FOUaiGL OFFICE, iiritereat* at Huahire any indication that thay doairod tala appoiutuant to be extended nutciia tic ally to his sueoassora. 3. On receipt of Colonel Fowls’a recent telegram,the matter woa accordingly disouaced with the present Norwegian Conaul*Oenera^ here (wno has only occupied the poet since 198&amp;)* Mo ifiieur Olsen Btatcd that,whoa he had taken the post otop from his predecessor,he had written to hia Govern ment to enquire about the position at uushlre and had received the reply that Colonel Fowle would dischar^ the nwm duties as Sir Hugh Mscoe had done and that any necessary communioa- tions would be a^dreosed direct to Colonel rowle by the Norwegian Ministry of Foreign Affaire. The recent request which he had made to Colonel powle to arrange facilities for a Norwegian Trade Commissioner wan an exceptional one which had arieon out of instructions re cived from the Norwegian % Minister in Moscow who is alao aooredited to the Iranian Government. monsieur Olson realised that some formalities had probably been overlooked with regard to Colonel Fowled appointment as Norwegian Vioe-( onoul and was inclined to wonaer whether an exequatur should not now be obtained for hia* 4. It would,however,appear that no further formalities are necessary vis-a-vis the Iranian Government. : ir Hugh Blsooo never received any Commission or exequatur and indeed the Norwegian Goveramo.it suggested (see Consular department's letter under reference) 'that the most practical arrangement would be for Mr # Biscoe not to be formally appointed to the position but simply he handed over the management of the Vioe-Coamilate as Acting Vice-Consul'. Moreover it would appear from oral discussions which took Place with the /PersianPersian iliniatry of Forsign Affairs in with regard to Sir Hugh Biscoe*® appointweiat that the Persian Governmant took the line that they could not ieeue t^o exequatur® to one pereon. They did not.howeyer,take objection to the handing over of itorwegian interests at Buahire to Hie Majesty^ Coneul-General and in Jure 1931 a note wae received from the Ministry of Foreign Affaire (eee Sir E.H* Clive’s despatch Ho.349 of July 1st 1931) stating that 'according to a letter received from the Norwegian legation the Norwegian Government has handed over the protection of its interests in Buahire to the British (onsulate-General there. Accordingly notification of this has been made to the author!tien of the locality'. You will observe that this note maices no jention of Sir Hugh Bincoe or any other Consular Officer by name and I think that it nay safely be taken as recognising His Majesty’s Consul-Ceneral.whoever he may be t as being in charge of .orweglan interests. lie further approach to the Iranian Government therefore seems necessary. B. The only question that reraalnn for consideration is whether it is not advisable to reach a clearer under standing of the position with the Norwegian Government. I should be grateful If I might be informed in due course of your views on this point and of any action which you may decide to take vis-a-vie the Norwegian Government. lean- while X have asied Colonel. Fowle to continue to protect Norwegian interests until further notice. 6. I am sending a copy of this despatch to the Honourable the political Resident la the Persian Gulf j$o.43 I have the honour to be with the highest respect, T&gt;ir, Your most obedient, humble Servant, (Signed) K.J. Seymour.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0000df_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/3661</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0000df</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/3661</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Coll 29/85 'Bushire: protection of Norwegian interests by British Consul-General'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1937/1937</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-09-25T10:50:39</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (8 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the inside front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 10; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file concerns the protection of Norwegian consular interests at Bushire by the British Consul-General at Bushire.The file is composed of correspondence between the Foreign Office and the Secretary of State for India and contains the translation of a letter from the Royal Norwegian Ministry of Foreign Affairs.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Secretary of State for India and Burma, United Kingdom</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Royal Norwegian Ministry of Foreign Affairs</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent; subject</roleTerm></role></name><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000648.0x0000df#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>