<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000517.0x0002bd_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-18T14:47:49.260Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">OUTWARD TELEGRAM s/' Cypher/OTP Confidential ^ — FROivi FOiU&amp;N QgglG^ T O BAHIiEIN. r 15th June, 1949. D: 1.30. p.m. 17th June )NC.^X&amp;9 ! Repeated to Kuwait. No. 52 CONFIDENTIAL. Adoressed to Bahrein t elegram No. 371 of June 15th. repeated for information to Kuwait. Legal opinion is that alternatives (h) and (o) in paragraph 3 of Kuwait telegram under reference would not really help and that if we have to admit a Consular Officer at all, he might as well he supplied’ with an exequatur in the normal way. 2. ^ Situation is further complicated by (a) negotiations now proceeding for Consular Conventions with certain states of which Egypt is one, though it is unlikely that such conventions v/ill he concluded with more than a small number of states within the next few years and even the^convention with Egypt may take a year or two to negotiate; (b) application by Iraq Government for appointment of Iraqi Consul at Kuwait (Bagdad despatch No. 103 [of May 25th]). 3. Consular Conventions would normally include a kind of most, favoured nation clause which would give the other signatory the right to appoint a Consul or Consular Officer wherever a third state has a Consulate. This unfortunately disposes of the United States argument that we. could refuse to allow other Consuls to be established at Kuwait on the grounds that other countries’ interests are not as great as theirs 0 Incidentally the existing Consular Convention with the United. States Government'also contains a clause which permits the’ United States to include within a consular district, though not necessarily to have a consulate in, any area which is open to the trade Commissioneis or commercial representatives of a third state, and it is likely that other Consular Conventions concluded by ’us will contain a similar clause Bahrein will be an area to ^hich a clause of this nature will apply when there is an Indian Trade Agent there. A. It must be assumed that irrespective of the existence of Consular Conventions with Egypt and Iraq, the appointment of an American Consular Officer at Kuwait will make it most difficult for us sooner or later to resist the /appointment oft CONFID E NTIAL. FOREIGN OFFICE TE LEGP^AlvI NO. 374 TO BAHREIN. —• ~2~ appointment of Egyptian or Iraqi Consuls if those Governments press strongly for this. We are disturbed at the prospect of representatives of either country being established in Kuwait, There would be endless opportunities • for political intrigue and Kuwait's special relations with us might get unwelcome publicity in Egyptian and Iraqi press. Moreover both countries would no doubt try to use Kuwait as a pawn in their own rivalry. Appointment of United States Consul will also make it far more difficult to resist'Indian and Pakistan Governments wishes to have consular officers in the Gulf, 5, On the other hand the United States Embassy are pressing us hard for a reply to their communication of April.29th and we feel that if we refuse them this facility, for which they have extremely strong practical grounds, there must be a danger that they will make some difficulty about accepting the continuance of our special position in the Persian Gulf, We therefore feel that we have really no alternative but to agree to the American proposal subject to the conditions stated in paragraph 1 of Kuwait telegram under reference. We would hold off the Egyptians and Iraqis for as long as possible but wc should almost certainly not be able to do so indefinitely, 6. Our idea is that exequatur would be given by us and that Consul should not receive any document from the Sheikh, 'U Before coming to final conclusions we should be glad* of your urgent views „ 8, Correspondence copied to Washington, B,M,E,0, Caiiro and Bagdad, Please repeat your reply Saving to those posts, [Copy sent to Middle East Secretariat], xxx11 ) V M '/fr I 9 ^ ^yi London, England. April 29, 1949 CONFIDENTIAL Dear Bernard: This Embassy has received an Instruction dated April 21, 1949, to approach you again regarding the opening or a United States Consulate in Kuwait. You will recall th this subject was discussed about a year ago, the most re- cent communlcation from the Foreign Office being Mr. L.F.I.. Pyman's letter of April 15, 1948 (File No. E 4221/3179/91). The views of the Department are set forth so clearly in its Instruction that I quote it below in full. (Instruction begins). The Secretary of State refers to the Departments telegram dated March 8, 1948, informing the Embassy that the Department had under consideration establishing a Consulate in the Sheikhdom of Kuwait and requesting the Embassy to ascertain whether the British Government, which enjoys a special treaty relationship with the ohaikn- dom, would be agreeable to the establishment of such an office• In its responsive telegram of April 16, 1948, tne Embassy quoted the following text of a letter dated April 15, 1948, addressed to the Embassy by the Eastern Depart ment of the Foreign Office: ’HVe fully appreciate the desire of State Department to provide routine consular services for US citizens in Kuwait and are anxious to meet their wishes. /»e feel that most practical4ay of providing facilities which State Department requires would be to arrange, on analogy of arrangements existing at Bahrein, the US consular representative in Basra should perform consular functions in Kuwait on an lnfor ^ 1 4 . b ^ 3is ^ ll and without exequatur. This would m ^ n .hYn^Ynsul not be officially appointed or described asUSGonsjl in Kuwait but we hope that you would not regard this as serious disadvantage. In view of our special treaty relationship with the Sheikh, the channel through US consular representative would conduct rela “°^ Bernard A.B.Burrows, Head, Eastern Department, Foreign Office, Whitehall, S.W.l. CONFIDENTIALCONFIDENTIAL -2 9 with the Sheikh and other authorities of Kuwait State would be our political agent# Latter would, of course, do everything possible to help your consular repre sentative and to ensure that interests of US citizens are fully cared for. *If these arrangements are acceptable to the State Department and you will let us know, we will at once send necessary instructions to our authorities in Persian Gulf to put them into effect and to give every possible help to US consular representative at Basra in carrying out his functions in Kuwait The Embassy explained that the British Government was unwilling to weaken the special treaty relationship which it enjoys with Kuwait and feared that should an American Consulate be established in Kuwait demands for similar facilities would be made by Saudi Arabia, Iran, Iraq, and possibly Soviet Russia. The Foreign Office believed that a fair trial should be given the procedure suggested in its letter of April 15, whereby the American Consul at Basra would undertake informal consular representation in Kuwait though remaining resident at Basra. The Consul at Basra has for a considerable period been endeavoring to perform consular services for the large American community in Kuwait by coitespondence and by visits to Kuwait on a monthly basis. Notwithstanding the sin cerity and extent of the Consult endeavors, his experience has shown that the arrangement is unsatisfactory, and that it is inherently incapable of working satisfactorily. The needs for having a Consul resident in Kuwait are real, urgent and immediate. They have been brought repeatedly to the attention of the Department during the past year by the Gulf Oil Company which has a fifty-percent interest in the Kuwait Oil Company^ concession in Kuwait, covering the largest proven petroleum reserves of any field in the Near East. More recently the American Independent Oil Company, a wholly American concern which has obtained an oil concession for the Shaikh of Kuwait*s undivided half interest in the so- called Kuwait-Saudi Arabian Neutral Zone, has also urgently requested the Department to establish a Consulate in Kuwait so that routine consular services will be available to the large number of American employees and their families it will soon be sending to Kuwait. The fundamental fact is that in Kuwait, as in every other ar« where such needs for consular services exist they must be handled by a resident consular officer personally and on a day-to-day basis. The following are examples of these needs: A. Citizenship work: V/ith hundreds of American already resident in the Kuwait district and additional large numbers expected to proceed there in connection with oil enterprises and construction programs, there is a constant demand for consular/ CONFIDENTIALCONFIDENTIAL 3 « % consular services of one sort or another in connection with passport matters* American passports are made valid for periods of two years or less and must be renewed or replaced thereafter* When an American community is first established overseas in connection with large-scale development projects as those in the Persian Gulf oil fields, experience has shown that at the outset most Americans are in possession of valid passports and during the first year or two their needs for passport services are relatively small* As time goes by, however, the demand for such services increases at a rate out of proportion to the number of people involved* Not only must passports be renewed and replaced, but amendments must be made to show the inclusion or exclusion of members of families of the bearer arriving in or departing from the area, as well as to show births and deaths in such families. Consuls must document births and marriages on standard forms and on request be present as witness at marriage ceremonies* Each American citizen and the members of his family are like wise registered at the Consulate and card files are maintained showing their whereabouts. To endeavor to perform the paper work on such documentation by mail from a distant post is cumbersome, inefficient and, where the volume is large, almost wholly impracticable. B. Protection of American Citizens: The United States Government has the obligation to afford suitable protection to its citizens wherever they may reside, and it Is often in this phase of consular work that physical presence of the consular officer is most urgently necessary. Cases have al ready arisen in Kuwait where American citizens have become involved in litigation or criminal processes, and it is logical to assume that with the steady increase in the number of Americans resident in Kuwait such cases will likewise tend to increase. This Government h as acQule anaA-X-or the time being in the trial of American citizens before the Agency Court in Kuwait under the legal system established by British Orders in Council. However, regardless of the type of enforcement agency and court procedures which apply to such cases, it is the right of the accused to have ready access to such pro tection as a representative of the United States may appropri ately extend to him. It seems self-evident that if such pro tection is to be available to the American citizens involved from the earliest moment of their need, such protection can only be afforded by an officer resident nearby. It is thought that the Government of the United Kingdom will recognize both the validity of this statement and the fact that.it may be to the advantage of the local authorities, especially the Poli tical Agent, to have close contact with the United States representative charged with such rights and obligations of protection. In cases of wider emergency such as have engulfed the Near East many times in the past century and twice within a relatively recent period of years, the weighty responsibilities of this Government’s representative in the area can only be carried out if he is in close proximity to those whom he is charged with protecting. Here again it is believed that the British Government will recognize the mutual interest of our two governments in having effective American consular represen tation in Kuwait. C. Shipping/ CONFIDENTIALCONFIDENTIAL i C. Shipping and Seamen: At present more than a hundred American tankers are loaded with petroleum products in the har bor of Kuwait annually, and with the steadily increasing rate of production of oil in Kuwait it Is anticipated that the number of tankers serving the port will also grow. Likewise, many merchant cargo vess&amp;s of American registry call at Kuwait each year. At present shipping services are performed by the Consul in Basra but, owing to the distance which sep arates him from the harbor of Kuwait, when absent from Kuwait he is unable to perform all the services required of him by law. Included in the list of services which he is precluded from performing are those with respect to the deposit of ship 1 s papers, which in some cases may seriously prejudice the fulfillment of other duties incumbent upon the officer. He is likewise unable to examine the ship^ papers and to issue crew list visas. He is unable to sign discharged sea men off the aticles and pay them the wages deposited by the master, as required by law. Other duties with respect to handling and affording relief to American seamen are made difficult, if not impossible, by virtue of the fact of his absence from the port. Insofar as he endeavors to handle the documentation in connection with shipping and seamen by mail or by signing forms in blank he is deprived of the opportunity to examine each case personally to determine Its bona fides, and may in fact by so doing be contravening the Foreign Ser vice Regulations or Statutes of Congress. The special duties of consuls with respect to seamen were among the first im posed by Congress in providing for consular representation abroad, and the very nature of such duties in a port served by American ships requires the presence of the Consul. D. Documentation of Merchandise: A limited but growing volume of work is involved in documenting merchandise for shipment to the United States of goods produced in or transit ing through the Sheikhdom. The issuance of consular invoices has hitherto been, handled by mail but a resident consul would be in a much better position to insure that shipments are being prepared in conformity with United States customs and import regulations. E. Consular Reporting: Consuls are charged by law with submission of reports on the above-mentioned matters and on other equally important subjects affecting our economic and commercial relations with the area. The importance of the American economic interest in Kuwait has already been mentioned and is of such magnitude as to require no further emphasis. The Department of State and other interested agencies of the United States Government reqiire reports from Consuls. These reports cover a wide variety of subjects, such as financial conditions, crop conditions, basic economic trends, character of commercial activity, recommended types of trading practices and agency connections, and many other related matters. The volume and extent of consular reporting on Kuwait has thus far been necessarily limited by the inability of the Consul to maintain constant touch with local conditions arising from the fact/CONFIDENTIAL CONFIDENTIAL -5- fact of his residence in Basra instead of Kuwait. The increas ing scope of American business activity in Kuwait makes it imperative that the volume and quality of consular^ reporting on the Kuwait district be improved. F. Relations with American Companies and with Local Officials: The present practice of assigning to the Consul in Basra the duty of maintaining contact with the representatives of American companies in Kuwait and with local officials has prevented the development of that intimate working relation ship so essential to the American interests involved as well as to the Governments of the United States and the United Kingdom. A case in point is that of the dispute which has arisen over the islands off the coast of Kuwait and the Kuwait Neutral Zone, involving two American companies, the American Independent Oil Company and the Gulf Oil Company which owns half interest in the Kuwait Oil Company. The Department be lieves that it would have greatly facilitated the satisfactory settlement of this dispute had an American consular represen tative been resident in Kuwait and working in close coopera- tion with the parties in dispute as well as with the Political Agent. However, it is also on matters of a more routine nature which when added together form an even greater fication for the establishment of a Consulate in Kuwait. The day-to-day problems are many and growing and in the spirit of the Anglo-American conversations on economic and cultural cooperation in the Near East held in Washington in Owtober 1947 it is believed that an American consular officer will be of great value in helping to work out the harmonious development of our commercial relations in Kuwait, In the course of executing his duties, the Consul will, of course, have regard for the special treaty relationship existing between the United Kingdom and the Shaikh of Kuwait. In view of the foregoing, you should renew the Embassy^ previous request to the British Government for its acquiescence in the establishment of an American consular office in Kuwait, in discussing the subject with the Foreign Office, the Embassy should convey the Department's view that the establishment of an American Consulate in Kuwait would not adversely effect tne existing British relations with Kuwait but on the contrary would work to the long-range mutual advantage of the Lnited States and the Wilted Kingdom. You may also point out that requests from other states for the establishment of consulates inVwait could still be refused on the just ground that they lack tangible interests in Kuwait comparable to those of the United States. With reference to the Foreign Office's analogy between the provision of consular facilities at Kuwait and Bahrein, the Embassy should point out that the handling of our consular ^eds It Bahrein by the Consulate in Dhahran is %n inconven- lent and unsatisfactory arrangement and one which we would not llll to duplicate in Kuwait where the demand for American consular services is greater and more pressing. ^CONFIDENTIAL In view of the constantly growing American interests in Kuwait, it is hoped that the Government of the United Kingdom agree that the request of the United States for consular representation there arises from normal and legitimate needs, and will accord this request its full approval, (instruction ends)• I hasten to get the foregoing into your hands because I believe that you may wish to study during your forthcoming visit to the Persian Gulf the very real problem involved. I am sure you will find there full corroboration of the facts as set forth by the Department. I look forward to discussing this question with you and learning your considered views at an early date. Sincerely yours. G. Lewis%Tones First Secretary of Embassy CONFIDENTIALCypher/OTP DEPARTMENTAL DISTRIBUTION I J Fi-OM KIT-AIT TO FOREIGN OFFICE iir. Jackson D. 11. L5 a.m. 15th ivlay, 19L9. No: L3 R. 1. 14 p.m, 15th Liay, 1949, 14th May, 1949. Repeated to Bahrein Saving. Addressed - to Foreign Office telegram No. 45 of May 14thj repeated Saving to Bahrein. Following for Chadwick, Eastern Department, from Burrows. Lewis jones letter to me of April 29th about United States Consular Office at Koweit. Preliminary reaction here and at Bahrein is that there is no insuperable objection to United States proposal provided that (a) there would be no change in question of juris diction. (b) United States Consular Officer v/ould not have direct dealings with the oheik. (c) There would be no change in political agreements witn oil companies which oblige them to deal with the Sheik through the Political Agent. 2. Possible complication is that if the United States establish Consular Office here India may no longer be content to operate from Basra. 3. Pending my return and final expression of views from here I suggest that you might obtain legal advice on formal position of United States Consular Officer. Possibilities seem to be (a) that the exequatur should be issued by His majesty's Government (as having charge of Koweit's foreign relation). (b) that United States office should be described as branch of their Basra consulate (but tnis might have undesirable implication). (c) that no exequatur should be issued but we would assure United States Government of all facilities and immunities necessary for functioning of Consular Officer. [Copy sent to Head of Eastern Department]. 11111DEPARTIviETmL DISTRIBUTION Cypher /OTP FR OM MSCAT TO FOREIGN OFFI CE 3rd April, 1948 Mr, Hay No, 5 Tour D. 11.30 a.m. 3rd April, 1948 R, 11.43 a.m. 3rd April, 1948 Reference Commonwealth Relations Office telegram No. 117 dated 27th March. American Consulate at Koweit. 2. Tandy reports that according to his information permanent United otates employees in Koweit are unlikely to exceed 200 half 400. 3. Objections to the proposal are (a) The Sheik is bound to conduct his foreign relations through United States and (b) A precedent would be created, and it would be difficult to object to the appointment of Consuls by Iraq and other Middle Eastern countries. 4. I fully support the suggestion contained in. paragraph 3 of telegram under reply and in fact practice described is already being followed. There is no. objection to United States Representative performing Consular functions in Koweit provided that he is not officially appointed or described as American Consul Koweit and he conducts his relations with the Sheik through the Political Agent. [Copy sent to Middle East Secretariat]. PPPf J/ ^ J'OHEIGN QPi'IGE, S.W.l (E 3179/3179/91) Confidential 24th March, 1948. I enclose a copy of a letter which we have received from the United States Embassy in which yon will see that the United States Government wish to know whether we should be agreeable to the establishment of a United States Consulate in Kowe it. We are inclined to think that the best solution would be to offer the Americans in respect of Koweit an arrangement similar to that which exists in respect of Bahrein. We suggest therefore that we should suggest to the Americans that Koweit should be included in their Basra Consular District, and shpuli undertake that if this is done we will give the United States Consular officials from Basra every assistance in performing their functions in Koweit, as long as they act informally and without Exequatur. We should be grateful if you would consult the Political Resident by telegram on this proposal and if you would ask him to let us have a reply urgently. (B.A.B. Burrows) J.P. Gibson, Esq . id son, i^oq., Commonwealth Relations Office.(E 3179/3179/91) COPY 'fyT / H- The Foreign Service of the United States of America American Embassy, 1, Orosvenor Square, London, W.l. March 9th 1948. Dear Lance: We have been advised by the ? f Rth State in Washington in a telegram dated March 8th that in view of the rapidly expancung Ane.. lean econonic interests in Kuwait and the growing community of US employees of he ons Company which may reach a total of 2,0°° persons, the Department has under Sheikhdom to establishing a Consulate in that oneitcnao meet the nefd for routine Consular assistance. Since the foreign relations ^l^hBve^been +. inoa ■h'tr the British Government we have oeen isFSlS American Consulate in Kuwait. Sincerely yours, (sgd) G-. Lewis Jones First Secretary of Embassy L, Lsi8taSt n ke!riastern Department, The P ore ign Oi x ice, S.W.l.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000517.0x0002bd_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/12/1307</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000517.0x0002bd</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/12/1307</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>Ext 878/48 'Establishment of USA consulate at Kuwait'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1948/1949</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-11-10T10:10:36</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (15 folios)</extent><extent>The file's contents are arranged in approximate chronological order from the rear to the front of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 17; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The file contains correspondence regarding: a request from the United States Department of State to the British Government to approve the establishment of an American Consulate in Kuwait; and the recommendation by the Foreign Office to include the Consulate in the American Basra Consular District instead. The other main correspondents are as follows Lancelot Frank Lee Pyman (Foreign Office, Eastern Department); John Percival Gibson (Commonwealth Relations Office); the Political Agent, Kuwait; and the Political Agent and Consul, Muscat.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Foreign Office, Eastern Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Embassy to the United Kingdom, London</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Department of State</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author; subject</roleTerm></role></name><subject><geographic>Kuwait</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Embassies and consulates</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000517.0x0002bd#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>