<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x0001e7_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T11:58:05.445Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">B. 181. This Document is the property of the Secretary of State for India in Council. CONFIDENTIAL. British relations with Turkey in the Persian Gulf. Memoraiulum on Lieutenant-Colonel Cox's telegram repeated in Government of India's Telegram of 1st December 1910. The immediate question out of which this arises is the desirability of concluding a treaty with a Sheikh or Sheikhs of the El Katr peninsula as a bulwark against Turkish aggression. In a Despatch of 22nd August 1910 Mis Majesty's Ambassador at Constantinople had written: 'Should His ' Majesty's Government and the Government of India now decide on the ' expediency of making such a treaty, there would seem to me no objection ' from the Constantinople point of view.' The Foreign Office referred to the India Office, the India Office to the Government of India, and the Government of India to Lieutenant-Colonel Cox. It will be convenient to take Lieutenant-Colonel Cox's telegram piece meal :— I. ' At the present juncture l find it di fficult to discuss question apart from general Anglo-Turkish situation in I he Gulf. In a letter just received Consul at Basrah writes that new Vali, when asked what action he had taken regarding Zakhnuniyeh, replied, that the island is Turkish territory and challenged right of Consul to discuss it officially or privately, lie added that he was astonished that Consul did not mind his own business which was trade. It is thus evident that communications made to Porte regardimj recent incidents have had no effect, and it seems to me that position has become impossible and humiliating, and that unless atmosphere is quickly cleared frequent recurrence of unpleasant incidents is inevitable. It appears to he generally agreed that temporising policy, which ice have pursued for years past, will not serve the purpose with the Young Turk regime, and I submit that their assertive attitude and recent attempts to upset status quo give us strong and imperative grounds for settling issues now.' The general position is at present as follows. In their letter of 4th October last the Foreign Office requested the observations of Viscount Morley on the terms of a draft despatch which it was proposed to address to His Majesty's Ambassador at Constantinople, ' respecting the vexatious ' treatment of British subjects in Asiatic Turkey, and the number of ' incidents of political aggression which have recently marked the conduct ' of the Ottoman authorities in the region of the Persian Gulf.' The draft despatch, after enumerating the complaints of His Majesty's Government, concluded as follows :— ' These occurrences, which individually have been the cause of painful surprise to His Majesty's Government, have produced in their cumu lative effect, an unfavourable impression as to the present attitude of the local Ottoman authorities,—an attitude which appears to be one of hostility and aggression. ' His Majesty's Government cannot believe that this attitude has the approval of the Central Government, or is based upon their specific instructions. I therefore have decided to instruct you to communicate a translation of this despatch to the Minister of Foreign Affairs, in order that his Excellency may be fully apprised of the views of His Majesty's Government and of their causes of complaint; in taking this step your Excellency should explain that His Majesty's Govern ment have decided to make friendly representations, believing that the Ottoman Government will redress the grievances referred to, for a situation of very considerable gravity would of course arise if they proved to be the result of deliberate and unfriendly policy.' S. 41.Lord Morley concurred in the draft, remarking that he ' is in entire acord with Sir E. Grey in thinking that the time has come when it is necessary to ' give the Turkish Government a sharp reminder of the interests of Great ' Britain and India in those regions.' The despatch issned on 17th October 1910. Then came the anti-British and pro-German explosion at Constantinople caused by the publication of a garbled version of the British note to Persia regarding the restoration of order on the southern roads. The Ambassador took fright, and begged to be allowed to postpone communication of the despatch ' until ill-feeling has died down ' (Sir G. Lowther's telegram No. 2.H2 of 24th October); and the Foreign Office, without again consulting this Office, agreed (Sir E. Grey's telegram No. 323 of 26th October). Lord Morley thereupon addressed a letter (28th October) to the Foreign Office, which was of the nature of a protest against this change of policy, observing that ' Sir G. Lowther's telegram No. 232 of 24th October contains no considerations that could not have been foreseen when the despatch in ' question issued ' ; that the object of His Majesty's Government is u less ' to secure an adjustment of the particular incidents, than to impress ' upon the Turkish Government, in a manner that shall preclude further ' misunderstanding, the importance which they attach to their interests ' in those regions, and their determination to see that they are respected ' ; and that the probability of attaining this object would be ' greatly ' diminished if the general protest is long deferred, and if His Majesty's ' Ambassador proceeds by means of piece-meal representations in the ' meantime.' To this letter the Foreign Office have not thought it necessary to reply, and we are therefore entirely in the dark as to what their general policy is. II. ' From a Jocal standpoint ichat is needed to clear the air is (1) that ire should cease to make a secret of our Agreement with Koweit, and should in form Porte that we intend to make it effective. If we can simidtane &gt;usly eliminate anomaly of Turkish flag at Koweit, I strongh/ recommend it.' The history of Turkish and British relations with Koweit will be found in pp. 155-100 of the Report and Proceedings of a Sub-Committee of the Committee of Imperial Defence on the Baghdad Railway, Southern Persia, and the Persian Gulf, dated 26th January 1909. We have two secret Agreements with the Sheikh. By the first, dated 23rd January 1899, he binds ' himself his heirs and successors not to receive the Agent or Repre- ' sentative of any Power or Government, without the previous sanction of ' the British Government,' and 'not to cede, sell, lease, mortgage, or give ' for occupation or for any other purpose any portion of his territory ' to the Government or subjects of any other Power without the previous ' consent of His Majesty's Government for these purposes.' In return he is assured of the good offices of the British Government' towards himself, his heirs, and successor?. The first of these conditions was inserted without the authority of His Majesty's Government, and in approving it Lord G. Hamilton remarked that its ' operation, more especially with regard to the relations of the Sheikh to the Turkish Government, will require ' the careful attention of Your Excellency.' (Secret Despatch No. 11 of 30th March 1899). By the second agreement, dated 15th October 1907, we secured (a) the lease of a strip of land on the foreshore to the mouth of Bunder Shweikh; (6) the right of pre-emption in sale or lease of certain other tracts, including ' the entire island of Warba, situated near Khor Abdullah and the surrounding foreshore.' The Sheikh in the same agreement confirmed the earlier one, and expressly included the Ottoman Government among the foreign Governments to whom he is not to alienate Koweit territory. For obvious reasons secrecy was necessary, but the German Government were informed confidentially of the second condition of the 1899 Agreement, and if they know of it the Turks certainly know of it also.It is not quite clear what Colonel Cox means by making the agreement 'effective.' It is ineffective only in the sense that the circumstances have never arisen in which it would take effect. Presumably he means a making explicit of what is implicit in it, viz., a denial of Turkish sovereignty and an assertion of a British protectorate. This would have to be considered with reference to its effect on Germany as well as on Turkey. x \s regards the later agreement, there is the further difficulty that the Sheikh's claim to the island of Warba is not indisputable, and as recently as March last Government of India, India Office, and Foreign Office were all agreed that it was inadvisable to take any steps to raise the question (S. 3130/JO). As regards the Turkish flag, it should be explained that the Sheikh of Koweit lias flown it certainly since 1871, and possibly since 1856. In 1901, when it was suggested by the Government of India that he should discontinue the use of it. Lord Lansclowne rejected the proposal, and was ' not prepared to support any action which could be interpreted as asserting the entire indepen- ' dence of the Sheikh of Koweit ' (Foreign Office letter, 24th August 1901, S. 2251/01). The proposal was pressed later in the year, with the suggestion that the Sheikh should fly the plain red Arab flag instead, but the Foreign Office adhered to their objection (Foreign Office letter 24th September 1901, S. 2366/01). In 1901 the Government of India suggested that the Sheikh might retain the Turkish flag for use at Koweit and use a distinctive flag {i.e. a Turkish flag with the word ' Koweit' written across it in Arabic) elsewhere (Secret letter No. 2217 of 8th December 1904), and this was agreed to by the Foreign Office (letter of 18th February 1905, S. 2653). ^ The Sheikh concurred at first (S. 873/06), but later in the same year demurred, on the ground that it 'was sure to get him into trouble' with the Turks, unless he was guaranteed by us against the consequences (S. 2010 ; 0t)). The Government of India thought that this 'might involve us in responsibilities of a somewhat extended character ' (Secret Letter Xo. 193 of_ 27th December 1906, S. -!205). The Foreign Office were consulted (27th January 1907), and the Ambassador at Constantinople was not opposed to according this guarantee, thinking it ' very unlikely ' that the Turkish Government would interfere with the Sheikh's action (Sir N. O'Conor's Despatch No. 105 of 18th February 1907); but the Foreign Office have never replied to our letter, and the question has remained in a state of suspended animation ever since. It will have been observed, from the passage referred to above in the Defence Committee's proceedings, that the basis of our policy at Koweit has puipoited to be adherence to the status (jno. Ihis has been a convenient formula, but it is two-eoged. 1 he lurkish Government understand it in their own sense (and what that sense is is shown by the fact that they have made the Sheikh a Kaim-makam, and that they are applying the utmost pressure to induce him to register himself as a Turkish subject). We under stand it in ours. One of the difficulties is to define our own meaning. Thus, the Foreign Office were parties to the agreement of 1899. Yet in September 1901 they declared that ' there does not appear to have been any ' period since [1871J when His Majesty's Government have not been ready to admit at least the suzerainty, it not the actual sovereignty, of the Sultan.' (Foreign Office letter of 24th September J901). For practical purposes the definition given by Sir T. Sanderson to Count Metternich a few days earlier seems sufficient, viz., that the status quo is 'the Sultan's authority as it exists in those parts.' Turkish authority 'as it exists' is limited to the Turkish title conferred oir the Sheikh (it maybe noted that within the last iew weeks the Sheikh has refused the offer of an allowance to accompany the title), the use by the Sheikh of the Turkish flag, and a Turkish guard sent to the island of Bubiyan, in violation of our definition of the status quo, in 1902. It would appear, therefore, that while there is nothing in the agreements that could not be made public without violating the status quo, we could not deny Turkish suzerainty if the Foreign Office view of 1901 is sound; nor could we assert a protectorate in view of Lord Lansdowne's pledge to the Turkish Government in 1901 so long as the Turks themselves maintain the status quo (as we understand it), and do not send troops to Koweit. A further question is whether the despatch of the Turkish guard to Bubiyan Island does not absolve us from this pledge.4 So much for theory. In practice it will 1)6 observed that His Majesty s Government have at times been inclined to go somewhat further. In •lanuary 1902 11.M.S. Pomonc landed guns to protect the Sheikh against an attack threatened by the Amir of Nejd and the Turks, and His Majesty's Government, in spite of Turkish protests, refused to remove them so long as danger ot attack existed. And in October 1902 His Majesty's Government, while refusing to give the Sheikh gnus for his own use, under- took to defend the Koweit district (understanding thereby the district adjoining or close to the bay) provided that he fulfilled his engagements and took their advice. Our definition of the {status quo seems therefore in practice to receive this extension, viz., that we should deny to the Turks the means oF asserting even such authority as they may possess. (2.) ' I hat ice should (a) bring about withdrawal of Turkish military posts from hi liidaa, Bubiyan, Um Kasr, Zakhnuniyeh, and Jimiah, and{h) finally to aholish mudirates at W'akra, cfcc., and (c) induce Turks to cou line themselves to their recognised possessions at Katif and Ujair.' (a} As Bubiyan, Lm Kasr, and Jinnah stand on a rather different footing t'rom the rest ol the places mentioned, they may be taken first. Bubiyan is an island immediately to the north of Koweit, between Koweit bav and the mouth ol the Shatt-al-Arab. it is claimed by the Sheikh of Koweit, mainly in virtue of the lact that some of his tribes (the Awazim) use it for fishing purposes. Hut in 19u2 the Turks sent a small guard there, and the Ambassador at Constantinople was directed to protest. The Turkish ^Minister lor 1'oreign Affairs stated that he was not aware of the occupation ot' Hubiyan Island, though he knew that troops had been sent to Um Kasr ; and he informed the Ambassador that the real motive of these proceedings was to keep a debouche for the Bagdad Railway under Turkish protection, as difficulties had been raised about extending it to Koweit (1912 02). In 1901 the Government of India recommended either that the Porte should be called upon to withdraw their post and that we should ourselves establish a post in behalf of the Sheikh at the northern end of the island, or that the Porte should be informed that we regard the island as belonging to the Sheikh, and that unless lurkish troops were withdrawn we should support him in establishing a post of his own (402/04). Sir N. O'Conor was thereupon authorised to repeat his former protest, and, after an interval of some months, if the post had not been withdrawn, to inform the Porte in the sense of the Government of India's second alternative (2665/04). I he first part of these instructions was carried out, and as regards the action subsequently to be taken the Government of India made the following recommendations in their telegram of 20th J une 1905 : - ' Mubarak welcomes idea of establishing post, on condition (1; that British Government give him full moral support, inform Porte that they recognise his claim to Bubiyan, and support him in instituting post; (2) Mubarak asks for following material support; (a) maintenance of Political Agent at Koweit as practically permanent; (6) occasional visit of man-of-war to Koweit and Khor Abdullah ; (c) contribution by British Government of Us. 500 for erection of guard quarters, and Ps. 100 a month for guard maintenance. We regard these terms as lair, and advise full acceptance. ( ost of (c) is less than subsidy sanctioned in your telegram of 17th January 1899. Sheikh suggests more than one post, and visit by Cox to Khor Abdullah should be sanctioned before number or location of posts is settled.' The Foreign Office thought that this went rather too far, and the question was held over for consideration by the Defence Committee in connection with that of the eventual terminus of the Bagdad Railway (3249/05). In September 1905 Sir N. O'Conor again spoke to the Turkish Minister for foreign Affairs, but without drawing a reply. In August 1906 the Govern ment of India returned to the charge (1372/06), and the whole question (which does not seem to have been considered by the Defence Committee) was referred to an inter-departmental committee (Foreign Office, Admiralty, and India Office), which, in its report dated 2nd October 1907, recom mended that ' if diplomatic considerations permit . . . the continued occupation of Bubiyan Island by a Turkish post, in derogation of the Sheikh s teintoiial claims (which have been recognised and supported bv' His Majesty's Government), should be neutralised hy the establishment ' forthwith of a Kovveiti post, with the countenance of His Majesty's Govern- ' ment, on Warba Island (immediately north of Bubiyan), or, if that should ' prove undesirable, on the northern shores of Bubiyan Island. If practi- ' cable we would even recommend tlie establishment of posts on both islands. We desire 10 emphasise the importance which we attach to the effective assertion of the Sheikh's territorial claims to Bubiyan.' The Foreign OHice accepted these conclusions (12th November 1907, 3903/07), and local enquiries were instituted as to the basis of the Sheikh's claims to Warba. It appeared that these were not very strong, historically; but in view of the fact that it is separated only by a narrow channel from Bubiyan, it might fairly be argued on geographical grounds that the ownership of Warba followed from that of Bubiyan. The Government of India reported in September 1908 that the Sheikh was not at the time anxious to move in the matter of his claims to the latter, and His Majesty's Government therefore decided to take no action (Secret Despatch No. 19, 30th October 1908), a decision which, as has already been mentioned, was reaffirmed in April last (Secret Despatch No. 9, 8th April 1910). To Um Kasr the Sheikh's claim appears to be much more shadowy than to Bubiyan. There is an old fort there, which is said to have been built by his grandfather, but in 1904 it was uninhabited. On the other hand the Turks were reported to have little claim beyond that of actual occupation. The importance of these places is indicated by the following passage from the Government of India's letter of 4th February 1904: ' With the ' shores of the mainland and of Bubiyan Island in the possession of a single Power, the anchorages below Um Kasr and at Warba Island can at any ' time be converted into an impregnable harbour.' Jinnah has not hitherto figured in the correspondence, but it is an island lying alongside of the Island of Musallamiya, which is claimed by the Sheikh of Koweit. The Sheikh protested against the landing of Turkish troops on the latter island in 1902. It may be explained that the southern limits of his territory have never been defined, but the Government of India were of opinion that the Sheikh's claim to Musallamiya could not be maintained, and that the island was clearly within the Turkish sphere of influence. (Telegram 10th May 1902.) Of the other places mentioned as occupied by Turkish troops. El Bidaa and Zakhnuniyeh are south of the region known as El Katif, in which His Majesty's Government have recognised continuous Turkish influence. As will have been seen from paragraph 155 of the Defence Com mittee's Proceedings, the southernmost point of that influence is Ujair. South of I jair and on the El Katr Peninsula, His Majesty's Government have declined to recognise Turkish sovereignty, but the Turks established a garrison at El Bidaa in 1872 and we have acquiesced in it. Zakhmmiyeh is 10 miles south of Ujair, and is claimed by the Sheikh of Bahrein. The Turks ran up their flag there in March 1909 and arranged to keep a guard there. The Government of India recommended that a protest should be made at Constantinople, and that the Sheikh of Bahrein should be allowed to fly his flag on the island (telegram of 23rd May 1909). The protest was made and the Ambassador was informed in September that the guard had been withdrawn at the beginning of June. In these circumstances it was decided to drop the question of the Bahrein flag, the policy of His Majesty's Government being to avoid disturbance of the status quo (telegram to \ iceroy 13th October 1909) In November the Political Agent, Bahrein, reported that there were no Turkish soldiers on the island, but by April 1910 they had reappeared, and the Turkish flag was again being flown. The Ambassador again protested, but received only evasive replies (telegram of 16th August 1910). The subject was therefore included in Sir E. Grey's despatch of 17th October, to which reference has already been made, and the Ambassador was instructed ' to request that orders may be issued for the immediate and permanent withdrawal of the garrison.' In a telegram dated 17t,h October 1910 Sir G. Lowther reported that the Porte had instructed the Vali of Basra that when the gendarmes left the island at the end of the fishing season they were not to return except under orders from Constanti nople ; and on 14th November he reported that the gendarmes had deserted. S. 41. Br 6 and conjectured that this was a Turkish expedient for avoiding formal with drawal. The Consul at Basra, however, reported on 27th October, that the Vnli denied receiving such orders, and still maintained that the island belongs to Turkey. El Bidaa is on the east coast of the Katr peninsula, and, as has already- been mentioned, the Turks have maintained a garrison there since 1872. Their nominal suzerainty has been tolerated, though no communication has been made to the Porte to this effect, but attempts to extend their control have been resisted. The garrison recently consisted of 00 men and 4 guns. Prom all these facts may be gathered the degree of opposition to be expected if His Majesty's Government announce at Constantinople their intention no longer to observe the status quo. (h) Wakra, Odeid, and Zobara are all on the coast of El Katr, a promontory south of the recognised Turkish sphere. In 1902 it was announced that all three were to be converted into administrative districts. The British Government had already forcibly dispersed a Turkish settlement at Zobara in 1895 as being dangerous to the safety of Bahrein ; and Odeid had been held for at least 30 years to be the property of the Chief of Abu Dhabi, with whom we have treaty relations. Accordingly in March 1903 Sir N. O Conor warned the Turkish Government against making any admini strative changes affecting the status quo in El Katr, and reminded them of previous representations made by His Majesty's Government in 1883, ISDo, and 1895). In reply he was informed that the question had been discussed at a Council of Ministers, and that there was no intention of sending mudirs to these places. Sir N. O Conor had been unwilling to raise the whole question of Turkish sovereignty unless His Majesty's Government were quite clear as to the policy to be pursued if the Turks—as he thought they probably would—merely reaffirmed their claims, and it was hoped that the incident was closed. But in the meantime a Turkish official had started for Wakra, and succeeded in establishing himself there, and His Majesty's Government had to pi ess for bis withdrawal. I he 1 urks dismissed him, but appointed a local sheikh (Abdur Rahman bin Ibani) niudir in his place, and it was not till November 1904 that His Majesty's Government succeeded in getting the post altogether abolished. In August last the Consul at Basra reported that n mudir had again been appointed to Odeid, and Sir G. Lowther (Despatch So. 603 of 22nd August 1910) thought that this, along with their action at Zakhnuniya, pointed to 'a determination to assert and extend Ottoman sovereignty in the neighbourhood of El Katr.' He was instructed to hand m a vritten protest, ' pointing out that El Odeid is in the territory of one of ' the Trucial Chiefs who are under the protection of Hi? Majesty's Govern- 'ment,' and requesting that the appointment might be 'immediately rescinded ' (Sir E. Grey's telegram of 20th September). The Eoreign Office at the same time consulted the Admiralty as to whether it would be possible to effect a landing at El Odeid for the purpose of expelling the mudir, if His Majesty's Government should decide to resort to forciblrne easures. The Admiralty in reply recommended that the necessary action should be taken by Indian tioops, the part of the ^Navy being limited to assisting in the landing operations, and they pointed out that the employment of the Royal Indian Marine Steamer Hardinge in connection with the blockade should facilitate any action which might be necessary. The Turkish Government, however replied that they knew nothing of any such appointment, and had telegraphed to the \ ali of Basra not to make it, and to cancel it if it had been made. Local enquiry left little doubt that the appointments had been made both to Zobara and Odeid, although the new officials had not taken up theii duties , and on 21st October Sir G. Eowther was instructed to make a f uj tliei piotcst, icpCciting that liJ Ivatr is outsid© lurkisli jurisdiction.' (c) AA ith regard to the limitation of Turkish authority to Katif and Uiair Sir G. Lowther, in his despatch of 22nd August, wrote as follows : — ' As regards Zakhnuniyeh, El Katr, and Bahrein which in a way form one group the active forward policy of the Young Turk Vali of Bussorah and the Mutessarif of El Hasa (Xejd) have already brought us into sharpconflict, and there seems no donbt that we should insist on Turkish exclusion from the district south of Ujair. If the Minister for Foreign Affairs, after studying the question of Zakhnuniyeh and Odied and consulting his colleagues, does not give categorical instructions for the non-interference of the Turkish local authorities, it would seem necessary, subject to the views of His Majesty's Government, to take a strong line. For, to the Turkish mind, Zakhnuniyeh is a sort of stepping stone to El Katr. and perhaps even to the Trucial coast. The Turks do not put forward any valid claims to justify their territorial acquisitions in those parts, but it is not difficult to glean that they base their claims on the fact that in the beginning of the iGth century a Turkish flotilla, under Piale Pasha, annexed Gwadur, in iSouth Baluchistan, and sailed up the Gulf, compelling the Arab Chiefs to acknowledge the sovereignty of the Ottoman Sultan and Caliph. They further feel that as the dominant Islamic power they have undefined right to bring under their allegiance and to protect the small Arab Moslem tribes, &amp;c., in the Arabian peninsula. Sir E. Grey's despatch of 17th October contained the following passage :— ' I do not propose to enter upon a detailed review of British relations with the Sheikh of Bahrein and the Trucial Chiefs, since the matter is one which in no wise concerns the Ottoman Government; J need simply observe that those relations have been the foundation of the maritime peace which has now been maintained in the Persian Gulf for well-nigh a century. ' Moreover, as Your Excellency is aware, in November and December 1871 the Ottoman Minister for Foreign Affairs himself gave assurances that hU Government had no intention of attacking or obtaining any supremacy over Bahrein or the independent tribes on the coast of the Persian Gulf, and similar assurances had already repeatedly been given to Her Majesty's Ambassador at Constantinople. ' But, apart altogether from the assurances of the Ottoman Government to which I have referred, Ujair, in the district of El Katif, is the most southerly point which His Majest3 7 's Government have ever recognised as being under Turkish influence on the coast of the Persian Gulf. ' In these circumstances Your Excellency was instructed to request the Ottoman Government to withdraw the garrison from Zakhnuniyeh on the ground of terminating a disturbance of the status quo; and your repre sentations were to be based, not only on the title of the Sheikh of Bahrein to the island, but also on the lact that it is situated some distance to the south east of Ujair, the furthest limit of Ottoman jurisdiction.' III. ' That having achieved second hew, ice should make treaties on lines of Trucial Coast agreements with Bin Thani, and, if necessary, with other headmen on the ivest coast of Katr' The question of making an agreement was first raised by the Govern ment of India in 1902 in connection with the desire of Sheikh Ahmed bin Thani to be taken under our protection, being alarmed at an intimation which he had received from the Turkish authorities that they intended to send more troops to those regions. The Government of India were in favour of the conclusion of an agreement, but in 1903 the idea was shelved because the abandonment by the Turks of the contemplated mudirates above referred to made it impossible for His Majesty's Government to do anything themselves inconsistent with the status quo. The Government of India, however, in 1901 suggested that without establishing a protectorate it might be justifiable to make such an agreement with the Sheikh as would secure the maintenance of the status quo and the exclusion of foreign interference, the Sheikh undertaking not to enter into relations with, receive the representative of, or cede territory to any foreign power. (Secret letter No 77 of 31st March 1904). His Majesty's Government had at the time a large number of questions outstanding with the Turkish Govern ment, and Sir N. O'Conor was unwilling to add to them, being moreover S. 41. c8 doubtful whether even the modified proposals of the Government of India could be squared with the status qvo. As a compromise the Government of India proposed the revival of an agreement of 186S made with a former Sheikh, but the Foreign Office (18th February 1905), thought that this would be ineffective, and the matter was reserved for consideration by the Defence Committee along with the whole question of the Persian Gulf. It is not known whether it was so considered, and it has not been heard of since, until Sir G. Lowther's Despatch of 22nd August, from which quotation has already been made, and the Foreign Office letter of 4th October, in which the views of the India Office were asked for. We have in the present telegram the views of Lieutenant-Colonel Cox and the Government of India. They are as follows :— (Colonel Cox):— 'I consider that it would he useless now to make treaty with Bin Thani, unless w are prepared to do so openly, and to bring about elimination of Turkish influence of Katr, as suggested in second item above. Without such simultaneous action existence of treaty would only be source of danger to the Thani family from the present Turkish regime, and they would themselves fight shy of it. (Government of India):— ■' We concur with Cox that no advantage would accrue from treaties with Katr Chiefs, and further that Chiefs would probably not now agree to enter into treaties, unless the Turks can be induced to confine themselves to their recognised possessions at Katif and Ujair.' It will be observed that in 1904, when the local situation was ripe, Constantinople was not ready ; and that now, when Constantinople is ready, the local situation is not ripe. Sir G. Lowther in his despatch of 22nd iVugust savs that ' the time may not be far distant when, as advocated by Lord ' Lansdowne in February 1905, a comprehensive, as opposed to piecemeal, ' treatment of outstanding questions in the Persian Gulf . . . may ' become imperative.' The nearest approach that has been made to anything comprehensive was Sir E. Grey's Despatch of 17th October, the fate of which has been described. If the settlement is to be friendly there must be some give and take. As to this Colonel Cox's view is:— ' Whether achievement of above ends is possible by means of comprehensive reciprocal compromise or whether coercive measures wdl be necessany, is a question beyond my purview, but I beg to say that I can conceive no quid pro quo which we could offer Porte in this sphere in exchange for withdrawal of her pretensions. It could perhaps be found in some other sphere.' This will presumably be accepted. The only points of contact that we have with Turkey in the neighbourhood of the Gulf are things that both of us want and neither can afford to part with. ' Should coercive measures (Colonel Cox says) be necessary, we can never expect the recurrence of such a. favourable junction locally as exists at present. The numerical strength of mUitary posts in question has just been reduced to a minimum under Nazim Pasha s scheme for concen trating troops at Bagdad; while we have strong squadron in the Persian Gulf in connection with Arms Tra ffic, which would, make naval demonstration simple matter.' The Foreign Office, as has been mentioned above, have already contem plated resort to force in the case of the mudirates in Katr, with the result— not uncommon in such cases—that it was proposed that India should perform the task. If troops are to be employed, it is perhaps natural that they should be Indian troops. But their employment would probably come within the scope of 21 &amp; 22 Vict. c. 106, s. 55: 'Except for preventing or repelling ' actual invasion of Her Majesty's Indian possessions, or under other sudden ' and urgent necessity, the revenues of India shall not, without the consent ' of both Houses of Parliament, be applicable to defray the expenses of any ' military operation carried on beyond the external frontiers of such ' possessions by Her Majesty's forces charged upon such revenues.' It isy true that the employment of Indian troops in the naval blockade has not been regarded as covered by the Act. But that can hardly be described as a military operation, whereas the ejection of Turkish gairisons could hardly he described otherwise. That, however, is perhaps d detail, since 1 arliamentary discussion might be inevitable in an} 7 case. As legardr- the local situation, Colonel Cox's views are borne out by recent repoits. the Consul-General at Bagdad has more than once called attention to the military weakness of the Province. In the August Summary (page 14) he noted that after denuding a large part of the country of troops Nazim Pasha had only been able to concentrate some 3,U00 men at Bagdad, a number not more than a sulhcient garrison for the capital. In order to effect this concentiation the foices in llasa have lately been considerably reduced ; in July 570 men were withdrawn (140 from El Bidaa), and 200 more were to follow. 1 hese were not to be replaced, but in cases of emergency troops would be sent from Basra (letter from Political Agent, Bahrein, 24th July 1910, S. 1317/10), the garrison of which the Consul-General, Bagdad, put at one battalion (September Summary, page o). There remained 70 infantry (to be raised to 100 probably), 40 police, and 6 guns at Katif; 60 infantry and 4 guns at El Bidaa ; 50 infantry and 2 guns at Ujair; and about 600 infantry, 35 cavalry, 130 police, and 12 guns at Hofuf (the capital of Hasa, 40 miles inland from Ujair). It remains to consider the question of a treaty with the Katr Sheikh on its merits. Arguments in favour of it are given on page 4 of Sir R. Ritchie's memorandum of 30th January 1905. Since that date the case for a treaty has become somewhat stronger. For example, the Katr peninsula is the only part of the coast of tne Persian Gulf on which the arms traffic is not pro hibited, and it tends to be a dumping ground in consequence ; thus we heard on 5th December that a dhow under French colours had left Muscat in that direction. If we had a treaty our chain of defences would be complete. Again, with regard to the pearl fisheries, the Law Officers in answering the reference made to them had no doubt as to the rights of the tribes in such waters as may justly be considered territorial. Outside these they were inclined to hold that the exclusive rights of the tribes might be maintained to banks in regard to which their exclusive possession is capable of historical proof ; but they considered that the point was not free from doubt. And as regards the deeper waters they were of opinion that there would be no reasonable chance of asserting with success the right of the tubes to debai othei nations Irom dredging. In these circumstances, the Secretary of State agreed with the general conclusion of the Law Officers, viz., that it was not expedient to raise the question internationally by forciblv preventing vessels of foreign nationalties from fishing on the banks. And he added, I he object m view may probably be attainable bv indirect methods.' (Secret Despatch No. 8, of 31st March 1905.) These indirect methods, which would consist mainly in putting difficulties in the way of interlopers, could probably only be successfully employed if our position vis-d-vis of the tubes were such as would be secured to us by the proposed treaties. A\ ith regard to the terms of such treaties, it has been suggested that they should follow the lines of the 1892 agreements with the Trucial Chiefs. 1 hese provide (1) that the Chiefs will on no account enter into any agreement or correspondence with any power other than the British Government; (2) that without the assent of the British Government they will not consent to the residence within their territory of the Agent of any other Government • (3) that they will on no account cede, sell, mortgage or otherwise give for occupation, any part of their territory, save to the British Government. CONCLUSIONS. ' Achievement of ahovc measures would completely consolidate our position on Arab coast and in Gulf generally, especially in regai^d to pearl fishery question, aud, if it is ever to be brought about, it seems essential that action should be taken now. If it is delayed, the suggested association of Turkey with Triple Alliance and increase10 of her navy may render fash very difficult, if not impossible, fu any case, therefore, by one method or another, I respectfully urge necessity of adjusting position with Turkey forthwith, and eliminating chronic elements of friction which have now become dangerous.' The conclusions to which, tluse considerations seem to point are as follows:— (1.) It is desirable to conclude treaties with the Katr tribes. 2.) It is not possible to do so unless we can guarantee them against 1 urkish aggression. (3.) There seem to be three ways of arriving at such a guarantee- (а) A comprehensive settlement by friendly agreement. 1 he materials for this do not appear to be forthcoming. (б) A comprehensive settlement by announcement to the Turks that we do not recognise their position at Koweit and south of Ujair, and the translation of that announcement into action by the removal of all signs of Turkish authority. r l his would obviously be a serious measure, but it might perhaps be taken in reply to some particularly objectionable action on the part of the Turks, either in the Gulf or elsewhere, such as will doubtless be forthcoming before long. (c) A piecemeal settlement. We should make no announcement of policy ; but as each case arises, instead of protesting, remove the objectionable Turks. In the case of Koweit this would also, presumably, mean that we should support the Sheikh by force in the question of the registration of his Turkish properties, i.e., guarantee him against the conse quences of forcibly ejecting any persons whom the Turks might send to take possession of those properties. (4.) When the Turkish difficulty has been finally removed by one or other of these means, the main reason for concluding the agreements will have disappeared. It is for the Foreign Office to decide. F. A. H. 7tli December 1910.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x0001e7_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/18/B181</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x0001e7</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/18/B181</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'British relations with Turkey in the Persian Gulf. Memorandum on Lieutenant-Colonel Cox's telegram reports in Government of India's telegram of 1 December 1910.'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1910/1910</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2014-10-30T10:58:43</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>5 folios</extent><extent>The memorandum is arranged in three sections with an introduction and conclusion.</extent><extent>Foliation: The foliation sequence commences at the first folio, and terminates at the last folio; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. Pagination: An original printed pagination sequence is also present in the booklet.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This memorandum concerns British relations with Turkey in the Persian Gulf and was written by Frederic Arthur Hirtzel in December 1910. The immediate question it addresses is 'the desirability of concluding a treaty with a Sheikh or Sheikhs of the El Katr [Qatar] peninsula as a bulwark against Turkish aggression' and comments on a telegram by Percy Zachariah Cox. It is divided into three parts; the first part assesses the general Anglo-Turkish situation in the Gulf and examines anti-British and pro-German developments as Constantinople.The second part concurs that the publication of the secret agreement with Shaikh Mubarak bin Sabah of Koweit [Kuwait] is necessary to clarify matters and lists settlements claimed by the Shaikh of Koweit. The third part argues that having achieved that they should make treaties on the lines of Trucial Coast agreements with 'Bin Thani' [Shaikh Jāsim bin Muḥammad Āl Thānī]. The memorandum discusses how such an agreement would be justifiable because by excluding foreign powers it would maintain the status quo.The memorandum concludes that it was desirable to conclude treaties with the Qatar tribes and that this would require giving them a guarantee against Turkish aggression.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>India Office, Secretary to the Political and Secret Department</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">author</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Emir of Qatar</namePart></name></subject><subject><geographic>El Katr</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Turkey</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Foreign relations</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x0001e7#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>