<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000050_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-16T11:50:30.406Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">TABLE OF CONTENTS. ,»c nt Boundary of Persia never accurately defined .. .. .. .. Arrowsmith’s Map of Persia. 1834 .. .. .. Zimmermann’s Map. Berlin. 1841 .. .. .. Vambery’s Map. 1863 .. .. .. .. .. .. . Supposed Secret Treaty between Persia and Russia for cession to latter of the Attrek Valley Official denial of Persian Government .. .. .. .. Agreement made between the two Courts on the 13th December, 1869, as to the Attrek Boundary Recognition by Russia of Persian authority and sovereignty up to the banks of the Attrek River. No forts to be built by Russia Russian Map. 1863 .. .. .. Existence of any Secret Treaty also denied by the Russian Foreign Office Proposal made by Russia to Persia in 1865 (?) to make the Attrek the boundary of Persia, for suppression of Brigandage and Piracy of Nomad Tribes on shores of the Caspian Arrowsmith’s Map. 1872 Walker’s Map. 1873 .. Advance of Russia into the Turcoman territory, and capture of Akhal, Kizzil-arvad, Barnee (or Barn), Berma (or Borrma), and Xaree-Kala . Karee-Kala said to be the boundary between the Tekka country and Khorassan .. Official arrangement said to have been made between Persia and Russia to the effect that “ the Attrek Waters up to Balkhan were to be with Russia ” Erection by the Russians of a Fort at Chikishlar on the Attrek Persian claim limited to the southern bank of the Attrek Claim of Khan of Khiva to allegiance of Tribes to the north of the Attrek as far as the Caspian.. .. .. .. .. •• •• •• • • Uneasiness of Persia at Russian movements. Persian Government informed of understanding between Great Britain and Russia in 1834 respecting Independence and Integrity of Persia .. Understanding of 1834 also appealed to by Russia .. .. .. . •• Territory between the Attrek and the Goorgaun Rivers considered by Russia to belong to the Turkoman Tribes.. .. .. .. •• Attrek Boundary again recognized by Russia in March 1873 .. Persia only recognizes the Attrek as the frontier between Persia and Russia on the Caspian 10, Russian Map of Central Asia reissued with colouring of boundary on the Attrek extended, March 1873. Comments of Sir Henry Rawlinson thereon Russian views with regard to the boundary of the Attrek on the Turkoman Steppe Suggestion made by Mr. R. Thomson to adopt 40° of north latitude as the Boundary Line ; not adopted Persian views explained to Prince Gortchakoff by Persian Grand Vizier at St. Petersburg, May 1873 Russian march on Khiva by way of the Attrek .. •• •• Refusal of Russian officials to allow Persians to visit districts lying between the Goorgaun and the Attrek Strategic importance of these districts to Russia .. •• •• •• [ 71 ] 3,4 12 /&gt;,mhhbh IV table of contents. Page M , Thomson's vie« with regard to Russian designs on Karee Ka.a and other points in the Attrek Valley Rumoured designs of Russia on Merve Views of the Shah as to the Attrek Boundary Treaty between Russia and Khiva, 24th August, 1873 •• ’' * , AttrVk Declaration made by the Persian Grand Viaier to Prince Gortchakow as to the At.rek The Persian 'Government become'alive to'the dangers with which they are surrounded by Russian encroachments. Memorandum of Malcolm Khan •• ** ’ * Attrek Boundary Question enters upon another phase. Question of Boundary along the Sources of that River .. • • • * * . * * .V, ol Persia prepared to act in concert with Russia on the Bine of the Attrek and the Akhal _• Russian Regulation of 2ist March, 1874, respecting the Trans-Casp.an Regton. Boundary .• • • * * * * * * Circular of General Lamakin to Chiefs of Attrek and GoorgannTnbes.. •• Alarm of Persia at hearing of this Circular or Proclamation. Appeal to England.. Proceedings of General Lamakin . Friendly reception of General Lamakin by the people south of the Attrek • ’ '' Description of an interview between the General and the Djafarba, and Ataba, people camping between the Attrek and the Goorgaun .. Their appeal for Russian protection . •• •• •' *' Removal of 30,000 Khivan Goklans from Khiva to Upper Waters of the Attrek and Goorgaun Rivers, June 1874 .. *• •* ** ** Rumoured visit of Russian General Lamakin to the Attrek and Goorgaun Rivers Explanation of the Russian Government as to General Lamakin’s visit to Ashurade .. Reported landing of General Lamakin with Troops at Shah-Kadem. His Circular to Toorkoman Chiefs.. .. • • • • • * ” Dissatisfaction of the Persian Government at General Lamakin’s proceedings .. General Lamakin appointed Governor over Toorkoman Tribes of the Attrek and Goorgann . Strategic importance of District of Merve in connection with Routes leading through Attrek and Goorgaun Valleys .. • • • • • * ’*,«,**, * V Captain Napier sent from Tehran to Khorassan, with orders to return to Tehran by way o the Attrek and the Goorgaun Captain Napier’s Report of his Journey. Submission of Yemoot Tribe to Russia .. .. Claim of Yemoots to shores of the Attrek 50 miles from its mouth admitted by Persia. Consequent gain to Russia .. • • • • • • * * * * Secret Protocol signed at St. Petersburgh, 8 t h August, 1874, and affirmed by the Emperor, 25th August, 1874. Territory between Khiva and the Attrek considered as annexed to Intention™ Russia to'occupy Baiat-Hodji-Olum. Proposed re-establishment of Fort of Tchikishlar .. .. •• ** ** ** ” * Importance of the position of Karee-Kala .. Proceedings of the Goklan Turcomans at Karee-Kala Advance of Russia on Karee-Kala ; and proposal of Persia to protest against her^proceedmgs British Government refuse to support protest of Persia if made Views of Her Majesty’s Government on Russian proceedings, January 8, 1875 .. Memorandum by Sir H. Rawlinson on the Attrek Frontier, January 1875 Profession of Emperor of Russia of anxiety to maintain friendly relations with England Determination of Emperor of Russia not to extend his frontiers in Central Asia or on the Attrek, April 1875 Reply of Her Majesty’s Government to Russian assurances .. Russian designs on the mainland of Persia opposite to Ashurada Steps taken by Russia to erect a fort at Bayat-Hajee, on the Attrek .. Proposal of the Grand Duke Michael to undertake a fresh expedition between the Balkan Mountains and the Attrek .. 16 17 19 20 20 21 21 21 22 22 22 23 24 24 25 26, 32 26 26 26 27 27 28 30 30 31 32 32 33General Laniakin undertakes a scientific and military expedition to explore the ancient bed of the Amu Daria, July 1875 .. .. .. .. He attacks the Akhal Tekhe tribe, who submit Proposal of Captain Napier to go to Karee-Kala, it being rumoured that General Lamakin was about to proceed thitlier Lord Derby and Lord Salisbury disapprove of Captain Napier’s proposed visit to Karee- •• •• •• •• •• •• Extracts from Captain Napier’s journal respecting Karee-Kala Persian claim to that fort .. .. .. ## Views of Sir H. Rawlinson on the point The Grand Duke Michael proposes that another expedition to the Attrek should be under taken ; but forbidden by the Emperor, April 1876 Kiepert's Map of Turkestan, 1876 Resume 34 34 34 34 34 36 36 37 38 38Printed for the use of the Foreign Officf. September 1877. CONFIDENTIAL. Memorandum on the Attrek, or Northern, Frontier of Persia. Geographical Magazine October 1874, p. 27‘2. Geographical Magazine October 1876, p. 274. Goldsmith’s Eastern Persia.” Khanikoff’s Travels.” Marco Polo.” By Colonel Yule. Vol. i, p. 9. Hee’s Cyclopiedia.’ Hayton’s Central Asia.' Penny Cyclopaedia,” i850; Persia. THE boundary between Persia and Turkestan has never been clearly defined ; and the conse quence has been that nearly all the unofficial published maps have traced the boundary in different directions; some have placed it above the River Attrek, some below it, whilst others have marked the course of that river as forming the northern boundary of Persia near the Caspian Sea. To make the following narrative intelligible, it will be necessary to insert a few outline maps in order to show how geographers have differed in this respect. In 1834, Arrowsmith published a map to illustrate Lieutenant Burnes’ travels in Persia, &amp;c., and he placed the boundary of Persia to the north of the River Attrek. The following is a sketch of a portion of his map:— Arrows* ith's Map, 1834. / - *7 * .V _ ) * 'v 1 ^ ^K \ / Ux • ASTHAB AO ;\&gt; ^ ^ \ K ^ M’ je’ In 1841 a map was published at Berlin, by C. Zimmermann, in which the boundary between Persia and Turkestan was drawn also as running [71] Bsome distance above the Attrek, as will be seen from the following sketch :— Zimmerman n's Map Berlin 1841. d’Asie,” published about 1750. In 1863 Murray published a map to illustrate Vambdry’s travels in Persia, &amp;c., when he gave the Attrek and Goorgaun Rivers to the Turkomans, and marked the Kara-Su as forming the northern boundary of Persia near the Caspian. The following is an extract from his map, which would appear to have been taken from “Delille’s Carte d’Asie, 1723,” and from “ Kinneir’s Persian Geography, 1813”:— Vamberv’s Map 1863. But the Persians say the districts lying between the Attrek and the Goorgaun Rivers have belonged to them for upwards of 1,000 years.'i &gt; '• Confidential Memorandum, No. 2150. Mr. Thomson, No. 21; February 7, 1870. Mr. Dickson, No. 13; Mav 18, 1872. Lord A. Loftus, No. 52, February 5, 1873; No. 211, May 27, 1873. Mr. Thomson, No. 30 ; March 26, 1873. 3 The result of this state of uncertainty as to the actual boundary has been that disputes have continually arisen between the Persians and Turco mans upon the subject, and have, during the last thirty-five years, been taken up by the Russians. It will be remembered that in 1842 the Russians took possession of the Island of Ashoorada in Asterabad Bay ; but as a special Mem &gt;randum has been prepared upon that subject, and an agreement was ultimately arrived at, it is unnecessary to describe here all that passed between 1842 and 1869. In December 1869 an understanding was come to between the Russians and the Persians respecting the Attrek Boundary. In that year the Persian Ministers wrote to the Governor of Asterabad to say that the Russians were not to cross the Attrek, which was six fursukhs distant from the Goorgaun River and Ak-Kaleh, and that they were at liberty to build whatever they liked on the other side of the Attrek, but not on the Persian side. In March 1872, the British Agent at Asterabad also wrote a Report to Mr. Dickson at Tehran, in which he said “ The Governor (of Asterabad) has been instructed from Tehran that the Attrek is to be the frontier between the Russians and Persians, and should the Turkomans make any raids in the Asteiabad Province, the Russians are to punish them ; on the other hand, should they annoy the Russian camp, the Persians are to punish them.’ And it was added, that since the tribes who were stationed on and near the Attrek had heard of this arrangement, they had become very quiet and peaceful, but Mr. Dickson was of opinion that this was simply another version of the arrangement made in 1869, which it no doubt was. It will, however, be evident, from what is stated hereafter, that this arrangement could only have had reference to the territory bordering on the Caspian Sea. In January 1873 certain articles appeared in the English press, and more especially in the “ Morning Post,” commenting on the Russian Expedition against Khiva, and on the affairs of Central Asia, in which it was stated that a SecretR. Mr. Thomson, No. 10; January 29, 1873. Treaty existed between Persia and Russia, by which the former ceded to the latter the Valley of the Attrek. It was officially denied by the Persian Minister To Lord A Loftus, No. 23; . * , . . January 29, 1873. m London that any such Secret treaty existed ; but the Persian Prime Minister informed Mr. Thomson that in 186D, when the Russians were about to occupy Krasnovodsk on the Caspian, an official declaration had been made by the Russian Minister at Tehran to the effect that the sovereign right of Persia to the territory extending as far as the Attrek was recognized by the Russian Govern ment ; and two years later Mr. Thomson succeeded in obtaining a copy of the autograph Memorandum of the Shah upon the subject, a translation from which he forwarded home, and in this Memorandum Dr. Jenet, January 27, 1875. the Shah stated that for the last 1,000 years the Yemoot Turkomans had been subjects of the Shah of Persia. The following is a copy of the Agreement of Inclosure in Mr. Thomson’s No. 10 13th December, 1869;— of January 29, 1873. “His Majesty the Shah having on the 12th Agreement of December 13,1869. instant (December 4) requested the Undersigned, Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary of His Majesty the Emperor, to explain for what object the fort at Kizil Soo (Krasnovodsk) was being constructed, and having also required an assurance that the Russian Authorities would in no way interfere in the affairs of the Yemoot Turkomans, and of those living on the Attrek and Goorgaun rivers; also, that no fort or stronghold should hereafter be built at the embouchures of the Attrek or Goorgaun rivers; and likewise that they should not interfere in any way with the possessions of Persia, but that the Persian Govern ment should continue to maintain the authority they have hitherto held in respect to these tribes and their territories, in accordance with the wish expressed by His Majesty the Shah, the Under signed lost no time in referring by telegraph to the Ministry of Foreign Affairs of His Majesty the Emperor, and he has now the pleasure to bring to the knowledge of the Ministers of His Majesty the Shah the reply which he has just received, to the effect that the Government of His Majesty the Emperor recognizes the authority and sovereigntyof Persia up to the banks of the Attrek River, and that they have no intention to construct any Fort* There existed at this time a map which had been published by the Russian Asiatic Society, and upon it the River Attrek was marked as is shown on the following sketch. The Russians at that time made no claim to any portion of the shores of the Caspian Sea between Krasnovodsk and the Attrek, and it will be observed that the northern boundary of Persia only is coloured. It should also be observed that in this map a portion, and not the w T hole, of the tributary streams of the Attrek are given to Persia. Johnstone’s map, published in 1846, traces the boundary line very much in the same direction as the above. On the 5th February, 1873, Lord A. Loftus reported that he had had an interview with M. de Stremoouchow, the Director of the Asiatic Depart ment in the Russian Foreign Office, respecting this supposed Secret Treaty, and that M. de Stremoouchow had also denied that any such engagement existed, supporting this denial by reminding Lord Augustus that an agreement (“ un accord ”) had been come to some years previously between England and Russia, by which both countries had agreed to respect the integrity of the Persian territory. Lord A. Loftus stated, however, that M. de Stremoouchow’ had informed him that, in 1865 [? 1869], the Russian Government, with a view to (Signed) “ M. Beoer.” Russian Map 1863facilitate the suppression of brigandage and piracy on the part of the nomad tribes frequenting the shores of the Caspian, had proposed to the Persian Govern ment to make the Attrek river the boundary of Persia, in lieu of another small river (the Koja-Su)* which was more to the south of the Attrek, and which had hitherto been the recognized frontier; and that, consequently, the Persian territoiy was increased rather than diminished; or, as his Lord- ship observed to M. de Stremoouchow, that Russia had by this arrangement disposed of a strip of land in favour of Persia which virtually did not belong to her. Arrowsmith’s Map 1872 . Lord A. Loftus further stated that he had been informed that this arrangement was recorded in an official communication addressed to the Persian Government without any instrument of a bilateral nature; and that it was agreed that the two Governments should mutually assist each other in the suppression of the forages of the nomad tribes, and that for this purpose, at the corner of the Caspian Sea, north of the Attrek, a small Russian encampment (said not to be a fort in the usual signification of the term) was established solely for the purpose of watching the nomad tribes and of protecting the Croats. This afterwards proved to be Chikishlar. With regard to the Goorgaun boundary, Mr. R. Thompson also reported that Persia had always asserted, and at times had established, their authority over the territory lying between the Goorgaun and the Attrek ; and that although they had not occu-Mr. R. Thomson, No. 100; December 28, 1872. (Received February 16, 1873.) pied in recent times the lands on the right bank of the latter river, the tribes on the left bank which professed allegiance to the Shah migrated from the lands on the left to those on the right bank for pastoral purposes. Just about this same time news reached Her Majesty’s Government that a Russian force had been sent from the Caspian into the Turkoman territory, and that it had captured Akhal, which was described as a “ place ” situated on the Attrek river, about three miles to the north of the Persian town of Boudjnourd, but which is marked as a district on Walker’s map, as will be seen from the following sketch:— Walker's Turkestan, 1873. (REDUCED kill kJuijti yeftA »Astraba Inclosure 2 in above. Inclosure 3 in above. The announcement of this capture was made to the Prince Governor (of Khorassan) by letters from the Governor of Khabushan and the Chiefs of the Turkomans of Karee-Kala, and it was stated in a letter from the British Agent at Meshed, to Mr. Thomson, that the places taken from the Akhales by the Russians, were Kizzil-Arvad, Barnee,* and Berma.f It was also stated in the letters from the Meshed Agent that the Russians were converting Karee-Kala into a stronghold ; and that the capture of Akhal had caused great consternation amongst the high classes of Meshed, who were constantly saying that it was only five stages from Akhal to the beginning of the Ab-i-Tijjen, and that, therefore, the Russians would soon take Herat. * Barn, Barnee, or Barni. f Boorrna or Beurma.■ „ ■ • •; **../.;; ;■ \ M-v'^ • The fort of Kizzil-Arvad was stated by the Asterabad Agent to be two stages distant from Karee-Kala, which, he said, was the boundary between the Tekka country and Khorassan. In a subsequent letter the Agent stated that Kizzil- Arvad had been vacated by the Russians, who had encamped at Chikishlar, on the shoies of the Caspian, four fursukhs from the embouchure of the Attrek river j and he added that he had been informed that an official arrangement existed between Persia and Russia, by which it was agreed that “from the Attrek waters up to Balkhan [to the north, toward Krasnovodsk] was to he with Russia. v Shortly after this, it was rumoured that the Russians possessed a fort on the Attrek; and on the 6th February, 1873, Consul-General Abbott, then of Odessa (but late Consul-General atTabreez), reported that he had learned from pretty good authority that such a fort really did exist, at a short distance from the mouth of the stream, and on its right, or north bank; and it was subsequently ascertained that a fort had really been erected by the Russians at Chikishlar. Mr. Abbott added, in this report, that “ Persia laid claim to the country only up to the southern bank of the Attrek, and that Russia, therefore, in taking possession of a spot on the northern bank of that stream, had seemingly infringed rather on the rights of Khiva than on those of Persia, as the former State claimed the allegiance of all the tribes lying between it and the Caspian, who were not actually under Persian dominion. v On the 27th February the Persian Minister in London called upon Lord Granville, and alter informing his Lordship that his Government were becominir uneasy at the tone taken by the press on the subject of the Central Asian question, inquired whether the time had not come for recog nizing the integrity of Persia as well as that ol Afghanistan : when he was informed of the under- standing which had been come to between England and Russia in 1834 upon the subject of the independence and integrity ol Persia. At a subsequent interview which Lord A. Loftus had with M. Stremoouchow, Director of the Asiatic Department in the Russian Foreign Office, his Mr. It. Thomson, No. 106; December 31, 187‘2. (Received tebruary 10, 1873.) Inclosure 2 in above. Mr. R. Thomson, No. 3; January 24, 1873. Inclosure 1 in above. Mr. Thomson, No. 3 ; February 24, 1873. Mr. Abbott, No. 7; February 6, 1873. To Mr. It. Thomson, No. 20 ; February 27, 1873: Confidential Paper No. 213G. Lord A. Loftus, No. 92; March 5, 1873.4 . Lord A. Loftus, No. 9‘i, March 5, 1873. Lord A. Loftus, No. 147; April 15, 1873. Lord A. Loftus, No. 150; April 16, 1873. Lord A. Loftus, No. 157 ; April 23, 1873. Mr. Thomson, No. 30; March 26, 1873. 9 Lordship inquired the date and the circumstances under which the River Attrek was declared to be the northern frontier of Persia, when his Excellency repeated what he had stated on a previous occasion,* that, in 1865 [? 1869], the Russian Government had suggested to that ot Persia to transfer the frontier from the Koja-su River (between the Attrek and the Goorgaun, which had hitherto been considered as the boundary) to the Attrek, with a view to establish a definite demarcation of the Persian territory ; but he denied that any Treaty or written engagement had been entered into between the two Govern ments, or that any Firman had been issued by the Government of the Shah on the subject; and M. de Stremoouchow remarked that the territory referred to was a wild, uncultivated, uninhabited steppe, and, in reality, had no other proprietor than the nomad lawless tribes of Turkomans. M. de Stremoouchow then placed in Lord A. Loftus’ hands, confidentially, a memoir which he had prepared, giving an historical analysis of the circumstances which had led to an understandinsr O between England and Russia in respect to the affairs of Persia in 1834, and Lord A. Loftus remarked, that from this statement it would appear that the change of the frontier line referred to gave an increase, and not a diminution, of territory to Persia. M. de Stremoouchow 7 at the same time disclaimed any intention on the part of the Imperial Government of encroaching on the Persian territory, reminding Lord Augustus of the understanding come to between Great Britain and Russia in 1834, and con firmed by Lord Palmerston in 1838, to respect the integrity of the Shah’s dominions; and he expressed some annoyance at the tone of the English Press, implying a continued distrust and suspicion of Russian designs. Nevertheless, on the 10th March following, a Russian detachment crossed the Attrek and attacked the Yamoud Turkomans within eight miles of Asterabad ; and on an explanation being demanded'by Persia, the Russian Government replied that the act was one of necessity, as the frontier w T as left unguarded by Persia, but that it 171 ] # \ * See page 5. D* Page 4. was not an act of aggression, and that the Imperial Government fully recognized the Attrek as the frontier between Russia and Persia. The Russian Government thought that the Persian note was written at the instigation of the British Government, and felt some uneasiness in consequence. The Russian Minister declared that he had informed the Persian Government beforehand of their intention to undertake such an expedition; but this was positively denied by the Persian Prime Minister, who assured Mr. R. Thomson that, on the contrary, on the occasion referred to, he had repeated the protest already made against an armed Russian force entering the.Persian territory on any pretext whatever; and his Excellency showed Mr. Thomson the letter in which he had also re monstrated against the movements of the Russian reconnoitring expedition, sent in the autumn of 1872, along the right bank of the Attrek, to Karee- Kala, and the districts lying to the north of Bouij- noord. Mr. Thomson also reported that the Persian Government considered that the declaration made by Russia on the 13th December, 1869,* had no reference to the territory in the interior towards Khoiassan, but regarded only the territory adjoining the Province of Asterabad, that is to say, from the Caspian Sea, at the mouth of the Attrek, along the banks of that river for about thirty miles, to where the Georgian district ended; but that, although this had been clearly explained by the Sadr Azim to the Russian Minister, he avoided a discussion of the question. It may here be as well to draw attention to the fact that up to this date the discussions which had passed between Persia and Russia had chiefly Mr. Thomson, No. 30 ; March 26, 1873. reference to the boundary of that portion only of the Persian territory which abutted on the Caspian Sea. But about this time an understanding was come to between Lord Granville and Count Schouvaloff respecting the boundary of Affghanistati, &amp;c., and almost immediately afterwards, that is to say, in March 1873, a revised edition was issued of the Map of Central Asia, which had been publishedin 1863 by the Russian Asiatic Society, and upon it was shown, for the first time, the Russian boundary as joining the Persian, and extending along the north bank of the Attrek, from its mouth to a very con siderable, but undefined, distance inland, and leaving Karee-Kala far without the Persian boundary. Russian Map 1873. Sir Henry Rawlinson drew the special attention of the India Office to this Russian Map, wherein the colouring had been altered in many directions from the previous Map; and with regard to the Attrek boundary, he said:— “ The Russian frontier is laid down from the embouchure of the Attrek in the Caspian along the main stream of the river for about 200 miles, or as far as the meridian of Bujnoord, but Persia certainly claims all the valleys through which flow the right hand affluents of the Attrek, these valleys indeed being inhabited by the Kurdish colonists who were placed there by Shah Abbas to guard the Khorassan frontier against the inroads of the Turkomans. Persia claims as her frontier in this quarter—1st, the line of the Attrek to the junction of the Sum- bar ; 2ndly, the course of that river to its source in the Kuren-dagh; and 3rdly, the watershed dividing the streams which flow into the Attrek from the running north-west towards the Turkoman desert, and watering the lands of the Tekehs at the base of the hills. It is interesting to observe from this map that the Russians appear to have surveyed a line of route along the northern slopes of these hills from the vicinitv of the Caspian to Merve,Lord A. Loftus, No. 213 ; May 27, 1873. Lord A. Loftus, No. 226; May 28, 1873. “ Le Cabinet Imperial devrait pouvoir compter sur un loyal concours de la part du Gouvernement Persan.” ^ In Ma Y following, the Shah of Persia visited St. Petersburg, accompanied by the Grand Vizier and others, and in a conversation which Lord A. Loftus had with the Grand Vizier, his Highness informed his Lordship that he had had an interview with Prince Gortchakow, and that, in referring to the frontier of the Attrek, he had told the Prince that a short time previously a report had been circu lated of a secret Treaty existing between Persia and Russia, by which the Persian Government had given up the line ot the Attrek to Russia; and that he had, therefore, instructed the Persian Representative in London to give a formal denial to this report, as no such Treaty existed: and he added that he had declared most positively and categorically to Prince Gortchakow that Persia had only agreed to the mouth of the Attrek as the frontier on the coast of the Caspian, but that it did not include the whole course of the Attrek to its source, which would have amounted to an abandon ment of Persian territory; but to this remark Prince Gortchakow made no reply, either in the affirmative or in the negative. Subsequently, Lord A. Loftus had an interview with Malcolm Khan, being anxious to ascertain what had taken place on political subjects between the Persian Minister and the Imperial Govern ment ; but his Lordship stated that he could not learn from his Highness that any positive pro posals had been made in regard to the frontier of the Attrek. He expressed his belief, however, that when the Shah had quitted Russian territory, it would be found that the Russian Government had strained every nerve to obtain the Shah’s assent to - the whole course of the Attrek as the frontier, and the withdrawal of the Concession to Baron Reuter. At another interview, the Sadr Azem told Lord Augustus that the Persian Government had not recognized the Attrek as the frontier of Persia, but only as the frontier of the Caspian; and he assured his Lordship that his Government had no intention of giving up that portion of the Attrek valley which had always formed part of the Persian territory. [71] E• See page 8. In reporting this conversation, Lord Augustus remarked that Russia claimed the whole course of the Attrek On the 30th June, Houssein Khan again Peyian Grand V-er ; inquired of Lord Granville what formal under standing existed between Great Britain and Russia for the maintenance of the integrity of Persia, when he was again informed of what had passed in 1834 and 1838;* at which he expressed his satisfaction. The Russian movements towards Khiva were still watched with much anxiety, and their pro ceedings on the Attrek frontier in the interior were fully reported on by the British Agent at Meshed, who stated that, on the 3rd April, 1873, he had paid a visit to the Governor of Boojnoord, and inquired after the Russian movements in Akhal, , 1 , 1 ,on the Governor had informed him that, in the Mr. W. Thomson, No. 28; May 2, 1873. previous November, 4,000 Russian troops went to Kizzil Arvad and Karee Kala and dispersed the Turkomans who were stationary at those places, and that after remaining twelve days they went away, but returned at the latter part of February, 1873.. The Agent then inquired why they had gone’by the Arkal ; to which the Governor replied that three stages on the other road to Khiva the mud was so deep that no horse or guns could pass over, and they were therefore obliged to go to Akhal, and march on Khiva by Kizzil Arvad A few days later, the Agent had another inter- view with the Governor, who told him that he had received letters from Boojnoord, stating that a body of more than 4,000 Russian horse had advanced to within twenty fursukhs of Boojnoord, where there was a lofty mountain, and that they had set up a mark thereon; that they then took a number of Turkomans as guides ; captured a number of the Yemoot and Gooklan Turkomans ; and seized some of the Gooklans who paid revenue to the Persian Crown. Mr. w. Thomson, No. 28; Upon this Report Mr. W. Thomson observed that May 2, 1873. although the Governor of Boojnoord (Yar Mahomed Khan) had just received investiture from the Shah as Governor of that important district, he did not hesitate to express the most amicable sentimentsMr. VV. Thomson, No. 69 ; June 20, 1873. Mr. W. Thomson, No. 81; July 19, 1873. Mr. W. Thomson, No. 99; August 16, 1873. Lord A. Loftus, No. 442, Most Secret; December 8, 1874. for the Russian General who had twice taken armed possession of the Persian territory in his immediate neighbourhood; and here it may be ob served that, when Colonel Baker, Captain Clayton, and Lieutenant Gill visited that neighbourhood in June 1873, they inquired of the Russian Consul at Asterabad whether a Persian escort and guides could be procured for the district lying between the Goor- gaun and the left bank of the Attrek, when they were told that if the Persians attempted to cross that district, it would be his (the Russian Consul’s) duty to prevent them, and that if found within it they would be taken prisoners. In the following month Mr. Thomson pointed out to the Persian Government that Krasnovodsk to the north, and Ashourada, in the Bay of Astera bad, to the south, were all that were required by Russia on the coast, but that Karee Kala, in the valley of the Attrek, and other po/ts in the upper portion of it, would not fail in due time to be occupied by the Russians. He also pointed out how in reality the excuse for the occupation of the Attrek, as a part of the military operations against Khiva, was a mere pretext j that Khiva, if captured, must be captured from the side of the Aral and Rivers Jihoon and Sihoon, of which the proof existed in the fact of MarcosofF’s reconnais sance in 1872, and of his having returned without having afforded the slightest aid to the columns really acting against Khiva; that the real object in gaining a footing on the Attrek was to enable the Russian troops in the first place, and Cossack colonists later, to act against the Turkomans, with whom, at the shortest warning, they could be, as best suited them, in a position to act offensively, not only throughout the whole length of the valley of the Attrek, but to follow them up, as need might be, across the plains of Surrukhs and Merve to the banks of the Oxus, and under the same pretext, if it should suit them, to parts of the Afghan territory, in which there was a joint occu pation of Turkoman and Afghan tribes. Mr. Thomson then assured Lord Granville that it seemed to him desirable that a declaration should be obtained from Russia, as early as possible, as to the meaning she attached to the statement, that she recognized the valley of the Attrek as her line offrontier with Persia; and in a subsequent despatch he informed his Lordship that in 1866 the Shah made a journey to the province of Khorassan, when His Majesty kept a journal, in which the following entry was made:—“ The River Battrek [sicj, which flows by Koochan, has its source on the north of the Deregez mountain. On its passing Koochan and entering the province of Boojnoord, it is called Soum Bar, and when it reaches Goor- gaun it is named the Attrek.” But this statement is both vague and unintelligible. Mr. Thomson then pointed out how the portion of territory lying between the Attrek and Goorgaun, as an aggressive strategical position, was of the utmost value to Russia. Mr. Thomson, No. 99; August 16, 1873. Shortly after this it was rumoured that the India Office ; J . , .... , October 15, 1873. Russians were assuming a threatening attitude towards the tribes of Merve, and a correspondence passed upon the subject; but it would extend this paper to an inconvenient length if an attempt were made either to describe the various events which have transpired with regard to Merve, which bear upon the general question of the northern frontier of Afghanistan, or to the Khiva expedition, and it has been thought advisable, therefore, to restrict this Memorandum to the simple question of the Attrek frontier. In November 1872 a Russian expedition was Lo ^ A * f oftu *’ 41 . November 22, 1873. undertaken against Khiva, and on the 24th August, 1873, a Treaty of Peace was signed between Russia and Khiva, wherein the boundary between the Russian and Khivan territories were thus defined:— The boundary between the Russian and Khivan territories shall be the Amu Daria from Kukertli down the river as far as the point at which the most westerly branch of the Amu Daria leaves the main stream, and from that point the frontier shall pass along such branch as far as its mouth in the Aral Sea. Farther, the frontier shall extend along the sea coast to Cape Urgu, and from thence along the base of the chink (escarpment) of the Ost-Ort, fol lowing the so-called ancient bed of the Amu Daria. On the 24th October, 1873, Sir Joseph Dickson, Mr. W. Thomson; Physician to the British Legation at Tehran, had 25 &gt; 1873 a confidential conversation with the ex-Grand Vizier on various points connected with Persianinterests, including those of Seistan, Merve, and the Attrek. With regard to the question of the Attrek, the ex-Grand Vizier said he was decidedly of opinion that there w r as every possibility for the Persian Government to get out of the dilemma caused by the Minister for Foreign Affairs; and that he had assured the Shah when in Russia that in two months after his return to Tehran he would settle that affair; for that whilst at St. Petersburg!], in the presence of the Shah and the Emperor, he had declared to Prince Gortchakow that the Persian Government only admitted “ to near the mouth of the river {Vembouchure), and not the line along its course.” But in sending home a copy of this memorandum Mr. Thomson pointed out that, with regard to the first statement, no indication was given of the manner in which the dilemma w’as to be overcome ; and in the second, that the declaration of the Persian Grand Vizier would appear to strengthen the pretensions of Russia to the Attrek line of frontier rather than to weaken them, n; The continued Russian movements in Turkestan now began greatly to alarm the Persian Govern ment, so much so, that on the 8th April, 1874, the Persian Minister in London, Malcolm Khan, communicated a Memorandum to the Earl of Derby in which he pointed out the dangers with which Persia w r as surrounded; and with reference to the Attrek, he said: “La perte de ces magnifiques provinces (Mazanderan et Ghilan), quelque mortelle qu’elle fut pour la Perse, ne pr&amp;enterait pas peut-dtre, &amp; certains esprits, une gravity assez immediate, pour prdoccuper des maintenant le Gouvernement Anglais. Mais ce Gouvernement pourrait-il garder une egale indif ference devant cette autre direction, si claire et si menagante, que prend la Russie, du cot6 de I’Atrak, a travers nos tribus Turconlanes, ayant pour objec tive inevitable Merve, fancienne capitale de Khoras- san. And again, “ Quant &amp; nous, nous sommes certains que le seul syst&amp;me des caravanes qu’on organise &amp; Moscou et au Caucase, avec les elements militaires, suffirait pour etablir paisiblement la domi nation Russe sur les deux rives de I’Atrak. Et alors que resterait-il aux Russes pour arriver a Merve?” J But at this very time it afterwards appeared that [71] FPersia had been renewing their proposals to the Russian Government for a concerted military action against the Turkomans in the neighbourhood of the Attrek. Early in 1874, Mr. Thomson reported that it was the intention of the Persian Government to form, in the spring of that year, a camp of 10,000 men at Cheh-Cheheh, a small fort then recently con structed between Korchan and Kelat-i-Nadir; and it was, at the same time, stated that the Russians would send a force against the Turkomans in that neighbourhood ; and Mr. Thomson, in one of his despatches, written about the same time, said, “ Persia appears to have become quite reconciled to acting in concert with Russia on the line of the Attrek and the Akhal, and such being the case, once Russia is established on that line, it is but reasonable to assume that her posts ot communi cation with the Caspian are intended to be pei“ manent ones.” But if any further doubt existed on this point, it was removed by the issue ot a Russian Imperial Regulation or Statute, on the 2 ut March, 1874, for the administration of the 4 rans-Caspian i egion, in which it was stated that the new territory would comprise Manghischlak and the country occupied by Russia on the eastern bank of the Caspian, around Kias- novodsk, extending from Mestry-Kouthouk ” up to the Attrek which formed the boundary between Russia and Persia,' or in other words that “ the Trans- Caspain region, which formed part of the Trans- Caspain military district, extended southward to the River Attrek and eastwards to the frontier of the Khanate of Khiva. But notwithstanding this notification, the then newdy-appointed Russian Governor of Krasnovodsk (Major-General Lamakin*) addressed to the Chiefs of the Attrek and Goorgun Turkoman tribes a Circular Letter or Proclamation informing them that he had been appointed by the Grand Duke Michael their Chief. As soon as the Persian Government became aware of this Proclamation, an explanation of it was demanded from the Russian Minister at Tehran, when he assured the Persian Government Mr. W. Thomson ; December 28, 1873. Mr. VV. Thomson, No. 40; February 20, 1874. Mr. W. Thomson, No. 50; February 28, 1874. Mr. W. Thomson, No. 51; March 1, 1874. Lord A. Loftus, No. 152; April 14, 1874. Lord A. Loftus, No. 156 ; April 15, 1874. Lord A. Loftus, No. 156 ; April 15, 1874. Mr. W. Thomson; May 19, 1874. To Mr. W, Thomson ; June 3, 1874. Lord A. Loftus, No. 412, Most Secret; November 11, 1874. * Llamakin, Lomaken, or Lamakine.III* / 19 w that “ there had been a mistake arising from there being two tribes of Yomouds, one near Khiva, another near the Caspian.” But as the Russian Governor had refused to admit that the Attrek formed the boundary of the two countries, but declared the frontier to be on the Karasso (Koja- Su ?)*, the Persian Minister in London called at the Foreign Office, and after explaining to Lord Derby his views of Russian designs, and calling attention to the fact that the Russian Governor had invited certain Turkoman Chiefs, who were Persian sub jects, to come to him, describing himself as Master ot the Attrek and the Goorgun, he asked for an assurance that England would help Persia in case of need; to which Lord Derby replied that the ques tion was too serious to be answered off-hand, more especially as it referred to a state of things which had not occurred, and possibly might never occur, but his Lordship expressed the friendly feelings which Her Majesty’s Government entertained to wards Persia, and his hope that the Persian Govern ment would on all occasions communicate frankly with that of Her Majesty. Ab Or; Confidential P™ 25^ ^ ^ ^ ^ “ miStake ” ^ ° CCU ™ d &gt; page 143 . as stated by the Russian Minister at Tehran, it afterwards transpired that Major-General Lamakin, while at Krasnovodsk, had received twenty elders of the Turkomans camping in the vicinity, whom he treated with the greatest kindness, endeavouring to inspire them with a perfect trust and confidence in the Russians, and that these elders thereupon promised to prevail upon all the leading men among the 1 rans-Caspian Yomoud Turkomans to present themselves to the General at Krasnovodsk in the spring of the year 1874. So that by this means, as well as by letters of invitation from Krasnovodsk to all the Yomouds, a large congregation of Turkomans (comprising upwards of seventy representatives) from various parts, as well as from the country between the Attrek and the Goorgun Rivers, assembled at Krasnovodsk in the spring. When they arrived, the elders represented that the Russian letters of invitation had produced a very favourable impression upon the people south of the Attrek; some of the Trans-Attrek elders going so * See page 9.20 far in their display of friendly feeling as to lay carpets along the pier when the General landed. The following is a description of the interview which took place:— After a great religious ceremony, General La- makin received the Turkoman elders, to whom he spoke in very assuring language, after acknow ledging their congratulations on his appointment as chief officer over the trans-Caspian region. His Government, he told them, had peaceful and friendly intentions which, with the demands that would be made upon the Turcomans, aimed ex clusively at the pacification of the steppes separating the Russians from their fresh acquisitions on the Oxus. Tranquillity and security in those steppes were, he said, indispensable for the maintenance of regular communication with the Russian troops in the new district on the Oxus. He pointed out that this condition of the steppes would prove to be a great benefit to the Turkomans, as they would then be able to pasture and multiply their flocks with out hindrance or fear; that trade would flourish among them, and the Turkomans would become prosperous and happy. To this the representatives of the Djafarbai and Atabai tribes,* numbering 15,000 tents, camping in the winter between the Attrek and the Goorgan, and in the summer in the Balkans and along the Uzboi (supposed ancient course of the Oxus) replied to the following effect:— After various congratulations in the name of their people, they stated to General Lamakin that they were fully assured that the Russians had established themselves for ever in the trans-Caspian region, that they could not oppose the Russians, that they them- selves had no other country to fall back upon, and were consequently convinced that it was only by an unconditional obedience to the Russians that their own happiness could be secured. They accordingly tendered their humble submission to the Russian Government, and prayed the Commander-in-chief of the Caucasus, the brother of the great Aga- Padishah, to accept their allegiance, and to take them under his merciful protection. It was subsequently repoited that about 30,000 Mr. R. Michell’s Memorandum; tents of Khivan Goklans had removed from Khiva June 19, l874 ' * See large Map facing page 1.,z 7 21 Lord A. Loftus, No, 217 ; June 24, 1874. Lord A. Loftus, No. 217 ; June 24, 1874. Lord A. Loftus, No. 210; June 23, 1874. Mr. W. Thomson, No. 130 June 19, 1874. to the upper waters of the Attrek and Goorgan Rivers. On the 16th June following, a telegram appeared in the “Times,” from Berlin, stating that Colonel Lamakin, the Governor of the new military district of the Caspian, had just visited the Attrek, and that between the Attrek and Goorgan Rivers he was met by the principal elders of the Yomoud Turkomans, who declared that their whole tribe considered themselves the subjects of the Czar, and were prepared to carry out his commands ; upon which, it was stated, Colonel Lamakin desired all the elders of the tribes to meet him towards the end of June on the Silver Hills. Lord A. Loftus took an opportunity of asking M. de Stremoouchow what truth there was in this statement, and he replied that, as far as he was informed, the General’s statement was true, but there were several inaccuracies which he was anxious to correct, and which he stated were as follows: — 1st. The General had not visited the Attrek, or met the Chiefs of the tribes between the Attrek and the Goorgun, but had received them at Ashurade,* where the Russians had a navalstation. 2 nd. That there was no expression of submission of the tribes to the Czar, nor any reference made by the General to their subjection to Russia. 3rd. That there was no promise exacted or given by the Teke Turkomans of allegiance to Russia (as was also stated in the telegram in the “ Times M. de Stremoouchow also assured Lord Augustus, at another interview, that General Lamakin had only addressed letters to the Chiefs of the Turkoman tribes who inhabited the country between Khiva and the Caspian, as well as to those who periodically visited the districts south of the Attrek and extended their wanderings as far north as Krasnovodsk, expressing a wish to be on friendly terms with them, and a hope that they would abstain from acts of disorder or destruction to the commerce of the steppes. But, notwithstanding this assurance, the Astera- bad Agent reported to Mr. Thomson, on the 30th * See la r ge Map facing page l.May, 1874, that the Russian General had recently landed with a number of soldiers at a place called Shah Kadem, which was 8 stages distant trom Asterabad, and had encamped there; that he had addressed a Circular to the Chiefs of the different tribes of the Yomoud Turkomans, saying that, from the Jerjan (Goorguri), which was 3 fursakhs distant from Asterabad, as far as Khiva belonged to Russia; that, therefore, each tribe must send several persons to him that he might arrange matters with them, as, in future, Russian merchants and carriers would travel by this route ; and that arrangements ought to be made for their safety. The Turkomans, it would appear, took this letter to the Governor-General of Asterabad, who referred the matter to Tehran, from whence he received an answer stating that, from the other side of the Attreh which was 8 fursakhs distant from Asterabad, was Russian territory, but that the Russians had no right to interfere with such tribes as resided on the banks of the Goorgun. The Governor-General, however, was instructed not to stir up matters, but to see what course events would take ; but subsequently the Governor-General received another telegram from Tehran, instructing him to proceed with troops to Akkaleh and sympathize with the Turkomans, assuring them that the Russian Government had nothing to do with them. General Lamakin endeavoured to persuade the Mr. W. Thomson, No. 137; Governor-General and other Persian authorities at June 30, 1874, Asterabad that they had greatly exaggerated the scope and purpose of his letters to the Turkoman Chiefs, and stated that his intention was simply to give them good advice, with a view to the preserva tion of peace and tranquillity on the frontier, but his language failed to produce any impression either at Asterabad or Tehran, his announcement having India office; been so explicit that he was appointed by the Grand October 2 , 1874. Duke Michael, under order of the Emperor, to be Supreme Commander (Sahib Jkhtiar) over the Tur koman tribes of the Attrek and Goorgun. Mr. Thomson again drew attention at this time Mr. W. Thomson, No. 136; to the great importance of the district of Merve, in a strategic point of view, in connection with the routes leading from the south-eastern corner of the Caspian through the valleys of the Attrek and Goorgun, and having in view how powerful these June 25, 1874.To Lord A. Loftus, No. 333 ; November 6, 1874. Lord A. Loftus, No. 421; November 17, 1874. Mr. W. Thomson, No. 129; June 19, 1874. Mr. W. Thomson, No. 141 ; July 3, 1874. districts might become for aggressive purposes in the hands of Russia, should she be permitted to establish in them Cossack Turkoman Colonies. Lord A. Loftus was accordingly instructed to call the attention of the Russian Government to that portion of General Lamakin’s circular in which he styled himself Commander over the Turkoman tribes of the Attrek and the Goorgun, and to point out that the territory between the Attrek and the Goorgun was unquestionably Persian territory, in which General Lamakin would not be justified in interfering ; and he was told to express a hope on the part of Her Majesty’s Government that the Government of the Emperor would impress upon General Lamakin the expediency of abstaining from molesting the Turks who frequented the country to the south of the Attrek. Lord A. Loftus accordingly spoke to M. de Westmann on the subject, when he assured his Lordship that General Lamakin’s circular had been a malentendu, which had given rise to a correspondence between the Russian and Persian Governments, and that the explanations given by the Russian Government had been perfectly satisfactory to that of Persia. The claim thus set up by Russia over the Attrek Valley was considered so important, that it was suggested by the Government of India to Mr. Thom- son, that, with the view of obtaining trustworthy information on the subject, Captain the Honourable. George Napier (the officer deputed by the Govern ment of India to report on the circumstances attending the raid on Herat territory by the people of Khaff) should be entrusted to visit the province of Khorassan, returning to Tehran by way of the Attrek and the Goorgan. Mr. Thomson was of opinion that great advantage might be derived from such a visit, and he accordingly instructed Captain Napier to undertake the journey. After explaining to him verbally the state of affairs, as they then existed between the Russian and the Persian authorities on the north-eastern frontier, he pointed out that it was very desirable that he should, without com mitting himself to any expression of opinion, ascertain the feelings of the principal feudal chiefs, whether Persian or Turkoman, having possessions in the north-eastern portion of Khorassan, and thedistricts lying between Dereghez, Koochau, and the Caspian. rii XT On the 10th August following, Captain Napier 874 ^ arrived at Meshed, when he at once forwarded to Mr. Thomson a report of his proceedings up to that date. With reference to the Yemout Tribe, he said he had beard it reported that the Russian Governor (General Lamakin), to whom the Yemouts had submitted, bad made a claim to tax the Yemout settlers, or “Chomoors,” as well as the “Charwars, a nomadic portion of the tribe; the latter, he stated, had their camps along the shores of the Caspian, and therefore naturally fell under Russian influence; but that the former had been for many years connected with the Persian Go\ ernment, and cultivated lands on both banks of the Attiek for about fifty miles up its course. Their claim, though resisted by the Governor of Asterabad, to whom these settlers paid tribute, had been, it was said admitted by the Persian Government. Captain Kapier pointed out that, though the loss of such subjects ought to be rather a source of congratula tion, the concession gave to Russia a “ pied aterre south of the Attrek, or, in fact, command of that river for fifty miles of its course. On the 2nd September, it was announced in the “ Turkestan Russian Gazette” that the Yamut and and Tagah Turkomans, and the branches of the Atabai and Jafarbai clans residing to the east of the Caspian Sea, as well as the Tagah Turkomans of Merve, had come under the allegiance of the Russian Government, and it was subsequently reported to the Persian Government that the Chief of the Ak-Ata Bai Tribe had become a Russian protege, with 100 families, most of whom were his relatives, and that the usual^ passports had been granted to all of them ; it was, however, subsequently Mr&gt; Thomson, No. 29 ; reported that the Ata Bai Tribe had gone to their February 26. 18/4. Chief and tried to persuade him to withdraw form Russian protection, so that they might make a raid upon Astrabad and the Jaafer Bai Tribe in order to release their companions who were then under arrest. The rumour as to what had taken place w : as Lord K. Loftus, Most Secret and soon after confirmed by a despatch from Lord Confidential; October 12 ,1874.Hi •25 Lord A. Loftus, No. 377, Secret Augustus Loftus, in which his Lordship reported and Confidential; October 14, • , , , r , , 1874 . m a most secret and confidential despatch that a Protocol of a Conference had been held at St. Petersburgh on the 1874, on the affairs of Central Asia, at which were present the Grand Duke Constantine, the Grand Duke Michael, General Milintine (Minister of War), M. de West- mann (Acting Minister for Foreign Affairs), and Admiral Sesowsky (Acting Minister of Marine) ; and that the Resolutions then adopted were ap proved by the Emperor on the ^Jth August, and attested by his signature. This Secret Protocol threw a clear light on the intentions of Russia in regard to the Turkoman tribe and to the territory between Khiva and the Attrek, which Steppe was regarded as annexed to Russia as far as the Attrek. It also showed that the Russian Government was fully alive to the importance of occupying a strategic point on the Attrek, and that it was their intention to occupy provisionally, if not perma nently, a place at or near Baiat-Hodji-Olum (or Hajee Bayat),* situated at a distance of about 80 versts from the Caspian. The Russian Government were evidently anxious to avoid taking any steps which might give rise to complications with England or Persia ; and it was suggested at the Conference that the re-establish ment of the port at Tchikishlar might be effected more easily and with less notice, and would not appear in the light of an aggressive movement, such as the occupation of Baiat-Hodji-Olum would do, since the Emperor had expressed his desire that no offensive expedition should be undertaken during the year 1874. An announcement then appeared in the “ Moscow Gazette ” to the effect that three companies of infantry would be dispatched by sea to Tchikishlar, from whence they would proceed up the Attrek River as far as a locality called Hodji-Bayat-Olum (Baiat-Hodji-Olum or Bayat-Hajee), where they would remain till the following December to watch the movements of Turkomans. The position of the fort of Kara-Kala, or Karee- Kala, now began to attract attention. * See large Map facing page 1. Lord A. Loftus, No. 373 ; October 14, 1874. Mr. Thomson, No. 127; August 12, 1875. Mr. Thomson, No. 189 ; September io, 1874.Mr. Thomson had reported, in September 18 &lt;4, that certain Goklan Turkomans, who had emigrated from Khiva, had established a settlement at Kara- Kala, which he described as “ an important site before it was ruined, on the Persian side of the Attrek and in December following he reported that General Llamakin had reached the Attrek with 600 men and two guns, and that it was believed that he would occupy Kara-Kala. Mr. Thomson added that Persia was prepared to protest against the Russians occupying any post in the interior on the line of the Attrek, provided she received British support in the shape of employment of remonstrances similar to those addressed to Russia in favour of Afghanistan; and he suggested that such support might be given in favour of British interests, inasmuch as the occupation of any strategic point on the line of the Attrek meant the occupa tion, within a certain space of time, of Merve, and Mr. Thomson, Telegraphic; December 7 and 8, 1874. Mr. Thomson, Telegraphic; December 12, 1874. constant intrigues in Afghanistan. On being asked to point out the exact position of Kara-Kala, Mr. Thomson stated that it was to Mn Thomso^^No^ 40 the north of the Attrek; and he added that it was ug taken by the Persian troops in 1869, and that it had always been considered by Persia as belonging to her. Subsequently the Persian Government called upon the Goklan Turkomans to quit Karee-Kala, MrJhomso^N 0 . 8S; but they refused to do so. In this same month a Russian detachment, under Lord A. Lottus, No. 464; the command of General Lamakin, made a iccon- ^ Loftus, No. 466, Secret naissance of the countries bordering on the Attrek, December 23, 1874. which was even more successful than the Russians anticipated, as, not only was a suitable site found for the erection of a Fort, but the Turkomans of the Attrek, as well as the Tekk4-Turkomans, showed not only submission to, but an inclination to assist, the Russian troops. The following is an extract of the report of the Russian Minister of War upon the subject:— “ Les reconnaissances faites sur plusieurs points inclosure in above, ont montre que le meilleur endroit pour la con struction d’un Fort serait Douz-Oioun, point situe a une tr&amp;s petite distance de Boyat-Hodgi- Olum. “ Une forte position sur ce point nous permet-To India Office; December 28, 1874. India Office; December 30, 1874. To Mr. Thomson, No. ; January 8, 1875. trait de dominer le cours de TAtrek, et nous garantirait en ra^me temps les moyens de tenir en respect les peuplades barbares des Steppes Chiviens.” On receipt of the telegram from Mr. Thomson above referred to, with reference to the Russian advance on Karee-Kala on the right bank of the Simbar, the Indian Office was informed that Lord Derby was of opinion that it would be an unwise act on the part of Persia to protest against this move of Russia; that his Lordship proposed, with Lord Salisbury’s concurrence, to state this to Her Majesty’s Minister at Tehran, and to add that Her Majesty’s Government were not prepared to lend their support to any such protest. The India Office concurred in these proposed instructions to Her Majesty’s Minister at Tehran, with the alteration of a few words, and the instruc tions, as sent, ran as follows:— . f ‘ l have received your telegrams of the 7th, 8th, and 12th instant, respecting the advance of the Russians to Karee-Kala, and suggesting that Her Majesty’s Government should join with Persia in protesting against this step. “ Her Majesty’s Government cannot but regret any inroad of Russia into the territories of the Teke-Turkoman tribes as likely to give rise to frontier disputes with Persia on the one hand, and Afghanistan on the other, upon which a misunder standing between England and Russia might not impossibly ensue. “ With a view to prevent any such contingency, you are aware that Her Majesty’s Ambassador at St. Petersburgh was instructed in January last to point out to the Russian Government the danger of a Russian occupation of Merve. Satisfactory assurances were given by the Emperor and Prince Gortchakow to the effect that Russia had no intention of attacking the Turkomans, except in self-defence, and that she had no wish to occupy Merve. “ As regards the present advance of the Russians to Karee-Kala, Her Majesty’s Government fear that, in the present ill-defined state of the Persian frontier, Persia would not be justified in protestingagainst this act, and still less would Her Majesty’s Government have a right to interfere. u Her Majesty’s Government have, however, lately instructed Her Majesty’s Ambassador at St. Peters- bur&lt;di to call the attention of the Russian Govern- ment to that part of General Lamakin’s Circular in which he styles himself Governor over the territory lying between the Attrek and the Gurgun, and M. de Westmann assured Lord A. Loftus that the expression used by General Lamakin was purely accidental.” A Memorandum on the Attrek frontier was at In ^ the time prepared by Sir H. Rawlinson for the use of the India Office, and a copy of it was sent to this Office, from which it may be useful to quote the following extracts :— “ Memorandum on the Attrek Frontier. “There is no evidence to show that Persia has ever accepted the line of the Attrek as the northern frontier of Khorassan. What she has accepted, or • rather what has been forced upon her by Russia, is an admission that the Attrek is the boundary between Russian and Persian territory on the Caspian. But Russia has hitherto never claimed anything beyond a zone or margin extending along the Caspian coast, of uncertain limits, but not exceeding at most thirty or forty miles in width. All beyond that margin has been, and still is, regarded as indepen dent Turcoman steppe; and it was in reference to this particular tract of country that the Persian Government, in December 1869, at the same time that it acquiesced in the adoption of the Attrek as the frontier line on the sea coast, invited the Russian Minister at Teheran, M. Beger, ‘to come to a distinct understanding as to what was to be recognized as the Persian boundary-line along the frontiers of the Turcoman country.’ (See Mr. Thomson’s despatch, Tehran, December 10, 1869.) The answer to this invitation, which was, I believe, dated December 29, 1869,* has never been reported to Her Majesty’s Government; but I was * A copy of the reply was transmitted by Mr. R. Thomson in his No. 10 of January 29, 1873; and see Mr. T. Thomson’s No. 39 of March 22, 1875.told by the Grand Vizier that it was to the effect that Russia was not concerned in fixing a boundary between Persia and Turcoman territory, but merely adhered to the Attrek as the boundary between Russia and Persia. The Grand Vizier further said that as the Perso-Turcoman boundary was thus left an open question, it was clear that the Attrek fiontiei-line could only apply to the lower course of the river, below the confluence of the Simbar or Kari-Kileh branch. “It was, indeed, he added, the intention of Persia, whenever the question came on for discus sion, to claim the watershed of the Attrek as the true territorial boundary, the valley, of the streams flowing from the Attrek northward belonging to the independent Tekkehs, while the valleys of the streams flowing from the Attrek southward into the Attrek, were the property of the Jomuts, who were dependent on Persia. Kareh-Kaleh, on the Simbar, is one of these Jomut settlements south of the Attrek, and belongs, therefore, to Persia. It was taken by Persian troops in 1869, and has remained tributary to Boojnord ever since. At the same time I can see no great object in Persia’s protesting against a Russian occupation of the place. Any such protest would be a mere brutum fulmen, and would not cause a day’s delay in the march of the Russian troops if it was really considered of importance to garrison the post; but why Russia should desire to occupy an isolated and badly-supplied post like Kareh-Kaleh, when there are so many other more favourable sites, such as Kizil-Arvat, or Kabriz, or Ashkabad, to the north of the Attrek and on the direct line from Kras- novodsk to Merv, I cannot understand. Kari-Keleh is certainly of no strategical importance compared with the posts to the north of the Attrek, or with those between the Attrek and the Gurgan. “There is, however, real danger in allowing the line of the Attrek to be recognized as the true Russo-Persian frontier, for the main stream of that river flows through the rich Monah valley, within a few miles of Boojnord to its source at Shirwan and if the i ight bank of this stream were ceded to Russia, she would thus be brought into the heart of Khorassan. Jt should, therefore, clearly be under [71] I30 stood that the Attrek forms the frontier-line only as far as the confluence of the Simbar.” On the 4th March, 1875, the Emperor of Russia Lord A. Loftus, No. 112; determined to postpone till a more favourable ^ moment the proposed occupation of a central point on the Attrek by means of a permanent fort. This was stated to be owing to want of funds for the construction of a fort at Dooz-Oolama; but it was 129; thought that the jealous susceptibility of England on the Russian advance on Merve had much to do with the Emperor’s decision. The Emperor at the Lord A. Loftus, No. 134; v t • • 11 i April 27, 1875. same time expressed his supreme will that nothing should occur which could disturb the friendly rela tions existing between England and Russia. [n the despatch from the Russisn Minister of War conveying these orders to the Grand Duke Michael the following passage occurs :—“ Up to the present time our frontiers with Persia in the Trans- Caspian country have been fixed only with regard to the Lower Attrek; further on towards the east no frontiers exist between our Trans-Caspian possessions and the Turcoman tribes.” At the same time a proposal was made by the -fkiL Grand Duke Michael to annex &gt;*/southern littoral of the Caspian, but it was simply referred to the Imperial Chancellor for his consideration. On the 5th April following, Prince Gortchakow addressed a note to Count Schouvaloff (a copy of which were communicated to Lord Derby on 11th May),and in which the following passage occurred;— “ Sa Majest6 Imp6riale n’a aucunement Pintention d’&amp;endre les fronti&amp;res de la Russie telles qu’elles existent actuellement dans 1’Asie Centrale, ni du cote du Bokhara ni du cot6, de Krasnovodsk et de PAtrek.” This was quite consistent with the Emperor’s Lord A. Loftus, No. 5-13; special charge to Lord A. Loftus in 1874 to refer November 1/1 1S76 - to Majesty in the event of any question of difficulty arising with regard to Central Asia. The India Office, to whom the papers were India Office; referred, drew attention to the statement made therein to the effect that the Agreement arrived at between England and Russia respecting Affghanistan left to Russia full liberty of action upon every portion of territory situated between the Russian frontiers and June 21, 1875. &amp; L.Affghanistan, without any apparent right of remon strance on the part of the English Government; and with reference to this assumption, Lord Salisbury observed as follows :—“ If this claim is allowed to pass unchallenged, it may sooner or later lead to complications affecting Indian interests with regard to Merv which may seriously embarrass Her Majesty’s 1 ^ a -a ^ E a ft l-v ft * -\ ft establishment of Russian supremacy in Khiva and on the south-east coast of the Caspian Sea has taken place since the course of negotiations described in the general body of the Memorandum, whilst the occupation of the Attrek districts by Russian troops may at any time materially affect our relations with Persia.” His Lordship added that for these and other con siderations it was impossible in his opinion for Her Majesty’s Government to accept the position of inaction which Prince Gortchakow’s letter appa rently wished to force upon it. Lord Derby, however, was of opinion that the reply which was to be returned to the Russian Government should be “very civilly as well as To Lord A. Loftus, No. 318; cautiously drawn.” A Memorandum was, there- October 25, 1875. £ ore ^ ^ rawn U p f or communication to the Russian Government in the same friendly manner in which the Memorandum had been communicated by Prince Gortchakow. In this Memorandum it was stated that “ Her Majesty’s Government could not regard with indifference, and as a matter with which they had no concern, further occupation and absorption by Russia of the region which still separated Affghanistan from the Russian territory; and, after reviewing the correspondence which passed between the two Governments respecting Central Asia, it ended with these words:—“ Her Majesty’s Government have always deprecated the further extension of Russian territory towards the Affghan border, and they have now received with the most sincere satisfaction the assurances conveyed in I rinct Gortchakow’s despatch as to the enlightened con viction of His Imperial Majesty that any such exten sion, either on the side of Bokhara, of Krasnovodsk, or of the Attrek, is contrary to Russian interests, and that general orders have been given that all future action in those regions is to be strictly con fined to the defence of existing limits and the32 protection of property and commerce from pillage and brigandage. ,, On this Memorandum being placed in the hands Lord A. Loftus, No. 331; of Baron Jomini by Lord A. Loftus, the Baron Nover nber 9, 1875. expressed his great satisfaction at the friendly tone and the conciliatory spirit in which the sentiments of Her Majesty’s Government had been conveyed. About this time a report reached the Persian Mr. Thomson, No. 57 ; Government that the Russians were about to estab- A P riI 22 ’ i® 75 - maia unice; lish themselves on the mainland at Gez, opposite Ashurada, and that the points selected were Khoja Ma&gt; 21 ' 1875 ‘ Nass and Moolla Kala. The position of Khoja Is ass, or Nefes, is shown on the extract from Captain Napier’s map facing page 1, but the exact position of Moolla Kala is not to be found on any map that I have been able to consult, although I ha\e reason to believe that it is in the same neighbourhood. In sending me a copy of the Report for the Mr. Thomson, No. 74 ; Astrabad Agent, Mr. Thomson observed that if his 1 ® 75 - statement w’as true it was of grave significance \ and it subsequently proved to be correct, as the places above-named were carefully inspected by General Llamakin and certain Russian naval officers, the object being to ascertain if these places possessed such advantages as would make it desirable for Russian posts on the line of the Goorgan and Attrek to be no longer necessary. A correspondence passed between the Russian and Persian Governments on this subject, as well as upon the interference of Russian authorities with the Turcoman tribes residing in the Attrek and Goorgun territory, when the Persian reminded the Russian Minister of the Agreement of December 13, 1869. The Russian Minister took great offence at the wording of this letter, and another was in consequence substituted for it, wherein special re ference was still made to the Agreement of 1869, as well as to the fact that the Turcoman tribes settled on the Attrek and Goorgun were the ancient subjects of Persia. It was then reported that the Russians had landed building materials at Kizzil Sou for the purpose of constructing the fort at “Bayat Hajee”* on the Attrek, about 40 miles east of Hassun Koolie, near * Captain Napier says : “ Beiat Haji” is fifty miles from Chekislar. Mr. Thomson, No. 6; June 18, 1875. India Office; September 11, 1875. Mr. Thomson, No. 63, Secret; April 30, 1875. Mr. Thomson, No. 122 ; August 11, 1875. No. 127, August 12, 1875. No. 145, September 24, 1875. India Office ; November 30, 1875.Mr. Thomson, No. 145 ; September '24, 1875. Mr. Thomson, No. 168; November 3, 1875. Mr. Thomson, No. 176; November *29, 1875. Lord A. Loftus, Secret; June 7, 1865. Mr. Doria, Telegraphic ; June 20, 1875. Mr. Doria, No. 210 ; July 7, 1875. the embouchure of that river, to which reference has already been made (p. 25); but Mr. Thomson was of opinion that the erection of the fort was entirely opposed to the spirit of the so-called “ arrange ment ” between Russia and Persia, of December 13, 1869, in which it will be remembered that the Emperor, in answer to the assurance asked for by Persia that no fort or stronghold should hereafter be built at the embouchures of the Attrek or Goororun rivers, replied that the Russians “ had no intention to construct any fort.” Nevertheless, in November 1875, it was reported that the Russians were engaged in establishing themselves at that spot, and that Moossa Khan, of the Ak tribe, with 200 families, had gone over to the Russians, which was followed by a Decree for the Chiefs of the Yamoot Turco mans of the Charva tribe, directing them to present themselves before him at Chekislar, and there receive his orders. But notwithstanding the orders given by the Emperor to the Grand Duke Michael to discon tinue all aggressive movements in the neighbour hood of Merve, His Imperial Highness forwarded to the Russian Minister of War a report in which he urged upon him the necessity of undertaking a military expedition (to consist of 2,000 men, four guns and a rocket battery) to scour the country between the Balkan mountains and the Attrek, but to be carried out in a “ most amicable spiritand this proposed expedition was approved by the Emperor of Russia when at Ems, on June 2, 1875. The proposed reconnaissance was to start from Krasnovodsk and to extend over the following districts :— From the Michaeloflfsky Gulf to the Well Kara-durum, Kutol, Kara-Ishan, Lake Aidim, near the Balkan hills, Shapreda, Lake Shinda, Shikh, and Esenadji, and thence by the old bed at the Attrek, the ruins of the cities of Meshed and Mestdovrass (Meandouvan) to the Ford Tchat, at the Junction at the Simbar with the Attrek. From Tchat, the expedition was to descend the Attrek, and having made a fortified camp at a suitable place, to move on in different directions along the Sarmen. It was, however, stated that orders would be given to the Commander in no case to pass to the left bank of the Attrek, and not to pass the bound- [71] Karies of the Persian Koords, although they might be encamped on Russian territory, as it had become known that on the right bank there was a numerous sedentary Koord population who acknowledged the supremacy of the Shah. General Lamakin started from Krasnovodsk on the so-called scientific and military expedition to explore the ancient bed of the Amu Daria early in July, 1875, and about the 21st of that month he passed Kizil Arvat to attack the Tekkle tribes, and early in September following the “ Journal de St. P6ters- bourj; ” announced that the Akhal Tekhe tribe had submitted to the Russian General. At this time it was reported that there was about 500 Yemoot families at Kizil Arvat living under Russian jurisdiction. In October following it was reported that General Lamakin was about to proceed to Karee-Kala, and Captain Napier suggested that he should be allowed to proceed to Nardeen, some distance east of Asterabad, whence he might proceed to Karee- Kala ; but in forwarding home this request, Mr. Thomson observed that, although accurate infor mation respecting this district was desirable, yet that the presence of Captain Napier there could not fail to irritate the Russians, and raise unfounded expectations among the Turcomans. These views were concurred in by Lord Derby and Lord Salisbury, and Mr. Thomson was accordingly told to inform Captain Napier that he must not proceed to the districts he proposed to visit for the present. He therefore collected such information as he could respecting this supposed important position without visiting it, and the following are extracts from the report of his journey to the northern districts of Persia, which was printed in 1876 :— “ Fhe little fort of Kara-kala ” (or, as he spells it, Karakalla), “on the northern Attrek tributary, has in many respects an important position. It dominates both the Yamoot and Akhal pastures, and has been long the bone of contention between those tribes. From it also is open a good road into the Attrek and Goorgan valleys, and across both these streams into Persia. Held by either the Yamoot or Aklial, it is a standing menace to the Persian border, and its occupation by the Koords Protocol, August 13, 1874. Russian encampments at Tchat arvi, Jaraforivief, and Agata bief. Mr. Thomson, Telegraphic; July 23, 1875. Lord A. Loftus, No. 274 ; September 7, 1875. Mr. Thomson, No. 114; July 23, 1875. Mr. Thomson, No. 158; October 28, 1875. Mr. Thomson, Telegraphic; December 6, 1875. To Mr. Thomson ; December 11, 1875. Mr. Thomson, No. 182 a ; December 6, 1875. Confidential Vol., 8vo., p. 290.Page 66, November 14, 1874. Page 115. 35 would be intolerable to both tribes. For years pre ceding 1860 it had been held by the Akhal Tekke. In that year a Persian force took and destroyed it, but no attempt at occupation was made —the distance and difficulty of access being too great to leave any hope of success in the face of the strenuous opposi tion that was certain to be aroused. “In 1869 it was again taken and destroyed after some fighting. “ Lately, after the occupation of Khiva, a Colony of Goklan, with a few Yamoots escaping from that place, rebuilt and occupied it. “ They now own a nominal allegiance to the Elkhanee, and, through his influence, their occupa tion appears to be acquiesced in by the tribes directly concerned. “ The Russians are credited with an intention to occupy the position, on the ground that the Goklan occupants are their subjects, being Khivans, and it is probable that they may also consider it as on their bank of the Attrek. “ The position is an important one with refe rence to any military movements from the Attrek directed against the Settlement of the Akhal in the ‘ Atok/ “ Its occupation by Persia should be the first step towards an extension of authority up to the Attrek, and the opening of friendly communications with the Tekkah Turcomans.” In another place he says :— “ The Goklan refugees from Khiva settled at Kara-Kala, a fort on the Ab-i-sunt, tributary of the Attrek, about sixty miles north of Bujnoord, said to number 1,000 families, have made overtures to the Elkhanee, and will, he says, make use of him if pressed by the Russians on the Tekkab. Mean while they pay no tribute.” Again: “ A road from Gurgan to Kara-Kala traverses the valley. This was the road most used by the Tekkah in their raids south when they had possession of Kara-Kala.” [If these are the Akhal Tekkahs, it was before I860.] “ At the edge of the ‘ Dasht,* on a spur of the mountain known as the Soonting Soor, or Soont Soor, stands the fort of Kara-Kala. # Its position, * The latest Russian survey places the fort on the northern slopes of the mountains.— C. G. Napier.36 commanding (as it does) the only good road on to the Dasht plateau and then to the ‘Atak/ has been the scene of frequent struggles between the Turkomans and Shahdilloo Koords. Some four years ago (? 1870) the Saham-u-dovvla, Elkhanee, or Chief of the Shahdillo, led a small force with a few guns against it, and succeeded in capturing it, after a siege of some days, and two unsuccessful assaults.” On the 21st November, 1874, Captain Napier drew special attention to the designs of Russia against Kara-Kalla. He said :—“I heard from a Turkoman, Solaiman by name, of the Kalta Terrah, who came to the caravanserai to-day, that the Russian General had given them notice to keep one camel for each family in readiness, as an expedition against Kara-Kalla was soon to be undertaken. After the capture of Kara-Kalla, he said, they proposed to advance to Akhal and Merve. He also mentioned that the Tekkahs of Akhal were quite disposed to become Russian subjects, since the Persian Government had stopped their trade.” And in another place he said that old accounts which he had received agreed that the road from Kara-Kalla to the Atak was passable for light guns, and that the country to the west was much broken, barren, and waterless. It woidd therefore appear, from these extracts, that although Persia may claim the fort of Kara- Kalla, she appears never to have occupied it in modern times. Nevertheless, Sir H. Rawlinson appears to be of opinion that the fort belongs to her. The following is an extract from his work entitled 'England and Russia in the East,” pub lished in 1875. “ As these last sheets are passing through the press, it is announced that operations have com menced, the Russian column from Chikishlar having appeared on the Attrek, with the avowed intention of attacking and occupying the Yomut post of Kari-Kileh, on the Simbar, which is the most western ly affluent of the Attrek on its right bank. This demonstration then raises the frontier question in a direct and tangible form. Persia maintains her frontier to be marked not by the main37 Lord A. Loftus, No. 145, Most Secret; April 14, 1876. Lord A. Loftus, No. 151; April , 1876. stream, but by the watershed of the Atlrek, the valleys of all the affluents of that river from the north, of which the Simbar, often called the Kari- Kileh, is one, belonging to her, and the Yomuts who inhabit those valleys being accounted her subjects. “ If Russia overrule this claim, and insist on her right to regard the main stream from its embou chure to its source as the boundary between Russian and Persian territory, the Shah will lose some of the fairest districts of Khorassan, and Russia will command not only the Attreck road to Merv, but the high road to Meshed from the Caspian. “ Of course the protest of Persia against what she calls a violation of frontier would be unavailing unless warmly supported by England; and Russia does not seem disposed to admit of our right of interference in such a matter.” In April 1876 a proposal w’as made by the Grand Duke Michael to the Emperor of Russia that General Lamakin should undertake another ex pedition to the Attrek during the ensuing summer, but His Majesty positively forbad any such expedi tion to be undertaken, possibly on account of Count Schouvaloff having reported to His Imperial Majesty and the Russian Government that, although the annexation of Khokand had produced no notable impression on public opinion in England, yet that any extension on the right hand from the Caspian towards the Persian and Affghanistan frontiers would be very differently viewed, and that any advance on the Attrek, or towards Merv, would immediately give rise to action on the part of the Indian Government. The following tracing from Kiepert’s Map of Turkestan shows what he considers to be the present boundary of Persia :—38 Kiepert's Turkestan 1876. ENLARGED The question of the Attrek, or northern frontier of Persia, appears then to stand thus :— In 1834 Great Britain and Russia entered into Confidential Memorandum an agreement to respect the independence and ^ 0 * 2150- integrity of Persia. In 1838 this agreement was confirmed. In 1842 the Russians, with the avowed object of 'assisting the Persians against the Turcomans, occu pied the Island of Ashoorada, near Asterabad, to the south of the River Goorgun, and erected buildings on the island. In 1845 they increased their buildings, when the Persians remonstrated against their doing so. In 1846 it became evident that the Russians intended to form a military establishment at Ashoorada, their object being, it was believed, to entice the Turcomans towards the Russian Govern ment, and to detach them from Persia. They then attempted to establish themselves on the mainland opposite Ashoorada, and asked the Persians to allow them to build a hospital there, and to surround the building and store-houses with a wall; but the Persians, on being cautioned by the39 Pajfes 3 and 4. Page 7. Page 8. British Minister that such a building would be in reality a Fortress, they withheld their consent. In 1849 the British Government informed the Russian Government that they thought the time had arrived for restoring Ashoorada to the Persians ; but it has never been restored to this day. In 1853 the Russians were engaged for fifteen days in surveying the whole line of coast of the Bay of Ashoorada. In 1854 the Persians were about to repair their fortifications at Enzelee, near Resht, and at Gez, near Asterabad ; but the Russians remonstrated, and they consequently deferred doing so, although the British Government urged the Persian Government to put Asterabad and Enzelee in a state of defence. At this time the Russian Charge d’Affaires at Tehran admitted that Ashoorada belonged to Persia. After the Crimean war, Russia increased her naval force in the Caspian, and Mr. Abbott pointed out to Her Majesty’s Government how this step could only be regarded in the light of a menace to Central Asia and British India, as the best route into Affghanistan was through Asterabad. In 1865 the Russian Government proposed to Persia to make the Attrek River the boundary of Persia, on the shores of the Caspian, in lieu of the Koja -Su, which was stated to be more to the south, and had hitherto been the recognized frontier. In 1869 the Russians took possession of Kizzil- Soo, or Krasnovodsk, in Balkan Bay, with the avowed object of opening a route to Khiva and and Turkestan in the interest of commerce. The Persians remonstrated, and claimed the coast as belonging to them, but the Russian Minister at Tehran asserted that Persia had no territorial rights on the shore of the Caspian Sea so far north ; and on the 13th December following an agreement was come to between Russia and Persia that the Attrek should form the boundary between their respective States in their neighbourhood, and that no Russian forts should be erected on the Attrek. In 1872 the Russians invaded Akhal, belonging to the Turcomans, and captured Kizzil-Arvad, Barne, and Berma, and it was reported that they had taken Karee-Kala also, which is claimed by Persia, with the intention of fortifying it. In 1873 the Russians, notwithstanding the Agree- r7ll Mment of 1869, erected a fort to the north of the Attrek River, near its mouth, called Chikish- lar ; they also crossed the Attrek and attacked the Yamoud Turkomans; but, on the Persians protest ing, the Russians said they fully recognized “ the Attrek as the frontier between Russia and Persia,” but a doubt has now been raised as to whether the Agreement of 1869 had reference to that part of the river which empties itself into the Caspian Sea, or to the river along its whole extent; and this again has led to another question, as that is what are the real sources of the Attrek. When the discussion on this latter point first Pages 5 arose in 1873, the Russian Asiatic Society re-issued their map of Central Asia of 1863, with the colouring altered, so as to show the boundary between Russia and Persia as extending for a distance of about forty or fifty miles up the River Attrek, but not so far as Karee Kala. In 1874 the Russians claimed jurisdiction over the districts to the south of the Attrek, and lying between that river and the Goorgan ; but so recently as November of that year the British Government informed the Russian Government % that the territory lying between the Attrek and the Goorgan was unquestionably Persian territory. Page 23. In the same year the Russians came to a secret Page 25. understanding among themselves to consider all the territory lying between Khiva and the Attrek as annexed to Russia, although they do not publicly avow it; and they would now appear to be again considering the question of obtaining a footing on the mainland, either at Moollah Kala or at Khoja Nefas, or at both, their chief object being to force from the Persians an admission that the Attrek forms the boundary between Persia and Russia from its source (wherever that may be) to the Caspian Sea. But as great doubts exist as to what is really the source of that river, Persia might find herself deprived not only of some of her most fertile districts, but also of her most important defensive positions, including Karee-Kala, which she firmly maintains belongs to her, were she to consent to the Russian proposals ; and from the latest accounts it appears that the Russians have evident designs of occupying Karee-Kala. But, notwithstanding these proceedings of Russia*1 41 C'onfidential Memorandum, No 2464. at Ashoorada, Kizzil-Soo, Chikishlar, Hajee-Bayat, Karee-Kala, and elsewhere, she has assured the British Government, so recently as July 1873, and December 1874, that she considers the Agreement entered into with the British Govern ment in 1834, which was confirmed in 1838, to maintain the independence and integrity of Persia, to be still binding; and the point, therefore, which hap to be determined is, what is considered by this country, by Persia, and by Russia, as the north boundary of Persia? Until some arrangement is come to on this point, the discussion is likely to be interminable. E. HERTSLET. Foreign Office, August 16, 1877.</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000050_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/L/PS/18/C18</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000050</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/L/PS/18/C18</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'Memorandum on the Attrek, or Northern, Frontier of Persia'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1877/1877</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2015-05-19T09:53:57</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">fre</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (25 folios)</extent><extent>The file consists of a table of contents (folios 114-115), followed by a map (folio 116), which is in turn followed by the body of the memorandum itself (folios 117-137).</extent><extent>Foliation: the foliation sequence commences at f 113, and terminates at f 137, as it is part of a larger physical volume; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio.Pagination: the file also contains an original printed pagination sequence.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>The memorandum concerns Persia's northern frontier with Russian Turkestan along the Attrek [Atrek] River valley. It outlines Russian activities in the region (e.g. troop movements, fort construction, and meetings with local chieftains), along with British and Persian diplomatic responses to these activities; this includes British efforts to prevent Persia from ceding the region to Russian control. It covers British suspicions that the Russians are encroaching on Persia's northern border, and attempting to draw the local Turkoman tribes away from their relations with Persia.The memorandum is illustrated with a number of map sketches, which show a number of different interpretations of the Persian-Russian frontier:Captain George Campbell Napier's Map 1876. Denoting supposed Persian border line (f 116);Arrowsmith Map. 1834 (f 117r);Zimmerman's Map. 1841 (f 117v);Vambery's Map 1863 (f 117v);Russian Map 1863 (f 119r);Arrowsmith Map 1872 (f 119v);Walker's Turkestan. 1873 (f 120r);Russian Map 1873 (f 122r);Kiepert's Turkestan 1876 (f 135v).The memorandum includes a number of brief insertions in French; these insertions consist of recollections from diplomatic conversations, which have occurred in relation to Persia's northern frontier.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Ambassador to Iran</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>HM Ambassador to Russia</namePart></name></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Russian Commander of the Transcaspian Military Sector</namePart></name></subject><subject><geographic>Atrek river</geographic></subject><subject><geographic>Kara Kalla</geographic></subject><subject><topic>Frontiers</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000833.0x000050#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>