<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0000f5_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-06-21T11:09:35.334Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">microfilmed document DO NOT IORNEGV CONFIDENTIAL. No - 532-S of 1933. 1 he Hon ble the Political Resident in the Persian Golf presents his com pliments to 1. His Majesty’s Secretary of State for India, London. 2. THe Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, Simla* and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu- To (2) Political esident’ o May 1933.The Hon ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to 1. 2 . 3. The Foreign Sedretary to the Government of India, Simla. The Political Agent, Kuwait. The lolitieal Agent, Bahrain. / and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment (s). Reference to previous correspondence : Bushire Printed letter Ho.433-S of 26th April, 1933. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. ' * Telegram^ 0 . 12 2, dated the 30th May 1933 from His Majesty’s Minister,Jedda. Subject. Hasa Oil ConcessionH£»4( Hie Hon ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to 1- His Majesty's Secretary of State for Inaia, London. 2* The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, Simla* and has the honour to transmit to him ment a copy of the undermentioned docu- British Residency and Consulate-General, BUS HIRE. Dated •S-t-fc-Guney Reference to previous correspondence: i'' Busbire Printed letter Ho.53^-3 of 22nd iay 1933. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Rushire despatch No*34 oi 3th June 1933 to His Majesty's Secretary of KUWAIT OIL* State for the Colonies. Copy, with copy of e nclosure, forwarded with compliments to the Political Agent, £ , Kuwait, for i nformation.The Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to (1) . The Political Agent, Kuwait* (2) . The Political Agent, Bahrain. 13). The Political Agent, Auscat. and is directed to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents, for information. Axt ' /c/ '✓A j Wine- Bt' British Residency and Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated... June 1933 Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Copy of Petroleum Departments Memorandum dated 1st May 1933, on Oil Concessions in Arabia and the Persian Gulf.1 Copfidential. Memorandum for Colonel ^owle. Oil Concession i n Arabia and the Persian G-ulf * The position in Arabia and the Persian Gulf area, so far as the information in the possession of the Petroleum Department goes is as follows:- (1) Kowait . The Anglo-Persian Oil Company and the Eastern and General Syndicate ( representing the Gulf Oil Corporation of America) have both applied for a concession, and are engaged in submitting rival offers to the Shaikh who still has the matter under considera- -tion. * (2) Hasa . O n May 6th 1923 , the Sultan of «ejd, |Abdul Bin Saud, granted an oil concession covering the !Province of H a sa ( including the Hatif and Jubail areas ) I |to the Eastern and General Syndicate, No information is available as to whether this has lapsed, but in view . . .. - . .•. . .. J of the length of time which has expired it appears I probable that it has done so. According to a tele- -gram from Sir Andrew Byan (Jedda) of March 22nd, 1933, jnegotiations for an oil concession in Hasa have been jproceeding between (l) The Standard Oil Company of California, and (2) The Irag Petroleum Company, repre- -sented by Longrigg and Muderris. Major Holmes has also recently visited Jedda but it is not clear on whose account he is acting in this area. (3) Neutral Zone . (South of Kuwait). On May 17th, 1924, an oil concession was granted jointly by Ibn Saud and the Shaikh of Koweit to the Eastern and General Syn dicate. The present position in regard to an oil con- -cession in this area is not known. The Eastern and General Syndicate, by an agreement of 30th November, 1927, transferred any rights which it might possess orI t» © 2 . possess or acquire or which could he reinstated in H asa or Neutral Zone, or any concession which it might secure in Koweit, to the Eastern Gulf Oil Oom- -pany. (4) . Bahrain*, Concession secured hy Bahrain Petrol- -eum Company (Standard Oil Company Sf California) and oil met with in trial borings. (5) £at r .«. The AnglorPersian Oil Company acting as far as the Petroleum Department were aware at the time on their own behalf, recently secured an exclusive option from the Sheikh to carry out geological investi- -gations for a period of 2 years. Any concession which they secure will for the reasons mentioned below probably have to be on behalf of the Iraq &amp;xi Petroleum Company. (6) lusaai. The Anglo*Persian Oil Company obtained a concession in 1925 to prospect for oil for a period of two years with the right to a mining lease, but this concession has now lapsed. (7) lokalla. The Anglo-Saxon Petroleum Company started negotiations for a concession in 1928-29, hut the matter was not proceeded with as they reached the conclusion that the prospects pf discovering petroleum were unfavourable. (8) dedcta- (Hejaz, west Coast of Arabia). Two American engineers (Twitchell and Crane) have recently carried out investigations, and the Petroleum Department brought the matter to the notine of the Ainglo-Persian Oil Company. It is regarded as important that every endeavour should be made to enable British interests to establish themselves in the Persian Bulf Area. The position is complicated by the fact that the Anglo?Persian Oil Com- -pany...3. Company who are geographically best suited to undertake developement work, are virtually excluded from operating in this area except as a nominee of the 1 raq. Petroleum Company. ^he same remarks apply to the Shell. The circumstances which have led up to this position are as follows: PQ£ltiQn of the Iraq Petroleum Company. The Turkish Petroleum Company ( now the Iraq. Petroleum Company) was formed in 1912 when the Deutsche #ank became associated with the National Bank of Turkey and the Anglo-Saxon Petroleum Company (Hoyal Duch-Shell guoup) in order to press certain claims to oil rights in Baghdad and Mosul, including those attached to the B a gh- -dad Bailway Concession. The chief rival of the new company at that time was the Anglot*P ersian Oil Company which had for some time been in negotiation with the Turkish Government* In 1914 an Agreement was entered into providing for the reconstitution of the Turkish Petroleum Company, from which the National Bank of Turkey withdrew, the new participants being the Anglo- -reisian Oil Company, 50^; the Anglo-Saxon Petroleum and the Deutsche Bank 25% each. This Agreement also /v provided that the 1£ree groups should give undertakings not to be interested directly or indirectly in the pro- -duction of oil in the Ottoman Empire in Europe and Asia except in Egypt, Kuwait or the Transferred Territories, except through the Turkish Petroleum Company. This Agreement was signed by the British and German Governments and by the groups concerned. As the Turkish Petroleum Company was then predominantly British, this arrangement had the effect of securing the whole of this area to interests which were predominantly British. After the entry of...o \v' 4. entry or American and .Frencli interests into ttie IraQ. Petroleum Company after the war, the arrangement as regards non-competition between the groups composing the Iraq. Petroleum Company was continued in an agreement between the groups, entered into in 1328. This was a private agreement between the groups with which the British Government was not concerned. Under this Agreement a line was drawn round Arabia, Palestine and Asia Minor, which excluded Koteeit and the Farsan islands, but included Bahrein aS^n, which defined an area within which the various groups constituting the Praq. Petroleum Company agreed that they would not seek for or obtain oil concessions otherwise than through the 1 raq. Petroleum Company or its nominee. The position as regards the distribution of capital in the Iraq. Petroleum Company is as follows: Anglo-Persian Oil Company. 23.75$ Boyal Butch Shell 23.74$ IVench Group 23.75$ American Group 23.75$ C.S.Gulbenkian 5.00$ In 1932 the American Shareholding in the American Group was held in the following proportions: Standard Oil Company of New Jersey 41 2 / 3 $ Standard 9il Company Company of 9 New York 41 V 3 % Gulf Oil Corporation of Pennsyl- 2 / Hania 16 / 3 $ As the Royal Butch Shell is 60$ Butch and 40$ British, the British shareholding in the Iraq Petroleum Company now only represents about 33-|$. The Iraq Petroleum^is technically a British Company, as in Article 32 of its Convention with the Government of Iraq, the Company must be and remain a British Company, registered in Great Britain, and the Chair- -man must be at all times a British subject. OneOne question whicti arises is whether H.M.Government can he expected to afford the same measure of support to the Iraq Petroleum Company as it could in the old days when it was a British Company in fact as well as in name. As the American oil interests have large grpups outside the Iraq Petroleum Company as well as inside they are at an advantage and it may he necess- -ary to support the Iraq Petroleum Company as against a purely American concern. This does not however affect Koweit as it is excluded from the 1928 Agreement and it only makes it all the more important to see that the Anglo-Persianj Gil Company secure the Eoweit concession. Petroleum Department. 1st ^ay 1933.. .. . vc- ... aeifcrsdiv ax aeai’ic do hi® aclJssuv saO ^‘.io-Mg-ya xo eTJassm 9im5S sou .bo.. tl.3 o«f bCvocgxs oO iXS-j M o BiU al Jblvco J'i: as lasoucO muelc'ijs ~ eiut c ’^ 3B II9W a? c? )M nx -^riagffloC ila.MM - s asw act a©n / s^Bb 9 s*xsl 9vc.o Mss'ieori Xio £Tbox‘xs....;A ©rid' aA .emi-a' ox 8 b XX$w bb YOBQ'inoO uiuelcaxfrs*! Pb*iX ©Avt ebiaJuc eq;jo;i^ “880090 3Cf ACO £TX bflA ffs Xs SAB ^9.:lu OMoff.-. JonicsB ©o v :r;:c, 3 ioC jnc/eXo'i^eX pjri* ©oo' oj go:£~ , n r xo oaoo rrool x-say--.. ^I© r xj.&gt; g. b ji 8.s ctxewoA uoe'il.c ‘■levcwoof tea aecb sirfT asAc.i v^Xcro x brr.s joeoee'xsi. MAX ©xfX beb)UXox9 ax .. ; . . 00 tnr^'iGqtii: ©*icqi e/iJ lls ax . a 01 s as0 a -• 0 1 1 i9wc a 9rio' eixosa •;,0.3 Mc 1 0 XI - • j ^ ts a.iJ ‘it: gs,. cm© I 01 : e i i rSc-2 1 ^£.- 2 3 x3f ■ r^/y 7 from To Jr. i&gt; H.M 9 3 Minlst©r t %leoda. Uecratary of for foreign / ffalrs, Lonazn. Ha. iiO. ^epaateO io Taiitio&amp;I KesiOent« Busuiro. Ho* 134* ii&amp;i&amp;£ oii^ rooelvea 6th i9S5* Your despatch No. 120. ?Wu&gt; informed me eonfidentlalXy and spoke to me yesterday that Xhn Saud 'hau aaaressed Shaikh of Kuwait a letter regarding o-jmmerclal re flations which contained proposal of nature to give ahalkh some satisfaction* He adaeu that King hau hean impressed &amp;y news of distressful local situation ^od that if tus letter produced good result proposal would in due course he put forward ^ffid- -ally* Fuad did not say through what channel this would be don©* It may be better not to use this in- -formation with shaikh unless he notifies ^ o itical resident of receipt of letter. In my opinion, this new dcvelopement must be considered in the light of two possibilities viz. (A), ring may be genuinely anxious tc 3 &gt;mpose his differences with all his neighbours or (B)• He may think he has Shaikh sufficiently at tis mercy to establish political ascendency over him by sum© sort of direct agreement. In thi&amp; eonnaction.•«•\ Telegram R, From Political Resident, Bushire. To Political l.gent, Kuwait. No. 472. Dated 15th (received 16th ) June 1933. Reference correspondence ending with my P.L. No. 651-S sent by fast mail. Minister at Jedda has no objection to our approach ing the Shaikh. Please do so and remind Shaikh tactfully that if communication from Ibn Saud concerns Neutral Zone he should not commit himself without reference to Hig Majesty’s Government. Resi dent. pprCONFIDENTIAL. No. 647-3 of 1933. The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com- phments to g is Majesty's Secretary of State for India, London, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned dccu- ment British Residency and Consulate-General, BUSHIKE. Dated J«ne-‘1933» Reference to previous correspondence : India Office t&amp;Jfeegrajji No. 1050, dated 28th April 1935 Description of Enclosure. Name and Date, Subject. Letter No. 646-S, dated IStlji Aune 1933, to The Foreign Secretary to the Government of IncB&amp;, Simla. Copy forward ed, /wi th Political Agent, Kuwait^, refe Printed Letter No. 446-S, dat Shaikh of Kuwait's visit to England. compliments, to the rence this Residency ed 29th April 1933. rtfaonriggntlal* HO* 646-3 of 1933. British BeslOenoy and Consulate-General) | Bushlr@t the 12th June 1933* Fro® The Eon*hle Lieut.-Colonel T.O. Fowle* C.B.S., lolitieal Resident in the Persian Gulf, To Xhe Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, Simla. With reference to correspondence ending with India Office telegram Ho. 1050, dated 28th April 1933, X have the honour to state that Colonel Dickson has informed me that Mis Excellency is-*$ Shaikh of Kuwait has stated to hi® verbally that he, » the Shaikh, has definitely refused the invitation of the Eastern and Central Syndicate. I am sending a copy of this letter to His Majesty*s Secretary of State for India. I have the honour to he. Sir, Your most obedient servant, (SD) T. 0. FOALS, Lt.-wOXon.l, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.» GOFF IDENTIC, yxJL f\p Ho. B (1). %*■ \ 2 W* T BU3HIKE, Dated the 7th June, 19 33. t! ' From - Lieut.-Colonel H.R.P.Dickson, C,I, political Agent, Kuwait, v / at Bushire* To The Honourable the political Resident in the Persian Culf Sir, I, ... As desired by you, I hare the honour to submit a very rough note embodying my ideas on the Kuwait Oil situation, as I see it in the light of His Majesty*s Minister, Jedda's telegram Ho.124, dated the bth June 1933, to yourself. I trust allowance will be made for the hurried nature of the note which I was anxious to get to you ■ / ^ ' \ before my return to Kuwait. If- llu^ /y&amp;R. I have the honour to be. Sir, Your most obedient servant, tr Lt .-Colonel Political Agent, Kuwait.Hote on the Kuwait Oil situation as I see it in the light of His Majesty’s Minister^ledda* s telegram No*l24 t dated the 5th June rj33 f to Bushire (110 to London}. &lt; .h l / ! . A V S. \ \ i \. ( V ■v’ U 1. The news that Bin Baud has addressed a letter to the Shaikh of Kuwait propounding certain proposals of a commer cial nature which can be counted on to give the Shaikh satisfaction, is most important, and as I read it means that Bin Baud is now definitely going to enter the lists in the matter of •Kuwait Oil', fik m 2. IV) &lt;: &gt;&gt; %j! ^ { 5 &lt;XlJ It entirely confirms what X rather fores^ar^ was coming, vide my Confidential leiter Bo#80, dated the 27th April, to Bushire, although the granting of the Hassa Oil concession to the Standard Oil Company, not then visualized somewhat confuses the issue. 3, I think we may for a start, disabuse our minds of the idea that the king has any sort of 'feelings' for the distressed condition of the people of Kuwait, seeing that it is his blockade of the last 10 years which has brought them to the pass they are in, j 4, We may also, in my opinion, reject entirely sugges tion (A) as put forward in Jedda’s telegram Bo, 124 of 5th June mentioned above, which was to the effect that the kin, was to-day anxious to compose his differences with all his / neighbours, ) Ja ' f 5, In my view possibility (B) as envisaged by His Majesty’s/V Majesty's Minister.Jedda, is tile correct interpretation of what is going to happen, and the king now thinks the time ripe for establishing his political ascendancy over Kuwait un. er the guise of an Oil agreement. 6. The plan of campaign to be adopted (part of which we have seen develop as below) will 1 believe be somewhat on the following lines t- (a) It has been pretty clearly established now that when the Shaikh went into the ITSII) desert on the 20th and 2bth February last, (see my Secret ho. 5th March 19 53), he met the king ,6 then 80 miles north of Hafar al Atz, hunting,!or possibly his son the hmir Saud, ot Saud al Arafa as reported at the time). At n this meeting details ol the mode oi proceduie to be adopted were I believe discussed, and quite probably emanated from the Shaikh of Kuwait in the first instance. (b) The Shaikh pointed out that Kuwait was on the verge of collapse due to the blockade and must obtain relief. 'fhe king expressed willingness to afford such relief provided the Shaikh would join forces in an Oil agreement, details of which would be submitted later. Both States would thus benefit equally# (c) The Shaikh pointed out that His Majesty^ Government wished him to give the Kuwait oil concession to the Anglo-Persian Oil Company Limited, but that he himself favoured Holmes and his American backers. That he, the Shaikh, could not go against His Majesty’s Government’s wishes, without getting into trouble. U)/9./ 3- (d) The king no doubt replied that he also fay cured the Americans before the Anglo-Persian Oil Company Limited and that if the Shaikh and he combined to keep the /nglo-Persian Oil Company Limited out, not only would both reap an advantage, but he, Bin Baud, would be prepared to relax the blockade and champion Kuwait in her difficulties with * IRAQ and His Majesty’s G-overnment. ( e) Behind the Shaikh’s mind was the pleasing idea of getting relief from the blockade, and assist ing Major Holmes and his Americans to get into Kuwait. Behind Bin Baud’s mind was the plan to get the Standard Oil Company (also Holmes) into the Kuwait Meutral Lone, and then using this as a lever, get them into Kuwait as well, which would give him the ascendancy he had for so long sought over the Shaikh of Kuwait. 7. Then followed certain moves in the game which we know subsequently took place. (a) Bin Baud invited certain foreign Oil Representa tives to come to Jedda to negotiate an Oil agreement, etc. ( b) Major Holmes who represented the Eastern and General Syndicate Limited in Kuwait and the Standard Oil in Bahrain was also invited by special telegram to go to Jedda. This he did. 8. As a result of negotiations mentioned in (7) above, the Hassa Concession has been given to the Standard Oil Company of America, vide Jedda telegram to Bushire,ho. 122 of 30th May 1933.I 14./ » &lt;VA -4- 9. There is little doubt in myt mind that the Hassa Concession in respect of area especially ; will be virtually the same as was given to Major Holmes in 1923 and which later lapsed. The important point for us to consider being that it will almost certainly have included in it the Kuwait heutral hone* 10o The next step will clearly be for Bin Baud to get the Shaikh of Kuwait to give his consent to the Standard Oil / working in the Heutral Zone. w |&gt; 11 . Bin Saud, in the letter which he has now addressed to the Shaikh of Kuwait»(Jedda telegram No.124 to Bushire, dated 5th June 1933), will no doubt suggest to the Shaikh that he has noticed the distressed condition of Kuwait with pain, and that he will be prepared to ease off the blockade at once either entirely or in part, if he, the Shaikh, will agree to give his consent to the Standard Oil working the Neutral Zone. Probably also he will suggest that the Shaikh receive a certain share in the oil profits of the Hassa concession, as a result of the meeting him in this matter. 12. Any difficulties that might have arisen between the Eastern and GeneTcl Syndicate Limited and the Standard Oil, (both represented by Holmes}* in the matter of the exploitation of the Neutral Zone have probably already been arranged; and Holmes* visit to Bin Saud at Jedda was no doubt partly connected with such adjustment. 13. Bin Saud will no doubt now expect the Shaikh, as per plan already made, to reply agreeing with his request,! in spite of the fact that His Majesty* s Government has told the Shaikh that he must do nothing in regard to the Neutral ^one without their previous sanction).. ; V — , —. - / lA -5- 1 14, The Shaikh will no doubt secretly give his consent to Bin Saud and then tell His Majesty's Government that he desires their permission to agree to Bin Baud's conditions, seeing ' that the benefits to be gained will be of such vital importance to Kuwait. 15. Bin Saud for his part will doubtless guarantee to get His Majesty's Government to put no difficulties in the Shaikh’s way and in this respect willbe prepared to fight Kuwait’s battles with His Majesty's Government. 16. Bin Saud at one stroke will (a) please Kuwait by settling the blockade question (b) please His Majesty’s Government by so doing (c) get the Americans into the Heutral Zone. 17. Then will follow the last and final move. Bin Saud will inform the Shaikh,( who 1 think it has been definitely established now, favours the Eastern and General Syndicate Limited before the Anglo-Persian Oil Company Limited), that it will be quite impossible for him, the Shaikh, to give the Kuwait Oil Concession to the Anglo-Per si an Oil Company Limited, and that he must settle the matter in favour of Major Holmes and the Americans - his official reasons Yri.ll be that to have the Standard Oil working alongside of the Amglo-Persian Oil Company Limited as rivals will create an impossible situation. It will further be pointed out that the suspected oil is in Horth Bassa and the j&amp;KkH Neutral ^one, and the port of Kuwait will be needed for the export of such oil, 18, Lastly it will be pointed out that the prosperity of Kuwait will be assured for all time with (a)/ 1 \♦ (a) the blockade removed; (b) a percentage of Oil revenues from Hassa going into the Shaikh* a pocket; (c) the shaikh getting all the profits from his Kuwait proper oil profits, 19, It may at this stage be even suggested as a further 'bait*, that if the standard Oil (Holmes) get Kuwait as well as Hassa, all profits from Hassa, Heutral &amp;one and Kuwait may be pooled between Kuwait and Saudiyeh. 20# The Shaikh will here find himself in difficulties, and will reply that he will be quite willing to fall into line, but that His Majesty’s Government are the difficulty. To this Bin Saud will again reply; 'leave the squaring of His Majesty’s Government to me'. This manoeuvre the Shaikh believes will get him out of all difficulty with His Majesty’s Government, and has probably already been suggested, discussed, and settled between Bin Saud, the Shaikh, and Holmes, 21. The final result, if everything goes according to plan, will be a close rapprochement between Kuwait and Saudiyeh, and the secret transference of our political ascendency over Kuwait to Bin Saud, (much as Qatar to-day comes under his unofficial protection). Mor will the honour and prestige of Kuwait, in the eyes of the Arab world, be impaired. 22. Last but not least Kuweit will have a no mean ally in her fight with [’RgQ,and His Majesty’s Government will find herself left out in the cold. 23. The above is I think not very far short of what is in the wind to-day. The crux of the whole business lies, to my mind,/7- mind, in tlie Neutral ^one* On no account must tills be allowed to be used as a pawn by either Bin Baud, the Shaikh of Kuwait, or Holmes, without His Majesty's Government's permission, for whoever gets the Heutral Zone will clearly get the Kuwait Oil concession# This is certain. BUSHIRE, Lie t.-Colonel, Political Agent, Kuwait. Dated the 7th June 1933COPY Telegram P Prom Secretary of State for Foreign Affairs, London. To H.M’s. Minister, Tedda, No. 71. Repeated to Political Resident, Bushire, No. 3 . Dated 12 th Received 13th Ji^ne 1933. Your telegram No. 110. It is important to know substance of Ibn Baud’s proposals but Shaikh’s recent attitude suggests that he 4 /ill not volunteer information. Would you therefore see objection to Political Resident or Political Agent raising matter with Shaikh should latteijnot mention it soon, provided Fuad Hamza is, if possible, not mentioned as source of information. SECRETARY OF STATE FOR FOREIGN AFFAIRS. Confidential. No. 651-S. of 1933. The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Political ^gent, Kuwait, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the under mentioned documents, with the remark that the Political Agent should not raise the question with His Excellency the Shaikh until a reply is received from Jedda. British Residency and Consulate-General, Bushire, 13th June 1933. Reference to previous correspondence: 64T4-S, dated 10 th June 1933. Bushire P.L. No Description of Enclosure . Name and Date Subject. Foreign Office telegram to H.M’s Minister, Jedda, No. 71, dated 12 th June 1933. Kuwait Blockade. T-^ \ 7 V (i J V. Telegram R. From Political Agent, Kuwait* To Political Resident, Bushire. No. 122. V TO! Dated 19th June 1933. V' Your endorsement No. 644-3 (dated 10th June 1933). Letter from Bin Saud arrived 16th June was at once shown me. Letter so obscurely worded as to be almost untranslateable. Contains nothing about oil, but makes following suggestion for settling blockade dispute. Shaikh to saise his sea customs to same figure as that existigg King’s Hassa ports (i.e. from 4$ to approximately 70%). King in return to take only ,T Khawa TT or tribal tax on caravans going into interior at rate collected in Bin Raschid’s time by certain tribes (which would total Rs. 3 per camel). King urges Shaikh settle business privately and not through His Majesty’s Government, who not to be trusted. Portions in brackets are my comments. Shaikh showed me his proposed reply which states that he unable to raise his existing customs tariff for obvious reasons,but will co-operate to best his power by manifest or other dystem if King will adopt reasonable course of pwiTTc placing customs posts along frontier line. - Political. Telegram R. From Political Agent, Kuwait. To Political Resident, Bushire. No. 123. Dated 19th June 1933. ^ My immediately preceding telegram. Clearly if King’s proposals were followed by Shaikh, existing trade of Kuwait would very soon fee diverted to Hasaa ports. Shaikh in his reply to King only reiterates what he has always asked for t namely t customs posts on frontier with manifest system. - Political.The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to / 1. The Political Agent, Kuwait* 2* The Political Agent, Bahrain. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment (3$. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. /t Pinal Record of a Meeting held at the Colonial Office on the 3rd May 1933, to discuss various questions relating to oil in the Persian Gulf.' f . ; OGPV BENT TO 7 r &gt; f ;'■ ^ ) 'J J'l /„ o H r,.. I V. ^ ^ Pinal Record of a Meeting (edjaurned from the 2bth April) held at the Colonial Office on the 3rd of May, IS33* *© disouse various questions relating to oil in the Persian Gulf. PRISMS?. Mr 0 Parkinson ) ) Mr. Blaster ) ) Mr.Jame a ) Colonial Office. Mr.Rendel ) ) Mr*Johnstone ) Foreign Office. Mr.Laithomite India Office. Captain Moore Admiralty. Mr.Starling Petroleum Department. Lieutenant Colonel Political Resident in the Fowls, Persian Gulf. Captain Prior Indian Political Densrtment. (lately Political Agent at Bahrein).’ I, KIT, A PE, Mr, .Tar kin son called attention to the latest telegram from Kuwait reporting that, on being consulted by the Shaikh regarding the last offer by the Anglo- Persian Oil Company, Major Holmes had immediately offered more favourable terms, on the condition that he should be allowed to submit a new draft concession allotting the 1 , 10 , 2 . them part of Kuwait to the British, and the southern part to the Americans. 2 . General diseussion regarding the intention behind this new proposal showed that there is reason to believe that Major Holmes may have discovered, as a result ofof his explorations for water, that one area lias more oh’ hearing possibilities than the other g and that if is nol out of the question that the part to be allotted to the British might be comparatively unremunerative« From information previously received from the Shaihh it is understood that the British area would comprise 1,300 square miles and the American area 400 square miles, anc that the initial payment in the case of each separate concession would be Be.45,000. 5o Mr* Pa ri: in son asked whether it would be practicable or advisable for Ills Majesty’s Government to intervene at once on the ground that the new proposal to divide Kuwait territory was unacceptable* 4o Mr* Mendel was inclined to think that to take this line might place us in a somewhat invidious posit icn. Moreover, he saw soma difficulty In intervening at this stage when we were unaware of the exact nature of the proposal and had act yet learned the reactions of the Anglo “Persian Oil Company. In any case it would seem desirable* before tendering further advice to the Shaikh, to wait until the respective offers of the competing Companies might be regarded as more or lees final. 5* In reply to a question Mr« Starling said it might be possible, on general principles, to take the Xiru that Kuwait was too small comfort ably to accommodate two i oil concerns. It must, however, be borne in mind that recent indications suggested that British interests might wish to acquire a footing in Bahrein* Bahrein was ccm~ siderably smaller than Kuwait and we should, therefore, '&gt;•' well advised to watch events in Bahrein before vetoing the* new proposal merely on the ground of the smallness of Kuwait iKuwait. Subject, howeTer, to development 9 in BahrQin, be eaw ^0 reaeon wby His Majesty’s Government should not adopt such an attitude with a certain measure of justifloation. 6c The suggestion was made that the Shaikh should he told that he must accept the advice of Hip Majesty’s Government on technical matters. It was pointed out that the Shaikh had f in effect s flatly contradicted the advice tendered by His Majesty’s Government on the technical aspects of the two original draft concessions by asserting that, in his opinion, the Syndicate’s offer, as it stood, was the better. ?« After some discussIon it was agreed that it would not be within the terms of our pledge to insist on the Shaikh accepting our advice, even in technical matters. We could only give him our advice and warn him that by disregarding it he would he endangering Ms own interests. j-'jftP%T. £.9.3- Q kowlp expressed the view that the Shaikh would probably accept advice so tendered. S. L leutenant~C q 1 p ncl Fowle also ©aid that the Anglo-Persian Oil Company were being kept well abreast of al 1 development s. 9« The conclusion was reached 'by the moating that nothing could be done until we had the draft of the new “■'twin 15 concession proposed by Major Holmes, and that it would he desirable to send a telegram to the Acting Resident asking that the draft should be obtained from the Shaikh, ready for the Resident on his arrival at Kuwait. XX* KUWAIT HEUTRAL 20HE. 10. Hr. ParkInson said that recent information from Jeddnh showed that the question of a concession in the neutralIII. neutral ^one again come into prominence* and he presumed that this would he dealt with quite separately from any concession in Kuwait proper* He understood that the ooncessiorA said to haTe heen granted in 1924 by the Shai&amp;h and Ibn Saud had neyer become operative, or was, in any case, now null and void* 11 . It was generally agreed that the ShalXch should he told that he must obtain the approval of His Majesty’s GoTernment before granting any concaasion in the neutral sone. Owing to the preesure exercised by the United States Government he had been told that in the matter of the concession in Kuwait proper the ultimate decision 1 must rest with him; and it was suggested that he mi#it wilfully, or under a genuine misapprehension, aot without freference to His Majesty’s Government in regard to the neutral ?.ohe * 12 * Mr* Kendel expressed the view that we must proceed with some care in the matter* Gur right of control in the neutral gone was less than in Kuwait, and it might consequently be difficult to justify the adoption of a more rigid attitude in rer.ard to the former area than in respect of the latter* 13* It was finally agreed that no written communion tion on the subject should he made to the Shaikh at present, but that the Resident should remind him orally what had actually happened in 1924, when a concession in the neutral £One is said to have been gr r v ted to the Sastem and Gcner.al Syndicate*Ill, QL'Skd. M. The maeting had some further discussion about oil in Qatar s during which it emerged that, in addition to the action approved by the meeting on the 26 th of April, the Shaikh should be reminded of his obligation under Article IT of the 1916 Treaty not to grant any concessions in respect of his territory without the approval of His Majesty^ Government, The Petroleum Department would also take a suitable opportunity to bring the position unofficially to the notice of the Anglo-Persian Oil Company, 15 , In the course of the discussion the posit ion of the Iraq Petroleum Company in respect of oil oonoessixin in the Persian Gulf mentioned, hr. Starling explained that Qatar was one of the territories in the Persian Gulf In which the members of the Iraq Petroleum Company group had undertaken not to seek concessions without the approval of the other members. If the Iraq Petroleum Company insisted in standing on the Agreement this would mean that any concession obtained by the Anglo Persian Oil Company in Qatar ?*ouXd have to be passed on to the Iraq Petroleum Company, In these circumstances, we had to face the possibility that the Ire-q Petroleum Company, which although a British Company, had large foreign interests, might eventually secure a footing in the Gulf* The Petroleum Department had for some time thought that it might be desirable for the whole question to be brought under review ao that all the Departments concerned might be able to consider the matter and Mr, Starling enquired whether it could be considered by theJ «!~' \ the Middle Eastern Suh-Conanitte© of the Committee of Imperial Defence, There was always the possihility that the Iraq Petroleum Company would take the line that their hands were full in Iraq and that they would not interest themselves in these smaller areas in the Gulf* In that event they might allow the Anglo Persian Oil Company which was very interested in the Gulf to take up concessions. (Since the meeting the Petroleum Department has learned unofficially that there are indications that seme of the Groups in the Iraq Petroleum Company are not disposed to support the Iraq Petroleum Company's efforts to secure a concession in Hasa)* 16. Mr,Parkinson said that he thought the Middle Eastern Suh-Committee could deal with the matter* if a memorandum were submitted by the Petroleum Department* or alternatively there oould be an Interdepartmental discussion. It was agreed that the Petroleum Department should initiate any action that might be required in this connection as and when they thought fit, by way of a memorandum which would be sent in the first instance to the Colonial Office. IT. BAHiiEIH . A, Extension of Prospecting licence and Amendments to Mining Lease. 17 , The meeting first discussed whether the Company iB entitled to an extension of their prospecting licence under Article IT of the 1925 Agreement. The Political Agent at Bahrein had called attention to the fact that the Company had used the word 'entitled” in their0 thetr letter of the 4th of April. The wording of Article IV provides that an extei: aion of the prospecting licence up to two years may he granted if the Shaikh on the advice of the Political Resident is satisfied that such an extension is justified. The Acting Resident has stated in a recent telegram that the interpretation is not 'quite free from doubt'. It was therefore decided that, on the whole, it would be better to obtain legal advice on this point, and that suoh advioe had better be sought from the Treasury Solicitor. In the meantime, however, the discussion would proceed on the assumption that the Company were not entitled to an extension. 13. In connection with this point Captain Prior said that Major Holmes knows quite well that the Company cannot claim an extension as a right, and that he had. In fact, urged the Americans to be content with the one yQar*s extension already granted. Captain Prior understands that the relations between the Americans and Major Holmes are not as cordial as they might be. 19. The meeting then discussed the alternative proposal submitted by the Company that in return for the right to select 200,000 instead of 100,000 acres they should make the Shaikh increased annual payments and a loan to be repaid from royalties. 20. Mr. SWling; said that on balance he thought it would be better not to grant the Company the inoreased area. He pointed out that the Company had not.as they should huv© done under the terms of the 1925 Agreement ? seleoted areas when they took up their prospecting XiGance, and it would, in his opinion, he better to insist on their taking out a mining lease, which would involve the selection of areas, and thus leave the field open for another Company,, There were, in fact, recent indications that the Anglo-Persian Oil Company were interested in Bahrein, 21 , Some doubt was felt as to the actual area affected by the concession, The right of exploration had been 'throughout the whole of the territories under his {the Shaikh*s) control', and. the prospecting licence should have been granted over 'Etreas to be selected by the Company'* Accurate information regarding the area of the whole of the Shaikh's dominions was not available, ! but Captafe Prior suggested that a figure of 156,000 acre? would be somewhere near the mark* Captain Prior also said he was given to understand that drilling could be carried out in the open eea at a depth of 15 to 20 feat, 22* It was generally agreed that it would be better not to permit an extension of the Company *3 area, but that another year’s extension of the prospecting licence should be considered and that the revision of the mining lease should be now taken up* *23 • Br» Parlcinaon ti^en aslsed tJae views of the meeting regarding the suggestion which, according to unofficial information, the Bahrein Government had put forward, that in return for the grant of one yesar 5 s extension the Company should make him a lean of Rs ,60,000 •, repayable from royalties when the latter exceeded one X&amp;hh in the year. Be thought the suggestion was worth consideration as the terms of repayment would preclude the Shaikh from getting into financial difficulties with the Company. 24 e After some discussion it was decided that the question of the grant of m extension in 2 ’sturn for a loan to the Shaikh should he linked up with the amendments which His Majesty’s Government desire to see introduced into the mining lease c 25, As regards the desired amendments to the mining lease, Mr^ Starling said that he did not anticipate that the Company would raise strong objections especially as the Agreement had already hoon altered to the advantage of the Company, He explained that it would have been out of place and cumbersome to overload the agreement in the first place with detailed provisions which would only apply if and when the existence of oil in commercial quantities had been proved. This stage had now reached in Bahrein, and all the amendments suggested by the Petroleum department ware such as are commonly found in agreements covering a 'proved* area * 26,■ \ f) (X 0 ^ 26, n, T t,,ln Moore said that the Admiralty attache fl. great iiapohtanca to securing the right of pre-emption ^3 introducing provisions for a proportion of the ^ ° i, 1 ^ i 3f lnsd ^ aaid that the S^h had aiready evinced some interest in the question of oil refining in Bahrein* 27 , xt was finally agreed that a draft letter to the _ Company should he prepared in the Colonial Office, £or th9 concurrence of the other interested Departments, i^jje n et ter would make an offer, as from the Shaikh of Bahrein, of one year's pension of the prospecting licenoe from the 2nd of December 1953 i» retlirn for which the Company would be asked to agree to - (a) A substantial loan to the Shaikh (Us* i» effect, advance royalties) to be repaid, without interest, from royalties over a period of 3 5 y ears wbea the latter exceedecl one in the ysax% Oj) ’Dhe amendments to the mining xea^e suggested hy the Petroleum Department* When approved the draft letter would be sent to the Persian Gulf for the concurrence of the local British authorities and the Shaikh of Bahrein. fhe amount of the loan would not be specified in the letter, but would be left for subsequent negotiations with the Company, B* Driller a*. 23. .. «,» U»*. »• P “” M proposes «• «»*• »P «“• 5&lt;‘“ ,1 « n Wh Ballaesyee .ea Kr.I-Wrti. «M J«* “«* ' inter^i®^interslewo © u v Majo r Holmee 9 Residence in Bahrein, *' i -mm m+t+m iv --•&gt;.,-mtrM ~r*^-~r4erv*.--wrt~xi&gt; 2 9* Mr, Laithwalte uientioned that Captain Prior had expressed the opinion that, if Major Holmes were required to reside in Bahrein for, aay # ten months in eyeiy year ? he would probably resign the appointment, if only for reasons of health. If this was so P insistenoe on suoh a period of residenoa might well be the easiest way out of our difficulties, MrJBlaxter mentioned that it had bean understood from ora * L discussions wiiih the representatives that they would prefer to avoid a fized period being laid down during which their Local Representative must reside in Bahrein. 3 0 - Mr,Parkinson said he would prefer not to take any action in this matter until he had had an opportunity of studying the statement of the facts which was to be dra?m up as the result of the discussions at the meeting of the 26 th of April,The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to 1, Poreiftn Secretary to the Oovernm^nt of India, P. Pia llajeaty’F Minister, Jedda. Name and Date. /k^ Ko.39, Subject. Bushire desnatch Ho.39, datelcl tilt 16th I'nne 1933, to His Majesty’s Secretary of ntate for the Colonies, with enclosure. Copy, with copy of coropl with coispliipents ,to the I’d informs ete enclosures, forv/arded, y itical Agent, Kuwait, for t fo n. K1PTAIT OIL. trTHOTS on the Euwait Oil situation as X see it in the light of His Majesty's Minister.Jedda’ s telegram Ho. 124, dated the 5th June 1933, to Bushire (110 to London). -*****#* 1 . The news that Bin Baud has addressed a letter to the Shaikh of Birwait propounding certainpro posals of a commercial nature which can he counted on to give the Shaikh satis faction, is most important, and as I read it means that Bin Saud is now definitely going to enter the lists in the matter of 'Kuwait Oil M . g. It entirely confirms vfriat I rather foresaw was coming, Tide my Confidential letter Ho.80,(copy forwarded to Colonial Office (Ho.28), Government of India and His Majesty’s Minister,Jedda (No.454-S) under BuEfaire Mnted letter dated the 2nd May 1933), dated the 27th April, to Bushire, although the granting of the Hassa Oil concession to the Standard Oil Company, not then visualized, some- what confuses the issue* 3 . I think we may for a start, disabuse our minds of the idea that the king has any sort of ’♦feelings' for the distressed condition of the people of Kuwait, seeing that it is his blockade of the last 10 years which has brou^it them to this Dass thev are in. 4 Majesty’s Minister, Jedda, is the correct interpretation of #iat is going to happen, and the king now thinks the time ripe for establishing his political ascendancy orer Kuwait/\X -a- Kuwait under the guise of an Oil agreement. 5 . The plan of campaign to he adopted (part of which we have seen develop as helow) will, X believe, he somewhat on the following lines (a) It has heen pretty clearly established now that Tdien the ShaiKh went into the Held desert on the SOth and 25th February last, (see my Secret No. I, dated the 5th March 1933 - copy forwarded to •~V, \V&lt; Colonial Office (No.19), Government of India and \ '''lV His Majesty's Minister ,Jedda (No.220-S under 1 &gt; ^ . Bushire Printed letter dated the 16th March 1933 - he met the king himself who was then 80 miles north of Hafar al Atz, hunting,( or possi'bly hie son the Amir Saud, not Saud al Arafa as reported at the time). At this meeting details of the mode of procedure to he adopted were, I helieve, discussed, and cpite prohahly emanated from the Shaikh of Kuwait in the first instance. (h) The Shaikh prohahly pointed out that Kuwait was on the verge of collapse due to the blockade and must obtain relief. The king expressed willing ness to afford such relief provided the Shaikh would join forces in an Oil agreement, details of which would he submitted later. Both States would thus benefit equally. (c) The Shaikh prohahly went on to say that in the matter of the competing Oil Companies at Kuwait he himself the whole was rather inclined to favour Holmes/Holmes and his American 'backers. (d) Tiie king no doubt replied that he also favoured the Americans before the Anglo-3?ersian Oil Company and that if the Shaikh and he combined to keep the Anglo-Persian Oil Company out, not only would both reap an advantage, but he, Bin Saud, would be pre pared to relax the blockade and champion Kuwait in her difficulties with ’Iraq. (e) Behind the Shaikh’s mind was the pleasing idea of getting relief from the blockade, and assisting Major Holmes and his Americans to get into Kuwait. Behind Bin Saud’s mind was the plan to get the Standard Oil Company (also Holmes) into the Mkh K uwait lieutral Zone, and then using this as a lever, get them into Kuwait as well, which would give him the ascendancy he had for so long sou^it over the Shaikh of Kuwait. 6. ^hen followed certain moves in the game which we know subsequently took place. (a) Bin Saud invited certain foreign Oil Representatives to come to Jedda to negotiate an Oil agreement, etc. (t&gt;) Major Koines who represented the Eastern and General Syndicate limited in Kuwait and the Standard Oil in Bahrain was also invited by special telegram to go to Jedda* This he did. 7. As a result of negotiations mentioned in (e) above, the Hasaa Concession has been given to the Standard Oil Com any of America,/12./ America, vide Jed&amp;a 'telegram of 30th. May 1933, (No*108 to 5*0reign Office, 122 to Bushire). 8* There is little doubt in my mind that the Hassa Concession in respect of area especially, will he virtually the same as was given to Major Holmes in 1923 and which later lapsed. The important point for us to consider being that it will almost certainly have included in it the Kuwait Neutral Zone. 9. The next step will;clearly he for Bin Saud to get the Shaikh of Kuwait to give his consent to the Standard Oil working in the Neutral Zone. * /I 10. Bin Saud, in the letter which he has now addressed to the Shaikh of Kuwait, (Jedda telegram No.124 to Bushire, dated 5th June 1933), will no doubt suggest to the Shaikh that he has noticed the distressed condition of Kuwait with pain, and th&amp;t he will be prepared to ease off the blockade at once either entirely or in part, if he, the Shaikh, will agree to give his consent to the Standard Oil working the Neutral Zone* Brobably also he will suggest that the Shaikh receive a certain share In the oil profits of the Hassa concession, as a result of meeting him in this matter. 11. Any difficulties that might have arisen between the Eastern and General Syndicate Limited and the Standard Oil (both represented by Holmes) in the matter of the exploita tion of the Neutral Zone have probably already been arranged; and Holmes f visit to Bin Saud at Je&amp;da was no doubt partly connected with such adjustment.-5- 12* Bin Saud vfill no doubt now expect the Sh&amp;ilch, as per plan already made, to reply agreeing with hie rec^est,(in spite of the fact that the ^Political Resident on his recent visit to Kuwait reminded the Shaihh that he must ma3ce no decision in regard to the Neutral Zone without reference to His Faj esty’s Government). 13. The Shaikh will no doubt secretly give his consent to Bin Saud and then tell His Majesty’s Government that he desires their permission to agree to Bin Saud’s conditions, seeing that the benefits to be gained will he of such vital importance to Euwait. 14. Bin Sand for his part will doubtless guarantee the Shaikh to get His Majesty’s Government to put no difficulties in the Shaikh’s way. 15. Bin Saud at one stroke will (a) please Kuwait by settling the blockade question (b) please His Majesty’s Government by so doing (c) get the Americans into the Neutral Zone. 16* Then will follow the last and final move* Bin Saud will probably then inform the Shaikh that it will be quite impossible for him, the Shaikh, to give the Kuwait Oil Con cession to the Anglo-Bersian Oil Company, and that he must settle the matter in favour of Major Holmes and the Ameri cans - his official reasons will he that to have the Standard Oil working alongside of the Anglo-Persian Oil Oospany as rivals in the same area will create an impossihle situation. It will further he pointed out that the sus- peo ed oil is in Horth Hassa and the Neutral Zone, and the port/( U(f port of Kuwait will be needed for the export of such oil. 17. Lastly it will he pointed out that the prosperity of Kuwait will he aesured for all time with (a) the blockade removed; (h) a percentage of Oil revenues from Hass a going into the Shaikh's pocket; (c) the Shaikh getting all the profits from his Kuwait proper oil profits. 18. It may at this stage he even suggested as a farther w bait ,, &gt; that if the Standard Oil (Holmes) get Kuwait as well as assa, all profits from Hassa, Heutral Zone and Kuwait may he pooled between Kuwait and Saudiyeh. 19* The final result, if everything fnx&gt; es according to plan, will he a close rapprochemen t between Kuwait and Saudiyeh, and the secret transference of our political ascendancy over Kuwait, to Bin Baud. Hor will the honour and prestige of Kuwait, in the eyes of the Arab world, be impaired. SO • the above is I think not very far short of what is in tne wind to-day. The crux of the whole business lies, to my mind,in the 3eutral Zone. On no account must this be allowed to be used as a pawn by either Bin Saud, the Shaikh of Kuwait, 0 r Holmes, without His Majesty's Goyern- ment's permission, for whoever gets the Heutral Zone will clearly get the Kuwait Oil concession. This is certain BOSHIHB, Dated the 7th June 19 33. (Bd 0 ) H„P.P.T)i 0 ]c BO fl # Lieut .-Colonel Political Agent, Kuwait.GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. Department. EXPRESS LETTERs [SB. —This is an ORIGINAL message sent hy AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more expeditions than the oldinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended Vo he treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had hcen telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer of the Department?^ No - 679 - s of 1933 -zw 3!*% 17th June, ^33, To - From - Political Besident, Bus hi re« To - Political, Bahrain. fro^olitlcal, Kuwait. 1933. Shaildi of Kuwait’s visit to Bahrain. It is quite possible that Shaikh of Kuwait’s visit is not unconnected with the subject of Oil since with grant of J 'V Hasa Concession to Standard Oil ( vide Residency -Printed Better Ro. 580-S, dated the 31st Hay 1933), Kuwait and Bahrain Oil questions are to some extent becoming interlocked, especially as we believe that there is a scheme on the part of Ibn Sa’ud and the Shaikh of Kuwait to endeavour to include the Kuwait Neutral Zone in the Hasa Concession. . Sd/- T.C.Fbwle. Lieut-Col., Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Attested. ;tary to the Pol for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. s 44. DCFP—33S&amp;P—(G-37)—25-5-31—15,000. (Signature) (Designat ion)CONFIDENTIAL. No - 688-B of 1933. The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to la The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, Girala* 2* The Political Agent, 'Kuwait „ 3* The Political Agent, “B^rain. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment /// British Residency and Consulate-General, BUS II IRE. Dated SOttv ■ '.Tune- • • Reference to previous correspondence: Bushire tinted letter Noa580~S of 31st Hay 1933, Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Savin gram dated let «Tune 1933 from His Majesty’s Minister, Jed da ► Ha»a Oil Concession.Sarin gran 'from To ^epaat e&amp; Dated 1st Company of California, left May 31st intending to proceed very leisurely to London* 1 have no knowledge of Sviss and Italian competitors, mentioned on page 5 of enclosure to Mushire despatch Mo*S8 to Colonial Office* I had heard of possible non-British European competitors including, I think, French but only in vaguest terms* I think that in report quoted in preceding paragraph Dickson underestimates affect of icing 1 s dislike of Holmes* It is increasingly probable that latter came here in April with primary object of securing Ibn Saud f s assent to concession in Kuwait Ifeutral £one and fo and that there was nothing doing in that direction. He may rlso have discovered, however, that he was not persona grata for any purpose except apparently enlargement of field of competitors for Hasa concession* his might explain his rapid departure at moment when King was expected to visit »Tedda within a few days* These considerations may have a bearing on future developments in connection with Kuwait and Neutral Zone concessions if there is any foundation r’br Dickson’s surmise that Shaikh of Khwait and Ibn Sand have been exchanging views about oil. King perhaps hopes one day to reduce/ P. K.M.’s Minister, ledda. Secretary of State for foreign Affairs, London. Ho.10-Saving. Political Resident, Bushire. ( received 19th ) lune 1933. b.*b My telegram Ho.168. Hamilton, representative of Standard Oilreduce Kuwait to position of Mb vassal. Ha bjIitM wall wish therefore to influence Hhaildh’s policy in a sense adverse to Anglo-^ersian Oil Company hut not necessarily favourable to Holmes. Might he not prefer to see standard Oil Company of California, who are already in Bahrain and have now got concession for Hasa Coast, cut out all present candidates for Kuwait and Heutral Kone including Eastern Culf to shich Holmes is committed in respect of these two areas? This is of course mere conjecture as I do not know whether Standard Oil Company of California wculd themselves wish to enter further areas in question. • BYAN -P. A / The Following notice Appears on t3ie w lIM-AIXURA.' paper dated the 8th Safar 1352, and 2nd June 1933. FORMAL NOTICE NO. 12 On Monday the 29th May 19 33, the Minister of Finance and the representative of the Standard Oil Co., of California agreed to give the Oil Concession to the latter, which is in the Eastern territories of the Kingdom According to the terms of the Contracts, and they will he published shortly after ±hs agreement of both the Government and the Company. '“f ^ ^ iA.yiA^ irfi. ^5 i urThe Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to 1 * 'The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, Simla* P. 'Hie Political Agent, Kuwait* and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment (s). British Residency and Consulate-General, BUSH IRE. Dated.. ^une 1933* Bushire ^rinted letter Ro Reference to previous correspondence: »669-S o: f 16th June 1933* Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. 1 * Telegram Ko.7 of 20th June 1933 from Hie Majesty’s Secretary of HState for the Colonies. ST^Bushire telegram No* 14 of 21st June 1933 to His Majesty’s Secretary of State for the Colonies. CtriUiL, jU* l 'J- Vj. 6 1 j Subject. Kuwait Oil and t 'X* Blockade* ♦ 0 J &lt;1^I ( 5 ?) -k!- Shaikh. It would not be advisable, however, for you to raise these two points with the Shaikh at present, but if you merely ask him whether he signed the concession he may volunteer more information of his own accord. Lieut .-Colonel, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. (\K- (JJijz, ^ ujvk fa***. ur ^ ^ L£t, hju t ywru. ^ TTo) yrf' 2 ‘ U^lrU^- ^ ^ •CONFIDENTIAL. No * 718-S of 1933. The Hon’ble the Political Pesiclent in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to. 1. 'Tie Political Bahrain. S. 'Tie Political Apent, Kuwait, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned dccu- ment (/y./ with special reference to paragraph 5 * British Residency and Consulate-General, BUS II IRE. &gt;73 Dated.... ^Ath*. Jvuie* .1.9.33'tf • • Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date, Subject. Bushire despatch Ho.41 of 24th June- 1933 to His Maj esty* 3 Secretary of State for the Colonies, London^with emclosures, Boundaries of Qatar.cmnm^'iAL. Britiah B» 8 identty &amp; Consulate -fkmera!, Buahtre, the 04th June, 1933# Hsuil of 1933. ZpmMrM.n p.f Sir# t have the honour to state that in view of the grant of the Haea Oil Concession to the ^Standard Oil Company of California aM of the negotiations entered into hy the Anglo-Aroian Oil Company Limited for an Oil Concession in Qatar# the early determination of the boundaries of Qatar is desirable. 0. In lorimer’s Oasetteer of the Persian Oulf (Volume IX page 1806) the Southern boundary is described as commencing at the foot of I&gt;obat as Salwa and proceeding South Hast wards to the wells of ^alcab. ^lienee two alternatives are mention*- ed, with a preference for the latter (i) striking iHast-Horth- Bast to the Berth end of the Baqlyan hills (ii) last hy South to the Southern end of the same hills on the North side of the entrance to '^hor al ’Odaid. 3* On his return from the Ojair Conference at the end of 1900 Sir ^ercy Cox# High Commissiomr for ♦Iraq, informed the Political Resident in the terms of memorandum Ho.947-0 of 20th Tecember 1900 (copy attached)from the tinder Secretary to the Political Resident to the Political Agent, Bahrain* r, his is the only record on my files of the arrangement come to between Sir &gt;rcy Cox and I bn Saud. x enclose in this connection a copy of a letter Ho./ His Majesty's Secretary of State for the Colonies# ^he Colonial Office# £ s. e &amp; sl a.H© .1.0*10, di&amp;tea th« 10th January 1983, from the Ha ere t ary to HI a Woollen cy thr Vl$h Cowniaolomr for ’Iran to the Secrotary to the SoTorraiert of India in the '^oreipn and Political department. If this line ie accepted ao the boundary between Saudi Arabia and |atar it would ^ire the Shaildi of r £atar a wider extent of territory than either of the two boundaries* mentioned in the Gazetteer. In any case the southern point at which this line terminates and the southern boundary line remain for determination. 3. Ho farther information is available on my records. I am, however, enquiring from the Political Agent, Bahrain, and Colonel lesson, the blit leal Agent, Kuwait, (the latter of whom accompanied Sir Percy Cox on Ms mission to Ojair), whether they can furnish any additional information. I am also asking the blit leal Agent, Pah rain, to enquire from the Shaikh of Qatar without expressing any opinion on the point what he - the Shaikh - considers to be the boundaries of his territory. 6. References are to Eraser Hunter’s Map of Arabia and the Persian Oulf (Beale l n to 32 miles), I am sending copies of this despatch to the (rovem- mtnt of India and His Majesty’s Minister, Jedda. I have the honour to be, Sir, Tour most obedient, humble servant, (Sgd.) T.C.Powle, uieut.-Colonel, blit leal feel dent in the brsi an (hilf.OoT)y Ho.94^*3 of 19?3c British Besidercy ard Consula-rreneral, Busltire. 90th Becemher 1992. Hie Political Aprent, Bahrain.. BoimPAKY mrwmjs najb abb oa^ab . Me mo randum. Reference correspondence ending with'this office endorsement No. 944 -3, dated 17th December 1927. I am directed to inform you that His Excellency Sir ■Percy Cox told the Resident that Saud had agreed to a boundary between Hajd and Qatar, which follows a line running due South from the end of the bay South of Bahrain Island and passing just E of Mabak as shown on ' r raBer Hunter’s map. (Sd. W. nifTILDAM, Cap&gt; tain , Hnder Secretary to the 'Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.Copy. TTo.I.O./lO. Secretariat of H.E. the High Cornni b a io ne r for ’I raq. Baghdad, the 19th January 1923. I am directed to reply to foreign Bepartnent letter ITo• 1262/65 2 -TSxt. dated '’th Becemher on the subject of the apparent inclination of His Highness Ihn Sa’ud to ahaorh the Q.at ar pri n ci pa 1 i ty. 2 . r,, he High Commissioner had recently spent some days with His Highness (from ' ?7 th Hovemher to 2 nd Becember) during whiclt the status of Qatar was in evidence in connection wi+ha project, under consideration by Tbn Sa’ud, for the grant of an Oil Concession for a tract of Hajd territory. Sir Percy Cox found that in his discussion with the Engineer representing the aspirant con cess ionnaires His Highness had apparently included the Qatar peninsula within the tract of country for which he was prepared to negotiate a concession - Sir Percy Cox at once took him to task, reminding him that he had nothing to do with Qatar except to respect it, under the terms of his treaty with us, and insisting on the limi&amp;.tion of his discuss ions t o country West of the longitude of the head of Sal wall Bay. / The Sultan accepted this injunction without argument and the High Commissioner accordingly doubts whether a further communication on the subject is necessary or, indeed, advisable after so short, an interval. He will be fully prepared however to return to the attack if there should be any fresh evidence of a disposition on the part of the Sultan to encroach upon Q^tar. A copy of this communication is being forwarded to the Bes iden t/_ o_ Resident iT» the -^erBian (rulf. I have the honour to he, Sir, Tour most obedient serfant, (Sd. B. H. Bourdiilon. Secretary to F.B.the High Coranissioner for ’Iraq. Secretary to the Government of India in the foreign and Political department, BelhioIRESS LETTER f his is an OHIGINAL MJEISSAG^E, sent by post to save' telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires* but intended to le treated* on receipt* with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched. 1 ] r vyn f j f ; '. f 0 Feom PaUtical Bahrain To Resident,Bushire Political,Kuwait• Bated 25th June ^3 % vvi of Kuwait in conversation told Adviser to Bahrain No. 0/228 Government that Bin Sa’ud had given American Oil Company concession over his territory. He was very heated about it and said that if Company 'thought they could drill in his territory they were mistaken. 2. kn thought it curious that Company should take up Concession from Bin Sa^d M an&amp; heirs” as Sa*udi Arabia would collapse at his death if not before. 3. Shaikh also rather laboured to Adviser idea of kinship and friendship between Kuwait and Bahrain as opposed to H&amp;ja and said that there had never been hostilities between Kuwait and Bahrain as there had been with Kajd. 4. I understand that Muhammad Yatia,Major Holmes’ man*is applying for visa for London. He baa had a telegram from Major Holmes in London 5. Addressed Bushire,repeated Kuwait. v xheut-Colonel. flrt- s - 8 . Maipc^FP- 596 DCP-is&amp;p—(G- 1807 )— 7 * 4 *i 7 —?,oo,ooo. Political Agent,Bahrain. Telegram G.T.C. From Political, Kuwait. To Britconsul, Bushire. No. 134. Dated the 28th June 1933. \4s ' v 1 M'* Reference Bahrain 5 25th June first paragraph. I think Shaikh referred to territory, which formerly belonged to Kuwait but nov/ is administered by Bin Saud. -POLITICAL-1 I CONFIDENTIAL. No * 726-P&gt; of 1933&lt; The Hon ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to !• The Foreifto Becretar^r to the (lOTerrment of India, Binla, S* ''he Political After!t, Kii'wait, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment ^^ British Residency and Consulate-General, BUSHIRE, Dated..,, artH'hTuhe Reference to previous correspondence: Bushire Printed letter of Plat &lt;Tune 1933. Description of Enclosure* Name and Date. .'■I® ^oliticai Resident’s despatch Ho.43, dated the P?th June 1933, to His Kajesty’s Secretary of State for the Colonies, London.cmnmwiM'. Britiah BealdaTicy ^ Congtaeta-Oenaral. BiMiMra* the «Ttme 1933* .43 of 1933® Puhlect : Kuwait Oil* ,V Sir. In continuation of ray teleRrara Mo.14. dated the Slat June 1933, I hare the honour to report that In addition to the Item wentioned in that telepram. in the interview which Colonel Mckeon and I had with the Shaikh I took the opportunity of reminding the Shaikh &gt;the coneideratione contained in your teleprara Ho.9, dated the sand eeentoer 1932.i.e. * the shaikh ehould he made fully aware,i.e. hy oral explanation, that if conceaeion i« granted to Worn and General Syndicate it raewna that it will he trnneferred to a Company controlled hy foreign oaaital even though nominally Britieh and auhject only to whatever raeaauree of over-riding British control way hereafter he decided uoon. while concession to taglo-^ereian Oil Company will eneur. entire British control'. I nleo reminded the Shaikh that whoever got the Concession Hie Majesty's Government would have various safeguards for inclusion in the agreement. Th, Shaikh - so Colonel Bickaon informed me - lu^agaiil to Verp him - Colonel ^ickoon - in the shown Biimn of trying to dark shout the Oil negotiation.. I again reminded the B^oFth. necessity of keeping the 'olitical Agent informed on this matter (in this eonneotion see paragre* 2 of mv express letter Mo.C-13, dated the 6th -Wuarv 1933/ Majesty's Secretary of ^tate for the Colonies. r, he Colonial Office, Lnndon.1953 (copy forwarded to the Ooverrment of ndia under Beeideney Printed letter Ko.C-15 of eawe dote). 1 aaked the WmiKh how he felt about the ccBinunlca- tion which I underetood Sir John Gadwan had made to hi» on the latter’e vleit to r uwait: i.e* that If the conceafllon went to the American Company the Anglo-^eraian f'il Company Limited - in their own interesta - would he compelled to make a local ’ oil war f on the said Company. Hie Shaikh confirmed that this eoMsunication had been made to him by Bir John Cadman 0 and also by Hr. 'Slkington, who waa then in Kuwait t but that he - the Bhaikh - felt that thio concerned the American Company and not himaelf. Hie Company (auppoa- in^ they got the concession) would have to pay him the a^sma, and the royalties, due under their agreement, artl if b^ reason of the ’ oil war * they were unable to carry on their work, their plant, etc. - under the a&lt;*reement - would heccne his property, and he could lease the concession to some other Company. Hiere seemed to me a |?ood deal in what the Bhaildi said. 3. I informed the Shaikh that 1 had heard that there was considerable dissatisfaction amongst the numerous members of his family as he was keeping them completely in the dark as to his oil negotiations. He was, of course, the ^ler, but in these days public opinion counted for a good deal, and public opinion in Kuwait was represented largely by the Subah family. Whichever party he finally gave the concession to, would it not be wise to take this t public opinion ’ more into his confidence ? The Shaikh replied/«»3* replied that he never eonflulted hie fauaily tm any matter. (This ie quite true; it ie one of hie neRkneeeee that hie rule ie n * one man’e show H t unlike that of the Sultan of Muscat, for instance, who makes nee of the members of his family to assist him in his administration). As far as the Oil Concession was concerned, said the Shaikh* whatever decision he come to, he would see to it that his family followed suit, The fftmildi’a attitude in this matter did not appear to me a particularly sensible one, hut I did not pursue the matter further. 4. 1 asked the ^haikh how he felt about an amalgama tion between the rival parties, supposing they decided amongst themselves at any stage that this would be more economical than to continue bidding against each other. He seemed to be confident that what ever Imppenec. ir *hxs direction he could manage affairs to his own advantage. I am sending a copy of this despatch to the Government of India. I have the honour to be, Bir, Your most obedient, humble servant, (Sgd.) T, C. Fowle, I4eut.-Colonel, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.&gt; ~ ^ Vfrl 7 v COHFI DS^ITIAL. Ho.143 POLITICAL AGENCY, I0DWAIT. Dated the 4th July 1933, From Lt.-Colonel Y.B.P.Dickson, C.I.E., I.A., Political Agent, Kuwait; To The Hon’ble the Political Besident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire, Boundaries of QATAB. Sir, J* M With reference to your No.718-S, dated the 24th June 1933 and paragraph 5, I have the honour to confirm i that I was present at the Ojair negotiations held between Sir Percy Cox and the then Sultan of Nejd (now H.M.King Abdul Aziz as Saud) from November 27th to End December 1922. jv l S' 2 * I perfectly well remember the incident referred to in Baghdad No.10/10, dated the 19th January 1923 to the Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, copy of which you have now sent me. 3. It happened after Sir Percy Cox had, after a five days personal struggle with Bin Saud, got his own way in the matter of the Iraq - Hejd frontier line, and Bin Saud was in very chastened mood in consequence. 4. The question of Major Holmes Hassa Concession had just come up for discussion, before the conference broke up, (Major Holmes was himself present)| and Bin Baud had produced before Sir Percy Cox, Hunters map of Arabie 1 ' to 32 miles, which, if my memory serves me right, belonged to Major Holmes. On it was marked in blue peneil, the area- 2 - area which Bin Saud proposed to grant to the Eastern &amp; Gene ral Syndicate for their concession* This area included the whole of the Hassa province and the Qjatar peninsula - the south western and southern boundary of the concession being marked on the map by a line drawn down the Wadi Faruq. as far as Jaw al Dukhan and then turning East from there to Khor Ad Dhuwaihin on the sea* 5* Sir Percy Cox, when he saw how the proposed line was made to include Qatar, drew a red pencil line from Jaw al Dukhan to Dohat Salwa, (the head of the bay to the south of Bahrain Island)and said 'that is the line'* He subsequently crossed out with the same red pencil the line as marked in by Lajor Holmes, i.e. to I hor Ad Dhuwaihin. 6. As far as I remember, Sir Percy Cox showed con siderable annoyance at this barefaced attempt on the part of both Major Holmes and Bin Saud, to bluff him, and explain ed to the latter that on no account could he include in any concession any of the country lying to the East of 'AHBAIP 1 (not MABAK as mentioned in Hunters map, though it is the same j;lace). This indeed is borne out by Bushire No«947- &gt;dated the 20th December 1922, to the Political Agent, Bahrain, copy of which has been sent me* 7, If the more accurate maps of man Thomas and Phi Toy are studied it will be^ found that ANBAK lies ik B0U th west of Idior Odelfl and nor/west and slightly north as in Hunters map. ?or this reason, if the deliniation of the yatar - Nejd frontier becomes necessary, I would suggest that the boundary follow the line Boh al Salwa - Hhor al Dhuwaihin. The wells of illBAK being made common to both. t the same time, though this sounds contradictory, I have always held the Tiew that tribal boundaries willCONfIDKNmL. POLITICAL AGENCY, KUWAIT. NO.146. Dated the 6th July 1933. To The Hon*hie the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, B U S H I R 1 * Kuwait - Me id Neutral Pons Oil Concession of 1924. M In reply to your Confidential memorandum No. 715-S, dated the S3rd June: S, X heg to say that I saw the chaikn this morning ( 6 . 7 . 33 ) j^^after we had discussed his Bahrain visit, which hy the way, he was very pleased with, 1 managed catiously to bring round the conversation to the Kuwait - iiejd Neutral Zone Oil Concession of 1924. 5. The Shaikh showed no inclination to keep any thing hack and quite frankly made the following points, without my having to ask for them:- (a) Bin Saud, as far as he remembered, gave the Has -a Concession proper to major Holmes Company in the Spring of 1923&lt;My files say May 6th 1923) Its chief clause was that unless ‘Major Holmes started work within o year^, the Concession would lapse. (b) Bin Baud wrote in the Summer of 1923 (my files say 28 th June) and sent him the draft joint Concession in respect of the Kuwait Neutral Zone, ^ (Bin Saud) wished to give to ajor Holmes Company, Th« Eastern &amp; General Syndicate, and asked him (the Shaikh) to sign it. At the same/2 same time Bin Baud intimated that whatever he (the Shaikh) decided on, he (Bin Baud) intended giving a concession for his share of the Neutral Zone to the Eastern &amp; General Syndicate# He (c)/(the Shaikh)replied to Bin Sands letter that he quite approved of the draft agreement, but that he must get Eis Majesty’s Government’s say that he duly asked the Political Agent to refer the matter to His Majesty’s Government# (d) After some months, His Majesty’s Government informed him (the Shaikh) (my files say this was on 1st April 1924) that he could go ahead and sign the joint concession (my files say this was done on 5th April 1924). (g) The actual draft concession signed by him (the Shaikh) consisted of only 4 pages of writing 0as far as he could remember)and was duly sent to Bin Sand. (The Shaikh offered to give no details as to clauses etc. and I did not ask for any#) (f) About one year afterwards or possibly less Major Holmes had a disagreement with Bin Baud in connection with a certain date mentioned in the body of the above mentioned Joint Con cession# Bin Sand wished h but he (Major Holmes) ref us so. After a sharp passage informed Major Holmes that Zone Concession was there s Bin Baud apparently took a^i Concession which Major Koln to return it ag 0 ! 11 * (g) Prom that day to thisAhmad had assmed the Joint Concession to be a dead letter; (that is to say from about April 1925). 4. I did not think it wise in view of your warning to pursue the subject further. 5. The Shaikh and I then talked about the latest grant of a Concession in Hassa to the Standard Oil Com pany. The Shaikh said he had tried hard to find out whilst in Bahrain, what were the terms and extent of the Concession, but without success. He did, however, hear from the Manager of the Bahrain Oil Company that the Company had promised Bin Baud a £20,000 a loan at once for 1933, and possibly another loan in 1934 (the latter point he was not sure of). if 6. On my asking the Shaikh^he had heard in any way at all whether Bln Saud had included the Neutral Bone in the Hassa Concession, the Shaikh replied that he did not know, and all his efforts to find out had so far failed. He thought it quite possible, however, that Bin Saud might have included the Neutral Bone, and would tell the Americans that he could 'sousre' the Shaikh of Kuwait later, on the strength of his having once before got his (the tshaikhs) agreement and signature in iyM to a similar Joint Concession. Colonel, Political Agent, Kuwait\j „ (-7^ CONFIDENTIAL. ^ 0 . 787-G of 1933, $6 Tlie Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to lie ''Vlitleal Age111 Luwait #‘ a • %, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment British Residency and Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated .* 1 ’ r»«;»«vu .&lt; Reference to previous correspondence: Description of Enclosure Name and Date. India Office Memorandum da' ed the On cl June 1933 Lnnnfidential&gt; MSIORANEUM, SIT OIL, Mr. Starling of the Petroleum Depe.rtment and Mr. Hearn of the Anglo-Persian Oil Company called at the Indih. Office on 2nd June to discuss informally the latest developments in the Kov/eit oil concession and to consider the line to he taken. 2. Mr. Hearn read telegrams from the local representatives of the A.P.O.C. in the Persian G-ulf. From these telegrams it appeared that the Sheikh had telegraphed a message of congratulation to Sir Jonn Cadman on the satisfactory outcome of the A.P.O.G. negotiations in Persia and had received an extremely cordial reply, the local effects of which had been considerable. The local. A.P.O.C. representatives indicated that in the light of the Sheikh*s reactions to this reply they thought there was some possibility of very rapid developments in the near future as regards Koweit oil. Prom remarks dropped eg uie Sheikh they thought, indeed, that there was some possibility of his making a statement of interest on or about the time of the King’s Birthday. H.E. had further touched on the possibility of a visit to England ana tne question whether if he came as the guest 01 the A.r.O.o. he would be recognised officially* me loml representatives of the Company were anxious go Know whet.uer anything encouraging to the Sheikh am likely uo mm him take the decision desired by them coula oe said ana in particular whether they might oe authorised go off ex him a visit and to make any statement as regards official recognition in this event. 3. Mr. Hearn had recently attended an inter departmental meeting in connection with the steps being2 &gt; - &lt;;&gt; taken W the A.P.O*C. and the I.F.C. to secure a definite concession in Qatar at which the general position seems to have been discussed with some freedom. Mr. Starling had, apart from this, given him generally to understand the ■position as regards Koweit. I said in the first place, that as regards the King’s Birthday, the Sheikh had received a K.C.I.ih very recently and there was, I understood, no question of an immediate further honour for him. The objections from the point of view of our understanding with the United States Government to giving him a special further honour at this juncture were patent. Mr. Hearn said he fully appreciated this. 4. As regards the visit home, I briefly referred to the I discussions which had previously taken place, of the general I sense of which Mr. Hearn was aware. I said that, anxious as we mi ant dq on general grounds tfmt tne A. a snoulo. succeed in getting this concession, we were quite definitely tied by the undertakings we had given to tne United States Government to give a fair field and no favour and tnnt it was obviously most important to take no step which could admit of misinterpretation. In these circumstances it was impossible not to feel that if the A.P.Q.C. were now formally to invite the Sheikh to England and he were to accept, and if on fop of I this H.M.G. were to extend official recognition to him and |possibly offer him some hospitality, fnat tne Americans, ■probably already by no means satisfied ox our ppna^fjhsn, |would regard it as a deliberate attempt on our part to [exercise influence, in a manner contrary to our undertakings, | in favour of the British company concerned. Miile 1 coula not | say what the view of the Foreign Office was likely to be, it seemed Improbable that it would differ from this and I thought it in the circumstances definitely preferable tnat tne greatest caution should be exercised as regards °-xy oUg&amp;eotion I: idTV O of 8-H invitation 'by tile A*r.u»C» .ii they decided in favour oi giving such un invitnoion before tne Sneikh nud nuide up his mind noout the concession x uid noo think thut officio,! recognition of the .Sheikh during his visit could be accorded by H.M.G. 5. ii , on the otrier hand, the Sheikh were, as the telega urns i ead oy fji • lie am suggested mignt, in one view of the local representatives of the A.P.O.C., be possible, by kny chance uo iliaxvc uu iixs ii-ind in one xmiieciia oe xuture in favour of the AtP.C.C. , the obstacles to a visit home and to official recognition of the Sheikh during such a visit would be very substantially reduced. But even in such circumstances it would seem definitely preferable from the point of view of our relations with the American Government that no visit should take place until a decent interval after the grant of the concession to British interests. Mr. Hearn .after some further discussion agreed that, having regard to the position adopted vis-a-vis the United States Government by it was undesirable to take any attitude different from that suggested in the conversation and proposes, I understand, to reply to his representatives in tne rersian Gulf that the greatest care must be exercised as regards urg extension of an invitation; that it should not be used at this stage; and that in tne event ox tne SheiKh granting the concession oo the A#P.0.0. it would be preferable that the visit, if it took place, should be only after a decent interval. 6. Ciatar concession . Mr. Hearn alluded to the discussion which had recently taken place about Qatar. I said that i had been on leave during this meeting and was not fully aware of the position, but a brief discussion took place. Mr. Hearn., who had previously refeiied to Hie possibility of some arrangement between the A.P.O.C. and the u Ulf/^1 - 4 - Gulf Oil Company * under which the exploitation of the Koweit concession, if it went to the A.P.G.C., should he entirely conducted by the A.P.O.C., the American interests having a share in distribution only, and had also referred to the recent acquisition of the Hasa concession by the Standard Oil Company, hinted at possible difficulties over safeguards in connection with Cottar, particularly having • regard to the international interests represented on the Iraq petroleum Company. The French, in particular, might see considerable difficulty about any right of preemption in the event of war. 7. I said that, while i did not know what had taken place in the previous discussions, it was only fair to say that, so far as could oe judgeu., the question or safegu^rds in respect of the Qatar area was likely to he of great importance. Having regard to the position of the Bneiidi, his treaty corrmitments end possible difficulties about jurisdiction, it would he unfair to hold out any hope that they were likely to he easy to surmount. A u iris rent position might arise, Indeed, ii the A.P.0♦ a. we±6 uo develop the Qatar concession, foreign companies having distributing interest only ana all personnel, a^ing British. ( 3d •) J • G-. LAI THWAl TB • 2nd June 1933.£ rt'Y CONFIDENTIAL. B05-B of 1933. The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to*t, © British ^#»ia#rcy &amp; ContmXate-Oener&amp;l ^uuhir#, the 6th ‘Tuly 1933. Wo.4B of 1933 nr. t h«ro the honour to »m*e the followInr cogent ulth referenoo to Section III (b) ttrtf to) of Colonel ‘niohoon TntcXliftonoe Stnwnary for the month ondlny 30th Juno 1933. foTwar^od under this Residency Printed letter No,47. dated the 6th July 1933. The ten al thd eprin#r way indicate presence of oil. nie fact th^t Aralc ha« now been proved to be In the Neutral ?one nay &gt;iave eon* future importance In connec tion with the subject of Kuwait Oil. I am sending copies of this despatch to the ftovemraent of India and his Majesty’s Minister, Jedda. I have the honour to be, Sir, Tour west obedient, humble servant, (Sd.) T.C.Ifowle, Limit ,-Oclonel, Political Resident in the Persian Hulf.I \)'l CONFIDENTIAL. No. 836-3 of 1933, The Hon ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com- pliments to The -Political Agent, Kuwait. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment ^// for information* British Residency and Consulate-General, BUS HIRE. Dated, 8th July 19 33 Reference to previous correspondence: Description of Enclosure Name and Date. Political Resident’s telegram RooSO of 3rd July. 1933 to His Majesty’s Secretary for the Colonies, London. Subject Bahrain Oil.telegram R Political ^enident, Bush ire. '*° Secretary of State for the Colonies, London. Repeated. Boreifni Secretary to the Oovernnent of Indip , aimla. % No. 20, Dated the 3rd July 1933. Manage*-', Bahrain Petroleum Company, has informed Political Agent that he has telegraphed for Holmes urgently. - ResidentCONFIDENTIAL. No - B45-« of 1935. The Hon ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to rT he ^oltticnl Bahrain, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu- ment ty/ for in format ion. British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated Xl£h.?.nXy..X3 Reference to previous correspondence : ^Tinted letter of 24th June 1933. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. jp'Tb .143, dat* Letter ^o.l^3, dated the 4th July 1933,from the ^oli^icol Agent, Kuwait. Copy forwarded, with ci Political Agent, Kuwait, Subject. Boundaries of Qatar, ernpliraents, to the for information.CONFIDENTIAL. No. 856-S of 19 33. ^6 P \ The Hon ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to The Political Agent, Kuv/ait and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment (4/ for information. British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated. 12th July 1933, Reference to previous correspondence lo^o Bushire Printed letter N 0 .668-3, dated the 15th June 1933 Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Pu 4 -a ^ ^ Political Resident’s despatch Ro o 50 of IRth Jul^r 1933 to His Majesty’s Secretary of State for the Colonies. Subject. Sa’udi - Kuwait Neutral Zone Oil Con ces sion*British Consulate-G-eneral, BUSHIRE. n 14th July 1933, JJaiGQ ••• •••••• H&gt; v If. — : Reference to previous correspondence : r V AiTV vV / ^ / Bushire Printed letter Ho.68B~S of 20th June 1933, •v/ Description of Enclosure. The Hon ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his pliments to com- 1 • 'Hie Political Agent, Kuwait, 2* The Political Agent, Bahrain, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment 1^/ for information.only. CONFIDENTIAL. No. 869~S of 1933, Name and Date. India Office letter dated 19th Tune 1933, No.P.Z. 3189/33, to the Foreign Office. Subject. HASA OIL COM CESSION,deceived under India Office endorsement No.P.Z.3189/33.). COPY. No .P.Z. 3189/33* Copy sent to India. India Office, IrVhitehall, S.Y/.i., 19th June, 1933. C.^.A♦Warner, ]5Bq. , Foreign Office, S.V/.l. My dear Warner, Would you kindly refer to Jedda telegram N o .108 of 30th May reporting that the Standard Oil Comnany of California have secured the Hasa Oil concession? Pc With the Standard Oil established in Hasa and a considerable prospect that the Iraq Petroleum Company with its foreign element of control, may secure a concession in Qatar, the argument for securing Kuwait for British interests if possible seems to be strengthened, still further and Sir Samuel Hoare has asked that we should mention to the Foreign Office the danger that we may other wise find ourselves confronted with a mostly foreign bloc along the Arabian Coast from Iraq to ^rucial Oman. 3. I am sending copies of this letter to Parkinson, Moore and Starling. Yours sincerely, (Sgd.) J.G.Laithwait e.Telegram From To Gr, T, C . Political, Bahrain. Addressed to Bushire, repeated to Kuwait. No. 280. Dated the 16th July 1933. 'V ( Major Holmes is expected by Air Mail due 20th July. Addressed to Bushire, repeated to Kuwait. -POLITICAL- S s -oooTelegram. rom “ Loch, Bushire. x ° ” Resident, Kuwait No. 572 Repeated to Secretary of State No.24 Copy by post to Government of India. Dated the 19th duly 1953. hr? Reference Fowle’s telegram 3rd July No.20 Holmes is expected to arrive at Bahrain 20th July. He probably knows roughly what has taken place and is likely to ask Folitical Agent points about activities of A.P.O.C. Propose Political Agent should reply that A.P.O.C. have made enquiries with a view nego tiations for remaining areas but that definite offer has not yet been received.CONFIDENTIAL. plimants to 0n ’ bl6 4116 P ° litiCal EeSiCleDt ^ the Perslan Gu,£ P resent8 llis oom- Political A^ent, Kuwait, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu- ment (/). British Besidency and Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated, ?5th July 1933, Reference to previous correspondence: Description of Enclosure. Name and Date, Subject. Political Resident’s telegram No. 609, dated 95th July 1933, Visit of Major Holmes to to the Political Agent, Bahraint, Bahrain.4' Telegram ^ 27. From iolitlcal Kesident, Bushire, fo Iolitleal Agent, Bahrain. Ho. 602 Bated 25th July 1935. Company in London say that arrangements * have been made for Holmes to travel by air mail leaving London July 29th. Resident.■ \ CONFIDENTIAL. No. 936-S of 1933. r. The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to The Political Agent, Kuwait, m he Political Agent, Bahrain, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment for information only. V % * r British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated. 28th July 1933. Reference to previous correspondence : Residency Printed letter No.869~S of 14th July 1933. Description of EnclosureP.Z.3841/33 (E 3253/12/91) FOREIGN OFFICE 3.W.I. 29th June, 1933. My dear Laithwaite, with reference to your letter Ro.P 0-^ .J.3189/33 a of the 19th June, regarding oil concessions? in Arabia, we entirely agree that it would he desirable, if possible, that British Interests should secure the Koweit concession* On the other hand, the undertaking which from considerations of general policy we gave to the Americans, commits us, as you know, to an attitude of Impartiality as between the Anglo-Persian Oil Company and the American Group, who are competing for the concession through the Eastern and General Syndicate. 2 . I understand that in the course of tne exhaustive interdepartmental discussions with Powle, when he was over here, the question what action we could take in the circumstances to Improve the prospects of the Koweit concession going to an exclusively British company was canvassed in all its rspects, and that Jowle knows what we think he can do in the matter within the above limits. 3 . We agree of course that it would be unfortunate that a bloc of predominantly foreign oil interests should be fomed along the Arabian coast of the Persian Gulf. But this appears inevitable in view of the facts (1) that under the Iraq Petroleum Company Agreement, in the whole of Arabia with the exception of Koweit and Laithwaite, Esq. the( the PerBan Islands, no component company of the Iraq Fctroieun Company may take a concession without first offering it to the Iraq Petroleun Company, and (2) that the Anglo-Persian Oil Company, which in bound by that agreement, appears to be the only entirely British company interested in that part of the world. 4 . i must confess that I do not see what more can be done, unless there is any hope of some exclusively British company, which is net included in the Iraq . Petroleum Company, interesting itself in the Persian Gulf arer. 5 . I sa sending copies of hoore and starling. this latter to Parkinson, Yours ..c., (3d) CHaiiSTOFHha 'iASNSK.Telegram. G-.T.C. From H.M T s Secretary of State for the To Colonies, London. Political Resident, Bushire No. 16 Repeated to Government of India, Foreign and Poli tical Department, Simla. Dated 29th received 30th July 1933. My despatch of the 15th April, 1924, No.13. His Majesty T s Government have decided that India Office shall with effect from 1st August take over responsibility hitherto discharged by Colonial Office in respect of Persian Gulf work &gt;» including oil. You should therefore from that date address Secretary of State for India in all cases in which you have hitherto addrsssed Secretary of State for the Colohies and instructions will issue to you from India Office on behalf of His i-ajesty’s Government on all matters on which they have hither- t to issued from Colonial Office, losition of Government of India in regard to Gulf work will remain unchanged and you should continue to repeat correspondence to them as at present. Secretary of State for the ColoniesQ. /V\,, Telegram. Cypher From - Resident, Bushire. ” Political, i^u ait c/o Prodrome,Baghdad. No. 627 Dated 3rd August 1933. Confidential. Major Holmes is travelling by air mail reaching Baghdad 2nd August. This is to warn you that he is returning to Bahrain somewhat under a cloud having misrepresented certain discussions with Shaikh. Resident VCONFIDENTIAL. |ft.A/ p ^7 H- '33 No.l004-r? Of 1933. |(r^ &lt;V The Hon ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his pliments to com- 'Hie Political Agent, Kuwait, 0k and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu mentfor information. British Consulate-General,V* P.Z.4173/33. India Of nee, Whitehall, s.W.l. 14th July, 1933. Dear Slffard, You will remember asking me a few days ago about the precise status and history of the Neutral gone between Nejd and Koweit. X ua sorry to have been so long in sending you a reply, but we have been very much pressed here. £ • ihe atai.ua oi Koweit was the subject oi considerable dhscussion in the period bexore the war. Mi agreement regarding it was finally reached with Turkey and a Convention signed to give effect to that Agreement on the 29th July, 1913. under this Agreement the territory of Koweit was recognised as an autonomous caza of the Ottoman Ebipire; the Ottoman flag was to be flown by the Sheikh who was, however, to have the right to insert a distinctive emblem in the corner; he was to continue to be a Turkish KatnaKaa and his successors were to be appointed to a similar position by the Ottoman Government; the full adninistrative antonoiiy of the Sheikh was recognised within the territories of Koweit proper, the limits of which were defined by the red circle on map No.2 appended to i .G.13; within the surrounding area (included within a green line on the map), which was occupied by tribes recognised as dependent on him, he was, as in the pest, to continue to levy tribute and to perform the adnlnistrative duties of Turkish K aimak an . and in both regions Turkey undertook to abstain entirely from any interference. This convention, Rw'nSrhot. Board of Trade, Dean Stanley street, S.W.l. /though initialled, had not been ratified on the outbreak of the war. 3. fhe boundaries between Koweit and Nej d were finally settled at the Ohair Conference of November - December, 1922. as stated in paragraph 34 of the Memorandum on Koweit in P.G.13 -it was recognised that / the power of the Sheikh of Koweit in the desert was much less then it had been at the time of the conclusion of the Anglo«Turki 8 h Agreement of 1913, and a settlement was finally reached under which the frontier as between Nejd and Koweit start* from the junction of the -adi-al- Aujah with the Batin on the west, running thence (leaving Biq&amp;i to Nejd) in a straight line to the junction of the 29th parallel of latitude with the red semi-circle on the map attached to the draft Anglo-Turkish Agreement and reproduced in Map Ho.2 appended to I .9.13, thence following the red stei-circle to the sea muXh of Bus-al- Qulaieli. The southern boundary of the recognised territory of Koweit is defined above. It was simultaneously agreed that the tract of country bounded on the north by the above line, on the west by the Shaqq, on the east by the sea and on the south by a straight line running eastward from the Shaqq in the west through Ain-al-Abd to the sea north of Bas-al-Mishab should be recognised as comon to the two States of Mejd and Koweit, who were to enjoy equal rights in it until such time as a fresh agreement should be arrived at between them regarding it through the good offices of Hie Majesty’s Government.* 4. The geographical area of the Koweit Nejd Neutral &amp;one is ae defined in the preceding paragraph, As regards itsits status, Nejd and K owe it have equal rights in it pending the conclusion of a further agreement, airid neither party, therefore, can grant a concession without t 18 consent of the other* as regards its earlier history it is, I think, fairly clear from paragraph 2 above that in the pre-war period the area now Included in the Neutral Zone was predominantly under Koweitl control. it was quite definitely not under the control of Xbn 3aud, whose active interest in it dates from a much later period. It would, I think, be reasonable to contend in all the circumstances that for the purposes of international oil agreements affecting 'Koweit' or 'the Sultanate of KoweiV* the Neutral Zone can properly be regarded as covered by either of those terras. 5. I m sending copies of this letter to Handel of the foreign Office, Moore of the Adnlrelty, and Blaster of the Colonial Office. Yours ., (3d) J•G.LArnr.YAITK•) iONFIDBNTIAL. No. 10 39-S of 1933. • l+'O X 2 ■ ? 'll y/V The Hon ble the Political Resident in the Persian Griilf presents his com pliments to ’The Political Agent, Kuv/ai t. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu- menfc t '°' r information. — British Consulate-Greneral, BUSHIRE. ii T - :: \ Dated Reference to previous correspondence: Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. h. mc&gt; Draft Uote’ of a Meeti Office on the 2tlth duly questions connected 5 ersx ng held at the Colonial 1933, to discuss certain with oil in the an Gulf.?. 2 . 4645/55 DRAE-T NOTE OF A MEET IMG HEED AT THE COLONIAL OFFICE ON THE 26 TH OF JULY, I 933 , TO DISCUSS CERTAIN QUESTIONS CONNECTED WITH OIL IN THE PERSIAN GULF* There were present:- Mr. Parkinson (in the Chair)) Colonial Mr. James ) office Lieutenant Colonel Fowle, Resident in the Persian Gulf Mr. Rendel ) Mr. Warner ) Foreign Office Mr. Laithwaite, India Office Captain Moore, Admiralty Petroleum Department BAHREIN 1* Some discussion took place as to whether the amendments to the mining lease desired hy His Majesty^ Government could be linked up with the Company f s application for an extension of their prospecting licenc# under Article IV of the 1925 Agreement, and a reference was made to the Treasury Solicitor's Opinion regarding the Company's right under that Article to secure an extension of their prospecting licence. Some difference of opinion appeared to exist as to the interpretation to be put on -the Treasury Solicitor's Opinion, but eventually general agreement was reached on the following lines:- (a) The desired alterations in the mining lease can not be made a condition of granting an extension of a/a prospecting licence under Article IV of the 1925 Agreement* (b) There is nothing to prevent the mining lease being altered by agreement with the Company. {The Company had already been warned in correspondence which took place in December 1932 that His Majesty’s Government would wish to make certain alterations, and this position was accepted in the Company’s letter of 30 th December, 1932 .} (c) When writing to the Company about the extension of their prospecting licence, it should be possible to introduce the question of the desired alterations in the mining lease, and whils. not making the latter dependent upon the former, to suggest that in view of the consideration extended to the Company in the past. His Majesty’s Government anticipate that the Company will make no difficulties in respect of Immediate fiction as Major Holmes’s latest pro posals* the amendment of the mining lease. The details of procedure were not, however, discussed. 2. Mr. Starling said that he had heard that the Iraq Petroleum Company intended to submit definite proposals regarding the remaining area in Bahrein. The proposals would be made through the Anglo-Persian Oil Company, who would, in this case, be acting as agents for the Iraq Petroleum Company. Mr. Starling said he would be able to confirm this very soon. In these circumstances it was decided that the action outlined in the recent telegraphic oorrespondenc could he initiated. This meanss- (a)(a) A letter to the Company in London recording in categorical terms the Sheiich r s denial of the accuracy of Major Holmes’s account of their interview, and explaining that it has been found necessary to approach the Company in London because of ( 1 ) Major Holmes s absence from Bahrein, ( 2 ) his breach of agreement by approaching the Sheiloh direct, and ( 3 ) the inaccuracy of the account of his interview with the Sheikh* The letter would foreshadow a separate letter regarding Major Holmes’s position as the Company’s Chief Local Representative in Bahrein. (b) A telegram to the Persian Gulf saying that (a) above is being sent, and asking for the Sheikh’s concurrence in a further communication to the Company in the terns already agreed regarding Major Holmes’s proposals. (c) On receipt of the Sheikh’s concurrence, the letter on this subject to issue to the Company in London. (d) The letter to the Treasury Solicitor regarding the position of His Majesty’s Government under Condition ,l C n scheduled to the Indenture of 1930, to issue as soon as possible. The draft of this letter had already been agreed by the Interested Departments. 3 . This question is to be taken up with the Company in London as a separate issue when the iressury Solicitor’s reply to (d) above has been received* The question of the replacement of Major Holmes, if the latter’s appointment is terminated, was discussed, and it was eventually agreed that faute de mieux the appointment of Mr. Skinner, the Company’ Field/Field Works Manager in Bahrein (an American subject) would probably be the best solution. Mr. Rendel and Mr• Starling, however, wished it to be borne in mind that this would be a reversal of the policy hitherto adopted by His Majesty’s Government, which had been that the Company’s Chief Local Representative should be a British subject. Lieutenant-Colonel Fowle said that he had re-considered his previous suggestion that the local bank manager in Bahrein should be asked to act as the Chief Local Representative. He thought there ?/ould be administrative difficulties about this, and that the Company would be strongly opposed to the idea. Q,ATAR. 4'. The latest information is that Mr. Sampson (the representative of the Anglo-Persian Oil Company) has visited Qatar, and discussed the financial aspect of the matter with the Sheikh. It is said that Mr. Sampson opened with an offer of 1 lakh of rupees, which was countered by a demand for 10 lakhs* lo action is required at the moment, as the comments of the Petroleum Department on the draft concession are awa ited* KUWAIT AND KUWAIT MEUTRAL ZQHB* The position in regard to the Kuwait concession is that the bidding has been called off by the Sheiioh. Lieutenant-Colonel Fowle said that the Shaikh knows that the free hand accorded to him to choose between the original offers is now cancelled, and that His Majesty's Government must be consultedm regard to ^ny fresh proposals. Mr. starling drew attention to Colonel Fowled de^atch of the l6th June covering a note by Colonel Dickson on the possible trend of events in Kuwait.. He regarded this as rather disturbing and wondered whether there was any further action which might be taken in the interests of the British Company which was endeavouring to secure the Kuwait concession. Colonel Bowie thought that it was not desirable to do anything further at the moment. He had seen the Sheikh fairly recently. Lieutenant-Colonel Bowie also said that the lull was partly due to the uncertainty in the Sheikh’s mind as to the neutral zone. It is not yet known whether the Hasa concession recently granted to the Standard Oil Company, includes the neutral zone. It is not unlikely that Ibn Saud added the neutral zone on the understanding that the Sheikh’s consent would be obtained, and that the King has already approached the Sheikh on the subject. The probability is that things will work out as they did in 19^4&gt; i*e. that Ibn Saud will submit proposals regarding the neutral zone to the Shaikh and that the latter will refer the matter to His Majesty’s Government who will be left with the odium of any refusal. There is a possibility that Ibn Saud might, by means of the neutral zone,, try to influence the Sheikh’s decision in regard to the Kuwait concession. Mr. Rendel expressed the view that, in this case, there would be good ground for strong representations at Jedda against interference on the part of Ibn Saud. It was suggested that the value of the Kuwait concession depended on the value oi the neutral zone,, and Mr. Starling undertook to ascertain from the Anglo-/ Persian Oil Company whether they regarded a concession in the neutral zone as an essential adjunct to the Kuwait concession* Mr. Rendel suggested that it might be possible to make a distinction between the neutral zone and Kuwait proper, in view of the former’s history and status, and to make a declaration that on political Yf grounds, ills Majesty’s Government could not allow the neutral zone to be exploited.V&amp;.4636/1W3, P.D.745. Dear i'aitbmite, PETROLEUM DEPARTPJNT (Mine© Department), Dean Stanley Street, Millbank, feetmineter, London, S.W.l 31 st July, 1933. x 1 ^ t Thank© for your letter of July 14th, addressed to Giffard, giving the history and status of the Neutral Zone between Nejd and Koweit; this detailed account will be most useful to the Department. le are particularly interested in this question because the point has arisen of whether the Neutral Zone fail© within the Iraq Petroleum Company’s sphere of influence which seems to depend partly on the question of how long the Neutral Zone ha© been in existence and whether politically it can still be regarded as a part of the Sultanate of Koweit, and partly on the view the I.P.C. my take. The I.P.C. Group Agreement of 1928, which defined the area within which the groups composing the I.P.C. agreed not to compete for concessions, drew a red line round Arabia and Asia Minor, but left out Kowieit and the Farsan Islands. Bahrein was included within the area. In regard to Koweit in particular, the definitions appended to the map which accompanied the Agreement state that the red line is intended to follow *the limit of the territorial waters of the Arabian i 6'iinsuits. Sultanate of Koweit and the Farsan islands Archipelago • As the Neutral Zone had been constituted when this Agreement was entered into it is not unlikely that the I.P.C, might take the line that for the purposes of their LLaithwaite, Esq., India Office, S.W.lAgreement it is not part of tiie ailtan&amp;te of Kowelt. It is interesting to see that politically you think it might he possible to assume that the 'Sultanate of Kowelt’’ covers the Neutral Zone ami that on that ground it might be open to the A. .O.C. to obtain a concession in the Neutral Zone independently of the I.P.C. The position is not free from doubt and you will see from my note of to-day's date to Parkinson that the A.P.O.C. would concur in the suggestion which we discussed at our meeting lust week to keep the Neutral Zone for the present out of the picture so tar as oil concessions sre concerned* I an sending copies of this letter semi-officially to the Foreign office, Adniralty and Colonial Office. Yours &amp;c., (3d) F.C.STARLING.PETROLEUM DEPARTMENT (Mines Department). Desn Stanley Street, MillbanK, Westminster, London, S.W*1 31st July, 1933. Dear Parkinson, Neutral Zone between ile.id and Koweit . j j^ In accordance with the suggestion made at our meeting last week regarding the Neutral Zone, I had a talk with Heam of the Angdo-Persian Oil Company as to the commercial value which they attached to this territory. Hearn’s view is that they would regard it as of about the same value as the other territories in this area. I discussed with him the attitude which the Iraq Petroleum Company might be likely to take as to the rights over this area under the I.P.C. Group Agreement and he expressed the view that it was quite possible thao the I.P.C. would consider that this area was a part of the territory covered by the I.P.C. Group Agreement. As oo this, see my letter (If today’s date to Laithwaite in reply to the latter 1 s letter of 14th July (P.Z.4173/33). $ ^ I sounded Heam quite informally as to whether the A.P.O.C. would be very disturbed if H.L. Government were to take the view that on political grounds it was undesirable to have any oil concession granted for the present m the Neutral Zone. His reaction was that it would be a very o°o d thing if this were to happen. From what he said I gathered that the local representatives of the a.P.'J.O. would P robao1 ^ not dissent from the reading of the situation as outlined in 5 A. k ^ n t &amp; Dickson's de.pJ’ifejuM ?th which .« appended to Fo-le's to * despatch of the 16th June, 1933. On politics! grounds and also because of the doubt jo xv, tup in regard to the Neutral ZiOne about the attitude of the I.P.c. m regara ou C.Parkinson, Esq., C.M.G. ,0.B.E., Colonial Office, S.W.l it/events turned out in the way I have outlined above, it would be possible to withdraw our veto on our own terms, and to use its withdrawal as a lever to extract from Ibn Baud concession for Koweit, e.g., the alleviation or termination of the blockade. If then the A.P.O.C's attitude on the point is assured and the other Departments concerned agree, we shall be prepared to concur in the imposition of the veto. I suppose that this would be done by informing the Sheikh of Koweit that His Majesty's Government could not agree to his riving his consent to any oil concession covering the Neutral Zone. I am sending copies of this letter to Starling, aid te Moore. Yours ever, (SD.) CHRISTOPHER '?AM JR. .Laithwaite, Ssq., India Office.IV-/ 4 i ll i / f Telegram Cypher. From Political, Kuwait. To Political, Bahrain. No. 204. Dated the 28th August 1933. Shaikh Kuwait has heard that Shaikh Qatar resigned or deposed in favour son. Have you any news. -POLITICAL-I- (?. rt/ ° 4^ Telegram, From To Repeated to Resident, Bushlre, No. 381 No. 380 Bated 29th and received the 29th August 1933 , Political, Bahrain, Political, Kuwait. V \'V' V | Your telegram 1 jo, 204 dated liie 28th inst, (1) News received August 28th that Shaikh Qatar left for Biath 5 days ago, at urgent summons King, who is said to be engaged at grant of oil concession to Anglo-Persian Oil Company* Q (2) During July^(gosaibi) received summons from King and began preparations (for visit) which was expected take S or 4 weeks, (3) Ruler Bahrain stated that he thought summons might be in connection either oil or recent proclamation re succession. Political* Confidential, No, 206 The Agency, Kuv/ait, the 30 th August 1933, Copy fdrwarded with compliments to Mr, A. Williamson, Kuwait • ^ Lt-Colonel, Political Agent, Kuwait,CO. ' ' JL. / Confidential. Ho:C/382-1.a/5, j-xL Political Agency, Bahrain,the 30th August 1933. To, The Political Agent, Kuwait, he no ran dum. |V Please refer to my telegram Ho:380 dated the 29th August 1933. 2. According to later news His Excellency Shaikh ABDULIAH Bin ^ASIM al THAHI,Ruler of Q,ATAR, left for IIOFFUE on the 26th Instant,en route to HIYABH, 3. He was accompanied ky his son,HAMAD,and his Brother,MIJHAB£EAD,whilst his eldest son,HASAH,was left in DOHAH to officiate for him. Political~Agent, Bahrain. Copy to:~ The Honourable the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf,Bushire,for information,in continuation of my telegram Ho:381 dated the 29th August 1933./v r British legation* J©dda# 25th JttXy 1953 Sir t With reference to Sir ndrew Eyt?n*s tele_ iOB of the 50th May last, relative to the grant of the Hasa oil concession to the Standard Oil Coiapany of California, I have the honour to inform you that the official ; nnouncement was made on the 10 th July by Government decree published in a specif 1 supplement of the ‘‘Usmi-tl^^ura** of that date* i*he decree, a copy of which is enclosed herewith, appeared unrccompanied by the terms of the concession but announced that an agreement would in fact shortly be published and illuded to a 'specie! agreement' which was also to be brought into force* The *Umra-al-^ura* duly published in two instalments. 2 in its issues of the 14th and 2lst July, the terms of the concession, f document of thirty-three articles * translation of which I enclose herewith* The concession is to come into force as from the ?th July 1953, and active operation^r© contemplated before the end of September 1^33* From a brief study of the text, the absence of &amp;*Ull in respect of the sums to be paid by the Company as a preliminary payment 1 rtiele 3), as rent 1 rticle 4, ana b1*o the leek of information regarding the exact are« to be exploited are conspicuous and in * number of other particulars the text is, perhaps not unintentionally, vague* The Eight Honourable, Sir John Simon, G*C*S.X*» K.C.V.O*, etc., etc*. etc*,the 'apecial agreemaBt^f to which c.lluaion ie made in the decree, must therc-fora contain these interesting items of information which the parties to tho agreement intend, it would appear, should not b« divulged* 4 # A copy of this despatch and enclosures are being sent to the hon , ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire* X have the honour to be with the highest respect, Sir, lour moot Obedient, humble servant, &gt;.s. otarnm.BiTt Zl** MKSf to the Mecca 'tfoia^&amp;l-^ura* Mo« 447* 17th K&amp;bt-uX-Aww*,l 1352 10th July 1933* DMmm Bo* 1135. GOBCmKIBS Granti&amp;g FkTRQL CQMCMSEim* fie, bdul *A»i» Ibn • bdurrahoi&amp;n al Feye&amp;l al 3t*' ud King of the 8a*udi rab Kingdom* fter reliance upon God* And after consideration of the fgreoment signed at Jedaa on the 4th day of 3afar of the year One thousand three hundred and fifty two by our Minister of finance and Mr* L.B. Hamilton the KepreeentatiTe of Standard Oil Company of California, merioa* And with reference to the approval of the Council of Ministers, We give the following Orders t Article 1* fhe standard Oil Company of California is permitted to render fruitful the resources of Petrol and its extract© that may be found in the eastern portion of our S* f udi Tcb Kingdom within the boundaries, and in pursuance of the conditions and provisions adduced in the agreement signed by our Minister of Finance and the Representative of of the said Company f t Gedda on the 4th day of $*far of the year one thousand three hundred and fifty two* Article 2* We sanction the agreement under reference which is attached herewith, and order that It should be put into force as from the d^te of it® publication* We &amp;lso sanction the special agreement which is inIbl in eu^plfcjaent to tn® origin&amp;X agreeeaeat asd order that it ©hall be yut ittto force# ^tlal© 4# Our Minister of Finance should see that the provisions of this Decree are put into force* ISSUED in our Xal&amp;ee at Riyadh on this day the 14th of E&amp;bl~ul~ mml of the year one thousand three hundred and fifty two* corresponding to the 7th day of July lSigned) ’ bdul f sis# i Bt cama of hi h*jkstt the kihOi His Majesty** Viceroy* (Signed) Feysal*mAioLmoH. EXTRACT fr&amp;to the Meccz a* Ho* 448 ©1 21st *iatoiwul- Awml 1352 14th 1933#) Thie agreement ha© bean concluded between Hie Excellency * Abdullah el Suleyman al namdgin, the atnister of Finance of the t»a f udl reb Eingdom # on behalf of the &amp;h' udi rab GoYerksmerit» called hereinafter the Government* a» on the one hand* and Mr* 1*B* Hamilton, on behalf of the Standard Oil Company of California, hereinafter called the C 02 ^any, on the other hand* fhe agreement concluded between the Government and the Company *» ae follow© t* /rtxclo 1* the Government grant the Company in pursuance of this agreement and in confdrmity with the f Hewing conditions concerning the fixed arm, the full right for the peri 4 of sixty year© &amp;e freest th&amp; date of putting this agreement into force for the purpose of surveying, prospecting, digging, extracting, producing, t/\rnsporting, hindling and exporting, of petrol, Asphalt, Haphthr (mineral oil), natural grease and tallow, other carbonaceous liquids and the extracts of these products* it is understood at any rate that this right does not include the gf^nt of full right xor the sale of crude or refined products within the limits of the undermentioned ©one in the interior of the udi rab Kingdom* A Article £. 1'he ione w&amp;icfa la subject to the full r%lit referred to in rticle 1 of thie bgreement ime alre&amp;ijf been agreed upon bet**eon tile two contacting portiee# Article 5. The Company shell gr,nt to the Ooeernment during the period agreed upon in this agreement e preliminary loan (Tpsyment} alrc&amp;cv ©-greed* Article «. the Company efcll pay to the Oorernment ennuaiy an amount/3&gt; an amount agreed upon, and for the purpose of facility thli payment will be defined ae annual rent which shall be paid in advance. The rent for the first year shall be paid during the period provided for the rticle 15 of this Agreement, and so long as this agreement is not cancelled the annual rent «ill be payable at the beginning of every year as from the date *f this agreement is put into force, and it (annual rent) must be paid within thirty days as from the beginning of each year, provided that immediately after the discovery of oil in considerable commercial quantities no other annual rents will be claimed or will be liable for payment • Article. 6* Directly cfter the date oi this agreement coming into force the Company shall proceed with its plans together with other preparations for geological work and arrangements for work so it may make use of the cold weather which enables it to undertake effectual field work, and to carry out the clerical work and make reports etc. during the hot season. In any case the field work should not be delayed more than the end of September 1935. Such work should be energetically and strenuously continued till the beginning of digging operations or up to the end of the e gr cement • Article 6 . Within 90 days from the date on which digging operations start the Company shall have leave or surrender to the Government the place, (areas) of the allowed zone, which the Company may decide are not needed for further work or for use in another form or manner in connection ,ith this fflVimild £&gt;180 surrender to tlie Government project, the Company should sj-eu from time to time during the period of this agreement other areas which the Company may decide are no longer required for inspection or investigation and for use for any purpose which may have connexion with this scheme, ai the places (areas) which will be given up by the Company will be li I (IIW frca the rtstrictloBb end conditions o. this a^eemsnt, but ths Company siU ha.T« the permanent right to employ those areas for the purposes of tr nepert and communications during the duration of this agreement, provided that this practice should hare a slight connection only with the other form or method in which these parte tareae) surrendered by the Company cm be used. ytip^ie 7. The Company should begin with the operations of digging as soon ae gssKihis it ithe Company) discovers the place suitable for the MM an., in any case if the Company fails to proceed with the operctienefwKSin I period of three years as from the end of September 19S- lsubject to the observation of the provlelone of rticle 2* of this agreement; the Government may then termimte this agreement, whenever the Company begins with the operations of digging it ahoulu persevere with energy until it discovers oil in commercial quantities or until it terminates this agreement, and if the Compaq? fails to give notice regarding the date on which the oil is discovered, then the date to be fixed for this purpose will be counted ae from the date on which toe Company complete the digging of one well or wells, examinee them nd discovers that they can supply not less than 2000 tons of crude oil doily and for a period of thirty days consecutively in conformity with the reliable practice obeerved in first class oil field#. The operations of digging include the ordering of tools »nd oth r machines and their shipment to Sa‘udi Arabia and also include the preparation of roads, camps, buildings, fittings, transport, communication*, and fitting machines and other means for *ell diggl&amp;g* Ag ticl. 6 . immediately after the discovery of oil in commercial quantities the Company should give the Government ^ „„ and after one year another loan the loan already agreed upon, and sit* should bo given to the Government, ihe date ol paying the first loan will be the date on which the oil is disc vered in commercial!l£ oGamerci«3- ne pr«rrid.a for io thi. ogre-aent !ad tbe ^te of offering the eecond loon .ill be ofter ooe yefir from t her dote, end in both c«e«&gt; the oor.nment will grant the Company a period of eixty deye delay •» «o to enable it to pey the loan during that period. rtloIC 9&lt; ha it toe been agreed that the annuel rent win be paid up to the date of diecorering oil In coaaereial liuantitiee and ae it too eleo been - greed that the annual ront should be paid in adT.noe, therefore it is poeeible that the last payment of the annual rent before the date of die- •vw.&amp;y . . aornim Ml 1&gt; II IIWlHI t „.M .«« «&gt;» « •»*•“ «&gt;“ »“ “ “■* ‘ f m. ««• •• &gt;/“» « &lt;■* &gt;«“ “ *“ .„u». prop.rtlonsta «. Ml -&gt;11 « “ * loan due by the ttorernaent. article 10. /a soon a. it become* possible i.e. that the Company will be allowed a reasonable time for ordering additional tools and for their shunts to Sa'udi rabia to meet th. additional work after the date of di.eor.ring oil m commercial quantities, the company ehould oontu.ue digging by means of employing two digging ^chines till it -it ♦vie* fixed £003 itx cooi*oraiity complfttee digging all ^ ^ nxm *** t wea^ in first Cl*.88 oii-neXds, or until the practice observed in first oa e* this e.greecjcnt expires* riicle u. The Company etoll pay to the Oorernment royalty on all crude cil drawn cut cr stored and which runs or flows from the field storage after deducting • Bt . eater and other foreign substanoee. 200 . Oil which will be required by the Company , / + V;i n udi /'■ , 'Xsbi&amp;-* for its ordinary wor,: within ■ 5rd . Oil Which Will be required for the yu p of benzine and Jcsrosen^ vsrMch of manufacturing quantities of rt t0 the OoTernment erery year in will be supplier iree rtiolc l^jbf this agreement. pursuance 01 crude oil * .4 realty on each ton net flights* cruae The nmount ol 2 ^ will be \l Iwin fc©* A, four shilling gold or Its uirolerit• or B* in accordance with the choice which the Compaq may Bfrke et the time of payment of each inet^liaent, one American dollar on er ch ton of crude oil # pi, » the difference in the rate of exchange in accordance with the average of the rates of exchange for the three months before the payment of the instalment* For instance if the average rate of exchange is one dollar or 14 cents U*Xi* currency for each four shilling gold U*e» that the vtilue of one pound gold has become equivalent to 5 dollars and 70 cent©) the amount of royalty on each ton net weight of crude oil will then be one dollar and 4 cents* rticle 12* If the Company extracts t stores and sells any kind of mineral oil it should pi&gt;y to the Government a royalty equivalent to l/Bth of the revenue from sales* t any r te it is understood that the company is not bound to extractt store and sell any mineral oil f and it Is &amp;lso understood th? t the Company le not bound to pry any royalty in respect of the oil which will be used by the company for its ordinary work* m; chines and other establishments in the Ba* udi r&amp;b Kingdom* rticle 15. fhe aovernment have the right through representatives on their behalf properly authorised to inspect during working hours the work carried out by the company in accordance with the provisions of this agreement «nd to check the quantities produced* 4 he company should keep correct accounts and aeasure# of quantities oi oil gained &amp;nd stored and which run from the depot of the field in r ccordanoe with the practice observed in the i irst claes oil fields* Government representatives who are properly authorised have the right to check the said account® et all convenient times* fter the expiration of one half year as from the date on which the oil is discovered in commercial quantities^f - 6 - tM cofflpli „ y should submit to the Government * tail i^rly fccc o. nt within . period of three months following the .*i* ^ ya „. Hid submit - statement showing the amount of royaty due to the Government for that half year, the Government should treat these accounts and statement, au confidential with the option of figures which the Government find it necessary to publish for certain financtal p Lees. Ih. royalty which will be due to the Government cfcould be paid at the end of each half year as from the date on which the oil is discovered in commercial quantities and such payment should be made within the period of the three month, following that half year. In the case of any dispuf which may occur in respect of the amount of royalty duo for a half year the company should hand over to the oovi.rnir.ent within the fixed period that part the royalty which is not in dispute, the dispute which may arise between th two parties shoulu be settled by the® and if they do not cou.e to a settlement in this way, then each dispute may be settled b y means of arbitr tion providod for in this agreement. «y amount which will bo docided after this settlement should be paid to the Government within 60 days r-s from the d: te on « rc - the decision in giv«n. » u ‘ u p “'7 ''‘ a ’ for in this agreement whether they are gold pounds or shilling, will be counted on the basis of gold pounds and in accordance with their weight and pureness at the time o. payment. It is also agreed that p^ents may be made in i „ BollftTSibr pounds sterling on the above mentioned mericen Dollars^ po ^ tjie ^ b ft B is. It is alec agreed that in case the p.-y fc&amp;sus. ^ * e %etlim V* the rent for the first year is *e&lt;ie in t . ^ te , lU then be calculi ted in acoordunc merican dollars the rate wild an or . t he dite of payment, th® rnte of exchange on to them direct or/their credit in the ban* * BTr 1 ^ ' ^ ^ ^ 1I A «»$&lt;•* !3&gt;&lt;5 factory efter completing the necessary preliminary arrangements and after obtaining the approY&amp;l of the Oorernment regarding the place which the company suggests. During every year following the establishment of this factory the company should offer to the Government a loose quantity of about 200 t 000 gallons petrol and another of fcbout ICGfOOG gallons of Jcerosfne free of charge, it is understood iiut the methods of taking oyer these quantities should not oppose the work of the company to any danger. Article iv» fhe company employs pt its own expense the ntteer of guards and guides needed for the protection of ith repx*fcscntatiYe4 camps and establishments, the Govorament promise to afford ©very assistance to the company in supplying It with their best soldiers and men and entrust them with this matter, fhe Government will offer the company all ressonable protection at certain wages which will not be more than the usual w^ges paid by the Government. It is understood that the expenses incurred in connexion with such services should be paid to the Government by the Company. rticla 16 » In return for the obligations undertaken by the Company in pursuance of this agreement, and in respect of the payments which are due from the company as provided for in this agreement, the Company and the project will be exempted from all direct and indirect taxes, dues charges arid foes i including customs dues on export and import;. It is understood that this privilege does not include the sale of products inside the country and the personal requirements of the members of the stiff of the Company, fhs Company is not allowed to sell within the country any of the tools and material brought without payment of customs dues unless after such dues are paid. Article i$» It is naturally understood that the company J»« the right to use ali the aterJK f *« UUiM V ' 1UOil “ ary iI'-l o tnink neeeeft&amp;ry Its work &amp;nd which enable it to rulfll the requirement® of this project and which comprise other affairs such r® buiXcings t using roads, camps, fittings and all road® for communications, and to erect and employ machines and other means which pare connection with the digging of wells or transport or storage or manufacture or exportation of petrol and its product® or any other thing which m.y have connection with the camps, buildings and the premise® to be engaged by the employee® of the ****** Company, ihe Company ha® the right to build and use cistern®, reservoirs and basins r nd also ha® the right to build pier®, quay© and line® for shipments and to use all other mean® for the transport of employees machine© end petrol and its product©* /t any rat© It 1® understood that the question of employing aeroplane© within the limits of the country will be subject to another separate agreement* the Company have the right to procure, take and use water and also ha® the right to take and us© any water which belong© to the uovernsaent for tiWpurpos© of carrying out the work in connection with the project provid d that such action must not cr use h^rm to irrigation or deprive- land houses and watering place® of sufficient water from time to time* the Company has the right also to make use of any natural products which belong to the Government such as sand, timber, lime, stones, gypsum and other materials oi the sime nature* Government employees and agents (during periormanc© of their official duties) will have the right to use the means of transport and coamunic* tions which will be established by the company provided that such action should not hinder or entangle the affairs of the Company indicated in this agreement, and should not cause the Company sny material loss, fh® engagement of the means of transport and communications belonging to the Company by the Government during the occurrence 01 national trouble will render the Company to be entitled lor reasonable componsetioh 1 or any for any harm which may occur to loss which it may undergo or the works and establishments of the\ H ♦ -10- the Uomp&amp;hy or hinder or entangle It© work* 20&gt; the project provided lor In this agreement sh&amp;ll be managed and supervised by merican person© who will engage ©o tar a* poueible person© from amonget the subjects of the udi Arab yovernsaent and ao 1 ng as it la possible for the Company to Hud capable and fit employees from amongst Se'udi subject©. It shall not engage the subject! of any other Government* the Company should observe the regulations taken Into force in this country in connection with the treatment of employees* Article 21» the Government reserves the right of prospecting In the allowed ©one for other product© end materials apart from those provided for In this agreement by the wells and establishment® of the Company and provided ttmt this right which Is reserved by the tfoverr;ment should not defect the rights granted to the Company and should not expose its work to danger, md provided Ih&amp;t th&amp; Government should pay to the Company a reasonable compensation lor any harm which the Company may undergo on account ©1 practising that right* whenever the rights reserved by the Government are granted, the person in possession of this concession will be bound with the provision© of this Article. rtiole 22* the Government authorise the Company to obtain from landowners the grounds which the company may suggest that are necessary for its work in connection with this project provided that the Company pay to the landowner a reasonable sum to be estimated on the basis o; the income which the landowner get© from those ground©* ihc government will offer reasonable assistance to the company in «*•« of difficulties which may * rise in this respect* the Company h*s no right to procure and engage any a&amp;erea place* fyfiale 23« the Company should submit to the Government the copies of the typographical map© *«* geological reports which are defihitcly certified by the Company in connection with the allowed aone included in this agreement. *he ( Company \Company autemit to tho within four months at the end of every year Us from the tiu te of di@cove#~ ing oil In comcaeroial quantities) a report explaining the work done during th-1 year and providdd for in this agreement» provided th; t the uov^rnment treat these maps and reports as confidential* Artiole 24* Any failure or negligence which may arise on part of the Company in respect of the execution of any of the conditions of this r gr cement sh? 11 not entitle the Government to claim compensation from the Company if such failure or negligence is accidental and umvoidefele* if the execution of any of the conditions of this fgreement is delayed on account of the coercive power the period of delay together with the period neoessrry for the reparation of the harm or damage sh 11 be added to the period rnd conditions specified in this agreement* rticle 25* rhe Company has the right to terminate this t greemont at any tiae and in such case it should give to the Government in writing thirty days 1 notice whether by letter or by telegram# provided that the telegraphic notice is followed by a confirmatory letter# ^e soon as the termina tion of this agreement is effected by the giving of the said notice or by any other moms the Government and the Company will both be free from any restrictions and obligations laid on them by this agreement with the exception of the following t (l) fhe immoveable property of the uompany such as roads oil or w^ter wells together with their pipes rn&amp; tide Immoveable buildings and fittings etc* will be the property of the Government and free of any charge# (20 The Compcny should grant the d over lament a period of delay to enable them to purchase the moveable property of this concern existing in fta’udi rabia at a reasonable price equivalent to that of another similar property at that time* subject to the reduction which is usual to second h&amp;nl / property#property* / ny dispute wHieU may arise in respect or fixing this reasonable price elmll be settled by arbitration in ttm same »&amp;y z* provided for in rtcle £8 or this agreement and in case the Government refuse or fail to buy those moveable properties within a period of t*o months from the date ©f terminating this agreement and ii the Government fail to pay the amount of the coat within thirty days after such cost is decided either by mutual agreement or by arbitration, the Company ahull have the right to take and transport awry its properties in question within a period of six months rticle £6# In case the Company breaks its undertakings in regard to paying the second loan agreed upon in accordance with this agreement or commencing with the ork of digging provided for in this agreement or paying the two loans agreed upon as in icated in rticle 8, or if it breaks its under- t kings in pursuance of /article £8 of this agreement relative to the matter of paying any compensation which may be imposed on the Company, the Government will then have the right to warn the Company tamed lately and if the company does not take immediate steps, with a view to carrying out the broken undertakings the Government sh 11 nave the right to terminate this agreement# rtlcle £7# In case the Compmy fails in any of its undertakings provided for in this agreement (except those mentioned in rtiele 2i) it shall be liable for m punish* meat by means of a fine to be paid to he Government under the following conditions i The Government warn the Company immediately about any breach attributed to it and explain to the Company the facts of this breach* /ny dispute which may ariee in view of the fact that •bather the Company toe committed euch breech of underUkinge or otherwise will be settled in eeeerdanoe with the methoj mentioned in ttoie tgrcement and if it proved th. t the ^.any has committed auch breach but failed to take immediate eye in this respect it shall be then e-poeed to the payment** ivx»» of compeng^tion for the ci&amp;a&amp;ge oau&amp;ed to the uoTerhioeot* If they cannot comt to agreement upon the amount of oompens? tion it can be settled b&gt; the tteatts of arbitration provided for in this agreement* the Company should then pay the Oovernment the amount of com* ensrtion decided by arbitration within a period of sixty days as from the date such decision is given* Article £k» if any doubt or difficulty of divergence take place between the Government and the company in connection with the interpretation of this agreement or its execution or in the interpretation of any thing of it or its execution or in the right© of the two parties or their undertakings, and in case the two parties fail to settle the same by any other method the case shall be settled by means of t*o arbitrator s to be ©elected by the two parties ieach party selecting one arbitrator) and one ch irmsn to be appointed by the arbitrator© before starting the arbitr tion* m.on party should appoint his arbitrator within a period of thirty days as from the date of the application to be forwarded by the other party in writing* If the two arbitrators fall to appoint the chairman the Government and Company should on mutual agreement appoint the chairman* If they fail to do this they should ask the Chief of the i eramnent international Court of Justice, to appoint the chairman who will be considered as chief arbitrator in the case and if the two arbitrators go not agree upon any suggestion the arbitration of the chairman tor th© chief arbitrator) shall be considered as final* the two parties should agree upon fixing the place for arbitration and in case of their failure the place to be fixed for this purpose shall be the Hague Holland* Art isle 29 * fhe Company is not allowed to tr&gt; nsfer its rights and obligations provided for in this agreement without the consent of the Government but it is understood th?.-.t th© Company m y hare the right to tran»f«r its rights and obligations presided for in this agreement to another Company whichwiileii be&lt; eetafeXisned by xm contactine Qm&amp;?ny in connection ^itn tnis pro4©ct ffter girin^ advice to tno uov©x &gt; n£c^nt to titis crioct# xlio Company wiXi aloo nave tne x*i fc nt to ©fst&amp;fcli»n otner coapniee and propV tlon» or a id n tore if it oppeers to tnc Company thrt they are nccoaaary for the pur poo e of carrying out the «f fairs of this project# /» bo &gt;n o,« tnt; companies and otner establisnmerito ne^ly eatablioned become entitled to part of tne ri^nts and under- tfJcingo provided for in tnis agreement or for all of tnemi tney anall eXso become bound by tiie condition© and prov eiona of tnis agreement# Xft case tile cemspany newly established is sues snares for public s^-Xe# the i nna fc i tent s of tht; sa* udi b Kingdom should be- allowed e reasonable time for the purpose of subscribing iunder the same conditions offered to other©} with 20 at least of the amount of the shares which will be offered for sale* rtiole 30* It is understood that period© referred to in this agreement sh 11 be. calculated on thft basis o-*&gt; the solar calendar• Article 51, The date on which this agreement shall be considered as coming into force shall be the date of its publication in the &amp;a*udi Arab country after its ratification by the Company* ! ft isle 12# in order to avoid the occurrence ol misunderstanding it sttould be oleerly understood ttot tms Company or any pereon belonging to or in relation with it tore no rignt to interfere in tne administrative, poiu -c 1 or religious affairs of the Sa'udi /rrb Kingdom. ra. It is understood that after tais a^eement is signed in Wadi /rabia it shall be liable for ratification by the principals of tne company at »an Francisco, Oalifornii. before it becomes operative. After signing the t.o copies I of this agreement in iia'udi /rtbia the signed copies should be forwarded in a registered cover to the headquarters of the Company at San Francisco (California) who should send a telegram to the Bovernment within fifteen days as from the date&lt;* liM on which, they receive tiie two copies declaring their rcceptance of the ratification of tnie agreement or otner«vise t and If this agreement is not ratified within fifteen day© as from th*i% date f it snail be considered nuX and /old and also in case the preliminary loan end the rent for the first year are not paid to the tfovtrranant within the period agreed upon in rticle 15 of this agreement the Government ©h 11 then have the right to announce the annulment of this agreement and consider It of no effect, but in case this agreement is ratified the Company should forward to the Government one of the two signed copies together with the certificate which proves that the agreement is ratified by the Company* After this agreement is ratified by the Company it shall be published in Ua* udi rabia in the usual way. signed on this day the 4th of Safar in the year one thousand three hundred ana fifty two (corresponding to the 2V th May 1955* 0 ) Abdullah al Suleyman al Mamdan* the Minister for finance* for fhe Government of the i^&amp;'udi Arab (Sgnd) A.M* IMmilton. for the Standard Oil Company of California* l m %,) (in the above translation the word 'lo^n' is an exact translation of the rebic word used but probably the word 'subsidy* would be more correct*}CONFIDENTIAL. No. 1112 -S of 1933o &lt;£. /■ q^igr The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Glulf presents his com pliments to The Political A^eirfc , Kuvfai 1 9 and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment for information• British Consulate-General, Name and Date. Subject. Secretary of State for Itk 5 ia. telegram «OaS115 dated the P5th August lyooo Balirain 0il 686/2 Telegram From To Repeated to XX. H.M*s Secretary of State for India, London. political nesiaent, Lusdire. Ho. 2115. Government of India, Foreign &amp; I clitical Department, Simla. Ho. 2116. Dated 25th received 26th August 19S5. Bahrain Oil. Bahrain letroleum Company consequent on oral r epresentatlons { papers to you an6 Government of India hy air issue August 26th; have decided to replace Holmes as Chief local Bepresentative. *ith concurrence of His hajes- -ty's Government he will temporarily He replaced hy Glcinner and question of proposing latter for perman- -snt post is under consideration hy Company. Hoti- -fication from Company goes to Holmes hy this week’s air mall. ^s to whether prior warning is being given to either him or Skinner, Company suggest as decision is likely to he very ill-taken hy Holmes, who may cause embarrassment locally by making ac- -cusations against British Qfficials etc., it would he well, if possible, that Political jigent etc., should avoid Holmes until effects of air letter has subsided. 2. Company will not renew application for extension of prospecting license for moment hut intimate that they propose to do so once Holmes has handed over. Secretary of State for India^ ^ GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. ^ S 0&lt; # 0 D e P ar tnient. Wm-Tgri^ . - q ‘ . EXPRESS LETTER (AIR MAIL) t'-iq [NcB *—This is an 01llGrINA.Ii message sent by AIN, MAIL which provides a means of communication more expeditions than the ordinary mait and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended tb be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer o f the Department.} No. 1141-8 of 1933. D hi , the Auguftt # W 33. XX ^row t^eeid ent , %ohi re• To -etaxonduw , Lond on • yayv 4,IN, ' lh %reign, -Inin. &gt;3 rodyone, Jed fin* blitical , uaait. blit leal, Bahrain. f^inUdt of ;atftr In rwort ed to hsi*» loft fox Riyadh about S5th August »t urgent nwiwonn fxon King, nho In nairt to be foraged at grant of 0*1 Cofteentsion to Anglo- ’em inn {) i^ Comnanv (Ccmeennion ban nest In fact *been granted, negotiation* for one haring been poatponed till October). ^h4i-rh ran in any oaee lofiown to be preparing In «nily fbr a rinlf to ’Riyadh and rinourod reason for ri«it nnsr merely be story spread by interested parties. Oh?d.) 0. *4idi. Lieut.-Colonel. officiating Political Resident in the Persian &lt;Hilf • tor tforeinitr to tbo Wl+lenl 9e«Wwt in the ’eraian Oulf. (Signature) (Designation) S. 4L DCFP—1124S&amp;l , --(M-1314)-4»8.32-12,000, C kM' JOCONFIDENTIAL. No. 1165-S of 1933&lt; tA The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian G-ulf presents his com pliments to The -Poli tl cal Agent» Kuwait, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu mentfor information only* British Consulate-Ceneral, bushire. Dated. 5th September 1933. /' Reference to previous correspondence : Residency Printed letter *0.1068-3 of SRnd Auyust 1933. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Letter dated the ISth August 1933 from the Petroleum ^ep^rttnenf (Mines Department) to -.ne inf ia Of fi ee„ Subject. Kuwait-Nejd neutral Zone * (y^JL© P.2.5015/19^5. PETROLEUM DEPARTMENT, (MINES DEPARTMENT), DEAN STANLEY STREET, MILLBANK, WESTMINSTER, LONDON, S*W.l. 15 th August, 1933* \ - &gt; Dear LaitLw&amp;ite, WitL referenoe to Warner’s letter of the 9th August, (15.4255/487/25) oonceraing the Koweit-Nejd Neutral Zone, I have had another talk with Heam^ and you may take it that Hearn's riew which X expressed in my letter of the Jlst July to Parkinson is the definite Yiew of the Anglo- Persian Oil Company. Hearn said he oould not speak definitely for the Iraa Petroleum Company, hut he feels sure that so long as no one is allowed to go into that territory the Yiew of the Ira 4 Petroleum Company will he ♦ n-p +h * Anfflo-P«rsiiwi OH lompeiny* the same as that of the Aiigxu Yours sincerely, (3d.) SEE* Starling. J.G. Laithwaite Esq.., India Office, King Charles street, S. W »1 •li'i Telegram G.T.C* 7rom Political, Bahrain. To Political, Kuwait. No. 431. Dated the 18th September 1933. 'p Addressed Resident repeated Kuwait My telegram dated 15th September K Holmes expects to travel by direct to London by Air from Bahrain 21st September. -POLITICAL- ooo- i(rs P.68* T24S375W60) British Legation, Jedda, 25rd ruguat 1935. Bir, f&gt;.hX With reference to my despatch ho. 235(2166/35^/51) of the 25th July last, relative to the terms of the Haea Oil Concession granted by the iia’udi Government to the StandaUd Oil Company of California, 1 have the honour to report that certain rumours which had been circulating in Jedda during the past few weeks regarding the payment of the first large sum as a loan to the Government, proved in the main to be correct with the arrival on the 2Cth August of the sum of £. 35,COO gold in English sovereigns, the specie was not, however, landed here owing to some deficiency in the shipping documents but remained on board the Khedivial steamer, the s.s. -Talodi'. and left with her again, the same day for Port Sudan, whence she is aue to return to dt.y. I understand that shipping arrangements were made in London through the Blue Funnel Line, by one of -hose ships the money was brought to Sues, where it was transhipped into the Khedivial sterner for Jedda. The documents, instead of being sent to the Dutch Bank here who are charged with the handling of the money, were addressed to the local agent of the Blue Funnel Line and were received by him too late for the £. 35,000 gold to be landed at the first visit. It will be landea to-day. . Tho t this large sum of money, amounting to over Right Honourable, Sir John Simon, G.C.S.I., K.C.V.O., li etc. 9 etc.» ©t c •»tl ('ft over £*50,000 sterling et present rates, is only a loan hr a been confidently asserted by persons who clai® have received their info mat ion direct from those concerned on behalf of the Company, and the repayment, it is further stated, is to be mad© gradually agl^nst the eventual royalties received by the Sa’udi Arab Government. This arrangement, if correctly stated, would therefore be provided for in the 'special agreement', the terms of which have not so far been disclosed. 3 , Mr. K. Twitehell who, in the continued absence of Mr. Hamilton, represents the Company here, states that he intends to leave Jedda about the 28th August for the hasa Coast by car. He has been away from the 1st August on a short tour of inspection, on behalf of the da’udi Government, of the old gold mines in the 'ejaz, which it is believed are by no means 'worked out', and returned unannounced on the 14th ugust, to prepare for the arrival of the Company*s consignment of specie to the sa’udi Government. 4# it ie stated here that tctive oper&amp;ti onSare contemplated by the Standard Oil Company of California within the next few weeks and that oil ouning ge r is already well bn its way to the Hasa Coast /way ol the Persian Gulf. 8p A copy of this despetch is being sent to the Honourable the Political Resident in the i ersii n (;uli, Bushire. X have the honour to be with the highest respect, Sir, Your most obedient, humble servant, A.S.C LVERT.rl ' iW t $ iiuo ■2 • 'p.4 X'xo j'!;* 000 f tc'i, ^ Xc '■■ ‘V ik ., C- ’ S ■''.'$ (.i-fri -a, L-ioz mtiJ « ' . i'Y. , : ,£.:. a|Jv'.. ^ i'Yi' 0? j &gt; v' d j , . T;*W.J &amp;#%■&gt; itzu* %&amp; pj$# ^j{jf : - ■ - : •, • -': : m*# ,,,, ,t©?i . . ^' &lt;,; ' Uv ■ i ■• •. Sx )# h r* »«&gt;X v ’ : ..; • ' v ; ; '. ■ - • ■- ■ ; .;. , ■■ : V j .;., r: ., '- '' ■ ' c ■ . 'si £&gt;' ; '' ' «# ■ ; si' -r... ' J ; ♦' ' ' ' v '..v /:•;:!: x.h'.uyy n- Kti ■ ■' ' ' ^ ^ ^ 1 ' V'» . SS «US,, .Z&amp;$ mM &amp; Z3 ! i * ■• ■' ' * J ' ' '■ 1 ■*£ ' j : 1 V&gt;' » ■ .., . . . ., ''' v, . j . : L .st'-ii. &gt;1*:}$: ' ' ' i J U ' ' : ' ' - i !»i:S ;.‘ Vi'.,; , ■ &gt; ■■ :x':Ho. 2458/353/61. British Legation, Jedda* 24th ■/ uguat 1933* Dear department. |j&gt; ^ With reference to our despatch iio. 268 (2453/353/60) of the 23rd ugust* relative to the arrival of £.35*000 gold for the Sa'udi Government in respect of the standard Oil Company of California’s h s&amp; Oil concession we would like to make, for the sake of ? ccur cy, the following 'mise au point”, fhe gold was not shipped from London to Sue- in a Blue Funnel steamer as we state in our despatch under refernce* but in a boet of the Haines Line, a p # &amp; 0. subsidiary, the reason for the confusion in addressing the shipping documents was a similarity in the names of jaederlandsehe Handel-Maatschappij n.V. (the Dutch Bank here) and the Hederlandsche Indische Handels Bank, an agency held by the International gencies Ltd., who are at the same time the agents of the Blue runnel ^ine. 2 # It may be of interest to add to the information contained in our despatch under reference thfct the 35,000 gold sovereigns re said to have been obtained for the Standard Oil Company of California by the Guaranty iruat Company’s London Office from the Hoyal Mint. 3 # the gold, in seven boxes, is said to have been scifely landed here yesterday. 4# A CO py of this letter is being sent to Bushire. lours ever, CHaHCJST. Eastern department, Foreign Office.V m ( yo - GoJ^, GOVERNMENT OF INDIA. ^ v ii f?.L rmi ffeparfmer^. fs, r wim nrnirmar sin oonamum owm/a.j wbhirs. EXPRESS LETTER fATR MfAtL). rjj g, TMs is an ORIGINAL message sent ly AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more expeditions than the ordinary mail and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended tb he treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature of a responsible officer o f the Departmentf No. Vron To %td. th „ -TQ 1297-^. ^Gtaxm&amp;vm, koraiem, **r0dr©t3«, JeddA. ^ollti cal t irttwait, Political. 7th October u 19 33. re. p % Kx^ress tetter 3i«t Aumiet. of ^it»r ia reported to have returned to ftohst-about 27th ^eptanber. Od/- 0. Loch.. Lleut-^ol.» Political Resident in the ternl an Gulf. Attested. for a.cret ary to tha Jill ^e Persian Gulf. %JLSL ^ * S tsl S- 44&gt; DCFP— 33S&amp;P— CG-37)' 25- 5-31—15,000.CONFIDENTIAL. No. 1310-S of 1933. ^ ■!. Ko. G/T ^ ^ ° . 31. vX The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to The Political A^ent, Bahrain, The Political Agent, Eiosait pu and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment (/y/foT information* British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated. llth October,1933 Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure Name and Date. Tibetract from the Mecca ^TTmra-al-Qiirst* Po*4f57 of 15th Bept emher 1933.- Subject. Visit of Shaikh of Qatar to Riyadh.(received under Jedda P.I.Ho.8734/^830/9 of 19th Septemher 1933). I TRAHSUTIOH. /(, 6 EXTRACT fpom th&amp; Mqcqa Bo* 457 of 1 15/0/3S* Wireless Message sent from PlySaii ^&gt;ecially to ^Uim-sl-Qura^ newspaper on 24th JumScl~al-Ula (September 14th) regarding the visit of H*H* the mtr of Qatar to WiyMh. H.H. the Aratr *, bdullah Ibn t'iSsein Ibn thSni, the Amir of Qatar came to -lyddh In order to visit H.J*. the King and to congratulate H.R.H. the Amir 8a'fid on the occasion of the V announcement of his succession to the throne* H.H. the j\mlr of Qatar and his fsully have entirely friendly relations with HUM* the King and *al Sa*dd, and was given a splendid reception at al Ahsa and Piytkdh* He came from Qatar to al Misa by camel and from al Ahsa to Riyadh by motor ear* He arrived at Riy&amp;dh^accompanied by his sons and some of his brother® hie suite and his servants, on Monday morning (Sept* 11th) and was received by H.H. the King at the door of H*M. f s palace. H.a* and his party took lunch and dinner with H. . tlie King and on the second day were entertained toy H.H. Aalr lHhaMaad, brother of r. . the King} on the third day by H.R.H. Amir Muhammad, son of His Majesty and on Friday by H.R.5'. Amir '.hftll-, son of H.h. tlie Amir of Qatar will leave Riyfidh tomorrow Friday night and will be seen off by H.H. the King who will go in company with H.H. as far as the wells near ad-Dahn*.CONFIDENTIAL. Hi The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian G-ulf presents his com pliments to wait. 1, The •Political .Ment, Kuwa 2, Political Agent, Bahrain and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment British Consulate-General, Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Petroleum Department(Mines Department) letter Mo.P.D. 236/8 dated the 10th October 1933 to the India Office, with enclosures. **■&gt; *#** Subject. HASA OIL COITCS3SION.V u 7 ? 1 :\H38 1 ) 6 / 8 . I Dean Stanley Street 8*9,1. October, 1933. C My dear Handel, With reference to your letter of September 2! rt endoelnf n treidatlon of the 'Tfnaa Oil Concession snmtad to the Stendnrd Oil oorapreiy of Ciiifoniia, I h- vo nes^had an opportunity of exanlninc Use concoeeion and I enclose sorae notes on its principal provisions. The ftbsor.ce of information ragar'iUng the area to be covered raid also details en to the financial arrangements meke it, however, difficult to wise up the value of the concession, end it would be of great value if H.M.»linistur could menage to got hold of a copy of the unpublished Supplementary Agreanent which contains those particulars. There may be same difficulty over this but it will presumably throw some lijdit on whet Ibn Saitd has done as regards tiio Neutral Zona, If oil is discovered, the Concession is likely to bs of considerable volus to the standard Oil Company of California as boing in such close proximity to their Bahrein concession and it gives thraa a big footing in the Gulf. As pointed out in the accompanying note, the agreement is rather vaguely wordsc in places raid l fin not sure that the translation is free from blaalehee in parts. It is interesting to note that the Company have cane into line with the 4/- rata of royalty provided . •’.Kendol, iSi Foreign office, Downing street, S .'4,1,( provided for in the Iraq Agreements (the rate in the Bahrein Agreement is just over 5/-) but if the other financial obligations are at ajl Eubstnntial they would have a bearing on this question. Several of the revisions we have suggested for the lining Lease in the case of Bahrein are included in this Agreement. 'Hie Arbitration. Clause shows some resemblance to that included in the new Anglo-Persian Oil Company Agreement. The recent experiences of the A.P.O.C. in Persia will not be overlooked by oil companies in entering into future agreements with foreign governments. While the Agreement could obviously be improved in several respects on the whole it is not, in its general conception, &amp; bad document from the Government's point of view. 1 am sending a copy of this letter and the enclosure to Lnithwaite. Yours &amp;c., (Sd) F.C.STARLING.Ar (n o) g ^otes by Petroleum Department on Haea Oil ConceBeion (granted to Standard Oil Company of California). Agreement of May 29th, 1953. linclosure to foreign Office Letter Ho. i£.4699/487/25 of September 2Cth,1933. 1. Period. ..of This is the same m in Persia and somewhat similar to the periods granted in Iraq and Bahrein, a. The Company has exclusive rights over the area for the exploitation of oil for the whole period but the ares is not defined in this agreement. 3. 4. Dead Bent* There is an annus,! dead rent, the amount of which is not stated. The first parent has to be made witum 15 days of the agreement becoming operative (17th 3 ui j , 1933). A loan slso has to be paid to the Government at the time »« the first dead rent payment is made (the amount of this loan Is not stated). Maps and geological reports have to he aubmitted the a overrent and an annual report on the *or&lt; done, rticle 23). / aiMtasi Wor* must commence by September 1»33. and drilling Vi4w % 11 mu«t continue witn two rige until the whole area has been explored in conformity with usual practice. ^ad rents cease when oil in considerable commercial quantity is discovered./ L i h. Hotes 'Corantreial tfiscovery* is defined in Article 7 ee when the Compemy completes the •digging* (Sinking) of one well or welle giving a test production (in conformity with reliable practice observed in first-class oil fields) of net less than 2,000 tons of crude oil dolly for a period of 30 days* This means nearly 730,000 tons &amp; year, and is a pretty severe test* It may be several years before this stage is reached. The absence of particulars • s to the amount of the loan and dead rents makes it impossible to say whether there is sufficient inducement to the Company to proceed to commercial production me quickly possible. The tonnage royalty payable under the Agreement is 4/«* gold {Article 115 and on 750,000 tons this would represent £150,000 per annum. The rate of royalty is the same as in Iraq* On the establishment of conimercial production another loan has to be made to the Government and a year 1 ter a further loan. Again no amounts are mentioned. Under Article 12, if the Company extracts, stores and sells any kind of mineral oil, a royalty of l/Sth of the revenue from sales is payable. This provision is rather difficult to understand. If it is worth anything it may involve the Company in substantial payments* ih@y may possibly get over it by setting up subsidiary compact Measurement of Oil Ac~.*.~ There are rsason&amp;hls provisions as to measurement ci oil won and the keeping of accounts. The Government has the right to cheek the quantities.9. 1 Bi'ljtiorloa ^ fixer© la a provision tliat the aompar^ xrn^i establish a reXinory ©uffloiont to neat the needs of the Government* fixe Government ma$- not sell any oil thus obtained either inside or outside tlx© country* After the eetobliatoent of a refinery tlxe Company has to offer to the Government a ’ loose” quantity (? bulk supply) of about EGOfOOO gallons ©f patrol and about 100*000 gallons of kerosene free of charge • Ihx© value of petrol at the refinery would not be leas than eay 5d a gallon and kerosene 3d or 44 a gallon so that this again represents a substantial obligation if the refinery is erected, but it is not clear that the . ■ mpa&amp;&amp; is obliged to inotal a r-ofinery* (The warding of tills and aomcs other parts of tixe agreement la somewhat vaipi© end may be du© to faulty translation)« 10* The Company is to be free from all direct and indirect taxes, dues, charges and fees (Including customs dues on export and import)* latlbnallty Beatriotiana The Conoossion is to be mema(&amp;&amp; o, Amarioons but subjects of Saudi Arabia are to be deployed a© far as poaaible* The Company shall not engage tlxa oubjeots of any other Government* 1£* hao eryat fon of lulnaralgjL Other Minerals are reserved to the Go vemment • 13 # pm Gompm? can terminate the agreement on giving 30 days* notice* The Government has the right to terminate the agreement for failure on tlx® part ox the Company to comply with those obligations« The uompany cmr also bo fined for broach of conditions.$ 4 *•' Tho arbitration o^jause proving tor tm ^QixvU^mit oX tai mr^iro and in tbe event of the failure of the arbitrators appointed bj the two parties to agree t the lunpire is to be appointed hj the President of the Permanent to art of Xnterimtion&amp;l Justice, lb. fra ngfer». Ohio Ooapan^r is not allowed to transfer its rights without the aonsent of the Government. Subsidiary omapanles may he foraad and ixdmbitaste of Saudi Arabia have the right to subsorih© ’ap to 30$ of the o-apitrfl of any coa^any formsd.CONFIDMTIAL. ®IC No.274, c POLITICAL AGENCY, KUWAIT. Dated the 18th November 1933 * To Lt.-Colonel H.R # P,Dickson, C*I # E., I.A., Political Agent, Kuwait; The Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, B u s h i r e . Oil - Major Holmes, Sir, I have the honour to report that there are indica tions that Major Holmes will shortly reach Kuwait, Such persons as his cook, other servants, etc., have arrived and are getting his home in order, 2 m Shaikh Abdulla al Salim, the Shaikh’s cousin, on whom I called to-day to offer condolences with him on the death of Shaikh Salman, told me in the course of general conversation that it was common property in Kuwait (probably spread by Mr.Mohamed Yatim, Major Holmes Confidential Agent) that Mr. Janson of the Eastern and General Syndicate, Lt.,London, had recently got together a powerful new oil Company in London, consisting of an American group and an English group, the latter holding the controlling interest, and would shortly ^ - send Major Holmes to Kuwait on behalf of this new combination to start fresh negotiations for an Oil Concession with the Shaikh. The Shaikh has said nothing to me about reo \ negotiations in the near future, nor have I mentioned the matter to him, 4. The above is for information only.CONFIDENTIAL. No. 1834-S of 1933 The Hon ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to 1» The Foreign Secretary to the Government of India, New Delhi. 2* The Political Agent, Kuwait.^ and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment (s). British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated • • &amp; 8thv*Nov ec/ber' • *1 £ 3 3 fj' V. . V 3T : , 7 Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. n Political Resident's Subject. telegram No. 1066, dated 28th November 1933, Kuwait Oil.Telegram ?rom B. Political Besiaent, Bushlre. H«M f s Secretary of State for ImU f London* Go^y Dy air mail to Government of Inaia, Foreign and Political Bepartment^ Hew Delhi* Ho. 1066 Dated 28th November 1933. For information. Political Agent reports that holies is expected shortly at Kuwait his servants having already arrived. Kuwait rum or has it that Jansen of Eastern and Sener&amp;l has got together re&amp; oil company in London consisting ot American ft English group. Besident.('ReceiTeri under «TKJ&gt;DA ^rifeted letter No. 3Q&amp;?&gt;/353/6fc of 31 ot October 1933). Brit! eh Legation, JISDBA. 3 lot etcher 1953. Sir S3rd Aufftiot iaat t relative *o the Haoa oil copceoei itran &lt;•«&lt;! hv the Sa*udi Arab Oovemwent to he Standard Ojti OoTsrxany of California, * have + }ir honour to inform vou that an official of the Company, Hr. W.J.Lenohon, air iTed here an its Jedda renresentativc on the IBth.October. Hr. Lankan, #io lias nreviouoly oerved hie Company in South America in an adminis trative rather than a practical capacity, h&amp;n had no previous emerience of this part of the ^rld. In conversation with me recently he ctated th« + ^ive fyeolo^ists, oresimably Amerieanc, had alread?^ arrived in Haoii and had been met by Mr. Mitchell, #io had assisted them in commencing- their work. Mr. Len|}mn added that more fteolo^ists were on their way and were shortly ejected to arrive in Hasa. P. It is understood that Mr.Mitchell is returninp to Jedda very shortly and that he expects to proceed on leave almost a + once. 3. I am sendinfr a copy of this despatch t© 'he Hon’ble the 'oliMcal Resident in the Persian hi If, Bush ire. I have the honour to be with the highest resrect, Sir, Hour moot obedient, humble servant, ad. A.B.aALVurr. to tVW; IWDlk OFFICE, P.2. 7741/33. ^ V ^ ! | rru^- WHITEHALL, S.W. 1. 3Ctli Novembei 1933. My dear Starling, Would you kindly refer to the Political Refciuent ? s telegram ITo. 1066 of 26th November about Kuwait oil, of tlx± which copies were sent to you, the Foreign Oil ice ana the Admiralty under our printed letter numbered as above on 28th November 7 2. You mentioned to me privately a few days ago that there was some reason to oelieve that a definite arrangement nao no 6 oeen reached between tne Anglo- Persian Oil Company an d the American interests concerned with Kuwait, but you were not yet in a position to give us any aefinite details. Would it be possible for you in any way to get any furtaer light on this latest Kuwait rumour which we could telegraph to the Political Resident 7 mnere/is another point which I think we ought to consider in this connection. Your impress ion was, I gather, that any arrangement between the A.f.C.C. American interests would probably be on the basis ox a , nr i v 0 p distribution but probably of b0/o0 aivision not ow oi x to in the Re&amp;iaent'J' - • + pi c o The rumour refers a — expxeitatr«n - . ncar ently contemplates telegram of 26th November equal y • , , T .m these circumstances if a joint Anglo-Arne&gt; ice 1 1. , . „ nv ev ent with an international we are dealing m any eve , rrpriC an a British or an American consortium ana not merely — * -y ; „H -a ™ **’' s u 111 ^ ^ imerican oil constitute an overt discrimination against A. .C. Starling, Esq., Petroleum Deprtment, Mines Department, Dean Stanley Street S.W. I-- 2 - (v?i\) ' 7 s ^ &amp; oil interests won -g ijresumably be greatly reaucea, if tae^ did not disappear altogether, ana having regard to nj difficulties wehave haa over the free hand which we gave to the Shaikh of Kuwait at an earlier stage in regard to the oil concessions which had been put forward to him by Holmes, we might, I think, consider whether we should not now instruct the Res inert to inform trie Shaikh in whatever manner was thought fit that the free hand in question xxx applied only to the specific concessions which he was the discussing ana that in the present altered circumstances we must require him to abide by his treaty engagements and to avoid eomraitting hiraself in any way ae regaros any oil propositions which might be put forward to him unless ana until he had received the auivce ofi them ox d.l. t. I am not sure that we might not also eon&amp;iaer i nf or mi him that the reply to any oil overtures should be that these must be in the first place suomittea through the Political Agent or through H.M.G. The question is, however, one of JUW some delicacy and we might nave a meeting to talk aboit it ana about the uraft A.p.O.C. Qatar oil concession, cne cay next wn.ek. 4 . i am sending copies of this letter to 'Warner at the Foreign Office and King at the Aomrarty. Yours sincerely, SD/ J. G. Laitbwaite. I\ v*&gt; QOVERNMENT OF INDIA. ‘ 1 / Department. EXPRESS LETTER ^,3.— This is an ORIGINAL message sent by AIR MAIL which provides a means of communication more expeditions than the ordinary mait and is cheaper than the telegraph. It is intended tb be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and to obviate formalities it is drafted in the form of a telegram. It is authenticated by the signature oj a responsible officer o f the Department.] No. 190R-'' of Dated the NeitTDelhi' 14th 'Pfscenber W 33, To XX 0*0*8 - “*er&gt;eat&lt;*d * ^cBidert t § BuaMre. India Office, London, f?ovemr!en + of India, Hen ’’’’elhi# Political Airent # ]r u ^ait. KHWAX^ OIL, *^iea8e refer to India Office letter Fo,41/33 dated the 30th Hovemher, 2. I agree nith the viena exnresaed in thin letter and suggest that 1 he authorised to nrite a letter *0 the !5)in’1* in the followinp terras, put of course in t netful language. (l) ^hat the free hand which he - the -ha^hh - had in the matter of the previotia Oil Oonceasion which was being Bought for hy the Anglo-Persian Oil Corapnny nnd the American Group represen + ert hy 3 f njor ] : olnes, Goes not apply to any new Group which nay approach him. (p) '’hat therefore he in bound hy Mb 'reaty enpapements. and that any new of'er which he receirea must lnnediately he c«mnicated to the 'bli’ical Apent I f0 r conriunication t 0 Ills iiajesty’s Government thro^ph ii't.-ht' the Political Resident. S. i4. DCFP—U24S&amp;P—(Ml*1314)-4r8-32-12,000. ( Designation)(3) That unMl Hie Majwty'B Oovprrnent ’ b aflvl oe on the offer in received he should not enter into negotiations. (4) '’hat eh en n spot i at ions are entered into, he should keep the Political Apent fully informed of their course. (5) ''hut he should not commit himself to the Company in any nay until His Majesty’s Coverwnent’s final advice on their final offer is received. 3, This letter, covering as it does all phases of an OH deal from hep-inniny to end, should ensure that se are not at any stage presented with a fait, accomj&amp;i.. 4 , with repard to the stiRpestion contained in India Office letter '•whether we nifdit not also consider infominp him (the Shaikh) that the reply to any oil overtures should he that these must he in the first place submitted through the Tolitical ipenf or through His Majesty’s Government'. I doubt whether it would he advisable to go as far as this, the Kuwait tpreement of 1913 (Aitchison. page 864. XLI - Volume XI) merely com it b the 'Shaikh not to give an Oil Concession to anyone except to a person appointed hv the British Government. though the Agreement of 1R9P (Aitohieon page 868. XXXVX, Volume XI) - -not to cede. sell. etc. « could also he invoked. '’he point is that apparently there is nothing in his treaties to prevent the Shaikh entering into negotiations with a Company, and merely applying for Mis Majesty’s Government’s sanction when these negotiations are completed. (The same applies to the other Ghaikhs on the Arabian Coast). however, have always taken up the stand that a Ghaikh must let us know isosftlli&amp;tftljr/and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment (s). for info mat Ion only. British Consulate-General, BUSHIKE. Dated. 30th December 1933, Name and Date. 1. India Office letter N o, P.7,.8035/33 dated the 13th December 10 33 to the ^oreipn Office. 2 e Vo reign Office letter H 0e B ^70l/l2/91 dated the 14th December 1933 to the India Office.I 7'’01/1S/91) . --wrsKjn omc , \\ Z. 14th i 193-3, f i f '« , 1 I - ^ IC’wJ ' My dear Oilhert, Maay thanks for your l-etter i-&gt; 8035/33 of 13 th December regarding the 50/50 arrangement between the Aa^le-Persian Oil company and the tfnited tateb Gulf Oil Company In regard to the development of oil in Kowelt* 2* I hiive not been able to traee any record of any definite approval having been given here on behalf of Hiy Majesty’s Government to any &amp;uch scheme, we are looking Into the question further, but meanwhile you may like to have the following note of the correspondence which I had in mind, and to which I think I alluded, at the meeting of December 11th* 3. The proposed 50/50 arrangement with the Americans was first mentioned in a conversation between Ir John Uadm&amp;n and Hall at the end of last year, as a result Laithwai te, - -&gt;q* H. itfbM fr!' -? » .5 lc i© -ai' (v -i ia /' ::&gt;•?:a I '• . ■ :rj£&gt;.; v... : :i i : ■ 't : ha- * .... ^ Hi 'tC 9tv»i'mr **n*u » . a# to p %sit r-j % m •i » - T * lit; ridl/i- «: 1 i-na «1 T t t t- ttin&amp;ov:? tc £!xJU«r:'&gt;a ,aiiX . 4 :a rij I O: \t -- Jv oq©^:;' x-*q A «S «©la^ -r^vnoD 4 ni iO«oXJn^r »s nil ...fit-ai'V „• . * «-:© f -i »i to Xxi ii-jis u./t'o% iii&gt; -*-.t -P- . . W -iJ-^ . 'V 4 . ' ^ ^ r n O / - - j ,&gt; ^ . n\ ''- o\ - ' ', •' ‘ ■ . ■ •' • ■ ' 1 • - ‘ - . i' u ‘ 4r&amp;unlt of which OUpturn! wrote to CadTnan on ’ rCvimber 50th 1952 and received a reply froa him the next day which it clear that the -ug^e,. tlon waa entirely tentative* Copies of the^e letters were «*ent to you, the etroleum department, the Admiralty and the Colonial Office in our printed letter No. &gt;S6/i2/9l of January 14th la at* 4. As a result of your letter P*'.« 311/35 of 19th January to Warner, I took the question uo with . ir John Cadman in Geneva and recorded the result of my conver ation in a letter of February 3rd to lamer, of which copies wore circulated by tamer to T eoartment. concerned under our So* ^ 3/12/91 of February 20th. The point was alluded to in the eour e of m interdepartmental meeting held at the Colonial office on March 3rd, when I said that my impression was that ir John Gadmen did not anticinate that he would be able to reach © final settlement with the American groun until the' th© di with the Persian Uowepxmemt w®t* settled am that he wa-..; therefore anxlou that negotiation® in cemnexlofi with the Koweit oil coneesaloa might he slowed down «sa far a** poai.-ihie until the Aagle-Perelan Oil C.osrpaa^ should he in a airoager po dtloa to tackle the Arne?lean group again. My recollection la that at this date we were all definitely in favour of the conelu ion of . r .uch c&gt;0/hO agreem-n,t between tho /\agio-Peraian Oil Company and the Mellon group, if it should prove the only me&amp;aa of preventing the conceailon from going to an American company outright? and it may he that, in the conversations ami eorreapondcace which parsed at thi^ time hctwcoa ir camel -illson of the Colonial Office and Hearn of the agio--- er..d©n Oil Company, acme kind of general approval of the proposed deal waa conveyed to the Company* b* Our ncmt reference to the 50/50 scheme in in paragraph 13 of the final record of the aeeUng held at .s.. ^at th@ QoloniaX Oftloa on April 26to dlacu-s various oil iue tlon ^ u i ^iiicfe yo\x, Moore and tarlin*,. were ir&gt;re ent f imt thti not nartieniariy illuminating,. 6 # I t&amp;lmk it emerges from all thi that our general attitude towards the sehewt wae that it waa a till entire.ly hypothetical ,,o that It was unnecessary to ejEpreas any definite view about it# I think our inclination, as X have said above, was to take the view that such a solution would he greatly preferable to the acquisition of the conees ion by a purely American group, which was a serious ** and at one time an i Tainent — possibility# On the other hand, ay own Impression, «„U 1 x m* your letter p « !&gt;• 7741/53 of Uoveaber 30th to ter Li mu *a» tluit any arrangeaant between the Anglo- ferai&amp;n Oil Co*w&gt;ny «Ki the Suit Oil Company would leeee teo aeta&amp;X exploitation of the coneeaaion in th- handu of the A&gt;vlo-Perslan Oil company, and in wlew of the earlier Admiralty tfbiootiona to the aohene expre„ ; ed in their letter Ho. M 0138/32 of January 27th, 1935, I do notnot think we emtla postlhly he ire given any kina of ofi’icial anniwaX to it without further prior tnteyde?&gt;artaentaX oansnltati on. 6* If, moreover, the nglo~”eratari Oil Coynnay .hiring tho really early stages of this quev-tlon derived the iffipres.-ion that the proposal had the 'bltmtng of His Majesty*- Government, t think it is clear from the nor re &lt;poo&amp;mm that that Me* star «souXd only have been giver, as I pointed out to Fraser at our meeting of Deeeatoer 11th, on th« ..^awptton that the extiioltotlon of thf concha on wouia In fact reaain In British hen.!. , t.trace all the r'i. oueelon of the natter had heen on that st. amotion. It wfto for that roe son that t saggeatcd that it might he well if Fraser could giT« »* further Infornation in writing a* to what had naueed. 7 . I t.aia over the telephone the other howler, I thlnt we ahall have to he extremely careful not to ralac wBiec.uaery oh^taclea at this rt m e to any scheme.eaerne which will ©How the Anglo-Oil Company to come In with at lea^t equal rights and vhleh rmy well, fui Fraaer suggested, lead to the exploitation of the conee-fculon being in, fact (if not by the terms of the agreement) in British hand;&gt;, luce it seem.* to me that there is &amp; very real danger, if we stiffen our conditions unduly, either of the Gulf Oil Company repudiating its agreement with the Angle-Persiait Oil Cosmany and coming back as an independent, and formidable, competitor, or of the tendard Oil Company of Qallforaia, which already holds the neighbouring concession on the Ha ,a coast, coming in as a new competitor, and the concession thus going: to purely American interest.-;- In view of our undertaking to the Ifni ted tat© Government that l?ailed states Interests will not be precluded from competing on more or less epu l terms, I think we might well find it iatxv Sbie to prevent thU. 8 . A«i you aeat copies of yonr letter to starling- , / CONFIDENTIAL. The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his com pliments to The Political Agrent 8 Kuwal and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned docu ment (s). for info mation « British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated. 30 $1 ,. ] ?ecpmhep..G9^3, Reference to previous correspondence : Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. ■Foreign Office letter No* E 7290/487/25 dated the 7th December 19 33 to the India Office, with enclosures. Subject. Kasa Oil Concession/ Kuwait Heutral Zone,(Received under India 0-*;j ce Prints Let+e- Ho. T’.Z. r &gt;944/33. ). ( S 7290/487/25 ) Foreign Office, S.W.i. 7th Becemher 1923. v My hear Laithwaite, I send you for your information the enclosed copies of correspondence between Lefroy of the Anglo-Persian Oil Company and myself regarding rights connected with oil in Saudi Arabia and/or the Koweit Neutral Aone which are said to have been granted by Ibn Baud to Mr. Abdulghani Idlibi of Manchester. It is, I think, self-explanatory, though vague We had some dealings with Idlibi,(who 2 is a British subject of Syrian origin) in 1932, when he claimed to have obtained from Ibn Saud permission to form a syndicate in order to prospect for oil and minerals. His prospects were thought by the Department of Overseas Trade to be poor l the capital of his firm is only £ 10,000 i , and he himself did not inspire confidence. It seems unlikely that Ibn Saud has 3 granted him authorisation to deal with the oil rights over the whole of Saudi Arabia, excluding the A a sa ccn- -cession, when as we know, the Saudi Government has had some dealings on the subject of oil in the Hejaz and asir with the # Iraa Petroleum Company, Italian interests, and possitly also Standara Oil. And as regards the Keweit JAG.Lai thwaite Hsqo, a. heard there of YdliM's alleged concession. 4. I am sending a similar letter to Starling at the tetroleum Department and a copy iarrer at the Department oi Overseas Trade. Yours ever, sd/- Christopher Warner.(Received under India Office Printed Le+ tfo.r.Z.7944/33). er Go py. ( B 6913/487/25 ). FOREIGN OFFICE,S.T/. 1. ^ 2 nd November, 1933. My dear Lefroy, 3ome time ago Lockhart of your Company made enquiries of us about the Traq-&gt; T ejd neptral zone, and. afterwards further enquiries about the Kuwait-ITejd neutral zone. About the same time Lew is on, of the Iraq Petroleum Company, also telephoned to us, and afterward.s came to see Johnstone of this department, on the subject of the exact geographical area and political position of the Kuwait-He jd neutral zone. Lockhart, in makiig his enquiries, spoke of a report that Ibn Saud had granted a concession in the Iraq-Nejd neutral zone to a Syrian. Lewison mentioned a similar report, but spoke of its being granted to an Assyrian. I asked Lockhart two or three days ago whether he could clear up the confusion, and he told me that his own enquiries had been made in consequence of a request from the I.P.C. and that their information about the reported concession was vague. ^e suggested th t, if I asked you you could very likely let ns know more clearly about the report which the I.P.C. received. Does it refer to the Iraq-Nejd or the Kuwait-Hejd neutral zone? Has the alleged concession been granted to a Byrain, or to an Assyrian? And do you know whether there is any substance in the report? I should be grateful for any information you can let me have. L.M.Lefroy Esquire, Britannic House, Finsbury Circus ,E. C. 2.Co py • ( E7S90/487/25) Britannic House, Finsbury Circus, LCHDOH,E. C. S, 27th I'Tovenber, 1933. My dear Warner, Here is the history of the worry to which you have been subjected, as requested in your letter U*6913/487/25 f . A month ago a Director of the Iraq Petroleum Company, representing the American Group, intimated to Sir John Cadnan , as Chairman of the I.P.C., that the N ear East Development Corporation had received information that a project was on foot for a concession for the Heutral Zone, either in its entirety or for the half which Ibn Baud assigned to an Assyrian (sicK ^he Management of the I.F.C., in circulating to the shareholding Groups particulars of the Neutral Zone, referred evidently to the Iraq-Nejd Neiitral Zone, west of Kuwait. It was clear to roe that the area really in question was the Kuwait-Hejd Neutral Zone, and I asked Lockhart to get what information he could about the history and exact boundaries of this area, which by your kindness he obtained shortly afterwards. Subsequently we received information which leads us to suppose that inptead of an actual concession having been granted, Ibn Baud has authorised a certain Mr. Abdulgani Ydlibi of Manchester to deal with the oil and mineral rights of Ibn Saud f s territory other than that covered by th e H a sa concession recently granted to the Standard Oil Company of California. This appears to be a method proposed of discharging a debt to Ydlibi for 'Manchester goods'! As to Ydlibi s nationality we have no information. Yours sincerely* (sd.) Lefroy. C^F.A.Warner Esquire, Foreign Office, S.W.l\fj/h CONFIDENTIAL. No - 0/7 of 1934. The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf phments to presents his com- Ttie Political Agent, Kuwait. and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned doom ment ($/)/ for information. Office of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Camp, Kuwait. Dated.. olh.. J anu ai;j;.. i.S.v.4 • Reference to previous correspondence » , . \ sc* 1 , \ Resiaemcy Printed Letter No.l993-S of 30th /,/ December 1933. Description of Enclosure. n Name and Date. India Office letter No.P.Z. 8054/33 dated the 18th December 1933 to the Anglo-Persian Oil Co.Ltd., London. Subject. Kuwait Oil.Whitehall,S.W.l. 18th December, 1933. Dear Mr.Eraser, You. will remember that at the meeting held here on the llth December you informed us that the A.P.O.C. had entered into an agreement with the Gulf Oil Company, which was signed and merely awaited ratification, to obtain and work a concession inkoweit jointly with that Company, on a 50/50 basis, which should extend to exploitation as well as to distribution, and you added that you had been requested to make it clear that this 50/50 arrangement with the Gulf Company had received the approval of His Majesty’s Government before the Company had entered into it. S. I remarked at the meeting that the India Office had no knowledge of such approval having been given, and we have not been able to trace any record of approval in any other Department. Perhaps you would be so kind as to let me know the nature of the approval to which you referred and the date on which it was given* Yours etc., (Sd.) L.D.Wakely.I Ho 3256/553/73 British Leg? ti on, o eucLi..,, 28th ^oveiaber 1 33* ideney, With reference to our despatch So 2167/ 3b3/51 of the 25th July last transmitting to you a copy of our despatch No 235 to the Foreign Office en closing t. trenail tion of the terms of the Kttt Ml Concession, we transmit to you herewith a reristd version. UeTeral inaccuracies in the. trans.ation wTing come to^light we decided to revise the whole document with the result that r. number tenuities, crudities of language and ommieaions have been rectified, iou will find that Articles 11, U ana 16 *ere pirticulrrly affected* Residency, Bush ire ith our apologies, ^~PfU-lsOEXTRACT from the Mecca M Umm-al- ur^*’ Rabi-ul-Awwal 1352 ( 14th July 1933) Ko 448 of the 17th DECREE Ho 1135. Grant of a cgnceasion for cocploit ,n K Petroleum. Je, Abdul '&amp;z£z ibn * Afedurr? timr n al Fey sal f»l Sa’ud , King of the Sr ’udi rab ingdom. After reliance upon God. And after per us 1 of the agreement signed at J edda on the 4th Day of Da far of the year One Thousand Three Hundred and Fifty Two by our Minister of Finance and Mr L.H. Hamilton, the Representative of the Standard Oil Company of 1*1 iy^P ^ i- . . ao-t e California, aurica. /nd after approval by the Council of Ministers, give the following Orders;- Articlel. The Standard Oil Company of C lifornia is per mitted to exploit Petroleum and its extracts in the eastern portion of our Sf * udi Arab Kingdom wit hi n i t^^ront^i&lt;g£s in f coordance with tile oonaitions and reguls tions laid down in the agreement signed by our Minister ot Finance ana trie Represent tire of the ssid Company at Jedda on the 4th day of oafa.r of the year One Thousand Three Hundred and Fifty Two. Article g. ■e sanction the agreement under reference which is attached to this our Decree, and order that it should be ,ut into force as from the date of its publication. Article 3 *'e also sanction the special agreement annexed to the origin 1 agreement and order th t it shill be put into force. Artie]e 4 . Our Minister of Finance should use that the pro- visions of this D e cree are put into force. issued in our Faladfe at “-'‘^OnE t hP 14th of Rabi-ul- «'«wal of the ^ e ^' T T p»o^ nS$S • orres ' ri- — (signed) ’Abdul ''Azfz. By erder of his Majesty the Kin^0 J- T^is Agreement h s been concluded between His Excellency ’ bdulleh al SuleymF,n?&gt;l He mdan Minister of Finance of the Sa’udi rab Kingdom, on beh If of the Se’udi Arab Government hereinafter called the Government, on the one hand, and Mr L.H. Hamilton, on behflf of the Standard Oil Company of California, hereinafter called the Compfny, on the other hand* The /greement concluded between the Government and the Company is as follows:- Articlel * The Government grant the Oompi ny in purs ance of this agreement and in conformity with the following con ditions concerning the area defined hereunder, for a period of sixty years as from the date on which this agreement is put into force, full right to survey, ; -r-&amp;yecrt, drill, extr ct, produce, treat, manufacture, transport, handle and export petroleum asphalt, Uaphta (min/er&amp;l oil) natural grease and tallow, other carbonaceous liquids^ and the extracts ol these produett* It is understood th t this right does not under any circumstances include the grant oi full light to sell crude or refined products within the limits of the undermen tioned. zone or within the S8.fiud.i Arab Kingdom* (sic, 1 rticle 8. The area to which tne full right referred to in Article 1 of this agreement applies has been agreed upon between the two contracting parties* 5 . The Company shell remit to the Gorernment within the period agreed upon in this agreement a preliminary loan as g&amp;reed. Article 4 . The Company shall pay to the Government annually an amount, which has been agreed upon. This payment will for the sake of simplicity be denoted as “annual rent” and this rent shall be paid in advance. The rent for the t.ist year shall be paid within theppriod provided for in the article 15 of this Agreement; and subsequently and for so long as this agreement is not cancelled the annual rent will be t^hle at the beginning of each period of one year reckoned trom^he1 lo H from the d.te on which thia agreement is put into force. ^ this rent must be paid within thirty days from the beginning of each year, provided that immediately after the discovery of oil is commercial quantities no further annual rent will be claimed or will toe liable for payment# Article 5. /s from the date of this agreement cooling into force the Company shall proceed with its plans and prepar - tions for the geological wort: end its arw ngements for wors so that it m y teJce adT ntage of the cold weather in order to undertake effectual field work, and may cerry out the clerical work ana make repprts, etc during the hot season. In any case the field work shall not be delayed beyond the end of September 19S3. Such work oh 11 nt energetically and continuously carried on until the beginning of boring oper tions or to the end of the agreement. At . tlele 6 . Within 90 day's of the date on which boring operations start the Company shall surrender to the Oovern- B.ent those parts of the included are in which it may aeeide , a/hiph it m Y decide to use in another to discontinue work or which xc m y manner in connection with this undertaking, ihe a.mptny shall also surrender to the Government from time to time during the period of this agreement such other areas as the Company may decide are no longer required for ,ros,ec ng ^ . rnr • nv our. ose in connection with or examination or for use for my pur t . ..viru. All the areas thus surrendered by the this undsrtiik in|j♦ , a from the restrictions and conditions Company shall be released f i om the «r,t but the Company shall h-ve the permanent ofb this agreement, tut rnt u p „ rnr the purpose of transport and right to employ those areas i or the p the duration of this agreement, pro- communicetions, dur.ng - nf them sh 11 cause only slight inter red thi t this use oi them sh t „ a aur ren- rnr which these Breas surrefu ference with the other purposes dared by the Co'STSS c » be used * s aoon „ nv sheU start boring operations s Article !• Xhe ■ 02li ' ' if he Company ..it-tie site and in any case a s it discovers a suit, tlCcni^any shall not h. ve stairted boring operations within ^ t, period of three years from the end of September 1935 (subject to the observ tion@ of the provisions of Article 24 of this Agreement) the Government m y then terminate this Agreement. he never the Goarrny begins boring operations it shall continue them energetic lly either until it discovers oil in commercial quantities or until the expiry of this agreement. If the Com any fails to announce the discovery of oil in comraercic 1 quantities at the time,then the date to be reckoned as being the date of dis covery of oil in commerci 1 quantities shall be tlie date on which the Company sh. 11 h ve completed the sinking of a well or wells and shall have examined them and found thea: capable of supplying not less than 2C0C tons of crude oil per day for a period of tuirty days consecutively in conformity with the practice observed in first class oil fields, erations include the ordering of implements and Xant and their shipment to Sa’udi Arabia and Iso in clude the makfog and : rep ration of roads, camps, buildings, fittings, transport and communications and the erection and runn ng of tools, machines and other means of well-sinking, etc. Article 8. Immediately after the discovery oi oil in commerni?X quantities the Coffl t any sh 11 remit to the Co vermaent the loan which has been agreed upon, and after one ye r shall m ke them another loan. The date of fcemittirg the first loan shall be th t on which oil is discovered in coniBierxi! 1 quantities bs laid down in this agreement, and that of remitting the second loan shall be after one year from that date. In both cases the Government sh 11 year from th&amp;t date, xn boti grant the Company a .eriod o: t o pay it. Article ■&gt;. rent sh 11 b commercial quantities and s erioci of sixty days delay in which it has also been agreed that • • • • • th tthnt the annual rent ohould fce paid in r dvr.nee, it is possible that the last payment of annual rent before the date of discovering oil in commercial quantities may in clude a certain period fter the date of discovery. If this extra/ perioa equals l/5th of a year or more, an amount of annual rent proportional to* this period will be considered as a loan due by the Government. Article 10 &gt; /s soton aa p esible (i.e. the Company will be allowed a reason ble time for ordering tools nd addition 1 materials ana for getting them shipped to S&amp;'udi arebia to st rt the ddition 1 work^ after the date of discovering oil in commerci 1 qunntities the Company shall resume boring operations employing at least two of the m chines and sh 11 continue these oper tions persistently and energetically till it completes boring all over theprescribed area, in conformity with the practice observe in first cl. ts oil fields, or until the expiry of th^P agreement. Article 11- The Company shi ll pay to th Government royalty on all crude oil drawn out and stored and which flows from the field stor ge reservoir after deductings (l) iater and other foreign substances. (?,) Oil required by the Company for the ordinary running of i&gt;$s .1 nt in the Sa'udi rab ing- dom. h _ t . .. (3) Oil requiredfor the purpose of mking those uantities of benzine and kerosene which will be supplied free to the Government every ye r in purs once of Article 16 of this .greement. The amount of royalty per ton net weight of crude oil will be • Four shillings gold or its e uiv lent. H?'♦ Xu c ee In accord; nee with the choice which the Company the time of p ysent of each instalment, one ; . currency per ton net ^ight of crude oil plus&amp;Ter&amp;^ft r. te of exchange is one dollar 14 cents • L •' • ^ currency for each four ahilltn^s gold (i.e. £ 1 gold^ 5*7 ) the-ni the amount of royalty on e&amp;cn ton net weignt of crude oil will be one dollar four cents* Article 12 * If the Cosut-. ny extracts, stores and sells any kind of miner 1 oil it sh 11 t &amp;y to ih* Governaent a r ealty uivalent to 1/8th of the revenue from the sales* It is understood th t the Coa^any is in no c ee bound to extract, store and sell &amp;*v mineral oil, and it is also understood tht the Company is not cound to jyy any royalty in res pect of the oil heed for the ordinary running of its plant in the Ba’udi Arab kingdom. Article id* Ty&gt;e Government have the right through their properly ut^orlsed representatives to inspect during ordinary working hours thework carried out by the Company in accordance with the provisions of this ! grcement and to check and verify the quantities produced, fhe company feit-ll always measure the quantities of oil produced and stored and which run from the iield depot, in accord nee with the practice observed in f&amp;ret class oil fieUr, cn-j shall keep true and correct accounts of them; similarly for the mineral oils which It may produce, store and sell, properly authorised Government representatives h ve the right to check these accounts at nil convenient times. After the expiry of one h If year from the date on which oil is discovered in commercial .unnfities, the Com^ny sir 11 « bmit to the Government a half-ye rly account within a period of three months from the end of the said * If *•**, *nd a statement showing the ***** ** royalty due to the Government for th t half year* the Government shall be bound to treat these accounts and statements as confidential, *ith the exception of those figure* which they my find it «. ,.«&gt;»»«&lt;•*—• 1 ,&gt; * itt au . ■» »* ““ «.«« - -««•“ :::'Z a 4 © commercial uantiliee, wit tun tftree months of itm end ol lull ye r* In thr* event of r.ny dispute occurring in res pect of Uw amount of royalty tfue for a half yc^r, the compeay n. ua over to th« Oovernment within the period stipulated v,bovt- that part of the royalty wnich is not in dispute, the m ttor of depute which my arise tefctweea %m two ^ties snail be afettlou by mutual a^eementp if settlement is not arrived at in this maimer, the dispute shall be Bottled ty arbitration &lt; &amp; provided for in thin grecaent. any amount the pry^ent of which Is dec ded to a result of this settlement shall be paid to the Government within GO days of the date on which the de cision is given. lI±*£A&lt;L.M* It la agreed fch*t all gold payment® proviaed lor in this agreement, whether goM pound® or gold efeiliing®, nim 11 be calculated by mei ns of Knglieh gold pounds in eccord- nuce with t. eir weiglit and pureness at the time pf payment. It is also agreed th t the payment® of gold currency provided for In this agreement, whether gold pound® or gold shillings, may be made by means? of an equivalent amount of American collars or pounds aterlin*,. U is furthermore agreed th t sueh payment in sterXi»u or in Americt.n doll are corresponding to thfc arneunt of the first loan and th® first year*® rent 8 ttH be calculated according to the rate of emc|sange on me day of payment of those &amp;imh&amp;, but that apart from tnia the equivalent in sterling or American dollar® of the gold pounds or gold shillings due under the term® of bhis agreoraent en 11 be reckoned on the b si® of zm ever go rate of e*ch »i?« du - ring the three months iiamodi ..fcc*y preceding the date Qi pry* msnt of th t equivalent* Article 15 * Ml payments provided for in this agreement and due to tm Government nft 11 either be y- id to them direct or sjKll be placed to their crecit in the tank which they uuiy a,point in writing. fh« Government a ve the right to ch, ngo tnii fc,hk fr m ti**e io time provided th t they inform the Com*tfte C0 V V ^ • uea *Cti■.» in writing .. , 8 to «iy C Com|M&gt;ny sufficient time to mi &amp;!c tneaa to arrange for safe* sequent peys»rit» to be mi- de to Ifte nm bank# it i a agreed tir&amp;'i the Dover me »it onould nominate for this purpose a bi-nk In elther dfe’e&amp;i the U i*A* i-ngl^na, or MollsM, provlaed th,t no b^k be ri^ea in Sft’udl /rabia unless it k,.® a cQirespondent in the u.d,,.. Sn^iand or hciUnc through whom money cm; be remitted^ to Ua*udi Arabia• in the event of the Company u- finn ai de an^eymen^to the Dovermient in the proper manner or having deposited the sum at du© to tiiem in any bank or having poid the sum to the e err respondent of a bardg for transmission to u.’udi r/ibii- then the Cojap&amp;ny shall be released from nil responsibility in res eet or eucn payment. It h. a been agreed tfc t the first p. yment egreea upon (i.e. the preliminary loan and tkerent or the first year} en 11 be paid within a period of %t days frtmt the date on which this agreement cornea into force to the correspondents of the Bet her lands Tr^din^ ;o- eiety of Jedd« {U&amp;*u&amp;i Ar^bi) at Bev York or London for ismedi?'to tr nsmission to tk Ketiicrl.- nds freding Bociety mentioned above at Ine expense of the Com.. &lt;■ ny, and for handing over to the Government agi inst proper receipt. If this first y&lt;ps&gt;Wt is not paid in gold it la y be paid la pouiida sterling at the rate of exe^nge ruling at the time when the Company pays the said mount to the correspondent of the b nk» Article 16 . ft#r the discovery of oil in comperei 1 quantities within ?&amp; rea»enable perio&lt;i t the con*-vny an xi choose &lt; .lace within &amp;&amp;*udi i rabia so ae tc cst blish « ^ factory to make o quantity of benaine and kerosene suffi cient for the ordin ry requirements of tnt Governaaent, pro vided thrtt^the crude oil f?'Un&lt; is ot n na ture « ciccuate for such m nuf cture on n commercl 1 kvh&amp;s b«u is by ordinary preoeases *f refining and th. t the oil produoid is adeou te6* Li« s' equate for tJaeec pur|&gt;o«ei* It is underatood thet the requi rements of tne Covernaserit will not include e*X«tt on their ps^rt inside or outside a^*udi .r^fei&gt;- # The Comp; n* aixa^X proceed to estahliah this factory after completing., tne necessary preliminary arrangements und ; f ter ofet&amp;iaiag the Government 1 u tpproml of the |l^ce w&amp;i .-h Ui y suggest* During each aucceeeive period of one year follow ing the arte of cosiplet.on of the eeiAhlieJfnee&amp;t of this factory the Oenp^ny sh&amp;ll supply to the C?:vernsient f in hulk uM free of charge, 800,000 .nerienn gj Hone of dentine and 100,090 America n gallons of kerosene. It Is understood tikit the met nods adopte hy the Government in taking delivery of these quantities shall act h&amp;mper or endanger the operations ®f the Company'. Artici ^ 1?. The Company ©h 11 es^loy at it© own expense the number of guard® and guides needed for the protect ion of its representatives, cam^ s, and eotahliohaents. The Government promise to afford full assistance to the Company by supplying the best so', diere and r-en they possess and raking them res pond ole for the disciurgs of this duty. The Government will supply to the Cmy&amp;n« all reasonable protect ion at rates not exceeding the usual ones they pay to them or to ther persons in return for similar services** It is understood th t the ex penses incurred in connection with such services ah 11 be paid to the Goverament by th- Com,any. Article IB* In return for the obligations undertaken by the CouptiQy in purs- nee at %AU sgrecaent, and in r..peot of tne jd^aentB eue troo tner Coat- ny as provided for in. tni» a^reoaent, tnt C 0 Bip 2 .no and the undartaiing Bhs.ll fee eAempted tvaa all diroctjwM indirect b b.b, dues, ehergeo end fee# Unoludin* euetome due. on export and iaportj. it i« underetood that this privilege doee not npply to tne sole at products inside/ the country nor to the pereonel re uireaente of the aw era of tne et ff of the Cwapany. i'he noapsni i« not ellWBd 10 s * 11 within ohe country «ny of its mtar^a iaported free of cuato.a duty, except after payment of auch duty.tendered liable to y, y compensation to the Government for the h rm caused. In the event of disagreement concerning the amount of corn- pens tion it shall be settled cy the means of arbitr tion provided for in thlis agreement, the Company ah?. 11 pay the Government the suai awarded fey way of compensation in themenner mentioned above within a eriod of sixty days from the date of the award. Tticle 28 , If any doubt, difiiculty or dispute snail arise bet ween the Government and tire Company concerning the interpretation of this agreement or its execution, or in the interpretation or execution of any thing in it or connected with it, or concerning the rights or responsibilities of either of the two parties, and if the two parties f il to settle it by any other method, the c se shall be referred to two arbitrators, one chosen by e- eh pprty, and one ch irnv n chosen by the arbitrators before the commencement of the arbitr tion, Bsch party sh. 11 nooiin te his ?rbitrstor in writing within ? -period of thirty days from the dejre of the appli- cation of the other party. If the two arbitrators fail to agree upon the appointment of a chairman, the Government and the Company shall appoint the ch irmen by grcement 5 if they fail to do this they s ell apply to the president of the lermrnent international Court of Justice to appoint the chairman, who sh 11 be definitely considered as otoief arbitrator in the cane, ’cut if the t*o arbitra tors do not gree in their opinion, the judgment of the etairm&amp;n inshell also have the right to establish other similar companies or institutions whenever it appears to the Company that they are advantageous or necessary in order to ce rry out the purposes of this undertaking. Such companies or institutions sh 11 imme diately become invested with some or all of the rights and under takings provided for in this agreement, and after the Government has been duly notified, they s^iall also be subject to the con ditions end provisions of this agreement. In case the newly formed company or institution issues shares for publi* sale, the inhabitants of the 3a* udi Arab Kingdom shall be allowed a treasonable time to subscribe (under the same conditions as tnose offered to others; to at least 20 % of the shares offered for s al e • 7rticle 3t- The date on wnich this agreement ehall be conside red as coming into force shall be the date ol its publication m the Sa’udi Arab country after its ratification by the Company. Article 56 . It is understood that the periods of time referred to in this agreement shall be c Iculsted on the h.sio solar calender• Article 32 . In order to avoid misunderstanding, it should x a + neither the Company not any person be clearly understood that neither rn- u y •d.n + Vi cs the ristht to interfere . , r*fstvned with it h^ s uii ■■a belonging to it or connect „Ti + ir l or religious affairs of the in the administrative, politic 1 oi rei g p, 'udi Arab Kingdom. rticle33. It ih understood that this agreement, after being signed in Sa’udi Arabia, shalj. be referred to the Company s P r n- . . h of California , for rstifi- cipals at San Irancisco, the etc - five After signature Oi the t M ore it becomes operative. cation before the signed „ sl „ .«« *&gt;“• copies sh ll be .01 . , ifor „i. ). Sithin fifteen ters of the Company at oan - ^ the 4 4- nf the copies the Company sh U days of recelp rRtii - iC ation of this agreement, or Government agreeing to the rafified/ * within fifteen otherwise, and if this egieemen days as from i vjl * ^ -i j . tt b k. U be ftanttcfflEd as oancilied an that date, it sibii oe .. andV iS r and of no effest. Likewise if the preliminary loan and trie renl f6r the first ye^r are not p&lt; id to the Government within the period rgreed upon in Article 15 of this firgreement, the Govern ment sh 11 hr. Ye tWright to announce the annulment and crnce- i llation of this agreement and to consider it of no effect. In the event of the agreement being ratified the Com. ^ny shall re turn to the Government one of the t^c signed copies of both texts together with the necessary certificate attesting to the Company 4 s ratific lion. Similarly, this agreement after r tifi- cation by the Company ah 11 be published in Sa’udi Ar. bi in the us uo1 me nner• Signed on this day the 4th of in far in the ye r or.e thous nd three hundred and fifity two 1 eor bs ponding to the 29th Aay 1953; (Sind) /.bduliah al Suleyman al Hand an fhe Minister of Finance. For the Government of the Sa’udi mo K ingdom. (Snd) L.K. Hamilton Apr the Standard Oil Company of galiforni: . Hi (M.B. In the -;.bove tranoiation the word*X.oac' is an exact transition of the :.r ; btc word hoed but probably the word 'subsidy' would be more correct;.. INDIA OFFICE LIBRARY and RECORDS Photocopying record Ref. No. IOL: ICR Date Name Process No. of exposures 1 aui fe'Wck '? 2 3 4 5 6 REFER TO THE SPECIALIST CONCERNED V</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0000f5_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/5/242</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0000f5</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/5/242</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>'File 5/1 VII Kuwait Oil Company'</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1933/1933</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2017-07-17T14:46:44</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (225 folios)</extent><extent>The papers are arranged in approximate chronological order from the front to the rear of the file.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the inside front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 227; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. Two additional foliation sequences are also present in parallel between ff 6-222, and ff 180-222; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>This file contains papers relating to the securing of oil agreements in Kuwait. Most of the papers consist of correspondence between various British Political Agents in Kuwait and Bahrain, the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, the India Office, and the British Legation at Jeddah. The papers discuss the British governments position with regards to exploring for oil in the Arabian Peninsula and Persian Gulf region with the view to securing as many contracts as possible for British firms as the region became increasingly visible to international oil companies after the discovery of oil in Bahrain in 1932.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Contract law</topic></subject><subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Eastern and General Syndicate Limited, oil company</namePart></name></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>British Legation to Saudi Arabia</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Petroleum</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000831.0x0000f5#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>