<record xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/2.0/" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"><header><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x00010a_en</identifier><datestamp>2018-04-18T03:07:06.081Z</datestamp></header><metadata><mods xmlns="http://www.loc.gov/mods/v3"><note type="ocr">L _ No. 298- 3 of 1^58 ^ i .sn Keciaettcy axici Consulate uezieral, Busnire, tne 2tttn May 1938. /- © i To * \ political ,\gent, Kuwait Political ^gent, Musca Political \gent f Banra 3ubject t Supply of spare copies * Memorandum It haa been observed recently that in several instances papers have been received witnout an adequate number of spare copies. Copy of Kesidency Memorandum No. 536-3* dated lOtn June 1933, is enclosed, and it is requested that tne instructions contained therein be strictly adhered to. Id. T.C. F&lt;ML3 Political Kesident in tne Persian cull. ATTRSTSD Secretary to the Political Resident in trie Persian uulf mi iBritiah Kesidency and (joneolate Geneml Buanire, tne lOtn June 1953. To Tne Political Tne Political The Political Agent, Kuwait. Agent, Banrain. Agent, Muscat. Memorandum As there is at present a certain lac* ox uniformity in tne supply of• spare copies of letters and enclosures tnareto received from Agencies it is requested tnct m future spare copies may be furnisned as follows. '.Vnen tne correspondence snows tnat copies are forwarded by tnis Residency to (a) tne Government of India only 2 spare copies (b) His Majesty’s Government ) and tne Government of India) 4 • • Additional spare copies, up to a total of 6 , snould oe furnisned in cases in wnicn it is lively tnat copies will be forwarded as well to otner posts, suen as Baghdad, Jedda, etc. As B flimsies can be struct at one impression tnis would involve no additional typing at tne Agencies and save much at tnis Residency. .Id. T.C. ro/LK, Lt .-Colonel, Political Kesiaent in tne Persian Gulf. attested : 5 d. J # 0 R(BfHTG fnr secretary to tne Political Resident in tne Persian uuif.to f . X~Tt&gt;ci'c'C» % jtilx fetus xytt 0 J 3 i fl.si 9ru*L n?ui an? I , * i6‘ 9/v. .ui«tfiaft » ane^ Xb 01 ;‘i i* r] xW . rtju «*?&lt; T2rnoii»r' K- &gt;o»X at».3*ivo s iraew^Tq 5 ^ iTuS'oi ai ;•. uj e» lirXIHLi v-c ii ri^noxaiut 90 B»*i.CC -** 0 ^ 5'TS 291 IC O JK112 fifOtlR !&gt;biS®fJtt&lt; #^|' r 0 3 in? £.«r; 07 x;ms*fcissft sia# \;tf feol-•■??%- ’rr/r ■ &amp; §0 CJLUCX12 f o I- XjC 7C 7 ~ 0 7 Qi' &lt;» '- - VX’- X. i*-. * •■ ^ t i ^o o 3 xux 7 al 7l no id* ai '®t^o ni fethaifr'-'-'T ,t&gt; H&gt; 1 * 3 *S a«{ nocc &lt; •U’aoQ i»n7o c: :.C®v «a ? H tfil toot tottqpii 9^0 7« aa ant n B e f |u^Of .C.T «M ‘rl'K,’' m^ i•’'Ttstvi J«ei . B9&gt;t JLfiOl 7 tier tmiir r .t .x*?: X^f&gt;.T ylX&lt;^ 303 &lt;7 w*iJ- •tiL'i? ctfilawi ®a7 ttiM. P. ROACH f LATE MANAGER LAWRENCE &amp;■ MAYO LTD. ^ RANGOON &amp;■ KARACHI. LATE MANAGER LAWRENCE &amp;■ MAYO LTD RANGOON &amp;■ KARACHI. 'ppoimtmcnt to the Admiralty, ) s \ P OPHTHALMIC OPTICIANS AND DEALERS IN SURVEYING, DRAWING NAUTICAL INSTRUMENTS, ETC .Bahrain « ( Iranian G-ulf ) . Dear Sir, In accordance with the instructions received', fron The Hon 1 hie Lt. Col. Sir Trenchard Towle • C . I• E. ,C .B.we he^ to acvise of having - desx)atcheci to Bahrain c/o ^our Agency the following pairs of spectacles,kindly accept the two parcels,and retain them till they are called for. One pair of spectacles per V.P.P. for Hi 33/14/-intended for Farash Ebrahim. Two pairs of spectacles per Regist ered Parcel for Sadiq,also to be called for. MAMA MANSIONS, D^U^RA&amp;ljylS&amp;AD, MAMA MAN 5 -INVERARJJY 1 The Political Agent. Kindly acknowledge receipt of the 3 packets. Thanking you.GTC. L Telegram From To TTo. Political Ageu^, Muscat;^ Political Agent, Bahrain 12 . Dated the 5th and received the t&gt;th January 1939 l\ &amp; Kindly redirect Bushire my registered envelope^ to Political Resident sent by post Bamora January 4th. - POLITICAL - tL (LA yvj^A- ■ jk UUcV-N N—' r-. /~S oU^r , I am desired to draw your attention to the way-cills» (our duplicate copies are enclosed for ready reference), which your office has teen sending out for some months past, and to request you to go into the matter with a view to re-commencirfc use of the usual printed forms. H. Weightnan Esquire, ICS., Political j^ent, Bahrain.\ A \ No. 80/XIX/B-8. L Political Agency, Muscat, January the 20th, 1939. hfy: Bear Agency, herewith We are sending/a cover addressed to His Britannic Majesty's Consul-General, Bushire and would be grateful if you would please despatch it to him by 8.8. Barpeta. The Political Agency, BAHRAIN. Yours ever, Agency. \131-16/32. The 22nd January 1939. Dear Agency, Your letter No. 80/XIX/B-8 of January 20th, 1939. We are sorry but your cover was not delivered until 6-0 p.ra., by which time the mail had gone. Yours ever, Agency./ ft 0 T E In Stovte j godown. Under instructions from the P.R. - (a) The Model Dhov which was received from Kuwait for the p.R. should be opened up and inspected• If necessary, it should be repacked carefully for ship ment to England^Later* (b) One Silver Arab Coffee pot; and (c) One Silver Tray - are to be jracked carefully and kept in the Agency. 2« All the above are to be forwarded to England on receipt of instructions from the Hon'ble the P.R. (Sir Trenchard Fowle). 18-2-1939. Agency Office File 16/32. Copy for P.R* Copy for Head Clerk, Bahrain Agency. I/* (i-p (b. ^ ■ bcT/ ^ ft/v, 7 jY ij. fU&gt;i- fe- &lt; 7ML — \ f Telegram From ^iC . To No. Dated and received - G.T.C. -Britconsul,3ushire (Relayed from Basrah). - Political,Bahrain. - 139. - 16th March, 1939. Rushton my new Secretary with his family is on board up slow mail en route to Bushire. You might like to meet him.flo.S^O -17/8. Will you pleaae supply t*G Document Cases (H 0 ./V.I 8 ) with three eliding shelves similar in size (appro*ime tely high 20 ' wide and 18' deep) to the one supplied by you in June 1933. For facility of identification your bill of 1933 is enclosed. 2* The oases should be painted green, without any let tering, and the locks should be stronger tton the type supplied in 1933. 3. The cases should be shipped to Bahrain addressed to The Political Agent, Bahrain, and the Bill of Lading should be sent to that officer. 4. Your bill should be sent direct to this office. Copy becretary in Yoi ^* 8 faithfully, to the Political Resident the Persian Gulf. to the Political Agent, Bahrain, with a request that the cases may be stored until the Political Resident can collect them on tour.cJ r ^ nU . * v*' h 1 ^ jD 4 i i I; f P ■■I h In B&gt; _gP Telegram G.T.c. From Political Resident, Bushire Political Agent, Bahrain. Unnumbered. Dated (and received) 1st May 1939 . » (Relayed under Unseat No. 5 of 1st Kay) Please Arrange to take delivery of onee cover The Bamora has not arrived as yeti May I send this to the .U.O. for favour of collection ?/• The Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Political Agent, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents (s). with the request that the seeds may he retained until they can he collected by the Political Resident on tour* British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated• Name and Date Subject. S' L l Residency letter No* ^3 dated 9th June to Messrs. / Pestonjee P. Pocha &amp; Sons, / V u s(_ /with enclosures* Flower and Vegetable seeds for Bushire Residency.i AIK IUIL AO* Krlti«h consulate uenoral* Kuohlre* the 9th June 1939# ^ear aire 9 ilease forward by the first sea Ball to ifee lolltloal He side nt la the jerelaa ttilf, o/o ifce } oil tleal .v^nt f uahraln # the flower and veritable seeds mentioned in the attached lists* Your 0har&lt;ges will be set on receipt of your involoe* 2* ihe oonsignBent should be aceosipanled by two ooples of the health certificates in reepect of the seeds# which should also be addressed to bahralu* 3* In no olrcuBStanass should the seeds be posted to hushlre* Yours faithfully# od. J'.OKOAIAG for Jeoretary to the i^olitloal He aide nt in the rerolan Ailf* Keesre iestoMjee y. locha 1 Jons* lost cox Ad*S 5» ieona* India*Kind Quantity Beetroot - Crossdy’s Egyptian 1 ounce Cabbage - Cape largest drumhead 1 ounce Carrots - Danvers 1 ounce Cauliflower - iSarly Snowball i ounce Celery Golden Self Blanching i ounce Indian Corn - Mamoth, white corn pound Knol Khol 1 variety 1 oz • Lettuce 2 varieties 1 oz• each Peas 3 varieties i pound each Raddish - Crimson Giant Globe 1 ounce Spinach 3 varieties 1 ounce each Turnip - 3arly Snowball Tomato 1 ounce Ponderosa 1 packet Crimson Cushion 1 packet Sage 2 packets Parsley 1 packet Onion 1 packet ******No. 1044-lb/32 Political Agency Bahrain, the 2bth June 1939 To Nesars. Lotia Storee, Elphinstone Street, Karachi. Dear Sirs, Two crates containing steel document cases for the Secretary to the Hon*ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf have been received. *** Copy to Buahire . *** Sent under P.L.No. 1045 dated the 26th June 1939. The document cases will be handed to the Hon’ble the Political Resident on arrival. Yours faith^lly for Political Agent,BahrainPOCHA'S SEEDS SATISFY &lt;S&gt; ESTABLISHED j 1 1884 ptdofifte (p. Pacha ^ E E RCHANTS ^ , 8 NAPIER ROAD, welzcframs 5 ^ms.'ip_oqna. Poona, ..19 39. Ref:F928/F1297/ELJ. The Political Resident in the Persian Golf, Bahrain. — uUH&gt; * Dear Sir, In accerdance with instructions from your secretary at Bushire, we have sent you some flower and vegetable seeds by registered parcel post,which please accept. Enclosed are two copies of health certificate. The seeds are from our fresh and tested stock and we are sure they v/ill do well under ordinary favourable conditions of climate and culture. Assuring you of our best attention at all times, we remain ? /a.C-p.—(J) Q 1—12,000—7-38— P2 Dir. Agri. No. S. 52-4206 dated 2-4-38 Department of Agriculture, Bombay. (PHYTOPATHOLOGICAL SERVICE) CERTIFICATE. ' This is to certify that the planl(s), liviug plant (a) ofr plant product(s), included in the consignment, of which particulars are given below, thoroughly examined on the June 21, 1959 by , pp. B.N.Uppal a duly authorised official of the Department of Agriculture, Bombay, and found to be healthy, no evidence of the presence of any injurious insect, pest, or- disease (destructive to agricultural or horticultural crops or to trees or bushes) having been found — them and that the consignment (including the packing) covered by this certificate ^ q t been treated in the-.following -manner (e.g-, fumigated or disinfected-with ) immediately wmsequent Inspected 111 tbS'lHdd by a duly authorised-InspacW oii~~ Not inspected- ORIGINAL [Spl.—Agri. 97 © Signature Plant Patholog-iet (Official Status) flwnmninnt, B. P., Po«n*- No. F.ai/yS'oyf 19 39» F 00 ^ . Dated Bombay ’ No. and description of packages 29 Distinguishing marks Description of plants or plant products or parts thereof. Stated to be grown at Exported by Name and Address of consignee Name of vessel or particulars of route Date of shipment Port or place of entry Additional Certificate(s) attached. \ • Packets containing flower seeds and packets containing vegetable seeds# Flower and vegetable seeds# Messrs# Pestonjee P. Pocha and Sons, Poona# The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, C/0 The Political Agent, Bahrain# By post#aOP.HJ) Q 1—12,000—7-38-P2 Dir. Agri. No. S. 52-4206 dated 2-4-38 [Spl.—Agri. 97 » Department of Agriculture, Bombay. r (PHYTOPATHOLOGICAL SERVICE) . % v CERTIFICATE. This is to certify that the plant(s), living plant(s) or plant product(s), included in the consignment, of which particulars are given below, ^ as thoroughly examined on the 22nd June 1939* byD r . V.G.Reshpande a duly authorised official of the Department of Agriculture, Bombay, and found to be healthy, no evidence of the presence of any injurious insect, pest, or disease (destructive to agricultural or horticultural crops or to trees or bushes) having been found ^ them and that the consignment (including the packing) covered by this certificate been treated - ra-tbe fol lowing manner -jpg^- fmaadgaltd with or disinfected with ) —v to insp ect ion sUHwiquuul ^ ‘ I«S}&gt;ecte&lt;l in the rieid by a July mi Net inspected Signature cf Fntomolofiry (Official Status) Cca ^ e C f Agriculture, Fouu*. No. 22/ ofl£69». Poona iioxDbey Dated 22nd June 1939» ■^No. and description of packages 29 Packets of flower and 22 of vegetable seeds* Distinguishing marks Description of plants or plant products Flower 2c vegetable seeds, or parts thereof. Stated to be grown at Exported by Messrs. Festoonjee P.Pocha Sc Sons, 8 l&amp;pier Road, Poona. Name and Address of consignee Name of vessel or particulars of route Date of shipment Port' or place of entry Additional Certificate(s) attached. The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. c/0 The T&amp;litical Agent, Bahrain, By Post.No. 1192-16/32. Political Agency, Bahrain, the 12 th July 1939. O To The Secret^ ^y to the Hon'ble Political Resident in the Bushire. the Persian Gulf, Memqmrjdum /{ With reference to your printed letter No. 784 dated the 9th June 1939, would you please inform the Hon'ble the Political Resident that the seeds have arrived in Bahrain. for Political Agent, Bahrain. ft C'Vi- BRITISH RESIDENCY &amp; CONSUDAT^-GEnERI . BUSHIRS, the 13th July 103B. To The Head Clerk, The Agency, Bahrain The Political Resident’s cases and carpets left in the Agency, Bahrain Memorandum. Could you please let me know whether any of the carpets have been sold which I left in the Agency ? 2. I propose leaving the carpets and my two cases in the Agency until I return from Shiraz in the middle of August when I will issue instructions re their disposal. Sd. T. C. Fowle. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. ATTESTED. Personal Assistant to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. /Pclitical Agency, Bahrain, the 22nd July 1939. To:- The Honourable Lt.-Col. 2ir Trencherd Fo77le,K. C. I.b., C.B.E. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Sir, With reference to your letter dated the 13th July 1939, I beg to state that none of your carpets have been sold yet. Your circular was sent round as ordered but no offers have been received. I beg to remain Sir, Your most obedient servant, fvt- 4 Head Clerk./ „ ' ■brill ah he aide nay and vionaulate General, ■buahire, the 16th itu^uat 1939. To ihe head ulerk. The Agency, •» Bahrain. Memorandua Reference Mr# Stephen*a note of the 18th February % last with regard to my gooda stored in the Agency, i#e# (a) a model dhow (b) one ailrer Arab coffee pot) (c) one silver tray (d) carpets for sale in the head Munahi's office. 1 box 2# Please arrange with Messrs. Gray Mackenzie &amp; Co#, Ltd. Bahrain, to have (a), (b) and (c) sent to me c/o Cox &amp; Kings (Agents) Ltd., Kings House, 10 Hay Market, London, S.W.i by any direct steamer thus avoiding transhipping of the packages. Please ask Messrs# Gray Mackenzie to insure the packages against total loss, theft and damage, to the value of (a) £ 1 /- (b) &amp; (c) £ 10 /- 3# The Bill of Lading and the Insurance Policy should be sent to me c/o Lloyds Bank Ltd#, 6 Pall Mall, London, S#V#i, by registered air Mall , and the Company should inform me to Bushire by what steamer the packages are being sent, and on what date the steamer will reach England. on receipt of the Company's bill I will send them a cheque# /4 • iTith regard to (d)• Please see your letter of the 22nd July informing me that ao far no offers have been received# Please let me have a reply by return post to Bushire whether any offera have since been received, 4 and in any case send out another notice aa in Mr# Walker's note of the lot July# I will keep the carpets for another miinth or ao in the Agency in case offers are received# if any offers are received later please let me know by air mail to c/o Lloyds Bank Ltd., 6 Pall Mall, London, •.W.i# • . Sd. T.C#FOWLS’ Political Heaident in the Persian Golf Attested Per it to the Political Hesi dent in the Persian Gulf.i c Polltleal Agency, Bahrain, the 23rd August 1939 To Messrs* Gray, Mackenzie A Co* Ltd*, Bahrain* Dear Sirs, I am sending herewith two packages marked (1) and (2) addressed tot~ Sir T.C. Fowls, c/o Cox and Kings, London* containing (1) a model dhow and (2) one silver Arab coffee pot and a silver tray, for despatch by direct steamer to avoid transhipment en route* The packages should please be insured against total loss, theft and damage, Ho* 1 for £*1 and Ho* 2 for £* 10/-* 2* The Bill of Lading and Insurance Policy should please be sent to me for despatch to the Hon'ble Lieutenant- Colonel Sir Trenchard Fowls, and your bill should be sent to him for settlement* 3* The Hon'ble Sir T*C. Fowle would be glad If you could inform him of the name of the steamer by which the packages are sent and the approximate date of their arrival in England* Yours faithfully, Head Clerk, Political Agency, Bahrain*Political Agency, Fshrain, the 26th August 1 o9. To:- The Hon T blc Lt.-Col. Sir T.C.Fowle, K.C.I.E., Politic?! Resident in the Persian Gulf, Pushire. Sir, I beg to refer to your letter of the iGth August 1939 and to say that as instructed the two packages containing (1) a model dhow, and (2) one silv r Arab coffee pot and one silver tray, have been sent to Messrs Grey Mackenzie and Co Ltd, for onward despatch to England, insured against total loss, theft and damage, by direct boat. A copy of my letter to them is attached for information. 2. No offers have yet been received for your carpets and another notice has been sent out c s ordered. I beg to renr in Sir, Your most obedient Servant, IleFd Clerk.7 i Telegram:- G.T.C. From:- Britconsul Bushire. To:- Political Bahrain. Unnumbered. Dated:- 29th August 1939. Please keep ray boxes till further notice.i oli icel Agency, Bahrein, the both /ugust 1939. To: - Messrs Grey Mackenzie &amp; Co Limited, Pa lira in. Deer Sirs, Please refer to my letter dated the 23rd August 1939. 2. The Honourable Lt.-Colonel Sir T.C.Fowle has instructed me by telegram not to despatch the two packages at present, '’ill you pierce, therefore return them to this Agency per bearer. Your 05 faithfully, Bead Clerk.HEAD OFFICE-. 122. LEADEN HALL STREET, L0ND0N.E.C.3. TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS. GRAY. CODES USED: BENTLEYS COMPLETE PHRASE. BENTLEYS SECOND PHRASE CODE. Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co. Ltd. (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND) BRANCHES: BUS R E H. AM AR AH. K UT. KHORAMSHAHR AHWAZ (for BANDAR-SHAH POUR) BUSH I RE. BUNDER-ABBAS. LINGAH. BAHREIN. KOWEIT. DUBAI. SHARJAH. MUSCAT. IN REPLY PLEASE QUOTE No. L/657. Bahrein, 30th August, 193 9. The Head Clerk, The Political Agency, BAHREIN. Dear Sir, Reference your letter of dates In accordance with your letter of the 23rd instant, the two packages in question were duly shipped per SS. H TURKISTAN H which sailed hence on the 26th idem. Enclosed herewith, please find the relative Bill of Lading and the Insurance Policy. Yours faithfully, EncsTelegram GTC From Political, Bahrain. To Britconsul, Bushire No 177 Dated the 30th August 1939. Your telegram of August 29th. Political Resident 1 s boxes left by TURKISTAN on August 26th. POLITICAL -Politicsl Agency, Pchrein, the 5th September 1959. To:- Lt.-Colonel Sir Trencherd Powle, K.C.I.E., C.B. c/o Lloyds Psnk Limited, 6 Pell Mall, London S.W.l. Sir, I h&amp;ve the honour to refer to your letter of the 16th August 1939, persgreph 5, and to forward herewith the Insurance Policy end Bill of Lading for two cases shipped by the S.S Turkisten. I have the honour to be Sir, Your most obedient servant, Head Clerk.Telegram Prom Brltconoul, Buahire Political, Bahrain. Nil QTC To No Dated and received the 1st September 1939. Following from PRIOR: Begins:* Please ask MESPKRS to send me by this up mail six cases good whisky three cases gin one case good light sherry half dozen French vermouth half dozen Italian vermouth four dozen bottles beer. I will send them sterling or rupee cheque for cost. Label should not mention military rank. y , f. AVo. 1184 t/17 1. © British Consulate-General, Bushire* 3rd Septemlier 1939* Messrs Army tc Navy Btores # B o n li a y* Gentlemen, Would you on the strength of the enclosed No fcjeetion Certifleate he good enough to send 60 rounds of .380 acnnunition for Colt poeket automat Is pistol to the address of Assistant ^olitieal Agent, Politieal Agency, Bahrain, as soon as posslhle. The hill may kindly he sent to me here. Yours faithfully. Copy to the Assistant Political \gent, Bahrain. Will he please hand over the ammunition on receipt to Mr. J. Croning./am ii /14 iritiah Coneulat•-General* Buakire, t¥e 8tli »tp4e*lier i9 IfroM The Secretary to the Hon’Ttle the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf* The Political Agent* Bahrain, The Political Agent, Muscat, The Political Agent, Kuwait H* 1* M's Consul, Kerman H. I* M’s Vice-Consul, Khorraas Memorandum * During the absence of the Hon’ble the Political Resident on tour at Bahrain all correspondence intended for the Town Office, Buahire, nay kindly be clearly endorsed to that effect on all cowers* By Older Secretary to tical Resident in the Persian Gulf*I u ARMY 8 NAVY STORES LIMITED (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND) TELEPHONE 2 5 0 0 1 f f 1 \ POST BOX N9 5 BOMBAY HEAD OFFICE: 105 VICTORIA STREET, LONDON BRANCHES: CALCUTTA &amp; NEW DELHI. TELEGRAMS 'ARMISTICe' 'IGth September, 1939. 2 4 SEP. 193u 1 The Assist Politioal Ag Bahrain. 1 as WHS WT, Sir, s.s. ,, Vita tt 14-9-1939 - 1 Ca^ y G artridges . In continuation of our letter of the 14th instant, we now enclose the following documents covering one box containing 50 Cartridges shipped by the s.s # M Vita rt receipt of which please aclmowledge. A. One Bill of Lading B. Invoice ITo.72. Thanking you, We are. Sir, Yours faithfully, ARMY &amp; NAVY STORES LIMIT2D, a ^er,Bombay Branch. incl: iOT/, Copy to:- The British Consulate General, Sushire, for information./4/$V No. Political Agency, Bahrain, the 1st October 1939 To The Director of Customs and Port Officer, Bahrain. Memorandum I forward herewith 'No objection certificate' No. 24 for 60 rounds of .380 ammunition for Colt Pocket Automatic Pistol, recently received for Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain. for Political Agent, BahrainARMY &amp; NAVY STORES LIMITED (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND) .. TELEPHONE 2 5 001 POST BOX N9 5 BOMBAY HEAD OFFICE : 105 VICTORIA STREET, LONDON BRANCHES: CALCUTTA dc NEW DELHI. TELEGRAMS 'ARMISTICE” Ref:0/827/S.&amp; A # The British Consulate General Bushire. 12th September,1930. Sir, We thank you for your letter Ho.1104/9/17 of the 3rd Instant. Arrangements are being made to ship 50 Cartridges .380 Bore by the first available steamer to The Assistant Political Agent, Political Agency, Bahrain, as Instructed by you. Thanking you. We are. Sir, Yours faithfully, ARMY &amp; NAVY ST0R3S LIMITED, Cy/O Manager,Bombay Branch. KNV. Copy to:- The Assistant Political Agent, Political Agency, Bahrain, for Information. -From To No. S,l*0/1-A # Political and Services Department, r ombay Castli&lt;' u Ti*t;b Septemberl 959. Sir Gilbert Wlle^K.C.I.i^,C.S.I., Chief Secretai^&gt;^&gt;/e Government of Bombay Political and Services Department. The Honourable the Political in the Persian Gulf, Bu Sir, I am directed to forward herewith, for your inform- tion a copy of a license No, , dated the ll^th September 1959 granted to Messrs. Army and Navy Stores, Limited of Bombay for the exoor^T to Bahrain of 50 rounds of .580 bore pistol cartridges consigned to the Assistant Political Agent, olitical Agency, Bahrain. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant. For Chief Secretary to the Government of Bombay, Political and Services Department. Copy, with a copy of its accompaniment, forward* ed with compliments to the Political Agent, Bahrain— - -CONDITIONS 1. This License is granted subject to all the provisions of the Indian Arms Act, 1878, and of the Indian Arms Hides, 1924. 2. The articles shall not he conveyed by any route other than that specified in column 7; and bulk shall not be broken, nor the consignment stopped, before the articles reach the place of destination. 3. An account of the contents of each package shall be legibly written thereon; and where the articles are conveyed by rail, each package shall be marked with the word or expression “ Arms,” “ Ammunition ” or “ Military Stores,” as the case may be, so as to be readily recognizable by the Railway authorities. No. of 193 POLITICAL AND REFORMS DEPARTMENT : Bombay Castle, 193 Copy forwarded to the for information. By order of the Governor in Council, for Chief Secretary to the Government of Bombay, Political and Reforms Department.12th instant, we now confirm having shipped ono box containing 50 Cartridges ,380 bore by the s.s. 'Vita' which sailed to-day and the relative Bill of Lading etc,, will be posted to you in due course. enclosed please find bill No,721-34 for F^.8/4/- being the cost of the Cartridges etc., and our shipping charges and licence fee etc., will be debited to your account in due course. Yours faithfully, .iincl: iaiv.'h ! I Form No. 24, (Copy of Bfll) ARMY &amp; NAVY STORES LIMITED. (INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND) BOMBAY. TELEPHONE 25001 TELEGRAMS 'ARMISTICE” Ma/c PersorFost Date H-9-39. Name The British Consulate General, No. 72134 Address Bushire. Dept. 8. Rs. a. P- 50 Cartridges .380 bore Pistol 8 Packing Box 4Please send to Kuwait by next mail my dhobi MAJKOO. - RESIDENT - Telegram From GTC Resident, Kuwait Political, Bahra Nil Dated and received the 10th October //-&gt; */// Telegram (U'v l| From / Resident, Kuwait. i To V &lt;1/0 Political, Bahrain. ) • o T/335- Dated 12th October 1939. Received 13th During my stay at Kuwait Slow Mailgwill call here weekly in both directions./ ■ r -,1 Dated the 21st October 1939. Your car has been landed here from 'City of Christchurch' under instructions received through Gray Mackenzie, Basra, from 'London principals'. Local agents have no further instructions. Please telegraph your wishes. - POLITICAL - 1From Political Agent, Kuwait. To Political Agent, Bahrain. No. 602 Dated a ;d received 16th October 1939. Grateful if you could send me for bookbinding purposes 50 sheets cardboard size 22 inches by 30 inches thickness 3/16 inch or thereabouts. Political - r£/}y~ $ S' | -*^6 3o i ft*-*£-**T, 1 ji ***&lt; aJ- 'I (6 h &gt;Telegram GTC From Political, Bahraii To Political, Kuwait No. 228 Dated the 22nd October 1939. Your telegram No. 602 of October 16th. Please take delivery s .s . ,f Barpeta M 35 sheets cardboard. No more available Bahrain. - POLITICAL -Political Agency, Bahrain, the 21st October 1939 To Messrs. Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co. Ltd., Bahrain. Dear Sirs, I forward herewith a package addressed to the Political Agent, Kuwait, and should be grateful if you would kindly forward it by hand of the Commander, S.S. 'Barpeta'. I am asking the Political Agent, Kuwait, to take delivery of it. for Political Agent, Bahrain.GTC Telegram From Resident, Kuwait C Political, Bahrain T/3T4 nd received 21st October 1939. Grateful if you will ask Mackenzie to send next mail 12 best whiskies 12 vintage champagne 12 non-vintage 6 gins (Coates if possible) 6 Italian vermouth 6 French vermouth 3 Bristol milk 6 rose lime juice cordial 1 bottle liqueur 1 brandy 6 best hocks. - PRIOR -FROM. POLI 'IC.A.L HESIDUTT, KU?/AIT. TO. POLITICAL AGENT, BAHRAIN. NO. T/390. RECEIVED. 22-10-39. Yoar telegram &lt; • Please have car shipped, to Bushire and insured journey. Is it damaged?No. 1869-16/32 The 26th October 1939 In your letter No. 1184-9/17E dated the 3rd September 1939 you asked the Army and Navy Stores, Bombay, to send me 60 rounds of pistol ammunition, and to send you the bill, fe have on our files a copy of a bill for its. 8/4/- and another . . A ■' invoice for 3s. 16/7/-. This letter includes &amp;. 8/4/- which is described as cost of the ammunition, and &amp;• 8/3/- on account of various charges incurred in the despatch of the ammunition. 2. If the 8s. 8/4/- sent by you for payment to me (see Buehire memorandum No. A.B. 870 dated the 11th October 1939) is on account of these cartridges, will you please send me a further as. 8/8/- to Include money order commission. 3. I enclose a copy of the Invoice referred to above in case you haven't received it. Yours sincerely, H.S.T. John, Esquire, I.C.S., British Consulate General, Bushire•No J7 8 ^-16/32 Political Agency, Bahrain, October 11, 1939 To Meeera. Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Company Limited, Bahrain. Dear Sira, Will you pleaae issue one deck ticket with food for Maiko dhobi available for journey to Kuwait by the next Up Slow Mail Steamer. 2 The cost will be paid on receipt of your* debit note Yours faithfully for Political Agent, Bahrain.^1. No. 1891-16/32. 6 L Political Agency, Bahrain, the 29th October 1939* (&amp;, To The Political Agent, Kuwait. Memorandum Reference ray telegram No. 228 dated the 22nd October 1939. 2. The sum of Hs. 22/4/-( 21/14/-+ -/6/- for coolie hire) paid by this Agency on your behalf may kindly be credited to this Agency Postage Account with you. for Political Agent, Bahrain. yi/A* iThe first line of this Telegram contains the following particulars in the order named:— Prefix Letters and Number of Message, Office of Origin, Number of Words, Date, Time handed in and Official instructions—if any.D*0*»0»Gy/668 • flee of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Camp, Kuwait. Dated the 6th November, 1939. Ify dear Weightman, I enclose for your information a card which 1 received from what is apparently a new organisation in Bahrain* I see that 'mess dress with decorations* is prescribed. You have presumably drawn their attention to the fact that no one is to prescribe A •mess dress* in Bahrain except yourself or, presumably, the Bahrain Government, if they should at any time give an official dinner at which evening dress was worn and at which tils Highness was present in person* H.Weightman Esquire, ICS*, Political Agent, Bahrain* Yours sincerely.Private Dated the 15th November 1939• 't I have had a letter frorn Colonel Prior in which he mentions that he received an invitation from the Bahrain Masonic Club to their dinner on the 2nd November 1939. On this invitation card 'mess dress with decorations' is pres cribed and he lias asked me to point out that no one in Balirain is able to prescribe mess dress v/ith decorations except mysslf or the Bahrain Government if they should at any time give an official dinner at which dress was worn and at which His Kignnesa was present in person* Yours sincerely f C.C.L. de Grenier, Esquire, Bahrain, i4 v / &amp; IMPERIAL AIRWAYS LTD. BAHRAIN ISLANDS PERSIAN GULF Codes : Bentley’s &amp; I.A.T.A. Telepk one : 43M Telegrams : Airways, Bakrain BAH/1/ 2971/P • 1 20th.F oy ember,1939 H. Weightman, Esq., Political Agent, Bahrein, Dear Mr. Weightman, I have your letter of yesterday and shall be pleased to look out for Daubeny. I have written to Basrah and told them that if he turns up there they are to tell him to come on here. Yours sincerely,From - Political Resident aboard FFARCHTJS. To - Political Agent, Bahrain. ?To. - 514 Dated and received 21st November 1939. dressed Bahrain and Muscat, you get any news of Daubney please inform programme and ask him to .join me at Bahrain or if possible at Dubai. RESIDENT - ^ &amp; i^vy ^ If U * f .TSl^GHAH. Code. From. To. No. l esr/' tched Received. G.T.C. Secret ry to the Political Resident, Bushire. Political Agent, B' hr- in. ’08. 21-11-39. Folio-sling telegram Jjas been received from Political Resident for Rooney begins, ''/hat action hes been taken on lists of drugs applied for b^ Sheikh of Kuwait? 2. If no application has been made to Government of India, copies of lists should be sent to them atonce with a request that they wil] kindly give facilities for export, ends. 'tt/xt/W ic^-r lw r 3. 1. H ^ u tp&gt;. Xlh P]The first line of this Telegram contains the following particulars in the order named:— Prefix Letters and Number of Message, Office of Origin, Number of Words, Date, Time handed in and Official instructions—if any. Printed in England. Sept. 1938. (12339 Pads.) CABLE AND WIRELESS LIMITED. (incorporated in England) - 168 . Clerk’s Time Cwc tu R EM 11 o'5 :e,ved y LC PRIOR AGENCY BAHREIN IK WHEEL BASE 120 INCHES MODEL 41 TOURING SEDAN 1939 CORF I ELD fjL ^ MARK YOUR REPLY Jm/ietuaC NO ENQUIRY RESPECTING THIS TELEGRAM CAN BE ATTENDED TO WITHOUT PRODUCTION OF THIS COPY.HEAD OFFICE: 122, LEADENHAUU STREET, LON DON E.C. 3. telegraphic address: •* GRAY ” CODES USED: BENTLEY'S COMPLETE PHRASE BENTLEY'S SECOND PHRASE CODE Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co. ltd. (incorporated IN ENGLAND,) BRANCHES; BUSREH. AMARAH. KUT. KHORAMSHAHR. AHWAZ (for BANDAR.SH AHPOUR.) BUSHIRE. BUNDER-ABBAS. LINOAH. BAHREIN. KOWEIT. DUBAI. SHARJAH. MUSCAT. IN REPLY PLEASE QUOTE No U- X s Agency, Bahrain. Dear Sir, 19 39 • 10 packages P.Effects of Colonel prior shipped per s.s.Bamora v.281 to Koweit. Me send you herewith the relative B/lading Nos.1/2 covering the above receipt of which please acknowledge# Encloj2 CCB. Yours faithfully.GOVERNMENT OF INDIA, Dkpabiment, EXPRESS LETTE [N. B, —This is an ORIGINAL MESSAGE, sent by post to save telegraphic expense and undue use of the wires, bat intended to be treated, on receipt, with the same expedition as if it had been telegraphed. To save time and formalities it is worded and signed as if it had been so despatched,] From Britconsul, Buahire. To Political Agent Political Agent ,p Political Agent No. ''Cv'T -13/177. Dated the 26th November 1933 . Reference method of cramponing end sealing of confi dential mail. 2. In future the following procedure should be adopted*- (a) Inner coTers should be fastened with crampons and sealed (but not over crampons) and (b) Outer corers should not be cramponed but merely ‘ sealed. v . a ®&gt; Kuwait. Bahrain. Muscat. (Sd.) C.G.PRIOR Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. ATT.ES 1 Secretary to the^Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. s. 6. MFP—1407 S&amp;P-(M-2339)—25-5-37—200,000.No j . Political Agency, Bahrain, the 19th December 1939 To:- f Messrs Or y Mackenzie &amp; Co Limited, Bahrain. Dear Sirs, T send herewith a parcel containing tennis balls and golf balls addre^s^d to the Honourable Lt.-Colonel C.O.Prior, C.I.E,, H.B.M's Cpnsul-General, Bushire, and should be glad if you could send it on by the next dae* up mail* Please send me the shipping documents as soon as possible. Yours faithfully, \ for Political Agent, Bahrain.7/ ® Telegram From To N 0 . GTC Political, Bahrain Britconsul, Bushire. 304 Dated 23rd December 1939. hj^ / RANGE requests payment of his pay up to date of handing over and advance of cne month's pay and under C.A.C.159 travelling allowance hs. 1,200/-^. Please telegraph sanction and total amount payable. He sails for India on 31st. - POLITICAL -TELEGRAM Code, From. To, No. Des pa tched Received. G.T.C. Political Resident, Bushire. Political Agent, Bahralm. 524. 23-12-39. IMMIDIATE. Kindly wifce immidiately time and date of slow mai^s expected arrival Bushire.TELEGRAM Code. From. To. No. Despatched Iramidiate. arrive 11 i G.T.C. Political Agent, HftXKXiQf.Bahrain. Political Resident, Bushire. 305. 23-12-39. Your telegram 524. Slow mail expected ,.M. 24th December.D. 0. 1 IP 1 ' 79 18th Decem'oer 1939, During a recent storm a number of telephone poles, bearing our private wire between the town office and Sabzabad, were blown down and whilst the wire lay exposed on the ground some 1,300 yards of it were stolen. 2. As we have no more wire in stock we have had to improvise a temporary expedient to enable us to carry on until such a time as we can replace that stolen. As it would be much quicker for us to buy it from Bahrain / I should be very grateful if you would let us know by telegram whether there is any available and if so whether there would be any objection to our buying it. The details of the wire are as follows:-- No.14 S.tf.G. Galvanized iron wire 65 lbs. The cost together with any other incidental charges could be debited to our unofficial account with your Agency. H. 'Veightman, Esq., I.C.S., Political Agent, Bahrain.Ho.G/899 of 1939. , Office of the Political Resident in the Persian ^ulf. Cagap, Kuwait. Dated the 16th December, 1939 To Copy to: e Political Agent, Bahrain • The Political Agent, Kuwait • Memorandum• Hamid bin Malik, Arab coffee man employed by the Residency, has been instructed to report to you with this memorandum. 2. Unless orders are received to the contrary, he should be sent to Kuwait by the slow mail leaving Bahrain on or about 13th January 1940, cost of passage with food being debited to the Residency. 3. Hamid bin Malik has been paid up to the end of December, but may be granted an advance up to Es.3C/- on leaving for Kuwait. Sd- C.G.Prior. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf ATTESTED. for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. CLjl t ' Ci-o7 &amp; Telegram - GTC - Political, Bahrain To - Britconsul, Bushire No. - 310 Dated 27th December 1939. Your demi-official letter No. 1666. No galvanised iron wire available but could send 15oo yards No. 12 copper wire used for Bahrain telephones. Approximate cost Rs. 150/-. - POLITICAL -n y G.T.C. Britconsul, Bushire. Political Agent, Bahrain. P Telegram From To No.1084. Dated and received the 25th December 1939. Balam. Your telegram 304. Please pay Ranee Rupees 2338 and annas 11 I am sending you supply bill for this amount. - Political 91 -Colonel Prior would be very if you could have photographs taken of the Bahrain Agency drawing-room furniture which was purchased by him. Would you kindly send me the photographs and the photographer^ bills. Colonel Prior hopes to get the local carpenter to make some furniture for the Residency similar to that in Bahrain, CLa 1^ H.Weightman, Esquire, I.C.S Political Agent, Bahrain. W'**’ 9 - ■) /'*■ From Political Resident, Bushire. To Political Agent, Bahrain. No. 240 Dated and received 30th December 1939,No. 10-16/32. Political Agency, ' q Bahrain, the 3rd January 1940 To The State Engineer, Bahrain Government, Bahrain* ? Vmorqnd\ im Reference your telephone conversation with the Assistant Political Agent on the 27th December 1939. 2. Will yv u please send me 1500 yards of No. 12 copper wire securely packed for despatch to the Hon'ble th&lt; Political Resident in the Persian Gulf at Bushire. for Political Agent, Bahrain.cs ^pcJ! ^SU-.L^SDI THE BAHRAIN GOVERNMENT ELECTRIC SUPPLY DEPT N0.PA/II/58 H.B.M’s Political Agent, BAHRAIN. Memorandum:- Reference your 3rd January,1939. Bahrain. 22nd Dilquada,1358 Dated: 1 3rd January, 1940 memorandum No.10-16/32 of -l am sending herewith 150 lbs. (equivalent 5w/ PP ^ Xlma ? ely I , 500 y ards &gt; of No.12 H.D.copper wiri s /g., securely packed as requested. State Engineer, Government of Bahrain.Guc&amp; Cd&amp;U.. To The .oritisn Consulate-General, Bushire, the 30th December, 1939. Memorandum . In continuation of my telegram No.1084, dated j the 23rd December, 1939, I enclose, herewith, two Supply Bills for Rs 2338/- and postage stamps of the value of l annas eleven representing the amount paid oy you to Lieut. \ H.D.H.,Ranee. Please acknowledge receipt. / A 3* /&lt; h b Treasury Officer, Bushire. yyv..No. 30-16/32. Political Agency, Bahrain, the 6th January 1940. To The Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. I acknowledge, with thanks, receipt of a Supply Bill for as. 2338/- and postage stamps of the halue of annas eleven sent with your memorandum No. 1093-3/8 dated the 30tfc December 1939. for Political Agent, Bahrain. &lt;- A* t tG.T.C. Telegram From To No.6. Political Resident, at Bushire. Political Agent, Bahrain. Dated and received the 3rd January 1940. jrateful if you would ask Kespers to send me 24 Noilly Prat French Vermouth by the next mail. ^«a-»vr A. /■ ^ / ' t+ff/40 Is* / l j &lt;?] l*. t. &lt;&lt;No: /*/ . Poiiticpl Agency, Prhrein, the 4th Jnnu r ry 1940. To:- Messrs Gray Mackenzie &amp; Co Limited, Bahrain. Dear Sirs, Will you please send 24 bottles of Noilly Prat French Vermouth to the Honourable Lt.-Colonel C.G.Prior, C.I.E., Pis Britannic Majesty’s Consul- General at Bushire, by the next up Slow Mail. Yours faithfully, for Political Agent, Bahrain. /No. 17 15-16/32. Political Agency, Bahrain, the 4th January 1940. To Messrs. Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co. Ltd., Bahrain. Dear Sirs, I send herewith one bundle of copper wire for despatch,by the up slow mail due here on or about the 6th instant, to the Hon’ble Lieut.-Colonel C.G. Prior, CIIC His Britannic Majesty’s Consul General, Bushire. y 2. Please send the shipping documents to me as soon as possible. Yours faithfully, p/e for Political Agent, Bahrain.HEAD OFFICE: 122, LEADENHALL STREET, LONDON E.C. 3, TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS; “GRAY” CODES used: BENTLEY'S COMPLETE PHRASE BENTLEY'S SECOND PHRASE CODE Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co. ltd. (incorporated in enslano,) BRANCHES: BUSREH. AM ARAH. KUT. KHORAMSHAHR. AHWAZ (FOR BAN OAR.SHAH POUR.) BUSHIRE. BUNDER-ABBAS. LINGAH. BAHREIN. KOWEIT. DUBAI. SHARJAH. MUSCAT. IN REPLY PLEASE QUOTE No T */ ' Bahrain D/4th January , 19 4Q The Political Agent, Bahrain• Dear Sir, British consul Bush ire • 1 Bdle copper Wire * Befrenc? your letter No.19-16/32 of even date we have to advise you that the above package we are arranging to ship per the s.s.Barala v.316 sailing hence on or about 6th instant. Attached please find the relative D/Latter no.1 to enable you go get the delivery of the package at that end* Enel;1. yours faithfully For GRAY, MACKENZIE X 144. CCB. Lj- h20-16/32 Political Agency, Bahrain, tho 6th January 1940. St (g) To The Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire. Memorandum Please refer to your telegram No. 240 dated the 30th December 1939. 2. I enclose herewith D/Letter No. 1 dated the 4th January 1940 in respect of one bundle copper wire shipped to you per S.S. 'Barala' which id due to sail from Bahrain to-day. / for Political Agent, BahrainGray, Mackenzie &amp; Co. Ltd. /ooj HEAD OFFICE: 122, LEADENHALL STREET, CONDON E.C. 3. TELEOPAPHIC ADDRESS: “GRAY” CODES used: BENTLEY'S COMPLETE PHRASE BENTLEY'S SECOND PHRASE CODE (incorporated IN ENSLANO.) BRANCHES: BUSREH. AMARAH. KUT. KHORAMSHAHR. AHWAZ (FOR BANDAR-SHAH POUR.) BUSHIRE BUNDER-ABBAS. L.INGAH. BAHREIN. KOWEIT. DUBAI. SHARJAH. MUSCAT. IN REPLY PLEASE QUOTE L/19. No . c il.k. Bahrein, 7th • i ry t 19 39. Ku 5M I R E . ■ ©. The Political ^gant, Dear Sir, 'vith reference to your letter Fo.14 of the 4th instant, in connection with shipment of two cases of Trench Vermouth to 3u hire for Lt./Colonel f.C.Prior, v;e have to advise that as our stock is very limited at present, only one case has been shipped. Yours faithfully, For GEAT, MACKENZIE &amp; Co.. Lt» Copy sent to P.R. under P.L.No. 59 of 10-1-1940.From The Assistant Engineer, Ind. Persian Gulf Sub-Divn*, Bushire. The Political Agent, Bahrain* I have the honour to inform you that one roll of copper wire-gauze is urgently required for the Hon’ble the Political Residents office and drawing room* I shall feel so grateful, if you would kindly get one from the Oil Company and Jr send down to the Consul General, Bushire* I have placed an order for the gauze from England, but it will take 2 to 3 months to receive the consignment* I have the honour to be, 0 Sir, Your most obedient servant, MX *No.-16/32 Political Agency, Bahrain, January 1^), 1940. To Messrs. Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Company Limited Bahrain. Dear Sirs, Would you kindly issue one deck ticket, with food, for Hamid bin Malik available for journey to Kuwait by the slow mail leaving Bahrain on or about 13th January 1940. 2. The cost will be paid on receipt of your debit note Yours faithfully, for Political Agent, BahrainThe 10th January 1940 T)«0*Ho* b 0 -16/32. Please refer to your demi-official letter dated the 23rd December 1939 to Mr. Vfeightman. 2. I forward herewith as desired two large-size photographs of the Agency drawing-room furniture. The photographer’s bill is also enclosed. Yours sincerely R.G. Daubeny, Esquire, Under Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf,Bushire.No. ^ -16/32 Political Agency f Bahrain, the _10th January 1940 I//C To The Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited, Bahrain. Dear Sir, Could you kindly supply, on payment, one roll of copper wire-gauze which is urgently required for the Hon*ble the Political Resident’s office at Bushire. Yours faithfully, for Political Agent, Bahrain1 No. 16/32 Political Agency, Bahrain, the 13th January 1940 To Messrs, Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co. Ltd., Bahrain. Dear Sirs I forward herewith a bundle containing one roll of copper wire gauze addressed to His Britannic Majesty^ Consul General, Bushire for despatch by this week's up slow mail. 'Vill you please send me the necessary shipping documents as soon as possible. Yours faithfully for Political Agent, Bahraini No. 77-16/32. Political Agency, Bahrain, the 13th January 1940 * To The Assistant Engineer, Independent Persian Gulf Sub-Division, Bushire• /■&gt; Memorandum Please refer to your letter No. 1/910 dated the 6th January 1940. 2. One bundle containing a roll of copper wire gauze is being sent by this week*a up slow mail addressed to His Britannic Majesty’s Consul General, Bushire. for Political Agent, Bahrain. ^ %G.T.C. Political Resident, Bushire Political Pgent, p ahrain- 36. 13th January 1940. Please telegraph immediate in due course date and time of arrival Pushire of BAMORA. - ^ritconsul - According to the mail notice received from Gray Mackenzie the 'Pamora” is due in Bahrain at midnight tomorrow, May ask G.M to let us know this as soon as they find out * | 'iM'l HO ^ A j /✓VU- 13 Z 1 ZJ ^ ^ //URGENT. Political /gency, Bahrain, the 14th January 1940. No: $$ . f&amp;/3z ^ , Political Agency, - ; ^ 4- 1/4-W, T *-) tm i r-) 10/10 To:- Messrs Gray Mackenzie &amp; Co Limited, Bahrain. Dear Sirs, V/ould you kindly let me know, for the information of the Honourable the Political Resident, immediately,you can ascertain it, the date and time of the arrival of S.3 Baraora at Bushire. Yours faithfully, / / /? r for Political /gent, Bahrain.a ? Telegram:- G.T.C. From:- Political /gent, p ehrain. To:- Political Resident, P ushire. No:- 13. Dated:- 15th January 1940. Immediate. Your telegrrm 36. BAMORA arrives p ushire January 16th 14.00 Hours. PoliticalGray, Mackenzie &amp; Co. Ltd (INCORPORATED in ENGLAND) BRANCHES: HEAD OFFICE: 122. LEADEN HALL STREET, LONDON,E.C. 3. tele graphic address; GRAY. CODES USED: BENTLEY'S COMPLETE PHRASE. BENTLEY’S SECOND PHRASE CODE. BUS R E H. AM AR AH. KUT. KHORAMSHAHR AHWAZ (for BANDAR-SHAH POUR) BUSHIRE. BUNDER-ABBAS. LI NG AH. BAH REIN. KOWEIT. DUBAI. SHARJAH. MUSCAT. IN REPLY PLEASE QUOTE 1/ A/ No. Bahrain D/14th January, 19£0. The Political Agent, Bahrain. Dear Sir, Address 1 Bdle Copper wire Gauze* » ^ % Reference your letter No.75-16/32 of 13th instant we have to inform you that we are arranging to ship the above package per the s.s.Bamora v.283 to Bushire,and send you herewith the relative D/Letter No.2 which may be forwarded to the consignee. Please acknowlwdge receipt. Your sfaithfully. Enclos; D/Letter no .2 La* t) CCB. &amp;16/32. The Political Agent, Bahrain, presents his compliments to The Assistant Engineer Independant Persian Gulf Sub-Diwision, Bushire and has the honour to send him a copy of the undermentioned document (s) The Agency, |&gt; BAHRAIN, Persian Gulf Dated_L5th January 1940. Reference to previous correspondence; Agency letter No:77-16/32 dated the 13th January 1940. Description of Enclosure. Name and Date. Subject. Delivery letter No:2 dated the 14th January 1940 in respect of one roll copper wire gau^e despatched by S.S BAMORA. %Camp, Kuwait. ted the 23rd January 1940. L Many thanks for your demi-official letter No.60-16/32 dated the lOth January 1940 and the photographs. The photographs are excellent. ' % '+ . * 2. I enclose a cheque No. ' lTbU4 A. 1 |. 4-0 - i - / for fc.19/- in payment of the* Bahrain Art Studio’s bill. J, i. R.I.Hallows» -Esquire, Assistant Political Agent, Behrain.No.C/149 of 1940 ! v (v 5 Office of the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Camp BAHRAIN. Dated the 23rd February 1^40. u' * The Political Agent, Bahrain. Memorandum. On my departure for Kuwait I am leaving behind at your disposal until I next require him, Hamad bin Malik Omani, Residency coffee man. He could perhaps be used by the Publicity Officer after the latter’s arrival. The coffee man’s pay of Rs.35/- per month may be debited to the Residency. Sd. C.G.Prior. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. ‘''’V c 11 *i&gt; ATTESTED — for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. (7b-^ &lt; j-Ci . J/vrv /'&lt;-w /-rr k~~ A .. # O/ m a j uA-J’ / ^ •Ls&gt; 1 1 • r- t&lt;- n, (No.470 Political Agency, Bahrain. 12th March, 1240 To The Secretory to the Bon 1 Me the Politicnl Heisdent in the Persian &lt;lulf, 3Usljirg. Memomndum. Among the last bundle of covers received for posting by air mai?. were the following:- 1. ''he Secretary* &lt;?' Treasure, Imperial Bank of India, v ew helhi 2. The Secretary &lt;S- Treasurer, Reserve Bank of India, Karachi 3. The Secretary o 'rea surer, Reserve B^nk of India, Bombay 4. Lloyds Bar^k limited, New ^elhi - v « ' 'Ok:A 5* The Accountant General, Central Revenues, New ^elhi - 2 covers* - 2 covers. - 2 covers. - 3 covers. - 4 covers. It has occured to me that there would be a saving in envelopes as well as in postage and registration fees if one cover was ussd for all letters to one addressee instead of a separate cover fen each letter* for Political Agent, Bahrain.© 26th March 1940 ^ '7 ^ f /( s UUL ) Will you please refer to your demi- official letter No.60-16/32 dated the 10 th January 1940. 2. Gould you send me the measurements of the writing table, the settee and the two different kinds of chairs. With the aid of these and the photographs it is hoped that the carpenter will be able to produce exact imitations. R.I.Hallows, Esquire, Assistant Political j Bahrain. nc ( lwIa ^7 Dated the 29th March 1940. Would you ask Mr.V/eightman if he would be kind enough to let one of the tables in the Agency drawing room be photographed, and could you send me the print ? The table to which I refer is a low one which I believe is Mr. * • Weightman’s personal property and usually stands in front of the sofa nearest the door. Colonel Prior admired it when he was in Bahrain and wishes to have a similar one made for Bushire. R.I.Hallows, ifis^uire, Assistant Political F Bahrain• **3* ^ t P.S. I wonder if the photographer LMsu could be persuaded to charge rather j/y- less. Rs.6/- for a print seems i exhorbitant.✓ No .682-16/32 Political Agency, Bahrain. £pril| 1940. To The Secretary to the ^on’Me tie Political Resident in the Persian Sulf Ruahl re. ? Memorandum . * The late Sir Trenchard Fowl© left thirteen ru^s with the Agency Head C?verk for sale in Bahrain. Of these seven have been sold for S3.65/- as noted on the list enclosed, and there is little likelihood of the iHimainin^ six bein^ sold at t&gt; e price fixed by the late Sir Trendsrd* 2. I should be glad if you would let ne know uhat should be dene with the regaining rugs and the £ts.t&gt;b/— • for Political Agent, Bahrain.Telegram GTC. From Britconsul, Bushire. To Political, Bahrain. No .A142 Dated 10th April, 1S40. c &lt; # • Please telegraph rates of x^ay offered by Bahrain Petroleum Company for T'unshis of standard suitable for employment in our vernacular cadre.GTC. Telegram From Britconsul, Bushire. To Political, Bahrain. No. Nil Da.ted 3rd April, 1940. Grateful if you could have two bottles of Yatsons mulsified shampoo sent me by next mail (post) ^U. Lc. % (rvCOc, . aNo .699-16/32 Political Agencji, Bahrein. 11th April, 1940 72X o The Chief Local lopT'o^^ntative, ' he Bahrain -'etroleum Company Llfiiited, Bahrain* j % 'near Sir, ould you be so good as to let me know the pay and allowances offered by the Bahrain Petroleum Company to Arab clerks or interpreters whose education would e sufficient for t'&gt;era to be employed as interpreters at this Agency* for Political agent, Bahrain. b s/cTe legrn.m GTC. From ' Political, Bahrain. To Britconsul, Bashire. No.109 Dated 14th A.pril, 1G40. Your telegram N0.A142 dated 10th April. Hate of pay offered by Bahrain Petroleum Company is Rs.5/- per day. No allowances.Telegram GTC rom To Britconsul, Bushmre Political , Bahrain. No. A149 Dated the 13th April, 1340. Grateful if you can purchase and send by Thomas six reearns typewriting paper and debit our account with you. / /l . H. 0 '//6 (^) No. 2/ 3 1 3 . Bushire, 20th April, 1940 From The Assistant Engineer, ina. Persian Gulf Sub-Division, Bushire• To Tne Political Agent, Banrain Sir, I nave the honour to request that two glass -V . 1 '' pans each mea suring two feet long, one and half feet wide and one quarter inch thick with rounded edges may very kindly oe purchased at Banrain and handed over to the Chief Officer of the next Up Slow nail B. I. Steamer v/ith a request to be handed over at Bushire to the Residency farash who goes on the board the steamers every week. The glass pans in question are urgently required oy the Secretary to the Hon f ble the Political Resident in the Persian ouif. The cost may be debited to this Residency - accounts v/ith you as usual. I have the honour to be Sir, Your most obedient servantI enclose a list of automobile lubricants etc., and I should be grateful if you could place an order for them with a firm in Bahrain, .'/ill you Kindly tell the firm that tne consignment must be landed from the snip at Bushire before the 2Sth lay 1940 otherwise delivery will not be accepted. The cost of these articles should be 'f debited to lol.Prior.THE RESIDENCY, BUSHIRp, the 27th April iy40. / ti Co&amp;onel Prior would be grateful if you would kindly enquire whether Fazl Durzi would come over to Bushire for a month| with or without an assistant| to work for him. If he is prepared to come would you let me know what terms he would accept* R*I.Hallows, ] Assistani BAffiNo.9I£-16/32 Poii'uio&amp;I Agency| Baiu\iin. 8Ui 1940* To Mr. Klialil bln Ebrahim Kanoo, Bahrain . if. ^ /’ct-jf'ff - olr, Will you oloa^e supply the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Qulf, with the automobile lubricants etc. given in the list enclosed# 2 . The consignment should be addressed to H British Consulate General, Buahire,' and must roach dushir e before 28th Mav 1940. otherwise dellvei-y will not be accepted * 3 . rioase lot me know at once if you are unable to supply auy of these items# Yours faithfully, for Political Agent, Bahrain# 'n« y D.3.M0. Political Agency, Pahrein the -th May 1 40. Would you please refer to your D.O.daten the l:7th April, I04y regard ng Fazal ^^ohammad Darzi? 2. Fazal Mohammed is prepared to come to Bush re for a month preferably w.th an assistant. He would not-be able to leave Bahrain before the end of this month. Col. Prior may think suitable but suggested Rs.5/- per day, with return passage with food to Bushire and similar terms for an assistant if he brought one. He would also require to be compensated for any customs duty paid on his sewing machine and baggage. 4. I do not know whether it is possible for you to arrange for him to land w thout proper travel documents but if not it will, of course, take some t me to obtain for him a fresh passport with an Iranian visa. He states that he is prepared to accept any terms which Yours sincerely, British Consulate-General, Bushire.Tele c 'ra:a From To No. nil Britconsu^-, Bushire. Political, T 3ah r a i n. Bat ‘d 30th April, 1940. Following for IIALLG'/S ,r &lt;roatftil if you Jould send me by the next mail debiting unofficial account black one pair nen*s/shoes, one pair men’s black evening shoes both sized 9. *■D.0.N©.934~i6/32 Bated the 11th ^y f 1940 • Pleesc refer to your demi-official of Uie 29th April i'egurdlng automobile lubricants etc. for Colonel Prior# to you by Khalil Kanoo* Kobilgre^se No #4 ie being supplied to you in cne lb tini as 7 Iba tins .vere not proourablo 24 tine Farrcl body polish 6 tine limoniz cleaner 6 tins Simonis wax 42 tinn Ti robilgreaBe No.4 24 gallons ’ obiloil 'A* 12 gallons ItoMloil HGL for cleaning mudguards but I will make further of forts# Bahrain and the Agent Khalil Kanoo dees net intend to replenish his supply after his present stocks are exhausted# a# G. Barbery, Lsquire, Under hecret&amp;ry to the Uorfble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, mah&amp;Zejt 2 • The following were available and are being shipped I have so far been unable to find any brushes suitable .Ccbiloil oils and. greases ar&lt;- very seldom used inNo♦935-16-32 Political Agency f Bahrain# 11th Kay y 1940• To Mr. Khalil bin ^rahim Kanoo, ^ah r alTi * Dear Sir, Flease refer to your latter Uo.84/L dated the 8 th jay, 1340# 2. The available items should be supplied at an very ctrly date# Wobiloll grease No#4 may be supplied in one lb tins# 3. Your bill will be paid by me# Yours faithfully f for Political Agont, Bahrain#ifs, .V, ^ A ~ N +2&lt;*/. -'^S^ r': i s s 4 ■^s c^ rjt * •S' V i ■« D.0.NO.312-S The Residency, Bushire, the 17th May 1940 isjj^ 'zf^ uc Will you please refer to your demi-official v —v ^ Jl ll — iMetter No.923 dated the 9th May 1940. 2. It would perhaps be more convenient if the Darzi postponed his visit until the Autumn. Colonel Prior would be grateful however if you would complete the necessary formalities and obtain travel documents for them so that they will be able to arrive in Bushire during October -N£ : 5 1940. 3. It will be possible to hire a sewing machine locally and this will dispense with the question of Customs charges if the Darzi imports his own *4? machine. H. Weightman, Esquire, I.C*S. Political Agent, Bahrain.Telegram From To GTC Political, Britconsul No. 150 Dated 25th May, 1940. Bahrain. Bushire• Following tax from Hallows for Latimer Parcel for you on “BA.RA.IA'*.D.O. Ho16/32 Hated 13th June* 1940• Please refer to your demi-official Ho.312-3 dated the 17th I 'ey 1940. kf fron Ffezal Ttoharanad and hiG aGsiGt^nt ^rnsan, th^ir old yaaeports being sndors3&lt;1 for Bahrain. given visas for Iran and t.nia may cause aona di.i'iculty in the case of :n-&gt; v i's r riad and hia assistant# This difficulty could tail ora a^d the second have been .^i^iea but left blank for you to fin in «*.«« you think fit# 7hen the paaeporta are ready they o.n be forwarded to the Consul at Bagdad /#ho should be instructed to return then to £;&lt;v • returned to tier- so tJvit the fresh paesoorte ftiay remain v/ithout a Bahrain endorsanent and liable to be used again for Iran if required. If this is rgroed to, lazal Mohammed^ expired passport No*234 may be renewed for a period of five yeara and returned. aptain A. C. Ct?nart f I.A.^ Secratsry to the lon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bushire• 2. I enclnfu herewith applications for fresh passports T understand thnt as a yener-:.“ rule taiil^rs are not probably bn obviated v%y snoviny 7 szr 1 ''oh^inrr.ed and his assistant an psrsonrl ^orw-ts ir. their visa applications or by a letter from you * Vitkng twt both non are being ^nnloyed as private servants for work at the Residency. I am therefore forwaj^ding two lots oi visa applications each for the : &gt;&lt;r*i and his assistant, ihe first 4 ahow them as A Jiy-'nlrn vis? r ore ynnerrlly valid for cue month only. ^he tailors request that their old passports may be— No•1174-16/32 Political Agency, f/« liahrain. 18th June, 1940. To n he Secretary to the Hcn’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Pushire • ' c no ran darn . ith reference to :ny Memorandum No .682-16/32 dated the 8th April 1940, I shou d be grateful for instructions regarding the disposal of t he late Sir Trenchard Fowle's rugs and the hs«65/-.Tne Political Agent, Dated the 16th July 1940. {9 it Bahrain. memorandum Reference your memorandum No.1174-16/32 dated the 18th June 1940. 2. Me have written to Lady Fowle asking her what should fce done with the rugs and with the sum of Ps. 65/-. 7/e will communicate her reply to you as soon as it is received. By order,at No.1399-16/32 Political Agency| Bahrain# 23rd ^uly, 1940. To Messrs. Gray Mackenzie &amp; Co. f Ltd. f Bahrain. Dear Sirs, Would you please ship the steel trunk sent herewith to Mr. R.G. Dsubeny C/0 Political Agent, Kuwait, by S.S. n BANKURA n due here tomorrow morning. The bill for freight etc. may please be sent to me. 2. I should be grateful if you would arrange to have the trunk insured against loss or damage. Yours faithfully, /?ybLc Captain for Political Agent, Bahrain.D.O. So.1400-16/32 uated the 23r&lt;3 July 1940. Please refer to your letter of 17th July to Weightman* 2* The steel trunk received for you from Kossrs. Angel &amp; Son has been shipped to Kuwait by this mil through Messrs* Gray &gt;4ackenzie &amp; Co*, Ltd*,* 3* The other three parcels received from Captain Hickinbotham, Morris Angel &amp; son and Mrs* C.C. Daubeny have been sent to Kuwait by post today* Yours sincerely* % K* G. Daubany, Esquire, c/o The Political Agenty, Kuwait.No. V / 13/1U4 of iy40. T. he Hon ble the Political Resident in the Persian Griilf presents his com pliments to The Political A&amp;ent, and has the honour to transmit to him a copy of the Bud^nnentinned docu ment (s). w ith the request that the seeds retained until they can be collected by the x J olitical Resident on tour# British Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. Dated.. 2 . 0 }}}.. J . u ^ &gt; 194c • Reference to previous correspondence :No. /13/1C4 of 1940. The 20th July,1940« To ilesars: Pestonjee P.Pocha k Sons, Post Box No.55, POONA , India. Dear Sirs, / / Please forward by the first sea mail to The Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, c/o The Political .gent, BAHRAIN, the flower seeds mentioned in the attached list. Your charges will be met on receipt of your invoice. ^* u ^ ie consignment should be accompanied by two copies oi the dealth Certificates in respect of the seeds, which should also be addressed to Bahrain. 5 * in no circumstances ehould the seeds be posted to Buanire. Yours faithfully, for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.Telegram From To No .A/267 GTC. Britconsul, Bushlre. Political, Bahrain. Dated 24th July, 1940. c{V ' Your telegram 109 of April 14th. Please telegraph whether any concessions such as Provident Fund, Bonus or Gratuity is offered to such employees.Political Agency, Bahrain. 25th 1940. No.1419-16/32 4^ fnn~ To -he Chief Local Representative f The n ahrain Petroleum Company Limited, jahraln. 3 «ir Sir, jP , (f U Flaase refer to ay letter No.699-16/32 dated tne lltl» April 1940, regarding the emoluments of Arab clerks, the reply to which was received by telephone. 2 * 'ill you please let me know if any I rovident Fum, Bonus or Gratuity is offered to such employee a/ Yours faithfully, for* Captain, Political Agent, Bahrain.Awali: Bahrein Island, Persian Gulf, July 28, 1940* 3 * . Referring to your letter No. 1419-16/32 dated July 25, 1940 regarding emoluments of Arab Clerks, we would advise that at the present time we have no Provident Fund, Bonus or Gratuity schemes in force for such employees. Yours very truly, R.A. KENNEDY Chief Lacal Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LTD:Telegram GTC. From Political, Bahrain. To Britconsul, Bushire. Mo.213 Dated 31st July, 1940. Your A/267 of July 24th. No Provident Fund, Bonus or Gratuity schemes for such employees.No.1437 Political Agency f Bahrain# -5th August 1940# To 11 * » » • llic Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf* Bush ire * Memor'ivadun « Your Printed Letter No •949-28/37 dfited the 23rd July 1940 addressed to the Accountant General* Central Revenues, New Delhi, has been sent to this office duly entered in the enclosed flay Bill* 2* Tould you please let ne know whether you wish me to forward it to the Accountant General, Central Revenues or whether this copy is meant for my files? Captain, for Political Agent, Bahrain*In their letter No. 887 of the 13th July last Bushire asked us to obtain Iranian visas for Ramzan and Fazal Mohammed, two tailors whom they propose to employ at the Consulate General and post their passports direct to you. We have accordingly obtained the visas and enclose the passports herev/ith. No charges were incurred. Kindly acknowledge receipt. % Yours ever,No* 1560-16/32 Political Agency, Bahrain* 19th August 1940. 1 Vvr fv* honour to acknowledge with thanks the rocelnt of the passports forwarded vjith your letter No*1726 dat-^d the 10th August 194.0. I have the honour to be, Sir, Your most obedient servant. /■ for Politico 1 A gent, k Captain, Bahrain* His Majesty 1 • Consul, British Consulate,Telegram GTC. From Colonel Prior, Shiraz. To Political, Bahrain. No .T/288 Dated 20th August 1940. Would there be any demand in Bahrain for my 8 cylinder 1939 Packard saloon? It has Philco radio special head and fog lights run 9,000 miles excellent condition. If oil Company interested would they pay dollars or rupees?Telegram From To No.239 GTC. Captain NOTES, Bahrain. Colonel PRIOR, Shiraz. Dated 24th August 1940. Your telegram 288 August 20th. Negative result so far, Companies prefering Fords. Am still trying CA30C. 2. Can you give me indication of (a) price ultimately acceptab:e and (b) price to be asked. That is size of tyres? Is car American or Canadian made?.No, /()kk. - at 1940 K ^ w -i* V £ - Z /■jT f/^Tj Pi ■v Dated the 21at To _ ^2 The Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain, MEMORANDUM Would you kindly arrange to forward one bag of washing soda and debit the cost to this Residency^ un official account with the Agency, 2, The bag should be addressed to:- \ The Hon’ble Mr. C.G. Prior, C.I.E., H.B.M’s Consul-General, Bushire. 3. Please send the bill or invoice in duplicate for customs purposes. By order, Secretary to‘'the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. 3 IPolitical Agency, Bahrain August 26th, l^^O. To, Messrs Gray Mackenzie &amp; Co# ktu., Bahrain. Dear 3ir, I am forwarding herewith one bag washing soda and request that this may be shipped to:- The Hon’ble Mr. C.G.Prior, C.I.E., K.B.M* s Consul-General, Bushire, by S.S.Warina due here tomorrow the 27th August 1940. Freight etc will be paid by this office. ' Yours faithfully, » for Political Agent, BahrainNo . I (bl 16/32 Political Agency, Bahrain August 26th, 1940. To, The Secretary to the Hon'ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Bus hire. Liemoranaum. f) | A '' Reference your memorandum No.1066 dated the 21st August 1940. 2. One bag washing soda is being shipped to you by S.S.Marina due here on or about August 27th, 19^0. The invoice in duplicate is enclosed. Captain,03 Telegram From To G.T.C. Political Resident, Camp Shiraz Political Agent, Bahrain. No. T/312 Dated 26th August, 1940. . Z* / ^ 3- Your telegram 239 of August 24th. -y Please cancel my telegram NO.T288 of August 20th. -Prior-No.//^ -13/257. The Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf presents his compliments to The Political Agent, ^ Bahrain, v ■ and is directed to transmit to him a copy of the undermentioned documents. for information and necessary action. British Residency and Consulate-General, BUSHIRE. A — / I Dated 9th Septembe r, .1,940. Beference to previous correspondence Bushire memorandum No.9i0-l?/?57 dated the 16th July 1940, Description of knclosure.(Copy of letter dated thel4th July 1940, from Lady Fowle, c/Q Lloyds 1 Bank, 6 Pall Mall, London, S.ii/.l.) Please forgive my having delayed so long in answering your letter. I had to pass it on to the executors. 7/ould you please remit the Rs.65/- to Lloyds Bank , Cox Sc Kings Branch, 6 Pall Mall, for the credit of 'the Executors of Sir T.C.Fowle deceased'. The remainder of the carpets I should like really securely so^vn up, with native tobacco in them, in t^ro layers of sacking, and the outer layer tarred. We have found that this keeps rugs in perfect condition, even if stored for years, and then I should like them kept in a safe place in the Bahrain Agency until shipping conditions are easier. The tobacco will probably cost a bit now, perhaps you could have that deducted from the ?3.65/- as well as the other expenses? I should be most grateful for the trouble this entails, it is difficult to arrange for any kind of imports or shipping now as you know and I would rather try and get that done later onf O . ^'C -;w&gt; ^\ s -'V' J*J D.O.No. Will you please refer to your demi- official letter No,1510-16/32 dated the 11th August 1940 regarding automobile lubricants supplied to Colonel Prior ? 2, A cheque for Ks.329/3/- is enclosed in full payment. Please obtain a receipt from Khalil Kanoo. Captain R.D.Metcalfe, The Agency, BAHRAIN.r No. I/Zf -77/2-A. Dated the 6th September 1940 The Political Agent, Bahrain. MEMORANDUM Reference your memorandum No.1437 dated the 5th August 1940. This Residency's printed letter No. 949 - 28/37 dated theSrd July 1940 addressed to the Accountant General, Central Revenues, New Delhi, was erroneously included in your mail and listed in the way bill, instead of being enclosed in a separate cover for posting by air mail. 3. Would you kindly send it on to the Account ant General, Central Revenues, New Delhi, by next air Jnail? o. • order, ^ ^ ^' y •—Secretary to the Political Resident in the p ersian Gulf.// Ko.1786-16/32 To Political Agency f Bahrain. 21st September, 1940. The Secretary to the llon^le the Political Hesident in the Persian Gulf Bushire. ' d L I Memorandu m* Reference your IMemorandum No.C/149 dated the 23rd February 1940. 2. Hamad's sumner clothing has cost fls.l3/« and this amount has been debited to the Bushire account with this Agency. i'. for Political Agent, Bahrain* ktelegram From To GTC. Political, Bahrain. / — Political Resident, Shiraz. No. 26^ Da.ted 22nd September, 1940. &gt;/ ' ■ // 7 • Your tele gram T/407 September 1940. Only one parcel seeds received.1 The Political Agent, Bahrain, Presents his compliments to:-' The Secretary to the !:) ^ e trie Political itesicient in the P e rs ian u a IT, B as hi re • and has the honour to send him a copy yof the nnd^rmentioned document (s ) A 22 nci s eptember T9&lt;0No.07^-3 H.M’S POLITICAL AGENCY, KUWAIT, PERSIAN GULF. 11th September, 1940 tM [) isf°\ Many thanks for your demi- official letter No.1669-16/32, dated the 7th September. I have credited the Bahrain Postage Account here with Rs. 14 / 3 /- Captain J.B. Howes, I.A., Political Agency, Bahrain.C s. P. P.—L (hi) 1102—500-11-31. w 1940 - [yj The Political Agency, Bahrein, Dated the 211(1 ** ***** 1940 Atf To The Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, BUSHIRE. MEMORANDUM. f. I £ f Reference your Printed letter tfo.1132-13/25? dated the Sth September, 1940# 2. The carpets liave b&amp;en packed and stored as instructed by lady Eowle* The sun cf Hs*55/- less Us. 1/3/-, the cost of packing, has been remitted by draft to Lloyds Bank, London, as desired. for Political Agent, Bahrain&gt; t trznia 3ht ; ' .. *&gt; 1)0 /:/ )• J'b i.Vi* No.1377-16/32 Political Agency, Bahrain. 6tri October, 1940. To The 'Manager, *rhe Lloyds Ba^k Liraited, Cox and Kings Branch. 6 Pall Ifell, London. Dear air, ^ In accordaiice with the instructions received from lady rowle, I enclose herewith a draft for £.4-4-f (equivalent of Ks.63/13/-) and request that this amount may be placed to the credit of the executors of Sir Fowle, deceased. The anount represents the sale proceeds of tlie late dir T.C. Foule f s carpets. //; i. 2 . WL Please acknowledge receipt. for Political Agent, -^rirainD«ar Sirs, ?/ould you please ship the three packages sent herewith to the Hon*ble Lt: Colonel C.G.Prior, C.I.E., Bushire, by s.s« M BARAIA M due here tomorrow. The bill for freight etc. may please be sent to me. 2. I should be grateful if you would arrange to have the packages insured against loss or damage. Yours faithfully, for Political Agent, Bahrain.) Code. G.T.C. From. Britconsul, ^ushire. To. Political, Bahrain. No. 709 Tilted. 12th October 1940. v our despatch of August 15th No. 1561. Please send tailors by the first available steamer.No.1937-16/32 Political *£#ncy f . ^ \ .Bahrain. ' 14th October f 1940. To Kessrs. Gray Mackenzie &amp; Co., Ltd., Dear Sirs, Please issue two deck tickets with food to FV/ial Mohammed and Ramzan tailors, by the next mail to Bushire. 2. The cost will be paid by this office. Bahrain Yours faithfully / for Political Agent, BahrainTelegram From To GTC • Mr. Weightman, -Bahrain. Britconsul, Bushlre. Mo.295 Date! 16th October, 1940. f'r- Keys of writing desk follow by next mailMEAD OFFICE. 122. LEADEN HALL STREET, L0ND0N.E.C.3. TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS. GRAY. CODES USED: BENTLEYS COMPLETE PHRASE. BENTLEY'S SECOND PHRASE CODE. Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co. Ltd INCORPORATED IN ENGLAND) BRANCHES: BUSR E H. AM ARAH. K UT. KHORAMSHAHR AHWAZ (for BAN DAR-SHAHPOUR BUSH I RE. RAS TANURA BUNDER-AB LINGAH. BAH REIN KO WE IT. DUBAI. SHARJAH* MUSCAT *•, REPLY PLEASE QUOTE L/ A 'VO 0 • Vv* ^ Bahrain D/20th October, 19 40* The Political Agent, Bahrain. I Dear Sir, / 3¥Packa^es Furniture to Bushire. Reference your letter No.1912-IS/SB of 12th instant we have to inform you that the above packages have been shipped to Bushire per s.s.Barala v.324 and send you herewith the relative B/Lading No.l receipt of which please acknowledge. Our bill of charges will follow. Yours faithfu^y* For Gray Mackenzie &amp; Co,Limited. Enclosl B/ladimg in duplicate. / CCB.C’s. P. P.—L (in) 1102—500-11-31. N ° ~i6/3a oy ^ 1940 * The Political Agency, Bahrein, Dated the 22 * d October, 1940^, To The Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, BUSHIRE. MEMORANDUM. Reference this office telegram Ko; 291 dated 13th October, 1940* 2# Bill of Lading No.l dated 13th October 1940, regarding three packages furniture is enclosed herewith in duplicate* for Political Agent, ^hrain.No.1994-16/32 Bahrain. 22nd October, 1940. To Messrs. Gray Mackenzie &amp; Co., Ltd., Bahrain. T) * ar 3ir8 » \ * The Bill of Lading forwarded under cover of your letter No. L/843 dated the 20th October, 1940 has been received. / A for A; Political Agent, “Bahrain.Ho •647-S of 1940 To British Residency &amp; Consulate-General, Memorandum « Please refer to my Memorandum Ho*0/149, dated the 23rd February 1940# 2 . I hope to proceed on my annual autumn tour by the down slow mail leaving Bushire on or about the 8th November 1940 and should be glad if you would arrange to put Hamad bin Malik Omani, my coffee man, with his paraphernalia on board this steamer on our arrival at Bahrain. 3* 1 will telegraph you a more definite date as soon as it is known. sd. C.G.Prior. Political Resident in the Persian Gulf. Attested.DEPARTMENT. BRANCH. INLAND : Immediate Class for telegrams important. Express Ordinary To be issued oa 1st Reminder 2nd Reminder 3rd Reminder Heading: Case or Diary No. If post copy of telegram required Date of despatch of above Draft' Memorand um Telegram FOREIGN : Immediate Important Dated Ordinary Without priority Issued on V ■iN-\$&amp; Political Agency, Bahrain tho S6th Octohor 1940 Messrs the California House Bahrain Dear Sirs, Would you please ship three bags wheat flour best quality,and thirty pounds (30 lbs) aooji to Captain A # C,Stev/art, I.A., Brit ish ConsuJLate-^renoral, Bushina, by the next up mil without fail. Shipping rlocunants nay bo sent to ne for onward transmission. Your bill will bo paid by this office. 3. Hecessary export permit is enclosed. Yours faithfully rA iA for Political Agont, Bahrain ATelegram GTC From Britconsul, Bushire Political, Bahrain. To No .A/384 Da ted 5th Received 6th November, 1940. Please send urgently following in dozens. 6 Khaki cotton reels No.50, 1 Khaki cotton reels No.40, 2 black cotton reels No.50, 3 machine needles No.12 and No.14, 20 Khaki buttons large, 130 Khaki buttons small, 40 hooks for coat, 160 press buttons large, 12 black buttons small, 4 black buttons large. Followiing in numbers. 6 Khaki cotton reels No.20, 6 black cotton reels No.40, 3 black cotton reels No.20, 1 ( tin machine oil. Debit us through unofficial account.■■MBPolitical Agency, Bahrain the 7th November, 1940. To Messrs* the California House Bahrain Bear Girs, r leaae send the following to Captain A. C.Stewart, British Consulate-Genei’al, Bu shire, by this up-slow mail : Six dozens Khaki cotton reels No.50 One dozen Khaki cotton reels No.40 Two dozen black cotton reels No.50 Three dozen sewing machine needles, No.12 Three dozen sewing machine needles, No.14 Twenty dozen Khaki buttons large One hundred c and thirty dozens Khaki buttons small Forty dozen hooks for coat One hundred and sixty dozens press buttons large Twelve dozens black buttons small Four dozens black buttons large Six Khaki cotton reels No.20 Six black cotton reels Nc.40 Three balck cotton reels No.20 One can (small) Sewing machine oil. 2. This letter may be treated also as an permit for the export from Bahrain of the above. 3. Your bill will be paid by me. 4. This order may please be treated as urgent. Yours faithfully, / i for Political Agent, BahrainCables : Moslafa, Bahrain CTel 68 M. Sole Distributors for : Wahl Company Garvey &amp; Company A. G. Spalding &amp; Bros. ( British ) Ltd. Wanderer - Werke A. G. Albert Badberg Phoebus Werke Treibaeher Chemische Werke Nationals Ltd. Famm Freres ( Lusina Watches ) West End Watch Co. (Arabian Peninsula Except Aden k Bahrain ) Acme Export Corporation Cardinal Loboratories, Inc. Kia- Ltd. Lincc! .Aire Products Ltd. Lionel Corporation Etc. Be/.M. 1401/937. Te, Codes Used : Bentley's Oriental and Private CAUPOIKMA ffMDU ( Prop. Mostafa bin Abdul Latiff ) IMPORTERS jj V EXPORTERS The Political Agent, Bahrein. /Ia - N.llth Novenber,1940. if', Bankers : CThe Eastern Bank Ltd. Direct Importers &lt;fc Dealers: Continental Typewriters (English, Arabic k Persian) Typewriter Ribbons Wanderer Cycles k M. Cycles Eversharp Pens &amp; Pencils Eveready Flashlights &amp; Cells Arrow Shirts k Shorts 'Krementz Products ports Goods Palmolive Soap k Colgate Goods Hosiery k Drapery Tootal Products Bourjois Perfumery Etc. Etc - Flameless Cig. Lighters-' Electric Toy Trains Etc. Keroga Stoves Johnson k Johnson’s General Stores &amp; Provisions ^ ' ///? Sir, We thank you for your esteemed favour of the 9th instant and trust the goods will be found t© the satisfaction ©f Captain. A. 0. Stewart. We have forwarded the parcel to Messrs. Cray Mackenzie &amp; Co L* for dispatch. Hoping to be favoured with your kind patronage and placing our humble services at all times at your disposal. \ We remain, Yours faithfully, CALIFORNIA I OUSE {Mostaja Bin Abdullatxtf) anagerNo.^ J ' -64/238. Dated the2^ November 1940. 3 /4\Z To The Political Agent, Bahrain. MEMORANDUM \ / Would you kindly purchase from Bahrain Petroleum Company Limited 4 reams of absorbent paper, foolscap size, for taking copies from stencils (Gestetner Duplicator), if available, and hand over the packet to Mr. Thomas when he passes through with Political Resident on the 3rd December next. By order, for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.Code G.T.C From. Political Resident, Muscat. To. Political Agent, Bterain.^ No. T/619. /L / J Dated. 28-11-40. (7 £J Please book one second class passage with food from Bahrain to Karachi for Laporte by the first mail steamer leaving after December 3rd.No. 2^23 -16/32-11 Political Agency, Bahrain. 28th November, 1940. To ' / a “ X Messrs. Gray Mackenzie &amp; Co., Ltd., Bahrain . Dear* Sirs, /ill you please book one second class passage with food from Bahrain to Karachi for Mr. tf. laporte by the first mail steamer leaving after 3rd December 1940? 2* The cost of passage will be paid by this office on receipt of your Debit Note. Yours faithfully, for Political Agent, Bahrain.1.1 No.2234-16/32 Political Agency, Bahrain. 1st December, 1940 To ^— Po-?* (&lt;?/ The^Chief Local Representative, The Bahrain Petroleum Company Ltd., Bahrain. Dear Sir, -v’oulci you kindly let jie know if you have any absorbent paper, foolscap size for taking copies from stencils (Oestetner Duplicator) to spare? If sc may I have four reams on payment? *{** \\ for Political Agent, i^ahrain fL ' ■ r,|the Bahrein petroleum Company Limited PA-267 Awali, Bahrein Island. Persian Gulf, His Britannic Majesty’s Political Agent, Bahrein* Dear Sir: In reply to your request #2234-16/32 of the 1st instant, we have forwarded to you one parcel contain ing 4 reams of Gestetner Paper, Legal size* Our Invoice will follow in due course* Tours very truly. ■*7. cc Acctg.(2) R. A. KENNEDY Chief Local Representative THE BAHREIN PETROLEUM COMPANY LTD,&gt;\ No. /^f To 7 -/^ ■ British Consulate General, Bushire. Dated the December 1940. 0FC5 ^ The Assistant Political Agent, Bahrain. MEMOHANDUh Will you please send by the next upmail three bags of flour and twenty pounds Sooji and debit the cost to this Residency’s unofficial account. By order, for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Oulf. «No./Vf/ British Consulate Oeneral, Bushire. To Dated the Bahrain. DeQenber 1940. MEMORANDUM Will you kindly purchase for the Residency an H.M.V. (U.S.A.) Battery radio receiving set, l£-90 volts, Model 4 QB, 4 valves, complete with* dry battery, and send it through Messrs, dray Mackenzie &amp; Co., Ltd. 2. The cost may please be debited to this Residency’s unofficial account; an invoice should however be made out in the name of the British Consulate Oeneral, Bushire, and despatched with the set in order to facilitate its clearance from the Customs. By order.——No.2271-16/32 Pol itleal *^enoy, *3ahra lr». 8th December, 19^0 To f'essrs. the California House Bahrain. Pear Sirs, • ould you j^lease ship three ba^s wheat flour, best, quality, and tventy pounds oooji to Capta in ^ A.C. Stewart , I.' ., British Consulate-General, Bushire, by the next up mail without fail. Chipping documents my l&gt;e sent to ne for onward transmission* 2 s/ our bill will be paid by this office Necessary export permit is enclosed. 3 lours faithfully for Political Agent, BahrainTelegram . Code. From. To. No. Dated. Following from DautSny begins. A Please send any communication for me to Vice Consulate Mohammerah. ends. G.T.C. Britconsul, Bushire. Political Agent, Bahrain, A-433. 7-12-40• &lt;&lt;Telegram 'S' From Political Agent, Bahrain. To Political Resident, Bushire. No. 458 Dated 15th December 1940 J«7- Vour memorandum No. 1481 dated 5th December. 'Radio sent by hand of Commander 'Rarpeta. Please also collect one sealed cover. - Political -No. C/524. /S' j(f * Office cf the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, Camp Kuv/ait, December iCth 1940 To The Fo 1 i t i ca 1 Agent Bahrain. Memorandum. Hamad bin Malik with his coffee making paraphernalia is being sent by this down boat. He has been laid travelling allowance for the period he has been on tour. for Secretary to the Political ResidentCables : Mostafa, Pahrain &lt;Tel. 68 M. Sole Distributors for : Wahl Company Garvey &amp; Company A. G. Spalding &amp; Bros. ( British ) Ltd. Wanderer - Werke A. G. Albert Badberg Phoebus Werke Treibacher Chemische Werke Nationals Ltd. Famra Freres ( Lusina Watches ) West End Watch Co. (Arabian Peninsula Except Aden k Bahrain ) Acme Export Corporation Cardinal Loboratories, Inc. Kia-Ora Ltd. Lincolnshire Products Ltd. Lionel Corporation Etc. /A Codes Used : Benlleij's Oriental and Private 2 0 3 H ( Prop. Mostafa bin Abdul Latiff ) MPORTERS MH . EXPORTERS BAH (p. RAIN 15th December^T94R* Gulf) Bankers : CThe Eastern Bank Ltd. Direct Importers &amp; Dealers: Continental Typewriters (English, Arabic k Persian) Typewriter Ribbons Wanderer Cycles k M. Cycles Eversharp Pens k Pencils E veready Flashlights &amp; Cells Arrow Shirts &amp; Shorts Krementz Products Sports Goods Palmolive Soap &amp; * Colgate Goods &amp; Drapery ^*wJ88tal Products Bourjois Perfumery Etc- Etc. Flameless Cig. Lighters Electric Toy Trains Etc. Keroga Stoves Johnson k Johnson’s General Stores k Provisions / r o The Political Agent, Bahrein. Dear Sir, , , n ,ve thank you very much for your kind ord^r of R+in m«tant and glad to let you know that .ame hai been excuted! We herewith attach the delivery letter and our bill, at all time at^oik'dCpoSal? aSaln and placin g our .ervioe^. We remain, Your» faithfully, ' ' Cuat . Bin Abdullatii Delivery Order No.2 D.15-12-40 sent to the Secy: to P.R. Bushire under P.L. No.2329-16/32 dated 16-12-40. li lATelegram From To No.346 GTC. Political, Bahrain. Britagent, Sharjah. Dated 23rd December, 1940. Please send Colonel Rooney*s rain coat to Bushire by next mail-No. -64/238. British Consulate General, Bushire. Dated the^/&lt;^ December 1940. To The Political Agent, Bahrain. u&amp;im Reference the Hon’ble the Political Resident’s telegram No. T/619 dated the 28th November 1940. 2. Would you please 'inform me when and by what steamer Mr. LaPorte actually sailed for Karachi. By order, for Secretary to the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf.The Residency, D.O.No.715-3 Bushira, the 25th December 1940 L &lt;/rv 4 Could you very kindly ask the iiastern Bank at Bahrain if interest is allowed on current accounts What is fixed deposit rate 3 months 6 months 12 months* What are their rates on Buying Belling India Iraq, London flew *ork. What is rate of interest for bills on India * • Hew York * London * * Local Overdrafts, What is rate of commission for collecting bills What is rate of commission for opening credits abroad. ,jr • 9 Major R.G.W.Alban, O.B.E Political Agent, BAHRAIN.No. Political /gency, Bahrein the 30th Dccemher 1j40. To, The mrne f er, The stern Ban*. Bahrain. Would you kindly give ne the foilowir^ informetion: &lt;i) Is interest allowed oa Current Accounts Xnd ia Iraq ^ondon New Yorjc (iv) What is rate of interest fur:- Bills on India Bills on New York Bills on London and Bills on Local Overdrafts. (v) What is rate cf commission for collecting hills. dear Sir, (ii) Khet is fixer deposit rete (p) £ months, (b) 6 months and (c) 12 months (lii; . h?t arc your buying and selling rai.es on (iv) What is rate of com ission for opening ere its abroad. Yours faithfully, for Political Agent, Pa brain.COP^° ALL LETTERS TO BE ADDRESSED TO THE EASTERN BANK LIMITED. TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS: EASTERTIDE. The Political ‘Agent, Bahrain* (Ik€n$tnn ^ank. Wumt^. (incorporated in England.) Dear Sir, With reference to your letter No. 24Q9/l6/fc2/H of the 30th of Deo«aber ladt, we here to advise that the rates asked for by you fluctuate daily, and our present rates are as under.- (i) We allow no Interest on Current Accounts* (ii) Fixed deposit rates are.* For 3 months •• ]}■ Jfc p.a. For 6 * .. 1 * ' For 1 year • • ' (ill) All Agency Bills on India are bought all the year round at par. Our toddy's selling rate on India is Rs. % praciiun per Rs. 1,000. We are selling on Iraq at Rs. 1,345 per I.D. 100. We are selling on London at Rs.1,345 per £100. We are buying bills on Iraq at Rs.1*330 and on London at Rs.l,540 t for counts net exceeding £1,000. Our g§ il^.ng i rI © on New ^fork is Rs.535 per &lt;jjp 100 end our buying rate is Rs.320 per $ 100. /&gt;_ (iv) (hu’ r«tt of interest for bills on India is 6 £ p.a. do. Hew Fbrk •• No business. d°» Londbn .. !fo business. (▼) Oux ynte of interest for local bills discounted is 7 £ to 10 £ p.a. do. oFtrdrgftf is do. rate of oQBpissio®. for collection bills is ^&gt; £ do. opening credits abroad Is J £. fdithfnliy. Mdheger,D.O.No.42-16/32 /) Jlated 7th January, 1941. I enclose herewith a copy of letter dated 4th January 1941 from the Kastem Bank Liraitod, Bahrain, which gives the information asked for in your demi-official No.715-5 dated 25th December, 1940. Yours sincerely, 3d/- R.G.E/y. Alban. The Hon’ble Lt-Colonel C.G. Prior, Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, BushireG.T.C. Politic?! Resident Pushire Politic?1 D f hr?in. Telegram From To No. 49 Dated itth January 1941. Following for Belgrrve.Begins 'Shrrpe hopes to he able to come over to Bahrain ?t the end of the month. Could you arrange accommodation for him for this time? PRIOR. Ay ^ ^ A ' ' ‘ Xr '// I’M—-' *° t /, ’ 7 r $'* ■ HTelegram GTC. From Political, Bahrain* To Britconsul, Bushire. No. 16 Dated 14th January, 1941* Your telegram No*49 of* 13th January* Following from Belgrave 'Archdeacon Jerusalem here from about 20th till end January. Welcome Sharpe after January'From To No Dated Political Resident, Bushire Political Agent, Bahrain. 73 22nd January 1941 IMPORTANT Please recover from 'Bamora' and return cover overcarried from Khorramshahr M X £ SJ. 4 •. Telegram From To No.23 Dated 22nd January, 1941 GTC. Political, Bahrain. Britconsul, Bushire. j.mI- vji Your telegram No.73. No cover with Commander Bamora but Stewart says he saw a cover from Daubeny in hands of Mespers agent Bushire.No. 5 -16/32. Political Agency, Bahrain. 17th February, 1941. To Messrs. The California House, Bahrain. Dear Sirs, ^ Please refer to your lett^* 1401/937, dated the 11th November, 1940. 12 dozen arge Khaki buttons have now been returned from Bushire as surplus to require ments. They are enclosed^ herewith, and I shall be grateful if you will refund their coat to this office. Yours faithfully, . / for Political Agent,Bahrain ' ■ ; k ligi- Copy to the Secretary to the Hoh’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Oulf, Bushire, with reference to his telegi^m No .A/384, dated the 6th November, 15)40. Credit of the refund will be afforded in the un-official account.Telegram To From No. Britconsul, Bushi Political, Musca A/23 Dated de s P atched 29th January 1941. received Please send following telegram en-clair to Central Research Institute, Kasauli. Begins -- Please send, in 5 c.c. and 10 c.c. vials, 60 c.c. prophylactic T.A.B. vaccine by air mail to the Political Agent, Bahrain. Cost debitable to Bushire - B-4 - Copy forwarded to the Political Agent, Bahrain, with the request that the parcel of vaccine may be taken delivery of and forwarded to Bushire by the first available opportunity. Contingencies. Resident Ends. = Britconsul = British Consulate General, Bushire. Dated the 31st January 1941. 1 * Co,Cables : Mostafa, Bahrain Cfel 68 M. Sole Distributors for : Wahl Company Garvey &amp; Company A. G. Spalding &amp; Bros. ( British ) Ltd. Wanderer - Werke A. G. Albert Bad berg Phoebus Werke 'J'reibacher Chemische Werke Nationals Ltd. Famm Freres ( Lusina Watches ) West End Watch Co. (Arabian Peninsula Except Aden k Bahrain ) Acme Export Corporation Cardinal Loboratories, Inc. Kia-Ora Ltd. Lincolnshire Products Ltd. Lionel Corporation Etc. n 1433 / 937 . Codes Used : Bentley's Oriental and Private CAMFOIKMA IHfcDtt ( Prop. Mostafa bin Abdul Latiff ) IMPORTERS 4 EXPORTERS I N 20th Peh., 1941. Bankers: CThe Eastern Bank Ltc Direct Importers &amp; Dealer Continental Typewrit.] (English, Arabic k Persiai Typewriter Ribboi Wanderer Cyclt &lt;fc M. Cycles _ Eversharp Pens k Pencils Eveready Flashlights &amp; Cells Arrow Shirts k Shorts Krementz Products Sports Goods Palmolive Soap k Colgate Good* Hosiery &amp; Drapery Tootal Products Bourjois Perfumery Etc- Etc -| Flameless Cig. Lighters Electric Toy Trains Etc. Keroga Stove Johnson k Johnson’s General Stores k Provision* Political Agent, Bahrain c Dear Sir, ^ ^ We thank you for your letter No.322-16/32 dated the 17th instant, and hereby acknowledge receipt of the 12 dozen large Khaki buttons which you have returned surplus to your requirements. We beg to enclose herewith our Cheque No.151952 for Rs.4/8/- covering cost of these 12 doz. buttons. Yours faithfully, -IrU NIA I OUSE: .s£q /a Bt n A uU rtiff Enel.- Cheque, No.151952.A* C s. P. P.—L (in) 1102 — 500 - 11 - 31 . No,' _-OH 19 ^^. fj,.. The Political Agency, Bahrein, Dated the 23rd February, taJ4l To The Secretary to the Hon’ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, BUSHIRE. MEMORANDUM. „ Reference this office endorsement No•322-16/32, dated the 17th February, 1941• A sum of its•4/8/- has been received in refund of the cost of 12 dozen buttons* The amount has been credited to the un-official account. for Political Agent, Bahrain.Book No. 3 G (The amount of the bill must be p^d in ea^h b^means of R. T. R. or postal money order). Payment by means of cheques on Banks other than the Imperial Bank of India at places where there isjio brancjK5S this bank should include exchange commission. u£&gt;a|- The DIRECTOR, , Central Research Institute, . Kasauli, dated 3/- T . t,* , BUI No. J 5 Dr. / 19$/ Quantity. Rate. 1 Amount. Rs. A. / - r /j/&gt;~£+£» iMl U Total Rs. % /» * .in continuation of my endorsement Uo. l 8 lQ A dated Jotli January I 94 I, I have the honour to forward herewith air consignment note ho. IiJ/lC 2212 g dated 11th February 1941 and receipt Ho. K 4552 dated 11-2-1941 for 2/8/- of the Indian national Airways Ltd., Karachi, for direct payment of uj. 2/8/- to the Airp 9 rt Health Oiiicer, Karachi Airport, Lrigh Road, Karachi, under intimation to tnis office. I have the honour to be, air. Your most ^obedient servant, Hnclo sure Two* onel, I.L.a. , Direct or.Conditions of Carriage Carriage by Air : The General Conditions of Carriage of Goods of the Inter national Air Traffic Association are applicable «to both internal and international carriage as ifrthe carriers hereunder were members of the aforesaid Association Cotnbined Trampoit: The General Conditions of Air-Rail Transport of Goods of the Internat ional Air Traffic Association are applicable to combined transport (air-rail) as if th?' carriers hereunder were members of the aforesaid Association. General Conditions : International Carriage, as defined by Article \ paragraphs '1 and 3 of the Convention of Warsaw of 1 2th October 1929, is subject to the rules relating to liability established by the said Convention, upon which the aforesaid General Conditions are based. In no case are goods accepted for carriage with a special declaration of value at delivery. The insertion of the value of goods, for any purpose, in any part of t his Consignment Note shall not constitute a special declaration of value at delivery. The right to substitute alternative carriers is reserved. Indian Trans-Continental Ainvays Ltd. and its subsidiary and associated companies are not common carriers and do not accept the obligations or liability of common carriers ; nor is there implied in the contract of carriage any warranty concerning the aircraft engaged in the carriage or concerning its fitness for the carriage of the goods to which such contract relates. . A.'tr. e ' : ' Conditions de Transport: Transports par air : Les Conditions Generales de Transport cfes Merchandises de rAssociation Internati6nale dn Trade A&lt;5rien S appiiqucnt egalement aux tran sports internes et internationaux eomme si ie transporteur exploitant le transport etait membre de ladite Association. Transports combines: Les Cbndit ions Gencrales de Trafic-Marchandises Air-Fer dc 1’A ssociation Internat ionale du Trafic Aerieii sont applicables aux transports combines air-fer eomme si le transporteur exploitant le transport etait membre de ladite Association. * Conditions communes : Les transports internationaux au sens special de l article 1, paragraphe 2 et 3 de la Convention dc Varsovie du 12 octobre 1929 , sont sounds au regime de responsabilite etabh par cette Convention sur laquelle les Conditions Generales susvisees sont egalment basees. Le transporteur ivaccepte pas de marchandises avec une declaration speciale d interet a la livraison. L'insertion de la valeur de la marchandise dans un but quelconque et en une partie quelconque de la lettre de transport ne constituera pas une declaration speciale dinteret a la livraison. Le transporteur se reserve'le droit de se substituer un ou plusieurs autres t ransporteurs. Indian Trans-Continental Airways Ltd. et ses compagnies affiliees ou associees ne sont pas des “ Common Carriers ' et n’acceptent pas les obligations et la responsabilite des “ Common Carriers. ' Le contrat de transport n’implique par aillcurs aucune garantie eoncernant l aeronef utilise dans le transport ni son aptitude pour le transport des marc handises qui font I'objet du contrat.No. 3~0 2&gt; 16/32 Political Agencyt Bahrain the 19th Uarch,1941 From, The Political Agent f Bahrain To The Director, Central Research Institute, Sir Kaaaull . (India) i &gt; v, 4 I have the honour to refer you to the 1. Your letter TTo.lOOC dated the 31st * correspondence noted January, 1941. * 2. Your reminder No.3630 dated the 26th:in the margin and to February,1941. j 3. Your letter No.2901 dated the ISth :say tlmt I have you,by money order,a sum of Re.10/- in settlement of your bill; a further sum of Rs.2/8/- has been sent to the Air Port Health Officer, Karachi Air Port, Drigh Road,Karachi; as you desired. should have been adjusted against H Bushire-B-4-ContIngencies ,, vide the telegram sent to you by the Political Agent,Muscat. Copy, with compliments, to:- (a) The Air Port Health Officer, Karachi. (b) The Secretary to the Hon*ble the Political Resident in the Persian Gulf, 3uahire,for information. A sum of Rs.12/14/- ( Rs.12/8 plus money order commission annas six) has been debited to the Buahire account with this Agency, and the vaccine has been handed over to the Confidential Assistant, February, 1941. ^♦&gt;*«/&gt; today remitted to 2 I would add that the cost of the vaccine I have the honour to be. Sir, * Your most obedient servant for Political Agent, BahrainAIK MAIL. Office of the Political Heeident in the Persian Gulf, No.C/i45. Campf Jahrain* ted the 2Cth Haroh# 1941. Dear Sire, J Please send as early as possible to the address of the Political /vgent, dahrain t Persian Gull, eight boxes made as specified in your letter JNo*^/G/64/l403# dated the 14th March 1941, except that the lifting handles should be of brass instead of iron and the boxes should be numbered on the face 9 serially* from 1 to 8 • possible by rail and steamer via iiombay to the Political Agent, Bahrain* and the clearing documents sent to him direct* the bill being sent to this office* 2* The boxes should be despatched as soon as Yours faithfully* for Secretary to the Political xiesident in the Persian Gulf* T*iS*Thomson 4c Co*Ltd** 9* Esplanade j£ast* Calcutta* request that the receipt of the boxes may be intimated to this office . dopy to the Political ^gent, Bahrain, with aTelegram (x » T » C « ^rom Political Resident at Bahrain* To Political Agent, Bahrain* No.T/113* Dated 2‘dnd received 23rd March 1941. *‘or Aranha from Croning. iou should reserve no^ your passage for leave from .Bushire on down trip of mail by which we return there* RiSiDENTBritish India Steam Navigation Company Ltd. (incorporated in England; TELEGRAPHIC ADDRESS: GRAY. No. Bahrein, 26tn inlarch, 19341 . Messrs, Gray, Mackenzie &amp; Co. Ltd., Agents, BASRAH. Dear Sirs, Mr»_ &amp; lira. C. Aranha . iVe Simli be pleased ii* you will make reservations for the above couple Second-class without food from Bushire to Karachi, per Mr. Johnson No.329. lleasa confirm this reservation to our Busnire office with a copy to us. Yours faithfully, i hA c.c. 1 ) Political Agent, Bahrein. 2) G.M.Co., Bushire - please note tiiat cost of above passages is recoverable from Mr. C. Aranha, c/o British Consulate General Bushire.2 The renewal foe of £*0/10/- and an eppllcation for renewal are enclosed* 5« Five copies each of their photographs are also enclosed for the fresh passports and the Iranian visas* V curs s it' oere ly k ^</note><identifier>81055/vdc_100000000282.0x00010a_en</identifier><location><shelfLocator>IOR/R/15/2/1531</shelfLocator><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x00010a</url><physicalLocation>British Library: India Office Records and Private Papers</physicalLocation></location><recordInfo><recordIdentifer>IOR/R/15/2/1531</recordIdentifer></recordInfo><titleInfo><title>‘File 16/32-II Miscellaneous. Correspondence with the Residency, Bushire.’</title></titleInfo><originInfo><dateIssued>1938/1941</dateIssued><dateCaptured>2016-04-15T09:16:01</dateCaptured></originInfo><language><languageTerm authority="iso639-2b">eng</languageTerm></language><physicalDescription><extent>1 file (271 folios)</extent><extent>The file’s contents are arranged in approximate chronological order, from the earliest item at the front to the latest at the end. The file notes at the end of the file (ff 250-272) mirror the chronological arrangement.</extent><extent>Foliation: the main foliation sequence (used for referencing) commences at the front cover with 1, and terminates at the inside back cover with 273; these numbers are written in pencil, are circled, and are located in the top right corner of the recto side of each folio. An additional foliation sequence is present in parallel between ff 2-268; these numbers are also written in pencil, but are not circled.</extent></physicalDescription><abstract>Copies of correspondence exchanged between British offices in the Persian Gulf, chiefly the Persian Gulf Political Residency or British Consulate in Bushire, and the Political Agency in Bahrain. The papers deal with matters of a routine nature, including:the order of goods from suppliers and merchants, and their shipment to consignees. Ordered goods include alcohol for the Residency, firearms and ammunition, furniture, automobiles and lubricant oils, copper wire to replace stolen telegram cables at Bushire, plant and vegetable seeds, office supplies, and sports equipment. Wartime correspondence makes reference to the export licenses required for shipped goods;telegrams giving notification of the departure, movements and anticipated arrival of British officers and other individuals in the Gulf;arrangements for passports and passage for individuals, including two tailors travelling from Bahrain to Shiraz;sale of and transfer to England of carpets belonging to the late Political Resident, Sir Trenchard William Craven Fowle.</abstract><typeOfResource>text</typeOfResource><subject><topic>Office supplies</topic></subject><name type="corporate"><namePart>Political Resident, Persian Gulf</namePart><role><roleTerm type="text">correspondent</roleTerm></role></name><subject><topic>Supplies</topic></subject><subject><topic>Postal services</topic></subject><subject><topic>Freight services</topic></subject><subject><topic>Colonial administration</topic></subject><accessCondition type="Use and reproduction"><url>http://www.qdl.qa/en/archive/81055/vdc_100000000282.0x00010a#share</url></accessCondition></mods></metadata></record>